<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Natural variation at FLOWERING LOCUS T2 mediates local adaptation in <lb/>a key life history trait in European aspen <lb/>Jing Wang 1,8 , Jihua Ding 2 , Biyue Tan 1,3 , Kathryn M. Robinson 4 , Ingrid H. Michelson 4 , Anna <lb/>Johansson 5 , Björn Nystedt 5 , Douglas G. Scofield 1,6,7 , Ove Nilsson 3 , Stefan Jansson 4 , <lb/>Nathaniel R. Street 4 , Pär K. Ingvarsson 1,9 <lb/>1 Umeå Plant Science Centre, Department of Ecology and Environmental Science, Umeå <lb/>University, SE-90187, Umeå, Sweden <lb/>2 Umeå Plant Science Centre, Department of Forest Genetics and Plant Physiology, Swedish <lb/>University of Agricultural Sciences, SE-901 83 Umeå, Sweden <lb/>3 Stora Enso Biomaterials, SE-13104, Nacka, Sweden <lb/>4 Umeå Plant Science Centre, Department of Plant Physiology, Umeå University, SE-90187, <lb/>Umeå, Sweden <lb/>5 Wallenberg Advanced Bioinformatics Infrastructure, Science for Life Laboratory, Uppsala <lb/>University, Uppsala, Sweden <lb/>6 Department of Ecology and Genetics, Evolutionary Biology, Uppsala University, Uppsala, <lb/>Sweden <lb/>7 Uppsala Multidisciplinary Center for Advanced Computational Science, Uppsala University, <lb/>Uppsala, Sweden <lb/>8 Present address: Centre for Integrative Genetics, Department of Animal and Aquacultural <lb/>Sciences, Faculty of Life Sciences, Norwegian University of Life Science, PO Box 5003, Ås, <lb/>Norway <lb/>9 Present address: Department of Plant Biology, Uppsala BioCenter, Swedish University of <lb/>Agricultural Sciences, PO Box 7080, SE-750 07 Uppsala, Sweden <lb/>Number of words (excluding introductory paragraph): 1420, Number of tables: 0, Number of <lb/>figures: 3 <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>The timing of growth and dormancy represent critical life-history trade-offs in perennial <lb/>plants and often show strong local adaptation. Despite their importance, the genetic <lb/>architecture of phenological traits remains poorly understood. Here we identify a ~700 Kbp <lb/>region mediating local adaptation in the timing of bud set in Populus tremula across a <lb/>latitudinal gradient (~56-66°N) in Sweden, where extensive gene flow has removed almost all <lb/>traces of population structure. The strongest genomic associations with bud set are centered <lb/>on a P. tremula homolog of FLOWERING LOCUS T2 (PtFT2) and explain 32-52% of the <lb/>variation in bud set across sites and years. This region also shows multiple signs of a recent <lb/>selective sweep restricted to the northernmost populations. Under field and greenhouse <lb/>conditions, variation in bud set among accessions originating from different latitudes is <lb/>strongly associated with variation in PtFT2 gene expression. Finally, transgenic down-<lb/>regulation of PtFT2 yields a phenotype that, under field conditions, closely mimics variation <lb/>observed between phenotypic extremes in natural populations. Our results thus provide <lb/>evidence of one genomic region in P. tremula, centered on PtFT2, with major effects on <lb/>adaptation to shorter growing seasons and colder climates following post-glacial colonization. <lb/>The most important environmental cue regulating the cessation of growth, the initiation of <lb/>dormancy and bud set in perennial plants growing at northern latitudes is a shortening of the <lb/>photoperiod 1 . We have integrated whole genome re-sequencing with field and greenhouse <lb/>experiments to characterize the genetic architecture of adaptive variation affecting bud set in <lb/>the obligately outcrossing, woody perennial plant European aspen (Populus tremula). We <lb/>performed whole-genome re-sequencing on 94 unrelated P. tremula trees that display a strong <lb/>latitudinal cline in bud set (Fig. 1A,B; Supplementary Table 1) 2-4 . After stringent variant <lb/>calling and filtering (see &quot;Online methods&quot;), we identified a total of 4,425,109 high-quality <lb/>single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) with a minor allele frequency (MAF) greater than <lb/>5%. We found very weak population structure across the entire range using principal <lb/>component analysis (PCA) 5 , with a single significant axis separating individuals according to <lb/>latitude (r=0.889, P-value &lt;0.001) but explaining only 1.3% of the total genetic variance (Fig. <lb/>1C; Supplementary Table 2). Consistent with this, a Mantel test also showed a weak pattern <lb/>of isolation by distance (r=0.210; P-value=0.047, Supplementary Fig. 1). Although recent <lb/>admixture of divergent postglacial lineages following the Last Glacial Maximum (LGM) is <lb/>capable of generating a genome-wide pattern of clinal variation 6 , the extremely low genetic <lb/>differentiation among populations (mean F ST =0.0021; Supplementary Fig. 2) suggests that <lb/>extensive gene flow within P. tremula has almost eradicated this signal. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1 A) Location of the twelve original sample sites of the SwAsp collection <lb/>(circles) and the location of the two common garden sites (squares). The original <lb/>collection sites span a latitudinal gradient of c. 10 latitude degrees across Sweden. B) <lb/>Breeding values for date of bud set for the 94 individuals included in the study across <lb/>the two common gardens and three years (2005, 2006 and 2007). C) Population <lb/>structure in the SwAsp collection based a principle component analysis of 217,489 <lb/>SNPs that were pruned to remove SNPs in high linkage disequilibrium (SNPs included <lb/>all have r 2 &lt;0.2). Although two axes are shown, only the first axis is significant <lb/>(P=3.65×10 -12 , Tacey-Widom test, 1.31% variance explained). <lb/>We used three complementary approaches to identify candidate SNPs involved in local <lb/>adaptation (See &quot;Online Methods&quot;). We identified SNPs that were most strongly associated <lb/>with observed population structure using PCAdapt 7 , SNPs showing strong associations with <lb/>environmental variables based on a latent factor mixed-effect model (LFMM) 8 and finally we <lb/>Latitude <lb/>Bud set (days) <lb/>56 <lb/>58 <lb/>60 <lb/>62 <lb/>64 <lb/>66 <lb/>200 <lb/>210 <lb/>220 <lb/>230 <lb/>240 <lb/>PC1 (1.31%) <lb/>PC2 (1.21%) <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>−0.3 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Pop1 <lb/>Pop2 <lb/>Pop3 <lb/>Pop4 <lb/>Pop5 <lb/>Pop6 <lb/>Pop7 <lb/>Pop8 <lb/>Pop9 <lb/>Pop10 <lb/>Pop11 <lb/>Pop12 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Days <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>performed genome-wide association mapping (GWAS) on the timing of bud set, our target <lb/>adaptive trait, using GEMMA (Fig. 2A, 9 ). SNPs identified as significant (false discovery <lb/>rate&lt;0.05) by the three methods showed a large degree of overlap (Supplementary Fig. 3) and <lb/>for subsequent analyses we consider SNPs that were identified as significant by at least two of <lb/>the three methods to be involved in local adaptation. 99.2% of the 910 SNPs identified by all <lb/>three methods and 89.1% of the additional 705 SNPs identified by two methods were located <lb/>in a single region spanning c. 700 Kbp on chromosome 10 (Fig. 2A,B; Supplementary Fig. S4 <lb/>and Supplementary Table 3). SNPs associated with local adaptation displayed strong clinal <lb/>patterns in allele frequencies with latitude, in stark contrast to 10,000 SNPs randomly selected <lb/>from across the genome that displayed no or negligible differences among populations <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 5). The 700 Kbp region on chromosome 10 encompasses 92 genes and <lb/>the most strongly associated variants for all three tests were located in a region containing two <lb/>P. tremula homologs of FLOWERING LOCUS T2 (PtFT2; Potra001246g10694 and an <lb/>unannotated copy located c. 20 Kbp upstream of PtFT2) (Fig. 2B; Supplementary Figs. 6). <lb/>PtFT2 is known to be involved in controlling seasonal phenology in perennial plants 10 and <lb/>has previously been implicated in regulating short-day induced growth cessation, bud set and <lb/>dormancy induction in Populus 11-13 . Although both copies of PtFT2 appear to be expressed <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 6), the SNP showing the strongest signal of local adaptation across all <lb/>three methods (Potra001246:25256) was located in the third intron of the annotated copy of <lb/>PtFT2 (Potra001246g10694, Supplementary Figs. 6C). This SNP explain 32-52% of the <lb/>observed phenotypic variation in the timing of bud set across years and sites (Supplementary <lb/>Table 4). <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2 A) Manhattan plots for SNPs associated with local adaptation using three <lb/>approaches, PCAdapt, LFMM and GEMMA. Negative log 10 -transformed P values from <lb/>6 <lb/>genome-wide scans are plotted against genome position for each of 19 chromosomes <lb/>(depicted in alternating colours). B) magnification of the GWAS results for the region <lb/>on Chr10. Individual data points are coloured according to LD with the most strongly <lb/>associated SNP (Potra001246:25256). C-G) A magnified view of the candidate region <lb/>on chromosome 10 showing values for different statistics sensitive to selective sweeps. <lb/>Statistics were calculated separately for individuals from southern (population 1-6), <lb/>middle (populations 7-8) and northern (populations 9-12) Sweden. C) Nucleotide <lb/>diversity, π D) Genetic differentiation, F ST , E) H12, F) H2/H1, G) composite likelihood <lb/>ratio (CLR) test for the presence of a selective sweep. In C-G, the grey bar marks the <lb/>location of the PtFT2 locus. and H) the decay of extended haplotype homozygosity <lb/>(EHH) of the derived (blue) and ancestral (red) alleles for the SNP Potra001246:25256. <lb/>I) The extent of the three most common haplotypes at Potra001246:25256. Rare <lb/>recombinant haplotypes were pooled and are displayed in grey. J) Joint inference of <lb/>allele age and selection coefficient for the region surrounding PtFT2. <lb/>In order to further understand the evolution of functional differences between northern <lb/>and southern PtFT2 alleles, we analysed sequence diversity in the region surrounding PtFT2 <lb/>and identified multiple signs of a strong and recent selective sweep that has been restricted to <lb/>the northern-most populations. We observed a strong reduction in genetic diversity in the <lb/>northern populations and high genetic differentiation between southern and northern <lb/>populations around the PtFT2 locus (Fig. 2C,D; Supplementary Fig. 7 and Supplementary <lb/>Table 5). Furthermore, height H12 but low H2/H1 statistics 14 provide a clear indication of a <lb/>single adaptive haplotype that has risen to high frequency in northern populations only (Fig. <lb/>2E,F; Supplementary Figs. 7, 8, and 9). The occurrence of a recent geographically restricted <lb/>selective sweep is further supported by a composite-likelihood based (CLR) test that <lb/>documents a distorted site frequency spectrum with an excess of rare and high frequency <lb/>derived variants near the PtFT2 gene in northern populations only (Fig. 2G; Supplementary <lb/>Table 5). Two haplotype homozygosity-based tests, iHS 15 and nSL 16 , also reveal a high <lb/>concentration of significant SNPs with signals of positive selection within this region <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 10). Using the most strongly associated SNP (Potra001246:25256) as a <lb/>proxy we observed that haplotypes carrying the derived allele have elevated extended <lb/>haplotype homozygosity (EHH, 17 ) relative to the ancestral allele (Fig. 2H,I) and the high <lb/>EHH allele is largely restricted to high-latitude populations (Fig. 3D). We assumed that the <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>allele present in northern populations has been driven to fixation by a hard selective sweep <lb/>and used an Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) method 18 to jointly infer the age and <lb/>strength of selection acting on the northern allele. The results (Fig. 2J) point to a recent origin <lb/>of the northern allele (T=18952 years, 95% credible interval 719 -114122 years) and that <lb/>selection during the sweep has been relatively strong (s=0.016, 95% credible interval 0.006 -<lb/>0.192). <lb/>Figure 3 A) Bud set phenotype under 19hr day-length conditions. Two southern clones <lb/>(SwAsp 18,Ronneby, latitude 56.2 ˚N; SwAsp 23, Vårgårda, latitudes 58 ˚N ) and two <lb/>northern clones (SwAsp 100, Umeå , latitude 63.9 ˚N; SwAsp 112, Luleå , latitudes 65.7 <lb/>˚N ) were chosen to be analyzed. Trees were grown under 23hr day-length for one <lb/>month and then shifted to 19hr day-length, Photos were taken one month after the shift <lb/>to 19hr day-length. B) Dynamic expression analysis of PtFT2 in two southern clones <lb/>(red) and two northern clones (blue) from the greenhouse experiment (same clone <lb/>number as in Fig 3A). Samples for RT-PCR were taken two weeks after the trees were <lb/>shifted to 19hr day-length. C) Dynamic expression analysis of PtFT2 in two southern <lb/>clones (red) and two northern clones (blue) from common garden experiment. Samples <lb/>were collected from the in Sävar common garden in early July 2014. D) Allele <lb/>frequencies of the most strongly associated SNP Potra001246:25256 for the 12 original <lb/>populations of the SwAsp collection. E) The top is genotypic means of the timing of bud <lb/>set for the three genotypes at the SNP Potra001246:25256, which displayed the <lb/>strongest signal of local adaptation identified by all three methods as shown in Fig. 2A. <lb/>The effect displayed is the mean time to bud set of genotypes after correcting for the <lb/>effects of common garden site, year and block. The bottom is the average timing of bud <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>set for wild type control lines and transgenic PtFT2 lines. <lb/>While the most highly associated SNP (Potra001246:25256) is a strong candidate for <lb/>representing the causal variant regulating the timing of growth cessation, many other SNPs <lb/>surrounding the PtFT2 locus that are not in tight linkage disequilibrium with <lb/>Potra001246:25256 also showed strong signals of local adaptation (Supplementary Fig. 11). <lb/>One possible role for the functional variation mediated by these SNPs surrounding PtFT2 is <lb/>regulatory, by altering levels or timing of PtFT2 expression across the latitudinal gradient. To <lb/>further assess this possibility, we performed greenhouse experiments and found that two <lb/>northern genotypes showed rapid growth cessation and bud set following a shift from long <lb/>(23hr day length) to short day (19hr day length) conditions whereas two southern genotypes <lb/>continued active growth under the same conditions (Fig. 3A). Analyses of PtFT2 gene <lb/>expression in these genotypes show a strong down-regulation of PtFT2 in the northern <lb/>genotypes in conjunction with growth cessation and bud set (Fig. 3B; Supplementary Table <lb/>6). Notably, northern genotypes showed lower expression of PtFT2 under field conditions at a <lb/>time point when all genotypes were actively growing (Fig. 3C). Furthermore, when PtFT2 <lb/>expression was reduced to about 20% of wild type levels through RNAi, bud set under field <lb/>conditions was accelerated by c. 23 days compared to the wild type, mimicking the phenotype <lb/>differences we observed among the most extreme wild-collected genotypes from opposite <lb/>ends of the latitudinal cline (Fig. 3E). Specifically trees carrying the derived G allele in <lb/>homozygous form for the most strongly associated SNP in PtFT2 (Potra001246:25256) set <lb/>bud on average 33 days earlier than those homozygous for the ancestral T allele, with the <lb/>derived G allele showing partial dominance (Fig. 3D,E). <lb/>When considered together with the very weak population structure in P. tremula across <lb/>Sweden, our findings provide empirical evidence supporting recent theoretical predictions <lb/>that local adaptation in the face of high levels of gene flow tends to favor a genomic <lb/>architecture of one or a few tightly clustered loci of large-effect as opposed to the more <lb/>traditional architecture of many loci of small effect expected for most complex traits 19 . This <lb/>is likely because a single large-effect or a group of tightly linked loci of smaller effects are <lb/>better able to resist the homogenizing effect of gene flow than independent small-effect loci <lb/>do 20 . While small-effect loci likely also contribute to local adaptation, variation at such loci is <lb/>expected to be transient and/or difficult to distinguish from neutral background variation, <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>especially when recent demographic history coincides with local adaptation, as is the case in <lb/>the present study (Supplementary Fig. S12) 21,22 . <lb/>In summary, we identified a recent and strong selective sweep at PtFT2, a P. tremula <lb/>homolog of FT, which is regionally restricted to the northernmost populations and likely <lb/>occurred in response to the substantially shorter growing seasons that are characteristic of <lb/>northern Scandinavia. While FT is mainly involved in controlling flowering in plants, <lb/>functional diversification of FT has occurred repeatedly in many plants 23 . The clustering of <lb/>adaptive variation surrounding PtFT2 together with its position as a key integrator of diverse <lb/>environmental signals makes it a likely target loci of selection for rapid adaptation to <lb/>changing environmental conditions in the face of high gene flow. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Carin Olofsson for extracting DNA for all samples used in this study. <lb/>STRÅNG data are obtained from the Swedish Meteorological and Hydrological Institute <lb/>(SMHI), which were produced with support from the Swedish Radiation Protection Authority <lb/>and the Swedish Environmental Agency. The research was funded through grants from <lb/>Vetenskapsrådet, Knut and Alice Wallenbergs stiftelse and a Young Researcher Award from <lb/>Umeå University to PKI. JW was supported by a scholarship from the Chinese Scholarship <lb/>Council. BT is supported by the UPSC &quot;Industrial graduate school in forest genetics, <lb/>biotechnology and breeding&quot;. NRS is supported by the Trees and Crops for the Future (TC4F) <lb/>project. The authors also would like to acknowledge support from Science for Life <lb/>Laboratory and the National Genomics Infrastructure (NGI) for providing assistance with <lb/>massive parallel sequencing. All analyses were performed on resources provided by the <lb/>Swedish National Infrastructure for Computing (SNIC) at Uppsala Multidisciplinary Center <lb/>for Advanced Computational Science (UPPMAX) under the projects b2010014 and <lb/>b2011141. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>JW, ON, SJ, NS and PKI conceived of and designed the experiments. JW, BT, AJ, BN, <lb/>DGS, NS, PKI carried out all population genetic analyses. JD performed greenhouse and RT-<lb/></div>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">PCR experiments, KMR and IHM collected data from common JW and PKI wrote the paper. <lb/>All other authors commented on the manuscript. <lb/>Literature Cited <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1. Singh, R. K., Svystun, T., AlDahmash, B., Jönsson, A. M. &amp; Bhalerao, R. P. Photoperiod-<lb/>and temperature-mediated control of phenology in trees -a molecular perspective. The <lb/>New phytologist 213, 511-524 (2017). <lb/>2. Hall, D. et al. Adaptive population differentiation in phenology across a latitudinal gradient <lb/>in European aspen (Populus tremula, L.): a comparison of neutral markers, candidate <lb/>genes and phenotypic traits. Evolution 61, 2849-2860 (2007). <lb/>3. Ma, X.-F., Hall, D., Onge, K. R. S., Jansson, S. &amp; Ingvarsson, P. K. Genetic differentiation, <lb/>clinal variation and phenotypic associations with growth cessation across the Populus <lb/>tremula photoperiodic pathway. Genetics 186, 1033-1044 (2010). <lb/>4. Luquez, V. et al. Natural phenological variation in aspen (Populus tremula): the SwAsp <lb/>collection. Tree Genetics &amp; Genomes 4, 279-292 (2008). <lb/>5. Patterson, N., Price, A. L. &amp; Reich, D. Population structure and eigenanalysis. PLoS <lb/>Genetics 2, e190 (2006). <lb/>6. De Carvalho, D. et al. Admixture facilitates adaptation from standing variation in the <lb/>European aspen (Populus tremula L.), a widespread forest tree. Mol Ecol 19, 1638-1650 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>7. Duforet-Frebourg, N., Bazin, É. &amp; Blum, M. G. B. Genome scans for detecting footprints <lb/>of local adaptation using a Bayesian factor model. Mol Biol Evol 31, 2483-2495 (2014). <lb/>8. Frichot, É., Schoville, S. D., Bouchard, G. &amp; François, O. Testing for associations between <lb/>loci and environmental gradients using latent factor mixed models. Mol Biol Evol 30, <lb/>1687-1699 (2013). <lb/>9. Zhou, X. &amp; Stephens, M. Genome-wide efficient mixed-model analysis for association <lb/>studies. Nat Genet 44, 821-824 (2012). <lb/>10. Ding, J. &amp; Nilsson, O. Molecular regulation of phenology in trees-because the seasons <lb/>they are a-changin&apos;. Curr. Opin. Plant Biol. 29, 73-79 (2016). <lb/>11. Böhlenius, H. et al. CO/FT regulatory module controls timing of flowering and seasonal <lb/>growth cessation in trees. Science 312, 1040-1043 (2006). <lb/>12. Hsu, C.-Y. et al. FLOWERING LOCUS T duplication coordinates reproductive and <lb/>vegetative growth in perennial poplar. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 108, 10756-10761 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>13. Evans, L. M. et al. Population genomics of Populus trichocarpa identifies signatures of <lb/>selection and adaptive trait associations. Nat Genet 46, 1089-1096 (2014). <lb/>14. Garud, N. R., Messer, P. W., Buzbas, E. O. &amp; Petrov, D. A. Recent selective sweeps in <lb/>North American Drosophila melanogaster show signatures of soft sweeps. PLoS Genetics <lb/>11, e1005004 (2015). <lb/>15. Voight, B. F., Kudaravalli, S., Wen, X. &amp; Pritchard, J. K. A map of recent positive <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>selection in the human genome. PLoS Biol. 4, e72 (2006). <lb/>16. Ferrer-Admetlla, A., Liang, M., Korneliussen, T. &amp; Nielsen, R. On detecting incomplete <lb/>soft or hard selective sweeps using haplotype structure. Mol Biol Evol 31, 1275-1291 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>17. Sabeti, P. C. et al. Detecting recent positive selection in the human genome from <lb/>haplotype structure. Nature 419, 832-837 (2002). <lb/>18. Ormond, L., Foll, M., Ewing, G. B., Pfeifer, S. P. &amp; Jensen, J. D. Inferring the age of a <lb/>fixed beneficial allele. Mol Ecol 25, 157-169 (2016). <lb/>19. Yeaman, S., Aeschbacher, S. &amp; Bürger, R. The evolution of genomic islands by increased <lb/>establishment probability of linked alleles. Mol Ecol 25, 2542-2558 (2016). <lb/>20. Yeaman, S. &amp; Whitlock, M. C. The genetic architecture of adaptation under migration-<lb/>selection balance. Evolution 65, 1897-1911 (2011). <lb/>21. Yeaman, S. Local Adaptation by alleles of small effect. Am Nat 186, S74-89 (2015). <lb/>22. Bergland, A. O., Tobler, R., González, J., Schmidt, P. &amp; Petrov, D. Secondary contact and <lb/>local adaptation contribute to genome-wide patterns of clinal variation in Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. Mol Ecol 25, 1157-1174 (2016). <lb/>23. Pin, P. A. &amp; Nilsson, O. The multifaceted roles of FLOWERING LOCUS T in plant <lb/>development. Plant Cell Environ 35, 1742-1755 (2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Online Materials and Methods <lb/>1. Sample collection and sequencing <lb/>We collected material from all available trees in the Swedish Aspen (SwAsp), <lb/>which consists of 116 individuals collected from 12 different locations spanning the <lb/>distribution range in Sweden 1 (Fig. 1A). Leaf material was sampled from one clonal <lb/>replicate of each individual growing at a common garden experiment located in Sävar, <lb/>northern Sweden. Total genomic DNA for each individual was extracted from frozen <lb/>leaf tissue using the DNeasy plant mini prep kit (QIAGEN, Valencia, USA). Paired-<lb/>end sequencing libraries with an average insert size of 650 bp were constructed for all <lb/>samples according to the Illumina manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Whole genome <lb/>sequencing and base calling were performed on the Illumina HiSeq 2000 platform for <lb/>all individuals to a mean, per-sample depth of approximately 30× at the Science for <lb/>Life Laboratory, Stockholm, Sweden. <lb/>2. Polymorphism detection <lb/>2.1 Sequence quality checking, read mapping and post-mapping filtering <lb/>A total of 103 SwAsp individuals were successfully sequenced. Prior to read <lb/>mapping, we used Trimmomatic v0.30 2 to identify reads with adapter contamination <lb/>and to trim adapter sequences from reads. After checking the quality of the raw <lb/>sequencing <lb/>data <lb/>using <lb/>FastQC <lb/>(http://www.bioinformatics.bbsrc.ac.uk/projects/fastqc/), the quality of sequencing <lb/>reads was found to drop towards the ends of reads (Supplementary Fig. 13). We <lb/>therefore used Trimmomatic v0.30 to trim bases from both ends of the reads if their <lb/>qualities were lower than 20. Reads shorter than 36 bases after trimming were <lb/>discarded completely. <lb/>After quality control, all high-quality reads were mapped to a de novo <lb/>assembly of the P. tremula genome (available at http://popgenie.org; 3 ) using the <lb/>BWA-MEM algorithm with default parameters using bwa-0.7.10 4 . We used <lb/>MarkDuplicates methods from the Picard packages (http://picard.sourceforge.net) to <lb/>correct for the artifacts of PCR duplication by only keeping one read or read-pair with <lb/>the highest summed base quality among those of identical external coordinates and/or <lb/>same insert lengths. Alignments of all paired-end and single-end reads for each <lb/>sample were then merged using SAMtools 0.1.19 5 . Sequencing reads in the vicinity <lb/>of insertions and deletions (indels) were globally realigned using the <lb/>RealignerTargetCreator and IndelRealigner in the Genome Analysis Toolkit (GATK <lb/>v3.2.2) 6 . To minimize the influence of mapping bias, we further discarded the <lb/>following site types: (i) sites with extremely low (&lt;400× across all samples, i.e. less <lb/>than an average of 4× per sample) or extremely high coverage (&gt;4500×, or <lb/>approximately twice the mean depth at variant sites) across all samples after <lb/>investigating the coverage distribution empirically; (ii) sites with a high number of <lb/>reads (&gt;200×, that is on average more than two reads per sample) with mapping score <lb/>equaling zero; (iii) sites located within repetitive sequences as identified using <lb/>RepeatMasker 7 ; (iv) sites that were in genomic scaffolds with a length shorter than 2 <lb/>Kbp. <lb/>2.2 SNP and genotype calling <lb/>SNP calling in each sample was performed using the GATK HaplotypeCaller, and <lb/>GenotypeGVCFs were then used to perform the multi-sample joint aggregation, re-<lb/>genotyping and re-annotation of the newly merged records among all samples. We <lb/>performed several filtering steps to minimize SNP calling bias and to retain only high-<lb/>quality SNPs: (i) Remove SNPs at sites not passing all previous filtering criteria; (ii) <lb/>Retain only bi-allelic SNPs with a distance of more than 5 bp away from any indels; <lb/>(iii) Remove SNPs for which the available information derived from &lt;70% of the <lb/>sampled individuals after treating genotypes with quality score (GQ) lower than 10 as <lb/>missing; (iv) Remove SNPs with an excess of heterozygotes and deviates from <lb/>Hardy-Weinberg Equilibrium test (P-value &lt;1e-8). After all steps of filtering, a total <lb/>of 4,425,109 SNPs with minor allele frequency higher than 5% were left for <lb/>downstream analysis. Finally, the effect of each SNP was annotated using SnpEff <lb/>version 3.6 8 based on gene models from the P. tremula reference genome (available <lb/>at http://popgenie.org; 3 ), and the most deleterious effect was selected if multiple <lb/>effects occurred for the same SNP using a custom Perl script. <lb/>3. Relatedness, population structure and isolation-by-distance <lb/>To identify closely related individuals and to infer population structure among the <lb/>sampled individuals, we discarded SNPs with missing rate &gt;10%, MAF &lt; 5% and that <lb/>failed the Hardy-Weinberg equilibrium test (P &lt;1×10 -6 ) after all filtering steps as <lb/>shown above. We also generated LD-trimmed SNP sets by removing one SNP from <lb/>each pair of SNPs when the correlation coefficients (r 2 ) between SNPs exceed 0.2 in <lb/>blocks of 50 SNPs using PLINK v1.9 9 . This yielded 217,489 independent SNPs that <lb/>were retained for downstream analyses of population structure. First, we used PLINK <lb/>v1.9 to estimate identity-by-state (IBS) scores among pairs of all individuals. Nine <lb/>individuals were excluded from further analyses due to their high pairwise genetic <lb/>similarity with another sampled individual (IBS&gt;0.8), leaving a total of 94 &apos;unrelated&apos; <lb/>individuals for all subsequent analyses (Supplementary Fig. 14). Then, we used the <lb/>smartpca program in EIGENSOFT v5.0 10 to perform the principal component <lb/>analysis (PCA) on the reduced set of genome-wide independent SNPs. A Tracey-<lb/>Widom test, implemented in the program twstats in EIGENSOFT v5.0, was used to <lb/>determine the significance level of the eigenvectors. Finally, isolation by distance <lb/>(IBD) analysis was computed based on the pairwise comparison of the genetic and <lb/>geographic distances between populations. We calculated the population <lb/>differentiation coefficient (F ST ) 11 for each pair of the twelve populations using <lb/>VCFtools v0.1.12b 12 . The relationship between genetic distance measured as F ST /(1-<lb/>F ST ) and geographic distance (km) was evaluated using Mantel tests in the R package <lb/>&quot;vegan&quot; 13 , and the significance of the correlation was estimated based on 9999 <lb/>permutations. <lb/>4. Screening for SNPs associated with local adaptation <lb/>We used three conceptually different approaches to test for genome-wide signatures <lb/>of local adaptation. <lb/>4.1 Population differentiation <lb/>
			First, we detected candidate SNPs involved in local adaptation using the principal <lb/>component analysis as implemented in PCAdapt 14 . PCAdapt examines the <lb/>correlations (measured as the squared loadings ρ 2 <lb/>jk , which is the squared correlation <lb/>between the jth SNP and the kth principal component) between genetic variants and <lb/>specific principal components (PCs) without any prior definition of populations. As <lb/>only the first principal component was significant from the PC analysis <lb/>(Supplementary Table 2), we only estimated the squared loadings ρ 2 <lb/>j1 with PC1 to <lb/>identify SNPs involved in local adaptation. Our results showed that most outlier SNPs <lb/>that were highly correlated with the first population structure PC also had high F ST <lb/>values between populations (Supplementary Fig. 15). Assuming a chi-square <lb/>distribution for the squared loadings ρ 2 <lb/>j1 , as suggested by 14 , we used PCAdapt to <lb/>compute P-values for all SNPs, and then calculated the false discovery rate (FDR) <lb/>using the method of 15 to generate a list of candidate SNPs showing significant <lb/>associations to population structure. Only SNPs with FDR &lt; 5% were retained as <lb/>those significantly involved in local adaptation. <lb/>4.2 Environmental associations <lb/>We tested for the presence of candidate SNPs that exhibited high correlations <lb/>with environmental gradients. To do this, a total of 39 environmental variables were <lb/>analysed. Precipitation and temperature values were retrieved from WorldClim <lb/>version 1 16 . Sunshine hours, photosynthetically active radiation and UV radiation <lb/>were obtained using the STRÅNG data model at the Swedish Meteorological and <lb/>Hydrological Institute (SMHI) (http://strang.smhi.se). Values were collected from the <lb/>years 2002-2012 for the original sample coordinates of each SwAsp individual and <lb/>the average values over years were then calculated. The environmental variables <lb/>include latitude, longitude, altitude, the number of days with temperatures higher than <lb/>5 ºC, UV irradiance, the photosynthetic photon flux density (PPFD), sunshine <lb/>duration, monthly and annual average precipitation and temperature. Due to the high <lb/>degree of correlation among these environmental variables (Supplementary Fig.16A), <lb/>we performed a PCA on these variables using the &apos;prcomp&apos; function in R to identify <lb/>PCs that best summarized the range of environmental variation. The first <lb/>environmental PC, which explained &gt; 60% of the total variance (Supplementary <lb/>Fig.16B,C) and had the strongest loadings for the length of growing season <lb/>(Supplementary Fig.16D), was kept to represent our target environmental variable for <lb/>further analyses. We then used a latent factor mixed-effect model (LFMM) <lb/>implemented in the package LEA in R 17 to investigate associations between SNPs <lb/>and the first environmental PC while simultaneously accounting for population <lb/>structure by introducing unobserved latent factors into the model 18 . Due to the weak <lb/>population structure found in the SwAsp collection (see Results), we ran the LEA <lb/>function lfmm with the number of latent factors (K) ranging from one to three, using <lb/>5000 iterations as burn-in followed by 10,000 iterations to compute LFMM <lb/>parameters for all SNPs. This was performed five times for each value of K, and we <lb/>observed identical results both across different values of K and across independent <lb/>runs within each value of K (data not shown). We only showed the results using K=2 <lb/>to account for the background population structure. LFMM outliers were detected as <lb/>those SNPs with FDR &lt; 0.05 after using the method of 15 to account for multiple <lb/>testing. <lb/>4.3 Genome-wide association mapping <lb/>We obtained previously published measurements of the timing of bud set, <lb/>which is a highly heritable trait that shows strong adaptive differentiation along the <lb/>latitudinal gradient 19,20 . To measure phenotypic traits, all SwAsp individuals have <lb/>previously been clonally replicated (four ramets per individual) and planted at two <lb/>common garden sites in 2004 (Sävar, 63ºN, and Ekebo, 56ºN) (Fig. 1A). The common <lb/>garden setup is described in detail in 1 . The timing of bud set was scored twice weekly <lb/>starting from mid-July and continuing until all trees had set terminal buds. Bud set <lb/>measurements were scored in three consecutive years, from 2005 to 2007, in both <lb/>common gardens 19 (Figure 1A). A severe drought in Sävar caused most of the trees <lb/>to set bud prematurely in 2006, and we therefore excluded data from Sävar in 2006 in <lb/>all downstream analyses (see 20 for further discussion). We combined data on bud set <lb/>from the two common garden sites and years by predicting genetic values with best <lb/>linear unbiased prediction (BLUP) for all individuals. The ASReml 21 was used to fit <lb/>Equation 1 to the data for calculating BLUP using restricted maximum-likelihood <lb/>techniques. <lb/>z ijklm =µ + s i + b j(i) + y k(i) + l + ijklm <lb/>(1) <lb/>where z ijklm is the phenotype of the mth individual in the jth block in the kth year <lb/>of the lth clone from the ith site. In Equation 1, µ denotes the grand mean and ijklm is <lb/>the residual term. The clone ( l , BLUP) and residual term ( ijklm ) were modeled as <lb/>random effects, whereas the site (s i ), site/block (b j(i) ) and site/year (y k(i) ) were treated <lb/>as fixed effects. The genetic value of each individual was then used as the dependent <lb/>trait in an univariate linear mixed model for SNP-trait association analyses performed <lb/>with GEMMA 22 . This method takes relatedness among samples into account through <lb/>the use of a kinship matrix. The mixed model approach implemented in GEMMA has <lb/>been shown to outperform methods that try to correct for population structure by <lb/>including it as a fixed effect in the GWAS analyses 23 . Given the extremely weak <lb/>population structure we observe in our GWAS population (see Results) we did not <lb/>pursue any further corrections for population structure in the association analyses as <lb/>this likely would severely reduce our power to detect significant associations. As <lb/>described previously, we used a FDR &lt; 5% 15 to control for the multiple testing across <lb/>the 4,425,109 SNPs. <lb/>5. Testing for positive selection on the region surrounding the PtFT2 <lb/>locus <lb/>5.1 Genotype imputation <lb/>For some haplotype-based selection tests, imputed and phased data sets were <lb/>needed. We therefore used BEAGLE v4.1 24 to perform imputation and haplotype <lb/>phasing on genotypes of 94 individuals with default parameters. Before performing <lb/>genotype imputation, we first used Chromosemble from the Satsuma packages 25 to <lb/>order and orient the scaffolds of the P. tremula assembly to 19 pseudo-chromosomes <lb/>according to synteny with the P. trichocarpa genome. We then performed pairwise <lb/>genome alignment between scaffolds of P. tremula and the 19 pseudochromosomes <lb/>using the BLAST algorithm (E-value cutoff of 1e-50), and finally, more than 99% of <lb/>the SNPs (4,397,537 out of 4,425,109) were anchored on the 19 pseudochromosomes. <lb/>To test for the accuracy of imputation, and its relationship with the MAF cutoff <lb/>and the missing rate of genotypes in our dataset, we selected 346,821 SNPs with a <lb/>rate of missing genotypes lower than 10% from the pseudo-chromosome 2 (~32.6 <lb/>Mb) for the simulation analysis. We randomly masked out varying proportions (5-<lb/>50%) of SNPs, which were treated as missing. BEAGLE v 4.1 was then used to <lb/>impute genotypes at the masked positions. We found high imputation accuracy <lb/>(&gt;0.97) across a wide range of MAF when rates of missing genotypes were less than <lb/>30% (Supplementary Fig.17), suggesting imputation and phasing by BEAGLE should <lb/>not bias the accuracy of our results. We therefore phased and imputed genotypes of <lb/>the SNPs anchored on pseudo-chromosomes using BEAGLE v 4.1. <lb/>
			5.2 Estimation of ancestral states for all SNPs <lb/>Since the ancestral states of SNPs are usually used for selection detection, for <lb/>each SNP, we classified alleles as either ancestral or derived on the basis of <lb/>comparisons with two outgroup species: P. tremuloides and P. trichocarpa. We <lb/>obtained publicly available short read Illumina data for one P. tremuloides (SRA ID: <lb/>SRR2749867) and one P. trichocarpa (SRA ID: SRR1571343) individual from the <lb/>NCBI Sequence Read Archive (SRA) 26 . We individually aligned the reads from these <lb/>two samples to the de novo P. tremula assembly (Potra v1.1, available at <lb/>PopGenIE.org) and used UnifiedGenotyper in GATK to call SNPs at all sites (--<lb/>output_mode EMIT_ALL_SITES). For each SNP, two procedures were performed to <lb/>define their ancestral states: (1) because P. trichocarpa is more distantly related to P. <lb/>tremula compared to P. tremuloides 27 and from our previous study there were less <lb/>than 1% polymorphic sites shared between P. tremula and P. trichocarpa 26 , we <lb/>inferred the ancestral state as the P. trichocarpa allele at sites where the P. <lb/>trichocarpa individual was homozygous and matched one of the P. tremula alleles; <lb/>Otherwise, (2) we inferred the ancestral state as the P. tremuloides allele at sites <lb/>where the P. tremuloides individual was homozygous and matched one of the P. <lb/>tremula alleles. If the above two requirements were not met, the ancestral state was <lb/>defined as missing. In total, we obtained information of ancestral states for 96.3% of <lb/>all SNPs. <lb/>5.3 Refine the anchoring and orientation of SNPs associated with local <lb/>adaptation to a single region on chromosome 10 <lb/>As we found that a large majority of significant SNPs (&gt;90%) detected by at <lb/>least two of the three methods (PCAdapt, LFMM, and GEMMA) were clustered in a <lb/>single genomic region on pseudo-chromosome 10, we performed several further steps <lb/>to refine the anchoring and orientation of these SNPs within this region. First, we <lb/>used ColaAlignSatsuma from the Satsuma packages 25 to align the genomes of P. <lb/>tremula and P. trichocarpa using default settings. The output was then converted and <lb/>filtered into GBrowse synteny compatible format that was available at <lb/>http://popgenie.org 3 . Based on the alignment of the two genomes, 15 scaffolds from <lb/>the P. tremula assembly that contain SNPs inferred to be associated with local <lb/>adaptation were completely or partially mapped to a single region on chromosome 10 <lb/>of P. trichocarpa genome (Supplementary Table 3). We then retained only seven <lb/>scaffolds that were completely mapped to the region and with length longer than 10 <lb/>Kbp. The seven scaffolds contained more than 95% (1465 out of 1528) of the total <lb/>number of significant SNPs in the single region of chromosome 10. Lastly, according <lb/>to the alignment results between the genome of P. tremula and P. trichocarpa, we re-<lb/>ordered and re-oriented the seven scaffolds to a ~700 Kbp region for all downstream <lb/>selection tests (Supplementary Fig. 4). <lb/>5.4 Linkage disequilibrium <lb/>A possible explanation for the occurrence of the clustering of SNPs involved in <lb/>local adaptation in the ~700 Kbp region is the presence of genomic rearrangements, <lb/>such as chromosomal inversions, that suppress recombination and create extensive <lb/>linkage disequilibrium (LD) spanning the region within the rearrangement 28 . We <lb/>calculated correlations (r 2 ) between all pairwise common SNPs (MAF&gt;5%, 9149 <lb/>SNPs) in the ~700 Kbp region using PLINK 1.9 9 . To explore and compare patterns of <lb/>LD between the ~700 Kbp region on chromosome 10 and genome-wide levels, we <lb/>first used PLINK 1.9 to randomly thin the number of common SNPs across the <lb/>genome to 200,000, and then calculated the squared correlation coefficients (r 2 ) <lb/>between all pairs of SNPs that were within a distance of 100 Kbp. The decay of LD <lb/>against physical distance was estimated using nonlinear regression of pairwise r 2 vs. <lb/>the physical distance between sites in base pairs 29 . In contrast to the expectation of <lb/>the presence of an inversion, we did not observe blocks of elevated LD across the <lb/>region on chromosome 10 (Supplementary Fig. 18A,B). Although LD is slightly <lb/>higher in this region compared to genome-wide averages, LD still decays rapidly and <lb/>falls to background levels within a few thousand bases (Supplementary Fig. 18A). <lb/>This suggests that frequent recombination has occurred in this region and that the <lb/>clustering of SNPs involved in local adaptation more likely arose from selective <lb/>sweeps 30 . Nonetheless, owing to the limited ability to detect inversions using short-<lb/>insert paired reads, future characterization of structural variation across the genome is <lb/>clearly required to determine whether, and how, genomic rearrangements are involved <lb/>in mediating adaptation in Populus. <lb/>5.5 Positive selection detection <lb/>We measured two haplotype-based tests, integrated haplotype score (iHS) 31 and <lb/>the number of segregating sites by length (nS L ) 32 , to test for possible positive <lb/>selection. These statistics were calculated for all SNPs with MAF higher than 0.05 <lb/>and with information on ancestral state across the genome using the software <lb/>selscan v1.1.0a 33 with its assumed default parameters. The iHS and the nS L values <lb/>were then normalized in frequency bins across the whole genome (we used 100 bins). <lb/>To test for whether there is significant concentration of selection signals on the region <lb/>surrounding the PtFT2, we divided the 19 pseudo-chromosomes (without the seven <lb/>scaffolds around the PtFT2 locus) into non-overlapping windows of 700 Kbp and <lb/>calculated the proportion of SNPs with |iHS| &gt; 2 or with [nS L |&gt;2 in each window. <lb/>Statistical significance was assessed using the ranking of genome-wide windows, with <lb/>windows having fewer than 100 SNPs being excluded. <lb/>5.6 Population-specific selective sweeps <lb/>Several standard methods were further applied to search for signs of selective <lb/>sweeps in different groups of populations: (i) pairwise nucleotide diversity (π) 34 , <lb/>which is expected to have a local reduction following a selective sweep, was <lb/>calculated using a sliding window approach with window size of 10 Kbp and moving <lb/>step of 5 Kbp using the software package -Analysis of Next-Generation Sequencing <lb/>Data (ANGSD v0.602) 35 separately for South (pop 1-6), Mid (pop 7-8) and North <lb/>(pop 9-12) populations. Only the reads with mapping quality &gt; 30 and the bases with <lb/>quality score &gt;20 were used in the analysis. Windows with &lt;10% of covered sites <lb/>remaining from the previous filtering steps (section 2.1) were excluded; (ii) Weir and <lb/>Cockerham&apos;s F ST , which measures genetic divergence between pairs of three groups <lb/>of populations, South, Mid and North, was calculated using a sliding-window <lb/>approach with window size of 10 Kbp and moving step of 5 Kbp by VCFtools; (iii) a <lb/>combination of H12 and H2/H1 36 , which measures haplotype homozygosity and can <lb/>distinguish hard from soft selective sweeps, were calculated in windows of 200 SNPs <lb/>(~15 Kbp) for common SNPs with MAF higher than 5% separately for South, Mid <lb/>and North populations. As the mean LD (r 2 ) in P. tremula decays to less than 0.1 <lb/>within 10 Kbp (Supplementary Fig. S18A and 26 ), the use of ~15 Kbp windows <lb/>should be large enough to differentiate the footprint of selective sweeps from those <lb/>caused by neutral processes. The H12 and H2/H1 values were then averaged using a <lb/>sliding window method with window size of 10 Kbp and moving step of 5 Kbp; (iv) a <lb/>composite likelihood ratio statistic (CLR) 37 , which contrasts the likelihood of the null <lb/>hypothesis based on the genome-wide site frequency spectrum with the likelihood of <lb/>a model where the site frequency has been altered by a recent selective sweep, was <lb/>computed using SweepFinder2 38 separately for South, Mid and North <lb/>populations. SweepFinder2 is most efficient when information on the ancestral <lb/>and derived states is available for SNPs and we therefore polarized SNPs as described <lb/>in Section 5.2. The small fraction of SNPs (~3.7%) that could not be polarized were <lb/>excluded from further analysis using SweepFinder2. CLRs were calculated using <lb/>non-overlapping windows with a spacing of 2 Kbp, and the empirical site frequency <lb/>spectrum across the whole P. tremula genome was estimated using the -f option in <lb/>SweepFinder2 after including all polymorphic sites in the genome (a total of <lb/>8,007,303 SNPs). As recommended by 39 we only used sites that were polymorphic or <lb/>that represented fixed substitutions in each group of populations to scan for sweeps. <lb/>To determine whether there are significant differences of the above statistics between <lb/>the 700 Kbp region around PtFT2 gene on chromosome 10 and genome-wide <lb/>estimates, we use the same strategy to divide the genome into the windows with the <lb/>same size for each test and calculated the above statistics across the genome (Results <lb/>are shown in Supplementary Fig. S7 and Table S5). Significance for the above <lb/>statistical measurements was evaluated using Mann-Whitney tests. <lb/>To assess the scale of a genomic region that is affected by a selective sweep, we <lb/>ran coalescent simulations modeling a selective sweep in the Northern populations. <lb/>Simulations were run assuming that the selected site was located at the centre of the <lb/>simulated region. Parameters for the simulations were taken from ABC calculations <lb/>dating the selective sweep inferred in the North populations (See Section 5.7). Briefly, <lb/>we used a scaled population mutation rate (4N e µ) of 0.0081/bp, which corresponds to <lb/>the average observed diversity in the North populations. Similarly we set the scaled <lb/>population recombination rate (4N e r) to 0.0019 to match the genome-wide ratio of <lb/>r/µ=0.229 in P. tremula 26 . Analyses of the simulated data using SweepFinder2 <lb/>showed that a single selective sweep often yields multiple significant peaks across a <lb/>region spanning up to, and even exceeding, 100 Kbp (95% quartile: 148221 bp; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 19). <lb/>5.7 Dating the selective sweep in the North populations <lb/>To date the inferred selective sweep in the North populations we used the <lb/>Approximate Bayesian Computation (ABC) method described in 40 to jointly estimate <lb/>s (the strength of selection on the beneficial mutation causing the sweep) and T (the <lb/>time since the beneficial allele fixed) assuming a model of selection from a de novo <lb/>mutation (hard selective sweep). We simulated 5×10 5 independent selective sweep <lb/>events using the coalescent simulation program msms 41 . For the coalescent <lb/>simulations, the ancestries of samples were traced backwards in time using standard <lb/>coalescent methods and allowing for recombination. Selection was modeled at a <lb/>single site by applying forward simulations, assuming additive selection so that the <lb/>fitness of heterozygous and homozygous genotypes carrying the selected (derived) <lb/>allele were 1 + s/2 and 1 + s, respectively. We simulated a chromosome region <lb/>consisting of L=25000 sites and assumed a diploid effective population size of <lb/>N e =92000, a mutation rate of µ=3.75×10 -8 per base pair per generation 42 , and a <lb/>recombination rate of r=0.729×10 -8 per base pair per generation. Together these <lb/>parameters yielded a scaled population mutation rate equal to Θ=4N e µL=86.27 and a <lb/>scaled population recombination rate ρ=4N e rL=19.76. For each simulation, values for <lb/>both s and T were drawn from uniform prior distributions, log 10 (T)~U(-4,-0.5) and <lb/>log 10 (s)~U(-4,-0.5). <lb/>6. Greenhouse and field experiments <lb/>6.1 Gene expression of PtFT2 under active growth and during growth <lb/>cessation <lb/>Samples used for the expression analysis of PtFT2 were collected from both <lb/>climate chamber and the field (Sävar, 63.4°N, Umeå) conditions. For treatment in the <lb/>climate chamber, two southern clones (SwAsp018, 56.2°N, Ronneby; SwAsp023, <lb/>56.2°N, Ronneby) and two northern clones (SwAsp100, 63.9°N, Umeå; SwAsp112, <lb/>65.6°N, Luleå) were selected. Plants were grown under 23h day lengths for one <lb/>month and then transferred to 19h day length condition for 2 weeks before the start of <lb/>sampling. Field samples were collected in the Sävar common garden in early July, <lb/>2014 and samples were taken from two southern clones (SwAsp005, 56.7°N, <lb/>Simlång; SwAsp023, 56.2°N, Ronneby) and two northern clones (SwAsp100, 63.9°N, <lb/>Umeå; SwAsp116, 65.6°N, Luleå). Leaves were harvested from three different clonal <lb/>replicates to serve as biological repeats, flash-frozen in in liquid nitrogen and stored at <lb/> -80°C until sample preparation. Samples were collected at 2h intervals for a total <lb/> period of 24 h. RNA extraction for all samples was performed using a CTAB-LiCl <lb/>method 43 . CDNA synthesis was performed using the iScript cDNA Synthesis Kit <lb/>(BIO-RAD) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Quantitative real-time PCR <lb/>analyses were performed using a Roche LightCycler 480 II instrument, and the <lb/>measurements were obtained using the relative quantification method 44 . We used <lb/>primers qFT2F (5&apos;-AGCCCAAGGCCTACAGCAGGAA-3&apos;) and qFT2R (5&apos;-<lb/>GGGAATCTTTCTCTCATGAT-3&apos;) for amplifying the transcript of FT2 and qUBQF <lb/>(5&apos;-GTTGATTTTTGCTGGGAAGC-3&apos;) <lb/>and <lb/>qUBQR <lb/>(5&apos;-<lb/>GATCTTGGCCTTCACGTTGT-3&apos;) for UBQ as the internal control. <lb/>6.2 Field experiment with transgenic PtFT2 lines <lb/>Construction of the PtFT2 RNAi lines are described in detail in 45 . Transformed <lb/>plants were planted together with wild type (WT) controls in a common garden at <lb/>Våxtorp, Halland (latitude 56.4N, longitude 13.1E) in 2014. 18 replicates of each line <lb/>were planted in a complete randomized block design together with six WT controls <lb/>per block. Starting in 2015, data were collected on growth cessation, bud formation <lb/>and bud set for all trees in the common garden. From early August plants were <lb/>visually inspected roughly every five days and top shoots were scored according to a <lb/>pre-determined scoring sheet (Supplementary Fig. 20) and classified as active growth <lb/>(score 3), growth cessation (score 2), bud formation (score 1) and bud set (score 0). <lb/>Scoring was continued until all plants had completely senesced in late October. Bud <lb/>scoring data was converted to Julian date of bud set and analysed using the following <lb/>linear model: <lb/>y ij = µ + α i + β j + ε ij <lb/>where µ is an overall mean, α i is the effect of treatment i (where i is either PtFT2 <lb/>RNAi or WT) and β j is the effect of block j and ε ij are individual residual errors. <lb/></div>


			<div type="availability">7. Data availability <lb/>7.1 Sequence and SNP data <lb/>The raw sequencing reads have been deposited in NCBI&apos;s short-read archive, <lb/>SRA, under accession number PRJNA297202. In total we identified 8,007,303 SNPs <lb/>and 4,425,109 SNPs with MAF high than 5% and VCF files with SNPs (original and <lb/>phased) and SNP annotations are available to download from <lb/>ftp://plantgenie.org/Data/PopGenIE/Populus_tremula/v1.1/VCF/. <lb/>7.2 Other data <lb/>The following data is available from zendo.org (https://doi. <lb/>org/10.5281/zenodo.844372) <lb/>• Bud set genetic values (BLUPs) for all clones used in the GWAS <lb/>7.3 BASH, Perl, Python and R scripts <lb/>All scripts used for the analysis described are available in an online repository at <lb/>https://github.com/parkingvarsson/PhotoperiodLocalAdaptation <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>8. References <lb/>1. Luquez, V. et al. Natural phenological variation in aspen (Populus tremula): the <lb/>SwAsp collection. Tree Genetics &amp; Genomes 4, 279-292 (2008). <lb/>2. Bolger, A. M., Lohse, M. &amp; Usadel, B. Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for <lb/>Illumina sequence data. Bioinformatics 30, 2114-2120 (2014). <lb/>3. Sundell, D. et al. The Plant Genome Integrative Explorer Resource: <lb/>PlantGenIE.org. The New phytologist 208, 1149-1156 (2015). <lb/>4. Li, H. Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-<lb/>MEM. (2013). <lb/>5. Li, H. et al. The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics <lb/>25, 2078-2079 (2009). <lb/>6. DePristo, M. A. et al. A framework for variation discovery and genotyping using <lb/>next-generation DNA sequencing data. Nat Genet 43, 491-498 (2011). <lb/>7. Tarailo-Graovac, M. &amp; Chen, N. Using RepeatMasker to identify repetitive <lb/>elements in genomic sequences. Curr Protoc Bioinformatics Chapter 4, Unit <lb/>4.10-4.10.14 (2009). <lb/>8. Cingolani, P. et al. A program for annotating and predicting the effects of single <lb/>nucleotide polymorphisms, SnpEff: SNPs in the genome of Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster strain w1118; iso-2; iso-3. Fly (Austin) 6, 80-92 (2012). <lb/>9. Purcell, S. et al. PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-<lb/>based linkage analyses. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 81, 559-575 (2007). <lb/>10. Patterson, N., Price, A. L. &amp; Reich, D. Population structure and eigenanalysis. <lb/>PLoS Genetics 2, e190 (2006). <lb/>11. Weir, B. S. &amp; Cockerham, C. C. Estimating F-statistics for the analysis of <lb/>population structure. Evolution (1984). doi:10.2307/2408641 <lb/>12. Danecek, P. et al. The variant call format and VCFtools. Bioinformatics 27, 2156-<lb/>2158 (2011). <lb/>13. Oksanen, J. et al. vegan: Community Ecology Package. https://cran.r-<lb/>project.org/web/packages/vegan/ <lb/>14. Duforet-Frebourg, N., Luu, K., Laval, G., Bazin, É. &amp; Blum, M. G. B. Detecting <lb/>genomic signatures of natural selection with principal component analysis: <lb/>application to the 1000 genomes data. Mol Biol Evol 33, 1082-1093 (2016). <lb/>15. Storey, J. D. &amp; Tibshirani, R. Statistical significance for genomewide studies. <lb/>100, 9440-9445 (2003). <lb/>16. Hijmans, R. J., Cameron, S. E., Parra, J. L., Jones, P. G. &amp; Jarvis, A. Very high <lb/>resolution interpolated climate surfaces for global land areas. International <lb/>Journal of Climatology 25, 1965-1978 (2005). <lb/>17. Frichot, E. &amp; François, O. LEA: an R package for landscape and ecological <lb/>association studies. Methods in Ecology and Evolution 6, 925-929 (2015). <lb/>18. Frichot, É., Schoville, S. D., Bouchard, G. &amp; François, O. Testing for associations <lb/>between loci and environmental gradients using latent factor mixed models. Mol <lb/>Biol Evol 30, 1687-1699 (2013). <lb/>19. Hall, D. et al. Adaptive population differentiation in phenology across a <lb/>latitudinal gradient in European aspen (Populus tremula, L.): a comparison of <lb/>neutral markers, candidate genes and phenotypic traits. Evolution 61, 2849-<lb/>2860 (2007). <lb/>20. Ingvarsson, P. K., Garcia, M. V., Luquez, V., Hall, D. &amp; Jansson, S. Nucleotide <lb/>polymorphism and phenotypic associations within and around the phytochrome <lb/>B2 Locus in European aspen (Populus tremula, Salicaceae). Genetics 178, <lb/>2217-2226 (2008). <lb/>21. Gilmour, A. R., Gogel, B. J., Cullis, B. R. &amp; Thompson, R. ASReml User Guide <lb/>Release 3.0 (vsni.co.uk, 2009). <lb/>22. Zhou, X. &amp; Stephens, M. Genome-wide efficient mixed-model analysis for <lb/>association studies. Nat Genet 44, 821-824 (2012). <lb/>23. Vilhjálmsson, B. J. &amp; Nordborg, M. The nature of confounding in genome-wide <lb/>association studies. Nat Rev Genet 14, 1-2 (2013). <lb/>24. Browning, B. L. &amp; Browning, S. R. A unified approach to genotype imputation <lb/>and haplotype-phase inference for large data sets of trios and unrelated <lb/>individuals. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 84, 210-223 (2009). <lb/>25. Grabherr, M. G. et al. Genome-wide synteny through highly sensitive sequence <lb/>alignment: Satsuma. Bioinformatics 26, 1145-1151 (2010). <lb/>26. Wang, J., Street, N. R., Scofield, D. G. &amp; Ingvarsson, P. K. Natural selection and <lb/>recombination rate variation shape nucleotide polymorphism across the <lb/>genomes of three related Populus species. Genetics 202, 1185-1200 (2016). <lb/>27. Wang, Z. et al. Phylogeny reconstruction and hybrid analysis of Populus <lb/>(Salicaceae) based on nucleotide sequences of multiple single-copy nuclear <lb/>genes and plastid fragments. PLoS ONE 9, e103645 (2014). <lb/>28. Kirkpatrick, M. &amp; Barton, N. Chromosome inversions, local adaptation and <lb/>speciation. Genetics 173, 419-434 (2006). <lb/>29. Remington, D. L. et al. Structure of linkage disequilibrium and phenotypic <lb/>associations in the maize genome. PNAS 98, 11479-11484 (2001). <lb/>30. Supple, M. A. et al. Genomic architecture of adaptive color pattern divergence <lb/>and convergence in Heliconius butterflies. Genome Res. 23, gr.150615.112-<lb/>1257 (2013). <lb/>31. Voight, B. F., Kudaravalli, S., Wen, X. &amp; Pritchard, J. K. A map of recent positive <lb/>selection in the human genome. PLoS Biol. 4, e72 (2006). <lb/>32. Ferrer-Admetlla, A., Liang, M., Korneliussen, T. &amp; Nielsen, R. On detecting <lb/>incomplete soft or hard selective sweeps using haplotype structure. Mol Biol <lb/>Evol 31, 1275-1291 (2014). <lb/>33. Szpiech, Z. A. &amp; Hernandez, R. D. Selscan: an efficient multi-threaded program <lb/>to perform EHH-based scans for positive selection. Mol Biol Evol 31, 2824-<lb/>2827 (2014). <lb/>34. Tajima, F. Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis by DNA <lb/>polymorphism. Genetics 123, 585-595 (1989). <lb/>35. Korneliussen, T. S., Albrechtsen, A. &amp; Nielsen, R. ANGSD: Analysis of Next <lb/>Generation Sequencing Data. BMC Bioinformatics 15, 356 (2014). <lb/>36. Garud, N. R., Messer, P. W., Buzbas, E. O. &amp; Petrov, D. A. Recent selective <lb/>sweeps in North American Drosophila melanogaster show signatures of soft <lb/>sweeps. PLoS Genetics 11, e1005004 (2015). <lb/>37. Kim, Y. &amp; Stephan, W. Detecting a local signature of genetic hitchhiking along a <lb/>recombining chromosome. Genetics 160, 765-777 (2002). <lb/>38. DeGiorgio, M., Huber, C. D., Hubisz, M. J., Hellmann, I. &amp; Nielsen, R. <lb/>SweepFinder2: increased sensitivity, robustness and flexibility. Bioinformatics <lb/>32, 1895-1897 (2016). <lb/>39. Huber, C. D., DeGiorgio, M., Hellmann, I. &amp; Nielsen, R. Detecting recent <lb/>selective sweeps while controlling for mutation rate and background selection. <lb/>Mol Ecol 25, 142-156 (2016). <lb/>40. Ormond, L., Foll, M., Ewing, G. B., Pfeifer, S. P. &amp; Jensen, J. D. Inferring the age <lb/>of a fixed beneficial allele. Mol Ecol 25, 157-169 (2016). <lb/>41. Ewing, G. &amp; Hermisson, J. MSMS: a coalescent simulation program including <lb/>recombination, demographic structure and selection at a single locus. <lb/>Bioinformatics 26, 2064-2065 (2010). <lb/>42. Ingvarsson, P. K. Multilocus patterns of nucleotide polymorphism and the <lb/>demographic history of Populus tremula. Genetics 180, 329-340 (2008). <lb/>43. Xu, M., Zang, B., Yao, H. S. &amp; Huang, M. R. Isolation of high quality RNA and <lb/>molecular manipulations with various tissues of Populus. Russian journal of <lb/>plant physiology 56, 716-719 (2009). <lb/>44. Livak, K. J. &amp; Schmittgen, T. D. Analysis of relative gene expression data using <lb/>real-time quantitative PCR and the 2(-ΔΔC(T)) Method. Methods 25, 402-408 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>45. Böhlenius, H. et al. CO/FT regulatory module controls timing of flowering and <lb/>seasonal growth cessation in trees. Science 312, 1040-1043 (2006). </listBibl>

	</text>
</tei>
