<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>A novel mechanism for volitional locomotion in larval zebrash <lb/>David E. Ehrlich and David Schoppik <lb/>Depts. of Otolaryngolo, Neuroscience &amp; Physiolo, and the Neuroscience Institute, New York University Langone School of Medicine, New York, NY <lb/>
			To locomote stably, animals must coordinate voli-<lb/>tional actions that change posture with opposing re-<lb/>flexes that hold posture constant [1-8]. These conflict-<lb/>ing actions are thought to necessitate integrated con-<lb/>trol, in which reflexes are modulated to permit or even <lb/>produce volitional movements [9-14]. Here we report <lb/>that larval zebrafish (Danio rerio) utilize a simpler <lb/>control scheme featuring independent volitional and <lb/>reflexive movements. We present behavioral evidence <lb/>that larvae swim in depth by appending destabilizing <lb/>trunk rotations to steer with independent rotations to <lb/>balance. When we manipulated buoyancy to deflect <lb/>fish up or down, they redirected steering without co-<lb/>ordinated changes to their balance reflex. As balance <lb/>developed and increasingly opposed destabilization-<lb/>mediated steering, larvae acquired compensatory use <lb/>of their pectoral fins to steer. Removing the pectoral <lb/>fins from older larvae impaired steering but preserved <lb/>the strong balance reflex. Consequentially, older lar-<lb/>vae without fins were strikingly less maneuverable -<lb/>unable to revert to destabilization-mediated steering <lb/>-revealing a rigidity inherent within the framework <lb/>of independent volitional and reflexive control. Lar-<lb/>val zebrafish therefore produce effective but inflexi-<lb/>ble locomotion by sequencing independent volitional <lb/>and reflexive movements. These results reveal a sim-<lb/>ple control scheme, applicable for robotic design, that <lb/>solves the general problem of coordinating volitional <lb/>movements with the vital reflexes that oppose them. <lb/></front>

			<body>Animals destabilize their bodies to move, complicating the <lb/>challenge of maintaining balance []. For example, humans <lb/>walk in &quot;controlled falls,&quot; toppling forward with each step be-<lb/>fore regaining stability []. The conict between movement <lb/>and stability is pervasive, but a simple body plan constrains the <lb/>problem for young zebrash. During the rst days of swim-<lb/>ming, zebrash larvae possess largely inefectual ns and sim-<lb/>ply propel where they point [, ]. Larvae must therefore ro-<lb/>tate away from horizontal to climb or dive for a number of vi-<lb/>tal behaviors, including prey capture, predator evasion, buoy-<lb/>ancy control, and circadian migration [-]. However, lar-<lb/>vae also exhibit a righting reex, a tendency to reorient towards <lb/>a preferred posture near horizontal [, ] (Figure A). Lar-<lb/>vae are therefore a simpler model system faced with a universal <lb/>challenge: to integrate reexes into locomotion so as to permit <lb/>mobility but maintain stability. <lb/>Due to their small size, larvae swim intermittently, alternat-<lb/>ing between passive periods when they are rotated and pushed <lb/>by external forces, and active bouts when they swim and ad-<lb/>just their posture [-]. Accordingly, freely-swimming lar-<lb/>vae spontaneously vary their posture and depth, but tend to <lb/>remain near horizontal (Figure B) []. Therefore, to dene <lb/>how larvae controlled their bodies to achieve both mobility <lb/>and stability, we examined their posture during spontaneous <lb/>swim bouts at week post-fertilization (wpf). First, we ex-<lb/>amined when larvae made spontaneous trunk rotations that <lb/>permitted changes to depth -volitional control of posture we <lb/>termed &quot;steering.&quot; Second, we determined when larvae exhib-<lb/>ited their righting reex -responses to instability in which they <lb/>reoriented towards their preferred posture. <lb/>We found that larvae changed their elevation by steering up <lb/>or down while they accelerated during bouts. Specically, we <lb/>examined whether rotations during a bout impacted its trajec-<lb/>tory, or if larvae propelled where they pointed when a bout <lb/>began (the null trajectory). Deviations from the null trajec-<lb/>tory were positively correlated with trunk rotations during <lb/>bouts, particularly those during the msec before speed <lb/>peaked (r=.; Figure C, D). This window corresponds to <lb/>the greatest acceleration each bout (Supplemental Figure S) <lb/>and includes rotations that precede trunk rotation (Supple-<lb/>mental Figure S). Therefore, larvae steer by rotating their <lb/>trunks at the start of a bout. <lb/>Larvae temporally ofset steering and their righting reex, ro-<lb/>tating towards their preferred posture while decelerating. In <lb/>control theoretic terms, the reex provides negative feedback <lb/>to reduce postural error, the extent posture deviates from its <lb/>&quot;set point.&quot; Postural error at the start of a bout was neg-<lb/>atively correlated with rotations during the bout, indicating <lb/>that bouts acutely stabilize posture (Figure E). In particular, <lb/>the best correlated rotations occurred for msec afer speed <lb/>peaked (r=-.; Figure F), corresponding to the greatest de-<lb/>celeration (Supplemental Figure S). Larvae rotated towards <lb/>an empirical set point, the posture at which no balance feed-<lb/>back was expected (intercept of the best-t line to pre-bout <lb/>posture and righting rotation), just nose-up to horizontal (. <lb/>± .°). Larvae therefore counteract destabilization, including <lb/>volitional rotations away from horizontal, while they deceler-<lb/>ate. <lb/>We tested whether the temporally dissociable rotations for <lb/>steering and righting might be independent. Surprisingly, we <lb/>found that steering and righting were not correlated (r=-.; <lb/>Figure G). These data indicate that larvae locomote by se-<lb/>quencing nose-up/down rotations that steer with indepen-<lb/>dent rotations that balance (Figure H). Accordingly, righting <lb/>rotations did not correlate with trajectory changes (r=-.; <lb/>Supplemental Figure SA), suggesting larvae balance without <lb/>directly impacting translation. Furthermore, steering rota-<lb/>tions were not correlated with postural error before a bout (r=-<lb/>.; Supplemental Figure SB), such that movement is not <lb/>constrained by stability. We therefore conclude that steering <lb/>and righting are both sequential and independent. <lb/>We next tested whether steering and righting were under in-<lb/>dependent control. We measured how larvae maintain eleva-<lb/>tion when challenged -a problem that could be solved by <lb/>modulating either steering or balance. To climb, for instance, <lb/>a larva could steer upwards, away from its posture set point <lb/>(Figure A, le); alternatively, a larva could reorient nose-up <lb/>using its righting reex, by biasing the set point upwards (Fig-<lb/>ure A, right) [, ]. Complementarily, larvae could facili-<lb/>tate steering by weakening their reex, permitting greater de-<lb/>viations from horizontal. Can larvae efectively control their <lb/>swims while steering and righting independently? <lb/>To challenge larvae to climb and dive, we leveraged their <lb/>propensity to actively maintain position [, ]. During pas-<lb/>sive periods between bouts, larvae are moved by gravity and <lb/>buoyancy (Supplemental Figure S) []. They tend to be <lb/>
			denser than water [-] and, consequently, tended to sink <lb/>between bouts (Figure B) []. Under typical conditions <lb/>larvae counteracted sinking by weakly biasing their bouts up-<lb/>wards, consistent with their natural nose-up bias to posture <lb/>(Figure C). <lb/>If we displaced larvae vertically by manipulating their buoy-<lb/>ancy, they biased swims to climb or dive. To exacerbate sink-<lb/>ing we altered the swim bladder, a sac larvae typically inate <lb/>with air from the surface ⇠ days post-fertilization []. Lar-<lb/>vae instead inate their swim bladders with denser paran oil <lb/>if raised with oil on the water&apos;s surface [] (Figure D, top). <lb/>Larvae with oil-lled swim bladders sank more between bouts <lb/>and biased those bouts systematically upwards, compared to <lb/>siblings with air-lled swim bladders (Figure E, top). In con-<lb/>trast, when we increased the force of buoyancy by placing lar-<lb/>vae acutely in a low concentration (.%) of glycerol, larvae <lb/>tended to rise between bouts and bias those bouts downwards <lb/>(Figure D, E, bottom). <lb/>Larvae could maintain elevation when challenged by modu-<lb/>lating either their steering and/or their righting reex. Denser <lb/>larvae climbed by steering upwards (Figure F; paired t-<lb/>test with Bonferroni correction: t =., p&lt;.), while <lb/>more buoyant larvae dove by steering downwards (t =-., <lb/>p&lt;.). In addition, denser larvae modulated their posture <lb/>set point, using their righting reex to skew posture, and there-<lb/>fore trajectory, upwards (p&lt;., t =.; Figure G, top). <lb/>However, larvae with elevated buoyancy did not adjust their <lb/>set point (p&gt;., t =-.; Figure G, bottom), meaning set <lb/>point modulation was selective. <lb/>If steering and righting are independent, larvae ought bias the <lb/>former up or down without coordinating the reex set point. <lb/>Crucially, we found that individual changes to steering and set <lb/>point were uncorrelated, whether larvae were climbing (Figure <lb/>H; Spearman&apos;s ρ = .) or diving (ρ = .). Furthermore, lar-<lb/>vae did not aid steering by suppressing reex strength, as mea-<lb/>sured by its gain -the proportion of postural error canceled <lb/>by the average bout (Table S; Oil vs. Air: t =-., p&gt;.; <lb/>.% vs. % glycerol: t =., p&gt;.). Together, these data <lb/>show that when challenged, zebrash larvae control elevation <lb/>by independently modulating the volitional and reexive com-<lb/>ponents of locomotion. <lb/>Independent control of steering and righting poses a poten-<lb/>tial problem as sh mature. Young larvae make destabilizing <lb/>rotations to steer, meaning developmental improvements to <lb/>stability [] will impair steering unless larvae compensate. <lb/>However, if steering and righting mature independently, larvae <lb/>would be unable to preserve mobility by ensuring that balance <lb/>does not come to dominate. Evidence that larvae are unable <lb/>to check their righting reex to maintain mobility would sup-<lb/>port the hypothesis of independent control. Therefore, we in-<lb/>vestigated and manipulated how steering and righting change <lb/>throughout early development. <lb/>We found that improvements to balance permit greater sta-<lb/>bility as sh develop. We measured locomotion in siblings <lb/>from to wpf (n= groups of sh), and found that older <lb/>larvae prolonged the balance phase of their bouts (Figure A). <lb/>With age, each bout came to reduce a greater proportion <lb/>of postural error, equating to larger reex gain (Figure B; <lb/>main efect of age: F (,) =., p&lt;.; main efect of clutch: <lb/>F (,) =., p&gt;.). When pooling all bouts, the gain dou-<lb/>bled from . at wpf ( bouts) to . at wpf ( <lb/>bouts). Reex gain was inversely correlated with posture vari-<lb/>ation, such that older larvae better constrained their trunks <lb/>about their preferred posture (Figure C; Spearman&apos;s ρ = -., <lb/>p&lt;.). Maturation of the righting reex therefore afords <lb/>greater stability while swimming. <lb/>As stability increased, larvae maintained maneuverability <lb/>through parallel improvements to steering. At one wpf, larvae <lb/>propelled where they pointed, such that steering rotations pro-<lb/>
			vided a proportional change to swim trajectory -correspond-<lb/>ing to steering gains near (Figure D,E; Theil-Sen estimated <lb/>slope of trajectory vs. posture; Supplemental Figure S). Older <lb/>larvae could efectively climb or dive while remaining closer to <lb/>horizontal, having gained additional control over their move-<lb/>ments. They did not simply propel where they pointed, but <lb/>skewed trajectories to amplify steering rotations, giving a steer-<lb/>ing gain much larger than (Figure D,E; two-way ANOVA, <lb/>main efect of age: F (,) =., p&lt;.; main efect of clutch: <lb/>F (,) =., p&gt;.). Therefore, developing larvae came to <lb/>swim with less trunk destabilization, much as human toddlers <lb/>walk more stably by learning to swing their arms [], and <lb/>gymnasts learn to prioritize trunk stability in their movements <lb/>[]. <lb/>We found that steering improvements reect emergent n <lb/>use. Mature sh use their pectoral ns, homologues of am-<lb/>niote forelimbs, to steer in depth [, -], but week-old <lb/>zebrash possess minimally functional pectoral ns []. Af-<lb/>ter surgical removal of the pectoral ns, all larvae propelled <lb/>precisely where they pointed, with steering gains reduced to <lb/>(Figure F; two-way ANOVA, main efect of n removal: <lb/>F (,) =., p&lt;.; main efect of age: F (,) =., <lb/>p&lt;.; interaction efect: F (,) =., p&lt;.; n= <lb/>clutches). Fin removal also abolished the acquired agility to <lb/>make large trajectory changes from one bout to the next (Sup-<lb/>plemental Figure S). While the efect of n removal was <lb/>large at wpf, cutting steering gain nearly in half (paired t-<lb/>test with Bonferroni correction, t =., p&lt;.), larvae at <lb/>wpf also exhibited signicant impairment (t =., p&lt;.). <lb/>For n use to increase steering gain, larvae must skew move-<lb/>ments upwards when their trunks are oriented up, and down-<lb/>wards when oriented down, suggesting larvae actively coordi-<lb/>nate their trunks and ns to steer. Together, these data sug-<lb/>gest larvae increasingly use pectoral ns to amplify the efects <lb/>of trunk rotation on their swimming movements. <lb/>We found that n development selectively impacted steering. <lb/>Aside from efects on the direction of locomotion, larvae swam <lb/>comparably afer loss of the ns. Fin removal had no impact <lb/>on their rate of swimming or the speed and displacement of <lb/>their bouts (Supplemental Table S). Furthermore, larvae pro-<lb/>duced comparable trunk rotations afer loss of the ns (Supple-<lb/>mental Table S; main efect of n removal on angular speed: <lb/>F (,) =., p&gt;.). The pectoral ns therefore complement <lb/>trunk-based steering but are not necessary to rotate the trunk. <lb/>Importantly, n-derived improvements to steering progressed <lb/>distinctly from the maturation of the righting reex, as changes <lb/>to steering and reex gains were uncorrelated throughout de-<lb/>velopment (Figure G; Spearman&apos;s ρ = ). Across clutches, lar-<lb/>vae improved steering and righting to diferent extents and at <lb/>diferent rates (Figure B,E). Thus steering and righting de-<lb/>velop complementarily, even as their control remains indepen-<lb/>dent. <lb/>Independent control made larvae inexible, unable to adapt <lb/>steering when challenged. Specically, older larvae could not <lb/>modulate their reex to restore efective trunk-based steering <lb/>when their ns were removed. Forced once more to propel <lb/>where they point, nless larvae at wpf must deviate from hor-<lb/>izontal to climb or dive. However, they failed to reduce their <lb/>reex gains afer n removal (Figure H, Supplemental Figure <lb/>SA; main efect of n removal: F (,) =., p&gt;.; main ef-<lb/>fect of age: F (,) =., p&lt;.) and therefore continued to <lb/>tightly restrict trunk posture afer n removal (Supplemental <lb/>Figure SB; two-way ANOVA of posture variance by clutch, <lb/>main efect of age: F (,) =., p&lt;.; main efect of n re-<lb/>moval: F (,) =., p&gt;.). Greater stability at wpf there-<lb/>fore equated to less maneuverability without the ns, evident <lb/>in reduced variation of swim trajectory (Figure I; main efect <lb/>of n removal: F (,) =., p&lt;.; paired t-test with Bon-<lb/>ferroni correction at wpf: t =., p&lt;.; at wpf: t =., <lb/>p&gt;.). By reverting larvae to undeveloped steering, we dis-<lb/>covered a limitation of their locomotion -age-expected voli-<lb/>tional and reexive control are necessary for proper swimming, <lb/>as the two are age-matched to achieve stability and maneuver-<lb/>ability. <lb/>By producing efective locomotion across a range of param-<lb/>eters for steering and righting, independent control allowed <lb/>larvae to modify existing movement patterns, a prerequisite <lb/>for locomotor development [-]. However, independent <lb/>control lef larvae unable to manage the trade-of between sta-<lb/>bility and maneuverability, to compensate for n loss by re-<lb/>verting to the trunk-based steering of younger larvae. Tempo-<lb/>ral dissociation thus provides a simple but limited means for <lb/>new swimmers to avoid conict between steering and stabiliz-<lb/>ing movements. <lb/>Temporary suppression of righting reexes may be a useful <lb/>and conserved mechanism to sequence volitional and reex-<lb/>ive control. Cycles of de-and re-stabilization are also appar-<lb/>ent in human gait []. Vestibular stimulation impacts step-<lb/>ping late but not early in the gait cycle [], when reexes may <lb/>
			be suppressed to avoid interference with volitional control of <lb/>walking. A neural means to inactivate vestibular reexes has <lb/>been described during voluntary movements of the eyes [-<lb/>], and an analogous circuit may exist to inactivate descend-<lb/>ing vestibular commands during locomotion. Modulation of <lb/>sensory signals according to gait cycle phase is a general mech-<lb/>anism to appropriately adjust locomotion to reect ongoing <lb/>sensation []. <lb/>In summary, our experiments show that efective locomo-<lb/>tion, in this case stable maneuvering under water, can emerge <lb/>from an unexpectedly straightforward control scheme with in-<lb/>dependent volitional and reexive movements. All animals <lb/>that move themselves must permit instability in some form <lb/>[]; the larval zebrash provides a natural proof-of-principle <lb/>for one of the simplest possible solutions to this general prob-<lb/>lem -destabilize oneself to move, then re-stabilize when n-<lb/>ished. Larvae also reveal one shortcoming of such rudimentary <lb/>control, lacking the exibility to revert to earlier modes of lo-<lb/>comotion as they develop. Requiring no coordination beyond <lb/>that which sequences volitional and reexive components, in-<lb/>dependent control is likely simpler to neurally implement than <lb/>the integrated control of more advanced locomotion [, ], <lb/>and thus well-suited for robotic control. Animals that move <lb/>and then balance may be a developmental and evolutionary <lb/>intermediary between those that move without balance and <lb/>those that move and balance in concert. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Fish Care <lb/>All procedures involving zebrash larvae (Danio rerio) were <lb/>approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Commit-<lb/>tee of New York University. Fertilized eggs were collected <lb/>from in-crosses of a breeding population of Schoppik lab wild-<lb/>type zebrash maintained at .°C on a standard / hour <lb/>light/dark cycle. Before dpf, larvae were maintained at densi-<lb/>ties of -larvae per petri dish of cm diameter, lled with <lb/>-mL E with . ppm methylene blue. Subsequently, lar-<lb/>vae were maintained on system water in -L tanks at densities <lb/>of -per tank and fed twice daily. Larvae received powdered <lb/>food (Otohime A, Reed Mariculture, Campbell, CA) until <lb/>dpf and brine shrimp thereafer. Larvae were checked visually <lb/>for swim bladder ination before all behavioral measurements. <lb/>Physical manipulations <lb/>To generate larvae with swim bladders lled with paran oil, <lb/>dpf larvae were visually checked for the absence of swim blad-<lb/>ders and transferred to mL conical tubes (Falcon, Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientic) at a density of larvae per tube, as previ-<lb/>ously []. The tubes were lled with mL E containing <lb/>methylene blue (as above), then topped with mL paran oil <lb/>(VWR, Radnor, PA) and incubated until dpf for experimen-<lb/>tation. Control siblings were maintained similarly in mL E <lb/>in conical tubes without an oil surface. <lb/>Pectoral ns were removed surgically from larvae anes-<lb/>thetized in .% ethyl--aminobenzoic acid ethyl ester <lb/>(MESAB, Sigma-Aldrich E, St. Louis, MO). Pairs <lb/>of anesthetized, length-matched siblings were immobilized <lb/>dorsal-up in % low-melting temperature agar (Thermo Fisher <lb/>Scientic ), and both pectoral ns of one larva were re-<lb/>moved by pulling the base laterally with forceps. Then, the <lb/>altered larva and its control sibling were freed from the agar <lb/>with a scalpel and allowed to recover in E for -hours prior <lb/>to behavioral measurement. <lb/>Swimming measurement <lb/>Data were analyzed from a previous study of larvae from <lb/>each of clutches at wpf, and from larvae with oil-lled swim <lb/>bladders and control siblings at days post-fertilization []. <lb/>For measuring efects of pectoral n removal, new data were <lb/>captured identically from -larvae per condition per clutch <lb/>(n=) at and wpf. For comparing swimming in and .% <lb/>glycerol solutions, larvae per condition per clutch (n=). Sib-<lb/>lings were transferred to a glass tank (/G/ xx mm, <lb/>Starna Cells, Inc., Atascadero, CA) lled with -mL E <lb/>and recorded for hours unless otherwise noted. The thin <lb/>tank ( mm) maximized the time the sh spent swimming in <lb/>the imaging plane. The enclosure containing the tank was kept <lb/>on the same / hour light/dark cycle as the aquaculture fa-<lb/>cility using overhead LEDs, which maintained water tempera-<lb/>ture at °C. Video was captured using a digital camera (BFLY-<lb/>PGE-SM, Point Grey Research, Richmond, BC, Canada) <lb/>equipped with a close-focusing, manual zoom lens (-mm <lb/>Macro Zoom Lens, Navitar, Inc., Rochester, NY, USA) <lb/>with f-stop set to to maximize depth of focus. The eld-of-<lb/>view, approximately x cm, was aligned concentrically with <lb/>the tank face. A W nm infrared LED backlight (eBay) was <lb/>transmitted through an aspheric condenser lens with a difuser <lb/>(ACL-DG-B, ThorLabs, NJ), and an infrared lter (-<lb/>, Edmund Optics, NJ) was placed in the light path before <lb/>the imaging lens. <lb/>Larvae with visually-conrmed paran oil-lled swimblad-<lb/>ders and control siblings were tested in parallel as above, lar-<lb/>vae per clutch per condition (n=), for hours starting the <lb/>day of dpf. When imaging larvae with oil-lled swim blad-<lb/>ders, E in the tanks was topped with a thin layer of paran <lb/>oil, outside the eld of view, to prevent supplementary ina-<lb/>tion with air over the course of testing. <lb/>To increase the density of the swimming medium, larvae <lb/>were acutely imaged in solutions of glycerol (Sigma-Aldrich, <lb/>St. Louis, MO). Three sets of siblings from each clutch (n= <lb/>clutches) were measured in parallel at dpf, in three concen-<lb/>trations of glycerol dissolved in E (, ., and % by volume). <lb/>Data were collected for only hours in glycerol solution to <lb/>minimize physical buoyancy adaptation. <lb/>Video acquisition and detection <lb/>Video acquisition was performed as previously []. Digital <lb/>video was recorded at Hz with an exposure time of ms, and <lb/>kinematic data were extracted online using the NI-IMAQ vi-<lb/>sion acquisition environment of LabVIEW (National Instru-<lb/>ments Corporation, Austin, TX, USA). Background images <lb/>were subtracted from live video, intensity thresholding and <lb/>particle detection were applied, and age-specic exclusion cri-<lb/>teria for particle maximum Feret diameter (the greatest dis-<lb/>tance between two parallel planes restricting the particle) were <lb/>used to identify larvae in each image. The position of the vi-<lb/>sual center of mass and the trunk posture (orientation of the <lb/>trunk in the pitch, or nose-up/down, axis) were collected each <lb/>frame. Trunk posture was dened as the orientation, relative <lb/>to horizontal, of the line passing through the visual centroid <lb/>that minimizes the visual moment of inertia, such that a larva <lb/>with trunk posture zero has its longitudinal axis approximately <lb/>horizontal. <lb/>Behavior analysis <lb/>Data analysis and modeling were performed using Matlab <lb/>(MathWorks, Natick, MA, USA). Epochs of consecutively <lb/>saved frames lasting at least . sec were incorporated in subse-<lb/>quent analyses if () they contained only one larva and () were <lb/>captured during the last hours of the light phase of the light-<lb/>dark cycle, to minimize efects of light onset. Instantaneous <lb/>diferences of body particle centroid position were used to cal-<lb/>culate swim speed. Consecutively detected bouts faster than <lb/>Hz were merged into single bouts. Larvae with paran <lb/>oil-lled swimbladders infrequently sank at speeds exceeding <lb/>mm/sec. For these larvae and control siblings with air-lled <lb/>swimbladders, bouts were excluded if the movement vector <lb/>was pointed vertically down (below -°to horizontal; about <lb/>% of bouts). <lb/>Bouts were excluded if initiated from a vertical orientation <lb/>(&gt;°or &lt;-°, constituting of , total bouts) due to <lb/>ambiguous detection of vertical up and down postures. The <lb/>posture set-point was calculated as the y-intercept of the best-<lb/>t line to pre-bout posture vs. late change in posture. The <lb/>gain of the righting reex was computed as the opposite of the <lb/>slope of the best t line of posture change (from the time of <lb/>maximal bout speed to msec later) to the pre-bout pos-<lb/>ture ( msec prior to maximal speed). Developmental trajec-<lb/>tories were analyzed by Two-way ANOVA treating clutch as <lb/>a categorical factor and age as a continuous factor. Trajectory <lb/>of a swim bout was dened as the direction of the translation <lb/>vector from msec before to msec afer max speed was <lb/>reached. The change in trajectory was the diference between <lb/>this trajectory and the pre-bout posture, such that a change in <lb/>trajectory of zero described a larvae that swam directly where <lb/>it pointed at the start of a bout. Changes in trajectory between <lb/>successive bouts were compared based on ts to the mean cu-<lb/>mulative probability distributions for clutches at a given age. <lb/>Scale factors of the best-t Weibull distributions were analyzed <lb/>with two-way ANOVA and pairwise t-tests with Bonferroni <lb/>correction. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data sharing <lb/>All raw data and analysis code are available online at <lb/>http://www.schoppiklab.com/ <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>Research was supported by the National Institute on Deaf-<lb/>ness and Communication Disorders of the National Insti-<lb/>tutes of Health under award number DC. The au-<lb/>thors would like to thank Katherine Harmon, Marie Greaney, <lb/>Basak Sevinc, Eva Lancaster, Fernando Fuentes, Tim Gerson, <lb/>Shane Hunt, and Belinda Sun for assistance with animal hus-<lb/>bandry; Simon Sun for apparatus construction; Katherine <lb/>Nagel, Michael Long, Rob Froemke, Nicolas Tritsch, Kishore <lb/>Kuchibhotla, Katherine Eyring, Damon Lamb, Sam McKen-<lb/>zie, and members of the Schoppik and Nagel labs for helpful <lb/>comments. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: DE and DS, Methodology: DE and DS, <lb/>Investigation: DE, Visualization: DE, Writing: DE, Editing: <lb/>DE and DS, Funding Acquisition: DS, Supervision: DS. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Competing Interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>Bibliography <lb/>. V. S. Gurnkel and M. L. Shik. The Control of Posture and Locomotion, pages -. Springer US, Boston, MA, . <lb/>. Sten Grillner. Locomotion in vertebrates: central mechanisms and reex interaction. Physiological Reviews, ():-, . <lb/>. William B Kristan Jr. and Ronald L Calabrese. Rhythmic swimming activity in neurones of the isolated nerve cord of the leech. Journal of Experimental <lb/>Biolo, ():-, . <lb/>. DA Winter. Human balance and posture control during standing and walking. Gait &amp; Posture, ():-, dec . <lb/>. W. P. Chan. Visual input to the eferent control system of a y&apos;s &quot;Gyroscope&quot;. Science, ():-, apr . <lb/>. E.Paul Zehr and Richard B. Stein. What functions do reexes serve during human locomotion? Progress in Neurobiolo, ():-, jun . <lb/>. Douglas G. Stuart. Integration of posture and movement: Contributions of sherrington, hess, and bernstein. Human Movement Science, (-):-<lb/>, oct . <lb/>. Paul W. Webb and Daniel Weihs. Stability versus maneuvering: Challenges for stability during swimming by shes. Integrative and Comparative <lb/>Biolo, ():-, may . <lb/>. Erich von Holst and Horst Mittelstaedt. Das reaferenzprinzip. Naturwissenschaen, ():-, . <lb/>. Thomas A. Easton. On the normal use of reexes: The hypothesis that reexes form the basic language of the motor program permits simple, exible <lb/>specications of voluntary movements and allows fruitful speculation. American Scientist, ():-, . <lb/>. M. B. Berkinblit, A. G. Feldman, and O. I. Fukson. Adaptability of innate motor patterns and motor control mechanisms. Behavioral and Brain <lb/>Sciences, ():, dec . <lb/>. Joseph McIntyre and Emilio Bizzi. Servo hypotheses for the biological control of movement. Journal of motor behavior, ():-, . <lb/>. Mark Latash. Evolution of motor control: From reexes and motor programs to the equilibrium-point hypothesis. Journal of Human Kinetics, (-), <lb/>jan . <lb/>. Emmanuel Guigon. Active control of bias for the control of posture and movement. Journal of neurophysiolo, ():-, . <lb/>. WR Hess. Teleokinetisches und ereismatisches kräfesystem in der biomotorik. Helv Physiol Pharmacol Acta, :C-C, . <lb/>. Jacquelin Perry, Jon R Davids, et al. Gait analysis: normal and pathological function. Journal of Pediatric Orthopaedics, ():, . <lb/>. Yuri Glebovich Aleyev. Nekton. Dr. W. Junk, . <lb/>. Melina E Hale. Developmental change in the function of movement systems: transition of the pectoral ns between respiratory and locomotor roles <lb/>in zebrash. Integrative and comparative biolo, ():-, . <lb/>. E. M. Goolish and K. Okutake. Lack of gas bladder ination by the larvae of zebrash in the absence of an air-water interface. Journal of Fish Biolo, <lb/>():-, nov . <lb/>. Arjun Nair, Grigor Azatian, and Matthew J McHenry. The kinematics of directional control in the fast start of zebrash larvae. Journal of Experimental <lb/>Biolo, ():-, . <lb/>. Qian Lin and Suresh Jesuthasan. Masking of a circadian behavior in larval zebrash involves the thalamo-habenula pathway. Scientic Reports, (), <lb/>jun . <lb/>. Wolfgang Pfeifer. Equilibrium orientation in sh. Academic Press, . <lb/>. David E Ehrlich and David Schoppik. Control of movement initiation underlies the development of balance. Current biolo, ():-, . <lb/>. Lee A. Fuiman and Paul W. Webb. Ontogeny of routine swimming activity and performance in zebra danios (teleostei: Cyprinidae). Animal Be-<lb/>haviour, ():-, feb . <lb/>. Matthew J. McHenry and George Lauder. The mechanical scaling of coasting in zebrash (danio rerio). Journal of Experimental Biolo, <lb/>():-, jun . <lb/>. PA Merton. Speculations on the servo-control of movement. In Ciba Foundation Symposium -The Spinal Cord, pages -. Wiley Online <lb/>Library, . <lb/>. GP Arnold. Rheotropism in shes. Biological reviews, ():-, . <lb/>. Pablo Oteiza, Iris Odstrcil, George Lauder, Ruben Portugues, and Florian Engert. A novel mechanism for mechanosensory-based rheotaxis in larval <lb/>zebrash. Nature, ():-, jul . <lb/>. R. McNeill Alexander. Functional Design in Fishes. Hutchinson University Library, rst edition, jan . <lb/>. Benjamin W. Lindsey, Frank M. Smith, and Roger P. Croll. From ination to otation: Contribution of the swimbladder to whole-body density and <lb/>swimming depth during development of the zebrash ( danio rerio ). Zebrash, ():-, mar . <lb/>. William J. Stewart and Matthew J. McHenry. Sensing the strike of a predator sh depends on the specic gravity of a prey sh. Journal of Experimental <lb/>Biolo, ():-, oct . <lb/>. Annick Ledebt. Changes in arm posture during the early acquisition of walking. Infant Behavior and Development, ():-, jan . <lb/>. L Mouchnino, R Aurenty, J Massion, and A Pedotti. Coordination between equilibrium and head-trunk orientation during leg movement: a new <lb/>strategy build up by training. Journal of Neurophysiolo, ():-, . <lb/>. P. W. Webb. Control of posture, depth, and swimming trajectories of shes. Integrative and Comparative Biolo, ():-, feb . <lb/>. George V Lauder and Eliot G Drucker. Morphology and experimental hydrodynamics of sh n control surfaces. IEEE Journal of Oceanic Engi-<lb/>neering, ():-, . <lb/>. Mark W Westneat, Dean H Thorsen, Jefrey A Walker, and Melina E Hale. Structure, function, and neural control of pectoral ns in shes. IEEE <lb/>Journal of Oceanic Engineering, ():-, . <lb/>. John C Fentress. The development of coordination. Journal of Motor Behavior, ():-, . <lb/>. Michael G Wade and Harold Thomas Anthony Whiting. Motor development in children: Aspects of coordination and control. Martinus Nijhof, . <lb/>. Esther Thelen. Motor development: A new synthesis. American Psychologist, ():-, . <lb/>. Leah R. Bent, J. Timothy Inglis, and Bradford J. McFadyen. Vestibular contributions across the execution of a voluntary forward step. Experimental <lb/>Brain Research, ():-, jan . <lb/>. K. E. Cullen, T. Belton, and R. A. McCrea. A non-visual mechanism for voluntary cancellation of the vestibulo-ocular reex. Experimental Brain <lb/>Research, ():-, Jan . <lb/>. Kathleen E. Cullen and Jeferson E. Roy. A neural correlate for vestibulo-ocular reex suppression during voluntary eye-head gaze shifs. Nature <lb/>Neuroscience, ():-, sep . <lb/>. Robert A McCrea, Greg T Gdowski, Richard Boyle, and Timothy Belton. Firing behavior of vestibular neurons during active and passive head <lb/>movements: vestibulo-spinal and other non-eye-movement related neurons. Journal of Neurophysiolo, ():-, . <lb/>. Jeferson E Roy and Kathleen E Cullen. Selective processing of vestibular reaference during self-generated head motion. Journal of Neuroscience, <lb/>():-, . <lb/>. Franc ¸ois M. Lambert, Denis Combes, John Simmers, and Hans Straka. Gaze stabilization by eference copy signaling without sensory feedback during <lb/>vertebrate locomotion. Current Biolo, ():-, sep . <lb/>. Serge Rossignol, Réjean Dubuc, and Jean-Pierre Gossard. Dynamic sensorimotor interactions in locomotion. Physiological reviews, ():-, <lb/>. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure : Zebrash larvae swim with independent rotations that steer and balance. (A) Larvae propel where they point, and must <lb/>steer in depth by rotating away from horizontal. An opposing righting reex maintains them near horizontal, via rotations towards a <lb/>preferred posture -the reex &quot;set point.&quot; (B) Positions of a wpf larva during a representative swimming epoch. Trajectories of swim <lb/>bouts are depicted as arrows (top). Peaks of swim speed corresponding to the bouts coincide with fast rotations of the body in the <lb/>nose-up/down (pitch) axis (bottom). (C) The relationship (Pearson&apos;s correlation coecient) between instantaneous trunk rotations <lb/>throughout the bouts with deviations from null trajectories. Bouts were aligned by peak swim speed (top). The red &quot;steering&quot; window <lb/>contains the largest positive correlation between changes to trajectory and posture. Data are plotted for individual clutches (sibling <lb/>groups, thin lines, n=) and their mean (thick line). (D) Deviation from the null trajectory is plotted versus trunk rotation across the <lb/>steering window (red in C), for each of observed bouts. The line conveys means for bins of bouts. (E) The relationship (Pear-<lb/>son&apos;s correlation coecient) between instantaneous trunk rotations with the pre-bout posture ( msec before peak swim speed) for <lb/>bouts aligned by peak swim speed (top). The tan &quot;righting&quot; window contains the largest negative correlation. (F) Trunk rotation across <lb/>the righting window (tan in E) is plotted as a function of pre-bout posture for bouts in (D). The empirical posture set point, com-<lb/>puted as the best-t line intercept, is indicated with a vertical dashed line. (G) Balancing rotations are plotted as a function of steering <lb/>rotations for the bouts in (D). (H) Schematic depicting how larvae swim in depth -by rst making steering rotations independent <lb/>from initial posture, then attaining speed, and nally with righting rotations that are independent from how they steered. <lb/>Figure : Larvae climb and dive by independently modulating their steering and righting rotations. (A) Larvae could theoretically <lb/>climb by steering upwards away from their reex set point (le) or adjusting that set-point upwards (right). (B) Schematic of dominant <lb/>forces -gravity and buoyancy -that act on larvae while passive between bouts. Polar probability distributions (right) show movement <lb/>trajectories between bouts (at speeds &lt; mm•sec ) for individual clutches (shaded, n=) and pooled data (line) at wpf. (C) Schematic <lb/>of the dominant force -thrust -that acts on larvae during bouts. Polar probability distributions (right) show trajectories of bouts <lb/>on identical scale to (B). The empirical reex set point is indicated with a dashed line. (D) Larvae with oil-lled swim bladders were <lb/>subjected to a greater force of gravity (top), while larvae swimming in glycerol were subjected to a greater force of buoyancy (bottom). <lb/>(E) Polar histograms depict movement trajectories while passive (le) and of bouts (right) for larvae with oil-lled swim bladders or <lb/>siblings with air-lled swim bladders (top), as well as larvae in .% glycerol and siblings in % glycerol (bottom). (F) Median steering <lb/>rotations of larvae with oil-lled swim bladders or siblings with air-lled swim bladders (top, n= clutches of larvae each), and larvae <lb/>in .% or % glycerol (bottom, n= clutches of larvae each). * p¡., paired t-test with Bonferroni correction. (G) Reex set point <lb/>for larvae with oil-lled swim bladders or siblings with air-lled swim bladders (top), as well as larvae in .% glycerol and siblings in <lb/>% glycerol (bottom). NS: not signicant. (H) Efects of swim bladder (top) or glycerol manipulations (bottom) on reex set point <lb/>versus steering rotation, with bootstrapped % condence intervals. Spearman&apos;s rank correlation coecients equal . (top) and <lb/>. (bottom). <lb/>Figure : Steering and righting mature independently. (A) As in Figure E, Pearson&apos;s correlation coecient relates instantaneous trunk <lb/>rotations with the pre-bout posture. Negative correlations are prolonged with age, plotted as the mean and S.D. across clutches at <lb/>each of , , and weeks post-fertilization (wpf). (B) Reex gain is plotted for clutches measured at , , and wpf. (C) Standard <lb/>deviation of posture is plotted as a function of reex gain, with a least-squares t inverse function and Spearman&apos;s rank correlation <lb/>coecient listed. (D) Trajectory at peak speed of each bout is plotted as a function of concurrent trunk posture for bouts at wpf (light <lb/>blue) and wpf (dark blue), with the unity line in black. (E) Steering gain, the Theil-Sen slope estimate for data in (D), is plotted for <lb/>clutches at , , and wpf. (F) Steering gain is plotted for larvae with surgically removed pectoral ns and unaltered siblings (n=) <lb/>at and wpf. Two-way ANOVA results in text; * p¡., paired t-test with Bonferroni correction. (G) Changes to reex gain and <lb/>steering gain from -or -wpf across the clutches, with bootstrapped % condence intervals and Spearman&apos;s rank correlation <lb/>coecient listed. (H) Reex gain for larvae with surgically removed ns and unaltered siblings at and wpf. Two-way ANOVA <lb/>results in text; NS: not signicant, p&gt;.. (I) Standard deviation of observed bout trajectories for larvae with surgically removed ns <lb/>and unaltered siblings at and wpf. Two-way ANOVA results in text. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
