<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Inconsistent Addiction Treatment for Patients Undergoing Cardiac Surgery for Injection <lb/>Drug Use-Associated Infective endocarditis <lb/>Max Jordan Nguemeni Tiako, MS; 1 Seong Hong; BS 1 Syed Usman Bin Mahmood MBBS; 1 <lb/>Makoto Mori, MD, 1 Abeel Mangi, MD, 1 James Yun, MD, PhD, 2 Manisha Juthani-Mehta, MD, <lb/>3,4 Arnar Geirsson, MD 1 <lb/>1 Section of Cardiac Surgery, Department of Surgery, Yale University School of Medicine, New <lb/>Haven, CT <lb/>2 Department of Thoracic and Cardiovascular Surgery, Cleveland clinic, Cleveland, OH <lb/>3 Section of Infectious Diseases, Department of Internal Medicine, Yale University School of <lb/>Medicine, New Haven, CT <lb/>4 Department of Epidemiology of Microbial Diseases, Yale School of Public Health, New Haven, <lb/>CT <lb/>Authors report no conflict of interests. This study was funded by the Horace Stansel Jr <lb/>Research Fund. <lb/>IRB protocol ID: 2000020356, approval date: 3/2/2017 <lb/>Word count: 3085 <lb/>Key words: Cardiac surgery, endocarditis, opioid epidemic, addiction <lb/>Corresponding author: <lb/>Arnar Geirsson, MD <lb/>Associate Professor of Surgery <lb/>Section of Cardiac Surgery <lb/>Yale School of Medicine <lb/>BB204, 330 Cedar Street <lb/>P.O. Box 208039 <lb/>New Haven, CT <lb/>Business phone: 203-785-6214 <lb/>Fax: 203-785-3346 <lb/>Email: arnar.geirsson@yale.edu <lb/></front>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract: <lb/>Introduction: <lb/>Cases of injection drug use-related infective endocarditis (IDU-IE) requiring surgery are <lb/>rising in the setting of the current U.S. opioid epidemic. We thus aimed to determine the nature <lb/>of addiction interventions in the perioperative period. <lb/>Methods: <lb/>This is a retrospective review of surgical IDU-IE from 2011 to 2016 at a tertiary care <lb/>center in New Haven, Connecticut. The data collected included substances consumed <lb/>recreationally, consultations by social work (SW), psychiatry, pharmacotherapy for addiction, <lb/>and evidence of enrollment in a drug rehabilitation program upon discharge. <lb/>Among patients with active drug use (ADU), we compared the 24-month survival of <lb/>those who received at least one form of addiction intervention to that of those who did not. <lb/>Results: <lb/>Forty-two patients (75%) had active drug use. Among them, 22 used heroin. Forty-one <lb/>patients (73.2%) saw SW, 17 (30.4%) saw psychiatry; 14 (25%) saw neither SW nor psychiatry. <lb/>Twenty-one patients (37.5%) received methadone, 6 (10.7%) received buprenorphine, 1 <lb/>(0.02%) received naltrexone; 26 (46.4%) did not receive any pharmacotherapy. Fifteen patients <lb/>(26.8%) attended a drug rehabilitation program, 13 (86.7%) of whom had seen SW and 8 (53%) <lb/>psychiatry. Among patients with ADU, there was no statistically significant difference in <lb/>survival between those who received at least one intervention and those who did not (p=0.1 by <lb/>log rank). <lb/>Conclusion: <lb/></front>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>Addiction interventions are deployed inconsistently for patients with surgical IDU-IE. <lb/>Untreated substance use disorder and recurrent endocarditis are the leading cause of death in this <lb/>population. Studying best-practices for perioperative interventions in IDU-IE and establishing <lb/>protocols are of the upmost importance. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction: <lb/>Heroin use has sharply increased in the United States. 1 With the current opioid epidemic, <lb/>data shows that individuals with prescription opioid use are 40 times more likely to inject <lb/>heroin. 2,3 Concurrently, the proportion of injection drug use-related infective endocarditis (IDU-<lb/>IE) cases requiring valve surgery has increased significantly. 4,5,6 . Although surgical interventions <lb/>play a major role in addressing IE refractory to pharmacotherapy, 7 studies suggest that patients <lb/>who use injection drugs (PUID) and undergo surgery for IDU-IE die mostly of causes related to <lb/>untreated substance use disorder (recurrent endocarditis or drug overdose). 8,9 In this study, we <lb/>sought to describe the patterns of addiction treatment in PUID with IDU-IE requiring surgery. <lb/>Methods: <lb/>Patient Population: <lb/>We conducted a retrospective review of 56 consecutive patients who underwent cardiac <lb/>surgery for IDU-IE from 2011 to 2016 at Yale New Haven Hospital, a tertiary care hospital in <lb/>the United States. The patients were defined as having IE based on presentation with valvular <lb/>disease of infectious etiology, as defined by the Center for Disease Control and Prevention <lb/>(CDC), and adopted by the Society of Thoracic Surgeons and the Duke Criteria for infective <lb/>endocarditis. 10 Intravenous drug use was defined as a patient having a history of illicit drug use. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Further chart review was performed to characterize the drug use as either ongoing or remote, as <lb/>well as determining the types of drugs, based on patient reporting and collateral information <lb/>from family members available in the medical record. The study was approved by the Yale <lb/>Institutional Review Board and individual patient consent was waived. <lb/>Data Sources: <lb/>Data were collected through the local database extracted from the EMR and additional <lb/>review of individual patients&apos; electronic medical record. Addiction treatment was defined as the <lb/>aggregate of psychiatry and social work consults during inpatient stay and inpatient medication <lb/>(buprenorphine, methadone, naltrexone, naloxone). Rehabilitation attendance upon discharge <lb/>was confirmed via electronic health record review, specifically by searching discharge <lb/>summaries, nursing notes and follow-up visit notes for mentions of rehabilitation attendance. <lb/>Survival: <lb/>24-month survival data was through linkage with the Connecticut state vital statistics <lb/>data. Kaplan Meier curve characterized mid-term survival. A p value &lt;0.05 was used to define <lb/>statistically significant difference. <lb/>Results: <lb/>Patient Characteristics: <lb/>This study included 56 PUID who underwent surgical intervention for IDU-IE. The <lb/>majority of patients were male (49, 87.5%) with average age of 44 ± 13 years. Prevalence of <lb/>liver disease (23, 41.1%) was high, 22 patients (39.3%) had a history of prior stroke, and 15 <lb/>(26.8%) had prior cardiac surgery, the majority of which had prior valve surgery (13/15, 86.7%). <lb/></body>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Seventeen patients (30.4%) received double-valve surgery, and 3 (5.4%) received triple-valve <lb/>surgery (table 1). <lb/>History of Drug Use: <lb/>In this population, 42 patients had active drug use at the time of their surgery, while the <lb/>rest were noted to have a remote history of drug use. Among the 42, more than half of patients <lb/>used heroin (22, 52.4%). Among the 22 patients who used heroin, over a third used heroin and <lb/>cocaine only (8, 36.4%), and nearly a quarter (5, 22.7%) used heroin along with 2 or more other <lb/>drugs (benzodiazepine, PCP, street suboxone, cocaine, Percocet, marijuana). Additionally, more <lb/>than half of patients in the entire group of 56 had a concurrent history of tobacco use (29, <lb/>51.8%). <lb/>Addiction Treatment Pattern: <lb/>Specialty Consults: <lb/>Among the 56 patients, 40 (71.4%) patients were seen by a social worker, and 17 (30.4%) <lb/>were seen by a psychiatrist during their hospitalization. Fourteen patients were not seen by either <lb/>a social worker or a psychiatrist; therefore, 25% of patients had no psychosocial consultation <lb/>before being discharged (table 2). <lb/>Among the 42 patients who had active drug use, 33 (79%) were seen by a social worker, <lb/>15 (36%) were seen by a psychiatrist, and 8 were not seen by either a social worker or a <lb/>psychiatrist; therefore, 19% of patients with active drug use had no psychosocial consultation <lb/>before being discharged (table 2). <lb/></body>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Pharmacotherapy: <lb/>Pharmacotherapy was defined as the administration of methadone, buprenorphine, <lb/>naltrexone or naloxone during the patient&apos;s hospitalization. 21 patients (37.5%) were prescribed <lb/>methadone, 6 patients (10.7%) were prescribed buprenorphine, 14 (25%) were prescribed <lb/>naloxone, and 1 (0.02%) was prescribed naltrexone. 26 patients (46.4%) were not prescribed any <lb/>of the aforementioned medications. <lb/>Among the 42 patients with active drug use, 14 (33%) patients received methadone, 5 <lb/>(11.9%) received buprenorphine (including 2 who received both buprenorphine and methadone) <lb/>and 1 (2.4%) received naltrexone. 18 (42.9%) patients total received at least 1 form of <lb/>pharmacotherapy. <lb/>A total of 6 (14.3%) patients out of the 42 patients with active drug use received both <lb/>pharmacotherapy and psychosocial interventions (table 2). <lb/>Drug Rehabilitation Program Attendance <lb/>Fifteen patients were discharged to a drug rehabilitation facility. Thirteen (86.7%) <lb/>patients discharged to a rehabilitation facility were seen by a social worker, and 8/15 (53.3%) <lb/>patients discharged to a rehabilitation facility had been seen by a psychiatrist. <lb/>Among patients with active drug use, 10 patients were discharged to a drug rehabilitation <lb/>facility. 9 (90%) were seen by a social worker and 7 (70%) were seen by a psychiatrist. <lb/>Conversely, among patients who did not go to a rehabilitation facility, 27 (65.9%) were <lb/>seen by a social worker, and 9 (22%) were seen by a psychiatrist. The rehabilitation programs <lb/>included 12-step group rehabilitation, narcotics anonymous, and adherence to daily methadone <lb/>programs (table 2). <lb/></body>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Survival: <lb/>Unadjusted mid-term survival showed no statistically significant (p=0.1 by log rank) difference <lb/>between patients who received no treatment and those who received at least 1 form of <lb/>intervention, including pharmacotherapy, psychiatry and social work consultations (Figure 1). <lb/>Discussion: <lb/>The aim of this study was to characterize patterns of addiction treatment at a tertiary <lb/>center for PUID with IDU-IE requiring surgical intervention and their participation in drug <lb/>rehabilitation programs upon discharge. We observed that there was a heterogeneous pattern of <lb/>care provided given the lack of standardized protocols for addiction care. Currently, there are no <lb/>guidelines for pharmacotherapy or usage of specialty consultations for addiction and <lb/>psychosocial concerns surrounding the surgical management of IDU-IE. <lb/>We observed that psychiatrists were consulted as a post-operative care pathway. <lb/>Methadone was most frequently prescribed as pharmacotherapy for addiction treatment <lb/>postoperatively; however, harm reduction interventions through naloxone prescription were not <lb/>deployed for all patients. As previously elaborated in a case-series for IDU-IE among PUID, <lb/>their hospitalization is an important but often missed window of opportunity for medication-<lb/>assisted therapy initiation. 11 These findings are in line with prior studies suggesting that PUID <lb/>hospitalized for IDU-IE receive suboptimal addiction treatment. 12 <lb/>An important finding in our study is the underutilization of transition to drug <lb/>rehabilitation facilities. Notably, among 42 patients who had been actively using drugs, only 10 <lb/>patients were discharged to a rehabilitation program. Most patients who were discharged to a <lb/>rehabilitation program/facility were seen by a social worker and by a psychiatrist during their <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>hospitalization, suggesting the importance of the role played by social workers and psychiatrists <lb/>in the care of these patients. <lb/>As rates of IDU-IE requiring surgical intervention have been increasing throughout the <lb/>opioid epidemic nationally, 5,13 cardiac surgeons have been deliberating on the best way to care <lb/>for these patients. Due to the risk of recurrence/reinfection associated with drug use 14 and the <lb/>limited nature of resources, different strategies have been proposed. A recent study highlighting <lb/>right-sided endocarditis cases requiring surgery recommends staging operations, starting with a <lb/>total tricuspid valvectomy, and a subsequent prosthetic valve implantation provided that patients <lb/>are able to demonstrate abstinence from using drugs during a latency period of 6 months in <lb/>between the two surgeries. 5 This period of abstinence, however, is a state of vulnerability for <lb/>patients, putting them at high risk of overdose should they relapse. 15 <lb/>Given that surgery for prosthetic valve endocarditis has been shown to have comparable <lb/>outcomes to surgery for native valve endocarditis, 16 some surgeons are inclined to opt for a <lb/>comprehensive approach with immediate valve replacement. 17 Bioethicists, however, raise the <lb/>concern of resource limitation. 18 In that vein, some suggest that contracts between patients and <lb/>surgeons, akin to contracts between pain specialists and patients, may contribute to curbing <lb/>return to drug use, and thus reinfection rates. 19 <lb/>However, this is a controversial position, and many oppose the notion of contracts <lb/>dictating future access to life saving measures such as cardiac surgery, especially for such a <lb/>marginalized population, given that addiction is the root problem. 20 As our study demonstrates, <lb/>peri-operative addiction management is not consistently employed in a large proportion of PUID. <lb/>Several studies have shown presumed continued drug use to be the leading cause of death among <lb/>PUID who underwent cardiac surgery for IDU-IE. 8 <lb/></body>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Continued drug use is a consequence of addiction, and inherently increases the risk of <lb/>reinfection. Addiction is a chronic neurobiological disorder, characterized in part by craving and <lb/>withdrawal symptoms. Studies show that initiation of pharmacotherapy for treatment of opioid <lb/>dependence in emergency room settings yields reduced self-reported illicit opioid use and <lb/>decreased use of inpatient addiction treatment services. 21-23 Additionally, studies suggest that for <lb/>comprehensive addiction care for patients with opioid use disorder during hospitalization <lb/>improves not only patient outcomes, but also provider outcomes. 24 Other interventions such as <lb/>long term residential addiction treatment and patient navigator programs have been shown to <lb/>improve outcomes and reduce readmission rates for at risk patients, hence the importance of <lb/>post-operative discharge to drug rehabilitation facilities or enrollment in rehabilitation <lb/>programs. 25 In cases where such resources may not be deployed, adequate outpatient follow-up <lb/>after initiation of pharmacotherapy could contribute to sustaining improvement in outcomes. <lb/>Limitations: <lb/>This retrospective study was conducted at a single-center by observational electronic <lb/>medical record chart review. Data on reoperation and recurrent endocarditis was not completely <lb/>captured. For patients with a history of remote drug use but no indication of active use, the type <lb/>of drugs consumed was not ascertained. Given that this is an observational study with a relatively <lb/>small sample, the direct impact of medication initiation for addiction treatment and psychosocial <lb/>consultations on rehabilitation attendance after discharge were not determined with statistical <lb/>significance. <lb/>Conclusion: <lb/></body>
	
			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Perioperative intervention for opioid use disorder in patients undergoing cardiac surgery <lb/>for IDU-IE does not happen in a standardized fashion. Some patients receive pharmacotherapy <lb/>and are seen by specialists equipped to address psychosocial factors, but not all. Given that <lb/>mortality in this patient population is predominantly due to untreated substance use disorder, the <lb/>concomitance of addiction treatment and surgical intervention through multidisciplinary care is <lb/>of extreme importance. In the context of an opioid epidemic in the U.S., our findings argue for <lb/>the development of a standard peri-operative addiction care pathway for this patient population. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: <lb/>Sources of Funding: <lb/>This study was funded by the Horace Stansel Jr Research Fund. <lb/>Disclosures: <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors report no conflict of interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References: <lb/>1. <lb/>Rudd RA, Aleshire N, Zibbell JE, Gladden RM. Increases in Drug and Opioid Overdose <lb/>Deaths -United States , 2000 -2014. MMWR Morb Mortal Wkly Rep. 2016;64(50-<lb/>51):1378-1382. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>2. <lb/>Keeshin SW, Feinberg J. Endocarditis as a Marker for New Epidemics of Injection Drug <lb/>Use. Am J Med Sci. 2016;352(6):609-614. <lb/>3. <lb/>Muhuri PK, Gfroerer JC, Davies MC. CBHSQ Data Review: Associations of Nonmedical <lb/>Pain Reliever Use and Initiation of Heroin Use in the United States. 2013. <lb/>4. <lb/>Shrestha NK, Jue J, Hussain ST, et al. Injection Drug Use and Outcomes After Surgical <lb/>Intervention for Infective Endocarditis. Ann Thorac Surg. 2015;100(3):875-882. <lb/>5. <lb/>Protos AN, Trivedi JR, Whited WM, et al. Valvectomy versus Replacement for the <lb/>Surgical Treatment of Tricuspid Endocarditis. Ann Thorac Surg. 2018;0(0). <lb/>6. <lb/>Schranz AJ, Fleischauer A, Chu VH, Wu L-T, Rosen DL. Trends in Drug Use-Associated <lb/>Infective Endocarditis and Heart Valve Surgery, 2007 to 2017. Ann Intern Med. <lb/>2019;170(1):31. <lb/>7. <lb/>Baddour LM, Wilson WR, Bayer AS, et al. Infective endocarditis in adults: Diagnosis, <lb/>antimicrobial therapy, and management of complications: A scientific statement for <lb/>healthcare professionals from the American Heart Association. Circulation. <lb/>2015;132(15):1435-1486. <lb/>8. <lb/>Hiratzka LF, Nelson RJ, Oliver CB, Jengo JA. Operative experience with infective <lb/>endocarditis. Drug users compared with non-drug users. J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. <lb/>1979;77(3):355-361. <lb/>9. <lb/>Rabkin DG, Mokadam NA, Miller DW, Goetz RR, Verrier ED, Aldea GS. Long-Term <lb/>Outcome for the Surgical Treatment of Infective Endocarditis With a Focus on <lb/>Intravenous Drug Users. Ann Thorac Surg. 2012;93(1):51-57. <lb/>10. Clark RE. Definitions of Terms of The Society of Thoracic Surgeons National Cardiac <lb/>Surgery Database.; 1994. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>11. Suzuki J. Medication-assisted treatment for hospitalized patients with intravenous-drug-<lb/>use related infective endocarditis. Am J Addict. 2016;25(3):191-194. <lb/>12. Rosenthal ES, Karchmer AW, Theisen-Toupal J, Castillo RA, Rowley CF. Suboptimal <lb/>Addiction Interventions for Patients Hospitalized with Injection Drug Use-Associated <lb/>Infective Endocarditis. Am J Med. 2016;129(5). <lb/>13. Wurcel AG, Anderson JE, Chui KKH, et al. Increasing Infectious Endocarditis <lb/>Admissions Among Young People Who Inject Drugs. Open Forum Infect Dis. <lb/>2016;3(3):ofw157. <lb/>14. Fedoruk LM, Jamieson WRE, Ling H, et al. Predictors of recurrence and reoperation for <lb/>prosthetic valve endocarditis after valve replacement surgery for native valve endocarditis. <lb/>J Thorac Cardiovasc Surg. 2009;137(2):326-333. <lb/>15. Møller LF, Matic S, van den Bergh BJ, Moloney K, Hayton P, Gatherer A. Acute drug-<lb/>related mortality of people recently released from prisons. Public Health. <lb/>2010;124(11):637-639. <lb/>16. Mori M, Shioda K, Nguemeni Tiako MJ, et al. Comparable perioperative outcomes and <lb/>mid-term survival in prosthetic valve endocarditis and native valve endocarditis. Eur J <lb/>Cardio-Thoracic Surg. May 2018. <lb/>17. Ribeiro IB, Ruel M. Valvectomy versus Replacement for the Surgical Treatment of <lb/>Tricuspid Endocarditis (Commentary). Ann Thorac Surg. June 2018. <lb/>18. Hull SC, Jadbabaie F. ETHICS IN CARDIOTHORACIC SURGERY When Is Enough <lb/>Enough? The Dilemma of Valve Replacement in a Recidivist Intravenous Drug User. Ann <lb/>Thorac Surg. 2014;97:1486-1487. <lb/>19. Hussain ST, Gordon SM, Streem DW, Blackstone EH, Pettersson GB. Contract with the <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>patient with injection drug use and infective endocarditis: Surgeons perspective. J Thorac <lb/>Cardiovasc Surg. 2017;154(6):2002-2003. <lb/>20. Wurcel AG, Yu S, Pacheco M, Warner K. Contracts with people who inject drugs <lb/>following valve surgery: Unrealistic and misguided expectations. J Thorac Cardiovasc <lb/>Surg. 2017;154(6):2002. <lb/>21. D&apos;Onofrio G, Chawarski MC, O&apos;Connor PG, et al. Emergency Department-Initiated <lb/>Buprenorphine for Opioid Dependence with Continuation in Primary Care: Outcomes <lb/>During and After Intervention. J Gen Intern Med. 2017;32(6):660-666. <lb/>22. D&apos;Onofrio G, O&apos;Connor PG, Pantalon M V., et al. Emergency Department-Initiated <lb/>Buprenorphine/Naloxone Treatment for Opioid Dependence. JAMA. 2015;313(16):1636. <lb/>23. Bernstein SL, D&apos;Onofrio G. Screening, treatment initiation, and referral for substance use <lb/>disorders. Addict Sci Clin Pract. 2017;12(1):18. <lb/>24. Weimer M, Morford K, Donroe J. Treatment of Opioid Use Disorder in the Acute <lb/>Hospital Setting: a Critical Review of the Literature (2014-2019). Curr Addict Reports. <lb/>July 2019:1-16. <lb/>25. Jewell C, Weaver M, Sgroi C, Anderson K, Sayeed Z. Residential Addiction Treatment <lb/>for Injection Drug Users Requiring Intravenous Antibiotics. J Addict Med. 2013;7(4):271-<lb/>276. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure legend: <lb/>Figure 1: Kaplan-Meir curve of mid-term mortality comparing patients who received at least 1 <lb/>addiction intervention and patients who did not receive any intervention <lb/>Tables: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: Pertinent patient characteristics <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>All patients (total 56) <lb/>Patients with active drug use (total 42) <lb/>Age <lb/>44.1±13 <lb/>42.6±13.8 <lb/>Caucasian race <lb/>43 (76.8%) <lb/>29 (69%) <lb/>Female sex <lb/>7 (12.5%) <lb/>4 (9.5%) <lb/>History of diabetes <lb/>4 (7.4%) <lb/>1 (2.4%) <lb/>History of hypertension <lb/>19 (33.9%) <lb/>11 (26.2%) <lb/>History of dialysis <lb/>3 (5.4%) <lb/>3 (7.1%) <lb/>History of stroke <lb/>22 (39.3%) <lb/>19 (45.2%) <lb/>Non-elective cases <lb/>42 (75%) <lb/>38 (90.5%) <lb/>History of cardiac surgery <lb/>15 (26.8%) <lb/>9 (21.4%) <lb/>Table 2: Summary of addiction interventions received by patients undergoing surgery for IE <lb/>with active drug use or a remote history of drug use <lb/>Addiction interventions <lb/>All patients <lb/>(total 56) <lb/>Patients with active drug <lb/>use (total 42) <lb/>Methadone <lb/>21 (37.5%) <lb/>14 (33.3%) <lb/>Buprenorphine <lb/>6 (10.7%) <lb/>5 (11.8%) <lb/>Naltrexone <lb/>1 (1.8%) <lb/>1 (2.3%)) <lb/>Naloxone <lb/>14 (25%) <lb/>13 (31%) <lb/>Social Work consults <lb/>40 (71.4%) <lb/>33 (78.6%) <lb/>Psychiatry consults <lb/>17 (30.4%) <lb/>15 (35.7%) <lb/>Rehabilitation attendance upon discharge <lb/>15 (26.8%) <lb/>10 (23.8%) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figures: <lb/>Figure 1: Kaplan-Meir curve of mid-term mortality comparing patients who received at least 1 <lb/>addiction intervention and patients who did not receive any intervention <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/19008482 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint </note>

	</text>
</tei>
