<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cellular reconstitution of apoptotic cell clearance reveals a <lb/>multi-step phosphorylation mechanism for Draper receptor triggering <lb/>Adam P. Williamson 1, 2 and Ronald D. Vale 1, 2* <lb/>1 Dept. of Cellular and Molecular Pharmacology and the 2 Howard Hughes Medical Institute, <lb/>University of California, San Francisco, CA 94158 <lb/>* Address correspondence to: ron.vale@ucsf.edu <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Summary <lb/>Apoptotic cells are cleared after exposing &quot;eat me&quot; ligands, including phosphatidylserine (PS), <lb/>but the signaling pathway in the phagocytic cell that leads to engulfment remains poorly <lb/>understood. Here, by transfecting the engulfment receptor Draper into Drosophila S2 cells and <lb/>using PS-coated beads to mimic apoptotic cells, we have created a simplified system for <lb/>studying this process. We show that ligand-bound Draper forms mobile microclusters that recruit <lb/>effector proteins and exclude a transmembrane phosphatase, suggesting a kinetic segregation <lb/>mechanism for receptor activation similar to T cell receptors. Like the TCR, Draper&apos;s <lb/>extracellular domain and ligand can be replaced with other interacting modules. We show that <lb/>phosphorylation of Draper&apos;s ITAM motif occurs first and is a dominant contributor to signaling. <lb/>After ITAM phosphorylation, additional residues become phosphorylated and contribute to <lb/>signaling efficiency. Our results demonstrate broad mechanistic similarities between Draper and <lb/>mammalian immune receptor activation and an ability to reprogram engulfment signaling. <lb/>Keywords: Signaling, phagocytosis, cell engulfment, corpse clearance, efferocytosis, apoptosis, <lb/>phosphatidylserine, Drosophila, Draper, Shark <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The prompt clearance of dying cells and debris is essential for maintaining homeostasis and <lb/>promoting tissue repair (Arandjelovic and Ravichandran, 2015; Neumann et al., 2015; Reddien <lb/>and Horvitz, 2004). In healthy tissue, resident and infiltrating phagocytes clear cell corpses and <lb/>debris through specific recognition, uptake, and digestion (Elliott and Ravichandran, 2010). <lb/>Defects in clearance result in autoimmunity and further tissue damage (Elliott and <lb/>Ravichandran, 2010; Iram et al., 2016). Despite the importance of efficient clearance across <lb/>multicellular life, our understanding of the underlying mechanism remains poorly understood in <lb/>comparison to other signaling systems. Important questions about how an apoptotic corpse <lb/>triggers its clearance by professional phagocytic cells remain unanswered. Developing a better <lb/>understanding of this process could lead to new strategies of enhancing clearance under <lb/>conditions of extreme injury or enabling engulfment of choice targets such as cancer cells. <lb/>Apoptotic cell clearance requires a complex signaling network triggered by interactions between <lb/>receptors on the phagocyte and ligands exposed on the dying cells. These &quot;eat me&quot; signals <lb/>trigger cytosolic signaling that ultimately promotes cytoskeletal rearrangements that power <lb/>corpse internalization (Ravichandran and Lorenz, 2007; Reddien and Horvitz, 2004). <lb/>Phagocytes express receptors that recognize distinct ligands either directly or through bridging <lb/>molecules (S. A. Freeman and Grinstein, 2014; Penberthy and Ravichandran, 2016). Although <lb/>the basic mechanics of clearance are likely conserved across metazoans, the receptors and <lb/>ligands are diverse. Perhaps as a consequence of this molecular diversity, the biochemical and <lb/>biophysical triggers of phagocytic receptor activation and the downstream consequences of <lb/>triggering remain unclear. Important open questions include: How do apoptotic ligands cause <lb/>the phosphorylation of receptor cytosolic tails? How do ligated receptors organize themselves <lb/>on plasma membranes? How are cytosolic effectors recruited to receptors? <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Draper is a Drosophila receptor that is expressed in glia, where it promotes clearance of <lb/>damaged axons, and in the somatic epithelium, where it functions to remove dying cells from <lb/>the follicle (Etchegaray et al., 2012; M. R. Freeman et al., 2003; MacDonald et al., 2006). <lb/>Draper is similar in domain structure to the mammalian protein Megf10 and CED-1, the first <lb/>described apoptotic corpse receptor in C. elegans. All three receptors contain single pass <lb/>transmembrane domains that connect extracellular EGF repeats to intracellular tyrosine <lb/>phosphorylation sites that are presumed to recruit one or more downstream effectors (Scheib et <lb/>al., 2012; Zhou et al., 2001; Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). Draper function has been dissected <lb/>genetically, especially in its damaged axon clearance role, which defined a &quot;parts list&quot; of other <lb/>proteins involved in engulfment signaling, including the kinases Src42a and Shark and the <lb/>adapter protein Crk (Lu et al., 2014; Ziegenfuss et al., 2008; 2012). However, biochemical <lb/>interactions are less well understood, and how these molecules work together to promote <lb/>clearance remains an open question. In particular, our understanding of Draper phosphorylation <lb/>and the immediate downstream events is poor. <lb/>A clue to the mechanism of Draper activity comes from the recognition that its sequence bears <lb/>an Immune Tyrosine Activation Motif (ITAM) domain that is found in several copies in the T cell <lb/>receptor, a receptor that evolved in vertebrates with an adaptive immune system (Schultz et al., <lb/>2000; Zhou et al., 2001; Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). Furthermore, Shark, an important kinase in the <lb/>engulfment signaling pathway uncovered through genetics, bears domain and sequence identify <lb/>to ZAP70 and Syk, tyrosine kinases involved in immune responses which bind directly to <lb/>doubly-phosphorylated tyrosines in the ITAM domain (Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). A subset of <lb/>molecules implicated in Draper signaling (e.g. Crk) also contain SH2 and SH3 domains that <lb/>bear some similarity to multivalent adapters such as Grb2 and Gads that function in mammalian <lb/>immune signaling and other systems (Choudhuri and Dustin, 2010). While these genetic and <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>sequence level clues are tantalizing, evidence showing that Draper has functional parallels with <lb/>mammalian adaptive immune signaling is lacking. Understanding both the functional similarities <lb/>and differences between Draper and adaptive immune receptor signaling could provide <lb/>important clues into the mechanism of phagocytosis. <lb/>Here, we have reconstituted Draper-mediated signaling in Drosophila S2 cells to understand <lb/>how this receptor triggers phagocytosis. We find that Draper ligation to the lipid <lb/>phosphatidylserine (PS) incorporated into supported lipid bilayers is sufficient to induce its <lb/>phosphorylation and a signaling cascade leading to engulfment. Like the TCR, ligated Draper <lb/>forms mobile microclusters that shift a kinase-phosphatase balance toward receptor <lb/>phosphorylation and the recruitment of downstream effector proteins. We also reveal other <lb/>mechanistic parallels between Draper signaling and T cell signaling, including the ability to <lb/>replace the extracellular module of Draper and PS with an inducible artificial receptor-ligand <lb/>interaction. Unlike the TCR, where the ITAM phosphorylation domain is sufficient for signaling, <lb/>we show that full activation of Draper requires an initial ITAM phosphorylation followed by the <lb/>phosphorylation of other tyrosines in its tail domain. The reconstitution and reprogramming of <lb/>Draper signaling reveals how distinct modules in the receptor work in concert to promote <lb/>signaling and uncovers new insight into functional similarities and differences between <lb/>phagocytic and mammalian adaptive immune signaling systems. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>Cellular reconstitution of Draper signaling <lb/>We used cultured Drosophila S2 cells, which are derived from a hemocyte lineage (Schneider, <lb/>1972), as a cellular system for reconstituting phagocytosis. Drosophila S2 cells display a very <lb/>low level of engulfment of cell corpses (Fig. 1A), which were prepared by inducing apoptosis in <lb/>S2 cells by addition of 1 µM actinomycin for 16 hr. We hypothesized that the level of <lb/>engulfment might be low because S2 cells lack sufficient levels of engulfment receptors. <lb/>Consistent with this idea Draper, the best known engulfment receptor in Drosophila, is <lb/>expressed at low levels in S2 cells as measured by RNA-Seq (Cherbas et al., 2011). <lb/>Fluorescently-labeled corpses were then added to cultures of either Draper-or control mCherry-<lb/>transfected S2 cells and, after 45 min, the presence of internalized annexinV-647-labeled <lb/>corpses was scored. Our results revealed that Draper transfection increased the uptake of <lb/>apoptotic cell corpses by ~5 fold (Fig. 1A). <lb/>Apoptotic cells express an array of &quot;eat me&quot; ligands (Ravichandran and Lorenz, 2007). As a <lb/>next step, we sought to provide a simplified target of uniform size. The lipid phosphatidylserine <lb/>(PS) is exposed on dying cells and is considered to be an important &quot;eat me&quot; signal (Fadok et <lb/>al., 1992). PS was proposed to be a Draper activator (Tung et al., 2013), but a protein ligand for <lb/>Draper has also been suggested (Kuraishi et al., 2009). It has not been established whether PS <lb/>is necessary and sufficient for Draper-mediated engulfment. To determine if PS alone might <lb/>suffice for Draper-mediated engulfment, we replaced the apoptotic cells with 6.5 micron <lb/>diameter silica beads coated with a supported lipid bilayer (SLB) containing 10% PS and 0.5% <lb/>atto390-PE lipid for visualization by microscopy (Fig. 1B). Draper-GFP S2 cells engulfed ~0.8 <lb/>PS beads/cell, on average, after a 30 min incubation (Fig. 1B), which was 50-fold higher than <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>the ingestion of beads coated only with PC alone. Control GFP S2 cells also engulfed PS-<lb/>coated beads ~7 fold less efficiently than the Draper-GFP transfected cells, (Fig. 1B). Draper-<lb/>GFP S2 cells engulfed beads at 2.5% PS lipid content and showed increasing engulfment up to <lb/>12.5% PS (Fig. 1C). The PS concentrations that promote engulfment of beads are within the <lb/>physiological range present on dead and dying cells (Leventis and Grinstein, 2010). Thus, our <lb/>S2 cell system represents a simplified engulfment assay that is dependent on 1) overexpression <lb/>of the Draper receptor, and 2) PS exposed on a SLB-coated bead. Importantly, these results <lb/>also demonstrate that PS is a functional ligand for Draper and is necessary and sufficient for <lb/>Draper-mediated engulfment. <lb/>We next performed live cell microscopy to visualize the process of Draper-mediated engulfment <lb/>of PS beads (stills Fig. 1D, Movie 1). We co-transfected Draper-mCherry and LifeAct-GFP in S2 <lb/>cells and imaged PS bead engulfment by time-lapse imaging. Draper-mCherry expressing cells <lb/>formed a synapse with PS beads and rapidly began forming a phagocytic cup; F-actin, as <lb/>assessed by LifeAct-GFP signal, localized at the edges of the cup and the leading edge of the <lb/>cup extended gradually around the bead. When the phagocytic cup was complete, the PS bead <lb/>was internalized. Thus, our system is useful for determining the kinetics of PS bead engulfment <lb/>and following the dynamics of the cytoskeleton and membranes downstream of Draper <lb/>activation. <lb/>Draper ligation nucleates the formation of mobile microclusters enriched in <lb/>phosphotyrosine and phosphotyrosine-binding proteins <lb/>After engaging with damaged axon, Draper expressed in glial cells becomes tyrosine <lb/>phosphorylated, which then enables it to recruit a Syk-related related tyrosine kinase called <lb/>Shark (Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). After incubating Draper-GFP S2 cells with 10% PS beads, we <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>found a strong pTyr signal at the plasma membrane at the interface between Draper-GFP S2 <lb/>cell and the PS bead, which diminished after internalization (Fig. 2A). Consistent with the <lb/>studies of Ziegenfuss et al. (2008), we also found that Shark-mCherry co-localized with Draper-<lb/>GFP at the interface between PS bead and the Draper-transfected S2 cell (Fig. 2B). <lb/>To better visualize the behavior of Draper and the recruitment of proteins to the plasma <lb/>membrane, we developed a signaling system that is compatible with Total Internal Reflection <lb/>Fluorescence-Microscopy (TIRF-M), a technique that confines illumination to within ~200 nm of <lb/>the glass coverslip. Instead of using a bead, we coated the glass coverslip with a supported lipid <lb/>bilayer contain 10% PS (Fig 2C). When Draper-GFP S2 cells settled on this PS supported lipid <lb/>bilayer, the cells spread rapidly on the surface in a futile effort to engulf the planar surface. <lb/>Strikingly, Draper-GFP organized in microclusters that underwent retrograde flow from the <lb/>leading edge towards a central synapse (Fig. 2D; Movie 2). The behavior of these Draper <lb/>clusters is very similar to that reported for adaptive immune receptor clusters that form in B and <lb/>T cells (Kaizuka et al., 2007; Murugesan et al., 2016). To determine if Draper clusters have local <lb/>effects on the actin cytoskeleton, we co-expressed Draper-GFP and LifeAct-BFP and allowed <lb/>these cells to settle on PS bilayers. Draper-GFP microclusters appeared at the SLB interface <lb/>with LifeAct-BFP; as the clusters grew, LifeAct-BFP signal was depleted (Movie 3). The central <lb/>synapse was depleted of F-actin, as imaged by LifeAct-BFP. Thus, Draper activation at the <lb/>plasma membrane leads to clusters that undergo retrograde flow and correlates with local actin <lb/>cytoskeleton remodeling. <lb/>Next, we asked if Draper-GFP clusters are sites of recruitment for downstream signaling <lb/>molecules. Draper is proposed to interact with Shark, a dual SH2 protein, and an adapter Crk, <lb/>which harbors one SH2 and two SH3 domains. To test if these proteins are recruited to Draper <lb/>microclusters, we allowed Draper-GFP, Shark-TagBFP, Crk-mCherry transfected S2 cells to <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>settle on 10% PS bilayers and then imaged them by TIRF microscopy. Draper-GFP <lb/>microclusters co-localized with Shark-TagBFP and Crk-mCherry (Fig. 2E, Movie 4), indicating <lb/>that Draper-GFP microclusters, like TCR microclusters, recruit a tandem SH2-domain <lb/>containing kinase and an adapter protein to the plasma membrane. Crk and the activating <lb/>subunit of the PI3K p85 also co-localize at the synapse between PS bead and Draper-<lb/>expressing S2 cell, indicating that Draper may organize multiple signaling outputs (Fig. S1). Our <lb/>results demonstrate that upon ligation to PS, Draper is phosphorylated and nucleates formation <lb/>of signaling microclusters that recruit SH2-domain containing proteins. <lb/>Exclusion of a transmembrane phosphatase at the ligated membrane-membrane <lb/>interface <lb/>We next used our reconstitution system to understand the mechanism of how PS triggers <lb/>Draper phosphorylation. The T cell receptor is believed to be triggered by the exclusion of the <lb/>transmembrane phosphatase CD45, which has a bulky extracellular domain, from zones of <lb/>close membrane-membrane contact created by the pMHC-TCR interaction (Burroughs et al., <lb/>2006; Choudhuri et al., 2005; James and Vale, 2012). Since the Src family kinase Lck is <lb/>attached to the membrane inner leaflet and remains uniformly distributed after pMHC-TCR <lb/>engagement, phosphatase exclusion shifts the kinase-phosphatase balance towards net <lb/>receptor phosphorylation. We sought to test whether a similar mechanism might function to <lb/>trigger Draper phosphorylation. Drosophila S2 cells expresses several transmembrane <lb/>phosphatases (Fig. S2A). We tested the transmembrane phosphatase Ptp69D, because of its <lb/>high expression and similar domain structure to CD45 (extracellular fibronectin repeats and <lb/>cytosolic tyrosine phosphatase activity (Fig. S2B)). To determine if Draper clusters are <lb/>segregated from Ptp69D, we co-transfected the two proteins with different fluorescent protein <lb/>tags and assessed localization during Draper ligation in living cells. Microscopy revealed that <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>ligated Draper-mCherry concentrated at the synapse between the S2 cell and PS bead, while <lb/>Ptp69D-GFP was partially excluded from this zone (Fig. 3A). Draper microclusters that formed <lb/>at the interface between an S2 cell and a PS-containing supported lipid bilayer also excluded <lb/>Ptp69D (Fig. S2C). Thus, ligated Draper is able to segregate away from an abundant <lb/>transmembrane phosphatase, a result that is consistent with a kinetic segregation triggering <lb/>mechanism. <lb/>In the kinetic segregation model, two opposing membranes are brought into close apposition by <lb/>the binding energy between receptor and its ligand, which results in the exclusion of larger <lb/>transmembrane phosphatases. To further examine whether Draper may trigger phosphorylation <lb/>through a kinetic segregation mechanism rather than a receptor conformational change, we <lb/>tested whether the extracellular domain of Draper and its ligand PS could be replaced with an <lb/>artificial receptor-ligand pair. Previous studies on the T cell receptor triggering showed that the <lb/>extracellular domain of the TCR and pMHC could be substituted with FKBP and FRB, which <lb/>upon addition of rapamycin to bridge FKBP and FRB, would trigger TCR phosphorylation <lb/>(James and Vale, 2012). We created a similar inducible system for Draper by replacing its <lb/>extracellular domain with FRB (FRB-EXT-Draper-INT) and replacing PS with His 10 -FKBP, which <lb/>was bound to the SLB on the bead via a NiNTA-lipid (Fig 3B). In the absence of rapamycin, <lb/>beads were engulfed at very low levels (0.003 beads/cell). However, in the presence of <lb/>rapamycin, the engineered receptor promoted robust engulfment of FKBP-bearing beads (Fig. <lb/>3C, Movie 5). Live cell microscopy revealed that the FRB-EXT-Draper-INT concentrated at the <lb/>cell-bead interface and recruited Shark kinase, suggesting that the chimeric receptor, like <lb/>Draper, is activated by tyrosine phosphorylation (Fig 3D). When His 10 -FKBP was attached to a <lb/>SLB on a coverslip, the cells spread on the surface. Like Draper-GFP, FRB-EXT-Draper-INT <lb/>excluded the phosphatase Ptp69D-GFP (Fig. 3E), consistent with a kinetic segregation-based <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>triggering mechanism. Thus a chimeric receptor that is designed to interact with a non-<lb/>physiological ligand is functional for engulfment. <lb/>Roles of Draper&apos;s cytoplasmic Tyr residues for engulfment of PS beads <lb/>We next sought to determine which Tyr residues are essential for full Draper activity. The <lb/>Draper tail domain contains an ITAM motif (YxxI/Lx 6-12 YxxI/L), an NPxY motif thought to interact <lb/>CED-6 (Fujita et al., 2012), and 10 other tyrosine residues, 2 of which are in close proximity to <lb/>the transmembrane domain. First, we created a construct in which 11 of the 13 tyrosines were <lb/>mutated to alanine, leaving the two tyrosines that are immediately adjacent to the <lb/>transmembrane segment since they potentially could have a structural role. We then compared <lb/>phagocytic proficiency of cells transfected with Draper-Ala11-GFP mutant to full-length Draper-<lb/>GFP and GFP alone control (endogenous background phagocytosis). Consistent with a role for <lb/>Tyr phosphorylation on Draper to promote phagocytosis, Draper-Ala11-GFP ingested PS-beads <lb/>at levels that were comparable to the GFP control and ~15-fold below Draper-GFP cells after a <lb/>45 min incubation (Fig 4A). <lb/>Genetic studies in Drosophila indicated at Shark kinase is involved in Draper signaling <lb/>(Ziegenfuss et al., 2008), but the Draper ITAM, which recruits Shark, is also important for other <lb/>aspects of Draper function including migration to sites of damage (Evans et al., 2015). To test <lb/>the roles of the ITAM in our system, we mutated the 2 Tyr residues in the ITAM to Phe (Draper-<lb/>∆ITAM; residues in 4B) and assessed its ability to promote phagocytosis. Draper-∆ITAM <lb/>showed a kinetic delay and a lower number of beads ingested (Figure 4C) compared to wildtype <lb/>Draper, although, it still promoted phagocytosis to a greater extent than the effectively null <lb/>Draper-Ala11 construct. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>We also tested if Draper&apos;s ITAM is sufficient to signal by adding back the ITAM tyrosines (Y934 <lb/>and Y949) to the null Ala-11 mutant. The Draper ITAM Only receptor promoted phagocytosis of <lb/>PS beads, but did so more slowly than wildtype and to a lesser extent than wildtype Draper. As <lb/>expected, the Draper ITAM was necessary and sufficient to recruit Shark kinase to the synapse <lb/>between S2 cell and PS bead (Fig. S3). Collectively, our mutational analyses suggest that both <lb/>Draper&apos;s ITAM plays a major role in signaling but that non-ITAM residues also contribute to full <lb/>receptor activity in engulfing PS beads. <lb/>Hierarchical multi-site Tyr phosphorylation in vitro <lb/>Using a biochemical system with purified components, we sought to test the role of the Draper&apos;s <lb/>ITAM domain on Shark binding and receptor phosphorylation. To detect binding between Shark <lb/>and Draper, we used a fluorescently-labeled tandem SH2 Shark construct (BG505-tSH2-Shark) <lb/>whose signal quenches upon binding to liposome-bound Draper (Hui and Vale, 2014) <lb/>(schematic Fig. 5A). With Src42a in solution and ATP added to trigger phosphorylation, we <lb/>observed a time-dependent quenching of Shark fluorescence as it bound to the phosphorylated <lb/>receptor (Fig. 5A, orange trace). Next we tested the Draper receptor with double tyrosine <lb/>mutation in its ITAM motif (Draper-∆ITAM). Draper-∆ITAM showed little or no recruitment of <lb/>Shark (Fig. 5A, blue trace). <lb/>Next, we tested the extent and order of Tyr phosphorylation events on Draper&apos;s cytoplasmic tail <lb/>in this biochemical assay. After a 30 min kinase reaction, immunoblotting with anti-<lb/>phosphotyrosine antibodies revealed a noticeable shift in the electrophoretic mobility of Draper, <lb/>which is suggestive of phosphorylation on multiple Tyr residues (Fig. 5B). Remarkably, even <lb/>though the Draper Y934F/Y949F mutant contains 9 additional tyrosine residues, its <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>phosphorylation as detected by phosphotyrosine immunoblotting was minimal (5% of wildtype <lb/>Draper) in the same kinase reaction (Fig. 5B). <lb/>This result greatly diminished phosphorylation of the Draper Y934F/Y949F mutant could be due <lb/>to 1) only the ITAM domains are phosphorylated by Src42a, or 2) or that phosphorylation of the <lb/>ITAM motif is needed for the phosphorylation of non-ITAM in Draper&apos;s tail. To distinguish <lb/>between these possibilities, we performed 1D mass spectrometry. After a 4 min incubation with <lb/>Src42a, we observed that the first ITAM tyrosine (Y934) was phosphorylated; phosphorylation <lb/>on the second ITAM residue Y949 was not detected but the Y949 containing peptide was not <lb/>highly covered in our mass spec (Fig. 5C). In addition to Y934, we found several other residues <lb/>that were phosphorylated (Y858, Y888, Y901, Y905, and Y925). This result indicates that the <lb/>ITAM is not only target for Src42a. Src42a is the most likely candidate for Draper <lb/>phosphorylation based upon genetic studies (Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). However, we also <lb/>wanted to establish whether other Src family kinases behave in a similar way to Src42a with <lb/>respect to Draper phosphorylation. We tested Lck, a well-studied Src family kinase in immune <lb/>cells. Like Src42a, Lck readily phosphorylated Draper on Y888, Y901, Y905, Y925, and the <lb/>Y934 ITAM residue (but not Y858)(Figure S4). Similar to results with Src42a, for the Draper <lb/>Y934F/Y949F mutant, phosphorylation by Lck was greatly reduced to 4% of wildtype (Figure <lb/>S5). Collectively these results indicate that multiple Draper tyrosines are phosphorylated by Src <lb/>family kinases, and that phosphorylation of non-ITAM residues strongly depends upon ITAM <lb/>phosphorylation. A potential mechanism for sequential phosphorylation is described in the <lb/>Discussion. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we have reconstituted Draper-dependent engulfment of PS-coated beads in <lb/>Drosophila S2 cells and used this system, in conjunction with a liposome-based biochemical <lb/>assay, to elucidate the initial steps of the phagocytic signaling pathway. Our data reveal that <lb/>corpse clearance, a conserved process required to recognize and remove dying cells, bears <lb/>striking mechanistic similarity to mammalian adaptive immune systems, which defend against <lb/>non-self pathogens and cancer. <lb/>Figure 6 shows our working model for Draper triggering. We show that ligation to the lipid PS is <lb/>sufficient to promote Draper clustering and segregation away from a transmembrane <lb/>phosphatase (1). Spatial separation between ligated Draper clusters and transmembrane <lb/>phosphatases shifts a kinase-phosphatase balance in favor of receptor phosphorylation by <lb/>Src42a, Draper&apos;s cognate activating kinase (2). Receptor phosphorylation occurs in a <lb/>hierarchical manner: Draper&apos;s ITAM residues are required for full activation of the system, <lb/>possibly though direct recruitment of Src42a to Draper&apos;s ITAM via its own SH2 domain (2). <lb/>Phosphorylation of Draper&apos;s tail activates a downstream cytosolic signaling cascade, including <lb/>recruitment of effectors including Shark kinase (3). Receptor phosphorylation and adapter <lb/>recruitment result in activation of the actin cytoskeleton and the coupling of receptors to actin <lb/>retrograde flow (4). We note that others have described further downstream Draper signaling <lb/>outputs, including a positive feedback mechanism to increase expression levels of the receptor <lb/>itself (drpr) (Ziegenfuss et al., 2012) and upregulation of other factors, including matrix <lb/>metallopeptidase 1 (mmp1) (Purice et al., 2017) (4). <lb/>PS is an activating ligand for Draper <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Draper is reported to recognize both PS (Tung et al., 2013) and the protein ligands Pretaporter <lb/>and DmCaBP1 (Kuraishi et al., 2009; Okada et al., 2012). For PS, Tung et al (2013) <lb/>demonstrated direct binding of PS to the extracellular domain of Draper. They also showed that <lb/>incubation of S2 cells with PS liposomes increased tyrosine phosphorylation levels on Draper, <lb/>but did not demonstrate a capability of engulfing liposomes. Here we extend this finding to <lb/>demonstrate that Draper over-expression and ligation to PS are necessary and sufficient to <lb/>promote efficient engulfment of beads coated with supported lipid bilayers (Fig. 1B). <lb/>Furthermore, PS is an activating ligand that triggers Draper clustering, localized tyrosine <lb/>phosphorylation, effector recruitment to mobile microclusters, and remodeling of the actin <lb/>cytoskeleton. These results provide strong evidence for direct binding of PS to Draper leading to <lb/>activation of a signaling pathway. The nature of the binding interaction is Our results do not rule <lb/>out a role for the protein ligands Pretaporter and DmCaBP1 that have been reported previously <lb/>to act as Draper ligands (Kuraishi et al., 2009; Okada et al., 2012). These additional ligands <lb/>may allow Draper to respond independently of PS in some contexts. <lb/>Mechanism of Draper triggering upon ligation <lb/>TCR and FcR activation are driven entirely by phosphorylation of ITAM tyrosines. Shark kinase, <lb/>like ZAP70, binds specifically to the ITAM motif, and we show that ITAM phosphorylation plays <lb/>an important role in signaling. However, unlike the TCR, Draper contains non-ITAM tyrosines, <lb/>and our kinetic assay for phagocytosis shows that non-ITAM tyrosines play a role in the full <lb/>activation of Draper. Our results are consistent with reports that both ITAM and non-ITAM <lb/>residues on Draper contribute to signaling (Fujita et al., 2012; Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). The <lb/>phosphorylated non-ITAM tyrosines in Draper may bind additional SH2-containing adapter <lb/>proteins-further studies will be needed to identify additional direct binding partners of the <lb/>phosphorylated cytoplasmic tail domain of Draper besides Shark. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Our in vitro results with a completely biochemically defined system also reveal that Draper&apos;s <lb/>ITAM domain is required for the phosphorylation of the non-ITAM tyrosines. This result indicates <lb/>a sequential mechanism for multisite phosphorylation on Draper. One model for how this might <lb/>occur is through the direct recruitment of Src family kinases to the phosphorylated ITAM domain <lb/>of Draper. The kinase (e.g. Src42a) has a higher specificity for the tyrosines in Draper&apos;s ITAM, <lb/>domain and phosphorylates these residues first. Once phosphorylated, Src42a then can bind to <lb/>the phosphorylated ITAM through its own SH2 domain; while bound to Draper, the kinase can <lb/>phosphorylate non-ITAM residues on Draper. A mechanism in which a kinase creates its own <lb/>binding site before modifying other residues has been suggested for both Src-dependent <lb/>phosphorylation of synthetic ITAM-containing substrate peptides (Pellicena et al., 1998) and <lb/>phosphorylation of p130 CAS by Abl kinase (Mayer et al., 1995). A similar phenomenon was <lb/>observed for Lck-dependent modification of sequential ITAM residues on the T cell receptor, <lb/>which is required for full activation of this receptor (Lewis et al., 1997). Thus, in common with <lb/>other signaling systems, Draper phosphorylation involves a hierarchal phosphorylation of <lb/>tyrosines in its tail domain and this hierarchal phosphorylation is required for full receptor <lb/>activation. <lb/>Our findings also may shed light on mechanism of action for phagocytic receptors in organisms <lb/>beyond the fly. Mammalian glial cells encode a Draper ortholog Megf10, a predicted single pass <lb/>transmembrane protein with putative ITAMs that recruit Syk kinase (Scheib et al., 2012). <lb/>Though mechanistic differences likely exist between Draper and Megf10 as a consequence of <lb/>evolutionary divergence and distinct organismal requirements, Megf10&apos;s cytoplasmic tail <lb/>contains 12 cytoplasmic tyrosine residues, only 4 of which comprise the putative ITAMs (Scheib <lb/>et al., 2012). Therefore, it will be interesting to investigate if full activation of Megf10 may <lb/>proceed through a similar sequential, multisite tyrosine phosphorylation mechanism as Draper. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Comparison between Draper triggering and activation of mammalian immune receptors <lb/>A potential similarity between Draper and T cell signaling was first suggested by the finding of <lb/>an ITAM in the Draper cytoplasmic tail (Ziegenfuss et al., 2008). Our findings provide <lb/>mechanistic support of this idea. T cells are triggered via a kinetic segregation mechanism <lb/>governed by local shifting of a kinase-phosphatase equilibrium toward receptor phosphorylation <lb/>(Davis and van der Merwe, 2006). Briefly, apposition of a membrane-membrane interface at the <lb/>synapse between T cell and the antigen presenting cell (APC) results in the exclusion of the <lb/>bulky transmembrane phosphatase CD45. When local CD45 concentration is reduced below a <lb/>threshold, activity of the membrane-bound kinase Lck is favored. Lck phosphorylates the TCR <lb/>cytoplasmic ITAM motifs which in turn recruit ZAP70 kinase, an essential downstream kinase <lb/>involved in T cell activation (James and Vale, 2012). A similar segregation mechanism was <lb/>recently proposed to regulate FcR activation through creating an integrin-based diffusion barrier <lb/>that excludes CD45 (S. A. Freeman et al., 2016). <lb/>Here, we provide evidence that Draper may be activated through a kinetic segregation <lb/>mechanism. Draper ligation to PS results in the formation of microclusters that are transported <lb/>by the actin cytoskeleton. The behavior of these microclusters is very similar to that described <lb/>for the T cell receptor (Bunnell et al., 2002; Douglass and Vale, 2005; Varma et al., 2006). <lb/>Draper ligation to PS on a second membrane (either an apoptotic cells or an artificial membrane <lb/>composed of a supported lipid bilayer) also excludes a transmembrane phosphatase from the <lb/>synapse at the region of receptor phosphorylation and kinase recruitment (Fig. 3A). In the case <lb/>of T cells, a single transmembrane phosphatase (CD45) is highly expressed on the surface and <lb/>appears to be the dominant phosphatase in regulating signaling. However, phagocytic cells <lb/>likely express several transmembrane phosphatases, which together may contribute to <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>regulating Draper and other phagocytic receptors. Draper is also regulated by at least one <lb/>cytosolic phosphatase, Corkscrew (Csw, SHP1/2), that is recruited to an alternative short splice <lb/>isoform of Draper, Draper-II (Logan et al., 2012), that encodes an Immunoreceptor Tyrosine-<lb/>based Inhibitory Motif (ITIM). In the future, it will be important to determine how the specific <lb/>composition of phosphatases on the membrane (different sizes and expression levels) are used <lb/>to dampen and fine-tune the sensitivity of engulfment. <lb/>Synthetic engulfment receptors <lb/>Analogous to TCRs, the extracellular ligand and receptor for Draper can be functionally <lb/>replaced by other interacting modules such as FKBP-rapamycin-FRB. These chimeric receptors <lb/>create signaling zones for both Draper (Fig. 3E) and TCR (James and Vale, 2012). The ability to <lb/>replace the extracellular modules implies that Draper signaling does not require a ligand-<lb/>induced conformational change to the cytoplasmic tail, although the possibility that such <lb/>changes augment signaling cannot be excluded. Our ability to replace Draper and PS with a <lb/>synthetic FKBP-rapamycin-FRB module also provides a mechanistic basis to reprogram <lb/>engulfment signaling toward non-native targets. This idea is a conceptually similar to that of <lb/>chimeric T cell receptors that recognize cancer antigen to promote specific cell killing (Lim and <lb/>June, 2017). Collectively, we have revealed that understanding the fundamental cell biology and <lb/>biochemistry underlying early steps of Draper activation provide a mechanistic basis to <lb/>reprogram engulfment signaling. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank C. Carbone, E. Hui, N.Kern, M. Morrissey, X. Su, and M. Taylor for reagents and <lb/>discussions, N. Stuurman for help with microscopy, and L. Kohlstaedt and Y-S Kim (QB3/UC <lb/>Berkeley) for performing the mass spectrometry. We also thank E. Hui, A. Jain, M. Morrissey, <lb/>K. McKinley, X. Su, and P. Williamson for critical reading of the manuscript. A.P.W. was <lb/>supported by a CRI-Irvington Postdoctoral Fellowship. This work was funded by the Howard <lb/>Hughes Medical Institute and the National Institutes of Health (R01EB007187, R.D.V.). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>A.P.W. and R.D.V. conceived of the study and designed the experiments. A.P.W. performed the <lb/>experiments, analyzed the data, and prepared the figures. A.P.W. and R.D.V. wrote the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Financial Interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Arandjelovic, S., Ravichandran, K.S., 2015. Phagocytosis of apoptotic cells in homeostasis. Nat. <lb/>Immunol. 16, 907-917. doi:10.1038/ni.3253 <lb/>Bunnell, S.C., Hong, D.I., Kardon, J.R., Yamazaki, T., McGlade, C.J., Barr, V.A., Samelson, <lb/>L.E., 2002. T cell receptor ligation induces the formation of dynamically regulated signaling <lb/>assemblies. J. Cell Biol. 158, 1263-1275. doi:10.1083/jcb.200203043 <lb/>Burroughs, N.J., Lazic, Z., van der Merwe, P.A., 2006. Ligand detection and discrimination by <lb/>spatial relocalization: A kinase-phosphatase segregation model of TCR activation. Biophys. <lb/>J. 91, 1619-1629. doi:10.1529/biophysj.105.080044 <lb/>Cherbas, L., Willingham, A., Zhang, D., Yang, L., Zou, Y., Eads, B.D., Carlson, J.W., Landolin, <lb/>J.M., Kapranov, P., Dumais, J., Samsonova, A., Choi, J.-H., Roberts, J., Davis, C.A., Tang, <lb/>H., van Baren, M.J., Ghosh, S., Dobin, A., Bell, K., Lin, W., Langton, L., Duff, M.O., Tenney, <lb/>A.E., Zaleski, C., Brent, M.R., Hoskins, R.A., Kaufman, T.C., Andrews, J., Graveley, B.R., <lb/>Perrimon, N., Celniker, S.E., Gingeras, T.R., Cherbas, P., 2011. The transcriptional diversity <lb/>of 25 Drosophila cell lines. Genome Res. 21, 301-314. doi:10.1101/gr.112961.110 <lb/>Choudhuri, K., Dustin, M.L., 2010. Signaling microdomains in T cells. FEBS Lett. 584, 4823-<lb/>4831. doi:10.1016/j.febslet.2010.10.015 <lb/>Choudhuri, K., Wiseman, D., Brown, M.H., Gould, K., van der Merwe, P.A., 2005. T-cell receptor <lb/>triggering is critically dependent on the dimensions of its peptide-MHC ligand. Nature 436, <lb/>578-582. doi:10.1038/nature03843 <lb/>Davis, S.J., van der Merwe, P.A., 2006. The kinetic-segregation model: TCR triggering and <lb/>beyond. Nat. Immunol. 7, 803-809. doi:10.1038/ni1369 <lb/>Douglass, A.D., Vale, R.D., 2005. Single-molecule microscopy reveals plasma membrane <lb/>microdomains created by protein-protein networks that exclude or trap signaling molecules <lb/>in T cells. Cell 121, 937-950. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2005.04.009 <lb/>Edelstein, A., Amodaj, N., Hoover, K., Vale, R., Stuurman, N., 2010. Computer control of <lb/>microscopes using µManager. Curr Protoc Mol Biol Chapter 14, Unit14.20-14.20.17. <lb/>doi:10.1002/0471142727.mb1420s92 <lb/>Elliott, M.R., Ravichandran, K.S., 2010. Clearance of apoptotic cells: implications in health and <lb/>disease. J. Cell Biol. 189, 1059-1070. doi:10.1083/jcb.201004096 <lb/>Etchegaray, J.I., Timmons, A.K., Klein, A.P., Pritchett, T.L., Welch, E., Meehan, T.L., Li, C., <lb/>McCall, K., 2012. Draper acts through the JNK pathway to control synchronous engulfment <lb/>of dying germline cells by follicular epithelial cells. Development 139, 4029-4039. <lb/>doi:10.1242/dev.082776 <lb/>Evans, I.R., Rodrigues, F.S.L.M., Armitage, E.L., Wood, W., 2015. Draper/CED-1 mediates an <lb/>ancient damage response to control inflammatory blood cell migration in vivo. Curr. Biol. 25, <lb/>1606-1612. doi:10.1016/j.cub.2015.04.037 <lb/>Fadok, V.A., Voelker, D.R., Campbell, P.A., Cohen, J.J., Bratton, D.L., Henson, P.M., 1992. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Exposure of phosphatidylserine on the surface of apoptotic lymphocytes triggers specific <lb/>recognition and removal by macrophages. J. Immunol. 148, 2207-2216. <lb/>Freeman, M.R., Delrow, J., Kim, J., Johnson, E., Doe, C.Q., 2003. Unwrapping glial biology: <lb/>Gcm target genes regulating glial development, diversification, and function. Neuron 38, <lb/>567-580. <lb/>Freeman, S.A., Goyette, J., Furuya, W., Woods, E.C., Bertozzi, C.R., Bergmeier, W., Hinz, B., <lb/>van der Merwe, P.A., Das, R., Grinstein, S., 2016. Integrins Form an Expanding Diffusional <lb/>Barrier that Coordinates Phagocytosis. Cell 164, 128-140. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2015.11.048 <lb/>Freeman, S.A., Grinstein, S., 2014. Phagocytosis: receptors, signal integration, and the <lb/>cytoskeleton. Immunol. Rev. 262, 193-215. doi:10.1111/imr.12212 <lb/>Fujita, Y., Nagaosa, K., Shiratsuchi, A., Nakanishi, Y., 2012. Role of NPxY motif in Draper-<lb/>mediated apoptotic cell clearance in Drosophila. Drug Discov Ther 6, 291-297. <lb/>Hui, E., Vale, R.D., 2014. In vitro membrane reconstitution of the T-cell receptor proximal <lb/>signaling network. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 21, 133-142. doi:10.1038/nsmb.2762 <lb/>Iram, T., Ramirez-Ortiz, Z., Byrne, M.H., Coleman, U.A., Kingery, N.D., Means, T.K., Frenkel, <lb/>D., Khoury, El, J., 2016. Megf10 Is a Receptor for C1Q That Mediates Clearance of <lb/>Apoptotic Cells by Astrocytes. J. Neurosci. 36, 5185-5192. doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3850-<lb/>15.2016 <lb/>James, J.R., Vale, R.D., 2012. Biophysical mechanism of T-cell receptor triggering in a <lb/>reconstituted system. Nature 487, 64-69. doi:10.1038/nature11220 <lb/>Kaizuka, Y., Douglass, A.D., Varma, R., Dustin, M.L., Vale, R.D., 2007. Mechanisms for <lb/>segregating T cell receptor and adhesion molecules during immunological synapse <lb/>formation in Jurkat T cells. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 104, 20296-20301. <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.0710258105 <lb/>Kuraishi, T., Nakagawa, Y., Nagaosa, K., Hashimoto, Y., Ishimoto, T., Moki, T., Fujita, Y., <lb/>Nakayama, H., Dohmae, N., Shiratsuchi, A., Yamamoto, N., Ueda, K., Yamaguchi, M., <lb/>Awasaki, T., Nakanishi, Y., 2009. Pretaporter, a Drosophila protein serving as a ligand for <lb/>Draper in the phagocytosis of apoptotic cells. EMBO J. 28, 3868-3878. <lb/>doi:10.1038/emboj.2009.343 <lb/>Leventis, P.A., Grinstein, S., 2010. The distribution and function of phosphatidylserine in cellular <lb/>membranes. Annu Rev Biophys 39, 407-427. doi:10.1146/annurev.biophys.093008.131234 <lb/>Lewis, L.A., Chung, C.D., Chen, J., Parnes, J.R., Moran, M., Patel, V.P., Miceli, M.C., 1997. The <lb/>Lck SH2 phosphotyrosine binding site is critical for efficient TCR-induced processive <lb/>tyrosine phosphorylation of the zeta-chain and IL-2 production. J. Immunol. 159, 2292-<lb/>2300. <lb/>Lim, W.A., June, C.H., 2017. The Principles of Engineering Immune Cells to Treat Cancer. Cell <lb/>168, 724-740. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2017.01.016 <lb/>Logan, M.A., Hackett, R., Doherty, J., Sheehan, A., Speese, S.D., Freeman, M.R., 2012. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Negative regulation of glial engulfment activity by Draper terminates glial responses to axon <lb/>injury. Nat. Neurosci. 15, 722-730. doi:10.1038/nn.3066 <lb/>Lu, T.-Y., Doherty, J., Freeman, M.R., 2014. DRK/DOS/SOS converge with Crk/Mbc/dCed-12 to <lb/>activate Rac1 during glial engulfment of axonal debris. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 111, <lb/>12544-12549. doi:10.1073/pnas.1403450111 <lb/>MacDonald, J.M., Beach, M.G., Porpiglia, E., Sheehan, A.E., Watts, R.J., Freeman, M.R., 2006. <lb/>The Drosophila cell corpse engulfment receptor Draper mediates glial clearance of severed <lb/>axons. Neuron 50, 869-881. doi:10.1016/j.neuron.2006.04.028 <lb/>Mayer, B.J., Hirai, H., Sakai, R., 1995. Evidence that SH2 domains promote processive <lb/>phosphorylation by protein-tyrosine kinases. Curr. Biol. 5, 296-305. <lb/>Murugesan, S., Hong, J., Yi, J., Li, D., Beach, J.R., Shao, L., Meinhardt, J., Madison, G., Wu, <lb/>X., Betzig, E., Hammer, J.A., 2016. Formin-generated actomyosin arcs propel T cell <lb/>receptor microcluster movement at the immune synapse. J. Cell Biol. 215, 383-399. <lb/>doi:10.1083/jcb.201603080 <lb/>Neumann, B., Coakley, S., Giordano-Santini, R., Linton, C., Lee, E.S., Nakagawa, A., Xue, D., <lb/>Hilliard, M.A., 2015. EFF-1-mediated regenerative axonal fusion requires components of the <lb/>apoptotic pathway. Nature 517, 219-222. doi:10.1038/nature14102 <lb/>Okada, R., Nagaosa, K., Kuraishi, T., Nakayama, H., Yamamoto, N., Nakagawa, Y., Dohmae, <lb/>N., Shiratsuchi, A., Nakanishi, Y., 2012. Apoptosis-dependent externalization and <lb/>involvement in apoptotic cell clearance of DmCaBP1, an endoplasmic reticulum protein of <lb/>Drosophila. J. Biol. Chem. 287, 3138-3146. doi:10.1074/jbc.M111.277921 <lb/>Pellicena, P., Stowell, K.R., Miller, W.T., 1998. Enhanced phosphorylation of Src family kinase <lb/>substrates containing SH2 domain binding sites. Journal of Biological Chemistry 273, <lb/>15325-15328. <lb/>Penberthy, K.K., Ravichandran, K.S., 2016. Apoptotic cell recognition receptors and scavenger <lb/>receptors. Immunol. Rev. 269, 44-59. doi:10.1111/imr.12376 <lb/>Purice, M.D., Ray, A., Münzel, E.J., Pope, B.J., Park, D.J., Speese, S.D., Logan, M.A., 2017. A <lb/>novel Drosophila injury model reveals severed axons are cleared through a Draper/MMP-1 <lb/>signaling cascade. Elife 6, R55. doi:10.7554/eLife.23611 <lb/>Ravichandran, K.S., Lorenz, U., 2007. Engulfment of apoptotic cells: signals for a good meal. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Immunol. 7, 964-974. doi:10.1038/nri2214 <lb/>Reddien, P.W., Horvitz, H.R., 2004. The engulfment process of programmed cell death in <lb/>caenorhabditis elegans. Annu. Rev. Cell Dev. Biol. 20, 193-221. <lb/>doi:10.1146/annurev.cellbio.20.022003.114619 <lb/>Scheib, J.L., Sullivan, C.S., Carter, B.D., 2012. Jedi-1 and MEGF10 signal engulfment of <lb/>apoptotic neurons through the tyrosine kinase Syk. J. Neurosci. 32, 13022-13031. <lb/>doi:10.1523/JNEUROSCI.6350-11.2012 <lb/>Schneider, I., 1972. Cell lines derived from late embryonic stages of Drosophila melanogaster. J <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Embryol Exp Morphol 27, 353-365. <lb/>Schultz, J., Copley, R.R., Doerks, T., Ponting, C.P., Bork, P., 2000. SMART: a web-based tool <lb/>for the study of genetically mobile domains. Nucleic Acids Res. 28, 231-234. <lb/>Tung, T.T., Nagaosa, K., Fujita, Y., Kita, A., Mori, H., Okada, R., Nonaka, S., Nakanishi, Y., <lb/>2013. Phosphatidylserine recognition and induction of apoptotic cell clearance by <lb/>Drosophila engulfment receptor Draper. J. Biochem. 153, 483-491. doi:10.1093/jb/mvt014 <lb/>Varma, R., Campi, G., Yokosuka, T., Saito, T., Dustin, M.L., 2006. T cell receptor-proximal <lb/>signals are sustained in peripheral microclusters and terminated in the central <lb/>supramolecular activation cluster. Immunity 25, 117-127. doi:10.1016/j.immuni.2006.04.010 <lb/>Zhou, Z., Hartwieg, E., Horvitz, H.R., 2001. CED-1 is a transmembrane receptor that mediates <lb/>cell corpse engulfment in C. elegans. Cell 104, 43-56. <lb/>Ziegenfuss, J.S., Biswas, R., Avery, M.A., Hong, K., Sheehan, A.E., Yeung, Y.-G., Stanley, <lb/>E.R., Freeman, M.R., 2008. Draper-dependent glial phagocytic activity is mediated by Src <lb/>and Syk family kinase signalling. Nature 453, 935-939. doi:10.1038/nature06901 <lb/>Ziegenfuss, J.S., Doherty, J., Freeman, M.R., 2012. Distinct molecular pathways mediate glial <lb/>activation and engulfment of axonal debris after axotomy. Nat. Neurosci. 15, 979-987. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nn.3135 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure Legends <lb/>Figure 1: Cellular reconstitution of Draper signaling <lb/>A. Schematic of apoptotic cell clearance by professional phagocytes; multiple receptors <lb/>including Draper (green) recognize distinct ligands to promote engulfment of dying cell corpses <lb/>(purple). Representative image of an Annexin V-APC labeled cell corpse fully internalized by a <lb/>Draper-GFP expressing S2 cell. Overexpression of Draper-GFP in S2 cells results in a ~5 fold <lb/>increase in phagocytic proficiency toward apoptotic cell corpses. Draper-GFP+ S2 cells were <lb/>incubated with labeled cell corpses and phagocytic proficiency was assessed after 45 min <lb/>incubation at 27 o C. Results from 3 independent biological replicates are shown (mean ± SD). B. <lb/>Schematic of reconstitution system to study Draper signaling. The cell corpse was replaced with <lb/>a silica bead coated with a supported lipid bilayer containing phosphatidylserine (PS). <lb/>Representative image of an atto390-labeled 10% PS bead fully internalized by a Draper-GFP <lb/>expressing S2 cell. Draper overexpression increases PS-bead phagocytic proficiency ~7 fold. <lb/>S2 cells were transfected with either Draper-GFP or a GFP control vector and incubated with <lb/>PC or 10% PS beads for 30 min at 27 o C. The mean number of beads fully ingested per cell for <lb/>three independent biological replicates are shown (mean ± SD). C. Draper-GFP expressing S2 <lb/>cells were incubated with beads containing increasing mol. % of PS in the supported lipid <lb/>bilayer and phagocytic proficiency was assessed after 30 min incubation at 27 o C (mean ± SD). <lb/>D. Upon completion of the phagocytic cup, beads internalized. Draper-GFP/Lifeact-BFP S2 cells <lb/>were incubated with 10% PS/0.1% rhodamine-PE beads and imaged every 3 min by spinning <lb/>disk confocal microscopy. A middle section from a z-stack movie is shown. Stills are taken from <lb/>Movie 1. Upon completion of the phagocytic cup (as assessed by Lifeact), internalization of the <lb/>bead occurs. Scale bars, 5 µm. <lb/>Figure 2: Draper organizes into mobile microclusters that recruit signaling molecules <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>A. Draper-GFP is tyrosine phosphorylated at the interface with a 10% PS bead. Draper-GFP+ <lb/>S2 cells were incubated with 10% PS beads. After 30 min incubation cells were fixed, <lb/>permeabilized and stained with phosphotyrosine (pTyr) antibody. pTyr staining is enriched at the <lb/>synapse between bead and cell. During fixation and permeabilization, the supported lipid bilayer <lb/>on the bead is stripped off; bead position is indicated by dashed white line. B. Shark kinase is <lb/>enriched at the synapse between 10% PS bead and the S2 cell. S2 cells were co-transfected <lb/>with Draper-GFP and Shark-mCherry and incubated with 10% PS beads labeled with 0.5% <lb/>atto390-DOPE. After 15 min, cells with active synapses were imaged by spinning disk confocal <lb/>microscopy. The middle slice from a z-stack is shown. C. Schematic of TIRF-M assay setup to <lb/>visualize ligated Draper-GFP at the plasma membrane. Draper-GFP+ S2 cells were allowed to <lb/>settle on 10% PS supported lipid bilayer (SLB) prepared on a glass coverslip, and Draper-GFP+ <lb/>was imaged directly in real time. D. Draper-GFP forms microclusters on 10% PS SLB. Draper-<lb/>GFP microclusters visualized by TIRF-M undergo retrograde flow towards a central synapse. <lb/>Microclusters fuse with one-another and are repopulated from the periphery. Time in min:sec. E. <lb/>Draper-GFP microclusters on 10% PS bilayers recruit Shark-TagBFP and Crk-mCherry to the <lb/>plasma membrane. Cells co-transfected with receptor, kinase and adapter were allowed to <lb/>settle on 10% PS bilayers as D. and imaged after spreading. Scale bars, 5 µm. <lb/>Figure 3: Segregation of Draper and a transmembrane phosphatase at the synapse <lb/>A. The transmembrane phosphatase Ptp69D segregates away from Draper at synapses <lb/>between 10% PS beads and the S2 cell. Draper-mCherry and Ptp69D-GFP were co-transfected <lb/>into S2 cells and localization at the synapse after a 15 min incubation. B. Schematic showing <lb/>extracellular FRB fused to the Draper transmembrane and cytosolic domains (FRB-EXT-Draper-<lb/>INT) to program clearance signaling towards FKBP-bearing beads (see Methods). FRB and <lb/>FKBP are brought together into a 100 fM ternary complex in the presence of 1 µM rapamycin. <lb/>C. FRB-EXT-Draper-INT promotes specific phagocytosis of FKBP beads. S2 cells transfected <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>with FRB-EXT-Draper-INT were incubated with 10 nM FKBP beads for 30 min, after which bead <lb/>ingestion was quantified after imaging using spinning disk confocal microscopy (see Methods). <lb/>The mean number of beads fully ingested per cell for three independent biological replicates are <lb/>shown (mean ± SD). Cells were incubated either with 1 µM rapamycin (right, +) or an equivalent <lb/>volume of DMSO vehicle (left, -). D. The kinase Shark is recruited to FRB-EXT-Draper-INT, <lb/>indicating local receptor activation by tyrosine phosphorylation. S2 cells expressing FRB-EXT-<lb/>Draper-INT-GFP and Shark-Cherry were incubated with FKBP beads coupled to 10 nM his10 <lb/>protein (see Methods) in the presence of 1 µM rapamycin for 15 min and localization was <lb/>assessed. A middle section from a confocal z-stack is shown. E. S2 cells were transfected with <lb/>FRB-EXT-Draper-INT-mCherry, Shark-TagBFP, and Ptp69D-GFP and allowed to settle on SLB <lb/>with bound His 10 -FKBP bilayers in the presence of 1 µM rapamycin for 15 min. Ptp69D <lb/>segregates away from activated Draper at the interface between FKBP bilayer and S2 cell. In <lb/>contrast, Draper and Shark overlapped, indicating local receptor activation and segregation <lb/>away from Ptp69D at the synapse. Scale bars, 5 µm. <lb/>Figure 4: Roles of Draper&apos;s cytoplasmic tyrosine residues in engulfment of PS beads <lb/>A. Engulfment of 10% PS beads by S2 cells expressing Draper-GFP, Draper-Ala11-GFP, or a <lb/>GFP control was assessed after 45 min incubation. Mean number of beads ingested per cell for <lb/>three biological replicates are shown (mean ± SD). B. Alignment of residues mutated to Phe in <lb/>Draper-∆ITAM. C. Draper-∆ITAM displays a kinetic delay and reduced phagocytic proficiency <lb/>relative to Draper-GFP, while Draper&apos;s ITAM (ITAM only) is sufficient for partial engulfment <lb/>activity. S2 cells transfected with Draper-GFP or indicated mutants were incubated with 10% PS <lb/>beads, allowed to settle, and imaged at the indicated time points. The mean number of beads <lb/>fully ingested per cell for three independent biological replicates are shown (mean ± SD). <lb/>Figure 5: In vitro reconstitution of hierarchical multisite Tyr phosphorylation on Draper <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>A. Schematic of liposome-FRET assay to detect direct binding between Draper&apos;s <lb/>phosphorylated tail and SH2-domain containing reporter proteins. Assay is described in detail in <lb/>the Methods. Briefly, when a BG505-labeled reporter protein comes into close proximity to a <lb/>rhodamine labeled liposome, the 505 nm fluorescence signal is quenched. If quenching that <lb/>occurs after addition of ATP binding is likely due to the Src42a-dependent phosphorylation of <lb/>Draper&apos;s cytoplasmic tyrosine residues. The results shown here reveal that direct binding of <lb/>BG505-Shark-tSH2 to Draper&apos;s tail is dependent on an intact ITAM on Draper. His 10 -Draper <lb/>cytosolic domain or His 10 -DraperY934F/Y949F (∆ITAM) receptor tail were ligated to 0.5% <lb/>rhodamine-PE liposomes and ATP dependent quenching was assessed. <lb/>B. On-liposome phosphorylation reactions to assess Draper activation by its cognate Src family <lb/>kinase Src42a. His 10 -Draper cytoplasmic domain or 10his-DraperY934F/Y949F (∆ITAM) <lb/>receptor tail (both at 1 µM) were ligated to liposomes doped with DGS-Ni-NTA and incubated <lb/>with 86 nM soluble Src42a and 1 mM ATP for 30 min. Reactions were quenched with SDS-<lb/>PAGE buffer containing DTT and 2-Me and boiled for 10 min at 95 o C. Samples were <lb/>immunoblotted with phosphotyrosine antibody or His 10 antibody. Quantification of <lb/>phosphorylation of WT or ∆ITAM by Src42a was determined as the ratio of total pTyr signal very <lb/>total His 10 signal internally for each lane. C. On-liposome phosphorylation reactions to assess <lb/>Draper activation by Src42a (86 nM) were performed as above. 1 µM His 10 -Draper cytoplasmic <lb/>domain were phosphorylated as 5B above with the exception that samples were quenched <lb/>using 10 mM EDTA and 8 M Urea and digested for 1D mass spectrometry (see Methods). <lb/>Height of bar corresponds to percent phosphorylated peptide (number of phosphorylated <lb/>peptides detected divided by total number of peptides detected). Total peptides detected for <lb/>each site residue in parentheses: Y838 (14), Y858 (14), Y888 (9), Y901 (29), Y905 (29), Y924 <lb/>(71), Y934 (68), Y943 (7), Y949 (10), Y954 (10), Y965 (0). <lb/>Figure 6: Mechanism of Draper triggering <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>(1) Draper ligation to PS on a cell corpse creates an exclusion zone where ligated receptors <lb/>cluster at the synapse and unligated molecules such as bulky transmembrane phosphatases <lb/>segregate away from receptors. (2) Spatial segregation between receptors and inhibitory <lb/>phosphatases shifts the balance towards receptor phosphorylation by Src42a, a reaction <lb/>strikingly similar to triggering of TCRs by the kinase Lck. Src42a first phosphorylates Draper&apos;s <lb/>ITAM and then modifies non-ITAM Tyr residues that also contribute to signaling. (3) Tyr <lb/>phosphorylation on Draper&apos;s tail recruits cytosolic effector proteins including the kinase Shark in <lb/>a manner similar to recruitment of the kinase ZAP70 to triggered TCRs. (4) Effector recruitment <lb/>to phosphorylated Draper molecules promotes signaling outputs including cytoskeletal <lb/>remodeling and engulfment. <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Movie Legends <lb/>Movie 1: Cellular reconstitution of Draper signaling <lb/>Movie of stills shown in Fig. 1D. An S2 cell co-transfected with Draper-GFP and Lifeact-BFP <lb/>was incubated with 10% PS/0.5% atto647-PE 6.4 µm silica beads. Movie is a maximum <lb/>projection of a z-stack (1 µm between z-positions). Z-stacks captured by spinning disk confocal <lb/>microscopy were recorded every 3 min. Scale bar, 5 µm. <lb/>Movie 2: Formation of mobile Draper-GFP microclusters on 10% PS bilayers <lb/>Movie of stills shown in Fig. 2D. An S2 cell transfected with Draper-GFP was allowed to settle <lb/>on 10% PS supported lipid bilayers and imaged by TIRF microscopy. Cell was imaged every 15 <lb/>sec. Draper-GFP forms mobile microclusters that appear at the edge of the spread cell and <lb/>migrate toward the prominent central synapse. Scale bar, 5 µm. <lb/>Movie 3: Visualization of Draper and F-actin on 10% PS bilayers <lb/>An S2 cell co-transfected with Draper-mCherry and Lifeact-eGFP was allowed to settle on 10% <lb/>PS supported lipid bilayers and imaged by TIRF microscopy. Cell was imaged every min. <lb/>Channels were split so Draper-mCherry and Lifeact-eGFP can be visualized simultaneously. <lb/>Note the F-actin &quot;hole&quot; visible at the last timepoint, where the central synapse of Draper-<lb/>mCherry signal appears to exclude F-actin as visualized by Lifeact-eGFP. Scale bar, 5 µm. <lb/>Movie 4: Visualization of signaling microclusters on 10% PS bilayers <lb/>Movie of stills shown in Fig. 2E. An S2 cell co-transfected with Draper-GFP, Shark-TagBFP, and <lb/>Crk-mCherry was allowed to settle on 10% PS supported lipid bilayers and imaged by TIRF <lb/>microscopy. Cell was imaged every 15 sec. Draper-GFP, Shark-TagBFP, and Crk-mCherry co-<lb/>localize at mobile microclusters that flow towards the central synapse. Scale bar, 5 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Movie 5: Visualization of FKBP-Bead engulfment by a chimeric FRB-Draper receptor <lb/>An S2 cell, co-transfected with FRB-EXT-Draper-INT-mCherry and Lifeact-eGFP, was <lb/>incubated with 2% DGS-Ni-NTA/0.5% atto390-PE 6.46 µm silica beads incubated with 10 nM <lb/>His 10 -FKBP, washed, and resuspended prior to imaging. FKBP beads were incubated with co-<lb/>transfected S2 cells in the presence of 1 µM rapamycin, allowed to settle in the imaging <lb/>chamber for 5 min, and visualized at 5 min intervals by spinning disk confocal microscopy. <lb/>Scale bar, 5 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Figure Legends <lb/>Figure S1 (related to Figure 2): p85 and Crk are recruited to Draper rich synapses with <lb/>10% PS beads <lb/>Draper-mCherry&apos;s ability to bring the indicated SH2-GFP proteins to the plasma membrane at <lb/>the synapse with a 10% PS bead. Shark, p85 (the PI3K activating subunit), and Crk were <lb/>recruited to Draper-mCherry at the synapse,while Stat92E was not recruited. Scale bars <lb/>indicate 5 µm. <lb/>Figure S2 (related to Figure 3): The transmembrane phosphatase Ptp69D. <lb/>A. Drosophila S2 cells express an array of transmembrane phosphatases. RNA levels measure <lb/>by RNA-Seq (NLM/NCBI GEO GSM410195), organized in descending order of RNA measured, <lb/>indicated in reads per kilobase of exon model per million mapped reads (RPKM). B. Schematic <lb/>of Ptp69D-GFP domain structure, highlighting features of its bulky extracellular domain. C. <lb/>Draper-mCherry clusters exclude Ptp69D-GFP on 10% PS supported lipid bilayers (SLBs). <lb/>Draper-mCherry/Ptp69D-GFP expressing S2 cells were allowed to settle and spread on bilayers <lb/>and localization of receptor and phosphatase assessed after 15 minutes. Phosphatase <lb/>exclusion was observed both at peripheral clusters and the central synapse. Scale bar indicates <lb/>5 µm. <lb/>Figure S3 (related to Figure 4): Draper&apos;s ITAM is necessary and sufficient to recruit Shark <lb/>in cells. <lb/>S2 cells co-transfected with Draper, Draper-∆ITAM, or Draper-ITAM Only-GFP and Shark-<lb/>TagBFP were incubated with 10% PS beads labeled with 0.5% atto647-PE. Localization of <lb/>receptor and Shark-TagBFP was assessed after 15 min cell settling by spinning disk confocal <lb/></div>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">microscopy. Images were acquired using the same microscope settings and scaled equally for <lb/>comparison. Scale bars indicate 5 µm. <lb/>Figure S4 (related to Figure 5): Identification of phosphorylation sites on Draper by Lck <lb/>A. On-liposome phosphorylation reactions to assess Draper activation by His10-Lck-Y505F (1 <lb/>nM) was performed as Fig. 5. 1 µM His10-Draper cytoplasmic domain was phosphorylated <lb/>andquenched using 10 mM EDTA and 8 M Urea and digested for 1D mass spectrometry. Height <lb/>of bar corresponds to percent phosphorylated peptide divided by total number of peptides <lb/>detected. Total peptides detected for each site residue in parentheses: Y838 (0), Y858 (0), <lb/>Y888 (4), Y901 (35), Y905 (35), Y924 (15), Y934 (16), Y943 (0), Y949 (0), Y954 (0), Y965 (0). <lb/>B. To perform on-liposome phosphorylation reactions to assess Draper activation by Lck, 1 µM <lb/>10his-Draper cytoplasmic domain or 10his-DraperY934F/Y949F (∆ITAM) receptor tail were <lb/>ligated to liposomes doped with DGS-Ni-NTA and incubated with 1 nM his10-Lck-Y505F and 1 <lb/>mM ATP for 30 min. Reactions were quenched with SDS-PAGE buffer containing DTT and 2-<lb/>Me and boiled for 10 min at 95oC. Samples were run on a 4-20% gradient gel and pan <lb/>phosphotyrosine (800 nm anti-mouse secondary) was assessed by western blotting and Licor <lb/>imaging. Presence of receptor tail was confirmed using his probe (700 nm anti-rabbit <lb/>secondary). Quantification of phosphorylation of WT or ∆ITAM by Lck was determined as the <lb/>ratio of total pTyr signal:total his signal internally for each lane and reported as the % signal on <lb/>∆ITAM. <lb/></div>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Note: See the completed KEY RESOURCES TABLE for supplier and catalog information <lb/>Contact for Reagent and Resource Sharing <lb/>Requests for further information and reagents should be directed to and will be fulfilled by the <lb/>corresponding author, Ronald D. Vale (ron.vale@ucsf.edu). <lb/>Experimental Model and Subject Details <lb/>Drosophila S2 Cell Culture <lb/>Drosophila S2U cells were cultured in Schneider&apos;s media (Gibco) supplemented with 10% Fetal <lb/>Bovine Serum (FBS, Atlanta) and 1x antibiotic-antimycotic (Gibco). S2 cells were grown in non-<lb/>vented T25 or T75 flasks (Corning) and split every 3-6 days from high density cultures (~50-<lb/>80%). S2U cells were not split to below ~25% confluency as S2U cells are unhappy at low <lb/>density. Healthy S2U cells adhere gently to the surface of the culture dish rather than floating, <lb/>but can be split by gently resuspending the adhered cells using a tissue culture pipet and a 10 <lb/>ml sterile tissue culture pipet. Enzymatic dissociation using trypsin or by scraping is <lb/>unnecessary for S2U cells. Frozen stocks were prepared regularly. S2U freeze media is: 45% <lb/>fresh complete media, 45% sterile filtered conditioned media prepared after spinning the media <lb/>for 5 min at 1000 x g, and 10% DMSO (Sigma). A confluent T75 dish of S2U cells was pelleted <lb/>for 5 min at 1000 x g, resuspended in 10 ml of freeze media (described above) and split as 1 ml <lb/>aliquots in externally-threaded cryotubes (Corning), stored at -80 o C in a cell freezing apparatus <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>containing isopropyl alcohol, and transferred to long term storage in liquid nitrogen, vapor <lb/>phase. Cells were regularly tested for mycoplasma using the MycoAlert kit (Lonza). <lb/>Method Details <lb/>Transfection of Drosophila S2U Cells <lb/>Cells were split to ~60% confluency into 6 well tissue culture dishes 4 to 12 hr prior to <lb/>transfection. All transfection mixes were prepared in 5 ml low-retention polystyrene round-<lb/>bottom tubes. To prepare transfection mixes a maximum of 2.5 µg plasmid DNA was added to <lb/>300 µl serum-free Schneider&apos;s media and gently mixed. 5 µl of TransIT-Insect (Mirus) was <lb/>added to diluted DNA and gently mixed. At this point the solution appears cloudy. Transfection <lb/>mixes were incubated at room temperature for 15 min and added drop-wise gently to the 6 well <lb/>plate using a p1000 pipet. After drop-wise addition of transfection mixes, the plate was gently <lb/>shaken laterally to ensure even distribution of TransIT-DNA particles. Transfection efficiencies <lb/>of at least 50% and up to 90% were regularly obtained using this method, an improvement <lb/>compared to other transient transfection methods employed for Drosophila S2U cells. <lb/>All constructs used in this study express proteins of interest in S2U cells were under control of a <lb/>pMT copper-inducible promoter. To induce expression in transfected cells, CuSO 4 was added <lb/>from a 50 mM sterile stock in water to a final concentration of 250 µM (1 to 200 dilution from <lb/>stock) 36 to 48 hr after transfection. The timing of induction is important -at this later time point, <lb/>we find expression levels to be lower and more uniform. At shorter time points (e.g. 12 to 24 hr <lb/>after transfection), transfection efficiency was lower and expression levels in transfected cells <lb/>higher, as assessed by live cell imaging of fluorescent proteins under control of the pMT <lb/>promoter. <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Preparation of APC Annexin V Labeled Apoptotic Cell Corpses <lb/>To prepare labeled apoptotic cell corpses for use in internalization assays, 1 µM final <lb/>concentration of Actinomycin D (Sigma; 1 mg/ml in DMSO, 833 µM stock) was added directly to <lb/>80% confluent cultures of Drosophila S2U cells in 6 well plates. Cells were incubated for 16 hr in <lb/>Actinomycin D prior to harvesting by centrifugation for 5 min at 1000 x g a 15 ml falcon tube. <lb/>Actinomycin D was washed out by rinsing corpses twice in complete Schenider&apos;s media in the <lb/>same falcon tube -sequential washes, each with 10 ml complete media were performed. <lb/>Corpses from 1 well of a 6 well dish were resuspended in 300 µl of complete media after <lb/>washes and transferred to a 1.7 ml Eppendorf tube for labeling. To label externalized <lb/>phosphatidylserine (PS), APC Annexin V (BioLegend) was added directly to the washed <lb/>corpses to a final concentration of 50 ng/ul (from 5 µg/ml stock). The tube was wrapped in foil <lb/>prior to labeling on a rotator at room temperature for 30 min. After labeling, cells were washed 3 <lb/>times by sequential harvesting and resuspension in complete media. After washing labeled <lb/>corpses were resuspended in 300 µl complete media. <lb/>Assay for Internalization of Apoptotic Cell Corpses <lb/>To assess internalization of apoptotic cell corpses, washed Draper-GFP or mCherry-control <lb/>transfected S2U cells were incubated with labeled cell corpses prepared as above. Transfected <lb/>cells were washed with complete S2U media, and culture media was replaced with 1 ml of <lb/>fresh. Cells in fresh media were gently resuspended by pipetting up and down. 10 µl of the <lb/>washed labeled cell corpses prepared as above were mixed in an Eppendorf tube with 300 µl of <lb/>washed transfected cells. Eppendorf tube was flipped up and down 4 times and complete <lb/>mixture was plated in 1 well of a 96-well glass bottomed MatriPlate imaging dish (Brooks). After <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>45 min incubation at room temperature in the dark, High Content Screening imaging and <lb/>quantification were performed as described below. <lb/>Preparation of 10% PS-coated Silica Beads <lb/>10 molar % phosphatidylserine (PS) beads were used for all experiments other than the PS <lb/>titration in Figure 1G. To prepare 10 molar % beads, chloroform suspended lipids sufficient for 1 <lb/>ml of a 10 mM solution were mixed at the following proportions: 89.5% POPC, 10% DOPS, <lb/>0.5% PEG5000-PE, 0.5% atto390-DOPE (label for visualization by microscopy). Lipids were <lb/>transferred to a chloroform-washed glass vial using gas-tight Hamilton syringes and dried to a <lb/>film under argon gas in a warm (~45 o C) water bath. Dried lipids were stored under foil (if <lb/>labeled lipids were used) and desiccated overnight at room temperature in a benchtop <lb/>desiccator filled with Drierite. Dried lipids were suspended in 1 ml tissue culture grade PBS by <lb/>vortexing for 1 min under parafilm and gentle pipetting. Suspended lipids were transferred to a <lb/>1.7 ml Eppendorf tube and stored under argon gas. The PBS-lipid mix was freeze/thawed 5 <lb/>times in liquid nitrogen/warm water and subjected to 2 x 5 min sonication in a Bioruptor Pico <lb/>bath sonicator (Diagenode). Sonicated lipids were spin at 35000 rpm for 35 min at 4 o C in a TLA <lb/>120.1 rotor in a benchtop Beckman ultracentrifuge. Only a small pellet should be visible after <lb/>spinning sonicated lipids. Small Unilamellar Vesicles (SUVs) prepared using this method were <lb/>used immediately or stored under argon gas, flash frozen, and stored at -80 o C. Lipid mixes are <lb/>best used within two weeks of preparation. Undiluted 10 mM lipid mixes were used as described <lb/>below to build bilayers on silica beads. For the PS titration in Figure 1G differences in PS <lb/>concentration were made up by balanced changes to the molar % of PC such that final lipid <lb/>concentration in 1 ml PBS matched the 10 mM concentration described above. <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>50 µl 6.46 µm silica beads (Bangs, Catalog #SS06N) were added to 300 µl Milli-Q water in 1.7 <lb/>ml Eppendorf tubes for washing. Beads in suspension were pelleted 3 times in 300 µl Milli-Q <lb/>water at 300 rcf and decanted. After the third wash, beads were resuspended in ~30 µl PBS <lb/>until the pellet was barely covered. 300 µl of 2 mM final concentration of the desired lipid mix <lb/>(diluted from 10 mM stock in PBS) was vortexed briefly, wrapped in foil, and rotated at room <lb/>temperature for 45 min. Beads were pelleted and washed 3 times by sequential pelleting and <lb/>resuspension in 300 µl fresh PBS. Washed beads were resuspended in 300 µl fresh PBS for <lb/>bead assay, described below. <lb/>Assay for Internalization of PS-coated Silica Beads <lb/>To assess internalization of PS-coated silica beads, 7 µl of bead suspension was mixed with <lb/>300 µl washed transfected S2U cells, flipped gently to mix 4 times, and the complete mixture <lb/>plated in 1 well of a 96-well glass bottomed MatriPlate imaging dish (Brooks). Cells were <lb/>allowed to settle and imaged as described below. For endpoint assays, quantification was <lb/>performed on images taken 30 or 45 min after plating. For kinetic experiments, imaging was <lb/>started 5 min after plating. Engulfment experiments were performed using S2U cells co-<lb/>transfected with GFP or a GFP-fusion receptor protein, mCherry-CAAX (full-length mCherry-<lb/>LEKMSKDGKKKKKKSKTKCVIM) for visualizing plasma membranes during quantification <lb/>(described below), and 10% PS atto390-PE labeled silica beads. <lb/>Assay for Internalization of his10-FKBP Silica Beads <lb/>Engulfment experiments using his10-FKBP ligated beads were performed as above with the <lb/>exception that FRB-EXT-Draper-INT-GFP expressing S2 cells were co-transfected with <lb/>mCherry-CAAX to serve as a specific receptor for the FKBP ligand. Silica beads above were <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>prepared as above with the exception that instead of the 10% PS lipid mix, the following lipid <lb/>mix was used: 97% POPC, 2% DGS-NTA-Nickel, 0.5% PEG5000-PE, 0.5% atto390-DOPE. <lb/>Beads were blocked for 15 min in 300 µl PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA. His 10 -FKBP was diluted to 10 <lb/>nM final concentration in PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA and 300 µl of this dilution was added to each 50 <lb/>µl bead pellet, as described above. Proteins were coupled to beads for 40 min under foil on a <lb/>rotator at room temperature, washed 3 x 5 min in PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA and resuspended in <lb/>PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA prior to the engulfment assay. 300 µl washed transfected cells were <lb/>mixed with 7 µl His 10 -FKBP ligated beads either in the presence of 1 µM rapamycin or a <lb/>matching volume of DMSO (vehicle), flipped 4 times to mix, and ingestion was quantified as <lb/>described below. <lb/>Staining for Phosphotyrosine (pTyr) and the Synapse between S2 Cell and Bead <lb/>To fix and stain bead-cell synapses in chambers described above for phosphotyrosine (pTyr) <lb/>localization, half the media (~150 µl) from imaging chambers was gently removed and replaced <lb/>with 150 µl 6.4% paraformaldehyde. Cells were fixed under foil for 15 min, washed 2 x 3 min in <lb/>PBS, permeabilized with 0.5% v/v Triton X-100 in PBS for 10 min, and set overnight to block in <lb/>PBS + 0.1% v/v TritonX-100 + 0.2% w/v BSA at 4 o C wrapped in parafilm in the dark. Cells were <lb/>stained in primary antibody (pY-20 mouse anti-phosphotyrosine (Santa Cruz), 2 µg/ml final <lb/>concentration, 1:100 dilution) for 1 hr at room temperature in the dark, washed 3 x 5 min room <lb/>temperature in PBS + 0.1% v/v Triton X-100 + 0.2% w/v BSA, and incubated in secondary <lb/>antibody (Thermo, anti-mouse IgG H+L Alexa Fluor 647 conjugated) for 1 hr at room <lb/>temperature, washed 3 x 5 minutes in PBS + 0.1% v/v Triton X-100 + 0.2% w/v BSA. Washed <lb/>fixed stained cells were gently covered in 200 µl PBS prior to imaging. Cells were imaged <lb/>immediately or stored for up to 2 days at 4 o C in the dark, wrapped in parafilm before imaging <lb/>my spinning disk confocal microscopy (see below). <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Building PS-containing Supported Lipid Bilayers (SLBs) <lb/>The night before the experiment, a 96 well MatriCal imaging plate was submerged in 2% v/v <lb/>Hellmanex III, microwaved for 2.5 min on full power, and set on a stir plate under saran wrap for <lb/>at least 12 hr. Hellmanex was washed away through 20 sequential washes using Milli-Q water <lb/>and the washed plate dried under Nitrogen gas. The dried plate was covered in thermal paper <lb/>using a roller. The desired number of wells were exposed using a razor and washed 3 x 5 min <lb/>5N NaOH. After NaOH washes, wells were cleaned 10 times with MilliQ water. <lb/>To prepare 10% PS bilayers, 250 µl 2 mM lipid mix in PBS described above gently pipetted on <lb/>the glass surface. The lipid mix was pipetted up and down and bilayer formation was allowed to <lb/>proceed for 30 min at room temperature. After bilayers formed, washes were performed using <lb/>PBS 3 x 5 min. For each wash, PBS was gently pipetted up and down over the surface of the <lb/>bilayer to remove SUVs not part of the SLB. Bilayers were washed into serum free Schneider&apos;s <lb/>media prior to adding cells. Imaging on bilayers should be complete within 45 min for best <lb/>results, as bilayer integrity cannot be assumed after this time. <lb/>After washing the SLB, 150 µl of washed cells were added to the surface, allowed to settle, and <lb/>imaged by Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence-Microscopy as described below. A lower <lb/>density of cells can be used, as cells will spread on bilayers and imaging overlapping cells is not <lb/>ideal. <lb/>Building His 10 -FKBP Bearing Supported Lipid Bilayers (SLBs) <lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Bilayers were prepared as above with the exception that the following lipid mix was used (note <lb/>the use of DGS-NTA-Nickel lipid to ligate His 10 proteins to the bilayer): 97% POPC, 2% DGS-<lb/>NTA-Nickel, 0.5% PEG5000-PE, 0.5% atto390-DOPE or 0.5% atto647-DOPE for labeling, <lb/>depending on the fluorescent proteins present on fusion proteins assessed. Washed bilayers <lb/>were blocked in PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA for 15 min prior to protein coupling. To couple His 10 -FKBP <lb/>to 2% DGS-NTA-doped bilayers, His 10 -FKBP was diluted to 10 nM final concentration in PBS + <lb/>0.1% w/v BSA and added to SLBs to couple for 40 min at room temperature. Uncoupled protein <lb/>was washed 3 x 5 min under foil at room temperature prior to adding cells as above with the <lb/>exception that when FKBP ligand was used with receptors fused to FRB-extracellular domains, <lb/>1 µM rapamycin was added to form the 100 fM FRB-rapamycin-FKBP ternary complex. <lb/>Liposome FRET Assay for Effector Recruitment to Phosphorylated Receptor Tails <lb/>This assay was based upon one used to reconstitute mammalian T cell signaling (Hui and Vale, <lb/>2014). To present receptor tails in physiological geometry for phosphorylation by Src-family <lb/>kinases, 1 µM His 10 receptor tails (either His 10 -Draper-INT or His 10 -Draper-ΔITAM-INT) were <lb/>ligated to liposomes comprised of the following molar percent: 74.5% POPC, 10% DGS-NTA, <lb/>0.5% Rhodamine-PE, 15% DOPS. Liposomes were prepared using an extruder with 200 nm <lb/>filters (Avanti). Receptor tails and 1 nM His 10 -Lck-Y505F or 86 nM Src42a (soluble) were <lb/>equilibrated with receptor tails in the presence of BG505-kinase-tSH2 reporter proteins were <lb/>incubated. After proteins were allowed to bind for 40 min at room temperature in the dark. At <lb/>this point, Mg-ATP was added to a 1 mM final concentration and BG505 signal was assessed at <lb/>indicated time points. Quenching of BG505 signal, dependent upon addition of ATP, indicates <lb/>recruitment of reporters to phosphorylated receptor tails. Quenching of the BG505 dye was <lb/>assessed using a Synergy H4 plate reader (BioTek). <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Determining Sites of Tyrosine Phosphorylation by 1D Mass Spectrometry <lb/>To determine sites of Tyr phosphorylation on Draper (Figure 6), 1 µM His 10 -Draper-INT was <lb/>ligated to unlabeled liposomes: 74.5% POPC, 10% DGS-NTA, 15% DOPS and phosphorylated <lb/>by 1 nM His 10 -Lck-Y505F after 40 min of protein coupling to liposomes. 100 µl Reactions were <lb/>quenched with 100 µl of 8 M Urea and 20 mM EDTA at the indicated time points (final <lb/>concentrations of 4 M urea and 10 mM EDTA) and shock frozen in liquid nitrogen until all <lb/>reactions were trypsinized in parallel for analysis by mass spectrometry. To perform <lb/>trypsinization, reactions were thawed by boiling, supplemented with 5 mM final concentration of <lb/>TCEP, and incubated for 20 min at room temperature. After denaturation samples 10 mM final <lb/>concentration of iodoacetamide (IAA) as added. Samples were then incubated in the dark for 15 <lb/>min. Urea concentration was reduced two-fold through addition of 200 µl PBS. 1 mM final <lb/>concentration of CaCl 2 and 1 µg/ml Trypsin Gold (Promega) was added before samples were <lb/>incubated overnight in the dark at 37 o C. Trypsinzation was quenched through addition of 100 µl <lb/>0.1% v/v mass spec grade formic acid. Samples were then subjected to 1D mass spectrometry <lb/>and peptides containing the characteristic shift for phosphorylation (+79.9663 Da) and <lb/>quantified as described below. <lb/>Immunoblot Analysis <lb/>To determine degree of tyrosine phosphorylation on His 10 -Draper intracellular domains, on <lb/>liposome phosphorylation assays were performed as above and quenched using SDS-PAGE <lb/>buffer + DTT and incubated for 5 min at 95 o C. Reactions were run on 4-20% gradient SDS-<lb/>PAGE gels and transferred onto nitrocellulose membranes using the iBlot system (Invitrogen). <lb/>Membranes were blocked for 1 hr at room temperature in PBS + 0.1% w/v bovine serum <lb/>albumin (BSA, Sigma) and incubated overnight at 4 o C with anti-His probe (rabbit) and anti-<lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>phosphotyrosine (mouse) antibodies (Key Resources Table). Primary antibodies were incubated <lb/>with membranes simultaneously. Both were used at 1:1000 final dilution PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA. <lb/>Membranes were washed 3 x 5 minutes at room temperature in PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA and <lb/>incubated with Licor secondary antibodies at 1:10,000 dilution (700 nm anti-rabbit, 800 nm anti-<lb/>mouse, Key Resources Table) for 1 hr at room temperature. Membranes were washed 3 x 5 <lb/>minutes at room temperature in PBS + 0.1% w/v BSA and imaged using a Licor Odyssey gel <lb/>imager. Quantification of anti-phosphotyrosine and anti-his intensity was performed using the <lb/>Gel Analysis feature of Fiji. <lb/>Protein Expression, Purification, and Labeling <lb/>His 10 -Draper and His 10 -Draper-ΔITAM were transformed into BL-21 DE3 RIPL cells (Agilent). <lb/>Cells were grown in Terrific Broth (TB), 12 g tryptone, 24 g yeast extract, 4 ml glycerol up to 1L <lb/>in MilliQ water + 10% v/v sterile salt solution in MilliQ water: 0.17M KH 2 PO 4 , 0.72 M K 2 HPO 4 , <lb/>until cells reached an OD 280 of ~0.6-0.8, chilled in a 4 o C room, and induced overnight by <lb/>addition of 0.5 mM final concentration of IPTG. Protein expression was performed in shaker set <lb/>to 18 o C. Bacterial pellets were resuspended in lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 300 mM <lb/>NaCl, 1 tablet Complete EDTA-free protease inhibitor tablet crushed per 100 ml buffer). Lysates <lb/>were prepared by probe sonication and bound to Ni-NTA agarose (Qiagen). Beads were <lb/>washed extensively with lysis buffer and proteins eluted in 500 mM imidazole in lysis buffer. <lb/>Imidazole elutions were subjected to gel filtration chromatography using a Superdex 200 10/30 <lb/>column (GE Healthcare) in gel filtration buffer: 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% <lb/>glycerol, and 1 mM TCEP. Monomer fractions were pooled, shock frozen in liquid nitrogen, and <lb/>stored in small aliquots at -80 o C. Soluble Src42a was purified from SF9 cells as a GST-(PP)-<lb/>SNAP-Src42a fusion where PP indicates a cut site for Precission Protease. Precission Protease <lb/>cleavage was performed overnight and post-cleavage supernatants were gel filtered as <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>described below. His 10 -Lck Y505F was purified from SF9 cells over Nickel agarose (Qiagen) <lb/>and eluted in 500 mM imidazole in lysis buffer. Both Src family kinases were subjected to gel <lb/>filtration chromatography using a Superdex 200 10/30 column (GE Healthcare) in gel filtration <lb/>buffer: 50 mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, and 1 mM TCEP. Monomer <lb/>fractions were pooled, shock frozen in liquid nitrogen, and stored in small aliquots at -80 o C. The <lb/>tandem SH2 domain reporter for Shark kinase was cloned as a GST-(PP)-SNAP-Shark-tSH2 <lb/>fusion where PP indicates a cut site for Precission Protease. The soluble SNAP-Shark-tSH2 <lb/>reporter was generated by on-resin cleavage with Precission Protease during purification. GST-<lb/>Precission Protease remained on the beads. Cleavage products were subjected to gel filtration <lb/>chromatography using a Superdex 200 10/30 column (GE Healthcare) in gel filtration buffer: 50 <lb/>mM HEPES, pH 7.5, 150 mM NaCl, 10% glycerol, and 1 mM TCEP. To prepare BG505-labeled <lb/>SNAP-Shark-tSH2 for the liposome FRET assay, 10 µM cleaved, gel filtered monomer was <lb/>incubated at a 1:2 molar ratio with SNAP-Cell 505 Star (NEB) overnight in the dark at 4 o C and <lb/>run over a PD Minitrap G-25 column (GE Healthcare) to eliminate excess dye. <lb/>Spinning Disk Confocal Microscopy <lb/>All internalization and bead co-localization imaging performed for this study was done of a <lb/>spinning disk confocal microscope (Nikon Ti-Eclipse inverted microscope with a Yokogawa <lb/>spinning disk). For bead internalization kinetic assays images were acquired using a 40x/0.95 <lb/>N/A air objective. Live image acquisition for internalization of corpses and beads was performed <lb/>using the High Content Screening (HCS) Site Generator plugin in µManager. All other images <lb/>were acquired using a 100x 1.49 N/A oil immersion objective. Images were captured using an <lb/>Andor iXon EM-CCD camera. The open source µManager software package was used to run <lb/>the microscope and capture the images. <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>Total Internal Reflection Fluorescence-Microscopy (TIRF-M) <lb/>All SLB imaging was performed using a TIRF microscope equipped with a motorized TIRF arm <lb/>and a Hamamatsu Flash 4 camera. For all TIRF-M imaging images were captured at 2 x 2 <lb/>binning. The open source µManager software package was used to run the microscope and <lb/>capture the images (Edelstein et al., 2010). <lb/>Imaging processing and analysis <lb/>All image quantification was done on raw, unprocessed images. All images in figures were <lb/>opened in ImageJ. A middle z-slice was extracted and the channels split. The image intensities <lb/>were scaled to enhance contrast in Photoshop (Adobe) using appropriate levels of linear <lb/>adjustment. Background correction was not performed. Where mutants are compared in the <lb/>same series, images are acquired using identical microscope and camera settings and scaled to <lb/>equal intensity values. <lb/>Quantification and Statistical Analysis <lb/>For both corpse internalization and bead internalization assays, targets were scored as <lb/>internalized following complete engulfment of the object, as assessed by visible mCherry-CAAX <lb/>or receptor-GFP signal visible completely around the target in stills from live imaging. Beads or <lb/>corpses attached but not internalized were not scored. Only targets with labeled Annexin V or <lb/>atto390 visible were scored as internalized. At least 150 cells per condition are shown. Mean <lb/>value and ± one standard deviation are plotted (GraphPad 6.0). <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability <lb/></div>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<div type="availability">Requests for raw data in support of the conclusions of this study should be directed to and will <lb/>be fulfilled by the corresponding author, Ronald D. Vale (ron.vale@ucsf.edu). <lb/></div>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<body>KEY RESOURCES TABLE <lb/>REAGENT or RESOURCE <lb/>SOURCE <lb/>IDENTIFIER <lb/>Antibodies <lb/>Anti-phosphotyrosine (pTyr) mouse; PY20 <lb/>Santa Cruz <lb/>Biotechnology <lb/>PY20 <lb/>Anti-mouse IgG (H+L) conjugated to Alexa Fluor 647 <lb/>Thermo/Lifetech <lb/>A-21236 <lb/>His-probe Antibody rabbit (G-18) <lb/>Santa Cruz <lb/>Biotechnology <lb/>G-18 <lb/>Anti-rabbit IgG (H+L) conjugated to Alexa Fluor 680 <lb/>(used with 700 nm Licor channel) <lb/>Thermo/Lifetech <lb/>A-21109 <lb/>IRDye 800CW Goat anti-Mouse IgG (H+L) antibody <lb/>(used with 800 nm Licor channel) <lb/>Licor <lb/>925-32210 <lb/>Bacterial and Virus Strains <lb/>Plasmid propagation: Top10 E. coli <lb/>Invitrogen <lb/>C404010 <lb/>Protein expression: BL-21 DE3 RIPL <lb/>Agilent <lb/>230280 <lb/>Biological Samples <lb/>n/a <lb/>Chemicals, Peptides, and Recombinant Proteins <lb/>DMSO, tissue culture grade (for cell freezing) <lb/>Sigma <lb/>D2650 <lb/>Copper (II) sulfate pentahydrate <lb/>Sigma <lb/>7758-99-9 <lb/>Actinomycin D <lb/>Sigma <lb/>50-76-0 <lb/>15 ml falcon tubes -Cellstar <lb/>Greiner <lb/>188 271 <lb/>1.7 ml Eppendorf Tubes <lb/>Olympus <lb/>24-282 <lb/>POPC lipid in chloroform <lb/>Avanti <lb/>850457C <lb/>Ni2+-DGS-NTA lipid in chloroform <lb/>Avanti <lb/>790404C <lb/>PEG5000-PE lipid in chloroform <lb/>Avanti <lb/>880230C <lb/>DOPS lipid in chloroform <lb/>Avanti <lb/>840035C <lb/>Atto390-DOPE <lb/>ATTO-TEC GmbH <lb/>AD 390-161 <lb/>Atto647-DOPE <lb/>ATTO-TECH GmbH <lb/>AD 647-161 <lb/>Rhodamine-PE <lb/>Avanti <lb/>810150C <lb/>Paraformaldehyde <lb/>Electron Microscopy <lb/>Sciences <lb/>15712 <lb/>Triton X-100 <lb/>Sigma <lb/>T8787 <lb/>Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA) <lb/>Sigma <lb/>A4737 <lb/>Hellmanex III <lb/>Sigma <lb/>Z805939 <lb/>5N Sodium Hydroxide <lb/>Fisher <lb/>SS256-500 <lb/>Rapamycin <lb/>Sigma <lb/>R0395 <lb/>Formic Acid (0.1% v/v), mass spec grade <lb/>Fisher <lb/>LS118-1 <lb/>Trypsin gold, Mass spectrometry grade <lb/>Promega <lb/>V5280 <lb/>Iodoacetamide (IAA) <lb/>Sigma <lb/>I6125 <lb/>Bovine Serum Albumin (BSA) <lb/>Sigma <lb/>A7906 <lb/>Precission Protease <lb/>GE Healthcare <lb/>27-0843-01 <lb/></body>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>SNAP-Cell 505-Star <lb/>NEB <lb/>S9103S <lb/>Critical Commercial Assays <lb/>MycoAlert Mycoplasma Detection Kit <lb/>Lonza <lb/>LT07-318 <lb/>MycoAlert Mycoplasma Control Set <lb/>Lonza <lb/>LT07-518 <lb/>TransIT-Insect <lb/>Mirus <lb/>MIR 6100 <lb/>APC Annexin V <lb/>BioLegend <lb/>640941 <lb/>Deposited Data <lb/>n/a <lb/>Experimental Models: Cell Lines <lb/>Drosophila S2U Cells <lb/>Ron Vale Lab <lb/>Flybase ID: <lb/>FBtc9000006 <lb/>Experimental Models: Organisms/Strains <lb/>n/a <lb/>Oligonucleotides <lb/>See Supplemental File_Constructs and Oligos, &quot;oligos&quot; <lb/>tab <lb/>Recombinant DNA <lb/>See Supplemental File_Constructs and Oligos, <lb/>&quot;constructs&quot; tab <lb/>Software and Algorithms <lb/>GraphPad Prism <lb/>GraphPad Software <lb/>6.0 <lb/>Adobe Photoshop <lb/>Adobe <lb/>CS6 <lb/>µManager <lb/>µManager/Open <lb/>Imaging <lb/>1.4 (updated) <lb/>Fiji (is just ImageJ) <lb/>Fiji.sc <lb/>2.0 (updated) <lb/>Other <lb/>Schenider&apos;s Cell Culture Media <lb/>Gibco <lb/>21720 <lb/>Fetal Bovie Serum, Heat inactivated <lb/>Atlanta <lb/>S11150H <lb/>Antibiotic-antimycotic <lb/>Gibco <lb/>15240062 <lb/>T75 non-vented tissue culture flask <lb/>Corning <lb/>430720 <lb/>T25 non-vented tissue culture flask <lb/>Corning <lb/>430168 <lb/>Externally threaded cryovials for freezing cells, 2 ml <lb/>Corning <lb/>430659 <lb/>Costar TC-treated 6 well plates <lb/>Corning <lb/>CLS3516 <lb/>Polystyrene round-bottom tubes (5 ml) for transfection <lb/>Falcon <lb/>352058 <lb/>MatriCal Imaging Plates <lb/>Brooks <lb/>MGB096-1-2-LG-L <lb/>Disposable Glass Culture Tubes (lipid mixes) <lb/>Fisher <lb/>14-961-26 <lb/>Hamilton Syringes (Gas Tight) <lb/>Fisher <lb/>8 1100 <lb/>Tissue Culture Grade PBS <lb/>GIbco <lb/>20012050 <lb/></body>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>Drierite <lb/>Fisher <lb/>AC219095000 <lb/>Bath Sonicator to make SUVs <lb/>Diagenode <lb/>Pico <lb/>Extruder for Liposome Preparation <lb/>Avanti <lb/>610023 <lb/>Silica beads for engulfment assay <lb/>Bangs Labs <lb/>SS06N <lb/>Ni-NTA agarose (regenerated) <lb/>Qiagen <lb/>30210 <lb/>Glutathione Sepharose (regenerated) <lb/>GE Healthcare <lb/>17527901 <lb/>Superdex 200 10/30 GL column <lb/>GE Healthcare <lb/>17517501 <lb/>PD Minitrap G-25 column (remove excess BG505 dye) <lb/>GE Healthcare <lb/>28-9180-07 <lb/></body>

			<body>Figure 1: Cellular reconsitution of Draper signaling <lb/>A <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Beads ingested per cell <lb/>PC 10% PS PC 10% PS <lb/>Draper <lb/>GFP <lb/>C <lb/>PS <lb/>Draper <lb/>silica bead <lb/>S2 cell <lb/>B <lb/>Beads ingested per cell <lb/>0 . 0 <lb/>0 . 4 <lb/>2 . 5 <lb/>5 . 0 <lb/>7 . 5 <lb/>1 0 . 0 <lb/>1 2 . 5 <lb/>1 5 . 0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Draper <lb/>mol.% PS on beads <lb/>Draper <lb/>S2 cell <lb/>cell corpse <lb/>ligands <lb/>mCherry <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>Corpse internalized (%) <lb/>Draper <lb/>D <lb/>0 min <lb/>3 min <lb/>6 min <lb/>Lifeact <lb/>Draper <lb/>PS bead <lb/>Lifeact <lb/>Draper <lb/>Corpse <lb/>Lifeact <lb/>Draper <lb/>PS bead <lb/>Lifeact <lb/>Figure 2: Draper organizes into mobile microclusters that recruit signaling molecules <lb/>A <lb/>0:00 0:00 <lb/>2:00 <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>Draper <lb/>pTyr <lb/>Draper <lb/>Shark <lb/>PS bead <lb/>B <lb/>merge <lb/>merge <lb/>Shark <lb/>Crk <lb/>Draper <lb/>merge <lb/>E <lb/>1:00 <lb/>cover glass <lb/>supported lipid <lb/>bilayer <lb/>settling cell <lb/>Figure 3: Segregation of Draper and a transmembrane phosphatase at the synapse <lb/>FKBP <lb/>bead <lb/>FKBP <lb/>rapamycin <lb/>FRB EXT <lb/>A. <lb/>plasma <lb/>membrane <lb/>B <lb/>FRB EXT -Draper INT <lb/>Ptp69D <lb/>FRB EXT -Draper INT <lb/>Shark <lb/>FKBP bead <lb/>Shark <lb/>merge <lb/>merge <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>merge <lb/>Draper <lb/>Ptp69D <lb/>PS bead <lb/>Draper INT <lb/>C <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>Rapamycin <lb/>Beads ingested per cell <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>Figure 4: Roles of Draper&apos;s cytoplasmic tyrosine residues in engulfment of PS beads <lb/>D r a p e r <lb/>-A la 1 1 <lb/>G F P <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>Beads ingested per cell <lb/>VYDEIKHKEGYKDPDEYDHLDYS <lb/>933 <lb/>Draper <lb/>ITAM <lb/>D r a p e r <lb/>B <lb/>955 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Minutes after PS beads <lb/>Mean beads internalized <lb/>WT <lb/>ITAM only <lb/>∆ITAM <lb/>Ala11 <lb/>GFP <lb/>Figure 5: In vitro reconstitution of hierarchical multisite Tyr phosphorylation on Draper <lb/>BG505-Shark-tSH2 <lb/>LUV <lb/>membrane <lb/>His 10 -Draper-INT <lb/>Src42a <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>quenching <lb/>Licor IR <lb/>his <lb/>pTyr <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>∆ I T A M <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>85 <lb/>90 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>105 <lb/>110 <lb/>time (minutes) <lb/>% donor fluorescence <lb/>WT <lb/>∆ITAM <lb/>ATP <lb/>BG505-Shark-tSH2 <lb/>838 858 <lb/>888 <lb/>901 905 924 934 943 949 954 965 <lb/>ITAM <lb/>Ø <lb/>Phosphorylated Peptides <lb/>(% of peptides covering site) <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>25 <lb/>C <lb/>Figure 6: Mechanism of Draper triggering <lb/>Cell Corpse <lb/>1. phosphatase <lb/>segregation <lb/>2. receptor <lb/>phosphorylation <lb/>Phosphatase <lb/>4. outputs <lb/>Shark <lb/>3. effector <lb/>recruitment <lb/>Src42a <lb/>Draper <lb/>Src42a <lb/>Phagocyte <lb/>Actin remodeling <lb/>&amp; engulfment <lb/>drpr, mmp1 <lb/>Figure S1 (related to Figure 2): p85 and Crk are recruited to the synapse with <lb/>a 10% PS bead <lb/>Draper <lb/>SH2 domain protein <lb/>PS bead <lb/>Draper <lb/>SH2 domain protein <lb/>Shark <lb/>p85 <lb/>Crk <lb/>Stat92E <lb/>Figure S2 (related to Figure 3): The transmembrane phosphatase Ptp69D <lb/>Phosphatase <lb/>RPKM <lb/>Ptp4E <lb/>25.87 <lb/>Ptp69D <lb/>21.82 <lb/>l(1)G0232 <lb/>16.56 <lb/>Ptp10D <lb/>11.23 <lb/>CG12746 <lb/>10.54 <lb/>Lar <lb/>10.10 <lb/>Ptp99A <lb/>7.89 <lb/>plasma <lb/>membrane <lb/>Ptp69D <lb/>Ig domain <lb/>Fibronectin repeats <lb/>Draper <lb/>Ptp69D <lb/>merge <lb/>Phosphatase <lb/>GFP <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Figure S3 (related to Figure 4): Draper&apos;s ITAM is necessary and sufficient to recruit Shark <lb/>in cells <lb/>Receptor <lb/>Shark <lb/>PS bead <lb/>ITAM Only <lb/>Shark <lb/>WT <lb/>∆ITAM <lb/>Receptor <lb/>Figure S4 (related to Figure 5): Identification of phosphorylation sites on Draper by Lck <lb/>838 858 <lb/>888 <lb/>901 905 924 934 943 949 954 965 <lb/>Ø <lb/>Phosphorylated Peptides <lb/>(% of peptides covering site) <lb/>100 <lb/>Ø <lb/>Ø <lb/>Ø <lb/>Ø <lb/>Ø <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>25 <lb/>ITAM <lb/>Licor IR <lb/>his <lb/>pTyr <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>∆ I T A M <lb/>A <lb/>B </body>


	</text>
</tei>
