<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_2006-149_hal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> New Trends for Pyrotechnic Automotive Safety in the European Union <lb/> Lionel Aufauvre <lb/>INERIS Certification Division <lb/>Parc Technologique Alata 񮽙 BP 2 <lb/>F-60550 Verneuil-en-Halate, France <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/> In the European Union (EU) pyrotechnic articles are subjected to comply with national regulations in <lb/>addition to a series of EU Directives. In order to harmonize regulations in the EU, the placing on the <lb/>market of pyrotechnic articles is going to fall under the scope of a new European Directive. Among these <lb/>articles, one finds pyrotechnic components of automotive safety equipment such as gas generators or <lb/>igniters. In the very fast growing market of automotive safety industry, regulations might be perceived as <lb/>non-technical barriers to innovation in the field. Conversely, through innovation arguments, industries <lb/>sometimes try to promote specific cases of exemptions to comply various regulations. <lb/>In a broad approach, we examine both regulation and industrial recent repercussions in the field of <lb/>pyrotechnic devices for automotive safety, as these points of view face each other too often. <lb/>Considerations regarding design, transport classification, approvals, safety features, environmental issues <lb/>and treatment of end-life waste disposal are provided along the life cycle of the products. We enlighten <lb/>needs in term of harmonized standards and technical procedures to answer regulation requirements. Such <lb/>needs bring new perspectives and make room to various stakeholders for possible and efficient <lb/>developments. <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> More than three decades ago pyrotechnic <lb/>articles appeared in automotive industry. <lb/>Pyrotechnics entered first in our car by the <lb/>steering wheel as energetic component of driver <lb/>inflatable restraint system commonly known as <lb/>airbag. This move started in the United States <lb/>and then reached Europe, mainly through <lb/>Germany and Sweden where it was proposed as <lb/>optional equipment for luxury cars at first. But <lb/>rapidly, airbag flourished in all car <lb/>manufacturers and was implemented on regular <lb/>cars as a standard marketing argument for selling <lb/>new car models. In the mean time, the number of <lb/>such pyrotechnical equipment multiplied in each <lb/>vehicle as they showed their efficiency to save <lb/>lives. After the airbag for the driver came <lb/>additional passenger, side, and curtain airbags <lb/>and other automotive pyrotechnic systems such <lb/>as seat-belt pretensioners (see Figure 1). The <lb/>tendency turns far away from the time when <lb/>some people thought unsafe to carry explosive <lb/>loads on board of a car in motion. Surprisingly, <lb/>nowadays customers don&apos;t pay any attention to <lb/>driving their car with hundreds of grams of <lb/>energetic materials distributed around the <lb/>passenger compartment. <lb/> Figure 1: locations of pyrotechnics in a car <lb/>(steering wheel, dashboard, doors, <lb/>seat-<lb/> However, in parallel to those <lb/>developments to safer environment for car <lb/>passengers, it was known that those articles were <lb/>potentially dangerous by nature [1]. Several <lb/> risks, mainly due to the presence of energetic <lb/>materials based hazardous components have to <lb/>be considered: these risks entail unexpected <lb/>basic explosions and toxic emanations during <lb/>normal operation of such systems. Moreover, <lb/>dangers are present on the whole value chain of <lb/>automotive pyrotechnics devices, comprising <lb/>equipment manufacturing, transportation to car <lb/>makers, operations during the car assembly and <lb/>eventually all along equipment life and even <lb/>during end life disposal. Safety and security <lb/>aspects were then with good reason carefully <lb/>regulated in different countries. <lb/> Situation in the EU <lb/> In Europe for the moment these <lb/>pyrotechnic articles (and many others) fall under <lb/>different national regulations and approval <lb/>procedures (e.g.: Decree n°90-153 in France [2], <lb/> are similarities between the tests procedures <lb/>applied in each country, manufacturers of such <lb/>systems have to pass different approvals to trade <lb/>their articles in different countries. The test <lb/>procedures usually consist to submit the items to <lb/>different stresses (vibrations, drop, impact, <lb/> pply these <lb/>solicitations is somewhat different from one <lb/>country to another, the tests are pertinent enough <lb/>to detect lack of consistency. <lb/>Soon the situation is going to be <lb/>harmonized to achieve the free movement of <lb/>pyrotechnic articles in the internal market of the <lb/>EU and at the same time ensuring a high degree <lb/>of protection of human health and safety of <lb/>consumers. Similarly to what have been done for <lb/>explosives for civil uses (Directive 93/15/EEC of <lb/>5 April 1993) a new Directive [3] is about to <lb/>cover the placing on the market of pyrotechnic <lb/>articles. <lb/> Cases study <lb/> Here we discuss cases encountered when <lb/>testing airbag inflators or other pyrotechnic <lb/>articles for automotive safety in the frame of the <lb/>French approval procedure. We believe that <lb/> other countries have similar experiences and that <lb/>detailed results have to remain in confidence. <lb/>We intend to show the need of regulations and <lb/>test procedures and how they conduct the <lb/>manufacturer of equipment for motor vehicles to <lb/>make safer devices. That has to be achieved not <lb/>only for &quot;final users&quot; (i.e. car drivers) but more <lb/>importantly for workers that handle these <lb/>pyrotechnical items at a low level of integration <lb/>in inert protective shielding systems. <lb/>When exposing airbag gas generator to <lb/>an external fire some &quot;non-mature&quot; models have <lb/>shown tendency to break and generate <lb/>projections at significant distance. That was a <lb/>clear remainder for those who have forgotten <lb/>what can happen if an energetic material is <lb/>placed inside a metallic case under certain <lb/>conditions. The manufacturers answered those <lb/>pitfalls by making thicker body case and by <lb/>crimping and swaging assembly allowing <lb/>improvement of the mechanical/thermal <lb/>resistance and relating stress compatibility. <lb/>Missile behaviors were also observed as <lb/>gas ejected through holes may create a <lb/>significant thrust. In this case it is the whole <lb/>inflator which is propelled, basically like a <lb/>rocket, as usually same components produce <lb/>same effects. Exhausts designed with radial <lb/>distribution to insure a &quot;neutral thrust&quot; when <lb/>gases are generated were rapidly adopted as an <lb/>ideal solution. <lb/>When operating, airbag inflators and <lb/>more generally pyrotechnic devices function <lb/>primarily as gas generators, through some kind <lb/>of combustion process. The combustion gases <lb/>emitted are then converted in several mechanical <lb/>actions or used directly. Toxicity of the resulting <lb/>emanations is an issue in passenger <lb/>compartment, especially due to confinement of a <lb/>passenger car environment. Early gas generating <lb/>compositions consisted in mixtures of potassium <lb/>nitrate, sodium azide and silica, which mainly <lb/>produce nitrogen gas in a chemical reaction (see <lb/>Figure 2). <lb/> 2 NaN 3 ------&gt; 2 Na + 3 N 2 (g) <lb/>K 2 O + Na 2 O + SiO 2 ------&gt; alkaline silicate <lb/>10 Na + 2 KNO 3 ------&gt; K 2 O + 5 Na 2 O + N 2 (g) <lb/> Figure 2: Decomposition of sodium azide <lb/> The toxicity of side products generated by <lb/>decomposition of sodium azide in the reaction <lb/>process as well as the intrinsic toxicity of sodium <lb/>azide itself made the technology shift to what is <lb/>known as &quot;hybrid gas generator&quot;. In such a <lb/> system, an inert gas is stored under high-pressure <lb/>in a tank and the pyrotechnic component reduced <lb/>often to a simple initiator is used to break a <lb/>rupture disk that releases the gas. But the weight <lb/>of these inflators due to high-pressure vessel <lb/>made of stainless steel can present as a <lb/>significant drawback when large amount of gas <lb/>is required. Hence, the late trend is to return to <lb/>the use of propellant at least less toxic as early <lb/>formulations and with formulations developed to <lb/>reduce combustion related toxicity as well. <lb/>Regarding transportation of these pyrotechnic <lb/>equipment the automotive industry requests to <lb/>keep constraints at a minimum, in order to cope <lb/> in the automotive industry. But, by nature of <lb/>some of their components, these devices have to <lb/>be viewed as dangerous goods regarding <lb/>transport regulations. Early consideration of <lb/>these products concluded to consider them as <lb/>explosive objects falling in the Class 1 <lb/>(Explosives) of the United Nations (UN) <lb/> Figure 3: UN transport classification <lb/>for dangerous goods <lb/> classification for dangerous goods (see Figure <lb/>3). Compromises were found later, under <lb/>particular conditions, for a classification in Class <lb/>9 (Miscellaneous dangerous substances and <lb/>articles), under UN number 3268 designated as <lb/>&quot;air bag inflators, or air bag modules, or seat-belt <lb/>pretensioners&quot;. The development of containers <lb/>with metallic perforated sheets or meshes <lb/>providing containment of potential projection <lb/>without confinement of gases released played an <lb/>important role for the acceptation of this <lb/>classification. These containers are essential to <lb/>allow storage in car manufacturing assembly <lb/>lines and are also designed to be used as <lb/>handling devices to avoid unnecessary <lb/>manipulations in workshop. <lb/> Testing procedures <lb/> As the automotive equipment technology <lb/>is moving fast, pyrotechnic items used for safety <lb/>also evolve quickly and appear now in various <lb/>systems (e.g.: protection to pedestrians or <lb/>equipment for motorcycle riders). Moreover, <lb/>similar items find applications in other field that <lb/>may not have the same capacity to develop the <lb/>technology. We can mention as example the <lb/>&quot;avalanche airbag system&quot; for off-track skier <lb/>protection, which avoid trapping them under <lb/>snow. The real need for harmonized test <lb/>procedures in Europe should soon be covered by <lb/>the implementation of a new Directive [3], <lb/>which should indeed cover these articles as well <lb/>as other pyrotechnics. Similarly, there is a <lb/>parallel need for test procedures to be able to <lb/>correctly evaluate new devices. <lb/>More and more, considerations to satisfy <lb/>all test criteria for exclusion of automotive <lb/>components containing energetic materials from <lb/>the UN Class 1 are taken into account as soon as <lb/>the conception phase of the item. Whenever it is <lb/>possible, this is achieved by containment of all <lb/>effects inside the object or at least by strong <lb/>limitation of external effects such as exhaust of <lb/> Recycling <lb/> Fortunately for the occupants, the <lb/>majority of pyrotechnic automotive safety <lb/>systems never operate during the lifetime of the <lb/>vehicle. Then there is another issue. Process to <lb/>recycle cars consists to compacting and <lb/>shredding usually, which can create troubles <lb/>when applied to energetic materials containing <lb/>components. In addition to the hazards of <lb/>explosion that can damage recycling equipment, <lb/>the dissemination of toxic propellant like sodium <lb/>azide endangers workers and environment. There <lb/>are currently no cost-efficient solutions as re-use <lb/>of second-hand airbags is not easy and not even <lb/>recommended. Operating all pyrotechnic devices <lb/> at the end of their life may not be ideal either [4]. <lb/>Dismantlement of such devices from the cars <lb/>requires special care and particular cautions for <lb/>handling and storing operations before further <lb/>treatment. <lb/>Then regarding environment protection, <lb/>the issue of treatment of pyrotechnic articles <lb/>withdrawn from wrecked vehicles is growing, <lb/>since this aspect was not really considered until <lb/>recently. There are no reasonable industrial ways <lb/>for safe disposal and, most often, devices are <lb/>operated before dismantling. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> It is now well established that airbag <lb/>systems contribute to decrease the number of <lb/>casualties in car accidents. The technology based <lb/>on pyrotechnic components has shown its utility <lb/>in safety automotive systems where a short <lb/>reaction time is required. But with the <lb/>multiplication of such equipment in vehicles and <lb/>of similar items in other fields, pyrotechnic <lb/>articles are promised to new developments. <lb/>However, as long as energetic materials will be <lb/>part of these items, special attention and careful <lb/>evaluation will have to be taken. In particular <lb/>  and environmental <lb/> would gain be putting on the scene more in <lb/>advance, at the design stage, for more easy and <lb/>sustainable development. <lb/> </body>
			
		<back>
			<listBibl>References <lb/> [1] C. Michot, G. Marlair and L. Aufauvre <lb/>&quot;Evaluation of the hazards presented by <lb/>pyrotechnic devices for public use: consumer <lb/>fireworks and protection systems for cars&quot;, <lb/>accepted for publication in Face Au Risque, (in <lb/>French) <lb/>[2] Aufauvre L., Branka R. &quot;French Approval <lb/>Procedures for Pyrotechnical Automotive Safety <lb/>Equipment&quot; presentation to International <lb/>Pyrotechnic Automotive Safety Symposium, <lb/>Bordeaux, November 22-23, 2005, Proc. (2005), <lb/>p249-253 <lb/>[3] Proposal for a Directive of the European <lb/>Parliament and of the Council on the placing on <lb/>the market of pyrotechnic articles, text <lb/>E2986-COM (2005)457 final, October 2005 <lb/>[4] G. Marlair, R. Turcotte, &amp; Q.K. Kwok &amp; R. <lb/>Branka &quot;Toxicity issues pertaining to burning <lb/>pyrotechnics&quot; paper presented at this 33 rd <lb/> International Pyrotechnics Seminar. </listBibl>

		</back>	
	</text>
</tei>
