<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Original Article <lb/>Design of multi epitope-based peptide vaccine against E protein of human <lb/>COVID-19: An immunoinformatics approach <lb/>Miyssa I. Abdelmageed 1 , Abdelrahman H. Abdelmoneim 2 , Mujahed I. Mustafa 3* , Nafisa M. <lb/>Elfadol 4 , Naseem S. Murshed 5 , Shaza W. Shantier 6 and Abdelrafie M. Makhawi 3 <lb/>1 Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Khartoum, Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>2 Faculty of Medicine, Alneelain University, Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>3 Department of Biotechnology, University of Bahri, Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>4 Department of Molecular biology, National University Biomedical Research Institute, National University, <lb/>Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>5 Department of Microbiology, International University of Africa, Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>6 Department of Pharmaceutical Chemistry, Faculty of Pharmacy, University of Khartoum, Khartoum, Sudan. <lb/>*Corresponding author: Mujahed I. Mustafa; mujahedibrahim44@gmail.com <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: New endemic disease has been spread across Wuhan City, China on December <lb/>2019. Within few weeks, the World Health Organization (WHO) announced a novel coronavirus <lb/>designated as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19). In late January 2020, WHO declared the <lb/>outbreak of a &quot;public-health emergency of international concern&quot; due to the rapid and increasing <lb/>spread of the disease worldwide. Currently, there is no vaccine or approved treatment for this <lb/>emerging infection; thus the objective of this study is to design a multi epitope peptide vaccine <lb/>against COVID-19 using immunoinformatics approach. <lb/>Method: Several techniques facilitating the combination of immunoinformatics approach and <lb/>comparative genomic approach were used in order to determine the potential peptides for <lb/>designing the T cell epitopes-based peptide vaccine using the envelope protein of 2019-nCoV as <lb/>a target. <lb/>Results: Extensive mutations, insertion and deletion were discovered with comparative <lb/>sequencing in COVID-19 strain. Additionally, ten peptides binding to MHC class I and MHC <lb/>class II were found to be promising candidates for vaccine design with adequate world <lb/>population coverage of 88.5% and 99.99%, respectively. <lb/>Conclusion: T cell epitopes-based peptide vaccine was designed for COVID-19 using envelope <lb/>protein as an immunogenic target. Nevertheless, the proposed vaccine is rapidly needed to be <lb/>validated clinically in order to ensure its safety, immunogenic profile and to help on stopping this <lb/>epidemic before it leads to devastating global outbreaks. <lb/>Keywords: Novel coronavirus (COVID-19), Envelope protein, Emerging infection, Epitope-<lb/>based vaccine, Immunoinformatics approach. <lb/>. <lb/>CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1. Introduction: <lb/>Coronaviruses (CoV) are a large family of zoonotic viruses that cause illness ranging from the <lb/>common cold to more severe diseases such as Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS-CoV) <lb/>and severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome (SARS-CoV). In the last decades, six strains of <lb/>coronaviruses were identified, however in December 2019; a new strain has been spread across <lb/>Wuhan City, China [1, 2]. It was designated as coronavirus disease 2019 (COVID-19) by the <lb/>World Health Organization (WHO) [3]. In late January 2020, WHO declared the outbreak a <lb/>global pandemic with cases in more than 45 countries where the COVID-19 spreading fast <lb/>outside China, most significantly in South Korea, Italy and Iran with over 2,924 deaths and <lb/>85,212 cases confirmed while 39,537 recovered at 29 February 2020, 06:05 AM (GMT). <lb/>COVID-19 is a positive-sense single stranded RNA virus (+ssRNA). Its RNA sequence is <lb/>approximately 30,000 bases in length [4]. It belongs to the subgenus Sarbecovirus, Genus <lb/>Betacoronavirus within the family Coronaviridae. The corona envelope (E) protein is a small, <lb/>integral membrane protein involved in several aspects of the virus&apos; life cycle, such as <lb/>pathogenesis, envelope formation, assembly and budding; alongside with its interactions with <lb/>both other CoVs proteins (M, N &amp; S) and host cell proteins (release of infectious particles after <lb/>budding) [5-9]. <lb/>The infected person characterized with fever, upper or lower respiratory tract symptoms, or <lb/>diarrhoea, lymphopenia, thrombocytopenia, and increased C-reactive protein and lactate <lb/>dehydrogenase levels or combination of all these within 3-6 days after exposure. Further <lb/>molecular diagnosis can be made by Real Time-PCR for genes encoding the internal RNA-<lb/>dependent RNA polymerase and Spike&apos;s receptor binding domain, which can be confirmed by <lb/>Sanger sequencing and full genome analysis by NGS, multiplex nucleic acid amplification and <lb/>microarray-based assays [10-14] <lb/>A phylogenetic tree of the mutation history of a family of viruses is possible to reconstruct with a <lb/>sufficient number of sequenced genomes. The phylogenetic analysis indicates that COVID-19 is <lb/>likely originated from bats [15]. It also showed that is highly related with at most seven <lb/>mutations relative to a common ancestor [16]. <lb/>The sequence of COVID-19 RBD, together with its RBM that contacts receptor angiotensin-<lb/>converting enzyme 2 (ACE2), was found similar to that of SARS coronavirus. On January 2020, <lb/>a group of scientists demonstrated that ACE2 could act as the receptor for COVID-19 [17-21]. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>However, COVID-19 differs from other previous strains in having several critical residues at <lb/>2019-nCoV receptor-binding motif (particularly Gln493) which provide advantageous <lb/>interactions with human ACE2 [15]. This difference in affinity possibly explains why the novel <lb/>coronavirus is more contagious than those other viruses. <lb/>At present, there is no vaccine or approved treatment for humans, but Chinese traditional <lb/>medicine, such ShuFengJieDu Capsules and Lianhuaqingwen Capsule, could be possible <lb/>treatments for COVID-19. However, there are no clinical trials approving the safety and efficacy <lb/>for these drugs [22]. <lb/>The main concept within all the immunizations is the ability of the vaccine to initiate an immune <lb/>response in a faster mode than the pathogen itself. Although traditional vaccines, which depend <lb/>on biochemical trials, induced potent neutralizing and protective responses in the immunized <lb/>animals but they can be costly, allergenic, time consuming and require in vitro culture of <lb/>pathogenic viruses leading to serious concern of safety [23, 24]. Thus the need for safe and <lb/>efficacious vaccines is highly recommended. <lb/>Peptide-based vaccines do not need in vitro culture making them biologically safe, and their <lb/>selectivity allows accurate activation of immune responses [25, 26]. The core mechanism of the <lb/>peptide vaccines is built on the chemical method to synthesize the recognized B-cell and T-cell <lb/>epitopes that are immunodominant and can induce specific immune responses. B-cell epitope of <lb/>a target molecule can be linked with a T-cell epitope to make it immunogenic. The T-cell <lb/>epitopes are short peptide fragments (8-20 amino acids), whereas the B-cell epitopes can be <lb/>proteins [27, 28]. Therefore, in this study, we aimed to design a peptide-based vaccine to predict <lb/>epitopes from corona envelope (E) protein using immunoinformatics analysis [29-34]. While <lb/>rapid further studies are recommended to prove the efficiency of the predicted epitopes as a <lb/>peptide vaccine against this emerging infection. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2. Materials and Methods <lb/>Workflow summarizing the procedures for the epitope-based peptide vaccine prediction is shown <lb/>in Fig. 1 <lb/>Figure 1: Descriptive workflow for the epitope-based peptide vaccine prediction. <lb/>2.1. Data retrieval: <lb/>Full genebank files of the complete genomes and annotation of COVID-19(NC_04551) SARS-<lb/>CoV(FJ211859), <lb/>MESA-CoV(NC_019843), <lb/>HCoV-HKU1(AY884001), <lb/>(HCoV-OC43 <lb/>(KF923903), HCoV-NL63 (NC_005831) and HCoV-229E (KY983587) were retrieved from the <lb/>National Center of Biotechnology Information (NCBI); while The FASTA format of envelope <lb/>(E) protein (YP_009724392.1) , spike (S)protein (YP_009724390.1), nucleocapsid (N) protein <lb/>(YP_009724397.2) and membrane (M) protein (YP_009724393.1) of 2019-nCoV and the <lb/>envelope (E) protein of two Chinese and two American sequences (YP009724392.1, <lb/>QHQ71975.1, QHO60596.1 and QHN73797.1) were obtained from the NCBI. <lb/>(https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/) <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.2. The Artemis Comparison Tool (ACT): <lb/>ACT is an in silico analysis software for visualization of comparisons between complete genome <lb/>sequences and associated annotations [35]. It is also applied to identify regions of similarity, <lb/>rearrangements and insertions at any level from base-pair differences to the whole genome. <lb/>(https://www.sanger.ac.uk/science/tools/artemis-comparison-tool-act). <lb/>2.3. VaxiJen server: <lb/>It is the first server for alignment-independent prediction of protective antigens. It allows antigen <lb/>classification solely based on the physicochemical properties of proteins without recourse to <lb/>sequence alignment. It predicts the probability of the antigenicity one or multiple of protein <lb/>based on auto cross covariance (ACC) transformation of protein sequence. Structural CoV-2019 <lb/>protein (N,S,E and M) was analyzed by VaxiJen with threshold of 0.4 [36]. (http://www.ddg-<lb/>pharmfac.net/vaxijen/VaxiJen/VaxiJen.html) <lb/>2.4. BioEdit: <lb/>It is a software package proposed to stream a distinct program that can run nearly any sequence <lb/>operation as well as a few basic alignment investigations. The sequences of E protein were <lb/>retrieved from UniProt were run in BioEdit to determine the conserved sites through ClustalW in <lb/>the application settings [37]. <lb/>2.5. The Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis (MEGA): <lb/>MEGA (version 10.1.6) is software for the comparative analysis of molecular sequences. It is <lb/>used for pairwise and multiple sequences alignment alongside construction and analysis of <lb/>phylogenetic trees and evolutionary relationships. The gap penalty was 15 for opening and 6.66 <lb/>for extending the gap for both pairwise and multiple sequences alignment. Bootstrapping of 300 <lb/>was used in construction of maximum like hood phylogenetic tree [38, 39]. <lb/>(https://www.megasoftware.net). <lb/>2.6. Prediction of T-cell epitopes: <lb/>IEDB tools were used to predict the conserved sequences (10-mersequence) from HLA class I <lb/>and class II T-cell epitopes by using artificial neural network (ANN) approach [40-42]. Artificial <lb/>Neural Network (ANN) version 2.2 was chosen as Prediction method as it depends on the <lb/>median inhibitory concentration (IC50) [40, 43-45]. For the binding analysis, all the alleles were <lb/>carefully chosen, and the length was set at 10 before prediction was done. Analysis of epitopes <lb/>binding to MHC class I and II molecules was assessed by the IEDB MHC prediction server at <lb/>(http://tools.iedb.org/mhci/) and (http://tools.iedb.org/mhcii/), respectively. All conserved <lb/>immunodominant peptides binding to MHC I and II molecules at score equal or less than 100 <lb/>median inhibitory concentrations (IC50) and 1000, respectively were selected for further analysis <lb/>while epitopes with IC50 greater than 100 were eliminated [46]. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.7. Population coverage analysis: <lb/>Population coverage for each epitope was carefully determined by the IEDB population coverage <lb/>calculation tool. Due to the diverse binding sites of epitopes with different HLA allele, the most <lb/>promising epitope candidates were calculated for population coverage against the whole world, <lb/>China and Europe population to get and ensure a universal vaccine [47, 48]. <lb/>(http://tools.iedb.org/population/) <lb/>2.8. Tertiary structure (3D) Modeling: <lb/>The reference sequence of E protein that has been retrieved from gene bank was used as an input <lb/>in RaptorX to predict the 3D structure of E protein [49, 50], the visualization of the obtained 3D <lb/>protein structure was performed in UCSF Chimera (version1.8) [51]. <lb/>2.9. In silico Molecular Docking: <lb/>2.9.1. Ligand Preparation: <lb/>In order to estimate the binding affinities between the epitopes and molecular structure of MHC I <lb/>and MHC II, in silico molecular docking were used. Sequences of proposed epitopes were <lb/>selected from COVID-19 reference sequence using UCSF Chimera 1.10 and saved as a PDB file. <lb/>The obtained files were then optimized and energy minimized. The HLA-A*02:01 was selected <lb/>as the macromolecule for docking. Its crystal structure (4UQ3) was downloaded from the RCSB <lb/>Protein Data Bank (http://www.rcsb.org/pdb/home/home.do), which was in a complex with an <lb/>azobenzene-containing peptide [52]. <lb/>All water molecules and heteroatoms in the retrieved target file 4UQ3 were then removed. <lb/>Target structure was further optimized and energy minimized using Swiss PDB viewer V.4.1.0 <lb/>software[53]. <lb/>2.9.2. Molecular docking <lb/>Molecular docking was performed using Autodock 4.0 software, based on Lamarckian Genetic <lb/>Algorithm; which combines energy evaluation through grids of affinity potential to find the <lb/>suitable binding position for a ligand on a given protein[54,55]Polar hydrogen atoms were added <lb/>to the protein targets and Kollman united atomic charges were computed. The target&apos;s grid map <lb/>was calculated and set to 60×60×60 points with grid spacing of 0.375 Ǻ. The grid box was then <lb/>allocated properly in the target to include the active residue in the center. The genetic algorithm <lb/>and its run were set to 100.The docking algorithms were set to default. Finally, results were <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>retrieved as binding energies and poses that showed lowest binding energies were visualized <lb/>using UCSF Chimera. <lb/>3. Results: <lb/>3.1. The Artemis Comparison Tool: <lb/>The reference sequence of envelope protein was aligned with HCov-HKU1 reference protein <lb/>using artemis comparison tool as illustrated in (Fig. 2). <lb/>Figure 2: Artemis analysis of envelope protein displaying 3 windows, the upper window <lb/>represents HCov-HKU1 reference sequence and its genes are highlighted in blue starting from <lb/>orflab gene and ending with N gene. The middle window describes the similarities and the <lb/>difference between the two genomes. Red lines indicate match between genes from the two <lb/>genomes blue lines indicates inversion which represents same sequences in the two genomes but <lb/>they are organized in the opposite direction, and the lower windows represents COVID-19and its <lb/>genes started from ARFLAB and ends with N genes. <lb/>3.2. VaxiJen server: <lb/>The mutated proteins were tested for antigenicity using VaxiJen software, where the envelope <lb/>protein found as the best immunogenic target in Table 1. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: VaxiJen overall prediction of probable COVID-19 antigen: <lb/>Protein <lb/>Result <lb/>VaxiJen prediction <lb/>Protein E <lb/>0.6025 <lb/>Probable antigen <lb/>Protein M <lb/>0.5102 <lb/>Probable antigen <lb/>Protein S <lb/>0.4646 <lb/>Probable antigen <lb/>Protein N <lb/>0.5059 <lb/>Probable antigen <lb/>3.3. BioEdit: <lb/>Sequence alignment of COVID-19envelope protein was done using BioEdit software which <lb/>shows total conservation across four sequences which were retrieved from China and USA (Fig. <lb/>3). <lb/>Figure 3: Sequence alignment of envelope protein of COVID-19 using BioEdit software (total <lb/>conservation through the 4 strains: 2 form China and 2 from USA) <lb/>3.4. The Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis: <lb/>To study the evolutionary relationship between all the seven strains of coronavirus, a multiple <lb/>sequence alignment (MSA) was performed using ClustalW by MEGA software. This alignment <lb/>was used to construct maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree as seen in Fig. 4. <lb/>ch <lb/>ig. <lb/>le <lb/>nt <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4: Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree which describes the evolutionary relationship <lb/>between the seven strains of coronavirus. <lb/>3.5. Prediction of T-cell epitopes and population coverage: <lb/>IEDB website was used to analyze 2019-nCoV envelope protein for T cell related peptides. <lb/>Results show ten MHC class I and II associated peptides with high population coverage (Tables <lb/>2 and 3; Fig. 5). The most promising peptides were visualized using UCSF Chimera software <lb/>(Fig.6a and b). <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2: The most promised MHC class I related peptides in envelope protein based vaccine of <lb/>COVID-19 along with the predicted World, China, Europe and East Asia coverage: <lb/>Peptide <lb/>Alleles <lb/>Coverage <lb/>Combined <lb/>coverage of 10 <lb/>peptide <lb/>YVYSRVKNL <lb/>HLA-C*14:02,HLA-C*12:03,HLA-<lb/>C*07:01,HLA-C*03:03,HLA-C*06:02 <lb/>50.02% <lb/>World: 88.5% <lb/>SLVKPSFYV HLA-A*02:06,HLA-A*02:01,HLA-A*68:02 <lb/>42.53% <lb/>China: 78.17% <lb/>SVLLFLAFV <lb/>HLA-A*02:06,HLA-A*68:02,HLA-A*02:01 <lb/>42.53% <lb/>Europe: 92.94% <lb/>FLAFVVFLL <lb/>HLA-A*02:01,HLA-A*02:06 <lb/>40.60% East Asia: 80.78% <lb/>VLLFLAFVV <lb/>HLA-A*02:01 <lb/>39.08% <lb/>RLCAYCCNI <lb/>HLA-A*02:01 <lb/>39.08% <lb/>FVSEETGTL <lb/>HLA-C*03:03,HLA-C*12:03,HLA-<lb/>A*02:06,HLA-A*68:02,HLA-B*35:01 <lb/>28.22% <lb/>LTALRLCAY HLA-A*01:01,HLA-A*30:02,HLA-B*15:01 <lb/>26.34% <lb/>LVKPSFYVY <lb/>HLA-B*15:01,HLA-A*29:02,HLA-<lb/>A*30:02,HLA-B*35:01 <lb/>21.72% <lb/>NIVNVSLVK <lb/>HLA-A*68:01,HLA-A*11:01 <lb/>20.88% <lb/>Table 3: The most promised MHC class II related peptides in envelope protein based vaccine of <lb/>COVID-19 along with the predicted World, China, Europe and East Asia coverage: <lb/>Peptide Sequence <lb/>Alleles <lb/>World <lb/>coverage <lb/>Coverage/10 <lb/>peptide <lb/>KPSFYVYSRVKNLNS <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*02:01,HLA-DPB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*06:01,HLA-DPB1*14:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*01:01,HLA-DQA1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:02,HLA-DQB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*02:01,HLA-DRB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*09:01,HLA-DRB1*11:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:03,HLA-DRB1*04:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*10:01,HLA-DRB1*04:05,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:01,HLA-DRB1*08:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*16:02,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB5*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*02:02,HLA-DRB1*04:04,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:02 <lb/>99.93% <lb/>World : <lb/>99.99% <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>VKPSFYVYSRVKNLN <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:01,HLA-DPB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*02:01,HLA-DPB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*06:01,HLA-DPB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*06:01,HLA-DQA1*01:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB1*09:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*11:01,HLA-DRB4*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*15:01,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*10:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*16:02,HLA-DRB1*08:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:05,HLA-DRB5*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:02,HLA-DRB3*02:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:01,HLA-DRB1*04:04 <lb/>99.92% <lb/>China: <lb/>99.96% <lb/>LVKPSFYVYSRVKNL <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:01,HLA-DPA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*05:01,HLA-DPB1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*02:01,HLA-DPB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*06:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:04,HLA-DQB1*05:03,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:02,HLA-DQB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*09:01,HLA-DRB1*11:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:03,HLA-DRB3*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*16:02,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*10:01,HLA-DRB1*08:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB5*01:01,HLA-DRB1*13:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:05,HLA-DRB3*02:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:01 <lb/>99.90% <lb/>Europe : <lb/>100.0% <lb/>PSFYVYSRVKNLNSS <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*02:01,HLA-DPB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*06:01,HLA-DQA1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*01:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>99.86% <lb/>East <lb/>Asia:99.91% <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>DRB1*04:01,HLA-DRB1*11:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*09:01,HLA-DRB1*07:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:03,HLA-DRB1*04:05,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*10:01,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:02,HLA-DRB1*16:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*15:01,HLA-DRB3*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*02:02,HLA-DRB1*04:04,HLA-<lb/>DRB5*01:01,HLA-DRB1*13:02 <lb/>NIVNVSLVKPSFYVY <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:01,HLA-DPB1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*02:01,HLA-DPB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:02,HLA-DQB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*02:01,HLA-DQB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*03:03,HLA-DQB1*03:03,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*04:02,HLA-DRB1*12:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB5*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:03,HLA-DRB1*04:04,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:02,HLA-DRB1*09:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:02,HLA-DRB1*11:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:05,HLA-DRB1*10:01 <lb/>99.77% <lb/>LLVTLAILTALRLCA <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*06:01,HLA-DPA1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*01:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*03:01,HLA-DQB1*03:03,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*06:01,HLA-DQA1*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*06:03,HLA-DRB4*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:04,HLA-DRB5*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*10:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*15:01,HLA-DRB1*07:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*11:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*12:01,HLA-DRB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:01,HLA-DRB1*16:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:02 <lb/>99.72% <lb/>SFYVYSRVKNLNSSR <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*02:01,HLA-DPA1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:02,HLA-DPA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*05:01,HLA-DPB1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>99.72% <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:02,HLA-DQB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:01,HLA-DRB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*11:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB1*09:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:03,HLA-DRB1*10:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:01,HLA-DRB1*04:05,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:02,HLA-DRB1*16:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*02:02,HLA-DRB3*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:04,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB5*01:01,HLA-DRB1*13:02 <lb/>LVTLAILTALRLCAY <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*06:01,HLA-DPA1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*01:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*03:01,HLA-DQB1*03:03,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*05:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*06:02,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*06:01,HLA-DRB4*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB1*13:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:04,HLA-DRB1*12:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*10:01,HLA-DRB5*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*15:01,HLA-DRB1*11:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:01,HLA-DRB1*07:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:01,HLA-DRB1*16:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:02,HLA-DRB1*08:02 <lb/>99.69% <lb/>VTLAILTALRLCAYC <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DPA1*03:01,HLA-DPB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*02:01,HLA-DQB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:02,HLA-DQB1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*06:02,HLA-DQA1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*04:02,HLA-DQB1*03:03,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*06:01,HLA-DQB1*04:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*01:01,HLA-DRB4*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:01,HLA-DRB1*04:04,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*12:01,HLA-DRB1*10:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB5*01:01,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*11:01,HLA-DRB1*03:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*08:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB4*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*04:02 <lb/>99.56% <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>CNIVNVSLVKPSFYV <lb/>HLA-DPA1*01:03,HLA-DPB1*06:01,HLA-<lb/>DPB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*01:02,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*05:01,HLA-DQA1*05:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*04:02,HLA-DQA1*02:01,HLA-<lb/>DQB1*03:01,HLA-DQB1*03:03,HLA-<lb/>DQA1*01:03,HLA-DQB1*06:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB3*03:01,HLA-DRB1*12:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB5*01:01,HLA-DRB1*01:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*07:01,HLA-DRB4*01:03,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*13:01,HLA-DRB1*15:01,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*08:02,HLA-DRB1*04:04,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*09:01,HLA-DRB1*13:02,HLA-<lb/>DRB1*11:01,HLA-DRB1*04:05,HLA-<lb/>DRB4*01:01,HLA-DRB1*10:01 <lb/>99.53% <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5: Schematic diagrams (A) and (B) showing world population coverage of envelope <lb/>protein of COVID-19 binding to MHC class I and MHC class II molecule respectively. <lb/>pe <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6: 3D structures visualized by UCSF Chimera: (A) and (B) showing the most promising <lb/>peptides in envelope protein of COVID-19 (yellow colored) binding to MHC class I and MHC <lb/>class II respectively, while (C, D, and E) showing the molecular docking of YVYSRVKNL, <lb/>LAILTALRL and SLVKPSFYV peptides of coronavirus docked in HLA-A*02:01 respectively y <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Discussion: <lb/>Designing of a novel vaccine is very crucial to defending the rapid endless of global burden of <lb/>disease [56-59]. In the last few decades, biotechnology has advanced rapidly; alongside with the <lb/>understanding of immunology which assisted the rise of new approaches towards <lb/>rational vaccines design [60]. Peptide-based vaccines are designed to elicit immunity particular <lb/>pathogens by selectively stimulating antigen specific for B and T cells [61].Applying the <lb/>advanced bioinformatics tools and databases, various peptide-based vaccines could be designed <lb/>where the peptides act as ligands [62-64]. This approach has been used frequently in Saint Louis <lb/>encephalitis virus [65], dengue virus [66], chikungunya virus [67] proposing promising peptides <lb/>for designing vaccines. <lb/>The COVID-19 is an RNA virus which tends to mutate more commonly than the DNA viruses <lb/>[68]. These mutations lied on the surface of the protein, which make COVID-19 more superior <lb/>than other previous strains by inducing its sustainability leaving the immune system in blind spot <lb/>[69]. <lb/>In our present work, different peptides were proposed for the designing of vaccine against <lb/>COVID-19 (Fig. 1). In the beginning, the whole genome of COVID-19 was analyzed by <lb/>comparative genomic approach to determine the potential antigenic target [70]. Artemis <lb/>Comparative Tool (ACT) was used to analyze human Coronavirus (HCov-HKU1) reference <lb/>sequence vs. Wuhan-Hu-1 COVID-19. Results obtained (Fig.2) revealed extensive mutation <lb/>among the tested genomes. New genes; ORF8 and ORF6; were found inserted in COVID-19 <lb/>which were absent in HCov-HKU1 that might be acquired by the horizontal gene transmission <lb/>[71]. High rate of mutation between the two genomes were observed in the region from 20000 bp <lb/>to the end of the sequence. This region encodes the four major structural proteins in coronavirus <lb/>which are envelope (E) protein, nucleocapsid (N) protein, membrane (M) protein, and spike (S) <lb/>protein, all of which are required to produce a structurally complete virus [72, 73]. <lb/>These conserved antigenic sites were revealed in previous studies through sequence alignment <lb/>between MERS-CoV and Bat-coronavirus [74] and analyzed in SARS-CoV [75]. <lb/>The four proteins were then analyzed by Vaxigen software to test the probability of antigenic <lb/>proteins. Protein E was found to be the most antigenic gene with the highest probability as <lb/>shown in Table 1. Literature survey confirmed this result in which protein E was investigated in <lb/>severe acute respiratory syndrome (SARS) in 2003 and, more recently, Middle-East respiratory <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>syndrome (MERS) [72]. Furthermore, the conservation of this protein against the seven strains <lb/>was tested and confirmed through the use of BioEdit package tool (Fig. 3). <lb/>As phylogenetic analysis is very powerful tool for determining the evolutionary relationship <lb/>between strains. Multiple sequence alignment (MSA) was performed using ClustalW for the <lb/>seven strains of coronavirus, which are COVID-19(NC_04551), SARS-CoV (FJ211859), <lb/>MESA-CoV (NC_019843), HCoV-HKU1 (AY884001), HCoV-OC43 (KF923903), HCoV-<lb/>NL63 (NC_005831) and HCoV-229E (KY983587). The maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree <lb/>revealed that COVID-19 is found in the same clade of SARS-CoV, thus the two strains are <lb/>highly related to each other (Fig. 4). <lb/>The immune response of T cell is considered as a long lasting response compared to B cell, <lb/>where the antigen can easily escape the antibody memory response [76]. Vaccines that <lb/>effectively generate cell-mediated response are needed to provide protection against the invading <lb/>pathogen. Moreover the CD8+ T and CD4+ T cell responses play a major role in antiviral <lb/>immunity [77]. Thus designing vaccine against T cell is much more important. <lb/>Choosing protein E as the antigenic site, the binding affinity to MHC molecules was then <lb/>evaluated. The protein reference sequence was submitted to IEDB MHC predication tool. 21 <lb/>peptides were found to bind MHC class I with different affinities (Table 1), from which ten <lb/>peptides were selected for vaccine design based on the number of alleles and world population <lb/>percentage (Table 2; Fig. 5).Analysis in IEDB MHC II binding prediction tool resulted in <lb/>prediction of 61 peptides (Table 2), from which ten peptides were selected for vaccine design <lb/>based on the number of alleles and world population percentage (Table 3; Fig.5). Unfortunately, <lb/>IEDB did not give any result for B cell epitopes, this might be due to the length of the COVID-<lb/>19 (75 amino acids). <lb/>It is well known that peptides recognized with high number of HLA molecules are potentially <lb/>inducing immune response. Based on the aforementioned results and taking into consideration <lb/>the high binding affinity to both MHC classes I and II, conservancy and population coverage, <lb/>three peptides are strongly proposed to formulate a new vaccine against COVID-19. <lb/>These findings were further confirmed by the results obtained for the molecular docking of the <lb/>proposed peptides and HLA-A*02:01. The formed complex between MHC molecule and the <lb/>three peptides (YVYSRVKNL, SLVKPSFYV and LAILTALRL) have shown peptide amino-and <lb/>carboxyl-termini forming one and three hydrogen bonds, respectively at the two ends of a binding <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>groove with MHC residues with least binding energy -13.2 kcal/mol, -11 kcal/mol and -11.3 <lb/>kcal/mol, respectively (Fig.6C, D and E). <lb/>Although both flu and anti-HIV drugs are used currently in China for treatment of COVID-19, <lb/>and chloroquine phosphate, an old drug for treatment of malaria, has recently found to have <lb/>apparent efficacy and acceptable safety against COVID-19 [78,79]; nevertheless more studies <lb/>are required to standardize these therapies. In addition, there has been some success in the <lb/>development of mouse models of MERS-CoV and SARS-CoV infection, and candidate vaccines <lb/>where the envelope (E) protein is mutated or deleted have been described [80-86]. To best of our <lb/>knowledge, this is the first study to identify certain peptides in envelope (E) protein as candidates <lb/>for COVID-19. Accordingly, these epitopes were strongly recommended as promising epitopes <lb/>vaccine candidate against T cell. <lb/>5. Conclusion: <lb/>Extensive mutations, insertion and deletion were discovered in COVID-19 strain using the <lb/>comparative sequencing. In addition, a number of MHC class I and II related peptides were <lb/>found promising candidates. Among which the peptides YVYSRVKNL, SLVKPSFYV and <lb/>LAILTALRL show high potentiality for vaccine design with adequate world population <lb/>coverage. T cell epitope-based peptide vaccine was designed for COVID-19 using envelope <lb/>protein as an immunogenic target; nevertheless, the proposed vaccine rapidly needs to be <lb/>validated clinically ensuring its safety and immunogenic profile to help on stopping this <lb/>epidemic before it leads to devastating global outbreaks. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement: <lb/>The authors acknowledge the Deanship of Scientific Research at University of Bahri for the <lb/>supportive cooperation. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability: <lb/>All data underlying the results are available as part of the article, and no additional source <lb/>data are required. <lb/></div>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions: <lb/>MIA: Conceptualization, Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology, Validation, Visualization, Writing-original <lb/>draft. AHA: Formal analysis, Investigation, Methodology. MIM: Methodology, Writing-original draft, Writing -<lb/>review and editing. NME: Formal analysis, Methodology, Visualization. NSM: Conceptualization, Resources, <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing. SWS: Visualization, Validation, Writing -review and editing, AMM: Data curation, <lb/>Conceptualization, Project administration, Supervision, Writing -review and editing. All authors have read and <lb/>approved the final manuscript. <lb/>Abbreviations: <lb/>WHO: World Health Organization; CoV: Coronaviruses; MERS-CoV: Middle East Respiratory Syndrome; SARS-<lb/>CoV: Acute Respiratory Syndrome; COVID-19: novel coronavirus; HCoV-HKU1: Human coronavirus HKU1; <lb/>HCoV-OC43: Human coronavirus OC43; HCoV-NL63: Human coronavirus NL63; HCoV-229E: Human <lb/>coronavirus 229E; ACE2: angiotensin converting enzyme 2; RBM: receptor-binding motif; RBM: receptor-binding <lb/>domain; vs.: versus; ACT: Artemis Comparison Tool; ACC: auto cross covariance; MEGA: Molecular Evolutionary <lb/>Genetics Analysis; ANN: Artificial Neural Network; IEDB: Immune Epitope Database; IC50: median inhibitory <lb/>concentrations; MHC I: Major Histocompatibility complex class I; MHC II: Major Histocompatibility complex class <lb/>II PDB: Protein database; MSA: multiple sequence alignment. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References: <lb/>1. H. Lu, C. W. Stratton, and Y. W. Tang, &quot;Outbreak of Pneumonia of Unknown Etiology in <lb/>Wuhan China: the Mystery and the Miracle,&quot; J Med Virol, Jan 16 2020. <lb/>2. D. S. Hui, I. A. E, T. A. Madani, F. Ntoumi, R. Kock, O. Dar, et al., &quot;The continuing <lb/>2019-nCoV epidemic threat of novel coronaviruses to global health -The latest 2019 <lb/>novel coronavirus outbreak in Wuhan, China,&quot; Int J Infect Dis, vol. 91, pp. 264-266, Jan <lb/>14 2020. <lb/>3. D. Benvenuto, M. Giovannetti, A. Ciccozzi, S. Spoto, S. Angeletti, and M. Ciccozzi, <lb/>&quot;The 2019-new coronavirus epidemic: evidence for virus evolution,&quot; J Med Virol, Jan 29 <lb/>2020. <lb/>4. &quot;CoV2020&quot;. GISAID EpifluDB. Archivedfrom the original on 12 January 2020. <lb/>Retrieved February 2020 <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. P. Venkatagopalan, S. M. Daskalova, L. A. Lopez, K. A. Dolezal, and B. G. Hogue, <lb/>&quot;Coronavirus envelope (E) protein remains at the site of assembly,&quot; Virology, vol. 478, <lb/>pp. 75-85, Apr 2015. <lb/>6. J. L. Nieto-Torres, M. L. Dediego, E. Alvarez, J. M. Jimenez-Guardeno, J. A. Regla-<lb/>Nava, M. Llorente, et al., &quot;Subcellular location and topology of severe acute respiratory <lb/>syndrome coronavirus envelope protein,&quot; Virology, vol. 415, pp. 69-82, Jul 5 2011. <lb/>7. K. M. Curtis, B. Yount, and R. S. Baric, &quot;Heterologous gene expression from <lb/>transmissible gastroenteritis virus replicon particles,&quot; J Virol, vol. 76, pp. 1422-34, Feb <lb/>2002. <lb/>8. J. Ortego, D. Escors, H. Laude, and L. Enjuanes, &quot;Generation of a replication-competent, <lb/>propagation-deficient virus vector based on the transmissible gastroenteritis coronavirus <lb/>genome,&quot; J Virol, vol. 76, pp. 11518-29, Nov 2002. <lb/>9. T. R. Ruch and C. E. Machamer, &quot;A single polar residue and distinct membrane <lb/>topologies impact the function of the infectious bronchitis coronavirus E protein,&quot; PLoS <lb/>Pathog, vol. 8, p. e1002674, 2012. <lb/>10. J. F. Chan, S. Yuan, K. H. Kok, K. K. To, H. Chu, J. Yang, et al., &quot;A familial cluster of <lb/>pneumonia associated with the 2019 novel coronavirus indicating person-to-person <lb/>transmission: a study of a family cluster,&quot; Lancet, Jan 24 2020. <lb/>11. N. Zhang, L. Wang, X. Deng, R. Liang, M. Su, C. He, et al., &quot;Recent advances in the <lb/>detection of respiratory virus infection in humans,&quot; J Med Virol, Jan 15 2020. <lb/>12. J. B. Mahony, A. Petrich, and M. Smieja, &quot;Molecular diagnosis of respiratory virus <lb/>infections,&quot; Crit Rev Clin Lab Sci, vol. 48, pp. 217-49, Sep-Dec 2011. <lb/>13. V. M. Corman, O. Landt, M. Kaiser, R. Molenkamp, A. Meijer, D. K. Chu, et al., <lb/>&quot;Detection of 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) by real-time RT-PCR,&quot; Euro <lb/>Surveill, vol. 25, Jan 2020. <lb/>14. Y. Chen, Q. Liu, and D. Guo, &quot;Emerging coronaviruses: genome structure, replication, <lb/>and pathogenesis,&quot; J Med Virol, Jan 22 2020 <lb/>15. Y. Wan, J. Shang, R. Graham, R. S. Baric, and F. Li, &quot;Receptor recognition by novel <lb/>coronavirus from Wuhan: An analysis based on decade-long structural studies of SARS, J <lb/>Virol, Jan 29 2020. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>16. &quot;Genomic epidemiology of novel coronavirus (nCoV)&quot;. nextstrain.org. Retrieved 11 <lb/>February 2020. <lb/>17. Letko M, Munster V (January 2020). &quot;Functional assessment of cell entry and receptor <lb/>usage <lb/>for <lb/>lineage <lb/>B <lb/>β-coronaviruses, <lb/>including <lb/>2019-<lb/>nCoV&quot;. bioRxiv 2020.01.22.915660 Check |biorxiv= value (help). <lb/>18. Letko, M, Marzi, et al. (February 2020). &quot;Functional assessment of cell entry and receptor <lb/>usage for SARS-CoV-2 and other lineage B betacoronaviruses&quot;. Nature <lb/>Microbiology. doi:10.1038/s41564-020-0688-y. PMID 32094589. <lb/>19. El Sahly HM. &quot;Genomic Characterization of the 2019 Novel Coronavirus&quot;. New England <lb/>Journal of Medicine. Retrieved 9 February 2020. <lb/>20. Gralinski LE, Menachery VD (January 2020). &quot;Return of the Coronavirus: 2019-<lb/>nCoV&quot;. Viruses. 12 (2): 135. doi:10.3390/v12020135. PMID 31991541. <lb/>21. Lu R, Zhao X, Li J, et al. (January 2020). &quot;Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of <lb/>2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus origins and receptor <lb/>binding&quot;. Lancet. 395(10224):565-574. doi:10.1016/S0140-6736(20)30251 <lb/>8. PMID 32007145. <lb/>22. H. Lu, &quot;Drug treatment options for the 2019-new coronavirus (2019-nCoV),&quot; Biosci <lb/>Trends, Jan 28 2020. <lb/>23. Y. T. Lo, T. W. Pai, W. K. Wu, and H. T. Chang, &quot;Prediction of conformational epitopes <lb/>with the use of a knowledge-based energy function and geometrically related neighboring <lb/>residue characteristics,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, vol. 14 Suppl 4, p. S3, 2013. <lb/>24. W. Li, M. D. Joshi, S. Singhania, K. H. Ramsey, and A. K. Murthy, &quot;Peptide Vaccine: <lb/>Progress and Challenges,&quot; Vaccines (Basel), vol. 2, pp. 515-36, Jul 2 2014. <lb/>25. A. W. Purcell, J. McCluskey, and J. Rossjohn, &quot;More than one reason to rethink the use <lb/>of peptides in vaccine design,&quot; Nat Rev Drug Discov, vol. 6, pp. 404-14, May 2007. <lb/>26. N. L. Dudek, P. Perlmutter, M. I. Aguilar, N. P. Croft, and A. W. Purcell, &quot;Epitope <lb/>discovery and their use in peptide based vaccines,&quot; Curr Pharm Des, vol. 16, pp. 3149-<lb/>57, 2010. <lb/>27. S. Dermime, D. E. Gilham, D. M. Shaw, E. J. Davidson, K. Meziane el, A. Armstrong, et <lb/>al., &quot;Vaccine and antibody-directed T cell tumour immunotherapy,&quot; Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta, vol. 1704, pp. 11-35, Jul 6 2004. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>28. R. H. Meloen, J. P. Langeveld, W. M. Schaaper, and J. W. Slootstra, &quot;Synthetic peptide <lb/>vaccines: unexpected fulfillment of discarded hope?,&quot; Biologicals, vol. 29, pp. 233-6, <lb/>Sep-Dec 2001. <lb/>29. V. Brusic and N. Petrovsky, &quot;Immunoinformatics and its relevance to understanding <lb/>human immune disease,&quot; Expert Rev Clin Immunol, vol. 1, pp. 145-57, May 2005. <lb/>30. N. Tomar and R. K. De, &quot;Immunoinformatics: a brief review,&quot; Methods Mol Biol, vol. <lb/>1184, pp. 23-55, 2014. <lb/>31. S. Khalili, A. Jahangiri, H. Borna, K. Ahmadi Zanoos, and J. Amani, &quot;Computational <lb/>vaccinology and epitope vaccine design by immunoinformatics,&quot; Acta Microbiol <lb/>Immunol Hung, vol. 61, pp. 285-307, Sep 2014. <lb/>32. N. Tomar and R. K. De, &quot;Immunoinformatics: an integrated scenario,&quot; Immunology, vol. <lb/>131, pp. 153-68, Oct 2010. <lb/>33. N. R. Hegde, S. Gauthami, H. M. Sampath Kumar, and J. Bayry, &quot;The use of databases, <lb/>data mining and immunoinformatics in vaccinology: where are we?,&quot; Expert Opin Drug <lb/>Discov, vol. 13, pp. 117-130, Feb 2018. <lb/>34. A. A. Bahrami, Z. Payandeh, S. Khalili, A. Zakeri, and M. Bandehpour, <lb/>&quot;Immunoinformatics: In Silico Approaches and Computational Design of a Multi-<lb/>epitope, Immunogenic Protein,&quot; Int Rev Immunol, vol. 38, pp. 307-322, 2019. <lb/>35. T. J. Carver, K. M. Rutherford, M. Berriman, M. A. Rajandream, B. G. Barrell, and J. <lb/>Parkhill, &quot;ACT: the Artemis Comparison Tool,&quot; Bioinformatics, vol. 21, pp. 3422-3, Aug <lb/>15 2005. <lb/>36. I. A. Doytchinova and D. R. Flower, &quot;VaxiJen: a server for prediction of protective <lb/>antigens, tumour antigens and subunit vaccines,&quot; BMC Bioinformatics, vol. 8, p. 4, Jan 5 <lb/>2007. <lb/>37. O. O. Oni, A. A. Owoade, and C. A. O. Adeyefa, &quot;Design and evaluation of primer pairs <lb/>for efficient detection of avian rotavirus,&quot; Trop Anim Health Prod, vol. 50, pp. 267-273, <lb/>Feb 2018. <lb/>38. G. Stecher, K. Tamura, and S. Kumar, &quot;Molecular Evolutionary Genetics Analysis <lb/>(MEGA) for macOS,&quot; Mol Biol Evol, Jan 6 2020. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>39. K. Tamura, J. Dudley, M. Nei, and S. Kumar, &quot;MEGA4: Molecular Evolutionary <lb/>Genetics Analysis (MEGA) software version 4.0,&quot; Mol Biol Evol, vol. 24, pp. 1596-9, <lb/>Aug 2007. <lb/>40. M. Nielsen, C. Lundegaard, P. Worning, S. L. Lauemoller, K. Lamberth, S. Buus, et al., <lb/>&quot;Reliable prediction of T-cell epitopes using neural networks with novel sequence <lb/>representations,&quot; Protein Sci, vol. 12, pp. 1007-17, May 2003. <lb/>41. C. Lundegaard, K. Lamberth, M. Harndahl, S. Buus, O. Lund, and M. Nielsen, <lb/>&quot;NetMHC-3.0: accurate web accessible predictions of human, mouse and monkey MHC <lb/>class I affinities for peptides of length 8-11,&quot; Nucleic Acids Res, vol. 36, pp. W509-12, <lb/>Jul 1 2008. <lb/>42. M. Andreatta and M. Nielsen, &quot;Gapped sequence alignment using artificial neural <lb/>networks: application to the MHC class I system,&quot; Bioinformatics, vol. 32, pp. 511-7, Feb <lb/>15 2016. <lb/>43. S. Buus, S. L. Lauemoller, P. Worning, C. Kesmir, T. Frimurer, S. Corbet, et al., <lb/>&quot;Sensitive quantitative predictions of peptide-MHC binding by a &apos;Query by Committee&apos; <lb/>artificial neural network approach,&quot; Tissue Antigens, vol. 62, pp. 378-84, Nov 2003. <lb/>44. C. Lundegaard, O. Lund, and M. Nielsen, &quot;Accurate approximation method for prediction <lb/>of class I MHC affinities for peptides of length 8, 10 and 11 using prediction tools trained <lb/>on 9mers,&quot; Bioinformatics, vol. 24, pp. 1397-8, Jun 1 2008. <lb/>45. C. Lundegaard, M. Nielsen, and O. Lund, &quot;The validity of predicted T-cell epitopes,&quot; <lb/>Trends Biotechnol, vol. 24, pp. 537-8, Dec 2006. <lb/>46. S. Southwood, J. Sidney, A. Kondo, M. F. del Guercio, E. Appella, S. Hoffman, et al., <lb/>&quot;Several common HLA-DR types share largely overlapping peptide binding repertoires,&quot; <lb/>J Immunol, vol. 160, pp. 3363-73, Apr 1 1998. <lb/>47. A. Patronov and I. Doytchinova, &quot;T-cell epitope vaccine design by immunoinformatics,&quot; <lb/>Open Biol, vol. 3, p. 120139, Jan 8 2013. <lb/>48. H. H. Bui, J. Sidney, K. Dinh, S. Southwood, M. J. Newman, and A. Sette, &quot;Predicting <lb/>population coverage of T-cell epitope-based diagnostics and vaccines,&quot; BMC <lb/>Bioinformatics, vol. 7, p. 153, Mar 17 2006. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>49. D. A. Benson, M. Cavanaugh, K. Clark, I. Karsch-Mizrachi, D. J. Lipman, J. Ostell, et <lb/>al., &quot;GenBank,&quot; Nucleic Acids Res, vol. 45, pp. D37-d42, Jan 4 2017. <lb/>50. S. Wang, W. Li, S. Liu, and J. Xu, &quot;RaptorX-Property: a web server for protein structure <lb/>property prediction,&quot; Nucleic Acids Res, vol. 44, pp. W430-5, Jul 8 2016. <lb/>51. E. F. Pettersen, T. D. Goddard, C. C. Huang, G. S. Couch, D. M. Greenblatt, E. C. Meng, <lb/>et al., &quot;UCSF Chimera--a visualization system for exploratory research and analysis,&quot; J <lb/>Comput Chem, vol. 25, pp. 1605-12, Oct 2004. <lb/>52. Choo JA, Thong SY, Yap J, van Esch WJ, Raida M, Meijers R, et al. Bioorthogonal <lb/>cleavage and exchange of major histocompatibility complex ligands by employing <lb/>azobenzene-containing peptides. Angewandte Chemie (International ed in English). <lb/>2014;53(49):13390-4. <lb/>53. Guex N, Peitsch MC. SWISS-MODEL and the Swiss-PdbViewer: an environment for <lb/>comparative protein modeling. Electrophoresis. 1997;18(15):2714-23. <lb/>54. Morris GM, Huey R, Lindstrom W, Sanner MF, Belew RK, Goodsell DS, et al. <lb/>AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking with selective receptor flexibility. <lb/>Journal of computational chemistry. 2009;30(16):2785-91. <lb/>55. Morris G, S. Goodsell D, S. Halliday R, Huey R, Hart W, Belew R, et al. Automated <lb/>Docking Using a Lamarckian Genetic Algorithm and Empirical Binding Free Energy <lb/>Function1998. 1639-62 p <lb/>56. S. J. Marshall, &quot;Developing countries face double burden of disease,&quot; Bull World Health <lb/>Organ, vol. 82, p. 556, Jul 2004. <lb/>57. A. S. De Groot and R. Rappuoli, &quot;Genome-derived vaccines,&quot; Expert Rev Vaccines, vol. <lb/>3, pp. 59-76, Feb 2004. <lb/>58. B. Korber, M. LaBute, and K. Yusim, &quot;Immunoinformatics comes of age,&quot; PLoS Comput <lb/>Biol, vol. 2, p. e71, Jun 30 2006. <lb/>59. A. S. Fauci, &quot;Emerging and re-emerging infectious diseases: influenza as a prototype of <lb/>the host-pathogen balancing act,&quot; Cell, vol. 124, pp. 665-70, Feb 24 2006. <lb/>60. S. Chaudhury, E. H. Duncan, T. Atre, S. Dutta, M. D. Spring, W. W. Leitner, et al., <lb/>&quot;Combining immunoprofiling with machine learning to assess the effects of adjuvant <lb/>formulation on human vaccine-induced immunity,&quot; Hum Vaccin Immunother, pp. 1-12, <lb/>Oct 7 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>61. Purcell AW, McCluskey J, Rossjohn J. More than one reason to rethink the use of peptides <lb/>in vaccine design. Nat Rev Drug Discov 2007; 6 (5): 404-14. PMID: 17473845. <lb/>62. S. S. Usmani, R. Kumar, S. Bhalla, V. Kumar, and G. P. S. Raghava, &quot;In Silico Tools and <lb/>Databases for Designing Peptide-Based Vaccine and Drugs,&quot; Adv Protein Chem Struct <lb/>Biol, vol. 112, pp. 221-263, 2018. <lb/>63. S. K. Dhanda, S. S. Usmani, P. Agrawal, G. Nagpal, A. Gautam, and G. P. S. Raghava, <lb/>&quot;Novel in silico tools for designing peptide-based subunit vaccines and <lb/>immunotherapeutics,&quot; Brief Bioinform, vol. 18, pp. 467-478, May 1 2017. <lb/>64. Y. Khazaei-Poul, S. Farhadi, S. Ghani, S. A. Ahmadizad, and J. Ranjbari, &quot;Monocyclic <lb/>Peptides: Types, Synthesis and applications,&quot; Curr Pharm Biotechnol, Jan 20 2020. <lb/>65. M. A. Hasan, M. Hossain, and M. J. Alam, &quot;A computational assay to design an epitope-<lb/>based Peptide vaccine against saint louis encephalitis virus,&quot; Bioinform Biol Insights, vol. <lb/>7, pp. 347-55, 2013. <lb/>66. S. Chakraborty, R. Chakravorty, M. Ahmed, A. Rahman, T. M. Waise, F. Hassan, et al., <lb/>&quot;A computational approach for identification of epitopes in dengue virus envelope <lb/>protein: a step towards designing a universal dengue vaccine targeting endemic regions,&quot; <lb/>In Silico Biol, vol. 10, pp. 235-46, 2010. <lb/>67. M. Tahir Ul Qamar, A. Bari, M. M. Adeel, A. Maryam, U. A. Ashfaq, X. Du, et al., <lb/>&quot;Peptide vaccine against chikungunya virus: immuno-informatics combined with <lb/>molecular docking approach,&quot; J Transl Med, vol. 16, p. 298, Oct 27 2018. <lb/>68. S. S. Twiddy, E. C. Holmes, and A. Rambaut, &quot;Inferring the rate and time-scale of <lb/>dengue virus evolution,&quot; Mol Biol Evol, vol. 20, pp. 122-9, Jan 2003. <lb/>69. J. M. Christie, H. Chapel, R. W. Chapman, and W. M. Rosenberg, &quot;Immune selection and <lb/>genetic sequence variation in core and envelope regions of hepatitis C virus,&quot; <lb/>Hepatology, vol. 30, pp. 1037-44, Oct 1999. <lb/>70. R. C. Hardison, &quot;Comparative genomics,&quot; PLoS Biol, vol. 1, p. E58, Nov 2003. <lb/>71. C. Gilbert, A. Chateigner, L. Ernenwein, V. Barbe, A. Bezier, E. A. Herniou, et al., <lb/>&quot;Population genomics supports baculoviruses as vectors of horizontal transfer of insect <lb/>transposons,&quot; Nat Commun, vol. 5, p. 3348, 2014. <lb/>72. D. Schoeman and B. C. Fielding, &quot;Coronavirus envelope protein: current knowledge,&quot; <lb/>Virol J, vol. 16, p. 69, May 27 2019. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>73. E. Mortola and P. Roy, &quot;Efficient assembly and release of SARS coronavirus-like <lb/>particles by a heterologous expression system,&quot; FEBS Lett, vol. 576, pp. 174-8, Oct 8 <lb/>2004. <lb/>74. R. Sharmin and A. B. Islam, &quot;Conserved antigenic sites between MERS-CoV and Bat-<lb/>coronavirus are revealed through sequence analysis,&quot; Source Code Biol Med, vol. 11, p. <lb/>3, 2016. <lb/>75. J. Xu, J. Hu, J. Wang, Y. Han, Y. Hu, J. Wen, et al., &quot;Genome organization of the SARS-<lb/>CoV,&quot; Genomics Proteomics Bioinformatics, vol. 1, pp. 226-35, Aug 2003. <lb/>76. Black M, Trent A, Tirrell M, Olive C. Advances in the design and delivery of peptide <lb/>subunit vaccines with a focus on toll-like receptor agonists. Expert Rev Vaccines 2010; 9: <lb/>157-173. <lb/>77. Sesardic D. Synthetic peptide vaccines. J Med Microbiol 1993; 39: 241-242. <lb/>78. Breakthrough: Chloroquine phosphate has shown apparentefficacy in treatment of COVID-<lb/>19 associated pneumonia inclinical studies. <lb/>79. Potential Inhibitors Against Papain-like Protease of Novel Coronavirus (COVID-19) from <lb/>FDA Approved Drugs. <lb/>80. J. W. Westerbeck and C. E. Machamer, &quot;A Coronavirus E Protein Is Present in Two Distinct <lb/>Pools with Different Effects on Assembly and the Secretory Pathway,&quot; J Virol, vol. 89, pp. <lb/>9313-23, Sep 2015. <lb/>81. M. L. Dediego, L. Pewe, E. Alvarez, M. T. Rejas, S. Perlman, and L. Enjuanes, <lb/>&quot;Pathogenicity of severe acute respiratory coronavirus deletion mutants in hACE-2 <lb/>transgenic mice,&quot; Virology, vol. 376, pp. 379-89, Jul 5 2008. <lb/>82. J. Netland, M. L. DeDiego, J. Zhao, C. Fett, E. Alvarez, J. L. Nieto-Torres, et al., <lb/>&quot;Immunization with an attenuated severe acute respiratory syndrome coronavirus deleted <lb/>in E protein protects against lethal respiratory disease,&quot; Virology, vol. 399, pp. 120-128, <lb/>Mar 30 2010. <lb/>83. P. B. McCray, Jr., L. Pewe, C. Wohlford-Lenane, M. Hickey, L. Manzel, L. Shi, et al., <lb/>&quot;Lethal infection of K18-hACE2 mice infected with severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus,&quot; J Virol, vol. 81, pp. 813-21, Jan 2007. <lb/>84. J. A. Regla-Nava, J. L. Nieto-Torres, J. M. Jimenez-Guardeno, R. Fernandez-Delgado, C. <lb/>Fett, C. Castano-Rodriguez, et al., &quot;Severe acute respiratory syndrome coronaviruses <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>with mutations in the E protein are attenuated and promising vaccine candidates,&quot; J Virol, <lb/>vol. 89, pp. 3870-87, Apr 2015. <lb/>85. J. Zhao, K. Li, C. Wohlford-Lenane, S. S. Agnihothram, C. Fett, J. Zhao, et al., &quot;Rapid <lb/>generation of a mouse model for Middle East respiratory syndrome,&quot; Proc Natl Acad Sci <lb/>U S A, vol. 111, pp. 4970-5, Apr 1 2014. <lb/>86. X. Guo, Y. Deng, H. Chen, J. Lan, W. Wang, X. Zou, et al., &quot;Systemic and mucosal <lb/>immunity in mice elicited by a single immunization with human adenovirus type 5 or 41 <lb/>vector-based vaccines carrying the spike protein of Middle East respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus,&quot; Immunology, vol. 145, pp. 476-84, Aug 2015. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.04.934232 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
