<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Network-based Drug Repurposing for Human Coronavirus <lb/>Yadi Zhou 1,# , Yuan Hou 1,# , Jiayu Shen 1 , Yin Huang 1 , William Martin 1 , Feixiong Cheng 1-3,* <lb/>1 <lb/>Genomic Medicine Institute, Lerner Research Institute, Cleveland Clinic, Cleveland, OH <lb/>44195, USA <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Molecular Medicine, Cleveland Clinic Lerner College of Medicine, Case <lb/>Western Reserve University, Cleveland, OH 44195, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Case Comprehensive Cancer Center, Case Western Reserve University School of <lb/>Medicine, Cleveland, Oh 44106, USA <lb/># <lb/>Equal contribution <lb/>*Correspondence to: <lb/>Feixiong Cheng, PhD <lb/>Lerner Research Institute <lb/>Cleveland Clinic <lb/>Tel: +1-216-444-7654; Fax: +1-216-636-0009 <lb/>Email: chengf@ccf.org <lb/>. <lb/>CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Human Coronaviruses (HCoVs), including severe acute respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus (SARS-CoV), Middle east respiratory syndrome coronavirus (MERS-CoV), <lb/>and 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV), lead global epidemics with high morbidity and <lb/>mortality. However, there are currently no effective drugs targeting 2019-nCoV. Drug <lb/>repurposing, represented as an effective drug discovery strategy from existing drugs, <lb/>could shorten the time and reduce the cost compared to de novo drug discovery. In this <lb/>study, we present an integrative, antiviral drug repurposing methodology implementing <lb/>a systems pharmacology-based network medicine platform, quantifying the interplay <lb/>between the HCoV-host interactome and drug targets in the human protein-protein <lb/>interaction network. Phylogenetic analyses of 15 HCoV whole genomes reveal that <lb/>2019-nCoV has the highest nucleotide sequence identity with SARS-CoV (79.7%) <lb/>among the six other known pathogenic HCoVs. Specifically, the envelope and <lb/>nucleocapsid proteins of 2019-nCoV are two evolutionarily conserved regions, having <lb/>the sequence identities of 96% and 89.6%, respectively, compared to SARS-CoV. <lb/>Using network proximity analyses of drug targets and known HCoV-host interactions in <lb/>the human protein-protein interactome, we computationally identified 135 putative <lb/>repurposable drugs for the potential prevention and treatment of HCoVs. In addition, we <lb/>prioritized 16 potential anti-HCoV repurposable drugs (including melatonin, <lb/>mercaptopurine, and sirolimus) that were further validated by enrichment analyses of <lb/>drug-gene signatures and HCoV-induced transcriptomics data in human cell lines. <lb/>Finally, we showcased three potential drug combinations (including sirolimus plus <lb/>dactinomycin, mercaptopurine plus melatonin, and toremifene plus emodin) captured by <lb/></front>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>the &apos;Complementary Exposure&apos; pattern: the targets of the drugs both hit the HCoV-host <lb/>subnetwork, but target separate neighborhoods in the human protein-protein <lb/>interactome network. In summary, this study offers powerful network-based <lb/>methodologies for rapid identification of candidate repurposable drugs and potential <lb/>drug combinations toward future clinical trials for HCoVs. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Coronaviruses (CoVs) typically affect the respiratory tract of mammals, including <lb/>humans, and lead to mild to severe respiratory tract infections [1] . In the past 2 decades, <lb/>two highly pathogenic human CoVs (HCoVs), including severe acute respiratory <lb/>syndrome coronavirus (SARS-CoV) and Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus <lb/>(MERS-CoV), emerging from animal reservoirs, have led to global epidemics with high <lb/>morbidity and mortality [2] . For example, 8,098 individuals were infected and 774 died in <lb/>the SARS-CoV pandemic, which cost the global economy with an estimated $30 to <lb/>$100 billion [3, 4] . According to the World Health Organization (WHO), as of November <lb/>2019, MERS-CoV has had a total of 2,494 diagnosed cases causing 858 deaths, the <lb/>majority in Saudi Arabia [2] . In December 2019, the third pathogenic HCoV, named 2019 <lb/>novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV), was found in Wuhan, China. As of February 02, 2020, <lb/>there have been over 14,000 cases with ~300 deaths for the 2019-nCoV pandemic <lb/>(https://www.cdc.gov/coronavirus/2019-ncov/index.html); furthermore, human-to-human <lb/>transmission has occurred among close contacts [5] . However, there are currently no <lb/>effective medications against 2019-nCoV. Several national and international research <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>groups are working on the development of vaccines to prevent and treat the 2019-<lb/>nCoV, but effective vaccines are not available yet. There is an urgent need for the <lb/>development of effective prevention and treatment strategies for 2019-nCoV outbreak. <lb/>Although investment in biomedical and pharmaceutical research and <lb/>development has increased significantly over the past two decades, the annual number <lb/>of new treatments approved by the U.S. Food and Drug Administration (FDA) has <lb/>remained relatively constant and limited [6] . A recent study estimated that pharmaceutical <lb/>companies spent $2.6 billion in 2015, up from $802 million in 2003, in the development <lb/>of an FDA-approved new chemical entity drug [7] . Drug repurposing, represented as an <lb/>effective drug discovery strategy from existing drugs, could significantly shorten the time <lb/>and reduce the cost compared to de novo drug discovery and randomized clinical <lb/>trials [8-10] . However, experimental approaches for drug repurposing is costly and time-<lb/>consuming. [11] Computational approaches offer novel testable hypotheses for <lb/>systematic drug repositioning [8-10, 12, 13] . However, traditional structure-based methods <lb/>are limited when three-dimensional (3D) structures of proteins are unavailable, which, <lb/>unfortunately, is the case for the majority of human and viral targets. In addition, <lb/>targeting single virus proteins often have high risk of drug resistance by the rapid <lb/>evolution of virus genomes [1] . <lb/>Viruses (including HCoV) require host cellular factors for successful replication <lb/>during infections [1] . Systematic identification of virus-host protein-protein interactions <lb/>(PPIs) offers an effective way toward elucidation of the mechanisms of viral infection [14, <lb/> 15] <lb/>. Subsequently, targeting cellular antiviral targets, such as virus-host interactome, <lb/>may offer a novel strategy for the development of effective treatments for viral <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>infections [1] , including SARS-CoV [16] , MERS-CoV [16] , Ebola virus [17] , and Zika virus [13, 18-<lb/>20] <lb/>. We recently presented an integrated antiviral drug discovery pipeline that <lb/>incorporated gene-trap insertional mutagenesis, known functional drug-gene network, <lb/>and bioinformatics analyses [13] . This methodology allows to identify several candidate <lb/>repurposable drugs for Ebola virus [10, 13] . Our work over the last decade has <lb/>demonstrated how network strategies can, for example, be used to identify effective <lb/>repurposable drugs [12, 21-24] and drug combinations [25] for multiple human diseases. For <lb/>example, network-based drug-disease proximity that sheds light on the relationship <lb/>between drugs (e.g., drug targets) and disease modules (molecular determinants in <lb/>disease pathobiology modules within the PPIs), and can serve as a useful tool for <lb/>efficient screening of potentially new indications for approved drugs, as well as drug <lb/>combinations, as demonstrated in our recent studies [12, 22, 25] . <lb/>In this study, we present an integrative, antiviral drug repurposing methodology <lb/>that combines a systems pharmacology-based network medicine platform that <lb/>quantifies the interplay between the virus-host interactome and drug targets in the <lb/>human PPI network. The basis for these experiments rests on the notions that (i) the <lb/>proteins that functionally associate with viral infection (including HCoV) are localized in <lb/>the corresponding subnetwork within the comprehensive human PPI network [26] ; and (ii) <lb/>proteins that serve as drug targets for a specific disease may also be suitable drug <lb/>targets for potential antiviral infection owing to common PPIs and functional pathways <lb/>elucidated by the human interactome (Figure 1). We follow this analysis with <lb/>bioinformatics validation of drug-induced gene signatures and HCoV-induced <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>transcriptomics in human cell lines to inspect the postulated mechanism-of-action in a <lb/>specific HCoV for which we propose repurposing (Figure 1). <lb/>Results <lb/>Phylogenetic Analyses of 2019-nCoV <lb/>To date, 7 pathogenic HCoVs (Figure 2A and 2B) have been found [1, 27] : (i) 2019-nCoV, <lb/>SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, HCoV-OC43, and HCoV-HKU1 are b genera, and (ii) HCoV-<lb/>NL63 and HCoV-229E are a genera. We performed the phylogenetic analyses using the <lb/>whole genome sequence data from 15 HCoVs to inspect the evolutionary relationship of <lb/>2019-nCoV with other HCoVs. We found that the whole genomes of 2019-nCoV had <lb/>~99.99% nucleotide sequence identity across three diagnosed patients (Supplementary <lb/>Table S1). The 2019-nCoV shares the highest nucleotide sequence identity (79.7%) <lb/>with SARS-CoV among the 6 other known pathogenic HCoVs, revealing conserved <lb/>evolutionary relationship between 2019-nCoV and SARS-CoV (Figure 2A). <lb/>HCoVs have five major protein regions for virus structure assembly and viral <lb/>replications [27] , including replicase complex (ORF1ab), spike (S), envelope (E), <lb/>membrane (M), and nucleocapsid (N) proteins (Figure 2B). The ORF1ab gene encodes <lb/>the non-structural proteins (nsp) of viral RNA synthesis complex through proteolytic <lb/>processing [28] . The nsp12 is a viral RNA-dependent RNA polymerase, together with co-<lb/>factors nsp7 and nsp8 possessing high polymerase activity. From the protein three-<lb/>dimensional (3D) structure view of SARS-CoV nsp12, it contains a larger N-terminal <lb/>extension (which binds to nsp7 and nsp8) and polymerase domain (Figure 2C). The <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>spike is a transmembrane glycoprotein that plays a pivotal role in mediating viral <lb/>infection through binding the host receptor [29, 30] . Figure 2D shows the 3D structure of <lb/>the spike protein bound with the host receptor angiotensin converting enznyme2 (ACE2) <lb/>in SARS-CoV (PDB ID: 6ACK). A recent study showed that 2019-nCoV is able to utilize <lb/>ACE2 as an entry receptor in ACE2-expressing cells [31] , suggesting potential drug <lb/>targets for therapeutic development. In addition, the nucleocapsid is also an important <lb/>subunit for packaging the viral genome through protein oligomerization [32] , and the <lb/>single nucleocapsid structure was shown in Figure 2E. <lb/>Protein sequence alignment analyses indicated that the 2019-nCoV was most <lb/>evolutionarily conserved with SARS-CoV (Supplementary Table S2). Specifically, the <lb/>envelope and nucleocapsid proteins of 2019-nCoV are two evolutionarily conserved <lb/>regions, with sequence identities of 96% and 89.6%, respectively, compared to SARS-<lb/>CoV (Supplementary Table S2). However, the spike protein exhibited the lowest <lb/>sequence conservation (sequence identity of 77%) between 2019-nCoV and SARS-<lb/>CoV. Meanwhile, the spike protein of 2019-nCoV only has 31.9% sequence identity <lb/>compared to MERS-CoV. <lb/>HCoV-host Interactome Network <lb/>First, we assembled the CoV-associated host proteins from 4 known HCoVs (SARS-<lb/>CoV, MERS-CoV, HCoV-229E, and HCoV-NL63), one mouse MHV, and one avian IBV <lb/>(N protein) (Supplementary Table S3). In total, we obtained 119 host proteins <lb/>associated with CoVs with various experimental evidences. Specifically, these host <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>proteins are either the direct targets of HCoV proteins or are involved in crucial <lb/>pathways of HCoV infection. The HCoV-host interactome network is shown in Figure <lb/>3A. We identified several hub proteins including JUN, XPO1, NPM1, and HNRNPA1, <lb/>with the highest number of connections within the 119 proteins. KEGG pathway <lb/>enrichment analysis revealed multiple significant biological pathways (adjusted P value <lb/>&lt; 0.05), including measles, RNA transport, NF-kappa B signaling, Epstein-Barr virus <lb/>infection, and influenza (Figure 3B). Gene ontology (GO) biological process enrichment <lb/>analyses further confirmed multiple viral infection-related processes (adjusted P value &lt; <lb/>0.001), including viral life cycle, modulation by virus of host morphology or physiology, <lb/>viral process, positive regulation of viral life cycle, transport of virus, and virion <lb/>attachment to host cell (Figure 3C). We then mapped the known drug-target network <lb/>(see Methods) into the HCoV-host interactome to search for druggable, cellular targets. <lb/>We found that 47 human proteins (39%, blue nodes in Figure 3A) can be targeted by at <lb/>least one approved drug or experimental drug under clinical trial. For example, GSK3B, <lb/>DPP4, SMAD3, PARP1, and IKBKB are the most targetable proteins. The high <lb/>druggability of HCoV-host interactome motivates us to develop a therapeutic strategy by <lb/>specifically targeting cellular proteins associated with HCoVs, such as drug repurposing. <lb/>Network-based Drug Repurposing for HCoVs <lb/>The basis for the proposed network-based drug repurposing methodologies rests on the <lb/>notions that the proteins that associate with and functionally govern a viral infection are <lb/>localized in the corresponding subnetwork (Figure 1A) within the comprehensive <lb/>human interactome network. For a drug with multiple targets to be effective against an <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>HCoV, its target proteins should be within or in the immediate vicinity of the <lb/>corresponding subnetwork in the human interactome (Figure 1), as we demonstrated in <lb/>multiple diseases [12, 21, 22, 25] using this drug repurposing strategy. We used a state-of-<lb/>the-art network proximity measure to quantify the relationship between HCoV-specific <lb/>subnetwork (Figure 3A) and drug targets in the human protein-protein interactome. We <lb/>constructed a drug-target network by assembling target information for more than 2,000 <lb/>FDA-approved or experimental drugs (see Methods). To improve the quality and <lb/>completeness of the human protein interactome network, we integrated PPIs with five <lb/>types of experimental data: (1) binary PPIs from 3D protein structures; (2) binary PPIs <lb/>from unbiased high-throughput yeast-two-hybrid assays; (3) experimentally identified <lb/>kinase-substrate interactions; (4) signaling networks derived from experimental data; <lb/>and (5) literature-derived PPIs with various experimental evidences (see Methods). We <lb/>used a Z-score (Z) measure and permutation test to reduce the study bias in network <lb/>proximity analyses (including hub nodes in the human interactome network by literature-<lb/>derived PPI data bias) as described in our recent studies [12, 25] . <lb/>In total, we computationally identified 135 drugs that were associated (Z &lt; -1.5 <lb/>and P &lt; 0.05, permutation test) with the HCoV-host interactome (Figure 4A and <lb/>Supplementary Table S4). To validate bias of the pooled cellular proteins from 6 CoVs, <lb/>we further calculated the network proximities of all the drugs for 4 CoVs with a high <lb/>enough number of know host proteins, including SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, IBV, and <lb/>MHV, separately. We found that the Z-scores showed consistency among the pooled <lb/>119 HCoV-associated proteins and other 4 individual CoVs (Figure 4B). The Pearson <lb/>correlation coefficients of the proximities of all the drugs for the pooled HCoV are 0.926 <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>vs. SARS-CoV (P &lt; 0.001, t distribution), 0.503 vs. MERS-CoV (P &lt; 0.001), 0.694 vs. <lb/>IBV (P &lt; 0.001), and 0.829 vs. MHV (P &lt; 0.001). These network proximity analyses <lb/>offer putative repurposable candidates for potential prevention and treatment of HCoVs. <lb/>Discovery of Repurposable Drugs for HCoV <lb/>To further validate the 135 repurposable drugs against HCoVs, we first performed gene <lb/>set enrichment analysis (GSEA) using transcriptome data of MERS-CoV and SARS-<lb/>CoV infected host cells (see Methods). These transcriptome data were used as gene <lb/>signatures for HCoVs. Additionally, we downloaded the expression data of drug-treated <lb/>human cell lines from the Connectivity Map (CMAP) database [33] to obtain drug-gene <lb/>signatures. We calculated a GSEA score (see Methods) for each drug and used this <lb/>score as an indication of bioinformatics validation of the 135 drugs. Specifically, an <lb/>enrichment score (ES) was calculated for each HCoV data set, and ES &gt; 0 and P &lt; 0.05 <lb/>(permutation test) was used as cut-off for a significant association of gene signatures <lb/>between a drug and a specific HCoV. The GSEA score, ranging from 0 to 3, is the <lb/>number of data sets that met these criteria for a specific drug. Mesalazine (an approved <lb/>drug for inflammatory bowel disease), sirolimus (an approved immunosuppressive <lb/>drug), and equilin (an approved agonist of the estrogen receptor for menopausal <lb/>symptoms) achieved the highest GSEA scores of 3, followed by paroxetine and <lb/>melatonin with GSEA scores of 2. We next selected 16 potential repurposable drugs <lb/>(Figure 5A and Table 1) against HCoVs using subject matter expertise based on a <lb/>combination of factors: (i) strength of the network-predicted associations (a smaller <lb/>network proximity score in Supplementary Table S4); (ii) validation by GSEA analyses; <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>(iii) literature-reported antiviral evidences, and (iv) fewer clinically reported side effects. <lb/>Specifically, we showcased several selected repurposable drugs with literature-reported <lb/>antiviral evidences as below. <lb/>Selective estrogen receptor modulators (SERMs). An overexpression of <lb/>estrogen receptor has been shown to play a crucial role in inhibiting viral replication [34] . <lb/>SERMs have been reported to play a broader role in inhibiting viral replication through <lb/>the non-classical pathways associated with estrogen receptor [34] . SERMs interfere at the <lb/>post viral entry step and affect the triggering of fusion, as the SERMs&apos; antiviral activity <lb/>still can be observed in the absence of detectable estrogen receptor expression [17] . <lb/>Toremifene (Z = -3.23, Figure 5A), the first generation of nonsteroidal SERM, exhibits <lb/>potential effects in blocking various viral infections, including MERS-CoV, SARS-CoV, <lb/>and Ebola virus in established cell lines [16, 35] . Interestingly, different from the classical <lb/>ESR1-related antiviral pathway, toremifene prevents fusion between the viral and <lb/>endosomal membrane by interacting with and destabilizing the virus membrane <lb/>glycoprotein, and eventually inhibiting viral replication [36] . As shown in Figure 5B, <lb/>toremifene potentially affects several key host proteins associated with HCoV, such as <lb/>RPL19, HNRNPA1, NPM1, EIF3I, EIF3F, and EIF3E [37, 38] . Equilin (Z = -2.52 and GSEA <lb/>score = 3), an estrogenic steroid produced by horses, also has been proven to have <lb/>moderate activity in inhibiting the entry of Zaire Ebola virus-glycoprotein and human <lb/>immunodeficiency virus (ZEBOV-GP/HIV) [17] . Altogether, network-predicted SERMs <lb/>(such as toremifene and equilin) offer potential repurposable candidates for HCoVs. <lb/>Angiotensin receptor blockers (ARBs). ARBs have been reported to associate <lb/>with viral infection, including HCoVs [39-41] . Irbesartan (Z = -5.98), a typical ARB, was <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>approved by the FDA for treatment of hypertension and diabetic nephropathy. Here, <lb/>network proximity analysis shows a significant association between Irbesartan&apos;s targets <lb/>and HCoV-associated host proteins in the human interactome. As shown in Figure 5C, <lb/>irbesartan targets SLC10A1, encoding the sodium/bile acid cotransporter (NTCP) <lb/>protein that has been identified as a functional preS1-specific receptor for the hepatitis <lb/>B virus (HBV) and the hepatitis delta virus (HDV). Irbesartan can inhibit NTCP, thus <lb/>inhibiting viral entry [42, 43] . SLC10A1 interacts with C11orf74, a potential transcriptional <lb/>repressor that interacts with nsp-10 of SARS-CoV [44] . There are several other ARBs <lb/>(such as eletriptan, frovatriptan, and zolmitriptan) in which their targets are potentially <lb/>associated with HCoV-associated host proteins in the human interactome. <lb/>Immunosuppressant or antineoplastic agents. Previous studies have <lb/>confirmed the mammalian target of rapamycin complex 1 (mTORC1) as the key factor <lb/>in regulating various viruses&apos; replications, including Andes orthohantavirus and <lb/>coronavirus [45, 46] . Sirolimus (Z = -2.35 and GSEA score = 3), an inhibitor of mammalian <lb/>target of rapamycin (mTOR), was reported to effectively block viral protein expression <lb/>and virion release effectively [47] . Indeed, the latest study revealed the clinical <lb/>application: sirolimus reduced MERS-CoV infection by over 60% [48] . Moreover, sirolimus <lb/>usage in managing patients with severe H1N1 pneumonia and acute respiratory failure <lb/>can improve those patients&apos; prognosis significantly [47] . Mercaptopurine (Z = -2.44 and <lb/>GSEA score = 1), an antineoplastic agent with immunosuppressant property, has been <lb/>used to treat cancer since the 1950s and expanded its application to several auto-<lb/>immune diseases, including rheumatoid arthritis, systemic lupus erythematosus, and <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease [49] . Mercaptopurine has been reported as a selective inhibitor of both <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV by targeting papain-like protease which plays key roles in <lb/>viral maturation and antagonism to interferon stimulation [50, 51] . Mechanistically, <lb/>mercaptopurine potentially target several host proteins in HCoVs, such as JUN, <lb/>PABPC1, NPM1, and NCL [37, 52] (Figure 5D). <lb/>Anti-inflammatory agents. Inflammatory pathways play essential roles in viral <lb/>infections [53, 54] . As a biogenic amine, melatonin (N-acetyl-5-methoxytryptamine) (Z = -<lb/>1.72 and GSEA score = 2) plays a key role in various biological processes, and offers a <lb/>potential strategy in the management of viral infections [55, 56] . Viral infections are often <lb/>associated with immune-inflammatory injury, in which the level of oxidative stress <lb/>increases significantly and leaves negative effects on multiple organ functions [57] . The <lb/>antioxidant effect of melatonin makes it a putative candidate drug to relieve patients&apos; <lb/>clinical symptoms in antiviral treatment, even though melatonin cannot eradicate or <lb/>even curb the viral replication or transcription [58, 59] . In addition, the application of <lb/>melatonin may prolong patients&apos; survival time, which may provide a chance for patients&apos; <lb/>immune systems to recover and eventually eradicate the virus. As shown in Figure 5E, <lb/>melatonin indirectly targets several HCoV cellular targets, including ACE2, BCL2L1, <lb/>JUN, and IKBKB. Eplerenone (Z = -1.59), an aldosterone receptor antagonist, is <lb/>reported to have a similar anti-inflammatory effect as melatonin. By inhibiting mast-cell-<lb/>derived proteinases and suppressing fibrosis, eplerenone can improve survival of mice <lb/>infected with encephalomyocarditis virus [60] . <lb/>In summary, our network proximity analyses offer multiple putative repurposable <lb/>drugs that target diverse cellular pathways for potential prevention and treatment of <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>HCoVs. However, further preclinical experiments and clinical trials are required to verify <lb/>the clinical benefits of these network-predicted candidates before clinical use. <lb/>Network-based Identification of Potential Drug Combinations for HCoV <lb/>Drug combinations, offering increased therapeutic efficacy and reduced toxicity, play an <lb/>important role in treating various viral infections [61] . However, our ability to identify and <lb/>validate effective combinations is limited by a combinatorial explosion, driven by both <lb/>the large number of drug pairs and dosage combinations. In our recent study, we <lb/>proposed a novel network-based methodology to identify clinically efficacious drug <lb/>combinations [25] . Relying on approved drug combinations for hypertension and cancer, <lb/>we found that a drug combination was therapeutically effective only if it was captured by <lb/>the &apos;Complementary Exposure&apos; pattern: the targets of the drugs both hit the disease <lb/>module, but target separate neighborhoods (Figure 6A). Here we sought to identify <lb/>drug combinations that may provide a synergistic effect in treating HCoVs with well-<lb/>defined mechanism-of-action by network analysis. For the 16 potential repurposable <lb/>drugs (Figure 5A), we showcased three network-predicted candidate drug <lb/>combinations in the potential treatment of HCoVs. <lb/>Sirolimus plus Dactinomycin. Sirolimus, an inhibitor of mTOR with both <lb/>antifungal and antineoplastic properties, has demonstrated to improves outcomes in <lb/>patients with severe H1N1 pneumonia and acute respiratory failure [47] . The mTOR <lb/>signaling plays an essential role for MERS-CoV infection [62] . Dactinomycin, also known <lb/>actinomycin D, is an approved RNA synthesis inhibitor for treatment of various cancer <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>types. An early study showed that dactinomycin (1 microgram/ml) inhibited the growth of <lb/>feline enteric CoV [63] . As shown in Figure 6B, our network analysis shows that sirolimus <lb/>and dactinomycin synergistically target HCoV-associated host protein subnetwork by <lb/>&apos;Complementary Exposure&apos; pattern, offering potential combination regimens for <lb/>treatment of HCoV. Specifically, sirolimus and dactinomycin may inhibit both mTOR <lb/>signaling and RNA synthesis pathway (including DNA topoisomerase 2-alpha (TOP2A) <lb/>and DNA topoisomerase 2-beta (TOP2B)) in HCoV infected cells (Figure 6B). <lb/>Toremifene plus Emodin. Toremifene is the approved first generation <lb/>nonsteroidal SERMs for the treatment of metastatic breast cancer [64] . SERMs (including <lb/>toremifene) inhibited Ebola virus infection [17] by interacting with and destabilizing the <lb/>Ebola virus glycoprotein [36] . In vitro assays have demonstrated that toremifene inhibited <lb/>growth of MERS-CoV [16, 65] and SARA-CoV [35] (Table 1). Emodin, an anthraquinone <lb/>derivative extracted from the roots of rheum tanguticum, have been reported to have <lb/>various anti-virus effects. Specifically, emdoin inhibited SARS-CoV associated 3a <lb/>protein [66] , and blocked an interaction between the SARS-CoV spike protein and <lb/>ACE2 [67] . Altogether, network analyses and published experimental data suggested that <lb/>combining toremifene and emdoin offered a potential therapeutic approach for HCoVs <lb/>(Figure 6C). <lb/>Mercaptopurine plus Melatonin. As shown in Figure 5A, targets of both <lb/>mercaptopurine and melatonin showed strong network proximity with HCoV-associated <lb/>host proteins in the human interactome network. Recent in vitro and in vivo studies <lb/>identified mercaptopurine as a selective inhibitor of both SARS-CoV and MERS-CoV by <lb/>targeting papain-like protease [50, 51] . Melatonin was reported in potential treatment of <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>viral infection via its anti-inflammatory and antioxidant effects [55-59] . Melatonin indirectly <lb/>regulates ACE2 expression, a key entry receptor involved in viral infection of HCoVs, <lb/>including 2019-nCoV [31] . JUN, also known as c-Jun, is a key host protein involving in <lb/>HCoV infectious bronchitis virus [68] . As shown in Figure 6D, mercaptopurine and <lb/>melatonin may synergistically block c-Jun signaling by targeting multiple cellular targets. <lb/>In summary, combination of mercaptopurine and melatonin may offer a potential <lb/>combination therapy for 2019-nCoV by synergistically targeting papain-like protease, <lb/>ACE2, c-Jun signaling, and anti-inflammatory pathways (Figure 6D). However, further <lb/>experimental and clinical validations are highly warranted. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we presented a network-based methodology for systematic identification of <lb/>putative repurposable drugs and drug combinations for potential treatment of HCoV. <lb/>Integration of drug-target networks, HCoV-host interactions, HCoV-induced <lb/>transcriptome in human cell lines, and human protein-protein interactome network are <lb/>essential for such identification. Based on comprehensive evaluation, we prioritized 16 <lb/>putative repurposable drugs (Figure 5) and 3 putative drug combinations (Figure 6) for <lb/>the potential treatment of HCoVs, including 2019-nCoV. However, all network-predicted <lb/>repurposable drugs and drug combinations must be validated in preclinical models and <lb/>randomized clinical trials before being used in patients. <lb/>We acknowledge several limitations in our current study. In this study, we used a <lb/>low binding affinity value of 10 µM as a threshold to define a physical drug-target <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>interaction. However, a stronger binding affinity threshold (e.g., 1µM) may be a more <lb/>suitable cut-off in drug discovery, although it will generate a smaller drug-target network. <lb/>Although sizeable efforts were made for assembling large-scale, experimentally <lb/>reported drug-target networks from publicly available databases, the network data may <lb/>be incomplete and some drug-protein interactions may be functional associations, <lb/>instead of physical bindings. We may use computational approaches to systematically <lb/>predict the drug-target interactions further [24, 69] . In addition, the collected virus-host <lb/>interactions are far from complete and the quality can be influenced by multiple factors, <lb/>including different experimental assays and human cell line models. We may <lb/>computationally predict a new virus-host interactome for HCoVs using sequence-based <lb/>and structure-based approaches [70] . The current systems pharmacology model cannot <lb/>separate therapeutic antiviral effects from those predictions due to lack of detailed <lb/>pharmacological effects of drug targets and unknown functional consequences of virus-<lb/>host interactions. Drug targets representing nodes within cellular networks are often <lb/>intrinsically coupled with both therapeutic and adverse profiles [71] , as drugs can inhibit or <lb/>activate protein functions (including antagonists versus agonists). Comprehensive <lb/>identification of the virus-host interactome for 2019-nCoV, with specific biological effects <lb/>using functional genomics assays [72, 73] , will significantly improve the accuracy of current <lb/>network-based methodologies. <lb/>Owing to lack of the complete drug target information (such as the molecular <lb/>&apos;promiscuity&apos; of drugs), the dose-response and dose-toxicity effects for both <lb/>repurposable drugs and drug combinations cannot be identified in current network <lb/>models. For example, Mesalazine, an approved drug for inflammatory bowel disease, is <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>a top network-predicted candidate drug (Figure 5A) associated with HCoVs. Yet, <lb/>several clinical studies showed the potential pulmonary toxicities (including pneumonia) <lb/>associated with mesalazine usage [74, 75] . Preclinical studies are warranted to evaluate in <lb/>vivo efficiency and side effects before clinical trials. Furthermore, we only limited to <lb/>predict pairwise drug combinations based on our previous network-based framework [25] . <lb/>However, we expect that our methodology reminds to be a useful network-based tools <lb/>for prediction of combining multiple drugs toward exploring network relationships of <lb/>multiple drugs&apos; targets with the HCoV-host subnetwork in the human interactome. <lb/>Finally, we aimed to systematically identify repurposable drugs by specifically targeting <lb/>nCoV host proteins only. Thus, our current network models cannot predict repurposable <lb/>drugs from the existing anti-virus drugs that target virus proteins only. Thus, <lb/>combination of the existing anti-virus drugs (such as remdesivir [76] ) with the network-<lb/>predicted repurposable drugs (Figure 5) or drug combinations (Figure 6) may improve <lb/>coverage of current network-based methodologies by utilizing multi-layer network <lb/>framework. <lb/>In conclusion, this study offers a powerful, integrated network-based systems <lb/>pharmacology methodology for rapid identification of repurposable drugs and drug <lb/>combinations for the potential treatment of HCoV. Our approach can minimize the <lb/>translational gap between preclinical testing results and clinical outcomes, which is a <lb/>significant problem in the rapid development of efficient treatment strategies for the <lb/>emerging 2019-nCoV outbreak. From a translational perspective, if broadly applied, the <lb/>network tools developed here could help develop effective treatment strategies for other <lb/>types of virus and human diseases as well. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods and Materials <lb/>Genome Information and Phylogenetic analysis <lb/>In total, we collected DNA sequences and protein sequences for 15 HCoVs, including <lb/>three most recent 2019-nCoV genomes, from the NCBI GenBank database (January <lb/>28, 2019, Supplementary Table S1). Whole genome alignment and protein sequence <lb/>identity calculation were performed by Multiple Sequence Alignment in EMBL-EBI <lb/>database with default parameters. The neighbor joining (NJ) tree was computed from <lb/>the pairwise phylogenetic distance matrix using MEGA X [77] with 1000 bootstrap <lb/>replicates. The protein alignment and phylogenetic tree of HCoVs were constructed by <lb/>MEGA X. <lb/>Building the Virus-Host Interactome <lb/>We collected HCoV-host protein interactions from various literatures based on our <lb/>sizeable efforts. The HCoV-associated host proteins of several HCoVs, including SARS-<lb/>CoV, MERS-CoV, IBV, MHV, HCoV-229E, and HCoV-NL63 were pooled. These <lb/>proteins were either the direct targets of HCoV proteins or were involved in critical <lb/>pathways of HCoV infection identified by multiple experimental sources, including high <lb/>throughput yeast-two-hybrid (Y2H) systems, viral protein pull-down assay, in vitro co-<lb/>immunoprecipitation and RNA knock down experiment. In total, the virus-host <lb/>interaction network included 6 HCoVs with 119 host proteins (Supplementary Table <lb/>S3). <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Functional Enrichment Analysis <lb/>Next, we performed Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) and Gene <lb/>Ontology (GO) enrichment analyses to evaluate the biological relevance and functional <lb/>pathways of the HCoV-associated proteins. All functional analyses were performed <lb/>using Enrichr [78] . <lb/>Building the Drug-Target Network <lb/>Here, we collected drug-target interaction information from the DrugBank database <lb/>(v4.3) [79] , Therapeutic Target Database (TTD) [80] , PharmGKB database, ChEMBL <lb/>(v20) [81] , BindingDB [82] , and IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY [83] . The chemical <lb/>structure of each drug with SMILES format was extracted from DrugBank [79] . Here, only <lb/>drug-target interactions meeting the following three criteria were used: (i) binding <lb/>affinities, including Ki, Kd, IC50 or EC50 each ≤ 10 μM; (ii) the target was marked as <lb/>&apos;reviewed&apos; in the UniProt database [84] ; and (iii) the human target was represented by a <lb/>unique UniProt accession number. The details for building the experimentally validated <lb/>drug-target network are provided in our recent study [12] . <lb/>Building the Human Protein-Protein Interactome <lb/>To build a comprehensive list of human PPIs, we assembled data from a total of 18 <lb/>bioinformatics and systems biology databases with five types of experimental <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>evidences: (i) Binary PPIs tested by high-throughput yeast-two-hybrid (Y2H) systems; <lb/>(ii) Binary, physical PPIs from protein three-dimensional (3D) structures; (iii) Kinase-<lb/>substrate interactions by literature-derived low-throughput or high-throughput <lb/>experiments; (iv) Signaling network by literature-derived low-throughput experiments; <lb/>and (v) Literature-curated PPIs identified by affinity purification followed by mass <lb/>spectrometry (AP-MS), Y2H, or by literature-derived low-throughput experiments. All <lb/>inferred data, including evolutionary analysis, gene expression data, and metabolic <lb/>associations, were excluded. The genes were mapped to their Entrez ID based on the <lb/>NCBI database [85] as well as their official gene symbols based on GeneCards <lb/>(https://www.genecards.org/). In total, the resulting human protein-protein interactome <lb/>used in this study includes 351,444 unique PPIs (edges or links) connecting 17,706 <lb/>proteins (nodes), representing a 50% increase in the number of the PPIs we have used <lb/>previously. Detailed descriptions for building the human protein-protein interactome are <lb/>provided in our previous studies [12, 86, 87] . <lb/>Network Proximity Measure <lb/>We posit that the human PPIs provide an unbiased, rational roadmap for repurposing <lb/>drugs for potential treatment of HCoVs in which they were not originally approved. <lb/>Given , the set of host genes associated with a specific HCoV, and , the set of drug <lb/>targets, we computed the network proximity of with the target set of each drug using <lb/>the &quot;closest&quot; method: <lb/>〈 %&amp; 〉 = <lb/>) <lb/>*|%|*,‖&amp;‖ <lb/>.∑ <lb/>3∈&amp; <lb/>5∈% <lb/>( , ) + ∑ <lb/>5∈% <lb/>3∈&amp; <lb/>( , )&lt; <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>where ( , ) is the shortest distance between gene and in the human protein <lb/>interactome. The network proximity was converted to Z-score based on permutation <lb/>tests: <lb/>&gt; ?@ = <lb/>&gt; ?@ A&gt; B <lb/>CCCC <lb/>D B <lb/>(2) <lb/>where E <lb/>CCC and E were the mean and standard deviation of the permutation test repeated <lb/>1,000 times, each time with two randomly selected gene lists with similar degree <lb/>distributions to those of and . The corresponding P value was calculated based on <lb/>the permutation test results. Z-score &lt; -1.5 and P &lt; 0.05 were considered significantly <lb/>proximal drug-HCoV associations. All networks were visualized using Gephi 0.9.2 <lb/>(https://gephi.org/). <lb/>Network-based Rational Design of Drug Combination Prediction <lb/>For this network-based approach for drug combinations to be effective, we need to <lb/>establish if the topological relationship between two drug-target modules reflects <lb/>biological and pharmacological relationships, while also quantifying their network-based <lb/>relationship between drug-targets and HCoV-associated host proteins (drug-drug-HCoV <lb/>combinations). To identify potential drug combinations, we combined the top lists of <lb/>drugs. Then, &quot;separation&quot; measure HI was calculated for each pair of drugs and <lb/>using the following method: <lb/>HI = 〈 HI 〉 − <lb/>〈&gt; MM 〉,〈&gt; NN 〉 <lb/>O <lb/>(3) <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>where 〈 • 〉 was calculated based on the &quot;closest&quot; method. Our key methodology is that a <lb/>drug combination is therapeutically effective only if it follows a specific relationship to <lb/>the disease module, as captured by Complementary Exposure patterns in targets&apos; <lb/>modules of both drugs without overlapping toxic mechanisms. [25] <lb/>Gene Set Enrichment Analysis <lb/>We performed the gene set enrichment analysis as an additional prioritization method. <lb/>We first collected three differential gene expression data sets of hosts infected by <lb/>HCoVs from the NCBI Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO). Among them, two <lb/>transcriptome data sets were SARS-CoV infected samples from patient&apos;s peripheral <lb/>blood [88] (GSE1739) and Calu-3 cells [89] (GSE33267) respectively. One transcriptome <lb/>data set was MERS-CoV infected Calu-3 cells [90] (GSE122876). Adjusted P value less <lb/>than 0.01 was defined as differentially expressed genes. These data sets were used as <lb/>HCoV host signatures to evaluate the treatment effects of drugs. Differential gene <lb/>expression in cells treated with various drugs were retrieved from the Connectivity Map <lb/>(CMAP) database [33] , and were used as gene profiles for the drugs. For each drug that <lb/>was in both the CMAP data set and our drug-target network, we calculated an <lb/>enrichment score (ES) for each HCoV signature data set based on previously described <lb/>methods [91] as follows: <lb/>= R ST − &gt;UVW , <lb/>( ST ) ≠ <lb/>( &gt;UVW ) <lb/>0, <lb/>(4) <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>ST and &gt;UVW were calculated separately for the up-and down-regulated genes from <lb/>the HCoV signature data set using the same method. We first computed ST/&gt;UVW and <lb/>ST/&gt;UVW as: <lb/>= max <lb/>)dedf <lb/>g <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>− <lb/>h(e) <lb/>E <lb/>i <lb/>(5) <lb/>= max <lb/>)dedf <lb/>g <lb/>h(e) <lb/>E <lb/>− <lb/>eA) <lb/>f <lb/>i <lb/>(6) <lb/>where = 1,2, ⋯ , were the genes of HCoV signature data set sorted in ascending <lb/>order by their rank in the gene profiles of the drug being evaluated. The rank of gene <lb/>is denoted by ( ), where 1 ≤ ( ) ≤ , with being the number of genes (12,849) from <lb/>the drug profile. Then, ST/&gt;UVW was set to ST/&gt;UVW if ST/&gt;UVW &gt; ST/&gt;UVW , and was <lb/>set to − ST/&gt;UVW if ST/&gt;UVW &gt; ST/&gt;UVW . Permutation tests repeated 100 times using <lb/>randomly generated gene lists with the same number of up-and down-regulated genes <lb/>as the HCoV signature data set were performed to measure the significance of the ES <lb/>scores. Drugs were considered to have potential treatment effect if ES &gt; 0 and P &lt; 0.05, <lb/>and the number of such HCoV signature data sets were used as the final GSEA score <lb/>that ranges from 0 to 3. &quot;NA&quot; indicates that the drug cannot be evaluated by this method <lb/>due to the lack of the drug profile. <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>F.C. conceived the study. Y.Z. and Y.H. developed the network methodology and <lb/>performed all computational experiments. J.S., Y.Z., Y.H., Y.H., and W.M. performed <lb/>data analysis. F.C., Y.Z. and Y.H. and J.S. wrote and critically revised the manuscript <lb/>with contributions from other co-authors. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests: The content of this publication does not necessarily reflect <lb/>the views of the Cleveland Clinic. The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data and Code Availability: All codes and predicted repurposable drugs can be <lb/>freely accessed at: https://github.com/ChengF-Lab/2019-nCoV <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Zumla A, Chan JF, Azhar EI, Hui DS, Yuen KY. Coronaviruses -drug discovery and <lb/>therapeutic options. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2016; 15(5):327-47. doi: 10.1038/nrd.2015.37. <lb/>2. <lb/>Paules CI, Marston HD, Fauci AS. Coronavirus Infections-More Than Just the Common <lb/>Cold. JAMA. 2020. doi: 10.1001/jama.2020.0757. <lb/>3. <lb/>de Wit E, van Doremalen N, Falzarano D, Munster VJ. SARS and MERS: recent insights <lb/>into emerging coronaviruses. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2016; 14(8):523-34. doi: <lb/>10.1038/nrmicro.2016.81. <lb/>4. <lb/>de Wilde AH, Snijder EJ, Kikkert M, van Hemert MJ. Host Factors in Coronavirus <lb/> Replication. Curr Top Microbiol Immunol. 2018; 419:1-42. doi: 10.1007/82_2017_25. <lb/>5. <lb/>Li Q, Guan X, Wu P, Wang X, Zhou L, Tong Y, Ren R, Leung KSM, Lau EHY, Wong JY, <lb/>Xing X, Xiang N, Wu Y, Li C, Chen Q, Li D, Liu T, Zhao J, Li M, Tu W, Chen C, Jin L, Yang R, <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Wang Q, Zhou S, Wang R, Liu H, Luo Y, Liu Y, Shao G, Li H, Tao Z, Yang Y, Deng Z, Liu B, Ma <lb/>Z, Zhang Y, Shi G, Lam TTY, Wu JTK, Gao GF, Cowling BJ, Yang B, Leung GM, Feng Z. Early <lb/>transmission dynamics in Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus-infected pneumonia. N Engl J <lb/>Med. 2020. doi: 10.1056/NEJMoa2001316. <lb/>6. <lb/>Greene JA, Loscalzo J. Putting the patient back together -Social medicine, network <lb/>medicine, and the limits of reductionism. N Engl J Med. 2017; 377(25):2493-9. doi: <lb/>10.1056/NEJMms1706744. <lb/>7. <lb/>Avorn J. The $2.6 billion pill--methodologic and policy considerations. N Engl J Med. <lb/>2015; 372(20):1877-9. doi: 10.1056/NEJMp1500848. <lb/>8. <lb/>Cheng F. In silico oncology drug repositioning and polypharmacology. Methods Mol Biol. <lb/>2019; 1878:243-61. doi: 10.1007/978-1-4939-8868-6_15. <lb/>9. <lb/>Cheng F, Hong H, Yang S, Wei Y. Individualized network-based drug repositioning <lb/>infrastructure for precision oncology in the panomics era. Brief Bioinform. 2017; 18(4):682-97. <lb/>doi: 10.1093/bib/bbw051. <lb/>10. <lb/>Cheng F, Murray JL, Rubin DH. Drug repurposing: New treatments for Zika virus <lb/>infection? Trends Mol Med. 2016; 22(11):919-21. doi: 10.1016/j.molmed.2016.09.006. <lb/>11. <lb/>Santos R, Ursu O, Gaulton A, Bento AP, Donadi RS, Bologa CG, Karlsson A, Al-<lb/>Lazikani B, Hersey A, Oprea TI, Overington JP. A comprehensive map of molecular drug <lb/>targets. Nat Rev Drug Discov. 2017; 16(1):19-34. doi: 10.1038/nrd.2016.230. <lb/>12. <lb/>Cheng F, Desai RJ, Handy DE, Wang R, Schneeweiss S, Barabasi AL, Loscalzo J. <lb/>Network-based approach to prediction and population-based validation of in silico drug <lb/>repurposing. Nat Commun. 2018; 9(1):2691. doi: 10.1038/s41467-018-05116-5. <lb/>13. <lb/>Cheng F, Murray JL, Zhao J, Sheng J, Zhao Z, Rubin DH. Systems biology-based <lb/>investigation of cellular antiviral drug targets identified by gene-trap insertional mutagenesis. <lb/>PLoS Comput Biol. 2016; 12(9):e1005074. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005074. <lb/>14. <lb/>Yang S, Fu C, Lian X, Dong X, Zhang Z. Understanding human-virus protein-protein <lb/>interactions using a human protein complex-based analysis framework. mSystems. 2019; 4(2). <lb/>doi: 10.1128/mSystems.00303-18. <lb/> 15. <lb/>Liu C, Ma Y, Zhao J, Nussinov R, Zhang Y, Cheng F, Zhang Z. Computational network <lb/>biology: Data, models, and applications. DOI: 10.1016/j.physrep.2019.12.004. Physics Reports. <lb/>2020. <lb/>16. <lb/>Dyall J, Coleman CM, Hart BJ, Venkataraman T, Holbrook MR, Kindrachuk J, Johnson <lb/>RF, Olinger GG, Jr., Jahrling PB, Laidlaw M, Johansen LM, Lear-Rooney CM, Glass PJ, <lb/>Hensley LE, Frieman MB. Repurposing of clinically developed drugs for treatment of Middle <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>East respiratory syndrome coronavirus infection. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014; <lb/>58(8):4885-93. doi: 10.1128/AAC.03036-14. <lb/>17. <lb/>Johansen LM, Brannan JM, Delos SE, Shoemaker CJ, Stossel A, Lear C, Hoffstrom BG, <lb/>Dewald LE, Schornberg KL, Scully C, Lehar J, Hensley LE, White JM, Olinger GG. FDA-<lb/>approved selective estrogen receptor modulators inhibit Ebola virus infection. Sci Transl Med. <lb/>2013; 5(190):190ra79. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3005471. <lb/>18. <lb/>He S, Lin B, Chu V, Hu Z, Hu X, Xiao J, Wang AQ, Schweitzer CJ, Li Q, Imamura M, <lb/>Hiraga N, Southall N, Ferrer M, Zheng W, Chayama K, Marugan JJ, Liang TJ. Repurposing of <lb/>the antihistamine chlorcyclizine and related compounds for treatment of hepatitis C virus <lb/>infection. Sci Transl Med. 2015; 7(282):282ra49. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3010286. <lb/>19. <lb/>Barrows NJ, Campos RK, Powell ST, Prasanth KR, Schott-Lerner G, Soto-Acosta R, <lb/>Galarza-Munoz G, McGrath EL, Urrabaz-Garza R, Gao J, Wu P, Menon R, Saade G, <lb/>Fernandez-Salas I, Rossi SL, Vasilakis N, Routh A, Bradrick SS, Garcia-Blanco MA. A Screen <lb/>of FDA-Approved Drugs for Inhibitors of Zika Virus Infection. Cell Host Microbe. 2016; <lb/>20(2):259-70. doi: 10.1016/j.chom.2016.07.004. <lb/>20. <lb/>Xu M, Lee EM, Wen Z, Cheng Y, Huang WK, Qian X, Tcw J, Kouznetsova J, Ogden SC, <lb/>Hammack C, Jacob F, Nguyen HN, Itkin M, Hanna C, Shinn P, Allen C, Michael SG, Simeonov <lb/>A, Huang W, Christian KM, Goate A, Brennand KJ, Huang R, Xia M, Ming GL, Zheng W, Song <lb/>H, Tang H. Identification of small-molecule inhibitors of Zika virus infection and induced neural <lb/>cell death via a drug repurposing screen. Nat Med. 2016; 22(10):1101-7. doi: 10.1038/nm.4184. <lb/>21. <lb/>Cheng F, Liu C, Jiang J, Lu W, Li W, Liu G, Zhou W, Huang J, Tang Y. Prediction of <lb/>drug-target interactions and drug repositioning via network-based inference. PLoS Comput Biol. <lb/>2012; 8(5):e1002503. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1002503. <lb/>22. <lb/>Cheng F, Lu W, Liu C, Fang J, Hou Y, Handy DE, Wang R, Zhao Y, Yang Y, Huang J, <lb/>Hill DE, Vidal M, Eng C, Loscalzo J. A genome-wide positioning systems network algorithm for <lb/>in silico drug repurposing. Nat Commun. 2019; 10(1):3476. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-10744-6. <lb/>23. <lb/>Zeng X, Zhu S, Liu X, Zhou Y, Nussinov R, Cheng F. deepDR: a network-based deep <lb/>learning approach to in silico drug repositioning. Bioinformatics. 2019; 35(24):5191-8. doi: <lb/>10.1093/bioinformatics/btz418. <lb/>24. <lb/>Zeng X, Zhu S, Lu W, Liu Z, Huang J, Zhou Y, Hou Y, Huang Y, Guo H, Fang J, Liu M, <lb/>Trapp D, Li L, Nussinov R, Eng C, Loscalzo J, Cheng F. Target identification among known <lb/>drugs by deep learning from heterogeneous networks. Chemical Science. 2019; DOI: <lb/>10.1039/C9SC04336E. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>25. <lb/>Cheng F, Kovacs IA, Barabasi AL. Network-based prediction of drug combinations. Nat <lb/>Commun. 2019; 10(1):1197. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-09186-x. <lb/>26. <lb/>Menche J, Sharma A, Kitsak M, Ghiassian SD, Vidal M, Loscalzo J, Barabasi AL. <lb/>Disease networks. Uncovering disease-disease relationships through the incomplete <lb/>interactome. Science. 2015; 347(6224):1257601. doi: 10.1126/science.1257601. <lb/>27. <lb/>Forni D, Cagliani R, Clerici M, Sironi M. Molecular Evolution of Human Coronavirus <lb/>Genomes. Trends Microbiol. 2017; 25(1):35-48. doi: 10.1016/j.tim.2016.09.001. <lb/>28. <lb/>Kirchdoerfer RN, Ward AB. Structure of the SARS-CoV nsp12 polymerase bound to <lb/>nsp7 and nsp8 co-factors. Nat Commun. 2019; 10(1):2342. doi: 10.1038/s41467-019-10280-3. <lb/>29. <lb/>Li F, Li W, Farzan M, Harrison SC. Structure of SARS Coronavirus Spike Receptor-<lb/>Binding Domain Complexed with Receptor. Science. 2005; 309(5742):1864-8. doi: <lb/>10.1126/science.1116480. <lb/>30. <lb/>Lu R, Zhao X, Li J, Niu P, Yang B, Wu H, Wang W, Song H, Huang B, Zhu N, Bi Y, Ma <lb/>X, Zhan F, Wang L, Hu T, Zhou H, Hu Z, Zhou W, Zhao L, Chen J, Meng Y, Wang J, Lin Y, <lb/>Yuan J, Xie Z, Ma J, Liu WJ, Wang D, Xu W, Holmes EC, Gao GF, Wu G, Chen W, Shi W, Tan <lb/>W. Genomic characterisation and epidemiology of 2019 novel coronavirus: implications for virus <lb/>origins and receptor binding. The Lancet. 2020. doi: 10.1016/s0140-6736(20)30251-8. <lb/>31. <lb/>Zhou P, Yang X, Wang X, Hu B, Zhang L, Zhang W, Si H, Zhu Y, Li B, Huang C, Chen <lb/>H, Chen J, Luo Y, Guo H, Jiang R, Liu M, Chen Y, Shen X, Wang X, Zheng X, Zhao K, Chen Q, <lb/>Deng F, Liu L, Yan B, Zhan F, Wang Y, Xiao G, Shi Z. Discovery of a novel coronavirus <lb/>associated with the recent pneumonia outbreak in humans and its potential bat origin. 2020, <lb/>bioRxiv available: https://www.biorxiv.org/content/10.1101/2020.01.22.914952v2.full.pdf. <lb/>32. <lb/>Chang CK, Chen CM, Chiang MH, Hsu YL, Huang TH. Transient oligomerization of the <lb/>SARS-CoV N protein--implication for virus ribonucleoprotein packaging. PLoS One. 2013; <lb/>8(5):e65045. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0065045. <lb/>33. <lb/>Lamb J, Crawford ED, Peck D, Modell JW, Blat IC, Wrobel MJ, Lerner J, Brunet JP, <lb/>Subramanian A, Ross KN, Reich M, Hieronymus H, Wei G, Armstrong SA, Haggarty SJ, <lb/>Clemons PA, Wei R, Carr SA, Lander ES, Golub TR. The Connectivity Map: using gene-<lb/>expression signatures to connect small molecules, genes, and disease. Science. 2006; <lb/>313(5795):1929-35. doi: 10.1126/science.1132939. <lb/>34. <lb/>Lasso G, Mayer SV, Winkelmann ER, Chu T, Elliot O, Patino-Galindo JA, Park K, <lb/>Rabadan R, Honig B, Shapira SD. A Structure-Informed Atlas of Human-Virus Interactions. Cell. <lb/>2019; 178(6):1526-41.e16. doi: 10.1016/j.cell.2019.08.005. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>35. <lb/>de Wilde AH, Jochmans D, Posthuma CC, Zevenhoven-Dobbe JC, van Nieuwkoop S, <lb/>Bestebroer TM, van den Hoogen BG, Neyts J, Snijder EJ. Screening of an FDA-approved <lb/>compound library identifies four small-molecule inhibitors of Middle East respiratory syndrome <lb/>coronavirus replication in cell culture. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2014; 58(8):4875-84. doi: <lb/>10.1128/AAC.03011-14. <lb/>36. <lb/>Zhao Y, Ren J, Harlos K, Jones DM, Zeltina A, Bowden TA, Padilla-Parra S, Fry EE, <lb/>Stuart DI. Toremifene interacts with and destabilizes the Ebola virus glycoprotein. Nature. 2016; <lb/>535(7610):169-72. doi: 10.1038/nature18615. <lb/>37. <lb/>Emmott E, Munday D, Bickerton E, Britton P, Rodgers MA, Whitehouse A, Zhou EM, <lb/>Hiscox JA. The cellular interactome of the coronavirus infectious bronchitis virus nucleocapsid <lb/>protein and functional implications for virus biology. J Virol. 2013; 87(17):9486-500. doi: <lb/>10.1128/JVI.00321-13. <lb/>38. <lb/>V&apos;Kovski P, Gerber M, Kelly J, Pfaender S, Ebert N, Braga Lagache S, Simillion C, <lb/>Portmann J, Stalder H, Gaschen V, Bruggmann R, Stoffel MH, Heller M, Dijkman R, Thiel V. <lb/>Determination of host proteins composing the microenvironment of coronavirus replicase <lb/>complexes by proximity-labeling. Elife. 2019; 8. doi: 10.7554/eLife.42037. <lb/>39. <lb/>Moskowitz DW, Johnson FE. The central role of angiotensin I-converting enzyme in <lb/>vertebrate pathophysiology. Curr Top Med Chem. 2004; 4(13):1433-54. doi: <lb/>10.2174/1568026043387818. <lb/>40. <lb/>Seko Y. Effect of the angiotensin II receptor blocker olmesartan on the development of <lb/>murine acute myocarditis caused by coxsackievirus B3. Clin Sci (Lond). 2006; 110(3):379-86. <lb/>doi: 10.1042/CS20050299. <lb/>41. <lb/>Erlandson KM, Kitch D, Wester CW, Kalayjian RC, Overton ET, Castillo-Mancilla J, <lb/>Koletar SL, Benson CA, Campbell TB, Robertson K, Lok JJ. The Impact of Statin and <lb/>Angiotensin-Converting Enzyme Inhibitor/Angiotensin Receptor Blocker Therapy on Cognitive <lb/>Function in Adults With Human Immunodeficiency Virus Infection. Clin Infect Dis. 2017; <lb/>65(12):2042-9. doi: 10.1093/cid/cix645. <lb/>42. <lb/>Wang XJ, Hu W, Zhang TY, Mao YY, Liu NN, Wang SQ. Irbesartan, an FDA approved <lb/>drug for hypertension and diabetic nephropathy, is a potent inhibitor for hepatitis B virus entry by <lb/>disturbing Na(+)-dependent taurocholate cotransporting polypeptide activity. Antiviral Res. <lb/>2015; 120:140-6. doi: 10.1016/j.antiviral.2015.06.007. <lb/>43. <lb/>Ko C, Park WJ, Park S, Kim S, Windisch MP, Ryu WS. The FDA-approved drug <lb/>irbesartan inhibits HBV-infection in HepG2 cells stably expressing sodium taurocholate co-<lb/>transporting polypeptide. Antivir Ther. 2015; 20(8):835-42. doi: 10.3851/IMP2965. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>44. <lb/>Hong M, Li W, Wang L, Jiang L, Liu L, Zhao H, Li Q. Identification of a novel <lb/>transcriptional repressor (HEPIS) that interacts with nsp-10 of SARS coronavirus. Viral <lb/>Immunol. 2008; 21(2):153-62. doi: 10.1089/vim.2007.0108. <lb/>45. <lb/>McNulty S, Flint M, Nichol ST, Spiropoulou CF. Host mTORC1 signaling regulates andes <lb/>virus replication. J Virol. 2013; 87(2):912-22. doi: 10.1128/jvi.02415-12. <lb/>46. <lb/>Stohr S, Costa R, Sandmann L, Westhaus S, Pfaender S, Anggakusuma, Dazert E, <lb/>Meuleman P, Vondran FW, Manns MP, Steinmann E, von Hahn T, Ciesek S. Host cell <lb/>mTORC1 is required for HCV RNA replication. Gut. 2016; 65(12):2017-28. doi: 10.1136/gutjnl-<lb/>2014-308971. <lb/>47. <lb/>Wang CH, Chung FT, Lin SM, Huang SY, Chou CL, Lee KY, Lin TY, Kuo HP. Adjuvant <lb/>treatment with a mammalian target of rapamycin inhibitor, sirolimus, and steroids improves <lb/>outcomes in patients with severe H1N1 pneumonia and acute respiratory failure. Crit Care Med. <lb/>2014; 42(2):313-21. doi: 10.1097/CCM.0b013e3182a2727d. <lb/>48. <lb/>Dyall J, Gross R, Kindrachuk J, Johnson RF, Olinger GG, Jr., Hensley LE, Frieman MB, <lb/>Jahrling PB. Middle East Respiratory Syndrome and Severe Acute Respiratory Syndrome: <lb/>Current Therapeutic Options and Potential Targets for Novel Therapies. Drugs. 2017; <lb/>77(18):1935-66. doi: 10.1007/s40265-017-0830-1. <lb/>49. <lb/>Karran P, Attard N. Thiopurines in current medical practice: molecular mechanisms and <lb/>contributions to therapy-related cancer. Nat Rev Cancer. 2008; 8(1):24-36. doi: <lb/>10.1038/nrc2292. <lb/>50. <lb/>Chen X, Chou CY, Chang GG. Thiopurine analogue inhibitors of severe acute <lb/>respiratory syndrome-coronavirus papain-like protease, a deubiquitinating and deISGylating <lb/>enzyme. Antivir Chem Chemother. 2009; 19(4):151-6. doi: 10.1177/095632020901900402. <lb/>51. <lb/>Cheng KW, Cheng SC, Chen WY, Lin MH, Chuang SJ, Cheng IH, Sun CY, Chou CY. <lb/>Thiopurine analogs and mycophenolic acid synergistically inhibit the papain-like protease of <lb/>Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus. Antiviral Res. 2015; 115:9-16. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.antiviral.2014.12.011. <lb/>52. <lb/>Chen H, Wurm T, Britton P, Brooks G, Hiscox JA. Interaction of the coronavirus <lb/>nucleoprotein with nucleolar antigens and the host cell. J Virol. 2002; 76(10):5233-50. doi: <lb/>10.1128/jvi.76.10.5233-5250.2002. <lb/>53. <lb/>Rainsford KD. Influenza (&quot;Bird Flu&quot;), inflammation and anti-inflammatory/analgesic <lb/>drugs. Inflammopharmacology. 2006; 14(1-2):2-9. doi: 10.1007/s10787-006-0002-5. <lb/>54. <lb/>Garcia CC, Guabiraba R, Soriani FM, Teixeira MM. The development of anti-<lb/>inflammatory drugs for infectious diseases. Discov Med. 2010; 10(55):479-88. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>55. <lb/>Silvestri M, Rossi GA. Melatonin: its possible role in the management of viral infections--<lb/>a brief review. Ital J Pediatr. 2013; 39:61. doi: 10.1186/1824-7288-39-61. <lb/>56. <lb/>Srinivasan V, Mohamed M, Kato H. Melatonin in bacterial and viral infections with focus <lb/>on sepsis: a review. Recent Pat Endocr Metab Immune Drug Discov. 2012; 6(1):30-9. doi: <lb/>10.2174/187221412799015317. <lb/>57. <lb/>Tan DX, Korkmaz A, Reiter RJ, Manchester LC. Ebola virus disease: potential use of <lb/>melatonin as a treatment. J Pineal Res. 2014; 57(4):381-4. doi: 10.1111/jpi.12186. <lb/>58. <lb/>Tan DX, Manchester LC, Terron MP, Flores LJ, Reiter RJ. One molecule, many <lb/>derivatives: a never-ending interaction of melatonin with reactive oxygen and nitrogen species? <lb/>J Pineal Res. 2007; 42(1):28-42. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-079X.2006.00407.x. <lb/>59. <lb/>Galano A, Tan DX, Reiter RJ. On the free radical scavenging activities of melatonin&apos;s <lb/>metabolites, AFMK and AMK. J Pineal Res. 2013; 54(3):245-57. doi: 10.1111/jpi.12010. <lb/>60. <lb/>Xiao J, Shimada M, Liu W, Hu D, Matsumori A. Anti-inflammatory effects of eplerenone <lb/>on viral myocarditis. Eur J Heart Fail. 2009; 11(4):349-53. doi: 10.1093/eurjhf/hfp023. <lb/>61. <lb/>Tan X, Hu L, Luquette LJ, 3rd, Gao G, Liu Y, Qu H, Xi R, Lu ZJ, Park PJ, Elledge SJ. <lb/>Systematic identification of synergistic drug pairs targeting HIV. Nat Biotechnol. 2012; <lb/>30(11):1125-30. doi: 10.1038/nbt.2391. <lb/>62. <lb/>Kindrachuk J, Ork B, Hart BJ, Mazur S, Holbrook MR, Frieman MB, Traynor D, Johnson <lb/>RF, Dyall J, Kuhn JH, Olinger GG, Hensley LE, Jahrling PB. Antiviral potential of ERK/MAPK <lb/>and PI3K/AKT/mTOR signaling modulation for Middle East respiratory syndrome coronavirus <lb/>infection as identified by temporal kinome analysis. Antimicrob Agents Chemother. 2015; <lb/>59(2):1088-99. doi: 10.1128/AAC.03659-14. <lb/>63. <lb/>Lewis EL, Harbour DA, Beringer JE, Grinsted J. Differential in vitro inhibition of feline <lb/>enteric coronavirus and feline infectious peritonitis virus by actinomycin D. J Gen Virol. 1992; 73 <lb/>( Pt 12):3285-8. doi: 10.1099/0022-1317-73-12-3285. <lb/>64. <lb/>Zhou WB, Ding Q, Chen L, Liu XA, Wang S. Toremifene is an effective and safe <lb/>alternative to tamoxifen in adjuvant endocrine therapy for breast cancer: results of four <lb/>randomized trials. Breast Cancer Res Treat. 2011; 128(3):625-31. doi: 10.1007/s10549-011-<lb/>1556-5. <lb/>65. <lb/>Cong Y, Hart BJ, Gross R, Zhou H, Frieman M, Bollinger L, Wada J, Hensley LE, <lb/>Jahrling PB, Dyall J, Holbrook MR. MERS-CoV pathogenesis and antiviral efficacy of licensed <lb/>drugs in human monocyte-derived antigen-presenting cells. PLoS One. 2018; 13(3):e0194868. <lb/>doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0194868. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>66. <lb/>Schwarz S, Wang K, Yu W, Sun B, Schwarz W. Emodin inhibits current through SARS-<lb/>associated coronavirus 3a protein. Antiviral Res. 2011; 90(1):64-9. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.antiviral.2011.02.008. <lb/>67. <lb/>Ho TY, Wu SL, Chen JC, Li CC, Hsiang CY. Emodin blocks the SARS coronavirus spike <lb/>protein and angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 interaction. Antiviral Res. 2007; 74(2):92-101. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.antiviral.2006.04.014. <lb/>68. <lb/>Fung TS, Liu DX. Activation of the c-Jun NH2-terminal kinase pathway by coronavirus <lb/>infectious bronchitis virus promotes apoptosis independently of c-Jun. Cell Death Dis. 2017; <lb/>8(12):3215. doi: 10.1038/s41419-017-0053-0. <lb/>69. <lb/>Zeng X, Zhu S, Hou Y, Zhang P, Li L, Li J, Huang LF, Lewis SJ, Nussinov R, Cheng F. <lb/>Network-based prediction of drug-target interactions using an arbitrary-order proximity <lb/>embedded deep forest. Bioinformatics. 2020. doi: 10.1093/bioinformatics/btaa010. <lb/>70. <lb/>Halder AK, Dutta P, Kundu M, Basu S, Nasipuri M. Review of computational methods for <lb/>virus-host protein interaction prediction: a case study on novel Ebola-human interactions. Brief <lb/>Funct Genomics. 2018; 17(6):381-91. doi: 10.1093/bfgp/elx026. <lb/>71. <lb/>Bedi O, Dhawan V, Sharma PL, Kumar P. Pleiotropic effects of statins: new therapeutic <lb/>targets in drug design. Naunyn Schmiedebergs Arch Pharmacol. 2016; 389(7):695-712. doi: <lb/>10.1007/s00210-016-1252-4. <lb/>72. <lb/>Li Q, Zhang YY, Chiu S, Hu Z, Lan KH, Cha H, Sodroski C, Zhang F, Hsu CS, Thomas <lb/>E, Liang TJ. Integrative functional genomics of hepatitis C virus infection identifies host <lb/>dependencies in complete viral replication cycle. PLoS Pathog. 2014; 10(5):e1004163. doi: <lb/>10.1371/journal.ppat.1004163. <lb/>73. <lb/>Gebre M, Nomburg JL, Gewurz BE. CRISPR-Cas9 Genetic Analysis of Virus-Host <lb/>Interactions. Viruses. 2018; 10(2). doi: 10.3390/v10020055. <lb/>74. <lb/>Kim JH, Lee JH, Koh ES, Park SW, Jang AS, Kim D, Park CS. Acute eosinophilic <lb/>pneumonia related to a mesalazine suppository. Asia Pac Allergy. 2013; 3(2):136-9. doi: <lb/>10.5415/apallergy.2013.3.2.136. <lb/>75. <lb/>Gupta A, Gulati S. Mesalamine induced eosinophilic pneumonia. Respir Med Case Rep. <lb/>2017; 21:116-7. doi: 10.1016/j.rmcr.2017.04.010. <lb/>76. <lb/>Sheahan TP, Sims AC, Leist SR, Schafer A, Won J, Brown AJ, Montgomery SA, Hogg <lb/> A, Babusis D, Clarke MO, Spahn JE, Bauer L, Sellers S, Porter D, Feng JY, Cihlar T, Jordan R, <lb/>Denison MR, Baric RS. Comparative therapeutic efficacy of remdesivir and combination <lb/>lopinavir, ritonavir, and interferon beta against MERS-CoV. Nat Commun. 2020; 11(1):222. doi: <lb/>10.1038/s41467-019-13940-6. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>77. <lb/>Kumar S, Stecher G, Li M, Knyaz C, Tamura K. MEGA X: Molecular Evolutionary <lb/>Genetics Analysis across Computing Platforms. Mol Biol Evol. 2018; 35(6):1547-9. doi: <lb/>10.1093/molbev/msy096. <lb/>78. <lb/>Kuleshov MV, Jones MR, Rouillard AD, Fernandez NF, Duan Q, Wang Z, Koplev S, <lb/>Jenkins SL, Jagodnik KM, Lachmann A, McDermott MG, Monteiro CD, Gundersen GW, <lb/>Ma&apos;ayan A. Enrichr: a comprehensive gene set enrichment analysis web server 2016 update. <lb/>Nucleic Acids Research. 2016; 44(W1):W90-W7. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkw377. <lb/>79. <lb/>Law V, Knox C, Djoumbou Y, Jewison T, Guo AC, Liu Y, Maciejewski A, Arndt D, Wilson <lb/>M, Neveu V, Tang A, Gabriel G, Ly C, Adamjee S, Dame ZT, Han B, Zhou Y, Wishart DS. <lb/>DrugBank 4.0: shedding new light on drug metabolism. Nucleic Acids Res. 2014; 42(Database <lb/>issue):D1091-7. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkt1068. <lb/>80. <lb/>Yang H, Qin C, Li YH, Tao L, Zhou J, Yu CY, Xu F, Chen Z, Zhu F, Chen YZ. <lb/>Therapeutic target database update 2016: enriched resource for bench to clinical drug target <lb/>and targeted pathway information. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016; 44(D1):D1069-74. doi: <lb/>10.1093/nar/gkv1230. <lb/>81. <lb/>Gaulton A, Bellis LJ, Bento AP, Chambers J, Davies M, Hersey A, Light Y, McGlinchey <lb/>S, Michalovich D, Al-Lazikani B, Overington JP. ChEMBL: a large-scale bioactivity database for <lb/>drug discovery. Nucleic Acids Research. 2012; 40(D1):D1100-D7. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkr777. <lb/>82. <lb/>Liu TQ, Lin YM, Wen X, Jorissen RN, Gilson MK. BindingDB: a web-accessible <lb/>database of experimentally determined protein-ligand binding affinities. Nucleic Acids Research. <lb/>2007; 35:D198-D201. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkl999. <lb/>83. <lb/>Pawson AJ, Sharman JL, Benson HE, Faccenda E, Alexander SPH, Buneman OP, <lb/>Davenport AP, McGrath JC, Peters JA, Southan C, Spedding M, Yu WY, Harmar AJ, Nc I. The <lb/>IUPHAR/BPS Guide to PHARMACOLOGY: an expert-driven knowledgebase of drug targets <lb/>and their ligands. Nucleic Acids Research. 2014; 42(D1):D1098-D106. doi: <lb/>10.1093/nar/gkt1143. <lb/>84. <lb/>Apweiler R, Bairoch A, Wu CH, Barker WC, Boeckmann B, Ferro S, Gasteiger E, Huang <lb/>HZ, Lopez R, Magrane M, Martin MJ, Natale DA, O&apos;Donovan C, Redaschi N, Yeh LSL. UniProt: <lb/>the Universal Protein knowledgebase. Nucleic Acids Research. 2004; 32:D115-D9. doi: <lb/>10.1093/nar/gkh131. <lb/>85. <lb/>Coordinators NR. Database resources of the National Center for Biotechnology <lb/> Information. Nucleic Acids Res. 2016; 44(D1):D7-19. doi: 10.1093/nar/gkv1290. <lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>86. <lb/>Cheng F, Jia P, Wang Q, Lin CC, Li WH, Zhao Z. Studying tumorigenesis through <lb/>network evolution and somatic mutational perturbations in the cancer interactome. Mol Biol <lb/>Evol. 2014; 31(8):2156-69. doi: 10.1093/molbev/msu167. <lb/>87. <lb/>Cheng F, Liu C, Lin CC, Zhao J, Jia P, Li WH, Zhao Z. A Gene Gravity Model for the <lb/>Evolution of Cancer Genomes: A Study of 3,000 Cancer Genomes across 9 Cancer Types. <lb/>PLoS Comput Biol. 2015; 11(9):e1004497. doi: 10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004497. <lb/>88. <lb/>Reghunathan R, Jayapal M, Hsu L-Y, Chng H-H, Tai D, Leung BP, Melendez AJ. <lb/>Expression profile of immune response genes in patients with Severe Acute Respiratory <lb/>Syndrome. BMC Immunology. 2005; 6(1):2. doi: 10.1186/1471-2172-6-2. <lb/>89. <lb/>Josset L, Menachery VD, Gralinski LE, Agnihothram S, Sova P, Carter VS, Yount BL, <lb/>Graham RL, Baric RS, Katze MG. Cell host response to infection with novel human coronavirus <lb/>EMC predicts potential antivirals and important differences with SARS coronavirus. mBio. 2013; <lb/>4(3):e00165-13. doi: 10.1128/mBio.00165-13. <lb/>90. <lb/>Yuan S, Chu H, Chan JF-W, Ye Z-W, Wen L, Yan B, Lai P-M, Tee K-M, Huang J, Chen <lb/>D, Li C, Zhao X, Yang D, Chiu MC, Yip C, Poon VK-M, Chan CC-S, Sze K-H, Zhou J, Chan IH-<lb/>Y, Kok K-H, To KK-W, Kao RY-T, Lau JY-N, Jin D-Y, Perlman S, Yuen K-Y. SREBP-dependent <lb/>lipidomic reprogramming as a broad-spectrum antiviral target. Nature Communications. 2019; <lb/>10(1):120. doi: 10.1038/s41467-018-08015-x. <lb/>91. <lb/>Sirota M, Dudley JT, Kim J, Chiang AP, Morgan AA, Sweet-Cordero A, Sage J, Butte AJ. <lb/> Discovery and preclinical validation of drug indications using compendia of public gene<lb/> expression data. Sci Transl Med. 2011; 3(96):96ra77. doi: 10.1126/scitranslmed.3001318.<lb/></listBibl>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Top drug candidates from network-based repurposing approach with <lb/>literature antiviral evidences. <lb/>Z-score DrugBank <lb/>ID <lb/>Drug Name <lb/>Structure <lb/>Category <lb/>Therapeutic effect on <lb/>virus <lb/>PubMed ID <lb/>-5.98 <lb/>DB01029 Irbesartan <lb/>antihypertensive <lb/>HBV, HDV <lb/>25929767, <lb/>26086883, <lb/>24717262 <lb/>-3.23 <lb/>DB00539 Toremifene <lb/>antineoplastic <lb/>EBOV, MERS-CoV, <lb/>SARS-CoV <lb/>27362232, <lb/>29566060, <lb/>24841273, <lb/>24841269 <lb/>-2.64 <lb/>DB01744 Camphor <lb/>antipruritic, anti-<lb/>infective <lb/>H1N1 <lb/>27823881, <lb/>30165308 <lb/>-2.52 <lb/>DB02187 Equilin <lb/>estrogen <lb/>ZEBOV-GP/HIV <lb/>27169275 <lb/>-2.44 <lb/>DB00244 Mesalazine <lb/>anti-inflammatory <lb/>EBV <lb/>25914477 <lb/>-2.44 <lb/>DB01033 Mercaptopurine <lb/>antimetabolite, <lb/>antineoplastic <lb/>SARS-CoV, MERS-<lb/>CoV <lb/>18313035, <lb/>19374142, <lb/>25542975 <lb/>-2.42 <lb/>DB00715 Paroxetine <lb/>selective serotonin <lb/>reuptake inhibitor <lb/>EBOV <lb/>29272110 <lb/>-2.35 <lb/>DB00877 Sirolimus <lb/>immunosuppressants ANDV, HCV <lb/>23135723, <lb/>26276683, <lb/>29143192, <lb/>24105455 <lb/>-1.94 <lb/>DB01136 Carvedilol <lb/>beta-blocker <lb/>EMCV <lb/>12535832 <lb/>-1.92 <lb/>DB01394 Colchicine <lb/>anti-inflammatory <lb/>EBV <lb/>28795759 <lb/>-1.88 <lb/>DB00970 Dactinomycin <lb/>antineoplastic <lb/>FECV <lb/>1335030 <lb/>-1.72 <lb/>DB01065 Melatonin <lb/>hormone <lb/>EBOV, RSV <lb/>25262626, <lb/>20070490 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N N <lb/>NH <lb/>N <lb/>Cl <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>HO <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>NH2 <lb/>O <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>HN <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>HN <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>-1.62 <lb/>DB01103 Quinacrine <lb/>antimalarial, antibiotic EV71, EBOV <lb/>23301007, <lb/>31307979, <lb/>27890675 <lb/>-1.59 <lb/>DB00700 Eplerenone <lb/>diuretic <lb/>viral myocarditis <lb/>19213804 <lb/>-1.54 <lb/>DB07715 Emodin <lb/>anthraquinones <lb/>HSV-1, HSV-2, HBV, <lb/>SARS-CoV, CVB₄ <lb/>21050882, <lb/>16940925, <lb/>21356245, <lb/>16730806, <lb/>24071990 <lb/>-1.53 <lb/>DB06412 Oxymetholone <lb/>anabolic steroid <lb/>HIV wasting <lb/>12815555 <lb/>-1.49 <lb/>DB02709 Resveratrol <lb/>polyphenolic <lb/>phytoalexin <lb/>MERS-CoV <lb/>29495250 <lb/>HBV, hepatitis B virus; HCV, hepatitis C virus; HDV, hepatitis delta virus; EBOV, Ebola viruses; ZEBOV-<lb/>GP, Zaire Ebola virus-glycoprotein; HIV, human immunodeficiency virus; EBV, Epstein-Barr virus; ANDV, <lb/>Andes orthohantavirus; EMCV, encephalomyocarditis virus; FECV, feline enteric coronavirus; RSV, <lb/>respiratory syncytial virus; EV71, enterovirus 71; HSV-1 and -2, Herpes simplex viruses; CVB₄, <lb/>Coxsackievirus B₄. <lb/>N <lb/>HN <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>Cl <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>HO <lb/>OH O <lb/>O <lb/>HO <lb/>HO <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>HO <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure Legends <lb/>Figure 1. Overall workflow of this study. Our network-based methodology combines <lb/>a systems pharmacology-based network medicine platform that quantifies the interplay <lb/>between the virus-host interactome and drug targets in the human PPI network. (A) <lb/>Human coronavirus (HCoV) associated host proteins were collected from literatures and <lb/>pooled to generate a pan-HCoV protein subnetwork. (B) Network proximity between <lb/>drug targets and HCoV-associated proteins was calculated to screen for candidate <lb/>repurposable drugs for HCoVs under the human protein interactome model. (C &amp; D) <lb/>Gene set enrichment analysis was utilized to validate the network-based prediction. (E) <lb/>Top candidates were further prioritized for drug combinations using network-based <lb/>method captured by the &apos;Complementary Exposure&apos; pattern: the targets of the drugs <lb/>both hit the HCoV-host subnetwork, but target separate neighborhoods in the human <lb/>interactome network. (F) Overall hypothesis of network-based methodology: (i) the <lb/>proteins that functionally associate with HCoVs are localized in the corresponding <lb/>subnetwork within the comprehensive human interactome network; and (ii) proteins that <lb/>serve as drug targets for a specific disease may also be suitable drug targets for <lb/>potential antiviral infection owing to common protein-protein interactions elucidated by <lb/>the human interactome. <lb/>Figure 2. Phylogenetic analysis of coronaviruses. (A) Phylogenetic tree of <lb/>coronavirus (CoV). Phylogenetic algorithm analyzed evolutionary conservation among <lb/>whole genomes of 15 coronaviruses. Red color highlights the recent emergent <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>coronavirus, 2019-nCoV, originating in Wuhan, China. Numbers on the branches <lb/>indicate bootstrap support values. The scale shows the evolutionary distance computed <lb/>using the p-distance method. (B) Schematic plot for HCoV genomes. The genus and <lb/>host information of viruses was labeled on the left by different colors. Empty dark gray <lb/>boxes represent accessory open reading frames (ORFs). The 3D structures of SARS-<lb/>CoV nsp12 (PDB ID: 6NUR) (C), spike (PDB ID: 6ACK) (D) and nucleocapsid (PDB ID: <lb/>2CJR) (E) shown were based on homology modeling. Genome information and <lb/>phylogenetic analysis results are provided in Supplementary Table S1-2. <lb/>Figure 3. Drug-target network analysis of the HCoV-host interactome. (A) A <lb/>subnetwork highlighting the HCoV-host interactome. Nodes represent three types of <lb/>HCoV-associated host proteins: targetgable (proteins can be targeted by approved <lb/>drugs or drugs under clinical trials), non-targetable (proteins don&apos;t have any known <lb/>ligands), neighbors (protein-protein interaction partners). Edge colors indicate five types <lb/>of experimental evidences of the protein-protein interactions (see Methods). 3D: three-<lb/>dimensional structure. (B) KEGG human pathway and (C) gene ontology enrichment <lb/>analyses for the HCoV-associated proteins. <lb/>Figure 4. A discovered drug-HCoV network. (A) A subnetwork highlighting network-<lb/>predicted drug-HCoV associations connecting 135 drugs and HCoVs. From the 2,938 <lb/>drugs evaluated, 135 ones achieved significant proximities between drug targets and <lb/>the HCoV-associated proteins in the human interactome network. Drugs are colored by <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>their first-level of the Anatomical Therapeutic Chemical (ATC) classification system <lb/>code. (B) A heatmap highlighting network proximity values for SARS-CoV, MERS-CoV, <lb/>IBV, and MHV respectively. Color key denotes network proximity (Z-score) between <lb/>drug targets and the HCoV-associated proteins in the human interactome network. P-<lb/>value was computed by permutation test. <lb/>Figure 5. A discovered drug-protein-HCoV network for 16 potential repurposable <lb/>drugs. (A) Network-predicted evidences and gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) <lb/>scores for 16 potential repurposable drugs for HCoVs. The overall connectivity of the <lb/>top drug candidates to the HCoV-associated proteins was examined. Most of these <lb/>drugs indirectly target HCoV-associated proteins via the human protein-protein <lb/>interaction networks. All the drug-target-HCoV-associated protein connections were <lb/>examined, and those proteins with at least 5 connections are shown. The box heights <lb/>for the proteins indicate the number of connections. GSEA scores for 8 drugs were not <lb/>available (NA) due to the lack of transcriptome profiles for the drugs. (B-E) Inferred <lb/>mechanism-of-action networks for four selected drugs: (B) toremifene (first generation <lb/>nonsteroidal selective estrogen receptor modulator), (C) irbesartan (an angiotensin <lb/>receptor blocker), (D) mercaptopurine (an antimetabolite antineoplastic agent with <lb/>immunosuppressant properties), and (E) melatonin (a biogenic amine for treating <lb/>circadian rhythm sleep disorders). <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Network-based rational design of drug combinations for HCoVs. (A) The <lb/>possible exposure mode of the HCoV-associated protein module to the pairwise drug <lb/>combinations. An effective drug combination will be captured by the &apos;Complementary <lb/>Exposure&apos; pattern: the targets of the drugs both hit the HCoV-host subnetwork, but <lb/>target separate neighborhoods in the human interactome network. ZCA and ZCB denote <lb/>the network proximity (Z-score) between targets (Drugs A and B) and a specific HCoV. <lb/>SAB denotes separation score (see Methods) of targets between Drug A and Drug B. (B-<lb/>D) Inferred mechanism-of-action networks for three selected pairwise drug <lb/>combinations: (B) Sirolimus (a potent immunosuppressant with both antifungal and <lb/>antineoplastic properties) plus Dactinomycin (a RNA synthesis inhibitor for treatment of <lb/>various tumors), (C) Toremifene (first generation nonsteroidal selective estrogen <lb/>receptor modulator) plus Emodin (an experimental drug for the treatment of polycystic <lb/>kidney), and (D) Melatonin (a biogenic amine for treating circadian rhythm sleep <lb/>disorders) plus Mercaptopurine (an antimetabolite antineoplastic agent with <lb/>immunosuppressant properties). <lb/></body>

			. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC 4.0 International license <lb/>It is made available under a <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>is the <lb/>(which was not peer-reviewed) <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.03.20020263 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1 <lb/>Targetable <lb/>d = <lb/>2+3 <lb/>2 <lb/>d <lb/>z = <lb/>d − μ R <lb/>σ R <lb/>μ R <lb/>σ R σ R <lb/>… <lb/>d1 <lb/>d n <lb/>… <lb/>HCoV-associated host proteins <lb/>Human interactome <lb/>Drug-target network <lb/>HCoV-associated host <lb/>protein subnetwork <lb/>Drug-induced transcriptome <lb/>Network-based drug repurposing <lb/>Network-based prediction <lb/>of drug combinations <lb/>Enrichment analysis <lb/>HCoV-induced transcriptome <lb/>HCoV-induced gene profile <lb/>Drug-induced gene profile <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>NSP12 <lb/>S <lb/>ACE2 <lb/>N <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>Binary <lb/>3D <lb/>Complex <lb/>Kinase-substrate <lb/>Signaling <lb/>Literature <lb/>Connectivity <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Targetable <lb/>Non-targetable <lb/>Neighbor <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>SARS-CoV <lb/>MERS-CoV <lb/>IBV <lb/>MHV <lb/>Alimentary tract and metabolism <lb/>Antineoplastic and immunomodulating <lb/>Antiparasitic products <lb/>Blood and blood forming organs <lb/>Cardiovascular system <lb/>Genito-urinary system &amp; sex hormones <lb/>Musculo-skeletal system <lb/>Nervous system <lb/>Respiratory system <lb/>Sensory organs <lb/>Various <lb/>Not available <lb/>Toremifene <lb/>Equilin <lb/>Irbesartan <lb/>Sirolimus <lb/>Mercaptopurine <lb/>Melatonin <lb/>Dactinomycin <lb/>Mesalazine <lb/>Oxymetholone <lb/>Quinacrine <lb/>Paroxetine <lb/>Pan-HCoV <lb/>Camphor <lb/>Carvedilol <lb/>Colchicine <lb/>The first-level of ATC code <lb/>E <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>GSEA score <lb/>Drug <lb/>Drug target <lb/>HCoV-associated protein <lb/>SARS-CoV <lb/>MERS-CoV <lb/>IBV <lb/>MHV <lb/>Shared <lb/>D <lb/>HCoV-associated protein <lb/>Drug <lb/>Drug target <lb/>HCoV-associated protein <lb/>and drug target <lb/>Figure 6 <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>HCoV-associated protein (C) <lb/>Drug A target <lb/>Drug B target <lb/>D <lb/>SAB = 0.65 <lb/>Z C A = <lb/>-2 . 3 5 <lb/>Z C B <lb/>= <lb/>-1 . 8 8 <lb/>SAB = 0.08 <lb/>Z C A = <lb/>-3 . 2 3 <lb/>Z C B <lb/>= <lb/>-1 . 5 4 <lb/>SAB = 0.24 <lb/>Z C A = <lb/>-1 . 7 2 <lb/>Z <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>= <lb/>-<lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>A a. Overlapping <lb/>b. Complementary <lb/>c. Single exposure <lb/>d. Non-exposure <lb/>ZCA &lt; 0, ZCB &lt; 0, SAB &lt; 0 <lb/>ZCA &lt; 0, ZCB &lt; 0, SAB ≥ 0 <lb/>ZCA &lt; 0, ZCB ≥ 0, SAB ≥ 0 <lb/>ZCA ≥ 0, ZCB ≥ 0, SAB ≥ 0 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
