<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>ACE2 expression by colonic epithelial cells is associated with <lb/>viral infection, immunity and energy metabolism <lb/>Jun Wang 1# , Shanmeizi Zhao 1# , Ming Liu 1 , Zhiyao Zhao 1 , Yiping Xu 2 , Ping Wang 3 , Meng Lin 1 , <lb/>Yanhui Xu 1 , Bing Huang 1 , Xiaoyu Zuo 1 , Zhanghua Chen 4 , Fan Bai 4 , Jun Cui 5 , Andrew M Lew 6 , <lb/>Jincun Zhao 1 , Yan Zhang 1* , Hai-Bin Luo 7* , and Yuxia Zhang 1,8* <lb/>1 Guangzhou Institute of Pediatrics, Guangzhou Women and Children&apos;s Medical Center, State <lb/>Key Laboratory of Respiratory Diseases, Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, 510623, <lb/>China <lb/>2 Department of Pediatric Surgery , Guangzhou women and Children&apos;s Medical Center , <lb/>Guangzhou Medical University, Guangzhou, 510623, China <lb/>3 Department of Neonatology, Guangzhou Women and Children&apos;s Medical Centre, Guangzhou <lb/>Medical University, Guangzhou, 510623, China <lb/>4 Biomedical Pioneering Innovation Center (BIOPIC), School of Life Sciences, Peking University, <lb/>Beijing, 100871, China <lb/>5 School of Life Sciences, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, 510006, China <lb/>6 Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research and Departments of Medical Biology and <lb/>Microbiology &amp; Immunology, University of Melbourne, Parkville, Melbourne, Victoria 3052, <lb/>Australia. <lb/>7 School of Pharmaceutical Science, Sun Yat-sen University, Guangzhou, Guangdong, 510006, <lb/>China <lb/>8 The Third Affiliated Hospital of Zhengzhou University, Zhengzhou, 450052, China <lb/># These authors contributed equally. <lb/>All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/>2 <lb/>*Correspondence to: <lb/>yannizy@gmail.com <lb/>luohb77@mail.sysu.edu.cn <lb/>yuxia.zhang@gwcmc.org <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Respiratory disease caused by the 2019 novel coronavirus (2019-nCoV) pneumonia first <lb/>emerged in Wuhan, Hubei Province, China, in December 2019 and spread rapidly to other <lb/>provinces and other countries. Angiotensin-converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) is the receptor for <lb/>SARS-CoV and has been suggested to be also the receptor for 2019-nCoV. Paradoxically, ACE2 <lb/>expression in the lung protects mice from SARS-CoV spike protein induced lung injury by <lb/>attenuating the renin-angiotensin system. In the intestine, ACE2 also suppresses intestinal <lb/>inflammation by maintaining amino acid homeostasis, antimicrobial peptide expression and <lb/>ecology of the gut microbiome. Upon analysis of single cell-RNA sequencing data from control <lb/>subjects and those with colitis or inflammatory bowel disease (IBD), we found that ACE2 <lb/>expression in the colonocytes was positively associated with genes regulating viral infection, <lb/>innate and cellular immunity, but was negatively associated with viral transcription, protein <lb/>translation, humoral immunity, phagocytosis and complement activation. In summary, we <lb/>suggest that ACE2 may play dual roles in mediating the susceptibility and immunity of 2019-<lb/>nCoV infection. <lb/></front>

			<body>Patients infected by 2019-nCoV can develop acute respiratory distress syndrome (ARDS) and <lb/>sepsis. However, there is mounting evidences that the gastrointestinal tract may be an alternative <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>route for 2019-nCoV infection. One (3%) of the first 41 reported cases had diarrhea [1]. In <lb/>another report describing a familial cluster, 2 of the 6 family members (33%) developed <lb/>diarrhea[2]. Furthermore, positive 2019-nCoV was detected from the stools of a patient with <lb/>loose of bowel movement in the United States [3]. <lb/>There have been many studies on the proteins associated with host entry by the SARS-CoV. <lb/>Cleavage of Spike protein by tissue factor Xa is required for the infectivity of SARS-CoV [4]. <lb/>Rivaroxaban is an oral anticoagulant used to combat acute pulmonary embolism with or without <lb/>deep-vein thrombosis [5]. As an Xa inhibitor, it may thus offer protection for 2019-nCoV <lb/>pneumonia. Angiotensin I converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) is the SARS-CoV receptor [6]. It also <lb/>has been linked to 2019-nCoV infection; ACE2 interacts with the Spike protein and mediates <lb/>2019-nCoV infection of the type II alveolar cells of the lung [7]. <lb/>Paradoxically, although ACE2 mediates viral entry to the host, its deficiency worsens lung injury <lb/>by activating the renin-angiotensin system (RAS) in experimental models [6]. The circulating <lb/>RAS regulates blood pressure and fluid homeostasis. Local tissue-based RAS exacerbates <lb/>pulmonary hypertension, acute lung injury and experimental lung fibrosis [8]. Thus, blocking of <lb/>the Angiotensin II receptor type I (AT1R) was associated with reduced SARS-CoV spike protein <lb/>mediated lung injury [6] and reduced pulmonary hypertension in experimental models [9]. The <lb/>AT1R blocker valsartan has recently been reported to improve clinical outcomes for patients <lb/>with chronic obstructive pulmonary disease (COPD) complicated with pulmonary hypertension <lb/>(DOI:10.1183/13993003.congress-2019.PA2469). In the PARADIGM-HF trial, valsartan and the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>neprilysin inhibitor prodrug sacubitril (Valsartan/sacubitril, branded Entresto by Novartis) also <lb/>significantly reduced mortality and hospitalization for patients with heart failure [10]. <lb/>Apart from the lung, ACE2 is also associated with gut function. ACE2 expression in the gut <lb/>epithelial cells is required for maintaining amino acid homeostasis, antimicrobial peptide <lb/>expression and the ecology of gut microbiome in the intestine [11, 12]. We had previously <lb/>generated a single-cell RNA sequencing dataset from control subjects and those with colitis or <lb/>IBD [13]. Using this dataset, we examined ACE2 expression and found that it was specifically <lb/>and highly expressed by the colonocytes (Figure 1 A-B). Compared with other epithelial <lb/>subtypes, colonocytes overexpressed genes regulating viral entry, budding and releasing from the <lb/>host cells (VAPA, CHMP4C, CHMP1A, CHMP2B, CHMP4B, CHMP1B, VPS37B, PDCD6IP, <lb/>VPS4B, CHMP3, VPS28, CHMP2A, PVRL2, CDH1, and MVB12A). Genes involved in nucleic <lb/>acid sensing and type I, type III interferon signaling (R2RX4, DDX58, NLRC5, IFNAR2, IFNGR1 <lb/>and IFNGR2), pro-inflammatory cytokine and chemokine (IL18, IL32, CXCL16, CXCL3, CXCL2, <lb/>CXCL1, CCL28, CCL20) production, antigen presentation via MHC class I molecules (HLA-A, <lb/>HLA-B, HLA-C, and HLA-E) and cytokine receptors (IL2G, IL10RB, and IL6R) were also <lb/>enriched in colonocytes (Figure 1C). <lb/>Given that ACE2 plays dual roles in mediating viral entry and preventing tissue injury [6, 11, 12, <lb/>14], we analyzed genes that are co-expressed with ACE2 in the colonic epithelial cells. In total, <lb/>3420 and 2136 genes were positively and negatively correlated with ACE2 expression, <lb/>respectively (Supplementary table 1 and Figure 2A). In Gene Ontology (GO) analysis, genes <lb/>positively correlated with ACE2 expression were enriched in viral infection and egress (viral <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>budding via host ESCRT complex, positive regulation of viral release from host cells, viral entry <lb/>into host cells), innate immune responses (type I interferon signaling pathway and toll-like <lb/>receptor signaling pathway), NK and T cell cytotoxicity (interferon-gamma-mediated signaling <lb/>pathway, regulation of natural killer cell mediated immunity, positive regulation of T cell <lb/>mediated cytotoxicity), energy metabolism (triglyceride biosynthetic process, pyruvate metabolic <lb/>process, NADH metabolic process, mitochondrial electron transport), inflammation and <lb/>apoptosis (positive regulation of I-kappaB kinase/NF-kappaB signaling and positive regulation <lb/>of apoptotic signaling pathway). In contrast, genes negatively correlated with ACE2 were <lb/>enriched for humoral immunity (positive regulation of B cell activation, antibacterial humoral <lb/>response, mature B cell differentiation, B cell receptor signaling pathway, immunoglobulin <lb/>production), protein translation (ribosomal big and small subunit assembly and translational <lb/>initiation), phagocytosis (Fc-epsilon receptor signaling pathway, Fc-gamma receptor signaling <lb/>pathway involved in phagocytosis, phagocytosis recognition) and classical pathway of <lb/>complement activation (Figure 2B). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Here we report the expression pattern of ACE2 in the human intestine at single-cell resolution. <lb/>Our data suggest that ACE2 is specifically expressed by colonocytes and positively associated <lb/>with viral entry and egress, consistent with observations that the gastrointestinal tract is a <lb/>potential route for 2019-nCoV infection. In supportive of the view that ACE2 expression <lb/>prevents intestinal inflammation [11, 12], bioinformatic analysis suggested that genes regulating <lb/>type I and type III innate immunity, NK and T cell mediated cytotoxicity and energy metabolism <lb/>are positively associated with ACE2 expression. By contrast, humoral immunity, phagocytosis <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>and complement activation are negatively associated with ACE2 expression. These findings may <lb/>facilitate concurrent and future investigations of the nature and function of the immune system at <lb/>systemic and local levels in patients with 2019-nCoV pneumonia. <lb/>Notably, SARS-CoV spike protein engagement downregulates ACE2 expression and activates <lb/>the RAS [6]. Given that hypertension is common in severe 2019-nCoV pneumonia [1], it is <lb/>highly likely that the RAS is activated in the lungs of patients with severe pneumonia. The Xa <lb/>inhibitor Rivaroxaban [5] and the AT1R blocker valsartan (DOI:10.1183/13993003.congress-<lb/>2019.PA2469) are effective in relieving pulmonary injury and embolism in experimental models <lb/>and clinical trials, their efficacy in treating 2019-nCoV may worth consideration. Dipyridamole <lb/>is another anti-coagulation drug. In a pilot trial, dipyridamole administration promoted mucosal <lb/>healing and improved clinical symptoms in patients with colitis or IBD [13]. More importantly, <lb/>published clinical studies [15-20], including those conducted in China (DOI: <lb/>CNKI:SUN:XIYI.0.2010-12-026;[21]; CNKI:SUN:YXLT.0.2014-32-031), have demonstrated <lb/>that dipyridamole has broad spectrum antiviral activity against virus infections. It may also be <lb/>worth investigating the therapeutic effects of dipyridamole in patients infected by 2019-nCoV. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Ethical statement <lb/>The study procedures (ID: 2017021504) were approved by the Medical Ethics Committee of <lb/>Guangzhou Women and Children&apos;s Medical Center. The implementations were in concordance <lb/>with the International Ethical Guidelines for Research Involving Human Subjects stated in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Helsinki Declaration. Informed written consents from the legal guardians of all participants were <lb/>obtained before conducting these procedures. <lb/>Single cell RNA sequencing data analysis <lb/>Colonic biopsies from 17 children (6 control, 6 colitis, 2 ulcerative colitis, 3 Crohn&apos;s disease) <lb/>were subjected to single-cell suspension preparation, 5 &apos; gene expression libraries construction, <lb/>and 10x Genomics single-cell RNA sequencing [13]. Cellranger v2.1 pipeline (10x genomics) <lb/>was utilized to demultiplex the cellular barcodes and align reads to the human transcriptome <lb/>(build GRCh38). The unique molecular identifier (UMI) count matrix was converted to Seurat <lb/>object using the R package Seurat v2.3.4 [22]. After quality control and data normalization, <lb/>dimension reduction and cell clustering were performed [13]. Different cell types were identified <lb/>by mapping canonical marker genes in the two-dimensional t-Distributed Stochastic Neighbor <lb/>embedding (tSNE) map [13]. <lb/>Co-expression analysis <lb/>Normalized single-cell RNA expression data was used for co-expression analysis. Pearson&apos;s <lb/>correlation analysis was performed between each gene in the single-cell transcriptome and ACE2. <lb/>Significantly correlated genes were chosen (p-value&lt;0.05) for downstream GO enrichment <lb/>analysis via GENEONTOLOGY at http://geneontology.org/. GO terms with False Detection <lb/>Rate (FDR) &lt;0.05 were selected. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">National Natural Sc The ience Foundation of China (91742109, 31770978, 31722003, 31770925, <lb/>31370847, 81770552), National Key Research and Development Program (2016YFC0900102), <lb/>National Science and Technology Major Project (2018ZX10302205), Guangdong Provincial Key <lb/>Laboratory of Research in Structural Birth Defect Disease (2019B030301004), Guangzhou <lb/>Women and Children&apos;s Medical Center Fund (5001-3001032) and National Health and Medical <lb/>Research Council of Australia (1037321, 1105209, 1143976, and 1080321 to A.L.) funded this <lb/>study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Yuxia.Z., H-B.L., and Yan.Z. conceived of and supervised the project. J.W. performed the <lb/>bioinformatic analysis. S.Z., M.L., Z. Z., Yiping.X, P.W, M. L., Yanhui.X., B.H., Xiaoyu.Z. and <lb/>Z.C. reviewed and discussed the manuscript. Yuxia.Z. and J.W. wrote the manuscript with <lb/>significant input from A.M.L., J.C., F.B. and All authors discussed and approved the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<body>Figures and legends <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. ACE2 was highly and specifically expressed by colonocytes. A. Left panel: two-<lb/>dimensional tSNE plot displaying major cell clusters; right panel: heatmap displaying ACE2 <lb/>expression across major cell clusters. B. Left panel: distribution of 10 epithelial sub-clusters on <lb/>the tSNE plot; right panel: heatmap showing ACE2 expression across epithelial clusters. C. <lb/>Heatmap plot showing expression of selected genes across 10 epithelial clusters. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Genes correlated with ACE2 expression in colonocytes. A. Valcano plot displaying <lb/>genes co-expressed with ACE2. B. Bar plot presenting significantly enriched GO terms obtained <lb/>from GO enrichment analysis performed with aforementioned ACE2 co-expressed genes. <lb/>Supplementary Table 1 Genes correlated with ACE2 expression. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Huang, C., et al., Clinical features of patients infected with 2019 novel coronavirus in <lb/>Wuhan, China. Lancet, 2020. <lb/>2. <lb/>Jasper Fuk-Woo Chan, S.Y., Kin-Hang Kok, Kelvin Kai-Wang To, Hin Chu, Jin Yang, <lb/>Fanfan Xing, Jieling Liu, Cyril Chik-Yan Yip, Rosana Wing-Shan Poon, Hoi-Wah Tsoi, <lb/>Simon Kam-Fai Lo, Kwok-Hung Chan, Vincent Kwok-Man Poon, Wan-Mui Chan, <lb/>Jonathan Daniel Ip, and V.C.-C.C. Jian-Piao Cai, Honglin Chen, Christopher Kim-Ming <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Hui, Kwok-Yung Yuen, A familial cluster of pneumonia associated with the 2019 novel <lb/>coronavirus indicating person-to-person transmission:a study of a family cluster. Lancet, <lb/>2020. <lb/>3. <lb/>Holshue, M.L., et al., First Case of 2019 Novel Coronavirus in the United States. N Engl <lb/>J Med, 2020. <lb/>4. <lb/>Du, L., et al., Cleavage of spike protein of SARS coronavirus by protease factor Xa is <lb/>associated with viral infectivity. Biochemical and biophysical research communications, <lb/>2007. 359(1): p. 174-179. <lb/>5. <lb/>Investigators, E.-P., et al., Oral rivaroxaban for the treatment of symptomatic pulmonary <lb/>embolism. N Engl J Med, 2012. 366(14): p. 1287-97. <lb/>6. <lb/>Kuba, K., et al., A crucial role of angiotensin converting enzyme 2 (ACE2) in SARS <lb/>coronavirus-induced lung injury. Nat Med, 2005. 11(8): p. 875-9. <lb/>7. <lb/>Chan, J.F., et al., Genomic characterization of the 2019 novel human-pathogenic <lb/>coronavirus isolated from a patient with atypical pneumonia after visiting Wuhan. Emerg <lb/>Microbes Infect, 2020. 9(1): p. 221-236. <lb/>8. <lb/>Marshall, R.P., The pulmonary renin-angiotensin system. Curr Pharm Des, 2003. 9(9): p. <lb/>715-22. <lb/>9. <lb/>Clements, R.T., et al., Treatment of Pulmonary Hypertension With Angiotensin II <lb/>Receptor Blocker and Neprilysin Inhibitor Sacubitril/Valsartan. Circ Heart Fail, 2019. <lb/>12(11): p. e005819. <lb/>10. <lb/>Hubers, S.A. and N.J. Brown, Combined Angiotensin Receptor Antagonism and <lb/>Neprilysin Inhibition. Circulation, 2016. 133(11): p. 1115-24. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>11. <lb/>Hashimoto, T., et al., ACE2 links amino acid malnutrition to microbial ecology and <lb/>intestinal inflammation. Nature, 2012. 487(7408): p. 477-81. <lb/>12. <lb/>Vuille-dit-Bille, R.N., et al., Human intestine luminal ACE2 and amino acid transporter <lb/>expression increased by ACE-inhibitors. Amino Acids, 2015. 47(4): p. 693-705. <lb/>13. <lb/>Huang, B., et al., Mucosal Profiling of Pediatric-Onset Colitis and IBD Reveals Common <lb/>Pathogenics and Therapeutic Pathways. Cell, 2019. 179(5): p. 1160-1176 e24. <lb/>14. <lb/>Ye, R. and Z. Liu, ACE2 exhibits protective effects against LPS-induced acute lung <lb/>injury in mice by inhibiting the LPS-TLR4 pathway. Exp Mol Pathol, 2019. 113: p. <lb/>104350. <lb/>15. <lb/>Tonew, E., M.K. Indulen, and D.R. Dzeguze, Antiviral action of dipyridamole and its <lb/>derivatives against influenza virus A. Acta Virol, 1982. 26(3): p. 125-9. <lb/>16. <lb/>Fata-Hartley, C.L. and A.C. Palmenberg, Dipyridamole reversibly inhibits mengovirus <lb/>RNA replication. J Virol, 2005. 79(17): p. 11062-70. <lb/>17. <lb/>Tenser, R.B., A. Gaydos, and K.A. Hay, Inhibition of herpes simplex virus reactivation <lb/>by dipyridamole. Antimicrob Agents Chemother, 2001. 45(12): p. 3657-9. <lb/>18. <lb/>Szebeni, J., et al., Dipyridamole potentiates the inhibition by 3&apos;-azido-3&apos;-deoxythymidine <lb/>and other dideoxynucleosides of human immunodeficiency virus replication in monocyte-<lb/>macrophages. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 1989. 86(10): p. 3842-6. <lb/>19. <lb/>Kozhukharova, M.S., et al., [Evaluation of dipyridamole efficacy as an agent for <lb/>preventing acute respiratory viral diseases]. Vopr Virusol, 1987. 32(3): p. 294-7. <lb/>20. <lb/>Kuzmov, K., et al., [Epidemiological trial of the prophylactic effectiveness of the <lb/>interferon inducer dipyridamole with respect to influenza and acute respiratory diseases]. <lb/>Zh Mikrobiol Epidemiol Immunobiol, 1985(6): p. 26-30. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>21. <lb/>Hu, X.Q. and X.L. wANG, Treatment of viral upper respiratory tract infection in <lb/>children with dipyridamole. Chinese Journal of Hospital Pharmacy, 1995(9). <lb/>22. <lb/>Butler, A., et al., Integrating single-cell transcriptomic data across different conditions, <lb/>technologies, and species. Nat Biotechnol, 2018. 36(5): p. 411-420. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.05.20020545 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
