<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>The reproductive number R 0 of COVID-19 based on <lb/>estimate of a statistical time delay dynamical system <lb/>Nian Shao * , Jin Cheng † , Wenbin Chen ‡ <lb/>Abstract. In this paper, we estimate the reproductive number R 0 of COVID-19 based on <lb/>Wallinga and Lipsitch framework [11] and a novel statistical time delay dynamic system. We use <lb/>the observed data reported in CCDC&apos;s paper to estimate distribution of the generation interval <lb/>of the infection and apply the simulation results from the time delay dynamic system as well as <lb/>released data from CCDC to fit the growth rate. The conclusion is: Based our Fudan-CCDC <lb/>model, the growth rate r of COVID-19 is almost in [0.30, 0.32] which is larger than the growth <lb/>rate 0.1 estimated by CCDC [9], and the reproductive number R 0 of COVID-19 is estimated by <lb/>3.25 ≤ R 0 ≤ 3.4 if we simply use R = 1 + r * T c with T c = 7.5, which is bigger than that of <lb/>SARS. Some evolutions and predictions are listed. <lb/>Key words. COVID-19; The reproductive number; Growth rate; Statistical time delay <lb/>dynamical system <lb/></front>

			<body>1 One formula for the distribution of generation interval <lb/>The serial interval distribution presented in the paper &quot;Early transmission dynamics in <lb/>Wuhan, China, of novel coronavirus-infected peneumonia&quot; [9] by the researches in Chinese Cen-<lb/>ter for Disease Control and Prevention(CCDC) et al, which is defined as the duration between <lb/>symptom onset insuccessive cases in the transmission chain in Fig.2B of [9]. We assume that <lb/>the distribution is Gamma distribution, i.e., the corresponding probability density function is <lb/>P (t) = <lb/>b n <lb/>Γ(n) <lb/>t n−1 e −bt = <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>Γ(5) <lb/>t 4 e − 2t <lb/>3 , <lb/>(1.1) <lb/>where the parameters are n = 5 and b = 2 <lb/>3 . So the mean of the distribution is n <lb/>b = 7.5 which is <lb/>exactly equal to the number announced in [9], where they claimed that the mean serial interval <lb/>of COVID-19 is 7.5 days (95% CI, 5.3 to 19). Besides the mean, comparison of (1.1) with Fig2B <lb/>is more convince. The formula is so beautiful, that we believe it must be true. The other <lb/>distributions are also given in our recent report [10]. <lb/>We think this distribution just as the one of generation interval mentioned in [11]. Now <lb/>we can determine the reproductive number R 0 of COVID-19 if we know the growth rate r of <lb/></body>

			<front> * School of Mathematical Sciences, Fudan University, 220 Handan Road, Yangpu District, Shanghai, 200433, <lb/>China, P. R. China. (16307130024@fudan.edu.cn). <lb/> † School of Mathematical Sciences and SKLCAM, Fudan University, 220 Handan Road, Yangpu District, Shang-<lb/>hai, 200433, China, P. R. China. (jcheng@fudan.edu.cn). <lb/> ‡ School of Mathematical Sciences and SKLCAM, Fudan University, 220 Handan Road, Yangpu District, Shang-<lb/>hai, 200433, China, P. R. China. (Corresponding author. wbchen@fudan.edu.cn). <lb/>1 <lb/>All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></front>

			<body>COVID-19 by <lb/>R c = 1 + rT c , <lb/>(1.2) <lb/>where T c = 7.5 can be obtained from (1.1). Before we discuss how to get the estimate of the <lb/>growth rate r of COVID-19, let us review the elegant framework by Wallinga and Lipsitch [11]. <lb/>2 Wallinga and Lipsitch&apos;s framework <lb/>According to the framework of Wallinga and Lipsitch [11], in order to obtain the reproductive <lb/>number R 0 , some variables and distributions should be known based on the data before we use <lb/>their uniform framework: <lb/>• the growth rate of the epidemic r; <lb/>• the mean generation interval of the infection T c ; <lb/>• or the generation interval distribution of the infection g(t). <lb/>We just mention that the mean generation interval T c is the first moment of the generation <lb/>interval distribution g(t): <lb/>T c = <lb/>∞ <lb/>0 <lb/>tg(t)dt. <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>If r and T c are computed, the value of the reproductive number R 0 can be simply estimated <lb/>through a linear equation([11, 1, 8, 4, 5]): <lb/>R c = 1 + rT c . <lb/>(2.2) <lb/>And if r and g(t) are estimated, R 0 can be computed as <lb/>R g = <lb/>1 <lb/>M (−r) <lb/>, <lb/>(2.3) <lb/>where M (z) is the moment generating function of the distribution g(t): <lb/>M (z) = <lb/>∞ <lb/>0 <lb/>e zt g(t)dt. <lb/>(2.4) <lb/>Wallinga and Lipstch&apos;s processes are simple but powerful, which clearly demonstrate how gener-<lb/>ation intervals shape the relationship between growth rate and reproductive number. Specially, <lb/>if g(t) is Gamma distribution with parameters (b, n) as in [11], then we can have two estimates <lb/>of R 0 , one is by (2.2) <lb/>R Γ,c = 1 + <lb/>nr <lb/>b <lb/>, <lb/>(2.5) <lb/>and the another is by (2.3) <lb/>R Γ,g = 1 + <lb/>r <lb/>b <lb/>n <lb/>. <lb/>(2.6) <lb/>Based on the formula of the generation interval, we know that b = 2 <lb/>3 and n = 5, R Γ,g will be too <lb/>sensitive on r, and we will choose (1.2) to obtain R 0 , and our main focus is to get an accurate <lb/>and stable estimate for the growth rate r. The modified second order approximation to (2.6) is <lb/>also important and has been widely used[11, 6]. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>In [11], Wallinga and Lipsitch point out that if the epidemic model is assumed to be <lb/>susceptible-exposed-infectious-recovered(SEIR) model, then the generation interval distribution <lb/>is Gamma distribution. <lb/>So we can obtain our first conclusion. <lb/>Conjecture 2.1. The epidemic model for COVID-19 is SEIR if CCDC&apos;s data are correct. <lb/>The above conclusion may be interpreted by that CCDC assumed that the epidemic model <lb/>should be SEIR. <lb/>Now we introduce how we can estimate the growth rate r. <lb/>3 Fudan-CCDC model <lb/>Our group has developed some models for the growth rate of COVID-19 (TDD-NCP models <lb/>[2, 13] and Fudan-CCDC models[10]) after Jin suggested to use the time delay model to fit the <lb/>real data [2]. Because of the outstanding agreement with data from CCDC and the estimations <lb/>on the growth rate are very stable, we decide to use the following Fudan-CCDC model. Other <lb/>models also work very well to fit the CCDC data. <lb/>Firstly, Let us introduce some variables: <lb/>• I(t): (the distribution of) the cumulative number of cases in the infected stage at time t; <lb/>• J(t): (the distribution of) the cumulative ones in hospitalization stage at time t; <lb/>• G(t): (the distribution of) the number of infected and isolated but yet diagnosed cases at <lb/>time t. They are infected in fact, but are not confirmed by the hospital, then not appeared <lb/>in the infected list of CCDC; <lb/>• I 0 (t): I 0 (t) = I(t) − J(t) − G(t). <lb/>We further make some assumptions on the transition probability functions f 2 (t), f 3 (t) and f 4 (t): <lb/>• f 2 (t): the transition probability from infection to illness onset; <lb/>• f 3 (t): the transition probability from illness onset to hospitalization; <lb/>• f 4 (t): the transition probability from infection to hospitalization, which can be calculated <lb/>via the convolution of f 2 (t) and f 3 (t). <lb/>We assume the log-normal distribution for f 2 (t) and the Weibull distrubution for f 3 (t)[10], <lb/>and the distribution parameters can be estimated from CCDC by fitting the figures in [9]. In <lb/>particular, two important parameters are used: <lb/>• β: denotes the growth rate, which is exactly the same as r: β = r. <lb/>• : denotes the quarantine strategy, for example, specially, we consider this parameter as <lb/>the isolation rate. Large value of suggests that the government more likes to control the <lb/>spreading of COVID-19. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Now we introduce our Fudan-CCDC model: I(t), J(t) and G(t) can be approximated by the <lb/>following (statistical) dynamical system: <lb/>dI <lb/>dt <lb/>= rI 0 (t), <lb/>(3.1) <lb/>dJ <lb/>dt <lb/>= r <lb/>t <lb/>−∞ <lb/>f 4 (t − s)I 0 (s)ds, <lb/>(3.2) <lb/>dG <lb/>dt <lb/>= (t) <lb/>t <lb/>−∞ <lb/>f 2 (t − s)I 0 (s)ds − (t) <lb/>t <lb/>−∞ <lb/>f 4 (t − s)I 0 (s)ds. <lb/>(3.3) <lb/>One can also use the discrete system with each step representing one day just as we have <lb/>implemented in the code: <lb/>I(t + 1) = I(t) + rI 0 (t), <lb/>(3.4) <lb/>J(t + 1) = J(t) + r <lb/>s≤t <lb/>f 4 (t − s)I 0 (s), <lb/>(3.5) <lb/>G(t + 1) = G(t) + (t) <lb/>s≤t <lb/>f 2 (t − s)I 0 (s) − (t) <lb/>s≤t <lb/>f 4 (t − s)I 0 (s). <lb/>(3.6) <lb/>We will fit and estimate appropriate values of β(or r) and based on the cumulative diagnosed <lb/>data from CCDC. Other versions of our Fudan-CCDC model are developing, specially, we are <lb/>considering the stochastic version: that is to take random inputs into account, which is important <lb/>to account for the influences from other regions. In math, we can easily generalize the model <lb/>by random terms such as Brownian motion in the system, meanwhile the parameters have to be <lb/>obtained from the real data. The another important version is to consider the interactions of <lb/>two or more regions, Jin&apos;s group have developed some models based on TTD-NCP model[3, 7]. <lb/>These models will also be developed in need of disease control and prevention. <lb/>The simulation is implemented via Matlab with some additional constraints imposed. Here <lb/>the results are summarized in Table 1 with the real data employed up to Feb 16, 2020. <lb/>Table 1: The growth rate r and the reproductive number R 0 <lb/>r(first strategy) <lb/>R 0 <lb/>r(second strategy) <lb/>R 0 <lb/>Wuhan <lb/>0.2830 <lb/>3.1225 <lb/>0.3100 <lb/>3.3250 <lb/>Hubei(without Wuhan) <lb/>0.2692 <lb/>3.0190 <lb/>0.3166 <lb/>3.3745 <lb/>China(without Hubei) <lb/>0.2720 <lb/>3.0400 <lb/>0.3122 <lb/>3.3415 <lb/>Beijing <lb/>0.3012 <lb/>3.2590 <lb/>0.3038 <lb/>3.2785 <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>0.2995 <lb/>3.2462 <lb/>0.3082 <lb/>3.3115 <lb/>In the Table 1, we use two kind of quarantine strategies introduced below. We are surprised <lb/>that our code can get uniform estimators on the growth rate r and the reproductive number R 0 . <lb/>Two quarantine strategy: We can observe that is distinct for different time stages at the <lb/>different regions. Now we assume two quarantine strategies, one uses the following assumption: <lb/>= <lb/>0 if t &lt; t <lb/>0 otherwise, <lb/>(3.7) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>and one can use another strategy <lb/>= <lb/>1 if t &lt; t <lb/>2 otherwise, <lb/>(3.8) <lb/>which means that the quarantine strategy was observably changed at the day t . We report the <lb/>results in Table 2. <lb/>Table 2: The isolation rate and the changed point t <lb/>0 <lb/>t <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>t <lb/>Wuhan <lb/>0.4300 Jan. 20 0.0964 0.4927 Jan. 20 <lb/>Hubei(without Wuhan) 0.5291 Jan. 20 0.1717 0.5996 Jan. 20 <lb/>China(without Hubei) <lb/>0.8044 Jan. 20 0.1477 0.8584 Jan. 20 <lb/>Beijing <lb/>0.5824 Jan. 16 0.0126 0.5861 Jan. 16 <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>0.6189 Jan. 16 0.0432 0.6299 Jan. 16 <lb/>We also find that for the Diamond Princes Cruise Ship is β = 0.3182, 1 = 0, 2 = 0.3239. <lb/>Moreover, the results from the model imply the case in the Diamond Princes Cruise Ship may be <lb/>very DANGEROUS, since below one key THRESHOLD, where the number of the infected <lb/>persons will growth quickly. We also very worry about the situations in Japan. We WARN <lb/>here that every CDC in every country should track the number of the infected persons, and <lb/>immediately increase to one suitable level. <lb/>Starting date t 0 : Our model can also track the initial date of the event t 0 if I(t 0 ) is fixed. <lb/>It is REALLY important to find the initial starting date statistically correct in different regions. <lb/>Table 3: The initial infections I(t 0 ) and the estimated initial date t 0 <lb/>parameter I(t 0 ) t 0 (first strategy) t 0 (second strategy) <lb/>Wuhan <lb/>4 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>Hubei(without Wuhan) <lb/>4 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>China(without Hubei) <lb/>4 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>Dec. 19 <lb/>Beijing <lb/>1 <lb/>Dec. 30 <lb/>Dec. 28 <lb/>Shanghai <lb/>1 <lb/>Dec. 30 <lb/>Dec. 28 <lb/>4 Evolutions and predictions <lb/>Now we present some figures of the evolutions and predictions of the event computed from <lb/>the model, The data used in the simulation is ONLY number of the cumulative diagnosed people <lb/>of different regions from CCDC until Feb. 16, everyone can download it from many websites <lb/>or APP, we find the data from WIND(like Bloomberg). And the second quarantine strategy is <lb/>imposed. <lb/>Evolutions: Here is the evolution of the cumulative number of the infected cases, cumulative <lb/>number of cases in hospitalization J(t), and the cumulative number of infected and isolated <lb/>but yet diagnosed cases G(t). According to our model, total number of infected cases will be <lb/>48060(Wuhan), and 78480(China). Based on this data, it is easy to estimate various data, <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>specially the fatality rate can be estimated directly. We would like to point out that the rate <lb/>calculated here will be varying once the quarantine strategy is changed as the rate depend on . <lb/>Figure 1: Evolution of COVID-19 <lb/>We also can obtain the cumulative incidence of diagnosed case and new cases that occurred in <lb/>a given period which is displayed in Figure 2. <lb/>Figure 2: New cases <lb/>6 <lb/>All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/>Figure 3: Cumulative incidence of diagnosed case <lb/>7 <lb/>All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/>Some figures and other results have been submitted to Chinese Center for Disease Control <lb/>and Prevention(CCDC), Wuhan. <lb/>5 Conclusions on the reproductive number <lb/>Based our Fudan-CCDC model, the growth rate r of COVID-19 is almost in [0.30, 0.32] <lb/>which is larger than the growth rate 0.1 estimated by CCDC [9], and the reproductive number <lb/>R 0 of COVID-19 is estimated by 3.25 ≤ R 0 ≤ 3.4 if we simply use R 0 = 1 + r * T c with T c = 7.5. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>We have not compared the results with [12] and [14], since we are not very familiar with their <lb/>methods. <lb/></body>

            <div type="annex">Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>The ethical approval or individual consent was not applicable. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>All data and materials used in this work were publicly available. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Conflict of interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

            <div type="funding">Funding <lb/>Wenbin Chen was supported in part by the National Science Foundation of China (11671098, <lb/>91630309) and 111 project(B08018), Jin Cheng was supported in part by the National Science <lb/>Foundation of China (11971121). <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Disclaimer <lb/>The funding agencies had no role in the design and conduct of the study; collection, man-<lb/>agement, analysis, and interpretation of the data; preparation, review, or approval of the <lb/>manuscript; or decision to submit the manuscript for publication.</div>

            <div type="annex">Authors contributions All <lb/>authors conceived the study, carried out the analysis, discussed the results, drafted the first <lb/>manuscript, critically read and revised the manuscript, and gave final approval for publication. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Authors contributions <lb/>The simulations are main implemented by Shao Nian and designed by Wenbin Chen. All <lb/>authors conceived the study, carried out the analysis, discussed the results, drafted the first <lb/>manuscript, critically read and revised the manuscript, and gave final approval for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements We should truly thank Prof. Daqian Li and Prof. Guanhong Ding <lb/>for their leading work on the SARS models, we are also sincerely grateful to every member in <lb/>our group, special to Dr. Yu Jiang, Dr. Yue Ye, Dr. Boxi Xu, Dr. Yu Chen, Dr. Keji Liu, Miss <lb/>Xinyue Luo, Dr. Ming Zhong, Dr. Xiang Xu and Prof. Shuai Lu and other group members. We <lb/>also thank Yongzhen Wang and Prof. Shanjian Tang(Fudan), Gang Liang(China CDC in Wuhai, <lb/>Hubei), our old friend Dr. Zhihua Shen(Fusion Fin Trade, fusionfintrade.com), Prof. Xingjie <lb/>Li(University of North Carolina at Charlotte), Ling Ye(China CDC in Daishan, Zhejiang), Long <lb/>Chen(University of California, Irvine), Prof. Jiongming Yong(University of Central Florida) and <lb/>Xinkang Chao(Mathworks). Wenbin Chen specially thank our colleague Prof. Rongmin Li who <lb/>mentioned us to use the Gamma distribution. Wenbin Chen thanks Dr. Xu Chen&apos;s group in the <lb/>Winning Health Technology Group Company(winning.com.cn), who always believe and support <lb/>us, he also thanks his wife Dr. Jie Xu, hers hometown is Wuhan. <lb/>We should thanks everyone who are fighting for Wuhan, specially we present our deep respects <lb/>to Doctor Wenling Li and Prof. Nanshan Zhong. 1 . <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">1 There may exists lots of typos and many references are note cited, since the paper is finished in a hurry and <lb/>the first version is submitted at Feb. 17, 5:25am, 2020, after Xingjie Li helps me to modify the notes. Please let <lb/>us know if you have any question and suggestions, please email us at wbchen@fudan.edu.cn. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] R. M. Anderson and R. M. May. Infectious diseases of humans: dyanmics and control. <lb/>Oxford, Uk: Oxford University Press. <lb/>[2] Y. Chen, J. Cheng, Y.Jiang and K. Liu. A time delay dynamical model for outbreak of <lb/>2019-nCov and the pramameter identification[EB/OL]. To appear in Journal in Inverse and <lb/>Ill-posed Problems, 2020. arXiv:2002.00418. <lb/>[3] Y. Chen, J. Cheng, Y. Jiang and K. Liu. A time delay dynamic system with external source <lb/>for the local outbreak of 2019-nCoV. arXiv:2002.02590, 2020. <lb/>[4] N. Ferguson et al. Strategies for containing an emerging influenza pandemic in Southeast <lb/>Asia. Nature 437, 209-214. <lb/>[5] N. Ferguson et al. Strategies for mitigating and influenza pandemic. Nature 442, 448-452. <lb/>[6] M. Lipsitch, T. Cohen, B. Cooper, J. M. Robins, S. Ma, L. James, G. Gopalakrishna, S. K. <lb/>Chew, C. C. Tan, M. H. Samore, D. Fisman, and M. Murray. Transmission dynamics and <lb/>control of severe acute respiratory syndrome, Science. 2003 June 20; 300(5627): 1966-1970. <lb/>doi:10.1126/science.1086616. <lb/>[7] K. Liu, Y. Jiang, Y. Yan, and W. Chen. A time delay dynamic model with external source <lb/>and the basic reproductive number estimation for the outbreak of Novel Coronavirus Pneu-<lb/>monia. Submitted to Contral Theory and Applications (in Chinese), 2020. <lb/>[8] O. G. Pybus et al. The epidemic behaviour of hepatitis C virus. Science 22, 2323-2325. <lb/>[9] L. Qun, G. Xuhua, W. Peng, W. Xiaoye, Z. Lei, T. Yeqing, R. Ruiqi, et al. Early Trans-<lb/>mission Dynamics in Wuhan, China, of Novel Coronavirus-Infected Pneumonia. N Engl J <lb/>Med, 2020. DOI: 10.1056/NEJMoa2001316. <lb/>[10] N. Shao, Y. Chen,J. Cheng and W. Chen. Some novel statistical time delay dynamic model <lb/>by statistics data from CCDC on Novel Coronavirus Pneumonia, submitted to Journal of <lb/>Control Theory and Applications(in Chinese), 2020. <lb/>[11] J. Wallinga and M. Lipstch. How generation intervals shape the relatoinship between growth <lb/>rates and reproductive number. Proc. R. Soc. B, 274, 599-604, 2007. <lb/>[12] J.T. Wu, K. Leung, G. M. Leung, Nowcasting and forecasting the potential domestic and <lb/>international spread of the 2019-nCov outbreak originating in Wuhan, China: a modelling <lb/>study. The Lancet., 2020,S0140-6736(20)30260-9. <lb/>[13] Y. Yan, Y. Chen, K. Liu, X. Luo, B. Xu, Y. Jiang and J. Cheng. Modeling and prediction <lb/>for the trend of outbreak of 2019-nCoV based on a time-delay dynamic system (in Chinese). <lb/>Sci. Sin. Math., 50(3), 1-8, 2020. https://doi.org/10.1360/SSM-2020-0026. <lb/>[14] S. Zhao, Q. Lin, J. Ran, S.S. Musa, G. Yang, Y. Lou, D. Gao, L. Yang and D. He, Pre-<lb/>liminary estimation of the basic reproduction number of novel coronaviurs(2019-nCov) in <lb/>China, from 2019 to 2020: A data-driver analysis in the early phase of the outbreak. Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Infectious Diseases, (92)2020, 214-217. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>author/funder, who has granted medRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.02.17.20023747 <lb/>doi: <lb/>medRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
