<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_243"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Multivariate-activity mining for molecular quasi-species<lb/> in a glutathione transferase mutant library<lb/> Sanela Kurtovic 1 , Arna Runarsdottir 1 , Lars O. Emrén 2 ,<lb/> Anna-Karin Larsson and Bengt Mannervik 3<lb/> Department of Biochemistry and Organic Chemistry, Uppsala University,<lb/> BMC, Box 576, SE-75123 Uppsala, Sweden<lb/> 1 Authors contributed equally to the work.<lb/> 2 Previously Lars O. Hansson.<lb/> 3 To whom correspondence should be addressed.<lb/> E-mail: Bengt.Mannervik@biorg.uu.se<lb/> A library of recombinant glutathione transferases (GSTs<lb/> generated by shuffling of DNA encoding human GST<lb/> M1-1 and GST M2-2 was screened with eight alternative<lb/> substrates, and the activities were subjected to multi-<lb/>variate analysis. Assays were made in lysates of bacteria<lb/> in which the GST variants had been expressed. The<lb/> primary data showed clustering of the activities in eight-<lb/>dimensional substrate-activity space. For an incisive<lb/> analysis, the rows of the data matrix, corresponding to<lb/> the different enzyme variants, were individually scaled to<lb/> unit length, thus accounting for different expression levels<lb/> of the enzymes. The columns representing the activities<lb/> with alternative substrates were subsequently individually<lb/> normalized to unit variance and a zero mean. By this<lb/> standardization, the data were adjusted to comparable<lb/> orders of magnitude. Three molecular quasi-species were<lb/> recognized by multivariate K-means and principal com-<lb/>ponent analyses. Two of them encompassed the parental<lb/> GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. A third one diverged func-<lb/>tionally by displaying enhanced activities with some sub-<lb/>strates and suppressed activities with signature substrates<lb/> for GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. A fourth cluster contained<lb/> mutants with impaired functions and was not regarded as<lb/> a quasi-species. Sequence analysis of representatives of<lb/> the mutant clusters demonstrated that the majority of the<lb/> variants in the diverging novel quasi-species were structu-<lb/>rally similar to the M1-like GSTs, but distinguished<lb/> themselves from GST M1-1 by a Ser to Thr substitution<lb/> in the active site. The data show that multivariate analysis<lb/> of functional profiles can identify small structural<lb/> changes influencing the evolution of enzymes with novel<lb/> substrate-activity profiles.<lb/> Keywords: directed evolution/DNA shuffling/glutathione<lb/> transferase/library/multivariate analysis<lb/> </front>
			
			<body>Introduction<lb/> Redesign of protein structures is a powerful approach to evol-<lb/>ving novel functions in already existing enzymes<lb/> (Anantharaman et al., 2003; Orengo and Thornton, 2005).<lb/> However, the rational creation of enzymes with novel activi-<lb/>ties on the basis of structural data remains a major challenge,<lb/> especially since even highly similar sequences may display<lb/> totally different functions (White, 2006). As a result, the<lb/> empirical approach of directed evolution has over a relatively<lb/> short period of time emerged as a powerful alternative to<lb/> structure-based redesign for altering and enhancing proper-<lb/>ties of enzymes and other proteins (Svendsen, 2004).<lb/> There are numerous strategies to create mutant libraries<lb/> with adequate sequence variations (Valetti and Gilardi, 2004;<lb/> Bloom et al., 2005; Meyer et al., 2006) and diverse pro-<lb/>cedures for examining such libraries for recombinant proteins<lb/> with the targeted properties (Farinas et al., 2001; Aharoni<lb/> et al., 2005). However, methods for analyzing the functional<lb/> consequences have not received comparable attention.<lb/> Structural studies of genomes and proteomes are essentially<lb/> limited to a small number of dimensions. The primary struc-<lb/>ture of a polynucleotide or a polypeptide is a one-<lb/>dimensional entity, whereas folded structures can be traced<lb/> in three-dimensions, and their temporal changes can be<lb/> described by adding time as a fourth dimension. In contrast,<lb/> functional properties can be expressed in numerous dimen-<lb/>sions defined by the parameters investigated.<lb/> In addition to the eventual goal of evolving enzymes with<lb/> tailor-made activities, we wanted to explore the distribution<lb/> of members of a mutant library in functional<lb/> substrate-activity space. This information could provide a<lb/> basis for choosing the optimal variants from a suitable<lb/> &apos;quasi-species&apos; of a mutant library (Eigen et al., 1988) to be<lb/> parents for a subsequent generation of mutants. The optimal<lb/> parentage for a new generation is not limited to the mutants<lb/> that have evolved the furthest in a desired direction, since<lb/> their genetic background may be too narrow (Ness et al.,<lb/> 1999). Therefore, the identification of an entire group of<lb/> near-optimal mutants is an important task.<lb/> The gene superfamily of glutathione transferases (GSTs)<lb/> illustrates how similar structures can display widely different<lb/> properties. GSTs were originally discovered as a group of<lb/> detoxication enzymes catalyzing the conjugation of a wide<lb/> variety of electrophilic substances with the sulfhydryl group<lb/> of the tripeptide glutathione (GSH) (Josephy and Mannervik,<lb/> 2006). The three-dimensional structure is highly conserved<lb/> among the soluble GSTs, and consists of two identical, or<lb/> similar, protein subunits (Armstrong, 1997). Each subunit has<lb/> an N-terminal domain with the same (a/b)-fold as the thiore-<lb/>doxin molecule. The second domain is a bundle of helical<lb/> segments. This canonical two-domain structure of soluble<lb/> GSTs is also found in other proteins with unrelated assign-<lb/>ments, such as lens crystallins of cephalopod eyes and an<lb/> eukaryotic translation elongation factor (Koonin et al.,<lb/> 1994). These alternative functions could probably not have<lb/> been predicted by currently available bioinformatics tools;<lb/> neither from the nucleotide sequence of the corresponding<lb/> DNA nor from the crystal structure of expressed proteins.<lb/> In recent investigations, we explored the concept of &apos;mol-<lb/>ecular quasi-species&apos; as the optimal group of recombinant<lb/> mutants for recursive mutagenesis toward novel properties<lb/> (Larsson et al., 2004; Emrén et al., 2006). In one model<lb/> system, a GST M1/M2 library obtained by shuffling of DNA<lb/> encoding human GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 (Hansson et al.,<lb/></body>
			
			<front># The Author 2007. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved.<lb/> For Permissions, please e-mail: journals.permissions@oxfordjournals.org<lb/> </front>
			
			<page>243<lb/> </page>
			
			<front>Protein Engineering, Design &amp; Selection vol. 20 no. 5 pp. 243– 256, 2007<lb/> Published online April 27, 2007 doi:10.1093/protein/gzm017<lb/> </front>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/>  Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
			
			<body>1999a) was characterized with a panel of alternative sub-<lb/>strates (Emrén et al., 2006). Multivariate analysis of the<lb/> activities of variant GSTs clearly demonstrated that the<lb/> enzymes segregate into functionally discrete distributions,<lb/> rather than displaying variants with properties ranging in a<lb/> continuum between those of the parental GSTs. However,<lb/> the analysis did not approach the bias that could arise when<lb/> mutant proteins are expressed at different levels in the<lb/> samples analyzed. Further, the structural basis for the cluster-<lb/>ing of the variant GSTs was lacking as a validation of the<lb/> functional analysis. These issues are addressed in this paper.<lb/> Materials and methods<lb/> GST M1/M2 library<lb/> A library of mutant enzymes was produced by shuffling of<lb/> cDNAs encoding human GST M1-1 and GST M2-2<lb/> (Hansson et al., 1999a). DNA from the library was used to<lb/> transform electrocompetent Escherichia coli XL1-Blue cells<lb/> (Stratagene). Transformants were allowed to recover in 2TY<lb/> medium [1.6% (w/v) Tryptone, 1% (w/v) yeast extract and<lb/> 0.5% (w/v) NaCl] at 378C for 1 h before spreading them on<lb/> LB-ampicillin plates [1% (w/v) Tryptone, 0.5% yeast extract,<lb/> 1% (w/v) NaCl, 1.5% Bacto-agar and 100 mg/ml of ampicil-<lb/>lin]. The M1/M2 library was estimated to contain 5 Â 10 6<lb/> independent clones.<lb/> Preparation of bacterial lysates<lb/> The parental GST M1-1 and GST M2-2, as well as 384<lb/> mutants randomly picked from the library, were expressed in<lb/> E.coli. The clones were individually grown overnight at 378C<lb/> with agitation in 2 ml of LB medium [1% (w/v) Tryptone,<lb/> 0.5% (w/v) yeast extract and 1% (w/v) NaCl] supplemented<lb/> with 100 mg/ml of ampicillin. Samples of the cultures were<lb/> diluted 100-fold into 10 ml 2TY medium supplemented as<lb/> above. After 2 hours at 378C the production of GST was<lb/> induced by addition of isopropyl-b-D-thiogalactopyranoside to<lb/> a final concentration of 0.2 mM. The bacteria were then grown<lb/> for an additional 16 h before being harvested by centrifugation<lb/> at 1500g for 10 min at 48C. The supernatant was removed and<lb/> the bacteria were resuspended in a 50-ml Falcon tube with<lb/> 250 ml 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer, pH 6.5, supplemented<lb/> with 0.2 mg/ml of lysozyme in order to lyse the cells. The sus-<lb/>pension was left on ice for 1 h prior to completing the lysis by<lb/> freezing and thawing at 2808C for 10 min and at 378C for<lb/> 5 min, respectively, performed three times. After the final<lb/> thawing, the samples were centrifuged for 30 min at 15 000 g.<lb/> The supernatants were collected and transferred to 96-well<lb/> plates and stored at 2808C before use.<lb/> Assays of catalytic activities<lb/> The GST activities of the lysates were tested with eight different<lb/> substrates. The measurements were made at 308C on a<lb/> SPECTRAmaxPLUS 384 microplate spectrophotometer<lb/> (Molecular Devices, Sunnyvale, CA, USA). The exception was<lb/> monochlorobimane (MCB), which was assayed fluorometrically<lb/> in microplates on a Fluoroskan Ascent (Labsystems, Helsinki,<lb/> Finland) at room temperature (Eklund et al., 2002). All measure-<lb/>ments were made in duplicate within 12 h after thawing of the<lb/> lysates. The volume of lysate added to the assay system was<lb/> adjusted to give linear progress curves of the reaction velocity<lb/> for each substrate. Reaction traces of every clone with all sub-<lb/>strates were inspected individually. The activity measurements<lb/> were performed in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer at pH 6.5,<lb/> except for p-nitrophenylacetate (pNPA) (Keen and Jakoby,<lb/> 1978), with which the measurements were performed in sodium<lb/> phosphate buffer at pH 7.0. The activity measured with pNPA<lb/> in the lysate was proven to be GST-catalyzed by addition of<lb/> S-(2-iodobenzyl) glutathione, a known GST inhibitor, as well as<lb/> by measuring the activity in lysates lacking expressed GST.<lb/> The assays for 1-chloro-2,4-dinitrobenzene (CDNB) and epoxy-<lb/>3-(4-nitrophenoxy)-propane (EPNP) were performed as<lb/> described by Shokeer et al. (2005). The measurements with<lb/> 3-(4-nitrophenyl)-glycidol (NPG) were performed according to<lb/> Comstock et al. (1994). Trans-4-phenyl-3-buten-2-one (tPBO)<lb/> was measured as described by Habig et al. (1974). The assay<lb/> with phenethyl isothiocyanate (PEITC) was according to Kolm<lb/> et al. (1995). The conditions for the novel substrate<lb/> 1-nitro-1-cyclohexene (NCH) were 0.5 mM GSH and 0.05 mM<lb/> NCH in 0.1 M sodium phosphate buffer, pH 6.5, at 308C. The<lb/> product formation was monitored at 280 nm, and the net extinc-<lb/>tion coefficient was determined to be 4.2 mM 21 cm 21 .<lb/> Purification and specific activity determinations<lb/> of selected GST variants<lb/> Purification of variants 72, 74, 295, 342 and 383 was made<lb/> from overnight cultures of E.coli XL1-Blue using expression<lb/> vectors carrying the respective clones. The bacteria were<lb/> grown in 2TY-medium supplemented with 100 mg/ml of<lb/> ampicillin, and induction and purification of the GST var-<lb/>iants were performed as described by Johansson et al.<lb/> (1999). Determination of specific activities of the purified<lb/> GSTs was performed as described for the lysates. The<lb/> substrate-activity profiles were expanded with three<lb/> additional substrates, trans-stilbene oxide (tSBO) (Ivarsson<lb/> et al., 2003), 2-cyano-1,3-dimethyl-1-nitrosoguanidine<lb/> (cyanoDMNG) (Jensen and Stelman, 1987) and<lb/> 4-chloro-7-nitro-1,2,3-benzoxadiazole<lb/> (NBD-Cl)<lb/> (Ricci<lb/> et al., 1994).<lb/> Sequence analysis<lb/> The amino-acid sequences of GSTs in bacterial 34 clones,<lb/> including the parental enzymes, were deduced from DNA<lb/> sequences determined by using DYEnamic ET Dye<lb/> Terminator Cycle Sequencing Kit for MegaBACE 1000<lb/> DNA Analysis Systems (GE Healthcare).<lb/> Data analysis<lb/> The molecular structures of the eight substrates used in<lb/> screening of the library and the additional three substrates<lb/> used in purified protein measurements were modeled and<lb/> represented in energy-minimized conformations in H 2 O. The<lb/> calculations were made in MMFF94x (Halgren, 1999) force<lb/> field using Molecular Operating Environment (MOE) soft-<lb/>ware (Chemical Computing Group Inc., Canada). All multi-<lb/>variate analyses were performed using mean values of<lb/> duplicate measurements. Throughout the whole analysis, the<lb/> measured reaction rates were used without subtraction of the<lb/> non-enzymatic contribution, which was relatively small for<lb/> measurements with high-enzyme activities. Subtraction of<lb/> the uncatalyzed reaction rates was undesirable, since it gave<lb/> rise to a large number of negative values. This occurred<lb/> because of the experimental scatter and a large proportion of<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>244<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

			bacterial lysates with activities not significantly different<lb/> from zero. However, analyses were also made on data cor-<lb/>rected for the non-enzymatic contribution, and the overall<lb/> results were similar to those presented, even though the<lb/> assignments of some individual clones were changed.<lb/> With the exception of the initial scatter plots of untrans-<lb/>formed data, all rows in the data matrix, corresponding<lb/> to different GST variants, were scaled to unit length.<lb/> Furthermore, the eight columns, corresponding to the alterna-<lb/>tive substrates, were individually normalized to a mean value<lb/> of zero and unit variance. In order to evaluate any bias<lb/> arising from the scaling of rows with uniformly low activi-<lb/>ties, a comparative analysis was made between the complete<lb/> data set and a subset restricted to the rows of the original<lb/> untransformed matrix in which at least one substrate gave<lb/> activity in the upper 30% percentile. The restricted data set<lb/> contained 62% of the original enzyme variants and was ana-<lb/>lyzed in the scaled and normalized form. Multivariate analy-<lb/>sis showed that the cluster assignments were essentially<lb/> unaffected by elimination of the clones with no or low<lb/> activity. In particular, the 34 sequenced clones (see Results)<lb/> were found in the corresponding clusters as in the multi-<lb/>variate analysis of the complete data set. The software used<lb/> was SIMFIT (W.G. Bardsley, http://www.simfit.man.ac.uk,<lb/> University of Manchester, UK) and SIMCA (Umetrics,<lb/> Umeå, Sweden).<lb/> Experimental error in the screening of lysates<lb/> and assays of purified proteins<lb/> GST activities of the lysates were measured in duplicate in<lb/> order to check the precision of the measurements. For the<lb/> entire data set, the medians of the relative standard deviations<lb/> of the activities were ,14% for each substrate. The sub-<lb/>strates of special significance for the cluster assignments<lb/> showed lower relative standard deviations: pNPA (1.4%),<lb/> EPNP (8.9%) and NCH (2.3%). If inactive clones were disre-<lb/>garded, the relative standard deviations were ,8%. The<lb/> day-to-day variability of the measurements in lysates was<lb/> determined with GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 by assays with<lb/> the same substrate on eight different days. The standard error<lb/> for these measurements was ,24% for all substrates. The<lb/> relative standard deviation of assays with purified protein<lb/> variants was ,9%. EPNP and pNPA are substrates showing<lb/> low relative standard deviation in purified protein fractions,<lb/> 4.4% and 3.8%, respectively, and the value for NCH was<lb/> 8.3%.<lb/> Results<lb/> Recombinant GST M1/M2 mutants catalyze both<lb/> substitution and addition reactions<lb/> The GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 catalyze the nucleophilic<lb/> attack of GSH on electrophilic centers in a variety of organic<lb/> molecules, but differ markedly in their substrate selectivity<lb/> profiles. It is particularly noteworthy that the activities are<lb/> not restricted to one single class of chemical reactions, but<lb/> comprise both addition and substitution reactions. The<lb/> probing of substrate-activity space therefore also includes<lb/> investigation of alternative chemical mechanisms.<lb/> Fig. 1 shows substrate structures and the electrophilic sites<lb/> undergoing nucleophilic attack by the sulfur of GSH. CDNB,<lb/> pNPA and MCB react with GSH via substitution reactions,<lb/> whereas NPG, tPBO, EPNP, NCH and PEITC are conjugated<lb/> through addition reactions. Both GST M1-1 and GST M2-2<lb/> have high activity with CDNB, but the specific activity of<lb/> GST M2-2 is three times higher than the specific activity of<lb/> GST M1-1 (Ivarsson et al., 2003). The GSH-dependent<lb/> release of p-nitrophenol from pNPA (Keen and Jakoby,<lb/> 1978) represents a transacylation reaction. The third<lb/> 
			
			Fig. 1. Structures of alternative electrophilic substrates used in the<lb/> characterization of the GST M1/M2 library. The substrates are represented in<lb/> energy-minimized conformation in H 2 O obtained by MMFF94x force field<lb/> computations in MOE software. The arrows indicate the positions and<lb/> directions of nucleophilic attack by the thiolate group of GSH. Dashed<lb/> arrows show alternative positions of the nucleophilic attack on the same<lb/> substrate molecule. A color version of this figure is available online at http://<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org, where the atoms are color-coded as follows: C, gray;<lb/> H, light gray; O, red; N, blue; Cl, green; S, yellow and Br, brown. (A)<lb/> Substrates used in assays of crude bacterial lysates. Three compounds undergo<lb/> substitution reactions: CDNB, pNPA and MCB; five undergo addition<lb/> reactions: NPG, tPBO, EPNP, NCH and PEITC. (B) Additional substrates<lb/> used in assays of purified GST variants: cyanoDMNG and NBD-Cl undergo<lb/> substitution reactions; tSBO undergoes an addition reaction.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>245<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

		substitution reaction involves MCB, a fluorogenic substrate<lb/> of both GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 (Eklund et al., 2002). The<lb/> NPG and EPNP are epoxides, and the opening of the oxirane<lb/> ring occurs via nucleophilic addition to either of the oxirane<lb/> carbons. tPBO is an enone to which GSH adds via the<lb/> b-carbon. NCH is a novel GST substrate in which GSH is<lb/> added to the double bond of the cyclohexene ring. The last<lb/> substrate of the addition reactions is PEITC, an isothiocya-<lb/>nate that forms a dithiocarbamate with GSH. These eight<lb/> substrates were all used for screening of the library. For the<lb/> characterization of purified enzymes (see below), the activi-<lb/>ties were also measured with NBD-Cl (aromatic substi-<lb/>tution), cyanoDMNG (transnitrosylation) and tSBO (epoxide<lb/> addition).<lb/> Activities of GSTs from the GST M1/M2 library demonstrate<lb/> divergent functional properties among the mutants<lb/> The two parental GSTs and 384 clones, randomly chosen<lb/> from the mutant library, were assayed in bacterial lysates<lb/> with the eight electrophilic substrates. The rosters of eight-<lb/>dimensional substrate-activity data for the 386 GST variants<lb/> were first examined by scatter plots. Projections in two or<lb/> three dimensions indicated multiple correlations between<lb/> some of the substrates (Fig. 2). For example, CDNB versus<lb/> NPG or EPNP versus PEITC suggested subgroupings radiat-<lb/>ing in different directions. In contrast, pNPA versus EPNP<lb/> did not show such well-defined divergent patterns. In three<lb/> dimensions, CDNB, NPG and EPNP strongly indicated three<lb/> diverging subdivisions of the activity values (Fig. 2D).<lb/> Pair-wise plots of rosters of multiple functional values can be<lb/> used to distinguish clones of dissimilar GSTs and identify<lb/> those with similar properties<lb/> A sensitive test for functional similarities of two enzyme<lb/> variants is the plot of the functional parameter values of the<lb/> two variants against one another. The parental enzymes GST<lb/> M1-1 and GST M2-2 clearly have divergent specific activi-<lb/>ties with the alternative substrates (Fig. 3A). GST M2-2 and<lb/> variant 74 show strong similarities with seven substrates<lb/> (Fig. 3B), but differ with respect to the eighth (MCB). If two<lb/> clones contain identical enzyme variants, the coordinates<lb/> will fall along a straight line, and the slope will be an esti-<lb/>mate of the relative amounts of active enzyme in the two<lb/> samples assayed. For example, variants 72 and 119, which<lb/> represent identical proteins, as evidenced by their amino-acid<lb/> sequences (see below), are expressed at different levels: the<lb/> slope of the regression line (R 2 ¼ 0.941, P ¼ 0.0001,<lb/> testing the probability that the rows are not correlated; not<lb/> depicted) shows that the lysate containing variant 72 holds<lb/> 2.1+0.2 times more active enzyme than does the lysate con-<lb/>taining variant 119 (Fig. 3C). When the corresponding<lb/> vectors of data are scaled to unit length (see the following<lb/> paragraph), the respective parameter values of two function-<lb/>ally identical variants should fall along a straight line<lb/> through the origin with a slope equal to 1.0. Variants 71 and<lb/> Fig. 2. Scatter plots demonstrating correlations between activities with alternative substrates in lysates of 384 clones randomly chosen from the GST M1/M2<lb/> library. The points represent mean values of duplicate measurements of activities with mutants as well as with the parental GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. The<lb/> data, in milliunits of absorbance change per minute, are untransformed and illustrate two-and three-dimensional projections selected from the<lb/> eight-dimensional substrate-activity space investigated. (A) NPG versus CDNB indicates distributions in two directions. (B) EPNP versus pNPA shows a<lb/> positive correlation in one main direction. (C) PEITC versus EPNP indicates distributions in two directions. (D) Three-dimensional plot of activities with<lb/> CDNB, NPG and EPNP indicating divergent distributions in three directions; note that the CDNB-NPG plane in the bottom of the cube corresponds to<lb/> panel A. Positions of representatives of each distribution are shown in (A)–(C).<lb/> 
		
		<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
		
		<page>246<lb/> </page>
		
		<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
		
		72 are such examples of catalytically identical GSTs, as<lb/> judged by analysis of the eight parameters values (Fig. 3D).<lb/> The functional properties of variant GSTs display clustering<lb/> in multidimensional substrate-activity space<lb/> The primary analysis gave clear indications for subgroups of<lb/> the data, but further refinement was made in order to avoid<lb/> bias that can be introduced by variations in the relative<lb/> amounts of enzyme in the lysates analyzed, as well as by<lb/> differences in the magnitudes of the activities measured with<lb/> the alternative substrates. Therefore, each row in the data<lb/> matrix was scaled to a vector of unit length. By this scaling,<lb/> all clones that produce functionally identical GSTs are<lb/> treated as if they were expressing the same amount of active<lb/> enzyme. Further, the eight columns of activities in the data<lb/> matrix were individually normalized to a mean value of zero<lb/> and unit variance. This normalization allows all substrates to<lb/> influence the analysis of the total data set to the same extent.<lb/> All subsequent analyses of cell lysates were made with the<lb/> transformed data.<lb/> The transformed data could be divided into four divergent<lb/> clusters based on the Euclidian distances among the GST<lb/> variants in eight-dimensional functional space. Fig. 4 shows<lb/> the results of a K-means analysis under the assumption of<lb/> four nodes. CDNB versus pNPA (Fig. 4A), NPG versus<lb/> EPNP (Fig. 4B) and CDNB versus NCH (Fig. 4C) are three<lb/> of the 28 possible two-dimensional projections of the eight-<lb/>dimensional substrate-activity data. The analysis shows two<lb/> clusters encompassing the parental GST M1-1 (58 variants<lb/> colored blue) and GST M2-2 (31 variants colored red). In<lb/> addition, two diverging clusters could be identified. One of<lb/> them (253 variants colored brown) is formed by GST<lb/> mutants with low absolute values of catalytic activities<lb/> overall. The scaling of activity vectors to unit length makes<lb/> the activities appear relatively high, but if the data matrix is<lb/> transformed only by normalizing the columns to unit var-<lb/>iance and a zero mean, the brown cluster is centered at the<lb/> origin, as expected. Disregarding this cluster of &apos;null&apos;<lb/> mutants, the centroid of the second novel cluster (containing<lb/> 44 variants colored yellow) is the highest on the pNPA,<lb/> EPNP and NCH axes (Fig. 4), and intermediate between the<lb/> centroids of the M1-like and M2-like clusters on the CDNB<lb/> and NPG axes. High relative activities with pNPA, EPNP<lb/> and NCH in comparison with other activities appear to<lb/> Fig. 3. Plots of kinetic parameter values of pairs of GST variants against one another. The points represent mean values of duplicate measurements of<lb/> activities in lysates measured with the eight alternative substrates used in screening of the GST M1/M2 library. (A) Parameter values of the parental enzymes<lb/> GST M1-1 (M1) and GST M2-2 (M2) do not give evidence for a correlation between the two enzymes (a regression line gives R 2 ¼ 0.027, P ¼ 0.70; not<lb/> shown). (B) Values of clone 74 versus GST M2-2 show a significant positive correlation (R 2 ¼ 0.907, P ¼ 0.0003). (C) Values of clone 72 versus clone 119<lb/> show a significant positive correlation (R 2 ¼ 0.941, P ¼ 0.0001). (D) Parameter values plotted for clones 72 and 71 derive from normalized activities. For this<lb/> analysis, each row in the data matrix was scaled to a vector of unit length (in order to treat all functionally identical clones as if they were expressing the same<lb/> amount of active enzyme). Further, the eight columns of activities in the data matrix were individually normalized to a mean value of zero and unit variance<lb/> (to give similar influences of substrates that give activities differing in absolute magnitude in the analysis). The data demonstrate a highly significant positive<lb/> correlation (R 2 ¼ 0.998, P , 0.0001) with a regression line through the origin and unit slope (1.016+0.018). The data set with rows scaled to unit length,<lb/> but without normalization of columns gave essentially the same slope (0.993+0.014). The completely untransformed data similarly gave the slope<lb/> 1.098+0.016, indicating similar amounts of active enzyme in clones 71 and 72. In the latter two graphs (not shown), the majority of the data points<lb/> accumulate more closely to the origin, as in panels (A)–(C).<lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/></note> 
			
			<page>247<lb/></page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

			characterize members of both the yellow and the brown clus-<lb/>ters. However, the NCH activity is primarily linked to the<lb/> brown cluster (Fig. 4C), and the pNPA and the EPNP activi-<lb/>ties are the hallmarks of the yellow cluster. As in the<lb/> K-means cluster analysis, a similar division of the data into a<lb/> minimum of four groups was indicated by hierarchical analy-<lb/>sis based on dendrograms (not shown), using a number of<lb/> alternative distance measures and group linkages. Indications<lb/> for further subgrouping of the data needed corroboration by a<lb/> larger data set. Furthermore, the structural identification of<lb/> some identical enzyme variants, which had to be joined, set<lb/> a limit to the maximum number of clusters.<lb/> Principal component analysis<lb/> A principal component (PC) analysis showed the dominating<lb/> functional relationships among the M1/M2 library mutants in<lb/> a PC1– PC2 score plot (Fig. 5A). The data points are colored<lb/> on the basis of the previous clustering in the K-means analy-<lb/>sis (Fig. 4). The two methods of analysis give consistent<lb/> groupings of the variants. The parental enzymes GST M1-1<lb/> and GST M2-2 are located in different quadrants and segre-<lb/>gate with variants in the two dominating swarms of the data<lb/> points. The two-dimensional projection, of the eight-<lb/>dimensional PC scores, in the PC1– PC2 plane (Fig. 5A)<lb/> suggests that, in addition to the M1-like and M2-like clusters<lb/> diverging in PC2, a third cluster (colored yellow) is emerging<lb/> in between the parental enzymes. In addition, a fourth cluster<lb/> (brown) encompasses mutants with low activities. The first<lb/> three eigenvalues account for 45, 27, and 9%, respectively,<lb/> of the variability in the PC analysis. Examination of PC3<lb/> (not shown) demonstrates that the members of the yellow<lb/> novel cluster diverge in a direction distinct from those of the<lb/> parental distributions. In addition, the yellow and brown clus-<lb/>ters clearly segregate in this dimension. The loading plot<lb/> (Fig. 5B) suggests that EPNP and pNPA are the substrates<lb/> contributing particularly prominently to forming the yellow<lb/> cluster, as indicated by loadings 1 and 3 (not shown),<lb/> whereas the other substrates primarily are responsible for the<lb/> separation of the M1-and M2-like clusters. In PC1, the<lb/> loading of NCH is similar to those of EPNP and pNPA<lb/> (Fig. 5B). In PC2-PC3, however, the loading of NCH is<lb/> distinctly separated into a different quadrant from the<lb/> loadings of EPNP and pNPA. NCH is thus linked to the<lb/> distribution of the brown cluster, whereas EPNP and pNPA<lb/> are associated with the yellow cluster.<lb/> Canonical variate analysis<lb/> PCs are obtained by a distance-preserving rotation of the<lb/> original axes of the substrate-activity space. In order to give<lb/> emphasis to the groupings of the data, a canonical variate<lb/> Fig. 4. K-means cluster analysis based on the division of the GST M1/M2 library into four clouds in eight-dimensional substrate-activity space. The data<lb/> analyzed derived from the matrix of mean activity values from measurements with the eight alternative substrates in lysates of bacterial clones. The 386 rows<lb/> of activity values representing parental enzymes GST M1-1 and GST M2-2, and the recombinant clones were scaled to unit length prior to normalizing each<lb/> substrate column to unit variance and zero mean. The clustering was based on the Euclidian distances from four nodes (black dots), and the members of the<lb/> respective clusters are color-coded: blue squares, M1-like mutants; red triangles, M2-like mutants; yellow diamonds, mutants with novel properties and brown<lb/> circles, &apos;null&apos; mutants with impaired or zero activities. A color version of this figure is available online at http://peds.oxfordjournals.org. The location of one<lb/> representative of each cluster is marked. The panels show two-dimensional projections of the clusters in eight-dimensional substrate-activity space: (A) pNPA<lb/> versus CDNB; (B) EPNP versus NPG and (C) NCH versus CDNB.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>248<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

			analysis was performed on the four clusters obtained by<lb/> K-means analysis. The transformation underlying canonical<lb/> variates best represents the Mahalanobis distance, which<lb/> highlights differences between groups (Krzanowski, 2000).<lb/> The canonical variate plot (Fig. 6) indeed underscores the<lb/> distinction between the clusters. The separation is clear<lb/> between the M1-like cluster (blue) and the M2-like cluster<lb/> (red), but somewhat less distinct between the &apos;null&apos; individ-<lb/>uals (brown) and the novel distribution (yellow). The data<lb/> were also analyzed under the assumption of three or five<lb/> clusters (not shown). However, the hierarchical dendrograms<lb/> analysis (mentioned above) strongly suggested a minimum of<lb/> four clusters, and for lack of additional experimental data,<lb/> the parsimonious choice of four was made. In an analysis in<lb/> which the members of the brown cluster were eliminated, the<lb/> remaining data still separated into the same M1-like, M2-like<lb/> and yellow clusters (not shown).<lb/> DNA sequences of 34 clones demonstrate the structural<lb/> diversity in the GST M1/M2 library<lb/> DNA sequences were determined for 34 variants in the GST<lb/> M1/M2 library. The GST variants were chosen such that<lb/> representatives of all four clusters were included (cf. Fig. 5).<lb/> Comparison with the GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 sequences<lb/> identified 23 different nucleotide segments in the variants<lb/> that had been exchanged between the two parental sequences<lb/> (data not shown). Owing to the degeneracy of the genetic<lb/> code, the resulting amino-acid sequences contained 14<lb/> alternative segments (Fig. 7). The exact size of each segment<lb/> exchanged remains undefined, because of the 89% sequence<lb/> identity of GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 at the DNA level; the<lb/> sequences separating the exchanged segments are identical<lb/> and therefore could derive from either GST M1-1 or GST<lb/> M2-2.<lb/> Fig. 7 displays a schematic alignment of the exchanged<lb/> segments of parental amino-acid sequences. Arrows indicate<lb/> the location of the four regions of primary structure that<lb/> form the binding site for the electrophilic substrate. Squares<lb/> mark two segments containing active-site residues that differ<lb/> between GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 and circles mark the<lb/> other segments. Deviations from both parents were noted in<lb/> the form of spurious amino-acid substitutions indicated by<lb/> vertical bars. The average number of mutations was about<lb/> two per DNA sequence, of which one was silent and the<lb/> other was altering the encoded amino acid. A noteworthy<lb/> modification is the Q110R point mutation, which appears in<lb/> 14 clones all containing a segment originating from the par-<lb/>ental GST M2-2. Residue 110 is located in the same<lb/> segment as the catalytically important Tyr116, but is still<lb/> distant from the active site and does not appear to influence<lb/> the catalytic properties. The structural diversity of the library<lb/> is quite high. Out of the 34 variants, 30 had unique DNA<lb/> sequences; only clones 72 and 119 as well as clones 284 and<lb/> 383 had exactly the same nucleotide sequence. Four pairs of<lb/> identical protein variants appeared when the codons were<lb/> translated: clones 23 and 295, clones 6 and 276, clones 161<lb/> and 320, as well as clones 141 and 245. The other sequences<lb/> translated into different protein variants.<lb/> The brown cluster, containing low-activity GSTs, was rep-<lb/>resented by five variants: 185, 95, 376, 297 and 140. Their<lb/> Fig. 5. PC analysis of activities displayed by the GST M1/M2 library. The substrate-activity data were doubly transformed as described in Fig. 4. (A) PC1/<lb/> PC2 plot showing the clones expressing the mutants color-coded according to their clustering in Fig. 4. A color version of this figure is available online at<lb/> http://peds.oxfordjournals.org. Locations of variants subjected to DNA sequence analysis are indicated. (B) Two-dimensional loading plot showing the<lb/> contributions to the PCs of each of the eight substrates used.<lb/> Fig. 6. Canonical variate analysis of the clusters obtained by K-means<lb/> analysis in Fig. 4. The doubly transformed data are plotted in the plane of<lb/> the first two canonical variates, CV1 and CV2. The mutants are color-coded<lb/> according to the clustering in Fig. 4. A color version of this figure is<lb/> available online at http://peds.oxfordjournals.org. In comparison with PCs,<lb/> canonical variates give stronger emphasis on the separation of groups.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>249<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
			
			sequences did not reveal any strikingly similar traits. Clone<lb/> 140 has seven point mutations, including the start codon,<lb/> which may compromise its expression. The M1-like blue<lb/> cluster contributed nine variants to the sequence analysis: 72,<lb/> 119, 23, 295, 71, 291, 12, 48 and 275. With the exception of<lb/> 48 and 275, they were dominated by segments derived from<lb/> GST M1-1. All enzymes other than variant 48 contained Ser<lb/> in position 210. Variant 48 had Thr in position 210, but con-<lb/>tained the centrally located active-site segment distinguishing<lb/> GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. The yellow cluster was rep-<lb/>resented by ten variants: 161, 320, 141, 245, 383, 284, 343,<lb/> 240, 7 and 28. Excepting variant 28, their primary structures<lb/> were dominated by segments from GST M1-1, but in contrast<lb/> to members of the M1-like cluster they contained Thr in pos-<lb/>ition 210. The deviating structure, 28, was similar to the<lb/> sequence of GST M2-2, but in distinction from the latter<lb/> contained Ser in position 210. Finally, ten variants from the<lb/> M2-like red cluster were sequenced: 286, 342, 168, 34, 74,<lb/> 6, 276, 8, 5 and 31. They are composed primarily of seg-<lb/>ments from GST M2-2 and have either Thr or Ser in position<lb/> 210. Instead, they all without exception contain the central<lb/> active-site segment distinguishing the parental enzymes, and<lb/> in this respect mimic GST M2-2 (black square in Fig. 7). As<lb/> mentioned above, clones 72 and 119 are identical at the<lb/> protein level, but they are also identical with the parental<lb/> GST M1-1. In contrast, there are no clones analyzed that are<lb/> structurally identical with the parental GST M2-2.<lb/> Purification and characterization of selected GST variants<lb/> After screening of the 384 GST mutants from the M1/M2<lb/> library, five variants (72, 74, 295, 342 and 383), together<lb/> with the parental enzymes GST M1-1 and GST M2-2, were<lb/> selected for purification. These five variants were chosen to<lb/> represent the three clusters recognized among active library<lb/> individuals (Fig. 5) in order to compare their substrate selec-<lb/>tivity profiles. Variants 72 and 295 belong to the M1-like<lb/> cluster (blue) and variant 74 belongs to the M2-like cluster<lb/> (red), while variant 383 is a member of the third distribution<lb/> of active mutants (yellow). Variant 342 clustered with the<lb/> M2-like GSTs by the K-means and dendrograms analyses,<lb/> but clearly appeared close to variant 383 of the yellow<lb/> cluster in dimensions three and four of the PC analysis. This<lb/> ambiguity apparently arises because variant 342 is in the<lb/> region between the red and yellow clusters in the original<lb/> eight-dimensional substrate-activity space. In the PC coordi-<lb/>nates, the major variability (81%), also including correlations<lb/> between activities with different substrates, is accounted for<lb/> in the first two dimensions. The higher dimensions three<lb/> (9%) and four (8%) can then display more weakly contribut-<lb/>ing, but still distinguishing, properties. In the present analy-<lb/>sis, they signify a distribution of activities diverging in a new<lb/> direction. The functional properties of variant 342 were<lb/> undoubtedly most similar to those of variant 383 (see<lb/> below).<lb/> The purified GST variants were assayed with eleven sub-<lb/>strates (Table I). Specific activities were determined with<lb/> NBD-Cl, cyanoDMNG and tSBO, in addition to the eight<lb/> substrates used in the screening. NBD-Cl and cyanoDMNG<lb/> are characteristic GST M2-2 substrates, showing 5 and 200<lb/> times, respectively, higher activities with GST M2-2 than<lb/> with GST M1-1. On the other hand, tSBO is a GST M1-1<lb/> distinctive substrate, giving 600 times higher activity with<lb/> GST M1-1 than with GST M2-2. GST variants belonging to<lb/> the M1-like cluster (variants 72 and 295) display higher<lb/> specific activity with tSBO than with the other two sub-<lb/>strates. On the other hand, variant 74 typifying the M2-like<lb/> Fig. 7. Amino-acid sequence alignment of clones from the GST M1/M2<lb/> library illustrated as beads on a string. Each bead represents a segment that<lb/> originates from one or the other of the parental enzymes. White beads derive<lb/> from GST M1-1 and black beads from GST M2-2. The string represents<lb/> sequences that cannot be distinguished as parental GST M1-1 or GST M2-2,<lb/> because they are identical. The vertical bars symbolize amino-acid<lb/> substitutions introduced by spurious mutations of the parental sequences.<lb/> The variant sequences are arranged in the order of descending percent<lb/> similarity to GST M1-1 (100%). Two pairs, clones 72 and 119 as well as<lb/> clones 383 and 284, are displayed together because their DNA sequence is<lb/> the same for each pair. The four arrows at the top point to parts of the<lb/> sequences that build the active site of the enzyme. The first two are identical<lb/> in the parental GSTs (and in all clones). The third and fourth arrows point to<lb/> squares instead of circles, indicating segments with amino-acid residues that<lb/> distinguish the active sites of GST M1-1 and GST M2-2. K-means cluster<lb/> assignments of the clones expressing the GST variants (cf. Figs. 4 and 5) are<lb/> given in the last column: cluster 1 represents brown; cluster 2, M2-like red;<lb/> cluster 3, M1-like blue and cluster 4, yellow variants.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>250<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
			
			cluster has low-specific activity with tSBO, but high-specific<lb/> activity with cyanoDMNG and NBD-Cl (Table I). The<lb/> remaining variants, 342 and 383, both clearly deviate in their<lb/> substrate-selectivity profile from the parent-like individuals,<lb/> having pronounced specific activities with NBD-Cl but not<lb/> with cyanoDMNG or tSBO (Table I). Variant 383 belongs to<lb/> the yellow cluster of mutants with novel activity profiles<lb/> recognized in multivariate analysis (Figs 4 and 5), and this<lb/> mutant definitely displays distinguishing properties also in<lb/> the purified form when characterized by activities with<lb/> parent-specific substrates. Variant 342, in spite of being<lb/> assigned to the M2-like cluster by the K-means analysis<lb/> (Fig. 4), displays essentially the same specific activity profile<lb/> as variant 383 (Table I), at least as a first approximation.<lb/> This finding is in agreement with the PC analysis, which<lb/> demonstrates, in the higher principal components PC3 and<lb/> PC4 (not shown), a clear association between variants 342<lb/> and 383 as well as with other mutants of the yellow cluster.<lb/> Substrate-selectivity profiles for purified members<lb/> of different clusters<lb/> The fractions of specific activity for the 11 substrates in<lb/> relation to the sum of all the specific activities are given as<lb/> illustrations of the profiles in &apos;exploded doughnut&apos; represen-<lb/>tation (Fig. 8). All of the seven purified GST variants share<lb/> high activities with CDNB. The M1-like variants 72 and 295<lb/> display a second high activity with PEITC, whereas the<lb/> second highest activity for the M2-like variants is found with<lb/> cyanoDMNG. Variants 342 and 383 are both markedly domi-<lb/>nated by the CDNB activity, indicating that no alternative<lb/> substrate tested gives an activity of the same magnitude as<lb/> the CDNB activity. In particular, these mutants have sup-<lb/>pressed activities with PEITC and cyanoDMNG, as com-<lb/>pared to the respective parental GSTs. On the other hand, the<lb/> members of the yellow cluster are also characterized by the<lb/> emerging activities with pNPA and EPNP (cf. Fig. 4), even<lb/> though the specific activities with these substrates are rela-<lb/>tively low in absolute numbers. The substrate-activity profiles<lb/> of GST M1-1 and variants 72 and 295 are very similar, as<lb/> also concluded from measurements in crude lysates. GST<lb/> M1-1 and variant 72 have the same amino-acid sequence and<lb/> are expected to have identical properties within the exper-<lb/>imental variance. They differ from variant 295 only by the<lb/> amino-acid residue in position 16. GST M2-2 and variant 74<lb/> are also functionally highly similar, in agreement with their<lb/> major structural similarities (Fig. 7), but variant 74 shows<lb/> decreased CDNB activity, and increased MCB and<lb/> cyanoDMNG activities in comparison with GST M2-2.<lb/> Discussion<lb/> Expressivity as a variable in protein engineering<lb/> In the search for recombinant proteins with enhanced proper-<lb/>ties, mutants with increased expressivity may confound the<lb/> identification of proteins with intrinsically altered functions.<lb/> For example, mutations of a b-lactamase that provide bac-<lb/>teria with enhanced resistance to an antibiotic may result in<lb/> both increased production of the enzyme protein and<lb/> enhanced catalytic efficiency of the enzyme (Ness et al.,<lb/> 2000). Direct monitoring of the expression of the enzyme<lb/> protein could resolve this issue, but suitable molecular<lb/> Table I. Specific activity (mmol/min/mg) of purified GST variants including GST M1-1 and GST M2-2 with alternative substrates<lb/> Reactions/<lb/> substrates Specific activity (mmol/min/mg)<lb/> GST M1-1<lb/> GST M2-2<lb/> 72<lb/> 74<lb/> 295<lb/> 342<lb/> 383<lb/> Substitutions CDNB<lb/> 193+5<lb/> 4 5 2 +16<lb/> 229+4<lb/> 2 2 6 +4<lb/> 2 1 3 +15<lb/> 180+2<lb/> 125+2<lb/> NBD-Cl<lb/> 4.9+0.3<lb/> 27+2.8<lb/> 6.6+0.03<lb/> 19+0.5<lb/> 7.7+0.3<lb/> 12+0.2<lb/> 9.3+0.2<lb/> MCB<lb/> 1.5+0.08<lb/> 0.2+0.01<lb/> 1.3+0.03<lb/> 0.6+0.009<lb/> 0.9+0.04<lb/> 1.5+0.09<lb/> 0.8+0.02<lb/> cyanoDMNG<lb/> 0.8+0.08<lb/> 190+6<lb/> 0.4+0.002<lb/> 332+15<lb/> 0.32+0.02<lb/> 2.4+0.1<lb/> 0.18+0.02<lb/> pNPA<lb/> 0.26+0.004<lb/> 0.04+0.001<lb/> 0.24+0.009<lb/> 0.05+0.002<lb/> 0.24+0.007<lb/> 0.23+0.01<lb/> 0.22+0.01<lb/> Additions NPG<lb/> 3.8+0.2<lb/> 0.05+0.003<lb/> 4.1+0.4<lb/> 0.03+0.002<lb/> 3.5+0.05<lb/> 0.03+0.002<lb/> 0.09+0.002<lb/> EPNP<lb/> 0.45+0.02<lb/> 0.1+0.006<lb/> 0.41+0.03<lb/> 0.1+0.003<lb/> 0.36+0.01<lb/> 0.26+0.01<lb/> 0.58+0.03<lb/> tSBO<lb/> 2.5+0.06<lb/> 0.004+0.0002<lb/> 2.8+0.04<lb/> 0.006+0.002<lb/> 3.7+0.05<lb/> 0.01+0.002<lb/> 0.01+0.0004<lb/> tPBO<lb/> 0.57+0.02<lb/> 0.01+0.0002<lb/> 0.36+0.02<lb/> 0.01+0.0004<lb/> 0.3+0.004<lb/> 0.03+0.001<lb/> 0.05+0.001<lb/> PEITC<lb/> 94+0.9<lb/> 2.4+0.03<lb/> 83+0.7<lb/> 2.0+0.01<lb/> 97+0.5<lb/> 4.6+0.02<lb/> 5.6+0.1<lb/> NCH<lb/> 1.8+0.05<lb/> 2.8+0.04<lb/> 1.2+0.03<lb/> 5.0+0.5<lb/> 1.4+0.2<lb/> 0.6+0.05<lb/> 2.3+0.4<lb/> The substrates are grouped according to their different chemical transformations, substitution and addition reactions. The values (mmol min 21<lb/> mg protein 21<lb/> ) are given as a means (n ¼<lb/> 3)+SD<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>251<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
			
			identifiers, such as intrinsic chromophores or engineered<lb/> labels, may not be available. Besides, the added task of<lb/> measuring the absolute levels of the proteins could limit the<lb/> search for mutants with targeted properties in large mutant<lb/> libraries.<lb/> In an earlier study of the GST M1/M2, library cluster<lb/> assignments were made by inspection of distributions in a<lb/> PC analysis, and only GST variants with relatively high<lb/> activities were annotated as members of the three clusters of<lb/> active enzymes (Emrén et al., 2006). The input data were<lb/> measurements of enzyme activities in crude lysates of bac-<lb/>teria in which the enzymes had been expressed. An enzyme<lb/> produced in small amounts could therefore inappropriately<lb/> have been regarded as essentially inactive, in spite of the fact<lb/> that its intrinsic properties may be similar to enzymes in one<lb/> of the other groupings. In a similar manner, clones may be<lb/> misassigned when their expression levels are markedly<lb/> higher than those of the majority in the cluster to which they<lb/> properly belong. The present investigation demonstrates how<lb/> the bias caused by differences in protein concentration can<lb/> be circumvented and the analysis improved.<lb/> Enzymes represented as vectors in functional space<lb/> Eleven alternative substrates were used to characterize GST<lb/> variants, eight in the initial screening and three additional<lb/> substrates in the assay of purified enzymes. Each individual<lb/> in the mutant population can thus be represented by a point,<lb/> or vector, in multidimensional substrate-activity space. In<lb/> enzymes with broad substrate specificities, such as GSTs<lb/> (Norrgård et al., 2006) and cytochrome P450s (Otey et al.,<lb/> 2004; Taly et al., 2007), mutations often differentially affect<lb/> the catalytic efficiencies with alternative substrates. This<lb/> feature provides a tool for distinguishing emerging mutants<lb/> with enhanced (or decreased) activity with a chosen substrate<lb/> from those that are simply characterized by altered<lb/> expression of the protein. In the case of a pure effect on<lb/> expression, all measurable catalytic activities should change<lb/> proportionally in a unique direction in multidimensional<lb/> substrate-activity space, given a linear relationship between<lb/> activity and enzyme concentration. In contrast, if the intrinsic<lb/> properties of the enzyme have changed by mutations, the<lb/> substrate-activity vector will deviate from that of the parental<lb/> enzyme.<lb/> In the data set of variant GST activities in bacterial<lb/> lysates, the length of the vector in the multidimensional<lb/> substrate-activity space will depend on the amount of<lb/> enzyme sampled and assayed. Silent mutations in the coding<lb/> sequence could markedly alter the expression levels of GSTs<lb/> (Mannervik, 2005). It is also possible that different yields of<lb/> enzyme are obtained in the different preparations of bacterial<lb/> lysates. Consequently, separate clones of the same enzyme<lb/> variant could be located at unequal distances from the origin,<lb/> even though the vectors have the same direction in multidi-<lb/>mensional space. Fig. 9 sketches this situation with three<lb/> clones (rendered in red) having the same GST protein<lb/> sequence and two additional clones with diverging vectors<lb/> (black). Experimental data obviously are subject to experi-<lb/>mental error such that the vectors of the same protein<lb/> sequence do not overlap exactly, but fall within a &apos;cone-<lb/>shaped&apos; boundary. In the actual GST M1/M2, library variants<lb/> 72 and 119 are sequence identical to the parental GST M1-1.<lb/> As expected, their vectors coincide along a line in<lb/> substrate-activity space as evidenced by the linear relation-<lb/>ship between their respective parameter values in eight-<lb/>dimensional space (cf. Fig. 3C). In principle, mutations that<lb/> give a proportional change of all activities tested could be an<lb/> alternative explanation of coinciding vectors of different<lb/> lengths. However, in the present case, quantification of the<lb/> GST protein by immunoblots with cross-reactive anti-GST<lb/> M2-2 antibodies (Hao et al., 1994) verified the different<lb/> Fig. 8. Exploded doughnut representation of the substrate-activity profiles<lb/> of seven purified GST variants assayed with eleven alternative substrates<lb/> (cf. Table I). The segments in different colors specify the activity of a given<lb/> substrate as a fraction of the sum of all the specific activities. A color<lb/> version of this figure is available online at http://peds.oxfordjournals.org.<lb/> The substrates listed from top to bottom appear clockwise in the graphs<lb/> beginning from 12 o&apos;clock.<lb/> Fig. 9. Illustration of cloned enzymes as vectors in a three-dimensional<lb/> substrate-activity space. The red arrows symbolize three cloned variants<lb/> from the GST M1/M2 library that translate into the same enzyme, but are<lb/> expressed to different degrees in bacterial lysates. These vectors, within<lb/> experimental error, fall along the same line within a conical confidence<lb/> contour, but their lengths differ in proportion to their different expression<lb/> levels. The two arrows in black represent deviating variants from the library.<lb/> A color version of this figure is available online at http://peds.<lb/> oxfordjournals.org.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/></note>

			<page>252<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

			expression levels in the lysates of variants 72, 119 and GST<lb/> M1-1 (data not shown).<lb/> Contributions of the alternative substrates to the<lb/> functional clustering of the GST variants<lb/> A notable result of the PC analysis was that pNPA, EPNP<lb/> and NCH together, but separate from all other substrates, dis-<lb/>tinguish the novel yellow and brown distributions from the<lb/> parental ones. The effect of NCH was most closely related to<lb/> the brown cluster of variants with low or zero activity<lb/> (Fig. 5B), and the association of NCH with the yellow and<lb/> the brown clusters was not evident unless the rows of the<lb/> data matrix were scaled to unit length. Apparently, the low-<lb/>enzyme activities with NCH in comparison to the<lb/> non-enzymatic reaction make the scaling of rows to exagger-<lb/>ate the importance of NCH for the identification of GST<lb/> variants with novel activities.<lb/> The chemical reactions of pNPA and EPNP are of different<lb/> types: pNPA is transformed via a transacetylation reaction<lb/> to form S-acetylglutathione and 4-nitrophenol, whereas EPNP<lb/> is subject to a GSH-addition reaction involving opening of<lb/> the oxirane ring, and NCH undergoes a Michael addition.<lb/> The structures of pNPA and EPNP share a 4-nitrophenoxy<lb/> moiety, and the reaction with GSH occurs at approximately<lb/> the same site in the second moiety of the molecules (Fig. 1).<lb/> In view of the similar contributions of pNPA and EPNP in the<lb/> PC analysis, we have considered the possibility that EPNP<lb/> would rather react in a substitution reaction liberating 4-<lb/>nitrophenol and S-2,3-epoxypropylglutathione, thus mimicking<lb/> the pNPA reaction. However, HPLC analysis of the reaction<lb/> products did not give any evidence for such an alternative<lb/> reaction with EPNP (data not shown). In spite of the appar-<lb/>ently similar effects of these two substrates on PC1 and PC2<lb/> (Fig. 5), the higher dimensions PC3 and PC4 and the corre-<lb/>sponding loading plots (not shown) demonstrate that the<lb/> effects of EPNP and pNPA are diverging, suggesting a further<lb/> subdivision of the yellow distribution.<lb/> The other substrates used in the screening are also corre-<lb/>lated and form groups in the loading plots (cf. Fig. 5B).<lb/> MCB and CDNB are positively contributing to formation of<lb/> the M2-like cluster, and both substrates undergo substitution<lb/> reactions (Fig. 1). NPG and PEITC form a third group in the<lb/> loading plot (Fig. 5B), and tPBO is most closely associated<lb/> with these latter substrates, which all three positively contrib-<lb/>ute to forming the M1-like cluster. These latter substrates all<lb/> undergo alternative addition reactions and have similarities<lb/> in size and structure (Fig. 1). Nevertheless, both of the two<lb/> major types of reaction mechanisms, substitution and<lb/> addition, are catalyzed by members of all clusters, and these<lb/> separate reaction types are therefore not fundamental in<lb/> dividing the GST variants into different distributions.<lb/> The influence of data transformation<lb/> It is common practice in multivariate analysis to standardize<lb/> data in order to handle variables of different dimensions. In<lb/> the present data set, groupings signifying at least three diver-<lb/>ging distributions can be recognized even in the absence of<lb/> any transformation (Fig. 2). The yellow cluster identified in<lb/> the K-means and PC analyses is represented by points in the<lb/> elongated distribution with low PEITC and high EPNP<lb/> activities in Fig. 2C, and in the distribution with low CDNB<lb/> and NPG activities and high EPNP activity in Fig. 2D.<lb/> Normalizing the activities to unit variance for each sub-<lb/>strate was previously shown to provide a clear separation of<lb/> different clusters (Emrén et al., 2006), but the issue of differ-<lb/>ent enzyme concentrations was not addressed. In the present<lb/> study, the data were first transformed by the previous<lb/> normalization, and subjected to K-means and PC analyses<lb/> (not shown). In this manner, the cluster assignments were<lb/> accomplished by the algorithm rather than by the investi-<lb/>gator. However, scaling of the activities of all enzyme var-<lb/>iants to vectors of unit length prior to normalizing the<lb/> columns to unit variance allowed us to identify variants that<lb/> apparently were misassigned, because of their low concen-<lb/>tration in the bacterial lysates analyzed. The 291 &apos;null&apos;<lb/> mutants of the analysis of the normalized data were redistrib-<lb/>uted after the additional scaling ( performed before the nor-<lb/>malization of columns), such that 15 apparent &apos;null&apos; mutants<lb/> were assigned to the new yellow cluster, 17 to the M1-like<lb/> blue cluster and seven to the M2-like red cluster. The<lb/> remaining 252 were found in the new brown &apos;null&apos; cluster,<lb/> which in addition received one mutant from the 21 members<lb/> of the first M2-like distribution. No further reassignments of<lb/> mutants in the first M2-like cluster were made. The 15<lb/> members of the first M1-like distribution were all present in<lb/> the new blue M1-like cluster. The most striking redistribution<lb/> of variants was noted in the first &apos;novel&apos; cluster consisting of<lb/> 59 GSTs with altered substrate-activity profiles. The new<lb/> yellow cluster retained 29 of these variants, but 26 were reas-<lb/>signed as M1-like and four as M2-like. Thus, half of the first<lb/> &apos;novel&apos; cluster members had intrinsic properties that were<lb/> obviously more similar to those of GST M1-1 or GST M2-2.<lb/> The assignments based on the double transformation were in<lb/> better agreement with the sequences determined (Fig. 7).<lb/> Any transformation of the data may cause bias in the<lb/> analysis, and different data treatments could serve different<lb/> purposes. It could be argued that the scaling of rows to<lb/> vectors of unit length may give unjustified weight to weakly<lb/> active enzymes. However, an enzyme with low activity in all<lb/> substrate dimensions will not show any of the distinctive pat-<lb/>terns that characterize different clusters, but owing to exper-<lb/>imental error will display a random scatter in all dimensions<lb/> of activity space. The present study shows that the majority<lb/> of the original &apos;low-activity&apos; variants are still &apos;null&apos; mutants<lb/> in the brown cluster, even if their activities with different<lb/> substrates appear exaggerated (cf. Fig. 4). The soundness of<lb/> the double transformation in the present study is supported<lb/> by the finding that five sequenced GSTs of the original<lb/> &apos;novel&apos; cluster (compared with cluster assignment of data<lb/> only normalized with respect to the eight substrates) were<lb/> reassigned to the M1-like (variants 119, 48 and 275) and<lb/> M2-like clusters (variants 286 and 168), in improved accord<lb/> with their primary structures.<lb/> It should be emphasized that the current multivariate<lb/> analysis does not attempt a definitive cluster assignment of<lb/> every enzyme variant. Obviously, not only the different<lb/> transformations, but also the composition and size of the<lb/> data set analyzed will influence the outcome. Furthermore,<lb/> the vectors of experimental substrate-activity data, as well as<lb/> the corresponding quasi-species, are stochastic variables<lb/> subject to variance. The main result of the analysis was that<lb/> a minimum of three divergent distributions, or quasi-species,<lb/> can be identified among the active members in the GST M1/<lb/> M2 library. The double transformation facilitated a more<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>253<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
			
			accurate assignment of differentially expressed enzymes. In<lb/> comparison with the more subjective cluster assignments<lb/> (Emrén et al., 2006), it is noteworthy that the results of the<lb/> two approaches are in general agreement for GST variants<lb/> expressed at high levels. However, a number of mutants<lb/> present in low concentrations in the bacterial lysates had to<lb/> be reassigned. It should also be noted that the higher dimen-<lb/>sions of the PC analysis were most reliable in the assignment<lb/> of some variants with novel properties, as exemplified with<lb/> variant 342 (cf. Emrén et al., 2006).<lb/> Linking primary structure to functional changes<lb/> The clustering of the GST M1/M2 variants was based<lb/> entirely on their functional properties without any prior<lb/> information about their amino-acid sequences. In order to<lb/> explore to what extent the clustering was a reflection of simi-<lb/>larities in structure, 34 enzyme variants were chosen for<lb/> sequence analysis. Pair-wise comparison of the activity data<lb/> (exemplified in Fig. 3) made it possible to evaluate the<lb/> effects of segment exchanges or spurious point mutations in<lb/> variants that have similar primary structures. In this manner,<lb/> it can be concluded that in the GST M1-1 sequence the<lb/> mutations of Ala16 into Ser, Ala67 into Thr or Asn173 into<lb/> Ser are without effect on the catalytic properties. The spur-<lb/>ious mutations in, e.g., clones 284, 343 and 383 also appear<lb/> to be without functional consequence. In general, the com-<lb/>parison of functional data and amino-acid sequences do not<lb/> indicate that the spurious mutations have had any noteworthy<lb/> effect on the cluster assignments of catalytically active GST<lb/> mutants.<lb/> The GST mutants assigned to the brown cluster have<lb/> low, or impaired, activity with the substrates tested. Since<lb/> inactive proteins can derive from a variety of modifications<lb/> of any structure, this cluster should be expected to be<lb/> highly heterogeneous and lack unifying structural character-<lb/>istics. The other three clusters, as a first approximation<lb/> based on the 34 sequences determined, can be characteri-<lb/>zed by two features, one is the parental GST scaffold, and<lb/> the second is the nature of active-site residue 210<lb/> (C-terminal square in Fig. 7). Thus, the members of the<lb/> M1-like blue cluster have high structural similarity to GST<lb/> M1-1, and Ser in position 210 (with one exception). The<lb/> variants in the M2-like red cluster are highly similar to the<lb/> parental GST M2-2, and all contain the centrally located<lb/> segment distinguishing the active sites of GST M1-1 and<lb/> GST M2-2 (central square in Fig. 7). The members of the<lb/> red cluster have either Thr or Ser in position 210. The<lb/> majority of enzymes in the novel yellow cluster appear to<lb/> be characterized by a GST M1-1-like structure with Thr<lb/> instead of Ser in position 210. Even though some key fea-<lb/>tures in the structure are recognized as identifiers of the<lb/> three clusters of active mutants, it should be borne in mind<lb/> that the library could possibly be further subdivided into<lb/> additional clusters with other functional and structural<lb/> characteristics. It may also contain outliers that cannot<lb/> readily be classified with other mutants.<lb/> A full agreement between cluster assignments and struc-<lb/>tural traits cannot be expected. Even though in our study, the<lb/> protein sequence analysis is largely in accord with cluster<lb/> assignments based on the functional characterization. On the<lb/> other hand, the parental amino-acid sequences are 85% iden-<lb/>tical, and only modest variations could be predicted for a<lb/> single round of recombinations. Therefore, it is reasonable to<lb/> find the members of the yellow cluster with the largest<lb/> number of peptide segments from either one or the other<lb/> of the parental structures GST M1-1 or GST M2-2.<lb/> Nevertheless, the majority of the members of the yellow dis-<lb/>tribution are structurally most similar to GST M1-1, some of<lb/> them differing only in one or a few amino acids. The<lb/> locations of the mutations characterizing variant 383 are<lb/> shown in a three-dimensional model of the parental GST<lb/> M1-1 subunit (Fig. 10).<lb/> The emergence of molecular quasi-species<lb/> The evolution of novel proteins with new functions in bio-<lb/>logical systems is largely based on remodeling of pre-<lb/>existing structural elements (Orengo and Thornton, 2005;<lb/> Aravind et al., 2006; Choi and Kim, 2006). At the genomic<lb/> level, this is accomplished by fusions and recombinations of<lb/> nucleotide sequences accompanied by stochastic point<lb/> mutations. Similar processes are expedient also in protein<lb/> engineering. It has been recognized that populations of<lb/> mutants can form clusters of similar sequences, called mol-<lb/>ecular quasi-species (Eigen et al., 1988) that are superior<lb/> evolving entities in comparison with single individuals. This<lb/> paradigm can also be applied to catalytic properties of evol-<lb/>ving proteins (Larsson et al., 2004; Emrén et al., 2006).<lb/> The functional properties of the GST mutants in the<lb/> M1-like and M2-like clusters are largely similar to those of<lb/> the parental enzymes, which are well characterized (Hansson<lb/> et al., 1999b). In some cases, the M1-like variants are indis-<lb/>tinguishable in their catalytic properties within the<lb/> Fig. 10. Molecular model of a subunit of human GST M1-1 variant 383<lb/> based on the crystal structure of the enzyme in complex with GSH (pdb<lb/> 1XW6). GSH in the active site is rendered in CPK representation. Variant<lb/> 383 of the yellow cluster of the GST M1/M2 library is structurally similar to<lb/> GST M1-1, but differs by three amino-acid residues. Two are derived from<lb/> GST M2-2 (sites 67 and 210) and one (tryptophan in position 145) is not<lb/> found in any of the two parental GSTs. The mutated residues in the parental<lb/> GST M1-1 structure are shown as CPK models, color-coded green for the<lb/> novel amino-acid side chains. A color version of this figure is available<lb/> online at http://peds.oxfordjournals.org.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>254<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/></note>

			experimental variance. This is in excellent agreement with<lb/> the fact that some of them, e.g., 23, 295, 71 and 291, are<lb/> merely altered by single point mutations superficially located<lb/> and distant from the active site of GST M1-1. This concor-<lb/>dance validates the independent cluster assignments based on<lb/> multivariate analyses of functional data. The blue and red<lb/> quasi-species are thus basically clusters of GSTs varying<lb/> modestly in both structure and function from their parents<lb/> GST M1-1 and GST M2-2, respectively. The third<lb/> quasi-species is functionally characterized by enhanced<lb/> activities with pNPA and EPNP. This distinction is evident<lb/> in the K-means cluster analysis (Fig. 4), and even more<lb/> obvious in the higher dimensions of the PC analysis. In<lb/> addition, the activities with signature substrates of the par-<lb/>ental GSTs are suppressed, e.g., the tSBO and cyanoDMNG<lb/> activities (Table I). It would appear that the formative attri-<lb/>butes in the present case involve a combination of enhanced<lb/> and suppressed properties.<lb/> Residue 210 is a pivotal determinant in the functional<lb/> clustering of the GST M1/M2 variants<lb/> A particularly noteworthy finding was that most of the var-<lb/>iants in the yellow cluster had M1-like structures, in which<lb/> the active-site residue Ser210 is replaced by Thr. This minor<lb/> structural difference of one methylene group has previously<lb/> been shown to cause dramatic alterations of the catalytic<lb/> properties in the Mu class GSTs (Norrgård et al., 2006).<lb/> Further variations from the parental amino acids in position<lb/> 210 were not found among the sequenced mutants from the<lb/> library.<lb/> Residue 210 is particularly important with respect to the<lb/> activity with epoxide substrates (Ivarsson and Mannervik,<lb/> 2005). GST M1-1, as well as GST M2-2 with a Thr210Ser<lb/> mutation, has high activity with epoxides, but low activity<lb/> with the same substrates when Ser is changed into Thr<lb/> (Ivarsson and Mannervik, 2005). The activities of the<lb/> sequenced mutants with NPG and tSBO are in general agree-<lb/>ment with these previous findings (Table I). The epoxide<lb/> EPNP is an exception, in affording good activity also with<lb/> Thr in position 210. The activity with the organic isothiocya-<lb/>nate PEITC is clearly also dependent on Ser in the active<lb/> site, as evidenced by comparison of GST M1-1 and variant<lb/> 383 (Table I).<lb/> In the naturally occurring Mu class GSTs, the residue in<lb/> this position has been identified as hypervariable and under-<lb/>going positive selection in evolution (Ivarsson et al., 2003;<lb/> Norrgård et al., 2006). The present results, from a completely<lb/> different approach, underscore the functional importance of<lb/> residue 210 and suggest that, in the Mu class GSTs, mutation<lb/> of this residue may provide access to altered activity profiles<lb/> by evolution.<lb/> In summary, the present investigation provides an<lb/> approach to handling the problem of varying expressivity<lb/> among mutants in the mining of an enzyme library for novel<lb/> substrate-activity profiles. The multivariate analysis of the<lb/> experimental data established that the crossing of GST M1-1<lb/> and GST M2-2 leads to a minimum of three distributions of<lb/> functional recombinants, which can be regarded as molecular<lb/> quasi-species. Assays with multiple alternative substrates<lb/> provide substrate-activity signatures characterizing members<lb/> of the different distributions. The sequence analyses of<lb/> representatives of the distributions corroborate the conclusion<lb/> drawn from functional studies.<lb/> Supplementary data<lb/> Color versions of Figures 1, 4, 5, 6, 8, 9 and 10 are available<lb/> online at http://proeng.oxfordjournals.org.<lb/> 
			
		</body>
				
		<back>	
			
			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements<lb/> We are grateful to Dr W.G. Bardsley, Manchester, UK for generously giving<lb/> guidance in the data analysis and providing subroutines in Simfit for our<lb/> needs. We also thank Birgit Olin for advice on protein purification. The<lb/> Swedish Research Council, the Swedish Cancer Society, and the Carl<lb/> Trygger Foundation supported this work.<lb/><lb/></div> 
					
			<listBibl>Aharoni,A., Griffiths,A.D. and Tawfik,D.S. (2005) Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol.,<lb/> 9, 210–216.<lb/> Anantharaman,V., Aravind,L. and Koonin,E.V. (2003) Curr. Opin. Chem.<lb/> Biol., 7, 12–20.<lb/> Aravind,L., Iyer,L.M. and Koonin,E.V. (2006) Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol., 16,<lb/> 409–419.<lb/> Armstrong,R.N. (1997) Chem. Res. Toxicol., 10, 2– 18.<lb/> Bloom,J.D., Meyer,M.M., Meinhold,P., Otey,C.R., MacMillan,D. and<lb/> Arnold,F.H. (2005) Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol., 15, 447– 452.<lb/> Choi,I.G. and Kim,S.H. (2006) Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 103,<lb/> 14056–14061.<lb/> Comstock,K.E., Widersten,M., Hao,X.-Y., Henner,W.D. and Mannervik,B.<lb/> (1994) Arch. Biochem. Biophys., 311, 487 –495.<lb/> Eigen,M., McCaskill,J. and Schuster,P. (1988) J. Phys. Chem., 92,<lb/> 6881– 6891.<lb/> Eklund,B.I., Edalat,M., Stenberg,G. and Mannervik,B. (2002) Anal.<lb/> Biochem., 309, 102–108.<lb/> Emrén,L.O., Kurtovic,S., Runarsdottir,A., Larsson,A-K. and Mannervik,B.<lb/> (2006) Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 103, 10866– 10870.<lb/> Farinas,E.T., Bulter,T. and Arnold,F.H. (2001) Curr. Opin. Biotechnol., 12,<lb/> 545–551.<lb/> Habig,W.H., Pabst,M.J. and Jakoby,W.B. (1974) J. Biol. Chem., 249,<lb/> 7130– 7139.<lb/> Halgren,T.A. (1999) J. Comput. Chem., 20, 730– 748.<lb/> Hansson,L.O., Bolton-Grob,R., Massoud,T. and Mannervik,B. (1999a)<lb/> J. Mol. Biol., 287, 265–276.<lb/> Hansson,L.O., Bolton-Grob,R., Widersten,M. and Mannervik,B. (1999b)<lb/> Protein Sci., 8, 2742– 2750.<lb/> Hao,X.-Y., Castro,V.M., Bergh,J., Sundström,B. and Mannervik,B. (1994)<lb/> Biochim. Biophys. Acta, 1225, 223– 230.<lb/> Ivarsson,Y. and Mannervik,B. (2005) Protein Eng. Des. Sel., 18, 607–616.<lb/> Ivarsson,Y., Mackey,A.J., Edalat,M., Pearson,W.R. and Mannervik,B. (2003)<lb/> J. Biol. Chem., 278, 8733– 8738.<lb/> Jensen,D.E. and Stelman,G.J. (1987) Carcinogenesis, 8, 1791–1800.<lb/> Johansson,A-S., Bolton-Grob,R. and Mannervik,B. (1999) Protein Expr.<lb/> Purif., 17, 105–112.<lb/> Josephy,P.D. and Mannervik,B. (2006) Molecular Toxicology. Oxford<lb/> University Press, Inc., New York.<lb/> Keen,J.H. and Jakoby,W.B. (1978) J. Biol. Chem., 253, 5654–5657.<lb/> Kolm,R.H., Danielson,U.H., Zhang,Y.S., Talalay,P. and Mannervik,B.<lb/> (1995) Biochem. J., 311, 453–459.<lb/> Koonin,E.V., Mushegian,A.R., Tatusov,R.L., Altschul,S.F., Bryant,S.H.,<lb/> Bork,P. and Valencia,A. (1994) Protein Sci, 3, 2045– 2054.<lb/> Krzanowski,W.J. (2000) Principles of Multivariate Analysis -A Users&apos;s<lb/> Perspective. Oxford University Press, Inc., New York.<lb/> Larsson,A-K., Emrén,L.O., Bardsley,W.G. and Mannervik,B. (2004) Protein<lb/> Eng. Des. Sel., 17, 49–55.<lb/> Mannervik,B. (2005) Methods Enzymol., 401, 254– 265.<lb/> Meyer,M.M., Hochrein,L. and Arnold,F.H. (2006) Protein Eng. Des. Sel.,<lb/> 19, 563–570.<lb/> Ness,J.E., Welch,M., Giver,L., Bueno,M., Cherry,J.R., Borchert,T.V.,<lb/> Stemmer,W.P. and Minshull,J. (1999) Nat. Biotechnol., 17, 893– 896.<lb/> Ness,J.E., Del Cardayre,S.B., Minshull,J. and Stemmer,W.P. (2000) Adv.<lb/> Protein Chem., 55, 261–292.<lb/> Norrgård,M.A., Ivarsson,Y., Tars,K. and Mannervik,B. (2006) Proc. Natl.<lb/> Acad. Sci. USA, 103, 4876– 4881.<lb/> Orengo,C.A. and Thornton,J.M. (2005) Annu. Rev. Biochem., 74, 867–900.<lb/> 
				
				<note place="headnote">Multivariate analysis of a GST library<lb/> </note>
				
				<page>255<lb/> </page>
				
				<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from<lb/> </note>
				
				Otey,C.R., Silberg,J.J., Voigt,C.A., Endelman,J.B., Bandara,G. and<lb/> Arnold,F.H. (2004) Chem. Biol., 11, 309 –318.<lb/> Ricci,G., Caccuri,A.M., Lo Bello,M., Pastore,A., Piemonte,F. and<lb/> Federici,G. (1994) Anal. Biochem., 218, 463– 465.<lb/> Shokeer,A., Larsson,A-K. and Mannervik,B. (2005) Biochem. J., 388,<lb/> 387–392.<lb/> Svendsen,A. (ed.) (2004) Enzyme Functionality: Design, Engineering, and<lb/> Screening. Marcel Dekker Inc., New York.<lb/> Taly,V., Urban,P., Truan,G. and Pompon,D. (2007) Biochim. Biophys. Acta,<lb/> 1770, 446–457.<lb/> Valetti,F. and Gilardi,G. (2004) Nat. Prod. Rep., 21, 490– 511.<lb/> White,R.H. (2006) J. Bacteriol., 188, 3431–3432.<lb/></listBibl> 
				
				<div type="annex">Received March 12, 2007; revised March 12, 2007;<lb/> accepted March 14, 2007<lb/> Edited by Frances Arnold<lb/></div> 
				
				<note place="headnote">S.Kurtovic et al.<lb/> </note>
				
				<page>256<lb/> </page>
				
				<note place="footnote">at European Patent Office on May 27, 2011<lb/> peds.oxfordjournals.org<lb/> Downloaded from </note>

			</back>
	</text>
</tei>
