<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Spatio-temporal relays control layer specificity of motion-direction sensitive <lb/>neurons in Drosophila <lb/>Holger Apitz 1 and Iris Salecker 1,* <lb/>1 Visual Circuit Assembly Laboratory, The Francis Crick Institute, London NW1 1AT, UK <lb/>* Correspondence should be addressed to I.S. (iris.salecker@crick.ac.uk) <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Visual motion detection in sighted animals is essential to guide behavioral actions <lb/>ensuring their survival. In Drosophila, motion direction is first detected by T4/T5 <lb/>neurons. Their axons innervate four lobula plate layers tuned to the four cardinal <lb/>motion directions. How T4/T5 neurons with layer-specific representation of motion-<lb/>direction preferences are specified during development is unknown. We show that <lb/>diffusible Wingless (Wg) between adjacent neuroepithelia induces its own expression to <lb/>form secondary signaling centers. These activate decapentaplegic (dpp) in apposing <lb/>tertiary domains dedicated to producing layer 3/4-specific T4/T5 neurons. In the <lb/>absence of Dpp signaling, T4/T5 neurons adopt the default layer 1/2 fate. Dpp signaling <lb/>induces the expression of the T-box transcription factor Optomotor-blind (Omb), <lb/>serving as a relay to postmitotic neurons. Omb-mediated repression of Dachshund <lb/>transforms layer 1/2-into layer 3/4-specific neurons. Hence, spatio-temporal relay <lb/>mechanisms, bridging the distances between neuroepithelial domains and their <lb/>postmitotic progeny, implement T4/T5 neuron layer-specificity. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Visual signals received by the retina are generally not stationary because objects in the <lb/>environment and/or the bodies of animals move. To detect motion, visual circuits perform <lb/>complex spatio-temporal comparisons that convert luminance changes initially collected by <lb/>photoreceptors into signals containing information about direction or speed. Despite the <lb/>seemingly divergent anatomy of visual systems in vertebrates and insects, they display <lb/>remarkable parallels in the computations underlying motion vision and the neuronal elements <lb/>performing them 1,2 . In most sighted animals, this involves neurons that respond to motion <lb/>signals in specific directions. Direction-selectivity emerges from differences in the <lb/>connectivity of their dendrites 2 . Motion-direction preferences by their axons are represented <lb/>by layer-specific innervation 3-8 . Thus, anatomical characteristics such as layer-specificity <lb/>seem to be intricately linked with motion-directionality. However, how these are implemented <lb/>during circuit development is poorly understood. <lb/>The Drosophila visual system has emerged as a powerful model for elucidating the <lb/>neural circuits and computations underlying motion detection. Photoreceptors (R-cells) in the <lb/>retina extend axons into the optic lobe consisting of the lamina, medulla, lobula plate and <lb/>lobula (Fig. 1a). Neuronal projections in these ganglia are organized into retinotopically <lb/>arranged columnar units. The medulla, lobula plate and lobula are additionally subdivided <lb/>into synaptic layers. They are innervated by more than a 100 neuronal subtypes that extract <lb/>distinct visual features, such as motion, in parallel pathways 9 . T4 and T5 lobula plate neurons <lb/>are the first motion direction-sensitive elements in this circuit 6,10 . They represent the most <lb/>numerous subtypes of the optic lobe (~5300 neurons/hemisphere) 11 . While T4 dendrites <lb/>arborize within the medulla layer 10, T5 dendrites are found in the lobula layer Lo1. T4/T5 <lb/>axons project to one of four synaptic lobula plate layers, thereby defining four different <lb/>neuron subtypes each 12 (Fig. 1a). Axonal projections segregate according to their motion-<lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>direction preferences. Thus, front-to-back, back-to-front, upward and downward cardinal <lb/>motion directions are represented by adjacent lobula plate layers 1-4 5,6 . T4 neurons are part of <lb/>the ON motion detection pathway reporting brightness increments, while T5 neurons are part <lb/>of the OFF pathway reporting brightness decrements 6 . Distinct sets of neurons in the lamina <lb/>and medulla relay ON and OFF information to T4 and T5 neurons 2,6,13 . Direction-selectivity <lb/>emerges within T4/T5 dendrites and involves the non-linear integration of input from these <lb/>upstream neurons for enhancement in the preferred direction and suppression in the null-<lb/>direction 10,14-16 . Dendritic arbors of the four T4 neuron subtypes have characteristic <lb/>orientations, that correlate with the direction preference of lobula plate layers innervated by <lb/>their axons 16-19 . Thus, direction-selectivity involves the establishment of neuron subtypes, <lb/>each with distinct spatial connectivities. Here, we address when and how layer-specificity of <lb/>T4 and T5 neuron subtypes is determined during development. <lb/>Optic lobe neurons originate from two horseshoe-shaped neuroepithelia, called the <lb/>outer and inner proliferation centers (OPC and IPC; Fig. 1b) 20,21 . Both neuroepithelia are <lb/>derived from the embryonic optic lobe placode 22 and expand by symmetric cell divisions <lb/>during early larval development 23,24 . At the late 2 nd instar larval stage, neurogenesis <lb/>commences first in the OPC, followed by the IPC 21 . Laterally, the OPC gives rise to lamina <lb/>neurons. Neuroepithelial (NE) cells from the medial edge of the OPC transform in a wave of <lb/>neurogenesis into medulla neural stem cells, called neuroblasts (Nbs), which undergo <lb/>asymmetric divisions to self-renew and produce ganglion mother cells (GMCs). These in turn <lb/>divide to generate two neurons or glia 23,25 . Furthermore, apposing the OPC, two dorsal and <lb/>ventral NE domains, called the glial precursor cell (GPC) areas, produce specific neuron <lb/>subtypes associated with all ganglia 26,27 . <lb/>The IPC gives rise to lobula and lobula plate neurons, including T4/T5 neurons. Our <lb/>recent studies showed that NE cells in one domain, called the proximal (p-) IPC, convert into <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>progenitors in an epithelial-mesenchymal transition (EMT)-like process 24,28 . Progenitors <lb/>migrate to a second proliferative zone, the distal (d-) IPC, where they mature into Nbs. These <lb/>transition through two competence windows to first produce C&amp;T neurons, corresponding to <lb/>C2 and C3 ascending neurons connecting the medulla and the lamina, as well as T2/T2a and <lb/>T3 neurons connecting the medulla and the lobula, followed by the formation of T4/T5 lobula <lb/>plate neurons (Fig. 1a,b). Cross-regulatory interactions between Dichaete (D) and Tailless <lb/>(Tll) control the switch in Nb competence defined by the sequential expression of the <lb/>proneural bHLH transcription factors Asense (Ase) and Atonal (Ato). The latter is co-<lb/>expressed with the retinal determination protein Dachshund (Dac). However, the molecular <lb/>mechanisms that control layer-specific T4/T5 neuron subtype identities within this sequence <lb/>of developmental events occurring at different locations have remained elusive. <lb/>T4/T5 neuron diversity could be achieved by postmitotic combinatorial transcription <lb/>factor codes upstream of guidance molecules. The positions of cell bodies in the cortex and <lb/>neurites in the neuropil within the developing lobula plate indicated that T4/T5 neurons <lb/>employ a birth-order dependent mechanism for retinotopic map formation 21,24 . Thus, layer-<lb/>specificities of T4/T5 neurons could also be determined by temporal differences in a common <lb/>postmitotic differentiation program, similar to the birth-order dependent R-cell growth cone <lb/>segregation strategy described in the medulla 29,30 . Here, we provide evidence for another <lb/>mechanism, whereby layer-specificity of T4/T5 neurons is determined early in the p-IPC <lb/>neuroepithelium. Their specification depends on two relay mechanisms involving Wnt and <lb/>Bone morphogenetic protein (Bmp) signaling and transcription factor interactions. These <lb/>establish and translate spatial patterning of NE cells into postmitotic neuronal subtype <lb/>identities to bridge distances created by this particular mode of neurogenesis. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>RESULTS <lb/>Formation of T4/T5 neurons for lobula plate layers 3/4 depends on Wg secretion <lb/>Wnt family members are evolutionary conserved signaling proteins that orchestrate the <lb/>patterning and growth of tissues during development. Recent findings showed that flies <lb/>expressing membrane-tethered instead of normally secreted Wingless (Wg) were viable and <lb/>had remarkably normal bodies and well-patterned, albeit slightly smaller wings 31 . This <lb/>indicated that the long-range spreading of Wg is not essential for the development of many <lb/>tissues. As the general fitness of these flies was reduced, this study also suggested that Wg <lb/>release could be required in tissues other than imaginal discs. In the visual system, Wg is <lb/>expressed and required in the GPC areas for neuron specification 26,27,32,33 . To explore whether <lb/>Wg could play a role in the IPC and whether the spreading of this signaling molecule is <lb/>essential, we examined brains of adult homozygous flies, engineered to solely express Wg <lb/>fused to the type 2 transmembrane protein Neurotactin 31 (wg{KO;NRT-wg}; Fig. 1c). We <lb/>uncovered a specific and highly penetrant phenotype in the lobula plate (Fig. 1d): unlike in <lb/>controls (Fig. 1e; n=13/13), either one (Fig. 1f; n=18/30) or two (Fig. 1g; n=12/30) of the <lb/>four lobula plate layers were missing. Moreover, T4/T5 neuron numbers were reduced by <lb/>approximately 25% in three-layered and 50% in two-layered samples, respectively (Fig. 1h). <lb/>To determine which layers were affected, optic lobes were immunolabeled with the cell <lb/>surface molecule Connectin, a specific marker of lobula plate layers 3/4. In contrast to <lb/>controls (Fig. 1d,i; n=26/26), Connectin was expressed either only in one (Fig. 1j; n=16/30) <lb/>or none (Fig. 1k; n=14/30) of the lobula plate layers in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies. These results <lb/>suggest that the T4/T5 neurons innervating layers 3/4 were preferentially affected in flies <lb/>solely expressing membrane-tethered Wg. <lb/>To elucidate the underlying causes of this phenotype, we examined the expression of <lb/>wild-type Wg in the 3 rd instar larval optic lobe. In line with previous reports 27 , Wg protein was <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>detected in the dorsal and ventral GPC areas adjacent to the OPC (Fig. 1l,n,o). Apposing the <lb/>ventral p-IPC, Wg was expressed in surface (s-) IPC NE cells, which give rise to two lobula <lb/>neuron clusters 24 . Additionally, Wg was expressed in a small Nb cluster adjacent to the dorsal <lb/>p-IPC (Fig. 1m-o). We also used the perdurance of wg-Gal4 to mark the progeny of these <lb/>domains (Supplementary Fig. 1a-d). This revealed that wg is not produced in T4/T5 neurons <lb/>or their progenitors in the d-IPC and p-IPC, suggesting a non-autonomous requirement of Wg <lb/>for the development or survival of T4/T5 neurons that innervate layers 3/4. <lb/>Wg secretion from the GPC areas is required to induce wg in the s-IPC <lb/>We next asked how the prevention of Wg release might cause the lobula plate-specific defect. <lb/>In the GPC areas, wg blocks expression of the transcriptional regulator Homothorax (Hth), a <lb/>member of the temporal series in the OPC 33 . We observed that Hth expression was correctly <lb/>suppressed in the GPC of wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, suggesting that NRT-Wg functions as wild-<lb/>type Wg in this context (Supplementary Fig. 2a,b). However, examining the IPC, we noted <lb/>that NRT-Wg expression was absent in the s-IPC (Fig. 2a,b). This NE domain and its <lb/>progeny developed normally, because Hth was expressed and two distinct lobula neuron <lb/>clusters were formed (Supplementary Fig. 2c-f). We considered therefore the possibility that <lb/>Wg originating in the GPC areas could induce Wg expression in the s-IPC. Indeed, Wg <lb/>protein and reporter gene expression were detected in the GPC before the s-IPC at the late 2 nd <lb/>instar larval stage (Fig. 2c,d). Furthermore, wg expression in the s-IPC of wg{KO;NRT-wg} <lb/>flies was lost at the mid 3 rd instar larval stage, when wg normally begins to be expressed in <lb/>these NE cells (Fig. 2e,f). <lb/>Failure of GPC-derived NRT-Wg to induce NRT-Wg expression in the s-IPC could <lb/>conceivably not be due to lack of Wg release but instead to sub-optimal signaling activity of <lb/>the NRT-Wg protein. To address this possibility, we asked whether boosting NRT-Wg <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>expression could overcome observed defects. This was tested by combining a UAS-NRT-wg <lb/>transgene, previously shown to be highly active 34 with the knock-in null allele wg{KO;Gal4}, <lb/>serving also as a driver that restricts activation to endogenous expression domains 31 . UAS-<lb/>FLP and wg{KO;FRT wg + FRT NRT-wg} 31 were introduced to ensure that the endogenous <lb/>locus only produced NRT-Wg following the induction of recombination events. Finally, a <lb/>tub-Gal80 ts transgene was used to control the timing of expression. Thus, at a restrictive <lb/>temperature, Wg expression is normal and no NRT-Wg is produced. After a shift to a <lb/>permissive temperature, UAS-NRT-wg is activated and the wg allele switches to expressing <lb/>NRT-Wg. We found that following a temperature shift at the mid 3 rd instar larval stage, NRT-<lb/>Wg was expressed in both the GPC areas and the s-IPC (Fig. 2g; n=16/16). However, <lb/>following an early temperature shift at the 1 st instar larval stage, no expression could be <lb/>detected in the s-IPC in the majority of samples (76%; n=26/34) (Fig. 2h). We suggest that <lb/>this partial phenotype is due to imperfect allele switching, i.e. residual wild-type Wg <lb/>produced by the GPC, and that Wg release from the GPC is required between the 1 st and mid <lb/>3 rd instar larval stage for induction of Wg expression in the s-IPC. Thus, impaired Wg release <lb/>and not reduced signaling activity accounts for the s-IPC-specific loss of NRT-Wg expression <lb/>in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies. <lb/>Next, we performed a converse allele switching experiments using wg{KO;FRT NRT-<lb/>wg FRT wg + } to express wild-type Wg in a wg{KO;NRT-wg} background 31 . We used <lb/>R46E01-Gal4 (Supplementary Fig. 2g,h) and UAS-FLP to induce recombination specifically <lb/>in the GPC areas. We observed that expression of wild-type wg in the GPC areas rescued the <lb/>s-IPC-specific loss of NRT-Wg (Fig. 2i,j; n=16/23), demonstrating that Wg release <lb/>specifically from the GPC areas is essential. <lb/>Consistent with Wg signaling-dependent induction of wg expression, Wg signaling <lb/>was activated in the s-IPC, because the Wg target genes frizzled 3 (fz3; Fig. 2k) and notum <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>were expressed (Fig. 2l). Moreover, Wg expression in the s-IPC was abolished following the <lb/>simultaneous knockdown of the Wg receptors frizzled (fz) and frizzled 2 (fz2) (Fig. 2m,n) in <lb/>the IPC by combining the fas3-Gal4 driver 24 (cf. Supplementary Fig. 6l) with UAS-RNA <lb/>interference (RNAi) transgenes. Together, these data show that Wg released from the GPC <lb/>areas is required to induce wg in the s-IPC (Fig. 2o). <lb/>wg in the s-IPC is required to induce dpp in p-IPC subdomains <lb/>How can wg expression in the s-IPC control T4/T5 neurogenesis in the p-IPC/d-IPC? The <lb/>Drosophila Bmp family member Decapentaplegic (Dpp) is a known target of wg in the OPC <lb/>and is expressed adjacent to the GPC areas in dorsal and ventral OPC subdomains 27 (Fig. 3a). <lb/>In the IPC, both genes displayed similar apposing expression domains: wg expression in the s-<lb/>IPC and the small Nb lineage was detected adjacent to dpp-positive ventral and dorsal p-IPC <lb/>subdomains (Fig. 3b). Furthermore, dpp reporter gene expression was maintained in the two <lb/>progenitor streams arising from these subdomains 24 (Fig. 3c,d). Consistent with stepwise <lb/>inductive events, dpp expression in the p-IPC was not found prior to wg expression in the s-<lb/>IPC at the late 2 nd instar larval stage (Fig. 3e). Furthermore, fz3 (Fig. 2k) and notum (Fig. 2l) <lb/>were expressed similarly to dpp in p-IPC subdomains and progenitor streams. In <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, dpp-lacZ in the p-IPC was either absent (Fig. 3h; n=16/32) or showed <lb/>only residual labeling in one progenitor stream (Supplementary Fig. 3a; n=16/32), in line <lb/>with the penetrance and expressivity of phenotypes observed in adults. By contrast, <lb/>expression in the OPC was unaffected, suggesting that releasable Wg is not required in this <lb/>region (Fig. 3g,h). Constitutively-active Wg signaling induced by IPC-specific expression of <lb/>Armadillo S10 resulted in ectopic dpp-lacZ labeling (Fig. 3i; Supplementary Fig. 3b), <lb/>confirming that dpp is a Wg target in the p-IPC. wg is required in the s-IPC, and not the GPC <lb/>areas, because IPC-specific wg knockdown abolished dpp-lacZ labeling (Fig. 3j). Since Dpp <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>signaling mediates EMT of migratory progenitors in the Dpp-expression domains 24 , cell <lb/>streams from these areas failed to form in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies and following IPC-specific <lb/>knockdown of wg and the Dpp type I receptor thickveins (tkv) (Fig. 3h,j,k). Although the <lb/>overall d-IPC morphology was altered (Supplementary Fig. 3c-f), progenitors and Nbs <lb/>generated from the remainder of the p-IPC showed wild-type cellular marker expression <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 3g-n). In adults, similar to wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, lobula plate layers <lb/>3/4 were absent following IPC-specific knockdown of fz, fz2 or tkv (Fig. 3l-n). Hence, wg <lb/>from the s-IPC regulates dpp expression in adjacent p-IPC subdomains and EMT of <lb/>progenitors that mature into Nbs producing T4/T5 neurons for layers 3/4 (Fig. 3o). <lb/>T4/T5 neurons for layers 3/4 originate from the Dpp-expression domain <lb/>To provide direct evidence that T4/T5 neurons innervating layers 3/4 specifically originated <lb/>from the Dpp-positive subdomains in the p-IPC, we next conducted lineage-tracing <lb/>experiments. Because dpp-Gal4 is expressed in the entire optic lobe, we searched for a driver <lb/>with activity restricted to the Dpp expression domain of the IPC and identified R45H05-Gal4 <lb/>as a suitable candidate (Fig. 4a). Expression is controlled by an enhancer fragment of <lb/>dorsocross 1, which encodes a T box domain containing transcription factor and a known <lb/>target gene of Dpp 35 . Reporter gene expression was detected in dorsal and ventral p-IPC <lb/>subdomains, cell streams, Nbs and postmitotic progeny in larval optic lobes and persisted <lb/>throughout pupal development into adulthood, where it specifically labeled T4/T5 neurons <lb/>innervating layers 3/4 but not layers 1/2 (Supplementary Fig. 4a,b; Fig. 4b). As expression <lb/>was weak, we used the FLPout approach in conjunction with tub-Gal80 ts to permanently label <lb/>R45H05-Gal4 expressing progeny throughout development, and again solely detected T4/T5 <lb/>neurons projecting into layers 3/4 (Fig. 4c). Finally, as an independent confirmation, we used <lb/>the Flybow approach to generate T4/T5 neuron clones labeled in different colors and <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>observed that clones consisted of T4/T5 neurons innervating either layers 1/2 or 3/4 but not <lb/>both (Fig. 4d; n=43 clones in 26 optic lobes). <lb/>In lineage tracing experiments using R45H05-Gal4, clones included C2, the T2-<lb/>variant T2a and/or T3 neurons, as judged by their characteristic cell body positions and their <lb/>terminals in the lamina and lobula, respectively (Fig. 4e). While C3, T2 and T3 neurons were <lb/>not affected (Supplementary Fig. 4d-j), C2 neurons were fully or partially absent in <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies with two or three remaining lobula plate layers, respectively (Fig. 4f,g; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 4c). Due to the lack of specific markers, we were unable to conduct tests <lb/>for T2a neurons. Together these experiments indicate that T4/T5 neurons innervating layers <lb/>3/4, C2 and possibly T2a neurons are specifically derived from the dorsal and ventral Dpp-<lb/>expression domains, while the p-IPC core generates T4/T5 for layers 1/2, as well as C3, T2 <lb/>and T3 neurons (Fig. 4h). <lb/>dac and ato mediate the switch from T2 and T3 to layer 1/2 innervating T4/T5 neurons <lb/>We next asked when and how layer-specific T4/T5 neurons become distinct during <lb/>development. Dac and Ato are expressed in the second Nb competence window of the d-IPC 24 <lb/>(Fig. 5a). We observed that Dac is maintained in all T4/T5 neurons at the 3 rd instar larval <lb/>stage, albeit with varying expression levels (Fig. 5b). However, Dac was only found in ~50% <lb/>of T4/T5 neurons in adults (Fig. 5c; cf. Fig. 7h). The enhancer trap dac p7d23 -Gal4 line <lb/>faithfully reported Dac expression in T4/T5 neurons throughout development (Fig. 5d; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 5a) and remained active in neurons innervating layers 1/2 (Fig. 5e). <lb/>Thus, Dac is downregulated in layer 3/4 innervating T4/T5 neurons and maintained in <lb/>neurons projecting to layers 1/2 (Fig. 5f). <lb/>To examine the possible role of dac in distinguishing layer 1/2 and 3/4 neuron <lb/>subtypes, we used MARCM to generate dac 1 mutant T4/T5 neurons labeled with the dac <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>enhancer Gal4 line R9B10-Gal4 (Supplementary Fig. 5b,c). In adults, some of these dac <lb/>mutant neurons adopted T2/T3 morphologies (cf. Fig. 5f) with neurites extending into <lb/>medulla layer M9 and higher (Fig. 5g,h), as well as synaptic terminals in lobula layers Lo2 <lb/>and Lo3 (Fig. 5i,j). This suggested that mutant neurons adopted features of neurons born in <lb/>the first d-IPC Nb competence window. To assess potential redundancy, we performed dac <lb/>and ato knockdown experiments using validated UAS-RNAi transgenes (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 5d-g). While dac or ato single knockdown revealed potential roles in the distinction of <lb/>layer 3 from layer 4 neurons (Supplementary Fig. 5h-j), simultaneous knockdown caused <lb/>striking defects. In controls, T4/T5 neurons formed four synaptic layers in the lobula plate <lb/>and Fas3-positive dendrites in medulla layer M10 and lobula layer Lo1 (Fig. 5k,m), <lb/>respectively. In contrast, dac and ato knockdown caused the loss of neurons with T4/T5 <lb/>neuron morphologies and in consequence an undersized lobula plate neuropil (Fig. 5l,n; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 5k). Remaining neurons innervated the medulla and lobula, consistent <lb/>with T2/T3 neuron morphologies. <lb/>Therefore, dac and ato are required for the transition between Nb competence states in <lb/>the d-IPC and the switch to T4/T5 neuron formation. Layer 1/2 innervating Dac-positive <lb/>T4/T5 neurons could represent a default fate while the subsequent downregulation of Dac is <lb/>required for specifying layer 3/4 innervating T4/T5 neurons. <lb/>Notch controls the choice between T4 and T5 neuron identity <lb/>In the OPC, Notch-dependent asymmetric GMC divisions contribute to the generation of <lb/>neuronal diversity 36 and NE patterning links these binary fate choices to differential apoptosis <lb/>in region-specific lineages 37 . We therefore assessed whether Notch signaling could mediate <lb/>the distinction of layer 1/2 and 3/4 innervating T4/T5 neurons downstream of Dpp. We did <lb/>not detect apoptotic cells in the 3 rd instar larval lobula plate when T4/T5 neurons form and <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>differentiate (Supplementary Fig. 6a). However, genetic manipulations of Notch signaling <lb/>uncovered a role for this pathway in the choice between T4 and T5 fate. Indeed, expression of <lb/>an activated, ligand-independent form of Notch (N intra ) in d-IPC Nbs during the second <lb/>competence window and their progeny using R9B10-Gal4 resulted in the absence of T4 <lb/>neurons, as revealed by the absence of dendrites in the medulla in 3 rd instar larval optic lobes <lb/>(Fig. 6a,b). Conversely, IPC-specific knockdown of the transcriptional regulator Suppressor <lb/>of Hairless (Su(H)) using R17B05-Gal4 caused the loss of T5 neurons in adults, whereas T4 <lb/>neurons were not impaired (Fig. 6c,d; Supplementary Fig. 6f). Adult flies with Notch <lb/>activation exhibited a mild phenotype, in which only the oldest T4 neurons were affected <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 6b-h). In Su(H) knockdown experiments, lobula plate layers 3 and 4 <lb/>could not be discriminated (Supplementary Fig. 6i). This phenotype was associated with <lb/>severe disorganization of the lobula plate and lobula neuropils, likely because of an early <lb/>requirement of Notch in p-IPC NE cells during the 3 rd instar larval stage 28 (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 6j,k). Hence, Notch controls the choice between T4 and T5 neuron fate (Fig. 6e), but not <lb/>between Dac-positive layer 1/2 innervating and Dac-negative layer 3/4 innervating T4/T5 <lb/>neurons. <lb/>Dpp-dependent specification of T4/T5 neurons for layers 3/4 is mediated by omb <lb/>Our data suggest that the distinction between layer 1/2 and 3/4 innervating T4/T5 neurons is <lb/>controlled by a Notch-independent mechanism. While dpp reporter gene activity extended <lb/>from the p-IPC to the d-IPC, phospho-Mad (pMad) labeling was restricted to p-IPC NE cells <lb/>(Fig. 6f). Consistently, knockdown experiments using Gal4 driver lines with progressively <lb/>restricted activities (Supplementary Fig. 6l-n) revealed a requirement of tkv for layer 3/4 <lb/>neuron formation in p-IPC NE cells (cf. Fig. 3n), but not in d-IPC Nbs and T4/T5 neurons <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 6o-q). <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Therefore, an additional mechanism must relay Dpp activity in p-IPC NE cells to <lb/>distant postmitotic T4/T5 neurons. The T-box transcription factor Optomotor blind (Omb) is a <lb/>target of Dpp in the p-IPC 24 . In 3 rd instar larval brains, Omb expression is maintained in <lb/>progenitors, Nbs and subsets of T4/T5 neurons derived from the Dpp-positive p-IPC <lb/>subdomains (Fig. 6g). Expression persisted in adult T4/T5 neuron subsets (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 6r). In wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, omb expression was specifically absent in the p-IPC and <lb/>progeny, but unaffected in the OPC (Fig. 6h,i). <lb/>To determine the function of omb, we conducted knockdown experiments using fas3-<lb/>Gal4 and two validated UAS-RNAi transgenes (Supplementary Fig. 6s-v). Experimental <lb/>animals were raised at 18°C and shifted to 29°C at the early 3 rd instar larval stage, because <lb/>omb is expressed in the embryonic optic lobe placode and null mutations cause severe <lb/>disorganization or complete loss of adult optic lobes 38 . Under these conditions, omb <lb/>knockdown did neither affect dpp expression nor the EMT of progenitors from the p-IPC <lb/>(Fig. 6j,k). However in adults, lobula plate layers 3/4 were absent (Fig. 6l,m). Notably, in <lb/>contrast to tkv knockdown, omb downregulation using Gal4 lines with progressively restricted <lb/>activities revealed that this transcription factor is required in postmitotic T4/T5 neurons for <lb/>layer 3/4 neuron specification (Fig. 6n,o). Thus, omb could relay subdomain-specific Dpp <lb/>signaling effects in p-IPC NE cells across intermediate cellular states, i.e. migratory <lb/>progenitors, Nbs and GMCs, to T4/T5 progeny (Fig. 6p). <lb/>Omb-mediated repression of Dac converts layer 1/2 into layer 3/4 T4/T5 neurons <lb/>Finally, we assessed whether Omb could be the factor responsible for downregulating Dac. At <lb/>the 3 rd instar larval stage, Omb was co-expressed with high levels of Dac in young and low <lb/>levels in older T4/T5 neurons, respectively (Fig. 7a). From 24 h after puparium formation <lb/>(APF) (Fig. 7b) to adulthood (Supplementary Fig. 7a), Omb and Dac showed mutually <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>exclusive expression in T4/T5 neurons. While Dac was maintained in ~50% of adult T4/T5 <lb/>neurons in controls (Fig. 7c,h), 95% of T4/T5 neurons expressed Dac and adopted layer 1/2 <lb/>identity following omb knockdown (Figs. 6o,7d,h). Conversely when omb was over-<lb/>expressed, none of the T4/T5 neurons expressed Dac and all acquired layer 3/4 identity (Fig. <lb/>7e,j). Under both conditions, many T4/T5 neurons underwent apoptosis at the 3 rd instar larval <lb/>stage (Supplementary Fig. 7b-d). Consistently in adults, their numbers were reduced by <lb/>33% and 48%, respectively (Fig. 7h). This suggests that excessive numbers of T4/T5 neurons <lb/>either for layers 1/2 or 3/4 could compete for limited trophic support. To demonstrate that <lb/>omb is indeed sufficient, we took advantage of wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, in which all T4/T5 <lb/>neurons adopted layer 1/2 identity and Dac was expressed in 97% of these (Fig. 7f,h; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 7e,f). In this background, omb over-expression only mildly affected <lb/>neuron numbers (19% reduction) and was sufficient to downregulate Dac (Fig. 7g,h). <lb/>Importantly, concomitant upregulation of Connectin suggested that these differentiated into <lb/>layer 3/4 innervating T4/T5 neurons (Fig. 7i,k). Thus, omb is required and sufficient for <lb/>specifying T4/T5 neurons innervating layers 3/4 by downregulating Dac (Fig. 7l). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The spread of Wg is dispensable for patterning of many tissues 31 . However, our studies <lb/>uncovered a highly specific requirement for diffusible Wg in the nervous system, where it <lb/>orchestrates the formation of T4/T5 neurons innervating lobula plate layers 3/4. Their <lb/>generation depends on two inductive mechanisms (Fig. 7m) that are relayed in space and <lb/>time. The spatial relay consists of a multistep signaling cascade across several NE domains: <lb/>Wg from the GPC areas induces wg expression in the s-IPC and likely a small Nb lineage <lb/>adjacent to ventral and dorsal p-IPC subdomains; this secondary Wg source activates dpp <lb/>expression, which in turn mediates EMT of migratory progenitors from these subdomains. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>The p-IPC core produces Dac-positive layer 1/2 specific T4/T5 neurons. By contrast, Dpp <lb/>signaling in p-IPC NE subdomains triggers a temporal relay across intermediate cellular states <lb/>by inducing omb. Omb in turn confers layer 3/4 identity to postmitotic T4/T5 neurons by <lb/>suppressing Dac. <lb/>When Wg is membrane-tethered, the very first step of this cascade is disrupted. <lb/>Several lines of evidence indicate that this defect is not caused by decreased signaling activity <lb/>of the NRT-Wg protein in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies. First, wild-type Wg signaling activity <lb/>inside the GPC areas and the adjacent OPC was not affected. Second, in allele switching <lb/>experiments, ectopic expression of a highly active UAS-NRT-wg transgene in the GPC areas <lb/>was unable to rescue the s-IPC-specific defect. By contrast, restoring wild-type wg function in <lb/>the GPC areas was sufficient to rescue, supporting the notion that Wg release and spread from <lb/>the GPC areas are required to induce its own expression in the s-IPC. <lb/>Although Wg release is essential, the range of action is likely limited. Wg expression <lb/>in the s-IPC commences at the early 3 rd instar larval stage after Wg expression in the GPC <lb/>areas, when both domains are still in close proximity. Consistently, defects in wg{KO;NRT-<lb/>wg} flies were observed from this early stage onwards. Half of the wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies <lb/>showed residual dpp expression in one progenitor stream and three lobula plate layers in 3 rd <lb/>instar larvae and adults, respectively. While this partial phenotypic penetrance is not fully <lb/>understood, NRT-wg was likely able to partially substitute for wg because of the initial close <lb/>proximity of these NE domains. Theoretically, the dpp expression defect in the p-IPC of <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies could reflect the dependence on long-range Wg from the GPC areas. <lb/>However, as we have shown, IPC-specific wg knockdown leads to loss of dpp in the p-IPC, <lb/>demonstrating that expression depends on wg in the adjacent s-IPC. Sequential Wnt signaling <lb/>has been proposed as a mechanism to explain long-range Wnt signaling activities 39,40 . <lb/>Moreover, sequentially acting primary and secondary sources of Wg have been described in <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>the developing Drosophila eye 41 , indicating that the underlying regulatory mechanism <lb/>observed in the optic lobe might be employed in several contexts. The different outcomes <lb/>when inducing wg to NRT-wg allele switching at early and late time points are consistent with <lb/>the idea that Wg secretion is required for the induction but not long-term maintenance of wg <lb/>expression in the s-IPC. In the developing optic lobe, GPC and s-IPC NE cells rapidly <lb/>become separated by compact rows of newly generated neuronal progeny. As part of a relay <lb/>system across several neuroepithelial domains, diffusible Wg may therefore be required to <lb/>bridge distances over a few cell diameters during the initial phase of neurogenesis. Notably, <lb/>the s-IPC in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies expressed Hth and generated two neuron clusters as in <lb/>wild-type, suggesting that the development and neurogenesis in this domain are independent <lb/>of wg. Thus, the sole function of wg in the s-IPC is to relay the GPC derived Wg signal to <lb/>induce dpp expression in the p-IPC. Based on the observation that Wg release is not required <lb/>in the GPC areas to induce dpp in the adjacent OPC, this secondary wg function in the s-IPC <lb/>is most likely juxtacrine. <lb/>In the OPC, three distinct mechanisms contribute to the generation of neuronal <lb/>diversity: dorso-ventral patterning of NE cells, temporal transcription factor expression in <lb/>Nbs and Notch-dependent asymmetric divisions of GMCs 36,37,42 . Compared to approximately <lb/>80 medulla neuron subtypes derived from the OPC, the specification of thirteen distinct <lb/>subtypes originating from the p-IPC appears simple. However, the mechanisms employed are <lb/>surprisingly complex and distinct. Previously, we found that cross-regulatory interactions <lb/>between D and tll regulate a Nb competence switch in the formation of early-born C2, C3, T2, <lb/>T2a and T3 neurons to the eight distinct layer-specific T4/T5 subtypes 24 . Ato and Dac were <lb/>known to be expressed in the 2 nd Nb competence window and to depend on tll, but their <lb/>precise functions remained elusive. We observed that dac mutant T4/T5 neurons adopted <lb/>early-born T2/T3 neuron morphologies. Similarly, ato mutant T4/T5 neurons develop <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>normally but display neurite connectivity defects 43 . Notably, simultaneous knockdown of dac <lb/>and ato resulted in the absence of T4/T5 neurons, demonstrating that both are required <lb/>together for the ability of d-IPC Nbs to produce a new set of neuron subtypes during the 2 nd <lb/>competence window. <lb/>Dac is initially expressed in all T4/T5 neurons but only maintained in layer 1/2 <lb/>innervating subtypes. Therefore, an essential step for the specification of layer 3/4 innervating <lb/>neurons is the downregulation of Dac and the suppression of the T4/T5 default neuron fate, <lb/>i.e. layer 1/2 identity. Although the mode of this inhibitory mechanism depends on the <lb/>outcome of the Nb-specific switching mechanism in the d-IPC, it is already primed in p-IPC <lb/>NE cells. Thus, layer-specificity and therefore motion-directionality are determined very early <lb/>in the NE precursors of T4/T5 neurons. Molecularly, it involves the Omb-mediated relay of <lb/>Dpp-dependent patterning in NE cells across intermediate cell states to postmitotic T4/T5 <lb/>neurons resulting in the repression of the layer 1/2 neuron-specific determinant Dac. In <lb/>contrast to the OPC 37 , we found no evidence for a link between NE patterning in the p-IPC <lb/>and Notch-dependent differential apoptosis of region-specific T4/T5 subtypes. Instead, Notch <lb/>controls the choice between T4 and T5 neuron fate, likely at the level of GMC divisions, <lb/>indicating that the distinction between layer 1/2 and layer 3/4 neuron fates precedes T4 and <lb/>T5 neuron specification. <lb/>Currently, the mechanisms controlling the maintenance of omb expression, as well as <lb/>Omb-mediated downregulation of Dac are unknown. Hypotheses regarding the latter have to <lb/>be reconciled with the fact that dac, together with ato, is required for the formation of all <lb/>T4/T5 neurons and hence is expressed in all d-IPC Nbs during the 2 nd competence window. <lb/>Omb and Dac are initially co-expressed in Nbs, GMCs and young T4/T5 neurons, suggesting <lb/>that Omb does not directly repress dac transcription. Yet, expression of the dac p7d23 enhancer <lb/>trap Gal4 line showed that dac is only transcribed in layer 1/2 neurons in adults. A possible <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>scenario is that Omb could break Dac autoregulation by triggering degradation of Dac. Since <lb/>T-box genes have been reported to act as activators and repressors of gene transcription 44 and <lb/>their effects can be influenced by various co-factors 45 , elucidating the molecular details of the <lb/>Omb-mediated repression of Dac provides exciting avenues for future studies. <lb/>Consistent with the observation that C2 and C3 neurons have distinct developmental <lb/>origins 46 , we found that Nbs derived from the Dpp-expression domain produce C2 and <lb/>possibly T2a neurons during the first Nb competence window, while the core p-IPC generates <lb/>C3, T2 and T3 neurons. dac mutant T4/T5 neurons adopt T3 and related T2 neuron <lb/>morphologies suggesting that this is the default neuron fate in this group of neurons. While <lb/>Omb is maintained in neurons derived from the Dpp-expression domain, Dac is not <lb/>expressed, suggesting that Omb interacts with other molecular determinants in C&amp;T neurons. <lb/>While we did not explore how layer 1 and 2 neurons or layer 3 and 4 neurons become distinct <lb/>from each other, our data suggest a possible contribution of dac/ato and Notch signaling. <lb/>Furthermore, it will be fascinating to identify the transcriptional targets of Notch, Dac and <lb/>Omb that mediate ganglion-and layer-specific targeting of T4/T5 dendrites and axons, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>Signaling centers, also called organizers, pattern tissues in a non-autonomous <lb/>fashion 47 . The vertebrate roof plate and the cortical hem, for instance, both release Wnts and <lb/>Bmps to pattern NE cells in the developing dorsal spinal cord and in the surrounding <lb/>forebrain, respectively 47-49 . In the Drosophila visual system, the GPC areas were known to <lb/>express wg and to pattern the OPC by inducing dpp expression in adjacent dorsal and ventral <lb/>OPC subdomains 27 . Together with our novel insights into the function of GPC-derived wg on <lb/>IPC patterning and neurogenesis, this firmly establishes the GPC areas as local organizers of <lb/>optic lobe development. At the onset of neurogenesis, wg is first expressed in the GPC areas <lb/>followed by the s-IPC. This observation provides an explanation for the well-established <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>delay in neurogenesis between the IPC and OPC 21 . We propose that Wg release from the GPC <lb/>areas coordinates the timely onset of neurogenesis in the OPC and IPC to safeguard the <lb/>alignment of matching partner neurons across several retinotopically organized neuropils. The <lb/>intercalation of new-born neurons between both neuroepithelia may have driven the need for <lb/>a relay system using primary and secondary sources of Wg in the GPC and IPC NE domains. <lb/>Wg induces Dpp to subdivide the adjacent OPC and p-IPC NE into distinct regions as basis <lb/>for generating neuronal diversity. The temporal relay mediated by Omb represents an efficient <lb/>strategy to pass the memory of spatial NE patterning information by Dpp signaling on to <lb/>postmitotic neurons generated at a distance. It is thus intricately tuned to the distinct <lb/>neurogenesis mode of the p-IPC essential for spatially matching birth-order dependent <lb/>neurogenesis between the OPC and IPC 24 . Interestingly, the progressive refinement of NE <lb/>patterning by the induction of secondary signaling centers plays a central role in vertebrate <lb/>brain development 47 . Furthermore, similar signaling cascades have been recently identified in <lb/>mammalian 3D optic tissue cultures where sequential Wnt and Bmp signaling induces the <lb/>expression of the Omb-related T-box transcription factor Tbx5 to specify dorsal identity of <lb/>retinal NE cells 50 . Hence, such cascades could represent conserved regulatory modules that <lb/>are employed repeatedly during invertebrate and vertebrate nervous system development. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Methods are provided in the extended Methods section below. <lb/>Note: Supplementary Information includes seven figures and two tables. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We are grateful to C. Alexandre, A. Baena-Lopez and J.P. Vincent (The Francis Crick <lb/>Institute, London) for all Wg reagents and their invaluable advice for this study. We thank A. <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Brand (The Gurdon Institute, Cambridge), A. Gould (The Francis Crick Institute), Y.N. Jan <lb/>(HHMI, San Francisco), R. Mann (Columbia University, New York), G. Pflugfelder <lb/>(University of Mainz), F. Pignoni (SUNY Upstate Medical University), S. Sigrist (FU Berlin), <lb/>J. Skeath (Washington University, St. Louis), L. Tsuda (NCGG, Obu), U. Walldorf <lb/>(University of Homburg), the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center, the Drosophila <lb/>Genomics Resource Center, the Vienna Drosophila Resource Center and the Developmental <lb/>Studies Hybridoma Bank for fly strains and antibodies. We thank A. Yuen and W. Wang for <lb/>help with Flybow and MARCM experiments. We thank H. Pynor for advice on the 3D <lb/>drawing of the larval optic lobe. We thank J.P. Vincent and C. Alexandre, as well as A. <lb/>Avola, C. de Miguel Vijandi, E.L. Powell and R. Kaschula (The Francis Crick Institute, <lb/>London) for critical reading of the manuscript. This work was supported by the Medical <lb/>Research Council (U117581332 I.S.) and the Francis Crick Institute (FC001151 I.S.), which <lb/>receives its core funding from Cancer Research UK, the Medical Research Council and the <lb/>Wellcome Trust. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>H.A. and I.S. conceived and designed the study. H.A. performed the experiments and <lb/>analyzed the data. H.A. and I.S. prepared the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">COMPETING INTERESTS <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. Wg release is essential for the formation of lobula plate layers 3/4. (a) Schematic of <lb/>the adult Drosophila visual system. Neurons in the lamina (L1/L2) and medulla (e.g. Mi1,4,9, <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tm1-4,9) relay ON/OFF motion cues to T4 and T5 neuron dendrites in medulla layer (Me) 10 <lb/>and lobula (Lo) layer 1. T4/T5 axons innervate lobula plate (Lop) layers 1-4. C&amp;T neurons <lb/>include C2/C3 and T2/T3 subtypes. (b) Schematic of the 3 rd instar larval optic lobe. The OPC <lb/>generates lamina (ln) and medulla (mn) neurons. p-IPC NE cells give rise to migratory <lb/>progenitors that mature into d-IPC Nbs. These produce C&amp;T and T4/T5 neurons. GMC, <lb/>ganglion mother cells; LPC, lamina precursor cells. (c) Structure of wild-type wg and <lb/>engineered wg loci (wg{KO;NRT-wg}). Open triangles indicate loxP sites. (d) R9B10-Gal4 <lb/>UAS-cd8GFP (green) labels T4/T5 neurons. Connectin (red) marks Lop layers 3/4. (d-g) <lb/>Neuropils were stained with nc82 (red) and aPKC (blue). Compared to controls (e), in <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies, one (f) or two (g) lobula plate layers were absent. (h) The decrease of <lb/>layers correlates with T4/T5 neuron numbers. The scatter plot with bars shows data points and <lb/>means with ±95% confidence interval error bars (n=15; three optical sections from five <lb/>samples per genotype). Unpaired, two-tailed Student&apos;s t-test not assuming equal variance: <lb/>P=4.72x10 -11 and P=3.23x10 -17 . **** P &lt; 0.0001. Unlike in controls (i), Connectin was found <lb/>in one (j) or none (k) of the Lop layers in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies. (l-n) In wild-type 3 rd instar <lb/>larvae (3L), the GPC areas (arrowheads), surface (s-)IPC (dashed line, double arrowheads) <lb/>and a Nb lineage (arrow) adjacent to the dorsal p-IPC subdomain (dashed line) express Wg <lb/>(green). (o) Schematics of larval Wg expression (blue) in 3D and a horizontal section. Arrow <lb/>indicates Nb lineage. For genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale <lb/>bars, 50 µm. <lb/>Figure 2. The GPC areas release Wg to induce wg in the s-IPC. (a,b) Schematic in (a) <lb/>highlights the region of interest shown in subsequent panels. Unlike in controls (a), Wg <lb/>immunolabeling (green) was absent in the s-IPC (dashed line, double arrowhead) in <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies (b). The GPC areas (arrowhead) were not affected. (c,d) In 2 nd instar <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>larvae (2L), Wg protein (c, green) and wg{KO;Gal4} UAS-cd8GFP (d, green) were detected <lb/>in GPC areas (arrowhead), but not adjacent IPC (dashed line). (e,f) s-IPC-specific <lb/>wg{KO;Gal4} UAS-cd8GFP expression (green, double arrowheads) in mid 3 rd instar larvae <lb/>(e) was absent in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies (f). Arrowheads indicate expression in GPC area. <lb/>(g,h) In controls, wg{KO;Gal4} UAS-FLP mediated wg{KO;FRT wg + FRT NRT-wg} allele <lb/>switching and simultaneous UAS-NRT-wg over-expression were induced at the mid 3 rd instar <lb/>larval stage (g, wg + background). Allele switching at the 1 st instar larval stage (h, NRT-wg <lb/>background) did not rescue s-IPC-specific Wg loss (green). (i,j) Unlike in controls (i), <lb/>R46E01-Gal4 UAS-FLP mediated GPC areas-specific wg{KO;FRT NRT-wg FRT wg + } allele <lb/>switching (j) rescued s-IPC-specific NRT-Wg loss (green). Filled and open triangles in <lb/>transgene schematics represent FRT and loxP sites, respectively (g-j). (k,l) The Wg target <lb/>gene reporter lines fz3 G00357 -GFP (k, green) and notum WRE -lacZ (l, green) show expression in <lb/>the GPC areas, the s-IPC, and in migratory progenitors (arrow) originating from the adjacent <lb/>p-IPC. (m,n) Unlike in controls (m), fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 mediated IPC-specific fz and fz2 <lb/>knockdown (n) caused loss of Wg (green) in the s-IPC. (o) Summary of wg function in the <lb/>GPC areas. For genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale bars, 50 <lb/>µm. <lb/>Figure 3. s-IPC-derived Wg is required for Dpp-dependent EMT in the p-IPC. (a,b) In 3 rd <lb/>instar larvae (3L), dpp-lacZ (blue) was detected in subdomains adjacent to wg{KO;Gal4} <lb/>UAS-cd8GFP (green) regions in the dorsal and ventral OPC (a, arrowheads) and p-IPC (b). <lb/>Double arrowhead indicates GFP-positive Nb clone adjacent to the dorsal p-IPC. (c,d) dpp-<lb/>lacZ (blue) was maintained in progenitor streams (arrows) from the ventral and dorsal p-IPC <lb/>subdomains. (e) In 2 nd instar larvae (2L), dpp-lacZ (blue) was present in the OPC (arrowhead) <lb/>adjacent to wg{KO;Gal4} UAS-cd8GFP positive GPC areas (green), but was absent in the <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>IPC (dashed line). (f) Schematic illustrating Wg and Dpp expression domains. Arrow <lb/>indicates progenitor stream originating from the ventral p-IPC subdomain. (g-k) Unlike in <lb/>controls (g, arrow), dpp-lacZ (green) was absent from the IPC in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies (h, <lb/>asterisk). The OPC was not affected. dpp-lacZ was ectopically induced in the IPC <lb/>(arrowheads) by h 1J3 -Gal4 mediated expression of UAS-arm S10 (i). dpp-lacZ was absent <lb/>following fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 mediated IPC-specific wg knockdown. In the Dpp-expression <lb/>domain, this caused EMT defects and loss of progenitor streams (j, asterisks). Similar defects <lb/>were caused by IPC-specific tkv knockdown. dpp-lacZ remains expressed in the p-IPC (k, <lb/>double arrowheads). (l-n) Compared to controls (l), fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 mediated IPC-specific <lb/>knockdown of fz and fz2 (m) and tkv (n) caused the loss of lobula plate (Lop) layers 3/4 <lb/>labeled with Connectin in adults. (o) Summary of wg and dpp function in the GPC areas, the <lb/>s-IPC and p-IPC. For genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale <lb/>bars, 50 µm. <lb/>Figure 4. The Dpp-expression domain generates C2 and T4/T5 neurons for layers 3/4. (a) <lb/>R45H05-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) colocalizes with the dpp-lacZ (blue) expression domain <lb/>in the IPC (arrow) but not the OPC (arrowhead) in 3 rd instar larvae (3L). (b) R45H05-Gal4 <lb/>UAS-cd8GFP (green) was weakly maintained in T4/T5 neurons innervating Connectin-<lb/>positive lobula plate (Lop) layers 3/4 (red, arrow) in adults. (c) Permanent GFP-labeling <lb/>(green) of the R45H05-Gal4 expression domain using act&gt;y + &gt;Gal4 UAS-GFP, UAS-FLP and <lb/>tub-Gal80 ts was specific to T4/T5 neurons innervating lobula plate layers 3/4. (d) R9B10-<lb/>Gal4 in conjunction with Flybow transgenes labeled T4/T5 neuron clones either innervating <lb/>lobula plate (Lop) layers 1/2 (mCitrine, yellow) or 3/4 (mCherry, red). (e) Permanent GFP <lb/>labeling (green) with R45H05-Gal4 included C2, as well as T2a and/or T3 neurons with <lb/>characteristic axon terminals in the lamina (La, arrow) and lobula (Lo, arrowhead). (f-g) <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unlike in controls (f), C2 neuron-specific R17C06-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP expression (green) <lb/>with axon terminals (arrow) in the lamina (La) was absent in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies that had <lb/>two remaining lobula plate layers (g). (h) Schematics illustrating the neuron-subtypes derived <lb/>from the Dpp-expression domain and the core IPC in 3 rd instar larvae and adults. For <lb/>genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale bars, 50 µm. <lb/>Figure 5. Formation of layer 1/2 innervating T4/T5 neurons requires dac and ato. (a) <lb/>Schematic illustrating the expression of Ase (turquoise), Ato (red) and Dac (blue) in d-IPC <lb/>Nbs during the first (1) and second (2) competence windows and their progeny. <lb/>(b,c) Dac (red) was expressed in all R9B10-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) labeled T4/T5 <lb/>neurons in 3 rd instar larvae (b). It was downregulated (arrowheads) in approximately 50% of <lb/>adult T4/T5 neurons (c). (d,e) dac p7d23 -Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) faithfully reported Dac <lb/>(red, double arrowhead) expression in adults (d), specifically labeling T4/T5 neurons <lb/>innervating lobula plate (Lop) layers 1 and 2 (e). (f) Schematic illustrating Dac expression <lb/>(blue) in adult T4/T5 neurons. (g-j) Unlike in controls (g,i), dac 1 mutant T4/T5 neurons <lb/>adopted T2/T3 neuron morphologies with R9B10-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green), displaying <lb/>neurite extensions into medulla (Me) layer M9 (arrows) and more distal layers (arrowhead) <lb/>(h), and UAS-brp-RFP labeled synaptic terminals (red, arrows) in lobula (Lo) layers 2 and 3 <lb/>(j). (k,l) Unlike in controls (k), fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) mediated IPC-specific <lb/>simultaneous knockdown of dac and ato generated neurons that failed to form a four layered <lb/>lobula plate (Lop) neuropil and dendrites in medulla (Me) layer 10 and lobula (Lo) layer 1 (l). <lb/>(m,n) Unlike in controls (m), Fas3-positive (red) T4/T5 neurons were absent following IPC-<lb/>specific simultaneous knockdown of dac and ato mediated by fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP <lb/>(green) (n). For genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale bars, 50 <lb/>µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Not Notch but Omb mediates Dpp-dependent specification of T4/T5 neurons for <lb/>layers 3/4. (a,b) Unlike in controls (a), R9B10-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP labeled T4 neurites were <lb/>absent in 3 rd instar larvae following UAS-N intra over-expression in d-IPC Nbs and their <lb/>progeny during the second competence window (b). T5 neurites in the lobula (Lo) were <lb/>unaffected. (c,d) Unlike in controls (c), following R17B05-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP mediated IPC-<lb/>specific Su(H) knockdown, T5 neurites were absent in the adult lobula (d). T4 neurites were <lb/>not affected. (e) Schematic illustrating Notch-dependent specification of T5 neurons. (f) <lb/>Phosphorylated Mad (pMad, red) in the dpp-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) expression domain <lb/>was found in p-IPC NE cells (double arrowheads), but not in progenitors (arrow), d-IPC <lb/>Nbs/GMCs or T4/T5 neurons. (g) Omb (red) was maintained in the dpp-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP <lb/>(green) expression domain in progenitors (arrow), d-IPC Nbs/GMCs (arrowhead), and T4/T5 <lb/>neuron subsets (double arrowheads). (h,i) Unlike in controls (h), omb P1 -lacZ (green) was <lb/>absent from the IPC (arrow) in wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies (i). OPC expression (arrowhead) was <lb/>not affected. (j,k) Indistinguishable from controls (j), fas3-Gal4 mediated IPC-specific <lb/>knockdown of omb (k) did not affect EMT of dpp-lacZ labeled progenitors (green, arrow) in <lb/>the IPC. (l-o) Unlike in controls (l), omb knockdown in the entire IPC and its progeny using <lb/>fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 (m), in the d-IPC and postmitotic T4/T5 neurons using R12G08-Gal4 (n), and <lb/>in postmitotic T4/T5 neurons using R9B10-Gal4 (o) resulted in the absence of Connectin-<lb/>positive lobula plate layers 3/4. Schematic insets highlight cell type-specificities of Gal4 lines <lb/>in green. (p) Schematics summarizing pMad and Omb distribution within the Dpp expression <lb/>domain, and the role of Dpp in inducing Omb expression to specify layer3/4 innervating <lb/>T4/T5 neurons. For genotypes and sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale bars, <lb/>50 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Omb converts layer 1/2 into layer 3/4 T4/T5 neurons by Dac downregulation. (a,b) <lb/>In 3 rd instar larvae (a), Omb (red) and Dac (blue) were initially co-expressed (arrows) in new-<lb/>born R9B10-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) labeled T4/T5 neurons. Dac (double arrowheads) <lb/>was downregulated in older Omb-positive (arrowheads) T4/T5 neurons. At 24 h after <lb/>puparium formation (APF) (b), Dac and Omb show mutually exclusive expression. (c-g) In <lb/>controls (c), Dac (red, double arrowheads) was expressed in approximately 50% of T4/T5 <lb/>neurons. Arrowheads indicate Dac-negative R9B10-Gal4 UAS-cd8GFP (green) labeled T4/T5 <lb/>neurons. Dac was maintained in almost all T4/T5 neurons following omb knockdown (d), and <lb/>downregulated following omb over-expression (e). Dac was expressed in all T4/T5 neurons in <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg} flies with two lobula plate layers (f). Ectopic Omb was sufficient to <lb/>downregulate Dac in these flies (g). (h) Quantification of all and Dac-positive T4/T5 neuron <lb/>numbers following omb manipulations. The scatter plot with bars shows data points and <lb/>means with ±95% confidence interval error bars (n=15 corresponding to three serial optical <lb/>sections, 6 µm apart, from five samples per genotype). Unpaired, two-tailed Student&apos;s t-test <lb/>not assuming equal variance: P=5.57x10 -12 , P=6.19x10 -15 , P=1.26x10 -10 , P=1.98x10 -17 , <lb/>P=3.60x10 -5 , P=4.79x10 -15 , P=0.020, P=0.017, P=0.0015, P=2.42x10 -13 . *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; <lb/>0.01; **** P &lt; 0.0001. (i-k) Unlike in controls (i), R9B10-Gal4 mediated ectopic UAS-omb <lb/>expression in T4/T5 neurons of wild type (j) or wg{KO;NRT-wg} (k) flies resulted in ectopic <lb/>Connectin expression in the lobula plate (Lop). (l) Schematic illustrating Dac and Omb <lb/>expression in adults. (m) Working model for spatial and temporal relay mechanisms <lb/>regulating the formation and specification of layer-specific T4/T5 neurons. For genotypes and <lb/>sample numbers, see Supplementary Table 1. Scale bars, 50 µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">METHODS <lb/>Genetics. Drosophila melanogaster strains were maintained on standard medium at 25°C <lb/>except for Gal80 ts and RNAi experiments, in which progeny were shifted from 18°C or 25°C <lb/>to 29°C at specific time points as indicated below. w 1118 flies were used as controls. If not <lb/>otherwise indicated, all stocks were obtained from the Bloomington Drosophila Stock Center <lb/>or the Vienna Drosophila Resource Center and are described in FlyBase. Crosses involved <lb/>approximately five males and seven virgin females. To avoid overcrowding, parents were <lb/>transferred to fresh vials every day or every second day. Control and experimental animals of <lb/>the correct age and genotype were selected irrespective of their gender randomly and <lb/>independently from several vials. If not otherwise indicated, wandering 3 rd instar larvae were <lb/>analyzed. Detailed genotypes of all experimental samples are listed in Supplementary <lb/>Tables 1 and 2. <lb/>The following stocks served as reporter lines: (1) fz3-GFP (Flytrap#G00357) 51 , (2) <lb/>dpp-lacZ Exel.2 , (3) omb P1 -lacZ (ref. 52 ), (4) notum WRE -lacZ (from J.P. Vincent, The Francis Crick <lb/>Institute, London). The following lines were used as Gal4 drivers: (1) dac p7d23 -Gal4/CyO (ref. <lb/>53 ), (2) dpp blk1 -Gal4/CyO (from J.P. Vincent) (3) fas3 NP1233 -Gal4 (Kyoto Drosophila Stock <lb/>Center), (4) fkh-Gal4 (from A. Gould, The Francis Crick Institute, London), (5) h 1J3 -Gal4 <lb/>(from A. Brand, The Gurdon Institute, Cambridge), (6) R9B10-Gal4, (7) R9H07-Gal4, (8) <lb/>R12G08-Gal4, (9) R17B05-Gal4, (10) R17C06-Gal4, (11) R34E01-Gal4, (12) R45H05-Gal4, <lb/>(13) R46E01-Gal4, (14) R67E05-Gal4 (refs. 54-56 ), (15) wg-Gal4/CyO, (16) <lb/>wg{KO;Gal4}/CyO (ref. 31 ), (17) wg{KO;Gal4}/CyO; UAS-HRP-cd8GFP/TM2 31 . For <lb/>presynaptic labeling, UAS-brp-RFP (from S. Sigrist, FU Berlin) was used, for membrane-<lb/>tethered GFP reporter gene expression (1) UAS-cd8GFP, (2) UAS-FB1.1B (ref. 57 ), or (3) <lb/>UAS-FB1.1C. In UAS-FB1.1C, cd8-mCherry and myr/palm (mp)-tethered mTurquoise in <lb/>UAS-FB1.1B were replaced by TagRFP-T and mTurquoise2, respectively (unpublished). For <lb/></div>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">R45H05-Gal4 cell lineage analysis using the hs-FLPout approach 58 , act&gt;y + &gt;Gal4 UAS-<lb/>GFP/GlaBc; UAS-FLP/TM6B flies were crossed to tubP-Gal80 ts ; R45H05-Gal4 and kept at <lb/>18°C before shifting to 29°C at the late 3 rd instar larval stage. For Flybow experiments 57,59 (1) <lb/>hs-mFLP5 MH12 /GlaBc flies were crossed to (2) UAS-FB1.1B 260b ; R9B10-Gal4, and (3) UAS-<lb/>FB1.1B 260b ; R9H07-Gal4. Progeny were heat shocked for 40-60 min at 48-72 h and 72-96 h or <lb/>at 24-48 h, 48-72 h and 72-96 h after egg laying (AEL) in a 37°C water bath. Loss-of-function <lb/>analysis using mosaic analysis with a repressible cell marker (MARCM) 60 were conducted by <lb/>crossing yw hs-FLP 122 ; tubP-Gal80 LL10 FRT40A/CyO; UAS-FB1.1B 49b R9B10-Gal4/TM6 flies <lb/>to (1) FRT40A, (2) dac 1 FRT40A, (3) FRT40A; UAS-brp-RFP, and (4) dac 1 FRT40A; UAS-<lb/>brp-RFP (dac 1 from F. Pignoni, SUNY Upstate Medical University). 24 h embryo collections <lb/>were heat shocked for 40-60 min at 48-72 h and 72-96 h after egg laying (AEL) in a 37°C <lb/>water bath. For knockdown experiments using UAS-RNAi transgenes, the following driver <lb/>lines were used: (1) yw ey 3.5 -Gal80; fas NP1233 -Gal4; UAS-Dcr2 UAS-cd8GFP/TM6B, (2) <lb/>R17B05-Gal4 UAS-FB1.1C 49B , (3) UAS-cd8GFP; R12G08-Gal4, and (4) UAS-FB1.1B 260b ; <lb/>R9B10-Gal4. RNAi lines used were (1) UAS-ato IR TRiP.JF02089 , (2) UAS-dac IR KK106040 , (3) UAS-fz IR <lb/>GD43077 , (4) UAS-fz2 IR KK108998 , (5) UAS-omb IR C1 (ref. 61 ; from G. Pflugfelder, University of <lb/>Mainz), (6) UAS-omb IR KK100598 , (7) UAS-Su(H) IR KK103597 , (8) UAS-tkv IR KK105834 , and (9) UAS-wg IR <lb/>GD13351 . UAS-Dcr2 was co-expressed in all experiments. Progeny were shifted from 25°C to <lb/>29°C 24 h AEL. Exceptions were crosses of ey 3.5 -Gal80; fas3 NP1233 -Gal4; UAS-Dcr2 UAS-<lb/>cd8GFP and UAS-omb IR or UAS-tkv IR animals, which were kept at 18°C before shifting to <lb/>29°C at the early 3 rd instar larval stage. For UAS-NRT-wg (ref. 34 ) gain-of-function <lb/>experiments, wg{KO;Gal4}/CyO; UAS-FLP flies were crossed to wg{KO;FRT wg + FRT NRT-<lb/>wg} UAS-NRT-wg; tubP-Gal80 ts flies and kept at 18°C. While experimental animals were <lb/>shifted to 29°C at the 1 st instar larval stage, control animals were maintained at 18°C until the <lb/>mid 3 rd instar larval stage and then shifted to 29°C. wg{KO;FRT wg + FRT NRT-wg} flies are <lb/></div>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">described in ref. 31 . For GPC-specific wg{KO;FRT NRT-wg FRT wg + }allele switching rescue <lb/>experiments 31 , wg{KO;FRT NRT-wg FRT wg + }/GlaBc; UAS-FLP flies were crossed to (1) <lb/>wg{KO;NRT-wg}/GlaBc 31 , and (2) wg{KO;NRT-wg}/GlaBc; R46E01-Gal4 and maintained at <lb/>25°C. For gain-of-function experiments, UAS-cd8-GFP; h 1J3 -Gal4 was crossed to UAS-<lb/>arm S10 ; dpp-lacZ Exel.2 (ref. 62 ), UAS-FB1.1B 260b ; R9B10-Gal4 was crossed to UAS-N intra (from L. <lb/>Tsuda, NCGG, Obu), and (1) UAS-FB1.1B 260b ; R9B10-Gal4 or (2) wg{KO;NRT-wg}; R9B10-<lb/>Gal4 UAS-FB1.1B 49b were crossed to UAS-omb (#2-1, ref. 63 ; from G. Pflugfelder). <lb/>Immunolabeling and imaging. Brains were dissected in phosphate-buffered saline <lb/>(PBS), fixed for 1 h at 20-24°C in 2% paraformaldehyde (wt/vol) in 0.05 M sodium <lb/>phosphate buffer (pH 7.4) containing 0.1 M L-lysine (Sigma-Aldrich) and washed in PBS <lb/>containing 0.5% Triton X-100 (Sigma-Aldrich). Primary and secondary antibodies were <lb/>diluted in 10% Normal Goat Serum (NGS) and PBT. The following primary antibodies were <lb/>used: rabbit antibody to Ase (1:5,000, from Y.N. Jan, HHMI, San Francisco, ref. 64 ), rabbit <lb/>antibody to Ato (1:5,000, from Y.N. Jan, ref. 65 ), mouse antibody to Brp (nc82, 1:10, <lb/>Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank [DSHB]), mouse antibody to Connectin (C1.427, <lb/>1:40, DSHB as marker for lobula plate layers 3/4, ref. 66 ), guinea pig antibody to D (1:200, <lb/>from A. Gould, ref. 67 ), mouse antibody to Dac (mAbdac2-3, 1:50, DSHB), rabbit antibody to <lb/>Dcp1 (#9578, 1:200, Cell Signaling Technologies), mouse antibody to Dlg (4F3, 1:50, <lb/>DSHB), guinea pig antibody to Dpn (1:500, from J. Skeath, Washington University, St. <lb/>Louis, ref. 68 ), rat antibody to E-cad (DCAD2, 1:2, DSHB), mouse antibody to Fas3 (7G10, <lb/>1:5, DSHB), chicken, mouse, and rabbit antibodies to b-galactosidase (#ab9361, 1:500, <lb/>Abcam; #Z3783, 1:300, Promega; #559762, 1:12,000, Cappel), rabbit antibody to GFP <lb/>(#A6455, 1:1,000, Molecular Probes), rabbit antibody to Hth (1:100, from R. Mann, <lb/>Columbia University, New York, ref. 69 ), rabbit antibody to Omb (1:400, G. Pflugfelder, <lb/>University of Mainz/J.P. Vincent, ref. 63 ), rabbit antibody to aPKC V (sc-216, 1:100, Santa <lb/></div>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Cruz Biotechnologies), rabbit antibody to pSmad3 (pS423/425 #1880-S, 1:2, Epitomics,), <lb/>rabbit antibody to Tll (812, 1:20, J. Reinitz Segmentation Antibodies, ref. 70 ), guinea pig <lb/>antibody to Toy (1.170, 1:200, from U. Walldorf, University of Homburg), and mouse <lb/>antibody to Wg (4D4, 1:20, DSHB). For immunofluorescence labeling, samples were <lb/>incubated for 2.5 h at 20-24°C in goat F(ab&apos;) 2 fragments coupled to FITC/DyLight 488, Cy3 <lb/>or Alexa Fluor 647 (1:400; Jackson ImmunoResearch Laboratories): antibody to guinea pig <lb/>(Cy3: #106-166-003; Alexa Fluor 647: #106-606-003), antibody to mouse (DyLight488: <lb/>#115-486-003; Cy3: #115-166-003; Alexa Fluor 647: #115-606-003), antibody to rabbit <lb/>(FITC: #111-096-003; Cy3: #111-166-003; Alexa Fluor 647: #111-606-003), antibody to rat <lb/>(Cy3: #112-166-003). Furthermore, goat antibody to chicken IgY (H+L) (Alexa Fluor 555, <lb/>Molecular Probes, #A21437, 1:400) was used. Images were collected with a Leica TCS SP5 <lb/>II laser scanning confocal microscope and processed using Adobe Photoshop and Fiji <lb/>software programs. <lb/>Quantifications and statistics. Statistical details of all experiments are reported in the <lb/>figures and figure legends. To quantify T4/T5 neuron numbers, adult optic lobes were imaged <lb/>in horizontal orientations and cell numbers were collected from three serial optical sections <lb/>(6-µm distance) in five sample (n=15) at the center of the optic lobe. Sample numbers and <lb/>genotypes for all experiments are provided in Supplementary Tables 1 and 2. If not <lb/>otherwise indicated, the penetrance of observed phenotypes was 100% for examined samples. <lb/>Sample sizes were not predetermined by statistical calculations, but were based on the <lb/>standard of the field. In a pool of control or experimental animals, specimen of the correct <lb/>stage and genotype were selected randomly and independently from different vials. Data <lb/>acquisition and analysis were not performed blinded but relied on samples with identified <lb/>genotypes that were not limited in repeatability. The calculations of 95% confidence interval <lb/>error bars and unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t-test P values were performed using Microsoft <lb/></div>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Excel software [Confidence.T and T.Test (type 3, not assuming equal variance)]. Prism 7 <lb/>GraphPad was used to perform Shapiro-Wilk and D&apos;Agostino-Pearson omnibus normality <lb/>tests and data met the assumption of normality in one or both tests. Quantifications are <lb/>presented as scatter plots and bar graphs with means ±95% confidence interval error bars. *P <lb/>&lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; *** P &lt; 0.001, **** P &lt; 0.0001. <lb/>A Supplementary Methods Checklist and Source Data have been included. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability. Image data sets supporting the findings of this study are available from the <lb/>corresponding author upon reasonable request. A source data file for quantifications are <lb/>provided with this manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Clark, D.A. &amp; Demb, J.B. Parallel Computations in Insect and Mammalian Visual <lb/>Motion Processing. Curr. Biol. 26, R1062-R1072 (2016). <lb/>2. <lb/>Mauss, A.S., Vlasits, A., Borst, A. &amp; Feller, M. Visual Circuits for Direction <lb/>Selectivity. Annu. Rev. Neurosci. 40, 211-230 (2017). <lb/>3. <lb/>Gabriel, J.P., Trivedi, C.A., Maurer, C.M., Ryu, S. &amp; Bollmann, J.H. Layer-specific <lb/>targeting of direction-selective neurons in the zebrafish optic tectum. Neuron 76, 1147-<lb/>1160 (2012). <lb/>4. <lb/>Robles, E., Filosa, A. &amp; Baier, H. Precise lamination of retinal axons generates multiple <lb/>parallel input pathways in the tectum. J. Neurosci. 33, 5027-5039 (2013). <lb/>5. <lb/>Buchner, E., Buchner, S. &amp; Bulthoff, I. Deoxyglucose mapping of nervous activity <lb/>induced in Drosophila brain by visual movement. I. Wildtype. J Comp Physiol A 155, <lb/>471-483 (1984). <lb/>6. <lb/>Maisak, M.S., et al. A directional tuning map of Drosophila elementary motion <lb/>detectors. Nature 500, 212-216 (2013). <lb/>7. <lb/>Huberman, A.D., et al. Genetic identification of an On-Off direction-selective retinal <lb/>ganglion cell subtype reveals a layer-specific subcortical map of posterior motion. <lb/>Neuron 62, 327-334 (2009). <lb/>8. <lb/>Kay, J.N., et al. Retinal ganglion cells with distinct directional preferences differ in <lb/>molecular identity, structure, and central projections. J. Neurosci. 31, 7753-7762 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>9. <lb/>Hadjieconomou, D., Timofeev, K. &amp; Salecker, I. A step-by-step guide to visual circuit <lb/>assembly in Drosophila. Curr. Opin. Neurobiol. 21, 76-84 (2011). <lb/>10. Fisher, Y.E., Silies, M. &amp; Clandinin, T.R. Orientation Selectivity Sharpens Motion <lb/>Detection in Drosophila. Neuron 88, 390-402 (2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>11. Mauss, A.S., Meier, M., Serbe, E. &amp; Borst, A. Optogenetic and pharmacologic <lb/>dissection of feedforward inhibition in Drosophila motion vision. J. Neurosci. 34, 2254-<lb/>2263 (2014). <lb/>12. Fischbach, K.F. &amp; Dittrich, A.P.M. The optic lobe of Drosophila melanogaster. I. A <lb/>Golgi analysis of wild-type structure. Cell Tissue Res. 258, 441-475 (1989). <lb/>13. Yang, H.H., et al. Subcellular imaging of voltage and calcium signals reveals neural <lb/>processing in vivo. Cell (2016). <lb/>14. Haag, J., Mishra, A. &amp; Borst, A. A common directional tuning mechanism of <lb/>Drosophila motion-sensing neurons in the ON and in the OFF pathway. Elife 6, pii: <lb/>e29044. doi: 29010.27554/eLife.29044 (2017). <lb/>15. Strother, J.A., et al. The Emergence of Directional Selectivity in the Visual Motion <lb/>Pathway of Drosophila. Neuron 94, 168-182 e110 (2017). <lb/>16. Takemura, S.Y., et al. The comprehensive connectome of a neural substrate for &apos;ON&apos; <lb/>motion detection in Drosophila. Elife 6 (2017). <lb/>17. Takemura, S.Y., et al. A visual motion detection circuit suggested by Drosophila <lb/>connectomics. Nature 500, 175-181 (2013). <lb/>18. Shinomiya, K., et al. Candidate neural substrates for off-edge motion detection in <lb/>Drosophila. Curr. Biol. 24, 1062-1070 (2014). <lb/>19. Haag, J., Arenz, A., Serbe, E., Gabbiani, F. &amp; Borst, A. Complementary mechanisms <lb/>create direction selectivity in the fly. Elife 5 (2016). <lb/>20. Apitz, H. &amp; Salecker, I. A challenge of numbers and diversity: neurogenesis in the <lb/>Drosophila optic lobe. J. Neurogenet. 28, 233-249 (2014). <lb/>21. Hofbauer, A. &amp; Campos-Ortega, J.A. Proliferation and and early differentiation of the <lb/>optic lobes in Drosophila melanogaster. Roux&apos;s Arch. Dev. Biol. 198, 264-274 (1990). <lb/>22. Green, P., Hartenstein, A.Y. &amp; Hartenstein, V. The embryonic development of the <lb/>Drosophila visual system. Cell Tissue Res. 273, 583-598 (1993). <lb/>23. Egger, B., Boone, J.Q., Stevens, N.R., Brand, A.H. &amp; Doe, C.Q. Regulation of spindle <lb/>orientation and neural stem cell fate in the Drosophila optic lobe. Neural Dev. 2, 1 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>24. Apitz, H. &amp; Salecker, I. A region-specific neurogenesis mode requires migratory <lb/>progenitors in the Drosophila visual system. Nat. Neurosci. 18, 46-55 (2015). <lb/>25. Yasugi, T., Umetsu, D., Murakami, S., Sato, M. &amp; Tabata, T. Drosophila optic lobe <lb/>neuroblasts triggered by a wave of proneural gene expression that is negatively <lb/>regulated by JAK/STAT. Development 135, 1471-1480 (2008). <lb/>26. Bertet, C., et al. Temporal patterning of neuroblasts controls Notch-mediated cell <lb/>survival through regulation of Hid or Reaper. Cell 158, 1173-1186 (2014). <lb/>27. Kaphingst, K. &amp; Kunes, S. Pattern formation in the visual centers of the Drosophila <lb/>brain: wingless acts via decapentaplegic to specify the dorsoventral axis. Cell 78, 437-<lb/>448 (1994). <lb/>28. Apitz, H. &amp; Salecker, I. Retinal determination genes coordinate neuroepithelial <lb/>specification and neurogenesis modes in the Drosophila optic lobe. Development 143, <lb/>2431-2442 (2016). <lb/>29. Petrovic, M. &amp; Hummel, T. Temporal identity in axonal target layer recognition. Nature <lb/>456, 800-803 (2008). <lb/>30. Kulkarni, A., Ertekin, D., Lee, C.H. &amp; Hummel, T. Birth order dependent growth cone <lb/>segregation determines synaptic layer identity in the Drosophila visual system. Elife 5, <lb/>e13715 (2016). <lb/>31. Alexandre, C., Baena-Lopez, A. &amp; Vincent, J.P. Patterning and growth control by <lb/>membrane-tethered Wingless. Nature 505, 180-185 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>32. Hayden, M.A., Akong, K. &amp; Peifer, M. Novel roles for APC family members and <lb/>Wingless/Wnt signaling during Drosophila brain development. Dev. Biol. 305, 358-376 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>33. Suzuki, T., Trush, O., Yasugi, T., Takayama, R. &amp; Sato, M. Wnt Signaling Specifies <lb/>Anteroposterior Progenitor Zone Identity in the Drosophila Visual Center. J. Neurosci. <lb/>36, 6503-6513 (2016). <lb/>34. Zecca, M., Basler, K. &amp; Struhl, G. Direct and long-range action of a wingless <lb/>morphogen gradient. Cell 87, 833-844 (1996). <lb/>35. Hamaguchi, T., Yabe, S., Uchiyama, H. &amp; Murakami, R. Drosophila Tbx6-related gene, <lb/>Dorsocross, mediates high levels of Dpp and Scw signal required for the development <lb/>of amnioserosa and wing disc primordium. Dev. Biol. 265, 355-368 (2004). <lb/>36. Li, X., et al. Temporal patterning of Drosophila medulla neuroblasts controls neural <lb/>fates. Nature 498, 456-462 (2013). <lb/>37. Erclik, T., et al. Integration of temporal and spatial patterning generates neural <lb/>diversity. Nature 541, 365-370 (2017). <lb/>38. Pflugfelder, G.O., et al. The lethal(1)optomotor-blind gene of Drosophila melanogaster <lb/>is a major organizer of optic lobe development: isolation and characterization of the <lb/>gene. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 89, 1199-1203 (1992). <lb/>39. Loh, K.M., van Amerongen, R. &amp; Nusse, R. Generating Cellular Diversity and Spatial <lb/>Form: Wnt Signaling and the Evolution of Multicellular Animals. Dev. Cell 38, 643-<lb/>655 (2016). <lb/>40. Nusse, R. &amp; Clevers, H. Wnt/beta-Catenin Signaling, Disease, and Emerging <lb/>Therapeutic Modalities. Cell 169, 985-999 (2017). <lb/>41. Kumar, S.R., Patel, H. &amp; Tomlinson, A. Wingless mediated apoptosis: How cone cells <lb/>direct the death of peripheral ommatidia in the developing Drosophila eye. Dev. Biol. <lb/>407, 183-194 (2015). <lb/>42. Suzuki, T., Kaido, M., Takayama, R. &amp; Sato, M. A temporal mechanism that produces <lb/>neuronal diversity in the Drosophila visual center. Dev. Biol. 380, 12-24 (2013). <lb/>43. Oliva, C., et al. Proper connectivity of Drosophila motion detector neurons requires <lb/>Atonal function in progenitor cells. Neural Dev. 9, 4 (2014). <lb/>44. Mihalas, A.B. &amp; Hevner, R.F. Control of Neuronal Development by T-Box Genes in <lb/>the Brain. Curr. Top. Dev. Biol. 122, 279-312 (2017). <lb/>45. Papaioannou, V.E. The T-box gene family: emerging roles in development, stem cells <lb/>and cancer. Development 141, 3819-3833 (2014). <lb/>46. Nern, A., Pfeiffer, B.D. &amp; Rubin, G.M. Optimized tools for multicolor stochastic <lb/>labeling reveal diverse stereotyped cell arrangements in the fly visual system. Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 112, E2967-2976 (2015). <lb/>47. Kiecker, C. &amp; Lumsden, A. The role of organizers in patterning the nervous system. <lb/>Annu. Rev. Neurosci. 35, 347-367 (2012). <lb/>48. Hoch, R.V., Rubenstein, J.L. &amp; Pleasure, S. Genes and signaling events that establish <lb/>regional patterning of the mammalian forebrain. Semin. Cell Dev. Biol. 20, 378-386 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>49. Caronia-Brown, G., Yoshida, M., Gulden, F., Assimacopoulos, S. &amp; Grove, E.A. The <lb/>cortical hem regulates the size and patterning of neocortex. Development 141, 2855-<lb/>2865 (2014). <lb/>50. Hasegawa, Y., et al. Emergence of dorsal-ventral polarity in ESC-derived retinal tissue. <lb/>Development 143, 3895-3906 (2016). <lb/>51. Kelso, R.J., et al. Flytrap, a database documenting a GFP protein-trap insertion screen <lb/>in Drosophila melanogaster. Nucleic Acids Res. 32, D418-420 (2004). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>52. Tsai, S.F., et al. Gypsy retrotransposon as a tool for the in vivo analysis of the <lb/>regulatory region of the optomotor-blind gene in Drosophila. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. <lb/>S. A. 94, 3837-3841 (1997). <lb/>53. Heanue, T.A., et al. Synergistic regulation of vertebrate muscle development by Dach2, <lb/>Eya2, and Six1, homologs of genes required for Drosophila eye formation. Genes Dev. <lb/>13, 3231-3243 (1999). <lb/>54. Pfeiffer, B.D., et al. Tools for neuroanatomy and neurogenetics in Drosophila. Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. U. S. A. 105, 9715-9720 (2008). <lb/>55. Jenett, A., et al. A GAL4-driver line resource for Drosophila neurobiology. Cell Rep 2, <lb/>991-1001 (2012). <lb/>56. Li, H.H., et al. A GAL4 driver resource for developmental and behavioral studies on the <lb/>larval CNS of Drosophila. Cell Rep 8, 897-908 (2014). <lb/>57. Shimosako, N., Hadjieconomou, D. &amp; Salecker, I. Flybow to dissect circuit assembly in <lb/>the Drosophila brain. Methods Mol. Biol. 1082, 57-69 (2014). <lb/>58. Ito, K., Awano, W., Suzuki, K., Hiromi, Y. &amp; Yamamoto, D. The Drosophila <lb/>mushroom body is a quadruple structure of clonal units each of which contains a <lb/>virtually identical set of neurones and glial cells. Development 124, 761-771 (1997). <lb/>59. Hadjieconomou, D., et al. Flybow: genetic multicolor cell labeling for neural circuit <lb/>analysis in Drosophila melanogaster. Nat. Methods 8, 260-266 (2011). <lb/>60. Lee, T. &amp; Luo, L. Mosaic analysis with a repressible cell marker for studies of gene <lb/>function in neuronal morphogenesis. Neuron 22, 451-461 (1999). <lb/>61. Shen, J., Dorner, C., Bahlo, A. &amp; Pflugfelder, G.O. optomotor-blind suppresses <lb/>instability at the A/P compartment boundary of the Drosophila wing. Mech. Dev. 125, <lb/>233-246 (2008). <lb/>62. Pai, L.M., Orsulic, S., Bejsovec, A. &amp; Peifer, M. Negative regulation of Armadillo, a <lb/>Wingless effector in Drosophila. Development 124, 2255-2266 (1997). <lb/>63. Grimm, S. &amp; Pflugfelder, G.O. Control of the gene optomotor-blind in Drosophila wing <lb/>development by decapentaplegic and wingless. Science 271, 1601-1604 (1996). <lb/>64. Brand, M., Jarman, A.P., Jan, L.Y. &amp; Jan, Y.N. asense is a Drosophila neural precursor <lb/>gene and is capable of initiating sense organ formation. Development 119, 1-17 (1993). <lb/>65. Jarman, A.P., Sun, Y., Jan, L.Y. &amp; Jan, Y.N. Role of the proneural gene, atonal, in <lb/>formation of Drosophila chordotonal organs and photoreceptors. Development 121, <lb/>2019-2030 (1995). <lb/>66. Gao, S., et al. The neural substrate of spectral preference in Drosophila. Neuron 60, <lb/>328-342 (2008). <lb/>67. Russell, S.R., Sanchez-Soriano, N., Wright, C.R. &amp; Ashburner, M. The Dichaete gene <lb/>of Drosophila melanogaster encodes a SOX-domain protein required for embryonic <lb/>segmentation. Development 122, 3669-3676 (1996). <lb/>68. Bier, E., Vaessin, H., Younger-Shepherd, S., Jan, L.Y. &amp; Jan, Y.N. deadpan, an <lb/>essential pan-neural gene in Drosophila, encodes a helix-loop-helix protein similar to <lb/>the hairy gene product. Genes Dev. 6, 2137-2151 (1992). <lb/>69. Noro, B., Culi, J., McKay, D.J., Zhang, W. &amp; Mann, R.S. Distinct functions of <lb/>homeodomain-containing and homeodomain-less isoforms encoded by homothorax. <lb/>Genes Dev. 20, 1636-1650 (2006). <lb/>70. Kosman, D., Small, S. &amp; Reinitz, J. Rapid preparation of a panel of polyclonal <lb/>antibodies to Drosophila segmentation proteins. Dev. Genes Evol. 208, 290-294 (1998). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
