<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Vps74 connects the Golgi apparatus and telomeres in <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>Joana Rodrigues 1 , Peter Banks 2 and David Lydall 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Institute for Cell and Molecular Biosciences, Newcastle University Medical School, <lb/>Newcastle upon Tyne, NE2 4HH, United Kingdom <lb/>2 <lb/>High Throughput Screening Facility, Newcastle Biomedicine, Newcastle University, <lb/>Newcastle upon Tyne, NE2 4HH, United Kingdom <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Vps74 connects Golgi and telomeres <lb/>Keywords: Saccharomyces cerevisiae, Vps74, telomere, Stn1, QFA, Golgi. <lb/>Corresponding author: <lb/>David Lydall <lb/>Faculty of Medical Sciences, Framlington Place, <lb/>Institute for Cell and Molecular Biosciences, Cookson Building (M2.022) <lb/>Newcastle University, Newcastle, NE2 4HH, United Kingdom <lb/>Tel: +44 (0) 191 208 5318 <lb/>E-mail: david.lydall@ncl.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>ABSTRACT <lb/>In mammalian cell culture, the Golgi apparatus fragment upon DNA damage. <lb/>GOLPH3, a Golgi component, is a phosphorylation target of DNA-PK after DNA <lb/>damage and contributes to Golgi fragmentation. The function of the yeast <lb/>(Saccharomyces cerevisiae) ortholog of GOLPH3, Vps74, in the DNA damage <lb/>response has been little studied, although genome-wide screens suggested a role at <lb/>telomeres. In this study we investigated the role of Vps74 at telomeres and in the <lb/>DNA damage response. We show that Vps74 decreases the fitness of telomere <lb/>defective cdc13-1 cells and contributes to the fitness of yku70Δ cells. Importantly, <lb/>loss of Vps74 in yku70Δ cells exacerbates the temperature dependent growth <lb/>defects of these cells in a Chk1 and Mec1-dependent manner. Furthermore, Exo1 <lb/>reduces fitness of vps74Δ yku70Δ cells suggesting that ssDNA contributes to the <lb/>fitness defects of vps74Δ yku70Δ cells. Systematic genetic interaction analysis of <lb/>vps74Δ, yku70Δ and yku70Δ vps74Δ cells suggests that vps74Δ causes a milder but <lb/>similar defect to that seen in yku70Δ cells. vps74Δ cells have slightly shorter <lb/>telomeres and loss of VPS74 in yku70Δ or mre11Δ cells further shortens the <lb/>telomeres of these cells. Interestingly, loss of Vps74 leads to increased levels of <lb/>Stn1, a partner of Cdc13 in the CST telomere capping complex. Overexpression of <lb/>Stn1 was previously shown to cause telomere shortening, suppression of cdc13-1 <lb/>and enhancement of yku70Δ growth defects, suggesting that increased levels of <lb/>Stn1 may be the route by which Vps74 affects telomere function. These results <lb/>establish Vps74 as a novel regulator of telomere biology. <lb/></front>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The Golgi apparatus is found in all eukaryotes, functioning in the maturation of <lb/>proteins and lipids destined for the cell surface or other internal compartments (Glick <lb/>and Nakano 2009; Potelle et al. 2015). Somewhat surprisingly, in mammalian cells, <lb/>the Golgi responds to DNA damage (Farber-Katz et al. 2014). Golgi becomes <lb/>fragmented after camptothecin (CPT)-induced DNA damage and Golgi fragmentation <lb/>persists long after DNA lesions are repaired. The fragmentation in response to DNA <lb/>damage was dependent on GOLPH3, which was phosphorylated by DNA-PK (a <lb/>DNA damage protein kinase). GOLPH3 phosphorylation increased its interaction <lb/>with MYO18A, a myosin that links Golgi membranes to the cytoskeleton (Dippold et <lb/>al. 2009). <lb/>GOLPH3 is highly conserved among eukaryotes and VPS74 is its budding yeast <lb/>(Saccharomyces cerevisiae) orthologue. Vps74 is reported to be important for the <lb/>localisation of glycosyltransferases to the Golgi apparatus and to activate Sac1, a <lb/>phosphoinositide phosphatase membrane protein, in Golgi (Schmitz et al. 2008; <lb/>Wood et al. 2012). Glycosyltransferases are responsible for protein glycosylation, <lb/>where sugar (glycan) chains are attached to proteins, contributing to the correct <lb/>folding and function of these proteins (Shental-Bechor and Levy 2008; Xu and Ng <lb/>2015). Sac1 regulates the levels of phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphates (PtdIns4P) <lb/>which are lipids known to promote protein trafficking in Golgi (Strahl and Thorner <lb/>2007). Phosphatidylinositols can also affect nuclear mRNA export, with a decrease <lb/>in InsP6 (whose precursor is PtdIns4P) levels, leading to an accumulation of <lb/>polyadenylated mRNA in the nucleus (Wera et al. 2001). Interestingly, large-scale <lb/>surveys suggested that VPS74 affected fitness of telomere defective yku70Δ and <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>cdc13-1 cells in opposite directions (Addinall et al. 2011). Here we carefully <lb/>examined the role of VPS74 in telomere defective cells. Low and high throughput <lb/>data suggest that Vps74 and Yku70 work in parallel pathways to contribute to <lb/>telomere capping and that Vps74 may affect telomere function by affecting levels of <lb/>the critical telomere capping protein Stn1. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Yeast strains <lb/>Standard procedures for yeast culture, mating and tetrad dissection were followed <lb/>(Adams et al. 1997). Unless otherwise stated, all experiments were performed using <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae W303 (RAD5) strains as listed in Table S1. Gene <lb/>disruptions were made in diploids using one step PCR to insert a kanMX or natMX <lb/>cassettes into the genome (Goldstein and McCusker 1999). Gene disruptions were <lb/>confirmed by PCR. Oligonucleotide sequences are available upon request. <lb/>Yeast growth assays <lb/>A pool of colonies (&gt;10) were grown until saturation overnight at 23°C (cdc13-1 <lb/>strains) or 30°C (other strains) in 2 ml of liquid YEPD (supplemented with adenine) <lb/>or -LEU medium (for strains carrying plasmids). 5 or 7-fold serial dilutions in water <lb/>were spotted onto YEPD or -LEU plates using a replica plating device. Plates were <lb/>incubated for 2 or 3 days at the appropriate temperatures before being <lb/>photographed. Unless stated otherwise, a single plate per temperature is shown for <lb/>each figure (round plates fit between 8 and 16 strains while rectangular plates fit <lb/>between 16 and 32 strains). For passage tests, single colonies (from germination <lb/>plates) were streaked onto a YEPD plate and then several colonies (&gt;10) from this <lb/>plate were restruck on a new YEPD plate for each passage. Cells were grown for <lb/>two days at 30°C. ImageJ (http://imagej.nih.gov/ij/) quantification was performed as <lb/>outlined at http://lukemiller.org/index.php/2010/11/analyzing-gels-and-western-blots-<lb/>with-image-j/. <lb/>Analysis of telomere structure <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Southern blot analysis was used to assess telomere length and performed as <lb/>previously described (Dewar and Lydall 2010). Genomic DNA was extracted, <lb/>digested with XhoI and then run overnight on a 1% agarose gel at 1V/cm. Southern <lb/>transfer was performed using a Biorad Vacuum Blotter according to manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>indications. Y&apos;+TG probe labelling and Southern detection were made according to <lb/>the DIG High Prime DNA Labelling and Detection Starter Kit II (Roche) <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. The probe is approximately 1 kb with ~880bp of Y&apos; and <lb/>120bp of TG repeats and was released from pDL1574 using XhoI and BamHI. <lb/>QFA <lb/>Query strains were created as described in Table S1 in using a PCR based lithium <lb/>acetate method followed by crossing and random spore analysis. SGA (synthetic <lb/>genetic array) was performed as previously described, crossing vps74Δ, yku70Δ, <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ with part of the genome-wide single gene deletion knock out <lb/>collection (Table S2) (Tong et al. 2001; Tong and Boone 2006). For QFA, strains <lb/>from the final SGA plates were inoculated robotically into 200 µl liquid media in 96-<lb/>well plates and grown for 2 days at 20°C without shaking, as previously described <lb/>(Dubarry et al. 2015). After resuspension saturated cultures were spotted onto solid <lb/>agar plates and were incubated and imaged as described before (Addinall et al. <lb/>2011; Dubarry et al. 2015). In order to measure fitnesses of the various query strains <lb/>at high temperatures, a total of eight replicates of QFA were performed at both 36°C <lb/>and 37°C. Fitness and genetic interaction strength estimates were performed as <lb/>described before (Dubarry et al. 2015). <lb/>Western blots <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Protein extracts were prepared by trichloroacetic acid (TCA) precipitation (Ngo and <lb/>Lydall 2015). Briefly, cells were resuspended in 10% TCA and mechanically broken <lb/>using glass beads. Protein suspensions in Laemmli buffer were boiled for 3 min, <lb/>spun down for 10 min and the supernatant were loaded onto 4-15% Mini-PROTEAN <lb/>TGX Gels (Bio-Rad). The proteins were transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane <lb/>(GE Healthcare) and probed with anti-Myc (Abcam ab32), anti-tubulin antibodies <lb/>(from Keith Gull, Oxford University) and anti-Rad53 (Abcam ab104232). <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>All strains and materials are available upon request. File S1 contains the <lb/>supplementary Figures S1-S7. File S2 contains the raw data from the QFA screens <lb/>performed in this study. Table S1 contains the list of strains used in the study. Table <lb/>S2 contains the genes analysed in the screens. Table S3 describes the plasmids <lb/>used in this study. <lb/></div>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>RESULTS <lb/>Vps74 is important for telomere biology <lb/>Yeast genome-wide screens in the S288C genetic background suggested that <lb/>VPS74 is involved in telomere biology (Addinall et al. 2011). Deletion of VPS74 <lb/>weakly suppressed cdc13-1 fitness defects at 27°C and strongly enhanced yku70Δ <lb/>fitness defects at 37°C (Addinall et al. 2011). In order to clarify the role of VPS74 at <lb/>telomeres, VPS74 was deleted in cdc13-1 and yku70Δ telomere defective cells in the <lb/>W303 genetic background and the fitness of the double mutants was carefully <lb/>assessed by spot test. <lb/>In agreement with the high-throughput data, vps74Δ cdc13-1 cells grow better at <lb/>27°C than cdc13-1 cells, showing that Vps74 reduces the fitness of cdc13-1 cells <lb/>(Figure 1A). On the other hand, vps74Δ yku70Δ cells are significantly less fit than <lb/>yku70Δ or vps74Δ cells at 36°C, showing that Vps74 is important for the fitness of <lb/>yku70Δ cells (Figure 1B). We note that vps74Δ cells grew poorly at 23°C (Figure 1). <lb/>We conclude that Vps74 slightly decreases the fitness of cdc13-1 cells but increases <lb/>the fitness of yku70Δ cells. <lb/>The DDR checkpoint is activated in vps74Δ yku70Δ cells <lb/>To better understand the molecular nature of the defect in vps74Δ yku70Δ cells, we <lb/>measured genetic interactions with gene deletions affecting the DNA damage <lb/>response using vps74Δ and yku70Δ single mutants as controls. We tested CHK1, <lb/>MEC1, EXO1 and MRE11 since these all affect fitness of yku70Δ cells (Maringele <lb/>and Lydall 2002). Chk1 and Mec1 were shown to be important for cell cycle arrest in <lb/>yku70Δ cells and Exo1 is the major exonuclease responsible for telomeric DNA <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>resection in these mutants (Maringele and Lydall 2002). Mre11, part of the MRX <lb/>complex, is important for yku70Δ cell fitness and simultaneous loss of Mre11 and <lb/>Yku70 leads to extensive telomere rearrangements (Maringele and Lydall 2004). <lb/>chk1Δ strongly suppressed yku70Δ vps74Δ fitness, and yku70Δ fitness defects as <lb/>expected, but did not affect vps74Δ fitness at 38°C (Figure 2A). mec1Δ (sml1Δ) <lb/>suppressed yku70Δ vps74Δ, yku70Δ and vps74Δ fitness defects, at 35°C and at <lb/>38°C, respectively (Figure 2B). exo1Δ strongly suppressed vps74Δ yku70Δ and <lb/>yku70Δ fitness defects, allowing these cells to grow at 38°C (Figure 2C). vps74Δ <lb/>exo1Δ cells grew similarly to vps74Δ cells at 38°C (Figure S1A and Figure 2C). In <lb/>contrast, mre11Δ strongly enhanced vps74Δ fitness defects at 23°C and 37°C <lb/>(Figure 2D). <lb/>Given that Exo1 decreases the fitness of vps74Δ yku70Δ cells when compared to <lb/>yku70Δ cells, we hypothesised that loss of VPS74 leads to increased telomeric <lb/>ssDNA in yku70Δ cells. To test this, telomeric ssDNA levels in vps74Δ and vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ cells was measured by in-gel assay after 4h growth at 36°C. However, loss <lb/>of VPS74 did not strongly affect the levels of telomeric ssDNA in WT or yku70Δ cells <lb/>(Figure S1C-E). Interestingly, vps74Δ decreased the ssDNA levels of cdc13-1 cells <lb/>as measured by both In-gel assay and quantitative amplification of ssDNA (QAOS) <lb/>(Figure S1C-E). This decrease in ssDNA is in agreement with the suppression of <lb/>cdc13-1 fitness defects by vps74Δ (Figure 1A), since increased levels of ssDNA in <lb/>cdc13-1 cells were shown to be responsible for the poor fitness of these cells <lb/>(Maringele and Lydall 2002). Together these data suggest that Vps74 functions with <lb/>Yku70 and Mre11 to help cap telomeres and protect from DDR pathways. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Loss of Vps74 leads to telomere shortening <lb/>Since vps74Δ mre11Δ cells have extensive fitness defects at all temperatures we <lb/>wondered if vps74Δ, like yku70Δ, when combined with mre11Δ, leads to progressive <lb/>telomere attrition and survivor appearance (Maringele and Lydall 2004). To test this, <lb/>we passaged vps74Δ mre11Δ cells and analysed their colony size and telomere <lb/>lengths. We observed that the fitness of vps74Δ mre11Δ cells improves with <lb/>passage (Figure 3A, B). Interestingly, vps74Δ cells show slightly short telomeres, <lb/>consistent with a role for Vps74 in telomere capping, but the effect is much less than <lb/>either Yku70 or Mre11 (Figure 3C). Telomeres of vps74Δ mre11Δ were slightly <lb/>shorter than telomeres of mre11Δ cells (Figure 3C). Furthermore, telomeres of <lb/>vps74Δ mre11Δ cells slightly lengthen with passage but do not show the major <lb/>telomere rearrangements seen in telomerase deficient survivors (Maringele and <lb/>Lydall 2004). These data show that Vps74 has a minor role affecting telomere <lb/>length, independent of Mre11 and Yku70. <lb/>Large-scale studies suggest that Vps74 has similar, but parallel, functions to <lb/>Yku70 <lb/>To systematically explore the role of Vps74 in telomere function, a medium scale <lb/>quantitative fitness analysis was conducted to compare genetic interactions of 358 <lb/>gene deletions in vps74Δ, yku70Δ and vps74Δ yku70Δ cells (Addinall et al. 2011). <lb/>The 358 gene deletions were chosen because they affect DNA damage responses, <lb/>intracellular protein transport, protein localization, protein maturation, regulation of <lb/>phosphatidylinositol dephosphorylation, retrograde vesicle-mediated transport (Golgi <lb/>to ER), telomere maintenance, endoplasmic reticulum unfolded protein response and <lb/>others (Table S2). Before embarking on these screens we first confirmed that <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>vps74Δ and yku70Δ are synthetically sick in the S288C genetic background, used for <lb/>high-throughput screens (Figure S2A). <lb/>The fitness of the double and triple mutants was then assessed by QFA (Figure 4). <lb/>In part to assess the quality the data we highlight gene deletions known to interact <lb/>with telomere defective strains (MRE11, EST1, CHK1, EST2, RAD50, DDC1, EXO1, <lb/>RIF1, RAD9, RAD17, RAD24, TEL1, RRM3, NMD2, and YKU80). Interestingly, <lb/>although vps74Δ cells are not as temperature sensitive as yku70Δ cells (or vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ cells), it is possible to see that the relative position of the highlighted genes <lb/>is very similar in vps74Δ, yku70Δ, vps74Δ yku70Δ (Figure 4A-C). For instance, <lb/>exo1Δ and chk1Δ are found as suppressors in all screens, while nmd2Δ and rad50Δ <lb/>are enhancers in all screens. This pattern across the screens suggests that VPS74 <lb/>deletion causes fitness defects that have a similar origin to those observed in <lb/>yku70Δ cells. We conclude that Vps74 and Yku70 have similar functions in the <lb/>maintenance of the genome/telomere integrity, however Vps74 contribution is more <lb/>minor. <lb/>Vps74 affects telomere biology similarly to Pmt1 and Pmt2 <lb/>Our results show that Vps74 potentially collaborates with Yku70 to affect telomere <lb/>function. However, since Vps74 is reported to be a cytoplasmic protein, its role at <lb/>telomeres is likely to be indirect. GOLPH3, the mammalian orthologue of Vps74, is <lb/>phosphorylated by DNA-PK upon DNA damage induction, and so it is possible that <lb/>yeast Vps74 affects telomere biology through a similar phosphorylation pathway <lb/>(Farber-Katz et al. 2014). In order to test if Vps74 is phosphorylated in response to <lb/>different types of DNA damage, Vps74-13Myc was analysed by western blot after <lb/>MMS treatment or in cdc13-1 cells at 37 o C. As a control, Rad53 was analysed as it is <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>extensively phosphorylated upon DNA damage (Pellicioli et al. 1999; Morin et al. <lb/>2008). As previously reported, Rad53 was phosphorylated upon MMS treatment and <lb/>in cdc13-1 cells at 37°C, showing that the DNA damage response was activated in <lb/>these cells (Figure S3). However, we found no evidence that Vps74 is <lb/>phosphorylated in response to either type of DNA damage since we did not detect a <lb/>mobility shift in Vps74-13Myc protein (Figure S3). Therefore, although we cannot <lb/>exclude that Vps74 is phosphorylated in response to DNA damage we see no <lb/>evidence that this is the case. <lb/>In yeast, Vps74 can be found in the cis and medial cisternae of the Golgi. Vps74 <lb/>facilitates the function of mannosyltransferases, in glycosylation, and Sac1, a <lb/>PtdIns4P phosphatase, to help modulate lipid levels and inositol phosphates, a class <lb/>of intracellular signalling molecules (Schmitz et al. 2008; Wood et al. 2012; Short <lb/>2014) (Figure 5A). To try to understand if Vps74 affects yku70Δ cell fitness by <lb/>affecting the function of mannosyltransferases or by affecting Sac1 function, we <lb/>screened for yeast gene deletions that behave similarly to vps74Δ across five <lb/>telomere related genetic screens (Figure 5B, Figure S4). To do this we used <lb/>Profilyzer, a web based interaction tool (Dubarry et al. 2015; Holstein et al. 2017). <lb/>Interestingly, pmt1Δ and pmt2Δ, affecting O-mannosyltransferases (transferring <lb/>mannose from dolichyl phosphate-D-mannose to serine and threonine residues in <lb/>proteins), behaved very similarly to vsp74Δ in cdc13-1 exo1Δ, cdc13-1, stn1-13, <lb/>yku70Δ and cdc13-1 rad9Δ genetic screens (Figure 5B and Figure S4). On the other <lb/>hand, sac1Δ caused extremely unfit cells in all screens (Figure 5B). The similarity <lb/>between the effects of deleting VPS74, PMT1 or PMT2 in telomere defective cells, <lb/>suggests that Vps74 affects the fitness of telomere defective cells through Pmt1 and <lb/>Pmt2-dependent pathways. This supports the notion that Vps74 regulates telomere <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>biology by affecting mannosyltransferase function. Interestingly, mnn2Δ (affecting an <lb/>α-1,2-mannosyltransferase) also showed similar genetic interactions to vps74Δ, <lb/>pmt1Δ and pmt2Δ across the telomere screens (Figure S4A-C). <lb/>Although sac1Δ did not appear to behave similarly to vps74Δ across the telomere <lb/>screens (Figure 5B), we decided to confirm this in a low-throughput manner in the <lb/>W303 genetic background. SAC1 was deleted in vps74Δ, yku70Δ and vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ cells and fitness was measured. Interestingly, vps74Δ and sac1Δ are <lb/>synthetically sick, even at 23°C, and this is not affected byYKU70 (Figure 5C). This <lb/>result suggests that Vps74 and Sac1 affect different pathways to maintain the fitness <lb/>of yeast cells. Furthermore, vps74Δ yku70Δ cells are less fit than sac1Δ yku70Δ <lb/>cells at 35°C, suggesting that Vps74 has a role in yku70Δ cells that is independent of <lb/>Sac1. We conclude that Vps74 and Sac1 act in different ways to affect cell fitness of <lb/>telomere proficient and deficient cells. Thus, the Vps74 role in telomere biology is at <lb/>least partially independent of the SAC1 pathway. <lb/>Finally, it cannot be excluded that Vps74 plays a more direct role in the nucleus, <lb/>since Vps74-GFP localizes to the nucleus, as well as the cytoplasm (Figure S5). <lb/>Indeed, using two nuclear localization prediction programs (cNLS mapper and <lb/>NucPred), Vps74 is predicted to have a weak nuclear localization signal in its N-<lb/>terminus (Brameier et al. 2007; Kosugi et al. 2009a; Kosugi et al. 2009b). We <lb/>conclude that Vps74 regulates the fitness of yku70Δ cells independently of Sac1. <lb/>Overall, genetic interaction data suggest that Vps74, Pmt1 and Pmt2 work in the <lb/>same pathway to affect the fitness of telomere defective cells. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Stn1 levels are regulated by a Vps74-dependent pathway <lb/>Since Vps74 is involved in at least two pathways likely to affect protein levels <lb/>(protein glycosylation and PtdIns4P-dependent protein synthesis), we wondered if <lb/>Vps74 might affect the levels of a protein or proteins that affect telomere biology. We <lb/>noted that nmd2Δ, affecting nonsense mediated mRNA decay, causes similar <lb/>phenotypes to vps74Δ, suppressing cdc13-1 and enhancing yku70Δ fitness defects <lb/>(Figure 1). nmd2Δ, like vps74Δ, also leads to telomere shortening (Figure 3C) <lb/>(Addinall et al. 2011; Holstein et al. 2014). The effect of nmd2Δ has been ascribed to <lb/>increased levels of Stn1 (Dahlseid et al. 2003), and indeed plasmid induced Stn1 <lb/>overexpression suppressed cdc13-1 and enhances yku70Δ fitness defects (Addinall <lb/>et al. 2011). Stn1, along with Cdc13 and Ten1 are components of the CST complex <lb/>involved in telomere capping (Addinall et al. 2011; Holstein et al. 2014). To test <lb/>whether Vps74 affects Stn1 levels, Stn1-Myc levels were measured in vps74Δ cells. <lb/>In addition, because vps74Δ cells show temperature dependent fitness defects <lb/>(Figure 2), we measured Stn1 levels at 30°C and 37°C. Interestingly, Stn1 levels <lb/>were increased approximately 40% in vps74Δ cells at 30°C (Figure 6A, B). <lb/>Additionally, Stn1 levels were also increased by growth at 37 o C. The increased Stn1 <lb/>levels in vps74Δ cells could explain the short telomeres of these cells and the <lb/>negative genetic interaction between vps74Δ and yku70Δ (Puglisi et al. 2008; <lb/>Romano et al. 2013). It is interesting to speculate that increases in Stn1 levels at <lb/>high temperature might help explain why telomeres get shorter in wild type cells at <lb/>increased temperatures (Romano et al. 2013). We had observed that vps74Δ was <lb/>synthetically sick with the mre11Δ mutation, and that vps74Δ mre11Δ double <lb/>mutants have shorter telomeres than either single mutant (Figures 2D and 3). We <lb/>wondered if the effect of vps74Δ in the mre11Δ context could be due to increased <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Stn1 levels. To test this we used a 2 micron plasmid to overexpress Stn1. Consistent <lb/>with our hypothesis Stn1 overexpression reduced fitness of mre11Δ cells at all <lb/>temperatures (Figure 6C). Overall we conclude that Vps74 helps maintain low levels <lb/>of Stn1, and this may be the mechanism by which Vps74 affects telomere function in <lb/>numerous different contexts. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>In mammalian cells, GOLPH3 phosphorylation by DNA-PK was shown to be <lb/>essential for Golgi fragmentation in response to DNA damage (Farber-Katz et al. <lb/>2014). The functional implications of Golgi fragmentation are not yet clear in <lb/>mammalian cells. Interestingly, yeast genetic data also support the existence of a <lb/>connection between Golgi and the DNA damage response (DDR), indicating that this <lb/>relationship might be evolutionary conserved. Specifically, yeast genome-wide <lb/>genetic interaction screens suggested that the yeast ortholog of GOLPH3, VPS74, <lb/>affected the fitness of telomere defective cdc13-1 and yku70Δ cells (Addinall et al. <lb/>2011). There is an intimate and complex relationship between functional telomeres <lb/>and the DDR, with many DDR proteins affecting telomere function and vice versa <lb/>(Lydall 2009). <lb/>In agreement with the published high-throughput data, our new low-throughput <lb/>experiments showed that vps74Δ suppressed cdc13-1 fitness defects and enhanced <lb/>yku70Δ defects (Addinall et al. 2011). These data confirm that yeast Vps74 affects <lb/>telomere function and are consistent with a role for Vps74 in the DNA damage <lb/>response. Our evidence suggests that the better fitness of vps74Δ cdc13-1 cells in <lb/>comparison to cdc13-1 cells is due to a decrease in the telomeric ssDNA levels in <lb/>the double mutants. On the other hand, the decrease in the fitness of vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ cells seems to be independent of telomeric ssDNA. Interestingly, numerous <lb/>gene deletions that suppressed or enhanced yku70Δ temperature defects, similarly <lb/>affected the temperature sensitivity of vps74Δ and vps74Δ yku70Δ cells, suggesting <lb/>that Vps74 and Yku70 perform similar functions at telomeres. Amongst the <lb/>confirmed strong suppressors of vps74Δ yku70Δ temperature defects were exo1Δ, <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>chk1Δ, mec1Δ (sml1Δ), affecting DDR genes, that also suppress yku70Δ fitness <lb/>defects (Maringele and Lydall 2002). Thus, our genetic interaction data suggests that <lb/>Vps74 contributes in some manner to telomere capping, and this role is more <lb/>important in the absence of Yku70. <lb/>It has previously been reported that nmd2Δ, affecting a core component of the <lb/>nonsense-mediated mRNA decay pathway, improved the fitness of cdc13-1 cells <lb/>and decreased the fitness of yku70Δ cells by increasing levels of Stn1 (Dahlseid et <lb/>al. 2003; Addinall et al. 2011; Holstein et al. 2014). Interestingly, nmd2Δ and vps74Δ <lb/>genetic interaction patterns are similar in cdc13-1 and yku70Δ contexts. Stn1 is an <lb/>essential telomere capping protein and functions with Cdc13 and Ten1 in the CST <lb/>complex. Increased levels of Stn1 are thought to help a partially defective Cdc13-1 <lb/>protein cap the chromosome end (Holstein et al. 2014). On the other hand, high <lb/>levels of Stn1 inhibit Cdc13-dependent recruitment of telomerase to telomeres, <lb/>causing a short telomere phenotype (Grandin et al. 2000). Stn1 overexpression <lb/>enhances growth defects of yku70Δ mutants with short telomeres, presumably by <lb/>exacerbating the short telomere phenotype (Dahlseid et al. 2003; Addinall et al. <lb/>2011; Holstein et al. 2014). Interestingly, in vps74Δ cells, as in nmd2Δ cells, <lb/>increased levels of Stn1, can explain the suppression of cdc13-1 and enhancement <lb/>yku70Δ cell fitness defects. Importantly, increased Stn1 levels could also explain the <lb/>short telomeres of vps74Δ cells and the poor fitness of vps74Δ mre11Δ cells, since <lb/>mre11Δ cells, like yku70Δ cells, have a short telomere phenotype. For all these <lb/>reasons we propose that Vps74 affects telomere function by maintaining low levels <lb/>of Stn1. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Vps74 regulation of Stn1 levels is unlikely to be direct since all known Vps74 <lb/>functions are in the Golgi and Stn1 is a nuclear protein (Schmitz et al. 2008; Wood et <lb/>al. 2012; Cai et al. 2014; Short 2014). High-throughput genetic interactions suggest <lb/>that VPS74, PMT1 and PMT2 could work in the same pathways to affect telomere <lb/>function. Pmt1 and Pmt2 are responsible for O-mannosylation of membrane <lb/>proteins, affecting the stability/function of such proteins (Schmitz et al. 2008; Petkova <lb/>et al. 2012; Loibl and Strahl 2013; Short 2014). We speculate that Vps74 (and <lb/>Pmt1/Pmt2) affect the levels of nuclear proteins, like Stn1, by affecting signal <lb/>transduction pathways whose cell surface components are targets of <lb/>mannosyltransferases. For example, we suggest that Vps74 may be important for <lb/>the Golgi localization and function of Pmt1 and Pmt2 (Figure S7, a) (Schmitz et al. <lb/>2008). It is known that Pmt1 and Pmt2 are responsible for the mannosylation of Mtl1, <lb/>a cytoplasmic transmembrane sensor protein upstream of the cytoplasmic Pkc1-<lb/>MAPK pathway (Figure S7, b) (Petkova et al. 2012). Pck1 activates Bck1, which in <lb/>turn activates Mkk1/2, which finally activates Mpk1, involved in nuclear and <lb/>cytoplasmic responses to oxidative and genotoxic stresses, including transcriptional <lb/>modulation and proteasome homeostasis (Figure S7, c) (Truman et al. 2009; <lb/>Jendretzki et al. 2011; Soriano-Carot et al. 2012; Rousseau and Bertolotti 2016). <lb/>Thus, it seems likely that Vps74 affects the levels of nuclear proteins, such as Stn1, <lb/>by modulating signal transduction pathways that depend on protein mannosylation. <lb/>In human cancer cells, GOLPH3 overexpression was associated with increased <lb/>activation of mTOR signalling, affecting protein synthesis in response to nutrient <lb/>changes (Scott et al. 2009). Perhaps, therefore, Vps74, Pmt1 and Pmt2 affect the <lb/>levels of Stn1 (and likely other proteins) by affecting the Tor and Pkc1-MAPK <lb/>pathways (Figure S7). Overall, our careful analysis of Vps74 function in telomere <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>defective yeast cells, leads us to believe that regulation of Stn1 levels is at least one <lb/>of the ways Vps74 affects telomere function. Future experiments will be required to <lb/>better understand the mechanisms by which Vps74 affects Stn1 levels, the DNA <lb/>damage response and telomere functions. It will also be interesting to determine if <lb/>these mechanisms are conserved across eukaryotes. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Adams A, Gottschcling DE, Kaiser CA, Stearns T. 1997. Methods in Yeast Genetics:. <lb/>Cold Spring Harbor Laboratory Press, New York. <lb/>Addinall SG, Holstein EM, Lawless C, Yu M, Chapman K, Banks AP, Ngo HP, <lb/>Maringele L, Taschuk M, Young A et al. 2011. Quantitative Fitness Analysis <lb/>Shows That NMD Proteins and Many Other Protein Complexes Suppress or <lb/>Enhance Distinct Telomere Cap Defects. PLoS genetics 7. <lb/>Brameier M, Krings A, MacCallum RM. 2007. NucPred--predicting nuclear <lb/>localization of proteins. Bioinformatics 23: 1159-1160. <lb/>Cai Y, Deng Y, Horenkamp F, Reinisch KM, Burd CG. 2014. Sac1-Vps74 structure <lb/>reveals a mechanism to terminate phosphoinositide signaling in the Golgi <lb/>apparatus. The Journal of cell biology 206: 485-491. <lb/>Dahlseid JN, Lew-Smith J, Lelivelt MJ, Enomoto S, Ford A, Desruisseaux M, <lb/>McClellan M, Lue N, Culbertson MR, Berman J. 2003. mRNAs encoding <lb/>telomerase components and regulators are controlled by UPF genes in <lb/>Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Eukaryotic cell 2: 134-142. <lb/>Dewar JM, Lydall D. 2010. Pif1-and Exo1-dependent nucleases coordinate <lb/>checkpoint activation following telomere uncapping. Embo Journal 29: 4020-<lb/>4034. <lb/>Dippold HC, Ng MM, Farber-Katz SE, Lee SK, Kerr ML, Peterman MC, Sim R, <lb/>Wiharto PA, Galbraith KA, Madhavarapu S et al. 2009. GOLPH3 bridges <lb/>phosphatidylinositol-4-phosphate and actomyosin to stretch and shape the <lb/>Golgi to promote budding. Cell 139: 337-351. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Dubarry M, Lawless C, Banks AP, Cockell S, Lydall D. 2015. Genetic Networks <lb/>Required to Coordinate Chromosome Replication by DNA Polymerases <lb/>alpha, delta, and epsilon in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. G3 5: 2187-2197. <lb/>Farber-Katz SE, Dippold HC, Buschman MD, Peterman MC, Xing M, Noakes CJ, Tat <lb/>J, Ng MM, Rahajeng J, Cowan DM et al. 2014. DNA damage triggers Golgi <lb/>dispersal via DNA-PK and GOLPH3. Cell 156: 413-427. <lb/>Glick BS, Nakano A. 2009. Membrane traffic within the Golgi apparatus. Annual <lb/>review of cell and developmental biology 25: 113-132. <lb/>Goldstein AL, McCusker JH. 1999. Three new dominant drug resistance cassettes <lb/>for gene disruption in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Yeast 15: 1541-1553. <lb/>Grandin N, Damon C, Charbonneau M. 2000. Cdc13 cooperates with the yeast Ku <lb/>proteins and Stn1 to regulate telomerase recruitment. Molecular and cellular <lb/>biology 20: 8397-8408. <lb/>Holstein EM, Clark KR, Lydall D. 2014. Interplay between nonsense-mediated <lb/>mRNA decay and DNA damage response pathways reveals that Stn1 and <lb/>Ten1 are the key CST telomere-cap components. Cell Rep 7: 1259-1269. <lb/>Holstein EM, Ngo G, Lawless C, Banks P, Greetham M, Wilkinson D, Lydall D. 2017. <lb/>Systematic Analysis of the DNA Damage Response Network in Telomere <lb/>Defective Budding Yeast. G3 7: 2375-2389. <lb/>Jendretzki A, Wittland J, Wilk S, Straede A, Heinisch JJ. 2011. How do I begin? <lb/>Sensing extracellular stress to maintain yeast cell wall integrity. Eur J Cell Biol <lb/>90: 740-744. <lb/>Kosugi S, Hasebe M, Matsumura N, Takashima H, Miyamoto-Sato E, Tomita M, <lb/>Yanagawa H. 2009a. Six classes of nuclear localization signals specific to <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>different binding grooves of importin alpha. The Journal of biological chemistry <lb/>284: 478-485. <lb/>Kosugi S, Hasebe M, Tomita M, Yanagawa H. 2009b. Systematic identification of <lb/>cell cycle-dependent yeast nucleocytoplasmic shuttling proteins by prediction <lb/>of composite motifs. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 106: 10171-10176. <lb/>Loibl M, Strahl S. 2013. Protein O-mannosylation: What we have learned from <lb/>baker&apos;s yeast. Bba-Mol Cell Res 1833: 2438-2446. <lb/>Lydall D. 2009. Taming the tiger by the tail: modulation of DNA damage responses <lb/>by telomeres. The EMBO journal 28: 2174-2187. <lb/>Maringele L, Lydall D. 2002. EXO1-dependent single-stranded DNA at telomeres <lb/>activates subsets of DNA damage and spindle checkpoint pathways in <lb/>budding yeast yku70 Delta mutants. Genes Dev 16: 1919-1933. <lb/>-. 2004. EXO1 plays a role in generating type I and type II survivors in budding yeast. <lb/>Genetics 166: 1641-1649. <lb/>Morin I, Ngo HP, Greenall A, Zubko MK, Morrice N, Lydall D. 2008. Checkpoint-<lb/>dependent phosphorylation of Exo1 modulates the DNA damage response. <lb/>The EMBO journal 27: 2400-2410. <lb/>Ngo GH, Lydall D. 2015. The 9-1-1 checkpoint clamp coordinates resection at DNA <lb/>double strand breaks. Nucleic acids research 43: 5017-5032. <lb/>Pellicioli A, Lucca C, Liberi G, Marini F, Lopes M, Plevani P, Romano A, Di Fiore PP, <lb/>Foiani M. 1999. Activation of Rad53 kinase in response to DNA damage and <lb/>its effect in modulating phosphorylation of the lagging strand DNA <lb/>polymerase. The EMBO journal 18: 6561-6572. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Petkova MI, Pujol-Carrion N, de la Torre-Ruiz MA. 2012. Mtl1 O-mannosylation <lb/>mediated by both Pmt1 and Pmt2 is important for cell survival under oxidative <lb/>conditions and TOR blockade. Fungal Genet Biol 49: 903-914. <lb/>Potelle S, Klein A, Foulquier F. 2015. Golgi post-translational modifications and <lb/>associated diseases. J Inherit Metab Dis 38: 741-751. <lb/>Puglisi A, Bianchi A, Lemmens L, Damay P, Shore D. 2008. Distinct roles for yeast <lb/>Stn1 in telomere capping and telomerase inhibition. The EMBO journal 27: <lb/>2328-2339. <lb/>Romano GH, Harari Y, Yehuda T, Podhorzer A, Rubinstein L, Shamir R, Gottlieb A, <lb/>Silberberg Y, Pe&apos;er D, Ruppin E et al. 2013. Environmental stresses disrupt <lb/>telomere length homeostasis. PLoS genetics 9: e1003721. <lb/>Rousseau A, Bertolotti A. 2016. An evolutionarily conserved pathway controls <lb/>proteasome homeostasis. Nature 536: 184-189. <lb/>Schmitz KR, Liu J, Li S, Setty TG, Wood CS, Burd CG, Ferguson KM. 2008. Golgi <lb/>localization of glycosyltransferases requires a Vps74p oligomer. Dev Cell 14: <lb/>523-534. <lb/>Scott KL, Kabbarah O, Liang MC, Ivanova E, Anagnostou V, Wu J, Dhakal S, Wu M, <lb/>Chen S, Feinberg T et al. 2009. GOLPH3 modulates mTOR signalling and <lb/>rapamycin sensitivity in cancer. Nature 459: 1085-1090. <lb/>Shental-Bechor D, Levy Y. 2008. Effect of glycosylation on protein folding: a close <lb/>look at thermodynamic stabilization. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 105: 8256-<lb/>8261. <lb/>Short B. 2014. Vps74 gives phosphatase directions. Journal of Cell Biology 206: <lb/>453-453. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Soriano-Carot M, Bano MC, Igual JC. 2012. The yeast mitogen-activated protein <lb/>kinase Slt2 is involved in the cellular response to genotoxic stress. Cell Div 7: <lb/>1. <lb/>Strahl T, Thorner J. 2007. Synthesis and function of membrane phosphoinositides in <lb/>budding yeast, Saccharomyces cerevisiae. Biochimica et biophysica acta <lb/>1771: 353-404. <lb/>Tong AH, Boone C. 2006. Synthetic genetic array analysis in Saccharomyces <lb/>cerevisiae. Methods in molecular biology 313: 171-192. <lb/>Tong AHY, Evangelista M, Parsons AB, Xu H, Bader GD, Page N, Robinson M, <lb/>Raghibizadeh S, Hogue CWV, Bussey H et al. 2001. Systematic genetic <lb/>analysis with ordered arrays of yeast deletion mutants. Science 294: 2364-<lb/>2368. <lb/>Truman AW, Kim KY, Levin DE. 2009. Mechanism of Mpk1 mitogen-activated <lb/>protein kinase binding to the Swi4 transcription factor and its regulation by a <lb/>novel caffeine-induced phosphorylation. Molecular and cellular biology 29: <lb/>6449-6461. <lb/>Wera S, Bergsma JC, Thevelein JM. 2001. Phosphoinositides in yeast: genetically <lb/>tractable signalling. FEMS yeast research 1: 9-13. <lb/>Wood CS, Hung CS, Huoh YS, Mousley CJ, Stefan CJ, Bankaitis V, Ferguson KM, <lb/>Burd CG. 2012. Local control of phosphatidylinositol 4-phosphate signaling in <lb/>the Golgi apparatus by Vps74 and Sac1 phosphoinositide phosphatase. <lb/>Molecular biology of the cell 23: 2527-2536. <lb/>Xu C, Ng DT. 2015. Glycosylation-directed quality control of protein folding. Nature <lb/>reviews Molecular cell biology 16: 742-752. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. VPS74 affects the fitness of telomere defective cells. <lb/>(A and B) Serial dilutions of saturated overnight cultures, grown at 23°C, were <lb/>spotted onto YEPD plates and incubated for 2 days at the indicated temperatures. All <lb/>strains are in the W303 genetic background and at each temperature were grown on <lb/>a single plate but images have been cut and pasted to allow better comparisons. <lb/>Figure 2. CHK1, MEC1, EXO1 and MRE11 affect the fitness of vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>and vps74Δ cells at high temperatures. <lb/>Spot test assays as described in Figure 1. <lb/>Figure 3. Loss of VPS74 leads to telomere shortening in WT and mre11Δ cells. <lb/>(A) Passage tests performed at 30°C. Cells were allowed to grow for 2 days before <lb/>pictures were taken and cells passaged. (B) Zoom in of the colonies in A. (C) Cells <lb/>from the plates in A were inoculated in liquid YEPD, grown until saturation and DNA <lb/>was extracted. The DNA was analysed by Southern blot with a telomere probe <lb/>(Y&apos;+TG). Horizontal red line represents the WT telomere length and the blue line is <lb/>roughly the telomere length of mre11Δ cells. Vertical dashed line indicates where the <lb/>gel picture was cut for presentation purposes. <lb/>Figure 4. Systematic analysis of the effects of 358 gene deletions in the fitness <lb/>of vps74Δ, yku70Δ and yku70Δ vps74Δ cells. <lb/>Part of the yeast genome knock out collection (358 strains, Table S2) was crossed <lb/>with vps74Δ (A), yku70Δ (B), vps74Δ yku70Δ (C) or lyp1Δ (A, B and C) mutations. <lb/>Double or triple mutants were then grown on solid agar plates and the fitness was <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>measured at 37°C (or 36°C for lyp1Δ). Fitness is measured as Maximum Doubling <lb/>Rate × Maximum Doubling Potential (MDR × MDP, units are doublings squared per <lb/>day, d2/day), as previously described (Addinall et al. 2011). Each dot indicates the <lb/>effect of a gene deletion (yfgΔ) on the fitness of vps74Δ (A), yku70Δ (B), vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ (C) or lyp1Δ (A, B and C). Grey dots indicate the deletions that did not <lb/>significantly alter the fitness of the mutants in the y axis relative to the x axis (lyp1Δ). <lb/>Blue inverted triangles represent gene deletions that are enhancers of the vps74Δ <lb/>(A), yku70Δ (B) or vps74Δ yku70Δ (C), red triangles are suppressors and the purple <lb/>dots represent the fitness of the deletion of 15 telomere related genes. Figures <lb/>showing vps74Δ screens versus yku70Δ screens, vps74Δ yku70Δ screens versus <lb/>yku70Δ screens and vps74Δ yku70Δ screens versus vps74Δ screens can be found <lb/>in Figure S2B, C and D, respectively. <lb/>Figure 5. vps74Δ, pmt1Δ and pmt2Δ show similar genetic interactions with <lb/>mutations affecting telomeres. <lb/>(A) Cartoon showing the Vps74 function in protein sorting within the Golgi apparatus <lb/>(Schmitz et al. 2008; Wood et al. 2012). Complex sphingolipids are preferentially <lb/>packaged with secretory cargo into anterograde-directed transport vesicles and can <lb/>end in exocytosis, multivesicular bodies (MVB) or the vacuole (a). In the trans Golgi, <lb/>Vps74 recognizes PtdIns4P and mannosyltransferases, sorting them into COPI-<lb/>coated retrograde vesicles (b). As a consequence of co-packaging PtdIns4P with <lb/>Golgi protein residents into retrograde vesicles, PtdIns4P is delivered to the medial <lb/>cisternae (c). In the medial/cis Golgi, Vps74 promotes Sac1-dependent PtdIns4P <lb/>dephosphorylation (d) and protein mannosylation (e). Sac1 and <lb/>mannosyltransferases cycle between the endoplasmic reticulum (ER) and the Golgi <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>apparatus (f). Similarly, mannosylated proteins could follow the anterograde pathway <lb/>(g, a) or eventually return to ER (f). Cartoon and legend adapted from (Wood et al. <lb/>2012). (B) Fitness profiles of vps74Δ, sac1Δ, pmt1Δ and pmt2Δ in combination with <lb/>several mutations affecting telomere biology (x axis) (Holstein et al. 2017). Box plots <lb/>show 50% range, the whiskers represent 1.5-fold the 50% range from the box, and <lb/>the horizontal black line is the median fitness. (C) Spot test assays as described in <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>Figure 6. Increased temperature and loss of Vps74 leads to increased Stn1-<lb/>Myc levels. <lb/>Three independent WT and vps74Δ strains carrying a Stn1-Myc construct (strains <lb/>numbers indicated), were cultured overnight at 30°C to saturation. Each culture was <lb/>diluted 1:100, cultured for 2h at 30°C and then divided into two cultures that were <lb/>further incubated at 30°C or 37°C for 4h. (A) Proteins were extracted using TCA and <lb/>a western blot was performed first against Myc and then against tubulin. (B) <lb/>Quantification of A and Figure S6 using Image J. Stn1-Myc intensity normalized for <lb/>tubulin levels is shown. Values are presented as fold change relative to WT at 30°C. <lb/>At 30°C, three independent strains were analysed in two independent experiments <lb/>(n=6), while at 37° two independent strains were analysed once while a third <lb/>independent strain was analysed twice (independent experiments, n=4). The mean is <lb/>indicated and the error bars indicate the standard deviation. Statistical analyses used <lb/>the two-tailed t-Test assuming unequal variance (*P&lt;0.05 and **P&lt;0.01) performed <lb/>with SigmaPlot (version 11). (C) WT and mre11Δ cells were transformed with a 2 µm <lb/>plasmid carrying STN1 or a vector plasmid (plasmids described in Table S3). Six <lb/>independent (WT and mre11Δ) transformants carrying either the STN1 plasmid or <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>the vector, were cultivated in selective media (-LEU, lacking leucine) until saturation <lb/>and spot tests were performed as described in Figure 1 (in -LEU plates). Pictures <lb/>were taken after 3 days of incubation. Two representative strains of each genotype <lb/>carrying either of the plasmids are shown. <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>WT <lb/>cdc13-1 <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>vps74Δ cdc13-1 <lb/>23°C <lb/>27°C <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>23°C <lb/>36°C <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>C <lb/>30°C <lb/>36°C <lb/>38°C <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>exo1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ exo1Δ <lb/>yku70Δ exo1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ exo1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>chk1Δ <lb/>yku70Δ chk1Δ <lb/>30°C <lb/>36°C <lb/>38°C <lb/>vps74Δ chk1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ chk1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>sml1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ sml1Δ <lb/>yku70Δ sml1Δ <lb/>mec1Δ sml1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ sml1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ mec1Δ sml1Δ <lb/>yku70Δ mec1Δ sml1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ mec1Δ sml1Δ <lb/>30°C <lb/>35°C <lb/>37°C <lb/>38°C <lb/>D <lb/>B <lb/>37°C <lb/>36°C <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>23°C <lb/>37°C <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>vps74Δ mre11Δ <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>A <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Passage 1 <lb/>Passage 2 <lb/>Passage 3 <lb/>Passage 6 <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>vps74Δ mre11Δ (b) <lb/>Passage 1 <lb/>Passage 2 <lb/>Passage 3 <lb/>Passage 6 <lb/>WT <lb/>vp s7 4Δ <lb/>exo1Δ <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>vp s7 4Δ m re 11 Δ <lb/>(a ) <lb/>v p s 7 4 Δ <lb/>m r e 1 1 Δ <lb/>( b ) <lb/>C <lb/>1 6 1 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 6 1 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 2 3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 1 2 3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>exo1Δ <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>vps74Δ mre11Δ <lb/>(a) <lb/>vps74Δ mre11Δ <lb/>(b) <lb/>950 <lb/>830 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1600 <lb/>2000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>4300 <lb/>3500 <lb/>Pass. <lb/>bp <lb/>Loading <lb/>control <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>lyp1Δ 36˚C <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>YKU80 <lb/>NMD2 <lb/>RAD50 <lb/>RRM3 <lb/>TEL1 <lb/>MRE11 <lb/>EST2 <lb/>EST1 <lb/>RAD24 <lb/>RAD17 <lb/>RAD9 <lb/>CHK1 <lb/>RIF1 <lb/>DDC1 <lb/>EXO1 <lb/>vps74Δ 37˚C <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>RAD50 <lb/>TEL1 <lb/>NMD2 <lb/>YKU80 <lb/>RRM3 <lb/>MRE11 <lb/>EST1 <lb/>EST2 <lb/>RAD24 <lb/>RAD17 <lb/>RIF1 <lb/>DDC1 <lb/>CHK1 <lb/>RAD9 <lb/>EXO1 <lb/>yku70Δ 37˚C <lb/>lyp1Δ 36˚C <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 100 <lb/>NMD2 <lb/>TEL1 <lb/>RAD50 <lb/>EST1 <lb/>RRM3 <lb/>MRE11 EST2 <lb/>YKU80 <lb/>RAD17 <lb/>RAD24 <lb/>CHK1 <lb/>DDC1 <lb/>RAD9 <lb/>RIF1 <lb/>EXO1 <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ 37˚C <lb/>lyp1Δ 36˚C <lb/>PtdIns4P <lb/>Mannosyltransferases <lb/>(e.g. Pmt1, Pmt2, Mnn2) <lb/>Sac1 <lb/>Vps74 <lb/>trans Golgi <lb/>cis, medial Golgi <lb/>Anterograde <lb/>pathway <lb/>Retrograde <lb/>pathway <lb/>Phosphate <lb/>PtdIns <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Sac1 <lb/>dephosphorylates <lb/>PtdIns4P <lb/>C <lb/>Exocytosis <lb/>Protein <lb/>mannosylation <lb/>ER <lb/>Protein X <lb/>Mannose <lb/>Extracellular <lb/>space <lb/>cdc13-1 exo1Δ (27˚C) <lb/>stn1-13 (33˚C) <lb/>yku70Δ (37˚C) <lb/>cdc13-1 (27˚C) <lb/>cdc13-1 rad9Δ (27˚C) <lb/>Fitness profile <lb/>Fitness <lb/>Cytoplasm <lb/>Nucleus <lb/>MVB <lb/>Vacuole <lb/>WT <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>yku70Δ <lb/>sac1Δ <lb/>sac1Δ <lb/>vps74Δ yku70Δ <lb/>vps74Δ sac1Δ <lb/>yku70Δ sac1Δ <lb/>30˚C <lb/>35˚C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>pmt1Δ <lb/>pmt2Δ <lb/>sac1Δ <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>pmt1Δ <lb/>pmt2Δ <lb/>sac1Δ <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>b <lb/>f <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>g <lb/>Figure 6 <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>30°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>37°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>30°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>37°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>30°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>37°C <lb/>WT <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>Fold change (rel to <lb/>WT) <lb/>Experiment 1 <lb/>Experiment 2 <lb/>WT (11813) <lb/>WT (12438) <lb/>WT (12439) <lb/>vps74Δ (12440) <lb/>vps74Δ (12441) <lb/>vps74Δ (12442) <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>30°C <lb/>vps74Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>37°C <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>p=0.3 <lb/>** <lb/>* <lb/>C <lb/>30°C <lb/>37°C <lb/>WT <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>WT <lb/>mre11Δ <lb/>vector <lb/>pSTN1 <lb/>vector <lb/>pSTN1 <lb/>23°C <lb/>p=0.08 <lb/>Stn1-Myc <lb/>Tubulin </body>


	</text>
</tei>
