<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ENVIRONMENTAL RESOURCE MANAGEMENT | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Exploring loss and damage from climate change and global perspectives that <lb/>influence response mechanism in vulnerable communities <lb/>Cyril Joseph Effiong , Jamila Musa Wakawa Zanna, David Hannah and Fraser Sugden <lb/>School of Geography and Environmental Science, University of Birmingham, Birmingham, UK <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Climate change has led to unprecedented environmental and socio-economic challenges globally, <lb/>especially in vulnerable communities. Loss and damage refer to the residual effects of climate <lb/>change, where adaptation and mitigation measures may not be enough to prevent adverse impacts. <lb/>This study examines the impact of loss and damage caused by climate change in the Lower Niger <lb/>River region of Nigeria and the influence of global perspectives on the region. The research adopted <lb/>a mixed-methods approach, including a survey of 198 households and 13 interviews with key <lb/>stakeholders. Furthermore, an open-source terra climate data of precipitation, runoff, and tempera-<lb/>ture covering a 30-year period (1990-2020) sourced from Climate Research Unit (CRU) dataset and <lb/>analysed to show distribution of trends and patterns in climate variables. Similarly, we conducted <lb/>a land use land cover change (1990-2020) to ascertain the level of changes. Findings from the study <lb/>have revealed that the anthropogenic factors contribute to hydrological changes in the Lower Niger <lb/>River Region and these changes result in climatic disasters like flooding which cause severe loss and <lb/>damage of livelihood including loss of agricultural productivity, fisheries, and accessibility. While <lb/>global efforts to mitigate and adapt to climate change are important, the study uncovers that the <lb/>influence of global perspectives on the Lower Niger River Region is often limited by factors such as <lb/>unequal power dynamics, insufficient funding, and a lack of local ownership of initiatives. The study <lb/>suggests the need for sustainable land management, resolution of farmers/headers conflict and <lb/>increased awareness as measures in addressing loss and damage. <lb/>ARTICLE HISTORY <lb/>Received 23 August 2023 <lb/>Accepted 19 December 2023 <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>climate change; loss; <lb/>damage; global perspectives <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Climate change is one of the challenges facing <lb/>human societies and the environment, and has <lb/>become a global issue with potential to cause social, <lb/>economic, and environmental disruption. In addi-<lb/>tion, it exacerbates existing vulnerability and poses <lb/>a significant threat to sustainable development, agri-<lb/>culture and food security (Kasperson et al., 2022). <lb/>For example, flooding causes significant loss and <lb/>damage to agricultural product and increases the <lb/>vulnerability of rural farmers especially in developing <lb/>countries (Tolika &amp; Skoulikaris, 2023). <lb/>The United Nations Framework Convention on <lb/>Climate Change (UNFCCC) recognises loss and damage <lb/>as an important aspect of climate change negotiations, <lb/>with discussions focusing on financing mechanisms to <lb/>support affected communities. However, different per-<lb/>spectives exist on loss and damage, especially on finan-<lb/>cing for addressing the issue. Developed countries tend <lb/>to focus on adaptation and mitigation measures, while <lb/>vulnerable communities demand urgent action and <lb/>transformative change (Boyd et al., 2017). <lb/>Nigeria, like many other countries in Africa, is faced <lb/>with the negative impacts of climate change in form of <lb/>flooding, sea level rise, erosion, and declining agricul-<lb/>tural productivity. Nature loss and damage in Nigeria <lb/>refer to the negative impact on the natural environment <lb/>and its biodiversity caused by human activities, climate <lb/>change, and other natural phenomena (Olaniyi et al., <lb/>2013). Climate change is adding to the nature of loss and <lb/>damage, with some countries experiencing more fre-<lb/>quent and intense weather events such as flooding and <lb/>droughts, which have led to crop failures, food insecur-<lb/>ity, and the displacement of people from their homes <lb/>(Taylor et al., 2016). <lb/>The Lower Niger River Region has experienced <lb/>severe climate disasters such as flooding and has <lb/>caused damage to farmland, crops, and infrastruc-<lb/>tures leading to loss of income and livelihoods. In <lb/>addition, other factors like climate disasters, land use <lb/></body>

			<front>CONTACT Cyril Joseph Effiong <lb/>cxe921@student.bham.ac.uk <lb/>School of Geography and Environmental Science, University of Birmingham, Edgbaston, <lb/>Birmingham B15 2TT, UK <lb/>This article has been republished with minor changes. These changes do not impact the academic content of the article. <lb/>Reviewing editor: Michelle Bloor Alagappa University, Department of Geology, India <lb/>SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/>2024, VOL. 10, NO. 1, 2299549 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/27658511.2023.2299549 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by Informa UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis Group. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The terms on which this article has been published allow the posting of the Accepted <lb/>Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent. <lb/></front>

			<body>change, food production, insecurity, insecure tenure, <lb/>and food insecurity contribute to loss and damage <lb/>which makes it an important aspect in the study of <lb/>climate change (Action, 2021). <lb/>In the global perspective, different arguments <lb/>have emerged from stakeholders on the process of <lb/>handling the issue of loss and damage. This has <lb/>resulted in countries having divergent opinions on <lb/>approaches to addressing damage. For example, <lb/>developed countries believe that existing adaptation <lb/>and mitigation efforts to reduce greenhouse gas <lb/>emissions do not support climate adaptation and <lb/>are insufficient to effectively address the loss and <lb/>damage arising from climate change (Change, <lb/>2012). In contrast, vulnerable developing countries <lb/>take an existential perspective, arguing that loss and <lb/>damage represent an urgent threat to their survival <lb/>and that additional dedicated finance is needed to <lb/>address them (Boyd et al., 2017; Kasperson et al., <lb/>2022). This therefore increases doubt whether neo-<lb/>liberal policies on climate change can fully address <lb/>loss and damage especially for vulnerable <lb/>communities. <lb/>This research aims to explores the impact of cli-<lb/>mate change on farming households in the Lower <lb/>Niger River Region of Nigeria, with a particular <lb/>focus on loss and damage. The study seeks to exam-<lb/>ine the different perspectives held by stakeholders <lb/>and the extent to which loss and damage from flood-<lb/>ing has influence the coping strategies of farmers in <lb/>the region. This research among other things will <lb/>contribute to the ongoing debate on loss and damage <lb/>from climate hazards and provide insights into effec-<lb/>tive ways to address loss and damage especially for <lb/>vulnerable communities. <lb/>Methodology <lb/>This study employs a mixed-methods approach, <lb/>combining quantitative and qualitative data to <lb/>explore the impacts of loss and damage from climate <lb/>change and how it influences global perspectives in <lb/>the lower Niger River area of Nigeria. The study area <lb/>was stratified based on proximity to the river, and <lb/>a random sampling technique was used to select <lb/>farming households in each stratum. A total of 198 <lb/>households were selected and surveyed using <lb/>a structured questionnaire. Additionally, key infor-<lb/>mant interviews were conducted with farmers and <lb/>community leaders to gain insights into how their <lb/>coping strategies influence global perspectives on <lb/>loss and damage. <lb/>Study site <lb/>The study area spans two states in Nigeria: Ogbaru in <lb/>Anambra State and Asaba (Oshimili South) in Delta <lb/>State, Nigeria, all in South-eastern part of Nigeria. The <lb/>field work was done in selected communities of these <lb/>local government areas. The study area is located on <lb/>longitude 7 0 30&apos;&apos;N and latitude 7°30&apos;&apos;E in Asaba, and 6 <lb/>0 <lb/>2&apos;52&apos;N and latitude 6°44&apos;18&apos;E in Anambra State; and is <lb/>bounded by Anambra west Local government area in <lb/>the North, Ihiala Local Government Area in the South; <lb/>Anioch LGA in Delta in the West and Onitsha South in <lb/>the East. The Niger river cut across the two states and <lb/>extends into the Atlantic Ocean in the South. See <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>Data collection <lb/>The survey questionnaire was administered in person by <lb/>trained research assistants, who explained the purpose <lb/>of the study and obtained informed consent from parti-<lb/>cipants. The questionnaire is organized into three dis-<lb/>tinct sections. The first section serves as the gateway, <lb/>encompassing the participant information sheet and the <lb/>consent form for participation. In this initial part, par-<lb/>ticipants are provided with essential information about <lb/>the study&apos;s purpose, potential risks and benefits, and <lb/>their rights as participants. They are required to read <lb/>and sign the consent form, signifying their informed <lb/>agreement to take part in the research. <lb/>Moving on to the second section, it is dedicated to <lb/>capturing the sociodemographic characteristics of the <lb/>respondents. This segment of the questionnaire collects <lb/>data on key demographic factors, including age, gender, <lb/>marital status, educational background, the agricultural <lb/>products cultivated, farm size, work experience, farm <lb/>ownership, and monthly income. These details offer <lb/>valuable context for analysing how climate change per-<lb/>ceptions and adaptation strategies may vary among <lb/>different groups of participants. <lb/>Lastly, the third section delves into the perceptions of <lb/>farmers regarding the extent of damage caused by flood-<lb/>ing and their response measures to climate change and <lb/>adaptation. Here, participants are asked to provide <lb/>insights into the impact of flooding on their agricultural <lb/>and Fishing endeavours, encompassing factors such as <lb/>property damage, crop loss, and livelihood disruption. <lb/>Additionally, this section explores the strategies and <lb/>actions that respondents have implemented or plan to <lb/>implement to adapt to the challenges posed by climate <lb/>change. <lb/>Drawing from the methodology of (Katirtzidou et al., <lb/>2023) who analysed stakeholder perceptions of various <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>climate-related phenomena, we inquired whether respon-<lb/>dents had observed or anticipated occurrences of episodic <lb/>coastal inundation, water scarcity, or changing tempera-<lb/>ture. The key informant interviews were conducted in <lb/>person or via phone, and responses were recorded and <lb/>transcribed for analysis. Stakeholders were asked to assess <lb/>specific hazards and decision-making process covering <lb/>flood risk and changing temperature and other observed <lb/>challenges. In discussing these challenges, we leverage on <lb/>the influence of global perspectives on loss and damage on <lb/>the Lower Niger River Region. Additionally, an open-<lb/>source terra climate data of precipitation, runoff, and tem-<lb/>perature covering a 30-year period (1990-2020) was <lb/>sourced from Climate Research Unit (CRU) dataset <lb/>( h t t p s : / / c l i m a t e . n o r t h w e s t k n o w l e d g e . n e t / <lb/>TERRACLIMATE/index_directDownloads.php) and ana-<lb/>lysed using R programming to show trends and patterns. <lb/>The reason for the choice of CRU is its long-term coverage <lb/>which aligns with my 30-year study. Secondly was the <lb/>quality and consistency of data and being that their data <lb/>undergoes rigorous quality control procedures, making it <lb/>reliable for research and analysis. <lb/>Time series data of Land Use Land Cover Change <lb/>of the study area was obtained from United States <lb/>Geological Survey (USGS, https://www.usgs.gov/) <lb/>and analysed using Landsat imagery (TM, ETM+, <lb/>OLIS/TIRS). The imageries were cloud free obtained <lb/>to cover 1990, 2000, 2010 and 2020. The imageries <lb/>were geographically projected on UTM 32N WGS84. <lb/>Using (Chander et al., 2009) reflectance value on <lb/>Figure 1. Map showing the study area. Source: Authors&apos; design, 2023 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>algorithm, the imageries were converted to TOA-Top <lb/>of Atmosphere and thereafter Dark Object <lb/>Subtraction was applied to the Landsat data for cor-<lb/>rection (Zhang et al., 2010). The image was extracted <lb/>to fit into the study area boundary shapefile in <lb/>ArcGIS 10.4 and image enhancement was performed <lb/>to classify the image into four land use (waterbody, <lb/>floodplain, vegetation and built up) following the <lb/>Random Forest image classification proposed by <lb/>(Breiman, 2001). The classification was adopted <lb/>because of its robustness and high classification accu-<lb/>racy when compared with traditional image classifi-<lb/>cation (Jin et al., 2018). <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>Quantitative data was analysed using descriptive statis-<lb/>tics such as frequencies and percentages, and qualitative <lb/>data was analysed in NVivo, where interview data was <lb/>coded and recategorized into themes to reflect global <lb/>perspectives on loss and damage. In addition, <lb/>R programming was used in analysing open-source <lb/>climate data from Climate Research Unit dataset to <lb/>show distribution of precipitation, runoff, and tempera-<lb/>ture. A Spearman ranked corelation was conducted to <lb/>determine the level of relationship among these <lb/>variables. <lb/>Ethical considerations <lb/>This study obtained ethical approval from the <lb/>Institutional Review Board of University of <lb/>Birmingham. Informed consent was obtained from all <lb/>participants, and confidentiality and anonymity were <lb/>ensured throughout the study. Participants were <lb/>informed that they could withdraw from the study at <lb/>any time without penalty. <lb/>Conceptualising loss and damage <lb/>Loss and damage, a topic garnering increasing atten-<lb/>tion in international climate change discussions, <lb/>denotes the repercussions faced by certain countries, <lb/>primarily developing countries, that lack the capacity <lb/>to manage climate change impacts effectively, result-<lb/>ing in adverse consequences for people, ecosystems, <lb/>and economies (Pörtner et al., 2022). This issue has <lb/>gained prominence as mounting evidence suggests <lb/>that countries are already experiencing loss and <lb/>damage, even with adaptation and mitigation efforts <lb/>in place (Roberts &amp; Huq, 2015). The United Nations <lb/>Framework Convention on Climate Change <lb/>(UNFCCC) recognizes the need for a wide range of <lb/>tools to address both preventable and inevitable loss <lb/>and damage (Verheyen &amp; Roderick, 2008). <lb/>Preventable loss and damage can be mitigated <lb/>through disaster risk reduction and climate change <lb/>adaptation, while inevitable impacts persist due to <lb/>socio-economic constraints. <lb/>Defining loss and damage involves recognizing cli-<lb/>mate risks from extreme events like flooding, cyclones, <lb/>sea level rise, and desertification, encompassing their <lb/>impacts on human and natural systems, such as loss of <lb/>life, property, displacement, food and water insecurity, <lb/>and ecosystem damage (James et al., 2014). The <lb/>absence of a precise definition has led to ambiguity <lb/>and disagreement among stakeholders, hindering pol-<lb/>icy development and delaying progress in global nego-<lb/>tiations (Calliari, 2018). The lack of clarity also affects <lb/>the implementation of risk transfer mechanisms like <lb/>insurance and financial instruments, crucial for <lb/>addressing loss and damage (Linnerooth-Bayer et al., <lb/>2011). <lb/>Liability and compensation issues pose further chal-<lb/>lenges, especially for developing countries that argue <lb/>addressing these is essential for advancing loss and damage <lb/>discussions (Tol &amp; Verheyen, 2004). The political context <lb/>surrounding loss and damage has evolved, initially focus-<lb/>ing on adaptation but later acknowledging the limits of <lb/>adaptation and exploring new approaches, including risk <lb/>transfer mechanisms (Khan &amp; Roberts, 2013). These <lb/>approaches face criticism for their inadequacy, particularly <lb/>in catastrophic events like hurricanes and floods. It is <lb/>imperative that the international community continues <lb/>working towards equitable solutions to support vulnerable <lb/>populations in adapting to climate change (Smith, 2013). <lb/>Incorporating various perspectives and interdisciplin-<lb/>ary collaboration is crucial in addressing loss and damage <lb/>effectively, as emphasized by (van der Geest &amp; Warner, <lb/>2015). Futhermore, (Boyd et al., 2021) underscores the <lb/>need for a climate justice agenda and compensation <lb/>mechanisms to rectify the inequality in climate impacts. <lb/>Vulnerable communities, despite minimal contributions <lb/>to greenhouse gas emissions, bear the brunt of climate <lb/>impacts due to the absence of clear compensation <lb/>mechanisms. While the literature on loss and damage <lb/>has grown, a more comprehensive, multidisciplinary <lb/>approach is required, integrating insights from climate <lb/>science, social sciences, and economics to understand the <lb/>complexities involved (Boyd et al., 2021). <lb/>Perspectives on loss and damage <lb/>In this section we examine four different perspectives on <lb/>loss and damage and how they fit into the overall goal of <lb/>climate risk reduction. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>Existential perspective <lb/>The existential perspective on loss and damage is held by <lb/>vulnerable developing countries. It emphasises the urgent <lb/>need for transformative action to address the root causes <lb/>of climate change (Boyd et al., 2017). In addition, it <lb/>recognises the threat posed by climate change to human <lb/>societies and ecosystems and argues for urgent and trans-<lb/>formative action to address the root causes of climate <lb/>change. This perspective challenges the current economic <lb/>and political systems that prioritise short-term economic <lb/>gains over long-term sustainability and social justice and <lb/>calls for radical changes in how we live and work. <lb/>Adaptation and mitigation perspective <lb/>This perspective emphasises the importance of adapta-<lb/>tion and mitigation with countries reducing greenhouse <lb/>gas emissions and adapting to the impacts of climate <lb/>change to prevent or minimise the occurrence of loss <lb/>and damage (Boyd et al., 2017). This perspective <lb/>acknowledges the limitations of relying solely on tech-<lb/>nical solutions for managing climate change impact <lb/>particularly in vulnerable developing countries. This is <lb/>the reason (Neufeldt et al., 2021) suggests that the chal-<lb/>lenges faced by these countries in effectively mitigating <lb/>and adapting to the impact of climate change, result in <lb/>ongoing loss and damage. <lb/>For example (Warner &amp; Van der Geest, 2013) focuses <lb/>on the residual impacts of climate change, which occur <lb/>when existing coping and adaptation measures are insuf-<lb/>ficient, the costs of implementing measures cannot be <lb/>recovered, measures have negative long-term effects <lb/>despite short-term benefits, or no measures are adopted <lb/>or feasible at all. Moreso, it includes examining the spe-<lb/>cific contexts and conditions under which different types <lb/>of residual impacts occur, as well as exploring potential <lb/>strategies for minimizing and addressing them. <lb/>Scholars have recognized that adaptation and mitiga-<lb/>tion strategies have their limitations, especially in <lb/>regions where socioeconomic constraints, inadequate <lb/>resources, and other vulnerabilities hinder their imple-<lb/>mentation (Klein et al., 2015; Kuruppu &amp; Willie, 2015; <lb/>Shackleton et al., 2015). Despite efforts to reduce green-<lb/>house gas emissions and implement adaptation mea-<lb/>sures, vulnerable countries may still experience <lb/>increasing loss and damage due to the complex and <lb/>interconnected nature of climate change impacts. <lb/>Technical perspective <lb/>The technical perspective on addressing loss and <lb/>damage fits into the overall goal of climate risk by <lb/>contributing to the reduction of vulnerability and the <lb/>enhancement of adaptive capacity (Homberg &amp; <lb/>McQuistan, 2019). By focusing on technological and <lb/>engineering solutions, this perspective aims to minimize <lb/>the impacts of climate-related stressors on individuals, <lb/>communities, infrastructure, and ecosystems. <lb/>The application of technical measures, such as engi-<lb/>neering solutions, early warning systems, and resilient <lb/>infrastructure, is crucial for protecting people, proper-<lb/>ties, and ecosystems from the adverse effects of climate <lb/>change. For example, in the case of the Lower Niger <lb/>Basin, where flooding is a significant hazard, the imple-<lb/>mentation of flood-resistant buildings or flood protec-<lb/>tion systems like levees and flood barriers can help <lb/>mitigate the impacts of floods and reduce potential <lb/>loss and damage. <lb/>The technical perspective emphasizes the use of scien-<lb/>tific knowledge and technological innovations to design <lb/>and construct physical systems that are more resistant <lb/>and resilient to climate-related hazards. By incorporating <lb/>advancements in engineering and technology, this per-<lb/>spective aims to minimize vulnerabilities and enhance the <lb/>ability of communities and infrastructure to withstand <lb/>and recover from climate-related events. <lb/>However, it is important to recognize that technical <lb/>perspectives alone are not sufficient to address all <lb/>aspects of loss and damage. They should be comple-<lb/>mented by other perspectives such as legal frameworks <lb/>to establish norms and facilitate dispute resolution, <lb/>humanitarian considerations for timely emergency <lb/>relief and crisis management, development strategies <lb/>for long-term resilience building, and recognition of <lb/>non-economic values associated with loss and damage. <lb/>Risk management perspective <lb/>The risk management perspective on loss and damage <lb/>recognizes the opportunity to integrate comprehensive <lb/>risk management approaches into discussions and <lb/>initiatives on this critical issue (Boyd et al., 2017). It <lb/>aligns Loss and Damage (L&amp;D) efforts with disaster risk <lb/>reduction (DRR), climate change adaptation, and <lb/>humanitarian work, aiming for a holistic approach <lb/>that links these initiatives with sustainable development, <lb/>DRR, and climate change resilience building. <lb/>This perspective aligns with the overarching goal of <lb/>climate risk management by offering a comprehensive <lb/>approach to addressing and managing climate-related <lb/>risks. It acknowledges the interconnectedness between <lb/>loss and damage, disaster risk reduction, climate change <lb/>adaptation, and sustainable development, aiming to <lb/>integrate these efforts into a unified risk management <lb/>framework. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>To reduce the likelihood and severity of loss and <lb/>damage, risk reduction strategies are employed, such <lb/>as implementing mitigation measures and promoting <lb/>sustainable practices. This includes building resilient <lb/>infrastructure capable of withstanding climate-related <lb/>hazards and adopting land use practices that minimize <lb/>vulnerability. <lb/>The risk management perspective takes a techno-<lb/>pragmatic problem-solving approach, emphasizing the <lb/>need to understand the interconnected nature of risks. It <lb/>discourages treating loss and damage and adaptation as <lb/>separate policy processes, advocating instead for an <lb/>integrated approach within a broader risk management <lb/>framework. <lb/>By integrating discussions and initiatives on loss <lb/>and damage with existing frameworks, stakeholders <lb/>can leverage synergies, build on existing knowledge <lb/>and experiences, and enhance overall risk manage-<lb/>ment efforts. This integrated approach enables <lb/>a more coordinated and effective response to mana-<lb/>ging the risks associated with loss and damage from <lb/>climate change, ultimately contributing to the over-<lb/>arching goal of reducing climate risk and promoting <lb/>resilience. <lb/>In summary, these perspectives are interconnected and <lb/>complementary. The Existential Perspective motivates <lb/>action, Adaptation and Mitigation Perspectives offer stra-<lb/>tegies, the Technical Perspective provides tools, and the <lb/>Management Perspective ensures effective implementation <lb/>and coordination. Together, they form a comprehensive <lb/>framework for understanding, addressing, and managing <lb/>loss and damage from climate change. <lb/>Result and discussion <lb/>Analysis of climate data (temperature, precipitation <lb/>and runoff -1990-2020) <lb/>The primary outcome derived from the analysis conducted <lb/>using R programming pertains to the distribution of <lb/>temperature, precipitation, and runoff. These key climatic <lb/>variables have been rigorously examined and subsequently <lb/>discussed within the context of the study. The results <lb/>obtained shed light on the distribution patterns observed <lb/>over a 30-year timeframe. This extended period of analysis <lb/>has been crucial in enhancing our comprehension of cli-<lb/>mate change dynamics and their profound implications on <lb/>the well-being of the farming community. <lb/>Specifically, these findings offer valuable insights into <lb/>how shifts in temperature, precipitation, and runoff <lb/>have unfolded over the three decades under considera-<lb/>tion. Such insights are paramount in comprehending <lb/>the evolving climate patterns and the ways in which <lb/>they impact the livelihoods of farmers. The repercus-<lb/>sions of these climatic shifts are notable, particularly in <lb/>terms of the associated loss and damage experienced by <lb/>agricultural communities. <lb/>Distribution of temperature (1990-2020) <lb/>The lower Niger River region experiences a tropical <lb/>climate, characterized by distinct wet and dry seasons. <lb/>In Nigeria, there are two seasons (dry and raining sea-<lb/>sons); with dry seasons starting in October-March and <lb/>the rainy reason starts late March to October. <lb/>During the wet season, temperatures are generally <lb/>warmer due to the higher humidity levels and increased <lb/>cloud cover. Average temperatures during this time can <lb/>range from 25°C to 35°C (77°F to 95°F) or even higher. <lb/>In contrast, during the dry season, temperatures can be <lb/>slightly cooler, ranging from 20°C to 30°C (68°F to 86°F) <lb/>on average. <lb/>Figure 2 shows a regular distribution of temperature <lb/>in the years under review which is reflected based on the <lb/>seasons of the year. The higher the temperature, the <lb/>hottest the weather which is represented with tempera-<lb/>ture above 30°C°. Similarly, the mean plot of tempera-<lb/>ture in the study area representing the two seasons <lb/>(rainy and dry seasons) in the years under study. <lb/>During the dry season the temperature is high and <lb/>Figure 2. Distribution of temperature in the Lower Niger River (1990-2020). <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>during the rainy season the temperature is low. <lb/>Invariably, it means the higher the temperature, the <lb/>hotter the weather and the lower the temperature, the <lb/>cooler the temperature. The downward trend shows the <lb/>cooler temperature, and the upward trend shows the <lb/>hotter temperature. The warmest temperatures, aver-<lb/>aging 0.6°C above the long-term means, were recorded <lb/>during the reference period spanning from 1990 to <lb/>2020. Notably, several high-temperature years were pin-<lb/>pointed, including 1990, 1999, 2001, 2002, 2003, 2004, <lb/>2005, and 2020. The data also highlighted the presence <lb/>of four of the warmest years within the second study <lb/>period (2000-2010), with only one of such occurrences <lb/>in the third study period (2010-2020). <lb/>Distribution of precipitation and runoff (1990-2020) <lb/>The Lower Niger River region undergoes a distinctive <lb/>rainfall pattern that spans from March to October, with <lb/>its zenith occurring between June and September. The <lb/>distribution of rainfall across space, depicted in Figure 3, <lb/>signifies the recurring nature of flooding on an annual <lb/>basis, with the severity of such events contingent upon the <lb/>intensity of rainfall. The inception of rainfall typically <lb/>takes place in March, coinciding with thunderstorms <lb/>and the progression of both the Intertropical <lb/>Convergence Zone (ITCZ) and the West African <lb/>Monsoon system, as highlighted by (Vasquez, 2009). <lb/>Furthermore, the precipitation in the Lower Niger <lb/>River area is a result of wind systems originating from <lb/>the southwest and sweeping across West Africa, <lb/>carrying moisture-laden air from the Atlantic Ocean, <lb/>as observed by (Lélé et al., 2015). The quantity and <lb/>timing of rainfall in this region vary based on the <lb/>potency and trajectory of these influencing factors, <lb/>including the ITCZ and the West African Monsoon <lb/>system, as well as other atmospheric conditions. This <lb/>variability is reflected in Figure 3, which portrays the <lb/>fluctuating occurrence of extreme weather events in the <lb/>area. The average annual rainfall in the region typically <lb/>ranges between 1500 mm and 2500 mm. However, the <lb/>Niger Delta zone experiences a more abundant annual <lb/>precipitation, ranging from 2500 mm to 4000 mm. This <lb/>region, characterized by a complex network of water-<lb/>ways, swamps, and wetlands, provides the essential <lb/>foundations for the livelihoods of its inhabitants. <lb/>Statistics analysis <lb/>Utilizing the available time-series data, a Spearman rank <lb/>correlation analysis was undertaken to investigate the inter-<lb/>relationships among precipitation, runoff, and tempera-<lb/>ture. To establish a robust foundation for our <lb/>investigations, we relied on hydrological data sourced <lb/>from the dataset outlined by (Amanambu et al., 2019). <lb/>This dataset served as a foundation for our simulations, <lb/>seeking to ensure precision and reliability. We anchored <lb/>our simulation on validated parameters derived from the <lb/>prior study conducted by (Efon et al., 2023), a methodology <lb/>widely recognized and successfully implemented in similar <lb/>contexts. Furthermore, in a bid to strengthen our validation <lb/>process, we integrated observed monthly runoff, <lb/>Figure 3. Hydrography showing distribution of precipitation and runoff in the Lower Niger River (1990-2020). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Precipitation Temperature data spanning from 1990 to <lb/>2020 obtained from the CRU dataset. Our analysis yielded <lb/>noteworthy coefficients for runoff, temperature and pre-<lb/>cipitation demonstrating a robust agreement between the <lb/>simulated and anticipated value. This reinforced the relia-<lb/>bility of our findings and the accuracy of our simulated data <lb/>for the Lower Niger River Basin. <lb/>This analytical approach was adopted with the objec-<lb/>tive of assessing the reliability of the data and its align-<lb/>ment with the observed events within the study area. <lb/>The formula for calculating the Spearman rank correla-<lb/>tion coefficient (rs) is as follows: <lb/>rs = 1 -[(6Σd 2 )/(n (n 2 -1))] <lb/>Where: <lb/>• Σd 2 represents the sum of the squared differences <lb/>between the ranks of corresponding pairs of data <lb/>points. <lb/>• n is the number of data points. <lb/>The result revealed that a positive correlation coefficient <lb/>(P) of 0.87 between precipitation and runoff suggests <lb/>a strong positive association. As precipitation levels <lb/>increase, runoff levels tend to increase as well. This <lb/>means that when there is more rainfall in the study <lb/>area, it leads to a higher volume of water runoff. <lb/>Furthermore, an inverse (negative) correlation coef-<lb/>ficient of -0.70 between runoff and temperature indi-<lb/>cates a negative relationship. When runoff increases, <lb/>temperature tends to decrease. In other words, when <lb/>there is more water runoff, it tends to be associated with <lb/>lower temperatures in the study area. For a visual repre-<lb/>sentation of these correlations, please refer to Figure 4, <lb/>which presents the correlation matrix, and Figure 5, <lb/>displaying the scatter plot of these correlations. <lb/>Analysis of land use land cover change (1990-2020) <lb/>To ascertain changes in land use, we carry out land <lb/>use land cover change within the 30-year period. The <lb/>result as shown in Figures 6 and 7 revealed that the <lb/>significance of anthropogenic factors, notably the <lb/>increase of physical development, intensive farming, <lb/>and land clearance practises, as contributing factors to <lb/>the changes in the hydrological regime of the Niger <lb/>River. These findings corroborate the conclusions <lb/>drawn in the research conducted by (Nkiruka et al., <lb/>2023). These human-induced activities possess the <lb/>potential to modify fundamental land surface attri-<lb/>butes, including alterations in vegetation cover and <lb/>changes in soil moisture content. Consequently, such <lb/>alterations can significantly impact the intricate <lb/>hydrological processes within the region. The cumu-<lb/>lative effect manifests in a series of consequences <lb/>directly affecting local farmers, their agricultural prac-<lb/>tices, and ultimately, their livelihoods. These outcomes <lb/>align closely with the conclusions drawn in the study <lb/>conducted by (Nand et al., 2023), further substantiat-<lb/>ing the observed loss and damage experienced by the <lb/>local farming communities. <lb/>Significant changes in land use and land cover have <lb/>been observed over a three-year study period in the <lb/>Lower Niger River region, as illustrated in Table 1. <lb/>Between 1990 and 2000, there was a notable 51.93% <lb/>increase in built-up areas, a 39.56% expansion of flood-<lb/>plain regions, and an 8.09% growth in water bodies. <lb/>However, this period also witnessed a substantial decrease <lb/>of 50.92% in vegetation cover. <lb/>Upon comparing the results across the three study <lb/>periods, distinct trends in land use changes emerge. The <lb/>built-up area demonstrated an increase of 51% during <lb/>the first study period (1990-2000), a more pronounced <lb/>rise of 66.84% during the second phase (2000-2010), <lb/>and a more modest growth of 3.04% during the third <lb/>study period. Particularly noteworthy is the sharp rise of <lb/>66.8% in the built-up area during the second study <lb/>period, closely followed by the 51.93% increase observed <lb/>in the first period. Conversely, the third study period <lb/>displayed only a 3.0% increase. <lb/>While there was a slight uptick of 3.3% in vegeta-<lb/>tion during the second study period, the trend was <lb/>divergent during the first and third study periods, <lb/>which saw substantial declines of 50.9% and 15.8%, <lb/>Figure 4. Correlation matrix. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>respectively. This decline can be attributed to the <lb/>increasing expansion of built-up areas across all <lb/>three study periods. <lb/>In terms of floodplain areas, a 39.5% increase was <lb/>recorded during the first study period, followed by <lb/>an 11.58% rise in the third period. However, <lb/>the second study period experienced a decrease of <lb/>2.9%. Despite this reduction, these areas remain cru-<lb/>cial for floodplain farming, a vital livelihood activity <lb/>for the local community. <lb/>Water bodies exhibited a declining trend of 165% <lb/>during the second study period and 3.5% during the <lb/>third study period. This decline is a consequence of <lb/>human activities linked to the overall expansion of built-<lb/>up areas across all study periods. Based on the available <lb/>data, a clear and compelling picture emerges, indicating <lb/>that human activities exert a substantial influence on the <lb/>climatic changes witnessed in the study area. The data <lb/>underscores a direct correlation between human actions <lb/>and the notable shifts in the local climate. These shifts, <lb/>in turn, have consequential effects on the region&apos;s liveli-<lb/>hoods, leading to evident loss and damage. <lb/>The study delves into the complex issue of loss and <lb/>damage resulting from climate change in the Lower <lb/>Niger River region of Nigeria. Climate change is <lb/>a global phenomenon with far-reaching consequences, <lb/>and the Lower Niger River region serves as <lb/>a microcosm where the local impacts intersect with <lb/>broader global perspectives. Central to this examina-<lb/>tion is the role of land-use change as a critical driver <lb/>of loss and damage in the region. <lb/>Qualitative analysis <lb/>Exploring stakeholders perception <lb/>To ascertain stakeholders&apos; perception, we conducted 13 <lb/>in-person interviews with a diverse group of partici-<lb/>pants, including local farmers, fishermen, and represen-<lb/>tatives from associations, cooperatives, unions, and <lb/>non-governmental organizations (NGOs). Data <lb/>included in the analysis observational tools and field <lb/>notes recorded during the fieldwork. The interview <lb/>recordings were transcribed using NVivo and emerging <lb/>theme which we used to gain valuable insights into the <lb/>challenges posed by floods, water scarcity, and changing <lb/>the result on the perspectives and decision-making pro-<lb/>cesses of key stakeholders in the Lower Niger River <lb/>region concerning climate-related hazards. <lb/>Perceptions of flood risks <lb/>During the interviews, participants engaged in candid <lb/>discussions regarding the growing frequency and sever-<lb/>ity of floods in the Lower Niger River region, under-<lb/>lining the substantial toll inflicted on homes, farmlands, <lb/>and vital infrastructure. Their narratives were marked <lb/>by a sense of urgency and concern stemming from the <lb/>escalating impact of flooding events. These floods, often <lb/>triggered by heavy rainfall, have led to severe losses and <lb/>damage, exacting a profound toll on the affected com-<lb/>munities. Participants recounted distressing stories of <lb/>inundated homes, damaged property, and the displace-<lb/>ment of families, testifying to the devastating conse-<lb/>quences of these recurring floods. <lb/>Figure 5. Correlation scatter plot for precipitation, runoff and temperature. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Amid these challenges, a noteworthy theme emerged <lb/>-local knowledge and traditional coping mechanisms. <lb/>Participants highlighted the value of indigenous wisdom <lb/>passed down through generations, offering insights into <lb/>flood forecasting based on natural indicators, such as <lb/>wildlife behaviour and river flow patterns. They <lb/>described how communities united during flood events, <lb/>extending support and shelter to those affected. <lb/>Additionally, participants touched upon another press-<lb/>ing issue related to flood impacts-the migration of <lb/>Fulani cattle from the northern part of Nigeria. This <lb/>phenomenon, as reported, has been causing severe <lb/>damage to farmlands, as the cattle invade cultivated <lb/>areas, resulting in the destruction of crops. This recur-<lb/>rent conflict between farmers and herders has com-<lb/>pounded the hardships faced by communities, further <lb/>underscoring the complex web of challenges associated <lb/>with floods and their aftermath. <lb/>Changing temperature patterns <lb/>During the interviews, participants candidly shared <lb/>their observations regarding shifting temperature pat-<lb/>terns in the Lower Niger River Region. They empha-<lb/>sized the discernible changes in temperature, <lb/>characterized by more frequent and prolonged heat-<lb/>waves. These altered temperature patterns have <lb/>emerged as a prominent climate-related concern within <lb/>the region, prompting discussions that spanned various <lb/>aspects of life. <lb/>Participants highlighted the multifaceted impact of <lb/>these temperature shifts, particularly the intensification <lb/>of heatwaves with consequences extending across <lb/>health, agriculture, and overall well-being. furthermore, <lb/>participants expressed concerns about the increased risk <lb/>of heat-related illnesses and discomfort, particularly <lb/>among vulnerable populations such as the elderly and <lb/>children having malaria. This problem tends to strain <lb/>Figure 6. Map of land use land cover changes (1990-2020). <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>healthcare systems and places additional burdens on <lb/>communities already grappling with other climate-<lb/>related challenges. <lb/>In agriculture, the effects of rising temperatures are <lb/>keenly felt. Participants shared their experiences of <lb/>how prolonged heatwaves and higher temperatures <lb/>can lead to drought conditions, reduced soil moisture, <lb/>bird mortality and stressed crops. These conditions <lb/>can result in reduced yields and agricultural losses, <lb/>with cascading impacts on food security and <lb/>livelihoods. <lb/>During the period from January to March, my birds <lb/>were subjected to high temperature due to the roofing <lb/>material I have in place, which consists of corrugated zinc <lb/>sheets. This roofing material does not allow the birds to <lb/>sweat, and as a result, they release heat primarily through <lb/>their bodies. However, during the night when the tem-<lb/>peratures drop significantly, the birds often encounter <lb/>coughing issues. This coughing problem potentially led <lb/>to the unfortunate and recurring occurrence of bird <lb/>mortality. <lb/>Beyond health and agriculture, participants also <lb/>acknowledged the broader implications of shifting tem-<lb/>perature patterns on their overall well-being. They <lb/>described the challenges of coping with extreme heat, <lb/>especially in the absence of adequate cooling and <lb/>infrastructure. <lb/>Other observed challenges <lb/>The study brings to light a critical perspective on the global <lb/>efforts to address climate change and their impact, or lack <lb/>thereof, on the Lower Niger River Region. While interna-<lb/>tional initiatives aimed at mitigating and adapting to cli-<lb/>mate change are undeniably crucial, the participants <lb/>underscored that their influence in the region is frequently <lb/>constrained by a range of challenging factors. These limit-<lb/>ing factors encompass unequal power dynamics, inade-<lb/>quate funding, and water scarcity for agricultural <lb/>production. <lb/>Firstly, participants highlighted the presence of <lb/>unequal power dynamics among different actors as <lb/>impediment to achieving the implementation of global <lb/>climate initiatives in the Lower Niger River Region. <lb/>Participants alluded that most often, decision-making <lb/>processes and resource allocation favours more power-<lb/>ful or influential entities in communities which may not <lb/>necessarily prioritize the specific needs and vulnerabil-<lb/>ities of the region. <lb/>Secondly, participants discussed the issue of insuf-<lb/>ficient funding as a significant impediment to <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>450 <lb/>1990 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2010 <lb/>2020 <lb/>Trend of LULC Change <lb/>Water Body <lb/>Flood Plain <lb/>VegetaƟon <lb/>Built-up / Bare Land <lb/>Figure 7. Trend in land use land cover changes. <lb/>Table 1. Land use land cover changes (gain, loss, and rate of change) in the Lower Niger River grouped between 1990-2000, 2000-<lb/>2010, and 2010-2020, where G=gain, L=loss <lb/>LULC <lb/>1990-2000 <lb/>2000-2010 <lb/>2010-2020 <lb/>G/L <lb/>% Rate of change <lb/>G/L <lb/>% Rate of change <lb/>G/L <lb/>% Rate of change <lb/>Water Body <lb/>8.275 <lb/>8.09 <lb/>-63.714 <lb/>-165.46 <lb/>-1.312 <lb/>-3.53 <lb/>Floodplain <lb/>119.858 <lb/>39.56 <lb/>-8.743 <lb/>-2.97 <lb/>38.548 <lb/>11.59 <lb/>Vegetation <lb/>-144.262 <lb/>-50.92 <lb/>9.866 <lb/>3.37 <lb/>-40.176 <lb/>-15.88 <lb/>Built up <lb/>16.129 <lb/>51.93 <lb/>62.591 <lb/>66.84 <lb/>2.94 <lb/>3.04 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>climate adaptation. They revealed that despite the <lb/>global discourse on climate financing, the Lower <lb/>Niger River Region faces challenges in securing ade-<lb/>quate financial resources for climate mitigation and <lb/>adaptation efforts. This dearth of funding hinders <lb/>the region&apos;s ability to implement essential projects <lb/>and strategies which could have been of immense <lb/>benefit to the community. For instance, <lb/>participants complained that water scarcity limits <lb/>irrigation farming and the community public water <lb/>has been abandoned for years without repairs and <lb/>now farmers are finding it difficult to access water <lb/>for irrigation farming. <lb/>Lastly, participants vividly conveyed the chal-<lb/>posed by water scarcity in meeting daily <lb/>household needs. They described situations where <lb/>access to clean and reliable drinking water was often <lb/>compromised, especially during periods of low rain-<lb/>fall. This scarcity has significant ramifications for <lb/>sanitation, hygiene, and overall well-being, as it <lb/>impedes the ability of households to maintain <lb/>basic standards of cleanliness and health. In addi-<lb/>tion, participants lamented the constraints placed <lb/>on their farming endeavours due to irregular water <lb/>supply for irrigation. Crops wither, and yields <lb/>diminish in the face of insufficient moisture, leading <lb/>to food insecurity and economic hardship for farm-<lb/>ing communities. <lb/>Questionnaire analysis <lb/>Climate change impact affecting households in the <lb/>last 10 years <lb/>In the initial phase of our study, respondents were <lb/>queried regarding their first-hand experiences with <lb/>heavy rainfall resulting in flooding over the past <lb/>decade. A striking majority, exceeding 80% of the <lb/>respondents, affirmed that they had indeed wit-<lb/>nessed heavy rainfall leading to flooding within <lb/>this timeframe. Furthermore, we sought to ascertain <lb/>the frequency of such flood events during the rainy <lb/>season. The responses revealed that 11.9% of <lb/>respondents reported witnessing extreme rainfall <lb/>events lasting 1-3 days, while a substantial 48.3% <lb/>indicated that they had observed rainfall episodes <lb/>spanning more than 7 days. Table 2 provides an <lb/>overview of cumulative percentages representing <lb/>respondents&apos; awareness and concern regarding cli-<lb/>mate change impacts in the Lower Niger River <lb/>region. Notably, 59.1% of respondents acknowl-<lb/>edged that climate change had adversely affected <lb/>irrigation agriculture over the past decade, while <lb/>40.9% indicated their lack of awareness regarding <lb/>this issue. Additionally, the responses underscored <lb/>a limited understanding of temperature fluctuations, <lb/>with a significant 57.6% reporting unawareness, <lb/>while only 42.4% recognized temperature increases <lb/>Table 2. Climate hazard affecting farming household in the last 10 years <lb/>Climate hazards <lb/>Sub Characteristics <lb/>Frequency <lb/>Percentage <lb/>Witness Extreme rainfall that result in flooding <lb/>Yes <lb/>197 <lb/>99.4 <lb/>No <lb/>2 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>Number of days witnessed flood in rainy season due to extreme rainfall in the last <lb/>None <lb/>6 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>10years <lb/>1-3days <lb/>24 <lb/>11.9 <lb/>4-6days <lb/>74 <lb/>36.8 <lb/>&gt;7days <lb/>94 <lb/>48.3 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/>Number of days experience flooding in the last 10years <lb/>None <lb/>3 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1-3days <lb/>28 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>4-6days <lb/>121 <lb/>61.1 <lb/>&gt;7days <lb/>46 <lb/>23.2 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/>Number of times experience water scarcity in the last 10years <lb/>1-3times <lb/>49 <lb/>24.7 <lb/>4-6times <lb/>63 <lb/>31.8 <lb/>&gt;7times <lb/>86 <lb/>43.4 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/>Awareness of changing temperature which affect farming system <lb/>Yes <lb/>84 <lb/>42.4 <lb/>No <lb/>114 <lb/>57.6 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/>Number of times witness flooding event cause displacement of community and livelihoods in the last <lb/>1-3times <lb/>73 <lb/>36.9 <lb/>4-6times <lb/>110 <lb/>55.6 <lb/>10years <lb/>&gt;7times <lb/>15 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/>Climate change impact have negative effect on irrigation <lb/>Yes <lb/>117 <lb/>59.1 <lb/>No <lb/>81 <lb/>40.9 <lb/>Total <lb/>198 <lb/>100 <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>as having already impacted the agricultural sector. <lb/>Lastly, a substantial 56.6% of respondents recounted <lb/>witnessing flooding events causing community dis-<lb/>placement and livelihood disruptions within the <lb/>past 10 years. This displacement occurred 4-6 <lb/>times for the majority, while 36.9% reported 1-3 <lb/>instances, and a minority of 7.6% stated that they <lb/>had observed such events more than 7 times. <lb/>Extent of damage from flooding in the Lower Niger <lb/>Basin <lb/>To ascertain the extent of loss and damage to livelihoods <lb/>resulting from flooding, respondents were provided with <lb/>a set of five-point indicators in the questionnaire designed <lb/>to assess the magnitude of damage across various facets of <lb/>livelihoods, encompassing both agriculture and fisheries. <lb/>Tables 3 and 4 present a comprehensive exposition of the <lb/>extent of loss and damage observed within the Lower Niger <lb/>River basin, delineating these impacts across multiple <lb/>dimensions of livelihood aspects. <lb/>Agriculture <lb/>The data revealed that various agricultural components <lb/>including crop yield, crop production, quality of water <lb/>and land availability are impacted by flood and contri-<lb/>bute to the damage and loss of farmers in the region. <lb/>Crop yield and crop produce: The data indicates that <lb/>a significant proportion of households experienced <lb/>moderate losses in crop yield and crop produce. For <lb/>example, with 34.34% crop yield moderately affected <lb/>by flood, and 21.21% of crop yield are significantly <lb/>destroyed during flood. Similarly, 20.20% of crop pro-<lb/>duce are moderately affected by flood and 24.24% of <lb/>crop produced are destroyed during flood. Therefore, <lb/>this could lead to high price fluctuation due to scarcity <lb/>of the farming product which can plunge farmers into <lb/>poverty and landlessness. Secondly, depending on the <lb/>duration of flood, farmers can experience extreme loss <lb/>which increase their vulnerability and impact on other <lb/>livelihood components of farmers. This suggests that <lb/>farmers in the region have been significantly affected <lb/>by flooding, leading to reduced agricultural productivity <lb/>and potential scarcity of farming products. <lb/>Consequently, this can result in high price fluctuations <lb/>and negatively impact farmers&apos; income and livelihoods. <lb/>Fisheries <lb/>Fisheries livelihood aspect was assessed covering Fish <lb/>stock, access to fishing gear, and access to fishing equip-<lb/>ment as shown in Table 4. The assessment reveals the <lb/>extent of loss and damage to fisheries livelihoods. <lb/>30.30% of fish stocks were moderately affected by <lb/>flood, while 21.21% of fish stock were destroyed by <lb/>flood. Similarly, 27.78% access to fishing gear and tech-<lb/>nology were moderately affected while 21.21% access to <lb/>fishing gear and technology were destroyed. The overall <lb/>percentage of fisheries and accessibility moderately and <lb/>extremely affected was more than 50% which suggests <lb/>that flooding has adversely affected the fishing industry <lb/>Table 3. Extent of damage from flooding agriculture <lb/>N= 198 <lb/>Livelihood aspect <lb/>Not affected at all (%) <lb/>Slightly affected loss (%) <lb/>Neutral (%) <lb/>Moderately affected (%) <lb/>Destroyed or extreme loss (%) <lb/>Crop yield <lb/>15(7.58%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>28(14.14%) <lb/>68(34.34%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>Crop produce <lb/>38(19.19%) <lb/>50(25.25%) <lb/>22(11.11%) <lb/>40(20.20%) <lb/>48(24.25%) <lb/>Quality of water <lb/>36(18.18%) <lb/>20(10.10%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>55(27.78%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>Land availability <lb/>39(19.70%) <lb/>15(7.58%) <lb/>50(25.25%) <lb/>46(23.23%) <lb/>48(24.24%) <lb/>Quality of river water <lb/>30(15.15%) <lb/>31(15.66%) <lb/>40(20.20%) <lb/>55(27.78%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>Table 4. Extent of damage from flooding (fishing and accessibility) <lb/>N = 198 <lb/>Livelihood aspect <lb/>Not affected at all <lb/>(%) <lb/>Slightly affected <lb/>loss (%) <lb/>Neutral <lb/>(%) <lb/>Moderately <lb/>affected (%) <lb/>Destroyed or extreme <lb/>loss (%) <lb/>Fish stock <lb/>24(12.12%) <lb/>36(18.18%) <lb/>36(18.18%) <lb/>60(30.30%) <lb/>42(21.22%) <lb/>Access to fishing gear and technology <lb/>35(17.68%) <lb/>40(20.20%) <lb/>26(13.13%) <lb/>55(27.78%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>Access to fishing equipment <lb/>28(14.14%) <lb/>38(19.19%) <lb/>35(17.68%) <lb/>52(26.26%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>Water flow pattern <lb/>20(10.10%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>38(19.19%) <lb/>58(29.29%) <lb/>40(20.21%) <lb/>Access to fishing ground <lb/>30(15.15) <lb/>40(20.20%) <lb/>33(16.67%) <lb/>50(25.25%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>Access to market <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>20(10.10%) <lb/>35(17.68%) <lb/>46(23.23%) <lb/>55(27.78%) <lb/>Price of product <lb/>32(16.16%) <lb/>26(13.13%) <lb/>40(20.21%) <lb/>52(26.26%) <lb/>48(24.24%) <lb/>Product availability <lb/>38(19.19%) <lb/>42(21.21%) <lb/>28(14.14%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/>Income <lb/>30(15.15%) <lb/>31(15.66%) <lb/>43(21.72%) <lb/>50(25.25%) <lb/>44(22.22%) <lb/>skills <lb/>35(17.68%) <lb/>40(20.20%) <lb/>36(13.13%) <lb/>52(26.26%) <lb/>45(22.73%) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the Lower Niger River basin, potentially leading to <lb/>decreased fish populations, limited access to essential <lb/>resources, and reduced fishing activities. The findings <lb/>from the assessment indicate that the extent of loss from <lb/>flooding has contributed to livelihood diversification <lb/>and, in some cases, abandonment. This means that <lb/>affected communities may be forced to explore alterna-<lb/>tive livelihood options or even abandon their traditional <lb/>livelihood activities due to the significant impact of <lb/>flooding. This can further exacerbate issues such as <lb/>scarcity of commodities, price inflation, and increased <lb/>vulnerability among affected households. The result <lb/>highlights the effects of flooding on infrastructure, par-<lb/>ticularly in terms of market accessibility and price fluc-<lb/>tuations. The findings suggest that flooding has <lb/>disrupted access to markets, making it challenging for <lb/>farmers to transport their agricultural commodities. <lb/>This can lead to forced sales at lower prices, reduced <lb/>profit margins, and potential financial hardships for <lb/>farmers. It may also result in the need for borrowing <lb/>capital for future planting seasons. <lb/>Contribution of climate change to the observed <lb/>flooding event <lb/>Climate change plays a pivotal role in exacerbating <lb/>flooding events observed in the Lower Niger River <lb/>region of Nigeria, impacting the region through var-<lb/>ious mechanisms. While it&apos;s crucial to acknowledge <lb/>that individual weather events result from a complex <lb/>interplay of factors, including natural variability, <lb/>human activities, and climate change, the contribution <lb/>of climate change to the observed flooding in the <lb/>Lower Niger River is notably significant, particularly <lb/>concerning continuous deforestation and land use <lb/>changes. <lb/>The observed increase in loss and damage in the <lb/>region can be attributed significantly to climate change, <lb/>although it is essential to acknowledge the interplay of <lb/>anthropogenic factors that exacerbate these impacts. <lb/>Notably, the intensification of physical development, <lb/>extensive farming practices, and land clearance activities <lb/>are focal contributors to the alteration of the hydrologi-<lb/>cal regime within the Niger River basin. <lb/>Climate change indeed has multifaceted impacts on <lb/>river flow regimes, with far-reaching consequences for <lb/>various aspects, including agriculture and ecosystem. <lb/>These impacts primarily stem from the projected <lb/>changes in precipitation patterns, sea level rise, and <lb/>temperature increases, each contributing to altered <lb/>river flows in distinct ways which aligns with the work <lb/>of (Nasr et al., 2023; Yang &amp; Frangopol, 2019) on cli-<lb/>mate change impact on long-term risk. <lb/>The rapid expansion of physical development, <lb/>including urbanization and infrastructure projects, has <lb/>led to alterations in land use and land cover. Changes in <lb/>land use is driven by urbanisation which has led to <lb/>expansion of cities thereby increasing the intensity of <lb/>climate disasters. For example, Nigerian urban popula-<lb/>tion in 1975, was approximately 16.3 million, constitut-<lb/>ing 21% of the total population. Consequently, by 1993, <lb/>this figure had risen to 36.2% (Arimah &amp; Adeagbo, 2000; <lb/>Lwali, 2008). While the overall urbanization rate for the <lb/>entire country is estimated at around 7% (Potts, 2012) <lb/>notable cities such as Lagos, Ibadan, Kano, Onitsha, and <lb/>Aba were already experiencing more rapid expansion. <lb/>The consequences of this transformation have been the <lb/>substitution of natural landscapes with impermeable <lb/>surfaces, such as concrete and asphalt. These alterations <lb/>have disrupted the inherent drainage patterns of the <lb/>region, giving rise to heightened surface runoff when <lb/>confronted with heavy rainfall events. Consequently, <lb/>this disruption has significantly escalated the vulnerabil-<lb/>ity of the area to the risk of flooding. <lb/>Furthermore, alteration of rainfall patterns, the <lb/>intensification of rainfall events, prolonged periods of <lb/>drought and extreme rainfall are facets of climate <lb/>change that have directly contributed to heightened <lb/>flood risks, crop failures, and the erosion of agricultural <lb/>productivity. These climate-driven changes have sub-<lb/>jected local communities to increased vulnerability and <lb/>have catalysed the surge in loss and damage incidents. <lb/>As observed in research findings, these changes have <lb/>contributed to a more prolonged and intense rainy <lb/>season in the Lower Niger River region which in turn, <lb/>exacerbates the risk of flooding, causing substantial <lb/>damage and losses for local farmers. <lb/>Another pivotal factor in the context of the region is <lb/>the pressing issue of deforestation, closely intertwined <lb/>with the heavy reliance on unsustainable energy sources <lb/>for cooking. Field study data sheds light on the alarming <lb/>extent of this dependency, revealing that a staggering <lb/>78.6% of households utilize firewood as their primary <lb/>cooking fuel, with 12.8% relying on charcoal and 8.4% <lb/>on kerosene. This pronounced and widespread reliance <lb/>on firewood has profound consequences, particularly in <lb/>terms of deforestation, which is both environmentally <lb/>unsustainable and a substantial contributor to green-<lb/>house gas emissions. Furthermore, it exacts a toll on <lb/>human health, with adverse effects. <lb/>Response mechanism of farming households in <lb/>the lower Niger region <lb/>The field data shows that farmers in the Lower Niger <lb/>region are experiencing extreme losses of agricultural <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>produce and income due to climate-related disasters. In <lb/>addition, factor such as the power relations, margin-<lb/>alization and insecurity have increased their vulnerabil-<lb/>ity. For example, loss of income due to flooding has <lb/>resulted in a livelihood shock that has affected their <lb/>living standards. This recognises the urgency need for <lb/>transformative action to address the impacts of climate <lb/>change and to provide financial and technical support to <lb/>vulnerable communities to cope with loss and damage. <lb/>By emphasizing the experiences of farmers in the Lower <lb/>Niger region who are facing extreme losses of agricul-<lb/>tural produce and income due to climate-related disas-<lb/>ters, the information underscores the urgent need for <lb/>transformative action and support for vulnerable com-<lb/>munities to cope with loss and damage. It also highlights <lb/>the importance of local stakeholders taking proactive <lb/>measures that fit their specific contexts. <lb/>Considering the challenges faced by farmers in the <lb/>region, we assessed the response mechanisms employed <lb/>by farmers to mitigate vulnerability. The results, as illu-<lb/>strated in Figures 8 and 9, unveiled a range of strategies <lb/>adopted by farmers before and after to proactively <lb/>address hazards. These strategies encompassed various <lb/>approaches, including casual manual labour, borrowing <lb/>resources from friends and neighbours, early planting <lb/>and harvesting practices, and diversifying crop varieties. <lb/>It is noteworthy that while a substantial portion of <lb/>farming households embraced these proactive mea-<lb/>sures, some were constrained by limited financial <lb/>resources and a lack of capacity to access and process <lb/>information, which hindered their ability to adopt pre-<lb/>emptive strategies to prepare for potential hazards. <lb/>Additionally, many farming households reported bor-<lb/>rowing resources from friends and neighbours to expand <lb/>their farming activities and mitigate the risks associated <lb/>with climate hazards. This included endeavours such as <lb/>planting trees, commencing planting early in anticipation <lb/>of rainfall, crafting irrigation channels in readiness for <lb/>rains, and cultivating flood-resistant crop varieties. <lb/>Of particular significance were the observations from <lb/>wetland farmers, who noted that the recurrent rise in sea <lb/>levels posed a considerable threat to their agricultural <lb/>endeavours. In response, they took the initiative to <lb/>construct local embankments, aimed at minimizing <lb/>water ingress into their farms during episodes of sea <lb/>level rise. <lb/>Another notable strategy implemented by farmers <lb/>was the practice of planting and harvesting crops <lb/>ahead of the typical onset of rainfall or in anticipation <lb/>of extreme rainfall events. Those farming households <lb/>that adopted this approach reported comparatively <lb/>minimal losses when compared to farmers who did <lb/>not engage in such preparatory actions. <lb/>These findings resonate with the work of (SeinnSeinn <lb/>et al., 2015) which suggests that farmers exposed to cli-<lb/>mate-related risks tend to opt for crop varieties that <lb/>exhibit resilience to flooding and other adverse condi-<lb/>tions. The adoption of such adaptive measures under-<lb/>scores the importance of proactive strategies in <lb/>enhancing the resilience of farming communities facing <lb/>climate-related challenges. <lb/>Likewise, our assessment encompassed an exploration <lb/>of the post-hazard strategies employed by farmers in <lb/>response to the challenges posed by climate-related <lb/>events. The findings, shown in Figure 9, shed light on <lb/>the multifaceted dynamics of these post-hazard strategies. <lb/>One of the predominant themes that emerged was <lb/>the significant role played by financial constraints in <lb/>limiting farmers&apos; capacity to adopt post-hazard strate-<lb/>gies effectively. Many farmers expressed their inability <lb/>to implement such strategies due to a lack of financial <lb/>resources. However, they exhibited resilience by resort-<lb/>ing to alternative coping mechanisms, relying on remit-<lb/>tances from family members, friends, and relatives to <lb/>navigate the aftermath of climate shocks. <lb/>As one respondent eloquently put it, &apos;I have lost <lb/>farmland and crops to flood. Now I&apos;m struggling to feed <lb/>because I do not have money. If not for my son who sent <lb/>me money, I would literally be begging people to feed my <lb/>family&apos;. This poignant testimony highlights the pivotal <lb/>role of remittances in providing a lifeline for vulnerable <lb/>farming households during times of crisis. <lb/>Furthermore, impoverished farming households, con-<lb/>fronted with financial constraints, often sent at least one <lb/>family member to seek employment as house help in <lb/>larger cities. The expectation was that remittances from <lb/>the family member working in urban areas would bolster <lb/>the household&apos;s ability to augment their consumption <lb/>needs in the face of climate shocks. This practice under-<lb/>scored the essential role of remittances in supporting <lb/>rural families&apos; resilience. <lb/>Additionally, farmers implemented various strategies to <lb/>adjust their household expenditures and adapt to reduced <lb/>income levels after climate disasters. These adjustments <lb/>included reducing the frequency of meals from three <lb/>square meals to two daily squares, adopting a more frugal <lb/>approach to spending by prioritizing essential family <lb/>needs, and avoiding unnecessary expenses. Moreover, <lb/>some farmers expanded their labour supply as <lb/>a substitute for lost income, particularly those with surplus <lb/>labour resources at their disposal. <lb/>These observations align with the findings of <lb/>(Giupponi et al., 2022), which emphasize the utilization <lb/>of labour market responses as a means to substitute <lb/>income and minimize vulnerability to risks in the <lb/>wake of climate-related hazards. In essence, the farmers&apos; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>ability to adapt and employ these post-hazard strategies <lb/>reflects their resilience and resourcefulness in the face of <lb/>adversity, demonstrating the critical importance of <lb/>diversified coping mechanisms in building resilience to <lb/>climate shocks. <lb/>Limitation of the study <lb/>The study presented valuable insights and findings, yet, <lb/>like any research endeavour, it is important to recognize <lb/>and acknowledge its limitations. Although these limita-<lb/>tions were not explicitly detailed, it is essential to <lb/>Nothing <lb/>22% <lb/>Increase Farm <lb/>Labour <lb/>24% <lb/>Reduce daily <lb/>eaƟng (2 meals <lb/>daily) <lb/>29% <lb/>Rely on <lb/>Remmitance <lb/>14% <lb/>STRATEGY ADOPTEED BEFORE CLIMATE HAZARD <lb/>Money <lb/>11% <lb/>PrioriƟze spending <lb/>Figure 8. Strategy adopted before hazards. <lb/>Nothing <lb/>22% <lb/>Increase Farm <lb/>Labour <lb/>24% <lb/>PrioriƟze spending <lb/>Money <lb/>11% <lb/>Reduce daily eaƟng <lb/>(2 meals daily) <lb/>29% <lb/>Rely on <lb/>Remmitance <lb/>14% <lb/>STRATEGY ADOPTEED AFTER CLIMATE HAZARD <lb/>Figure 9. Strategy adopted after hazards. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>contemplate potential shortcomings that could impact the <lb/>study&apos;s applicability and the interpretation of its outcomes. <lb/>One potential limitation is the data source as the <lb/>research heavily relied on dataset from climate research <lb/>units, questionaries, and interview. These sources might <lb/>have failed to comprehensively represent the full diver-<lb/>sity of experiences and perspectives across the entire <lb/>region. <lb/>Furthermore, the size and diversity of the study&apos;s <lb/>sample might not adequately capture the entire spec-<lb/>trum of viewpoints and encounters linked to climate <lb/>change, flooding, water scarcity, and temperature fluc-<lb/>tuations. In addition, the study may not have accounted <lb/>for external factors or events that could potentially <lb/>influence the perceptions and experiences of the study&apos;s <lb/>participants. These external factors might encompass <lb/>government policies, economic fluctuations, or other <lb/>ongoing developments within the region. <lb/>Recommendations <lb/>Based on the findings of the study, several recommen-<lb/>dations can be made to address loss and damage in the <lb/>region and support vulnerable communities. <lb/>Firstly, the adoption of sustainable land management <lb/>practices holds the potential to significantly mitigate the <lb/>adverse impacts of flooding, if not entirely prevent <lb/>them, thereby minimizing the extent of loss and <lb/>damage. A fundamental approach within this realm <lb/>involves the implementation of techniques such as shift-<lb/>ing cultivation and land fallowing. These strategies can <lb/>play a crucial role in maintaining soil health, enhancing <lb/>water retention capacities, and fostering a more resilient <lb/>ecosystem in the face of flooding events. <lb/>Furthermore, a secondary approach involves advo-<lb/>cating for nature-based solutions as a proactive measure <lb/>to prevent loss and damage. This entails initiatives such <lb/>as tree planting and safeguarding greenbelts to prevent <lb/>the conversion of reserved land into alternative uses. <lb/>These strategies not only enhance the natural environ-<lb/>ment but also act as a protective barrier against the <lb/>potential consequences of land use changes, contribut-<lb/>ing to the reduction of vulnerability and potential losses. <lb/>Resolving the conflicts between farmers and herders <lb/>is paramount in establishing a sustainable environment <lb/>that fosters investment and enables the continuation of <lb/>farming and other business activities. By addressing <lb/>these conflicts, a conducive atmosphere can be culti-<lb/>vated, ensuring that individuals can engage in their <lb/>livelihood pursuits without disruptions or threats to <lb/>their security. This proactive approach not only pro-<lb/>motes economic growth but also contributes to social <lb/>harmony and stability within the community. <lb/>Initiating an intensified awareness campaign serves <lb/>as a pivotal step in educating farmers about the impera-<lb/>tive of taking preventive measures to mitigate loss and <lb/>damage in the event of flooding. By disseminating this <lb/>crucial information, farmers can gain insights into effec-<lb/>tive strategies aimed at minimizing the impact of flood-<lb/>ing on their endeavours. Additionally, providing the <lb/>community with accessible and relevant climate infor-<lb/>mation equips them with valuable insights into potential <lb/>climate-related disasters, enabling proactive prepared-<lb/>ness and response measures to be put in place. This <lb/>comprehensive approach not only empowers indivi-<lb/>duals with knowledge but also fosters a culture of resi-<lb/>lience in the face of climatic challenges. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The research was to explore damage and loss and how they <lb/>influence the global perspective debate on loss and damage. <lb/>The findings obtained from the study have brought to light <lb/>a critical insight that anthropogenic factors play a pivotal <lb/>role in driving significant alterations in the hydrological <lb/>dynamics of the Lower Niger River Region. These altera-<lb/>tions, in turn, give rise to climatic hazards, with flooding <lb/>being a prominent outcome. This flooding, in its wake, <lb/>inflicts substantial and far-reaching consequences, particu-<lb/>larly in the form of severe loss and damage to various <lb/>aspects of livelihoods. Among the most impacted sectors <lb/>are agriculture and fisheries, both of which experience <lb/>significant declines in productivity. Additionally, the acces-<lb/>sibility of the region is compromised, exacerbating the <lb/>challenges faced by the local community. <lb/></body>

            <div type="conflict">Disclosure statement <lb/>No potential conflict of interest was reported by the author(s). <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID <lb/>Cyril Joseph Effiong http://orcid.org/0000-0001-9210-9748 <lb/></front>

			<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>The data that supports the findings of this study are available <lb/>upon request. Due to the sensitive nature of the data collected, <lb/>which includes personal information and community-level <lb/>data from vulnerable populations, restrictions apply to the <lb/>public availability of the dataset. However, researchers who <lb/>wish to access the data for valid research purposes may con-<lb/>tact the corresponding author to request access. <lb/>The primary data consist of qualitative interviews con-<lb/>ducted with farmers and community leaders to gain insights <lb/>into how their coping strategies influence global perspectives <lb/>on loss and damage. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="availability">These data capture valuable insights, experiences, and per-<lb/>spectives of the participants regarding the impacts of climate <lb/>change and the response mechanisms employed in their com-<lb/>munities. For the survey, a total of 198 households were <lb/>selected and surveyed using a structured questionnaire. <lb/>Due to the sensitive nature of the data, which includes <lb/>personal information and potentially identifying details, it <lb/>cannot be made publicly available. However, researchers <lb/>interested in accessing the primary data for legitimate <lb/>research purposes can contact the corresponding author [pro-<lb/>vide contact information] to request access. Any requests will <lb/>be subject to review to ensure compliance with ethical con-<lb/>siderations, privacy protection, and data sharing agreements. <lb/>The secondary data was sourced through an open-source <lb/>terra climate data of precipitation and temperature covering <lb/>a 30-year period (1990 -2020) was sourced Climate <lb/>Research Unit (CRU) dataset and analysed using <lb/>R programming to show trend and pattern. Additionally, we <lb/>obtained relevant information from report, academic studies, <lb/>government publication and other sources within the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>To facilitate transparency and reproducibility, the manu-<lb/>script includes a comprehensive description of the methodol-<lb/>ogies employed for data collection, data cleaning, and data <lb/>analysis. This information enables readers to understand the <lb/>research process and the basis for the presented findings. <lb/>We recognize the importance of data sharing and the poten-<lb/>tial for collaboration and further research in this field. However, <lb/>we also respect the privacy and confidentiality of the research <lb/>participants and the communities involved. Therefore, access to <lb/>the primary data will be granted in a manner that upholds <lb/>ethical standards and protects the rights of the individuals and <lb/>communities who contributed to this study. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Action, P. (2021). Assessing and addressing climate-induced <lb/>loss and damage in Bangladesh. Practical Working Paper, <lb/>1-34. <lb/>Amanambu, A. C., Li, L., Egbinola, C. N., Obarein, O. A., <lb/>Mupenzi, C., &amp; Chen, D. (2019). Spatio-temporal variation <lb/>in rainfall-runoff erosivity due to climate change in the <lb/>Lower Niger Basin, West Africa. Catena, 172, 324-334. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.catena.2018.09.003 <lb/>Arimah, B. C., &amp; Adeagbo, D. (2000). Compliance with urban <lb/>development and planning regulations in Ibadan, Nigeria. <lb/>Habitat International, 24(3), 279-294. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/S0197-3975(99)00043-0 <lb/>Boyd, E., Chaffin, B. C., Dorkenoo, K., Jackson, G., <lb/>Harrington, L., N&apos;guetta, A., Johansson, E. L., <lb/>Nordlander, L., De Rosa, S. P., Raju, E., Scown, M., Soo, J., <lb/>&amp; Stuart-Smith, R. (2021). Loss and damage from climate <lb/>change: A new climate justice agenda. One Earth, 4(10), <lb/>1365-1370. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.oneear.2021.09.015 <lb/>Boyd, E., James, R. A., Jones, R. G., Young, H. R., &amp; Otto, F. E. <lb/>(2017). A typology of loss and damage perspectives. Nature <lb/>Climate Change, 7(10), 723-729. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nclimate3389 <lb/>Breiman, L. (2001). Random forests. Machine Learning, 45(1), <lb/>5-32. https://doi.org/10.1023/A:1010933404324 <lb/>Calliari, E. (2018). Loss and damage: A critical discourse <lb/>analysis of parties&apos; positions in climate change negotiations. <lb/>Journal of Risk Research, 21(6), 725-747. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1080/13669877.2016.1240706 <lb/>Chander, G., Markham, B. L., &amp; Helder, D. L. (2009). <lb/>Summary of current radiometric calibration coefficients <lb/>for landsat MSS, TM, ETM+, and EO-1 ALI sensors. <lb/>Remote Sensing of Environment, 113(5), 893-903. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.rse.2009.01.007 <lb/>Change, U. N. F. C. O. C. (2012). A literature review on the <lb/>Topics in the context of thematic area 2 of the Work <lb/>Programme on loss and damage: A range of approaches to <lb/>address loss and damage associated with the adverse effects <lb/>of climate change: Note. UN. <lb/>Efon, E., Ngongang, R. D., Meukaleuni, C., Wandjie, B. B., <lb/>Zebaze, S., Lenouo, A., &amp; Valipour, M. (2023). Monthly, <lb/>seasonal, and annual variations of precipitation and runoff <lb/>over west and Central Africa using remote sensing and <lb/>climate reanalysis. Earth Systems and Environment, 7(1), <lb/>67-82. https://doi.org/10.1007/s41748-022-00326-w <lb/>Giupponi, G., Landais, C., &amp; Lapeyre, A. (2022). Should we <lb/>insure workers or jobs during recessions? Journal of <lb/>Economic Perspectives, 36(2), 29-54. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1257/jep.36.2.29 <lb/>Homberg, M. V. D., &amp; McQuistan, C. (2019). Technology for <lb/>climate justice: A reporting framework for loss and damage <lb/>as part of key global agreements. Loss and Damage from <lb/>Climate Change: Concepts, Methods and Policy Options, <lb/>513-545. https://doi.org/10.1007/978-3-319-72026-5_22 <lb/>James, R., Otto, F., Parker, H., Boyd, E., Cornforth, R., <lb/>Mitchell, D., &amp; Allen, M. (2014). Characterizing loss and <lb/>damage from climate change. Nature Climate Change, 4 <lb/>(11), 938-939. https://doi.org/10.1038/nclimate2411 <lb/>Jin, Y., Liu, X., Chen, Y., &amp; Liang, X. (2018). Land-cover <lb/>mapping using random forest classification and incorporat-<lb/>ing NDVI time-series and texture: A case study of central <lb/>Shandong. International Journal of Remote Sensing, 39(23), <lb/>8703-8723. https://doi.org/10.1080/01431161.2018.1490976 <lb/>Kasperson, J. X., Kasperson, R. E., Turner, B., Hsieh, W., &amp; <lb/>Schiller, A. (2022). Vulnerability to global environmental <lb/>change. In R. E. Kasperson, &amp; J. Kasperson (Eds.), The <lb/>social contours of risk (pp. 245-285). Routledge. <lb/>Katirtzidou, M., Skoulikaris, C., Makris, C., Baltikas, V., <lb/>Latinopoulos, D., &amp; Krestenitis, Y. (2023). Modeling stake-<lb/>holders&apos; perceptions in participatory multi-risk assessment <lb/>on a deltaic environment under climate change conditions. <lb/>Environmental Modeling &amp; Assessment, 28(3), 367-388. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10666-023-09890-5 <lb/>Khan, M. R., &amp; Roberts, J. T. (2013). Adaptation and interna-<lb/>tional climate policy. Wiley Interdisciplinary Reviews: <lb/>Climate Change, 4(3), 171-189. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>wcc.212 <lb/>Klein, R. J., Midgley, G., Preston, B. L., Alam, M., Berkhout, F., <lb/>Dow, K., &amp; Shaw, M. R. (2015). Adaptation opportunities, <lb/>constraints, and limits. In climate change 2014: Impacts, <lb/>adaptation, and vulnerability. Part A: Global and sectoral <lb/>aspects. Contribution of working group II to the fifth <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. J. EFFIONG ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>assessment report of the intergovernmental panel on climate <lb/>change (pp. 899). Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Kuruppu, N., &amp; Willie, R. (2015). Barriers to reducing climate <lb/>enhanced disaster risks in Least Developed Country-Small <lb/>Islands through anticipatory adaptation. Weather and <lb/>Climate Extremes, 7, 72-83. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.wace. <lb/>2014.06.001 <lb/>Lélé, M. I., Leslie, L. M., &amp; Lamb, P. J. (2015). Analysis of <lb/>low-level atmospheric moisture transport associated with <lb/>the West African monsoon. Journal of Climate, 28(11), <lb/>4414-4430. https://doi.org/10.1175/JCLI-D-14-00746.1 <lb/>Linnerooth-Bayer, J., Mechler, R., &amp; Hochrainer, S. (2011). <lb/>Insurance against losses from natural disasters in develop-<lb/>ing countries. Evidence, gaps and the way forward. Journal <lb/>of Integrated Disaster Risk Management, 1(1), 59-81. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.5595/idrim.2011.0013 <lb/>Lwali, E. K. (2008). Challenges of international housing <lb/>finance institutions: The case of shelter afrique. University <lb/>of Nairobi Research Archive. <lb/>Nand, M. M., Bardsley, D. K., &amp; Suh, J. (2023). Addressing <lb/>unavoidable climate change loss and damage: A case study <lb/>from Fiji&apos;s sugar industry. Climatic Change, 176(3), 21. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10584-023-03482-8 <lb/>Nasr, A., Björnsson, I., &amp; Johansson, J. (2023). National-level <lb/>analysis of the impact of climate change on local scour <lb/>under bridge piers in Sweden. Journal of Infrastructure <lb/>Systems, 29(2), 05023001. https://doi.org/10.1061/JITSE4. <lb/>ISENG-2177 <lb/>Neufeldt, H., Christiansen, L., &amp; Dale, T. W. (2021). <lb/>Adaptation gap report 2021-the gathering storm: Adapting <lb/>to climate change in a post-pandemic world. UNEP DTU <lb/>Partnership. <lb/>Nkiruka, E. M., Chinedu, A. D., &amp; Smart, U. N. (2023). <lb/>Landuse, landcover change dynamics and flooding in the <lb/>lower Niger basin Onitsha, South Eastern Nigeria. Land <lb/>Use Policy, 131, 106748. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.landuse <lb/>pol.2023.106748 <lb/>Olaniyi, O. A., Ojekunle, Z., &amp; Amujo, B. T. (2013). Review of <lb/>climate change and its effect on Nigeria ecosystem. <lb/>International Journal of African and Asian Studies-An <lb/>Open Access International Journal, 1(1), 55-65. <lb/>Pörtner, H. N. A. I. N.-O., Roberts, D. C., Adams, H., <lb/>Adler, C., Aldunce, P., Ali, E., Begum, R. A., Betts, R., <lb/>Kerr, R. B., &amp; Biesbroek, R. (2022). Climate change 2022: <lb/>Impacts, adaptation and vulnerability. <lb/>Potts, D. (2012). Challenging the myths of urban dynamics in <lb/>sub-saharan Africa: The evidence from Nigeria. World <lb/>Development, 40(7), 1382-1393. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>worlddev.2011.12.004 <lb/>Roberts, E., &amp; Huq, S. (2015). Coming full circle: The history <lb/>of loss and damage under the UNFCCC. International <lb/>Journal of Global Warming, 8(2), 141-157. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1504/IJGW.2015.071964 <lb/>SeinnSeinn, M., Ahmad, M., Thapa, G., &amp; Shrestha, R. (2015). <lb/>Farmers&apos; adaptation to rainfall variability and salinity <lb/>through agronomic practices in lower Ayeyarwady Delta, <lb/>Myanmar. Journal of Earth Science &amp; Climatic Change, 6 <lb/>(2), 1. https://doi.org/10.4172/2157-7617.1000258 <lb/>Shackleton, S., Ziervogel, G., Sallu, S., Gill, T., &amp; Tschakert, P. <lb/>(2015). Why is socially-just climate change adaptation in <lb/>sub-Saharan Africa so challenging? A review of barriers <lb/>identified from empirical cases. Wiley Interdisciplinary <lb/>Reviews: Climate Change, 6(3), 321-344. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/wcc.335 <lb/>Smith, K. (2013). Environmental hazards: Assessing risk and <lb/>reducing disaster. Routledge. <lb/>Taylor, M., McGregor, A., &amp; Dawson, B. (2016). Vulnerability <lb/>of Pacific agriculture and forestry to climate change. <lb/>Secretariat of the Pacific Community. <lb/>Tolika, K., &amp; Skoulikaris, C. (2023). Atmospheric circulation <lb/>types and floods&apos; occurrence; a thorough analysis over <lb/>Greece. Science of the Total Environment, 865, 161217. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2022.161217 <lb/>Tol, R. S., &amp; Verheyen, R. (2004). State responsibility and <lb/>compensation for climate change damages-a legal and <lb/>economic assessment. Energy Policy, 32(9), 1109-1130. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S0301-4215(03)00075-2 <lb/>van der Geest, K., &amp; Warner, K. (2015). Loss and damage from <lb/>climate change: Emerging perspectives. International <lb/>Journal of Global Warming, 8(2), 133-140. <lb/>Vasquez, T. (2009). The intertropical convergence zone. <lb/>Weatherwise: THE POWER, the BEAUTY, the <lb/>EXCITEMENT, 62(6), 24-30. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>00431670903337573 <lb/>Verheyen, R., &amp; Roderick, P. (2008). Beyond Adaptation: The <lb/>legal duty to pay compensation for climate change damage. <lb/>WWF-UK Climate Change Programme discussion paper, <lb/>25-32. <lb/>Warner, K., &amp; Van der Geest, K. (2013). Loss and damage from <lb/>climate change: Local-level evidence from nine vulnerable <lb/>countries. International Journal of Global Warming, 5(4), <lb/>367-386. https://doi.org/10.1504/IJGW.2013.057289 <lb/>Yang, D. Y., &amp; Frangopol, D. M. (2019). Physics-based assess-<lb/>ment of climate change impact on long-term regional <lb/>bridge scour risk using hydrologic modeling: Application <lb/>to Lehigh River watershed. Journal of Bridge Engineering, <lb/>24(11), 04019099. https://doi.org/10.1061/(ASCE)BE.1943-<lb/>5592.0001462 <lb/>Zhang, Z., He, G., &amp; Wang, X. (2010). A practical DOS <lb/>model-based <lb/>atmospheric <lb/>correction <lb/>algorithm. <lb/>International Journal of Remote Sensing, 31(11), <lb/>2837-2852. https://doi.org/10.1080/01431160903124682 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">SUSTAINABLE ENVIRONMENT <lb/></note>

			<page>19 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
