<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Title <lb/>A thermo-responsive plasmid for biconditional protein expression <lb/>Authors <lb/>Agathe Lermant (1), Alicia Magnanon (1), Alexandra Silvain (1), Paul Lubrano (1), Marie Lhuissier (1), <lb/>Camille Dury (1), Maryne Follenfant (1), Zoe Guiot (1), Gaëtan Christien (1), Pauline Coudert (1), <lb/>Antoine Arvor (1), Maxime Sportich (1), Gabrielle Vuillaume (1), Nicolas Delettre (1), Julie Henry (1), <lb/>Eliott Lafon (1), Thomas Lhernould (1), Fanny Richard (1), Alexandre Ismail (1) <lb/>1. Sup&apos;Biotech, School of Engineering in Biotechnologies, Paris <lb/>This work was assessed during the iGEM/PLOS Realtime Peer Review Jamboree on February 23 rd <lb/>2018 and has been revised in response to the reviewers&apos; comments. A transcript of these comments <lb/>is available with the original article as a supplementary file. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Here we develop a temperature sensitive expression vector that allows the selective production of <lb/>distinct proteins over different temperature ranges with a single plasmid. We use the E. coli cold <lb/>shock translational control system (the cspA 5&apos;Untranslated Transcribed Region -UTR) to drive the <lb/>expression of a desired protein below a certain temperature threshold, and the lambda phage <lb/>pL/cI857 transcriptional repressor system to drive the expression of a different protein above a <lb/>certain temperature threshold. In this developmental work we use the chromogenic reporter <lb/>proteins amilCP (blue chromoprotein) and monomeric red fluorescent protein (mRFP) to assess the <lb/>function of the thermo-sensitive regulatory sequences over the desired temperature ranges. Our <lb/>results show temperature dependent response of the cold shock regulatory sequence. However, our <lb/>sequence design for the heat shock regulatory sequence did not give the intended result. The <lb/>integration of these two temperature sensitive elements into a single plasmid awaits the re-design <lb/>of the heat shock sequence. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>-Motivation <lb/>Climate change is increasing the severity and frequency of high and low temperature extremes. [REF <lb/>0]. Departures from normal temperature ranges in agricultural regions has been responsible for <lb/>major agricultural yield losses around the world [REF 1]. <lb/>Therefore, the development of a low-cost thermal crop protection system is of great value to <lb/>maintaining agricultural output in the current context of climate change. Here we describe the <lb/>development of a thermo-responsive expression vector that allows the selective production of <lb/>different protective compounds over different temperature ranges with a single plasmid. This work <lb/>also demonstrates the value of molecular modeling in the rational design of genetic control <lb/>sequences. Molecular modeling was used extensively in the development of the cold shock <lb/>component and is likely to benefit the improvement of the heat shock component. <lb/>Departures from normal temperature ranges in agricultural regions can subject crops to conditions <lb/>outside of their growth or even survival ranges. Outside of the semi-controlled conditions of <lb/>agriculture, many organisms live in environments where temperatures can exceed the freezing and <lb/>boiling points of water, which is essential to life. Many of these organisms, such as micro-organisms, <lb/>insects, and plants, have little or no ability to move in response to temperature extremes. They have <lb/>consequently evolved molecular mechanisms for sensing temperature extremes and coupled them <lb/>to genetic responses to adapt cellular processes to these physical challenges. These are known as <lb/>the cold shock and heat shock responses, whose biological bases have been well described in the <lb/>literature. [REF 5] [REF 18] In this project we use temperature sensitive genetic sequences from <lb/>known cold shock and heat shock systems to induce protein expression only above or only below <lb/>certain temperatures thresholds. <lb/>-Cold responsive system <lb/>The survival and growth of E. coli can be significantly impaired when subjected to cold (near <lb/>freezing) shocks or sustained cold temperatures. Membranes lose fluidity, global enzyme activity <lb/>decreases, and mRNAs tend to form secondary structures which impair ribosomal translation [REF <lb/>3]. To counter the effects of cold temperatures, cells express cold shock proteins (CSP). <lb/>CSPs help translation to proceed at low temperatures [REF 4]. They are a large family of nucleic acid <lb/>chaperone proteins whose expression is significantly up-regulated in response to cold stress [REF 2]. <lb/>The E. coli Cold Shock Protein A (CspA) and its upstream regulatory sequences is one of the most <lb/>well studied examples [REF 5] and forms the basis of our cold-responsive expression control <lb/>sequence. <lb/>Cold induced protein expression by the CspA promoter has both a transcriptional and translational <lb/>basis, although some details are still unclear. CspA transcription has been shown to increase up to <lb/>three-fold relative to its level at 37°C [REF 6]. CspA promoter activity is additionally enhanced by an <lb/>upstream sequence motif called the UP element [REF 7] [REF 8]. CspA expression is also controlled <lb/>at the translational level through at least two molecular mechanisms. At temperatures near 37°C <lb/>CspA messenger RNA (mRNA) is actively degraded by an RNAse and has a half-life of 12 seconds, <lb/>making it essentially unavailable for ribosomal translation [REF 6]. At temperatures near 15°C and <lb/>lower the RNAse is inactive and CspA accounts for nearly 10% of cellular protein production [REF 10] <lb/>[REF 11] [REF 12]. The CspA mRNA is likely stabilized through the formation of specific secondary <lb/>structure motifs that are stable only at low temperatures. In this work we focus on the translational <lb/>control system to apply it to other proteins of interest. <lb/>The translational control system comes from the CspA 5&apos;UTR, an unusually long and conserved <lb/>sequence common to all cold shock proteins [REF 3]. This region contains several sequence motifs <lb/>important for low temperature protein expression, including the Cold Box [REF 7], the &quot;UP element&quot; <lb/>(upstream sequence of the CspA promoter), and the DownStream Box (DS Box). The DS box is an <lb/>unusual sequence motif in that it extends past the start codon and into the coding region of the <lb/>expressed protein [REF 7], requiring careful placement of the DS Box sequence in the reporter or <lb/>effector gene of interest. <lb/>Molecular modeling was used to rationally design the placement of the DS Box in the reading frame <lb/>of our low temperature chromogenic reporter protein amilCP. Further molecular modeling in this <lb/>work strongly suggests that the DS Box contributes to the formation of a specific 5&apos;UTR mRNA <lb/>secondary structure which is recognized by ribosomal protein S1 in the formation of the ribosomal <lb/>pre-initiation complex [REF 13] [REF 14] [REF 15]. <lb/>The UP element, CspA promoter, 5&apos;UTR, and DS Box work synergistically to promote conditional low-<lb/>temperature expression [Figure 1: Wild type CspA genetic structure]. Therefore, our design retains <lb/>all of these regulatory sequence features as a control system for expressing the gene of interest. <lb/>[Figure 2: Proposed genetic construction for cold-specific gene expression]. <lb/>Figure 1 : Wild type CspA genetic structure <lb/>Figure 2 : Proposed genetic construction for cold-specific gene expression <lb/>-Heat responsive system <lb/>The lambda phage of E.coli contains a well-studied transcriptional control system for heat induced <lb/>conditional protein expression: the pL (or pR promoter) and its λcI repressor [REF 9]. Originally, <lb/>these components serve as the genetic switch between the lysogenic and lytic phases of the phage <lb/>life cycle. The creation of the cI857 repressor mutant of λcI made it thermo-labile above 37°C [REF <lb/>17], meaning repression becomes inactive above a certain temperature. This system is widely used <lb/>for industrial production of recombinant proteins in E. coli under up-shift in temperature [REF 16]. <lb/>
			Figure 3: Representation of the pL/pR promoters controlled by the cI857 repressor [REF 18] <lb/>Our strategy to induce the expression of any gene of interest at high temperature only will therefore <lb/>be to create a recombinant plasmid containing the sequence coding for our reporter gene inserted <lb/>downstream the pL promoter in presence of the cI857 repressor (Figure 4). <lb/>Figure 4: Proposed genetic construction for heat-specific gene expression <lb/>Ultimately, we intend to combine both the cold and heat responsive systems into a single construct <lb/>for a biconditional thermo-responsive plasmid for expression of plant-protecting compounds upon <lb/>departure from temperatures compatible with a given crop. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>-Chassis <lb/>E.coli was used as a chassis for plasmid construction because its genome is well studied and has <lb/>several strains useful for molecular and cellular biology studies. The DH5α and BL21 strains were <lb/>supplied by NEB (New England Biolabs) through the partnership with the iGEM Foundation. The <lb/>DH5α strain was used for plasmid construction and cloning procedures because of its high <lb/>transformation efficiency. The BL21 strain was used for expression assays because of its high level of <lb/>protein expression. All our constructs were codon optimized for E.coli DH5α and verified through <lb/>sequencing. <lb/>-BioBrick naming <lb/>The genes and genetic constructions used for the iGEM are commonly called &quot;BioBricks&quot;. A BioBrick <lb/>is any sequence of DNA (promoter, Ribosome binding site, protein sequence, terminator…) that is <lb/>flanked by a prefix (EcoRI and XbaI restriction sites) and a suffix (SpeI and PstI restriction sites). Every <lb/>BioBrick shares the same prefix and suffix, allowing for efficient assembly. <lb/>The common naming of BioBricks in the iGEM registry is &quot;BBa_x&quot; where x is any identifier for the <lb/>part in the registry. This naming strategy was used in this paper to refer directly to the part <lb/>submitted to the registry by our team. <lb/>The registry is accessible here : http://parts.igem.org/Main_Page <lb/>-Plasmid backbones <lb/>Designed sequences were constructed with the pSB1C3 and pSB1A3 plasmid backbones. Final <lb/>constructions were delivered on the pSB1C3 per iGEM Parts Registry standards. Plasmid pSB1A3 <lb/>was used for the propagation of BBa_K2282011 (cold-response construct) which permits conditional <lb/>low temperature expression of amilCP. The pSB1A3 backbone includes the ampicillin resistance gene <lb/>and pSB1C3 includes chloramphenicol resistance and a high copy replication origin, which allows a <lb/>high copy number per cell, facilitating DNA purification. <lb/>-Primer design <lb/>Primers were designed using the BioBrick suffix and prefix from the pSB1C3 backbone. Using <lb/>Geneious 10.07 [REF 19], we extracted the sequences containing the EcoRI and PstI restriction sites <lb/>in a reverse form from the BioBricks. The sequences had a size between 20 and 30bp with a Melting <lb/>temperature (Tm) around 50°C and 60°C and a Guanine/Cytosine (GC) ratio of 50%. The sequences <lb/>were then converted into primers. A &quot;TATATA&quot; sequence was added at the beginning of the forward <lb/>primer and at the end of the reverse primer for DNA polymerase binding. All of our sequences were <lb/>designed using Geneious by adding single BioBricks of DNA to form the intended DNA construct. <lb/>Each sequence is formed by a BioBrick prefix and suffix flanking the sequences to which the primer <lb/>binds. Each element was then introduced (Promoter -Ribosome Binding Site (RBS) -Gene of <lb/>interest-terminator). Geneious was used to detect the restriction sites, design our primers, choose <lb/>the best Tm for polymerase chain reaction (PCR), and visualize our system while adhering to the <lb/>pSB1C3 backbone assembly standard. <lb/>-Molecular modeling software <lb/>Molecular modeling was used to rationally design the placement of the downstream box (DS box) <lb/>inside the amilCP coding sequence for the cold shock system sequences (BBa_K2282011) and <lb/>(BBa_K2282006). Molecular modeling was also used to explore the structural basis of cspA 5&apos; <lb/>Untranslated transcribed region (UTR) function. Phyre2 [REF 20] was used to generate a 3D model of <lb/>wild type amilCP and the DS box designed mutation. Phyre2 was also used to generate a 3D model of <lb/>domain 3 of wild type ribosomal protein S1. SimRNA [REF 21] was used to generate 3D models of a <lb/>187 base-pair stretch of the cspA 5&apos;UTR mRNA, including the downstream box present in the coding <lb/>region. GROMACS [REF 22] was used to generate all atom XTC format trajectory files of SimRNA <lb/>trajectories for visualization and analysis in VMD [REF 23]. ConSurf [REF 24] was used to identify the <lb/>likely mRNA binding site of ribosomal protein S1 domain 3. Autodock Vina [REF 25] was used to <lb/>perform a global blind docking of small model peptides from the DS box sequence onto the 3D <lb/>model of ribosomal protein S1 domain 3. PatchDock [REF 26] was used to perform rigid body <lb/>docking of the mRNA structure (from SimRNA) with the homology model of ribosomal protein S1-<lb/>domain 3 (from Phyre2). PyMol [REF 27] and DiscoveryStudio [REF 28] were used to visualize <lb/>selected results and prepare images. <lb/>-Design of sequences <lb/>Sequences were ordered and constructed by Integrated DNA Technologies (IDT) from the <lb/>partnership with the iGEM Foundation of Boston. We imported the sequences from Geneious to IDT. <lb/>IDT has to test the complexity of the sequences before synthesizing it. The sequence BBa_K2282013 <lb/>had to be modified from its first draft due to its repetitive sequence content (arising from two <lb/>double terminators). We integrated the last part of the sequence in a reverse form and we added a <lb/>different terminator from the first part of the sequence to avoid concatemers. All the designed parts <lb/>and their current status regarding the iGEM Parts Registry are summarized in Table 1. <lb/>Part reference Part components <lb/>BBa_K2282005 Anderson constitutive promoter (BBa_J23100) -amilCP <lb/>BBa_K2282006 Anderson constitutive promoter (BBa_J23100) -amilCP+DSbox <lb/>BBa_K2282011 UP element -CspA promoter -5&apos;UTR -amilCP+DSbox <lb/>BBa_K2282012 pL promoter -mRFP (BBa_E1010) <lb/>BBa_K2282013 <lb/>Anderson constitutive promoter (BBa_J23100) -cL857 repressor (BBa_K098997) <lb/>-pL promoter -mRFP (BBa_E1010) <lb/>Table 1. ID and description of the used designed parts <lb/>-Cloning strategy <lb/>All sequences were digested with EcoRI-HF and PstI from NEB with a final concentration of 40U/µL <lb/>and the digestion mix was incubated for two hours at 37°C. We used the same protocol for the <lb/>pSB1C3 backbone. Each digested sequence was ligated with digested pSB1C3 using T4 DNA ligase <lb/>from NEB with a final concentration of 40U/µL. Competent E.coli DH5α were transformed with the <lb/>ligation product into Super Optimal Broth (SOC) medium, using the classic heat-shock technique, and <lb/>then spread on solid Lysogeny Broth (LB) medium with chloramphenicol and incubated at 37°C for <lb/>24 hours. Constructs were checked by colony PCR. Colony PCR is a protocol permitting the extraction <lb/>of the total DNA of any transformed bacteria and the amplification of its plasmid DNA with primers <lb/>to visualize if the bacteria have included the right plasmid DNA. <lb/>-Part characterization: colorimetric measurements over time <lb/>• Visual color test <lb/>Cold and heat response were tested through colorimetry. The test was run over three days. Because <lb/>their growth rate is slower in cold temperatures, bacteria were first pre-incubated at 37°C until <lb/>reaching an OD600 of 0.5, corresponding to the exponential phase. Cultures were then split in half <lb/>and held at temperatures according to the genetic construction to be tested : <lb/>-For the Cold-Response system, one half at 12°C/15°C/20°C/27°C and the other at 37°C <lb/>-For the Heat-response system, one half at 27°C and the other at 37°C <lb/>For each condition, a sample of 1 mL was collected after 20h and centrifuged at 13.000 g. This <lb/>duration was sufficient to obtain similar OD600 values around 0.7. Incubation at 37°C was necessary <lb/>to obtain a positive control. Other controls were used as well for the heat and cold-response system <lb/>based on the constitutive expression of amilCP and mRFP (see BBa_K2282005 and BBa_K2282012). <lb/>Incubation temperatures were chosen based on bibliographic studies [REF 3]. <lb/>• Absorbance measurements over time <lb/>After being transformed, bacteria were grown at 37°C for 60 hours and Optical Density (OD) <lb/>at 588 nm was measured every 10 min approximately with a Spark 10M Tecan. OD 800 was taken as <lb/>a bacterial growth indicator, as the commonly used OD600 was too close to our wavelength of <lb/>interest and could therefore interact in the results. <lb/>• Blue profile plots <lb/>Blue intensity profile plots of bacteria pellets were obtained using the ImageJ software. <lb/>Rectangular areas were defined within each pellet obtained on the picture, the RGB intensity values <lb/>were extracted from each pixel of the area selected and integrated into a profile plot. Red and Green <lb/>intensities were discarded. <lb/>Results <lb/>Modeling results <lb/>amilCP homology modeling <lb/>The cold-sensitive regulatory sequence of this construct is the E. coli cspA 5&apos; untranslated region <lb/>(5&apos;UTR). The majority of this sequence is upstream of the start codon. However, the Downstream <lb/>(DS) box motif is present after the start codon and is translated as part of the target protein. <lb/>Therefore, we studied the N-terminal region of amilCP (a blue chromogenic reporter protein) with <lb/>molecular modeling in order to determine a DS box sequence placement that would preserve the <lb/>structure and function of the protein. <lb/>While the structure of amilCP has not been experimentally solved, several other members of the <lb/>family (coral chromoproteins which are GFP-like) have been crystallized and their coordinates <lb/>deposited in the Protein Data Bank (PDB). Therefore, we decided to use homology modeling to <lb/>create model of amilCP to understand the structure of the N-terminal region and the likely impact of <lb/>modifications to this region. <lb/>The Phyre2 homology modeling server [REF 2] was used to find templates, generate alignments and <lb/>create 3D models. Phyre2 was selected because of its hidden Markov Model-based fold library, <lb/>which allows detection of remote sequence homologs down to ~15% sequence identity. In the case <lb/>of amilCP, this search revealed a homologous coral chromoprotein (PDB entry 1MOU) with 93.2% <lb/>sequence identity (as shown in the template-target alignment in Figure 5), permitting the <lb/>construction of a reliable model. <lb/>Figure 5 shows the highly similar structure between the template (PDB structure 1MOU) and the <lb/>Phyre2 homology model with an RMSD of 0.232 angstroms over identical residues. The first six N-<lb/>terminal residues (GGVIAT of 1MOU) does not display backbone angle values describing a regular <lb/>secondary structure element and is predicted to be solvent accessible, implying that it does not form <lb/>essential structures or contacts with the rest of the amilCP structure. <lb/>
			Figure 5: Sequence alignment and 3D structures of 1MOU, Homology Model_WT, Homology <lb/>Model_DSB <lb/>Based on these structures, we decided to insert the DS box sequence MTGIV (AUGACUGGUAUCGUA) <lb/>after the first two residues of the wild type amilCP sequence. <lb/>We then made a homology model of this mutant amilCP sequence with Phyre2 in order to assess the <lb/>likely position and structure of the additional residues relative to the amilCP beta barrel, as shown in <lb/>orange in Figure 5 above. <lb/>Based on these results, we decided to proceed with the synthesis of this mutant sequence IDT and <lb/>plasmid construction. <lb/>cspA 5&apos;UTR structure modeling <lb/>The cspA 5&apos;UTR is known to exhibit the following behaviors which drive conditional expression as a <lb/>function of temperature. At low temperatures it enhances transcription by binding to ribosomal <lb/>subunit 1 through the S1 protein [REF1], whereas at high temperatures it negatively regulates <lb/>expression by favoring RNAse mediated degradation of its transcript [REF2]. <lb/>The cspA 5&apos;UTR has been partially structurally characterized by the use of the Tn5-lac transposon <lb/>insertion [REF3] and gel retardation analysis [REF4]. The general hypothesis is that the cspA 5&apos;UTR <lb/>mRNA assumes a specific secondary structure at low temperatures. However, experimental <lb/>characterization of this conformation thus far has not yet proposed a 3D structure for this mRNA <lb/>sequence, leaving ambiguity concerning structure-function relationships of various other CspA 5&apos;UTR <lb/>sequence motifs such as the Cold box and DS box. <lb/>In order to get a better idea of possible structure-function relationships for rational design we used <lb/>molecular modeling to create structural models of the 3&apos; end of our cold shock construct mRNA (a <lb/>187-nucleotide segment). This includes the DS Box, a key sequence motif of the cspA 5&apos;UTR mRNA. <lb/>SimRNA (an ab initio coarse grained replica exchange Monte Carlo method) was used to generate an <lb/>ensemble of conformations covering a folding trajectory of the given mRNA sequence. <lb/>The ensembles converge to a set of similar structures, revealed through all vs all root-mean-square <lb/>deviation (RMSD) based clustering. The resulting top cluster centroid was selected as a <lb/>representative conformation and retained for further study. <lb/>Figure 6: iGEM 187 mRNA structure computed by SimRNA. The SD sequence is in red; the DS box is <lb/>in yellow; the putative S1 protein binding sequence is in green; the start AUG codon is in blue. <lb/>This portion of the mRNA is predicted to form an extended double helix structure, separated by a <lb/>single stranded segment. The DS box sequence itself often forms a double helix structure, as it is <lb/>present in 27 out of the 39 cluster centroids. This suggests that the DS box sequence may participate <lb/>in a conserved structural motif important for low temperature transcription initiation -and one that <lb/>involves other known conserved sequence motifs. <lb/>Review of the literature suggests that assembly of functional ribosomes at low temperatures <lb/>depends on binding of mRNA to the small subunit in the pre-initiation complex, mediated by <lb/>ribosomal protein S1 [REF 5]. In order to explore this, we pursued rigid body docking with a <lb/>homology model of this protein. <lb/>cspA 5&apos;UTR -S1 protein interaction modeling <lb/>We found from the literature that the Subunit 1 (S1) of the ribosome was necessary for the binding <lb/>of RNA constructs [REF1] and more specifically for the initiation of the RNA-ribosome complex. This <lb/>applies to many mRNAs, especially for those with none or weak Shine-Dalgarno sequences, and <lb/>those with highly structured 5&apos; regions. More specifically, the domain 3 of S1 (S1-D3) was very likely <lb/>to bind first to the 5&apos;UTR of our protein(RNA) construct[REF2]. <lb/>In order to explore the hypothesis of an interaction between the 3&apos; region of the temperature <lb/>sensitive 5&apos;UTR and ribosomal protein S1 domain 3 we decided to pursue docking of structural <lb/>models of each. <lb/>Since there is no crystal structure of S1 domain 3 we searched for a template using the Phyre2[REF3] <lb/>server. The model sequence was re-aligned against the top template using MAFFT-L-INSI [REF4], <lb/>followed by I-TASSER[REF5] to build a final 3D model. On this structure, we observed a specific motif <lb/>with conserved residues (as calculated by ConSurf [REF]) that we will call &quot;valley&quot; from now <lb/>onwards. This valley seemed to be an externally accessible site, being located on the exterior side of <lb/>S1-d3, while having two strands of highly conserved residues bordering it. As such, we considered it <lb/>a likely binding site for our cspA 5&apos;UTR mRNA structure. <lb/>As a reference, we compared it to a sequence found in the Protein Data Bank (PDB). This sequence, <lb/>referred as the code 4v9r [REF6] on the PDB, consisted of S1-d3 bound to single stranded RNA <lb/>(ssRNA) (as seen in Figure 7 panel A). We applied the same steps used for our homology model of <lb/>S1-d3. On this structure, we also observe the same valley motif with highly conserved residues, <lb/>reinforcing our previous hypothesis. <lb/>From the previous models, we decided to study more precisely the conservation of residues to <lb/>determine the best docking site possible and test our valley hypothesis. This was done using the <lb/>ConSurf web server [REF7] for both 4v9r and S1-d3. A globally blind docking by Autodock Vina was <lb/>able to find poses at a site homologous to that seen in the 4v94 crystal structure. <lb/>Figure 7: A) Thermus thermophilus S1-d3 (colored by residue conservation) complexed with ssRNA <lb/>(green) from PDB entry 4v9r (X-ray structure). B) E. coli S1-d3 homology model colored according to <lb/>residue conservation docked with DS Box ssRNA (green). <lb/>These small-scale results were encouraging and so we proceeded to use our homology model of S1-<lb/>d3 in docking with the larger mRNA structure previously computed with SimRNA. We used the <lb/>PatchDock server[REF8], setting the receptor as S1_d3, the ligand as our 5&apos;UTR (SimRNA cluster 1 <lb/>result) and using default settings. <lb/>Figure 8: S1-d3 (cyan) and cspA 5&apos;UTR mRNA (grey) docking results. The SD sequence is in red; the <lb/>DS box is in yellow; the putative S1 protein binding sequence is in green; the start AUG codon is in <lb/>blue. <lb/>The top 20 results contain a set of interesting positions. First, we note that the DS box forms part of <lb/>a double helix secondary structure which appears as a favorable binding site for our homology <lb/>model of S1-d3. We also not that there are several other binding sites in approximately linear <lb/>distribution on an extended mRNA double helix -indeed there appear to be room for 5 or 6 <lb/>simultaneously bound S1 sub-domains, all of which have homology to domain 3. <lb/>Experimental results <lb/>Influence of the DS box on amilCP expression <lb/>1. Impact of the DS box on amilCP color <lb/>We first needed to verify the expression and color properties of amilCP (blue chromoprotein) with <lb/>the addition of the Downstream (DS) Box. Wild-type amilCP under constitutive expression was <lb/>tested as Registry Part BBa_K2282005. DS Box-amilCP under constitutive expression was tested as <lb/>Registry Part BBa_K2282006. The genetic structures of these constructs are presented in the figure <lb/>below. <lb/>Figure 9: Genetic structures of the designed parts coding for the constitutive expression of Wild-type <lb/>(WT) amilCP with/without the DS Box. a. Part BBa_K2282005 coding for WT amilCP; b. Part <lb/>BBa_K2282006 coding for DS Box-amilCP <lb/>We observed the same color for both constructs, as confirmed through the absorbance spectra <lb/>obtained (Figure 10). However, the DS Box version produced a slightly fainter color (Figure 11), <lb/>which may be related to total amilCP expression levels. <lb/>Figure 10: Absorbance spectrum of amilCP with/without the DS Box expressed at 37°C. <lb/>a. WT amilCP from part BBa_K2282005; b. DS Box-amilCP from part BBa_K2282006 <lb/>
			Figure 11: Color of amilCP liquid culture at 37°C and 15°C with/without the DS box <lb/>Pellets of E.coli DH5-α transformed with a. pSB1C3-BBa_K2282005 (WT amilCP) b. pSB1C3-<lb/>BBa_K2282006 (DS Box-amilCP), and cultivated in liquid LB medium supplemented with <lb/>chloramphenicol at 37°C and 15°C for 18 hours <lb/>2. Impact of the DS box on amilCP expression over time <lb/>The impact of the DS box on amilCP expression level was evaluated at two different temperatures <lb/>through the measurement of the OD588nm over time. The expression was first measured at 37°C, as <lb/>it is the E. coli optimal growth temperature, then a lower temperature was chosen in order to assess <lb/>the potential impact of the DS Box on the protein expression in cold conditions. 18°C was selected <lb/>based on the material available. <lb/>The increasing of the signal at OD588nm over time for both transformed bacterial batches shows the <lb/>expression of functional amilCP compared to the non-transformed ones. <lb/>This confirms that the presence of the DS box does not impact the protein absorbance properties. <lb/>The same protein expression pattern is observable at both temperatures, with an overall lower <lb/>expression at 18°C. This result suggests the absence of enhancing properties on protein expression <lb/>at 18°C from the DS box alone. Despite the presence of the protein in both cases, these curves also <lb/>show a slightly better expression without the DS box, the difference being more pronounced at 37°C. <lb/>This result is in accordance with our hypothesis that the presence of the DS box influences the <lb/>amilCP expression level, which may be related to the modification of amilCP mRNA folding. <lb/>Originally, the DS box is suggested to enhance mRNA translation during cold shocks [REF 29]. <lb/>However, those results tend to show that without the whole cold-inducing machinery, the DS box <lb/>does not seem to operate its enhancing action. Further characterization of our complete cold-shock <lb/>plasmid showed its efficiency through a good protein expression at 15°C and not 37°C. This proves <lb/>that a lower expression rate possibly induced by the presence of the DS box is not problematic when <lb/>combined with the CspA promoter and 5&apos;UTR sequence, allowing its activation. <lb/>Figure 12: amilCP expression over time with/without the DS box at 37°C and 18°C <lb/>a. OD588nm given by pSB1C3-BBa_K2282005 (WT amilCP) and pSB1C3-BBa_K2282006 (DS Box-<lb/>amilCP) expression at 37°C; b. OD588nm given by pSB1C3-BBa_K2282005 (WT amilCP) and pSB1C3-<lb/>BBa_K2282006 (DS Box-amilCP) expression at 18°C <lb/>Test of the complete cold-responsive system <lb/>The complete cold-inducible construct was tested as Registry Part BBa_K2282011, whose genetic <lb/>structure is presented in Figure 13. <lb/>Figure 13: Genetic structure of the designed part coding for the conditional expression of amilCP at <lb/>low temperatures (Part BBa_K2282011 in the iGEM part registry) <lb/>The construct was reported to induce a conditional expression under 15°C, and no expression above <lb/>37°C. Most of the previous experiments on cold-shock proteins were carried out only at 15°C and <lb/>37°C and the gene expression pattern between those limits is poorly known. In order to get a better <lb/>insight of it, we evaluated the amilCP level over different temperatures ranging from 37°C to 12°C. <lb/>Bacteria transformed with the cold-responsive construct were pre-incubated at 37°C until the OD at <lb/>600nm reached 0.5. They were then grown at different temperatures (12°C, 15°C, 20°C, 27°C, 37°C). <lb/>Pellets containing an equivalent amount of bacteria were collected for each condition, based on <lb/>similar OD600 measurements and equal culture volumes sampled. Their respective coloration was <lb/>observed and compared as a function of the temperature gradient. Almost absent at 37°C, a blue <lb/>color started to develop slightly at 27°C and appeared gradually higher as the temperature was <lb/>lowered down to 12°C (Figure 14). <lb/>Figure 14: Visual aspect of amilCP expression gradient induced by the complete cold-responsive <lb/>system from 37°C to 12°C. Pellets of DH5α transformed with BBaK2282011, after 20h of incubation <lb/>at respectively 12°C, 15°C, 20°C, 27°C and 37°C (left), pellets of DH5α transformed with <lb/>BBaK2282005 after 20h of incubation at respectively 15°C and 37°C (middle, positive control), and <lb/>pellets of wild type DH5α (right, negative control). <lb/>Since equivalent bacteria amounts were collected here, we can consider that any difference in pellet <lb/>coloration correlates with a differential amilCP expression per bacteria. Visual observations <lb/>confirmed that our part BBa_K2282011 works as expected and allows efficient protein production at <lb/>temperatures below approximately 20°C only, until low temperature as 12°C. Moreover, the cold <lb/>response system blocks greatly but not completely the protein expression at higher temperatures <lb/>above 27°C. <lb/>As we did not have a fluorimeter in our laboratory, amilCP was used as a reporter gene for observing <lb/>the results with the naked eye. However, it was difficult to perform OD measurements without <lb/>extracting proteins. Indeed, amilCP maximum of absorbance of 588 nm is close to 600 nm, the <lb/>wavelength commonly used to measure the bacteria concentration. This proximity was prone to <lb/>alter the actual signal corresponding to the amilCP protein. Measurements of OD588nm on <lb/>extracted proteins would therefore constitute an interesting perspective to precise those results. <lb/>Despite this lack of equipment, we decided to complete these visual observations by a quantification <lb/>of the blue value per pixel in each respective pellet obtained in Figure 14. The results are given in <lb/>Figure 15: <lb/>Figure 15: Blue profile plot of bacteria pellets expressing amilCP under the complete cold-responsive <lb/>system from 37°C to 12°C. <lb/>The blue intensity profile obtained for each pellet obtained was globally in accordance with our <lb/>expectations, displaying a gradual increase as the temperature drops for bacteria transformed with <lb/>the cold-responsive plasmid. At 37°C however, a slightly higher value compared to the negative <lb/>controls suggest a small residual expression of amilCP at high temperatures and therefore the <lb/>absence of a complete switch-off system. A significant gap was observed in amilCP expression <lb/>between 20°C and 15°C, which appears to be the range where the cold-shock response mainly takes <lb/>place. The intensity values obtained for the BBa_K2282005 positive control at 37°C appeared <lb/>inconsistent with the intense coloration observed in the pellet, and where therefore not shown <lb/>here. These results allowed us to precise our visual observations in absence of accurate equipment <lb/>to properly extract and quantify proteins, however this method is prone to uncertainties when using <lb/>a picture of medium quality, displaying pellets of unequal sizes. <lb/>According to our characterization results, the mRNA stability seems to increase progressively as the <lb/>temperature decreases. This observation is in line with a degressive pattern more than an absolute <lb/>expression switch-off system under a certain threshold. This is in accordance with the existing data <lb/>on the CspA cold-shock system, which suggests a very short mRNA stability at high temperatures. It <lb/>is then possible that a low translation still occurs during this time-lapse (1). Additionally, those <lb/>multiple results were interesting in the sense that we did not find any previous data on amilCP <lb/>expression between 15°C and 37°C. <lb/>amilCP expression induced by BBa_K2282011 as a function of time at 37°C and 18°C <lb/>In order to follow the gene expression allowed by our cold-responsive genetic construct at high and <lb/>low temperatures over time, E.coli BL21 were transformed with BBa_K2282011 coding for the cold-<lb/>dependent amilCP expression. The amilCP expression was measured over 60 hours of growth at <lb/>either 37°C and 18°C and the results were compared with E.coli transformed with BBa_K2282005 <lb/>coding for constitutive amilCP expression (Figure 15). <lb/>Figure 16: amilCP expression over time under the cold-responsive system at 37°C and 18°C <lb/>a. OD588nm given by pSB1C3-BBa_K2282005 (constitutive amilCP expression) and pSB1C3-<lb/>BBa_K2282011 (cold-induced amilCP expression) at 37°C; b. OD588nm given by pSB1C3-<lb/>BBa_K2282005 (constitutive amilCP expression) and pSB1C3-BBa_K2282011 (cold-induced amilCP <lb/>expression) at 18°C. <lb/>At 37°C, the cold-responsive system induced a significantly lower amilCP expression compared to the <lb/>control plasmid. This is in accordance with a conditional expression at low temperatures only. At <lb/>18°C however, the expression profile showed no difference between both constructions. Previous <lb/>studies tended to show a significant expression under 15°C, however this temperature could not be <lb/>tested due to the material available. <lb/>Test of the complete heat-responsive system <lb/>The complete heat-inducible construct was tested as Registry Part BBa_K2282013, with the genetic <lb/>structure is presented in Figure 17. <lb/>Figure 17: Genetic structure of the designed part coding for the conditional expression of mRFP at <lb/>high temperatures (Part BBa_K2282013 in the iGEM part registry) <lb/>After bacterial transformation of DH5-α E.coli cells with the heat-shock and the positive control <lb/>plasmids, we incubated them into Petri dishes added with solid medium at 30°C and 37°C. At 37°C, <lb/>both bacterial populations appeared strongly red. Surprisingly, at 30°C, the populations also <lb/>displayed a slight red color. Because of this temperature was not optimal for E.coli growth, the <lb/>results were not conclusive. To get a better insight into the monomeric red fluorescent protein <lb/>(mRFP) expression level at low and high temperature, we incubated our transformed bacteria in <lb/>liquid culture and monitored the mRFP expression over time at 37°C and 18°C (Figure 18 a and b). <lb/>
			Figure 18: Expression of mRFP induced by the heat-responsive plasmid compared to the positive <lb/>control over time. a. OD500nm given by pSB1C3-BBa_K2282012 (constitutive mRFP expression) and <lb/>pSB1C3-BBa_K2282013 (heat-induced mRFP expression) at 37°C; b. OD500nm given by pSB1C3-<lb/>BBa_K2282012 (constitutive mRFP expression) and pSB1C3-BBa_K2282013 (heat-induced mRFP <lb/>expression) at 18°C. <lb/>As expected, the graph obtained at 37°C shows that mRFP was expressed at a similar level <lb/>under the expression of both genetic constructions. The results at 18°C globally show a lower protein <lb/>expression, explained by a non-optimal growth temperature. Surprisingly, both curved do not differ <lb/>and suggest a same expression level in presence and absence of the cI857 repressor, in accordance <lb/>with the previous results obtained on petri dishes. The considerable standard deviations and the <lb/>apparent lowering of the wild-type DH5-α curve was probably due to little evaporation of the culture <lb/>medium. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Cold response <lb/>In this article we demonstrated a proof of concept using the blue color reporter amilCP that our <lb/>cold-inducible system works as expected. Even though the results we have are limited because we <lb/>relied on a colorimetric assay, this shows the potential of the mechanism for many applications. The <lb/>temperature starting point of the high expression activation seems to be around 20°C. This is <lb/>interesting regarding scientific literature since most of the articles we reviewed about Cold-shock <lb/>proteins (CSPs) relies on the 15°C threshold rather than the 20°C one [REF 3]. The appearance of the <lb/>gradient indicates clearly that the mechanism is not a strict switch mechanism but a progressive one. <lb/>The modified mRNA of amilCP shows high stability at low temperature, low stability at high <lb/>temperature, and an intermediate stability between both. What we wanted to achieve with the CSP <lb/>mechanism is the deletion of the protein expression under its regulation at a temperature close to <lb/>the activating temperature of our heat response (30°C). At 27°C, the grey color shows low expression <lb/>of AmilCP and gives us promises about the validation of our strategy. <lb/>The promises given by our results to validate the CSPs mimicry as being a reliable mechanism for <lb/>cold-inducible protein expression are interesting. Perspectives of characterization for the future are <lb/>numerous. We designed several parts for improving the characterization of our cold-response <lb/>system. Although we did not have the time to use them in the iGEM competition, they can <lb/>potentially be used by other teams: <lb/>BBa_K2282007: to check the influence of 5&apos;-UTR (5&apos; Untranslated Region) on the amilCP expression. <lb/>Fig. 19: Anderson Constitutive promoter (BBa_J23100) -5&apos;UTR (BBa_K2282002) -AmilCP <lb/>(BBa_K592009) -Double terminator (BBa_B0015) <lb/>BBa_K2282008: to check if both DS Box and 5&apos;-UTR have an influence on the amilCP expression at <lb/>different temperatures. <lb/>Fig. 20: Anderson constitutive promoter (BBa_J23100) -5&apos;UTR (BBa_K2282002) -AmilCP &amp; DS Box <lb/>(BBa_K2282001) -Double Terminator (BBa_B0015) <lb/>BBa_K2282009: to check the influence of the UP element and CspA promoter on the amilCP <lb/>expression (at a transcriptional level) <lb/>Fig. 21: UP element + CspA promoter (BBa_K2282003) -RBS (BBa_B0034) -AmilCP (BBa_K592009) -<lb/>Double terminator (BBa_B0015) <lb/>BBa_K2282010: Checking the influence of the UP element, the CspA promoter and the DS Box on the <lb/>amilCP expression <lb/>Fig. 22: UP element + CspA promoter (BBa_K2282003) -RBS (BBa_B0034) -AmilCP &amp; DS Box <lb/>(BBa_K2282001) -Double terminator (BBa_B0015) <lb/>These parts can provide a solid background concerning the behavior of each elements of the Cold-<lb/>shock protein (CSP) system when characterized separately and together with the DS box. What could <lb/>also be interesting is to use a Green Fluorescent Protein (GFP) rather than amilCP for protein <lb/>quantification. We chose amilCP in our lab due to the lack of a fluorimeter. <lb/>Once the system is completely characterized, the next step would be to replace the reporter gene in <lb/>the construction by a protein of interest to be expressed at low temperature only. This will require <lb/>further modeling as for the effect of the Downstream (DS) box insertion in the new protein and its <lb/>expression at low temperature as well. Based on the protein of interest, a Type III expression system <lb/>might also be needed to enable secretion of the protein. This will also need characterization because <lb/>secretion system at low temperature might be difficult to implement for a given protein. <lb/>Heat response <lb/>The efficiency of the complete heat-inducible genetic construct created here was also evaluated. The <lb/>results obtained at 37°C shows that monomeric red fluorescent protein (mRFP) under the expression <lb/>of the pL promoter was expressed at a similar level with or without its thermo-labile cI857 repressor. <lb/>This is consistent with what we expected, as the pL promoter is constitutively activated in both cases <lb/>at this temperature. Indeed, at this temperature, cI857 is denatured and cannot dimerize. It can no <lb/>longer bind the pL promoter, allowing a regular mRFP expression [REF 17]. <lb/>The results at 18°C are not consistent with our theoretical expectations, and confirm the visual <lb/>results previously obtained. Indeed, the heat-shock plasmid induced a similar mRFP expression <lb/>compared to the positive control, whereas this genetic construction was supposed to trigger gene <lb/>expression above 37°C only. This lack of cI857 inhibition could have several explanations. First, the <lb/>BioBrick construction itself could be questioned. The transcription of mRFP may have induced a <lb/>conformational change in the double terminator we used, preventing the transcription of cI857 or <lb/>considerably lowering it to a point where the repressor cannot perform its inhibitory action <lb/>anymore. <lb/>As the ribosome binding sites (RBS) used are the same, we could also question the relative <lb/>strength of both promoters used. The promoter used for cI857 expression comes from a small <lb/>combinatorial library of constitutive promoters derived from a consensus sequence by Chris <lb/>Anderson. Among the different promoters existing in the collection, displaying variable strengths, we <lb/>chose BBa_J23100 which induces the highest relative expression after the consensus promoter <lb/>(iGEM Registry of Standard Biological Parts). The challenge is then to compare its relative strength <lb/>with the pL promoter, derived from a phage, in standardized units. To test this hypothesis, we could <lb/>design a new sequence coding for the mRFP expression under the Anderson promoter used. <lb/>Measuring the relative expression of the same reporter gene under both promoters will allow us to <lb/>assess if a significant difference can be observed. <lb/>Finally, this result could come from a lower affinity of the Anderson promoter for the RNA <lb/>polymerase. Its systematic binding to the pL promoter would explain the absence of difference <lb/>between our constitutive control and the sequence in which the repressor has been added. Several <lb/>axes of research are then opened to test our hypothesis: we could first use another promoter for the <lb/>expression of cI857, known to have a similar affinity for the RNA polymerase as the pL promoter. An <lb/>alternative would consist in constructing another BioBrick by using standard iGEM parts and test the <lb/>same construction with the pR promoter. Indeed, the system based on pR promoter regulated by cI <lb/>repressor under the Anderson BBa_J23114 promoter has already been successfully tested by <lb/>previous teams (Part BBa_K608351). <lb/>The negative results obtained from our heat-inducible system are not a significant drawback for <lb/>Thermo-responsive plasmid (TRP) development. The system using the pL/pR promoters with the <lb/>cl857 repressor has already been widely characterized and there are several possible reasons for its <lb/>failure in our experiments: our genetic construction might have simply been wrong: the reverse <lb/>orientations of both cl857 and mRFP genes might have accounted for the negative results. What is <lb/>possible is to test the system with a clean BioBrick standard assembly R10, using cl857 and an mRFP <lb/>gene regulated by either pL or pR. If the mechanism persists in being non-functional, we could test <lb/>on other high temperature induced mechanisms. For example, the 5&apos; Untranslated Transcribed <lb/>Region (UTR) of P. aeruginosa virulence factors has been shown to regulate its mRNA stability, much <lb/>like the 5&apos;UTR of Cold-shock protein A (CspA) but at high temperature [REF 30]. <lb/>In summary, one of the two mechanisms tested worked as expected and we provided a great basis <lb/>for other projects to rely on for the future. Many things need to be done but we are confident that <lb/>the TRP development can be achieved and used for many different applications. <lb/>Each year plants are subjected to temperature stresses such as ice crystal formation at low <lb/>temperatures and desiccation at high temperature, leading to yield and economic loss. Transforming <lb/>a microorganism with the TRP to make it express a specific protectant at the plant surface depending <lb/>on the outside temperatures could be of great value. <lb/>Below 15°C, ice-binding proteins will interact with ice crystals to either inhibit their growth <lb/>(antifreeze proteins) or favoring the nucleation process (ice-nucleation proteins). Despite their <lb/>opposite functions, both strategies could be of great help to prevent frost damage in their own way <lb/>and small-scale tests are required to make a final choice. Above 37°C, light-reflecting compounds will <lb/>limit evapotranspiration by creating a reflective layer. Once applied on crops, the solution will <lb/>possess a double protection: anti-drought and anti-frost (Figure 23). <lb/>Fig. 23: TRP plant application graphic <lb/>Plants record the daily average temperature and store it in a total accumulated sum called <lb/>&quot;thermal time&quot;. As soon as the needed thermal time is reached, the plant can go to the next stage of <lb/>development. The challenge of recording a total of heat accumulated over time, instead of a <lb/>temperature absolute value, could be addressed by our bi-functional plasmid. An organism could be <lb/>transformed with TRP to accumulate a red pigment above a certain temperature in an irreversible <lb/>manner. A red progression would then be visible as a function of the heat recorded over time. Being <lb/>able to visualize thermal time could be useful to predict crop development in a particular location or <lb/>retro-calculate the best sowing date. Alternatively, we could use a TRP-transformed organism to <lb/>record the average temperature every day, by comparing the color obtained to a reference scale of <lb/>colors (like pH paper). Directly visualizing the temperature recorded at the plant scale could allow a <lb/>highly precise evaluation of the potential variations of temperature average within a crop field. <lb/>Alternatively, we could use our organism in a patch such as the company Cryolog. The company uses <lb/>organisms in a patch attached to frozen food during its transport. If the cold-chain is broken during <lb/>the transport of the product, the patch irreversibly turns red. We could inspire ourselves from this <lb/>system and engineer patches that we could spread across any crop field. If a critical temperature is <lb/>reached, the TRP will be triggered and a color (blue for low temperature and red for high <lb/>temperature) will be displayed. It would be a great way to monitor whether the crops have been <lb/>subjected to critical temperatures. This could furnish an efficient way of monitoring temperature in <lb/>open fields with contained microorganisms. <lb/>Thermoregulation solutions can be costly to implement for industrial or research <lb/>applications. What could be interesting is to make a thermo-responsive organism induce an <lb/>exothermic reaction as the temperatures decrease, to reheat the medium, and an endothermic <lb/>reaction as the temperatures increase in order to cool it down. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[REF 0] <lb/>Li et al, Widespread persistent changes to temperature extremes occurred earlier than predicted, <lb/>Scientific Reports, January 2018 <lb/>[REF 1] <lb/>Hatfield et al., Temperature extremes: Effect on plant growth and development, Weather and <lb/>climate extremes, Volume 10, Part A, December 2015, Pages 4-10 <lb/>[REF 2] <lb/>Graumann et al., A superfamily of proteins that contain the cold-shock domain, TBS, Volume 23, <lb/>Issue 8, p286-290, 1 August 1998 <lb/>[REF 3] <lb/>Barria et al., &quot;Bacterial adaptation to cold&quot;, Microbiology (2013), 159, 2437-2443 <lb/>[REF 4] <lb/>Keto-Timonen R, Hietala N,Palonen E, Hakakorpi A,Lindström M and Korkeala H (2016), Cold Shock <lb/>Proteins: A Minireview with Special Emphasis on Csp-family of Enteropathogenic Yersinia. Front. <lb/>Microbiol. 7:1151.doi: 10.3389/fmicb.2016.01151 <lb/>[REF 5] <lb/>Gualerzi, C. O., Giuliodori, A. M. &amp; Pon, C. L. (2003). Transcriptional and post-transcriptional control <lb/>of cold-shock genes. J Mol Biol 331, 527-539. <lb/>[REF 6] <lb/>Goldstein, J., Pollitt, N. S. &amp; Inouye, M. (1990). Major cold shock protein of Escherichia coli. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A 87, 283-287. <lb/>[REF 7] <lb/>Masanori Mitta et al, Deletion analysis of cspA of Escherichia coli requirement of the AT-rich UP <lb/>element for cspA transcription and the downstream box in the coding region for its cold shock <lb/>induction, Molecular Microbiology (1997) 26(2), 321-335 <lb/>[REF 8] <lb/>Phadtare S, Severinov K. Extended −10 Motif Is Critical for Activity of the cspA Promoter but Does <lb/>Not Contribute to Low-Temperature Transcription. Journal of Bacteriology. 2005;187(18):6584-6589. <lb/>doi:10.1128/JB.187.18.6584-6589.2005. <lb/>[REF 9] Ian B.Dodd, Action at a distance in CI repressor regulation of the bacteriophage 186 genetic <lb/>switch, Mol Microbiol. 2002 Aug; 45(3): 697-710. <lb/>[REF 10] <lb/>Fang, L., Jiang, W., Bae, W. &amp; Inouye, M. (1997). Promoter independent cold-shock induction of cspA <lb/>and its derepression at 37°C by mRNA stabilization. Mol Microbiol 23, 355-364. <lb/>[REF 11] <lb/>Goldenberg, D., Azar, I., Oppenheim, A. B., Brandi, A., Pon, C. L. &amp; Gualerzi, C. O. Role of Escherichia <lb/>coli cspA promoter sequences and adaptation of translational apparatus in the cold shock response. <lb/>Mol Gen Genet 256, 282-290, 1997. <lb/>[REF 12] <lb/>Hankins, Janet S., Christopher Zappavigna, Annie Prud&apos;homme-Généreux, and George A. Mackie. <lb/>&quot;Role of RNA Structure and Susceptibility to RNase E in Regulation of a Cold Shock mRNA, cspA <lb/>mRNA.&quot; Journal of Bacteriology 189, no. 12 (June 15, 2007): 4353-58. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00193-07. <lb/>[REF 13] <lb/>Studer, Sean M., and Simpson Joseph. &quot;Unfolding of mRNA Secondary Structure by the Bacterial <lb/>Translation Initiation Complex.&quot; Molecular Cell 22, no. 1 (April 7, 2006): 105-15. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.molcel.2006.02.014. <lb/>[REF 14] <lb/>Duval, Mélodie, Alexey Korepanov, Olivier Fuchsbauer, Pierre Fechter, Andrea Haller, Attilio <lb/>Fabbretti, Laurence Choulier, et al. &quot;Escherichia Coli Ribosomal Protein S1 Unfolds Structured mRNAs <lb/>Onto the Ribosome for Active Translation Initiation.&quot; PLOS Biology 11, no. 12 (December 10, 2013): <lb/>e1001731. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1001731f <lb/>[REF 15] <lb/>Qu, Xiaohui, Laura Lancaster, Harry F. Noller, Carlos Bustamante, and Ignacio Tinoco. &quot;Ribosomal <lb/>Protein S1 Unwinds Double-Stranded RNA in Multiple Steps.&quot; Proceedings of the National Academy <lb/>of Sciences 109, no. 36 (September 4, 2012): 14458-63. doi:10.1073/pnas.1208950109. <lb/>[REF 16] <lb/>Makrides SC: Strategies for achieving high-level expression of genes in Escherichia coli. Microbiol Rev <lb/>1996, 60(3):512-53 <lb/>[REF 17] <lb/>Lieb M: A fine structure map of spontaneous and induced mutations in the lambda repressor gene, <lb/>including insertions of IS elements. Mol Gen Genet 1981, 184(3):364-371 <lb/>[REF 18] <lb/>Norma A Valdez-Cruz, Luis Caspeta, Néstor O Pérez, Octavio T Ramírez, Mauricio A Trujillo-Roldán -<lb/>Production of recombinant proteins in E.Coli by the heat inducible expression system based on the <lb/>phage lambda pL and/or pR promoters -Microbial Cell Factories 2010, 9:18. <lb/>[REF 19] <lb/>[(http://www.geneious.com, Kearse et al., 2012)] <lb/>[REF 20] <lb/>[Kelley, Lawrence A., Stefans Mezulis, Christopher M. Yates, Mark N. Wass, and Michael J. E. <lb/>Sternberg. &quot;The Phyre2 Web Portal for Protein Modeling, Prediction and Analysis.&quot; Nature Protocols <lb/>10, no. 6 (June 2015): 845-58. https://doi.org/10.1038/nprot.2015.053.] <lb/>[REF 21] <lb/>[Boniecki, Michal J., Grzegorz Lach, Wayne K. Dawson, Konrad Tomala, Pawel Lukasz, Tomasz <lb/>Soltysinski, Kristian M. Rother, and Janusz M. Bujnicki. &quot;SimRNA: A Coarse-Grained Method for RNA <lb/>Folding Simulations and 3D Structure Prediction.&quot; Nucleic Acids Research 44, no. 7 (April 20, 2016): <lb/>e63-e63. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkv1479.] <lb/>[REF 22] <lb/>[Van Der Spoel, David, Erik Lindahl, Berk Hess, Gerrit Groenhof, Alan E. Mark, and Herman J. C. <lb/>Berendsen. &quot;GROMACS: Fast, Flexible, and Free.&quot; Journal of Computational Chemistry 26, no. 16 <lb/>(December 1, 2005): 1701-18. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.20291.] <lb/>[REF 23] <lb/>[Humphrey, William, Andrew Dalke, and Klaus Schulten. &quot;VMD: Visual Molecular Dynamics.&quot; Journal <lb/>of Molecular Graphics 14, no. 1 (February 1996): 33-38. https://doi.org/10.1016/0263-<lb/>7855(96)00018-5.] <lb/>[REF 24] <lb/>[Ashkenazy, Haim, Elana Erez, Eric Martz, Tal Pupko, and Nir Ben-Tal. &quot;ConSurf 2010: Calculating <lb/>Evolutionary Conservation in Sequence and Structure of Proteins and Nucleic Acids.&quot; Nucleic Acids <lb/>Research 38, no. suppl 2 (July 1, 2010): W529-33. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gkq399.] <lb/>[REF 25] <lb/>[Trott, Oleg, and Arthur J. Olson. &quot;AutoDock Vina: Improving the Speed and Accuracy of Docking with <lb/>a New Scoring Function, Efficient Optimization, and Multithreading.&quot; Journal of Computational <lb/>Chemistry 31, no. 2 (January 30, 2010): 455-61. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.21334.] <lb/>[REF 26] <lb/>[Duhovny D, Nussinov R, Wolfson HJ. Efficient Unbound Docking of Rigid Molecules. In Gusfield et <lb/>al., Ed. Proceedings of the 2&apos;nd Workshop on Algorithms in Bioinformatics(WABI) Rome, Italy, <lb/>Lecture Notes in Computer Science 2452, pp. 185-200, Springer Verlag, 2002] <lb/>[REF 27] <lb/>[DeLano, W. L. (2002). Pymol: An open-source molecular graphics tool. CCP4 Newsletter On Protein <lb/>Crystallography, 40, 82-92.] <lb/>[REF 28] <lb/>[BioVia, D. S. (2015). Discovery studio modeling environment. San Diego, Dassault Systemes, <lb/>Release, 4.] <lb/>[REF 29] <lb/>Etchegaray J.P. &amp; Inouye M., &quot;A sequence downstream of the initiation codon is essential for cold <lb/>shock induction of cspB of Escherichia coli&quot;, J Bacteriol. 1999 Sep;181(18):5852-4 <lb/>[REF 30] <lb/>Grosso-Becerra MV et al., Regulation of Pseudomonas aeruginosa virulence factors by two novel <lb/>RNA thermometers., Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2014 Oct 28;111(43):15562-7 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="funding">Funding: This project was funded by the IONIS engineering schools Sup&apos;Biotech and Epita, the French <lb/>Embassy in USA, French departments Val de Marne and Sèvres, Les Mousquetaires group and the <lb/>private company Chamorin.The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics statement: N/A <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability: All data are fully available without restriction. </div>


	</text>
</tei>
