<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Partially methylated domains are hypervariable in breast cancer <lb/>and fuel widespread CpG island hypermethylation <lb/>AUTHORS <lb/>Arie B. Brinkman 1* , Serena Nik-Zainal 2,3 , Femke Simmer 1# , F. Germán Rodríguez-González 4 , <lb/>Marcel Smid 4 , Ludmil B. Alexandrov 2,6,7 , Adam Butler 2 , Sancha Martin 2 , Helen Davies 2 , <lb/>Dominik Glodzik 2 , Xueqing Zou 2 , Manasa Ramakrishna 2 , Johan Staaf 5 , Markus Ringnér 5 , Anieta <lb/>Sieuwerts 4 , Anthony Ferrari 8 , Sandro Morganella 9 , Thomas Fleischer 10 , Vessela Kristensen 10,11,12 , <lb/>Marta Gut 13 Marc J. van de Vijver 14 , Anne-Lise Børresen-Dale 10,11 , Andrea L. Richardson 15,16 , <lb/>Gilles Thomas 8 , Ivo G. Gut 13 , John W.M. Martens 4 , John A. Foekens 4 , Mike Stratton 2 , Hendrik <lb/>G. Stunnenberg 1* <lb/>AFFILIATIONS <lb/>1 Radboud University, Department of Molecular Biology, Faculty of Science, Radboud Institute <lb/>for Molecular Life Sciences, Nijmegen, Netherlands <lb/>2 Wellcome Trust Sanger Institute, Hinxton, Cambridge CB10 1SA, UK <lb/>3 Academic Department of Medical Genetics, University of Cambridge, Cambridge CB2 0QQ, <lb/>UK <lb/>4 Erasmus MC Cancer Institute and Cancer Genomics Netherlands, Erasmus University Medical <lb/>Center, Department of Medical Oncology, Rotterdam, The Netherlands <lb/>5 Division of Oncology and Pathology, Department of Clinical Sciences Lund, Lund University, <lb/>Lund, Sweden <lb/>6 Theoretical Biology and Biophysics (T-6), Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, <lb/>New Mexico, United States of America <lb/>2 <lb/>7 Center for Nonlinear Studies, Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, New Mexico, <lb/>United States of America <lb/>8 Synergie Lyon Cancer,Centre Léon Bérard, 28 rue Laënnec, Lyon Cedex 08, France <lb/>9 European Molecular Biology Laboratory, European Bioinformatics Institute, Wellcome Trust <lb/>Genome Campus,Hinxton, Cambridgeshire, CB10 1SD <lb/>10 Department of Genetics, Institute for Cancer Research, Oslo University Hospital, The <lb/>Norwegian Radium Hospital, Oslo, 0310 Norway <lb/>11 K.G. Jebsen Centre for Breast Cancer Research, Institute for Clinical Medicine, University of <lb/>Oslo, Oslo, 0316 Norway <lb/>12 Department of Clinical Molecular Biology and Laboratory Science (EpiGen), Division of <lb/>Medicine, Akershus University Hospital, Lørenskog, 1478 Norway <lb/>13 Centro Nacional de Análisis Genómico (CNAG), Parc Científic de Barcelona, Barcelona, <lb/>Spain <lb/>14 Department of Pathology, Academic Medical Center, Meibergdreef 9, 1105 AZ Amsterdam, <lb/>the Netherlands <lb/>15 Department of Pathology, Brigham and Women&apos;s Hospital, Boston, MA 02115 USA <lb/>16 Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA 02215 USA <lb/># Current address: Department of Pathology, Radboud University Nijmegen Medical Centre, P.O. <lb/>Box 9101, Nijmegen 6500 HB, The Netherlands <lb/>* Corresponding authors: A.B. Brinkman (a.brinkman@science.ru.nl), H.G. Stunnenberg <lb/>(h.stunnenberg@ncmls.ru.nl) <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>SUMMARY <lb/>Global loss of DNA methylation and CpG island (CGI) hypermethylation are regarded as <lb/>key epigenomic aberrations in cancer. Global loss manifests itself in partially methylated <lb/>domains (PMDs) which can extend up to megabases. However, the distribution of PMDs <lb/>within and between tumor types, and their effects on key functional genomic elements <lb/>including CGIs are poorly defined. Using whole genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) of <lb/>breast cancers, we comprehensively show that loss of methylation in PMDs occurs in a <lb/>large fraction of the genome and represents the prime source of variation in DNA <lb/>methylation. PMDs are hypervariable in methylation level, size and distribution, and <lb/>display elevated mutation rates. They impose intermediate DNA methylation levels <lb/>incognizant of functional genomic elements including CGIs, underpinning a CGI <lb/>methylator phenotype (CIMP). However, significant repression effects on cancer-genes are <lb/>negligible as tumor suppressor genes are generally excluded from PMDs. The genomic <lb/>distribution of PMDs reports tissue-of-origin of different cancers and may represent tissue-<lb/>specific &apos;silent&apos; regions of the genome, which tolerate instability at the epigenetic, <lb/>transcriptomic and genetic level. <lb/></front>

			<body>Global loss of methylation was among the earliest recognized epigenetic alterations of cancer <lb/>cells 1 . It is now known to occur in large genomic blocks that partially lose their default <lb/>hypermethylated state, termed partially methylated domains (PMDs) 2-6 . PMDs have been <lb/>described for a variety of cancer types and appear to represent repressive chromatin domains that <lb/>are associated with nuclear lamina interactions, late replication and low transcription. PMDs are <lb/>not exclusive to cancer cells and have also been detected in some normal tissues 2,7-11 , but not in <lb/>pluripotent cells and brain tissue 12,13 . PMDs can comprise up to half of the genome 3,4 , and it has <lb/>been suggested that PMDs in different tissues are largely identical 3 . PMDs have been shown to <lb/>harbor &apos;focal&apos; sites of hypermethylation that largely overlap with CGIs 3 . Questions remain as to <lb/>what instigates such focal hypermethylation, whether loss of methylation inside PMDs is linked <lb/>to repression of cancer-relevant genes and whether the genomic distribution of PMDs is invariant <lb/>throughout primary tumors of the same type, perhaps determined by tissue-of-origin. In breast <lb/>cancer, PMDs have been detected in two cultured cancer cell lines 5 , but their extent and variation <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>in primary tumors is hitherto unknown. A major limitation of most DNA methylation studies is <lb/>that only a small subset of CpGs are interrogated. This prevents accurate determination of the <lb/>extent and location of PMDs. Few samples of a certain tissue/tumor have typically been analyzed <lb/>using whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS). Thus, observations cannot be extrapolated to <lb/>individual cancer types, let alone generalized to other cancers. Here, we analyzed DNA <lb/>methylation profiles of 30 primary breast tumors at high resolution through WGBSsThis allowed <lb/>us to, and delineate PMD characteristics in detail. We show that PMDs define (breast) cancer <lb/>methylomes and are linked to other key epigenetic aberrations such as CGI hypermethylation. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Primary breast tumors display variable loss of DNA methylation <lb/>To study breast cancer epigenomes we performed WGBS encompassing ~95% of annotated <lb/>CpGs (Suppl. Fig. 1A, Suppl. Table 1). For 25/30 and 24/30 of these tumors we previously <lb/>analyzed their full genomes 14,15 and transcriptomes 16 , respectively. Of the 30 tumors, 25 and 5 <lb/>are ER-positive and ER-negative, respectively (Suppl. Fig. 1B). <lb/>To globally inspect aberrations in DNA methylation patterns we generated genome-wide and <lb/>chromosome-wide methylome maps by displaying mean methylation in consecutive tiles of 10 <lb/>kb (see Methods). These maps revealed extensive inter-tumor variation at genome-wide scale <lb/>(Fig. 1A), that lacked obvious association with ER-status (p=0.15, t-test, Suppl. Fig. 2A). At <lb/>chromosome level, we observed stably hypermethylated regions next to regions that were <lb/>hypomethylated to various extents and across tumors (Fig. 1B). Chromosomes 1 and X were <lb/>exceptionally prone to methylation loss. At megabase scale (Fig. 1C) DNA methylation profiles <lb/>showed that the widespread loss of methylation occurred in block-like structures previously <lb/>defined as PMDs 2 . Across primary breast tumor samples, DNA methylation levels and genomic <lb/>sizes of PMDs differ extensively between tumors and PMDs do appear as separate units in some <lb/>tumors and as merged or extended in others, underscoring the high variation with which <lb/>methylation loss occurs. Despite this variation, however, we observed common PMD boundaries <lb/>as well. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Given the variation between tumors, we asked whether the patterns of methylation loss were <lb/>associated with distribution of copy-number variations (CNVs) throughout the genome. We <lb/>found no evidence for such association (Pearson R=0.17), although we noticed that chromosomes <lb/>with the most pronounced loss of methylation (chr1, chrX, chr8-p) frequently contained <lb/>amplifications (Suppl. Fig. 1C). Next, we asked whether loss of methylation was associated with <lb/>aberrant expression of genes involved in writing, erasing, or reading the 5-methylcytosine <lb/>modification. However, we found no such correlation (Suppl. Fig. 1D). <lb/>To provide a reference for the observed patterns of methylation loss we compared WGBS <lb/>profiles of primary breast tumors to that of 72 normal tissues (WGBS profiles from Roadmap <lb/>Epigenomics Project and 10 , Suppl. Fig. 2A,B). In sharp contrast to breast cancer, most normal <lb/>tissues were almost fully hypermethylated (except for pancreas and skin), with heart, thymus, <lb/>embryonic stem cell(-derived), induced pluripotent stem cells and brain having the highest levels <lb/>of methylation. Importantly, inter-tissue variation was much lower as compared to breast tumors <lb/>(p &lt; 2.2e-16, MWU-test on standard deviations). Thus, breast tumors show widespread loss of <lb/>DNA methylation in PMDs, and the extent and patterns appear to be hypervariable between <lb/>tumor samples. In line with this, principal component analysis confirmed that methylation inside <lb/>PMDs is the primary source of variation across full-genome breast cancer DNA methylation <lb/>profiles (Fig. 1D): the first principal component (PC1) is strongly associated with mean PMD <lb/>methylation (p=6.8e-07). The second-largest source of variation, PC2, is associated with ER <lb/>status (p=1.9e-06, Fig. 1D), while successive PCs were not significantly associated with any <lb/>clinicopathological feature. It should be noted that with 30 tumors only very strong associations <lb/>can achieve statistical significance. Taken together, breast tumor whole-genome DNA <lb/>methylation profiles reveal global loss of methylation due to PMDs, the extent of which is <lb/>hypervariable across tumors and represent the major source of variation between tumors. <lb/>Distribution and characteristics of breast cancer PMDs <lb/>We set out to further characterize breast cancer PMDs and their variation (see Methods: data <lb/>access). The genome fraction covered by PMDs varies greatly across our WGBS cohort of 30 <lb/>tumors, ranging between 10% and 50% across tumors, covering 32% of the genome on average <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Fig. 2A). We define &apos;PMD frequency&apos; as the number of tumors in which a PMD is detected. A <lb/>PMD frequency of 30 (PMDs common to all 30 cases) occurs in only a very small fraction of the <lb/>genome (2%), while a PMD frequency of 1 (representing the union of all PMDs from 30 cases) <lb/>involves 70.2% of the genome (Fig. 2B). We tested to which extent PMD distribution is random, <lb/>by counting PMD borders in 30-kb genomic tiles (Fig. 2C). Randomly shuffled PMDs yield a <lb/>normal distribution centered at a PMD frequency of four. In contrast, observed PMDs show a <lb/>skewed distribution: the mode was for a PMD frequency of 0 suggesting that many tiles (23,492, <lb/>25%) do not coincide with any PMD borders. The majority of tiles (62%) had a low PMD border <lb/>frequency (1-10). The tail represents low numbers of tiles with up to maximal PMD frequency of <lb/>30. We conclude that PMD distribution is not random: part of the genome appears not to tolerate <lb/>PMDs while PMDs occur in a large fraction of the genome with varying frequencies. <lb/>PMDs have been shown to coincide with lamin-associated domains (LADs) 3,4 : large repressive <lb/>domains that preferentially locate to the nuclear periphery 17 . LADs are characterized by low gene <lb/>density and late replication 17,18 . Accordingly we found that PMDs show reduced gene densities <lb/>(Fig. 2E, Suppl. Fig. 3A), have high LaminB1 signals (associated with LADs 17 , Fig. 2D), are late <lb/>replicating (ENCODE data, Fig. 2D) and have a low frequency of (Hi-C) 3D loops 19 , an <lb/>indicator of lower levels of transcription. Finally, we observed a local increase in binding of the <lb/>transcription factor CTCF at the borders of PMDs (Fig. 2D) as shown in previous reports 3,17,20-<lb/>22 <lb/>. <lb/>We previously analyzed the full transcriptomes (RNA-seq) in a breast cancer cohort of 266 <lb/>cases 16 from which our WGBS cohort is a subset. We determined the mean expression of genes <lb/>as a function of PMD frequency. Genes inside PMDs are expressed at consistently lower levels <lb/>than genes outside of PMDs (Fig. 2F, p &lt; 2.2e-16, t-test), with a tendency towards lower <lb/>expression in highly-frequent PMDs (p &lt; 2.2e-16, linear regression). Given the variable nature of <lb/>DNA methylation patterns of PMDs, we also determined the variation in gene expression as a <lb/>function of PMD frequency and found higher variation for genes inside PMDs (Fig. 2F, p &lt; 2.2e-<lb/>16, MWU-test). Even when restricting this analysis to only the subset of 24 overlapping cases <lb/>from the transcriptome and WGBS cohort we observed the same trends, with similar statistical <lb/>significance (Suppl. Fig. 3B, p &lt; 2.2e-16, t-test for expression; p &lt; 2.2e-16, MWU-test for <lb/>variation). Given the observed variability of DNA methylation and gene expression inside PMDs, <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>we asked whether genetic stability, i.e. the number of somatic mutations, was also altered within <lb/>PMDs. In our cohort of 560 full breast cancer genomes 14 , substitutions, insertions, and deletions <lb/>occur more frequently within than outside PMDs, with a clear increase in highly frequent PMDs <lb/>(p &lt; 2.2e-16 for each mutation type, logistic regression, Fig. 2G). In contrast, rearrangements are <lb/>more abundant outside of PMDs (p &lt; 2.2e-16, logistic regression), in keeping with the <lb/>hypothesis that regions with higher transcriptional activity are more susceptible to <lb/>translocations 23 . As above, a restrictive analysis of only the 25 overlapping cases from the full <lb/>genomes and WGBS cohorts revealed the same trends except for insertions (p &lt; 2.2e-16 <lb/>(substitutions); p = 0.362 (insertions), p = 1.7e-05 (deletions), p = 1.1e-09 (rearrangements), <lb/>logistic regressions, Suppl. Fig. 3C). Taken together, breast cancer PMDs share key features of <lb/>PMDs including low gene density, low gene expression, and colocalization with LADs, <lb/>suggesting that they reside in the &apos;B&apos; (inactive) compartment of the genome 24 . Importantly, in <lb/>addition to epigenomic instability, breast cancer PMDs also tolerate transcriptomic variability <lb/>and genomic instability. <lb/>Relationship between CpG island methylation and PMDs in breast cancer <lb/>To determine how PMDs affect methylation of functional genomic elements we accordingly <lb/>stratified all CpGs from all tumors and assessed the methylation distribution in these elements <lb/>(Fig. 2H). We found that the normally observed near-binary methylation distribution is lost <lb/>inside PMDs; the hypermethylated bulk of the genome and hypomethylated CGIs/promoters <lb/>acquire intermediate levels of DNA methylation inside PMDs. DNA methylation deposition <lb/>inside PMDs thus appears incognizant of genomic elements, resulting in intermediate <lb/>methylation levels regardless of the genomic elements&apos; functions. Among all elements, the effect <lb/>of incognizant DNA methylation deposition is most prominent for CGIs as they undergo the <lb/>largest change departing from a strictly hypomethylated state. This has been described also as <lb/>focal hypermethylation inside PMDs 3 . <lb/>We further focused on methylation levels of CGIs. When indiviual PMDs are regarded, CGIs <lb/>inside of them lose their strictly hypomethylated state and become more methylated to a degree <lb/>that varies between tumors (Fig. 3A). Across all tumors and all CGIs, this effect is extensive (Fig. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>3B,C), affecting virtually all CGIs inside PMDs: on average 92% of CGIs lose their <lb/>hypomethylated state and gain some level of methylation (Fig. 3B, left panel). Outside of PMDs <lb/>only 25-30% of the CGIs is hypermethylated, although to a higher level (Fig. 3B, right panel). <lb/>Thus, incognizant deposition of DNA methylation inside PMDs results in extensive <lb/>hypermethylation of virtually all PMD-CGIs. <lb/>Concurrent hypermethylation of CGIs in cancer has been termed CIMP 25 , and in breast cancer <lb/>this phenomenon has been termed B-CIMP 26-28 . To determine whether CIMP is directly related <lb/>to PMD variation we defined B-CIMP as the fraction of CGIs that are hypermethylated (&gt;30% <lb/>methylated), and determined its association with the fraction of CGIs inside PMDs. Regression <lb/>analysis (see Methods) showed that this association is highly significant (Fig. 3D, p=2.1e-08, <lb/>R 2 =0.51, n=30). The fraction of hypermethylated CGIs is generally higher than the fraction of <lb/>hypermethylated CGIs in PMDs, suggesting that CGI hypermethylation is not solely dependent <lb/>on PMD occurrence. However, CGI methylation levels outside PMDs are far more stable than <lb/>inside PMDs (Fig. 3E), which likely represents an invariably methylated set of CGIs (Suppl. <lb/>Table 2). <lb/>We applied the same regression analysis to other tumor types (TCGA, 29 , Fig. 3F). Although <lb/>sample sizes were small, we found significant CIMP-PMD associations for lung adenocarcinoma <lb/>(LUAD), rectum adenocarcinoma (READ), uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma (UCEC) and <lb/>bladder urothelial carcinoma (BLCA). We did not find significant associations for Burkitt&apos;s <lb/>lymphoma (BL), lung squamous cell carcinoma (LUSC), follicular lymphoma (FL), and <lb/>glioblastoma (GBM), even though G-CIMP has been previously described 30 . Taken together, we <lb/>conclude that PMD occurrence is an important determinant for CIMP. <lb/>PMD demethylation effects on gene expression <lb/>To assess whether widespread hypermethylation of CGI-promoters within PMDs instigates gene <lb/>repression we analyzed expression as a function of gene location inside or outside of PMDs. <lb/>Overall, CGI-promoter genes showed a mild but significant downregulation when inside PMDs <lb/>(p=4.5e-12, t-test), while strong downregulation was specifically restricted to low-frequency <lb/>PMDs (Fig. 3G). For non-CGI-promoter genes this trend was very weak or absent (Suppl. Fig. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>4A). As healthy controls were not included in transcriptome analysis of our cohort 16 we used <lb/>gene expression (RNA-seq) profiles from breast tumors (769) and normal controls (88) from <lb/>TCGA. Similar to our cohort (see Fig. 2F) we found that overall gene expression for the TCGA <lb/>tumors is lower inside PMDs, with lowest expression for genes inside high-frequent PMDs (Fig. <lb/>3H, p &lt; 2.2e-16, linear regression). However, the expression of genes in tumor PMDs is very <lb/>similar to healthy control samples (p = 0.807, linear regression). To analyze this in more detail <lb/>we selected normal/tumor matched pairs (i.e. from the same individuals, n=86) and analyzed the <lb/>fold change over the different PMD frequencies (Fig. 3I). As in our cohort, downregulation is <lb/>restricted to genes with low PMD-frequency (p &lt; 2.2e-16 for PMD frequency 1-3, linear <lb/>regression). No obvious changes occur in high-frequency PMD genes, nor in non-CGI-promoter <lb/>genes (Suppl. Fig. 4B). Taken together, widespread cancer-associated repression of all genes <lb/>inside PMDs is limited: downregulation is restricted to low-frequency (i.e. the more variable) <lb/>PMDs and affects only CGI-promoter genes, which undergo widespread hypermethylation inside <lb/>PMDs. <lb/>Given the widely accepted model of hypermethylated promoter-CGIs causing repression of <lb/>tumor suppressor genes (TSGs) we determined whether breast cancer PMDs overlap with these <lb/>genes to instigate such repression. For non-TSGs as a reference we found that 64% (14,037) are <lb/>located outside of PMDs (Fig. 3J), while 36% are located inside, (see also Fig. 2E). Strikingly, <lb/>TSGs (Cancer Gene Census) overlap poorly with PMDs: most TSGs (218/254, 86%) are located <lb/>outside of PMDs. Only 14% overlap with mostly low-frequency PMDs, implying exclusion of <lb/>TSGs from PMDs (p=8.8e-16, hypergeometric test). When we specifically focused on breast <lb/>cancer-related TSGs (Cancer Gene Census), this exclusion was even stronger: practically all <lb/>(27/28, 96%) breast cancer TSGs are located outside of PMDs (p=3.5e-06, hypergeometric test). <lb/>Similarly, from our previously identified set of genes containing breast cancer driver mutations 14 : <lb/>86/93 (92%) were located outside of PMDs (p=2.0e-11, hypergeometric test). Alltoghether, only <lb/>31 breast cancer-mutated genes were not excluded from PMDs. We assessed whether these genes <lb/>are downregulated in tumors when inside PMDs. 24/31 (74%) genes were downregulated (Suppl. <lb/>Fig. 5A,B), and an overall negative correlation between CGI-promoter methylation and <lb/>expression was evident (Suppl. Fig. 5C). For 16 out of these 24 genes we confirmed that <lb/>significant downregulation also takes place in cancer relative to normal in an independent breast <lb/>cancer expression dataset (TCGA, Suppl. Fig. 5D and data not shown). Among the <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>downregulated genes in PMDs are EGFR (epidermal growth factor receptor) and PDGFRA <lb/>(platelet-derived growth factor receptor α) that have tumor promoting mutations (Suppl. Fig. <lb/>5A,B,C). Paradoxically, both genes are significantly downregulated in our as well as the TCGA <lb/>breast cancer dataset (Suppl. Fig. 5D). Taken together, despite the large number of <lb/>hypermethylated CpG islands inside breast cancer PMDs (13,013 CGIs; 47%, Suppl. Fig. 4C), <lb/>these CGIs do not generally co-occur with TSGs and other breast cancer-relevant genes. <lb/>Repression of these genes through classical promoter-hypermethylation in PMDs does not occur <lb/>at large scale, and is likely limited to a few genes. <lb/>We next identified genes that are downregulated when inside PMDs regardless of any <lb/>documented TSG function or mutation in breast cancer. 400 genes were downregulated at least <lb/>2.5 log2-fold (Suppl. Table 3). Gene set enrichment analysis showed that these genes were <lb/>involved in processes such as signaling and adhesion (Suppl. Fig. 6A). In addition, there is a <lb/>significant enrichment of genes downregulated in luminal B breast cancer (and upregulated in <lb/>basal breast cancer) 31 . This suggests that PMDs are involved in downregulation of luminal B-<lb/>specific genes. Examples of luminal B-downregulated genes include CD3G, encoding the <lb/>gamma polypeptide of the T-cell receptor-CD3 complex (gene sets &apos;signaling&apos; and &apos;adhesion&apos;), <lb/>and RBP4, encoding retinol binding protein 4 (gene set &apos;signaling&apos;) (Suppl. Fig. 6B). <lb/>Stratification of tumors according to low and high median expression of the 400 PMD-<lb/>downregulated genes revealed significant differences in overall survival of the corresponding <lb/>patients (p=2.6e-03, chi-square test, Suppl. Fig. 6C), suggesting clinical significance of PMD-<lb/>associated gene repression. Taken together, downregulation of genes inside PMDs occurs rarely <lb/>and is restricted to low-frequency PMDs. However, these rare cases include genes relevant to <lb/>breast cancer given the overlap with previously identified luminal B breast cancer-relevant genes <lb/>and differential overall survival. <lb/>PMDs are not unique to cancers, but reduced DNA methylation in PMDs is a feature of <lb/>many cancers <lb/>To assess the generality of PMD occurrence in cancer, we extended our analysis to other cancer <lb/>types and normal tissues. We performed PMD detection in a total of 134 WGBS profiles (57 <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>tumors from TCGA, 29 and 77 normal tissues from the Roadmap Epigenomics Project and 5 ). <lb/>PMDs are detectable in virtually all tumors, but also in 30% of normal tissues (Fig. 4A, see <lb/>Methods: data access). However, mean DNA methylation inside detected PMDs is much lower <lb/>in tumors as compared to normal tissues (Fig. 4B, Suppl. Fig. 7A, p=1.0e-18, t-test), and is not <lb/>associated with tumor tissue origin: upon ranking the samples according their mean PMD <lb/>methylation, tumors of the same type are dispersed rather than clustered together (Fig. 4B). Thus, <lb/>PMDs are not unique to tumors per se but the overall loss of methylation inside PMDs is <lb/>consistently greater in tumors. Still, the absolute loss does not typify tumor tissue origin, <lb/>underscoring the variable nature of methylation within PMDs. To assess whether CGI <lb/>hypermethylation in PMDs is as extensive in these additional tumor types as in breast cancer, we <lb/>analyzed CGI methylation of the 57 tumor samples in total (Suppl. Fig. 7B, see Methods: data <lb/>access). As in breast cancer, widespread hypermethylation of CGIs inside PMDs was consistent <lb/>in most tumor types. The levels of hypermethylation in Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma (BL) 29 were among <lb/>the highest of all tested tumors, while hypermethylation levels in lung <lb/>adenocarcinoma/squamous cell carcinoma (LUAD/LUSC) were slightly lower than in other <lb/>tumors. Possibly, these differences are linked to tumor cellularity of the samples. In two <lb/>glioblastoma multiforme tumors, CGI hypermethylation was not restricted to PMDs, which is <lb/>suggestive of inaccurate PMD detection due to high methylation inside glioblastoma PMDs (see <lb/>Fig. 4B). Importantly, these results extend the observed tendency of CGI hypermethylation <lb/>inside PMDs to other tumors. <lb/>Lastly, to assess whether the distribution of tumor PMDs reflects tissue of origin we scored the <lb/>presence of PMDs in genomic tiles of 30 kb and subsequently clustered the resulting binary <lb/>profiles. The analysis showed that the majority of tumors of the same type clustered together, <lb/>although not fully accurately (Fig. 4C), suggesting that the genomic distribution of PMDs is <lb/>linked to tissue of origin. Thus, even though methylation levels of PMDs are independent of <lb/>tissue-of-origin (Fig. 4B), the distribution of PMDs associates with tissue of origin, likely <lb/>reflecting differences in the genomic parts that tolerate PMDs. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this study we analyzed breast cancer DNA methylation profiles to high resolution. The main <lb/>feature of breast cancer epigenomes is the extensive loss of methylation in PMDs and their <lb/>hypervariability. Directly linked to this is the concurrent CGI hypermethylation, for which PMDs <lb/>appear to be a major driver or even causal. Although various features of PMDs have been <lb/>described before, our study is the first to include a larger WGBS cohort from one tumor type, <lb/>while integrating sparse WGBS data from other tumor types. PMDs may be regarded as tissue-<lb/>type-specific inactive constituents of the genome: the distribution shows tissue-of-origin <lb/>specificity, gene expression inside PMDs is low and they are late replicating. Inside PMDs the <lb/>accumulation of breast cancer mutations is higher than outside of them. The resulting domain-<lb/>like fluctuation in mutation density is likely related to the fluctuating mutational density along <lb/>the genome in cancer cells observed by others 32-34 . The phenomena observed in breast cancer <lb/>extend to tumors of at least 10 additional tissue types underscoring the generality of our findings. <lb/>We conclude that loss of methylation in PMDs and concurrent CGI hypermethylation is a <lb/>general hallmark of most tumor types with the exception of AMLs (data not shown). <lb/>The phenomena that we describe for breast cancer have remained elusive in genome-scale <lb/>studies that only assessed subsets of the CpGs; the sparsity of included CpGs does not allow <lb/>accurate PMD detection. Typical analysis strategies include tumor stratification by clustering of <lb/>the most highly variable CpGs which at least in our breast cancer cohort are located in PMDs. In <lb/>effect such approaches are biased towards CGIs due to their design and consequently, the <lb/>hypermethylation groups represent tumors in which PMDs are highly abundant (e.g. 30,35-43 ). It is <lb/>very likely that for some tumor types hypermethylation groups associate with clinicopathological <lb/>features, amongst which a positive association with tumor cellularity is recurrent 36,40-42 . This <lb/>suggests that PMDs are more pronounced in tumor cells than in the non-tumor tissue of a cancer <lb/>sample. This makes hypermethylated CGIs useful diagnostic markers but less likely informative <lb/>as prognostic markers informing about tumor state, progression and outcome. <lb/>Since PMDs are domains in which instability at the genetic, epigenetic, and transcriptome level <lb/>is tolerated, they may provide plasticity that is beneficial for the heterogeneity of tumor cells. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>METHODS <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data access <lb/>Tables containing CpG methylation values (bigwig), genomic coordinates and mean methylation <lb/>values of PMDs and CGIs are available via DOI 10.5281/zenodo.1217427 or DOI <lb/>10.17026/dans-276-sda6. Raw data for whole-genome bisulfite sequencing of the 30 breast <lb/>tumor samples of this study is available from the European Genome-phenome Archive <lb/>(https://www.ebi.ac.uk/ega) under dataset accession EGAD00001001388. <lb/>Sample selection, pathology review and clinical data collection <lb/></div>

			<body>Sample selection, pathology review and clinical data collection for this study has been described <lb/>in 14 . <lb/>Processing of whole-genome bisulfite sequencing data <lb/>WGBS library preparation, read mapping, and methylation calling was done as described <lb/>before 44 . The genome build used for mapping of bisulfite sequencing reads, and throughout this <lb/>study was hg19 (GRCh37). <lb/>Principal component analysis of WGBS data <lb/>For principal component analysis (PCA) of WGBS profiles, CpGs with coverage of at least 10 <lb/>were used. Subsequently, the top 5% most variable CpGs were selected. We used the <lb/>FactoMineR package 45 for R to perform PCA and to determine association of principal <lb/>components with clinicopathological features. <lb/>Detection of PMDs <lb/>Detection of partially methylated domains (PMDs) in all methylation profiles throughout this <lb/>study was done using the MethylSeekR package for R 46 . Before PMD calling, CpGs overlapping <lb/>common SNPs (dbSNP build 137) were removed. The alpha distribution 46 was used to determine <lb/>whether PMDs were present at all, along with visual inspection of WGBS profiles. After PMD <lb/>calling, the resulting PMDs were further filtered by removing regions overlapping with <lb/>centromers (undetermined sequence content). <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Mean methylation in PMDs and genomic tiles <lb/>Wherever mean methylation values from WGBS were calculated in regions containing multiple <lb/>CpGs, the &apos;weighted methylation level&apos; 47 was used. Calculation of mean methylation within <lb/>PMDs or genomic tiles involved removing all CpGs overlapping with CpG island(-shores) and <lb/>promoters, as the high CpG densities within these elements yield unbalanced mean methylation <lb/>values, not representative of PMD methylation. For genome/chromosome-wide visualizations <lb/>(Fig. 1), 10-kb tiles were used. For visualization, the samples were ordered according <lb/>hierarchical clustering of the tiled methylation profiles, using &apos;ward.D&apos; linkage and [1-Pearson <lb/>correlation] as a distance measure. <lb/>Clustering on PMD distribution <lb/>For each sample, the presence of PMDs was binary scored (0 or 1) in genomic tiles of 5 kb. <lb/>Based on these binary profiles, a distance matrix was calculated using [1-Jaccard] as a distance <lb/>metric, which was used in hierarchical clustering using complete linkage. <lb/>Tumor suppressor genes and driver mutations <lb/>For <lb/>overlaps <lb/>with <lb/>tumor <lb/>suppressor <lb/>genes, <lb/>Cancer <lb/>Gene <lb/>Census <lb/>(http://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/census, October 2017) genes were used. Overlaps with genes <lb/>containing breast cancer driver mutations were determined using the list of 93 driver genes as <lb/>published previously by us 14 . <lb/>CIMP <lb/>To determine the association between B-CIMP (fraction of CGIs that are hypermethylated, <lb/>&gt;30% methylated) and PMD occurrence we used beta-regression using the &apos;betareg&apos; package in <lb/>R 48 . <lb/>Survival analysis <lb/>Survival analysis of patient groups stratified by expression of genes downregulated in PMDs. For <lb/>each tumor sample of our breast cancer transcriptome cohort (n=266, 16 ), the median expression <lb/>of all PMD-downregulated genes (Suppl. Table 3) was calculated. The obtained distribution of <lb/>these medians was used to stratify patient groups, using a two-way split over the median of this <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>distribution. Overall survival analysis using these groups was done using the &apos;survival&apos; package <lb/>in R, with chi-square significance testing. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>This work has been funded through the ICGC Breast Cancer Working group by the Breast <lb/>Cancer Somatic Genetics Study (BASIS), a European research project funded by the European <lb/>Community&apos;s Seventh Framework Programme (FP7/2010-2014) under the grant agreement <lb/>number 242006; the Triple Negative project funded by the Wellcome Trust (grant reference <lb/>077012/Z/05/Z). For contributions towards specimens and collections: Tayside Tissue Bank, <lb/>OSBREAC consortium, Icelandic Centre for Research (RANNIS), Swedish Cancer Society, <lb/>Swedish Research Council, Fondation Jean Dausset-Centre d&apos;Etudes du polymorphisme humain, <lb/>Icelandic Cancer Registry, Brisbane Breast Bank, Breast Cancer Tissue and Data Bank and <lb/>ECMC (King&apos;s College London), NIHR Biomedical Research Centre (Guy&apos;s and St Thomas&apos;s <lb/>Hospitals), Breakthrough Breast Cancer, Cancer Research UK. We thank E.M. Janssen-Megens, <lb/>K. Berentsen, H. Kerstens and K.J. Francoijs for technical support. We thank H. Kretzmer and R. <lb/>Siebert for providing processed data files of the lymphoma dataset. Funding to A.B.B. was <lb/>through the Dutch Cancer Foundation (KWF) grant KUN 2013-5833. SN-Z is personally funded <lb/>by a CRUK Advanced Clinician Scientist Award (C60100/A23916). M.S. was supported by the <lb/>EU-FP7-DDR response project. L.B.A. is supported through a J. Robert Oppenheimer <lb/>Fellowship at Los Alamos National Laboratory. A.L.R. is partially supported by the Dana-<lb/>Farber/Harvard Cancer Center SPORE in Breast Cancer (NIH/NCI 5 P50 CA168504-02). J.A.F. <lb/>was funded through an ERC Advanced Grant (ERC-2012-AdG-322737) and ERC Proof-of-<lb/>Concept Grant (ERC-2017-PoC-767854). A.S. was supported by Cancer Genomics Netherlands <lb/>(CGC.nl) through a grant from the Netherlands Organisation of Scientific research (NWO). We <lb/>received additional support from the Dutch national e-infrastructure (SURF Foundation). Finally, <lb/>we would like to acknowledge all members of the ICGC Breast Cancer Working Group. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1 | Visualization of inter-tumor variation at genome-wide scale. <lb/>(A), Genome-wide and (B), chromosome-wide maps of WGBS DNA methylation profiles from <lb/>30 breast tumor samples. Mean methylation is displayed in consecutive tiles of 10 kb (see <lb/>Methods). Ordering of tumor samples is according clustering of the tiled profiles. (C), WGBS <lb/>DNA methylation visualization at megabase-scale. Pink coloring indicates common methylation <lb/>loss (PMDs), although tumor-specific PMD borders vary. A scale bar (100 kb) is shown at the <lb/>top of each panel. CpG islands are indicated in green. (D), Principal component analysis of <lb/>WGBS DNA methylation profiles (see Methods). Each tumor sample is represented with its <lb/>estrogen-receptor (ER) status (point shape) and mean PMD methylation (point color). <lb/>Figure 2 | Characterization of breast cancer PMDs. <lb/>(A), Fraction of the genome covered by PMDs. Each dot represents one tumor sample, the <lb/>boxplot summarizes this distribution. (B), Fraction of the genome covered by PMDs that are <lb/>common between breast tumors. PMD frequency: the number of tumors in which a genomic <lb/>region or gene is a PMD. (C), Breast cancer PMDs are not distributed randomly over the genome. <lb/>The genome was dissected into 30-kb tiles, PMD frequency (number of boundaries) was <lb/>calculated for each tile. The same analysis was done after shuffling the PMDs of each tumor <lb/>sample. (D), Average profiles of LaminB 17 , repliSeq (DNA replication timing, ENCODE), 3D <lb/>chromatin interaction loops (HiC 21 , and CTCF (ENCODE) over PMD borders. If available, data <lb/>from the breast cancer cell line (MCF7) and mammary epithelial cells (HMEC) was used, <lb/>otherwise data from fibroblasts (IMR90, Tig3) was used. (E), Gene distribution inside PMDs (as <lb/>a fraction of all annotated genes). (F), Gene expression inside PMDs. Gene expression (top) and <lb/>standard deviation (bottom) was plotted as a function of PMD frequency. (G), Somatic mutations <lb/>inside PMDs. Substitutions, insertions, deletions, and rearrangements were calculated for each of <lb/>the 560 fully sequenced breast cancer genomes 14 , and plotted as a function of PMD frequency. <lb/>(H), Distribution of DNA methylation over functional genomic elements, inside and outside <lb/>PMDs. CpGs were classified according PMD status and genomic elements, and the distribution <lb/>of DNA methylation within each element was plotted. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3 | CpG island hypermethylation inside PMDs. <lb/>(A), Example of a genomic region with CGI hypermethylation inside PMDs. Red bars, PMDs for <lb/>each tumor sample; below, CGI methylation for each tumor sample (same ordering). Green bars, <lb/>CGIs. (B), Distribution of CGI methylation, represented as the fraction of all CGIs (x-axis). Each <lb/>horizontal bar represents one tumor sample. (C), Average profile of methylation over all CGIs <lb/>inside (red) or outside (black) PMDs, over all 30 tumor samples. Black/red lines, median; <lb/>grey/pink area, 1st and 3rd quartiles. (D), Regression analysis of B-CIMP (y-axis) as a function <lb/>of the fraction CGIs inside PMDs (x-axis). B-CIMP is defined as the genome-wide fraction of <lb/>hypermethylated CGIs (&gt;30% methylation). (E), Variation of CGI methylation (standard <lb/>deviation) as a function of PMD frequency. (F), Summary of regression analysis as in (D), <lb/>including additional cancer types. n, the number of samples for each type. For abbreviations of <lb/>cancer type names, see Fig. 4C. (G), Expression change of CGI-promoter genes inside vs. <lb/>outside of PMDs, as a function of PMD frequency. (H), Gene expression levels as a function of <lb/>PMD frequency in an independent breast cancer dataset (TCGA). PMD frequency for each gene <lb/>was taken from our own dataset. (I), Expression change of CGI-promoter genes of tumor vs. <lb/>normal, as a function of PMD frequency. From the TCGA breast cancer dataset, matched <lb/>tumor/normal pairs were selected. PMD frequency for each gene was taken from our own dataset. <lb/>(J), Tumor-suppressor genes (TSGs) are excluded from PMDs. For each TSG its PMD <lb/>frequency was determined and the resulting distribution was plotted. Main plot, relative <lb/>distribution; inset, absolute number of genes. &apos;Non-TSGs&apos;, genes not annotated as TSGs; &apos;TSGs <lb/>all cancers&apos;, genes annotated as TSGs regardless of cancer type; &apos;TSGs breast cancer&apos;, genes <lb/>annotated as TSG in breast cancer; &apos;Nik-Zainal breast cancer driver mutations&apos;, genes with driver <lb/>mutations in breast cancer 14 . <lb/>Figure 4 | PMD methylation in normal tissues and tumors of various tissues. <lb/>(A), PMDs are detectable in virtually all tumors, but only in a fraction of normal tissues. WGBS <lb/>data was used for PMD detection. (B), Mean PMD methylation of normal tissues and tumors of <lb/>various tissues. Each dot represents one sample. Arrows represent breast tumor samples from <lb/>this study. (C), Hierarchical clustering of tumor samples based on genomic distribution of their <lb/>PMDs. <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental Figure 1 <lb/>(A), CpG coverage in WGBS DNA methylation profiles of 30 breast tumor samples used in this <lb/>study (see also Suppl. Table 1). (B), Clinicopathological features of the 30 tumor samples. (C), <lb/>Mean copy-number profiles of 25/30 tumor samples used in this study. Copy-number data was <lb/>taken from our previous work 14 . (D), Association between mean PMD methylation and <lb/>expression of genes involved in writing, erasing, or reading the 5-methylcytosine modification. <lb/>Each dot represents one tumor sample. Linear regression was used to determine the variation <lb/>explained (R 2 ) and the p-value of the association. Expression data was taken from our previous <lb/>work 16 . <lb/>Supplemental Figure 2 <lb/>Visualization of inter-tumor variation at genome-wide scale, as in main Figure 1, but including <lb/>WGBS data from 72 additional, non-tumor tissues (Roadmap Epigenomics Project and ref. 10 ). <lb/>(A), Genome-wide and (B), chromosome-wide maps. Mean methylation is displayed in <lb/>consecutive tiles of 10 kb (see Methods). For breast tumors of this study, the ER-status is <lb/>indicated at the right (A). <lb/>Supplemental Figure 3 <lb/>(A), Gene coding density plotted as a function of PMD frequency. (B), Gene expression as a <lb/>function of PMD frequency, as in main Figure 2F, but here restricted to the 24 cases overlapping <lb/>between our WGBS cohort and the breast tumor (RNA-seq) transcriptomes cohort 16 . Top, gene <lb/>expression; bottom, standard deviation. (C), Somatic mutations plotted as a function of PMD <lb/>frequency, as in main Figure 2G, but here restricted to the 25 cases overlapping between our <lb/>WGBS cohort and the breast tumor full genomes cohort 14 . <lb/>Supplemental Figure 4 <lb/>(A), Expression change of non-CGI-promoter genes inside vs. outside of PMDs, as a function of <lb/>PMD frequency. (B), Expression change of non-CGI-promoter genes of tumor vs. normal, as a <lb/>function of PMD frequency. From the TCGA breast cancer dataset, matched tumor/normal pairs <lb/>were selected. PMD frequency for each gene was taken from our own dataset. (C), Number of <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">CGIs inside and outside of breast cancer PMDs. CGIs are classified as &apos;in&apos; when inside a PMD <lb/>in at least one tumor sample. <lb/>Supplemental Figure 5 <lb/>(A), Expression change of TSGs/breast cancer driver mutated genes when inside PMDs. 31 of <lb/>such genes are located inside PMDs in a subset of tumor samples. &apos;TSGs all cancers&apos;, genes <lb/>annotated as TSGs regardless of cancer type; &apos;TSGs breast cancer&apos;, genes annotated as TSG in <lb/>breast cancer; &apos;Nik-Zainal breast cancer driver mutations&apos;, genes with driver mutations in breast <lb/>cancer 14 . (B), Examples of genes from panel (A) being repressed when inside PMDs. Blue line, <lb/>DNA methylation (WGBS); green bars, CGIs; red bars, PMDs. Gene expression (RNA-seq) of <lb/>the corresponding gene is represented at the right of each panel. (C), Pearson correlation between <lb/>CGI-promoter methylation and expression. Gene classes are indicated as in panel (A). (D), <lb/>Expression changes (RNA-seq) of genes in panel (B), breast tumor vs. normal. Data is from an <lb/>independent cohort (TCGA). Left panels, non-matched normal (n=88) and tumor samples <lb/>(n=769); right panels, matched normal/tumor samples (n=86). p-values were calculated using a t-<lb/>test. <lb/>Supplemental Figure 6 <lb/>(A), Gene set enrichment analysis (GSEA) of genes downregulated when inside PMDs (&gt;2.5 <lb/>log2-fold, 400 genes, Suppl. Table 3). (B), Examples of downregulated genes inside PMDs. <lb/>CD3D encodes the gamma polypeptide of the T-cell receptor-CD3 complex (gene sets <lb/>&apos;signalling&apos;, &apos;adhesion&apos;, and &apos;breast cancer luminal B down&apos;); RBP4 encodes retinol binding <lb/>protein 4 (gene set &apos;signalling&apos;, and &apos;breast cancer luminal B down&apos;). Blue line, DNA <lb/>methylation (WGBS); green bars, CGIs; red bars, PMDs. Gene expression (RNA-seq) of the <lb/>corresponding gene is represented at the right of each panel. (C), Overall survival of patient <lb/>groups stratified according expression of the 400 PMD-downregulated genes (see Methods). <lb/>Supplemental Figure 7 <lb/>(A), Boxplot summarizing mean PMD methylation of normal tissues and tumors of various <lb/>tissues (summary of Fig. 4B). (B), Distribution of CGI methylation, represented as the fraction of <lb/>all CGIs (x-axis). Each horizontal bar represents one tumor sample (WGBS). Top panel, tumor <lb/>20 <lb/>samples other than breast cancer (TCGA and ref. 29 , abbreviations are given below); bottom panel, <lb/>repeated from main Figure 3B for comparison. <lb/>Supplemental Table 1 <lb/>Quality metrics and global methylation values from whole-genome bisulfite sequencing (WGBS) <lb/>of 30 breast tumor samples from this study. <lb/>Supplemental Table 2 <lb/>PMD frequency of all annotated CpG islands (. For each CGI, PMD frequency indicates the <lb/>number of tumors in which the CGI is inside a detected PMD. <lb/>Supplemental Table 3 <lb/>Genes that are downregulated when inside PMDs. 400 genes are downregulated at least 2.5 log2-<lb/>fold. <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Feinberg, A. P. &amp; Vogelstein, B. Hypomethylation distinguishes genes of some human <lb/>cancers from their normal counterparts. Nature 301, 89-92 (1983). <lb/>2. Lister, R. et al. Human DNA methylomes at base resolution show widespread epigenomic <lb/>differences. Nature 462, 315-322 (2009). <lb/>3. Berman, B. P. et al. Regions of focal DNA hypermethylation and long-range hypomethylation <lb/>in colorectal cancer coincide with nuclear lamina-associated domains. Nature genetics 44, 40-6 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>4. Hansen, K. D. et al. Increased methylation variation in epigenetic domains across cancer types. <lb/>Nature Genetics 43, 768-775 (2011). <lb/>5. Hon, G. C. G. et al. Global DNA hypomethylation coupled to repressive chromatin domain <lb/>formation and gene silencing in breast cancer. Genome research 22, 246-258 (2012). <lb/>6. Hovestadt, V. et al. Decoding the regulatory landscape of medulloblastoma using DNA <lb/>methylation sequencing. Nature 510, 537-41 (2014). <lb/>7. Schroeder, D. I., Lott, P., Korf, I. &amp; LaSalle, J. M. Large-scale methylation domains mark a <lb/>functional subset of neuronally expressed genes. Genome Research 21, 1583-1591 (2011). <lb/>8. Timp, W. &amp; Feinberg, A. P. Cancer as a dysregulated epigenome allowing cellular growth <lb/>advantage at the expense of the host. Nature reviews. Cancer 13, 497-510 (2013). <lb/>9. Schroeder, D. I. et al. The human placenta methylome. Proceedings of the National Academy <lb/>of Sciences of the United States of America 110, 6037-42 (2013). <lb/>10. Schultz, M. D. et al. Human body epigenome maps reveal noncanonical DNA methylation <lb/>variation. Nature 523, 212-6 (2015). <lb/>11. Kulis, M. et al. Whole-genome fingerprint of the DNA methylome during human B cell <lb/>differentiation. Nature genetics 47, 746-756 (2015). <lb/>12. Lister, R. et al. Hotspots of aberrant epigenomic reprogramming in human induced <lb/>pluripotent stem cells. Nature 471, 68-73 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13. Lister, R. et al. Global epigenomic reconfiguration during mammalian brain development. <lb/>Science (New York, N.Y.) 341, 1237905 (2013). <lb/>14. Nik-Zainal, S. et al. Landscape of somatic mutations in 560 breast cancer whole-genome <lb/>sequences. Nature 534, 1-20 (2016). <lb/>15. Morganella, S. et al. The topography of mutational processes in breast cancer genomes. <lb/>Nature Communications 7, 11383 (2016). <lb/>16. Smid, M. et al. Breast cancer genome and transcriptome integration implicates specific <lb/>mutational signatures with immune cell infiltration. Nature Communications 7, 12910 (2016). <lb/>17. Guelen, L. et al. Domain organization of human chromosomes revealed by mapping of <lb/>nuclear lamina interactions. Nature 453, 948-951 (2008). <lb/>18. Hansen, R. S. et al. Sequencing newly replicated DNA reveals widespread plasticity in <lb/>human replication timing. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States <lb/>of America 107, 139-144 (2010). <lb/>19. Rao, S. S. S. P. et al. A 3D Map of the Human Genome at Kilobase Resolution Reveals <lb/>Principles of Chromatin Looping. Cell 159, 1665-1680 (2014). <lb/>20. Sexton, T. &amp; Cavalli, G. The Role of Chromosome Domains in Shaping the Functional <lb/>Genome. Cell 160, 1049-1059 (2015). <lb/>21. Dixon, J. R. et al. Topological domains in mammalian genomes identified by analysis of <lb/>chromatin interactions. Nature 485, 376-80 (2012). <lb/>22. Hou, C., Li, L., Qin, Z. S. &amp; Corces, V. G. Gene Density, Transcription, and Insulators <lb/>Contribute to the Partition of the Drosophila Genome into Physical Domains. Molecular Cell 48, <lb/>471-484 (2012). <lb/>23. Roukos, V. &amp; Misteli, T. The biogenesis of chromosome translocations. Nature cell biology <lb/>16, 293-300 (2014). <lb/>24. Lieberman-aiden, E. et al. Comprehensive Mapping of Long-Range Interactions Reveals <lb/>Folding Principles of the Human Genome. Science 326, 289-293 (2009). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>25. Toyota, M. et al. CpG island methylator phenotype in colorectal cancer. Medical Sciences 96, <lb/>8681-8686 (1999). <lb/>26. Fang, F. et al. Breast Cancer Methylomes Establish an Epigenomic Foundation for <lb/>Metastasis. Science Translational Medicine 3, 75ra25 (2011). <lb/>27. Conway, K. et al. DNA methylation profiling in the Carolina Breast Cancer Study defines <lb/>cancer subclasses differing in clinicopathologic characteristics and survival. Breast Cancer <lb/>Research 16, 450 (2014). <lb/>28. Roessler, J. et al. The CpG island methylator phenotype in breast cancer is associated with <lb/>the lobular subtype. Epigenomics 7, 1-13 (2014). <lb/>29. Kretzmer, H. et al. DNA methylome analysis in Burkitt and follicular lymphomas identifies <lb/>differentially methylated regions linked to somatic mutation and transcriptional control. Nature <lb/>genetics 47, 1316-25 (2015). <lb/>30. Noushmehr, H. et al. Identification of a CpG island methylator phenotype that defines a <lb/>distinct subgroup of glioma. Cancer Cell 17, 510-522 (2010). <lb/>31. Smid, M. et al. Subtypes of breast cancer show preferential site of relapse. Cancer Research <lb/>68, 3108-3114 (2008). <lb/>32. Schuster-Böckler, B. &amp; Lehner, B. Chromatin organization is a major influence on regional <lb/>mutation rates in human cancer cells. Nature 488, 504-7 (2012). <lb/>33. Supek, F. &amp; Lehner, B. Differential DNA mismatch repair underlies mutation rate variation <lb/>across the human genome. Nature 521, 81-84 (2015). <lb/>34. Polak, P. et al. Cell-of-origin chromatin organization shapes the mutational landscape of <lb/>cancer. Nature 518, 360-4 (2015). <lb/>35. Koboldt, D. C. et al. Comprehensive molecular portraits of human breast tumours. Nature <lb/>490, 61-70 (2012). <lb/>36. Collisson, E. A. et al. Comprehensive molecular profiling of lung adenocarcinoma. Nature <lb/>511, 543-550 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>37. Abeshouse, A. et al. The Molecular Taxonomy of Primary Prostate Cancer. Cell 163, 1011-<lb/>1025 (2015). <lb/>38. Holm, K. et al. An integrated genomics analysis of epigenetic subtypes in human breast <lb/>tumors links DNA methylation patterns to chromatin states in normal mammary cells. Breast <lb/>Cancer Research 18, (2016). <lb/>39. Johann, P. D. et al. Atypical Teratoid/Rhabdoid Tumors Are Comprised of Three Epigenetic <lb/>Subgroups with Distinct Enhancer Landscapes. Cancer Cell 29, 379-393 (2016). <lb/>40. Burk, R. D. et al. Integrated genomic and molecular characterization of cervical cancer. <lb/>Nature 543, 378-384 (2017). <lb/>41. Robertson, A. G. et al. Comprehensive Molecular Characterization of Muscle-Invasive <lb/>Bladder Cancer. Cell 171, 540-556 (2017). <lb/>42. Raphael, B. J. et al. Integrated Genomic Characterization of Pancreatic Ductal <lb/>Adenocarcinoma. Cancer Cell 32, 185-203.e13 (2017). <lb/>43. Ally, A. et al. Comprehensive and Integrative Genomic Characterization of Hepatocellular <lb/>Carcinoma. Cell 169, 1327-1341 (2017). <lb/>44. Habibi, E. et al. Whole-Genome Bisulfite Sequencing of Two Distinct Interconvertible DNA <lb/>Methylomes of Mouse Embryonic Stem Cells. 13, 360-369 (2013). <lb/>45. Le, S., Josse, J. &amp; Husson, F. FactoMineR: An R Package for Multivariate Analysis. J. of <lb/>Statistical Software 25, 1-18 (2008). <lb/>46. Burger, L., Gaidatzis, D., Schübeler, D. &amp; Stadler, M. B. Identification of active regulatory <lb/>regions from DNA methylation data. Nucleic Acids Research 41, (2013). <lb/>47. Schultz, M. D., Schmitz, R. J. &amp; Ecker, J. R. &apos;Leveling&apos; the playing field for analyses of <lb/>single-base resolution DNA methylomes. Trends in Genetics 28, 583-585 (2012). <lb/>48. Cribari-Neto, F. &amp; Zeileis, A. Beta Regression in R. Journal of Statistical Software 34, 1-24 <lb/>(2010). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>breast tumors <lb/>ATM <lb/>EXPH5 <lb/>RDX <lb/>RDX <lb/>RDX <lb/>NPAT <lb/>C11orf65 <lb/>DDX10 <lb/>EXPH5 <lb/>ZC3H12C <lb/>C11orf65 <lb/>KDELC2 <lb/>C11orf87 <lb/>CGI <lb/>100 kb <lb/>chr11 <lb/>chr10 <lb/>100 kb <lb/>NPS <lb/>FAM196A <lb/>MKI67 <lb/>DOCK1 <lb/>PTPRE <lb/>PTPRE <lb/>PTPRE <lb/>MGMT <lb/>MKI67 <lb/>CLRN3 <lb/>FOXI2 <lb/>LINC01163 <lb/>AS−PTPRE <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>breast tumors <lb/>breast tumors <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>centromere <lb/>centromere <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>methylation <lb/>chr1 <lb/>chr2 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>chr4 <lb/>chr5 <lb/>chr6 <lb/>chr7 <lb/>chr8 <lb/>chr9 <lb/>chr10 <lb/>chr11 <lb/>chr12 <lb/>chr13 <lb/>chr14 <lb/>chr15 <lb/>chr16 <lb/>chr17 <lb/>chr18 <lb/>chr19 <lb/>chr20 <lb/>chr21 <lb/>chr22 <lb/>chrX <lb/>D <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD7219a <lb/>PD4965a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD4608a <lb/>PD14439a <lb/>PD5937a <lb/>PD10010a <lb/>PD6684a <lb/>PD8979a <lb/>PD11750a <lb/>PD4970a <lb/>PD8619a <lb/>PD11372a <lb/>PD11379a <lb/>PD11339a <lb/>PD13619a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD11382a <lb/>PD11394a <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>PD11377a <lb/>PD11390a <lb/>PD7218a <lb/>PD4982a <lb/>PD7215a <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD4981a <lb/>−600 <lb/>−400 <lb/>−200 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>−500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>PC1 (19% of variance) <lb/>PC2 (13% of variance) <lb/>ER-<lb/>ER+ <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>mean PMD <lb/>methylation <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>repliSeq MCF7 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>−50 <lb/>−25 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>distance to PMD border (kb) <lb/>signal <lb/>(z−score) <lb/>LaminB1 Tig3 <lb/>HMEC loops <lb/>IMR90 loops <lb/>HMEC CTCF <lb/>MCF7 CTCF <lb/>repliSeq IMR90 <lb/>3 <lb/>repliSeq <lb/>early <lb/>late <lb/>D <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>0 5 10 15 20 25 30 <lb/>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 <lb/>(number of tumors) <lb/>fraction of genome <lb/>covered by common PMDs <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>fraction of genome <lb/>covered by PMDs <lb/>tumors <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>18 <lb/>19 <lb/>20 <lb/>21 <lb/>22 <lb/>23 <lb/>24 <lb/>25 <lb/>26 <lb/>27 <lb/>28 <lb/>29 <lb/>30 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>#genomic tiles (30 kb) <lb/>with PMD boundaries <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>PMDs <lb/>shuffled PMDs <lb/>(x1000) <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>methylation <lb/>p r o m <lb/>o t e r s <lb/>C <lb/>G <lb/>I <lb/>C <lb/>G <lb/>I <lb/>s h o r e s <lb/>H <lb/>M <lb/>E C <lb/>e n h a n c e r s <lb/>g e n e <lb/>b o d i e s <lb/>i n t e r g e n i c <lb/>inside PMDs <lb/>outside PMDs <lb/>p r o m <lb/>o t e r s <lb/>C <lb/>G <lb/>I <lb/>C <lb/>G <lb/>I <lb/>s h o r e s <lb/>H <lb/>M <lb/>E C <lb/>e n h a n c e r s <lb/>g e n e <lb/>b o d i e s <lb/>i n t e r g e n i c <lb/>H <lb/>E <lb/>G <lb/>mean expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>−10 <lb/>−5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 4 <lb/>2 5 − <lb/>2 7 <lb/>2 8 − <lb/>3 0 <lb/>mean StDev <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>mean subst / Mb <lb/>substitutions <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.050 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>mean ins / Mb <lb/>0.100 <lb/>deletions <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>mean del / Mb <lb/>0.20 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 4 <lb/>2 5 − <lb/>2 7 <lb/>2 8 − <lb/>3 0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>mean breakponts / Mb <lb/>0.4 <lb/>insertions <lb/>rearrangements <lb/>gene fraction <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>F <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 4 <lb/>2 5 − <lb/>2 7 <lb/>2 8 − <lb/> 3 0 <lb/> Figure 3 <lb/>C <lb/>breast tumors <lb/>0.4 -0.6 <lb/>CGIs inside PMDs <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 0.50 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>proportion <lb/>CGIs outside PMDs <lb/>CGI methylation <lb/>0.0 -0.2 <lb/>0.2 -0.4 <lb/>0.6 -0.8 <lb/>0.8 -1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 0.50 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>A <lb/>GNRH1 <lb/>NEFM <lb/>NKX2−6 <lb/>ADAMDEC1 <lb/>ADAM28 <lb/>CDCA2 <lb/>DOCK5 <lb/>STC1 <lb/>ADAM7 <lb/>NEFL <lb/>KCTD9 <lb/>DOCK5 <lb/>NKX3−1 <lb/>MIR6841 <lb/>MIR6876 <lb/>LOC101929294 <lb/>LOC101929315 <lb/>ADAM28 <lb/>1 <lb/>30 <lb/>1 <lb/>30 <lb/>PMDs <lb/>genes <lb/>DNAme <lb/>CGI <lb/>chr8:23,233,438-25,343,262 <lb/>100 kb <lb/>tumors <lb/>tumors <lb/>B <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>StDev <lb/>CGI methylation <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 4 <lb/>2 5 − <lb/>2 7 <lb/>2 8 − <lb/>3 0 <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>fraction CGIs in PMDs <lb/>B-CIMP <lb/>R 2 = 0.51 <lb/>p = 2.1e−08 <lb/>fraction <lb/>methylated CGIs (≥0.3) <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>D <lb/>F <lb/>E <lb/>J <lb/>G <lb/>log2 fold change <lb/>tumor/normal <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>TCGA normal/tumor matched (n=86) <lb/>−4 −3 −2 −1 0 <lb/>+4 <lb/>+3 <lb/>+2 <lb/>+1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>distance to CGI (kb) <lb/>methylation <lb/>inside PMDs <lb/>outside PMDs <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>BL (n=13) <lb/>BLCA (n=6) <lb/>FL (n=6) <lb/>GBM (n=6) <lb/>LUAD (n=6) <lb/>LUSC (n=5) <lb/>READ (n=3) <lb/>STAD (n=5) <lb/>UCEC <lb/>(n=5) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>R 2 (variation explained) <lb/>-log10 p-value <lb/>• <lb/>breast (n=30) <lb/>(this study) <lb/>−4 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>log2 fold change <lb/>in/out PMDs <lb/>I <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>CGI-promoter genes <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>CGI-promoter genes <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>mean expression <lb/>(log2) <lb/>TCGA normals (n=88) <lb/>TCGA tumors (n=769) <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>H <lb/>0.00 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>gene fraction <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>non-TSGs <lb/>TSGs all cancers <lb/>TSGs breast cancer <lb/>Nik-Zainal breast cancer driver mutations <lb/>14,037 <lb/>27 <lb/>218 <lb/>86 <lb/>0 <lb/>16 <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>#genes <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>breast <lb/>READ <lb/>COAD <lb/>GBM <lb/>LUAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>BL <lb/>UCEC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>FL <lb/>breast cancer (this study) <lb/>rectum adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>colon adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>glioblastoma multiforme (TCGA) <lb/>lung adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>stomach adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma (Kretzmer et al.) <lb/>uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>lung squamous cell carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>follicular lymphoma (Kretzmer et al.) <lb/>BLCA <lb/>bladder urothelial carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>primary tissue <lb/>cultured primary cells <lb/>tumor <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>this study <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• • <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• • <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BL <lb/>BLCA <lb/>BLCA <lb/>BLCA <lb/>BLCA <lb/>BLCA <lb/>BLCA <lb/>COAD <lb/>COAD <lb/>brain <lb/>brain <lb/>skin <lb/>vascular <lb/>liver <lb/>brain <lb/>brain <lb/>esophagus <lb/>stomach <lb/>heart <lb/>lung <lb/>ovary <lb/>pancreas <lb/>muscle <lb/>heart <lb/>heart <lb/>colon <lb/>intestine <lb/>spleen <lb/>FL <lb/>FL <lb/>FL <lb/>FL <lb/>FL <lb/>FL <lb/>GBM <lb/>GBM <lb/>GBM <lb/>GBM <lb/>GBM <lb/>GBM <lb/>germinal center B <lb/>HMEC <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUAD <lb/>LUSC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>breast <lb/>READ <lb/>READ <lb/>READ <lb/>STAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>UCEC <lb/>UCEC <lb/>UCEC <lb/>UCEC <lb/>UCEC <lb/>germinal center B <lb/>germinal center B <lb/>germinal center B <lb/>mean PMD methylation <lb/>t u m <lb/>o r s <lb/>n o r m <lb/>a l s <lb/>fraction of samples <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>PMDs <lb/>not detected <lb/>detected <lb/>n = 89 77 <lb/>B <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Figure 1 <lb/> Whole-genome bisulfite sequencing <lb/>30 cases <lb/>ER / PR / HER2 status <lb/>ER status <lb/>B <lb/>CpG coverage (fold) <lb/>0 20 40 60 80 <lb/>P D <lb/>4 6 0 8 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 6 2 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 6 5 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 6 7 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 7 0 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 8 1 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 8 2 a <lb/>P D <lb/>4 9 8 5 a <lb/>P D <lb/>5 9 3 7 a <lb/>P D <lb/>6 6 8 4 a <lb/>P D <lb/>7 2 1 5 a <lb/>P D <lb/>7 2 1 6 a <lb/>P D <lb/>7 2 1 8 a <lb/>P D <lb/>7 2 1 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>8 6 1 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>8 9 7 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>9 7 5 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 0 0 1 0 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 0 0 1 4 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 3 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 6 5 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 7 2 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 7 7 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 7 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 8 2 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 9 0 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 3 9 4 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 1 7 5 0 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 3 6 1 9 a <lb/>P D <lb/>1 4 4 3 9 a <lb/> A <lb/> chr1 <lb/>chr2 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>chr4 <lb/>chr5 <lb/>chr6 <lb/>chr7 <lb/>chr8 <lb/>chr9 <lb/>chr10 <lb/>chr11 <lb/>chr12 <lb/>chr13 <lb/>chr14 <lb/>chr15 <lb/>chr16 <lb/>chr17 <lb/>chr18 <lb/>chr19 <lb/>chr20 <lb/>chr21 <lb/>chr22 <lb/>chrX <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>mean CN (25 WGBS-tumors) <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>2.0 3.0 4.0 5.0 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0 <lb/>p = 0.91 <lb/>MBD4 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.02 <lb/>p = 0.49 <lb/>MECP2 <lb/>−6 <lb/>−2 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.06 <lb/>p = 0.26 <lb/>MBD3 <lb/>1.5 2.5 3.5 4.5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.03 <lb/>p = 0.45 <lb/>MBD1 <lb/>1.5 2.5 3.5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.01 <lb/>p = 0.61 <lb/>MBD2 <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0 <lb/>p = 0.91 <lb/>UHRF2 <lb/>−3 −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.07 <lb/>p = 0.22 <lb/>UHRF1 <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>1 2 3 4 5 6 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.08 <lb/>p = 0.21 <lb/>IDH2 <lb/>1 2 3 4 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.06 <lb/>p = 0.26 <lb/>TET3 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.12 <lb/>p = 0.12 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>1.0 2.0 3.0 4.0 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.21 <lb/>p = 0.034 <lb/>TET2 <lb/>−4 −2 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.01 <lb/>p = 0.67 <lb/>TET1 <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.17 <lb/>p = 0.055 <lb/>DNMT3A <lb/>−6 −5 −4 −3 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0 <lb/>p = 0.93 <lb/>DNMT3L <lb/>2 3 4 5 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.01 <lb/>p = 0.62 <lb/>DNMT1 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−1 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>R 2 = 0.17 <lb/>p = 0.06 <lb/>DNMT3B <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>mean PMD methylation <lb/>mean PMD methylation <lb/>mean PMD methylation <lb/>mean PMD methylation <lb/>ER− (5) <lb/>ER+ (25) <lb/>ER− PR− HER2− (4) <lb/>ER− PR+ HER2− (1) <lb/>ER+ PR− HER2− (2) <lb/>ER+ PR+ HER2− (22) <lb/>ER+ PR+ HER2+ (1) <lb/>Supplemetary Figure 2 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>methylation <lb/>chr1 <lb/>chr2 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>chr4 <lb/>chr5 <lb/>chr6 <lb/>chr7 <lb/>chr8 <lb/>chr9 <lb/>chr10 <lb/>chr11 <lb/>chr12 <lb/>chr13 <lb/>chr14 <lb/>chr15 <lb/>chr16 <lb/>chr17 <lb/>chr18 <lb/>chr19 <lb/>chr20 <lb/>chr21 <lb/>chr22 <lb/>chrX <lb/>intestine 1 <lb/>intestine <lb/>brain 9 <lb/>brain 2 <lb/>ESC derived 5 <lb/>ESC derived 3 <lb/>ESC derived 4 <lb/>ESC 5 <lb/>iPSC 3 <lb/>iPSC 4 <lb/>ESC 1 <lb/>ESC 7 <lb/>ESC derived 7 <lb/>ESC 6 <lb/>ESC derived 6 <lb/>ESC derived <lb/>blood 18 <lb/>brain 1 <lb/>brain <lb/>ovary <lb/>ovary 2 <lb/>lung 2 <lb/>lung 3 <lb/>psoas 2 <lb/>adrenal 2 <lb/>fat 2 <lb/>spleen 2 <lb/>oesophagus 2 <lb/>gastric 2 <lb/>liver <lb/>liver 11 <lb/>pancreas 1 <lb/>pancreas 3 <lb/>fat 1 <lb/>pancreas 2 <lb/>adrenal 3 <lb/>spleen <lb/>spleen 3 <lb/>small bowel 2 <lb/>small bowel 3 <lb/>sigmoid colon 3 <lb/>colon 1 <lb/>intestine 2 <lb/>lung 1 <lb/>spleen 1 <lb/>thymus <lb/>thymus 1 <lb/>psoas 1 <lb/>muscle 1 <lb/>psoas 3 <lb/>skin 5 <lb/>oesophagus 3 <lb/>bladder 1 <lb/>stomach 3 <lb/>gastric 3 <lb/>small bowel 1 <lb/>sigmoid colon 1 <lb/>fat 3 <lb/>gastric 1 <lb/>aorta 2 <lb/>vascular <lb/>aorta 3 <lb/>ESC derived 8 <lb/>left ventricle 1 <lb/>right ventricle 1 <lb/>heart 1 <lb/>heart 2 <lb/>heart 3 <lb/>right atrium 3 <lb/>left ventricle 3 <lb/>right ventricle 3 <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD7219a <lb/>PD4965a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD4608a <lb/>PD14439a <lb/>PD5937a <lb/>PD10010a <lb/>PD6684a <lb/>PD8979a <lb/>PD11750a <lb/>PD4970a <lb/>PD8619a <lb/>PD11372a <lb/>PD11379a <lb/>PD11339a <lb/>PD13619a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD11382a <lb/>PD11394a <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>PD11377a <lb/>PD11390a <lb/>PD7218a <lb/>PD4982a <lb/>PD7215a <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD4981a <lb/>oesophagus <lb/>chr11 <lb/>chr10 <lb/>centromere <lb/>centromere <lb/>intestine 1 <lb/>intestine <lb/>brain 9 <lb/>brain 2 <lb/>ESC derived 5 <lb/>ESC derived 3 <lb/>ESC derived 4 <lb/>ESC 5 <lb/>iPSC 3 <lb/>iPSC 4 <lb/>ESC 1 <lb/>ESC 7 <lb/>ESC derived 7 <lb/>ESC 6 <lb/>ESC derived 6 <lb/>ESC derived <lb/>blood 18 <lb/>brain 1 <lb/>brain <lb/>ovary <lb/>ovary 2 <lb/>lung 2 <lb/>lung 3 <lb/>psoas 2 <lb/>adrenal 2 <lb/>fat 2 <lb/>spleen 2 <lb/>oesophagus 2 <lb/>gastric 2 <lb/>liver <lb/>liver 11 <lb/>pancreas 1 <lb/>pancreas 3 <lb/>fat 1 <lb/>pancreas 2 <lb/>adrenal 3 <lb/>spleen <lb/>spleen 3 <lb/>small bowel 2 <lb/>small bowel 3 <lb/>sigmoid colon 3 <lb/>colon 1 <lb/>intestine 2 <lb/>lung 1 <lb/>spleen 1 <lb/>thymus <lb/>thymus 1 <lb/>psoas 1 <lb/>muscle 1 <lb/>psoas 3 <lb/>skin 5 <lb/>oesophagus 3 <lb/>bladder 1 <lb/>stomach 3 <lb/>gastric 3 <lb/>small bowel 1 <lb/>sigmoid colon 1 <lb/>fat 3 <lb/>gastric 1 <lb/>aorta 2 <lb/>vascular <lb/>aorta 3 <lb/>ESC derived 8 <lb/>left ventricle 1 <lb/>right ventricle 1 <lb/>heart 1 <lb/>heart 2 <lb/>heart 3 <lb/>right atrium 3 <lb/>left ventricle 3 <lb/>right ventricle 3 <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD7219a <lb/>PD4965a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD4608a <lb/>PD14439a <lb/>PD5937a <lb/>PD10010a <lb/>PD6684a <lb/>PD8979a <lb/>PD11750a <lb/>PD4970a <lb/>PD8619a <lb/>PD11372a <lb/>PD11379a <lb/>PD11339a <lb/>PD13619a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD11382a <lb/>PD11394a <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>PD11377a <lb/>PD11390a <lb/>PD7218a <lb/>PD4982a <lb/>PD7215a <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD4981a <lb/>oesophagus <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>ER <lb/> Supplementary Figure 3 <lb/> 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>mean subst / Mb <lb/>substitutions <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.050 <lb/>0.075 <lb/>insertions <lb/>mean ins / Mb <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>mean del / Mb <lb/>deletions <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>gene coding density <lb/>(bp coding/bp genomic) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 4 <lb/>2 5 − <lb/>2 7 <lb/>2 8 − <lb/>3 0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 5 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>mean breakpoints / Mb <lb/>rearrangements <lb/>−10 <lb/>−5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>mean expression <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 − <lb/>3 <lb/>4 − <lb/>6 <lb/>7 − <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 − <lb/>1 2 <lb/>1 3 − <lb/>1 5 <lb/>1 6 − <lb/>1 8 <lb/>1 9 − <lb/>2 1 <lb/>2 2 − <lb/>2 5 <lb/>mean StDev <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>
			3 <lb/> 
			Supplementary Figure 4 <lb/> −4 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>log2 fold change <lb/>in/out PMDs <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 2 5 -2 7 2 8 -3 0 <lb/>non-CGI-promoter genes <lb/>A <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>log2 fold change <lb/>tumor/normal <lb/>PMD frequency <lb/>0 <lb/>1 -3 <lb/>4 -6 <lb/>7 -9 <lb/>1 0 -1 2 <lb/>1 3 -1 5 <lb/>1 6 -1 8 <lb/>1 9 -2 1 <lb/>2 2 -2 4 <lb/>2 5 -2 7 <lb/>2 8 -3 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>-1 <lb/>TCGA normal/tumor matched (n=86) <lb/>non-CGI-promoter genes <lb/>B <lb/>0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>in out <lb/>PMDs <lb/>#CpG islands <lb/>C <lb/>Supplementary Figure 5 <lb/>A <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>F A T 1 <lb/>E G <lb/>F R <lb/>G <lb/>R <lb/>IN <lb/>2 A <lb/>P T P R <lb/>C <lb/>P R <lb/>E X 2 <lb/>W <lb/>T 1 <lb/>E B F 1 <lb/>IK <lb/>Z F 1 <lb/>A T P 2 B 3 <lb/>P R <lb/>F 1 <lb/>P D <lb/>G <lb/>F R <lb/>A <lb/>S F R <lb/>P 4 <lb/>E L F 4 <lb/>B C <lb/>O <lb/>R <lb/>L 1 <lb/>F O <lb/>X L 2 <lb/>G <lb/>P C <lb/>3 <lb/>G <lb/>A T A 1 <lb/>M <lb/>E D <lb/>1 2 <lb/>F O <lb/>X O <lb/>4 <lb/>R <lb/>B M <lb/>1 0 <lb/>A T R <lb/>X <lb/>S T A G <lb/>2 IR <lb/>F 4 <lb/>R <lb/>P L 1 0 <lb/>P H <lb/>F 6 <lb/>R U <lb/>N <lb/>X 1 T 1 B T K <lb/>R <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>B C <lb/>L 9 L <lb/>S L C <lb/>3 4 A 2 <lb/>A P O <lb/>B E C <lb/>3 B <lb/>Nik-Zainal breast cancer driver mutations <lb/>TSGs all cancers <lb/>TSGs breast cancer <lb/>mean fold change <lb/>in/out PMDs (log2) <lb/>normal tumor <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>FPKM (log2) <lb/>p = 1e−53 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>−4 <lb/>−2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>fold change <lb/>tumor/normal (log2) <lb/>p = 4.1e−23 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>normal tumor <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>FPKM (log2) <lb/>p = 2e−29 <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>fold change <lb/>tumor/normal (log2) <lb/>p = 8.8e−14 <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>normal tumor <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>FPKM (log2) <lb/>p = 1.9e−36 <lb/>EBF1 <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>fold change <lb/>tumor/normal (log2) <lb/>p = 1.1e−22 <lb/>EBF1 <lb/>normal tumor <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>FPKM (log2) <lb/>p = 1.2e−10 <lb/>GRIN2A <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>fold change <lb/>tumor/normal (log2) <lb/>p = 3.4e−07 <lb/>GRIN2A <lb/>normal tumor <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>FPKM (log2) <lb/>p = 2.1e−42 <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>−4 <lb/>−3 <lb/>−2 <lb/>−1 <lb/>0 <lb/>fold change <lb/>tumor/normal (log2) <lb/>p = 5.9e−20 <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>FAT1 expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD5937a <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD7215a <lb/>F11 <lb/>KLKB1 <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>MTNR1A <lb/>F11−AS1 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>EBF1 expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>RNF145 <lb/>EBF1 <lb/>LINC02202 <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD6684a <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>PDGFRA expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>CHIC2 <lb/>GSX2 <lb/>RPL21P44 <lb/>LINC02283 <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD14439a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>15 <lb/>EGFR expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>VOPP1 <lb/>VOPP1 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>EGFR <lb/>SEC61G <lb/>LANCL2 <lb/>VSTM2A <lb/>EGFR <lb/>EGFR <lb/>VSTM2A−OT1 <lb/>EGFR−AS1 <lb/>LOC100996654 <lb/>ELDR <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD4982a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD11750a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD7215a <lb/>0 <lb/>B <lb/>normal/tumor <lb/>matched pairs <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>GRIN2A expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>GRIN2A <lb/>ATF7IP2 <lb/>EMP2 <lb/>C16orf72 <lb/>LINC01195 <lb/>LINC01177 <lb/>LINC02177 <lb/>LINC01290 <lb/>PD11750a <lb/>PD9759a <lb/>PD10010a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD11390a <lb/>PD8979a <lb/>normal/tumor <lb/>matched pairs <lb/>normal/tumor <lb/>matched pairs <lb/>normal/tumor <lb/>matched pairs <lb/>normal/tumor <lb/>matched pairs <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>(TCGA) <lb/>D <lb/>• <lb/>• • • <lb/>• • • <lb/>• • • • • • • • • • • • • • <lb/>• • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • • <lb/>• • • • • • • • <lb/>• • • • • <lb/>• • • <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>EGFR <lb/>BCORL1 <lb/>GRIN2A <lb/>RBM10 <lb/>MED12 <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>BCOR <lb/>GPC3 <lb/>IRF4 <lb/>EBF1 <lb/>FOXO4 <lb/>IKZF1 STAG2 <lb/>FAT4 <lb/>RPL10 <lb/>FOXO4 <lb/>PREX2 <lb/>IKZF1 <lb/>ELF4 <lb/>BCL9L <lb/>ATRX <lb/>PHF6 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>correlation <lb/>CGI-promoter meth. vs. expression <lb/>(Pearson <lb/>R) <lb/>Nik-Zainal breast cancer <lb/>driver mutations <lb/>TSGs all cancers <lb/>C <lb/>note: APOBEC3B has no CGI <lb/>non-TSGs <lb/>• <lb/>Supplementary Figure 6 <lb/>A <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>biological adhesion <lb/>system process <lb/>extracellular space <lb/>FDR (-log10) <lb/>breast cancer luminal B down (Smid et al.) <lb/>breast cancer basal up (Smid et al.) <lb/>signalling <lb/>PD4970a <lb/>PD10014a <lb/>PD7216a <lb/>PD14439a <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>CD3G expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PD4981a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>CD3G <lb/>CD3D <lb/>CD3E <lb/>UBE4A <lb/>ATP5L <lb/>LOC100131626 <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>RBP4 expr. <lb/>(log2 FPKM) <lb/>PMDs <lb/>CGI <lb/>RBP4 <lb/>FRA10AC1 <lb/>PDE6C <lb/>CEP55 <lb/>FFAR4 <lb/>PD4962a <lb/>PD4967a <lb/>PD11365a <lb/>PD11390a <lb/>PD4985a <lb/>PD6684a <lb/>B <lb/>p = 2.6e-03 <lb/>expression high <lb/>expression low <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1.0 <lb/>overall survival (years) <lb/>survival probability <lb/>C <lb/>Supplementary Figure 7 <lb/>UCEC_5 <lb/>UCEC_4 <lb/>UCEC_3 <lb/>UCEC_2 <lb/>UCEC_1 <lb/>STAD_5 <lb/>STAD_4 <lb/>STAD_3 <lb/>STAD_2 <lb/>STAD_1 <lb/>READ_3 <lb/>READ_2 <lb/>READ_1 <lb/>LUSC_5 <lb/>LUSC_4 <lb/>LUSC_3 <lb/>LUSC_2 <lb/>LUSC_1 <lb/>LUAD_6 <lb/>LUAD_5 <lb/>LUAD_4 <lb/>LUAD_3 <lb/>LUAD_2 <lb/>LUAD_1 <lb/>GBM_6 <lb/>GBM_5 <lb/>GBM_4 <lb/>GBM_3 <lb/>GBM_2 <lb/>GBM_1 <lb/>FL_6 <lb/>FL_5 <lb/>FL_4 <lb/>FL_3 <lb/>FL_2 <lb/>FL_1 <lb/>COAD_2 <lb/>COAD_1 <lb/>BLCA_6 <lb/>BLCA_5 <lb/>BLCA_4 <lb/>BLCA_3 <lb/>BLCA_2 <lb/>BLCA_1 <lb/>BL_13 <lb/>BL_12 <lb/>BL_11 <lb/>BL_10 <lb/>BL_9 <lb/>BL_8 <lb/>BL_7 <lb/>BL_6 <lb/>BL_5 <lb/>BL_4 <lb/>BL_3 <lb/>BL_2 <lb/>BL_1 <lb/>tumor <lb/>breast tumors (this study) <lb/>0.4 -0.6 <lb/>CGIs inside PMDs <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 0.50 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>proportion <lb/>CGIs outside PMDs <lb/>CGI methylation <lb/>0.0 -0.2 <lb/>0.2 -0.4 <lb/>0.6 -0.8 <lb/>0.8 -1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 0.50 0.75 <lb/>1 <lb/>READ <lb/>COAD <lb/>GBM <lb/>LUAD <lb/>STAD <lb/>BL <lb/>UCEC <lb/>LUSC <lb/>FL <lb/>rectum adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>colon adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>glioblastoma multiforme (TCGA) <lb/>lung adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>stomach adenocarcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>Burkitt&apos;s lymphoma (Kretzmer et al.) <lb/>uterine corpus endometrial carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>lung squamous cell carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>follicular lymphoma (Kretzmer et al.) <lb/>BLCA bladder urothelial carcinoma (TCGA) <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>Normal <lb/>Tumor <lb/>0.55 0.65 0.75 0.85 <lb/>mean PMD meth <lb/>p = 1.0e-18 </div>


	</text>
</tei>
