<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Title (20 words, currently 11) <lb/>MicroRNA-196a is regulated by ER and is a prognostic biomarker in ER+ Breast <lb/>Cancer <lb/>Michael J.G. Milevskiy 1,2 # , Udai Gujral 1 , Carolina Del Lama Marques 1 , Andrew Stone 3 , <lb/>Korinne Northwood 1,4 , Lez J. Burke 1 , Julia M.W. Gee 5 , Kenneth Nephew 6 , Susan Clark 3 , <lb/>Melissa A. Brown 1 . <lb/>*shared first <lb/># Corresponding author <lb/>1. School of Chemistry and Molecular Biosciences, University of Queensland, St Lucia, <lb/>Queensland, Australia. <lb/>2. Present Address: ACRF Stem Cells and Cancer, The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of <lb/>Medical Research, Parkville, Victoria Australia <lb/>3. Epigenetics Research Laboratory, Division of Genomics and Epigenetics, Garvan Institute <lb/>of Medical Research, Sydney, NSW <lb/>4. The University of Queensland, UQ Centre for Clinical Research, Herston, Australia <lb/>5. School of Pharmacy &amp; Pharmaceutical Sciences, Cardiff University, Cardiff, UK, <lb/>6. Indiana University, School of Medicine, Bloomington, IN, USA <lb/># Correspondence should be addressed to MJG Milevskiy, ACRF Stem Cells and Cancer, <lb/>The Walter and Eliza Hall Institute of Medical Research, 1G Royal Parade, Parkville, <lb/>Victoria, 3052, <lb/>E-mail: milevskiy.m@wehi.edu.au <lb/>Telephone #: +61 3 9345 2546 <lb/>Full-length papers should be no more than 5,000 words, reduced appropriately to allow for up <lb/>to six figures or tables, and should be supported by key references. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract (193 words) <lb/>MicroRNAs are potent post-transcriptional regulators involved in all hallmarks of cancer. <lb/>Mir-196a is transcribed from two loci and has been implicated in a wide range of <lb/>developmental and pathogenic processes, with targets including Hox, Fox, Cdk inhibitors and <lb/>annexins. Genetic variants and altered expression of miR196a are associated with risk and <lb/>progression of multiple cancers including breast cancer, however little is known about the <lb/>regulation of the genes encoding this miRNA, nor the impact of variants therein. Here we <lb/>demonstrate that MIR196A displays complex and dynamic expression patterns, in part <lb/>controlled by long range transcriptional regulation between promoter and enhancer elements <lb/>bound by ERα. Expression of this miRNA is significantly increased in models of hormone <lb/>receptor positive disease resistance. The expression of MIR196A also proves to be a robust <lb/>prognostic factor for patients with advanced and post-menopausal ER+ disease. This work <lb/>sheds light on the normal and abnormal regulation of MIR196A and provides a novel <lb/>stratification method for therapeutically resistant breast cancer. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>MicroRNAs are short non-coding RNAs that post-transcriptionally regulate gene expression <lb/>(1). MicroRNAs have been implicated in many disease, ranging from rare inherited <lb/>syndromes arising from germline mutations in MiRNA genes through cancers arising from an <lb/>accumulation of germline and somatic mutations and epigenetic deregulation (2). Research <lb/>into the biology and pathology of these molecules has led to the identification of clinically <lb/>useful genetic and epigenetic biomarkers and novel therapeutic agents, often based on <lb/>antagomiR technology, that have shown promise in the control of disease symptoms and <lb/>progression (3). <lb/>MicroRNA-196A (miR-196a, MIR196A) is transcribed in two genomic locations, the HOXC <lb/>(Chr12 in humans, gene MIR196A2) and HOXB (Chr17 in humans, gene MIR196A1) loci, <lb/>downstream of HOXC10 and upstream of HOXB9 respectively. It has been strongly <lb/>implicated in a range of cancers, primarily as an oncogene. For example, MIR196A is <lb/>overexpressed in breast tumours (4), and a single nucleotide polymorphism (SNP, <lb/>rs116149130) within the MIR196A2 gene is associated with a decreased risk of breast cancer <lb/>(5). MIR196A has been shown to target the 3&apos; UTR of Annexin-1 (ANXA1), an important <lb/>mediator of apoptosis in various pathways (6), in response to the pro-angiogenic vascular <lb/>endothelium growth factor (VEGF), leading to alterations in angiogenesis. A separate study <lb/>demonstrated that MIR196A could increase growth, migration and invasion of a non-small <lb/>cell lung cancer cell line through direct targeting of HOXA5 (7). Two studies have recently <lb/>shown that MIR196A can directly influence the cell cycle by targeting p27/Kip1, an inhibitor <lb/>of cell cycle progression, to dramatically increase growth and pro-oncogenic features of <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>cancer cell lines (8, 9). Despite the clear importance on miR-196a in cancer, its <lb/>transcriptional regulation remains poorly understood. <lb/>Transcriptional regulation is a complex multi-faceted biological process that is significantly <lb/>altered in cancer. MicroRNA genes are regulated transcriptionally in a similar manner to <lb/>protein coding and long non-coding RNA genes. Promoters mostly lie upstream (within 10kb <lb/>of the mature miRNA), contain a CpG island and in an active state when the miRNAs are <lb/>transcribed by RNA Pol II are enriched for H3K4me3 and lack H3K27me3 similar to protein <lb/>coding genes (10, 11). Taken together, these data indicate that potential promoters for <lb/>miRNAs can be identified in a similar manner to methods for protein coding genes. Several <lb/>instances of miRNA regulation by enhancers have been described, but this area is very much <lb/>in its infancy (12, 13). <lb/>In this study, we aimed to characterise the expression landscape of MIR196A including <lb/>factors regulating its expression and explore potential roles of regulatory elements and factors <lb/>in breast cancer prognostication. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>MIR196A expression correlates with HOXC genes in breast cancer <lb/>Several HOXC protein coding and non-coding genes have shown associations with breast <lb/>cancer progression. We first identified expression patterns of HOXC genes in breast cancers <lb/>(Supp Figure 1). These data indicate that MIR196A expression highly correlates to HOXC <lb/>genes, particularly HOXC10. <lb/>Next we investigated whether these associations are also observed in normal cells of the <lb/>human breast. The association between MIR196A expression and HOXC genes is more <lb/>limited, observed most strongly with HOXC11 and HOXC10, the genes surrounding the <lb/>MIR196A gene (Supp Figure 2A). MIR196A appears to be mostly expressed within the basal <lb/>stem-cell (BSC) derived cells, whilst much lower in expression of the more differentiated cell <lb/>types (Supp Figure 2B). <lb/>MIR196A expression is regulated by oestrogen <lb/>We and others have previously demonstrated regulation of HOXC genes by oestrogen in <lb/>breast cancer (14-18). Given that MIR196A expression strongly correlates with expression of <lb/>HOXC protein coding genes in breast cancer (Supp Figure 1), we sought to determine if <lb/>oestrogen also regulates MIR196A2. Chromatin immunoprecipitation (ChIP-Seq) for RNA <lb/>polymerase II demonstrates that polymerase binding in the region surrounding the HOXC10 <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>gene and MIR196A gene is dependent on oestrogen in MCF7 cells and is repressed with both <lb/>tamoxifen or fulvestrant treatment (Figure 1A). Global-run-on sequencing (GRO-Seq) is able <lb/>to measure nascent RNA, assessing changes in transcription with high sensitivity. Analysis of <lb/>MCF7 GRO-Seq data clearly indicates a dramatic increase in RNA production in the <lb/>genomic region surrounding MIR196A2, peaking at 40 mins following addition of oestradiol <lb/>(E2) (Figure 1B). This increase in RNA production from the HOXC locus was validated with <lb/>qRT-PCR and RNA-Seq from MCF7 cells following addition of E2 (Figures 1C and D). <lb/>These data clearly indicate an increase in precursor miRNA from MIR196A2 but not <lb/>MIR196A1 in response to E2. Taken together this suggests that MIR196A2 is transcriptionally <lb/>regulated by oestrogen. <lb/>Transcriptional regulation of miR196A <lb/>To identify the structural elements associated with the transcriptional regulation of MIR196A, <lb/>histone methylation patterns in the MCF7 breast cancer cell line were assessed. This analysis <lb/>uncovered putative promoter elements upstream of MIR196A including a shared promoter <lb/>with HOXC10 (Figure 1A). <lb/>Given that MIR196A expression is regulated by oestrogen we hypothesized that its <lb/>transcription may be controlled by the oestrogen receptor (ER). Using publically available <lb/>datasets we established that oestrogen mediated upregulation of miR-196A expression is <lb/>accompanied by binding of ERα and its pioneer factor FOXA1 to two putative promoter <lb/>regions, putative promoters 1 and 3 (PP1 and PP3), upstream of the miR196A2 transcription <lb/>start site (Figure 1B). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Upon cloning of these putative promoter sites into luciferase reporter vectors where PP1 and <lb/>also PP2; modestly; increases luciferase gene transcription (Figure 1E), with the most active <lb/>promoter in MCF7 cells, PP1 (HOXC10 promoter). <lb/>Given that ERα often binds to distal enhancer elements to exert its function, we examined the <lb/>hypothesis that MIR196A2 is controlled by long-range transcriptional regulation, mediated by <lb/>ERα tethered gene looping. Using ChIA-PET (Chromatin Interact Analysis by Paired End <lb/>Tags) genome-wide chromatin interactions that immunoprecipitate with either ERα or RNA <lb/>Polymerase II (correlative with active promoters and enhancers), we identified two major <lb/>sites of interaction with the MIR196A2 promoters (Figure 2A). One of these is a previously <lb/>identified HOTAIR enhancer (HOTAIR distal enhancer, HDE (15)) and the other a novel <lb/>interacting partner (MIR196A2-Enhancer, mE). Chromosome conformation capture (3C) <lb/>digestion of the HOXC genomic locus digests the MIR196A2 region into two fragments. 3C-<lb/>qPCR demonstrates that both enhancer elements physically interact with each of the two <lb/>MIR196A2/HOXC10 promoter region (Figure 2B). Cloning of these fragments downstream <lb/>of the putative promoter luciferase reporters clearly demonstrates significant augmentation of <lb/>transcription for both the PP1 and PP2, with HDE appearing to be the most active in MCF7 <lb/>cells (Figure 2C). <lb/>Interestingly, a previous study (5) identified a SNP and an upstream CpG island associated <lb/>with a decrease in breast cancer risk. This SNP lies within the MIR196A2 gene and the CpG <lb/>island (CpG_Hoffman) is immediately upstream, falling into the 3&apos; end of the PP3. Analysis <lb/>of DNA methylation reveals that this CpG island is mostly methylated in non-malignant <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>MCF10A and cancerous MCF7 cells, whilst unmethylated in human mammary epithelial <lb/>cells (HMEC) (Figure 1A). <lb/>MIR196A is differentially expressed in breast cancer <lb/>Given that MIR196A is regulated by ERα, we investigated its expression patterns in relation <lb/>to commonly utilised molecular markers of breast tumours (Figure 3A). This analysis <lb/>identified four distinct clusters of MIR196A expression (Clusters 1-4). Interestingly clusters 1 <lb/>and 3 show a strong correlation to expression of hormone receptors (HR) (AR, ERα, PGR, <lb/>HER2) and HR cofactors (Figure 3B). In contrast, clusters 2 and 4 have significant negative <lb/>correlation to expression of ERα, PGR, FOXA1 and GATA3, whilst associating with EGFR <lb/>and HER2. This expression is further defined by the PAM50 intrinsic subtypes where <lb/>MIR196A is strongly expressed in the HER2 subtype, whist in the luminal A and B subtypes <lb/>expression is very dynamic (Figure 3C). <lb/>MIR196A is a biomarker of breast cancer progression <lb/>To further explore the expression of MIR196A in breast cancer, we utilised expression data <lb/>from the METABRIC cohort of breast tumours. Expression analysis of this miRNA indicate <lb/>that it is significantly over-expressed in breast tumours compared to normal adjacent tissue <lb/>and over-expression is associated with an increase in tumour stage (Figure 4A and 4B). <lb/>Interestingly, high expression of MIR196A is associated with a poor survival in estrogen <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>receptor positive (ER+) breast cancer, whilst high expression associates with a better <lb/>outcome in triple-negative breast cancer (TNBC) (Figure 4C and D). <lb/>MIR196A is a prognostic biomarker in advanced ER+ disease <lb/>Using MIR196A expression, overall survival of ER+ tumours responding to both hormone <lb/>therapy (HT) and chemotherapy (CT) was stratified (Figure 5A). Women with low MIR196A <lb/>expression had exhibited a high rate of survival (&gt;95% at 10 years), whilst most women <lb/>within the high expression group died within 17 years (61% at 10 years). <lb/>Given that MIR196A is regulated in part by oestrogen, and the disparity in prognostication of <lb/>ER+ and TNBC, we investigated the effects of menopause on the stratification of survival for <lb/>ER+ women. The effects of menopause on the human breast are largely unknown, however <lb/>serum levels of oestrogen and progesterone dramatically reduce post menopause. In pre-<lb/>menopausal women, high expression of MIR196A is associated with a good outcome in ER+ <lb/>disease (Table 1). Multivariate analysis demonstrates that MIR196A is one of the few <lb/>significant biomarkers for ER+ tumours arising before menopause. In post-menopausal <lb/>women, all tested biomarkers were significant in ER+ disease, including MIR196A, however <lb/>high expression is now associated with a poor outcome. <lb/>Therapeutic resistance leads to increases in MIR196A expression <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>TNBC is resistant to hormone-based therapies and HR+ disease often becomes resistant to <lb/>anti-oestrogen treatment. Using established models of HR+ disease resistance we found that <lb/>MIR196A expression is significantly increased in tamoxifen resistant MCF7 cells (TAMR) <lb/>whilst it is almost depleted in fulvestrant resistance (FASR) (Figure 5B). These expression <lb/>patterns match changes in DNA methylation to the HOXC10/MIR196A2 promoters in these <lb/>same cells (Figure 5C). For HR+ resistant tumours the only remaining therapeutic options are <lb/>radiotherapy and chemotherapy. Using RNA-Seq data for cell line models of resistance to <lb/>paclitaxel and adromycin, two common chemotherapeutics, MIR196A expression again <lb/>increases in resistant cell lines compared to the treatment sensitive cell line (Figure 5D). <lb/>Utilising ERα ChIP-Seq performed in human patients with HR+ disease, binding sites for <lb/>ERα were identified in the genomic region of MIR196A. This tumour cohort contains women <lb/>who respond to HR therapy, those who do not and metastases from resistant tumours. An <lb/>increase in ERα occupancy is seen at both enhancer and promoter regions of MIR196A in <lb/>non-responders and metastases (Figure 5E). The increased genome-wide ERα binding in the <lb/>more resistant tumours was shown by the authors to associate with changes to expression <lb/>patterns crucial for the resistant tumour to survive therapy and become resistant. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>The expression of MIR196A in breast cancer is both dynamic and complex. In this paper, we <lb/>have elucidated important elements, factors and mechanisms controlling the transcriptional <lb/>regulation of MIR196A and shown that changes in this regulation are associated with breast <lb/>cancer progression and therapeutic resistance. <lb/>Previous genetic association studies have shown that SNPs within MIR196A2 confer a <lb/>reduced risk of breast cancer (5, 19, 20). Hoffman and colleagues (5) postulated that the <lb/>polymorphism located within the MIR196A2 gene reduces microRNA maturation thereby <lb/>reducing expression of the gene. They also identified that an upstream CpG island is <lb/>associated with reduced risk when hypermethylated. Here we show that this upstream CpG <lb/>island lies within the transcriptionally active region of HOXC10 and MIR196A2 as observed <lb/>through GRO-Seq. Interestingly, this CpG island is completely methylated in models of <lb/>oestrogen deprivation and fulvestrant treatment, but not in tamoxifen resistant cells. DNA <lb/>methylation is most commonly associated with repressed transcription (21), <lb/>hypermethylation of this region in a transcriptional high region may severely impair <lb/>expression. Given that various transcription factors strongly influence transcription in <lb/>endocrine resistant breast cancer, these data suggest that binding of ERα accompanied by <lb/>cofactors may be needed to maintain low methylation levels and active transcription in breast <lb/>cancer (22-26). <lb/>We have previously demonstrated that long-range regulation of HOXC genes occurs in breast <lb/>cancer and is influenced by ERα and its associated cofactors (15). HOX gene expression is <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>tightly controlled in a spatiotemporal manner to ensure proper axial formation along the <lb/>anterior-posterior axis (27). Within the cell types of the human breast, HOX gene expression <lb/>appears dynamic and the association between MIR196A and HOXC genes is not significant. <lb/>The strong correlation in expression of all HOXC genes in breast tumours with MIR196A is in <lb/>stark contrast to expression in normal tissues. Several instances have been described <lb/>regarding the influence of multiple distal enhancers on gene expression, such as the well <lb/>characterised locus-control-region (LCR) of the Beta-globin genes or the c-Myc enhancers <lb/>active across multiple cancer types (28-31). Given the extensive interactions between this <lb/>locus and its adjacent gene desert, we hypothesise that a consorted effort of multiple <lb/>enhancers is responsible for the overexpression of these genes in cancer possibly driven by <lb/>extensive binding and activity of ERα. To explore this hypothesis a high resolution <lb/>chromatin interaction analysis of this region in breast cancer cells would be required, such as <lb/>5C (32) or NG Capture-C (33), coupled with ERα ChIP-Seq and ChIA-PET (34). <lb/>Whilst this manuscript was in preparation new data has come to light which corroborates our <lb/>conclusions. Jiang et al (35) demonstrate that the mature MIR196A transcript positively <lb/>responds to oestrogen stimulation in MCF7 cells, and this is mediated by upstream ERα <lb/>binding. This binding peak falls within PP3. Whilst we show that PP3 is not able to increase <lb/>luciferase expression in a luciferase reporter assay, the binding of ERα may be important for <lb/>the activity of the HOXC10 and MIR196A2 promoters. <lb/>Using hierarchical clustering of breast tumour RNA-Seq data, we observed two distinct <lb/>expression patterns associated with MIR196A expression. Data presented here suggests that <lb/>the two loci encoding for this miRNA contribute greatly to the complexity of its expression. <lb/>It is currently unclear how dual-encoded miRs are regulated of which many exist (36). <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Interestingly, DNA methylation at several sites within the HOXC locus negatively correlates <lb/>with the expression of this miRNA, supporting the notion of DNA methylation as a <lb/>repressive epigenetic modification in this context (21). <lb/>High expression of MIR196A is a biomarker of poor prognosis in ER+ tumours, especially in <lb/>those patients resistant to therapy. Expression of MIR196A increases in response to tamoxifen <lb/>and chemotherapeutic agents in oestrogen responsive MCF7 cells. This increase in <lb/>expression is associated with loss of DNA methylation within the promoter regions of the <lb/>miRNA. In poor responders with ER+ tumours, HOXC enhancer elements appear to more <lb/>readily bind the ER. These data raise the possibility that the pathway to resistance to therapy <lb/>in ER+ tumours involves the de-repression and over-activation of promoter and enhancer <lb/>elements. This is commonly seen throughout cancer (37-39), with suggestions that enhancer <lb/>disruption can revert cells to a non-terminally-differentiated state a common hallmark of <lb/>tumourigenesis. HOX genes are essential in embryonic development, these genes would be a <lb/>valuable asset for any tumour cell to use to sustain a stem-cell like state (40, 41). <lb/>Breast cancer incidence and relative subtype changes after menopause (42, 43). In women <lb/>younger than 45, luminal breast tumours account for 33-44% (44, 45). This increases to 70-<lb/>72% in women older than 65. In contrast, basal-like tumours are more common in younger <lb/>women, suggesting a switch or evolution in the factors driving cancer following menopause, <lb/>most likely related to the decline in oestrogen production. It is then interesting to note that <lb/>higher expression of MIR196A associates with good outcome in pre-menopausal women with <lb/>ER+ tumours, and a poor outcome of ER+ tumours following menopause. Given the strong <lb/>involvement of HOX genes in development, we hypothesise that there is a change in the <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>regulation and expression of these genes through and following menopause, which in turn <lb/>impacts their contribution to the development of certain breast cancer subtypes. <lb/>MIR196A is a dynamically expressed miRNA in both normal mammary cells and breast <lb/>tumours. This miRNA is a possible biomarker for the progression of breast tumour to <lb/>becoming resistant to therapy. Future studies should aim to uncover the purpose of increase <lb/>MIR196A expression and if it is required for development of resistance alone or in <lb/>combination with other HOXC genes. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Material and Methods <lb/>Cell Culture <lb/>MCF7 cells, for the development of endocrine resistance sub-lines were obtained from <lb/>AstraZeneca. MCF7, Tamoxifen-resistant (TAMR), Fulvestrant-resistant (FASR), and <lb/>oestrogen-deprived (MCF7x) cells were cultured as described (46-48). All cell lines were <lb/>cultured for less than 6 months after authentication by short-tandem repeat (STR) profiling <lb/>(Cell Bank, Australia). <lb/>Cloning and reporter assays <lb/>All PCR products for luciferase reporter assays were ligated into Invitrogen&apos;s pCR-Blunt <lb/>plasmid using T4 DNA Ligase, at 4 0 C overnight. MIR196A enhancers and promoters were <lb/>digested from pCR-Blunt and cloned into the luciferase reporter plasmid pGL3-Basic. <lb/>Enhancers were cloned into the BamHI/SalI site whilst promoters were cloned into the <lb/>multiple cloning site immediately upstream of the luciferase gene. See Supplementary Table1 <lb/>for primers. <lb/>MCF7 cells were transfected in antibiotic free media with 500 ng of modified pGL3 reporter <lb/>constructs, 20 ng of pRL-TK (Renilla transfection control) and with 0.5μL of Lipofectamine <lb/>3000 (Life Technologies, L3000-008). 48 hours post transfection luciferase readings were <lb/>measured using a DTX-880 luminometer and Dual-Glo Stop and Glo luciferase reporter kit <lb/>(Promega, E2920), following the manufacturer&apos;s recommended protocol. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>RNA extraction and Gene Expression <lb/>Cell lysates were prepared using Life Technologies TRIzol® reagent and RNA was <lb/>chloroform extracted and isopropanol precipitated. RNA was DNaseI treated with the DNA <lb/>free kit from Ambion (Life Technologies, AM1906). RNA for miRNA analysis was reverse <lb/>transcribed using the miScript RT II kit from Qiagen (218161), following instructions as per <lb/>the manufacturer. Assays for all miRNAs were performed with Qiagen&apos;s miScript SYBR <lb/>Green PCR Kit (218073). Primers specific to each mature or precursor miRNA were assayed <lb/>coupled with a universal primer, see Supplementary Table 2 for assay IDs. Expression data <lb/>for miRNAs was normalised to the snoRNA RNU6b. All qRT-PCRs were performed using <lb/>the protocols advised by the manufacturers on a Corbet Rotorgene-6000. <lb/>RNA-Seq on MCF7 cells following oestradiol treatment was performed as described <lb/>previously by K. Nephew (see author list) (49). RNA-Seq from Adriamycin (ADM) and <lb/>paclitaxel (PTX) resistant MCF7 derived cells was sourced from GSE68815 (50). Expression <lb/>of HOX genes in human breast cells was sourced from Gascard et al (51). <lb/>Genomic Data Analysis <lb/>Accession codes for publically available data were, MCF7 ChIP-Seq (GSE14664, (52)), <lb/>GRO-Seq (GSE27463, (53)), ChIA-PET (GSE39495, (34, 54)), Breast tumour ERα ChIP-<lb/>Seq (GSE32222, (55)). MCF7 histone ChIP-Seq and breast cell 450K array data was sourced <lb/>from ENCODE via http://genome.ucsc.edu/ENCODE/downloads.html. ChIP-Seq data was <lb/>mapped with Bowtie (56) and peaks called by MACS (57) and viewed in the Interactive <lb/>Genome Viewer (IGV) (58) available through the Broad Institute servers. DNA methylation <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>450K array data for MCF7 and endocrine resistant sublines was previously published, see <lb/>Stone et al (59). DNA methylation of breast tumours was sourced from The Cancer Genome <lb/>Atlas (TCGA) (60) and correlated to the gene expression of MIR196A from the TCGA <lb/>cohort. <lb/>Breast Tumour Expression Analysis <lb/>METABRIC expression and clinical information were sourced from EGAS00000083 (61, <lb/>62). Clustering of Illumina Array and miR-Seq data was performed using the Multiple <lb/>Experiment Viewer (MeV, (63)). Data was mean-centred and hierarchically clustered via <lb/>Manhattan average-linkage based clustering of both rows and columns. Genes were <lb/>correlated within clusters using the CORREL function of Microsoft Excel. <lb/>Survival Analysis <lb/>Univariate and multivariate Cox proportional hazard regression analyses were performed <lb/>using MedCalc for Windows, version 12.7 (MedCalc Software, Ostend, Belgium). Kaplan-<lb/>Meier survival analysis and generation of survival curves was done GraphPad Prism. Optimal <lb/>cutoffs for low and high expression groups were determined using receiver operator <lb/>characteristic (ROC) curves. <lb/>3C and ChIA-PET <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Chromosome conformation capture (3C) was adapted from Vakoc 2005 (29), Hagege 2007 <lb/>(64) and Tan-Wong 2008 (65). Briefly, cells were grown to 60-80% confluence and fixed <lb/>with 1% formaldehyde. Libraries were generated for each cell line using HindIII with control <lb/>libraries undigested and unligated, representing native gDNA without chromosome <lb/>conformation. GAPDH primers (amplified fragment contains no cut sites for these enzymes) <lb/>were used to determine the digestion and ligation efficiency of each library by comparing 3C-<lb/>qPCR values to primers that amplify a fragment containing a HindIII cut site. For each 3C-<lb/>qPCR, primers were designed between 100-250 bp up or downstream of each HindIII cut site <lb/>with the primer across the putative enhancer used as bait in each 3C-qPC. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This study makes use of data generated by the Molecular Taxonomy of Breast Cancer <lb/>International Consortium. Funding for the project was provided by Cancer Research UK and <lb/>the British Columbia Cancer Agency Branch (61, 62). <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure Legends <lb/>Figure 1. E2 influences MIR196A2 expression in breast cancer. A) Identification of <lb/>putative promoter regions for the MIR196A2 gene using histone markers and ChIP-Seq <lb/>indicated in figure (E2 = oestradiol, Tam = 4-hydroxytamoxifen, Fulv = Fulvestrant). Refseq <lb/>genes are indicated in blue at the top with coordinates based on hg19 chromosome 12. <lb/>Putative promoter regions (PP1,2,3) and the previously implicated SNP (rs116149130) and <lb/>CpG from Hoffman et al (5) are indicated by black rectangles. MCF7 DNA methylation <lb/>450K array data indicate unmethylated (black), partial methylation (blue) and methylated <lb/>(red). B) GRO-Seq measurements of RNA Polymerase engagement and elongation points <lb/>from the putative promoters, after E2 stimulation in MCF7 cells. Lower part, ChIP-Seq for <lb/>binding of ERα and FOXA1 to the putative promoters. C) qRT-PCR the MIR196A2 response <lb/>to E2 in MCF7 cells. Qiagen precursor primers were used to detect the precursor miRNA at <lb/>the specified time points and CT values were normalised to a DMSO vehicle control and the <lb/>qPCR control of RNU6b. D) MiRNA-Seq reads per kilobase per million (RPKM) for the <lb/>precursor miRNAs following E2 addition to MCF7 cells. E) Luciferase reporter assay <lb/>measuring the influence of MIR196A2 putative promoter on the luciferase gene transcription. <lb/>Measurements are relative light units (RLU) normalised to the renilla plasmid (pRL-TK) <lb/>acting as a transfection control and to the pGL3/Empty plasmid. Experimental measures are <lb/>done in triplicate with the experiment repeated, data not shown. <lb/>Figure 2. Distal putative enhancer elements of the MIR196A2 putative promoters. A) <lb/>Histone modification and ChIA-PET for ESR1 and RNA Pol II in MCF7 cells of the HOXC <lb/>locus and corresponding gene desert. The histone modification H3K27ac is a measure of <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>regulatory element activity and was assessed in HMEC and MCF7 cells plus or minus E2. <lb/>ChIA-PET interactions are represented by red lines, solid rectangles indicate the sequenced <lb/>tag and the two points that were physically interacting and tethered to either ESR1 or RNA <lb/>Pol II. B) Zoom in of the MIR196A2 enhancer (mE) and HOTAIR distal enhancer (HDE) <lb/>(left) and the putative promoter elements (right). Black rectangles indicate the genome <lb/>fragment sizes post digestion with HindIII. Graph is 3C-qPCR for either the 3C PP1 or 3C <lb/>PP2-3 fragments with the Y-axis the relative interaction and the X-axis the genomic location. <lb/>All genomic coordinates were based on chromosome 12 in the hg19. C) Luciferase reporter <lb/>assay showing the augmentation of HOXC promoters with either mE or HDE, shown a RLU <lb/>normalised to the co-transfected control renilla plasmid and to the vector backbone pGL3-<lb/>Basic. <lb/>Figure 3. MIR196A is differentially expressed in breast cancer. A) Mean-centred log2-<lb/>expression of MIR196A and commonly utilised breast cancer molecular markers. Expression <lb/>values were hierarchically clustered and the PAM50 tumour subtypes are indicated above the <lb/>plot. Expression values are indicated by colour scale bar. B) Pearson correlation coefficients, <lb/>and corresponding P-values, for each gene against the expression of MIR196A either in the <lb/>orange or purple clusters. C) Intensity values for the expression of MIR196A across the five <lb/>molecular subtypes, PAM50. All data was sourced by the METABRIC cohort (61, 62). <lb/>Figure 4. MIR196A is a biomarker of breast cancer progression. A) Log2 miR-Array <lb/>intensity for the expression of MIR196A in normal adjacent tissue and breast tumours. A T <lb/>test was used to find statistical significance with **** = a p value of &lt; 0.0001. B) Log2 <lb/>intensity for the expression of MIR196A in normal adjacent and tumour stages 0 to 4. A One-<lb/>Way ANOVA was used to find a significant trend with a p-value = &lt; 0.0001. C and D) <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Kaplan-Meier curves stratifying overall survival of breast tumours by expression of <lb/>MIR196A. Log-rank p-value (P) and hazard ratios (HR) displayed. All expression data <lb/>sourced from METABRIC (61, 62). <lb/>Figure 5. Therapeutic resistance leads to increase in MIR196A expression. A) qRT-PCR <lb/>relative expression for the mature and precursor MIR196A transcripts in MCF7 derived cell <lb/>line models of endocrine therapy resistance. miRNA expression values are normalised to the <lb/>expression of RNU6b and the MCF7 cell line. Error bars are the standard deviation of two <lb/>technical replicates and four biological replicates. MCF7-C = Control, MCF7-X = Oestrogen <lb/>deprived, TAMR =Tamoxifen resistant and FASR =Fulvestrant resistant. B) Corresponding <lb/>DNA methylation for MCF7 derived cell lines, as measured by 450K methylation array, for <lb/>the MIR196A2 genomic region. C) Log2 reads-per-kilobase-per-million (RPKM) expression <lb/>of MIR196A in MCF7 wild-type and adriamycin (ADM, aka Doxorubicin) and paclitaxel <lb/>(PTX) derived resistance cell lines. D) Peak scores for the binding of ERα to MIR196A2 <lb/>regulatory elements in ER+ breast tumours. Peak scores were generated using MACS, <lb/>normalised to the Input control for the ChIP-Seq library. Peak scores are the average for 9 <lb/>responders, 9 non-responders and 3 metastases. Data is sourced from Ross-Innes et al (55). <lb/>E) Kaplan-Meier survival curves for patients with ER+ disease, treated with both <lb/>chemotherapy (CT) and hormone therapy (HT). Patient survival is stratified by expression of <lb/>MIR196A into low or high expression subgroups. Expression and survival data sourced from <lb/>METABRIC (61, 62). <lb/>Table 1. Menopause effects the stratification of patient survival by MIR196A in ER+ <lb/>disease. The overall survival of patients with ER+ disease was stratified by MIR196A, HER2, <lb/>PGR expression or commonly utilised clinical markers. On the left is the univariatie cox-<lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>proportional hazard ratios for each condition, and the right the multivariate cox-proportional <lb/>hazard model and the conditions which contribute to the most significant model. HR = <lb/>Hazard ratio, CI = Confidence interval. Expression and survival data sourced from <lb/>METABRIC (61, 62). <lb/>Supp Figure 1. MIR196A expression correlates with HOXC genes in breast cancer. <lb/>Hierarchically clustered normalised expression for HOXC genes across breast tumours. <lb/>Pearson correlation coefficients to MIR196A expression are indicated on the right-hand side. <lb/>Supp Figure 2. MIR196A is highly expressed in breast stem cells. A) Heatmap, Manhattan <lb/>hierarchically clustered demonstrating expression data for HOX genes in human breast cells. <lb/>Data is reads per million (RPM) for miRNAs and reads per million per kilobase (RPKM) for <lb/>mRNAs. Data is log2 normalised and mean centred by row. Right, Pearson correlation <lb/>coefficients for the expression of each gene again MIR196A. B) RPM for MIR196A across the <lb/>human breast cells. Error bars represent biological replicates when available. Data for A and <lb/>B sourced from GSE16368 (51). BSC = breast stem cell, BF = breast fibroblast, BME = <lb/>breast myoepithelium, BLEC = breast luminal epithelial cell and HMEC = human mammary <lb/>epithelial cell. <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Wilczynska A, Bushell M. The complexity of miRNA-mediated repression. Cell death <lb/>and differentiation. 2015;22(1):22-33. <lb/>2. <lb/>Iorio MV, Croce CM. MicroRNA dysregulation in cancer: diagnostics, monitoring and <lb/>therapeutics. A comprehensive review. EMBO Mol Med. 2012;4(3):143-59. <lb/>3. <lb/>Simonson B, Das S. MicroRNA Therapeutics: the Next Magic Bullet? Mini Rev Med <lb/>Chem. 2015;15(6):467-74. <lb/>4. <lb/>Hui AB, Shi W, Boutros PC, Miller N, Pintilie M, Fyles T, et al. Robust global micro-<lb/>RNA profiling with formalin-fixed paraffin-embedded breast cancer tissues. Laboratory <lb/>investigation; a journal of technical methods and pathology. 2009;89(5):597-606. <lb/>5. <lb/>Hoffman AE, Zheng T, Yi C, Leaderer D, Weidhaas J, Slack F, et al. microRNA miR-<lb/>196a-2 and breast cancer: a genetic and epigenetic association study and functional <lb/>analysis. Cancer research. 2009;69(14):5970-7. <lb/>6. <lb/>Luthra R, Singh RR, Luthra MG, Li YX, Hannah C, Romans AM, et al. MicroRNA-196a <lb/>targets annexin A1: a microRNA-mediated mechanism of annexin A1 downregulation in <lb/>cancers. Oncogene. 2008;27(52):6667-78. <lb/>7. <lb/>Liu XH, Lu KH, Wang KM, Sun M, Zhang EB, Yang JS, et al. MicroRNA-196a promotes <lb/>non-small cell lung cancer cell proliferation and invasion through targeting HOXA5. BMC <lb/>cancer. 2012;12:348. <lb/>8. <lb/>Sun M, Liu XH, Li JH, Yang JS, Zhang EB, Yin DD, et al. MiR-196a is upregulated in <lb/>gastric cancer and promotes cell proliferation by downregulating p27(kip1). Molecular <lb/>cancer therapeutics. 2012;11(4):842-52. <lb/>9. <lb/>Hou T, Ou J, Zhao X, Huang X, Huang Y, Zhang Y. MicroRNA-196a promotes cervical <lb/>cancer proliferation through the regulation of FOXO1 and p27(Kip1.). British journal of <lb/>cancer. 2014;110(5):1260-8. <lb/>10. <lb/>Wang G, Wang Y, Shen C, Huang YW, Huang K, Huang TH, et al. RNA polymerase II <lb/>binding patterns reveal genomic regions involved in microRNA gene regulation. PloS <lb/>one.5(11):e13798. <lb/>11. <lb/>Corcoran DL, Pandit KV, Gordon B, Bhattacharjee A, Kaminski N, Benos PV. Features <lb/>of mammalian microRNA promoters emerge from polymerase II chromatin <lb/>immunoprecipitation data. PloS one. 2009;4(4):e5279. <lb/>12. <lb/>Attema JL, Bert AG, Lim YY, Kolesnikoff N, Lawrence DM, Pillman KA, et al. <lb/>Identification of an enhancer that increases miR-200b~200a~429 gene expression in breast <lb/>cancer cells. PloS one. 2013;8(9):e75517. <lb/>13. <lb/>Punnamoottil B, Rinkwitz S, Giacomotto J, Svahn AJ, Becker TS. Motor neuron-<lb/>expressed microRNAs 218 and their enhancers are nested within introns of Slit2/3 genes. <lb/>Genesis. 2015;53(5):321-8. <lb/>14. <lb/>Bhan A, Hussain I, Ansari KI, Kasiri S, Bashyal A, Mandal SS. Antisense Transcript Long <lb/>Noncoding RNA (lncRNA) HOTAIR is Transcriptionally Induced by Estradiol. Journal of <lb/>molecular biology. 2013. <lb/>15. <lb/>Milevskiy MJ, Al-Ejeh F, Saunus JM, Northwood KS, Bailey PJ, Betts JA, et al. Long-<lb/>range regulators of the lncRNA HOTAIR enhance its prognostic potential in breast cancer. <lb/>Human molecular genetics. 2016;25(15):3269-83. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>16. <lb/>Ansari KI, Hussain I, Shrestha B, Kasiri S, Mandal SS. HOXC6 Is transcriptionally <lb/>regulated via coordination of MLL histone methylase and estrogen receptor in an estrogen <lb/>environment. Journal of molecular biology. 2011;411(2):334-49. <lb/>17. <lb/>Ansari KI, Hussain I, Kasiri S, Mandal SS. HOXC10 is overexpressed in breast cancer <lb/>and transcriptionally regulated by estrogen via involvement of histone methylases MLL3 and <lb/>MLL4. J Mol Endocrinol. 2012;48(1):61-75. <lb/>18. <lb/>Ansari KI, Kasiri S, Hussain I, Mandal SS. Mixed lineage leukemia histone methylases <lb/>play critical roles in estrogen-mediated regulation of HOXC13. The FEBS journal. <lb/>2009;276(24):7400-11. <lb/>19. <lb/>Hu Z, Liang J, Wang Z, Tian T, Zhou X, Chen J, et al. Common genetic variants in pre-<lb/>microRNAs were associated with increased risk of breast cancer in Chinese women. Hum <lb/>Mutat. 2009;30(1):79-84. <lb/>20. <lb/>Jedlinski DJ, Gabrovska PN, Weinstein SR, Smith RA, Griffiths LR. Single nucleotide <lb/>polymorphism in hsa-mir-196a-2 and breast cancer risk: a case control study. Twin Res Hum <lb/>Genet. 2011;14(5):417-21. <lb/>21. <lb/>Siegfried Z, Eden S, Mendelsohn M, Feng X, Tsuberi BZ, Cedar H. DNA methylation <lb/>represses transcription in vivo. Nature genetics. 1999;22(2):203-6. <lb/>22. <lb/>Mohammed H, D&apos;Santos C, Serandour AA, Ali HR, Brown GD, Atkins A, et al. <lb/>Endogenous purification reveals GREB1 as a key estrogen receptor regulatory factor. Cell <lb/>reports. 2013;3(2):342-9. <lb/>23. <lb/>Hurtado A, Holmes KA, Ross-Innes CS, Schmidt D, Carroll JS. FOXA1 is a key <lb/>determinant of estrogen receptor function and endocrine response. Nat Genet. <lb/>2011;43(1):27-33. <lb/>24. <lb/>Magnani L, Ballantyne EB, Zhang X, Lupien M. PBX1 genomic pioneer function drives <lb/>ERalpha signaling underlying progression in breast cancer. PLoS genetics. <lb/>2011;7(11):e1002368. <lb/>25. <lb/>Franco HL, Nagari A, Kraus WL. TNFalpha signaling exposes latent estrogen receptor <lb/>binding sites to alter the breast cancer cell transcriptome. Molecular cell. 2015;58(1):21-34. <lb/>26. <lb/>Millour J, Constantinidou D, Stavropoulou AV, Wilson MS, Myatt SS, Kwok JM, et al. <lb/>FOXM1 is a transcriptional target of ERalpha and has a critical role in breast cancer <lb/>endocrine sensitivity and resistance. Oncogene. 2010;29(20):2983-95. <lb/>27. <lb/>Heimberg A, McGlinn E. Building a robust a-p axis. Curr Genomics. 2012;13(4):278-<lb/>88. <lb/>28. <lb/>Sawado T, Halow J, Bender MA, Groudine M. The beta -globin locus control region <lb/>(LCR) functions primarily by enhancing the transition from transcription initiation to <lb/>elongation. Genes &amp; development. 2003;17(8):1009-18. <lb/>29. <lb/>Vakoc CR, Letting DL, Gheldof N, Sawado T, Bender MA, Groudine M, et al. Proximity <lb/>among distant regulatory elements at the beta-globin locus requires GATA-1 and FOG-1. <lb/>Molecular cell. 2005;17(3):453-62. <lb/>30. <lb/>Ko JY, Oh S, Yoo KH. Functional Enhancers As Master Regulators of Tissue-Specific <lb/>Gene Regulation and Cancer Development. Mol Cells. 2017;40(3):169-77. <lb/>31. <lb/>Sotelo J, Esposito D, Duhagon MA, Banfield K, Mehalko J, Liao H, et al. Long-range <lb/>enhancers on 8q24 regulate c-Myc. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the <lb/>United States of America. 2010;107(7):3001-5. <lb/>32. <lb/>Dostie J, Richmond TA, Arnaout RA, Selzer RR, Lee WL, Honan TA, et al. Chromosome <lb/>Conformation Capture Carbon Copy (5C): a massively parallel solution for mapping <lb/>interactions between genomic elements. Genome Res. 2006;16(10):1299-309. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>33. <lb/>Davies JO, Telenius JM, McGowan SJ, Roberts NA, Taylor S, Higgs DR, et al. <lb/>Multiplexed analysis of chromosome conformation at vastly improved sensitivity. Nature <lb/>methods. 2016;13(1):74-80. <lb/>34. <lb/>Fullwood MJ, Liu MH, Pan YF, Liu J, Xu H, Mohamed YB, et al. An oestrogen-receptor-<lb/>alpha-bound human chromatin interactome. Nature. 2009;462(7269):58-64. <lb/>35. <lb/>Jiang CF, Shi ZM, Li DM, Qian YC, Ren Y, Bai XM, et al. Estrogen-induced miR-196a <lb/>elevation promotes tumor growth and metastasis via targeting SPRED1 in breast cancer. <lb/>Molecular cancer. 2018;17(1):83. <lb/>36. <lb/>Landgraf P, Rusu M, Sheridan R, Sewer A, Iovino N, Aravin A, et al. A mammalian <lb/>microRNA expression atlas based on small RNA library sequencing. Cell. 2007;129(7):1401-<lb/>14. <lb/>37. <lb/>Kron KJ, Bailey SD, Lupien M. Enhancer alterations in cancer: a source for a cell <lb/>identity crisis. Genome Med. 2014;6(9):77. <lb/>38. <lb/>Herz HM, Hu D, Shilatifard A. Enhancer malfunction in cancer. Molecular cell. <lb/>2014;53(6):859-66. <lb/>39. <lb/>Chen H, Li C, Peng X, Zhou Z, Weinstein JN, Cancer Genome Atlas Research N, et al. A <lb/>Pan-Cancer Analysis of Enhancer Expression in Nearly 9000 Patient Samples. Cell. <lb/>2018;173(2):386-99 e12. <lb/>40. <lb/>Whyte WA, Orlando DA, Hnisz D, Abraham BJ, Lin CY, Kagey MH, et al. Master <lb/>transcription factors and mediator establish super-enhancers at key cell identity genes. Cell. <lb/>2013;153(2):307-19. <lb/>41. <lb/>Hu Y, Zhang Z, Kashiwagi M, Yoshida T, Joshi I, Jena N, et al. Superenhancer <lb/>reprogramming drives a B-cell-epithelial transition and high-risk leukemia. Genes &amp; <lb/>development. 2016;30(17):1971-90. <lb/>42. <lb/>Burger H. The menopausal transition--endocrinology. J Sex Med. 2008;5(10):2266-<lb/>73. <lb/>43. <lb/>Hale GE, Robertson DM, Burger HG. The perimenopausal woman: endocrinology and <lb/>management. J Steroid Biochem Mol Biol. 2014;142:121-31. <lb/>44. <lb/>Azim HA, Jr., Partridge AH. Biology of breast cancer in young women. Breast cancer <lb/>research : BCR. 2014;16(4):427. <lb/>45. <lb/>Azim HA, Jr., Michiels S, Bedard PL, Singhal SK, Criscitiello C, Ignatiadis M, et al. <lb/>Elucidating prognosis and biology of breast cancer arising in young women using gene <lb/>expression profiling. Clinical cancer research : an official journal of the American Association <lb/>for Cancer Research. 2012;18(5):1341-51. <lb/>46. <lb/>McClelland RA, Barrow D, Madden TA, Dutkowski CM, Pamment J, Knowlden JM, et <lb/>al. Enhanced epidermal growth factor receptor signaling in MCF7 breast cancer cells after <lb/>long-term culture in the presence of the pure antiestrogen ICI 182,780 (Faslodex). <lb/>Endocrinology. 2001;142(7):2776-88. <lb/>47. <lb/>Knowlden JM, Hutcheson IR, Jones HE, Madden T, Gee JM, Harper ME, et al. <lb/>Elevated levels of epidermal growth factor receptor/c-erbB2 heterodimers mediate an <lb/>autocrine growth regulatory pathway in tamoxifen-resistant MCF-7 cells. Endocrinology. <lb/>2003;144(3):1032-44. <lb/>48. <lb/>Staka CM, Nicholson RI, Gee JM. Acquired resistance to oestrogen deprivation: role <lb/>for growth factor signalling kinases/oestrogen receptor cross-talk revealed in new MCF-7X <lb/>model. Endocrine-related cancer. 2005;12 Suppl 1:S85-97. <lb/>49. <lb/>Miller DF, Yan PS, Buechlein A, Rodriguez BA, Yilmaz AS, Goel S, et al. A new method <lb/>for stranded whole transcriptome RNA-seq. Methods. 2013;63(2):126-34. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>50. <lb/>He DX, Gu F, Gao F, Hao JJ, Gong D, Gu XT, et al. Genome-wide profiles of <lb/>methylation, microRNAs, and gene expression in chemoresistant breast cancer. Scientific <lb/>reports. 2016;6:24706. <lb/>51. <lb/>Gascard P, Bilenky M, Sigaroudinia M, Zhao J, Li L, Carles A, et al. Epigenetic and <lb/>transcriptional determinants of the human breast. Nat Commun. 2015;6:6351. <lb/>52. <lb/>Welboren WJ, van Driel MA, Janssen-Megens EM, van Heeringen SJ, Sweep FC, Span <lb/>PN, et al. ChIP-Seq of ERalpha and RNA polymerase II defines genes differentially responding <lb/>to ligands. The EMBO journal. 2009;28(10):1418-28. <lb/>53. <lb/>Hah N, Danko CG, Core L, Waterfall JJ, Siepel A, Lis JT, et al. A rapid, extensive, and <lb/>transient transcriptional response to estrogen signaling in breast cancer cells. Cell. <lb/>2011;145(4):622-34. <lb/>54. <lb/>Li G, Ruan X, Auerbach RK, Sandhu KS, Zheng M, Wang P, et al. Extensive promoter-<lb/>centered chromatin interactions provide a topological basis for transcription regulation. <lb/>Cell. 2012;148(1-2):84-98. <lb/>55. <lb/>Ross-Innes CS, Stark R, Teschendorff AE, Holmes KA, Ali HR, Dunning MJ, et al. <lb/>Differential oestrogen receptor binding is associated with clinical outcome in breast cancer. <lb/>Nature. 2012;481(7381):389-93. <lb/>56. <lb/>Langmead B, Trapnell C, Pop M, Salzberg SL. Ultrafast and memory-efficient <lb/>alignment of short DNA sequences to the human genome. Genome biology. 2009;10(3):R25. <lb/>57. <lb/>Zhang Y, Liu T, Meyer CA, Eeckhoute J, Johnson DS, Bernstein BE, et al. Model-based <lb/>analysis of ChIP-Seq (MACS). Genome biology. 2008;9(9):R137. <lb/>58. <lb/>Robinson JT, Thorvaldsdottir H, Winckler W, Guttman M, Lander ES, Getz G, et al. <lb/>Integrative genomics viewer. Nature biotechnology. 2011;29(1):24-6. <lb/>59. <lb/>Stone A, Zotenko E, Locke WJ, Korbie D, Millar EK, Pidsley R, et al. DNA methylation <lb/>of oestrogen-regulated enhancers defines endocrine sensitivity in breast cancer. Nat <lb/>Commun. 2015;6:7758. <lb/>60. <lb/>Cancer Genome Atlas N. Comprehensive molecular portraits of human breast <lb/>tumours. Nature. 2012;490(7418):61-70. <lb/>61. <lb/>Curtis C, Shah SP, Chin SF, Turashvili G, Rueda OM, Dunning MJ, et al. The genomic <lb/>and transcriptomic architecture of 2,000 breast tumours reveals novel subgroups. Nature. <lb/>2012;486(7403):346-52. <lb/>62. <lb/>Dvinge H, Git A, Graf S, Salmon-Divon M, Curtis C, Sottoriva A, et al. The shaping and <lb/>functional consequences of the microRNA landscape in breast cancer. Nature. <lb/>2013;497(7449):378-82. <lb/>63. <lb/>Eisen MB, Spellman PT, Brown PO, Botstein D. Cluster analysis and display of <lb/>genome-wide expression patterns. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the <lb/>United States of America. 1998;95(25):14863-8. <lb/>64. <lb/>Hagege H, Klous P, Braem C, Splinter E, Dekker J, Cathala G, et al. Quantitative <lb/>analysis of chromosome conformation capture assays (3C-qPCR). Nature protocols. <lb/>2007;2(7):1722-33. <lb/>65. <lb/>Tan-Wong SM, French JD, Proudfoot NJ, Brown MA. Dynamic interactions between <lb/>the promoter and terminator regions of the mammalian BRCA1 gene. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 2008;105(13):5160-5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 1: E2 influences MIR196A2 expression in breast cancer <lb/>0 mins <lb/>10 mins <lb/>40 mins <lb/>160 mins <lb/>GRO-Seq <lb/>ERα <lb/>FOXA1 <lb/>ChIP-Seq <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>Promoter Identification <lb/>Promoter Response to E2 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>12 <lb/>24 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Time Post E2 <lb/>ΔΔCt (RNU6b/DMSO) <lb/>miR-196a Expression <lb/>miR-196a <lb/>pre-miR-196a2 <lb/>E 2 In d u c ib le M IR S in M C F 7 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 .5 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>2 .5 <lb/>5 .0 <lb/>7 .5 <lb/>1 0 .0 <lb/>5 5 <lb/>8 0 <lb/>1 0 5 <lb/>1 3 0 <lb/>T im e ( h r s ) P o s t E 2 T r e a tm e n t <lb/>R P K M <lb/>M IR 1 9 6 A 1 <lb/>M IR 1 9 6 A 2 <lb/>Empty PP1 Overlap PP2 PP3 A2-Gene <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>RLU (Ren/Empty) <lb/>MCF7 MIR196A2 <lb/>Putative Promoters <lb/>Scale <lb/>chr12: <lb/>HMEC <lb/>MCF10A <lb/>MCF-7 <lb/>2 kb <lb/>hg19 <lb/>54,378,000 <lb/>54,380,000 <lb/>54,382,000 <lb/>54,384,000 <lb/>HOXC10 <lb/>MIR196A2 <lb/>CpG <lb/>PP1 <lb/>Overlap <lb/>PP2 <lb/>PP3 <lb/>CpG_Hoffman <lb/>A2-Gene <lb/>SNP_Hoffman <lb/>H3K4me3 <lb/>H3K27ac <lb/>H3K27me3 <lb/>Untreat <lb/>E2 <lb/>Tam <lb/>Fulv <lb/>Methyl <lb/>450K <lb/>MCF-7 <lb/>Histone <lb/>MCF-7 <lb/>RNA Pol II <lb/>A <lb/>Figure 2: Distal putative enhancer elements of the MIR196A2 putative promoters <lb/>B <lb/>mE <lb/>HDE <lb/>HDE <lb/>mE <lb/>C <lb/>E m <lb/>p t y <lb/>H D E m <lb/>E P P 1 <lb/>P P 1 + H D E <lb/>P P 1 + m <lb/>E <lb/>O v e r l a p <lb/>O v e r l a p + H D E <lb/>O v e r l a p + m <lb/>E P P 2 <lb/>P P 2 + H D E <lb/>P P 2 + m <lb/>E <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>RLU (Ren/Empty) <lb/>MCF7 MIR196A2 <lb/>Enhancers <lb/>Mean Centred Expression <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>Correlation to miR-196a <lb/>PAM50 Subtypes <lb/>N-Adj Basal HER2 LumA LumB N-Like <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>MIR196A <lb/>Expression (log2) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Figure 3: MIR196A is differentially expressed in breast cancer <lb/>A <lb/>+3 <lb/>-3 <lb/>Basal <lb/>HER2 <lb/>LumA <lb/>LumB <lb/>N-Like <lb/>Expression Clusters <lb/>TTest, P = &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>One-Way ANOVA, P = &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Breast Tissue <lb/>Norm-Adj Tumour <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>MIR196A <lb/>Expression (log2) <lb/>**** <lb/>Norm-Adj 0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>MIR196A <lb/>Expression (log2) <lb/>Clinical Stage <lb/>Breast Cancer <lb/>Figure 4: MIR196A is a biomarker of breast cancer progression <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>ER+ <lb/>Years <lb/>OS (%) <lb/>Low (355) <lb/>(High (648) <lb/>P = 0.0013 <lb/>HR = 1.6312 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>Years <lb/>OS (%) <lb/>TNBC <lb/>Low (122) <lb/>High (83) <lb/>P = 0.0471 <lb/>HR = 0.5760 <lb/></body>

			<body>Table1: Menopause effects the stratification of patient survival by MIR196A in ER+ disease <lb/>eno <lb/>HR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>P-Value <lb/>HR <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>P-Value <lb/>HER2 (high vs low) <lb/>2.695 1.2479 -5.8213 0.0120 3.352 1.3483 -8.3325 0.0096 <lb/>MIR196A (high vs low) 0.463 0.2325 -0.9202 0.0288 0.342 0.1534 -0.7623 0.0091 <lb/>Tumour Grade (1,2,3) 1.638 0.9988 -2.6844 0.0517 <lb/>Tumour Stage (0-4) <lb/>1.652 0.9937 -2.7472 0.0541 <lb/>Lymph Node (+, -) <lb/>1.857 0.9836 -3.5069 0.0575 <lb/>Size (T1, T2, T3) <lb/>1.470 0.9518 -2.2688 0.0840 1.798 1.0893 -2.9693 0.0225 <lb/>PGR (high vs low) <lb/>0.552 0.2770 -1.0978 0.0919 <lb/>Age At Diagnosis <lb/>0.985 0.9261 -1.0469 0.6221 <lb/>Meno <lb/>Lymph Node (+, -) <lb/>2.739 2.0075 -3.7358 &lt;0.0001 1.720 1.1510 -2.5711 0.0085 <lb/>Tumour Stage (0-4) <lb/>2.363 1.8658 -2.9926 &lt;0.0001 1.519 1.0557 -2.1868 0.0251 <lb/>Size (T1, T2, T3) <lb/>1.866 1.4837 -2.3461 &lt;0.0001 1.560 1.1146 -2.1832 0.0099 <lb/>Tumour Grade (1,2,3) 1.822 1.4057 -2.3622 &lt;0.0001 1.455 1.0926 -1.9385 0.0107 <lb/>MIR196A (high vs low) 1.847 1.3065 -2.6110 0.0005 1.599 1.0806 -2.3652 0.0195 <lb/>HER2 (high vs low) <lb/>2.165 1.3982 -3.3521 0.0006 2.210 1.3624 -3.5847 0.0014 <lb/>PGR (high vs low) <lb/>0.636 0.4708 -0.8594 0.0034 <lb/>Age At Diagnosis <lb/>1.023 1.0059 -1.0403 0.0086 <lb/>Condition <lb/>Univariate Cox-proportional hazard Multivariate Cox-proportional <lb/>ER+ Post-Menopausal <lb/>ER+ Pre-Menopausal <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 5: Therapeutic resistance leads to increases in MIR196A expression <lb/>Promoters HDE <lb/>mE <lb/>Combined <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>Tumour ERα ChIP <lb/>Peak Score <lb/>Metastases <lb/>Non-Responders <lb/>Responders <lb/>P = &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>E <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>ER+ CT/HT <lb/>Years <lb/>OS (%) <lb/>Low (28) <lb/>High (79) <lb/>P = 0.0125 <lb/>HR = 8.003 <lb/>Wt ADM PTX <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>MCF7 Line <lb/>RPKM (log2 Scale) <lb/>MIR196A <lb/>Expression <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>miR-196a <lb/>pre-miR-196a2-1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>miR-196a Expression <lb/>ΔΔCt (RNU6b/MCF7) <lb/>MCF7-C <lb/>MCF7-X <lb/>TAMR <lb/>FASR <lb/> **** <lb/>*** <lb/>*** <lb/>n.s. <lb/>**** <lb/>* </body>

	</text>
</tei>
