<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Title: Multiple sclerosis-associated changes in the composition and immune functions of <lb/>spore-forming bacteria <lb/>Running title: Spore-forming bacteria in multiple sclerosis <lb/>Authors: Egle Cekanaviciute 1, † , Anne-Katrin Pröbstel 1 , Anna Thomann 1, ‡ , Tessel F. Runia 1, § , <lb/>Patrizia Casaccia 4,5 , Ilana Katz Sand 4 , Elizabeth Crabtree 1, ¶ , Sneha Singh 1 , John Morrissey 1 , <lb/>Patrick Barba 1 , Refujia Gomez 1 , Rob Knight 6 , Sarkis K. Mazmanian 7 , Jennifer Graves 1 , Bruce <lb/>A.C. Cree 1 , Scott S. Zamvil 1 and Sergio E. Baranzini 1,2,3# <lb/>Affiliations: <lb/>1 UCSF Weill Institute for Neurosciences, Department of Neurology, University of California, <lb/>San Francisco, CA. USA. <lb/>2 Institute for Human Genetics. University of California, San Francisco, CA. USA. <lb/>3 Graduate Program for Biomedical Informatics. University of California, San Francisco, CA. <lb/>USA. <lb/>4 Icahn School of Medicine at Mount Sinai. New York, NY. USA <lb/>5 Advanced Science Research Center at The Graduate Center of City University New York, New <lb/>York, NY. USA <lb/>6 University of California, San Diego. San Diego, CA. USA <lb/>7 California Institute of Technology. Pasadena, CA. USA <lb/> † Current address: USRA/Space Biosciences Division, NASA Ames Research Center, Moffett <lb/>Field, CA, USA. <lb/> ‡ Current address: Department of Neuroimmunology, Max Planck Institute of Neurobiology, <lb/>Martinsried, Germany. <lb/> § Current address: Erasmus MC, Rotterdam, Netherlands. <lb/> ¶ Current address: Tulane Center for Comprehensive MS Care. New Orleans, LA <lb/>Abstract word count: 236 <lb/>Manuscript word count: 3326 <lb/>Number of Figures: 4 <lb/>Number of tables: 1 <lb/>Number Supplementary Figures: 1 <lb/>Number of supplementary Tables: 3 <lb/>Corresponding author: <lb/>Sergio E. Baranzini, PhD <lb/>Sergio.baranzini@ucsf.edu <lb/>Ph: 415-502-6865 <lb/>Fax: 415-476-5229 <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is an autoimmune disease of the central nervous system characterized by <lb/>adaptive and innate immune system dysregulation. Recent work has revealed moderate <lb/>alteration of gut microbial communities in subjects with MS and in experimental, induced <lb/>models. However, a mechanistic understanding linking the observed changes in the microbiota <lb/>and the presence of the disease is still missing. Chloroform-resistant, spore-forming bacteria <lb/>have been shown to exhibit immunomodulatory properties in vitro and in vivo, but they have not <lb/>yet been characterized in the context of human disease. This study addresses the community <lb/>composition and immune function of this bacterial fraction in MS. We identify MS-associated <lb/>spore-forming taxa and show that their presence correlates with impaired differentiation of IL-10 <lb/>secreting, regulatory T lymphocytes in-vitro. Colonization of antibiotic-treated mice with spore-<lb/>forming bacteria allowed us to identify some bacterial taxa favoring IL-10 + lymphocyte <lb/>differentiation and others inducing differentiation of pro-inflammatory, IFN + T lymphocytes. <lb/>However, when fed into antibiotic-treated mice, both MS and control derived spore-forming <lb/>bacteria were able to induce immunoregulatory responses. <lb/>Our analysis also identified Akkermansia muciniphila as a key organism that may interact either <lb/>directly or indirectly with spore-forming bacteria to exacerbate the inflammatory effects of MS-<lb/>associated gut microbiota. Thus, changes in the spore-forming fraction may influence T <lb/>lymphocyte-mediated inflammation in MS. This experimental approach of isolating a subset of <lb/>microbiota based on its functional characteristics may be useful to investigate other microbial <lb/>fractions at greater depth. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>Importance: <lb/>Despite the rapid emergence of microbiome related studies in human diseases, few go beyond a <lb/>simple description of relative taxa levels in a select group of patients. Our study integrates <lb/>computational analysis with in vitro and in vivo exploration of inflammatory properties of both <lb/>complete microbial communities and individual taxa, revealing novel functional associations. <lb/>We specifically show that while small differences exist between the microbiomes of MS patients <lb/>and healthy subjects, these differences are exacerbated in the chloroform resistant fraction. We <lb/>further demonstrate that, when purified from MS patients, this fraction is associated with <lb/>impaired immunomodulatory responses in vitro. <lb/></front>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The human gut microbiota is emerging as a major immune regulator in health and disease, <lb/>particularly in relation to autoimmune disorders. Most human microbiota studies to date have <lb/>been based on unbiased exploration of complete microbial communities. However, limited <lb/>sequencing depth, combined with high community richness and natural sample heterogeneity, <lb/>might hinder the discovery of physiologically relevant taxonomical differences. Thus, targeted <lb/>studies of specific microbial populations with defined characteristics may serve as a <lb/>complementary approach to investigate disease-associated changes in gut microbiome. <lb/>Spore-forming bacteria constitute a subset of Gram-positive bacteria that are resistant to 3% <lb/>chloroform treatment (1, 2). Both human and mouse spore-forming bacteria have <lb/>immunoregulatory functions (3, 4). Mouse spore-forming bacteria include segmented <lb/>filamentous bacteria and Clostridia species, which have been shown to induce gut T helper <lb/>lymphocyte responses (3, 5). More recently, human spore-forming bacteria from a healthy <lb/>subject were also reported to induce Tregs in vitro and in gnotobiotic mice (4). However, <lb/>whether the composition and functions of spore-forming bacteria are altered in immune mediated <lb/>diseases is unknown. <lb/>Multiple sclerosis (MS) is a chronic disease of the central nervous system, characterized by <lb/>autoimmune destruction of myelin. MS pathogenesis is in part mediated by effector T <lb/>lymphocytes, and counterbalanced by Tregs, that limit the autoimmune damage inflicted by the <lb/>former population (6, 7) and potentially promote remyelination (8). Recent studies, including our <lb/>own, associated MS with moderate changes in the relative amounts of gut microbiota that <lb/>exacerbate T lymphocyte-mediated inflammation in vitro and in vivo by stimulating pro-<lb/>inflammatory IFN+ Th1 and inhibiting IL-10+ regulatory T lymphocytes (9, 10). <lb/>We hypothesized that these MS-associated changes in gut microbial communities may involve <lb/>spore-forming bacteria thus altering its overall immunoregulatory properties. To address this <lb/>hypothesis, we isolated spore-forming bacteria from untreated patients with relapsing-remitting <lb/>MS (RRMS) and matched controls and analyzed their community composition and <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>immunoregulatory functions in vitro and in the experimental autoimmune encephalomyelitis <lb/>(EAE) mouse model. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>MS-associated differences in microbial community composition are more evident in the <lb/>spore-forming fraction <lb/>We isolated the spore-forming bacterial fraction from stool samples of 25 untreated MS patients <lb/>and 24 controls and tested their relative abundance by amplicon sequencing of 16S rRNA V4 <lb/>gene sequencing. This analysis revealed no differences in community richness between patients <lb/>and controls (Chao1 metric of alpha diversity, Fig. 1A). However, a focused analysis on the <lb/>spore-forming fraction increased sample variability both within and between groups (Fig. 1B) <lb/>possibly by reducing the number of taxa of interest and thus amplifying the differences in their <lb/>relative abundances (Fig. 1A, 1C). <lb/>Spore-forming bacteria showed notable differences in taxonomical composition between cases <lb/>and controls, with 22.43% (135 out of 602 total) OTUs significantly different (p=0.05, negative <lb/>binomial Wald test, Benjamini-Hochberg correction) (Fig. 1D and Suppl. Table 1). These <lb/>taxonomical differences were also noticeable at the class level in which Bacilli were significantly <lb/>overrepresented in controls (Fig. 1E), and Clostridia, including Clostridium perfringens were <lb/>significantly overrepresented in MS patients (Fig. 1F and Suppl. Fig. S1). <lb/>Spore-forming bacteria from MS patients fail to induce anti-inflammatory T lymphocytes <lb/>in vitro <lb/>To investigate whether MS-associated differences in community composition of spore-forming <lb/>bacteria were sufficient to alter the immune functions of primary blood mononuclear cells <lb/>(PBMCs) from healthy human donors, we exposed human PBMCs to extracts of spore-forming <lb/>bacteria isolated either from unrelated controls or from MS patients and used flow cytometry to <lb/>evaluate T lymphocyte differentiation under different polarizing conditions (18-20). A <lb/>comparison of the PBMC response to extracts of spore-forming bacteria from controls or from <lb/>MS patients identified lower conversion into CD4+FoxP3+ Tregs (Fig. 2 A, C), including IL-10 <lb/>expressing Treg population (Fig. 2 B, D) in the PBMCs exposed to the MS-derived spore-<lb/>forming bacteria. These data suggest that spore-forming bacteria from MS patients are <lb/>significantly less effective at inducing Treg differentiation. Of note, the small population of <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tregs that still differentiated in response to MS bacteria, retained their suppressive capacities in <lb/>vitro (Fig. 2E), thereby indicating that this was a functionally active population. Interestingly, the <lb/>percentage of IL-10+ Tregs induced by extracts of spore-forming bacteria positively correlated <lb/>with the relative abundance of Bacilli and negatively correlated with the relative abundance of <lb/>Clostridia (Fig. 2 F, expressed as Clostridia-Bacilli difference). Thus, the community <lb/>composition of spore-forming bacteria (i.e. high Clostridia, low Bacilli) associated with MS was <lb/>also correlated with an inhibition of their respective immunoregulatory functions. <lb/>Gnotobiotic mouse models reveal associations between individual bacterial taxa and T <lb/>lymphocyte responses <lb/>To determine whether the MS-associated reduction in the ability of spore-forming bacteria to <lb/>stimulate Treg differentiation was physiologically significant, we colonized a group of female <lb/>antibiotic-treated mice (21) with spore-forming bacteria from either controls (n=2) or MS <lb/>subjects (n=2) and measured the course and severity of EAE. We observed a significant <lb/>reduction in disease severity in all mice whose GI tracts were reconstituted with spore-forming <lb/>bacteria. However, this reduction was independent of whether the spore-forming fraction was <lb/>isolated from MS or controls (Fig. 3 A). This indicated that while MS-derived spore-forming <lb/>bacteria could be functionally distinguished in vitro, these differences were not sufficient to <lb/>induce a phenotype in vivo in our experimental setting. <lb/>We next analyzed whether spore-forming bacteria regulated T lymphocyte responses in vivo. To <lb/>this end we colonized antibiotic-treated mice with spore-forming bacteria from 3 controls and 3 <lb/>MS patients and analyzed the resulting changes in bacterial composition and T lymphocyte <lb/>differentiation. Principal coordinate analysis (PCoA) of the beta diversity of gut microbiota <lb/>separated SPF mice from antibiotic-treated and colonized (i.e. gnotobiotic) mice. While no major <lb/>shifts in community composition based on disease state of the donor were observed (Fig. 3B), <lb/>multiple microbial taxa were differentially abundant (Fig. 3C, Suppl. Tables 2, 3), including an <lb/>increase in Akkermansia (3 OTUs corresponding to A. muciniphila; Suppl. Table 3) in mice <lb/>colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Further investigation identified individual taxa that were classified as either pro-inflammatory or <lb/>anti-inflammatory-based on the correlation between their relative abundance in mouse stool <lb/>samples and their ability to alter differentiation of IFN+ Th1 or IL-10+ regulatory lymphocytes <lb/>from either spleen or mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN) in vitro (Fig. 3D, 3E). The pro-<lb/>inflammatory category (Fig. 3D, red rectangle) included taxa significantly increased in mice <lb/>colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients compared to controls (highlighted in <lb/>red), while the anti-inflammatory category (mostly evident in splenocytes; blue rectangle) <lb/>contained taxa significantly reduced in mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS <lb/>patients (highlighted in blue). <lb/>The increase in Akkermansia muciniphila, a non-spore-forming bacteria, in gnotobiotic mice <lb/>colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients led to the hypothesis that spore-forming <lb/>bacteria may regulate Akkermansia levels. The correlation between spore-forming community <lb/>composition and relative abundance of Akkermansia is shown in Fig. 4A. The increase in <lb/>Akkermansia was present not only in the mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS <lb/>donors, but also in MS donors themselves (p = 1.5E -09 , negative binomial Wald test) (Fig. 4B). <lb/>Of interest, we and others (9, 10) recently reported the increased abundance of Akkermansia in <lb/>untreated MS patients and identified this bacterium as sufficient for driving T lymphocyte <lb/>differentiation into the pro-inflammatory IFN+ Th1 phenotype in-vitro (10). Consistent with <lb/>this result, we also observed a significant positive correlation between the relative abundance of <lb/>Akkermansia and IFN+ Th1 lymphocyte differentiation (Fig. 4C) in gnotobiotic mice. While <lb/>other taxa also correlated with Akkermansia levels and T lymphocyte differentiation (Fig. 4D) <lb/>our data suggest that the observed immunological effects may be at least partially mediated by <lb/>Akkermansia. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>The spore-forming fraction of gut bacteria has been associated with immunoregulatory properties <lb/>(4). Here we examined the structural composition and immunological effects of the spore-<lb/>forming fraction of gut microbiota from subjects with MS compared to controls. MS-associated <lb/>differences in bacterial community composition were correlated with impaired anti-inflammatory <lb/>functions, as evidenced by a reduction in their ability to drive T lymphocyte differentiation into <lb/>IL-10+ Tregs in vitro. Meanwhile, colonizing antibiotic-treated mice with spore-forming <lb/>bacteria allowed us to identify specific taxa correlated with T lymphocyte differentiation into <lb/>IFN+ and IL-10+ subtypes in vivo. <lb/>Our results contribute to the evidence supporting the immunoregulatory functions of spore-<lb/>forming bacteria and show that these functions may be compromised in the context of <lb/>autoimmunity. Previous studies on spore-forming bacteria had been conducted by isolating this <lb/>fraction from a single healthy donor (4, 22). This approach allowed focusing on donor-specific <lb/>bacterial strains, but provided limited information about the &quot;baseline&quot; composition and <lb/>variability of this bacterial community in healthy humans. Here we used multiple healthy control <lb/>donors to establish the baseline community composition of spore-forming bacteria, and <lb/>compared these healthy profiles with those from patients with MS. <lb/>Our data corroborate previous findings that spore-forming bacteria, almost exclusively belonging <lb/>to the phylum Firmicutes, and classes Clostridia and Bacilli, induce anti-inflammatory T <lb/>lymphocytes in vitro and protect from autoimmune inflammation in vivo (4, 5). We also show <lb/>that the taxonomical distribution and immunoregulatory functions of spore-forming bacteria are <lb/>altered in MS patients. While were able to show that these differences have functional <lb/>consequences in-vitro, they were not sufficient to alter the course of EAE using antibiotic treated <lb/>mice. One possible explanation for this counterintuitive finding is that since our mice were <lb/>treated with antibiotics, they were not completely germ-free prior to colonization. As a <lb/>consequence, unexpected interactions among antibiotic resistant communities and the spore-<lb/>forming fraction may have influenced the course of EAE. We recognize that using GF mice for <lb/>these experiments could address some of these concerns. However, raising GF animals is still a <lb/>highly specialized enterprise only available at select institutions. Further studies of gene <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>expression and metabolic output of spore-forming bacteria may provide therapeutic targets for <lb/>regulating T lymphocyte responses to reduce autoimmune inflammation. <lb/>The mechanisms by which spore-forming bacteria regulate host T lymphocyte differentiation <lb/>remain to be discovered. Interestingly, an overlapping subset of bacterial taxa has recently been <lb/>shown to inhibit host proteases, including cathepsins (23), which mediate adaptive immune <lb/>responses by increasing Th17 (24) and limiting Treg differentiation (25). Although future studies <lb/>are needed to establish this firmly, it is possible that spore-forming bacteria from controls, but <lb/>not MS patients are able to stimulate Treg responses via cathepsin inhibition. <lb/>Furthermore, healthy human spore-forming bacteria produce short chain fatty acids (SCFAs), <lb/>including butyrate and acetate (26), which have been observed to stimulate Treg and inhibit Th1 <lb/>differentiation in vitro and in vivo (27), Mizuno 2017). Either pure butyrate or butyrate-<lb/>producing spore-forming bacteria from healthy humans have been shown to be sufficient Treg <lb/>induction (28) in mice. Thus, human T lymphocyte differentiation into Tregs may be driven by a <lb/>yet-undiscovered SCFA-synthesizing subset of spore-forming bacteria that is present in controls <lb/>and absent in MS patients. <lb/>Akkermansia muciniphila has previously been reported to be increased in MS patients compared <lb/>to controls (9, 10, 29) and to have pro-inflammatory functions in vitro (10). In addition, <lb/>Akkermansia has been shown to be resistant to broad-spectrum antibiotics (30), which in part <lb/>may explain its persistence in mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria. The fact that high <lb/>levels of Akkermansia were only seen in mice colonized with MS chloroform-resistant bacteria <lb/>suggests that its population is normally regulated by commensals that are depleted in MS thus <lb/>enabling Akkermansia overgrowth. <lb/>Our finding that Clostridium perfringens is more abundant in the spore-forming bacterial fraction <lb/>of MS patients is consistent with the association of C. perfringens with neuromyelitis optica <lb/>(NMO), another demyelinating autoimmune disease (31-33). Putative mechanisms of C. <lb/>perfringens-mediated autoimmunity include molecular mimicry between C. perfringens peptide <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>and a self-antigen in the human host (Varrin-Doyer 2012), and toxin-mediated increase in <lb/>neuronal damage (32, 34). <lb/>Due to the high variability of spore-forming bacteria across donors, mouse colonization with <lb/>samples from additional donor pairs would be required to assess whether MS-associated <lb/>reduction in regulatory T lymphocyte differentiation in vitro can be reliably reproduced in vivo. <lb/>However, a major advantage of gnotobiotic mouse models is the ability to assess the association <lb/>between immune responses and microbial abundance within experimental communities. The <lb/>identification of additional taxa capable of inducing clear differentiation paths in immune cells <lb/>will further contribute to our understanding their role in immune regulation. For example, our <lb/>findings corroborate the anti-inflammatory functions of relatively unknown bacterial genera such <lb/>as Anaeroplasma and Dehalobacterium in mouse models of inflammation (35, 36). <lb/>In conclusion, we have investigated the immune functions of the spore-forming fraction of <lb/>human gut microbiota in health and disease, using MS as a model of autoimmune inflammation. <lb/>We identified novel bacterial taxa associated with MS as well as with T lymphocyte <lb/>differentiation into both pro-inflammatory and regulatory phenotypes. Further studies of spore-<lb/>forming bacteria and other experimentally defined bacterial populations may reveal specific <lb/>immunoregulatory mechanisms in MS and other diseases that may be targeted by therapeutic <lb/>interventions. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements: We thank all subjects who participated in this study. Funding was provided by <lb/>a grant (CA_1072-A-7) from the National MS Society. This study was also supported by a generous gift from <lb/>the Valhalla Charitable Foundation. S.E.B is the Heidrich Family and Friends Endowed Chair in Neurology. <lb/></div>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>Isolation of spore-forming bacteria from human fecal samples <lb/>Fecal samples were collected from 25 adult patients with RRMS that had not received disease-<lb/>modifying or steroid treatment for at least 3 months prior to the time of collection and 24 <lb/>subjects without MS or any other autoimmune disorder (controls) at the University of California, <lb/>San Francisco (UCSF) (Table 1). The inclusion criteria specified no use of antibiotics or <lb/>oncologic therapeutics in 3 months prior to the study. All individuals signed a written informed <lb/>consent in accordance with the sampling procedure approved by the local Institutional Review <lb/>Board. Samples were stored in collection vials (Fisher #NC9779954) at -80° C until bacterial <lb/>isolation. <lb/>Spore-forming bacteria were isolated based on their resistance to chloroform as described <lb/>previously (Atarashi 2013). Briefly, total bacteria were isolated from stool samples by <lb/>suspending ~0.5mg stool sample in 1.5ml PBS, passing it three times through a 70m cell <lb/>strainer and washing twice with 1.5ml PBS by spinning at 8000rpm. The resulting suspension <lb/>was diluted in 5ml PBS, mixed with chloroform to the final concentration of 3%, and incubated <lb/>on a shaker for 1h at room temperature. After incubation, chloroform was removed from the <lb/>solution by bubbling nitrogen (N2) gas for 30min. Chloroform-treated bacteria were then <lb/>cultured on OxyPRAS Brucella Blood Agar plates (Oxyrase #P-BRU-BA) for 96 hours followed <lb/>by Brucella Broth (Anaerobe Systems #AS-105) for 48 hours, and isolated for sequencing, in <lb/>vitro experiments and in vivo experiments. <lb/>16S rRNA amplicon sequencing and computational analysis <lb/>DNA was extracted from mouse fecal or human chloroform-resistant bacterial culture samples <lb/>using MoBio Power Fecal DNA extraction kit (MoBio #12830) according to manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. For each sample, PCR targeting the V4 region of the prokaryotic 16S rRNA gene <lb/>was completed in triplicate using the 515/806 primer pair, and amplicons were sequenced on <lb/>NextSeq at the Microbiome Profiling Services core facility at UCSF using the sequencing <lb/>primers and procedures described in the Earth Microbiome Project standard protocol (11). <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Analysis was performed using QIIME v1.9 as described (12). Essentially, amplicon sequences <lb/>were quality-filtered and grouped to &quot;species-level&quot; OTUs via SortMeRNA method (13), using <lb/>Greengenes v.13.8 97% dataset for closed reference. Sequences that did not match reference <lb/>sequences in the Greengenes database were dropped from analysis. Taxonomy was assigned to <lb/>the retained OTUs based on the Greengenes reference sequence, and the Greengenes tree was <lb/>used for all downstream phylogenetic community comparisons. OTUs were filtered to retain <lb/>only OTUs present in at least 5% of samples and covering at least 100 total reads. After filtering, <lb/>samples were rarefied to 10000 sequences per sample. Alpha diversity was calculated using the <lb/>Chao1 method (14). For analysis of beta diversity, pairwise distance matrices were generated <lb/>using the phylogenetic metric unweighted UniFrac (15) and used for principal coordinate <lb/>analysis (PCoA). For comparison of individual taxa, samples were not rarefied. Instead, OTU <lb/>abundances were normalized using variance-stabilizing transformation and taxa distributions <lb/>were compared using Wald negative binomial test from R software package DESeq2 as <lb/>described previously (16, 17) with Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons. <lb/>Linear correlations between bacterial taxa and lymphocyte proportions were computed after <lb/>variance-stabilizing transformation of bacterial abundances (16). <lb/>Mouse colonization with microbiota <lb/>Female littermates 5 week old C57BL/6J mice (JAX #000664) were treated with 1% solution of <lb/>Amphotericin B in drinking water for 3 days, followed by 2 weeks of a solution composed of 1% <lb/>Amphotericin B, 1mg/ml ampicillin, 1mg/ml neomycin, 1mg/ml metronidazole and 0.5mg/ml <lb/>vancomycin in drinking water. After 2 weeks, the drinking solution was replaced by sterile water <lb/>and mice were gavaged with specific bacteria of interest at 2*10^8 CFU in 100ul per mouse <lb/>every 2 days for 2 weeks (7 total gavages). Bacterial colonization was either followed by the <lb/>induction of EAE or immunophenotyping of mesenteric and cervical lymph nodes. <lb/>To induce EAE, mice were immunized in both flanks with 0.1ml MOG 35-55 emulsion (1.5 <lb/>mg/ml) mixed with Complete Freud&apos;s Adjuvant and killed Mycobacterium tuberculosis H37Ra <lb/>(2mg/ml), followed by two 0.1ml intraperitoneal injections of pertussis toxin (2µg/ml) <lb/>immediately and at 48h after MOG/CFA injections. Mice were scored daily in a blinded fashion <lb/>for motor deficits as follows: 0, no deficit; 1, limp tail only; 2, limp tail and hind limb weakness; <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>3, complete hind limb paralysis; 4, complete hind limb paralysis and at least partial forelimb <lb/>paralysis; 5, moribund. <lb/>At the time of euthanasia, mouse mesenteric lymph nodes, and spleens were dissected and <lb/>processed by grinding tissues through a 70µm cell strainer. Entire mesenteric and cervical lymph <lb/>nodes and 10^7 splenocytes per mouse were stimulated for 4-5 hours with 20ng/ml PMA and <lb/>1µg/ml ionomycin in presence of protein transport inhibitor (GolgiPlug, BD #51-2301KZ) and <lb/>used immediately for immunophenotyping, while the remaining splenocytes were stored for in <lb/>vitro bacterial stimulations. <lb/>Bacterial stimulation of human immune cells <lb/>Human peripheral blood mononuclear cells were isolated from healthy volunteers and stored at -<lb/>80° C in cryovials at 10^7 cells/ml concentration in FBS containing 10% DMSO. Before plating, <lb/>cells were washed in PBS twice, re-counted, and plated at 10^6 cells/ml concentration in RPMI <lb/>media supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% penicillin/streptomycin/glutamine. Cells were <lb/>stimulated for 3 days as described previously (18) with anti-human CD3 (BD #555336, 0.3 <lb/>µg/ml), anti-human CD28 (BD #555725, 2 µg/ml) and recombinant human TGF-1 (R&amp;D <lb/>#240B002, 2.5ng/ml). <lb/>Bacteria isolated from human chloroform-resistant cultures were resuspended in PBS <lb/>supplemented with protease inhibitor (Roche #4693159001) and phosphatase inhibitor (Roche <lb/>#4906845001), heat-inactivated at 65° C for 1h and sonicated for 10min as described previously <lb/>(19). Protein concentration in the resulting suspension was measured using the Pierce BCA <lb/>protein assay kit (Thermo Scientific #23227). Bacterial extracts were added to PBMCs at 1µg/ml <lb/>1h after plating as described previously (20). PBS with the same protease inhibitor and <lb/>phosphatase inhibitor was added as the no-bacteria control. Each human in vitro experiment <lb/>contained at least 6 independent donor bacterial samples and was repeated at least twice. <lb/>Immunostaining, flow cytometry and FACS of human immune cells <lb/>Human PBMCs were immunostained using standard protocols. Live/dead cell gating was <lb/>achieved using Live/Dead Fixable Aqua kit (ThermoFisher #L34957). FoxP3/transcription factor <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>staining buffer set (eBioscience #00-5523-00) was used for staining of intracellular and <lb/>intranuclear cytokines. The following antibodies were used for human PBMC staining: anti-<lb/>CD3-PE.Cy7 (BD #563423), anti-CD4-PerCP.Cy5.5 (BioLegend #300530), anti-CD25-APC <lb/>(BD #555434), anti-FoxP3-AlexaFluor488 (BD #560047) and anti-IL-10-PE (eBioscience #12-<lb/>7108). <lb/>Flow cytometry was performed on BD Fortessa cell analyzer and analyzed using FlowJo <lb/>software (TreeStar). Cells were gated to identify the lymphocyte population based on forward <lb/>and side scatter, followed by gating for single color and live cell populations. Fluorescence <lb/>minus one (FMO) was used for gating. Unstained, single color and fluorescence-minus-one <lb/>controls were used to identify stained populations. For T lymphocyte suppression assay, control <lb/>CD4+ CD25+ lymphocytes were sorted from PBMC cultures incubated with extracts from <lb/>unrelated control or MS spore-forming bacteria in Treg-differentiating conditions on Aria III cell <lb/>sorter (BD Biosciences) and cultured with CD4+ CD25-from the same donor pre-loaded with a <lb/>CFSE cell division tracker kit. Statistical significance of expression changes in markers of T <lb/>lymphocyte differentiation and proliferation was determined using two-tailed Student&apos;s t test to <lb/>compare samples from different donors and two-tailed repeated measures t test to compare <lb/>samples from the same donor. GraphPad Prism 6 software was used to analyze and plot the data. <lb/>P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability: <lb/>All 16S amplicon sequencing data presented in this article are available from the corresponding <lb/>author upon request. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References: <lb/>1. <lb/>Itoh, K., and T. Mitsuoka. 1985. Comparison of media for isolation of mouse <lb/>anaerobic faecal bacteria. Lab Anim 19: 353-358. <lb/>2. <lb/>Itoh, K., and T. Mitsuoka. 1985. Characterization of clostridia isolated from faeces of <lb/>limited flora mice and their effect on caecal size when associated with germ-free <lb/>mice. Lab Anim 19: 111-118. <lb/>3. <lb/>Gaboriau-Routhiau, V., S. Rakotobe, E. Lecuyer, I. Mulder, A. Lan, C. Bridonneau, V. <lb/>Rochet, A. Pisi, M. De Paepe, G. Brandi, G. Eberl, J. Snel, D. Kelly, and N. Cerf-<lb/>Bensussan. 2009. The key role of segmented filamentous bacteria in the coordinated <lb/>maturation of gut helper T cell responses. Immunity 31: 677-689. <lb/>4. <lb/>Atarashi, K., T. Tanoue, K. Oshima, W. Suda, Y. Nagano, H. Nishikawa, S. Fukuda, T. <lb/>Saito, S. Narushima, K. Hase, S. Kim, J. V. Fritz, P. Wilmes, S. Ueha, K. Matsushima, H. <lb/>Ohno, B. Olle, S. Sakaguchi, T. Taniguchi, H. Morita, M. Hattori, and K. Honda. 2013. <lb/>Treg induction by a rationally selected mixture of Clostridia strains from the human <lb/>microbiota. Nature 500: 232-236. <lb/>5. <lb/>Atarashi, K., T. Tanoue, T. Shima, A. Imaoka, T. Kuwahara, Y. Momose, G. Cheng, S. <lb/>Yamasaki, T. Saito, Y. Ohba, T. Taniguchi, K. Takeda, S. Hori, Ivanov, II, Y. Umesaki, K. <lb/>Itoh, and K. Honda. 2011. Induction of colonic regulatory T cells by indigenous <lb/>Clostridium species. Science 331: 337-341. <lb/>6. <lb/>Ochoa-Reparaz, J., and L. H. Kasper. 2017. The influence of gut-derived CD39 <lb/>regulatory T cells in CNS demyelinating disease. Transl Res 179: 126-138. <lb/>7. <lb/>Kleinewietfeld, M., and D. A. Hafler. 2014. Regulatory T cells in autoimmune <lb/>neuroinflammation. Immunol Rev 259: 231-244. <lb/>8. <lb/>Dombrowski, Y., T. O&apos;Hagan, M. Dittmer, R. Penalva, S. R. Mayoral, P. Bankhead, S. <lb/>Fleville, G. Eleftheriadis, C. Zhao, M. Naughton, R. Hassan, J. Moffat, J. Falconer, A. <lb/>Boyd, P. Hamilton, I. V. Allen, A. Kissenpfennig, P. N. Moynagh, E. Evergren, B. Perbal, <lb/>A. C. Williams, R. J. Ingram, J. R. Chan, R. J. M. Franklin, and D. C. Fitzgerald. 2017. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Regulatory T cells promote myelin regeneration in the central nervous system. Nat <lb/>Neurosci 20: 674-680. <lb/>9. <lb/>Berer, K., L. A. Gerdes, E. Cekanaviciute, X. Jia, L. Xiao, Z. Xia, C. Liu, L. Klotz, U. <lb/>Stauffer, S. E. Baranzini, T. Kumpfel, R. Hohlfeld, G. Krishnamoorthy, and H. Wekerle. <lb/>2017. Gut microbiota from multiple sclerosis patients enables spontaneous <lb/>autoimmune encephalomyelitis in mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>10. <lb/>Cekanaviciute, E., B. B. Yoo, T. F. Runia, J. W. Debelius, S. Singh, C. A. Nelson, R. <lb/>Kanner, Y. Bencosme, Y. K. Lee, S. L. Hauser, E. Crabtree-Hartman, I. Katz Sand, M. <lb/>Gacias, Y. Zhu, P. Casaccia, B. A. C. Cree, R. Knight, S. K. Mazmanian, and S. E. <lb/>Baranzini. 2017. Gut bacteria from multiple sclerosis patients modulate human T <lb/>cells and exacerbate symptoms in mouse models. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. <lb/>11. <lb/>Caporaso, J. G., C. L. Lauber, W. A. Walters, D. Berg-Lyons, J. Huntley, N. Fierer, S. M. <lb/>Owens, J. Betley, L. Fraser, M. Bauer, N. Gormley, J. A. Gilbert, G. Smith, and R. Knight. <lb/>2012. Ultra-high-throughput microbial community analysis on the Illumina HiSeq <lb/>and MiSeq platforms. Isme J 6: 1621-1624. <lb/>12. <lb/>Navas-Molina, J. A., J. M. Peralta-Sanchez, A. Gonzalez, P. J. McMurdie, Y. Vazquez-<lb/>Baeza, Z. Xu, L. K. Ursell, C. Lauber, H. Zhou, S. J. Song, J. Huntley, G. L. Ackermann, D. <lb/>Berg-Lyons, S. Holmes, J. G. Caporaso, and R. Knight. 2013. Advancing our <lb/>understanding of the human microbiome using QIIME. Methods Enzymol 531: 371-<lb/>444. <lb/>13. <lb/>Kopylova, E., J. A. Navas-Molina, C. Mercier, Z. Z. Xu, F. Mahé, Y. He, H.-W. Zhou, T. <lb/>Rognes, J. G. Caporaso, and R. Knight. 2016. Open-Source Sequence Clustering <lb/>Methods Improve the State Of the Art. mSystems 1. <lb/>14. <lb/>Colwell, R. K., A. Chao, N. J. Gotelli, S.-Y. Lin, C. X. Mao, R. L. Chazdon, and J. T. <lb/>Longino. 2012. Models and estimators linking individual-based and sample-based <lb/>rarefaction, extrapolation and comparison of assemblages. Journal of Plant Ecology <lb/>5: 3-21. <lb/>15. <lb/>Lozupone, C., and R. Knight. 2005. UniFrac: a new phylogenetic method for <lb/>comparing microbial communities. Appl Environ Microbiol 71: 8228-8235. <lb/>16. <lb/>McMurdie, P. J., and S. Holmes. 2013. phyloseq: an R package for reproducible <lb/>interactive analysis and graphics of microbiome census data. PLoS One 8: e61217. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>17. <lb/>McMurdie, P. J., and S. Holmes. 2015. Shiny-phyloseq: Web application for <lb/>interactive microbiome analysis with provenance tracking. Bioinformatics 31: 282-<lb/>283. <lb/>18. <lb/>Joller, N., E. Lozano, P. R. Burkett, B. Patel, S. Xiao, C. Zhu, J. Xia, T. G. Tan, E. Sefik, V. <lb/>Yajnik, A. H. Sharpe, F. J. Quintana, D. Mathis, C. Benoist, D. A. Hafler, and V. K. <lb/>Kuchroo. 2014. Treg cells expressing the coinhibitory molecule TIGIT selectively <lb/>inhibit proinflammatory Th1 and Th17 cell responses. Immunity 40: 569-581. <lb/>19. <lb/>Sarrabayrouse, G., C. Bossard, J. M. Chauvin, A. Jarry, G. Meurette, E. Quevrain, C. <lb/>Bridonneau, L. Preisser, K. Asehnoune, N. Labarriere, F. Altare, H. Sokol, and F. <lb/>Jotereau. 2014. CD4CD8alphaalpha lymphocytes, a novel human regulatory T cell <lb/>subset induced by colonic bacteria and deficient in patients with inflammatory <lb/>bowel disease. PLoS Biol 12: e1001833. <lb/>20. <lb/>Lozupone, C. A., M. Li, T. B. Campbell, S. C. Flores, D. Linderman, M. J. Gebert, R. <lb/>Knight, A. P. Fontenot, and B. E. Palmer. 2013. Alterations in the gut microbiota <lb/>associated with HIV-1 infection. Cell Host Microbe 14: 329-339. <lb/>21. <lb/>Scher, J. U., A. Sczesnak, R. S. Longman, N. Segata, C. Ubeda, C. Bielski, T. Rostron, V. <lb/>Cerundolo, E. G. Pamer, S. B. Abramson, C. Huttenhower, and D. R. Littman. 2013. <lb/>Expansion of intestinal Prevotella copri correlates with enhanced susceptibility to <lb/>arthritis. Elife 2: e01202. <lb/>22. <lb/>Yano, J. M., K. Yu, G. P. Donaldson, G. G. Shastri, P. Ann, L. Ma, C. R. Nagler, R. F. <lb/>Ismagilov, S. K. Mazmanian, and E. Y. Hsiao. 2015. Indigenous bacteria from the gut <lb/>microbiota regulate host serotonin biosynthesis. Cell 161: 264-276. <lb/>23. <lb/>Guo, C. J., F. Y. Chang, T. P. Wyche, K. M. Backus, T. M. Acker, M. Funabashi, M. <lb/>Taketani, M. S. Donia, S. Nayfach, K. S. Pollard, C. S. Craik, B. F. Cravatt, J. Clardy, C. A. <lb/>Voigt, and M. A. Fischbach. 2017. Discovery of Reactive Microbiota-Derived <lb/>Metabolites that Inhibit Host Proteases. Cell 168: 517-526 e518. <lb/>24. <lb/>Hou, L., J. Cooley, R. Swanson, P. C. Ong, R. N. Pike, M. Bogyo, S. T. Olson, and E. <lb/>Remold-O&apos;Donnell. 2015. The protease cathepsin L regulates Th17 cell <lb/>differentiation. J Autoimmun 65: 56-63. <lb/>25. <lb/>Sugita, S., S. Horie, O. Nakamura, Y. Futagami, H. Takase, H. Keino, H. Aburatani, N. <lb/>Katunuma, K. Ishidoh, Y. Yamamoto, and M. Mochizuki. 2008. Retinal pigment <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>epithelium-derived CTLA-2alpha induces TGFbeta-producing T regulatory cells. J <lb/>Immunol 181: 7525-7536. <lb/>26. <lb/>Narushima, S., Y. Sugiura, K. Oshima, K. Atarashi, M. Hattori, M. Suematsu, and K. <lb/>Honda. 2014. Characterization of the 17 strains of regulatory T cell-inducing human-<lb/>derived Clostridia. Gut Microbes 5: 333-339. <lb/>27. <lb/>Arpaia, N., C. Campbell, X. Fan, S. Dikiy, J. van der Veeken, P. deRoos, H. Liu, J. R. <lb/>Cross, K. Pfeffer, P. J. Coffer, and A. Y. Rudensky. 2013. Metabolites produced by <lb/>commensal bacteria promote peripheral regulatory T-cell generation. Nature 504: <lb/>451-455. <lb/>28. <lb/>Furusawa, Y., Y. Obata, S. Fukuda, T. A. Endo, G. Nakato, D. Takahashi, Y. Nakanishi, C. <lb/>Uetake, K. Kato, T. Kato, M. Takahashi, N. N. Fukuda, S. Murakami, E. Miyauchi, S. <lb/>Hino, K. Atarashi, S. Onawa, Y. Fujimura, T. Lockett, J. M. Clarke, D. L. Topping, M. <lb/>Tomita, S. Hori, O. Ohara, T. Morita, H. Koseki, J. Kikuchi, K. Honda, K. Hase, and H. <lb/>Ohno. 2013. Commensal microbe-derived butyrate induces the differentiation of <lb/>colonic regulatory T cells. Nature 504: 446-450. <lb/>29. <lb/>Jangi, S., R. Gandhi, L. M. Cox, N. Li, F. von Glehn, R. Yan, B. Patel, M. A. Mazzola, S. Liu, <lb/>B. L. Glanz, S. Cook, S. Tankou, F. Stuart, K. Melo, P. Nejad, K. Smith, B. D. Topcuolu, J. <lb/>Holden, P. Kivisakk, T. Chitnis, P. L. De Jager, F. J. Quintana, G. K. Gerber, L. Bry, and <lb/>H. L. Weiner. 2016. Alterations of the human gut microbiome in multiple sclerosis. <lb/>Nat Commun 7: 12015. <lb/>30. <lb/>Caputo, A., G. Dubourg, O. Croce, S. Gupta, C. Robert, L. Papazian, J. M. Rolain, and D. <lb/>Raoult. 2015. Whole-genome assembly of Akkermansia muciniphila sequenced <lb/>directly from human stool. Biol Direct 10: 5. <lb/>31. <lb/>Varrin-Doyer, M., C. M. Spencer, U. Schulze-Topphoff, P. A. Nelson, R. M. Stroud, B. A. <lb/>Cree, and S. S. Zamvil. 2012. Aquaporin 4-specific T cells in neuromyelitis optica <lb/>exhibit a Th17 bias and recognize Clostridium ABC transporter. Ann Neurol 72: 53-<lb/>64. <lb/>32. <lb/>Rumah, K. R., J. Linden, V. A. Fischetti, and T. Vartanian. 2013. Isolation of <lb/>Clostridium perfringens type B in an individual at first clinical presentation of <lb/>multiple sclerosis provides clues for environmental triggers of the disease. PLoS One <lb/>8: e76359. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>33. <lb/>Cree, B. A., C. M. Spencer, M. Varrin-Doyer, S. E. Baranzini, and S. S. Zamvil. 2016. Gut <lb/>microbiome analysis in neuromyelitis optica reveals overabundance of Clostridium <lb/>perfringens. Ann Neurol 80: 443-447. <lb/>34. <lb/>Rumah, K. R., Y. Ma, J. R. Linden, M. L. Oo, J. Anrather, N. Schaeren-Wiemers, M. A. <lb/>Alonso, V. A. Fischetti, M. S. McClain, and T. Vartanian. 2015. The Myelin and <lb/>Lymphocyte Protein MAL Is Required for Binding and Activity of Clostridium <lb/>perfringens epsilon-Toxin. PLoS Pathog 11: e1004896. <lb/>35. <lb/>Miller, P. G., M. B. Bonn, C. L. Franklin, A. C. Ericsson, and S. C. McKarns. 2015. TNFR2 <lb/>Deficiency Acts in Concert with Gut Microbiota To Precipitate Spontaneous Sex-<lb/>Biased Central Nervous System Demyelinating Autoimmune Disease. J Immunol 195: <lb/>4668-4684. <lb/>36. <lb/>Coretti, L., C. Cristiano, E. Florio, G. Scala, A. Lama, S. Keller, M. Cuomo, R. Russo, R. <lb/>Pero, O. Paciello, G. Mattace Raso, R. Meli, S. Cocozza, A. Calignano, L. Chiariotti, and <lb/>F. Lembo. 2017. Sex-related alterations of gut microbiota composition in the BTBR <lb/>mouse model of autism spectrum disorder. Sci Rep 7: 45356. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure Legends <lb/>Figure 1. Differences in community composition of spore-forming bacterial fraction in MS <lb/>patients and healthy controls. A-C. Comparison of microbial community composition of <lb/>spore-forming bacterial subset and total stool bacteria in untreated MS patients (n=25) and <lb/>controls (n=24). A. Chao1 metric of alpha diversity. B. Median and range of distances <lb/>(unweighted Unifrac distance matrix) within and between sample groups. C. Mean relative <lb/>abundance of microbial genera. D-F. Comparison of relative abundances of individual microbial <lb/>taxa in untreated MS patients (n=25) and controls (n=24). D. Volcano plot of relative abundance <lb/>distribution of microbial OTUs. X axis, log2 fold of relative abundance ratio between MS <lb/>patients and controls after variance-stabilizing transformation. Y axis, negative log10 of P value, <lb/>negative binomial Wald test, Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons. E, F. <lb/>Relative abundances of bacterial classes Bacilli (E) and Clostridia (F) within phylum Firmicutes <lb/>out of spore-forming bacteria from controls and MS patients. Error bars, mean +/-SEM. CTRL, <lb/>total stool bacteria from controls. CTRL_spore, spore-forming bacteria from controls. MS, total <lb/>stool bacteria from MS patients. MS_spore, spore-forming bacteria from MS patients. <lb/>Figure 2. Spore-forming bacteria from MS patients inhibit IL-10+ Treg differentiation in <lb/>vitro. A, B. Representative flow cytometry plots (A) and quantification (B) of CD4+FoxP3+ <lb/>Tregs within CD3+ lymphocytes differentiated in response to spore-forming bacteria isolated <lb/>from controls or untreated MS patients. N = 7 PBMC donors; each dot represents an average <lb/>response from PBMC donor to isolates from 6 control or MS bacteria donors. **P&lt;0.01, two-<lb/>tailed repeated measures t test. C, D. Representative flow cytometry plots (C) and quantification <lb/>(D) of IL-10+ lymphocyte population within CD3+CD4+FoxP3+ Tregs differentiated in <lb/>response to spore-forming bacteria isolated from controls or untreated MS patients. N = 6 <lb/>bacteria donors per group. *P&lt;0.05, two-tailed t test. Error bars, mean +/-SEM. Experiment was <lb/>repeated with non-overlapping PBMC and bacterial donors and gave the same results. E. <lb/>Quantification of T effector cell proliferation in response to Tregs differentiated in presence of <lb/>spore-forming bacteria from MS patients or controls. N = 3 bacterial donors per group, each <lb/>representing an average of 3 technical replicates. F Linear correlation between IL-10+ <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>population within CD3+ CD4+ FoxP3+ Tregs and Clostridia-Bacilli relative abundances. R 2 = <lb/>0.214, p = 0.0459. Red dots, MS patients. Blue dots, controls. R^2 = 0.214, p = 0.046. <lb/>Figure 3. Spore-forming bacteria composition is correlated with T lymphocyte phenotypes <lb/>in vivo. A. Clinical EAE scores of mice that after antibiotic treatment had been colonized with <lb/>spore-forming bacteria from controls (CTRL_spore) or MS patients (MS_spore) for 2 weeks, or <lb/>kept on antibiotics (ABX) or in SPF condition as controls, prior to induction of EAE at 9-10 <lb/>weeks of age. N = 5-10 mice per group. B, C. Principal coordinate plot of beta diversity (PCoA; <lb/>unweighted Unifrac) (B) and genus-level taxonomical distribution (C) of mouse fecal microbiota <lb/>at 2 weeks of colonization with spore-forming bacteria, 2 separate experiments. D. Bacterial <lb/>genera whose abundance is correlated with changes in immune cell differentiation in gnotobiotic <lb/>mice are shown. The linear correlation between relative abundances of bacterial genera and the <lb/>percentage of IL-10+ regulatory and IFN+ Th1 out of CD4+ Th lymphocytes from both spleens <lb/>and mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN) of mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria are depicted <lb/>as a heatmap. Same samples as in B-C. Only the genera that show significant linear correlation <lb/>with immune parameters (p&gt;0.05 after Benjamini-Hochberg adjustment for multiple <lb/>comparisons) are included in the heat map. Red rectangle, putative pro-inflammatory subset. <lb/>Blue rectangle, putative anti-inflammatory subset. Red font, taxa significantly increased in mice <lb/>colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients compared to controls. Blue font, taxa <lb/>significantly reduced in mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients compared <lb/>to controls. E. Examples of positive and negative correlation between bacteria and Th <lb/>lymphocyte differentiation from D. <lb/>Figure 4. Increased Akkermansia is linked with MS-associated changes in spore-forming <lb/>bacteria and pro-inflammatory T lymphocytes. A. Principal coordinate plot of beta diversity <lb/>(PCoA; unweighted Unifrac) of mouse fecal microbiota excluding Akkermansia at 2 weeks of <lb/>colonization with spore-forming bacteria, 2 separate experiments, colored by Akkermansia <lb/>presence (red to green: low to high). p &lt; 0.001, significant contribution of Akkermansia presence <lb/>to determining distance variation (adonis method for continuous variables). B. Relative <lb/>abundance of Akkermansia in controls and MS patients used for isolation of spore-forming <lb/>bacteria. p = 1.5E-09, negative binomial Wald test, Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>comparisons (across all 144 species detected in the dataset). C. Linear correlation of relative <lb/>abundance of Akkermansia with IFN+ Th1 lymphocyte differentiation in spleens of mice <lb/>colonized with spore-forming bacteria. R^2 = 0.18, p= 0.0003. D. Bacterial genera significantly <lb/>correlated with Akkermansia in vivo. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Material <lb/>Supplementary Table 1. Spore-forming OTUs that were significantly different between MS <lb/>patients and controls. Negative binomial Wald test with Benjamini-Hochberg correction for <lb/>multiple comparisons. <lb/>Supplementary Table 2. Genera that were significantly different between antibiotic-treated <lb/>mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients and controls. Negative <lb/>binomial Wald test with Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons. <lb/>Supplementary Table 3. OTUs that were significantly different between antibiotic-treated <lb/>mice colonized with spore-forming bacteria from MS patients and controls. Negative <lb/>binomial Wald test with Benjamini-Hochberg correction for multiple comparisons. <lb/>Supplementary Figure 1. Relative abundance of Clostridium perfringens OTUs in spore-<lb/>forming bacteria of MS patients and controls. N=30 patients, 24 controls. X axis, OTU IDs <lb/>taken from GreenGenes 13.8 database. Y axis, relative abundances after rarefaction to 10,000 <lb/>reads/sample. Last two columns (highlighted on graph) represent the sum of all individual OTUs. <lb/>Table 1. Subject characteristics <lb/>Feature <lb/>Cases <lb/>Controls <lb/>n <lb/>25 <lb/>24 <lb/>Proportion female (%) <lb/>80.0% <lb/>12.5% <lb/>Mean age (years [stdev]) <lb/>44.0 (±13.0) <lb/>49.3 (±12.0) <lb/>Average BMI (stdev) <lb/>23.8 (±4.7) <lb/>24.2 (±4.2) <lb/>Average disease duration (Years [stdev]) <lb/>13.5 (±11.9) <lb/>N/A <lb/>Proportion Off-therapy <lb/>28% <lb/>N/A <lb/>Proportion therapy naïve <lb/>72% <lb/>N/A </div>


	</text>
</tei>
