<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Knowledge and attitudes of Ebola among the general public of Trinidad and Tobago during the <lb/>2014-15 West Africa outbreak <lb/>S Pooransingh, S Mohammed, K Melville, C Mohammed, M Mohammed, R Mohammed, W <lb/>Mootoo, M Morris, D Motilal, B Bhagwandeen, I Dialsingh <lb/>All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Objective: Health system resilience and resilience of a country include the capacity of health <lb/>personnel, institutions, and populations to prepare for and effectively respond to crises. This <lb/>study investigates the knowledge and attitudes of the public concerning Ebola Virus Disease in <lb/>Trinidad and Tobago. <lb/>Design and Methods: A cross sectional study whereby respondents (n = 920) were sampled from <lb/>public places. Data were collected via interviewer administered questionnaires. Data were <lb/>analysed using SPSS version 23. <lb/>Results: The response rate was 67.6 % (622/920). The main age category of responders was the <lb/>20 to 30 year age category (40.5%); responders were mostly female (58.0 %). Regarding <lb/>knowledge, there were significant differences among occupational categories (F = 2.811, df1 = 6, <lb/>df2 = 571, p-value = 0.011). Tukey&apos;s HSD post hoc test revealed that the mean knowledge scores <lb/>for professional and sales occupations differed significantly (p-value = 0.003). There was a <lb/>significant association between being afraid to go for treatment and age (p-value = 0.001). <lb/>Significant associations were also found between occupational grouping and education <lb/>attainment with opinion about the preparedness of private medical facilities, likelihood to shun <lb/>family members with Ebola, being afraid to go for treatment and preference for traditional <lb/>medicine (p-value &lt;0.05). <lb/>Conclusion: <lb/>This study highlights opportunities for community engagement to enhance health system <lb/>resilience during outbreaks which would maximise national and global health security. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Countries have been working to strengthen their alert and response capacities for acute public <lb/>health threats since 2007 under the International Health Regulations (IHR 2005) (1). Several <lb/>events have served to test these efforts such as the H1N1 Pandemic 2009, the 2011 Japan <lb/>earthquake and tsunami, the emergence of Middle East Respiratory Syndrome (MERS) in 2012, <lb/>various global terrorist events, Zika in the Americas in 2015 and the Ebola (EVD) outbreak in <lb/>West Africa in 2014/5 (1). Ebola constituted a Public Health Emergency of International <lb/>Concern as it left Africa for the first time, presenting a real threat to other countries. No longer <lb/>could Ebola be considered a disease of &apos;over there&apos; (2). The Ebola epidemic raised to the fore the <lb/>fragility of health systems. It showed what happens when a crisis hits and the health systems are <lb/>not prepared (3). <lb/>EVD is highly contagious with human to human spread via direct bodily contact with the blood, <lb/>secretions, organs or other bodily fluids of infected people, and with surfaces and materials (e.g. <lb/>bedding, clothing) contaminated with these fluids. The case fatality rate is high if persons are not <lb/>treated (1,4). <lb/>With increased air travel and persons from West Africa setting abroad including in Trinidad and <lb/>with links to their home country, the likelihood of a case or a contact arriving into the country or <lb/>any country, though rare, is now possible. Countries need to increase their resilience i.e. the <lb/>intrinsic capacity of individuals, populations and infrastructure to rebound from shocks (5,6). <lb/>The status of Trinidad and Tobago&apos;s health systems preparedness is known from annual IHR <lb/>2005 status reports; it was therefore decided to seek the public&apos;s knowledge and attitudes on <lb/>Ebola as the community is a central player in in the emergency response and a successful <lb/>response relies on the participation and cooperation of the public. A well informed and well-<lb/>rehearsed public would be better able to act faster and effectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>Study Design <lb/>A cross-sectional survey was undertaken. <lb/>Study Period <lb/>The survey was undertaken from January to May 2016. <lb/>Study setting <lb/>The study was undertaken in public spaces in Trinidad and Tobago (TT), a twin island republic <lb/>in the chain of islands collectively termed the Caribbean. The population of TT is approximately <lb/>1.4 million persons (7). <lb/>Study Population <lb/>The study population comprised the adult (18 years and older) population of Trinidad and <lb/>Tobago. This included males and females of varying ethnic compositions, representative of the <lb/>general population. Responders were chosen by convenience sampling. Questionnaires were <lb/>distributed along busy streets, at malls, near bus stops, as well as other high traffic areas across <lb/>the different regions of Trinidad and Tobago. <lb/>Sample size <lb/>The sample size for the study was initially calculated at the onset as 913 responders. <lb/>Data Collection <lb/>A total of 920 questionnaires were distributed across Trinidad and Tobago. Responders were <lb/>briefed on the study&apos;s objectives before verbal consent was obtained for participation. <lb/>Interviewers assured the responders that their responses would be anonymous, that there would <lb/>be no way identifying them through the results. The questionnaire collected demographic <lb/>information, general knowledge and attitudes towards Ebola and views of responders on the <lb/>healthcare system in the country. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Data analysis <lb/>All data collected were analyzed using SPSS version 23. A knowledge scale was constructed <lb/>using the sum total score of nineteen binary questions concerning respondents&apos; knowledge about <lb/>EVD. The two-sample independent t-test was used to compare the mean knowledge score <lb/>between males and females. An ANOVA test was used to determine whether there were <lb/>differences among categories in the age, occupation and education variables. Tukey&apos;s HSD <lb/>Procedure was carried out to determine which pairs of mean scores across occupational <lb/>categories differed (adjusted p-value &lt;0.05). In order to determine if there was a relationship <lb/>between the attitudes toward Ebola and demographic factors (age, gender, occupation and <lb/>education), Chi-Squared Tests of Independence were carried out. In the cases where at least <lb/>20% of the cells had expected counts less than 5, Fisher&apos;s Exact Test was used. <lb/>Ethical Approval <lb/>The University of the West Indies, St. Augustine, Trinidad and Tobago Ethics Committee <lb/>granted ethical approval for this study (Reference: CEC063/11/15). <lb/>FINDINGS <lb/>A total of 920 participants were approached to participate of which 622 (67.6%) agreed. There <lb/>were 42% male and 58% female responders. The ethnic groups of the responders comprised <lb/>those of East Indian origin (35.9%), African origin (27.2%) and other, including mixed ethnicity <lb/>(36.9%). The majority of responders reported attaining tertiary education (55.6%) followed by <lb/>secondary education (41.1%). Table 1 summarises the age breakdown of responders and Table 2 <lb/>the occupational categories. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Table showing the age and occupational groupings breakdown of responders <lb/>Age Group (years) <lb/>Frequency (%) <lb/>Occupational Category <lb/>Frequency (%) <lb/>&lt;20 <lb/>74 (11.2) <lb/>Managers/Directors/Senior <lb/>Officials <lb/>58 (9.9) <lb/>20 -30 <lb/>267 (40.5) <lb/>Professional Occupations <lb/>78 (13.3) <lb/>31 -40 <lb/>128 (19.4) <lb/>Administrative/Secretarial <lb/>32 (5.5) <lb/>41 -50 <lb/>87 (13.2) <lb/>Skilled Trades <lb/>17 (2.9) <lb/>&gt;50 <lb/>104 (15.7) <lb/>Caring/Leisure/Other <lb/>293 (50.1) <lb/>Sales/Customer Service <lb/>102 (17.4) <lb/>Elementary Occupations <lb/>5 (0.9) <lb/>Total <lb/>660 (100.0) <lb/>585 (100.0) <lb/>Findings related to Knowledge about Ebola <lb/>In terms of knowledge questions about Ebola, more than 70% of responders knew what EVD was and how <lb/>it is transmitted. Forty-five per cent (45%) of responders reported that there is a cure for EVD. The average <lb/>knowledge score, based on 622 (67.6%) participants, was 10.61 (sd = 3.756). A Cronbach&apos;s alpha <lb/>coefficient of 0.681 indicated the constructed knowledge scale was a relatively consistent measure of the <lb/>concept. <lb/>There were no differences in the knowledge scores between males and females (T=-0.959, df= 608, p-value <lb/>= 0.338). <lb/>There were no significant differences in the knowledge scores among the five age groups (F = 2.186, df1 = <lb/>4, df2= 613, p-value = 0.069). However, there were significant differences among the mean knowledge <lb/>score of the seven occupational categories (F = 2.811, df1 = 6, df2 = 571, p-value = 0.011). It was found <lb/>that the mean knowledge scores for professional and sales occupations differed significantly (Tukey&apos;s HSD <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>adjusted p-value = 0.003). There were also significant differences among education categories (p value = <lb/>&lt;0.001). Table 2 summarizes the results. <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Knowledge of Ebola Scores versus Age, Gender, Occupation and Education <lb/>Knowledge Scores <lb/>Independent <lb/>Variable <lb/>Mean (95% CI) <lb/>Standard <lb/>Deviation <lb/>Test <lb/>statistic <lb/>p-value <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>10.49 (10.05, 10.93) <lb/>3.586 <lb/>T = <lb/>-0.959 <lb/>0.338* <lb/>Female <lb/>10.78 (10.38, 11.18) <lb/>3.837 <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>&lt;20 <lb/>9.43 (8.42, 10.45) <lb/>4.237 <lb/>F = <lb/>2.186 <lb/>0.069** <lb/>20-30 <lb/>10.83 (10.41, 11.25) <lb/>3.465 <lb/>31-40 <lb/>10.57 (9.86, 11.28) <lb/>3.929 <lb/>41-50 <lb/>10.99 (10.14, 11.83) <lb/>3.678 <lb/>&gt;50 <lb/>10.78 (10.00, 11.56) <lb/>3.765 <lb/>Occupation <lb/>Managers/Directors/Senior <lb/>Officials <lb/>10.76 (9.88, 11.64) <lb/>3.352 <lb/>F = <lb/>2.811 <lb/>0.011** <lb/>Professional Occupations <lb/>12.05 (11.30, 12.81) <lb/>3.320 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Administrative/Secretarial <lb/>10.41 (8.86, 11.95) <lb/>4.279 <lb/>Skilled Trades <lb/>10.44 (8.33, 12.54) <lb/>3.949 <lb/>Caring/Leisure/Other <lb/>10.76 (10.31, 11.20) <lb/>3.852 <lb/>Sales/Customer Service <lb/>9.96 (9.32, 10.60) <lb/>3.226 <lb/>Elementary Occupations <lb/>8.40 (5.28, 11.52) <lb/>2.510 <lb/>Education <lb/>Primary <lb/>8.20 (5.67, 10.73) <lb/>5.415 <lb/>F = <lb/>16.647 <lb/>&lt; 0.001** <lb/>Secondary <lb/>9.81 (9.32, 10.29) <lb/>3.872 <lb/>Tertiary <lb/>11.32 (10.96, 11.68) <lb/>3.355 <lb/>*Two sample t-Test <lb/>**ANOVA Test <lb/>Findings related to Attitudes towards Ebola <lb/>Of the 586 participants, 50% believed that an outbreak of the EVD was very likely in TT and the most <lb/>common reason cited for this was easy travel between countries. Furthermore, 97% thought the citizens of <lb/>TT were not prepared for an outbreak. In terms of age groups, 355 (60.1%) of the 591 respondents were <lb/>between the ages of 20 and 40 years and believed the country is not prepared to deal with an outbreak of <lb/>the EVD. It was found that opinions on the likelihood of an outbreak were not dependent on gender, age, <lb/>occupation and education (p-values &gt; 0.05). <lb/>The top three reasons given for the country being ill-prepared for an outbreak were outdated healthcare <lb/>facilities, lack of education and awareness, and ignorance and laziness among the public. <lb/>The majority of participants thought both private and public health care facilities were not prepared to deal <lb/>with an outbreak. They reported that an outbreak would result in death and panic. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>The majority of responders (62%) would be likely or very likely to shun someone with the disease; while <lb/>21% were neutral in response. When asked about a family member with EVD, 24% were neutral, and 35% <lb/>likely or very likely to shun their family member. <lb/>Almost one fifth of responders said they would be afraid to go for treatment; 14% stated they would opt for <lb/>traditional medicine over a health facility. There was no association between citizens who believed there <lb/>is a cure for the disease and those who would rather use traditional medicine than go to a medical facility <lb/>(p-value = 0.307). <lb/>Being afraid to go for treatment was significantly associated with age of the respondent (p-value = 0.001). <lb/>Occupational category was found to be significantly associated with opinion towards private medical <lb/>facilities preparedness, likelihood to shun family members, being afraid to go for treatment and preference <lb/>for traditional medicine (p-value &lt; 0.05). <lb/>Education was found to be significantly associated with opinion towards private medical facilities <lb/>preparedness, likelihood to shun a person with EVD, being afraid to go for treatment and preference for <lb/>traditional medicine (p value &lt; 0.05). <lb/>No association with any aspect of attitude was found with gender (p-values &gt; 0.05). <lb/>Table 3 <lb/>Association of Attitudes toward Ebola and Age Category <lb/>Variable <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>p-value <lb/>1 &lt;20 <lb/>20-30 <lb/>31-40 <lb/>41-50 <lb/>&gt;50 <lb/>Public medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>No <lb/>63 <lb/>242 <lb/>107 <lb/>71 <lb/>78 <lb/>0.926*** <lb/>Yes <lb/>2 <lb/>9 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>(95% C.I.) <lb/>1.171 (0.247, <lb/>5.558) <lb/>1.766 <lb/>(0.346, <lb/>9.018) <lb/>1.331 <lb/>(0.215, <lb/>8.223) <lb/>1.615 (0.287, <lb/>9.108) <lb/>Private <lb/>medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>No <lb/>46 <lb/>194 <lb/>86 <lb/>62 <lb/>69 <lb/>0.477**** <lb/>Yes <lb/>15 <lb/>48 <lb/>19 <lb/>9 <lb/>14 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Odds Ratio <lb/>(95% C.I.) <lb/>0.759 (0.391, <lb/>1.472) <lb/>0.678 <lb/>(0.315, <lb/>1.457) <lb/>0.445 <lb/>(0.179, <lb/>1.106) <lb/>0.622 (0.275, <lb/>1.410) <lb/>Likely to shun <lb/>person? <lb/>Not Very Likely <lb/>3 <lb/>24 <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>0.414**** <lb/>Not Likely <lb/>5 <lb/>20 <lb/>8 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>19 <lb/>55 <lb/>19 <lb/>9 <lb/>13 <lb/>Likely <lb/>36 <lb/>16 <lb/>9 <lb/>13 <lb/>Very Likely <lb/>24 <lb/>106 <lb/>51 <lb/>39 <lb/>42 <lb/>Likely to shun <lb/>family <lb/>member? <lb/>Not Very Likely <lb/>11 <lb/>53 <lb/>29 <lb/>16 <lb/>22 <lb/>0.775**** <lb/>Not Likely <lb/>10 <lb/>47 <lb/>28 <lb/>12 <lb/>18 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>17 <lb/>58 <lb/>25 <lb/>17 <lb/>25 <lb/>Likely <lb/>12 <lb/>39 <lb/>16 <lb/>12 <lb/>10 <lb/>Very Likely <lb/>17 <lb/>55 <lb/>18 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>Afraid to go <lb/>for treatment? <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>32 <lb/>136 <lb/>72 <lb/>41 <lb/>62 <lb/>0.001**** <lb/>Disagree <lb/>15 <lb/>46 <lb/>18 <lb/>11 <lb/>6 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>12 <lb/>26 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>Agree <lb/>1 <lb/>22 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>Strongly Agree <lb/>7 <lb/>24 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/>Rather use <lb/>traditional <lb/>medicine? <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>33 <lb/>138 <lb/>68 <lb/>42 <lb/>62 <lb/>0.402**** <lb/>Disagree <lb/>11 <lb/>35 <lb/>19 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>11 <lb/>44 <lb/>13 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>Agree <lb/>5 <lb/>18 <lb/>9 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Strongly Agree <lb/>5 <lb/>19 <lb/>8 <lb/>5 <lb/>9 <lb/>*** <lb/>Fisher&apos;s Exact Test <lb/>****χ 2 Test <lb/>1 Reference Category <lb/>Table 4 <lb/>Association of Attitudes toward Ebola and Occupation <lb/>Variable <lb/>Occupation <lb/>p-<lb/>value <lb/>1 Manager <lb/>Professional <lb/>Administrative <lb/>Skilled <lb/>Trade <lb/>Caring <lb/>Sales <lb/>Elementary <lb/>No <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Public medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>Yes <lb/>54 <lb/>69 <lb/>30 <lb/>13 <lb/>262 <lb/>92 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.607* <lb/>** <lb/>Odds <lb/>Ratio <lb/>(95% <lb/>C.I.) <lb/>3.130 (0.340, <lb/>28.824) <lb/>3.724 (0.324, <lb/>42.834) <lb/>4.154 <lb/>(0.243, <lb/>70.896) <lb/>2.669 <lb/>(0.342, <lb/>20.836) <lb/>0.587 <lb/>(0.036, <lb/>9.576) <lb/>Private medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>No <lb/>47 <lb/>60 <lb/>28 <lb/>4 <lb/>208 <lb/>75 <lb/>5 <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>*** <lb/>Yes <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>9 <lb/>59 <lb/>11 <lb/>0 <lb/>Odds <lb/>Ratio <lb/>(95% <lb/>C.I.) <lb/>1.567 (0.501, <lb/>4.896) <lb/>1.741 (0.462, <lb/>6.561) <lb/>21.150 <lb/>(4.739, <lb/>94.384) <lb/>2.654 <lb/>(1.010, <lb/>6.973) <lb/>1.379 <lb/>(0.451, <lb/>4.218) <lb/>Likely to shun <lb/>person? <lb/>Not <lb/>Very <lb/>Likely <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>28 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.116* <lb/>** <lb/>Not <lb/>Likely <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>17 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>5 <lb/>18 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>55 <lb/>19 <lb/>2 <lb/>Likely <lb/>9 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>41 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>Very <lb/>Likely <lb/>33 <lb/>39 <lb/>11 <lb/>7 <lb/>119 <lb/>34 <lb/>2 <lb/>Likely to shun <lb/>family member? <lb/>Not <lb/>Very <lb/>Likely <lb/>9 <lb/>18 <lb/>11 <lb/>8 <lb/>51 <lb/>27 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.014* <lb/>** <lb/>Not <lb/>Likely <lb/>9 <lb/>21 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>58 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>14 <lb/>12 <lb/>7 <lb/>3 <lb/>72 <lb/>24 <lb/>1 <lb/>Likely <lb/>5 <lb/>12 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>44 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>Very <lb/>Likely <lb/>17 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>58 <lb/>17 <lb/>2 <lb/>Afraid to go for <lb/>treatment? <lb/>Strongl <lb/>y <lb/>Disagr <lb/>ee <lb/>35 <lb/>49 <lb/>24 <lb/>10 <lb/>161 <lb/>47 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.044* <lb/>** <lb/>Disagr <lb/>ee <lb/>11 <lb/>14 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>45 <lb/>13 <lb/>0 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>31 <lb/>7 <lb/>1 <lb/>Agree <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>32 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Strongl <lb/>y <lb/>Agree <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>32 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>Rather use <lb/>traditional <lb/>medicine? <lb/>Strongl <lb/>y <lb/>Disagr <lb/>ee <lb/>30 <lb/>50 <lb/>21 <lb/>10 <lb/>169 <lb/>43 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.039* <lb/>** <lb/>Disagr <lb/>ee <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>8 <lb/>3 <lb/>30 <lb/>14 <lb/>1 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>45 <lb/>19 <lb/>1 <lb/>Agree <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>17 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>Strongl <lb/>y <lb/>Agree <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>23 <lb/>11 <lb/>1 <lb/>*** <lb/>Fisher&apos;s Exact Test <lb/>****χ 2 Test <lb/>1 Reference Category <lb/>Table 5 <lb/>Association of Attitudes toward Ebola and Education <lb/>Variable <lb/>Education <lb/>p-value <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Primary Secondary <lb/>Tertiary <lb/>Public <lb/>medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>No <lb/>15 <lb/>223 <lb/>311 <lb/>0.216**** <lb/>Yes <lb/>2 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>(95% C.I.) <lb/>0.370 (0.075, 1.823) <lb/>0.265 <lb/>(0.054, <lb/>1.305) <lb/>Private <lb/>medical <lb/>facilities <lb/>prepared? <lb/>No <lb/>9 <lb/>179 <lb/>257 <lb/>0.004**** <lb/>Yes <lb/>8 <lb/>48 <lb/>49 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Odds Ratio <lb/>(95% C.I.) <lb/>0.302 (0.111, 0.824) <lb/>0.214 <lb/>(0.079, <lb/>0.583) <lb/>Likely to <lb/>shun <lb/>person? <lb/>Not Very Likely <lb/>3 <lb/>34 <lb/>18 <lb/>0.006*** <lb/>Not Likely <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>22 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>0 <lb/>47 <lb/>64 <lb/>Likely <lb/>1 <lb/>33 <lb/>45 <lb/>Very Likely <lb/>9 <lb/>89 <lb/>161 <lb/>Likely to <lb/>shun family <lb/>member? <lb/>Not Very Likely <lb/>2 <lb/>56 <lb/>73 <lb/>0.909*** <lb/>Not Likely <lb/>2 <lb/>42 <lb/>70 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>5 <lb/>59 <lb/>73 <lb/>Likely <lb/>3 <lb/>37 <lb/>47 <lb/>Very Likely <lb/>3 <lb/>45 <lb/>64 <lb/>Afraid to go <lb/>for <lb/>treatment? <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>4 <lb/>128 <lb/>207 <lb/>&lt;0.001*** <lb/>Disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>31 <lb/>59 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>3 <lb/>27 <lb/>22 <lb/>Agree <lb/>1 <lb/>13 <lb/>18 <lb/>Strongly Agree <lb/>5 <lb/>40 <lb/>22 <lb/>Rather use <lb/>traditional <lb/>medicine? <lb/>Strongly <lb/>Disagree <lb/>3 <lb/>137 <lb/>197 <lb/>0.013*** <lb/>Disagree <lb/>2 <lb/>31 <lb/>48 <lb/>Neutral <lb/>5 <lb/>32 <lb/>46 <lb/>Agree <lb/>1 <lb/>19 <lb/>16 <lb/>Strongly Agree <lb/>4 <lb/>21 <lb/>19 <lb/>*** <lb/>Fisher&apos;s Exact Test <lb/>****χ 2 Test <lb/>1 Reference Category <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Preparedness <lb/>Further Chi-Squared Tests were carried out to determine the dependence between having a preparedness <lb/>plan for an outbreak of EVD and demographic factors. In the cases where at least 20% of the cells had <lb/>expected counts less than 5, Fisher&apos;s Exact Test was used. It was found that preparedness did not depend <lb/>on demographic factors (p-values &gt; 0.05). <lb/>Obtaining Information about Ebola <lb/>Of the 598 respondents who responded to this question, 499 (83.4%) obtained information from various <lb/>forms of media. Of the 499 responders, the majority (53.3%) were under 30 years of age. However, it was <lb/>found that the method by which information was obtained was independent of the individual&apos;s age (p-value <lb/>= 0.673). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The study&apos;s response rate of 67% presented some useful findings about the public&apos;s knowledge <lb/>and attitudes towards Ebola. <lb/>Females outnumbered males but this was somewhat expected since the data collection took place <lb/>at shopping areas during the day time when more men than women are likely to be at work. The <lb/>study revealed some useful findings for improving health and healthcare during an outbreak. For <lb/>example, the significant difference in knowledge scores noted between professional and sales <lb/>occupations could direct health education measures towards certain occupational groupings. <lb/>There was no association between age group and knowledge scores; in Nigeria, sub optimal <lb/>knowledge was found among secondary school students despite a case of imported EVD in 2014 <lb/>(8). <lb/>There was a significant association between age group and being afraid to seek treatment. Fear of <lb/>seeking treatment suggests a lack of knowledge. The findings show that education level was also <lb/>significantly associated with being afraid to seek treatment. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Occupational grouping and educational category were associated with likelihood to shun <lb/>someone with the disease, being afraid to go for treatment and choice of traditional medicine. <lb/>Education has been found to influence people&apos;s knowledge about EVD in Nigeria (9). In Uganda <lb/>being educated beyond primary level was a significant predictor of awareness towards EVD and <lb/>Marburg (10). Our survey showed a significant association between education level and <lb/>knowledge about EVD. These findings have potentially serious implications for the health <lb/>system during an outbreak and in peace time as this factor likely applies to all disease and <lb/>conditions. When patients are prepared to anticipate an untoward situation, they are more likely <lb/>to cope effectively (11). If persons do not present for treatment, their risk of a poor outcome <lb/>increases. If they are likely to shun those who are ill, the likelihood of spread would be greater <lb/>since infection control measures would not be maintained. A knowledge attitude and practices <lb/>survey undertaken in Liberia (12) found that more than 90% of responders were fearful of EVD <lb/>patients and of those who live with EVD patients. Choosing to attend traditional healers will lead <lb/>to further spread as these practitioners would not usually have personal protective equipment and <lb/>the appropriate training in their usage. <lb/>A cause for concern was the finding of the likelihood to shun someone with the disease if you <lb/>were in a caring occupation. The health workforce density in Guinea, Sierra Leone and Liberia <lb/>which were the three most affected countries is less than 1.5 per 10 000 population, 2.2 per 10 <lb/>000 population and less than 3.7 per 10 000 population, respectively (13). In comparison, in TT <lb/>there are 8 physicians per 10000 people; there are 26 per 10 000 in the USA (14). According to <lb/>WHO at least 23 physicians, nurses and midwives per 10 000 population are needed for well -<lb/>functioning primary healthcare interventions (15). The workforce should be well-qualified, <lb/>capable, responsive and efficient. Lack of a skilled workforce was found to be a major factor in <lb/>controlling the outbreaks. Lack of knowledge about basic infection prevention and control <lb/>measures among health care workers was a critical factor in the outbreak response. Lack of PPE <lb/>and knowing who to report to affected the outcome of the outbreaks (7). Training and rehearsing <lb/>are critical to a smooth response (16,17,18). However it should be noted that in several studies <lb/>health workers indicated a reluctance to present to work under emergency conditions because of <lb/>competing priorities such as family responsibility. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>The Government and Public Health practitioners need to change the mindset of the public by <lb/>providing training and education. When persons are educated and possess the skills to manage a <lb/>disease which have been rehearsed the fears become less. <lb/>Responders obtained their information from various media sources. Media coverage can have a <lb/>great impact. Governments may therefore use this route for dissemination of clear, accurate <lb/>information during outbreaks (19). <lb/>The little confidence in the health system for handling an outbreak was attributed to a perception <lb/>that facilities are outdated along with an indifferent attitude. It is noteworthy that responders also <lb/>had little confidence in private facilities in addition to the public facilities. It seems the <lb/>Government of TT needs to act to change this perception and /modify their current strategy to <lb/>inform and educate the public. <lb/>The study shows many potential areas for capacity strengthening not only for EVD but for any <lb/>disease/event that poses a threat to national and thus global health security. The responders are <lb/>not totally incorrect in their perception that the country is not prepared for an outbreak, since <lb/>Trinidad and Tobago has not yet fully met its obligations under the IHR 2005. <lb/>To build a resilient health system there is a need for community engagement which can aid <lb/>containment efforts during an outbreak. In addition to the healthcare workers who need to train <lb/>and to exercise their preparedness plans, the community needs to be involved in the planning and <lb/>preparedness. In addition to health system strengthening in terms of surveillance and response <lb/>capacity to early detect and manage outbreaks, the community needs to be engaged and made <lb/>aware of the risks for each potential threat and of their roles and responsibilities in securing <lb/>national health security. This could address the issue of staff not presenting to work since <lb/>community involvement in planning could positively influence decisions healthcare workers take <lb/>during an emergency with respect to work and surge capacity. In Nigeria respondents suggested <lb/>sensitisation of communities for effective prevention and control. A survey in the USA stated the <lb/>need for honest accurate information, &apos;even if that information worried people.&apos; The survey <lb/>report indicated that &apos;These results suggest the value of proactive communications designed to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>inform the lay public&apos;s decisions, thoughts, and emotions, and informed by concurrent surveys of <lb/>their responses and needs&apos; (20). <lb/>Limitations <lb/>The study used convenience sampling which could affect the generalizability of the findings. In <lb/>terms of the response rate, the non-responders were in the minority. The demographic <lb/>characteristics (age, sex) of the non-responders were consistent with those of respondents and <lb/>hence we could have some confidence in the findings from the 622 responders. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Ebola virus disease was chosen for this study as this disease was of grave concern at the time of <lb/>the outbreaks since the disease left the African continent for the first time. To quote Dr Keiji <lb/>Fukuda, a WHO expert, &quot;what happens in Africa affects your neighborhood, either directly or <lb/>indirectly…the IHR are founded on that principle...but the world beyond public health remains <lb/>largely unconvinced of it. To really make strides against diseases like Ebola, we have to <lb/>convince people that there is no &quot;over there&quot; for infectious pathogens in a globalized world (2). <lb/>We therefore all need to be prepared at all times which means rehearsals and drills in the form of <lb/>table top exercises and multisectoral simulation exercises. Community support and involvement <lb/>are key. Sensitisation, communication and training are essential. Unfortunately lessons learned <lb/>from previous outbreaks are not being used to modify existing services and practices and for <lb/>each new public health event it seems we are starting from square one. An understanding of the <lb/>community perceptions about a public health threat is what is needed to be able to develop and <lb/>target information about the disease and its control (21). This study attempted to achieve this, to <lb/>aid the Government in its capacity building efforts to increase the country&apos;s resilience during a <lb/>major public health event. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. www.who.int <lb/>2. The Ebola Epidemic in West Africa Proceedings of a Workshop 2016 the National <lb/>Academies Press Washington DC <lb/>3. Kruk M, Myers M, Varpilah ST, Dahn BT What is a resilient health system? Lessons <lb/>from Ebola Lancet 2015; 385:1910-12. <lb/>4. www.cdc.gov <lb/>5. Castleden M Mc Kee M Murray V Leonardi G Resilience thinking in health protection <lb/>Journal of Public Health 2011; 33 (3): 369-377. doi:10.1093/pubmed/fdr027 <lb/>6. Blanchet K, Nam SL, Ramalingam B, Pozo-Martin F. Governance and capacity to <lb/>manage resilience of health systems: towards a new conceptual framework. Int J Health <lb/>Policy Manag. 2017;6 (8) : 431-435. doi:10.15171/ijhpm.2017.36 <lb/>7. http://cso.gov.tt/census/2011-census-data/ <lb/>8. Saheed Gidado, Abisola M. Oladimeji, Alero Ann Roberts, Patrick Nguku, Iruoma <lb/>Genevieve Nwangwu, Ndadilnasiya Endie Waziri, Faisal Shuaib, Olukayode <lb/>Oguntimehin, Emmanuel Musa, Charles Nzuki, Abdulsalami Nasidi, Peter Adewuyi, <lb/>Tom-Aba Daniel, Adebola Olayinka, Oladoyin Odubanjo, and Gabriele Poggensee* <lb/>Version 1. PLoS Curr. 2016 March 4; 8: <lb/>ecurrents.outbreaks.c04b88cd5cd03cccb99e125657eecd76. Published online 2016 <lb/>March 4. doi: 10.1371/currents.outbreaks.c04b88cd5cd03cccb99e125657eecd76 <lb/>Knowledge, Attitude and Perception of Ebola Virus Disease among Secondary School <lb/>Students in Ondo State, Nigeria, October, 2014 <lb/>9. Iliyasu G, Ogoina D, Otu AA, Dayyab FM, Ebenso B, otokpa D et al A multi-site <lb/>knowledge attitude and practice survey of ebola virus disease in Nigeria PLOS One 2015; <lb/>10 (8): e 0135955. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0135955. <lb/>10. Nyakarahuka L, Skjerve E, Nabadda D, Sitali DC, Mumba C, Mwiine FN, et al. (2017) <lb/>Knowledge and attitude towards Ebola and Marburg virus diseases in Uganda using <lb/>quantitative and participatory epidemiology techniques. PLoS Negl Trop Dis 11(9): <lb/>e0005907. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005907 <lb/>11. Dracup K, Moser D (1997) Beyond socio-demographic: factors influencing to seek <lb/>treatment for symptoms of acute myocardial infarction. Heart Lung 26:253-262 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>12. M Kobayashi, K D. Beer, A Bjork, K Chatham-Stephens, C C. Cherry, S Arzoaquoi, W <lb/>Frank, O Kumeh, J Sieka, A Yeiah, J E. Painter, J S. Yoder, B Flannery, F Mahoney, TG. <lb/>Nyenswah, Community Knowledge, Attitudes, and Practices Regarding Ebola Virus <lb/>Disease -Five Counties, Liberia, September-October, 2014 MMWR; 2015; Vol. 64; <lb/>No. 26. <lb/>13. Shoman H, Karafillakis E, Rawaf S the link between the West Africa Ebola outbreak and <lb/>health systems in Guinea, Liberia and Sierra Leone: a systematic review Globalization <lb/>and Health 2017; 13:1 doi: 10.1186/s12992-016-0224-2. <lb/>14. Boda PJ The challenge of combatting non communicable diseases in Trinidad: Access to <lb/>hospital care Health 2013; 5(11B): 12-18. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.4236/health.2013.511A2003 <lb/>15. www.who.int <lb/>16. Pooransingh S Hawker J Are we preparedness for a deliberate release of a biological <lb/>agent? Public Health. 2006 Jul; 120(7):613-7. Epub 2006 Jun 5. <lb/>17. Biddinger PD, Savoia E, Massin-Short SB, Preston J, Stoto M, Public Health Emergency <lb/>Preparedness Exercises: Lessons Learned Public Health Reports / 2010 Supplement 5 / <lb/>Volume 125 p 100-106. <lb/>18. BMJ warns that too few people know response to a terrorist attack BMJ 2003;326:516. <lb/>19. Kelly B, Squiers L, Bann C, Stine A, Hansen H, Lynch M Perceptions and plans for <lb/>prevention of Ebola: results from a national survey BMC Public Health (2015) 15: 1136. <lb/>Doi 10.1186/s12889-015-2441-7 <lb/>20. Fischhoff B, Wong-Parodi G, Garfin DR, Holman EA, Silver RC Public Understanding <lb/>of Ebola Risks: Mastering an Unfamiliar Threat Risk Analysis doi: 10.1111/risa.12794 <lb/>21. Kinsman J de Bruijne K Jalloh AM, Harris M, Abdullah H, Boye Thompson T, et al <lb/>Development of a set of community informed Ebola messages for Sierra Leone PLOS <lb/>Neglected Tropical Diseases 11(8): <lb/>e0005742.https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pntd.0005742 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the author/funder. <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/346999 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
