<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Epigenetic-scale comparison of human iPSCs generated by retrovirus, Sendai virus or <lb/>episomal vectors <lb/>Koichiro Nishino 1,2 , Yoshikazu Arai 1 , Ken Takasawa 1 , Masashi Toyoda 3 , Mayu Yamazaki-Inoue 4 , <lb/>Tohru Sugawara 4 , Hidenori Akutsu 4 , Ken Nishimura 5 , Manami Ohtaka 6 , Mahito Nakanishi 7 and <lb/>Akihiro Umezawa 4 * <lb/>1 Laboratory of Veterinary Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Graduate School of Medicine and <lb/>Veterinary Medicine/Faculty of Agriculture, University of Miyazaki, Miyazaki, Japan. <lb/>2 Center for Animal Disease Control, University of Miyazaki, Miyazaki, Japan. <lb/>3 Research Team for Geriatric Medicine, Tokyo Metropolitan Institute of Gerontology, University of <lb/>Miyazaki, Miyazaki, Japan.Tokyo, Japan. <lb/>4 Department of Reproductive Biology, Center for Regenerative Medicine, National Research Institute <lb/>for Child Health and Development, Tokyo, Japan. <lb/>5 Laboratory of Gene Regulation, Faculty of Medicine, University of Tsukuba, Ibaraki, Japan. <lb/>6 TOKIWA-Bio, Inc., Ibaraki, Japan. <lb/>7 Biotechnology Research Institute for Drug Discovery, National Institute of Advanced Industrial <lb/>Science and Technology (AIST), Ibaraki, Japan. <lb/>*Correspondence to Akihiro Umezawa <lb/>E-mail: umezawa@1985.jukuin.keio.ac.jp <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Human induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) are established by introducing several <lb/>reprogramming factors, such as OCT3/4, SOX2, KLF4, c-MYC. Because of their pluripotency and <lb/>immortality, iPSCs are considered to be a powerful tool for regenerative medicine. To date, iPSCs have <lb/>been established all over the world by various gene delivery methods. All methods induced high-<lb/>quality iPSCs, but epigenetic analysis of abnormalities derived from differences in the gene delivery <lb/>methods has not yet been performed. Here, we generated genetically matched human iPSCs from <lb/>menstrual blood cells by using three kinds of vectors, i.e., retrovirus, Sendai virus, and episomal <lb/>vectors, and compared genome-wide DNA methylation profiles among them. Although comparison of <lb/>aberrant methylation revealed that iPSCs generated by Sendai virus vector have lowest number of <lb/>aberrant methylation sites among the three vectors, the iPSCs generated by non-integrating methods did <lb/>not show vector-specific aberrant methylation. However, the differences between the iPSC lines were <lb/>determined to be the number of random aberrant hyper-methylated regions compared with embryonic <lb/>stem cells. These random aberrant hyper-methylations might be a cause of the differences in the <lb/>properties of each of the iPSC lines. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Human induced pluripotent stem cells (iPSCs) are powerful resources for disease modeling, <lb/>drug discovery, and regenerative medicine because of their potential for pluripotency, ability to self-<lb/>renew indefinitely, avoidance of rejection of their derivatives by the immune system and for ethical <lb/>issues [1]. Studies of reprogramming mechanisms and characterization of iPSCs are imperative to <lb/>ensure the safety of their derivatives in regenerative medicine [2]. Epigenetic reprogramming is an <lb/>essential event during transformation from somatic cells to iPSCs. DNA methylation is an important <lb/>epigenetic modification and has a critical role in many aspects of normal development and disease [3-<lb/>5]. Expression of OCT-4 and NANOG genes, known as reprogramming factors, are induced in <lb/>restricted tissues with an inverse correlation of DNA methylation during development [6, 7]. Transient <lb/>ectopic expression of defined reprogramming factors forces genome-wide epigenetic exchange and <lb/>transforms somatic cells to iPSCs [8-12]. After reprogramming, epigenetic profiles of the human iPSCs <lb/>can be clearly discriminated from the parent somatic cells and are similar to human embryonic stem <lb/>cells (ESCs), though there is a small fraction of differentially methylated regions [11-15]. In addition, <lb/>the degree of global DNA methylation in human pluripotent stem cells, ESCs and iPSCs, is higher <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>when compared to somatic cells [11, 12]. This global hyper-methylation of human pluripotent stem <lb/>cells is a feature shared with primed murine epiblast stem cells, although mouse ESCs, that are naïve <lb/>state stem cells, have global hypomethylation corresponding to early embryonic cells [16-21]. <lb/>Human iPSCs have been established by various gene delivery methods. After the first report of <lb/>iPSC generation by using retrovirus vectors [8], lentivirus vectors [22], Sendai virus vectors [23, 24], <lb/>PiggyBac vectors [10], plasmid vectors [25], episomal vectors [26], protein transfer [27, 28], mRNA <lb/>transfer [29], and miRNA transfer [30] have been reported as methods for iPSC generation. All <lb/>methods induced high-quality iPSCs, but epigenetic abnormalities associated with the specific gene <lb/>delivery method have not been well analyzed. In this study, we generated human iPSCs derived from <lb/>menstrual blood cells with three kinds of vectors, i.e., retrovirus, Sendai virus, and episomal vectors, <lb/>and evaluated them for the scale of genome-wide DNA methylation. <lb/>Results <lb/>Comparison of DNA methylation level in pluripotent stem cells and somatic cells <lb/>We generated genetically matched human iPSCs from menstrual blood cells (Edom22) in our <lb/>laboratory by retrovirus vector infection [12], episomal vector transfection or Sendai viral SeVdp-iPS <lb/>vector infection (designated as Retro-, Episomal-, and Sendai-iPSCs, respectively) (Fig. 1A and 1B, <lb/>Supplemental Fig. 1 and 2). To investigate the differences in DNA methylation between iPSCs <lb/>generated with the three kinds of vectors, we obtained DNA methylation profiles from ESCs, iPSCs <lb/>including Retro-iPSCs, Sendai-iPSCs, and Episomal-iPSCs, and parent somatic cells, using Illumina&apos;s <lb/>Infinium HumanMethylation450K BeadChip. Methylation levels are represented as β-values, which <lb/>range from &quot;0&quot;, for completely unmethylated, to &quot;1&quot;, for completely methylated. Additional data sets <lb/>from 5 ESCs were obtained from the GEO database [31]. We completely analyzed global DNA <lb/>methylation of 49 samples (Supplemental Table 1), all with XX karyotypes. All iPSC lines in this study <lb/>were derived from the same parental somatic cell, Edom22. The promoter regions of pluripotency-<lb/>associated genes such as POU5F1, NANOG, SALL4, PTPN6, RAB25, EPHA1, TDGF1 and LEFTY1 <lb/>showed low levels of methylation, whereas the promoter regions of somatic cell-associated genes such <lb/>as EMILIN1, LYST, RIN2 and SP100 were highly methylated in all pluripotent cells (Fig. 1C). These <lb/>results indicate that all iPSC lines were completely reprogrammed at the core genes, regardless of type <lb/>of vector used. As assessed by unsupervised hierarchical cluster analysis (HCA) (Fig. 1D) and principal <lb/>component analysis (PCA) (Fig. 1E) using each iPSC lines (passaged about 30 times), human iPSCs <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>were clearly distinguishable from their parent cells and were similar to ESCs. Sendai-iPSCs appeared <lb/>to be more similar to ESCs, but no clear difference among the three methods was defined. <lb/>Identification of differentially methylated regions <lb/>In further analysis, we defined a differentially methylated region (DMR) between ESCs and <lb/>iPSCs as a CpG site whose delta-β-value score differed by at least 0.3 (Fig. 2A). We compared the <lb/>DNA methylation states of each iPSC line with those of ESCs (the averaged value from 12 ESC lines). <lb/>The number of DMRs between ESCs and each iPSC line (ES-iPS-DMRs) ranged from 448 to 1,175 in <lb/>Retro-iPSCs, from 101 to 168 in Sendai-iPSCs, and from 202 to 875 in Episomal-iPSCs. Sendai-iPSCs <lb/>had lowest number of ES-iPS-DMRs among three kinds of vectors (Fig. 2B). The number of ES-iPS-<lb/>DMRs in all 6 Sendai-iPSCs was under 168. In Episomal-iPSCs, 2 out of 3 lines showed 300 or fewer <lb/>ES-iPS-DMRs. Although 1 out of 3 Retro-iPSC lines showed a relatively low number of ES-iPS-<lb/>DMRs, the range of ES-iPS-DMRs number was wider. These results suggest that the number of ES-<lb/>iPS-DMRs depended on each cell line rather than on the vectors used for iPSC generation. ES-iPS-<lb/>DMRs can be categorized into two groups: hyper-methylated and hypo-methylated sites in iPSCs, as <lb/>compared with ESCs. There was little difference in the number of hypo-methylated ES-iPS-DMRs, <lb/>especially between Sendai-iPSCs and Episomal-iPSCs (Fig. 2C). The difference between each iPSC <lb/>line therefore appears to be dependent on the number of abnormal hyper-methylated sites. <lb/>Correlation between expression of DNMT/TET genes and ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>In order to investigate whether abnormal hyper-methylation in iPSCs was caused by irregular <lb/>expression of DNA methyltransferases (DNMTs) and/or Ten-eleven translocations (TETs) that induce <lb/>de-methylation, we examined expression level of DNMT and TET genes. All iPSC lines, regardless of <lb/>type of vector, showed hyper expression of both DNMT3B and TET1 genes compared to ESC (Fig. 2D <lb/>and 2F). However, there was no correlation between the number of ES-iPS-DMRs and the expression <lb/>levels of DNMT3B or TET1 gene (Fig. 2E and 2G). Similarly, other DNMTs (DNMT1, DNMT3A and <lb/>DNMT3L) and TETs (TET2 and TET3) did not show correlation between the number of ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>and expression level. <lb/>Vector-specific ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>We next aimed to detect vector-specific ES-iPS-DMR. We extracted 229 DMRs that <lb/>overlapped in all 3 Retro-Esom-iPSC lines. The 44 and 76 DMRs also overlapped in all 6 Sendai-<lb/>Esom-iPSC lines and in all 3 Episomal-Esom-iPSC lines, respectively (Fig. 3A). Approximately 80% <lb/>of ES-iPS-DMR in each vector group was detected in only one or two lines, suggesting that most of the <lb/>DMRs occurred randomly in the genome. Comparison of each the overlapping ES-iPS-DMR revealed <lb/>that 167, 2, 13 ES-iPS-DMRs were detected as the Retro-, Sendai-and Episomal-iPSC-specific DMRs, <lb/>respectively. Because these aberrant methylation sites at promoter region possibly affect gene <lb/>expression, we further investigated ES-iPS-DMRs at promoters. While no ES-iPS-DMRs overlapped <lb/>for all Sendai-iPSC lines, 44 and 5 ES-iPS-DMRs were common in all Retro-and Episomal-iPSC lines <lb/>at the promoter regions, respectively (Fig. 3B). Details of vector-specific DMRs are summarized in <lb/>Table 1 and Supplemental Table 2. Interestingly, 5 ES-iPS-DMRs in Episomal-iPSC lines appeared <lb/>transiently. They were not DMRs at different passages and in different lines (Fig. 3C). In the Retro-<lb/>iPSC line, 11 out of 44 ES-iPS-DMRs were also transient abnormal regions. These results indicated <lb/>that Retro-iPSCs had a small subset of the vector-specific ES-iPS-DMRs, but iPSCs generated by non-<lb/>integrating methods did not have the vector-specific ES-iPS-DMRs, especially those were located <lb/>promoter regions. <lb/>Aberrant methylation in imprinted genes in pluripotent stem cells. <lb/>We also compared DNA methylation of imprinted genes between somatic cells and <lb/>iPSCs/ESCs, and identified 413 differentially methylated regions at promoter regions including 68 <lb/>imprinted genes. These 68 genes comprised 69.4 % of imprinted genes examined. Representative <lb/>imprinted genes including MEG3, H19, PEG3, IGFR2, PEG10 and XIST in ESCs and iPSCs showed <lb/>aberrant methylation compared with parent somatic cells, independent of the vector type (Fig. 4). In <lb/>addition, most of the aberrant methylation was not adapted during culture (Supplemental Fig. 3). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Choi et al. [32] reported that hiPSCs, which were generated by using a Sendai virus vector, <lb/>were molecularly and functionally equivalent to genetically matched hESCs. Schlaeger et al. [33] also <lb/>reported that there were no substantial method-specific differences in DNA methylation, marker <lb/>expression levels or patterns, or developmental potential by comparing among Retro-, Lenti-, Sendai-, <lb/>Episomal-, and mRNA-iPSCs. Our study bridges the gap between the two previous studies. In this <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>study, we compared iPSC lines derived from the same parental somatic cell line, menstrual blood-<lb/>derived cells, using three types of vectors. Three types of menstrual blood cell-derived-iPSCs are <lb/>preferable for comparison analysis to avoid any influence from different parental cells. Over 99% of <lb/>CpG sites in all iPSC lines did not show differences in the methylation levels, compared with ESCs; <lb/>therefore, iPSCs were almost identical to ESCs in epigenetics regardless of vector types used for iPSC <lb/>generation. Our findings are consistent with the results of previous studies. However, when focusing <lb/>the ES-iPS-DMRs of each iPSC line in details, we found that Sendai-iPSCs were more similar to ESCs <lb/>than Retro-and Episomal-iPSCs at the epigenetic scale. Also, the ranges of the numbers of ES-iPS-<lb/>DMRs among Retro-iPSC line was wider than those seen in Sendai-and Episomal-iPSCs. This wide <lb/>variation might result from genome integration of transgenes. Among Episomal-iPSC lines, some lines <lb/>as well as Sendai-iPSCs showed low numbers of DMRs. The differences between ESCs and iPSCs, <lb/>especially Sendai-and Episomal-iPSCs, might be derived from characteristics of each of the iPSC <lb/>lines, rather than type of vectors used for iPSC generation. The type of vector might influence the <lb/>variety of line-specific properties. The line-specific differences depended on the number of aberrant <lb/>hyper-methylated DMRs. There was no correlation between this aberrant hyper-methylation and the <lb/>expression levels of the DNMT or TET genes; therefore, this aberrant hyper-methylation might be <lb/>generated at the initial reprogramming step and maintained during culture. Approximately 80% of <lb/>aberrant hyper-methylated ES-iPS-DMR in each vector group was detected in only one or two lines <lb/>and there were no vector-specific DMRs in non-integrating methods, suggesting that most of the DMRs <lb/>occurred randomly in the genome. Therefore, this random hyper-methylation might be a cause of the <lb/>differences in the properties of each of the iPSC lines. <lb/>Aberrant methylation of some imprinted genes in ESCs and iPSCs have been reported by <lb/>several groups [12, 34, 35]. In this study, we detected 68 imprinted genes that exhibited aberrant <lb/>methylation, which comprised 69.4% of imprinted genes examined. These abnormalities have been <lb/>widely detected in pluripotent stem cells. Most iPSC lines as well as ESCs, were abnormally hyper-<lb/>methylated at MEG3, H19, PEG3, IGFR2 and XIST, regardless of the vector type. The aberrant <lb/>methylation at imprinted gene and XIST gene promoters was maintained throughout continuous passage <lb/>(data not shown). The aberrant methylation of imprinted genes should therefore be monitored for <lb/>validation of PSC quality. <lb/>In conclusion, we compared genetically matched iPSCs and revealed that there were no <lb/>vector-specific aberrant methylated regions in iPSCs generated by non-integrating methods. The line-<lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>specific properties depended on the number of random aberrant hyper-methylated DMRs rather than <lb/>type of vectors used for iPSC generation. The differences between the vectors might influence the <lb/>variety of line-specific properties. It is noteworthy that epigenetic information can be useful to <lb/>determine iPSC quality. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Ethics Statement <lb/>Human cells were collected with ethical approval of the Institutional Review Board of <lb/>National Institute for Child Health and Development, Japan. Signed informed consent was obtained <lb/>from donors, and the specimens were irreversibly de-identified. All experiments handling human cells <lb/>and tissues were performed in line with the Tenets of the Declaration of Helsinki. <lb/>Human cell culture <lb/>Menstrual blood (Edom22) cells were independently established in our laboratory [36, 37], <lb/>and were maintained in the POWEREDBY10 medium (Glyco Technica Ltd., Sapporo, Japan). Human <lb/>Retro-iPSCs were generated from Edom22 by retroviral vector pMXs, which encodes the cDNA for <lb/>human OCT3/4, SOX2, c-MYC, and KLF4, via previously described procedures [8] with slight <lb/>modifications [11, 36, 38, 39]. Episomal-iPSCs were established from Edom 22 by episomal vectors, <lb/>pCXLE-hOCT3/4-shp53, pCXLE-hSK, and pCXLE-hUL, via procedures described [26]. Sendai-iPSCs <lb/>were produced from Edom 22 by Sendai viral vector SeVdp-iPS, which encodes the polycisrtonic <lb/>cDNAs for mouse Oct3/4, Sox2, c-Myc, and Klf4, via procedures described [24]. These iPSCs clearly <lb/>showed human ESC-like characters in terms of morphology; gene expression of stem cell markers; <lb/>cell-surface antigens; growth (over than 20 passages); normal karyotypes; and teratoma formation <lb/>(Supplemental Fig. 1 and 2). Non-integrating episomal vectors in the genome or erasing SeVdp vector <lb/>RNA genome was also confirmed. Human ESCs, SEES, were generated in our laboratory [40]. Human <lb/>iPSCs and ESCs were maintained on irradiated MEFs in iPSellon medium (Cardio Incorporated, <lb/>Osaka, Japan) supplemented with 10 ng/ml recombinant human basic fibroblast growth factor (bFGF, <lb/>Wako Pure Chemical Industries, Ltd., Osaka, Japan). ESC genomes [41, 42] were kindly gifted from <lb/>Drs. C. Cowan and T. Tenzan (Harvard Stem Cell Institute, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA). <lb/>DNA methylation analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>DNA methylation analysis was performed using the Illumina infinium assay with the <lb/>HumanMethylation450K BeadChip (Illumina inc.). Genomic DNA was extracted from the cells using <lb/>QIAamp DNA Mini Kit (Qiagen). One microgram of genomic DNA from each sample was bisulfite-<lb/>converted using EZ DNA Methylation kit (Zymo Research), according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>recommendations. Bisulfite-converted genomic DNA was hybridized to the HumanMethylation450K <lb/>BeadChip and the BeadChip was scanned on a BeadArray Reader (Illumina inc.), according to the <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Methylated and unmethylated signals were used to compute a β-value, <lb/>which was a quantitative score of DNA methylation levels, ranging from &quot;0&quot;, for completely <lb/>unmethylated, to &quot;1&quot;, for completely methylated. On the HumanMethylation450K BeadChip, <lb/>oligonucleotides for 485,577 CpG sites covering more than 96% of Refseq and 95% of CpG islands <lb/>were mounted. The probe with MAF (minor allele frequency of the overlapping variant) ≥ 5% [43] <lb/>and CpG sites with ≥ 0.05 &quot;Detection p value&quot; (computed from the background based on negative <lb/>controls) were eliminated from the data for further analysis, leaving 416,528 CpGs valid for use with <lb/>the 49 samples tested. Average methylation was calculated from ESCs, in which 46,681 DMRs among <lb/>each ESC line in each set were removed. In Fig.1C, each iPSC line (at about the 30th passage) was <lb/>used and the probes were follows; POU5F1 (cg15948871, TSS1500), NANOG (cg25540142, TSS200), <lb/>SALL4 (cg25570495, TSS200), PTPN6 (cg12690127, TSS200), RAB25 (cg15896939, TSS200), <lb/>EPHA1 (cg02376703, TSS200), TDGF1 (cg27371741, TSS200), LEFTY1 (cg15604953, TSS1500), <lb/>EMILIN1 (cg19399165, TSS200), LYST (cg13677741, TSS1500), RIN2 (cg17016000, TSS1500), <lb/>SP100 (cg23539753, TSS200). TSS200 and TSS1500 indicated the position of the probe; TSS200, 0 -<lb/>200 bases and TSS1500, 200 -1500 bases upstream of the transcriptional start site (TSS). <lb/>Quantitative reversetranscription-PCR <lb/>Total RNA was extracted from samples by the conventional method using ISOGEN II <lb/>(NIPPON GENE, Toyama, Japan). An aliquot of total RNA was reverse-transcribed using ReverTra <lb/>Ace (TOYOBO, Japan) with random hexamer primers. The cDNA template was amplified using <lb/>specific primers for DNMT1, DNMT3A, DNMT3B, DNMT3L, TET1, TET2 and TET3. Expression of <lb/>glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase (GAPDH) was used as a control. Primers used in this study <lb/>are summarized in Supplemental Table 3. Quantitative PCR was performed in at least triplicate for each <lb/>sample on LightCycler®96 Real-Time PCR system (Roche) with Power SYBR Green PCR Master Mix <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Life Technologies) using a standard protocol. Relative expression was calculated by the ddCT method <lb/>using GAPDH as an internal standard. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Accession numbers <lb/>NCBI GEO: HumanMethylation450K BeadChip data in this study has been submitted under accession <lb/>number GSE73938 and GSExxxxxx (in progress). Additional data sets of 5 ESCs were obtained from <lb/>GSE31848. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We would like to express our sincere thanks to Drs. C. Cowan and T. Tenzan for HUESC lines, <lb/>to Dr. H. Makino for establishing the Edom22 cells, to Ms. Y. Takahashi for bioinformatics analyses. <lb/>This research was supported in part by AMED under Grant Number JP18bm0704003 to KoN, and by <lb/>grants from the Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science, and Technology (MEXT) of Japan; by <lb/>Ministry of Health, Labor and Welfare (MHLW) Sciences research grant to AU. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Park IH, Arora N, Huo H, Maherali N, Ahfeldt T, Shimamura A, et al. Disease-specific induced <lb/>pluripotent stem cells. Cell. 2008;134(5):877-86. <lb/>[2] Teshigawara R, Cho J, Kameda M, Tada T. Mechanism of human somatic reprogramming to iPS <lb/>cell. Lab Invest. 2017;97(10):1152-7. <lb/>[3] Li E. Chromatin modification and epigenetic reprogramming in mammalian development. Nat <lb/>Rev Genet. 2002;3(9):662-73. <lb/>[4] Reik W. Stability and flexibility of epigenetic gene regulation in mammalian development. <lb/>Nature. 2007;447(7143):425-32. <lb/>[5] Feng S, Jacobsen SE, Reik W. Epigenetic reprogramming in plant and animal development. <lb/>Science. 2010;330(6004):622-7. <lb/>[6] Hattori N, Nishino K, Ko YG, Hattori N, Ohgane J, Tanaka S, et al. Epigenetic control of mouse <lb/>Oct-4 gene expression in embryonic stem cells and trophoblast stem cells. J Biol Chem. <lb/>2004;279(17):17063-9. <lb/>[7] Hattori N, Imao Y, Nishino K, Hattori N, Ohgane J, Yagi S, et al. Epigenetic regulation of Nanog <lb/>gene in embryonic stem and trophoblast stem cells. Genes Cells. 2007;12(3):387-96. <lb/>[8] Takahashi K, Tanabe K, Ohnuki M, Narita M, Ichisaka T, Tomoda K, et al. Induction of <lb/>pluripotent stem cells from adult human fibroblasts by defined factors. Cell. 2007;131(5):861-72. <lb/>[9] Park IH, Zhao R, West JA, Yabuuchi A, Huo H, Ince TA, et al. Reprogramming of human <lb/>somatic cells to pluripotency with defined factors. Nature. 2008;451(7175):141-6. <lb/>[10] Woltjen K, Michael IP, Mohseni P, Desai R, Mileikovsky M, Hamalainen R, et al. piggyBac <lb/>transposition reprograms fibroblasts to induced pluripotent stem cells. Nature. <lb/>2009;458(7239):766-70. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[11] Nishino K, Toyoda M, Yamazaki-Inoue M, Makino H, Fukawatase Y, Chikazawa E, et al. <lb/>Defining hypo-methylated regions of stem cell-specific promoters in human iPS cells derived <lb/>from extra-embryonic amnions and lung fibroblasts. PLoS One. 2010;5(9):e13017. <lb/>[12] Nishino K, Toyoda M, Yamazaki-Inoue M, Fukawatase Y, Chikazawa E, Sakaguchi H, et al. <lb/>DNA methylation dynamics in human induced pluripotent stem cells over time. PLoS Genet. <lb/>2011;7(5):e1002085. <lb/>[13] Lister R, Pelizzola M, Dowen RH, Hawkins RD, Hon G, Tonti-Filippini J, et al. Human DNA <lb/>methylomes at base resolution show widespread epigenomic differences. Nature. <lb/>2009;462(7271):315-22. <lb/>[14] Doi A, Park IH, Wen B, Murakami P, Aryee MJ, Irizarry R, et al. Differential methylation of <lb/>tissue-and cancer-specific CpG island shores distinguishes human induced pluripotent stem cells, <lb/>embryonic stem cells and fibroblasts. Nat Genet. 2009;41(12):1350-3. <lb/>[15] Lister R, Pelizzola M, Kida YS, Hawkins RD, Nery JR, Hon G, et al. Hotspots of aberrant <lb/>epigenomic reprogramming in human induced pluripotent stem cells. Nature. 2011;471(7336):68-<lb/>73. <lb/>[16] Nichols J, Smith A. Naive and primed pluripotent states. Cell Stem Cell. 2009;4(6):487-92. <lb/>[17] Tesar PJ, Chenoweth JG, Brook FA, Davies TJ, Evans EP, Mack DL, et al. New cell lines from <lb/>mouse epiblast share defining features with human embryonic stem cells. Nature. <lb/>2007;448(7150):196-9. <lb/>[18] Habibi E, Brinkman AB, Arand J, Kroeze LI, Kerstens HH, Matarese F, et al. Whole-genome <lb/>bisulfite sequencing of two distinct interconvertible DNA methylomes of mouse embryonic stem <lb/>cells. Cell Stem Cell. 2013;13(3):360-9. <lb/>[19] Ficz G, Hore TA, Santos F, Lee HJ, Dean W, Arand J, et al. FGF signaling inhibition in ESCs <lb/>drives rapid genome-wide demethylation to the epigenetic ground state of pluripotency. Cell <lb/>Stem Cell. 2013;13(3):351-9. <lb/>[20] Leitch HG, McEwen KR, Turp A, Encheva V, Carroll T, Grabole N, et al. Naive pluripotency is <lb/>associated with global DNA hypomethylation. Nat Struct Mol Biol. 2013;20(3):311-6. <lb/>[21] Yagi M, Yamanaka S, Yamada Y. Epigenetic foundations of pluripotent stem cells that <lb/>recapitulate in vivo pluripotency. Lab Invest. 2017;97(10):1133-41. <lb/>[22] Shao L, Feng W, Sun Y, Bai H, Liu J, Currie C, et al. Generation of iPS cells using defined <lb/>factors linked via the self-cleaving 2A sequences in a single open reading frame. Cell Res. <lb/>2009;19(3):296-306. <lb/>[23] Fusaki N, Ban H, Nishiyama A, Saeki K, Hasegawa M. Efficient induction of transgene-free <lb/>human pluripotent stem cells using a vector based on Sendai virus, an RNA virus that does not <lb/>integrate into the host genome. Proceedings of the Japan Academy, Series B. 2009;85(8):348-62. <lb/>[24] Nishimura K, Sano M, Ohtaka M, Furuta B, Umemura Y, Nakajima Y, et al. Development of <lb/>defective and persistent Sendai virus vector: a unique gene delivery/expression system ideal for <lb/>cell reprogramming. J Biol Chem. 2011;286(6):4760-71. <lb/>[25] Okita K, Nakagawa M, Hyenjong H, Ichisaka T, Yamanaka S. Generation of mouse induced <lb/>pluripotent stem cells without viral vectors. Science. 2008;322(5903):949-53. <lb/>[26] Okita K, Matsumura Y, Sato Y, Okada A, Morizane A, Okamoto S, et al. A more efficient <lb/>method to generate integration-free human iPS cells. Nat Methods. 2011;8(5):409-12. <lb/>[27] Zhou H, Wu S, Joo JY, Zhu S, Han DW, Lin T, et al. Generation of induced pluripotent stem <lb/>cells using recombinant proteins. Cell Stem Cell. 2009;4(5):381-4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[28] Kim D, Kim CH, Moon JI, Chung YG, Chang MY, Han BS, et al. Generation of human induced <lb/>pluripotent stem cells by direct delivery of reprogramming proteins. Cell Stem Cell. <lb/>2009;4(6):472-6. <lb/>[29] Warren L, Manos PD, Ahfeldt T, Loh YH, Li H, Lau F, et al. Highly efficient reprogramming to <lb/>pluripotency and directed differentiation of human cells with synthetic modified mRNA. Cell <lb/>Stem Cell. 2010;7(5):618-30. <lb/>[30] Anokye-Danso F, Trivedi CM, Juhr D, Gupta M, Cui Z, Tian Y, et al. Highly efficient miRNA-<lb/>mediated reprogramming of mouse and human somatic cells to pluripotency. Cell Stem Cell. <lb/>2011;8(4):376-88. <lb/>[31] Nazor KL, Altun G, Lynch C, Tran H, Harness JV, Slavin I, et al. Recurrent variations in DNA <lb/>methylation in human pluripotent stem cells and their differentiated derivatives. Cell Stem Cell. <lb/>2012;10(5):620-34. <lb/>[32] Choi J, Lee S, Mallard W, Clement K, Tagliazucchi GM, Lim H, et al. A comparison of <lb/>genetically matched cell lines reveals the equivalence of human iPSCs and ESCs. Nat Biotechnol. <lb/>2015;33(11):1173-81. <lb/>[33] Schlaeger TM, Daheron L, Brickler TR, Entwisle S, Chan K, Cianci A, et al. A comparison of <lb/>non-integrating reprogramming methods. Nat Biotechnol. 2015;33(1):58-63. <lb/>[34] Rugg-Gunn PJ, Ferguson-Smith AC, Pedersen RA. Epigenetic status of human embryonic stem <lb/>cells. Nat Genet. 2005;37(6):585-7. <lb/>[35] Rugg-Gunn PJ, Ferguson-Smith AC, Pedersen RA. Status of genomic imprinting in human <lb/>embryonic stem cells as revealed by a large cohort of independently derived and maintained <lb/>lines. Hum Mol Genet. 2007;16 Spec No. 2:R243-51. <lb/>[36] Nagata S, Toyoda M, Yamaguchi S, Hirano K, Makino H, Nishino K, et al. Efficient <lb/>reprogramming of human and mouse primary extra-embryonic cells to pluripotent stem cells. <lb/>Genes Cells. 2009;14(12):1395-404. <lb/>[37] Cui CH, Uyama T, Miyado K, Terai M, Kyo S, Kiyono T, et al. Menstrual blood-derived cells <lb/>confer human dystrophin expression in the murine model of Duchenne muscular dystrophy via <lb/>cell fusion and myogenic transdifferentiation. Mol Biol Cell. 2007;18(5):1586-94. <lb/>[38] Makino H, Toyoda M, Matsumoto K, Saito H, Nishino K, Fukawatase Y, et al. Mesenchymal to <lb/>embryonic incomplete transition of human cells by chimeric OCT4/3 (POU5F1) with <lb/>physiological co-activator EWS. Exp Cell Res. 2009;315(16):2727-40. <lb/>[39] Toyoda M, Yamazaki-Inoue M, Itakura Y, Kuno A, Ogawa T, Yamada M, et al. Lectin <lb/>microarray analysis of pluripotent and multipotent stem cells. Genes Cells. 2011;16(1):1-11. <lb/>[40] Akutsu H, Machida M, Kanzaki S, Sugawara T, Ohkura T, Nakamura N, et al. Xenogeneic-free <lb/>defined conditions for derivation and expansion of human embryonic stem cells with <lb/>mesenchymal stem cells. Regenerative Therapy. 2015;1:18-29. <lb/>[41] Cowan CA, Klimanskaya I, McMahon J, Atienza J, Witmyer J, Zucker JP, et al. Derivation of <lb/>embryonic stem-cell lines from human blastocysts. N Engl J Med. 2004;350(13):1353-6. <lb/>[42] Osafune K, Caron L, Borowiak M, Martinez RJ, Fitz-Gerald CS, Sato Y, et al. Marked <lb/>differences in differentiation propensity among human embryonic stem cell lines. Nat Biotechnol. <lb/>2008;26(3):313-5. <lb/>[43] Okamura K, Kawai T, Hata K, Nakabayashi K. Lists of HumanMethylation450 BeadChip probes <lb/>with nucleotide-variant information obtained from the Phase 3 data of the 1000 Genomes Project. <lb/>Genom Data. 2016;7:67-9. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>E <lb/>Parental menstrul blood cell <lb/>-derived somatic cell line <lb/>(Edom22) <lb/>Retrovirus <lb/>O,S,K,M <lb/>Sendai virus <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Episomal vector <lb/>O-shp53,SK,UL <lb/>Retro <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Sendai <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Episomal <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Avg_ESCs <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>PC2 (18.65%) <lb/>PC1 (25.26%) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-10 <lb/>20 <lb/>PC3 (17.27%) <lb/>PC1 (25.26%) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-10 <lb/>20 <lb/>PC3 (17.27%) <lb/>PC2 (18.65%) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>-10 <lb/>20 <lb/>Avg_ESCs <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-35_P30 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-30_P30 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-23_P30 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-05_P30 <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPS-02_P31 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-39_P30 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-31_P30 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-09_P30 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-01_P30 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-08_P30 <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPS-01_P23 <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPS-03_P29 <lb/>Somatic-Edom22_P5 <lb/>140 <lb/>130 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>Epigenetic distance <lb/>POU5F1 <lb/>RAB25 <lb/>PTPN6 <lb/>SALL4 <lb/>RIN2 <lb/>SP100 <lb/>EMILIN1 <lb/>TDGF1 <lb/>LEFTY1 <lb/>NANOG <lb/>EPHA1 <lb/>Stem cell genes <lb/>Somatic <lb/>genes <lb/>#05_P30 <lb/>#31_P30 <lb/>#01_P30 <lb/>#08_P30 <lb/>#09_P30 <lb/>#01_P23 <lb/>#02_P31 <lb/>SEES-1_P30 <lb/>#03_P29 <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSC <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-iPSC <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSC <lb/>SEES-2_P30 <lb/>#35_P30 <lb/>#39_P30 <lb/>#30_P30 <lb/>#23_P30 <lb/>Edom22_P5 <lb/>Edom22_P7 <lb/>ESC <lb/>Somatic <lb/>Methylation rate <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>LYST1 <lb/>D <lb/>Parent cell (Edom22) <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-31 <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPS-2 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-1 <lb/>Fig. 1 Generation of genetically matched human iPSCs from the same parent somatic cells using three <lb/>kinds of vetors. A, Schematic for generation of the genetically matched human iPSC lines. Human <lb/>iPSCs were derived from the same parent somatic cell, Edom-22 using retrovirus, Sendai virus and <lb/>episomal vectors. B, Morphology of the parent somatic cells and iPSCs. C, Heatmap presenting DNA <lb/>methylation levels at promoter regions of pluripotency-associated and somatic cell-associated genes. D, <lb/>Unsupervised hierarchical clustering analysis (HCA) based on DNA methylation scores in the averaged <lb/>ESCs (black), Retro-Edom-iPSCs (green), Sendai-Edom-iPSCs (red), Episomal-Edom-iPSCs (blue) <lb/>and the parent comatic cell, Edom-22 (purple). E, Principal component analysis (PCA) based on DNA <lb/>methylation scores in the averaged ESCs (black diamond), Retro-iPSCs (green circles), Sendai-iPSCs <lb/>(red triangles) and Episomal-iPSCs (blue squares). <lb/> E <lb/>G <lb/>R 2 = 0.0476 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>30 <lb/>15 <lb/>No. ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>Relative DNMT3B <lb/>Expression <lb/>1400 <lb/>800 <lb/>600 <lb/>200 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1000 <lb/>400 <lb/>R 2 = 0.0126 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>No. ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>Relative TET1 <lb/>Expression <lb/>1400 <lb/>800 <lb/>600 <lb/>200 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1000 <lb/>400 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(Average <lb/>from 12 lines) <lb/>Each iPSC line <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>F <lb/>hDNMT3B <lb/>#05 <lb/>0 <lb/>30 <lb/>15 <lb/>Relative Expression <lb/>#31 <lb/>#01 <lb/>#08 <lb/>#09 <lb/>#01 <lb/>#02 <lb/>ESC (SEES-1) <lb/>#03 <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPS-<lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>hTET1 <lb/>#05 <lb/>0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>Relative Expression <lb/>#31 <lb/>#01 <lb/>#08 <lb/>#09 <lb/>#01 <lb/>#02 <lb/>ESC (SEES-1) <lb/>#03 <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPS-<lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>∆ ß-value 0.3 <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>P &lt; 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1200 <lb/>800 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>No. ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>1000 <lb/>600 <lb/>Hypo-methylated DMR <lb/>Hyper-methylated DMR <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1200 <lb/>600 <lb/>200 <lb/>No. ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-iPS-<lb/>#01 <lb/>#02 <lb/>#03 <lb/>#09 <lb/>#08 <lb/>#01 <lb/>#39 <lb/>#35 <lb/>#31 <lb/>#30 <lb/>#23 <lb/>#05 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Avg_ESCs <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Avg_ESCs <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPSCs <lb/></body>

			<body>Fig. 2 Comparison of differentially methylated regions between ESCs and each iPSC line. A, <lb/>Comparison of DNA methylation scores for each iPSC lines with that of the average for ESCs. The <lb/>DMRs between the average for ESCs and iPSCs are designated as ES-iPS-DMRs. B, Comparison of <lb/>the number of ES-iPS-DMRs in Retro-Edom-iPSCs (n=3), Sendai-Edom-iPSCs (n=6) and Episomal-<lb/>Edom-iPSCs (n=3). C, Proportion of the hyper-and hypomethylated ES-iPS-DMRs in each iPSC lines. <lb/>D, Quantitative RT-PCR for hDNMT3B in each PSC lines. E, Correlation between expression level of <lb/>hDNMT3B and the number of ES-iPS-DMRs. The averaged ESCs, black diamond; Retro-iPSCs, green <lb/>circles; Sendai-iPSCs, red triangles; Episomal-iPSCs, blue squares. F, Quantitative RT-PCR for hTET1 <lb/>in each PSC lines. G, Correlation between expression level of hTET1 and the number of <lb/>ES-iPS-DMRs. The averaged ESCs, black diamond; Retro-iPSCs, green circles; Sendai-iPSCs, red <lb/>triangles; Episomal-iPSCs, blue squares. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Retro-iPSCs <lb/>(229) <lb/>Sendai-iPSCs <lb/>(44) <lb/>Episomal-iPSCs <lb/>(76) <lb/>167 <lb/>2 <lb/>13 <lb/>1 <lb/>39 <lb/>2 <lb/>22 <lb/>Gene: 14 <lb/>DMR at TSS: 44 <lb/>Gene with <lb/>TSS DMR: 12 <lb/>Gene: 8 <lb/>DMR at TSS: 5 <lb/>Gene with <lb/>TSS DMR: 5 <lb/>Gene: 2 <lb/>DMR at TSS: 0 <lb/>Gene with <lb/>TSS DMR: 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1400 <lb/>1200 <lb/>800 <lb/>200 <lb/>No. ES-iPS-DMRs <lb/>Overlapping frequency in Edom-iPSC lines <lb/>Retro-<lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1205 <lb/>227 229 <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>0 <lb/>6 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>275 <lb/>61 19 19 11 44 <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>956 <lb/>87 76 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>P22 <lb/>P31 <lb/>P42 <lb/>Difference value <lb/>(∆ Avg_ESCs) <lb/>Hyper <lb/>Hypo <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPS-02 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>P16 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>c <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-01 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>e <lb/>d c <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-08 <lb/>0 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>c <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-09 <lb/>Fig. 3 Aberrant methylation in human iPSCs. A, The number of overlapping ES-iPS-DMRs in 3 <lb/>RetroEdom-iPSC lines, 6 Sendai-iPSC lines and 3 Episomal-iPSC lines. B, Venn diagram showing <lb/>method-specific DMRs among three kinds of vectors. C, Effect of continuous cultivation on 44 <lb/>and 5 ES-iPS-DMRs at TSS in Retro-iPSC line and in Episomal-iPSC lines, respectively. The <lb/>difference values were estimated by subtracting the scores of the averaged ESCs from that of each <lb/>passage sample. Each line shows a difference value of each probe during culture. Red lines <lb/>represent transiently ES-iPS-DMRs, which are not DMR at different passage and in different line. <lb/>a, EPHA10 (probe ID: cg06163371), b, WIPF2 (cg04977733), c, FTH1 (cg25270670), d, ZNF629 <lb/>(cg05549854), e, SLC19A1 (cg07658590). <lb/>Table 1. Details of the vector-specific DMRs. <lb/>Type of vector <lb/>Retrovirus <lb/>Sendai virus <lb/>Episomal <lb/>Common <lb/>a) No. DMR CpG <lb/>167 <lb/>2 <lb/>13 <lb/>39 <lb/>b) hyper-methylated DMR in a) <lb/>154 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>c) hyo-methylated DMR in a) <lb/>13 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>34 <lb/>d) % hyper-methylated DMR (b / a) <lb/>92.22% <lb/>0.00% <lb/>53.85% <lb/>12.82% <lb/>e) No. DMR CpG on Gene locus in a) <lb/>121 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>28 <lb/>f) % gene locus (e / a) <lb/>72.46% <lb/>100.00% <lb/>76.92% <lb/>71.79% <lb/>g) hyper-methylated DMR in e) <lb/>117 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>h) hyo-methylated DMR in e) <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>26 <lb/>i) % hyper-methylated DMR (f / e) <lb/>96.69% <lb/>0.00% <lb/>70.00% <lb/>7.14% <lb/>Relationship to canonical CpG Island* <lb/>j) CpG island in e) <lb/>94 <lb/>0 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>k) N_Shore in e) <lb/>8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>l) N_Shelf in e) <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>m) S_Shore in e) <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>n) S_Shelf in e) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>o) non-CpG island in e) <lb/>9 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>15 <lb/>Gene region feature category ** <lb/>p) TSS1500 in e) <lb/>42 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>q) TSS200 in e) <lb/>24 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>r) 1stExon in e) <lb/>22 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>s) 5&apos;UTR in e) <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>t) Body in e) <lb/>94 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>60 <lb/>u) 3&apos;UTR in e) <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>9 <lb/>v) No, Gene in e) <lb/>14 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 <lb/>41 <lb/>W) No. probe in p) and q) <lb/>44 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>x) No. Gene with TSS-DMR (v and w) <lb/>12 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>*Relationship to canonical CpG Island: Shores, -0-2 kb from CpG island; Shelves, -2-4 kb from CpG island; <lb/>N, upstream of CpG island; S, downstream of CpG island. <lb/>**Gene region feature category: Gene region feature category describing the CpG position, from UCSC. <lb/>TSS200 = 0-200 bases upstream of the transcriptional start site (TSS). <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">TSS1500 = 200-1500 bases upstream of the TSS. <lb/>5&apos;UTR = Within the 5&apos; untranslated region, between the TSS and the ATG start site. <lb/>Body = Between the ATG and stop codon; irrespective of the presence of introns, exons, TSS, or promoters. <lb/>3&apos;UTR = Between the stop codon and poly A signal. <lb/>This information on HumanMethylation450K was provided by Illumina Inc. <lb/>Fig. 4 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>H19 <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>MEG3 <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>XIST <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>PEG3 <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>IGF2R <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>PEG10 <lb/>Episomal-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Retro-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=3) <lb/>Sendai-<lb/>Edom-<lb/>iPSCs <lb/>(n=6) <lb/>Fig. 4 Distribution of methylation scores at promoters of imprint genes and XIST gene. H19, <lb/>MEG3, PEG3, PEG10, IGF2R and XIST genes are shown. ESCs (n=12, black circles); <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPSCs (n=3, green circles); Sendai-Edom-iPSCs (n=6, red circles); <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPSCs (n=3, blue circles); parent somatic cells, Edom-22 (n=2, yellow circles). <lb/>The probe IDs and probe positions of each gene were cg17985533, TSS200 for H19, cg09926418, <lb/>TSS200 for MEG3, cg13960339, TSS200 for PEG3, cg27504782, TSS1500 for PEG10, <lb/>cg10894318, TSS1500 for IGF2R and cg11717280, TSS200 for XIST. TSS200 and TSS1500 <lb/>indicated the position of the probe; TSS200, 0 -200 bases and TSS1500, 200 -1500 bases <lb/>upstream of the transcriptional start site (TSS). <lb/> Cell line ID <lb/>Karyotype <lb/>Cell number <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-05 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-23 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-30 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-31 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-35 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-39 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Epidermis <lb/>Cartilage <lb/>Gut-like epithelium <lb/>Neural tissues <lb/>SSEA-4 <lb/>TRA1-60 <lb/>SOX2 <lb/>OCT3/4 <lb/>NANOG <lb/>SSEA-4 <lb/>TRA1-60 <lb/>SOX2 <lb/>OCT3/4 <lb/>NANOG <lb/>Supplemental Fig. 1 Characterization of Sendai-Edom-iPSCs. A, Immunohistochemistry of stem <lb/>cell-specific surface antigens, SSEA-4, TRA1-60, and SOX2, OCT3/4, NANOG in <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPS-31. B, Teratoma formation of Sendai-Edom-iPS-31 by subcutaneous <lb/>implantation into NOD/Scid mice. The Sendai-Edom-iPSCs differentiated to various tissues <lb/>including ectoderm (epidermis and neural tissues), mesoderm (cartilage) and endoderm (gut-like <lb/>epithelium). Immunostaining and teratoma formation were carried out as previously described [36, <lb/>38]. C, Karyotypic analysis of Sendai-Edom-iPSCs. D, STR analysis of Sendai-Edom-iPSCs. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex"> A <lb/>B <lb/> 11 <lb/> Cell line ID <lb/>Karyotype <lb/>Cell number <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-1 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-8 46, XX <lb/>50 <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-9 46, XX <lb/>49 <lb/>47, XX <lb/>1 <lb/>SSEA-4 <lb/>TRA1-60 <lb/>OCT3/4 <lb/>NANOG <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Gut-like epithelium <lb/>Cartilage <lb/>Neural tissues <lb/>Supplemental Fig. 2 Characterization of Episomal-Edom-iPSCs. A, Immunohistochemistry of <lb/>stem cell-specific surface antigens, SSEA-4, TRA1-60, and SOX2, OCT3/4, NANOG in <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPS-01. B, Teratoma formation of Episomal-Edom-iPS-01 by subcutaneous <lb/>implantation into NOD/Scid mice. The Episomal-Edom-iPSCs differentiated to various tissues <lb/>including ectoderm (epidermis and neural tissues), mesoderm (cartilage) and endoderm (gut-like <lb/>epithelium). Immunostaining and teratoma formation were carried out as previously described [36, <lb/>38]. C, Karyotypic analysis of Episomal-Edom-iPSCs. D, STR analysis of Episomal-Edom-iPSCs. <lb/>Retro-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Episomal-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Sendai-Edom-iPSCs <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>H19 <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>MEG3 <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>XIST <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>PEG3 <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>IGFR2 <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Methylation score <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>PEG10 <lb/>ESCs <lb/>(n=12) <lb/>Parent <lb/>Somatic <lb/>cells <lb/>(n=2) <lb/>Edom-iPSCs <lb/>P10 <lb/>P20 <lb/>P30 <lb/>P40 <lb/>Supplemental Fig. 3 Effect of continuous cultivation on ES-iPS-DMRs at promoters of imprint <lb/>genes and XIST gene. ESCs (n=12, black circles); Retro-Edom-iPSCs (n=3, green circles and <lb/>lines); Sendai-Edom-iPSCs (n=6, red circles and lines); Episomal-Edom-iPSCs (n=3, blue circles <lb/>and lines); parent somatic cells, Edom-22 (n=2, yellow circles). The probe IDs and probe positions <lb/>of each gene were cg17985533, TSS200 for H19, cg09926418, TSS200 for MEG3, cg13960339, <lb/>TSS200 for PEG3, cg27504782, TSS1500 for PEG10, cg10894318, TSS1500 for IGF2R and c <lb/>g11717280, TSS200 for XIST. TSS200 and TSS1500 indicated the position of the probe; TSS200, <lb/>0 -200 bases and TSS1500, 200 -1500 bases upstream of the transcriptional start site (TSS). <lb/>Supplemental Table 1. Sample details <lb/>Cell line name in this paper <lb/>Passage number Cell type <lb/>Gender Vector type Vector name Factors <lb/>Origin <lb/>Reference for cell line Cell line name in reference <lb/>GSE ID <lb/>GEO ID <lb/>Reference for GEO <lb/>Cell line name in reference <lb/>ES-CM6_P19 <lb/>19 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Laurent et al., 2010 CM-6 <lb/>GSE31848 <lb/>GSM867941 <lb/>Nazor et al., 2012 CM6 <lb/>ES-CSC14_P29 <lb/>29 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Harnesset al., 2011 CSC14 <lb/>GSE31848 <lb/>GSM867939 <lb/>Nazor et al., 2012 CSC14 <lb/>ES-HES2_P105 <lb/>5 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Reubinoff et al., 2000 HES-2 <lb/>GSE31848 <lb/>GSM867947 <lb/>Nazor et al., 2012 HES2 <lb/>ES-WA07_P35 <lb/>35 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Thomson et al., 1998 H7 <lb/>GSE31848 <lb/>GSM867952 <lb/>Nazor et al., 2012 WA07 <lb/>ES-WA09_P39 <lb/>39 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Thomson et al., 1998 H9 <lb/>GSE31848 <lb/>GSM867936 <lb/>Nazor et al., 2012 WA09 <lb/>ES-HUES-06_P25 <lb/>25 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Cowan et al., 204 <lb/>HUES6 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906514 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-HUES-09_P33 <lb/>33 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Cowan et al., 204 <lb/>HUES9 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906515 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-SEES-01_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Akutsu et al., 2015 SEES-1 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906516 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-SEES-02_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Akutsu et al., 2015 SEES-2 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906517 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-SEES-04_P11 <lb/>11 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Akutsu et al., 2015 SEES-4 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906518 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-SEES-05_P45 <lb/>45 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Akutsu et al., 2015 SEES-5 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906519 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>ES-SEES-07_P45 <lb/>45 <lb/>ES cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Blastocyst <lb/>Akutsu et al., 2015 SEES-7 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906520 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Retro-iPS-Edom-iPS-01_P23 <lb/>23 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Retro <lb/>pMX <lb/>O, S, K ,M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Nishino et al., 2011 Edom-iPS-1_P23 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906529 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Retro-iPS-Edom-iPS-02_P31 <lb/>31 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Retro <lb/>pMX <lb/>O, S, K ,M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Nishino et al., 2011 Edom-iPS-2_P31 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906530 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Retro-iPS-Edom-iPS-03_P29 <lb/>29 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Retro <lb/>pMX <lb/>O, S, K ,M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Nishino et al., 2011 Edom-iPS-3_P29 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906531 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-05_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906533 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-23_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906532 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-30_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906534 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-31_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906537 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-35_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906535 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-39_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906536 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-01_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906538 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-08_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906539 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-09_P30 <lb/>30 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906540 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Primary-Edom22_P5 <lb/>5 <lb/>Primary cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Cui et al., 2007 <lb/>Edom22 <lb/>GSE73938 <lb/>GSM1906542 <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Different passage <lb/>Cell line name in this paper <lb/>Passage number Cell type <lb/>Gender Vector type Vector name Factors <lb/>Origin <lb/>Reference for cell line Cell line name in reference <lb/>GSE ID <lb/>GEO ID <lb/>Reference for GEO <lb/>Cell line name in reference <lb/>Retro-iPS-Edom-iPS-02_P22 <lb/>22 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Retro <lb/>pMX <lb/>O, S, K ,M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Nishino et al., 2011 Edom-iPS-2_P22 <lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Retro-iPS-Edom-iPS-02_P42 <lb/>42 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Retro <lb/>pMX <lb/>O, S, K ,M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Nishino et al., 2011 Edom-iPS-2_P42 <lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-05_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-05_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-23_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-23_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-30_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-30_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-31_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-31_P40 <lb/>40 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-35_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-35_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-39_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Sendai-iPS-Edom-iPS-39_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Sendai <lb/>SeVdp <lb/>O-S-K-M <lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-01_P16 <lb/>16 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-01_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-01_P40 <lb/>40 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-08_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-08_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-08_P40 <lb/>40 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-09_P10 <lb/>10 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-09_P20 <lb/>20 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Episomal-iPS-Edom-iPS-09_P40 <lb/>40 <lb/>iPS cells <lb/>XX <lb/>Episomal <lb/>pCXLE <lb/>O-shp53, SK, UL Menstrual blood <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Primary-Edom22_P7 <lb/>7 <lb/>Primary cells <lb/>XX <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Menstrual blood <lb/>Cui et al., 2008 <lb/>Edom22 <lb/>in progress <lb/>in progress <lb/>in this study <lb/>-<lb/>Supplemental Table 2. List of gene with DMRs at the promoters <lb/>Supplemental Table 4 List of primers <lb/>Primers for quantitative RT-PCR <lb/>Name <lb/>Sequence (5&apos; -&gt; 3&apos;) <lb/>Anealing temp. <lb/>hDNMT1-F <lb/>ATTCTGATGGATCCCAGTCCC <lb/>hDNMT1-R <lb/>GTCCTTCTCCCTGGTAGAATG <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hDNMT3A-F <lb/>GCCAAAACTGCAAGAACTGC <lb/>hDNMT3A-R <lb/>CCTTTGGAGGGTCAAATTCC <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hDNMT3B-F <lb/>AATCCTGGAGGCTATCCGCAC <lb/>hDNMT3B-R <lb/>GTCAGAGCCATCCCCATCTTC <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hDNMT3L-F <lb/>ATGTGGTTGATGTCACAGAC <lb/>hDNMT3L-R <lb/>GACAGCATTCTGCAAGGATC <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hTET1-F <lb/>CTGGACTTCTGTGCTCATCC <lb/>hTET1-R <lb/>ACATGGAGCTGCTCATCTTG <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hTET2-F <lb/>CAGCAGCCAATAGGACATGATC <lb/>hTET2-R <lb/>ATGGGAGGTGATGGTATCAG <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hTET3-F <lb/>CAAGGACCAGCATAACCTCTAC <lb/>hTET3-R <lb/>AGAACATGCAGCTGCTCATC <lb/>60˚C <lb/>hGAPDH-F <lb/>GCTCAGACACCATGGGGAAGGT <lb/>hGAPDH-R <lb/>GTGGTGCAGGAGGCATTGCTGA <lb/>60˚C </div>


	</text>
</tei>
