<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> ZetaHunter: a reproducible taxonomic classification tool for tracking the ecology of the <lb/>Zetaproteobacteria and other poorly-resolved taxa <lb/>Sean M. McAllister, a # Ryan M. Moore, b and Clara S. Chan a,c <lb/>a School of Marine Science and Policy, University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware, USA <lb/>b Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology, University of Delaware, Newark, <lb/>Delaware, USA <lb/>c Department of Geological Sciences, University of Delaware, Newark, Delaware, USA <lb/>Running Head: ZetaHunter: a Zetaproteobacteria classification tool <lb/>#Address correspondence to Sean M. McAllister, zetahunter.help@gmail.com. <lb/>S.M.M. and R.M.M. contributed equally to this work. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract. Like many taxa, the Zetaproteobacteria lack well-defined taxonomic divisions, <lb/>making it difficult to compare between studies. We designed ZetaHunter to reproducibly <lb/>assign 16S rRNA gene sequences to previously-described OTUs based on a curated <lb/>database. While ZetaHunter can use any given database, we include a curated <lb/>classification of publically-available Zetaproteobacteria. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction. Taxonomic groups with limited cultivated representatives are often <lb/>lumped into a single taxonomic label encompassing multiple distinct ecological units. <lb/>This makes it difficult to explicitly discuss the abundance, significance, and niche <lb/>preference of these units between studies. One group with poor taxonomic resolution is <lb/>the Zetaproteobacteria class, which is only accurately classified to this taxonomic level <lb/>by standard small subunit ribosomal RNA (16S rRNA) gene classification tools. <lb/>ZetaHunter allows for reproducible, higher-resolution comparisons across studies by <lb/>using a curated dataset with a defined taxonomy based on operational taxonomic units <lb/>(OTUs). ZetaHunter comes with a curated database to identify the members of the <lb/>Zetaproteobacteria, though it may be used with any curated 16S rRNA gene database. <lb/>ZetaHunter implementation. ZetaHunter is a command line program written in Ruby, <lb/>designed to assign user-supplied 16S rRNA gene sequences to OTUs defined by a <lb/>reference sequence database. ZetaHunter can be used on Linux, MacOSX, and Windows <lb/>platforms through a Docker container, or through installation from source (Linux and <lb/>MacOSX only). By default, ZetaHunter uses a curated database of Zetaproteobacteria <lb/>16S rRNA genes from ARB SILVA (release 128) and Zetaproteobacteria genomes from <lb/>JGI&apos;s Integrated Microbial Genomes (IMG) (see Supplemental Table 1). <lb/>Zetaproteobacteria OTU (ZOTU) definitions include those reported by McAllister et al. <lb/>(2011) at 97% identity, maintaining ZOTU number order from ZOTU1 to ZOTU28 for <lb/>ease in comparisons across studies. Numbered ZOTUs from ZOTU29 upward were <lb/>discovered after 2011. Sequences for use in ZetaHunter must be aligned using SINA <lb/>(Pruesse et al., 2012). <lb/>The default pipeline of ZetaHunter (Figure 1) takes SINA-aligned 16S rRNA <lb/>gene sequences and processes them as follows: 1) Input sequences are masked to the <lb/>1,282 bp used by McAllister et al. (2011). 2) Sequences are checked for chimeras using <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>mothur&apos;s uchime algorithm (Schloss et al., 2009; Edgar et al., 2011). 2) SortmeRNA is <lb/>used to cluster new sequences with the reference database, assigning ZOTU based on <lb/>genetic distance (closed reference binning; Kopylova et al., 2012). 3) The remaining <lb/>sequences are clustered into novel OTUs (NewZetaOtus) with mothur (de novo binning; <lb/>average neighbor; numbered by abundance) (Schloss et al., 2009). 4) Summary files <lb/>(including final ZOTU calls and closest database hits), a biom table showing OTU <lb/>abundance per sample, and OTU network files are exported for use. The ZetaHunter <lb/>database includes 21 Proteobacteria outgroup sequences, allowing ZetaHunter to flag <lb/>sequences potentially outside the Zetaproteobacteria. Additionally, sequences that are <lb/>short, chimeric, or singletons are also flagged. This pipeline is an implementation of <lb/>open-reference OTU picking similar to the one found in QIIME (Navas-Molina et al., <lb/>2013). <lb/>To use ZetaHunter for non-Zetaproteobacteria, users need: 1) a database of SINA-<lb/>aligned 16S rRNA gene sequences, 2) a sequence mask with asterisks at each informative <lb/>alignment column to be used for taxonomic assignment, and 3) a tab-delimited file <lb/>assigning each sequence to a particular taxonomic group at the similarity threshold <lb/>desired by the user. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Software availability. ZetaHunter is available for download at <lb/>&lt;https://github.com/mooreryan/ZetaHunter&gt;. GitHub documentation includes examples <lb/>for Zetaproteobacteria and non-Zetaproteobacteria classification and output file <lb/>explanations. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Dave Emerson for providing 16S rRNA sequences for the ZetaHunter database <lb/>from novel Zetaproteobacteria isolates. D Emerson and B Chiu are thanked for their <lb/>comments on early versions of this manuscript. We also thank K Hager, H Fullerton, J <lb/>Scott, and J Vander Roost for testing and troubleshooting ZetaHunter using multiple <lb/>platforms and datasets. We also acknowledge the ARB/SILVA group for their work with <lb/>stable 16S rRNA alignments using the SINA tool; this tool is key to ZetaHunter&apos;s <lb/>function. SMM and RMM designed the ZetaHunter program. SMM developed the <lb/>Zetaproteobacteria database. RMM wrote the ZetaHunter program. SMM, RMM, and <lb/></div>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">CSC wrote and edited this manuscript. This work was funded by NSF grant OCE-<lb/>1155290 (to CSC) and USDA National Institute of Food and Agriculture award number <lb/>2012-68003-30155. Computational infrastructure support by the University of Delaware <lb/>Center for Bioinformatics and Computational Biology Core Facility was made possible <lb/>through funding from Delaware INBRE (NIH P20 GM103446) and the Delaware <lb/>Biotechnology Institute. The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Edgar RC, BJ Haas, JC Clemente, C Quince, and R Knight. 2011. UCHIME improves <lb/>sensitivity and speed of chimera detection. Bioinformatics, <lb/>doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btr381 <lb/>Kopylova E, L Noé, and H Touzet H. 2012. SortMeRNA: Fast and accurate filtering of <lb/>ribosomal RNAs in metatranscriptomic data. Bioinformatics <lb/>doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/bts611 <lb/>McAllister SM, RE Davis, JM McBeth, BM Tebo, D Emerson, and CL Moyer. 2011. <lb/>Biodiversity and emerging biogeography of the neutrophilic iron-oxidizing <lb/>Zetaproteobacteria. Appl. Environ. Microbiol. 77:5445-57. <lb/>Navas-Molina JA, Peralta-Sánchez JM, González A, McMurdie PJ, Vázquez-Baeza Y, <lb/>Xu Z, Ursell LK, Lauber C, Zhou H, Song SJ, Huntley J, Ackermann GL, Berg-<lb/>Lyons D, Holmes S, Caporaso JG, Knight R. 2013. Advancing our understanding of <lb/>the human microbiome using QIIME. Methods in Enzymology. 531:371-444. doi: <lb/>10.1016/B978-0-12-407863-5.00019-8 <lb/>Pruesse E, J Peplies, and FO Glöckner. 2012. SINA: accurate high-throughput multiple <lb/>sequence alignment of ribosomal RNA genes. Bioinformatics 28:1823-1829. <lb/>Schloss PD, SL Westcott, T Ryabin, JR Hall, M Hartmann, EB Hollister, RA Lesniewski, <lb/>BB Oakley, DH Parks, CJ Robinson, JW Sahl, B Stres, GG Thallinger, DJ Van Horn, <lb/>and CF Weber. 2009. Introducing mothur: Open-source, platform-independent, <lb/>community-supported software for describing and comparing microbial communities. <lb/>Appl Environ Microbiol, 75(23):7537-41. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Flow chart showing the ZetaHunter pipeline. Third-party tools used in the <lb/>pipeline are indicated to the left. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
