<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>-1-<lb/></page>

			<front>Fndc3a (Fibronectin Domain Containing Protein 3A) influences median fin fold <lb/>development and caudal fin regeneration in zebrafish by ECM alteration. <lb/>Daniel Liedtke 1,* , Melanie Orth 1 , Michelle Meissler 1 , Sinje Geuer 2 , Sabine Knaup 1 , Isabell <lb/>Köblitz 1,3 , Eva Klopocki 1 <lb/>1 Institute of Human Genetics, Biocenter, University of Würzburg, 97074 Würzburg, Germany <lb/>2 Department of Human Genetics, Donders Institute for Brain, Cognition and Behaviour, <lb/>Radboud University Medical Center, 6500 HB Nijmegen, The Netherlands <lb/>3 Department of Cell and Developmental Biology, Biocenter, University of Würzburg, 97074 <lb/>Würzburg, Germany <lb/>* Corresponding author: Daniel Liedtke <lb/>Institut für Humangenetik, <lb/>Biozentrum, Am Hubland <lb/>Julius-Maximilians Universität Würzburg <lb/>D-97074 Würzburg <lb/>Tel.: +49-931-31-81350 <lb/>Fax.: +49-931-31-81350-0 <lb/>E-mail address: liedtke@biozentrum.uni-wuerzburg.de <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-2-<lb/></page>

			<front>Keywords (max. 6) <lb/>median fin fold, caudal fin regeneration, epidermal cells, zebrafish, CRISPR/Cas9, ECM <lb/>Summary statement <lb/>We investigated potential functions of Fndc3a during caudal fin development and <lb/>regeneration in zebrafish. Reduced function interferes with correct epidermal cells structure <lb/>and implies a role during vertebrate extremity development. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Inherited genetic alterations are often found to be disease-causing factors of patient <lb/>phenotypes. To unravel the molecular consequences of newly identified factors functional <lb/>investigations in vivo are eminent. We investigated molecular functions of FNDC3A <lb/>(Fibronectin Domain Containing Protein 3A; HUGO), a novel candidate gene for split-<lb/>hand/foot malformations (SHFM) in humans, by utilizing zebrafish (Danio rerio) as a <lb/>vertebrate model. Patients with congenital SHFM display prominent limb malformations, <lb/>which are caused by disturbance of limb development due to defects in apical ectodermal <lb/>ridge (AER) establishment and maintenance. Initial gene expression and protein localization <lb/>studies clarified the presence of fndc3a in developing and regenerating fins of zebrafish. For <lb/>functional studies we established a hypomorphic fndc3a mutant line (fndc3a wue1/wue1 ) via <lb/>CRISPR/Cas9, exhibiting phenotypic malformations and changed gene expression patterns <lb/>during early stages of median fin fold development. Furthermore, fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants <lb/>display abnormal collagen localization, actinotrichia breakup and cellular defects in epidermal <lb/>cells during caudal fin development. The observed effects are only temporary and later result <lb/>in rather normal fin development in adults. In accordance with early fin development, proper <lb/>caudal fin regeneration in adult fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants is hampered by interference with <lb/>actinotrichia formation and epidermal cell abnormalities. Investigation of cellular matrix <lb/>formation implied that loss of ECM structure is a common cause for both phenotypes. Our <lb/>results thereby provide a molecular link between Fndc3a function during both developmental <lb/>processes in zebrafish and foreshadow Fndc3a as a novel temporal regulator of epidermal <lb/>cell properties during extremity development in vertebrates. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-3-<lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Patients suffering from SHFM display prominent limb malformations, lacking the central <lb/>autopod rays, resulting in syndactyly, aplasia and/or hypoplasia of the phalanges, <lb/>metacarpals and metatarsals, and median clefts of hands and feet (Duijf et al., 2003; <lb/>Gurrieri and Everman, 2013). Several genetic loci and causes have been associated with this <lb/>inherited disease, for example mutations in TP63 (OMIM *603273), DLX5 (OMIM *600028) <lb/>or DLX6 (OMIM *600030). A large number of animal experiments and cell culture studies <lb/>further clarified the underlying genetic network, but still unresolved patient cases disclose the <lb/>necessity to identify novel contributing molecular factors. <lb/>We identified FNDC3A as a new potential candidate gene in pathogenesis of human non-<lb/>syndromic SHFM by exome sequencing of a consanguineous family from Syria with four <lb/>affected individuals (unpublished data). FNDC3A consists of up to nine fibronectin type III <lb/>domains, which are a common feature of a large number of extracellular proteins acting by <lb/>modulation of different signaling pathways (Cheng et al., 2013; Zhu and Clark, 2014). <lb/>FNDC3A has initially been described to be overexpressed in human odontoblasts (Carrouel <lb/>et al., 2008). Functional experiments in Symplastic spermatids (sys) knockout mice indicated <lb/>that FNDC3A is essential for cell adhesion between spermatids and Sertoli cells, resulting in <lb/>sterile males (Obholz et al., 2006). Besides these two studies the developmental function of <lb/>FNDC3A is still unknown and no association to extremity development or regeneration has <lb/>been described yet. The purpose of this study was to investigate potential functions of <lb/>Fndc3a during extremity development and regeneration in zebrafish. <lb/>Differences between tetrapod limb and fin development in ray-finned fishes (Actinopterygii) <lb/>are obvious in anatomy and structure, but both are homologous appendages and thought to <lb/>share common genetic features (Yano and Tamura, 2013). Also the development of pectoral <lb/>fins in fish species is assumed to closely resemble extremity development in higher <lb/>vertebrates, by sharing common molecular signals arising from a structure called the apical <lb/>ectodermal ridge (AER) (Amaral and Schneider, 2017; Yano et al., 2012). Only recently <lb/>differences between fin and limb AER have been reported and hint at a fin specific cellular <lb/>process in fish species (Masselink et al., 2016; Yano et al., 2012). Even more eminent are <lb/>developmental differences between paired fins (pectoral fins) and unpaired fins (caudal, anal <lb/>and dorsal fins), as the establishment of the is achieved by evolutionary more distant <lb/>processes (van den Boogaart et al., 2012). All unpaired fins arise from a common <lb/>developmental precursor structure during larval stages called the median fin fold, which is <lb/>exclusively found in larval teleosts. A wide number of molecular processes and distinct genes <lb/>have been identified by several genetic screens in zebrafish revealing a complex network of <lb/>factors necessary for correct median fin fold development (Carney et al., 2010; van Eeden et <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-4-<lb/></page>

			<body>al., 1996). More than years ago changes of epidermal cell shape and modulation of the <lb/>extracellular matrix (ECM) have been described as one of the essential factors for correct <lb/>median fin fold and caudal fin morphogenesis in zebrafish (Dane and Tucker, 1985). Later, <lb/>signals from the WNT signaling pathway have been shown to be crucial for regulation of <lb/>epithelial cell morphology by modulating laminin levels and thereby orchestrating correct <lb/>patterning in growing fins (Nagendran et al., 2015). These early cellular steps of caudal fin <lb/>development are prerequisites for subsequent processes; i.e. mesoderm cell migration, cell <lb/>differentiation and normal fin growth. After initiation and pattern formation within the fin fold, <lb/>further tissue differentiation results in the development of cartilage and bone, as skeletal <lb/>elements in the later fin, and the gradual resorption of the median fin fold during juvenile <lb/>stages (Parichy et al., 2009). Fin rays are formed by the assembly of actinotrichia and <lb/>lepidotrichia in the ECM of epidermal cells (Grandel and Schulte-Merker, 1998; Zhang et al., <lb/>2010). While lepidotrichia are segmented and calcified bone rays, actinotrichia are non-<lb/>calcified collagen fibers. Two collagens are essential for actinotrichia formation during fin <lb/>development: Col2a1 and Col1a1 (Duran et al., 2011). In addition to the collagens actinodin <lb/>proteins, encoded by the and1 and and2 genes, have been identified to be essential for <lb/>actinotrichia formation (Zhang et al., 2010). During development actinotrichia fibers are <lb/>normally formed at the fin tips, depicting characteristic brush-shaped structures. <lb/>Fin regeneration is a developmental process in adult fish sharing a number of conserved <lb/>molecular mechanisms with extremity development at earlier stages of development (Iovine, <lb/>2007; Wehner and Weidinger, 2015). For both processes correct epidermal cell function, <lb/>epithelial cell structure, and actinotrichia fibers are essential to correctly build all skeletal and <lb/>mesenchymal fin elements (Mari-Beffa et al., 1989; Pfefferli and Jazwinska, 2015). Additional <lb/>structural factors, especially ECM proteins like integrins and laminins, have been implied in <lb/>regulating Wnt signaling during regeneration and in correct assembly of the teleost fin <lb/>(Carney et al., 2010; Nagendran et al., 2015; Webb et al., 2007). Although a large number of <lb/>involved &quot;molecular players&quot; have been described to date, not all factors necessary for <lb/>correct ECM assembly in the regenerating caudal fin have been identified yet. We propose <lb/>Fndc3a as a novel player in both fin development and regeneration. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-5-<lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>The FNDC3A orthologous gene in zebrafish, fndc3a, is located on zebrafish chromosome 15 <lb/>(ENSEMBL Zv9: 3,066,162-3,114,443 reverse strand; ENSDARG00000067569; ZFIN ID: <lb/>ZDB-GENE-030131-7015) and encodes in 29 exons for a transcript of 3501 bp. The <lb/>corresponding zebrafish 1166aa Fndc3a protein (ENSDART00000097261) consists of 4 <lb/>transmembrane domains and 9 fibronectin type III domains. Two different predicted transcript <lb/>variants have recently been reported for fndc3a (GenBank: XM_021466300.1, <lb/>XM_021466301), encoding for proteins of 1247 and 1217aa. Both transcript variants are <lb/>highly similar and differ only in a 30aa stretch at the N-terminus. <lb/>Phylogenetic and syntheny analyses showed that the FNDC3A gene is highly conserved <lb/>throughout vertebrate evolution and orthologues are not duplicated in ray-finned fish species <lb/>(data not shown). Amino acid alignments resulted in an up to 57% amino acid identity with <lb/>95% coverage, indicating a high level of conservation between human and zebrafish <lb/>proteins. Two fndc3a paralogues can be identified in the zebrafish genome: fndc3ba <lb/>(chromosome 2; ENSDARG00000078179; ZFIN ID: ZDB-GENE-070510-1) and fndc3bb <lb/>(chromosome 24; ENSDARG00000062023; ZFIN ID: ZDB-GENE-070510-2). Both genes <lb/>share highest sequence similarities with FNDC3B genes in other species and are dedicated <lb/>in genomic analyses to an evolutionary distinct group when compared to FNDC3 genes. All <lb/>three gene family members have not been functionally investigated in zebrafish yet. <lb/>Expression of fndc3a during early zebrafish development. <lb/>To resolve the spatiotemporal expression of fndc3a during zebrafish development, we <lb/>performed RNA in-situ hybridization experiments. fndc3a transcripts were detected spatially <lb/>restricted to the tail bud region and the ventral fin fold mesenchyme from 14hpf onwards (hpf <lb/>= hours post-fertilization; Fig. 1). Expression of fndc3a at later stages of embryonic <lb/>development is mainly present in distinct brain regions; e.g. mid-hindbrain boundary, <lb/>rhombencephalon, and mesencephalon; as well as in pectoral fins, in the notochord, in <lb/>somites and in the caudal median fin fold (Fig. 1A and Fig. S8A). Restricted expression in the <lb/>developing tail bud region at later stages (&gt;16hpf) could be observed in the median fin fold, <lb/>in Kupffer´s vesicle, and in cells of the chordo neural hinge region by longer staining times <lb/>(Fig. 1B). <lb/>&gt;Fig. 1 <lb/>Detection of Fndc3a protein localization was performed via immunofluorescence by <lb/>application of a human FNDC3A antibody. This experiment showed similar regional <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-6-<lb/></page>

			<body>localization of Fndc3a in Kupffer´s vesicle, the median fin fold region, and the caudal <lb/>neuronal hinge during different stages of embryonic development consistent with RNA in-situ <lb/>hybridization (24hpf: Fig. 1C and 48hpf: Fig.1D). The two most noticeable differences <lb/>between RNA and protein localization were a spotted pattern of Fndc3a in notochord cells <lb/>and in chevron shaped stripes between somite boundaries (higher magnification images in <lb/>Fig.1C). Moreover this experiment clarified the cellular localization of Fndc3a at the cell <lb/>membrane of epidermal cells during early stages of median fin fold development (higher <lb/>magnification images Fig. 1C and D). <lb/>Generation of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>To investigate consequences of fndc3a loss in zebrafish, we established a fndc3a wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutant line via the CRISPR/Cas9 system (Hwang et al., 2013; Jao et al., 2013). sgRNAs <lb/>were designed to target the evolutionary highly conserved third fibronectin III domain of <lb/>Fndc3a (Fig. 2A), as incomplete genome information about the 5´end of fndc3a at the <lb/>initiation of the project prevented the identification of a distinct start codon for sRNA <lb/>targeting. For further analyses a zebrafish line with a 5bp substitution leading to a premature <lb/>Stop codon in exon 13 (Zv9: ENSDARE00000690608) of fndc3a was chosen (fndc3a wue1 line; <lb/>ZFIN ID: ZDB-ALT-170417-3; Fig. S1A). The alteration was validated by sequencing of <lb/>genomic DNA and cDNA (Fig. 2A; Fig. S1C) and could be detected continuously in <lb/>subsequent inbred generations (data not shown). Off-site targets of the used fndc3a sgRNA <lb/>were computationally predicted and investigated by sequencing the three most likely <lb/>potential off-target sites. No off-site sequence alterations were detected in fndc3a wue1/+ or <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (Fig. S1B). <lb/>&gt;Fig. 2 <lb/>&gt;Fig. S1 <lb/>Phenotypic investigation and validation of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>Initial visual investigation of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants indicated a tail bud and median fin fold <lb/>phenotype in homozygous embryos (Fig. 2B-D). A first indication of changed fin development <lb/>could be observed 20-22hpf, as a number of fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos showed straightened <lb/>tail buds and reduced ventral fin fold structures (47%, n=40; arrow in Fig.2B). During <lb/>subsequent stages of embryonic development fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutant embryos developed <lb/>kinked tails (27%, n= 100; 48hpf; Fig. 2C) and caudal fin fold malformations (22%, n= 41; <lb/>120hpf; arrows in Fig. 2D). The observed fin malformations in 120hpf embryos are sites of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-7-<lb/></page>

			<body>actinotrichia aggregation and show accumulation of apoptotic cells at this position (Fig. S2). <lb/>Further assessment of temperature sensitivity of the fndc3a wue1/wue1 phenotype revealed that <lb/>raised temperatures result in an increased number and severity of the caudal fin phenotype <lb/>(32°C incubation: 60%, n= 85; 28°C incubation: 48%, n= 40; 20°C incubation: 18%, n= 28; <lb/>Fig. S3). <lb/>&gt;Fig. S2 <lb/>&gt;Fig. S3 <lb/>Besides the observed early median fin fold effects, fndc3a wue1/wue1 juvenile and adult <lb/>individuals in general showed normal development and behavior. The generated <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 lines did not show reduction of fertility rates, which could have been suspected <lb/>from published mouse knock-out lines (Fndc3a Gt(RRP208)Byg or Fndc3a sys ; Mouse Genome <lb/>Database (MGD) at the Mouse Genome Informatics website, The Jackson Laboratory, Bar <lb/>Harbor, Maine. http://www.informatics.jax.org; Obholz et al., 2006). Although, in <lb/>approximately 30% of adult homozygous fndc3a wue1/wue1 fish alterations of the caudal fin <lb/>shape and the posterior body part could be visually detected (n=21/71). The observed <lb/>phenotype ranged from minor fin shape changes in the majority of affected fish, up to axis <lb/>shortening and stronger caudal fin deformations (Fig. 2E). We did not observe changes in <lb/>phenotype severity or appearance rates in subsequent, homozygous generations, excluding <lb/>a potential stronger maternal zygotic effect in fndc3a wue1/wue1 or mitigation of the phenotype. <lb/>The observation of variable adult phenotypes, incomplete phenotypic penetrance and <lb/>temperature sensitivity of the embryonic phenotype led us to the assumption that <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants are hypomorphic. Further investigations of the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutant <lb/>line via qPCR were performed to investigate potential nonsense mediated decay of fndc3a <lb/>mRNAs. We quantified fndc3a mRNA expression in three independent embryo groups with <lb/>two independent primer pairs (Fig. 2F; primer sequences are given in Table S1). Relative to <lb/>AB controls fndc3a transcripts in fndc3a wue1/+ and fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants were reduced to <lb/>approximately 60% in heterozygotes and correspondingly to 30% relative expression in <lb/>homozygotes. This experiment showed a reduction, but not a complete loss, of fndc3a <lb/>mRNA in the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants and thereby implies a potential residual function of <lb/>Fndc3a in these mutants. <lb/>To achieve a full loss-of-function fndc3a phenotype two sgRNAs targeting exon 13 and 18 <lb/>were designed and simultaneously used, resulting in a potential larger intragenic deletion or <lb/>the introduction of several sequence alterations in the fndc3a locus. The corresponding <lb/>transient phenotype indicated a more severe tail fin malformations in these fish (n=12/32) <lb/>when compared to fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (Fig. S4). Phenotypically the observed tail <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-8-<lb/></page>

			<body>malformation defects showed strong caudal fin reduction and tail curling, similar to smad5 <lb/>(somitabun or piggytail) (Mullins, 1996 #124;Hild, 1999 #123} or bmp1a zebrafish mutants <lb/>(frilly fins) (Asharani et al., 2012). The double fndc3a CRISPR phenotype could not be <lb/>maintained and next generation crossings did not result in a stable line, indicating, similar to <lb/>Symplastic spermatids (sys) mice constricted fertility after complete loss or stronger <lb/>reduction of Fndc3a function. However, this transient experiment supported our observations <lb/>of the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutant and indicated a noticeable influence of Fndc3a function on <lb/>caudal fin development. <lb/>&gt;Fig. S4 <lb/>Reduction of Fndc3a function results in median fin fold defects. <lb/>To elucidate the molecular causes underlying the early changes in caudal fin development of <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants we analyzed expression patterns of different, well established <lb/>markers, expressed in the median fin fold tissues (Fig. 3). Expression of fras1 is observed in <lb/>the apical region of median fin fold (Carney et al., 2010; Gautier et al., 2008; Talbot et al., <lb/>2012). hmcn1 expression is present in the epithelial cells of the apical fin fold, while <lb/>expression of hmcn2 can be detected in the fin fold epithelium and the fin mesenchyme <lb/>(Carney et al., 2010; Feitosa et al., 2012). bmp1a expression is described in osteoblasts, fin <lb/>mesenchyme cells, floor plate and hypochord cells (Asharani et al., 2012; Jasuja et al., <lb/>2006). fbln1 is detected in presomitic mesoderm cells and in the dorsal neural rod (Feitosa et <lb/>al., 2012; Zhang et al., 1997) . In fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants expression of fras1 and hmcn1 were <lb/>still present in the dorsal fin apical region 20 to 22hpf, but lost in the ventral region between <lb/>Kupffer´s vesicle and the tail bud tip (number of affected fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos: fras1: 9/32; <lb/>hmcn1: 11/26; Fig. 3A). Vice versa, expression patterns of hmcn2, bmp1a, and fbln1 in this <lb/>region were slightly changed and transverse sections indicated that ventral fin fold structures <lb/>were lost (number of affected fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos: hmcn2: 24/43; bmp1a: 22/45; fbln1: <lb/>16/32). Expression of these three genes in the presomitic mesoderm was present in <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants but indicated convergence or even fusion of somites at ventral <lb/>positions (indicated by arrows in Fig. 3A). The affected regions in the mutants correlated to <lb/>the regions of fndc3a expression during the investigated stages (Fig. 1). Investigation of <lb/>further mesodermal markers in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants at this developmental stage <lb/>additionally confirmed misplaced myod expression in ventral positions and indicated changes <lb/>in chordo neural hinge cells by reduced shha, ta(ntl), and fgf8 expression (number of affected <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos: myoD: 12/22; shha: 7/17; ta(ntl): 5/13; fgf8a: 5/13; Fig. S5), hinting <lb/>at a structural or steric effect on tail development after Fndc3a reduction at this stage of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-9-<lb/></page>

			<body>development. <lb/>Analyses in 48hpf mutant embryos showed reduced expression of fras1 in fndc3a wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutants, but a slight increase of hmnc2, bmp1a and fbln1 expressing cells in the posterior fin <lb/>tip (number of affected fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos: fras1: 10/24; hmcn2: 12/25; bmp1a: 8/21; <lb/>fbln1: 9/24; Fig. 3B). In the same set of embryos expressional changes of fras1, hmcn2, and <lb/>fbln1 in the ventral fin fold, posterior to the proctodeum were less evident, and indicated only <lb/>a slight reduction of fras1 expression and a slightly broader hmcn2 expression (Fig. 3C). <lb/>Similar to the investigated markers the ventral expression domain of and1, an essential <lb/>factor for actinotrichia formation (Duran et al., 2011), was also different in 22hpf <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos (number of affected fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos: 12/25; Fig. 3D). and1 <lb/>expression was recovered in fin folds of 48hpf embryos, but seemed to be slightly weaker in <lb/>comparison to controls (control n=16; weaker expression in fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos <lb/>n=10/18). In general, the gene expression analyses indicate that fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos <lb/>started to recover normal gene expression patterns in median fin fold cells and developed <lb/>only temporal defects during early median fin fold development. Most prominently apical cells <lb/>of the median fin fold were influenced by reduced levels of Fndc3a during the first 2 days of <lb/>zebrafish development. <lb/>&gt;Fig. 3 <lb/>&gt;Fig. S5 <lb/>Morpholino knockdown and rescue experiments support specific role of Fndc3a in <lb/>median fin fold development. <lb/>Validation of fndc3a wue1/wue1 knockdown specific effects on median fin fold development in <lb/>mutants was done by Morpholino knockdown and rescue experiments (Fig. S6 and S7). <lb/>Phenotypic investigation of fndc3a morphants further clarified, that similar to fndc3a wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutant embryos, median fin fold malformations were induced in a dosage dependent manner <lb/>in the first 48h of development (AB control embryos with tail phenotype 24hpf injected with <lb/>0.1mM fndc3a MO: 0/35; 0.25mM fndc3a MO: 17/96; 0.5mM fndc3a MO: 29/56; control: <lb/>2/348; Fig. S6B and C). Notably, injection of fndc3a Morpholino into fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos <lb/>resulted in an enhanced number of embryos showing tail phenotypes and supports the <lb/>hypothesis of a hypomorphic mutation (fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos with tail phenotype 24hpf <lb/>injected with 0.1mM fndc3a MO: 12/36; 0.25mM fndc3a MO: 42/81; 0.5mM fndc3a MO: <lb/>17/18 with high mortality rates; control: 51/207; Fig. S6B and C). Loss of median fin fold <lb/>markers fras1 and hmcn1 and changes in hmcn2 expression in ventral fin folds were <lb/>observed in fndc3a morphants and further confirm the observations in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-10-<lb/></page>

			<body>(summarized altered marker gene expression in control: 0/57; fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 30/58; 0.25nM <lb/>fndc3a MO injection in AB: 14/28; fndc3a 0.25nM MO injection in fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 12/12; Fig. <lb/>S6D). <lb/>&gt;Fig. S6 <lb/>Rescue and overexpression experiments were performed by injection of full-length human <lb/>FNDC3A RNA (Fig. S7). These experiments indicated a rescue of the tail phenotype in <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants after moderate RNA supplementation (tail phenotype in uninjected <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 51/207; fndc3a wue1/wue1 rescue with 25ng/µl FNDC3A RNA: 9/107; <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 rescue with 50ng/µl FNDC3A RNA: 64/94; Fig. S7A and B). In addition, regain <lb/>of fras1 and hmcn1 and hmcn2 marker gene expression was detected in ventral median fin <lb/>folds of rescued embryos (summarized altered marker gene expression in control: 0/20; <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 25/55; fndc3a wue1/wue1 rescue with 25 mg/µl FNDC3A RNA: 4/80; Fig. S7C). <lb/>Injection of FNDC3A RNA into AB control embryos did rarely result in tail malformations (tail <lb/>phenotype in control: 2/345; 25ng/µl FNDC3A RNA: 4/36; 50ng/µl FNDC3A RNA: 7/93; Fig. <lb/>S7B). These experiments indicate a narrow threshold level for Fndc3a to fulfill its function in <lb/>early median fin fold cells and support the observed fndc3a wue1/wue1 phenotype. <lb/>&gt;Fig. S7 <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants show actinotrichia breakdown and basal epidermal cell defects. <lb/>Our observations in homozygous mutants and in morphants implied a transient function of <lb/>Fndc3a during early median fin fold development resulting in caudal fin malformation at later <lb/>stages of development. Localization of fndc3a mRNA expression and Fndc3a protein during <lb/>these stages further suggests that the observed effects are directly or indirectly linked to <lb/>epidermal cells or associated structures. To clarify this question and to investigate structural <lb/>defects causing the observed developmental phenotype we at first investigated actinotrichia <lb/>formation in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>Actinotrichia are a fish-specific structural element consisting of collagen fibers (Col1a1 and <lb/>Col2a1) and actinodin proteins (Duran et al., 2011; Zhang et al., 2010). Characteristically <lb/>transverse striation of actinotrichia can be observed in several fish species via electron <lb/>microscopy and suggests that these fibers are giant collagen fibrils of hyperpolymerized <lb/>collagen (Montes et al., 1982). Actinotrichia were visualized in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants either <lb/>by differential interference contrast (DIC) microscopy (Fig. 4A) or by immunofluorescent <lb/>staining of Col2a, a structural component of actinotrichia ((Duran et al., 2011); Fig. 4B). <lb/>Actinotrichia fibers in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants were still present, but displayed obvious <lb/>structural alterations and signs of breakdown in the ventral caudal fin (control: 0/10; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-11-<lb/></page>

			<body>fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 7/12). While control fish at 52hpf showed radiant symmetrical arrangement of <lb/>Col2a in the actinotrichia fibers of the developing caudal fin, fndc3a wue1/wue1 embryos partly <lb/>lack these structures and depicted unstructured, crumbled collagen fibers in the fin <lb/>mesenchyme (control: 0/7; fndc3a wue1/wue1 :12/14) . High levels of remaining Col2a in <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants could be detected in apical cells at the fin border (arrows in Fig.4B), <lb/>which were also visible as distinct cells in the DIC microscopy (Fig. 4A). <lb/>&gt;Fig. 4 <lb/>Potential cellular reasons for actinotrichia breakdown and Col2 misallocation in the median <lb/>fin fold can be numerous. Based on the expression timing of fndc3a during median fin fold <lb/>development and Fndc3a localization we assumed that epidermal cells might be influenced <lb/>by reduced function of Fndc3a and that the normal cellular organization in the developing fin <lb/>is lost (Dane and Tucker, 1985; Duran et al., 2011). To assess the potential effects of fndc3a <lb/>mutation on epidermal cells during median fin fold development we performed staining for <lb/>TP63 in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (Lee and Kimelman, 2002) (Fig. 4C). In 22-24hpf embryos <lb/>epidermal cells of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants showed lack of ventral fin fold structures and <lb/>reduced median fin fold width at this position (arrows in Fig. 4C9; quantification in Fig. 4D). <lb/>Along with this observation, a reduced number of epidermal cells could be detected at this <lb/>stage in the ventral fin fold. At 48hpf fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants developed outgrowing ventral <lb/>median folds. Although these were still shorter in length they did not display a significant <lb/>lower number of epidermal cells in comparison to control embryos (Fig. 4D10 and D11; <lb/>quantification in Fig. 4E), indicating cellular recovery of the median fin fold structure. <lb/>Additionally, fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants displayed aggregation of epidermal cells at the fin fold <lb/>border, which were not observed in control embryos (Fig. 4D12). <lb/>To further clarify the cellular consequences of Fndc3a reduction in epidermal cells of the <lb/>median fin fold, we performed Transmission Electron Microscopy (TEM). Control or <lb/>fndc3a wue1/+ embryos showed normal arrangement of anatomical fin structures: the outer <lb/>epithelial layer (oel), the basal epidermal layer (bel), the basal membrane (bm), and <lb/>actinotrichia (a) in dorsal and ventral trunk fin folds (Fig. 4F). Actinotrichia fibers are normally <lb/>attached to the basal membrane and display prominent stratification (van den Boogaart et <lb/>al., 2012). fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutant embryos showed an almost complete loss of actinotrichia in <lb/>ventral fin folds, while in dorsal fin folds of the same individuals actinotrichia were only <lb/>slightly reduced but still present (lower row Fig. 4F). Small remains of actinotrichia, showing <lb/>characteristic stratification, were present in ventral fin folds (arrows Fig. 4F). But also <lb/>misplaced collagen fibers not attached to the basal membrane could be detected (circles Fig. <lb/>4F). The ventral median fin fold of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants displayed the presence of <lb/>mesenchymal cells, the outer and basal epidermal cell layer (Fig. 4F). But the sub-cellular <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-12-<lb/></page>

			<body>structure of the basal epidermal layer was altered. It exhibited cavities between the outer and <lb/>basal epidermal layers (marked by arrow heads) and displayed changes in the ECM <lb/>surrounding these cells. This observation strongly implies that the disruption of actinotrichia <lb/>fibers and the observed effects on TP63 positive cells after Fndc3a reduction are due to <lb/>cellular defects in the basal epidermal cell layer. <lb/>Contemporaneous to the caudal median fin fold, pectoral fins are formed during embryonic <lb/>development and share common structural components and genetic factors with caudal fins <lb/>(Iovine, 2007). RNA in-situ hybridization and immunofluorescence indicated fndc3a <lb/>expression and localization during the first days of embryonic development in epidermal cells <lb/>of pectoral fins (Fig. 1; Fig. S8A). A potential effect of fndc3a reduction on pectoral fin <lb/>development was investigated by phenotypic observation (Fig. S8B) and Col2a as well as <lb/>TP63 immunofluorescence staining (Fig. S8C). These experiments indicated no alterations in <lb/>pectoral fin development in fndc3a wue1/wue1 during embryogenesis. Likewise adult <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants and transient double fndc3a CRISPR injected fish did not show <lb/>changed pectoral fin morphology (data not shown) and indicated no or only a minor role of <lb/>Fndc3a in pectoral fin development. <lb/>&gt;Fig. S8 <lb/>Fin regeneration is only temporally influenced in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>Besides their function during fin development, actinotrichia and epidermal cells possess <lb/>essential roles during the regeneration of adult caudal fins after amputation (Duran et al., <lb/>2011; Santamaria and Becerra, 1991). Similar to their role in fin development Col2a and <lb/>Col1a were identified to be necessary factors of actinotrichia formation during this process <lb/>(Duran et al., 2015), implying comparable cellular processes during fin development and <lb/>regeneration. We therefore hypothesized that reduction of Fndc3a function might also <lb/>interfere with actinotrichia formation and basal epidermal cells during fin regeneration. <lb/>&gt;Fig. S9 <lb/>&gt;Fig. S10 <lb/>To test this hypothesis, we performed regeneration experiments on adult caudal fins with <lb/>control and fndc3a wue1/wue1 fish (Fig. 5 and Fig. S9). Two remarkable observations were made: <lb/>First, regenerates looked opaque, disorganized and tubercular extensions attached to the <lb/>epidermal layer of the fin regenerates were eminent between 4dpa and 6dpa (days post <lb/>amputation) in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (arrowheads in Fig. 5A; Fig. S9B and D; abnormal <lb/>regenerate phenotypes 6dpa: control: 3/19; fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 13/19). Subsequent histological <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-13-<lb/></page>

			<body>investigation via H&amp;E staining on sections of these regenerates confirmed detached or <lb/>loosely attached cells in the outer epidermal layer of the fndc3a wue1/wue1 regenerates. These <lb/>cells were additionally investigated by immunofluorescence and depicted high levels of Col2a <lb/>at the regenerative front (arrows in Fig. 5B). TEM analysis further clarified that these cells <lb/>were still attached to the epidermal cell layer and incorporate electronic dense material in <lb/>their Golgi apparatus and in intracellular vesicles (Fig. 5E). In accordance with this <lb/>observation, fndc3a expression in fin regenerates could be detected in the distal wound <lb/>blastema at 4dpa and 6dpa (Fig. S9C). Localization of Fndc3a protein in regenerates was <lb/>confirmed by immunofluorescence in the epidermal cell layers of regenerates (Fig. 5C). <lb/>Second, actinotrichia fibers at the tip of 4dpa regenerates looked disorganized and clumped <lb/>in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (arrows in Fig. 5A). In 4dpa regenerates of control individuals TEM <lb/>analysis of formed actinotrichia fibers showed bundles of stratified actin fibers in close <lb/>proximity to the basal membrane cells (Fig.5F). In contrast, fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants lack these <lb/>prominent compact actinotrichia fibers and only depicted loose filaments adjacent to the <lb/>membrane layer. Subsequent investigation of epidermal cells by TP63 staining in <lb/>regenerates 4dpa showed interference with normal regenerate structure and disturbance of <lb/>epidermal cells in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutant regenerates (Fig. 5D). This indicates altered <lb/>epidermal organization as a potential reason for the observed effects in regenerates after <lb/>reduced Fndc3a function, similar to the processes observed in the median fin fold during <lb/>early development. <lb/>&gt;Fig.5 <lb/>Similar to the temperature dependency of the hypomorphic fndc3a wue1/wue1 phenotype during <lb/>fin development, the observed effects during fin regeneration could be enhanced by keeping <lb/>fish at a raised temperature of 32°C during the phase of regeneration (incubation at 24°C in <lb/>Fig. S9A and B; incubation at 32°C in Fig 5A and Fig. S9D). Although prominent cellular <lb/>abnormalities were detected during the first days past amputation (dpa), the investigated <lb/>control and mutant fish showed no significant differences in overall tail length growth in the <lb/>first 10dpa and only at 6dpa a difference in regenerate length was detected (Fig. S10). All <lb/>fins grew normally to their former size after ~14dpa (data not shown), but small changes in <lb/>fin morphology, e.g. cooped fin rays and loss of intersegmental tissues, could be observed in <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants 6 weeks past amputation (wpa; control: 1/10; fndc3a wue1/wue1 : 8/10; <lb/>Fig. S9E). Our regeneration experiments hint to rather minor and temporal effects of Fndc3a <lb/>on regeneration during initiation and the first few days of regeneration and point to a potential <lb/>compensatory mechanism or residual function of Fndc3a in the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-14-<lb/></page>

			<body>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants display disorganized cellular arrangement in median fin folds <lb/>and in caudal fin regenerates. <lb/>Correct assembly of actinotrichia and correct caudal fin morphology are greatly dependent <lb/>on the extracellular composition and the cell shape of surrounding epidermal cells during <lb/>development and regeneration. These cellular characteristics within the median fin fold <lb/>determine correct signaling, e.g. by Wnt signals, and cell behavior (Wehner et al., 2014; <lb/>Wehner and Weidinger, 2015). Fibronectin domain containing proteins like Fndc3a have <lb/>been linked to functions during ECM assembly and maintenance (Henderson et al., 2011). <lb/>Thus, we assume that Fndc3a function during median fin fold development and caudal fin <lb/>regeneration is provoked by cell shape or by ECM alterations in epidermal cells. <lb/>To follow-up on this assumption we analyzed cell membrane structure and the ECM in the <lb/>median fin fold of control and fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants by investigating F-actin (Phalloidin <lb/>staining) or β-catenin localization (Fig 6). Cell boundaries of control embryos displayed a <lb/>dense, stereotypical assembly of epidermal cells in the ventral median fin fold at 22hpf (Fig. <lb/>6A). Reduction of Fndc3a resulted in clustering of cells, altered cell shapes of ventral median <lb/>fin fold epidermal cells (white arrows Fig. 6A) and appearance of cavities within the fin folds <lb/>(white arrowheads and white dashed lines Fig. 6A). The cavities are zones within the tissue <lb/>showing no F-actin and no nuclear staining, suggesting cell free spaces within the median fin <lb/>fold. Further cellular observations were made by investigation of β-catenin localization at <lb/>similar developmental stages (Fig. 6B). Homogeneous membranous localization was <lb/>detected in cells of the ventral median fin fold of control embryos 24hpf and nuclear <lb/>localization of β-catenin was detected in epithelial cells at the fin border (arrowheads in Fig. <lb/>6B)(Nagendran et al., 2015). In fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants uniform localization of β-catenin at the <lb/>cell membrane of epithelial cells was impaired and instead appeared as accumulations of the <lb/>protein in a speckled fashion within the cytoplasm (white arrows in Fig. 6B). Nuclear <lb/>localization of β-catenin was not completely abolished in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants and was <lb/>clearly detected in epithelial cells at the apical fin border, indicating maintenance of a Wnt <lb/>gradient in these mutants (grey arrowheads in Fig. 6B). These experiments suggest a partial <lb/>loss of epidermal cellular structure and loss of adhesion within the median fin fold of <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants during embryonic development. <lb/>Besides the effects on median fin fold development we additionally investigated potential <lb/>ECM changes in regenerates of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants by F-actin (Fig. 6C and 6D) and β-<lb/>catenin staining (Fig. 6E and 6F). Comparison between controls and fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants <lb/>clarified that similar distinctive features, i.e. altered cell matrix and appearance of cavities <lb/>within the tissue, were also observed in regenerates between 2 and 8dpa. F-actin depicted <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-15-<lb/></page>

			<body>altered regenerate border shapes of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants (dashed white line Fig. 6C) and <lb/>appearance of regions showing cellular alterations (white arrows Fig. 6C). These obviously <lb/>fragmented structures within the blastema appeared 2dpa and could be detected until 6dpa. <lb/>High resolution microscopy clarified, that fragmented structures in 2dpa regenerates are <lb/>cavities within the blastema (white arrowheads Fig. 6D). Cellular alterations were also <lb/>detected in cells at the regenerative front of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants at 4 to 8dpa by β-catenin <lb/>immunostaining (Fig. 6E). Irregular blastema borders 4dpa were detected distinctly with the <lb/>same staining (white arrows and close-up pictures in Fig. 6E). High resolution imaging also <lb/>revealed β-catenin negative, detached cells outside of the regenerate (white arrowheads in <lb/>Fig. 6F) and cavities (white arrows in Fig. 6F). Later stages of caudal regeneration did not <lb/>seem to be compromised by reduced Fndc3a level, as fin regenerates of fndc3a wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutants were able to grow to similar fin lengths as control fish at 10dpa (Fig. S10). Our <lb/>observations thereby indicate a partial loss of cellular structure and loss of adhesion within <lb/>the blastema during early stages of caudal fin regeneration in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>&gt;Fig. 6 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-16-<lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>Our functional investigations in zebrafish were initiated to proof clinical relevance and the <lb/>pathomechanism of a novel candidate gene (FNDC3A) detected by whole-exome-<lb/>sequencing in a family diagnosed with split-hand/split-food malformation (SHFM; data not <lb/>shown). SHFM has been associated with mutations in well described transcription factors, <lb/>e.g. DLX5/6 (OMIM *600028; SHFM1; Crackower et al., 1996) or TP63 (OMIM *603273; <lb/>SHFM4; Ianakiev et al., 2000). Mouse studies clarified the functional role of TP63 and DLX5 <lb/>during extremity development in mammals and linked both factors within a common <lb/>regulatory pathway (Lo Iacono et al., 2008; Restelli et al., 2014). Further investigations show <lb/>that functional and regulatory analyses of human SHFM candidate genes are feasible in <lb/>zebrafish and result in detailed insights into molecular function of these genetic factors during <lb/>vertebrate development (Birnbaum et al., 2012; Heude et al., 2014; Klopocki et al., 2012; <lb/>Kouwenhoven et al., 2010). <lb/>fndc3a expression in developing zebrafish was first detected 14hpf in the tail bud and later in <lb/>apical cells of the ventral median fin fold, the pectoral fins, the notochord and in cells of the <lb/>chordo neural hinge. Fndc3a protein localization during these early stages of median fin fold <lb/>development was detected mostly in the cell membrane of ectoderm derived cells and in <lb/>notochord cells. Spatiotemporally similar expression patterns in the zebrafish median fin fold <lb/>have been described for other genes causative for SHFM, e.g. dlx5a and tp63 (Bakkers et <lb/>al., 2002; Heude et al., 2014; Lee and Kimelman, 2002). Comparison of zebrafish fndc3a <lb/>expression during extremity development to mouse Fndc3a expression shows a partially <lb/>similar pattern, i.e. early in the AER of the limb bud and later in interdigital regions of feet <lb/>(unpublished data; Gene expression database; <lb/>http://www.informatics.jax.org/expression.shtml). Mouse Fndc3a loss-of-function knockouts <lb/>result in male infertility, while defects in limb development were however not described <lb/>(Obholz et al., 2006). <lb/>The CRISPR/Cas9 generated fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutation in zebrafish, presented in our study, <lb/>resulted in a premature Stop codon and predicted loss of six fibronectin domains in the <lb/>corresponding protein. The mutation did not lead to complete nonsense mediated decay and <lb/>a full loss-of-function phenotype, as residual fndc3a mRNA expression could be detected <lb/>and the observed phenotypes are rather weak and partly transient. Morpholino knockdown <lb/>and RNA overexpression experiments in wild type and in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants, <lb/>respectively, displayed on the one hand a consistent phenotype of the mutant and further a <lb/>partial rescue of the induced mutation. On the other hand the experiments resulted also in an <lb/>increased severity after Morpholino and RNA injection into fndc3a wue1/wue1 , implying that the <lb/>induced mutation does not abolish the function of the gene completely, but rather leads to a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-17-<lb/></page>

			<body>reduced function and results in a hypomorphic mutation. Our results cannot exclude a <lb/>compensation mechanism for fin development and regeneration in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants, <lb/>which after reduction of Fndc3a function would be able to recover cellular functions and <lb/>ultimately lead to a rather normally developed caudal fin during larval development and in <lb/>adult fish. Compensation could either be facilitated by residing functional Fndc3a proteins, as <lb/>indicated by remaining transcripts in mutants, by other fibronectin homologues, or by <lb/>activation of known signaling networks during fin development and regeneration (Wehner <lb/>and Weidinger, 2015). The severe tail phenotype of transient double CRISPR injected <lb/>individuals suggests a stronger phenotype after complete loss of Fndc3a and points towards <lb/>interference with prominent signaling pathways, e.g. BMP and TGF-Beta signaling. Potential <lb/>compensating factors might also be determined by looking at other orthologues of the fndc3 <lb/>gene family, e.g. fndc3ba and fndc3bb, but expression as well as function of these genes <lb/>have not been investigated yet. <lb/>Initial mutant examination revealed a specific phenotype in the developing caudal fin of <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants, by showing loss of ventral median fin fold cells, loss of gene <lb/>expression domains in the ventral fin fold, loss of actinotrichia fibers and Col2a accumulation. <lb/>Most prominently a number of early markers in the ventral median fin fold 20 to 24hpf were <lb/>reduced or altered in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants, indicating cellular Fndc3a function in this <lb/>specific region and phase of development, which correspond to regions with fndc3a <lb/>expression. In contrast to more globally expressed genes linked to early caudal fin <lb/>development and to actinotrichia deposition in zebrafish, e.g. pinfin mutants lacking Fras1 <lb/>function or nagel mutants lacking Hmcn1 function (Carney et al., 2010), the hypomorphic <lb/>phenotype in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants is milder and locally restricted. One cellular <lb/>consequence of Fndc3a reduction was suspected to be involved with the assembly process <lb/>of actinotrichia and collagen fibers during development, as indicated by altered Col2a <lb/>location in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants and by EM imaging. Collagen helix assembly is performed <lb/>at the ER and is controlled by chaperones, especially Hsp47/SerpinH1 (Ricard-Blum, 2011). <lb/>Interestingly, knockdown of hsp47/serpinH1 results in a phenotype resembling <lb/>fndc3a wue1/wue1 , i.e. actinotrichia organization failure and regenerating fin deformations <lb/>(Bhadra and Iovine, 2015). In comparison to published loss-of-function mutations in zebrafish <lb/>collagen genes (e.g. col1a1: chi, Chihuahua; col9a1: prp, persistent plexus) which result in <lb/>characteristic severe bone growth defects, skeletal dysplasia and vascular plexus formation <lb/>(Fisher et al., 2003; Huang et al., 2009) the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutation has only a mild effect on <lb/>late caudal fin development by interference with collagen assembly. Additional interference <lb/>with expression domains of mesenchymal markers, e.g. myoD, hints to the notion that <lb/>Fncd3a is required for the establishment of ventral cells fates of the developing median fin <lb/>fold, by setting up the correct cellular structure in this region. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-18-<lb/></page>

			<body>The process of median fin fold development is tightly regulated by modulation of epidermal <lb/>cell shape and correct ECM assembly (Dane and Tucker, 1985; Nagendran et al., 2015). <lb/>TP63 positive epidermal cells are still present in the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants during median fin <lb/>fold development 20 to 48hpf, but show reduced epidermal cell numbers at ventral positions, <lb/>delayed ventral fin fold growth and altered morphological properties. Fndc3a shares <lb/>fibronectin domain III protein domains with other well studied factors like Fibronectin 1, which <lb/>are known to interact with prominent ECM proteins (Akiyama, 1996) and are essential for <lb/>matrix assembly (Singh et al., 2010). The observed breakup of correct epidermal cell <lb/>assembly and appearance of cavities in the ECM of basal epidermal cells after reduction of <lb/>Fndc3a function indicate that Fndc3a might play a similar role in correct ECM assembly and <lb/>establishment of correct cellular structures in the median fin fold. Potential downstream <lb/>effects like misplaced mesodermal cells, loss of actinotrichia fibers and detached epidermal <lb/>cells are most likely explained by deranged ECM structure in the early epidermal cell layer <lb/>after Fndc3a reduction. Irregular caudal fin structures, for example, might be a consequence <lb/>of early developmental irregularities as mesenchymal cells migrate after their induction along <lb/>predetermined ECM structures and actinotrichia fibers to form the fin skeleton (Feitosa et al., <lb/>2012). Future experiments will have to clarify if binding of Fndc3a to integrins is abandoned <lb/>in fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants, thereby directly influencing cell adhesion, basal epithelium <lb/>establishment, and signaling (Towers and Tickle, 2009; Wada, 2011). This idea is supported <lb/>by the phenotypic similarity of fndc3a wue1/wue1 to lmna5 and itga3 mutants (Carney et al., 2010; <lb/>Nagendran et al., 2015; Webb et al., 2007) and the occurrence of aberrant cells in the <lb/>epidermal layer of regenerates in the fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants. Moreover our experiments do <lb/>not rule out a potential function of Fndc3a during intracellular processes in the Golgi <lb/>apparatus. Protein localization by Carrouel et al. (2008) clearly detected FNDC3A in the <lb/>Golgi apparatus of human odontoblast. Reduction of Fndc3a function therefore may also <lb/>result in hampered protein processing within this organelle and thereby interfere with <lb/>modification of ECM proteins or membranous export. <lb/>Besides median fin fold development we investigated a potential function of Fndc3a during <lb/>caudal fin regeneration. In accordance with median fin fold development, regeneration and <lb/>blastema formation depends on correct epidermal cell assembly and a distinct ECM structure <lb/>(Govindan and Iovine, 2015; Govindan et al., 2016). We initially detected fndc3a transcripts <lb/>and Fndc3a protein in the distal blastema and in epidermal cell layers of regenerates 2 to <lb/>8dpa. In fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants we observed several temporal effects on caudal fin <lb/>regeneration: detached epidermal cells, Col2a accumulation, disorganized epidermal cells <lb/>layers and lacking actinotrichia. These are comparable to the observed developmental <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-19-<lb/></page>

			<body>phenotype within the median fin fold and indicate ECM malformation to be causative for this <lb/>effect on adult structures as well. <lb/>&gt;Fig. 7 <lb/>In summary, investigation of fndc3a expression and function in zebrafish reveals a transient <lb/>and spatially restricted role of this genetic factor during extremity development and during fin <lb/>regeneration. The observed effects after reduction of Fndc3a function on actinotrichia fibers <lb/>and correct fin morphology are probably secondary and provoked by cellular changes. Most <lb/>likely disruption of correct ECM structure in basal epidermal cells is the consequential <lb/>underlying cellular mechanism responsible for the observed fin malformations. Our results <lb/>demonstrate a cellular link between median fin fold development and caudal fin regeneration <lb/>due to the necessity for correct cell shape and tissue cohesion in both processes via Fndc3a. <lb/>Beyond this, our zebrafish experiments now suggest that Fndc3a can influence TP63 <lb/>positive epidermal cells by altering cell shape or cell adhesion during extremity development. <lb/>Thus, Fndc3a can be functionally linked to known SHFM genes supporting a potential <lb/>pathogenic relevance in SHFM phenotypes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-20-<lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>Animal maintenance <lb/>Laboratory zebrafish embryos (Danio rerio) of the AB/TU and AB/AB strain (ZDB-GENO-<lb/>010924-10; ZDB-GENO-960809-7) were maintained as described by Westerfield <lb/>(Westerfield, 2000) under standard aquatic conditions at an average of 24°C water <lb/>temperature. Embryos were staged by morphological characteristics according to Kimmel et <lb/>al. (Kimmel et al., 1995). hpf indicate hours-post fertilization at 28.5°C. All procedures <lb/>involving experimental animals were performed in compliance with German animal welfare <lb/>laws, guidelines, and policies. Generation of fndc3a wue1/wue1 mutants and fin clipping was <lb/>approved by the Committee on the Ethics of Animal Experiments of the University of <lb/>Würzburg and the &quot;Regierung von Unterfranken&quot; (Permit Number: DMS-2532-2-13 and <lb/>DMS-2532-2-9). The generated fndc3a wue1/wue1 line was submitted to ZFIN.org (ZFIN ID: ZDB-<lb/>ALT-170417-3). <lb/>CRISPR/Cas9 system and construction of short guiding RNA (sgRNA) constructs <lb/>For oligo cloning of sgRNA target sequences the previously published pDR274 vector was <lb/>used (Hwang et al., 2013) (Addgene Plasmid #42250; sequences of primers used in this <lb/>study are given in Table S1). For cas9 RNA synthesis the MLM3613 (Hwang et al., 2013) <lb/>(Addgene Plasmid #42251) or the pCS2-nCas9n vector (Jao et al., 2013) (Addgene Plasmid <lb/>#47929) were utilized. Both vectors were purchased from Addgene (www.addgene.org; <lb/>Cambridge, USA). For designing and constructing of sgRNAs the open access ZiFit Targeter <lb/>software (http://zifit.partners.org/ZiFiT/) was used. Specific target sites were identified by <lb/>alignments of zebrafish and human sequences. sgRNA target site <lb/>(GGATTCCAGGCCAGTTATGA) is located in exon 13 of fndc3a (ENSEMBL Zv9 Transcript: <lb/>ENSDART00000097261) and targets the second Fibronectin type III domain, while sgRNA <lb/>target site in exon 18 (GGCGTACAGTGGTTCGGCTC) targets the third Fibronectin type III <lb/>domain. <lb/>sgRNA transcription and microinjection <lb/>sgRNAs were transcribed via the MAXIscript T7 kit (Ambion/ life technologies, Darmstadt, <lb/>Germany) and were purified via phenol/chloroform extraction. Cas9 RNA was transcribed via <lb/>the mMESSAGE mMACHINE kit (Ambion/ Life Technologies, Darmstadt, Germany) and <lb/>subsequently cleaned via RNeasy purification kit (Qiagen, Venlo, Netherlands). If the <lb/>MLM3613 vector was used for Cas9 Synthesis, polyA tail synthesis was performed with <lb/>E.coli Poly(A) Polymerase (New England Biolabs, Ipswich, MA, USA) prior to purification. <lb/>One cell stage zebrafish embryos were injected with solutions comprising sgRNA (25-50ng/µl <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-21-<lb/></page>

			<body>each), cas9 RNA (75-100ng/µl), Phenol red (pH7.0; 0.05% final concentration; for <lb/>visualization of injection solution) and Fluorescein isothiocyanate-dextran (Sigma-Aldrich; <lb/>1mg/µl). Positively injected embryos were identified 24hpf by transient green fluorescence of <lb/>Fluorescein isothiocyanate-dextran and were raised for line establishment. <lb/>Whole mount RNA in-situ hybridization <lb/>RNA in situ hybridization was performed according to standard protocols (Hauptmann and <lb/>Gerster, 1994; Thisse and Thisse, 2008). RNA probes were synthesized from cloned partial <lb/>mRNA sequences of target genes using the DIG or FLU RNA Labeling Kit (Roche, Basel, <lb/>Switzerland). We used a fndc3a cDNA fragment of 595bp size (used primers: <lb/>zf_fndc3a_ribo_fwd2 and zf_fndc3a_ribo_rev2) to synthesize a specific anti-sense RNA <lb/>probe. Sense probes were synthesized as negative control for each anti-sense probe and <lb/>were used under the same reaction conditions. Primers used for probe cloning are listed in <lb/>Table S1. <lb/>Immunofluorescence and histology <lb/>Immunofluorescence was performed on embryos, cryosections or on whole regenerating fins <lb/>by standard protocols (Duran et al., 2011; Inoue and Wittbrodt, 2011). Apoptosis assays <lb/>were performed according to Sorrells et al. (2013) (Sorrells et al., 2013) by visualization of <lb/>cleaved caspase 3 via immunofluorescence. Primary antibodies used: Fndc3a (HPA008927; <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich; dilution 1:50-100; Antibody Registry: AB_1078899), Col2a (II-II6B3 was <lb/>deposited to the DSHB by Linsenmayer, T.F. (DSHB Hybridoma Product II-II6B3); dilution <lb/>1:500; Antibody Registry: AB_528165), cleaved Caspase-3 (C92-605; Thermo Fisher <lb/>Scientific; dilution 1:500; Antibody Registry: AB_397274), β-catenin (610153; BD <lb/>Biosciences; dilution 1:250; Antibody Registry: AB_397554), TP63 (ab735; Abcam; dilution <lb/>1:200; Antibody Registry: AB_305870). Except Fndc3a, all used antibodies have been used <lb/>previously for experiments in zebrafish and validated protocols have been previously <lb/>published. Specificity of the used Fndc3a antibody was validated by the Human Protein Atlas <lb/>project for usage in human tissues (https://www.proteinatlas.org/ENSG00000102531-<lb/>FNDC3A/antibody). Validation for usage in zebrafish was performed by epitope sequence <lb/>analysis, antibody dilution series, and incorporation of adequate negative controls in all <lb/>experiments. Cell nuclei were counterstained with Hoechst 33258 (Sigma-Aldrich; dilution <lb/>1:5000). F-Actin was stained with Actin-stain 488 phalloidin (Cytoskeleton, Inc.; PHDG1-A; <lb/>dilution 1:20). <lb/>Whole mount alcian blue staining was performed according to Walker and Kimmel (Walker <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-22-<lb/></page>

			<body>and Kimmel, 2007). H&amp;E staining on 10µm paraffin sections was performed according to a <lb/>general histology protocol using Mayer´s Hematoxylin and Eosin. <lb/>Fin regeneration experiments <lb/>For fin amputation experiments adult zebrafish (mixed sex, age 3-5 months, 3 independent <lb/>experiments) were anesthetized with tricaine (MS-222; 3-amino benzoic acid ethyl ester; final <lb/>concentration ~150mg/l) prior to amputation of ~20% length the of caudal fin. Images were <lb/>taken 0, 2, 6, 8 and 10 days post-amputation (dpa) under a stereomicroscope. To increase <lb/>the expected phenotype fish were kept at an increased temperature (32°C) during the <lb/>experiments. Regenerate samples for immunofluorescence, in-situ hybridization, genotyping, <lb/>or histology were taken by a second amputation anterior to the first lesion site (2, 4, 6 and <lb/>8dpa). <lb/>Image acquisition and quantification <lb/>Images were acquired depending on the experiment either with a Leica S8 APO <lb/>Stereomicroscope (whole embryos), a Zeiss Imager A1 (in-situ hybridizations) or a Nikon <lb/>A1+ Laser scanning confocal microscope (Immunofluorescence). Image acquisition was <lb/>performed via device specific cameras/detector and corresponding software (Leica <lb/>Application suite; Zeiss AxioVision; Nikon NIS-Elements). Further image analyses and <lb/>quantifications were performed with ImageJ/Fiji (https://fiji.sc/). For figure arrangement <lb/>CorelDraw Graphics Suite x7 software (Corel Corporation) was used. <lb/>Quantification of median fin fold width was performed with ImageJ/Fiji by length <lb/>measurement of maximum intensity projections of TP63/Hoechst stained embryos 24 and <lb/>48hpf. Each embryo was measured at three independent positions at the dorsal or ventral <lb/>median fin fold. Median fin fold width was measured between the apical fin and somite <lb/>borders. Quantification of epidermal cells in 24hpf embryos was performed by automated <lb/>counting of TP63 positive cells in confocal stacks (size z: 40; z-step: 2µm) on the complete <lb/>ventral and dorsal median fin folds. While in 48hpf embryos three independent positions of <lb/>the same size (ventral and dorsal median fin fold, tail tip; 8800 µm 2 ) were investigated per <lb/>sample. Used ImageJ plugins and commands: Stack/Z Project, Despeckle, Watersheed, <lb/>Analyze particles (size 2-10µm, circularity 0.5-1.0). A minimum of 12 samples for each <lb/>condition was investigated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-23-<lb/></page>

			<body>Electron microscopy <lb/>Embryos or regenerates were washed with PBS and fixed (2.5% glutaraldehyde, 50 mM <lb/>cacodylat pH 7.2, mM KCl, and 2.5 mM MgCl 2 ) overnight at 4°C. Subsequently, embryos <lb/>or tissues were washed five times with 50 mM cacodyl buffer (pH 7.2) and fixed for 4 h with <lb/>2% OsO in 50 mM cacodylat (pH 7.2) buffer. Embryos or tissues were subsequently stained <lb/>with 2% uranylacetate overnight. After gradual dehydration with ethanol, they were <lb/>transferred to propylenoxid and embedded in Epon (SERVA Electrophoresis GmbH, <lb/>Heidelberg, Germany). Ultrathin sections were analyzed using an EM10 from Zeiss <lb/>(Oberkochen, Germany). <lb/>qPCR experiments <lb/>For qPCR experiments RNA was extracted from pools of 12 embryos each (age 24hpf; F3 <lb/>fndc3a wue1/+ and fndc3a wue1/wue1 generation; control: AB). For each genotype three <lb/>independent pools were generated and compared. For cDNA synthesis 1µg RNA was <lb/>transcribed into cDNA and further analyzed in a ViiA7 Real-Time PCR System (Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientific). Each group and primer sample was analyzed in triplicates on a single <lb/>qPCR plate utilizing HOT FIREPol Eva Green Mix Plus (Solis Biodyne). Data analysis of was <lb/>performed via QuantStudio Real-Time PCS Software v1.1 by ΔΔCt method. AB control <lb/>samples were used as reference sample for relative comparison. Amplification of gapdh and <lb/>eef1a1l1 was used as endogenous/housekeeping controls. Used primer pairs, amplicon <lb/>sizes and targeted regions are noted in table S1. Experiments were performed according to <lb/>MIQE guidelines. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-24-<lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors thank Anja Kirschbauer for professional fish keeping support, Tabea Röder for <lb/>in-situ probe synthesis, Prof. Dr. Manfred Schartl for sharing aquatic equipment, as well as <lb/>Claudia Gehrig and Daniela Bunsen from the Electron Microscopy Unit of the Biozentrum at <lb/>the University of Würzburg, for preparation of ultrathin sections and support with the electron <lb/>microscopy analysis. We are indebted to Prof. Dr. Christoph Winkler for fruitful discussions. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>D.L., S.G. and E.K. designed the experiments. D.L., I.K., S.K., M.M. and M.O. conducted the <lb/>experiments. D.L. and E.K. wrote the manuscript with input from all authors. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-25-<lb/></page>

			<body>Figures and Tables <lb/>Fig. 1: Localization of fndc3a RNA and protein during embryonic zebrafish development. <lb/>(A and B) Expression of fndc3a is detected in the tail bud and the median fin fold from 14hpf onwards. During <lb/>subsequent stages of zebrafish development fndc3a is expressed in pectoral fins, somites and notochord cells. <lb/>Neuronal tissues express fndc3a starting from 16hpf in the midbrain-hindbrain boundary (marked by the chevron), <lb/>the mesencephalon, and the rhombencephalon. (B) Investigation of long-time stained embryos and transversal <lb/>sections indicated varying fndc3a expression in the tail bud region, at the lateral edge of the neural keel, at the <lb/>ventral median fin fold, at Kupffer´s vesicle, and in chordo neural hinge cells. (C) Detection of Fndc3a protein via <lb/>immunofluorescence indicated similar regional localization as fndc3a mRNA in 22-24hpf embryos. Furthermore it <lb/>showed intracellular accumulation of Fndc3a at notochord cells, at somite boundaries and epidermal cells at this <lb/>stage. (D) Cellular localization of Fndc3a during median fin fold development at 48hpf corresponds to regions of <lb/>mRNA expression and could be observed intracellular and at cell boundaries of epidermal cells. <lb/>Dashed lines in B indicate planes of the corresponding numbered sections 1-5. Dashed lines in C indicate <lb/>notochord boundary. Dashed lines in D indicate fin fold border. <lb/>cnh: chordo neural hinge; kv: Kupffer´s vesicle; le: lateral edge; mc: mesencephalon; mff: median fin fold; mhb: <lb/>midbrain hindbrain boundary (marked with chevron); nk: neural keel; no: notochord; nt: neural tube; pf: pectoral <lb/>fin; sb: somite boundary; so: somites; tb: tail bud; rc: rhombencephalon. <lb/>Scale bars: 100µm, except higher magnification in C: 20µm. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-26-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2: Generation and phenotype of fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 zebrafish mutants. <lb/>(A) The CRISPR/Cas9 system was used to target exon 13 in the zebrafish fndc3a gene coding for the third <lb/>fibronectin type III domain (nucleotides marked in blue indicate sgRNA target sequence; nucleotides marked in <lb/>red indicate the region of mutated sequence). (B-D) fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants show straightened tail buds <lb/>(n=19/40), kinked tails (n= 27/100), and actinotrichia fiber aggregation during the first days of embryonic <lb/>development (n= 9/41; indicated by arrows). (E) A fraction of adult fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants display weak (n= <lb/>15/71) to strong (n= 6/71) caudal fin phenotypes and tail malformations. (F) qPCR quantification of relative <lb/>fndc3a expression levels in genotypic different groups of embryos indicated reduction of fndc3a transcripts in <lb/>fndc3a <lb/>wue1/+ and fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 (ΔΔCt calculation; comparison of biological triplicates for each genotype with <lb/>twelve 24hpf embryos each; two independent fndc3a primer pairs; normalized against AB controls; gapdh and <lb/>ef1a1l1 expression were used as endogenous/housekeeping controls; significance levels and p-values of a 2-<lb/>sided paired student t-test are given). <lb/>Scale bars for embryo overview: 250µm; scale bars for tail magnifications: 100µm. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-27-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3: Normal development of the ventral median fin fold is altered in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>(A) Investigation of fras1, hmcn1, hmcn2, bmp1a, and fbln1 expression in the tail bud 20-22hpf indicates loss of <lb/>mesenchymal cells in the median fin fold in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants (arrows; fras1: 9/32; hmcn1: 11/26; hmcn2: <lb/>24/43; bmp1a: 22/45; fbln1: 16/32). (B) Expression of mesenchymal markers in posterior fins of 48hpf old <lb/>embryos is slightly changed following loss of fndc3a (fras1: 10/24; hmcn2: 12/25; bmp1a: 8/21; fbln1: 9/24). (C) <lb/>Ventral fin folds in 48hpf old embryos do not show loss of mesenchymal markers after fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutation. <lb/>(D) Expression of and1 in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 in the ventral fin fold is partly lost in 22hpf embryos (12/25), but recovers <lb/>in 48hpf old embryos to a reduced expression level (control n=16; weaker expression in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 embryos <lb/>n=10/18). <lb/>Dashed lines in A and D indicate planes of shown sections. Dashed lines in B and C indicate fin boundaries. <lb/>Scale bars: 50µm <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-28-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 4: The fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutation results in structural defects in epidermal cells during fin development. <lb/>Visualization of actinotrichia either by differential interference contrast microscopy (A) or by immunofluorescence <lb/>staining of Col2a (B) showed loss of mature actinotrichia in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants 48 to 52 hpf (number of <lb/>affected embryos: control = 0/17; fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 = 19/26; white arrows indicate lost actinotrichia and Col2a <lb/>accumulation in apical cells of the median fin fold). (C) Investigation of TP63 positive cells in in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutants showed reduced width and reduced epidermal cell number in the ventral median fin fold in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 <lb/>mutants. (D, E) Quantification of median fin fold width and TP63 positive cells in 24 and 48hpf embryos (Mann-<lb/>Whitney U test; p&lt;0.05; two-tailed, U values are indicated for significant changes). (F) Ultrastructural analyses of <lb/>dorsal and ventral fins of control (upper row) or fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants (lower row) reveal breakdown of <lb/>actinotrichia fibers and cellular malformations in cells of the basal epidermal layer in the ventral fin folds of 52hpf <lb/>old embryos (arrows indicate site of remaining actinotrichia, circles indicate misplaced fibers; dashed grey lines <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-29-<lb/></page>

			<body>indicate the basal membrane; yellow lines indicate outer epidermal cells and green lines indicate basal epidermal <lb/>cells; Black arrowheads indicate cavities). <lb/>a: actinotrichia; bel: basal epidermal layer; epi: epidermis; mff: median fin fold; m: mesenchymal cell; N: nucleus; <lb/>oel: outer epidermal layer. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-30-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 5: Interference with Fndc3a function during fin regeneration results in epidermal cells defects. <lb/>(A) Phenotypical and histological investigations of fin regeneration in fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants indicate abnormal <lb/>regeneration by showing unorganized fin borders at the regenerative front (arrows) and aberrant epidermal cells <lb/>(arrowheads; abnormal regenerate phenotypes 6dpa: control: 3/19; fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 : 13/19). (B) Col2a protein <lb/>localization visualized via immunofluorescence on 8dpa regenerates shows accumulation of collagen in these <lb/>abnormal cells of fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants (white arrows; n=6 for each group). (C) Localization of Fndc3a in <lb/>regenerates can be detected in epidermal cell layers (white arrowheads indicate amputation site). (D) TP63 <lb/>staining in regenerates of fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants 4dpa indicates disorganization of epidermal cells (white arrows; <lb/>white arrowheads indicate amputation site; n=4 for each group). (E) TEM analysis showed accumulation of <lb/>electron dense material in the Golgi apparatus of abnormal cells attached to the epidermal layer (arrow). (F) TEM <lb/>analyses of actinotrichia in fin regenerates 4dpa reveal loss of these fibers located near the basal membrane <lb/>(arrows) in fndc3a depleted fish. <lb/>a: actinotrichia; epi: epidermis; dashed lines indicate basal membrane. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-31-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 6: Correct ECM structure in the median fin fold and regenerating caudal fins is hampered in <lb/>fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants. <lb/>(A) F-actin in the median fin fold 22hpf was visualized by phalloidin staining, (B) localization of β-catenin during fin <lb/>development was visualized by immunofluorescence of 24hpf embryos (n=6 for each group). Both colorations <lb/>mark cell membranes and ECM structures. Cellular organization of ventral median fin fold cells and ECM matrix is <lb/>symmetrically structured in control embryos and shows nuclear localization of active Wnt signals in cells at the fin <lb/>fold tip (white arrowheads in B). fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants depict cellular alterations and unstructured ECM <lb/>assembly by showing irregular cell shapes (white arrows in A), cavities within the fin fold (white arrowheads in A2) <lb/>and speckled accumulation of β-catenin between cells (white arrows in B). Nuclear localization of β-catenin in <lb/>cells at the fin fold tip was maintained (grey arrowheads in B). (C and D; n=4 for each group) Fin regenerates of <lb/>fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants incubated at 32°C and stained for F-actin showed regenerate abnormalities (white arrows <lb/>in C), irregular regenerate borders (white dashed lines in C) and cellular cavities (white arrowheads in D) (E and <lb/>F; n=3 for each group) Fin regenerates of fndc3a <lb/>wue1/wue1 mutants also depicted intracellular accumulation of β-<lb/>catenin, divergent ECM assembly (white arrows) in addition to appearance of abnormal cells loosely attached to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-32-<lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">the regenerate (white arrowheads). <lb/>Images either show maximum intensity projections (30 to 40 single z-slices; z-distance: 1.5µm) or a <lb/>representative higher resolution single z slice. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-33-<lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 7: Model of Fndc3a function during zebrafish median fin fold development and caudal fin <lb/>regeneration. <lb/>Expression and localization of fndc3a can be detected during early phases of median fin fold development and in <lb/>caudal fin regenerates. Reduced Fndc3a function results in prominent changes of ECM structure of epidermal <lb/>cells. During development this results in impaired collagen assembly of actinotrichia fibers and loss of ventral <lb/>median fin fold cells. During regeneration altered ECM structure results in actinotrichia breakdown and detached <lb/>epidermal cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-34-<lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Akiyama, S. K. (1996). Integrins in cell adhesion and signaling. Hum Cell 9, 181-6. <lb/>Amaral, D. B. and Schneider, I. (2017). Fins into limbs: Recent insights from sarcopterygian <lb/>fish. Genesis. <lb/>Asharani, P. V., Keupp, K., Semler, O., Wang, W., Li, Y., Thiele, H., Yigit, G., Pohl, E., Becker, <lb/>J., Frommolt, P. et al. (2012). Attenuated BMP1 function compromises osteogenesis, leading to bone <lb/>fragility in humans and zebrafish. Am J Hum Genet 90, 661-74. <lb/>Bakkers, J., Hild, M., Kramer, C., Furutani-Seiki, M. and Hammerschmidt, M. (2002). <lb/>Zebrafish DeltaNp63 is a direct target of Bmp signaling and encodes a transcriptional repressor <lb/>blocking neural specification in the ventral ectoderm. Dev Cell 2, 617-27. <lb/>Bhadra, J. and Iovine, M. K. (2015). Hsp47 mediates Cx43-dependent skeletal growth and <lb/>patterning in the regenerating fin. Mech Dev 138 Pt 3, 364-74. <lb/>Birnbaum, R. Y., Everman, D. B., Murphy, K. K., Gurrieri, F., Schwartz, C. E. and Ahituv, N. <lb/>(2012). Functional characterization of tissue-specific enhancers in the DLX5/6 locus. Hum Mol Genet <lb/>21, 4930-8. <lb/>Carney, T. J., Feitosa, N. M., Sonntag, C., Slanchev, K., Kluger, J., Kiyozumi, D., Gebauer, J. <lb/>M., Coffin Talbot, J., Kimmel, C. B., Sekiguchi, K. et al. (2010). Genetic analysis of fin development in <lb/>zebrafish identifies furin and hemicentin1 as potential novel fraser syndrome disease genes. Plos <lb/>Genetics 6, e1000907. <lb/>Carrouel, F., Couble, M. L., Vanbelle, C., Staquet, M. J., Magloire, H. and Bleicher, F. (2008). <lb/>HUGO (FNDC3A): a new gene overexpressed in human odontoblasts. J Dent Res 87, 131-6. <lb/>Cheng, P., Andersen, P., Hassel, D., Kaynak, B. L., Limphong, P., Juergensen, L., Kwon, C. <lb/>and Srivastava, D. (2013). Fibronectin mediates mesendodermal cell fate decisions. Development <lb/>140, 2587-96. <lb/>Crackower, M. A., Scherer, S. W., Rommens, J. M., Hui, C. C., Poorkaj, P., Soder, S., Cobben, <lb/>J. M., Hudgins, L., Evans, J. P. and Tsui, L. C. (1996). Characterization of the split hand/split foot <lb/>malformation locus SHFM1 at 7q21.3-q22.1 and analysis of a candidate gene for its expression during <lb/>limb development. Hum Mol Genet 5, 571-9. <lb/>Dane, P. J. and Tucker, J. B. (1985). Modulation of epidermal cell shaping and extracellular <lb/>matrix during caudal fin morphogenesis in the zebra fish Brachydanio rerio. J Embryol Exp Morphol <lb/>87, 145-61. <lb/>Duijf, P. H., van Bokhoven, H. and Brunner, H. G. (2003). Pathogenesis of split-hand/split-<lb/>foot malformation. Hum Mol Genet 12 Spec No 1, R51-60. <lb/>Duran, I., Csukasi, F., Taylor, S. P., Krakow, D., Becerra, J., Bombarely, A. and Mari-Beffa, M. <lb/>(2015). Collagen duplicate genes of bone and cartilage participate during regeneration of zebrafish <lb/>fin skeleton. Gene Expr Patterns 19, 60-9. <lb/>Duran, I., Mari-Beffa, M., Santamaria, J. A., Becerra, J. and Santos-Ruiz, L. (2011). <lb/>Actinotrichia collagens and their role in fin formation. Dev Biol 354, 160-72. <lb/>Feitosa, N. M., Zhang, J., Carney, T. J., Metzger, M., Korzh, V., Bloch, W. and <lb/>Hammerschmidt, M. (2012). Hemicentin 2 and Fibulin 1 are required for epidermal-dermal junction <lb/>formation and fin mesenchymal cell migration during zebrafish development. Dev Biol 369, 235-48. <lb/>Fisher, S., Jagadeeswaran, P. and Halpern, M. E. (2003). Radiographic analysis of zebrafish <lb/>skeletal defects. Dev Biol 264, 64-76. <lb/>Gautier, P., Naranjo-Golborne, C., Taylor, M. S., Jackson, I. J. and Smyth, I. (2008). <lb/>Expression of the fras1/frem gene family during zebrafish development and fin morphogenesis. Dev <lb/>Dyn 237, 3295-304. <lb/>Govindan, J. and Iovine, M. K. (2015). Dynamic remodeling of the extra cellular matrix during <lb/>zebrafish fin regeneration. Gene Expr Patterns 19, 21-9. <lb/>Govindan, J., Tun, K. M. and Iovine, M. K. (2016). Cx43-Dependent Skeletal Phenotypes Are <lb/>Mediated by Interactions between the Hapln1a-ECM and Sema3d during Fin Regeneration. PLoS One <lb/>11, e0148202. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-35-<lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Grandel, H. and Schulte-Merker, S. (1998). The development of the paired fins in the <lb/>zebrafish (Danio rerio). Mech Dev 79, 99-120. <lb/>Gurrieri, F. and Everman, D. B. (2013). Clinical, genetic, and molecular aspects of split-<lb/>hand/foot malformation: an update. Am J Med Genet A 161A, 2860-72. <lb/>Hauptmann, G. and Gerster, T. (1994). Two-color whole-mount in situ hybridization to <lb/>vertebrate and Drosophila embryos. Trends Genet 10, 266. <lb/>Henderson, B., Nair, S., Pallas, J. and Williams, M. A. (2011). Fibronectin: a multidomain <lb/>host adhesin targeted by bacterial fibronectin-binding proteins. FEMS Microbiol Rev 35, 147-200. <lb/>Heude, E., Shaikho, S. and Ekker, M. (2014). The dlx5a/dlx6a genes play essential roles in the <lb/>early development of zebrafish median fin and pectoral structures. PLoS One 9, e98505. <lb/>Huang, C. C., Wang, T. C., Lin, B. H., Wang, Y. W., Johnson, S. L. and Yu, J. (2009). Collagen IX <lb/>is required for the integrity of collagen II fibrils and the regulation of vascular plexus formation in <lb/>zebrafish caudal fins. Dev Biol 332, 360-70. <lb/>Hwang, W. Y., Fu, Y., Reyon, D., Maeder, M. L., Tsai, S. Q., Sander, J. D., Peterson, R. T., <lb/>Yeh, J. R. and Joung, J. K. (2013). Efficient genome editing in zebrafish using a CRISPR-Cas system. <lb/>Nat Biotechnol 31, 227-9. <lb/>Ianakiev, P., Kilpatrick, M. W., Toudjarska, I., Basel, D., Beighton, P. and Tsipouras, P. <lb/>(2000). Split-hand/split-foot malformation is caused by mutations in the p63 gene on 3q27. Am J <lb/>Hum Genet 67, 59-66. <lb/>Inoue, D. and Wittbrodt, J. (2011). One for all--a highly efficient and versatile method for <lb/>fluorescent immunostaining in fish embryos. PLoS One 6, e19713. <lb/>Iovine, M. K. (2007). Conserved mechanisms regulate outgrowth in zebrafish fins. Nat Chem <lb/>Biol 3, 613-8. <lb/>Jao, L. E., Wente, S. R. and Chen, W. (2013). Efficient multiplex biallelic zebrafish genome <lb/>editing using a CRISPR nuclease system. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 110, 13904-9. <lb/>Jasuja, R., Voss, N., Ge, G., Hoffman, G. G., Lyman-Gingerich, J., Pelegri, F. and Greenspan, <lb/>D. S. (2006). bmp1 and mini fin are functionally redundant in regulating formation of the zebrafish <lb/>dorsoventral axis. Mech Dev 123, 548-58. <lb/>Kimmel, C. B., Ballard, W. W., Kimmel, S. R., Ullmann, B. and Schilling, T. F. (1995). Stages of <lb/>embryonic development of the zebrafish. Dev Dyn 203, 253-310. <lb/>Klopocki, E., Lohan, S., Doelken, S. C., Stricker, S., Ockeloen, C. W., Soares Thiele de Aguiar, <lb/>R., Lezirovitz, K., Mingroni Netto, R. C., Jamsheer, A., Shah, H. et al. (2012). Duplications of BHLHA9 <lb/>are associated with ectrodactyly and tibia hemimelia inherited in non-Mendelian fashion. J Med <lb/>Genet 49, 119-25. <lb/>Kouwenhoven, E. N., van Heeringen, S. J., Tena, J. J., Oti, M., Dutilh, B. E., Alonso, M. E., de <lb/>la Calle-Mustienes, E., Smeenk, L., Rinne, T., Parsaulian, L. et al. (2010). Genome-wide profiling of <lb/>p63 DNA-binding sites identifies an element that regulates gene expression during limb development <lb/>in the 7q21 SHFM1 locus. Plos Genetics 6, e1001065. <lb/>Lee, H. and Kimelman, D. (2002). A dominant-negative form of p63 is required for epidermal <lb/>proliferation in zebrafish. Dev Cell 2, 607-16. <lb/>Lo Iacono, N., Mantero, S., Chiarelli, A., Garcia, E., Mills, A. A., Morasso, M. I., Costanzo, A., <lb/>Levi, G., Guerrini, L. and Merlo, G. R. (2008). Regulation of Dlx5 and Dlx6 gene expression by p63 is <lb/>involved in EEC and SHFM congenital limb defects. Development 135, 1377-88. <lb/>Mari-Beffa, M., Carmona, M. C. and Becerra, J. (1989). Elastoidin turn-over during tail fin <lb/>regeneration in teleosts. A morphometric and radioautographic study. Anat Embryol (Berl) 180, 465-<lb/>70. <lb/>Masselink, W., Cole, N. J., Fenyes, F., Berger, S., Sonntag, C., Wood, A., Nguyen, P. D., <lb/>Cohen, N., Knopf, F., Weidinger, G. et al. (2016). A somitic contribution to the apical ectodermal <lb/>ridge is essential for fin formation. Nature 535, 542-6. <lb/>Montes, G. S., Becerra, J., Toledo, O. M., Gordilho, M. A. and Junqueira, L. C. (1982). Fine <lb/>structure and histochemistry of the tail fin ray in teleosts. Histochemistry 75, 363-76. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-36-<lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Nagendran, M., Arora, P., Gori, P., Mulay, A., Ray, S., Jacob, T. and Sonawane, M. (2015). <lb/>Canonical Wnt signalling regulates epithelial patterning by modulating levels of laminins in zebrafish <lb/>appendages. Development 142, 2080. <lb/>Obholz, K. L., Akopyan, A., Waymire, K. G. and MacGregor, G. R. (2006). FNDC3A is required <lb/>for adhesion between spermatids and Sertoli cells. Dev Biol 298, 498-513. <lb/>Parichy, D. M., Elizondo, M. R., Mills, M. G., Gordon, T. N. and Engeszer, R. E. (2009). <lb/>Normal table of postembryonic zebrafish development: staging by externally visible anatomy of the <lb/>living fish. Dev Dyn 238, 2975-3015. <lb/>Pfefferli, C. and Jazwinska, A. (2015). The art of fin regeneration in zebrafish. Regeneration <lb/>(Oxf) 2, 72-83. <lb/>Restelli, M., Lopardo, T., Lo Iacono, N., Garaffo, G., Conte, D., Rustighi, A., Napoli, M., Del <lb/>Sal, G., Perez-Morga, D., Costanzo, A. et al. (2014). DLX5, FGF8 and the Pin1 isomerase control <lb/>DeltaNp63alpha protein stability during limb development: a regulatory loop at the basis of the <lb/>SHFM and EEC congenital malformations. Hum Mol Genet 23, 3830-42. <lb/>Ricard-Blum, S. (2011). The collagen family. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Biol 3, a004978. <lb/>Santamaria, J. A. and Becerra, J. (1991). Tail fin regeneration in teleosts: cell-extracellular <lb/>matrix interaction in blastemal differentiation. J Anat 176, 9-21. <lb/>Singh, P., Carraher, C. and Schwarzbauer, J. E. (2010). Assembly of fibronectin extracellular <lb/>matrix. Annu Rev Cell Dev Biol 26, 397-419. <lb/>Sorrells, S., Toruno, C., Stewart, R. A. and Jette, C. (2013). Analysis of apoptosis in zebrafish <lb/>embryos by whole-mount immunofluorescence to detect activated Caspase 3. J Vis Exp, e51060. <lb/>Stemmer, M., Thumberger, T., Del Sol Keyer, M., Wittbrodt, J. and Mateo, J. L. (2015). <lb/>CCTop: An Intuitive, Flexible and Reliable CRISPR/Cas9 Target Prediction Tool. PLoS One 10, <lb/>e0124633. <lb/>Talbot, J. C., Walker, M. B., Carney, T. J., Huycke, T. R., Yan, Y. L., BreMiller, R. A., Gai, L., <lb/>Delaurier, A., Postlethwait, J. H., Hammerschmidt, M. et al. (2012). fras1 shapes endodermal pouch <lb/>1 and stabilizes zebrafish pharyngeal skeletal development. Development 139, 2804-13. <lb/>Thisse, C. and Thisse, B. (2008). High-resolution in situ hybridization to whole-mount <lb/>zebrafish embryos. Nat Protoc 3, 59-69. <lb/>Towers, M. and Tickle, C. (2009). Generation of pattern and form in the developing limb. Int <lb/>J Dev Biol 53, 805-12. <lb/>van den Boogaart, J. G., Muller, M. and Osse, J. W. (2012). Structure and function of the <lb/>median finfold in larval teleosts. J Exp Biol 215, 2359-68. <lb/>van Eeden, F. J., Granato, M., Schach, U., Brand, M., Furutani-Seiki, M., Haffter, P., <lb/>Hammerschmidt, M., Heisenberg, C. P., Jiang, Y. J., Kane, D. A. et al. (1996). Genetic analysis of fin <lb/>formation in the zebrafish, Danio rerio. Development 123, 255-62. <lb/>Wada, N. (2011). Spatiotemporal changes in cell adhesiveness during vertebrate limb <lb/>morphogenesis. Dev Dyn 240, 969-78. <lb/>Walker, M. B. and Kimmel, C. B. (2007). A two-color acid-free cartilage and bone stain for <lb/>zebrafish larvae. Biotech Histochem 82, 23-8. <lb/>Webb, A. E., Sanderford, J., Frank, D., Talbot, W. S., Driever, W. and Kimelman, D. (2007). <lb/>Laminin alpha5 is essential for the formation of the zebrafish fins. Dev Biol 311, 369-82. <lb/>Wehner, D., Cizelsky, W., Vasudevaro, M. D., Ozhan, G., Haase, C., Kagermeier-Schenk, B., <lb/>Roder, A., Dorsky, R. I., Moro, E., Argenton, F. et al. (2014). Wnt/beta-catenin signaling defines <lb/>organizing centers that orchestrate growth and differentiation of the regenerating zebrafish caudal <lb/>fin. Cell Rep 6, 467-81. <lb/>Wehner, D. and Weidinger, G. (2015). Signaling networks organizing regenerative growth of <lb/>the zebrafish fin. Trends Genet 31, 336-43. <lb/>Westerfield, M. (2000). The zebrafish book. A guide for the laboratory use of zebrafish <lb/>(Danio rerio): Univ. of Oregon Press. <lb/>Wilkinson, R. N., Elworthy, S., Ingham, P. W. and van Eeden, F. J. (2013). A method for high-<lb/>throughput PCR-based genotyping of larval zebrafish tail biopsies. Biotechniques 55, 314-6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<page>-37-<lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Yano, T., Abe, G., Yokoyama, H., Kawakami, K. and Tamura, K. (2012). Mechanism of <lb/>pectoral fin outgrowth in zebrafish development. Development 139, 2916-25. <lb/>Yano, T. and Tamura, K. (2013). The making of differences between fins and limbs. J Anat <lb/>222, 100-13. <lb/>Zhang, H. Y., Lardelli, M. and Ekblom, P. (1997). Sequence of zebrafish fibulin-1 and its <lb/>expression in developing heart and other embryonic organs. Dev Genes Evol 207, 340-351. <lb/>Zhang, J., Wagh, P., Guay, D., Sanchez-Pulido, L., Padhi, B. K., Korzh, V., Andrade-Navarro, <lb/>M. A. and Akimenko, M. A. (2010). Loss of fish actinotrichia proteins and the fin-to-limb transition. <lb/>Nature 466, 234-7. <lb/>Zhu, J. and Clark, R. A. (2014). Fibronectin at select sites binds multiple growth factors and <lb/>enhances their activity: expansion of the collaborative ECM-GF paradigm. J Invest Dermatol 134, 895-<lb/>901. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY 4.0 International license <lb/>author/funder. It is made available under a <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which was not peer-reviewed) is the <lb/>. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/386813 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
