<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>| Epidemiology | Research Article <lb/>Whole genome analysis of multidrug-resistant Escherichia coli <lb/>isolate collected from drinking water in Armenia revealed the <lb/>plasmid-borne mcr-1.1-mediated colistin resistance <lb/>Anna Karpenko, 1 Andrey Shelenkov, 1 Igor Manzeniuk, 2 Nina Kulikova, 1 Arman Gevorgyan, 3 Yulia Mikhaylova, 1 Vasiliy Akimkin 4 <lb/>AUTHOR AFFILIATIONS See affiliation list on p. 9. <lb/>ABSTRACT The rate of polymyxin-resistant Enterobacteriaceae, as well as human and <lb/>animal infections caused by them, is increasing worldwide, posing a high epidemiologi <lb/>cal threat since colistin represents a last-resort antibiotic to treat complicated infections. <lb/>The study of environmental niches, in particular, aquatic ecosystems in terms of genome <lb/>analysis of inhabiting antimicrobial-resistant (AMR) microorganisms as reservoirs of <lb/>acquired resistance determinants (AMR genes), represents a specific concern from a One <lb/>Health approach. Here, we present a phenotypic AMR analysis and molecular character <lb/>ization of Escherichia coli isolate found in municipal drinking water after an accident <lb/>in the water supply system of a residential building in Armenia in 2021. CrieF1144 E. <lb/>coli isolate was resistant to ampicillin, ampicillin/sulbactam, cefuroxime, ciprofloxacin, <lb/>levofloxacin, trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, colistin, and tigecycline, whereas whole <lb/>genome sequencing (WGS) revealed blaTEM-1B, tet(A), and a combination of dfrA14 with <lb/>sul1 resistance determinants, which corresponds well with phenotypic resistance above. <lb/>Moreover, the multidrug-resistant isolate studied harbored mcr-1.1 gene on a conjuga <lb/>tive 251 Kb IncHI2 plasmid, whose structure was determined using hybrid short-and <lb/>long-reads assembly. CrieF1141_p1 plasmid carried all antimicrobial resistance genes <lb/>revealed in the isolate and did not harbor any virulence determinants, so it could <lb/>contribute to the spread of AMR genes in the bacterial population. Two copies of ISApl1 <lb/>transposase-encoding element, which is likely to mediate mcr-1.1 gene mobilization, <lb/>were revealed surrounding this gene in a plasmid. <lb/>IMPORTANCE Evolutionary patterns of Escherichia coli show that they usually develop <lb/>into highly pathogenic forms by acquiring fitness advantages such as antimicro <lb/>bial resistance (AMR) and various virulence factors through horizontal gene transfer <lb/>mediated by mobile elements. This has led to high prevalence of multidrug-resistant <lb/>(MDR) strains, which highlights the relevancy of enhanced surveillance to monitor <lb/>and prevent transmission of the MDR bacteria to human and animal populations. <lb/>However, the limited number of reports regarding the whole genome sequencing (WGS) <lb/>investigation of MDR E. coli strains isolated from drinking water and harboring mcr <lb/>genes hampers the adoption of a comprehensive approach to address the relationship <lb/>between environmental E. coli populations and human and veterinary infections. Our <lb/>results highlight the relevance of analyzing the environment, especially water, as a part <lb/>of the surveillance programs to understand the origins and dissemination of antimicro <lb/>bial resistance within the One Health concept. <lb/>KEYWORDS Escherichia coli, colistin, One Health concept, WGS, multidrug resistance, <lb/>mcr-1.1, conjugative plasmid structure <lb/>October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24 1 <lb/>Editor Felix Ngosa Toka, Ross University School of <lb/>Veterinary Medicine, Basseterre, Saint Kitts and Nevis <lb/>Address correspondence to Anna Karpenko, <lb/>bioanna1995@gmail.com. <lb/>Anna Karpenko and Andrey Shelenkov contributed <lb/>equally to this article. Author order was determined <lb/>on the basis of contribution format. <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>See the funding table on p. 9. <lb/>Received 22 March 2024 <lb/>Accepted 19 July 2024 <lb/>Published 21 August 2024 <lb/>Copyright © 2024 Karpenko et al. This is an open-<lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>license. <lb/>Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></front>

			<body>T he One Health approach highlights the importance of antimicrobial resistance (AMR) <lb/>as a major issue in public health, livestock, and agriculture. The increasing rate <lb/>of AMR, especially in clinically significant bacterial species, has become a serious and <lb/>growing global public health problem in this century, leading to limiting possible <lb/>treatment options. Currently, a huge number of studies involving clinically relevant <lb/>pathogens are conducted. However, effective control of the emergence and spread of <lb/>AMR determinants requires a comprehensive analysis of human and animal health and <lb/>environmental conditions (1). In fact, there is growing evidence of the environment&apos;s <lb/>role in the dissemination of AMR genes and strains, especially in anthropogenically <lb/>impacted ecosystems. For example, human or animal waste can be discharged into <lb/>water, contaminating it (2). Thus, the environment, and the agroecosystem particularly, <lb/>represents an important source of AMR (3). In this sense, the aquatic environments can <lb/>contribute to the spread of AMR bacteria and promote the increasing risk of transfer <lb/>ring resistant bacteria, in particular, the representatives of Enterobacteriaceae family, to <lb/>humans and animals. <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae members include important ubiquitous Gram-negative bacterial <lb/>pathogens like Escherichia coli, Klebsiella pneumoniae, and many others (4), whose ability <lb/>to acquire mobile genetic elements carrying AMR and virulence determinants through <lb/>horizontal transfer by plasmids has become a public healthcare problem worldwide. <lb/>In the recent years, a dramatic decrease in the rates of successful treatment of infec <lb/>tions associated with multidrug-resistant (MDR) Gram-negative bacteria has occurred, <lb/>especially in the cases of β-lactams and carbapenems (3), which led to further limita <lb/>tion of treatment options for infections caused by these bacteria. The dissemination <lb/>of extended-spectrum β-lactamases (ESBL) and plasmid-mediated carbapenemases has <lb/>essentially left no drug to treat such infections, except for the older and less patient-safe <lb/>last-resort antibiotic like colistin (4, 5). <lb/>Colistin, also known as polymyxin E, was widely used in veterinary medicine <lb/>previously, which ultimately led to the emergence of colistin-resistant isolates. Colistin <lb/>resistance was earlier associated with point mutations in chromosomal genes, whereas in <lb/>2015, the first plasmid-mediated colistin-resistant gene mcr-1 encoding a phosphoetha <lb/>nolamine transferase was revealed (6). Since then, 10 different mcr gene variants have <lb/>been reported, with mcr-1 being globally spread (7, 8). In the recent years, there was a <lb/>significant number of reports regarding colistin-resistant E. coli strains harboring mcr-1 <lb/>gene, which were isolated from farm animals and poultry in Europe and Asia (9-12). <lb/>Moreover, the number of studies reporting environmental contamination by colistin and <lb/>colistin-resistant strains is growing very quickly (13, 14). <lb/>In particular, E. coli isolates carrying mcr gene variants were reported in many cases <lb/>from humans, animals, food, and the environment worldwide (5). The presence of mcr-1 <lb/>and mcr-3 genes in animals, agricultural soils, and irrigation water was revealed in Algeria <lb/>(3), whereas the study from Bangladesh reported widespread dissemination of colistin-<lb/>resistant E. coli strains carrying mcr-1 in food, hand rinse, and surface water (4). Other <lb/>reports concerning non-potable water contamination included the detection of mcr-3-<lb/>and mcr-5-carrying E. coli in three rivers of the Western Cape of South Africa (15), a <lb/>colistin-resistant mcr-1-harboring E. coli isolate from touristic coastal water in Brazil (16), <lb/>and a recent report regarding two isolates carrying mcr-1 and mcr-3 from different rivers <lb/>in Thailand (17). <lb/>In summary, colistin resistance has become an important epidemiological prob <lb/>lem worldwide. However, only a limited number of reports concerning mcr-harboring <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae in drinking water have been published. <lb/>Here, we supplement the existing data with a detailed genomic analysis of colistin-<lb/>resistant mcr-1.1-carrying E. coli isolate collected from drinking water, and provide insight <lb/>into resistance mechanisms and spreading pathways. We believe that our research will <lb/>contribute to better management of the risks associated with further contamination of <lb/>the environment by colistin-resistant bacteria. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>2 <lb/></page>
		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Sample collection, susceptibility testing, and DNA isolation <lb/>One E. coli isolate named CrieF1144 was selected for this study from the set of 11 <lb/>samples collected by the Armenia Center of Hygiene and Epidemiology as a part of <lb/>regular food and water monitoring activities in 2021. CrieF1144 was isolated from <lb/>municipal water after an accident in the water supply system in a residential build <lb/>ing. Worth noting, this water is usually used as drinking fresh water in Armenia, as <lb/>it is supplied from glaciers and mountain rivers. Matrix-assisted laser desorption/ion <lb/>ization time-of-flight mass spectrometry (MALDI-TOF) with Microflex LT system and <lb/>the MALDI Biotyper Compass v.4.1.80 software (Bruker Daltonics, Germany) were used <lb/>for species detection, and an antimicrobial susceptibility test for CrieF1144 E. coli <lb/>was performed using the minimum inhibitory concentration (MIC) method with a <lb/>Sensititre Analyzer (TREK Diagnostics Systems, USA). The susceptibility/resistance was <lb/>checked for amikacin, ampicillin, ampicillin/sulbactam, cefepime, ceftazidime, cefurox <lb/>ime, ciprofloxacin, levofloxacin, trimethoprim/sulfamethoxazole, colistin, imipenem, and <lb/>tigecycline. Broth microdilution method was used for colistin resistance determination. <lb/>SWIN software was applied to interpret the results in accordance with EUCAST version <lb/>11.0 (http://www.eucast.org, accessed in 2021). E. сoli ATCC25922 and E. coli ATCC35218 <lb/>were used for routine internal quality control tests for MIC determination. <lb/>Real-time PCR assay for mcr-1 <lb/>Real-time polymerase chain reaction (qPCR) was performed using the PCR-kit «AmpliS <lb/>ens MDR MCR-1-FL» (Central Research Institute of Epidemiology, Moscow, Russia). The <lb/>qPCR assay was performed on a Rotor-Gene 6000 (Corbett Research, Mortlake, Australia), <lb/>and the data were analyzed with the Rotor-Gene 6000 v1.8 software. <lb/>Whole-genome sequencing <lb/>Genomic DNA was isolated with the DNeasy Blood and Tissue kit (Qiagen, Hilden, <lb/>Germany). Quantity was evaluated by fluorimetry with Qubit 4.0 (Thermo Fisher <lb/>Scientific, USA), then the Nextera DNA Sample Prep Kit (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA) <lb/>was used for paired-end library preparation and whole genome sequencing (WGS) of the <lb/>isolate on Illumina NextSeq 2000 platform (Illumina, San Diego, CA, USA). <lb/>Oxford Nanopore MinION sequencing system (Oxford Nanopore Technologies, <lb/>Oxford, UK) with the Rapid Barcoding Sequencing kit SQK-RBK004 (Oxford Nanopore <lb/>Technologies, Oxford, UK) was used for long-read WGS. The libraries were prepared <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocols and were sequenced on FLO-MIN106 R9.4 <lb/>flow cell with a standard 72-h sequencing protocol using the MinKNOW software version <lb/>22.03 (Oxford Nanopore Technologies, Oxford, UK). <lb/>Genome assembly, data processing, and annotation <lb/>Base calling of the raw MinION data was performed with Guppy Basecaller version 6.4.6 <lb/>(Oxford Nanopore Technologies, Oxford, UK), whereas demultiplexing was performed <lb/>using Guppy barcoding software version 6.4.6 (Oxford Nanopore Technologies, Oxford, <lb/>UK). Hybrid short-and long-read assembly was generated using Unicycler version 0.5.0 <lb/>(bold mode, SPAdes version 3.15.4 for short reads) (18). The contigs with a length lower <lb/>than 1,000 bp were discarded. <lb/>The genome assembly was uploaded to NCBI Genbank under the project number <lb/>PRJNA1075679, with the genome accession number JBAGRT000000000. <lb/>Resfinder 4.3.0 software was used for antimicrobial gene detection (https:// <lb/>cge.cbs.dtu.dk/services/ResFinder/, accessed on 20 January 2024, using default <lb/>parameters) and point mutation analysis. Virulence factors were searched in VFDB <lb/>(http://www.mgc.ac.cn/VFs/main.htm, accessed on 20 January 2024, using default <lb/>parameters). Plasmid replicon types, predicted mobility, and other plasmid annotation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>3 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>features were revealed using MOB-suite (19) with default parameters (mob_typer version <lb/>3.1.2). Plasmid visualization was created using BRIG (version 0.95, https://github.com/ <lb/>happykhan/BRIG, accessed on 20 February 2024). <lb/>Insertion sequences were searched in the ISfinder database (https://www-is.bio <lb/>toul.fr/index.php, accessed on 26 February 2024). <lb/>The cgMLST profile building and comparison with reference data, as well as <lb/>plasmid comparison, were performed using BacWGSTdb server (20) (http://bacdb.cn/ <lb/>BacWGSTdb/index.php, accessed on 22 January 2024). <lb/>Plasmid multilocus sequence typing (MLST) analysis was performed using Plas <lb/>mid PubMLST sequence definitions (21) (https://pubmlst.org/bigsdb?db=pubmlst_plas <lb/>mid_seqdef, accessed on 24 January 2024). <lb/>CRISPRCasFinder (22) was used to check for the presence of CRISPR/Cas systems <lb/>and spacers in the genome. Anti-CRISPR elements were searched in AcrBank (http:// <lb/>cefg.uestc.cn/anti-CRISPRdb, accessed on 20 January 2024). Additional data processing <lb/>and output formatting were performed using the computational pipeline we developed <lb/>earlier (23, 24). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Isolate typing and resistance profile <lb/>In silico MLST typing revealed that the CrieF1144 sample isolated from drinking water <lb/>in Armenia belonged to ST457. According to the antimicrobial susceptibility analy <lb/>sis, it was susceptible to extended-spectrum cephalosporins (cefepime and ceftazi <lb/>dime), aminoglycosides (amikacin and gentamicin), and carbapenems (imipenem and <lb/>meropenem), and resistant to the other groups of antimicrobial compounds tested <lb/>(Fig. 1A). Moreover, the MIC for colistin was 4 µg/mL, which indicates strong resistance <lb/>properties for the isolate studied because it is two times higher than the reference value <lb/>provided by the EUCAST standard, version 11.0. <lb/>In silico search for antimicrobial resistance determinants provided the results that <lb/>corresponded well to the phenotypic profile (Fig. 1). For example, the presence of <lb/>blaTEM-1B gene corresponds to ampicillin resistance, tet(A) gene provides resistance <lb/>to the group of tetracyclines, and combination of dfrA14 with sul1 confers resistance to <lb/>trimethoprim-sulfamethoxazole. Moreover, phenotypic resistance to colistin determined <lb/>for the isolate studied was attributed to the mcr-1.1 gene revealed by WGS, the presence <lb/>of which was additionally confirmed by the specific qPCR. At the same time, no <lb/>mutations known to provide colistin resistance were revealed in the pmrB gene. Besides, <lb/>lnu(F) and mph(A) were additionally found, which could be responsible for lincosamide <lb/>and erythromycin resistance, respectively. <lb/>FIG 1 (A) Phenotypic antimicrobial resistance profile of MDR E. coli isolate from drinking water in Armenia. Red color indicates resistance; MIC, milligram per <lb/>liter meanings, corresponds to EUCAST v11 standards. (B) Genotypic antimicrobial resistance profile of the CrieF1144 isolate from drinking water. Colors indicate <lb/>different antibiotic groups: blue shows β-lactams, green is used for fluoroquinolones, yellow for polymyxins, pink for carbapenems, white for aminoglycosides, <lb/>purple for tetracyclines, and orange for sulfonamides. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>4 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>Acquired ciprofloxacin resistance genes were not revealed in CrieF1144, but the <lb/>mutations in the chromosomal genes gyrA (S83L, D87Y), parC (S80I), and parE (S458A) <lb/>shown to provide such a resistance (25) were found. <lb/>In order to obtain additional information regarding bacteria similarity, a search for <lb/>similar isolates in terms of complete genome sequences was conducted. The closest <lb/>isolate in terms of cgMLST profile (presented in Table S1 for CrieF1144) was UFZG01 <lb/>from the UK, uploaded to Genbank in 2018. CrieF1144 and UFZG01 had only four allele <lb/>mismatches and, thus, can be considered as belonging to one clone according to criteria <lb/>proposed by Schürch et al. (26). Unfortunately, no data were provided regarding the <lb/>source of isolation for this sample. Two other close isolates contained 37 (SWME01, <lb/>Thailand) and 40 (JAAJTG01, Lebanon) allelic mismatches, respectively. Both of them <lb/>were clinical samples. Other reference isolates from NCBI Genbank included more than <lb/>80 allelic mismatches and, thus, were not considered to be similar to our isolate. <lb/>Virulence profiling <lb/>Virulence genes can be located on the chromosome or plasmids and are involved in a <lb/>complex of bacteria-host interactions. The set of virulence determinants for the isolate <lb/>studied was quite extensive (97 genes) and is presented in Table S2; all of them were <lb/>located on the chromosome. The major virulence factors are given in Table 1. Operons <lb/>of adhesion, nutrition, invasion, and effector delivery system proteins were identified <lb/>among them. In addition, Type VI Secretion System (tss), responsible for inter-bacterial <lb/>communication and survival (27), and outer membrane porin ompA associated with ion <lb/>transport, conjugation, and host-pathogen interactions (28) were found. <lb/>Plasmid typing, classification, and annotation <lb/>Plasmids are important subunits in dissemination of antibiotic resistance and virulence <lb/>genes via horizontal gene transfer. We identified the plasmids from four incompatibility <lb/>groups in the CrieF1144, the characteristics of which are shown in Table 2. IncHI2 <lb/>megaplasmid had a length of about 251 Kb, whereas another plasmid, IncHI1B, had a <lb/>size of almost twice less. Additionally, IncI2 plasmid was identified, and Col(KPHS6) was <lb/>the smallest one. Only IncHI2 plasmid carried AMR genes, whereas no AMR or virulence <lb/>determinants were revealed in other plasmids. <lb/>The smallest plasmid&apos;s nearest neighbor was pJJ1886_1 from E. coli JJ1886 (Genbank <lb/>accession CP006785). According to the MOB-typer tool, Col(KPHS6) was predicted to <lb/>be non-mobilizable, as well as IncHI1B, which had a similarity with the p266917_2_02 <lb/>plasmid from E. coli (CP026725.1). Conjugative IncI2 was similar to a plasmid from <lb/>Shigella flexneri (CP034061.1). The most interesting megaplasmid (pCrieF1144_1) was <lb/>also conjugative, despite the significant size, and was aligned perfectly to E. coli <lb/>plasmid 2 from UFZG01 isolate. Other similar plasmids of comparable length included <lb/>pCFSAN061771_02 (CP042898.1) and p19M12 (KY689632.1), although they lacked some <lb/>resistance genes revealed in pCrieF1144_1. <lb/>TABLE 1 Virulence profile of colistin-resistant E. coli isolate CrieF1144 <lb/>Isolate <lb/>MLST Function <lb/>Localization <lb/>Virulence genes <lb/>CrieF1144 ST457 Nutrition/metabolic factors <lb/>Chromosome <lb/>chuASTUVWXY <lb/>entABCDEFS <lb/>fepABCDEG iucABCD <lb/>Bacterial communication and <lb/>survival <lb/>Chromosome <lb/>Type VI Secretion System <lb/>(tssAMLJ) <lb/>Effector delivery system <lb/>Chromosome <lb/>espL1R1 × 4Y2Y4 <lb/>Adherence <lb/>Chromosome <lb/>fdeC <lb/>fimABCDEFGHI <lb/>yagVWXYZ/ecpEDCBA <lb/>ykgK/ecpR <lb/>Invasion <lb/>Chromosome <lb/>ibeBC kpsCDEFMSU <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>5 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>Hybrid assembly allowed us to determine the refined plasmid structure and obtain <lb/>the data regarding AMR and virulence gene location, which represents an important step <lb/>in revealing the possible mechanisms of their transfer. <lb/>Below, we will focus on the IncHI2 megaplasmid carrying AMR genes. <lb/>The geographic location for a large part of closely related plasmids was China (see <lb/>Fig. 2). The plasmids were possessed by E. coli and Salmonella enterica isolates of human, <lb/>animal, and food origin. In total, 66 plasmids carried the mcr-1.1 gene, and one of them <lb/>-mcr-3.2 gene (p131681 [MH114596.1]). All these plasmids were selected for further <lb/>comparison if they possessed the IncHI2 replicon type, and the complete list with typing <lb/>results can be found in Table S3. <lb/>The double-locus sequence typing (DLST) typing of IncHI2 revealed smr0018 = 2 and <lb/>smr0099 = 2 alleles for pCrieF1141_1 plasmid. It is interesting that the reference plasmids <lb/>possessing the same allele variants did not carry mcr genes, whereas the ones with <lb/>smr0018 = 3 or 4 usually carried mcr-1.1. <lb/>It is also interesting that IncHI2 plasmid carried an anti-CRIPR protein AcrIIA7 targeted <lb/>against II-A system. CrieF1144 did not possess CRISPR-Cas system, and, in general, E. <lb/>coli isolates possessed either I-E or I-F systems (29), whereas II-A is more common for <lb/>streptococcal species (30). The map from Figure 2 was generated by BacWGSTdb server <lb/>(http://bacdb.cn/BacWGSTdb/index.php, accessed on 22 January 2024). <lb/>The structures of pCrieF1141_1 and similar reference plasmids are given in Figure 3. <lb/>The plasmids pCrieF1144_1, UFZG01_contig2 (purple), p19M12 (green), and <lb/>pCFSAN061771_02 (yellow) are shown. AMR genes carried by pCrieF1144_1 are <lb/>indicated. UFZG01_contig2 carried exactly the same set of genes, whereas two other <lb/>plasmids missed some AMR determinants. We found that mcr-1.1 gene in pCrieF1144_1 <lb/>FIG 2 The geographic locations of reference plasmids from Genbank similar to the pCrieF1144_1 IncHI2 plasmid. <lb/>TABLE 2 Plasmids revealed in the CrieF1144 E. coli isolate <lb/>Plasmid name <lb/>Plasmid replicon <lb/>Size <lb/>GC content <lb/>Relaxase type <lb/>mpf type <lb/>Predicted mobility <lb/>pCrieF1144_1 <lb/>IncHI2 <lb/>251,464 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>MOBH <lb/>MPF_F <lb/>Conjugative <lb/>pCrieF1144_2 <lb/>IncHI1B <lb/>97,763 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Non-mobilizable <lb/>pCrieF1144_3 <lb/>IncI2 <lb/>59,984 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>MOBP <lb/>MPF_T <lb/>Conjugative <lb/>pCrieF1144_4 <lb/>Col(KPHS6) <lb/>1,308 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Non-mobilizable <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>6 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>was flanked by two transposase-encoding insertion elements ISApl1 belonging to the <lb/>IS30 transposon family. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Antibiotic-resistant bacteria pose a significant threat to public health worldwide. In <lb/>particular, the emergence of plasmid-mediated resistance to colistin in MDR Entero <lb/>bacteriaceae is dangerous due to decreased effectiveness of polymyxins representing <lb/>the last-resort drugs for the treatment of infections caused by carbapenem-resistant <lb/>Gram-negative bacteria. The plasmid-borne colistin resistance genes (mcr) represent a <lb/>serious threat due to possible dissemination between different bacterial species through <lb/>horizontal gene transfer. The widespread usage of colistin in livestock and the presence <lb/>of mcr-1-positive E. coli strains in the food chain are considered to be the main rea <lb/>sons for the emergence of mcr-1-carrying E. coli in clinical cases (31, 32). The aquatic <lb/>FIG 3 Comparison of the structures of pCrieF1144_1 plasmid and reference plasmids UFZG01_contig2 (purple), p19M12 (green), and pCFSAN061771_02 <lb/>(yellow). AMR genes and insertion elements of pCrieF1144_1 are indicated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>7 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>environment acts as a connection medium between different environments, thus playing <lb/>a critical role in the dissemination of AMR in nature, humans, and other animals (33, 34). <lb/>On the one hand, water represents an important vehicle for the introduction and <lb/>spread of drug-resistant organisms in nature; on the other hand, it is an ideal environ <lb/>ment for the horizontal exchange of AMR genes (35, 36). Accordingly, several studies <lb/>have reported the detection of resistant bacteria in rivers (15, 17), lakes (37), and sea <lb/>water (16). In addition, direct transmission of clinically significant bacteria with high <lb/>levels of antibiotic resistance to humans through the river water has been reported <lb/>(38). Moreover, farm wastewater and damaged sewer pipes also represent possible ways <lb/>of transferring AMR bacteria to groundwaters (33). Poisoned surface and groundwater <lb/>can lead to contamination of purification filters and drinking water in general. Thus, <lb/>it is essential to detect such bacteria in drinking water representing an important <lb/>source of AMR transmission to humans (39). For a better understanding of the role of <lb/>such environments and dissemination routes of mcr genes, we performed detection <lb/>and characterization of the colistin-resistant E. coli isolate, named CrieF1144, carrying <lb/>plasmid-mediated mcr-1.1 gene revealed in drinking water collected in Armenia. <lb/>All virulence genes in the CrieF1144 isolate were located on the chromosome, which <lb/>agrees with other studies (40). The main functions of the 96 determinants found included <lb/>adherence, invasion, nutrition and metabolic factors, delivery systems, survival, and <lb/>bacterial and host-pathogen interactions. <lb/>CrieF1144 belonged to ST457, which represents a globally disseminated E. coli lineage <lb/>with a broad host range revealed in all continents (41). ST457 isolates obtained from <lb/>clinical patients (42, 43), wildlife, and poultry (44, 45) were also frequently reported to <lb/>carry plasmid mcr genes. <lb/>In silico analysis of AMR determinants in CrieF1144 revealed a combination of dfrA14 <lb/>with sul1, blaTEM-1B, and tet(A), besides mcr-1, which corresponds well with phenotypic <lb/>resistance revealed in susceptibility tests. Such isolates co-harboring multiple AMR genes <lb/>are of special concern because they may further limit treatment options for E. coli <lb/>infections (46). Results similar to our findings were obtained in Japan (47), in which the <lb/>mcr-1 carried by E. coli isolates from wastewater treatment plants was revealed. At the <lb/>same time, numerous studies reported a dissemination of mcr-1 gene by E. coli among <lb/>humans, animals, and food products. For instance, a PCR analysis revealed mcr-1 in 62.5% <lb/>of samples isolated from production animals in Poland, particularly, from turkeys (48). <lb/>Moreover, a dual mechanism of colistin resistance, namely production of mcr-1 and <lb/>amino acid substitution in PmrA/PmrB, was detected in clinical isolates from Egypt (49). <lb/>Several mcr-positive E. coli isolates were obtained from rivers in Thailand (17) and <lb/>Africa (15), surface water in Bangladesh (4), and irrigation water in Algeria (3). However, <lb/>these reports did not include the plasmid data. Currently, the plasmids are considered as <lb/>the major vehicles for horizontal gene transfer of the mcr-1 variants (50). <lb/>IncHI2 is a common type of large mcr-1-carrying plasmids found worldwide (51), and <lb/>such plasmids play an important role in the mcr-1 transmission (52). To the best of our <lb/>knowledge, this is the first report of an IncHI2 carrying the mcr-1 gene revealed in E. coli <lb/>from drinking water in Armenia. Previously, mcr-1-positive IncHI2 plasmid-harboring E. <lb/>coli strains were revealed in clinical samples from Egypt (49), Vietnam (53), and China <lb/>(54), and in food-producing animals from China (55), Poland (48), and other European <lb/>countries (56). <lb/>We suppose that the mcr-1.1 gene carried by IncHI2 plasmid in CrieF1144 plays a <lb/>major role in colistin resistance of this isolate for two reasons. First, no known mutations <lb/>providing such a resistance were revealed in pmrA/pmrB, phoP/phoQ, and mgrB genes. <lb/>Second, we revealed two transposase-encoding IsApl1 elements flanking mcr-1.1 in <lb/>the plasmid sequence, which were shown to mediate the mobilization of this gene <lb/>leading to resistance acquisition (57). The presence of such plasmid-encoded transpos <lb/>able elements raises concerns of fast resistance spreading within the environmental <lb/>bacterial population. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>8 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>Thus, the hybrid assembly of the genome studied allowed us not only to reveal <lb/>the accurate structure of the chromosome and plasmids, but also to gain insights into <lb/>possible colistin resistance mechanisms for the CrieF1144 isolate. <lb/>In summary, this study focuses on high-resolution genomic analysis of the E. coli <lb/>isolate from drinking water, aiming to understand the genetic structure and pathogene <lb/>sis of this environmental strain. As the prevalence and dissemination of MDR E. coli is <lb/>a significant concern in the context of both human and animal populations, a compre <lb/>hensive One Health-based approach is necessary to study this important pathogen. <lb/>This approach involves the interconnections between human, animal, and environmen <lb/>tal health, and establishes the collaboration between various scientific and medical <lb/>fields to mitigate the growing threat of AMR spread and associated risks in urban <lb/>environments (37). In the current study, we performed WGS-based characterization <lb/>and phenotypic AMR analysis of the E. coli isolate obtained from drinking water, and <lb/>revealed the possible mechanism of colistin resistance transfer. The results emphasize <lb/>the importance of WGS-based monitoring of mcr-harboring Enterobacteriaceae in both <lb/>clinical and environmental settings in agreement with the One Health concept. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>This research was funded by a grant from the Ministry of Science and Higher Education <lb/>of the Russian Federation (agreement No. 075-15-2019-1666). <lb/>All authors contributed to this study. A.K.: investigation, methodology, validation, <lb/>visualization, writing -original draft; A.S.: conceptualization, data curation, formal <lb/>analysis, validation, visualization, writing -original draft; I.M.: resources, project <lb/>administration; N.K.: investigation, methodology; A.G.: project administration, funding <lb/>acquisition; Y.M.: conceptualization, supervision, validation, writing -review and editing; <lb/>V.A.: resources, project administration, funding acquisition. All authors have read and <lb/>agreed to the published version of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<front>AUTHOR AFFILIATIONS <lb/>1 Department of Molecular Diagnostics and Epidemiology, Central Research Institute of <lb/>Epidemiology, Moscow, Russia <lb/>2 Administrative and Management Department -Directorate, Central Research Institute <lb/>of Epidemiology, Moscow, Russia <lb/>3 Republican Veterinary and Phytosanitary Laboratory Services Center, Yerevan, Armenia <lb/>4 <lb/>Central Research Institute of Epidemiology, Moscow, Russia <lb/>AUTHOR ORCIDs <lb/>Anna Karpenko http://orcid.org/0000-0003-0486-1353 <lb/>Andrey Shelenkov http://orcid.org/0000-0002-7409-077X <lb/></front>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>Funder <lb/>Grant(s) <lb/>Author(s) <lb/>Ministry of Science and Higher Education of the <lb/>Russian Federation (Minobrnauki of Russia) <lb/>075-15-2019-1666 Anna Karpenko <lb/>Andrey Shelenkov <lb/>Yulia Mikhaylova <lb/>Vasiliy Akimkin <lb/></div>

		<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY <lb/>The genome assembly was uploaded to NCBI Genbank under the project number <lb/>PRJNA1075679, with the genome accession number JBAGRT000000000. <lb/></div>


		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>9 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">ADDITIONAL FILES <lb/>The following material is available online. <lb/>Supplemental Material <lb/>Table S1 (Spectrum00751-24-s0001.csv). cgMLST profile for CrieF1144 Escherichia coli <lb/>isolate. <lb/>Table S2 (Spectrum00751-24-s0002.csv). List of virulence determinants found in <lb/>CrieF1144. <lb/>Table S3 (Spectrum00751-24-s0003.csv). List of reference plasmids used in <lb/>CrieF1144_p1 analysis. <lb/></div>

		<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Pan M, Chu LM. 2017. Transfer of antibiotics from wastewater or animal <lb/>manure to soil and edible crops. Environ Pollut 231:829-836. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.envpol.2017.08.051 <lb/>2. <lb/>Ben Said L, Jouini A, Alonso CA, Klibi N, Dziri R, Boudabous A, Ben Slama <lb/>K, Torres C. 2016. Characteristics of extended-spectrum β-lactamase <lb/>(ESBL)-and pAmpC beta-lactamase-producing Enterobacteriaceae of <lb/>water samples in Tunisia. Sci Total Environ 550:1103-1109. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2016.01.042 <lb/>3. <lb/>Touati M, Hadjadj L, Berrazeg M, Baron SA, Rolain JM. 2020. Emergence <lb/>of Escherichia coli harbouring mcr-1 and mcr-3 genes in North West <lb/>Algerian farmlands. J Glob Antimicrob Resist 21:132-137. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.jgar.2019.10.001 <lb/>4. <lb/>Johura F-T, Tasnim J, Barman I, Biswas SR, Jubyda FT, Sultana M, George <lb/>CM, Camilli A, Seed KD, Ahmed N, Alam M. 2020. Colistin-resistant <lb/>Escherichia coli carrying mcr-1 in food, water, hand rinse, and healthy <lb/>human gut in Bangladesh. Gut Pathog 12:5. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s13099-020-0345-2 <lb/>5. <lb/>Baron S, Hadjadj L, Rolain J-M, Olaitan AO. 2016. Molecular mechanisms <lb/>of polymyxin resistance: knowns and unknowns. Int J Antimicrob Agents <lb/>48:583-591. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag.2016.06.023 <lb/>6. <lb/>Liu Y-Y, Wang Y, Walsh TR, Yi L-X, Zhang R, Spencer J, Doi Y, Tian G, Dong <lb/>B, Huang X, Yu L-F, Gu D, Ren H, Chen X, Lv L, He D, Zhou H, Liang Z, Liu <lb/>J-H, Shen J. 2016. Emergence of plasmid-mediated colistin resistance <lb/>mechanism MCR-1 in animals and human beings in China: a microbio <lb/>logical and molecular biological study. Lancet Infect Dis 16:161-168. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(15)00424-7 <lb/>7. <lb/>Wang X, Wang Y, Zhou Y, Li J, Yin W, Wang S, Zhang S, Shen J, Shen Z, <lb/>Wang Y. 2018. Emergence of a novel mobile colistin resistance gene, <lb/>mcr-8, in NDM-producing Klebsiella pneumoniae. Emerg Microbes Infect <lb/>7:122. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41426-018-0124-z <lb/>8. <lb/>Mbanga J, Amoako DG, Abia A, Fatoba D, Essack S. 2021. Genomic <lb/>analysis of antibiotic-resistant Enterobacter spp. from wastewater <lb/>sources in South Africa: the first report of the mobilisable colistin <lb/>resistance mcr-10 gene in Africa. Ecol Genet Genom 21:100104. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.egg.2021.100104 <lb/>9. <lb/>Ćwiek K, Woźniak-Biel A, Karwańska M, Siedlecka M, Lammens C, Rebelo <lb/>AR, Hendriksen RS, Kuczkowski M, Chmielewska-Władyka M, Wieliczko A. <lb/>2021. Phenotypic and genotypic characterization of mcr-1-positive <lb/>multidrug-resistant Escherichia coli ST93, ST117, ST156, ST10, and ST744 <lb/>isolated from poultry in Poland. Braz J Microbiol 52:1597-1609. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s42770-021-00538-8 <lb/>10. Guenther S, Falgenhauer L, Semmler T, Imirzalioglu C, Chakraborty T, <lb/>Roesler U, Roschanski N. 2017. Environmental emission of multiresistant <lb/>Escherichia coli carrying the colistin resistance gene mcr-1 from German <lb/>swine farms. J Antimicrob Chemother 72:1289-1292. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1093/jac/dkw585 <lb/>11. Shafiq M, Huang J, Ur Rahman S, Shah JM, Chen L, Gao Y, Wang M, Wang <lb/>L. 2019. High incidence of multidrug-resistant Escherichia coli <lb/>coharboring mcr-1 and bla CTX-M-15 recovered from pigs. Infect Drug <lb/>Resist 12:2135-2149. https://doi.org/10.2147/IDR.S209473 <lb/>12. Song Y, Yu L, Zhang Y, Dai Y, Wang P, Feng C, Liu M, Sun S, Xie Z, Wang F. <lb/>2020. Prevalence and characteristics of multidrug-resistant mcr-1-<lb/>positive Escherichia coli isolates from broiler chickens in Tai&apos;an, China. <lb/>Poult Sci 99:1117-1123. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.psj.2019.10.044 <lb/>13. Drali R, Berrazeg M, Zidouni LL, Hamitouche F, Abbas AA, Deriet A, <lb/>Mouffok F. 2018. Emergence of mcr-1 plasmid-mediated colistin-<lb/>resistant Escherichia coli isolates from seawater. Sci Total Environ 642:90-<lb/>94. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018.05.387 <lb/>14. Chabou S, Leangapichart T, Okdah L, Le Page S, Hadjadj L, Rolain J-M. <lb/>2016. Real-time quantitative PCR assay with Taqman probe for rapid <lb/>detection of MCR-1 plasmid-mediated colistin resistance. New Microbes <lb/>New Infect 13:71-74. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.nmni.2016.06.017 <lb/>15. Snyman Y, Whitelaw AC, Barnes JM, Maloba MRB, Newton-Foot M. 2021. <lb/>Characterisation of mobile colistin resistance genes (mcr-3 and mcr-5) in <lb/>river and storm water in regions of the Western Cape of South Africa. <lb/>Antimicrob Resist Infect Control 10:96. https://doi.org/10.1186/s13756-<lb/>021-00963-2 <lb/>16. Cordeiro-Moura JR, Kraychete GB, Longo L de A, Corrêa LL, da Silva NMV, <lb/>Campana EH, Oliveira CJB, Picão RC. 2022. Description and comparative <lb/>genomic analysis of a mcr-1-carrying Escherichia coli ST683/CC155 <lb/>recovered from touristic coastal water in Northeastern Brazil. Infect <lb/>Genet Evol 97:105196. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.meegid.2021.105196 <lb/>17. Chotinantakul K, Chusri P, Okada S. 2022. Detection and characterization <lb/>of ESBL-producing Escherichia coli and additional co-existence with mcr <lb/>genes from river water in northern Thailand. PeerJ 10:e14408. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.7717/peerj.14408 <lb/>18. Wick RR, Judd LM, Gorrie CL, Holt KE. 2017. Unicycler: resolving bacterial <lb/>genome assemblies from short and long sequencing reads. PLoS <lb/>Comput Biol 13:e1005595. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1005595 <lb/>19. Robertson J, Bessonov K, Schonfeld J, Nash JHE. 2020. Universal whole-<lb/>sequence-based plasmid typing and its utility to prediction of host <lb/>range and epidemiological surveillance. Microb Genom 6:mgen000435. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1099/mgen.0.000435 <lb/>20. Feng Y, Zou S, Chen H, Yu Y, Ruan Z. 2021. BacWGSTdb 2.0: a one-stop <lb/>repository for bacterial whole-genome sequence typing and source <lb/>tracking. Nucleic Acids Res 49:D644-D650. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/ <lb/>gkaa821 <lb/>21. Jolley KA, Bray JE, Maiden MCJ. 2018. Open-access bacterial population <lb/>genomics: BIGSdb software, the PubMLST.org website and their <lb/>applications. Wellcome Open Res 3:124. https://doi.org/10.12688/ <lb/>wellcomeopenres.14826.1 <lb/>22. Couvin D, Bernheim A, Toffano-Nioche C, Touchon M, Michalik J, Néron <lb/>B, Rocha EPC, Vergnaud G, Gautheret D, Pourcel C. 2018. CRISPRCas <lb/>Finder, an update of CRISRFinder, includes a portable version, enhanced <lb/>performance and integrates search for Cas proteins. Nucleic Acids Res <lb/>46:W246-W251. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/gky425 <lb/>23. Shelenkov A, Petrova L, Fomina V, Zamyatin M, Mikhaylova Y, Akimkin V. <lb/>2020. Multidrug-resistant Proteus mirabilis strain with cointegrate <lb/>plasmid. Microorganisms 8:1775. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorgan <lb/>isms8111775 <lb/>24. Shelenkov A, Petrova L, Zamyatin M, Mikhaylova Y, Akimkin V. 2021. <lb/>Diversity of international high-risk clones of Acinetobacter baumannii <lb/>revealed in a Russian multidisciplinary medical center during 2017-2019. <lb/>Antibiotics (Basel) 10:1009. https://doi.org/10.3390/antibiotics10081009 <lb/>25. Hu YS, Shin S, Park YH, Park KT. 2017. Prevalence and mechanism of <lb/>fluoroquinolone resistance in Escherichia coli isolated from swine feces in <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>10 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>Korea. J Food Prot 80:1145-1151. https://doi.org/10.4315/0362-028X. <lb/>JFP-16-502 <lb/>26. Schürch AC, Arredondo-Alonso S, Willems RJL, Goering RV. 2018. Whole <lb/>genome sequencing options for bacterial strain typing and epidemio <lb/>logic analysis based on single nucleotide polymorphism versus gene-by-<lb/>gene-based approaches. Clin Microbiol Infect 24:350-354. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2017.12.016 <lb/>27. Gallique M, Bouteiller M, Merieau A. 2017. The type VI secretion system: <lb/>a dynamic system for bacterial communication? Front Microbiol 8:1454. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2017.01454 <lb/>28. Hirakawa H, Suzue K, Takita A, Tomita H. 2021. Roles of OmpA in type III <lb/>secretion system-mediated virulence of enterohemorrhagic Escherichia <lb/>coli. Pathogens 10:1496. https://doi.org/10.3390/pathogens10111496 <lb/>29. Long J, Xu Y, Ou L, Yang H, Xi Y, Chen S, Duan G. 2019. Polymorphism of <lb/>Type I-F CRISPR/Cas system in Escherichia coli of phylogenetic group B2 <lb/>and its application in genotyping. Infect Genet Evol 74:103916. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.meegid.2019.103916 <lb/>30. Bauer R, Haider D, Grempels A, Roscher R, Mauerer S, Spellerberg B. <lb/>2023. Diversity of CRISPR-Cas type II-A systems in Streptococcus <lb/>anginosus. Front Microbiol 14:1188671. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb. <lb/>2023.1188671 <lb/>31. Chen K, Chan EW-C, Xie M, Ye L, Dong N, Chen S. 2017. Widespread <lb/>distribution of mcr-1-bearing bacteria in the ecosystem, 2015 to 2016. <lb/>Euro Surveill 22:17-00206. https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2017. <lb/>22.39.17-00206 <lb/>32. Andrade FF, Silva D, Rodrigues A, Pina-Vaz C. 2020. Colistin update on its <lb/>mechanism of action and resistance, present and future challenges. <lb/>Microorganisms <lb/>8:1716. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/microorgan <lb/>isms8111716 <lb/>33. Cherak Z, Loucif L, Moussi A, Rolain J-M. 2021. Epidemiology of mobile <lb/>colistin resistance (mcr) genes in aquatic environments. J Glob <lb/>Antimicrob Resist 27:51-62. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jgar.2021.07.021 <lb/>34. Sanderson H, Fricker C, Brown RS, Majury A, Liss SN. 2016. Antibiotic <lb/>resistance genes as an emerging environmental contaminant. Environ <lb/>Rev 24:205-218. https://doi.org/10.1139/er-2015-0069 <lb/>35. Berglund B. 2015. Environmental dissemination of antibiotic resistance <lb/>genes and correlation to anthropogenic contamination with antibiotics. <lb/>Infect Ecol Epidemiol 5:28564. https://doi.org/10.3402/iee.v5.28564 <lb/>36. dela Peña L, Nacario MAG, Bolo NR, Rivera WL. 2022. Multiple antibiotic <lb/>resistance in Escherichia coli isolates from fecal and water sources in <lb/>Laguna Lake, Philippines. Water (Basel) 14:1517. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>w14091517 <lb/>37. Saini P, Bandsode V, Singh A, Mendem SK, Semmler T, Alam M, Ahmed <lb/>N. 2024. Genomic insights into virulence, antimicrobial resistance, and <lb/>adaptation acumen of Escherichia coli isolated from an urban environ <lb/>ment. mBio 15:e0354523. https://doi.org/10.1128/mbio.03545-23 <lb/>38. Laurens C, Jean-Pierre H, Licznar-Fajardo P, Hantova S, Godreuil S, <lb/>Martinez O, Jumas-Bilak E. 2018. Transmission of IMI-2 carbapenemase-<lb/>producing Enterobacteriaceae from river water to human. J Glob <lb/>Antimicrob Resist 15:88-92. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jgar.2018.06.022 <lb/>39. Odonkor ST, Addo KK. 2018. Prevalence of multidrug-resistant <lb/>Escherichia coli isolated from drinking water sources. Int J Microbiol <lb/>2018:7204013. https://doi.org/10.1155/2018/7204013 <lb/>40. Pakbin B, Brück WM, Rossen JWA. 2021. Virulence factors of enteric <lb/>pathogenic Escherichia coli: a review. Int J Mol Sci 22:9922. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3390/ijms22189922 <lb/>41. Nesporova K, Wyrsch ER, Valcek A, Bitar I, Chaw K, Harris P, Hrabak J, <lb/>Literak I, Djordjevic SP, Dolejska M. 2020. Escherichia coli sequence Type <lb/>457 is an emerging extended-spectrum-β-lactam-resistant lineage with <lb/>reservoirs in wildlife and food-producing animals. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 65:e01118-20. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.01118-20 <lb/>42. Tada T, Nhung PH, Shimada K, Tsuchiya M, Phuong DM, Anh NQ, <lb/>Ohmagari N, Kirikae T. 2017. Emergence of colistin-resistant Escherichia <lb/>coli clinical isolates harboring mcr-1 in Vietnam. Int J Infect Dis 63:72-73. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2017.07.003 <lb/>43. Merida-Vieyra J, De Colsa-Ranero A, Arzate-Barbosa P, Arias-de la Garza <lb/>E, Méndez-Tenorio A, Murcia-Garzón J, Aquino-Andrade A. 2019. First <lb/>clinical isolate of Escherichia coli harboring mcr-1 gene in Mexico. PLoS <lb/>One 14:e0214648. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0214648 <lb/>44. Yang QE, Tansawai U, Andrey DO, Wang S, Wang Y, Sands K, Kiddee A, <lb/>Assawatheptawee K, Bunchu N, Hassan B, Walsh TR, Niumsup PR. 2019. <lb/>Environmental dissemination of mcr-1 positive Enterobacteriaceae by <lb/>Chrysomya spp. (common blowfly): an increasing public health risk. <lb/>Environ Int 122:281-290. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.envint.2018.11.021 <lb/>45. Zhang P, Wang J, Wang X, Bai X, Ma J, Dang R, Xiong Y, Fanning S, Bai L, <lb/>Yang Z. 2019. Characterization of five Escherichia coli isolates co-<lb/>expressing ESBL and MCR-1 resistance mechanisms from different <lb/>origins in China. Front Microbiol 10:1994. https://doi.org/10.3389/fmicb. <lb/>2019.01994 <lb/>46. Zhang S, Huang Y, Yang G, Lei T, Chen M, Ye Q, Wang J, Gu Q, Wei X, <lb/>Zhang J, Wu Q. 2021. High prevalence of multidrug-resistant Escherichia <lb/>coli and first detection of IncHI2/IncX4-plasmid carrying mcr-1 E. coli in <lb/>retail ready-to-eat foods in China. Int J Food Microbiol 355:109349. https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.1016/j.ijfoodmicro.2021.109349 <lb/>47. Hayashi W, Tanaka H, Taniguchi Y, Iimura M, Soga E, Kubo R, Matsuo N, <lb/>Kawamura K, Arakawa Y, Nagano Y, Nagano N. 2019. Acquisition of <lb/>mcr-1 and cocarriage of virulence genes in avian pathogenic Escherichia <lb/>coli isolates from municipal wastewater influents in Japan. Appl Environ <lb/>Microbiol 85:e01661-19. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01661-19 <lb/>48. Zając M, Sztromwasser P, Bortolaia V, Leekitcharoenphon P, Cavaco LM, <lb/>Ziȩtek-Barszcz A, Hendriksen RS, Wasyl D. 2019. Occurrence and <lb/>characterization of mcr-1-positive Escherichia coli isolated from food-<lb/>producing animals in Poland, 2011-2016. Front Microbiol 10:1753. https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.3389/fmicb.2019.01753 <lb/>49. Zakaria AS, Edward EA, Mohamed NM. 2021. Genomic insights into a <lb/>colistin-resistant uropathogenic Escherichia coli strain of O23:H4-ST641 <lb/>lineage harboring mcr-1.1 on a conjugative IncHI2 plasmid from Egypt. <lb/>Microorganisms 9:799. https://doi.org/10.3390/microorganisms9040799 <lb/>50. Sun J, Zhang H, Liu Y-H, Feng Y. 2018. Towards understanding MCR-like <lb/>colistin resistance. Trends Microbiol 26:794-808. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.tim.2018.02.006 <lb/>51. Ma K, Feng Y, Zong Z. 2018. Fitness cost of a mcr-1-carrying IncHI2 <lb/>plasmid. PLoS One 13:e0209706. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone. <lb/>0209706 <lb/>52. Arcilla MS, van Hattem JM, Matamoros S, Melles DC, Penders J, de Jong <lb/>MD, Schultsz C, COMBAT consortium. 2016. Dissemination of the mcr-1 <lb/>colistin resistance gene. Lancet Infect Dis 16:147-149. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/S1473-3099(15)00541-1 <lb/>53. Vu Thi Ngoc B, Le Viet T, Nguyen Thi Tuyet M, Nguyen Thi Hong T, <lb/>Nguyen Thi Ngoc D, Le Van D, Chu Thi L, Tran Huy H, Penders J, <lb/>Wertheim H, van Doorn HR. 2022. Characterization of genetic elements <lb/>carrying mcr-1 gene in Escherichia coli from the community and hospital <lb/>settings in Vietnam. Microbiol Spectr 10:e0135621. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1128/spectrum.01356-21 <lb/>54. Zhong Y-M, Liu W-E, Zheng Z-F. 2019. Epidemiology and molecular <lb/>characterization of mcr-1 in Escherichia coli recovered from patients with <lb/>bloodstream infections in Changsha, central China. Infect Drug Resist <lb/>12:2069-2076. https://doi.org/10.2147/IDR.S209877 <lb/>55. Sun J, Li X-P, Fang L-X, Sun R-Y, He Y-Z, Lin J, Liao X-P, Feng Y, Liu Y-H. <lb/>2018. Co-occurrence of mcr-1 in the chromosome and on an IncHI2 <lb/>plasmid: persistence of colistin resistance in Escherichia coli. Int J <lb/>Antimicrob Agents 51:842-847. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijantimicag. <lb/>2018.01.007 <lb/>56. Bortolaia V, Ronco T, Romascu L, Nicorescu I, Milita NM, Vaduva AM, <lb/>Leekitcharoenphon P, Kjeldgaard JS, Hansen IM, Svendsen CA, <lb/>Mordhorst H, Guerra B, Beloeil P-A, Hoffmann M, Hendriksen RS. 2021. <lb/>Co-localization of carbapenem (bla OXA-162 ) and colistin (mcr-1) <lb/>resistance genes on a transferable IncHI2 plasmid in Escherichia coli of <lb/>chicken origin. J Antimicrob Chemother 76:3063-3065. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1093/jac/dkab285 <lb/>57. Poirel L, Kieffer N, Nordmann P. 2017. In vitro study of ISApl1-mediated <lb/>mobilization of the colistin resistance gene mcr-1. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 61:e00127-17. https://doi.org/10.1128/AAC.00127-17 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">October 2024 Volume 12 Issue 10 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.00751-24</note>

		<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
