<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Assessment of quality of care given to diabetic <lb/>patients at Jimma University Specialized Hospital <lb/>diabetes follow-up clinic, Jimma, Ethiopia <lb/>Esayas K Gudina <lb/>1* , Solomon T Amade <lb/>2 , Fessahaye A Tesfamichael <lb/>3 and Rana Ram <lb/>4 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Sub-Saharan Africa is currently enduring the heaviest global burden of diabetes and diabetes care in <lb/>such resource poor countries is far below standards. This study aims to describe the gaps in the care of Ethiopian <lb/>diabetic patients at Jimma University Specialized Hospital. <lb/>Methods: 329 diabetic patients were selected as participants in the study, aged 15 years or greater, who have <lb/>been active in follow-up for their diabetes for more than 1 year at the hospital. They were interviewed for their <lb/>demographic characters and relevant clinical profiles. Their charts were simultaneously reviewed for characters <lb/>related to diabetes and related morbidities. Descriptive statistics was used for most variables and Chi-square test, <lb/>where necessary, was used to test the association among various variables. P-value of &lt; 0.05 was used as statistical <lb/>significance. <lb/>Results: Blood glucose determination was done for 98.5% of patients at each of the last three visits, but none ever <lb/>had glycosylated haemoglobin results. The mean fasting blood sugar (FBS) level was 171.7 ± 63.6 mg/dl and 73.1% <lb/>of patients had mean FBS levels above 130 mg/dl. Over 44% of patients have already been diagnosed to be <lb/>hypertensive and 64.1% had mean systolic BP of &gt; 130 and/or diastolic &gt; 80 mmHg over the last three visits. <lb/>Diabetes eye and neurologic evaluations were ever done for 42.9% and 9.4% of patients respectively. About 66% <lb/>had urine test for albumin, but only 28.2% had renal function testing over the last 5 years. The rates for lipid test, <lb/>electrocardiography, echocardiography, or ultrasound of the kidneys during the same time were &lt; 5% for each. <lb/>Diabetic neuropathy (25.0%) and retinopathy (23.1%) were the most common chronic complications documented <lb/>among those evaluated for complications. <lb/>Conclusions: The overall aspects of diabetes care at the hospital were far below any recommended standards. <lb/>Hence, urgent action to improve care for patients with diabetes is mandatory. Future studies examining patterns <lb/>and prevalence of chronic complications using appropriate parameters is strongly recommended to see the true <lb/>burden of diabetes. <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>Diabetes mellitus (DM) is one of the chronic illnesses <lb/>with multi-system complications; the prevalence of <lb/>which is alarmingly increasing [1,2]. It is often accompa-<lb/>nied by various chronic complications that may affect <lb/>the productivity and quality of life inevitably [3]. Today, <lb/>at least in the western world, DM is the leading cause of <lb/>blindness; non-traumatic amputation; and chronic renal <lb/>failure [4]. Diabetes reduces life expectancy by 5 to 10 <lb/>years. Premature cardiovascular disease is the most <lb/>common cause of mortality [5]. <lb/>The duration of diabetes, degree of hyperglycaemia, <lb/>hypertension, dyslipidaemia, and smoking are the stron-<lb/>gest risk factors for chronic complications of diabetes <lb/>[5]. The risk of vascular complications can thus be <lb/>greatly reduced by tight management of these risk fac-<lb/>tors [5-8]. In fact, diabetes care is complex and requires <lb/>continuing medical care and patient self-management <lb/>education [6]. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: esakgd@gmail.com <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Jimma University, Jimma, Ethiopia <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/> © 2011 Gudina et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<body>The situation is far worse in the developing world [9]. <lb/>Indeed, coronary heart disease is already the leading <lb/>cause of mortality in some developing countries [10]. In <lb/>sub-Saharan Africa in particular, the condition is even <lb/>worse due to late diagnosis and poor access to diabetes <lb/>care [9-12]. <lb/>Diabetes is not uncommon in Ethiopia but the inci-<lb/>dence and prevalence of the disease is not well known <lb/>in the community. Limited studies have shown a signifi-<lb/>cant increase in its prevalence over the last four decades <lb/>[13-17], poor access to diabetes care [18], and high rates <lb/>of chronic complications [19-26]. In one of the recent <lb/>studies, accesses for blood glucose monitoring and dia-<lb/>betes health education were found to be very low. <lb/>About half of the patients didn&apos;t have urine analysis, <lb/>renal function and lipid test done in the previous 1-2 <lb/>years and none ever had glycosylated haemoglobin <lb/>(HbA1c) determination. About 75% of the patients <lb/>required admissions directly or indirectly due to uncon-<lb/>trolled diabetes [18]. The cost of inpatient diabetes man-<lb/>agement in the country is enormous being significantly <lb/>higher than the cost of other inpatient managements <lb/>[27]. <lb/>However, diabetes in Ethiopia has never been given <lb/>the attention it deserves. Glycaemic control and man-<lb/>agement of co-morbid conditions and diabetes compli-<lb/>cations are alarmingly sub-optimal and perhaps one of <lb/>the worst in the world [18]. Furthermore, the overall <lb/>disease burden in the country is unknown due to very <lb/>limited studies in the country. The available studies lack <lb/>generalizability due to small sample sizes most of which <lb/>were limited to the capital, Addis Ababa. Besides, there <lb/>is no national strategy for the prevention and control of <lb/>diabetes. <lb/>The aim of this study was to describe the current <lb/>situation for a group of Ethiopian diabetic patients <lb/>regarding diabetes specific characteristics, assessment of <lb/>hypertension management and the occurrence of dia-<lb/>betes related morbidities. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design <lb/>a cross-sectional study design was used. <lb/>Settings <lb/>This study was conducted from August 29 to November <lb/>2, 2009 at Jimma University Specialized Hospital <lb/>(JUSH). JUSH is a teaching and referral hospital located <lb/>in Jimma town, Southwest Ethiopia. Diabetes clinic is <lb/>one of the many chronic follow-up clinics of the hospi-<lb/>tal occurring twice weekly on Mondays and Tuesdays. <lb/>The service is rendered by internists, medical residents, <lb/>medical interns, and general nurses (with no special <lb/>training). <lb/>Frequency of follow-up visits is at least 3 times a year <lb/>and depends on proximity to hospital and need for close <lb/>follow-up. Patients with evidence of complications get <lb/>more frequent check-ups. On each visits, patients are <lb/>usually given diabetes health education by members of <lb/>Ethiopian Diabetes Society, who are non-professionals <lb/>and have diabetes themselves. On the follow-up day, all <lb/>patients are expected to come with results of FBS done <lb/>within 48 hours. Their charts are kept at diabetes fol-<lb/>low-up clinic. <lb/>Participants of this study were diabetic patients who <lb/>have been active in follow-up for their diabetes for more <lb/>than 1 year at JUSH. At the time of the study there <lb/>were a total of 1716 diabetic patients (both adult and <lb/>paediatric patients) on follow-up care at the hospital. Of <lb/>these, 1353 were older than 15 years and were taken as <lb/>a target population from which study participants were <lb/>selected. <lb/>Selection of study participants <lb/>a sample size of 329 patients was obtained using a mini-<lb/>mum sample size calculation. All eligible patients who <lb/>were willing to participate in the study were scrutinized <lb/>until the planned sample size was obtained. They were <lb/>invited to participate in the study in consecutive order <lb/>and their records were reviewed after their consents <lb/>were obtained. For those who had repeated clinic visits <lb/>during the study period, data were collected during their <lb/>first visits. For the 19 patients who declined to partici-<lb/>pate in the study, no further information was obtained <lb/>from them or their records. <lb/>Data collection <lb/>The data were collected by using a structured question-<lb/>naire which was specifically prepared for this study and <lb/>was compared with those used in previous studies done <lb/>in the country. Patients were interviewed for their <lb/>demographic features, characters related to diabetes and <lb/>hypertension management where applicable, hospital <lb/>admission, current symptoms, and their attitude towards <lb/>care given to them. Their charts were reviewed for types <lb/>of diabetes; types of treatments for diabetes and hyper-<lb/>tension; last three records of blood glucose, BP, and <lb/>weight; and causes of admission. Documented findings <lb/>of laboratory data, ECG, imaging studies, eye evalua-<lb/>tions, neurologic examinations, and diabetes complica-<lb/>tions were also sought from their medical records. <lb/>Patients were interviewed in a separate room with com-<lb/>plete privacy. Both the interviews and record reviews <lb/>were done by medical interns and residents. <lb/>Data quality control <lb/>to ensure the quality of data, data collectors were <lb/>selected based on their interests and were adequately <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>oriented and data collection was supervised by principal <lb/>investigators. Information provided by patients for doses <lb/>of drugs, treatment modifications, and clinical evalua-<lb/>tions were cross checked from their records for consis-<lb/>tency. The collected data were also checked for <lb/>completeness and internal consistency. <lb/>Data processing, analysis and interpretation <lb/>the data were coded, cleaned, entered and analysed with <lb/>the help of SPSS window program version 16. Descrip-<lb/>tive statistics was used for most variables and Chi-<lb/>square test, where necessary, was used to test the asso-<lb/>ciation among various variables. P-value of &lt; 0.05 was <lb/>used as statistical significance. Average blood sugar, <lb/>blood pressure and weight refer to the average of the <lb/>last three measures. <lb/>Ethical considerations <lb/>Ethical approval was obtained from Jimma University <lb/>Ethical review board. Informed and written consent was <lb/>obtained from each study participant. People with life <lb/>threatening illnesses were referred for emergency <lb/>management. <lb/>Results <lb/>Background Characteristics <lb/>The male to female ratio was 1.46:1. The mean age of <lb/>patients at the time of the study was 48.4 ± 15.1 years <lb/>with range of 15 to 82. The duration since DM diagno-<lb/>sis ranged between 1 and 41 years with a mean of 7.4 ± <lb/>5.2 years. Family history of DM was reported by a fifth <lb/>of patients, with the proportion being higher among <lb/>type 2 patients (Table 1). <lb/>Adequacy of glycaemic control <lb/>Blood glucose was measured for 98.5% of the patients <lb/>during all of their last 3 visits. None of the patients ever <lb/>had glycosylated haemoglobin test (Table 1). The aver-<lb/>age FBS was comparable among both types of diabetes <lb/>with mean of 171.7 ± 63.6 mg/dl. Over 2/3 <lb/>rd of both <lb/>groups had a mean FBS above the target level of 130 <lb/>mg/dl (Table 2). <lb/>Except for 1 patient, all were on pharmacologic ther-<lb/>apy for their diabetes at the time of study. The delay in <lb/>pharmacologic treatment after diagnosis was about 3 <lb/>months and was longer in type 2 patients, 1 and 4 <lb/>months for type 1 and 2 respectively(p &lt; 0.01). At the <lb/>time of the study, more than half of the patients were <lb/>taking insulin alone or in combination with OGLA. The <lb/>mean daily dose of glibenclamide was high with 54.0% <lb/>of the patients taking at least 20 mg daily (Table 2). <lb/>Patients taking a single OGLA alone had a better glu-<lb/>cose levels than those taking insulin alone or combina-<lb/>tion of OGLAs or insulin and OGLA (p = 0.0006). <lb/>Patients taking lower doses of oral agents also had bet-<lb/>ter blood sugar control than those taking higher doses. <lb/>However, a similar trend did not occur for insulin. <lb/>Among patients taking combination OGLA, 56.6% were <lb/>taking glibenclamide ≥20 mg/d and metformin ≥1000 <lb/>mg/d and over 90% of them had sub-optimal glycaemic <lb/>control. Despite having FBS well above target level over <lb/>the last three visits, no modification was done for <lb/>Table 1 Background characteristic of diabetic patients on <lb/>follow-up at JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Frequency <lb/>% <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>15 -34 <lb/>62 <lb/>18.8 <lb/>35 -64 <lb/>212 <lb/>64.4 <lb/>≥ 65 <lb/>55 <lb/>16.7 <lb/>Gender <lb/>Male <lb/>195 <lb/>59.3 <lb/>Female <lb/>134 <lb/>40.7 <lb/>Occupation <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>115 <lb/>35.0 <lb/>Farmer <lb/>93 <lb/>28.3 <lb/>Employed (paid work) <lb/>106 <lb/>32.2 <lb/>Student <lb/>15 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>Literacy status <lb/>Illiterate <lb/>112 <lb/>34.0 <lb/>Non-formal education <lb/>14 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>Elementary <lb/>105 <lb/>31.9 <lb/>High school <lb/>57 <lb/>17.3 <lb/>Above high school <lb/>41 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>Type of diabetes <lb/>Type 1 <lb/>117 <lb/>35.6 <lb/>Type 2 <lb/>212 <lb/>64.4 <lb/>Family history of diabetes <lb/>Yes <lb/>67 <lb/>20.4 <lb/>No <lb/>262 <lb/>79.6 <lb/>Duration since diagnosis (years) <lb/>1-5 <lb/>157 <lb/>47.7 <lb/>6-10 <lb/>106 <lb/>32.2 <lb/>≥ 11 <lb/>66 <lb/>20.1 <lb/>Blood glucose on each visits <lb/>Not done <lb/>5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>FBS <lb/>312 <lb/>94.8 <lb/>RBS <lb/>12 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>Access for SMBG <lb/>Yes <lb/>18 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>No <lb/>311 <lb/>94.5 <lb/>Access for drugs* <lb/>Free <lb/>321 <lb/>97.9 <lb/>Paid <lb/>7 <lb/>2.1 <lb/> RBS -random blood sugar, SMBG -self monitoring of blood glucose, FBS -<lb/>fasting blood sugar <lb/>*One patient was not taking any glucose lowering agent and was not <lb/>included. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>glycaemic management for 69.3% of these patients <lb/>(Table 3). <lb/>Level of glycaemic control was not significantly <lb/>affected by sociodemographic characteristics of the <lb/>patient, duration of diabetes, health education, and fre-<lb/>quency of visits. <lb/>Assessment of Adequacy of Hypertension management <lb/>The mean BP over the last three visits was 124.1 ± 17.2 <lb/>and 80.7 ± 9.4 mmHg for SBP and DBP respectively. At <lb/>the time of the study, 44.4% of patients had already <lb/>been diagnosed to have hypertension. The majority <lb/>(89.0%) of them were on pharmacologic treatments. The <lb/>commonly used antihypertensive drugs were ACE inhi-<lb/>bitors. About 75% of them were taking a single antihy-<lb/>pertensive agent (Table 4). <lb/>Only 6.8% of patients already diagnosed to have <lb/>hypertension had target BP level of &lt;130/80 mmHg. <lb/>Among patients who have never been diagnosed to have <lb/>hypertension, 41.0% (75/183) had measurements higher <lb/>than the target. Overall, 64.1% of the patients had BP <lb/>higher than the target level at least over the last three <lb/>visits. Despite having higher BP over the last three visits, <lb/>only 21.8% of these patients had modification of their <lb/>antihypertensive treatment (Table 5). <lb/>Assessment of efforts done to watch for and prevent <lb/>diabetes related morbidities <lb/>Only 68.1% of the patients had their weight measured <lb/>on each visits of the last 3 with mean of 64.4 ± 12.1 Kg <lb/>(59.3 ± 10.8 kg in type 1 and 67.1 ± 11.9 kg in type 2). <lb/>No patient had his BMI ever done as there is no routine <lb/>height measurement at the clinic (Table 6). <lb/>Diabetes eye evaluations (visual acuity and ophthalmo-<lb/>scopic examination) were done for only 42.9%. Of them <lb/>only 35.5% were sent as part of routine evaluation. Dia-<lb/>betic retinopathy was documented in 18.4% of them. <lb/>Among 31 for whom neurologic examination was done, <lb/>28 (90.3%) had evidence of sensory polyneuropathy <lb/>(Tables 6). <lb/>Only 29.5% (97) of the patients had renal function test <lb/>(RFT) done over the last 5 years, 19.8% (19) of them <lb/>had impaired renal function. Urinalysis was done for <lb/>65.7% of patients. The rates of proteinuria, glycosuria, <lb/>and ketonuria were 28.7, 63.4, and 9.3% respectively <lb/>(Table 6). <lb/>Over 10% of patients reported hospital admission over <lb/>the past year due to diabetes related conditions. Dia-<lb/>betes related complications were documented in 32.8% <lb/>of the patients. About 75% of them were complaining of <lb/>DM related symptoms at the time of study (Table 6). <lb/>Table 2 Patterns of glycaemic management among diabetic patients at JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>Glycemic managements <lb/>Type 1 DM <lb/>Type 2 DM <lb/>Total <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Initial management <lb/>MNT <lb/>4 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>14 <lb/>6.6 <lb/>18 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>OGLA <lb/>15 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>188 <lb/>88.7 <lb/>203 <lb/>61.7 <lb/>Insulin <lb/>98 <lb/>83.8 <lb/>9 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>107 <lb/>32.5 <lb/>Herbal treatment <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Current management <lb/>MNT alone <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Insulin alone <lb/>109 <lb/>93.2 <lb/>61 <lb/>28.8 <lb/>170 <lb/>51.7 <lb/>Insulin and OGLA <lb/>7 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>13 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>Single OGLA <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>69 <lb/>32.5 <lb/>69 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>Combination OGLA <lb/>1 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>75 <lb/>35.4 <lb/>76 <lb/>23.1 <lb/>Initiation of pharmacologic treatment <lb/>At the time of diagnosis <lb/>112 <lb/>95.7 <lb/>184 <lb/>86.8 <lb/>296 <lb/>90.0 <lb/>Later on <lb/>5 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>28 <lb/>13.2 <lb/>33 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>FBS (mg/dl) <lb/>&lt; 70 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>70-130 <lb/>24 <lb/>22.4 <lb/>58 <lb/>28.3 <lb/>82 <lb/>26.3 <lb/>&gt; 130 <lb/>83 <lb/>77.6 <lb/>145 <lb/>70.7 <lb/>228 <lb/>73.1 <lb/>Doses of drugs (mean ± SD) <lb/>Insuline -IU <lb/>52.4 ± 20.1 <lb/>45.0 ± 15.8 <lb/>49.7 ± 19.0 <lb/>Glibenclamide -mg/dl <lb/>20.0 ± 0 <lb/>15.2 ± 6.5 <lb/>15.3 ± 6.5 <lb/>Metformine-mg/dl <lb/>625.0 ± 231.5 <lb/>882.0 ± 406.1 <lb/>860.8 ± 400.1 <lb/>MNT -medical nutritional therapy, OGLA -oral glucose lowering agent, FBS -fasting blood sugar <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Patients&apos; satisfaction with diabetes care <lb/>Despite all the above findings, 95.3% (313) of the <lb/>patients reported that they are satisfied with the care <lb/>they are given at diabetic clinic of JUSH. <lb/>Discussions <lb/>This study assessed a wide scope of diabetes care at <lb/>Jimma University Specialized Hospital in Ethiopia using <lb/>information from chart reviews and patients. Glycaemic <lb/>control and blood pressure control were far below any <lb/>recommended standards and attempts to prevent, detect <lb/>early and manage chronic complications of diabetes <lb/>were alarmingly poor. The mean FBS of 171.1 ± 63.6 <lb/>mg/dl is better than the 190 ± 89.6 mg/dl in Addis <lb/>Ababa [18] however; it is far higher than the recommen-<lb/>dations in the developed world [6,28]. The majority of <lb/>patients (73.1%) had FBS above the target level of 130 <lb/>mg/dl as compared with 79% having &gt;120 mg/dl in pre-<lb/>vious study [18] indicating that glycaemic control in <lb/>Ethiopia is in dire need of being addressed. Similar to <lb/>most studies in the country [18], no patient had HbA1c <lb/>determination in this study because it is not available in <lb/>public health sector in the country. <lb/>Over 99% of the patients were on pharmacologic <lb/>treatment for their diabetes at the time of study with <lb/>the delay after diagnosis for drug treatment being 3 <lb/>months. Reasons may be lack of routine medical check-<lb/>up and lack of knowledge of diabetic symptoms which <lb/>resulted in patients presenting only when they were <lb/>overtly sick. <lb/>Over 55% of the patients needed insulin and about <lb/>33% of type 2 patients have become insulin requiring <lb/>during the course of their diabetes. This can be <lb/>explained by the secondary insulin failure as the disease <lb/>progresses since most patients were over 5 years post <lb/>diagnosis. A similar trend has been documented in UK <lb/>Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) 33 in which case a <lb/>significant proportion of patients on sulfonylurea subse-<lb/>quently required insulin due to severe hyperglycemia <lb/>[7]. The daily insulin requirement was significantly <lb/>higher in type 1 patients (52.4 Vs 45.0IU/Kg/d, p = <lb/>0.0001) which can be explained by the pathophysiology <lb/>of the disease. <lb/>Patients taking a single oral agent were found to have <lb/>a better glycaemic control than those taking insulin or <lb/>combination OGLAs (p = 0.002). Possible explanation <lb/>for this is the duration since diagnosis of diabetes as <lb/>72.5% patients taking single OGLA had diabetes for less <lb/>than 5 years. In contrast, over 60% of patients requiring <lb/>insulin and 56.6% of patients taking combination <lb/>OGLAs had DM for over 5 years. This implies that <lb/>good control in the single OGLA was due to the early <lb/>Table 3 Adequacy of glycaemic management in diabetic patients on follow-up at JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>FBS <lb/>Treatment categories <lb/>Average FBS, mg/dl <lb/>≤ 130 mg/dl <lb/>&gt; 130 mg/dl <lb/>P-value <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>Pharmacotherapeutic options <lb/>Insulin alone <lb/>170.8 <lb/>37 <lb/>23.6 <lb/>120 <lb/>76.4 <lb/>Insulin and OGLA <lb/>190.3 <lb/>3 <lb/>23.1 <lb/>10 <lb/>76.9 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>One OGLA <lb/>152.7 <lb/>28 <lb/>41.8 <lb/>39 <lb/>58.2 <lb/>Both OGLA <lb/>188.7 <lb/>15 <lb/>22.4 <lb/>59 <lb/>77.6 <lb/>Doses of drugs <lb/>Insulin <lb/>&lt; 1IU/Kg/d <lb/>167.7 <lb/>36 <lb/>25.5 <lb/>105 <lb/>74.5 <lb/>0.175 <lb/>≥ 1IU/kg/d <lb/>194.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>25 <lb/>86.2 <lb/>Glibenclamide (G) <lb/>&lt; 20 mg/d <lb/>149.4 <lb/>30 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>30 <lb/>50.0 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>≥ 20 mg/d <lb/>190.0 <lb/>11 <lb/>15.1 <lb/>62 <lb/>84.9 <lb/>Metformin(M) <lb/>&lt; 1000 mg/d <lb/>163.1 <lb/>15 <lb/>38.5 <lb/>24 <lb/>61.5 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>≥ 1000 mg/d <lb/>204.3 <lb/>5 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>52 <lb/>91.1 <lb/>Glibenclamide + metformin <lb/>G &lt; 20 mg/d or M &lt; 1000 mg/d <lb/>168.1 <lb/>12 <lb/>36.4 <lb/>21 <lb/>63.6 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>G ≥ 20 mg/d &amp; M ≥ 1000 mg/d <lb/>203.3 <lb/>4 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>38 <lb/>90.5 <lb/>Modification of glycaemic treatment during the last 3 visits <lb/>Yes <lb/>16 <lb/>* <lb/>19.0 <lb/>70 <lb/>30.7 <lb/>No <lb/>68 <lb/>81.0 <lb/>158 <lb/>69.3 <lb/> * In 13 of these patients treatment modification was for low FBS or symptoms of hypoglycemia. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>disease course than the effect of the treatment given. A <lb/>good illustration for this hypothesis is UKPDS 33 find-<lb/>ing which showed progressive increments in fasting <lb/>plasma glucose levels and doses of insulin and OGLA. <lb/>During the follow-up period in that study, the median <lb/>insulin dose increased by about 64% from 22IU at 3 <lb/>years to 36IU at 12 years [7]. <lb/>Similarly, patients taking lower doses of oral agents <lb/>had a far better FBS level than those taking higher <lb/>doses. More than 90% of patients taking glibenclamide &gt; <lb/>20 mg/d and metformin &gt; 1000 mg/d had persistently <lb/>high FBS over the last 3+ visits. The mean FBS for them <lb/>Table 4 Patterns of Hypertension management in <lb/>diabetic patients on follow-up at JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Frequency <lb/>(%) <lb/>History of hypertension <lb/>Yes <lb/>146 <lb/>44.4 <lb/>No <lb/>183 <lb/>55.6 <lb/>Pharmacologic treatment for hypertension <lb/>Yes <lb/>130 <lb/>89.0 <lb/>No <lb/>16 <lb/>11.0 <lb/>Proportion with hypertension by diabetes type <lb/>Type 1 (N = 117) <lb/>30 <lb/>20.5 <lb/>Type 2 (N = 212) <lb/>116 <lb/>79.5 <lb/>BP in mmHg <lb/>&lt; 130/80 <lb/>118 <lb/>35.9 <lb/>130/80 to &lt; 140/90 <lb/>110 <lb/>33.4 <lb/>140/90 to &lt; 160/100 <lb/>81 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>≥ 160/100 <lb/>20 <lb/>6.1 <lb/>Antihypertensive agents <lb/>HCT <lb/>16 <lb/>12.3 <lb/>ACE inhibitor <lb/>110 <lb/>84.6 <lb/>Beta blocker <lb/>10 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>Calcium channel blocker <lb/>21 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>Others <lb/>11 <lb/>8.4 <lb/>Option of drugs <lb/>Single agent <lb/>95 <lb/>73.1 <lb/>Two drugs <lb/>32 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>Three drugs <lb/>3 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>BP -blood pressure, HCT -hydrochlorothiazide, ACE -angiotensin converting <lb/>enzyme <lb/>Table 5 Adequacy of Hypertension management in <lb/>diabetic patients on follow-up at JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>BP (in mmHg) <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>&lt; 130/ <lb/>80 <lb/>≥ 130/ <lb/>80 <lb/>P <lb/>value <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>N <lb/>% <lb/>History of hypertension <lb/>Yes <lb/>10 6.8 136 93.2 0.0001 <lb/>No <lb/>108 59.0 75 41.0 <lb/>Pharmacologic treatment of <lb/>hypertension <lb/>Yes <lb/>9 <lb/>6.9 121 93.1 0.92 <lb/>No <lb/>109 54.8 90 45.2 <lb/>Treatment modification of the last 3 <lb/>visits <lb/>Yes <lb/>3 <lb/>2.5 46 21.8 0.599 <lb/>No <lb/>115 97.5 165 78.2 <lb/>Table 6 Clinical follow-up patterns of diabetic patients at <lb/>JUSH, November 2009 <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Frequency (%) <lb/>Physical examination <lb/>Weight measurements during the last 3 visits 224 <lb/>68.1 <lb/>Evaluation for DM neuropathy <lb/>31 <lb/>9.4 <lb/>Diabetic eye evaluation ever <lb/>141 <lb/>42.9 <lb/>Recent finding of eye evaluation <lb/>Normal <lb/>36 <lb/>25.5 <lb/>Cataract/glaucoma <lb/>14 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>Diabetic retinopathy <lb/>26 <lb/>18.4 <lb/>No documentation <lb/>65 <lb/>46.1 <lb/>Investigation over the last 5 years <lb/>RFT <lb/>97 <lb/>29.5 <lb/>Urinalysis <lb/>216 <lb/>65.6 <lb/>Lipid profile <lb/>16 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>ECG <lb/>13 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>Echocardiography <lb/>9 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>Ultrasound of the kidneys <lb/>13 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>Treatments to prevent complications <lb/>Aspirin <lb/>46 <lb/>14.0 <lb/>Lipid lowering drugs <lb/>9 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>DM related admissions during the last year <lb/>39 <lb/>10.9 <lb/>DKA <lb/>28 <lb/>71.8 <lb/>Hypoglycemia <lb/>2 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>Ulcer or gangrene of extremities <lb/>5 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>Stroke <lb/>2 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>Other <lb/>2 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>Documented complications <lb/>108 <lb/>32.8 <lb/>DKA <lb/>44 <lb/>40.7 <lb/>Peripheral neuropathy <lb/>27 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>Diabetic retinopathy <lb/>25 <lb/>23.1 <lb/>Diabetic foot ulcer <lb/>11 <lb/>10.2 <lb/>Stroke/IHD <lb/>12 <lb/>11.1 <lb/>Others <lb/>7 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>Current symptoms <lb/>247 <lb/>75.1 <lb/>Blurring of vision <lb/>106 <lb/>32.2 <lb/>Numbness <lb/>100 <lb/>30.4 <lb/>Polysymptoms <lb/>74 <lb/>22.5 <lb/>Easy fatigability <lb/>71 <lb/>21.6 <lb/>Breathlessness/Chest pain/Body swelling <lb/>51 <lb/>15.5 <lb/>Foot ulcer/delayed wound healing <lb/>22 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>Impotence <lb/>15 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>Others <lb/>21 <lb/>6.4 <lb/> RFT -renal function test, ECG -electrocardiography, DKA -diabetic <lb/>ketoacidosis, IHD -ischemic heart disease <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>was 203.3 mg/dl and 65% of them had diabetes diagno-<lb/>sis for over 5 years. Surprisingly, over 80% of them did <lb/>not have any modification in their glycaemic manage-<lb/>ment over the last three visits. It is probably important <lb/>here that patients taking such a high dose of oral agents <lb/>are no more responsive to them and may sooner need <lb/>insulin therapy [7]. Overall, a high FBS over the last 3 <lb/>visits did not attract attention of treating physicians. In <lb/>about 70% of the patients with high blood sugar, no <lb/>modification in treatment regimen was done. Possible <lb/>reasons are lack of awareness, time constraint, lack of <lb/>adequate human power, and most importantly lack of <lb/>appropriate guidelines and diabetes education for both <lb/>care givers and patients. <lb/>Access for SMBG remains to be very low as it has <lb/>been in previous study [18] (5.5 vs. 5.0%). However, <lb/>access for blood glucose determination at the hospital <lb/>was not found as a constraint as 98.5% of the patients <lb/>had it done during each of the last three visits. Blood <lb/>glucose determination is free at the hospital, but <lb/>patients need to buy the glucometer and the strips for <lb/>SMBG. <lb/>Morbidities and mortalities in patients having coexis-<lb/>tence of hypertension and DM are immense [29,30]. <lb/>Due to this fact, the target BP level for diabetes is con-<lb/>sistently dropping and has become lower than the target <lb/>level of the general population [6]. In previous studies <lb/>in Ethiopia, hypertension was found to be an associated <lb/>morbidity in 19.9% of diabetic patients as in Lester FT <lb/>1988 [31] and 34% Feleke Y 2005 [18]. However, the <lb/>proportion of patients with hypertension in this study is <lb/>much higher than the national findings and figures in <lb/>the western world [29,30]. In this study, 44% patients <lb/>have already been diagnosed with hypertension at the <lb/>time of the study. Overall, 64.1% of the patients had sys-<lb/>tolic BP ≥130 mmHg and/or diastolic≥80 mmHg, and <lb/>24.6% had &gt;140 and/or ≥ 90 mmHg. <lb/>About 90% of patients diagnosed to have hypertension <lb/>were on pharmacologic therapy, the majority of which <lb/>were taking ACE inhibitors, which abides with the gen-<lb/>eral recommendation [6,32]. However, only 6.9% of <lb/>patients currently taking antihypertensive medications <lb/>had target BP. This figure, which does not look better <lb/>than placebo effect, might have been due to under <lb/>dosage, poor adherence to medications and lifestyle <lb/>management, and less concern by health care providers. <lb/>The same as in the glycemic management, even <lb/>though 100% of the patients had BP measurement on <lb/>each visits; it was rarely used for patient management. <lb/>Among patients not considered to have hypertension, <lb/>41.0% had mean BP of hypertensive ranges over the last <lb/> 3 visits. Despite having BP of hypertensive range over <lb/>the last three visits, 79.2% of the patients did not have <lb/>modification to their hypertension regimen. <lb/>The proportion of patients who have been evaluated <lb/>for diabetes related morbidities is very low. Less than <lb/>30% had RFT done and about 35% of patients did not <lb/>have urinalysis within the last 5 years. Less than 5% of <lb/>the patients had ECG, echocardiography, lipid test, or <lb/>ultrasound of the kidneys. Alarmingly a significant pro-<lb/>portion of tested patients had abnormal findings. Most <lb/>of the imaging studies would have been expensive and <lb/>inaccessible in the hospital setting; however, urine dip-<lb/>stick for albumin test is cheap and readily available at <lb/>the hospital. <lb/>Far from recommended practice less than 10% of <lb/>patients had ever had an evaluation for diabetic neuro-<lb/>pathy. Those who had been examined were those with <lb/>disabling symptoms as 90.3% of those evaluated had evi-<lb/>dences for peripheral sensory polyneuropathy. Similarly, <lb/>only 42.9% of patients in this study ever had a recom-<lb/>mended yearly eye evaluation and the majority were <lb/>evaluated for their symptoms rather than as a routine <lb/>screening follow-up. <lb/>Diabetic ketoacidosis was found to be the commonest <lb/>cause of hospital admission. Peripheral neuropathy and <lb/>retinopathy were the most typical chronic complications <lb/>identified. These findings are compatible with previous <lb/>studies in Ethiopia [19] and other countries in Africa <lb/>[22-26]. Similarly, the chief complaints for most patients <lb/>were eye and sensory related. A significant proportion <lb/>of them also had polysymptoms of diabetes that indi-<lb/>cates poor sugar control. <lb/>Lifestyle management is an important component of <lb/>diabetic care [6] and intensive nutrition treatment <lb/>besides the conventional pharmacotherapy has been <lb/>shown to improve both glycaemic control and anthro-<lb/>pometric measures [33]. In this regard, diabetes nurse <lb/>educators and diabetes dietitian play an important role <lb/>in diabetic care. However, no emphasis has been given <lb/>to diabetes health education at the clinic and in Ethio-<lb/>pia in general. To date there are no diabetes nurse <lb/>educators and diabetes dietitian in the country. Those <lb/>rendering health service for diabetes patients at the <lb/>hospital had no special training for diabetes care and <lb/>most of them were medical interns who were naïve <lb/>not only to diabetes care but also to the general medi-<lb/>cal practice. <lb/>Demographic backgrounds, type and duration of DM <lb/>since diagnosis, and duration of pharmacologic treat-<lb/>ment of hyperglycemia were not found to affect level of <lb/>glycaemic control. Similarly, the influences of good gly-<lb/>cemic and hypertension control on morbidity were not <lb/>observed in this study probably due to two major rea-<lb/>sons. Firstly, most of the patients did not have adequate <lb/>glycaemic and BP control. Secondly, documentation for <lb/>diabetes related morbidities was found for only 1/3 <lb/>rd of <lb/>patients. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Most alarming is that there is very poor record keeping <lb/>system and widespread trend of not documenting physi-<lb/>cal findings, laboratory results, and reason for changing <lb/>managements. Despite this, the majority of the patients <lb/>reported that they were satisfied with the care they were <lb/>given at the clinic indicating that patients have inap-<lb/>propriate expectation about diabetes care. Poor aware-<lb/>ness among patients about the extent and components of <lb/>diabetes care affects not only their expectations but <lb/>importantly the quality of services they obtain and the <lb/>outcome of diabetes. In this study it may be mentioned <lb/>here that patients might have been satisfied with the free <lb/>laboratory services (for blood glucose) and medications, <lb/>which were probably their main expectations of the care. <lb/>The strengths of our study was the high patient <lb/>response rate, good cooperation from hospital staff, and <lb/>the fact that it was one of the few studies on diabetes <lb/>care in Ethiopia. <lb/>There are potential shortcomings in our study that <lb/>require comment. The major limitation was poor chart <lb/>keeping that might have limited us from getting full <lb/>information about chronic complications of diabetes. <lb/>Another limitation was the cross-sectional study design <lb/>that is not adequate to assess most of the chronic com-<lb/>plications of diabetes. The classification of diabetes to <lb/>type 1 and type 2 was based solely on history and age of <lb/>the patient. In this study, the proportion of type1 was <lb/>35.6% which is much higher than findings in the wes-<lb/>tern world of 5 -10% [6]. We thus think that the pro-<lb/>portion of type 1 diabetes may be lower than our <lb/>finding with appropriate antibody study. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Glycaemic and hypertension controls in diabetic patients <lb/>at JUSH were far below any recommended standards and <lb/>attempts to prevent, detect early, and manage chronic <lb/>complications of diabetes were alarmingly poor. Besides <lb/>these, inadequate knowledge and perception of patients <lb/>about the scope of diabetic management and trends of <lb/>poor documentation at the clinic were major constraints <lb/>identified affecting over all care of diabetes patients. <lb/>Thus, we strongly recommend that urgent action <lb/>should be taken to improve the management of such an <lb/>alarmingly increasing morbidity that, if not acted upon, <lb/>is debilitating to the patient and heavy burden to the <lb/>economy of the country in particular. Due emphasis <lb/>should be given to clinical examination and urine albu-<lb/>min test to screen for chronic complications of diabetes <lb/>which are highly cost effective in such resource con-<lb/>straint settings. Available information should also be <lb/>carefully interpreted and the findings be acted upon <lb/>timely and appropriately. The documentation systems <lb/>not only for diabetic patients but also for the general <lb/>medical practice should improve so that patients will <lb/>obtain an optimum and timely care. Further clinical <lb/>investigations for adequacy of diabetes care and diabetes <lb/>complications with appropriate parameters are also <lb/>warmly recommended. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Above all, we would like to thank Jimma University for funding this research. <lb/>We would also like to thank the data collectors for their endeavor and <lb/>interest to take part in data collection. We would also like to appreciate the <lb/>patients who willingly gave us all the information we needed without any <lb/>reservation and diabetic clinic employees of JUSH whom we owe a lot for <lb/>making everything possible during data collection. <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Jimma University, Jimma, Ethiopia. <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Jimma University, Jimma, Ethiopia. <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Epidemiology and Biostatistics, Jimma University, Jimma, <lb/>Ethiopia. <lb/> 4 <lb/>Emergency Medicine Resident, St Barnabas Hospital. Bronx, NY. <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>EKG designed the study, developed instruments, supervised data collection <lb/>and data entry, analyzed data and wrote manuscript. ST and FA participated <lb/>in the study design, supervised instrument development, reviewed analysis <lb/>and contributed to manuscript editing. RR participated in the revisions of <lb/>the manuscript. All authors have read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/>Received: 26 November 2010 Accepted: 20 December 2011 <lb/>Published: 20 December 2011 <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Id21 health highlights: The economic impact of chronic diseases on <lb/>developing countries. Disease and disability: Id21 2007 [http://www.id21. <lb/>org]. <lb/>2. King H, Rewers MG: Diabetes in adults is now a third world problem. <lb/>Bulletin WHO 1991, 69:643-48. <lb/>3. Hennekens CH: Increasing burden of cardiovascular disease. Circulation <lb/>1998, 97:1095-1102. <lb/>4. Laing SP, Swerdlow AJ, Slater SD, Botha JL, Burden AC, Waugh NR: The <lb/>British Diabetic Association cohort study II: cause-specific mortality in <lb/>patients with insulin-treated diabetes mellitus. Diabetic Med 1999, <lb/>16:466-71. <lb/>5. Marshall SM, Flyvbjerg A: Prevention and early detection of vascular <lb/>complications of diabetes. BMJ 2006, 333:475-480. <lb/>6. American Diabetes Association: Standards of Medical Care in Diabetes. <lb/>Diabetes Care 2008, 31:S1-43. <lb/>7. UK Prospective Diabetes Study (UKPDS) Group: Intensive blood-glucose <lb/>control with sulphonylureas or insulin compared with conventional <lb/>treatment and risk of complications in patients with type 2 diabetes <lb/>(UKPDS 33). The Lancet 1998, 352(9131):837-53. <lb/>8. UK Prospective Diabetes Study Group: Tight blood pressure control and <lb/>risk of macrovascular and microvascular complications in type 2 <lb/>diabetes (UKPDS 38). BMJ 1998, 317:703-13. <lb/>9. Osei K: Global epidemic of type 2 diabetes: implications for developing <lb/>countries. Ethn Dis 2003, 13:S102-S106. <lb/>10. Yach D, Hawkes C, Gould CL, Hofman KJ: The global burden of chronic <lb/>diseases: overcoming impediments to prevention and control. JAMA <lb/>2004, 291:2616-22. <lb/>11. The World Health Report: Reducing Risks, Promoting Healthy Life. Geneva, <lb/>Switzerland: WHO; 2002. <lb/>12. Frenk J, Bobadilla JL, Sepulveda J, Cervantes LM: Health transition in <lb/>middle-income countries: new challenges for health care. Health Policy <lb/>Plan 1989, 4:29-39. <lb/>13. Ducorps M, Ndong W, Jupkwo B, Belmejdoud G, Poirier JM, Mayaudon H, <lb/>Watkins p, Alemu S: Delivery of diabetes care in rural Ethiopia: an <lb/>experience from Gondar. Ethiop Med J 2003, 41(1):9-17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Seyoum B, Abdulkadir J, Gebriziabher F, Alemayehu B: Analysis of Diabetic <lb/>patients admitted to Tikur Anbessa Hospital over 8 years period. Ethiop J <lb/>Health Dev 1999, 13:9-13. <lb/>15. Lester FT, Tsega E: The Pattern of Adult Medical Admission in Addis <lb/>Ababa, Ethiopia. East Afri Med J 1976, 53:620-34. <lb/>16. Lester FT: Hospitalization Patterns of Ethiopians with Diabetes Mellitus. <lb/>Diabetes Care 1987, 10(2):184-90. <lb/>17. Lester FT: The clinical pattern of diabetes mellitus in Ethiopians. Diabetes <lb/>Care 1984, 7(1):6-11. <lb/>18. Feleke Y, Enquselassie F: An assessment of the health care system for <lb/>diabetes in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. Ethiop J Health Dev 2005, 19(3):203-210. <lb/>19. Abera Ejigu: Patterns of chronic complications of diabetic patients in <lb/>Menelik II Hospital, Ethiopia. Ethiop J Health Dev 2000, 14(1):113-116. <lb/>20. Mensah GA: Ischemic Heart Disease in Africa. Heart 2008, 94(7):836-43. <lb/>21. Abba ZG, Archibald LK: Epidemiology of Diabetic foot in Africa. Med Sci <lb/>Monit 2005, 11:262-70. <lb/>22. Lester FT: Clinical status of Ethiopian Diabetic Patients after 20 years of <lb/>Diabetes. Diabetes Medicine 1991, 8:272-6. <lb/>23. Lester FT: Clinical Features, Complications and Mortality in Type 1 <lb/>Diabetic Patients in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 1976-1990. Q J Med 1992, <lb/>83:389-99. <lb/>24. Lester FT: Clinical Features, Complications and in Type 2 Diabetic <lb/>patients in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia, 1976-1990. Ethiop Med J 1993, <lb/>31:2109-26. <lb/>25. Rahlenbeck SI, Gebre-Yohannes A: Prevalence and Epidemiology of Micro-<lb/>and Macroalbuminemia in Ethiopian Diabetic Patients. Journal of Diab <lb/>and its compl 1997, 11(6):343-9. <lb/>26. Gill GV: Outcome of Diabetes in Africa. In Gill GV, Mbanya JC, and Alberti <lb/>KGMM. Diabetes in Africa Cambridge: Biddles Ltd; 1997, 65-71. <lb/>27. Feleke Y, Enquselassie F: Cost of Hospitalization of Diabetic patients <lb/>admitted at Tikur Anbessa Specialized Hospital, Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. <lb/>Ethiop Med J 2007, 45(3):275-82. <lb/>28. Nathan DM, Buse JB, Davidson MB, Heine RJ, Holman RR, Sherwin R, <lb/>Zinman B: Management of Hyperglycemia in Type 2 Diabetes: A <lb/>Consensus Algorithm for the Initiation and Adjustment of Therapy: A <lb/>consensus statement from the American Diabetes Association and the <lb/>European Association for the Study of Diabetes. Diabetes Care 2006, <lb/>29(8):1963-72. <lb/>29. Epstein M, Sowers JR: Diabetes mellitus and hypertension. Hypertension <lb/>1992, 19(5):403-18. <lb/>30. Hypertension in Diabetes Study (HDS): Prevalence of hypertension in <lb/>newly presenting type 2 diabetic patients and the association with risk <lb/>factors for cardiovascular and diabetic complications. J Hypertens 1993, <lb/>11(3):309-1. <lb/>31. Lester FT, Keen H: Macrovascular Diseases in Middle aged Diabetic <lb/>patients in Addis Ababa, Ethiopia. Diabetologia 1988, 31(6):361-7. <lb/>32. Nathan DM, Buse JB, Davidson MB, Heine RJ, Holman RR, Sherwin R, <lb/>Zinman B: Management of Hyperglycemia in Type 2 Diabetes: A <lb/>Consensus Algorithm for the Initiation and Adjustment of Therapy: A <lb/>consensus statement from the American Diabetes Association and the <lb/>European Association for the Study of Diabetes. Diabetes Care 2006, <lb/>29(8):1963-72. <lb/>33. Coppell KJ, Kataoka M, Williams SM, Chisholm AW, Vorgers SM, Jim I, <lb/>Mann JI: Nutritional intervention in patients with type 2 diabetes who <lb/>are hyperglycaemic despite optimised drug treatment–Lifestyle Over <lb/>and Above Drugs in Diabetes (LOADD) study:randomised controlled <lb/>trial. BMJ 2010, 341:c3337. <lb/>Pre-publication history <lb/>The pre-publication history for this paper can be accessed here: <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19/prepub <lb/>doi:10.1186/1472-6823-11-19 <lb/>Cite this article as: Gudina et al.: Assessment of quality of care given to <lb/>diabetic patients at Jimma University Specialized Hospital diabetes <lb/>follow-up clinic, Jimma, Ethiopia. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011 11:19. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and take full advantage of: <lb/>• Convenient online submission<lb/>• Thorough peer review<lb/>• No space constraints or color figure charges<lb/>• Immediate publication on acceptance<lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar<lb/>• Research which is freely available for redistribution<lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gudina et al. BMC Endocrine Disorders 2011, 11:19 <lb/>http://www.biomedcentral.com/1472-6823/11/19 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
