<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>NUCOME: A Comprehensive Database of Nucleosome <lb/>Organizations in Mammalian Genomes <lb/>Xiaolan Chen <lb/>1 , Hui Yang <lb/>1 <lb/>, Yong Zhang <lb/>1 <lb/>* <lb/>1 Translational Medical Center for Stem Cell Therapy &amp; Institute for Regenerative Medicine, <lb/>Shanghai East Hospital, School of Life Science and Technology, Shanghai Key Laboratory of <lb/>Signaling and Disease Research, Tongji University, Shanghai 200092, China <lb/> * To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel.: 086-021-65981196; Fax: 086-021-65981041; <lb/>E-mail: yzhang@tongji.edu.cn. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Nucleosome organization is involved in many regulatory activities in various organisms. <lb/>However, studies integrating nucleosome organizations in mammalian genomes are very <lb/>limited mainly due to the lack of comprehensive data management. Here, we present <lb/>NUCOME, which is the first database to organize publicly available MNase-seq data resource <lb/>and manage unified processed datasets covering various cell types in human and mouse. The <lb/>NUCOME provides standard, qualified and informative nucleosome organization data at the <lb/>genome scale and at any genomic regions for users&apos; downstream analyses. NUCOME is freely <lb/>available at http://compbio.tongji.edu.cn/NUCOME/. <lb/>Keywords: Nucleosome, Database, Transcriptional regulation, MNase <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The nucleosome is the fundamental unit of eukaryotic chromatin and is involved in regulatory <lb/>activities through interactions with DNA-binding proteins, including regulatory factors, <lb/>chromatin remodelers, histone chaperones and polymerases (1). Genome-wide nucleosome <lb/>organization maps have been established in multiple species, and some consistent <lb/>nucleosome positioning patterns of specific regulatory elements have been reported. For <lb/>example, nucleosomes act as barriers to transcription factors (TFs) interacting with <lb/>cis-regulatory elements. Nucleosome-free regions (NFR) and regularly spaced nucleosome <lb/>arrays are strongly associated with transcription initiation (1-4). Nucleosome remodelers are <lb/>essential for nucleosome dynamics that remove, slide and reposition nucleosomes to <lb/>overcome barriers and facilitate transcription initiation and elongation (3,5-7). The conserved <lb/>nucleosome positioning patterns on transcription start sites (TSSs) and other regulatory <lb/>elements highlight the importance of the nucleosome in regulatory activities. <lb/>Furthermore, previous studies have shown that tissue-and disease-specific nucleosome <lb/>organization widely exists in the mammalian genome and is involved in cell differentiation (8,9), <lb/>reprogramming (9,10), tissue impairment (11-13) and diseases (14-16). Most studies focus on <lb/>identifying specific nucleosome organization features and associating these features to gene <lb/>transcription or chromatin modifications. Cell type-specific nucleosome organizations typically <lb/>indicate the chromatin environment that involves distinct regulatory factors and cellular <lb/>processes (17). Therefore, nucleosome organization maps are critical for deriving a panoramic <lb/>view regarding the chromatin structure, modification and their relationship in regulatory <lb/>function. However, compared to other types of regulatory landscapes, such as histone <lb/>modification, DNA methylation and transcription factors, nucleosome organizations have not <lb/>been sufficiently explored. <lb/>To systematically explore the regulatory function of the nucleosome, a comprehensive and <lb/>dedicated database of nucleosome landscapes is urgently needed to manage, explore and <lb/>analyze these data resources. MNase-seq is the most widely used technology for generating <lb/>nucleosome organization maps (18,19). The large size of mammalian genomes is a major <lb/>challenge in experiments that require a very high sequencing depth, thus, MNase-seq data <lb/>analyses are complicated and time-consuming. We established a comprehensive database <lb/>named NUCOME (Nucleosome Organizations in Mammalian Genomes, Figure 1) that <lb/>organizes extensive MNase-seq data and characterizes nucleosome organizations. The <lb/>following are the three major features of NUCOME database: 1) NUCOME is one of the most <lb/>extensive catalog of MNase-seq data and is managed via a standard analysis pipeline and <lb/>quality control (QC) metrics. 2) NUCOME provides high-quality nucleosome organization <lb/>information for various human and mouse cell and tissue types. 3) NUCOME provides a web <lb/>interface containing multiple modules, including data search, nucleosome organization <lb/>visualization and an application that quantifies informative nucleosome organization data in <lb/>genomic regions. <lb/>
			MATERIAL AND METHODS <lb/>Calculation of QC measurements <lb/>NUCOME provides seven QC measurements for MNase-seq data to help users judge the data <lb/>quality. The definitions of sequencing coverage, AA/TT/AT di-nucleotide frequency, <lb/>nucleosomal DNA length, nucleosome depletion at TSSs, enrichment of well-positioned <lb/>nucleosome arrays at DNase hypersensitive sites (DHSs) and untranslated regions (UTRs) <lb/>were described previously (20). Nucleosome fuzziness downstream TSSs was defined as the <lb/>coefficient of variance (CV) of the distance between +1, +2, +3 and +4 nucleosomes, while the <lb/>position of nucleosomes was defined as the local maximum positions. For the measurement of <lb/>nucleosomal DNA length, samples were ranked by the deviation of the measurement values to <lb/>146 bp in ascending order. For the measurement of nucleosome fuzziness downstream TSSs, <lb/>samples were ranked based on the measurement values in ascending order. For each of other <lb/>five measurements, samples were ranked based on the measurement values in descending <lb/>order. For each sample, a &quot;Pass&quot; or &quot;Fail&quot; label was assigned for each QC measurement, <lb/>except for sequencing coverage. The criteria of &quot;Pass&quot; and &quot;Fail&quot; for AA/TT/AT di-nucleotide <lb/>frequency, nucleosomal DNA length, nucleosome depletion at TSSs, enrichment of <lb/>well-positioned nucleosome arrays at DHSs and UTRs were defined previously (20). For <lb/>nucleosome fuzziness downstream TSSs, samples with values lower than 0.4 was defined <lb/>as &quot;Pass&quot;, while others were defined as &quot;Fail&quot;. <lb/>For each cell or tissue type, the reference nucleosome organization map was selected via two <lb/>indicators. Firstly, the total number of &apos;Pass&apos; QC measurements for each sample was defined <lb/>as the first rank indicator. Then, we calculated the sum of rank quantiles of all QC <lb/>measurements for each sample as the second indicators. For each cell or tissue type, the <lb/>sample with the top rank for both two indicators was selected as the reference nucleosome <lb/>organization map. <lb/>Prediction of TF binding sites <lb/>We collected TF ChIP-seq data from Cistrome DB database (21) as the actual TF binding <lb/>profile. Qualified ChIP-seq samples were selected by the QC measurements that provided in <lb/>the database. For each TF ChIP-seq sample, the top 5,000 binding peaks (ordered by the fold <lb/>change of peaks) were defined as the positive binding sites (bound sites). The negative <lb/>binding sites (unbound sites) were defined as 20,000 random DHSs that do not overlap with <lb/>any detected peaks in the ChIP-seq sample. All 25,000 bound and unbound sites were used <lb/>for evaluating the TF binding prediction. Motif score was the first predictor. We scanned the <lb/>entire genome for significant motif hits for each TF by using BINOCh (22). For any TF bound or <lb/>unbound site with one or more significant motif hits, the highest motif matching score among <lb/>those hits was assigned as the motif score of that site. For sites without any significant motif <lb/>hits, their motif scores were assigned as 0. Nucleosome depletion level acted as the second <lb/>predictor to improve the prediction performance. Here, the nucleosome depletion level at a <lb/>given site was calculated as the degree of nucleosome occupancy deficiency at the center of <lb/>the site. The maximum nucleosome occupancy at the centeral 200 bp bin of the site was <lb/>defined as N center , and the maximum nucleosome occupancy surrounding the centeral bin <lb/>spanning 200 bp on both sides was defined as N background . If N center was larger than N background , <lb/>the nucleosome depletion level of the site was assigned to 0. Otherwise, the nucleosome <lb/>depletion level of the site was calculated as 1 -N center /N background . <lb/>A logistic linear regression conducted by a &apos;glm&apos; function in R was performed to match the <lb/>actual TF binding status (bound or unbound) by scoring motif score and nucleosome depletion <lb/>level. The R package &apos;pROC&apos; was used to evaluate the prediction power by calculating the <lb/>true-positive rate and true-negative rate with different thresholds, and area under the curve <lb/>(AUC) scores calculated by &apos;auc&apos; function in R were used as an indicator to evaluate the <lb/>performance of the TF binding prediction. The prediction improvement was calculated as AUC <lb/>(motif score + nucleosome depletion level) -AUC (motif score). <lb/>
			DATABASE CONSTRUCTION AND CONTENT <lb/>NUCOME organizes extensive MNase-seq data of the mammalian genome <lb/>NUCOME focuses on human and mouse MNase-seq data. We collected and obtained 354 <lb/>available data sets from Gene Expression Omnibus (GEO; https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) <lb/>and downloaded raw data sets from Sequence Read Archive (SRA; <lb/>http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/sra). The database comprises 28 mouse cell and tissue types and <lb/>25 human cell and tissue types (Table S1), representing one of the most extensive data sets of <lb/>nucleosome organization in mammalian genome reported to date. <lb/>NUCOME provides standard qualified nucleosome organization maps <lb/>To avoid variation in the processed data among the datasets, we applied a streamlined <lb/>analysis pipeline starting with the raw sequenced data. We developed a standard workflow for <lb/>managing MNase-seq data named CAM that includes read mapping, nucleosome organization <lb/>profiling, nucleosome array detection an QC assessment (20). The workflow guarantees the <lb/>quality of the data in the database and offers a convenient approach for users to download <lb/>processed, standard and qualified data for their downstream analyses. <lb/>Reference nucleosome organization maps selected based on quality comparison <lb/>To avoid users&apos; confusion in selecting high quality data among various samples, we <lb/>determined reference nucleosome organization maps based on a quality comparison. We <lb/>compared the data quality of samples from each cell and tissue type based on MNase-seq <lb/>data specific QC measurements. The following seven QC measurements were introduced: <lb/>sequencing coverage, AA/TT/AT di-nucleotide frequency, nucleosomal DNA length, <lb/>nucleosome depletion at TSSs, nucleosome fuzziness downstream TSSs, enrichment of <lb/>well-positioned nucleosome arrays at DHSs and UTRs (see Methods for details). We ranked <lb/>the samples from the same cell or tissue type based on the values of QC measurements, and <lb/>the top sample of each cell or tissue type was selected as the reference nucleosome <lb/>organization map. <lb/>We integrated standard processed data for all samples and the reference nucleosome <lb/>organization maps in a publicly accessible database named NUCOME <lb/>(http://compbio.tongji.edu.cn/NUCOME/). The standard processed data for all samples allow <lb/>users to conduct their analyses without difficulties in data pre-processing and QC. The <lb/>reference nucleosome organization maps provide users with direct, quantified and reliable <lb/>nucleosome organization information for any genomic region. NUCOME also retains the <lb/>information of experimental condition for advanced users who are experts in nucleosome field <lb/>to select suitable datasets for their analyses. <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>NUCOME includes three main modules (Figure 1), i.e. (a) &apos;Search&apos;, (b) &apos;JBrowser&apos; and (c) &apos;NuP <lb/>Browser&apos; (nucleosome positioning browser), and the usage and interpretation of each module <lb/>is briefly explained below. We present two examples of the usage of NUCOME. The first <lb/>example involves a traditional analysis of MNase-seq data by aggregating nucleosome profiles <lb/>around TSSs to illustrate the association of nucleosome organization and transcription activity. <lb/>The second example focuses on the expanded usage of MNase-seq data for predicting TF <lb/>binding events to illustrate interaction mechanisms of nucleosome organizations with other <lb/>regulatory factors. <lb/>Quality-supervised data query guides users in filtering samples <lb/>The &apos;Search&apos; module in NUCOME allows for data retrieval in a quality-supervised manner to <lb/>help users select data (Figure 2a). Two layers of QC assessments are included. The first layer <lb/>displays the QC status of each QC measurement to allow users to judge the data quality <lb/>directly (Figure 2a middle, Supplementary Figure 1a, b). In addition, users can compare <lb/>samples from the same cell or tissue type in terms of each QC measurement using a polar plot <lb/>(Figure 2a bottom, Supplementary Figure 1c, d) to filter and select high quality samples. The <lb/>black line represents the average rank quantile of the QC scores for all samples in the <lb/>corresponding cell or tissue type, while the blue line represents the rank quantile of the <lb/>selected data. Supplementary Figure 1c presents an example in which the data quality of the <lb/>sample is better than the average quality of all samples from the same cell or tissue type. In <lb/>contrast, Supplementary Figure 1d presents an example of the sample with relatively worse <lb/>data quality. <lb/>In addition, the &apos;Search&apos; module provides other useful information about the samples. The <lb/>&apos;sample description&apos; section includes brief and basic information about the samples. The <lb/>&apos;nucleosome array&apos; section presents the locations of detected nucleosome arrays around <lb/>TSSs ordered by the enrichment of the arrays on the promoters. The &apos;download&apos; section <lb/>provides access to processed files, including mapped reads, nucleosome occupancy and <lb/>nucleosome arrays. <lb/>Data visualization of reference nucleosome organization maps <lb/>The &apos;JBrowser&apos; module provides an overview of the reference nucleosome organization maps <lb/>of the entire genome queried by gene or genomic region (Figure 2b). The nucleosome <lb/>organization maps focus on genome-wide nucleosome occupancy and the location of <lb/>nucleosome arrays. Nucleosome occupancy is measured as the number of reads mapped to <lb/>the genomic site in a cell population and presents the probability that a nucleosome is <lb/>localized at the genome site. Thus, nucleosome occupancy is an important feature that reflects <lb/>DNA accessibility. It has been reported that well-positioned nucleosome arrays downstream <lb/>TSSs participate in transcription regulation with either positive or negative effects (1) in a <lb/>cooperative context with other regulatory factors (23). We hypothesized that the location of <lb/>nucleosome arrays may indicate significant regulatory activities. Thus, we display the <lb/>nucleosome occupancy and nucleosome arrays in the module of data visualization to present <lb/>nucleosome organization on a genome-wide scale. <lb/>Informative nucleosome organization illustrating regulatory function <lb/>The &apos;NuP Browser&apos; module provides users with a friendly and flexible platform to query <lb/>nucleosome organization information in any genomic region or any gene. Compared with the <lb/>&apos;JBrowser&apos; module, &apos;NuP Browser&apos; module provides more nucleosome organization features <lb/>and quantifies the information as easily processed scores describing the local chromatin <lb/>structure, including nucleosome occupancy, nucleosome array score, nucleosome depletion <lb/>level and nucleosome profile. The text format output allows users to perform nucleosome <lb/>positioning analyses without encountering difficulties in data processing. <lb/>The nucleosome typically participates in biological processes by interacting with other <lb/>regulatory factors. Here, we used an example to explore the function of nucleosome <lb/>organizations around TSSs in transcription activity. We profiled aggregated nucleosome <lb/>positioning patterns around TSSs of genes with different expression levels and compared the <lb/>differences between the nucleosome positioning patterns (Supplementary Figure 2a). The <lb/>analysis illuminated the relationship between nucleosome organization and transcription <lb/>activity. The promoters of highly expressed genes tend to exhibit stronger canonical <lb/>nucleosome organization, including nucleosome depletion level at TSSs and a regularly <lb/>spaced nucleosome array downstream the TSSs (Figure 2c). The better nucleosome <lb/>positioning pattern exhibits an increased nucleosome depletion level (Figure 2d) and reduced <lb/>nucleosome fuzziness (Figure 2e). Many previous studies have reported similar observations <lb/>using specific cell cultured systems or tissues(24-30). Here, we showed that the regulation <lb/>manner is conserved among various human and mouse tissues and cell types by performing <lb/>this analysis in multiple samples stored in NUCOME (Supplementary Figure 2b-e). Using this <lb/>comprehensive database, researchers can deeply explore the features of <lb/>nucleosome-mediated regulation. <lb/>Nucleosome organization influences transcription factor binding <lb/>Previous studies have confirmed that nucleosome positioning patterns around TFs may <lb/>indicate the regulatory function of the TFs and play a predictive role in gene expression (31). <lb/>Here, we explored the ability to predict TF binding in vivo by introducing informative <lb/>nucleosome organization (Supplementary Figure 3a). We used a logistic linear regression to <lb/>match the binding status of TFs in 140 ChIP-seq datasets of TFs covering 7 different cell types <lb/>and 73 TFs in human by scoring motif score of DNA sequencing and nucleosome depletion <lb/>level for those sites. Then, we applied a Receiver Operating Characteristic (ROC) curve <lb/>analysis to evaluate the performance of the prediction based on AUC scores (see Methods for <lb/>details). The results demonstrate that the AUC scores improve universally after including the <lb/>nucleosome depletion level in the prediction model (Figure 3a). The improvements may result <lb/>from the effect of nucleosome organizations on chromatin accessibility for TFs binding. The <lb/>improvements are not equal in all TFs, and the TFs can be classified as Improve_G and <lb/>Improve_S groups, with great or slight improvement of prediction power by adding <lb/>nucleosome depletion level (Figure 3b). We found that the prediction improvements in TF <lb/>binding prediction are significantly negatively correlated with the intrinsic DNA motif prediction <lb/>contribution (Figure 3c). Next, we divided TFs into two groups, Motif_H and Motif_L, with <lb/>higher or lower DNA motif prediction contribution separately (Figure 3d). The TFs in <lb/>Improve_G and Motif_L groups are significantly overlapped (Figure 3e), indicating the valuable <lb/>contribution of nucleosome organization in TF binding prediction, especially for TFs with poor <lb/>prediction power based on DNA motifs. Similar results were also observed for TFs binding <lb/>prediction in mouse (Supplementary Figure 3b, c). Taken together, these results demonstrate <lb/>that nucleosome organization information derived from NUCOME can be widely applied to <lb/>elucidate the transcription regulatory program in human and mouse. <lb/>
			CONCLUSIONS <lb/>NUCOME is a comprehensive database that organizes the most extensive data sources of <lb/>MNase-seq data and provides standard nucleosome organization maps of various cell and <lb/>tissue types in human and mouse. NUCOME provides three modules in a web interface for 1) <lb/>querying data, 2) visualizing reference nucleosome organization maps and 3) querying <lb/>nucleosome organization information in any genomic regions and providing text format outputs <lb/>for users&apos; downstream analyses. Given that nucleosome organization participates in various <lb/>regulatory activities, and NUCOME is the first comprehensive database of nucleosome <lb/>organization data, the database can be a valuable resource to elucidate the panoramic view of <lb/>transcription regulatory program in human and mouse. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">AVAILABILITY <lb/>The database is available at http://compbio.tongji.edu.cn/NUCOME/. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDINGS <lb/>This work was funded by the National Key Research and Development Program of China <lb/>(2017YFA0102602 and 2016YFA0100400), National Natural Science Foundation of China <lb/>(31322031, 31371288, and 31571365), Program of Shanghai Academic Research Leader <lb/>(17XD1403600) and National Program for Support of Top-notch Young Professionals. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank Ji Liao for his contribution in the early stage of this project. <lb/>REFERENCE <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1. <lb/>Lai, W.K.M. and Pugh, B.F. (2017) Understanding nucleosome dynamics and their <lb/>links to gene expression and DNA replication. Nature reviews. Molecular cell biology. <lb/>2. <lb/>Mavrich, T.N., Ioshikhes, I.P., Venters, B.J., Jiang, C., Tomsho, L.P., Qi, J., Schuster, <lb/>S.C., Albert, I. and Pugh, B.F. (2008) A barrier nucleosome model for statistical <lb/>positioning of nucleosomes throughout the yeast genome. Genome research, 18, <lb/>1073-1083. <lb/>3. <lb/>Hainer, S.J., Gu, W., Carone, B.R., Landry, B.D., Rando, O.J., Mello, C.C. and Fazzio, <lb/>T.G. (2015) Suppression of pervasive noncoding transcription in embryonic stem cells <lb/>by esBAF. Genes &amp; development, 29, 362-378. <lb/>4. <lb/>Teves, S.S., Weber, C.M. and Henikoff, S. (2014) Transcribing through the <lb/>nucleosome. Trends in biochemical sciences, 39, 577-586. <lb/>5. <lb/>Racki, L.R. and Narlikar, G.J. (2008) ATP-dependent chromatin remodeling enzymes: <lb/>two heads are not better, just different. Current opinion in genetics &amp; development, 18, <lb/>137-144. <lb/>6. <lb/>Teif, V.B., Beshnova, D.A., Vainshtein, Y., Marth, C., Mallm, J.P., Hofer, T. and Rippe, K. <lb/>(2014) Nucleosome repositioning links DNA (de)methylation and differential CTCF <lb/>binding during stem cell development. Genome research, 24, 1285-1295. <lb/>7. <lb/>Petesch, S.J. and Lis, J.T. (2012) Overcoming the nucleosome barrier during <lb/>transcript elongation. Trends in genetics : TIG, 28, 285-294. <lb/>8. <lb/>Li, Y., Schulz, V.P., Deng, C., Li, G., Shen, Y., Tusi, B.K., Ma, G., Stees, J., Qiu, Y., <lb/>Steiner, L.A. et al. (2016) Setd1a and NURF mediate chromatin dynamics and gene <lb/>regulation during erythroid lineage commitment and differentiation. Nucleic acids <lb/>research, 44, 7173-7188. <lb/>9. <lb/>West, J.A., Cook, A., Alver, B.H., Stadtfeld, M., Deaton, A.M., Hochedlinger, K., Park, <lb/>P.J., Tolstorukov, M.Y. and Kingston, R.E. (2014) Nucleosomal occupancy changes <lb/>locally over key regulatory regions during cell differentiation and reprogramming. <lb/>Nature communications, 5, 4719. <lb/>10. <lb/>Takaku, M., Grimm, S.A., Shimbo, T., Perera, L., Menafra, R., Stunnenberg, H.G., <lb/>Archer, T.K., Machida, S., Kurumizaka, H. and Wade, P.A. (2016) GATA3-dependent <lb/>cellular reprogramming requires activation-domain dependent recruitment of a <lb/>chromatin remodeler. Genome biology, 17, 36. <lb/>11. <lb/>Bochkis, I.M., Przybylski, D., Chen, J. and Regev, A. (2014) Changes in nucleosome <lb/>occupancy associated with metabolic alterations in aged mammalian liver. Cell reports, <lb/>9, 996-1006. <lb/>12. <lb/>Chambers, S.M., Shaw, C.A., Gatza, C., Fisk, C.J., Donehower, L.A. and Goodell, M.A. <lb/>(2007) Aging hematopoietic stem cells decline in function and exhibit epigenetic <lb/>dysregulation. PLoS biology, 5, e201. <lb/>13. <lb/>Jin, J., Wang, G.L., Iakova, P., Shi, X., Haefliger, S., Finegold, M. and Timchenko, N.A. <lb/>(2010) Epigenetic changes play critical role in age-associated dysfunctions of the liver. <lb/>Aging cell, 9, 895-910. <lb/>14. <lb/>Chen, L., Chen, K., Lavery, L.A., Baker, S.A., Shaw, C.A., Li, W. and Zoghbi, H.Y. <lb/>(2015) MeCP2 binds to non-CG methylated DNA as neurons mature, influencing <lb/>transcription and the timing of onset for Rett syndrome. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 112, 5509-5514. <lb/>15. <lb/>Druliner, B.R., Vera, D., Johnson, R., Ruan, X., Apone, L.M., Dimalanta, E.T., Stewart, <lb/>F.J., Boardman, L. and Dennis, J.H. (2016) Comprehensive nucleosome mapping of <lb/>the human genome in cancer progression. Oncotarget, 7, 13429-13445. <lb/>16. <lb/>Gomez, N.C., Hepperla, A.J., Dumitru, R., Simon, J.M., Fang, F. and Davis, I.J. (2016) <lb/>Widespread Chromatin Accessibility at Repetitive Elements Links Stem Cells with <lb/>Human Cancer. Cell reports, 17, 1607-1620. <lb/>17. <lb/>Teif, V.B., Vainshtein, Y., Caudron-Herger, M., Mallm, J.P., Marth, C., Hofer, T. and <lb/>Rippe, K. (2012) Genome-wide nucleosome positioning during embryonic stem cell <lb/>development. Nature structural &amp; molecular biology, 19, 1185-1192. <lb/>18. <lb/>Hughes, A.L. and Rando, O.J. (2014) Mechanisms underlying nucleosome positioning <lb/>in vivo. Annual review of biophysics, 43, 41-63. <lb/>19. <lb/>Meyer, C.A. and Liu, X.S. (2014) Identifying and mitigating bias in next-generation <lb/>sequencing methods for chromatin biology. Nature reviews. Genetics, 15, 709-721. <lb/>20. <lb/>Hu, S., Chen, X., Liao, J., Chen, Y., Zhao, C. and Zhang, Y. (2017) CAM: A quality <lb/>control pipeline for MNase-seq data. PloS one, 12, e0182771. <lb/>21. <lb/>Mei, S., Qin, Q., Wu, Q., Sun, H., Zheng, R., Zang, C., Zhu, M., Wu, J., Shi, X., Taing, <lb/>L. et al. (2017) Cistrome Data Browser: a data portal for ChIP-Seq and chromatin <lb/>accessibility data in human and mouse. Nucleic acids research, 45, D658-D662. <lb/>22. <lb/>Meyer, C.A., He, H.H., Brown, M. and Liu, X.S. (2011) BINOCh: binding inference from <lb/>nucleosome occupancy changes. Bioinformatics, 27, 1867-1868. <lb/>23. <lb/>Krietenstein, N., Wal, M., Watanabe, S., Park, B., Peterson, C.L., Pugh, B.F. and <lb/>Korber, P. (2016) Genomic Nucleosome Organization Reconstituted with Pure <lb/>Proteins. Cell, 167, 709-721 e712. <lb/>24. <lb/>Huang, K., Zhang, X., Shi, J., Yao, M., Lin, J., Li, J., Liu, H., Li, H., Shi, G., Wang, Z. et <lb/>al. (2015) Dynamically reorganized chromatin is the key for the reprogramming of <lb/>somatic cells to pluripotent cells. Scientific reports, 5, 17691. <lb/>25. <lb/>Ishii, H., Kadonaga, J.T. and Ren, B. (2015) MPE-seq, a new method for the <lb/>genome-wide analysis of chromatin structure. Proceedings of the National Academy <lb/>of Sciences of the United States of America, 112, E3457-3465. <lb/>26. <lb/>Li, Z., Schug, J., Tuteja, G., White, P. and Kaestner, K.H. (2011) The nucleosome map <lb/>of the mammalian liver. Nature structural &amp; molecular biology, 18, 742-746. <lb/>27. <lb/>Snyder, M.W., Kircher, M., Hill, A.J., Daza, R.M. and Shendure, J. (2016) Cell-free <lb/>DNA Comprises an In Vivo Nucleosome Footprint that Informs Its Tissues-Of-Origin. <lb/>Cell, 164, 57-68. <lb/>28. <lb/>Valouev, A., Johnson, S.M., Boyd, S.D., Smith, C.L., Fire, A.Z. and Sidow, A. (2011) <lb/>Determinants of nucleosome organization in primary human cells. Nature, 474, <lb/>516-520. <lb/>29. <lb/>Voong, L.N., Xi, L., Sebeson, A.C., Xiong, B., Wang, J.P. and Wang, X. (2016) Insights <lb/>into Nucleosome Organization in Mouse Embryonic Stem Cells through Chemical <lb/>Mapping. Cell, 167, 1555-1570 e1515. <lb/>30. <lb/>Yazdi, P.G., Pedersen, B.A., Taylor, J.F., Khattab, O.S., Chen, Y.H., Chen, Y., <lb/>Jacobsen, S.E. and Wang, P.H. (2015) Nucleosome Organization in Human <lb/>Embryonic Stem Cells. PloS one, 10, e0136314. <lb/>31. <lb/>Maehara, K. and Ohkawa, Y. (2016) Exploration of nucleosome positioning patterns in <lb/>transcription factor function. Scientific reports, 6, 19620. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURES LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. Structure of the NUCOME database. <lb/>Figure 2. Examples of database usage. a) NUCOME provides a data quality supervised <lb/>&apos;Search&apos; module. Two layers of QC assessments are included. The first layer assesses the <lb/>data quality of each sample as &apos;Pass&apos; or &apos;Fail&apos; for each QC measurement. The second layer QC <lb/>assessment compares the data quality among samples from the same cell or tissue type by <lb/>the rank quantile of the measurement value of each QC measurement. The black line in the <lb/>polar plot represents the average rank quantile of the QC scores for all samples in the <lb/>corresponding cell or tissue type, while the blue line represents the rank quantile of the <lb/>selected data. b) An example snapshot of the usage of the &apos;JBrowser&apos; module. The red box <lb/>shows the location of nucleosome arrays in three tissues. c) The average nucleosome profiles <lb/>around TSSs of four gene groups classified by expression level. d) Nucleosome depletion <lb/>level around TSS of four gene groups classified by expression level. e) Nucleosome fuzziness <lb/>downstream TSS of four gene groups classified by expression level. <lb/>Figure 3. Nucleosome organization information improves TF binding prediction. a) A scatter <lb/>plot displays the improvement of prediction power by introducing nucleosome depletion level in <lb/>the prediction model. The x-axis represents the AUC score by using DNA motif score only. The <lb/>y-axis represents the AUC score by using both DNA motif score and nucleosome depletion <lb/>level. Different colors represent the TFs in various cell and tissue types. The gray dot line <lb/>indicates that the AUC scores of the two predictions are equal. The black dot line indicates that <lb/>adding the nucleosome depletion level improves the prediction power by 0.05. The triangle <lb/>points are TFs that AUC scores improve more than 0.05, while the round points are TFs that <lb/>AUC scores improve less than 0.05. b) The distribution of AUC score improvements by <lb/>introducing nucleosome depletion level in the prediction model. &apos;Improve_G&apos; group includes <lb/>TFs exhibits at least a 0.05 improvement, while &apos;Improve_S&apos; group includes TFs with less than <lb/>0.05 AUC score improvement. c) A scatter plot with the red regression line revealing the <lb/>significantly negative correlation between prediction improvement by introducing nucleosome <lb/>depletion level and prediction performance by DNA motif score only (p-value &lt; 2.2 x 10 <lb/>-16 ). The <lb/>x-axis represents the AUC score by using DNA motif score only. The y-axis represents the <lb/>AUC score improvements by introducing nucleosome depletion level. d) The distribution of <lb/>prediction performance by DNA motif score only. &apos;Motif_L&apos; group includes TFs that have AUC <lb/>scores less than 0.65 by using DNA motif score, while &apos;Motif_H&apos; group includes TFs with AUC <lb/>scores higher than 0.65. e) Overlapping among TFs in &apos;Improve_S&apos; group and &apos;Motif_L&apos; group. <lb/>The p-value is calculated by the Chi-square test. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
