<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cuomo and Ambrosino Cell Death and Disease (2019) 10:88 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41419-019-1334-6 <lb/>Cell Death &amp; Disease <lb/>C O M M E N T <lb/>O p e n A c c e s s <lb/>Non-coding RNAs as integrators of the <lb/>effects of age, genes, and environment <lb/>on ovarian aging <lb/>Danila Cuomo 1,2 and Concetta Ambrosino 1 <lb/></front>

			<body>One of the significant social changes seen in the past <lb/>few decades is the decision taken by an increasing number <lb/>of women, particularly career women, to delay starting a <lb/>family. These decisions often invite undesirable con-<lb/>sequences such as difficulties in conception, and a major <lb/>contributing factor to such difficulties is ovarian aging 1 . A <lb/>primary cause of ovarian aging is depletion of the ovarian <lb/>pool of nongrowing follicles (NGFs) 2 . While this process <lb/>is a natural consequence of aging, its onset also varies <lb/>significantly among individuals as indicated by large range <lb/>in age at which women undergo menopause. It is also <lb/>becoming increasingly clear that other factors besides <lb/>normal hormonal cycles influence ovarian aging. In par-<lb/>ticular, we are now coming to appreciate that large vari-<lb/>abilities in diminished ovarian reserve (DOR) between <lb/>individuals reflect both genetic and environmental factors <lb/>and, above all, their complex interplay. <lb/>Genome-wide association studies have identified at least <lb/>44 genomic loci that influence the age of menopause <lb/>onset 3 . Furthermore, environmental factors (e.g., diet and <lb/>chemical toxins) also modulate the rate of decline in <lb/>ovarian reserve (OR). Overall, they can impact processes <lb/>such as oxidative stress, inflammation and hormone <lb/>secretion, all contributing to follicular atrophy 4 . Thus, the <lb/>onset of ovarian aging is recognized as an exceedingly <lb/>complex process in which age, genetics and environment <lb/>participate, although the precise mechanisms by which <lb/>these may do so are poorly understood. <lb/>Where do we stand from the perspective of clinical <lb/>diagnosis of progression of ovarian aging or predisposition <lb/>to ovarian aging? Unfortunately, there are no genetic or <lb/>exposure markers for assessing OR available for routine <lb/>clinical use. Current methods for measuring OR and <lb/>predicting onset of fertility loss and menopause involve <lb/>measurements of serum levels of follicle-stimulating hor-<lb/>mone, inhibin B, anti-Müllerian hormone, and antral fol-<lb/>licle counts. However, none of these parameters accurately <lb/>estimate the reproductive lifespan of an individual 5 . Thus, <lb/>new strategies for assessing OR progression, or predis-<lb/>position are needed. One promising approach to this end <lb/>is to use gene-environment interaction studies to identify <lb/>sensitive and specific biomarkers for evaluating the <lb/>&quot;biological ovarian age&quot;. That is, a reliable measure of <lb/>ovarian health that does not factor chronological age since <lb/>ovarian health and chronological age are rather loosely <lb/>coupled 6 . A productive execution of such an approach <lb/>requires a detailed understanding of the molecular <lb/>mechanisms that operate during the ovarian aging process. <lb/>New diagnostic tools could be rationally designed focusing <lb/>on the identification of molecules impaired by all the <lb/>factors influencing ovarian aging. <lb/>Such as approach has been undertaken by Cuomo et al. 7 <lb/>in their paper recently published in Cell Death Discovery. <lb/>They applied a differential transcriptomics approach in a <lb/>mouse model system to identify novel candidate bio-<lb/>markers for reliably estimating ovary lifespan as a function <lb/>of age, genetic background and exposure to environ-<lb/>mental stressors (e.g., diets and endocrine disruptors). <lb/>The cohort of differentially expressed genes in ovaries <lb/>from young (3-month-old) as compared to middle-aged <lb/>(12-month-old) mice highlighted pathways previously <lb/>shown to be involved in ovarian aging (e.g., EIF2 <lb/>and mTOR signaling, mitochondrial stress pathways <lb/>TGF-beta signaling), as well as protein translation systems <lb/>which had not been previously associated with ovarian <lb/></body>

			<front>© The Author(s) 2019 <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction <lb/>in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if <lb/>changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If <lb/>material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain <lb/>permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>Correspondence: Concetta Ambrosino (coambros@unisannio.it) <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Science and Technology, University of Sannio, Via Port&apos;Arsa 11, <lb/>Benevento 82100, Italy <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Molecular and Cellular Medicine, College of Medicine, Texas <lb/>A&amp;M University, College Station, TX 77843, USA <lb/>Official journal of the Cell Death Differentiation Association <lb/></front>

			1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>

			<body>aging (e.g., ribosomal proteins, Rps3, Rps24; regulatory <lb/>Eif3a, Eif3m, Eif4g2; small nucleolar RNAs, <lb/>Snord16a, Snora34). <lb/>The most interesting aspect of the Cuomo et al. study 7 <lb/>was the unexpected identification of differentially <lb/>expressed non-coding RNAs (ncRNAs) in this tran-<lb/>scriptomics study. Specifically, the relevant ncRNAs <lb/>included miRNAs (Mir143, Mir145, Mir505, Mir681, and <lb/>Mir692-1), small nucleolar RNAs (Snord16a and Snora34) <lb/>and a long non-coding RNA (Gas5). Particular attention <lb/>was focused on Mir143 and Mir145. Indeed, the work of <lb/>Cuomo et al. represents the first evidence of the asso-<lb/>ciation of this microRNA pair with ovarian aging and <lb/>DOR. The case for these miRNAs as the basis for a <lb/>diagnostic strategy is reinforced by the demonstration that <lb/>Mir143 and Mir145 expression was consistently deranged <lb/>by all factors that promote ovarian aging-i.e., age, genetic <lb/>background, and environmental factors. Moreover, the <lb/>bioinformatic analyses of the transcripts targeted by both <lb/>Mir143 and Mir145 implicate these miRNAs in regulation <lb/>of cellular pathways whose compromise is linked to <lb/>ovarian aging. Specifically, Mir143 and Mir145 do have <lb/>different targets which enrich for signaling <lb/>pathways: PI3K/AKT, JAK/STAT, and AMPK. This sug-<lb/>gests that miRNAs might act on the same cellular path-<lb/>ways but at different levels and most definitely through <lb/>different mechanisms. An example is the PI3K/AKT <lb/>pathway, whose components are known to be required <lb/>for: (i) follicles development 8 and (ii) telomere protection 9 <lb/>(Fig. 1). Noteworthy, the authors report Mir681 up reg-<lb/>ulation in the ovaries from middle-aged mice which is <lb/>known to functionally suppress AKT 10 . While it remains <lb/>unclear exactly how these pathways modulate physiolo-<lb/>gical and induced ovarian aging processes, these data <lb/>nevertheless offer a new path for establishing a <lb/>mechanistic-based diagnostic marker linking age, genetic, <lb/>and environmental factors in the ovarian aging process. <lb/>The fact that Mir143 and Mir145 abundance can be fol-<lb/>lowed in follicular fluid (FF) from women is yet another <lb/>advantage for their development as suitable biomarkers. <lb/>How faithfully mouse studies translate to the human <lb/>condition is always a concern. In that regard, there is no <lb/>question that much work needs to be done to validate the <lb/>efficacy of these ncRNA biomarkers in estimating human <lb/>ovarian aging. But, the early returns are promising. <lb/>Cuomo and colleagues 7 present preliminary results <lb/>showing that FF from women with DOR exhibit elevated <lb/>Mir143, Mir145 levels. Although those analytical data <lb/>were derived from a small sample size, the results none-<lb/>theless remain consistent with Mir143 and Mir145 <lb/>expression being associated with reductions in mature <lb/>oocyte loads and compromised oocyte reprogramming <lb/>capacities (an indicator of MII oocyte quality). The pro-<lb/>filing of Mir143, Mir145, and other ncRNAs in FF samples <lb/>now offers a promising translational strategy for devel-<lb/>oping an effective and predictive biomarker platform to <lb/>monitor ovarian aging in the general human population <lb/>using noninvasive methods. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was supported by: the Italian Workers&apos; Compensation Authority <lb/>(Grant no.12010), the Italian Ministry of Health (Grant no. RF 2010-2309484), <lb/>Legge Regionale 5/02 (CUP: F82I14001270002), Sensor Regione Campania <lb/>(Grant no. 23). We thank IRGS (Biogem) for support and the mouse facility for <lb/>the technical support. <lb/></div>

			<body>Fig. 1 Proposed mechanism linking Mir143/Mir145 and ovarian aging. Ovarian aging triggers miRNAs dysregulation that would impact on <lb/>genes/proteins involved in the PI3K/AKT signaling pathway, thereby contributing to the depletion of the primordial follicle pool <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cuomo and Ambrosino Cell Death and Disease (2019) 10:88 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Official journal of the Cell Death Differentiation Association <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that have no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in <lb/>published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 17 October 2018 Revised: 21 December 2018 Accepted: 7 <lb/>January 2019 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Subrat, P., Santa, S. A. &amp; Vandana, J. The concepts and consequences <lb/>of early ovarian ageing: a caveat to women&apos;s health. J. Reprod. &amp; Infertil. <lb/>14, 3-7 (2013). <lb/>2. Hansen, K. R. et al. A new model of reproductive aging: decline in ovarian <lb/>non-growing follicle number from birth to menopause. Hum. Reprod. 23, <lb/>699-708 (2008). <lb/>3. Day, F. R. et al. Large-scale genomic analyses link reproductive aging to <lb/>hypothalamic signaling, breast cancer susceptibility and BRCA1-mediated <lb/>DNA repair. Nat. Genet. 47, 1294-1303 (2015). <lb/>4. Moslehi, N., Mirmiran, P., Tehrani, F. R. &amp; Azizi, F. Current evidence on asso-<lb/>ciations of nutritional factors with ovarian reserve and timing of menopause: a <lb/>systematic review. Adv. Nutr. 8, 597-612 (2017). <lb/>5. Amanvermez, R. &amp; Tosun, M. An update on ovarian aging and ovarian reserve <lb/>tests. Int. J. Fertil. Steril. 9, 411-415 (2016). <lb/>6. Wiweko, B. et al. Chronological age vs biological age: an age-related nor-<lb/>mogram for antral follicle count, FSH and anti-Mullerian hormone. J. Assist. <lb/>Reprod. Genet. 30, 1563-1567 (2013). <lb/>7. Cuomo, D. et al. Transcriptional landscape of mouse-aged ovaries reveals a <lb/>unique set of non-coding RNAs associated with physiological and environ-<lb/>mental ovarian dysfunctions. Cell Death Discov. 4, 112 (2018). <lb/>8. Sobinoff, A. P., Nixon, B., Roman, S. D. &amp; McLaughlin, E. A. Staying alive: PI3K <lb/>pathway promotes primordial follicle activation and survival in response to <lb/>3MC-induced ovotoxicity. Toxicol. Sci. 128, 258-271 (2012). <lb/>9. Mendez-Pertuz, M. et al. Modulation of telomere protection by the PI3K/AKT <lb/>pathway. Nat. Commun. 8, 1278 (2017). <lb/>10. Liang, R. et al. Post-transcriptional regulation of IGF1R by key microRNAs in <lb/>long-lived mutant mice. Aging Cell 10, 1080-1088 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Cuomo and Ambrosino Cell Death and Disease (2019) 10:88 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Official journal of the Cell Death Differentiation Association </note>


	</text>
</tei>
