<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>Swimming behaviour tunes fish <lb/>polarization vision to double prey <lb/>sighting distance <lb/>Iñigo Novales Flamarique 1,2 <lb/>the analysis of the polarization of light expands vision beyond the realm of colour and intensity and is <lb/>used for multiple ecological purposes among invertebrates including orientation, object recognition, <lb/>and communication. How vertebrates use polarization vision as part of natural behaviours is widely <lb/>unknown. In this study, I tested the hypothesis that polarization vision improves the detection of <lb/>zooplankton prey by the northern anchovy, Engraulis mordax, the only vertebrate with a demonstrated <lb/>photoreceptor basis explaining its polarization sensitivity. Juvenile anchovies were recorded free <lb/>foraging on zooplankton under downwelling light fields of varying percent polarization (98%, 67%, <lb/>19%, and 0% -unpolarized light). Analyses of prey attack sequences showed that anchovies swam in <lb/>the horizontal plane perpendicular, on average, to the polarization direction of downwelling light and <lb/>attacked prey at pitch angles that maximized polarization contrast perception of prey by the ventro-<lb/>temporal retina, the area devoted to polarization vision in this animal. Consequently, the mean prey <lb/>location distance under polarized light was up to 2.1 times that under unpolarized conditions. All <lb/>indicators of polarization vision mediated foraging were present under 19% polarization, which is within <lb/>the polarization range commonly found in nature during daylight hours. these results demonstrate: <lb/>(i) the first use of oriented swimming for enhancing polarization contrast detection of prey, (ii) its <lb/>relevance to improved foraging under available light cues in nature, and (iii) an increase in target <lb/>detection distance that is only matched by polarization based artificial systems. <lb/></front>

			<body>Besides colour and intensity, light has another physical attribute that some animal visual systems can detect <lb/>termed its polarization 1 . The polarization of light refers to the dominant electric field direction of the ensemble <lb/>of photons that comprise it. If all the photons from a light source oscillate in the same plane, light is termed 100% <lb/>linearly polarized in that plane (the E-vector plane). In contrast, light without a preferred plane of electric field <lb/>oscillation, like that emitted by the sun, is unpolarized or 0% polarized. Unpolarized light becomes partially <lb/>polarized in multiple ways including scattering by particles in the atmosphere and water and reflections from <lb/>smooth surfaces 2 . This provides additional visual cues that can be used to improve the contrast of targets or for <lb/>orientation and navigation, as is the case for various invertebrates 2,3 . <lb/>As opposed to the retinal photoreceptors found in invertebrates, which differentially absorb naturally incident <lb/>light on the retina as a function of polarization 2-4 , a phenomenon known as axial dichroism, those of vertebrates <lb/>have no equivalent preferred axial absorbance. As such, polarization sensitivity in vertebrates, except in a group <lb/>of anchovies in the family Engraulididae 5-9 , does not have a demonstrated mechanistic foundation at the photore-<lb/>ceptor level and is highly controversial 10 . An exception to the lack of axial dichroism of vertebrate photoreceptors <lb/>is found in the retinas of anchovies 11 . These animals have unique cone photoreceptors in that their outer segments <lb/>consist of lamellae (i.e., the lipid bilayers which house the visual pigments) parallel to their lengths 5-9 . Because <lb/>absorbance is restricted to the plane of the lamellae 11 , these photoreceptors are axially dichroic. <lb/>Two types of cone, a long cone with cuneate outer segment and a short cone with bilobed outer segment, alter-<lb/>nate with orthogonal lamellar disposition between them forming axially dichroic rows that are primarily restricted <lb/>to the ventro-temporal retina in the northern anchovy and other anchovy species (Fig. 1) 7-9 . Other areas of the <lb/>retina in the northern anchovy have cones with regular lamellar disposition, i.e., transverse to the length of the cell 12 . <lb/>The two types of axially dichroic cones house a middle wavelength sensitive visual pigment with statistically similar <lb/>wavelength of maximum absorbance (λ max ) 10,13 . The remainder of the retina has at least two visual pigments among <lb/>the cone population with λ max in the middle and long wavelength regions of the spectrum 10,13 . <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Department of Biological Sciences, Simon Fraser University, Burnaby, British Columbia, V3J 4M5, Canada. <lb/>2 Department of Biology, University of Victoria, Victoria, British Columbia, V8W 2Y2, Canada. Correspondence and <lb/>requests for materials should be addressed to i.n.f. (email: inigo@sfu.ca) <lb/>Received: 30 July 2018 <lb/>Accepted: 7 December 2018 <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/>opeN <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>In the northern anchovy, Engraulis mordax, optic nerve recordings show that the ventro-temporal area of the <lb/>retina comprising axially dichroic cones exhibits polarization sensitivity but lacks colour sensitivity, as judged by <lb/>a single peak, at 520 nm, spectral sensitivity function 10 . The rest of the retina shows a two peak spectral sensitivity <lb/>Figure 1. Characteristics of the anchovy retina and illustrations of prey capture behaviour and measured <lb/>variables. (a) Retinal flat mount superimposed on the head of a northern anchovy showing the polarization-<lb/>sensitive area in the ventro-temporal retina with axially dichroic cones. This area appears green due to <lb/>reflectance by stacks of plates associated with the outer segments of the long cones. The blue circle depicts the <lb/>location of the lens. The arrow points to the embryonic fissure, which extends from the ventral periphery to the <lb/>centre of the retina (location of the optic nerve head) and points toward the temporal retina. In this (typical) <lb/>retina, the field of view associated with the polarization sensitive area expands 100-167° of the trigonometric <lb/>circle (or 13-80° from the horizontal). (b) Radial cryosection showing the disposition of the axially dichroic <lb/>cones and associated diagrams illustrating the orientation of the lamellae in the long cone (lc) and short cone <lb/>(sc). The long cone has a cuneate outer segment flanked by stacks of platelets (pl) on the ventral and dorsal <lb/>sides (one such set is shown). Each long cone inner segment is squeezed between opposite lobes of adjacent <lb/>bilobed outer segments of two short cones. The rightmost diagram shows the disposition of lamellae looking <lb/>down on the retina. In the area of highest cone density, the long cone lamellae are approximately parallel to the <lb/>horizontal whereas those of the short cone are oriented vertically. The cross-hatched areas denote regions of <lb/>overlap between the two outer segment types. (c) Schematic of an eye-cup showing the approximate region of <lb/>the ventro-temporal retina with axially dichroic cones (in green) and the disposition of the lamellae of a long <lb/>cone with associated flanking short cones [same depiction as in (b)] in two areas of the retina. (d) Northern <lb/>anchovy illustrating the pitch (elevation) angle. (e) Two prey capture silhouette sequences obtained under <lb/>unpolarized light (top) and 98% polarization (bottom). In each sequence, the leftmost silhouette (1) shows <lb/>the fish immediately prior to attack initiation with associated location distance (dash line uniting the fish to <lb/>the prey, the latter represented as a dot) before correction for pitch angle, and location angle. The associated <lb/>diagrams (1-5) on the right are postures of the fish, every 0.2 seconds, after attack initiation. Silhouette 5 shows <lb/>opercular expansion at the moment of prey capture. Silhouette 4 from the top sequence and 3 from the bottom <lb/>sequence are representative of those used to estimate pitch angle. The magnification bar in (a) is 1.5 mm, 3.3 µm <lb/>for the section in (b), and 1 cm in (d). Abbreviations: N, nasal; D, dorsal; V, ventral; T, temporal directions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>function, at 500 nm and 540 nm, suggesting colour discrimination 10,14 . The spectral sensitivity findings are in <lb/>accord with the number of visual pigments and the distribution of opsin transcripts in the retina 14 . In essence, <lb/>the retina of the northern anchovy is structurally and functionally divided for polarization and colour vision in <lb/>analogy with the retina of multiple insect species and stomatopods 2 . <lb/>In a previous investigation 10 , the northern anchovy was observed to discriminate between a wide angle 100% <lb/>linearly polarized downwelling light field and an unpolarized (0% polarized) light field of the same intensity and <lb/>spectral composition. Furthermore, anchovies changed their swimming behaviour from horizontal when under <lb/>unpolarized light, to oblique loops at pitch angles above the horizontal when under 100% polarization, and the <lb/>anchovy was often oriented with its body perpendicular to the downwelling polarization. These observations <lb/>gave rise to the hypothesis that the northern anchovy may be orienting its body axis to maximize sensitivity to the <lb/>background polarization by preferential stimulation of the long cones 8,10 , thus improving polarization contrast <lb/>vision of targets in the upper frontal field, the area viewed by the polarization sensitive ventro-temporal retina <lb/>(Fig. 1) 8,10,15 . Here, this hypothesis was tested by examining the behaviour of juvenile anchovies free foraging on <lb/>saltwater tolerant Daphnia pulex, a translucent zooplankton prey. <lb/>Based on the location and extent of the polarization-sensitive area in the northern anchovy retina and <lb/>the orientation of lamellae of the axially dichroic cones 8 , a series of predictions could be advanced to test the <lb/>hypothesis of oriented swimming for improved polarization contrast of prey. First, within the area occupied <lb/>by axially dichroic cones (Fig. 1a), the region of greatest cone density is concentrated in the mid to peripheral <lb/>ventro-temporal retina 8 viewing an upper frontal field around 30°-60° in elevation (pitch) from the horizontal <lb/>and about 0-45° in azimuth from the forward direction. Thus, if high resolution polarization contrast vision were <lb/>used by the anchovy to focus on prey, the pitch angle of the body should be within the 30-60° range during the <lb/>strike phase. In contrast, this angle should be generally lower, approximating horizontal attacks, under unpolar-<lb/>ized conditions, when the visual advantage conferred by axially dichroic cones would, theoretically, diminish. The <lb/>horizontal (azimuth) angle of attack should in general be greater under unpolarized versus polarized conditions <lb/>given the limited azimuth viewing angle (~0-45°) associated with the axially dichroic cone area. Non-axially <lb/>dichroic cones are present in the upper third of the ventro-temporal retina (Fig. 1a,c) providing the polarization <lb/>independent photoreceptor input looking forward and sideways. <lb/>Second, in the area with the highest density of axially dichroic cones, the lamellae of the long cones are <lb/>approximately aligned with the horizontal direction whereas those of the short cones are aligned with the vertical <lb/>direction 8,10 (Fig. 1b,c). Because the retina is hemi-spherical, the lamellae of the long cones would primarily be <lb/>oriented perpendicular to the fish length whereas those of the short cones would approach the vertical toward <lb/>the mid-retina and above, and align with the length of the fish toward the lower ventral retina (Fig. 1c). Thus, if <lb/>swimming parallel to the water surface, maximum sensitivity by the ventral retina to a downwelling polarized <lb/>light field could be achieved by swimming perpendicular to the polarization (E-vector) direction, preferentially <lb/>activating the long cones, or by swimming parallel to the E-vector, preferentially activating the short cones. If the <lb/>polarized background were primarily in the forward direction, however, maximum sensitivity to the background <lb/>polarization would involve long cone activation, as the fish would need to swim sideways in order to preferentially <lb/>activate the short cones under this optical scenario. Swimming sideways is only associated with loss of the upside <lb/>reflex in dying anchovies (personal observation). As such, for natural behaviours, overall maximum sensitivity to <lb/>the background polarization could be achieved by swimming perpendicular to the E-vector. <lb/>Third, if polarization vision improved detection of prey by the northern anchovy, then the mean distance at <lb/>which the animal locates prey, termed the location distance 16 , should be significantly greater under polarized <lb/>versus unpolarized conditions. This is because zooplankton prey have chitineous exoskeletons that transform <lb/>the polarization of background light via scattering 17 and birefringence 16 , thereby enhancing their contrast to <lb/>a polarization-sensitive predator. Polarization sensitivity should therefore give an ecological advantage to the <lb/>anchovy in enhanced foraging. Analysis of the above variables [i.e., body axis orientation in the horizontal plane <lb/>with respect to E-vector, pitch angle of attack, horizontal (azimuth) angle of attack, and location distance] should <lb/>therefore reveal the polarization percentage that the anchovy can detect and use for enhanced prey contrast. In <lb/>surface waters inhabited by anchovies, percent polarization is commonly in the range 10-30% during daylight <lb/>hours 17,18 , depending on cloud cover, and can reach up to 67% during clear sky crepuscular periods 18 . Thus, any <lb/>use of polarization vision for foraging during daylight hours would require a threshold detection level below 30%. <lb/>In summary, this study tested whether oriented swimming constitutes a novel means of dynamically enhancing <lb/>polarization contrast vision of prey by a vertebrate and its relevance to natural behaviours. <lb/>Results <lb/>Under unpolarized light, anchovies swam randomly, on average, immediately prior to initiating attacks (Fig. 2a, <lb/>Table 1). In contrast, under the various polarizations tested (19%, 67% and 98%), swimming prior to attack initi-<lb/>ation was not random but with mean orientation perpendicular to the E-vector (Fig. 2b-d, Table 1). Thus, ancho-<lb/>vies aligned their body axes for maximum stimulation of the long cone lamellae by the downwelling polarization <lb/>(Fig. 1a,b). Analysis of the pitch (elevation) angle (Fig. 1c) associated with the attacks further reinforced this <lb/>conclusion as the mean angle under 98% polarization was 43° (Fig. 3a), which approached the median (45° ± 4°, <lb/>n = 5) of the angular range associated with the axially dichroic cone area (Fig. 1a). As the percent polarization <lb/>decreased, so did the mean pitch angle of attack, but even under 19% polarization, it was significantly greater than <lb/>under 0% polarization (Fig. 3a). <lb/>The azimuth, or horizontal, prey location angle (Fig. 1e) was on average lower for the highest polarizations <lb/>(98% and 67%) compared to the 19% polarization and to unpolarized light (Fig. 3b). This may indicate the use of <lb/>the upper third of the ventro-temporal retina, which is populated by non-axially dichroic cones, when foraging <lb/>under low percent polarizations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>The mean location distance of prey (Fig. 1e) was 1.7, 1.9, and 2.1 times greater under 19%, 67% and 98% polar-<lb/>ization, respectively, compared to that under unpolarized light, which had a mean of 58.6 mm (Fig. 3c). These <lb/>results reveal an unprecedented improvement (&gt;200%) in sighting distance of targets due to polarization vision. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The increase in location distance of targets achieved by the northern anchovy under the various downwelling <lb/>polarization fields far exceeds similar measures reported in the literature for other animals. Squid hatchlings, <lb/>for instance, improved their location distance of zooplankton prey by an average of 70% under 100% polariza-<lb/>tion over that under 0% polarization 19 whereas the same comparison led to mean increases of 22% and 13% for <lb/>juvenile rainbow trout 16 and marine stickleback 20 , respectively. For fiddler crabs, mean response distance to an <lb/>approaching target increased by 17% or 24% depending on whether the target was unpolarized or vertically polar-<lb/>ized, respectively, with respect to a horizontally polarized target, over a natural background which was 30-50% <lb/>horizontally polarized 21 . It is only for machine polarization visual systems that a comparable 2-3 fold increase in <lb/>location distance of targets has been documented 22 . <lb/>Figure 2. Angular orientation of northern anchovy to different percent polarizations. The measured E-vector <lb/>(E max ) bearing (shown as E) and percent polarization are indicated on each panel. The 0% polarization is <lb/>indicated as crossed E-vectors. See Table 1 for statistics of distributions. <lb/>Corresponding <lb/>figure <lb/>% polarization <lb/>ā (°) <lb/>SD <lb/>a (°) <lb/>R <lb/>z <lb/>u <lb/>2a <lb/>0 <lb/>178 <lb/>101 <lb/>none <lb/>11.384 <lb/>1.296 <lb/>N/A <lb/>2b <lb/>19 <lb/>210 <lb/>78 <lb/>218 <lb/>23.156 <lb/>5.362 <lb/>3.229 <lb/>2c <lb/>67 <lb/>193 <lb/>95 <lb/>190 <lb/>28.765 <lb/>8.274 <lb/>4.052 <lb/>2d <lb/>98 <lb/>185 <lb/>105 <lb/>180 <lb/>28.956 <lb/>8.384 <lb/>4.086 <lb/>Table 1. Statistical results of Rayleigh&apos;s test applied to northern anchovy double swimming angles. Symbols are <lb/>as follows: ā, mean double angle; SD, standard deviation; a, theoretical double angle; R, Rayleigh&apos;s statistic; z, <lb/>statistic for circular uniformity; u, statistic for distribution along a mean direction. The data represented by the <lb/>mean double angle are uniformly distributed around the trigonometric circle if z ≤ z 0.05,100 = 2.988. The data are <lb/>distributed along a specific mean direction (the angle a, corresponding to E min ) if u ≥ u 0.05,100 = 1.645. The panels <lb/>on Fig. 2 corresponding to each statistic are indicated on the Table. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>The northern anchovy is the first species reported to exhibit oriented swimming for the purpose of enhancing <lb/>polarization-based contrast detection of prey. This novel behaviour finds its functional equivalent in the rota-<lb/>tional movements of stomatopod eyes 23 . These crustaceans align the microvilli of two sets of photoreceptors <lb/>with orthogonal polarization sensitivity to maximize the contrast of the visual scene 23 . The anchovy achieves the <lb/>same feat but by re-orienting its body. This is accomplished by swimming in a direction that aligns the lamellae of <lb/>the long cones with the prevailing polarization, maximizing the contrast of objects that disrupt the background <lb/>Figure 3. Mean (±SD) of the prey attack variables measured as a function of percent polarization. (a) Pitch <lb/>(elevation) angle. (b) Location (azimuth or horizontal) angle. (c) Location distance. The ANOVA statistics <lb/>were as follows: F 3,399 = 150.1, p &lt; 0.0001 (pitch angle); F 3,399 = 6.437, p &lt; 0.0001 (location angle); F 3,399 = 46.14, <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 (location distance). In each graph, means designated with different numbers are statistically different. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>polarization. Body realignments but for the purpose of orientation to polarization patterns in the sky are also <lb/>carried out by multiple insect species 3,24,25 . <lb/>The low threshold percentage (≤19%) for polarization use by the northern anchovy is also unprecedented <lb/>among vertebrates. In fishes, the percent polarization threshold has only been estimated for juvenile rainbow <lb/>trout and is between 63% and 72% 16,18 . Initial reports of polarization sensitivity of freshwater sunfishes have not <lb/>been replicated 26 and, with the exception of Zenarchopterus dispar 27 , other fish species have shown either no <lb/>polarization responses 28 or only to polarizations ≥ 95% 20,29 , which far exceed the available cues in nature 17,18 . <lb/>The percent polarization threshold of the anchovy is in the range reported for crustaceans (15-30%) 30,31 , locusts <lb/>(~30%) 32 , and other insects (5-10%) 24,33 . <lb/>As has been reported for insect interneurons 2,34 , the polarization signal at the level of the optic nerve in ancho-<lb/>vies is the result of an antagonistic interaction between two photoreceptor channels (cone mechanisms) with <lb/>orthogonal polarization sensitivity 10 . The net effect of this interaction is an increase in the gain of the differ-<lb/>ential signal between the two cone mechanisms 10 . In addition, light capture by the long cone is to some extent <lb/>pre-filtered by the outer segments of the two flanking short cones (Fig. 1b) 8,11 . Capture of the transmitted hori-<lb/>zontal polarization is then enhanced by plate stacks on either side of the long cone outer segment 8 . These special-<lb/>izations result in strongest sensitivity to the background (horizontal) polarization 10 , sensed primarily by the long <lb/>cones, and minimal interference of polarization signals between cone types. Such a filtering scenario has been <lb/>demonstrated to enhance the polarization sensitivity of the cell receiving the filtered light in invertebrate photore-<lb/>ceptors 4 . Any disturbance to the horizontal polarization of the water background, like that created by zooplankton <lb/>prey, would therefore be readily detected by the anchovy. <lb/>The illumination set-up in the present study mimicked the downwelling direction under crepuscular periods <lb/>when percent polarization is at its maximum in nature 18 . In this study, the Daphnia would have scattered light and <lb/>appeared slightly darker against the downwelling background to the anchovy, and this contrast increased when <lb/>the light was polarized via oriented swimming, as shown by the results. When viewing prey horizontally, however, <lb/>prey contrast would have arisen primarily from the scattered downwelling light against the darker horizontal <lb/>background with polarization playing little to no role in the modulation of perceived contrast. In nature, juvenile <lb/>anchovies are commonly found feeding in surface waters during daylight hours. In these conditions, prey can be <lb/>imaged against a lower intensity, sidewelling background that is predominantly horizontally polarized 17,18 . This <lb/>would also allow the anchovy to maximize prey contrast using polarization but, in this case, scattered down-<lb/>welling light would make the zooplankton appear brighter against the background 17 . In summary, the northern <lb/>anchovy should be able to use polarization vision for improved contrast of zooplankton, and therefore achieve <lb/>enhanced foraging 16 , throughout the day. This would give the anchovy a competitive advantage when foraging <lb/>with other zooplanktivorous fishes, like herring and sardine, in detecting prey at greater distances and facilitating <lb/>prey selectivity. There is, indeed, increasing evidence of trophic partitioning among such mixed fish schools with <lb/>anchovies often performing selective feeding on larger taxa (e.g., cladocerans, copepods, and euphausiids) while <lb/>sardines and herring carry out filter-feeding and capture smaller, less nutritious prey 35,36 . <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Animals. Wild, young-of-the-year northern anchovy schools were caught in surface waters (&lt;10 m depth) using <lb/>a boat equipped with a purse seine net by staff from the Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife and the US <lb/>Geological Survey (Marrowstone Marine Station) and by staff from Westport Seafood Ltd (Washington State, USA). <lb/>The fish were then transported to the University of Victoria Aquatic Facility where they were held in a 5,000 l out-<lb/>door tank with circulating ocean water. The study took place during the month of August, and the fish experienced <lb/>the natural daylight cycle throughout the study. Fish measuring 5.2 cm in total length were selected from the school <lb/>for foraging experiments. It was important that there be no variation in length between fish as two individuals were <lb/>used in each experiment and the pitch angle associated with each prey attack was derived from the length of the fish <lb/>silhouette in the video (Fig. 1e) and the actual length of the fish using trigonometry. The fish were fed live Daphnia <lb/>pulex for two weeks prior to the start of experiments. These Daphnia were the progeny of a population gathered <lb/>in brackish waters near Victoria that had been selected for salt water tolerance for &gt;5 years. All animal use was <lb/>approved by the Animal Care committees of Simon Fraser University (protocol #1126B-10) and the University of <lb/>Victoria (protocol #2017-005), which abide by regulations set by the Canadian Council for Animal Care. <lb/>Imaging and illumination systems. Silhouette video photography was used to record northern anchovy <lb/>free foraging on Daphnia pulex under a full spectrum downwelling light field that varied in percent polarization. <lb/>The system was configured to record fish positions from above with a resolution of ~0.2 mm and a depth of field of <lb/>15 cm. Silhouettes of animals were achieved using a dim light emitting diode (LED) located below the aquarium <lb/>at the focal point of a 20 cm diameter collimating lens whose output traversed the aquarium. The outermost walls <lb/>of the aquarium were covered with black matte surface contact paper. The upwelling LED emission at the level <lb/>of the bottom surface of the aquarium was below the detection threshold (10 12 photons m −2 s −1 ) of a USB-2000 <lb/>spectroradiometer equipped with a UV-visible liquid light guide (0.22 NA) and cosine collector (Ocean Optics). <lb/>Projected silhouettes of the fish and prey within the field of view (a 20 cm diameter circle) were acquired with a <lb/>camera situated above the aquarium. The field of view was a minimum of 10 cm from the walls of the aquarium <lb/>reducing the probability of edge effects; only animals swimming freely in the water column were imaged and their <lb/>displacements analyzed. <lb/>The illumination consisted of a Fiber-lite MI-150 (Dolan-Jenner Industries) coupled to a UV-visible liquid <lb/>light guide (Photon Technology International) equipped with a diffuser and lens at its end. This emission was <lb/>unpolarized, as verified with irradiance measurements for different rotations of a polarizer placed after the lens. <lb/>To achieve various percent polarizations (98%, 67%, 19%, and 0%) of the same intensity and spectral content (λ: <lb/>320-800 nm; irradiance: 8.12 × 10 14 photons cm −2 s −1 ; see Supplementary Fig. S1 for sample spectral irradiance <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>at E max and E min for the 19% polarization) a holder was fitted after the lens containing a linear polarizer (HNP&apos;B, <lb/>Polaroid) and a mica quarter wave plate (Melles Griot) 30 . Percent polarizations for various rotations of the quarter <lb/>wave plate were calculated from irradiance measurements at the maximum (E max ) and minimum (E min ) planes of <lb/>polarization, the latter determined visually at the level of the aquarium with an E-vector finder (Oriel). Percent <lb/>polarization was computed as: Polarization (%) = 100 (I Emax − I Emin )/(I Emax + I Emin ), where I Emax and I Emin were the <lb/>irradiances in the E max and E min planes, respectively. <lb/>Because of the central positioning of the recording camera, the downwelling illumination was projected at an <lb/>angle of 5° with respect to the vertical and was confined, quasi-uniformly, to the central 20 cm diameter circle of <lb/>observation. Downwelling irradiance measurements on either half of the aquarium showed a difference of less <lb/>than 1%. This difference was insignificant to the orientation behaviour of the anchovy, as indicated by the results <lb/>obtained. Sidewelling irradiance measurements were below the detection threshold of the spectroradiometer, <lb/>which was similar to that of the northern anchovy as assessed using optic nerve recordings 10 . <lb/>Foraging experiments. Each experiment consisted of filming 2 new fish at a time foraging for 30 minutes <lb/>in the 30 × 30 × 30 cm glass aquarium filled to a depth of 15 cm, after 30 minutes of fish acclimation. The fish were <lb/>starved for 24 hrs prior to testing and experiments were performed during the day, i.e., during the light phase <lb/>of the animal&apos;s circadian rhythm. Prey concentration in all experiments was 5 l −1 and prey size (overall mean <lb/>Daphnia pulex carapace length ± SD: 1.1 ± 0.18 mm, n = 150) was statistically equivalent between experiments. <lb/>Anchovies searched for prey using pause-travel movements whereby the fish combined stationary periods of <lb/>scanning for prey with repositioning, swimming movements. Foraging behaviour was evaluated by measuring the <lb/>following variables associated with each attack on prey (Fig. 1d,e): angle of the body axis with respect to the dom-<lb/>inant polarization (E-vector, or E max ); pitch (elevation) angle with respect to the horizontal; horizontal (azimuth) <lb/>location angle of prey with respect to the fish; and prey location distance. The prey location angle was the angle <lb/>between the longitudinal body axis of the fish just prior to attack initiation and the line connecting the fish&apos;s ros-<lb/>trum and the position of the prey upon attack initiation (Fig. 1e). Prey location distance was defined as the distance <lb/>between the point (fish rostrum) at which the fish first reacted to the prey and the position of the prey itself (Fig. 1e), <lb/>but corrected for pitch angle. From the prey capture moment, characterized by fish opercular expansion (Fig. 1e), <lb/>the video was back-tracked to the point when the fish first spotted the prey and initiated the attack. This moment <lb/>was characterized by a quick change in the fish&apos;s head direction, increased swimming velocity, and realignment of the <lb/>body axis with the prey (Fig. 1e). The pitch angle was the angle between the body axis of the fish and the horizontal <lb/>(Fig. 1d), assessed within the first 0.5 seconds of attack initiation. All attacks within this time period had frames <lb/>showing alignment of the body axis from which an estimate of the pitch angle could be obtained using trigonometry <lb/>given the fish length of 5.2 cm. The accuracy of this estimate was assessed to ±7° from trials where the walls of the <lb/>aquarium were not blocked with matte contact paper and simultaneous filming was carried out with two additional <lb/>cameras, positioned horizontally, at right angles to the aquarium. This potential error would change the computation <lb/>of location distance by a maximum of 0.75%, which was insignificant to the statistics. <lb/>statistical analyses. A total of 100 prey attack sequences were analyzed from 5 replicate experiments per <lb/>polarization condition. None of the attacks involved interference between anchovies so that each attack was <lb/>considered an independent observation. Various statistical analyses were performed to detect any differences <lb/>in the measured variables with polarization condition. Analysis of fish orientation with respect to the domi-<lb/>nant E-vector (E max ) involved Rayleigh&apos;s test for circular uniformity. If the data were not uniformly distributed, <lb/>a V-test was carried out to determine whether there was a preferred distribution in the E min direction, i.e., per-<lb/>pendicular to E max <lb/>30 . The V test is a modification of the Rayleigh test that compares the mean directional angle <lb/>of a non-uniform distribution to a single (theoretical) angle that is expected a priori 37 . Here, the expected angu-<lb/>lar direction was E min based on activation of the long cones for maximal overall sensitivity of the fish to the <lb/>background polarization. Differences in pitch angle, location angle, and location distance between polarizations <lb/>were assessed by one-way Analysis of Variance (ANOVA) followed by Student-Neuman-Keuls and Tukey&apos;s HSD <lb/>post-hoc tests with α = 0.05. <lb/>Animal experimentation approval. All animal use was approved by the Animal Care committees of <lb/>Simon Fraser University (protocol #1126B-10) and the University of Victoria (protocol #2013-005) which abide <lb/>by regulations set by the Canadian Council for Animal Care. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Availability of Data <lb/>Supplementary Fig. S1 is included. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Shurcliff, W. A. Polarized Light, Production and Use (Harvard University Press, Cambridge, Massachusetts), 1-31 (1962). <lb/>2. Labhart, T. Can invertebrates see the e-vector of polarization as a separate modality of light? J. Exp. Biol. 219, 3844-3856 (2016). <lb/>3. Wehner, R. &amp; Labhart, T. Polarization vision in Invertebrate Vision (ed. Warrant, E. &amp; Nilsson, D. E) 291-438 (Cambridge University <lb/>Press, Cambridge, 2006). <lb/>4. Snyder, A. W. Polarization sensitivity of individual retinula cells. J. Comp. Physiol. 83, 331-360 (1973). <lb/>5. Fineran, B. A. &amp; Nicol, J. A. C. Studies of the photoreceptors of Anchoa mitchilli and Anchoa hepsetus Engraulidae with particular <lb/>reference to the cones. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B 283, 5-60 (1978). <lb/>6. Zueva, L. V. Retinal cones of the Black Sea anchovy Engraulis encrasicholus -An analyzer of polarized light in vertebrates. J. Evol. <lb/>Bioch. Physiol. 17, 420-425 (1981). <lb/>7. Heβ, M., Melze, R. R. R., Eser, R. &amp; Smola, U. The structure of anchovy outer retinae (Engraulididae, Clupeiformes) -A comparative <lb/>light-and electron-microscopy study using museum-stored material. J. Morphol. 267, 1356-1380 (2006). <lb/>8. Novales Flamarique, I. Unique photoreceptor arrangements in a fish with polarized light discrimination. J. Comp. Neurol. 519, <lb/>714-737 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:944 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>9. Kondrashev, S. L., Gnyubkina, V. P. &amp; Zueva, L. V. Structure and spectral sensitivity of photoreceptors of two anchovy species: <lb/>Engraulis japonicus and Engraulis encrasicolus. Vision Res. 68, 19-27 (2012). <lb/>10. Novales Flamarique, I. A vertebrate retina with segregated colour and polarization sensitivity. Proc. R. Soc. 284, 20170759 (2017). <lb/>11. Novales Flamarique, I. &amp; Hárosi, F. I. Visual pigments and dichroism of anchovy cones: A model system for polarization detection. <lb/>Vis. Neurosci. 19, 467-473 (2002). <lb/>12. Hárosi, F. I. &amp; Novales Flamarique, I. Functional significance of the taper of vertebrate cone photoreceptors. J. Gen. Physiol. 139, <lb/>159-187 (2012). <lb/>13. Kondrashev, S. L., Miyazaki, T., Lamash, N. E. &amp; Tsuchiya, T. Three cone opsin genes determine the properties of the visual spectra <lb/>in the Japanese anchovy, Engraulis japonicus (Engraulidae, Teleostei). J. Exp. Biol. 216, 1041-1052 (2013). <lb/>14. Savelli, I. &amp; Novales Flamarique, I. Variation in opsin transcript expression explains intraretinal differences in spectral sensitivity of <lb/>the northern anchovy. Vis. Neurosci. 35, e005 (2018). <lb/>15. Heβ, M. Triple cones in the retinae of three anchovy species: Engraulis encrasicolus, Cetengraulis mysticetus and Anchovia macrolepidota <lb/>(Engraulididae, Teleostei). Vision Res. 49, 1569-1582 (2009). <lb/>16. Novales Flamarique, I. &amp; Browman, H. I. Foraging and prey search behaviour of small juvenile rainbow trout (Oncorhynchus mykiss) <lb/>under polarized light. J. Exp. Biol. 204, 2415-2422 (2001). <lb/>17. Johnsen, S., Marshall, N. J. &amp; Widder, E. A. Polarization sensitivity as a contrast enhancer in pelagic predators: lessons from in situ <lb/>polarization imaging of transparent zooplankton. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B. 366, 655-670 (2011). <lb/>18. Novales Flamarique, I. &amp; Hawryshyn, C. W. Is the use of underwater polarized light by fish restricted to crepuscular time periods? <lb/>Vision Res. 37, 975-989 (1997). <lb/>19. Shashar, N., Hanlon, R. T. &amp; Petz, A. D. Polarization vision helps detect transparent prey. Nature 393, 222-223 (1998). <lb/>20. Zukoshi, R., Savelli, I. &amp; Novales Flamarique, I. Foraging performance of two fishes, the threespine stickleback and the Cumaná <lb/>guppy, under different light backgrounds. Vision Res. 145, 31-38 (2018). <lb/>21. How, M. J. et al. Target detection is enhanced by polarization vision in a fiddler crab. Curr. Biol. 25, 3069-3073 (2015). <lb/>22. Tyo, J. S., Rowe, M. P., Pugh, E. N. &amp; Engheta, N. Target detection in optically scattering media by polarization-difference imaging. <lb/>Appl. Opt. 35, 1855-1870 (1996). <lb/>23. Daly, I. M. et al. Dynamic polarization vision in mantis shrimp. Nat. Commun. 7, 12140 (2016). <lb/>24. Henze, M. J. &amp; Labhart, T. Haze, clouds and limited sky visibility: polarotactic orientation of crickets under difficult stimulus <lb/>conditions. J. Exp. Biol. 210, 3266-3276 (2007). <lb/>25. el Jundi, B., Smolka, J., Baird, E., Byrne, M. J. &amp; Dacke, M. Diurnal dung beetles use the intensity gradient and the polarization <lb/>pattern of the sky for orientation. J. Exp. Biol. 217, 2422-2429 (2014). <lb/>26. Lynch, E. M., Engheta, N., Rosenthal, J. M. &amp; Pugh, E. N. Lack of polarization discrimination by green sunfish. Invest. Ophthalmol. <lb/>Vis. Sci. 38, 4734 (1997). <lb/>27. Waterman, T. H. &amp; Forward, R. B. Field demonstration of polarotaxis in the fish. Zenarchopterus. J. Exp. Zool. 180, 33-54 (1972). <lb/>28. Pignatelli, V. et al. Behavioural relevance of polarization sensitivity as a target detection mechanism in cephalopods and fishes. Phil. <lb/>Trans. R. Soc. B. 366, 734-741 (2011). <lb/>29. Berenshtein, I. et al. Polarized light sensitivity and orientation in coral reef fish post-larvae. PLOS One 9, e88468 (2014). <lb/>30. Novales Flamarique, I. &amp; Browman, H. I. Wavelength-dependent polarization orientation in Daphnia. J. Comp. Physiol. A 186, <lb/>1073-1087 (2000). <lb/>31. Manor, S., Polak, O., Saidel, W. M., Goulet, T. L. &amp; Shashar, N. Light intensity mediated polarotaxis in Pontella karachiensis <lb/>(Pontellidae, Copepoda). Vision Res. 49, 2371-2378 (2009). <lb/>32. Pfeiffer, K., Negrello, M. &amp; Homberg, U. Conditional perception under stimulus ambiguity: polarization-and azimuth-sensitive <lb/>neurons in the locust brain are inhibited by low degrees of polarization. J. Neurophysiol. 105, 28-35 (2011). <lb/>33. von Frisch, K. The dance language and orientation of bees (Harvard University Press, Boston, Massachusetts, 1967). <lb/>34. Labhart, T. J. Polarization-opponent interneurons in the insect visual system. Nature 331, 435-437 (1988). <lb/>35. van der Lingen, C. D., Hutchings, L. &amp; Field, J. G. Comparative trophodynamics of anchovy Engraulis encrasicolus and sardine <lb/>Sardinops sagax in the southern Benguela: are species alternations between small pelagic fish trophodynamically mediated? Afr. J. <lb/>Mar. Sci. 28, 465-477 (2006). <lb/>36. Rumolo, P. et al. Spatial variations in feeding habits and trophic levels of two small pelagic fishes in the central Mediterranean Sea. <lb/>Mar. Env. Res. 115, 65-77 (2016). <lb/>37. Zar, J. H. Biostatistical analysis (Prentice Hall, New Jersey, 1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>I thank Taylor Frierson and Dayv Lowry (Washington Department of Fish and Wildlife), Paul Hershberger, <lb/>Jacob Gregg and Ashley Mackenzie (US Geological Survey at Marrowstone Marine Station), and Mike Cornman <lb/>(Westport Seafood Inc.) for donating the anchovies and Lisa Grebinsky for assistance with the behavioural work. <lb/>This work was supported with Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada (NSERC) grant <lb/>238886 to I.N.F. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37632-1. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests: The author declares no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2019 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
