<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/> the role of metalloproteases in <lb/>fertilisation in the ascidian Ciona <lb/>robusta <lb/>shiori Nakazawa 1,2 , Maki shirae-Kurabayashi 1 &amp; Hitoshi sawada 1 <lb/>In the ascidian Ciona robusta (formerly C. intestinalis type A), the mechanism underlying sperm <lb/>penetration through the egg investment remains unknown. We previously reported that proteins <lb/>containing both an astacin metalloprotease domain and thrombospondin type 1 repeats are abundant <lb/>in the sperm surface protein-enriched fraction of C. robusta. Here we investigated the involvement <lb/>of those proteins in fertilisation. We refined the sequences of astacin metalloproteases, confirmed <lb/>that five of them are present in the sperm, and labelled them as tunicate astacin and thrombospondin <lb/>type 1 repeat-containing (Tast) proteins. Fertilisation of C. robusta eggs was potently inhibited by a <lb/>metalloprotease inhibitor GM6001. The eggs cleaved normally when they were vitelline coat-free or <lb/>the inhibitor was added after insemination. Furthermore, vitelline coat proteins were degraded after <lb/>incubation with intact sperm. These results suggest that sperm metalloproteases are indispensable <lb/>for fertilisation, probably owing to direct or indirect mediation of vitelline-coat digestion during sperm <lb/>penetration. TALEN-mediated knockout of Tast genes and the presence of GM6001 impaired larval <lb/>development at the metamorphic stage, suggesting that Tast gene products play a key role in late <lb/>development. <lb/></front>

			<body>Egg fertilisation is key to achieving genetic diversity in the next generation. In most animals, the eggs are covered <lb/>with an acellular investment called the egg coat, also called the vitelline coat (VC) in some marine invertebrates, <lb/>including ascidians and zona pellucida in mammals. The egg investment protects the eggs from mechanical dam-<lb/>age and interspecific crossing, in addition to serving as a barrier against the sperm of even the same species. <lb/>Sperm are therefore equipped with specialised systems to recognise and penetrate the egg coat. This includes a <lb/>lytic agent which acts against the egg coat, referred to as lysin. <lb/>The ascidian Ciona robusta (Formerly C. intestinalis type A; see Brunetti et al. 1 and Pennati et al. 2 for details; <lb/>note that it is still referred to with the former name in NCBI Protein database and some publications) is a model <lb/>organism for exploring the mechanisms underlying fertilisation owing to the easy acquisition of mature gam-<lb/>etes, the established database and the 3-month life span. We have previously performed proteomic analyses of <lb/>sperm-surface proteins and those released from the sperm 3 to document the sperm proteins that would mediate <lb/>gamete interactions in C. robusta. Proteins containing both an astacin metalloprotease domain and thrombos-<lb/>pondin type 1 repeats were abundant in the sperm-surface protein-enriched fraction prepared by labeling sperm <lb/>with a cell-impermeable biotinylating agent followed by affinity purification with avidin. <lb/>The role of sperm-based astacin metalloproteases in reproduction remains unclear, with the only exception of <lb/>Semp1 4 , which is the seminal-fluid protease in Drosophila melanogaster. Semp1 processes the ovulation hormone <lb/>ovulin and the sperm storage protein Acp36DE in the female reproductive tract 4,5 . <lb/>In the ascidian Halocynthia roretzi, the ubiquitin-proteasome system is thought to mediate the digestion of the <lb/>VC by the sperm 6 , but its relevance in C. robusta remains unclear. Although the abundance of astacin metallopro-<lb/>teases on the sperm surface of C. robusta suggests that the proteins play an essential role in gamete interaction, no <lb/>astacin family metalloprotease has been shown to be involved in fertilisation as a spermatic factor. Therefore, we <lb/>aimed to elucidate the function of C. robusta metalloproteases in fertilisation. <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Sugashima Marine Biological Laboratory, Graduate School of Science, Nagoya University, 429-63 Sugashima, <lb/>Toba, 517-0004, Mie, Japan. 2 Present address: Hitachi, Ltd., Research &amp; Development Group, Akanuma, Hatoyama, <lb/>Hiki, Saitama, Japan. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to S.N. (email: s-nakazawa@ <lb/>nagoya-u.jp) or H.S. (email: hsawada@bio.nagoya-u.ac.jp) <lb/>Received: 8 August 2018 <lb/>Accepted: 12 December 2018 <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/>opeN <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>Results <lb/>GM6001 affects fertilisation. Putative metalloproteases belonging to the astacin superfamily were abun-<lb/>dant in the surface protein-enriched fraction of C. robusta sperm, as mentioned earlier 3 . To check the role of <lb/>metalloproteases in fertilisation, C. robusta eggs were inseminated in the presence of the following metallopro-<lb/>tease inhibitors (experiments are briefly described in Fig. S1): wide-spectrum metalloprotease inhibitor GM6001, <lb/>inhibitory activity-free analogue GM6001NC, aminopeptidase-selective inhibitor bestatin, and thermolysin-se-<lb/>lective and bacterial metalloprotease-selective inhibitor phosphoramidon (Fig. 1). Most eggs (no inhibitor: 385 <lb/>cleaved eggs/439 total eggs, 87.7% egg cleavage; GM6001NC: 320/338, 94.7%; bestatin: 409/428, 95.6%; phospho-<lb/>ramidon: 208/224, 92.9%) underwent cleavage, and few (0/364, 0.0% egg cleavage) that were inseminated in the <lb/>presence of GM6001 achieved cleavage at a concentration of 25 μM (Fig. 1a,b). Most eggs exposed to inhibitors at <lb/>the same concentration after insemination (no inhibitor: 171/174, 98.3%; GM6001: 112/121, 92.6%; GM6001NC: <lb/>142/145, 97.9%; bestatin: 131/135 97.0%; phosphoramidon: 118/125, 94.4%) underwent cleavage, suggesting that <lb/>the decreased cleavage ratio was the result of inhibited fertilisation instead of egg cleavage itself. The inhibi-<lb/>tory effect of GM6001 was dose dependent (0 µM: 430 cleaved eggs/570 total eggs, 75.4% cleaved eggs; 0.2 µM: <lb/>352/461, 76.4%; 1 µM: 296/405, 73.1%; 5 µM: 278/458, 60.7%; 25 µM: 6/575, 1.0%) (Fig. 1c). To clarify whether the <lb/>inhibition occurred before or after sperm penetration through the VC, eggs deprived of the VC were inseminated <lb/>(Fig. 1d,e). VC-free eggs were cleaved after insemination in the presence of 25 μM GM6001 (73.3% egg cleavage) <lb/>and absence of it (76.9%) whereas VC-intact eggs were affected (66.9% and 0.7% egg cleavage in the absence and <lb/>presence of GM6001, respectively), indicating that GM6001 inhibited fertilisation by blocking sperm penetration <lb/>through the VC, or through a process before this stage. <lb/>Sperm-surface metalloproteases are needed for VC digestion. In order to investigate whether <lb/>sperm surface GM6001-sensitive proteases (i.e. metalloproteases) are involved in digestion of the VC, VCs <lb/>mechanically isolated from the C. robusta eggs were incubated with sperm. Incubation with sperm in the absence <lb/>of the inhibitor caused changes in the band pattern of the VC (Fig. 2a), whereas these changes were inhibited by <lb/>GM6001. Mass spectrometry identified the affected bands as VC57 and VC16, two of the major constituents of <lb/>Figure 1. GM6001 inhibited fertilisation of C. robusta eggs only in the presence of VC. (a,b) Eggs were <lb/>inseminated in the presence (left) and in the absence of inhibitors and were then exposed to inhibitors (right). <lb/>Fertilised eggs are at the 2-or 4-cell stages. (c) The dose dependency of the inhibitory effect of GM6001 on the <lb/>ratio of cleaving eggs. (d,e) Eggs with the VC intact or deprived were inseminated in the presence or absence of <lb/>GM6001 (N = 3, markers indicate independent data points, bars indicate means). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>the C. robusta VC 7 (Fig. 2b). These results suggested that sperm metalloprotease(s) are necessary for either direct <lb/>digestion of the VC or activation of the VC-digesting enzyme(s). <lb/>At least five metalloproteases are present in C. robusta sperm. We previously reported that the <lb/>most prominent metalloproteases in the sperm surface protein-enriched fraction of C. robusta were astacin family <lb/>metalloproteases: XP_002131733.1, XP_009857439.1, XP_002119895.1 and BAH59283.1 (NCBI Protein data-<lb/>base) 3 . They were found to correspond with KH.C9.806, KH.C1.618, KH.C1.533 and KH.C1.493 respectively <lb/>in the KH2012 gene model by BLAST search on the Aniseed database. Another putative protein with an astacin <lb/>domain and thrombospondin type 1 repeats, KH.C1.332, was also found in the KH2012 gene model. <lb/>These five proteins were cloned, and their sequences were confirmed. The refined sequences are shown <lb/>in Fig. S2 and were designated in the NCBI Protein database (accession numbers: MH108630, MH108631, <lb/>MH108632, MH108633 and MH108634). The predicted domain compositions based on the refined sequences <lb/>(Fig. 3) showed striking similarity to each other, possessing one astacin family metalloprotease domain (except <lb/>C1.332; the subtype of its zinc metalloprotease domain was not identified) followed by two or three thrombos-<lb/>pondin type 1 repeats. No signal sequence, transmembrane region or consensus for an anchor was detected. <lb/>The mass spectra acquired from the sperm-surface protein-enriched fraction 3 were re-searched against a data-<lb/>base consisting of these five refined sequences. All the five proteins were detected (Fig. S3) in both intact and <lb/>Figure 2. Digestion of the VC by the sperm was inhibited by GM6001. (a) Isolated VC and intact sperm of <lb/>C. robusta were incubated together in the absence or presence of GM6001. Changes in the intensity caused by <lb/>sperm were observed in the five labelled bands (1-5), all of which were cancelled by the addition of GM6001. <lb/>These bands in lanes 3 and 4 were analysed by mass spectrometry. The full-length gel image is available in <lb/>Fig. S6. (b) The top hit proteins detected from the bands and their protein scores (Mascot ver 2.4.1). <lb/>Figure 3. The domain compositions of C. robusta Tast gene products predicted by NCBI Conserved Domain <lb/>Search. Detected conserved motifs with the E-values less than 1E-04 are shown. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/></note>

			<body>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/>ionomycin-treated sperm, indicating that these proteins are probably present on the surface of the C. robusta <lb/>sperm, before and after sperm activation. <lb/>C9.806 was coded in chromosome 9, and C1.533, C1.618, C1.493 and C1.332 formed a gene cluster in chro-<lb/>mosome 1 (Fig. 4), and the predicted amino acid sequences of C1.533, C1.618, C1.493 and C1.332 showed higher <lb/>similarity to each other than to that of C9.806 (Fig. S2). <lb/>Proteins with the same domain composition (CBY07040.1, CBY10777.1, CBY14419.1, CBY19488.1, <lb/>CBY21110.1, CBY32407.1 and CBY35258.1) were found to be present in the appendicularian Oikopleura dioica <lb/>but not in vertebrates by using BLAST search in the NCBI Protein database. Therefore, we labelled these proteins <lb/>as tunicate astacin domain and thrombospondin type 1 repeats-containing (Tast) proteins. C9.806 was labelled <lb/>Tast1, and C1.533, C1.618, C1.493 and C1.332 were respectively labelled Tast2a, Tast2b, Tast2c and Tast2d <lb/>according to the order in which they are encoded in the gene cluster (Fig. 4). <lb/>Metalloproteases are essential for post-embryonic viability. To examine the involvement of Tast <lb/>proteins in fertilisation, TALEN-mediated knockout was performed. The TALEN pairs (Fig. S4) were designed <lb/>to target the first or second exons of Tast1, Tast2a and Tast2d with a single knockout aimed for Tast1 and a <lb/>cluster-wide knockout for Tast2a, Tast2b, Tast2c and Tast2d. The TALEN pairs resulted in a high efficiency of <lb/>mutagenesis (Fig. S4d-f); however, the mutated larvae went through an apparently impaired development during <lb/>the metamorphic stage (Fig. 5a). In addition, the effect of GM6001 and expression of Tast genes during develop-<lb/>ment were examined in order to address the possibility that metalloproteases, or Tasts, take part in development. <lb/>Wild type fertilised eggs incubated in the presence of GM6001 showed failed metamorphosis (Fig. 5b), even <lb/>though they appeared normal during the earlier stages with a slight delay in hatching out (14 hpf in Fig. 5b), <lb/>slightly bent tails (18 hpf), and moderate delay in tail contraction (24 hpf). The mRNAs of Tast1, Tast2a and <lb/>Tast2d were found to be expressed during the metamorphic stage (Fig. S5). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Inhibition of fertilisation (Fig. 1) by GM6001 but not by bestatin or phosphoramidon suggests that metallopro-<lb/>tease(s) belong to bestatin-or phosphoramidon-insensitive and GM6001-sensitive subtype(s) would be required <lb/>for fertilisation. <lb/>The successful fertilisation of VC-free eggs even in the presence of GM6001 (Fig. 1d,e) suggests that the tar-<lb/>get(s) of GM6001 in fertilisation would be involved in event(s) before the sperm enter the perivitelline space, i.e. <lb/>when the sperm bind to the VC or when they penetrate the VC. <lb/>Both scenarios are plausible-inhibitors of aminopeptidase B (o-phanenthroline, bestatin and arphamenine B) <lb/>have been shown to attenuate sperm binding to the vitelline envelope in Xenopus laevis 8 . Murine ADAMTS10, a <lb/>disintegrin and metalloprotease with thrombospondin motif 10, participates in sperm adhesion to the zona pel-<lb/>lucida 9 . These studies confirm that metalloproteases on sperm serve as the receptor for the egg coat. Moreover, sea <lb/>urchin EBR1, the surface receptor for sperm expressed on the egg, also contains an ADAMTS domain 10 . It is also <lb/>significant that mouse ovastacin is an astacin family metalloprotease released from cortical granules and respon-<lb/>sible for the post-fertilisation cleavage of ZP2 11,12 , which inhibits the sperm from binding to 2-cell embryos. <lb/>Hatching enzymes, astacin family metalloproteases secreted from the hatching gland cells of the embryos of <lb/>ray-finned fishes and from amphibians, are known to digest the egg envelopes 13 . These studies indicate that asta-<lb/>cin metalloproteases play the role of lytic agents, digesting the egg envelopes for the sperm penetration. <lb/>Intact sperm of C. robusta altered the SDS-PAGE band pattern of VC57, the main VC component; these <lb/>changes in the band pattern were inhibited by GM6001 (Fig. 2). This suggests that the sperm metalloprotease(s) <lb/>either directly serve as the lysin(s) or are necessary for the activation of true lysin(s). Whether the metallopro-<lb/>teases responsible for digestion of the VC are Tast proteins or other undetected metalloproteases is still unclear. <lb/>Tasts are the most promising candidates for GM6001-mediated inhibition of fertilisation and digestion of the <lb/>VC, given that most of the metalloproteases detected in the sperm-surface protein-enriched fraction 3 were Tasts <lb/>despite at least 18 non-astacin metzincin genes being present in the C. robusta genome 14 . However, the possibility <lb/>of undetected proteases cannot be ruled out. <lb/>Previous studies have reported that metalloproteases are involved in sperm-egg fusion in Ciona spp. 15 and sea <lb/>urhcins 16 , along with playing a part in the acrosome reaction in sea urchins 17 . In these studies, metal chelators <lb/>and/or a succinyl-Ala-Ala-Phe-MCA substrates were tested. These inhibitors are not specific to metalloproteases, <lb/>and their IC 50 values were as high as 0.5-1 mM. Although our finding that VC-free eggs were fertilised in the <lb/>Figure 4. The loci of Tast genes in the genome of C. robusta (KH2012). Exons are indicated with rectangles. <lb/>Introns are shown with bent lines. The predicted ORFs are highlighted green. Arrows and labels indicate the <lb/>target sites and the names of the TALEN pairs (Fig. S4). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>presence of GM6001 did not support the involvement of metalloproteases in gamete fusion, it is still possible that <lb/>GM6001-resistant metalloproteases mediate gamete fusion. <lb/>The interference with the late development by TALEN-mediated knockout of Tast genes or GM6001 suggests <lb/>that metalloproteases, possibly Tasts, also play important roles after fertilization (Fig. 5). Expression of at least <lb/>three of the Tast genes during the metamorphic stage (Fig. S5) supports this hypothesis. Little is known about the <lb/>involvement of astacin-like metalloproteases in the development of ascidians. No va, a gene encoding an astacin <lb/>family protein is expressed maternally and zygotically in the mesenchyme of neurula-and tailbud-stage embryos <lb/>in C. intestinalis 18 . The ascidian ortholog of Tolloid is thought to be involved in the regulation of cell migration 19 . <lb/>In vertebrates, metalloproteases play an indispensable role in development; e.g. BMP-1 and tolloid-like protein <lb/>are involved in dorsal-ventral patterning and skeletogenesis 20 , and matrix metalloproteinases play a role in skele-<lb/>togenesis 21,22 . Thus, Tasts and other metalloproteases could be involved in the development of ascidians. <lb/>Figure 5. Depletion of metalloproteases caused developmental anomaly at the metamorphic stage. (a) <lb/>Examples of 6 day juveniles injected with C1.533-1 TALEN pairs (right) and their wild type siblings (left). (b) <lb/>Development of wild type fertilised eggs in the absence or presence of 25 μM GM6001. Embryos seemed normal <lb/>until the hatching was slightly delayed in embryos exposed to GM6001. Larvae in both conditions went through <lb/>tail contraction; however, only GM6001-free larvae achieved metamorphosis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>The lethality caused by the knockout of even one of the five Tast genes suggests that either these genes are <lb/>functionally differentiated and incapable of compensating each other, or that the total amount of the products <lb/>of these five genes is critical for normal development. This explains why multiple copies of the similar genes are <lb/>encoded in the genome of C. robusta. Germ line-selective knockout technique 23 will be required to avoid the <lb/>lethal effect of Tast depletion and to analyse their function in fertilisation. <lb/>Metalloproteases of Ciona spp. may also be involved in hatching considering the delayed hatching in the <lb/>presence of GM6001 (Fig. 5b) and the role of metalloprotease in the hatching of C. intestinalis 24 , as expressed <lb/>at the gastrula stage in the ectoderm 25 . The relevance of Tasts and the ascidian hatching enzyme, however, <lb/>should be further examined because the reported N-terminus sequence of the ascidian hatching enzyme <lb/>(MLNPGSILTLFLMILAGTQH) 24 currently shows no BLAST hit in the gene model of C. robusta (KH2012) and <lb/>the genome assemblies of C. robusta (KH2012) and C. intestinalis (MTP2012). <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Metalloproteases are required for sperm penetration through the VC or steps before that in fertilisation of the <lb/>ascidian C. robusta. A metalloprotease inhibitor interfered with digestion of the VC by the sperm, indicating that <lb/>sperm metalloprotease(s) should either directly cleave the components of the VC or mediate activation of the true <lb/>lysin(s). Tasts, the astacin metalloproteases with thrombospondin type 1 repeats, are the top candidates for the <lb/>responsible metalloproteases, given their abundance on the sperm surface. Furthermore, we found that metallo-<lb/>proteases are also needed later in development. The proteolytic activity, the substrates and the activator of Tasts <lb/>need further study. Genetic approaches including conditional knockout will help elucidation of the functions of <lb/>Tast genes as well. A limited taxonomic range of animals, i.e., tunicates, seem to have Tast genes on their genomes. <lb/>It would also be interesting to compare Tasts with the functional counterparts of other chordates (vertebrates and <lb/>cephalochordates) if any, or to address the evolutionary origin of Tasts in regard to their uniqueness in tunicates <lb/>after through elucidation of the functions of Tasts. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Animals. C. robusta was purchased from the National BioResource Project of MEXT (Japan). <lb/>Cloning and sequencing of Tast genes. Testis cDNA of C. robusta was prepared using SuperScript III <lb/>First-Strand Synthesis System (18080051; Thermo Fisher Scientific, Waltham, MA, USA) with an oligo (dT) 20 <lb/>primer by transcribing 0.5 μg of mRNA prepared from the testes of six adults using RNAzol RT (RN 190; <lb/>Molecular Research Center, Inc., Cincinnati, OH, USA) following the manufacturer instructions. Tast cDNAs <lb/>were amplified using Pfu DNA polymerase (M7741; Promega, Madison, WI, USA). The primers (Supplementary <lb/>Table 1) were designed on the basis of sequences designated as C9.806.v1.A.nonSL4-1, C1.618.v1.A.SL2-1, <lb/>C1.533.v1.A.ND1-1, C1.493.v1.A.SL1-1 and C1.332.v1.A.SL1-1 in the KH 2012 transcript model of C. robusta <lb/>acquired from the Aniseed database (https://www.aniseed.cnrs.fr/) and cloned into pBluescript SK(+) vector. <lb/>5′-RACE was performed to determine the 5′ terminal sequence of C1.493 as the amino acid sequence of C1.493. <lb/>v1.A.SL1-1 on the gene model was shorter at the N-terminus by about 100 residues than those of other Tast <lb/>genes. The testis cDNA was modified with an oligo (dG) overhang using terminal deoxynucleotidyl transferase <lb/>(2230 A; Takara Bio Inc., Shiga, Japan) and was amplified with PCR by using the primers shown in Supplementary <lb/>Table 2. The 5′-RACE product was cloned using TOPO TA Cloning Kit for Sequencing (450071; Thermo Fisher <lb/>Scientific). The sequences of the cloned constructs were analysed using BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing <lb/>Kit (4337455; Thermo Fisher Scientific); the primers are shown in Supplementary Table 3. <lb/>Fertilisation assay. Procedures for gamete collection and fertilization assay are illustrated in Fig. S1a-c. The <lb/>sperm were surgically harvested from the sperm duct with a micropipette. The eggs were surgically harvested <lb/>from the oviduct. After transferring them to a glass dish, they were defolliculated by passing them through a glass <lb/>pipette in filtered seawater (FSW), and washing them in it. <lb/>The suspension of defolliculated eggs in FSW was aliquoted into a 12-or 24-well dish, and they were insemi-<lb/>nated by adding 5-15 μL of 1000-or 2000-fold diluted suspension of sperm. <lb/>The inhibitors were used at a final concentration of 25 μM, unless otherwise mentioned. Each sample, includ-<lb/>ing the inhibitor-free control in the inhibition experiments, was loaded with dimethyl sulfoxide at a final concen-<lb/>tration of 0.1% (v/v). <lb/>VC-free eggs were prepared by suspending the surgically collected eggs in 2% sodium thioglycolate and 0.1% <lb/>actinase E (90002-1611; Kaken Pharmaceutical, Tokyo, Japan) in FSW and then by adding 1/20-fold volume of <lb/>1 M sodium hydroxide to the suspension, pipetting the mixture at room temperature and washing the eggs with <lb/>FSW. <lb/>TALEN-mediated knockout. Plasmids coding TALE nucleases were constructed using the Platinum Gate <lb/>TALEN Kit (1000000043: Addgene, Cambridge, MA, USA) 26 . mRNAs coding the TALE nucleases were synthe-<lb/>sised using mMESSAGE mMACHINE T7 Transcription kit (AM1344; Thermo Fisher Scientific) and injected <lb/>into dechorionated unfertilised eggs with a glass capillary at the concentration of 150 ng/μL each with rhodamine <lb/>dextran as an injection marker (Fig. S1e). <lb/>The mutagenic efficiency of TALEN pairs was examined by amplifying the target regions from the genomic <lb/>DNA extracted from a mixture of 10 tailbud larvae with primers shown in Supplementary Table 4, cloning the <lb/>products with TOPO TA Cloning Kit (450641; Thermo Fisher Scientific), performing colony PCR with M13For <lb/>and M13Rev primers, and analysing the sequence of the gel exudates after agarose gel electrophoresis using <lb/>BigDye Terminator v3.1 Cycle Sequencing Kit. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<body>Digestion assay. Experimental procedures are schematically shown in Fig. S1d. The VC of C. robusta was <lb/>isolated by repeatedly squeezing defolliculated eggs with a plastic pestle in a 1.5 mL tube, and then passing the <lb/>eggs through a 26-gauge injection needle in 0.2 × calcium-and magnesium-free artificial seawater (0.2 × CM-free <lb/>ASW; 86 mM NaCl, 2 mM KCl, 4 mM EPPS, pH 8.0) supplied with a protease inhibitor cocktail (cOmplete mini <lb/>EDTA-free, 11836170001; Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany). They were then washed in 0.2 × CM-free ASW <lb/>containing 0.005% Triton X-100 on a 40 μm nylon cell strainer (352340; Corning, Corning, NY, USA) and equil-<lb/>ibrated with FSW. <lb/>Isolated VC, a 1/200-dilute of intact sperm and 25 μM GM6001 were mixed and incubated at 4 °C in 100 μL <lb/>FSW overnight. The FSW-insoluble components were solubilised with 5 × SDS sample buffer (50% glycerol, 10% <lb/>SDS, 0.5% bromophenol blue, 0.25 M Tris-HCl pH 6.8, supplied with 1/20-fold volume of 2-mercaptoethanol), <lb/>diluted with 4-fold volume water and separated using SDS-PAGE. <lb/>Identification of the VC proteins. The selected protein bands were excised and analysed using mass spec-<lb/>trometry and database search as previously described 3 against a database consisting of the sequences of taxonomy <lb/>ID 7719 (although they are labelled C. intestinalis, most of the entries are the sequences of C. robusta) acquired <lb/>from NCBI Protein database on 22 June 2017, using Mascot ver 2.4.1 software (Matrix Science Inc., Boston, MA, <lb/>USA). <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability <lb/>The raw mass spectra and the spectra converted to mascot generic format for database search will be available <lb/>on Dryad (https://doi.org/10.5061/dryad.3kc345s). The sequences of Tast proteins will be available on the NCBI <lb/>Protein database (accession numbers: MH108630, MH108631, MH108632, MH108633 and MH108634). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Brunetti, R. et al. Morphological evidence that the molecularly determined Ciona intestinalis type A and type B are different species: <lb/>Ciona robusta and Ciona intestinalis. J. Zool. Syst. Evol. Res. 53, 186-193 (2015). <lb/>2. Pennati, R. et al. Morphological Differences between Larvae of the Ciona intestinalis Species Complex: Hints for a Valid Taxonomic <lb/>Definition of Distinct Species. PloS one 10, e0122879 (2015). <lb/>3. Nakazawa, S., Shirae-Kurabayashi, M., Otsuka, K. &amp; Sawada, H. Proteomics of ionomycin-induced ascidian sperm reaction: <lb/>Released and exposed sperm proteins in the ascidian Ciona intestinalis. Proteomics 15, 4064-79 (2015). <lb/>4. Ravi Ram, K., Sirot, L. K. &amp; Wolfner, M. F. Predicted seminal astacin-like protease is required for processing of reproductive proteins <lb/>in Drosophila melanogaster. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 103, 18674-9 (2006). <lb/>5. LaFlamme, B. A., Ram, K. R. &amp; Wolfner, M. F. The Drosophila melanogaster seminal fluid protease &apos;seminase&apos; regulates proteolytic <lb/>and post-mating reproductive processes. PLoS Genet. 8, e1002435 (2012). <lb/>6. Sawada, H., Mino, M. &amp; Akasaka, M. Sperm proteases and extracellular ubiquitin-proteasome system involved in fertilization of <lb/>ascidians and sea urchins. Adv. Exp. Med. Biol. 759, 1-11 (2014). <lb/>7. Yamada, L., Saito, T., Taniguchi, H., Sawada, H. &amp; Harada, Y. Comprehensive egg coat proteome of the ascidian Ciona intestinalis <lb/>reveals gamete recognition molecules involved in self-sterility. J. Biol. Chem. 284, 9402-10 (2009). <lb/>8. Kubo, H., Kotani, M., Yamamoto, Y. &amp; Hazato, T. Involvement of Sperm Proteases in the Binding of Sperm to the Vitelline Envelope <lb/>in Xenopus laevis. Zool. Sci. 31, 80-87 (2008). <lb/>9. Dun, M. D. et al. Investigation of the expression and functional significance of the novel mouse sperm protein, a disintegrin and <lb/>metalloprotease with thrombospondin type 1 motifs number 10 (ADAMTS10). Int. J. Androl. 35, 572-589 (2012). <lb/>10. Kamei, N. &amp; Glabe, C. The species-specific egg receptor for sea urchin sperm adhesion is EBR1, a novel ADAMTS protein. Genes <lb/>Dev. 17, 2502-2507 (2003). <lb/>11. Burkart, A., Xiong, B., Baibakov, B., Jiménez-Movilla, M. &amp; Dean, J. Ovastacin, a cortical granule protease, cleaves ZP2 in the zona <lb/>pellucida to prevent polyspermy. J. Cell Biology 197, 37-44 (2012). <lb/>12. Avella, M. A., Xiong, B. &amp; Dean, J. The molecular basis of gamete recognition in mice and humans. Mol. Hum. Reprod. 19, 279-89 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>13. Nagasawa, T. et al. Evolutionary Changes in the Developmental Origin of Hatching Gland Cells in Basal Ray-Finned Fishes. Zool. <lb/>Sci. 33, 272-81 (2016). <lb/>14. Huxley-Jones, J. et al. The evolution of the vertebrate metzincins; insights from Ciona intestinalis and Danio rerio. BMC Evol. Biol. 7, <lb/>63 (2007). <lb/>15. De Santis, R. et al. Evidence that metalloendoproteases are involved in gamete fusion of Ciona intestinalis, ascidia. Dev. Biol. 153, <lb/>165-71 (1992). <lb/>16. Roe, J. L., Farach, H. A., Strittmatter, W. J. &amp; Lennarz, W. J. Evidence for involvement of metalloendoproteases in a step in sea urchin <lb/>gamete fusion. J. Cell Biol. 107, 539-44 (1988). <lb/>17. Farach, H. A., Mundy, D. I., Strittmatter, W. J. &amp; Lennarz, W. J. Evidence for the involvement of metalloendoproteases in the <lb/>acrosome reaction in sea urchin sperm. J. Biol. Chem. 262, 5483-7 (1987). <lb/>18. Davis, S. W. &amp; Smith, W. C. Expression cloning in ascidians: isolation of a novel member of the asctacin protease family. Dev. Genes <lb/>Evol. 212, 81-6 (2002). <lb/>19. Christiaen, L., Stolfi, A. &amp; Levine, M. BMP signaling coordinates gene expression and cell migration during precardiac mesoderm <lb/>development. Dev. Biol. 340, 179-187 (2010). <lb/>20. Hopkins, D., Keles, S. &amp; Greenspan, D. The bone morphogenetic protein 1/Tolloid-like metalloproteinases. Matrix Biol. 26, 508-523 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>21. Vu, T. &amp; Werb, Z. Matrix metalloproteinases: effectors of development and normal physiology. Genes Dev. 14, 2123-2133 (2000). <lb/>22. Lemaître, V. &amp; D&apos; Armiento, J. Matrix metalloproteinases in development and disease. Birth Defects Res. C Embryo Today 78, 1-10 <lb/>(2006). <lb/>23. Yoshida, K. et al. Germ cell regeneration-mediated, enhanced mutagenesis in the ascidian Ciona intestinalis reveals flexible germ cell <lb/>formation from different somatic cells. Dev. Biol. 423, 111-125 (2017). <lb/>24. D&apos; Aniello, A., Vincentiis, M., de, Fiore, M. M., Di &amp; Scippa, S. Hatching enzyme from the sea-squirt Ciona intestinalis: purification <lb/>and properties. Biochim. Biophys. Acta 1339, 101-12 (1997). <lb/>25. Scippa, S., De Candia, A., De, Groppelli, S. &amp; De Vincentiis, M. Hatching enzyme immunolocalization during embryonic <lb/>development of the ascidians Ciona intestinalis and Phallusia mammillata. Invertebr. Reprod. Dev. 49, 121-123 (2006). <lb/>26. Sakuma, T. et al. Repeating pattern of non-RVD variations in DNA-binding modules enhances TALEN activity. Sci. Rep. 3, 3379 <lb/>(2013). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:1009 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The ascidian C. robusta was provided by the National BioResource Project. Three of the TALEN module plasmids <lb/>used in this work were kindly presented from Dr Tetsushi Sakuma and Professor Takashi Yamamoto (Hiroshima <lb/>University). We thank Dr Shunsuke Nishio (Nagoya University) and Professors Tsukasa Matsuda (Nagoya <lb/>University) and Shigeki Yasumasu (Sophia University) for their advice. This work was financially supported by <lb/>the Japan Society for the Promotion of Science 15K18862 (SN) and 25291024 (HS) and the Naito Foundation <lb/>Natural Science Scholarship (MSK). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>M.S.K. designed TALENs for Tast1, conducted TALEN-mediated knockout and revised the draft. S.N. designed <lb/>and conducted other experiments with advice from M.S.K. and H.S., wrote the main manuscript and prepared <lb/>the figures. H.S. supervised the project and made a throughout revision on the manuscript. All authors reviewed <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/>Supplementary information accompanies this paper at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37721-1. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests: The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2019 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
