<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>An adaptive fall-free rehabilitation <lb/>mechanism for ischemic stroke rat <lb/>patients <lb/>Chi-Chun Chen 1 , Ching-ping Chang 2 &amp; Chin-Lung Yang 3 <lb/>today&apos;s commercial forced exercise platforms had been validated not as a well-designed rehabilitation <lb/>environment for rats with a stroke, for the reason that rat with a stroke cannot take exercise at a <lb/>constant intensity for a long period of time. In light of this, this work presented an adaptive, fall-free <lb/>ischemic stroke rehabilitation mechanism in an animal model, which was implemented in an infrared-<lb/>sensing adaptive feedback control running wheel (IAFCRW) platform. Consequently, rats with a stroke <lb/>can be safely rehabilitated all the time, and particularly at full capacity for approximately one third of <lb/>a training duration, in a completely fall-free environment according to individual physical differences <lb/>by repeated use of an acceleration/deceleration mechanism. the performance of this platform was <lb/>assessed using an animal ischemic stroke model. the IAFCRW therapy regimen was validated to <lb/>outperform a treadmill and a conventional running wheel counterpart with respect to the reduction <lb/>in the neurobehavioral deficits caused by middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAo). IAFCRW is the first <lb/>adaptive forced exercise training platform short of electrical stimulation-assistance in the literature, <lb/>and ischemic stroke rats benefit more in terms of the behavioral tests run at the end of a 3-week <lb/>rehabilitation program after a stroke thereby. <lb/></front>

			<body>Medical expense in ischemic stroke patents has long been considered a huge burden to health care companies in <lb/>many countries, and patients often experience difficulty performing their activities of daily living 1,2 . Therefore, <lb/>an effective and completely safe rehabilitation program is seen as crucial to improve patients&apos; quality of life, and <lb/>increasing evidence has suggested that physical exercise can enhance the neurological function and motor recov-<lb/>ery after stroke 3-5 . In addition, post-ischemic stroke exercise rehabilitation has been proposed as a practical cer-<lb/>ebral stroke treatment 6-8 . Rodent, e.g. rat, injury models are frequently employed as a preliminary approach to <lb/>validating the effectiveness of physical rehabilitation methods 5,9,10 , and rats are trained at a fixed running speed <lb/>over a specified time period. These rehabilitation methods have been validated as effective in cerebral stroke <lb/>prevention 11,12 , while has been found not to be as effective in cerebral stroke rehabilitation 13,14 as in prevention. A <lb/>reason behind this is that these forced platforms are designed to train normal and healthy rats, but their training <lb/>parameters could not be directly applied to cerebral stroke rehabilitation programs. <lb/>There exist a number of limitations on today&apos;s training platforms, including treadmills and running wheels. <lb/>Rats are stimulated when they run at the end of treadmill runways, accounting for part of a physiological out-<lb/>come 15 . Therefore, treadmill data were very likely to be collected with an interference factor induced by electric <lb/>shocks. Moreover, electric shock may impose stress on or directly hurt the rats during rehabilitation 13,14 . Running <lb/>wheel platforms can be designed as either a voluntary or a motorized form. As its name indicates, rats are permit-<lb/>ted to run voluntarily on a voluntary running wheel. However, due to individual differences, this type of running <lb/>wheel platforms often yields large variations in the final results. To avoid such discrepancies, rats often needed to <lb/>be selected carefully in advance 16,17 , and voluntary running wheels were not treated as a key issue. As pointed out <lb/>in 18 , rats were afraid of running, held on to the cross bars of a wheel or even stopped running, when trained using <lb/>commercially available motorized running wheels (MRWs). In addition, commercially available running wheels <lb/>with a diameter of 35 cm and a width of 12 cm were generally too small for average sized white rats, and were <lb/>liable to cause rat patient injury 19 . In addition, it is more difficult to run on a curved runway than on a flat one, <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Department of Electronic Engineering, National Chin-Yi University of Technology, Taichung, Taiwan. 2 Department <lb/>of Medical Research, Chi Mei Medical Center, Tainan, Taiwan. 3 Department of electrical engineering, national cheng <lb/>Kung University, Tainan, Taiwan. Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to C.-C.C. (email: <lb/>chichun@ncut.edu.tw) or C.-L.Y. (email: cyang@mail.ncku.edu.tw) <lb/>Received: 8 June 2018 <lb/>Accepted: 4 December 2018 <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/>opeN <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>and rats often accidentally fell or tumble 20,21 . Therefore, this study aims to develop and then integrate an adaptive <lb/>training mechanism into a larger sized running wheel for an improved motor function recovery after stroke. <lb/>For the sake of an improved recovery quality, a training mechanism must be made adaptive together with a low <lb/>level of interference according to the physical conditions of rats during rehabilitation. Previous studies suggested <lb/>that the stress response to electrical shocks in treadmills resulted in adverse physiological injuries, such as adrenal <lb/>hypertrophy, splenic atrophy and circulating corticosterone 22-24 . For those taking a rehabilitation program, stress <lb/>response could be a destructive factor to their recovery 13 , and is as well an uncontrolled parameter that can affect <lb/>the final neurological outcomes. Therefore, it is advantageous to remove such potential disadvantages for the sake <lb/>of clinical research. This study reviewed a number of running wheel platforms that were developed to assist in <lb/>the effective recovery of rats with an ischemic stroke but short of electric shock. Utilizing an IR sensor-embedded <lb/>wheel module to detect the running position of a rat, an acceleration/deceleration mechanism was enabled herein <lb/>in such a way that rats were rehabilitated well in a completely fall-free environment, and adaptively within their <lb/>capacity for an improved motor function recovery and a reduced cerebral infarct volume. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Development of the infrared-sensing adaptive feedback control running wheel (IAFCRW) is detailed as follows. <lb/>As an IR sensor-equipped measurement apparatus, IAFCRW was designed to sense the running positions of <lb/>rats and to adaptively adjust the exercise speed. An acceleration/deceleration mechanism was built, and was <lb/>controlled by a micro-processor for stroke rat rehabilitation according to individual physical status. Then, the <lb/>effectiveness of this platform was verified with an animal ischemic stroke model. One week after middle cerebral <lb/>arterial occlusion (MCAo) surgery, the animals were assigned to three experimental groups, i.e. treadmill, MRW <lb/>and IAFCRW groups, to participate in a 3-week rehabilitation program. Finally, an inclined plane, a beam walk-<lb/>ing test and MCAo were used to evaluate their recovery outcomes. <lb/>Infrared-sensing adaptive feedback control running wheel system. A novel infrared-sensing adap-<lb/>tive feedback control running wheel system was presented herein as an extension of a piece of prior studies for an <lb/>exercise quantification of animals, such as rats 19 , and offered a fully automated adaptive and fall-free rehabilitation <lb/>environment to rat patients. As illustrated in Fig. 1, it involves a computer (U1), a microcontroller (MCU) (U2), <lb/>a motor and a driver (U3) and an infrared sensing running wheel platform (U4). <lb/>U1 downloads a rehabilitation training software program to U2 through an RS-232 serial adapter. U2 is a <lb/>C8051F330 development board, using pulse-width modulation (PWM) to initiate a 10-bit digital-to-analog con-<lb/>verter (DAC) and to control the motor driver (BLED12A, Oriental Driver, Japan). The motor (BLEM512-GFS, <lb/>Oriental Motor, Japan) drives the rotation of U4. After U4 has been initiated, infrared sensors are activated to <lb/>monitor the position of a rat. <lb/>Figure 1. System architecture of the presented infrared-sensing adaptive running wheel rehabilitation platform. <lb/>Stereogram of the platform together with key features. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>The interior of the wheel can be divided into the safe and the unsafe zones. Ideally, rats could always catch <lb/>up with the running wheel, and stayed in the safe zone during rehabilitation. In practice, rats were occasionally <lb/>brought up to the unsafe zone, lost the support from the railway, and fell down consequently once unable to catch <lb/>up. As soon as the lower part of a rat&apos;s body reached the 0 degree position in Fig. 1, a deceleration mechanism was <lb/>automatically enabled by U2 as a preventive measure in IAFCRW, the rat were brought back to the safe zone, an <lb/>acceleration mechanism was enabled right away, and the wheel continued to accelerate again for uninterrupted <lb/>rehabilitation. For comparison purposes, pairs of infrared sensors were positioned in the same way as in an MRW <lb/>counterpart in the absence of any deceleration mechanism. <lb/>As illustrated in Fig. 1, U4 is mechanical drawing of the presented apparatus built in the Chimei Hospital <lb/>Laboratory. The running wheel mechanism is actually a modified version of the previously developed ISRW 19 , <lb/>but with 3 key features illustrated in the stereogram of Fig. 1. The first key feature was an improved sensitivity <lb/>of IR position sensing, the second was a rat friendly rehabilitation environment using a high-density rubber <lb/>track, and the third was an improved driving motor mounting technique using a strong spring embedded into an <lb/>L-shaped supporting iron frame on the side, as shown in Fig. 1 (U4). The infrared transmitter and sensor pair at <lb/>the 0 degree position were tubed to reduce the scattering range, and accordingly the IR sensor was trigger with <lb/>an improved sensitivity once the 0 degree position was reached by the lower part of a rat&apos;s body. Four pairs of <lb/>transmitters and sensors were equally mounted between 0 to 135 degrees, an area defined as the safe zone 19 , and <lb/>the received IR signals were delivered to an MCU through general-purpose input/output port 1 (GPIO P1). The <lb/>area beyond the 0 degree position was defined as the unsafe zone, and hence the 0 degree position was the thresh-<lb/>old between both zones. As illustrated in Fig. 2, the interior of the IARCRW can be divided into the safe exercise <lb/>zone, marked by spots 1 and 2, and the unsafe exercise zone, marked by spot 3. Once the IR sensor at the 0 degree <lb/>position was triggered by the lower part of a rat&apos;s body, the deceleration mechanism was enabled instantly, and <lb/>the rat was brought back to spot 1 safely for persistent rehabilitation, meaning that the fall-free requirement was <lb/>fulfilled. In contrast, rehabilitation on MRW inevitably resulted in injury to rats, once they were brought up to <lb/>spot 2 or even 3, since MRW was not equipped with a position detection and deceleration mechanism. Hence, it <lb/>is concluded that the IAFCRW platform was experimentally validated as a fall-free and definitely a much safer <lb/>rehabilitation environment than the MRW counterpart. <lb/>Automated adaptive acceleration and deceleration training models. For rats with a stroke, per-<lb/>sistent forced exercise for a long period of time at a fixed speed leads to less therapeutic effects than voluntary <lb/>exercise 13,14 . Therefore, an adaptive rehabilitation mechanism is required to meet the individual physical require-<lb/>ments. An automated training model was constructed by the curve fitting of manual training data on rats. This <lb/>model not only reduces human error in operations, but covers as much physical diversity as possible for injured <lb/>rats. It must be noted that a formal rehabilitation training program does not apply to the rats for the construction <lb/>of the adaptive training model. <lb/>Automated adaptive acceleration training model. Rehabilitation began one week after an MCAo sur-<lb/>gery. During the first three days of the rehabilitation program on the IAFCRW platform, rats were trained in a <lb/>Figure 2. The interior of a running wheel. Spot 2 is the threshold between the safe and the unsafe zones. Once <lb/>beyond spot 2, a rat will lose its support from the railway, and fall consequently. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>manual manner to get the raw data for model construction, were assured to get familiar with the training envi-<lb/>ronment at the onset, and the training intensity that each rat could withstand was measured as well. In the manual <lb/>mode, the running wheel was gradually accelerated. If a rat was not able to keep pace with the running wheel, <lb/>then the speed was turned down as a way to prevent the rats from being overwhelmed by the exercise and to <lb/>complete their rehabilitation. A family of dotted curves in Fig. 3(A) represented the raw data of a group of seven <lb/>rats on day 3, and a formal rehabilitation training involved another group of 30. Each rat achieved different ulti-<lb/>mate speed, although a similar exponential growth in speed was shared. A close observation on Fig. 3(A) reveals <lb/>that 5 out of 7 rats reached a speed beyond 15 m/min during the rehabilitation, but not for a long period of time, <lb/>whereas the remaining two failed, and were ruled out in the subsequent curve fitting accordingly. As the first step, <lb/>the average performance of the 5 rats, marked by circles, was presented in Fig. 3(B) with standard deviation error <lb/>bars, and the curve fitting was then performed. The other curve, marked by squares therein represents the best fit <lb/>of the acceleration model in Eq. (1), and the values of the best fit parameters A, B and τ in Eq. (1) were found to <lb/>be 12, 3 and 120, respectively. Particularly, a good model fit is indicated by an R-squared value of 0.93. The speed <lb/>curve for week 1 was slightly shifted upward as the week 2 case so as to enhance the exercise intensity, but with <lb/>the initial and the ultimate speeds fixed. Consequently, the τ value of the curve, marked by triangles, was tuned <lb/>to 100. Weeks 2-3 shared the same rising slope at t = 0, although the week 3 case had a stretch training period of <lb/>60 min. <lb/>= × − <lb/>+ <lb/>τ <lb/>− <lb/>V A <lb/>e <lb/>B <lb/>(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1) <lb/>t/ <lb/>Automated adaptive deceleration training model. As a fall prevention mechanism, a deceleration <lb/>training model is far more important than an acceleration one. A group of seven rats were involved to construct <lb/>an adaptive deceleration training mode. Beginning one week after the MCAo surgery, a 3-day test was performed <lb/>to construct the adaptive deceleration model. A family of deceleration curves in Fig. 4(A) were treated as can-<lb/>didates to best describe the deceleration characteristics of rats after reaching the danger zone. First, a linear <lb/>deceleration model, marked by squares, was described by Eq. (2) with the parameters A and B set to 375 and 25, <lb/>respectively, and gives a deceleration of 2.4 m/s 2 together with an R-squared value of 0.84. The other curves were <lb/>tested by turns leftward, and the leftmost curve, marked by circles, was found to best fit the raw deceleration data. <lb/>The best fit exponential decay model was described by Eq. (3) with A, B and τ set to 12, 3 and 20, respectively, and <lb/>gives an R-squared value of 0.88. The wheel decelerated rapidly, but not abruptly, to below 6 m/min within 30 s, <lb/>for safety concern of rats, as a way to avoid falling forward. Superimposed on Fig. 4(B) for comparison purposes, <lb/>the best fit curve gives an average deceleration of 18.75 m/s 2 over the time interval (0, 30) using Eq. (4), while <lb/>substitution of the raw deceleration data between 170 and 230 s, highlighted in dotted blue, into Eq. (5) gives an <lb/>average deceleration of 18.44 m/s 2 . There is a good agreement between the manual and the best fitted average <lb/>decelerations, that is, an error as low as 1.6% is found using Eq. (6). In other words, this accounts for a superior <lb/>R-squared value in the best fit exponential decay model than the linear one. <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>V t <lb/>A t B <lb/>( ) ( <lb/>)/ <lb/>(2) <lb/>= × <lb/>+ <lb/>τ <lb/>− <lb/>V t <lb/>A <lb/>e <lb/>B <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(3) <lb/>t/ <lb/>τ <lb/>= ′ = × <lb/>× − <lb/>τ <lb/>− <lb/>m <lb/>V t <lb/>A <lb/>e <lb/>t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) ( / ) <lb/>(4) <lb/>automated <lb/>t/ <lb/>Figure 3. Adaptive acceleration curve construction. (A) The dotted curve represents the raw data on day 3 of a <lb/>manual rehabilitation training program one week after MCAo surgery. (B) The curve, marked by squares, is the <lb/>adaptive acceleration training curve best fitted to the averaged raw data, marked by circles, for week 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>= <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>m <lb/>V t <lb/>V t <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>(5) <lb/>manual <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>× <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>100% <lb/>(6) <lb/>error <lb/>automated <lb/>m anual <lb/>automated <lb/>software. The presented fall-free rehabilitation mechanism is implemented as a software program running <lb/>on a microcontroller. The main program flow is shown in Fig. 5(A), and the three interrupt service routine pro-<lb/>cesses are shown in Fig. 5(B-D). The main program was responsible for system initialization, danger zone iden-<lb/>tification and adaptive deceleration model initiation. The three interrupted service routine programs comprised <lb/>adaptive acceleration model initiation, position detection and danger zone signal triggering. The operational <lb/>architecture of the entire program could be divided into five parts. Part 1 consists of the initial establishment of <lb/>the global variables and internal microcontroller registers. These registers include input and output (I/O port) <lb/>pins, a basic time interval interrupt, an external interrupt trigger, RS-232 transmission rate (115,200 bps) and a <lb/>DAC (Fig. 4(A)). Part 2 initializes the acceleration training model (Fig. 5(B)), using the Timer 0 interrupt service <lb/>routine. Part 3 reads and records four sets of infrared sensing signals, using the Timer 1 interrupt service routine <lb/>(Fig. 5(C)). These signals are connected to the P1 register I/O port. Real-time monitoring on rat positions during <lb/>the trial can be read from the P1 register (Fig. 5(C)). Part 4 detects the danger zone, i.e. the 0 degree position, <lb/>using an external interrupt service routine. When a rat reaches the danger zone, this interrupt is triggered to set <lb/>up a danger zone flag (IR_flag = 1) (Fig. 5(D)). Part 5 determines whether the danger zone flag has been set. Once <lb/>set, the deceleration training model will be enabled instantly to slow down the running wheel for rat protection <lb/>(Fig. 5(A)). <lb/>experimental animals. The experimental animals, weighing approximately between 270-320 g and pro-<lb/>vided by the National Laboratory Animal Center, Taiwan, were Sprague-Dawley male rats. A group of seven <lb/>rats were involved to construct an adaptive deceleration training mode, and another group of 30 got involved <lb/>in a rehabilitation program. The rats were maintained in an air conditioned animal chamber, and the chamber <lb/>temperature was set at 24 ± 1 °C. A light/dark cycle of 12 hours with lights turned on at 6 am and off at 6 pm <lb/>was used, and unlimited water and feed were provided. All of the experiments were conducted in the daytime <lb/>condition under light. The experimental procedures were approved by the animal ethics committee of Chi Mei <lb/>Medical Center, Ministry of Science and Technology, Taiwan. All methods were performed in accordance with <lb/>the approved guidelines and regulations. <lb/>experimental groups and exercise training. First, the rats were randomly divided into the following five <lb/>groups: IAFCRW (n = 10), treadmill (n = 10), MRW (n = 10), sham (n = 10), and control (n = 10) groups. MCAo <lb/>surgery was performed for all of the groups except the sham group, and exercise rehabilitation training was not <lb/>provided for the sham and the control groups. The exercise training groups (IAFCRW, treadmill and MRW) took <lb/>a three-week rehabilitation training program one week after a surgically triggered stroke. During weeks 1-2, the <lb/>treadmill and MRW groups received a 30 min training at a speed of 20 m/min five days per week. During week 3, <lb/>the training duration was extended to 60 min but at the same speed 25,26 . However, the IAFCRW group received <lb/>exercise training using the acceleration and deceleration models developed in this study. Thus, the treadmill and <lb/>Figure 4. A family of deceleration curves. (A) A family of deceleration training curves for curve fitting, (B) <lb/>superposition of the best fit curve in (A) onto the raw data in Fig. 3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>MRW groups took fixed-speed rehabilitation training, whereas the IAFCRW group had no choice but to receive <lb/>a time-varying speed counterpart during the rehabilitation exercise. As illustrated in Fig. 6, the day that MCAo <lb/>or Sham surgeries were performed was viewed as a point of reference, represented as Day 0, and all the motor <lb/>function assessments, including mNSS, incline plane and beam balance tests, were conducted a day before and <lb/>Figure 5. A software program on a microcontroller. (A) Main program flow of a microcontroller. (B) <lb/>Flowchart of timer 0 service routines of the microcontroller. (C) Flowchart of timer 1 service routines of the <lb/>microcontroller. (D) Flowchart of external interrupt 0 service routine of the microcontroller. <lb/>Figure 6. Experimental timeline of the rehabilitation process for ischemic stroke to compare the performance <lb/>among the treadmill, MRW and IAFCRW platforms. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>on a weekly basis after the surgeries, that is, Days -1, 7, 14, 21 and 28, for comparison purposes. The rats were <lb/>sacrificed after the 3-week training program, and the infarct volume was obtained using the triphenyltetrazolium <lb/>chloride (TTC) method. <lb/>Middle cerebral artery occlusion (MCAo). The induction procedure of an MCAo surgery was based on <lb/>Longa&apos;s brain endovascular occlusion method 27 . Rats were anesthetized with intraperitoneal injection of Ketamine <lb/>(50 mg/kg; Nankuang Pharmaceutical, Tainan, Taiwan), Atropine (0.03 mg/kg; Sintong Chemical, Taoyuan City, <lb/>Taiwan) and Xylazine (10 mg/kg; Bayer AG, Leverkusen, Germany) cocktail. If required and depending on a <lb/>reflex withdrawal response and breathing rate, an additional dose of the KAX cocktail (i.p.) was administered to <lb/>maintain anesthesia. Body core temperature was thermostatically maintained at 37 °C with a feedback-controlled <lb/>heating pad (PhysioSuite, Kent Scientific, Torrington, CT, USA) during surgery. After the rats were anesthetized, a <lb/>midline incision was performed at the neck to expose the left common carotid artery (CCA), the external carotid <lb/>artery (ECA) and the internal carotid artery (ICA). A white suture was used to tie the left CCA and the ECA. <lb/>Then, a 4-0 monofilament nylon suture (Doccol Corporation, Redlands, CA, USA) was inserted into the ECA <lb/>and then the ICA, until the middle cerebral artery (MCA) was blocked to induce a cerebral ischemic stroke. Sixty <lb/>minutes later, reperfusion was achieved by withdrawal of the suture. The sham group only received operations <lb/>involving ECA and ICA isolation without ligation. To relieve pain and discomfort in the postoperative period, <lb/>topical 2% Lidocaine gel (Astra-Zeneca Pharmaceuticals, Wilmington, DE, USA) was applied on the wound, and <lb/>Carprofen (5 mg/kg; YUNGSHIN PHARM IND. CO. LTD. Taichung, Taiwan) was injected subcutaneously for <lb/>postoperative analgesia immediately after surgery and then daily, until the fifth postoperative days. <lb/>Successful ischemia during MCA occlusion was confirmed by reduction in cerebral blood flow (CBF) down to <lb/>20% of the original level using an OxyLite/OxyFlo (Oxford Optronics Ltd., Oxford, UK) fiber-optic laser Doppler <lb/>system. Exclusion criteria were as stated follows: insufficient MCAo (a reduction in CBF to &gt;20% of the baseline <lb/>value), rats that died before the end of MCAo surgery, and without induction of brain ischemia (infarction) as <lb/>quantified by TTC stain. Behavioral tests, as will be detailed below, were conducted as motor function assess-<lb/>ments on all the animals by two investigators who were blinded to the experimental groups. <lb/>Behavioral tests. For baseline performance and testing, animals were acclimatized to a testing room and <lb/>experimental devices. One week before surgery, rats were placed, and freely walked on an inclined plane and a <lb/>beam. Three days before surgery, rats were pre-trained to grab the inclined plane and traverse, but not fall off, the <lb/>beam. If any of them failed the pre-training, it was excused before the group assignment. <lb/>Modified neurological severity score. The modified neurologic severity scores (mNSSs) 28 is commonly used to <lb/>assess the motor, sensory, reflex and balance function of testees, and it was conducted here on each testee before <lb/>and after MCAO surgery. A testee scored a point in case it failed a task, mNSS was consequently rated on a scale <lb/>of 0 to 18, and a more severe neural impairment is indicated by a higher mNSS. Baseline readings on Day −1 were <lb/>used as the internal controls. All the behavioral experiments were performed between 10 AM and 3 PM. <lb/>Inclined plane test. An inclined plane test is a quantitative, objective and high sensitivity approach to assessing <lb/>the gripping strength of the hindlimbs of rats after ischemic stroke 29 . The evaluation was primarily conducted to <lb/>test the lasting grip strength of the forelimbs or hindlimbs in rats on a weekly basis. The inclined plane used in this <lb/>study was constructed of a 60 cm × 60 cm incline adjustable acrylic panel. A motor and a ball screw were used to <lb/>control the inclined angle of the acrylic plane from 0 (horizontal) to 70 degrees 29 . A rectangular box was placed <lb/>on the acrylic plane to initially hold a rat, and a layer of Velcro was attached to the bottom of the box to allow the <lb/>rat to grip with its fore or hindlimbs. This experimental process involved placing the rats in the rectangular box <lb/>with their hind legs on the Velcro and fore legs on the acrylic plane. The inclined plane was slowly raised starting <lb/>at 25 degrees, and the angle of the inclined plane was increased in 5-degree increments to determine the maximal <lb/>angle at which a rat could hold onto the Velcro. At this point, the angle of the plane immediately stopped rising, <lb/>and the angle of inclination was recorded accordingly. <lb/>Beam balance test. Motor coordination was evaluated in a quantitative manner using a beam balance test. The <lb/>apparatus was as simple as the surface of an elevated wooden beam ((100 cm (L) × 5 cm (W) × 2 cm (H)) at a <lb/>height of 10 cm from the ground. The number of times that a testee fell off the beam was recorded, and the perfor-<lb/>mance was rated on a scale of 0 to 6. As tabulated in Table 1 30 , zero point represents &quot;balances with steady posture <lb/>and successfully reaching the goal box&quot;, while 6 points represents fall off within a 20 s duration. Three trials were <lb/>performed on each testee. The testees took a 10-min break in their home cages between trails. The final beam <lb/>balance score was defined as the mean of the scores received in the three trials. In short, the higher the score, the <lb/>poorer the balance performance. <lb/>Assessing cerebral infarction. The determination of brain infarction by triphenyltetrazolium chloride <lb/>(TTC) staining is commonly used in rats with a stroke 13 . Four weeks after the MCAo, all of the rats were sacri-<lb/>ficed, and their brains were carefully removed. A brain slicer was used to cut the brain coronal sections at a width <lb/>of 2 mm from the top front brain. The fresh brain slices were incubated in 2,3,5-TTC at 37 °C for 30 min. The <lb/>TTC-stained slices were observed under a microscope to determine the infarct volume caused by ischemic stroke <lb/>in the rats. Normal cells appeared red after staining, whereas necrotic cells appeared white. To minimize the error <lb/>introduced by edema and liquefaction after infarction, a corrected percentage of infarct volume 31 was achieved <lb/>using the following equation: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>= <lb/>− <lb/>× <lb/>. <lb/>Corrected percentage of infarct volume (CIV%) <lb/>{(contralateral hemispheric volume <lb/>ipsilateral noninfarcted volume)/contralateral hemispheric volume} 100 <lb/>statistical analysis. All values are presented as mean ± standard error of mean (SD). Statistical analyses <lb/>were performed using SigmaPlot 11.0 (Systat Software Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). To test the treatment effect on each <lb/>of the behavioral tests, we used the repeated measures analysis of variance (ANOVA) followed by Mann-Whitney <lb/>U comparisons. For infarction volume was assess by ANOVA followed by Fisher&apos;s least significant difference <lb/>(LSD) post-hoc test. If there was a significant difference, a Student&apos;s t-test was used to compare variables for two <lb/>groups. P values less than 0.05 was considered to be statistically significant. <lb/>ethics approval and consent to participate. The statements on Ethics approval and consent to partici-<lb/>pate in the study are reported in the Methods-Experimental animals section. <lb/>Results <lb/>Motor function. Behavior test is known to be used to determine the severity of neurological motor dys-<lb/>function in rats after a stroke or MCAo. A higher average score in either the mNSS or a beam walking test, or a <lb/>smaller inclination angle in an inclined plane test, indicates a more severe ischemic stroke injury. As illustrated <lb/>in Fig. 7(A,B), the IAFCRW group was found to outperform the rest of the lesioned groups in terms of the <lb/>average score received in the mNSS and the beam walking test over the 28-day period after injury. As illus-<lb/>trated in Fig. 7(C), the sham group gives an inclination angle of 60 ± 0.5 degrees, the highest among groups and <lb/>a figure far beyond 50 ± 0.5 degrees in the control group. Moreover, the IAFCRW group received an angle of <lb/>56 ± 0.25 degrees on day 28, and significantly outperformed the treadmill and MRW groups. More importantly, <lb/>the IAFCRW group was the only exercise group showing a significant recovery via stroke rehabilitation on day <lb/>28 after stroke. No significant difference was observed among the other two exercise groups (treadmill (52 ± 0.5 <lb/>degrees) and MRW (51 ± 0.5 degrees)) and the control group. <lb/>Infarct volume. TTC staining was then used to assess the infarct volume. Figure 7(D) presents a statistical <lb/>comparison of the volume of dead brain cells among groups. As illustrated in Fig. 7(C), the infarct volumes in <lb/>the treadmill (278 ± 18 mm 3 ) and MRW (269 ± 22 mm 3 ) groups were comparable to that in the control group <lb/>(302 ± 15 mm 3 ), while the IAFCRW group gave a significantly lower cerebral infarct volume (198 ± 12 mm 3 ) than <lb/>the control group (P &lt; 0.05). <lb/>Chance of reaching the threshold. Rats with a stroke are known to have inferior motor functions and <lb/>response, meaning that once they are brought up to the 0-degree position, they are very liable to cross the thresh-<lb/>old, enter the unsafe zone, and fall consequently. Figure 8 gives respective chances of reaching the threshold in <lb/>the IAFCRW and MRW groups on a weekly basis during the 3-week rehabilitation program. The comparison <lb/>results of IAFCRW vs. MRW were 32 ± 1% vs. 57 ± 3.5% during week 1, 26 ± 0.5% vs. 50 ± 2.5% during week <lb/>2, and 29 ± 1.5% vs. 54 ± 4.5% during week 3. The average chance comparison over three weeks was 29 ± 1% <lb/>vs. 53 ± 3.5%. As illustrated in Fig. 8, MRW gave chances above 50%, much higher than those in IAFCRW, sim-<lb/>ply due to the fact that the IAFCRW platform is physically a larger wheel than the MRW counterpart, and was <lb/>designed as a rat-friendly rehabilitation environment. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, it was found that rats with a surgically triggered stroke (such as MCAo) cannot be well rehabili-<lb/>tated at a fixed intensity, using existing rehabilitation platforms, since the rats&apos; motor functions were dulled and <lb/>reduced. The experimental results showed that the IAFCRW group presented significant improvements in both <lb/>the motor function recovery and the cerebral infarct volume with the control group as a benchmark (Fig. 7; <lb/>P &lt; 0.05) on Day 28, validating the performance of the IAFCRW platform. In contrast, there is an indistinguish-<lb/>able statistical difference in all the behavioral test results among the rehabilitated groups and the benchmark on <lb/>Day 7, validating the argument that it takes time to observe the efficacy of rehabilitation.) Besides, significant dif-<lb/>ferences in the motor function and the cerebral infarct volume were not observed as well among the treadmill, the <lb/>MRW and the control groups, in agreement with two pieces of prior studies 13,14 . Hence, commercial forced exer-<lb/>cise platforms were validated not as a well-designed stroke rehabilitation environment, and the outperformance <lb/>of the IAFCRW platform was demonstrated accordingly. <lb/>Score <lb/>Behavior <lb/>0 point <lb/>Balances with steady posture and successfully reaching the goal box <lb/>1 point <lb/>Grasps side of beam <lb/>2 points <lb/>Hugs the beam and one limb falls down from the beam <lb/>3 points <lb/>Hugs the beam and two limbs fall down from the beam or spins on beam (&gt;60 s) <lb/>4 points <lb/>Attempts to balance on the beam but falls off (&gt;40 s) <lb/>5 points <lb/>Attempts to balance on the beam but falls off ( &gt; 20 s) <lb/>6 points <lb/>Falls off: No attempt to balance or hang on to the beam (&lt;20 s) <lb/>Table 1. Beam balance test graded on a scale of 0 to 6 (normal = 0; maximum = 6). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 7. Rehabilitation performance comparison among groups. The neurological motor function was <lb/>evaluated using (A) a mNSS, (B) a beam balance test, and (C) an inclined plane test before and after MCAo or <lb/>sham surgery. All the rats displayed normal motor behavior at baseline (pre-stroke). On day 7 after stroke, but <lb/>before rehabilitation, MCAo induction groups (including the control, treadmill, MRW and IAFCRW groups) <lb/>of rats exhibited motor deficit behaviors, indicating that rats received successful stroke. (D) Representative <lb/>TTC staining of 13 consecutive coronal brain sections of each group on day 28 after sham or MCAo is shown <lb/>as an upper panel. TTC-stained 1 mm coronal brain slices show the white infarct area, and red color indicates <lb/>intact tissue. The black line indicates the contralateral hemisphere area, while the light blue dotted lines indicate <lb/>the ipsilateral non-infarct area. Infarcted volumes determined in the rats are shown as the percentage of the <lb/>hemisphere. Data are expressed as mean ± SD of independent experiments (n = 10 for each group). *p &lt; 0.05, <lb/>compared with the sham group. # p &lt; 0.05, compared with the control group. + p &lt; 0.05, compared with the <lb/>treadmill group. &amp; p &lt; 0.05, compared with the MRW group. <lb/>Figure 8. Comparison on the chance of reaching the threshold on a weekly basis between the IAFCRW and <lb/>the MRW groups. The comparison results of IAFCRW vs. MRW were 32 ± 1% vs. 57 ± 3.5% during week 1, <lb/>26 ± 0.5% vs. 50 ± 2.5% during week 2, and 29 ± 1.5% vs. 54 ± 4.5% during week 3. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>Obviously, the IAFCRW platform has a great advantage over existing commercially available training plat-<lb/>forms due to the use of the presented rehabilitation model. Even though there was a (29 ± 1)% chance of reach-<lb/>ing the threshold, the chance of fall was completely ruled out for the following reason. Once unable to keep pace <lb/>with the running wheel, a rat was brought up to the threshold. Meanwhile, a deceleration mechanism was ena-<lb/>bled instantly, the rat was brought back to the safe zone consequently, and then an acceleration mechanism was <lb/>enabled to speed up the running wheel. In simple terms, the acceleration and deceleration mechanisms were <lb/>enabled alternatingly, such that rats could be rehabilitated all the time in an uninterrupted, adaptive and fall-free <lb/>manner, and resulted in the great outperformance relative to the MRW counterpart. It is worth noting that a <lb/>significant efficacy of stroke rehabilitation was not observed in the MRW group, due to an up to (53 ± 3.5)% <lb/>chance of reaching the threshold and the fact that MRW was not equipped with a deceleration mechanism. In <lb/>other words, the MRW training was frequently interrupted by a fall over approximately half the training dura-<lb/>tion, and the trainee was made physically weaker each time after getting a fall injury. This partially accounts for <lb/>the poor efficacy of rehabilitation in the MRW group. However, it must be pointed out that an IAFCRW group <lb/>member, when reaching the threshold, did cling to a local vertical surface completely by limb strength, or it <lb/>might slide down the runway right away. At this moment, the trainee can be seen as taking training at full capac-<lb/>ity. As referred to previously, there were a (29 ± 1)% chance of reaching the threshold and a zero chance of fall, <lb/>meaning that the IAFCRW group members can be safely rehabilitated at full capacity for approximately one <lb/>third of a training duration. This accounts for the outperformance of the IAFCRW platform in another sense. <lb/>The psychological stress interference, caused by electric shock when using treadmills, remains a key issue in <lb/>the field of physiology, and might interrupt rehabilitation exercise. In this work, the treadmill group members <lb/>were observed to be frequently electrically stimulated at the end of the treadmill, and were even to exhausted to <lb/>be trained in the second half of a training duration, which is a major cause of second injury. Today&apos;s commer-<lb/>cially available MRWs cause as well training interference due to fall injuries. Therefore, the fall-free rehabilitation <lb/>mechanism was developed herein in such a way that rats can be rehabilitated under a low level of stress interfer-<lb/>ence, and analysis on collected raw neurophysiological data can be made more convincing by clinical researchers. <lb/>The training speed and the duration of a conventional training platform needs to be preset, and the wheel accel-<lb/>erates from rest to a specified training speed directly. However, this move makes it difficult for the rats to adapt to the <lb/>running speed, and may cause injury, thereby deteriorating the rehabilitation performance. The presented adaptive <lb/>acceleration model was developed based on the diverse physical characteristics of rats, and the rehabilitated members <lb/>were permitted to gradually adapt to the final training speed. An advantage of this design is an improved repeatability <lb/>of a training process. Another clear advantage is the feature to record all the running states and monitor the position <lb/>of a trainee throughout the entire training process, a feature not available in commercially available platforms. A fixed <lb/>training intensity and a duration are employed to estimate the total amount of exercise in commercial platforms, <lb/>which may involve invalid or ineffective exercises, such as electric shocks, abnormal running, falls, etc. Recording <lb/>of all the running states and position monitoring may help the physiological laboratory personnel understand the <lb/>overall training condition of animals, and may as well account for the variability of experimental results. As a con-<lb/>sequence, a deeper understanding and more convincing arguments can be made using the presented mechanism. <lb/>Table 2 presents a feature and hardware cost comparison among platforms. In addition to the above-referred <lb/>advantages, the IAFCRW platform has a hardware cost advantage over counterparts. The hardware cost therein <lb/>refers to the expense of building a platform, but excluding those of medical treatments. The fees for medical treat-<lb/>ments, e.g. MCAo surgeries and rehabilitation expense, are exactly the same among various training platforms, <lb/>meaning that there is no need to compare such medical treatment costs. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>This study presented a fall-free, adaptive rehabilitation mechanism for ischemic stroke rat patients, which was <lb/>implemented in an IAFCRW platform. The severity of an ischemic stroke caused by MCAo in rats can be eval-<lb/>uated using 3 behavioral tests. The IAFCRW platform was found to outperform a traditional running wheel <lb/>counterpart in terms of motor function and infarct volume, and to provide a completely safe and adaptive reha-<lb/>bilitation environment according to individual differences. The issue of motion rehabilitation had been explored <lb/>Features <lb/>Treadmill 13 <lb/>Motorized running wheel 14 <lb/>IAFCRW (this study) <lb/>Driving mode <lb/>Motorized and electrically <lb/>stimulated <lb/>Centrally motorized <lb/>Laterally motorized <lb/>running speed <lb/>Fixed <lb/>Fixed <lb/>Variable <lb/>Speed control mechanism <lb/>Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Feedback adjusted <lb/>Number of Rats trained at a time Multiple <lb/>Single <lb/>Single <lb/>Automated acceleration training Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Available <lb/>Automated deceleration training Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Available <lb/>Track material <lb/>Rubber belt <lb/>Cross bar <lb/>Acrylic and rubber belt <lb/>Threshold sensing <lb/>Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Available <lb/>Effective exercise assessment <lb/>Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Available <lb/>Fall prevention mechanism <lb/>Not available <lb/>Not available <lb/>Available <lb/>Training interference level <lb/>High <lb/>Intermediate <lb/>Low <lb/>Hardware cost <lb/>High <lb/>Intermediate <lb/>Lower-Intermediate <lb/>Table 2. Feature and hardware cost comparison among platforms for cerebral stroke rehabilitation purposes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<body>for disease treatment in neurophysiology and pathology. However, most existing forced animal training platforms <lb/>inevitably produced interfering factors, including shocks and falls, which were presumed to be reduced to a great <lb/>extent herein. A significant recovery (Fig. 7; P &lt; 0.05) was achieved in motor function tests and cerebral infarct <lb/>volume measurements. Moreover, the IAFCRW group was the only exercise group showing a significant recovery <lb/>through stroke rehabilitation, and the group members thereof can be safely rehabilitated all the time, and particu-<lb/>larly at full capacity for approximately one third of a training duration. Therefore, this platform can be used by <lb/>clinical researchers as a training platform for experimental verification purposes in future studies. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability <lb/>The data that support the findings of this study are available from the corresponding author upon reasonable <lb/>request. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Duncan, P. W. et al. Similar motor recovery of upper and lower-extremities after stroke. Stroke 25, 1181-1188, https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1161/01.str.25.6.1181 (1994). <lb/>2. Mayo, N. E., Wood-Dauphinee, S., Cote, R., Durcan, L. &amp; Carlton, J. Activity, participation, and quality of life 6 months poststroke. <lb/>Archives of Physical Medicine and Rehabilitation 83, 1035-1042, https://doi.org/10.1053/apmr.2002.33984 (2002). <lb/>3. Livingston-Thomas, J. et al. Exercise and environmental enrichment as enablers of task-specific neuroplasticity and stroke recovery. <lb/>Neurotherapeutics 13, 395-402, https://doi.org/10.1007/s13311-016-0423-9 (2016). <lb/>4. Pin-Barre, C. &amp; Laurin, J. Physical exercise as a diagnostic, rehabilitation, and preventive tool: influence on neuroplasticity and <lb/>motor recovery after stroke. Neural Plasticity, https://doi.org/10.1155/2015/608581 (2015). <lb/>5. Zheng, H. Q. et al. Physical exercise promotes recovery of neurological function after ischemic stroke in rats. International Journal <lb/>of Molecular Sciences 15, 10974-10988, https://doi.org/10.3390/ijms150610974 (2014). <lb/>6. Zhang, P. Y. et al. Early exercise improves cerebral blood flow through increased angiogenesis in experimental stroke rat model. <lb/>Journal of Neuroengineering and Rehabilitation 10, https://doi.org/10.1186/1743-0003-10-43 (2013). <lb/>7. Zheng, Q. P. et al. Exercise improves recovery after ischemic brain injury by inducing the expression of angiopoietin-1 and tie-2 in <lb/>rats. Tohoku Journal of Experimental Medicine 224, 221-228, https://doi.org/10.1620/tjem.224.221 (2011). <lb/>8. Luft, A., Macko, R., Forrester, L., Goldberg, A. &amp; Hanley, D. F. Post-stroke exercise rehabilitation: what we know about retraining the <lb/>motor system and how it may apply to retraining the heart. Cleveland Clinic journal of medicine 75(Suppl 2), S83-86 (2008). <lb/>9. Auriat, A. M., Grams, J. D., Yan, R. H. &amp; Colbourne, F. Forced exercise does not improve recovery after hemorrhagic stroke in rats. <lb/>Brain Research 1109, 183-191, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brainres.2006.06.035 (2006). <lb/>10. Leasure, J. L. &amp; Grider, M. The effect of mild post-stroke exercise on reactive neurogenesis and recovery of somatosensation in aged <lb/>rats. Experimental Neurology 226, 58-67, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.expneurol.2010.08.003 (2010). <lb/>11. Ding, Y. et al. Exercise pre-conditioning reduces brain damage in ischemic rats that may be associated with regional angiogenesis <lb/>and cellular overexpression of neurotrophin. Neuroscience 124, 583-591, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2003.12.029 (2004). <lb/>12. Wang, R. Y., Yang, Y. R. &amp; Yu, S. M. Protective effects of treadmill training on infarction in rats. Brain Research 922, 140-143, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/s0006-8993(01)03154-7 (2001). <lb/>13. Ke, Z., Yip, S. P., Li, L., Zheng, X. X. &amp; Tong, K. Y. The effects of voluntary, involuntary, and forced exercises on brain-derived <lb/>neurotrophic factor and motor function recovery: a rat brain ischemia model. Plos One 6, https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0016643 (2011). <lb/>14. Ploughman, M. et al. Exercise intensity influences the temporal profile of growth factors involved in neuronal plasticity following <lb/>focal ischemia. Brain Research 1150, 207-216, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brainres.2007.02.065 (2007). <lb/>15. Hayes, K. et al. Forced, not voluntary, exercise effectively induces neuroprotection in stroke. Acta Neuropathologica 115, 289-296, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s00401-008-0340-z (2008). <lb/>16. Zhao, X. R. et al. Wheel-running modestly promotes functional recovery after a unilateral cortical lesion in rats. Behavioural <lb/>Neurology 16, 41-49, https://doi.org/10.1155/2005/105341 (2005). <lb/>17. Waters, R. P. et al. Selection for aerobic capacity affects corticosterone, monoamines and wheel-running activity. Physiology &amp; <lb/>Behavior 93, 1044-1054, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2008.01.013 (2008). <lb/>18. Leasure, J. L. &amp; Jones, M. Forced and voluntary exercise differentially affect brain and behavior. Neuroscience 156, 456-465, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2008.07.041 (2008). <lb/>19. Chen, C. C. et al. Improved infrared-sensing running wheel systems with an effective exercise activity indicator. Plos One 10, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0122394 (2015). <lb/>20. Kennard, J. A. &amp; Woodruff-Pak, D. S. A comparison of low-and high-impact forced exercise: Effects of training paradigm on <lb/>learning and memory. Physiology &amp; Behavior 106, 423-427, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.physbeh.2012.02.023 (2012). <lb/>21. Chen, C. C. et al. A forced running wheel system with a microcontroller that provides high-intensity exercise training in an animal <lb/>ischemic stroke model. Brazilian Journal of Medical and Biological Research 47, 858-868, https://doi.org/10.1590/1414-<lb/>431x20143754 (2014). <lb/>22. Brown, D. A. et al. Short-term treadmill running in the rat: what kind of stressor is it? Journal of Applied Physiology 103, 1979-1985, <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1152/japplphysiol.00706.2007 (2007). <lb/>23. Moraska, A., Deak, T., Spencer, R. L., Roth, D. &amp; Fleshner, M. Treadmill running produces both positive and negative physiological <lb/>adaptations in Sprague-Dawley rats. American Journal of Physiology-Regulatory Integrative and Comparative Physiology 279, <lb/>R1321-R1329 (2000). <lb/>24. Arida, R. M., Scorza, C. A., da Silva, A. V., Scorza, F. A. &amp; Cavalheiro, E. A. Differential effects of spontaneous versus forced exercise <lb/>in rats on the staining of parvalbumin-positive neurons in the hippocampal formation. Neuroscience letters 364, 135-138, https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.neulet.2004.03.086 (2004). <lb/>25. Nomura, T. et al. I.v. infusion of brain-derived neurotrophic factor gene-modified human mesenchymal stem cells protects against <lb/>injury in a cerebral ischemia model in adult rat. Neuroscience 136, 161-169, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.neuroscience.2005.06.062 (2005). <lb/>26. Kim, W. S. et al. Effect of electroacupuncture on motor recovery in a rat stroke model during the early recovery stage. Brain Research <lb/>1248, 176-183, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.brainres.2008.11.009 (2009). <lb/>27. Longa, E. Z., Weinstein, P. R., Carlson, S. &amp; Cummins, R. Reversible middle cerebral artery occlusion without craniectomy in rats. <lb/>Stroke 20, 84-91 (1989). <lb/>28. Chen, J. L. et al. Intravenous administration of human umbilical cord blood reduces behavioral deficits after stroke in rats. Stroke 32, <lb/>2682-2688, https://doi.org/10.1161/hs1101.098367 (2001). <lb/>29. Chang, M. W., Young, M. S. &amp; Lin, M. T. An inclined plane system with microcontroller to determine limb motor function of <lb/>laboratory animals. Journal of Neuroscience Methods 168, 186-194, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jneumeth.2007.09.013 (2008). <lb/>30. Chen, J. L. et al. Therapeutic benefit of intravenous administration of bone marrow stromal cells after cerebral ischemia in rats. <lb/>Stroke 32, 1005-1011, https://doi.org/10.1161/01.str.32.4.1005 (2001). <lb/>31. Chen, F. et al. Rodent stroke induced by photochemical occlusion of proximal middle cerebral artery: evolution monitored with MR <lb/>imaging and histopathology. European journal of radiology 63, 68-75, https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejrad.2007.01.005 (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | <lb/>(2019) 9:984 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-018-37282-3 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors gratefully acknowledge the support provided for this study by the Ministry of Science and <lb/>Technology, Taiwan, under grant number MOST 106-2221-E-167 -004 -MY3. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>C.-C.C. established the whole running wheel systems. C.-C.C. and C.-P.C. planned and performed the <lb/>experiments. C.-C.C., C.-L.Y. and C.-P.C. analyzed the data, conceived and designed the experiments. C.-C.C. <lb/>and C.-P.C. contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools. C.-C.C. and C.-L.Y. wrote the paper. C.-P.C. designed <lb/>the animal experiments and statistical analysis. <lb/>Additional Information <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests: The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2019 </front>

	</text>
</tei>
