<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Transite: A computational motif-based analysis platform <lb/>that identifies RNA-binding proteins modulating changes <lb/>in gene expression <lb/>Konstantin Krismer 1,2,3,5,7 , Shohreh Varmeh 2,3 , Molly A. Bird 2,3,5 , Anna Gattinger 3,7 , Yi Wen Kong 2,3 , Thomas <lb/>Bernwinkler 2,3,7 , Daniel A. Anderson 4,5 , Andreas Heinzel 7 , Brian A. Joughin 2,3 , Ian G. Cannell 2,3,8, * and Michael B. <lb/>Yaffe 2,3,5,6, * <lb/>1 Computer Science and Artificial Intelligence Laboratory, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 32 Vassar Street, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA, 2 Center for <lb/>Precision Cancer Medicine, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 500 Main Street, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA, 3 David H. Koch Institute for Integrative <lb/>Cancer Research, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 500 Main Street, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA, 4 Synthetic Biology Center, Massachusetts Institute <lb/>of Technology, 500 Technology Square, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA, 5 Department of Biological Engineering, Massachusetts Institute of Technology, 77 <lb/>Massachusetts Avenue, Cambridge, MA 02139, USA, 6 Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, 415 Main Street, Cambridge, MA 02142, USA, 7 Department <lb/>for Medical and Bioinformatics, University of Applied Sciences Upper Austria, Softwarepark 11, 4232 Hagenberg, Austria and 8 New York Genome Center, <lb/>101 Avenue of the Americas, New York, NY 10013, USA <lb/> * To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +1 617 452 2103; Fax: +1 617 452 4978; Email: myaffe@mit.edu. Correspondence may also be <lb/>addressed to Ian G. Cannell. Tel: +1 646 977 7241 ; Email: icannell@nygenome.org <lb/> Abstract-RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) play critical roles <lb/>in regulating gene expression by modulating splicing, RNA <lb/>stability, and protein translation and are frequently the targets <lb/>of signal transduction pathways that control RBP function <lb/>through post-translational modifications such as phosphoryla-<lb/>tion. In response to various stimuli, alterations in RBP function <lb/>contribute to global changes in gene expression, but identifying <lb/>which specific RNA-binding protein(s) are responsible for the <lb/>observed changes in gene expression patterns remains an unmet <lb/>need. Here, we present Transite -a computational approach to <lb/>systematically infer RBPs influencing gene expression changes <lb/>through alterations in RNA stability and degradation. Specif-<lb/>ically, our approach builds on pre-existing differential gene <lb/>expression data and performs sequence-based enrichment anal-<lb/>ysis. By matching the enriched sequences to a compendium of <lb/>RBP-binding motifs, we can identify potential RBPs responsible <lb/>for the observed gene expression changes. As an example, we <lb/>applied Transite to examine RBPs potentially involved in the <lb/>response of human patients with non-small cell lung cancer to <lb/>platinum-based chemotherapy, since RBPs have been recently <lb/>identified as one of the primary classes of proteins influencing <lb/>the DNA damage response. Transite implicated known RBP <lb/>regulators of the DNA damage response and identified hnRNPC <lb/>as a new modulator of chemotherapeutic resistance, which was <lb/>subsequently validated experimentally. These data show that <lb/>Transite is a generalizable framework for the identification <lb/>of RBPs responsible for gene expression changes driving cell-<lb/>state transitions and adds value to the vast wealth of publicly-<lb/>available gene expression data. To ensure that Transite is <lb/>available to a broad range of scientists for routine differential <lb/>gene expression analysis workflows we have built a user-friendly <lb/>web interface that is accessible at https://transite.mit.edu. <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>RNA-binding proteins are major modulators of gene ex-<lb/>pression at the post-transcriptional level, where they control <lb/>RNA splicing, stability, localization, degradation, and trans-<lb/>lation [1,2]. For mRNAs, the role of RBPs in modulating <lb/>global changes in gene expression at both the RNA and <lb/>protein level becomes particularly important under conditions <lb/>where new gene transcription is repressed, such as during <lb/>inflammation, cell stress, and in response to genomic dam-<lb/>age [3-5]. In addition, mutations affecting the expression of <lb/>specific RBPs, or their function, have been implicated in a <lb/>variety of diseases, including cancer [5-8]. <lb/>RBPs appear to play an especially critical role in or-<lb/>chestrating the DNA damage response (DDR) by regulating <lb/>mRNA expression changes that control the onset and dura-<lb/>tion of cell cycle checkpoints and drive DNA repair [9-11]. <lb/>Recent large-scale screening efforts have converged on RBPs <lb/>as one of the most enriched classes of proteins modulating <lb/>the DDR, even more so than annotated DNA damage repair <lb/>proteins [12-16]. In addition, emerging evidence from our <lb/>lab and others has identified RBPs as critical targets of DDR <lb/>kinases, including both upstream responder kinases such as <lb/>ATM, ATR and DNA-PK, and downstream effector kinases <lb/>such as Chk1 and MK2 [12,13,17-19]. The discovery <lb/>of RBPs as integration points of the cellular response to <lb/>genomic damage has important clinical applications, since <lb/>the efficacy of many commonly used chemotherapeutic drugs <lb/>is dependent on the integrity (or lack thereof) of the DNA <lb/>damage response (DDR) [20,21]. For example, we found that <lb/>a key target of the DNA damage-activated MK2 pathway was <lb/>the RBP hnRNPA0, which was required for maintenance of <lb/>the G1/S and G2/M checkpoints following cisplatin treat-<lb/>ment [22,23]. Furthermore, this finding dictated the response <lb/>of non-small cell lung cancers (NSCLCs) to chemotherapy in <lb/>both mouse models and human patients, where the expression <lb/>levels of two critical hnRNPA0 target RNAs, Gadd45α and <lb/>p27, predicted the clinical response of mouse and human <lb/>tumors to platinum therapy. Despite these types of data, <lb/>and the recent surge of interest in the roles of RBPs in <lb/>cancer chemosensitivity and resistance [5,9,24], methods for <lb/>systematic prioritization of RBPs that influence the response <lb/>to therapy in diverse clinically relevant data sets are lacking. <lb/>Motivated by our long standing interest in the DNA <lb/>damage response, protein kinase signaling and the centrality <lb/>of RBPs in dictating cell death decisions in response to <lb/>chemotherapy, we developed Transite. Transite is a computa-<lb/>tional method that leverages the wealth of publicly available <lb/>gene expression data to infer RBPs influencing mRNA <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>gene expression profiles <lb/>RNA-seq, microarray <lb/>differential expression <lb/>analysis <lb/>sequence extraction <lb/>3&apos; UTR, 5&apos; UTR, mature mRNA <lb/>identify relevant RBPs <lb/>TSMA, SPMA <lb/>limma, edgeR, DESeq, ... <lb/>Transite <lb/>Transcript Set Motif Analysis / Spectrum Motif Analysis <lb/>T <lb/>ACGU <lb/>GEO, SRA <lb/>ENA <lb/>1: CCAGCAUCGAUCAUGAC... <lb/>2: GGCAGUUUCAGCAGUUU... <lb/>3: UUGGGGAAAUUGCCGUA... <lb/>4: GAAAAUUUUGUCAACGU... <lb/>5: CCCCACAGCCCAGCAAA... <lb/>6: CACCCCCCCUUCGUUCA... <lb/>7: GGUUCACACCGGGUUAC... <lb/>8: AAAAGCAAAUCCAUUCC... <lb/>n: CAGGCAAUGGGGCACAA... <lb/>Fig. 1. Schematic of the Transite analysis pipeline: The initial steps of the canonical Transite data analysis workflow include preprocessing and differential <lb/>expression analysis of gene expression profiles, which are usually obtained from NCBI and EMBL-EBI repositories such as GEO, SRA, and ENA. Differential <lb/>expression analysis is used to either identify groups of upregulated and downregulated genes (for Transcript Set Motif Analysis) or establish a ranked list <lb/>of genes from most upregulated to most downregulated (for Spectrum Motif Analysis). Transite then collects the sequences of all genes in the data set and <lb/>identifies RBPs whose targets concordantly change their expression level. <lb/>expression changes through modulation of mRNA stability. <lb/>Specifically, our method performs motif enrichment analysis <lb/>on a user-specified region of the mRNA, e.g., the 3 -UTR. <lb/>By identifying RBPs whose targets are overrepresented in <lb/>differentially-expressed genes, Transite nominates potential <lb/>RBP drivers of the observed gene expression changes, a <lb/>workflow that has been effective in the study of the kinases <lb/>associated with a particular biological stimulus [25]. A <lb/>schematic overview of the Transite pipeline is shown in <lb/>figure 1. <lb/>Application of Transite to a NSCLC patient data set of <lb/>chemoresistant tumors identified hnRNPC as a top putative <lb/>driver of increased mRNA levels in resistant patients. An <lb/>orthogonal analysis of hnRNPC-target mRNAs derived from <lb/>CLIP-Seq data confirmed upregulation of hnRNPC-target <lb/>mRNAs identified by our in silico approach. We then exper-<lb/>imentally validated that knock-down of hnRNPC enhanced <lb/>cisplatin-induced cell death in vitro, while hnRNPC over-<lb/>expression reduced cisplatin induced cell death. Furthermore, <lb/>high levels of hnRNPC expression were associated with <lb/>failure to respond to adjuvant platinum-based chemotherapy <lb/>in an independent NSCLC patient cohort. <lb/>Since the data input requirements for using Transite are <lb/>very general, the approach is not limited to DNA damage <lb/>or cancer chemotherapy responses, but instead Transite can <lb/>take advantage of the plethora of publicly available gene <lb/>expression data sets for any perturbation, and can be used to <lb/>investigate the effects of RBPs on gene expression using the <lb/>result of any experiment measuring the expression levels of <lb/>large numbers of genes simultaneously. Most prominently, <lb/>these include RNA-Seq, ribosome profiling and microarray <lb/>experiments. Transite is a versatile tool for inferring the <lb/>RBPs modulating gene expression and as such, should be <lb/>a valuable resource for the entire RNA community. <lb/>II. MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>A. Differential gene expression analysis <lb/>The analysis was done with the R/Bioconductor package <lb/>limma [26]. The design matrix for this analysis contains <lb/>two sample groups, untreated adenocarcinoma (10 microar-<lb/>ray samples) and recurrent adenocarcinoma (15 microarray <lb/>samples). A linear model was fit to each row of the log 2 -<lb/>transformed expression value matrix, where rows correspond <lb/>to transcripts and columns correspond to samples. The <lb/>coefficients of the fitted models describe the differences <lb/>between the untreated adenocarcinoma and recurrent adeno-<lb/>carcinoma groups. An empirical Bayes method was used to <lb/>obtain the significance and the strength of the log fold change <lb/>between sample groups for each transcript [27], resulting in <lb/>an estimate of the fold-change analysis between groups and <lb/>the significance of the change. Raw p-values were adjusted <lb/>using the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure [28]. <lb/>B. Motif databases <lb/>Transite incorporates sequence motifs of RBP binding <lb/>sites from two databases: CIS-BP, the Catalog of Inferred <lb/>Sequence Binding Preferences [29], and RBPDB, a database <lb/>of RNA-binding specificities [30]. Together these contribute <lb/>174 sequence motifs of varying lengths (between six and <lb/>18 nucleotides). All motifs were obtained using in vitro <lb/>techniques for determining RNA targets. The majority of <lb/>motifs was determined by either systematic evolution of <lb/>ligands by exponential enrichment (SELEX) [31] or RNA-<lb/>compete [32]. The RNA binding specificities of two further <lb/>RBPs were obtained by electrophoretic mobility shift assays <lb/>(EMSA) [33]. <lb/>C. Motif representations <lb/>Motif descriptions provided from the databases described <lb/>above were converted from count matrices to position weight <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>matrices (PWMs), obtained by normalizing each nucleotide&apos;s <lb/>probability at each position by the mean probability of each <lb/>nucleotide, 25%. <lb/>For k-mer-based analyses, PWMs were converted to hex-<lb/>amers and heptamers by generating all k-mers for which each <lb/>position has a probability higher than a certain threshold. In <lb/>the work presented here, we used a threshold probability of <lb/>0.215, which is a stringency level that works well empirically <lb/>with the motifs from the motif databases. <lb/>Laplace smoothing (also known as additive smoothing) is <lb/>applied to avoid zeros in count matrices before conversion <lb/>to PWMs. Zeros might occur if the number of sequences on <lb/>which the PSSM is based, is too small to contain at least <lb/>one occurrence of each nucleotide per position. In this case, <lb/>pseudocounts are introduced [34]. <lb/>D. CLIP-seq data analysis <lb/>The BED files (output from Piranha analysis) for <lb/>all CLIP-Seq data sets were downloaded from CLIPdb <lb/>(http://lulab.life.tsinghua.edu.cn/clipdb/). Read counts were <lb/>mapped to RefSeq identifiers using a UCSC table with <lb/>either just 3 -UTR sequences or the entire mature mRNA of <lb/>all human mRNAs in Hg19 coordinates. RefSeq identifiers <lb/>were then summarized to gene symbols. For gene symbols <lb/>with multiple RefSeq identifiers, the one with the maximum <lb/>counts was taken, as it was assumed this indicated the <lb/>most highly expressed transcript. This analysis created two <lb/>gene lists, one where there was binding in the 3 -UTR (3 -<lb/>UTR targets) or where there was binding in any region of <lb/>the mRNA (entire mature mRNA targets). These gene lists <lb/>were then merged with fold change lists from GEO gene <lb/>expression data set GSE7880. To generate the non-targets <lb/>list, the entire mature mRNA list was subtracted from the <lb/>GSE7880 list. <lb/>E. Package and web development <lb/>R package development and documentation was stream-<lb/>lined with devtools and roxygen2, respectively. Core algo-<lb/>rithms were implemented in C++. ggplot2 [35] was used for <lb/>data visualization. <lb/>The website was developed in R with the reactive web <lb/>application framework shiny from RStudio. The components <lb/>of the graphical user interface were provided by shiny and <lb/>shinyBS, which serves as an R wrapper for the Twitter <lb/>Bootstrap HTML/CSS/JavaScript components. <lb/>F. Cell culture and colony formation assays <lb/>T6a (mouse lung adenocarcinoma) cells were grown in <lb/>RPMI-1640 medium supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine <lb/>serum at 37 • C in a humidified incubator supplied with <lb/>5 % CO 2 . Colony formation assays were performed as <lb/>previously described [22]. Briefly, 48 hours after transfection <lb/>with siRNAs or pcDNA vectors, cells were treated with <lb/>either 4 or 8 μM cisplatin or vehicle for 4 hours. Cells <lb/>were then re-plated in 6-well plates using 1000 mock-treated <lb/>or 10,000 cisplatin-treated cells per well. In overexpression <lb/>assays, 500 μg/ml G418 was added to the media to select <lb/>for cells transfected with pcDNA vectors. After 10 to 14 <lb/>days, cells were fixed with 4 % formaldehyde and stained <lb/>with either SYTO 60 (Thermo Fisher Scientific) or modified <lb/>Wright-stain (Sigma-Aldrich). Colonies were scanned and <lb/>counted using Odyssey R CLx Imaging System (LI-COR <lb/>Biosciences). <lb/>G. siRNA transfection <lb/>Silencer select siRNAs (Ambion) transfection was per-<lb/>formed using RNAiMax following manufacturer instructions <lb/>(Life Technologies) with a final concentration of 5 nM. Cells <lb/>were then treated as described in the previous section. <lb/>H. Overexpression of hnRNPC <lb/>pcDNA3.1 vectors expressing FLAG-tagged mouse <lb/>hnRNPC were generated as follows. First, total RNA was <lb/>prepared from KP7B (mouse lung carcinoma) cells using <lb/>RNeasy purification kit (Qiagen) and was used to synthesize <lb/>cDNAs using Superscript cDNA Synthesis System (Life <lb/>Technologies). cDNAs were used as templates in PCR <lb/>reactions using PfuUltra II HF DNA polymerase (Agilent) <lb/>and the following primers: 5 -GCCCATAAGCTTATG-<lb/>GACTACAAAGACGATGACGACAAGGCTAGCAAT-<lb/>GTTACCAACAAGACAGATCCTCGG-3 (forward) and <lb/>5 -GCCCATTCTAGATTATTAAGAGTCATCCTCCCCA-<lb/>TTGGCGCTGTCTCTG-3 (reverse). Restriction sites for <lb/>HindIII (in forward primer) and XbaI (in reverse primer) <lb/>are in bold. Sequences encoding FLAG are underlined. <lb/>The PCR products were cleaved with the indicated <lb/>restriction enzymes (New England BioLabs Inc), purified <lb/>(QIAquick PCR Purification Kit, Qiagen) and sub-cloned <lb/>into pcDNA3.1 vectors. The integrity of the plasmids were <lb/>confirmed by sequencing (Eton Bioscience Inc). <lb/>I. Immunoblotting <lb/>Cells were harvested 24 (siRNA transfected) or 48 <lb/>(pcDNA vectors transfected) hours after cisplatin treatment <lb/>and re-plating. Cells were then lysed in RIPA buffer and <lb/>subjected to standard SDS/PAGE electrophoresis and trans-<lb/>ferred to nitrocellulose membranes. The membranes were <lb/>immunoblotted with hnRNPC (ab10294, Abcam Inc., Cam-<lb/>bridge, MA) and γ-tubulin (Sigma-Aldrich) following man-<lb/>ufacturers instructions. <lb/>III. RESULTS <lb/>RNA-binding proteins (RBPs) influence all stages of the <lb/>mRNA life cycle through specific interactions involving <lb/>short linear sequence motifs containing 6 -8 nucleotides <lb/>within their target RNAs [36]. The identity of these RBP-<lb/>binding motifs has been determined for a subset of all <lb/>known RBPs using various in vitro based oligonucleotide <lb/>selection methods such as SELEX [31], RNAcompete [32] <lb/>and Bind-n-Seq [37], and directly confirmed for a smaller <lb/>set of RBPs through experimental analysis of RBP-RNA <lb/>interactions using CLIP-Seq and various extensions thereof. <lb/>These latter techniques are laborious and costly to perform, <lb/>and the direct experimental identification of the complete set <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>of RNA targets for most RBPs is therefore not yet known. <lb/>Furthermore, identification of these RNA targets are likely <lb/>to differ depending upon the experimental situation under <lb/>which CLIP-Seq was performed. This has limited our ability <lb/>to understand which RBPs are critical mediators of changes <lb/>in RNA levels in pre-existing gene expression datasets like <lb/>those contained in the gene expression omnibus (GEO), <lb/>including cancer-relevant datasets that describe treatment <lb/>responses. <lb/>In order to systematically mine these existing data sets <lb/>for RBPs that may influence gene expression changes, with <lb/>a focus of patient response to therapy, we have developed <lb/>Transite. Transite takes either a discrete set of differentially <lb/>expressed genes, or a continuous list of genes, and searches <lb/>for enriched short linear oligonucleotide motifs within spe-<lb/>cific regions of the transcripts they encode, and then matches <lb/>these motifs to the likely RBP that binds them using a com-<lb/>pendium of RBP motifs. By default, Transite uses 3 -UTR <lb/>sequences, as our major focus is mRNA stability and motifs <lb/>that determine mRNA stability are known to generally reside <lb/>within the 3 -UTR. Gene sets used for Transite analysis can <lb/>be defined in either a discrete or a continuous fashion. For <lb/>discrete sets of genes we implement Transcript Set Motif <lb/>Analysis, which takes the predefined sets of transcripts such <lb/>as upregulated and downregulated transcripts and performs <lb/>motif analysis based on systematic differences between these <lb/>sets and the total gene expression data. For continuous <lb/>collections of genes we developed Spectrum Motif Analysis, <lb/>which uses a continuous quantity to establish an ordered <lb/>ranking of transcripts and analyzes motif enrichment along <lb/>that ordered list of transcripts, similar to the approach taken <lb/>by Gene Set Enrichment Analysis [38]. For this continuous <lb/>quantity, a measure of differential expression is commonly <lb/>used, such as fold change or signal-to-noise ratio, thus <lb/>exploiting information across the entire spectrum of changes <lb/>rather than limiting analysis to the up-and down-regulated <lb/>extremes. <lb/>A. Transcript Set Motif Analysis identifies RBPs with sub-<lb/>strate sites enriched or depleted among differentially ex-<lb/>pressed genes <lb/>Transcript Set Motif Analysis (TSMA) can identify the <lb/>overrepresentation or underrepresentation of putative binding <lb/>sites of 174 RNA-binding proteins in a set (or sets) of <lb/>transcripts, i.e., the foreground set, relative to the entire <lb/>population of transcripts measured in an experiment. The <lb/>latter is called background set, and is a proper superset of <lb/>the foreground sets. <lb/>Foreground sets are proper subsets of the background set <lb/>and their definition depends on the desired motif analysis <lb/>approach. In any case, foreground and background sets define <lb/>the groups of transcripts wherein the overrepresentation <lb/>and underrepresentation of putative RBP binding sites is <lb/>investigated. <lb/>When gene expression data is used, the two foreground <lb/>sets for TSMA are usually the statistically significantly <lb/>upregulated and downregulated transcripts. (Figure 2A). Var-<lb/>ious deviations of this canonical use of foreground sets are <lb/>possible. Upregulated and downregulated sets can be defined <lb/>in various ways, depending on the method of differential <lb/>expression analysis [39]. It is not even necessary to use <lb/>gene expression data to define foreground and background <lb/>transcripts. For example, all human or all murine genes as-<lb/>sociated with a certain Gene Ontology (GO) [40] term could <lb/>be compared to all genes of human or mouse, respectively, <lb/>which are annotated with at least one GO term, to identify <lb/>RBPs associated with particular ontological terms. <lb/>Two different methods are used to assign transcript targets <lb/>to specific RBPs, k-mer-based TSMA and matrix-based <lb/>TSMA. <lb/>B. k-mer-based TSMA <lb/>In the k-mer based approach of TSMA the sequence motifs <lb/>recognized by each RBP are specified by lists of RBP-<lb/>specific hexamers or heptamers, collated from current motif <lb/>databases [29,30]. <lb/>After foreground and background sets are defined and the <lb/>preferred sequence region is selected (3 -UTR, 5 -UTR, or <lb/>complete mature mRNA including the coding region), the <lb/>sequences of both sets are broken down into overlapping <lb/>hexamers (i.e., k-mers of length 6) (Figure 2B, left column), <lb/>and for each k-mer its frequency in the foreground set <lb/>and background set is determined. While Transite supports <lb/>both hexamer-and heptamer-matching, hexamers are recom-<lb/>mended, since run-time increases exponentially with k and <lb/>the results for heptamers mirror those for hexamers in our <lb/>experience. <lb/>1) k-mer enrichment values: The enrichment value of k-<lb/>mer i, e i , is calculated as follows: <lb/>e i = <lb/>f i /n F <lb/>b i /n B <lb/>, <lb/>where f i and b i are the absolute counts of k-mer i in <lb/>foreground and background set and n F and n B are the <lb/>total counts of k-mers in the foreground and background, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>2) Significance of k-mer enrichment values: The statisti-<lb/>cal significance of the enrichment for all possible k-mers is <lb/>then determined. First, a contingency table C i for k-mer i is <lb/>defined as <lb/>C i = <lb/>f i (n F − f i ) <lb/>b i (n B − b i ) <lb/>. <lb/>Then, the p-value p i for C i is approximated with Pearson&apos;s <lb/>χ 2 test. If p i &lt; 5α, p i is replaced by the p-value obtained by <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test for C i . This step-wise procedure reduces <lb/>computation time dramatically (approximately 50-fold), be-<lb/>cause the computationally expensive Fisher&apos;s exact test is <lb/>only used in cases where the approximate p-value from the <lb/>computationally inexpensive χ 2 test is close to the decision <lb/>boundary (α) and is avoided in cases where a precise p-value <lb/>is unnecessary. Furthermore, Fisher&apos;s exact test is always <lb/>used if at least one of the expected counts is less than five, <lb/>because this constitutes a violation of the assumptions of the <lb/>approximate test. The p-values are subsequently adjusted for <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>B TSMA: Motif enrichment analysis <lb/>k-mer-based TSMA <lb/>matrix-based TSMA <lb/>1. Break down sequences into k-mers: <lb/>AGUCCUGAAAGCGGUAUACAUGGAUCAGCAGUCUGAUCAUCGACGGUACUGCAGUGGAAAC... <lb/>AGUCCU AAAGCG UAUACA GGAUCA CAGUCU AUCAUC ACGGUA UGCAGU <lb/>GUCCUG AAGCGG AUACAU GAUCAG AGUCUG UCAUCG CGGUAC GCAGUG <lb/>UCCUGA AGCGGU UACAUG AUCAGC GUCUGA CAUCGA GGUACU CAGUGG <lb/>CCUGAA GCGGUA ACAUGG UCAGCA UCUGAU AUCGAC GUACUG AGUGGA <lb/>CUGAAA CGGUAU CAUGGA CAGCAG CUGAUC UCGACG UACUGC GUGGAA <lb/>UGAAAG GGUAUA AUGGAU AGCAGU UGAUCA CGACGG ACUGCA UGGAAA <lb/>GAAAGC GUAUAC UGGAUC GCAGUC GAUCAU GACGGU CUGCAG GGAAAC <lb/>2. Calculate k-mer enrichment between foreground and <lb/>background sets and visualize with volcano plots: <lb/>1. Score whole transcript region (e.g., 3&apos; UTR) of all <lb/>foreground and background transcripts with PSSM and <lb/>count putative binding sites (hits): <lb/>AGUCCUGAAAGCGGUAUACAUGGAUCAGCAGUCUGAUCAUCGACGGUACUGCAGUGGAAAC... <lb/>→ <lb/>PWM <lb/>2. Calculate enrichment of putative binding sites <lb/>between each foreground set and the background set. <lb/>AGUCCUGAAAGCGGUAUACAUGGAUCAGCAGUCUGAUCAUCGACGGUACUGCAGUGGAAAC... <lb/>→ <lb/>hit <lb/>PWM <lb/>AGUCCUGAAAGCGGUAUACAUGGAUCAGCAGUCUGAUCAUCGACGGUACUGCAGUGGAAAC... <lb/>→ <lb/>PWM <lb/>A <lb/>transcripts upregulated in condition 1 <lb/>Gene expression profile <lb/>Condition 1 <lb/>Condition 2 <lb/>transcripts upregulated in condition 2 <lb/>high negative log fold change <lb/>log fold change close to zero <lb/>high positive log fold change <lb/>TSMA: Foreground and background sets <lb/>Foreground sets: upregulated and downregulated transcripts <lb/>foreground set 1 <lb/>foreground set 2 <lb/>log 2 (FC) <lb/>-log <lb/>10 (p) <lb/>3. Obtain p-value estimates of k-mer enrichment by <lb/>Monte Carlo sampling: <lb/>mean enrichment value <lb/>density <lb/>3. Obtain matrix-based motif enrichment and estimate <lb/>p-value by Monte Carlo sampling: <lb/>enrichment value <lb/>density <lb/>background set <lb/>foreground set 1 <lb/>foreground set 2 <lb/>highly enriched <lb/>highly depleted <lb/>hit <lb/>hit <lb/>background set <lb/>Fig. 2. Schematic figure of Transcript Set Motif Analysis. (A) The foreground sets in TSMA are usually defined by differential gene expression analysis <lb/>of RNA-seq or microarray data. In this case, the foreground sets are most naturally defined as statistically significantly upregulated and downregulated <lb/>genes, whereas the background set is all genes of the microarray platform or all measured genes in RNA-seq. In the heatmap of the gene expression profile <lb/>in panel A, the two rows (Condition 1, Condition 2) are the mean gene expression values of the replicates of the respective groups (e.g., Condition 1 could <lb/>be treated with drug A and Condition 2 untreated). The columns of the heatmap correspond to the genes, and the superimposed gray curve is the log fold <lb/>change between Condition 1 and Condition 2. (B) TSMA then estimates the enrichment or depletion of putative binding sites between each foreground set <lb/>and the background set. There are two ways to describe putative binding sites of RNA-binding proteins (i.e., the motif). The column on the left depicts <lb/>k-mer-based TSMA, which uses a list of k-mers to describe putative binding sites. The column on the right is matrix-based TSMA, which instead uses <lb/>Position Weight Matrices (PWMs). <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>multiple hypothesis testing. The available p-value adjustment <lb/>methods are described in section 5 of the supplement. <lb/>3) k-mer volcano plots: Volcano plots are then used to vi-<lb/>sualize the enrichment values (x-coordinate, log transformed) <lb/>and associated p-values (y-coordinate, log transformed and <lb/>multiplied by -1) for all 4 k k-mers in a Transite TSMA run <lb/>(Figure 2B, left column, step 2). The black dots represent k-<lb/>mers without significant enrichment or depletion, while blue <lb/>dots denote significantly depleted and red dots significantly <lb/>enriched k-mers. Yellow k-mers are part of the RBP motif. <lb/>4) RBP assignment by average of k-mer enrichment val-<lb/>ues: As a way to quantify the overrepresentation (or under-<lb/>representation, respectively) of putative binding sites for a <lb/>particular RBP, the geometric mean of the enrichment values <lb/>of all k-mers associated with that RBP is used. Monte Carlo <lb/>tests (permutation tests) are used to obtain an estimate of <lb/>their significance (see section 2 in the supplement for details <lb/>on Monte Carlo sampling). In step 3 of figure 2, panel B, an <lb/>example histogram is shown, which depicts the empirical null <lb/>distribution of mean enrichment values associated with an <lb/>RBP&apos;s k-mers after repeated random selection of foregrounds <lb/>from the background. The dashed red line denotes the mean <lb/>enrichment value of motif-associated hexamers (which are <lb/>the yellow dots in the volcano plot in step 2) which were <lb/>actually observed in the true, unpermuted foreground. <lb/>C. Matrix-based TSMA <lb/>In the matrix-based TSMA approach, the sequence motifs <lb/>of 174 RBPs are represented as PWMs. Next, all sequence <lb/>positions in all transcripts in foreground and background <lb/>gene sets are scored by these PWMs, as shown in step 1 of <lb/>the right column of panel B, figure 2. The PWM slides along <lb/>the sequence, assigns a score to each position, and scores <lb/>above a certain threshold are considered putative binding <lb/>sites (hits). These hits are tallied in both the foreground and <lb/>the background set and enrichment values and associated <lb/>p-values are calculated analogously to the k-mer-based ap-<lb/>proach. Again, all p-values are multiple testing corrected. <lb/>A disadvantage of the matrix-based TSMA method relative <lb/>to the k-mer-based approach is that a PWM assumes inde-<lb/>pendence among positions, making it impossible to construct <lb/>a PWM that assigns high scores to AAAAAA and CCCCCC, <lb/>but a low score to ACACAC. <lb/>An advantage of our matrix-based approach is the possibil-<lb/>ity of detecting clusters of putative binding sites. This can be <lb/>done by counting regions with many hits using positional hit <lb/>information or by simply applying a hit count threshold per <lb/>sequence, e.g., only sequences with more than some number <lb/>of hits are considered. Homotypic clusters of RBP binding <lb/>sites may play a similar role as clusters of transcription <lb/>factors [41]. <lb/>D. Spectrum Motif Analysis identifies RBPs with nonrandom <lb/>arrangement of substrate sites in a ranked list of transcripts. <lb/>A limitation of the TSMA method described above is that <lb/>it will only capture those RBPs for which putative substrate <lb/>sequences are statistically significantly enriched among a <lb/>foreground defined using a collection of either the most or <lb/>least differentially-regulated genes. As an alternative method, <lb/>we present Spectrum Motif Analysis (SPMA), which is an <lb/>effort to more broadly and generally identify non-random <lb/>distributions of RBP substrate sequences in an ordered list <lb/>of genes without having to pre-define a specific foreground <lb/>set (compare Figures 2A and 3A). <lb/>Instead of using an arbitrary threshold (e.g., p-value less <lb/>than or equal to 0.05) to assign transcripts to a single <lb/>foreground set, SPMA subdivides the entire list of rank-<lb/>ordered transcripts into a number of foreground sets (bins) <lb/>of equal width, calculates enrichment scores for k-mers or <lb/>PWM motifs in each bin as described above, and then <lb/>searches for non-random bin-wise assortment of k-mer or <lb/>matrix hit frequencies associated with individual RBPs. <lb/>SPMA thereby helps to illuminate the relationship between <lb/>RBP binding evidence (putative binding site enrichment) and <lb/>the transcript sorting criterion (e.g., fold change between <lb/>treatment and control samples). Figure 3A illustrates how <lb/>the sorted list of transcripts is divided into bins. <lb/>1) Spectrum plots: The results of SPMA are displayed <lb/>as spectrum plots, compact graphical representations of the <lb/>distribution of putative binding sites for a single RBP, across <lb/>a range of transcripts (which are sorted in a meaningful way). <lb/>A spectrum plot visualizes putative binding site enrichment <lb/>or depletion, and associated p-values, for an RBP motif <lb/>across the spectrum of transcripts. Spectrum plots are one-<lb/>dimensional heatmaps, where red-blue coloring encodes the <lb/>putative binding site enrichment values and the columns <lb/>are the individual bins of transcripts. Significance levels are <lb/>indicated by one, two, or three asterisks (p-value less than <lb/>or equal to 0.05, 0.01, and 0.001, respectively). Examples of <lb/>spectrum plots are shown in panels B and C of figure 3. <lb/>2) Spectrum plot classification: SPMA generates one <lb/>spectrum plot for each RBP motif in the motif database. With <lb/>174 motifs currently available, it is imperative to provide a <lb/>means to aid in the identification of biologically meaningful <lb/>spectrum plots that exhibit non-random patterns. A typical <lb/>non-random pattern is shown in the first spectrum plot in <lb/>figure 3C, where the enrichment values are observed to <lb/>positively correlate with the sorting criterion. This type of <lb/>positive linear relationship between RBP motif enrichment <lb/>values and sorting criterion might arise in a situation where <lb/>transcripts are sorted according to their fold change between <lb/>treatment and control groups and the target transcripts of <lb/>the RBP are collectively upregulated in the treatment group, <lb/>perhaps via stabilization by the RBP itself. Transite further <lb/>aids the user in the process of identifying spectrum plots <lb/>with a meaningful pattern-one that might be indicative <lb/>of an underlying biological process-by separating them <lb/>from spectrum plots with more random distributions of motif <lb/>enrichment, which are more likely to occur by chance. Each <lb/>spectrum plot is automatically labeled either non-random or <lb/>random, based on three criteria. (1) the adjusted R 2 of a poly-<lb/>nomial model fit, (2) the local consistency score, and (3) the <lb/>number of bins with a significant enrichment or depletion of <lb/>putative binding sites. For (1), polynomial regression models <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>B SPMA: Motif enrichment analysis <lb/>k-mer-based SPMA <lb/>matrix-based SPMA <lb/>Perform matrix-based TSMA on binned data and <lb/>visualize enrichment values with spectrum plots: <lb/>Perform k-mer-based TSMA on binned data and <lb/>visualize k-mer enrichment values with spectrum plots: <lb/>C SPMA: Classification of distribution of putative binding sites (motif enrichment) <lb/>non-random -strong positive linear relationship <lb/>non-random -negative linear relationship <lb/>random -inherently inconsistent spectrum <lb/>A <lb/>transcripts upregulated in condition 1 <lb/>Gene expression profile <lb/>Condition 1 <lb/>Condition 2 <lb/>transcripts upregulated in condition 2 <lb/>high negative log fold change <lb/>log fold change close to zero <lb/>high positive log fold change <lb/>Subdivision of fold change sorted transcripts into n foreground sets <lb/>n foreground sets <lb/>SPMA: Foreground and background sets <lb/>non-random -nonlinear relationship <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>depleted <lb/>enriched <lb/>depleted <lb/>enriched <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>background set <lb/>Fig. 3. Schematic figure of Spectrum Motif Analysis. (A) Similar to TSMA, in SPMA the input data usually comes from differential gene expression <lb/>analysis. Transcripts are sorted by some measure of differential expression (e.g., fold change or signal-to-noise ratio) and then the entire spectrum of <lb/>transcripts is subdivided into a number of foreground &quot;bins&quot;. (B) The motif enrichment step is identical to TSMA. SPMA results are visualized as spectrum <lb/>plots, which are one-dimensional heatmaps of motif enrichment values, where the columns correspond to the bins and the color encodes the enrichment <lb/>value (strong depletion in dark blue to strong enrichment in dark red) of a particular k-mer or PWM. (C) The distribution of putative binding sites (as <lb/>visualized by spectrum plots) is deemed random or non-random (i.e., putative binding sites are distributed in a way that suggest biological relevance), <lb/>based on a number of criteria described in section Spectrum plot classification. A polynomial model is fit to the enrichment values of the foreground sets <lb/>to characterize the relationship between the sorting criterion (e.g., fold change) and the enrichment values. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Fig. 4. The Transite website analysis submission forms for TSMA and SPMA make the Transite functionality accessible to scientists outside the R <lb/>community. (A) Users of the website can submit TSMA and SPMA jobs in five simple steps, which include the specification of foreground and background <lb/>sets and additional optional parameters. (B) For SPMA, users are asked to upload a file that contains two columns, an identifier column that holds RefSeq <lb/>identifiers or gene symbols, and a value column, which is used to sort the transcripts (e.g., by fold change). Shown here is the configuration panel for <lb/>SPMA. (C) Part of the k-mer-based TSMA submission form, where sequence region, k-mer length, and other parameters can be specified. (D) The website <lb/>supports analysis runs with the Transite motif database as well as with user-defined motifs, where both PWMs and lists of hexamers and heptamers are <lb/>supported. <lb/>of various degrees are fitted to the spectrum of enrichment <lb/>values, and the model that best reflects the true nature of <lb/>the data is selected by means of the F-test. Models with <lb/>positive and negative coefficients of the linear term (depicting <lb/>increasing and decreasing linear relationships) are illustrated <lb/>in the first two examples of figure 3C, respectively (see <lb/>section 6.2 of the supplement for details on the polynomial <lb/>model approach). With approach (2), a local consistency <lb/>score quantifies the local noise of the spectrum by calculating <lb/>the deviance between the linear interpolation of the scores <lb/>of two bins separated by exactly one other, and the observed <lb/>score of the middle bin, for each position in the spectrum. <lb/>The lower the score, the more consistent the trend in the <lb/>spectrum plot (see section 6.1 of the supplement for a formal <lb/>definition of the local consistency score and section 2 for <lb/>details on the Monte Carlo sampling procedure of the null <lb/>distribution of the score). Spectrum plots are classified as <lb/>non-random if (1) the adjusted R 2 of the polynomial fit is <lb/>greater than or equal to 0.4, and (2) the p-value associated <lb/>with the local consistency score is less than or equal to <lb/>5 * 10 −6 , and (3) at least 10% of the bins have significant <lb/>(α = 0.05) enrichment or depletion of putative binding sites. <lb/>E. Transite R package and website <lb/>To make gene expression dataset analysis for assigning pu-<lb/>tative RBPs widely available to the scientific community, the <lb/>Transite analysis platform is hosted at https://transite.mit.edu. <lb/>Both Transcript Set Motif Analysis and Spectrum Motif <lb/>Analysis are available with customizable user-friendly forms <lb/>and familiarity with the R programming language is not <lb/>required (Figure 4). The full functionality of Transite is <lb/>also provided as an R/Bioconductor package to ensure a <lb/>seamless integration into existing bioinformatics workflows. <lb/>The source code of the Transite package is hosted on GitHub. <lb/>Both website and R package support motif enrichment anal-<lb/>ysis with user-defined motifs, in addition to the 174 motifs <lb/>provided by the Transite motif database, enabling users to <lb/>search for enrichment of any motif in a discrete set of genes <lb/>or a rank ordered list. <lb/>F. Transite identifies RBPs known to be involved in the DNA <lb/>damage response <lb/>As an application of Transite-based RBP scoring, we <lb/>analyzed a data set of non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) <lb/>patients at diagnosis or at recurrence after cisplatin-based <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>cumulative frequency <lb/>F <lb/>C <lb/>E <lb/>D <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>cumulative frequency <lb/>A <lb/>non−targets <lb/>ELAVL1 CLIP-targets (entire mature mRNA) <lb/>ELAVL1 CLIP-targets (only 3&apos; UTR) <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>log(FC) <lb/>ELAVL1 putative binding site log(enrichment) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>TIA1 putative binding site log(enrichment) <lb/>non−targets <lb/>TIA1 CLIP-targets (entire mature mRNA) <lb/>TIA1 CLIP-targets (only 3&apos; UTR) <lb/>**** <lb/>*** <lb/>log(FC) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>-0.25 0.00 0.50 <lb/>-0.2 0.0 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>B <lb/>untreated <lb/>NSCLC <lb/>patients <lb/>NSCLC patients whose <lb/>tumors failed to respond to <lb/>platinum-based chemotherapy <lb/>gene expression profiles of <lb/>differential gene <lb/>expression analysis <lb/>T <lb/>ACGU <lb/>identify potential post-transcriptional <lb/>regulators of resistance to chemotherapy <lb/>with Transite <lb/>RBP <lb/>R² <lb/>slope p-value <lb/>ELAVL1, ELAVL3 <lb/>0.841 0.994 0.000002 <lb/>TIA1 <lb/>0.804 0.868 0.000002 <lb/>RALY <lb/>0.804 0.868 0.000002 <lb/>HNRNPC <lb/>0.801 0.800 0.000003 <lb/>HNRNPCL1 <lb/>0.801 0.800 0.000002 <lb/>TIA1 <lb/>0.798 0.764 0.000002 <lb/>CPEB3, CPEB2 <lb/>0.787 0.644 0.000003 <lb/>U2AF2 <lb/>0.783 0.613 0.000002 <lb/>PCBP2-4 <lb/>0.729 -0.695 0.000241 <lb/>CPEB3, CPEB4 <lb/>0.727 0.877 0.000002 <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>untreated tumors <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>recurrent tumors <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>untreated tumors <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>recurrent tumors <lb/>Fig. 5. SPMA identifies ELAVL1 and TIA1 motifs as highly enriched in recurrent NSCLC patients. (A) Differential gene expression analysis was performed <lb/>on samples of patients with untreated NSCLC tumors and patients with recurrent tumors. (B) Transite was used to identify RBPs whose targets were <lb/>overrepresented among upregulated genes in samples of recurrent tumors. Shown is a table of k-mer-based SPMA showing RBPs with highly non-random <lb/>motif enrichment pattern. Among the top hits are ELAVL1, TIA1, and hnRNPC. (C) Spectrum plot from SPMA depicting the distribution of putative <lb/>ELAVL1 binding sites across all transcripts. The transcripts are sorted by ascending signal-to-noise ratio. Transcripts downregulated in resistant samples <lb/>relative to untreated samples are on the left, and those upregulated are on the right of the spectrum. Putative binding sites of ELAVL1 are highly enriched <lb/>in transcripts upregulated in resistant cells (shown in red) and highly depleted in transcripts downregulated in resistant cells (shown in blue). (D) Spectrum <lb/>plot of putative TIA1 binding sites using same transcript order as in panel C. (E) Enrichment of ELAVL1 targets in resistant NSCLC cells is recapitulated <lb/>in an independent HITS-CLIP experiment (publicly available data). The distribution of fold changes of transcripts that have ELAVL1 binding sites is shifted <lb/>in the positive direction, even more so when the binding sites are in the 3 -UTR. The p-values were calculated with the one-sided Kolmogorov-Smirnov <lb/>test. (F) As in panel E, transcripts with TIA1 binding sites are upregulated in resistant cells according to an iCLIP experimenmt, confirming results from <lb/>SPMA. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>chemotherapy (GEO Series accession GSE7880) in order to <lb/>prioritize RBPs that may influence the response of these <lb/>patients to chemotherapy. We ranked the gene expression <lb/>changes between pre-treatment and recurrent patients based <lb/>on signal-to-noise ratio where transcripts present in higher <lb/>quantities in recurrent patients had positive values and <lb/>those upregulated in naive patients had negative values (see <lb/>Figure 5A for schematic). The results of k-mer-based and <lb/>matrix-based TSMA and SPMA (including all 174 motifs) <lb/>are available as sample output on the Transite website, <lb/>About page, Example output section. Ranking the Transite <lb/>output of both SPMA runs by adjusted R squared (ARS) <lb/>revealed ELAVL1 and TIA1 to be among the top RBPs <lb/>predicted to be associated with the 3 -UTRs of transcripts <lb/>upregulated in recurrent patients relative to untreated patients <lb/>(Figure 5B shows top 10 RBPs in k-mer-based SPMA). <lb/>Individual spectrum plots for ELAVL1 (Figure 5C) or TIA1 <lb/>(Figure 5D) demonstrated consistent behavior of these motifs <lb/>across the gene expression continuum, being enriched in <lb/>3 -UTRs of genes that are up in recurrent patients and <lb/>depleted in 3 -UTRs of genes that are up in naive patients. <lb/>Importantly, upregulation of ELAVL1 and TIA1-target mR-<lb/>NAs was further validated by analyzing the distribution of <lb/>known CLIP-Seq identified targets [42,43] for these two <lb/>RBPs (Figure 5E and 5F). Moreover, both ELAVL1 [44] <lb/>and TIA1 [45] are known to be involved in the DNA damage <lb/>response. The fact that two well-known players in the DNA <lb/>damage response are among the top hits of the motif analysis <lb/>provides confidence that Transite&apos;s predictions are likely to <lb/>reflect bona fide regulators of the DNA damage response <lb/>and drivers of chemoresistance. Although CLIP-Seq-defined <lb/>target mRNAs remain the gold standard for known RBP <lb/>targets, there are very few RBPs that have been subjected <lb/>to extensive CLIP-Seq analysis. In the absence of this data, <lb/>Transite currently utilizes information about putative binding <lb/>sites from 174 motifs, covering 142 distinct RBPs. Therefore, <lb/>Transite presents the possibility of identifying RBPs whose <lb/>true targets as identified by CLIP-Seq and related methods <lb/>are currently unknown, thus nominating novel RBPs as <lb/>putative modulators of chemoresistance or other biological <lb/>processes, in order to prioritize those RBPs for further <lb/>analysis by CLIP. <lb/>G. Motif analysis of the non-small cell lung cancer response <lb/>to cisplatin treatment identfies hnRNPC as a potential mod-<lb/>ulator of resistance to chemotherapy <lb/>The data in Figure 5 shows that Transite analysis can <lb/>identify known RBPs involved in the DNA damage response. <lb/>We were particularly interested in using Transite as a tool <lb/>to discover new biology related to the DDR in data from <lb/>human clinical trials. We therefore focused on hnRNPC, <lb/>one of the highest-scoring RBPs that emerged from our <lb/>analysis of chemoresistant NSCLC patients, and has not <lb/>to our knowledge been strongly implicated in the response <lb/>to chemotherapy-induced DNA damage [46]. As shown in <lb/>Figure 6A, the spectrum plot of the distribution of putative <lb/>hnRNPC binding sites shows a strong enrichment of mRNAs <lb/>with hnRNPC motifs in their 3 -UTRs in patients with tumor <lb/>recurrence after platinum therapy. This Transite prediction <lb/>was independently confirmed by analysis of iCLIP-defined <lb/>target mRNAs [47], which also showed an overrepresentation <lb/>of hnRNPC targets in upregulated transcripts in recurrent <lb/>patients (Figure 6B), with those with binding in the 3 -UTR <lb/>showing the strongest enrichment. <lb/>H. hnRNPC modulates sensitivity to cisplatin <lb/>To experimentally validate these Transite results, we ex-<lb/>amined the effect of knockdown or over-expression of hn-<lb/>RNPC on sensitivity to cisplatin treatment in T6a murine <lb/>lung carcinoma cells. Colony formation assays in T6a cells <lb/>demonstrated that hnRNPC over-expression promoted re-<lb/>sistance to cisplatin as evidenced by a 1.6 fold increase <lb/>in the number of surviving colonies (Figure 6C, red bar). <lb/>Conversely, siRNA-downregulation of hnRNPC significantly <lb/>enhanced T6a cell sensitivity to cisplatin as evidenced by a <lb/>5-fold decrease in the number of colonies formed by cells <lb/>treated with hnRNPC siRNA compared to those of control <lb/>siRNA-treated cells after cisplatin treatment (Figure 6C, blue <lb/>bar). These data indicate that hnRNPC is a key player in <lb/>mediating resistance of NSCLC cells to chemotherapy, and <lb/>demonstrate that our computational approach can identify <lb/>new RBPs influencing the DDR. To independently vali-<lb/>date the importance of hnRNPC in mediating chemother-<lb/>apy response in patients, we took advantage of a unique <lb/>adjuvant chemotherapy trial, JBR.10 (Figure 6D). In this <lb/>trial, early stage NSCLC patients had their tumors surgi-<lb/>cally resected and subjected to gene expression profiling. <lb/>Patients were then randomized to receive cisplatin / vi-<lb/>norelbine doublet chemotherapy or observation and palliative <lb/>care [48](GSE14814), allowing us to specifically assess <lb/>the role of hnRNPC in the response to chemotherapy. We <lb/>focused our analysis on stage 2 patients, as their benefit from <lb/>adjuvant chemotherapy is most pronounced. Separation of <lb/>patients based on hnRNPC expression revealed that patients <lb/>whose tumors display low expression of hnRNPC benefited <lb/>significantly from chemotherapy in terms of survival (Fig-<lb/>ure 6D, right panel, p = 0.019) while patients whose tumors <lb/>have high hnRNPC expression did not benefit (Figure 6D, <lb/>left panel, p = 0.68). Together these data define hnRNPC <lb/>as an important new RBP involved in the chemotherapeutic <lb/>response in NSCLC and suggest that Transite is a highly <lb/>effective tool to pinpoint novel RBPs that drive chemoresis-<lb/>tance in human cancer patients. <lb/>IV. DISCUSSION <lb/>Despite their crucial role in post-transcriptional regulation <lb/>of gene expression, the majority of RNA-binding proteins <lb/>(RBPs) have unknown functions. To help understand the <lb/>influence of RBPs on their target transcripts, we developed <lb/>Transite, a novel computational method for the analysis of <lb/>the regulatory role of RBPs in various cellular processes <lb/>for which differential gene expression data, or other rele-<lb/>vant gene sets are available. Our analysis is based on the <lb/>fact that most RBPs recognize short linear oligonucleotide <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>C <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>log(FC) <lb/>cumulative frequency <lb/>non−targets <lb/>hnRNPC CLIP-targets (entire mature mRNA) <lb/>hnRNPC CLIP-targets (only 3&apos; UTR) <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>v e c t o r <lb/>h n R <lb/>N <lb/>P C <lb/>o v e r e x p r e s s i o n <lb/>c o n t r o l s i R <lb/>N <lb/>A <lb/>h n R <lb/>N <lb/>P C <lb/>s i R <lb/>N <lb/>A <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>% survival 4 µM Cisplatin (vs Veh) <lb/>T6a cells <lb/>+ <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ + <lb/>+ + <lb/>++ <lb/>++ ++ + + + <lb/>p = 0.68 HR = 0.82 (0.32 -2.13) <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>observation <lb/>chemotherapy <lb/>disease-specific survival probability <lb/>hnRNPC high <lb/>18 16 13 10 8 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>17 14 12 12 12 10 8 <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>time in years <lb/>strata <lb/>number at risk <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>++++ ++ <lb/>+ <lb/>p = 0.019 HR = 0.29 (0.87 -1.04) <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>disease-specific survival probability <lb/>hnRNPC low <lb/>9 6 4 1 1 1 1 1 1 0 <lb/>16 13 12 12 10 9 8 4 1 1 <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>time in years <lb/>strata <lb/>number at risk <lb/>observation <lb/>chemotherapy <lb/>hnRNPC putative binding site log(enrichment) <lb/>log(enrichment) <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0.2 0.0 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>untreated tumors <lb/>highly upregulated in <lb/>recurrent tumors <lb/>Fig. 6. hnRNPC modulates sensitivity to cisplatin. (A) Spectrum plot from k-mer-based SPMA depicting the distribution of putative hnRNPC binding <lb/>sites across all transcripts. The transcripts are sorted by ascending signal-to-noise ratio from lowest to highest abundance in resistant relative to untreated <lb/>samples. Putative hnRNPC binding sites are highly enriched in the upregulated fraction of transcripts. (B) Enrichment of hnRNPC binding sites in <lb/>upregulated transcripts is independently confirmed by CLIP experiments. The p-values were calculated with the one-sided Kolmogorov-Smirnov test. (C) <lb/>siRNA-mediated reduction in hnRNPC levels significantly impairs long-term survival of T6a cells in response to cisplatin (blue bar). Overexpression of <lb/>hnRNPC (red bar) protects against cisplatin-induced cell death of T6a cells in colony formation assays. Bar graphs represent percent number of colonies <lb/>formed, normalized to untreated control cells. White bars represent control cells transfected with control vehicles (control siRNA or empty pcDNA). Error <lb/>bars represent standard deviation among 3 replicates. (D) High expression of hnRNPC impedes the efficacy of platinum-based chemotherapy in patients <lb/>with stage 2 disease from the JBR.10 lung cancer adjuvant chemotherapy trial (GSE14814). The p-value was calculated with the log-rank test (HR is <lb/>Hazard Ratio). hnRNPC low group = patients with hnRNPC expression Z-scores of less than or equal to −0.2, and hnRNPC high group = patients with <lb/>hnRNPC expression Z-scores greater than or equal to 0.2. <lb/>sequences whose over-representation can be computed from <lb/>gene expression data, and that a large collection pre-existing <lb/>motif data for RBPs has been compiled in publicly available <lb/>databases [29,30]. <lb/>It is important to note that not all RBPs have strong motif <lb/>preferences, and that there may be considerable redundancy <lb/>in motif recognition by multiple RBPs. Furthermore, their in <lb/>vitro-derived motifs may not always reflect motifs derived <lb/>from in vivo binding analysis. These caveats have raised <lb/>questions about the ability of consensus motifs and PWMs <lb/>to accurately predict RBP targets a priori on a genome-wide <lb/>scale, and have led to the development of more sophisticated <lb/>approaches for predicting specific RBP RNA targets [49,50]. <lb/>In contrast, Transite does not make any specific RBP RNA <lb/>target predictions, and instead simply looks at the statistical <lb/>distribution of RBP motif representation in sets of expressed <lb/>genes to infer putative roles for specific RBPs in some <lb/>biological process. <lb/>By using two approaches to identify non-random distri-<lb/>butions of RBP-binding motifs, followed by back-mapping <lb/>of those motifs onto those of 174 known RBPs, Transite <lb/>identified 3 RBPs involved in the human DDR which we <lb/>could further validate based on independent CLIP-Seq data <lb/>of their known mRNA targets in cells, rather than using mo-<lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>tifs derived from in vitro sequence libraries. These findings <lb/>suggest that, although there are limitations to utilizing in <lb/>vitro-derived motifs, Transite serves as an excellent discovery <lb/>tool for new biology. Moreover, since users can define their <lb/>own motifs in addition to those from the database, users are <lb/>able to upload motifs from CLIP-Seq data of their favorite <lb/>RBP and use that as a means to analyze enrichment in <lb/>preexisting data sets. <lb/>To further demonstrate the utility of Transite, we per-<lb/>formed an analysis of human NSCLC patient data we were <lb/>able to recover previously-known biology and also identify <lb/>novel sources of chemoresistance. Well-known players in the <lb/>DNA damage response such as ELAVL1 and TIA1 were <lb/>among the top hits in the tumor resistance gene expression <lb/>data set, showing that our approach is consistent with previ-<lb/>ous DNA damage response literature. Transite was also able <lb/>to identify hnRNPC as a new potential modulator of cisplatin <lb/>sensitivity in NSCLC patients. Experimental validation of the <lb/>in silico prediction further provides independent support for <lb/>a critical role for hnRNPC in mediating resistance of NSCLC <lb/>cells to chemotherapy, which was independently validated in <lb/>an additional NSCLC patients data set. <lb/>Transite is a versatile tool that can be used with any type <lb/>of gene expression data, the only requirements being a list <lb/>of gene identifiers and some means to separate foreground <lb/>and background sets or rank the gene list. Examples of types <lb/>of data users may utilize Transite to analyze are: (1) search-<lb/>ing for RBP motif enrichment in 5 or 3 -UTRs of genes <lb/>whose translational efficiency changes in response to some <lb/>stimulus as measured by ribosome or polysome profiling. <lb/>(2) searching for enrichment of RBP motifs in mRNAs that <lb/>are localized to specific sub-cellular compartments. (3) de <lb/>novo motif analysis in the entire mRNA of gene expression <lb/>changes upon knockdown of a nuclease of unknown function. <lb/>These are just a few examples of the versatility of Transite. <lb/>The Transite website (https://transite.mit.edu) makes this tool <lb/>accessible to a broad group of scientists and provides insight <lb/>as to how key post-transcriptional regulators contribute to <lb/>the concerted regulation and function of specific cellular <lb/>processes. With Transite, the large body of gene expression <lb/>data from microarray and RNA sequencing experiments can <lb/>be further leveraged to identify changes in mRNA expression <lb/>associated with specific RBPs. In this way, hypotheses can <lb/>be generated regarding which RBPs interact preferentially <lb/>with mRNAs that are specific to a particular condition. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">AVAILABILITY <lb/>The Transite website is available at https://transite.mit.edu. <lb/>For workflow integration and advanced analysis, the Transite <lb/>functionality is also offered as an R/Bioconductor package <lb/>at https://www.bioconductor.org. The Transite source code is <lb/>hosted on GitHub (https://github.com/kkrismer/transite). <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We wish to thank all members of the Yaffe and He-<lb/>mann labs for helpful advice and discussions. Additionally, <lb/>we thank Anne E. van Vlimmeren for feedback on the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>This work was supported by scholarships of the Mar-<lb/>shall Plan Foundation and the Austrian Federal Ministry for <lb/>Education (to K.K., A.G., and T.B.), National Institutes of <lb/>Health (NIH) grants R01-ES015339, R35-ES028374, U54-<lb/>CA112967, the Charles and Marjorie Holloway Foundation, <lb/>the and a Starr Cancer Consortium Award I9-A9-077 (to <lb/>M.B.Y. and I.G.C.). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest statement: None declared. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] Gerstberger, S., Hafner, M., and Tuschl, T. (12, 2014) A census of <lb/>human RNA-binding proteins. Nat. Rev. Genet., 15(12), 829-845. <lb/>[2] Lunde, B. M., Moore, C., and Varani, G. (Jun, 2007) RNA-binding <lb/>proteins: modular design for efficient function. Nat. Rev. Mol. Cell <lb/>Biol., 8(6), 479-490. <lb/>[3] Stumpo, D. J., Lai, W. S., and Blackshear, P. J. (2010) Inflammation: <lb/>cytokines and RNA-based regulation. Wiley Interdiscip Rev RNA, 1(1), <lb/>60-80. <lb/>[4] Sugiura, R., Satoh, R., Ishiwata, S., Umeda, N., and Kita, A. (2011) <lb/>Role of RNA-Binding Proteins in MAPK Signal Transduction Path-<lb/>way. J Signal Transduct, 2011, 109746. <lb/>[5] Pereira, B., Billaud, M., and Almeida, R. (07, 2017) RNA-Binding <lb/>Proteins in Cancer: Old Players and New Actors. Trends Cancer, 3(7), <lb/>506-528. <lb/>[6] Cooper, T. A., Wan, L., and Dreyfuss, G. (Feb, 2009) RNA and <lb/>disease. Cell, 136(4), 777-793. <lb/>[7] Licatalosi, D. D. and Darnell, R. B. (Jan, 2010) RNA processing <lb/>and its regulation: global insights into biological networks. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Genet., 11(1), 75-87. <lb/>[8] Lukong, K. E., Chang, K. W., Khandjian, E. W., and Richard, S. (Aug, <lb/>2008) RNA-binding proteins in human genetic disease. Trends Genet., <lb/>24(8), 416-425. <lb/>[9] Reinhardt, H. C., Cannell, I. G., Morandell, S., and Yaffe, M. B. (Jan, <lb/>2011) Is post-transcriptional stabilization, splicing and translation of <lb/>selective mRNAs a key to the DNA damage response?. Cell Cycle, <lb/>10(1), 23-27. <lb/>[10] Rieger, K. E. and Chu, G. (2004) Portrait of transcriptional responses <lb/>to ultraviolet and ionizing radiation in human cells. Nucleic Acids Res., <lb/>32(16), 4786-4803. <lb/>[11] Gasch, A. P., Huang, M., Metzner, S., Botstein, D., Elledge, S. J., <lb/>and Brown, P. O. (Oct, 2001) Genomic expression responses to DNA-<lb/>damaging agents and the regulatory role of the yeast ATR homolog <lb/>Mec1p. Mol. Biol. Cell, 12(10), 2987-3003. <lb/>[12] Matsuoka, S., Ballif, B. A., Smogorzewska, A., McDonald, E. R., <lb/>Hurov, K. E., Luo, J., Bakalarski, C. E., Zhao, Z., Solimini, N., <lb/>Lerenthal, Y., Shiloh, Y., Gygi, S. P., and Elledge, S. J. (May, 2007) <lb/>ATM and ATR substrate analysis reveals extensive protein networks <lb/>responsive to DNA damage. Science, 316(5828), 1160-1166. <lb/>[13] Paulsen, R. D., Soni, D. V., Wollman, R., Hahn, A. T., Yee, M. C., <lb/>Guan, A., Hesley, J. A., Miller, S. C., Cromwell, E. F., Solow-Cordero, <lb/>D. E., Meyer, T., and Cimprich, K. A. (Jul, 2009) A genome-wide <lb/>siRNA screen reveals diverse cellular processes and pathways that <lb/>mediate genome stability. Mol. Cell, 35(2), 228-239. <lb/>[14] Hurov, K. E., Cotta-Ramusino, C., and Elledge, S. J. (Sep, 2010) <lb/>A genetic screen identifies the Triple T complex required for DNA <lb/>damage signaling and ATM and ATR stability. Genes Dev., 24(17), <lb/>1939-1950. <lb/>[15] Floyd, S. R., Pacold, M. E., Huang, Q., Clarke, S. M., Lam, F. C., <lb/>Cannell, I. G., Bryson, B. D., Rameseder, J., Lee, M. J., Blake, E. J., <lb/>Fydrych, A., Ho, R., Greenberger, B. A., Chen, G. C., Maffa, A., <lb/>Del Rosario, A. M., Root, D. E., Carpenter, A. E., Hahn, W. C., <lb/>Sabatini, D. M., Chen, C. C., White, F. M., Bradner, J. E., and Yaffe, <lb/>M. B. (Jun, 2013) The bromodomain protein Brd4 insulates chromatin <lb/>from DNA damage signalling. Nature, 498(7453), 246-250. <lb/>[16] Adamson, B., Smogorzewska, A., Sigoillot, F. D., King, R. W., and <lb/>Elledge, S. J. (Feb, 2012) A genome-wide homologous recombination <lb/>screen identifies the RNA-binding protein RBMX as a component of <lb/>the DNA-damage response. Nat. Cell Biol., 14(3), 318-328. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[17] Wilker, E. W., van Vugt, M. A., Artim, S. A., Huang, P. H., Petersen, <lb/>C. P., Reinhardt, H. C., Feng, Y., Sharp, P. A., Sonenberg, N., White, <lb/>F. M., and Yaffe, M. B. (Mar, 2007) 14-3-3sigma controls mitotic <lb/>translation to facilitate cytokinesis. Nature, 446(7133), 329-332. <lb/>[18] Fan, J., Yang, X., Wang, W., Wood, W. H., Becker, K. G., and Gorospe, <lb/>M. (Aug, 2002) Global analysis of stress-regulated mRNA turnover <lb/>by using cDNA arrays. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A., 99(16), 10611-<lb/>10616. <lb/>[19] Kim, H. H., Abdelmohsen, K., and Gorospe, M. (Jul, 2010) Regulation <lb/>of HuR by DNA Damage Response Kinases. J Nucleic Acids, 2010. <lb/>[20] Ciccia, A. and Elledge, S. J. (Oct, 2010) The DNA damage response: <lb/>making it safe to play with knives. Mol. Cell, 40(2), 179-204. <lb/>[21] Jackson, S. P. and Bartek, J. (Oct, 2009) The DNA-damage response <lb/>in human biology and disease. Nature, 461(7267), 1071-1078. <lb/>[22] Cannell, I. G., Merrick, K. A., Morandell, S., Zhu, C. Q., Braun, <lb/>C. J., Grant, R. A., Cameron, E. R., Tsao, M. S., Hemann, M. T., and <lb/>Yaffe, M. B. (Nov, 2015) A Pleiotropic RNA-Binding Protein Controls <lb/>Distinct Cell Cycle Checkpoints to Drive Resistance of p53-Defective <lb/>Tumors to Chemotherapy. Cancer Cell, 28(5), 623-637. <lb/>[23] Reinhardt, H. C., Hasskamp, P., Schmedding, I., Morandell, S., van <lb/>Vugt, M. A., Wang, X., Linding, R., Ong, S. E., Weaver, D., Carr, <lb/>S. A., and Yaffe, M. B. (Oct, 2010) DNA damage activates a spatially <lb/>distinct late cytoplasmic cell-cycle checkpoint network controlled by <lb/>MK2-mediated RNA stabilization. Mol. Cell, 40(1), 34-49. <lb/>[24] Hong, S. (Dec, 2017) RNA Binding Protein as an Emerging Thera-<lb/>peutic Target for Cancer Prevention and Treatment. J Cancer Prev, <lb/>22(4), 203-210. <lb/>[25] Joughin, B. A., Naegle, K. M., Huang, P. H., Yaffe, M. B., Lauffen-<lb/>burger, D. A., and White, F. M. (Jan, 2009) An integrated comparative <lb/>phosphoproteomic and bioinformatic approach reveals a novel class <lb/>of MPM-2 motifs upregulated in EGFRvIII-expressing glioblastoma <lb/>cells. Mol Biosyst, 5(1), 59-67. <lb/>[26] Ritchie, M. E., Phipson, B., Wu, D., Hu, Y., Law, C. W., Shi, W., <lb/>and Smyth, G. K. (Jan, 2015) limma powers differential expression <lb/>analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray studies. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Res.,. <lb/>[27] Smyth, G. K. (2004) Linear models and empirical bayes methods for <lb/>assessing differential expression in microarray experiments. Stat Appl <lb/>Genet Mol Biol, 3, Article3. <lb/>[28] Benjamini, Y. and Hochberg, Y. (1995) Controlling the False Dis-<lb/>covery Rate: A Practical and Powerful Approach to Multiple Testing. <lb/>Journal of the Royal Statistical Society. Series B (Methodological), <lb/>57(1), 289-300. <lb/>[29] Weirauch, M. T., Yang, A., Albu, M., Cote, A. G., Montenegro-<lb/>Montero, A., Drewe, P., Najafabadi, H. S., Lambert, S. A., Mann, I., <lb/>Cook, K., Zheng, H., Goity, A., van Bakel, H., Lozano, J. C., Galli, <lb/>M., Lewsey, M. G., Huang, E., Mukherjee, T., Chen, X., Reece-Hoyes, <lb/>J. S., Govindarajan, S., Shaulsky, G., Walhout, A. J., Bouget, F. Y., <lb/>Ratsch, G., Larrondo, L. F., Ecker, J. R., and Hughes, T. R. (Sep, <lb/>2014) Determination and inference of eukaryotic transcription factor <lb/>sequence specificity. Cell, 158(6), 1431-1443. <lb/>[30] Cook, K. B., Kazan, H., Zuberi, K., Morris, Q., and Hughes, T. R. <lb/>(Jan, 2011) RBPDB: a database of RNA-binding specificities. Nucleic <lb/>Acids Res., 39(Database issue), D301-308. <lb/>[31] Tuerk, C. and Gold, L. (Aug, 1990) Systematic evolution of ligands <lb/>by exponential enrichment: RNA ligands to bacteriophage T4 DNA <lb/>polymerase. Science, 249(4968), 505-510. <lb/>[32] Ray, D., Kazan, H., Chan, E. T., Pena Castillo, L., Chaudhry, S., <lb/>Talukder, S., Blencowe, B. J., Morris, Q., and Hughes, T. R. (Jul, 2009) <lb/>Rapid and systematic analysis of the RNA recognition specificities of <lb/>RNA-binding proteins. Nat. Biotechnol., 27(7), 667-670. <lb/>[33] Garner, M. M. and Revzin, A. (Jul, 1981) A gel electrophoresis method <lb/>for quantifying the binding of proteins to specific DNA regions: <lb/>application to components of the Escherichia coli lactose operon <lb/>regulatory system. Nucleic Acids Res., 9(13), 3047-3060. <lb/>[34] Nishida, K., Frith, M. C., and Nakai, K. (Feb, 2009) Pseudocounts for <lb/>transcription factor binding sites. Nucleic Acids Res., 37(3), 939-944. <lb/>[35] Wickham, H. (2009) ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis, <lb/>Springer-Verlag New York, . <lb/>[36] Coppin, L., Leclerc, J., Vincent, A., Porchet, N., and Pigny, P. (Feb, <lb/>2018) Messenger RNA Life-Cycle in Cancer Cells: Emerging Role <lb/>of Conventional and Non-Conventional RNA-Binding Proteins?. Int J <lb/>Mol Sci, 19(3). <lb/>[37] Zykovich, A., Korf, I., and Segal, D. J. (Dec, 2009) Bind-n-Seq: <lb/>high-throughput analysis of in vitro protein-DNA interactions using <lb/>massively parallel sequencing. Nucleic Acids Res., 37(22), e151. <lb/>[38] Subramanian, A., Tamayo, P., Mootha, V. K., Mukherjee, S., Ebert, <lb/>B. L., Gillette, M. A., Paulovich, A., Pomeroy, S. L., Golub, T. R., <lb/>Lander, E. S., and Mesirov, J. P. (Oct, 2005) Gene set enrichment <lb/>analysis: a knowledge-based approach for interpreting genome-wide <lb/>expression profiles. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A., 102(43), 15545-<lb/>15550. <lb/>[39] Costa-Silva, J., Domingues, D., and Lopes, F. M. (2017) RNA-Seq <lb/>differential expression analysis: An extended review and a software <lb/>tool. PLoS ONE, 12(12), e0190152. <lb/>[40] Ashburner, M., Ball, C. A., Blake, J. A., Botstein, D., Butler, H., <lb/>Cherry, J. M., Davis, A. P., Dolinski, K., Dwight, S. S., Eppig, J. T., <lb/>Harris, M. A., Hill, D. P., Issel-Tarver, L., Kasarskis, A., Lewis, S., <lb/>Matese, J. C., Richardson, J. E., Ringwald, M., Rubin, G. M., and <lb/>Sherlock, G. (May, 2000) Gene ontology: tool for the unification of <lb/>biology. The Gene Ontology Consortium. Nat. Genet., 25(1), 25-29. <lb/>[41] Gotea, V., Visel, A., Westlund, J. M., Nobrega, M. A., Pennacchio, <lb/>L. A., and Ovcharenko, I. (May, 2010) Homotypic clusters of tran-<lb/>scription factor binding sites are a key component of human promoters <lb/>and enhancers. Genome Res., 20(5), 565-577. <lb/>[42] Kishore, S., Jaskiewicz, L., Burger, L., Hausser, J., Khorshid, M., and <lb/>Zavolan, M. (May, 2011) A quantitative analysis of CLIP methods <lb/>for identifying binding sites of RNA-binding proteins. Nat. Methods, <lb/>8(7), 559-564. <lb/>[43] Wang, Z., Kayikci, M., Briese, M., Zarnack, K., Luscombe, N. M., <lb/>Rot, G., Zupan, B., Curk, T., and Ule, J. (Oct, 2010) iCLIP predicts <lb/>the dual splicing effects of TIA-RNA interactions. PLoS Biol., 8(10), <lb/>e1000530. <lb/>[44] Masuda, K., Abdelmohsen, K., Kim, M. M., Srikantan, S., Lee, E. K., <lb/>Tominaga, K., Selimyan, R., Martindale, J. L., Yang, X., Lehrmann, <lb/>E., Zhang, Y., Becker, K. G., Wang, J. Y., Kim, H. H., and Gorospe, M. <lb/>(Mar, 2011) Global dissociation of HuR-mRNA complexes promotes <lb/>cell survival after ionizing radiation. EMBO J., 30(6), 1040-1053. <lb/>[45] Lal, A., Abdelmohsen, K., Pullmann, R., Kawai, T., Galban, S., <lb/>Yang, X., Brewer, G., and Gorospe, M. (Apr, 2006) Posttranscriptional <lb/>derepression of GADD45alpha by genotoxic stress. Mol. Cell, 22(1), <lb/>117-128. <lb/>[46] Shkreta, L. and Chabot, B. (Oct, 2015) The RNA Splicing Response <lb/>to DNA Damage. Biomolecules, 5(4), 2935-2977. <lb/>[47] Knig, J., Zarnack, K., Rot, G., Curk, T., Kayikci, M., Zupan, B., <lb/>Turner, D. J., Luscombe, N. M., and Ule, J. (Jul, 2010) iCLIP reveals <lb/>the function of hnRNP particles in splicing at individual nucleotide <lb/>resolution. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol., 17(7), 909-915. <lb/>[48] Winton, T., Livingston, R., Johnson, D., Rigas, J., Johnston, M., Butts, <lb/>C., Cormier, Y., Goss, G., Inculet, R., Vallieres, E., Fry, W., Bethune, <lb/>D., Ayoub, J., Ding, K., Seymour, L., Graham, B., Tsao, M. S., <lb/>Gandara, D., Kesler, K., Demmy, T., and Shepherd, F. (Jun, 2005) <lb/>Vinorelbine plus cisplatin vs. observation in resected non-small-cell <lb/>lung cancer. N. Engl. J. Med., 352(25), 2589-2597. <lb/>[49] Perron, G., Jandaghi, P., Solanki, S., Safisamghabadi, M., Storoz, C., <lb/>Karimzadeh, M., Papadakis, A. I., Arseneault, M., Scelo, G., Banks, <lb/>R. E., Tost, J., Lathrop, M., Tanguay, S., Brazma, A., Huang, S., <lb/>Brimo, F., Najafabadi, H. S., and Riazalhosseini, Y. (May, 2018) A <lb/>General Framework for Interrogation of mRNA Stability Programs <lb/>Identifies RNA-Binding Proteins that Govern Cancer Transcriptomes. <lb/>Cell Rep, 23(6), 1639-1650. <lb/>[50] Weyn-Vanhentenryck, S. M. and Zhang, C. (2016) mCarts: Genome-<lb/>Wide Prediction of Clustered Sequence Motifs as Binding Sites for <lb/>RNA-Binding Proteins. Methods Mol. Biol., 1421, 215-226. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>13 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
