<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> A target enrichment bait set for studying relationships among <lb/>ostariophysan fishes <lb/>Brant C. Faircloth* ,1,2 , Fernando Alda 2 , Kendra Hoekzema 3 , Michael D. Burns 3,4 , Claudio Oliveira 5 , <lb/>James S. Albert 6 , Bruno F. Melo 5 , Luz E. Ochoa 5 , Fábio F. Roxo 7 , Prosanta Chakrabarty 1,2 , Brian L. <lb/>Sidlauskas 3 , Michael E. Alfaro 8 <lb/>1 Department of Biological Sciences, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA, USA <lb/>2 Museum of Natural Science, Louisiana State University, Baton Rouge, LA, USA <lb/>3 Department of Fisheries and Wildlife, Oregon State University, Corvallis, OR, USA <lb/>4 Department of Biological Sciences, Western Michigan University, Kalamazoo, MI, USA <lb/>5 Departamento de Morfologia, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade Estadual Paulista, <lb/>Botucatu, SP, Brazil <lb/>6 Department of Biology, University of Louisiana at Lafayette, Lafayette, LA, USA <lb/>7 Departamento de Zoologia, Instituto de Biociências, Universidade Estadual Paulista, Botucatu, <lb/>SP, Brazil <lb/>8 Department of Ecology and Evolutionary Biology, University of California, Los Angeles, CA, USA <lb/>* Corresponding author: brant@faircloth-lab.org <lb/>Running Title: Ostariophysan UCE bait set <lb/>Word Count: <lb/>Key Words: ultraconserved elements, phylogenomics, phylogenetics, fishes <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Summary <lb/>1. Target enrichment of conserved nuclear loci has helped reconstruct evolutionary <lb/>relationships among a wide variety of species. While there are preexisting bait sets to <lb/>enrich a few hundred loci across all fishes or a thousand loci from acanthomorph fishes, <lb/>no bait set exists to enrich large numbers (&gt;1000 loci) of ultraconserved nuclear loci from <lb/>ostariophysans, the second largest actinopterygian superorder. <lb/>2. In this manuscript, we describe how we designed a bait set to enrich 2,708 ultraconserved <lb/>nuclear loci from ostariophysan fishes by combining an existing genome assembly with <lb/>low coverage sequence data collected from two ostariophysan lineages. <lb/>3. We perform a series of enrichment experiments using this bait set across the <lb/>ostariophysan Tree of Life, from the deepest splits among the major groups (&gt;150 MYA) <lb/>to more recent divergence events that have occured during the last 50 million years. <lb/>4. Our results demonstrate that the bait set we designed is useful for addressing <lb/>phylogenetic questions from the origin of crown ostariophysans to more recent <lb/>divergence events, and our in silico results suggest that this bait set may be useful for <lb/>addressing evolutionary questions in closely related groups of fishes, like Clupeiformes. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Target enrichment of highly conserved, phylogenetically informative loci (Faircloth et al., 2012) <lb/>has helped reconstruct and study the evolutionary history of organismal groups ranging from <lb/>cnidaria and arthropods to vertebrate clades such as birds and snakes (Moyle et al., 2016; <lb/>Streicher and Wiens, 2016; Branstetter et al., 2017; Quattrini et al., 2018). Among fishes, <lb/>researchers have designed enrichment bait sets that can collect data from hundreds of loci <lb/>shared among a majority of ray-finned fishes (Actinopterygii; 33,444 species) (Faircloth et al., <lb/>2013) or more than one thousand loci shared among actinopterygian subclades (Alfaro et al., <lb/>2018) like the group of spiny-finned fishes that dominates the world&apos;s oceans (Acanthomorpha; <lb/>19,244 species). However, no target enrichment bait set exists that is tailored to collect sequence <lb/>data from conserved loci shared by ostariophysan fishes, which constitute the second largest <lb/>actinopterygian superorder (Ostariophysi; 10,887 species). <lb/>This ostariophysan radiation (Figure 1) has produced the majority (~70%) of the world&apos;s <lb/>freshwater fishes and includes catfishes, the milkfish, tetras, minnows, electric knifefishes, and <lb/>their allies. The evolutionary success of ostariophysans may stem from shared derived possession <lb/>of an alarm substance called Schreckstoff (von Frisch, 1938) and/or a remarkable modification of <lb/>the anterior vertebral column known as the Weberian apparatus (Weber, 1820; Rosen et al., <lb/>1970), which enhances hearing by transmitting sound vibrations from the swim bladder to the <lb/>ear. Morphological (Fink and Fink, 1981; Fink and Fink, 1996) and molecular studies (Nakatani et <lb/>al., 2011; Betancur-R et al., 2013; Arcila et al., 2017; Chakrabarty et al., 2017) have demonstrated <lb/>monophyly of the clade and provided numerous hypotheses of relationships among the five <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>ostariophysan orders (reviewed in Chakrabarty et al., 2017; Arcila et al., 2017). Because several <lb/>of these hypotheses disagree substantially, major questions about ostariophysan evolution <lb/>remain unresolved. For example, some studies suggest that Siluriformes (catfishes) and <lb/>Gymnotiformes (electric knifefishes) are not each other&apos;s closest relatives, which would imply <lb/>that the electroreceptive capacities of these two orders evolved independently. Other studies <lb/>have suggested non-monophyly of Characiformes (Chakrabarty et al., 2017), which implies a <lb/>more complicated pattern of evolution in the morphology and development of oral dentition and <lb/>anatomical systems in this group, as well as suggesting an alternative biogeographical hypothesis <lb/>to the classical Gondwanan vicariance model (Lundberg, 1993; Sanmartín and Ronquist, 2004). A <lb/>similar debate concerns the composition of the immediate outgroups to Ostariophysi (see <lb/>discussion in Lavoué et al., 2014), which involve the enigmatic marine family Alepocephalidae <lb/>(slickheads), as well as the world&apos;s diverse radiation of Clupeiformes (herrings and anchovies), a <lb/>taxonomic order long allied to Ostariophysi on the basis of anatomical and molecular evidence <lb/>(Lecointre, 1995). <lb/>Though molecular and morphological hypotheses of interfamilial and intergeneric <lb/>relationships have been advanced within each of the five ostariophysan orders, substantial work <lb/>remains before our understanding of the evolutionary history of ostariophysans will rival that of <lb/>the best studied acanthomorph groups, such as cichlids (Brawand et al., 2014; Malinsky et al., <lb/>2018). The majority of previous work among ostariophysans has involved parsimony analysis of <lb/>osteological characters or model-based analysis of multilocus Sanger datasets, with even the <lb/>largest molecular studies (e.g. Schönhuth et al., 2018) including less than 15% of the species <lb/>diversity in the targeted clades. At the genome scale, ostariophysans have been included in <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>studies sampling across the diversity of ray-finned fishes (e.g. Faircloth et al., 2013; Hughes et al., <lb/>2018), while studies focusing on Ostariophysi have only recently begun to appear (Arcila et al., <lb/>2017; Chakrabarty et al., 2017; Dai et al., 2018). However, these genome-scale projects have <lb/>sampled less than 1% of total ostariophysan species diversity and have only begun to address <lb/>questions of interrelationships among families or genera. A robust and well-documented <lb/>approach to collect a large number of nuclear loci across ostariophysan orders and appropriate <lb/>outgroups will accelerate our ability to conduct taxon-rich studies of phylogenetic relationships <lb/>within and across the group and allow us to synthesize these data into a more complete and <lb/>modern picture of ostariophysan evolution than previously possible. <lb/>Here, we describe the design of an enrichment bait set that targets 2,708 conserved, <lb/>nuclear loci shared among ostariophysan fishes, and we empirically demonstrate how sequence <lb/>data collected using this bait set can resolve phylogenetic relationships at several levels of <lb/>divergence across the ostariophysan Tree of Life, from the deepest splits among ostariophysan <lb/>orders and their outgroup(s) (Otocephala, crown age 210-178 MYA; (Hughes et al., 2018)) to <lb/>more recent divergence events among lineages comprising the Gymnotiformes (crown age 86-<lb/>43 MYA) or Anostomoidea (crown age within 76-51 MYA; (Hughes et al., 2018)). An earlier <lb/>manuscript (Arcila et al., 2017) developed a bait set targeting 1,068 exon loci shared among <lb/>otophysans, one of the ostariophysan subclades that includes Characiformes, Cypriniformes, <lb/>Gymnotiformes, and Siluriformes (Figure 1). The bait set that we describe differs from that of <lb/>Arcila et al. (2017) by targeting a larger number of loci that includes coding and non-coding <lb/>regions shared among a larger and earlier diverging clade (i.e., ostariophysans and their <lb/>proximate outroup(s)). As with most bait sets targeting conserved loci shared among related <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>groups, the designs are generally complementary rather than incompatible, and researchers can <lb/>easily combine loci targeted by both designs to accomplish their research objectives. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Conserved element identification and bait design strategy <lb/>When we began this project, few genome assemblies other than zebrafish (Danio rerio) were <lb/>available to represent the diversity of ostariophysans. To identify conserved regions shared <lb/>among species within this group and design a target enrichment bait set to collect data from <lb/>these regions, we followed the general steps outlined in (Faircloth, 2017). This means that we <lb/>needed to identify a &quot;base&quot; genome (D. rerio; NCBI Genome GCA_000002035.2) against which to <lb/>align low coverage sequencing data from exemplar species representing the diversity of <lb/>ostariophysan lineages. We also needed to identify several exemplar lineages from which to <lb/>collect low coverage genome sequencing data. Our exemplar taxon selection strategy was to <lb/>identify and purchase commercially available fish species from orders related to Cypriniformes <lb/>(to which D. rerio belongs) because they were easy to &quot;collect&quot; and provided a ready source of <lb/>high quality DNA. As a result, we selected Apteronotus albifrons and Corydoras paleatus as our <lb/>exemplar taxa. These taxa represent the orders Gymnotiformes (electric knifefishes) and <lb/>Siluriformes (catfishes), respectively, and together with D. rerio, span three of the five orders <lb/>within Ostariophysi. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Low coverage genome sequencing <lb/>We purchased specimens of A. albifrons and C. paleatus from commercial wholesalers in the Los <lb/>Angeles, CA area, collected tissues following protocols approved by the University of California <lb/>Los Angeles Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee (Approval 2008-176-21), and extracted <lb/>DNA from each tissue using a commercial kit following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions (DNeasy, <lb/>Qiagen N.V.). After extraction, we quantified 2 μL of DNA using a Qubit fluorometer (Invitrogen, <lb/>Inc.) following the manufacturer&apos;s protocol, and we visualized 50-100 ng of each extract by <lb/>electrophoresis through 1.5% (w/v) agarose gel in TBE or TAE. Following this quality check, we <lb/>prepared 100 µL (~10 ng/μL) aliquots of extracted DNA, and we sheared each sample to 300-600 <lb/>bp in length using 5-10 cycles of sonication (High; 30 s on; 90 s off) on a BioRuptor (Diagenode, <lb/>Inc.). We prepared single-indexed sequencing libraries from 0.5-1.0 µg sheared DNA extracts <lb/>using a commercial library preparation kit (Kapa Biosystems, Inc.) and a set of custom-indexed <lb/>sequencing adapters (Faircloth and Glenn, 2012). Following library preparation, we size-selected <lb/>the C. paleatus library to span a range of 200-300 bp using agarose-gel-based size selection. We <lb/>did not size-select the A. albifrons library. We amplified both libraries using 6-10 cycles of PCR, <lb/>and we purified library amplifications using SPRI beads (Rohland and Reich, 2012). Following <lb/>purification, we checked the insert size distribution of each library using a BioAnalyzer (Agilent, <lb/>Inc.), and we quantified libraries using a commercial qPCR quantification kit (Kapa Biosystems, <lb/>Inc.). We ran each library on a separate lane of Illumina, paired-end, 100 bp sequencing (PE100) <lb/>by combining each library into a pool of unrelated (and differently indexed) samples, and we <lb/>sequenced each library pool using an Illumina HiSeq 2500 at the UCLA Neuroscience Genomics <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Core (UNGC). We demultiplexed the sequencing data using bcl2fastq 1.8.4 and allowed one base <lb/>pair mismatches between the expected and observed indexes (the index sequences we used <lb/>were robust to ≤ 3 insertion, deletion, or substitution errors). <lb/>Exemplar species validation <lb/>We validated the species identification of each sample by aligning FASTQ reads to a related <lb/>mtDNA genome using bwa mem v0.7.17 (Li, 2013), reducing the resulting BAM file to aligning <lb/>reads using samtools v0.1.18 (Li et al., 2009), and converting the BAM file of aligned reads back <lb/>to paired FASTQ reads using bedtools v2.17.0 (Quinlan and Hall, 2010). We assembled the <lb/>resulting FASTQ data using spades v3.10.1 (Nurk et al., 2013) with read correction, a kmer length <lb/>of 55, and the `--careful` assembly option. From the contig that resulted (which was either equal <lb/>to or slightly shorter than the general mtDNA sequence length for vertebrates), we used a <lb/>program within the phyluce package (Faircloth, 2015) to extract the portions of each contig that <lb/>were similar to COI sequences from Apteronotus (NCBI GenBank AB054132.1:5453-7012) and <lb/>Corydoras (NCBI GenBank JN988809.1). We then matched these extracted COI sequences against <lb/>the Species Level Barcode Records in the BOLD Systems Database (http://www.boldsystems.org; <lb/>search performed August 2018). For A. albifrons, the top hit (100% sequence identity) was A. <lb/>albifrons (NCBI GenBank AB054132.1; (Saitoh et al., 2003)), and for C. paleatus, the top publicly <lb/>available hit (99.85% sequence identity) was C. paleatus (NCBI GenBank JX111734.1; (Rosso et <lb/>al., 2012)). <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Conserved element identification and bait design <lb/>To identify conserved elements shared among the genomes of D. rerio, A. albifrons, and C. <lb/>paleatus, we followed the general workflow described in Faircloth (2017). Specifically, we <lb/>downloaded the genome assembly of D. rerio (hereafter danRer7; NCBI GCA_000002035.2) and <lb/>aligned the low-coverage, raw reads generated from A. albifrons and C. paleatus (hereafter <lb/>&quot;exemplar taxa&quot;) to this reference genome using stampy v1.0.21 with the substitution rate set to <lb/>0.05. After alignment, we used samtools to convert SAM files to BAM format, sort the BAM files, <lb/>and reduce sorted BAM files to only those reads mapping from the exemplar taxa to the base <lb/>genome. Using bedtools, we converted BAM files to BED coordinates, merged overlapping <lb/>intervals into a single interval, and computed the intersection of merged intervals among all three <lb/>taxa. Then, we used programs available as part of the phyluce package to filter sequences &lt; 100 <lb/>bp from the BED files; we extracted the shared, overlapping regions ≥ 100 bp from the danRer7 <lb/>genome assembly; and we filtered any extracted regions including &gt; 25% masked bases. We then <lb/>used phyluce and lastz (Harris, 2007) to search for duplicate hits among these extracted regions, <lb/>identifying as duplicate two regions that aligned to one another over &gt; 25% of their length with <lb/>&gt; 85% sequence identity. We used phyluce to filter these duplicate hits from the set. These <lb/>filtered regions represented reasonably long (≥ 100 bp), conserved loci shared among all three <lb/>taxa. We then ran another filtering step to remove loci from this set that were &lt; 150 bp in length <lb/>and &lt; 10,000 bp from one another as indicated by their alignment position in the danRer7 <lb/>genome assembly. We ran a secondary screen for potential duplication against this reduced list <lb/>using the same parameters as before. Then, we used a program from phyluce to design <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>enrichment baits targeting these loci. We attempted to select at least two bait sequences per <lb/>locus where baits overlapped by 80 bp, and we removed baits from the resulting set with GC <lb/>content outside the range of 30% to 70%. We used phyluce and lastz to search for and remove <lb/>any other baits from this candidate set that were &gt; 50% identical over &gt; 50% of their length. This <lb/>produced the final ostariophysan bait design file (&quot;ostariophysan bait set&quot; hereafter) which we <lb/>submitted to Arbor Biosciences, Inc. in order to synthesize myBaits custom target enrichment <lb/>kits which we used in the empirical tests described below. <lb/>Empirical sequence data collection overview <lb/>To test the utility of the resulting bait set for ostariophysan phylogenetics, we designed several <lb/>experiments that spanned the breadth of species diversity (Table 1) and divergence times in this <lb/>group. Different research groups performed target captures spanning a range of subclade ages <lb/>from young (&lt;50 MYA) to old (~200 MYA): Gymnotiformes (crown age 83-46 MYA (Hughes et al., <lb/>2018)), Anostomoidea (a characiform subclade that includes headstanders and detritivorous <lb/>characiforms; crown age falls within 76-51 MYA (Hughes et al., 2018)), Loricarioidei (armored <lb/>catfishes; crown age 125 MYA (Rivera-Rivera and Montoya-Burgos, 2017)), and the <lb/>Characiformes sensu lato (tetras and allies; crown age 133-112 MYA (Hughes et al., 2018). We <lb/>then combined data from several species within each group with additional enrichments from <lb/>outgroup lineages and conserved loci harvested from available genome sequences to create a <lb/>data set spanning Otocephala, a diverse teleostean clade that includes ostariophysans and <lb/>clupeomorphs (sardines, herrings and allies; crown age 210-178 MYA). <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Library preparation and enrichment from Gymnotiformes <lb/>We extracted DNA from vouchered museum specimens (Table 1) for taxa in the Gymnotiformes <lb/>data set using DNeasy Tissue kits (Qiagen N.V.). We quantified DNA using a Qubit fluorometer <lb/>(Invitrogen, Inc.), checked the quality of extracted DNA by visualization using gel electrophoresis <lb/>(1.5% agarose w/v), and sheared 300-500 ng of DNA extracts to a target size of 400-600 bp using <lb/>20 cycles of sonication (15 s on; 30 s off) on an EpiSonic Multi-Functional Bioprocessor (Epigentek <lb/>Group, Inc). We prepared sequencing libraries using Kapa Hyper Prep Kits (Kapa Biosystems, Inc). <lb/>We incorporated sample-specific dual-indexes to library fragments by ligating universal iTru stubs <lb/>to DNA and performing 10 cycles of PCR with iTru dual-indexed primers (Glenn et al., 2016) and <lb/>Kapa HiFi Hotstart ReadyMix polymerase. We cleaned indexed libraries using SPRI beads <lb/>(Rohland and Reich, 2012), quantified clean libraries using a Qubit fluorometer, and created pools <lb/>of 8 libraries at 62.5 ng each (500 ng total). We diluted the ostariophysan bait set synthesized by <lb/>Arbor Biosciences at a 1:6 ratio, and we enriched library pools following the MYBaits kit v3.0 <lb/>protocol. We PCR-recovered enriched library pools using 16 PCR cycles, Kapa HiFi HotStart Taq, <lb/>and the Illumina P5/P7 primer pair. We purified the resulting product using SPRI beads; <lb/>quantified enriched, clean libraries using a Qubit fluorometer; and combined libraries at <lb/>equimolar concentrations with other enriched pools having different indexes. We then <lb/>sequenced enriched libraries by combining them with other library pools having different indexes <lb/>in two separate runs of a PE150 Illumina NextSeq 300 (University of Georgia Genomics Facility) <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>or a PE150 Illumina HiSeq 3000 (Oklahoma Medical Research Foundation). We received <lb/>demultiplexed sequence data from the sequencing facilities. <lb/>Library preparation and enrichment from Anostomoidea <lb/>We extracted DNA from vouchered museum samples (Table 1) for the taxa in the Anostomoidea <lb/>data set using either a DNeasy Tissue kit or a modified NaCl extraction protocol adapted from <lb/>Lopera-Barrero et al. (2008). Following extraction, we quantified DNA using a Qubit fluorometer <lb/>and visualized 50-100 ng of each extract by electrophoresis through 1.5% (w/v) agarose gel in <lb/>TBE. We prepared 100 μL aliquots (~10 ng/μL) of each sample for sonication, and we sheared <lb/>samples to 300-600 bp using 5-10 cycles of sonication (High; 30 s on; 90 s off) on a BioRuptor <lb/>(Diagenode, Inc.). We prepared sequencing libraries from sheared DNA using a commercial <lb/>library preparation kit (Kapa Biosystems, Inc.). We indexed individual libraries using either a set <lb/>of single, custom indexes (Faircloth and Glenn, 2012) or the iTru dual-indexing approach (Glenn <lb/>et al., 2016). We PCR-amplified libraries using Kapa HiFi HotStart ReadyMix polymerase, 14 cycles <lb/>of PCR, and the manufacturer&apos;s recommended thermal profile. We purified library amplifications <lb/>using SPRI beads, quantified libraries with a Qubit fluorometer, and concentrated libraries to 147 <lb/>ng/µL with a Speed-Vac prior to preparing pools of 8 libraries at 62.5 ng each (500 ng total). We <lb/>enriched libraries by diluting the ostariophysan bait set (1:5) and following the procedure <lb/>described for Gymnotiformes. We combined enriched library pools with other libraries having <lb/>different indexes, and we sequenced the pool of pooled libraries using PE125 sequencing on an <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Illumina HiSeq 2000 in the Center for Genome Research and Biocomputing at Oregon State <lb/>University. <lb/>Library preparation and enrichment from Loricaroidei and Characiformes <lb/>We extracted DNA from vouchered museum samples (Table 1) for the taxa in the Loricaroidei <lb/>and Characiformes data sets using DNeasy Tissue kits. Subsequent library preparation and <lb/>enrichment steps were performed by Arbor Biosciences, Inc. (AB). AB staff quantified and <lb/>sheared DNA extracts with a Q800R (QSonica, Inc.) instrument and performed dual SPRI size <lb/>selection to produce sheared DNAs having a modal length of approximately 500 bp. AB staff then <lb/>prepared sequencing libraries using NEBNext Ultra DNA Library Preparation Kits (New England <lb/>Biolabs, Inc.). Following ligation, AB staff amplified libraries using dual P7 and P5 indexing primers <lb/>(Kircher et al., 2012), KAPA HiFi HotStart ReadyMix (Kapa Biosystems, Inc.), six PCR cycles, and <lb/>the manufacturer&apos;s recommended thermal profile. AB staff purified libraries with SPRI beads, <lb/>quantified libraries with the Quant-iT Picogreen dsDNA Assay kit (ThermoFisher, Inc.), prepared <lb/>pools of 8 libraries at 100 ng each (800ng total input material), and enriched libraries using an <lb/>undiluted ostariophysan bait set following following the MYBaits kit v3.0 protocol. After capture, <lb/>AB staff resuspended enriched, bead-bound library pools in the recommended solution and PCR-<lb/>recovered enriched library pools using 10 PCR cycles, Kapa HiFi polymerase, and the Illumina <lb/>P5/P7 primer pair. AB staff purified PCR-recovered libraries using SPRI beads, quantified <lb/>enriched, clean libraries with PicoGreen, and combined enriched pools with other libraries having <lb/>different indexes at the desired ratio prior to PE100 sequencing using an Illumina HiSeq 2500. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Sequence data quality control and assembly <lb/>After sequencing, we received FASTQ data from each sequencing provider, and we removed <lb/>adapters and trimmed the sequence data for low quality bases using illumiprocessor <lb/>(https://illumiprocessor.readthedocs.io/) which is a wrapper around Trimmomatic (Bolger et al., <lb/>2014). We assembled trimmed reads using a phyluce wrapper around the Trinity assembly <lb/>program (Grabherr et al., 2011). Before creating data sets for phylogenetic processing, we <lb/>integrated the sequence data collected in vitro with those collected in silico. <lb/>In-silico sequence data collection <lb/>We used computational approaches to extract data from 11 fish genome assemblies available <lb/>from UCSC, NCBI, and other sites (Table 1). We identified and extracted UCE loci that matched <lb/>the ostariophysan bait set using phyluce and a standardized workflow <lb/>(https://phyluce.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorial-three.html), except that we adjusted the <lb/>sequence coverage value to 67% and the sequence identity parameter to 80%. After locus <lb/>identification, we sliced UCE loci ± 500 bp from each genome and output those slices into FASTA <lb/>files identical to the FASTA files generated from assemblies of the samples we processed in vitro. <lb/>After harvesting the in silico data, we merged these with the in vitro data and processed both <lb/>simultaneously. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>UCE identification, alignment, and phylogenetic analyses <lb/>We used a standard workflow (https://phyluce.readthedocs.io/en/latest/tutorial-one.html) and <lb/>programs within phyluce to identify and filter non-duplicate contigs representing conserved loci <lb/>enriched by the ostariophysan bait set (hereafter UCEs). Then, we used lists of taxa to create one <lb/>data set for each taxonomic group outlined in Table 1, and we extracted FASTA data from the <lb/>UCE contigs enriched for group members. We exploded these data files by taxon to compute <lb/>summary metrics for UCE contigs, and we used phyluce to generate mafft v.7 (Katoh and <lb/>Standley, 2013) alignments of all loci. We trimmed alignments using trimAL (Capella-Gutierrez et <lb/>al., 2009) and the &apos;-automated1&apos; routine, and we computed alignment statistics using phyluce. <lb/>We then generated 75% complete data matrices for all data sets, and we computed summary <lb/>statistics across each 75% complete matrix. We concatenated alignments using phyluce, and we <lb/>conducted maximum likelihood (ML) tree and bootstrap replicate searches with the GTRGAMMA <lb/>site rate substitution model using RAxML (v8.0.19). We used the &apos;-autoMRE&apos; function of RAxML <lb/>to automatically determine the bootstrap replicate stopping point. Following best and bootstrap <lb/>ML tree searches, we added bootstrap support values to each tree using RAxML. We did not run <lb/>Bayesian or coalescent-based analyses because we were interested in determining whether this <lb/>bait set produced reasonable results at the levels of divergence examined rather than <lb/>exhaustively analyzing the evolutionary relationships among the taxa included. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>We collected an average of 3.47 M reads from enriched libraries (Table 2), and we assembled <lb/>these reads into an average of 18,048 contigs having a mean length of 440 bp (Table 3). After <lb/>searching for enriched, conserved loci among the contig assemblies, we identified an average of <lb/>1,446 targeted, conserved loci per library (range 525-1882; Table 4) having a mean length of 666 <lb/>bp per locus. From these loci, we created five different data sets (Table 1) that spanned the <lb/>diversity of relationships within ostariophysans and extended beyond this clade to include <lb/>Clupeiformes and other distantly related lineages (the Otocephala data set). We describe specific <lb/>results from each of these data sets below. <lb/>Gymnotiformes data set <lb/>The Gymnotiformes data set (Table 1) was one of two &quot;young&quot; ostariophysan subclades we <lb/>studied (crown age 83-46 MYA (Hughes et al., 2018)). We enriched an average of 1,871 UCE loci <lb/>from members of this group that averaged 591 bp in length and represented 2,259 of 2,708 loci <lb/>(83%) that we targeted (Table 4). Alignments generated from these loci contained an average of <lb/>7 taxa (range 3-9). After alignment trimming, the 75% matrix contained 1,771 UCE loci including <lb/>an average of 8 taxa (range 6-9) and having an average trimmed length of 466, a total length of <lb/>825,574 characters, and an average of 62 parsimony informative sites per locus. RAxML bootstrap <lb/>analyses required 50 iterations to reach the MRE stopping point. <lb/>The relationships we recover among the main lineages of Gymnotiformes (Figure 2) agree <lb/>with previous studies that used mtDNA genomes (Elbassiouny et al., 2016) or exons (Arcila et al., <lb/>2017). Similar to the results in these studies, we resolve Apteronotidae, represented in our data <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>set by Sternarchorhamphus muelleri, as the earliest diverging branch in the order. This placement <lb/>of Apteronotidae disagrees with previous morphological and Sanger-based hypotheses which <lb/>suggested either Gymnotidae (banded knifefishes of the genus Gymnotus and electric eel) <lb/>(Tagliacollo et al., 2016) or only the electric eel Electrophorus (i.e., non-monophyletic <lb/>Gymnotidae) (Janzen, 2016) were the sister group to all the other families. <lb/>Our UCE results resolve representatives of the pulse-type families that produce electric <lb/>organ discharges (Rhamphichthyidae (sand knifefishes) and Hypopomidae (bluntnose <lb/>knifefishes)) as a monophyletic group while we resolved families producing electric signals in the <lb/>form of waves (Apteronotidae (ghost knifefishes) and Sternopygidae (glass and rat-tail <lb/>knifefishes)) as paraphyletic, a phylogenetic hypothesis that contrasts with previous studies that <lb/>used morphology and Sanger sequencing data to suggest these families were monophyletic <lb/>(Albert, 1998; Albert, 2001; Albert and Crampton, 2005; Janzen, 2016; Tagliacollo et al., 2016). <lb/>The differences we observed among the placement of gymnotiform families relative to <lb/>previous studies reflects the confusing history of gymnotiform evolution where almost any <lb/>possible hypothesis of relationships among gymnotiform families has been suggested (Triques, <lb/>1993; Gayet et al., 1994; Alves-Gomes et al., 1995; Albert, 1998; Albert, 2001; Albert and <lb/>Crampton, 2005; Janzen, 2016; Tagliacollo et al., 2016; Arcila et al., 2017). These conflicts may <lb/>arise from a very rapid diversification event that occurred around the origin of Gymnotiformes <lb/>which created an evolutionary history muddled by incomplete lineage sorting. The causes of <lb/>these incongruences and methods to increase consistency in the inferences drawn from UCE data <lb/>are being explored as part of a separate study (Alda et al., In Review). <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Anostomoidea data set <lb/>The Anostomoidea data set (Table 1) was the second of two &quot;young&quot; ostariophysan subclades <lb/>we studied (crown age falls within 76-51 MYA (Hughes et al., 2018)), and we enriched an average <lb/>of 1,272 UCE loci from members of this group. These UCE loci averaged 493 bp in length and <lb/>represented 1,987 of the 2,708 loci (73%) that we targeted (Table 4). Alignments of these loci <lb/>contained an average of 9 taxa (range 3-15). After alignment trimming, the 75% matrix included <lb/>879 UCE loci containing an average of 13 taxa (range 11-15), having an average length of 487 bp, <lb/>a total length of 428,381 characters, and an average of 68 parsimony informative sites per locus. <lb/>RAxML bootstrap analyses required 50 iterations to reach the MRE stopping point. <lb/>Our ML analyses (Figure 3) recover a clear division between the omnivorous/herbivorous <lb/>Anostomidae (headstanders) and a clade of three fully or partially detritivorous families <lb/>(Chilodontidae, Curimatidae and Prochilodontidae), a result also found by earlier, Sanger-based <lb/>analyses (Melo et al., 2014; Melo et al., 2016; Melo et al., 2018). Relationships within <lb/>Anostomidae match the Sanger-based results of Ramirez at al. (2016) and differ from the <lb/>morphology-based hypothesis of Sidlauskas and Vari (2008) in the placement of Anostomus as <lb/>sister to Leporellus (rather than Laemolyta). Relationships within Curimatidae are fully congruent <lb/>with Vari&apos;s (1989) morphological hypothesis and a recent multilocus Sanger phylogeny (Melo et <lb/>al., 2018). <lb/>We resolve Prochilodontidae and Chilodontidae as successive sister groups to <lb/>Curimatidae. These results differ from recent Sanger sequencing studies (Oliveira et al., 2011; <lb/>Melo et al., 2018) which reverse this order, and they also differ from Vari&apos;s (1983) morphological <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>hypotheses, which suggested Chilodontidae were sister to Anostomidae. Regardless of the exact <lb/>relationships between Prochilodontidae, Chilodontidae, and Curimatidae, the resolution of <lb/>branching order among these three primarily detritivorous characiform families is biologically <lb/>interesting because either resolution implies a different and complex pattern of evolution in oral <lb/>and pharyngeal dentition, the epibranchial organ, and numerous other anatomical systems. As <lb/>noted for Gymnotiformes, the short branches associated with the near simultaneous origin of all <lb/>three families may explain differences between this study and Sanger-based studies, and future <lb/>work investigating these relationships would benefit from sampling more broadly across these <lb/>families and more thorough phylogenetic analyses. <lb/>Loricarioidei data set <lb/>The Loricarioidei data set (Table 1) represented an ostariophysan subclade of moderate age <lb/>(crown age ~125 MYA (Rivera-Rivera and Montoya-Burgos, 2017)), and from these taxa we <lb/>enriched an average of 1,379 UCE loci having an average length of 781 bp. Before trimming and <lb/>matrix reduction, the alignments represented 2,176 of the 2,708 loci (80%) we targeted (Table <lb/>4), each alignment contained a mean of 9 taxa (range 3-15), and average alignment length was <lb/>566. After alignment trimming, the 75% matrix included 938 UCE loci containing an average of <lb/>13 taxa (range 11-15), having a total length of 608,044 characters, an average length of 648 bp, <lb/>and an average of 261 parsimony informative sites per locus. RAxML bootstrap analyses required <lb/>50 iterations to reach the MRE stopping criterion. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>The major relationships we resolve among families of Loricarioidei (Figure 4) are <lb/>congruent with previous morphological hypotheses (Mo, 1991; Lundberg, 1993; Pinna, 1993; de <lb/>Pinna, 1996; de Pinna, 1998), an earlier Sanger molecular hypothesis (Sullivan et al., 2006), and <lb/>the exon-enrichment based molecular hypothesis of Arcila et al. (2017). Interestingly, we resolve <lb/>family Scoloplacidae (spiny-dwarf catfishes) and family Astroblepidae (climbing catfishes) as <lb/>successive sister groups to Loricariidae (armored catfishes), a placement reported by other <lb/>studies (de Pinna, 1998; Sullivan et al., 2006) that suggests the loss of armor plating in <lb/>Astroblepidae (de Pinna, 1998). Because relationships within this group remain controversial <lb/>(Sullivan et al., 2006; Rivera-Rivera and Montoya-Burgos, 2017) and because Loricarioidei is the <lb/>most diverse suborder of Neotropical catfishes (Sullivan et al., 2006), additional studies of <lb/>interfamilial relationships and family status within the group are needed. <lb/>Characiformes data set <lb/>The Characiformes data set (Table 1) represented our second ostariophysan subclade of <lb/>moderate age (~122 MYA (Hughes et al., 2018)), and we enriched an average of 1,701 UCE loci <lb/>from each taxon having an average length of 784 bp (Table 4). Before trimming and matrix <lb/>reduction, the alignments represented 2,493 of the 2,708 loci we targeted (92%), each alignment <lb/>contained a mean of 15 taxa (range 3-22), and average alignment length was 526. After alignment <lb/>trimming, the 75% data matrix included 1,399 UCE loci containing an average of 19 taxa (range <lb/>16-22), having a total length of 807,240 characters, an average length of 577 bp, and an average <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>of 220 parsimony informative sites per locus. RAxML bootstrap analyses required 50 iterations <lb/>to reach the MRE stopping criterion. <lb/>The overall pattern of relationships we resolved for Characiformes (Figure 5) is similar to <lb/>those from multilocus Sanger sequencing (Oliveira et al., 2011) or exon-based (Arcila et al., 2017) <lb/>studies. For example, our results include separation of the African Citharinoidei (Citharinidae and <lb/>Distichodontidae) from other characiforms in the earliest divergence within the order and <lb/>resolution of Crenuchidae (Neotropical darters) as sister to all other members of Characiformes <lb/>(suborder Characoidei). Within Characoidei, we resolved two major lineages: one comprising <lb/>Ctenoluciidae (pike-characins), Lebiasinidae (pencilfishes), Acestrorhynchidae (dogtooth <lb/>characins), Bryconidae (dorados and allies), Triportheidae (elongate hatchetfishes) and members <lb/>of the hyperdiverse family Characidae (tetras) and the other including a monophyletic <lb/>superfamily, Anostomoidea (headstanders, toothless characiforms and relatives), that is closely <lb/>aligned to Serrasalmidae (piranhas and pacus), Hemiodontidae (halftooths) and Parodontidae <lb/>(scrapetooths), and more distantly related to Erythrinidae (trahiras) and the second clade of <lb/>African families Alestidae and Hepsetidae. Within Characoidei, the short branches connecting <lb/>internodes along the backbone of the phylogeny reflect previous results suggesting a rapid initial <lb/>diversification of families within this suborder (Arcila et al., 2017; Chakrabarty et al., 2017). <lb/>Otocephala data set <lb/>The Otocephala data set (Table 1) represented the oldest clade of fishes we investigated (~193 <lb/>MYA (Hughes et al., 2018)), and we created this data set by combining enrichment data from <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>select lineages used in the data sets above with enrichment data collected using the same array <lb/>from taxa representing Clupeiformes and Cypriniformes (Table 1). To these empirical data, we <lb/>integrated in silico data harvested from even more distant outgroups to show that the <lb/>ostariophysan bait set is useful to study these other groups and also to demonstrate that it <lb/>recovers reasonable relationships among these various lineages. From the taxa in this data set <lb/>where we used targeted enrichment to collect data, we enriched an average of 1,447 UCE loci <lb/>having an average length of 784 bp. When we combined these data with the in silico data, the <lb/>alignments represented 2,573 of 2,708 loci (95%), each alignment contained a mean of 11 taxa <lb/>(range 3-21), and average alignment length was 445 bp. After alignment trimming, the 75% data <lb/>matrix included 658 UCE loci containing an average of 17 taxa (range 15-21), having an average <lb/>length of 384 characters, a total length of 252,749 characters, and an average of 146 parsimony <lb/>informative sites per locus. RAxML bootstrap analyses required 350 iterations to reach the MRE <lb/>stopping criterion. <lb/>The branching order we resolve among Lepisosteiformes, Anguilliformes, <lb/>Osteoglossiformes, and Euteleostei relative to the otocephalan ingroup (Figure 6) is similar to the <lb/>pattern of major relationships among these fish groups resolved by other phylogenomic studies <lb/>(Faircloth et al., 2013; Hughes et al., 2018). Similarly, the UCE data we enriched from lineages <lb/>representing Clupeiformes and Cypriniformes produced the same phylogenetic hypothesis for <lb/>the branching order of these groups relative to the Characiphysi (Characiformes + <lb/>Gymnotiformes + Siluriformes) as seen in other genome-scale (Hughes et al., 2018) and Sanger <lb/>sequencing (Near et al., 2012; Betancur-R et al., 2013) studies. Relationships among the orders <lb/>comprising otophysans are similar to some genome-scale studies and different from others, <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>reflecting the difficulties noted when studying these groups (reviewed in Chakrabarty et al., 2017; <lb/>Arcila et al., 2017). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The bait set that we designed effectively collected data from the majority of the 2,708 UCE loci <lb/>that we targeted across the four ostariophysan subclades we investigated: averaging across all <lb/>of our experiments except the Otocephala data set, which included many genome-enabled taxa, <lb/>we enriched an average of 2,229 of the 2,708 loci (82%). This bait set also performed well when <lb/>enriching putatively orthologous loci from Amazonsprattus scintilla (Clupeiformes). Because of <lb/>our success enriching loci from Clupeiformes, which are a close outgroup to Ostariophysi, and <lb/>despite our lack of a lineage representing Gonorynchiformes, we refer to this bait set as targeting <lb/>Ostariophysi/ostariophysans rather than smaller subclades within this group. <lb/>As detailed above, the data we collected using the ostariophysan bait set reconstruct <lb/>reasonable phylogenetic hypotheses for all datasets, despite low taxon sampling (less than 1% of <lb/>diversity for the overall study and less than 5% in Anostomoidea, the most densely sampled <lb/>subclade). By reasonable, we mean that the phylogenetic hypotheses we resolved largely agree <lb/>with previous investigations using multilocus Sanger sequencing data or genome-scale data <lb/>collection approaches. Where we observed differences from some prior studies were those <lb/>relationships having very short internal branches suggesting rapid or explosive radiation of a <lb/>particular clade. These areas of treespace are hard to reconstruct (Pamilo and Nei, 1988; <lb/>Maddison, 1997; Maddison and Knowles, 2006; Oliver, 2013), and many current studies are <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>focused on analytical approaches that produce the most accurate phylogenetic hypothesis given <lb/>the data. The congruence of our results with stable parts of the trees inferred during these earlier <lb/>studies and the overall ability of this bait set to pull down significant proportions of the targeted <lb/>loci suggests that our ostariophysan bait set provides one mechanism to begin large-scale data <lb/>collection from and inference of the relationships among the more than 10,000 species that <lb/>comprise Ostariophysi, many of which have never been placed on a phylogeny. <lb/>Future work should explicitly test the effectiveness of this ostariophysan bait set for <lb/>enriching loci from Gonorynchiformes, the smallest ostariophysan order and a group for which <lb/>tissue samples are few. Similarly, this bait set should be tested in Alepocephaliformes, an <lb/>enigmatic order of marine fishes that may form a close outgroup to Ostariophysi. Despite those <lb/>gaps, our in silico results suggest: (1) that this bait set may be useful in even more distant groups <lb/>like Osteoglossiformes or Euteleostei, and (2) the exciting possibility that we may be able to <lb/>create a large (&gt;1000-2000 loci), combined bait set targeting orthologous, conserved loci that are <lb/>shared among actinopterygians to reconstruct a Tree of Life spanning the largest vertebrate <lb/>radiation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank the curators, staff, and field collectors at the institutions listed in Table 1 for loans of <lb/>tissue samples used in this project. This work was supported by grants from NSF to BCF (DEB-<lb/>1242267), BLS (DEB-1257898), and PC (DEB-1354149) and FAPESP to CO (14/26508-3), BFM <lb/>(16/11313-8), FFR (14/05051-5), and LEO (14/06853-8). Animal tissues collected as part of this <lb/></div>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">work followed protocols approved by the University of California Los Angeles Institutional Animal <lb/>Care and Use Committee (Approval 2008-176-21). Portions of this research were conducted with <lb/>high-performance computing resources provided by Louisiana State University <lb/>(http://www.hpc.lsu.edu). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA ACCESSIBILITY <lb/>Sequence data from A. albifrons and C. paleatus used for locus identification are available from <lb/>NCBI BioProject PRJNA493643, and sequence data from enriched libraries using the <lb/>ostariophysan bait set are available from NCBI BioProject PRJNA492882. The ostariophysan bait <lb/>design file is available from FigShare (doi:10.6084/m9.figshare.7144199), where it can be <lb/>updated, if needed. A static copy of the bait design file and all other associated files, including <lb/>contig assemblies, UCE loci, and inferred phylogenies are available from Zenodo.org <lb/>(doi:10.5281/zenodo.1442082). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERERENCES <lb/>Albert, J.S. (1998) Phylogenetic systematics of Gymnotiformes with diagnoses of 58 clades: a <lb/>review of available data. Phylogeny and classification of Neotropical fishes (eds <lb/>Malabarba, L.R., Reis, R.E., Vari, R.P., Lucena, Z.M.S., &amp; Lucena, C.A.S.), pp. 419-446. <lb/>EDIPUCRS, Porto Alegre. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>---. (2001) Species diversity and phylogenetic systematics of American knifefishes <lb/>(Gymnotiformes, Teleostei). University of Michigan Museum of Zoology Miscellaneous <lb/>Publications, <lb/>Albert, J.S., &amp; Crampton, W.G.R. (2005) Diversity and phylogeny of Neotropical electric fishes <lb/>(Gymnotiformes). Electroreception (eds Bullock, T.H., Hopkins, C.D., Popper, A.N., &amp; Fay, <lb/>R.R.), pp. 360-409. Springer, New York, NY. <lb/>Alda, F., Tagliacollo, V.A., Bernt, M.J., Waltz, B.T., Ludt, W.B., Faircloth, B.C., Alfaro, M.E., Albert, <lb/>J.S., &amp; Chakrabarty, P. (In Review) Resolving Deep Nodes in an Ancient Radiation of <lb/>Neotropical Fishes in the Presence of Conflicting Signal From Incomplete Lineage Sorting. <lb/>Systematic Biology, <lb/>Alfaro, M.E., Faircloth, B.C., Harrington, R.C., Sorenson, L., Friedman, M., Thacker, C.E., Oliveros, <lb/>C.H., Černý, D., &amp; Near, T.J. (2018) Explosive diversification of marine fishes at the <lb/>Cretaceous-Palaeogene boundary. Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution, <lb/>Alves-Gomes, J.A., Ortí, G., Haygood, M., Heiligenberg, W., &amp; Meyer, A. (1995) Phylogenetic <lb/>analysis of the South American electric fishes (order Gymnotiformes) and the evolution of <lb/>their electrogenic system: a synthesis based on morphology, electrophysiology, and <lb/>mitochondrial sequence data. Molecular Biology and Evolution, <lb/>Arcila, D., Ortí, G., Vari, R., Armbruster, J.W., Stiassny, M.L.J., Ko, K.D., Sabaj, M.H., Lundberg, J., <lb/>Revell, L.J., &amp; Betancur-R, R. (2017) Genome-wide interrogation advances resolution of <lb/>recalcitrant groups in the tree of life. Nature Ecology &amp; Evolution, <lb/>Betancur-R, R., Broughton, R.E., Wiley, E.O., Carpenter, K., López, J.A., Li, C., Holcroft, N.I., <lb/>Arcila, D., Sanciangco, M., Cureton, J.C., Ii, Zhang, F., Buser, T., Campbell, M.A., <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Ballesteros, J.A., Roa-Varon, A., Willis, S., Borden, W.C., Rowley, T., Reneau, P.C., Hough, <lb/>D.J., Lu, G., Grande, T., Arratia, G., &amp; Ortí, G. (2013) The tree of life and a new <lb/>classification of bony fishes. PLoS Currents, <lb/>Bolger, A.M., Lohse, M., &amp; Usadel, B. (2014) Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for Illumina <lb/>sequence data. Bioinformatics, <lb/>Branstetter, M.G., Danforth, B.N., Pitts, J.P., Faircloth, B.C., Ward, P.S., Buffington, M.L., Gates, <lb/>M.W., Kula, R.R., &amp; Brady, S.G. (2017) Phylogenomic Insights into the Evolution of Stinging <lb/>Wasps and the Origins of Ants and Bees. Current Biology, <lb/>Brawand, D., Wagner, C.E., Li, Y.I., Malinsky, M., Keller, I., Fan, S., Simakov, O., Ng, A.Y., Lim, <lb/>Z.W., Bezault, E., Turner-Maier, J., Johnson, J., Alcazar, R., Noh, H.J., Russell, P., Aken, B., <lb/>Alföldi, J., Amemiya, C., Azzouzi, N., Baroiller, J.-F., Barloy-Hubler, F., Berlin, A., <lb/>Bloomquist, R., Carleton, K.L., Conte, M.A., D&apos;Cotta, H., Eshel, O., Gaffney, L., Galibert, F., <lb/>Gante, H.F., Gnerre, S., Greuter, L., Guyon, R., Haddad, N.S., Haerty, W., Harris, R.M., <lb/>Hofmann, H.A., Hourlier, T., Hulata, G., Jaffe, D.B., Lara, M., Lee, A.P., MacCallum, I., <lb/>Mwaiko, S., Nikaido, M., Nishihara, H., Ozouf-Costaz, C., Penman, D.J., Przybylski, D., <lb/>Rakotomanga, M., Renn, S.C.P., Ribeiro, F.J., Ron, M., Salzburger, W., Sanchez-Pulido, L., <lb/>Santos, M.E., Searle, S., Sharpe, T., Swofford, R., Tan, F.J., Williams, L., Young, S., Yin, S., <lb/>Okada, N., Kocher, T.D., Miska, E.A., Lander, E.S., Venkatesh, B., Fernald, R.D., Meyer, A., <lb/>Ponting, C.P., Streelman, J.T., Lindblad-Toh, K., Seehausen, O., &amp; Di Palma, F. (2014) The <lb/>genomic substrate for adaptive radiation in African cichlid fish. Nature, <lb/>Capella-Gutierrez, S., Silla-Martinez, J.M., &amp; Gabaldon, T. (2009) trimAl: a tool for automated <lb/>alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses. Bioinformatics, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Chakrabarty, P., Faircloth, B.C., Alda, F., Ludt, W.B., Mcmahan, C.D., Near, T.J., Dornburg, A., <lb/>Albert, J.S., Arroyave, J., Stiassny, M.L.J., Sorenson, L., &amp; Alfaro, M.E. (2017) Phylogenomic <lb/>Systematics of Ostariophysan Fishes: Ultraconserved Elements Support the Surprising <lb/>Non-Monophyly of Characiformes. Systematic Biology, <lb/>Dai, W., Zou, M., Yang, L., Du, K., Chen, W., Shen, Y., Mayden, R.L., &amp; He, S. (2018) <lb/>Phylogenomic Perspective on the Relationships and Evolutionary History of the Major <lb/>Otocephalan Lineages. Scientific Reports, <lb/>de Pinna, M.C.C. (1996) A phylogenetic analysis of the Asian catfish families Sisoridae, Akysidae <lb/>and Amblycipitidae, with a hypothesis on the relationships of the neotropical <lb/>Aspredinidae (Teleostei, Ostariophysi). Fieldiana Zoology, <lb/>de Pinna, M.C.C. (1998) Phylogenetic Relationships of Neotropical Siluriformes (Teleostei: <lb/>Ostariophysi): Historical overview and synthesis of hypothesis. (eds Malabarba, L.R., Reis, <lb/>R.E., Vari, R.P., Lucena, C., &amp; Lucena, M.), pp. 279-330. EDIPUCRS, Porto Alegre. <lb/>Elbassiouny, A.A., Schott, R.K., Waddell, J.C., Kolmann, M.A., Lehmberg, E.S., Van Nynatten, A., <lb/>Crampton, W.G.R., Chang, B.S.W., &amp; Lovejoy, N.R. (2016) Mitochondrial genomes of the <lb/>South American electric knifefishes (Order Gymnotiformes). Mitochondrial DNA Part B, <lb/>Faircloth, B.C. (2015) PHYLUCE is a software package for the analysis of conserved genomic loci. <lb/>Bioinformatics, <lb/>---. (2017) Identifying conserved genomic elements and designing universal bait sets to <lb/>enrich them. Methods in Ecology and Evolution, <lb/>Faircloth, B.C., &amp; Glenn, T.C. (2012) Not all sequence tags are created equal: Designing and <lb/>validating sequence identification tags robust to indels. PLoS One, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Faircloth, B.C., McCormack, J.E., Crawford, N.G., Harvey, M.G., Brumfield, R.T., &amp; Glenn, T.C. <lb/>(2012) Ultraconserved elements anchor thousands of genetic markers spanning multiple <lb/>evolutionary timescales. Systematic Biology, <lb/>Faircloth, B.C., Sorenson, L., Santini, F., &amp; Alfaro, M.E. (2013) A phylogenomic perspective on <lb/>the radiation of ray-finned fishes based upon targeted sequencing of ultraconserved <lb/>elements (UCEs). PLoS One, <lb/>Fink, S.V., &amp; Fink, W.L. (1981) Interrelationships of the ostariophysan fishes (Teleostei). <lb/>Zoological Journal of the Linnean Society, <lb/>---(eds.) 1996. Interrelationships of ostariophysan fishes (Teleostei) Academic Press, San <lb/>Diego <lb/>Gayet, M., Meunier, F.J., &amp; Kirschbaum, F. (1994) Ellisella kirschbaumi Gayet &amp; Meunier, 1991, <lb/>gymnotiforme fissole de Bolivie et ses relations phylogénétiques au sein des formes <lb/>actuelles. Cybium, <lb/>Glenn, T.C., Nilsen, R., Kieran, T.J., Finger, J.W., Pierson, T.W., Bentley, K.E., Hoffberg, S., Louha, <lb/>S., Garcia-De-Leon, F.J., del Rio Portilla, M.A., Reed, K., Anderson, J.L., Meece, J.K., Aggery, <lb/>S., Rekaya, R., Alabady, M., Belanger, M., Winker, K., &amp; Faircloth, B.C. (2016) Adapterama <lb/>I: Universal stubs and primers for thousands of dual-indexed Illumina libraries (iTru &amp; <lb/>iNext). bioRxiv, doi:10.1101/049114. <lb/>Grabherr, M.G., Haas, B.J., Yassour, M., Levin, J.Z., Thompson, D.A., Amit, I., Adiconis, X., Fan, L., <lb/>Raychowdhury, R., Zeng, Q., Chen, Z., Mauceli, E., Hacohen, N., Gnirke, A., Rhind, N., Di <lb/>Palma, F., Birren, B.W., Nusbaum, C., Lindblad-Toh, K., Friedman, N., &amp; Regev, A. (2011) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Full-length transcriptome assembly from RNA-Seq data without a reference genome. <lb/>Nature Biotechnology, <lb/>Harris, R.S. (2007) Improved pairwise alignment of genomic DNA. PhD thesis, The Pennsylvania <lb/>State University. <lb/>Hughes, L.C., Ortí, G., Huang, Y., Sun, Y., Baldwin, C.C., Thompson, A.W., Arcila, D., Betancur-R, <lb/>R., Li, C., Becker, L., Bellora, N., Zhao, X., Li, X., Wang, M., Fang, C., Xie, B., Zhou, Z., Huang, <lb/>H., Chen, S., Venkatesh, B., &amp; Shi, Q. (2018) Comprehensive phylogeny of ray-finned fishes <lb/>(Actinopterygii) based on transcriptomic and genomic data. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, <lb/>Janzen, F.H. (2016) Molecular Phylogeny of the Neotropical Knifefishes of the Order <lb/>Gymnotiformes (Actinopterygii). PhD thesis, University of Toronto. <lb/>Katoh, K., &amp; Standley, D.M. (2013) MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: <lb/>improvements in performance and usability. Molecular Biology and Evolution, <lb/>Kircher, M., Sawyer, S., &amp; Meyer, M. (2012) Double indexing overcomes inaccuracies in <lb/>multiplex sequencing on the Illumina platform. Nucleic Acids Research, <lb/>Lavoué, S., Konstantinidis, P., &amp; Chen, W.-J. (2014) Progress in clupeiform systematics. Biology <lb/>and ecology of sardines and anchovies (ed Ganias, K.), pp. 3-42. CRC Press, Boca Raton. <lb/>Lecointre, G. (1995) Molecular and morphologicalevidence for a Clupeomorpha-Ostariophysi <lb/>sister-group relationship (Teleostei). Geobios, <lb/>Li, H. (2013) Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with BWA-MEM. <lb/>arxiv:1303.3997v2. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Li, H., Handsaker, B., Wysoker, A., Fennell, T., Ruan, J., Homer, N., Marth, G., Abecasis, G., <lb/>Durbin, R., &amp; Proc, G.P.D. (2009) The Sequence Alignment/Map format and SAMtools. <lb/>Bioinformatics, <lb/>Lopera-Barrero, N.M., Povh, J.A., Ribeiro, R.P., Gomes, P.C., Jacometo, C.B., &amp; da Silva Lopes, T. <lb/>(2008) Comparison of DNA extraction protocols of fish fin and larvae samples: modified <lb/>salt (NaCl). Ciencia e Investigación Agraria, <lb/>Lundberg, J.G. (1993) African South America freshwater fish clade and continental drift: <lb/>problems with a paradigm. Biological Relationships between Africa and South America (ed <lb/>pp. 156-199. Yale University Press, New Haven, CT. <lb/>Maddison, W.P. (1997) Gene trees in species trees. Systematic Biology, <lb/>Maddison, W.P., &amp; Knowles, L.L. (2006) Inferring phylogeny despite incomplete lineage sorting. <lb/>Systematic Biology, <lb/>Malinsky, M., Svardal, H., Tyers, A.M., Miska, E.A., Genner, M.J., Turner, G.F., &amp; Durbin, R. <lb/>(2018) Whole genome sequences of malawi cichlids reveal multiple radiations <lb/>interconnected by gene flow. biorxiv, <lb/>Melo, B.F., Sidlauskas, B.L., Hoekzema, K., Frable, B.W., Vari, R.P., &amp; Oliveira, C. (2016) <lb/>Molecular phylogenetics of the Neotropical fish family Prochilodontidae (Teleostei: <lb/>Characiformes). Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/>Melo, B.F., Sidlauskas, B.L., Hoekzema, K., Vari, R.P., Dillman, C.B., &amp; Oliveira, C. (2018) <lb/>Molecular phylogenetics of Neotropical detritivorous fishes of the family Curimatidae <lb/>(Teleostei: Characiformes). Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Melo, B.F., Sidlauskas, B.L., Hoekzema, K., Vari, R.P., &amp; Oliveira, C. (2014) The first molecular <lb/>phylogeny of Chilodontidae (Teleostei: Ostariophysi: Characiformes) reveals cryptic <lb/>biodiversity and taxonomic uncertainty. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/>Mo, T.A.P. (1991) Anatomy, relationships and systematics of the Bagridae (Teleostei: Siluroidei) <lb/>with a hypothesis of siluroid phylogeny. Theses Zoologicae, <lb/>Moyle, R.G., Oliveros, C.H., Andersen, M.J., Hosner, P.A., Benz, B.W., Manthey, J.D., Travers, <lb/>S.L., Brown, R.M., &amp; Faircloth, B.C. (2016) Tectonic collision and uplift of Wallacea <lb/>triggered the global songbird radiation. Nature Communications, <lb/>Nakatani, M., Miya, M., Mabuchi, K., Saitoh, K., &amp; Nishida, M. (2011) Evolutionary history of <lb/>Otophysi (Teleostei), a major clade of the modern freshwater fishes: Pangaean origin and <lb/>Mesozoic radiation. BMC Evolutionary Biology, <lb/>Near, T.J., Eytan, R.I., Dornburg, A., Kuhn, K.L., Moore, J.A., Davis, M.P., Wainwright, P.C., <lb/>Friedman, M., &amp; Smith, W.L. (2012) Resolution of ray-finned fish phylogeny and timing of <lb/>diversification. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of <lb/>America, <lb/>Nurk, S., Bankevich, A., Antipov, D., Gurevich, A., Korobeynikov, A., Lapidus, A., Prjibelsky, A., <lb/>Pyshkin, A., Sirotkin, A., Sirotkin, Y., Stepanauskas, R., McLean, J., Lasken, R., Clingenpeel, <lb/>S.R., Woyke, T., Tesler, G., Alekseyev, M.A., &amp; Pevzner, P.A. (2013) Assembling Genomes <lb/>and Mini-metagenomes from Highly Chimeric Reads. Lecture Notes in Computer Science: <lb/>Research in Computational Molecular Biology (eds pp. 158-170. Springer Berlin <lb/>Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Oliveira, C., Avelino, G.S., Abe, K.T., Mariguela, T.C., Benine, R.C., Ortí, G., Vari, R.P., &amp; e Castro, <lb/>R.M.C. (2011) Phylogenetic relationships within the speciose family Characidae (Teleostei: <lb/>Ostariophysi: Characiformes) based on multilocus analysis and extensive ingroup <lb/>sampling. BMC Evolutionary Biology, <lb/>Oliver, J.C. (2013) Microevolutionary processes generate phylogenomic discordance at ancient <lb/>divergences. Evolution, <lb/>Pamilo, P., &amp; Nei, M. (1988) Relationships between gene trees and species trees. Molecular <lb/>Biology and Evolution, <lb/>Pinna, M.C.C.D. (1993) Higher-level phylogeny of Siluriformes, with a new classification of the <lb/>order (Teleostei, Ostariophysi). PhD thesis, The City University of New York. <lb/>Quattrini, A.M., Faircloth, B.C., Dueñas, L.F., Bridge, T.C.L., Brugler, M.R., Calixto-Botía, I.F., <lb/>DeLeo, D.M., Forêt, S., Herrera, S., Lee, S.M.Y., Miller, D.J., Prada, C., Rádis-Baptista, G., <lb/>Ramírez-Portilla, C., Sánchez, J.A., Rodríguez, E., &amp; McFadden, C.S. (2018) Universal target-<lb/>enrichment baits for anthozoan (Cnidaria) phylogenomics: New approaches to long-<lb/>standing problems. Molecular Ecology Resources, <lb/>Quinlan, A.R., &amp; Hall, I.M. (2010) BEDTools: a flexible suite of utilities for comparing genomic <lb/>features. Bioinformatics, <lb/>Rivera-Rivera, C.J., &amp; Montoya-Burgos, J.I. (2017) Trunk dental tissue evolved independently <lb/>from underlying dermal bony plates but is associated with surface bones in living <lb/>odontode-bearing catfish. Proceedings of the Royal Society Series B Biological Sciences, <lb/>Rohland, N., &amp; Reich, D. (2012) Cost-effective, high-throughput DNA sequencing libraries for <lb/>multiplexed target capture. Genome Research, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Rosen, D.E., Greenwood, P.H., Anderson, S., &amp; Weitzman, S.H. (1970) Origin of the Weberian <lb/>apparatus and the relationships of the ostariophysan and gonorynchiform fishes. <lb/>American Museum Novitates, <lb/>Rosso, J.J., Mabragaña, E., Castro, M.G., &amp; de Astarloa, J.M. (2012) DNA barcoding Neotropical <lb/>fishes: recent advances from the Pampa Plain, Argentina. Molecular Ecology Resources, <lb/>Saitoh, K., Miya, M., Inoue, J.G., Ishiguro, N.B., &amp; Nishida, M. (2003) Mitochondrial genomics of <lb/>ostariophysan fishes: perspectives on phylogeny and biogeography. Journal of Molecular <lb/>Evolution, <lb/>Sanmartín, I., &amp; Ronquist, F. (2004) Southern hemisphere biogeography inferred by event-based <lb/>models: plant versus animal patterns. Systematic Biology, <lb/>Schönhuth, S., Gagne, R.B., Alda, F., Neely, D.A., Mayden, R.L., &amp; Blum, M.J. (2018) <lb/>Phylogeography of the widespread creek chub Semotilus atromaculatus (Cypriniformes: <lb/>Leuciscidae). Journal of Fish Biology, <lb/>Streicher, J.W., &amp; Wiens, J.J. (2016) Phylogenomic analyses reveal novel relationships among <lb/>snake families. Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/>Sullivan, J.P., Lundberg, J.G., &amp; Hardman, M. (2006) A phylogenetic analysis of the major groups <lb/>of catfishes (Teleostei: Siluriformes) using rag1 and rag2 nuclear gene sequences. <lb/>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/>Tagliacollo, V.A., Bernt, M.J., Craig, J.M., Oliveira, C., &amp; Albert, J.S. (2016) Model-based total <lb/>evidence phylogeny of Neotropical electric knifefishes (Teleostei, Gymnotiformes). <lb/>Molecular Phylogenetics and Evolution, <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Triques, M.L. (1993) Filogenia dos gêneros de Gymnotiformes (Actinopterygii, Ostariophysi), <lb/>com base em caracteres esqueléticos. Comunicações do Museu de Ciências de PUCRS, <lb/>série Zoologia, <lb/>Vari, R.P. (1983) Phylogenetic relationships of the Families Curimatidae, Prochilodontidae, <lb/>Anostomidae, and Chilodontidae (Pisces, Characiformes). Smithsonian Contributions to <lb/>Zoology, <lb/>---. (1989) A phylogenetic study of the Neotropical characiform family Curimatidae (Pisces: <lb/>Ostariophysi). Smithsonian Contributions to Zoology, <lb/>von Frisch, K. (1938) Zur Psychologie des Fisch-Schwarmes. Naturwissenschaften, <lb/>Weber, E.H. (1820) De aure et auditu hominis et animalium. Pars I. De aure animalium <lb/>aquatilium. Gerhard Fleischer, Leipzig. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Order, family, species, source, accession and data set membership of fish species from which we enriched or <lb/>bioinformatically harvested UCE loci. Charac. = Characiformes, Anosto. = Anostomoidea, Lorica. = Loricarioidei, Gymnot. = <lb/>Gymnotiformes, Otomorph. = Otomorpha. <lb/>Data Set <lb/>Order <lb/>Family <lb/>Species <lb/>Source Accession <lb/>Charac. Anosto. Lorica. Gymnot. Otomorph. <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus <lb/>LBP <lb/>1828 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis <lb/>OS <lb/>18337 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus <lb/>OS <lb/>18310 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama <lb/>LBP <lb/>12776 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/>Parodon hillari <lb/>LBP <lb/>10408 <lb/>O <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Acestrorhynchidae <lb/>Acestrorhynchus falcatus <lb/>LBP <lb/>7016 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Alestidae <lb/>Alestes inferus <lb/>AMNH 242137 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Astyanax mexicanus* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_000372685.2 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Bryconidae <lb/>Brycon amazonicus <lb/>LBP <lb/>14082 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Charax niger <lb/>LBP <lb/>21217 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Citharinidae <lb/>Citharinus congicus <lb/>AMNH 252692 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Crenuchidae <lb/>Crenuchus spilurus <lb/>LBP <lb/>10622 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Ctenoluciidae <lb/>Ctenolucius hujeta <lb/>LBP <lb/>6136 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Distichodontidae <lb/>Distichodus affinis <lb/>AMNH 252633 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Erythrinidae <lb/>Erythrinus erythrinus <lb/>LBP <lb/>6625 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hemiodontidae <lb/>Hemiodus quadrimaculatus <lb/>LBP <lb/>21151 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hepsetidae <lb/>Hepsetus lineata <lb/>AMNH 263038 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Lebiasinidae <lb/>Lebiasina bimaculata <lb/>LBP <lb/>1354 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Serrasalmidae <lb/>Serrasalmus rhombeus <lb/>LBP <lb/>14239 <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Characiformes <lb/>Triportheidae <lb/>Triportheus albus <lb/>LBP <lb/>4118 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Ictaluridae <lb/>Ictalurus punctatus* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_001660625.1 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Anostomus anostomus <lb/>USNM 402905 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Chilodus punctatus <lb/>OS <lb/>18781 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Cyphocharax spilurus <lb/>ANSP <lb/>189157 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Laemolyta proxima <lb/>OS <lb/>18778 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporellus vittatus <lb/>ANSP <lb/>182609 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporinus fasciatus <lb/>MHNG 2717.030 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Potamorhina laticeps <lb/>LBP <lb/>6133 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Prochilodus argenteus <lb/>LBP <lb/>11343 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Psectrogaster rhomboides <lb/>LBP <lb/>5533 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Steindachnerina bimaculata <lb/>LBP <lb/>173 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Astroblepidae <lb/>Astroblepus grixalvii <lb/>ANSP <lb/>188920 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus <lb/>LBP <lb/>1295 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Corydoras aeneus <lb/>LBP <lb/>18917 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Hoplosternum littorale <lb/>LBP <lb/>466 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Delturus carinotus <lb/>LGC <lb/>1709 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hisonotus notatus <lb/>LBP <lb/>3472 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hypostomus strigaticeps <lb/>LBP <lb/>14627 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera <lb/>LBP <lb/>7394 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rineloricaria lima <lb/>LBP <lb/>6318 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Scoloplacidae <lb/>Scoloplax dicra <lb/>LBP <lb/>11001 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Copionodon pecten <lb/>LBP <lb/>17361 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Ituglanis laticeps <lb/>LBP <lb/>19339 <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Stauroglanis gouldingi <lb/>LBP <lb/>3159 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Trichomycterus aerolatus <lb/>LBP <lb/>3118 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Apteronotidae <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus muelleri <lb/>ANSP <lb/>182579 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Gymnotidae <lb/>Electrophorus electricus* <lb/>FTP a <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Hypopomidae <lb/>Brachyhypopomus brevirostris <lb/>LBP <lb/>16705 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae <lb/>Steatogenys elegans <lb/>ANSP <lb/>200421 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae <lb/>Rhamphichthys apurensis <lb/>LBP <lb/>43111 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Eigenmannia vicentespelaea <lb/>LBP <lb/>62040 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Rhabdolichops cf. stewarti <lb/>LBP <lb/>41406 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Sternopygus macrurus <lb/>LBP <lb/>46840 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Danionidae <lb/>Danio rerio* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_000002035.2 <lb/>O <lb/>Beloniformes <lb/>Adrianichthyidae <lb/>Oryzias latipes* <lb/>UCSC <lb/>oryLat2 <lb/>Anguilliformes <lb/>Anguillidae <lb/>Anguilla japonica* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_002723815.1 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Clupeidae <lb/>Clupea harengus* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_000966335.1 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Cyprinus carpio <lb/>LBP <lb/>9776 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Engraulidae <lb/>Amazonsprattus scintilla <lb/>LBP <lb/>16131 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Carassius auratus <lb/>LBP <lb/>9215 <lb/>Perciformes <lb/>Gasterosteidae <lb/>Gasterosteus aculeatus* <lb/>UCSC <lb/>gasAcu1 <lb/>Lepisosteiformes <lb/>Lepisosteidae <lb/>Lepisosteus oculatus* <lb/>Broad L_oculatus_v1 <lb/>O <lb/>Osteoglossiformes Osteoglossidae <lb/>Scleropages formosus* <lb/>NCBI <lb/>GCA_001624265.1 <lb/>Tetraodontiformes Tetraodontidae <lb/>Takifugu rubripes* <lb/>UCSC <lb/>fr2 <lb/>a Traeger et al. (2017) A tail of two voltages: Proteomic comparison of the three electric organs of the electric eel. Science Advances 3(7) e1700523. <lb/>O Indicates taxon used as outgroup in analysis. <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. The number of reads sequenced and summary statistics of trimmed reads for each DNA library from which we enriched <lb/>UCEs using the ostariophysan bait set. <lb/>Order <lb/>Family <lb/>Species <lb/>Reads <lb/>Mean <lb/>Trimmed <lb/>Length <lb/>95 CI <lb/>Trimmed <lb/>Length <lb/>Min Max Median <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Acestrorhynchidae Acestrorhynchus falcatus <lb/>2,046,124 <lb/>98.24 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Alestidae <lb/>Alestes inferus <lb/>1,847,106 <lb/>118.76 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Anostomus anostomus <lb/>1,357,565 <lb/>95.15 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Laemolyta proxima <lb/>3,330,657 <lb/>96.09 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporellus vittatus <lb/>3,734,248 <lb/>96.08 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporinus fasciatus <lb/>1,054,553 <lb/>95.53 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus <lb/>6,350,444 <lb/>96.72 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Bryconidae <lb/>Brycon amazonicus <lb/>3,916,413 <lb/>120.13 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Charax niger <lb/>4,557,912 <lb/>118.99 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus <lb/>8,097,664 <lb/>98.53 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Chilodus punctatus <lb/>5,695,056 <lb/>95.90 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Citharinidae <lb/>Citharinus congicus <lb/>5,077,942 <lb/>119.74 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Crenuchidae <lb/>Crenuchus spilurus <lb/>2,693,174 <lb/>94.68 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Ctenoluciidae <lb/>Ctenolucius hujeta <lb/>3,758,899 <lb/>119.84 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis <lb/>5,082,531 <lb/>96.24 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Cyphocharax spilurus <lb/>6,010,208 <lb/>95.92 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Potamorhina laticeps <lb/>1,559,277 <lb/>95.61 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Psectrogaster rhomboides <lb/>10,674,224 <lb/>98.61 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Steindachnerina bimaculata <lb/>1,656,298 <lb/>93.52 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Distichodontidae <lb/>Distichodus affinis <lb/>5,431,103 <lb/>119.44 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Erythrinidae <lb/>Erythrinus erythrinus <lb/>3,639,480 <lb/>118.76 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hemiodontidae <lb/>Hemiodus quadrimaculatus <lb/>1,631,554 <lb/>117.11 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hepsetidae <lb/>Hepsetus lineata <lb/>4,790,584 <lb/>119.77 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>40 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Lebiasinidae <lb/>Lebiasina bimaculata <lb/>3,046,673 <lb/>118.68 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/>Parodon hillari <lb/>4,561,066 <lb/>98.14 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Prochilodus argenteus <lb/>1,092,497 <lb/>95.65 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama <lb/>8,465,340 <lb/>98.87 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 101 <lb/>101 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Serrasalmidae <lb/>Serrasalmus rhombeus <lb/>1,662,084 <lb/>118.92 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Triportheidae <lb/>Triportheus albus <lb/>1,131,229 <lb/>118.80 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Engraulidae <lb/>Amazonsprattus scintilla <lb/>1,666,800 <lb/>115.99 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Cyprinus carpio <lb/>1,232,988 <lb/>120.37 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Carassius auratus <lb/>2,828,778 <lb/>119.19 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Apteronotidae <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus muelleri <lb/>9,914,493 <lb/>129.60 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>149 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Hypopomidae <lb/>Brachyhypopomus brevirostris <lb/>2,493,236 <lb/>127.80 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>149 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Rhamphichthyidae Rhamphichthys apurensis <lb/>3,358,202 <lb/>124.09 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>149 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Rhamphichthyidae Steatogenys elegans <lb/>4,932,755 <lb/>117.97 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>136 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Sternopygidae <lb/>Eigenmannia vicentespelaea <lb/>4,754,970 <lb/>126.41 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>149 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Sternopygidae <lb/>Rhabdolichops cf. stewarti <lb/>5,764,578 <lb/>123.57 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>149 <lb/>Gymnotiformes Sternopygidae <lb/>Sternopygus macrurus <lb/>3,667,938 <lb/>128.86 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 151 <lb/>150 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Astroblepidae <lb/>Astroblepus grixalvii <lb/>1,227,559 <lb/>118.33 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus <lb/>2,309,437 <lb/>98.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Corydoras aeneus <lb/>3,070,805 <lb/>119.78 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Hoplosternum littorale <lb/>2,602,840 <lb/>98.38 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Delturus carinotus <lb/>823,134 <lb/>120.64 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hisonotus notatus <lb/>1,869,986 <lb/>98.05 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hypostomus strigaticeps <lb/>524,859 <lb/>120.55 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>40 125 <lb/>125 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera <lb/>1,833,881 <lb/>98.57 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rineloricaria lima <lb/>1,569,938 <lb/>97.59 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Scoloplacidae <lb/>Scoloplax dicra <lb/>3,626,939 <lb/>97.38 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Copionodon pecten <lb/>2,000,677 <lb/>98.30 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Ituglanis laticeps <lb/>3,235,129 <lb/>97.94 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Stauroglanis gouldingi <lb/>2,053,042 <lb/>98.09 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/></body>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Siluriformes <lb/> Trichomycteridae <lb/>Trichomycterus aerolatus <lb/>2,820,795 <lb/>97.87 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>40 100 <lb/>100 <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. The number of assembled contigs and summary statistics of assembled contigs for each enriched DNA library. <lb/>Order <lb/>Family <lb/>Species <lb/>Contigs <lb/>Total <lb/>BP <lb/>Mean <lb/>Length <lb/>(BP) <lb/>Mean <lb/>Length <lb/>(95 CI) <lb/>Min <lb/>Length <lb/>Max <lb/>Length <lb/>Number <lb/>of <lb/>Contigs &gt; <lb/>1Kbp <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Acestrorhynchidae <lb/>Acestrorhynchus falcatus <lb/>4,885 <lb/>2,755,244 <lb/>564.0 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>7,107 <lb/>455 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Alestidae <lb/>Alestes inferus <lb/>11,347 <lb/>5,078,669 <lb/>447.6 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>2,220 <lb/>816 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Anostomus anostomus <lb/>2,008 <lb/>429.6 <lb/>9.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>14,083 <lb/>56 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Laemolyta proxima <lb/>6,643 <lb/>2,745,355 <lb/>413.3 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,683 <lb/>229 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporellus vittatus <lb/>8,480 <lb/>3,768,412 <lb/>444.4 <lb/>5.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>6,562 <lb/>493 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporinus fasciatus <lb/>1,730 <lb/>661,620 <lb/>382.4 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,216 <lb/>27 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus <lb/>19,711 <lb/>7,302,899 <lb/>370.5 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,702 <lb/>443 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Bryconidae <lb/>Brycon amazonicus <lb/>21,322 <lb/>7,950,573 <lb/>372.9 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,572 <lb/>774 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Charax niger <lb/>35,699 <lb/>14,067,296 <lb/>394.1 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>8,474 <lb/>1482 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus <lb/>23,513 <lb/>8,633,443 <lb/>367.2 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,642 <lb/>772 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Chilodus punctatus <lb/>10,526 <lb/>5,218,663 <lb/>495.8 <lb/>5.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,837 <lb/>816 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Citharinidae <lb/>Citharinus congicus <lb/>23,913 <lb/>10,478,252 <lb/>438.2 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>3,888 <lb/>1607 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Crenuchidae <lb/>Crenuchus spilurus <lb/>6,996 <lb/>2,839,099 <lb/>405.8 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>10,170 <lb/>192 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Ctenoluciidae <lb/>Ctenolucius hujeta <lb/>21,309 <lb/>7,846,381 <lb/>368.2 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,521 <lb/>1027 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis <lb/>10,925 <lb/>4,367,422 <lb/>399.8 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,689 <lb/>353 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Cyphocharax spilurus <lb/>15,187 <lb/>5,689,979 <lb/>374.7 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,708 <lb/>388 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Potamorhina laticeps <lb/>2,190 <lb/>868,744 <lb/>396.7 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>3,530 <lb/>72 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Psectrogaster rhomboides <lb/>27,373 <lb/>9,921,408 <lb/>362.5 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,707 <lb/>934 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Steindachnerina bimaculata <lb/>3,013 <lb/>1,196,573 <lb/>397.1 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>12,181 <lb/>58 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Distichodontidae <lb/>Distichodus affinis <lb/>25,269 <lb/>10,864,170 <lb/>429.9 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,566 <lb/>1583 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Erythrinidae <lb/>Erythrinus erythrinus <lb/>21,360 <lb/>9,496,550 <lb/>444.6 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,463 <lb/>1610 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hemiodontidae <lb/>Hemiodus quadrimaculatus <lb/>11,421 <lb/>5,750,493 <lb/>503.5 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,338 <lb/>1475 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hepsetidae <lb/>Hepsetus lineata <lb/>23,395 <lb/>9,657,190 <lb/>412.8 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>5,248 <lb/>1451 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Lebiasinidae <lb/>Lebiasina bimaculata <lb/>15,515 <lb/>6,691,985 <lb/>431.3 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>8,342 <lb/>1089 <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>Characiformes <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/>Parodon hillari <lb/>9,155 <lb/>4,088,808 <lb/>446.6 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,653 <lb/>487 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Prochilodus argenteus <lb/>1,822 <lb/>1,060,891 <lb/>582.3 <lb/>18.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,610 <lb/>211 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama <lb/>22,037 <lb/>9,334,273 <lb/>423.6 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,698 <lb/>1011 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Serrasalmidae <lb/>Serrasalmus rhombeus <lb/>9,238 <lb/>3,903,182 <lb/>422.5 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,685 <lb/>103 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Triportheidae <lb/>Triportheus albus <lb/>7,708 <lb/>3,604,829 <lb/>467.7 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>6,015 <lb/>640 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Engraulidae <lb/>Amazonsprattus scintilla <lb/>11,784 <lb/>4,179,791 <lb/>354.7 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>6,005 <lb/>253 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Cyprinus carpio <lb/>9,653 <lb/>6,076,242 <lb/>629.5 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>2,691 <lb/>1444 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Carassius auratus <lb/>13,623 <lb/>10,087,435 <lb/>740.5 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>6,213 <lb/>4748 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Apteronotidae <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus <lb/>muelleri <lb/>181,463 <lb/>53,120,647 <lb/>292.7 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>15,867 <lb/>942 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Hypopomidae <lb/>Brachyhypopomus <lb/>brevirostris <lb/>20,756 <lb/>7,063,131 <lb/>340.3 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>12,845 <lb/>359 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae <lb/>Rhamphichthys apurensis <lb/>29,156 <lb/>9,759,853 <lb/>334.7 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>14,667 <lb/>448 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae <lb/>Steatogenys elegans <lb/>37,852 <lb/>12,734,048 <lb/>336.4 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,893 <lb/>905 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Eigenmannia vicentespelaea <lb/>50,355 <lb/>16,448,810 <lb/>326.7 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,574 <lb/>862 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Rhabdolichops cf. stewarti <lb/>64,172 <lb/>20,084,569 <lb/>313.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>731 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Sternopygus macrurus <lb/>35,246 <lb/>12,939,384 <lb/>367.1 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>16,553 <lb/>1161 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Astroblepidae <lb/>Astroblepus grixalvii <lb/>3,581 <lb/>1,575,742 <lb/>440.0 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>6,294 <lb/>270 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus <lb/>7,634 <lb/>3,940,562 <lb/>516.2 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,791 <lb/>766 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Corydoras aeneus <lb/>13,219 <lb/>5,634,895 <lb/>426.3 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>5,205 <lb/>703 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Hoplosternum littorale <lb/>9,086 <lb/>4,331,667 <lb/>476.7 <lb/>3.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>8,398 <lb/>535 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Delturus carinotus <lb/>5,393 <lb/>2,244,651 <lb/>416.2 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>7,613 <lb/>147 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hisonotus notatus <lb/>5,680 <lb/>2,985,156 <lb/>525.6 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,834 <lb/>189 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hypostomus strigaticeps <lb/>3,421 <lb/>1,471,826 <lb/>430.2 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,464 <lb/>86 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera <lb/>6,607 <lb/>3,810,693 <lb/>576.8 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,627 <lb/>937 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rineloricaria lima <lb/>6,259 <lb/>3,810,618 <lb/>608.8 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>7,809 <lb/>1117 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Scoloplacidae <lb/>Scoloplax dicra <lb/>8,128 <lb/>4,274,975 <lb/>526.0 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>8,006 <lb/>852 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Copionodon pecten <lb/>8,174 <lb/>3,392,810 <lb/>415.1 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,599 <lb/>336 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Ituglanis laticeps <lb/>8,752 <lb/>4,773,973 <lb/>545.5 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>7,467 <lb/>1019 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Stauroglanis gouldingi <lb/>4,894 <lb/>2,427,340 <lb/>496.0 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>4,347 <lb/>292 <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<body>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Trichomycterus aerolatus <lb/>7,943 <lb/>4,129,335 <lb/>519.9 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>8,134 <lb/>525 <lb/></body>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. The number of ultraconserved element (UCE) loci identified among the assembled contigs and summary statistics of these <lb/>UCE loci for all taxa included in this study. Asterisks by species names indicate those taxa for which we included UCE loci harvested <lb/>in silico. <lb/>Order <lb/>Family <lb/>Species <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contigs <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contig <lb/>Mean <lb/>Length <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contig <lb/>95 CI <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contig <lb/>Min <lb/>Length <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contig <lb/>Max <lb/>Length <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contig <lb/>Median <lb/>Length <lb/>UCE <lb/>Contigs <lb/>&gt; 1 <lb/>Kbp <lb/>Anguilliformes <lb/>Anguillidae <lb/>Anguilla japonica* <lb/>897 <lb/>196.1 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>110 <lb/>771 <lb/>187 <lb/>0 <lb/>Beloniformes <lb/>Adrianichthyidae <lb/>Oryzias latipes* <lb/>969 <lb/>196.9 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>78 <lb/>726 <lb/>190 <lb/>0 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Acestrorhynchidae Acestrorhynchus falcatus <lb/>1667 <lb/>713.0 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>4420 <lb/>728 <lb/>257 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Alestidae <lb/>Alestes inferus <lb/>1788 <lb/>777.5 <lb/>7.1 <lb/>202 <lb/>1551 <lb/>792.5 <lb/>480 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Anostomus anostomus <lb/>855 <lb/>432.9 <lb/>16.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>14083 <lb/>387 <lb/>1 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Laemolyta proxima <lb/>1280 <lb/>484.6 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>1075 <lb/>468 <lb/>6 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporellus vittatus <lb/>1379 <lb/>443.4 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>1003 <lb/>429 <lb/>1 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Leporinus fasciatus <lb/>790 <lb/>386.1 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>2363 <lb/>371.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus <lb/>1613 <lb/>519.8 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>1173 <lb/>507 <lb/>11 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Bryconidae <lb/>Brycon amazonicus <lb/>1792 <lb/>709.1 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>203 <lb/>5902 <lb/>714 <lb/>251 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Astyanax mexicanus* <lb/>1880 <lb/>1102.6 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>265 <lb/>1647 <lb/>1132.5 <lb/>1626 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Charax niger <lb/>1701 <lb/>851.3 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>1888 <lb/>878 <lb/>641 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus <lb/>1676 <lb/>672.0 <lb/>11.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>16642 <lb/>637.5 <lb/>249 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Chilodus punctatus <lb/>1579 <lb/>596.5 <lb/>6.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>2453 <lb/>570 <lb/>99 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Citharinidae <lb/>Citharinus congicus <lb/>1721 <lb/>875.2 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>202 <lb/>3765 <lb/>887 <lb/>664 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Crenuchidae <lb/>Crenuchus spilurus <lb/>1195 <lb/>495.0 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>201 <lb/>1323 <lb/>485 <lb/>5 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Ctenoluciidae <lb/>Ctenolucius hujeta <lb/>1594 <lb/>799.4 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>202 <lb/>1423 <lb/>832 <lb/>466 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis <lb/>1474 <lb/>506.2 <lb/>4.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>1160 <lb/>492 <lb/>7 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Cyphocharax spilurus <lb/>1477 <lb/>460.1 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>1392 <lb/>441 <lb/>4 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Potamorhina laticeps <lb/>799 <lb/>357.4 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>1604 <lb/>335 <lb/>1 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Psectrogaster rhomboides <lb/>1465 <lb/>594.1 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>1734 <lb/>535 <lb/>176 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Steindachnerina bimaculata <lb/>868 <lb/>462.1 <lb/>14.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>12181 <lb/>419 <lb/>1 <lb/></body>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<body>Characiformes <lb/>Distichodontidae <lb/>Distichodus affinis <lb/>1710 <lb/>915.6 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>2114 <lb/>958.5 <lb/>769 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Erythrinidae <lb/>Erythrinus erythrinus <lb/>1756 <lb/>859.6 <lb/>7.2 <lb/>202 <lb/>2259 <lb/>892 <lb/>673 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hemiodontidae <lb/>Hemiodus quadrimaculatus <lb/>1836 <lb/>874.8 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>203 <lb/>2066 <lb/>918 <lb/>764 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Hepsetidae <lb/>Hepsetus lineata <lb/>1814 <lb/>918.3 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>202 <lb/>5248 <lb/>955 <lb/>835 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Lebiasinidae <lb/>Lebiasina bimaculata <lb/>1779 <lb/>852.8 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>1855 <lb/>885 <lb/>629 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/>Parodon hillari <lb/>1472 <lb/>525.1 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>1098 <lb/>502.5 <lb/>18 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Prochilodus argenteus <lb/>693 <lb/>365.5 <lb/>23.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>16610 <lb/>320 <lb/>1 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama <lb/>1671 <lb/>597.8 <lb/>5.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>1408 <lb/>597 <lb/>63 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Serrasalmidae <lb/>Serrasalmus rhombeus <lb/>1830 <lb/>656.2 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>1283 <lb/>687 <lb/>25 <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Triportheidae <lb/>Triportheus albus <lb/>1660 <lb/>753.6 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>201 <lb/>1793 <lb/>774 <lb/>394 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Clupeidae <lb/>Clupea harengus* <lb/>1360 <lb/>1118.1 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>188 <lb/>2785 <lb/>1136 <lb/>1246 <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Engraulidae <lb/>Amazonsprattus scintilla <lb/>867 <lb/>607.3 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>3038 <lb/>556 <lb/>96 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Cyprinus carpio <lb/>780 <lb/>767.3 <lb/>9.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>2599 <lb/>802.5 <lb/>160 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Danionidae <lb/>Danio rerio* <lb/>2218 <lb/>227.7 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>141 <lb/>751 <lb/>210 <lb/>0 <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Cyprinidae <lb/>Carassius auratus <lb/>525 <lb/>960.8 <lb/>17.3 <lb/>202 <lb/>2919 <lb/>1050 <lb/>278 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Apteronotidae <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus muelleri <lb/>1881 <lb/>611.5 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>5445 <lb/>615 <lb/>54 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Gymnotidae <lb/>Electrophorus electricus* <lb/>1928 <lb/>1152.7 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>388 <lb/>1640 <lb/>1156 <lb/>1877 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Hypopomidae <lb/>Brachyhypopomus brevirostris <lb/>1779 <lb/>531.4 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>201 <lb/>12845 <lb/>528 <lb/>7 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae Rhamphichthys apurensis <lb/>1759 <lb/>557.6 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>202 <lb/>1139 <lb/>567 <lb/>9 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae Steatogenys elegans <lb/>1771 <lb/>491.6 <lb/>3.8 <lb/>201 <lb/>2194 <lb/>488 <lb/>2 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Eigenmannia vicentespelaea <lb/>1836 <lb/>582.1 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>202 <lb/>2019 <lb/>593 <lb/>17 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Rhabdolichops cf. stewarti <lb/>1824 <lb/>593.2 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>202 <lb/>4650 <lb/>597 <lb/>30 <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Sternopygus macrurus <lb/>1849 <lb/>569.4 <lb/>9.5 <lb/>202 <lb/>16553 <lb/>566 <lb/>9 <lb/>Lepisosteiformes <lb/>Lepisosteidae <lb/>Lepisosteus oculatus* <lb/>1158 <lb/>202.7 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>125 <lb/>710 <lb/>199 <lb/>0 <lb/>Osteoglossiformes Osteoglossidae <lb/>Scleropages formosus* <lb/>944 <lb/>194.3 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>67 <lb/>690 <lb/>190 <lb/>0 <lb/>Perciformes <lb/>Gasterosteidae <lb/>Gasterosteus aculeatus* <lb/>1052 <lb/>202.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>100 <lb/>650 <lb/>199 <lb/>0 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Astroblepidae <lb/>Astroblepus grixalvii <lb/>859 <lb/>680.2 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>1791 <lb/>674 <lb/>186 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus <lb/>1525 <lb/>838.1 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>202 <lb/>1630 <lb/>856 <lb/>455 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Corydoras aeneus <lb/>1411 <lb/>758.1 <lb/>7.3 <lb/>201 <lb/>2179 <lb/>784 <lb/>276 <lb/></body>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<body>Siluriformes <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Hoplosternum littorale <lb/>1587 <lb/>779.6 <lb/>6.3 <lb/>202 <lb/>1782 <lb/>792 <lb/>324 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Ictaluridae <lb/>Ictalurus punctatus* <lb/>1862 <lb/>1138.9 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>465 <lb/>1599 <lb/>1144 <lb/>1804 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Delturus carinotus <lb/>1329 <lb/>639.6 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>202 <lb/>1618 <lb/>660 <lb/>86 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hisonotus notatus <lb/>1491 <lb/>705.6 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>201 <lb/>1556 <lb/>740 <lb/>71 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Hypostomus strigaticeps <lb/>1070 <lb/>538.6 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>1293 <lb/>532 <lb/>13 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera <lb/>1542 <lb/>855.6 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>202 <lb/>1723 <lb/>879 <lb/>533 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>Rineloricaria lima <lb/>1416 <lb/>899.4 <lb/>8.4 <lb/>201 <lb/>1771 <lb/>917 <lb/>579 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Scoloplax dicra <lb/>1087 <lb/>821.4 <lb/>9.4 <lb/>203 <lb/>2020 <lb/>825 <lb/>315 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae Copionodon pecten <lb/>1380 <lb/>742.0 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>201 <lb/>2535 <lb/>764 <lb/>186 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae Ituglanis laticeps <lb/>1511 <lb/>848.5 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>202 <lb/>1996 <lb/>856 <lb/>491 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae Stauroglanis gouldingi <lb/>1191 <lb/>697.9 <lb/>8.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>2612 <lb/>690 <lb/>179 <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Trichomycteridae Trichomycterus aerolatus <lb/>1432 <lb/>782.4 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>201 <lb/>2245 <lb/>818 <lb/>233 <lb/>Tetraodontiformes Tetraodontidae <lb/>Takifugu rubripes* <lb/>991 <lb/>196.0 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>96 <lb/>740 <lb/>184 <lb/>0 <lb/></body>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figures <lb/>Figure 1. A depiction of relationships among the groups comprising Otocephala and the taxonomic <lb/>nomenclature used to refer to otocephalan subclades. <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Osteoglossiformes <lb/>Gonorynchiformes <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Otocephala (syn. Otomorpha) <lb/>Ostariophysi <lb/>Otophysi <lb/>Characiphysi <lb/></body>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic hypothesis of relationships among taxa comprising the <lb/>Gymnotiformes data set with family names in color. Danio rerio is the outgroup taxon, and bootstrap <lb/>support is indicated at each node. An asterisk by any taxon name indicates that these data were harvested, <lb/>in silico, from existing genome assemblies, and the numbers in parentheses to the right of each taxon <lb/>denote the count of loci enriched/harvested from that organism. <lb/>Danio rerio* (2218 loci) <lb/>Rhabdolichops cf. stewarti (1824 loci) <lb/>Rhamphichthys apurensis (175 9 loci) <lb/>Sternopygus macrurus (1849 loci) <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus muelleri (1881 loci) <lb/>Brachyhypopomus brevirostris (1779 loci) <lb/>Electrophorus electricus* (1928 loci) <lb/>Steatogenys elegans (1771 loci) <lb/>Eigenmannia vicentespelaea (183 6 loci) <lb/>0.03 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>9 8 <lb/>Danionidae (Cypriniformes) <lb/>Apteronotidae <lb/>Sternopygidae <lb/>Gymnotidae <lb/>Hypopomidae <lb/>Rhamphichthyidae <lb/></body>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic hypothesis of relationships among taxa comprising the <lb/>Anostomoidea data set with family names in color. Parodon hillari is the outgroup taxon, and bootstrap <lb/>support is indicated at each node. The numbers in parentheses to the right of each taxon denote the count <lb/>of loci enriched from that organism. <lb/>Psectrogaster rhomboides (1465 loci) <lb/>Laemolyta proxima (1280 loci) <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama (1671 loci) <lb/>Cyphocharax spilurus (1477 loci) <lb/>Parodon hillari (1472 loci) <lb/>Potamorhina laticeps (799 loci) <lb/>Chilodus punctatus (1579 loci) <lb/>Steindachnerina bimaculata (868 loci) <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis (1474 loci) <lb/>Anostomus anostomus (855 loci) <lb/>Leporellus vittatus (1379 loci) <lb/>Prochilodus argenteus (693 loci) <lb/>Leporinus fasciatus (790 loci) <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus (1676 loci) <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus (1613 loci) <lb/>0.02 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>9 8 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/></body>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic hypothesis of relationships among taxa comprising the <lb/>Loricarioidei data set with family names in color. Ictalurus punctatus is the outgroup taxon, and bootstrap <lb/>support is indicated at each node. An asterisk by any taxon name indicates that these data were harvested, <lb/>in silico, from existing genome assemblies, and the numbers in parentheses to the right of each taxon <lb/>denote the count of loci enriched/harvested from that organism. <lb/>Ituglanis laticeps (1511 loci) <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera (1542 loci) <lb/>Copionodon pecten (1380 loci) <lb/>Astroblepus grixalvii (859 loci) <lb/>Corydoras aeneus (1411 loci) <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus (1525 loci) <lb/>Stauroglanis gouldingi (1191 loci) <lb/>Hypostomus strigaticeps (1070 loci) <lb/>Scoloplax dicra (1087 loci) <lb/>Hoplosternum littorale (1587 loci) <lb/>Ictalurus punctatus* (1862 loci) <lb/>Trichomycterus aerolatus (1432 loci) <lb/>Delturus carinotus (1329 loci) <lb/>Rineloricaria lima (1416 loci) <lb/>Hisonotus notatus (1491 loci) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Ictaluridae <lb/>Trichomycteridae <lb/>Callichthyidae <lb/>Scoloplacidae <lb/>Astroblepidae <lb/>Loricariidae <lb/>100 <lb/></body>

			<page>52 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic hypothesis of relationships among taxa comprising the <lb/>Characiformes data set with family names in color. Ictalurus punctatus is the outgroup taxon, and <lb/>bootstrap support is indicated at each node. An asterisk by any taxon name indicates that these data were <lb/>harvested, in silico, from existing genome assemblies, and the numbers in parentheses to the right of each <lb/>taxon denote the count of loci enriched/harvested from that organism. <lb/>Caenotropus labyrinthicus (1676 loci) <lb/>Ctenolucius hujeta (1594 loci) <lb/>Parodon hillari (1472 loci) <lb/>Schizodon fasciatus (1613 loci) <lb/>Ictalurus punctatus* (1862 loci) <lb/>Hemiodus quadrimaculatus (1836 loci) <lb/>Semaprochilodus brama (1671 loci) <lb/>Crenuchus spilurus (1195 loci) <lb/>Triportheus albus (1660 loci) <lb/>Lebiasina bimaculata (1779 loci) <lb/>Curimatopsis macrolepis (1474 loci) <lb/>Distichodus affinis (1710 loci) <lb/>Alestes inferus (1788 loci) <lb/>Erythrinus erythrinus (1756 loci) <lb/>Brycon amazonicus (1792 loci) <lb/>Citharinus congicus (1721 loci) <lb/>Serrasalmus rhombeus (1830 loci) <lb/>Acestrorhynchus falcatus (1667 loci) <lb/>Hepsetus lineata (1814 loci) <lb/>Pygocentrus nattereri* (1943 loci) <lb/>Astyanax mexicanus* (1880 loci) <lb/>Charax niger (1701 loci) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>8 4 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>Ictaluridae (Siluriformes) <lb/>Distichodontidae <lb/>Citharinidae <lb/>Crenuchidae <lb/>Lebiasinidae <lb/>Ctenoluciidae <lb/>Characidae <lb/>Acestrorhynchidae <lb/>Bryconidae <lb/>Triportheidae <lb/>Alestidae <lb/>Hepsetidae <lb/>Erythrinidae <lb/>Parodontidae <lb/>Hemiodontidae <lb/>Serrasalmidae <lb/>Anostomidae <lb/>Chilodontidae <lb/>Prochilodontidae <lb/>Curimatidae <lb/></body>

			<page>53 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Maximum likelihood phylogenetic hypothesis of relationships among taxa comprising the <lb/>Otocephala data set with family names in color. Lepisosteus oculatus is the outgroup taxon, and bootstrap <lb/>support is indicated at each node. An asterisk by any taxon name indicates that these data were harvested, <lb/>in silico, from existing genome assemblies, and the numbers in parentheses to the right of each taxon <lb/>denote the count of loci enriched/harvested from that organism. <lb/>Alestes inferus (1788 loci) <lb/>Ictalurus punctatus* (186 2 loci) <lb/>Clupea harengus* (136 0 loci) <lb/>Steatogenys elegans (1771 loci) <lb/>Oryzias latipes* (96 9 loci) <lb/>Amazonsprattus scintilla (86 7 loci) <lb/>Scleropages formosus* (944 loci) <lb/>Distichodus affinis (1710 loci) <lb/>Rhinelepis aspera (1542 loci) <lb/>Hepsetus lineata (1814 loci) <lb/>Takifugu rubripes* (991 loci) <lb/>Carassius auratus (525 loci) <lb/>Sternarchorhamphus muelleri (1881 loci) <lb/>Danio rerio* (2218 locI) <lb/>Astyanax mexicanus* (1880 loci) <lb/>Anguilla japonica* (897 loci) <lb/>Citharinus congicus (1721 loci) <lb/>Lepisosteus oculatus* (1158 loci) <lb/>Aspidoras fuscoguttatus (1525 loci) <lb/>Gasterosteus aculeatus* (1052 loci) <lb/>Cyprinus carpio (780 loci) <lb/>0.07 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>5 2 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>9 7 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>5 8 <lb/>100 <lb/>Lepisosteiformes <lb/>Anguilliformes <lb/>Osteoglossiformes <lb/>Clupeiformes <lb/>Cypriniformes <lb/>Gymnotiformes <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Characiformes <lb/>Siluriformes <lb/>Euteleostei </body>


	</text>
</tei>
