<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Mortality in trauma patients admitted during, before, and after national academic <lb/>emergency medicine and trauma surgery meeting dates in Japan <lb/>Tetsuya Yumoto 1* , Hiromichi Naito 1 , Hiromi Ihoriya 1 , Takashi Yorifuji 2 , Atsunori Nakao 1 <lb/>1 Department of Emergency, Critical Care, and Disaster Medicine, Okayama University Graduate <lb/>School of Medicine, Dentistry and Pharmaceutical Sciences, Okayama, Japan <lb/>2 Department of Human Ecology, Okayama University Graduate School of Environmental and Life <lb/>Science, Okayama, Japan <lb/>*Corresponding author: <lb/>E-mail: tyumoto@cc.okayama-u.ac.jp (TYu) <lb/>2 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Annually, many physicians attend national academic meetings. While participating in these meetings <lb/>can have a positive impact on daily medical practice, attendance may result in reduced medical <lb/>staffing during the meeting dates. We sought to examine whether there were differences in mortality <lb/>after trauma among patients admitted to the hospital during, before, and after meeting dates. Using <lb/>the Japan Trauma Data Bank, we analyzed in-hospital mortality in patients with traumatic injury <lb/>admitted to the hospital from 2004 to 2015 during the dates of two national academic meetings -the <lb/>Japanese Association for Acute Medicine (JAAM) and the Japanese Association for the Surgery of <lb/>Trauma (JAST). We compared the data with that of patients admitted with trauma during identical <lb/>weekdays in the weeks before and after the meetings, respectively. We used multiple logistic <lb/>regression analysis to compare outcomes among the three groups. A total of 7,491 patients were <lb/>included in our analyses, with 2,481, 2,492, and 2,518 patients in the during, before, and after <lb/>meeting dates groups, respectively; their mortality rates were 7.3%, 8.0%, and 8.5%, respectively. <lb/>After adjusting for covariates, no significant differences in in-hospital mortality were found among <lb/>the three groups (adjusted odds ratio [95% CI] of the before meeting dates and after meeting dates <lb/>groups; 1.18 [0.89-1.56] and 1.23 [0.93-1.63], respectively, with the during meeting dates group as <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>the reference category). No significant differences in in-hospital mortality were found among trauma <lb/>patients admitted during, before, and after the JAAM and JAST meeting dates. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Appropriate medical staffing is essential to provide optimal trauma care [1]. Weekend or off-hours <lb/>admission has been shown to be associated with worse outcomes in patients with acute myocardial <lb/>infarction (AMI), stroke, pulmonary embolism, or those who required emergency general surgery <lb/>and were admitted to the intensive care unit [2-6]. This so-called &quot;weekend effect&quot; could possibly be <lb/>explained by reduced medical staffing and resources [7, 8]. <lb/>This &quot;national meeting effect&quot; has been examined in recent years [9-12]. Each year, many <lb/>physicians attend national academic meetings and conferences to present their work, gain new <lb/>knowledge, and network. Although hospitals aim to consistently deliver high quality patient care <lb/>through efficient allocation of staff physicians, medical staffing during national meetings dates may <lb/>be lower than that during non-meeting dates. The &quot;national meeting effect&quot; in Japan has been <lb/>investigated; no significant differences were observed in outcomes among patients hospitalized with <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>AMI or cardiac arrest between meeting dates and non-meeting dates [9, 10]. Interestingly, lower 30-<lb/>day mortality was found among high-risk patients with AMI, cardiac arrest, and heart failure in <lb/>teaching hospitals in the United States during national cardiology meeting dates [11, 12]. <lb/>Although a &quot;weekend effect&quot; in terms of mortality has not been detected [13-15], longer emergency <lb/>department stay and increased risk for missed injuries have been demonstrated for trauma patients <lb/>admitted during off-hours in a community hospital setting [16]. To our knowledge, the &quot;national <lb/>meeting effect&quot; among trauma patients has never been well elucidated. We hypothesized that <lb/>hospital mortality would be higher during the meeting dates of national scientific emergency <lb/>medicine and trauma surgery professional organizations than non-meeting dates and hospital <lb/>mortality would be lower after the meeting dates than before the meeting dates because of reduced <lb/>staffing and the positive impact of the academic meeting on high physician performance. Our <lb/>study&apos;s aim was to compare hospital mortality after trauma among patients admitted during, before, <lb/>and after national meeting dates. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and methods <lb/>Study design and data sources <lb/>This study was designed as a nationwide retrospective cohort study. We used data from the Japan <lb/>Trauma Data Bank (JTDB), which was established in 2003 with the Committee for Clinical Care <lb/>Evaluation of the Japanese Association for Acute Medicine and the Trauma Surgery Committee of <lb/>the Japanese Association for the Surgery of Trauma (JAST). Patients with Abbreviated Injury Scale <lb/>(AIS) scores of 3 or above are recorded in the database from 264 Japanese hospitals participating in <lb/>trauma research and care [17]. The registry database contains patient demographics, mechanism of <lb/>injury, vital signs at the scene and on arrival, admission date, AIS scores, Injury Severity Score <lb/>(ISS), treatments, and survival status at discharge from hospitals. The Okayama University Hospital <lb/>ethical committee approved the study (ID 1805-020). Since patient data was extracted anonymously, <lb/>the requirement for informed consent was waived. <lb/>Study sample <lb/>We obtained annual national meeting dates of two academic organizations -the Japanese Association <lb/>for Acute Medicine (JAAM) and JAST -from 2004 to 2015. The during meeting dates group included <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>patients admitted after traumatic injury during the dates of these meetings. The before and after <lb/>meeting dates groups were defined as patients admitted with trauma during the same weekdays in the <lb/>weeks before and after the meetings, respectively [9, 10]. The JAAM and JAST meetings are each <lb/>usually held for two or three consecutive days. For example, the 2015 JAAM meeting was held from <lb/>Wednesday, October 21 through Friday, October 23; the before and after meeting dates groups <lb/>included patients admitted Wednesday through Friday in the weeks before and after the meeting, <lb/>respectively. In this study, patients who were 16 years of age or older admitted with traumatic injury <lb/>from 2004 to 2015 were enrolled. Patients in cardiac arrest at the scene or on arrival and those without <lb/>age, hospital arrival date, and in-hospital mortality data were excluded. <lb/>Outcome measures <lb/>Our primary outcome was post-trauma in-hospital mortality from all causes among patients <lb/>hospitalized during, before, and after national meeting dates. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Comparisons among the three groups were made using the chi-square test for categorical variables <lb/>and analysis of variance for continuous variables. We used multiple logistic regression analysis to <lb/>compare outcomes between the three groups, with the during meeting dates group as the reference <lb/>category. Adjusted odds ratios (ORs) and their 95% confidence intervals (CIs) were obtained after <lb/>adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤); gender; mechanism of injury (blunt or others); transfer <lb/>from outside hospitals; ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. 90mmHg≤ on arrival); Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 <lb/>vs. 9-15); presence or absence of emergency surgical or hemostatic intervention (craniotomy, <lb/>thoracotomy, laparotomy, or angioembolization); and type of institution (high vs. low volume <lb/>centers). Because outcomes would be better at the high-volume centers, an additional analysis was <lb/>conducted by dividing the patients into two groups; high volume centers (≥1,200 cases with ISS≥9 <lb/>registered for 12 years) and low volume centers (&lt;1,200 cases with ISS≥9 registered for 12 years) <lb/>[18]. A subgroup analysis was also conducted, stratifying patients with or without shock and the type <lb/>of national meeting. Sensitivity analysis was conducted using alternative definitions of the before <lb/>and after meeting dates groups; two, three, and four weeks before and two, three, and four weeks <lb/>after meeting dates, respectively, instead of one week. A two-tailed P value of &lt;0.05 was considered <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>statistically significant. All analyses were performed using IBM SPSS Statistics 25 (IBM SPSS, <lb/>Chicago, IL, U.S.A.). <lb/>Results <lb/>Patient characteristics <lb/>A total of 236,698 trauma patients were registered in the JTDB during the study period. Of those, <lb/>182,877 adult trauma patients were assessed for eligibility. After 175,386 patients were excluded <lb/>due to not being admitted on eligible days, 7,491 subjects were included in our analyses, with 2,481 <lb/>patients in the during meeting dates group, 2,492 patients in the before meeting dates group, and <lb/>2,518 patients in the after meeting dates group (Fig. 1). Among the three groups of patients, basic <lb/>characteristics including severity of trauma and life-saving surgical procedures were similar except <lb/>for the age category (Table 1). <lb/>Fig 1. Flow diagram of the study population. <lb/>JTDB, Japan Trauma Data Bank. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Characteristics of trauma injury patients admitted during, before, and after national meeting <lb/>dates. <lb/>Before meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>n=2,492 <lb/>During meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>n=2,481 <lb/>After meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>n=2,518 <lb/>P-Value <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>63 (41, 77) <lb/>63 (41, 77) <lb/>65 (43, 78) <lb/>0.131 <lb/>16-39, n (%) <lb/>541 (21.7) <lb/>604 (24.3) <lb/>566 (22.5) <lb/>40-64, n (%) <lb/>750 (30.1) <lb/>708 (28.5) <lb/>675 (26.8) <lb/>65≤, n (%) <lb/>1,201 (48.2) <lb/>1,169 (47.1) <lb/>1,277 (50.7) <lb/>0.015 <lb/>Male, n (%) <lb/>1,557 (62.5) <lb/>1,513 (61.1) <lb/>1,607 (63.9) <lb/>0.126 <lb/>Blunt mechanism, n (%) <lb/>2,347 (94.2) <lb/>2,348 (94.6) <lb/>2,398 (95.2) <lb/>0.249 <lb/>Transfers from an outside hospital, n (%) <lb/>345 (13.8) <lb/>367 (14.8) <lb/>345 (13.7) <lb/>0.485 <lb/>Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) <lb/>136 (116, 158) <lb/>136 (116, 156) <lb/>137 (117, 158) <lb/>0.624 <lb/>&lt;90mmHg, n (%) <lb/>180 (7.2) <lb/>180 (7.3) <lb/>170 (6.8) <lb/>0.731 <lb/>Glasgow Coma Scale <lb/>15 (14, 15) <lb/>15 (14, 15) <lb/>15 (14, 15) <lb/>0.532 <lb/>≤8, n (%) <lb/>245 (9.8) <lb/>242 (9.8) <lb/>256 (10.1) <lb/>0.874 <lb/>Surgical or hemostatic intervention, n (%) <lb/>266 (10.7) <lb/>237 (9.6) <lb/>237 (9.4) <lb/>0.261 <lb/>Craniotomy, n (%) <lb/>101 (4.0) <lb/>83 (3.4) <lb/>82 (3.3) <lb/>0.249 <lb/>Thoracotomy, n (%) <lb/>32 (1.3) <lb/>31 (1.3) <lb/>20 (0.8) <lb/>0.181 <lb/>Laparotomy, n (%) <lb/>76 (3.1) <lb/>72 (2.9) <lb/>66 (2.6) <lb/>0.652 <lb/>Angioembolization, n (%) <lb/>73 (2.9) <lb/>65 (2.6) <lb/>78 (3.1) <lb/>0.592 <lb/>Injury Severity Score <lb/>10 (9, 20) <lb/>10 (9, 20) <lb/>10 (9, 21) <lb/>0.590 <lb/>≤8, n (%) <lb/>407 (16.3) <lb/>399 (16.1) <lb/>398 (15.8) <lb/>9-15, n (%) <lb/>993 (39.8) <lb/>980 (39.5) <lb/>1,016 (40.3) <lb/>16≤, n (%) <lb/>1,009 (40.5) <lb/>1,042 (42.0) <lb/>1,034 (41.1) <lb/>0.904 <lb/>High volume center, n (%) <lb/>1,437 (57.7) <lb/>1,486 (59.9) <lb/>1450 (57.6) <lb/>Low volume center, n (%) <lb/>1,055 (42.3) <lb/>995 (40.1) <lb/>1,068 (42.4) <lb/>0.172 <lb/>In-hospital mortality, n (%) <lb/>200 (8.0) <lb/>181 (7.3) <lb/>213 (8.5) <lb/>0.306 <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Comparison of mortality between the three groups <lb/>No significant differences in in-hospital mortality were observed during, before, and after meeting <lb/>dates (7.3% vs. 8.0% vs. 8.5%, respectively; P=0.306; unadjusted OR [95% CI] of the before and <lb/>after meeting dates groups; 1.11 [0.90-1.37], 1.17 [0.96-1.44], respectively, with the during meeting <lb/>dates group as the reference category; Table 2). Even after adjusting for covariates, no significant <lb/>differences in in-hospital mortality were found among the three groups (adjusted OR [95% CI] of the <lb/>before and after meeting dates groups; 1.18 [0.89-1.56], 1.23 [0.93-1.63], respectively, with the <lb/>during meeting dates group as the reference category; Table 2). <lb/>Table 2. In-hospital mortality after trauma among patients hospitalized during, before, and after <lb/>national meeting dates. <lb/>Before meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>During meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>After meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>P-value <lb/>Overall <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>8.0 (200/2,492) <lb/>7.3 (181/2,481) <lb/>8.5 (213/2,518) <lb/>0.306 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CIs) <lb/>1.11 (0.90-1.37) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.17 (0.96-1.44) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CIs) <lb/>1.18 (0.89-1.56) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.23 (0.93-1.63) <lb/>Adjusted OR and their 95% CIs were obtained after adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤), <lb/>gender, mechanism of injury (blunt or others), transfer from an outside hospital, ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>16≤), presence or absence of shock, Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 vs. 9-15), presence or absence <lb/>emergency surgical or hemostatic intervention, and type of institution (high vs. low volume centers). <lb/>OR: odds ratio; CI: confidence interval; ISS: Injury Severity Score <lb/>Subgroup analysis <lb/>Although high volume centers were associated with better outcomes (6.8% overall in-hospital <lb/>mortality of high volume centers vs. 9.5 % for the low volume centers; P&lt;0.001), in-hospital <lb/>mortality did not differ among the three groups according to center volume (Table 3). Additional <lb/>analyses were conducted by stratifying presence or absence of shock; no differences in in-hospital <lb/>mortality were found among the three groups (Table 3). Also, no significant differences according to <lb/>type of national meeting were found (Table 3). The same results were obtained when considering <lb/>alternative definitions of the before and after meeting dates groups (Table 4). <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3. In-hospital mortality among the three groups with stratification for high vs. low volume <lb/>centers, presence or absence of shock, and type of national meeting. <lb/>Before meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>During meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>After meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>P-value <lb/>High volume centers <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>7.2 (103/1,437) <lb/>6.0 (89/1,486) <lb/>7.3 (106/1,450) <lb/>0.129 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>1.21 (0.90-1.62) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.24 (0.93-1.66) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) a <lb/>1.12 (0.77-1.64) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.30 (0.89-1.89) <lb/>Low volume centers <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>9.2 (97/1,055) <lb/>9.2 (92/995) <lb/>10.0 (107/1,068) <lb/>0.968 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>0.99 (0.74-1.34) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.09 (0.82-1.47) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) a <lb/>1.25 (0.82-1.90) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.17 (0.77-1.78) <lb/>Systolic blood pressure ≤ 90mmHg <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>29.4 (53/180) <lb/>35.6 (64/180) <lb/>34.7 (59/170) <lb/>0.413 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>0.76 (0.49-1.18) <lb/>Reference <lb/>0.96 (0.62-1.50) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) b <lb/>1.09 (0.62-1.90) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.14 (0.66-1.97) <lb/>Systolic blood pressure &gt; 90mmHg <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>6.0 (134/2,252) <lb/>4.5 (101/2,247) <lb/>6.0 (138/2,293) <lb/>0.040 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>1.34 (1.03-1.75) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.36 (1.05-1.77) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) b <lb/>1.28 (0.93-1.74) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.29 (0.95-1.77) <lb/>JAAM <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>8.3 (130/1,560) <lb/>7.4 (112/1,513) <lb/>9.1 (147/1,612) <lb/>0.221 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>1.14 (0.87-1.48) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.26 (0.97-1.62) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) c <lb/>1.28 (0.90-1.80) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.28 (0.91-1.80) <lb/>JAST <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>7.5 (70/932) <lb/>7.1 (69/968) <lb/>7.3 (66/906) <lb/>0.950 <lb/>Crude OR (95% CI) <lb/>1.06 (0.75-1.49) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.02 (0.72-1.45) <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CI) c <lb/>1.21 (0.78-1.88) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.18 (0.75-1.87) <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>a Adjusted OR and their 95% CIs were obtained after adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤), <lb/>gender, mechanism of injury (blunt or others), transfer from an outside hospital, ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. <lb/>16≤), presence or absence of shock, Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 vs. 9-15), and presence or <lb/>absence of emergency surgical or hemostatic intervention. <lb/>b Adjusted OR and their 95% CIs were obtained after adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤), <lb/>gender, mechanism of injury (blunt or others), transfer from an outside hospital, ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. <lb/>16≤), Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 vs. 9-15), presence or absence of emergency surgical or <lb/>hemostatic intervention, and type of institution (high vs. low volume centers). <lb/>c Adjusted OR and their 95% CIs were obtained after adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤), <lb/>gender, mechanism of injury (blunt or others), transfer from an outside hospital, ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. <lb/>16≤), presence or absence of shock, Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 vs. 9-15), presence or absence <lb/>of emergency surgical or hemostatic intervention, and type of institution (high vs. low volume <lb/>centers). <lb/>OR: odds ratio; CIs: confidence intervals; ISS: Injury Severity Score; JAAM, Japanese Association <lb/>for Acute Medicine; JAST, Japanese Association for the Surgery of Trauma. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. In-hospital mortality among the three groups with alternative definitions of the before and <lb/>after meeting dates groups. <lb/>Before meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>During meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>After meeting <lb/>dates group <lb/>P-value <lb/>±2 a <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>7.1 (169/2,397) <lb/>7.3 (181/2,481) <lb/>7.5 (190/2,544) <lb/>0.851 <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CIs) <lb/>1.07 (0.80-1.42) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.27 (0.96-1.68) <lb/>±3 b <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>7.6 (193/2,546) <lb/>7.3 (181/2,481) <lb/>8.2 (207/2,517) <lb/>0.450 <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CIs) <lb/>1.22 (0.92-1.61) <lb/>Reference <lb/>1.21 (0.92-1.61) <lb/>±4 c <lb/>In-hospital mortality, % (n/N) <lb/>7.7 (196/2,538) <lb/>7.3 (181/2,481) <lb/>6.6 (176/2,650 <lb/>0.316 <lb/>Adjusted OR (95% CIs) <lb/>1.23 (0.92-1.62) <lb/>Reference <lb/>0.94 (0.71-1.26) <lb/>a Two weeks before and after meeting dates as the before meeting dates group and after meeting <lb/>dates group. <lb/>b Three weeks before and after meeting dates as the before meeting dates group and after meeting <lb/>dates group. <lb/>c Four weeks before and after meeting dates as the before meeting dates group and after meeting <lb/>dates group. <lb/>Adjusted OR and their 95% CIs were obtained after adjusting for age (16-39 vs. 40-64 vs. 65≤), <lb/>gender, mechanism of injury (blunt or others), transfer from an outside hospital, ISS (≤8 vs. 9-15 vs. <lb/>16≤), presence or absence of shock, Glasgow Coma Scale score (≤8 vs. 9-15), presence or absence <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>of emergency surgical or hemostatic intervention, and type of institution (high vs. low volume <lb/>centers). <lb/>OR: odds ratio; CIs: confidence intervals; ISS: Injury Severity Score. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we investigated whether there was a difference in mortality among patients admitted <lb/>due to traumatic injuries during, before, and after dates of national academic acute medicine and <lb/>trauma meetings. Contrary to our hypothesis, we found no significant differences in in-hospital <lb/>mortality among the three groups, even after adjusting for measurable confounders. <lb/>To our knowledge, &quot;national meeting effects&quot; were first investigated in the United States, focusing <lb/>on national cardiology meetings; lower staffing and differences in composition of physicians during <lb/>the meeting dates were found to possibly affect treatment utilization and outcomes [11]. In this <lb/>study, no significant differences in mortality of AMI patients were found between those in the <lb/>hospital during meeting and non-meeting dates; however, high-risk patients with AMI, cardiac <lb/>arrest, and heart failure admitted to teaching hospitals during meeting dates were found to have <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>lower mortality than those admitted during non-meeting dates [11]. The present study is the first to <lb/>examine the &quot;national meeting effect&quot; regarding mortality in trauma patients. <lb/>Previous studies have not detected the &quot;weekend effect&quot;; admission on nights or weekends for <lb/>trauma patients was not associated with increased mortality [13-16, 19, 20] or even better outcomes <lb/>[21]. Generally, a plausible explanation for the &quot;weekend effect&quot; includes several factors such as <lb/>reduced medical staffing, decreased access to some tests and procedures, and the influence of <lb/>variations in case mix [19, 20, 22]. For trauma patients, hospitals are explicitly required to be <lb/>appropriately staffed and to provide optimal care, regardless of when injured patients are admitted <lb/>[21, 23]. However, trauma patients presenting off-hours were more likely to have missed injuries, <lb/>[16, 24], in particular thoracic spine or abdominal injuries [24]. Specifically, Schwartz DA, et al. <lb/>showed that off-hour presentation of pelvic fracture patients with hemorrhagic shock caused a delay <lb/>in door-to-angioembolization time, resulting in increased mortality [23]. <lb/>In theory, variations of patient characteristics would not be influenced by admission dates occurring <lb/>during, before, and after national meetings. While relatively less experienced emergency physicians <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>or trauma surgeons providing leadership would be expected during academic national meeting dates, <lb/>strong leadership, teamwork, and technical skills are essential components for team performance and <lb/>patient care in initial trauma management [25, 26]. Our results showed no significant differences in <lb/>mortality among those admitted during, before, and after national meeting dates; these findings may <lb/>be explained by the possibility that every hospital strives to consistently deliver high quality care. <lb/>Although no clear evidence exists that national academic meetings directly improve medical staff <lb/>performance and positively impact patient outcomes, hospital participation in a trauma quality <lb/>improvement program has been demonstrated to be associated with better patient outcomes [27]. <lb/>Hence, we compared hospital mortality among patients admitted during, before, and after national <lb/>meeting dates to investigate the &quot;post-national meeting effect,&quot; assuming that participation in <lb/>national academic meetings has a positive effect on clinical performance and patient outcomes. <lb/>Despite our hypothesis, our results detected no &quot;post-national meeting effect.&quot; <lb/>Our study has several limitations. First, we could not identify differences in medical staffing among <lb/>the three groups, such as composition of emergency physicians vs. trauma surgeons who treated the <lb/>patients; therefore, we are unable to explain why no significant differences in mortality were found. <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Second, the influence of national meeting geographical regions and locations was not accounted for, <lb/>which may have affected our results. Third, as Jena AB, et al. showed that high-risk AMI patients <lb/>admitted to teaching hospitals during national meeting dates received less percutaneous coronary <lb/>intervention, hospital type should have been taken into consideration [11]. We performed additional <lb/>analyses according to hospital volume, in which the same results were obtained. Fourth, possible <lb/>confounders, including comorbidities, were unavailable in this study. Fifth, although major tertiary <lb/>hospitals providing high-quality trauma care participate in the JTDB, a degree of random error and <lb/>selection bias may have occurred, as this was not a comprehensive study [17]. Finally, since we <lb/>focused on national academic meetings only in Japan, our results could not be applied to other <lb/>countries, considering differences in the settings and geography of Japanese healthcare systems. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>We observed no significant differences in in-hospital mortality after trauma among patients admitted <lb/>during, before, and after national acute medicine and trauma meeting dates. As hospitals are <lb/>assumed to be struggling to consistently provide optimal care for trauma patients, participating in <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>these meetings is acceptable for sharing and generating new knowledge. Further population-based <lb/>studies are required to validate our results. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We express our gratitude to all the participants in the JTDB registry, members of the Trauma <lb/>Registry Committee (Japanese Association for Trauma Surgery), and the Committee for Clinical <lb/>Care Evaluation (Japanese Association for Acute Medicine). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Mains C, Scarborough K, Bar-Or R, Hawkes A, Huber J, Bourg P, et al. Staff commitment to <lb/>trauma care improves mortality and length of stay at a level I trauma center. J Trauma. 2009;66: <lb/>1315-1320. <lb/>2. Khoshchehreh M, Groves EM, Tehrani D, Amin A, Patel PM, Malik S. Changes in mortality on <lb/>weekend versus weekday admissions for Acute Coronary Syndrome in the United States over the <lb/>past decade. Int J Cardiol. 2016;210: 164-172. <lb/>3. Roberts SE, Thorne K, Akbari A, Samuel DG, Williams JG. Mortality following Stroke, the <lb/>Weekend Effect and Related Factors: Record Linkage Study. PLoS One. 2015;10: e0131836. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>4. Nanchal R, Kumar G, Taneja A, Patel J, Deshmukh A, Tarima S, et al; from the Milwaukee <lb/>Initiative in Critical Care Outcomes Research (MICCOR) Group of Investigators. Pulmonary <lb/>embolism: the weekend effect. Chest. 2012;142: 690-696. <lb/>5. Metcalfe D, Castillo-Angeles M, Rios-Diaz AJ, Havens JM, Haider A, Salim A. Is there a <lb/>&quot;weekend effect&quot; in emergency general surgery? J Surg Res. 2018;222: 219-224. <lb/>6. Uusaro A, Kari A, Ruokonen E. The effects of ICU admission and discharge times on mortality in <lb/>Finland. Intensive Care Med. 2003;29: 2144-2148. <lb/>7. Neuraz A, Guérin C, Payet C, Polazzi S, Aubrun F, Dailler F, et al. Patient Mortality Is <lb/>Associated with Staff Resources and Workload in the ICU: A Multicenter Observational Study. Crit <lb/>Care Med. 2015;43: 1587-1594. <lb/>8. Sorita A, Ahmed A, Starr SR, Thompson KM, Reed DA, Prokop L, et al. Off-hour presentation <lb/>and outcomes in patients with acute myocardial infarction: systematic review and meta-analysis. <lb/>BMJ. 2014;348: f7393. <lb/>9. Mizuno S, Kunisawa S, Sasaki N, Fushimi K, Imanaka Y. In-hospital mortality and treatment <lb/>patterns in acute myocardial infarction patients admitted during national cardiology meeting dates. <lb/>Int J Cardiol. 2016;220: 929-936. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>10. Kitamura T, Kiyohara K, Matsuyama T, Hatakeyama T, Shimamoto T, Izawa J, et al. Is Survival <lb/>After Out-of-Hospital Cardiac Arrests Worse During Days of National Academic Meetings in <lb/>Japan? A Population-Based Study. J Epidemiol. 2016;26: 155-162. <lb/>11. Jena AB, Prasad V, Goldman DP, Romley J. Mortality and treatment patterns among patients <lb/>hospitalized with acute cardiovascular conditions during dates of national cardiology meetings. <lb/>JAMA Intern Med. 2015;175: 237-244. <lb/>12. Jena AB, Olenski A, Blumenthal DM, Yeh RW, Goldman DP, Romley J. Acute Myocardial <lb/>Infarction Mortality During Dates of National Interventional Cardiology Meetings. J Am Heart <lb/>Assoc. 2018;7: e008230. <lb/>13. Carr BG, Jenkins P, Branas CC, Wiebe DJ, Kim P, Schwab CW, et al. Does the trauma system <lb/>protect against the weekend effect? J Trauma. 2010;69: 1042-1047. <lb/>14. Giannoudis V, Panteli M, Giannoudis PV. Management of polytrauma patients in the UK: Is <lb/>there a &apos;weekend effect&apos;? Injury. 2016;47: 2385-2390. <lb/>15. Metcalfe D, Perry DC, Bouamra O, Salim A, Lecky FE, Woodford M, et al. Is there a &apos;weekend <lb/>effect&apos; in major trauma? Emerg Med J. 2016;33: 836-842. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>16. Ono Y, Ishida T, Iwasaki Y, Kawakami Y, Inokuchi R, Tase C, et al. The off-hour effect on <lb/>trauma patients requiring subspecialty intervention at a community hospital in Japan: a retrospective <lb/>cohort study. Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med. 2015;23: 20. <lb/>17. Japan Trauma Care and Research. Japan Trauma Data Bank Annual Report 2017 (2012-2016) <lb/>[Internet]. Available from: https://www.jtcr-jatec.org/traumabank/dataroom/data/JTDB2017e.pdf. <lb/>18. Sewalt CA, Wiegers EJA, Venema E, Lecky FE, Schuit SCE, Den Hartog D, et al. The volume-<lb/>outcome relationship in severely injured patients: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Trauma <lb/>Acute Care Surg. 2018;85: 810-819. <lb/>19. Guly HR, Leighton G, Woodford M, Bouamra O, Lecky F; Trauma Audit and Research <lb/>Network. The effect of working hours on outcome from major trauma. Emerg Med J. 2006;23: 276-<lb/>280. <lb/>20. Laupland KB, Ball CG, Kirkpatrick AW. Hospital mortality among major trauma victims <lb/>admitted on weekends and evenings: a cohort study. J Trauma Manag Outcomes. 2009;3: 8. <lb/>21. Carr BG, Reilly PM, Schwab CW, Branas CC, Geiger J, Wiebe DJ. Weekend and night <lb/>outcomes in a statewide trauma system. Arch Surg. 2011;146: 810-817. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>22. Aldridge C, Bion J, Boyal A, Chen YF, Clancy M, Evans T, et al; HiSLAC Collaborative. <lb/>Weekend specialist intensity and admission mortality in acute hospital trusts in England: a cross-<lb/>sectional study. Lancet. 2016;388: 178-186. <lb/>23. Schwartz DA, Medina M, Cotton BA, Rahbar E, Wade CE, Cohen AM, et al. Are we delivering <lb/>two standards of care for pelvic trauma? Availability of angioembolization after hours and on <lb/>weekends increases time to therapeutic intervention. J Trauma Acute Care Surg. 2014;76: 134-139. <lb/>24. Mazahir S, Pardhan A, Rao S. Office hours vs after-hours. Do presentation times affect the rate <lb/>of missed injuries in trauma patients? Injury. 2015;46: 610-615. <lb/>25. Hjortdahl M, Ringen AH, Naess AC, Wisborg T. Leadership is the essential non-technical skill <lb/>in the trauma team--results of a qualitative study. Scand J Trauma Resusc Emerg Med. 2009;17: 48. <lb/>26. Ford K, Menchine M, Burner E, Arora S, Inaba K, Demetriades D, et al. Leadership and <lb/>Teamwork in Trauma and Resuscitation. West J Emerg Med. 2016;17: 549-556. <lb/>27. Hemmila MR, Cain-Nielsen AH, Jakubus JL, Mikhail JN, Dimick JB. Association of Hospital <lb/>Participation in a Regional Trauma Quality Improvement Collaborative with Patient Outcomes. <lb/>JAMA Surg. 2018;153: 747-756. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">344 Supporting information captions <lb/> 345 Not applicable. </div>

	</text>
</tei>
