<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>A more physiological approach to lipid metabolism alterations in cancer: CRC-like <lb/>organoids assessment <lb/>Silvia Cruz-Gil 1 , Dr. Ruth Sanchez-Martinez 1 , Sonia Wagner-Reguero 1 , Dr. Daniel Stange 2 , Dr. <lb/>Sebastian Schölch 3,4,5 , Dr. Kristin Werner 2 and Dr. Ana Ramirez de Molina 1, * . <lb/>1 Molecular Oncology Group/ IMDEA Food Institute, CEI UAM + CSIC, Ctra. De Cantoblanco, <lb/>8 E-28049 Madrid, Spain. <lb/>2 Department of Gastrointestinal, Thoracic and Vascular Surgery, University Hospital Carl Gustav <lb/>Carus, Technische Universität Dresden, Fetscherstraße 74, 01307 Dresden, Germany. <lb/>3 Medizinische Fakultät und Universitätsklinikum Mannheim, Ruprecht-Karls-Universität <lb/>Heidelberg, Theodor-Kutzer-Ufer 1-3, 68167 Mannheim <lb/>4 German Cancer Consortium (DKTK) <lb/>5 German Cancer Research Center (DKFZ), Heidelberg, Germany <lb/>* Correspondence to Dr. Ana Ramirez de Molina. (E-mail: ana.ramirez@imdea.org). <lb/>Running head <lb/>Handling organoids for an optimal lipid metabolism-related CRC analysis. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Precision medicine might be the response to the recent questioning of the use of metformin as an <lb/>anticancer drug in colorectal cancer (CRC). Thus, in order to establish properly its benefits, its <lb/>application need to be assayed on the different progression stages of CRC. In this way, organoids <lb/>imply a more physiological tool, representing a new therapeutic opportunity for CRC <lb/>personalized treatment to assay tumor stage-dependent drugs effects. Since the lipid metabolism-<lb/>related axis, ACSL/SCD, stimulates colon cancer progression and Metformin is able to rescuing <lb/>the invasive and migratory phenotype conferred to cancer cells upon this axis overexpression; we <lb/>checked ACSL/SCD status, its regulatory miRNAs and the effect of Metformin treatment in <lb/>organoids as a model for specific and personalized treatment. Despite ACSL4 expression is <lb/>upregulated in CRC-like organoids, Metformin is able to downregulate it, especially in the first <lb/>stages. Besides, organoids are clearly more sensitive in this first stage (Apc mutated) to <lb/>Metformin than current chemotherapeutic drugs such as fluorouracil (5-FU). Metformin performs <lb/>an independent &quot;Warburg effect&quot; blockade to cancer progression and is able to reduce crypt stem <lb/>cell markers expression such as Lgr5+. These results suggest a putative increased efficiency of <lb/>the use of Metformin in the first stages of CRC than in advanced disease. <lb/>Keywords: CRC-like organoids, colorectal cancer, ACSL/SCD axis, lipid metabolism, acyl-CoA <lb/>synthetases, Stearoyl-CoA desaturase, Metformin, LGR5+, non-Warburg metabolism, <lb/>personalized medicine. <lb/>Abbreviations: ACSL1: Acyl-CoA synthetase 1; ACSL4: Acyl-CoA synthetase 4; CRC: <lb/>Colorectal cancer; EMT: Epithelial-mesenchymal transition; 5-FU: Fluorouracil; MiRNAs/ miR: <lb/>MicroRNAs; MTT: 3-(4, 5-dimethylthiazol-2-yl)-2, 5-diphenyltetrazolium bromide; OAA: <lb/>Oxaloacetate; SCD: Stearoyl-CoA desaturase; TCA: Tricarboxylic Acid cycle; 2D: 2-<lb/>dimensional; 3D: 3-dimensional. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Colorectal cancer (CRC) is the third most common cancer in men (10% of the total), after lung <lb/>and prostate cancer, and the second in women (9.2% of the total), after breast cancer [1]. Most of <lb/>the CRC cases are sporadic (70-80%), which consists of the acquisition of somatic mutations and <lb/>in which there is no family history or genetic predisposition. The remaining cases (20-30%) are <lb/>those among close relatives, which are divided into inherited or familial CRC, [2]. Genetically, <lb/>sporadic CRC development is due to the abnormalities accumulation in tumor suppressor genes <lb/>and oncogenes [3,3]. Previous research postulated the adenoma-carcinoma transition theory, in <lb/>which specific somatic mutations promoting tumorigenesis are acquired; proposed by Fearon and <lb/>Vogelstein (Vogelgram). The Vogelgram proposes that the adenoma-carcinoma sequence model <lb/>would start with loss of the APC gene, followed by mutations in KRAS or BRAF genes, mutations <lb/>or loss of TP53 gene and of SMAD family member 4 (SMAD4) [4]. <lb/>Over the last decade, the interest in metabolic research with respect to cancer has been <lb/>expansively increased. The first and most characterized tumor metabolism event to be described <lb/>is the exacerbated glucose uptake and glycolysis utilization; which even in normoxic condition, <lb/>are not used for maximal ATP generation via mitochondrial respiration. This phenomenon is <lb/>denoted as the &quot;Warburg effect&quot;. <lb/>Even though lipid-associated pathways are functionally dependent on glucose and glutamine <lb/>catabolic pathways, are now a well-recognized and frequently described cancer metabolic feature <lb/>with a key role in their tumorigenesis. This is the case for the ACSL/SCD axis [5], a lipid <lb/>metabolism-related network described to promote tumorigenesis through an epithelial-<lb/>mesenchymal transition (EMT) program that promotes migration and invasion of colon cancer <lb/>cells. The mesenchymal phenotype produced upon overexpression of these enzymes is reverted <lb/>through reactivation of AMPK signaling performed by the well-known anti-diabetic drug, <lb/>Metformin. Though its mechanism of action is not fully understood, Metformin has shown a <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>robust anti-proliferative effect on several types of cancer such as colon, pancreatic, breast, <lb/>ovarian, prostate and lung cancer cells [6]. Furthermore, Metformin has been recently associated <lb/>with improved survival of cancer patients, including CRC, though its use as an antitumoral agent <lb/>has not been established yet [7] <lb/>The ACSL/SCD axis pro-tumorigenic activity has been also described to be post-transcriptionally <lb/>regulated by miRNAs. miR-544a, miR-142, and miR-19b-1 has been proposed as major <lb/>regulators of the ACSL/SCD network and the miR-19b-1-3p isoform decreased expression <lb/>associated with a poorer survival rate in CRC patients, consistently with ACSL/SCD involvement <lb/>in patients relapse [8]. <lb/>To get insight into the metabolic implication on CRC progression with a special focus on the <lb/>ACSL/SCD axis and the effect of metformin in each case, more personalized and physiological <lb/>tools are needed since most of the available data rely on traditional studies using cancer cell lines <lb/>cultures. In this way, the organoid culture system opens a new methodological door for ex vivo <lb/>studies. <lb/>Adult tissue-derived epithelial organoids, also called &quot;mini guts&quot; [9] are stereotypic tissue-like <lb/>structures derived from digestive healthy tissues or tumors which mimics in vitro the tissue <lb/>composition and morphology of their in vivo counterparts [10]. This methodology was first <lb/>established in long-term primary culture from mouse small intestinal crypts to generate epithelial <lb/>organoids with crypt-and villus-like epithelial domains representing both progenitor and <lb/>differentiated cells [11]. <lb/>The organoids technology takes advantage of the intestinal epithelium self-renewing capacity. <lb/>Organoids starts from LGR5+ gut epithelial stem cells forming symmetric cyst structures, which <lb/>finally will form budding structures resembling intestinal crypts. These budding structures are <lb/>formed by these LGR5+ stem cells flanked by differentiated daughter cells [9]. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Organoids are currently employed in colorectal cancer studies and chemotherapy assessment <lb/>[12,13]. Along with intestinal organoids, similar epithelial organoids culture conditions for other <lb/>mouse and human digestive epithelial tissues have been also adapted [14-17] including tumor-<lb/>derived organoids from cancer patients. Importantly, organoids grow as pure epithelial cultures <lb/>without any contamination of vessels, immune cells or non-transformed mesenchymal which <lb/>leads to an accurate sequencing or expression profiling [10]. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>CRC-like organoids: culture and maintenance <lb/>Mice: Mutant intestinal murine organoids were obtained from the Universitätsklinikum Carl <lb/>Gustav Carus, Dresden. All procedures involving animals were conducted strictly in accordance <lb/>with FELASA regulations and approved by the animal welfare committees of the Technische <lb/>Universität Dresden and the Landesdirektion Sachsen prior to initiation of the experiments. <lb/>Mice with conditional mutations in Apc, Kras, Tp53 and Smad4 were obtained from the NCI <lb/>Mouse Repository (Apc, Kras Tp53) or the Jackson Laboratory (Smad4) and interbred to obtain <lb/>compound mutant mice (Table 1). The CRC-like organoid model represents the adenoma-<lb/>carcinoma sequence with the most common acquired mutations in a sporadic CRC: APC fl/fl , <lb/>KRAS G12D/WT , P53 R172H/WT and Smad4 fl/fl (corresponding to stages I to IV) (Table 2). The parental <lb/>mouse lines were described in Table 2. <lb/>Table 1: Parental mouse lines and publication´s PMID of the mutations in the organoids <lb/>Mutation <lb/>Designation <lb/>PMID <lb/>APC <lb/>NCI: 01XAA <lb/>17002498 <lb/>KRAS G12D <lb/>JAX: 008179 <lb/>11323676 <lb/>P53 R172H <lb/>JAX: 008652 <lb/>15607980 <lb/>P53 floxed <lb/>NCI: 01XC2 <lb/>11694875 <lb/>Smad4 floxed <lb/>JAX: 017462 <lb/>11857783 <lb/>Table 2: CRC-like organoids with the acquired mutations related to the stage. <lb/>Organoid mutation <lb/>CRC-like stage <lb/>WT <lb/>-<lb/>APC fl/fl <lb/>I <lb/>APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT <lb/>II <lb/>APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 fl/R172H <lb/>III <lb/>APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 fl/R172H ,Smad4 fl/fl <lb/>IV <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Murine organoids mutagenesis is conditioned by the Cre/loxP system. Adenoviral infections <lb/>were performed as explained in [18] to provide active mutations. <lb/>Crypt isolation and organoid culture: Crypts were isolated from the murine small <lb/>intestine by incubation for 30 min at 4°C in PBS containing 2 mM EDTA as previously reported <lb/>[11,19]. Isolated crypts were seeded in Matrigel (Corning® Matrigel® Matrix). The basic culture <lb/>medium (Advanced Dulbecco&apos;s modified Eagle Medium DMEM/F12 complemented with <lb/>penicillin/streptomycin, 10 mmol/L HEPES, 1x Glutamax [Gibco], named ADF +++) was <lb/>supplemented with: 100 ng/ml Noggin (Peprotech), R-spondin (conditioned medium, 10% final <lb/>volume), 1x B27 (Invitrogen), 1x N2 (Invitrogen), 1,25 mM N-acetylcysteine (Sigma-Aldrich), <lb/>100 μg/mL Primocin TM (InvivoGen) and 50 ng/mL mEGF (Thermofisher). The complete media <lb/>is named supplemented ADF +++ media. For passaging, organoids were removed from Matrigel <lb/>and mechanically dissociated with a glass pipette, pelleted and then transferred to fresh Matrigel <lb/>[11,14,20]. Splitting was performed twice a week in a 1:3 split ratio. Cultures were kept at 37 °C, <lb/>5% CO2 in humidity. <lb/>Drugs treatment -viability assays <lb/>Cell viability was determined by counting and seeding 1000 crypts in 60% of Matrigel in 48-well <lb/>plates. After 2 days of culture, organoids were exposed 48 hours to 10 µM Metformin (Sigma) or <lb/>10, 100 or 150 µM 5-FU (Sigma) in supplemented ADF +++ media, as indicated in the figures. <lb/>At this point, organoids were collected, split and reseeded for recovery experiments over 72 hours <lb/>in supplemented ADF +++ media. <lb/>Upon treatments (48h) or recovery assays (post-72h), organoids were incubated 3 hours with 3-<lb/>(4,5-dimethyl-thyazol-2-yl)-2,5-diphenyl-tetrazolium (MTT, Sigma). After discarding the media, <lb/>20 μl of 2% SDS (Sigma) solution in H2O was added to solubilize Matrigel (2 h, 37 °C). The <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>resultant formazan was dissolved in 100 μl of DMSO for 1 h (37 °C). The absorbance was <lb/>measured on the microplate reader (Asys UVM 340, Isogen life science) at 562 nm. <lb/>Untreated organoids were defined as 100% viable. Data were expressed as the fold change of <lb/>viable cells from treated organoids compared to the non-treated organoids. <lb/>RNA isolation and RT-QPCR <lb/>For RNA isolation, organoids were released from Matrigel (Corning) with cold Dispase (Corning) <lb/>and pelleted by centrifugation. The supernatant was removed and pelleted organoids were <lb/>carefully resuspended in Trizol (Qiagen), and storage at -80ºC. RNA was isolated according to <lb/>the supplier&apos;s protocol (Invitrogen) and the concentration and purity (A260/A280 ratio) were <lb/>determined by spectrophotometric analysis (NanoDrop 2000 Spectrophotometer <lb/>ThermoScientific). 20 ng/μl RNA was reverse-transcribed using the High Capacity RNA-to-<lb/>cDNA kit (ThermoFisher), according to manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Relative gene expression <lb/>was measured using VeriQuest Fast SYBR Green qPCR Master Mix (2X) (Isogen). Primers used <lb/>are listed in S1 Table. Regarding miRNAs, their expression was monitored using TaqMan® <lb/>MicroRNA Reverse Transcription Kit (ThermoFisher Scientific) and Taq-man miRNA probes for <lb/>RT-qPCR (S2 Table). RT-QPCRs were performed on the QuantStudio 12K Flex (Applied <lb/>Biosystems) and the 2 -ΔΔCt method was applied to calculate the relative gene or miRNA <lb/>expression. <lb/>L-Lactate quantification <lb/>Organoids were seeded at a density of 1000 crypts per well in a 48-well plate. After 48 hours, the <lb/>medium was changed to PBS, 10 mM of Metformin or 10 µM 5-FU in supplemented ADF +++ <lb/>media overnight at 37°C before quantification. Using Cayman&apos;s Glycolysis cell-based assay <lb/>(Cayman, Ann Arbor, MI, USA, 600450) extracellular L-Lactate was measured by determining <lb/>absorbance at 490 nm. L-Lactate measurements (mM) were normalized to total protein <lb/>concentration (mg) x100. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Statistical analysis <lb/>All statistical analyses were performed using the Graph Pad Prism software (Ver. 7.03) (GraphPad <lb/>Software, San Diego, CA, USA). Significance between groups was determined by t-test analyses <lb/>(unpaired Student&apos;s t-tests). Data with P &lt; 0.05 were considered statistically significant (ns, P &gt; <lb/>0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). All reported p values were <lb/>two-sided. All values are reported as mean ± S.D. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>ACSL4 is overexpressed throughout CRC-like organoids <lb/>stages <lb/>ACSL4 has been previously reported to be overexpressed in malignant tumors, and together with <lb/>ACSL1 and SCD form an axis involved in CRC progression. ACSL1, ACSL4, and SCD mRNA <lb/>expression was measured in CRC-like organoids. ACSL4 mRNA was very significantly <lb/>augmented in more aggressive stages compared to WT (Fig 1A). It is shown an intermediate <lb/>expression pattern in Apc-mutated organoids, with a significantly differential expression (p-<lb/>value: **) compared to the following second stage (Apc, Kras mutated stage) henceforth. <lb/>Conversely, ACSL1 and SCD levels were maintained or increased from the third stage henceforth, <lb/>respectively (S1 Fig). <lb/>Figure 1: ACSL4 is overexpressed throughout CRC-like organoids stages while miR-19b-1-<lb/>3p preserves its protective role. <lb/>A) RT-QPCR analysis showing ACSL4 mRNA expression levels throughout CRC-like organoids <lb/>stages. B) RT-QPCR analysis showing miR-19b-1-3p mRNA expression levels throughout CRC-<lb/>like organoids stages. Results represent the fold-change mean ±SD (n = 4) in plots A, (n = 3) in <lb/>plots B. (ns, P &gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001) <lb/>Interestingly, organoids in more advanced stages (III and IV) presented a genetic misbalance in <lb/>ACSL4 expression (Fig 1A) with huge differences in their fold inductions ranges in the same <lb/>stage, though with a similar tendency. <lb/>MiR-19b-1-3p keeps its protective role in CRC-like organoids <lb/>MiRNAs expression was assayed in 3 different RNA extractions over time. Previous results from <lb/>our group pointed toward a correlation between miR-19b-1-3p lower expression and a poorer <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>prognosis in CRC patients (which might have a putative high clinical interest due to its potential <lb/>to be assed in plasma as a non-invasive biomarker); very likely through its involvement in cell <lb/>invasion and lipid metabolism regulation [8]. In the case of CRC-like organoids, this tendency <lb/>was maintained and miR-19b-1-3p expression was decreased in a stage-dependent manner (Fig <lb/>1B). <lb/>Together with miR-19b-1-3p, miR-142 (3p and 5p isoforms) and miR-544a (without murine <lb/>isoform) were also involved on targeting ACSL/SCD axis [8]. Hence, the previous mentioned <lb/>miRs plus miR-19b-1-5p isoform was measured though no statistically significant differences <lb/>were found in its expression (S2 Fig) <lb/>Metformin decreases CRC-like organoids viability to the same <lb/>extent as current chemotherapy without significant effects on <lb/>WT organoids <lb/>Since Metformin treatment, an AMPK activator used as antidiabetic treatment that has been <lb/>recently associated to increased survival of cancer patients, was able to rescue the epithelial <lb/>phenotype from the EMT process caused by the overexpression of ACSL/SCD in CRC cells [5]; <lb/>we wondered what this drug effect would be through the different stages in tumor progression. <lb/>CRC-like organoids were treated with PBS, 10 µM of Metformin or with the commonly used <lb/>chemotherapeutic agent 5-FU; and the organoids viability was examined by MTT assays 48 hours <lb/>upon treatment. None of the drugs affected significantly the viability of WT organoids (Fig 2A), <lb/>while they were able to cause a decrease of about 50% in the viability of mutated organoids <lb/>corresponding to the most aggressive phenotypes (Fig 2B-E). 5-FU higher concentrations (100 <lb/>µM and 150 µM) showed the same effects than the lower concentration (10 µM) in mutated <lb/>organoids, while they had stronger effects on WT ones (S3A-E Figs). <lb/>Figure 2: Metformin decreases CRC-like organoids viability to the same extent as current <lb/>chemotherapy without significant effects on WT organoids <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>MTT cell viability assays upon 48 hours treatments with Metformin or 5-FU in the different CRC-<lb/>like organoids representative stages (A) WT organoids; (B) APC fl/fl organoids resembling stage <lb/>I; (C) APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT organoids resembling stage II; (D) APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 R172H/WT <lb/>organoids resembling stage III; (E) APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 R172H/WT ,Smad4 fl/fl organoids <lb/>resembling stage IV. Data are represented by the fold-change mean ±SD (n = 3) in all the plots <lb/>except A: (n=2). (ns, P &gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>Metformin treatment recovery is significantly lower compared <lb/>to 5FU in first stages organoids while WT organoids present an <lb/>opposite behavior <lb/>To further check the treatments scope, and analyzing not only the effect but also the potential <lb/>reversibility of the treatment in normal and tumoral cells in different stages, organoids viability <lb/>was assayed upon 48 hours treatment (PBS, Metformin or 5-FU) plus the subsequent recovery of <lb/>72 additional hours in their growing media. In this case, WT organoids showed differential <lb/>recovery sensitivity to the treatment. Metformin treated and recovered WT organoids presented <lb/>almost similar measurements than only treated organoids. Nonetheless, 5FU treated WT <lb/>organoids recoveries are noteworthy more sensitive and upon 72h recovery time their viability <lb/>was quite significant reduced (p-value: ***) (Fig 3A). In Apc mutated organoids the recovery is <lb/>very significantly lower upon Metformin treatment (p-value: ****) than 5-FU (p-value: *), <lb/>compared to PBS recovery control; making these Apc mutated organoids the most responsive to <lb/>the Metformin treatment compared to 5-FU (Fig 3B). Regarding organoids corresponding to <lb/>stages II-III (Figs 3C and D), both treatments presented almost similar recovery effects, while in <lb/>stage IV organoids, 5-FU presented a stronger effect shown by the lower recovery of these 5-FU <lb/>treated organoids (Fig 3E). Again 5-FU higher concentrations (100 µM and 150 µM) had nearly <lb/>the same recovery effects than the lower concentration (10 µM) (S4A-E Figs). <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3: Metformin treatment recovery is significantly lower compared to 5FU in first <lb/>stages organoids while WT organoids present an opposite behavior <lb/>MTT cell viability assays upon 48 hours treatments (black bars) and upon extra 72h post-<lb/>treatment recovery with PBS (light grey bars) Metformin (yellow bars) or 5-FU (dark grey bars) <lb/>in the different CRC-like organoids representative stages (A) WT organoids; (B) APC fl/fl <lb/>organoids resembling stage I; (C) APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT organoids resembling stage II; (D) APC fl/fl <lb/>, KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 R172H/WT organoids resembling stage III; (E) APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 R172H/WT <lb/>,Smad4 fl/fl organoids resembling stage IV. Data are represented by the fold-change mean ±SD (n <lb/>= 3) in all the plots. (ns, P&gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>(F) Organoids pictures with PBS, Metformin or 5-FU, upon 48 hours treatments and upon extra <lb/>72h post-treatment recovery as indicated. Pictures were captured using the × 10 objective, in <lb/>bright field. Leica microscope (Leica microsystems). <lb/>Since WT organoids require more time to achieve their size and their crypt-like phenotype (Fig <lb/>3F), the recovery measures are lesser than the mutated organoids. On the other hand, WT <lb/>organoids recovered upon Metformin treatment presented a higher size than the ones treated with <lb/>5-FU (Fig 3F). On the contrary, stage I (Apc mutated) organoids recovered upon Met treatment <lb/>showed an evident reduced size compared with the control and the 5-FU treated ones. In <lb/>accordance with viability assays results, this effect is lost in further stages; where Metformin is <lb/>less effective and Metformin treated recovered organoids presented a bigger size than the ones <lb/>treated with 5-FU. <lb/>By way of clarification, all mutated organoids presented Apc mutated since is the first gene in the <lb/>adenocarcinoma sequence. Apc completed deletion provokes a hyperactive Wnt signaling. This <lb/>aberration makes an organoids phenotype switch, losing their crypt-like structure and adopting a <lb/>cystic morphology [17,21] <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Metformin action is stronger on ACSL4 and SCD <lb/>overexpressing first stages organoids <lb/>Since stage I organoids seemed to present a differential sensitivity to metformin compared to <lb/>other stages, together with a differential expression of ACSL4, we aimed to analyze the possible <lb/>link between Metformin and ACSL/SCD axis in intestinal organoids. <lb/>To this aim, ACSL4 expression was measured, as well as the other enzymes of the ACSL/SCD <lb/>metabolic network (ACSL1 and SCD) upon 10 µM Metformin treatment. ACSL4 mRNA <lb/>expression was strongly reduced by this drug compared to their non-treated controls in stage I and <lb/>II organoids. By contrast, stage III and IV presented no significance in their reduction or a slight <lb/>significance, respectively. WT organoids also presented a slight reduction of ACSL4 mRNA upon <lb/>Metformin treatment (Fig 4B). In addition, SCD expression levels were clearly decreased by <lb/>Metformin in WT and stage I organoids, while a less marked tendency was found for stage III <lb/>and IV organoids (Fig 4C). ACSL1 mRNA analysis showed less significant results (Fig 4A) upon <lb/>Metformin treatment. <lb/>Figure 4: Metformin action is stronger on ACSL4 and SCD overexpressing first stages <lb/>organoids and downregulates stem cell biomarker LGR5 and Wnt target genes expression <lb/>in all organoid stages. <lb/>mRNA expression levels of enzymes related to the ACSL/SCD axis, ACSL4 (A), SCD (B), by <lb/>RT-QPCR; and expression levels of different stem cell markers, Lgr5 (C), Axin-2 (D) and Ctnnb-<lb/>1 (E) by RT-QPCR upon PBS (black bars) and 10 uM Metformin (yellow bars). Data are <lb/>represented by the fold-change mean to each PBS control ±SD (n = 3). (ns, P&gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; <lb/>**, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>The expression of these enzymes was also measured upon 10 µM 5-FU treatment. This drug was <lb/>able to significantly downregulate ACSL4 and SCD mRNA in most of the stages, though no <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>differences were showed between the effects in initial and later stages such as the case for <lb/>Metformin treatment (S5A-C Figs). <lb/>Metformin, but not 5-FU, downregulates stem cell biomarker <lb/>LGR5 and Wnt target genes expression in all organoid stages <lb/>To further assay whether Metformin treatment was targeting the organoids crypts stem cell <lb/>marker, LGR5; we analyzed its expression together with two other Wnt target genes, Axin2 and <lb/>Ctnnb-1. Importantly, LGR5 expression was significantly diminished in the whole CRC-like <lb/>organoids series upon Metformin treatment (Fig 4C) as well as Axin-2 (Fig 4D) and Ctnnb-1 (Fig <lb/>4E) mRNAs. Surprisingly, this pattern was not maintained when organoids were treated with 10 <lb/>µM 5-FU (S5D-F Figs). <lb/>Metformin action in CRC-like organoids is not related to a <lb/>Warburg-effect impairement <lb/>The avidity to perform glycolysis even in the presence of oxygen, known as the Warburg effect, <lb/>is one of the hallmarks of tumors. For this reason, we measured the levels of L-lactate, the end <lb/>product of glycolysis. CRC-like organoids presented increased glycolysis compared to WT <lb/>organoids, reflecting an increasing Warburg effect throughout the stages, as expected. Even <lb/>though 5-FU treatment caused a slight decrease in the glycolytic performance of the mutant <lb/>organoids (Fig 5), Metformin treatment caused an opposite effect, increasing the glycolytic <lb/>capacity in all stages, especially in stage I, the most sensitive to the drug. Thus, it seems that <lb/>Metformin effect on CRC-like organoids viability relies in mechanisms other than preventing pro-<lb/>tumorigenic Warburg effect, likely through the regulation of lipid metabolism. <lb/>Figure 5: Metformin action in CRC organoids is not related to a Warburg-effect <lb/>impairement <lb/>Bars represent the extracellular L-lactate production upon overnight PBS treatment (black bars), <lb/>Metformin treatment (yellow bars) and 5-FU treatment (grey bars) using the Cayman&apos;s Glycolysis <lb/>cell-based assay. L-lactate production measurement is normalized by total protein content (x100). <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Data are represented by the fold-change mean ±SD (n = 3) in all the plots. (ns, P&gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ <lb/>0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Organoids seem to represent a good tool to study lipid metabolism [22] and previous studies <lb/>employing intestinal organoids have linked the critical role of fatty acid metabolism to the <lb/>intestinal epithelial integrity in vivo [23]. Therefore, we propose this system to get insight into <lb/>cancer progression mechanisms in regards to fatty acid metabolism and therefore, to assay <lb/>ACSL/SCD protumorigenic axis action in CRC. <lb/>We showed that ACSL4 augmented while miR-19b-1-3p diminished its expression, both <lb/>progressively, in murine CRC-like organoids. Metformin action compared to the <lb/>chemotherapeutic agent 5-FU, in terms of viability reduction, was similar; although no significant <lb/>reduction was found in WT organoids viability with any treatment. Stage I organoids were the <lb/>most susceptible to Metformin action compared to 5-FU; while further stages presented similar <lb/>or stronger sensitivity to 5-FU, including WT organoids. Besides, Metformin was able to reduce <lb/>the intestinal crypt stem cell marker LGR5 in all the stages, together with two other Wnt <lb/>downstream targets, Ctnnb-1 and Axin-2. Finally, we showed that even though the CRC-<lb/>organoids series present a growing Warburg effect through the stages consistent with increased <lb/>L-lactate levels; Metformin action on CRC organoids viability was not related to an ablation of <lb/>Warburg effect. <lb/>The individual role of ACSL isoform 1 [24,25] and 4 [24,26] as well as SCD [27-31] in CRC has <lb/>been extensively reported. Surprisingly, while ACSL4 mRNA levels are clearly increased through <lb/>the stages in this organoids model, this was not the case for ACSL1, and SCD was only <lb/>overexpressed in advanced stages. These results differ from previous ones using human CRC cells <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>which can be due to differential expression in murine tissues compared to human 2D cultures [5] <lb/>[8]. Nevertheless, the use of murine organoids allows their genetic engineering and to accurately <lb/>control the mutations for a better mechanistic characterization, rather than patient tumor-derived <lb/>biopsies with the high variability that each tumor represent. Thus, our CRC model mimics a <lb/>sporadic colorectal tumor with the common mutations acquired during the progression of this <lb/>cancer. Due to the organoids results, the overexpression of the three enzymes could be only <lb/>present in some punctual tumors. However, the overexpression of ACSL4 is preserved in murine <lb/>organoids with the acquired CRC most common mutations (Fig 1A), indicating a predominant <lb/>role of this ACSL/SCD component in these cancer progression aspects. The ACSL4 mRNA huge <lb/>range of expression considering the most mutated stages (Fig 1A) could be explained since stages <lb/>III and IV in real tumors present an uncontrolled genetic variability with the accumulation of <lb/>other undetermined mutations. Organoids would be mimicking these uncontrolled stages, <lb/>compared to the homogeneity presented in 2D cultures. Conversely, ACSL1 static role (S1A Fig) <lb/>could be due to a lesser implication in tumor development in this system which can be also <lb/>explained by the fact that the rodent protein is one residue longer (699 amino acids) than the <lb/>human protein (698 amino acids), making it necessary to study the extent of this dissimilarity. <lb/>For its part, SCD overexpression has been mainly reported in mesenchymal tissues, rather than <lb/>epithelial ones, which are the only scaffold for organoids [32,33] giving a reason for the <lb/>distinctive results found in these epithelial systems among the first stages (S1B Fig). <lb/>Regarding miRs expression, miR-19b-1-3p kept its tumor-suppressor role in murine CRC-like <lb/>organoids, also reported as a good prognosis miRNA, able to target the axis [8]. The immature <lb/>isoform of miR-19b-1-3p, miR-19b, and other members of the miR-17-92 cluster, where this <lb/>miRNA is involved, regulate the self-renewal ability of gastric cancer stem cells [34]. The miR-<lb/>17-92 cluster role is controversial and dependent on the cancer type [35,36]. However, it is <lb/>interesting the reported role of this miRNA in digestive cancer stem cells, and its role in CRC <lb/>stem cells may be a potential line of research henceforth. In line with our results, miR-19b was <lb/>also reported to downregulate suppressor of cytokine signaling 3 (SOC3), modulating chemokine <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>production in intestinal epithelial cells and thereby avoiding intestinal inflammation in Crohn&apos;s <lb/>disease, which may ultimately prevent the derived disease, CRC [37]. <lb/>Since Metformin was able to revert the ACSL/SCD EMT phenotype, we tried to gain insight on <lb/>this process using organoid cultures resembling the different stages of a CRC progression. <lb/>Metformin treatment seems to be more efficient than 5-FU only during first tumor stages, making <lb/>organoids recovery harder compared to the ones treated with 5-FU. We propose that Metformin <lb/>therapies could be an appealing alternative in those cases when the tumor is detected in very early <lb/>stages rather than 5-FU treatments. However, some studies of Metformin treatment in CRC <lb/>patients points to stage III to be the most likeable to present an effect [38]. Since CRC is very <lb/>improbable to detect on its very early stages, known as one of the most silent and deadly cancer; <lb/>we wonder whether these studies with a low number of candidates in stage I are enough <lb/>representative. <lb/>As well, Metformin therapies has been proposed alone or in combination with other drugs, in <lb/>CRC. For example, Metformin has been recently combined with aspirin to treat middle stages in <lb/>non-diabetic CRC patients.( II and III stages) [39]. Furthermore, it exists a Phase 2 Trial for the <lb/>study of Metformin and 5-Fluorouracil combination in metastatic CRC [40] ,concluded with a <lb/>longstanding cancer control. An older report also claimed the benefits of this combination, but <lb/>they also reported that Metformin alone has antineoplastic activity per se in colon cancer cells, <lb/>and enhanced the activity of 5-FU, oxaliplatin and irinotecan in cells previously treated [41]. <lb/>Previous reports hypothesized that the inhibition of mitochondrial complex I was the main <lb/>mechanism of action for Metformin. However, recent studies suggest that cancer progression is <lb/>compromised upon Metformin treatment, by decreasing the TCA cycle´s anaplerosis. Metformin <lb/>decreases the flow of glucose-and glutamine-derived metabolic intermediates into the TCA cycle, <lb/>decreasing the citrate output of the mitochondria and leading to a reduction of acetyl-CoA (Ac-<lb/>CoA) and oxaloacetate (OAA) in the cytoplasm and therefore a reduction in de novo FA synthesis <lb/>[42]. This way, Metformin could be targeting lipid metabolism through ACSL/SCD axis. ACSL4 <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>downregulation in the presence of Metformin is clearly evident and the results are larger <lb/>significant in first stages (I, II) (Fig 4A). Maybe, the reduced overexpression of ACSL4 in the <lb/>first stages (Fig 1A) increases the sensitivity to Metformin action (Fig 4A); while in more <lb/>advanced stages, the overexpression is so high that Metformin action could appear to be less <lb/>effective. This would not be the case for SCD, which showed no overexpression in the first stages <lb/>and enhanced overexpression in III and IV stages, though it is significantly reduced upon <lb/>Metformin exposure again in the first stages (Fig 4B). On the other hand, it has been reported that <lb/>variations in the types and amounts of fatty acids, are able to modify intracellular ACSLs <lb/>expression [43], thus, this conditions could be also affecting ACSL/SCD components expression <lb/>besides that the network connection between those enzymes could make them present coordinated <lb/>effects upon Metformin treatment, reducing its expression due to the lack of their substrate. <lb/>Metformin was also previously reported to downregulate ACSL expression, lowering fatty acid <lb/>synthesis and normalizing lipid profile in diabetic rats [44]; as well as limiting its products, 18-<lb/>carbon chain length fatty acids, in skeletal muscle insulin resistant rats [45], suggesting in this <lb/>case that metformin is increasing FAs mitochondrial channeling due to the reduction of CPT1 <lb/>inhibition by malonyl-CoA and therefore decreasing 18-carbon acyl-chain-derived bioactive <lb/>lipids in the cytoplasm [45], This action of Metformin could be additional to the aforementioned, <lb/>detoxifying ACSLs probable over activity. <lb/>Metformin seems also to target cancer stem cells of different cancer types [46]. However, we <lb/>have described for the first time the LGR5 downregulation in CRC-like organoids upon <lb/>Metformin treatment; consistent with previous reports using 2D CRC cultures [47]. LGR5 was <lb/>diminished in the whole CRC-like organoids series to minimum levels, an indicative that <lb/>Metformin action is affecting the stem cells of the crypt, responsible for the progression of the <lb/>organoids lineage. Curiously, Metformin treated organoids do not present apoptosis or even <lb/>necrosis, but they kept at a minimum size compared to other treatments, where the organoids layer <lb/>disappeared and the cells appeared apoptotic in the lumen (S6 Fig), showing that cell membrane <lb/>biogenesis is somehow blocked, mostly built by de novo lipogenesis routes. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>Finally, Metformin treated CRC organoids exhibit a greater compensatory increase in aerobic <lb/>glycolysis. Since ATP levels are diminished due to complex I inhibition, the metabolic sensor <lb/>AMPK is activated, inhibiting mTOR and proliferative events; and promoting glycolysis as an <lb/>alternative ATP source [48]. We found that even though the CRC-organoids serie presented an <lb/>increasing glycolysis with the stages, (Fig 5); Metformin was able to increase more this glycolytic <lb/>phenotype, especially in stage I organoids, coincident with the higher sensitivity to the drug in <lb/>this organoids. These results point towards Metformin targeting different metabolic routes other <lb/>that Warburg effect to perform its effect on CRC organoids viability. <lb/>Even though the Warburg effect is a priority for current drugs, each day the evidence grows that <lb/>other metabolic pathways should be targeted for cancer progression ablation. CRC is a leading <lb/>cause of death in the developed world, though yet simplistic preclinical models that mimic the <lb/>usual stages of CRC progression are lacking [13]. In this way, organoids further analysis need to <lb/>be included as the tool of choice for stage-dependent drugs screening. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>General conclusion <lb/>1. Organoids display a precise platform to assay tumor stage-dependent drugs being <lb/>suitable for personalized medicine, constituting an invaluable tool due to their relatively <lb/>low costs, animal saving suffering and their ease and legibility to genetically manipulate. <lb/>Metformin-related conclusions <lb/>2. Metformin treatment is further proved as an efficient drug in CRC: <lb/>-It is able to decrease CRC-like organoids viability at the same rate as current <lb/>chemotherapy (5-FU) but it does not affect to WT organoids. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>-Metformin treatment recovery is significantly inferior compared to 5-FU in first stages <lb/>organoids, but with a greater recovery in WT organoids; becoming an appealing <lb/>chemotherapy drug in first tumor phases. <lb/>-Metformin downregulates the stem cell biomarker LGR5 and Wnt target genes <lb/>expression in all CRC-like organoid stages, reaffirming its potential use in intestinal <lb/>cancers. <lb/>-Metformin action in CRC organoids is not related to a Warburg-effect impairment, <lb/>presuming that other metabolisms rather than Warburg should be targeted to complete <lb/>the cancer progression obstruction <lb/>ACSL/SCD-related conclusions <lb/>3. ACSL4 is progressively overexpressed throughout CRC-like organoids stages; while <lb/>miR-19b-1-3p preserves its protective role, reflecting the role of ACSL/SCD axis action <lb/>on CRC progression. Besides, Metformin action is stronger on ACSL4 and SCD-<lb/>overexpressing first stages organoids, agreeing with Metformin greater action on this <lb/>stage. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgment <lb/>We kindly thank Dr. Daniel Stange and Dr. Schölch for providing the CRC-like organoids and to <lb/>the whole Department of Gastrointestinal, Thoracic and Vascular Surgery at University Hospital <lb/>Carl Gustav Carus for its continuous support .The research stay on this lab was kindly financed <lb/>with the assistance of a Boehringer Ingelheim Fonds travel grant. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest statement <lb/>Authors declare no potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Source of funding <lb/>This work was supported by Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad del Gobierno de España <lb/>(MINECO, Plan Nacional I+D+i AGL2016-76736-C3), Gobierno regional de la Comunidad de <lb/>Madrid (P2013/ABI-2728, ALIBIRD-CM) and EU Structural Funds. <lb/></div>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Ferlay J, Soerjomataram I, Dikshit R, Eser S, Mathers C, Rebelo M, et al. Cancer <lb/>incidence and mortality worldwide: sources, methods and major patterns in <lb/>GLOBOCAN 2012. Int J Cancer. 2015;136: E359-386. doi:10.1002/ijc.29210 <lb/>2. Müller MF, Ibrahim AEK, Arends MJ. Molecular pathological classification of <lb/>colorectal cancer. Virchows Arch. 2016;469: 125-134. doi:10.1007/s00428-016-<lb/>1956-3 <lb/>3. Yamagishi, H., Kuroda, H., Imai, Y., &amp; Hiraishi, H. (2016). Molecular pathogenesis <lb/>of sporadic colorectal cancers. Chinese Journal of Cancer, 35, 4. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1186/s40880-015-0066-y <lb/>4. Fearon ER, Vogelstein B. A genetic model for colorectal tumorigenesis. Cell. <lb/>1990;61: 759-767. <lb/>5. Sánchez-Martínez R, Cruz-Gil S, Gómez de Cedrón M, Álvarez-Fernández M, <lb/>Vargas T, Molina S, et al. A link between lipid metabolism and epithelial-<lb/>mesenchymal transition provides a target for colon cancer therapy. Oncotarget. <lb/>2015;6: 38719-38736. doi:10.18632/oncotarget.5340 <lb/>6. Nasri H, Rafieian-Kopaei M. Metformin: Current knowledge. J Res Med Sci Off J <lb/>Isfahan Univ Med Sci. 2014;19: 658-664. <lb/>7. Baglia ML, Cui Y, Zheng T, Yang G, Li H, You M, et al. Diabetes Medication <lb/>Use in Association with Survival among Patients of Breast, Colorectal, Lung, or <lb/>Gastric Cancer. Cancer Res Treat Off J Korean Cancer Assoc. 2018; <lb/>doi:10.4143/crt.2017.591 <lb/>8. Cruz-Gil S, Sanchez-Martinez R, Gomez de Cedron M, Martin-Hernandez R, <lb/>Vargas T, Molina S, et al. Targeting the lipid metabolic axisACSL/SCDin <lb/>colorectal cancer progression by therapeutic miRNAs: miR-19b-1 role. J Lipid <lb/>Res. 2018;59: 14-24. doi:10.1194/jlr.M076752 <lb/>9. Sato T, Clevers H. SnapShot: Growing Organoids from Stem Cells. Cell. <lb/>2015;161: 1700-1700.e1. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2015.06.028 <lb/>10. Werner K, Weitz J, Stange DE. Organoids as Model Systems for Gastrointestinal <lb/>Diseases: Tissue Engineering Meets Genetic Engineering. Curr Pathobiol Rep. <lb/>2016;4: 1-9. doi:10.1007/s40139-016-0100-z <lb/>11. Sato T, Vries RG, Snippert HJ, van de Wetering M, Barker N, Stange DE, et al. <lb/>Single Lgr5 stem cells build crypt-villus structures in vitro without a mesenchymal <lb/>niche. Nature. 2009;459: 262-265. doi:10.1038/nature07935 <lb/>12. Golovko D, Kedrin D, Yilmaz ÖH, Roper J. Colorectal cancer models for novel <lb/>drug discovery. Expert Opin Drug Discov. 2015;10: 1217-1229. <lb/>doi:10.1517/17460441.2015.1079618 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13. O&apos;Rourke KP, Loizou E, Livshits G, Schatoff EM, Baslan T, Manchado E, et al. <lb/>Transplantation of engineered organoids enables rapid generation of metastatic <lb/>mouse models of colorectal cancer. Nat Biotechnol. 2017;35: 577-582. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nbt.3837 <lb/>14. Barker N, Huch M, Kujala P, van de Wetering M, Snippert HJ, van Es JH, et al. <lb/>Lgr5(+ve) stem cells drive self-renewal in the stomach and build long-lived gastric <lb/>units in vitro. Cell Stem Cell. 2010;6: 25-36. doi:10.1016/j.stem.2009.11.013 <lb/>15. Boj SF, Hwang C-I, Baker LA, Chio IIC, Engle DD, Corbo V, et al. Organoid <lb/>models of human and mouse ductal pancreatic cancer. Cell. 2015;160: 324-338. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cell.2014.12.021 <lb/>16. Huch M, Dorrell C, Boj SF, van Es JH, Li VSW, van de Wetering M, et al. In vitro <lb/>expansion of single Lgr5+ liver stem cells induced by Wnt-driven regeneration. <lb/>Nature. 2013;494: 247-250. doi:10.1038/nature11826 <lb/>17. Sato T, Stange DE, Ferrante M, Vries RGJ, Van Es JH, Van den Brink S, et al. <lb/>Long-term expansion of epithelial organoids from human colon, adenoma, <lb/>adenocarcinoma, and Barrett&apos;s epithelium. Gastroenterology. 2011;141: 1762-<lb/>1772. doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2011.07.050 <lb/>18. Seidlitz T, Merker SR, Rothe A, Zakrzewski F, von Neubeck C, Grützmann K, et <lb/>al. Human gastric cancer modelling using organoids. Gut. 2018; <lb/>doi:10.1136/gutjnl-2017-314549 <lb/>19. Barker N, Huch M, Kujala P, van de Wetering M, Snippert HJ, van Es JH, et al. <lb/>Lgr5(+ve) stem cells drive self-renewal in the stomach and build long-lived gastric <lb/>units in vitro. Cell Stem Cell. 2010;6: 25-36. doi:10.1016/j.stem.2009.11.013 <lb/>20. Farin HF, Van Es JH, Clevers H. Redundant sources of Wnt regulate intestinal <lb/>stem cells and promote formation of Paneth cells. Gastroenterology. 2012;143: <lb/>1518-1529.e7. doi:10.1053/j.gastro.2012.08.031 <lb/>21. Andersson-Rolf A, Mustata RC, Merenda A, Kim J, Perera S, Grego T, et al. One-<lb/>step generation of conditional and reversible gene knockouts. Nat Methods. <lb/>2017;14: 287-289. doi:10.1038/nmeth.4156 <lb/>22. Bijsmans ITGW, Milona A, Ijssennagger N, Willemsen ECL, Ramos Pittol JM, <lb/>Jonker JW, et al. Characterization of stem cell-derived liver and intestinal <lb/>organoids as a model system to study nuclear receptor biology. Biochim Biophys <lb/>Acta. 2017;1863: 687-700. doi:10.1016/j.bbadis.2016.12.004 <lb/>23. Ciorba MA. Scap and the intestinal epithelial stem cell niche: new insights from <lb/>lipid biology. J Lipid Res. 2015;56: 1381-1382. doi:10.1194/jlr.C061309 <lb/>24. Chen W-C, Wang C-Y, Hung Y-H, Weng T-Y, Yen M-C, Lai M-D. Systematic <lb/>Analysis of Gene Expression Alterations and Clinical Outcomes for Long-Chain <lb/>Acyl-Coenzyme A Synthetase Family in Cancer. PLoS ONE. 2016;11. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0155660 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>25. Heimerl S, Moehle C, Zahn A, Boettcher A, Stremmel W, Langmann T, et al. <lb/>Alterations in intestinal fatty acid metabolism in inflammatory bowel disease. <lb/>Biochim Biophys Acta. 2006;1762: 341-350. doi:10.1016/j.bbadis.2005.12.006 <lb/>26. Cao Y, Dave KB, Doan TP, Prescott SM. Fatty acid CoA ligase 4 is up-regulated <lb/>in colon adenocarcinoma. Cancer Res. 2001;61: 8429-8434. <lb/>27. Roongta UV, Pabalan JG, Wang X, Ryseck R-P, Fargnoli J, Henley BJ, et al. <lb/>Cancer cell dependence on unsaturated fatty acids implicates stearoyl-CoA <lb/>desaturase as a target for cancer therapy. Mol Cancer Res MCR. 2011;9: 1551-<lb/>1561. doi:10.1158/1541-7786.MCR-11-0126 <lb/>28. Igal RA. Stearoyl CoA desaturase-1: New insights into a central regulator of <lb/>cancer metabolism. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2016;1861: 1865-1880. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.bbalip.2016.09.009 <lb/>29. Chen L, Ren J, Yang L, Li Y, Fu J, Li Y, et al. Stearoyl-CoA desaturase-1 <lb/>mediated cell apoptosis in colorectal cancer by promoting ceramide synthesis. Sci <lb/>Rep. 2016;6: 19665. doi:10.1038/srep19665 <lb/>30. Ran H, Zhu Y, Deng R, Zhang Q, Liu X, Feng M, et al. Stearoyl-CoA desaturase-1 <lb/>promotes colorectal cancer metastasis in response to glucose by suppressing <lb/>PTEN. J Exp Clin Cancer Res CR. 2018;37: 54. doi:10.1186/s13046-018-0711-9 <lb/>31. Qiu Y, Cai G, Zhou B, Li D, Zhao A, Xie G, et al. A distinct metabolic signature <lb/>of human colorectal cancer with prognostic potential. Clin Cancer Res Off J Am <lb/>Assoc Cancer Res. 2014;20: 2136-2146. doi:10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-13-1939 <lb/>32. Lu Y, Zhou Z, Tao J, Dou B, Gao M, Liu Y. Overexpression of stearoyl-CoA <lb/>desaturase 1 in bone marrow mesenchymal stem cells enhance the expression of <lb/>induced endothelial cells. Lipids Health Dis. 2014;13: 53. doi:10.1186/1476-511X-<lb/>13-53 <lb/>33. Tao J, Shi J, Lu Y, Dou B, Zhou Z, Gao M, et al. Overexpression of stearoyl-CoA <lb/>desaturase 1 in bone-marrow mesenchymal stem cells increases osteogenesis. <lb/>Panminerva Med. 2013;55: 283-289. <lb/>34. Wu Q, Yang Z, Wang F, Hu S, Yang L, Shi Y, et al. MiR-19b/20a/92a regulates <lb/>the self-renewal and proliferation of gastric cancer stem cells. J Cell Sci. 2013;126: <lb/>4220-4229. doi:10.1242/jcs.127944 <lb/>35. Xiang J, Wu J. Feud or Friend? The Role of the miR-17-92 Cluster in <lb/>Tumorigenesis. Curr Genomics. 2010;11: 129-135. <lb/>doi:10.2174/138920210790886853 <lb/>36. Zhang K, Zhang L, Zhang M, Zhang Y, Fan D, Jiang J, et al. Prognostic value of <lb/>high-expression of miR-17-92 cluster in various tumors: evidence from a meta-<lb/>analysis. Sci Rep. 2017;7: 8375. doi:10.1038/s41598-017-08349-4 <lb/>37. Cheng X, Zhang X, Su J, Zhang Y, Zhou W, Zhou J, et al. miR-19b downregulates <lb/>intestinal SOCS3 to reduce intestinal inflammation in Crohn&apos;s disease. Sci Rep. <lb/>2015;5. doi:10.1038/srep10397 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>38. Lee JH, Kim TI, Jeon SM, Hong SP, Cheon JH, Kim WH. The effects of <lb/>metformin on the survival of colorectal cancer patients with diabetes mellitus. Int J <lb/>Cancer. 2012;131: 752-759. doi:10.1002/ijc.26421 <lb/>39. De Monte A, Brunetti D, Cattin L, Lavanda F, Naibo E, Malagoli M, et al. <lb/>Metformin and aspirin treatment could lead to an improved survival rate for Type <lb/>2 diabetic patients with stage II and III colorectal adenocarcinoma relative to non-<lb/>diabetic patients. Mol Clin Oncol. 2018;8: 504-512. doi:10.3892/mco.2018.1554 <lb/>40. Miranda VC, Braghiroli MI, Faria LD, Bariani G, Alex A, Bezerra Neto JE, et al. <lb/>Phase 2 Trial of Metformin Combined With 5-Fluorouracil in Patients With <lb/>Refractory Metastatic Colorectal Cancer. Clin Colorectal Cancer. 2016;15: 321-<lb/>328.e1. doi:10.1016/j.clcc.2016.04.011 <lb/>41. Effect of metformin alone and in combination with 5-fluorouracil (5FU), <lb/>oxaliplatin (O) and irinotecan (I) on human colon cancer cell lines.: Journal of <lb/>Clinical Oncology: Vol 29, No 15_suppl [Internet]. [cited 26 Jul 2018]. Available: <lb/>http://ascopubs.org/doi/abs/10.1200/jco.2011.29.15_suppl.e13041 <lb/>42. Griss T, Vincent EE, Egnatchik R, Chen J, Ma EH, Faubert B, et al. Metformin <lb/>Antagonizes Cancer Cell Proliferation by Suppressing Mitochondrial-Dependent <lb/>Biosynthesis. PLoS Biol. 2015;13: e1002309. doi:10.1371/journal.pbio.1002309 <lb/>43. Yan S, Yang X-F, Liu H-L, Fu N, Ouyang Y, Qing K. Long-chain acyl-CoA <lb/>synthetase in fatty acid metabolism involved in liver and other diseases: an update. <lb/>World J Gastroenterol. 2015;21: 3492-3498. doi:10.3748/wjg.v21.i12.3492 <lb/>44. Ghadge A, Harsulkar A, Karandikar M, Pandit V, Kuvalekar A. Comparative anti-<lb/>inflammatory and lipid-normalizing effects of metformin and omega-3 fatty acids <lb/>through modulation of transcription factors in diabetic rats. Genes Nutr. 2016;11. <lb/>doi:10.1186/s12263-016-0518-4 <lb/>45. Zabielski P, Chacinska M, Charkiewicz K, Baranowski M, Gorski J, Blachnio-<lb/>Zabielska AU. Effect of metformin on bioactive lipid metabolism in insulin-<lb/>resistant muscle. J Endocrinol. 2017;233: 329-340. doi:10.1530/JOE-16-0381 <lb/>46. Metformin and Cancer Stem Cells: Old Drug, New Targets | Cancer Prevention <lb/>Research [Internet]. [cited 30 Jul 2018]. Available: <lb/>http://cancerpreventionresearch.aacrjournals.org/content/5/3/351 <lb/>47. Mogavero A, Maiorana MV, Zanutto S, Varinelli L, Bozzi F, Belfiore A, et al. <lb/>Metformin transiently inhibits colorectal cancer cell proliferation as a result of <lb/>either AMPK activation or increased ROS production. Sci Rep. 2017;7: 15992. <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41598-017-16149-z <lb/>48. Andrzejewski S, Gravel S-P, Pollak M, St-Pierre J. Metformin directly acts on <lb/>mitochondria to alter cellular bioenergetics. Cancer Metab. 2014;2: 12. <lb/>doi:10.1186/2049-3002-2-12 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Table. Primers´ sequences (Invivogen) used for quantitative real-time PCR. <lb/>S2 Table. Probes from TaqMan® MicroRNA Assays (ThermoFisher) used for <lb/>quantitative real-time PCR. <lb/>S1 Fig. ACSL1 and SCD mRNA expression throughout CRC-like organoids stages <lb/>RT-QPCR analysis showing ACSL1 (A) and SCD (B) mRNA expression levels <lb/>throughout CRC-like organoids stages. Results represent the fold-change mean ±SD (n <lb/>= 3) (ns, P &gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001) <lb/>S2 Fig. ACSL/SCD regulatory miRNAs expression in CRC-like organoids <lb/>RT-QPCR analysis showing mRNA expression levels throughout CRC-like organoids <lb/>stages of different ACSL/SCD regulatory miRNAS: miR-19b-1-5p (A), miR-142-3p (B), <lb/>miR-142-5p (C). Results represent the fold-change mean ±SD (n = 3). (ns, P&gt; 0.05; *, P <lb/>≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>S3 Fig. Metformin and 5-FU effect in CRC-like organoids. <lb/>MTT cell viability assays upon 48 hours treatments with PBS (black bars), 10 uM <lb/>Metformin (yellow bars) or 10, 100 and 150 uM 5-FU (grey bars) in the different CRC-<lb/>like organoids representative stages: WT organoids (A); APC fl/fl organoids resembling <lb/>stage I (B); APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT organoids resembling stage II (C); APC fl/fl , <lb/>KRAS G12D/WT , P53 R172H/WT organoids resembling stage III (D); APC fl/fl , <lb/>KRAS G12D/WT ,P53 R172H/WT ,Smad4 fl/fl organoids resembling stage IV (E). Data <lb/></div>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">are represented by the fold-change mean ±SD (n = 3) in all the plots. (ns, P &gt; 0.05; *, P <lb/>≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>S4 Fig. Metformin and 5-FU recovery effect in CRC-like organoids. <lb/>MTT cell viability assays upon 48 hours treatments (black bars) and upon extra 72h post-<lb/>treatment recovery with PBS (light grey bars), 10 uM Metformin (yellow bars) or 10, 100 <lb/>and 150 uM 5-FU (dark grey bars) in the different CRC-like organoids representative <lb/>stages:: WT organoids (A); APC fl/fl organoids resembling stage I (B); APC fl/fl , <lb/>KRAS G12D/WT organoids resembling stage II (C); APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT <lb/>,P53 fl/R172H organoids resembling stage III (D); APC fl/fl , KRAS G12D/WT <lb/>,P53 fl/R172H ,Smad4 fl/fl organoids resembling stage IV (E). Data are represented by the <lb/>fold-change mean ±SD (n =3) in all the plots. (ns, P &gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/>S5 Fig. ACSL/SCD axis and stem cell markers expression (Lgr5, Axin-2 and Ctnnb-<lb/>1) upon Metformin and 5-FU treatment <lb/>Expression leveles of enzymes related to the ACSL/SCD axis, ACSL1 (A), ACSL4 (B) <lb/>and SCD (C) by RT-QPCR; and expression levels of different stem cell markers, Lgr5 <lb/>(D), Axin-2 (E) and Ctnnb-1 (F) by RT-QPCR; upon PBS (black bars), 10 uM Metformin <lb/>(yellow bars) or 10, 100 and 150 uM 5-FU (grey bars). Data are represented by the fold-<lb/>change mean ±SD (n = 3). (ns, P&gt; 0.05; *, P ≤ 0.05; **, P ≤ 0.01; ***, P ≤ 0.001; ****, <lb/>P ≤ 0.0001). <lb/></div>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S6 Fig. Comparative organoids morphology between Metformin and other <lb/>oncologic treatments. <lb/>Organoids (stage I and III) representative pictures with DMSO, Metformin and other <lb/>metabolic drugs against CRC progression, upon 48 hours treatments plus upon extra 72h <lb/>post-treatment recovery. Pictures were captured using the × 10 objective, in bright field. <lb/>Leica microscope (Leica microsystems). </div>


	</text>
</tei>
