<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>The importance of assigning responsibility during evaluation in order to <lb/>increase student satisfaction from physical education classes: A model <lb/>of structural equations <lb/>The importance of assigning responsibility during evaluation in order to <lb/>increase student satisfaction. <lb/>Marta Leyton 1#a* , Susana Lobato 2 , Marco Batista 3 , Ruth Jiménez 4 . <lb/>1 Sports Studies Center. Rey Juan Carlos University. Madrid. Spain. <lb/>2 Faculty of Sports Science. The University of Extremadura. Cáceres. <lb/>Extremadura. Spain. <lb/>3 Sport, Health and Exercise Research Unit (SHERU) -Polytechnic Institute of <lb/>Castelo Branco. Castelo Branco. Portugal. <lb/>4 Didactic and Behavioural Analysis in Sport Research Group. Faculty of <lb/>Sports Science. University of Extremadura. Cáceres. Extremadura. Spain. <lb/>#a Current Address: Sports Study Centre. Rey Juan Carlos University. Madrid. <lb/>Spain. <lb/>*Corresponding author <lb/>Email: marta.leyton@urjc.es (ML) <lb/>Author Contributions <lb/>Conceived and designed the experiments: ML SL RJ. Performed the <lb/>experiments: ML SL MB RJ. Analysed the data: SL RJ. Contributed analysis <lb/>tools: ML SL MB RJ. Wrote the paper: ML. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Considering the benefits that students report when evaluating <lb/>physical education classes, the purpose of the present study was to analyse <lb/>the relationships between the assignment of student responsibility in the <lb/>evaluation, motivational variables and the satisfaction with the physical <lb/>education classes, using The Theory of Self-determination as a support <lb/>method. The sample for this study was 922 students, of both genres and in <lb/>Compulsory Secondary Education, aged between 14 and 18 years. To carry <lb/>out the study, the Student&apos;s Scale of Responsibility was used in the physical <lb/>education assessment, the Basic Psychological Needs Measuring Scale, the <lb/>Percentage Scale for Physical Education Causality and the Satisfaction Scale <lb/>in Physical Education. The results of the structural equations model revealed <lb/>a good adjustment to the data. This finding highlights the importance of giving <lb/>responsibilities to the students in the evaluation process, in order to satisfy the <lb/>psychological needs of the students and, therefore, self-determined <lb/>motivation, thus increasing satisfaction towards physical education classes. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Physical education (PE) has become a framework for many youngsters <lb/>to carry out physical activities, which then increases their motivation and <lb/>adherence to do exercise after school [1, 2, 3]. <lb/>The teacher is one of the main promotors of the practising of physical <lb/>activities [4], for which their figure is crucial for the students to increase, or <lb/>not, their level of regular physical activity [5]. However, in PE there are still <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>authors [6, 7] who indicate that, traditionally, teaching has consisted in a <lb/>pedagogical model of direct instruction. <lb/>Research has determined that the teacher&apos;s use of strategies, with <lb/>positive psychological aspects, such as the increase of students&apos; intrinsic <lb/>motivation in PE classes, will allow for the development and consolidation of <lb/>behaviours related to physical activity [8, 9, 10]. <lb/>Motivational phenomena combining a set of biological, emotional, <lb/>cognitive and social aspects, which at the same time are interrelated with <lb/>each other, influence persistence, intensity and frequency of behaviour, and <lb/>interact with each other by increasing, maintaining or decreasing this <lb/>behaviour [11]. <lb/>One of the theories that helps to explain the motivation of students in <lb/>PE classes is called the Self-determination Theory (SDT) [12, 13]. The SDT, <lb/>proposes that motivation is framed throughout a three-level continuum [14, <lb/>15]: autonomous motivation (the most self-determined, required for an activity <lb/>to be carried out for sheer pleasure), controlled motivation (carrying out an <lb/>activity for reward or recognition outside of the activity) and demotivation (the <lb/>least self-determined) [16]. <lb/>Furthermore, it establishes three Basic Psychological Needs (BPN): <lb/>autonomy (the desire to engage in activities by one&apos;s own choice), <lb/>competence (the desire to interact efficiently with the means to feel <lb/>competent) and relatedness (the desire to feel part of a group) [16, 12]. <lb/>According to the SDT, the BPN constitute the psychological mediators <lb/>that influence the three main types of motivation [12, 17]. Several studies <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>have used the BPN as mediators that positively predict the more self-<lb/>determined forms of motivation [18, 19, 20]. <lb/>The Hierarchical Model of Motivation (HMM) [21] associates BPN with <lb/>the SDT [22]. According to the HMM, the pedagogical model used by the <lb/>teacher will influence the satisfaction of the BPN and, consequentially, the <lb/>level of autonomous motivation of the student. The level of self-determined <lb/>motivation achieved can help to positively or negatively predict the cognitive, <lb/>affective and behavioural results. As a result, the students who experience <lb/>positive results in PE, such as enjoyment and the intention to be physically <lb/>active, present a more self-determined, and therefore more autonomous <lb/>motivation [23, 24] than the students that experience negative results like <lb/>boredom. It is most likely that the latter demonstrate controlled motivation or <lb/>demotivation and that they will run a greater risk of giving up physical activity <lb/>and sport [25]. The model establishes that the social aspects of the <lb/>environment (background variables) influence motivation, depending on the <lb/>achievement or not of a series of BPN (autonomy, competence and <lb/>relatedness), where satisfaction increases the degree of intrinsic motivation <lb/>(motivational variables) [12, 16] and will lead to positive consequences on a <lb/>cognitive, affective and behavioural level (consequent variables). <lb/>In PE classes, a linear and mechanistic pedagogical model has been <lb/>predominant, oriented towards the psychometric results of students at the <lb/>expense of social and cognitive results [26]. However, a climate in which <lb/>responsibility is given to the student will generate positive thoughts about <lb/>physical activity [27]. Different studies have revealed that when the teacher <lb/>provides students with autonomy and responsibility, they value more highly <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>the PE classes and their enjoyment also increases [28, 29, 30]. In a recent <lb/>study [31], with 532 students, guided by the TAD hypothesis, it was concluded <lb/>that the student profiles of PE classes were mainly autonomous ones. <lb/>Evaluation can be considered as an instrument for monitoring and <lb/>evaluating the results obtained by a student. The teacher can employ a more <lb/>controlling teaching style, where more importance is given to results than to <lb/>the learning process, or a teaching style that favours the autonomy of the <lb/>student, where the student is a participant in their own learning process, using <lb/>techniques such as self-evaluation, co-evaluation or hetero-evaluation [32]. <lb/>Given the importance of the process in the achievement of results by the <lb/>students, in this study, as a prior variable to the motivational variables, the <lb/>perception of the assigning of student responsibility was used in the <lb/>evaluation. <lb/>According to Hortigüela-Alcalá et al. [32], students take pleasure from <lb/>being offered different strategies and alternatives to achieve their goals; This, <lb/>in turn, increases intrinsic motivation towards classes and thereby the <lb/>likelihood of students exercising outside of the classroom [33, 34]. Studies like <lb/>that of Yonemura et al. [35], indicated that student participation in evaluation <lb/>produced an increase in their commitment to learning. In the same way, it <lb/>revealed the importance of proposing different strategies for evaluation in <lb/>which student participation is included [36, 37]. Likewise, other authors [38, <lb/>39, 40, 41] highlight the importance of PE and sport being directed towards <lb/>student autonomy and the designation of student responsibilities, claiming <lb/>that a teaching style that gives subjects the chance to choose, participate and <lb/>make decisions in classes, will give rise to a more enjoyable participation and <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>an increase in intrinsic motivation [18, 42, 43]. Therefore, students need to be <lb/>given the opportunity to participate, by being given responsibilities. [44, 45, <lb/>46]. <lb/>Following the HMM, the consequent variable of the present study was <lb/>satisfaction with PE classes. According to Herrera-Mor et al. [47], the <lb/>enjoyment that is experienced from an activity, understood as satisfaction in <lb/>relation to pleasure and well-being, allows for participation to remain <lb/>throughout time, for a greater adherence and for participation to become an <lb/>integral part of lifestyle. <lb/>Similarly, enjoyment can be understood as the valued sense of the <lb/>activities carried out in PE classes by the students [48]; and this variable <lb/>(satisfaction with PE classes) is even related to the obtaining of a better <lb/>academic qualification [49, 50]. As some studies have indicated, to avoid the <lb/>abandonment of physical activity, teachers must try to make activities fun and <lb/>avoid those which are not entertaining [51], thus presenting the teacher with <lb/>an essential role to play in the development of these activities [52]. <lb/>In this regard, Ntoumanis [53] explained that when subjects have fun <lb/>they tend to be intrinsically motivated and give more importance to the <lb/>subject. Satisfaction with PE classes will be positively related to the <lb/>satisfaction of BPN as well as to a more self-determined motivation [48, 52]. <lb/>Moreno et al. [54], in a sample of 819 students aged between 14 and <lb/>17 years, discovered that the most self-determined form of motivation <lb/>positively predicted the importance given to PE classes and with this, <lb/>satisfaction with the same. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>In relation to satisfaction, motivation and boredom with PE classes, as <lb/>several studies have shown [10, 55, 56, 57, 58, 59], high levels of self-<lb/>determination are associated with greater effort, enjoyment, the importance of <lb/>PE and the development of positive behaviour. In contrast, if motivation is less <lb/>self-determined, the consequences will be negative, such as boredom in <lb/>classes [9, 60]. <lb/>Thus, the objective for this study was to analyse the relationships <lb/>between the designation of student responsibility in evaluation, motivational <lb/>variations and student satisfaction with PE classes, through obtaining a model <lb/>of structural equations. Specifically, the hypothesis of the study was that the <lb/>perception of the assignment of student responsibility during evaluation would <lb/>positively predict the satisfaction of the BPN, positively predicting autonomous <lb/>motivation, which would positively predict the satisfaction with PE classes. <lb/>Material and methods <lb/>Research design <lb/>The study carried out was correlational of a transversal style, in which <lb/>the variables described above have not been altered or manipulated, only <lb/>what occurs with them under natural conditions having been observed [61]. <lb/>Likewise, it is located within quantitative empirical studies and, within <lb/>these, it refers to the descriptive study of populations through surveys [62]. <lb/>Sample <lb/>The study sample was 922 students of both sexes (430 male and 492 <lb/>female) from compulsory secondary education, more specifically from 3rd and <lb/>4th year of secondary school. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>The type of sampling that was carried out was intentional by <lb/>conglomerates. Each conglomerate was constituted by a classroom of about <lb/>18-19 students, obtaining 50 conglomerates. The ages of the sample were <lb/>between 14 and 18 years (M = 14.95, SD = .98). <lb/>In Table 1, the distribution of the sample in terms of gender and year-<lb/>group can be seen. <lb/>Table 1. Distribution of the sample according to gender and year group. <lb/>Year-Group <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Total <lb/>3º <lb/>247 <lb/>265 <lb/>512 <lb/>4º <lb/>183 <lb/>227 <lb/>410 <lb/>Total <lb/>430 <lb/>492 <lb/>922 <lb/>In Table 2, the distribution of the sample in terms of organisations that <lb/>participated in the study and year-group is represented. <lb/>Table 2. Distribution of the sample according to the school and the year-<lb/>group. <lb/>3º <lb/>4º <lb/>School <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Total <lb/>School 1 <lb/>22 <lb/>20 <lb/>16 <lb/>10 <lb/>68 <lb/>School 2 <lb/>19 <lb/>27 <lb/>11 <lb/>3 <lb/>60 <lb/>School 3 <lb/>22 <lb/>36 <lb/>24 <lb/>32 <lb/>114 <lb/>School 4 <lb/>54 <lb/>56 <lb/>47 <lb/>48 <lb/>205 <lb/>School 5 <lb/>29 <lb/>19 <lb/>22 <lb/>32 <lb/>102 <lb/>School 6 <lb/>42 <lb/>43 <lb/>18 <lb/>60 <lb/>163 <lb/>School 7 <lb/>18 <lb/>21 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>39 <lb/>School 8 <lb/>41 <lb/>43 <lb/>38 <lb/>35 <lb/>157 <lb/>School 9 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>7 <lb/>7 <lb/>14 <lb/>Total <lb/>247 <lb/>265 <lb/>183 <lb/>227 <lb/>922 <lb/>Total <lb/>Year-<lb/>Group <lb/>512 <lb/>410 <lb/>922 <lb/>Variables and measurement tools <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>In this section, the variables present in this investigation are revealed, <lb/>divided according to the HMM: antecedent, motivational and consequent. In <lb/>addition, a description is given of the instruments used to measure each of <lb/>them. <lb/>Antecedent variables and measurement tools <lb/>Level of responsibility of the student during evaluation: In order to know <lb/>the perception of the level of responsibility that is given to the student in the <lb/>evaluation, The Scale of Student Responsibility during Evaluation in Physical <lb/>Education (ERAEEF) was used, adapted to Spanish by Moreno et al. [63]. It is <lb/>made up of 11 items divided into 2 factors. In the present study, the factor <lb/>known as the value of the transfer of responsibility in the result of the <lb/>evaluation was used composed of 5 items (E.g. Working with the PE teacher <lb/>to decide my score is important). Thus, in the Confirmatory Factor Analysis <lb/>(CFA), the results showed acceptable adjustment indices [64]: χ2 = 55.00, gl <lb/>= 19, p = .00, χ2 / df = 2.89, CFI = .99, TLI = .98, RMSEA = .05 (IC 90% = .03, <lb/>.06). <lb/>Motivational variables and measurement tools <lb/>Basic Psychological Needs: To measure the satisfaction of the BPN, <lb/>the Basic Psychological Needs Measurement Scale (BPNMS) was used, the <lb/>original scale of Vlachopoulos &amp; Michailidou [65] and validated to Spanish by <lb/>Moreno et al. [66]. It is composed of 12 items divided into 3 factors. Each <lb/>factor is made up of 4 items: Satisfaction of the BPN of Competence (E.g. The <lb/>exercises that I perform are in line with my interests), Satisfaction of the BPN <lb/>of Competence (E.g. I do the exercises effectively), Satisfaction of the BPN of <lb/>Relatedness (E.g. I feel that I can communicate openly with my colleagues). <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Regarding the CFA, the results showed acceptable adjustment indices [64]: <lb/>χ2 = 57.79, df = 24, p = .00, χ2 / df = 2.41, CFI = .99, TLI = .99, RMSEA = .04 <lb/>(IC 90% = .03, .05). <lb/>Levels of Self-Determined Motivation: To measure the levels of self-<lb/>determined motivation, the Perceived Locus of Causality in Physical <lb/>Education (PLOC) was used. Original scale by Goudas et al. [67], and <lb/>validated in Spanish by Moreno et al. [13]. It consists of 20 items divided into <lb/>5 factors. In the present study, a single factor has been used, autonomous <lb/>motivation, composed of the grouping of intrinsic motivation (E.g. Because I <lb/>enjoy learning new skills) and identified regulation (E.g. Because it is <lb/>important for me to do well in PE). Regarding the CFA, the results showed <lb/>acceptable adjustment indices [64]: χ2 = 296.79, gl = 62, p = .00, χ2 / gl = <lb/>4.35, CFI = .96, TLI = .97, RMSEA = .06 (90% CI = .05, .07). <lb/>Consequent variables and measurement tools <lb/>Satisfaction Level and Boredom in PE classes: To measure the level of <lb/>satisfaction or boredom that students present in PE classes, the Basic Needs <lb/>in Sport Satisfaction Scale (BNSSS) was used. A scale validated for sports by <lb/>Duda &amp; Nicholls [68] and validated to Spanish by Balaguer et al. [69]. It is <lb/>composed of 8 items divided into two factors, of which only satisfaction with <lb/>PE classes was used, with 5 items (E.g. Normally I find PE interesting). Thus, <lb/>in the Confirmatory Factor Analysis (CFA), the results showed acceptable <lb/>adjustment indices [64]: χ2 = 5.29, df = 2, p = .00, χ2 / df = 2.65, CFI = .99, <lb/>TLI = .99, RMSEA = .06 (IC 90% = .04, .09). <lb/>In all of the questionnaires that were used, answers were given to all of <lb/>the items through a Likert Scale of 5 points, with a range from 0, which means <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>the student is in complete disagreement, to 5, meaning that the student <lb/>completely agrees. <lb/>Procedure <lb/>Having defined the objectives of the study, the measurement <lb/>instruments were selected in order to collect information, a dossier was <lb/>prepared, and some interesting data was gathered, such as age, school year, <lb/>the practice of extracurricular physical activity and the school to which the <lb/>students belonged. Subsequently, the different schools were contacted and <lb/>the objective of the study was explained. They were given a consent form for <lb/>the parents to sign, as the students were under 18 years of age. <lb/>Following this, specific days were chosen for visiting the schools and <lb/>handing out the questionnaires to those subjects with parent authorisation, <lb/>never in the presence of the PE teacher. <lb/>The time employed for the completion of the questionnaires was 40 <lb/>minutes per class. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>The Confirmatory Factorial Analysis (CFA) was performed in order to <lb/>verify the internal consistency of the questionnaires, and later, once the <lb/>different variables were created, the descriptive statistics. The corresponding <lb/>variables were created with the factors that showed adequate reliability <lb/>indexes. Normality tests were performed, in order to determine what type of <lb/>statistics should be used. The measurements of asymmetry, kurtosis, <lb/>Kolmogorov-Smirnov, with the correction of Lilliefors, verified that the <lb/>distribution of the sample was normal, for which parametric statistics were <lb/>applied. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Then, Structural Equation Modelling (SEM) was employed, as it is <lb/>considered to be the most effective tool for the study of causal relationships in <lb/>non-experimental data [70]. <lb/>The values p &lt; .05 and p &lt; .01 were used for statistical significance. <lb/>Validity was also examined through confirmatory factor analysis, respecting <lb/>the criterion of eliminating those items with a regression weight that did not <lb/>present an adequate value (greater than .40) [72]. <lb/>Regarding the CFA and SEM, they were carried out with Mplus [73], <lb/>version 7.11. These analyses reveal some coefficients or fit indexes that allow <lb/>us to check the validity of the variables of the instruments. These indexes of <lb/>goodness of fit are the chi-square (χ2), the degrees of freedom (gl), the <lb/>significance (p), the χ2 / gl, the RMSEA (Root Mean Square Error of <lb/>Approximation), the index CFI (Comparative Fit Index) and the Tucker-Lewis <lb/>Index (TLI). The χ2 / gl is considered acceptable when it is lower than 5, the <lb/>RMSEA with values lower than .05, and the CFI and TLI with values higher <lb/>than .90 [64, 74]. <lb/>For the reliability, descriptive, asymmetric, kurtosis and correlation <lb/>analyses, the statistical program SPSS 21.0 was used. <lb/>For the analysis of reliability, two indices were used, Cronbach&apos;s Alpha <lb/>(α) (equal to or greater than .70) [75], and Omega Coefficient (ω) [76], which <lb/>also serves to check the internal consistency of the variables used in the <lb/>investigation and, according to some authors (77), have shown evidence of <lb/>greater accuracy. This means that in McDonald&apos;s Omega Coefficient the <lb/>established range is between 0 and 1, with the highest values giving us the <lb/>most reliable measurements [77]. With the Omega Coefficient of McDonald, <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>the calculations were made with the &quot;psych&quot; 1.4.2.3 [71] of R 3.0.3 (RCore-<lb/>Team, 2014). <lb/>Results <lb/>Descriptive, reliability, asymmetry and kurtosis <lb/>statistics <lb/>Table 3 presents the descriptive statistics of the instruments used for <lb/>this study. This table shows the mean (M) and standard deviation (SD) of all <lb/>study variables, observing that, in terms of BPN, the highest mean value was <lb/>for the need for relatedness, which is equal to the satisfaction with PE <lb/>classes, with the lowest average being the BPN of autonomy. <lb/>The results from the reliability analysis are also observed, in order to <lb/>check the internal consistency of the questionnaires. All the factors were <lb/>accepted and used in the analyses, given that Cronbach&apos;s Alpha (α) was <lb/>equal to or greater than .70 [75] and that the Omega Coefficient of McDonald <lb/>has high, close to 1 [77]. <lb/>Table 3. Reliability analysis and descriptive statistics. <lb/>Instrument / Variable <lb/>M <lb/>TD <lb/>α <lb/>ω <lb/>ERAEEF <lb/>Value Assignment Evaluation <lb/>3.58 <lb/>.96 <lb/>.77 <lb/>.82 <lb/>BPNES <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Autonomy <lb/>2.97 <lb/>.91 <lb/>.80 <lb/>.84 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Competence <lb/>3.68 <lb/>.95 <lb/>.80 <lb/>.84 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Relatedness <lb/>3.89 <lb/>.94 <lb/>.85 <lb/>.89 <lb/>PLOC <lb/>Autonomous Motivation <lb/>3.69 <lb/>.87 <lb/>.88 <lb/>.91 <lb/>SSI-EF <lb/>PE Classes Satisfaction <lb/>3.89 <lb/>.98 <lb/>.89 <lb/>.91 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M, Media; TD, Typical Deviation; α, Cronbach&apos;s Alpha; ω, Omega coefficient. <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>In accordance with the normality rules proposed by Curran et al. [78] all <lb/>of the variables comply with the univariate normality, since the values of <lb/>asymmetry were below 2 and those of kurtosis below 7. These results can be <lb/>seen in Table 4. <lb/>Table 4. Asymmetry and kurtosis of the variables under study. <lb/>Instrument / Variable <lb/>Asymmetry Kurtosis <lb/>ERAEEF <lb/>Value Assignment Evaluation <lb/>-.36 <lb/>-.34 <lb/>BPNES <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Autonomy <lb/>.00 <lb/>-.30 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Competence <lb/>-.46 <lb/>-.38 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Relatedness <lb/>-.92 <lb/>.45 <lb/>PLOC <lb/>Autonomous Motivation <lb/>-.57 <lb/>-.12 <lb/>SSI-EF <lb/>PE Classes Satisfaction <lb/>-.80 <lb/>.03 <lb/>Analysis of structural equations <lb/>In line with the HMM [21, 79], the antecedent variables (perception of <lb/>the transfer of responsibility to the student in evaluation), the mediators <lb/>(satisfaction of the BPN), self-determined types of motivation (autonomous <lb/>motivation, controlled motivation and demotivation) and consequences <lb/>(satisfaction with PE classes) were included. <lb/>In this model, the aim was to find out the predictors of satisfaction with <lb/>PE classes, based on the perception of assigning responsibility to students <lb/>and the motivational variables (satisfaction of BPN and autonomous <lb/>motivation). The results are shown in Fig. 1. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 1. SEM. <lb/>Predicting the students&apos; satisfaction with PE classes from assigning them with <lb/>responsibility in evaluation and motivational variables. All of the parameters <lb/>are standardised, the most statistically significant are indicated with *p &lt; .01. <lb/>The contribution of each of the factors to the prediction of other <lb/>variables was examined through the standardised regression weights, hence, <lb/>the value of the assignment of responsibility in the result of the evaluation <lb/>predicted in a positive and significant way the satisfaction of the BPN of <lb/>autonomy (β = .72), competence (β = .87) and relatedness (β = .70). On the <lb/>other hand, autonomous motivation was predicted in a positive way by the <lb/>satisfaction of the BPN of autonomy (β = .49), competence (β = .43) and <lb/>relatedness (β = .04), with self-motivation predicting in a positive and <lb/>meaningful way the satisfaction with PE classes (β = .85). <lb/>The results of the model of structural equations revealed a good <lb/>alignment to the data [64, 74], as can be seen in Table 5. <lb/>Table 5. Adjustment indices of the Structural Equation Modelling. <lb/>Indices <lb/>Values <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>1004.16 <lb/>gl <lb/>202 <lb/>p <lb/>.00 <lb/>χ 2 /gl <lb/>4.93 <lb/>CFI <lb/>.94 <lb/>TLI <lb/>.93 <lb/>RMSEA <lb/>.06 (IC 90% = .06, .07) <lb/>Regarding the indirect effects between the latent variables, the results <lb/>are shown in the Table 6. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 6. Indirect effects in Structural Equation Model. <lb/>Variables <lb/>Effects <lb/>Value Assignment Responsability Evaluation  Autonomous <lb/>Motivation <lb/>.75 <lb/>Value Assignment Responsability Evaluation  Classes <lb/>Satisfaction <lb/>.64 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Autonomy  Classes Satisfaction <lb/>.42 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Competence  Classes Satisfaction <lb/>.37 <lb/>Satisfaction BPN Relatedness  Classes Satisfaction <lb/>.03 <lb/>Table 6 shows the totals of the indirect effects. However, the results <lb/>demonstrate that the indirect effects of the assigning of student responsibility <lb/>in evaluation upon autonomous motivation vary according to the production <lb/>level, via the satisfaction of the BPN of autonomy, which was β=.35. The <lb/>satisfaction of the BPN of competence being β=.37 and the satisfaction of the <lb/>BPN of relatedness β=.03. Regarding the variable for the value of assigning <lb/>students with responsibility during evaluation, we obtained that, via the <lb/>satisfaction of students in PE classes and autonomous motivation, β=.30, via <lb/>the satisfaction of the BPN of competence β=.32 and, via the satisfaction of <lb/>the BPN of relations and autonomous motivation β=.02. <lb/>Discussion and conclusions <lb/>Given the relevance of assigning responsibility to the student in the <lb/>evaluation for improving motivational processes and increasing student <lb/>satisfaction with PE classes, the present study aimed to validate a model that <lb/>would analyse these relationships from the HMM. The hypothesis stated that <lb/>the perception of the assignment of responsibility to the student during <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>evaluation would positively predict the satisfaction of the BPN, which would <lb/>positively predict autonomous motivation, in turn positively predicting the <lb/>satisfaction with PE classes. <lb/>In terms of the results previously mentioned, It can be observed that <lb/>the hypothesis was fulfilled, as it was already demonstrated that the <lb/>perception of the assignment of responsibility to the student in the evaluation <lb/>predicted in a positive and significant way the satisfaction of the BPN <lb/>(autonomy, competence and relatedness), and that the satisfaction of the <lb/>BPN positively predicted autonomous motivation, with a significant prediction <lb/>of the BPN of autonomy and competence. Finally, the most self-determined <lb/>form of motivation positively and significantly predicted satisfaction with PE <lb/>classes. <lb/>In line with the model obtained, Moreno et al. [80] showed that <lb/>responsibility positively predicted psychological mediators, and this predicted <lb/>intrinsic motivation, which positively predicted the importance that students <lb/>give to physical education, and this, finally, positively predicted the student&apos;s <lb/>intention to continue playing sports. <lb/>Other studies have demonstrated that when students are offered the <lb/>opportunity to choose tasks they improve their skills, their physical activity and <lb/>their perceived competence [81]. It was also proven that there was a greater <lb/>learner involvement when given the opportunity to make decisions with <lb/>various methodological aspects such as space, time, material or grouping <lb/>[82]. <lb/>Motivation involves a set of emotional, cognitive and social <lb/>phenomena, with which, according to studies, if a teaching style is used <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>where students are allowed to participate in the teaching-learning process, the <lb/>cognitive and physical involvement will be greater [83]. This explains a greater <lb/>satisfaction towards PE classes, and a greater commitment to learning, as <lb/>students are more intrinsically motivated thanks to their involvement in the <lb/>evaluation process [35]. Research carried out by Vera [30], with 49 students, <lb/>also showed that the assignment of responsibilities to the students makes the <lb/>satisfaction of the BPN of autonomy higher, and with it the satisfaction and <lb/>enjoyment towards physical activity. <lb/>It has been confirmed that one key aspect to improving motivation is <lb/>the assignment of responsibility to the student [18], along with the use of <lb/>styles that favour the autonomy of the students [84]. Thanks to different works <lb/>[18, 42], which are in line with our results, it can be affirmed that an <lb/>assignment of responsibilities increases the most self-determined forms of <lb/>motivation. The study by Gómez-Rijo et al. [85], reached the conclusion that <lb/>the transfer of responsibilities to the student, by the teacher, contributes to the <lb/>development of student autonomy. It also demonstrated [85] that giving <lb/>autonomy to the student for the learning of physical skills improves <lb/>autonomous motivation. <lb/>Evaluation must not only be linked to the teacher giving a score, but <lb/>the student must be given the possibility to decide and intervene, taking into <lb/>account initial and bidirectional agreements [87]. Other works developed in <lb/>the educational field [88, 89], that related the satisfaction of the BPN to the <lb/>self-determined forms of motivation, revealed, like in our study, that an <lb/>adequate satisfaction of the BPN would increase intrinsic motivation. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>The authors of these works have shown that a greater feeling of <lb/>autonomy will increase intrinsic motivation [8, 9, 53, 60, 90, 91] and with this, <lb/>satisfaction when participating in activities [39, 40, 41], supporting the results <lb/>found in this study. However, other authors, performing intervention <lb/>programmes to support teachers with the BNP, did not find significant results <lb/>in intrinsic motivation [91]. <lb/>A teaching-style where autonomy and decision-making is stimulated <lb/>will reduce the demotivation of the students, as well as boredom with PE <lb/>classes [94], as pointed out in the study by Moreno et al. [93]. Different works <lb/>have indicated that the less self-determined forms of motivation and a lower <lb/>perception of satisfaction of BPN [95] are related to the giving up of physical <lb/>activity, which may be due to the lack of satisfaction with the PE classes. <lb/>Other studies which had similar results to ours, indicate that an <lb/>increase in autonomy will make satisfaction with PE classes higher [82], and <lb/>that students will be more involved in their tasks and their own learning <lb/>process [82]. Different investigations, such as the one carried out by Méndez <lb/>et al. [94], found that if a suitable atmosphere that involves the task is <lb/>generated in the classroom, the satisfaction of the BPN will be greater, which <lb/>will be positively related to more self-determined motivation and with less <lb/>boredom with the classes of PE. <lb/>Research that is also related to our variables [48, 52, 54, 55], indicated <lb/>that the satisfaction of the BPN predicted high levels of intrinsic motivation <lb/>and that this was related to an increase in enjoyment and satisfaction with <lb/>classes. It can therefore be said that there is a close relationship between <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>intrinsic motivation and satisfaction with classes [24, 96]. Some authors, in <lb/>their results give particular importance to the BPN of autonomy [61, 98]. <lb/>As many researchers have been proposing for some time [36, 37, 98], <lb/>it is necessary to come up with new evaluation strategies which offer more <lb/>student involvement. Strategies such as developing the students&apos; ability to <lb/>reflect on what they have done, substitute the final exam for a continuous <lb/>process in which the students learn from their mistakes and successes, <lb/>involve the student in making decisions, among others, which will mean that, <lb/>based on the theoretical postulates of the HMM, the satisfaction of the BPN <lb/>will be higher, as well as that the more self-determined forms of motivation will <lb/>be increased, with levels of demotivation decreasing. This will have positive <lb/>consequences, such as satisfaction with PE classes, and therefore, increase <lb/>the possibility of physical activity outside the classroom. <lb/>One of the limitations found in this study was the sample, which would <lb/>be interesting to expand to other areas and even differentiate by age, gender <lb/>and socioeconomic level. Another limitation was seen from only using <lb/>questionnaires, as only opinion is determined through a scale of answers. It <lb/>would be interesting to make a methodological triangulation, using systematic <lb/>observation and the use of interviews, both with students and with teachers. <lb/>Once the results are known, a longitudinal or quasi-experimental study could <lb/>be carried out, through an intervention that would allow us to establish cause-<lb/>effect relationships, in order to know the effect caused by the application of <lb/>different motivational strategies in the variables under analysis. <lb/>In conclusion, thanks to results from models such as ours, in PE <lb/>classes intervention programmes are necessary to achieve more self-<lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>determined motivation of our students, using different strategies such as <lb/>posing tasks that are fun for them, by assigning them with responsibilities, <lb/>proposing self-evaluation activities, as well as reciprocal evaluation so that <lb/>they feel they are participants in their teaching and learning process. In this <lb/>way, we can achieve that the students increase their levels of satisfaction of <lb/>the BPN, which will lead to them showing higher levels of autonomous <lb/>motivation in the classes and, consequently, to their satisfaction with the PE <lb/>classes being greater. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Franco E, Coterón J, Martínez HA, Brito J. Motivational profiles in <lb/>physical education students from three countries and their relationship <lb/>with <lb/>physical <lb/>activity. <lb/>Suma <lb/>Psicol. <lb/>2017; <lb/>24: <lb/>1-8. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.sumpsi.2016.07.001 <lb/>2. <lb/>Pulido JJ, Sánchez-Oliva D, Amado D, González-Ponce I, Sánchez-<lb/>Miguel PA. Influence of motivational processes on enjoyment, boredom <lb/>and intention to persist in young sportspersons. S Afr J Res Sport PH. <lb/>2014; 36(3): 135-49. <lb/>3. <lb/>Taylor IM, Spray C, Pearson N. The influence of thephysical education <lb/>environment on children&apos;s well-being and physical activity across the <lb/>transition from primary to secondary school. J Sport Exerc Psychol. <lb/>2014;36:574-83. http://dx.doi.org/10.1123/jsep. 2014-0038. <lb/>4. <lb/>Egan CA, Webster CA. Using Theory to Support Classroom Teachers as <lb/>Physical Activity Promoters. J Physical Educ, Recre Dance. 2018; 89(1): <lb/>23-9. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. <lb/>Yilmaz A, Esenturk OK, Demir GT, Ilhan EL. Metaphoric Perception of <lb/>Gifted Students about Physical Education Course and Physical <lb/>Education Teachers. J Educ Learn. 2017; 6(2): 220-34. <lb/>6. <lb/>Gil-Arias A, Harvey S, Cárceles A, Práxedes A, Del Villar F. Impact of a <lb/>hybrid TGfU-Sport Education unit on student motivation in physical <lb/>education. PloS ONE. 2017; 12(6) :e0179876. <lb/>7. <lb/>Ayuso JAZ. Benefits of teaching styles and student-centred <lb/>methodologies in Physical Education. E-Balonmano. 2018; 13(3): 237-<lb/>50. <lb/>8. <lb/>Sánchez-Oliva D, Pulido-González JJ, Leo FM, González-Ponce I, <lb/>García-Calvo T. Effects of an intervention with teachers in the physical <lb/>education context: A Self-Determination Theory approach. PloS ONE. <lb/>2017; 12(12): e0189986. <lb/>9. <lb/>Standage M, Duda JL, Ntoumanis N. A test of Self-Determination Theory <lb/>in school physical education. Brit J Educ Psychol. 2005; 75: 411-33. <lb/>pmid:16238874. <lb/>10. Taylor IM, Ntoumanis N, Standage M, Spray CM. Motivational predictors <lb/>of physical education students&apos; effort, exercise intentions, and leisure-<lb/>time physical activity: A multilevel linear growth analysis. J Sport Exerc <lb/>Psychol. 2010; 32(1): 99-120. <lb/>11. Escartí A, Cervelló EM. Motivation in Sport. In I. Balaguer (Ed.), <lb/>Psychological training in sport: Principles and applications (pp. 61-90). <lb/>Valencia: Albatros Educación; 1994. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>12. Ryan RM, Deci EL. Self-determination theory and the facilitation of <lb/>intrinsic motivation, social development, and well-being. Am Psychol. <lb/>2000;55:68-8. pmid:11392867 <lb/>13. Moreno JA, González-Cutre D, Chillón M. Preliminary validation in <lb/>Spanish of a scale designed to measure motivation in physical education <lb/>classes: the Perceived Locus of Causality (PLOC) Scale. Spa J Psychol. <lb/>2009; 12: 327-37. <lb/>14. Vansteenkiste M, Lens W, Deci EL. Intrinsic versus extrinsic goal <lb/>contents in self-determination theory: Another look at the quality of <lb/>academic <lb/>motivation. <lb/>Educ <lb/>Psychol. <lb/>2006; <lb/>41(1): <lb/>19-31. <lb/>doi:10.1207/s15326985ep4101_4 <lb/>15. Vansteenkiste M, Niemiec C, Soenens B. The development of the five <lb/>mini-theories of self-determination theory: An historical overview, <lb/>emerging trends, and future directions. In T. Urdan &amp; S. Karabenick <lb/>(Eds.). Advances in Motivation and Achievement, vol. 16: The decade <lb/>ahead (pp.105-166). Bingley, UK: Emerald; 2010. doi:10.1108/S0749-<lb/>7423(2010)000016A007. <lb/>16. Deci EL, Ryan RM. The &apos;&apos;what&quot; and &apos;&apos;why&quot; of goal pursuits: human needs <lb/>and the self-determination of behaviour. Psychol Inq. 2000; 11: 227-68. <lb/>17. Deci EL, Ryan RM. Intrinsic motivation and Self-determination in human <lb/>behavior. New York: Plenum; 1985. <lb/>18. González-Cutre D, Sicilia A, Moreno JA. A Quasi-experimental Study of <lb/>the Effects of Task-involving Motivational Climate in Physical Education <lb/>Classes. Rev Educ. 2011; 356: 677-700. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. McDonough MH, Crocker PRE. Testing self-determined motivation as a <lb/>mediator of the relationship between psychological needs and affective <lb/>and behavioral outcomes. J Sport Exerc Psychol. 2007; 29(5): 645-63. <lb/>20. Standage M, Duda JL, Ntoumanis N. Students motivational processes <lb/>and their relationship to teacher ratings in school physical education: A <lb/>self-determination theory approach. Res Q Exerc Sport. 2006; 77(1): <lb/>100-10. <lb/>21. Vallerand RJ. A hierarchical model of intrinsic and extrinsic motivation in <lb/>sport and exercise. In G. Roberts (Ed.). Advances in motivation in sport <lb/>and exercise (2nd ed., pp.263-319). Champaign, IL: Human Kinetics; <lb/>2001. <lb/>22. Deci EL, Ryan RM. Handbook of self-determination research. Rochester, <lb/>New York: University of Rochester Press; 2002. <lb/>23. Gucciardi DF, Jackson B. Understanding sport continuation: An <lb/>integration of the theories of planned behaviour and basic psychological <lb/>needs. J Sci Med Sport. 2015; 18(1): 31-6. pmid:24378719. <lb/>24. Sánchez-Oliva D, Sánchez-Miguel PA, Leo FM, Kinnafick FE, García-<lb/>Calvo T. Physical education lessons and physical activity intentions <lb/>within Spanish secondary schools: a self-determination perspective. J <lb/>Teach Phys Educ. 2014; 33: 232-49. <lb/>25. Ntoumanis N, Standage M. Motivation in physical education classes: A <lb/>self-determination theory perspective. Theory Res Educ. 2009; 7: 194-<lb/>202. <lb/>26. Light R, Fawns R. Knowing the game: Integrating speech and action in <lb/>games teaching through TGfU. Quest. 2003; 55(2): 161-76. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>27. Derry JA. Single-sex and coeducation physical education: perspective of <lb/>adolescent girls and female physical education teachers (research). <lb/>Melpomene Journal. 2002; 22: 17-28. <lb/>28. Allen JB. Social motivation in youth sport. J Sport Exerc Psychol. 2003; <lb/>25: 551-67. <lb/>29. Guan J, Xiang P, McBride R, Bruene A. Achievement goals, social goals <lb/>and students&apos; reported persistence and effort in high school physical <lb/>education. J Teach Phys Educ. 2006; 25: 58-74. <lb/>30. Vera JA. Dilemmas in the negotiation of curriculum to students from the <lb/>trasnfer of responsability for the evaluation in Physical Education <lb/>classroom. Rev Inv Educ. 2010; 7: 72-82. <lb/>31. Bechter BE, Dimmock JA, Howard JL, Whipp PR, Jackson B. Student <lb/>motivation in high school physical education: A latent profile analysis <lb/>approach. J Sport Exerc Psychol. 2018; 40(4): 206-16. <lb/>32. Hortigüela-Alcalá D, Pérez-Pueyo Á, Fernández-Río J. Connection <lb/>between the attitudinal style and students&apos; assessment responsibility in <lb/>Physical Education. Cul Cien Dep. 2017; 12(35): 89-99 <lb/>33. Baena A, Gómez M, Granero A, Ortíz MM. Predicting satisfaction in <lb/>physical education from motivational climate and self-determined <lb/>motivation. <lb/>J <lb/>Teach <lb/>Phys <lb/>Educ. <lb/>2015; <lb/>34(2): <lb/>210-24. <lb/>doi.org/10.1123/jtpe.2013-0165. <lb/>34. Hassandra M, Goudas M, Chroni S. Examining factors associated with <lb/>intrinsic motivation in physical education: a qualitative approach. Psychol <lb/>of Sport Exerc. 2003; 4: 211-23. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>35. Yonemura K, Fukugusakio Y, Yoshinaga T, Takahashi T. Effects of <lb/>Momentum and climate in Physical Education class on students´ <lb/>formative evaluation. Int J Sport Health Sci. 2003; 2: 25-33. <lb/>36. Álvarez-Méndez JM. The formative evaluation. Cuad Pedag. 2007; 364: <lb/>96-100. <lb/>37. Vera JA, Moreno JA. The teaching of responsibility in the physical <lb/>education classroom. Habilidad Motriz. 2008; 32: 39-43. <lb/>38. Moreno JA, Vera JA, Del Villar F. Search for autonomy in motor task <lb/>learning in physical education university students. Eur J Psychol Educ. <lb/>2010; 25(1): 37-47. <lb/>39. Prusak KA, Treasure DC, Darst PW, Pangrazi RP. The effects of choice <lb/>on the motivation of adolescent girls in physical education. J Teach Phys <lb/>Educ. 2004; 23: 19-29. <lb/>40. Wallhead TL, Ntoumanis N. Effects of a sport education intervention on <lb/>students&apos; motivational responses in physical education. J Teach Phys <lb/>Educ. 2004; 23: 4-18. <lb/>41. Ward P. What we teach is as important as how we teach it. J Physical <lb/>Educ, Recre Dance. 2006; 77: 20-3. <lb/>42. Moreno JA, Sicilia A, Sáenz-López P, González-Cutre D, Almagro BJ, <lb/>Conde C. Motivational analysis comparing three contexts of physical <lb/>activity. Rev Int Med Cienc Ac. 2014; 14(56): 665-85. <lb/>43. Moreno JM, Vera JA. Model Causal of the Satisfaction with the Life in <lb/>Adolescent Students of Physical Education. Rev Psic. 2011; 16(2): 367-<lb/>80. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>44. Hellison D. Teaching personal and social responsibility in physical <lb/>education. En S. J. Silverman y C. D. Ennis (Eds.), Student learning in <lb/>physical education: applying research to enhance instruction (pp. 241-<lb/>254). Champiagn: Human Kinetics; 2003. <lb/>45. Hellison D, Martinek T. Social and individual responsibility programs. En <lb/>D. Kirk, D. Mcdonald &amp; M. O´Sullivan (Eds), The handbook of physical <lb/>education (pp. 610-626). Thousand Oaks, CA: Sage; 2006. <lb/>46. Ruiz LM, Rodríguez P, Martinek T, Schilling T, Durán LJ, Jiménez P. <lb/>Project Effort: A model for the Development of Social and Personal <lb/>Responsibility through Sport. Rev de Educ. 2006; 341: 933-58. <lb/>47. Herrera-Mor E, Pablos-Monzó A, Chiva-Bartoll O, Pablos-Abella C. <lb/>Effects of a global physical activity program on the physical condition, <lb/>self-esteem and enjoyment on elderly adults. Ágora. 2016; 18(2): 167-<lb/>83. <lb/>48. Moreno JA, González-Cutre D, Ruiz LM. Selfdetermined motivation and <lb/>physical education importance. Hum Mov. 2009; 10(1): 5-11. <lb/>49. Moreno JA, Silveira Y, Alias A. Predictive model to improve the <lb/>competence perception and academic performance in colleges. REDU. <lb/>Rev Doc Univ. 2015; 13: 173-88. <lb/>50. Sevil J, Aibar A, Abós A, García L. Motivational climate of teaching <lb/>physical education: Could it affect student grades?. Retos. 2017; 31: 98-<lb/>102. <lb/>51. Ortega E, Calderón A, Palao JM, Puigcerver C. Design and validation of <lb/>a questionnaire to evaluate the perceived attitude of the professor and of <lb/>a questionnaire to evaluate the actitudinal contents of the students <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>during the physical education classes in secondary education. Retos. <lb/>2008; 14: 22-9. <lb/>52. Sevil J, Abós A, Generelo E, Aibar A, García-González L. Importance of <lb/>support of the basic psychological needs in predisposition to different <lb/>contents in Physical Education. Retos. 2016; 29: 3-8. <lb/>53. Ntoumanis N. A prospective study of participation in optional school <lb/>physical education using a Self-Determination Theory framework. J Educ <lb/>Psychol. 2005; 97: 444-53. doi:10.1037/0022-0663.97.3.444 <lb/>54. Moreno JA, Zomeño T, Marín LM, Ruiz LM, Cervelló E. Perception of the <lb/>usefulness and importance of physical education according to motivation <lb/>generated by the teacher. Rev Educ. 2013; 362: 380-401. <lb/>55. Grasten A, Jaakkola T, Liukkonen J, Watt, A, Yli-Piipari S. Prediction of <lb/>the enjoyment in school physical education. J Sport Sci Med. 2012; 11: <lb/>260-69. <lb/>56. Cheon SH, Reeve J, Ntoumanis N. A needs-supportive intervention to <lb/>help PE teachers enhance students&apos; prosocial behavior and diminish <lb/>antisocial behavior. Psychol Sport Exerc. 2018; 35: 74-88. <lb/>57. Moy B, Renshaw I, Davids K. The impact of nonlinear pedagogy on <lb/>physical education teacher education students&apos; intrinsic motivation. Phys <lb/>Educ Sport Pedagog. 2016; 21(5): 517-38. <lb/>58. Sánchez-Oliva D, Leo FM, Sánchez-Miguel PA, Amado D, García-Calvo <lb/>T. Development of a causal model to explain positive behaviors in <lb/>physical education classes. Acción Motriz. 2013; 10: 48-58. <lb/>59. Granero-Gallegos A, Baena-Extremera A, Sánchez-Fuentes JA, <lb/>Martínez-Molina M. Motivational profiles of autonomy support, self-<lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>determination, satisfaction, importance of physical education and <lb/>intention to partake in leisure time physical activity. Cuad Psicol Deporte. <lb/>2014; 14(2): 59-70. <lb/>60. Ntoumanis N. A self-determination approach to the understanding of <lb/>motivation in physical education. Br J Educ Psychol. 2001; 71: 225-42. <lb/>61. Cubo S, Martín B, García JL. Research methods and data analysis in <lb/>social sciences and health. Madrid: Ediciones Pirámide Grupo Anaya, <lb/>S.A.; 2011. <lb/>62. Montero I, León OG. A guide for naming research studies in <lb/>Psychology. INT J Clin Health Psychol. 2007; 7(3): 847-62. <lb/>63. Moreno JA, Vera JA, Cervelló E. Participative evaluation and <lb/>responsibility in physical education. Rev Educ. 2006; 340: 731-54. <lb/>64. Hu L, Bentler PM. Cutoff criteria for fit indexes in covariance structure <lb/>analysis: Conventional criteria versus new alternatives. Struct Equ <lb/>Model. 1999; 6:1-55. <lb/>65. Vlachopoulos SP, Michailidou S. Development and initial validation of a <lb/>measure of autonomy, competence, and relatedness in exercise: The <lb/>Basic psychological needs in exercise scale. Meas Phys Educ Exerc Sci. <lb/>2006; 103: 179-201. <lb/>66. Moreno JA, González-Cutre D, Chillón M, Parra N. Adaptation of the <lb/>Basic Psychological Needs in Exercise Scale to Physical Education. Rev <lb/>Mex Psicol. 2008; 25: 295-303. <lb/>67. Goudas M, Biddle SJH, Fox KR. Achievement goal orientations and <lb/>intrinsic motivation in physical fitness testing with children. Pediatr Exerc <lb/>Sci. 1994; 6; 159-67. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>68. Duda JL, Nicholls JG. Dimensions of achievement motivation in <lb/>schoolwork and sport. J Educ Psychol. 1992; 84(3): 290-99. <lb/>69. Balaguer I, Atienza FL, Castillo I, Moreno Y, Duda JL. Factorial structure <lb/>of measures of satisfaction/interest in sport and classroom in the case of <lb/>Spanish adolescents. Abstracts of 4th European Conference of <lb/>Psychological Assessment (p. 76). Lisbon: Portugal; 1997. <lb/>70. Aron A, Aron E. Statistics for Psychology. Buenos Aires: Pearson <lb/>Education; 2001. <lb/>71. Mullan E, Markland D, Ingledew DK. A graded conceptualisation of <lb/>selfdetermination in the regulation of exercise behaviour: Development <lb/>of a measure using confirmatory factor analytic procedures. Personal <lb/>Individ Differ. 1997; 23: 745-52. doi:10.1016/S0191-8869(97)00107-4. <lb/>72. Revelle W. Psych: Procedures for Psychological, Psychometric, and <lb/>Personality Research. Illinois: Evanston; 2014. <lb/>Retrieved from <lb/>http://cran.r-project.org/package=psych <lb/>73. Muthén LK, Muthén BO. Mplus User&apos;s Guide (7th ed.). Los Angeles, CA: <lb/>Muthén &amp; Muthén; 2014. <lb/>74. Kline RB. Principles and practice of structural equation modeling. <lb/>Structural Equation Modeling. New York: Guilford Press; 2011. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1038/156278a0. <lb/>75. Nunnally JC. Psychometric theory. New York: McGraw-Hill; 1978. <lb/>76. McDonald RP. Test theory. A unified treatment. Mahwah, NJ, Lawrence <lb/>Erlbaum Associates; 1999. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>77. Revelle W, Zinbarg RE. Coefficients Alpha, Omega, and the Gbl: <lb/>Comments on Sijtsma. Psychometrika. 2009; 74(1): 145-54. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1007/s11336-008-9102-z <lb/>78. Curran PJ, West SG, Finch JF. The robustness of test statistics to <lb/>nonnormality and specification error in Confirmatory Factor Analysis. <lb/>Psychol Methods. 1996; 1:16-29. <lb/>79. Vallerand RJ. Toward a hierarchical model of intrinsic and extrinsic <lb/>motivation. En M. P. Zanna (Ed.), Advances in experimental social <lb/>psychology (pp.271-360). Academic Press: New York; 1997. <lb/>80. Moreno JA, Huéscar E, Cervelló E. Prediction of adolescents doing <lb/>physical activity after completing secondary education. Spa J Psychol. <lb/>2012; 15(1): 90-100. <lb/>81. Hastie PA, Rudisill ME, Wadsworth DD. Providing students with voice <lb/>and choice: lessons from intervention research on autonomy-supportive <lb/>climates in physical education. Sport Educ and Soc. 2013; 18: 38-56. <lb/>82. Calderón A, Martínez D, Hastie P. Students and teachers&apos; perception <lb/>after practice with two pedagogical models in Physical Education. <lb/>RICYDE. <lb/>2013; <lb/>9(32): <lb/>137-53. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.5232/ricyde2013.03204 <lb/>83. Sánchez B, Byra M, Wallhead T. Students&apos; perceptions of the command, <lb/>practice, and inclusion styles of teaching. Phys Educ Sport Pedagog. <lb/>2012; 17(3): 317-30. http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/17408989.2012.690864 <lb/>84. Reeve J, Vansteenkiste M, Assor A, Ahmad I, Cheon SH, Jang H, <lb/>Kaplan H, Moss J, Olaussen B, Wang CKJ. The beliefs that underlie <lb/>autonomy supportive and controlling teaching: A multinational <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>investigation. <lb/>Motiv <lb/>Emot. <lb/>2014; <lb/>38(1): <lb/>93-110. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.1007/s11031-013-9367-0. <lb/>85. Gómez-Rijo A, Jiménez-Jiménez F, Sánchez-López CR. Development of <lb/>Autonomy of Elementary Students in Physical Education through a <lb/>process of action research. RICYDE. 2015; 42(11): 310-28. <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.5232/ricyde2015.04201 <lb/>86. Behzadnia B, Mohammadzadeh H, Ahmadi M. Autonomy-supportive <lb/>behaviors promote autonomous motivation, knowledge structures, motor <lb/>skills learning and performance in physical education. Curr Psychol. <lb/>2017; 1-14. https://doi.org/10.1007/s12144-017-9727-0. <lb/>87. Papinczak T, Babri A, Peterson R, Kippers V, Wilkinson D. Students <lb/>Generating Questions for Their Own Written Examinations. Adv Health <lb/>Sci Educ. 2011; 16(5): 703-10. <lb/>88. Méndez JI, Fernández-Río J. Social responsibility, basic psychological <lb/>needs, intrinsic motivation, and friendship goals in physical education. <lb/>Retos. 2017; 32: 134-39. <lb/>89. Núñez JL, León J. The Mediating Effect of Intrinsic Motivation to Lear <lb/>non the Relationship between Student&apos;s Autonomy Support and Viality <lb/>and Deep Learning. Spa J Psychol. 2016; 19(42): 1-6. <lb/>http://doi.org/10.1017/sip.2016.43 <lb/>90. Taylor IM, Ntoumanis N. Teacher motivational strategies and student <lb/>self-determination in physical education. J Educ Psychol. 2007; 99(2): <lb/>747-60. doi:10.1037/0022-0663.99.4.747 <lb/>91. Amado D, Del Villar F, Leo FM, Sánchez-Oliva D, Sánchez-Miguel PA, <lb/>García-Calvo T. Effect of a multi-dimensional intervention programme on <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>the motivation of physical education students. PLoS ONE. 2014; 9(1): <lb/>e85275. <lb/>92. Tessier D, Sarrazin P, Ntoumanis N. The effect of an intervention to <lb/>improve newly qualified teachers&apos; interpersonal style, students <lb/>motivation and psychological need satisfaction in sport-based physical <lb/>education. Contemp Educ Psychol. 2010; 35: 242-53 <lb/>93. Moreno JA, Parra N, González-Cutre D. Influence of autonomy support, <lb/>social goals and relatedness on amotivation in physical education <lb/>classes. Psicoth. 2008; 20(4): 636-41. <lb/>94. Méndez A, Fernández J, Cecchini JA. Motivational climates, needs, <lb/>motivation and outcomes in Physical Education. Aula Abierta. 2013; <lb/>41(1): 63-72. <lb/>95. Cervelló E. Psychological variables related to the choice of sports tasks <lb/>with different level of difficulty. Considerations for the design of <lb/>motivational programs of psychological training in sport. Eur J Hum Mov. <lb/>1999; 5: 35-52. <lb/>96. Sparks C, Lonsdale C, Dimmock J, Jackson B. An intervention to <lb/>improve teachers&apos; interpersonally involving instructional practices in high <lb/>school physical education: Implications for student relatedness support <lb/>and in-class experiences. J Sport Exerc Psychol. 2017; 39(2): 120-33. <lb/>97. Baena A, Gómez-López M, Granero-Gallegos A, Martínez-Molina M. <lb/>Prediction model of satisfaction and enjoyment in Physical Education <lb/>from the autonomy and motivational climate. Universitas Psychologica. <lb/>2016; 15(2): 15-25. doi: 10.11144/Javeriana. upsy15-2.mpsd <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>787 <lb/>98. Lewis R. Classroom discipline student responsibility: the students` view. <lb/>788 <lb/>Teach Teacher Educ. 2001; 17: 307-19. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
