<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>| Open Peer Review | Clinical Microbiology | Research Article <lb/>The impact of the COVID-19 pandemic on blood culture <lb/>practices and bloodstream infections <lb/>Matt Driedger, 1 Nick Daneman, 2,3 Kevin Brown, 4,5 Wayne L. Gold, 6 Sarah C.J. Jorgensen, 7 Colleen Maxwell, 8 Kevin L. Schwartz, 3,4,5,9 <lb/>Andrew M. Morris, 10 Deva Thiruchelvam, 3 Bradley Langford, 4,5 Elizabeth Leung, 9 Derek MacFadden 1,3,11 <lb/>AUTHOR AFFILIATIONS See affiliation list on p. 11. <lb/>ABSTRACT The COVID-19 pandemic has likely influenced the epidemiology of bacterial <lb/>infections through wide-ranging changes to clinical practices and infection control and <lb/>prevention interventions. We sought to determine how the detection and incidence of <lb/>bloodstream infections (BSIs) have been influenced by the pandemic. We performed a <lb/>retrospective analysis of blood culture data in the province of Ontario, Canada, from 1 <lb/>January 2017 to 31 December 2020. Outcomes included a weekly incidence of blood <lb/>culture tests, BSIs, and contaminant results. Results were stratified by hospital, commun <lb/>ity, and long-term care (LTC) settings. An interrupted time series analysis using segmen <lb/>ted regression models was used to determine changes in outcome incidence/prevalence <lb/>during the pre-and peri-pandemic periods. Of the 14,083,853 individuals included, <lb/>129,329 (0.92%) developed a bloodstream infection. The blood culture ordering rate <lb/>increased during the pandemic in the hospital setting only [Incidence rate ratio (IRR) <lb/>1.09, 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.01-1.19]. There was a decline in the incidence of <lb/>community-acquired (IRR 0.95, 95% CI 0.91-0.99) and LTC-acquired (IRR 0.85, 95% CI <lb/>0.76-0.94) BSIs. Hospital-acquired BSIs were unchanged. The proportion of blood culture <lb/>contaminants increased in the community (7% increase, P &lt; 0.01) and LTC settings (14% <lb/>increase, P &lt; 0.05). There was decreased incidence of community-acquired Streptococcus <lb/>pneumoniae (IRR 0.43, 95% CI 0.33-0.57) and Staphylococcus aureus (IRR 0.91, 95% CI <lb/>0.84-0.99) bacteremia. Pandemic-related changes in the performance of blood cultures <lb/>and the epidemiology of BSIs have implications for current and future pandemic <lb/>antimicrobial use, healthcare resource allocation, and hospital and laboratory policies. <lb/>IMPORTANCE Bacterial infections are a significant cause of morbidity and mortality <lb/>worldwide. In the wake of the COVID-19 pandemic, previous studies have demonstrated <lb/>pandemic-related shifts in the epidemiology of bacterial bloodstream infections (BSIs) <lb/>in the general population and in specific hospital systems. Our study uses a large, <lb/>comprehensive data set stratified by setting [community, long-term care (LTC), and <lb/>hospital] to uniquely demonstrate how the effect of the COVID-19 pandemic on BSIs <lb/>and testing practices varies by healthcare setting. We showed that, while the number <lb/>of false-positive blood culture results generally increased during the pandemic, this <lb/>effect did not apply to hospitalized patients. We also found that many infections were <lb/>likely under-recognized in patients in the community and in LTC, demonstrating the <lb/>importance of maintaining healthcare for these groups during crises. Last, we found a <lb/>decrease in infections caused by certain pathogens in the community, suggesting some <lb/>secondary benefits of pandemic-related public health measures. <lb/>KEYWORDS bloodstream infections, pandemic, COVID-19, blood cultures, epidemiol <lb/>ogy <lb/>November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23 1 <lb/>Editor Ahmed Babiker, Emory University School of <lb/>Medicine, Atlanta, Georgia, USA <lb/>Address correspondence to Matt Driedger, <lb/>madriedger@toh.ca. <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>See the funding table on p. 11. <lb/>Received 26 June 2023 <lb/>Accepted 11 October 2023 <lb/>Published 17 November 2023 <lb/>Copyright © 2023 Driedger et al. This is an open-<lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>license. <lb/>Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></front>

			<body>T he COVID-19 pandemic has dominated recent efforts within public health and <lb/>infectious diseases, yet bacterial infection remains a critically important global <lb/>challenge. Despite the low rate of bacterial co-infection among SARS-CoV-2-infected <lb/>patients (1, 2), various pandemic-related factors have likely altered the incidence and <lb/>microbiology of bacterial infections. These include an increased incidence of hospi <lb/>tal-acquired bacterial infections, the use of empiric antimicrobials among patients <lb/>hospitalized with COVID-19 (3-5), patient crowding, and shortages in health human <lb/>resources and personal protective equipment (PPE) (6). Conversely, mitigating factors <lb/>may include improved hospital infection prevention and control measures and reduced <lb/>contact patterns in the community (6). <lb/>Large-scale multicenter studies can be used to determine population-level changes <lb/>in the epidemiology of invasive bacterial infections prior to and during the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic. However, existing multicenter studies are generally limited to data from select <lb/>hospital systems (7-12) and intensive care units (ICUs) (13-16), with varying outcomes <lb/>perhaps relating to institution-specific factors during the pandemic. Larger nation-wide <lb/>studies, on the other hand, have generally been limited to hospital-reported nosocomial <lb/>infections in administrative surveillance data, which may be subject to reporting errors, <lb/>particularly during the pandemic onset and its associated institutional pressures (15-19). <lb/>Furthermore, while the pandemic would be expected to have had differential effects <lb/>on community-acquired infections compared to those acquired in hospitals and other <lb/>institutions, only a few studies have stratified their analysis accordingly. One recently <lb/>published large multicenter study in the United States demonstrated an increase in both <lb/>community-and hospital-acquired bloodstream infections (BSIs) during the first year of <lb/>the pandemic (20), whereas another analysis demonstrated an increase in only hospital-<lb/>acquired infections (21). Importantly, both studies utilized only one pre-pandemic year <lb/>as the comparison period, and so they have limited ability to control for pre-existing <lb/>trends. <lb/>In order to fill these research gaps, we used an interrupted time-series approach to <lb/>determine changes in the incidence and microbiology of BSIs during the first year of the <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic in the province of Ontario. We hypothesized that there would be <lb/>increased blood culture ordering and blood culture contamination in the hospital setting <lb/>due to staffing shortages and changes in PPE protocols, whereas culture ordering rates <lb/>would decrease in long-term care (LTC) and community settings due to pandemic-rela <lb/>ted changes to the provision of healthcare in these settings. We also predicted increased <lb/>BSI incidence among hospitalized patients and decreased BSI in the community among <lb/>organisms associated with transmissible infectious syndromes. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Study design and data sources <lb/>We performed a retrospective analysis of clinical and microbiology data to determine <lb/>changes in the incidence rates of bacteremia in the province of Ontario, Canada, prior to <lb/>and during the first year of the COVID-19 pandemic. Our cohort was derived using data <lb/>sets at ICES (previously the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences), which were linked <lb/>using unique encoded identifiers. Data sets included the registered persons database <lb/>(RPDB), the Canadian Institute for Health Information Discharge Abstract Database <lb/>(CIHI-DAD), the Continuing Care Reporting System (CCRS), the Ontario Laboratories <lb/>Information System (OLIS), and others. Linked data sets included demographic and <lb/>laboratory data from all individuals in the province of Ontario eligible for the provincial <lb/>health insurance program. Since healthcare in Ontario is publicly funded, this cohort <lb/>captures information from virtually all 14.5 million residents of Ontario. The use of these <lb/>data is authorized under Section 45 of Ontario&apos;s Personal Health Information Protection <lb/>Act and does not require research ethics board review (22). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>2 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>Inclusion criteria and study period <lb/>We analyzed all individuals in Ontario from 1 January 2017 to 31 December 2020. We <lb/>excluded individuals with invalid birth dates, death dates, or sex. We also excluded <lb/>individuals who were not Ontario residents or had an invalid ICES linkage number. <lb/>Demographic information <lb/>Demographic data including age and sex were extracted, along with clinical data <lb/>including the Deyo-Charlson Comorbidity Index and recent COVID-19 infection (any <lb/>microbiologic diagnosis of COVID-19 in the preceding 3 months). <lb/>Outcome definitions <lb/>The occurrence of a bloodstream infection was the primary outcome of interest. BSI <lb/>was defined as blood cultures demonstrating any organism except for Corynebacterium <lb/>spp., Cutibacterium acnes, Micrococcus spp., or Bacillus spp., which were classified as <lb/>contaminants because they are commonly isolated from the skin and rarely cause BSI. <lb/>Blood cultures of the same pathogen within a 14-day window were defined as a single <lb/>BSI episode. Since the growth of coagulase-negative staphylococci (CoNS) is typically <lb/>interpreted as a contaminant, only sustained CoNS BSI was included as a BSI episode, <lb/>defined as the same CoNS species detected in two separate blood cultures on separate <lb/>dates within 14 days. CoNS contaminants, defined as CoNS isolated from cultures for only <lb/>one day within a 14-day window, were reported separately as a proxy for contamination <lb/>rate. <lb/>Secondary outcomes included BSI by pathogen. All pathogens with sufficient <lb/>incidence rates to allow interrupted time series (ITS) analysis were included. Common <lb/>resistance profiles were reported, including methicillin-resistant Staphylococcus aureus <lb/>(MRSA), extended-spectrum beta-lactamase-producing organisms (ESBL), carbapene <lb/>mase-producing Enterobacterales (CPE), and vancomycin-resistant enterococci (VRE), <lb/>as determined by susceptibility testing by regional clinical laboratories. Blood culture <lb/>ordering rates were also expressed as total blood cultures performed per patient-day (or <lb/>per person for the community cohort). <lb/>Incidence rates <lb/>Primary and secondary outcomes were reported in aggregate and by setting. Commun <lb/>ity-acquired BSI (CBSI) was defined as BSI detected from a blood culture drawn in an <lb/>ambulatory setting, in the emergency department, or within 2 days of admission; LTC-BSI <lb/>as blood cultures performed on a patient currently residing in an LTC or within 2 days <lb/>of admission; and hospital-acquired BSI (HBSI) as detected from blood cultures drawn <lb/>greater than 2 days after admission. Weekly incidence rates were calculated as a function <lb/>of total patient days for the hospital and LTC settings and the eligible population (total <lb/>population minus population in LTC and hospital settings) for community settings. <lb/>Patient-days and eligible populations used to calculate incidence rates were determined <lb/>on weekly index dates. Due to reporting limitations on administrative data, incidence <lb/>rate data were displayed graphically only if they reflected a minimum case count of 5, <lb/>resulting in the censoring of individual data points from figures (not analyses). For some <lb/>outcomes with very low rates, monthly incidence rates are shown in figures, but weekly <lb/>rates were used for underlying analytic models. <lb/>Interrupted time series analysis <lb/>Interrupted time series regression models were fitted to detect changes in the incidence <lb/>of BSI and other outcomes of interest during the pandemic. All ITS models included a <lb/>binary indicator to determine the change in weekly rates of BSI and other secondary <lb/>outcomes during the pandemic period (1 March-31 December 2020) compared to the <lb/>pre-pandemic period (1 January 2017-29 February 2020). 1 March 2020 was selected <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>3 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>as this was the month during which the Ontario government declared a state of <lb/>emergency requiring the closure of public facilities, masking, and other public health <lb/>recommendations. We used negative binomial models with log links for rates (blood <lb/>culture and BSI) and binomial models with logit link for proportions (contaminants). <lb/>Pre-pandemic temporal trends (slope) and seasonality (where visually present) were <lb/>incorporated into all-time series in order to control for these variables in determining <lb/>the pandemic effect. Seasonality was modeled using annual sine and cosine functions <lb/>to control for seasonality in outcomes and was applied to all time series that visually <lb/>demonstrated seasonal patterns. Autocorrelation, partial autocorrelation, and residual <lb/>plots were used to assess model validity. Graphs of weekly or monthly BSI were used to <lb/>visually examine changes in incidence over time. All statistical analyses were performed <lb/>using SAS Enterprise Guide version 7.1 (Cary, NC). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>At the start of the historical cohort, the open cohort included 14,084,853 individuals, <lb/>with 13,992,030 in the community, 75,941 residing in LTCs, and 16,882 who were <lb/>hospitalized. A total of 129,329 individuals throughout the cohort had BSI, including <lb/>7,196 with LTC-BSI, 30,836 with HBSI, and 36,780 with CBSI. Baseline demographic <lb/>characteristics are shown in Table 1. Age, Deyo-Charlson Comorbidity Index, and sex <lb/>were comparable before and during the pandemic. Patients with HBSI were more likely <lb/>to have had a preceding COVID-19 infection compared to those with CBSI (6.8% vs 0.4%, <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test P &lt; 0.001). <lb/>Blood culture ordering <lb/>Figure 1 demonstrates the blood culture ordering rate by setting. In the hospital setting, <lb/>the weekly blood culture rate increased above pre-pandemic levels (IRR 1.09, 95% CI <lb/>1.01-1.19) despite decreased patient volumes (Fig. S1). Blood culture ordering rates in <lb/>the community and LTC settings were unchanged. <lb/>Probable blood culture contamination <lb/>The proportion of CoNS contaminants relative to the weekly blood culture ordering rate <lb/>increased in the community-acquired [Odds ratio (OR) 1.07, 95% CI 1.02-1.13] and the <lb/>LTC-acquired settings (OR 1.14, 95% CI 1.01-1.29) (Fig. 2; Table S2). There was a decrease <lb/>in the proportion of contaminants in the hospital setting (OR 0.90, 95% CI 0.84-0.97). <lb/>BSI incidence <lb/>Weekly BSI incidence trends are depicted in Fig. 3A through C. There was no change in <lb/>the incidence of HBSI (IRR 1.04, 95% CI 0.97-1.11). Conversely, BSI rates decreased at the <lb/>TABLE 1 Baseline characteristics of patients with BSI, by time period and setting a <lb/>Long-term care <lb/>Hospital <lb/>Community <lb/>Pre-pandemic <lb/>N = 5,897 <lb/>Pandemic <lb/>N = 1,299 <lb/>Pre-pandemic <lb/>N = 23,997 <lb/>Pandemic <lb/>N = 6,839 <lb/>Pre-pandemic <lb/>N = 28,560 <lb/>Pandemic <lb/>N = 8,210 <lb/>Age, years <lb/>Mean ± SD <lb/>81.8 ± 11.2 <lb/>80.6 ± 11.4 <lb/>64.5 ± 19.1 <lb/>63.8 ± 18.0 <lb/>64.6 ± 20.4 <lb/>66.2 ± 19.2 <lb/>Age group, years <lb/>&lt;18 <lb/>502 (2.1%) <lb/>101 (1.5%) <lb/>819 (2.9%) <lb/>164 (2.0%) <lb/>18-64 <lb/>487 (8.3%) <lb/>134 (10.3%) <lb/>10,214 (42.6%) <lb/>2,988 (43.7%) <lb/>11,229 (39.3%) <lb/>3,040 (37.0%) <lb/>≥ 65 <lb/>5,410 (91.7%) <lb/>1,165 (89.7%) <lb/>13,281 (55.3%) <lb/>3,750 (54.8%) <lb/>16,512 (57.8%) <lb/>5,006 (61.0%) <lb/>Deyo-Charlson Index <lb/>Mean ± SD <lb/>2.9 ± 2.22 <lb/>2.5 ± 2.1 <lb/>3.5 ± 2.6 <lb/>2.2 ± 2.3 <lb/>2.8 ± 2.6 <lb/>2.1 ± 2.2 <lb/>Sex <lb/>Female <lb/>3,040 (51.6%) <lb/>661 (50.9%) <lb/>10,005 (41.7%) <lb/>2,602 (38.0%) <lb/>12,955 (45.4%) <lb/>3,583 (43.6%) <lb/>Male <lb/>2,857 (48.4%) <lb/>638 (49.1%) <lb/>13,992 (58.3%) <lb/>4,237 (62.0%) <lb/>15,605 (54.6%) <lb/>4,627 (56.4%) <lb/>COVID-19 status <lb/>(prior to 90 days) <lb/>Negative <lb/>5,897 (100.0%) <lb/>1,244 (95.8%) <lb/>23,997 (100.0%) <lb/>6,375 (93.2%) <lb/>28,560 (100.0%) 8,178 (99.6%) <lb/>Positive <lb/>0 (0.0%) <lb/>55 (4.2%) <lb/>0 (0.0%) <lb/>464 (6.8%) <lb/>0 (0.0%) <lb/>32 (0.4%) <lb/>a The percentages are column percentages. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>4 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>FIG 1 Weekly blood culture ordering rate in community (A), hospital (B), and LTC (C) settings. The green <lb/>vertical line indicates the onset of the pandemic period (March 2020). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>5 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>FIG 2 Weekly proportion of CoNS contaminants per weekly blood cultures in community (A), hospital <lb/>(B), and LTC (C) settings at one time point censored for low counts (LTC plot). The green vertical line <lb/>indicates the onset of the pandemic period (March 2020). <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>6 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>FIG 3 Weekly BSI incidence in community (A), hospital (B), and LTC (C) settings. The green vertical line <lb/>indicates the onset of the pandemic period (March 2020). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>pandemic onset in community-acquired (IRR 0.95, 95% CI 0.91-0.99) and LTC-acquired <lb/>(IRR 0.85, 95% CI 0.76-0.94) settings. <lb/>Microbiology of BSI <lb/>In the community-acquired setting (Fig. S2; Fig. 2), the pandemic onset was associated <lb/>with a notable decline in the incidence of S. pneumoniae BSI (IRR 0.43, 95% CI 0.33-0.57) <lb/>and a decline in S. aureus BSI (IRR 0.91, 95% CI 0.84-0.99). In the hospital setting (Table <lb/>2; Fig. S3), there was an increase in sustained CoNS BSI (IRR 1.24, 95% CI 1.03-1.48) <lb/>and Klebsiella spp. BSI (IRR 1.17, 95% CI 1.04-1.31) figures not shown due to low case <lb/>counts. Changes in the LTC-acquired setting are shown in Table 2 and Fig. S4. There was <lb/>a significant decrease in the incidence of LTC-acquired Escherichia coli (IRR 0.70, 95% CI <lb/>0.52-0.92; figures not shown due to low case counts). <lb/>Resistant organisms <lb/>There were no observed differences in the incidence of bacteremia with resistant <lb/>organisms (MRSA, ESBL, and VRE) in the hospital setting during the pandemic (Table <lb/>S3; figures not shown due to low case counts). Insufficient incidence rates of BSIs <lb/>from resistant organisms precluded analysis in community-acquired and LTC-acquired <lb/>settings. <lb/>Sensitivity analyses <lb/>We performed a sensitivity analysis considering the possibility of a post-pandemic slope <lb/>change (based on visual inspection) in three instances: blood culture ordering rates in <lb/>the community, blood culture ordering rates in LTCs, and BSI incidence in LTCs (Table S4). <lb/>While there was a post-pandemic slope change detected in each case, the remainder of <lb/>the pandemic effect findings were not largely impacted. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this large province-wide study, we demonstrated that the COVID-19 pandemic onset <lb/>was associated with changes in the quality and number of blood cultures performed <lb/>and in the incidence and microbiology of BSIs. There was an increase in the number <lb/>of blood cultures performed on hospitalized patients. Blood culture contamination <lb/>increased in the community-and LTC-origin cultures. Overall, BSI incidence decreased <lb/>in the community and LTC settings but increased for certain pathogens in the hospital <lb/>setting. <lb/>Our cohort, including all blood cultures over 4 years from more than 14 million <lb/>individuals across various settings, from rural communities to urban referral centers, <lb/>represents one of the most comprehensive studies to date of the overall incidence of BSI <lb/>TABLE 2 Incidence rate ratios of pathogen-specific BSI in community, hospital, and LTC settings using <lb/>segmented regression models, comparing peri-pandemic to pre-pandemic periods <lb/>BSI pathogen <lb/>Community <lb/>Hospital <lb/>Long-term care <lb/>IRR a <lb/>95% CI b <lb/>IRR <lb/>95% CI <lb/>IRR <lb/>95% CI <lb/>S. pneumoniae <lb/>0.43 e <lb/>0.33-0.57 <lb/>-<lb/>c <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Group A Streptococcus <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.74-1.01 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Coagulase-negative staphylococci <lb/>1.18 <lb/>0.95-1.46 <lb/>1.24 d 1.03-1.48 -<lb/>-<lb/>S. aureus <lb/>0.91 d <lb/>0.84-0.99 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>0.90-1.15 1.06 <lb/>0.76-1.47 <lb/>Enterococcus spp. <lb/>1.05 <lb/>0.94-1.17 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>1.00-1.28 1.14 <lb/>0.74-1.77 <lb/>E. coli <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.89-1.09 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.85-1.08 0.70 d <lb/>0.52-0.92 <lb/>Klebsiella spp. <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.94-1.09 <lb/>1.17 <lb/>1.04-1.31 0.73 <lb/>0.50-1.07 <lb/>a Incidence rate ratio. <lb/>b 95% confidence interval. <lb/>c Analysis not conducted due to insufficient incidence rates. <lb/>d P value &lt; 0.05. <lb/>e P value &lt; 0.01. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<body>during the COVID-19 pandemic. Stratifying results by setting of blood culture collection <lb/>allowed for novel findings, including that community and hospitalized BSI rates were <lb/>differentially influenced by the pandemic and that the increase in contaminant rates <lb/>during the pandemic is largely attributable to those cultures performed in emergency <lb/>department or outpatient settings. The inclusion of data from 3 years of pre-pandemic <lb/>data allowed us to model each outcome to control for seasonal and temporal trends <lb/>present prior to the pandemic, which strengthens the validity of our findings given the <lb/>seasonal variation of bacterial infections. <lb/>Smaller cohort studies suggest that while contamination rates increased overall <lb/>during the pandemic (7, 8), the specific department implicated (ICU, inpatient, or <lb/>emergency department) varied by institution (13, 23, 24). Similarly, we observed a <lb/>disproportionate increase in blood cultures ordered in the hospital setting without <lb/>a change in the proportion of contaminants, whereas there was an increase in the <lb/>proportion of contaminated cultures in the LTC and community settings, including <lb/>from outpatient laboratories, emergency departments, and hospitals within 2 days of <lb/>admission. This may suggest that the various factors theorized to explain the increased <lb/>contaminant rates during the pandemic (new PPE protocols, increased workload, <lb/>reassignment of nursing staff to new units) have especially affected emergency <lb/>departments and ambulatory laboratories rather than admitted patients. Additionally, <lb/>certain pressures unique to the emergency department, including patient acuity, the <lb/>backlog of patients due to saturated wards, and the proportion of patients requiring PPE, <lb/>may have contributed (25). Given that contaminant blood cultures lead to unnecessary <lb/>empiric antimicrobial use, our findings demonstrate a potential underappreciated cost of <lb/>the pandemic to patients, including adverse drug events, antimicrobial resistance, and <lb/>length of stay (26). <lb/>We demonstrated no change in hospital-acquired BSI during the pandemic. While this <lb/>mirrors the findings of smaller studies (14, 27), most cohorts (13, 17, 18, 28, 29) have <lb/>reported an increase in hospital-acquired bacterial infections. While Ontario faced similar <lb/>pandemic-related factors as other settings, the decrease in patient volumes in our cohort <lb/>suggests that crowding may have had a lesser impact on BSI in our setting, which may <lb/>explain our findings. The increases in gram-positive infections likely relate to increased <lb/>line-associated infections in hospitals, which may have been balanced by a decreased <lb/>incidence of other nosocomial bacteremias, perhaps due to factors such as the delay of <lb/>elective surgeries. <lb/>The observed changes in the microbiology of BSI likely represent true epidemiologic <lb/>shifts during the pandemic. Decreased community-acquired S. pneumoniae infections <lb/>have been described in recent studies (30-32); we identified this same trend in addition <lb/>to a decline in S. aureus. These changes may be due to public health measures leading <lb/>to a decrease in both the community transmission of these pathogens and of respira <lb/>tory viruses such as influenza that can result in secondary bacterial pneumonia due <lb/>to these pathogens (33, 34). In support of this hypothesis, there has recently been an <lb/>increase in these pathogens attributed to the cessation of public health measures (35, <lb/>36). In the hospital setting, the pandemic was associated with an increase in CoNS <lb/>BSI. Similar trends have been reported in other studies (9, 37) and among SARS-CoV-2-<lb/>infected patients specifically (3, 4, 37), with explanations including the use of central <lb/>venous devices, increased line infections due to altered infection prevention protocols <lb/>to prevent staff exposure, and empiric use of antimicrobials in patients with COVID-19, <lb/>including third-generation cephalosporins, which may be selected for these organisms <lb/>(5, 9). <lb/>Community-and LTC-onset BSI decreased in our cohort. A proportion of this signal <lb/>represents a true decrease in the incidence of BSI due to reduced community transmis <lb/>sion. However, as a significant proportion of community-acquired BSI events involve <lb/>pathogens that are typically implicated in &quot;endogenous&quot; infectious disease syndromes <lb/>(e.g., urinary tract infection) not predominantly transmitted through person-to-person <lb/>contact, this finding may be attributable to under-detection due to reluctance to seek <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>9 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

		<body>care during the pandemic (38). Similarly, the decline in reported LTC-BSI, including <lb/>Gram-negative organisms such as E. coli, may be due to under-detection during the <lb/>early part of the pandemic as a result of well-documented challenges in meeting care <lb/>needs in Ontario LTCs during the early pandemic and directives to care for persons in the <lb/>community due to issues related to hospital capacity (39). <lb/>Certain limitations should be acknowledged. First, while patients with bacteremia <lb/>are typically quite unwell and seek medical attention, the incidence of positive blood <lb/>cultures would not have captured all true bacteremia episodes, especially as pandemic-<lb/>related factors may have prevented patients from accessing care and increased palliative <lb/>supports in LTCs that may have reduced transfers to acute care settings. Second, limiting <lb/>our analysis to blood culture data allowed us to generally discern true infection among <lb/>a large data set while avoiding contaminant bacteria from non-sterile cultures. However, <lb/>individual chart review is required to definitively discern infection from contaminants <lb/>even among blood cultures, and certain contaminant culture results may have been <lb/>misclassified as true BSI; this limitation also applies to our classification of persistent <lb/>and intermittent CoNS BSI. Furthermore, without other corresponding cultures, we were <lb/>unable to determine the diagnoses underlying BSI (e.g., S. pneumoniae BSI secondary <lb/>to meningitis vs pneumonia). Last, since our analysis was limited to the first year of <lb/>the pandemic, our findings do not represent the effects of more recent phases of the <lb/>pandemic. <lb/>Our findings serve to highlight certain future priorities. First, our findings related <lb/>to blood culture contamination emphasize the need for institution-level surveillance <lb/>and quality improvement initiatives, such as phlebotomy and central venous catheter <lb/>protocols, to monitor and prevent potentially harmful and costly consequences of care, <lb/>especially during times of healthcare and public health crises. Second, the potentially <lb/>undetected BSI in LTCs underscores the need for equitable healthcare to ensure that <lb/>vulnerable individuals are adequately cared for in a pandemic context. Last, the observed <lb/>changes in the microbiology and resistance profiles of BSI provide hypotheses for <lb/>prospective research to better characterize the modifiable factors in clinical care (e.g., <lb/>empiric antimicrobials) and infection prevention and control measures (e.g., isolation <lb/>procedures, room sharing) that may underlie our findings and how these can be <lb/>optimized in advance of future pandemics. <lb/>In summary, we found that pandemic-related factors led to changes in the detection, <lb/>incidence, and microbiology of BSI and that these effects differed by patient setting. <lb/>Future studies should aim to characterize the specific modifiable factors that underlie <lb/>the relationship between emerging viral pandemics and the ever-present challenges of <lb/>invasive bacterial infections and antimicrobial resistance. <lb/></body>

		<div type="acknowldgment">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>Parts of these materials are based on data and information compiled and provided by <lb/>the Ontario Ministry of Health (MOH), the Canadian Institute for Health Information <lb/>(CIHI), Ontario Health (OH), and the Ontario Ministry of Health. This document also used <lb/>data adapted from the Statistics Canada Postal CodeOM Conversion File, which is based <lb/>on data licensed from Canada Post Corporation, and/or data adapted from the Ontario <lb/>Ministry of Health Postal Code Conversion File, which contains data copied under license <lb/>from Canada Post Corporation and Statistics Canada. The analyses, conclusions, opinions, <lb/>and statements expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those <lb/>of the funding or data sources; no endorsement is intended or should be inferred. <lb/>This work was supported by the Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences (ICES), which <lb/>is funded by an annual grant from the Ontario Ministry of Health (MOH) and the Ministry <lb/>of Long-Term Care (MLTC). This work was also supported by the Ontario Health Data <lb/>Platform (OHDP), a Province of Ontario initiative to support Ontario&apos;s ongoing response <lb/>to COVID-19 and its related impacts. This study also received funding from the Cana <lb/>dian Institutes of Health Research. The analyses, conclusions, opinions, and statements <lb/>expressed herein are solely those of the authors and do not reflect those of the funding <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>10 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">or data sources; no endorsement by ICES, OHDP, the MOH, the MLTC, or CIHI is intended <lb/>or should be inferred. <lb/>All authors contributed to the study concept and design. M.D., D.M., and D.T. <lb/>performed the data analyses. M.D., D.M., and N.D. drafted the manuscript. All authors <lb/>contributed to the critical review of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<front>AUTHOR AFFILIATIONS <lb/>1 Department of Medicine, The University of Ottawa, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada <lb/>2 <lb/>Sunnybrook Health Sciences Centre, University of Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>3 ICES, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>4 <lb/>Public Health Ontario, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>5 Dalla Lana School of Public Health, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>6 The University Health Network, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>7 Institute of Medical Science, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>8 University of Waterloo, Waterloo, Ontario, Canada <lb/>9 Unity Health Toronto, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>10 Sinai Health System, Toronto, Ontario, Canada <lb/>11 The Ottawa Hospital Research Institute, Ottawa, Ontario, Canada <lb/>AUTHOR ORCIDs <lb/>Matt Driedger http://orcid.org/0000-0001-6921-4443 <lb/>Nick Daneman http://orcid.org/0000-0001-8827-3764 <lb/>Kevin Brown http://orcid.org/0000-0002-1483-2188 <lb/>Kevin L. Schwartz http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3666-7005 <lb/></front>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>Funder <lb/>Grant(s) Author(s) <lb/>Institute for Clinical Evaluative Sciences (ICES) <lb/>Derek MacFadden <lb/>Ontario Ministry of Health and Long-Term Care (MOHLTC) <lb/>Derek MacFadden <lb/>Ontario Health Data Platform <lb/>Derek MacFadden <lb/>Gouvernement du Canada | Canadian Institutes of Health <lb/>Research (IRSC) <lb/>Derek MacFadden <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Matt Driedger, Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Methodology, Writing <lb/>-original draft, Writing -review and editing | Nick Daneman, Conceptualization, <lb/>Supervision, Writing -review and editing | Kevin Brown, Conceptualization, Writing -<lb/>review and editing | Wayne L. Gold, Conceptualization, Writing -review and editing | <lb/>Sarah C.J. Jorgensen, Conceptualization, Writing -review and editing | Colleen Maxwell, <lb/>Conceptualization, Writing -review and editing | Kevin L. Schwartz, Conceptualization, <lb/>Writing -review and editing | Andrew M. Morris, Conceptualization, Writing -review and <lb/>editing | Deva Thiruchelvam, Conceptualization, Data curation, Formal analysis, Writing <lb/>-review and editing | Bradley Langford, Conceptualization, Writing -review and editing <lb/>| Elizabeth Leung, Conceptualization, Writing -review and editing | Derek MacFad <lb/>den, Conceptualization, Data curation, Methodology, Supervision, Writing -review and <lb/>editing <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY <lb/>Data was provided and stored by MOH and CIHI as above. The dataset from this study <lb/>is held securely in coded form at ICES. While legal data sharing agreements between <lb/>ICES and data providers (e.g., healthcare organizations and government) prohibit ICES <lb/>from making the dataset publicly available, access may be granted to those who meet <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>11 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<div type="availability">pre-specified criteria for confidential access, available at www.ices.on.ca/DAS (email: <lb/>das@ices.on.ca). The full dataset creation plan and underlying analytic code are available <lb/>from the authors upon request, understanding that the computer programs may rely <lb/>upon coding templates or macros that are unique to ICES and are therefore either <lb/>inaccessible or may require modification. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">ADDITIONAL FILES <lb/>The following material is available online. <lb/>Supplemental Material <lb/>Supplemental material (Spectrum02630-23-s0001.docx). Tables S1 to S4; Fig. S1 to S4. <lb/>Open Peer Review <lb/>PEER REVIEW HISTORY (review-history.pdf). An accounting of the reviewer comments <lb/>and feedback. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Langford BJ, So M, Raybardhan S, Leung V, Westwood D, MacFadden DR, <lb/>Soucy J-P, Daneman N. 2020. Bacterial co-infection and secondary <lb/>infection in patients with COVID-19: a living rapid review and meta-<lb/>analysis. Clin Microbiol Infect 26:1622-1629. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>cmi.2020.07.016 <lb/>2. <lb/>Rawson TM, Moore LSP, Zhu N, Ranganathan N, Skolimowska K, Gilchrist <lb/>M, Satta G, Cooke G, Holmes A. 2020. Bacterial and fungal coinfection in <lb/>individuals with coronavirus: a rapid review to support COVID-19 <lb/>antimicrobial prescribing. Clin Infect Dis 71:2459-2468. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1093/cid/ciaa530 <lb/>3. <lb/>Buetti N, Ruckly S, de Montmollin E, Reignier J, Terzi N, Cohen Y, Siami S, <lb/>Dupuis C, Timsit J-F. 2021. COVID-19 increased the risk of ICU-acquired <lb/>bloodstream infections: a case-cohort study from the multicentric <lb/>OUTCOMEREA network. Intensive Care Med 47:180-187. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1007/s00134-021-06346-w <lb/>4. <lb/>Puzniak L, Finelli L, Yu KC, Bauer KA, Moise P, De Anda C, Vankeepuram L, <lb/>Sepassi A, Gupta V. 2021. A multicenter analysis of the clinical <lb/>microbiology and antimicrobial usage in hospitalized patients in the US <lb/>with or without COVID-19. BMC Infect Dis 21. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s12879-021-05877-3 <lb/>5. <lb/>Langford BJ, So M, Raybardhan S, Leung V, Soucy J-P, Westwood D, <lb/>Daneman N, MacFadden DR. 2021. Antibiotic prescribing in patients <lb/>with COVID-19: rapid review and meta-analysis. Clin Microbiol Infect <lb/>27:520-531. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi.2020.12.018 <lb/>6. <lb/>Monnet DL, Harbarth S. 2020. Will Coronavirus disease (COVID-19) have <lb/>an impact on antimicrobial resistance? Euro Surveill. 25:2001886. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2020.25.45.2001886 <lb/>7. <lb/>Denny S, Rawson TM, Hart P, Satta G, Abdulaal A, Hughes S, Gilchrist M, <lb/>Mughal N, Moore LSP. 2021. Bacteraemia variation during the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic; a multi-centre UK secondary care ecological analysis. BMC <lb/>Infect Dis 21:556. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-021-06159-8 <lb/>8. <lb/>Yu D, Ininbergs K, Hedman K, Giske CG, Strålin K, Özenci V, Leekha S. <lb/>2020. Low prevalence of bloodstream infection and high blood culture <lb/>contamination rates in patients with COVID-19. PLoS ONE 15:e0242533. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0242533 <lb/>9. <lb/>Amarsy R, Trystram D, Cambau E, Monteil C, Fournier S, Oliary J, Junot H, <lb/>Sabatier P, Porcher R, Robert J, Jarlier V. 2022. Surging bloodstream <lb/>infections and antimicrobial resistance during the first wave of <lb/>COVID-19: a study in a large multihospital institution in the Paris region. <lb/>Int J Infect Dis 114:90-96. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijid.2021.10.034 <lb/>10. Zhu NJ, Rawson TM, Mookerjee S, Price JR, Davies F, Otter J, Aylin P, <lb/>Hope R, Gilchrist M, Shersing Y, Holmes A. 2022. Changing patterns of <lb/>bloodstream infections in the community and acute care across 2 <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019 epidemic waves: a retrospective analysis using <lb/>data linkage. Clinical Infectious Diseases 75:e1082-e1091. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1093/cid/ciab869 <lb/>11. Farfour E, Clichet V, Péan de Ponfilly G, Carbonnelle E, Vasse M. 2023. <lb/>Impact of COVID-19 pandemic on blood culture practices and <lb/>bacteremia epidemiology. Diagn Microbiol Infect Dis 107:116002. https:/ <lb/>/doi.org/10.1016/j.diagmicrobio.2023.116002 <lb/>12. Mitchell BG, Stewardson AJ, Kerr L, Ferguson JK, Curtis S, Busija L, <lb/>Lydeamore MJ, Graham K, Russo PL. 2023. The incidence of nosocomial <lb/>bloodstream infection and urinary tract infection in Australian hospitals <lb/>before and during the COVID-19 pandemic: an interrupted time series <lb/>study. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control 12:1-9. https://doi.org/10.1186/ <lb/>s13756-023-01268-2 <lb/>13. Damonti L, Kronenberg A, Marschall J, Jent P, Sommerstein R, De Kraker <lb/>MEA, Harbarth S, Gasser M, Buetti N. 2021. The effect of the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic on the epidemiology of positive blood cultures in Swiss <lb/>intensive care units: a nationwide surveillance study. Crit Care 25:403. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13054-021-03814-z <lb/>14. Geffers C, Schwab F, Behnke M, Gastmeier P. 2022. No increase of device <lb/>associated infections in German intensive care units during the start of <lb/>the COVID-19 pandemic in 2020. Antimicrob Resist Infect Control 11:1-7. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1186/s13756-022-01108-9 <lb/>15. Lee Y-M, Kim DY, Kim EJ, Park K-H, Lee MS. 2023. Impact of the <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019 pandemic on healthcare-associated infections <lb/>at intensive care units in South Korea: data from the Korean National <lb/>Healthcare-Associated Infections Surveillance System (KONIS). J Hosp <lb/>Infect 138:52-59. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhin.2023.05.010 <lb/>16. Lepape A, Machut A, Bretonnière C, Friggeri A, Vacheron C-H, Savey A, <lb/>REA-REZO network. 2023. Effect of SARS-CoV-2 infection and pandemic <lb/>period on healthcare-associated infections acquired in intensive care <lb/>units. Clin Microbiol Infect 29:530-536. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cmi. <lb/>2022.10.023 <lb/>17. Weiner-Lastinger LM, Pattabiraman V, Konnor RY, Patel PR, Wong E, Xu <lb/>SY, Smith B, Edwards JR, Dudeck MA. 2022. The impact of coronavirus <lb/>disease 2019 (COVID-19) on Healthcare-associated infections in 2020: a <lb/>summary of data reported to the national healthcare safety network. <lb/>Infect. Control Hosp. Epidemiol 43:12-25. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice. <lb/>2021.362 <lb/>18. Evans ME, Simbartl LA, Kralovic SM, Clifton M, DeRoos K, McCauley BP, <lb/>Gauldin N, Flarida LK, Gamage SD, Jones MM, Roselle GA. 2023. <lb/>Healthcare-associated infections in veterans affairs acute-care and long-<lb/>term healthcare facilities during the coronavirus disease 2019. Infect <lb/>Control Hosp Epidemiol 44:420-426. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice.2022.93 <lb/>19. Baker MA, Sands K, Huang SS, Kleinman K, Septimus E, Varma N, <lb/>Blanchard EJ, Poland R, Coady MH, Yokoe DS. n.d. 171, p S102-S103. In <lb/>The impact of COVID-19 on Healthcare-associated infections. Oxford <lb/>University Press US. <lb/>20. Bauer KA, Puzniak LA, Yu KC, Finelli L, Moise P, Ai C, Watts JA, Gupta V. <lb/>2022. Epidemiology and outcomes of culture-positive bloodstream <lb/>pathogens prior to and during the SARS-CoV-2 pandemic: a multicenter <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>12 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>evaluation. BMC Infect Dis 22:841. https://doi.org/10.1186/s12879-022-<lb/>07810-8 <lb/>21. Sturm LK, Saake K, Roberts PB, Masoudi FA, Fakih MG. 2022. Impact of <lb/>COVID-19 pandemic on hospital onset bloodstream infections (HOBSI) <lb/>at a large health system. Am J Infect Control 50:245-249. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.ajic.2021.12.018 <lb/>22. Ontario Go. 2004. Personal health information protection act. Available <lb/>from: https://www.ontario.ca/laws/statute/04p03 -BK5 <lb/>23. Ohki R, Fukui Y, Morishita N, Iwata K. 2021. Increase of blood culture <lb/>contamination during COVID-19 pandemic. a retrospective descriptive <lb/>study. Am J Infect Control 49:1359-1361. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic. <lb/>2021.08.025 <lb/>24. Sacchetti B, Travis J, Steed LL, Webb G. 2022. Effects of COVID-19 on <lb/>blood culture contamination at a tertiary care academic medical center. <lb/>Microbiol Spectr 10:e0027722. https://doi.org/10.1128/spectrum.00277-<lb/>22 <lb/>25. Lundgren G, Bengtsson M, Liebenhagen A. 2023. Swedish emergency <lb/>nurses&apos; experiences of the preconditions for the safe collection of blood <lb/>culture in the emergency department during the COVID-19 pandemic. <lb/>Nurs Open 10:1619-1628. https://doi.org/10.1002/nop2.1416 <lb/>26. Alahmadi YM, Aldeyab MA, McElnay JC, Scott MG, Darwish Elhajji FW, <lb/>Magee FA, Dowds M, Edwards C, Fullerton L, Tate A, Kearney MP. 2011. <lb/>Clinical and economic impact of contaminated blood cultures within the <lb/>hospital setting. J Hosp Infect 77:233-236. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jhin. <lb/>2010.09.033 <lb/>27. Mohammadi A, Khatami F, Azimbeik Z, Khajavi A, Aloosh M, Aghamir <lb/>SMK. 2022. Hospital-acquired infections in a tertiary hospital in Iran <lb/>before and during the COVID-19 pandemic. Wien Med Wochenschr <lb/>172:220-226. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10354-022-00918-1 <lb/>28. LeRose J, Sandhu A, Polistico J, Ellsworth J, Cranis M, Jabbo L, Cullen L, <lb/>Moshos J, Samavati L, Chopra T. 2021. The impact of coronavirus disease <lb/>2019 (COVID-19) response on central-line-associated bloodstream <lb/>infections and blood culture contamination rates at a tertiary-care <lb/>center in the greater detroit area. Infect Control Hosp Epidemiol 42:997-<lb/>1000. https://doi.org/10.1017/ice.2020.1335 <lb/>29. Halverson T, Mikolajczak A, Mora N, Silkaitis C, Stout S. 2022. Impact of <lb/>COVID-19 on hospital acquired infections. Am J Infect Control 50:831-<lb/>833. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ajic.2022.02.030 <lb/>30. Brueggemann AB, Jansen van Rensburg MJ, Shaw D, McCarthy ND, <lb/>Jolley KA, Maiden MCJ, van der Linden MPG, Amin-Chowdhury Z, <lb/>Bennett DE, Borrow R, et al. 2021. Changes in the incidence of invasive <lb/>disease due to Streptococcus pneumoniae, Haemophilus influenzae, and <lb/>Neisseria meningitidis during the COVID-19 pandemic in 26 countries <lb/>and territories in the invasive respiratory infection surveillance initiative: <lb/>a prospective analysis of surveillance data. Lancet Digit Health 3:e360-<lb/>e370. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2589-7500(21)00077-7 <lb/>31. Feldman I, Natsheh A, Nesher G, Breuer GS. 2022. Social distancing and <lb/>bacteraemia in the time of COVID-19. Intern Med J 52:223-227. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1111/imj.15560 <lb/>32. Lim RH, Chow A, Ho HJ. 2020. Decline in pneumococcal disease <lb/>incidence in the time of COVID-19 in Singapore. J Infect 81:e19-e21. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jinf.2020.08.020 <lb/>33. Rice TW, Rubinson L, Uyeki TM, Vaughn FL, John BB, Miller RR, Higgs E, <lb/>Randolph AG, Smoot BE, Thompson BT, NHLBI ARDS Network. 2012. <lb/>Critical illness from 2009 pandemic influenza A (H1N1) virus and <lb/>bacterial co-infection in the united States. Crit Care Med 40:1487-1498. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1097/CCM.0b013e3182416f23 <lb/>34. Rynda-Apple A, Robinson KM, Alcorn JF. 2015. Influenza and bacterial <lb/>superinfection: illuminating the immunologic mechanisms of disease. <lb/>Infect Immun 83:3764-3770. https://doi.org/10.1128/IAI.00298-15 <lb/>35. Perniciaro S, van der Linden M, Weinberger DM. 2022. Reemergence of <lb/>invasive pneumococcal disease in Germany during the spring and <lb/>summer of 2021. Clin Infect Dis 75:1149-1153. https://doi.org/10.1093/ <lb/>cid/ciac100 <lb/>36. Venkatesan P. 2023. Rise in group A streptococcal infections in England. <lb/>Lancet <lb/>Respir <lb/>Med <lb/>11:e16. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S2213--<lb/>2600(22)00507-0 <lb/>37. Bonazzetti C, Morena V, Giacomelli A, Oreni L, Casalini G, Galimberti LR, <lb/>Bolis M, Rimoldi M, Ballone E, Colombo R, Ridolfo AL, Antinori S. 2021. <lb/>Unexpectedly high frequency of enterococcal bloodstream infections in <lb/>coronavirus disease 2019 patients admitted to an Italian ICU: An <lb/>observational study. Crit Care Med 49:e31-e40. https://doi.org/10.1097/ <lb/>CCM.0000000000004748 <lb/>38. Blecker S, Jones SA, Petrilli CM, Admon AJ, Weerahandi H, Francois F, <lb/>Horwitz LI. 2021. Hospitalizations for chronic disease and acute <lb/>conditions in the time of COVID-19. JAMA Intern Med 181:269-271. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1001/jamainternmed.2020.3978 <lb/>39. Fisman DN, Bogoch I, Lapointe-Shaw L, McCready J, Tuite AR. 2020. Risk <lb/>factors associated with mortality among residents with coronavirus <lb/>disease 2019 (COVID-19) in long-term care facilities in Ontario. JAMA <lb/>Netw Open 3:e2015957. https://doi.org/10.1001/jamanetworkopen. <lb/>2020.15957 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Research Article <lb/>Microbiology Spectrum <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">November/December 2023 Volume 11 Issue 6 <lb/>10.1128/spectrum.02630-23</note>

		<page>13 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Downloaded from https://journals.asm.org/journal/spectrum on 10 October 2024 by 2a01:e0a:d12:4600:6f65:dae8:67:55e1. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
