<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>THE JOURNAL OF BIOLOGICAL CHEMISTRY <lb/>0 1989 by The American Society for Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, Inc <lb/>Vol. 264, No. 2, Issue of January 15, pp. 872-883,1989 <lb/>Printed in U S. A. <lb/>Structures of Neutral 0-Linked Polylactosaminoglycans on Human <lb/>Skim Milk Mucins <lb/>A NOVEL TYPE OF LINEARLY EXTENDED POLY-N-ACETYLLACTOSAMINE BACKBONES WITH <lb/>Galp( 1-4)GlcNAcp(1-6) REPEATING UNITS* <lb/>(Received for publication, May 5, 1988) <lb/>Franz-Georg Hanisch and Gerhard Uhlenbruck <lb/>From the Department of Immurwbiology, Medical University Clinic I of Cologne, Kerpener Strasse 15, <lb/>0-5000 Cologne 41, Federal Republic of Germany <lb/>Jasna Peter-Katalinic and Heinz Egge <lb/>From the Institute of Physiological Chemistry, University of Bonn, Nussallee 11, 0-5300 Bonn 1, Federal Republic of Germany <lb/>Janusz Dabrowski and Ursula Dabrowski <lb/>From the Max Planck Institute of Medical Research, Jahnstrasse 29,0-6900 Heidelberg, Federal Republic of Germany <lb/> 0-Linked oligosaccharides were isolated from hu-<lb/>man skim milk mucins and from mucin-derived gly-<lb/>copeptides by reductive &amp;elimination. The released <lb/>alditols were fractionated by DEAE-Sephadex chro-<lb/>matography and purified by high performance liquid <lb/>chromatography on primarj. amine bonded phase. The <lb/>structures of the major neutral oligosaccharide alditols <lb/>could be established by fast atom bombardment and <lb/>electron impact mass spectrometry, <lb/>combined with <lb/>methylation analysis, 500-MHz &apos;H nuclear magnetic <lb/>resonance spectroscopy, and endo-&amp;galactosidase <lb/>(from Bacteroides frugilis, EC 3.2.1.103) digestion <lb/>(where n = 0-3): <lb/>GaW 1 , <lb/>3) <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>Galfl(1-3/4)GlcNAcfl (1 <lb/>[\ 6)Galfl(l-4)GlcNAcfl ] ,(I 7) <lb/>Major 0-glycosidically linked oligosaccharides <lb/>on <lb/>skim milk mucins are of the Galj3(1-3)[GlcNAcfl(1-6)] <lb/>GalNAc core type 2 and exhibit linearly extended <lb/>backbone chains of the poly N-acetyllactosamine type <lb/>comprizing up to at least four repeating units, which <lb/>are linked by the hitherto unknown sequence GlcNAc-<lb/>j3(1-6) Gal rather than GlcNAcj3(1-3)Gal. A consid-<lb/>erable portion of neutral alditols is represented by <lb/>branched isomers of the linear species, which are dis-<lb/>tinguished by their content of 3,6-disubstituted galac-<lb/>tose and their partial resistance to endo-8-galactosid-<lb/>ase digestion. <lb/></front>

			<body>Oligosaccharides of the polylactosamine type have been <lb/>identified on glycoproteins and glycolipids expressing various <lb/>developmental and tumor-associated antigens (1, 2). On gly-<lb/></body>

			<front>* This investigation was supported by Deutsche Forschungsge-<lb/>meinschaft Grant Uh 8/14-2 and by the Fritz Thyssen Stiftung (to <lb/>J. D. and U. D.). The costs of publication of this article were defrayed <lb/>in part by the payment of page charges. This article must therefore <lb/>be hereby marked &quot;advertisement&quot; in accordance with 18 U.S.C. <lb/>Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact. <lb/></front>

			<body>coproteins these oligosaccharides are linked to <lb/>a (Man)a <lb/>(GlcNAc)Z1 core common to N-glycans and exhibit repetitive <lb/>Galpl-4GlcNAcpl-3 sequences comprizing up to six or more <lb/>units. Polyglycosyl chains (3) or polylactosaminoglycans (4) <lb/>have been described to occur on erythrocytes, (1,3) teratocar-<lb/>cinoma cells ( 5 ) , granulocytes (6), and pheochromocytoma <lb/>cells (7). Recently, immunochemical and enzymatic evidence <lb/>has been obtained for the occurrence of 0-glycosidically linked <lb/>polylactosaminoglycans on human leucocyte common antigen <lb/>(8). <lb/>This contribution presents chemical evidence for 0-linked <lb/>polylactosaminoglycans as major components of secreted mu-<lb/>cins in the fraction of human milk caseins. These mucins <lb/>have been described in a preceding paper to express tumor-<lb/>associated antigens Ca 19-9 and Ca 125 and to carry a series <lb/>of monosialylated oligosaccharides (9). <lb/>Similar mucin-type <lb/>glycoproteins have been demonstrated on a variety of human <lb/>(10) and animal mammary carcinoma cells (11). Expression <lb/>of these high molecular weight glycoproteins on plasma mem-<lb/>branes has been reported to be associated with the metastatic <lb/>phenotype of carcinoma cells (11), pointing to a possible <lb/>functional involvement of mucins in the metastatic process. <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES~ <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Isolation of Mucins and Mucin-derived Glycopeptides <lb/>Purification of mucins contained in the fraction of caseins <lb/>and their chemical and physicochemical characterization have <lb/>been described in a preceding paper (9). Structural informa-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">l The abbreviations used are: GlcNAc, N-acetylglucosamine; Fuc, <lb/>fucose; GalNAc, N-acetylgalactosamine; FAB-MS, fast atom bom-<lb/>bardment mass spectrometry; EI-MS, electron impact mass spec-<lb/>trometry; HPLC, high performance liquid chromatography; Hex, <lb/>hexose; HexNAc, N-acetylhexosamine; &apos;H NMR, proton nuclear mag-<lb/>netic resonance; D l andD2, one-dimensional and two-dimensional; <lb/>COSY, two-dimensional correlated spectroscopy. <lb/>* Portions of this paper (including &quot;Experimental Procedures,&quot; <lb/>Tables 1-3, and 7, and additional references 1-6) are presented in <lb/>miniprint at the end of this paper. Miniprint is easily read with the <lb/>aid of a standard magnifying glass. Full size photocopies are included <lb/>in the microfilm edition of the Journal that is <lb/>available from Waverly <lb/>Press. <lb/></note>

			<page>872 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans o n <lb/>H u m a n <lb/>Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<page>873 <lb/></page>

			<body>tion of relevance with regard to the present contribution came <lb/>from compositional analyses suggesting that the high molec-<lb/>ular weight glycoproteins, excluded from Sephacryl S400 in <lb/>the presence of 4 M guanidinium chloride and designated as <lb/>mucins, were actually devoid of D-mannOSe. The total yield <lb/>of mucins calculated for 1 liter of human milk was 70 mg. <lb/>Isolation of mucin-derived glycopeptides (250 mg) from a <lb/>Pronase digest of crude human casein was achieved by phenol, <lb/>6 M urea extraction. The crude glycopeptide mixture was <lb/>further fractionated by gel exclusion chromatography on Bio-<lb/>Gel P-30 as shown in Fig. 1. Monosaccharide analyses of <lb/>fractions A-D revealed only traces of D-mannose on large <lb/>glycopeptides (fraction A), whereas a considerable content of <lb/>D-mannose was measured in fractions C and D indicating N -<lb/>glycan carrying glycopeptides, which may have originated <lb/>from contaminating whey glycoproteins (Table 1). Large gly-<lb/>copeptides in fraction A (50 mg) or mucins were subjected to <lb/>alkaline borohydride treatment. <lb/>0.8-<lb/>04 -<lb/>0.4. <lb/>0.2-<lb/>0 <lb/>U <lb/>C <lb/>$ <lb/>$ 10&apos; <lb/>0.5. <lb/>i&quot;&quot;&quot; <lb/>I <lb/>b <lb/>+e <lb/>30 <lb/>3 100 <lb/>fraction number <lb/>FIG. 1. Gel exclusion chromatography of mucin (a) and mu-<lb/>cin-derived glycopeptides (b) on Sephacryl S400 (a) or Bio-<lb/>Gel P-30 (b). a, phenol/saline-extracted glycoproteins from skim <lb/>milk (1 g) were applied onto a column of Sephacryl S400 (2.5 X 100 <lb/>ern) equilibrated and run in 4 M guanidinium chloride, 1 mM sodium <lb/>phosphate, pH 7.0, 1 mM Nag-EDTA. Elution was performed with a <lb/>flow rate of 24 rnI/h. 4-ml fractions were collected and analyzed <lb/>spectrophotometrically at 280 nm. b, phenol/urea-extractedglycopep-<lb/>tides from milk caseins (30 mg) were applied onto a column of Bio-<lb/>Gel P-30 (2.2 X 80 cm) equilibrated and run in 0.01 M pyridine <lb/>acetate, pH 5.0. Elution was performed with a flow rate of 24 ml/h <lb/>and 3-ml fractions were collected. Fractions were analyzed by the <lb/>thiobarbituric acid method for their content of sialic acid (absorbance <lb/>at 549 nm, 0 ) or by enzyme immunoassay of 5 0 -~l aliquots using <lb/>monoclonal antibodies 115C2 (absorbance at 405 nm, 0) or Leu M1 <lb/>(absorbance at.405 nm, . . . .). <lb/>Immunochemical Characterization of Carbohydrate Antigens <lb/>Expressed on Mucins or Mucin-derived Glycopeptides <lb/>Antigen patterns on mucins and mucin-derived glycopep-<lb/>tides were analyzed using a series of monoclonal antibodies <lb/>with defined carbohydrate epitopes in enzyme assays or radio-<lb/>immunoassays (Table 2). Fractionation of Pronase-stable gly-<lb/>copeptides on Bio-Gel P-30 was registered by measuring an-<lb/>tigen activities Le&quot;-X or X, respectively: <lb/>GalP(1-3)GlcNAcfl(l-3)Gal~(1-4)GlcNAc <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Fuca <lb/>Fuca <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>defined by monoclonal antibody 115 C2, and <lb/>Galfl(1-4)GlcNAc <lb/>3 <lb/>I <lb/>1 <lb/>Fuca <lb/>defined by monoclonal antibody Leu M1. <lb/>The activity profiles in Fig. 1 suggest that both isomeric <lb/>terminal sequences are coexpressed and restricted to large <lb/>glycopeptides contained in fraction A. Le*-X distribution on <lb/>large and smaller-sized glycopeptides may represent 0-glycan <lb/>elution, since this hybrid of type 1-and type 2-based struc-<lb/>tures has never been found to occur on N-glycans but is a <lb/>regular constituent of secreted mucins and mucin-derived <lb/>oligosaccharide alditols3 (19). Concerning the latter, 2 pg of <lb/>fractions MM-MS or MM-DS (see &quot;Experimental Proce-<lb/>dures&quot;) compared with 10 pg of fraction MM-N were able to <lb/>inhibit 50% of 115 C2 binding in enzyme immunoassay. <lb/>Milk mucins and mucin-derived glycopeptides, moreover, <lb/>exhibit antigen activities T (defined by antibody 49H8), H2 <lb/>(defined by antibody A46-B/B10), sialyl-Le&quot; (defined by an-<lb/>tibody NS 19-9) and Lea, Leb (defined by antibodies Le&quot; 01 or <lb/>Leb 01, respectively). Antigen sialyl dimeric X (defined <lb/>by <lb/>monoclonal antibody FH6) was not detectable on mucin-0-<lb/>glycans. <lb/>Human breast carcinoma-associated antigens <lb/>MCA (20) <lb/>(&gt;50 units/mg) and Ca 15-3 (21) (230 units/mg) are coex-<lb/>pressed on skim milk mucins together with the previously <lb/>detected tumor markers Ca 19-9 and Ca 125 (9). <lb/>Neutral Oligosaccharides from Milk Mucins and Mucin-<lb/>derived, Large Glycopeptides <lb/>0-glycan liberation from mucins or glycopeptides by alka-<lb/>line reductive treatment provided a mixture of oligosaccharide <lb/>alditols, which was fractionated by ion-exchange chromatog-<lb/>raphy on DEAE-Sephadex A25 followed by high performance <lb/>liquid chromatography on primary amine bonded phase (Fig. <lb/>2). Independent of the source, neutral alditols representing <lb/>-50% of total carbohydrates released from large glycopeptides <lb/>or mucins (20-30 mg) comprized a t least 30 different species <lb/>ranging in size from 2 to 16 monosaccharides. Major compo-<lb/>nents were nonfucosylated species resistant to mild trichlo-<lb/>roacetic acid treatment, which eluted in fractions MM-N4, <lb/>MM-N6, MM-N8, MM-N10, and MM-Nl2. As judged from <lb/>the HPLC profiles the molar proportions estimated for each <lb/>component contained in the fraction of neutral alditols were <lb/>similar for mucin-and glycopeptide-derived oligosaccharides <lb/>(Table 3 and Fig. 2). <lb/>F.-G. Hanisch and G. Uhlenbruck, unpublished results. <lb/></body>

			<page>874 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<body>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>retention <lb/>t i m e (rnin) <lb/>FIG. 2. High performance liquid chromatography of mucin <lb/>(a)-or glycopeptide (b)-derived oligosaccharide alditols. 1 mg <lb/>of neutral saccharide alditols (fraction MM-N) were applied onto a <lb/>column of primary amine bonded silica (0.46 X 25 cm). Carbohydrates <lb/>were eluted at a flow rate of 1 ml/min with acetonitril/water using a <lb/>gradient of 7/3 up to 1/4 (v/v). Eluting carbohydrates were registered <lb/>tions MM-N1 to MM-NI4. <lb/>spectrophotometrically at 192 nm. Peak numbers 1-14 refer to frac-<lb/>Structural Analysis of Oligosaccharide Alditols <lb/>The freeze-dried saccharide alditols from each HPLC frac-<lb/>tion were divided into three portions. Part of the saccharide <lb/>alditols was permethylated and subjected to FAB-or EI-mass <lb/>spectrometry followed by methylation analysis. Another por-<lb/>tion was digested with endo-/3-galactosidase prior to per-<lb/>acetylation of the reaction products and FAB-MS analysis. A <lb/>third portion of underivatized alditols was used for &apos;H NMR <lb/>analysis. Since the structures of the major components in <lb/>each fraction turned out to be identical for the mucin-and <lb/>glycopeptide-derived alditols, but on the other hand, a consid-<lb/>erable heterogeneity of minor components became evident <lb/>particularly for the glycopeptide derived fractions, the pre-<lb/>sented structural data are confined to mucin-derived O-gly-<lb/>cans. <lb/>Fraction MM-Ri4-FAB-mass spectrometry of permethyl-<lb/>ated oligosaccharide alditols in fraction MM-N4 revealed the <lb/>presence of one major species being represented by the pseu-<lb/>domolecular ion M + H at m/z 961 (Table 4). In accordance <lb/>with data from a monosaccharide analysis (Table l), this <lb/>pseudomolecular ion corresponds to a tetrasaccharide com-<lb/>posed of GalzGlcNAcGalNAc-01. Sequence analysis by EI-<lb/>mass spectrometry suggested the structural elements Hex-<lb/>HexNAc (represented at m/z 219, 464) and Hex-HexNAc-ol <lb/>TABLE 4 <lb/>Pseudomolecular ions from positive ion FAB-MS annlysis and <lb/>compositional assignment for permethylated oligosaccharide alditols <lb/>Pseudomolecular <lb/>Fraction <lb/>ions <lb/>Compositional <lb/>assignment <lb/>M + H <lb/>( M + N a ) <lb/>MM-N4 <lb/>MM-NG <lb/>MM-N7 <lb/>MM-N8 <lb/>MM-N9 <lb/>MM-NLO <lb/>MM-NI1 <lb/>MM-N12 <lb/>961 <lb/>1135 <lb/>1410 <lb/>1584 <lb/>1655 <lb/>1859 <lb/>2033 <lb/>2104 <lb/>2308 <lb/>2033 <lb/>2207 <lb/>2482 <lb/>2553 <lb/>2207 <lb/>2757 <lb/>2656 <lb/>2381 <lb/>(983) <lb/>(1157) <lb/>(1432) <lb/>(1606) <lb/>(1677) <lb/>(1881) <lb/>(2055) <lb/>(2126) <lb/>(2330) <lb/>(2055) <lb/>(2229) <lb/>(2504) <lb/>(2575) <lb/>(2229) <lb/>(2779) <lb/>(2678) <lb/>(2403) <lb/>(HexzHexNAcz)-ol <lb/>(dHexHexZHexNAcz)-ol <lb/>(HexaHexNAc3)-ol <lb/>(dHexHex3HexNAc3)-01 <lb/>(Hex3HexNAc4)-ol <lb/>(Hex4HexNAc4)-ol <lb/>(dHexHex4HexNAc4)-ol <lb/>(Hex4HexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(HexsHexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(dHexHex4HexNAc4)-ol <lb/>(dHex2Hex4HexNAc4)-01 <lb/>(dHexHe%HexNAc5)-ol <lb/>(Hex5HexNAce)-ol <lb/>(dHex2Hex4HexNAc4)-ol <lb/>(HexsHexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(dHex2Hex5HexNAc5)-01 <lb/>(dHex3HexrHexNAc4)-01 <lb/>~~ <lb/>Pseudomolecular <lb/>ion <lb/>(M + Na) <lb/>Fraction <lb/>Compositional <lb/>assignment <lb/>MM-NI3 <lb/>2575 <lb/>2749 <lb/>2852 <lb/>2953 <lb/>3024 <lb/>3127 <lb/>3301 <lb/>3402 <lb/>3473 <lb/>3576 <lb/>3677 <lb/>MM-NI4 <lb/>3228 <lb/>(Hex5HexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(dHexHex5HexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(dHex3HexsHexNAc5)-01 <lb/>(dHexHe&amp;HexNAc6)-ol <lb/>(He%HexNAc7)-ol <lb/>(dHex2Hex6HexNAce)-o1 <lb/>(Hex7HexNAc7)-ol <lb/>(dHex3He~~.HexNAc~)-ol <lb/>(dHexHex7HexNAc7)-ol <lb/>(Hex,HexNAca)-ol <lb/>(dHex2Hex7HexNAc7)-01 <lb/>(HexsHexNAc6)-ol <lb/>~~ <lb/>(represented at m/z 219, 480) and a branched core structure <lb/>at the terminal HexNAc-ol, indicated by a series of alditol <lb/>fragments at m/z 378, 422 and 538, 582). <lb/>187 <lb/>CHzOCH3 <lb/>219 <lb/>T <lb/>I p H 3 <lb/>&apos; I <lb/>&apos; <lb/>I <lb/>&quot; _ &quot; 378 <lb/>CHNCOCH3 <lb/>HEX-0-CH <lb/>1 <lb/>CHOCH, <lb/>582 <lb/>1 <lb/>422 <lb/>1 <lb/>CHOCHs <lb/>538 <lb/>HEX-+O-~-HEXNACLO-~H~ <lb/>1 <lb/>J 1 <lb/>219 ) <lb/>187 <lb/>432 <lb/>182 <lb/>11 <lb/>4 6 4 1 <lb/>480 <lb/>The branching pattern at the alditol terminus is also cor-<lb/>roborated by formation of 1,4,5-tri-O-methyl-N-methylacet-<lb/>amido-2-deoxygalactitol in methylation analysis (Table 6), <lb/>which confirms a substitution of the GalNAc-ol residue in <lb/>positions 0-3 and 0-6. The partially methylated GlcNAc <lb/>derivative 3,6-di-O-methyl-N-methylacetamid0-2-deoxy-<lb/>glucitol and the fragment ions registered in EI-mass spectrom-<lb/>etry at m/z 182 (22) and 432 (23) are indicative of a 4-<lb/>substituted hexosamine. The above presented results may be <lb/>summarized in the following structure model for the major <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<page>875 <lb/></page>

			<body>component in <lb/>fraction <lb/>MM-N4: <lb/>the formation of pseudomolecular ions M + H at m/z 1410 or <lb/>M + Na at m/z 1432, respectively (Fig. 3a and Table 4), <lb/>indicating a hexasaccharide of the general composition <lb/>(HexBHexNAca)-ol and corresponding to Ga13GlcNAc2Gal-<lb/>NAc-ol according to monosaccharide analysis. The major <lb/>/ <lb/>signals in the region of molecular ions are accompanied by a <lb/>series of primary fragment ions at m/z 464 and 913, which <lb/>A minor component in fraction M&quot;N4 is represented in the are presumed to be derived from a linear tetrasaccharide <lb/>FAB spectrum by the pseudomolecular ion M + H at m/z sequence of the general structure Hex-HexNAc-Hex-HexNAc <lb/>1135 corresponding to (dHexHexzHexNAc2)-01 or Fuc-(Fig. 3a). This sequence is corroborated by hydrolytic frag-<lb/>GalzGlcNAcGalNAc-ol (Tables 1 and 4). <lb/>ments Hex2HexNAc and (HexHexNAc2)-01 formed on endo-<lb/>Fraction MM-N6-On FAB-mass spectrometry permethyl-P-galactosidase digestion of MM-N6 oligosaccharides (Table <lb/>ated oligosaccharide. alditols in fraction MM-N6 gave rise to 5). <lb/>Gal(1, <lb/>3) <lb/>6) <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l <lb/>&apos;Ooo a <lb/>-<lb/>800-<lb/>&gt; <lb/>t. <lb/>m <lb/>-<lb/>z <lb/>W <lb/>c <lb/>5 600-<lb/>I <lb/>voo <lb/>2olh I BO <lb/>3: 28 <lb/>26m <lb/>I <lb/>300 <lb/>9 00 <lb/>x 2 <lb/>H2C-O-CH3 <lb/>, <lb/>HC-N-CO-CH3 <lb/>I <lb/>/ <lb/>I , c n 3 <lb/>/ <lb/>I <lb/>Hex-O-CH <lb/>CH -0-C <lb/>I <lb/>_(&quot;&quot;&quot;_ <lb/>-J <lb/>3 _,&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; <lb/>2 <lb/>( 3 7 8 ) <lb/>( 4 2 2 ) <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I 7-0-cH3 <lb/>Iiex-O-HexNAc-O-Hex-O-HexNAc-O-CH2 <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>464, <lb/>91 3 <lb/>I <lb/>432 <lb/>228 <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>La&apos; <lb/>1632 <lb/>91 3 <lb/>MAS5 PER CHARGE <lb/>IL /&apos; IO <lb/>nt <lb/>I <lb/>I*I&apos; <lb/>&apos; i <lb/>&quot; 5 <lb/>. IO <lb/>E . = , <lb/>0. <lb/>464 <lb/>913 <lb/>136.3 J <lb/>1111 J <lb/>/ \ <lb/>43.3 <lb/>111 <lb/>FIG. 3. Positive ion FAB-mass spectra of permethylated saccharide alditols. a, fraction MM-N6; b, <lb/>fraction MM-N&amp; c, fraction MM-NlO. For details refer to &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot; Structural assignments of <lb/>fragment ions are given in the figures. Fragment ions in brackets refer to signals registered in EI-mass spectrometry. <lb/></body>

			<page>876 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<body>TABLE 5 <lb/>Pseudomolecular ions of peracetylated oligosaccharide fragments obtained on endo-0-galactosidase digestion of <lb/>nonfucosylated wlvlactosamine alditols <lb/>Reducing fragments <lb/>~~ <lb/>Alditol fragments <lb/>HPLC <lb/>Pseudomolecular <lb/>fraction <lb/>Pseudomolecular <lb/>ions <lb/>Compositional <lb/>ions <lb/>Compositional <lb/>assignment <lb/>M + H <lb/>(M + Na) <lb/>M + H <lb/>(M + Na) <lb/>assignment <lb/>MM-N6 <lb/>966 <lb/>(988) <lb/>HexzHexNAc <lb/>1009 <lb/>(1031) <lb/>(HexHexNAcz)-ol <lb/>MM-N8 <lb/>1541 <lb/>(1563) <lb/>HexsHexNAcz <lb/>1009 <lb/>(1031) <lb/>966 <lb/>(988) <lb/>Hex2HexNAc <lb/>1584 <lb/>(1606) <lb/>(Hex2HexNAc3)-ol <lb/>(HexHexNAcz)-ol <lb/>2116 <lb/>(2138) <lb/>Hex4HexNAca <lb/>1009 <lb/>(1031) <lb/>(HexHexNAc2)-01 <lb/>1541 <lb/>(1563) <lb/>Hex3HexNAc2 <lb/>1584 <lb/>( 1606) <lb/>966 <lb/>(HexzHexNAc3)-ol <lb/>(988) <lb/>HexzHexNAc <lb/>2159 <lb/>(2181) <lb/>(Hex3HexNAcr)-ol <lb/>MM-NlO <lb/>The secondary fragments at m/z 432 (464-methanol) and <lb/>228 (464-hexose1, which are formed by preferential elimina-<lb/>tion of the 0-3-linked HexNAc substituent (23), could point <lb/>to the presence of two molecular species with isomeric ter-<lb/>minal sequences Hex(1-4)HexNAc and Hex( 1-3)HexNAc, <lb/>respectively. Methylation analysis confirmed the presence of <lb/>both GlcNAc substitution isomers 3,6-di-O-methyl-N-meth-<lb/>ylacetamido-2-deoxyglucitol and 4,6-di-O-methyl-N-methyl-<lb/>acetamido-2-deoxyglucitol (Table 6). Branching at the ter-<lb/>minal alditol is revealed by formation of 1,4,5-tri-O-methyl-<lb/>N-methylacetamido-2-deoxygalactitol and by the absence of <lb/>the primary fragment ion at m/z 276 in the El-mass spectrum. <lb/>6-Mono-0-substitution of internal galactose is indicated by <lb/>2,3,4-tri-O-methy1-1,5,6-tri-O-acetyl galactitol formed on <lb/>methylation analysis as the only tri-0-acetylated hexitol (Ta-<lb/>ble 6 and Fig. 6). Approximately 30% of the internal galactose <lb/>was represented by 2,4-di-O-methyl galactitol acetate, point-<lb/>ing to the occurrence of a branch point in a second major <lb/>alditol species, which may also contain an incomplete side <lb/>chain terminating in nonreducing GlcNAc (Table 6). Based <lb/>on the above-presented combined data, the primary structure <lb/>of the major saccharide alditol in MM-N6 is proposed as: <lb/>Gal(1, <lb/>3) <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc(l, <lb/>6) <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>G)Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l&apos; <lb/>Fraction MM-N8&quot;The major oligosaccharide alditol in <lb/>permethylated fraction MM-N8 is characterized by the pseu-<lb/>domolecular ions M + H at m/z 1859 and M + Na at mlz <lb/>1881 in FAB-mass spectrometry (Fig. 2; and Table 4) and <lb/>with reference to a monosaccharide analysis is calculated to <lb/>have the composition Ga14GlcNAc3GalNAc-01. Fragmentation <lb/>of the oligosaccharide alditol revealed the primary ion series <lb/>at m/z 464, 913, and 1362, suggesting the presence of three <lb/>repetitive, linearly linked Hex-HexNAc units (Fig. 3b). Lin-<lb/>earity of the hexasaccharide sequence of one of the major <lb/>species is corroborated by a set of corresponding fragments <lb/>obtained on endo-P-galactosidase digestion and peracetylation <lb/>of the reaction mixture: Hex3HexNAct and (HexHexNAcd-<lb/>01 or HexnHexNAc and (HexzHexNAc&amp;ol (Table 5 ) . A con-<lb/>siderable portion of alditols in M&quot;N8 <lb/>was resistant to en-<lb/>zymatic cleavage. <lb/>The intense fragment ions registered at m/z 432 (464-<lb/>methanol) and 228 (464-hexose) are presumably derived by <lb/>elimination of 03-linked substituents from the penultimate <lb/>GlcNAc (23) and may be interpreted in terms of a heteroge-<lb/>neity with respect to the substitution pattern of this residue. <lb/>This heterogeneity becomes also obvious on methylation <lb/>analysis, which revealed a formation of isomeric GlcNAc <lb/>TABLE 6 <lb/>Methylation analysis of oligosaccharide alditols <lb/>Values represent molar proportions relative to 1,4,5-tri-O-methyl-<lb/>N-methylacetamido-2-deoxygalactitol= 1. <lb/>Partially methylated <lb/>alditol <lb/>MM-N4 MM-N6 MM-N8 MM-N10 <lb/>Fucitol <lb/>Galactitol <lb/>2,3,4-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Trace <lb/>0.4 <lb/>2,3,4,6-Tetra-O-rnethyl <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>2,3,6-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>0.3 <lb/>3,4,6-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>0.3 <lb/>2,3,4-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>2,4-Di-O-methyl <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>2-N-Methylacetamido 2-<lb/>deoxygalactitol <lb/>1,4,5,6-Tetra-O-methyl <lb/>0.3 <lb/>1,4,5-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2-N-Methylacetamido 2-<lb/>deoxyglucitol <lb/>3,4,6-Tri-O-methyl <lb/>0.5 <lb/>Trace <lb/>3,6-Di-O-methyl <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>4,6-Di-O-methyl <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>6-Mono-0-methyl <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>derivatives 3,6 di-0-methyl-N-methylacetamido-2-deoxyglu-<lb/>citol and 4,6 di-0-methyl-N-methylacetamido-2-deoxyglucitol <lb/>in approximate molar proportions 311. The core structure of <lb/>the saccharide could be deduced from the partially methylated <lb/>GalNAc-ol derivative 1,4,5-tri-0-methyl-N-methylacetam-<lb/>ido-2-deoxygalactitol (Table 6). Approximately 60% of inter-<lb/>nal galactose residues is represented by the 6-mono-0-substi-<lb/>tuted derivative, and the remainder, by 3,6-di-O-substituted <lb/>galactose. This suggests that a considerable portion of fraction <lb/>MM-N8 alditols is branched. The presented data can be <lb/>summarized in the tentative structural model postulated for <lb/>the major component in fraction MM-N8 (refer also to &apos;H <lb/>NMR data in Table 8). <lb/>Gal(1, <lb/>3) <lb/>[ &apos;6)Gal(l-4)GlcNAc] 1 1 2 &apos; <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc (1 <lb/>STRUCTURE^ <lb/>There is only a limited number of structural alternatives of <lb/>the linear species (Structure 1) in MM-N8. Only one (Struc-<lb/>ture 2 ) partially fits the data from FAB-MS (primary frag-<lb/>ment ions at m/z 464 and 1362), methylation analysis (3,6 di-<lb/>0-substituted galactose), and endo-&amp;galactosidase digestion <lb/>(hydrolytic resistance) and is in accordance with &apos;H chemical <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<page>877 <lb/></page>

			<body>shifts measured in NMR spectroscopy (Table 8). <lb/>Gal(1, <lb/>3) <lb/>Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l 2 ) <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc(l, <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>6) <lb/>Gal(l-B/4)GlcNAc(l <lb/>/3&apos; <lb/>STRUCTURE 2 <lb/>Fraction MM-NIO-FAB-mass spectrometry of this per-<lb/>methylated fraction revealed the presence of three molecular <lb/>species represented by the respective pseudomolecular ions M <lb/>+ H at m/z 2308, 2033, and 2207, respectively (Fig. 3c and <lb/>Table 4). Based on mass increment calculation and monomer <lb/>analysis, the major component of this fraction is a decasac-<lb/>charide alditol composed of Ga16GlcNAc4GalNAc-ol (Table <lb/>1). Sequence analysis revealed a series of primary fragments <lb/>at m/z 464, 913, 1362, and 1811 which are compatible with a <lb/>linear octasaccharide sequence consisting of repetitive Hex-<lb/>HexNAc units (Fig. 3c). A branch point within this sequence <lb/>can be excluded at least for a major portion of the nonfuco-<lb/>Although a trisaccharide fragment dHex-Hex-HexNAc has sylated species on the basis of endo-@-galactosidase digestion <lb/>been registered in FAB-MS at m/z 638, a corresponding and FAB-MS analysis of the peracetylated products (Table 5 <lb/>pseudomolecular ion could not be detected in the high mass and Fig. 4). The respective enzyme from Bacteroides fragilis <lb/>range. <lb/>cleaved the nonfucosylated alditol at three <lb/>distinct <lb/>points <lb/>TABLE 8 <lb/>&apos; H chemical shifts for the dominant components of oligosaccharitols MM-N4, -N6, and -N8 <lb/>Chemical shifts are relative to acetone set equal to 2.225 ppm. The formula given in the caption refers to MM-<lb/>N8, ;.e. the IV and V units are lacking for MM-N6 and so are the IV-VI1 units for MM-N4. <lb/>VI1 <lb/>VI <lb/>V <lb/>IV <lb/>111 <lb/>I1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Substance Protons <lb/>ture <lb/>Tempera-GalP(I-3) GlcNAcP(1-6) [GalP(1-4) GlcNAcB(l-6)] GalP(1-4) GlcNAcP (I+)GalNAc-ol <lb/>v111 <lb/>-<lb/>Gal@( 1-3) <lb/>&quot;K <lb/>MM-N4 <lb/>H-1 <lb/>293 <lb/>4.472 <lb/>4.557 <lb/>4.462 <lb/>3.738; <lb/>3790 <lb/>H-2 <lb/>3.535 <lb/>3.760 <lb/>3.564 4.401 <lb/>H-3 <lb/>3.666 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>3.670 4.060 <lb/>H-4 <lb/>3.921 <lb/>3.715 <lb/>3.895 <lb/>3.455 <lb/>H-5 <lb/>3.586 <lb/>H-6 <lb/>H-6&apos; <lb/>4.287 <lb/>3.679 <lb/>MM-NG <lb/>H-1 <lb/>293 <lb/>4.697 <lb/>4.471 <lb/>4.555 <lb/>4.465 3.73; 3.79 4.453 <lb/>3.933 <lb/>H-2 <lb/>3.527 <lb/>3.90 <lb/>3.535 <lb/>3.75 <lb/>3.561 4.404 <lb/>H-3 <lb/>3.647 <lb/>H-4 <lb/>H-5 <lb/>3.56 <lb/>H-6 <lb/>H-6&apos; <lb/>3.830 <lb/>3.998 <lb/>3.670 <lb/>3.71 <lb/>3.675 4.065 <lb/>3.910 <lb/>3.922 <lb/>3.71 <lb/>3.895 3.448 <lb/>4.286 <lb/>3.83 <lb/>3.68 <lb/>4.00 <lb/>3.93 <lb/>H-1 <lb/>278 <lb/>4.45 <lb/>4.670 <lb/>4.47 <lb/>4.589 <lb/>H-2 <lb/>4.47 <lb/>4.546 <lb/>4.46 <lb/>3.75 <lb/>3.51 <lb/>3.914 <lb/>3.53 <lb/>H-3 <lb/>3.757 <lb/>3.65 <lb/>3.53 <lb/>3.757 <lb/>3.54 <lb/>4.42 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>3.67 <lb/>4.07 <lb/>H-4 <lb/>3.90 <lb/>3.915 <lb/>3.915 <lb/>3.72 <lb/>3.89 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>H-5 <lb/>3.60 <lb/>H-6 <lb/>4.28 <lb/>H-6&apos; <lb/>3.84 <lb/>4.00 <lb/>3.94 <lb/>MM-N8 <lb/>H-1 <lb/>293 <lb/>4.45 <lb/>4.694 <lb/>4.468 <lb/>4.593 <lb/>4.468 <lb/>4.554 <lb/>4.46 <lb/>9 8 8 <lb/>2 1 8 1 <lb/>2 1 3 8 <lb/>l o l l <lb/>6 a 1 <lb/>MASS PER CHAPGE <lb/>FIG. 4. Positive ion FAB-mass spectrum of peracetylated fraction MM-N10 after endo-b-galactosid-<lb/>m e digestion. For details refer to &quot;Experimental Procedures.&quot; Structural assignments of pseudomolecular ions <lb/>M + Na are given in Table 5. Pseudomolecular ions derived from the nonfucosylated species are rendered <lb/>prominent by bold letters. <lb/></body>

			<page>878 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on <lb/>Human <lb/>Milk <lb/>Mucins <lb/></note>

			<body>with formation of reducing fragments Hex2HexNAc,Hexs-<lb/>HexNAcn and HeaHexNAc3 and the corresponding alditol <lb/>fragments (Hex3HexNAc4)-ol,(Hex2HexNAc3)-ol, and <lb/>(HexHexNAcz)-01. <lb/>Gal <lb/>\ <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>/ <lb/>Gal-GlcNAc-Gal GlcNAc-Gal GlcNAc-Gal <lb/>GlcNAc <lb/>t <lb/>3 <lb/>M + Na 9&amp;2181 <lb/>1563 A 1606 <lb/>Also in this fraction, approximately 50% of the alditols was <lb/>found to be resistant to endo-@-galactosidase digestion. <lb/>Alditol fragmentation in EI-mass spectrometry giving rise <lb/>to ions at m/z 378 and 422 (refer to MM-N4) and data from <lb/>methylation analysis (Table 6) confirmed a branched core <lb/>structure identical with that established for oligosaccharide <lb/>alditols in fractions MM-N4, MM-N6, and MM-N8. As pre-<lb/>viously observed for the hexa-and octasaccharides in fractions <lb/>MM-N6 or MM-N8, a heterogeneity with respect to the <lb/>substitution of subterminal GlcNAc became also evident for <lb/>the decasaccharide on methylation analysis (Table 6) com-<lb/>bined with analysis of secondary fragments (m/z 228, 432 <lb/>presumably derived from the ion at m/z 464) formed on FAB-<lb/>mass spectrometry (Fig. 3c). 6-Mono-0-substituted and 3,6-<lb/>di-0-substituted galactose were represented by the respective <lb/>partially methylated alditol acetates in the approximate molar <lb/>proportions 2/1, indicating the presence of branched isomers. <lb/>The following structure can be assigned to a major component <lb/>A <lb/>8 <lb/>! <lb/>9 <lb/>w &quot; 9 <lb/>I <lb/>C <lb/>c+o&quot;o.D 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>&quot; <lb/>&quot; <lb/>J <lb/>&quot;A <lb/>O -&quot; + d <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>FIG. 5. Proposed biosynthetic pathways of mucin-0-gly-<lb/>cans. A, major neutral oligosaccharides synthesized preferentially on <lb/>mucins of human seminal plasma; B, major neutral and acidic oligo-<lb/>saccharides common to seminal plasma and milk mucins; C, major <lb/>neutral polylactosaminoglycans synthesized on mucins <lb/>of human <lb/>milk; Explanation of symbols used e, N-acetylgalactosamine; 0, N-<lb/>acetylglucosamine; O, galactose; A, fucose; A, N-acetylneuraminic <lb/>acid. <lb/>100 -I <lb/>HCHOCOCH, <lb/>-1 .&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;__ <lb/>129 <lb/>. I . . . <lb/>&quot; _ . <lb/>.&quot;!&lt; <lb/>CHOCH, <lb/>277 <lb/>I <lb/>CH,OHC <lb/>233 <lb/>.l. <lb/>0 <lb/>u <lb/>-1-. ~ . . . . &apos; 0 &apos; <lb/>189 <lb/>C <lb/>CH,OHC -1-. . . -. . -2% <lb/>0 <lb/>-c <lb/>3 <lb/>I <lb/>n <lb/>0 <lb/>117 <lb/>cnococn, <lb/>HCHOCOCH, <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>m l z <lb/>FIG. 6. EI-mass spectrum of 2,3,4 tri-0-methyl galactitol acetate <lb/>formed in methylation analysis <lb/>of fraction MM-N10: <lb/>G a l 0 <lb/>&apos; <lb/>3) <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc (1, <lb/>[ 6)Gal(l-4)GlcNAc 3(1 <lb/>] 7 ) <lb/>I <lb/>Also in this fraction a considerable portion of&apos; nonfucosylated <lb/>decasaccharides is represented by branched isomers of the <lb/>linear species with the possible structures <lb/>endo-@-galactosidase <lb/>Gal(\ <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc(l, <lb/>3) <lb/>6)Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l, <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>6) <lb/>3) <lb/>Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l <lb/>9&apos; <lb/>Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(l&apos; <lb/>and <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc(l <lb/>Gal(1, <lb/>6) <lb/>3) <lb/>GalNAc-ol <lb/>Gal(l-4)GlcNAc(1, <lb/>3) <lb/>?) <lb/>Gal(l-3/4)GlcNAc(i <lb/>G ) G S~(~-~) C~C N A C (~ <lb/>f <lb/>endo-@-galactosidase <lb/>Both structures are expected to be susceptible to endo-@-<lb/>galactosidase digestion at internal galactose residues indicated <lb/>by arrows, but should not yield hydrolytic fragments <lb/>HexaHexNAc2 and (Hex2HexNAc3)-ol due to the established <lb/>enzymatic resistance of disubstituted galactose residues (24). <lb/>The minor components of fraction MM-N10 represent h-<lb/>cosylated species containing one (M + H at m/z 2033) or two <lb/>(M + H at m/z 2207) deoxyhexose residues and being derived <lb/>from an octasaccharide alditol of the composition GaLGlc-<lb/>NAc3GalNAc-01 (Table 4 and Fig. 3c). <lb/>Fractions MM-N7, -9, -11, -12, -13, and -14-These frac-<lb/>tions represent heterogeneous mixtures of fucosylated and <lb/>nonfucosylated species as may be inferred from the pseudo-<lb/>molecular ions presented in Table 4. Although conclusive data <lb/>on the component alditols could not be obtained and definite <lb/>structural assignments were impossible, some of their struc-<lb/>tural.aspects may be summarized. <lb/>The nonfucosylated species in these fractions comprize up <lb/>to 16 monosaccharide units, which on the basis of composi-<lb/>tional analyses and FAB-MS fragmentation (homologous se-<lb/>ries of intense signals differing by the mass increment of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on <lb/>Human <lb/>Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<page>879 <lb/></page>

			<body>HexHexNAc) are presumably arranged in polylactosamine-<lb/>type chains. <lb/>Special attention should be focused on the fucosylated <lb/>species contained in fractions MM-N7 <lb/>to MM-N14 with <lb/>respect to their fucosylation patterns (Table 7). Since the <lb/>alditols had been isolated from pooled milk samples of indi-<lb/>viduals with undefined secretory status and Lewis blood <lb/>groups, substitution of terminal Gal@(l-3/4)GlcNAc should <lb/>reflect the genetic distribution of Se and Le genes. Accord-<lb/>ingly, the primary fragment ion at m/z 638, detected in <lb/>fractions MM-N9 to MM-N14, represents terminal trisaccha-<lb/>ride dHexHexHexNAc, a major portion being assumed to <lb/>contain the structural element Fuca(l-2)Gal, as normally <lb/>found in secretors. <lb/>Pseudomolecular ions and primary fragment ions in FAB-<lb/>MS corroborated the presence of mono-, di-, and trifuco-<lb/>sylated oligosaccharide alditols (Tables 4 and 7). Based on <lb/>the respective series of primary fragment ions, the possible <lb/>sites of fucosylation along the polylactosamine chain are <lb/>shown in Table 7. <lb/>&apos;H NMR Spectroscopy <lb/>Fractions MM-N4, -N6, and -N8 were analyzed by one-<lb/>111 1 <lb/>h <lb/>h <lb/>Vlll 1 <lb/>and two-dimensional &apos;H NMR spectroscopy at 500 MHz (Fig. <lb/>7 and Table 8). The GalNAc-01-1 resonances for these three <lb/>fractions are almost identical and differ only little from those <lb/>assigned by Mutsaers et al. (25) for a GalNAc-ol residue <lb/>having the same proximal environment. The 2 terminal Gal <lb/>residues linked to different aglycons show slightly different <lb/>Hl-H2-H3-H4 connectivity paths in the two-dimensional <lb/>spectrum of MM-N4. All Gal and GlcNAc residues have a 0 <lb/>configuration, as follows from their 3J1,2 coupling constants <lb/>The substitution patterns of Gal and GlcNAc residues in <lb/>MM-N6 and -N8 were elucidated with the aid of the previ-<lb/>ously established regularities concerning glycosylation-in-<lb/>duced shifts. It was observed (26, 27) that glycosylation in-<lb/>duces marked downfield shifts for the protons at the substi-<lb/>tution site and at both vicinal sites, but leaves other proton <lb/>resonances much less, or not at all, affected. This was recently <lb/>confirmed by the data reported by Baumann et al. (28). <lb/>Consequently, since the chemical shifts of Gal-I11 H2, H3, <lb/>and H4 are practically identical for MM-N4, -N6, and -N8, <lb/>these protons are obviously located at hydroxylated carbons, <lb/>which means that C6 must be glycosylated (the same refers <lb/>to Gal-V of MM-N8). However, as pointed out in the discus-<lb/>of 7.5-9.5 HZ. <lb/>FIG. 7. The 500-MHz &apos;H NMR <lb/>spectra of the oligosaccharide aldi-<lb/>to1 MM-N4. a, partial one-dimensional <lb/>spectrum. Arabic numerak denote the <lb/>proton position in a given sugar residue <lb/>specified by a Roman numeral (see for-<lb/>mula in Table 8). b, &apos;H shift-autocorre-<lb/>lated two-dimensional NMR spectrum <lb/>(COSY). Labeling as in a, but super-<lb/>scripts and subscripts refer to connectiv-<lb/>ities between two coupled protons. The <lb/>chemical shift of the proton labeled by a <lb/>superscript should be read on the hori-<lb/>zontal scale (up) and the shift of the <lb/>proton marked with a subscript is de-<lb/>fined by the vertical scale (ul). To avoid <lb/>crowding, only one cross-peak from each <lb/>pair is labeled, either above or below the <lb/>diagonal. <lb/>(b) COSY <lb/>6sa <lb/>14 <lb/>Og <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>15 <lb/></body>

			<page>880 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-O-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<body>sion of the data on MS and methylation analysis, the samples <lb/>were heterogeneous, and the 2,4-di-O-methyl galactitol found <lb/>for both MM-N6 and -N8 (Table 6) requires that about 10% <lb/>of Gal residues present in the samples are 3,6-diglycosylated. <lb/>This, in turn, would require that Gal H4 signal be shifted <lb/>from the 3.92 ppm into the 4.13-4.15 ppm region, where H4 <lb/>resonances of 3,6-diglycosylated Gal residues have been found <lb/>for oligosaccharides obtained from human <lb/>milk (29) and <lb/>erythrocytes (30) and that Gal H3 signal be shifted to 3.72 <lb/>ppm, as shown in Ref. 29. As a matter of fact, a very weak <lb/>cross-peak at 4.14/3.73 ppm was found in the COSY spectrum <lb/>of MM-N6, but in that of MM-N8, the corresponding contour <lb/>was barely above the noise level. Due to the small amount of <lb/>the substances investigated (see &quot;Experimental Procedures&quot;), <lb/>it is not unexpected that the proof of 10% of a constituent of <lb/>a microheterogeneous system may be problematic. <lb/>Concerning the 3 uersus 4 linkage to a GlcNAc residue, it <lb/>is the H2 resonance which is diagnostic, since in the former <lb/>case it should be shifted toward lower field due to the neigh-<lb/>borhood of the glycosylated C3. In the COSY spectrum of <lb/>MM-N6 (Table 8), one of the two GlcNAc H2 resonances is <lb/>practically identical with that found for MM-N4 (3.75 uersus <lb/>3.760 ppm), whereas the other one is shifted <lb/>by 0.15 ppm <lb/>toward lower field (to 3.90 ppm), pointing to a 1-3 terminal <lb/>linkage. Again, this is confirmed by the data on several human <lb/>milk oligosaccharides (29), whose GlcNAc H2 resonances were <lb/>found a t 3.76 and 3.88-3.90 ppm for the Galp(1-4)GlcNAc <lb/>and Galp( l-3)GlcNAc fragments, respectively, and also by <lb/>the results obtained for glycopeptides derived from calf fe-<lb/>tuin, whose corresponding GlcNAc H2 chemical shifts were <lb/>3.79 uersus 3.89 ppm (27). The GlcNAc H2/H1 correlations <lb/>of MM-N6 were found at almost identical shifts for MM-N8, <lb/>but, in addition, the <lb/>high field H2 resonance exhibited a <lb/>correlation to a new H 1 resonance (3.757/4.589 ppm) of one <lb/>proton intensity, thus showing that the molecule contains one <lb/>more internal Galp(1-4)GlcNAc disaccharide unit. The above <lb/>analysis applies to the main component of each of the three <lb/>fractions investigated. However, due to the heterogeneity of <lb/>the samples, a number of minor NMR signals occur along <lb/>with those referring to the dominant component. One <lb/>of these <lb/>weak signals in the one-dimensional spectrum of MM-N6 (at <lb/>4.605 ppm; not mentioned in Table 8) is probably due to a <lb/>-25% admixture of molecules containing a terminal Galp <lb/>(l-4)GlcNAc disaccharide fragment. In the two-dimensional <lb/>spectrum, a H1/H2 cross-peak at 4.57/3.67 ppm points to <lb/>some admixture of species containing terminal GlcNAc resi-<lb/>dues. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This study presents structural evidence for the organ char-<lb/>acteristic expression of highly clustered O-glycosidically <lb/>linked polylactosaminoglycans on mucins of human skim <lb/>milk. These mucins had <lb/>previously been demonstrated to <lb/>carry oncofetal carbohydrate antigens Ca 19-9 and Ca 125 (9) <lb/>and are presumed to be related antigenically and structurally <lb/>to a high molecular weight membrane glycoprotein isolated <lb/>from human milk fat globules3 (31). Similar mucin-like gly-<lb/>coproteins on human milk fat globule membranes have been <lb/>reported by Shimizu and Yamaguchi (32), Ormerod et at. (33), <lb/>and Krohn et al. (34), who also demonstrated an antigenic <lb/>relationship to secreted <lb/>mucins or high molecular weight <lb/>glycoproteins of skim milk (33, 34). As human milk fat glob-<lb/>ular membranes originate from the apical cell membrane of <lb/>milk-secreting cells, these soluble mucins of skim milk may <lb/>serve as a model for studies on organ-characteristic O-glycan <lb/>structure and biosynthesis in mammary epithelial cells. <lb/>The mucins of human skim milk have previously been <lb/>shown to precipitate with the casein fraction at pH 4.6 and <lb/>to contain -70% of mannose-free, alkali-labile carbohydrates <lb/>(9). Large glycopeptides with clustered <lb/>O-glycans could be <lb/>separated from a Pronase digest of crude caseins exhibiting <lb/>the same pattern of carbohydrate antigens and reductively <lb/>cleaved oligosaccharide alditols as skim milk mucins. The 0-<lb/>glycans characterized in this study are definitely not derived <lb/>from K-casein, as may be argued, since this highly glycosylated <lb/>glycoprotein of human casein could be separated from the <lb/>mucins according to its size (9) and has been demonstrated <lb/>to be devoid of antigenic activities Ca 19-9, Ca 125, and Ca <lb/>15-3 (9).3 Moreover, O-glycans of human K-casein have been <lb/>studied by JollGs and co-workers (35, 3G), who could charac-<lb/>terize a series of smaller-sized oligosaccharides. Despite this, <lb/>there is evidently also no relation to secretory immunoglob-<lb/>ulin A contained in human whey (37, 38) or to proteoglycans <lb/>secreted by mammary epithelial cells (39). On the other hand, <lb/>O-glycans with repetitive lactosamine exceeding 3 units, <lb/>which accordingly may be designated as polylactosaminogly-<lb/>cans, have not been described so far on a chemical basis, <lb/>whether in human milk nor in any other source of human or <lb/>animal origin. Childs et at. (8), however, have demonstrated <lb/>polylactosamino-O-glycans to occur on human leucocyte com-<lb/>mon antigen, and Fukuda et al. (40) were able to chemically <lb/>characterize minor O-linked oligosaccharides with repetitive <lb/>lactosamine (up to 3 units) on normal human granulocytes. <lb/>In a recent publication Wu et al. (41) described a sulfated <lb/>polysaccharide of high molecular weight <lb/>O-glycosidically <lb/>linked to an ovarian cyst glycoprotein, which proved to be <lb/>related to highly branched polylactosamines. <lb/>The unique structural aspects of major polylactosamino-0-<lb/>glycans on skim milk mucins may be summarized as follows: <lb/>1) the carbohydrate chains <lb/>comprize up to 16 (or more) <lb/>monosaccharide units; 2) the core structures are of the com-<lb/>mon type 2 Gal~(l-3)[GlcNAc~(l-6)]GalNAc; 3) the polylac-<lb/>tosamine sequence of major species is unbranched; 4) the <lb/>repetitive N-acetyllactosamine units are linearly linked via <lb/>0 -6 of the galactose residues; and 5 ) another major portion of <lb/>polylactosamine sequences is branched via 3,6 di-O-substi-<lb/>tuted galactose. <lb/>The structural aspects stated <lb/>in points 3 and 4 are of <lb/>considerable interest with respect to the biosynthesis and <lb/>immunochemistry of polylactosamine-type carbohydrates. As <lb/>has been pointed out by Schachter (42), the known p6 GlcNAc <lb/>transferases responsible for synthesis of mucin core types 2 <lb/>and 4 and the branch point of the blood group I determinant <lb/>require an 0-3 substitution of their target sugar. Taking this <lb/>into account, the P3GlcNAc transferase (&quot;extension enzyme&quot;) <lb/>would have to act before the P6-GlcNAc transferase (&quot;branch-<lb/>ing enzyme&quot;) (43). <lb/>Accordingly, unbranched carbohydrate <lb/>chains of the polylactosamine type, as described in the present <lb/>paper, exhibiting 6-mono-0-substitution of internal galactose <lb/>residues are hardly to be expected as regular biosynthetic <lb/>products, if the &quot;3 before 6 rule&quot; is of general validity. Core <lb/>oligosaccharides with the <lb/>common structural element <lb/>GlcNAcp( l-G)GalNAc-ol have been described recently to oc-<lb/>cur on human glycoproteins from meconium, K-casein, and <lb/>seminal plasma (44,35, 45) pointing to the possible existence <lb/>of a p6GlcNAc transferase in human tissues, which is inde-<lb/>pendent from 0 -3 substitution of its target sugars GalNAc or <lb/>Gal, respectively. <lb/>Cold agglutinins of the anti-I,i family have been demon-<lb/>strated to define polylactosamine sequences with <lb/>branched <lb/>(I-antigen) or linearly extented backbones (i-antigen) (46). <lb/>Reactivity of anti-I or anti-i antibodies with the novel type of <lb/>backbone structure exhibiting unbranched polylactosamine <lb/>sequences with a structural element of branched chains re-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosarnino-0-glycans on <lb/>Human <lb/>Milk <lb/>Mucins <lb/></note>

			<page>881 <lb/></page>

			<body>mains to be investigated. <lb/>A comparison of the major oligosaccharides found on mu-<lb/>cins from seminal plasma and skim milk reveals that the <lb/>former are represented by short carbohydrate chains (di-to <lb/>hexasaccharides) with prominent fucosylated or sialylated <lb/>species (45, 47) (Fig. 5 ) . This is in accordance with the high <lb/>activities of fucosykransferases and, to a lesser extent, of <lb/>sialyltransferases, measured in human seminal plasma (48), <lb/>which block chain elongation mainly on the tetrasaccharide <lb/>level. Milk mucin-producing cells on the other hand probably <lb/>exhibit high activities of a P6-GlcNAc transferase, thus pro-<lb/>ducing long carbohydrate chains of the polylactosamine type, <lb/>which may later become fucosylated or sialylated to a minor <lb/>extent. <lb/>Several biological functions of these polylactosamine-ex-<lb/>pressing mucins in human milk may be postulated, particu-<lb/>larly a protective role within the digestive tract of the newborn <lb/>infants. Mucins have been reported to stimulate lysozyme <lb/>activity (49), to enhance the growth of Bifidus flora in the <lb/>intestine (49), and to bind pathogenic microorganisms via <lb/>their surface l e c t i n~.~ <lb/>Coexpression of human cancer antigens MCA (20) and Ca <lb/>15-3 (21) on skim milk mucins of lactating women and their <lb/>detection in the sera of patients suffering from metastatic <lb/>breast carcinoma suggests that the respective carbohydrate <lb/>sequences belong to the family of oncodevelopmental antigens <lb/>and that they may be located on members of the mucin-0-<lb/>glycan series characterized in this study. A possible functional <lb/>role of 1,i-active polylactosamine-0-glycans on skim milk <lb/>mucins with regard to the metastatic process of epithelial <lb/>mammary tumors directed to the human liver is currently <lb/>under investigation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments-We are obliged to Prof. Dr. A. Bolte, University <lb/>Clinic of Gynecology and Obstetrics, Cologne, for providing the <lb/>samples of human milk, Prof. Dr. M. Donike and Dr. W. Schantzer <lb/>for kind support by gas-liquid chromatography-mass spectrometry, <lb/>and G. Stellbrinck and C. Bottinger for their skillful technical assist-<lb/>ance. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Fukuda, M. (1985) Biochim. Biophys. Acta 780, 119-150 <lb/>2. Feizi, T., Gooi, H. C., Childs, R. A., Pickard, J. K., Uemura, K., <lb/>Loomes, L. M., Thorpe, S. J., and Hounsell, E. F. (1984) <lb/>Biochem. SOC. Trans. 12,591-596 <lb/>3. Jarnefelt, J., Rush, J., Li, Y.-T., and Laine, R. A. (1978) J. Biol. <lb/>Chem. 253,8006-8009 <lb/>4. Fukuda, M., Fukuda, M. N., Papayonnopoulou, T., and Hako-<lb/>mori, S. (1980) Proc. Natl. Acud. Sci. U. S. A. 77, 3474-3478 <lb/>5. Muramatsu, H., Muramatsu, T., and Avner, P. (1984) Cancer <lb/>Res. 4 2 , 1744-1752 <lb/>6. Spooncer, E., Fukuda, M., Klock, 3. C., Oates, J. E., and Dell, A. <lb/>(1984) J. Bid. Chem. 259,4792-4801 <lb/>7. Margolis, R. K., <lb/>Greene, L. A., and Margolis, R. U. (1986) <lb/>Biochemistry 2 5 , 3463-3468 <lb/>8. Childs, R. A., Dalchau, R., Scudder, P., Hounsell, E. A., Fabre, J. <lb/>W., and Feizi, T. (1983) Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 1 1 0 , <lb/>9. Hanisch, F.-G., Uhlenbruck, G., Dienst, C., Stottrop, M., and <lb/>10. Johnson, V. G., Schlom, J., Paterson, A. J., Bennett, T., Magnani, <lb/>11. Steck, P. A., North, S. M., and Nicolson, G. (1987) Biochem. J. <lb/>12. Hanisch, F.-G., Uhlenbruck, G., and Dienst, C. (1984) Eur. J. <lb/>Biochem. 1 4 4 , 467-474 <lb/>13. Voller, A., Bidwell, D., and Barlett, A. (1976) in Manual of Clinical <lb/>Immunology (Rose, M. P., and Friedmann, H., eds) pp. 506-<lb/>512, American Society of Microbiology, Washington, DX. <lb/>424-431 <lb/>Hippauf, E. (1985) Eur. J. Biochem. 149, 323-330 <lb/>J. L., and Colcher, D. (1986) Cancer Res. 46,850-857 <lb/>242,779-787 <lb/>14. Hakomori, S. (1964) J. Biochem. (Tokyo) 55, 205-208 <lb/>15. Stellner, K., Saito, H., and Hakomori, S. (1973) Arch. Biochem. <lb/>16. Chaplin, M. F. (1982) Anal. Biochem. 123, 336-341 <lb/>Biophys. 155,464-472 <lb/>17. Paz-Parente, J., Strecker, G., Monteuil, J., and Fournet, B. (1983) <lb/>18. Aue, W. P., Bartholdi, E., and Ernst, R. R. (1976) J. Chem. Phys. <lb/>19. Hanisch, F.-G., Uhlenbruck, G., Peter-Katalinic, J., and Egge, H. <lb/>20. Staehli, C. (1985) Experientia 4 1 , 1377-1380 <lb/>21. Hilkens, J., Kroezen. V.. Bonfrer. J. M. G.. Brunine. P. F.. <lb/>FEBS Lett. 156,357-362 <lb/>64,2229-2246 <lb/>(1988) Carbohydr. Res. 178, 29-47 <lb/>22. <lb/>23. <lb/>24. <lb/>25. <lb/>26. <lb/>27. <lb/>28. <lb/>29. <lb/>30. <lb/>31. <lb/>32. <lb/>33. <lb/>34. <lb/>35. <lb/>36. <lb/>37. <lb/>38. <lb/>39. <lb/>40. <lb/>41. <lb/>42. <lb/>43. <lb/>44. <lb/>45. <lb/>46. <lb/>47. <lb/>48. <lb/>49. <lb/>Hilgers, J., and van Eijkeren, M. (1984) in Protides of the <lb/>BiologicalFluids (Peters, H., ed) Vol. 32, pp. 651-654, Pergamon <lb/>Press, New York <lb/>Smith, E. L., McKibbin, J. M., Karlsson, K.-A., Pascher, J., and <lb/>Samuelsson, B. E. (1975) Biochemistry 1 4 , 2120-2124 <lb/>Egge, H., and Peter-Katalinic, J. (1987) Moss Spectrom. Reu. 6, <lb/>Scudder, P., Hanfland, P., Uemura, K.-J., and Feizi, T. (1984) J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 259,6586-6592 <lb/>Mutsaers, J. H. G. M., Van Halbeek, H., Vliegenthardt, J. F. G., <lb/>Wu, A. M., and Kabat, E. A. (1986) Eur. J. Biochem. 157, <lb/>Dabrowski, J., Hanfland, P., and Egge, H. (1982) Methods En-<lb/>zymol. 8 3 , 69-86; and references cited therein <lb/>Berman, E., Dabrowski, U., and Dabrowski, J. (1988) Carbohydr. <lb/>Res. 1 7 6 , 1-15 <lb/>Baumann, H., Jansson, P.-E., and Kenne, L. (1988) J. Chem. <lb/>SOC. Perkin Trans. I, 209-217 <lb/>Kocis, P., Dabrowski, U., Dabrowski, J., Dreyer, S., Hergersberg, <lb/>M., Peter-Katalinic, J., and Egge, H. (1987) 4th European <lb/>Carbohydrate Symposium, Darmstadt (Lichtenthaler F. W., <lb/>and Neff, K. H., eds) C-54, Gesellschaft Deutscher Chemiker, <lb/>July 12-17, 1987, Frankfurt <lb/>Hounsell, E. F., Feeney, J., and Scudder, P. (1988) Biochem. J. <lb/>Fischer, J., Klein, P.-J., Farrar, G., Hanisch, F.-G., and Uhlen-<lb/>Shimizu, M., and Yamaguchi, K. (1982) J. Biochern. (Tokyo) 9 1 , <lb/>Ormerod, M. G., Steele, K., Westwood, J. H., and Mazzini, M. N. <lb/>Krohn, K., Ashorn, R., and Helle, M. (1985) Tumour Biol. 6 , 13-<lb/>331-393 <lb/>139-146 <lb/>250,9-13 <lb/>bruck, G. (1984) Biochem. J. 2 2 4 , 581-589 <lb/>515-524 <lb/>(1983) Br. J. Cancer 48, 533-541 <lb/>23 <lb/>vanHalbeek, H., Vliegenthart, J. F. G., Fiat, A. M., and Jolks, <lb/>P. (1985) FEBS Lett. 187.81-88 <lb/>Saito, T., Hoh, T., and Adachi, S. (1988) Biochim. Biophys. Acta <lb/>Pierce-Cretel, A., Pamblanco, M., Strecker, G., Montreuil, J., and <lb/>Spik, G. (1981) Eur. J. Biochem. 114,169-178 <lb/>Pierce-Cretel, A., Decottignies, J. P., Wieruszeski, J. M., Strecker, <lb/>G., Montreuil, J., and Spik, G. (1987) in Proceedings of the 9th <lb/>International Symposium on Glycoconjugates, Lille, pp. A l l 0 <lb/>July 6-11, 1987, A. Lerouge, Toarcoing <lb/>Gowda, D. C., Bhavanandan, V. P., and Davidson, E. A. (1986) <lb/>J. Biol. Chem. 261,4935-4939 <lb/>Fukuda, M., Carlsson, S. R., Klock, C., and Dell, A. (1986) J. <lb/>Biol. Chem. 2 6 1 , 12796-12806 <lb/>Wu, S.-S., Lee, A. C., and Bush, C. A. (1987) Biochim. Biophys. <lb/>Acta 924,420-431 <lb/>Schachter, H. (1986) Biochem. Cell Biol. 64, 163-181 <lb/>Piller, F., Cartron, J.-P., Maranduba, A., Veyrieres, A., Leroy, Y., <lb/>and Fournet, B. (1984) J. Biol. Chem. 2 5 9 , 13385-13390 <lb/>Hounsell, E. F., Lawson, A. M., Feeney, J., Gooi, H. C., Pickering, <lb/>N. J., Stoll, M. S., Lui, S. C., and Feizi, T. (1985) Eur. J. <lb/>Biochem. 148, 367-377 <lb/>Hanisch, F.-G., Egge, H., Peter-Katalinic, J., and Uhlenbruck, G. <lb/>(1986) Eur. J. Biochem. 155, 239-247 <lb/>Feizi, T., Gooi, H. C., Childs, R. A., Picard, J. K., Uemura, K., <lb/>Loomes, L. M., Thorpe, S. J., and Hounsell, E. F. (1984) <lb/>Biochem. SOC. Trans. 12,591-596 <lb/>Hanisch, F.-G., Egge, H., <lb/>Peter-Katalinic, J., Uhlenbruck, G., <lb/>Dienst, C., and Fangmann, R. (1985) Eur. J . Biochem. 152, <lb/>Ronquist, G., and Stegmeyer, B. (1983) Int. J. Fertil. 28, 239-<lb/>964,213-220 <lb/>343-351 <lb/>242 <lb/>Minagawa, K. (1968) Nippon Syonikagaku Kaishi (in Japanese) <lb/>72,1324-1333 <lb/>Additional references are found on p. 882. <lb/>Continued on next page. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>882 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">supp1smsnt.1 <lb/>Material to <lb/>STRUCTURES OF NKUTRAL 0-LINKKD POLYLACTOSMINOOLYCANS ON HUUAU SKIM MILK UIICINS <lb/>A NOVEL TYPE OF LINEARLY EXTENDED POLY-N-ACETYL-LACTOSMTNB BACNBONES WITH <lb/>Gal 11-4~GlcNAc11-6J RKPEATING UNITS <lb/>Franr-G. Hanisch. Gerhard Uhlenbruck. <lb/>Jaana Peter-Katalinio, Hainz Egge <lb/>J.nusz DabrO*ski and Ursula Dabrorski <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES <lb/>The samples were repeatedly exchanged with D.0 with intermediate lyophili-<lb/>&apos;H-NnRsDectroscopy <lb/>which was vSed a s internal reference (6 2.225 sf all t e m~e r a t w e~&gt; . <lb/>The =once&quot;-<lb/>zatlon. and then dissolved in 0.3 ml of 010 containing a trace of acetone, <lb/>tratlon was &lt; 3 mn for M W N 4 and &apos;0.4 nul for W -N 6 and -NE. The upper Concen-<lb/>tration llrnit was calculllted for t h e gross weight Of the samples. but s t o w <lb/>signals of a HPLC carrier in their MIR Spectra (particularly in that of M&quot;N8I <lb/>All spectra were obtained af 293&apos;K <lb/>(in the case of 1&quot;NB also at 278+Ll and 500 <lb/>point to W C h lower net concentrations. <lb/>MHz with e Bruker An-500 spectrometer equipped with an Aspect 3000 cornpurer and <lb/>an array proce5901-, using Bruker standard software. For rerolurian enhancement <lb/>of the 1D Spectra. the free inducing d e m y s were multiplied by the Lorentrian-<lb/>~a v a r i a n rransfornarion function. scalar autocorrelated <lb/>20 ~p e c f r a IcOsYl (181 <lb/>were recorded with the 90-tl-90-tr pulse SeQUence with two-level HDO DYPPres-<lb/>aion. The <lb/>time 1nterV.1 <lb/>berueen rubsequent BequencieD Y~I I 2 3. The spectral <lb/>width YBS 1872 Hz in both dimensions and the spectral sire in the time domain <lb/>was 1K X 256. Far each tl, 144-240 transients preceded <lb/>by 2 dummy rrcanr were <lb/>plied by sine-bell window function. zero-filled in t&gt; and symmetrized relative <lb/>accumulated. Prior to Fourier transformation. <lb/>the rime domain data were muli-<lb/>to the diagonal. <lb/>&lt;&quot;Hanjan. <lb/>S.N.S.. <lb/>Kearney, J.F. and Cooper. 1.0. I19821 Clin Immunol. <lb/>&quot;&apos;Fukushi. <lb/>Y . . <lb/>Hakomorl. S . . <lb/>Nudelman. E. and Cachran. N. (1984) <lb/>J. B i d . <lb/>c3&apos;Fukushi. Y . . <lb/>Nudelman. E., Levery. S.B. and Hekanori. S . (19841 J. Biol. <lb/>GOO^, H.C.. Jones. N.J.. Hilkens. J.. Hileers. J. and F e i r i . T. (1985) <lb/>Irn~unopBth. 23, 172 <lb/>Chea. 259, 4681-4685 <lb/>Chen. 259. 10511-10511 <lb/>&apos;I&apos;Rahman. R. and Longenecker. M . 11982) J. Ienunol. 129. 2021-2024 <lb/>,*&apos;Pilgrim, G. and Karsten. U. 119811 EXp1. clin. Immunogenet. 4 . 89-94 <lb/>Glyco;on&gt;ugate J. 2, 409-420 <lb/>Tab. 1 <lb/>Monosaccharide ane.ly9is of mucins O r glycopeptide fractions la1 <lb/>and of saccharide alditols in HPLC-fractions lbl <lb/>a1 <lb/>sample <lb/>Fuc <lb/>Wan <lb/>Gal <lb/>GalNAc <lb/>GlCNAc <lb/>NeuAc <lb/>mucins <lb/>&quot;&quot;__.~....&quot;_. &quot;^....&quot;&quot;..~.....&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot;..&quot;&quot;....&quot;&quot;..&quot;&quot;..&quot;&quot; <lb/>93.2 <lb/>trace <lb/>350.2 <lb/>51.0 <lb/>146.5 <lb/>35.5 <lb/>glycopeptide <lb/>Blo-Gel P30 <lb/>fractions <lb/>A <lb/>101.3 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>319.0 <lb/>104.6 <lb/>239.1 <lb/>128.5 <lb/>C <lb/>47.9 <lb/>65.9 <lb/>54.6 <lb/>11.9 <lb/>B <lb/>54.6 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>147.2 <lb/>62.6 <lb/>119.2 <lb/>103.2 <lb/>D <lb/>15.3 <lb/>54.6 <lb/>25.9 <lb/>10.6 <lb/>44.6 <lb/>46.6 <lb/>51.6 <lb/>41.9 <lb/>bl HFLC-fraction <lb/>MM-N <lb/>FYc <lb/>Man <lb/>Gal <lb/>GalNAc-a1 GalNAc <lb/>GlcNAc <lb/> 4 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>13 <lb/>trace <lb/>trice <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>-<lb/>3.6 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>2.2 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>4.1 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>5 . 4 <lb/>1 . 0 <lb/>-<lb/>3.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>5.1 <lb/>-<lb/>5.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>6.2 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-<lb/>6.6 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>3 . 2 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>4 . 1 <lb/>Unbranched Polylactosamino-0-glycans on Human Milk Mucins <lb/>Tab. 2 Monoclonal antibodies and corresponding carbohydrate epitopes referred t o in <lb/>this paper <lb/>MO&quot;OclO&quot;a1 <lb/>Carbohydrate <lb/>epifope <lb/>antibody <lb/>Le&quot; 01 <lb/>NS 19-9 <lb/>L e b 01 <lb/>115 C2 <lb/>A46-BlB10 <lb/>FH3 <lb/>FH6 <lb/>~e u <lb/>nl <lb/>Tab. 3 <lb/>Relative malar amounts of rllycapepzxde-derlved <lb/>carbohydrates <lb/>mol % of total carbohydrates <lb/>22.1 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>13.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2 . 5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>traction <lb/>vorrlble sequences deduced from prmary fragment m n s <lb/>. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/></div>

			<page>883 </page>

	</text>
</tei>
