<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Ultrasensitive Surface Plasmon Resonance Detection of<lb/> Trinitrotoluene by a Bis-aniline-Cross-Linked Au<lb/> Nanoparticles Composite<lb/> Michael Riskin, Ran Tel-Vered, Oleg Lioubashevski, and Itamar Willner*<lb/> Institute of Chemistry, The Hebrew UniVersity of Jerusalem, Jerusalem 91904, Israel<lb/> Received January 11, 2009; E-mail: willnea@vms.huji.ac.il<lb/> Abstract: A bis-aniline-cross-linked Au nanoparticles (NPs) composite is electropolymerized on Au surfaces.<lb/> The association of trinitrotoluene, TNT, to the bis-aniline bridging units via π-donor-acceptor interactions<lb/> allows the amplified detection of TNT by following the surface plasmon resonance (SPR) reflectance changes<lb/> as a result of the coupling between the localized plasmon of the AuNPs and the surface plasmon wave<lb/> associated with the gold surface. The detection limit for analyzing TNT by this method is ∼10 pM. The<lb/> electropolymerization of the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite in the presence of picric acid results<lb/> in a molecular-imprinted matrix for the enhanced binding of TNT. The imprinted AuNPs composite enabled<lb/> the sensing of TNT with a detection limit that corresponded to 10 fM. Analysis of the SPR reflectance<lb/> changes in the presence of different concentrations of TNT revealed a two-step calibration curve that included<lb/> the ultrasensitive detection of TNT by the imprinted sites in the composite, K ass I . for the association of TNT<lb/> to the imprinted sites, 6.4 × 10 12 M -1 , followed by a less sensitive detection of TNT by the nonimprinted<lb/> π-donor bis-aniline sites (K ass.<lb/> NI<lb/> ) 3.9 × 10 9 M -1 ). The imprinted AuNPs composite reveals impressive<lb/> selectivity. The structural and functional features of the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composites were<lb/> characterized by different methods including ellipsometry, AFM, and electrochemical means. The dielectric<lb/> properties of the AuNPs composite in the presence of different concentrations of TNT were evaluated by<lb/> the theoretical fitting of the respective experimental SPR curves. The ultrasensitive detection of the TNT<lb/> by the AuNPs composite was attributed to the changes of the dielectric properties of the composite, as a<lb/> result of the formation of the π-donor-acceptor complexes between TNT and the bis-aniline units. These<lb/> changes in the dielectric properties lead to a change in the conductivity of the AuNPs matrix.<lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction<lb/> Surface plasmon resonance (SPR) is a versatile tool to probe<lb/> and detect refractive index changes occurring on metal thin<lb/> films, e.g., gold films, as a result of chemical events. 1 The<lb/> assembly of monolayers or thin films on metal surfaces was<lb/> characterized by SPR spectroscopy, 2 and the method became a<lb/> widely used tool to monitor biorecognition events on metal<lb/> surfaces. 3 Numerous studies have applied SPR to develop<lb/> sensors for analyzing protein-protein interactions 4 and to probe<lb/> the formation of immunocomplexes. 5 The method is, however,<lb/> hindered by the degree of refractive index changes, which affect<lb/> the observable changes in the SPR spectra. This requires high-<lb/>molecular-weight analytes, e.g. proteins that provide sufficient<lb/> refractive index changes even at a low coverage of the analyte.<lb/> Different means to enhance the SPR shifts by the conjugation<lb/> of labels which amplify the refractive index changes, occurring<lb/> as a result of biorecognition events, were reported, and these<lb/> include latex particles, 6 liposomes, 7 or secondary proteins 8 as<lb/> amplifying labels.<lb/> Metal nanoparticles (NPs) were also implemented to enhance<lb/> the SPR response. 9 The coupling between the localized surface<lb/> plasmon (LSP) of the metal NPs and the surface plasmon<lb/> polariton (SPP) associated with the thin metal surface leads to<lb/> a deformation in the dispersion curve of the SPP, and to a shift<lb/> in the SPR energy. The effects of this coupling were treated<lb/> theoretically, 9b and the changes in the SPR curves resulting from<lb/> the alteration of the dielectric properties of the metal surface<lb/> </body>

			<listBibl>(1) (a) Raether, H. Surface Plasmons on Smooth and Rough Surfaces and<lb/> on Gratings, Springer Tracts in Modern Physics; Springer-Verlag:<lb/> Berlin, Heidelberg, 1988; Vol. 111. (b) Knoll, W. Annu. ReV. Phys.<lb/> Chem. 1998, 49, 569–638.<lb/> (2) (a) Ehler, T. T.; Malmberg, N.; Noe, L. J. J. Phys. Chem. B 1997,<lb/> 101, 1268–1272. (b) Hutter, E.; Fendler, J. H.; Roy, D. J. Phys.Chem.<lb/> B 2001, 105, 11159–11168.<lb/> (3) (a) Homola, J. Chem. ReV. 2008, 108, 462–493. (b) Phillips, K. S.;<lb/> Cheng, Q. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2007, 387, 1831–1840.<lb/> (4) (a) Schuck, P. Annu. ReV. Biophys. Biomol. Struct. 1997, 26, 541–<lb/> 566. (b) Garland, P. B. Q. ReV. Biophys. 1996, 29, 91–117. (c) Löfås,<lb/> S. Pure Appl. Chem. 1995, 67, 829–834. (d) Heyse, S.; Ernst, O. P.;<lb/> Dienes, Z.; Hofmann, K. P.; Vogel, H. Biochemistry 1998, 37, 507–<lb/> 522. (e) Berger, C. E. H.; Beumer, T. A. M.; Kooyman, R. P. H.;<lb/> Greve, J. Anal. Chem. 1998, 70, 703–706. (f) Minunni, M. Anal. Lett.<lb/> 1995, 28, 933–944.<lb/> (5) (a) Fivash, M.; Towler, E. M.; Fisher, R. J. Curr. Opin. Biotechnol.<lb/> 1998, 9, 97–101. (b) Malmborg, A. C.; Borrebaeck, C. A. K.<lb/> J. Immnunol. Methods 1995, 183, 7–13.<lb/> (6) Kubitschko, S.; Spinke, J.; Bruckner, T.; Pohl, S.; Oranth, N. Anal.<lb/> Biochem. 1997, 253, 112–122.<lb/> (7) Wink, T.; van Zuilen, S.-J.; Bult, A.; van Bennekom, W.-P. Anal.<lb/> Chem. 1998, 70, 827–832.<lb/> (8) Zayats, M.; Raitman, O. A.; Chegel, V. I.; Kharitonov, A. B.; Willner,<lb/> I. Anal. Chem. 2002, 74, 4763–4773.<lb/> (9) (a) Lyon, L. A.; Musick, M. D.; Smith, P. C.; Reiss, B. D.; Peña,<lb/> D. J.; Natan, M. J. Sens. Actuators, B 1999, 54, 118–124. (b) Agarwal,<lb/> G. S.; Dutta Gupta, S. Phys. ReV. B 1985, 32, 3607–3611.<lb/> </listBibl>
			
			<front>Published on Web 05/08/2009<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>10.1021/ja9001212 CCC: $40.75  2009 American Chemical Society<lb/> </front>
			
			<page>7368</page> 
			
			<front>9 J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 2009, 131, 7368–7378<lb/></front>

			<body>were discussed. Indeed, numerous experiments applied conju-<lb/>gated metallic NPs, mainly AuNPs, as amplifying labels to study<lb/> biorecognition or biocatalytic events. For example, the formation<lb/> of immunocomplexes 10 or DNA hybridization 11 were amplified<lb/> by the conjugation of AuNPs. Also, biocatalytic transformations<lb/> were enhanced by functionalized AuNPs, 12 and the effects of<lb/> the particles size 13 and their coverage 13 on the SPR responses<lb/> were investigated. Specifically, plasmonic coupling between<lb/> AuNPs aggregates and the surface plasmon wave not only<lb/> showed shifts of the SPR minimum angle position, but also<lb/> resulted in a broadening of the resonance curve and in an<lb/> increase in the minimum reflectance. 14<lb/> Different studies implemented functionalized AuNPs as<lb/> conjugates that amplify an existing recognition complex. This<lb/> approach limits, however, the use of the NPs to analyze<lb/> substrates exhibiting multidentate binding sites. Thus, the use<lb/> of NPs as amplifying labels for low-molecular-weight substrate<lb/> is scarce. In the present study we apply a AuNPs composite for<lb/> the SPR detection of the trinitrotoluene (TNT) explosive. The<lb/> analysis of TNT attracts recent research efforts due to homeland<lb/> security needs. Different sensors for analyzing explosives, and<lb/> particularly, nitroaromatic derivatives were reported in the past<lb/> decade. 15 These include optical sensors employing functional<lb/> fluorescent polymers that were quenched by the nitroaromatic<lb/> explosives, 16,17 luminescent polysilole nanoparticles that were<lb/> quenched by TNT, 18 or fluorescent silicon nanoparticles that<lb/> were quenched by nitroaromatic vapors. 19 Furthermore, the<lb/> electrochemical activity of the nitroaromatic groups was imple-<lb/>mented to design modified sensing electrodes, e.g., mesoporous<lb/> SiO 2 films for electrochemical TNT detection. 20 Other nitroaro-<lb/>matic sensors used the surface acoustic wave readout of the<lb/> association of TNT to cyclodextrin polymers, 21 carbowax, 22 or<lb/> silicon polymer 23 matrices deposited on surfaces. Similarly,<lb/> competitive immuno-assays were developed for the analysis of<lb/> TNT. The competitive association of the dye-functionalized TNT<lb/> and the TNT analyte to anti-TNT-antibody-functionalized<lb/> quantum dots, and the application of the FRET quenching<lb/> process were used to develop an optical TNT sensor. 24 Also,<lb/> the displacement of antigen-anti-TNT antibody complexes<lb/> linked to surfaces by the TNT analyte was used to develop<lb/> SPR 25 or microgravimetric quartz crystal microbalance (QCM) 26<lb/> antibody-based sensors. In a recent study, 27 we demonstrated<lb/> the use of thioaniline-modified AuNPs as building units to<lb/> construct an electropolymerized bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs<lb/> composite on Au electrodes. The cross-linked AuNPs matrix<lb/> associated with the electrode was used for the electrochemical<lb/> detection of TNT. π-Donor-acceptor interactions between TNT<lb/> and the bis-aniline bridges enabled the binding and the<lb/> concentration of TNT at the electrode surface. Furthermore, we<lb/> demonstrated the use of the thioaniline-functionalized AuNPs<lb/> as electropolymerizable units for the generation of specific<lb/> imprinted sites in the cross-linked AuNPs composite. With the<lb/> latter tailored nanostructures we were able to detect TNT with<lb/> a detection limit that corresponded to 200 pM (46 ppt).<lb/> Here we report on the highly sensitive detection of trinitro-<lb/>toluene, TNT (1), by a bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs matrix<lb/> associated with a Au-coated glass surface. The formation of<lb/> the π-donor-acceptor complexes between the TNT and the bis-<lb/>aniline bridging units is, then, probed by following the effect<lb/> of these complexes on the plasmon coupling of the AuNPs<lb/> matrix to the surface plasmon wave. We describe the effect of<lb/> molecular imprinting of TNT recognition sites into the bis-<lb/>aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite on the sensitivity and<lb/> selectivity of the resulting sensing surface. The bis-aniline-cross-<lb/>linked AuNPs matrix is characterized by means of electro-<lb/>chemical, AFM, and SPR measurements. Furthermore, by fitting<lb/> of the experimental SPR curves, we extract the dielectric<lb/> functions of the sensing matrix upon analyzing TNT. The<lb/> theoretical fittings of the SPR suggest that the formation of π<lb/> donor-acceptor complexes between TNT and the bis-aniline<lb/> units bridging the AuNPs leads to conductivity changes in the<lb/> NPs composite, and these stimulate the changes in the SPR<lb/> spectra. Besides the specific application of the bis-aniline-cross-<lb/>linked AuNPs, composite for the specific analysis of TNT, one<lb/> may envisage the application of the method for other analytes<lb/> as well.<lb/> Results and Discussion<lb/> Thioaniline-functionalized AuNPs, mean diameter 3.5 nm,<lb/> were prepared by capping the AuNPs with a mixed monolayer<lb/> of thioaniline (2) and mercaptoethane sulfonate (3). The resulting<lb/> functionalized AuNPs were electropolymerized on a thioaniline<lb/> monolayer-modified flat Au electrode (a glass plate coated with<lb/> a Au layer, ∼50 nm), by applying 10 electropolymerization<lb/> cycles ranging between 0.80 to -0.35 V vs Ag/QRE, Scheme<lb/> 1A. The thickness of the resulting matrix was estimated by<lb/> ellipsometry measurements to be 9.7 ( 2.1 nm with a volume<lb/> fraction of AuNPs that equals to approximately 65% ( 19%<lb/> </body>
			
			<listBibl>(10) (a) Lyon, L. A.; Musick, M. D.; Natan, M. J. Anal. Chem. 1998, 70,<lb/> 5177–5183. (b) Mauriz, E.; Calle, A.; Lechuga, L. M.; Quintana, J.;<lb/> Montoya, A.; Manclus, J. Anal. Chim. Acta 2006, 561, 40–47.<lb/> (11) He, L.; Musick, M. D.; Nicewarner, S. R.; Sallinas, F. G.; Benkovic,<lb/> S. J.; Natan, M. J.; Keating, C. D. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2000, 122, 9071–<lb/> 9077.<lb/> (12) Zayats, M.; Pogorelova, S. P.; Kharitonov, A. B.; Lioubashevski, O.;<lb/> Katz, E.; Willner, I. Chem.-Eur. J. 2003, 9, 6108–6114.<lb/> (13) (a) Lyon, L. A.; Musick, M. D.; Smith, P. C.; Reiss, B. D.; Peña,<lb/> D. J.; Natan, M. J. Sens. Actuators, B 1999, 54, 118–124. (b) Lyon,<lb/> L. A.; Holliway, W. D.; Natan, M. J. ReV. Sci. Instrum. 1999, 70,<lb/> 2076–2081. (c) Lyon, L. A.; Peña, D. J.; Natan, M. J. J. Phys. Chem.<lb/> B 1999, 103, 5826–5831.<lb/> (14) Lyon, L. A.; Peña, D. J.; Natan, M. J. J. Phys. Chem. B 1999, 103,<lb/> 5826–5831.<lb/> (15) (a) Toal, S. J.; Trogler, W. C. J. Mater. Chem. 2006, 16, 2871–2883.<lb/> (b) Senesac, L.; Thundat, T. G. Mater. Today 2008, 11, 28–36.<lb/> (16) (a) Swager, T. M. Acc. Chem. Res. 1998, 31, 201–207. (b) McQuade,<lb/> D. T.; Pullen, A. E.; Swager, T. M. Chem. ReV. 2000, 100, 2537–<lb/> 2574. (c) Yang, J.-S.; Swager, T. M. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1998, 120,<lb/> 11864–11873.<lb/> (17) (a) Chang, C.-P.; Chao, C.-Y.; Huang, J.-H.; Li, A.-K.; Hsu, C.-S.;<lb/> Lin, M.-S.; Hsieh, B.-R.; Su, A.-C. Synth. Met. 2004, 144, 297–301.<lb/> (b) Sohn, H.; Sailor, M. J.; Magde, D.; Trogler, W. C. J. Am. Chem.<lb/> Soc. 2003, 125, 3821–3830.<lb/> (18) Toal, S. J.; Magde, D.; Trogler, W. C. Chem. Commun. 2005, 5465–<lb/> 5467.<lb/> (19) Content, S.; Trogler, W. C.; Sailor, M. J. Chem.-Eur. J. 2000, 6,<lb/> 2205–2213.<lb/> (20) Zhang, H.-X.; Cao, A.-M.; Hu, J.-S.; Wan, L.-J.; Lee, S.-T. Anal.<lb/> Chem. 2006, 78, 1967–1971.<lb/> (21) Yang, X.; Du, X. X.; Shi, J.; Swanson, B. Talanta 2001, 54, 439–<lb/> 445.<lb/> (22) Kannan, G. K.; Nimal, A. T.; Mittal, U.; Yadava, R. D. S.; Kapoor,<lb/> J. C. Sens. Actuators, B 2004, 101, 328–334.<lb/> (23) McGill, R. A.; Mlsna, T. E.; Chung, R.; Nguyen, V. K.; Stepnowski,<lb/> J. Sens. Actuators, B 2000, 65, 5–9.<lb/> (24) Goldman, E. R.; Medintz, I. L.; Whitley, I. L.; Hayhurst, A.; Clapp,<lb/> A. R.; Uyeda, H. T.; Deschamps, J. R.; Lassman, M. E.; Mattoussi,<lb/> H. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2005, 127, 6744–6751.<lb/> (25) Larsson, A.; Angbrant, J.; Ekeroth, J.; Mansson, P.; Liedberg, B. Sens.<lb/> Actuators, B 2006, 113, 730–748.<lb/> (26) Shankaran, D. R.; Gobi, K. V.; Sakai, T.; Matsumoto, K.; Toko, K.;<lb/> Miura, N. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2005, 20, 1750–1756.<lb/> (27) Riskin, M.; Tel-Vered, R.; Bourenko, T.; Granot, E.; Willner, I. J. Am.<lb/> Chem. Soc. 2008, 130, 9726–9733.<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009 </note>

			<page>7369<lb/> </page>

			<note place="headnote">AuNPs Composite for Ultrasensitive SPR Detection of TNT<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<body>(realizing a 4.5 nm diameter for the AuNPs: 3.5 nm core and<lb/> 0.5 nm capping shell). This translates to the formation of a<lb/> AuNPs composite consisting of an average number of ap-<lb/>proximately three layers (Vide infra). The bis-aniline cross-<lb/>linking units exhibit a quasi-reversible redox wave at 0.2 V vs<lb/> Ag/QRE. Coulometric analysis of the anodic peak corresponding<lb/> to the bis-aniline units indicated a charge of 6 × 10 -5 C · cm -2<lb/> that translates to a total surface coverage of ∼3.8 × 10 14<lb/> thioaniline molecules · cm -2 .<lb/> The thioaniline units and bis-aniline bridging units exhibit<lb/> π-donor properties and, thus, are expected to change the TNT<lb/> electron acceptor by π-donor-acceptor interactions. The forma-<lb/>tion of the charge-transfer complex between the bis-aniline<lb/> π-donor and TNT is, thus, anticipated to alter the dielectric<lb/> properties of the composite, and this is expected to change the<lb/> surface plasmon resonance (SPR) features. The change in the<lb/> dielectric properties at the vicinity of the AuNPs is anticipated<lb/> to affect the localized surface plasmon of the AuNPs, and<lb/> consequently, this will be reflected by the plasmon coupling to<lb/> the surface plasmon wave. That is, the coupling of the localized<lb/> plasmon to the surface plasmon is expected to transduce the<lb/> changes in the dielectric properties of the matrix as a result of<lb/> the formation of the donor-acceptor complexes.<lb/> Figure 1A shows the SPR curve of the bis-aniline-cross-linked<lb/> AuNPs matrix before interaction with TNT, curve (a), and after<lb/> interaction with 200 nM of TNT, curve (b). The minimum<lb/> reflectivity angle of the spectrum is shifted by 0.4°. In a control<lb/> experiment, a two-layer AuNPs matrix was assembled on the<lb/> Au-coated glass surface by the primary association of thiopro-<lb/>pionic acid-stabilized AuNPs (mean diameter 3.5 nm) on a<lb/> cystamine-monolayer-functionalized gold slide, followed by the<lb/> assembly of a second AuNPs layer by cross-linking the AuNPs<lb/> to the base AuNPs layer with butane dithiol. Interaction of this<lb/> AuNPs matrix with TNT, 200 nM, did not yield any significant<lb/> Scheme 1. (A) Electropolymerization of a Bis-aniline-Crosslinked AuNPs Composite for the Sensing of TNT by Donor-Acceptor Interactions;<lb/> (B) Imprinting of TNT Molecular Recognition Sites into the Bis-aniline-Crosslinked AuNPs Composite Associated with a Au Electrode<lb/> 
			
			<page>7370</page> 
			
			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">Riskin et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			change in the SPR spectrum of the surface (Figure 1A, inset),<lb/> and only upon the interaction of the surface with 1 µM TNT,<lb/> was a minute shift in the SPR spectrum observed. Thus, when<lb/> the bridging units lack electron-donating properties, the SPR<lb/> spectrum of the system is almost unaffected by the addition of<lb/> TNT. This is consistent with the primary assumption that the<lb/> association of TNT to the AuNPs surface occurs only upon the<lb/> formation of π-donor-acceptor complexes between the bis-<lb/>aniline units and TNT (for further supporting evidence, Vide<lb/> infra). In a further control experiment polyaniline was elec-<lb/>tropolymerized on a Au-coated glass surface, and the SPR<lb/> curves of the film were recorded before and after interaction<lb/> with TNT, 200 nM. The measurements indicated no changes<lb/> in the SPR spectrum of the film in the presence of TNT. This<lb/> implies that the changes in the SPR spectrum of the AuNPs<lb/> composite upon the association of TNT are amplified through<lb/> the coupling of the localized plasmon of the NPs with the surface<lb/> plasmon wave. Figure 1B shows the sensogram corresponding<lb/> to the reflectance changes, ∆R, upon the treatment of the bis-<lb/>aniline-cross-linked AuNPs matrix with variable concentrations<lb/> of TNT, and Figure 1C depicts the corresponding calibration<lb/> curve derived from the reflectance changes at θ ) 62.4°, upon<lb/> the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs-modified electrode interac-<lb/>tion with variable concentrations of TNT. The time-response<lb/> of the sensing device is ∼1 min, Figure 1B, inset. The modified<lb/> electrode enables the detection of TNT with a detection limit<lb/> corresponding to ∼10 pM (signal/noise (S/N) ) 5).<lb/> We searched, however, to improve the sensitivity of the<lb/> analysis of TNT. Any method to enhance the binding affinity<lb/> of TNT to the sensing matrix is anticipated to lead to improved<lb/> sensitivities. In a previous report, 27 we implemented the<lb/> molecular imprinting principle to generate TNT binding sites<lb/> by the electropolymerization of the AuNPs under conditions<lb/> that yielded imprinted sites with enhanced binding affinities for<lb/> TNT. According to this method, Scheme 1 B, the thioaniline-<lb/>functionalized AuNPs act as electropolymerizable nanometer-<lb/>sized units for generating the imprinted sites, and picric acid<lb/> (4) serves as an analogue for TNT and is used for the imprinting<lb/> process. Formation of the π-donor-acceptor complexes between<lb/> the picric acid and the thioaniline-modified AuNPs occurs during<lb/> the electropolymerization on the Au-coated slide. The subse-<lb/>quent removal of the picric acid imprint molecules yields<lb/> molecular contours with optimal positioning of the π-donor sites<lb/> for the association of the TNT analyte. Indeed, in the previous<lb/> study 27 it was demonstrated that the synergistic binding of TNT<lb/> to the AuNPs matrix by π-donor-acceptor interactions and<lb/> molecular contours improved the association constant of TNT<lb/> to the matrix. Figure 2A depicts the SPR curve of the imprinted<lb/> cross-linked AuNPs composite before, curve (a), and after<lb/> treatment with 1 pM of TNT, curve (b). The SPR shift at this<lb/> low concentration is comparable to the response of the nonim-<lb/>printed matrix at 200 nM TNT, Figure 1A, indicating that an<lb/> increased coverage of TNT on the sensing surface occurred.<lb/> Figure 2B depicts the reflectance changes at the angle θ ) 62.7°,<lb/> upon treating the imprinted sensing matrix with variable<lb/> concentrations of TNT. As the concentration of TNT is elevated,<lb/> the reflectance changes increase. Figure 2C shows the derived<lb/> calibration curve that corresponds to the analysis of TNT by<lb/> the imprinted matrix. The detection limit for the analysis of<lb/> TNT using the imprinted composite corresponds to a concentra-<lb/>tion of 10 fM TNT (S/N ) 5, the response time for the TNT<lb/> analysis is ∼15 s., Figure 2B, inset) that is ∼10 3 -fold improved<lb/> relative to the nonimprinted matrix. Figure 3, depicts the<lb/> comparison of the derived calibration curves for the imprinted,<lb/> curve (a), and the nonimprinted, curve (b), matrices, presented<lb/> for clarity on a semilogarithmic scale. The enhanced SPR shifts<lb/> and the improved sensitivity for the detection of TNT by the<lb/> imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs matrix are attributed<lb/> Figure 1. (A) SPR curves corresponding to the bis-aniline-AuNPs<lb/> composite: (a) before the addition of TNT and (b) after the addition of<lb/> TNT, 200 nM. Inset: SPR curves corresponding to a bilayer of AuNPs cross-<lb/>linked by 1,4-butane dithiol and linked to the cystamine-modifed Au surface:<lb/> (a) before, and, (b) after the addition of TNT, 200 nM. (B) Sensogram<lb/> corresponding to the changes in the reflectance intensities, at θ ) 62.4°,<lb/> upon addition of variable concentrations of TNT: (a) 10 pM, (b) 20 pM,<lb/> (c) 40 pM, (d) 100 pM, (e) 1 nM, (f) 10 nM, (g) 50 nM, (h) 200 nM, (i) 1<lb/> µM, (j) 5 µM. Arrows indicate the time of addition of the analyte. Inset:<lb/> enlarged time-dependent reflectance changes. (C) Calibration curve relating<lb/> the reflectance changes to the concentration of TNT. Inset: responses in<lb/> low concentration range. All measurements were performed in a 0.1 M<lb/> HEPES buffer solution, pH ) 7.2.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009 </note>
			
			<page>7371<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="headnote">AuNPs Composite for Ultrasensitive SPR Detection of TNT<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/></note>

			to the higher affinity of TNT to the imprinted matrix, resulting<lb/> in higher content of bound TNT (Vide infra).<lb/> One may note that for the imprinted AuNPs composite two<lb/> steps of changes in the reflectance values as a function of the<lb/> concentration of added TNT, are observed. The first step is<lb/> initiated at ∼10 fM TNT, and the reflectance change (∆R)<lb/> saturates at ∼5 pM. The second step of reflectance change is<lb/> initiated at ∼100 pM and the reflectance levels off at ∼1 nM.<lb/> In contrast, the nonimprinted matrix shows a single domain of<lb/> ∆R that is initiated at ∼10 pM and it reaches a saturation value<lb/> at ∼1 µM. The two-step reflectance calibration curve, Figure<lb/> 3, curve (a), is attributed to the existence of two types of TNT<lb/> binding sites. The reflectance changes at low TNT concentra-<lb/>tions (10 fM &lt; [TNT] &lt; 5 pM) are attributed to the association<lb/> of TNT to the imprinted donor sites of the matrix. The<lb/> reflectance changes observed at higher TNT concentrations (100<lb/> pM &lt; [TNT] &lt; 10 µM) that are also observed for the<lb/> nonimprinted matrix are attributed to the association of TNT<lb/> to the nonimprinted bis-aniline π-donor units. It should be noted<lb/> that the inflection point of the second step for analyzing TNT<lb/> by imprinted Au NPs matrix in Figure 3, curve (a), occurs at a<lb/> concentration that is ∼2 orders of magnitude lower than the<lb/> inflection point for the analysis by the nonimprinted Au NPs<lb/> matrix, curve (b). This presumably originates from the fact that<lb/> the imprinting process leads to nonoptimal, partially fitting<lb/> binding sites for TNT molecules. The association constant to<lb/> these sites is still higher than to the nonimprinted bridging units,<lb/> leading to the inflection point at a lower concentration. Also,<lb/> the imprinted Au NPs composite and the nonimprinted one reach<lb/> similar saturation reflectance changes. This is consistent with<lb/> the fact that the content of bis-aniline bridging units in both<lb/> composites is similar. The only difference between the com-<lb/>posites is that a fraction of the bis-aniline binding sites<lb/> participated in structurally imprinted domains that revealed<lb/> enhanced binding toward TNT.<lb/> The specificity of the picric acid-imprinted polymer matrices<lb/> toward the analysis of TNT was further examined by subjecting<lb/> the imprinted AuNPs composite to 2,4-dinitrotoluene (DNT),<lb/> 5. Figure 4A depicts the comparison between the calibration<lb/> curves derived for TNT, curve (a), and DNT, curve (b). While<lb/> the interaction of the imprinted matrix yields detectable<lb/> reflectance changes with a bulk TNT concentration of 10 fM,<lb/> Figure 2. (A) SPR curves corresponding to the picric acid-imprinted bis-<lb/>aniline-AuNPs composite: (a) before the addition of TNT, and (b) after the<lb/> addition of TNT, 1 pM. Inset: SPR curves (enlarged at the minimum<lb/> reflectance angle) corresponding to the picric acid-imprinted bis-aniline-<lb/>AuNPs composite in the presence of different concentrations of TNT. (B)<lb/> Sensogram corresponding to the changes in the reflectance intensities, at θ<lb/> ) 62.4°, upon addition of variable concentrations of TNT: (a) 10 fM, (b)<lb/> 20 fM, (c) 50 fM, (d) 100 fM, (e) 1 pM, (f) 5 pM. Arrows indicate the time<lb/> of addition of the analyte. Inset: enlarged time-dependent reflectance<lb/> changes. (C) Calibration curve relating the reflectance changes to the<lb/> concentration of TNT. All measurements were performed in a 0.1 M HEPES<lb/> buffer solution, pH ) 7.2.<lb/> Figure 3. Changes in the reflectance intensities upon analyzing TNT within<lb/> a broad range of concentrations (presented on a semilogarithmic scale): (a)<lb/> Imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite. (b) Nonimprinted bis-<lb/>aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite. All measurements were performed<lb/> in a 0.1 M HEPES buffer solution, pH ) 7.2.<lb/> 
			
			<page>7372</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">Riskin et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			comparable ∆R values for DNT are observed only at bulk<lb/> concentrations above 50 pM. Also, the saturation values of ∆R<lb/> for TNT sensing (∆R ∼ 300 au) are substantially higher than<lb/> ∆R upon sensing of DNT (∆R ∼ 40 au). These results are<lb/> consistent with the fact that DNT exhibits substantially lower<lb/> affinity toward the picric acid-imprinted matrix, as compared<lb/> to TNT. The lower affinity of DNT to the imprinted matrix<lb/> defines the lower content of DNT associated with the matrix,<lb/> resulting in a substantially higher detection limit and a lower<lb/> response.<lb/> While the imprinted AuNPs matrices sense TNT in the<lb/> femtomolar concentration range, these matrices respond to DNT<lb/> only in the picomolar concentration range. That is, the analysis<lb/> of TNT by the imprinted AuNPs matrix is ∼10 3 -fold more<lb/> sensitive than the detection of DNT. This result is consistent<lb/> with the fact that DNT exhibits decreased electron-acceptor<lb/> properties as compared to TNT due to the lack of one of the<lb/> electron-attracting nitro groups. The lower electron affinity of<lb/> DNT results in a weaker binding constant with the π-donor<lb/> cross-linking units, and thus, higher bulk concentrations are<lb/> needed to yield a measurable SPR response. These conclusions<lb/> are even further emphasized upon the analysis of 4-nitrotoluene<lb/> (MNT), 6, Figure 4B. The detection limit for analyzing<lb/> mononitrotoluene, MNT is in the 10 -5 M concentration range<lb/> only, and no difference is observed upon sensing MNT by the<lb/> imprinted or nonimprinted matrices. Evidently, the lack of two<lb/> of the electron-withdrawing NO 2 groups weakens the electron-<lb/>acceptor features of MNT as compared to TNT and DNT, and<lb/> thus, higher bulk concentrations of MNT are required to allow<lb/> their association to the π-donor sites. It should be noted that<lb/> the selectivity does not originate only from the π-donor-acceptor<lb/> interactions of the explosives with the matrix but is also<lb/> controlled by the steric fitting of the explosive molecules to<lb/> the imprinted sites. For example, trinitrotriazine (RDX), exhibit-<lb/>ing similar electron-acceptor features to those of TNT, is not<lb/> sensed by the picric acid-imprinted composite below the<lb/> nanomolar region, due to the larger dimensions of the RDX<lb/> molecules.<lb/> Further support that the successful ultrasensitive detection<lb/> of TNT originates, indeed, from π-donor-acceptor interactions<lb/> with the bis-aniline bridges was obtained by following the SPR<lb/> changes in reflectance, ∆R, of the imprinted, or nonimprinted,<lb/> AuNPs cross-linked composites in the presence of TNT (100<lb/> fM), upon applying an external potential on the Au surface,<lb/> Figure 5, curves (a) and (b), respectively. A sharp change in<lb/> the SPR reflectance intensities is observed at ∼-0.1 V (vs a<lb/> quasi-reversible Ag wire reference electrode). Prior to the<lb/> addition of TNT, the potential scan of the electrode revealed<lb/> only a minute reflectance change in the entire potential range,<lb/> specifically, at -0.1 V vs the Ag wire electrode, (&lt;5 au of<lb/> reflectance). These results further support the formation of the<lb/> π-donor-acceptor complexes in the bis-aniline-cross-linked<lb/> AuNPs composite, and re-emphasize that the charge transfer<lb/> process in the donor-acceptor complexes strongly affects the<lb/> SPR spectra. In the potential region of +0.6 to 0.0 V, the<lb/> bridging units exist in their oxidized, quinoide, form. In this<lb/> state, the bridges exhibit electron-acceptor features, and thus,<lb/> the formation of the donor-acceptor complexes with TNT is<lb/> prohibited. At the potential of ∼-0.1 V, the bridging units are<lb/> reduced to the bis-aniline π-donor form. In this configuration,<lb/> the formation of the π-donor-acceptor complex with TNT<lb/> proceeds, resulting in the changes in the SPR spectra. The<lb/> increased changes in the reflectance intensities observed for the<lb/> imprinted cross-linked AuNPs composite (cf. Figure 5, curve<lb/> Figure 4. (A) Calibration curves (presented on a semilogarithmic scale)<lb/> corresponding to the analysis of: (a) TNT, and (b) 2,4-dinitrotoluene by<lb/> the imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite. (B) Calibration<lb/> curves (presented on a semilogarithmic scale) corresponding to the analysis<lb/> of: (a) 2,4-dinitrotoluene, and (b) 4-nitrotoluene, by the imprinted bis-aniline-<lb/>cross-linked AuNPs composite. All measurements were performed in a<lb/> 0.1 M HEPES buffer solution, pH ) 7.2.<lb/> Figure 5. Effect of applied potential on the reflectance changes, at θ )<lb/> 62.4°, of the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite, upon analyzing<lb/> TNT, 100 fM: (a) the imprinted composite and (b) the nonimprinted<lb/> composite. All measurements were performed in a 0.1 M HEPES buffer<lb/> solution, pH ) 7.2.<lb/>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009 </note>

			<page>7373<lb/> </page>

			<note place="headnote">AuNPs Composite for Ultrasensitive SPR Detection of TNT<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			(a) as compared to (b)) are consistent with the enhanced binding<lb/> of TNT to the imprinted sites.<lb/> Further attempts were directed to characterize the structure<lb/> and composition of the bis-aniline-bridged AuNPs matrix.<lb/> Ellipsometry was implemented as a spectroscopic tool. Ellip-<lb/>sometry is a powerful optical technique for the investigation of<lb/> the dielectric properties of thin films, 28 and it has been widely<lb/> used to characterize polymer layers and NP-polymer compos-<lb/>ites. 29 In ellipsometric measurements the incident polarized<lb/> monochromatic light beam is reflected from the sample. The<lb/> reflected beam intensity and polarization changes are then<lb/> measured, yielding the ellipsometric angles Ψ and ∆. These<lb/> experimental quantities are compared with the values calculated<lb/> according to the suggested model describing the order of the<lb/> layers on the surface, and a least-squares value minimization is<lb/> performed. The optical properties of 2-4 nm diameter AuNPs<lb/> were recently studied through optical absorption and ellipso-<lb/>metric measurements, and their dielectric function was found<lb/> to be nearly equal to that of bulk gold in the spectral range of<lb/> 207-414 nm. 30 These observations allowed us to integrate the<lb/> optical properties of bulk gold in the ellipsometric model for<lb/> the characterization of the electropolymerized AuNP matrices<lb/> by fitting the ellipsometric data in the spectral range of 300-500<lb/> nm. By analyzing the ellipsometry results, we estimated the<lb/> thickness of the thioaniline monolayer to be 1.1 ( 0.2 nm, using<lb/> a refractive index of n ) 1.56 for thioaniline. 31 The thickness<lb/> of the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs matrix was estimated by<lb/> using the effective medium approximation, based on the<lb/> Maxwell-Garnett approach that describes the relationship<lb/> between the effective dielectric function of the composite and<lb/> the dielectric function and volume fraction of the metallic NPs.<lb/> We used a model that included a composite consisting of gold<lb/> spheres embedded in a thioaniline linker medium containing<lb/> voids. The estimated thickness of the cross-linked AuNPs<lb/> composite was found to be 9.7 ( 2.1 nm with a volume fraction<lb/> of AuNPs corresponding to ∼65 ( 19%. This value translates<lb/> to a surface coverage of ∼1.3 × 10 13 NPs · cm -2 . Using the<lb/> measured dimensions of the AuNPs (4.5 nm, including the<lb/> capping shell), this thickness translates to approximately three<lb/> monolayers of AuNPs in the matrix. Further characterization<lb/> of the composite was accomplished by electrochemical mea-<lb/>surements. The AuNPs were synthesized with a molar ratio of<lb/> thioaniline/ethane-sulfonic acid mixture (mercaptoethane sul-<lb/>fonate) that corresponded to 1:6. It was previously estimated 32<lb/> that ∼220 thiol molecules bind to a single AuNP with a core<lb/> size of 4.0 nm. This value was recalculated for the 3.5 nm<lb/> AuNPs used in the present study, to yield a coverage of ∼170<lb/> thiol molecules per single AuNP. Realizing that thioaniline<lb/> provides only 1/7 of the total coverage, we estimated that a<lb/> single AuNP is covered by ∼25 thioaniline units.<lb/> The amount of the thioaniline units, electropolymerized in<lb/> the AuNP composite, was further probed by the coulometric<lb/> analysis of the cathodic redox wave at 0.05 V vs SCE. The<lb/> charge associated with the oxidation of the thioaniline units<lb/> corresponded to 6 × 10 -5 C · cm -2 , a value that translates to a<lb/> coverage of 3.8 × 10 14 thioanilne molecules · cm -2 in the<lb/> composite. Realizing that each AuNP is covered by 24 thioa-<lb/>niline units, we estimate the surface coverage of the AuNPs to<lb/> be 1.6 × 10 13 particles · cm -2 . Using the derived surface coverage<lb/> of the AuNPs, and knowing the volume of a single AuNP, we<lb/> estimate the thickness of the composite to be ∼11.6 nm,<lb/> assuming a random close packing model for the AuNPs in the<lb/> matrix. 33 This result suggests that the composite consists of<lb/> approximately three random densely packed AuNPs layers,<lb/> consistent with the ellipsometry results. It should be noted that<lb/> the ellipsometric and the electrochemical methods yielded<lb/> similar surface coverage values of the AuNPs.<lb/> We then evaluated the association constant of TNT binding<lb/> to the bis-aniline-AuNPs units in the imprinted matrix and the<lb/> content of imprinted sites in the matrix to estimate the relative<lb/> population of the sites bound by TNT. The binding of TNT to<lb/> the π-donor binding sites in the imprinted and nonimprinted<lb/> AuNPs matrices can be described by eq 1 and the Langmuir<lb/> isotherm model. 34 According to this model, the association<lb/> constant of TNT to the π-donor binding sites, is given by eq 2<lb/> where θ is the number of sites occupied by TNT, and R is the<lb/> total number of binding sites. At any given bulk concentration<lb/> of TNT, the value of θ can be evaluated by rearranging eq 2 in<lb/> the form of eq 2a.<lb/> TNT + π-donor sites h TNT-bound sites<lb/> R-θ<lb/> θ (1)<lb/> K ass. )<lb/> θ (R -θ)[TNT]<lb/> (2)<lb/> or<lb/> θ )<lb/> RK ass. [TNT]<lb/> 1 + K ass. [TNT]<lb/> (2a)<lb/> The double reciprocal of the Langmuir equation yields the<lb/> Lineweaver-Burk relation, eq 3:<lb/> 1 θ<lb/> ) 1<lb/> R +<lb/> 1 RK ass. [TNT]<lb/> (3)<lb/> From the values of the slope and the y-axis intercept the<lb/> values of R and K ass. can then be derived. Assuming that the<lb/> reflectivity, R, is proportional to the number of TNT-occupied<lb/> sites, θ, we analyzed the calibration curves for the nonimprinted<lb/> and the imprinted matrices, Figures 1C and 2C, respectively,<lb/> according to the Lineweaver-Burk relation, eq 3. The derived<lb/> association constants for the imprinted and the nonimprinted<lb/> sites correspond to, K ass.<lb/> I<lb/> ) 6.4 × 10 12 M -1 , and K ass.<lb/> NI<lb/> ) 3.9<lb/> × 10 9 M -1 , respectively.<lb/> Figure 3 presents the calibration curves derived for the<lb/> imprinted and nonimprinted matrices on a semilogarithmic scale.<lb/> One can realize a two-step sensing response in the calibration<lb/> curve for the imprinted matrix. We believe that this behavior is<lb/> defined by two populations of binding sites which possess<lb/> </body>
			
			<listBibl>(28) Tompkins, H. G. A Users&apos;s Guide to Ellipsometry; Academic Press<lb/> Inc; London, 1993.<lb/> (29) (a) Kurbitz, S.; Porstendorfer, J.; Berg, K.-J.; Berg, G. Appl. Phys. B<lb/> -Lasers and Optics 2001, 73, 333–337. (b) Okamura, M.; Kondo, T.;<lb/> Uosaki, K. J. Phys. Chem. B 2005, 109, 9897–9904. (c) Schelm, S.;<lb/> Smith, G.-B.; Wei, G. Nano Lett. 2004, 4, 335–339.<lb/> (30) Palpant, B.; Prevel, B.; Lerme, J.; Cottancin, E.; Pellarin, M.; Treilleux,<lb/> M.; Perez, A.; Vialle, J. V.; Broyer, M. Phys. ReV. B 1998, 57, 1963–<lb/> 1970.<lb/> (31) Okamura, M.; Kondo, T.; Uosaki, K. J. Phys. Chem. B 2005, 109,<lb/> 9897–9904.<lb/> (32) Hostetler, M. J.; Wingate, J. E.; Zhong, C. J.; Harris, J. E.; Vachet,<lb/> R. W.; Clark, M. R.; Londono, J. D.; Green, S. J.; Stokes, J. J.; Wignall,<lb/> G. D.; Glish, G. L.; Porter, M. D.; Evans, N. D.; Murray, R. W.<lb/> Langmuir 1998, 14, 17–30.<lb/> (33) We assume a AuNPs volume filling coefficient of 0.64, in accordance<lb/> with a random close packing model, and use a AuNP diameter that<lb/> equals to 4.5 nm (3.5 nm mean core diameter with a 0.5 nm capping<lb/> layer).<lb/> (34) Mazel, R. Principles of Adsorption and Reaction on Solid Surfaces;<lb/> Wiley Interscience: New York, 1996; Vol. 240.<lb/> </listBibl>

			<page>7374 </page>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="footnote">Riskin et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			<body>different association constants for TNT binding, and correspond<lb/> to the association to the imprinted and nonimprinted sites in<lb/> the imprinted matrix. We use the Langmuir model for these<lb/> two populations in order to describe the experimentally derived<lb/> calibration curve. Assuming that the imprinted AuNPs matrix<lb/> includes only two types of sites, imprinted and nonimprinted,<lb/> then each of the independent sites binds TNT according to eq<lb/> 3, and the relation describing the coverage of TNT in these two<lb/> types of sites is given by eq 4:<lb/> θ )<lb/> R 1 K ass.<lb/> I [TNT]<lb/> 1 + K ass.<lb/> I [TNT]<lb/> + R 2 K ass.<lb/> NI [TNT]<lb/> 1 + K ass.<lb/> NI [TNT]<lb/> (4)<lb/> The experimental calibration curve was then fitted to eq 4,<lb/> allowing the extraction of K ass.<lb/> I<lb/> ) 1.7 × 10 13 M -1 and K ass.<lb/> NI<lb/> ) 5.4 × 10 9 M -1 , which correspond to the association constants<lb/> of TNT to the imprinted and nonimprinted sites, respectively.<lb/> Also, the analysis indicated that the relative fraction of imprinted<lb/> sites is ∼48% of the total number of binding sites in the matrix.<lb/> Evidently, both the Lineweaver-Burk analysis and the two<lb/> population fitting methods resulted in close values for each of<lb/> the association constants between TNT and the two types of<lb/> binding sites associated with the sensing matrix.<lb/> The lowest SPR detectable concentration of TNT by the<lb/> imprinted AuNPs matrix corresponded to 10 fM. Substitution<lb/> of the derived values of association constants K ass.<lb/> I and K ass.<lb/> NI<lb/> (derived from the calibration curves) into eq 4 yields the relative<lb/> coverage of the TNT occupied sites, θ/R, ∼ 4.7%. Thus, at the<lb/> lowest concentration detected, less than 5% of the total number<lb/> of binding sites are occupied. In order to understand the effects<lb/> of bound TNT on the SPR shifts and particularly to realize the<lb/> effect of the low detectable concentrations of TNT on the SPR<lb/> changes, we analyzed the experimental curves. The SPR curve<lb/> is characterized by three major values: θ p , Γ w , and R min , where<lb/> θ p and R min correspond to the minimum reflectivity plasmon<lb/> angle and the reflectance at this angle, respectively, and Γ w is<lb/> the width of the SPR curve at half of the maximum reflectance<lb/> intensity. The experimental results reveal that the binding of<lb/> TNT results in changes in R min , θ p , and Γ w . Accordingly, we<lb/> fitted the different SPR spectra in a reduced range of SPR angles<lb/> ((1.5° around the plasmon angle), by using Frenel&apos;s equations-<lb/>based five-layer model in the Winspall 2.0 program. The derived<lb/> values for the real and imaginary parts of the complex index of<lb/> refraction n ) n R + ik for the different curves were, then,<lb/> translated into the real and imaginary parts of the complex<lb/> dielectric constant values, ε&apos; and ε′′, respectively. Equation 5<lb/> relates the complex index of refraction to the complex dielectric<lb/> function, ε ) ε′ + ε″.<lb/> ε)n 2<lb/> (5)<lb/> ε′)n R<lb/> 2 -k 2<lb/> (5a)<lb/> ε″)2n R k<lb/> (5b)<lb/> The results for the fitting of the SPR curves corresponding<lb/> to the Au layer-coated SPR slide, the thioaniline monolayer-<lb/>modified surface, the surface after the stepwise deposition of<lb/> the bis-aniline-bridged AuNPs composite, and the modified<lb/> surface treated with variable concentrations of TNT are sum-<lb/>marized in Table 1. The values of the dielectric constants for<lb/> the Au-coated SPR slide are very close to the reported values<lb/> for bulk gold 35 (ε&apos; ) -13.4; ε′′ ) 1.4) and provide a further<lb/> support for the fitting procedure. Parts A and B of Figure 6<lb/> </body>

			<listBibl>(35) Palik, E. D., Ed. Handbook of Optical Constants of Solids III;<lb/> Academic Press: New York, 1998.<lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 6. (A) Calculated changes in the real-part of the dielectric constant<lb/> of the imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite upon analyzing<lb/> different concentrations of TNT. (B) Calculated changes in the imaginary<lb/> part of the dielectric constant of the imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked<lb/> AuNPs composite upon analyzing different concentrations of TNT.<lb/> Figure 7. Calculated conductivity of the imprinted bis-aniline-cross-linked<lb/> AuNPs composite upon analyzing different concentrations of TNT.<lb/>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009</note>

			<page>7375<lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AuNPs Composite for Ultrasensitive SPR Detection of TNT<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			depict the calculated values of the real part, ε′, and of the<lb/> imaginary part, ε′′, respectively, of the dielectric constant<lb/> associated with the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs matrix in<lb/> the presence of variable concentrations of TNT. The values of<lb/> the dielectric constant components are smaller than those of<lb/> bulk Au 36 and are strongly affected by the association of TNT<lb/> with the formation of the respective donor-acceptor complexes.<lb/> The real part of the dielectric constant, ε′, for the AuNPs exhibits<lb/> values that are 2-fold lower than the corresponding value for<lb/> bulk gold. Upon the increase of the TNT concentration and the<lb/> formation of the respective π-donor-acceptor complexes the<lb/> real part of the dielectric constant increases and becomes less<lb/> negative. The same tendency is observed for the imaginary part<lb/> of the dielectric constant, ε′′, that increases as the coverage of<lb/> TNT is elevated. For example, at a bulk TNT concentration of<lb/> 50 fM, ε′′ increases by 10%. The changes in ε′′ are possibly<lb/> connected to the electrical conductivity of the bis-aniline-AuNPs<lb/> matrix. According to the semiclassical Drude model for metal-<lb/>like conductor, the electrical conductivity in the optical frequen-<lb/>cies range is coupled to its optical properties. 36 The conducting<lb/> material is characterized by the complex dielectric function, ε,<lb/> and in the presence of an incident light of wavelength λ, the<lb/> conductivity, σ, is given by eq 6, where ε′′ is the imaginary<lb/> part of the dielectric constant, c is the speed of light, and ε 0 is<lb/> the free-space permittivity.<lb/> ε″ ) i2σλ/cε 0<lb/> (6)<lb/> It can be seen from this equation, that a variation of the<lb/> conductivity of the layer can cause a change in the imaginary<lb/> part of the dielectric constant. The fitting of the SPR curves,<lb/> upon the association of TNT, revealed that the imaginary part<lb/> of the dielectric constant increases as the TNT concentration is<lb/> elevated. This implies that the conductivity of the AuNPs matrix<lb/> increases, too, as the coverage of TNT becomes higher. Figure<lb/> 7 presents the calculated values of the conductivity changes as<lb/> a function of the TNT concentration. Our analysis suggests that<lb/> the electrical conductivity of the imprinted bis-aniline-cross-<lb/>linked AuNPs matrix in the absence of TNT is ∼200 S · cm -1 ,<lb/> and upon the association of 50 fM TNT with the matrix, the<lb/> conductivity changes by ∼10%, Figure 7. This conductivity<lb/> change may then lead to successful ultrasensitive detection of<lb/> TNT by the AuNPs composite. That is, at a TNT concentration<lb/> of 50 fM, and according to eq 4, and the derived values of the<lb/> association constants, we estimate that ∼17% of the binding<lb/> sites are occupied by TNT molecules. Although very few<lb/> recognition events occur in the matrix, the electronic perturba-<lb/>tions at the interparticle bis-aniline bridges translate into a<lb/> collective conductivity change of the whole composite. Presum-<lb/>ably, the localized charge transfer between the π-donor and<lb/> acceptor units alters the dielectric function and therefore the<lb/> conductivity of the interconnected nanoparticle composite,<lb/> resulting in the SPR curve changes. 37<lb/> It should be noted that recent measurements for the truly<lb/> metallic state of polyaniline reported conductivities in the order<lb/> of 10 3 S · cm -1 , in accordance with the predictions of the Drude<lb/> theory. 38 Also, the electrical conductivity of thin π-conjugated<lb/> polymer layers was recently evaluated by SPR, 39 and a value<lb/> of 600 S · cm -1 was estimated, which is in a good agreement<lb/> with the experimental value of 500 S · cm -1 , measured by the<lb/> widely used Van der Pauw method. These results support our<lb/> conclusion that the ultrasensitive, label-free, SPR method for<lb/> analyzing TNT originates, indeed, from conductivity changes<lb/> within the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNP matrix, as a result of<lb/> the association of TNT. It should be noted that in a recent STM<lb/> study 40 regarding the formation of a donor-acceptor complex<lb/> between tetracyanoethylene (acceptor) and a monolayer of a<lb/> tetramethyl xylyl dithiol (donor), a 50-fold increase in the<lb/> conductivity through the monolayer was observed upon the<lb/> formation of the complex, consistent with our analysis.<lb/> In order to highlight the importance of the present label-free<lb/> SPR method for the detection of TNT, we decided to compare<lb/> the sensitivity of our method (detection limit ∼1.2 × 10 -3 ppt)<lb/> to other reported TNT detection methods, Table 2. We found<lb/> that our method is at least 10 3 -fold more sensitive than any of<lb/> the previously reported methods.<lb/> Conclusions<lb/> A bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite synthesized on<lb/> a Au surface by an electropolymerization process was introduced<lb/> as an active matrix for the amplified surface plasmon resonance<lb/> (SPR) detection of trinitrotoluene, TNT. The formation of<lb/> π-donor-acceptor complexes between the π-donor bis-aniline<lb/> units and the TNT electron-acceptor units alters the dielectric<lb/> properties of the matrix, thus enabling the amplified SPR<lb/> detection of the TNT analyte by following the SPR reflectance<lb/> changes originating from the coupling of the localized NPs<lb/> plasmon with the surface plasmon wave associated with the Au<lb/> surface. We found that the association constant of TNT to the<lb/> bis-aniline units is 3.9 × 10 9 M -1 and defined the detection<lb/> limit for the analysis of TNT by the composite to be 10 pM.<lb/> The significance of the existence of the π-donor-acceptor<lb/> complex for analyzing TNT was demonstrated by eliminating<lb/></body>

			<listBibl>(36) Jackson, J. D. Classical Electrodynamics, 2nd ed.; John Wiley &amp; Sons:<lb/> New York, 1975.<lb/> (37) (a) Georgiadis, R.; Peterlinz, K. A.; Rahn, J. R.; Peterson, A. W.;<lb/> Grassi, J. H. Langmuir 2000, 16, 6759–6762. (b) Chegel, V. I.;<lb/> Raitman, O. A.; Lioubashevski, O.; Shirshov, Y.; Katz, E; Willner, I.<lb/> AdV. Mater. 2002, 14, 1549–1553.<lb/> (38) Lee, K.; Cho, S.; Park, S. H.; Heeger, A. J.; Lee, C.-W.; Lee, S.-H.<lb/> Nature (London) 2006, 441, 65–68.<lb/> (39) Hur, Y.; Jin, S.; Gal, Y.; Kim, J.; Kim, S.; Koh, K. Mol. Cryst. Liq.<lb/> Cryst. 2002, 377, 217–220.<lb/> (40) Kasibhatla, B. S. T.; Labonte, A. P.; Zahid, F.; Reifenberger, R. G.;<lb/> Datta, S.; Kubiak, C. P. J. Phys. Chem. B 2003, 107, 12378–12382.<lb/> (41) Wang, J.; Bhada, R. K.; Lu, J.; MacDonald, D. Anal. Chim. Acta 1998,<lb/> 361, 85–91.<lb/> (42) Zhang, H.-X.; Hu, J.-S.; Yan, C.-J.; Jiang, L.; Wan, L.-J. Phys. Chem.<lb/> Chem. Phys. 2006, 8, 3567–3572.<lb/> (43) Hrapovic, S.; Majid, E.; Liu, Y.; Male, K.; Luong, J. H. T. Anal. Chem.<lb/> 2006, 78, 5504–5512.<lb/> (44) Wang, J.; Hocevar, S. B.; Ogorevc, B. Electrochem. Commun. 2004,<lb/> 6, 176–179.<lb/> (45) Mizuta, Y.; Onodera, T.; Singh, P.; Matsumoto, K.; Miura, N.; Toko,<lb/> K. Biosens. Bioelectron. 2008, 24, 191–197.<lb/> (46) Singh, P.; Onodera, T.; Mizuta, Y.; Matsumoto, K.; Miura, N.; Toko,<lb/> K. Sens. Mater. 2007, 19, 261–273.<lb/> (47) Shankaran, D. R.; Kawaguchi, T.; Kim, S. J.; Matsumoto, K.; Toko,<lb/> K.; Miura, N. Anal. Bioanal. Chem. 2006, 386, 1313–1320.<lb/> </listBibl>

			<body>Table 1. Parameters Derived by Fitting the Experimental SPR<lb/> Curves<lb/> d, nm<lb/> n k<lb/> ε′ ε′′<lb/> σ, S · cm -1<lb/> bare Au/Cr<lb/> 54.3<lb/> 0.186<lb/> 3.91 -13.92 1.39<lb/> thioaniline SAM<lb/> 1.29 1.68<lb/> 0 2.82<lb/> AuNPs matrix<lb/> 7.03 0.1546 2.61<lb/> -6.79 0.81<lb/> 207 TNT 5 fM<lb/> 0.1601 2.58<lb/> -6.64 0.824<lb/> 212 TNT 10 fM<lb/> 0.1616 2.57<lb/> -6.60 0.83<lb/> 213 TNT 20 fM<lb/> 0.1665 2.52<lb/> -6.30 0.84<lb/> 215 TNT 50 fM<lb/> 0.1834 2.43<lb/> -5.87 0.89<lb/> 228<lb/>

			<page>7376</page>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">Riskin et al.<lb/> </note>
			
			the formation of the complex through the potential-induced<lb/> transformation of the bis-aniline π-donor units into their<lb/> quinoide electron-acceptor state.<lb/> We further advanced the analysis of TNT by introducing the<lb/> imprinting process, whereby the electropolymerization of the<lb/> bis-aniline-cross-linked composite was performed in the pres-<lb/>ence of picric acid, as a TNT analogue. The imprinted bis-aniline<lb/> AuNPs composite revealed a two-step response that included<lb/> an ultrasensitive analysis region in which TNT was detected at<lb/> a limit of 10 fM, and is attributed to the analysis of TNT by<lb/> the high-affinity imprinted association sites (K ass.<lb/> I<lb/> ) 6.4 × 10 12<lb/> M -1 ). The second detection region was observed in the 10 -10<lb/> M TNT range and is attributed to the association of TNT by<lb/> the nonimprinted bis-aniline π-donor sites (K ass.<lb/> NI<lb/> ) 3.9 × 10 9<lb/> M -1 ). The imprinted AuNPs matrix revealed impressive selec-<lb/>tivity toward the analysis of TNT.<lb/> The ultrasensitive detection of TNT by SPR spectroscopy<lb/> using the imprinted bis-aniline AuNPs composite is, to the best<lb/> of our knowledge, the most sensitive and specific sensing<lb/> interface for the TNT explosive. The resulting sensitivity of the<lb/> AuNPs composite and its stability (over two months with no<lb/> noticeable degradation), demonstrate the potential future ap-<lb/>plicability of the method, (i.e., detection of TNT in mine fields).<lb/> Furthermore, the sensing matrices could be regenerated by<lb/> rinsing off the associated TNT with a buffer solution (the<lb/> matrices were reused five times without noticeable effect on<lb/> their performance). Besides the analytical value of this research,<lb/> the study tried to address the origin for the observed sensitivity,<lb/> and to explain how a few recognition events can induce a<lb/> readable reflectance change in the SPR spectra. The theoretical<lb/> fitting of the experimental SPR curves, measured in the presence<lb/> of variable concentrations of TNT, allowed us to follow the<lb/> dielectric properties of the composite. We find that the changes<lb/> in the dielectric properties of the matrix, as a result of a few<lb/> charge transfer events at the donor-acceptor recognition sites,<lb/> are translated into a collective measurable phenomenon, namely,<lb/> a change in the dielectric function and conductivity of the<lb/> AuNPs matrix.<lb/> Experimental Section<lb/> Nanoparticles Synthesis. Au nanoparticles (AuNPs) function-<lb/>alized with 2-mercaptoethane sulfonic acid and p-aminothiophenol<lb/> were prepared by mixing a 10 mL solution containing 197 mg of<lb/> HAuCl 4 in ethanol, and a 5 mL solution containing 42 mg of<lb/> mercaptoethane sulfonate and 8 mg of p-aminothiophenol in<lb/> methanol. The two solutions were stirred in the presence of 2.5<lb/> mL of glacial acetic acid on an ice bath for 1 h. Subsequently, 7.5<lb/> mL of aqueous solution of 1 M sodium borohydride, NaBH 4 , was<lb/> added dropwise, resulting in a dark colored solution associated with<lb/> the presence of the AuNPs. The solution was stirred for one<lb/> additional hour in an ice bath, and then, for 14 h at room<lb/> temperature. The particles were successively washed and centrifuged<lb/> (twice in each solvent) with methanol, ethanol, and diethyl ether.<lb/> A mean particle size of 3.5 nm was estimated using TEM.<lb/> Chemical Modification of the Electrodes. p-Aminothiophenol-<lb/>functionalized electrodes were prepared by immersing the Au slides<lb/> for 24 h into a p-aminothiophenol ethanolic solution, 50 mM. In<lb/> order to prepare the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite on<lb/> the electrode, the surface-tethered p-aminothiophenol groups were<lb/> electropolymerized in a 0.1 M HEPES buffer solution (pH ) 7.2)<lb/> containing 1 mg · mL -1 of p-aminothiophenol-functionalized AuNPs.<lb/> The polymerization was performed by the application of 10 potential<lb/> cycles between -0.35 and 0.8 V vs Ag wire quasi-reference<lb/> electrode, at a potential scan rate of 100 mV s -1 , followed by<lb/> applying a fixed potential of 0.8 V for 30 min. The resulting films<lb/> were, then, washed with the background buffer solution to exclude<lb/> any residual monomer from the electrode. Similarly, picric acid-<lb/>imprinted oligoaniline-cross-linked films were prepared by adding<lb/> 1 mg· mL -1 picric acid to the AuNPs mixture prior to the<lb/> electropolymerization process. The extraction of the picric acid from<lb/> the film was carried out by immersing the electrodes in a 0.1 M<lb/> HEPES solution, pH ) 7.2, for 2 h at room temperature. The full<lb/> removal of picric acid from the electropolymerized film was verified<lb/> electrochemically. In a control experiment, a two-layer AuNPs<lb/> matrix was assembled on the Au-coated glass surface by the primary<lb/> association of thiopropionic acid-stabilized AuNPs (diameter 3.5<lb/> nm) on the cystamine-monolayer-functionalized gold slide, followed<lb/> by the assembly of a second AuNPs layer by cross-linking the<lb/> second layer of AuNPs to the base AuNPs layer using 1,4-butane<lb/> dithiol.<lb/> Instrumentation. A surface plasmon resonance (SPR) Kretschmann<lb/> type spectrometer NanoSPR 321 (NanoSPR devices, USA), with a<lb/> LED light source, λ ) 650 nm, and with a prism refraction index<lb/> of n ) 1.61, was used in this work. The SPR sensograms (time-<lb/>dependent reflectance changes at a constant angle) represent real-<lb/>time changes, and these were measured in situ using a home-built<lb/> fluid cell. Au-coated semitransparent glass slides (Mivitec GmbH,<lb/> Analytical µ-Systems, Germany) were used for the SPR measure-<lb/>ments. Prior to modification, the Au surface was cleaned in hot<lb/> ethanol, at 60 °C, for 30 min. For the electrochemical polymeri-<lb/>zation and SPR measurements employing in situ constant potential<lb/> application, an auxiliary Pt (0.5 mm diameter wire) and a quasi-<lb/>reversible reference Ag electrode (QRE) (0.5 mm diameter wire)<lb/> were installed into a Perspex cell (volume 0.5 cm 3 , working area<lb/>

			Table 2. Comparison of different TNT sensors.<lb/> detection method<lb/> detection limit<lb/> reference<lb/> remote microelectrode electrochemical sensor in water<lb/> 50 ppb<lb/> 41 luminiscent oligo(tetraphenyl)silole nanoparticles in water<lb/> 20 ppb<lb/> 18 quenching of fluorescence of polymer films in air<lb/> 10 ppb<lb/> 16 electrochemical detection by carbon nanotubes in water<lb/> 5 ppb<lb/> 42 biochip (on Au) via QCM or SPR in water<lb/> 1-10 ppb<lb/> 25 electrochemical detection using metallic NP-CNT composites in water<lb/> 1 ppb<lb/> 43 adsorptive stripping by carbon nanotubes-modified GCE in water<lb/> 600 ppt<lb/> 44 electrochemical detection by mesoporous SiO 2 -modified electrodes in<lb/> water<lb/> 414 ppt<lb/> 20<lb/> oligo(ethylene glycol)-based SPR in water<lb/> 80 ppt<lb/> 45 electrochemical sensing by imprinted electropolymerized<lb/> bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs in water<lb/> 46 ppt<lb/> 28<lb/> SPR, fabricated dinitrophenylated-keyhole lympet hemocyanin<lb/> (DNP-KLH) protein conjugate (in water)<lb/> 5 ppt<lb/> 46<lb/> indirect competitive immunoassay using SPR (in water)<lb/> 2 ppt<lb/> 47 SPR sensing by bis-aniline-cross-linked picric acid-imprinted<lb/> Au-nanoparticles composite<lb/> 1.2 × 10 -3 ppt<lb/> present study<lb/>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009 </note>

			<page>7377<lb/> </page>

			<note place="headnote">AuNPs Composite for Ultrasensitive SPR Detection of TNT<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/></note>

			0.4 cm 2 ). For the constant potential measurements the SPR electrode<lb/> potential was biased (vs Ag QRE), and the respective SPR curve<lb/> was recorded in the presence of 100 fM TNT. For these measure-<lb/>ments an Autolab electrochemical system (Echo Chemie, The<lb/> Netherlands) driven by GPES software was used. The error bars<lb/> presented for the different measurements correspond to N ) 5<lb/> experiments. Atomic force microscopy (AFM) images were cap-<lb/>tured in a tapping mode on a Digital Nanoscope IV instrument<lb/> employing Si cantilevers (NSC15/AIBS, MicroMash, Estonia,<lb/> resonance frequency order of 320 kHz). Ellipsometry measurements<lb/> were performed with a Woollam M-88 spectroscopic ellipsometer<lb/> equipped with the WVASE 32 software.<lb/> Fitting of Experimental Results. Fresnel&apos;s equation-based SPR<lb/> modeling for a five-layer system was performed using Winspall<lb/> 2.0 program, generously provided by Prof. W. Knoll (Max Planck<lb/> Institute for Polymer Research in Mainz, Germany. Present address:<lb/> Austrian Research Centers GmbH Donau-City-Strasse 1, 1220<lb/> Vienna, Austria). A refractive index for bulk Au, n ) 0.173 +<lb/> 3.422i, was used for the modeling as the refractive index for the<lb/> AuNPs. The Langmuir isotherm fittings were performed using<lb/> Origin 7.5 software (Origin Laboratory Corporation).<lb/> 
			</body>
			
			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgment. Parts of this research are supported by the<lb/> Voltage-Sensitive Plasmon-Resonant Nanoparticles (VSN) EC<lb/> project, and by the Israeli Ministry of Defense. M.R. is supported<lb/> by CAMBR fellowship.<lb/> Supporting Information Available: The AFM topography<lb/> image of the bis-aniline-cross-linked AuNPs composite. This<lb/> material is available free of charge via the Internet at http://<lb/> pubs.acs.org.<lb/> JA9001212<lb/></div> 

			<page>7378<lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J. AM. CHEM. SOC. 9 VOL. 131, NO. 21, 2009<lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">A R T I C L E S<lb/> </note>
			
			<note place="headnote">Riskin et al. </note>

	</text>
</tei>
