<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cytokine and Growth Factor Reviews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/>Survey <lb/>The GDNF/RET signaling pathway and human diseases <lb/>Masahide Takahashi * <lb/>Department of Pathology, Nagoya Uni6ersity Graduate School of Medicine, 65 Tsurumai-cho, Showa-ku, Nagoya 466-8550, Japan <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor (GDNF) and related molecules, neurturin, artemin and persephin, signal through a <lb/>unique multicomponent receptor system consisting of RET tyrosine kinase and glycosyl-phosphatidylinositol-anchored coreceptor <lb/>(GFRa1-4). These neurotrophic factors promote the survival of various neurons including peripheral autonomic and sensory <lb/>neurons as well as central motor and dopamine neurons, and have been expected as therapeutic agents for neurodegenerative <lb/>diseases. In addition, it turned out that the GDNF/RET signaling plays a crucial role in renal development and regulation of <lb/>spermatogonia differentiation. RET mutations cause several human diseases such as papillary thyroid carcinoma, multiple <lb/>endocrine neoplasia types 2A and 2B, and Hirschsprung&apos;s disease. The mutations resulted in RET activation or inactivation by <lb/>various mechanisms and the biological properties of mutant proteins appeared to be correlated with disease phenotypes. The <lb/>signaling pathways activated by GDNF or mutant RET are being extensively investigated to understand the molecular <lb/>mechanisms of disease development and the physiological roles of the GDNF family ligands. © 2001 Elsevier Science Ltd. All <lb/>rights reserved. <lb/>Keywords: RET proto-oncogene; Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor; Papillary thyroid carcinoma; Multiple endocrine neoplasia 2; <lb/>Hirschsprung&apos;s disease <lb/></front>

			<div type="toc">Contents <lb/>1. RET proto-oncogene . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>362 <lb/>2. GDNF family ligands and their receptors . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>363 <lb/>3. The signaling pathways via GDNF/GFRa1/RET complex. . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>364 <lb/>4. RET mutations and multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>365 <lb/>4.1. RET mutations in MEN 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>365 <lb/>4.2. Genotype-phenotype correlations in MEN 2 . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>365 <lb/>5. Transgenic mouse models for MEN 2A and MEN2B . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>367 <lb/>6. Loss-of-function RET mutations in Hirschsprung&apos;s disease . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>367 <lb/>7. Cosegregation of MEN 2A/FMTC and HSCR . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>368 <lb/>8. Concluding remarks . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>369 <lb/></div>

			<front>www.elsevier.com/locate/cytogfr <lb/> * Tel.: +81-52-744-2092; fax: + 81-52-744-2098. <lb/>E-mail address: mtakaha@med.nagoya-u.ac.jp (M. Takahashi). <lb/>1359-6101/01/$ -see front matter © 2001 Elsevier Science Ltd. All rights reserved. <lb/>PII: S 1 3 5 9 -6 1 0 1 ( 0 1 ) 0 0 0 1 2 -0 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>362 <lb/></page>

			<div type="toc">Acknowledgements . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>369 <lb/>References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>369 <lb/></div>

			<body>1. RET proto-oncogene <lb/>RET was originally identified as an oncogene acti-<lb/>vated by DNA rearrangement in 1985 [1 -3]. The RET <lb/>proto-oncogene encodes a receptor tyrosine kinase with <lb/>a cadherin-related motif and a cysteine-rich domain in <lb/>the extracellular domain and is located on chromosome <lb/>10q11.2. [4-7]. So far, three isoforms (short, middle <lb/>and long isoforms) that are generated by alternative <lb/>splicing in the 3% region have been cloned [8,9] (Fig. <lb/>1A). <lb/>RET expression was detected in human tumors of <lb/>neural crest origin such as neuroblastoma, pheochro-<lb/>mocytoma and medullary thyroid carcinoma [10 -12]. <lb/>In rodent embryonic and adult tissues, it is highly <lb/>expressed in peripheral enteric, sympathetic and sensory <lb/>neurons as well as central motor, dopamine and nora-<lb/>drenalin neurons [13 -17], suggesting an important role <lb/>of Ret in differentiation and survival of these neurons. <lb/>In addition to the nervous system, Ret expression is <lb/>observed in the excretory system such as mesonephric <lb/>duct and branching ureteric bud during embryogenesis <lb/>although it almost disappears after birth [13,15]. Con-<lb/>sistent with its expression pattern, Ret knockout mice <lb/>showed lack of enteric neurons and superior cervical <lb/>ganglion as well as renal agenesis or dysgenesis [18,19]. <lb/>Moreover, based on the precise studies of the mutant <lb/>mice, it was demonstrated that a common pool of <lb/>neural crest cells derived from the postotic hindbrain <lb/>gives rise to most of the enteric nervous system and the <lb/>superior cervical ganglion, depending on the c-Ret <lb/>function [19]. <lb/>The RET proto-oncogene was identified as the <lb/>causative gene for human papillary thyroid carcinoma, <lb/>multiple endocrine neoplasia (MEN) types 2A and 2B, <lb/>and Hirschsprung&apos;s disease (HSCR) [20 -26]. Ten rear-<lb/>ranged forms of RET referred to as RET/PTC1-9 and <lb/>ELKS/RET have been cloned from sporadic and radia-<lb/>tion-associated papillary thyroid carcinomas [27 -29]. <lb/>The intracellular domain of RET was fused to each <lb/>amino-terminal sequence of nine different activating <lb/>genes including H4 (for RET/PTC1), RIa (RET/ <lb/>PTC2), ELE1(RET/PTC3 and RET/PTC4), RFG5 <lb/>(RET/PTC5), hTIF (RET/PTC6), RFG7 (RET/PTC7), <lb/>kinectin (RET/PTC8), RFG9 (RET/PTC9) and ELKS <lb/>(ELKS/RET). Among these, the RET/PTC1 gene was <lb/>most frequently detected in sporadic papillary thyroid <lb/>carcinoma, although the frequency of RET rearrange-<lb/>ment was very different among countries. It was high <lb/>(10 -35%) in papillary carcinoma from Europe and the <lb/>United States [30,31] whereas it was very low (B 5%) in <lb/>those from Japan and Saudi Arabia [32 -34]. This may <lb/>be due to racial differences in the genetic background <lb/>or to environmental factors in these countries. <lb/>In addition, it turned out that RET rearrangement <lb/>occurred at high frequency (60 -70%) in papillary thy-<lb/>roid carcinoma of children from areas contaminated by <lb/>the Chernobyl nuclear reactor accident [35 -37]. In <lb/>contrast to sporadic papillary thyroid carcinoma from <lb/>the adult patients, a high predominance of RET/PTC3 <lb/>(approx. a 3:1 ratio of RET/PTC3 and RET/PTC1) <lb/>was observed in these childhood papillary thyroid car-<lb/>cinomas. Interestingly, several reports demonstrated <lb/>that different types of RET rearrangement confer dis-<lb/>tinct phenotypic properties on neoplastic thyroid cells <lb/>[38 -41]. That is, RET/PTC3 was frequently found in <lb/>solid/follicular variant of papillary thyroid carcinoma <lb/>whereas RET/PTC1 was more common in typical pap-<lb/>illary type. Moreover, RET/PTC1 and RET/PTC3 ap-<lb/>peared to be associated with post-Chernobyl papillary <lb/>carcinomas of long and short latency, respectively [40]. <lb/>Because similar RET rearrangement can be induced in <lb/>cell lines by in vitro X-irradiation and was found in <lb/>thyroid tumors from patients who had received external <lb/>radiation [42 -44], it seems likely that post-Chernobyl <lb/>papillary carcinomas developed as a direct consequence <lb/>of radiation exposure. <lb/>RET mutations identified in MEN 2A, MEN 2B and <lb/>HSCR, and their biological effects are described in <lb/>detail in the separate sections. <lb/>Fig. 1. (A) Schematic illustration of three RET isoforms and binding <lb/>sites for signaling molecules. Three isoforms are generated by alterna-<lb/>tive splicing in the 3% region downstream of tyrosine 1062 (Y1062). <lb/>Y905, Y1015, Y1062 and Y1096 represent binding sites for the <lb/>designated signaling molecules. S, signal sequence; CAD, cadherin-re-<lb/>lated motif; CYS, cysteine-rich region; TK1 and TK2, tyrosine kinase <lb/>domain. (B) Amino acid sequences around tyrosine 1062 in three <lb/>isoforms. The underline indicates the putative binding site for the <lb/>PTB domains of SHC and SNT/FRS2 docking proteins. Isoleucine <lb/>(I) at codon 1057 and asparagine (N) at codon 1059 were reported to <lb/>be important for binding of their PTB domains. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>363 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2. Intracellular signaling pathways mediated by activated RET. <lb/>2. GDNF family ligands and their receptors <lb/>The glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor <lb/>(GDNF) family ligands (GDNF, neurturin (NRTN), <lb/>artemin (ARTN) and persephin (PSPN)) form a new <lb/>family of neurotrophic factors that are structurally <lb/>related to transforming growth factor (TGF)-b [45-48]. <lb/>These factors contain seven conserved, similarly spaced <lb/>cysteine residues, referred to as a cysteine knot motif, <lb/>and show approximately 40% amino acid identity each <lb/>other. GDNF, NRTN and ARTN were reported to <lb/>support the survival of a broad spectrum of both <lb/>peripheral and central neurons, whereas PSPN pro-<lb/>moted the survival of motor and nigral dopaminergic <lb/>neurons in culture as well as in vivo but did not support <lb/>the survival of any peripheral neurons examined. <lb/>Unlike ligands for other receptor tyrosine kinases, <lb/>the GDNF family ligands signal through a unique <lb/>multicomponent receptor complex consisting of glyco-<lb/>syl-phosphatidylinositol (GPI)-anchored coreceptor <lb/>(GFRa1 -4) as a ligand binding component and RET <lb/>receptor tyrosine kinase as a signaling component (Fig. <lb/>2) [48 -70]. GDNF, NRTN, ARTN and PSPN use <lb/>GFRa1, GFRa2, GFRa3 and GFRa4 as the preferred <lb/>ligand-binding receptors, respectively, although alterna-<lb/>tive ligand-coreceptor interaction also appears to occur <lb/>in culture. That is, GDNF can bind to GFRa2 and <lb/>GFRa3 in the presence of RET, and NRTN and <lb/>ARTN can bind to GFRa1 [48,55,57,58,60]. In addi-<lb/>tion, consistent with the fact that a cadherin-related <lb/>motif is present in the RET extracellular domain, Ca 2 + <lb/>ions were required for RET activation by GDNF and <lb/>NRTN [56]. <lb/>Despite the promiscuity in ligand-receptor specificity <lb/>in culture, however, each of the GDNF family ligands <lb/>showed a rather specific role in vivo through the pre-<lb/>ferred GFRa -RET complex. Gdnf −/− or Gfra1 −/− <lb/>mice exhibited phenotypes similar to that of Ret −/− <lb/>mice [18,71-75]. These mice lacked enteric neurons <lb/>and showed renal agenesis or dysgenesis, although <lb/>the superior cervical ganglion that Ret −/− mice lacked <lb/>was normal or moderately affected in Gdnf −/− or <lb/>Gfra1 −/− mice. In Nrtn −/− or Gfra2 −/− mice, the <lb/>parasympathetic cholinergic innervation was dramati-<lb/>cally reduced in the lacrimal and submandibular sali-<lb/>vary glands as well as in the intestine [76,77]. Gfra3 −/− <lb/>mice exhibited severe defects in the superior cervical <lb/>ganglion whereas other ganglia appeared normal [78]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>364 <lb/></page>

			<body>Taken together, it is likely that the preferred ligand-<lb/>GFRa -RET complexes have specific roles in vivo, <lb/>although Artn −/− , Pspn −/− or Gfra4 −/− mice have <lb/>not been reported yet. <lb/>3. The signaling pathways via GDNF/GFRa1/RET <lb/>complex <lb/>Since GDNF was discovered to represent a RET <lb/>ligand, extensive studies on intracellular signaling <lb/>through RET have been performed. Like other receptor <lb/>tyrosine kinases, RET can activate various signaling <lb/>pathways including RAS/extracellular signal-regulated <lb/>kinase (ERK), phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K)/ <lb/>AKT, p38 mitogen activated protein kinase (MAPK) <lb/>and c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK) pathways [79-92]. <lb/>It is well known that these signals are transmitted via <lb/>phosphotyrosine present in the intracellular domains of <lb/>activated receptors. RET short and middle isoforms <lb/>contain 16 tyrosine residues in their intracellular do-<lb/>mains and RET long isoform has two additional tyrosi-<lb/>nes in the carboxy-terminal tail. Among these tyrosines, <lb/>tyrosine 905, 1015, 1062 and 1096 represent binding <lb/>sites for GRB10, phospholipase Cg (PLCg), SHC/ <lb/>SNT(FRS2)/Enigma and GRB2, respectively (Fig. 1A) <lb/>[82,93 -100]. The former three tyrosines are conserved <lb/>in all three RET isoforms but tyrosine 1096 is present <lb/>in the long isoform only. Although the sequence <lb/>around tyrosine 981 matches the consensus sequence <lb/>for binding of p85 subunit of PI3K, it does not appear <lb/>to directly bind to RET as described below. <lb/>Interestingly, our recent results demonstrated that all <lb/>of the RAS/ERK, PI3K/AKT, p38MAPK and JNK <lb/>pathways are activated mainly through tyrosine 1062 <lb/>that is a binding site for SHC adaptor proteins [92]. <lb/>After binding of SHC to tyrosine 1062 following <lb/>GDNF stimulation, SHC further associates with <lb/>GAB1/2 adaptor proteins and GRB2/SOS complex, <lb/>leading to the activation of PI3K/AKT and RAS/ERK <lb/>signaling pathways, respectively (Fig. 2). GAB1/2 di-<lb/>rectly associates with p85 subunit of PI3K, resulting in <lb/>the activation of PI3K [86,92,101]. However, the fact <lb/>that mutation of tyrosine 1062 did not completely <lb/>abolish the activation of RAS/ERK and PI3K/AKT <lb/>pathways suggested the presence of alternative path-<lb/>ways. Besset et al. [101] reported that because AKT but <lb/>not ERK activation was almost completely abolished <lb/>by double mutations of tyrosines 1062 and 1096, bind-<lb/>ing of GRB2/GAB2 complex to tyrosine 1096 may <lb/>offer an alternative route for activation of the PI3K/ <lb/>AKT signaling pathway. Unexpectedly, although ty-<lb/>rosine 1096 represents a binding site for GRB2 (Fig. <lb/>1A), it does not appear that GRB2 biding to this <lb/>tyrosine plays an important role in the activation of the <lb/>RAS/ERK signaling pathway [92,101]. We and others <lb/>found that the RAS/ERK and PI3K pathways via <lb/>tyrosine 1062 are important for activation of CREB <lb/>and NFkB transcription factors, respectively, [92] as <lb/>well as for PC12 cell survival (Fig. 2) [102]. In addition, <lb/>RAS activation was essential for RET-induced cell <lb/>differentiation in PC12 cells [103] whereas PI3K signal-<lb/>ing independent of AKT was necessary for lamellipodia <lb/>formation that is a critical event in neuritegenesis (Fig. <lb/>2) [81,100]. <lb/>SNT/FRS2 is a lipid anchored docking protein with <lb/>a phosphotyrosine-binding (PTB) domain. We recently <lb/>found that SNT/FRS2 binds to tyrosine 1062 of RET <lb/>in a GDNF-dependent manner and is associated with <lb/>GRB2/SOS complex but not GAB1, suggesting that <lb/>SNT/FRS2 may be involved mainly in the activation of <lb/>the RAS/ERK signaling pathway (Fig. 2) [104]. These <lb/>findings imply that tyrosine 1062 in RET provides a site <lb/>for the interaction of multiple signaling molecules and <lb/>that the balance of SHC and SNT/FRS2 binding may <lb/>affect the nature of the intracellular signaling in RET-<lb/>expressing cells. Interestingly, it was suggested that <lb/>RET which moved to lipid rafts following GDNF <lb/>stimulation triggers the signal through SNT/FRS2 <lb/>whereas RET outside rafts triggers it through SHC <lb/>(Fig. 2) [105]. <lb/>The binding affinity of SHC and SNT/FRS2 to RET <lb/>was different among three isoforms, although the con-<lb/>sensus sequence for binding of the phosphotyrosine <lb/>binding (PTB) domain of SHC and SNT/FRS2 is con-<lb/>served in the sequence amino-terminal to tyrosine 1062 <lb/>in them (Fig. 1B) [104]. Their binding affinity to RET <lb/>middle isoform was significantly low compared with <lb/>that to RET short and long isoforms. Because the <lb/>sequences carboxy-terminal to tyrosine 1062 were dif-<lb/>ferent among three isoforms (Fig. 1B), this suggested <lb/>the importance of these carboxy-terminal sequences for <lb/>the binding of SHC and SNT/FRS PTB domains [104]. <lb/>In addition, their low binding affinity to RET middle <lb/>isoform was in agreement with the fact that transform-<lb/>ing activity of RET middle isoform with MEN2A mu-<lb/>tation was much lower than that of RET short or long <lb/>isoform with MEN2A mutation [106]. <lb/>The p38MAPK, JNK and MEK5/big mitogen-acti-<lb/>vated protein kinase 1 (BMK1) pathways are also <lb/>activated through tyrosine 1062 [92,107]. Although it is <lb/>unknown whether SHC or SNT/FRS2 binding to ty-<lb/>rosine 1062 is required for activation of these pathways, <lb/>activation of the JNK pathway by mutant RET protein <lb/>was shown to be induced via Rho/Rac-related small <lb/>GTPase, such as CDC42 [84]. Because it is possible that <lb/>the PI3K signaling regulates the functions of these <lb/>small G proteins following GDNF stimulation, the <lb/>JNK pathway may be downstream of PI3K. In addi-<lb/>tion, tyrosine phosphorylation of several other signal-<lb/>ing molecules including FAK, paxillin, p130 CAS and <lb/>p62Dok was induced by PI3K signaling [85,86]. Among <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>365 <lb/></page>

			<body>these proteins, phosphorylation of FAK was Rho-de-<lb/>pendent (Fig. 2) whereas phosphorylation of paxillin <lb/>and p130 CAS was Rho-independent. <lb/>More recently, the presence of RET-independent sig-<lb/>nals triggered by GDNF was suggested [88,108]. <lb/>GDNF was able to activate Src-type kinases and PLCg <lb/>in sensory neurons from Ret −/− mice and Src kinases <lb/>were associated with GFRa1 in Triton-insoluble frac-<lb/>tions including lipid rafts. GDNF also promoted the <lb/>survival of cultured neuronal cells expressing GFRa1 <lb/>but lacking RET, and induced CREB and Fos activa-<lb/>tion in them [88,108]. Because the phenotypes of <lb/>Gdnf −/− and Gfra1 −/− mice were very similar to that <lb/>of Ret −/− mice, these findings suggested that RET-in-<lb/>dependent GDNF signaling through GFRa1 may play <lb/>a role postnatally in neuronal functions rather than <lb/>neuronal differentiation during embryogenesis. <lb/>4. RET mutations and multiple endocrine neoplasia <lb/>type 2 <lb/>4.1. RET mutations in MEN 2 <lb/>Germline RET mutations are responsible for devel-<lb/>opment of multiple endocrine neoplasia (MEN) types <lb/>2A and 2B and familial medullary thyroid carcinoma <lb/>(FMTC) [21 -24,109]. MEN2A and MEN2B are auto-<lb/>somal dominant cancer syndromes characterized by <lb/>medullary thyroid carcinoma and pheochromocytoma. <lb/>In addition to these, parathyroid hyperplasia develops <lb/>in 10-30% of the affected members of MEN 2A <lb/>families. MEN 2B patients are known to develop <lb/>medullary thyroid carcinoma with an earlier age of <lb/>tumor onset and show a more complex phenotype <lb/>including ganglioneuromatosis of the gastrointestinal <lb/>tract and mucosa, medullated corneal nerves, and mar-<lb/>fanoid habitus. FMTC is characterized by medullary <lb/>thyroid carcinoma only that usually develops at a later <lb/>stage in life. <lb/>MEN2A mutations have been identified in one of six <lb/>cysteine residues (codons 609, 611, 618 and 620 in exon <lb/>10, and codons 630 and 634 in exon 11) in the RET <lb/>extracellular domain [109]. In FMTC, point mutations <lb/>were detected at cysteine residues like MEN2A muta-<lb/>tions or at codon 768, 804 or 891 (exons 13, 14 or 15) <lb/>in the tyrosine kinase domain [109]. In addition, a 9 or <lb/>12 base pair duplication in exon 11 and a 9 base pair <lb/>duplication in exon 8 that create an additional cysteine <lb/>residue were reported in two MEN 2A families and one <lb/>FMTC family, respectively [110-112]. Although mis-<lb/>sense mutations at codon 790 or 791 were reported in <lb/>five German FMTC or MEN 2A families [113], these <lb/>have not been identified in families from any other <lb/>countries. <lb/>Two missense point mutations at codon 918 (exon <lb/>16) or codon 883 (exon 15) were associated with MEN <lb/>2B [109]. Methionine at codon 918 and alanine at <lb/>codon 883 were replaced with threonine and phenylala-<lb/>nine (designated M918T and A883F), respectively. <lb/>More than 95% of MEN 2B patients are accounted for <lb/>by the M918T mutation but fewer than 4% are ac-<lb/>counted for by the A883F mutation. Recently, double <lb/>germline mutations at codon 804 and 806 were reported <lb/>in a Japanese patient that had clinical features charac-<lb/>teristic of MEN 2B including medullary carcinoma, <lb/>mucosal neuroma, marfanoid habitus, thickening of <lb/>corneal nerves (grade 4) and medullary hyperplasia of <lb/>bilateral adrenal gland [114,115]. <lb/>4.2. Genotype-phenotype correlations in MEN 2 <lb/>We and others demonstrated that all of MEN2A, <lb/>MEN2B and FMTC mutations except mutations of <lb/>codons 790 and 791 can induce constitutive activation <lb/>of RET proteins [115-123]. As a consequence, RET <lb/>became the first case that gain-of-function mutations of <lb/>a proto-oncogene were implicated in the etiology of an <lb/>inherited cancer syndrome. Cysteine mutations iden-<lb/>tified in the MEN 2A and FMTC families activate RET <lb/>by inducing its disulfide-linked homodimerization <lb/>(Table 1) [116,117]. These cysteine residues are thought <lb/>to be normally involved in the formation of intramolec-<lb/>ular disulfide bonds that are necessary for appropriate <lb/>tertiary structure of the RET extracellular domain. Our <lb/>hypothesis on RET activation by the MEN2A mutation <lb/>is that when a cysteine residue is mutated to a non-cys-<lb/>teine residue, a partner cysteine that is involved in the <lb/>formation of a disulfide bond may become free and <lb/>form an aberrant intermolecular disulfide bond between <lb/>two mutant RET, leading to the constitutive activation <lb/>of intrinsic tyrosine kinase. <lb/>In the cases of MEN2B mutations identified in the <lb/>tyrosine kinase domain, RET was activated in a <lb/>monomeric form, probably due to a conformational <lb/>change of catalytic core of the kinase domain [117-<lb/>119]. Several reports suggested that the MEN2B muta-<lb/>tions alter the substrate specificity of the RET protein <lb/>[86,117,124,125], although which signaling pathway is <lb/>important for development of the MEN 2B clinical <lb/>phenotype is still unclear. In addition, we found that <lb/>tyrosine residues in the kinase domain essential for <lb/>transforming activity are different between RET-<lb/>MEN2A and RET-MEN2B mutant proteins. That is, <lb/>tyrosine 905 and tyrosines 864 and 952 were required <lb/>for the activity of RET-MEN2A and RET-MEN2B <lb/>proteins, respectively (Table 1) [119,123]. It is well <lb/>known that a tyrosine residue is conserved in all ty-<lb/>rosine kinases at the same position as tyrosine 905 in <lb/>RET and plays an crucial role in their biological and <lb/>biochemical activities. Because the MEN2B mutations <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>366 <lb/></page>

			<body>at codons 918 and 883 are located near tyrosine 905, a <lb/>conformational change in the region including these <lb/>amino acids may result in the shift of tyrosine residues <lb/>(tyrosine 905 tyrosines 864 and 952) that are required <lb/>for transforming activity of the RET-MEN2B mutant <lb/>protein. <lb/>Recently, a novel V804M/Y806C double mutation <lb/>was identified in a Japanese female MEN2B patient <lb/>[114]. These two mutations were present in the same <lb/>allele and the Y806C mutation was inherited from her <lb/>father who showed no symptoms of tumor. On the <lb/>other hand, the V804M mutation was a de novo muta-<lb/>tion in the patient. Transforming activity of RET with <lb/>the V804M/Y806C double mutation was approximately <lb/>8 -13-fold higher than that of RET with a single <lb/>V804M or Y806C mutation [115]. Moreover, we found <lb/>that tyrosines 864 and 952 are also important for <lb/>transforming activity of RET with this double mutation <lb/>as observed for RET-M918T and RET-A883F mutant <lb/>proteins, suggesting that these three RET-MEN2B mu-<lb/>tant proteins have similar biological properties (Table <lb/>1) [115]. This was the first example to show that two <lb/>germline RET mutations in the same allele were respon-<lb/>sible for development of MEN 2B. <lb/>Cysteine mutations in the RET extracellular domain <lb/>sometimes induce the FMTC phenotype. Of these mu-<lb/>tations (codons 609, 611, 618, 620, 630 and 634), ap-<lb/>proximately 30% occurred at codon 634 and more than <lb/>60% occurred at codons 609, 618 and 620 in FMTC <lb/>families [126]. This is in contrast with the fact that <lb/>cysteine 634 mutations were detected in approximately <lb/>85% of the MEN 2A families. The transforming activity <lb/>of RET with codon 609, 618 or 620 mutation was <lb/>significantly low compared with that of RET with <lb/>codon 634 mutation (designated RET-Cys634) (Table <lb/>1), resulting from the impairment of cell surface expres-<lb/>sion of the former mutant proteins [121,127]. Their low <lb/>transforming activity may predispose to development of <lb/>FMTC rather than MEN 2A. Although three kinase <lb/>domain mutations at codons 768, 804 and 891 identified <lb/>in some FMTC families activate RET in a monomeric <lb/>form like the MEN2B mutations, the transforming <lb/>activity of these FMTC mutant proteins was also very <lb/>low compared with that of RET-Cys634 or RET-<lb/>MEN2B protein (Table 1) [123]. Taken together with <lb/>the fact that pheochromocytoma does not always de-<lb/>velop in the affected members of MEN 2A, low trans-<lb/>forming activity of the FMTC mutant proteins <lb/>supported the view that the threshold of transformation <lb/>is low in thyroid C cells and relatively high in adrenal <lb/>chromaffin cells. As observed for RET with cysteine <lb/>mutations, tyrosine 905 was required for transforming <lb/>activity of the RET-FMTC proteins with codon 768, <lb/>804 or 891 mutation (Table 1) [123], suggesting these <lb/>FMTC mutations may not alter the substrate specificity <lb/>of the RET protein. <lb/>In addition, we found that mutation of tyrosine 1062 <lb/>markedly decrease the transforming activity of all of <lb/>RET-MEN2A, RET-MEN2B and RET-FMTC mutant <lb/>proteins (Table 1) [93,115,123]. This finding is reason-<lb/>able because many signals including the RAS/ERK, <lb/>PI3K/AKT, JNK, p38MAPK and MEK5/BMK1 path-<lb/>ways are activated through tyrosine 1062 as mentioned <lb/>above (Fig. 2) [91,92,107]. Recently, Segouffin-Cariou <lb/>and Billaud [91] reported the importance of the PI3K/ <lb/>AKT signaling pathway for transforming activity of <lb/>RET-MEN2 proteins, although further investigation of <lb/>intracellular signaling pathways activated by mutant <lb/>RET will be required to deeply understand the molecu-<lb/>lar mechanisms of tumor development by RET <lb/>mutations. <lb/>Table 1 <lb/>Characterization of RET with MEN2A, MEN2B or FMTC mutations <lb/>Mutations <lb/>Transforming activity <lb/>Disulfide-linked dimerization <lb/>Tyrosines required for transforming activity <lb/>Phenotype <lb/>High <lb/>Yes <lb/>C634X a <lb/>Y905, Y1062 <lb/>MEN 2A <lb/>FMTC <lb/>C609X <lb/>Low Intermediate <lb/>FMTC <lb/>C618X <lb/>Y905, Y1062 <lb/>Yes <lb/>C620X <lb/>MEN 2A <lb/>E768D <lb/>V804L <lb/>Low <lb/>No <lb/>Y905, Y1062 <lb/>FMTC <lb/>S891A <lb/>M918T <lb/>A883F <lb/>No <lb/>High <lb/>Y864, Y952, Y1062 <lb/>MEN 2B <lb/>V804M/ <lb/>Y806C <lb/>a X, any amino acids. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>367 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. Transgenic mouse models for MEN 2A and MEN2B <lb/>To date, several transgenic mouse models for MEN <lb/>2A or MEN 2B have been generated by introducing <lb/>mutant RET genes. Mice expressing a RET-MEN2A <lb/>gene under the control of the rat calcitonin gene-related <lb/>peptide/calcitonin (CGRP/CT) promoter or Moloney <lb/>murine leukemia virus long terminal repeat (LTR) have <lb/>been produced [128,129]. In case the CGRP/CT pro-<lb/>moter was used to specifically express the transgene in <lb/>thyroid C cells, animals of two transgenic mouse lines <lb/>displayed C cell hyperplasia and subsequently devel-<lb/>oped medullary thyroid carcinoma with a complete <lb/>penetrance at 14 months of age [128]. Despite the <lb/>transgene expression, no pathological change was ob-<lb/>served in the adrenal gland of transgenic mice. It was <lb/>suggested that this may be due to an insufficient level of <lb/>the RET-MEN2A mutant protein to exert an effect in <lb/>the adrenal gland. <lb/>We recently generated transgenic mice carrying the <lb/>RET-MEN2A gene under the control of MoMuLV <lb/>LTR [129]. They also developed C cell hyperplasia as <lb/>early as 4 weeks and developed medullary thyroid <lb/>carcinoma with a complete penetrance at 6 months of <lb/>age. Interestingly, although the mice expressed the <lb/>transgene and its protein product at high levels in <lb/>several tissues including brain, liver, and heart, no <lb/>pathological change was found in these tissues. RET <lb/>dimerization and its complex formation with Shc and <lb/>Grb2 adaptor proteins were detected in medullary car-<lb/>cinoma but not in brain, liver and heart of transgenic <lb/>mice. Our experimental results suggested the possibility <lb/>that high levels of expression of certain cell surface <lb/>proteins such as GFRa may interfere with dimerization <lb/>of the RET-MEN2A protein in brain, liver and heart, <lb/>leading to tissue-specific tumor development in trans-<lb/>genic mice. In this respect, it is interesting to note that <lb/>overexpression of Leukocyte Common Antigen-Related <lb/>(LAR) protein tyrosine phosphatase on the cell surface <lb/>also interfered with dimerization of the RET-MEN2A <lb/>protein and suppressed its oncogenic activity [130]. <lb/>Thus, it seems likely that expression of certain cell <lb/>surface proteins in the affected cells modifies the clinical <lb/>phenotypes of MEN 2 syndromes by impairing the <lb/>RET dimerization. <lb/>Transgenic mice expressing the RET-MEN2B gene <lb/>were produced using the human dopamine b-hydroxy-<lb/>lase (DbH) promoter or the human calcitonin gene <lb/>promoter [131-133]. The DbH promoter was expected <lb/>to efficiently function in the sympathetic and enteric <lb/>nervous systems as well as the adrenal gland. DbH-<lb/>RET-MEN2B transgenic mice developed benign neu-<lb/>roglial tumors, histologically identical to human <lb/>ganglioneuromatosis, in the sympathetic ganglia and <lb/>adrenal medullae, although malignant transformation <lb/>never occurred. On the other hand, the enteric nervous <lb/>system was not affected in these mice [131]. This resis-<lb/>tance may reflect, in part, a relatively low level of the <lb/>DbH promoter activity in enteric neurons. Unexpect-<lb/>edly, mice expressing high levels of the DbH-RET-<lb/>MEN2B gene displayed renal agenesis or dysgenesis as <lb/>observed in Ret-knockout mice. Gestblom et al. [132] <lb/>suggested that renal malformation could be secondary <lb/>to the expression of the RET-MEN2B transgene by <lb/>hyperplastic sympathoadrenal tissues that competes <lb/>with endogenous renal Ret for Gfra-1 or other signal-<lb/>ing components. <lb/>In case the human calcitonin gene promoter as a <lb/>regulatory unit was used for the expression of the <lb/>RET-MEN2B gene, one transgenic mouse line that <lb/>developed C cell hyperplasia at a high frequency was <lb/>established, although development of medullary thyroid <lb/>carcinoma was observed in only 13% of mice [133]. <lb/>Taken together with the fact that the CGRP/CT-RET-<lb/>MEN2A transgenic mice mentioned above had the vari-<lb/>able latency period for medullary carcinoma, this <lb/>finding supported the view that additional genetic alter-<lb/>ations are required for malignant transformation of <lb/>thyroid C cells. <lb/>More ideal transgenic mouse model for MEN 2B was <lb/>generated by introducing the mutation into mouse en-<lb/>dogenous Ret gene [134]. Gene targeting techniques in <lb/>conjunction with Cre/loxP site-specific recombination <lb/>were used to introduce the MEN2B (Met919Thr) muta-<lb/>tion into the corresponding exon of the mouse Ret <lb/>gene. Heterozygous mutant mice displayed hyperplasia <lb/>of thyroid C-cells and adrenal chromaffin cells, al-<lb/>though they were less severely affected than humans <lb/>with MEN 2B. Mutant homozygotes resembled the <lb/>human syndrome more closely, displaying an earlier <lb/>incidence and increased severity of C-cell hyperplasia <lb/>and chromaffin cell hyperplasia that progressed to <lb/>pheochromocytoma. However, these homozygotes did <lb/>not develop medullary thyroid carcinoma and gan-<lb/>glioneuromatosis of the gastrointestinal tract and mu-<lb/>cosa that are characteristic of human MEN 2B, <lb/>suggesting that the accumulation of secondary genetic <lb/>alterations is also required for development of <lb/>medullary carcinoma in these mice. Moreover, neuro-<lb/>matous enlargement of sympathetic ganglia as well as a <lb/>male reproductive defect were observed in ho-<lb/>mozygotes. They exhibited normal mouting and pro-<lb/>duced mature sperm. Because erectile dysfunction with <lb/>a neuroloical basis is common in human with MEN 2B, <lb/>a likely explanation was that mutant mice also had a <lb/>erectile defect [134] <lb/>6. Loss-of-function RET mutations in Hirschsprung&apos;s <lb/>disease <lb/>Hirschsprung&apos;s disease (HSCR) is a congenital mal-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>368 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3. Mechanisms of RET dysfunction by HSCR mutations. Three <lb/>representative mechanisms of RET dysfunction by the designated <lb/>HSCR mutations are shown. In addition to these, we recently found <lb/>that several mutations (E762Q, S767R, R972G, M980T) identified in <lb/>the kinase domain severely impaired the PLCg signaling pathway in <lb/>a neuronal cell line [145]. <lb/>of the tyrosine kinase family [145]. Fourth, some muta-<lb/>tions (E762Q, S767R, R972G, M980T) that were also <lb/>identified in the kinase domain severely impaired the <lb/>activation of PLCg in SK-N-MC human neuronal cells, <lb/>whereas the RAS/ERK and PI3K/AKT pathways were <lb/>slightly affected [145]. Taken together, these results <lb/>suggested that several signaling pathways including <lb/>RAS/ERK. PI3K/AKT and PLCg pathways may coop-<lb/>eratively function for normal development of the en-<lb/>teric nervous system. <lb/>Recently, Bordeaux et al. [146] reported that the <lb/>expression of normal RET kinase can induce apotosis <lb/>and this pro-apoptotic effect is inhibited by GDNF. In <lb/>addition, It turned out that RET is a substrate for <lb/>caspase-3 and this caspase cleavage is required for its <lb/>pro-apoptotic effect. All of five HSCR mutations exam-<lb/>ined impaired GDNF-control of RET pro-apoptotic <lb/>activity [146], implying that HSCR may result from <lb/>apoptosis of RET-expressing enteric neuroblasts. <lb/>7. Cosegregation of MEN 2A/FMTC and HSCR <lb/>It has been reported that HSCR and MEN 2A/ <lb/>FMTC co-segregate in a sizeable fraction of families <lb/>and that affected members carry a single RET muta-<lb/>tions within the coding sequence [147,148]. Screening of <lb/>the RET gene in these families led to the identification <lb/>of point mutations at either cysteine 609, 618 or 620 <lb/>that segregated with both HSCR and MEN 2A/FMTC <lb/>phenotypes. These mutations were identical to previ-<lb/>ously described MEN2A/FMTC mutations and no ad-<lb/>ditional mutations were found after sequencing of the <lb/>entire RET coding region. We and others demonstrated <lb/>that these mutations markedly decreased the RET cell <lb/>surface expression like the HSCR mutations identified <lb/>formation associated with aganglionosis of the gas-<lb/>trointestinal tract. Based on the length of the agan-<lb/>glionic segment, it is classified into two groups: patients <lb/>with aganglionosis as far as the rectosigmoidal junction <lb/>(short segment type) and patients with aganglionosis <lb/>beyond the rectosigmoidal junction (long segment <lb/>type). RET mutations appeared to account for approxi-<lb/>mately 50% of familial and 10-20% of sporadic cases <lb/>of HSCR, most of which (approx. 75%) were associated <lb/>with long segment HSCR. A variety of missense, non-<lb/>sense and frameshift mutations have been identified <lb/>along the whole coding sequence of RET [25,26,135-<lb/>137]. <lb/>Based on functional analyses of RET with HSCR <lb/>mutations, it turned out that at least four mechanisms <lb/>of RET dysfunction are responsible for development of <lb/>HSCR. First, most mutations identified in the RET <lb/>extracellular domain markedly impaired the RET cell <lb/>surface expression, probably due to incorrect folding of <lb/>the RET protein (Fig. 3) [138-140]. As a result, the low <lb/>amount of the RET protein at the cell surface would <lb/>transmit a signal below the threshold required to elicit <lb/>a trophic response in enteric neuroblasts during em-<lb/>bryogenesis. It is interesting to note that long segment <lb/>HSCR mutations more severely impair the RET cell <lb/>surface expression than short segment HSCR mutation, <lb/>suggesting that the levels of the RET cell surface ex-<lb/>pression may correlate to the severity of HSCR [139]. <lb/>Second, a couple of mutations identified in the carboxy-<lb/>terminal tail impaired the SHC binding to RET (Fig. <lb/>3), thus resulting in RET-mediated signaling defect <lb/>[106,141]. As mentioned above, SHC binding is respon-<lb/>sible for at least two major signaling pathways includ-<lb/>ing RAS/ERK and PI3K/AKT pathways that may play <lb/>a crucial role in neuronal differentiation and survival <lb/>(Fig. 2). Third, several mutations in the kinase domain <lb/>almost completely abolished the RET tyrosine kinase <lb/>activity (Fig. 3) [142-145]. These mutations occurred at <lb/>amino acids that are highly conserved among members <lb/>Fig. 4. Dual effects of cysteine 609, 618 and 620 mutations on RET <lb/>function. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>369 <lb/></page>

			<body>in the RET extracellular domain, whereas they were <lb/>also able to induce the aberrant formation of disulfide-<lb/>linked RET homodimers at low levels, leading to con-<lb/>stitutive activation of the mutant RET proteins (Fig. 4) <lb/>[121,149,150]. Cysteine 609, 618 or 620 mutation might <lb/>alter the folding of RET, partially interfering with RET <lb/>maturation, intracellular trafficking or stable expression <lb/>at the plasma membrane. Although the level of RET <lb/>dimerization was low, the activity of these mutant RET <lb/>could be sufficient to trigger the development of <lb/>medullary thyroid carcinoma as well as pheochromocy-<lb/>toma. On the other hand, the decrease of RET cell <lb/>surface expression in enteric neuroblasts during em-<lb/>bryogenesis would transmit a signal below the <lb/>threshold necessary for their complete differentiation or <lb/>for prevention of their inappropriate apoptosis. Thus, it <lb/>seems likely that a single mutation at codon 609, 618 or <lb/>620 functions as either a gain-of-function mutation or a <lb/>loss-of-function mutation, depending on the cell types <lb/>expressed (Fig. 4) [150]. <lb/>8. Concluding remarks <lb/>In the past 10 years, studies on RET signaling have <lb/>provided us with many interesting findings on kidney <lb/>morphogenesis, neurogenesis and oncogenesis. In addi-<lb/>tion, it was recently reported that GDNF regulates <lb/>differentiation of spermatogonia, suggesting the possi-<lb/>bility that reduced spermatogonia pools in infertile men <lb/>might be restored by activating the RET signaling [151]. <lb/>However, despite these extensive studies of the signaling <lb/>pathways mediated by activated RET, we still do not <lb/>know precisely how each signaling component con-<lb/>tributes to these biological events. A deeper under-<lb/>standing of the signaling network will be necessary not <lb/>only elucidate to the molecular mechanisms of cell <lb/>growth, differentiation and survival but also to develop <lb/>therapeutic strategies for human diseases caused by <lb/>RET mutations. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>I would like to thank members of my laboratory for <lb/>their excellent contributions to the work presented in <lb/>this review. This study was supported in part by a <lb/>grant-in-aid for COE (Center of Excellence) research <lb/>from the Ministry of Education, Science, Sports and <lb/>Culture of Japan. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Takahashi M, Ritz J, Cooper GM. Activation of a novel <lb/>human transforming gene, ret, by DNA rearrangement. Cell <lb/>1985;42:581 -8. <lb/>[2] Takahashi M, Cooper GM. ret transforming gene encodes a <lb/>fusion protein homologous to tyrosine kinases. Mol Cell Biol <lb/>1987;7:1378 -85. <lb/>[3] Takahashi M, Inaguma Y, Hiai H, Hirose F. Developmentally <lb/>regulated expression of a human &apos;finger&apos;-containing gene en-<lb/>coded by the 5% half of the ret transforming gene. Mol Cell Biol <lb/>1988;8:1853 -6. <lb/>[4] Takahashi M, Buma Y, Iwamoto T, Inaguma Y, Ikeda H, Hiai <lb/>H. Cloning and expression of the ret proto-oncogene encoding <lb/>a tyrosine kinase with two potential transmembrane domains. <lb/>Oncogene 1988;3:571 -8. <lb/>[5] Takahashi M, Buma Y, Hiai H. Isolation of ret proto-oncogene <lb/>cDNA with an amino-terminal signal sequence. Oncogene <lb/>1989;4:805 -6. <lb/>[6] Iwamoto T, Taniguchi M, Asai N, Ohkusu K, Nakashima I, <lb/>Takahashi M. cDNA cloning of mouse ret proto-oncogene and <lb/>its sequence similarity to the cadherin superfamily. Oncogene <lb/>1993;8:1087 -91. <lb/>[7] Ishizaka Y, Itoh F, Tahira T, Ikeda I, Sugimura T, Tucker J, et <lb/>al. Human ret proto-oncogene mapped to chromosome <lb/>10q11.2. Oncogene 1989;4:1519 -21. <lb/>[8] Tahira T, Ishizaka Y, Itoh F, Sugimura T, Nagao M. Charac-<lb/>terization of ret proto-oncogene mRNAs encoding two iso-<lb/>forms of the protein product in a human neuroblastoma cell <lb/>line. Oncogene 1990;5:97 -102. <lb/>[9] Myers SM, Eng C, Ponder BAJ, Mulligan LM. Characteriza-<lb/>tion of RET proto-oncogene 3% splicing variants and polyadeny-<lb/>lation sites: a novel C-terminus for RET. Oncogene <lb/>1995;11:2039 -45. <lb/>[10] Ikeda I, Ishizaka Y, Tahira T, Suzuki T, Onda M, Sugimura T, <lb/>et al. Specific expression of the ret proto-oncogene in human <lb/>neuroblastoma cell lines. Oncogene 1990;5:1291 -6. <lb/>[11] Santoro M, Rosati R, Grieco M, Berlingieri MT, D&apos;Amato <lb/>GL-C, de Franciscis V, et al. The ret proto-oncogene is consis-<lb/>tently expressed in human pheochromocytomas and thyroid <lb/>medullary carcinomas. Oncogene 1990;5:1595 -8. <lb/>[12] Takahashi M, Buma Y, Taniguchi M. Identification of the ret <lb/>proto-oncogene products in neuroblastoma and leukemia cells. <lb/>Oncogene 1991;6:297 -301. <lb/>[13] Pachnis V, Mankoo B, Costantini F. Expression of the c-ret <lb/>proto-oncogene during mouse embryogenesis. Development <lb/>1993;119:1005 -17. <lb/>[14] Avantaggiato V, Dathan NA, Grieco M, Fabien N, Lazzaro D, <lb/>Fusco A, et al. Developmental expression of the Ret pro-<lb/>tooncogene. Cell Growth Differ 1994;5:305 -11. <lb/>[15] Tsuzuki T, Takahashi M, Asai N, Iwashita T, Matsuyama M, <lb/>Asai J. Spatial and temporal expression of the ret proto-onco-<lb/>gene product in embryonic, infant and adult rat tissues. Onco-<lb/>gene 1995;10:191 -8. <lb/>[16] Trupp M, Belluardo N, Funakoshi H, Ibáñ ez CF. Complemen-<lb/>tary and overlapping expression of glial cell line-derived neuro-<lb/>trophic factor (GDNF), c-ret proto-oncogene and GDNF <lb/>receptor-a indicates multiple mechanisms of trophic actions in <lb/>the adult rat CNS. J Neurosci 1997;17:3554 -67. <lb/>[17] Bennett DLH, Michael GJ, Ramachandran N, Munson JB, <lb/>Averill S, Yan Q, et al. A distinct subgroup of small DRG cells <lb/>express GDNF receptor components and GDNF is protective <lb/>for these neurons after nerve injury. J Neurosci 1998;18:3059 -<lb/>72. <lb/>[18] Schuchardt A, D&apos;Agati V, Larsson-Blomberg L, Costantini F, <lb/>Pachnis V. Defects in the kidney and enteric nervous system of <lb/>mice lacking the tyrosine kinase receptor Ret. Nature <lb/>1994;367:380 -3. <lb/>[19] Durbec PL, Larsson-Blomberg LB, Schuchardt A, Costantini <lb/>F, Pachnis V. Common origin and developmental dependence <lb/>on c-ret of subsets of enteric and sympathetic neuroblasts. <lb/>Development 1996;122:349 -58. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>370 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[20] Grieco M, Santoro M, Berlingieri MT, Melillo RM, Donghi R, <lb/>Bongarzone I, et al. PTC is a novel rearranged form of the ret <lb/>proto-oncogene and is frequently detected in vivo in human <lb/>thyroid papillary carcinomas. Cell 1990;60:557 -63. <lb/>[21] Mulligan LM, Kwok JBJ, Healey CS, Elsdon MJ, Eng C, <lb/>Gardner E, et al. Germ-line mutations of the RET proto-onco-<lb/>gene in multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A. Nature <lb/>1993;363:458 -60. <lb/>[22] Donis-Keller H, Dou S, Chi D, Carlson KM, Toshima K, <lb/>Lairmore TC, et al. Mutations in the RET protooncogene are <lb/>associated with MEN 2A and FMTC. Hum Mol Genet <lb/>1993;2:851 -6. <lb/>[23] Hofstra RMW, Landsvater RM, Ceccherini I, Stulp RP, Stel-<lb/>wagen T, Luo Y, et al. A mutation in the RET proto-oncogene <lb/>associated with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B and spo-<lb/>radic medullary thyroid carcinoma. Nature 1994;367:375 -6. <lb/>[24] Carlson KM, Dou S, Chi D, Scavarda N, Toshima K, Jackson <lb/>CE, et al. Single missense mutation in the tyrosine kinase <lb/>catalytic domain of the RET protooncogene is associated with <lb/>multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA <lb/>1994;91:1579 -83. <lb/>[25] Romeo G, Ronchetto P, Luo Y, Barone V, Seri M, Ceccherini <lb/>I, et al. Point mutations affecting the tyrosine kinase domain of <lb/>the RET proto-oncogene in Hirschsprung&apos;s disease. Nature <lb/>1994;367:377 -8. <lb/>[26] Edery P, Lyonnet S, Mulligan LM, Pelet A, Dow E, Abel L, et <lb/>al. Mutations of the RET protooncogene in Hirschsprung&apos;s <lb/>disease. Nature 1994;367:378 -80. <lb/>[27] Jhiang SM. The RET proto-oncogene in human cancers. Onco-<lb/>gene 2000;19:5590 -7. <lb/>[28] Salassidis K, Bruch J, Zitzelsberger H, Lengfelder E, Kellerer <lb/>AM, Bauchinger M. Translocation t(10;14)(q11.2;q22.1) fusing <lb/>the Kinectin to the ret gene creates a novel rearranged form <lb/>(PTC8) of the ret proto-oncogene in radiation-induced child-<lb/>hood papillary thyroid carcinoma. Cancer Res 2000;60:2786 -9. <lb/>[29] Klugbauer S, Jauch A, Lengfelder E, Demidchik E, Rabes HM. <lb/>A novel type of RET rearrangement (PTC8) in childhood <lb/>papillary thyroid carcinomas and characterization of the in-<lb/>volved gene (RFG8). Cancer Res 2000;60:7028 -32. <lb/>[30] Santoro M, Carlomagno F, Hay ID, Herrmann MA, Grieco <lb/>M, Melillo R, et al. Ret oncogene activation in human thyroid <lb/>neoplasms is restricted to the papillary cancer subtype. J Clin <lb/>Invest 1992;89:1517 -22. <lb/>[31] Jhiang SM, Caruso DR, Gilmore E, Ishizaka Y, Tahira T, <lb/>Nagao M, et al. Detection of the PTC/ret TPC oncogene in <lb/>human thyroid cancers. Oncogene 1992;7:1331 -7. <lb/>[32] Ishizaka Y, Kobayashi S, Ushijima T, Hirohashi S, Sugimura <lb/>T, Nagao M. Detection of ret TPC /PTC transcripts in thyroid <lb/>adenomas and adenomatous goiter by an RT-PCR method. <lb/>Oncogene 1991;6:1667 -72. <lb/>[33] Wajjwalku W, Nakamura S, Hasegawa Y, Miyazaki K, Satoh <lb/>Y, Funahashi H, et al. Low frequency of rearrangements of the <lb/>ret and trk proto-oncogenes in Japanese thyroid papillary car-<lb/>cinomas. Jpn J Cancer Res 1992;83:671 -5. <lb/>[34] Zou M, Shi Y, Farid NR. Low rate of ret proto-oncogene <lb/>activation (PTC/ret TPC ) in papillary thyroid carcinomas from <lb/>Saudi Arabia. Cancer 1994;73:176 -80. <lb/>[35] Ito T, Seyama T, Iwamoto KS, Mizuno T, Tronko ND, <lb/>Komissarenko IV, et al. Activated RET oncogene in thyroid <lb/>cancers of children from area contaminated by Chernobyl <lb/>accident. Lancet 1994;344:259. <lb/>[36] Fugazzola L, Pilotti S, Pinchera A, Vorontsova TV, Mondellini <lb/>P, Bongarzone I, et al. Oncogenic rearrangements of the RET <lb/>proto-oncogene in papillary thyroid carcinomas from children <lb/>exposed to the Chernobyl nuclear accident. Cancer Res <lb/>1995;55:5617 -20. <lb/>[37] Klugbauer S, Lengfelder E, Demidchik EP, Rabes HM. High <lb/>prevalence of RET rearrangement in thyroid tumors of children <lb/>from Belarus after the Chernobyl reactor accident. Oncogene <lb/>1995;11:2459 -67. <lb/>[38] Nikiforov YE, Rowland JM, Bove KE, Monforte-Munoz H, <lb/>Fagin JA. Distinct pattern of ret oncogene rearrangements in <lb/>morphological variants of radiation-induced and sporadic thy-<lb/>roid papillary carcinomas in children. Cancer Res <lb/>1997;57:1690 -4. <lb/>[39] Thomas GA, Bunnell H, Cook HA, Williams ED, Nerovnya A, <lb/>Cherstvoy ED, et al. High prevalence of RET/PTC rearrange-<lb/>ments in Ukrainian and Belarussian post-Chernobyl thyroid <lb/>papillary carcinomas: a strong correlation between RET/PTC3 <lb/>and the solid-follicular variant. J Clin Endocrinol Metab <lb/>1999;84:4232 -8. <lb/>[40] Smida J, Salassidis K, Hieber L, Zitzelsberger H, Kellerer AM, <lb/>Demidshik EP, et al. Distinct frequency of ret rearrangements <lb/>in papillary thyroid carcinomas of children and adults from <lb/>Belarus. Int J Cancer 1999;80:32 -8. <lb/>[41] Santoro M, Thomas GA, Vecchio G, Williams GH, Fusco A, <lb/>Chiappetta G, et al. Gene rearrangements and Chernobyl re-<lb/>lated thyroid cancers. Br J Cancer 2000;82:315 -22. <lb/>[42] Ito T, Seyama T, Iwamoto KS, Hayashi T, Mizuno T, <lb/>Tsuyama N, et al. In vitro irradiation is able to cause RET <lb/>oncogene rearrangement. Cancer Res 1993;53:2940 -3. <lb/>[43] Mizuno T, Iwamoto KS, Kyoizumi S, Nagamura H, Shinohara <lb/>T, Koyama K, et al. Preferential induction of RET/PTC1 <lb/>rearrangement by X-ray irradiation. Oncogene 2000;19:438 -43. <lb/>[44] Bounacer A, Wicker R, Caillou B, Cailleux AF, Sarasin A, <lb/>Schlumberger M, et al. High prevalence of activating ret proto-<lb/>oncogene rearrangements, in thyroid tumors from patients who <lb/>had received external radiation. Oncogene 1997;15:1263 -73. <lb/>[45] Lin L-FH, Doherty DH, Lile JD, Bektesh S, Collins F. GDNF: <lb/>a glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor for midbrain do-<lb/>paminergic neurons. Science 1993;260:1130 -2. <lb/>[46] Kotzbauer PT, Lampe PA, Heuckeroth RO, Golden JP, Cree-<lb/>don DJ, Johnson Jr EM, et al. Neurturin, a relative of glial cell <lb/>line-derived neurotrophic factor. Nature 1996;384:467 -70. <lb/>[47] Milbrandt J, de Sauvage FJ, Fahrner TJ, Baloh RH, Leitner <lb/>ML, Tansey MG, et al. Persephin, a novel neurotrophic factor <lb/>related to GDNF and Neurturin. Neuron 1998;20:245 -53. <lb/>[48] Baloh RH, Tansey MG, Lampe PA, Fahrner TJ, Enomoto H, <lb/>Simburger KS, et al. Artemin, a novel member of the GDNF <lb/>ligand family, supports peripheral and central neurons and <lb/>signals through the GFRa3-RET receptor complex. Neuron <lb/>1998;21:1290 -302. <lb/>[49] Trupp M, Arenas E, Fainzilber M, Nilsson A-S, Sieber B-A, <lb/>Grigoriou M, et al. Functional receptor for GDNF encoded by <lb/>the c-ret proto-oncogene. Nature 1996;381:785 -9. <lb/>[50] Durbec P, Marcos-Gutierrez CV, Kilkenny C, Grigoriou M, <lb/>Wartiowaara K, Suvanto P, et al. GDNF signalling through the <lb/>Ret receptor tyrosine kinase. Nature 1996;381:789 -93. <lb/>[51] Jing S, Wen D, Yu Y, Holst PL, Luo Y, Fang M, et al. <lb/>GDNF-induced activation of the Ret protein tyrosine kinase is <lb/>mediated by GDNFR-a, a novel receptor for GDNF. Cell <lb/>1996;85:1113 -24. <lb/>[52] Treanor JJS, Goodman L, de Sauvage F, Stone DM, Poulsen <lb/>KT, Beck CD, et al. Characterization of a multicomponent <lb/>receptor for GDNF. Nature 1996;382:80 -3. <lb/>[53] Klein RD, Sherman D, Ho W-H, Stone D, Bennett GL, Moffat <lb/>B, et al. A GPI-linked protein that interacts with Ret to form a <lb/>candidate neurturin receptor. Nature 1997;387:717 -21. <lb/>[54] Buj-Bello A, Adu J, Piñ ó n LG, Horton A, Thompson J, <lb/>Rosenthal A, et al. Neurturin responsiveness requires a GPI-<lb/>linked receptor and the Ret receptor tyrosine kinase. Nature <lb/>1997;387:721 -4. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>371 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[55] Baloh RH, Tansey MG, Golden JP, Creedon DJ, Heuckeroth <lb/>RO, Keck CL, et al. TrnR2, a novel receptor that mediates <lb/>neurturin and GDNF signaling through Ret. Neuron <lb/>1997;18:793 -802. <lb/>[56] Nozaki C, Asai N, Murakami H, Iwashita T, Iwata Y, Horibe <lb/>K, et al. Calcium-dependent Ret activation by GDNF and <lb/>neurturin. Oncogene 1998;16:293 -9. <lb/>[57] Sanicola M, Hession C, Worley D, Carmillo P, Ehrenfels C, <lb/>Walus L, et al. Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor-de-<lb/>pendent RET activation can be mediated by two different <lb/>cell-surface accessory proteins. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA <lb/>1997;94:6238 -43. <lb/>[58] Jing S, Yu Y, Fang M, Hu Z, Holst PL, Boone T, et al. <lb/>GFRa-2 and GFRa-3 are two new receptors for ligands of the <lb/>GDNF family. J Biol Chem 1997;272:33111 -7. <lb/>[59] Suvanto P, Wartiovaara K, Lindahl M, Arumäe U, Mosh-<lb/>nyakov M, Horelli-Kuitunen N, et al. Cloning, mRNA distri-<lb/>bution and chromosomal localisation of the gene for glial cell <lb/>line-derived neurotrophic factor receptor b, a homologue to <lb/>GDNFR-a. Hum Mol Genet 1997;6:1267 -73. <lb/>[60] Creedon DJ, Tansey MG, Baloh RH, Osborne PA, Lampe PA, <lb/>Fahrner TJ, et al. Neurturin shares receptors and signal trans-<lb/>duction pathways with glial cell line-derived neurotrophic fac-<lb/>tor in sympathetic neurons. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA <lb/>1997;94:7018 -23. <lb/>[61] Baloh RH, Gorodinsky A, Golden JP, Tansey MG, Keck CL, <lb/>Popescu NC, et al. GFRa3 is an orphan member of the <lb/>GDNF/neurturin/persephin receptor family. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci USA 1998;95:5801 -6. <lb/>[62] Masure S, Cik M, Pangalos MN, Bonaventure P, Verhasselt P, <lb/>Lesage AS, et al. Molecular cloning, expression and tissue <lb/>distribution of glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor family <lb/>receptor a-3 (GFRa-3). Eur J Biochem 1998;251:622 -30. <lb/>[63] Naveilhan P, Baudet C, Mikaels A , , Shen L, Westphal H, <lb/>Ernfors P. Expression and regulation of GFRa3, a glial cell <lb/>line-derived neurotrophic factor family receptor. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci USA 1998;95:1295 -300. <lb/>[64] Nomoto S, Ito S, Yang LX, Kiuchi K. Molecular cloning and <lb/>expression analysis of GFRa-3, a novel cDNA related to <lb/>GDNFRa and NTNRa. Biochem Biophys Res Commun <lb/>1998;244:849 -53. <lb/>[65] Trupp M, Raynoschek C, Belluardo N, Ibáñ ez CF. Multiple <lb/>GPI-anchored receptors control GDNF-dependent and inde-<lb/>pendent activation of the c-Ret receptor tyrosine kinase. Mol <lb/>Cell Neurosci 1998;11:47 -63. <lb/>[66] Worby CA, Vega QC, Chao HH-J, Seasholtz AF, Thompson <lb/>RC, Dixon JE. Identification and characterization of GFRa-3, <lb/>a novel co-receptor belonging to the glial cell line-derived <lb/>neurotrophic receptor family. J Biol Chem 1998;273:3502 -8. <lb/>[67] Enokido Y, de Sauvage F, Hongo JA, Ninkina N, Rosenthal <lb/>A, Buchman VL, et al. GFRa4 and the tyrosine kinase Ret <lb/>form a functional receptor complex for persephin. Curr Biol <lb/>1998;8:1019-22. <lb/>[68] Thompson J, Doxakis E, Piñ ó n LGP, Strachan P, Buj-Bello A, <lb/>Wyatt S, et al. GFRa-4, a new GDNF family receptor. Mol <lb/>Cell Neurosci 1998;11:117 -26. <lb/>[69] Masure S, Cik M, Hoefnagel E, Nosrat CA, Van der Linden I, <lb/>Scott R, et al. Mammalian GFRa-4, a divergent member of the <lb/>GFRa family of coreceptors for glial cell line-derived neuro-<lb/>trophic factor family ligands, is a receptor for the neurotrophic <lb/>factor persephin. J Biol Chem 2000;275:39427 -34. <lb/>[70] Lindahl M, Poteryaev D, Yu L, Arumäe U, Timmusk T, <lb/>Bongarzone I et al. Human GFRa4 is the receptor for <lb/>persephin, and is predominantly expressed in normal and ma-<lb/>lignant thyroid medullary cells. J Biol Chem (in press). <lb/>[71] Sánchez MP, Silos-Santiago I, Frisén J, He B, Lira SA, Bar-<lb/>bacid M. Renal agenesis and the absence of enteric neurons in <lb/>mice lacking GDNF. Nature 1996;382:70 -3. <lb/>[72] Pichel JG, Shen L, Sheng HZ, Granholm A-C, Drago J, <lb/>Grinberg A, et al. Defects in enteric innervation and kidney <lb/>development in mice lacking GDNF. Nature 1996;382:73 -6. <lb/>[73] Moore MW, Klein RD, Fariñ as I, Sauer H, Armanini M, <lb/>Phillips H, et al. Renal and neuronal abnormalities in mice <lb/>lacking GDNF. Nature 1996;382:76 -9. <lb/>[74] Cacalano G, Fariñ as I, Wang L-C, Hagler K, Forgie A, Moore <lb/>M, et al. GFRa1 is an essential receptor component for GDNF <lb/>in the developing nervous system and kidney. Neuron <lb/>1998;21:53 -62. <lb/>[75] Enomoto H, Araki T, Jackman A, Heuckeroth RO, Snider <lb/>WD, Johnson EM Jr., et al. GFRa1-deficient mice have deficits <lb/>in the enteric nervous system and kidneys. Neuron <lb/>1998;21:317 -24. <lb/>[76] Heuckeroth RO, Enomoto H, Grider JR, Golden JP, Hanke <lb/>JA, Jackman A, et al. Gene targeting reveals a critical role for <lb/>neurturin in the development and maintenance of enteric, sen-<lb/>sory, and parasympathetic neurons. Neuron 1999;22:253 -63. <lb/>[77] Rossi J, Luukko K, Poteryaev D, Laurikainen A, Sun Y-F, <lb/>Laakso T, et al. Retarded growth and deficits in the enteric and <lb/>parasympathetic nervous system in mice lacking GFRa2, a <lb/>functional neurturin receptor. Neuron 1999;22:243 -52. <lb/>[78] Nishino J, Mochida K, Ohfuji Y, Shimazaki T, Meno C, Ohishi <lb/>S, et al. GFRa3, a component of the artemin receptor, is <lb/>required for migration and survival of the superior cervical <lb/>ganglion. Neuron 1999;23:725 -36. <lb/>[79] van Weering DHJ, Medema JP, van Puijenbroek A, Burgering <lb/>BMT, Baas PD, Bos JL. Ret receptor tyrosine kinase activates <lb/>extracellular signal-regulated kinase 2 in SK-N-MC cells. Onco-<lb/>gene 1995;11:2207 -14. <lb/>[80] Worby CA, Vega QC, Zao Y, Chao HHJ, Seasholtz AF, Dixon <lb/>JE. Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor signals through <lb/>the RET receptor and activates mitogen-activated protein ki-<lb/>nase. J Biol Chem 1996;271:23619 -22. <lb/>[81] van Weering DHJ, Bos JL. Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic <lb/>factor induces Ret-mediated lamellipodia formation. J Biol <lb/>Chem 1997;272:249 -54. <lb/>[82] Ohiwa M, Murakami H, Iwashita T, Asai N, Iwata Y, Imai T, <lb/>et al. Characterization of Ret-Shc-Grb2 complex induced by <lb/>GDNF, MEN 2A and MEN 2B mutations. Biochem Biophys <lb/>Res Commun 1997;237:747 -51. <lb/>[83] Xing S, Furminger TL, Tong Q, Jhiang SM. Signal transduc-<lb/>tion pathways activated by RET oncoproteins in PC12 <lb/>pheochromocytoma cells. J Biol Chem 1998;273:4909 -14. <lb/>[84] Chiariello M, Visconti R, Carlomagno F, Melillo RM, Bucci C, <lb/>de Franciscis V, et al. Signalling of the Ret receptor tyrosine <lb/>kinase through the c-Jun NH 2 -terminal protein kinases (JNKs): <lb/>evidence for a divergence of the ERKs and JNKs pathways <lb/>induced by Ret. Oncogene 1998;16:2435 -45. <lb/>[85] Murakami H, Iwashita T, Asai N, Iwata Y, Narumiya S, <lb/>Takahashi M. Rho-dependent and -independent tyrosine phos-<lb/>phorylation of focal adhesion kinase, paxillin and p130Cas <lb/>mediated by Ret kinase. Oncogene 1999;18:1975 -82. <lb/>[86] Murakami H, Iwashita T, Asai N, Shimono Y, Iwata Y, Kawai <lb/>K, et al. Enhanced phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase activity and <lb/>high phosphorylation state of its downstream signalling <lb/>molecules mediated by Ret with the MEN 2B mutation. <lb/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun 1999;262:68 -75. <lb/>[87] Melillo RM, Barone MV, Lupoli G, Cirafici AM, Carlomagno <lb/>F, Visconti R, et al. Ret-mediated mitogenesis requires Src <lb/>kinase activity. Cancer Res 1999;59:1120 -6. <lb/>[88] Trupp M, Scott R, Whittemore SR, Ibáñ ez CF. Ret-dependent <lb/>and -independent mechanisms of glial cell line-derived neuro-<lb/>trophic factor signaling in neuronal cells. J Biol Chem <lb/>1999;274:20885 -94. <lb/>[89] Soler RM, Dolcet X, Encinas M, Egea J, Bayascas JR, Comella <lb/>JX. Receptors of the glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>372 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>family of neurotrophic factors signal cell survival through the <lb/>phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase pathway in spinal cord motoneu-<lb/>rons. J Neurosci 1999;19:9160 -9. <lb/>[90] Feng L, Wang C-Y, Jiang H, Oho C, Dugich-Djordjevic M, <lb/>Mei L, et al. Differential signaling of glial cell line-derived <lb/>neurotrophic factor and brain-derived neurotrophic factor in <lb/>cultured ventral mesencephalic neurons. Neuroscience <lb/>1999;93:265 -73. <lb/>[91] Segouffin-Cariou C, Billaud M. Transforming ability of <lb/>MEN2A-RET requires activation of the phosphatidylinositol <lb/>3-kinase/AKT signaling pathway. J Biol Chem 2000;275:3568 -<lb/>76. <lb/>[92] Hayashi H, Ichihara M, Iwashita T, Murakami H, Shimono Y, <lb/>Kawai K, et al. Characterization of intracellular signals via <lb/>tyrosine 1062 in RET activated by glial cell line-derived neuro-<lb/>trophic factor. Oncogene 2000;19:4469 -75. <lb/>[93] Asai N, Murakami H, Iwashita T, Takahashi M. A mutation at <lb/>tyrosine 1062 in MEN2A-Ret and MEN2B-Ret impairs their <lb/>transforming activity and association with Shc adaptor <lb/>proteins. J Biol Chem 1996;271:17644 -9. <lb/>[94] Borrello MG, Alberti L, Arighi E, Bongarzone I, Battistini C, <lb/>Bardelli A, et al. The full oncogenic activity of Ret/ptc2 de-<lb/>pends on tyrosine 539, a docking site for phospholipase C-g. <lb/>Mol Cell Biol 1996;16:2151 -63. <lb/>[95] Arighi E, Alberti L, Torriti F, Ghizzoni S, Rizzetti MG, Pelicci <lb/>G, et al. Identification of Shc docking site on Ret tyrosine <lb/>kinase. Oncogene 1997;14:773 -82. <lb/>[96] Lorenzo MJ, Gish GD, Houghton C, Stonehouse TJ, Pawson <lb/>T, Ponder BAJ, et al. RET alternate splicing influences the <lb/>interaction of activated RET with the SH2 and PTB domains of <lb/>Shc, and the SH2 domain of Grb2. Oncogene 1997;14:763 -71. <lb/>[97] Alberti L, Borrello MG, Ghizzoni S, Torriti F, Rizzetti MG, <lb/>Pierotti MA. Grb2 binding to the different isoforms of Ret <lb/>tyrosine kinase. Oncogene 1998;17:1079 -87. <lb/>[98] Durick K, Gill GN, Taylor SS. Shc and Enigma are both <lb/>required for mitogenic signaling by Ret/ptc2. Mol Cell Biol <lb/>1998;18:2298 -308. <lb/>[99] Pandey A, Duan H, Di Fiore PP, Dixit VM. The Ret receptor <lb/>protein tyrosine kinase associates with the SH2-containing <lb/>adapter protein Grb10. J Biol Chem 1995;270:21461 -3. <lb/>[100] van Weering DHJ, Bos JL. Signal transduction by the receptor <lb/>tyrosine kinase Ret. Recent Res Cancer Res 1998;154:271 -81. <lb/>[101] Besset V, Scott RP, Ibáñ ez CF. Signaling complexes and <lb/>protein-protein interactions involved in the activation of the <lb/>Ras and phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase pathways by the c-Ret <lb/>receptor tyrosine kinase. J Biol Chem 2000;275:39159 -66. <lb/>[102] De Vita G, Melillo RM, Carlomagno F, Visconti R, Castellone <lb/>MD, Bellacosa A, et al. Tyrosine 1062 of RET-MEN2A medi-<lb/>ates activation of Akt (protein kinase B) and mitogen-activated <lb/>protein kinase pathways leading to PC12 cell survival. Cancer <lb/>Res 2000;60:3727 -31. <lb/>[103] Califano D, Rizzo C, D&apos;Alessio A, Colucci-D&apos;Amato GL, Calì <lb/>G, Bartoli PC, et al. Signaling through Ras is essential for ret <lb/>oncogene-induced cell differentiation in PC12 cells. J Biol Chem <lb/>2000;275:19297 -305. <lb/>[104] Kurokawa K, Iwashita T, Murakami H, Hayashi H, Kawai K, <lb/>Takahashi M. Identification of SNT/FRS2 docking site on <lb/>RET receptor tyrosine kinase and its role for signal transduc-<lb/>tion. Oncogene 2001;20:1929 -38. <lb/>[105] Paratcha G, Ladda F, Baars L, Coulpier M, Besset V, Anders <lb/>J, et al. Released GFRa1 potentiates downstream signaling, <lb/>neuronal survival, and differentiation via a novel mechanism of <lb/>recruitment of c-Ret to lipid rafts. Neuron 2001;29:171 -84. <lb/>[106] Ishiguro Y, Iwashita T, Murakami H, Asai N, Iida K, Goto H, <lb/>et al. The role of amino acids surrounding tyrosine 1062 in Ret <lb/>in specific binding of the Shc phosphotyrosine binding domain. <lb/>Endocrinology 1999;140:3992 -8. <lb/>[107] Hayashi Y, Iwashita T, Murakami H, Kato Y, Kawai K, <lb/>Kurokawa K et al. Activation of BMK1 via tyrosine 1062 in <lb/>RET by GDNF and MEN2A mutation. Biochem Biophys Res <lb/>Commun (in press). <lb/>[108] Poteryaev D, Titievsky A, Sun YF, Thomas-Crusells J, Lindahl <lb/>M, Billaud M, et al. GDNF triggers a novel Ret-independent <lb/>Src kinase family-coupled signaling via a GPI-linked GDNF <lb/>receptor a1. FEBS Lett 1999;463:63 -6. <lb/>[109] Eng C. RET proto-oncogene in the development of human <lb/>cancer. J Clin Oncol 1999;17:380 -93. <lb/>[110] Hö ppener W, Ritter MM. A duplication of 12bp in the critical <lb/>cysteine rich domain of the RET proto-oncogene results in a <lb/>distinct phenotype of multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A. <lb/>Hum Mol Genet 1997;6:587 -90. <lb/>[111] Hö ppener W, Dralle H, Brabant, G. Duplication of 9 base <lb/>pairs in the critical cysteine-rich domain of the RET proto-<lb/>oncogene causes multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A, Hum <lb/>Mutat 1998;Suppl 1:S128 -S130 <lb/>[112] Pigny P, Bauters C, Wemeau J-L, Houcke ML, Crepin M, <lb/>Caron P, et al. A novel 9-base pair duplication in RET exon 8 <lb/>in familial medullary thyroid carcinoma. J Clin Endocrinol <lb/>Metab 1999;84:1700 -4. <lb/>[113] Berndt I, Reuter M, Saller B, Frank-Raue K, Groth P, <lb/>Grubendorf M, et al. A new hot spot for mutations in the ret <lb/>proto-oncogene causing familial medullary thyroid carcinoma <lb/>and multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A. J Clin Endocrinol <lb/>Metab 1998;83:770 -4. <lb/>[114] Miyauchi A, Futami H, Hai N, Yokozawa T, Kuma K, Aoki <lb/>N, et al. Two germline missense mutations at codons 804 and <lb/>806 of the RET proto-oncogene in the same allele in a patient <lb/>with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B without codon 918 <lb/>mutation. Jpn J Cancer Res 1999;90:1 -5. <lb/>[115] Iwashita T, Murakami H, Kurokawa K, Kawai K, Miyauchi <lb/>A, Futami H, et al. A two-hit model for development of <lb/>multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B by RET mutations. <lb/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun 2000;268:804 -8. <lb/>[116] Asai N, Iwashita T, Matsuyama M, Takahashi M. Mechanism <lb/>of activation of ret proto-oncogene by multiple endocrine neo-<lb/>plasia 2A mutation. Mol Cell Biol 1995;15:1613 -9. <lb/>[117] Santoro M, Carlomagno F, Romano A, Bottaro DP, Dathan <lb/>NA, Grieco M, et al. Activation of RET as a dominant <lb/>transforming gene by germline mutations of MEN2A and <lb/>MEN2B. Science 1995;267:381 -3. <lb/>[118] Borrello MG, Smith DP, Pasini B, Bongarzone I, Greco A, <lb/>Lorenzo MJ, et al. RET activation by germline MEN2A and <lb/>MEN2B mutations. Oncogene 1995;11:2419 -27. <lb/>[119] Iwashita T, Asai N, Murakami H, Takahashi M. Identification <lb/>of tyrosine residues that are essential for transforming activity <lb/>of the ret proto-oncogene with MEN2A or MEN2B mutation. <lb/>Oncogene 1996;12:481 -7. <lb/>[120] Rossel M, Pasini A, Chappuis S, Geneste O, Fournier L, <lb/>Schuffenecker I, et al. Distinct biological properties of two RET <lb/>isoforms activated by MEN2A and MEN2B mutations. Onco-<lb/>gene 1997;14:265 -75. <lb/>[121] Ito S, Iwashita T, Asai N, Murakami H, Iwata Y, Sobue G, et <lb/>al. Biological properties of Ret with cysteine mutations corre-<lb/>late with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A, familial <lb/>medullary thyroid carcinoma, and Hirschsprung&apos;s disease phe-<lb/>notype. Cancer Res 1997;57:2870 -2. <lb/>[122] Pasini A, Geneste O, Legrand P, Schlumberger M, Rossel M, <lb/>Fournier L, et al. Oncogenic activation of RET by two distinct <lb/>FMTC mutations affecting the tyrosine kinase domain. Onco-<lb/>gene 1997;15:393 -402. <lb/>[123] Iwashita T, Kato M, Murakami H, Asai N, Ishiguro Y, Ito S, <lb/>et al. Biological and biochemical properties of Ret with kinase <lb/>domain mutations identified in multiple endocrine neoplasia <lb/>type 2B and familial medullary thyroid carcinoma. Oncogene <lb/>1999;18:3919 -22. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">M. Takahashi / Cytokine &amp; Growth Factor Re6iews 12 (2001) 361-373 <lb/></note>

			<page>373 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[124] Songyanag Z, Carraway IIIKL, Eck MJ, Harrison SH, Feld-<lb/>man RA, Mohammadi M, et al. Catalytic specificity of protein-<lb/>tyrosine kinase is critical for selective signalling. Nature <lb/>1995;373:536 -9. <lb/>[125] Bocciardi R, Mograbi B, Pasini B, Borrello MG, Pierotti MA, <lb/>Bourget I, et al. The multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2B point <lb/>mutation switches the specificity of the Ret tyrosine kinase <lb/>towards cellular substrates that are susceptible to interact with <lb/>Crk and Nck. Oncogene 1997;15:2257 -65. <lb/>[126] Ponder BAJ, Smith D. The MEN II syndromes and the role of <lb/>the ret proto-oncogene. Adv Cancer Res 1996;70:179 -222. <lb/>[127] Carlomagno F, Salvatore G, Cirafici AM, De Vita G, Melillo <lb/>RM, de Franciscis V, et al. The different RET-activating capa-<lb/>bility of mutations of cysteine 620 or cysteine 634 correlates <lb/>with the multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2 disease phenotype. <lb/>Cancer Res 1997;57:391 -5. <lb/>[128] Michiels F-M, Chappuis S, Caillou B, Pasini A, Talbot M, <lb/>Monier R, et al. Development of medullary thyroid carcinoma <lb/>in transgenic mice expressing the RET protooncogene altered <lb/>by a multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A mutation. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci USA 1997;94:3330 -5. <lb/>[129] Kawai K, Iwashita T, Murakami H, Hiraiwa N, Yoshiki A, <lb/>Kusakabe M, et al. Tissue-specific carcinogenesis in transgenic <lb/>mice expressing the RET proto-oncogene with a multiple en-<lb/>docrine neoplasia type 2A mutation. Cancer Res 2000;60:5254 -<lb/>60. <lb/>[130] Qiao S, Iwashita T, Furukawa T, Yamamoto M, Sobue G, <lb/>Takahashi M. Differential effects of LAR on biochemical and <lb/>biological activities of RET-MEN2A and RET-MEN2B mu-<lb/>tant proteins. J Biol Chem 2001;276:9460 -7. <lb/>[131] Sweetser DA, Froelick GJ, Matsumoto AM, Kafer KE, Marck <lb/>B, Palmiter RD, et al. Ganglioneuromas and renal anomalies <lb/>are induced by activated RET MEN2B in transgenic mice. Onco-<lb/>gene 1999;18:877 -86. <lb/>[132] Gestblom C, Sweetser DA, Doggett B, Kapur RP. Sympathoa-<lb/>drenal hyperplasia causes renal malformations in Ret MEN2B -<lb/>transgenic mice. Am J Pathol 1999;155:2167 -79. <lb/>[133] Acton DS, Velthuyzen D, Lips CJM, Hö ppener JWM. Multiple <lb/>endocrine neoplasia type 2B mutation in human RET oncogene <lb/>induces medullary thyroid carcinoma in transgenic mice. Onco-<lb/>gene 2000;19:3121 -5. <lb/>[134] Smith-Hicks CL, Sizer KC, Powers JF, Tischler AS, Costantini <lb/>F. C-cell hyperplasia, pheochromocytoma and sympathoad-<lb/>renal malformation in a mouse model of multiple endocrine <lb/>neoplasia type 2B. EMBO J 2000;19:612 -22. <lb/>[135] Angrist M, Bolk S, Thiel B, Puffenberger EG, Hofstra RM, <lb/>Buys CHCM, et al. Mutation analysis of the RET receptor <lb/>tyrosine kinase in Hirschsprung disease. Hum Mol Genet <lb/>1995;4:821 -30. <lb/>[136] Attié T, Pelet A, Edery P, Eng C, Mulligan LM, Amiel J, et al. <lb/>Diversity of RET proto-oncogene mutations in familial and <lb/>sporadic Hirschsprung disease. Hum Mol Genet 1995;4:1381 -6. <lb/>[137] Chakravarti A. Endothelin receptor-mediated signaling in <lb/>Hirschsprung&apos;s disease. Hum Mol Genet 1996;5:303 -7. <lb/>[138] Carlomagno F, De Vita G, Berlingieri MT, de Franciscis V, <lb/>Melillo RM, Colantuoni V, et al. Molecular heterogeneity of <lb/>RET loss of function in Hirschsprung&apos;s disease. EMBO J <lb/>1996;15:2717 -25. <lb/>[139] Iwashita T, Murakami H, Asai N, Takahashi M. Mechanism of <lb/>Ret dysfunction by Hirschsprung mutations affecting its extra-<lb/>cellular domain. Hum Mol Genet 1996;5:1578 -80. <lb/>[140] Cosma MP, Cardone M, Carlomagno F, Colantuoni V. Muta-<lb/>tions in the extracellular domain cause RET loss of function by <lb/>a dominant negative mechanism. Mol Cell Biol 1998;18:3321 -<lb/>9. <lb/>[141] Geneste O, Bidaud C, De Vita G, Hofstra RMW, Tartare-<lb/>Deckert S, Buys CHCM, et al. Two distinct mutations of the <lb/>RET receptor causing Hirschsprung&apos;s disease impair the bind-<lb/>ing of signalling effector to a multifunctional docking site. Hum <lb/>Mol Genet 1999;8:1989 -99. <lb/>[142] Pasini B, Borrello MG, Greco A, Bongarzone I, Luo Y, <lb/>Mondellini P, et al. Loss of function effect of RET mutations <lb/>causing Hirschsprung disease. Nat Genet 1995;10:35 -40. <lb/>[143] Pelet A, Geneste O, Edery P, Pasini A, Chappuis S, Attié T, et <lb/>al. Various mechanisms cause RET-mediated signaling defects <lb/>in Hirschsprung&apos;s disease. J Clin Invest 1998;101:1415 -23. <lb/>[144] Cosma MP, Panariello L, Quadro L, Dathan NA, Fattoruso O, <lb/>Colantuoni V. A mutation in the RET proto-oncogene in <lb/>Hirschsprung&apos;s disease affects the tyrosine kinase activity asso-<lb/>ciated with multiple endocrine neoplasia type 2A and 2B. <lb/>Biochem J 1996;314:397 -400. <lb/>[145] Iwashita T, Kurokawa K, Qiao S, Murakami H, Asai N, <lb/>Hashimoto M, et al. Functional analysis of RET with <lb/>Hirschsprung&apos;s mutations affecting the extracellular domain. <lb/>Gastroenterology 2001;121:24 -33. <lb/>[146] Bordeaux M-C, Forcet C, Granger L, Corset V, Bidaud C, <lb/>Billaud M, et al. The RET proto-oncogene induces apoptosis: a <lb/>novel mechanism for Hirschsprung disease. EMBO J <lb/>2000;19:4056 -63. <lb/>[147] Mulligan LM, Eng C, Attié T, Lyonnet S, Marsh DJ, Hyland <lb/>VJ, et al. Diverse phenotypes associated with exon 10 mutations <lb/>of the RET proto-oncogene. Hum Mol Genet 1994;3:2163 -7. <lb/>[148] Decker RA, Peacock ML, Watson P. Hirschsprung disease in <lb/>MEN 2A: increased spectrum of RET exon 10 genotypes and <lb/>strong genotype -phenotype correlation. Hum Mol Genet <lb/>1998;7:129 -34. <lb/>[149] Chappuis-Flament S, Pasini A, De Vita G, Segouffin-Cariou C, <lb/>Fusco A, Attié T, et al. Dual effect on the RET receptor of <lb/>MEN 2 mutations affecting specific extracytoplasmic cysteines. <lb/>Oncogene 1998;17:2851 -61. <lb/>[150] Takahashi M, Iwashita T, Santoro M, Lyonnet S, Lenoir GM, <lb/>Billaud M. Co-segregation of MEN2 and Hirschsprung&apos;s dis-<lb/>ease: the same mutation of RET with both gain and loss-of-<lb/>function? Hum Mutat 1999;13:331 -6. <lb/>[151] Meng X, Lindahl M, Hyvö nen ME, Parvinen M, de Rooij DG, <lb/>Hess MW, et al. Regulation of cell fate decision of undifferenti-<lb/>ated spermatogonia by GDNF. Science 2000;287:1489 -93. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
