<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Unconventional Fabrics, Architectures, and Models <lb/>for Future Multi-core Systems <lb/> Radu Marculescu <lb/> Carnegie Mellon University <lb/>Department of Electrical and <lb/>Computer Engineering <lb/>Pittsburgh, PA 15213-3890 <lb/> radum@ece.cmu.edu <lb/>Christof Teuscher <lb/> Portland State University <lb/>Department of Electrical and <lb/>Computer Engineering <lb/>Portland, OR 97201 <lb/> teuscher@pdx.edu <lb/>Partha Pratim Pande <lb/> Washington State University <lb/>School of Electrical Engineering and <lb/>Computer Science <lb/>Pullman, WA 99164 <lb/> pande@eecs.wsu.edu <lb/>
			
			ABSTRACT <lb/> Massive level of integration is making modern multi-core chips <lb/>all-pervasive in several domains. Hence, high performance, <lb/>robustness, and low power are crucial for the widespread adoption <lb/>of such platforms. However, achieving all these goals forces us to <lb/>re-think the basis of designing multi-core systems at nanoscale, <lb/>starting with the very substrate we need to use to implement such <lb/>systems in the future, particularly for nanowire (or carbon <lb/>nanotube) based on-chip interconnect obtained through self-<lb/>assembly techniques. Due to the lack of control over these <lb/>processes, such interconnects are expected to be largely <lb/>unstructured [1][2][3]. While large unstructured networks are easy <lb/>to fabricate, they require unconventional architectures and <lb/>communication paradigms. For instance, by getting inspiration <lb/>from many natural systems with network-based architectures [1], <lb/>the future multi-core systems at nanoscale are expected to be <lb/>hierarchical and heterogeneous in nature, as many powerful <lb/>features such as increased performance, better resource <lb/>utilization, and an increased robustness against failures  of many <lb/>natural networks come precisely from their heterogeneity, <lb/>unstructuredness, and hierarchical nature. As such, an important <lb/>performance limitation of multi-core chips designed with regular <lb/>network architectures arises from planar metal interconnect-based <lb/>multi-hop links, where the data transfer between two distant <lb/>blocks can cause high latency and power consumption. <lb/>

			Different revolutionary approaches for creating low latency, long-<lb/>range communication channels like optical interconnects, on-chip <lb/>transmission lines and wireless interconnects have been explored, <lb/>particularly in the context of network-on-chip (NoC) based <lb/>communication. These emerging interconnect technologies can <lb/>enable the design of hierarchical on-chip network architectures, <lb/>where closely spaced cores communicate through traditional <lb/>metal wires, but long distance communications is predominantly <lb/>achieved through high performance specialized links. It is <lb/>possible to find optimal interconnection architectures for massive <lb/>multi-core chips by drawing inspiration from natural (complex) <lb/>networks that minimize resource consumption, while optimizing <lb/>the relevant performance metrics, such as latency, throughput, <lb/>power and area overhead. <lb/>The architecture-space exploration and optimization, however, <lb/>require the incorporation of realistic models of network behavior <lb/>depending on the region of network operation. Hence, a detailed <lb/>understanding of the communication workload can be exploited to <lb/>provide more performance and better resource utilization via <lb/>network customization. At the same time, most application <lb/>mapping or dynamic power management approaches considered <lb/>so far for NoCs are based on average metrics that assume <lb/>implicitly that the network is not congested and operates in <lb/>stationary regimes. In practice, however, the network is used in <lb/>regimes closer to congestion by most on-chip applications. <lb/>Consequently, the optimization metric should also consider the <lb/>communication dynamics in order to produce meaningful results <lb/>and so completely new performance models are needed for <lb/>successful optimization of future multi-core systems. These are <lb/>just a few examples of network-related issues that require our <lb/>immediate attention. <lb/>Starting from these ideas, this special session considers a holistic <lb/>approach to the on-chip network paradigm and identifies a few <lb/>critical issues related to the theoretical basis (e.g. graph theory, <lb/>stochastic modeling and analysis), essential properties (e.g. <lb/>structure, hierarchy, heterogeneity, dynamics, communication <lb/>paradigm), and optimization metrics (e.g. energy, fault-tolerance, <lb/>robustness, cost, performance) of designing and characterizing the <lb/>communication infrastructure of future multi-core systems. <lb/>Towards this end, this session consists of three forward-looking <lb/>talks (going from the substrate-, all the way up to the application-<lb/>level) addressing these fundamental challenges and opportunities. <lb/>The first talk by Christof Teuscher ( &quot; Self-assembled Nanoscale <lb/>On-Chip Interconnect: The Good, the Bad and the Ugly &quot; ) <lb/>addresses the opportunities and challenges of novel self-<lb/>assembled nanoscale interconnects that are imperfect and <lb/>disordered to a large extent. While such interconnects are <lb/>relatively easy and cheap to fabricate, they pose many challenges <lb/>for placement, routing, and QoS [1]. On the other hand, such <lb/>interconnects have also many advantages, such as lower latencies <lb/>because of non-local links and an increased and inherent <lb/>robustness against certain types of failures. One of the challenges <lb/>we address is to find network topologies that are both efficient <lb/>and possible to fabricate by the chemical self-assembly of <lb/>nanowires or carbon nanotubes. For that purpose, we have built a <lb/> Copyright is held by the author/owner(s). <lb/> CODES/ISSS&apos;10, October 24–29, 2010, Scottsdale, Arizona, USA. <lb/>ACM 978-1-60558-905-3/10/10. <lb/>

			<page> 327 <lb/></page>

			network evaluation framework combined with simple wire-<lb/>growth models, which allows us to determine the optimal points, <lb/>i.e., &quot; sweet spots, &quot; in both the network and the physical design <lb/>space. The ultimate goal is to relate the relevant network <lb/>parameters to the chemical parameters of the self-assembly <lb/>process, which would bring us a step closer to application-specific <lb/>fabrication. The central message of this talk is that the benefits of <lb/>disordered interconnects can be harnessed if we challenge the <lb/>traditional communication and computing paradigms. <lb/>The second talk by Partha Pande ( &quot; Small-World Hybrid Wireless <lb/>Network-on-Chip Architecture for Massive Multi-Core Systems &quot; ) <lb/>addresses the performance limitations of traditional metal <lb/>interconnect-based multi-hop on chip networks by inserting long-<lb/>range single-hop wireless links between distant cores. Despite <lb/>their advantages, an important performance limitation in regular <lb/>(e.g., mesh like) NoCs arises from planar metal interconnect-<lb/>based multi-hop links; wherein the data transfer between two <lb/>distant blocks causes high latency and power consumption [4]. <lb/>This limitation of conventional NoCs can be addressed by <lb/>drawing inspiration from the human cerebral cortex. A large <lb/>proportion of intra-cortical connections are established locally. <lb/>Another large proportion of connections spread over longer <lb/>distances, linking neurons that are located in different cortical <lb/>regions. These connections ensure that the distant cortical sites <lb/>can communicate fast enough in addition to the local intra-cortical <lb/>communications. This network topology commonly referred to as <lb/>small-world, can be incorporated in NoCs by introducing long-<lb/>range, high bandwidth and low power wireless links between <lb/>distant cores [5-6]. The central theme of this talk is to show the <lb/>achievable performance benefit of the small-world wireless NoC <lb/>(WiNoC) architecture, as well as various technological challenges <lb/>and relevant design trade-offs for WiNoCs. <lb/>The third talk by Radu Marculescu ( &quot; Is the Network the Real <lb/>Problem for Future Multi-core Systems? &quot; ) argues that, in contrast <lb/>to traditional platforms such as PCs, servers, and parallel <lb/>computers whose behavior has been well-studied, workloads have <lb/>not been well characterized for multicore implementation of <lb/>complex applications. Moreover, the current approaches for <lb/>analyzing network performance are predominantly based on <lb/>Poisson modeling which typically assumes exponentially <lb/>distributed arrival processes. Unfortunately, these models are too <lb/>simplistic to capture the complex behavior of the network when <lb/>running real applications, particularly at high packet injection <lb/>rates. Consequently, finding better approaches to workload <lb/>characterization remains a fundamental open problem in <lb/>multicore system design as precise workload characterization can <lb/>enable better mechanisms for multi-tasking, routing protocols and <lb/>priorities, power and memory management, caching -virtually all <lb/>aspects of the computational infrastructure of multicore platforms <lb/>[7]. The central message of this talk is that taking into account the <lb/>characteristics of the workload becomes of crucial importance for <lb/>performance analysis and optimization of the communication <lb/>infrastructure, as well as proper resource management of future <lb/>multicore platforms. <lb/>In summary, this session brings to discussion a few major <lb/>challenges and appropriate design solutions that will enable multi-<lb/>core systems to become the paradigm of choice when solving real <lb/>problems in the future. <lb/> 
			
			Categories and Subject Descriptors <lb/> J.6 [Computer-Aided Engineering]: Computer-Aided Design, <lb/>C.2.1 [Computer-Communication Networks]: Network <lb/>Architecture and Design, B.7.1 [Integrated Circuits]: Types and <lb/>Design Styles. <lb/> 
			
			General Terms <lb/> Algorithms, Measurement, Performance, Design, Reliability, <lb/>Experimentation, Theory. <lb/> 
			
			Keywords <lb/> Multi-core, networks-on-chip, routing, architecture, interconnect, <lb/>self-assembly, workload. <lb/>
		</front> 
			
		<back>
			<listBibl> 1. REFERENCES <lb/> [1] C. Teuscher &quot; Nature-inspired interconnects for emerging <lb/>large-scale network-on-chip designs, &quot;  Chaos, 17(2), 026106. <lb/>DOI= http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.2740566 <lb/>[2] C. Teuscher and A. A. Hansson, &quot; Non-traditional irregular <lb/>interconnects for massive scale SoC, &quot;  Proceedings of the <lb/>IEEE International Symposium on Circuits and Systems <lb/> (ISCAS), pp. 2785–2788. <lb/>[3] C. Teuscher, N. Gulbahc and T. Rohlf, &quot; An assessment of <lb/>random dynamical network automata for nanoelectronics, &quot; <lb/> International Journal of Nanotechnology and Molecular <lb/>Computation, 1(4):39–57. <lb/>[4] A. Kumar et al., &quot; Toward Ideal On-Chip Communication <lb/>Using Express Virtual Channels, &quot; IEEE Micro, Vol. 28, <lb/>Issue 1, January-February 2008, pp. 80-90 <lb/>[5] U. Y. Ogras and R. Marculescu, &quot; It&apos;s a Small World After <lb/>All &quot; : NoC Performance Optimization Via Long-Range Link <lb/>Insertion &quot; , IEEE Transactions on Very Large Scale <lb/>Integration (VLSI) Systems, Vol. 14, No. 7, July 2006, pp. <lb/>693-706. <lb/>[6] A. Ganguly et al., &quot; Scalable Hybrid Wireless Network-on-<lb/>Chip Architectures for Multi-Core Systems &quot; , IEEE <lb/>Transactions on Computers (in press). <lb/>[7] P. Bogdan and R. Marculescu, &quot; Workload Characterization <lb/>and its Impact on Multicore Platform Design, &quot; in Proc. <lb/>IEEE/ACM Proc. Hardware/Software Codesign and System <lb/>Synthesis (CODES+ISSS), Scottsdale, AZ, Oct. 2010. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page> 328 </page>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
