<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Phyrochemisrry, Vol. 24, No. 4, pp. 815-811, 1985. <lb/>0031~9422/85 53.00 + 0.00 <lb/>F&apos;rinted in Great Britain. <lb/>0 1985 Pergamon F&apos;ress Ltd. <lb/>PIGMENTS FROM SAL VIA MZLTIORRHlZA <lb/>HOU-WEI Luo, BAO-JING Wu, MEI-YU Wu,* ZHONG-GEN YONG,* MASATAKE NIWA~$ and YOSHIMASA HIRATA~ <lb/>Nanjing College of Pharmacy, Nanjing, China; *Institute of Jingsu Industrial Chemical Research, Nanjing, China; t Faculty of <lb/>Pharmacy, Meijo University, Tempaku, Nagoya 468, Japan <lb/>(Revised received 25 July 1984) <lb/>Key Word Index-Salvia <lb/>miltiorrhiza; Labiatae; pigment; diterpene; o-naphthaquinone; tanshindiol A; tanshindiol <lb/>B; tanshindiol C, nortanshinone; 3a-hydroxytanshinone <lb/>IIA. <lb/>Abstract-Five <lb/>new o-naphthaquinone diterpenes, tanshindiol A, tanshindiol B, tanshindiol C, nortanshinone and <lb/>3a-hydroxytanshinone HA, have been isolated from the roots of Saluia miltiorrhiza as minor components. Their relative <lb/>stereochemistries have been established on the basis of spectral and chemical evidence. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCIION <lb/>&apos;Dan-Shen&apos;, the dried roots of Salvia miltiorrhiza Bunge, is <lb/>a clinically important Chinese drug in the treatment of <lb/>heart disease. Many chemists have studied the physiologi-<lb/>cally active constituents of this drug and have isolated <lb/>more than 16 orange-red crystalline pigments, abietanoids <lb/>[l, 2 and refs. therein]. Most abietanoids have either a <lb/>furano-ortho-naphthaquinone <lb/>or a furano-para-naphtha-<lb/>quinone skeleton and are classified biogenetically <lb/>as diterpenes. In the course of our search for physiologi-<lb/>cally active substances in Chinese drugs [3 and refs. <lb/>therein], we have isolated five new pigments, tanshindiol <lb/>A (l), tanshindiol B (2), tanshindiol C (3), nortanshinone <lb/>(4) and 3cr-hydroxytanshinone IIA (5), from Dan-Shen as <lb/>minor components. This paper describes the isolation and <lb/>characterization of these pigments. <lb/>Tanshindiols B (2) and C (3) had the same molecular <lb/>formula, ClsH160s (m/z 312 [Ml&apos;), and their spectral <lb/>data were quite similar to each other, indicating that they <lb/>must be stereoisomers. Thus, in addition to each tertiary <lb/>hydroxyl group, 2 had a secondary axial hydroxyl group <lb/>cS3.98 (lH, dd, J = 4.8, 2.9 Hz)] and 3 had a secondary <lb/>equatorial one cS3.96 (lH, dd, J = 4.0, 12 Hz)]. In fact, <lb/>oxidation of either 2 or 3 with sodium periodate gave the <lb/>same product (8). 8 had an acetophenone-type methyl <lb/>ketone moiety c62.61 (3H, s)] and a phenylpropion-<lb/>aldehyde moiety. The presence of the latter moiety <lb/>(Ar-CH&amp;H&amp;HO) <lb/>in 8 was established by the <lb/>&apos;H NMR spectrum with the aid of double resonance <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Repeated column chromatography of the ethanolic <lb/>extract of Dan-Shen on silica gel afforded five new <lb/>abietanoids (l-S), in addition to many known abietanoids <lb/>which are described in the Experimental. <lb/>Tanshindiol A (l), orange-red needles, C1sH1605, gave <lb/>rise to spectra which were similar to those of tanshinone <lb/>IIA (6) [4,5]. However, notable differences between 1 and <lb/>6 were seen with regard to the following points. The <lb/>&apos;H NMR spectrum of 6 had a singlet due to a geminal <lb/>dimethyl group at 61.30 [631.9 (q +q) and 34.9 (s) in the <lb/>13C NMR spectrum (Table l)] and the IR spectrum of 6 <lb/>showed no hydroxyl band. On the other hand, 1 had two <lb/>hydroxyl groups instead of a geminal dimethyl group. <lb/>One of them was a primary alcohol attached to a <lb/>tetrasubstituted carbon ES3.60 (2H, s); m/z 281 [M <lb/>-3 l] &apos;1 and the other was a tertiary alcohol attached to <lb/>the same carbon. This was further confirmed by acety-<lb/>lation of 1 with acetic anhydride-pyridine <lb/>to give the <lb/>corresponding monoacetate (7) [v3500 and 1725 cm-&apos;; <lb/>62.14 (3H, s), and 4.22 (2H, s); 669.6 (t)and 71.4 (s)]. From <lb/>the above results, the structure of tanshindiol A can be <lb/>represented as 1. <lb/>*To whom correspondence sho$d be addressed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">PWTD 24:4-t <lb/></note>

			<page>815 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. 13C NMR spectra of 4, 6 and 7 <lb/>(25 MHz, CDCl, + CD30D, TMS as internal <lb/>standard) <lb/>C <lb/>7 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>28.8 t <lb/>2 <lb/>l9.2t <lb/>3 <lb/>32.3 t <lb/>4 <lb/>71.4s <lb/>5 <lb/>143.0s <lb/>6 <lb/>134.3d <lb/>7 <lb/>120Sd <lb/>8 <lb/>129.3s <lb/>9 <lb/>125.8s <lb/>10 <lb/>145.2 s <lb/>11 <lb/>182.9s <lb/>12 <lb/>175.2 s <lb/>13 <lb/>121.3st <lb/>14 <lb/>161.2s <lb/>15 <lb/>142.1 d <lb/>16 <lb/>120.5 St <lb/>17 <lb/>8.7q <lb/>18 <lb/>69.6 t <lb/>19 <lb/>-<lb/>Me <lb/>20.8 q <lb/>co <lb/>182.9s <lb/>30.2 t <lb/>19.3 t <lb/>38.0 t <lb/>34.9 s <lb/>144.8 s <lb/>134.0d <lb/>120.6d <lb/>127.5s <lb/>126.3 s <lb/>150.6 s <lb/>183.5s <lb/>175.7s <lb/>121.3st <lb/>162.2s <lb/>141.9d <lb/>120.6 st <lb/>8.7q <lb/>31.9q <lb/>31.9q <lb/>28.3 t <lb/>22.2 t <lb/>38.0 t <lb/>197.3 s <lb/>134.6 s <lb/>134.2d <lb/>120.9d <lb/>133.6s <lb/>126.4s <lb/>150.5 s <lb/>182.8 s <lb/>175.5 s <lb/>122.0st <lb/>162.7 s <lb/>143.2d <lb/>120.9 st <lb/>8.7q <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>tValues can be interchanged. <lb/></body>

			<page>816 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">H.-W. Luo et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>1 R&apos;=CH*OH, <lb/>R&apos;=OH, <lb/>R3=R4=H <lb/>2 R&apos;=Me, <lb/>R2=R3=OH, <lb/>R4=H <lb/>3 R&apos;= Me, R2= R4=OH, <lb/>R3= H <lb/>4 R&apos;= R2=0, <lb/>R3=R4=H <lb/>7 RI= CH,OAc, R&apos;=OH, R3= R4=H <lb/>5 R&apos;=OH, <lb/>Ra=H <lb/>6 R&apos;=R&apos;=H <lb/>10 R&apos;=OAc, <lb/>R&apos;=OH <lb/>11 R&apos;=H, R&apos;=OH <lb/>, <lb/>OHC! <lb/>j$@ <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>experiments cS3.32 (2H, m), 2.90 (2H, m) and 9.85 (lH, <lb/>near s)]. Irradiation at 62.90 caused, respectively, the <lb/>multiplet at 63.32 and the near singlet at 69.85 to collapse <lb/>to a singlet and a sharp singlet, whereas on irradiation at <lb/>63.32 the multiplet at 62.90 became a near singlet. The <lb/>stereochemistries of the two vicinal hydroxyl groups in 2 <lb/>and 3 were determined on the basis of the following <lb/>chemical evidence. Treatment of 2 with acetone in the <lb/>presence of anhydrous cupric sulphate resulted in the <lb/>recovery of the starting material, but treatment of 3 under <lb/>the same conditions readily afforded the corresponding <lb/>acetonide (9). The structures of tanshindiols B and C can <lb/>therefore be represented as 2 and 3, respectively, including <lb/>the stereochemistries of the two vicinal hydroxyl groups. <lb/>Nortanshinone (4), C,,H,104, <lb/>gave rise to spectra <lb/>similar to those of tanshinone IIA (6). Moreover, 4 had <lb/>one arylic carbonyl group [S 197.3 (s)] instead of a geminal <lb/>dimethyl group in addition to two orthoquinone car-<lb/>bony1 groups [S 175.5 (s) and 182.8 ($1. The location of the <lb/>arylic carbonyl group was assigned by analysis of the <lb/>&apos;H NMR spectrum with the aid of double resonance <lb/>experiments. On irradiation at 62.12, the multiplets at <lb/>6 2.7 1 and 3.46 were changed to sharp singlets. The signal <lb/>at 6 2.12 was changed to a triplet on irradiation at 6 2.71 as <lb/>well as at 3.46. Furthermore, the doublet at 67.96 in 1 was <lb/>shifted to 68.37 in the &apos;H NMR spectrum of 4. This <lb/>downfield shift seemed to be due to the anisotropic effect <lb/>of the carbonyl group. From these results, the structure of <lb/>nortanshinone can be represented as 4. In addition, <lb/>tanshindiol A (1) was subjected to oxidation using sodium <lb/>periodate to afford a carbonyl compound which was <lb/>identical to nortanshinone (4). <lb/>The last pigment, 3a-hydroxytanshinone <lb/>IIA (S), <lb/>CigHlsO,, had a geminal dimethyl group C61.33 (6H, s)] <lb/>and a secondary hydroxyl group [a 3.67 (1 H, m)], which <lb/>was readily acetylated by acetic anhydride-pyridine <lb/>to <lb/>give the corresponding acetate (10) cS2.05 (3H, s) and 5.00 <lb/>(1 H, t, J = 4.9 Hz)]. The presence of the partial structure <lb/>ECH2-CHI-CH-~ <lb/>in 5 was established by the follow-<lb/>ing experiments. On irradiation of 10 at 65.00, the <lb/>multiplet at 62.03 changed to a triplet, and then the <lb/>multiplet at 63.32 as well as that at 65.00 changed to a <lb/>singlet on irradiation at 62.03. Finally, the multiplet at <lb/>62.03 changed to a doublet on irradiation at 63.32. In <lb/>1968, hydroxytanshinone <lb/>II (11) having a secondary <lb/>hydroxyl group at C-l was reported by Kalcisawa et al. <lb/>[S]. The physical data of 5 are clearly different from those <lb/>of 11. Therefore, the hydroxyl group in 5 must be located <lb/>at C-3. This was also confirmed by the &apos;H NMR spectra, <lb/>which showed the signals due to the benzylic methylene <lb/>protons at 63.26 (2H) in 5 and at 63.32 (2H) in 10, <lb/>respectively. From the above results, the structure of 3a-<lb/>hydroxytanshinone IIA can be represented as 5. <lb/>With the exception of 4, we have not established the <lb/>absolute configurations of the new pigments (l-5). <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL <lb/>Mps: uncorr; &apos;H NMR (100 and 60 MHz) and 13C NMR <lb/>(25 MHz): CDCI, unless stated otherwise, TM.9 as internal <lb/>standard, IR: KBr; MS: direct inlet system. <lb/>Extraction and separation. Dan-Shen (ca 120 kg) from the <lb/>Shandong Province (China) was mechanically crushed and <lb/>extracted with hot 95% EtOH. The cont. extract (1.2 kg) was <lb/>treated with CsHs to give a C,H6-soluble fraction (ca 800 g) and <lb/>a CdH,-insoluble fraction (ca 400 g). <lb/>The former fraction was chromatographed on silica gel and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pigments from Salvia miltiorrhiza <lb/></note>

			<page>817 <lb/></page>

			<body>eluted successively with C6He and CIH,-CHCI,-MeOH <lb/>(9: 1:0.5). Each fraction obtained was rechromatographed on <lb/>silica gel using a gradient of CHCI&amp;IezCO to afford five known <lb/>pigments, tanshinone IIA (78 g), tanshinone I (6 g), methylene-<lb/>tanshiquinone (2 g), cryptotanshinone <lb/>(2 g) and dihydro-<lb/>tanshinone I (1 g) as crystals, respectively. The mother liquor of <lb/>tanshinone I from CHCI,-MeOH <lb/>was coned and further <lb/>separated by CC on silica gel using CHCI, containing an <lb/>increasing amount of MezCO to give nortanshinone (4) (101 mg). <lb/>The CeH,-insoluble fraction, which was soluble in a <lb/>mixture of C6Hs-MeOH (9:1), was subjected to dry CC on <lb/>silica gel. The very polar fraction (ca 260g) eluted with <lb/>&amp;H,-MeOH-formamide <lb/>(7: 3 : 0.5) after elution with C6H6 was <lb/>rechromatographed on polyamide powder using 95 y0 EtOH to <lb/>afford a mixture of reddish pigments (120 g). The mixture was <lb/>separated further by CC on sil&amp;a gel using CHzClz-EtOAc (3: 1) <lb/>to afford four crude pigments (1, 2,3 and 5). These pigments were <lb/>purified by prep. TLC on silica gel (CHzClz-EtOAcMeOH, <lb/>15: 5: 1) followed by recrystalization from CHCl,-MeOH to <lb/>afford pure pigments, 1 (9Omg), 2 (9Omg), 3 (30mg) and 5 <lb/>(85 mg), respectively. <lb/>Tamhindiol A (1). Mp 222-223&quot;; HRMS m/z: Found 3 12.0992 <lb/>[Ml&apos; (C,sH,60, requires 312.09%); IRvcm-&apos;: <lb/>3530, 3400, <lb/>1655, 1570, 1530; &apos;HNMR: 61.81 (2H, m), 2.26 (3H, d, <lb/>J = 1.8Hz), 2.69 (2H, m), 3.21 (2H, m), 3.60 (ZH, s), 7.39 (lH, <lb/>q, J = 1.8 Hz), 7.64 (lH, d, J = 7 Hz), 7.91 (lH, d, J = 7 Hz). <lb/>Tanshindiol E (2). Mp 210-213&quot;; HRMS m/z: Found 312.0987 <lb/>[M]+ (C,,HlcO, requires 312.0996); IRvcm-&apos;: <lb/>3470, 1655, <lb/>1570,153O; &apos;H NMR: 61.50 (3H, s), 2.14 (2H, m), 2.27 (3H, d, J <lb/>= 1.5 Hz),3.35(2H,m),3.98(1H,dd,J <lb/>= 4.4,2.9Hz),7.26(1H,q, <lb/>J = 1.5 Hz), 7.66 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz), 8.03 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz). <lb/>Tanshindiol C (3). Mp 213-215&quot;; HRMS m/z: Found 312.0988 <lb/>[Ml&apos; (C,sH1605 requires 312.09%); IRvcm-&apos;: <lb/>3480, 1660, <lb/>1574 1530; &apos;H NMR: 6 1.46 (3H, s), 1.55 (2H, s, O_H, disappeared <lb/>on addition of DzO), 2.16 (2H, m), 2.27 (3H, d, J = 1.5 Hz), 3.36 <lb/>(2H, m), 3.96 (lH, dd (br), J = 12,4 Hz, changed to a sharp dd on <lb/>additionofDzO),7.26(1H,q.J <lb/>= 1.5 Hz),764(1H,d,J = 8 Hz), <lb/>7.97 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz). <lb/>Nortanshinone (4). Mp 231-232&quot;; HRMS m/z: Found 280.0711 <lb/>[Ml&apos; (C,,H,zO* requires 280.07343; IR vcm-I: 3120, 1660, <lb/>1570,153Q&apos;HNMR:62.12(2H,m),2.30(3H,d,J <lb/>= 1.8Hz),2.70 <lb/>(2H, m), 3.40 (2H, m), 7.31 (lH, q, J = 1.8Hz), 7.77 (lH, d, <lb/>J = 8 Hz), 8.33 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz). <lb/>3a-Hydroxytanshinone IIA (5). Mp 205-206&quot;; HRMS m/z; <lb/>Found 310.1183 [Ml&apos; <lb/>(C19H180G requires 310.1204); <lb/>IR v cm-&apos;: 3500,1665,1575,1530; &apos;H NMR: 6 1.33 (3H, s), 1.35 <lb/>(3H,s),1.94(2H,m),2.26(3H,nears),3.31(2H,m),3.74(1H,dd,J <lb/>= 4, 8 Hz), 7.24 (lH, s), 7.56 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz), 7.68 (lH, d, J <lb/>= 8 Hz). <lb/>Acetylation oftanshindiol A (1). A mixture of 1 (10 mg), AczO <lb/>(0.3 ml) and C,HsN (0.3 ml) was stirred at room temp. for 3 hr. <lb/>The residue obtained on removal of solvent was separated by CC <lb/>on silica gel with CHCI,-MeOH (5:l) to give 7 (10mg) as <lb/> orange-red crystals, mp 125-127&quot;; MS m/z: 354 [M]+ <lb/>(C2,,H1s06), 281 [M-CHzOCOMe]+; <lb/>IR vcm-&apos;: 3500,1725, <lb/>1660,1570,1530; &apos;H NMR: 61.87 (2H, m), 2.14 (3H, s), 2.26 (3H, <lb/>d, J = 1.8 Hz), 2.75 (2H, m), 3.20 (2H, m), 4.22 (2H, s), 7.25 (lH, q, <lb/>J = 1.8 Hz), 7.54 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz), 7.91 (lH, d, J = 8 Hz). <lb/>Oxidation of tanshindiol B (2) and tanshindiol C (3). A mixture <lb/>of 2 (11 mg) and NaI04 (26 mg) in 90 % MeOH (10 ml) was <lb/>stirred at room temp. for 5 hr. The mixture was coned under <lb/>reduced pressure, diluted with HzO, and extracted with CHCI,. <lb/>Evapn of solvent afforded 8 (7 mg), mp 182-184&quot;; MS m/z: 310 <lb/>[M]+ (ClsH1.,05); IRvcm-&apos;: <lb/>2840, 2720, 1720, 1680, 1580, <lb/>1535; &apos;H NMR: 62.29 (3H, d, J = 1.5 Hz), 2.61 (3H, s), 2.90 (2H, <lb/>m), 3.32 (2H, m), 7.33 (lH, q, J = 1.5 Hz), 7.73 (2H, s), 9.85 (lH, <lb/>near s). <lb/>Under the same conditions, oxidations of 3 (4 mg) with NaIO, <lb/>(10 mg) gave 8 (2.5 mg). Identification was made by spectral <lb/>comparison (IR and &apos;H NMR). <lb/>Reaction of3 with Me&amp;O. A mixture of 3 (4 mg), anhydrous <lb/>CuSO, (5 mg) and MezCO (10 ml) was stirred at 40&quot; for 5 hr, <lb/>coned under reduced pressure, diluted with HzO, and extracted <lb/>with CHCl,. Evapn of solvent afforded the acetonide (9) (2.5 mg), <lb/>mp 117-119&quot;; MS m/z 352 [Ml&apos; (CzlHzOOs); &apos;H NMR: 61.54 <lb/>(3H, s), 1.61 (6H, s), 1.99 (2H, m), 2.27 (3H, d, J = 1.2 Hz), 3.22 <lb/>(2H, m), 4.15 (lH, m), 7.30 (lH, q, J = 1.2 Hz), 7.68 (lH, d, <lb/>J = 8.4 Hz), 7.89 (lH, d, J = 8.4 Hz). <lb/>Oxidation of lanshindiol A (1). Oxidation of 1 (10 mg) with <lb/>NaIO, (20 mg) in aq. MeOH gave 4 (7 mg), which was identical <lb/>with the authentic sample. <lb/>Acetylation of 3a-hydroxytanshinone IIA (5). A mixture of 5 <lb/>(6 mg), AczO (0.2 ml) and CsH,N (0.5 ml) was stirred at room <lb/>temp. for 5 hr. The residue, coned under reduced pressure, was <lb/>chromatographed on silica gel with CHCl,-MeOH (5:l) to <lb/>afford 10 (5 mg), mp 200-201&quot;; MS m/z: 352 [Ml&apos; (C2,Hz00s); <lb/>IR vcm-&apos;: 1730, 1665,1575,1530; &apos;H NMR: 61.33 (6H, s), 2.03 <lb/>(2H, m), 2.05 (3H, s), 2.26 (3H, d, J = 1.5 Hz), 3.32 (2H, t, <lb/>J=6.6Hz),5.OO(lH,t,J=4.9Hz),7.24(1H,q,J= <lb/>1.5Hz),7.62 <lb/>(2H, s). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement-We thank Professor H. Kakisawa (Tsukuba <lb/>University) for providing the authentic sample of tanshinone IIA. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Fang, C., Chang, P. and Hsu, T. (1976) Huahsueh Hsuehpao <lb/>34, 197; (1978) Chem. Abst. 88, 1770782. <lb/>2. Onitsuka, M., Fujiu, M., Shinma, N. and Maruyama, H. B. <lb/>(1983) Chem. Pharm. Bull. 31, 1670. <lb/>3. Luo, H., Sheng, L., Zhang, S., Xy L. and Wei, P. (1983) Yaoxue <lb/>Xuebao 18, 1; (1983) Chem. Abslr. 99, 16073f. <lb/>4. Okumura, Y., Kakisawa, H., Kato, M. and Hirata, Y. (1961) <lb/>Bull. Chem. Sot. Jpn. 34, 1895. <lb/>5. Kakisawa, H., Hayashi, T., Okazaki, I. and Ohashi, M. (1968) <lb/>Tetrahedron Letters 3231. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
