<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/>DEVICE FOR MEASURING THE PAINTING THICKNESS AND <lb/>CIRCUNFERENCIAL DEFORMATION ON 14&quot; PIPELINES <lb/>Vitor Ferreira Romano, romano@mecanica.ufrj.br <lb/>Federal University of Rio de Janeiro -Poli/UFRJ <lb/>Mechanical Engineering Department -Robotics Laboratory <lb/>Cidade Universitária -CT, Bloco G-204 <lb/>CEP 21945-970 Rio de Janeiro -RJ -Brazil <lb/>Cesar Gomes Ferreira, cesarlog@gmail.com <lb/>Digital Dinâmica Automação Ltda. <lb/>Luiz Eduardo da Silva Demenicis, demenicis@hotmail.com <lb/>Patriot Mechanical Handling Ltd. <lb/>West Yorkshire BD17 7DW, UK <lb/>Ney Robinson Salvi dos Reis, salvireis@petrobras.com.br <lb/>Petrobras/CENPES/PDP/Underwater Technology Dept. <lb/>Abstract. This article presents the mechanical design aspects of a measuring device prototype (Tinta-P) designed to <lb/>evaluate the internal operational condition on a 14&quot; diameter pipeline for oil &amp; derivates transportation. The scenario <lb/>of application is a 28 km length and 40 years old pipeline located in the State of Bahia, from Madre Deus marine <lb/>terminal to the Petrochemical Complex of Camaçari. The pipeline operator, Petrobras, made a contract with a company <lb/>to provide an extended life procedure against coating and corrosion, using a technology based on internal deposition <lb/>of a chemical inhibitor along the pipe. The Tinta-P prototype was developed to verify the right distribution of internal <lb/>painting in a given section of the pipeline and its circumference deformation. Tinta-P prototype has radial and <lb/>angular positioning control (R -θ directions), waterproof facilities (two meters H 2 O) and auto-compensation <lb/>mechanisms. The design phases of the three constructed prototypes are the main topics related to this paper. <lb/>Keywords: mechatronic design, measuring device, pipeline, robotics. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>1.1. Operational site <lb/>Madre Deus marine terminal (Temadre) is located in the State of Bahia and since 1957 is controlled by Petrobras <lb/>(SICM, 2007). In Temadre arrives at about 40 ships per month, mainly from offshore oil drilling platforms in the <lb/>Sergipe-Alagoas Basin. Its installed facilities operate nearly 1,000,000 m 3 of crude oil and derivates per month. Most <lb/>part of these products is transported by pipelines to Mataripe refinery (RLAM) and to the Petrochemical Complex of <lb/>Camaçari. Both pipelines are under the soil and in many regions the nearby area is populated. This paper deals with the <lb/>development of prototypes conceived to make internal inspections on the 28 km length pipeline from Temadre to <lb/>Camaçari. <lb/>1.2. Pipeline maintenance <lb/>Inspection of the inside surface of the pipe is necessary to verify the existence of anomalies like corrosion and <lb/>crack. Other important information regards pipe structural deformations such as bending and ovality as the result of <lb/>external forces caused by soil motion or increase of pressure due to human constructions. <lb/>Pipeline cleaning is a usual procedure to increase the capacity of product transportation, since organic deposits as <lb/>paraffin in crude oil and inner surface irregularities due to corrosion inside the pipe can cause turbulence and <lb/>consequently increase friction loss, reduce pipe bore and decrease capacity in the product flow. <lb/>2. INTERNAL INSPECTION TOOLS <lb/>2.1. Pigs <lb/>Pig is a cylinder-shaped electromechanical device designed for cleaning or inspection of the internal wall of a pipe <lb/>with non destructive testing techniques (Baldez1 et all, 2001). The term pig is associated to a device that travels with <lb/>the propelling force of the fluid being pumped (liquid) or compressed (gas) through the pipeline. Rubber seals on the <lb/>pig make it act like a piston in the pipeline. Instrumented Pig uses sensors, electronics, and recording or output <lb/></body>

			<front>ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/> Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></front>

			<body>functions integral to the system. While traveling the onboard data acquisition system records the defect data, sensed by <lb/>the sensors touching the internal surface of pipe wall. These data usually corresponds to defects sizing and location <lb/>along the inspected pipe (Baldez1 et all, 2001). <lb/>Pig tools can be classified according to their operational tasks as metal loss tools: magnetic flux leakage and <lb/>ultrasonic; crack detection tools: ultrasonic and transverse magnetic flux; elastic wave tools: ultrasound in two <lb/>directions; geometrical tools: caliper (mechanical fingers or electromagnetic methods to detect dent or deformations); <lb/>pipe deformation tool: caliper and gyroscopes provide pipe bend information; mapping tools: use of GPS (Da Silva et <lb/>all, 2001). <lb/>Figure 1. Pig with geometrical tool. (Da Silva,2001). <lb/>2.2. Special tools <lb/>Pigs are very useful for pipeline cleaning and inspection, but are not able to make interventions or activities that <lb/>require large consumption of electrical and mechanical power in specific positions, as occur in welding and ovality <lb/>deformation repair in a circular pipe. Pigs cannot also be used in situations where the fluid has low velocity since the <lb/>friction forces against the pipe wall can be higher than the propelling force of the fluid-pig interaction. <lb/>The development of special devices and tools for internal pipe intervention are necessary to execute those <lb/>activities that a Pig is not able to do. In general they are teleoperated units formed by modules (locomotion or traction, <lb/>data processing, instrumentation, power supply and so on) connected to an external operational base by an umbilical <lb/>cable. <lb/>In Fig. 2 is presented the concept of a locomotion module denominated G.I.R.I.N.O. -Get Inside Robot to Impel <lb/>and Normal Operation -. This teleoperated prototype was designed and constructed at CENPES/Petrobras (Reis,1999). <lb/>It has an umbilical cable containing hydraulic and electrical lines, is hydraulically actuated and moves in a discrete <lb/>mode. <lb/>Figure 2. Prototype of G.I.R.I.N.O. traction module. <lb/>3. PROTOTYPE DESIGN CONCEPTS <lb/>3.1. Project scenario <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/> Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>In 2002 Petrobras made a contract with a company to provide an extended life procedure against coating and <lb/>corrosion, using a technology based on internal deposition of a chemical inhibitor along the pipe. The scenario of <lb/>application was a 14&quot; diameter pipeline with 28 km length and 40 years old located in the State of Bahia, from Madre <lb/>Deus marine terminal to the Petrochemical Complex of Camaçari. <lb/>The first activity performed by the company was a &quot;Pre-Inspection Preparation&quot; of the internal surface using some <lb/>cleaning Pigs. Then, an instrumented Pig with appropriate tool was used to paint the pipe inner surface with the <lb/>chemical inhibitor. <lb/>In order to evaluate the contracted service, Petrobras asked for the development of a special instrumented device <lb/>able to verify if the distribution of chemical inhibitor product in a given point of the pipe section was attending <lb/>international standards and to quantify its circumference deformation. This device here denominated Tinta-P should be <lb/>connected to the traction module G.I.R.I.N.O. and support an external pressure of two meters of water column. The <lb/>measurements should be made with no flow at the pipeline. <lb/>Two prototypes were constructed and tested before the final conception of Tinta-P. <lb/>3.2. Design general aspects <lb/>The general design aspects needed for the project are: <lb/>• Use of a commercial ultra-sound sensor to measure paint thickness. <lb/>• Capability of moving in curved pipes (curvature radius of 10 x diameter). <lb/>• Protection facilities to onboard camera and electronic hardware. <lb/>• Mechanism to guarantee the alignment of the prototype axis relative to the pipe axis. <lb/>• Weightless parts. <lb/>• Easy procedures for mounting and dismounting of parts. <lb/>• Commercial component for fast maintenance. <lb/>• Compact design. <lb/>3.3. First prototype <lb/>The first prototype (Fig. 3) was developed to test a solution based on a two degrees-of-freedom (d.o.f.) mechanism <lb/>and step motors (1.8 o resolution). This device was characterized by: <lb/>• No pressure protection. <lb/>• No waterproof protection. <lb/>• Actuators: <lb/>1 step motor for angular motion (sensor orientation). <lb/>1 step motor for radial motion (sensor positioning). <lb/>• Radial motion: screw mechanism with a limit switch. <lb/>• Angular motion: direct drive. <lb/>• Safety return electro-mechanism actuated in case of energy fault (solenoid). <lb/>• Alignment mechanism. <lb/>• Programmed motion for data acquisition procedures. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 3. First prototype. (a) Photo. (b) CAD model. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. First prototype: mechanism main parts. <lb/>The first prototype mechanism worked properly but undesired vibrations occurred in the radial motion. Another <lb/>critical part was the small amplitude of the alignment mechanism, reducing the system capability to move in curved <lb/>pipes. <lb/>3.4. Second prototype <lb/>The main improvements made on the second prototype (Fig. 5) are related to the modified alignment system, <lb/>ensuring more amplitude and rigidity to the system, and the adjustments on the motion mechanism to reduce vibration. <lb/>Figure 5. Second prototype. <lb/>The performance of this prototype was acceptable for the measuring of the specified parameters. After some tests <lb/>the design team started the development of the final prototype. <lb/>4. TINTA-P PROTOTYPE <lb/>This final version prototype is characterized by the following improvements (Figs. 6 and 7): <lb/>• Radial and angular positioning control (R -θ directions). <lb/>elevator unit <lb/>motor 1 <lb/>motor 2 <lb/>ultra-sound sensor <lb/>solenoid <lb/>alignment mechanism <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>• Teleoperated or robotic operation modes. <lb/>• Waterproof (2 meters H 2 O) and explosion-proof container unit. <lb/>• Auto-compensated alignment system. <lb/>• Radial motion unit: pneumatic actuator and 2 d.o.f. mechanism. <lb/>• Angular motion: DC motor and planetary gear reduction. <lb/>• Pendulum sensor system to keep horizontal reference. <lb/>Figure 6. Tinta-P prototype and pipeline CAD model. <lb/>Figure 7. Details of Tinta-P components. <lb/>4.1. Structural unit <lb/>The structural unit provides the necessary rigidity, alignment and protection to all system units. It has stainless steel <lb/>components and is formed by two circular shape flanges rigidly interconnected by three structural bars in pretension <lb/>with screws. <lb/>The structure is also responsible for container unit protection against external forces/moments due to pipeline <lb/>interaction. <lb/>4.2. Container unit <lb/>alignment unit <lb/>(back side) <lb/>central flange <lb/>motor <lb/>compressor <lb/>pendulum <lb/>back side <lb/>flange <lb/>frontal flange <lb/>Motion direction <lb/>structural bar <lb/>umbilical <lb/>alignment unit <lb/>(front side) <lb/>container unit <lb/>14&quot; pipeline <lb/>alignment unit <lb/>radial motion <lb/>mechanism <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>The container unit is located inside the structure and has cylinder components made in PVC. Its main functions are: <lb/>isolation from external pressure and humidity (waterproof for 2 meters H 2 O) of the onboard components, such as <lb/>electronics -motor, encoders, data acquisition and control circuits, communication circuit -and pneumatic system -<lb/>compressor, directional valves, air pressure reservoir -, and explosion-proof capability <lb/>The onboard components can be easily accessed due to container unit modular concept, as presented in Fig. 8. <lb/>Figure 8. Details of the Tinta-P container unit and onboard components. <lb/>4.3. Sensor unit <lb/>Tinta-P was designed to measure in a given transverse section of the pipeline inner surface, the coordinates of <lb/>selected points referenced to pipeline symmetry axis and their associated chemical inhibitor thickness. The database of <lb/>sampled points represents the section mapping situation in terms of geometrical parameters: radial deformations due to <lb/>external pressure from soil interaction and distribution of the internal painting. <lb/>A commercial ultra-sound calibrated transducer was used to evaluate the chemical inhibitor thickness. The sensor is <lb/>located in a linear platform that moves in connection with a piston rod. When the piston rod moves upward and touches <lb/>the pipe inner surface, the sensor achieves its proper position, orientation and contact force due to adjustment of a <lb/>spring located in the extended extremity of a two d.o.f. arm. <lb/>Figure 9. Details of the Tinta-P container unit and onboard components. <lb/>4.4. Alignment Unit <lb/>thickness transducer <lb/>spring <lb/>piston rod <lb/>arm <lb/>encoder axis <lb/>container unit <lb/>(main body) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>The auto-compensated alignment system is formed by back side and front side units (Fig. 7). Each one contains a <lb/>tripod mechanism with wheels actuated by a rigid spring. <lb/>This system tends to keep the geometrical axis of the Tinta-P concentrically to the theoretical symmetry axis of <lb/>the pipeline, in the vicinity of the region of analysis. <lb/>5. Motion Especification <lb/>In order to sample representative points located in the internal circumference of the pipeline wall, Tinta-P is able to <lb/>move in the radial and angular directions. <lb/>5.1. Radial motion <lb/>The radial motion is obtained with the displacement of a piston rod associated to a pneumatic cylinder. This <lb/>motion is necessary to move the ultra-sound transducer nearby the measurement point. <lb/>A planar two d.o.f. arm measuring system with revolute joints is used to quantify the radial displacements <lb/>referred to the geometrical axis of the Tinta-P. One of its extremities is connected to the piston rod and the other to an <lb/>encoder (Fig. 9). When the piston rod moves, induces the movement of the arm and consequently the angular <lb/>displacement of the encoder. <lb/>A Denavit-Hartenberg parameterization (Sciavicco and Siciliano, 2001) was used to establish the analytical <lb/>relation of the arm positioning and encoder angular displacement. The limit configurations of the radial motion are <lb/>described in Fig. 10. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 10. Arm measuring system. (a) retracted configuration. (b) extended configuration. <lb/>5.2. Angular motion <lb/>A DC motor and planetary gearhead module furnishes the torque to move the main body units, relative to the <lb/>alignment units, that remain fixed to the pipeline. An encoder integrated to a pendulum gives the value of the relative <lb/>angular motion (Fig. 7). <lb/>6. TESTS <lb/>6.1. Laboratory Set Up <lb/>The prototypes were mounted and calibrated at the Robotics Laboratory at Mechanical Eng. Department -<lb/>UFRJ/COPPE (LabRob DEM-PEM). <lb/>To validate the performance of the equipments, test facilities such as 2 meters length linear and curved 14&quot; pipes <lb/>were installed at the Lab. <lb/>A &quot;last minute&quot; design modification on the alignment units of the 3 rd prototype was necessary to permit the system <lb/>to move along a visiting hole located at the upper part of the pipe. This consisted in the addition of wheels at the tripod <lb/>mechanism. It should be noted that a visiting hole exists at each 200 m of pipeline length. <lb/>In Figs. 11 and 12 are presented the constructed prototype and a data mapping of a pipe section. <lb/> 6.2. On Site Tests <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<body>While the 3 rd prototype was under tests at the LabRob DEM-PEM, the 2 nd prototype was sent to Bahia, in order to <lb/>measure a pipeline sample submitted to the internal painting. <lb/>The 2 nd prototype measured data proved that the distribution of chemical inhibitor product in a tested pipe section <lb/>was not according to Petrobras standards. <lb/>Based on these results Petrobras was able to punish the company and redefine the service. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 11. (a) Prototype at the Lab. (b) Testes in a curved 14&quot; pipe. <lb/>Figure 12. Mapping of a pipe section. <lb/>7. CONCLUSIONS <lb/>The mechanical characteristics of the second and third prototypes were able to measure the internal distribution of <lb/>chemical inhibitor product in a 14&quot; pipeline section and its circumference deformation. <lb/>Although the concept of the 3 rd prototype was more sophisticated then the 2 nd one, the on site measuring tests with <lb/>the 2 nd prototype was enough to evaluate the pipeline conditions, according to Petrobras standards. <lb/>The successful performance of the equipment helped Petrobras to redefine the service and new conditions were <lb/>established. <lb/>For future developments the authors suggest a new concept based on hydraulic actuators, so that a high pressure <lb/>could be applied to the equipment and measurements be made with the presence of fluid flow at the pipeline. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgment">8. ACKNOLEDGEMENTS <lb/> The authors thank prof. Liu Hsu for his participation as Project Coordinator. <lb/>This project was mainly financed with FINEP/CT-Petro 1 funds. Partial funds were also obtained with CNPq. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>9. REFERENCES <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM <lb/>Proceedings of COBEM 2009 <lb/>20th International Congress of Mechanical Engineering <lb/>Copyright © 2009 by ABCM <lb/>November 15-20, 2009, Gramado, RS, Brazil <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Beitz, W. and Küttner K.-H., Editors, 1994, &quot;Dubbel Handbook of Mechanical Engineering&quot;, Springer-Verlag, U.K. <lb/>Dorf, R.C., Bishop. R. H., 2001, &quot; Modern Control Systems&quot; (in Portuguese), Ed. LTC, pp. 93-127. <lb/>Reis, N.R.S., &quot;Get Inside Robot to Impel and Normal Operation -G.I.R.I.N.O.&quot;, 1999 <lb/>http://www.bahiainvest.com.br/ing/index.asp, BahiaInvest Portal&apos;s, State Secretariat of Industry, Commerce, and <lb/>Mining (SICM), 2007. <lb/>Da Silva, J. A. Pereira and Pinho, A. F. &quot;Ferramenta para Inspeção Geométrica de Dutos de 3 pol.&quot; (in portuguese), 3rd <lb/>Seminar on Pipeline, CD version, Brazilian Petroleum and Gas Institute -IBP, Rio de Janeiro, Brazil, November 2001. <lb/>Baldez1 M., Pereira, J.A., Janvrot, I.V., Camerini C.S., &quot;Inspeções com Pigs Geométricos: Principais Resultados de <lb/>Campo&quot; (in portuguese), 3rd Seminar on Pipeline, CD version, Brazilian Petroleum and Gas Institute -IBP, Rio de <lb/>Janeiro, Brazil, November 2001 <lb/>Sciavicco, L. and Siciliano, B., Modeling and Control of Robot Manipulators. UK, Springer-Verlag, 2001. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">10. RESPONSIBILITY NOTICE <lb/>The authors are the only responsible for the printed material included in this paper. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">ABCM Symposium Series in Mechatronics -Vol. 4 -pp.784-792 <lb/>Copyright © 2010 by ABCM </note>


	</text>
</tei>
