<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Vascular Endothelial Growth Factor Inhibits Mitogen-Induced Vascular<lb/> Smooth Muscle Cell Proliferation 1,2<lb/> Amir H. Dorafshar, M.D.,* Niren Angle, M.D.,* ,3 Michael Bryer-Ash, M.D., , Danshan Huang, M.D., ,<lb/> Michael M. Farooq, M.D.,* Hugh A. Gelabert, M.D.,* and Julie A. Freischlag, M.D.<lb/> *Division of Vascular Surgery and Division of Endocrinology, Diabetes and Hypertension, UCLA Gonda (Goldschmied) Diabetes Center,<lb/> David Geffen School of Medicine at UCLA, Los Angeles, CA; and Research Service, West Los Angeles Veterans Administration<lb/> Medical Center, Los Angeles, CA<lb/> Submitted for publication December 11, 2002<lb/> Introduction. Delivery of vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor (VEGF) protein or gene transfer has<lb/> been shown to accelerate re-endothelialization and at-<lb/>tenuate neointimal hyperplasia in various arterial in-<lb/>jury models, including balloon injury, stent implanta-<lb/>tion, and vein grafts. In addition to stimulating re-<lb/>endothelialization, we hypothesize that VEGF has<lb/> further vascular protective functions to prevent neo-<lb/>intimal hyperplasia by directly inhibiting mitogen-<lb/>induced proliferation of vascular smooth muscle cells<lb/> (VSMCs) via the mitogen-activated protein kinase<lb/> pathway.<lb/> Materials and methods. Human aortic VSMCs were<lb/> seeded and serum starved for 24 h. The cells were then<lb/> stimulated with a mitogen, recombinant human plate-<lb/>let derived growth factor at 20 ng/mL together with 0,<lb/> 10, 20, 30, 40, 50 ng/mL recombinant human VEGF. A<lb/> proliferation assay was used to quantitate bromode-<lb/>oxyuridine uptake into newly synthesized DNA. West-<lb/>ern immunoassay was used to quantify extracellular<lb/> signal-regulated kinase (ERK) 2 protein and phos-<lb/>phorylation of retinoblastoma and ERK 1/2 protein.<lb/> Results. VEGF inhibited bromodeoxyuridine incor-<lb/>poration into mitogen-induced VSMC in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner, reaching statistical significance at<lb/> concentrations of 30 (P &lt; 0.05), 40 (P &lt; 0.05), and 50<lb/> ng/mL (P &lt; 0.01). Densitometry of western immuno-<lb/>blots revealed an inhibition of phosphorylation of ret-<lb/>inoblastoma at VEGF concentrations of 40 and 50<lb/> ng/mL and ERK 1/2 phosphorylation at concentrations<lb/> of 30, 40 and 50 ng/mL.<lb/> Conclusion. In addition to stimulating re-<lb/>endothelialization, VEGF appears to have a vascular<lb/> protective function by directly inhibiting VSMC pro-<lb/>liferation. This effect occurs in the absence of endo-<lb/>thelial cells and via the mitogen-activated protein ki-<lb/>nase pathway. VEGF may serve as an important<lb/> modulator of mitogen-induced VSMC proliferation af-<lb/>ter vascular injury. © 2003 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/> Key Words: vascular endothelial growth factor; hu-<lb/>man aortic smooth muscle; neointimal hyperplasia.<lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION<lb/> The treatment of arterial occlusive disease, whether<lb/> it is in the coronary, peripheral, or cerebrovascular<lb/> circulation, has evolved considerably both with regard<lb/> to operative techniques as well as angioplasty and<lb/> stenting. Although these aggressive revascularization<lb/> techniques have resulted in better outcomes, the suc-<lb/>cess of these treatments is limited by a finite failure<lb/> rate because of restenosis resulting from neointimal<lb/> hyperplasia. The incidence of this conduit failure is<lb/> high, with restenosis rates of up to 32% after coronary<lb/> stenting at 6-month follow up [1] and 31% after carotid<lb/> endarterectomy at 7 years [2].<lb/> Neointimal hyperplasia results from injury to the<lb/> endothelial lining leading to the activation and uncon-<lb/>trolled proliferation of vascular smooth muscle cells<lb/> (VSMCs) within the medial layer of the blood vessel.<lb/> VSMCs then migrate from the medial layer to the<lb/> intimal layer, secrete and deposit matrix, and cause<lb/> intimal thickening. This results in luminal narrowing<lb/> </body>
			
			<front>1 Presented at the 36th Annual Meeting of the Association of<lb/> Academic Surgery, November 10, 2002, Boston, MA.<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>2 This work was supported in part by a Merit Review Award from<lb/> the Veterans&apos; Administration Research Service (MBA) and by fund-<lb/>ing from the Gonda Family Endowment. MBA received partial sup-<lb/>port from the Gonda Family Endowment.<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>3 To whom correspondence and reprint requests should be ad-<lb/> dressed at UCSD Section of Vascular Surgery, 200 West Arbor Drive,<lb/> San Diego, CA 92103-8403. E-mail: nangle@ucsd.edu.<lb/></front>

			<front>Journal of Surgical Research 114, 179 –186 (2003)<lb/> doi:10.1016/S0022-4804(03)00254-3<lb/></front>

			<page>179<lb/></page>

			<front>0022-4804/03 $35.00<lb/> © 2003 Elsevier Inc. All rights reserved.<lb/></front>

			<body>of the vessel and can eventually lead to thrombosis and<lb/> failure of the intervention or graft [3, 4].<lb/> Platelet-derived growth factor (PDGF) is produced<lb/> by endothelial cells [5], VSMCs [6], activated macro-<lb/>phages [7], and from platelets in thrombi [8] and is<lb/> thought to be important in lesion formation. Increased<lb/> expression of PDGF and PDGF receptors have been<lb/> shown in neointimal lesions after balloon catheter in-<lb/>jury [9, 10] and percutaneous transluminal coronary<lb/> angioplasty [11]. Furthermore, PDGF-BB infusion into<lb/> rats after carotid injury directly promoted neointimal<lb/> thickening [12]. PDGF binding to its receptor is known<lb/> to result in an increase of the active, GTP-bound form<lb/> of Ras [13]. This in turn activates the signaling in the<lb/> Raf/MAP kinase-ERK kinase (MEK)/extracellular<lb/> signal-regulated (ERK) kinase pathway (also known as<lb/> the mitogen-activated protein kinase [MAPK] cascade)<lb/> [14], which stimulates cyclin D1 gene transcription and<lb/> leads to phosphorylation of the retinoblastoma (Rb)<lb/> tumor suppressor protein. This phosphorylation inac-<lb/>tivates the capability of Rb to interact with the E2F<lb/> transcription factors, causing them to accumulate and<lb/> activate the transcription of a large number of genes<lb/> essential for DNA synthesis and cell cycle progression<lb/> from G1 to S phase [15]. Therefore, it is believed that<lb/> PDGF has an essential role in the tissue response to<lb/> injury by activating the MAPK cascade in VSMCs,<lb/> thereby causing cellular proliferation, migration, and<lb/> differentiation and thus the formation of a neointimal<lb/> lesion.<lb/> Vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) is a 46-<lb/>kDa dimeric peptide [16] that is essential for angiogen-<lb/>esis (sprouting of capillaries from preexisting vessels)<lb/> and vasculogenesis (endothelial cell differentiation)<lb/> [17, 18]. The biological effects of VEGF are mainly<lb/> regulated by two tyrosine kinase receptors, Flt-1 [19]<lb/> and Flk-1/KDR [20], the latter being important in cell<lb/> proliferation, antiapoptosis, and cell survival in endo-<lb/>thelial cells [16, 21, 22]. The angiogenic effects of<lb/> VEGF have been used clinically to stimulate collateral<lb/> artery formation in regions of tissue with vascular<lb/> deficits such as occurs with ischemic heart disease and<lb/> peripheral vascular disease [23, 24]. More recently, it<lb/> has been hypothesized that VEGF has additional vas-<lb/>cular protective properties that may be useful in the<lb/> treatment of cardiovascular occlusive diseases [25].<lb/> Specifically, it has been shown in a number of studies<lb/> that VEGF gene or protein infusion increases<lb/> re-endothelialization and therefore, it has been hy-<lb/>pothesized that as a consequence of this re-<lb/>endothelialization, neointimal hyperplasia is inhibited<lb/> [26 –30].<lb/> Evidence suggests that VEGF receptors, Flt-1 and<lb/> Flk-1/KDR, are present not only on endothelial cells<lb/> but are present on a number of other cell types [31–33].<lb/> Moreover, two independent groups have detected func-<lb/>tional VEGF receptors on VSMC that can induced mi-<lb/>gration but not proliferation [34,35]. However, the ef-<lb/>fect of VEGF on mitogen-induced VSMC proliferation<lb/> is unknown.<lb/> In this study, we show that VEGF directly inhibits<lb/> PDGF-BB-induced proliferation of VSMC using a<lb/> bromo deoxy uridine (BrdU) proliferation assay. Fur-<lb/>thermore, we show by western blotting immunoassay<lb/> that VEGF inhibits PDGF-BB-mediated phosphoryla-<lb/>tion of Rb and ERK 1/2 protein.<lb/> MATERIALS AND METHODS<lb/> Reagents<lb/> Human recombinant VEGF and PDGF-BB were obtained from<lb/> PeproTech (Rocky Hill, NJ). Human aortic VSMCs, smooth muscle<lb/> basal media (SmBM), smooth muscle growth media (SmGM) contain-<lb/>ing 0.5 g/mL hEGF, 1 g/ml hFGF, 50 mg/mL gentamicin, 50<lb/> g/mL amphotericin-B, 5 mg/mL insulin, and 5% fetal bovine serum,<lb/> 0.025% tryspin/0.01% EDTA solution, trypsin neutralizing solution,<lb/> and HEPES-buffered saline solution were all-obtained from Clonet-<lb/>ics Biowhittaker (Walkersville, MD). The following monoclonal an-<lb/>tibodies were purchased: phosphorylated retinoblastoma (pRb)<lb/> (554136) from BD Biosciences Pharmingen (San Diego, CA),<lb/> -smooth muscle actin (A-2547) from Sigma (St. Louis, MO) and<lb/> ERK2 (E-4) and pERK 1/2 (D-2) from Santa Cruz Biotechnology<lb/> (Santa Cruz, CA). Supersignal Chemiluminescence kit and horserad-<lb/>ish peroxidase were purchased from Pierce (Rockford, IL). Protein<lb/> concentration assay solutions were purchased from Bio-Rad (Her-<lb/>cules, CA). Film was obtained from Eastman Kodak (Rochester, NY).<lb/> Nitrocellulose membrane was from Schleicher and Schuell (Keene,<lb/> NH). All other chemicals were purchased from Sigma (St. Louis,<lb/> MO), unless otherwise stated.<lb/> Cell Culture<lb/> VSMCs were grown in SmGM containing 5% fetal bovine serum at<lb/> 37°C in 5% CO 2 and 95% ambient air. SmGM containing 5% fetal<lb/> bovine serum was used for proliferating cells and SmBM, which is<lb/> devoid of growth factors or cytokines was used for the purpose of<lb/> serum starvation. Culture medium was changed every 3 days.<lb/> Trypsin/EDTA was used with HEPES-buffered saline solution and<lb/> trypsin neutralizing solution to passage the cells. Cells were used at<lb/> passage number 3– 6. Cells were allowed to proliferate until they<lb/> reached 60 –70% confluency, at which point the SmGM was aspirated<lb/> and the media changed to SmBM to allow cell cycle synchronization.<lb/> Cells were serum-starved overnight (18 h) using SmBm and treated<lb/> the following morning. Treatment consisted of 20 ng/mL PDGF-BB<lb/> with the addition of 0, 10, 20, 30, 40, or 50 ng/ml VEGF in a solution<lb/> of SmBM for a 24-h period.<lb/> BrdU Incorporation<lb/> Cells were seeded onto a 96-well plate at 3  10 5 cells/mL, serum-<lb/>starved, and treated with the solutions stated above. A BrdU cell<lb/> proliferation assay (QIA58; Oncogene Research Products, Boston,<lb/> MA) was used per manufacturer&apos;s instructions to detect BrdU incor-<lb/>poration into dividing cells. BrdU labeling was added to each well at<lb/> the time of treatment, therefore the cells were incubated with BrdU<lb/> label for a 24-h period to allow adequate cellular uptake before<lb/> analysis. A spectrometer was used for colorimetric detection of BrdU<lb/>

			<page>180<lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JOURNAL OF SURGICAL RESEARCH: VOL. 114, NO. 2, OCTOBER 2003<lb/></note>

			incorporation. In addition, in separate wells, for each treatment dose<lb/> and time point, cell viability was assessed using trypan blue exclu-<lb/>sion.<lb/> Western Blot Analysis<lb/> VSMC were plated at 2–3  10 5 cells/well in 100-mm 2 culture<lb/> dishes. After serum starvation and treatment with various solutions,<lb/> liquid N 2 was added. Two-hundred microliters of RIPA buffer (50<lb/> mM Tris-HCL, pH 7.4, 150 mM NaCl, 0.5% deoxycholate, and 1%<lb/> Nonidet P-40) containing aprotinin (1 g/mL), leupeptin (1 g/mL),<lb/> 10 mM sodium orthovanadate, 10 mM NaF, and 1 mM phenylmeth-<lb/>ylsulfonylfluoride was then added, and the cells were scraped off and<lb/> transferred into 1.5-mL microcentrifugation tubes. They were then<lb/> incubated on ice and vortexed for 20 s. After centrifugation at<lb/> 100,000 g at 4°C for 20 min, the supernatants were obtained. The<lb/> protein content of each cell lysate was measured using a standard<lb/> spectrophotometric protein concentration assay (Bio-Rad). Protein<lb/> samples were then diluted with RIPA buffer to equalize protein<lb/> concentrations in all samples (1 mg/mL). Protein lysates were then<lb/> boiled for 5 min in 6  Laemmli buffer and 30 g of protein was<lb/> loaded into each well and separated by 7.5% (pRb and -actin) or 12%<lb/> (ERK-2 and pERK) sodium dudecyl sulfate–polyacrylanide gel elec-<lb/>trophoresis. The gels were run at 80 V for approximately 2 h. Pro-<lb/>teins were electroblotted onto a nitrocellulose membrane at 40 V<lb/> overnight at 4°C, and the membrane blocked in 5% nonfat dry milk<lb/> in Tris-buffered saline containing 0.05% Tween 20 for 30 mins.<lb/> Membranes were blotted with various primary antibodies for 2 h<lb/> followed by the appropriate horseradish peroxidase-conjugated sec-<lb/>ondary antibody for 45 min. The membrane was then treated with<lb/> the chemiluminescence kit, wrapped in plastic, and visualized on<lb/> radiographic film. Densitometry was performed using standard Na-<lb/>tional Institute of Health software.<lb/> Statistical Analysis<lb/> Each experiment was repeated a minimum of three times. Statis-<lb/>tical analyses were performed by one-way analysis of variance with<lb/> comparison against control, with Bonferroni adjustments for multi-<lb/>ple comaparisons. Data are presented as mean  standard deviation.<lb/> A value of P  0.05 was considered to be statistically significant.<lb/> RESULTS<lb/> VEGF Inhibits Mitogen-Induced Proliferation of VSMCs<lb/> A BrdU proliferation assay was used to assess pro-<lb/>liferation in human aortic smooth muscle cells. VEGF<lb/> inhibited PPDGF-BB-induced VSMC proliferation in a<lb/> dose-dependent manner and significantly reduced pro-<lb/>liferation from 40  9% with PDGF-BB at a concentra-<lb/>tion of 20 ng/mL to 36  12, 29  13, 23  10, 9  6,<lb/> and 5  5% of baseline (serum-starved conditions) at a<lb/> VEGF concentration of 10, 20, 30, (P  0.05), 40 (P <lb/> 0.05), and 50 ng/mL (P  0.01), respectively (Fig. 1).<lb/> Results are reported as mean  SD.<lb/> Cell Viability<lb/> Cell viability, as assessed by trypan blue exclusion,<lb/> was 98% at each time point with and without VEGF.<lb/> There was no evidence of cell death or necrosis based<lb/> on trypan blue testing.<lb/> FIG. 1. VEGF inhibits PDGF-BB-mediated BrdU incorporation into VSMCs. After serum starvation (18 h), human aortic VSMCs were<lb/> incubated with PDGF-BB 20 ng/mL and the indicated concentrations of VEGF for 24 h. Shown is the mean percentage ( SD) of BrdU<lb/> incorporation (as a marker of proliferation) as a percentage of serum starved conditions in three independent experiments. Significance<lb/> determined using one-way analysis of variance with Bonferroni correction, *P  0.05, **P  0.01.<lb/>

			<page>181<lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DORAFSHAR ET AL.: VEGF INHIBITS VSMC PROLIFERATION<lb/></note>

			VEGF Inhibits Phosphorylation of Rb<lb/> Western immunoblotting for phosphorylation of Rb<lb/> was used to assess cell cycle progression from G1 to S<lb/> phase. Cell cycle progression is represented by an in-<lb/>crease in the amount of phosphorylated Rb protein.<lb/> VEGF inhibited PDGF-BB-induced Rb phosphoryla-<lb/>tion in a dose-dependent manner (Fig. 2A). -actin<lb/> western immunoblot densitometry was performed to<lb/> confirm equivalent protein loading in each lane. Den-<lb/>sitometry revealed significant inhibition of Rb phos-<lb/>phorylation from 1.9- 0.2%-fold increase above base-<lb/>line with PDGF-BB at a concentration of 20 ng/mL to<lb/> 1.5  0.19-, 1.3  0.16-, 1.1  0.02-, 1.0  0.08-, and 0.8<lb/>  0.05%-fold increase above baseline at a VEGF con-<lb/>centration of 10, 20, 30, 40 (P  0.05) and 50 ng/mL (P<lb/>  0.01), respectively (Fig. 2B). Results are reported as<lb/> mean  SD.<lb/> VEGF Inhibits Phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 Protein<lb/> ERK 1/2 phosphorylation was used to determine<lb/> whether VEGF inhibits cell signaling by PDGF-BB<lb/> through the MAPK pathway. Cell signaling as result of<lb/> PDGF-BB-induced stimulation resulted in an increase<lb/> of phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 protein. VEGF inhibited<lb/> PDGF-BB-induced ERK 1/2 phosphorylation in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner (Fig. 3A). ERK 2 western immuno-<lb/>blot densitometry did not demonstrate a significant<lb/> difference in loading between each lane. Densitometry<lb/> revealed significant inhibition of ERK 1/2 phosphory-<lb/>lation from 1.5- 0.17-fold increase above baseline<lb/> with PDGF-BB at a concentration of 20 ng/mL to 1.3 <lb/> 0.31-, 1.2  0.17-, 1.2  0.12-, 1.0  0.12-, and 0.93 <lb/> 0.06-fold increase above baseline at VEGF concentra-<lb/>tions of 10, 20, 30 (P  0.05), 40 (P  0.05), and 50<lb/> FIG. 2. VEGF inhibits PDGF-mediated phosphorylation of Rb protein. After serum starvation (18 h), human VSMCs were incubated with<lb/> PDGF-BB 20 ng/mL and the indicated concentrations of VEGF for 24 h. A, Representative western immunoblots showing a dose-dependent<lb/> decrease in the phosphorylation of Rb and equal total -actin as a marker of protein loading. The  lane indicates the positive control, i.e.,<lb/> incubated with 5% fetal bovine serum. The  lane indicates the negative control, i.e., serum-starved with no VEGF and no PDGF. The<lb/> remaining lanes all contain 20 ng/mL of PDGF and increasing doses of VEGF from 0 ng/mL to 50 ng/mL. B, Densitometry of phosphorylation<lb/> of Rb protein. Shown are the mean densitometry values ( SD) derived from three independent experiments compared to serum starved<lb/> conditions. Significance was determined using one-way analysis of variance with Bonferroni correction, *P  0.05, **P  0.01.<lb/>

			<page>182<lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JOURNAL OF SURGICAL RESEARCH: VOL. 114, NO. 2, OCTOBER 2003<lb/></note>

			ng/mL (P  0.01; Fig. 3B). Results are reported as<lb/> mean  SD.<lb/> CONCLUSION<lb/> Previous studies have determined that VEGF has<lb/> vascular protective effects as well as a role in thera-<lb/>peutic angiogenesis. In a rat carotid balloon injury<lb/> model, delivery of intravenous VEGF protein or VEGF<lb/> gene transfer was shown to accelerate re-<lb/>endothelialization and attenuate neointimal hyperpla-<lb/>sia [26, 27]. Further experiments studying stent im-<lb/>plantation in rabbit iliac arteries have shown that<lb/> intravenous VEGF protein or gene transfer accelerated<lb/> re-endothelialization, decreased neointima formation,<lb/> and reduced mural thrombosis [28, 29]. There is also<lb/> evidence of reduction in rabbit vein graft intimal hy-<lb/>perplasia following topical VEGF administration [36].<lb/> However, this issue has been the subject of consider-<lb/>able debate, since, for instance, it has been reported<lb/> that intravenous VEGF protein infusion in dogs after<lb/> iliofemoral balloon denudation actually resulted in in-<lb/>creased neointimal hyperplasia and had no effect on<lb/> maximal collateral blood flow [37]. Additionally, an-<lb/>FIG. 3. VEGF inhibits PDGF-BB–mediated phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 protein. After serum starvation (18 h) human aortic smooth<lb/> muscle cells were incubated with PDGF-BB 20 ng/mL and the indicated concentrations of VEGF for 24 h. A, Representative western<lb/> immunoblots showing a dose-dependent decrease in the phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 protein and equal total ERK 2 protein. () indicates the<lb/> positive control, i.e., incubated with SmGM and () indicates the negative control, i.e., incubated with SmBM. B, Densitometry of<lb/> phosphorylation of ERK 1/2 protein. Shown is the mean densitometry values ( SD) derived from three independent experiments compared<lb/> to serum starved conditions. Significance was determined using one-way analysis of variance with Bonferroni correction *P  0.05, **P <lb/> 0.01.<lb/>

			<page>183<lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">DORAFSHAR ET AL.: VEGF INHIBITS VSMC PROLIFERATION<lb/></note>

			other group of investigators found that administration<lb/> of VEGF by various techniques did not increase endo-<lb/>thelial cell regrowth post denudation of either the<lb/> aorta or the carotid arteries of rats and mice, but only<lb/> increased vascular permeability [38].<lb/> Despite the above controversy, a significant body of<lb/> evidence points to VEGF being able to promote re-<lb/>endothelialization and reduce neointimal hyperplasia<lb/> after balloon-induced catheter injury, stent implanta-<lb/>tion and after vein grafting. Asahari et al. have hypoth-<lb/>esized that the mechanism by which VEGF inhibits<lb/> neointimal hyperplasia is principally through its pro-<lb/>liferating action on endothelial cells leading to the<lb/> re-endothelialization of denuded arteries, and that this<lb/> re-endothelialization secondarily inhibits neointimal<lb/> hyperplasia [26]. However, in an experiment per-<lb/>formed using an extravascular silastic collar to induce<lb/> VSMC proliferation (without endothelial cell denuda-<lb/>tion) in rabbit carotid arteries, it was discovered that<lb/> soaking the collar with VEGF gene, and using the cuff<lb/> as a gene delivery reservoir significantly inhibited neo-<lb/>intimal VSMC hyperplasia [39]. This implies that<lb/> VEGF may have vascular protective effects indepen-<lb/>dent of its mitogenic action on endothelial cells.<lb/> Interestingly, Taniguchi et al. demonstrated that, in<lb/> a cell culture model using human uterine myometrial<lb/> cells, addition of VEGF-neutralizing antibody to<lb/> PDGF-BB stimulated cells resulted in a linear increase<lb/> in proliferation beyond plateau maximal concentra-<lb/>tions of PDGF-BB [40]. They hypothesized that VEGF<lb/> may negatively regulate the myometrial cell prolifera-<lb/>tion induced by PDGF-BB. In that particular study, the<lb/> investigators did not perform any further experiments<lb/> to elucidate the mechanism by which VEGF might be<lb/> suppressing PDGF-BB induced proliferation. Addition-<lb/>ally, Hu et al. reported that VEGF-2, which differs<lb/> from VEGF protein by one amino acid residue within<lb/> the signal peptide portion, inhibits PDGF-BB induced<lb/> human aortic cell proliferation. The authors also hy-<lb/>pothesized that VEGF-2 may have a regulatory action<lb/> on the vasculature [41].<lb/> Our experiments clearly demonstrate that VEGF<lb/> has a direct effect on mitogen-induced proliferation of<lb/> VSMC. PDGF was used as a known VSMC mitogen<lb/> because it has been shown in previous studies to play<lb/> an important role in the pathogenesis of the neointimal<lb/> lesion [9 –12]. Using the BrdU proliferation assay, we<lb/> have shown that when PDGF induces the proliferation<lb/> of VSMC, VEGF inhibits DNA synthesis in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner. Furthermore, western immuno-<lb/>assay reveals that the inhibition of proliferation is<lb/> paralleled by a dose-dependent decrease in Rb phos-<lb/>phorylation. This implies that the VSMCs are unable<lb/> to pass from the G1 to the S phase of the cell cycle and<lb/> thus were in cell cycle arrest. In addition, ERK phos-<lb/>phorylation was also inhibited in a dose-dependent<lb/> manner suggesting that VEGF has effects upstream<lb/> from ERK phosphorylation in the MAPK cascade. Fur-<lb/>ther studies are necessary to determine the exact point<lb/> of action of VEGF in the MAPK pathway, and whether<lb/> it acts through its own Flt-1 or Flk-1/KDR receptor or<lb/> whether it acts as a PDGF antagonist at the receptor<lb/> level. The latter may be a more likely mechanism be-<lb/>cause VEGF has a similar 3-D structure to PDGF-BB<lb/> and also has a related amino acid sequence [42]. Addi-<lb/>tional investigations are required to determine<lb/> whether VEGF induces apoptosis in VSMC. Apoptosis,<lb/> however, is unlikely to be the explanation for the de-<lb/>creased proliferation of VSMC to PDGF-BB in the pres-<lb/>ence of VEGF because there was no evidence of nonvi-<lb/>able or dead cells at any of the time points or treatment<lb/> arms, as evidenced by the trypan blue exclusion test.<lb/> However, this particular piece of data is a gross, but<lb/> inadequate test to rule cell death as a cause of the<lb/> observed phenomenon and will have to be confirmed by<lb/> detailed investigation into morphologic features of and<lb/> other markers of apoptosis.<lb/> In summary, we have demonstrated that VEGF may<lb/> have direct inhibitory effects on VSMC proliferation<lb/> and that this occurs in the absence of endothelial cells.<lb/> This occurs upstream of ERK in the MAPK pathway.<lb/> In addition to re-endothelialization, we believe that<lb/> this is another important vascular protective mecha-<lb/>nism of VEGF in modulating mitogen-induced VSMC<lb/> proliferation following vascular injury and in attenu-<lb/>ating the development of neointimal hyperplasia.<lb/> Moreover, VEGF may act as a negative feedback reg-<lb/>ulator of mitogen-induced VSMC proliferation. Fur-<lb/>ther investigation is necessary to better understand<lb/> the exact mechanism of action, so that, perhaps, new<lb/> insight may be gained into the interaction between<lb/> PDGF and VEGF and the role that each may play in a<lb/> regulatory response to arterial injury.<lb/> </body>
			
		<back>	

			<listBibl>REFERENCES<lb/>1. Fischman, D. L., Leon, M. B., Baim, D. S., Schatz, R. A., Savage,<lb/> M. P., Penn, I., Detre, K., Veltri, L., Ricci, D., Nobuyoshi, M.,<lb/> Cleman, M., Heuser, R., Almond, D., Teirstein, P. S., Fish,<lb/> R. D., Colombo, A., Brinker, J., Moses, J., Shaknovich, A.,<lb/> Hirshfeld, J., Bailey, S., Ellis, S., Rake, R., and Goldberg, S. for<lb/> the STRESS Investigators. A randomized comparison of<lb/> coronary-stent placement and balloon angioplasty in the treat-<lb/>ment of coronary artery disease. N. Engl. J. Med. 331: 496,<lb/> 1994.<lb/> 2. Healy, D. A., Zierler, R. E., and Nicholls, S. C. Long-term<lb/> follow-up and clinical outcome of carotid restenosis. J. Vasc.<lb/> Surg. 10: 662, 1989 discussion 668.<lb/> 3. Clowes, A. W., Reidy, M. A., and Clowes, M. M. Kinetics of<lb/> cellular proliferation after arterial injury. I. Smooth muscle<lb/> growth in the absence of endothelium. Lab. Invest. 49: 327,<lb/> 1983.<lb/> 4. Clowes, A. W., Reidy, M. A., and Clowes, M. M. Mechanisms of<lb/> stenosis after arterial injury. Lab. Invest. 49: 208, 1983.<lb/> 5. Dicorleto, P. E., and Bowen-Pope, D. F. Cultured endothelial<lb/> 
			
			<page>184<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="headnote">JOURNAL OF SURGICAL RESEARCH: VOL. 114, NO. 2, OCTOBER 2003<lb/> </note>
			
			cells produce a platelet-derived growth factor-like protein. Proc.<lb/> Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 80: 1919, 1983.<lb/> 6. Nilsson, J., Sjölund, M., Palmberg, L., Thyberg, J., and Heldin,<lb/> C. H. Arterial smooth muscle cells in primary culture produce a<lb/> platelet-derived growth factor-like protein. Proc. Natl. Acad.<lb/> Sci. USA 82: 4418, 1985.<lb/> 7. Shimokado, K., Raines, E. W., Madtes, D. K., Barrett, T. B.,<lb/> Benditt, E. P., and Ross, R. A significant part of macrophage-<lb/>derived growth factor consists of at least two forms of PDGF.<lb/> Cell 43: 277, 1985.<lb/> 8. Kaplan, D. R., Chao, F. C., Stiles, C. D., Antoniades, H. N., and<lb/> Scher, C. D. Platelet -granules contain a growth factor for<lb/> fibroblasts. Blood 53: 1043, 1979.<lb/> 9. Uchida, K., Sasahara, M., Morigami, N., Hazama, F., and Ki-<lb/>noshita, M. Expression of platelet-derived growth factor<lb/> B-chain in neointimal smooth muscle cells of balloon injured<lb/> rabbit femoral arteries. Atherosclerosis 124: 9, 1996.<lb/> 10. Majesky, M. W., Reidy, M. A., Bowen-Pope, D. F., Hart, C. E.,<lb/> Wilcox, J. N., and Schwartz, S. M. PDGF ligand and receptor<lb/> gene expression during repair of arterial injury. J. Cell Biol.<lb/> 111: 2149, 1990.<lb/> 11. Ueda, M., Becker, A. E., Kasayuki, N., Kojima, A., Morita, Y.,<lb/> and Tanaka, S. In situ detection of platelet-derived growth<lb/> factor-A and -B chain mRNA in human coronary arteries after<lb/> percutaneous transluminal coronary angioplasty. Am. J.<lb/> Pathol. 149: 831, 1996.<lb/> 12. Jawien, A., Bowen-Pope, D. F., Lindner, V., Schwartz, S. M.,<lb/> and Clowes, A. W. Platelet-derived growth factor promotes<lb/> smooth muscle migration and intimal thickening in a rat model<lb/> of balloon angioplasty. J. Clin. Invest. 89: 507, 1992.<lb/> 13. Schlessinger, J. How receptor tyrosine kinases activate Ras.<lb/> Trends Biochem. Sci. 18: 273, 1993.<lb/> 14. Seger, R., and Krebs, E. G. The MAPK signaling cascade.<lb/> FASEB J. 9: 726, 1995.<lb/> 15. Nevins, J. R. Toward an understanding of the functional com-<lb/>plexity of the E2F and retinoblastoma families. Cell Growth<lb/> Differ. 9: 585, 1998.<lb/> 16. Ferrara, N., and Henzel, W. J. Pituitary follicular cells secrete<lb/> a novel heparin-binding growth factor specific for vascular en-<lb/>dothelial cells. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 161: 851,<lb/> 1989.<lb/> 17. Ferrara, N. Vascular endothelial growth factor. Eur. J. Cancer<lb/> 32A: 2413, 1996.<lb/> 18. Risau, W. Mechanisms of angiogenesis. Nature 386: 671, 1997.<lb/> 19. de Vries, C., Escobedo, J. A., Ueno, H., Houck, K., Ferrara, N.,<lb/> and Williams, L. T. The fms-like tyrosine kinase, a receptor for<lb/> vascular endothelial growth factor. Science. 255: 989, 1992.<lb/> 20. Millauer, B., Wizigmann-Voos, S., Schnurch, H., Martinez, R.,<lb/> Moller, N. P. H., Risau, W., and Ulrich, A. High affinity VEGF<lb/> binding and developmental expression suggest Flk-1 as a major<lb/> regulator of vasculogenesis and angiogenesis. Cell 72: 835,<lb/> 1993.<lb/> 21. Gerber, H. P., Dixit, V., and Ferrara, N. Vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor induces expression of the antiapoptotic proteins<lb/> Bcl-2 and A1 in vascular endothelial cells. J. Biol. Chem. 273:<lb/> 13313, 1998.<lb/> 22. Gerber, H. P., McMurtrey, A., Kowalski, J., Yan, M., Keyt,<lb/> B. A., Dixit, V., and Ferrara, N. Vascular endothelial growth<lb/> factor regulates endothelial cell survival through the phospha-<lb/>tidylinositol 3-kinase/Akt signal transduction pathway.<lb/> J. Biol. Chem. 273: 30336, 1998.<lb/> 23. Hockel, M., Schlenger, K., Doctrow, S., Kissel, T., and Vaupel,<lb/> P. Therapeutic angiogenesis. Arch. Surg. 128: 423, 1993.<lb/> 24. Isner, J. M., and Losordo, D. W. Therapeutic angiogenesis for<lb/> heart failure. Nat. Med. 5: 491, 1999.<lb/> 25. Zachary, I. Signaling mechanisms mediating vascular protec-<lb/>tive actions of vascular endothelial growth factor. Am. J.<lb/> Physiol. Cell. Physiol. 280: C1375, 2001.<lb/> 26. Asahara, T., Bauters, C., Pastore, C., Kearney, M., Rossow, S.,<lb/> Bunting, S., Ferrara, N., Symes, J., and Isner, J. M. Local<lb/> delivery of vascular endothelial growth factor accelerates reen-<lb/>dothelialization and attenuates intimal hyperplasia in balloon-<lb/>injured rat carotid artery. Circulation 91: 2793, 1995.<lb/> 27. Asahara, T., Chen, D., Tsurumi, Y., Kearney, M., Rossow, S.,<lb/> Passeri, J., Symes, J. F., and Isner, J. M. Accelerated resti-<lb/>tution of endothelial integrity and endothelial dependent<lb/> function after phVEGF165 gene transfer. Circulation 94:<lb/> 3291, 1996.<lb/> 28. Van Belle, E., Tio, F. O., Couffinhal, T., Maillard, L., Passeri, J.,<lb/> and Isner, J. M. Stent endothelialization: time course, impact of<lb/> local catheter delivery, feasibility of recombinant protein ad-<lb/>ministration, and response to cytokine expedition. Circulation<lb/> 95: 438, 1997.<lb/> 29. Van Belle, E., Tio, F. O., Chen, D., Maillard, L., Kearney, M.,<lb/> and Isner, J. M. Passivation of metallic stents after arterial<lb/> gene transfer of phVEGF165 inhibits thrombus formation and<lb/> intimal thickening. J. Am. Coll. Cardiol. 29: 1371, 1997.<lb/> 30. Luo, Z., Asahara, T., Tsurumi, Y., Isner, J. M., and Symes, J. F.<lb/> Reduction of vein graft intimal hyperplasia and preservation of<lb/> endothelium-dependent relaxation by topical vascular endothe-<lb/>lial growth factor. J. Vasc. Surg. 27: 167, 1998.<lb/> 31. Guerrin, M., Moukadiri, H., Chollet, P., Moro, F., Dutt, K.,<lb/> Malecaze, F., and Plouet, J. Vasculotropin/vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor is an autocrine growth factor for human retinal<lb/> pigment epithelial cells cultured in vitro. J. Cell. Physiol. 164:<lb/> 385, 1995.<lb/> 32. Oberg-Welsh, C., Sandler, S., Andersson, A., and Welsh, M.<lb/> Effects of vascular endothelial growth factor on pancreatic duct<lb/> cell replication and the insulin production of fetal islet-like cell<lb/> clusters in vitro. Mol. Cell. Endocrinol. 126: 125, 1997.<lb/> 33. Sondell, M., Lundborg, G., and Kanje, M. Vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor has neurotrophic activity and stimulates axonal<lb/> outgrowth, enhancing cell survival and Schwann cell prolifera-<lb/>tion in the peripheral nervous system. J. Neurosci. 19: 5731,<lb/> 1999.<lb/> 34. Ishida, A., Murray, J., Saito, Y., Kanthou, C., Benzakour, O.,<lb/> Shibuya, M., and Wijelath, E. S. Expression of vascular endo-<lb/>thelial growth factor receptors in smooth muscle cells. J. Cell.<lb/> Physiol. 188: 359, 2001.<lb/> 35. Grosskreutz, C., Anand-Apte, B., Duplá a, C., Quinn, T., Ter-<lb/>man, B. I., Zetter, B., and D&apos;Amore, P. A. Vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor-induced migration of vascular smooth muscle<lb/> cells in vitro. Microvasc. Res. 58: 128, 1999.<lb/> 36. Luo, Z., Asahara, T., Tsurumi, Y., Isner, J. M., and Symes, J. F.<lb/> Reduction of vein graft intimal hyperplasia and preservation of<lb/> endothelium-dependent relaxation by topical vascular endothe-<lb/>lial growth factor. J. Vasc. Surg. 27: 167, 1998.<lb/> 37. Lazarous, D. F., Shou, M., Scheinowitz, M., Hodge, E., Thiru-<lb/>murti, V., Kitsiou, A. N., Stiber, J. A., Lobo, A. D., Hunsberger,<lb/> S., Guetta, E., Epstein, S. E., and Unger, E. F. Comparative<lb/> effects of basic fibroblast growth factor and vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor on coronary collateral development and the arte-<lb/>rial response to injury. Circulation 99: 1726, 1999.<lb/> 38. Lindner, V., and Reidy, M. A. Expression of VEGF receptors in<lb/> arteries after endotheilial injury and lack of increased endothe-<lb/>lial regrowth in response to VEGF. Arterioscl. Throm. Vasc.<lb/> Biol. 16: 1399, 1996.<lb/> 39. Laitinen, M., Zachary, I., Breier, G., Paikkanen, T., Hä kki-<lb/>
			
			<page>185<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="headnote">DORAFSHAR ET AL.: VEGF INHIBITS VSMC PROLIFERATION<lb/> </note>
			
			nen, T., Luoma, J., Abedi, H., Risau, W., Soma, M., Laakso,<lb/> M., Martin, J. F., and Ylä -Herttuala, S. VEGF gene transfer<lb/> reduces intimal thickening via increased production of nitric<lb/> oxide in carotid arteries. Human Gene Ther. 8: 1737, 1997.<lb/> 40. Taniguchi, Y., Morita, I., Kubota, T., Murota, S., and Aso, T.<lb/> Human uterine myometrial smooth muscle cell proliferation<lb/> and vascular endothelial growth-factor production in re-<lb/>sponse to platelet-derived growth factor. J. Endocrinol. 169:<lb/> 79, 2001.<lb/> 41. Hu, J. S., Hastings, G. A., Cherry, S., Gentz, R., Ruben, S., and<lb/> Coleman, T. A. A novel regulatory function of proteolytically<lb/> cleaved VEGF-2 for vascular endothelial and smooth muscle<lb/> cells. FASEB. J. 11: 498, 1997.<lb/> 42. Muller, Y. A., Li, B., Christinger, H. W., Wells, J. A., Cunning-<lb/>ham, B. C., and De Vos, A. M. Vascular endothelial growth<lb/> factor: crystal structure and functional mapping of the kinase<lb/> domain receptor binding site. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 94:<lb/> 7192, 1997.<lb/> </listBibl>
			
			<page>186<lb/> </page>
			
			<note place="headnote">JOURNAL OF SURGICAL RESEARCH: VOL. 114, NO. 2, OCTOBER 2003</note>

		</back>
			
	</text>
</tei>
