<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>DOI: 10.1002/adsc.200700082 <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon a, * <lb/>a Department of Biotechnology, Delft University of Technology, Julianalaan 136, 2628 BL Delft, The Netherlands <lb/>Fax: (+ 31)-15-278-1415; e-mail: r.a.sheldon@tudelft.nl <lb/>Received: February 5, 2007 <lb/>Abstract: Immobilization is often the key to optimiz-<lb/>ing the operational performance of an enzyme in in-<lb/>dustrial processes, particularly for use in non-aque-<lb/>ous media. Different methods for the immobilization <lb/>of enzymes are critically reviewed. The methods are <lb/>divided into three main categories, viz. (i) binding to <lb/>a prefabricated support (carrier), (ii) entrapment in <lb/>organic or inorganic polymer matrices, and (iii) <lb/>cross-linking of enzyme molecules. Emphasis is <lb/>placed on relatively recent developments, such as the <lb/>use of novel supports, e.g., mesoporous silicas, hydro-<lb/>gels, and smart polymers, novel entrapment methods <lb/>and cross-linked enzyme aggregates (CLEAs). <lb/></front>

			<div type="toc">1 Introduction <lb/>2 Types of Immobilization <lb/>3 Immobilization on Supports: Carrier-Bound En-<lb/>zymes <lb/>3.1 Synthetic Organic Polymers <lb/>3.2 Biopolymers <lb/>3.3 Hydrogels <lb/>3.4 Inorganic Supports <lb/>3.5 Smart Polymers <lb/>4 Entrapment <lb/>5 Carrier-Free Immobilization by Cross-Linking <lb/>5.1 Cross-Linked Enzyme Crystals (CLECs) <lb/>5.2 Cross-Linked Enzyme AggregatesA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (CLEAs ) <lb/>6 Combi-CLEAs and Catalytic Cascade Processes <lb/>7 Enzyme-Immobilized Microchannel Reactors for <lb/>Process Intensification <lb/>8 Conclusions and Prospects <lb/></div>

			<front>Keywords: biotransformations; cross-linked enzyme <lb/>aggregates; entrapment; enzymes; immobilization; <lb/>support binding <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>In the drive towards green, sustainable methodologies <lb/>for chemicals manufacture [1] biocatalysis has much to <lb/>offer: [2] mild reaction conditions (physiological pH <lb/>and temperature), a biodegradable catalyst and envi-<lb/>ronmentally acceptable solvent (usually water), as <lb/>well as high activities and chemo-, regio-and stereo-<lb/>selectivities. Furthermore, the use of enzymes general-<lb/>ly obviates the need for functional group protection <lb/>and/or activation, affording synthetic routes which are <lb/>shorter, generate less waste and, hence, are both envi-<lb/>ronmentally and economically more attractive than <lb/>traditional organic syntheses. <lb/>Modern developments in biotechnology have paved <lb/>the way for the widespread application of biocatalysis <lb/>in industrial organic synthesis. [3-14] Thanks to recombi-<lb/>nant DNA techniques [15] it is, in principle, possible to <lb/>produce most enzymes for a commercially acceptable <lb/>price. Advances in protein engineering have made it <lb/>possible, using techniques such as site-directed muta-<lb/>genesis and in vitro evolution via gene shuffling, [16-19] <lb/>to manipulate enzymes such that they exhibit the de-<lb/>sired properties with regard to, inter alia, substrate <lb/>specificity, activity, selectivity, stability and pH opti-<lb/>mum. Nonetheless, industrial application is often <lb/>hampered by a lack of long-term operational stability <lb/>and difficult recovery and re-use of the enzyme. <lb/>These drawbacks can often be overcome by immobili-<lb/>zation of the enzyme. [20-25] <lb/>There are several reasons for using an enzyme in <lb/>an immobilized form. In addition to more convenient <lb/>handling of the enzyme, it provides for its facile sepa-<lb/>ration from the product, thereby minimizing or elimi-<lb/>nating protein contamination of the product. Immobi-<lb/>lization also facilitates the efficient recovery and re-<lb/>use of costly enzymes, in many applications a conditio <lb/>sine qua non for economic viability, and enables their <lb/>use in continuous, fixed-bed operation. A further ben-<lb/>efit is often enhanced stability, [26] under both storage <lb/>and operational conditions, e.g., towards denaturation <lb/>by heat or organic solvents or by autolysis. Improved <lb/>enzyme performance via enhanced stability and re-<lb/>peated re-use is reflected in higher catalyst productiv-<lb/>ities (kg product/kg enzyme) which, in turn, deter-<lb/>mine the enzyme costs per kg product. As a rule of <lb/>thumb the enzyme costs should not amount to more <lb/>than a few percent of the total production costs. In <lb/></body>

			<front>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>1289 <lb/>REVIEWS <lb/></front>

			<body>the production of 6-aminopenicillanic acid (6-APA) <lb/>by penicillin G amidase (penicillin amidohydrolase, <lb/>E.C. 3.5.1.11)-catalyzed hydrolysis of penicillin G, for <lb/>example, 600 kg of 6-APA are produced per kg of im-<lb/>mobilized enzyme and the production of the com-<lb/>modity, fructose, by glucose isomerase-catalyzed iso-<lb/>merization of glucose has a productivity of 11,000. [22] <lb/>Indeed, the development of an effective method for <lb/>its immobilization was crucial for the application of <lb/>penicillin amidase in the industrial synthesis of b-<lb/>lactam antibiotics. [27] <lb/>Immobilization is generally necessary for optimum <lb/>performance in non-aqueous media. In the traditional <lb/>method of using enzymes as lyophilized (freeze-dried) <lb/>powders, many of the enzyme molecules are not read-<lb/>ily accessible to substrate molecules. Furthermore, <lb/>lyophilization can cause pronounced structural pertur-<lb/>bations often leading to deactivation. In contrast, dis-<lb/>persion of the enzyme molecules by immobilization <lb/>generally provides for a better accessibility and/or an <lb/>extra stabilization of the enzymes towards denatura-<lb/>tion by the organic medium. <lb/>Another benefit of immobilization is that it enables <lb/>the use of enzymes in multienzyme and chemoenzy-<lb/>matic cascade processes (see later). [28-31] A major <lb/>problem encountered in the design of catalytic cas-<lb/>cade processes is the incompatibility of the different <lb/>catalysts and a possible solution is compartmentaliza-<lb/>tion (i.e., immobilization) of the different catalysts <lb/>thus circumventing their mutual interaction which <lb/>could result in inhibition and or deactivation. <lb/>In this review we shall focus on recent develop-<lb/>ments in novel immobilization techniques, such as the <lb/>use of novel supports, e.g., smart polymers, novel en-<lb/>trapment methods, and the recent development of <lb/>cross-linked enzyme aggregates (CLEAs), in the <lb/>quest for optimum performance in biotransforma-<lb/>tions. Another approach to facilitating the recovery <lb/>and re-use of enzymes is to perform the reactions, <lb/>with the free enzyme, in a membrane bioreactor con-<lb/>sisting of an ultrafiltration membrane which retains <lb/>the enzyme on the basis of its size but allows sub-<lb/>strates and products to pass through. This combines <lb/>ease of recovery and recycling with the high activity <lb/>of the free enzyme. The methodology is applied com-<lb/>mercially, for example, by Degussa in the commercial <lb/>synthesis of enantiomerically pure amino acids using <lb/>hydrolases or dehydrogenases. [32] However, since it in-<lb/>volves the free enzyme it falls outside the scope of <lb/>this review. <lb/>2 Types of Immobilization <lb/>Basically, three traditional methods of enzyme immo-<lb/>bilization can be distinguished, binding to a support <lb/>(carrier), entrapment (encapsulation) and cross-link-<lb/>ing. <lb/>(i) Support binding can be physical (such as hydro-<lb/>phobic and van der Waals interactions), ionic, or co-<lb/>valent in nature. However, physical bonding is gener-<lb/>ally too weak to keep the enzyme fixed to the carrier <lb/>under industrial conditions of high reactant and prod-<lb/>uct concentrations and high ionic strength. Ionic bind-<lb/>ing is generally stronger and covalent binding of the <lb/>enzyme to the support even more so, which has the <lb/>advantage that the enzyme cannot be leached from <lb/>the surface. However, this also has a disadvantage: if <lb/>the enzyme is irreversibly deactivated both the <lb/>enzyme and the (often costly) support are rendered <lb/>unusable. The support can be a synthetic resin, a bio-<lb/>polymer or an inorganic polymer such as (mesopo-<lb/>rous) silica or a zeolite. <lb/>(ii) Entrapment via inclusion of an enzyme in a po-<lb/>lymer network (gel lattice) such as an organic poly-<lb/>mer or a silica sol-gel, or a membrane device such as <lb/>a hollow fiber or a microcapsule. The physical re-<lb/>straints generally are too weak, however, to prevent <lb/>enzyme leakage entirely. Hence, additional covalent <lb/>attachment is often required. The difference between <lb/>entrapment and support binding is often not clear. <lb/>For the purpose of this review we define support <lb/>binding as the binding of an enzyme to a prefabricated <lb/>support (carrier) irrespective of whether the enzyme <lb/>is situated on the external or internal surface. Entrap-<lb/>ment requires the synthesis of the polymeric network <lb/>in the presence of the enzyme. For example, when an <lb/>enzyme is immobilized in a prefabricated mesoporous <lb/>Roger Sheldon (1942) <lb/>is Professor of Bioca-<lb/>talysis and Organic <lb/>Chemistry at Delft <lb/>University of Technol-<lb/>ogy (Netherlands). He <lb/>received a PhD in or-<lb/>ganic chemistry from <lb/>the University of Lei-<lb/>cester (UK) in 1967. <lb/>This was followed by <lb/>post-doctoral <lb/>studies <lb/>with Prof. Jay Kochi in <lb/>the USA. From 1969 to 1980 he was with Shell Re-<lb/>search in Amsterdam and from 1980 to 1990 he was <lb/>R&amp;D Director of DSM Andeno. His primary re-<lb/>search interests are in the application of catalytic <lb/>methodologies -homogeneous, heterogeneous and <lb/>enzymatic -in organic synthesis, particularly in rela-<lb/>tion to fine chemicals production. He developed the <lb/>concepts of E factors and atom utilization for assess-<lb/>ing the environmental impact of chemical processes. <lb/></body>

			<page>1290 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>silica the enzyme may be situated largely in the meso-<lb/>pores but this would not be entrapment. On the other <lb/>hand when the enzyme is present during the synthesis <lb/>of a silica sol-gel the enzyme is entrapped. <lb/>A C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (iii) Cross-linking of enzyme aggregates or crystals, <lb/>using a bifunctional reagent, to prepare carrierless <lb/>macroparticles. <lb/>The use of a carrier inevitably leads to dilution of <lb/>activity, owing to the introduction of a large portion <lb/>of non-catalytic ballast, ranging from 90 % to &gt; 99 %, <lb/>which results in lower space-time yields and produc-<lb/>tivities. [22] Moreover, immobilization of an enzyme on <lb/>a carrier often leads to the loss of more than 50 % <lb/>native activity, [33] especially at high enzyme load-<lb/>ings. [34] The design of carrier-bound immobilized en-<lb/>zymes also relies largely on laborious and time-con-<lb/>suming trial and error experiments, because of the <lb/>lack of guidelines that link the nature of a selected <lb/>carrier to the performance expected for a given appli-<lb/>cation. [35] Consequently, there is an increasing interest <lb/>in carrier-free immobilized enzymes, such as cross-<lb/>linked enzyme crystals (CLECs), [36] and cross-linked <lb/>enzyme aggregates (CLEAs). [37] This approach offers <lb/>clear advantages: highly concentrated enzyme activity <lb/>in the catalyst, high stability and low production costs <lb/>owing to the exclusion of an additional (expensive) <lb/>carrier. <lb/>It should be pointed out that, from the literally <lb/>thousands of papers on enzyme immobilization, it is <lb/>difficult to make comparisons of the different meth-<lb/>odologies as most authors compare the performance <lb/>of the immobilized enzyme, prepared using a particu-<lb/>lar technique, with that of the free enzyme but do not <lb/>compare different methods of immobilization. In ad-<lb/>dition, details of the immobilization of industrial bio-<lb/>catalysts are often not disclosed. <lb/>3 Immobilization on Supports: <lb/>Carrier-Bound Enzymes <lb/>The properties of supported enzyme preparations are <lb/>governed by the properties of both the enzyme and <lb/>the carrier material. The interaction between the two <lb/>provides an immobilized enzyme with specific chemi-<lb/>cal, biochemical, mechanical and kinetic properties. <lb/>The support (carrier) can be a synthetic organic poly-<lb/>mer, a biopolymer or an inorganic solid. <lb/>3.1 Synthetic Organic Polymers <lb/>Acrylic resins such as Eupergit C are widely used as <lb/>supports. Eupergit C is a macroporous copolymer of <lb/>N,N&apos;-methylene-bi-(methacrylamide), glycidyl meth-<lb/>acrylate, allyl glycidyl ether and methacrylamide with <lb/>average particle size of 170 mm and a pore diameter <lb/>of 25 nm. [38] It is highly hydrophilic and stable, both <lb/>chemically and mechanically, over a pH range from 0 <lb/>to 14, and does not swell or shrink even upon drastic <lb/>pH changes in this range. It binds proteins via reac-<lb/>tion of its oxirane moieties, at neutral or alkaline pH, <lb/>with the free amino groups of the enzyme to form co-<lb/>valent bonds which have long-term stability within a <lb/>pH range of pH 1 to 12 (see Figure 1). The remaining <lb/>epoxy groups can be rendered inactive by capping <lb/>using a variety of reagents (mercaptoethanol, ethanol-<lb/>amine, glycine, etc.) to prevent any undesired sup-<lb/>port-protein reaction. Due to the high density of oxir-<lb/>ane groups on the surface of the beads enzymes are <lb/>immobilized at various sites of their structure. This <lb/>&quot;multi-point-attachment&quot; is largely responsible for <lb/>the high operational stability of enzymes bound to <lb/>Eupergit C. <lb/>Immobilization by covalent attachment to Eupergit <lb/>C has been successfully applied to a variety of en-<lb/>zymes for industrial application. [27,38] Penicillin ami-<lb/>dase on Eupergit C, for example, maintained 60 % of <lb/>its initial activity over &gt; 800 cycles. [38] A major draw-<lb/>back of Eupergit C is diffusion limitations, the effects <lb/>of which, as would be expected, are more pronounced <lb/>in kinetically controlled processes. Sepa beads FP-EP <lb/>(Resindion, Milan, Italy) consist of a polymethacry-<lb/>late-based resin functionalized with oxirane groups <lb/>and exhibit characteristics similar to Eupergit C. [39] <lb/>Similarly, various porous acrylic resins, such as Am-<lb/>berlite XAD-7, are used to immobilize enzymes via <lb/>simple adsorption without covalent attachment. For <lb/>example, the widely used enzyme C. antarctica lipase <lb/>B (CaLB), [40] is commercially available in immobilized <lb/>form as Novozym 435 which consists of the enzyme <lb/>adsorbed on a macroporous acrylic resin. A disad-<lb/>vantage of immobilization in this way is that, because <lb/>Figure 1. Immobilization of enzymes on Eupergit C. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1291 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>it is not covalently bound, the enzyme can be leached <lb/>from the support in an aqueous medium. In a compar-<lb/>ison of the immobilization of lipases of Humicola la-<lb/>nuginosa, Candida antarctica and Rhizomucor miehei <lb/>on supports with varying hydrophobicity with Novo-<lb/>zym 435 (see below), in the esterification of oleic acid <lb/>with 1-butanol in isooctane, the highest activity was <lb/>observed with sepa beads (see above) containing octa-<lb/>decyl chains. [41] This was attributed to the hydropho-<lb/>bic nature of the support facilitating opening of the <lb/>hydrophobic lid of the lipase. <lb/>3.2 Biopolymers <lb/>A variety of biopolymers, mainly water-insoluble <lb/>polysaccharides such as cellulose, starch, agarose and <lb/>chitosan [42] and proteins such as gelatin and albumin <lb/>have been widely used as supports for immobilizing <lb/>enzymes. Indeed, the first industrial application of an <lb/>immobilized enzyme in a biotransformation is the <lb/>Tanabe process, [43] first commercialized more than 40 <lb/>years ago, for the production of l-amino acids by res-<lb/>olution of racemic acylamino acids using an aminoa-<lb/>cylase from Aspergillus oryzae (Figure 2). The <lb/>enzyme was immobilized by ionic adsorption on <lb/>DEAE-Sephadex which consists of cellulose modified <lb/>with diethylaminoethyl functionalities (Figure 2) and <lb/>the process was performed in continuous operation in <lb/>a fixed-bed reactor. <lb/>This method is still widely used, e.g., in the immo-<lb/>bilization of a recombinant epoxide hydrolase from <lb/>Aspergillus niger. [44] An activity retention of 70 % was <lb/>observed in the resolution of p-chlorostyrene oxide <lb/>under biphasic conditions. The immobilized biocata-<lb/>lyst was active at high substrate concentrations (306 g/ <lb/>L) and could be recycled 7 times but it exhibited a <lb/>slightly lower enantioselectivity compared to the free <lb/>enzyme (E = 76 vs. E = 90). <lb/>3.3 Hydrogels <lb/>In non-aqueous media enzymes can also be immobi-<lb/>lized in natural or synthetic hydrogels or cryogels. <lb/>Polyvinyl alcohol (PVA) cryogels formed by the <lb/>freeze-thawing method, [45] for example, have been <lb/>widely used for immobilization of whole cells. [46] A <lb/>mild and highly efficient method for preparing PVA <lb/>hydrogels by partial drying at room temperature af-<lb/>forded lens-shaped hydrogels (Lentikats) exhibiting <lb/>good mechanical stability, easy separation (diameter <lb/>3-5 mm and thickness 200-400 mm) and stability to-<lb/>wards degradation. [47] Lentikats have been successful-<lb/>ly used for the entrapment of whole cell biocata-<lb/>lysts, [48,49] for example, in the immobilization of whole <lb/>cells of Rhodococcus equi A4, which contains nitrile <lb/>hydratase and amidase activities. [49] However, free en-<lb/>zymes, owing to their smaller size, can diffuse out of <lb/>the gel matrix and are, consequently, leached in an <lb/>aqueous medium. In order to entrap free enzymes the <lb/>size of the enzyme must be increased, e.g., by cross-<lb/>linking (see later). In contrast, immobilization of free <lb/>enzymes in PVA hydrogels can be useful in organic <lb/>media, where the enzyme is not leached from the gel <lb/>matrix. For example, Ansorge-Schumacher and co-<lb/>workers reported the co-immobilization of an alcohol <lb/>dehydrogenase (EC 1.1.1.1) from Lactobacillus kefir <lb/>together with its co-factor, NADP, in PVA beads. [50] <lb/>The resulting immobilisate was used for the enantio-<lb/>selective reduction of a broad range of hydrophobic <lb/>prochiral ketones to the corresponding (R)-secondary <lb/>alcohols (Figure 3) in n-hexane as solvent. For exam-<lb/>ple, acetophenone afforded (R)-1-phenylethanol in <lb/>&gt; 98 % ee. Co-factor regeneration was achieved <lb/>within the gel matrix using isopropyl alcohol as the <lb/>co-substrate (total turnover number of the co-factor <lb/>10 2 -10 3 ). In addition to stability towards the organic <lb/>solvent, the immobilized biocatalyst showed improved <lb/>thermal stability and long-term stability under the re-<lb/>action conditions. <lb/>The same group reported the enantioselective ben-<lb/>zoin condensation of aromatic and heteroaromatic al-<lb/>dehydes, in n-hexane as solvent, using a recombinant <lb/>benzaldehyde lyase (BAL) from Pseudomonas fluo-<lb/>rescens immobilized in a PVA hydrogel. [51] As noted <lb/>above, in order to retain the enzyme in a PVA hydro-<lb/>Figure 2. Tanabe aminoacylase process. <lb/></body>

			<page>1292 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>gel, in the presence of water, the molecular weight <lb/>must be increased. Grçger and co-workers [52] achieved <lb/>this by cross-linking an (R)-oxynitrilase using a mix-<lb/>ture of glutaraldehyde and chitosan (Figure 4). The <lb/>cross-linked enzyme was subsequently entrapped in a <lb/>Lentikat PVA hydrogel. The resulting immobilized <lb/>biocatalyst had a well-defined particle size of 3-5 mm <lb/>and showed no leaching in the enantioselective hydro-<lb/>cyanation of benzaldehyde in a biphasic aqueous <lb/>buffer/organic solvent system. It could be recycled 20 <lb/>times without loss of yield or enantioselectivity. <lb/>An alternative method to increase the size of the <lb/>enzyme is to form a complex with a polyelectrolyte. <lb/>Owing to their ampholytic character, proteins exist as <lb/>polycations or polyanions, depending on the pH of <lb/>the medium. Hence, they can form complexes with <lb/>oppositely charged polyelectrolytes. This principle <lb/>was used by Dautzenberg and co-workers [53] to immo-<lb/>bilize amyloglucosidase (EC 3.2.1.3) by coupling to an <lb/>excess of a complex of sodium polystyrenesulfonate <lb/>(PSS) or poly-diallyldimethylammonium chloride <lb/>(PDM). The immobilized biocatalyst retained 45 % of <lb/>its activity and lost no activity over five cycles. <lb/>In an interesting recent development, directed evo-<lb/>lution of the formate dehydrogenase (EC 1.2.1.2) <lb/>from Candida boidinii, in two rounds of error-prone <lb/>PCR, was used to create variants that were more <lb/>suited for immobilization in a polyacrylamide gel. [54] <lb/>The best mutant had a 4.4-fold higher activity com-<lb/>pared to the free enzyme immobilized in the gel. The <lb/>stabilization resulted from a substitution of lysine, <lb/>glutamic acid and cysteine residues remote from the <lb/>active site. <lb/>Bruns and Tiller have reported [55] a novel immobili-<lb/>zation of enzymes in a prefabricated, nanophase sepa-<lb/>rated, amphiphilic network (see Figure 5), whereby <lb/>the enzyme is situated in its hydrophilic domains <lb/>which consist of poly(2-hydroxyethyl acrylate) <lb/>(PHEA). The substrate that diffuses into the hydro-<lb/>phobic polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) phase can <lb/>access the enzyme via the large interface, owing to its <lb/>nanophase separation and peculiar swelling proper-<lb/>ties. The amphiphilic network was synthesized by UV-<lb/>initiated radical copolymerization of a silylated 2-hy-<lb/>droxyethyl acrylate monomer and a bifunctional a,w-<lb/>methacroyloxypropyl-poly(dimethylsiloxane) (see Fig-<lb/>ure 5).The hydrophilic domain swells in the presence <lb/>of water and the polymer is loaded with the enzyme <lb/>by immersing it in an aqueous solution of the biocata-<lb/>lyst. Upon drying the phase shrinks, trapping the <lb/>enzyme in an enzyme-friendly environment. When <lb/>the polymer network is immersed in a non-polar or-<lb/>ganic solvent the hydrophobic PDMS domain swells <lb/>allowing access of a dissolved substrate which can ap-<lb/>proach the enzyme via the interface between the two <lb/>domains. Immobilization of horseradish peroxidase <lb/>(HRP; EC 1.11.1.7) and chloroperoxidase (CPO; EC <lb/>1.11.1.10) in this way afforded immobilisates showing <lb/>substantially enhanced activities and operational sta-<lb/>bilities in heptane, compared to the free enzymes (see <lb/>Figure 5). In contrast, no enhancement of activity was <lb/>observed in isopropyl alcohol as solvent, which was <lb/>Figure 3. Alcohol dehydrogenase in Lentikat. <lb/>Figure 4. Cross-linked (R)-oxynitrilase in Lentikat hydrogel. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1293 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>attributed to swelling of the PHEA phase rather than <lb/>the PDMS phase in this polar solvent. <lb/>3.4 Inorganic Supports <lb/>A variety of inorganic solids can be used for the im-<lb/>mobilization of enzymes, e.g., alumina, silica, [56] zeo-<lb/>lites [57,58] and mesoporous silicas [59-62] such as MCM-<lb/>41, and SBA-15. One of the simplest and most inex-<lb/>pensive methods to immobilize an enzyme is by silica <lb/>granulation. [40] It is used, for example, to formulate <lb/>enzymes for detergent powders which release the <lb/>enzyme into the washing liquid during washing. Gran-<lb/>ulation technology was used to immobilize CaLB <lb/>lipase on silica granules, by first adsorbing the lipase <lb/>on silica powder followed by agglomeration. [40] Owing <lb/>to the composition of the granulates, they are intend-<lb/>ed for use only in organic media. In an aqueous <lb/>medium the lipase is desorbed and the particle slowly <lb/>disintegrates. However, the CaLB silica granules can <lb/>be used in a direct ester synthesis if the water is re-<lb/>moved by, e.g., evaporation under vacuum. Applying <lb/>the granules in packed-bed reactors also minimizes <lb/>the contact time with high water concentrations. The <lb/>CaLB silica granules exhibited a similar activity to <lb/>Novozym 435 in the direct synthesis of the skin emol-<lb/>lient, isopropyl myristate. <lb/>In order to maintain its integrity in an aqueous en-<lb/>vironment the enzyme needs to be covalently bonded <lb/>to the silica support. For example, immobilization of <lb/>epoxide hydrolase from Aspergillus niger by covalent <lb/>attachment to functionalized silica resulted in 90 % <lb/>activity retention, which was retained over a period of <lb/>months, in the enantioselective (E = 85) hydrolysis of <lb/>p-nitrostryrene oxide. [56] Furthermore, an enhanced <lb/>stability towards 20 % DMSO as solvent was observed <lb/>and no leaching occurred in a filtration test. <lb/>Mesoporous silicas, which are nowadays often refer-<lb/>red to as nanosilicas, have several advantages as sup-<lb/>ports: they have uniform pore diameters (2-40 nm), <lb/>very high surface areas (300-1500 m 2 g À1 ) and volumes <lb/>(ca. 1 mL g À1 ), and are inert and stable at elevated <lb/>temperatures. Moreover, the surface can be easily <lb/>functionalized. Because of the large pore sizes of <lb/>these materials they can accommodate relatively <lb/>small enzymes in the pores. Whether the enzyme is <lb/>situated inside the pores or on the outer surface can <lb/>be determined by comparing immobilization on cal-<lb/>cined and non-calcined material (i.e., the latter still <lb/>contains the template). If these values are roughly the <lb/>same then most of the enzyme is on the outer surface. <lb/>On the other hand, when the calcined material ad-<lb/>sorbs much more enzyme this indicates that most of <lb/>the enzyme is situated in the pores. [59] <lb/>Covalent binding of a-chymotrypsin (EC 3.4.21.2) <lb/>to a mesoporous sol-gel glass, which had been modi-<lb/>fied by reaction of surface hydroxy groups with 3,3,3-<lb/>trimethoxypropanal, afforded an immobilized catalyst <lb/>with a half-life one thousand times that of the free <lb/>enzyme. [61] Immobilization of chloroperoxidase (CPO) <lb/>from Caldariomyces fumago on the same material re-<lb/>sulted in increased stability towards organic sol-<lb/>vents. [62] The immobilized preparation was used to-<lb/>gether with free glucose oxidase which generated hy-<lb/>drogen peroxide in situ,by aerobic oxidation of glu-<lb/>cose. [62] Similarly, immobilization of Mucor javanicus <lb/>lipase (EC 3.1.1.3) on functionalized silica nanoparti-<lb/>cles resulted in enhanced thermal stability and a high <lb/>retention of activity over a wider pH range <lb/>(Figure 6). [63] <lb/>In a variation on this theme, Wang and Caruso [64] <lb/>immobilized catalase (EC 1.11.1.6) on nanoporous <lb/>silica spheres, having a surface area of 630 m 2 g À1 and <lb/>mesopores with a pore size of up to 40 nm, and subse-<lb/>quently assembled a nano-composite shell coating <lb/>composed of three layers of poly-dimethyldiallylam-<lb/>monium chloride (PDM) and 21 nm silica nanoparti-<lb/>cles. The resulting immobilisate displayed an activity <lb/>Figure 5. Amphiphilic polymer network for enzyme immobilization. <lb/></body>

			<page>1294 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>75 times that of catalase immobilized on mesoporous <lb/>silica spheres. <lb/>A novel type of immobilization on inorganic sup-<lb/>ports comprises the so-called protein-coated micro-<lb/>crystals (PCMCs). [65,66] The stabilization of lyophilized <lb/>enzyme powders through the addition of lyoprotec-<lb/>tants [67] and inorganic salts [68] is well documented. <lb/>PCMCs are prepared by mixing an aqueous solution <lb/>of the enzyme with a concentrated solution of a salt <lb/>such as potassium sulfate (a sugar or an amino acid <lb/>can also be used). The resulting solution is added <lb/>dropwise with vigorous mixing to a water-miscible sol-<lb/>vent such as isopropyl alcohol, whereupon micron-<lb/>sized crystals, containing the enzyme on the surface, <lb/>are formed. A major advantage of the technique is <lb/>that the enzyme molecules are dehydrated by a mech-<lb/>anism that leaves the majority of the enzymes in an <lb/>active conformation and minimizes denaturation. The <lb/>PCMCs can be separated and stored or used as a sus-<lb/>pension in an organic solvent. Obviously in an aque-<lb/>ous medium they dissolve to liberate the free enzyme. <lb/>In a transesterification of N-acetyltyrosine ethyl ester <lb/>with isopropyl alcohol (Figure 7) PCMCs of subtilisin <lb/>Carlsberg (EC 3.4.21.62) exhibited an activity three <lb/>Figure 6. Immobilization of a lipase on silica nanoparticles. <lb/>Figure 7. Resolutions with protein coated micro crystals (PCMCs). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1295 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>orders of magnitude higher than that of the lyophi-<lb/>lized powder. [65] Similarly, PCMCs of lipases showed a <lb/>substantial rate enhancement in most cases, compared <lb/>to the corresponding lyophilized powders, in the ki-<lb/>netic resolution (Figure 7) of 1-phenylethanol by <lb/>transesterification. [65] A further elaboration of the <lb/>technique employs solid state buffers as the support <lb/>to be coated. [66] The technique was also successfully <lb/>applied to oxidoreductases -an alcohol dehydrogen-<lb/>ase, catalase, soybean peroxidase and horse radish <lb/>peroxidase -affording PCMCs with enhanced activi-<lb/>ties in organic media. [66] <lb/>3.5 Smart Polymers <lb/>A novel approach to immobilization of enzymes is via <lb/>covalent attachment to stimulus-responsive or smart <lb/>polymers which undergo dramatic conformational <lb/>changes in response to small changes in their environ-<lb/>ment, e.g., temperature, pH and ionic strength. [69-71] <lb/>The most studied example is the thermo-responsive <lb/>and biocompatible polymer, poly-N-isopropylacryla-<lb/>mide (polyNIPAM). Aqueous solutions of polyNI-<lb/>PAM exhibit a critical solution temperature (LCST) <lb/>around 32 8C, below which the polymer readily dis-<lb/>solves in water while, above the LCST it becomes in-<lb/>soluble owing to expulsion of water molecules from <lb/>the polymer network. Hence, the biotransformation <lb/>can be performed under conditions where the enzyme <lb/>is soluble, thereby minimizing diffusional limitations <lb/>and loss of activity owing to protein conformational <lb/>changes on the surface of a support. Subsequently, <lb/>raising the temperature above the LCST leads to pre-<lb/>cipitation of the immobilized enzyme, thus facilitating <lb/>its recovery and reuse. An additional advantage of <lb/>using such thermo-responsive immobilized enzymes is <lb/>that runaway conditions are avoided because when <lb/>the reaction temperature exceeds the LCST the cata-<lb/>lyst precipitates and the reaction shuts down. <lb/>Two methods are generally used to prepare the <lb/>enzyme-polyNIPAM conjugates: (i) introduction of <lb/>polymerizable vinyl groups into the enzyme followed <lb/>by copolymerization with NIPAM or (ii) reaction of <lb/>NH 2 groups on the surface of the enzyme with a co-<lb/>polymer of NIPAM containing reactive ester groups <lb/>or the homopolymer containing an N-succinimide <lb/>ester function as the end group (Figure 8). <lb/>For example, penicillin G amidase (PA) was immo-<lb/>bilized by condensation with a copolymer of NIPAM <lb/>containing active ester groups. [72] The resulting <lb/>enzyme-polymer conjugate exhibited hydrolytic activ-<lb/>ity close to that of the free enzyme and was roughly <lb/>as effective as the free PA in the synthesis of cepha-<lb/>Figure 8. Thermoresponsive polymers for enzyme immobilization. <lb/></body>

			<page>1296 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>lexin by reaction of d-phenylglycine amide with 7-<lb/>ADCA (Figure 9). <lb/>More recently, an alternative thermo-responsive po-<lb/>lymer has been described. [73] It consists of random co-<lb/>polymers derived from 2-(2-methoxyethoxy)ethyl <lb/>methacrylate and oligo(ethylene glycol) methacrylate <lb/>(OEGMA) (see Figure 8) and combines the positive <lb/>features of poly(ethylene glycol), non-toxicity and <lb/>anti-immunogenicity, with thermo-responsive proper-<lb/>ties similar to polyNIPAM. The LCST could be <lb/>varied between 26 and 90 8C depending on the rela-<lb/>tive amounts of OEGMA used. These properties <lb/>make this a potentially interesting support for biocat-<lb/>alysts. <lb/>4 Entrapment <lb/>Enzymes can be immobilized by entrapment in sol-gel <lb/>matrices formed by hydrolytic polymerization of <lb/>metal alkoxides. Immobilization in silica sol gels pre-<lb/>pared by hydrolytic polymerization of tetraethoxysi-<lb/>lane, in the presence of the enzyme, was pioneered by <lb/>Avnir and co-workers [74] and has been used for the <lb/>immobilization of a wide variety of enzymes. [75] It <lb/>should be pointed out that the morphologies of the <lb/>silica sol-gels depend on the method of drying. [76] <lb/>Drying by evaporation affords so-called xerogels in <lb/>which capillary stress causes a shrinkage of the nano <lb/>cages and pores. When alkylsiloxanes, RSi(OR) 3 are <lb/>used together with Si(OR) 4 the surface of the sol-gel <lb/>is more densely populated by the hydrophobic alkyl <lb/>groups and the capillary stresses which operate during <lb/>evaporation are largely attenuated, affording a so-<lb/>called ambigel in which there is no contraction of the <lb/>nano cages. Alternatively, drying with supercritical <lb/>carbon dioxide affords a so-called aerogel in which <lb/>the delicate pore structure is maintained. Silica aero-<lb/>gels have a phenomenal porosity; the Guinness Book <lb/>of Records refers to a silica aerogel with a density of <lb/>0.001 as the worlds lightest solid. [76] <lb/>Reetz and co-workers found that when lipases were <lb/>entrapped in sol-gels produced from SiA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OEt) 4 the re-<lb/>sulting immobilisates exhibited disappointingly low <lb/>activities in the esterification of lauric acid by 1-octa-<lb/>nol. [77] Reasoning that the microenvironment in the <lb/>sol-gel may be too hydrophilic they entrapped the <lb/>lipase in a sol-gel prepared from a mixture of Si-<lb/>A C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OMe) 4 and RSiA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OMe) 3 containing non-hydrolyzable <lb/>alkyl moieties, on the premise that the more hydro-<lb/>phobic matrix would facilitate interfacial activation of <lb/>the lipase. This proved to be the case; they observed <lb/>rate enhancements of 2-8-fold compared with the tra-<lb/>ditional lyophilized lipase powder. This method has <lb/>been widely used for the immobilization of en-<lb/>zymes. [78] An interesting elaboration involves the ad-<lb/>dition of porous supports such as Celite during the <lb/>sol-gel process to bind the lipase-containing gels. This <lb/>&quot;double immobilization&quot; afforded materials with <lb/>higher thermal stability and activity. [79] More recently, <lb/>Reetz and co-workers [80] have reported a further im-<lb/>provement of the methodology, involving the use of <lb/>higher alkyl groups in the RSiA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OMe) 3 precursor and/ <lb/>or the use of additives such as isopropyl alcohol, <lb/>crown ethers, surfactants and KCl, with or without <lb/>the addition of Celite. These second generation sol-<lb/>gel immobilisates contained high lipase loadings, and <lb/>were highly active, robust and recyclable. <lb/>Pierre and co-workers have reported seminal stud-<lb/>ies on the entrapment of enzymes in silica aero-<lb/>gels. [76,81,82] For example, entrapment of Burkholderia <lb/>cepacia lipase in a hydrophobic silica sol-gel resulted <lb/>in an increase of all the kinetic constants, e.g., V max by <lb/>a factor of 10, in the esterification of lauric acid with <lb/>1-octanol. [83] More recently, lipases from Burkholderia <lb/>cepacia and Candida antarctica were entrapped in <lb/>silica aerogels, prepared from mixtures of SiA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OMe) 4 <lb/>and MeSiA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (OMe) 3 and reinforced with silica quartz <lb/>fiber felt to improve their mechanical properties. [84] <lb/>The resulting biocatalysts showed activities similar to <lb/>that of Novozym 435 in the synthesis of biodiesel by <lb/>interesterification of sunflower seed oil with methyl <lb/>acetate in iso-octane. However, at high substrate con-<lb/>centrations, in the absence of solvent, they were less <lb/>effective than Novozym 435, presumably owing to dif-<lb/>fusion limitations. <lb/>Additives such as polyethylene glycol (PEG), poly-<lb/>vinyl alcohol and albumin, can have a stabilizing <lb/>effect on sol-gel entrapped enzymes. For example, <lb/>Zanin and co-workers [85] compared three different <lb/>methods -physical binding, covalent attachment and <lb/>gel entrapment, in the presence and absence of PEG <lb/>Figure 9. Cephalexin synthesis with pen G amidase/polyNIPAM conjugate. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/> 2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1297 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>1450 -for the immobilization of Candida rugosa <lb/>lipase. Their activities were determined in the hydrol-<lb/>ysis of olive oil. Immobilization yields varied from 3 <lb/>to 32 %, the most active biocatalyst resulting from the <lb/>encapsulation in the presence of PEG. <lb/>In an interesting variation on this theme, Naik and <lb/>co-workers [86] entrapped catalase and horseradish per-<lb/>oxidase (HRP) using a biosilification process. In <lb/>nature, diatoms are able to synthesize silica nanopar-<lb/>ticles by polymerization of silicic acid, catalyzed by <lb/>enzymes known as silicateins. A peptide subunit of <lb/>the silicatein from Cylindrotheca fusiformis has been <lb/>shown [87] to catalyze the formation of silica in vitro. <lb/>When this process was performed in the presence of <lb/>catalase or HRP this resulted in their entrapment. <lb/>Enzymes can also be entrapped in silicone elasto-<lb/>mers [88] and polydimethylsiloxane membranes. [89] Ko-<lb/>bayashi and co-workers [90] have recently described a <lb/>novel polymer-incarceration methodology for immo-<lb/>bilizing enzymes. The immobilization procedure is de-<lb/>picted in Figure 10. It involves dissolving polystyrene <lb/>containing hydrophilic tetraethylene glycol and glyci-<lb/>dol moieties as pendant groups in dichloromethane <lb/>and then adding a solution of CaLB. This is followed <lb/>by the addition of 1-hexane which causes coacerva-<lb/>tion to occur, affording a precipitate containing the <lb/>lipase in the polymer phase. After decantation of the <lb/>supernatant the polymeric matrix was cross-linked by <lb/>reaction of the pendant glycidol groups with a tria-<lb/>mine at 60 8C in hexane (see Figure 10) to afford a <lb/>polymer incarcerated lipase. The immobilisate was <lb/>used in the kinetic resolution of chiral secondary alco-<lb/>hols and could be reused 5 times without any loss of <lb/>activity. <lb/>5 Carrier-Free Immobilization by <lb/>Cross-Linking <lb/>In the early 1960s, studies of solid phase protein <lb/>chemistry led to the discovery that cross-linking of <lb/>dissolved enzymes via reaction of surface NH 2 groups <lb/>with a bifunctional chemical cross-linker, such as glu-<lb/>taraldehyde, afforded insoluble cross-linked enzymes <lb/>(CLEs) with retention of catalytic activity. [91] Howev-<lb/>er, this method of producing cross-linked enzymes <lb/>(CLEs) had several drawbacks, such as low activity <lb/>retention, poor reproducibility, low mechanical stabili-<lb/>ty, and difficulties in handling the gelatinous CLEs. <lb/>Mechanical stability and ease of handling could be <lb/>improved by cross-linking the enzyme in a gel matrix <lb/>or on a carrier but this led to the disadvantageous di-<lb/>lution of activity mentioned above. Consequently, in <lb/>the late 1960s, emphasis switched to carrier-bound en-<lb/>zymes, which became the most widely used industrial <lb/>methodology for enzyme immobilization for the next <lb/>three decades. <lb/>5.1 Cross-Linked Enzyme Crystals (CLECs) <lb/>The cross-linking of a crystalline enzyme by glutaral-<lb/>dehyde was first described by Quiocho and Richards <lb/>Figure 10. Polymer-incarcerated (PI) Candida antarctica lipase. <lb/></body>

			<page>1298 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>in 1964. [92] Their main objective was to stabilize <lb/>enzyme crystals for X-ray diffraction studies but they <lb/>also showed that catalytic activity was retained. The <lb/>use of cross-linked enzyme crystals (CLECs) as indus-<lb/>trial biocatalysts was pioneered by scientists at Vertex <lb/>Pharmaceuticals in the early 1990s [93] and subsequent-<lb/>ly commercialized by Altus Biologics. [36] The initial <lb/>studies were performed with CLECs of thermolysin <lb/>(EC 3.4.24.4), of interest in the manufacture of aspar-<lb/>tame, but the method was subsequently shown to be <lb/>applicable to a broad range of enzymes. [36] CLECs <lb/>proved significantly more stable to denaturation by <lb/>heat, organic solvents and proteolysis than the corre-<lb/>sponding soluble enzyme or lyophilized (freeze-dried) <lb/>powder. CLECs are robust, highly active immobilized <lb/>enzymes of controllable particle size, varying from 1 <lb/>to 100 mm. Their operational stability and ease of re-<lb/>cycling, coupled with their high catalyst and volumet-<lb/>ric productivities, renders them ideally suited for in-<lb/>dustrial biotransformations. In a more recent exam-<lb/>ple, a CLEC of chloroperoxidase (CPO) from Caldar-<lb/>iomyces fumago exhibited a higher thermal stability <lb/>and tolerance to organic solvents than the free <lb/>CPO. [94] <lb/>5.2 Cross-Linked Enzyme AggregatesA C H T U N G T R E N N U N G (CLEAs ) <lb/>An inherent disadvantage of CLECs is the need to <lb/>crystallize the enzyme, which is often a laborious pro-<lb/>cedure requiring enzyme of high purity. On the other <lb/>hand, it is well-known [95] that the addition of salts, or <lb/>water-miscible organic solvents or non-ionic polymers, <lb/>to aqueous solutions of proteins leads to their precipi-<lb/>tation as physical aggregates of protein molecules, <lb/>held together by non-covalent bonding without per-<lb/>turbation of their tertiary structure, that is without de-<lb/>naturation. It was reasoned that subsequent cross-<lb/>linking of these physical aggregates would render <lb/>them permanently insoluble while maintaining their <lb/>pre-organized superstructure, and, hence their catalyt-<lb/>ic activity. This indeed proved to be the case and led <lb/>to the development of a new family of immobilized <lb/>enzymes: cross-linked enzyme aggregates (CLEA ) <lb/>(Figure 11). Since precipitation from an aqueous <lb/>medium, by addition of ammonium sulfate or polyeth-<lb/>ylene glycol, is often used to purify enzymes, the <lb/>CLEA methodology essentially combines purification <lb/>and immobilization into a single unit operation that <lb/>does not require a highly pure enzyme. It could be <lb/>Figure 11. Preparation of a CLEA. <lb/>Figure 12. Ampicillin synthesis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/> 2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/> asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1299 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>used, for example, for the direct isolation of an <lb/>enzyme, in a purified and immobilized form suitable <lb/>for performing biotransformations, from a crude fer-<lb/>mentation broth. <lb/>The first examples of CLEAs were derived from <lb/>penicillin G amidase, an industrially important <lb/>enzyme used in the synthesis of semi-synthetic peni-<lb/>cillin and cephalosporin antibiotics (see earlier). The <lb/>free enzyme exhibits limited thermal stability and a <lb/>low tolerance to organic solvents, making it an ideal <lb/>candidate for stabilization by immobilization. Indeed, <lb/>penicillin G amidase CLEAs, prepared by precipita-<lb/>tion with, for example, ammonium sulfate or tert-<lb/>butyl alcohol, proved to be effective catalysts for the <lb/>synthesis of ampicillin (Figure 12). [96] <lb/>The CLEA exhibited a synthesis/hydrolysis ratio <lb/>(S/H) comparable with that of the commercial cata-<lb/>lyst, PGA-450 (penicillin G amidase immobilized on <lb/>polyacrylamide), and substantially higher than that of <lb/>the penicillin G amidase CLEC suggesting that diffu-<lb/>sional limitations are more severe in the CLEC. Re-<lb/>markably, the productivity of the CLEA was higher <lb/>even than that of the free enzyme that it was made <lb/>from and substantially higher than that of the CLEC. <lb/>In stark contrast, the commercial catalyst mainly con-<lb/>sists of non-catalytic ballast in the form of the poly-<lb/>acrylamide carrier which was reflected in its much <lb/>lower productivity. Analogous to the corresponding <lb/>CLECs, the penicillin G amidase CLEAs also main-<lb/>tained their high activity in organic solvents. [97,98] <lb/>CLEAs were subsequently prepared from seven <lb/>commercially available lipases (EC 3.1.1.3) and the <lb/>effects of various parameters, such as the precipitant <lb/>and the addition of additives such as surfactants and <lb/>crown ethers, on their activities were investigated. [99] <lb/>The activation of lipases by additives, such as surfac-<lb/>tants and crown ethers, is well-documented and is <lb/>generally attributed to the lipase being induced to <lb/>adopt a more active conformation. [100] Co-precipita-<lb/>tion of such additives with the enzyme followed by <lb/>cross-linking of the enzyme aggregates, can lock the <lb/>enzyme in this more favourable conformation. Fur-<lb/>thermore, since the additive is not covalently bonded <lb/>to the enzyme, it can subsequently be washed from <lb/>the CLEA using, for example, an appropriate organic <lb/>solvent to leave the immobilized enzyme locked in <lb/>the favourable confirmation. Using this procedure, a <lb/>variety of hyperactive lipase CLEAs exhibiting activi-<lb/>ties up to twelve times that of free enzyme were pre-<lb/>pared (Figure 13). [99] The experimental procedure was <lb/>further simplified by combining precipitation, in the <lb/>presence or absence of additives, with cross-linking <lb/>into a single operation. [99] <lb/>These results clearly demonstrate the tremendous <lb/>potential of the CLEAs as immobilized enzymes, with <lb/>high catalyst and volumetric productivities, prepared <lb/>in a simple procedure from relatively impure enzyme <lb/>preparations. Indeed, the simplicity of the operation <lb/>lends itself to automation, e.g., using 96-well <lb/>plates. [101] <lb/>Initial studies of CLEAs derived from the popular <lb/>Candida antarctica lipase B (CaLB) revealed that the <lb/>excellent performance observed in water, compared <lb/>to that of the standard immobilized form, Novozym <lb/>435 (CaLB immobilized on a macroporous acrylic <lb/>resin), could not be directly translated to organic <lb/>media. Consequently the preparation was modified to <lb/>produce a more lipophilic CLEA which could better <lb/>accommodate organic solvents. This afforded a dra-<lb/>matic improvement in the activity of CaLB CLEA in <lb/>the enantioselective acylation of 1-phenethylamine in <lb/>diisopropyl ether as solvent (Figure 14). [102] Clearly <lb/>the optimized CaLB CLEAs have activities surpass-<lb/>ing those of Nov 435 in both aqueous and organic <lb/>media. <lb/>Figure 13. Hyperactivation of lipase CLEAs. <lb/></body>

			<page>1300 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>CaLB CLEAs also exhibit excellent activities in su-<lb/>percritical carbon dioxide [103] and ionic liquids. [104] <lb/>Thus, CaLB CLEA displayed superior activity to that <lb/>of Novozym 435 in the kinetic resolution of 1-phenyl-<lb/>ethanol and 1-tetralol, by acylation with vinyl acetate, <lb/>in scCO 2 . The enzymatic resolution could also be <lb/>combined with the production of the 1-phenylethanol <lb/>substrate, by palladium-catalyzed hydrogenation of <lb/>acetophenone, using two separate columns in series <lb/>(one containing the Pd catalyst and the other the <lb/>CaLB CLEA), without the need for depressurization <lb/>(Figure 15). [103] <lb/>In the kinetic resolution of 1-phenylethanol and 1-<lb/>phenylethylamine in the ionic liquids, [bmim] [NO 3 ] <lb/>and [bmim] [N(CN) 2 ] the best results were observed <lb/>with CaLB adsorbed and cross-linked on a polypropy-<lb/>lene carrier (Accurel EP100). In contrast, the free <lb/>CaLB or immobilized as Novozym 435 dissolves in <lb/>these ionic liquids with complete loss of activity. <lb/>An important property of CLEAs from the point of <lb/>view of large-scale applications is their particle size <lb/>which obviously has a direct effect on mass transfer <lb/>limitations and filterability. The enzyme and glutaral-<lb/>dehyde concentrations are, inter alia, important fac-<lb/>tors in determining the particle size of CLEAs as was <lb/>reported for Candida rugosa lipase. [105] Optimum ac-<lb/>tivity was observed with particles of 40-50 nm. <lb/>Glutaraldehyde is generally the cross-linking agent <lb/>of choice as it is inexpensive and readily available in <lb/>commercial quantities. However, with some enzymes, <lb/>e.g., nitrilases, low or no retention of activity was <lb/>sometimes observed using glutaraldehyde as the <lb/>cross-linker. A possible cause of deactivation is reac-<lb/>tion of the cross-linker with amino acid residues <lb/>which are crucial for the activity of the enzyme. <lb/>Owing to its high reactivity and small size, which <lb/>allows it to penetrate the interior of the protein, this <lb/>will be particularly severe with glutaraldehyde. <lb/>Hence, this could be avoided by using bulky polyalde-<lb/>hydes, obtained by periodate oxidation of dextrans, as <lb/>the cross-linkers, [106] followed by reduction of the <lb/>Schiffs base moieties with sodium borohydride to <lb/>form irreversible amine linkages. The activity reten-<lb/>tion of these CLEAs was generally much higher than <lb/>that observed with CLEAs prepared using glutaralde-<lb/>hyde. Dramatic results were obtained, for example, <lb/>Figure 14. Comparison of Novozym 435 with CaLB-CLEAs. <lb/>Figure 15. Sequential hydrogenation and resolution in scCO 2 . <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1301 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/> Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>with a nitrilase (EC 3.5.5.13) from P. fluorescens and <lb/>with a nitrilase from the company Biocatalytics. <lb/>Cross-linking with glutaraldehyde produced a com-<lb/>pletely inactive CLEA while with dextran polyalde-<lb/>hyde 50-60 % activity retention (not optimized) was <lb/>observed (see Table 1). Similarly, better activity reten-<lb/>tions were observed when penicillin amidase CLEAs <lb/>were prepared with dextran polyaldehyde compared <lb/>to glutaraldehyde. [106] <lb/>Since cross-linking largely involves reaction of the <lb/>amino groups of lysine residues on the external sur-<lb/>face of the enzyme, every enzyme can be expected to <lb/>be, and is, different. For electronegative enzymes, that <lb/>contain a paucity of lysine residues on the surface, <lb/>cross-linking is expected to be less effective. One way <lb/>of compensating for this lack of surface amino groups <lb/>is to co-precipitate the enzyme with a polymer con-<lb/>taining numerous free amino groups, e.g., poly-l-<lb/>lysine [107] or polyethylene imine. [108,109] In a variation <lb/>on this theme, Gupta and co-workers [110] reported that <lb/>addition of bovine serum albumin (BSA) as a &quot;prote-<lb/>ic feeder&quot; in the preparation of CLEAs from solu-<lb/>tions containing low concentrations of enzymes facili-<lb/>tated the formation of the CLEA. <lb/>Other examples of hydrolases that have been suc-<lb/>cessfully cleated include pig liver esterase (EC <lb/>3.1.1.1), aminoacylase (EC 3.5.1.14), proteases, and <lb/>glycosidases (EC 3.2.1). [111] For example, the alkaline <lb/>protease from Bacillus licheniformis (alcalase, EC <lb/>3.4.21.62, also known as subtilisin Carlsberg), an inex-<lb/>pensive enzyme used in laundry detergents, has been <lb/>widely used in organic synthesis, e.g., in the resolution <lb/>of (amino acid) esters [112] and amines [113] and peptide <lb/>synthesis. [114] An alcalase CLEA showed excellent ac-<lb/>tivities and enantioselectivities in amino acid ester hy-<lb/>drolyses. [115] <lb/>Interestingly, a CLEA of aminoacylase prepared <lb/>from a crude extract from Aspergillus sp. fermenta-<lb/>tion lacked the esterase activity observed with the <lb/>crude enzyme. [116] This strongly suggests that the ester-<lb/>olytic activity is derived from a protein impurity in <lb/>the crude aminoacylase preparation and illustrates the <lb/>potential of the CLEA methodology for performing <lb/>purification and immobilization in a single operation. <lb/>Similarly, CLEAs were successfully prepared from <lb/>the glycosidase, b-galactosidase (EC 3.2.1.23) from <lb/>Aspergillus oryzae and phytase (EC 3.1.3.26) from As-<lb/>pergillus niger. [101] The former enzyme catalyzes the <lb/>hydrolysis of lactose in dairy products and is adminis-<lb/>tered as tolerase to people suffering from lactose in-<lb/>tolerance and the latter is an acid phosphatase which <lb/>is added to animal feed in order to hydrolyse phytate <lb/>(inositol hexaphosphate). <lb/>Recyclable CLEAs were also prepared [101] from a <lb/>variety of oxidoreductases, e.g., glucose oxidase <lb/>(EC1.1.3.4), galactose oxidase (EC 1.1.3.9) and lac-<lb/>case (EC 1.10.3.2). Laccase, in particular, has many <lb/>potential applications, e.g., for bleaching in the pulp <lb/>and paper or textile industries, aqueous effluent treat-<lb/>ment and, in combination with the stable radical <lb/>TEMPO (2,2,6,6-tetramethyl-1-piperidinoxyl), for the <lb/>catalytic aerobic oxidation of starch to carboxystarch <lb/>(Figure 16). The latter can be made by TEMPO cata-<lb/>lyzed hypochlorite oxidation of starch but greener, <lb/>aerobic oxidation is more attractive. Immobilization <lb/>as a CLEA improves the stability of the laccase under <lb/>the reaction conditions, thereby reducing the enzyme <lb/>cost contribution. <lb/>Another benefit of the CLEA technology is that it <lb/>can stabilize the quaternary structures of multimeric <lb/>enzymes, a structural feature often encountered with <lb/>redox metalloenzymes. For example, the stability of <lb/>CLEAs from two tetrameric catalases (EC 1.11.1.6) <lb/>which, for the soluble enzymes is dependent on con-<lb/>centration, became independent of this parameter in <lb/>the CLEA, which allowed for the use of low concen-<lb/>trations of catalase. [117] Similarly, CLEAs have been <lb/>prepared from an alcohol dehydrogenase (EC 1.1.1.1) <lb/>from Rhodococcus erythropolis and a formate dehy-<lb/>drogenase (EC 1.2.1.2) from Candida boidinii. [101] <lb/>Table 1. Effect of cross-linker on recovered activity of CLEA. [106] <lb/>Enzyme <lb/>Recovered activity [%] [a] <lb/>Glutaraldehyde <lb/>Dextran polyaldehyde <lb/>Nirilase (Ps. fluorescens) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 0 <lb/>Nitrilase (Biocatalytics 1004) <lb/>0 <lb/>60 <lb/>Penicillin G amidase <lb/>48 <lb/>85-90 <lb/>[a] Relative to the free enzyme. <lb/>Figure 16. Laccase-catalyzed aerobic oxidation of starch. <lb/></body>

			<page>1302 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<body>The methodology has also been successfully ap-<lb/>plied [102] to various C À C bond forming lyases, notably <lb/>the R-and S-specific oxynitrilases (hydroxynitrile <lb/>lyases, EC 4.1.2.10) which catalyze the hydrocyana-<lb/>tion of a wide range of aldehydes. For example, a <lb/>CLEA prepared from the (R)-specific oxynitrilase <lb/>from almonds, Prunus amygdalis (PaHnL) was highly <lb/>effective in the hydrocyanation of aldehydes under <lb/>microaqueous conditions and could be recycled ten <lb/>times without loss of activity. [118] CLEAs were similar-<lb/>ly prepared from the (S)-specific oxynitrilases from <lb/>Manihot esculenta and Hevea brasiliensis. [119,120] These <lb/>oxynitrilase CLEAs perform exceptionally well in or-<lb/>ganic solvents, affording higher enantioselectivities <lb/>than observed with the free enzymes owing to the es-<lb/>sentially complete suppression of competing non-en-<lb/>zymatic hydrocyanation. <lb/>A further elaboration of the CLEA methodology <lb/>involves the immobilization of lipase CLEAs by inclu-<lb/>sion in hydrophobic polytetrafluoroethylene mem-<lb/>branes for use in membrane bioreactors. [121] This <lb/>method has advantages compared with physical ad-<lb/>sorption or covalent binding. Similarly, inclusion of <lb/>glucose oxidase CLEAs in magnetic mesocellular <lb/>carbon foam was used to construct a magnetically <lb/>switchable bioelectrocatalytic system. [122] The prepara-<lb/>tion of CLEAs from CO 2 expanded micellar solutions <lb/>afforded dendritic CLEAs with tunable nanometer di-<lb/>mensions (7-38 nm). [123] <lb/>6 Combi-CLEAs and Catalytic Cascade <lb/>Processes <lb/>The ultimate in environmental and economic efficien-<lb/>cy is to combine atom-efficient, catalytic, steps into a <lb/>one-pot, catalytic cascade process without the need <lb/>for separation of intermediates. [28] Catalytic cascade <lb/>processes have numerous potential benefits: fewer <lb/>unit operations, less reactor volume, and higher volu-<lb/>metric and space-time yields, shorter cycle times and <lb/>less waste generation. Furthermore, by coupling steps <lb/>together unfavourable equilibria can be driven to-<lb/>wards product. In principle, this can be achieved by <lb/>co-precipitation and cross-linking of two or more en-<lb/>zymes in combi CLEAs. For example, combi CLEAs <lb/>have been prepared from catalase in combination <lb/>with glucose oxidase or galactose oxidase. The cata-<lb/>lase serves to catalyze the rapid degradation of the <lb/>hydrogen peroxide formed in the aerobic oxidation of <lb/>glucose and galactose, respectively, catalyzed by these <lb/>enzymes. <lb/>A combi CLEA containing an S-selective oxynitri-<lb/>lase from Manihot esculenta and an aselective nitrilase <lb/>from Pseudomonas fluorescens, catalyzed the smooth, <lb/>one-pot conversion of benzaldehyde to S-mandelic <lb/>acid (Figure 17) [124] in diisopropyl ether/water (9:1) at <lb/>pH 5.5. The enantioselectivity is provided by the oxy-<lb/>nitrilase and in situ conversion by the nitrilase serves <lb/>to drive the equilibrium of the first step towards prod-<lb/>uct. In principle, this could also be achieved by using <lb/>an S-selective nitrilase in combination with non-enzy-<lb/>matic hydrocyanation but, unfortunately, there are no <lb/>nitrilases that exhibit S-selectivity with mandeloni-<lb/>triles. Interestingly, the combi CLEA was more effec-<lb/>tive than a mixture of the two separate CLEAs. A <lb/>possible explanation is that the close proximity of the <lb/>two enzymes inside the combi CLEA is more favour-<lb/>able, compared to the case with two separate CLEAs, <lb/>for transfer of the product of the first step to the <lb/>active site of the enzyme for the second step. <lb/>7 Enzyme-Immobilized Microchannel Reactors for <lb/>Process Intensification <lb/>Microreactor technology is an interdisciplinary field <lb/>that has attracted much attention recently. [125] Process <lb/>intensification through the use of microchannel reac-<lb/>tors (microfluidic devices) has many advantages com-<lb/>pared with traditional batch process technologies, <lb/>such as rapid mass and heat transfer and large surface <lb/>area to volume ratios. These are attractive features <lb/>for conducting catalytic reactions in microreactors <lb/>containing the enzyme immobilized on their inner <lb/>walls. Maeda and co-workers [107,126,127] developed a mi-<lb/>croreactor in which enzymes are immobilized as an <lb/>enzyme-polymer membrane on the inner walls of the <lb/>microchannels. [127] Thus, a solution of the enzyme <lb/>(e.g., a-chymotrypsin) in aqueous buffer was mixed <lb/>with glutaraldehyde and formaldehyde as cross-link-<lb/>ers in commercially available polytetrafluoroethylene <lb/>(PTFE) tubing (inner diameter 500 mm). This results <lb/>in the formation of a CLEA membrane on the inner <lb/>walls of the tubing. This technique has been used to <lb/>prepare CLEA-based enzyme microreactors (CEMs) <lb/>Figure 17. One-pot conversion of benzaldehyde to (S)-man-<lb/>delic acid. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1303 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<body>from a wide variety of enzymes. [107] With electronega-<lb/>tive enzymes (such as aminoacylase) coprecipitation <lb/>of the enzyme in the presence of poly-l-lysine (see <lb/>above) was used to realize fast and efficient CLEA <lb/>formation. [107] The use of such enzyme-immobilized <lb/>microchannel reactors clearly has considerable poten-<lb/>tial for the design of green and sustainable biotrans-<lb/>formations. <lb/>In the context of incorporating the immobilized <lb/>biocatalyst in the reactor configuration, the develop-<lb/>ment of a monolithic stirrer reactor by Lathouder and <lb/>co-workers deserves a special mention. [128] According <lb/>to this novel concept, the enzyme is immobilized on a <lb/>honeycomb, ceramic monolith, analogous to those <lb/>used in catalytic exhaust systems in automobiles. Cor-<lb/>dierite monoliths were functionalized, by coating with <lb/>polyethylene imine or different types of carbon, in <lb/>order to create adsorption sites for the enzyme <lb/>(CaLB). These were then employed in a monolithic <lb/>stirrer reactor in which the monolithic structure is in-<lb/>corporated in the stirrer blades. This concept was <lb/>tested in the CaLB-catalyzed transesterification of 1-<lb/>butanol with vinyl acetate. [128] <lb/>Carbon nanofiber-coated monoliths performed the <lb/>best with regard to catalyst productivity and did not <lb/>exhibit any leaching under the reaction conditions. <lb/>The activity was lower (by a factor of 2-4) than Novo-<lb/>zym 435 or free CaLB but the latter preparations de-<lb/>activated much faster. In contrast, the monolithic cat-<lb/>alysts were operationally stable for several weeks, <lb/>without significant loss of activity. <lb/>8 Conclusions and Prospects <lb/>Hopefully, it is clear from this review that the subject <lb/>of enzyme immobilization continues to attract consid-<lb/>erable attention from researchers in both industry <lb/>and academia. Novel concepts continue to appear, a <lb/>recent example being single enzyme nanoparticles <lb/>(SENs) in nanoporous silica. [129] However, many of <lb/>these innovations involve the use of rather exotic sup-<lb/>ports which are substantially more expensive than the <lb/>enzyme to be immobilized. Consequently, they are <lb/>unlikely to be applied in industrial biotransformations <lb/>but could be interesting for applications in biosensors <lb/>or other devices where the enzyme cost contribution <lb/>is less of an issue. They can also provide important in-<lb/>sights into the effects of enzyme immobilization on <lb/>activity and stability. <lb/>For application in industrial biotransformations the <lb/>cost contribution of the (immobilized) enzyme is an <lb/>important issue. Clearly, the immobilization method-<lb/>ology, in addition to providing an active and stable <lb/>biocatalyst, should be a relatively simple operation <lb/>that does not require a highly pure enzyme prepara-<lb/>tion or an expensive support that may not be com-<lb/>mercially available. Immobilization as silica granu-<lb/>lates, for example, meets all these criteria but the <lb/>methodology is not applicable to aqueous environ-<lb/>ments (see earlier). Cross-linked enzyme aggregates <lb/>(CLEAs) would appear to have considerable industri-<lb/>al potential based on their high activity retention and <lb/>stability coupled with ease of preparation from crude <lb/>enzyme samples and no requirement for a support. <lb/>Because they are close to 100 % active catalyst they <lb/>also display high catalyst productivities and space-<lb/>time yields. However, properties such as mechanical <lb/>strength and filterability still have to be demonstrated <lb/>on an industrially relevant scale. <lb/>It is also clear that every enzyme is different and, <lb/>consequently, there is no all-encompassing, one size <lb/>fits all solution to the problem of enzyme immobili-<lb/>zation. Based on the increasing importance of en-<lb/>zymes in a plethora of industrial applications, interest <lb/>in improving their operational performance will cer-<lb/>tainly continue unabated. The quest for optimum per-<lb/>formance continues. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] R. A. Sheldon, Pure Appl. Chem. 2000, 72, 1233. <lb/>[2] R. A. Sheldon, F. van Rantwijk, Aust. J. Chem. 2004, <lb/>57, 281 -289. <lb/>[3] H. E. Schoemaker, D. Mink , M. G. Wubbolts, Science <lb/>2003, 299, 1694. <lb/>[4] A. J. J. Straathof, S. Panke, A. Schmid, Curr. Opin. <lb/>Biotechnol. 2002, 13, 548. <lb/>[5] R. N. Patel, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. 2001, 12, 587; <lb/>R. N. Patel, Enz. Microb. Technol. 2002, 31, 804. <lb/>[6] A. Schmid, F. Hollmann, J. B. Park, B. Bühler, Curr. <lb/>Opin. Biotechnol. 2002, 13, 359. <lb/>[7] K. Laumen, M. Kittelmann, O. Ghisalba, J. Mol. <lb/>Catal. B: Enzymatic 2002, 19-20, 55. <lb/>[8] N. M. Shaw, K. T. Robins, A. Kiener, Adv. Synth. <lb/>Catal. 2003, 345, 425. <lb/>[9] A. Schmid, J. S. Dordick, B. Hauer, A. Kiener, M. <lb/>Wubbolts, B. Witholt, Nature 2001, 409, 258. <lb/>[10] A. Zaks, Curr. Opin. Biol. 2001, 5, 130. <lb/>[11] A. Liese, M. Villela Filho, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. <lb/>1999, 10, 595. <lb/>[12] S. Panke, M. G. Wubbolts, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. <lb/>2002, 13, 111. <lb/>[13] S. M. Thomas, R. DiCosimo, V. Nagarajan, Tibtech <lb/>2002, 20, 238. <lb/>[14] G. W. Huisman, D. Gray, Curr. Opin. Biotechnol. <lb/>2002, 13, 352. <lb/>[15] J. D. Stewart, Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol. 2001, 5, 120. <lb/>[16] K. A. Powell, S. W. Ramer, S. B. del Cardayre, W. P. C. <lb/>Stemmer, M. B. Tobin, P. F. Longchamp, G. W. Huis-<lb/>man, Angew. Chem. 2001, 40, 3948. <lb/>[17] M. T. Reetz, K.-E. Jaeger, Chem. Eur. J. 2000, 6, 407. <lb/>[18] J. Minshull, W. P. C. Stemmer, Curr. Opin. Chem. Biol. <lb/>1999, 3, 284. <lb/>[19] O. May, P. T. Nguyen, F. H. Arnold, Nat. Biotechnol. <lb/>2000, 18, 317. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1304 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[20] For a recent comprehensive review of enzyme immo-<lb/>bilization, see: L. Cao, Carrier-bound Immobilized <lb/>Enzymes, Principles, Applications and Design, Wiley-<lb/>VCH, Weinheim, 2005; see also: L. Cao, Curr. Opin. <lb/>Chem. Biol. 2005, 9, 217 -226. <lb/>[21] U. T. Bornscheuer, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2003, 42, <lb/>3336 -3337. <lb/>[22] W. Tischer, V. Kascher, Tibtech 1999,17, 326 -335. <lb/>[23] W. Tischer, F. Wedekind, Top. Curr. Chem. 1999, 200, <lb/>95 -126. <lb/>[24] M. Adamczak, S. H. Krishna, Food Technol. Biotech-<lb/>nol. 2004, 42, 251 -264. <lb/>[25] B. Krajewska, Enz. Microb. Technol. 2004, 35, 126 -<lb/>139. <lb/>[26] J. M. S. Cabral, J. F. Kennedy, in: Thermostability of <lb/>Enzymes, (Ed.: M. N. Gupta), Springer Verlag, Berlin, <lb/>1993, pp 163 -179. <lb/>[27] A. I. Kallenberg, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Adv. <lb/>Synth. Catal. 2005, 347, 905 -926; M. A. Wegman, <lb/>M. H. A. Janssen, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2001, 343, 559 -576. <lb/>[28] A. Bruggink, R. Schoevaart, T. Kieboom, OPRD <lb/>2003, 7, 622. <lb/>[29] S. F. Meyer, W. Kroutil, K. Faber, Chem. Soc. Rev. <lb/>2001, 30, 332. <lb/>[30] F. F. Huerta, A. B. E. Minidis, J-E. Bäckvall , Chem. <lb/>Soc. Rev. 2001, 30, 321. <lb/>[31] L. Veum, U. Hanefeld, Chem. Commun. 2006, 825. <lb/>[32] See, for example: A. S. Bommarius, K. Drauz, U. <lb/>Groeger, C. Wandrey, in: Chirality in Industry, (Eds.: <lb/>A. N. Collins, G. N. Sheldrake, J. Crosby), Wiley, New <lb/>York, 1992, pp 372 -397. <lb/>[33] J. Bryjak, B. N. Kolarz, Biochemistry 1998, 33, 409 -<lb/>417. <lb/>[34] M. H. A. Janssen, L. M. van Langen, S. R. M. Pereira, <lb/>F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Biotechnol. Bioeng. <lb/>2002, 78, 425 -432. <lb/>[35] T. Boller, C. Meier, S. Menzler, Org. Process Res. De-<lb/>velop. 2002, 6, 509 -519. <lb/>[36] For reviews, see: A. L. Margolin, M. A. Navia, Angew. <lb/>Chem. Int. Ed. 2001, 40, 2204; J. Lalonde, CHEM-<lb/>TECH 1997, 27, 38 -45; J. J. Roy, T. E, Abraham, <lb/>Chem. Rev. 2004, 104, 3705 -3721; J. D. Vaghjiani, T. S. <lb/>Lee, G. J. Lye, M. K. Turner, Biocat. Biotrans. 2000, <lb/>18, 151 -175. <lb/>[37] For reviews, see: R. A. Sheldon, R. Schoevaart, L. M. <lb/>van Langen, in: Immobilization of Enzymes and <lb/>Cells, 2 nd edn., Methods in Biotechnology, Vol. 22, <lb/>(Ed.: M. Guisan), Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, 2006, <lb/>pp 31 -45; R. A. Sheldon, in: Biocatalysis in the Phar-<lb/>maceutical and Biotechnological Industries, (Ed.: R. <lb/>Patel), CRC Press, Boca Raton, 2006, pp. 351 -362; <lb/>R. A. Sheldon, R. Schoevaart, L. M. van Langen, <lb/>Biocat. Biotrans. 2005, 23, 141; R. A. Sheldon, R. <lb/>Schoevaart, L. M. van Langen, Speciality Chem. 2003, <lb/>July/August, 40 -42. <lb/>[38] E. Katchalski-Katzir, D. M. Kraemer, J. Mol. Catal. B: <lb/>Enzymatic 2000, 10, 157 -176. <lb/>[39] C. Mateo, O. Abian, G. Fernandez-Lorente, J. Pedro-<lb/>che, R. Fernandez-Lafuente, J. M. Guisan, Biotechnol. <lb/>Prog. 2002, 18, 629 -634. <lb/>[40] O. Kirk, M. W. Christensen, Org. Proc. Res. Dev. 2002, <lb/>6, 446 -451. <lb/>[41] M. Petkar, A. Lali, P. Caimi, M. Daminati, J. Mol. <lb/>Catal. B: Enzymatic 2006, 39, 83 -90. <lb/>[42] B. Krajewska, Enz. Microb. Technol. 2004, 35, 126 -<lb/>139. <lb/>[43] I. Chibata, T. Tosa, T. Shibatani, in. Chirality in In-<lb/>dustry, (Eds.: A. N. Collins, G. N. Sheldrake, J. <lb/>Crosby), Wiley, New York, 1992, pp. 351 -370; T. <lb/>Tosa, T. Mori, N. Fuse, I. Chibata, Enzymologia 1966, <lb/>31, 214. <lb/>[44] S. Karboune, A. Archelas, R. Furstoss, J. Barratti, J. <lb/>Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 2005, 32, 175 -184. <lb/>[45] V. I. Lozinsky, I. Y. Galaev, F. M. Plieva, I. N. Savina, <lb/>H. Jungvid, B. Mattiasson, Trends Biotechnol. 2003, <lb/>21, 445 -451. <lb/>[46] V. I. Lozinski, F. M. Plieva, Enz. Microb. Technol. <lb/>1998, 23, 227 -242. <lb/>[47] M. Jekel, A. Buhr, T. Willke, K.-D. Vorlop, Chem. <lb/>Eng. Technol. 1998, 21, 275 -278. <lb/>[48] A. Durieux, X. Nicolay, J.-P. Simon, Biotechnol. Lett. <lb/>2000, 22, 175 -182. <lb/>[49] D. Kubac, A. Cejkova, J. Masak, V. Jirku, M. Lemaire, <lb/>E. Gallienne, J. Bolte, R. Stloukal, L. Martinkova, J. <lb/>Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 2006, 39, 59 -61. <lb/>[50] D. Metrangolo-Ruiz De Temino, W. Hartmeier, M. B. <lb/>Ansorge-Schumacher, Enz. Microb. Technol. 2005, 36, <lb/>3 -9. <lb/>[51] T. Hischer, D. Gocke, M. Fernandez, P. Hoyos, A. R. <lb/>Alcantara, J. V. Sinisterra, W. Hartmeier, M. B. An-<lb/>sorge-Schumacher, Tetrahedron 2005, 61, 7378 -7383. <lb/>[52] H. Grçger, E. Capine, A. Barthuber, K.-D. Vorlop, <lb/>Org. Lett. 2001, 3, 1969 -1972. <lb/>[53] G. Czichocki, H. Dautzenberg, E. Capine, K.-D. <lb/>Vorlop, Biotechnol. Lett. 2001, 23, 1303 -1307. <lb/>[54] M. B. Ansorge-Schumacher, H. Slusarczyk, J. Schüm-<lb/>ers, D. Hirtz, FEBS J. 2006, 273, 3938 -3945. <lb/>[55] N. Bruns, J. C. Tiller, Nano Lett. 2005, 5, 45 -48. <lb/>[56] A. Petri, P. Marconcini, P. Salvadori, J. Mol. Catal. B: <lb/>Enzymatic 2005, 32, 219 -224. <lb/>[57] J. Diaz, K. J. Balkus, J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 1996, <lb/>2, 115 -126. <lb/>[58] A.-X. Yan, X.-W. Li, Y.-H. Ye, Appl. Biochem. Bio-<lb/>technol. 2002, 101, 113 -129. <lb/>[59] D. Moelans, P. Cool, J. Baeyans, E. F. Vansant, Catal. <lb/>Commun. 2005, 6, 307 -311. <lb/>[60] H. Takahashi, B. Li, T. Sasaki, C. Myazaki, T. Kajino, <lb/>S. Inagaki, Micropor. Mesopor. Mater. 2001, 44-45, <lb/>755 -762. <lb/>[61] P. Wang, S. Dai, S. D. Waezsada, A. Y. Tsao, B. H. Da-<lb/>vison, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 2001, 74, 249 -255. <lb/>[62] A. Borole, S. Dai, C. L. Cheng, M. Rodriguez, B. H. <lb/>Davison, Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol. 2004, 113-116, <lb/>273-285. <lb/>[63] M. I. Kim, H. O. Ham, S. D. Ho, H. G. Park, H. N. <lb/>Chang, S. H. Choi, J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic, 2006, <lb/>39, 62 -68. <lb/>[64] Y. Wang, F. Caruso, Chem. Commun. 2004, 1528 -<lb/>1529. <lb/>[65] M. Kreiner, B. D. Moore, M.-C. Parker, Chem. <lb/>Commun. 2001, 1096 -1097. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1305 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[66] M. Kreiner, M.-C. Parker, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 2004, <lb/>87, 24 -33; M. Kreiner, M.-C. Parker, Biotechnol. Lett. <lb/>2005, 27, 1571 -1577. <lb/>[67] K. Dabulis, A. M. Klibanov, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 1993, <lb/>41, 566. <lb/>[68] Y. L. Khmelnitzky, S. H. Welch, D. S. Clark, J. S. Dor-<lb/>dick, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1994, 116, 2647; M. T. Ru, <lb/>J. S. Dordick, J. A. Reiner, D. S. Clark, Biotechnol. <lb/>Bioeng. 1999, 63, 233. <lb/>[69] I. Y. Galaev, B. Mattiasson, Trends Biotechnol. 1999, <lb/>17, 335 -340. <lb/>[70] I. Y. Galaev, B. Mattiasson, (Eds.), Smart Polymers for <lb/>Bioseparation and Bioprocessing, Taylor and Francis, <lb/>London, 2004. <lb/>[71] I. Roy, S. Sharma, M. N. Gupta, Advan. Biochem. <lb/>Eng. Biotechnol. 2004, 86, 159 -189; I. Roy, M. N. <lb/>Gupta, in: Immobilization of Enzymes and Cells, 2 nd <lb/>edn., (Ed.: J. M. Guisan), Methods in Biotechnology, <lb/>Vol. 22, Humana Press, Totowa, NJ, 2006. <lb/>[72] A. E. Ivanov, E. Edink, A. Kumar, I. Y. Galaev, A. F. <lb/>Arendsen, A. Bruggink, B. Mattiasson, Biotechnol. <lb/>Progr. 2003, 19, 1167 -1175. <lb/>[73] J. F. Lutz, O. Akdemir, A. Hoth, J. Am. Chem. Soc. <lb/>2006, 128, 13046. <lb/>[74] S. Braun, S. Rappoport, R. Zusman, D. Avnir, M. Ot-<lb/>tolenghi, Mater. Lett. 1990, 10, 1. <lb/>[75] D. Avnir, S. Braun, O. Lev, M. Ottolenghi, Chem. <lb/>Mater. 1994, 6, 1605 -1614; D. Avnir, Acc. Chem. Res. <lb/>1995, 28, 328 -334; I. Gill, Chem. Mater. 2001, 13, <lb/>3404 -3421. <lb/>[76] A. C. Pierre, G. M. Pajonk, Chem. Rev. 2002, 102, <lb/>4243 -4265. <lb/>[77] M. T. Reetz, A. Zonta, J. Simpelkamp, Angew. Chem. <lb/>1995, 107, 373 -376. <lb/>[78] M. T. Reetz, Adv. Mater. 1997, 9, 943 -954. <lb/>[79] M. T. Reetz, A. Zonta, J. Simpelkamp, W. Kçnen, <lb/>Chem. Commun. 1996, 1397 -1398. <lb/>[80] For a review, see: M. T. Reetz, P. Tielmann, W. Wie-<lb/>senhçfer, W. Kçnen, A. Zonta, Adv. Synth. Catal. <lb/>2003, 345, 717 -728. <lb/>[81] A. C. Pierre, Biocat. Biotrans. 2004, 22, 145 -170. <lb/>[82] M. Pierre, P. Buisson, F. Fache, A. C. Pierre, Biocat. <lb/>Biotrans. 2000, 18, 237 -251. <lb/>[83] S. Maury, P. Buisson, A. Perrard, A. C. Pierre, J. Mol. <lb/>Catal. B: Enzymatic 2005, 32, 193 -203. <lb/>[84] O. OrÅaire, P. Buisson, A. C. Pierre, J. Mol. Catal. B: <lb/>Enzymatic 2006, 42, 106 -113. <lb/>[85] C. M. F. Soares, O. A. Dos Santos, H. F. De Castro, <lb/>F. F. De Moraes, G. M. Zanin, Appl. Biochem. Bio-<lb/>technol. 2004, 113-116, 307 -319; C. M. F. Soares, <lb/>O. A. Dos Santos, H. F. De Castro, F. F. De Moraes, <lb/>G. M. Zanin, J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 2006, 39, <lb/>69 -76. <lb/>[86] R. R. Naik, M. M. Tomcaz, H. R. Luckarift, J. C. <lb/>Spain, M. O. Stone, Chem. Commun. 2004, 1684 -<lb/>1685. <lb/>[87] N. Kroger, R. Deutzmann, M. Sumper, Science 1999, <lb/>286, 1129. <lb/>[88] A. Ragheb, M. A. Brook, M. Hrynyk, Chem. <lb/>Commun. 2003, 2314 -2315. <lb/>[89] H. Y. Wang, T. Kobayashi, H. Saitoh, N. Fuji, J. Appl. <lb/>Sci. 1996, 60, 2339. <lb/>[90] J. Kobayashi, Y. Mori, S. Kobayashi, Chem. Commun. <lb/>2006, 4227 -4229. <lb/>[91] F. A. Quiocho, F. M. Richards, Biochemistry 1966, 5, <lb/>4062 -4076. <lb/>[92] F. A. Quiocho, F. M. Richards, Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>1964, 52, 833 -839. <lb/>[93] N. L. St. Clair, M. A. Navia, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 1992, <lb/>114, 7314 -7316. <lb/>[94] M. Ayala, E. Horjales, M. A. Pickard, R. Vazquez-Du-<lb/>hault, Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 2002, 295, <lb/>828 -831. <lb/>[95] D. L. Brown, C. E. Glatz, Chem. Eng. Sci. 1966, 47, <lb/>1831 -1839. <lb/>[96] L. Cao, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Org. Lett. <lb/>2000, 2, 1361 -1364; L. Cao, L. M. van Langen, F. van <lb/>Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic <lb/>2001, 11, 665 -670. <lb/>[97] L. M. van Langen, N. H. P. Oosthoek, F. van Rantwijk, <lb/>R. A. Sheldon, Adv. Synth. Catal. 2003, 345, 797 -801. <lb/>[98] A. Illanes, L. Wilson, E. Caballero, R. Fernandez-La-<lb/>fuenta, J. M. Guisan, Appl. Biochem. Biotechnol. 2006, <lb/>133, 189 -202. <lb/>[99] P. Lopez-Serrano, L. Cao, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Shel-<lb/>don, Biotechnol. Lett. 2002, 24, 1379 -1383. <lb/>[100] F. Theil, Tetrahedron 2000, 56, 2905 -2909. <lb/>[101] R. Schoevaart, M. W. Wolbers, M. Golubovic, M. <lb/>Ottens, A. P. G. Kieboom, F. van Rantwijk, L. A. M. <lb/>van der Wielen, R. A. Sheldon, Biotechnol. Bioeng. <lb/>2004, 87, 754 -762. <lb/>[102] R. A. Sheldon, M. Sorgedrager, M. H. A. Janssen, <lb/>Chimica Oggi (Chemistry Today) 2007, 25(1), 48 -52. <lb/>[103] H. R. Hobbs, B. Kondor, P. Stephenson, R. A. Shel-<lb/>don, N. R. Thomas, M. Poliakoff, Green Chem. 2006, <lb/>8, 816 -821. <lb/>[104] A. Ruiz Toral, A. P. de Los Rios, F. J. Hernandez, <lb/>M. H. A. Janssen, R. Schoevaart, F. van Rantwijk, <lb/>R. A. Sheldon, Enz. Microb. Technol. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>j.enzmictec. 2006.08.027. <lb/>[105] H. W. Yu, H. Chen, X. Wang, Y. Y. Yang, C. B. Ching, <lb/>J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 2006, 43, 124 -127. <lb/>[106] C. Mateo, J. M. Palomo, L. M. van Langen, F. van <lb/>Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Biotechnol. Bioeng. 2004, <lb/>86, 273 -276. <lb/>[107] T. Honda, M. Miyazaki, H. Nakamura, H. Maeda, <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2006, 348, 2163 -2171. <lb/>[108] F. Lopez-Gallego, L. Betancor, A. Hidalgo, N. Alonso, <lb/>R. Fernandez-Lafuenta, J. M. Guisan, Biomacromoles <lb/>2005, 6, 1839 -1842; L. Wilson, A. Illanes, O. Abian, <lb/>B. C. C. Pessela, R. Fernandez-Lafuenta, J. M. Guisan, <lb/>Biomacromoles 2004, 5, 852 -857. <lb/>[109] C. Mateo, B. Fernandes, F. van Rantwijk, A. Stolz, <lb/>R. A. Sheldon, J. Mol. Catal. B: Enzymatic 2006, 38, <lb/>154 -157. <lb/>[110] S. Shah, A. Sharma, M. N. Gupta, Anal. Biochem. <lb/>2006, 351, 207 -213. <lb/>[111] CLEAs are commercially available from CLEA Tech-<lb/>nologies (www.cleatechnologies.com). <lb/>[112] T. Miyazawa, Amino Acids, 1999, 16, 191 -213; K. <lb/>Laumen, O. Ghisalba, K. Auer, Biosci. Biotechnol. <lb/>Biochem. 2001, 65, 1977 -1980. <lb/>[113] F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Tetrahedron 2004, 60, <lb/>501 -519. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1306 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Roger A. Sheldon <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[114] X. Z. Zhang, X. Wang, S. Chen, X. Fu, X. Wu, C. Li, <lb/>Enz. Microb. Technol. 1996, 19, 538 -544. <lb/>[115] Unpublished results. <lb/>[116] M. L. Bode, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Biotech-<lb/>nol. Bioeng. 2003, 84, 710 -713. <lb/>[117] L. Wilson, L. Betancor, G. Fernandez-Lorente, M. <lb/>Fuentes, A. Hidalgo, J. M. Guisan, B. C. C. Pessela, R. <lb/>Fernandez-Lafuenta, Biomacromoles 2004, 5, 814 -<lb/>817. <lb/>[118] L. M. van Langen, R. P. Selassa, F. van Rantwijk, <lb/>R. A. Sheldon, Org. Lett. 2005, 7, 327 -329. <lb/>[119] F. L. Cabirol, U. Hanefeld, R. A. Sheldon, Adv. Synth. <lb/>Catal. 2006, 348, 1645 -1654. <lb/>[120] A. Chmura, G. M. van der Kraan, F. Kielar, L. M. van <lb/>Langen, F. van Rantwijk, R. A. Sheldon, Adv. Synth. <lb/>Catal. 2006, 348, 1655 -1661. <lb/>[121] N. Hilal, R. Nigmatullin, A. Alpatova, J. Membrane <lb/>Sci. 2004, 238, 131 -141. <lb/>[122] J. Lee, D. Lee, E. Oh, J. Kim, Y.-P. Kim, S. Jin, H.-S. <lb/>Park, Y. Hwang, J. H. Kwak, J.-G. Park, C.-H. Shin, J. <lb/>Kim, T. Hyeon, Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. 2005, 44, <lb/>7427 -7432. <lb/>[123] J. Chen, J. Zhang, B. Han, Z. Li, X. Feng, Colloids <lb/>Surf. B: Biointerfaces 2006, 48, 72-76. <lb/>[124] C. Mateo, A. Chmura, S. Rustler, F. van Rantwijk, A. <lb/>Stolz, R. A. Sheldon, Tetrahedron: Asymmetry 2006, <lb/>17, 320 -323. <lb/>[125] P. Watts, S. J. Haswell, Chem. Soc. Rev. 2005, 34, 235-<lb/>246; T. Chovan, A. Guttman, Trends Biotechnol. 2002, <lb/>20, 116 -122; H. Wang, J. D. Holliday, Microreactor <lb/>Technology and Process Intensification, ACS Symp. <lb/>Ser. 914, American Chemical Society, Washington <lb/>D. C. 2005. <lb/>[126] M. Miyazaki, H. Maeda, Trends Biotechnol. 2006, 24, <lb/>463 -470. <lb/>[127] T. Honda, M. Miyazaki, H. Nakamura, H. Maeda, <lb/>Chem. Commun. 2005, 5062 -5064. <lb/>[128] K. M. de Lathouder, T. Marques Fló, F. Kapteijn, J. A. <lb/>Moulijn, Catal. Today 2005, 105, 443 -447. <lb/>[129] J. Kim, H. Jia, C.-W. Lee, S.-W. Chung, J. H. Kwak, Y. <lb/>Shin, A. Dohnalkova, B.-G. Kim, P. Wang, J. W. <lb/>Grate, Enz. Microb. Technol. 2006, 39, 474 -480. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Adv. Synth. Catal. 2007, 349, 1289 -1307 <lb/>2007 Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>asc.wiley-vch.de <lb/></note>

			<page>1307 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">REVIEWS <lb/>Enzyme Immobilization: The Quest for Optimum Performance </note>


	</text>
</tei>
