<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Precision-weighting of superior frontal cortex unsigned prediction error signals benefits <lb/>learning, is mediated by dopamine, and is impaired in psychosis. <lb/>J. Haarsma <lb/>1 <lb/>, P.C. Fletcher <lb/>1,2 <lb/>, J.D. Griffin <lb/>1 <lb/>, H.J. Taverne <lb/>1 <lb/>, H. Ziauddeen <lb/>1,2,3 <lb/>, T.J. Spencer <lb/>4 <lb/>, I. Goodyer, K.M.J. <lb/>Diederen <lb/>1,4 <lb/>*, G.K Murray <lb/>1,3 <lb/>* <lb/>1 Department of Psychiatry, University of Cambridge, United Kingdom, 2 Wellcome Trust MRC Institute of Metabolic Science, Cambridge <lb/>Biomedical Campus, United Kingdom, 3 Behavoural and Clinical N eurosci ence Institute, University of Cambri dge, United Kingdom, <lb/>4Department of Psychosis studi es, Institute of Psychi atry, Psychology and Neuroscience King&apos;s Coll ege London, De Crespigny Park, United <lb/>Kingdom <lb/>*= joint last author/equal contributions <lb/>Correspondence to: <lb/>Dr Di ederen, Department of Psychosis studies, Institute of Psychiatry, Psychology and Neuroscience King&apos;s College London, De Crespigny <lb/>Park, London, SE5 8AF, United Kingdom (kelly.diederen@kcl.ac. uk) or <lb/>Dr Murray, Depart ment of Psychiatry, University of Cambridge, Douglas House, Trumpington Road 18b, Cambridge, CB2 8AH, United <lb/>Kingdom (gm285@cam.ac.uk) <lb/>Abstract (150 words) <lb/>Recent theories of cortical function construe the brain as performing hierarchical Bayesian <lb/>inference. According to these theories, the precision of cortical unsigned prediction error <lb/>(i.e., surprise) signals plays a key role in learning and decision-making, to be controlled by <lb/>dopamine, and to contribute to the pathogenesis of psychosis. To test these hypotheses, we <lb/>studied learning with variable outcome-precision in healthy individuals after dopaminergic <lb/>modulation and in patients with early psychosis. Behavioural computational modelling <lb/>indicated that precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors benefits learning in health, <lb/>and is impaired in psychosis. FMRI revealed coding of unsigned prediction errors relative to <lb/>their precision in bilateral superior frontal gyri and dorsal anterior cingulate, which was <lb/>perturbed by dopaminergic modulation, impaired in psychosis, and associated with task <lb/>performance and schizotypy. We conclude that precision-weighting of cortical prediction <lb/>error signals is a key mechanism through which dopamine modulates inference and <lb/>contributes to the pathogenesis of psychosis. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>A common theme in contemporary theories of brain function, ranging from perception (Rao <lb/>&amp; Ballard, 1999) to reinforcement learning (Mathys et al., 2011), is an emphasis on the <lb/>critical role played by prior predictions in inference (Rao &amp; Ballard, 1999; Friston, 2009; <lb/>Bastos et al., 2012; Adams et al., 2013; Mathys et al., 2011 &amp; 2014; Iglesias et al., 2013; <lb/>Clark, 2013 &amp; 2015; Hohwy, 2013). According to these theories, predictions and incoming <lb/>sensory input each have an associated precision (inverse variance), reflecting their <lb/>confidence or reliability. Predictions and sensory input are thought to be compared against <lb/>one other, generating a discrepancy signal termed the prediction error which indicates the <lb/>difference between the expectation and sensory input. Such prediction error signals update <lb/>prior beliefs in a manner that is weighted by their associated precision, such that more is <lb/>learned from precise and reliable prediction errors compared to noisy and unreliable <lb/>prediction errors (Friston, 2009; Bastos et al., 2012; Mathys et al., 2011 &amp; 2014; Iglesias et <lb/>al., 2013). Several theorists have suggested that neuromodulator systems, including <lb/>dopamine, play an important role in mediating the precision of these prediction errors, and <lb/>that impaired precision-weighting of prediction errors (through dopaminergic or other <lb/>neuromodulator dysfunction) may be part of the cascade that result in psychotic symptoms <lb/>(Bastos et al., 2012; Adams et al., 2013; Friston, 2009; Mathys et al., 2014; Fletcher &amp; Frith <lb/>2009). However, to the best of our knowledge no direct evidence for these hypotheses <lb/>exists. Specifically, whilst several neuroimaging studies have indicated abnormal brain <lb/>prediction error signals in schizophrenia and related psychoses (Corlett et al 2007, Murray et <lb/>al 2008, Schlagenhauf et al 2014, Ermakova et al 2018), none of these studies have <lb/>addressed precision-weighting of prediction errors in patients. <lb/>In the context of reinforcement learning models, a distinction can be made between two <lb/>types of prediction errors. First, the signed prediction error indicates whether an outcome is <lb/>better or worse than expected, and thereby plays a crucial role in changing the value <lb/>allocated to cues, thereby guiding future decisions (Schultz et al., 1997; O&apos;Doherty et al., <lb/>2003 &amp; 2004; Pessiglione et al., 2006; D&apos;Ardenne et al., 2008; Diederen et al., 2016 &amp; 2017, <lb/>Tian et al., 2016). A second type of prediction error, the unsigned prediction error, signals <lb/>the degree of surprise, without indicating valence (better/ worse than expected). In addition <lb/>to signed prediction errors, unsigned prediction error are included in various reinforcement <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>learning models to control how much should be learned from new information. Large <lb/>unsigned prediction errors signal that the brain&apos;s model of the world is inaccurate, thereby <lb/>increasing the amount that is learned from new information. This can be achieved in various <lb/>ways, including a non-Bayesian approach by using a dynamic learning rate parameter <lb/>(Pearce &amp; Hall, 1980; Sutton &amp; Barto, 1998) or a Bayesian approach by decreasing the <lb/>precision of prior beliefs (Courville et al., 2006; Gershman, 2015) across different levels in <lb/>the hierarchy so that new sensory information has more of an impact on learning (Mathys et <lb/>al., 2011 &amp; 2014; Iglesias et al., 2013). In these hierarchical models both signed and unsigned <lb/>prediction errors are weighted by their precision. Whilst evidence has been provided for a <lb/>dopamine-mediated precision-weighted signed prediction error in learning (Diederen et al., <lb/>2015, 2016 &amp; 2017), no such evidence exists for dopaminergic modulation of the precision-<lb/>weighting of unsigned prediction errors. This is despite many computational theorists <lb/>hypothesizing a role for neuromodulator systems in precision-weighting of unsigned <lb/>prediction errors (Bastos et al., 2012; Adams et al., 2013; Mathys et al., 2014), and that the <lb/>dysfunctional precision-weighting is a key contributor to the pathogenesis of psychosis <lb/>(Fletcher &amp; Frith 2009; Adams et al 2013, Sterzer et al 2018, Heinz et al 2018). <lb/>Here we therefore studied whether unsigned prediction errors are indeed coded relative to <lb/>their associated precision; whether dopamine modulates the precision of these prediction <lb/>errors; where precision-weighted prediction errors are represented in the cortex and <lb/>whether and how precision weighting of cortical prediction error signals is disrupted in <lb/>psychosis. Our methods elicit reliable measures of prediction error, as we use a task where <lb/>prediction error is directly observable, rather than inferred as a latent variable as is common <lb/>in many paradigms. To probe the role of precision-weighted prediction errors in learning, <lb/>and the influence of dopamine, we employed pharmacological modulation in healthy <lb/>volunteers, combined with fMRI, associative learning and computational modelling. We next <lb/>examined how individual differences in computational learning signals and brain precision <lb/>weighting signals relate to clinical psychosis, and psychotic-like thinking in health <lb/>(schizotypy). We show that unsigned prediction errors are coded in superior frontal cortex, <lb/>where the unsigned prediction error signal is coded relative to the precision of <lb/>environmental outcomes; that the degree of precision-weighting benefits learning, is <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>mediated by dopamine, is perturbed in first episode psychosis, and relates to schizotypy in a <lb/>health. <lb/>Results <lb/>Participants undertook a cognitive task in which they were presented with <lb/>rewards/monetary outcomes on each trial that were drawn from distributions with specific <lb/>degrees of precision (i.e. inverse variance). They were instructed to best-predict drawn <lb/>rewards, with the most accurate prediction corresponding to the mean of the reward <lb/>distribution. Crucially, we manipulated the precision of reward information by including <lb/>distributions with different degrees of precision. We first examined the role of precision <lb/>weighting of unsigned prediction errors on learning and the effect of dopaminergic <lb/>modulation, by applying a novel, theoretically motivated, analysis to a dataset from an <lb/>experiment (Diederen et al 2017) in which healthy volunteers were randomised to receive <lb/>either placebo, sulpiride (a dopamine D2 receptor antagonist), or bromocriptine (a <lb/>dopamine receptor agonist) and undertook the task in the MRI scanner. Subsequently, we <lb/>repeated the same fMRI task in patients with early psychosis and matched controls. Finally, <lb/>we also examine inter-individual differences in trait psychosis &quot;schizotypy&quot; in relation to <lb/>precision-weighting. <lb/>Figure 1: Example of a trial. The participants were instructed to learn the mean of a reward distribution. First a fixation <lb/>cross was presented after which the participants were informed about the standard deviation (which indicated the <lb/>precision) of the reward distribution. Subsequently the participants were asked to make a prediction regarding the <lb/>upcoming reward, which was presented to the participant in combination with the prediction error (in yellow) after an <lb/>anticipation period. <lb/>High Low <lb/>(Cue; Precision = medium) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Study 1: Dopamine modulation study <lb/>Environmental precision and dopamine D2 receptor antagonism modulate task performance. <lb/>In the dopamine modulation study we explored the influence of precision and dopaminergic <lb/>medication on performance, which was defined as the distance between the participants <lb/>prediction and the mean of the distribution, as the latter corresponds to the most accurate <lb/>prediction. We found that participants&apos; performance increased when the precision of the <lb/>reward distributions increased, and reduced average performance under sulpiride (a <lb/>dopamine D2 receptor antagonist). Trial-by-trial analysis revealed lower performance in low-<lb/>precision conditions at the start of the experiment, but no significant group differences. We <lb/>studied whether dopaminergic modulation influenced scrolling distance, missed trials and <lb/>reaction times as this might explain differences in performance. However, dopaminergic <lb/>modulation did not affect scrolling distance or missed trials, although reaction times were <lb/>increased under sulpiride (see Fig. 2 and supplementary information). <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2: A. Behavioural results for the dopamine study. A-E display the average learning curves , reflecting the absolute <lb/>distance between the actual mean of the distribution and the participants estimate of the mean distribution over 30 trials <lb/>averaged over the 3 sessions for each participant. Asterisks indicate Bonferoni corrected significant differences across <lb/>conditions. A: Performance was significantly higher in the high precision condition compared to the low precision <lb/>condition when combing all participants, especially at the beginning of the experiment. B: There were no clear differences <lb/>between groups when analysing trial-by-trial performance. C-E: The placebo, Sulpiride and Bromocriptine group showed <lb/>only a significant difference between the precision conditions on or two trials in the beginning of the experiment. F: <lb/>Averaging performance across all trials, we see overall better performance in the placebo condition compared to the <lb/>Bromocriptine condition, and higher performance in more precision conditions. G: Learning rates were higher in the <lb/>Bromocriptine condition compared to the Sulpiride condition. H: Precision and group did not affect the learning rate <lb/>decay parameter. I: No differences were found in number of missed trials, and K: scrolling distance.. J: Reaction times <lb/>were quicker in the Sulpiride group. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Reinforcement learning modelling of behavioural data indicates precision-weighted unsigned <lb/>and signed prediction errors <lb/>We used two complementary approaches to demonstrate the contribution of unsigned <lb/>prediction errors. First we used a general linear model with signed and unsigned prediction <lb/>errors and their interaction term as independent variables and learning -defined as the <lb/>change in predicted reward from one trial to the next -as the dependent variable. Here we <lb/>showed that the unsigned*signed prediction error interaction term was highly significant in <lb/>predicting learning (F{1,10763}=51.7, p&lt;.0001), demonstrating the importance of unsigned <lb/>prediction errors (for more details, see supplementary results). In addition, we fitted various <lb/>reinforcement learning models to the participants&apos; trial-wise predictions to investigate <lb/>whether participants were likely to make use of precision-weighted unsigned and signed <lb/>prediction errors. In all three medication groups a Pearce-Hall model with separate <lb/>estimated precision weighted signed and unsigned prediction errors best predicted <lb/>participants&apos; predictions (model comparison using AIC to penalize models for the number of <lb/>free parameters; see table 1 for an overview of the model (free) parameters and models&apos; fits <lb/>and comparisons). These results indicate that both unsigned and signed prediction errors are <lb/>precision-weighted to facilitate efficient learning under uncertainty. By simulating data using <lb/>the estimated model parameters and correlating this with the acquired data, we show that <lb/>the correlation between the simulated and the real data is comparable across groups (R 2 <lb/>placebo: .20 (SE= .035), sulpiride: .18 (SE= .034), bromocriptine: .19 (SE= .026), similar to <lb/>other studies (e.g. Powers et al., 2017). <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1: Overview of AIC values for each learning model per medication group. The lowest AIC, which indicates <lb/>the best performing model, is printed in bold. RW: Rescorla-Wagner. PH -Pearce-Hall. <lb/>Bromocriptine increases learning rates <lb/>The best-performing computational model contained 4 free parameters (initial learning rate, <lb/>decay parameter, precision-weighting of signed prediction error and unsigned prediction <lb/>error -see methods for details). As the model with a precision-weighting parameter <lb/>outperformed the models without, precision is expected to affect the learning rate and <lb/>decay parameters in the model. In order to explore this question further, we fitted the data <lb/>to each precision condition separately for each participant and tested for an effect of <lb/>precision on the model parameters. We tested for a main effect of group and precision on <lb/>the initial learning rate and decay parameter (see methods), and their interactions. We <lb/>found a significant effect of precision on the initial learning rate in the winning model, <lb/>reflecting higher learning rates when reward information was more precise (F{1,52}=16.83, <lb/>p&lt;.001). In addition we found a small, but significant, effect of group (F{2,52}=3.252, <lb/>p=.047), which was driven by higher learning rates in the bromocriptine group compared to <lb/>the sulpiride group (F{1,36}=7.266, p=.011). However, no significant interaction was found <lb/>F{2,52}=1.348, p=.27). We also explored the effects of precision and medication group on <lb/>the decay parameter, and found no significant main effect of precision F{1,52}=2.48, p=.12), <lb/>medication group F{2,52}=1.80, p=.18), or interaction F{2,52}=.44, p=.65) (see Fig. 2 G-H). <lb/>Free <lb/>parameters <lb/>AIC overall <lb/>Placebo <lb/>Sulpiride <lb/>Bromocriptine <lb/>RW <lb/>1 <lb/>894.7 <lb/>824.2 <lb/>935.9 <lb/>924.0 <lb/>RW scaled <lb/>1 <lb/>903.2 <lb/>829.0 <lb/>947.3 <lb/>933.4 <lb/>PH not scaled <lb/>2 <lb/>884.2 <lb/>808.2 <lb/>931.1 <lb/>913.4 <lb/>PH both scal ed <lb/>2 <lb/>883.6 <lb/>807.3 <lb/>930.1 <lb/>913.4 <lb/>PH-estimated precision-weighting <lb/>3 <lb/>882.7 <lb/>806.1 <lb/>928.9 <lb/>914.1 <lb/>PH-estimated precision-weighting <lb/>separate for signed and unsigned <lb/>prediction error <lb/>4 <lb/>879.4 <lb/>803.1 <lb/>926.3 <lb/>910.4 <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Unsigned prediction errors are coded in the SFC and pre SMA/dACC <lb/>Trial-by-trial unsigned prediction error (absolute difference between predicted and observed <lb/>rewards) was included as a parametric modulator in our fMRI model. Whilst correcting for <lb/>whole brain comparisons, unsigned prediction errors were coded in various regions within <lb/>the frontal cortex, and parietal cortex (see Table 2). We used the left and right SFC and dACC <lb/>clusters as ROIs, as informed by previous work, to take forward our analysis of dopaminergic <lb/>effects on precision weighting. Secondary analyses examined these effects in occipital and <lb/>parietal regions (supplementary materials). <lb/>Table 2: Regions coding unsigned prediction error voxelwise whole brain corrected &lt;.05. SFC = Superior frontal <lb/>cortex. SMA/dACC=supplementary motor area/dorsal anterior cingulate cortex. sOC= superior occipital cortex. <lb/>FWE: family-wise error corrected. <lb/>Region <lb/>MNI <lb/>Voxels <lb/>T <lb/>Z <lb/>pFWE <lb/>Right SFC <lb/>27 8 54 <lb/>145 <lb/>8.43 <lb/>7.68 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Left SFC <lb/>-26 0 54 <lb/>32 <lb/>7.66 <lb/>7.09 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Pre SMA/ dACC <lb/>-7 12 50 <lb/>6 <lb/>5.32 <lb/>5.10 <lb/>=.002 <lb/>Right sOC <lb/>24 -74 34 <lb/>21 <lb/>7.24 <lb/>6.75 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Parietal cortex <lb/>34 -48 38 <lb/>18 <lb/>5.69 <lb/>5.43 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Parietal cortex <lb/>20 -60 26 <lb/>4 <lb/>5.24 <lb/>5.03 <lb/>=.003 <lb/>Precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors is mediated by dopamine in the SFC/dACC <lb/>To test whether precision and dopaminergic perturbations affected the coding of unsigned <lb/>prediction errors, we extracted the parameter estimates (betas) of the unsigned prediction <lb/>error parametric modulators from the left and right superior frontal cortex (SFC) and dACC <lb/>cluster that showed a main effect of unsigned prediction error coding at whole brain <lb/>corrected pFWE&lt;.01. We used a two-factor mixed model ANOVA with medication group as <lb/>the between-subjects variable and precision condition as the within-subjects variable, using <lb/>a linear contrast across precision conditions for the main effect of precision and interaction. <lb/>In the left SFC cluster, there was a significant interaction across precision conditions and <lb/>medication group, suggesting that medication had a significant effect on precision-weighting <lb/>of unsigned prediction errors (F{2,56}=4.025 p=.023; Fig.6B). We then explored whether the <lb/>effect was driven by bromocriptine or sulpiride compared to placebo. We found a significant <lb/>interaction between medication group (placebo vs sulpiride) and precision condition (F{2,37} <lb/></body>

			<page>1 0 <lb/></page>

			<body>= 5.44, p=.025), with less precision-weighting in the sulpiride than in the placebo group, <lb/>which suggests that sulpiride dampens precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors. <lb/>Comparing the placebo and bromocriptine group, there was a significant effect of precision <lb/>(F{1,37} = 14.93, p&lt;.001), but no significant effect of medication group (placebo vs <lb/>bromocriptine) (F{1,37} = 2.781, p=.104) or interaction between medication group and <lb/>precision (F{2,36} = 0.02, p=.894). This finding suggests that left SFC unsigned prediction <lb/>error signals are precision-weighted, but relatively unaffected by bromocriptine. <lb/>In the right SFC we did not find a significant interaction between medication and precision <lb/>condition (F{2,56}=1.70, p=.193; Fig. 3C). However, signal changes in the right SFC are largely <lb/>the same as in the left SFC (see Fig. 3B). We did find a significant main effect of medication <lb/>(F{2,56}=3.65, p=.032). This effect was driven by a stronger main effect of unsigned <lb/>prediction error in the bromocriptine group compared to the placebo group (F{1,37}=6.740, <lb/>p=.013), whereas the difference was only trend-level significant between the sulpiride and <lb/>placebo group (F{1,38}=3.55, p=.067). <lb/>In the dACC we found a trend-level significant interaction between precision and medication <lb/>(F{2,56}=2.81, p=.069; Fig. 3D). Post-hoc tests between the placebo and sulpiride group <lb/>revealed a trend-level interaction between precision and medication (F{1,38}=3.043, <lb/>p=.089). Testing the placebo and bromocriptine group revealed a significant effect of <lb/>precision (F{1,37}=9.32, p=.004), but no effect of group (F{1,37}=1.17, p=.29) or interaction <lb/>(F{1,37}=.172, p=.68). A similar pattern was thus found in the dACC as in the left SFC (see Fig. <lb/>3B+D). <lb/>The degree of precision-weighting in the left and right SFC and dACC correlated with task <lb/>performance (controlling for group), such that higher precision-weighting relates to better <lb/>performance (Left Rho=-.45, p&lt;.001; Fig. 7A, Right: Rho=-.37, p=.005; Fig. 7B, dACC: Rho=-<lb/>.25, p=.057). Performance was quantified as the mean performance error (abs(actual mean -<lb/>predicted mean)) on the last three trials in each session (Fig. 4). <lb/>Figure. 3: A. Unsigned prediction errors were coded in bilateral superior frontal cortex and dorsal anterior cingulate <lb/>cortex. The left side of the brain is the left side of the image. B-D. When exploring these regions further, we find that <lb/>unsigned prediction errors are coded in a precision-weighted fashion as indicated by the strong unsigned prediction error <lb/>signal in the high precision condition which declines over the medium and low precision condition in the placebo and <lb/>bromocriptine group. Importantly, sulpiride perturbed precision-weighting significantly in the left SFC. Error bars <lb/>represent standard error of the mean. <lb/></body>

			<page>1 2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure. 4: Precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors in the A. left SFC and B. right SFC correlates with <lb/>performance (i.e. difference between mean of the reward distribution and predicted mean) on the task. <lb/>Study 2: Psychosis study <lb/>Having established the role of dopamine in the precision-weighting of cortical unsigned <lb/>prediction errors, we tested whether precision-weighting is perturbed in psychosis by using <lb/>the same experimental paradigm -in a slightly altered form -to assess a group of healthy <lb/>controls (HCS), patients with first episode psychosis (FEP) and current psychotic symptoms <lb/>(as assessed by scoring over 3 on the PANSS rating scale for the delusions or hallucinations <lb/>items P1&amp;P3, Kay et al., 1987), and a help-seeking group of people at risk for psychosis (At <lb/>Risk Mental State, ARMS, Yung et al., 2005). <lb/>First Episode Psychosis (FEP) is associated with decreased overall performance and less <lb/>benefit from more precise information <lb/>We explored the difference between participants&apos; estimates of the mean and the actual <lb/>mean across trials, and tested for significant differences across groups and precision <lb/>conditions while correction for multiple comparisons using a Bonferonni correction. We <lb/>found increased performance when precision was high in healthy control participants and <lb/>ARMS individuals but not in people with FEP. We also found decreased performance in the <lb/>FEP group compared to controls. There were no significant differences in missed trials, <lb/></body>

			<page>1 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>reaction times and scrolling distances between the groups (see Fig. 5 and supplementary <lb/>results). <lb/>Figure. 5: Behavioural results for the patient study. A-E display the average learning curves , reflecting the absolute <lb/>distance between the actual mean of the distribution and the participants estimate of the mean distribution over 30 trials <lb/>averaged over the 3 sessions for each participant. Asterisks indicate Bonferoni corrected significant differences across <lb/>conditions. A: Performance was significantly higher in the high precision condition compared to the low precision <lb/></body>

			<page>1 4 <lb/></page>

			<body>condition when combing all participants, especially at the beginning of the experiment. B: HC performed better than <lb/>FEPs, but not compared to ARMS. The colour of the asterisk indicates a significant difference of the patient group with <lb/>HC. C-E: Healthy controls showed a significant difference between the precision conditions, whereas the patient groups <lb/>did not. F: Averaging performance across all trials, HC and ARMS perform better than FEP, and benefitted from more <lb/>precise information, whereas FEP did not. G: Learning rates were higher in the high precision condition compared to the <lb/>low precision condition in HC and ARMS, but not for FEPS, although an interaction was not significant. H: Precision did <lb/>not affect the learning rate decay parameter. I: HC had slightly fewer missed trials than FEP. J: Reaction times were equal <lb/>across groups. K: Scrolling distance was equal across groups. <lb/>FEP is associated with a lack of precision-weighting as revealed by computational modelling <lb/>As before, we compared two different families of computational models; two Rescorla-<lb/>Wagner reinforcement learning models and four Pearce-Hall learning models. We found that <lb/>for the HCS and ARMS participants the best model was the Pearce-Hall model with a <lb/>precision-weighting parameter for both the signed and unsigned prediction error term. <lb/>However, the FEP group followed a simple RW-learning rule without precision-weighting of <lb/>prediction error. This suggests that the FEP group specifically is not precision-weighting <lb/>prediction errors (Table 3). <lb/>To confirm the lack of precision-weighting in the FEP group compared to control <lb/>participants, we modelled the data separately for the high precision and low precision <lb/>condition, and compared the model parameters between the two conditions. We found that <lb/>both the HCS group T{29}=4.26, p&lt;.001) and the ARMS group T{22}=4.99, p&lt; .001) <lb/>presented with significantly higher learning rates in the high precision condition compared <lb/>to the low precision condition. By contrast, the FEP group did not show such a significant <lb/>difference between high and low precision conditions (T{18}=1.5, p=.15). However, when we <lb/>tested the precision by group interaction using a mixed (3x2) two-way ANOVA we did not <lb/>see a significant interaction (F{2,76}=1.68 , p=.193) (Fig. 5G). We found no differences in <lb/>learning rate decay between precision conditions for the HC group (T{29}=1.52, p= .14), <lb/>ARMS group (T{22}=-.26, p= .74), and FEP group (T{18}=-1.39, p= .18) (Fig. 5H). <lb/></body>

			<page>1 5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 3: Overview model comparisons <lb/>Free <lb/>parameters <lb/>AIC overall <lb/>HC <lb/>ARMS <lb/>FEP <lb/>RW <lb/>1 <lb/>1365.5 <lb/>1316.1 <lb/>1375.5 <lb/>1077.1 <lb/>RW scaled <lb/>1 <lb/>1364.8 <lb/>1311.7 <lb/>1376.5 <lb/>1077.3 <lb/>PH not scaled <lb/>2 <lb/>1359.8 <lb/>1298.7 <lb/>1362.0 <lb/>1094.2 <lb/>PH both scaled <lb/>2 <lb/>1361.4 <lb/>1299.7 <lb/>1362.9 <lb/>1096.5 <lb/>PH-estimated precision <lb/>3 <lb/>1355.6 <lb/>1292.9 <lb/>1356.7 <lb/>1097.1 <lb/>PH-estimated <lb/>precision <lb/>separate <lb/>for <lb/>signed <lb/>and <lb/>unsigned PE <lb/>4 <lb/>1349.8 <lb/>1288.6 <lb/>1348.5 <lb/>1087.8 <lb/>Unsigned prediction-errors are precision-weighted bilaterally in the SFC <lb/>In bilateral SFC (see methods for ROI derivation) there were brain signals that encoded <lb/>unsigned prediction error (Right: T=7.33, voxels: 150, p&lt;.001, [24 4 52]; Left: T=6.78, voxels: <lb/>149, p&lt;.001, [-24 6 52], small volume correction). Importantly, there was significantly <lb/>stronger encoding of unsigned prediction errors in the high precision condition compared to <lb/>the low precision condition in both the right and left SFC, demonstrating precision-weighting <lb/>(Right: T=3.82, voxels: 66, p=.011, [22 12 52]; Left: T=3.52, voxels: 45, p=.025, [-21 -2 52]; <lb/>small volume corrected), and replicating the effect observed in the dopaminerigc <lb/>modulation study. <lb/>In a whole brain analysis, additional regions demonstrated precision weighting of prediction <lb/>error: bilateral superior frontal cortex, right lateral frontal cortex, and medial parietal lobe <lb/>(see Table 3). <lb/></body>

			<page>1 6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4: Overview significant clusters precision-weighting of unsigned prediction error <lb/>Region <lb/>MNI <lb/>N-voxels <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>Medial parietal <lb/>lobe <lb/>[-9 -61 48] <lb/>383 <lb/>5.59 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Occipital <lb/>[-12 -101 2] <lb/>87 <lb/>5.29 <lb/>.011 <lb/>Right SFC <lb/>[24 12 58] <lb/>171 <lb/>4.53 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Right PFC <lb/>[36 52 24] <lb/>171 <lb/>4.46 <lb/>&lt;.001 <lb/>Left SFC <lb/>[-21 -2 52] <lb/>94 <lb/>4.20 <lb/>.007 <lb/>FEP is associated with diminished precision-weighting in the right SFC <lb/>There was a significant difference in precision-weighting of prediction error between the FEP <lb/>group and the control group in the right SFC (T=3.38, voxels: 9, p=.035,[24 9 48]; small <lb/>volume corrected) (see Fig. 6A). Importantly, group differences were not driven by <lb/>medication as precision-weighting in medicated psychosis patients was not significantly <lb/>different from patients who non-medicated (T{18}=.14, p=.89; analysis conducted on voxels <lb/>that showed a FEP v control group difference), and there was no correlation between <lb/>medication dose and precision-weighting (r=.17, p=.52). No voxels differentiated the groups <lb/>on whole-brain analysis, or left SFC ROI analysis, corrected for multiple comparisons. We <lb/>tested whether precision-weighting in these 9 voxels (that differentiated the first episode <lb/>psychosis and control groups) correlated to symptom severity. To increase the number of <lb/>participants for this analysis with a wide variety of symptoms we included both the ARMS <lb/>group the FEP group. This revealed a significant relationship with positive symptoms <lb/>(F{1,49}=5.21, p=.027), however this became trend-level after controlling for group <lb/>(F{1,49}=3.42, p=.07). <lb/></body>

			<page>1 7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6: A: Precision-weighting of prediction error in ROI. Precision-weighting is significantly diminished in <lb/>first episode psychosis. B: Diminished precision-weighting of prediction error is correlated with positive <lb/>symptoms. <lb/>Higher SPQ scores is related to decreased performance and diminished precision-weighting <lb/>of cortical prediction errors in a separate healthy sample <lb/>We next examined the relationship between psychotic-like symptoms and precision-<lb/>weighting of prediction error in health, free from the possible confounds of medication or <lb/>illness duration driving effects. For this purpose we pooled the participants in the <lb/>dopaminergic modulation study (N=59) and the participants of a previously published <lb/>normative sample (N=27) (Diederen et al., 2016). From these participant measures of <lb/>schizotypy (trait levels of schizophrenia-like thoughts and behaviour that occur on a <lb/>continuum in the general population) were taken around the time of scanning (Schizotypal <lb/>Personality Questionnaire, SPQ (Raine et al., 1991)). We tested for a relationship between <lb/>SPQ scores and precision-weighting of prediction error, while controlling for experimental <lb/>group. There was a significant correlation between performance and SPQ scores (Rho=-.23, <lb/>p=.034). This was mirrored by a significant brain signal-schizotypy correlation between SPQ <lb/>scores and the extracted right SFC precision-weighting parameter estimates (Rho=-.25, <lb/>p=.024)(Figure 6C). The higher schizotypal personality, the less the participants exhibited <lb/>cortical precision-weighting of prediction errors. Importantly, no relationship was observed <lb/>between schizotypy and the main-effect of prediction error (p&gt;.3), suggesting that the effect <lb/>is specific to the precision-weighting of prediction error. <lb/></body>

			<page>1 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIgure 7: Higher SPQ scores were correlated with less precision-weighting in the right SFC, including when controlling for <lb/>experimental group <lb/></body>

			<page>1 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>Recent theories (Friston, 2009; Bastos et al., 2012; Adams et al., 2013; Fletcher &amp; Frith, <lb/>2009; Sterzer et al., 2018) have hypothesised that precision-weighting of cortical prediction <lb/>errors is mediated by neuromodulators (including dopamine), and link a malfunctioning <lb/>dopamine system to psychosis through aberrant precision-weighting of these prediction <lb/>errors. However, to our knowledge, no direct evidence for any of these claims exists. Here <lb/>we showed that separately estimated precision-weighted signed and unsigned prediction <lb/>errors provided the best description of the behavioural data, thus suggesting that both <lb/>precision-weighted and unsigned prediction errors should be represented in the brain. The <lb/>representation of precision weighted signed prediction errors in subcortical areas was <lb/>confirmed previously by fMRI in humans (Diederen et al., 2016). In the present study, we <lb/>tested the prediction that unsigned prediction errors would be represented in the brain, and <lb/>found evidence for a precision weighted cortical representation of unsigned prediction in <lb/>the bilateral superior frontal cortex and dorsal anterior cingulate cortex/pre-supplementary <lb/>motor area (that we collectively referred to as SFC). Importantly, this precision weighting <lb/>was significantly diminished in the sulpiride (dopamine D2 receptor antagonism) group in <lb/>comparison to the other groups in the right SFC; there was marginal evidence of a <lb/>medication effect in the dACC. This finding suggests that the dopamine D2 receptor plays a <lb/>key role in the mechanisms underlying precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors. <lb/>We furthermore found that a greater degree of superior frontal precision-weighting of <lb/>unsigned prediction error was significantly correlated to performance on the task, where an <lb/>increase in precision-weighting resulted in more accurate predictions of upcoming rewards. <lb/>These results confirm the hypothesis that there exist cortical unsigned prediction error <lb/>signals, which influence performance and are precision weighted by dopamine. <lb/>The coding of unsigned prediction errors in the superior and middle frontal gyri and dACC is <lb/>in line with earlier findings by Hayden (et al., 2011) who found unsigned prediction errors in <lb/>the dACC of monkeys, and with prior fMRI studies in humans (Fletcher et al 2001, Turner et <lb/>al 2004, Fouragnan et al., 2017; Fouragnan et al 2018; Metereau et al., 2013; Ide et al., <lb/>2013). Our findings are consistent with those of Katthagen et al 2018, who used reaction <lb/>time data (rather than choice data) from a human fMRI reversal learning study to derive a <lb/></body>

			<page>2 0 <lb/></page>

			<body>relevance weighted unsigned prediction error signal, which was also represented in the <lb/>dACC. Our data in both the dopaminergic modulation dataset, and in the psychosis study <lb/>dataset show that SFC prediction error signals based on choice data are precision-weighted <lb/>in humans. We note that dopaminergic innervation of cortex is greatest in superior frontal <lb/>regions (Lewis et al., 1987; Berger et al., 1991; Paus, 2001), compatible with the hypothesis <lb/>that precision weighting is influenced here by dopaminergic input. <lb/>If the precision-weighting of prediction errors is important in learning, we can expect <lb/>aberrant learning to occur when prediction errors are not scaled optimally to the <lb/>environmental statistics determining the precision of available information. We tested <lb/>whether this mechanism could be of importance to psychosis, which is characterized by <lb/>delusional beliefs and hallucinatory perception (Fletcher &amp; Frith et al., 2009). Previous work <lb/>showed aberrant cortical and subcortical prediction error coding in people with psychosis <lb/>(Murray et al., 2008; Corlett et al., 2007, Ermakova et al., 2018). As psychosis has <lb/>consistently been associated with dopamine dysfunction (Howes et al., 2009), it is likely that <lb/>a dopamine mediated precision-weighting process would be impaired in psychosis. Indeed, it <lb/>has been suggested that dopamine dysregulation causes psychosis due to affecting the <lb/>brains capacity to precision-weight prediction error (Adams et al., 2013). That is, if unreliable <lb/>prediction errors were given excessive weight, they could have an exaggerated influence on <lb/>driving changes in the brain&apos;s model of the world, thereby contributing to the formation of <lb/>abnormal beliefs. <lb/>We extended previous studies showing abnormal brain prediction error signals in psychosis <lb/>by testing the degree of precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors in a clinical <lb/>psychosis population. Here we found several lines of evidence suggesting that FEP in <lb/>particular is associated with a failure to precision-weight prediction errors. First, FEP was <lb/>associated with decreased performance on the task. Furthermore, the FEP group did not <lb/>benefit as much from more precision reward information than the healthy controls and <lb/>ARMS group did. This could potentially be driven by a ceiling effect, where the performance <lb/>in the FEP group is so poor that the difference between the high precision and low precision <lb/>condition is attenuated. However, this is unlikely: the distance between the participants <lb/>predictions and actual mean of the distribution towards the end of the experiment (the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 1 <lb/></page>

			<body>measure of performance used in the present study) were below 14 points in both precision <lb/>conditions, which is better than expected from random guessing on a 100 point scale. <lb/>Secondly, computational modelling suggests that the FEP group does not precision-weight <lb/>prediction errors, as they follow a simple RW learning rule without precision-weighted <lb/>prediction errors. By contrast, controls and ARMS follow a Pearce-Hall learning rule with <lb/>precision-weighted prediction errors. This invites the question whether the poor <lb/>performance of the FEP group might have more to do with the failure to diminish their <lb/>learning rate appropriately over time (as this is what characterizes a Pearce-Hall model). <lb/>However, subsequent analysis revealed that whereas controls and ARMS show a clear effect <lb/>of precision on learning rate, the FEP group does not. In contrast, no differences were found <lb/>for the decay parameter, suggesting that the differences lie in how much prediction errors <lb/>are used in different precision conditions. Thirdly, neural evidence suggests that the FEP <lb/>group does not precision-weight cortical prediction errors to the extent that healthy controls <lb/>do, and that the degree of neural abnormality may relate to positive psychotic symptom <lb/>severity. <lb/>Although we demonstrate that in health, dopaminergic modulation influences precision <lb/>weighting of the prediction error signal in the superior cortex, and we demonstrate <lb/>abnormal SFC precision weighting in psychosis, we cannot conclude that the abnormalities in <lb/>patients were of dopaminergic origin, as we make no neurochemical measures in patients. <lb/>Such inference would require either a pharmacological design in patients, or the use of <lb/>neurochemical imaging such as PET. One possible confound in the patient study is the use of <lb/>anti-psychotic medication in some patients, given that we showed that precision-weighting <lb/>of prediction errors is diminished after healthy controls take a dopamine D2-receptor <lb/>antagonist in controls. We addressed this issue by showing that there are no differences in <lb/>precision-weighting within the participants who take anti-psychotics and those who do not. <lb/>We furthermore showed that there is no relationship between anti-psychotic dosage and <lb/>the degree of precision-weighting in this study. Furthermore we demonstrated evidence for <lb/>aberrancies in cortical precision-weighting of prediction errors, and impaired task <lb/>performance, relating to schizotypal personality in the healthy population, where <lb/>medication cannot be a confound. We thus conclude that there is no evidence in the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 2 <lb/></page>

			<body>present study that the reported effects in patients are driven by the use of anti-psychotic <lb/>medications. <lb/>Several other studies have used this computational framework to study learning in <lb/>individuals with psychosis that imply a failure to precision weight prediction errors. For <lb/>example in a pharmacological model of psychosis, Vinckier (et al., 2015) found that ketamine <lb/>modulated a confidence parameter in a reinforcement learning model, which controls the <lb/>degree to which prediction errors influence learning. Confidence might be implicated in the <lb/>brain through a precision-weighting process, where prediction errors are coded as less <lb/>precise when confidence increases, so less is learned from new prediction errors. <lb/>Furthermore, Deserno (et al., 2017) and Powers (et al., 2017) have used hierarchical <lb/>Bayesian models to make inferences about the way individuals with schizophrenia and <lb/>psychosis respectively form beliefs about the environment. Critically in these models a <lb/>prediction error is weighted by the precision of beliefs regarding cue-outcome <lb/>contingencies, and the volatility of these relationships (Mathys et at., 2011 &amp; 2014; Iglesias <lb/>et al., 2013). As such, these models imply precision-weighting of prediction, however they <lb/>do not test the degree to which these prediction errors are precision-weighted explicitly. <lb/>Our results complement these studies and provide an additional direct test of the degree of <lb/>precision weighting of prediction errors in psychosis. <lb/>A previous study has reported differences between healthy controls and individuals with <lb/>schizophrenia in the degree to which they adapt the coding of value to the variability in the <lb/>environment (Kirschner et al., 2016). This process of adaptive coding is similar to precision <lb/>weighting of unsigned prediction errors, as it reflects the brains capacity to scale neural <lb/>signals to what is referred to as economic &apos;risk&apos;, in other words the spread of possible <lb/>reward outcomes. In combination with the present findings, psychotic disorder might be <lb/>associated with a broader failure to adapt neural signals to the statistics of the environment. <lb/>We thus conclude that there is evidence for a diminishment in precision-weighting of <lb/>unsigned prediction errors in individuals with first episode psychosis. This was most strongly <lb/>related to the intensity of the positive symptoms experienced by the patients in this study. <lb/>Our current study provides evidence for a key hypothesis in the field of predictive coding <lb/>theories of psychosis, which is that psychosis is associated with a failure to accurately take <lb/></body>

			<page>2 3 <lb/></page>

			<body>into account the reliability of new information, leading to the formation of aberrant <lb/>inferences about the world, predisposing to delusional beliefs. <lb/>Our findings are in line with the wide literature on adaptive coding of neural signals to <lb/>context. Adaptive coding seems to be a feature of many neural systems (Brenner et al., <lb/>2000; Fairhall et al., 2001; Barlow et al., 1961; Laughlin et al., 1981), ranging from the <lb/>perceptual system (Ohzawa et al., 1982; Smirnakis et al., 1997) to reward systems (Tobler et <lb/>al., 2005; Park et al., 2012). Indeed, previous studies that used the present paradigm have <lb/>framed these questions in terms of adaptive coding of signed reward prediction errors <lb/>rather than precision-weighting of unsigned prediction errors (Diederen et al., 2016 &amp; 2017). <lb/>However, adaptive coding of neural signals to the statistics of the environment follows <lb/>directly from predictive coding models of neural functioning which suggest that prediction <lb/>errors should be weighted by their precision (Srinivasan et al., 1982). Here the adaptive <lb/>coding of prediction errors equals precision-weighting. Therefore, we believe that the <lb/>framework of adaptive coding and precision-weighting do not constitute competing <lb/>interpretations of the data, but rather that adaptive coding is a feature that follows from <lb/>predictive coding models. <lb/>In the present study, no differences were found with regards to the ARMS group. This is in <lb/>line with recent work showing intact cortical prediction error responses in ARMS (Ermakova <lb/>et al., 2018). There might be different reasons for this. First, considering that the effects <lb/>were correlated with severity of symptoms, and the symptoms in the ARMS group were <lb/>significantly lower, the lack of a significant finding for the ARMS group might be a matter of <lb/>severity. Indeed, if we separate the ARMS group and FEP group and correlate the degree of <lb/>precision-weighting with positive symptoms, we find comparable r values for both groups <lb/>(ARMS: r=-.30, FEP: r=-.36), although neither is significant in isolation due to the small N. An <lb/>alternative is that the aberrancies are disease category specific, which could be relevant as <lb/>only a minority of ARMS patients will go on to develop psychotic illness (Morrison et al 2012 <lb/>BMJ). Future studies with more power, ideally including longitudinal follow-up, would clarify <lb/>these issues. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 4 <lb/></page>

			<body>In conclusion, we found evidence of precision-weighted unsigned prediction errors in the <lb/>superior frontal and dorsal anterior cingulate cortices. Furthermore, we found that the <lb/>precision-weighting of prediction errors was modulated by the dopaminergic antagonist <lb/>sulpiride, and we found that the degree of precision-weighting in this area was correlated to <lb/>performance on the task, providing evidence for the first time that dopamine plays a role in <lb/>precision-weighting of unsigned prediction error signals during learning. We demonstrate <lb/>the clinical relevance of the unsigned prediction error signal by showing that it is, as <lb/>predicted, abnormal in psychotic illness, and that it relates to trait levels of schizotypy in the <lb/>healthy population. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 5 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank the staff of the Clinical Research Facility and Wolfson Brain Imaging Centre, <lb/>Cambridge Biomedical Research Centre, Rachel Anderson and Eleanor van Sprang for their <lb/>help in data collection, CAMEO staff for help with recruitment, the participants, and thank <lb/>Wolfram Schultz for his role in designing the experimental paradigm and pharmacological <lb/>study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author roles: J.H.: Conceptualization, methodology, formal analysis, writing (original draft <lb/>preparation, review and editing); P.C.F.: Conceptualization, project administration, funding <lb/>acquisition, writing (review and editing). J.D.G Conceptualization, investigation, <lb/>methodology, project administration. H.T. project administration, implementation, formal <lb/>analysis. T.S. and H.Z. investigation, project administration, writing (review and editing). I.G. <lb/>Conceptualization, investigation, methodology, project administration. K.M.J.D. <lb/>Conceptualization, methodology, project administration, implementation, formal analysis, <lb/>supervision, writing (original draft preparation, review and editing) G.K.M., <lb/>conceptualization, project administration, methodology, supervision, writing (original draft <lb/>preparation, review and editing). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest: P.C.F. has received payments in the past for ad hoc consultancy <lb/>services to GlaxoSmithKline. All other authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding: This work was supported by the Neuroscience in Psychiatry Network, a strategic <lb/>award from the Wellcome Trust to the University of Cambridge and University College <lb/>London (095844/Z/11/Z), Wellcome Trust (093270), Bernard Wolfe Health Neuroscience <lb/>Fund (P.C.F. and H.Z)., and the Niels Stensen Foundation (K.M.J.D). <lb/></div>

			<page>2 6 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Methods <lb/>Table 5: Demographics for dopamine and schizotypy study <lb/>Normative <lb/>Dopamine study <lb/>Placebo <lb/>Sulpiride <lb/>Bromocriptine <lb/>p-value <lb/>N <lb/>27 <lb/>20 <lb/>20 <lb/>19 <lb/>Male <lb/>10 (17) <lb/>9 (11) <lb/>12 (8) <lb/>10 (9) <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Age <lb/>24.2 <lb/>5.4 <lb/>23.9 <lb/>4.8 <lb/>24.8 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>23.7 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>Schizotypy <lb/>16.0 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>16.6 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>15.4 <lb/>11.5 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>11.2 <lb/>p=.99 <lb/>Table 6: Demographics for psychosis study <lb/>Group <lb/>HCS <lb/>ARMS <lb/>FEP <lb/>N <lb/>30 <lb/>24 <lb/>26 <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>p-value <lb/>Age <lb/>22.57 <lb/>3.53 <lb/>21.00 <lb/>3.48 <lb/>24.7 <lb/>4.90 <lb/>p=.007 <lb/>Male <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>21 <lb/>p=.07 <lb/>IQ <lb/>118.8 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>118.7 <lb/>11.65 <lb/>105.8 <lb/>19.8 <lb/>p=.002 <lb/>PANSS positive <lb/>7.20 <lb/>0.76 <lb/>14.00 <lb/>2.97 <lb/>19.27 <lb/>6.45 <lb/>p&lt;.001 <lb/>PANSS negative <lb/>7.23 <lb/>.94 <lb/>13.50 <lb/>6.22 <lb/>15.46 <lb/>8.05 <lb/>p&lt;.001 <lb/>Taking antipsychotic <lb/>medication <lb/>0/30 <lb/>4/24 <lb/>14/26 <lb/>p&lt;.001 <lb/>Antipsychotic dosage <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>55.5 <lb/>64.3 <lb/>328.2 <lb/>181.54 <lb/>p=.010 <lb/>Participants -psychosis study <lb/>Healthy volunteers (HCS, n=30, average 22.6 years, 15 female) without a history of <lb/>psychiatric illness or brain injury were recruited as control subjects. Healthy volunteers did <lb/>not report any personal or family history of neurological, psychiatric or medical disorders. <lb/>Participants with first episode psychosis (FEP, n=26, average 24.8 years, 6 female) or at-risk <lb/>(ARMS, n=24, average 21.5 years, 8 female) were recruited from the Cambridge Early <lb/></div>

			<page>2 7 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">intervention service North and South. In addition, psychosis-prone participants were <lb/>recruited on the basis of belonging to a help-seeking, low-mood, high schizotypy sub-group <lb/>following a latent class analysis on the Neuroscience in Psychiatry Network (NSPN) cohort <lb/>(Davis et al., 2017) or through advertisement via posters displayed at the Cambridge <lb/>University counselling services. at-risk for psychosis were identified by meeting <lb/>At-Risk-Mental-State (ARMS) criteria on the CAARMS interview in the past six months. All <lb/>participants had normal hearing and normal or corrected to normal vision. All participants <lb/>gave written informed consent. The study was approved by the West of Scotland (REC 3) <lb/>ethical committee. See Table 1 for details on demographics and symptom scores. <lb/>Participants -dopamine and schizotypy study <lb/>Healthy volunteers were recruited for a normative study and a pharmacology study <lb/>exploring adaptation of reward prediction errors to context variability (see Diederen et al., <lb/>2016 &amp; 2017). 28 participants were recruited for the normative study (one excluded due to <lb/>scanning issues). A further 63 participants were recruited, of which 4 were excluded due to <lb/>feeling unwell during scanning and/or a failure to complete the paradigm, or side-effects of <lb/>the medication. All participants were recruited via the distribution of flyers in Cambridge and <lb/>advertisements on Gumtree. Drug screenings were all negative. After receiving detailed <lb/>information about the study, all participants gave written informed consent. Schizotypy was <lb/>measured on these participants using the Schizotypal Personality Questionnaire. <lb/>Pharmacological dopaminergic challenge <lb/>Participants received a single dose of the D2-antagonist sulpiride (600mg), the dopamine <lb/>agonist Bromocriptine (2.5 mg), or placebo, in a double-blind fashion. Domperidone was <lb/>added to prevent potential nausea, as it would be an indicative factor of having taken a <lb/>drug, and could thus influence the blinding procedure, as well as making people feel unwell <lb/>(see Diederen et al., 2017 for a detailed description of the dopaminergic manipulation). <lb/>Task design <lb/>During functional (f)MRI data acquisition, participants predicted the magnitude of upcoming <lb/>rewards. Optimal performance on this task required the participant to estimate the mean of <lb/>the distribution from which the rewards were drawn. The task consisted of three sessions of <lb/></div>

			<page>2 8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">10 minutes each. The rewards were drawn from six different pseudo-Gaussian distributions <lb/>that differed with respect to their precision (i.e. inverse variance) and expected value (i.e. <lb/>mean of the distribution; EV). For the dopamine and Schizotypy study, the standard <lb/>deviations from the distributions were 5, 10 &amp; 15, corresponding to precision of .01, .04 and <lb/>.004. For the psychosis study, the standard deviation of the distributions were either 5 or 15, <lb/>corresponding to precision of .01 and .004. Distributions were counterbalanced to ensure <lb/>that the two conditions within each session differed with respect to the EV and precision. <lb/>The conditions were presented in short blocks, each including 4-6 trials. Each distribution <lb/>consisted of 31 trials, which resulted in a total number of trials of 62 per session. The <lb/>participants were informed beforehand that each distribution (of which two per session) had <lb/>a different level of precision, which could be one of three levels: low, medium or high <lb/>precision, corresponding to precisions of 0.004, 0.04 and 0.01 although the exact precisions <lb/>were not revealed to the participants (in the psychosis study there was no medium <lb/>condition). Each trial started with a fixation cross that was presented between 2100 and <lb/>4200ms. The fixation cross was followed by a cue that was presented for 500ms. This cue <lb/>informed the participant from which of two distributions (high, medium or low) in that block <lb/>the upcoming reward was being drawn. After the cue was presented the participants were <lb/>required to predict the magnitude of the upcoming reward. They had 3500ms to make this <lb/>prediction. Making the prediction involved scrolling a mouse ball with their fingers up and <lb/>down, and clicking the left mouse button to state their prediction. This resulted in moving a <lb/>bar up and down the screen on a scale that ranged from 0 to 100. The starting point on the <lb/>bar was randomized throughout the experiment, to ensure that scrolling distance did not <lb/>correlate with participants&apos; predictions. The participants were instructed to minimize the <lb/>prediction error, i.e. the difference between the expected and the actual obtained reward. <lb/>After the prediction, another fixation cross was presented for duration between 2100 and <lb/>5250ms. Thereafter, the obtained reward was presented in addition to the prediction and <lb/>the reward prediction error for 1000ms (see Fig. 7 for an example trial). <lb/>Pay-off <lb/>If the participants would always receive the amount of money drawn by the computer, this <lb/>might have reduced their motivation to reveal their true prediction. Therefore, the <lb/>participants were rewarded according to their accuracy (i.e., proximity to the mean of the <lb/></div>

			<page>2 9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">reward distribution) on 20% of the trials in order to keep them motivated to predict as well <lb/>as possible. <lb/>Behavioural analyses <lb/>Behavioural data was analysed in Matlab. In order to test the performance of the <lb/>participants, we analysed whether the predictions of the participants approached the mean <lb/>of the distribution (or expected value (EV)), during the experiment. We calculated the <lb/>absolute difference between the EV and the prediction in across all trials and averaged <lb/>across the 3 sessions. We computed bonferonni corrected paired t-tests to test the effect of <lb/>precision across and within groups and the differences across groups (see figure 2&amp;5A-E). <lb/>We also tested for an effect of group and precision on average distance across the <lb/>experiment. In addition, we analysed differences in scrolling distance to exclude the <lb/>possibility that drug effects influenced willingness to do the task, resulting in a decrease in <lb/>scrolling distance. We also analysed differences in reaction times and missed trials for the <lb/>same reason. <lb/>Linear regression model <lb/>In order to explore the contribution of signed and unsigned prediction error to learning we <lb/>used a linear regression model with belief-updating as dependent variable and both <lb/>unsigned and signed prediction error as independent variables. Belief updating here is <lb/>defined as the change in value estimate from t n to t n+1 . That is, when the participant expects <lb/>a value of 20 on t 1 and expect as value of 30 on t 2 there was a belief update of 10, which is <lb/>expected to be explained by a prediction error experienced at t 1 . Since signed prediction <lb/>errors, but not unsigned prediction errors inform the participant about the direction of <lb/>learning, we expect the former but not the latter to have a main effect on belief-updating. <lb/>Furthermore, since formal learning models like the Pearce-Hall model (Pearce &amp; Hall, 1980), <lb/>suggest that unsigned prediction errors increase learning, we expect an interaction between <lb/>unsigned and signed prediction error on belief-updating. In order to visualise the effect of <lb/>signed and unsigned prediction errors on belief-updating, we will create bins on the basis of <lb/>signed prediction errors and plot belief-updating on the y-axis. If unsigned prediction errors <lb/>interact with signed prediction error in predicting belief-updating we should expect to see a <lb/>logit or sigmoid relationship between signed prediction error and belief updating. <lb/></div>

			<page>3 0 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Behavioural modelling <lb/>To investigate learning, we fitted several reinforcement learning models to participants&apos; <lb/>prediction sequences. Each model used a common updating rule in which predictions on trial <lb/>n depended on the prediction error and the learning rate on trial n-1: <lb/>y n = y n-1 + k n  n <lb/>Equation 1 <lb/>Here, y n is the prediction made on trial n, k n refers to the learning rate and  n denotes the <lb/>size of the prediction error. This is a standard reinforcement learning model, and allows to <lb/>estimate to which degree prediction errors are being used by the participant by estimating <lb/>the learning rate parameter (Sutton &amp; Barto et al., 1998). <lb/>The first model consisted of a Rescorla-Wagner (RW) reinforcement learning model with a <lb/>fixed learning rate. A fixed learning rate prescribes that each prediction error is weighted <lb/>equally during learning (e.g., independent of whether a prediction error occurred at the <lb/>start, or the end of a session): <lb/>k n =  <lb/>Equation 2 <lb/>The second model consisted of a Pearce-Hall (PH) model with a trial-wise, dynamic, learning <lb/>rate, which prescribes higher weighting of prediction errors (i.e., more learning) at the start <lb/>of a task session compared to later trials (Pearce et al., 1980). In uncertain environments, it <lb/>is more optimal to decrease the weighting of prediction errors as learning progresses (once <lb/>participants become more certain of their predictions) as prediction errors will continue to <lb/>occur as a result of the imposed uncertainty. The PH learning rate decays as trial progress, as <lb/>a function of the previous learning rate and the experienced prediction error, which allows <lb/>for fast updating of predictions at the beginning of each task session: <lb/>k n = +C| n-1 | + (1 -+) k n-1 <lb/>Equation 3 <lb/>in which || is the absolute prediction error, C is an arbitrary scaling coefficient and X is the <lb/>learning rate decay. <lb/></div>

			<page>3 1 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">We additionally explored whether scaling prediction error to the reliability of the <lb/>environment (i.e., precision-weighting) benefitted learning by comparing models that scaled <lb/>the prediction error term and models that did not. We both explored models that simply <lb/>precision-weighted the prediction error by a constant term  (equation 4&amp;5), and models <lb/>that estimated the degree  of precision-weighting for each individual (equation 6). The <lb/>precision here is the true precision, and not the trial-by-trial estimated precision as <lb/>participants were informed prior to the experiment which of the cues indicated the high, <lb/>medium and low variance condition. We estimated both models that had a single estimated <lb/> for both signed and unsigned prediction errors and a model that had a separate variable <lb/>for signed and unsigned prediction errors. In contrast to earlier studies (Diederen et al., <lb/>2015, 2016 &amp; 2017) we used a more simplified model that utilised a linear precision-<lb/>weighted model to ease interpretation. <lb/>y n = y n-1 + k n (/ ) n <lb/>Equation 4 <lb/>k n = +C|( n-1 / )| + (1 -+) k n-1 <lb/>Equation 5 <lb/> = 1-+ *(SD) <lb/>Equation 6 <lb/>For the Pearce-Hall model we explored the scaling of the signed and unsigned prediction <lb/>error separately, as well as combined. <lb/>We fitted the free parameter  to the subjective predictions Y by maximizing the likelihood <lb/>|     | , where  |   ,     , and       . .   are the <lb/>subjective predictions. We used a combination of nonlinear optimization algorithms <lb/>implemented in MATLAB to estimate the free parameters to each participant&apos;s full dataset <lb/>over the trials of all conditions. <lb/>We used the Akaike Information Criterion (AIC) to estimate the model evidence in favour of <lb/>each of the two models. The model with the lowest AIC was used for further analyses. <lb/>fMRI pre-processing steps <lb/>All <lb/>pre-processing steps <lb/>were <lb/>performed <lb/>using SPM8 (available <lb/>at <lb/>http://www.fil.ion.ucl.ac.uk; Wellcome Department of Cognitive Neurology, London, <lb/>England) in combination with the Donders matlab (dmb) toolbox for combining data from <lb/>different echo acquisition times. Data was acquired at 4 different echo times (TE&apos;s) of 12, <lb/></div>

			<page>3 2 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">27,91, 43,82 and 59,73 ms. Corrections for slice timing was not applied considering the <lb/>relatively fast repetition times (TR) of 2100ms. Using SPM8 the functional images were <lb/>realigned first, after which the four different echoes were summed and averaged in order to <lb/>minimize signal intensity inhomogeneity due to differences in T2* relaxation times across <lb/>the brain (Poser et al., 2006). The functional images were subsequently coregistered to the <lb/>T1-weighted anatomical image in native-space by first coregistering one averaged functional <lb/>image, after which the coregistration parameters of this registration were applied to the all <lb/>the functional images in order to registered to native space. Unified segmentation was used <lb/>in order to achieve the normalization of the functional and anatomical images to MNI space <lb/>(Ashburner et al., 2005). Unified segmentation is a single iterative model that combines <lb/>segmentation, bias correction and normalization in order to achieve optimal results. The <lb/>segmentation step was omitted for one of the participants; since it gave erroneous <lb/>segmentation parameters resulting in distortions in the normalized anatomical T1 scan. The <lb/>segmentation step was later conducted using a different template, namely the East-Asian <lb/>template, which resulted in a correct segmentation. Spatial smoothing was performed using <lb/>8mm Gaussian kernels. The time series in each session were high-pas filtered at 128 Hz. <lb/>These pre-processing steps were the same for all studies, with the exception that the patient <lb/>study did not use a multi-echo sequence. <lb/>1 st -level analysis <lb/>fMRI analyses were conducted using SPM8. We used a single statistical linear regression <lb/>model for our main analyses. We modelled for each trial the onset of the cue as an event <lb/>(i.e. a delta function of zero duration), the onset of the prediction event (i.e., when <lb/>participant could start making their prediction) as a single epoch lasting until they indicated <lb/>their prediction. Each event was convolved by the standard canonical haemodynamic <lb/>response function in SPM8. Importantly, we used parametric modulation to identify neural <lb/>correlates of unsigned prediction error responses by specifying for all outcome events the <lb/>unsigned prediction errors. The signed prediction error was not included in the 1 st -level <lb/>model, as it is uncorrelated with unsigned prediction error. The reward events were <lb/>separately modelled for the different precision conditions in order to test for differences in <lb/>precision-weighting of prediction errors as evidences by different sizes of slopes for the <lb/>coding of unsigned prediction errors under different levels of certainty. Contrast were <lb/></div>

			<page>3 3 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">created on the 1 st -level which combined the two EV conditions for each precision condition <lb/>in order to leave a single contrast for each precision conditions which could be taken to the <lb/>2 nd -level (i.e., group-level). <lb/>2 nd -level analysis dopamine study <lb/>For the analysis of the main effect of unsigned prediction errors we first created 1 st -level <lb/>contrast in which we combined the 2 EV&apos;s for each separate precision condition, resulting in <lb/>3 contrasts corresponding to the 3 different precision conditions (high, medium, low). We <lb/>modelled these 3 precision contrasts for each pharmacological condition separately <lb/>specifying the effects to be dependent, and having equal variance. We subsequently tested <lb/>for a main effect of prediction error by doing a positive 2 nd -level contrast on the parametric <lb/>modulators for the unsigned prediction error. <lb/>To test for an effect of precision on the coding of unsigned prediction error and the effect of <lb/>pharmacological group, we extracted the parameter estimates (beta&apos;s) for all precision <lb/>conditions for each medication group separately from the left and right superior frontal <lb/>cortex clusters and dACC cluster surviving FWE&lt;.01 coding unsigned prediction errors; for <lb/>each cluster we used the mean values per cluster per participants in a mixed-2-factor-<lb/>ANOVA with a 3-level within subject factor (high, medium, low) and a 3-level between <lb/>subject factor (medication), and tested for main effect of precision and interaction between <lb/>precision conditions and medication using a mixed-model ANOVA in SPSS (version 21). <lb/>Specifically we used a linear contrast (termed &quot;linear polynomial contrast&quot; by SPSS) across <lb/>precision to examine the main effect of precision and interaction between group and <lb/>precision. When a significant interaction was found we explored this further to see which <lb/>group was driving the interaction. <lb/>2 nd -level analysis psychosis study <lb/>For the analysis of the main effect of unsigned prediction errors we first created 1 st -level <lb/>contrasts in which we combined the 3 EV&apos;s for each separate precision condition, resulting in <lb/>2 contrasts corresponding to the 2 different precision conditions (high, low). We modelled <lb/>these 2 precision contrasts for each pharmacological condition separately specifying the <lb/>effects to be dependent, and having equal variance. We subsequently tested for a main <lb/>effect of prediction error by doing a positive 2 nd -level contrast on the parametric modulators <lb/></div>

			<page>3 4 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">for the unsigned prediction error. We tested for a main effect of precision by doing a 2 nd -<lb/>level contrast on the two precision conditions. A small volume correction was implemented <lb/>as follows: these tests were performed wholebrain uncorrected &lt;.005, after which we used <lb/>an ROI on the basis of the peak coordinates of the dopamine study [27 8 54] in form of a <lb/>10mm sphere, which was used to do a small-volume correction. We subsequently tested for <lb/>differences in precision-weighting by creating a 1 st -level contrast which subtracted the low-<lb/>precision condition from the high-precision condition as a measure of precision-weighting. <lb/>On 2 nd -level we contrasted precision-weighting in the ARMS and FEP group against the HC <lb/>group to test for significant differences in precision-weighting, again at &lt;.005 uncorrected, <lb/>after which we used the same ROI to test for differences in precision-weighting. <lb/>2 nd -level analysis schizotypy study <lb/>In order to test for a relationship between schizotypy and precision-weighting of prediction <lb/>error, we extracted the betas from the precision-weighting contrast from a cluster which <lb/>showed a significant main effect of unsigned prediction error at FWE&lt;.01 in the dopamine <lb/>study (which is the same criteria used for testing the effect of medication). In addition we re-<lb/>analysed an existing normative data-set consisting of 27 healthy controls (pre-processing <lb/>and 1 st level analysis is the same as in the dopamine study). We used an ROI (10mm sphere) <lb/>based on the peak-voxel of the dopamine study [27 8 54], and tested for a main effect of <lb/>prediction error at FWE&lt;.01. Again we subtracted from these voxels the betas reflecting <lb/>precision-weighting. Subsequently we used a general linear model to test for a relationship <lb/>between SPQ scores and the extracted precision-weighting betas whilst controlling for <lb/>medication group and study. <lb/>Data availability: the data analysed in this study are available from the corresponding <lb/>author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<page>3 5 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary results <lb/>Study 1: Dopamine study <lb/>Environmental precision and D2 antagonism modulate task performance. <lb/>First, we explored whether performance increases when environmental precision is high (i.e. <lb/>when the standard deviation of rewarding outcomes is low). We measured performance by <lb/>investigating how close participants&apos; predictions were to the actual mean of the distribution <lb/>on average (i.e., the average difference between the mean of the reward distribution). We <lb/>used a two-factor mixed model ANOVA with medication group as the between-subjects <lb/>variable and precision conditions as the within-subjects variable, using a linear contrast <lb/>across precision conditions for the main effect of precision and interaction between <lb/>precision and medication. We found that performance increased when the precision <lb/>increased (F{1,56}=11.3, p=.001), but there was no significant interaction between precision <lb/>and medication group (F{2,56}=1.3, p=.27). However, there was a trend-level effect of group <lb/>on average final performance (F{2,56}=2.5, p=.094). Post-hoc tests indicated reduced overall <lb/>performance in the sulpiride group compared to placebo (F{1,38}=5.10, p=.030), but no <lb/>significant interaction with precision (F{1,38}=.18, p=.68). Comparing the bromocriptine <lb/>group to placebo there was no significant overall difference (F{1,37}=2.01, p=.17) and no <lb/>significant interaction (F{1,37}=1.70, p=.20) (See Fig.2). <lb/>Elimination of possible confounding by effects on motivation <lb/>Since dopamine also plays an important role in motivation, we explored whether the <lb/>dopaminergic manipulation influenced measures of motivation, such as response times <lb/>(Crespi, 1942; Niv, 2007), how much the participants moved the mouse ball to state their <lb/>prediction (Fig. 3B; see methods section for more detail), and the number of missed trials <lb/>(Fig. 3D). Using one-way ANOVAs, we found that only response times were significantly <lb/>different across medication groups, with the sulpiride group being faster than placebo (RT: <lb/>F{2,55}=4.21, p=.019; Misses: F{2,55}=0.33, p=.72; Scrolling distance: F{2,55}=0.56, p=.57; <lb/>Fig. 3B-D). Differences in response times remained significant when controlling for scrolling <lb/>distance: F{2,55}=3.32, p=.044. More rapid reactions in the sulpiride condition render it <lb/>unlikely that any performance deficit secondary to sulpiride could be driven by motivational <lb/>impairments. In the clinical psychosis study we also tested for differences in reaction times, <lb/></div>

			<page>3 6 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">scrolling distance, and missed trials, to see whether there could have been motivational <lb/>and/ or motor/movement differences between groups. Using one-way ANOVA&apos;s, we found <lb/>that none of these measures were different across groups (RT: F{2,75}=1.77, p=.17; Misses: <lb/>F{2,75}=0.1, p=.91; Scrolling distance: F{2,75}=0.12, p=.89) (Figure 2I-K). <lb/>Unsigned and signed prediction errors contribute to belief updating <lb/>In order to explore whether signed and unsigned prediction errors contribute to learning, we <lb/>fitted a simple regression model to the behavioural data, where the extent of learning, <lb/>defined as the change in predicted reward from a trial to the next, was the dependent <lb/>variable and signed and unsigned prediction errors were the independent variables. Signed <lb/>prediction errors are defined in this task as the signed difference between predicted and <lb/>received reward. Unsigned prediction errors are defined as the absolute difference between <lb/>predicted and received reward. Both of these prediction errors can be observed directly in <lb/>our task, and thus in contrast to many other experimental paradigms, do not have to be <lb/>inferred as a latent variable using a modelling procedure. We expected a main effect of <lb/>signed prediction error on learning, but not of unsigned prediction as the former informs the <lb/>participants about the direction of belief updating, whereas the latter does not, and can <lb/>therefore not drive learning directly. However, Pearce-Hall reinforcement learning models <lb/>suggest that unsigned prediction errors increase the amount of attention devoted to a <lb/>stimulus. Thus we expect that when unsigned prediction errors are high, the effect of signed <lb/>prediction errors on learning is higher. That is, we expect there to be an interaction between <lb/>unsigned and signed prediction errors. In line with this expectation, we found a significant <lb/>interaction between signed and unsigned prediction errors (F{1,10763}=51.7, p&lt;.0001), <lb/>suggesting that learning is a function of both the signed and unsigned prediction error. In <lb/>addition, we observed a significant effect of signed prediction errors on learning <lb/>(F{1,10763}=246.95, p&lt;.0001), whereas the effect of unsigned prediction errors was <lb/>insignificant (F{1,10763}=.95, p=.33). We furthermore tested whether the precision <lb/>condition interacted with signed prediction errors on belief updating. Although there was no <lb/>main-effect of precision (F{2,10761}=.25, p=.78), there was indeed a significant interaction <lb/>between precision and signed prediction error (F{2,10761}=25.8, p&lt;.0001). The significant <lb/>interaction between signed and unsigned prediction errors predicts a pseudo logit-function <lb/>amplifying the contribution of signed prediction error on belief updating when the unsigned <lb/></div>

			<page>3 7 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">prediction errors are highest (i.e. when signed prediction errors are highly positive or highly <lb/>negative). To visualise the interaction between signed and unsigned prediction error we <lb/>binned signed prediction errors and plotted learning on the y-axis (Fig.4A). We indeed find <lb/>the predicted pseudo-logit shape between the relationship between signed prediction errors <lb/>and learning such that the line is steeper when signed prediction errors are higher, indicating <lb/>that unsigned prediction errors contribute to learning in addition to signed prediction errors. <lb/>We furthermore visualised the effect of precision, where we see that signed prediction <lb/>errors have a stronger effect on learning in the high precision condition compared to low <lb/>precision condition (Fig. 4B). The significant interaction predicts a stronger effect of signed <lb/>prediction error on belief updating in the high precision condition compared to the low <lb/>precision condition. We thus conclude that signed prediction errors contribute more to <lb/>learning when reward information is more precise. <lb/>Supplementary Figure 1: Here we show the relationship between signed prediction errors (x-axis) and belief-updating (y-<lb/>axis) collapsed for the high, medium, and low precision conditions (A) and separate for high and low precision (B) (The <lb/>medium precision condition is not plotted for clarity purposes). The shaded area is one standard error of the mean. In A <lb/>the interaction effect between unsigned prediction error and signed prediction is shown (above the top and below the <lb/>bottom dotted line unsigned prediction errors are strongest, amplifying the effect of the signed prediction error). In B the <lb/>effect of precision is shown, revealing a stronger effect of signed prediction error in the high precision condition <lb/>compared to low precision. <lb/>Secondary outcome variable analyses <lb/>In addition to the analyses we conducted in our primary regions of interest, i.e. SFC and <lb/>dACC, we also tested for an interaction between precision conditions and medication in the <lb/>remainder of clusters that coded unsigned prediction errors. There were no significant <lb/></div>

			<page>3 8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">precision by medication interactions: superior occipital cortex cluster, (F{2,56}=1.60, p=.21), <lb/>larger parietal cluster (F{2,56}=.82, p=.45), smaller parietal cluster (F{2,56}=1.53, p=.23). <lb/>Study 2: Psychosis study <lb/>No evidence for an effect of antipsychotic medication on precision-weighting in patients <lb/>We found no significant difference between FEP participants who take antipsychotic <lb/>medication and those who do not in terms of precision weighting of the prediction error <lb/>(T{18}=.14, p=.89; analysis conducted on voxels that showed a group difference). There was <lb/>no significant relationship between anti-psychotic medication dosage and degree of <lb/>precision-weighting in the 14 participants who took antipsychotic medications (r=.17, p=.52). <lb/></div>

			<page>3 9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Adams, R. A., Stephan, K. E., Brown, H. R., Frith, C. D., &amp; Friston, K. J. (2013). The computational anatomy of <lb/>psychosis. Frontiers in Psychiatry, 4(May), 47. <lb/>Ashburner, J., &amp; Friston, K. J. (2005). Unified segmentation. Neuroimage, 26(3), 839-851. <lb/>Bar, M. (2009). Predictions: a universal principle in the operation of the human brain. <lb/>Barlow, H. B. (1961). Possible principles underlying the transformations of sensory messages. <lb/>Bastos, A. M., Usrey, W. M., Adams, R. A., Mangun, G. R., Fries, P., &amp; Friston, K. J. (2012). Canonical <lb/>microcircuits for predictive coding. Neuron, 76(4), 695-711. <lb/>Berger, B., Gaspar, P., &amp; Verney, C. (1991). Dopaminergic innervation of the cerebral cortex: unexpected <lb/>differences between rodents and primates. Trends in neurosciences, 14(1), 21-27. <lb/>Brenner, N., Bialek, W., &amp; Van Steveninck, R. D. R. (2000). Adaptive rescaling maximizes information <lb/>transmission. Neuron, 26(3), 695-702. <lb/>Clark, A. (2013). Whatever next? Predictive brains, situated agents, and the future of cognitive science. <lb/>Behavioral and Brain Sciences, 36(3), 181-204. <lb/>Clark, A. (2015). Surfing uncertainty: Prediction, action, and the embodied mind. Oxford University Press. <lb/>Courville, A. C., Daw, N. D., &amp; Touretzky, D. S. (2006). Bayesian theories of conditioning in a changing world, <lb/>10(7). <lb/>Cools, R., &amp; D&apos;Esposito, M. (2011). Inverted-U-shaped dopamine actions on human working memory and <lb/>cognitive control. Biological psychiatry, 69(12), e113-e125. <lb/>Corlett, P. R., Murray, G. K., Honey, G. D., Aitken, M. R. F., Shanks, D. R., Robbins, T. W.,  Fletcher, P. C. (2007). <lb/>Disrupted prediction-error signal in psychosis: Evidence for an associative account of delusions. Brain, <lb/>130(9), 2387-2400. <lb/>Corlett, P. R., Honey, G. D., &amp; Fletcher, P. C. (2007). From prediction error to psychosis: ketamine as a <lb/>pharmacological model of delusions. Journal of Psychopharmacology (Oxford, England), 21(3), 238-252. <lb/>Crespi LP: Quantatative variation of incentive and performance in the white rat. American Journal of <lb/>Psychology. 1942, 55: 467-517. 10.2307/1417120. <lb/>D&apos;ardenne, K., McClure, S. M., Nystrom, L. E., &amp; Cohen, J. D. (2008). BOLD responses reflecting dopaminergic <lb/>signals in the human ventral tegmental area. Science, 319(5867), 1264-1267. <lb/>Den Ouden, H. E., Friston, K. J., Daw, N. D., McIntosh, A. R., &amp; Stephan, K. E. (2008). A dual role for prediction <lb/>error in associative learning. Cerebral cortex, 19(5), 1175-1185. <lb/>Den Ouden, H. E., Kok, P., &amp; De Lange, F. P. (2012). How prediction errors shape perception, attention, and <lb/>motivation. Frontiers in psychology, 3. <lb/>Diederen, K. M. M. J., Spencer, T., Vestergaard, M. D. D., Fletcher, P. C. C., &amp; Schultz, W. (2016). Adaptive <lb/>Prediction Error Coding in the Human Midbrain and Striatum Facilitates Behavioral Adaptation and <lb/>Learning Efficiency. Neuron, 90(5), 1127-1138. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 0 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Diederen, K. M. J., &amp; Schultz, W. (2015). Scaling prediction errors to reward variability benefits error-driven <lb/>learning in humans. Journal of Neurophysiology, 114(3), 1628-1640. <lb/>Diederen, K. M. J., Ziauddeen, H., Vestergaard, M. D., Spencer, T., Schultz, W., &amp; Fletcher, P. C. (2017). <lb/>Dopamine Modulates Adaptive Prediction Error Coding in the Human Midbrain and Striatum. Journal of <lb/>Neuroscience, 37(7), 1708-1720. <lb/>Esber, G. R., Roesch, M. R., Bali, S., Trageser, J., Bissonette, G. B., Puche, A. C., ... &amp; Schoenbaum, G. (2012). <lb/>Attention-related Pearce-Kaye-Hall signals in basolateral amygdala require the midbrain dopaminergic <lb/>system. Biological psychiatry, 72(12), 1012-1019. <lb/>Fairhall, A. L., Lewen, G. D., Bialek, W., &amp; van Steveninck, R. R. D. R. (2001). Efficiency and ambiguity in an <lb/>adaptive neural code. Nature, 412(6849), 787. <lb/>Fletcher, P. C., Anderson, J. M., Shanks, D. R., Honey, R., Carpenter, T. A., Donovan, T., ... &amp; Bullmore, E. T. <lb/>(2001). Responses of human frontal cortex to surprising events are predicted by formal associative <lb/>learning theory. Nature neuroscience, 4(10), 1043. <lb/>Fletcher, P. C., &amp; Frith, C. D. (2009). Perceiving is believing: a Bayesian approach to explaining the positive <lb/>symptoms of schizophrenia. Nature Reviews. Neuroscience, 10(1), 48-58. <lb/>Ford, C. P. (2014). The role of D2-autoreceptors in regulating dopamine neuron activity and <lb/>transmission. Neuroscience, 282, 13-22. <lb/>Fouragnan, E., Queirazza, F., Retzler, C., Mullinger, K. J., &amp; Philiastides, M. G. (2017). Spatiotemporal neural <lb/>characterization of prediction error valence and surprise during reward learning in humans, (May), 1-18. <lb/>Fouragnan, E., Retzler, C., &amp; Philiastides, M. G. (2018). Separate neural representations of prediction error <lb/>valence and surprise: Evidence from an fMRI meta-analysis. Human brain mapping. <lb/>Fresnoza, S., Stiksrud, E., Klinker, F., Liebetanz, D., Paulus, W., Kuo, M. F., &amp; Nitsche, M. A. (2014). Dosage-<lb/>dependent effect of dopamine D2 receptor activation on motor cortex plasticity in humans. Journal of <lb/>Neuroscience, 34(32), 10701-10709. <lb/>Friston, K. (2009). The free-energy principle: a rough guide to the brain?. Trends in cognitive sciences, 13(7), <lb/>293-301. <lb/>Friston, K. J., Stephan, K. E., Montague, R., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2014). Computational psychiatry: The brain as a <lb/>phantastic organ. The Lancet Psychiatry. <lb/>Friston, K., Schwartenbeck, P., FitzGerald, T., Moutoussis, M., Behrens, T., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2014). The anatomy of <lb/>choice: dopamine and decision-making. Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B, 369(1655), 20130481. <lb/>Function, M., &amp; Wiley, J. (1991). Dopaminergic innervation of the cerebral cortex: unexpeded differences <lb/>between rodents and primates, (1966), 35-39. <lb/>Hall, G., &amp; Pearce, J. M. (1982). Restoring the associability of a pre-exposed CS by a surprising event. The <lb/>Quarterly Journal of Experimental Psychology Section B, 34(3b), 127-140. <lb/>Hayden, B. Y., Heilbronner, S. R., Pearson, J. M., &amp; Platt, M. L. (2011). Surprise Signals in Anterior Cingulate <lb/>CortexN: Neuronal Encoding of Unsigned Reward Prediction Errors Driving Adjustment in Behavior, <lb/>31(11), 4178-4187. <lb/>Hohwy, J. (2013). The predictive mind. Oxford University Press. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 1 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Howes, O. D., &amp; Kapur, S. (2009). The dopamine hypothesis of schizophrenia: version III-the final common <lb/>pathway. Schizophrenia bulletin, 35(3), 549-562. <lb/>IBM Corp. Released 2012. IBM SPSS Statistics for Macintosh, Version 21.0. Armonk, NY: IBM Corp. <lb/>Ide, J. S., Shenoy, P., Yu, A. J., &amp; Li, C. R. (2013). Bayesian Prediction and Evaluation in the Anterior Cingulate <lb/>Cortex, 33(5), 2039-2047. <lb/>Kvernmo, T., Houben, J., &amp; Sylte, I. (2008). Receptor-binding and pharmacokinetic properties of dopaminergic <lb/>agonists. Current topics in medicinal chemistry, 8(12), 1049-1067. <lb/>Laughlin, S. (1981). A simple coding procedure enhances a neuron&apos;s information capacity. Zeitschrift fr <lb/>Naturforschung c, 36(9-10), 910-912. <lb/>Lewis, D. A., Campbell, M. J., Foote, S. L., Goldstein, M., &amp; Morrison, J. H. (1987). The distribution of tyrosine <lb/>hydroxylase-immunoreactive fibers in primate neocortex is widespread but regionally specific. Journal of <lb/>Neuroscience, 7(1), 279-290. <lb/>Li, J., Schiller, D., Schoenbaum, G., Phelps, E. A., &amp; Daw, N. D. (2011). Differential roles of human striatum and <lb/>amygdala in associative learning. Nature neuroscience, 14(10), 1250. <lb/>Mathys, C., Daunizeau, J., Friston, K. J., &amp; Stephan, K. E. (2011). A Bayesian foundation for individual learning <lb/>under uncertainty. Frontiers in human neuroscience, 5, 39. <lb/>Metereau, E., &amp; Dreher, J. C. (2012). Cerebral correlates of salient prediction error for different rewards and <lb/>punishments. Cerebral Cortex, 23(2), 477-487. <lb/>Murray, G. K., Corlett, P. R., Clark, L., Pessiglione, M., Blackwell, a D., Honey, G.,  Fletcher, P. C. (2008). <lb/>Substantia nigra/ventral tegmental reward prediction error disruption in psychosis. Molecular Psychiatry, <lb/>13(3), 239, 267-276. <lb/>Murray, G. K., Corlett, P. R., &amp; Fletcher, P. C. (2010). The neural underpinnings of associative learning in health <lb/>and psychosis: how can performance be preserved when brain responses are abnormal?. Schizophrenia <lb/>bulletin, 36(3), 465-471. <lb/>Newman-Tancredi, A., Cussac, D., Quentric, Y., Touzard, M., Verrile, L., Carpentier, N., &amp; Millan, M. J. (2002). <lb/>Differential actions of antiparkinson agents at multiple classes of monoaminergic receptor. III. Agonist <lb/>and antagonist properties at serotonin, 5-HT1 and 5-HT2, receptor subtypes. Journal of Pharmacology <lb/>and Experimental Therapeutics, 303(2), 815-822. <lb/>Niv Y: Cost, benefit, tonic, phasic: what do response rates tell us about dopamine and motivation?. Ann N Y <lb/>Acad Sci. 2007, 1104: 357-376. 10.1196/annals.1390.018. <lb/>O&apos;Doherty, J. P., Dayan, P., Friston, K., Critchley, H., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2003). Temporal difference models and <lb/>reward-related learning in the human brain. Neuron, 38(2), 329-337. <lb/>O&apos;Doherty, J., Dayan, P., Schultz, J., Deichmann, R., Friston, K., &amp; Dolan, R. J. (2004). Dissociable roles of ventral <lb/>and dorsal striatum in instrumental conditioning. science, 304(5669), 452-454. <lb/>Ohzawa, I., Sclar, G., &amp; Freeman, R. D. (1982). Contrast gain control in the cat visual cortex. Nature, 298(5871), <lb/>266. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 2 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Park, S. Q., Kahnt, T., Talmi, D., Rieskamp, J., Dolan, R. J., &amp; Heekeren, H. R. (2012). Adaptive coding of reward <lb/>prediction errors is gated by striatal coupling. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, <lb/>201119969. <lb/>Paus, T. (2001). Primate anterior cingulate cortex: where motor control, drive and cognition interface. Nature <lb/>reviews neuroscience, 2(6). <lb/>Pearce, J. M., &amp; Hall, G. (1980). A model for Pavlovian learning: variations in the effectiveness of conditioned <lb/>but not of unconditioned stimuli. Psychological review, 87(6), 532. <lb/>Pessiglione, M., Seymour, B., Flandin, G., Dolan, R. J., &amp; Frith, C. D. (2006). Dopamine-dependent prediction <lb/>errors underpin reward-seeking behaviour in humans. Nature, 442(7106), 1042. <lb/>Poser, B. a., Versluis, M. J., Hoogduin, J. M., &amp; Norris, D. G. (2006). BOLD contrast sensitivity enhancement and <lb/>artifact reduction with multiecho EPI: Parallel-acquired inhomogeneity-desensitized fMRI. Magnetic <lb/>Resonance in Medicine, 55(6), 1227-1235. <lb/>Rao, R. P. N., &amp; Ballard, D. H. (1999). Predictive coding in the visual cortex: a functional interpretation of some <lb/>extra-classical receptive-field effects. Nature Neuroscience, 2(1), 79-87. <lb/>Rescorla, R. A., &amp; Wagner, A. R. (1972). A theory of Pavlovian conditioning: Variations in the effectiveness of <lb/>reinforcement and nonreinforcement. Classical conditioning II: Current research and theory, 2, 64-99. <lb/>Roesch, M. R., Esber, G. R., Li, J., Daw, N. D., &amp; Schoenbaum, G. (2012). Surprise! Neural correlates of Pearce-<lb/>Hall and Rescorla-Wagner coexist within the brain. European Journal of Neuroscience, 35(7), 1190-1200. <lb/>Schultz, <lb/>W., <lb/>Dayan, <lb/>P., <lb/>&amp; <lb/>Montague, <lb/>P. <lb/>R. <lb/>(1997). <lb/>A <lb/>neural <lb/>substrate <lb/>of <lb/>prediction <lb/>and <lb/>reward. Science, 275(5306), 1593-1599. <lb/>Smirnakis, S. M., Berry, M. J., Warland, D. K., Bialek, W., &amp; Meister, M. (1997). Adaptation of retinal processing <lb/>to image contrast and spatial scale. Nature, 386(6620), 69. <lb/>Srinivasan, M. V., Laughlin, S. B., &amp; Dubs, A. (1982). Predictive coding: a fresh view of inhibition in the <lb/>retina. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B, 216(1205), 427-459. <lb/>Sutton, R. S. (1988). Learning to predict by the methods of temporal differences. Machine learning, 3(1), 9-44. <lb/>Sutton, R. S., &amp; Barto, A. G. (1998). Reinforcement learning: An introduction (Vol. 1, No. 1). Cambridge: MIT <lb/>press. <lb/>Tian, J., Huang, R., Cohen, J. Y., Osakada, F., Kobak, D., Machens, C. K., ... &amp; Watabe-Uchida, M. (2016). <lb/>Distributed and mixed information in monosynaptic inputs to dopamine neurons. Neuron, 91(6), 1374-<lb/>1389. <lb/>Tobler, P. N., Fiorillo, C. D., &amp; Schultz, W. (2005). Adaptive coding of reward value by dopamine <lb/>neurons. Science, 307(5715), 1642-1645. <lb/>Turner, D. C., Aitken, M. R., Shanks, D. R., Sahakian, B. J., Robbins, T. W., Schwarzbauer, C., &amp; Fletcher, P. C. <lb/>(2004). The role of the lateral frontal cortex in causal associative learning: exploring preventative and <lb/>super-learning. Cerebral Cortex, 14(8), 872-880. <lb/>Wang, J., &amp; O&apos;donnell, P. (2001). D1 dopamine receptors potentiate NMDA-mediated excitability increase in <lb/>layer V prefrontal cortical pyramidal neurons. Cerebral Cortex, 11(5), 452-462. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
