<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>PHi-C: deciphering Hi-C data into polymer dynamics <lb/>Soya Shinkai 1,2 * , Masaki Nakagawa 2,3 , Takeshi Sugawara 2,4 , Yuichi Togashi 2,5,6 , Hiroshi <lb/>Ochiai 5,7 , Ryuichiro Nakato 8 , Yuichi Taniguchi 7,9 &amp; Shuichi Onami 1 * <lb/>1 Laboratory for Developmental Dynamics, RIKEN Center for Biosystems Dynamics Research, <lb/>Kobe, Hyogo, Japan. <lb/>2 Research Center for the Mathematics on Chromatin Live Dynamics, Hiroshima University, <lb/>Higashi-hiroshima, Hiroshima, Japan. <lb/>3 Graduate School of Informatics and Engineering, The University of Electro-Communications, <lb/>Chofu, Tokyo, Japan. <lb/>4 Graduate School of Medicine and Faculty of Medicine, The University of Tokyo, Bunkyo-ku, <lb/>Tokyo, Japan. <lb/>5 Graduate School of Science, Hiroshima University, Higashi-hiroshima, Hiroshima, Japan. <lb/>6 Laboratory for Cell Field Structure, RIKEN Center for Biosystems Dynamics Research, Higashi-<lb/>hiroshima, Hiroshima, Japan. <lb/>7 PRESTO, Japan Science and Technology Agency, Kawaguchi, Saitama, Japan. <lb/>8 Institute for Quantitative Biosciences, The University of Tokyo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo, Japan. <lb/>9 Laboratory for Cell Systems Control, RIKEN Center for Biosystems Dynamics Research, Suita, <lb/>Osaka, Japan. <lb/> * e-mail: soya.shinkai@riken.jp; sonami@riken.jp <lb/> 1 <lb/> Computational modelling methods for Hi-C data have revealed averaged and static features <lb/>of the 3D genome in cell nuclei. Here, we describe a 4D simulation method, PHi-C (Polymer <lb/> dynamics deciphered from Hi-C data), that depicts dynamic 3D genome features through <lb/>polymer modelling. This method allows for demonstrations of dynamic characteristics of <lb/>genomic loci and chromosomes, as observed in live-cell imaging experiments, and provides <lb/>physical insights into Hi-C data. <lb/></front>

			<body>Genomes consist of one-dimensional DNA sequences and are spatio-temporally organized <lb/>within the cell nucleus. Contact frequencies in the form of matrix data, measured using genome-<lb/>wide chromosome conformation capture (Hi-C) technologies, have uncovered three-dimensional <lb/>(3D) features of average genome organization in a cell population 1, 2 . Moreover, live-cell imaging <lb/>experiments can reveal dynamic chromatin organization in response to biological perturbations <lb/>within single cells 3, 4 . Bridging the gap between these different sets of data derived from population <lb/>and single cells is a challenge for modelling dynamic genome organization 5, 6 . <lb/>Several modelling methods have been developed to reconstruct 3D genome structures and <lb/>predict Hi-C data 7, 8 . In addition, there has been development of bioinformatic normalization <lb/>techniques in Hi-C matrix data processing to reduce experimental biases 9-11 . However, the mean-<lb/>ing of a contact matrix as quantitative probability data has not been discussed; moreover, a four-<lb/>dimensional (4D) simulation method to explore dynamic 3D genome organization remains lacking. <lb/>Here, we introduce PHi-C, a method that can overcome these challenges by polymer mod-<lb/>elling from a mathematical perspective and at low computational cost. PHi-C is a method that <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>deciphers Hi-C data into polymer dynamics simulations (Fig. 1a, https://github.com/ <lb/>soyashinkai/PHi-C). PHi-C uses Hi-C contact matrix data generated from a hic file through <lb/>JUICER 12 as input (Supplementary Fig. 1a). PHi-C assumes that a genomic region of interest at <lb/>an appropriate resolution can be modelled using a polymer network model, in which one monomer <lb/>corresponds to the genomic bin size of the contact matrix data with attractive and repulsive interac-<lb/>tion parameters between all pairs of monomers described as matrix data (Methods, Supplementary <lb/>Note). Instead of finding optimized 3D conformations, we can utilize the optimization procedure <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 1b,c) to obtain optimal interaction parameters of the polymer network model <lb/>by using an analytical relationship between the parameters and the contact matrix. We can then <lb/>reconstruct an optimized contact matrix validated by input Hi-C matrix data using Pearson&apos;s cor-<lb/>relation r. Finally, we can perform polymer dynamics simulations of the polymer network model <lb/>equipped with the optimal interaction parameters. <lb/>First, we evaluated PHi-C&apos;s theoretical assumption about chromosome contact. Here, we <lb/>started with a simple polymer model called the bead-spring model, in which the characteristic <lb/>length b between adjacent beads (or monomers) represents the physical size corresponding to one <lb/>genomic bin of the contact matrix data. To mathematically define the contact between a pair of <lb/>monomers, we introduced the contact Gaussian kernel with the contact distance σ (Fig. 1b). The <lb/>above assumption can be used to derive the theoretical scaling relationship of the contact probabil-<lb/>ity, P (s) ∼ s −d f /3 , as a function of genomic distance s in terms of the fractal dimension of polymer <lb/>organization d f <lb/>13 (Supplementary Fig. 2a,b). In addition, interestingly, the ratio of the contact dis-<lb/>tance to the length between adjacent monomers, σ/b, makes the shape of the contact probability <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>rounder at a small genomic distance (Supplementary Fig. 2b). This phenomenon implies that the <lb/>rounded shape conveys information about the ratio σ/b. To assess our theoretical framework about <lb/>contact and how the contact distance varies in Hi-C experiments, we analysed yeast Hi-C data at <lb/>nucleosome resolution 14 . The fitted value was σ/b = 1.12, suggesting that contacts mainly occur <lb/>within a distance corresponding to the size of a nucleosome in this super-resolution Hi-C experi-<lb/>ment (Fig. 1c, Supplementary Fig. 2c). Other high-resolution Hi-C data for human GM12878 10 <lb/>revealed σ/b = 1.38, suggesting that cross-linking of Hi-C experiments almost exactly captures <lb/>chromosome contacts with an appropriate resolution (Supplementary Fig. 2d). <lb/>An important step in the optimization procedure is based on analytical matrix transforma-<lb/>tions between the polymer network model and the contact matrix (Fig. 1d, Methods). The matrix <lb/>transformations provided us with a low computational cost optimization strategy that can be ap-<lb/>plied to find optimal interaction parameters of the polymer network model without sampling op-<lb/>timal static 3D polymer conformations (Supplementary Fig. 1b,c). Moreover, we can depict any <lb/>contact patterns in a moment by using the matrix transformations and perform polymer dynamics <lb/>simulations by designing interactions in the polymer network model (Fig. 1e-g, Supplementary <lb/>Videos 1-3). Intra-and inter-domain interactions generate a chequerboard pattern reminiscent of <lb/>A/B compartments 1, 2 , and the attractive interaction domains form a combined domain (Fig. 1e). <lb/>Loop interactions show a clear punctate pattern (Fig. 1f). Furthermore, we can depict a topolog-<lb/>ically associating domain (TAD)-like pattern 1, 2 by only tuning heterogeneous connectivity along <lb/>the polymer backbone, where less connected regions behave as domain boundaries (Fig. 1g; left). <lb/>The 3D conformation suggests that the boundary regions are physically elongated with insulat-<lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>ing inter-TAD-like-domain interactions. In addition, the removal of a boundary part causes the <lb/>adjacent domain fusion (Fig. 1g; right) that reminds us of fusions of TADs 8, 15 . <lb/>To investigate how PHi-C explains 4D features of chromosomes within living cells, we ap-<lb/>plied this approach to Hi-C data for mouse embryonic stem cells (mESCs) 16 . A live-cell imaging <lb/>experiment showed a marked difference in the movements of Nanog and Oct4 loci in mESCs 17 : <lb/>statistically significant enhancement of Nanog diffusive movement compared with Oct4 diffusive <lb/>movement was revealed (Supplementary Fig. 3). The optimization step of the PHi-C analysis <lb/>for chromosomes 6 and 17 provided optimized contact matrices with correlations of more than <lb/>97% between the Hi-C and optimized contact matrices (Fig. 2a). The mean-squared displacement <lb/>(MSD) curves that were theoretically derived from the optimized data for the Nanog locus on chro-<lb/>mosome 6 and the Oct4 locus on chromosome 17 are consistent with the experimental dynamics <lb/>(Fig. 2b). We also compared the physical sizes of 50.5-Mb genomic regions around the Nanog and <lb/>Oct4 loci, with the inclusion of several areas that highly interact with each locus, and observed <lb/>more compact organization of the Nanog region (Fig. 2c). Taking together, these findings indicate <lb/>that PHi-C analysis can provide new insights into genome organization and dynamics: for exam-<lb/>ple, a region of 50.5 Mb around Nanog adopts a more compact organization than an equivalent <lb/>region around Oct4, and the Nanog locus on chromosome 6 is more mobile than the Oct4 locus on <lb/>chromosome 17 (Fig. 2d). <lb/>Finally, we used PHi-C to demonstrate the dynamic chromosome condensation process for <lb/>the highly synchronous entry of DT-40 cells, which revealed a pathway for mitotic chromosome <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>formation 18 . The optimized contact matrices at five different time points were reconstructed with <lb/>high correlations (Fig. 2e, Supplementary Fig. 4). Using the optimized interaction parameters in <lb/>the polymer network model (Supplementary Fig. 5), we conducted 4D simulations starting from a <lb/>comparatively elongated conformation at 0 min. The polymer conformation dynamically changed <lb/>into a rod-shaped structure, revealing the condensation state of chromosomes at prometaphase <lb/>(Fig. 2f, Supplementary Videos 4, 5). We evaluated dynamic changes in polymer conformations <lb/>in simulations by calculating the characteristic shape lengths of the major and minor axes. As <lb/>observed by microscopy, rapid and gradual decreases in the minor and major axes within 15 and <lb/>60 min indicated thin and thick rod-shaped formations, respectively (Fig. 2g). In addition, the <lb/>optimized interaction parameters averaged at each genomic separation represent not only strong <lb/>compaction within 2 Mb during mitosis but also increase of periodicity of long-range attractive <lb/>interactions from 3 Mb to 12 Mb in prometaphase (Fig. 2h). These physical findings are consistent <lb/>with a helical organization in rod-shaped chromosomes during prometaphase 18 . <lb/>We have shown that PHi-C can decipher Hi-C data into polymer dynamics, based on a math-<lb/>ematical theory of chromosome contacts in the polymer network model. As shown for mESC <lb/>Hi-C data, PHi-C analysis can bridge the gap between Hi-C data and imaging data with respect <lb/>to chromatin dynamics in living cells. In addition, PHi-C&apos;s theoretical basis allows for the de-<lb/>piction of any Hi-C pattern by designing the appropriate interaction parameters, which supports <lb/>a model for TAD formation: physical chromatin stiffness based on certain molecular interactions <lb/>creates insulation at TAD boundaries 19 . Polymer modelling studies have revealed that chromatin <lb/>modifications alter the physical properties of chromatin fibres and affect chromosome organiza-<lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>tion 11, 20 . Because PHi-C analysis can extract physical interaction parameters from Hi-C data, it <lb/>should be elucidated which molecular interactions on chromatin are related to physical parameters. <lb/>Further comprehensive PHi-C analysis could provide physical insights into molecular interactions <lb/>on chromosomes. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Dekker, J., Marti-Renom, M. A. &amp; Mirny, L. A. Nat. Rev. Genet. 14, 390-403 (2013). <lb/>2. Bonev, B. &amp; Cavalli, G. Nat. Rev. Genet. 17, 661-678 (2016). <lb/>3. Nozaki, T. et al. Mol. Cell 67, 282-293 (2017). <lb/>4. Hauer, H. M. et al. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 24, 99-107 (2017). <lb/>5. Marti-Renom, M. A. &amp; Mirny, L. A. PLoS Comput. Biol. 7, e1002125 (2011). <lb/>6. Fudenberg, G. &amp; Imakaev, M. Nat. Methods 14, 673-678 (2017). <lb/>7. Serra, F. et al. FEBS Lett. 589, 2987-2995 (2015). <lb/>8. Bianco, S. et al. Nat. Genet. 50, 662-667 (2018). <lb/>9. Imakaev, M. et al. Nat. Methods 9, 999-1003 (2012). <lb/>10. Rao, S. et al. Cell 159, 1665-1680 (2014). <lb/>11. Serra, F. et al. PLoS Comput. Biol. 13, e1005665 (2017). <lb/>12. Durand, N. C. et al. Cell Systems 3, 95-98 (2016). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13. Shinkai, S. et al. PLoS Comput. Biol. 12, e1005136 (2016). <lb/>14. Ohno, M. et al. Cell, 176, 520-534.e25 (2019). <lb/>15. Lupiáñez, D. G. et al. Cell 161, 1012-1025 (2015). <lb/>16. Bonev, B. et al. Cell 171, 557-572 (2017). <lb/>17. Ochiai, H., Sugawara, T. &amp; Yamamoto, T. Nucleic Acids Res. 43, e127 (2015). <lb/>18. Gibcus, J. H. et al. Science 359, eaao6135 (2018). <lb/>19. Dixon, J. R., Gorkin, D. B. &amp; Ren, B. Mol. Cell 62, 668-680 (2016). <lb/>20. Di Pierro, M. et al. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 114, 12126-12131 (2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments We thank K. Shiroguchi and K. Kinoshita for helpful comments. We thank M. Marti-<lb/>Renom and M. Di Stefano for stimulative discussions. We thank I. Hiratani for critical reading of this <lb/>manuscript. We also thank Nature Research Editing Service for English language editing. This work was <lb/>supported by JSPS KAKENHI Grant Numbers 16H01408 and 18H04720 (to S.S.). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions S.S., M.N. and T.S. conceived the mathematical concept to define the chromosome <lb/>contacts. S.S. and S.O. designed the study. S.O. supervised the study. S.S., M.N. and T.S. performed <lb/>mathematical calculations. S.S. and Y.To. developed the optimization algorithm. S.S. and Y.To. wrote the <lb/>codes. S.S., R.N. and Y.Ta. analysed the Hi-C data. S.S. and H.O. analysed the movements of genome loci. <lb/>S.S. wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Financial Interests The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Methods <lb/>Overview of PHi-C. PHi-C enables us to decipher Hi-C data into polymer dynamics simulation. <lb/>PHi-C is based on a theory of the polymer network model and defining contacts between two <lb/>monomers on the polymer (Supplementary Note). The theoretical framework provides the follow-<lb/>ing matrix transformations (Fig. 1d), where the matrix size is N ×N : (i) the normalized interaction <lb/>matrix K = σ 2 <lb/>3k B T (k ij ) = <lb/>( <lb/>kij <lb/>) <lb/>into the normalized Laplacian matrix L = σ 2 <lb/>3k B T (L ij ) by L = D− K, <lb/>where the normalized degree matrix D = diag <lb/>( <lb/>D0 , D1 , • • • , DN−1 <lb/>) <lb/>, where Di = <lb/>∑ N −1 <lb/>j=0 kij , (ii) L <lb/>into the normalized covariant matrix relative to the centre-of-mass M = 3k B T <lb/>σ 2 (M ij ) = <lb/>( <lb/>Mij <lb/>) <lb/>by <lb/>M = Q diag <lb/>( <lb/>0, λ−1 <lb/>1 , λ−1 <lb/>2 , • • • , λ−1 <lb/>N −1 <lb/>) <lb/>Q T , where 0 = λ0 &lt; λ1 ≤ λ2 ≤ • • • ≤ λN−1 are eigenval-<lb/>ues of the matrix L and Q is the orthogonal matrix satisfying Q T LQ = diag <lb/>( <lb/>0, λ1 , λ2 , • • • , λN−1 <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(iii) M into the normalized variance matrix Σ2 = <lb/>( <lb/>Σ 2 <lb/>ij /σ 2 <lb/>) <lb/>= <lb/>([ <lb/>Mii + Mjj − 2 Mij <lb/>] <lb/>/3 <lb/>) <lb/>, and (iv) <lb/>Σ2 into the contact matrix C = (C ij ) = <lb/>( <lb/>1 + Σ2 <lb/>) −3/2 <lb/>. The matrix K describing attractive and <lb/>repulsive interactions of the polymer network model is optimized so that the difference between <lb/>an input Hi-C contact matrix C Hi−C and the reconstructed contact matrix C reconstructed , through the <lb/>above transformations, is minimized. Finally, a 4D simulation of the polymer network model with <lb/>the optimized matrix Koptimized is performed. Below, we describe each step in Fig. 1a in detail. <lb/>Input data. PHi-C requires N × N contact matrix data for a genomic region of interest as an <lb/>input, which is generated through the JUICER and JUICER TOOLS 12 from public Hi-C data <lb/>with a normalization option (VC / VC SQRT / KR). Here, we used the KR normalization 21 . In <lb/>our theoretical framework, the diagonal elements of the contact matrix should satisfy C ii = 1, so <lb/></div>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">we additionally normalized the contact matrix such that the shape of the contact probability as a <lb/>function of genomic distance P (s) is unaltered, with an interpolation if needed (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 1a). Note that the interpolation may result in artefacts for sparse contact matrix data. Finally, <lb/>we obtained a normalized Hi-C contact matrix C Hi−C . <lb/>Optimization and validation. The optimization algorithm is designed to minimize the Frobenius <lb/>norm || log 10 C reconstructed − log 10 C Hi−C || F as a cost function, where the contact matrix C reconstructed <lb/>is generated from the normalized interaction matrix K. At every optimization step, an integer <lb/>pair (i, j) is randomly selected, and the values of kij and kji are slightly altered. If the alteration <lb/>decreases the cost function, the matrix K is updated. A flowchart of the algorithm is presented in <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 1b. <lb/>As our optimization method is based on the random sampling of integer pairs, the amount of <lb/>calculation in the procedure is proportional to O (N 2 ). In our demo codes, the hyper-parameters for <lb/>the optimization are tuned, and it takes about 13 min to obtain an optimized solution for N = 97, <lb/>even on our laptop PC (Intel R <lb/>⃝ CoreTM i7-6600U, dual-core 2.60GHz). <lb/>After optimization, an optimized contact matrix C optimized is converted from an optimized <lb/>matrix Koptimized . To assess the compatibility between contact matrices C optimized and C Hi−C in a <lb/>logarithmic scale, we used Pearson&apos;s correlation coefficient. <lb/>Polymer dynamics simulation. We performed 4D simulations of the polymer network model <lb/>by using the normalized interaction matrix K. First, K = <lb/>( <lb/>kij <lb/>) <lb/>is converted into the normal-<lb/></div>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">ized Laplacian matrix L. Using the eigendecomposition of the matrix L, the normalized eigen-<lb/>values <lb/>{ <lb/>λp <lb/>} N −1 <lb/>p=0 <lb/>and the orthogonal matrix Q are obtained. For a normalized polymer confor-<lb/>mation vector Rα = <lb/>( <lb/>R 0,α <lb/>σ , R 1,α <lb/>σ , • • • , <lb/>R N −1,α <lb/>σ <lb/>) T <lb/>, where R i,α stands for the α (= x, y, z) coordi-<lb/>nate of the i-the monomer, the converted vector Xα = Q T <lb/>Rα satisfies the variance relationship <lb/>⟨ <lb/>X2 <lb/>p,α <lb/>⟩ <lb/>= 1/(3 λp ) for p = 1, 2, • • • , N − 1. Therefore, an initial conformation of the converted <lb/>vector in thermal equilibrium is given: X0,α | t=0 = 0, so that the centre-of-mass is the origin, and <lb/>Xp,α | t=0 is a random variable obeying the normal distribution with mean 0 and variance 1/(3 λp ) for <lb/>p = 1, 2, • • • , N −1. Then, the initial normalized conformation in thermal equilibrium is calculated <lb/>as Rα | t=0 = Q Xα | t=0 . Finally, to calculate the polymer dynamics, we numerically integrated the <lb/>stochastic differential equation (SDE) by using Heun&apos;s method 22 : the integral algorithm is defined <lb/>by first predicting <lb/>Rα | t = −3 ϵ L Rα | t + <lb/>√ <lb/>2ϵ ξ α , <lb/>(1) <lb/>and then correcting <lb/>Rα | t+ϵ = −3 ϵ <lb/>L Rα | t + Rα | t <lb/>2 <lb/>+ <lb/>√ <lb/>2ϵ ξ α , <lb/>(2) <lb/>where ϵ = k B T ∆t <lb/>γσ 2 <lb/>and the vector ξ α = (ξ 0,α , ξ 1,α , • • • , ξ N −1,α ) T consists of random variables <lb/>{ξ i,α } N −1 <lb/>i=0 obeying the normal distribution with mean 0 and variance 1. The parameter ϵ is non-<lb/>dimensional and represents a normalized step time, and it determines the accuracy of the SDE <lb/>integration. ∆t stands for the step time of the integration in actual time. Here, we set ϵ = 0.0001. <lb/>Visualization of polymer conformation. The code for polymer dynamics simulation outputs XYZ <lb/>and PSF files to visualize the simulated polymer dynamics. Polymer conformations were visual-<lb/>ized using VMD 23 by reading these files. <lb/></div>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Fitting contact probability. We theoretically derived how the contact probability as a function <lb/>of genomic distance averaged across the genome, P (s), behaves in terms of the fractal polymer <lb/>(Supplementary Note, Supplementary Fig. 2). The function from high-resolution Hi-C data was <lb/>fitted by <lb/>P (s) = <lb/>( <lb/>1 + <lb/>1 <lb/>3(σ/b) 2 <lb/>( s <lb/>c <lb/>) 2/d f <lb/>) −3/2 <lb/>(3) <lb/>for a small genomic region and <lb/>P (s) ∼ s −3/d f <lb/>(4) <lb/>for a large genomic region. Here, the ratio σ/b and the fractal dimension d f are the fitted parame-<lb/>ters, and c stands for the genomic size corresponding to the bin size of the Hi-C matrix. We used <lb/>the nonlinear least-squares Marquardt-Levenberg algorithm on GNUPLOT. <lb/>Calculating MSD of genome loci. We re-analysed movements of Nanog and Oct4 loci in mESCs. <lb/>In each session of live imaging, 3D time-series of a genome locus (Nanog or Oct4) and the nucleus <lb/>centre-of-mass, <lb/>{ <lb/>S locus (t m ) <lb/>} M −1 <lb/>m=0 <lb/>and <lb/>{ <lb/>S nucleus (t m ) <lb/>} M −1 <lb/>m=0 <lb/>, were simultaneously acquired 17 , where <lb/>the maximum frame number was M = 50, the time interval was ∆t = 10 s, and t m = m ∆t <lb/>(m = 0, 1, 2, • • • , M − 1). To eliminate the effect of movement of the nucleus, we dealt with <lb/>movements of the locus relative to the nucleus centre described by the time-series {S(t m )} M −1 <lb/>m=0 = <lb/>{ <lb/>S locus (t m ) − S nucleus (t m ) <lb/>} M −1 <lb/>m=0 <lb/>. Then, the time-averaged mean square displacement (TAMSD) <lb/>for a time-series {S(t m )} M −1 <lb/>m=0 was calculated as follows: <lb/>TAMSD(t m ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>M − m <lb/>M −1−m ∑ <lb/>i=0 <lb/>[S(t m+i ) − S(t i )] 2 . <lb/>(5) <lb/></div>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Calculating theoretical MSD curve. The optimized matrix Koptimized derives a theoretical MSD <lb/>curve for the i-th monomer in the polymer network model as follows (Supplementary Note): <lb/>MSD(t; i)/σ 2 = <lb/>6 <lb/>N <lb/>(ϵt/∆t) + 2 <lb/>N −1 <lb/>∑ <lb/>p=1 <lb/>Q 2 <lb/>ip <lb/>λ−1 <lb/>p <lb/>( <lb/>1 − e −3 λp(ϵt/∆t) <lb/>) <lb/>. <lb/>(6) <lb/>Here, not only is the MSD normalized by σ 2 in the length scale, but the time-step is also normalized <lb/>in time, that is, MSD/σ 2 and ϵt/∆t are dimensionless. <lb/>Calculating radius of gyration. As we described in polymer dynamics simulation, a normalized <lb/>polymer conformation <lb/>{ <lb/>Ri = ( Ri,x , Ri,y , Ri,z ) <lb/>} N −1 <lb/>i=0 <lb/>in thermal equilibrium can be sampled on the <lb/>basis of the optimized matrix Koptimized . We calculated the radius of gyration for the 50.5-Mb <lb/>genomic regions around Nanog and Oct4 loci in mESCs. By using two integers n start and n end <lb/>corresponding to the 50.5-Mb region, the radius of gyration is calculated as <lb/>Rg = <lb/>1 <lb/>n end − n start + 1 <lb/>n end <lb/>∑ <lb/>i=nstart <lb/>( <lb/>Ri − RG <lb/>) 2 <lb/>, <lb/>(7) <lb/>where RG = <lb/>1 <lb/>n end −nstart+1 <lb/>∑ n end <lb/>i=nstart Ri represents the centre-of-mass of the polymer conformation <lb/>of the 50.5-Mb genomic region. <lb/>Simulating polymer dynamics during chromosome condensation. We applied PHi-C to Hi-C <lb/>data during mitotic chromosome formation in chicken DT-40 cells 18 . We used the second dataset <lb/>of chromosome 7 (binned at 100 kb) for the wild type at G2 (0 min), 5, 15, 30 and 60 min. We elim-<lb/>inated the centromere region due to the lack of associated read counts. Through the optimization of <lb/>PHi-C, we obtained the optimized matrices K0 , K500 , K1500 , K3000 and K6000 , respectively (Supple-<lb/>mentary Fig. 5). To simulate the polymer dynamics during chromosome condensation, we linearly <lb/></div>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">interpolated the matrices <lb/>{ <lb/>Kn <lb/>} 6000 <lb/>n=0 <lb/>at n <lb/>100 min as follows: Kn = K0 + ( K500 − K0 ) × n <lb/>500 for 0 ≤ n &lt; <lb/>500, Kn = K500 +( K1500 − K500 )× n−500 <lb/>1000 for 500 ≤ n &lt; 1500, Kn = K1500 +( K3000 − K1500 )× n−1500 <lb/>1500 <lb/>for 1500 ≤ n &lt; 3000, and Kn = K3000 + ( K6000 − K3000 ) × n−3000 <lb/>3000 for 3000 ≤ n ≤ 6000. By using <lb/>K0 , an initial polymer conformation was sampled. Then, the polymer dynamics between n <lb/>100 min <lb/>and n+1 <lb/>100 min was calculated by 1000 steps of numerical integration with Kn based on the integral <lb/>algorithm (equations (1) and (2)). <lb/>In the visualization, we fixed the centre-of-mass of polymer conformations to the origin (Fig. <lb/>2f, Supplementary Videos 4, 5). <lb/>Calculating shape length of polymer conformation. To quantify the characteristic shape of a <lb/>polymer conformation <lb/>{ <lb/>Rα <lb/>} <lb/>α=x,y,z <lb/>during chromosome condensation, we evaluated the character-<lb/>istic shape lengths as an ellipsoidal conformation based on the gyration tensor G = 1 <lb/>N <lb/>( <lb/>Rα • Rβ <lb/>) <lb/>. <lb/>We calculated the three eigenvalues g 2 <lb/>1 ≤ g 2 <lb/>2 ≤ g 2 <lb/>3 of the tensor G. Then, we adopted g 3 and <lb/>√ <lb/>(g 2 <lb/>1 + g 2 <lb/>2 )/2 as the characteristic shape lengths of the major and minor axes, respectively (Fig. <lb/>2g). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Code availability. Python codes of PHi-C are available at https://github.com/soyashinkai/ <lb/>PHi-C/Codes. Scripts to generate data and the figures shown in Fig. 1a can be found at <lb/>https://github.com/soyashinkai/PHi-C/Demos. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability. Published publicly available Hi-C data were used in this study: Ohno et al. 14 <lb/>(PRJNA427106), Rao et al. 10 (GSE63525), Bonev et al. 16 (GSE96107), and Gibcus et al. 18 <lb/></div>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<div type="availability">(GSE102740). Input Hi-C matrix data of PHi-C were generated through the JUICER and JUICER <lb/>TOOLS 12 . <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>21. Knight, P. &amp; Ruiz, D. IMA J. of Numer. Anal. 33, 1029-1047 (2013). <lb/>22. Sekimoto, K. Stochastic Energetics (Springer-Verlag Berlin Heidelberg, 2010). <lb/>23. Humphrey, W., Dalke, A. &amp; Schulten, K. J. Mol. Graph. 14, 33-38 (1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure legends <lb/>Figure 1: Features of PHi-C. a, Overview of PHi-C procedure. b, (Upper) In the bead-spring <lb/>model, the probability density of the distance r ij between the i-th and j-th beads (or monomers) <lb/>is characterized by only the standard deviation Σ ij . (Lower) The contact Gaussian kernel function <lb/>can capture contacts with the contact distance σ. c, Contact probability (blue) for yeast cells with <lb/>160-bp nucleosome-resolution 14 as a function of genomic distance averaged across the genome, <lb/>and the theoretically fitted curve (orange) at a small genomic distance. d, The polymer network <lb/>model is characterized by connectivity between all pairs of monomers, expressed by the interac-<lb/>tion matrix k ij . The matrix k ij is reversibly converted into the contact matrix C ij through matrix <lb/>transformations. Each matrix has dimensionless values with a normalization factor. e-g, Painting <lb/>contact patterns for intra-and inter-domain interactions (e), loop interactions (f), and heteroge-<lb/>neous connectivity along the polymer backbone (g). (Upper) Designed interactions in the polymer <lb/>network model. (Lower) Converted contact matrix, with a snapshot of polymer conformations in <lb/>the polymer dynamics simulation (Supplementary Videos 1-3). g, TAD-like domains are high-<lb/>lighted by dashed lines. (Right) Removal of a domain-boundary part (yellow) results in domain <lb/>fusion. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2: Demonstrations of PHi-C for Hi-C data of mESCs and DT-40 cells. a, PHi-C anal-<lb/>ysis for chromosomes 6 (left) and 17 (right) of mESCs. (Upper) Contact matrices of the Hi-C <lb/>experiment (binned at 500 kb), and contact probabilities as a function of genomic distance. (Mid-<lb/>dle) 4C-like profiles of Nanog (left) and Oct4 (right) loci. High-interaction regions are highlighted <lb/>(pink). (Lower) Optimized contact matrices by PHi-C, and correlation plots between log 10 C Hi−C <lb/>and log 10 C Optimized . b, Theoretical MSD curves of Nanog and Oct4 loci. c, Probability densities <lb/>of the gyration radius of 10 5 conformations for the 50.5-Mb genomic regions around Nanog and <lb/>Oct4 loci in mESCs. d, Polymer models derived from PHi-C analysis for Nanog and Oct4 loci on <lb/>chromosomes 6 and 17, respectively. Pink-highlighted regions on the polymer models correspond <lb/>to the regions in the 4C-like profile of a. e, PHi-C analysis for chromosome 7 of DT-40 cells at G2 <lb/>(0 min), 5, 15, 30 and 60 min. Contact matrices of the Hi-C experiment with 100-kb-sized bins <lb/>(upper) and optimized contact matrices with the correlation value (lower). f, Snapshots of poly-<lb/>mer conformations in a 4D polymer dynamics simulation. g, Time series of the shape lengths of <lb/>the major (yellow) and minor (purple) axes for polymer conformations in 100 polymer dynamics <lb/>simulations starting from the same initial conformation. Thick curves represent the averages. h, <lb/>Curves of optimized interaction parameters, <lb/>⟨ <lb/>kij <lb/>⟩ <lb/>, averaged at each genomic distance (separation, <lb/>|i − j| × 100 kb). A triangle indicates a position of a local peak inducing compaction within 2 Mb. <lb/>Arrows indicate positions of a local peak generating periodicity of attractive interactions around 4, <lb/>6 and 10 Mb at 15, 30 and 60 min, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
