<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Title: Pax9 is required for cardiovascular development and interacts with Tbx1 in the <lb/>pharyngeal endoderm to control 4 th pharyngeal arch artery morphogenesis. <lb/>Running Title: Tbx1 and Pax9 interact in arch artery morphogenesis. <lb/>Helen M. Phillips 1 , Catherine A. Stothard 1 , Wasay Mohiuddin Shaikh Qureshi 1,8 , Anastasia I. <lb/>Kousa 2 , J. Alberto Briones-Leon 1,9 , Ramada R. Khasawneh 1,10 , Rachel Sanders 1,11 , Silvia <lb/>Mazzotta 1,12 , Rebecca Dodds 1 , Kerstin Seidel 1,13 , Timothy Bates 3,14 , Mitsushiro Nakatomi 1,15 , <lb/>Simon J. Cockell 4 , Jürgen E. Schneider 5 , Timothy J. Mohun 6 , René Maehr 7 , Ralf Kist 1,3 , <lb/>Heiko Peters 1 &amp; Simon D. Bamforth 1, * <lb/>1 Institute of Genetic Medicine, Newcastle University, Newcastle-upon-Tyne, NE1 3BZ, UK. <lb/>2 Memorial Sloan Kettering Cancer Center, NY 10065, USA. <lb/>3 School of Dental Sciences, Newcastle University, Newcastle-upon-Tyne, NE2 4BW, UK. <lb/>4 Bioinformatics Support Unit, Newcastle University, Newcastle-upon-Tyne, NE2 4HH, UK. <lb/>5 Biomedical Imaging, University of Leeds, Leeds, LS2 9JT, UK. <lb/>6 The Francis Crick Institute, London, NW1 1AT, UK. <lb/>7 Diabetes Center of Excellence, University of Massachusetts Medical School, MA 01605, <lb/>USA. <lb/>8 Current address: School of Biological Sciences, University of Manchester, Manchester, <lb/>M13 9PT, UK. <lb/>9 Current address: Cambridge Healthcare Research, Cambridge, CB4 0WS, UK. <lb/>10 Current address: Yarmouk University, Irbid, Jordan. <lb/>11 Current address: The Queen&apos;s Medical Research Institute, University of Edinburgh, EH16 <lb/>4TJ, UK. <lb/>12 Current address: TC BioPharm Limited, Motherwell, ML1 4WR, UK. <lb/>13 Current address: Genentech Inc., South San Francisco, CA 94080, USA. <lb/>14 Current address: Queen Elizabeth Hospital, Birmingham, B15 2GW, UK. <lb/>15 Current address: Kyushu Dental University, Kitakyushu, 803-8580, Japan. <lb/>*Author for correspondence (simon.bamforth@newcastle.ac.uk) <lb/>Key words: pharyngeal endoderm, arch artery development, Tbx1, Pax9, neural crest, <lb/>genetics <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Author contributions <lb/>CAS, WMSQ, JABL, RRK, RS, SM, RD, TB, RK: performed experiments <lb/>AIK, SC: performed RNA-seq data analysis <lb/>KS, MN, RM, RK, HP: created the Pax9Cre mouse <lb/>JES, TJM: generated imaging data <lb/>HMP, RK, HP: supervised the project and critiqued the manuscript <lb/>SDB: conceived and planned the experiments, supervised the project, analysed the data, <lb/>created figures and wrote the manuscript <lb/>Summary statement <lb/>Pax9 is required for outflow tract and aortic arch development, and functions together with <lb/>Tbx1 in the pharyngeal endoderm for 4 th arch artery formation. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Developmental defects affecting the heart and aortic arch arteries are a key phenotype <lb/>observed in DiGeorge syndrome patients and are caused by a microdeletion on <lb/>chromosome 22q11. Heterozygosity of TBX1, one of the deleted genes, is expressed <lb/>throughout the pharyngeal arches and is considered a key component for the arch artery <lb/>defects. Pax9 is expressed in the pharyngeal endoderm and is downregulated in Tbx1 <lb/>mutant mice. We show here that Pax9 deficient mice are born with complex cardiovascular <lb/>malformations affecting the outflow tract and aortic arch arteries with failure of the 3 rd and 4 th <lb/>pharyngeal arch arteries to form correctly. Transcriptome analysis indicated that Pax9 and <lb/>Tbx1 may function together, and mice double heterozygous for Tbx1/Pax9 presented with a <lb/>significantly increased incidence of interrupted aortic arch when compared to Tbx1 <lb/>heterozygous mice. Using a novel Pax9Cre allele we demonstrated that the site of this Tbx1-<lb/>Pax9 genetic interaction is in the pharyngeal endoderm, therefore revealing that a <lb/>Tbx1/Pax9-controlled signalling mechanism emanating from the pharyngeal endoderm is <lb/>required for critical tissue interactions during normal morphogenesis of the pharyngeal arch <lb/>artery system. <lb/></front>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Conotruncal heart malformations, affecting the outflow tract and aortic arch arteries, occur in <lb/>30% of all cases of congenital heart defects (Thom et al., 2006) and are a major cause of <lb/>morbidity and death. Approximately 20% of foetuses identified with conotruncal defects by <lb/>ultrasound are diagnosed with 22q11 deletion syndrome (22q11DS) (Boudjemline et al., <lb/>2001), the most common microdeletion syndrome with an incidence of 1:4000 live births <lb/>(Scambler, 2000). Patients typically have a 3Mb deletion on chromosome 22 that <lb/>encompasses 45 protein coding genes (Morrow et al., 2018) and ~80% of patients present <lb/>with some form of congenital cardiovascular defect (Momma, 2010), of which one of the <lb/>most common observed is interruption of the aortic arch (Unolt et al., 2018). Although <lb/>clinically rare in the general population, approximately 50% of all cases of interrupted aortic <lb/>arch occur in 22q11DS patients (Boudjemline et al., 2001; Lewin et al., 1997; Van Mierop <lb/>and Kutsche, 1986). Interrupted aortic arch is a consequence of the left 4 th pharyngeal arch <lb/>artery (PAA) failing to form correctly during embryonic development. There are five pairs of <lb/>PAA that arise within a series of repeated protuberances on either side of the developing <lb/>pharynx known as the pharyngeal arches. These arches consist of paraxial mesoderm-and <lb/>neural crest cell (NCC)-derived mesenchyme, and are externally enclosed by ectoderm and <lb/>internally lined by endoderm (Graham, 2003). The initially bilaterally symmetrical PAA <lb/>develop sequentially in a cranial to caudal sequence during embryogenesis but undergo a <lb/>complex remodelling process that is conserved in mammals to form the asymmetrical <lb/>mature aortic arch configuration (Bamforth et al., 2013; Hiruma et al., 2002). Of the genes <lb/>deleted in 22q11DS, hemizygosity of TBX1 is considered to be the cause of the <lb/>cardiovascular defects seen in these patients (Jerome and Papaioannou, 2001; Lindsay et <lb/>al., 2001; Merscher et al., 2001). Tbx1 is expressed throughout the pharyngeal arches within <lb/>the ectoderm, endoderm and mesoderm cells and is critical for pharyngeal arch and PAA <lb/>development. Complete loss of Tbx1 from the mouse results in a failure of the pharyngeal <lb/>arches to form correctly resulting in hypoplasia of the second arch and aplasia of the <lb/>remaining caudal arches, leading to an absent thymus and common arterial trunk (Jerome <lb/>and Papaioannou, 2001; Merscher et al., 2001). In contrast, heterozygous deletion of Tbx1 <lb/>only affects development of the 4 th PAA resulting in interruption of the aortic arch in a <lb/>minority of mice with aberrant right-subclavian artery observed more frequently (Lindsay et <lb/>al., 2001). Although almost all 22q11DS patients are hemizygous for the deletion, the <lb/>phenotypic spectrum is highly variable (Unolt et al., 2018), thus it has been proposed that <lb/>genes outside of the deleted region may impact on the clinical phenotype (Guo et al., 2011). <lb/>Several genes have been identified as potential modifiers of 22q11DS as determined by <lb/>genetic interaction studies and transcriptome analyses in Tbx1 mutant mice (Aggarwal and <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Morrow, 2008; Ivins et al., 2005; Liao et al., 2008; Papangeli and Scambler, 2013). One such <lb/>candidate gene is Pax9 whose expression in the pharyngeal endoderm was found to be <lb/>significantly reduced in Tbx1-deficient embryos (Ivins et al., 2005; Liao et al., 2008), <lb/>although further investigations into the nature of any putative interaction have not been <lb/>reported. Pax9 belongs to a family of Pax genes encoding for transcription factors involved <lb/>in various cellular roles during embryonic development (Chi and Epstein, 2002; Mansouri et <lb/>al., 1996) and is specifically expressed in the endoderm of all four pharyngeal pouches of <lb/>the mouse by E9.5 (Neubuser et al., 1995). At later stages in mouse development, Pax9 is <lb/>expressed in the oesophagus, somites and limbs, and within the neural crest contributing to <lb/>craniofacial development (Peters et al., 1998). Embryos deficient for Pax9 exhibit <lb/>craniofacial defects, including cleft secondary palate as well as absent teeth, skeletal <lb/>defects, and lack derivatives of the 3 rd and 4 th pharyngeal pouches, i.e. the thymus, <lb/>parathyroids and ultimobranchial bodies (Peters et al., 1998) yet the role of Pax9 in <lb/>cardiovascular development has not been determined. <lb/>In this study we have investigated cardiovascular development in Pax9-deficient mice, and <lb/>show that loss of Pax9 leads to complex cardiovascular defects affecting the outflow tract <lb/>and aortic arch arteries. We also uncover a strong genetic interaction between Tbx1 and <lb/>Pax9 that leads to 4 th PAA-derived defects in double heterozygous mice, and this interaction <lb/>is cell-autonomous within the pharyngeal endoderm. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>Pax9-deficient embryos have cardiovascular defects. <lb/>Mice lacking Pax9 die perinatally and exhibit craniofacial, pharyngeal gland and skeletal <lb/>defects (Peters et al., 1998). A cleft secondary palate had initially been suggested as a <lb/>cause for postnatal lethality of Pax9-deficient mice, however, recent observations showed <lb/>that ~1% of Pax9 -/-mice have an intact secondary palate but still die shortly after birth (data <lb/>not shown). We therefore carefully re-analysed Pax9 -/-neonates from a Pax9 +/-intercross to <lb/>identify the cause of death. When dissected, we found that all Pax9 -/-neonates had a <lb/>patterning defect of their aortic arch arteries which included an interrupted aortic arch with <lb/>aberrant right subclavian artery (Fig. 1B; Table 1). To investigate these defects in more <lb/>detail we processed Pax9 -/-embryos for histology and magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) <lb/>and found that Pax9 -/-embryos presented with a wide range of cardiovascular abnormalities <lb/>(Fig. 1C-Q; Table 1). These defects included perimembranous ventricular septal defect <lb/>(VSD), double-outlet right ventricle with interventricular communication, interruption of the <lb/>aortic arch and aberrant right subclavian artery. The common carotid arteries were also <lb/>frequently absent resulting in unilateral or bilateral internal and external carotids arising <lb/>directly from the dorsal aorta and the aberrant right subclavian artery. Pax9 -/-embryos also <lb/>had a hypoplastic aorta (Fig. 1M-O) and bicuspid aortic valves (Fig. 1Q). <lb/>Developmental defects of the arch arteries occur when the PAA fail to form or remodel <lb/>correctly. To investigate the morphogenesis of the PAA we performed high-resolution <lb/>episcopic microscopy (HREM) on E10.5 and E11.5 Pax9 -/-embryos and manually <lb/>segmented the datasets to create 3-D images of the PAA. Analysis of E10.5 coronal <lb/>sections revealed that the 3 rd and 4 th pharyngeal arches of Pax9 -/-embryos were smaller <lb/>compared to Pax9 +/+ controls (Fig. 2A-C), as previously reported (Peters et al., 1998). At <lb/>E10.5 the developing PAA are bilaterally symmetrical, having formed in a cranial to caudal <lb/>sequence. The 1 st and 2 nd PAA have normally regressed by this stage, and the 3 rd , 4 th and <lb/>6 th PAA are present (Bamforth et al., 2013; Hiruma et al., 2002) (Fig. 2A). In Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos the 1 st and 2 nd PAA were abnormally persistent, the 3 rd PAA was either absent, <lb/>hypoplastic or interrupted, and the 4 th PAA was absent (Fig. 2B, C; Table 2). The aortic sac <lb/>was also hypoplastic in Pax9 -/-embryos compared to the controls (Fig. 2B, C). Intra-cardiac <lb/>injection of India ink at E10.5-E11.0 showed that, in controls, the caudal PAA were patent to <lb/>ink and of equivalent size (Fig. 2D). In Pax9 -/-embryos, however, persisting 1 st and 2 nd PAA <lb/>were patent to ink, and the 3 rd PAA were hypoplastic (Fig. 2J -L) or non-patent to ink, and <lb/>therefore presumed absent. The majority of the 4 th PAA were bilaterally non-patent to ink <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Fig. 2J -L; Table 2). Immunohistochemical staining for Pecam1 showed that the <lb/>endothelium within the 3 rd and 4 th pharyngeal arches had formed lumenised PAA at E10.5 in <lb/>control embryos (Fig. 2G), but in Pax9 -/-embryos the 3 rd PAA was visibly smaller in size and <lb/>only isolated endothelial cells were seen within the 4 th pharyngeal arch (Fig. 2H, I). <lb/>During E11.5 of mouse development, the PAA system begins to remodel and becomes <lb/>asymmetric in appearance (Bamforth et al., 2013; Hiruma et al., 2002). In Pax9 control <lb/>embryos at this stage the right 6 th PAA appeared thinner and the distal outflow tract was <lb/>septated. The carotid duct, the region of the dorsal aorta between the 3 rd and 4 th PAA, had <lb/>begun to involute but the 3 rd , 4 th and 6 th PAA remained connected to the dorsal aortae (Fig. <lb/>3A). In Pax9 -/-embryos at E11.5, evidence of presumed persisting 1 st or 2 nd PAA were <lb/>observed extending anteriorly from the aortic sac, and the 3 rd PAA were also affected, either <lb/>unilaterally or bilaterally, and were either absent, hypoplastic or interrupted and not <lb/>connected to the dorsal aortae (Fig. 3B-D). The carotid ducts were maintained, and this, <lb/>coupled with the abnormal detachment of the 3 rd PAA from the dorsal aorta and the <lb/>persistence of the 1 st or 2 nd PAA, resulted in an absent common carotid artery and the <lb/>internal and external carotid arteries arising directly from the aortic arch arteries as observed <lb/>at E15.5 (Fig. 1). Additionally, the distal outflow tract was unseptated and the 4 th PAA were <lb/>bilaterally absent (Fig. 3B-D; Table 2). <lb/>Looping of the heart tube at E10.5 was not affected in Pax9 -/-embryos (Fig. 3E, F). <lb/>In normal mouse development the outflow tract cushions rotate through an anticlockwise <lb/>direction (Bajolle et al., 2006) resulting in the major septal and parietal cushions being <lb/>positioned side by side (Fig. 3G-I). In Pax9 -/-embryos, however, by the end of the E11.5 <lb/>stage these cushions were aberrantly positioned, with the parietal cushion more anterior to <lb/>the septal cushion, indicating that a clockwise rotation of the outflow tract cushions had <lb/>occurred (Fig. J-L). This failure in proper rotation of the major cushions is potentially the <lb/>cause of the double-outlet right ventricle phenotype observed at E15.5. <lb/>This data demonstrates that Pax9 -/-embryos display a range of cardiovascular <lb/>developmental defects resulting from the abnormal morphogenesis of the PAA. The 1 st and <lb/>2 nd PAA often persist, the 3 rd PAA forms but is smaller and subsequently collapses, and the <lb/>4 th PAA fails to form at all. These defects directly lead to the absent common carotid artery, <lb/>aberrant right subclavian artery and interrupted aortic arch phenotypes seen in foetal and <lb/>neonatal stages in Pax9 -/-mice. Moreover, delayed outflow tract septation occurs with <lb/>abnormal rotation leading to the double-outlet right ventricle phenotype. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Pharyngeal endoderm signalling influences neural crest cell differentiation. <lb/>During normal embryogenesis, a subset of NCC, the cardiac neural crest, migrate into the <lb/>caudal pharyngeal arches to provide support to the developing PAA and also contribute to <lb/>outflow tract septation (Hutson and Kirby, 2003). Pax9 is predominantly expressed in the <lb/>pharyngeal endoderm (Fig. S1), but is also known to be expressed within the NCC <lb/>contributing to craniofacial development (Kist et al., 2007), although expression in cardiac <lb/>NCC has not been described. We therefore looked to see if a cell autonomous loss of Pax9 <lb/>from NCC resulted in cardiovascular defects. Conditional deletion of Pax9 using Wnt1Cre <lb/>transgenic mice (Danielian et al., 1998), and the Pax9 flox allele (Kist et al., 2007), however, <lb/>did not result in cardiovascular abnormalities, although cleft palate was observed as <lb/>expected (Fig. 4A-D). We next looked to see if the migration of NCC was affected in global <lb/>Pax9 -/-embryos using Wnt1Cre and eYFP (Srinivas et al., 2001) reporter mice to create <lb/>embryos where the NCC could be lineage traced. Live fluorescence imaging of <lb/>Pax9 +/+ ;Wnt1Cre;eYFP embryos at E10.5 revealed NCC present in the head and dorsal <lb/>route ganglia, as well as migrating towards and filling the pharyngeal arches (Fig. 4E, G, I). <lb/>A similar pattern was observed in Pax9 -/-;Wnt1Cre;eYFP embryos (Fig. 4F, H, J). <lb/>Immunostaining for BrdU incorporation specifically in NCC showed no significant difference <lb/>in NCC proliferation in the 4 th pharyngeal arch at E10.5 (Fig. 4K-M), and very little apoptosis <lb/>occurred throughout the caudal pharyngeal arches in both control and Pax9 -/-embryos (Fig. <lb/>4N-P). These observations indicated that the migration of NCC per se to the pharyngeal <lb/>arches were not affected in Pax9 -/-embryos. <lb/>It therefore appears that the rapid collapse of the 3 rd PAA at E11.5 in Pax9 -/-embryos, <lb/>resulting in an absent common carotid artery, cannot be explained by aberrant NCC death, <lb/>proliferation or migration pattern at E10.5. Given that NCC differentiate into the smooth <lb/>muscle cells that support the remodelling PAA (Waldo et al., 1996), we looked to see if <lb/>smooth muscle cell recruitment to the 3 rd PAA was affected in Pax9 -/-embryos. Sections <lb/>from E10.5 embryos were immunostained using an anti-alpha smooth muscle actin antibody <lb/>to visualise smooth muscle cells around the 3 rd PAA. As expected, no staining was observed <lb/>in control embryos around the 4 th PAA at this stage (Losa et al., 2017). Evidence of smooth <lb/>muscle cell recruitment to the 3 rd PAA was seen in each control embryo examined (Fig. 4Q, <lb/>R), however no evidence of any smooth muscle cell investment around the 3 rd PAA in Pax9 -<lb/>/-embryo sections was observed (Fig. 4S, T). These results indicated that the 3 rd PAA in <lb/>Pax9 -/-embryos forms but collapses due to a failure of smooth muscle cell investment, <lb/>possibly from a perturbation in signals that emanate from the pharyngeal endoderm under <lb/>Pax9 control. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tbx1 and Pax9 interact in 4 th PAA formation <lb/>The failure of the 4 th PAA to form in Pax9 -/-embryos, however, is likely to be due to an <lb/>alternative mechanism as NCC are not required for initial PAA formation (Waldo et al., <lb/>1996). To further investigate the role of Pax9 in cardiovascular development, we looked at <lb/>the effect of Pax9 loss on the pharyngeal arch transcriptome at E9.5 (Fig. 5A-C). Analysis of <lb/>the RNA-seq data identified a total of 3863 significant differentially expressed genes <lb/>(adjusted p value &lt;0.1; 2073 genes up and 1790 genes down). Interestingly, Tbx1 was <lb/>significantly reduced in Pax9 -/-embryos at E9.5, and this was confirmed by qPCR (Fig. 5H). <lb/>We also confirmed that Pax9 expression was reduced in Tbx1-null embryos (Fig. S2). As <lb/>Tbx1 expression is crucial for 4 th PAA morphogenesis (Lindsay et al., 2001; Zhang et al., <lb/>2005) this data suggested that Pax9 may function together with Tbx1 rather than being <lb/>downstream of it. We therefore compiled a list of all the genes reported to be significantly <lb/>differentially expressed in Tbx1-null embryos from published microarray and mouse genetic <lb/>interaction studies (Ivins et al., 2005; Liao et al., 2008; van Bueren et al., 2010) giving a total <lb/>of 1476 unique Tbx1-related genes. These were then compared to all genes significantly <lb/>changed in Pax9 -/-embryo pharyngeal arch tissue giving 342 genes that were common to <lb/>both datasets (Fig. 5D-F) and suggesting that Tbx1 and Pax9 may share a genetic network. <lb/>Among these common genes were Chd7 and Gbx2 (Fig. 5I, J) which have been shown to <lb/>interact with Tbx1 in mice (Calmont et al., 2009; Randall et al., 2009). <lb/>To investigate a potential genetic interaction in vivo between Tbx1 and Pax9 we confirmed <lb/>that both genes were co-expressed in the pharyngeal endoderm (Fig. S3). We then crossed <lb/>Tbx1 +/-mice (Jerome and Papaioannou, 2001) with Pax9 +/-mice to create Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>double heterozygotes. Genotype analysis of 168 pups at weaning revealed that only two <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-mice were alive, a highly significant deviation from the 42 expected of each <lb/>genotype from this cross (p=1.4x10 -12 ; Table S1). To identify the timing of lethality, neonates <lb/>were observed from the day of birth with all Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-mutants dying during the first 24 <lb/>h. Examination of neonatal aortic arch arteries revealed that all controls had normal arch <lb/>arteries (Fig. 6A) while Tbx1 +/-neonates frequently presented with aberrant right subclavian <lb/>artery (Fig. 6B; Table 1). All dead Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-neonates had 4 th PAA-derived defects <lb/>including interruption of the aortic arch (Fig. 6C, D; Table 1). <lb/>Having established postnatal cardiovascular defects we next analysed E15.5 Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>embryos by MRI (Fig. 6E-H). All wild-type and Pax9 +/-embryos were normal. Of the Tbx1 +/-<lb/>embryos examined, a high proportion had some form of 4 th PAA-derived defect, including <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>interrupted aortic arch and aberrant right-subclavian artery (Fig. 6F; Table 1). All <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos examined, however, had some form of 4 th PAA-derived defect (Fig. <lb/>6G, H; Table 1) with the incidence of interrupted aortic arch being significantly increased <lb/>compared to Tbx1 +/-embryos (p&lt;0.001). The incidence of perimembranous VSD was also <lb/>significantly increased (p=0.04), but none of the embryos examined displayed outflow tract <lb/>defects or bicuspid aortic valve. Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos at E10.5 were injected intra-<lb/>cardially with ink (Fig. 6I-L) and the patency of the developing 4 th PAA was then compared <lb/>between Tbx1 +/-and Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos (Table 2). All Tbx1 +/-embryos displayed a 4 th <lb/>PAA defect, predominantly a hypoplastic vessel, consistent with previously published <lb/>observations (Calmont et al., 2009; Lindsay et al., 2001; Randall et al., 2009; Ryckebusch et <lb/>al., 2010). In Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos a significant increase in bilateral aplasia of the 4 th PAA <lb/>(p=0.004) was seen, explaining the increase in 4 th PAA related cardiovascular defects <lb/>observed in the Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos at E15.5 and in neonates (i.e. interrupted aortic <lb/>arch, aberrant right subclavian artery, and cervical origins of the right subclavian artery and <lb/>aorta). No defects of PAA 1, 2 and 3 were seen. This analysis therefore revealed that a <lb/>concomitant heterozygosity of Tbx1 and Pax9 resulted in a significantly increased incidence <lb/>of interrupted aortic arch caused by the failure of the 4 th PAA to form. <lb/>Tbx1 and Pax9 interact cell autonomously in the pharyngeal endoderm for 4 th PAA <lb/>formation <lb/>The presumed site of the Tbx1-Pax9 interaction is the pharyngeal endoderm, and to <lb/>demonstrate a cell-autonomous interaction in this tissue we crossed Tbx1 flox mice (Xu et al., <lb/>2004), with a novel Pax9Cre transgenic mouse (Fig. 7A-C). This Pax9Cre strain has the Cre <lb/>recombinase gene inserted into the Pax9 coding region and effectively results in a Pax9-null <lb/>allele. The Pax9Cre allele functions as expected by activating R26R lacZ expression <lb/>specifically in the pharyngeal endoderm from E9.5 to E11.5 (Fig. 7D-G; Fig. S4) and <lb/>Pax9Cre;Pax9 flox neonates (i.e. Pax9-null) die at birth with the typical Pax9 -/-phenotype <lb/>(Fig. 7H-Q). To test the specificity of the Pax9Cre allele the pharyngeal arches of <lb/>Pax9Cre;eYFP E9.5 embryos (Fig. 8A) were dissociated into single cells and flow-sorted <lb/>into eYFP-positive and -negative populations. The eYFP-positive population was significantly <lb/>enriched for eYFP and Pax9 transcripts (Fig. 8B, C). Tbx1 flox and Pax9Cre mice were <lb/>intercrossed to create Tbx1 +/ flox ;Pax9Cre embryos which are double heterozygous for each <lb/>gene but only in the Pax9 expression domain. A significant reduction in Tbx1 RNA levels <lb/>was observed in eYFP-positive flow-sorted pharyngeal endoderm cells from conditionally <lb/>deleted E9.5 mutant embryos compared to Pax9Cre;eYFP controls (Fig. 8D). Litters from a <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox and Pax9Cre cross were collected on the day of birth, and a significant reduction in <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>the expected number of Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre mutants was found (p=2.4x10 -5 ; Table S2) and <lb/>62.5% of these mutants displayed an arch artery defect (Fig. 8F). We then collected <lb/>embryos (E13.5-E15.5) and analysed them by MRI or µCT which revealed that 37% of <lb/>mutants presented with an arch artery defect (Fig. 8H). We also collected embryos at E10.5 <lb/>and injected them intracardially with ink to visualise the PAA. All Tbx1 +/flox control embryos <lb/>analysed had normal PAA, with all three vessels being patent to ink and of a similar <lb/>diameter, whilst the majority of Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre mutant embryos presented with some form <lb/>of 4 th PAA defect (Fig. 8J; Table 2). <lb/>Our data, therefore, demonstrate that Pax9 is critical for cardiovascular development and <lb/>functionally interacts with Tbx1 in the pharyngeal endoderm. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/> Loss of Pax9 results in complex cardiovascular defects <lb/>Pax9 plays a key role in cardiovascular development as Pax9 -/-neonates and embryos <lb/>display a range of cardiovascular defects. Chromosomal deletions that include PAX9 have <lb/>been identified in patients with cardiovascular abnormalities (Hayashi et al., 2015; <lb/>Kamnasaran et al., 2001; Santen et al., 2012; Schuffenhauer et al., 1999; Shapira et al., <lb/>1994) suggesting it has potential importance in human cardiovascular development. Of <lb/>these, one patient with a 105 kb hemizygous deletion of 14q13 presented with interruption of <lb/>the aortic arch, a hypoplastic aorta, bicuspid aortic valve, and a ventricular septal defect <lb/>(Santen et al., 2012), all of which appear with high penetrance in mouse Pax9-null embryos. <lb/>This small deletion only removed PAX9, NKX2-1 and NKX2-8, although deletion of either <lb/>Nkx2 gene in mice does not result in any cardiovascular defects (Kimura et al., 1996; Pabst <lb/>et al., 2003). It is therefore possible that hemizygous deletion of PAX9 in humans can <lb/>recapitulate, in part, the mouse knockout phenotype. <lb/>Tbx1 and Pax9 interact in 4 th PAA development <lb/>Published microarray studies investigating the transcriptome of Tbx1-null embryos have <lb/>implicated Pax9 as a downstream target of Tbx1, although this was not demonstrated with <lb/>any functional assays (Ivins et al., 2005; Liao et al., 2008). Analysis of our Pax9-null <lb/>pharyngeal arch transcriptome data revealed that Tbx1 levels were significantly reduced <lb/>suggesting that perhaps Pax9 and Tbx1 may function together rather than work in a <lb/>hierarchal pathway. Further analysis identified that many genes differentially expressed in <lb/>Tbx1-null embryos, or shown to interact with Tbx1 in mouse models, were also significantly <lb/>differentially expressed in Pax9-null embryos, e.g. Chd7 and Gbx2. Mice heterozygous for <lb/>Chd7 have abnormal 4 th PAA derivatives and a combined heterozygosity with Tbx1 results in <lb/>an increased incidence of 4 th PAA defects (Randall et al., 2009). Gbx2-null embryos display <lb/>cardiovascular defects (Byrd and Meyers, 2005) and Tbx1 and Gbx2 have also been shown <lb/>to genetically interact in PAA development (Calmont et al., 2009). Although both these Tbx1 <lb/>targets have been demonstrated to interact in the pharyngeal ectoderm, they are also <lb/>expressed in the pharyngeal endoderm and could therefore interact with Pax9 either directly <lb/>or indirectly in this tissue. As our data strongly suggested that Pax9 may interact with Tbx1 <lb/>and its related genes in the morphogenesis of the PAA we therefore looked for a genetic <lb/>interaction between Tbx1 and Pax9 in mice. We found that all mice examined (embryos and <lb/>neonates) double heterozygous for each gene (i.e. Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-) displayed some defect <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>associated with abnormal development of the 4 th PAA, most notably interrupted aortic arch. <lb/>Although hypoplasia or absence of the 4 th PAA is a feature in mouse embryos heterozygous <lb/>for Tbx1 (Lindsay et al., 2001), this phenotype was significantly more prevalent in <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-mice, and much higher than observed in Tbx1 +/-embryos. It therefore <lb/>appears that combining one Pax9-null allele with one Tbx1-null allele exacerbates the <lb/>Tbx1 +/-phenotype. <lb/>We used our novel Pax9Cre mouse to conditionally delete Tbx1 from the pharyngeal <lb/>endoderm, whilst simultaneously creating double haploinsufficiency for the two genes in this <lb/>tissue. A highly significant reduction in the number of Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre neonates born was <lb/>observed indicating that heterozygous loss of Tbx1 and Pax9 from the pharyngeal endoderm <lb/>has a major impact on post-natal survival, with almost two-thirds of the recovered neonates <lb/>examined having identifiable cardiovascular defects. A similar proportion of affected mutants <lb/>was found at foetal stages. When embryos were examined at mid-embryogenesis, however, <lb/>we found that almost all displayed 4 th PAA defects. When compared to our Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>embryo data it was apparent that there was no significant difference in the incidence of <lb/>bilateral 4 th PAA defects between Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre and Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos. This <lb/>indicates that the conditional deletion of Tbx1 from the pharyngeal endoderm, in the context <lb/>of Pax9 heterozygosity, has the same effect on 4 th PAA morphogenesis as seen in the global <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos at E10.5. Although the ink injection data from Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre <lb/>embryos matches that seen in Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos, and shows that heterozygous loss <lb/>of Tbx1 from the pharyngeal endoderm severely affects PAA morphogenesis, there is a <lb/>discrepancy in the cardiovascular phenotype observed at foetal and neonatal stages that <lb/>does not reflect that seen at mid-embryogenesis, nor that observed in Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>embryos. It is well documented, however, that the Tbx1 +/-4 th PAA phenotype does recover <lb/>during development (see Table S3). It therefore appears that a conditional deletion of Tbx1 <lb/>from the pharyngeal endoderm in the context of Pax9 haploinsufficiency replicates the Tbx1 <lb/>heterozygous arch artery phenotype in terms of a highly penetrant 4 th PAA defect at mid-<lb/>embryogenesis that partially recovers by the foetal stage. Our data, however, does raise the <lb/>question as to whether we are seeing the effect of a pharyngeal endoderm specific loss of <lb/>Tbx1 with Pax9Cre, or a genetic interaction occurring between Tbx1 and Pax9 in the <lb/>pharyngeal endoderm. Conditional deletion experiments have been performed in transgenic <lb/>mice to unpick the role of Tbx1 in specific tissues and have examined the effect of Tbx1 <lb/>heterozygosity in the pharyngeal mesoderm and/or epithelium for 4 th PAA development (see <lb/>Table S4). When compared, our data clearly shows that the 4 th PAA phenotype is much <lb/>more penetrant than that seen in embryos only heterozygous for Tbx1 in the pharyngeal <lb/>epithelia. We therefore conclude that we are showing a strong genetic and cell-autonomous <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>interaction between Tbx1 and Pax9 within the pharyngeal endoderm which impacts on 4 th <lb/>PAA morphogenesis. Moreover, and in support of a phenotype extending beyond what is <lb/>expected from a Tbx1 heterozygous phenotype, our Tbx1 flox ;Pax9Cre mice display a <lb/>vascular ring defect and a high incidence of perinatal lethality, features not previously <lb/>described in Tbx1 +/-mice. <lb/>Pax9 signalling from the pharyngeal endoderm is required for 3 rd PAA maintenance <lb/>The mammalian PAA develop symmetrically in a cranial to caudal sequence, and then <lb/>subsequently remodel to form the typical asymmetric aortic arch artery system seen in the <lb/>adult (Bamforth et al., 2013; Hiruma et al., 2002). In normal PAA development the 1 st artery <lb/>forms first, followed by the 2 nd , but these two vessels rapidly remodel and contribute to <lb/>capillary beds and the maxillary and stapedial arteries. In some Pax9 -/-embryos, these <lb/>vessels aberrantly persisted into E10.5 and E11.5 and may contribute to the anomalous <lb/>arrangement of the aortic arch arteries when the 3 rd PAA collapses. In normal development <lb/>the 3 rd PAA will form part of the common and proximal internal carotid arteries, which <lb/>elongate as the embryo grows. The carotid duct involutes and the dorsal aorta anterior to <lb/>this segment will form the distal internal carotid artery, with the external carotid artery <lb/>derived from the proximal parts of the 1 st and 2 nd PAA (Hiruma et al., 2002). The persistence <lb/>of the 1 st and/or 2 nd PAA in Pax9 -/-embryos, coupled with the failure of the 3 rd PAA to be <lb/>maintained and the carotid duct to involute, results in the external carotid arteries rising <lb/>directly from the aorta, and the internal carotid arteries from the anterior dorsal aortae. This <lb/>phenomenon has been described clinically (Roberts and Gerald, 1978). Although migration, <lb/>apoptosis or proliferation of NCC did not appear to be impaired in Pax9-null embryos, it is <lb/>well recognised that NCC differentiate into the smooth muscle cells that are important for the <lb/>stabilisation of the remodelled PAA (Hutson and Kirby, 2003; Losa et al., 2017) and it is the <lb/>failure of smooth muscle cells to envelop the 3 rd PAA in Pax9-null embryos that results in the <lb/>collapse of this vessel. This has also been described in Hoxa3-null embryos, where smooth <lb/>muscle cells fail to develop around the 3 rd PAA which degenerate at E11.5 (Kameda, 2009) <lb/>and reduced NCC migration in genetic mouse and surgical chick models also leads to <lb/>defects of the 3 rd PAA (Bradshaw et al., 2009; Epstein et al., 2000; Franz, 1989; Nishibatake <lb/>et al., 1987). Signalling between the pharyngeal endoderm and NCC does occur (Graham et <lb/>al., 2005) so it is therefore possible that signals emanating from the pharyngeal endoderm <lb/>under Pax9 control are necessary to influence the differentiation of NCC into smooth muscle <lb/>cells, and without these signals the 3 rd PAA is not supported during the remodelling phase of <lb/>arch artery development and it collapses. The double outlet right ventricle phenotype <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>observed at E15.5 in Pax9-null embryos probably arises from the marked outflow tract <lb/>rotation defect due to a change in the aortic to pulmonary valve axis angle (Bostrom and <lb/>Hutchins, 1988; Lomonico et al., 1986) and, possibly, aberrations in the NCC that migrate to <lb/>the outflow tract may contribute to this phenotype (Bradshaw et al., 2009). <lb/>In summary, Pax9 expression in the pharyngeal endoderm has regional (anterior/posterior) <lb/>roles in regulating the morphogenesis of the PAA (Fig. 9). In the 3 rd pharyngeal arch Pax9 is <lb/>important for controlling NCC differentiation into the smooth muscle cells that support the <lb/>remodelling vessel, whereas in the 4 th pharyngeal arch endoderm, the interaction of Pax9 <lb/>with Tbx1 and its targets is crucial for the formation of the 4 th PAA. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Jessica Addison, Kathleen Allinson and Divya Venkatesh for technical assistance, <lb/>Sushma Grellscheid for facilitating the RNA-seq experiment, and Nicoletta Bobola for <lb/>critically reading the manuscript. Tbx1 +/-mice were obtained from Robert Kelly and Virginia <lb/>Papaioannou. We acknowledge the Newcastle University Flow Cytometry Core Facility <lb/>(FCCF) for assistance with the generation of Flow Cytometry data. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>No competing interests declared. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding statement <lb/>This work was funded by a British Heart Foundation Intermediate Basic Science Research <lb/>Fellowship (FS/08/016/24741; to SDB), a British Heart Foundation project grant <lb/>(PG/16/39/32115; to SDB), a British Heart Foundation PhD Non-Clinical PhD Studentship <lb/>(FS/16/8/31984 to; SDB) and a grant from the Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS <lb/>Charities (BH120404; to SDB). JABL received a PhD Scholarship from the National Science <lb/>and Technology Council of Mexico (CONACyT). RRK received a PhD Scholarship from <lb/>Yarmouk University, Jordan. <lb/></div>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Materials and methods <lb/>Mice <lb/>The mice used in this study have previously been described: Pax9 +/-(Peters et al., 1998), <lb/>Pax9 flox (Kist et al., 2007), Tbx +/-(Jerome and Papaioannou, 2001), Tbx1 flox (Xu et al., 2004), <lb/>Wnt1Cre (Danielian et al., 1998), R26R eYFP (Srinivas et al., 2001), R26R lacZ (Soriano, 1999) <lb/>and FLPe (Dymecki, 1996). All mice were maintained on a C57Bl/6J genetic background. All <lb/>studies involving animals were performed in accordance with UK Home Office Animals <lb/>(Scientific Procedures) Act 1986. <lb/>Generation of Pax9Cre mice <lb/>The Pax9Cre targeting construct was designed to replace a 1.06 kb section of the Pax9 <lb/>gene, spanning the second half of exon two, containing the start codon, and the first half of <lb/>the 3 rd exon, containing the paired box and octapeptide motif, with a promoterless Cre <lb/>recombinase gene preceded by a consensus Kozak sequence, in the pPNT4 targeting <lb/>vector (Conrad et al., 2003), using standard molecular biology methods (Fig. 7A). The 1.3kb <lb/>right homology arm, generated as previously described (Kist et al., 2005), was inserted <lb/>between the FRT-flanked PGK-Neomycin cassette and the HSV-Thymidine Kinase cassette <lb/>of pPNT4. The unwanted loxP site of pPNT4 was removed by XbaI partial digestion, <lb/>followed by Klenow treatment and re-ligation. The left homology arm was generated as a 7.4 <lb/>kb SalI to SmaI fragment of the Pax9 genomic region including exon 1 and the first half of <lb/>the second exon, and inserted 5&apos; of the Cre recombinase gene. The targeting vector was <lb/>linearized with SfiI and mouse ES cells were targeted and selected as previously described <lb/>(Kearns et al., 2013). Southern blot analysis was performed according to standard methods <lb/>following XbaI digest of genomic DNA. An external southern probe was used to verify <lb/>integration of the targeting cassette in the 5&apos; region (Fig. 7B) and PCR was used to validate <lb/>integration of the 3&apos; region (not shown). The FRT-flanked PGK-Neomycin cassette was <lb/>removed by crossing the derived Pax9Cre-Neo mice with FLPe mice (Dymecki, 1996) to <lb/>create Pax9Cre mice, which were then backcrossed to strain C57Bl/6J for &gt;6 generations. <lb/>Genotyping by multiplex PCR [primers: F1-ACTCAAGCCTCTTTCAGCCC (common), R1-<lb/>TTGTTCTCACTGAGCCGGCCTGT (Pax9 exon 2), and R2-GTTGCATCGACCGGTAATGC (Cre)] <lb/>were used to simultaneously identify the wild-type and Pax9Cre alleles (Fig. 7C). <lb/>Breeding <lb/></div>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Male and female mice were mated and the detection of a vaginal plug the next morning <lb/>considered to be E0.5. Pregnant females were culled on the required day and embryos <lb/>collected. Embryos at E9.5-E11.5 were staged by somite counting. <lb/>Imaging <lb/>Magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) was performed using a 9.4T MR system (Varian, US) as <lb/>previously described (Bamforth et al., 2012; Schneider et al., 2004) on embryos at E15.5. <lb/>High Resolution Episcopic Microscopy (HREM) and micro-computed tomography (µCT) <lb/>techniques have been described in detail elsewhere (Degenhardt et al., 2010; Geyer et al., <lb/>2009). All MRI, HREM and µCT images were converted into a volume data set and <lb/>segmented using Amira software (ThermoFisher Scientific) to create 2-and 3-dimensional <lb/>(3-D) images. Structures were manually outlined using the label field function of Amira and <lb/>surface rendered to produce the 3-D images. Intra-cardiac ink injections were performed as <lb/>described (Calmont et al., 2009). Aorta measurements were taken from the region just <lb/>proximal to the point at which the ascending aorta becomes the aortic arch. Haematoxylin <lb/>and eosin and X-gal staining, and Pax9 whole-mount in situ hybridisation, were performed <lb/>using standard techniques. Tbx1 and Pax9 mRNA co-expression was examined by RNA in <lb/>situ hybridisation using RNAscope ® Multiplex Fluorescent v2 Assay (Advanced Cell <lb/>Diagnostics, Newark, CA, USA) following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Probes used: mm-<lb/>Pax9-C2 (454321-C2 at 1:50 dilution) and mm-Tbx1 (481911 used directly). For proliferation <lb/>assays BrdU (Sigma) dissolved in PBS was administered by intraperitoneal injection at a <lb/>dose of 50mg/kg to pregnant dams one hour before embryo collection. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry was performed using standard techniques (antibody details in Table <lb/>S5) on paraformaldehyde fixed embryo sections, and fluorescently imaged on an Axioimager <lb/>(Zeiss). To assess an apoptotic index within the pharyngeal arches, control and Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos at E10.5 (n=3 per genotype; 30-35 somites) were examined following <lb/>immunostaining with the caspase-3 antibody. To assess a proliferative index within the NCC <lb/>in the pharyngeal arches, control and Pax9 -/-embryos expressing Wnt1Cre activated eYFP <lb/>at E10.5 were examined following immunostaining with anti-BrdU and anti-GFP antibodies <lb/>(n=5 for each genotype; 31-39 somites). All positively stained and DAPI positive cells within <lb/>the pharyngeal arches were counted from at least three slides for each embryo, and the ratio <lb/>of positively stained cells over the total number of cells calculated. For endothelial cell and <lb/>smooth muscle actin immunostaining n=7 control (31-36 somites) and n=6 Pax9 -/-embryos <lb/>(32-35 somites) were examined. <lb/>Transcriptome analysis <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Wild-type (Pax9 +/+ ) and Pax9-null (Pax9 −/− ) embryos at E9.5 (n=3 of each genotype, stage-<lb/>matched for 26-27 somites) were collected in ice-cold DEPC-PBS, and the pharyngeal <lb/>region, from the junction between the first and second pharyngeal arch to the base of the <lb/>heart, dissected free in RNAlater (Sigma). Genotypes were identified by PCR from the <lb/>embryo tails and/or yolk sac material. Total RNA was extracted using the QIAGEN Plus <lb/>Micro kit with genomic DNA Eliminator columns, and total RNA eluted in 30 μl RNase-free <lb/>water. RNA concentration and purity were assessed by NanoDrop spectrophotometry and <lb/>Agilent Bioanalyzer with all samples producing a RIN of 10. Genomic DNA contamination <lb/>was excluded by PCR for intronic regions (sensitivity 5 pg/μl). To confirm that the correct <lb/>genotypes were processed, cDNA was made from 100 ng total RNA and a qPCR for Pax9 <lb/>performed (Fig. 5B). The total RNA samples were shipped on dry-ice to EMBLM-GeneCore <lb/>(Heidelberg, Germany) for RNA-seq first-strand specific library preparation using Illumina <lb/>TruSeq, and 100bp paired end reads were generated from an Illumina HiSeq 2000 <lb/>Sequencer. Quality control by FastQC suggested a small amount of adaptor contamination <lb/>in each sample, so raw reads were trimmed of adaptor sequence with Trimmomatic (Bolger <lb/>et al., 2014). Reads shorter than 36bp after trimming were discarded, and reads whose pair <lb/>had been discarded were also removed. Trimmed reads were further filtered to keep only <lb/>uniquely aligned and non-redundant reads to remove a vast majority of pseudogenes <lb/>caused by multi-mapping. Also, to avoid bias due to imbalanced library sizes among <lb/>conditions, all samples were sub-sampled towards the smallest sample (mt-663_1). The <lb/>resulting reads were aligned to the Mouse Genome (Ensembl release 81, GRCm38) using <lb/>the splice aware read aligner STAR 2 (star-2.5.2a-0, 20/01/2017) (Dobin et al., 2013). <lb/>Finally, aligned reads were assigned to Ensembl genes using featureCounts (Liao et al., <lb/>2014) with default parameters. These count tables were imported into R and analysed using <lb/>the package LIMMA (Ritchie et al., 2015) and voom function from Bioconductor (Gentleman <lb/>et al., 2004). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data accessibility <lb/>The RNA-seq data have been deposited in NCBI&apos;s Gene Expression Omnibus and are <lb/>accessible through GEO Series accession number GSE128087 <lb/>(https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/query/acc.cgi?acc=GSE18087). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Flow cytometry <lb/>The pharyngeal arch region of E9.5 Pax9Cre;eYFP control (n=5; 23-27 somites) and mutant <lb/>Tbx1 +/ flox ;Pax9Cre;eYFP (n=5; 24-29 somites) embryos was dissected free as described <lb/>above and dissociated to single cells with Accumax (eBioscience) by incubating at 37°C for <lb/> 30 minutes. The reaction was stopped by the addition of 10% fetal calf serum (FCS), the <lb/></div>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">cells washed in PBS, and resuspended in 10% FCS. Cells were stained with propidium <lb/>iodide. Flourescence activated cell sorting was performed on a Becton Dickinson FACS Aria <lb/>II using a 100µm nozzle and a sheath pressure of 20 psi. Single cells were gated using FSC-<lb/>A vs SSC-A followed by FSC-A vs FSC-H and FSC-A vs SSC-W to remove any doublets. <lb/>Live single cells were gated using propidium iodide vs FSC-A, and this population finally <lb/>gated on eYFP-positive and -negative cells and sorted into collection tubes. <lb/>Quantitative real-time RT-PCR (qPCR) <lb/>RNA, from either dissociated pharyngeal arch cells or flow-sorted cells, was extracted using <lb/>Trizol reagent (Invitrogen) combined with a Purelink RNA Mini Kit (Ambion) and on-column <lb/>DNase1 treatment. RNA was eluted with 30 µl RNase-free water. Total RNA was converted <lb/>to cDNA using a High-Capacity cDNA Reverse transcription kit (Applied Biosystems) and <lb/>random hexamers. qPCR was performed using SYBR Green JumpStart Taq ReadyMix <lb/>(Sigma) using the primers listed in Table S6. All qPCR reactions were performed in triplicate <lb/>on a QuantStudio 7 Real-Time PCR System (Thermo Fisher). Data was analysed using the <lb/>comparative Ct method (Schmittgen and Livak, 2008). <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Chi-squared test was used to compare genotype frequencies of litters, and Pearson&apos;s chi-<lb/>squared test for associations was used to compare defect frequencies between the different <lb/>genotypes. For analysis of qPCR data, aorta measurements, and cell counts, datasets were <lb/>tested for variance using the Shapiro-Wilk test (Prism 8.01 software, GraphPad). Two-tailed <lb/>unpaired t-tests were performed on normally distributed data, and a two-tailed Mann-<lb/>Whitney U non-parametric test was used for not normally distributed data. Groups were <lb/>considered significantly different when p&lt;0.05, or p&lt;0.1 for RNA-seq data. No statistical <lb/>methods were used to predetermine sample size which were chosen based on previous <lb/>experience to obtain statistical significance and reproducibility. No data points were <lb/>excluded, and all data collected from each individual experiment were used for analysis. <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Aggarwal, V. S. and Morrow, B. E. (2008). Genetic modifiers of the physical malformations <lb/>in velo-cardio-facial syndrome/DiGeorge syndrome. Dev Disabil Res Rev 14, 19-25. <lb/>Bajolle, F., Zaffran, S., Kelly, R. G., Hadchouel, J., Bonnet, D., Brown, N. A. and <lb/>Buckingham, M. E. (2006). Rotation of the myocardial wall of the outflow tract is <lb/>implicated in the normal positioning of the great arteries. Circ Res 98, 421-428. <lb/>Bamforth, S. D., Chaudhry, B., Bennett, M., Wilson, R., Mohun, T. J., Van Mierop, L. H., <lb/>Henderson, D. J. and Anderson, R. H. (2013). Clarification of the identity of the <lb/>mammalian fifth pharyngeal arch artery. Clin Anat 26, 173-182. <lb/>Bamforth, S. D., Schneider, J. E. and Bhattacharya, S. (2012). High-throughput analysis <lb/>of mouse embryos by magnetic resonance imaging. Cold Spring Harb Protoc 2012, <lb/>93-101. <lb/>Bolger, A. M., Lohse, M. and Usadel, B. (2014). Trimmomatic: a flexible trimmer for <lb/>Illumina sequence data. Bioinformatics 30, 2114-2120. <lb/>Bostrom, M. P. and Hutchins, G. M. (1988). Arrested rotation of the outflow tract may <lb/>explain double-outlet right ventricle. Circulation 77, 1258-1265. <lb/>Boudjemline, Y., Fermont, L., Le Bidois, J., Lyonnet, S., Sidi, D. and Bonnet, D. (2001). <lb/>Prevalence of 22q11 deletion in fetuses with conotruncal cardiac defects: a 6-year <lb/>prospective study. J Pediatr 138, 520-524. <lb/>Bradshaw, L., Chaudhry, B., Hildreth, V., Webb, S. and Henderson, D. J. (2009). Dual <lb/>role for neural crest cells during outflow tract septation in the neural crest-deficient <lb/>mutant Splotch(2H). J Anat 214, 245-257. <lb/>Byrd, N. A. and Meyers, E. N. (2005). Loss of Gbx2 results in neural crest cell patterning <lb/>and pharyngeal arch artery defects in the mouse embryo. Dev Biol 284, 233-245. <lb/>Calmont, A., Ivins, S., Van Bueren, K. L., Papangeli, I., Kyriakopoulou, V., Andrews, W. <lb/>D., Martin, J. F., Moon, A. M., Illingworth, E. A., Basson, M. A., et al. (2009). Tbx1 <lb/>controls cardiac neural crest cell migration during arch artery development by <lb/>regulating Gbx2 expression in the pharyngeal ectoderm. Development 136, 3173-<lb/>3183. <lb/>Chi, N. and Epstein, J. A. (2002). Getting your Pax straight: Pax proteins in development <lb/>and disease. Trends Genet 18, 41-47. <lb/>Conrad, M., Brielmeier, M., Wurst, W. and Bornkamm, G. W. (2003). Optimized vector for <lb/>conditional gene targeting in mouse embryonic stem cells. Biotechniques 34, 1136-<lb/>1138, 1140. <lb/>Danielian, P. S., Muccino, D., Rowitch, D. H., Michael, S. K. and McMahon, A. P. (1998). <lb/>Modification of gene activity in mouse embryos in utero by a tamoxifen-inducible form <lb/>of Cre recombinase. Curr Biol 8, 1323-1326. <lb/>Degenhardt, K., Wright, A. C., Horng, D., Padmanabhan, A. and Epstein, J. A. (2010). <lb/>Rapid 3D phenotyping of cardiovascular development in mouse embryos by micro-<lb/>CT with iodine staining. Circ Cardiovasc Imaging 3, 314-322. <lb/>Dobin, A., Davis, C. A., Schlesinger, F., Drenkow, J., Zaleski, C., Jha, S., Batut, P., <lb/>Chaisson, M. and Gingeras, T. R. (2013). STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq <lb/>aligner. Bioinformatics 29, 15-21. <lb/>Dymecki, S. M. (1996). Flp recombinase promotes site-specific DNA recombination in <lb/>embryonic stem cells and transgenic mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93, 6191-6196. <lb/>Epstein, J. A., Li, J., Lang, D., Chen, F., Brown, C. B., Jin, F., Lu, M. M., Thomas, M., <lb/>Liu, E., Wessels, A., et al. (2000). Migration of cardiac neural crest cells in Splotch <lb/>embryos. Development 127, 1869-1878. <lb/>Franz, T. (1989). Persistent truncus arteriosus in the Splotch mutant mouse. Anat Embryol <lb/>(Berl) 180, 457-464. <lb/>Gentleman, R. C., Carey, V. J., Bates, D. M., Bolstad, B., Dettling, M., Dudoit, S., Ellis, <lb/>B., Gautier, L., Ge, Y., Gentry, J., et al. (2004). Bioconductor: open software <lb/>development for computational biology and bioinformatics. Genome Biol 5, R80. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Geyer, S. H., Mohun, T. J. and Weninger, W. J. (2009). Visualizing Vertebrate Embryos <lb/>with Episcopic 3D Imaging Techniques. TheScientificWorldJOURNAL 9, 1423-1437. <lb/>Graham, A. (2003). Development of the pharyngeal arches. Am J Med Genet A 119, 251-<lb/>256. <lb/>Graham, A., Okabe, M. and Quinlan, R. (2005). The role of the endoderm in the <lb/>development and evolution of the pharyngeal arches. J Anat 207, 479-487. <lb/>Guo, T., McGinn, D. M., Blonska, A., Shanske, A., Bassett, A., Chow, E., Bowser, M., <lb/>Sheridan, M., Beemer, F., Devriendt, K., et al. (2011). Genotype and <lb/>Cardiovascular Phenotype Correlations with TBX1 in 1,022 Velo-Cardio-<lb/>Facial/DiGeorge/22q11.2 Deletion Syndrome Patients. Human Mutation, n/a-n/a. <lb/>Hayashi, S., Yagi, M., Morisaki, I. and Inazawa, J. (2015). Identical deletion at 14q13.3 <lb/>including PAX9 and NKX2-1 in siblings from mosaicism of unaffected parent. J Hum <lb/>Genet. <lb/>Hiruma, T., Nakajima, Y. and Nakamura, H. (2002). Development of pharyngeal arch <lb/>arteries in early mouse embryo. J Anat 201, 15-29. <lb/>Hutson, M. R. and Kirby, M. L. (2003). Neural crest and cardiovascular development: a 20-<lb/>year perspective. Birth Defects Res C Embryo Today 69, 2-13. <lb/>Ivins, S., Lammerts van Beuren, K., Roberts, C., James, C., Lindsay, E., Baldini, A., <lb/>Ataliotis, P. and Scambler, P. J. (2005). Microarray analysis detects differentially <lb/>expressed genes in the pharyngeal region of mice lacking Tbx1. Dev Biol 285, 554-<lb/>569. <lb/>Jerome, L. A. and Papaioannou, V. E. (2001). DiGeorge syndrome phenotype in mice <lb/>mutant for the T-box gene, Tbx1. Nat Genet 27, 286-291. <lb/>Kameda, Y. (2009). Hoxa3 and signaling molecules involved in aortic arch patterning and <lb/>remodeling. Cell Tissue Res 336, 165-178. <lb/>Kamnasaran, D., O&apos;Brien, P. C., Schuffenhauer, S., Quarrell, O., Lupski, J. R., <lb/>Grammatico, P., Ferguson-Smith, M. A. and Cox, D. W. (2001). Defining the <lb/>breakpoints of proximal chromosome 14q rearrangements in nine patients using flow-<lb/>sorted chromosomes. Am J Med Genet 102, 173-182. <lb/>Kearns, N. A., Genga, R. M., Ziller, M., Kapinas, K., Peters, H., Brehm, M. A., Meissner, <lb/>A. and Maehr, R. (2013). Generation of organized anterior foregut epithelia from <lb/>pluripotent stem cells using small molecules. Stem cell research 11, 1003-1012. <lb/>Kimura, S., Hara, Y., Pineau, T., Fernandez-Salguero, P., Fox, C. H., Ward, J. M. and <lb/>Gonzalez, F. J. (1996). The T/ebp null mouse: thyroid-specific enhancer-binding <lb/>protein is essential for the organogenesis of the thyroid, lung, ventral forebrain, and <lb/>pituitary. Genes &amp; Development 10, 60-69. <lb/>Kist, R., Greally, E. and Peters, H. (2007). Derivation of a mouse model for conditional <lb/>inactivation of Pax9. Genesis 45, 460-464. <lb/>Kist, R., Watson, M., Wang, X., Cairns, P., Miles, C., Reid, D. J. and Peters, H. (2005). <lb/>Reduction of Pax9 gene dosage in an allelic series of mouse mutants causes <lb/>hypodontia and oligodontia. Hum Mol Genet 14, 3605-3617. <lb/>Lewin, M. B., Lindsay, E. A., Jurecic, V., Goytia, V., Towbin, J. A. and Baldini, A. (1997). <lb/>A genetic etiology for interruption of the aortic arch type B. Am J Cardiol 80, 493-497. <lb/>Liao, J., Aggarwal, V. S., Nowotschin, S., Bondarev, A., Lipner, S. and Morrow, B. E. <lb/>(2008). Identification of downstream genetic pathways of Tbx1 in the second heart <lb/>field. Dev Biol 316, 524-537. <lb/>Liao, Y., Smyth, G. K. and Shi, W. (2014). featureCounts: an efficient general purpose <lb/>program for assigning sequence reads to genomic features. Bioinformatics 30, 923-<lb/>930. <lb/>Lindsay, E. A., Vitelli, F., Su, H., Morishima, M., Huynh, T., Pramparo, T., Jurecic, V., <lb/>Ogunrinu, G., Sutherland, H. F., Scambler, P. J., et al. (2001). Tbx1 <lb/>haploinsufficieny in the DiGeorge syndrome region causes aortic arch defects in <lb/>mice. Nature 410, 97-101. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Lomonico, M. P., Moore, G. W. and Hutchins, G. M. (1986). Rotation of the junction of the <lb/>outflow tract and great arteries in the embryonic human heart. Anat Rec 216, 544-<lb/>549. <lb/>Losa, M., Latorre, V., Andrabi, M., Ladam, F., Sagerstrom, C., Novoa, A., Zarrineh, P., <lb/>Bridoux, L., Hanley, N. A., Mallo, M., et al. (2017). A tissue-specific, Gata6-driven <lb/>transcriptional program instructs remodeling of the mature arterial tree. Elife 6. <lb/>Mansouri, A., Hallonet, M. and Gruss, P. (1996). Pax genes and their roles in cell <lb/>differentiation and development. Current Opinion in Cell Biology 8, 851-857. <lb/>Merscher, S., Funke, B., Epstein, J. A., Heyer, J., Puech, A., Lu, M. M., Xavier, R. J., <lb/>Demay, M. B., Russell, R. G., Factor, S., et al. (2001). TBX1 is responsible for <lb/>cardiovascular defects in velo-cardio-facial/DiGeorge syndrome. Cell 104, 619-629. <lb/>Momma, K. (2010). Cardiovascular Anomalies Associated With Chromosome 22q11.2 <lb/>Deletion Syndrome. The American Journal of Cardiology 105, 1617-1624. <lb/>Morrow, B. E., McDonald-McGinn, D. M., Emanuel, B. S., Vermeesch, J. R. and <lb/>Scambler, P. J. (2018). Molecular genetics of 22q11.2 deletion syndrome. American <lb/>Journal of Medical Genetics Part A 176, 2070-2081. <lb/>Neubuser, A., Koseki, H. and Balling, R. (1995). Characterization and developmental <lb/>expression of Pax9, a paired-box-containing gene related to Pax1. Dev Biol 170, <lb/>701-716. <lb/>Nishibatake, M., Kirby, M. L. and Van Mierop, L. H. (1987). Pathogenesis of persistent <lb/>truncus arteriosus and dextroposed aorta in the chick embryo after neural crest <lb/>ablation. Circulation 75, 255-264. <lb/>Pabst, O., Rummelies, J., Winter, B. and Arnold, H.-H. (2003). Targeted disruption of the <lb/>homeobox gene Nkx2.9 reveals a role in development of the spinal accessory nerve. <lb/>Development 130, 1193-1202. <lb/>Papangeli, I. and Scambler, P. (2013). The 22q11 deletion: DiGeorge and velocardiofacial <lb/>syndromes and the role of TBX1. Wiley Interdiscip Rev Dev Biol 2, 393-403. <lb/>Peters, H., Neubuser, A., Kratochwil, K. and Balling, R. (1998). Pax9-deficient mice lack <lb/>pharyngeal pouch derivatives and teeth and exhibit craniofacial and limb <lb/>abnormalities. Genes Dev 12, 2735-2747. <lb/>Randall, V., McCue, K., Roberts, C., Kyriakopoulou, V., Beddow, S., Barrett, A. N., <lb/>Vitelli, F., Prescott, K., Shaw-Smith, C., Devriendt, K., et al. (2009). Great vessel <lb/>development requires biallelic expression of Chd7 and Tbx1 in pharyngeal ectoderm <lb/>in mice. J Clin Invest 119, 3301-3310. <lb/>Ritchie, M. E., Phipson, B., Wu, D., Hu, Y., Law, C. W., Shi, W. and Smyth, G. K. (2015). <lb/>limma powers differential expression analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray <lb/>studies. Nucleic Acids Res 43, e47. <lb/>Roberts, L. K. and Gerald, B. (1978). Absence of both common carotid arteries. American <lb/>Journal of Roentgenology 130, 981-982. <lb/>Ryckebusch, L., Bertrand, N., Mesbah, K., Bajolle, F., Niederreither, K., Kelly, R. G. and <lb/>Zaffran, S. (2010). Decreased Levels of Embryonic Retinoic Acid Synthesis <lb/>Accelerate Recovery From Arterial Growth Delay in a Mouse Model of DiGeorge <lb/>Syndrome. Circ Res 106, 686-694. <lb/>Santen, G. W., Sun, Y., Gijsbers, A. C., Carre, A., Holvoet, M., Haeringen, A., Lesnik <lb/>Oberstein, S. A., Tomoda, A., Mabe, H., Polak, M., et al. (2012). Further <lb/>delineation of the phenotype of chromosome 14q13 deletions: (positional) <lb/>involvement of FOXG1 appears the main determinant of phenotype severity, with no <lb/>evidence for a holoprosencephaly locus. J Med Genet 49, 366-372. <lb/>Scambler, P. J. (2000). The 22q11 deletion syndromes. Hum. Mol. Genet. 9, 2421-2426. <lb/>Schmittgen, T. D. and Livak, K. J. (2008). Analyzing real-time PCR data by the <lb/>comparative C(T) method. Nat Protoc 3, 1101-1108. <lb/>Schneider, J. E., Bose, J., Bamforth, S. D., Gruber, A. D., Broadbent, C., Clarke, K., <lb/>Neubauer, S., Lengeling, A. and Bhattacharya, S. (2004). Identification of cardiac <lb/>malformations in mice lacking Ptdsr using a novel high-throughput magnetic <lb/>resonance imaging technique. BMC Dev Biol 4, 16. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Schuffenhauer, S., Leifheit, H.-J., Lichtner, P., Peters, H., Murken, J. and Emmerich, P. <lb/>(1999). De novo deletion (14)(q11.2q13) including PAX9: clinical and molecular <lb/>findings. J Med Genet 36, 233-236. <lb/>Shapira, S. K., Anderson, K. L., Orr-Urtregar, A., Craigen, W. J., Lupski, J. R. and <lb/>Shaffer, L. G. (1994). De novo proximal interstitial deletions of 14q: cytogenetic and <lb/>molecular investigations. Am J Med Genet 52, 44-50. <lb/>Soriano, P. (1999). Generalized lacZ expression with the ROSA26 Cre reporter strain. Nat <lb/>Genet 21, 70-71. <lb/>Srinivas, S., Watanabe, T., Lin, C. S., William, C. M., Tanabe, Y., Jessell, T. M. and <lb/>Costantini, F. (2001). Cre reporter strains produced by targeted insertion of EYFP <lb/>and ECFP into the ROSA26 locus. BMC Dev Biol 1, 4. <lb/>Thom, T., Haase, N., Rosamond, W., Howard, V. J., Rumsfeld, J., Manolio, T., Zheng, Z. <lb/>J., Flegal, K., O&apos;Donnell, C., Kittner, S., et al. (2006). Heart disease and stroke <lb/>statistics--2006 update: a report from the American Heart Association Statistics <lb/>Committee and Stroke Statistics Subcommittee. Circulation 113, e85-151. <lb/>Unolt, M., Versacci, P., Anaclerio, S., Lambiase, C., Calcagni, G., Trezzi, M., Carotti, A., <lb/>Crowley, T. B., Zackai, E. H., Goldmuntz, E., et al. (2018). Congenital heart <lb/>diseases and cardiovascular abnormalities in 22q11.2 deletion syndrome: From well-<lb/>established knowledge to new frontiers. American Journal of Medical Genetics Part A <lb/>176, 2087-2098. <lb/>van Bueren, K. L., Papangeli, I., Rochais, F., Pearce, K., Roberts, C., Calmont, A., <lb/>Szumska, D., Kelly, R. G., Bhattacharya, S. and Scambler, P. J. (2010). Hes1 <lb/>expression is reduced in Tbx1 null cells and is required for the development of <lb/>structures affected in 22q11 deletion syndrome. Dev Biol 340, 369-380. <lb/>Van Mierop, L. H. S. and Kutsche, L. M. (1986). Cardiovascular anomalies in digeorge <lb/>syndrome and importance of neural crest as a possible pathogenetic factor. The <lb/>American Journal of Cardiology 58, 133-137. <lb/>Waldo, K. L., Kumiski, D. and Kirby, M. L. (1996). Cardiac neural crest is essential for the <lb/>persistence rather than the formation of an arch artery. Dev Dyn 205, 281-292. <lb/>Xu, H., Morishima, M., Wylie, J. N., Schwartz, R. J., Bruneau, B. G., Lindsay, E. A. and <lb/>Baldini, A. (2004). Tbx1 has a dual role in the morphogenesis of the cardiac outflow <lb/>tract. Development 131, 3217-3227. <lb/>Zhang, Z., Cerrato, F., Xu, H., Vitelli, F., Morishima, M., Vincentz, J., Furuta, Y., Ma, L., <lb/>Martin, J. F., Baldini, A., et al. (2005). Tbx1 expression in pharyngeal epithelia is <lb/>necessary for pharyngeal arch artery development. Development 132, 5307-5315. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Loss of Pax9 results in cardiovascular developmental defects. <lb/>A, Arch arteries of control neonates were normal (n=8). B, Pax9 -/-neonates (n=5) displayed <lb/>interrupted aortic arch (IAA), absent right subclavian artery (presumed retro-esophageal), <lb/>and atypical right and left carotid arteries (LC, RC). Scale, 1mm. C-H, E14.5 histology. C-E, <lb/>Pax9 +/+ embryos show normal outflow tract, arch arteries and thymus. F-H, In Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos (n=4) the aorta (Ao) arises aberrantly from the right ventricle giving double-outlet <lb/>right ventricle (DORV; F). The aorta is hypoplastic and interrupted (IAA), and an aberrant <lb/>right subclavian artery (A-RSA) is present (G). More cranially the thymus is absent and <lb/>aberrant internal and external carotid arteries (iRCA, eRCA, iLCA, eLCA) are seen. I-L, 3-D <lb/>reconstructions of E15.5 hearts from MRI datasets. I, Pax9 +/+ embryo with normal aortic arch <lb/>arteries. J-L, In Pax9 -/-embryos (n=15) defects seen are DORV with interventricular <lb/>communication (IVC), IAA, A-RSA (retro-esophageal in J, K and isolated in L) and aberrant <lb/>carotid arteries. Scale, 500μm. M-O, The ascending aorta is significantly smaller in Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos (n=5) compared to Pax9 +/-control embryos (n=7). Mean ± s.e.m.; ****p&lt;0.0001; <lb/>two-tailed unpaired t-test. P, Pax9 +/-control embryos have three normal aortic valve leaflets <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>(n=6), the right (RC), left (LC) and non-coronary (NC). Q, Pax9 -/-embryos (n=5) have <lb/>bicuspid aortic valve. Scale, 100μm. Abbreviations: Ao, aorta; AoA, aortic arch; AD, arterial <lb/>duct; BC, brachiocephalic; dAo, dorsal aorta; LCC, left common carotid artery; LSA, left <lb/>subclavian artery; LV, left ventricle; RCC, right common carotid artery; RSA, right subclavian <lb/>artery; RV, right ventricle; Th, thymus. <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Pax9 loss causes aberrations in pharyngeal arch artery formation. <lb/>A-C, Coronal views of control (Pax9 +/+ ) and mutant (Pax9 -/-) embryos at E10.5 (30-40s), <lb/>examined by high-resolution episcopic microscopy. A, In Pax9 +/+ control embryos (n=5) the <lb/>3 rd , 4 th and 6 th PAA are of equal size and bilaterally symmetrical. B, C, In Pax9 -/-embryos <lb/>(n=4) the 4 th PAA was bilaterally absent (asterisk), the 3 rd PAA and aortic sac (as) were <lb/>hypoplastic, and the 1 st and/or 2 nd PAA abnormally persisted. D-F, Intracardiac ink injection <lb/>into E10.5-E11.0 (31-42s) embryos. D, In control embryos (n=12) PAA 3-6 are patent to ink, <lb/>are of equivalent diameter and bilaterally symmetrical. E, F, In Pax9 -/-embryos (n=12) the <lb/>3 rd PAA is hypoplastic and the 4 th PAA non-patent to ink (asterisk). F, The 1 st and 2 nd PAA <lb/>are persisting anomalously. G-I, Immunostaining using Pecam1 antibody at E10.5 (31-36s). <lb/>G, Control embryos (n=3) have a ring of Pecam1 labelled endothelium lining the 3 rd and 4 th <lb/>PAA. H, I, In Pax9 -/-embryos (n=5) the 3 rd PAA is visibly smaller and disorganized <lb/>endothelial cells are within the 4 th pharyngeal arch (pa; arrows). Somite counts (s) indicated. <lb/>Scale, 100μm. <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Pax9 -/-embryos display aberrant rotation of the outflow tract and abnormal <lb/>PAA remodelling. <lb/>Image datasets were acquired by high-resolution episcopic microscopy. A-D, 3-D <lb/>reconstructions of the PAA at E11.5 (45-50s). A, In Pax9 +/+ control embryos (n=5) the <lb/>outflow tract is septated, the right 6 th PAA has thinned and the carotid duct (cd) has begun to <lb/>involute. B-D, In Pax9 -/-embryos (n=4) the 4 th PAA are absent and the 3 rd PAA are <lb/>aberrantly connected or detached from the dorsal aorta (asterisks). The carotid duct has <lb/>failed to involute and septation of the outflow tract is delayed. Persisting 1 st or 2 nd PAA are <lb/>observed coursing anteriorly from the abnormal 3 rd PAA (B, D) or from the aortic sac (C). E, <lb/>F, Looping of the heart tube at E10.5 was not affected in Pax9 -/-embryos (n=4). G-L, <lb/>Outflow tract rotation from E10.5 to E11.5 (39-49s). G-I, In control embryos the major outflow <lb/>tract cushions (parietal in green; septal in yellow) rotated in an anti-clockwise direction <lb/>resulting in the cushions being aligned side-by-side. J-L, In Pax9 -/-embryos the cushions <lb/>rotated in a clockwise direction resulting in the parietal cushion anterior to the septal <lb/>cushion. Abbreviations: as, aortic sac; at, aortic trunk; da, dorsal aorta; pa, pulmonary <lb/>arteries; pt, pulmonary trunk. Somite (s) counts indicated. Scale, 100μm. <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. Failure in smooth muscle cell recruitment causes the 3 rd PAA to collapse. <lb/>A-D, E15.5 embryos with a Pax9 conditional deletion in neural crest cells (NCC) were <lb/>examined by MRI. A, Control embryos had a normal palate (P). B, Pax9 f/f ;Wnt1Cre mutant <lb/>embryos (n=6) had cleft palate (CP). C, D, No cardiovascular defects were observed in <lb/>control or mutant embryos. Abbreviations as in Figure 1. E-J, NCC in Pax9 +/+ (E, G, I) or <lb/>Pax9 -/-(F, H, J) embryos were labelled using Wnt1Cre and eYFP alleles. E, F, <lb/>Fluorescence imaging showed no difference in NCC migration into the pharyngeal arches <lb/>(arrowheads) in control (n=7; 31-34s) and mutant embryos (n=5; 28-35s). G, H, Labelled <lb/>NCC viewed by confocal microscopy also showed similar NCC migration patterns in control <lb/>and mutant embryos (arrowheads). I, J, Fluorescent embryos were sectioned coronally and <lb/>immunostained using anti-GFP and anti-Pax9 antibodies. J, The caudal pharyngeal arches <lb/>were smaller in Pax9 -/-embryos. K-L, Embryo sections at E10.5 were immunostained with <lb/>anti-BrdU and anti-GFP antibodies to detect proliferation in NCC in Pax9 +/+ (K) and Pax9 -/-<lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>(L) embryos at E10.5 (n=5 per genotype; 31-39s). M, No significant difference in the rate of <lb/>proliferation was found between control and Pax9 -/-NCC. N-O, Embryo sections at E10.5 <lb/>were immunostained with an anti-Caspase3 antibody to detect apoptosis in the caudal <lb/>pharyngeal arches of Pax9 +/+ (N) and Pax9 -/-(O) embryos at E10.5 (n=3 per genotype; 31-<lb/>35s). Higher magnification views shown in dashed boxes (N&apos;, O&apos;). P, No significant <lb/>difference in the rate of apoptosis was found between control and Pax9 -/-embryos. Two-<lb/>tailed unpaired t-test. Q-T, E10.5 embryo sections were immunostained using anti-αSMA <lb/>and anti-Pecam1 antibodies for smooth muscle and endothelium respectively (Q, S) or anti-<lb/>αSMA and anti-GFP to label NCC in Wnt1Cre;eYFP embryos (R, T). In all control embryos <lb/>smooth muscle cells surrounding the 3 rd PAA was observed (n=4; 31-36s; Q, R). In Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos the 3 rd PAA had no visible recruitment of smooth muscle cells (n=6; 32-35s; S, T). <lb/>Abbreviations: en, endoderm; mc, mesenchyme; pa, pharyngeal arch. Somite counts (s) <lb/>indicated. Scales: A -D, 500μm; E-O, 100μm; Q-T, 50µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5. Pax9 shares a genetic network with Tbx1. <lb/>A, The pharyngeal arch region of control and Pax9 -/-embryos at E9.5 (n=3 per genotype; <lb/>26-27s) was dissected free (indicated by arrows and dashed lines). Scale, 500µm. B, Total <lb/>RNA was extracted, converted to cDNA and checked by qPCR. C, Principle component <lb/>analysis of RNA-seq data showed a clear separation between control and mutant samples <lb/>(shown on PC2) and only slight biological variation across replicates (shown on PC1). D, <lb/>Tbx1-related genes (n=1476) were compared to those genes significantly differentially <lb/>expressed in Pax9 -/-embryo tissue (n=3863, adjusted p value &lt;0.1) giving 342 genes <lb/>common to both datasets. E, Volcano plot highlighting Tbx1 interacting genes significantly <lb/>differentially expressed in Pax9 -/-embryos (based on adjusted p value £0.05). F, Heat map <lb/>showing Tbx1-Pax9 common genes that were differentially expressed (adjusted p value <lb/>£0.05 are shown) between Pax9 +/+ (wt) and Pax9 -/-(mt) embryos. G-J, qPCR analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>confirmed that Pax9 (G), Tbx1 (H), Chd7 (I) and Gbx2 (J) were significantly reduced in <lb/>Pax9 -/-pharyngeal tissue (n=5 embryos per genotype). **p&lt;0.01; two-tailed unpaired t-test <lb/>(Tbx1 and Chd7) and two-tailed Mann-Whitney (Pax9 and Gbx2). <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Tbx1;Pax9 double heterozygous embryos have 4 th PAA defects. <lb/>A-D, Neonates from a Tbx1 +/-and Pax9 +/-intercross were recovered and the aortic arches <lb/>examined. A, Aortic arches were normal in all Pax9 +/-neonates (n=10). B, Tbx1 +/-neonates <lb/>(n=6) often presented with aberrant right subclavian artery, inferred by the absence of the <lb/>brachiocephalic and right subclavian arteries. C, D, All Tbx1 +/-; Pax9 +/-neonates (n=9) died <lb/>within 24 h of birth with IAA and/or A-RSA. E-H, 3-D reconstructions of E15.5 embryo hearts <lb/>from MRI datasets. E, Pax9 +/-hearts were normal (n=15). F, Tbx1 +/-hearts (n=19) frequently <lb/>displayed 4 th PAA defects such as A-RSA. G, H, All Tbx1 +/-; Pax9 +/-embryos (n=20) <lb/>presented with a 4 th PAA-derived defect such as IAA, A-RSA and cervical right subclavian <lb/>artery (cRSA). I-L, Intracardiac ink injections into E10.5 embryos (27-38s). I, PAA in control <lb/>embryos was normal (n=10). J, In Tbx1 +/-embryos (n=8) the 4 th PAA was often hypoplastic. <lb/>K, L, In Tbx1 +/-; Pax9 +/-embryos (n=9) the 4 th PAA was frequently bilaterally absent. <lb/>Abbreviations as Figure 1. Somite counts (s) indicated. Scale: A-D, 2mm; E-H, 500μm; I-L, <lb/>100μm. <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Generation of the Pax9Cre mouse. <lb/>A, A Pax9Cre targeting vector was created with a Cre cassette inserted into the SmaI <lb/>restriction sites found in exons 2 and 3 of the Pax9 gene. For transformation the vector was <lb/>linearised with SfiI. B, Correctly targeted ES cells were identified by Southern blotting on <lb/>XbaI (X) digested genomic DNA. The derived Pax9Cre-Neo mice were crossed with FLPe-<lb/>expressing mice to remove the Neomycin cassette and create Pax9Cre mice, which were <lb/>genotyped using the indicated primers (C). D-G, Pax9Cre mice were mated with R26R lacZ <lb/>reporter mice and embryos were stained with X-Gal at E8.5 (n=3), E9.5 (n=7), E10.5 (n=6) <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>and E11.5 (n=5). Positive staining in regions known to express Pax9 was observed (alb, <lb/>anterior limb bud; np, nasal process; pp, pharyngeal pouch; vc, vertebral column). H-Q, <lb/>Pax9Cre and Pax9 flox/flox mice were crossed to create Pax9 +/flox (control) and Pax9 Cre/flox <lb/>(mutant) mice. All Pax9 Cre/flox neonates died on the day of birth and presented with the typical <lb/>Pax9-null phenotype (n=5), including a bloated abdomen (I, arrow) and pre-axial digit <lb/>duplication (d) in the hind limb (K, arrow). Sections of E14.5-E15.5 embryos (n=6) showed <lb/>cleft palate (CP; M), absent thymus and cardiovascular defects (O, Q). Abbreviations as <lb/>Figure 1. Somite counts (s) indicated. Scale, 500µm. <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 8. Conditional deletion of Tbx1 from the pharyngeal endoderm. <lb/>A, Pax9Cre drives expression of the eYFP reporter gene in the pharyngeal endoderm at <lb/>E9.5. Scale, 500 µm. B-D, Flow sorting and qPCR of eYFP-positive and -negative <lb/>pharyngeal arch cells from Pax9Cre;eYFP control and Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre E9.5 embryos (n=5 <lb/>of each; dissected as shown in A). From control embryos the eYFP-positive cells (yellow <lb/>circles) were significantly enriched for eYFP (B) and Pax9 (C) compared to eYFP-negative <lb/>cells (black squares). D, There was a significant reduction in Tbx1 levels in <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre (mutant) eYFP-positive cells (yellow squares) compared to controls <lb/>(yellow circles). *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01; two-tailed unpaired t-test. E-J, Cardiovascular defects in <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre mice. E, F, Neonates were collected shortly after birth and the aortic arch <lb/>arteries examined. E, Control neonates (n=39 wild-type, n=43 Pax9Cre and n=33 Tbx1 +/flox ) <lb/>all had normal arch arteries. F, Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre mutants (n=8) had cardiovascular defects <lb/>such as a right-sided aorta (R-Ao) and A-RSA. Scale, 1mm. G, H, Embryos at E13.5-E15.5 <lb/>were analysed by imaging (n=27 mutants). G, Control embryo with normal cardiovascular <lb/>system. H, In the mutant there is a vascular ring formed by a R-Ao and an A-RSA. Scale, <lb/>500µm. I, J, Embryos collected at E10.5 (38-43s) were injected intra-cardially with ink. I, In <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox control embryos (n=15) PAA 3-6 were patent to ink. J, In Tbx1 +/flox ;Pax9Cre mutant <lb/>embryos (n=17) the 4 th PAA was frequently absent. Somite counts (s) are indicated. Scale, <lb/>100µm. Abbreviations as Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 9. Proposed model for role of Pax9 mediated signalling during pharyngeal arch <lb/>artery development. <lb/>A, In wild-type embryos Pax9 expression in the 3 rd pharyngeal arch endoderm induces <lb/>neural crest cells (NCC), either directly or indirectly, to differentiate into the smooth muscle <lb/>cells that invest around the endothelium of the remodelling 3 rd PAA. In the 4 th arch <lb/>endoderm, Tbx1 and Pax9 function together to control formation of the 4 th PAA, potentially <lb/>through collaboration with Chd7 and Gbx2. B, In Pax9 deficient embryos, signals from the <lb/>3 rd pharyngeal arch endoderm are compromised and NCC differentiation into smooth muscle <lb/>cells is impaired resulting in the collapse of the 3 rd PAA by E11.5. In Tbx1-Pax9 double <lb/>heterozygous embryos, reduced levels of Tbx1 and Pax9 in the 4 th pharyngeal arch <lb/>endoderm are insufficient to allow the 4 th PAA to form. <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tables <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Stage <lb/>n <lb/>VSD <lb/>DORV <lb/>+ IVC <lb/>IAA a <lb/>IAA + <lb/>A-RSA a <lb/>A-<lb/>RSA b <lb/>Cervical <lb/>AoA + <lb/>A-RSA <lb/>Absent <lb/>CC c <lb/>Pax9 -/-<lb/>Neonate 5 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>(100%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>(40%) <lb/>E14.5-<lb/>E15.5 <lb/>19 <lb/>3 <lb/>(16%) <lb/>15 <lb/>(79%) <lb/>3 <lb/>(16%) <lb/>14 <lb/>(74%) <lb/>2 <lb/>(11%) <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>(79%) <lb/>Tbx1 +/-<lb/>Neonate <lb/>6 <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>(17%) <lb/>3 <lb/>(50%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>(11%) <lb/>5 <lb/>(55%) <lb/>2 <lb/>(22%) <lb/>1 <lb/>(11%) <lb/>0 <lb/>Tbx1 +/-<lb/>E15.5 <lb/>19 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>(5%) <lb/>9 <lb/>(47%) <lb/>2 <lb/>(11%) <lb/>0 <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>20 <lb/>6* <lb/>(30%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>14** <lb/>(70%) <lb/>3 <lb/>(15%) <lb/>4 <lb/>(20%) <lb/>0 <lb/>Table 1. Cardiovascular defects observed in mutant embryos (&gt;E14.5) and neonates. <lb/>Pax9 -/-neonates (n=5) were analysed by dissection, and embryos at E14.5 by histology <lb/>(n=4) and at E15.5 by MRI (n=15). Tbx1 +/-(n=19) and Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-(n=20) embryos were <lb/>analysed by MRI. All wild-type (n=16) and Pax9 +/-(n=15) embryos assessed were normal. <lb/>There was a statistically significant increase in the incidence of VSD and IAA in the <lb/>Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-embryos compared to the Tbx1 +/-embryos; *p&lt;0.05; **p&lt;0.0001; Pearson&apos;s <lb/>chi-squared test for associations. <lb/>a Combined incidence of interrupted aortic arch (IAA), irrespective of co-occurrence with <lb/>aberrant right subclavian artery (A-RSA), in Pax9 -/-neonates and embryos (n=24), was 92% <lb/>(n=19 type-B and n=3 type-C). <lb/>b A-RSA refers to a retroesophageal, cervical origin or isolated right subclavian artery. Two <lb/>Pax9 -/-embryos had isolated RSA. <lb/>c Absent common carotid artery (CC), resulting in the internal and external carotid arteries <lb/>arising directly from the main aortic vessels, unilaterally (n=4) or bilaterally (n=11) in Pax9 -/-<lb/>embryos. <lb/>Abbreviations: AoA, aortic arch; DORV + IVC, double-outlet right ventricle with <lb/>interventricular communication; VSD, perimembranous ventricular septal defect; NA, not <lb/>assessed. <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>Bilateral defects <lb/>Genotype <lb/>n <lb/>PAA <lb/>Abnormal <lb/>(%) <lb/>Unilateral <lb/>defect <lb/>Bilateral <lb/>defect <lb/>Present <lb/>Hypo/Int/ <lb/>Abs <lb/>Absent <lb/>Pax9 -/-<lb/>20 <lb/>1 <lb/>11 (55%) <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>8 (40%) <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>3 <lb/>15 (75%) <lb/>3 <lb/>12 <lb/>-<lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>20 (100%) <lb/>1 <lb/>19 <lb/>-<lb/>3 <lb/>16 <lb/>Tbx1 +/-<lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 (100%) <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>-<lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>Tbx1 +/-; <lb/>Pax9 +/-<lb/>9 <lb/>4 <lb/>9 (100%) <lb/>1 <lb/>8 <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>7* <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox <lb/>15 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Tbx1 +/flox ; <lb/>Pax9Cre <lb/>17 <lb/>4 <lb/>16 (92%) <lb/>3 <lb/>13 <lb/>-<lb/>7 <lb/>6 <lb/>Table 2. Pharyngeal arch artery defects. <lb/>Embryos were collected and assessed for PAA defects. Pax9 -/-embryos were either injected <lb/>intra-cardially with ink (E10.5; n=12) or imaged using HREM (E10.5-E11.5; n=8) to visualise <lb/>the PAA. Data are combined. For Pax9 -/-embryos each left and right PAA 1-4 was scored <lb/>as having a unilateral or bilateral defect, and the bilateral defects categorised as either <lb/>present, a combination of hypoplastic, interrupted and/or absent (Hypo/Int/Abs), and <lb/>bilaterally absent. For Tbx1;Pax9 genotypes ink injection was performed at E10.5 and only <lb/>the 4 th PAA was scored. The increase in bilaterally absent 4 th PAA in Tbx1 +/-;Pax9 +/-<lb/>embryos is significant compared to Tbx1 +/-embryos; *p=0.004; Pearson&apos;s chi-squared test <lb/>for associations. All control embryos, Pax9 +/+ (n=18), Pax9 +/-(n=25), were normal. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
