<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Noname manuscript No. <lb/>(will be inserted by the editor) <lb/>A generic deviance detection principle for cortical On/Off <lb/>responses, omission response, and mismatch negativity <lb/>Shih-Cheng Chien • Burkhard Maess • Thomas R. Knösche <lb/>Received: date / Accepted: date <lb/> Abstract Neural responses to sudden changes can be <lb/>observed in many parts of the sensory pathways at dif-<lb/>ferent organizational levels. For example, deviants that <lb/>violate regularity at various levels of abstraction can <lb/>be observed as simple On/Off responses of individual <lb/>neurons or as cumulative responses of neural popula-<lb/>tions. The cortical deviance-related responses support-<lb/>ing different functionalities (e.g. gap detection, chunk-<lb/>ing, etc.) seem unlikely to arise from different function-<lb/>specific neural circuits, given the relatively uniform and <lb/>self-similar wiring patterns across cortical areas and <lb/>spatial scales. Additionally, reciprocal wiring patterns <lb/>(with heterogeneous combinations of excitatory and in-<lb/>hibitory connections) in the cortex naturally speak in <lb/>favor of a generic deviance detection principle. Based on <lb/>this concept, we propose a network model consisting of <lb/>reciprocally coupled neural masses as a blueprint of a <lb/>universal change detector. Simulation examples repro-<lb/>duce properties of cortical deviance-related responses <lb/>including the On/Off responses, the omitted-stimulus <lb/>response (OSR), and the mismatch negativity (MMN). <lb/>We propose that the emergence of change detectors <lb/>relies on the involvement of disinhibition. The analy-<lb/>sis on network connection settings further suggests a <lb/>supportive effect of synaptic adaptation and a destruc-<lb/>tive effect of N-methyl-D-aspartate receptor (NMDA-<lb/>r) antagonists on change detection. We conclude that <lb/>the nature of cortical reciprocal wirings gives rise to <lb/>a whole range of local change detectors supporting the <lb/> This study is funded by IMPRS NeuroCom. <lb/>http://imprs-neurocom.mpg.de <lb/>Thomas R. Knösche <lb/>Max Planck Institute for Human Cognitive and Brain Sci-<lb/>ences, Stephanstraße 1a Leipzig, Germany <lb/>E-mail: knoesche@cbs.mpg.de <lb/>notion of a generic deviance detection principle. Several <lb/>testable predictions are provided based on the network <lb/>model. Notably, we predict that the NMDA-r antago-<lb/>nists would generally dampen the cortical Off response, <lb/>the cortical OSR, and the MMN. <lb/>Keywords Deviance detection • Neural mass model • <lb/>Auditory perception • Adaptation • NMDA <lb/></front>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Automatic detection of sudden acoustic changes cru-<lb/>cially enables reorientation of attention towards rele-<lb/>vant events in the environment and thereby is impor-<lb/>tant for survival. From a functional perspective, the <lb/>sensitivity to deviants at the various levels serves differ-<lb/>ent functionalities (e.g. noise rejection, duration tuning, <lb/>chunking and grouping, beat perception, see reviews <lb/>in [58, 106]) and enriches the hierarchical representa-<lb/>tions of percepts. The ability to detect abrupt tempo-<lb/>ral changes is thought to be a pervasive property of the <lb/>sensory systems, given that deviance-related responses <lb/>have been widely observed from cellular to system lev-<lb/>els, across species, sensory modalities, and spanning <lb/>from the lower levels of the sensory pathway to the cor-<lb/>tex. For example, some cells can be sensitive only to the <lb/>onsets and offsets of stimuli. These On/Off responses <lb/>have been observed using extracellular recording in the <lb/>superior paraolivary nucleus (SPON) of rodents [7, 19, <lb/>21, 44, 47], inferior colliculus (IC) of chinchillas [24], me-<lb/>dial geniculate body (MGB) of the guinea pig [26]. <lb/>Cortical On/Off responses have been observed using <lb/>different recording and imaging techniques, including <lb/>single-cell recording in primary auditory cortex (A1) <lb/>of awake cats [16, 69], and anesthetized rats [80], ex-<lb/>tracellular recording in A1 of awake marmoset mon-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>keys [76], surface micro-electrode array in auditory cor-<lb/>tex (AC) of rats [92], multi-unit extracellular record-<lb/>ings across broad range of AC of mice [39], flavopro-<lb/>tein fluorescence imaging [4] and two-photon calcium <lb/>imaging [4, 20] in AC of mice, and MEG in human au-<lb/>ditory evoked responses [61]. Generally speaking, these <lb/>cells can be sensitive to the sudden changes in specific <lb/>regular features such as the constancy in pitch, loud-<lb/>ness, duration, and patterns. The deviants that violate <lb/>these perceptual regularities trigger mismatch response <lb/>at different stages such as frequency following responses <lb/>(FFR), middle latency responses (MLR), as well as long <lb/>latency responses (LLR) such as the mismatch nega-<lb/>tivity (MMN) [85]. An omitted stimulus in a periodic <lb/>train of stimuli is a special case of deviants, which elic-<lb/>its the so-called omitted-stimulus responses /potentials <lb/>(OSRs/OSPs). The OSR is time-locked not to the last <lb/>but to the omitted stimulus, which reflects temporal ex-<lb/>pectancy represented in the neural circuits. OSRs have <lb/>been observed in different sensory systems (e.g., visual, <lb/>auditory, somatosensory) in various species, for exam-<lb/>ple, the visual pathway of fish, reptile, and invertebrate <lb/>in vivo [12, 68, 71, 40], retinas of salamander in vitro [83, <lb/>104], and the electrosensory system of rays [14]. The <lb/>OSR at the cortical level (often termed as omission re-<lb/>sponse or omission MMN) has also been observed in hu-<lb/>man EEG/MEG [29, 2, 13, 41, 15]. So far, investigations <lb/>of the underlying mechanisms have been mostly con-<lb/>fined in a certain level and a particular phenomenon. <lb/>A unifying view of deviance detection that considers <lb/>phenomena across levels is still missing. <lb/>Many of the deviance-related activities, though orig-<lb/>inating from different stages of the auditory pathway, <lb/>can be observed pervasively in the auditory cortex. We <lb/>hypothesize that the cortical deviance-related activi-<lb/>ties are primarily generated locally through reciprocally <lb/>connected neural circuits. In this study, we outline a <lb/>generic deviance detection principle, in an effort to rec-<lb/>oncile some confusions and conflictions related to the <lb/>questions below. <lb/>What neural circuits give rise to the diverse <lb/>cortical On/Off responses? The response of a neu-<lb/>ron or a neural circuit to a sustained stimulus can bear <lb/>three basic features: a response to the stimulus onset <lb/>(On response), a sustained response as long the stim-<lb/>ulus is present, and a response to the stimulus offset <lb/>(Off response). The On/Off responses are found in neu-<lb/>rons of the superior paraolivary nucleus (SPON) of the <lb/>brainstem, the inferior colliculus (IC) of the midbrain <lb/>[22], and the auditory cortex [80, 4, 20]. These On/Off <lb/>neurons are thought to support functions such as du-<lb/>ration selectivity (duration tuning), gap detection, and <lb/>noise rejection [106]. Knowledge in the generation of <lb/>On/Off responses is mainly derived from observations <lb/>at non-cortical stages. The On responses are thought <lb/>to be due to adaptive and post-onset inhibitory mech-<lb/>anisms that shape the responses in the auditory nerve <lb/>[66]. The Off responses are widely accepted to arise from <lb/>post-inhibitory rebound (see review in [43] for the de-<lb/>tailed celluar and synaptic mechanisms), as concluded <lb/>from observation in SPON neurons [21]. Other response <lb/>patterns such as On-Off, On-sustained-Off can then po-<lb/>tentially be explained by mixing of excitatory and in-<lb/>hibitory inputs with different delays in a feed-forward <lb/>network [106]. As for the On/Off responses recorded in <lb/>the auditory cortex, they may originate from the as-<lb/>cending non-cortical On/Off responses [80] or be gen-<lb/>erated locally in the cortex. The cortical On/Off neu-<lb/>rons show diverse temporal profiles [20]. Also, a sin-<lb/>gle cortical neuron may have distinct onset-and offset-<lb/>frequency receptive fields (FRFs) [69]. It is still unclear <lb/>how the neural circuits give rise to these properties of <lb/>cortical On/Off responses. <lb/>Is the OSR just sustained resonance? The OSR, <lb/>elicited by an unexpected omission in periodic stim-<lb/>uli, is found in the cortex [29, 2, 13, 41, 15], but not in <lb/>the midbrain (IC, tectum) [61] and the brainstem [50], <lb/>where only Off responses are observed. The OSR re-<lb/>sembles the Off response as they both peak at the end <lb/>of a stimulus (or a train of stimuli), except that the <lb/>OSR also reflects temporal expectancy (i.e., neural rep-<lb/>resentation of periodicity), which distinguishes it from <lb/>the Off response. The properties of the OSR include: <lb/>(1) The peak latency includes an additional constant <lb/>delay (e.g., around 100 ms in human MEG/EEG) af-<lb/>ter the due-time of the missing stimulus which does <lb/>not depend on the stimulus-onset asynchrony (SOA) of <lb/>stimuli [2, 84]. (2) The peak amplitude can be larger <lb/>than the entrained responses during periodic stimuli <lb/>[29]. Althought neural activities that show sustained <lb/>resonance can be a mechanism underlying the temporal <lb/>expectancy [52, 94], sustained response alone does not <lb/>explain the additional delay and higher peak amplitude. <lb/>How the neural circuits maintain the input periodicity <lb/>and detect the change is unclear. <lb/>Does the OSR reflect prediction or prediction <lb/>error? This question rests on whether the OSR is trig-<lb/>gered by a similar mechanism as the MMN. The MMN, <lb/>elicited by a deviant among repetitive standard stim-<lb/>uli, is a negative deflection in the event-related potential <lb/>(ERP) with the sources most prominently localized in <lb/>the auditory cortex. The underlying process leads to the <lb/>reorientation of attention for higher cognitive processes. <lb/>Deviants which differed in a variety of sound properties <lb/>from the standard have been shown to elicit MMNs, <lb/>for example pitch [78, 95, 56, 93, 108, 109, 33, 64, 63], in-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>tensity [57, 73], duration [1, 75, 59, 30, 57, 103, 81, 32, 31, <lb/>17,36], SOA [46, 97, 11], sequence (or pattern) [82, 28, <lb/>10,112, 45, 96], and more complex features such as ris-<lb/>ing and falling tones (reviewed in [65]) or voice [42]. The <lb/>MMN is generally accepted to be elicited by the deviant <lb/>that violates the regularities, but the underlying mech-<lb/>anism is still under debate. The MMN is thought to <lb/>reflect either the prediction-error signal resulting from <lb/>the comparison between the input and the top-down <lb/>prediction (prediction hypothesis), or the fresh stimu-<lb/>lus propagating through un-adapted synapses (adapta-<lb/>tion hypothesis). The omission paradigms that elicit the <lb/>OSR are often used in the debate to emphasize the need <lb/>for active prediction, since the adaptation mechanism <lb/>alone does not produce extra neural activities without <lb/>any input. However, according to the computational <lb/>models based on either hypothesis, the OSR is quali-<lb/>tatively different from the classical MMNs elicited by <lb/>other deviants. The adaptation-based model suggests <lb/>the OSR to be a rebound response (i.e. sustained reso-<lb/>nance) rather than a modulated N1 [52]. The prediction-<lb/>based model suggests the OSR to reflect predictive sig-<lb/>nals rather than prediction error [102]. Both interpre-<lb/>tations implicitly suggest pure endogenous activities <lb/>where a change detection mechanism is not involved, <lb/>which conflicts with the two properties of ORS men-<lb/>tioned above. The interpretation to MMN generation <lb/>therefore is not comprehensive yet. <lb/>The above issues underscore the need for a unifying <lb/>view to deviance detection covering the cortical On/Off <lb/>responses, the cortical OSR, and the MMN. Given the <lb/>non-specific wiring patterns across areas in the cortex, <lb/>we ask whether cortical deviance detection can be sup-<lb/>ported by neural circuits of a common structural mo-<lb/>tif. We propose a generic deviance detection principle <lb/>(Figure 1a), where change detection can take place lo-<lb/>cally under proper reciprocal connections (Figure 1b), <lb/>monitoring the neighboring neural activities that rep-<lb/>resent a regular feature. This principle is based on the <lb/>assumption that the process of deviance detection can <lb/>be functionally separated into stages of regularity for-<lb/>mation and change detection. <lb/>In the first part of the Results section, we provide <lb/>simulation examples that reproduce several properties <lb/>of cortical On/Off responses, cortical OSR, and MMN. <lb/>In examples I and II, we demonstrate that the various <lb/>types of cortical On/Off responses in terms of their tem-<lb/>poral profiles and frequency receptive fields (RFRs) can <lb/>be attributed to the connection patterns between input <lb/>and observation points. In example III, we demonstrate <lb/>that the OSR can be regarded as a change detection <lb/>response (or an Off response) to the cessation of con-<lb/>stant periodicity, In example IV, we demonstrate that <lb/>R-C pair for <lb/>deviance detection <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>f <lb/>f C <lb/>f <lb/>f <lb/>f <lb/>f R <lb/>f C <lb/>f <lb/>f <lb/>f <lb/>feature representation <lb/>Levels of <lb/>Node 2 <lb/>E <lb/>I <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>W <lb/>Input1 Input2 <lb/>E <lb/>I <lb/>Excitatory <lb/>Inhibitory <lb/>Input 1 <lb/>Input 2 <lb/>Node 1 <lb/>Fig. 1 Illustration of the role of deviance detection in hier-<lb/>archical feature representation. a The process of feature rep-<lb/>resentation includes the interaction between regularity for-<lb/>mation (R) and change detection (C). The R nodes repre-<lb/>sent temporally stable feature (regularity, f R ) by accumulat-<lb/>ing and extracting the ascending information from the lower-<lb/>level features. The C nodes detect abrupt temporal changes <lb/>in the neighboring R node(s) and pass them as new features <lb/>(f C , gray arrows) to the higher levels. In this sense, an R-<lb/>C pair forms a basic mechanism of deviance detection which <lb/>takes place at every level in the hierarchy. b An R-C pair is <lb/>formed by two reciprocally coupled nodes. In the simulations, <lb/>all nodes are allowed to receive external weighted inputs that <lb/>reach the excitatory and inhibitory populations. The inter-<lb/>node connections (green) are the free parameters, and the <lb/>intra-node connections are fixed for simplicity. <lb/>the sequence MMN can be regarded as change detec-<lb/>tion responses to the switch in sequence regularity (or <lb/>a mixture of an On response to the deviant and an Off <lb/>response to the cessation of regularities). In the sec-<lb/>ond part of the Results section, we study the underly-<lb/>ing mechanism of change detection by investigating the <lb/>generation of simulated On and Off responses. We then <lb/>study how altered connection patterns (e.g., reduced <lb/>external connections to inhibitory populations, effect <lb/>of NMDA-r antagonists, and synaptic adaptation) af-<lb/>fect the emergence of change detectors. In the Discus-<lb/>sion section, we derive conclusions with regard to the <lb/>above mentioned questions. Finally, we provide testable <lb/>predictions for future verification. <lb/>2 Methods <lb/>2.1 Model description <lb/>The simulations are done with rate-based models which <lb/>allow for a simple and scalable network motif while <lb/>keeping the network dynamics comparable to the exper-<lb/>imental observations such as LFP, MEG/EEG. In the <lb/>simulations, a network is used to represent an area in <lb/>the auditory cortex, and each node in the network com-<lb/>prises one excitatory (E) and one inhibitory (I) neural <lb/>population. The dynamics of the E and I populations <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>are represented by the overall postsynaptic membrane <lb/>potential (PSP) v p (t) and the mean firing rate m p (t), <lb/>p ∈ {E, I}. Neural populations interact with each other <lb/>by means of firing rate via connections defined in the <lb/>matrices W EE , W IE , W EI and W II which correspond <lb/>to excitatory to excitatory, excitatory to inhibitory, in-<lb/>hibitory to excitatory, and inhibitory to inhibitory con-<lb/>nections, respectively. Self-feedback is allowed. All E <lb/>populations in the network are fed with constant back-<lb/>ground input. External stimuli X(t) reach the E and I <lb/>populations via external connections specified by W EX <lb/>and W IX . <lb/>Neural populations The processing of neural activities <lb/>in a population is governed by two operators [34, 35, <lb/>88,89]. The rate-to-potential operator describes a linear <lb/>transformation from the mean firing rate to the mean <lb/>PSP. The input firing rate x c (t), c ∈ {e, i} reaches a <lb/>population via excitatory/inhibitory synapses and is <lb/>transformed to the EPSP/IPSP v c (t) in that popula-<lb/>tion. This transformation is described by the rate-to-<lb/>potential process which is achieved by convolving the <lb/>input firing rate x c (t) with a synaptic kernel h c (t). <lb/>v c (t) = x c (t) ⊗ h c (t) <lb/>(1) <lb/>The synaptic kernels h c (t) describe the synaptic spike <lb/>responses and are specified according to different char-<lb/>acteristics of the excitatory and inhibitory synapses. In <lb/>Equation 2, the average synaptic gain H c controls the <lb/>maximum of the synaptic spike response curve, and the <lb/>time constant τ c represents the delay due to dendritic <lb/>effects and neurotransmitter kinetics. Θ(t) denotes the <lb/>Heaviside step function, where Θ(0) = 1. <lb/>h c (t) = <lb/>H c <lb/>τ c <lb/>tΘ(t)e <lb/>−t <lb/>τc <lb/>(2) <lb/>The convolution in Equation 1 can be further repre-<lb/>sented by two first-order ordinary differential equations: <lb/>v c (t) = u c (t) <lb/>(3) <lb/>u c (t) = <lb/>H c <lb/>τ c <lb/>x(t) − <lb/>2 <lb/>τ c <lb/>u c (t) − <lb/>1 <lb/>τ 2 <lb/>c <lb/>v c (t) <lb/>(4) <lb/>Finally, the overall PSP v(t) in the neural popula-<lb/>tion is the summed effect of EPSP and IPSP. <lb/>v(t) = v e (t) − v i (t) <lb/>(5) <lb/>The potential-to-rate operator transforms v(t) into <lb/>output firing rate m(t) by a non-linear sigmoid function <lb/>S as described in Equation 6, where e 0 controls the <lb/>maximum firing rate and r controls the slope at the <lb/>membrane potential v 0 for firing. <lb/>m(t) = S (v(t)) = <lb/>2e 0 <lb/>1 + e r(v0−v(t)) <lb/>(6) <lb/>Nodes A node, consisting of one excitatory and one in-<lb/>hibitory neural population, represents the basic build-<lb/>ing block in a hierarchical feature representation (Fig-<lb/>ure 1). It represents more as a functional unit rather <lb/>than a structural one such as a &apos;cortical column&apos;. For N <lb/>nodes that represent N locations in the auditory cortex <lb/>and M external inputs that represent the intensity of a <lb/>certain feature such as M tones, the network structure <lb/>is defined by four N × N connection matrices W EE , <lb/>W IE , W EI and W II , and two N × M external connec-<lb/>tion matrices W EX and W IX . Each element w (non-<lb/>negative) in the connection matrices stands for the gain <lb/>factor between the outgoing and incoming firing rates <lb/>of the source and target population, respectively. It de-<lb/>pends on number and strengths of synapses established <lb/>between the two populations. The overall PSP of the <lb/>excitatory population in node j v E <lb/>j (t) is calculated in <lb/>Equation 7 as the joint effect of the EPSP v EE <lb/>j (t) and <lb/>the IPSP v EI <lb/>j (t). <lb/>v E <lb/>j (t) = v EE <lb/>j (t) − v EI <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(7) <lb/>The v EE <lb/>j (t) and v EI <lb/>j (t) are found by solving the dif-<lb/>ferential equations: <lb/>v EE <lb/>j (t) = u EE <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(8) <lb/>u EE <lb/>j (t) = <lb/>H e <lb/>τ e <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>a jk w EE <lb/>jk m E <lb/>k (t) + w EX <lb/>jq X q (t) + B <lb/>− <lb/>2 <lb/>τ e <lb/>u EE <lb/>j (t) − <lb/>1 <lb/>τ 2 <lb/>e <lb/>v EE <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(9) <lb/>v EI <lb/>j (t) = u EI <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(10) <lb/>u EI <lb/>j (t) = <lb/>H i <lb/>τ i <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>w EI <lb/>jk m I <lb/>k (t) − <lb/>2 <lb/>τ i <lb/>u EI <lb/>j (t) − <lb/>1 <lb/>τ 2 <lb/>i <lb/>v EI <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(11) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>In Equation 9 and 11, w EE <lb/>jk , w EI <lb/>jk and w EX <lb/>jq <lb/>are el-<lb/>ements in W EE , W EI and W EX . The element w EI <lb/>jk <lb/>stands for the connection strength from the inhibitory <lb/>population in node k to the excitatory population in <lb/>node j. m E <lb/>k (t) and m I <lb/>k (t) are the outgoing firing rates <lb/>of the excitatory and inhibitory population in node k. <lb/>X q (t) is external input q, and B is a constant back-<lb/>ground input. The synaptic adaptation term a jk modu-<lb/>lates the connections strength w EE <lb/>jk . Similarly, the over-<lb/>all PSP of the inhibitory population in node j v I <lb/>j (t) is <lb/>calculated in Equation 12 as the joint effect of the EPSP <lb/>v IE <lb/>j (t) and the IPSP v II <lb/>j (t). <lb/>v I <lb/>j (t) = v IE <lb/>j (t) − v II <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(12) <lb/>The v IE <lb/>j (t) and v II <lb/>j (t) are found by solving the dif-<lb/>ferential equations: <lb/>v IE <lb/>j (t) = u IE <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(13) <lb/>u IE <lb/>j (t) = <lb/>H e <lb/>τ e <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>w IE <lb/>jk m E <lb/>k (t) + w IX <lb/>jq X q (t) <lb/>− <lb/>2 <lb/>τ e <lb/>u IE <lb/>j (t) − <lb/>1 <lb/>τ 2 <lb/>e <lb/>v IE <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(14) <lb/>v II <lb/>j (t) = u II <lb/>j (t) <lb/>(15) <lb/>u II <lb/>j (t) = <lb/>H i <lb/>τ i <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>w II <lb/>jk m I <lb/>k (t) − <lb/>2 <lb/>τ i <lb/>u II <lb/>j (t)− <lb/>1 <lb/>τ 2 <lb/>i <lb/>v II <lb/>j (t) (16) <lb/>The value of constant background input B is chosen <lb/>so that the nodes work in proper conditions (i.e., near <lb/>bifurcation point for an isolated node). The external <lb/>input X q (t) reaches both the excitatory and inhibitory <lb/>populations in node j with connection strengths w EX <lb/>jq <lb/>and w IX <lb/>jq , where the ratio w IX <lb/>jq /w EX <lb/>jq <lb/>is set to 0.5 by <lb/>default. The synaptic adaptation term a represents the <lb/>efficacy of excitatory to excitatory connections W EE . <lb/>The synaptic efficacy (in range [0,1]) varies according <lb/>to Equation 17 when synaptic adaptation is considered, <lb/>otherwise a is fixed to 1. <lb/>Synaptic adaptation When synaptic adaptation on W EE <lb/>is considered, the connection strength w EE <lb/>jk is modu-<lb/>lated by the term a jk in Equation 9 that varies accord-<lb/>ing to the pre-synaptic activity m E <lb/>k (t). <lb/>a jk (t) = <lb/>1 − a jk (t) <lb/>τ a <lb/>− κa jk (t)m E <lb/>k (t) <lb/>(17) <lb/>The adaptation time constant τ a represents the re-<lb/>covery rate of the synaptic efficacy, and the constant κ <lb/>influences the falling speed and the minimum value of <lb/>a jk (t) according to m E <lb/>k (t). <lb/>Short-term plasticity The short-term plasticity is not <lb/>a focus in this study and is used only in simulation <lb/>example III as a possible solution for the regularity for-<lb/>mation in input periodicity. The plasticity adjusts the <lb/>bindings among the nodes with different resonance so <lb/>that the group response maintains a stable representa-<lb/>tion of input periodicity. The plasticity is applied on <lb/>w EE <lb/>jk and w EI <lb/>jk , where nodes j and k are used to encode <lb/>periodicity. The connection w EE <lb/>jk increases if σ EE <lb/>jk (t, d), <lb/>the covariance between m E <lb/>j (t) and m E <lb/>k (t) during time <lb/>t − d to t, is positive and decreases gradually back to <lb/>zero otherwise (Equations 18,19). Similarly, the connec-<lb/>tion w EI <lb/>jk increases if σ EI <lb/>jk (t, d) is negative and decreases <lb/>gradually back to zero otherwise (Equations 20,21). In <lb/>Equations 19 and 21, η is the learning rate. The weights <lb/>α jk and β jk are calculated from two Gaussian func-<lb/>tions based on the distance between nodes j and k <lb/>(The nodes with similar resonance frequencies are closer <lb/>to each other). This short-term plasticity learning rule <lb/>is rather function-driven than based on biological evi-<lb/>dence. More studies need to be done for a more realistic <lb/>network model that maintains the input periodicity. <lb/>C EE <lb/>jk (t) = max σ EE <lb/>jk (t, d), 0 <lb/>(18) <lb/>w EE <lb/>jk (t) = −w EE <lb/>jk (t) + ηα jk C EE <lb/>jk (t) <lb/>(19) <lb/>C EI <lb/>jk (t) = |min σ EI <lb/>jk (t, d), 0 | <lb/>(20) <lb/>w EI <lb/>jk (t) = −w EI <lb/>jk (t) + ηβ jk C EI <lb/>jk (t) <lb/>(21) <lb/>Simulated MEG signals To synthesize a gross signal <lb/>from the activities of all neural populations in the net-<lb/>work, both the excitatory current (or active sink) and <lb/>inhibitory current (or active source) at the excitatory <lb/>populations (i.e. Pyramidal cells) are taken into account <lb/>[87]. This is a more generalized approach than just con-<lb/>sidering the sum of the excitatory inputs weighted by <lb/>excitatory to excitatory connection strength and the <lb/>adaptation term [54]. For the network of N nodes, the <lb/>simulate MEG signal R(t) is calculated as the weighted <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>sum of currents contributed by the active sinks and <lb/>sources, in an assumption that the active sinks are due <lb/>to the EPSP at apical dendrites through W EE , and <lb/>the active sources are due to be the IPSP at the soma <lb/>through W EI . In order to highlight the activities of spe-<lb/>cific nodes (e.g. the change detectors), the signals are <lb/>weighted by b, where <lb/>N <lb/>j b j = 1. <lb/>R(t) = <lb/>N <lb/>j <lb/>b j <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>a jk (t)w EE <lb/>jk m E <lb/>k (t) + <lb/>N <lb/>k <lb/>w EI <lb/>jk m I <lb/>k (t) <lb/>(22) <lb/>2.2 Model configurations <lb/>The parameter settings of neural population model are <lb/>kept the same as proposed by Jansen and Rit model [34, <lb/>35], unless otherwise specified. In order to reduce the <lb/>number of free parameters, we fix the intra-node con-<lb/>nections and only analyze the inter-node connections <lb/>in the simulations. The values of intra-node connections <lb/>are chosen such that a single node stays inactivated un-<lb/>der weak excitatory input and starts to oscillate as the <lb/>excitatory input strength increases to e 0 (i.e., half of the <lb/>maximum value of the sigmoid function). The adapta-<lb/>tion parameters τ a and κ are chosen such that a single <lb/>node remains oscillating during prolonged stimulation, <lb/>rather than showing only a transient peak response at <lb/>the onset. The general configurations are listed in Table <lb/>1. <lb/>2.3 Categorization of network behavior <lb/>In a two-node network where a prolonged stimulus (2000 <lb/>ms) is fed to node 1 (Figure 2a), the behavior of node <lb/>2 (i.e., the time course m E <lb/>2 (t)) is categorized into one <lb/>of the eight types based on the level changes and the <lb/>peak at edges: (1) sustained-Pure, (2) sustained-On, <lb/>(3) sustained-Off, (4) sustained-On&amp;Off, (5) inhibited-<lb/>Pure, (6) inhibited-On, (7) inhibited-Off, and (8) inhibited-<lb/>On&amp;Off. The &apos;sustained&apos; and &apos;inhibited&apos; stand for in-<lb/>creased and decreased activity during the stimulus. The <lb/>&apos;On&apos;, &apos;Off&apos; and &apos;On&amp;Off&apos; stand for transient peak(s) at <lb/>only the onset, only the offset and both the onset&amp;offset <lb/>of the stimulus. The &apos;Pure&apos; stands for no clear peaks at <lb/>the edges of the stimulus. Bistable behaviors are not in-<lb/>cluded in the categorization. (See Figure 2b and Table <lb/>2 for details of categorization.) <lb/>3 Results <lb/>The generic deviance detection principle suggests that <lb/>deviance detections take place locally in the percep-<lb/>tual hierarchy as illustrated in Figure 1. Any two re-<lb/>ciprocally coupled nodes in a network can potentially <lb/>form an R-C pair that serves deviance detection. The <lb/>connections within an R-C pair can be heterogeneous <lb/>across locations, thus giving rise to various behaviors of <lb/>change detectors. Below, we reproduce some observed <lb/>phenomena of deviance-related responses using simple <lb/>networks (e.g., comprising two, three, and twenty one <lb/>nodes) in simulation examples (Section 3.1), and then <lb/>we investigate the behavior of change detectors and the <lb/>corresponding network settings in Section 3.2. <lb/>3.1 Simulation examples <lb/>Example I: temporal profiles of cortical On/Off responses <lb/>A sustained tone stimulus can elicit diverse temporal <lb/>patterns of On/Off responses in the auditory cortex. <lb/>Neurons can be sensitive to the onset/offset of the stim-<lb/>ulus (i.e., transient responses at the edges), and mean-<lb/>while also show increased or decreased firing rate dur-<lb/>ing the stimulus (i.e., level changes) compared with the <lb/>spontaneous activity [16, 69, 39, 20, 72, 100]. In this simu-<lb/>lation, we feed the input stimulus (2000 ms duration) to <lb/>a two-node network (Figure 2a), where the change de-<lb/>tector does not directly receive the input stimulus (i.e., <lb/>the external connections to node 2, w EX <lb/>2 <lb/>= w IX <lb/>2 <lb/>= 0). <lb/>Varying the inter-node connections W alters the re-<lb/>sponse of the change detector (e.g., the firing rate of its <lb/>excitatory population m E <lb/>2 (t)). We scan through a range <lb/>of inter-node connections (W EE , W IE ∈ {0, 0.1, ..., 0.5}; <lb/>W EI , W II ∈ {0, 0.1, 0.2}), and categorize the time courses <lb/>of m E <lb/>2 (t) into one of the eight types based on the level <lb/>changes and the peak at edges (Figure 2b). The W so-<lb/>lutions are connection settings that give rise to one of <lb/>the eight categorized On/Off types under this specific <lb/>simulation settings (e.g., the intensity and onset/offset <lb/>time of stimulus, the intensity of background input, and <lb/>intra-node connections, etc). <lb/>To further investigate the relation between the inter-<lb/>node connections W and the On/Off responses, we project <lb/>the W solutions {W type i , i = 1, 2, ..., 8} to a 2D plane <lb/>by t-Distributed Stochastic Neighbor Embedding [51] <lb/>to visualize the mutual proximity of W solutions in <lb/>the original eight-dimensional space. From Figure 2d <lb/>we observe that: (1) Although the W solutions show <lb/>clustered pattern from a broader scale, different types <lb/>are found to be mixed in space when zooming in. The <lb/>clustering patterns and its sensitivity to W may poten-<lb/>tially explain the diverse but spatially clustered On/Off <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 General configurations <lb/>Par. <lb/>Value <lb/>Unit <lb/>Description <lb/>Impulse response function <lb/>τ e <lb/>10 <lb/>ms <lb/>Time constant of average delay through excitatory synapses <lb/>τ i <lb/>20 <lb/>ms <lb/>Time constant of average delay through inhibitory synapses <lb/>H e <lb/>3.25 <lb/>mV <lb/>Average gain through excitatory synapses <lb/>H i <lb/>22 <lb/>mV <lb/>Average gain through inhibitory synapses <lb/>Sigmoid function <lb/>e 0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>spikes/s Controlling maximum firing rate <lb/>r <lb/>0.56 <lb/>1/mV <lb/>Slop at v 0 <lb/>v 0 <lb/>6 <lb/>mV <lb/>Membrane potential threshold for firing <lb/>Intra-node connections <lb/>w EE <lb/>jj <lb/>135 × 0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>Self-feedback excitatory synapses in the jth excitatory population <lb/>w IE <lb/>jj <lb/>135 × 0.6 <lb/>1 <lb/>Excitatory synapses from the jth excitatory to the jth inhibitory population <lb/>w EI <lb/>jj <lb/>135 × 0.2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Inhibitory synapses from the jth inhibitory to the jth excitatory population <lb/>w II <lb/>jj <lb/>135 × 0.05 <lb/>1 <lb/>Self-feedback inhibitory synapses in the jth inhibitory population <lb/>Inter-node connections <lb/>w EE <lb/>jk <lb/>135 × {0, 0.1, ..., 0.5} 1 <lb/>Excitatory synapses from the kth excitatory population to the jth excitatory <lb/>population <lb/>w IE <lb/>jk <lb/>135 × {0, 0.1, ..., 0.5} 1 <lb/>Excitatory synapses from the kth excitatory population to the jth inhibitory <lb/>population <lb/>w EI <lb/>jk <lb/>135 × {0, 0.1, 0.2} <lb/>1 <lb/>Inhibitory synapses from the kth inhibitory population to the jth excitatory <lb/>population <lb/>w II <lb/>jk <lb/>135 × {0, 0.1, 0.2} <lb/>1 <lb/>Inhibitory synapses from the kth inhibitory population to the jth inhibitory <lb/>population <lb/>External connections <lb/>w EX <lb/>jq <lb/>220 × 0.2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Excitatory synapses from external input q to the jth excitatory population <lb/>w IX <lb/>jq <lb/>220 × 0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Excitatory synapses from external input q to the jth inhibitory population <lb/>Inputs <lb/>B <lb/>220 × 2.5 <lb/>spikes/s Constant background input <lb/>X q (t) -<lb/>spikes/s External input q (step function, amplitude=1.5, rise/fall time=10ms) <lb/>Synaptic adaptation <lb/>τ a <lb/>200 <lb/>ms <lb/>Time constant of recovery rate of synaptic efficacy <lb/>κ <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>Drop rate in synaptic efficacy <lb/>responses shown in Figure 5 of [20]. (2) The Off types <lb/>are not constrained within sustained/inhibited clusters, <lb/>suggesting that Off responses are not crucially deter-<lb/>mined by the level change of m E <lb/>2 (t) during stimulus. <lb/>(3) The On and Off types occupy distinct areas in the <lb/>2D plane, which agrees with the conclusion that On <lb/>and Off responses are driven by largely nonoverlap-<lb/>ping sets of synaptic inputs [80]. (4) However, there <lb/>are also areas where the On, Off and On&amp;Off types are <lb/>close to each other, which supposedly are more sensi-<lb/>tive to neuroplasticity (e.g. synaptic adaptation, spike-<lb/>timing-dependent plasticity, or homeostatic plasticity) <lb/>that change neural response from one type to another. <lb/>Example II: distinct onset and offset frequency recep-<lb/>tive fields (FRFs) As demonstrated in Example I, the <lb/>two-node network can account for the different tempo-<lb/>ral profiles of On/Off responses. The same network can <lb/>account for the distinct onset and offset FRFs in in-<lb/>dividual cells in the auditory cortex [69]. For example, <lb/>the exemplary cell in Figure 3a is sensitive to the on-<lb/>sets of sound stimuli at higher frequencies (3,200-15,872 <lb/>Hz) and the offsets of sound stimuli at lower frequen-<lb/>cies (512-16,000 Hz), as reflected by higher spike den-<lb/>sity (yellow and red). In addition, this cell shows sup-<lb/>pressed spike density (deep blue) during stimuli at low <lb/>and middle frequencies. In short, the On/Off responses <lb/>vary across tonal frequencies and across cells. <lb/>In the simulation, we use the two-node network to <lb/>reproduce the distinct FRFs in Figure 3a-c. For each <lb/>simulation trial, the stimulus input (500 ms duration), <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 Settings and variables for categorization of network behavior <lb/>Par. <lb/>Value <lb/>Unit <lb/>Description <lb/>Time windows <lb/>[t On , t Of f ] <lb/>[0, 2000] <lb/>ms <lb/>Stimulus onset and offset <lb/>[t 1 , t 2 ] <lb/>[−500, 0] <lb/>ms <lb/>Pre-onset window <lb/>[t 2 , t 3 ] <lb/>[0, 500] <lb/>ms <lb/>Post-onset window <lb/>[t 4 , t 5 ] <lb/>[1500, 2000] ms <lb/>Pre-offset window <lb/>[t 5 , t 6 ] <lb/>[2000, 2500] ms <lb/>Post-offset window 1 <lb/>[t 7 , t 8 ] <lb/>[3500, 4000] ms <lb/>Post-offset window 2 <lb/>Variables comparing max m E (t i &lt; t &lt; t j ) <lb/>∆m P reP ost -<lb/>spikes/s Bistability check ([t 1 , t 2 ] vs. [t 7 , t 8 ]) <lb/>∆m Stim <lb/>-<lb/>spikes/s Level change ([t 4 , t 5 ] vs. [t 1 , t 2 ] and [t 7 , t 8 ]) <lb/>∆m On <lb/>-<lb/>spikes/s Onset peak height ([t 1 , t 2 ] vs. [t 2 , t 3 ]) <lb/>∆m Of f <lb/>-<lb/>spikes/s Offset peak height ([t 4 , t 5 ] vs. [t 5 , t 6 ]) <lb/>Thresholds <lb/>θ P reP ost <lb/>0.1 <lb/>spikes/s Bistable behavior, if ∆m P reP ost ≥ θ P reP ost <lb/>θ Stim <lb/>0 <lb/>spikes/s Sustained response, if ∆m Stim &gt; θ Stim <lb/>Inhibited response, otherwise <lb/>θ On <lb/>0.5 <lb/>spikes/s On response, if ∆m On &gt; θ On <lb/>θ Of f <lb/>0.5 <lb/>spikes/s Off response, if ∆m Of f &gt; θ Of f <lb/>corresponding to a pure tone in one trial of the ex-<lb/>perimental recordings, is fed to both nodes with dif-<lb/>ferent strength of external connections (i.e., w EX <lb/>1 <lb/>= <lb/>44 × ratio1; w IX <lb/>1 <lb/>= 22 × ratio1; w EX <lb/>2 <lb/>= 44 × ratio2; <lb/>w IX <lb/>2 <lb/>= 22 × ratio2, as in 3d). The ratios (orange and <lb/>green) reflect how far the two nodes are from the stim-<lb/>ulus source. Considering the tonotopic organization in <lb/>the auditory cortex, the ratios are also changed for each <lb/>simulation trial because the stimulus input in each sim-<lb/>ulation trial represents a different tonal frequency. The <lb/>inter-node connections W is picked up from the W so-<lb/>lutions and is fixed in each example, and the ratios are <lb/>adjusted such that the responses of node 2 (i.e., the time <lb/>courses of m E <lb/>2 (t) mimic qualitatively the experimental <lb/>observations. The simulation trials are then merged to <lb/>make simulated FRFs (Figure 3e-g). <lb/>In Figure 3e, the excitatory population E 2 shows <lb/>inhibited-Off response when ratio1 = 1 and ratio2 = 0 <lb/>(same as the ideal case used in Example I). The On re-<lb/>sponse emerges as ratio1 decreases, and a small amount <lb/>of ratio2 results in stronger On responses and weaker <lb/>Off responses. In Figure 3f, E 2 shows inhibited-Off re-<lb/>sponse when ratio1 = 1 and ratio2 = 0, and it turns <lb/>into sustained-Pure type when ratio2 is larger than <lb/>ratio1. In Figure 3g, E 2 shows inhibited-On&amp;Off re-<lb/>sponse, and a small amount of ratio2 results in stronger <lb/>On responses. <lb/>The two-node network, although rate-based, may <lb/>provide a sense how the exemplary cells in Figure 3a-c <lb/>are influenced by different sound tones: ratio2 (green) <lb/>indicates which tones are closer to (or more directly <lb/>influencing) the cell, and ratio1 (orange) reflects how <lb/>its surrounding neurons are sensitive to the tonal scope. <lb/>Example III: omitted-stimulus response (OSR) The OSR <lb/>resembles the Off response as they both peak at the off-<lb/>set of a prolonged stimulus or a train of periodic stim-<lb/>uli. However, the OSR differentiates itself from the Off <lb/>response by its property of temporal expectation. The <lb/>peak latencies of OSR are not constant but proportional <lb/>to the stimulus onset asynchrony (SOA) of the repeti-<lb/>tive stimuli as illustrated in Figure 4a. The OSR at cor-<lb/>tical level (aka. omission response or omission MMN) <lb/>resembles the classic MMN, as both responses are re-<lb/>lated to violations to certain expectations (e.g. expec-<lb/>tation to the &apos;when&apos; or the &apos;what&apos; in the stimuli). <lb/>The generic deviance detection principle suggests <lb/>that the cortical OSR is a change detection response <lb/>(or an Off response) to the end of stable periodicity rep-<lb/>resentation. In our simulation, the periodicity is repre-<lb/>sented by a bank of oscillators [52, 48] comprising multi-<lb/>ple nodes (i.e. R nodes) with different resonant frequen-<lb/>cies (implemented by different time constants τ e and τ i <lb/>for simplicity). In this way, the temporal feature of peri-<lb/>odicity is transformed into a spatial pattern represented <lb/>by the R nodes. Unlike the conventional bank of oscil-<lb/>lators where the oscillators are not connected to each <lb/>other, the R nodes are inter-connected with short-term <lb/>plasticity on W EE and W EI (Note: short-term plas-<lb/>ticity on W EE and W IE also works in this example). <lb/>The plasticity enhances the connections between two <lb/>nodes if they oscillate in high covariance, and reduces <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Sustained <lb/>Inhibited <lb/>On <lb/>O¡ <lb/>On&amp;O¡ <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>∆m PrePost <lb/>Time <lb/>Stimulus <lb/>t 1 <lb/>t 2 <lb/>t 3 <lb/>t 4 <lb/>t 5 <lb/>t 6 t 7 <lb/>t 8 <lb/>∆m Off <lb/>∆m Stim <lb/>∆m On <lb/>m(t) <lb/>Firing rate <lb/>(1) Sustained Pure <lb/>(5) Inhibited Pure <lb/>(6) Inhibited On <lb/>(7) Inhibited O <lb/>(8) Inhibited On&amp;O <lb/>(2) Sustained On <lb/>(3) Sustained O <lb/>(4) Sustained On&amp;O <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Fig. 2 Change detectors and the corresponding W solutions. <lb/>a In the simulation settings, a prolonged stimulus of 2000 ms <lb/>is fed to node 1. A range of inter-node connections W are <lb/>scanned through and the various temporal behaviors of the <lb/>change detector (i.e., time courses of m E <lb/>2 (t)) are to be catego-<lb/>rized. b For categorization, four variables ∆m On , ∆m Stim , <lb/>∆m Of f and ∆m P reP ost are calculated according to the time <lb/>windows (light blue areas) for each time course m E <lb/>2 (t). The <lb/>time courses that are not bistable are then categorized into <lb/>one of the eight On/Off types. See detailed categorization set-<lb/>tings in Table 2. c The exemplary responses of eight On/Off <lb/>types. Gray bands represent the duration of stimulus. The <lb/>black curves represent the time courses of m E <lb/>2 (t), and the <lb/>bold black curves are the envelopes. d All W solutions of eight <lb/>On/Off types in the scanned range are projected to 2D plane <lb/>for visualization (Matlab function: tsne), where color dots <lb/>represent the eight types ({Sustained, Inhibited} × {Pure, <lb/>On, Off, On&amp;Off}). The eight exemplary behaviors in c are <lb/>labeled in the zoomed area. <lb/>Ratio 1 Ratio 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>W <lb/>500ms <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>Pre <lb/>During <lb/>Post <lb/>16 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>9.6 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>16 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>9.6 <lb/>6.4 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Frequency (kHz) <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>Spike density (spikes/s) <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>80 <lb/>40 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>Input ratio <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fig. 3 Distinct onset and offset FRFs. a-c Three exemplary <lb/>cells that show distinct onset and offset FRFs (adapted from <lb/>[69]). The cells were recorded in the primary auditory cortex <lb/>in awake cats. Sound stimuli of pure tone (ranging from 128Hz <lb/>to 16,000Hz) were presented for 500 ms. The pre-, during-, <lb/>and post-stimulus spike density of the cell is color coded. d In <lb/>the simulation settings, a two-node network with adjustable <lb/>external connections w EX <lb/>1 <lb/>and w EX <lb/>2 <lb/>(orange and green color) <lb/>are used to mimic the experimental observations.e-g Simu-<lb/>lation results that mimic the observations in a-c. The green <lb/>and orange input ratios at the left-side bar of each plot rep-<lb/>resent the settings of external connections w EX <lb/>1 <lb/>and w EX <lb/>2 <lb/>for each simulation trial. The firing rate is color coded. The <lb/>pre-stimulus firing rate is used as baseline, and the negative <lb/>value (deep blue color) during stimulus stands for inhibited <lb/>activity. <lb/>the connections otherwise (Equation 19 and 21). This <lb/>enables the resonance among R nodes to sustain for one <lb/>more cycle after the periodic stimuli are turned off. The <lb/>change detector (C node) that connects to the R nodes <lb/>(as in Figure 4b) is expected to peak when the sustained <lb/>resonance drops. In Figure 4c, we simulate MEG signals <lb/>resulting from prolonged (CONST) and periodic stim-<lb/>uli (SOAs: 75, 125, 175, and 250 ms; stimulus duration: <lb/>50 ms). The OSR peaks are marked by blue triangles. <lb/>When the SOA is increased, the peak latency increases <lb/>and the peak amplitude decreases, which is in line with <lb/>the MEG observation [2]. The small peak before the <lb/>OSR (especially clear for SOA 125 and 175) locates at <lb/>the time of the omitted stimulus, which resembles the <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>expected evoked potential before the OSR (e.g., Figure <lb/>7B in [12]). In Figure 4d, we show that the n-node net-<lb/>work (n = 21 in this example) is able to respond at the <lb/>right timing (i.e. a constant delay after the detectable <lb/>omission) with the limitation that the SOA is within <lb/>150 ms. The peak latencies become unstable for SOAs <lb/>larger than 200 ms. The limitation is due to the limit of <lb/>resonant frequencies in the bank of oscillators, as can <lb/>be seen in Figure 4c the simulated MEG for SOA 250 <lb/>is not as stable compared to faster SOAs. <lb/>In this example, we demonstrate that the cortical <lb/>OSR can reflect a detection mechanism upon the stable <lb/>representation of periodicity. The sustained resonance <lb/>is crucial for temporal expectation. This is in line with <lb/>the observation that the auditory brainstem does not <lb/>generate overt OSR [50] because sustained resonance <lb/>has not happened at that stage. We have not yet fully <lb/>investigated the neural mechanism underlying tempo-<lb/>ral expectancy. The auditory cortex is assumed to have <lb/>the capacity to represent a certain range of periodicity <lb/>locally (e.g. under 200 ms), and the bank of oscillators, <lb/>which only assumes heterogeneity across neural popu-<lb/>lations, is so far a good candidate for implementation. <lb/>Example IV: sequence mismatch negativity (MMN) The <lb/>responses in a roving paradigm reveal the progress of <lb/>regularity formation and change detection, and thus <lb/>is a good example for demonstrating the generic de-<lb/>viance detection principle. In Figure 5a, an MEG study <lb/>shows how the human brain responds to the switch be-<lb/>tween regular and random complex acoustic patterns <lb/>[5]. There are On and Off responses at the onsets and <lb/>offsets of the stimulus sequence. An MMN response is <lb/>elicited by the transition from regular to random se-<lb/>quences (REG-RAND), but there is only gradually ris-<lb/>ing root mean square (RMS) amplitude for the other <lb/>way around (RAND-REG). Also, the RMS amplitude <lb/>is higher during regular sequences compared to random <lb/>sequences. <lb/>In the simulation, we use a three-node network to <lb/>reproduce the temporal profile of the RMS in Figure 5a. <lb/>Two stimulus inputs (REG and RAND) that represent <lb/>the random and regular features are fed to the nodes <lb/>1 and 2 respectively as in Figure 5b. The intensity and <lb/>rise/fall time of the two stimulus inputs are the same as <lb/>in the previous examples, and the durations are set to <lb/>match the experiment. The inter-node connections W <lb/>between nodes 1,2 and node 3 are chosen from the W <lb/>solutions in Figure 2d. The connections between nodes <lb/>1 and 2 do not have to be symmetric and are manu-<lb/>ally tuned to match the observed RMS. In Figure 5c, <lb/>the simulated MEG signal shows (1) On and Off re-<lb/>sponses at the onset and offset of stimulus sequences. <lb/>0 <lb/>-200 <lb/>Peak latency <lb/>Cont. <lb/>SOA 100 <lb/>SOA 200 <lb/>-400 <lb/>-600 <lb/>Time (ms) <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>SOA=75, 100, …, 250 ms <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>SOA (ms) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>Peak latency (ms) <lb/>Time (ms) <lb/>-1000 -500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>CONT <lb/>SOA 75 <lb/>SOA 125 <lb/>SOA 175 <lb/>SOA 250 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>n-1 <lb/>n <lb/>W <lb/>Fig. 4 Omitted stimulus response (OSR). a Illustrative re-<lb/>sponses that show temporal expectation. The peak latencies <lb/>should be linear to the SOA if the offsets of stimuli are aligned <lb/>(red line), or a constant d if the due times are aligned (empty <lb/>rectangles). See, for example, Figure 2 in [2]. b In the sim-<lb/>ulation settings, the R nodes (left column) are simply im-<lb/>plemented with different time constants τ e and τ i , leading <lb/>to different resonance frequencies. A prolonged stimulus or <lb/>periodic stimuli are fed to these R nodes. c Simulated MEG <lb/>signals (black curves) peak at the end of stimuli and show dif-<lb/>ferent peak latencies and peak amplitudes (marked with blue <lb/>triangles). d Simulated peak latencies are linear to the SOA. <lb/>Simulations are run for several trials for each SOA where the <lb/>offset time is changed. The peak latencies in each simulation <lb/>trial (blue dots) under the same SOA can be different, which <lb/>depends on the network stability during stimulus and the off-<lb/>set time. Black dots are the mean peak latencies. The peak <lb/>latencies show approximately constant delay with respect to <lb/>due time (time of predictable omission, dashed line) when the <lb/>SOAs are below 200 ms. The peak latencies become unstable <lb/>across trials when SOAs are above 200 ms. In other words, the <lb/>temporal expectation is preserved in this network for SOAs <lb/>smaller than 200 ms. <lb/>(2) MMN response to the transition from regular to ran-<lb/>dom sequences (REG-RAND), and (3) different RMS <lb/>amplitudes during REG and RAND presentations. <lb/>The three-node network demonstrates how the inter-<lb/>node connections W among the three nodes alone can <lb/>account for the transient responses to the onsets and <lb/>offsets, and the selectivity to the direction of transi-<lb/>tion, as well as the level changes in RMS amplitude <lb/>during random or regular sequences. For more realistic <lb/>settings, the rise/fall time of the two stimulus inputs <lb/>can be set differently. For example, it is reasonable to <lb/>set longer rise time for the REG stimulus input because <lb/>it takes some time (at least a sequence length) to form <lb/>regularity representation, which then already explains <lb/>why there is no MMN in the RAND-REG transition. <lb/>Moreover, the intensity of the two stimulus inputs may <lb/>be reasonably set differently because the status of neu-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>ral populations under regular and random sequences <lb/>can be dramatically different, which then explains the <lb/>level changes in RMS amplitude. In this simulation ex-<lb/>ample we use identical stimulus inputs, in an attempt <lb/>to highlight the effect of inter-node connections W on <lb/>shaping the network activities. Note that this simula-<lb/>tion example elucidates on the contribution of a change <lb/>detector, rather than the details of regularity formation. <lb/>To understand how REG sequence causes higher RMS <lb/>amplitude, we assume short-term plasticity on W EE <lb/>and W IE in the lower-level neural populations at the <lb/>stage of regularity formation. This follows the sugges-<lb/>tion by a dynamic causal modeling study [3] that synap-<lb/>tic gain modulation in the auditory cortex is involved <lb/>in processing regular sequences. <lb/>3.2 The requirements for a change detector <lb/>The generic deviance detection principle emphasizes on <lb/>the ubiquity of local change detection and its sepa-<lb/>ration from regularity formation. In previous simula-<lb/>tion examples, we demonstrate that the behavior of <lb/>a change detector can account for many phenomena <lb/>(e.g., diverse cortical On/Off responses, distinct onset-<lb/>and offset-FRFs, cortical OSR, and sequence MMN). <lb/>Here, we present a more detailed analysis of the exact <lb/>requirements for a change detector to work. First, we <lb/>investigate how and under which conditions the On and <lb/>Off responses occur. Then we examine how changes in <lb/>connection strengths affects the generation of On/Off <lb/>responses through three factors: (1) external input to <lb/>inhibitory populations, (2) blockage of NMDA receptor <lb/>channels, and (3) synaptic adaptation. <lb/>The generation of On responses It has been proposed <lb/>that On responses can be due to adaptive and post-<lb/>onset inhibitory mechanisms that reshape the onset re-<lb/>sponse in auditory nerve fibers [66]. In our simulations, <lb/>we found that the On responses can be also due to the <lb/>transiently inhibited activity of the inhibitory popula-<lb/>tion I 2 at the onset of stimulus. As can be seen in Figure <lb/>6b and d, population I 2 is shortly inhibited by popula-<lb/>tion I 1 , and the low v I <lb/>2 (t) leads to a transient peak in <lb/>v E <lb/>2 (t) (indicated by the red and black arrows in the ma-<lb/>genta rectangles). The system returns to stability soon <lb/>after the v E <lb/>2 (t) peak brings v I <lb/>2 (t) up again. These On <lb/>responses are due to the transient disinhibition, there-<lb/>fore the inter-node connection W II plays an important <lb/>role in the generation of the On responses. <lb/>The generation of Off responses Off responses proceeded <lb/>by inhibited activity (i.e. the inhibited-Off responses) <lb/>have been widely accepted to arise from post-inhibitory <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Simulated MEG <lb/>RAND-REG <lb/>Envelope <lb/>Simulated MEG <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>Time (ms) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Simulated MEG <lb/>REG-RAND <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Change <lb/>detector <lb/>W <lb/>1 <lb/>REG <lb/>RAND <lb/>RAND REG <lb/>REG RAND <lb/>Feature <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>Fig. 5 Sequence MMN (roving paradigm). a Brain responses <lb/>to transitions between regular and random sound sequences <lb/>(adapted from [5]). There are transient peaks at the on-<lb/>sets/offsets of sound sequences as well as at the transition <lb/>from regular (REG) to random (RAND) sequences. In addi-<lb/>tion, the RMS amplitude is higher during regular sequences. <lb/>b In the simulation settings, a three-node network is used <lb/>for mimicking the observation in a. The R nodes (nodes 1 <lb/>and 2) receive the stimulus inputs representing RAND and <lb/>REG, respectively. The inter-node connections W between <lb/>the C node (node 3) and the R nodes are picked up from the <lb/>W solutions such that the C node shows sustained-On&amp;Off <lb/>responses to the stimulus inputs. The connections between <lb/>the R are tuned to result in the different level shifts dur-<lb/>ing stimulus and the elimination of the transient peak at the <lb/>transition from RAND to REG. c Simulated MEG signals of <lb/>the three-node network. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>Population responses <lb/>Population responses <lb/>Firing rate (spikes/s) <lb/>PSP (mV) <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Fig. 6 The generation of On response. a In the simulation <lb/>settings, a prolonged stimulus of 2000 ms is fed to the R <lb/>node (node 1) in a two-node network. The inter-node con-<lb/>nections W is chosen from the W solutions that give rise to <lb/>inhibited-On&amp;Off responses in the C node (node 2) (see Fig-<lb/>ure 2b). b Node responses to the stimulus (gray period) are <lb/>shown in firing rates (upper plot) and in PSPs (lower plot). As <lb/>an inhibited-On&amp;Off response, the time course m E <lb/>2 (t) (black <lb/>curve) shows lower amplitude during stimulus and transient <lb/>peaks at the onset and offset of stimulus. To understand the <lb/>generation of On response in population E 2 , the magenta <lb/>rectangle indicate the period of transient disinhibition where <lb/>population I 2 is transiently inhibited by population I 1 (red <lb/>arrow), and population E 2 peaks right after the transient <lb/>disinhibition (black arrow). c and d show a similar example <lb/>for sustained-On&amp;Off response, where the generation of On <lb/>response is also due to the transient disinhibition. <lb/>rebound that is related to the intrinsic conductance <lb/>property of the neuron membranes [44]. However, the <lb/>generation of the Off responses that follow sustained ac-<lb/>tivity (i.e. the sustained-Off responses) cannot be sim-<lb/>ply explained by the post-inhibition mechanism (see re-<lb/>view in [106,43]). Here we examine under which con-<lb/>ditions the inhibited-Off and sustained-Off responses <lb/>might arise at the network level. <lb/>In Figure 7, the population E 2 shows Off responses <lb/>for both cases: the inhibited and sustained activity dur-<lb/>ing stimulus. In the simulations, both inhibited-Off and <lb/>sustained-Off responses result from the same mecha-<lb/>nism. As shown in Figure 7b and e, the Off response <lb/>comes in two steps. First, the population I 2 receives <lb/>strong inhibition from population I 1 during stimulus <lb/>(reflected by the negative PSP v I <lb/>2 (t) during t=3000 to <lb/>5000 ms). Second, the population E 2 activity peaks be-<lb/>fore I 2 recovers after stimulus offset (the transient peak <lb/>v E <lb/>2 (t) during t=5000 to 5100 ms). The occurrence of Off <lb/>responses can be also represented by phase portraits <lb/>shown in Figure 7c and f. The trajectories of the phase <lb/>portraits show how v E <lb/>2 (t) and v I <lb/>2 (t) evolve interactively. <lb/>When there is only background input, E 2 and I 2 oscil-<lb/>late in the normal steady state (the counter-clockwise <lb/>blue trajectories) where E 2 excites I 2 , and I 2 inhibits <lb/>E 2 . During stimulus presentation, E 2 and I 2 oscillate <lb/>in a reversed steady state (the clockwise green trajec-<lb/>tories) where E 2 has an additional inhibitory effect on <lb/>I 2 through the pathway E 2 → I 1 → I 2 , and I 2 has an <lb/>additional disinhibitory effect on E 2 through the path-<lb/>way I 2 → I 1 → E 2 , due to the involvement of active <lb/>I 1 during stimulus. The Off responses are depicted by <lb/>the magenta trajectories during the transition from the <lb/>reversed steady state to the normal steady state. <lb/>The simulations provide clues for the underlying <lb/>neural mechanism. The inter-node connection W II is <lb/>critical for a network to give rise to the Off responses <lb/>because some inhibitory population I 2 has to be in-<lb/>hibited (i.e. disinhibition) first. The inter-node connec-<lb/>tion W EI is important to maintain the network in the <lb/>working state (e.g., the reversed steady state) other-<lb/>wise the network gets &apos;overheated&apos; during disinhibition. <lb/>With these structural prerequisites, the excitatory pop-<lb/>ulation E 2 may show a transient Off response before <lb/>the inhibitory population I 2 catches up again after the <lb/>stimulus offset. <lb/>The timing of the stimulus offset (i.e. the initial <lb/>point in the state space when the transition begins) <lb/>and other parameters that alter the trajectories of the <lb/>two steady states (such as the stimulus intensity, and <lb/>the settings of W EE and W IE ) also affect the genera-<lb/>tion of Off response, but these factors are not critical. <lb/>Moreover, the inhibited activity during stimulus is not <lb/>critical for the generation of the Off response at net-<lb/>work level (cf., it is necessary in the post-inhibitory <lb/>mechanism at cellular level). As can be seen in Figure <lb/>7f, the amplitude of v E <lb/>2 (t) during stimulus (green tra-<lb/>jectory) can be larger compared to no stimulus (blue <lb/>trajectory). <lb/>Factors influencing the On/Off responses We consider <lb/>the effect of three factors with respect to the gener-<lb/>ation of On/Off responses: (1) external input to in-<lb/>hibitory populations, (2) blockage of NMDA receptor <lb/>channels, and (3) synaptic adaptation. More specifi-<lb/>cally, we checked how these three factors influence the <lb/>distribution of W solutions in the two-node network. <lb/>Since disinhibition plays an important role in the <lb/>generation of both On and Off responses as illustrated <lb/>in the above simulations (Figure 6 and 7), it is inter-<lb/>esting to see the contribution of external input to the <lb/>inhibitory population I 1 . In condition II, the external <lb/>connection W IX is set to zero in comparison with the <lb/>default setting W IX = 0.5W EX (condition I). <lb/>The NMDA-r antagonist MK-801 is found to reduce <lb/>inhibition during stimulation and thus reduce the Off <lb/>responses [4]. NMDA-r antagonists are also known to <lb/>reduce the amplitude of the MMN [55]. In condition III, <lb/>we mimic the effect of NMDA-r antagonists by reduc-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>P1 <lb/>P3 <lb/>P2 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>P1 <lb/>P3 <lb/>P2 <lb/>Phase portrait <lb/>Phase portrait <lb/>Population responses <lb/>Population responses <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>E 2 PSP (mV) <lb/>I <lb/>2 PSP (mV) <lb/>E 2 PSP (mV) <lb/>P1 <lb/>P2 P3 <lb/>P1 <lb/>P2 P3 <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>d <lb/>Firing rate (spikes/s) <lb/>PSP (mV) <lb/>Fig. 7 The generation of the Off response. a In the simula-<lb/>tion settings, a prolonged stimulus of 2000 ms is fed to the <lb/>R node (node 1) in a two-node network. The inter-node con-<lb/>nections W is chosen from the W solutions that give rise to <lb/>inhibited-Off responses in the C node (node 2) (see Figure <lb/>2b). b Node responses to the stimulus (the gray period) are <lb/>shown in firing rates (upper plot) and in PSPs (lower plot). <lb/>As an inhibited-Off response, the time course m E <lb/>2 (t) (black <lb/>curve) shows lower amplitude during stimulus and a tran-<lb/>sient peak at the offset of stimulus. Population I 2 is strongly <lb/>inhibited during stimulus, which is reflected by the negative <lb/>PSP of population I 2 v I <lb/>2 (t) (red curve in the green rectangle). <lb/>The disinhibition is followed by the Off response in popula-<lb/>tion E 2 thereafter (black curve in the magenta rectangle). <lb/>c Phase portraits (P 1: during stimulus, P 2: offset of stimu-<lb/>lus, P 3: post stimulus) of node 2. The phase portrait P 3 (i.e., <lb/>when there is only background input) runs counter-clockwise, <lb/>and the phase portrait P 1 (i.e., during stimulus) shifts down-<lb/>ward and runs clockwise, reflecting the strong inhibition on <lb/>I 2 . The phase portrait P 2 shows the transient trajectory of <lb/>transition from P 1 to P 3. The magenta dot denotes the time <lb/>of stimulus offset. d The simulation settings for a sustained-<lb/>Off response. e The firing rate m E <lb/>2 (t) shows higher amplitude <lb/>during stimulus and a transient peak at the offset of stimu-<lb/>lus. Same as in b, population I 2 is strongly inhibited during <lb/>stimulus, which is then followed by the Off response. f The <lb/>phase portraits are similar as in c except that the amplitude <lb/>of v E <lb/>2 (t) is larger during P 1 than P 3. The two examples show <lb/>that the generation of Off responses are not relevant to the <lb/>sustained or inhibited activity in E 2 , but the inhibition on <lb/>I 2 during stimulus. <lb/>ing the connection strength W EE by 25% and reducing <lb/>W IE by 50%. The difference in reduction applied to <lb/>the two connections is based on the fact that excita-<lb/>tory synapses on inhibitory neurons are mainly covered <lb/>by NMDA channels and therefore are more sensitive to <lb/>NMDA-r antagonists than the excitatory synapses on <lb/>excitatory neurons [74]. The setting of external connec-<lb/>tions remains the same as the default setting. redNote <lb/>that, in principle, both conditions II and III might be <lb/>sensitive to NMDA-r antagonists. So, if NMDA-r an-<lb/>tagonists are indeed the cause of reduced connection <lb/>strengths to inhibitory populations, the effect in con-<lb/>dition II and III in Figure 8h should occur simulta-<lb/>neously. Other effects by NMDA-r antagonists such as <lb/>the changes in NMDA currents, synaptic plasticity and <lb/>synaptic time constant are not included. <lb/>The phenomenon of synaptic adaptation is ubiqui-<lb/>tous and has been suggested to be one of the mecha-<lb/>nisms underlying deviance detection. Since we suggest <lb/>that deviance-related responses can be interpreted as <lb/>the change detection responses to regularity represen-<lb/>tation, it is good to know whether synaptic adaptation <lb/>promotes the emergence of change detectors. To con-<lb/>sider synaptic adaptation in the simulation, the intra-<lb/>and inter-node connections W EE are modulated by a <lb/>synaptic efficacy term a as described in Equation 17. <lb/>Note that as described in Equation 9, the external input <lb/>via W EX to the excitatory populations is not affected <lb/>by synaptic adaptation. <lb/>The responses of two-node network with a range of <lb/>inter-node connections W s (same as in Example I in <lb/>Section 3.1) are simulated, and each W is assigned to <lb/>one of the nine types of responses (i.e., eight On/Off <lb/>types and type 9: others. See also Figure 2b) under <lb/>four conditions: (I) the default condition, where synap-<lb/>tic adaptation is not applied, and W IX = 0.5W EX , <lb/>(II) W IX = 0, (III) W EE = 0 is reduced by 25% and <lb/>W IE = 0 is reduced by 50%, and (IV) synaptic adapta-<lb/>tion is applied. To visualize the result, the W solutions <lb/>of types 1 to 9 are projected to 2D plane (Figure 8a-d). <lb/>The number of W solutions under the four condition <lb/>are summarized in the contingency table (Figure 8e-g) <lb/>and the bar chart (Figure 8h). <lb/>The bar chart (Figure 8h) shows that the number <lb/>of W solutions of Off types in condition II are reduced <lb/>compared to condition I. Most of the Off types under <lb/>condition I turn to Pure types under condition II (e.g., <lb/>sustained-Off → sustained-Pure among 1.25% of the <lb/>scanned W s. See the cyan rectangle in Figure 8e). This <lb/>suggests that the external connection W IX is support-<lb/>ive for the generation of Off responses, because the I 1 -<lb/>to-I 2 disinhibition is enhanced due to the external input <lb/>via W IX . <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>In condition III the number of W solutions of Off <lb/>types are reduced, but the number of W solutions of <lb/>On types are slightly increased compared to condition I <lb/>(Figure 8h). This is in line with the experimental result <lb/>that NMDA-r antagonist reduce the Off responses but <lb/>the On responses are not affected [37, 99]. <lb/>In condition IV, the number of W solutions of both <lb/>On and Off types are greatly increased (Figure 8h). <lb/>Many of the Pure types under condition I turn into On <lb/>and Off types under condition III (e.g., 3.28%: sustained-<lb/>Pure → sustained-On; 1.62%: inhibited-Pure → sustained-<lb/>Off; 2.82%: inhibited-Pure → inhibited-Off. See the ma-<lb/>genta rectangle in Figure 8f). This suggests that synap-<lb/>tic adaptation greatly promotes the emergence of change <lb/>detectors. To see how synaptic adaptation alters the <lb/>network responses, Figure 9a-c show three examples of <lb/>altered responses due to synaptic adaptation. The three <lb/>examples show typical type transitions from condition <lb/>I to condition IV. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>We propose a generic deviance detection principle based <lb/>on the fact that many deviance-related responses can <lb/>be observed in the cortex without clear evidence of <lb/>functionally-specific wiring patterns. The mechanism <lb/>suggests that the reciprocal wirings in the cortex give <lb/>rise to the emergence of change detectors that respond <lb/>to the abrupt change in regular features. With this no-<lb/>tion, the deviance-related responses observed in the cor-<lb/>tex such as the cortical On/Off responses, the cortical <lb/>OSR and the MMN are regarded as responses of change <lb/>detectors at different levels of abstraction. <lb/>The simulation examples demonstrate the network <lb/>responses can resemble the properties of cortical On/Off <lb/>responses (Figure 2 and 3), the cortical OSR (Figure <lb/>4), and the MMN (Figure 5). We then study the wiring <lb/>patterns in the network that support the generation of <lb/>On/Off responses (Figure 6 and 7). The results suggest <lb/>that the inhibitory to inhibitory connections are impor-<lb/>tant for both On and Off responses, which implies that <lb/>these deviance-related responses are closely related to <lb/>disinhibition. In the simulations that mimic the effect of <lb/>NMDA-r antagonists and synaptic adaptation, the re-<lb/>sults show that NMDA-r antagonists suppress the Off <lb/>responses and slightly promote the On responses, and <lb/>synaptic adaptation generally boosts both On and Off <lb/>responses (Figure 8 and 9). Below we provide our view-<lb/>points regarding the questions raised in the introduc-<lb/>tion. Some testable predictions by our model are listed <lb/>at the end of the discussion. <lb/>Different processes in regularity formation, but <lb/>same mechanism in change detection. The generic <lb/>deviance detection principle suggests that the change <lb/>detection may rely on a common neural mechanism (i.e. <lb/>the local reciprocal wiring), while the regularity forma-<lb/>tion may, depending on the level of abstraction, require <lb/>different brain resources and time to collect relevant in-<lb/>formation. <lb/>There are a number of dissimilarities among differ-<lb/>ent deviance-related responses, which are, as we will <lb/>discuss hereunder, mainly due to differences in the pro-<lb/>cess of regularity formation. We take the differences be-<lb/>tween cortical OSR and MMN as an example. In terms <lb/>of temporal window of integration (TWI), a pitch MMN <lb/>can be elicited by traditional oddball paradigms even <lb/>when the SOA is larger than 500 ms [77, 6], while the es-<lb/>timated length of TWI for cortical OSR is much shorter <lb/>(160-170 ms) [107]. In terms of attention, it is sug-<lb/>gested that fast and slow periodic sequences elicit cor-<lb/>tical OSRs by two different mechanisms: The fast OSR <lb/>(periodicity &gt; 5 Hz) is elicited automatically, while the <lb/>slow OSR (periodicity &lt; 2 Hz) requires the involve-<lb/>ment of attention [41]. For example, the slow OSR can <lb/>be elicited at large SOAs such as 800 ms in [25]; and <lb/>1000 to 2000 ms in [15]. The need for attention suggests <lb/>that cortical OSR and MMN are different processes [60]. <lb/>In terms of required repetition, a successful elicitation <lb/>of MMN needs only two or three repetitions for sim-<lb/>ple feature-repetition regularities [8, 18, 91, 105], while <lb/>the cortical OSR requires up to 9 repetitions in a train <lb/>for a successful elicitation [29]. The above observations <lb/>suggest for different processes that are related to the <lb/>degree of difficulty in regularity formation. <lb/>There are several similarities among the deviance-<lb/>related responses that support the notion of a common <lb/>mechanism for change detection. In terms of latency, <lb/>the peak latencies of cortical On/Off responses, corti-<lb/>cal OSR, and MMN all fall in the range of 100-200 ms <lb/>[2, 57, 73, 107, 70]. In terms of spatial distribution, the <lb/>sources of cortical Off response and MMN are similar. <lb/>As revealed in animal studies, the sources of Off re-<lb/>sponses appear to be in the non-tonotopic area that is <lb/>adjacent to the tonotopic area [92, 4]. In studies of dense <lb/>mapping of MMN, the pitch MMN was reported to be <lb/>generated in the secondary auditory area (or spreading <lb/>more widely over the core and belt areas), which is sepa-<lb/>rate from the sources of P1 and N1 at the core areas (A1 <lb/>and AAF) [86, 67]. The cortical responses to the onset, <lb/>offset, and pitch change in a continuous stimulus share <lb/>similar topography and temporal profile, as suggested <lb/>in the EEG/MEG studies [110, 111, 62]. These obser-<lb/>vations support the notion of a common neural sub-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 0.02 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.12 0.01 0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.46 0.01 0.01 <lb/>1.25 0.07 0.02 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.28 0.01 0.01 0.65 0.34 0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.13 0.01 0.24 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.05 0.01 43.2 3.51 0.27 <lb/>0.07 0.04 0.05 0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>22.83 22.91 0.32 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.74 0.33 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i OnO¡ s OnO¡ i Pure s Pure i Others <lb/>condition II <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i <lb/>OnO¡ s <lb/>OnO¡ i <lb/>Pure s <lb/>Pure i <lb/>Others <lb/>condition I <lb/>0.04 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.16 0.01 0.02 <lb/>0.04 0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 0.04 0.04 0.01 <lb/>0.02 0.01 0.22 0.16 0.02 0.03 0.64 0.71 0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 0.05 0.13 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 0.17 0.94 0.06 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 0.04 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.37 0.22 0.21 0.16 0.01 0.02 32.52 12.77 1.24 <lb/>0.05 0.11 0.35 0.71 0.01 0.02 5.56 38.78 0.66 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 0.05 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.18 0.73 0.41 <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i OnO¡ s OnO¡ i Pure s Pure i Others <lb/>condition III <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i <lb/>OnO¡ s <lb/>OnO¡ i <lb/>Pure s <lb/>Pure i <lb/>Others <lb/>condition I <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.13 0.07 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 0.03 0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.42 1.16 0.01 <lb/>0.34 0.19 <lb/>0.27 0.61 0.01 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 0.01 <lb/>0.02 0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>3.28 0.44 0.55 0.49 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 27.29 12.2 3.26 <lb/>0.26 0.13 1.62 2.82 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.03 12.06 28.65 0.67 <lb/>0.12 0.01 0.23 0.21 <lb/>0.95 0.55 0.36 <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i OnO¡ s OnO¡ i Pure s Pure i Others <lb/>condition IV <lb/>On s <lb/>On i <lb/>O¡ s <lb/>O¡ i <lb/>OnO¡ s <lb/>OnO¡ i <lb/>Pure s <lb/>Pure i <lb/>Others <lb/>condition I <lb/>Condition I <lb/>(Default) <lb/>Condition II <lb/>(W IX =0) <lb/>Condition III <lb/>(NMDA-r ant.) <lb/>Condition IV <lb/>(Adaptation) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Proportion (%) <lb/>On s <lb/>O s <lb/>OnO s <lb/>On i <lb/>O i <lb/>OnO i <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>h <lb/>Fig. 8 The effect of factors influencing the strength of connections W on the occurrence of On/Off responses. The W solutions <lb/>of On/Off responses projected to 2D plane under a condition I: default, b condition II: W IX = 0, c condition III: NMDA-r <lb/>antagonist, and d condition IV: synaptic adaptation. Dots with different colors and sizes represent different response types.e <lb/>The contingency table of W solutions for condition I vs. II. The value in each cell of the table (in red, with grayscale background) <lb/>is the number of W solutions over total number of scanned W s. The subscripts s and i stand for sustained and inhibited types. <lb/>A cell without a value means no W solution in that case. The cyan and magenta rectangles highlight the W solutions of On/Off <lb/>types under one condition but not under the other. f Condition I vs. III. g Condition I vs. IV. h The bar chart represents the <lb/>proportions of W solutions of On/Off types under the four conditions. <lb/>strate of change detection for different deviance-related <lb/>responses. <lb/>The deviance-related responses also show similari-<lb/>ties in their dependency on some factors regarding the <lb/>regularities (e.g., probability of deviant, randomness in <lb/>SOA, number of repetition, effect of the NMDA-r antag-<lb/>onists) and the deviance magnitude (e.g., the sharpness <lb/>in temporal, spectral, contextual changes). <lb/>The recurrent nature of the intracortical wiring <lb/>makes the change detection ubiquitous. Function-<lb/>ally speaking, the ubiquity of change detection facil-<lb/>itates the perceptual representation in the hierarchy. <lb/>The edge information at all levels provided by the local <lb/>change detectors augments the representational space. <lb/>Such information compression may also contribute to <lb/>energy saving. In this sense, the change detectors are <lb/>more like high-pass filters than comparators that sub-<lb/>tract top-down signals from the bottom-up signals. The <lb/>abundant recurrent wiring patterns in the cortex pro-<lb/>vide a suitable environment for the emergence of change <lb/>detectors. We take the diversity of cortical On/Off re-<lb/>sponses [16, 20, 100] as an example. Even though these <lb/>responses could originate from the feedforward mixture <lb/>of the non-cortical On/Off responses at earlier stages <lb/>such as the thalamus, midbrain and brainstem, the cor-<lb/>tex provides more abundant chances for the emergence <lb/>of On/Off responses. In example simulation I, we demon-<lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>Without adaptation <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>With adaptation <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>Without adaptation <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>Without adaptation <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>With adaptation <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>E pop. <lb/>I pop. <lb/>With adaptation <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Time (sec) <lb/>Firing rate (spikes/s) <lb/>Firing rate (spikes/s) <lb/>Firing rate (spikes/s) <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>node 2 <lb/>node 1 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>Fig. 9 Network responses without and with synaptic adap-<lb/>tation. a Example of sustained-Pure type response in popu-<lb/>lation E 2 under condition I (i.e., no adaptation) turning into <lb/>sustained-On type under condition IV (i.e., when synaptic <lb/>adaptation is applied on W EE ). b Example of inhibited-Pure <lb/>type turning into sustained-Off type. c Example of inhibited-<lb/>Pure type turning into inhibited-Off type. <lb/>strate that various types of On/Off responses can be <lb/>generated by different inter-node connections (Figure <lb/>2). In example simulation II, we further demonstrate <lb/>that for a specific connection setting, the difference in <lb/>input ratios to nodes gives rise to distinct onset and <lb/>offset FRFs (Figure 3). The W solutions of On/Off re-<lb/>sponses projected to the 2D plane (Figure 2c) also pro-<lb/>vide explanation to the diverse (and spatially clustered) <lb/>cell responses observed in auditory cortex in awake mice, <lb/>as shown in Figure 5 in [20]. These results suggest that <lb/>change detection is a basic and ubiquitous operation in <lb/>the cortex. <lb/>We then study the generation of On and Off re-<lb/>sponses. The On responses can be due to a transient <lb/>disinhibition (i.e., a quick and light inhibition on the in-<lb/>hibitory population of the change detector) before the <lb/>network reaches the steady state (Figure 6). The Off <lb/>responses are always due to a release from long-lasting <lb/>disinhibition (i.e., a long and strong inhibition on the <lb/>inhibitory population of the change detector) before the <lb/>network comes back to the steady state without stimu-<lb/>lus (Figure 7), in line with the rebound after inhibition <lb/>hypothesis [92, 27]. We suggest that the inhibitory to <lb/>inhibitory connections are a key ingredient for change <lb/>detection. <lb/>NMDA-r antagonists dampen the deviance-related <lb/>responses. We suggest that the NMDA-r antagonists <lb/>could generally dampen the deviance-related responses <lb/>through three aspects: (1) voltage-dependency, (2) synap-<lb/>tic plasticity and (3) E/I balance. First, the NMDA-r <lb/>antagonists block the voltage-dependent NMDA chan-<lb/>nels and reduce the additional NMDA currents that <lb/>reflect mismatch signals [37]. Second, the NMDA-r an-<lb/>tagonists damage the spike-timing-dependent plastic-<lb/>ity (STDP) and hamper the ability of regularity for-<lb/>mation [4, 38, 98]. Third, the NMDA-r antagonists al-<lb/>ter the connection patterns and E/I balance. Blocking <lb/>NMDA receptors leads to decreased activities in the <lb/>GABAergic interneurons and increased pyramidal ex-<lb/>citation, because the GABAergic interneurons are ten-<lb/>fold more sensitive to the NMDA-r antagonists than the <lb/>pyramidal neurons [74, 23]. <lb/>The adaptation-based and prediction-based mod-<lb/>els of MMN agree on the voltage-dependency aspect <lb/>and suggest that the reduced MMN amplitude is due <lb/>to the reduction in NMDA currents [53, 102, 101]. The <lb/>prediction-based models also mention the need for STDP <lb/>to form prediction signals [102, 101]. In addition to these <lb/>two aspects, our simulation results show that the al-<lb/>tered E/I balance as an effect of NMDA-r antagonists <lb/>can reduce the emergence of change detectors. In con-<lb/>dition III (Figure 8c), we reduce the strengths of W EE <lb/>and W IE by 25% and 50% respectively and count again <lb/>the number of each On/Off types in the scanned range <lb/>of inter-node connection W s. The number of Off types <lb/>is decreased and the number of On types is slightly <lb/>increased relative to the default setting (Figure 8h). <lb/>The results suggest that the NMDA-r antagonists may <lb/>dampen the cortical Off response, cortical OSR and <lb/>MMN. <lb/>We cannot draw further quantitative conclusion on <lb/>the effect of NMDA-r antagonists because the uniform <lb/>search range of W s in the simulation is just a simplifi-<lb/>cation, and the exact proportion of strength reduction <lb/>due to NMDA-r antagonists is not available. The set-<lb/>ting of 25% and 50% in connection strength reduction <lb/>in condition III was arbitrary so that a single node still <lb/>oscillates under a certain range of input intensity, which <lb/>eliminates the case when the nodes get saturated and <lb/>no On/Off responses are not generated at all. The time <lb/>constant τ e due to the blockage of NMDA channels was <lb/>not modified in the simulation in order to focus on the <lb/>effect of W change. <lb/>Synaptic adaptation facilitates change detection. <lb/>Synaptic adaptation is a pervasive short-term synaptic <lb/>plasticity that is considered as a mechanism underlying <lb/>deviance detection, in the sense that a rare stimulus <lb/>triggers stronger neural activities via un-adapted path-<lb/>ways. Given the pervasiveness of synaptic adaptation, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>we are interested in how it affects the behavior of the <lb/>change detector in the simulation. In the simulation of <lb/>condition IV (Figure 8d), the strength of W EE is mod-<lb/>ulated by short-term adaptation according to the activ-<lb/>ities of presynaptic excitatory populations. After scan-<lb/>ning through the W s, we found that the number of W <lb/>solutions of both On and Off types are increased com-<lb/>pared with the default condition (Figure 8g). Many W <lb/>solutions of Pure type turn into On and Off types when <lb/>synaptic adaptation is applied (as examples in Figure <lb/>9). We suggests that the synaptic adaptation facilitates <lb/>change detection by bringing many otherwise Pure re-<lb/>sponses (usually reflected by saturated activities in the <lb/>excitatory populations) to either On or Off responses. <lb/>The OSR is not just sustained resonance. The <lb/>OSR differentiates itself from the Off response by its <lb/>peak latencies that are proportional to the SOA in repet-<lb/>itive stimuli, which reflects the role of temporal ex-<lb/>pectancy. The models that claim to account for the <lb/>OSR utilize either an adaptive approach [94] or popu-<lb/>lation coding approach [52] to maintain a short contin-<lb/>uation of neural activities (i.e., sustained resonances) <lb/>that preserve the periodicity of the repetitive stimuli. <lb/>However, the sustained resonances alone cannot fulfil <lb/>all observations in terms of peak amplitude and peak <lb/>latency of the response: (1) For the peak amplitude, <lb/>the OSR cannot simply rely on the sustained resonance <lb/>since the amplitude of OSR can be stronger than the <lb/>evoked response during entrainment [29]; (2) For the <lb/>peak latency, there should a constant delay upon one <lb/>more period at the end of the stimuli [2, 84], but the <lb/>sustained resonance rises exactly after one more period <lb/>at the end of the stimuli. Therefore, even though the <lb/>sustained resonance is time-locked to the next stimu-<lb/>lus, there seem to be extra neural circuits responsible <lb/>for the extra constant delay in peak latency and the <lb/>stronger peak amplitude than the evoked responses. In <lb/>the example simulation III, we demonstrate that the <lb/>simulated OSR solves the two issues mentioned above <lb/>(Figure 4). Our model suggests that the cortical OSR <lb/>can be interpreted as the cortical Off response after <lb/>the end of sustained resonance. The simulation result is <lb/>also in line with the finding that there is pre-activated <lb/>response at the time of expected onset followed by a <lb/>mismatch response [2, 9, 79]. <lb/>The OSR is not prediction signal. The omission <lb/>paradigm is often used to differentiate the contribution <lb/>of adaptation and prediction in MMN generation. This <lb/>is based on the assumption that the OSR could not arise <lb/>without any stimulus without the involvement of active <lb/>prediction. Interestingly, the models based on either the <lb/>adaptation or the prediction hypothesis interpret the <lb/>OSR as essentially different from the MMN triggered <lb/>by classic oddball paradigm. In the adaptation-based <lb/>model, the OSR is regarded as the rebound response <lb/>(i.e. the sustained resonance) rather than delayed N1 <lb/>[52, 53]. In the prediction-based model, the OSR is re-<lb/>garded as pure prediction signal that originates from <lb/>the memory unit rather than prediction error [102]. <lb/>Both interpretations imply that the OSR is essentially <lb/>different from the MMN because no additional NMDA <lb/>current is generated. The problem is that neither the <lb/>rebound response nor the prediction signal do explain <lb/>the two observations in terms of amplitude and latency <lb/>mentioned above. As demonstrated in the example sim-<lb/>ulations III and IV (Figure 4 and 5), we suggest that <lb/>the cortical OSR and MMN are essentially the same, <lb/>both being the activities of change detectors. <lb/>The cross-modal omission paradigm is also used to <lb/>emphasize the need for prediction. The brain can pre-<lb/>dict the upcoming event (e.g. handclap sound) from the <lb/>preceding events in another modality (e.g. silent hand-<lb/>clap video, or self-paced button press), and an OSR <lb/>is triggered if the expected stimulus is omitted. In a <lb/>motor-auditory (MA) paradigm, the participants show <lb/>OSRs when the sound that was expected to be initi-<lb/>ated by the self-paced button press is omitted [79]. In <lb/>a visual-auditory (VA) paradigm, an OSR is elicited <lb/>by occasionally omitting the sound that accompanied <lb/>a handclap video [90]. So far, the cross-modal OSRs <lb/>have not been considered by the existing computational <lb/>models. How does the generic deviance detection prin-<lb/>ciple view the OSRs in these cross-modal paradigms <lb/>that seem to be bound to an active predicting process? <lb/>Here we provide a different view point. First, the pre-<lb/>diction is likely to be supported by the association be-<lb/>tween the cross-modal events (e.g., handclap video or <lb/>button press, followed by a sound stimulus) that has <lb/>to be paired or learned (e.g., by Hebbian learning) in <lb/>advance either via direct or indirect connections. The <lb/>existence of association is reflected by the pre-activation <lb/>at 40 to 80 ms in the auditory cortex elicited by a visual <lb/>event [90] or by a motor event [79, 90]. There is no pre-<lb/>activation in the auditory cortex in the random condi-<lb/>tion where the button press is followed by a randomly <lb/>selected sound from 48 samples in the MA paradigm <lb/>and there is also no OSR thereafter [79], suggesting <lb/>that there are not enough trials to associate the but-<lb/>ton press to all 48 sound samples. Second, due to the <lb/>pre-activation in the auditory cortex, the MA and VA <lb/>paradigms can then be regarded as a classic oddball <lb/>paradigm where the standard is a &apos;weak-strong&apos; sound <lb/>pair and the deviant is a &apos;weak-omission&apos; sound pair. In <lb/>this sense, the cross-modal omission paradigm resem-<lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>bles an &apos;intensity MMN&apos; or &apos;duration MMN&apos; paradigms <lb/>rather than an omission paradigm. This analogy ex-<lb/>plains why OSRs are elicited in the VA and MA con-<lb/>ditions but not in auditory-only condition (like a clas-<lb/>sic omission paradigm) [90] because the SOAs (average <lb/>1155 ms) in the paradigm is above the temporal win-<lb/>dow of integration (TWI) for temporal feature such as <lb/>periodicity but still within the TWI for identity fea-<lb/>tures such as intensity and duration. The analogy can <lb/>be verified if the VA and MA conditions fail to elicit <lb/>&apos;omission&apos; responses when the SOAs are larger than <lb/>TWI for identify features. Based on this analogy, the <lb/>deviance detection that takes place in the auditory cor-<lb/>tex stands alone from the process of association, which <lb/>explains why the pre-activation does not differ between <lb/>the 50% and 12% chance of sound omission, while the <lb/>mismatch response following the pre-activation depends <lb/>on the proportion of omission trials for both VA and <lb/>MA conditions [90], because association is less likely to <lb/>be reduced by the 50% omissions, but deviance detec-<lb/>tion relies much on probability. Taken together, given <lb/>the pre-activation via association and the analogy to <lb/>classic MMN paradigm, the computational models that <lb/>account for classic MMN (e.g., either prediction-based <lb/>or not) could potentially also account for the mismatch <lb/>responses in cross-modal omission paradigm. From the <lb/>viewpoint of generic deviance detection principle, the <lb/>process of deviance detection (including regularity for-<lb/>mation and change detection) takes place locally in the <lb/>auditory cortex, even in the case of cross-modal VA and <lb/>MA paradigms. <lb/>Testable predictions. In terms of the location of re-<lb/>sponse: (1) The cortical Off response, cortical OSR, and <lb/>MMN should show similar laminar profiles, for example, <lb/>sink in layer 2/3 [37]. (2) Inhibited activity of inhibitory <lb/>interneurons near the location of the deviance response <lb/>should be observed during stimulus presentation (regu-<lb/>larity formation). Taking the pitch MMN for an exam-<lb/>ple (assuming cortical area A has best frequency (BF) <lb/>of standard tone A, area B has BF of deviant tone B, <lb/>and area X is the location of MMN), the inhibitory in-<lb/>terneurons in area X should be inhibited by tone A. <lb/>In addition, area X can be a broader area (which may <lb/>still include area B) that surrounds area A. In terms of <lb/>the effect of NMDA-r antagonists: (1) The cortical OSR <lb/>should be sensitive to the NMDA-r antagonists as are <lb/>the other MMNs. (2) The amplitude of entrainment to <lb/>periodic stimuli in omission paradigms should be also <lb/>reduced by NMDA-r antagonists. Note: this prediction <lb/>may have been partially supported by impaired delta <lb/>entrainment in patients with schizophrenia [49]. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements We would like to thank Dr. Alejandro <lb/>Tabas for the helpful suggestions. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Amenedo, E., Escera, C.: The accuracy of sound dura-<lb/>tion representation in the human brain determines the <lb/>accuracy of behavioural perception. European Journal <lb/>of Neuroscience 12(7), 2570-2574 (2000) <lb/>2. Andreou, L.V., Griffiths, T.D., Chait, M.: Sensitivity to <lb/>the temporal structure of rapid sound sequencesan meg <lb/>study. Neuroimage 110, 194-204 (2015) <lb/>3. Auksztulewicz, R., Barascud, N., Cooray, G., Nobre, <lb/>A.C., Chait, M., Friston, K.: The cumulative effects of <lb/>predictability on synaptic gain in the auditory process-<lb/>ing stream. Journal of Neuroscience 37(28), 6751-6760 <lb/>(2017) <lb/>4. Baba, H., Tsukano, H., Hishida, R., Takahashi, K., <lb/>Horii, A., Takahashi, S., Shibuki, K.: Auditory cortical <lb/>field coding long-lasting tonal offsets in mice. Scientific <lb/>reports 6, 34421 (2016) <lb/>5. Barascud, N., Pearce, M.T., Griffiths, T.D., Friston, <lb/>K.J., Chait, M.: Brain responses in humans reveal <lb/>ideal observer-like sensitivity to complex acoustic pat-<lb/>terns. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences <lb/>113(5), E616-E625 (2016) <lb/>6. Bartha-Doering, L., Deuster, D., Giordano, V., <lb/>am Zehnhoff-Dinnesen, A., Dobel, C.: A systematic re-<lb/>view of the mismatch negativity as an index for auditory <lb/>sensory memory: From basic research to clinical and <lb/>developmental perspectives. Psychophysiology 52(9), <lb/>1115-1130 (2015) <lb/>7. Behrend, O., Brand, A., Kapfer, C., Grothe, B.: Au-<lb/>ditory response properties in the superior paraolivary <lb/>nucleus of the gerbil. Journal of neurophysiology 87(6), <lb/>2915-2928 (2002) <lb/>8. Bendixen, A., Roeber, U., Schröger, E.: Regularity ex-<lb/>traction and application in dynamic auditory stimulus <lb/>sequences. Journal of Cognitive Neuroscience 19(10), <lb/>1664-1677 (2007) <lb/>9. Bendixen, A., Schröger, E., Winkler, I.: I heard that <lb/>coming: event-related potential evidence for stimulus-<lb/>driven prediction in the auditory system. Journal of <lb/>Neuroscience 29(26), 8447-8451 (2009) <lb/>10. Boh, B., Herholz, S.C., Lappe, C., Pantev, C.: Process-<lb/>ing of complex auditory patterns in musicians and non-<lb/>musicians. PLoS One 6(7), e21458 (2011) <lb/>11. Brannon, E.M., Roussel, L.W., Meck, W.H., Woldorff, <lb/>M.: Timing in the baby brain. Cognitive Brain Research <lb/>21(2), 227-233 (2004) <lb/>12. Bullock, T.H., Hofmann, M.H., Nahm, F.K., New, J.G., <lb/>Prechtl, J.C.: Event-related potentials in the retina and <lb/>optic tectum of fish. Journal of Neurophysiology 64(3), <lb/>903-914 (1990) <lb/>13. Bullock, T.H., Karamürsel, S., Achimowicz, J.Z., Mc-<lb/>Clune, M.C., Başar-Eroglu, C.: Dynamic properties <lb/>of human visual evoked and omitted stimulus poten-<lb/>tials. Electroencephalography and clinical neurophysi-<lb/>ology 91(1), 42-53 (1994) <lb/>14. Bullock, T.H., Karamürsel, S., Hofmann, M.H.: Interval-<lb/>specific event related potentials to omitted stimuli in <lb/>the electrosensory pathway in elasmobranchs: an ele-<lb/>mentary form of expectation. Journal of Comparative <lb/>Physiology A 172(4), 501-510 (1993) <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>15. Busse, L., Woldorff, M.G.: The erp omitted stimulus <lb/>response to no-stim events and its implications for fast-<lb/>rate event-related fmri designs. Neuroimage 18(4), 856-<lb/>864 (2003) <lb/>16. Chimoto, S., Kitama, T., Qin, L., Sakayori, S., Sato, Y.: <lb/>Tonal response patterns of primary auditory cortex neu-<lb/>rons in alert cats. Brain research 934(1), 34-42 (2002) <lb/>17. Colin, C., Hoonhorst, I., Markessis, E., Radeau, M., <lb/>De Tourtchaninoff, M., Foucher, A., Collet, G., Del-<lb/>tenre, P.: Mismatch negativity (mmn) evoked by sound <lb/>duration contrasts: an unexpected major effect of de-<lb/>viance direction on amplitudes. Clinical neurophysiol-<lb/>ogy 120(1), 51-59 (2009) <lb/>18. Cowan, N., Winkler, I., Teder, W., Näätänen, R.: Mem-<lb/>ory prerequisites of mismatch negativity in the auditory <lb/>event-related potential (erp). Journal of Experimental <lb/>Psychology: Learning, Memory, and Cognition 19(4), <lb/>909 (1993) <lb/>19. Dehmel, S., Kopp-Scheinpflug, C., Dörrscheidt, G.J., <lb/>Rübsamen, R.: Electrophysiological characterization of <lb/>the superior paraolivary nucleus in the mongolian gerbil. <lb/>Hearing research 172(1-2), 18-36 (2002) <lb/>20. Deneux, T., Kempf, A., Daret, A., Ponsot, E., Bathel-<lb/>lier, B.: Temporal asymmetries in auditory coding and <lb/>perception reflect multi-layered nonlinearities. Nature <lb/>communications 7, 12682 (2016) <lb/>21. Felix, R.A., Fridberger, A., Leijon, S., Berrebi, A.S., <lb/>Magnusson, A.K.: Sound rhythms are encoded by <lb/>postinhibitory rebound spiking in the superior parao-<lb/>livary nucleus. Journal of Neuroscience 31(35), 12566-<lb/>12578 (2011) <lb/>22. Gai, Y.: On and off inhibition as mechanisms for forward <lb/>masking in the inferior colliculus: a modeling study. <lb/>American Journal of Physiology-Heart and Circulatory <lb/>Physiology (2016) <lb/>23. Grunze, H.C., Rainnie, D.G., Hasselmo, M.E., Barkai, <lb/>E., Hearn, E.F., McCarley, R.W., Greene, R.W.: Nmda-<lb/>dependent modulation of ca1 local circuit inhibition. <lb/>Journal of Neuroscience 16(6), 2034-2043 (1996) <lb/>24. Guo, Y., Burkard, R.: Onset and offset responses from <lb/>inferior colliculus and auditory cortex to paired noise-<lb/>bursts: inner hair cell loss. Hearing research 171(1-2), <lb/>158-166 (2002) <lb/>25. Halgren, E., Baudena, P., Clarke, J.M., Heit, G., <lb/>Liégeois, C., Chauvel, P., Musolino, A.: Intracerebral <lb/>potentials to rare target and distractor auditory and <lb/>visual stimuli. i. superior temporal plane and parietal <lb/>lobe. Electroencephalography and clinical neurophysi-<lb/>ology 94(3), 191-220 (1995) <lb/>26. He, J.: Corticofugal modulation on both on andoff re-<lb/>sponses in the nonlemniscal auditory thalamus of the <lb/>guinea pig. Journal of Neurophysiology 89(1), 367-381 <lb/>(2003) <lb/>27. He, J., Hashikawa, T., Ojima, H., Kinouchi, Y.: Tempo-<lb/>ral integration and duration tuning in the dorsal zone <lb/>of cat auditory cortex. Journal of Neuroscience 17(7), <lb/>2615-2625 (1997) <lb/>28. Herholz, S.C., Lappe, C., Pantev, C.: Looking for a pat-<lb/>tern: an meg study on the abstract mismatch negativ-<lb/>ity in musicians and nonmusicians. BMC neuroscience <lb/>10(1), 42 (2009) <lb/>29. Horváth, J., Müller, D., Weise, A., Schröger, E.: Omis-<lb/>sion mismatch negativity builds up late. Neuroreport <lb/>21(7), 537-541 (2010) <lb/>30. Hsiao, F.J., Cheng, C.H., Liao, K.K., Lin, Y.Y.: Cortico-<lb/>cortical phase synchrony in auditory mismatch process-<lb/>ing. Biological Psychology 84(2), 336-345 (2010) <lb/>31. Hsu, W.Y., Cheng, C.H., Lin, H.C., Liao, K.K., Wu, <lb/>Z.A., Ho, L.T., Lin, Y.Y.: Memory-based mismatch re-<lb/>sponse to changes in duration of auditory stimuli: An <lb/>meg study. Clinical Neurophysiology 121(10), 1744-<lb/>1750 (2010) <lb/>32. Jacobsen, T., Schröger, E.: Measuring duration mis-<lb/>match negativity. Clinical Neurophysiology 114(6), <lb/>1133-1143 (2003) <lb/>33. Jacobsen, T., Schröger, E., Horenkamp, T., Winkler, I.: <lb/>Mismatch negativity to pitch change: varied stimulus <lb/>proportions in controlling effects of neural refractoriness <lb/>on human auditory event-related brain potentials. Neu-<lb/>roscience letters 344(2), 79-82 (2003) <lb/>34. Jansen, B.H., Rit, V.G.: Electroencephalogram and vi-<lb/>sual evoked potential generation in a mathematical <lb/>model of coupled cortical columns. Biological cyber-<lb/>netics 73(4), 357-366 (1995) <lb/>35. Jansen, B.H., Zouridakis, G., Brandt, M.E.: A <lb/>neurophysiologically-based mathematical model of flash <lb/>visual evoked potentials. Biological cybernetics 68(3), <lb/>275-283 (1993) <lb/>36. Jaramillo, M., Paavilainen, P., Näätänen, R.: Mismatch <lb/>negativity and behavioural discrimination in humans as <lb/>a function of the magnitude of change in sound duration. <lb/>Neuroscience Letters 290(2), 101-104 (2000) <lb/>37. Javitt, D.C., Steinschneider, M., Schroeder, C.E., <lb/>Arezzo, J.C.: Role of cortical n-methyl-d-aspartate re-<lb/>ceptors in auditory sensory memory and mismatch neg-<lb/>ativity generation: implications for schizophrenia. Pro-<lb/>ceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 93(21), <lb/>11962-11967 (1996) <lb/>38. Javitt, D.C., Sweet, R.A.: Auditory dysfunction in <lb/>schizophrenia: integrating clinical and basic features. <lb/>Nature Reviews Neuroscience 16(9), 535 (2015) <lb/>39. Joachimsthaler, B., Uhlmann, M., Miller, F., Ehret, G., <lb/>Kurt, S.: Quantitative analysis of neuronal response <lb/>properties in primary and higher-order auditory cortical <lb/>fields of awake house mice (m us musculus). European <lb/>Journal of Neuroscience 39(6), 904-918 (2014) <lb/>40. Karamürsel, S., Bullock, T.H.: Dynamics of event-<lb/>related potentials to trains of light and dark flashes: <lb/>responses to missing and extra stimuli in elasmobranch <lb/>fish. Electroencephalography and clinical neurophysiol-<lb/>ogy 90(6), 461-471 (1994) <lb/>41. Karamürsel, S., Bullock, T.H.: Human auditory fast and <lb/>slow omitted stimulus potentials and steady-state re-<lb/>sponses. International Journal of Neuroscience 100(1-<lb/>4), 1-20 (2000) <lb/>42. Knösche, T.R., Lattner, S., Maess, B., Schauer, M., <lb/>Friederici, A.D.: Early parallel processing of auditory <lb/>word and voice information. NeuroImage 17(3), 1493-<lb/>1503 (2002) <lb/>43. Kopp-Scheinpflug, C., Sinclair, J.L., Linden, J.F.: When <lb/>sound stops: offset responses in the auditory system. <lb/>Trends in neurosciences 41(10), 712-728 (2018) <lb/>44. Kopp-Scheinpflug, C., Tozer, A.J., Robinson, S.W., <lb/>Tempel, B.L., Hennig, M.H., Forsythe, I.D.: The sound <lb/>of silence: ionic mechanisms encoding sound termina-<lb/>tion. Neuron 71(5), 911-925 (2011) <lb/>45. Kuchenbuch, A., Paraskevopoulos, E., Herholz, S.C., <lb/>Pantev, C.: Effects of musical training and event prob-<lb/>abilities on encoding of complex tone patterns. BMC <lb/>neuroscience 14(1), 51 (2013) <lb/>46. Kujala, T., Kallio, J., Tervaniemi, M., Näätänen, R.: <lb/>The mismatch negativity as an index of temporal pro-<lb/>cessing in audition. Clinical Neurophysiology 112(9), <lb/>1712-1719 (2001) <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Shih-Cheng Chien et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>47. Kulesza Jr, R.J., Spirou, G.A., Berrebi, A.S.: Physio-<lb/>logical response properties of neurons in the superior <lb/>paraolivary nucleus of the rat. Journal of neurophysiol-<lb/>ogy (2003) <lb/>48. Large, E.W., Almonte, F.V., Velasco, M.J.: A canonical <lb/>model for gradient frequency neural networks. Physica <lb/>D: Nonlinear Phenomena 239(12), 905-911 (2010) <lb/>49. Lee, M., Sehatpour, P., Hoptman, M.J., Lakatos, P., <lb/>Dias, E.C., Kantrowitz, J.T., Martinez, A.M., Javitt, <lb/>D.C.: Neural mechanisms of mismatch negativity dys-<lb/>function in schizophrenia. Molecular psychiatry 22(11), <lb/>1585 (2017) <lb/>50. Lehmann, A., Arias, D.J., Schönwiesner, M.: Tracing <lb/>the neural basis of auditory entrainment. Neuroscience <lb/>337, 306-314 (2016) <lb/>51. Maaten, L.v.d., Hinton, G.: Visualizing data using t-sne. <lb/>Journal of machine learning research 9(Nov), 2579-2605 <lb/>(2008) <lb/>52. May, P., Tiitinen, H.: Human cortical processing of au-<lb/>ditory events over time. NeuroReport 12(3), 573-577 <lb/>(2001) <lb/>53. May, P.J., Tiitinen, H.: Mismatch negativity (mmn), the <lb/>deviance-elicited auditory deflection, explained. Psy-<lb/>chophysiology 47(1), 66-122 (2010) <lb/>54. May, P.J., Westö, J., Tiitinen, H.: Computational mod-<lb/>elling suggests that temporal integration results from <lb/>synaptic adaptation in auditory cortex. European Jour-<lb/>nal of Neuroscience 41(5), 615-630 (2015) <lb/>55. Näätänen, R., Kähkönen, S.: Central auditory dysfunc-<lb/>tion in schizophrenia as revealed by the mismatch neg-<lb/>ativity (mmn) and its magnetic equivalent mmnm: a <lb/>review. International Journal of Neuropsychopharma-<lb/>cology 12(1), 125-135 (2009) <lb/>56. Näätänen, R., Lehtokoski, A., Lennes, M., Cheour, <lb/>M., Huotilainen, M., Iivonen, A., Vainio, M., Alku, <lb/>P., Ilmoniemi, R.J., Luuk, A., et al.: Language-specific <lb/>phoneme representations revealed by electric and mag-<lb/>netic brain responses. Nature 385(6615), 432 (1997) <lb/>57. Näätänen, R., Paavilainen, P., Alho, K., Reinikainen, <lb/>K., Sams, M.: Do event-related potentials reveal the <lb/>mechanism of the auditory sensory memory in the hu-<lb/>man brain? Neuroscience letters 98(2), 217-221 (1989) <lb/>58. Näätänen, R., Paavilainen, P., Rinne, T., Alho, K.: The <lb/>mismatch negativity (mmn) in basic research of central <lb/>auditory processing: a review. Clinical neurophysiology <lb/>118(12), 2544-2590 (2007) <lb/>59. Näätänen, R., Syssoeva, O., Takegata, R.: Automatic <lb/>time perception in the human brain for intervals ranging <lb/>from milliseconds to seconds. Psychophysiology 41(4), <lb/>660-663 (2004) <lb/>60. Ng, K.K., Penney, T.B.: Probing interval timing with <lb/>scalp-recorded electroencephalography (eeg). In: Neuro-<lb/>biology of Interval Timing, pp. 187-207. Springer (2014) <lb/>61. Nishihara, M., Inui, K., Morita, T., Kodaira, M., <lb/>Mochizuki, H., Otsuru, N., Motomura, E., Ushida, T., <lb/>Kakigi, R.: Echoic memory: investigation of its tempo-<lb/>ral resolution by auditory offset cortical responses. PloS <lb/>one 9(8), e106553 (2014) <lb/>62. Nishihara, M., Inui, K., Motomura, E., Otsuru, N., <lb/>Ushida, T., Kakigi, R.: Auditory n1 as a change-related <lb/>automatic response. Neuroscience research 71(2), 145-<lb/>148 (2011) <lb/>63. Novitski, N., Huotilainen, M., Tervaniemi, M., <lb/>Näätänen, R., Fellman, V.: Neonatal frequency <lb/>discrimination in 250-4000-hz range: Electrophysiologi-<lb/>cal evidence. Clinical Neurophysiology 118(2), 412-419 <lb/>(2007) <lb/>64. Novitski, N., Tervaniemi, M., Huotilainen, M., <lb/>Näätänen, R.: Frequency discrimination at differ-<lb/>ent frequency levels as indexed by electrophysiological <lb/>and behavioral measures. Cognitive Brain Research <lb/>20(1), 26-36 (2004) <lb/>65. Paavilainen, P.: The mismatch-negativity (mmn) com-<lb/>ponent of the auditory event-related potential to vio-<lb/>lations of abstract regularities: a review. International <lb/>journal of psychophysiology 88(2), 109-123 (2013) <lb/>66. Phillips, D.P., Hall, S., Boehnke, S.: Central auditory <lb/>onset responses, and temporal asymmetries in auditory <lb/>perception. Hearing research 167(1-2), 192-205 (2002) <lb/>67. Pincze, Z., Lakatos, P., Rajkai, C., Ulbert, I., Karmos, <lb/>G.: Separation of mismatch negativity and the n1 wave <lb/>in the auditory cortex of the cat: a topographic study. <lb/>Clinical Neurophysiology 112(5), 778-784 (2001) <lb/>68. Prechtl, J.C., Bullock, T.H.: Event-related potentials to <lb/>omitted visual stimuli in a reptile. Electroencephalogra-<lb/>phy and Clinical Neurophysiology 91(1), 54-66 (1994) <lb/>69. Qin, L., Chimoto, S., Sakai, M., Wang, J., Sato, Y.: <lb/>Comparison between offset and onset responses of pri-<lb/>mary auditory cortex on-off neurons in awake cats. Jour-<lb/>nal of neurophysiology (2007) <lb/>70. Raij, T., McEvoy, L., Mäkelä, J.P., Hari, R.: Human <lb/>auditory cortex is activated by omissions of auditory <lb/>stimuli. Brain research 745(1-2), 134-143 (1997) <lb/>71. Ramón, F., Hernández, O.H., Bullock, T.H.: Event-<lb/>related potentials in an invertebrate: crayfish emit omit-<lb/>ted stimulus potentials. Journal of experimental biology <lb/>204(24), 4291-4300 (2001) <lb/>72. Recanzone, G.H.: Response profiles of auditory cortical <lb/>neurons to tones and noise in behaving macaque mon-<lb/>keys. Hearing research 150(1-2), 104-118 (2000) <lb/>73. Rinne, T., Särkkä, A., Degerman, A., Schröger, E., Alho, <lb/>K.: Two separate mechanisms underlie auditory change <lb/>detection and involuntary control of attention. Brain <lb/>research 1077(1), 135-143 (2006) <lb/>74. Rujescu, D., Bender, A., Keck, M., Hartmann, A.M., <lb/>Ohl, F., Raeder, H., Giegling, I., Genius, J., McCarley, <lb/>R.W., Möller, H.J., et al.: A pharmacological model for <lb/>psychosis based on n-methyl-d-aspartate receptor hy-<lb/>pofunction: molecular, cellular, functional and behav-<lb/>ioral abnormalities. Biological psychiatry 59(8), 721-<lb/>729 (2006) <lb/>75. Ruusuvirta, T., Lipponen, A., Pellinen, E., Penttonen, <lb/>M., Astikainen, P.: Auditory cortical and hippocampal-<lb/>system mismatch responses to duration deviants in <lb/>urethane-anesthetized rats. PloS one 8(1), e54624 <lb/>(2013) <lb/>76. Saha, D., Sun, W., Li, C., Nizampatnam, S., Padovano, <lb/>W., Chen, Z., Chen, A., Altan, E., Lo, R., Barbour, <lb/>D.L., et al.: Engaging and disengaging recurrent inhibi-<lb/>tion coincides with sensing and unsensing of a sensory <lb/>stimulus. Nature communications 8, 15413 (2017) <lb/>77. Sams, M., Hari, R., Rif, J., Knuutila, J.: The human au-<lb/>ditory sensory memory trace persists about 10 sec: neu-<lb/>romagnetic evidence. Journal of cognitive neuroscience <lb/>5(3), 363-370 (1993) <lb/>78. Sams, M., Paavilainen, P., Alho, K., Näätänen, R.: Au-<lb/>ditory frequency discrimination and event-related po-<lb/>tentials. Electroencephalography and Clinical Neuro-<lb/>physiology/Evoked Potentials Section 62(6), 437-448 <lb/>(1985) <lb/>79. SanMiguel, I., Saupe, K., Schröger, E.: I know what is <lb/>missing here: electrophysiological prediction error sig-<lb/>nals elicited by omissions of predicted what but not <lb/>when. Frontiers in human neuroscience 7, 407 (2013) <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">A generic deviance detection principle <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>80. Scholl, B., Gao, X., Wehr, M.: Nonoverlapping sets of <lb/>synapses drive on responses and off responses in audi-<lb/>tory cortex. Neuron 65(3), 412-421 (2010) <lb/>81. Schönwiesner, M., Novitski, N., Pakarinen, S., Carlson, <lb/>S., Tervaniemi, M., Naatanen, R.: Heschl&apos;s gyrus, pos-<lb/>terior superior temporal gyrus, and mid-ventrolateral <lb/>prefrontal cortex have different roles in the detection of <lb/>acoustic changes. Journal of Neurophysiology (2007) <lb/>82. Schröger, E., Paavilainen, P., Näätänen, R.: Mismatch <lb/>negativity to changes in a continuous tone with regularly <lb/>varying frequencies. Electroencephalography and Clin-<lb/>ical Neurophysiology/Evoked Potentials Section 92(2), <lb/>140-147 (1994) <lb/>83. Schwartz, G., Harris, R., Shrom, D., Berry II, M.J.: De-<lb/>tection and prediction of periodic patterns by the retina. <lb/>Nature neuroscience 10(5), 552 (2007) <lb/>84. Schwartz, G.W., Berry II, M.J.: Sophisticated temporal <lb/>pattern recognition in retinal ganglion cells. Journal of <lb/>neurophysiology (2008) <lb/>85. Shiga, T., Althen, H., Cornella, M., Zarnowiec, K., <lb/>Yabe, H., Escera, C.: Deviance-related responses along <lb/>the auditory hierarchy: Combined ffr, mlr and mmn ev-<lb/>idence. PloS one 10(9), e0136794 (2015) <lb/>86. Shiramatsu, T.I., Kanzaki, R., Takahashi, H.: Cortical <lb/>mapping of mismatch negativity with deviance detec-<lb/>tion property in rat. PLoS One 8(12), e82663 (2013) <lb/>87. da Silva, F.L.: Functional localization of brain sources <lb/>using eeg and/or meg data: volume conductor and <lb/>source models. Magnetic resonance imaging 22(10), <lb/>1533-1538 (2004) <lb/>88. Spiegler, A., Kiebel, S.J., Atay, F.M., Knösche, T.R.: <lb/>Bifurcation analysis of neural mass models: Impact of <lb/>extrinsic inputs and dendritic time constants. NeuroIm-<lb/>age 52(3), 1041-1058 (2010) <lb/>89. Spiegler, A., Knösche, T.R., Schwab, K., Haueisen, J., <lb/>Atay, F.M.: Modeling brain resonance phenomena us-<lb/>ing a neural mass model. PLoS computational biology <lb/>7(12), e1002298 (2011) <lb/>90. Stekelenburg, J.J., Vroomen, J.: Predictive coding of <lb/>visual-auditory and motor-auditory events: An electro-<lb/>physiological study. Brain research 1626, 88-96 (2015) <lb/>91. Sussman, E.S., Horváth, J., Winkler, I., Orr, M.: The <lb/>role of attention in the formation of auditory streams. <lb/>Perception &amp; psychophysics 69(1), 136-152 (2007) <lb/>92. Takahashi, H., Nakao, M., Kaga, K.: Cortical mapping <lb/>of auditory-evoked offset responses in rats. Neuroreport <lb/>15(10), 1565-1569 (2004) <lb/>93. Tervaniemi, M., Schröger, E., Saher, M., Näätänen, R.: <lb/>Effects of spectral complexity and sound duration on <lb/>automatic complex-sound pitch processing in humans-<lb/>a mismatch negativity study. Neuroscience Letters <lb/>290(1), 66-70 (2000) <lb/>94. Thivierge, J.P., Cisek, P.: Spiking neurons that keep the <lb/>rhythm. Journal of computational neuroscience 30(3), <lb/>589-605 (2011) <lb/>95. Tiitinen, H., May, P., Reinikainen, K., Näätänen, R.: <lb/>Attentive novelty detection in humans is governed by <lb/>pre-attentive sensory memory. Nature 372(6501), 90 <lb/>(1994) <lb/>96. Toufan, R., Moossavi, A., Aghamolaei, M., Ashayeri, <lb/>H.: Topographic comparison of mmn to simple versus <lb/>pattern regularity violations: The effect of timing. Neu-<lb/>roscience research 112, 20-25 (2016) <lb/>97. Tse, C.Y., Penney, T.B.: Preattentive timing of empty <lb/>intervals is from marker offset to onset. Psychophysiol-<lb/>ogy 43(2), 172-179 (2006) <lb/>98. Uhlhaas, P.J., Singer, W.: Abnormal neural oscillations <lb/>and synchrony in schizophrenia. Nature reviews neuro-<lb/>science 11(2), 100 (2010) <lb/>99. Umbricht, D., Schmid, L., Koller, R., Vollenweider, <lb/>F.X., Hell, D., Javitt, D.C.: Ketamine-induced deficits <lb/>in auditory and visual context-dependent processing in <lb/>healthy volunteers: implications for models of cognitive <lb/>deficits in schizophrenia. Archives of general psychiatry <lb/>57(12), 1139-1147 (2000) <lb/>100. Volkov, I., Galazjuk, A.: Formation of spike response to <lb/>sound tones in cat auditory cortex neurons: interaction <lb/>of excitatory and inhibitory effects. Neuroscience 43(2-<lb/>3), 307-321 (1991) <lb/>101. Wacongne, C.: A predictive coding account of mmn re-<lb/>duction in schizophrenia. Biological psychology 116, <lb/>68-74 (2016) <lb/>102. Wacongne, C., Changeux, J.P., Dehaene, S.: A neuronal <lb/>model of predictive coding accounting for the mismatch <lb/>negativity. Journal of Neuroscience 32(11), 3665-3678 <lb/>(2012) <lb/>103. van Wassenhove, V., Lecoutre, L.: Duration estima-<lb/>tion entails predicting when. Neuroimage 106, 272-283 <lb/>(2015) <lb/>104. Werner, B., Cook, P.B., Passaglia, C.L.: Complex tem-<lb/>poral response patterns with a simple retinal circuit. <lb/>Journal of neurophysiology (2008) <lb/>105. Winkler, I., Karmos, G., Näätänen, R.: Adaptive model-<lb/>ing of the unattended acoustic environment reflected in <lb/>the mismatch negativity event-related potential. Brain <lb/>research 742(1-2), 239-252 (1996) <lb/>106. Xu, N., Fu, Z.Y., Chen, Q.C.: The function of offset neu-<lb/>rons in auditory information processing. Translational <lb/>Neuroscience 5(4), 275-285 (2014) <lb/>107. Yabe, H., Tervaniemi, M., Sinkkonen, J., Huotilainen, <lb/>M., Ilmoniemi, R.J., Näätänen, R.: Temporal window of <lb/>integration of auditory information in the human brain. <lb/>Psychophysiology 35(5), 615-619 (1998) <lb/>108. Yago, E., Corral, M.J., Escera, C.: Activation of brain <lb/>mechanisms of attention switching as a function of audi-<lb/>tory frequency change. Neuroreport 12(18), 4093-4097 <lb/>(2001) <lb/>109. Yago, E., Escera, C., Alho, K., Giard, M.H.: Cerebral <lb/>mechanisms underlying orienting of attention towards <lb/>auditory frequency changes. Neuroreport 12(11), 2583-<lb/>2587 (2001) <lb/>110. Yamashiro, K., Inui, K., Otsuru, N., Kakigi, R.: Change-<lb/>related responses in the human auditory cortex: An meg <lb/>study. Psychophysiology 48(1), 23-30 (2011) <lb/>111. Yamashiro, K., Inui, K., Otsuru, N., Kida, T., Kakigi, <lb/>R.: Automatic auditory off-response in humans: an meg <lb/>study. European Journal of Neuroscience 30(1), 125-<lb/>131 (2009) <lb/>112. Yaron, A., Hershenhoren, I., Nelken, I.: Sensitivity to <lb/>complex statistical regularities in rat auditory cortex. <lb/>Neuron 76(3), 603-615 (2012) </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
