<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Gweon et al. <lb/>1 <lb/>The impact of sequencing depth on the inferred taxonomic <lb/>composition and AMR gene content of metagenomic samples <lb/>H. Soon Gweon 1,2 , Liam P. Shaw 3 , Jeremy Swann 3 , Nicola De Maio 3 , Manal <lb/>AbuOun 4 , Alasdair T. M. Hubbard 3 , Mike J. Bowes 2 , Mark J. Bailey 2 , Tim E. A. <lb/>Peto 3,5 , Sarah J. Hoosdally 3 , A. Sarah Walker 3,5 , Robert P. Sebra 6 , Derrick W. <lb/>Crook 3,5 , Muna Anjum 4 , Daniel S. Read 2 , Nicole Stoesser 3 , on behalf of the <lb/>REHAB consortium. <lb/>1 Harborne Building, School of Biological Sciences, University of Reading, <lb/>RG6 6AS, UK <lb/>2 Centre for Ecology &amp; Hydrology, Wallingford, Oxfordshire, OX10 8BB, UK <lb/>3 Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK <lb/>4 Department of Bacteriology, Animal and Plant Health Agency, Addlestone, <lb/>Surrey, KT15 3NB, UK <lb/>5 NIHR Health Protection Research Unit (HPRU) in Healthcare-associated <lb/>Infections and Antimicrobial Resistance at University of Oxford in partnership <lb/>with Public Health England, Oxford, UK <lb/>6 Department of Genetics and Genomics, Icahn School of Medicine at Mt <lb/>Sinai, New York, NY, USA <lb/>Corresponding authors <lb/>H. Soon Gweon, h.s.gweon@reading.ac.uk <lb/>Nicole Stoesser, nicole.stoesser@ndm.ox.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background. Shotgun metagenomics is increasingly used to characterise <lb/>microbial communities, particularly for the investigation of antimicrobial <lb/>resistance (AMR) in different animal and environmental contexts. There are <lb/>many different approaches for inferring the taxonomic composition and AMR <lb/>gene content of complex community samples from shotgun metagenomic <lb/>data, but there has been little work establishing the optimum sequencing <lb/>depth, data processing and analysis methods for these samples. In this study <lb/>we used shotgun metagenomics and sequencing of cultured isolates from the <lb/>same samples to address these issues. We sampled three potential <lb/>environmental AMR gene reservoirs (pig caeca, river sediment, effluent) and <lb/>sequenced samples with shotgun metagenomics at high depth (~200 million <lb/>reads per sample). Alongside this, we cultured single-colony isolates of <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae from the same samples and used hybrid sequencing <lb/>(short-and long-reads) to create high-quality assemblies for comparison to <lb/>the metagenomic data. To automate data processing, we developed an open-<lb/>source software pipeline, &apos;ResPipe&apos;. <lb/>Results. Taxonomic profiling was much more stable to sequencing depth <lb/>than AMR gene content. 1 million reads per sample was sufficient to achieve <lb/>&lt;1% dissimilarity to the full taxonomic composition. However, at least 80 <lb/>million reads per sample were required to recover the full richness of different <lb/>AMR gene families present in the sample, and additional allelic diversity of <lb/>AMR genes was still being discovered in effluent at 200 million reads per <lb/>sample. Normalising the number of reads mapping to AMR genes using gene <lb/>length and an exogenous spike of Thermus thermophilus DNA substantially <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>changed the estimated gene abundance distributions. While the majority of <lb/>genomic content from cultured isolates from effluent was recoverable using <lb/>shotgun metagenomics, this was not the case for pig caeca or river sediment. <lb/>Conclusions. Sequencing depth and profiling method can critically affect the <lb/>profiling of polymicrobial animal and environmental samples with shotgun <lb/>metagenomics. Both sequencing of cultured isolates and shotgun <lb/>metagenomics can recover substantial diversity that is not identified using the <lb/>other methods. Particular consideration is required when inferring AMR gene <lb/>content or presence by mapping metagenomic reads to a database. ResPipe, <lb/>the open-source software pipeline we have developed, is freely available <lb/>(https://gitlab.com/hsgweon/ResPipe). <lb/>Keywords. Antimicrobial resistance (AMR), One Health, metagenomics, <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>BACKGROUND <lb/>Antimicrobial resistance (AMR) is a significant global health threat (1,2) and <lb/>understanding the evolution, emergence and transmission of AMR genes <lb/>requires a &apos;One Health&apos; approach considering human, animal and <lb/>environmental reservoirs (3). Methods for profiling species and AMR gene <lb/>content in samples from these niches can be broadly categorised as either <lb/>culture-dependent or culture-independent. Culture-dependent methods have <lb/>the advantage of isolating individual strains for detailed analysis, but hugely <lb/>underestimate species and AMR gene diversity. Culture-independent <lb/>methods typically involve shotgun metagenomics, in which the DNA of a <lb/>complete microbial community in a sample is extracted and sequenced, and <lb/>the sequencing reads are used to estimate AMR gene and/or species <lb/>distributions. The advantage of shotgun metagenomics is its relative lack of <lb/>bias, but it tends to be less sensitive than targeted, culture-based or molecular <lb/>approaches identifying specific drug-resistant isolates or AMR genes of <lb/>interest (4-6). <lb/>Problems in characterising the epidemiology of AMR are exemplified by the <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae family of bacteria. This family contains over 80 genera, <lb/>and includes many common human and animal pathogens, such as <lb/>Escherichia coli, that can also asymptomatically colonise human and animal <lb/>gastrointestinal tracts, and are also found in environmental reservoirs (7). <lb/>The genetic diversity of some Enterobacteriaceae species is remarkable: in E. <lb/>coli, it has been estimated that only ~10% of the 18,000 orthologous gene <lb/>families found in the pangenome are present in all strains (8). AMR in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Enterobacteriaceae is mediated by &gt;70 resistance gene families, and &gt;2,000 <lb/>known resistance gene variants have been catalogued (9,10). In addition to <lb/>mutational resistance, AMR genes are also commonly shared both within and <lb/>between species on mobile genetic elements such as insertion sequences, <lb/>transposons and plasmids. Individuals have been shown to harbour multiple <lb/>diverse AMR gene variants, strains and species of Enterobacteriaceae in their <lb/>gastrointestinal tract (11,12), highlighting that single-colony subcultures do not <lb/>recover the true AMR reservoir even within a small subsection of a microbial <lb/>community. <lb/>Attempting to near-completely classify AMR gene and species diversity by <lb/>any culture-based approach for raw faeces, effluent, and river sediment is <lb/>therefore unlikely to be feasible; hence, the use of shotgun metagenomics to <lb/>achieve this aim. However, the replicability of metagenomic surveys and the <lb/>sequencing depth (reads per sample) required to analyse these sample types <lb/>has not yet been explored in detail (13,14). <lb/>Motivated by the need to analyze large numbers of these samples in the <lb/>REHAB study (http://modmedmicro.nsms.ox.ac.uk/rehab/), here we carried <lb/>out a pilot study (Figure 1) to investigate: (i) the replicability of sequencing <lb/>outputs using common DNA extraction and sequencing methods; and the <lb/>impact of (ii) widely used taxonomic and AMR gene profiling approaches; (iii) <lb/>sequencing depth on taxonomic and AMR gene profiles; and (iv) sequencing <lb/>depth on the recoverability of genetic contents from isolates identified in the <lb/>same samples using culture-based approaches. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>RESULTS <lb/>Impact of sequencing depth on AMR profiles <lb/>Metagenomic sequencing produced approximately 200 million metagenomic <lb/>150bp paired-end reads per sample i.e. over 56 gigabases per sample <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1), of which &lt;0.05% of reads mapped with 100% <lb/>identity to a known AMR-related sequence (see next section). The number of <lb/>reads mapping to AMR gene families was largest in pig caeca (88,816 reads) <lb/>and effluent (77,044 reads). Upstream sediment did not have enough AMR-<lb/>related reads for further analysis (49 reads). <lb/>The effluent sample had the highest total richness of both AMR gene families <lb/>and AMR allelic variants (Figure 2). Sequencing depth significantly affected <lb/>the ability to evaluate richness of AMR gene families in effluent and pig caeca, <lb/>which represent highly diverse microbial environments. The number of AMR <lb/>gene families observed in effluent and pig caeca stabilized (see Methods: <lb/>&apos;Rarefaction curves&apos;) at a sequencing depth of ~80 million reads per sample <lb/>(depth required to achieve 95% of estimated total richness, 𝑑 !.!&quot; : 72-127 <lb/>million reads per sample). For AMR allelic variants in effluent, the richness did <lb/>not appear to have plateaued even at a sequencing depth of 200 million reads <lb/>per sample, suggesting the full allelic diversity was not captured (𝑑 !.!&quot; : 193 <lb/>million reads per sample). <lb/>Specific mapping to AMR genes and allelic variants <lb/>We exploited the hierarchical structure of the Comprehensive Antimicrobial <lb/>Resistance Database (CARD) to assign reads to their respective AMR gene <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>families and AMR allelic variants using a specific read mapping strategy i.e. to <lb/>count only reads which mapped to a unique region of an allele or a gene <lb/>family. In order to place a lower bound on the AMR diversity present, we <lb/>adopted a stringent approach which counted only alignments with 100% <lb/>sequence identity to CARD sequences. The resulting AMR gene family <lb/>profiles differed significantly between the samples (Figure 3). The most <lb/>abundant AMR gene families in effluent and pig caeca were &quot;23S rRNA with <lb/>mutations conferring resistance to macrolide&quot; and &quot;tetracycline-resistant <lb/>ribosomal protection protein&quot;, respectively. There were 10,631 and 733 reads <lb/>assigned to a &quot;multiple gene family&quot; category in the effluent and pig caeca, <lb/>respectively. These represent reads that were mapped across multiple AMR <lb/>gene families and therefore could not be uniquely assigned to any single <lb/>family. <lb/>Reads that mapped to one specific AMR gene family but onto multiple allelic <lb/>variants (i.e. could not be assigned to one specific allele) were classified as <lb/>&quot;multiple alleles&quot;. There was evidence of high allelic diversity, including among <lb/>clinically relevant AMR gene families. For example, 47.7% of the reads <lb/>mapped to the &quot;OXA beta-lactamase&quot; family could not be assigned to a <lb/>specific allele (4,466 out of 9,357 reads; third-most abundant gene family by <lb/>reads). Similarly, the most abundant gene family by reads in pig caeca was <lb/>&quot;tetracycline-resistant ribosomal protection protein&quot;, and 35.8% of the reads <lb/>that mapped within this family could not be assigned to a specific allele <lb/>(18,228 out of the 50,886 reads). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Impact of normalisation strategies on AMR allelic variant abundances <lb/>Normalising by gene length (see Methods: &apos;Normalisation of gene counts&apos;) <lb/>had a profound effect on the distributions and the ranking order of AMR allelic <lb/>variants in general (Figure 4). Further normalisation by T. thermophilus reads <lb/>did not affect the per sample distributions of AMR allelic variants, but it <lb/>allowed more accurate comparison between samples by estimating absolute <lb/>abundance of any given variant in the sample. The number of reads that <lb/>mapped to T. thermophilus were similar between three samples, and this <lb/>meant that the changes were small (i.e. a slight relative increase in the <lb/>effluent compared to the pig caeca sample). While most of the alleles had <lb/>lateral coverages between 90% and 100% in effluent and pig caeca samples <lb/>(Figure 3, right panels), &quot;Moraxella catarrhalis 23S rRNA with mutation <lb/>conferring resistance to macrolide antibiotics&quot; had lateral coverage of 29% <lb/>despite being one of the most abundant alleles in the effluent. <lb/>Impact of different assignment methods on taxonomic composition <lb/>While Centrifuge overall classified more reads than Kraken, both methods <lb/>showed a similar trend of effluent having a greater proportion of reads <lb/>classified as bacterial compared to upstream sediment, which had more than <lb/>pig caeca (Figure 5a). Apart from Centrifuge classifying noticeably more <lb/>Eukaryota and Viruses (0.7% and 0.05% respectively) than Kraken (0.09% <lb/>and 0.01% respectively), a large proportion of reads from both methods were <lb/>unclassified (70.0% and 83.3% for Centrifuge and Kraken respectively). The <lb/>proportions of recoverable bacterial 16S rRNA fragments were low for all <lb/>samples (0.16%, 0.23% and 0.04% for effluent, pig caeca and upstream <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>sediment samples respectively), highlighting that shotgun metagenomics is an <lb/>extremely inefficient method for obtaining 16S rRNA gene sequences. <lb/>The bacteria phylum-level classication (Figure 5b) showed structural <lb/>differences among all three classification methods. The overall community <lb/>structure and composition were more similar between Kraken and Centrifuge <lb/>than the &apos;in silico 16S&apos; approach (see Methods: &apos;Taxonomic profiling&apos;). This <lb/>was particularly apparent in the upstream sediment, where using &apos;in silico 16S&apos; <lb/>produced distinctively different community profiles from the other methods. <lb/>Kraken and Centrifuge classified between 377,675 to over 4 million reads as <lb/>Enterobacteriaceae. Again, overall composition was similar between these <lb/>two methods but showed some granularity in structure for pig caeca e.g. the <lb/>relative abundances of Escherichia were 34.3% and 50.9%, and for Klebsiella <lb/>10.6% and 4.9%, for Centrifuge and Kraken respectively. <lb/>Impact of sequencing depth on genus-level richess and taxonomic <lb/>profiles <lb/>Kraken and Centrifuge taxonomic profiles were highly stable to sequencing <lb/>depth within samples. Comparing different sequencing depths within samples <lb/>using Bray-Curtis dissimilarity showed that the relative taxonomic composition <lb/>was highly robust to sequencing depth, with 1 million reads per sample <lb/>already sufficient for &lt;1% dissimilarity to the composition inferred from 200 <lb/>million reads per sample (Supplementary Figure 1). This was true at both the <lb/>genus and species level, even though all classification methods are known to <lb/>have less precision and sensitivity at the species level (15,16). Intriguingly, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>the genus-level richness rapidly reached a plateau for all samples at ~1 <lb/>million reads per sample (Figure 6a and Figure 6b), suggesting a database <lb/>artifact (see &apos;Discussion&apos;). <lb/>Recovery of known genomic structures from cultured isolates using <lb/>metagenomes <lb/>In order to assess how well shotgun metagenomics could recapitulate culture-<lb/>dependent diversity, we cultured seven Enterobacteriaeceae isolates (four <lb/>from effluent, two from pig caeca, one from upstream sediment; Table 1), then <lb/>performed hybrid assembly (Supplementary Table 2). We then assembled <lb/>near-complete genomes and mapped metagenomic reads back to these <lb/>genomes (see Methods: &apos;Mapping of metagenomic sequences onto isolates&apos;; <lb/>Supplementary Table 3). 26/28 contigs from effluent isolates rapidly achieved <lb/>100% lateral coverage at 1X using metagenomic reads at 80-100 million <lb/>reads per sample (Figure 7a), with the two other contigs having almost-<lb/>complete coverage at 200 million reads (98.7% and 99.8% respectively). Pig <lb/>caeca isolates showed lower but fairly comprehensive lateral coverage of at <lb/>least 75% for chromosomes at 200 million reads (Figure 7b), but only one <lb/>contig (P1-5, shown in yellow) reached complete lateral coverage. The single <lb/>chromosomal contig recovered from the upstream sediment isolate only had <lb/>0.2% of its bases covered at 200 million reads per sample, reflecting its <lb/>scarcity in the metagenome (Figure 7c, Supplementary Table 3). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>To our knowledge, our study is the first to have simultaneously investigated <lb/>effluent, animal caecal and environmental metagenomics with deep <lb/>sequencing of 200 million 150 bp paired-end reads per sample (~60 <lb/>gigabases per sample). Previous studies have used from 10 million to 70 <lb/>million reads per sample (approximate bases per sample: 3Gb (17), 4 Gb (19), <lb/>7 Gb (6), 12 Gb (18)), often with shorter reads. We have demonstrated the <lb/>significant effect of sequencing depth on taxonomic and AMR gene content <lb/>profiling, and the ability to recover genomic content (obtained via single-<lb/>colony culture of isolates from the sample) from metagenomics. In brief, we <lb/>find that while accurately capturing broad-scale taxonomic composition <lb/>requires relatively low sequencing depth, this is emphatically not the case for <lb/>AMR gene diversity. This has critical importance for the many studies that <lb/>seek to characterise animal and environmental reservoirs of AMR, and for the <lb/>contextualisation of findings reported in previous metagenomics studies. <lb/>Deep metagenomic sequencing has been investigated more thoroughly in the <lb/>context of the human microbiome. Hillmann et al. (2018) recently reported <lb/>ultradeep metagenomics (2.5 billion reads) on two human stool samples, <lb/>concluding that as few as 0.5 million reads per sample could recover broad-<lb/>scale taxonomic changes and species profiles at &gt;0.05% relative abundance <lb/>(14). In line with this, we find that 1 million reads per sample is already <lb/>sufficient to accurately obtain taxonomic composition (at &lt;1% dissimilarity to <lb/>the &apos;true&apos; composition at 200 million reads). However, even 200 million reads <lb/>per sample is not enough to obtain the complete diversity of AMR genes in <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>effluent. This is potentially concerning because environmental metagenomics <lb/>studies often use sequencing depths of as little as ~10 million reads per <lb/>sample (~3.6Gb). For pig caeca samples, 80 million reads per sample <lb/>appears to be adequate for sampling all AMR gene families represented in <lb/>CARD, but still not adequate for exhausting AMR allelic variants. Notably, we <lb/>adopted the stringent criterion of a perfect (i.e. 100%) match to assign any <lb/>given read to a reference AMR sequence. This strategy obviously reduces the <lb/>risk of false positives, while increasing false negatives. Therefore, our results <lb/>represent a conservative lower bound on the AMR diversity present in the <lb/>samples we analysed. <lb/>An additional challenge of metagenomics analysis in the context of AMR is <lb/>choosing a consistent strategy for &apos;counting&apos; AMR genes, whether in terms of <lb/>their presence or relative abundance, from mapped reads. It remains unclear <lb/>what the best approach is for this problem. One option is to count all the reads <lb/>which map to a reference gene; however, this means that reads are <lb/>potentially counted multiple times when the reference gene shares homology <lb/>with other genes in the database, or that counts may be underestimated if <lb/>reads are randomly assigned to best reference matches. In addition, reads <lb/>which map to a wildtype, non-resistant sequence may also be inadvertently <lb/>and inappropriately counted. Another option is to use only reads which map to <lb/>regions of a gene that are unique and not shared with other genes in the <lb/>database (e.g. as in ShortBRED (20)). This is a more conservative approach, <lb/>but may be inherently biased against closely-related genes in the database. <lb/>For example, CARD contains 14 sequences for bla NDM genes, which differ at <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>less than 2% of their positions, so each gene individually has very few specific <lb/>regions. Exploiting knowledge of the often complex genetic variation within <lb/>AMR gene families is necessary to avoid erroneous conclusions regarding <lb/>presence/absence. Inferred abundances of particular AMR genes are likely <lb/>frequently contingent not only on mapping and counting strategies, but also <lb/>on the particular genetic features of the AMR genes catalogued in the chosen <lb/>reference database. Interpreting and comparing results across studies <lb/>utilising different methods therefore becomes difficult. <lb/>Once the type of count data to be considered (in terms of number of reads <lb/>mapping to a gene) has been chosen, a normalisation strategy is required to <lb/>compare across genes and samples. We found that normalising by gene <lb/>length changed the inferred abundance distributions of AMR genes across all <lb/>the sample types studied, again with important implications for those studies <lb/>that have not undertaken this kind of normalisation. We have also outlined a <lb/>protocol to obtain a pseudo-absolute gene copy number of specific regions of <lb/>AMR genes by normalising by both gene length and an exogenous spike of T. <lb/>thermophilus. While we do not claim that this accurately reflects the true <lb/>abundance of individual genes, we believe it is useful for comparisons across <lb/>samples within a study. In our study we took great care to ensure <lb/>standardised DNA extraction and had small batches of samples; probably as <lb/>a result, we obtained similar proportions of sequences of T. thermophilus for <lb/>all samples (range: 0.067-0.082%), but this may not always be the case. <lb/>Appropriate normalisation using exogenous DNA spikes to account for some <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the extraction biases could have potentially dramatic effects on results and <lb/>their interpretation. <lb/>As well as examining normalised abundances, the lateral coverage of a gene <lb/>is also an important metric to decide whether a certain allele is likely present <lb/>in the sample. In effluent, the most abundant gene by specific read count was <lb/>&quot;Moraxella catarrhalis 23S rRNA with mutation conferring resistance to <lb/>macrolide antibiotics&quot;. However, the gene only had 29% lateral coverage, and <lb/>this result should therefore be interpreted cautiously. In fact, the high specific <lb/>read count is probably because CARD only includes one Moraxella rRNA <lb/>gene with an AMR mutation compared to twenty Escherichia rRNA genes; the <lb/>lateral coverage suggests that the AMR allele is not in fact present. This <lb/>underlines the importance of considering multiple metrics simultaneously. <lb/>Both taxonomic and AMR gene profiling outputs are clearly dependent on the <lb/>species and AMR databases used as references. It should be additionally <lb/>noted that for AMR gene profiling, some genes are variants of a wildtype <lb/>which may differ by as little as a single SNP. Because short-read <lb/>metagenomics typically surveys ≤150 bp fragments, even specific read counts <lb/>can in fact plausibly be wildtypes rather than particular resistance variants. <lb/>This can be overcome by adopting our stringent approach which requires an <lb/>exact match (i.e. at 100%) to call a given variant in the database; although <lb/>obviously this increases the rate of false negatives, we have shown that this <lb/>strategy appears successful given adequate sequencing depth. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>We found a reasonable consistency between taxonomic classification <lb/>methods, but there were differences between Kraken and Centrifuge, and <lb/>undoubtedly there would have been differences with other methods, had we <lb/>tested them. This is a previously recognised issue (e.g. as in (21)) and has no <lb/>single solution; methods are optimised for different purposes and perform <lb/>differently depending on the combination of sample type, sequencing method, <lb/>and reference database used. As the field changes so rapidly and newer <lb/>methods become available, we strongly recommend that researchers with <lb/>shotgun metagenomic data review excellent benchmarking efforts such as <lb/>CAMI (21) and LEMMI (22) and assess the tools using a particular <lb/>quantitative metric rather than making a (perhaps arbitrary) choice for their <lb/>analysis. Investigating the robustness of conclusions to choice of method is <lb/>also a recommended step (23,24). <lb/>Remarkably, there were no &apos;unique genera&apos; at high sequencing depth: reads <lb/>assigned to all genera were present in all three sample types at high depth. <lb/>We believe this is an artifact due to the limited number of genomes available <lb/>in the species database used for the assignment methods. The RefSeq <lb/>database contains complete genomes for 11,443 strains, but these represent <lb/>only 1,065 genera. Our samples almost exhausted the entire genus space: <lb/>the number of genera that were classified by Centrifuge was 1,036, and this <lb/>number was the same for the effluent, pig caeca and upstream sediment <lb/>samples, i.e. all three samples had the same number of total unique genera <lb/>observed at 200 million reads depth. This was the same with Kraken, which <lb/>classified 1,035 genera in total and there was no difference in richness <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>between the three samples. This highlights the importance of using diversity <lb/>measures which take into account the relative abundance of taxa rather than <lb/>just their presence or absence. <lb/>We also found that a large number of reads (&gt;50%) were unclassified by <lb/>either Kraken or Centrifuge. The absence of organisms such as fungi from our <lb/>reference database could have played a role in this, but other studies of <lb/>effluent have also found that between 42% and 68% of short metagenomic <lb/>reads cannot be assigned to any reference sequence (25-27). Our focus was <lb/>on using the best available tools to assess the bacterial composition of <lb/>samples; understanding what this unassigned microbial &apos;dark matter&apos; <lb/>represents was beyond the scope of this study, but would be valuable future <lb/>work. <lb/>Our analyses confirm that using culture-based methods offered <lb/>complementary and additional information to shotgun metagenomics. By <lb/>mapping metagenomic reads back to high-quality hybrid assemblies obtained <lb/>via culture, we found that the majority of isolates from effluent were <lb/>recoverable by metagenomics at sequencing depths. However, the majority of <lb/>isolates from pig caeca were not recovered. These results exemplify the need <lb/>for exploring both methods in analysing AMR genes and microbial <lb/>communities, as both show different perspectives on the AMR profiles and <lb/>strains present in a given sample. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>In summary, we have used a combination of deep metagenomic sequencing, <lb/>hybrid assembly of cultured isolates, and taxonomic and AMR gene profiling <lb/>methods to perform a detailed exploration of methodological approaches to <lb/>characterise animal and environmental metagenomic samples. Sequencing <lb/>depth critically affects the inferred AMR gene content and taxonomic diversity <lb/>of complex, polymicrobial samples, and even 200 million reads per sample <lb/>was insufficient to capture total AMR allelic diversity in effluent. Choice of <lb/>taxonomic profiler can result in significant differences in inferred species <lb/>composition. <lb/>The open-source software pipeline we have developed is freely available as <lb/>&apos;ResPipe&apos;. As well as packaging existing tools, ResPipe provides detailed <lb/>information on various metrics that are useful for assessing AMR gene <lb/>abundances, including: a novel normalisation technique for read counts, <lb/>specific mapping counts, and lateral coverage, all of which can provide <lb/>different but important insights. There is undoubtedly vast diversity present in <lb/>microbial communities. Establishing best practices and pipelines for analysing <lb/>this diversity with shotgun metagenomics is crucial to appropriately assess <lb/>AMR in environmental, animal and human faecal samples. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Sample types and settings <lb/>We sampled three distinct potential AMR reservoirs, namely: (i) pooled pig <lb/>caecal contents from 10 pigs from a breeder farm in Yorkshire and the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Humber (denoted as &quot;pig caeca&quot;); (ii) river sediment 100m upstream of a <lb/>sewage treatment works (STW) at Cholsey STW, Cholsey, Oxfordshire <lb/>(&quot;upstream sediment&quot;); and (iii) treated sewage effluent emitted from Cholsey <lb/>STW (&quot;effluent&quot;). Cholsey STW is a plant that serves a population equivalent <lb/>of ~21,000 with a consented flow of 3200 m 3 /day; processes include primary <lb/>settlement tanks, followed by biological disc filters and humus tanks, and <lb/>subsequently disc filtration. These sample types were chosen to represent a <lb/>spectrum of predicted diversity of microbial communities (i.e. high to low: <lb/>effluent, pig caeca, upstream sediment). <lb/>The pooled pig caeca had been collected as part of a separate study <lb/>surveying the presence of AMR genes in E. coli in pigs from 56 farms across <lb/>the UK (28). In brief, caecal contents were sampled from 10 randomly <lb/>selected healthy finishing pigs from each of the farms at 12 different abattoirs <lb/>(March 2014 -October 2015), and suspended in 22.5 mL of PBS (processing <lb/>within 24hrs of collection). Aliquots of 100 µL were frozen at -80 °C. This <lb/>study used an aliquot of pooled pig caeca selected randomly from this <lb/>collection. <lb/>For effluent and upstream sediment samples, sterile Whirl-pack TM bags were <lb/>attached to extendable sampling arms and placed into flow at the relevant site. <lb/>Samples in the bags were stirred with sterile spoons, and 5 mLs added to a <lb/>sterile 50 mL centrifuge tube. This process was repeated five times to create <lb/>a composite sample of approximately 25 mL. Samples were stored in a cool <lb/>box at 4 °C for transport and processed within 24 hrs. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Metagenomic DNA extractions and Thermus spike-in <lb/>Metagenomic extractions on all samples were performed using the MoBio <lb/>PowerSoil® DNA Isolation Kit (Qiagen, Venlo, Netherlands), as per the <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s protocol, and including a beadbeating step of two 40 second <lb/>cycles at 6 m/s in lysing matrix E. 12.5 ng of naked Thermus thermophilus <lb/>DNA (reference strain HB27, Collection number ATCC BAA-163, ordered <lb/>from DSMZ, Germany) was added to each sample in the PowerBead tube at <lb/>the start of the experiment, prior to the addition of Solution C1 of the DNA <lb/>Isolation Kit. The rationale for this was to enable subsequent normalisation to <lb/>the number of T. thermophilus genomes sequenced to adjust for varying <lb/>amounts of sample input, and extraction bias (33) (see &apos;Normalisation of gene <lb/>counts&apos;, below). <lb/>Metagenomic sequencing <lb/>Pooled libraries of all DNA extracts were sequenced across four lanes of an <lb/>Illumina HiSeq 4000 platform, generating a median of 102,787,432 150 bp <lb/>paired-end reads (30.8 Gb) of data per extract. For the samples extracted in <lb/>replicate, we therefore had a median of 202,579,676 paired-end reads (60.7 <lb/>Gb) of data available for evaluation and sub-sampling analyses <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). To confirm replicability of our extraction method on <lb/>the same sample, duplicate extractions of all three samples were performed. <lb/>To test replicability of sequencing, pooled libraries derived from extracts were <lb/>each sequenced across four sequencing lanes. The sequences were pooled <lb/>into each sample resulting in 202,579,676, 215,047,930 and 198,865,221 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>reads for the effluent, pig caeca and upstream sediment respectively. The <lb/>effluent and pig caeca samples were both randomly subsampled down to 200 <lb/>million reads per sample for downstream analysis. <lb/>Analysis of both AMR gene profiles and taxonomic profiles for the same <lb/>extract pooled across multiple sequencing lanes (HiSeq) were highly <lb/>reproducible, with little evidence of differences across lanes, although there <lb/>was a significant difference between replicates of AMR gene profiles from <lb/>pooled pig caeca (p=0.03), and replicates of taxonomic profiles for upstream <lb/>sediment (p=0.03) (Supplementary Table 4). <lb/>Sequencing depth subsampling and quality filtering <lb/>In order to simulate the effect of sequencing at different depths, each set of <lb/>pooled reads from the three samples was repeatedly subsampled (n=10) <lb/>using VSEARCH (fastx_subsampling, (34)) into the following set of depth <lb/>intervals: 1M, 2M, 4M, 6M, 7M, 8M, 9M, 10M, 20M, 40M, 60M, 80M, 100M, <lb/>120M, 140M, 160M and 180M. Low-quality portions of all reads were trimmed <lb/>using TrimGalore (v.0.4.4_dev, (35)). Specifically, we used a length cut-off of <lb/>75 bp and average Phred score ≥25, and the first 13 bp of Illumina standard <lb/>adapters (AGATCGGAAGAGC) for adapter trimming. <lb/>Taxonomic profiling <lb/>For profiling the abundance of bacterial species, the reads were classified <lb/>with Kraken (v.1.1, default settings; (16)) and Centrifuge (v.1.0.4, default <lb/>settings; (15)), which were chosen based on recency and reported frequency <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>of use in the literature. RefSeq sequences (v.91; (36)) at a &quot;Complete genome&quot; <lb/>assembly level for bacteria (11,443 strains), archaea (275 strains), viral (7,855 <lb/>strains) and human were downloaded from the NCBI repositories and used to <lb/>build two sets of indexed databases for both Kraken and Centrifuge using <lb/>respective scripts provided by each classifier. An &apos;in silico 16S&apos; marker-gene <lb/>based classification was performed by extracting 16S rRNA genes from the <lb/>reads using METAXA2 (4) followed by taxonomic assignment with the naïve <lb/>Bayesian RDP classifier (v2.10; (37)) with a minimum confidence of 0.5 <lb/>against the GreenGenes database (v.13.5; (38)). <lb/>To validate the taxonomic profiling component of our pipeline, we analyzed <lb/>ten previously simulated gut metagenomes (GI tract data from &quot;2nd CAMI Toy <lb/>Human <lb/>Microbiome <lb/>Project <lb/>Dataset&quot;, <lb/>https://openstack.cebitec.uni-<lb/>bielefeld.de:8080/swift/v1/CAMI_Gastrointestinal_tract) <lb/>produced <lb/>for <lb/>benchmarking as part of CAMI (21). Comparing to the ground truth of the <lb/>simulated composition, using either Centrifuge or Kraken recovered the major <lb/>features of the taxonomic composition (Supplementary Figure 2a) with high <lb/>correlation between simulated and inferred species abundances <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 2b), although there were apparent discrepancies <lb/>between methods which we did not investigate further. <lb/>AMR gene profiling <lb/>The quality filtered reads were mapped with bbmapskimmer.sh (BBMap suite; <lb/>(39)) with default settings against sequences from the Comprehensive <lb/>Antibiotic Resistance Database (CARD, v.3.0.0, (10)) and the genome <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>sequence of T. Thermophilus which was spiked into the samples. At the time <lb/>of writing, CARD contained 2,439 AMR sequences. As CARD is primarily <lb/>designed for genomic data, each sequence has an associated &apos;model&apos; of <lb/>detection i.e. criteria determining matches to the CARD reference sequences <lb/>for any given query sequence. The chief distinction is between genes that <lb/>have a &quot;protein homolog&quot; model, where detection is assessed using a <lb/>BLASTP cut-off to find functional homologs (n=2,238; e.g. NDM-1 beta-<lb/>lactamase), and those with a &quot;non protein homolog&quot; model, where detection is <lb/>assessed using other methods including the locations of specific SNPs <lb/>(n=247; e.g. M. tuberculosis gyrA conferring resistance to fluoroquinolones). <lb/>Although we use a mapping-based approach from shotgun metagenomic <lb/>reads, we have included this information in ResPipe. For simplicity, we <lb/>designate &quot;protein homolog&quot; model genes and &quot;non protein homolog&quot; model <lb/>genes under the broad headings &quot;resistance by presence&quot; and &quot;resistance by <lb/>variation&quot;, respectively (where &quot;variation&quot; can encompass SNPs, knockout, or <lb/>overexpression). The BAM files generated by the mapping were processed by <lb/>a custom script to generate a count table where only alignments with a strict <lb/>100% sequence identity (without allowing any deletions or insertions) to <lb/>CARD sequences were counted. Where a read mapped to more than one <lb/>AMR gene family or an AMR allelic variant (i.e. could not be designated into <lb/>any one AMR gene family or AMR allelic variant) it was counted as &quot;multiple <lb/>families&quot; or &quot;multiple alleles&quot; respectively. For each AMR allelic variant, we <lb/>calculated &quot;lateral coverage&quot;, defined as the proportion of the gene covered <lb/>by at least a single base of mapped reads. Where reads mapped to multiple <lb/>families or alleles, lateral coverage could not be calculated. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>Rarefaction curves <lb/>For fitting the relationship between sequencing depth per sample 𝑑 and the <lb/>richness 𝑟 of AMR gene families or allelic variants, we used the species <lb/>accumulation model defined by Clench (40): 𝑟 𝑑 = <lb/>!×! <lb/>!!!×! . This model may be <lb/>flawed, but is only used here to give a rough estimate of the sequencing depth <lb/>required to achieve a proportion of 𝑞 (e.g. 95%) of the total richness, which is <lb/>then 𝑑 ! = <lb/>! <lb/>!×(!!!) . <lb/>Normalisation of gene counts <lb/>Assuming random sequencing, longer genes are more likely to be <lb/>represented in reads. In order to alleviate this gene length bias, the resulting <lb/>table was adjusted by multiplying each count by the average length of <lb/>mapped reads followed by dividing by the length of the AMR allelic variant to <lb/>which the reads were mapped. Where there were multiple alleles, average <lb/>length was used. In order to adjust for varying amounts of sample input and <lb/>extraction bias, the table was further normalised to the number of reads that <lb/>mapped to T. thermophilus using an adopted protocol from Satinsky et al. (33). <lb/>We added 12.5ng of Thermus thermophilus to each sample. This corresponds <lb/>to adding 6,025,538 copies of the T. thermophilus genome. The size of the T. <lb/>thermophilus genome is 1,921,946 bases, so the number of bases of T. <lb/>thermophilus added is 𝑁 !! <lb/>!&quot;&quot;#&quot; = 6,025,538 x 1,921,946. To obtain the number <lb/>of bases of T. thermophilus recovered by sequencing (𝑁 !! <lb/>!&quot;#$%&quot;!&quot;&amp; ), we take the <lb/>number of reads assigned to T. thermophilus and multiply it by the insert size <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>(300 bp). The read count 𝑁 ! for a particular subject g (e.g. a gene family or <lb/>allelic variant) can then be normalised as: <lb/>𝑁 ! = 𝑁 ! ×(𝑁 !! <lb/>!&quot;&quot;#&quot; ÷ 𝑁 !! <lb/>!&quot;#$%&quot;!&quot;&amp; ) <lb/>These normalisation protocols are intended to produce a pseudo-absolute <lb/>gene copy number of each AMR gene family and AMR allelic variant, while <lb/>recognising that this remains an estimated of the actual copy number of <lb/>genes present in any given sample. <lb/>Isolate culture and DNA extraction <lb/>For effluent samples, the effluent filter was mixed with 20 mL of nutrient broth <lb/>and shaken for 10 mins at 120 rpm. 100 µL of neat sample, and 10 -1 and 10 -2 <lb/>dilutions (in nutrient broth) were plated onto a CHROMagar Orientation agar <lb/>supplemented with a 10 µg cefpodoxime disc placed on one half of the agar <lb/>plate. For pig caeca and upstream sediment samples, aliquots of 100 µL of <lb/>sample at neat, 10 -1 , 10 -2 , and 10 -3 -fold dilutions were plated onto a <lb/>CHROMagar Orientation agar supplemented supplemented with a 10 µg <lb/>cefpodoxime disc placed on one half of the agar plate. Serial dilutions were <lb/>plated to enable morphological identification and isolation of individual <lb/>colonies. All plates were incubated at 37 °C for 18 hours. We used <lb/>cefpodoxime resistance as a surrogate marker for the selective culture of <lb/>more drug-resistant Enterobacteriaceae (29,30). <lb/>Up to four individual colonies from each sample with a typical appearance for <lb/>Escherichia coli, Klebsiella spp., Enterobacter spp. or Citrobacter spp., and <lb/>from either within or external to the cefpdoxime zone, were subcultured on <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>MacConkey agar with or without cefpodoxime discs, respectively. Following <lb/>sub-culture, species was confirmed by MALDI-ToF (Bruker), and stored in <lb/>nutrient broth + 10% glycerol at -80 °C prior to repeat sub-culture for DNA <lb/>extraction. <lb/>DNA was extracted from pure sub-cultures using the Qiagen Genomic <lb/>tip/100G (Qiagen, Venlo, Netherlands), according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Extracts from seven isolates (four from effluent, two from pig <lb/>caeca, and one from upstream sediment) were selected for combination long-<lb/>read (Pacific Biosciences) and short-read sequencing, based on sufficient <lb/>DNA yield (with a requirement at the time of the study for ~5µg DNA for library <lb/>preparation), and appropriate fragment size distributions (assessed using <lb/>TapeStation 4200, Agilent, Santa Clara, USA). These isolates were identified <lb/>using MALDI-ToF as Citrobacter freundii (two isolates), Enterobacter <lb/>kobei/cloacae (three isolates), and Escherichia coli (two isolates) (Table 1). <lb/>Isolate sequencing <lb/>Aliquots of the same DNA extract were sequenced by two methods: short-<lb/>read (Illumina), and long-read (Pacific BioSciences). For Illumina sequencing, <lb/>extracts were sequenced on the HiSeq 4000 platform. Libraries were <lb/>constructed using the NEBNext Ultra DNA Sample Prep Master Mix Kit (NEB), <lb/>with minor modifications and a custom automated protocol on a Biomek FX <lb/>(Beckman). Sequenced reads were 150 bp paired-end, with a median of <lb/>1,355,833 reads per isolate (range: 1.06-1.66 million) after read correction <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>with SPAdes (Supplementary Table 2), corresponding to a chromosomal <lb/>coverage per isolate of ~30X with a insert size of 300 bp. <lb/>To generate long-read data from the same DNA extract for any given isolate, <lb/>we used single molecule real-time sequencing using the PacBio RSII. Briefly, <lb/>DNA library preparation was performed according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions (P5-C3 sequencing enzyme and chemistry, respectively see <lb/>Supplementary Material of Sheppard et al. (31)). After read correction and <lb/>trimming, there were a median of 14,189 reads per isolate (range: 12,162-<lb/>17,523) with a median read length of 13,146 bp (range: 10,106-14,991) <lb/>(Supplementary Table 2). <lb/>Hybrid assembly for isolates <lb/>We assembled genomes for isolates using a version of a pipeline we had <lb/>previously developed and validated against multiple Enterobacteriaceae <lb/>genomes including two reference strains (De Maio, Shaw et al. 2019). In brief, <lb/>we corrected Illumina reads with SPAdes (v3.10.1) and corrected and <lb/>trimmed PacBio reads with Canu (v1.5), then performed hybrid assembly <lb/>using Unicycler (v0.4.0) with Pilon (v1.22) without correction, with a minimum <lb/>component size of 500 and a minimum dead end size of 500. Out of 35 total <lb/>contigs across seven isolates, 28 were circularised (78%), including two <lb/>chromosomes and 24 plasmids. Normalised depths of plasmids ranged from <lb/>0.6-102.6x relative to chromosomal depth, and lengths between 2.2-162.9kb <lb/>(Supplementary Table 3). The majority of plasmids were found in effluent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>isolates (24/29). We checked MALDI-ToF species identification with mlst <lb/>(v2.15.1; (32)) and found agreement (Supplementary Table 2). <lb/>Mapping of metagenomic sequences onto isolates <lb/>To investigate the feasibility of accurately identifiying genetic structures <lb/>(chromosomes and plasmids) in the metagenomic reads in relation to the <lb/>impact of sequencing depth, we used the assembled chromosomes and <lb/>plasmids derived from the cultured and sequenced isolates as reference <lb/>genomes (in silico genomic &quot;probes&quot;) to which the metagenomic short reads <lb/>were mapped. We used the same mapping protocol used for the <lb/>aforementioned functional profiling and lateral coverage was calculated for <lb/>each chromosome/plasmid at any given sequencing depth. <lb/>Implementation into a Nextflow pipeline <lb/>The entire workflow (both taxonomic and AMR gene profiling) has been <lb/>implemented into a Nextflow (41) pipeline complying with POSIX standards, <lb/>written in Python: ResPipe (https://gitlab.com/hsgweon/ResPipe). All analyses <lb/>were performed on a compute cluster hosted by the NERC Centre for Ecology <lb/>and Hydrology, Wallingford, UK, with 50 compute nodes, each with a total of <lb/>1TB of RAM. <lb/>Statistical analyses <lb/>We assessed differences in taxonomic and AMR gene profiles between <lb/>replicates and sequencing lanes by calculating Bray-Curtis dissimilarities, <lb/>which quantify compositional differences based on relative abundances. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>These were then used to perform permutational multivariate analysis of <lb/>variance tests (PERMANOVA) using the vegan package (v.2.4-1; (42)). A t-<lb/>test from R base package (43) was performed to assess the differences in <lb/>richness between subsampled groups of consecutive sequencing depths. <lb/>Figures were produced using ggplot2 (44). <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">LIST OF ABBREVIATIONS <lb/>AMR: antimicrobial resistance <lb/>SNP: single nucleotide polymorphism <lb/>CARD: (the) Comprehensive Antibiotic Resistance Database <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">DECLARATIONS <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate. No ethical permission was <lb/>required as the samples were collected from pig caeca, at abattoir, post <lb/>slaughter, by FSA or APHA vets. APHA gained permission from pig <lb/>farmers/owners to obtain these samples. <lb/>Consent for publication. Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of data and material. The datasets generated and/or analysed <lb/>during the current study are available in the NCBI repository (BioProject <lb/>number: PRJNA529503). The ResPipe pipeline is available under a GPC <lb/>licence at: https://gitlab.com/hsgweon/ResPipe. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests. The authors declare that they have no competing <lb/>interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding. This work was funded by the Antimicrobial Resistance Cross-<lb/>council Initiative supported by the seven research councils [NE/N019989/1 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="funding">and NE/N019660/1]. DWC, TEAP, and ASW are affiliated to the National <lb/>Institute for Health Research Health Protection Research Unit (NIHR HPRU) <lb/>in Healthcare Associated Infections and Antimicrobial Resistance at University <lb/>of Oxford in partnership with Public Health England (PHE) [grant HPRU-2012-<lb/>10041]. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily <lb/>those of the NHS, the NIHR, the Department of Health or Public Health <lb/>England. This work is supported by the NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research <lb/>Centre. The funders had no role in the design of the study, analyses, <lb/>interpretation of the data or writing of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions. NS and HSG designed the study, with input from all <lb/>authors. DSR, MB and MA collected samples. ATH and DSR performed the <lb/>laboratory work (culture, DNA extractions). RS performed PacBio long-read <lb/>sequencing; Illumina sequencing was undertaken at the Wellcome Trust <lb/>Centre for Human Genetics as part of a collaborative agreement. HSG <lb/>developed ResPipe with input from NS; HSG and JS implemented ResPipe in <lb/>NextFlow. NDM, LS, and HSG performed the data processing and <lb/>bioinformatics analyses. HSG, LS, JS and NS drafted the manuscript. All <lb/>authors read, improved and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. The REHAB consortium includes (bracketed individuals <lb/>included in main author list): (Abuoun M), (Anjum M), (Bailey MJ), Barker L, <lb/>Brett H, (Bowes MJ), Chau K, (Crook DW), (De Maio N), Gilson D, (Gweon <lb/>HS), (Hubbard ATM), (Hoosdally S), Kavanagh J, Jones H, (Peto TEA), (Read <lb/>DS), (Sebra R), (Shaw LP), Sheppard AE, Smith R, Stubberfield E, (Swann J), <lb/>(Walker AS), Woodford N. This publication made use of the PubMLST <lb/>website (https://pubmlst.org/) developed by Keith Jolley (45) and sited at the <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">University of Oxford. The development of that website was funded by the <lb/>Wellcome Trust. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interests. The authors declare they have no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURES <lb/>Figure 1. Schematic overview of the study. For each sample, we used both a <lb/>metagenomics and culture-based approach. We developed a software pipeline (&apos;ResPipe&apos;) for <lb/>the metagenomic data. For more details on each step of the workflow, see Methods. <lb/>METAGENOMICS <lb/>CULTURE-BASED <lb/>long read <lb/>short read <lb/>HYBRID ASSEMBLY <lb/>Isolates on selective media <lb/>SEQUENCING <lb/>chromosomes/plasmids <lb/>200M PE reads (2 x 150 bps) per sample <lb/>Subsampled to various sequencing depths <lb/>TABULATE <lb/>MAPPING ONTO AMR GENES <lb/>gene family Z -<lb/>gene family Z -allele A <lb/>gene family Z -allele B <lb/>multiple <lb/>alleles <lb/>(A &amp; B) <lb/>gene family Z -<lb/>gene family Z -allele A <lb/>gene family Z -allele B <lb/>multiple <lb/>alleles <lb/>specific read count <lb/>10 <lb/>6 <lb/>11 <lb/>RECOVERABILITY <lb/>OF ISOLATES BY METAGENOMIC READS <lb/>74% <lb/>21% <lb/>lateral coverage <lb/>for each depth <lb/>effluent pig caeca upstream <lb/>sediment <lb/>SAMPLES <lb/>for each sample <lb/>selected isolates <lb/>TAXONOMIC <lb/>CLASSIFICATION <lb/>Centrifuge <lb/>Kraken <lb/>in silico 16S <lb/>ResPipe* <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Rarefaction curve at various sequencing depths for (a) AMR gene families, and (b) AMR gene allelic variants. <lb/>Colours indicate sample type. For each sampling depth, sequences were randomly subsampled 10 times, with each point representing a different <lb/>subsampling. Lines connect the means (large circles) of these points for each sample type. <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>Richness <lb/>Richness <lb/>a. Gene families <lb/>Sequencing depth (million reads) <lb/>Sequencing depth (million reads) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>180 <lb/>200 <lb/>b. Allelic variants <lb/>Upstream <lb/>Sediment <lb/>Pig Caecal <lb/>Effluent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. The most common AMR gene families and gene allelic variants in each sample. Left panel: the top 20 AMR gene families <lb/>from effluent, pig caeca and upstream sediment by number of reads (top to bottom), with the top three most abundant highlighted in colour (hue indicates <lb/>sample type) for comparison with the right-hand panel. Right panel: the most abundant AMR gene allelic variants within these top three most abundant gene <lb/>families (left to right), sorted by abundance. For more information on the definitions of &apos;AMR gene family&apos; and &apos;allelic variant&apos;, see Methods: &apos;AMR gene <lb/>profiling&apos;. <lb/>22931 <lb/>10631 <lb/>9357 <lb/>9069 <lb/>6659 <lb/>3780 <lb/>2332 <lb/>1986 <lb/>1605 <lb/>1524 <lb/>822 <lb/>650 <lb/>597 <lb/>594 <lb/>507 <lb/>493 <lb/>420 <lb/>350 <lb/>216 <lb/>186 <lb/>small multidrug resistance (SMR) antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>CfxA beta−lactamase <lb/>AAC(3) <lb/>APH(6) <lb/>APH(3&apos;&apos;) <lb/>macrolide phosphotransferase (MPH) <lb/>resistance−nodulation−cell division antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>MOX beta−lactamase <lb/>tet−resistant ribo. protection protein <lb/>ABC−F ATP binding cassette ribosomal protection protein <lb/>AAC(6&apos;) <lb/>trimethoprim resistant dihydrofolate reductase dfr <lb/>16s rRNA wmcr. to aminoglycoside <lb/>qnr <lb/>sulfonamide resistant sul <lb/>ANT(3&apos;&apos;) <lb/>MFS antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>OXA beta−lactamase <lb/>Multiple gene families <lb/>23S rRNA wmcr. to macrolide <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>All AMR Gene Families <lb/>Top 20 AMR Gene Families <lb/>Allelic variants from top 3 AMR gene families <lb/>Allelic variants from top 3 AMR gene families <lb/>Allelic variants from top 3 AMR gene families <lb/>50886 <lb/>16198 <lb/>3862 <lb/>3213 <lb/>2728 <lb/>2299 <lb/>1443 <lb/>1323 <lb/>1305 <lb/>733 <lb/>726 <lb/>538 <lb/>458 <lb/>300 <lb/>292 <lb/>258 <lb/>248 <lb/>218 <lb/>132 <lb/>124 <lb/>efflux pump regulator <lb/>elfamycin resistant EF−Tu <lb/>ANT(9) <lb/>streptothricin acetyltransferase <lb/>APH(3&apos;&apos;) <lb/>ROB beta−lactamase <lb/>ANT(3&apos;&apos;) <lb/>sulfonamide resistant sul <lb/>resistance−nodulation−cell division antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>APH(3&apos;) <lb/>Multiple gene families <lb/>ANT(6) <lb/>23S rRNA wmcr. to macrolide antibiotics <lb/>ACI beta−lactamase <lb/>lincosamide nucleotidyltransferase <lb/>tetracycline inactivation enzyme <lb/>CfxA beta−lactamase <lb/>Erm 23S ribosomal RNA methyltransferase <lb/>major facilitator superfamily antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>tet−resistant ribo. protection protein <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>22 <lb/>22 <lb/>4 <lb/>1 <lb/>AER beta−lactamase <lb/>tetracycline−resistant ribosomal protection protein <lb/>23S rRNA wmcr. macrolidee <lb/>16S rRNA wmcr. aminoglycoside <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>26 <lb/>84 <lb/>182 <lb/>5650 <lb/>16975 <lb/>10631 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>18 <lb/>25 <lb/>28 <lb/>29 <lb/>34 <lb/>36 <lb/>98 <lb/>518 <lb/>1826 <lb/>2220 <lb/>4466 <lb/>0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>C. reinhardtii 23S <lb/>wmcr. erythromycin <lb/>M. avium 23S <lb/>wmcr. clarithromycin <lb/>S. ambofaciens 23S <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>M. smegmatis 23S <lb/>wmcr. clarithromycin <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>S. pneumoniae 23S <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>H. pylori 23S <lb/>wmcr. clarithromycin <lb/>E. coli 23S w.m.c.r. <lb/>erythromycin &amp; telithromycin <lb/>M. catarrhalis 23S <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>OXA−199 <lb/>OXA−21 <lb/>OXA−278 <lb/>OXA−347 <lb/>OXA−198 <lb/>OXA−212 <lb/>OXA−46 <lb/>OXA−334 <lb/>OXA−256 <lb/>OXA−333 <lb/>OXA−253 <lb/>OXA−33 <lb/>OXA−20 <lb/>OXA−119 <lb/>OXA−5 <lb/>OXA−118 <lb/>OXA−9 <lb/>OXA−205 <lb/>OXA−2 <lb/>OXA−47 <lb/>OXA−368 <lb/>OXA−211 <lb/>OXA−129 <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>OXA beta−lactamase <lb/>23S rRNA wmcr. to macrolide <lb/>Multiple <lb/>tet36 <lb/>tetM <lb/>tetB(P) <lb/>tet32 <lb/>tet44 <lb/>tetO <lb/>tet(W/N/W) <lb/>tetQ <lb/>tetW <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>fexA <lb/>floR <lb/>Escherichia coli mdfA <lb/>tet(H) <lb/>tet(Y) <lb/>tet(G) <lb/>mdtM <lb/>tet(33) <lb/>emrY <lb/>tet(C) <lb/>mefA <lb/>emrA <lb/>emrR <lb/>mdtG <lb/>mdtN <lb/>mdtP <lb/>cmx <lb/>emrK <lb/>mdtH <lb/>tet(Z) <lb/>mef(B) <lb/>tet(A) <lb/>mdtO <lb/>emrB <lb/>tet(D) <lb/>tetR <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>tetA(P) <lb/>tet(L) <lb/>tet(40) <lb/>ErmA <lb/>ErmC <lb/>Erm(36) <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>ErmX <lb/>ErmQ <lb/>ErmT <lb/>ErmG <lb/>ErmB <lb/>ErmF <lb/>1 <lb/>31 <lb/>87 <lb/>121 <lb/>1437 <lb/>3167 <lb/>4952 <lb/>8294 <lb/>14568 <lb/>18228 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>14 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>19 <lb/>19 <lb/>19 <lb/>21 <lb/>23 <lb/>24 <lb/>26 <lb/>26 <lb/>30 <lb/>32 <lb/>32 <lb/>42 <lb/>54 <lb/>61 <lb/>70 <lb/>217 <lb/>240 <lb/>340 <lb/>14825 <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>10 <lb/>33 <lb/>71 <lb/>274 <lb/>1341 <lb/>2116 <lb/>tet−resistant ribo. protection protein <lb/>0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>15000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>Number of reads <lb/>major facilitator superfamily antibiotic efflux pump <lb/>Erm 23S ribosomal <lb/>RNA methyltransferase <lb/>M. tuberculosis 16S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. streptomycin <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>M. kansasii 23S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. clarithromycin <lb/>S. pneumoniae 23S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>M. catarrhalis 23S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>M. smegmatis 23S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. clarithromycin <lb/>S. ambofaciens 23S rRNA <lb/>wmcr. macrolide <lb/>E. coli 23S rRNA w.m.c.r. <lb/>erythromycin &amp; telithromycin <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>tetO <lb/>Multiple alleles <lb/>Effluent <lb/>Pig Caeca <lb/>Upstream Sediment <lb/>1 <lb/>21 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>9 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>16S rRNA wmcr. to <lb/>aminoglycoside <lb/>23S rRNA wmcr. to <lb/>macrolidee <lb/>tetracycline−resistant <lb/>ribosomal protection protein <lb/>Top 20 AMR Gene Families <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. The effect of normalization on the most common AMR gene allelic variants from each sample. Shown are the top 20 <lb/>AMR gene allelic variants from each sample (effluent, pig caeca and upstream sediment), and the effect of different normalisations (left: raw count, middle: <lb/>normalisation by gene length, right: further normalisation by Thermus thermophilus count). Arrows show the changing rank of each variant with normalisation. <lb/>Note that a different x-axis is used for upstream sediment in all three panels. Asterisks denote AMR allelic variants that do not have a &quot;protein homolog&quot; <lb/>detection model in CARD (see Methods: &apos;AMR gene profiling&apos;). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5. Taxonomic classification of metagenomes by method. Resulting taxonomic composition of effluent (E), pig caeca (P) and <lb/>upstream sediment (U) metagenomes using Kraken, Centrifuge and classification by in silico 16S rRNA extraction (16S). (a) Domain-level classification. (b) <lb/>Relative abundance of bacterial phyla (c) Relative abundance of Enterobacteriaceae. <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>RELATIVE ABUNDANCE <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>Kraken <lb/>Centrifuge <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>16S <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>a. Domain-level classification <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>Kraken <lb/>Centrifuge <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>16S <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>b. Bacterial phylum-level classification <lb/>Acidobacteria <lb/>Actinobacteria <lb/>Bacteroidetes <lb/>Proteobacteria <lb/>Firmicutes <lb/>OD1 <lb/>TM7 <lb/>Verrucomicrobia <lb/>Cyanobacteria <lb/>Chlorobi <lb/>Chloroflexi <lb/>Nitrospirae <lb/>Gemmatimonadetes <lb/>Spirochaetes <lb/>Planctomycetes <lb/>Tenericutes <lb/>Fusobacteria <lb/>Others <lb/>Unclassified <lb/>Archaea <lb/>Eukaryota <lb/>Viruses <lb/>Unclassified <lb/>Bacteria <lb/>N/A <lb/>U: <lb/>Upstream <lb/>Sediment <lb/>P: <lb/>Pig <lb/>Caecal <lb/>E: <lb/>Effluent <lb/>200,000,000 <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>Kraken <lb/>Centrifuge <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>16S <lb/>E <lb/>P <lb/>U <lb/>c. Enterobacteriaceae <lb/>Klebsiella <lb/>Enterobacter <lb/>Citrobacter <lb/>Escherichia <lb/>Raoultella <lb/>Salmonella <lb/>Cronobacter <lb/>Kosakonia <lb/>Pluralibacter <lb/>Lelliottia <lb/>Leclercia <lb/>Cedecea <lb/>Gibbsiella <lb/>Buttiauxella <lb/>Shimwellia <lb/>Trabulsiella <lb/>Yersinia <lb/>Serratia <lb/>Brenneria <lb/>Arsenophonus <lb/>Erwinia <lb/>Dickeya <lb/>Sodalis <lb/>Others <lb/>Read <lb/>Count <lb/>85,549,513 <lb/>(42.8 %) <lb/>35,127,523 <lb/>(17.6 %) <lb/>56,155,907 <lb/>(28.1 %) <lb/>320,609 <lb/>(0.16 %) <lb/>463,755 <lb/>(0.23 %) <lb/>84,249 <lb/>(0.04 %) <lb/>63,189,842 <lb/>(31.6 %) <lb/>16,551,690 <lb/>(8.3 %) <lb/>21,252,170 <lb/>(10.6 %) <lb/>4,574,833 <lb/>(2.287 %) <lb/>652,094 <lb/>(0.326 %) <lb/>565,970 <lb/>(0.283 %) <lb/>10,480 <lb/>(5.25e-3 %) <lb/>740 <lb/>(3.7e-4 %) <lb/>17 <lb/>(8.5e-06 %) <lb/>4,234,486 <lb/>(2.117 %) <lb/>377,675 <lb/>(0.190 %) <lb/>125,845 <lb/>(0.063 %) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6. Impact of sequencing depth on genus-level richness. Three methods are shown: (a) Kraken, (b) Centrifuge and (c) in <lb/>silico 16S rRNA extraction. <lb/>0 <lb/>250 <lb/>500 <lb/>750 <lb/>1000 <lb/>Richness <lb/>0 20 40 60 80 100 120 140 160 180 200 <lb/>0 20 40 60 80 100 120 140 160 180 200 <lb/>0 20 40 60 80 100 120 140 160 180 200 <lb/>Sequencing Depth (million reads) <lb/>Upstream <lb/>Sediment <lb/>Pig Caecal <lb/>Effluent <lb/>b. Centrifuge <lb/>a. Kraken <lb/>c. 16S <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. Metagenomic read coverage of assembled genetic structures from isolates cultured from each sample. (a) Effluent <lb/>isolates: E1-E4, (b) Pig caeca isolates: P1-P2, (c) Upstream sediment isolate: U1. Genetic structures are coloured by size. Note the different y-axis scale for <lb/>the upstream sediment sample. <lb/>P1-5 <lb/>P1-4 <lb/>P1-1 <lb/>P1-2 <lb/>P1-3 <lb/>P2-1 <lb/>P2-2 <lb/>U1-1 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Details of cultured isolates and assembled genomes. For more details on isolate sequencing, see Supplementary Table 4. <lb/>Sample Isolate <lb/>number <lb/>Species <lb/>(MALDI-ToF) <lb/>Genome size <lb/>(bp) <lb/>Number of contigs <lb/>(number circularized) <lb/>Effluent <lb/>1 <lb/>Citrobacter braakii <lb/>5,213,846 <lb/>4 (4) <lb/>2 <lb/>Enterobacter kobei <lb/>5,590,302 <lb/>9 (7) <lb/>3 <lb/>Enterobacter <lb/>cloacae <lb/>5,465,276 <lb/>7 (5) <lb/>4 <lb/>Enterobacter <lb/>cloacae <lb/>5,393,186 <lb/>8 (4) <lb/>Pig <lb/>caeca <lb/>1 <lb/>E. coli/S. <lb/>dysenteriae <lb/>4,898,477 <lb/>5 (5) <lb/>2 <lb/>E. coli/S. <lb/>dysenteriae <lb/>4,967,077 <lb/>2 (2) <lb/>Upstream <lb/>sediment <lb/>1 <lb/>Citrobacter gillenii <lb/>4,839,493 <lb/>1 (1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTARY LEGENDS <lb/>Supplementary Figure 1. Effect of sequencing depth on Bray-Curtis <lb/>dissimilarity to taxonomic composition of full sample. Results are shown <lb/>for (a) Kraken and (b) Centrifuge for all samples at both genus and species <lb/>level, comparing to the taxonomic composition at a depth of 200 million reads <lb/>per sample. <lb/>Supplementary Figure 2. Comparison of taxonomic classification output <lb/>to simulated ground truth for CAMI gut metagenome dataset. (a) <lb/>Taxonomic composition inferred using Kraken, Centrifuge, compared to <lb/>ground truth, for ten simulated samples. The top 20 most abundant genera <lb/>across all samples are shown in colour. (b) Relative species abundances <lb/>compared to ground truth values for Kraken (blue) and Centrifuge (red). Lines <lb/>show a linear best fit. <lb/>Supplementary Table 1. Metagenomic data. Each sample was sequenced <lb/>in replicate across four lanes (2x4=8 files per sample), combining to give the <lb/>~200 million reads per sample used in the study. The number of reads <lb/>mapping to T. thermophilus from each sample is also given. <lb/>Supplementary Table 2. Hybrid sequencing details for cultured isolates. <lb/>Statistics are shown for both short reads (Illumina) and long reads (PacBio) <lb/>sequenced from the same DNA extracts. <lb/>Supplementary Table 3. Details of mapping metagenomic reads to <lb/>isolate hybrid assemblies. Each sample is shown on a different sheet. <lb/>Supplementary Table 4. PERMANOVA results based on Bray-Curtis <lb/>dissimilarities for sample replicates. Analyses are shown in relation to <lb/>sample replicates and sequencing lanes for both (a) CARD AMR abundance <lb/>data, (b) Centrifuge taxonomic abundance data. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Jee Y, Carlson J, Rafai E, Musonda K, Huong TTG, Daza P, et al. <lb/>Antimicrobial resistance: a threat to global health. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018 <lb/>Sep 1;18(9):939-40. <lb/>2. O&apos;Neill J. Tackling drug-resistant infections globally: final report and <lb/>recommendations [Internet]. London: The Review on Antimicrobial <lb/>Resistance; <lb/>2016. <lb/>Available <lb/>from: <lb/>https://amr-<lb/>review.org/sites/default/files/160525_Final paper_with cover.pdf <lb/>3. Puyvelde SV, Deborggraeve S, Jacobs J. Why the antibiotic resistance <lb/>crisis requires a One Health approach. Lancet Infect Dis. 2018 Feb <lb/>1;18(2):132-4. <lb/>4. Bengtsson-Palme J, Hartmann M, Eriksson KM, Pal C, Thorell K, <lb/>Larsson DGJ, et al. METAXA2: improved identification and taxonomic <lb/>classification of small and large subunit rRNA in metagenomic data. Mol <lb/>Ecol Resour. 2015 Nov;15(6):1403-14. <lb/>5. Bengtsson-Palme J, Larsson DGJ, Kristiansson E. Using metagenomics <lb/>to investigate human and environmental resistomes. J Antimicrob <lb/>Chemother. 2017 01;72(10):2690-703. <lb/>6. Munk P, Andersen VD, de Knegt L, Jensen MS, Knudsen BE, <lb/>Lukjancenko O, et al. A sampling and metagenomic sequencing-based <lb/>methodology for monitoring antimicrobial resistance in swine herds. J <lb/>Antimicrob Chemother. 2017;72(2):385-92. <lb/>7. Jang J, Hur H-G, Sadowsky MJ, Byappanahalli MN, Yan T, Ishii S. <lb/>Environmental Escherichia coli: ecology and public health implications-a <lb/>review. J Appl Microbiol. 2017 Sep;123(3):570-81. <lb/>8. Touchon M, Hoede C, Tenaillon O, Barbe V, Baeriswyl S, Bidet P, et al. <lb/>Organised genome dynamics in the Escherichia coli species results in <lb/>highly diverse adaptive paths. PLoS Genet. 2009 Jan;5(1):e1000344. <lb/>9. Gupta SK, Padmanabhan BR, Diene SM, Lopez-Rojas R, Kempf M, <lb/>Landraud L, et al. ARG-ANNOT, a new bioinformatic tool to discover <lb/>antibiotic resistance genes in bacterial genomes. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother. 2014;58(1):212-20. <lb/>10. Jia B, Raphenya AR, Alcock B, Waglechner N, Guo P, Tsang KK, et al. <lb/>CARD 2017: expansion and model-centric curation of the comprehensive <lb/>antibiotic <lb/>resistance <lb/>database. <lb/>Nucleic <lb/>Acids <lb/>Res. <lb/>2017 <lb/>04;45(D1):D566-73. <lb/>11. Lautenbach E, Bilker WB, Tolomeo P, Maslow JN. Impact of diversity of <lb/>colonizing strains on strategies for sampling Escherichia coli from fecal <lb/>specimens. J Clin Microbiol. 2008 Sep;46(9):3094-6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>12. Stoesser N, Sheppard AE, Moore CE, Golubchik T, Parry CM, Nget P, et <lb/>al. Extensive Within-Host Diversity in Fecally Carried Extended-<lb/>Spectrum-Beta-Lactamase-Producing <lb/>Escherichia <lb/>coli <lb/>Isolates: <lb/>Implications for Transmission Analyses. J Clin Microbiol. 2015 <lb/>Jul;53(7):2122-31. <lb/>13. Zaheer R, Noyes N, Ortega Polo R, Cook SR, Marinier E, Van <lb/>Domselaar G, et al. Impact of sequencing depth on the characterization <lb/>of the microbiome and resistome. Sci Rep. 2018 Apr 12;8(1):5890. <lb/>14. Hillmann B, Al-Ghalith GA, Shields-Cutler RR, Zhu Q, Gohl DM, <lb/>Beckman KB, et al. Evaluating the Information Content of Shallow <lb/>Shotgun Metagenomics. mSystems. 2018 Oct 30;3(6):e00069-18. <lb/>15. Kim D, Song L, Breitwieser FP, Salzberg SL. Centrifuge: rapid and <lb/>sensitive classification of metagenomic sequences. Genome Res. <lb/>2016;26(12):1721-9. <lb/>16. Wood DE, Salzberg SL. Kraken: ultrafast metagenomic sequence <lb/>classification using exact alignments. Genome Biol. 2014 Jan;15(3):R46. <lb/>17. Pal C, Bengtsson-Palme J, Kristiansson E, Larsson DGJ. The structure <lb/>and diversity of human, animal and environmental resistomes. <lb/>Microbiome. 2016 Oct 7;4(1):54. <lb/>18. Noyes NR, Weinroth ME, Parker JK, Dean CJ, Lakin SM, Raymond RA, <lb/>et al. Enrichment allows identification of diverse, rare elements in <lb/>metagenomic resistome-virulome sequencing. Microbiome. 2017 Oct <lb/>17;5(1):142. <lb/>19. Li B, Yang Y, Ma L, Ju F, Guo F, Tiedje JM, et al. Metagenomic and <lb/>network analysis reveal wide distribution and co-occurrence of <lb/>environmental <lb/>antibiotic <lb/>resistance <lb/>genes. <lb/>ISME <lb/>J. <lb/>2015 <lb/>Nov;9(11):2490-2502. <lb/>20. Kaminski J, Gibson MK, Franzosa EA, Segata N, Dantas G, Huttenhower <lb/>C. High-Specificity Targeted Functional Profiling in Microbial <lb/>Communities <lb/>with <lb/>ShortBRED. <lb/>PLoS <lb/>Comput <lb/>Biol. <lb/>2015 <lb/>Dec;11(12):e1004557. <lb/>21. Sczyrba A, Hofmann P, Belmann P, Koslicki D, Janssen S, Dröge J, et al. <lb/>Critical Assessment of Metagenome Interpretation-a benchmark of <lb/>metagenomics software. Nat Methods. 2017 Nov;14(11):1063-71. <lb/>22. Seppey M, Manni M, Zdobnov EM. LEMMI: A Live Evaluation of <lb/>Computational Methods for Metagenome Investigation. bioRxiv. 2018 <lb/>Dec 28;507731. <lb/>23. Quince C, Walker AW, Simpson JT, Loman NJ, Segata N. Shotgun <lb/>metagenomics, from sampling to analysis. Nat Biotechnol. 2017 Sep <lb/>12;35(9):833-44. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>24. Knight R, Vrbanac A, Taylor BC, Aksenov A, Callewaert C, Debelius J, et <lb/>al. Best practices for analysing microbiomes. Nat Rev Microbiol. 2018 <lb/>Jul;16(7):410-22. <lb/>25. Hendriksen RS, Munk P, Njage P, Bunnik B van, McNally L, Lukjancenko <lb/>O, et al. Global monitoring of antimicrobial resistance based on <lb/>metagenomics analyses of urban sewage. Nat Commun. 2019 Mar <lb/>8;10(1):1124. <lb/>26. Nordahl Petersen T, Rasmussen S, Hasman H, Carøe C, Baelum J, <lb/>Charlotte Schultz A, et al. Meta-genomic analysis of toilet waste from <lb/>long distance flights; a step towards global surveillance of infectious <lb/>diseases and antimicrobial resistance. Sci Rep. 2015 Jul 10;5:11444. <lb/>27. Afshinnekoo E, Meydan C, Chowdhury S, Jaroudi D, Boyer C, Bernstein <lb/>N, et al. Geospatial Resolution of Human and Bacterial Diversity with <lb/>City-Scale Metagenomics. Cell Syst. 2015 Jul 29;1(1):72-87. <lb/>28. AbuOun M, Stubberfield EJ, Duggett NA, Kirchner M, Dormer L, Nunez-<lb/>Garcia J, et al. mcr-1 and mcr-2 (mcr-6.1) variant genes identified in <lb/>Moraxella species isolated from pigs in Great Britain from 2014 to 2015. <lb/>J Antimicrob Chemother. 2017 Oct 1;72(10):2745-9. <lb/>29. Public Health England. English Surveillance Programme for Antimicrobial <lb/>Utilisation and Resistance (ESPAUR) [Internet]. Public Health England; <lb/>2017 <lb/>[cited <lb/>2019 <lb/>Nov <lb/>3]. <lb/>Available <lb/>from: <lb/>https://www.gov.uk/government/publications/english-surveillance-<lb/>programme-antimicrobial-utilisation-and-resistance-espaur-report <lb/>30. Logan LK, Braykov NP, Weinstein RA, Laxminarayan R. Extended-<lb/>Spectrum β-Lactamase-Producing and Third-Generation Cephalosporin-<lb/>Resistant Enterobacteriaceae in Children: Trends in the United States, <lb/>1999-2011. J Pediatr Infect Dis Soc. 2014 Dec 1;3(4):320-8. <lb/>31. Sheppard AE, Stoesser N, Wilson DJ, Sebra R, Kasarskis A, Anson LW, <lb/>et al. Nested Russian doll-like genetic mobility drives rapid dissemination <lb/>of the carbapenem resistance gene blaKPC. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother. 2016 Jun;60(6):3767-3778. <lb/>32. Seemann <lb/>T. <lb/>mlst <lb/>[Internet]. <lb/>Available <lb/>from: <lb/>https://github.com/tseemann/mlst <lb/>33. Satinsky BM, Gifford SM, Crump BC, Moran MA. Use of internal <lb/>standards for quantitative metatranscriptome and metagenome analysis. <lb/>Methods Enzymol. 2013;531:237-50. <lb/>34. Rognes T, Flouri T, Nichols B, Quince C, Mahé F. VSEARCH: a versatile <lb/>open source tool for metagenomics. PeerJ. 2016 Oct;4:e2584. <lb/>35. Babraham <lb/>Bioinformatics. <lb/>TrimGalore <lb/>[Internet]. <lb/>Babraham <lb/>Bioinformatics; <lb/>2017. <lb/>Available <lb/>from: <lb/>https://www.bioinformatics.babraham.ac.uk/projects/trim_galore/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Gweon et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>36. O&apos;Leary NA, Wright MW, Brister JR, Ciufo S, Haddad D, McVeigh R, et al. <lb/>Reference sequence (RefSeq) database at NCBI: current status, <lb/>taxonomic expansion, and functional annotation. Nucleic Acids Res. <lb/>2016 Jan 4;44(D1):D733-745. <lb/>37. Wang Q, Garrity GM, Tiedje JM, Cole JR. Naive Bayesian classifier for <lb/>rapid assignment of rRNA sequences into the new bacterial taxonomy. <lb/>Appl Environ Microbiol. 2007 Aug;73(16):5261-7. <lb/>38. DeSantis TZ, Hugenholtz P, Larsen N, Rojas M, Brodie EL, Keller K, et al. <lb/>Greengenes, a chimera-checked 16S rRNA gene database and <lb/>workbench compatible with ARB. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2006 <lb/>Jul;72(7):5069-72. <lb/>39. Bushnell B. BBMap: A Fast, Accurate, Splice-Aware Aligner [Internet]. <lb/>Lawrence Berkeley National Lab. (LBNL), Berkeley, CA (United States); <lb/>2014 Mar [cited 2019 Mar 8]. Report No.: LBNL-7065E. Available from: <lb/>https://www.osti.gov/biblio/1241166 <lb/>40. Clench HK. How to make regional lists of butterflies: some thoughts. J <lb/>Lepidopterists Soc. 1979;33:216-31. <lb/>41. Di Tommaso P, Chatzou M, Floden EW, Barja PP, Palumbo E, <lb/>Notredame C. Nextflow enables reproducible computational workflows. <lb/>Nat Biotechnol. 2017 11;35(4):316-9. <lb/>42. Oksanen J. vegan: community ecology package [Internet]. 2016. <lb/>Available from: https://cran.r-project.org/package=vegan <lb/>43. R Core Team. R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing <lb/>[Internet]. Vienna, Austria: R Foundation for Statistical Computing; 2017. <lb/>Available from: https://www.R-project.org/ <lb/>44. Wickham H. ggplot2: Elegant Graphics for Data Analysis [Internet]. <lb/>Springer-Verlag New York; 2016. Available from: http://ggplot2.org <lb/>45. Jolley KA, Bray JE, Maiden MCJ. Open-access bacterial population <lb/>genomics: BIGSdb software, the PubMLST.org website and their <lb/>applications. Wellcome Open Res. 2018;3:124. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
