<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> Patterns of genetic variability in genomic regions with low rates of <lb/>recombination <lb/>Hannes Becher 1 , Benjamin C. Jackson and Brian Charlesworth <lb/>Institute of Evolutionary Biology, School of Biological Sciences, University of Edinburgh, <lb/>Charlotte Auerbach Road, Edinburgh EH9 3FL <lb/>1 Lead contact <lb/>Correspondence: hbecher@ed.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>SUMMARY <lb/>Surveys of DNA sequence variation have shown that the level of genetic variability in a <lb/>genomic region is often strongly positively correlated with its rate of crossing over (CO) [1-<lb/>3]. This pattern is caused by selection acting on linked sites, which reduces genetic variability <lb/>and can also cause the frequency distribution of segregating variants to contain more rare <lb/>variants than expected without selection (skew). These effects of selection may involve the <lb/>spread of beneficial mutations (selective sweeps, SSWs), the elimination of deleterious <lb/>mutations (background selection, BGS) or both together, and are expected to be stronger with <lb/>lower rates of crossing over [1-3]. However, in a recent study of human populations, the <lb/>skew was reduced in the lowest CO regions compared with regions with somewhat higher <lb/>CO rates [4]. A similar pattern is seen in the population genomic studies of Drosophila <lb/>simulans described here. We propose an explanation for this paradoxical observation, and <lb/>validate it using computer simulations. This explanation is based on the finding that partially <lb/>recessive, linked deleterious mutations can increase rather than reduce neutral variability <lb/>when the product of the effective population size (Ne) and the selection coefficient against <lb/>homozygous carriers of mutations (s) is ≤ 1, i.e. there is associative overdominance (AOD) <lb/>rather than BGS [5]. We show that AOD can operate in a genomic region with a low rate of <lb/>CO, opening up a new perspective on how selection affects patterns of variability at linked <lb/>sites. <lb/></front>

			<body>Results and Discussion <lb/>Diversity Statistics in Relation to CO Rates in Drosophila simulans <lb/>The top two panels of Figure 1 show the relations between the rate of crossing over and mean <lb/>pairwise diversity at four-fold degenerate nucleotide sites (p4), for two populations of <lb/>Drosophila simulans. Consistent with previous studies of many species [1-3, 6], there is a <lb/>significant positive relation between CO rate and nucleotide site diversity for both X <lb/>chromosome (X) and autosomes (A). As reported previously [7], X has much lower diversity <lb/>than A for all bins of CO rates. Diversity is higher for the Madagascan than the Kenyan <lb/>population, consistent with the latter having been founded as a relatively small population by <lb/>flies descended from the putatively ancestral Madagascan population [7]. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>The bottom panels of Figure 1 show the relations between CO rate and a measure of <lb/>the skew of the site frequency spectrum (SFS) towards rare variants, Dqw4 = 1 -p4 / qw4 , <lb/>where p4 and qw4 are the estimates of diversity based on the mean pairwise difference <lb/>between alleles [8] and the number of segregating sites [9], respectively. Other measures of <lb/>skew behave similarly (Supplemental Figure S1). As was also found in a Rwandan <lb/>population of D. melanogaster [10], there is much greater skew on X than A, although the <lb/>absolute level of skew for both X and A is much higher than in D. melanogaster, suggesting a <lb/>more intense recent population expansion in D. simulans. The skew is also larger in the <lb/>Madagascan than the Kenyan population, consistent with the latter having experienced a <lb/>bottleneck in population size or a slower rate of population expansion. The parameters of the <lb/>population expansion for the Madagascan population were estimated by [11]. <lb/>The most surprising feature of these results is that there is a nearly monotonic <lb/>increase of Dqw4 with CO rate in the autosomal CO regions. The overall autosomal values of <lb/>Dqw4 for non-CO regions are 0.22 and 0.13 for Madagascar and Kenya, respectively. A meta-<lb/>analysis of 10 independent autosomal non-CO regions from six Drosophila species <lb/>(Supplemental Table S1) gave a mean of 0.18, with s.e. 0.04. The pattern is more complex <lb/>for the X in D. simulans -there is a significant quadratic relation between Dqw4 and CO rate, <lb/>with an initial increase followed by a decrease at the highest CO rates. The non-CO regions <lb/>of the X show values of Dqw4 comparable to the CO regions, with the exception of the <lb/>telomere in the Madagascan population, which has a value of 0.44, possibly reflecting a <lb/>recent selective sweep, consistent with its very low p4 value. <lb/>If the skew in the SFS were in part caused by selective sweeps (SSWs), it would be <lb/>expected to decrease, not increase, with CO rate, as was found in computer simulations with <lb/>parameter values that are realistic for Drosophila [12]. If background selection (BGS) also <lb/>contributes, these simulation results showed that it should only produce a strong effect on <lb/>skew in the non-CO regions, and cause these to have higher skews than regions with CO. <lb/>Indeed, the simulations predicted higher skews in the non-CO regions than the observed <lb/>autosomal means presented above: Dqw4 was 0.24 for autosomal simulations with BGS and <lb/>SSWs, and 0.21 with BGS alone. Given that demographic effects probably contribute <lb/>substantially to the skew in the SFS in D. simulans, especially in Madagascar [11], an even <lb/>higher proportion of singletons in the non-CO regions is expected. <lb/>We will address elsewhere the question of relations between the level of skew of the <lb/>SFS towards low frequency variants and the CO rate outside the non-CO regions, and simply <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>note that it probably reflects the joint effects of SSWs and population size changes, which <lb/>vary among genomic regions with different effective population sizes (Ne) associated with <lb/>different CO rates, so that low Ne can reduce the effect on skew of a recent population <lb/>expansion [10]. We focus here on the fact that the level of skew in the non-CO regions is <lb/>smaller than expected with BGS and/or SSWs. <lb/>Simulation Results and an Explanation for Low Skew <lb/>The simulations in [12] assumed a dominance coefficient (h) of 0.5 for deleterious mutations, <lb/>where the fitness of the heterozygous carriers of a deleterious mutation is reduced by hs <lb/>relative to wild-type, with homozygotes suffering a reduction of s. However, studies of the <lb/>effects of deleterious mutations on fitness components [13-15] suggest that there is likely to <lb/>be partial recessivity of most slightly deleterious mutations, with 0 &lt; h &lt; 0.5. Because <lb/>selection against rare deleterious mutations in randomly mating populations acts mainly on <lb/>their heterozygous carriers [16], the value of h does not greatly affect the fate of rare <lb/>deleterious mutations with similar values of hs, so that h = 0.5 was used previously for <lb/>convenience. <lb/>Empirical estimates of the parameters of the distribution of deleterious mutational <lb/>effects on fitness (DFE) in Drosophila suggest that it has a large standard deviation relative <lb/>to its mean [17-20]. Under a gamma distribution, the shape parameter for both <lb/>nonsynonymous (NS) and UTR mutations has been estimated to be approximately 0.3 [20]. <lb/>Such a wide distribution implies that there is a substantial proportion of selection coefficients <lb/>against mutant homozygotes (s) that have Ne s of the order of 1. For example, with h = 0.2, a <lb/>shape parameter of 0.3 and 2Ne s = 5000 (the value for NS sites in our simulations), the <lb/>proportion of mutations with 2Ne s ≤ 2.5 is 0.08. <lb/>This raises the possibility that a subset of partially recessive deleterious mutations <lb/>could cause associative overdominance (AOD), whereby loss of variability at neutral sites is <lb/>retarded by linkage disequilibrium (LD) between selected and linked neutral sites [21]. Such <lb/>LD causes a correlation in homozygosity between sites, so that homozygotes for variants at <lb/>the neutral sites are associated with reduced fitness compared to heterozygotes when <lb/>deleterious mutations have some degree of recessivity [5]. Recent theoretical work has <lb/>shown that partially recessive deleterious mutations can result in AOD when 2Nes is of the <lb/>order of 2.5 [5], given sufficiently close linkage between neutral and selected sites, which is <lb/>prevalent in low recombination genomic regions. By definition, AOD acts similarly to true <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>overdominance, a form of balancing selection. Long-term balancing selection is known to <lb/>increase the lengths of the internal branches of coalescent trees relative to the total tree size <lb/>[22-25]; AOD should have a similar effect, causing the SFS to become biased towards more <lb/>frequent variants than with strict neutrality. BGS without AOD has the opposite effect, <lb/>especially in low CO regions where selective interference among deleterious mutations <lb/>increases the skew towards rare variants [12, 26-30]. <lb/>If the more abundant strongly selected mutations cause standard BGS effects in a low <lb/>recombination region, but some weakly selected mutations cause AOD, the net outcome for a <lb/>low CO region should be lower diversity and a site frequency spectrum (SFS) more skewed <lb/>towards low frequency variants than with no selection, but with higher diversity and less <lb/>skew than with standard BGS. This process could account for the relatively low skew <lb/>towards low frequency variants in the non-CO regions of humans [4] and six Drosophila <lb/>species (Supplemental Table S1). <lb/>We have investigated this possibility by simulations using a range of different <lb/>dominance coefficients (see STAR Methods for details). Figure 2A shows results with h = <lb/>0.2 and h = 0.5, for a range of CO rates that are all ≤ the mean rate of 2 x 10 -8 for female <lb/>meiosis in D. melanogaster [31, 32]. With deleterious mutations alone, advantageous <lb/>mutations alone, and with both deleterious and advantageous mutations, the mean value of <lb/>neutral diversity increases as the CO rate increases, whereas the degree of skew towards low <lb/>frequency variants decreases. In the presence of deleterious mutations, the degree of skew in <lb/>very low CO rate regions is substantially lower with h = 0.2 than h = 0.5, both in the presence <lb/>(0.16, 0.24) and absence of advantageous mutations (0.10, 0.21), and is not far from the <lb/>observed mean autosomal value across Drosophila species of 0.18. In addition, neutral <lb/>diversity with deleterious mutations is higher for h = 0.2 (0.0041) than h = 0.5 (0.0024) in <lb/>non-CO regions. Figure 2B shows the behaviour of a non-CO region with a range of <lb/>dominance coefficients, showing that low h greatly reduces the skew caused by BGS, and <lb/>increases diversity. As was found previously [12], BGS is the main cause of reduced <lb/>variability in the non-CO cases, reflecting the fact that the rate of sweeps is greatly reduced <lb/>by BGS when CO is absent. These findings are consistent with the hypothesis that AOD <lb/>(caused by the relatively small fraction of mutations that are weakly selected) reduces the <lb/>effect of BGS when mutations are partially recessive. <lb/>Linkage Disequilibrium Patterns and a Further Test for AOD <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>This hypothesis can be further tested by noting that that AOD increases the relative lengths of <lb/>internal branches of the coalescent tree for a neutral site (see above). By analogy with the <lb/>effects on LD of a recent population size change, this change in tree topology increases the <lb/>magnitude of LD [33, 34]. Conversely, BGS with low CO rates has the opposite effect, since <lb/>it increases the relative lengths of the external branches of coalescent trees, as noted above. <lb/>We can use the simulated values of neutral diversity to estimate the corresponding value of <lb/>Ne from the formula p = 4Neu, where u is the mutation rate per site) [35]. This can be used to <lb/>determine the approximate expected value of r 2 , the squared correlation coefficient between <lb/>the allelic states of pairs of neutral sites from equation (3) in [36]. As can be seen in Figure 3 <lb/>(top left), the simulation values of median r 2 for all pairs of neutral sites with deleterious <lb/>mutations and without CO (but with gene conversion) are more than an order of magnitude <lb/>lower than the neutral expectations, which are 0.200 with h = 0.2 and 0.209 with h = 0.5, <lb/>indicating a strong influence of BGS. Nonetheless, the magnitude of LD with h = 0.2 is much <lb/>greater than with h = 0.5 despite a higher level of diversity and hence Ne (note that low Ne is <lb/>expected to increase r 2 ). <lb/>The bottom panels of Figure 3 show plots of median r 2 for 4-fold sites against <lb/>physical location for 50 bins of distances between pairs of variants across genes on the non-<lb/>CO chromosome four in the Madagascan and Kenyan populations. As is expected from <lb/>bottleneck effects or a lower rate of population expansion, LD is markedly higher in Kenya <lb/>than Madagascar, but the overall levels of LD are of similar magnitude to the simulation <lb/>results, and are much lower than predicted from the estimates of Ne using p4 and the D. <lb/>melanogaster mutation rate [37]. There is an indication that there is a low level of crossing <lb/>over on this chromosome, from the significant negative relation between r 2 and distance <lb/>between pairs of sites, which is not observed in simulations with gene conversion alone. <lb/>It is, of course, possible that true balancing selection, rather than AOD, could <lb/>contribute to these patterns. Supplemental Figure S2 shows plots of 4-fold and 0-fold <lb/>diversities per gene along chromosome four, for the Madagascan and Kenya populations. <lb/>There is one gene, FBgn0268752, which stands out as having unusually high diversities at <lb/>both types of site in both populations. In the case of Madagascar, there are two intermediate-<lb/>frequency nonsynonymous variants (at positions 40149 and 40648) (Supplemental Table S2), <lb/>whereas Kenya is segregating for nonsynonymous variants only at 40648, possibly because <lb/>of loss of variability after a bottleneck. The polymorphisms at sites 40149 and 40648 in <lb/>Madagascar are not in LD with each other, whereas there are strong associations between one <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the variants at 40149 and synonymous variants to its left (Supplemental Table S2). It is, <lb/>therefore, possible that there is balancing selection acting at this locus, which appears to be <lb/>unique to D. simulans. However, there is no evidence that the LD created by the 40149 <lb/>variant extends outside this locus, so that it does not contribute to the general patterns <lb/>described above. <lb/>Previous theoretical work on AOD due to deleterious, partially recessive mutations <lb/>suggested that it is likely only to occur in small populations, where there is indeed evidence <lb/>that the rate of loss of variability for molecular markers is slower than expected from the <lb/>neutral value of Ne [5]. This is because AOD requires Nes to be of the order of 1, which is <lb/>likely to be met by only a small minority of deleterious mutations in a large, randomly mating <lb/>population. However, when Ne for neutral sites is greatly reduced by selection at linked sites, <lb/>the extent of randomly generated LD between neutral and selected sites will be considerably <lb/>enhanced, and LD is the driving force for AOD [5]. <lb/>The simulation results shown in Figures 2 and 3 suggest that, with partially recessive <lb/>mutations and the wide distribution of s values suggested by population genomic analyses of <lb/>the effects of deleterious mutations, there is a noticeable effect of AOD on the SFS and extent <lb/>of LD at neutral sites when CO rates are very low. This interpretation can be tested by <lb/>comparing the results of simulations with a narrow versus wide range of selection <lb/>coefficients for deleterious mutations, keeping the mean constant (Figure 4). In this case, <lb/>diversity, skew and the magnitude of LD are independent of h; with the wide range of <lb/>selection coefficients, diversity and LD decrease with h, but skew increases. This is what is <lb/>expected if AOD is influencing the behaviour of neutral variants in low CO regions. <lb/>The properties of genomes or genomic regions with low rates of genetic <lb/>recombination are of considerable interest for a range of biological questions, including <lb/>evolution and variation in bacteria [38, 39], asexual higher organisms [40, 41], organisms <lb/>with high rates of self-fertilisation [42, 43], and Y and W chromosomes [44-47]. There is a <lb/>general expectation that genetic diversity and molecular signatures of adaptive evolution <lb/>should be greatly reduced in such systems, as a result of selection at linked sites. This <lb/>reduction in adaptation is important for understanding phenomena such as the degeneration <lb/>of Y chromosomes and the lack of evolutionary success of asexual and highly selfing species. <lb/>However, comparisons between different species with different modes of <lb/>reproduction that influence the recombination rate are often made difficult by confounding <lb/>factors, such as differences in the extent of colonisation events involving population size <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>bottlenecks [42, 43]. The use of comparisons among genomic regions with different <lb/>recombination rates largely removes this difficulty, and has revealed many of the expected <lb/>results [2, 3, 6]. Here, we have shown that an unexpected pattern emerging from such <lb/>comparisons suggests that the largely neglected process of associative overdominance may <lb/>influence patterns of variability when recombination rates are very low. Because it requires <lb/>partial recessivity of the fitness effects of deleterious mutations, and the opportunity for them <lb/>to be present in both heterozygous and homozygous states, it will only operate in diploid or <lb/>polyploid organisms with some degree of outbreeding. It will, therefore, not affect haploid, <lb/>asexual or highly selfing organisms, or effectively haploid chromosomes such as Y and W. <lb/>This suggests that we might expect to see differences in their patterns of variability compared <lb/>with the non-CO regions of outbreeding diploid species. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>BC designed the project and contributed to the analyses of the data and simulations; HB <lb/>conducted the simulations and contributed to the analyses of the population data and <lb/>simulations; BCJ conducted the bioinformatic analyses of the raw sequencing data. All three <lb/>authors contributed to the writing of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We wish to thank Ching-Ho Chang and Amanda Larracuente for providing the sequence <lb/>diversity data for the dot chromosome in D. pseudoobscura and D. miranda. We made use of <lb/>the resources provided by the Edinburgh Compute and Data Facility (ECDF) <lb/>(http://www.ecdf.ed.ac.uk/). This research was funded by a Leverhulme Trust grant (IRPG-<lb/>2015-033) to BC. <lb/></div>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figures and legends <lb/>Figure 1. Genetic Diversity Statistics at Four-fold Degenerate Sites in Two Populations <lb/>of Drosophila simulans in Relation to the Rate of Crossing Over. All panels share the <lb/>same X axis, the mean proportion of the standard crossover (CO) rate per megabase in <lb/>homologous regions of Drosophila melanogaster for each group of genes. Estimates of the <lb/>pairwise nucleotide diversity (π4) for each group are shown in the top panels, and estimates <lb/>of a measure of the skew of the site-frequency spectrum (Δθw4) in the bottom panels. These <lb/>statistics were computed for each gene and then binned by CO rate, after weighting by the <lb/>number of four-fold sites per gene in each bin. Autosomal bins are shown in orange and X <lb/>chromosomal bins in blue. The solid lines indicate significant regression fits for the X <lb/>chromosomal values, with the following significance levels for the quadratic terms -<lb/>Madagascar π4: p = 0.00960; Madagascar Δθw4: p = 0.0083; Kenya π4: p = 0.00598; Kenya <lb/>Δθw4: p = 0.00262. The dashed lines indicate linear regression fits for the autosomal bins. <lb/>The significance levels from Spearman rank correlations were as follows -Madagascar π4: r <lb/>= 0.939, p &lt; 2.2 × 10 -16 ; Madagascar Δθw4: r = 0.891, p = 0.00138; Kenya π4: r = 0.927, p = <lb/>0.000130; Kenya Δθw4: r = 0.685, p = 0.0351). Non-CO regions are shown as black dots. <lb/>These are spread out for better visibility and are labelled with their identities; Xc is the <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>0.000 0.010 0.020 0.030 <lb/>0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>Proportion of the standard CO rate <lb/>Kenya <lb/>Madagascar <lb/>π <lb/>4 <lb/>Δθ <lb/>w4 <lb/>0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>X-chromosome <lb/>Autosomes <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>centromeric region of the X and Xt is its telomeric region; 2 and 3 are centromeric regions of <lb/>chromosomes 2 and 3, respectively; 4 is the dot chromosome. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Expectations for the Patterns of Genetic Diversity Statistics from Forwards-<lb/>in-Time Simulations. <lb/>(A) The pairwise diversities at simulated autosomal synonymous sites (π, top row) <lb/>and a measure of the distortion of the site-frequency spectrum (Δθw, bottom row) for <lb/>different rates of crossing over, expressed as a proportion of the mean sex-averaged <lb/>rate for autosomes in D. melanogaster. Gene conversion was allowed with the <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>Proportion of the standard CO rate <lb/>No dominance (h=0.5) Partial recessivity (h=0.2) <lb/>π <lb/>Δθ <lb/>w <lb/>0.00 0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.00 0.25 0.50 0.75 1.00 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>Selection regime <lb/>deleterious <lb/>Neutral <lb/>advantageous <lb/>adv + del <lb/>Dominance coe cient (h) <lb/>π <lb/>Δθ <lb/>w <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>A range of dominance coe cients, no CO <lb/>Selection regime <lb/>deleterious <lb/>Neutral <lb/>advantageous <lb/>adv + del <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>standard parameter values for D. melanogaster, regardless of the CO rate. The <lb/>theoretical expectations with no selection are given by the horizontal green lines. <lb/>Simulations with selection against deleterious mutations alone are indicated as <lb/>&apos;deleterious&apos;, simulations with advantageous mutations alone as &apos;advantageous&apos;, and <lb/>those with both kinds of selection as &apos;adv + del&apos;. The results in the left-hand panels <lb/>are for simulation runs with semi-dominant mutations (h = 0.5), and those in the <lb/>right-hand panels are with partial recessivity (h = 0.2). Each data point shows the <lb/>mean and 95% confidence intervals for 20 replicate simulations, for a group of 70 <lb/>genes subject to selection (see STAR Methods for details of the parameters used in <lb/>the simulations). <lb/>(B) Simulated values of π and Δθw for a range of different dominance coefficients (h) <lb/>without crossing over but with gene conversion occurring at the standard rate for D. <lb/>melanogaster <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Linkage Disequilibrium (LD) as Measured by the Median of r 2 Between Pairs of <lb/>Sites The top panels show simulation results for a diploid population size of N = 2500 with BGS <lb/>and sweeps, with either no CO or CO at 1% of the standard rate. Red circles indicate runs <lb/>without dominance (h = 0.5) and blue triangles indicate runs with partial recessivity (h = 0.2). <lb/>Mantel tests carried out on individual simulation runs are only significant in the presence of CO. <lb/>The bottom panels show the average values of the LD measure across bins of pairwise distances, <lb/>between four-fold degenerate variant sites on chromosome four for the Madagascan and Kenyan <lb/>populations. Mantel tests carried out on the (un-binned) data show that there is a significant <lb/>decay of LD with increasing distance (Madagascar four-fold: 222 sites, Mantel statistic R = <lb/>0.061, p = 0.001; Madagascar zero-fold: 320 sites, R = 0.040, p = 0.001; Kenya four-fold: 187 <lb/>sites, R = 0.026, p = 0.015; Kenya zero-fold: 267 sites, R= 0.027, p = 0.002). <lb/>Pairwise distance in kbp <lb/>(bins of 10kbp) <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>Median r 2 <lb/>per bin <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>h = <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>h = <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>Median r 2 <lb/>per bin <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>Pairwise distance in kbp <lb/>(bins of 10kbp) <lb/>Simulated, no CO <lb/>Simulated, 1% CO <lb/>Madagascar <lb/>Kenya <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4. Weakly Deleterious Mutations are Required for AOD Effects on Variability. <lb/>The panels show the results of simulations with deleterious mutations alone, in the absence of <lb/>CO and a range of dominance coefficients, with the mean strength of selection being kept <lb/>constant. Red and blue indicate two different distributions of deleterious fitness effects with <lb/>the same mean but different shape parameters (b). The results with b = 0.3 (a wide <lb/>distribution of selection coefficients), are the same as those shown previously, and are <lb/>contrasted with the results for a narrow distribution (b = 10), where AOD is unlikely to <lb/>occur. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>Δθ <lb/>Skew <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>0.0075 <lb/>0.0100 <lb/>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>π <lb/>Nucleotide Diversity <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.1 0.2 0.3 0.4 0.5 <lb/>Median pair-wise r 2 <lb/>Linkage Disequilibrium <lb/>Dominance coe cient (h) <lb/>Deleterious DFE <lb/>standard (β = 0.3) <lb/>narrow (β = 10) <lb/>Dominance coe cient (h) <lb/>Dominance coe cient (h) <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental Information for Becher, Jackson &amp; Charlesworth <lb/>Supplemental Figure S1. Related to figure 1. Additional statistics for the skew of the site-<lb/>frequency spectrum and Watterson&apos;s theta, an estimate of sequence diversity. <lb/>Proportion of the standard CO rate <lb/>Watterson&apos;s theta ( <lb/>w ) <lb/>Madagascar <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>Kenya <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>X chromoso <lb/>Autosomes <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 2.5 3.0 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>Xc <lb/>Xt <lb/>Tajima&apos;s D <lb/>Proportion of singeltons <lb/>X chromosome <lb/>Autosomes <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental figure S2. Related to section: Linkage Disequilibrium Patterns and a Further <lb/>Test for AOD <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Madagascar <lb/>Position in assembly (in kbp) <lb/>Per gene nucleotide diversity <lb/>Kenya <lb/>Nucleotide diversity on the 4 th chromosome <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>200 <lb/>600 800 1000 0 <lb/>400 <lb/>200 <lb/>600 800 1000 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>4fold sites <lb/>0fold sites <lb/></div>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental Table S1. Related to Figure 1, Figure 2, and to the first section of the Results <lb/>and Discussion. Metaanalysis of delta theta in non-crossover regions of other Drosophila <lb/>species. <lb/>Supplemental Table S2. Haplotypes around the high-diversity region on the Drosophila <lb/>simulans 4th chromosome. Related to section &quot;Linkage Disequilibrium Patterns and a Further <lb/>Test for AOD&quot; <lb/>Supplemental Table S3. Binned population genetic statistics from two populations of <lb/>Drosophila simulans. Related to figures 1 and S1 <lb/>Supplemental Table S4. Results of forwards-in-time simulations with parameters relevant to <lb/>Drosophila populations. Related to figure 2. <lb/></div>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">STAR Methods <lb/>LEAD CONTACT AND MATERIALS AVAILABILITY <lb/>Hannes Becher <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS <lb/>The results described in here are based on whole genome sequences of isofemale lines of D. <lb/>simulans, established from fertilized females collected in Kenya and Madagascar by William <lb/>Ballard. These were maintained in the laboratory of Peter Andolfatto for several generations, <lb/>and subsequently inbred by brother-sister mating in the Charlesworth laboratory. The details <lb/>of the breeding procedures and sequencing methods are described in [7]. <lb/>METHOD DETAILS <lb/>Sampling and sequencing <lb/>We downloaded raw read data in fastq format for 21 isofemale Madagascan genomes and 18 <lb/>Kenyan genomes from the European Nucleotide Archive (study accession numbers: <lb/>PRJEB7673; PRJNA215932), as in [7]. We mapped the reads to version 2.02 of the D. <lb/>simulans genome (FlyBase release 2017_04) [48] using BWA MEM [49], then sorted, <lb/>merged and marked duplicates on the resulting BAM files using Picard Tools version 2.8.3 <lb/>(https://broadinstitute.github.io/picard/). We called variants separately for each individual <lb/>line using the HaplotypeCaller tool from GATK version 3.7 [50] with the options -<lb/>emitRefConfidence, BP_RESOLUTION and -max-alternate-alleles 2, then made per-<lb/>chromosome VCF files for the whole population using the GATK v3.7 tools combineGVCFs <lb/>and genotypeGVCFs. All the scripts necessary for downloading the fastq files and calling <lb/>variants are available at https://github.com/benja-<lb/>mincjackson/dsim_variant_pipeline_ref_v2.02.git. We defined sites as 4-fold degenerate in <lb/>all transcripts using information from the gff format annotation of the D. simulans genome <lb/>v2.02 (available from ftp://ftp. <lb/>flybase.net/genomes/Drosophila_simulans/dsim_r2.02_FB2017_04/ gff/dsim-all-<lb/>r2.02.gff.gz). <lb/>Data analyses <lb/>In the absence of a high-density genetic map for D. simulans, we used the mapping data of <lb/>[31] for D. melanogaster. As described in [10], the D. melanogaster crossing over (CO) rates <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">were smoothed by Loess regressions against the physical positions of markers in the genome. <lb/>Each D. simulans gene was assigned the CO rate per megabase in female meiosis of the <lb/>corresponding position in D. melanogaster, using an alignment of the genome sequences of <lb/>D. simulans (v2.02) and D. melanogaster (v5.57) [48]. Following [10], the absence of <lb/>recombinational exchange between homologous chromosomes in Drosophila males was <lb/>taken into account by multiplying the autosomal CO rates by one-half, and the X linked rates <lb/>by two-thirds. All CO rates presented below have been corrected in this way. <lb/>For genomic regions with non-zero CO rates, genes were grouped into ten equally-<lb/>sized bins. For the autosomes (A), there were approximately 730 genes per bin, and <lb/>approximately 180 genes per bin for the X chromosome (X). All D. simulans genes that were <lb/>aligned to D. melanogaster scaffold heterochromatin, or to regions defined as lacking CO in <lb/>[10], were excluded before binning. These non-CO genes were then binned by chromosome <lb/>(2: 86, 3: 54, X (tip): 23, X (centromere): 33), and were used for the analyses of the non-CO <lb/>regions described below. <lb/>Chromosome arm 3R, which contains a large inversion relative to D. melanogaster <lb/>[51], was excluded from our analyses. The genetic maps of the X chromosome appear to be <lb/>similar in the two species [52] so that we used the D. melanogaster CO rate estimates as a <lb/>proxy for those in D. simulans. For the analyses of chromosome 2 and 3L, the binning <lb/>procedure assumes the rank order of the CO rate of a gene to be related to its physical <lb/>position in the same way as in D. melanogaster, even though the absolute CO rates per <lb/>megabase differ between the species: D. simulans has higher CO rates, especially in the low <lb/>CO rate regions near the centromere and telomere [52]. Non-parametric rank correlations <lb/>were therefore used to assess statistical relationships between the summary statistics for the <lb/>autosomal polymorphism data and CO rates. <lb/>Levels of polymorphisms per gene were measured by estimates of mean pairwise <lb/>nucleotide site diversity (p) [8] and Watterson&apos;s theta (qw) [9] for fourfold and zero-fold <lb/>sites, distinguished here by subscripts 4 and 0. The extent of skew of the folded site <lb/>frequency spectra (SFS) at fourfold and zero-fold sites for a CO bin was assessed in various <lb/>ways: the proportion of singleton variants (PS), the mean value of Tajima&apos;s D statistic (DT) <lb/>across genes in a bin [53], and the relative difference between the mean values of qw4 and p <lb/>(Dqw4 = 1 -p /qw4) for the genes in a bin. This is related to the Dp statistic of [54], but has the <lb/>opposite sign and is not multiplied by Watterson&apos;s correction factor for sample size [9]. An <lb/>excess of rare variants over the equilibrium neutral expectation for mutation and drift under <lb/></div>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">the infinite sites model [35] is indicated by an excess of PS over the theoretical value of the <lb/>probability of observing derived variants present at frequencies of 1/n and 1 -1/n in a sample <lb/>of n alleles [9], by a negative value of DT, and by a positive value of Dqw. The last statistic <lb/>has the advantage of being independent of the sample size at mutation-drift equilibrium with <lb/>constant N e and is used in the figures presented in the text. Results for the other statistics are <lb/>shown in the Supplemental Figure S1. <lb/>LD was computed between pairs of 4-fold sites as the square of Pearson&apos;s correlation <lb/>coefficient, r, between the allelic states of the sites [55]. Pairs of sites were then grouped by <lb/>distance into bins of 10 kbp and the mean r 2 was computed for each bin, discarding bins over <lb/>5 x 10 5 bp apart, since these contained very few datapoints. <lb/>Simulations <lb/>Forwards-in-time simulations were carried out with SLiM v2.6 [56]. The values of the <lb/>deterministic parameters of mutation, selection and recombination were chosen on the basis <lb/>of estimates from D. melanogaster, as described by [12, 20]. For the simulations, these values <lb/>were multiplied by (1.33 x 10 6 )/N, where N is the number of diploid individuals used in the <lb/>simulations, to ensure that the products of N and these parameters correspond approximately <lb/>to the values for a real Drosophila population [12]; this rescaling should conserve the <lb/>properties of the evolutionary process, with some exceptions discussed in [12]. Population <lb/>sizes of 2500, 10000 and 25000 diploid individuals were simulated, with a 1:1 sex ratio. The <lb/>genome consisted of 69 intergenic regions of 4 kb each, and 70 genes plus 4kb of non-coding <lb/>sequence at both ends of the genome. Each gene was made up of a 5´ and a 3´ UTR of 190bp <lb/>and 280bp, respectively, and five coding exons of 300 bp separated by four 100bp introns, <lb/>resulting in a total gene length of 2370 bp and a total chromosome length of 449900bp. This <lb/>provides an approximate model of the Drosophila fourth chromosome, the best-studied non-<lb/>CO genomic region [57]. <lb/>A constant unscaled per-basepair mutation rate of 4.5 x 10 -9 was assumed. To speed <lb/>up the simulations, no mutations were allowed in the intergenic regions, but CO and gene <lb/>conversion were allowed at uniform rates over the whole region. Following [12], all intronic <lb/>mutations were neutral. For simulations that included both background selection (BGS) and <lb/>selective sweeps (SSWs), UTR mutations were either deleterious or beneficial, with a <lb/>probability of being beneficial of p u = 9.04 x 10 -4 (see Table 1). Coding regions were <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">assumed to consist of 30% 4-fold degenerate sites and 70% 0-fold sites. 30% of new <lb/>mutations were thus neutral; of the remainder, most were deleterious, with a probability of p a <lb/>= 2.21 x 10 -4 that a mutation at such a site was advantageous [12]. In addition, simulations <lb/>were run with SSWs only, or with BGS only. Some purely neutral simulations were also run <lb/>for the purpose of testing. For these configurations, the appropriate mutation types were <lb/>replaced by neutral ones. <lb/>Gamma distributions of selection coefficients were used for the deleterious mutations, <lb/>and exponential distributions for the beneficial mutations (see Methods Table 1). Since the <lb/>main question investigated here is the possibility of associative overdominance effects in <lb/>genomic regions with low CO rates, which requires partial recessivity of deleterious <lb/>mutations [5], we adjusted the scaled selection coefficients shown in Methods Table 1 by a <lb/>factor of 1/(2h) for runs with dominance coefficient h that differed from 0.5, in order to <lb/>maintain the same heterozygous fitness effects of mutations. In large, randomly mating <lb/>populations of the type used here, the fates of new mutations are largely determined by their <lb/>heterozygous fitness effects [16, 58]. The value of h should thus not greatly affect the rates of <lb/>fixation of deleterious and beneficial mutations, or their probability distributions at <lb/>segregating sites, provided that it is sufficiently far from zero. <lb/>Following [12], the standard CO rate in female meiosis was set to 2 x 10 -8 , and a <lb/>range of values below this, including no CO, was simulated. The rate of initiation of gene <lb/>conversion (GC) tracts in female meiosis was set to 4 x 10 -8 , double the observed rate for D. <lb/>melanogaster [32], to compensate for the fact that gene conversion in SLiM v2.6 assumes <lb/>that tracts are initiated in only one direction. The mean tract length was 440 bp, and <lb/>individual values were drawn from a geometric distribution. No recombination was allowed <lb/>in males, so that the evolutionarily effective autosomal recombination rate is half the <lb/>assigned rate. <lb/>The simulations were run for 35,000 (= 14N) generations and a sample of 20 genomes <lb/>was taken every N generations. The first 20,000 (= 8N) generations were treated as a burn-in <lb/>period, during which the population approached mutation-selection-drift equilibrium, except <lb/>for runs with zero crossing over, where equilibrium was approached very quickly because of <lb/>strong effects of selection at linked sites. A few simulations were carried out with larger <lb/>values of N (10,000 and 25,000) in the absence of crossing over. For these, we used the same <lb/>burn-in and run times, because the simulations reached equilibrium much sooner than with <lb/>crossing over. Summary statistics were calculated from the state of the population after the <lb/></div>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">simulation finished, and fixations of new mutations were recorded if they arose after the <lb/>burn-in period. <lb/>The large population sizes were used to check whether the rather strong selection <lb/>against deleterious mutations with a population size of 2,500 caused a very strong haplotype <lb/>structure in the absence of CO. This can occur because of the build-up of pseudo-<lb/>overdominance between complementary haplotypes of the type 1010… /0101… , where 1 <lb/>denotes the wild-type state at a site, and 0 denotes the mutant state [59-62]. However, there <lb/>were relatively small differences in outcomes for the different population sizes, and even the <lb/>smallest population size showed no evidence for such an effect (see Figure 3). <lb/></div>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Selection parameters used in the simulations with h = 0.5 <lb/>Genomic region <lb/>Fitness effect <lb/>Proportion of different <lb/>types of mutations in a <lb/>region <lb/>Distribution of <lb/>homozygous selection <lb/>coefficients (scaled by <lb/>2N) <lb/>Coding <lb/>Beneficial <lb/>0.7pa <lb/>(pa = 2.21 x 10 -4 ) <lb/>Exponential (mean = <lb/>250) <lb/>Neutral <lb/>0.3 <lb/>Deleterious <lb/>0.7(1 -pa) <lb/>Gamma (mean = <lb/>2000, shape = 0.3) <lb/>UTR <lb/>Beneficial <lb/>pu = 9.04 x 10 -4 <lb/>Exponential (mean = <lb/>213) <lb/>Deleterious <lb/>1 -pu <lb/>Gamma (mean= 110, <lb/>shape = 0.3) <lb/>Intron <lb/>Neutral <lb/>1 <lb/>Intergenic <lb/>Neutral <lb/>1 <lb/>For simulations with other h values, the mean selection coefficients are multiplied by <lb/>0.5/h. <lb/></div>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS <lb/>For the analysis of the D. simulans population genetic statistics, genes were binned by <lb/>crossover rate (10 bins of approx. 730 genes for autosomes, 10 bins of approx. 180 genes for <lb/>the X chromosome) as detailed in Supplementary Table S1. Per-bin means, weighted by the <lb/>number of relevant sites per gene, were analysed with Spearman rank correlations for the <lb/>autosomes, and with least-squares regression models (containing a quadratic term) for the X. <lb/>Both methods were implemented in R. The p values reported are the overall values for the <lb/>rank correlations, and for the quadratic terms in the X models. <lb/>The confidence intervals for the empirical and simulated data were generated via <lb/>bootstrapping using the R package &quot;boot&quot;. For the empirical data, bootstrapping was carried <lb/>out on the level of genes per bin (see Table S1). All simulations were run with 20 replicates, <lb/>which provide the basis for bootstrapping. We report the 95% confidence intervals of the <lb/>mean based on 1000 bootstrap replicates. For analyses of linkage disequilibrium, we used the <lb/>same approach for the medians of the r 2 statistic described above. <lb/>The decay of linkage disequilibrium with pairwise distance between sites was <lb/>assessed using Mantel tests as implemented in the R package &quot;vegan&quot;. The value of the <lb/>Mantel statistic and the associated p-values are reported in the legend of figure 3. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA AND CODE AVAILABILITY <lb/>The original data are available from the European Nucleotide Archive, accession numbers <lb/>PRJEB7673 and PRJNA215932. The scripts developed here are available on GitHub. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">KEY RESOURCES TABLE <lb/>Submitted separately as requested. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Titles of the Supplementsl Tables <lb/>Supplemental Table S1. Related to Figure 1, Figure 2, and to the first section of the Results <lb/>and Discussion. Metaanalysis of delta theta in non-crossover regions of other Drosophila <lb/>species. <lb/></div>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental Table S2. Haplotypes around the high-diversity region on the Drosophila <lb/>simulans 4th chromosome. Related to section &quot;Linkage Disequilibrium Patterns and a Further <lb/>Test for AOD&quot; <lb/>Supplemental Table S3. Binned population genetic statistics from two populations of <lb/>Drosophila simulans. Related to figures 1 and S1 <lb/>Supplemental Table S4. Results of forwards-in-time simulations with parameters relevant to <lb/>Drosophila populations. Related to figure 2. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Begun, D., and Aquadro, C.F. (1992). Levels of naturally occurring DNA polymorphism <lb/>correlate with recombination rate in Drosophila melanogaster. Nature 356, 519-520. <lb/>2. <lb/>Cutter, A.D., and Payseur, B.A. (2013). Genomic signatures of selection at linked <lb/>sites: unifying the disparity among species. Nature Rev. Genet. 14, 262-272. <lb/>3. <lb/>Charlesworth, B., and Campos, J.L. (2014). The relations between recombination rate <lb/>and patterns of molecular evolution and variation in Drosophila. Ann. Rev. Genet. 48, <lb/>383-403. <lb/>4. <lb/>Pouyet, F., Aeschbacher, S., Thiery, A., and Excoffier, L. (2018). Background selection <lb/>and biased gene conversion affect more than 95% of the human genome and bias <lb/>demographic inferences. eLife 7, e36317. <lb/>5. <lb/>Zhao, L., and Charlesworth, B. (2016). Resolving the conflict between associative <lb/>overdominance and background selection. Genetics 203, 1315-1334. <lb/>6. <lb/>Corbett-Detig, R.B., Hartl, D.L., and Sackton, T.B. (2015). Natural selection constrains <lb/>neutral diversity across a wide range of species. PloS Biology 13, e1002112. <lb/>7. <lb/>Jackson, B.C., Campos, J.L., Haddrill, P.R., Charlesworth, B., and Zeng, K. (2017). <lb/>Variation in the intensity of selection on codon bias over time causes contrasting <lb/>patterns of base composition evolution in Drosophila. Genome. Biol. Evol. 9, 102-<lb/>123. <lb/>8. <lb/>Nei, M., and Tajima, F. (1983). DNA polymorphism detectable by restriction <lb/>endonucleases. Genetics 97, 145-163. <lb/>9. <lb/>Watterson, G.A. (1975). On the number of segregating sites in genetical models <lb/>without recombination. Theor. Pop. Biol. 7, 256-276. <lb/>10. <lb/>Campos, J.L., Halligan, D.L., Haddrill, P.R., and Charlesworth, B. (2014). The relation <lb/>between recombination rate and patterns of molecular evolution and variation in <lb/>Drosophila melanogaster. Mol. Biol. Evol. 31, 1010-1028. <lb/>11. <lb/>Zeng, K., Jackson, B.C., and Barton, H.J. (2019). Methods for estimating demography <lb/>and detecting between-locus differences in the effective population size and <lb/>mutation rate. Mol .Biol. Evol. 36, 423-433. <lb/>12. <lb/>Campos, J.L., and Charlesworth, B. (2019). The effects on neutral variability of <lb/>recurrent selective sweeps and background selection. Genetics 212, 287-303. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>13. <lb/>Crow, J.F. (1993). Mutation, mean fitness, and genetic load. Oxf. Surv. Evol. Biol. 9, 3-<lb/>42. <lb/>14. <lb/>Manna, F., Martin, G., and Lenormand, T. (2011). Fitness landscapes: An alternative <lb/>theory for the dominance of mutation. Genetics 189, 923-937. <lb/>15. <lb/>Charlesworth, B. (2015). Causes of natural variation in fitness: evidence from studies <lb/>of Drosophila populations. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 12, 1662-1669. <lb/>16. <lb/>Haldane, J.B.S. (1927). A mathematical theory of natural and artificial selection. Part <lb/>V. Selection and mutation. Proc. Camb. Phil. Soc. 23, 838-844. <lb/>17. <lb/>Loewe, L., Charlesworth, B., Bartolomé, C., and Nöel, V. (2006). Estimating selection <lb/>on nonsynonymous mutations. Genetics 172, 1079-1092. <lb/>18. <lb/>Keightley, P.D., and Eyre-Walker, A. (2007). Joint inference of the distribution of <lb/>fitness effects of deleterious mutations and population demography based on <lb/>nucleotide polymorphism frequencies. Genetics 177, 2251-2261. <lb/>19. <lb/>Kousathanas, A., and Keightley, P.D. (2013). A comparison of models to infer the <lb/>distribution of fitness effects of new mutations. Genetics 193, 1197-1208. <lb/>20. <lb/>Campos, J.C., Zhao, L., and Charlesworth, B. (2017). Estimating the parameters of <lb/>background selection and selective sweeps in Drosophila in the presence of gene <lb/>conversion. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 114, E4762-E4771. <lb/>21. <lb/>Frydenberg, O. (1963). Population studies of a lethal mutant in Drosophila <lb/>melanogaster. I. Behaviour in populations with discrete generations. Hereditas 50, <lb/>89-116. <lb/>22. <lb/>Nordborg, M., and Innan, H. (2003). The genealogy of sequences containing multiple <lb/>sites subject to strong selection in a subdivided population. Genetics 163, 1201-<lb/>1213. <lb/>23. <lb/>Zeng, K., Fu, X.-Y., Shi, S., and Wu, C.-I. (2006). Statistical tests for detecting positive <lb/>selection by utilizing high-frequency variants. Genetics 174, 1431-1439. <lb/>24. <lb/>Charlesworth, B., and Charlesworth, D. (2010). Elements of Evolutionary Genetics, <lb/>(Greenwood Village, CO: Roberts and Company). <lb/>25. <lb/>Bitarello, B.D., de Filippo, C., Teixeira, J.C., Schmidt, J.M., Kleinert, P., Meyer, D., and <lb/>Andres, A.M. (2018). Signatures of long-term balancing selection <lb/>in human genomes. Genome Biol. Evol. 10, 939-955. <lb/>26. <lb/>Comeron, J.M., and Kreitman, M. (2002). Population, evolutionary and genomic <lb/>consequences of interference selection. Genetics 161, 389-410. <lb/>27. <lb/>Gordo, I., Navarro, A., and Charlesworth, B. (2002). Muller&apos;s ratchet and the pattern <lb/>of variation at a neutral locus. Genetics 161, 835-848. <lb/>28. <lb/>Kaiser, V.B., and Charlesworth, B. (2009). The effects of deleterious mutations on <lb/>evolution in non-recombining genomes. Trnds. Genet. 25, 9-12. <lb/>29. <lb/>Seger, J., Smith, W.A., Perry, J.J., Hunn, K., Kaliszewska, Z.A., et al. (2010). Gene <lb/>genealogies distorted by weakly interfering mutations in constant environments. <lb/>Genetics 184, 529-545. <lb/>30. <lb/>Good, B.H., Walczak, A.M., Neher, R.A., and Desai, M.M. (2014). Genetic diversity in <lb/>the interference selection limit. PLos Genetics 10, e1004222. <lb/>31. <lb/>Comeron, J., Ratnappan, R., and Bailin, S. (2012). The many landscapes of <lb/>recombination in Drosophila melanogaster. PLos Genetics 8, e1002905. <lb/>32. <lb/>Miller, D.E., Smith, C.B., Kazemi, N.Y., Cockrell, A.J., Arvanitakas, A.V., Blumenstiel, <lb/>J.P., S.L., J., and Hawley, R.S. (2016). Whole-genome analysis of individual meiotic <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>events in Drosophila melanogaster reveals that noncrossover gene conversions are <lb/>insensitive to interference and the centromere effect. Genetics 203, 159-171. <lb/>33. <lb/>Slatkin, M. (1994). Linkage disequilibrium in stable and growing populations. <lb/>Genetics 137, 331-336. <lb/>34. <lb/>McVean, G.A.T. (2002). A genealogical interpretation of linkage disequilibrium. <lb/>Genetics 162, 987-991. <lb/>35. <lb/>Kimura, M. (1971). Theoretical foundations of population genetics at the molecular <lb/>level. Theor. Pop. Biol. 2, 174-208. <lb/>36. <lb/>Weir, B.S., and Hill, W.G. (1986). Nonuniform recombination within the human b-<lb/>globin gene cluster. Am. J. Hum. Genet. 38, 776-778. <lb/>37. <lb/>Schrider, D.R., Houle, D., Lynch, M., and Hahn, M.W. (2013). Rates and genomic <lb/>consequences of spontaneous mutational events in Drosophila melanogaster. <lb/>Genetics 194, 937-954. <lb/>38. <lb/>Neher, R.A. (2013). Genetic draft, selective interference and population genetics of <lb/>rapid adaptation. Ann. Rev. Ecol. Evol. Syst. 44, 195-215. <lb/>39. <lb/>Price, M.N., and Arkin, A.P. (2015). Weakly deleterious mutations and low rates of <lb/>recombination limit the impact of natural selection on bacterial genomes. mBio 6, <lb/>e01302-01315. <lb/>40. <lb/>Agrawal, A.F., and Hartfield, M. (2916). Coalescence with background and balancing <lb/>selection in systems with bi-and uniparental reproduction: Contrasting partial <lb/>asexuality and selfing. Genetics 202, 313-326. <lb/>41. <lb/>Bast, J., Parker, D.J., Dumas, Z., Jalvingh, K.M., Van, P.T., Jaron, K.S., Figuet, E., <lb/>Brandt, A., Galtier, N., and Schwander, T. (2018). Consequences of asexuality in <lb/>natural populations: Insights from stick insects. Mol .Biol. Evol. 35, 1668-1677. <lb/>42. <lb/>Charlesworth, D., and Wright, S.I. (2001). Breeding systems and genome evolution. <lb/>Curr. Opn. Genet. Dev. 11, 685-690. <lb/>43. <lb/>Wright, S.I., Kalisz, S., and Slotte, T. (2013). Evolutionary consequences of self-<lb/>fertilization in plants. Proc. R. Soc. B 280, 20130133. <lb/>44. <lb/>Charlesworth, B., and Charlesworth, D. (2000). The degeneration of Y chromosomes. <lb/>Phil. Trans. R. Soc. B. 355, 1563-2572. <lb/>45. <lb/>Bachtrog, D. (2008). The temporal dynamics of processes underlying Y chromosome <lb/>degeneration. Genetics 179, 1513-1525. <lb/>46. <lb/>Kaiser, V.B., and Charlesworth, B. (2010). Muller&apos;s ratchet and the degeneration of <lb/>the Drosophila miranda neo-Y chromosome. Genetics 185, 339-348. <lb/>47. <lb/>Hough, J., Wang, W., Barrett, S.C.H., and Wright, S.I. (2017). Hill-Robertson <lb/>interference reduces genetic diversity on a young plant Y-chromosome. Genetics <lb/>207, 685-695. <lb/>48. <lb/>Thurmond, J., Goodman, J.L., Strelets, V.B., Attrill, H., Gramates, L.S., Marygold, S.J., <lb/>Matthews, B.B., Millburn, M., Antonazzo, G., Trovisco, V., et al. (2019). FlyBase 2.0: <lb/>the next generation. Nucl. Acids Res. 47, D759-D756. <lb/>49. <lb/>Li, H. (2013). Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with <lb/>BWA-MEM. ArXiv 1303.3997. <lb/>50. <lb/>McKenna, A., Hanna, M., Banks, E., Sivachenko, A., Cibulskis, K., Kernytsky, A., <lb/>Garimella, K., Altshuler, D., Gabriel, S., M., D., et al. (2010). The Genome Analysis <lb/>Toolkit: a MapReduce framework for analyzing next-generation DNA sequencing <lb/>data. . Genome Res. 20, 1297-1303. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>51. <lb/>Sturtevant, A.H. (1921). A case of rearrangement of genes in Drosophila. Proc. Natl. <lb/>Acad. Sci. USA 7, 235-237. <lb/>52. True, J.R., Mercer, J.M., Laurie, C.C. (1996). Differences in crossover frequency and <lb/>distribution among three sibling species of Drosophila. Genetics 142: 507-523. <lb/>53. <lb/>Tajima, F. (1989). Statistical method for testing the neutral mutation hypothesis. <lb/>Genetics 123, 585-595. <lb/>54. <lb/>Langley, S.A., Karpen, G.H., and Langley, C.H. (2014). Nucleosomes shape DNA <lb/>polymorphism and divergence. PloS Genetics 10: e1004457. <lb/>55. <lb/>Hill, W.G., and Robertson, A. (1968). Linkage disequilibrium in finite populations. <lb/>Theor. Appl. Genet. 38, 226-231. <lb/>56. <lb/>Haller, B.C., and Messer, P.W. (2016). SLiM 2: Flexible, interactive forward genetic <lb/>simulations. Mol .Biol. Evol. 34, 230-240. <lb/>57. <lb/>Riddle, N.C., and Elgin, S.C. (2018). The Drosophila dot chromosome: Where genes <lb/>flourish amidst repeats. Genetics 210, 757-772. <lb/>58. <lb/>Fisher, R.A. (1922). On the dominance ratio. Proc. Roy. Soc. Edinburgh 42, 321-341. <lb/>59. <lb/>Charlesworth, D., Morgan, M.T., and Charlesworth, B. (1993). Mutation <lb/>accumulation in finite outbreeding and inbreeding populations. Genet. Res. 61, 39-<lb/>56. <lb/>60. <lb/>Pamilo, P., and Palsson, S. (1998). Associative overdominance, heterozygosity and <lb/>fitness. Heredity 81, 381-389. <lb/>61. <lb/>Palsson, S., and Pamilo, P. (1999). The effects of deleterious mutations on linked <lb/>neutral variation in small populations. Genetics 153, 475-483. <lb/>62. <lb/>Palsson, S. (2001). The effects of deleterious mutations in cyclically parthenogetic <lb/>organisms. J. Theor. Biol. 208, 201-214. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
