<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ZCWPW1 is recruited to recombination <lb/>hotspots by PRDM9, and is essential for <lb/>meiotic double strand break repair <lb/>Authors: Daniel Wells 1,2, † , Emmanuelle Bitoun 1,2, † , Daniela Moralli 1 , Gang <lb/>Zhang 1 , Anjali Gupta Hinch 1 , Peter Donnelly 1,2 , Catherine Green 1 , Simon <lb/>R Myers 1,2, *. <lb/>1 <lb/>The Wellcome Centre for Human Genetics, Roosevelt Drive, University of <lb/>Oxford, Oxford OX3 7BN, UK. <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Statistics, University of Oxford, Oxford OX1 3LB, UK. <lb/> † <lb/>These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Email: myers@stats.ox.ac.uk <lb/> 1 <lb/> Abstract <lb/>During meiosis, homologous chromosomes pair (synapse) and recombine, <lb/>enabling balanced segregation and generating genetic diversity. In many <lb/>vertebrates, recombination initiates with double-strand breaks (DSBs) within <lb/>hotspots where PRDM9 binds, and deposits H3K4me3 and H3K36me3. However, <lb/>no protein(s) recognising this unique combination of histone marks have yet been <lb/>identified. <lb/>We identified Zcwpw1, which possesses H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 <lb/>recognition domains, as highly co-expressed with Prdm9. Here, we show that <lb/>ZCWPW1 has co-evolved with PRDM9 and, in human cells, is strongly and <lb/>specifically recruited to PRDM9 binding sites, with higher affinity than sites <lb/>possessing H3K4me3 alone. Surprisingly, ZCWPW1 also recognizes CpG <lb/>dinucleotides, including within many Alu transposons. <lb/>Male Zcwpw1 homozygous knockout mice show completely normal DSB <lb/>positioning, but persistent DMC1 foci at many hotspots, particularly those more <lb/>strongly bound by PRDM9, severe DSB repair and synapsis defects, and <lb/>downstream sterility. Our findings suggest a model where ZCWPW1 recognition of <lb/>PRDM9-bound sites on either the homologous, or broken, chromosome is critical <lb/>for synapsis, and hence fertility. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Graphical Abstract Legend <lb/>In humans and other species, recombination is initiated by double strand breaks at <lb/>sites bound by PRDM9. Upon binding, PRDM9 deposits the histone marks <lb/>H3K4me3 and H3K36me, but the functional importance of these marks has <lb/>remained unknown. Here, we show that PRDM9 recruits ZCWPW1, a reader of <lb/>both these marks, to its binding sites genome-wide. ZCWPW1 does not help <lb/>position the breaks themselves, but is essential for their downstream repair and <lb/>chromosome pairing, and ultimately meiotic success and fertility in mice. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Meiosis is a specialised cell division, producing haploid gametes essential for <lb/>reproduction. Uniquely during this process, homologous maternal and paternal <lb/>chromosomes pair and exchange DNA (recombine) before undergoing balanced <lb/>independent segregation. Alongside de novo mutations, this generates all genetic <lb/>diversity -providing a substrate on which natural selection can act. <lb/>In humans, mice, and likely many other vertebrates (Baker et al., 2017), the <lb/>locations at which recombination occurs is determined by the binding locations of <lb/>PRDM9, which recognises a specific sequence motif encoded by its zinc finger <lb/>array (Baudat et al., 2010; Myers et al., 2010; Parvanov et al., 2010). At these sites, <lb/>Spo11 catalyzes recombination-initiating double strand breaks (DSBs), a subset of <lb/>which are repaired by recombination with the homologous chromosome. The sister <lb/>chromatid can also provide a repair substrate, e.g. for DSBs on the X chromosome <lb/>in males, and there is evidence that this also occurs at some autosomal hotspots <lb/>(Allen and Latt, 1976; R. Li et al., 2019; Lu and Yu, 2015). <lb/>In Prdm9-null mice, DSBs form at promoter regions rich in H3K4me3 (Brick <lb/>et al., 2012), and fail to repair resulting in severe asynapsis, meiotic arrest at <lb/>pachytene, and sterility in both males and females on the B6 background (Hayashi <lb/>et al., 2005). We previously showed (Davies et al., 2016) that across DSB sites, <lb/>increased binding of PRDM9 to the homologous chromosome aids synapsis and <lb/>fertility in hybrid mice, implying an impact of binding downstream of DSB <lb/>positioning. Mice where most DSBs occur at sites where PRDM9 does not bind the <lb/>homologue show widespread asynapsis (Davies et al., 2016; Gregorova et al., <lb/>2018). More recently, we showed that binding of PRDM9 to the homologous <lb/>chromosome promotes repair of DSBs by homologue-templated recombination, <lb/>potentially by aiding homology search (R. Li et al., 2019). <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>DSB sites are processed by resection, resulting in single-stranded DNA <lb/>(ssDNA) that becomes decorated with DMC1 (Hong et al., 2001; Neale and <lb/>Keeney, 2006; Sehorn et al., 2004). In WT mice, DMC1 foci start to appear in early <lb/>zygotene cells upon loading to the ssDNA ends of the DSBs created during <lb/>leptotene. From mid-zygotene to early pachytene, as part of the recombinational <lb/>repair process, DMC1 dissociates from the ssDNA and counts decrease until all <lb/>breaks (except those on the XY chromosomes) are repaired in late pachytene <lb/>(Moens et al., 2002). At DSB sites where the homologous chromosome is not <lb/>bound by PRDM9, DMC1 signal is strongly elevated (Davies et al., 2016), <lb/>suggesting delayed DSB repair, while fewer homologous recombination events <lb/>occur (Hinch et al., 2019; R. Li et al., 2019), suggesting that (eventual) DSB repair <lb/>may sometimes use a sister chromosome pathway. However, the underlying <lb/>mechanism(s) by which PRDM9 effectively contributes to DSB repair are not yet <lb/>known. <lb/>PRDM9 deposits both H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 histone methylation <lb/>marks at the sites it binds, and this methyltransferase activity is essential for its <lb/>role in DSB positioning (Diagouraga et al., 2018; Powers et al., 2016). What reads <lb/>this unique combination of marks at recombination sites, however, is currently <lb/>unknown. Notably, outside of hotspots and the pseudoautosomal region (PAR) on <lb/>sex chromosomes, H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 occur at largely nonoverlapping <lb/>locations (Powers et al., 2016), suggesting potentially highly specialised reader(s). <lb/>Indeed, in somatic cells H3K4me3 is deposited mainly at promoters, in particular <lb/>by the SET1 complex targeted by CXXC1/CFP1 and Wdr82 which binds Ser5 <lb/>phosphorylated polymerase II (Barski et al., 2007; Lee and Skalnik, 2008, 2005). <lb/>H3K36me3 is deposited by different methlytransferases, including SETD2 bound <lb/>to Ser2 phosphorylated (elongating) polymerase II, and is enriched at exon bound <lb/>nucleosomes, particularly for 3&apos; exons (reviewed in (McDaniel and Strahl, 2017; <lb/>Wagner and Carpenter, 2012)). H3K36me3 has multiple important roles, including <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>in directing DNA methylation by recruiting DNMT3B, somatic DSB repair by <lb/>homologous recombination (Aymard et al., 2014; Carvalho et al., 2014; Pfister et <lb/>al., 2014), mismatch repair by recruiting MSH6 (Huang et al., 2018; Li et al., 2013), <lb/>and V(D)J recombination during lymphopoiesis (Ji et al., 2019). <lb/>Using single cell RNA-sequencing of mouse testis, we identified a set of <lb/>genes co-expressed in (pre)leptotene cells which are highly enriched for genes <lb/>involved in meiotic recombination (Jung et al., 2019). Zcwpw1, which ranks 3 rd in <lb/>this set after Prdm9 (2 nd ), is of unknown function but contains two recognised <lb/>protein domains: CW and PWWP, shown to individually bind H3K4me3 and <lb/>H3K36me3 respectively (F. He et al., 2010; Rona et al., 2016). This raises the <lb/>attractive possibility that ZCWPW1 might recognize and physically associate with <lb/>the same marks deposited by PRDM9 (Jung et al., 2019). <lb/>In humans, ZCWPW1 is specifically expressed in testis (Carithers et al., <lb/>2015; Uhlén et al., 2015) (Supplementary Figure 1). It is also one of 104 genes <lb/>specific to meiotic prophase in murine fetal ovary (Soh et al., 2015), further <lb/>suggesting a conserved meiotic function. This was confirmed by a recent study <lb/>showing that ZCWPW1 is required for male fertility, with ZCWPW1 hypothesised <lb/>to recruit the DSB machinery to hotspot sites (M. Li et al., 2019). Here, we show <lb/>that ZCWPW1 co-evolves with PRDM9, and is recruited to recombination hotspots <lb/>by the combination of histone marks deposited by PRDM9. However, ZCWPW1 is <lb/>not required for the positioning of DSBs at PRDM9-bound sites, which occurs <lb/>normally in ZCWPW1-null mice. Instead, ZCWPW1 is required for proper inter-<lb/>homologue interactions: synapsis and the repair of DSBs. In ZCWPW1-null mice, <lb/>DMC1 signals show strong perturbations, with signals at autosomal hotspots <lb/>resembling those on the X-chromosome, which does not have a homologue. Thus, <lb/>ZCWPW1 represents the first protein directly positioned by PRDM9 binding, but <lb/>impacting homologous DSB repair. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results <lb/>ZCWPW1 co-evolves with PRDM9 <lb/>Based on publicly available databases, we identified likely ZCWPW1 orthologues <lb/>in 167 species in total, aligned each to the human reference ZCWPW1 protein, and <lb/>compared against a previous analysis of PRDM9 (Baker et al., 2017). The <lb/>alignment reveals the regions containing the CW and PWWP domains to be the <lb/>most conserved among species (Figure 1), while other parts of the protein appear <lb/>to have been lost in some species. In addition, there is a region of moderate <lb/>conservation downstream of the PWWP domain, not overlapping any known <lb/>domain. Notably, an SYCP1 (SCP1) domain is annotated in the mouse protein <lb/>only, which although only suggestive, is interesting given that SYCP1 physically <lb/>connects homologous chromosomes in meiosis. In addition, protein threading <lb/>suggests that the C terminal end of ZCWPW1 may contain a methyl-CpG binding <lb/>domain (Methods, (Lobley et al., 2009). <lb/>Because of incomplete available DNA and protein sequences, we are <lb/>almost certain to miss some species where ZCWPW1 is present, and similarly it is <lb/>challenging to identify PRDM9 orthologues (Baker et al., 2017). Despite this, we <lb/>see extremely high overlap between PRDM9 and ZCWPW1 occurrence. All <lb/>identified ZCWPW1 orthologues are in vertebrates, similar to identified PRDM9 <lb/>orthologues (Baker et al., 2017). 99 of 167 (149) species with ZCWPW1 (PRDM9) <lb/>respectively have the other protein; an even higher fraction of species have a close <lb/>relative with an identified orthologue: 131 species with ZCWPW1 are in a family <lb/>possessing PRDM9. Only 8 species possess ZCWPW1 but are in an order with no <lb/>identified species possessing PRDM9: three amphibians including Xenopus frogs, <lb/>and five placental mammals. Given widespread conservation of PRDM9 among <lb/>mammals other than canids (Baker et al., 2017), these five might plausibly <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>represent false negatives. Thus, ZCWPW1 appears to mainly occur in species, <lb/>and even more clearly in groups of species, possessing PRDM9. <lb/>We identified ZCWPW1 orthologues across the full spectrum of vertebrates <lb/>possessing PRDM9, including jawless, cartilaginous and bony fish, coelacanths, <lb/>turtles, snakes and lizards, and mammals. Previous work (Baker et al., 2017) has <lb/>identified at least 6 independent complete PRDM9 loss events; in birds and <lb/>crocodiles; in three distinct groups of teleost fish (although these fish possess a <lb/>PRDM9 &quot;beta&quot; orthologue with mutations in key catalytic amino acids within the <lb/>SET domain); in canids; and tentatively, in amphibians. The first four losses appear <lb/>to have been completely mirrored by corresponding ZCWPW1 losses, with no <lb/>species previously studied by Baker et al. in these groups possessing a ZCWPW1 <lb/>orthologue. For the latter two, we did find potential orthologues (e.g. in canids), but <lb/>with mutations at positions in ZCWPW1 that are conserved among all PRDM9-<lb/>SET-possessing species (Methods). Thus, there has been similar (co)evolution of <lb/>presence/absence of ZCWPW1 and PRDM9. <lb/>We observe a greater number of species -28 -possessing PRDM9 <lb/>orthologues but having no relative closer than their class possessing an identified <lb/>ZCWPW1 orthologue. All of these are bony fish. Strikingly, 24 of these 28 <lb/>orthologues possess one or more mutations in their SET domain (Supplementary <lb/>Table 1), predicted to disrupt H3K4me3 and/or H3K36me3 deposition. In strong <lb/>contrast, 94% of PRDM9-containing species with non-mutant SET domains have <lb/>a closer relative possessing ZCWPW1 (odds ratio=90; indicative p&lt;10 -15 by FET, <lb/>though we note these observations are not all independent). This implies that <lb/>ZCWPW1 is most often lost, whenever mutations occur in the SET domain of <lb/>PRDM9. Interestingly, PRDM9-containing species with non-mutant SET domains <lb/>are near-identical to those also possessing SSXRD domains, and SSXRD has <lb/>been reported as essential for PRDM9&apos;s H3K4me3 methyltransferase activity at <lb/>hotspots ex vivo (Thibault-Sennett et al., 2018). However, other domains of <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>PRDM9 (KRAB, and the zinc finger array) have been lost across multiple species, <lb/>and it is hypothesized PRDM9 does not position recombination in these species <lb/>(Baker et al., 2017). Nonetheless, they mainly retain ZCWPW1 (Supplementary <lb/>Table 1). In conclusion, among vertebrates at least, it appears the set of species <lb/>with ZCWPW1 is extremely similar to those species possessing PRDM9 with both <lb/>an intact SET domain, and an SSXRD domain, with considerable evidence of co-<lb/>evolution of gain/loss events for each protein. We note that this pattern is precisely <lb/>what would be expected a priori, if ZCWPW1&apos;s main function involves recognition <lb/>of the histone modifications catalysed by PRDM9-SET during early meiosis, as <lb/>predicted from functional considerations. <lb/>Figure 1. Domain organisation (A) and evolutionary conservation (B) of ZCWPW1. <lb/>(A) Protein domains in the human and mouse proteins (source: UniProt). Start and <lb/>end positions of each domain are shown above and below the rectangles <lb/>respectively. Prediction of SCP-1 domain from (Marchler-Bauer and Bryant, 2004) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>and of MBDs from (Lobley et al., 2009) (Methods) (B) Conservation of human <lb/>amino acids, normalised Jensen-Shanon divergence from (Capra and Singh, 2007; <lb/>Johansson and Toh, 2010) using multiple alignment of 167 orthologues (Methods). <lb/>Localisation of ZCWPW1 in meiosis and details of asynapsis in infertile male <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-mice <lb/>To investigate the role of ZCWPW1 during meiosis in vivo, we produced an <lb/>antibody against the full-length recombinant mouse protein (Supplementary <lb/>Figure 2) and studied the phenotype of a newly generated knockout (KO) mouse <lb/>line for Zcwpw1, with a particular focus on fertility and meiotic recombination. <lb/>Figure 2. Expression of ZCWPW1 across meiosis prophase I in mouse testis. <lb/>Nuclear spreads were immunostained with antibodies against ZCWPW1 (red) and <lb/>the synaptonemal complex protein SYCP3 (green) which labels the chromosome <lb/>axis, and counterstained with DAPI (blue) to visualise nuclei. Developmental <lb/>stages indicated above. Yellow arrows show apparent ZCWPW1 foci at both ends <lb/>of the synaptonemal complex. The dashed circle shows staining in the XY body. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>In testes from wild-type (WT) mice, we observe a dynamic localisation of ZCWPW1 <lb/>protein (Figure 2), similar but non-identical to that reported in a recent study (M. Li <lb/>et al., 2019). ZCWPW1 shows a strong, punctate nuclear staining excluding the <lb/>pericentromeric regions (clustered into chromocenters brightly stained with DAPI) <lb/>in zygotene and early pachytene cells; we detected transcript expression in earlier <lb/>pre-leptotene to leptotene cells (Jung et al., 2019). In pachytene cells, ZCWPW1 <lb/>expression drops, with the protein now mainly localised in the XY body and as <lb/>bright foci at the ends of the synaptonemal complex labelled by SYCP3, not <lb/>previously observed using an antibody raised against a 174 base-pair (bp) C-<lb/>terminal region of the protein (M. Li et al., 2019). By diplotene, little expression is <lb/>visible. Using FISH to label telomeric ends of chromosomes, we established that <lb/>these discrete foci of ZCWPW1 are located at subtelomeric regions <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 3). <lb/>We next studied mice from a constitutive Zcwpw1 KO line (Methods), <lb/>carrying a ~1.5kb frameshift deletion encompassing exons 5 to 7 upstream of the <lb/>CW domain, creating a premature stop codon resulting in the production and <lb/>predicted degradation (by RNA-mediated decay) of a short 492bp (vs 1893bp for <lb/>WT) transcript (Figure 3A). Confirming this, ZCWPW1 expression was completely <lb/>absent in testis chromosome spreads from Zcwpw1 -/-mice, in zygotene cells <lb/>(Figure 3B) and all other meiotic stages of prophase I where expression is <lb/>detected in WT mice (Supplementary Figure 4). Confirming recent findings in a <lb/>different Zcwpw1 -/-mouse (M. Li et al., 2019), we observed no overt fertility <lb/>phenotype in either sex in the heterozygous Zcwpw1 +/-mice (data not shown). <lb/>However Zcwpw1 -/-male mice were sterile with complete azoospermia and <lb/>reduced testis size (Figure 3B,D), while female mice retained fertility until around <lb/>7-8 months of age (Supplementary Table 2), and otherwise both sexes develop <lb/>normally. As in (M. Li et al., 2019), we observe widespread asynapsed <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>chromosomes in male mice, marked by γ-H2AX and HORMAD2, persistent DMC1 <lb/>foci marking unrepaired DSBs (Figure 4), no meiotic progression beyond <lb/>(pseudo)pachytene, failure to form the sex body, and a complete absence of MLH1 <lb/>foci marking recombination crossover sites (Supplementary Figure 5). <lb/>Figure 3. Male Zcwpw1 -/-mice show reduced testis size and asynapsis, <lb/>similar to the Prdm9 -/-mutant. (A) Schematic of the Zcwpw1 knockout mouse <lb/>line. E: Exon. gRNA guideRNA. Sanger sequencing DNA chromatograms of wild-<lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>type (WT) and knockout (KO) mice encompassing the deletion are shown. The <lb/>intron-exon organization is not to scale. (B) Immunofluorescence staining of testis <lb/>nuclear spreads from Zcwpw1 +/+ and Zcwpw1 -/-mice for ZCWPW1, the <lb/>synaptonemal complex protein SYCP3 which labels the chromosome axis, or <lb/>HORMAD2 which marks unsynapsed chromosomes. (C) Representative testes <lb/>from 9-10 weeks old WT (+/+), Het (+/-) and Hom (-/-) Zcwpw1 KO mice are shown. <lb/>(D) Paired testes weight was normalized to lean body weight. The p-value is from <lb/>Welch&apos;s two-sided, two sample t-test. Raw data in Supplementary Table 3. (E) <lb/>Synapsis quantification in testis chromosome spreads immunostained with <lb/>HORMAD2, as in (B). The percentage of pachytene cells with all autosomes fully <lb/>synapsed is plotted by genotype; n≥50 cells. Vertical lines are 95% Wilson binomial <lb/>confidence intervals. Raw data in Supplementary Table 4. <lb/>Figure 4. Similar DMC1 count elevation in Zcwpw1 -/-and Prdm9 -/-mice, <lb/>compared to wild-type. (A) Testis chromosome spreads from wild-type and <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-mice were immunostained for DMC1 and SYCP3. Representative late <lb/>pachytene cells are shown. (B) The number of DMC1 foci in cells from the various <lb/>stages of prophase I were counted. p-values are from Welch&apos;s two sided, two <lb/>sample t-test. L: Leptotene, Z: Zygotene, P: Pachytene. n=3 mice per genotype <lb/>(Zcwpw1 -/-and WT), n=2 for Prdm9 -/-. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>Each of these properties resembles observations in the Prdm9 -/-mutant, and so <lb/>we compared to this mutant. In our Zcwpw1 -/-male mice, &gt;98% of pachytene cells <lb/>failed to properly synapse at least one pair of chromosomes (Figure 3B, E), similar <lb/>to Prdm9 -/-males. However, the nature of the synaptic defects observed differed <lb/>(Supplementary Table 4). In the Prdm9 -/-mutant, 63.2% of the pseudopachytene <lb/>cells showed mispairing of non-homologous chromosomes in a typical branched <lb/>structure (referred to as &quot;tangled&quot;, Supplementary Table 4). In contrast, we only <lb/>observed 24.8% of Zcwpw1 -/-pseudopachytene cells with this type of error, while <lb/>the majority (74.5%) of cells contained multiple bundles of HORMAD2-positive <lb/>unsynapsed chromosomes, which resemble the XY body and may merge with the <lb/>sex chromosomes (thus referred to as &quot;multibodies&quot;, Supplementary Figure 5). <lb/>These results imply that the Prdm9 -/-mutant often mispairs chromosomes, while <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-spermatocytes mainly fail to pair a subset of chromosomes at all. The <lb/>expression levels and staining pattern of ZCWPW1 were not visibly altered in testis <lb/>nuclear spreads from Prdm9 -/-mice (data not shown). <lb/>Comparing levels of DMC1 foci as a proxy for DSB repair, or a potential <lb/>cause for the asynapsis in Zcwpw1 -/-males, in both Zcwpw1 -/-and Prdm9 -/-mice <lb/>foci count was significantly elevated from early zygotene onwards, indicating <lb/>delayed repair of DSBs (Figure 4). However, we observed a wider spread for <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-males. A similar increase was observed at pachytene stage in the levels <lb/>of RAD51 (Supplementary Figure 6), another ssDNA-binding protein which <lb/>functions in concert with DMC1, with the large majority of RAD51 and DMC1 foci <lb/>co-localizing (Brown et al., 2015; Tarsounas et al., 1999). In contrast, there was no <lb/>difference in the levels of RPA2 (Supplementary Figure 7). In Zcwpw1 -/-males, <lb/>like in the Prdm9 -/-mutant, DSBs form and recruit RPA2, RAD51 and DMC1 in <lb/>similar numbers (M. Li et al., 2019), but fail to repair efficiently, accompanied by <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>asynapsis and meiotic arrest at pseudo-pachytene. Indeed, we observe late <lb/>unrepaired DMC1 foci mainly on asynapsed chromosomes (Supplementary <lb/>Figure 8). <lb/>We also performed analyses of which chromosomes fail to synapse. FISH <lb/>analysis revealed that chromosomes 18 and 19 are most often among these <lb/>asynapsed chromosomes, while grouping of chromosomes based on their size <lb/>revealed some asynapsis of all chromosomes, but at higher levels for shorter <lb/>chromosomes (Supplementary Figure 9). This is similar to results observed for <lb/>infertile hybrid male mice (Bhattacharyya et al., 2013), whose asynapsis is driven <lb/>by lack of binding to the homologous chromosome by PRDM9 (Davies et al., 2016). <lb/>ZCWPW1 is recruited to PRDM9 binding sites in an allele-specific manner <lb/>We previously studied the binding properties of human PRDM9 and established a <lb/>genome-wide map in transfected human mitotic (HEK293T) cells by ChIP-seq <lb/>(Altemose et al., 2017), observing binding to the majority of human meiotic <lb/>recombination hotspots. Based on the presence of H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 <lb/>recognition domains in ZCWPW1, we hypothesized that it would be recruited to <lb/>PRDM9-bound genomic sites, where these marks are deposited upon binding in <lb/>HEK293T cells (Altemose et al., 2017). <lb/>To test this, we co-transfected HEK293T cells with full-length human HA-tagged <lb/>ZCWPW1 and either no other protein, or full-length PRDM9 alleles carrying the <lb/>human or chimpanzee ZF-array, as studied previously (Altemose et al., 2017), and <lb/>then performed ChIP-seq against the ZCWPW1 tag. Confirming the recruitment <lb/>hypothesis, in the presence of human PRDM9 and compared to cells lacking <lb/>human PRDM9, ZCWPW1 shows a strong enrichment at human PRDM9 binding <lb/>sites (Figure 5A, B). Notably, even without PRDM9 we observed sequence-<lb/>specific binding of ZCWPW1 to many sites in the genome (Figure 5C and <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Supplementary Figure 10). However, upon transfection, 91% (98%) of the <lb/>strongest 10,132 (3,016) peaks are PRDM9 binding sites (cf. 7% expected overlap <lb/>with randomised peaks), so PRDM9 is able to strongly reprogram ZCWPW1 <lb/>binding, suggesting that non-PRDM9 peaks are bound more weakly. Because our <lb/>transfection has &lt;100% efficiency (Supplementary Figure 11), some cells <lb/>containing ZCWPW1 will not possess PRDM9, and so it is possible that an even <lb/>greater fraction of ZCWPW1 is redirected to PRDM9 binding sites in cells where <lb/>both proteins are present. <lb/>Importantly, when co-transfecting with a modified version of PRDM9 in <lb/>which the zinc finger array is replaced with that from chimp (which binds different <lb/>locations in the genome (Altemose et al., 2017)), we find that the enrichment at <lb/>human binding sites disappears, but instead ZCWPW1 is enriched at chimp <lb/>PRDM9 binding sites (Figure 5A and Supplementary Figure 12). This <lb/>perturbation experiment provides strong evidence that PRDM9 causes recruitment <lb/>of ZCWPW1 (as opposed to for example independent recruitment of both proteins). <lb/>Notably, the strength of binding of ZCWPW1 at these sites provides a better <lb/>predictor of DSB formation (DMC1 sites) than does PRDM9 binding strength itself <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 13): although we show (see below) that ZCWPW1 is not <lb/>directly involved in DSB positioning, this might suggest involvement of similar <lb/>features to those it recognizes, in recruiting DSBs. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5. (A) Enrichment of ZCWPW1 (with vs without PRDM9) at PRDM9 binding <lb/>sites when co-transfected with PRDM9 with either Human or Chimp Zinc Finger. Q <lb/>= quartile. Human PRDM9 sites are centered and stranded by the motif. (B) <lb/>Profiles and heatmaps of reads around top 25% of individual human (h) PRDM9 <lb/>binding sites (rows). Heatmaps: log-fold change of target (indicated in column titles, <lb/>Methods) vs input, for various labeled target proteins, ordered by human PRDM9. <lb/>ZCWPW1, H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 each become enriched at human PRDM9 <lb/>sites, following (co-)transfection with human PRDM9. (C) ChIP-seq data and <lb/>annotation in a genome plot illustrate the behaviour of ZCWPW1 and other factors. <lb/>ChIP-seq tracks show fragment coverage. Tracks where PRDM9 is present are <lb/>labelled &quot;w/ PRDM9&quot;, and below corresponding tracks with out PRDM9. ZCWPW1 <lb/>binds to Alus, CpG islands and other CpG-rich sequences even in the absence of <lb/>PRDM9. On addition of PRDM9, ZCWPW1 becomes strongly enriched at PRDM9 <lb/>binding locations (center left peak within DIO1). <lb/>We tested whether this recruitment might be mediated by the dual histone <lb/>modifications H3K4me3 and H3K36me3. Consistent with this idea, ZCWPW1 <lb/>binding is positively associated with levels of both H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 marks <lb/>(Supplementary Figures 14 and 15). We examined transcription start sites, which <lb/>possess H3K4me3 at high levels, but lack H3K36me3, observing some ZCWPW1 <lb/>signal at these sites, but with a uniformly lower mean ZCWPW1 enrichment <lb/>compared to those with evidence of PRDM9 binding (and hence both histone <lb/>marks) (Figure 6 and Supplementary Figure 16). Although it is not possible to <lb/>measure H3K4me3 presence/absence in individual cells in our system, even the <lb/>most weakly bound PRDM9 sites -which must therefore possess H3K4me3 in <lb/>only a fraction of cells -show stronger ZCWPW1 enrichment than the strongest <lb/>promoters, which are likely to have near 100% H3K4me3 marking, and possess <lb/>&gt;2-fold more H3K4me3 than even the strongest PRDM9 binding sites. We <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>conclude that H3K4me3 alone endows only relatively weak binding, while PRDM9 <lb/>is therefore able to recruit ZCWPW1 with a much greater efficiency than sites <lb/>marked by H3K4me3 alone, suggesting that both histone modifications might aid <lb/>efficient binding. <lb/>Figure 6. PRDM9 (H3K4me3 and H3K36me3) is a stronger recruiter of <lb/>ZCWPW1 than promoters (H3K4me3 only). H3K4me3 and ZCWPW1 were force <lb/>called in 100bp windows. Each subset is defined as indicated in the legend with <lb/>the additional constraint of requiring input fragment coverage &gt;5 for ZCWPW1 and <lb/>&gt;15 for H3K4me3. For each subset H3K4me3 was split into 25 bins with equal <lb/>number of data points. Horizontal bars: 2 standard errors of the mean. Vertical <lb/>dotted bars: upper and lower quartiles. Grey ribbons show 2 standard errors for a <lb/>Generalized additive model on log(mean H3K4me3 enrichment + 0.1). Dashed <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>black horizontal line highlights that the mean enrichment of the highest bin for <lb/>promoters is similar to that of the lowest bin for PRDM9 bound sites. <lb/>DSBs occur at their normal locations in Zcwpw1 -/-mice but show altered <lb/>DMC1 persistence <lb/>Previous work has shown that Prdm9 -/-mice use a new set of DSB hotspots, <lb/>localising at CpG islands and/or promoter regions (Brick et al., 2012). Given that <lb/>PRDM9 recruits ZCWPW1, one possible function of ZCWPW1 may be that, in turn, <lb/>it recruits the DSB machinery and hence forms part of the causal chain in normal <lb/>positioning of DSBs at PRDM9-specified hotspots. Alternatively, the Zcwpw1 -/-<lb/>mutant phenotypes we observe might reflect a more downstream role. To <lb/>distinguish these hypotheses, we gathered data on DSB positioning and repair <lb/>dynamics genome-wide, by carrying out single stranded DNA (ssDNA) sequencing <lb/>(SSDS) by ChIP-seq against DMC1 (Khil et al., 2012). <lb/>In the Zcwpw1 -/-mutant, we observed normal localisation of DMC1 at the <lb/>expected B6 hotspots for this background, with no activity at Prdm9 -/-hotspots <lb/>(Figure 7A). Moreover, individual wild-type hotspots appear always to be active in <lb/>the Zcwpw1 -/-mutant (Figure 7C): we only fail to see evidence of DMC1 signal in <lb/>a subset of the weakest hotspots, where we are likely to lack statistical power <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 17). Thus DSBs occur in unchanged hotspot regions in <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-males. To check if they occur at the same locations within hotspot <lb/>regions, we leveraged data for SPO11-mapped DSB sites (Lange et al., 2016). <lb/>Specifically, we identified three sets of hotspots whose respective mapped breaks <lb/>occur mainly upstream, central, or downstream of the PRDM9 binding site <lb/>(Methods), and compared their DMC1 ChIP-Seq signal profiles, as well as their <lb/>SPO11 signals (Supplementary Figure 18). This revealed that in the Zcwpw1 -/-<lb/>males, as in the wild-type, DMC1 signals, though broader, mirror this break <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>positioning. Therefore, ZCWPW1 is not required to specify hotspot locations, and <lb/>neither does it strongly influence where DSBs occur within hotspots. <lb/>One perhaps important difference between the Zcwpw1 -/-and wild-type <lb/>DMC1 profiles is that the latter signal grows slightly (up to ~200bp) wider in <lb/>hotspots with increasing PRDM9-induced H3K4me3 (Figure 7B), while this effect <lb/>is absent in the Zcwpw1 -/-case. This might be explained by small differences in <lb/>chromatin accessibility subtly impacting SPO11 locations, DNA end resection <lb/>which generates the 3&apos; ssDNA tail to which DMC1 binds, or downstream <lb/>processing differences altering DMC1 span in the mutant mice. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 7. (A) DSBs occur at normal hotspot locations in the Zcwpw1 -/-mouse. <lb/>Average coverage of reads from DMC1 SSDS ChIP-seq at previously mapped <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>regions (Methods) in B6 WT (left) and Prdm9 -/-(right) mice is shown, centered at <lb/>the PRDM9 motif (left). DMC1 profiles from a WT mouse are shown in red, data <lb/>from (Brick et al., 2012). (B) Normalised DMC1 profile is plotted for WT and <lb/>Zcwpw1 -/-, stratified by H3K4me3. Greyed out lines show the alternative genotype <lb/>for comparison. (C) Altered DMC1 signals in Zcwpw1 -/-mice. Relationship between <lb/>SPO11-oligos (measuring the number of DSBs) vs DMC1 (a measure of the <lb/>number and persistence of DSBs) at each B6 hotspot for WT and Zcwpw1 -/-. Green <lb/>line is y=x for reference. <lb/>Despite very similar DSB locations, we saw much greater, and systematic, <lb/>differences in the strength of the DMC1 signal at individual hotspots. As previously <lb/>(Davies et al., 2016; Khil et al., 2012), we note that observed average DMC1 signal <lb/>strength at a hotspot reflects the product of the frequency at which DSBs occur <lb/>there, and the average length of time DMC1 remains bound to the ssDNA repair <lb/>intermediate, with the latter reflecting DSB processing/repair time. In contrast, <lb/>available SPO11 ChIP-Seq data (Lange et al., 2016) reflect mainly the former, the <lb/>frequency of DSBs. We therefore compared DMC1 and SPO11 signal strength at <lb/>each autosomal and X-chromosome hotspot, in WT and Zcwpw1 -/-mice. In WT <lb/>mice (as seen previously in other mice (Davies et al., 2016) including, albeit <lb/>somewhat more weakly, even sterile hybrids) the non-PAR X-chromosome shows <lb/>a very strong elevation of DMC1 signal strength, reflecting the persistent DMC1 <lb/>foci on this chromosome also visible using microscopy, at DSB sites that eventually <lb/>repair using the sister chromatid. Moreover, in WT mice hotspot heat (with hotter <lb/>hotspots having stronger H3K4me3 signal also) shows a sub-linear relationship <lb/>between SPO11 and DMC1. This is thought to reflect a wider phenomenon of <lb/>faster DSB repair occurring within those hotspots whose homologue is more <lb/>strongly bound by PRDM9, i.e. those hotspots with a stronger H3K4me3 signal in <lb/>the WT mouse (Davies et al., 2016; Hinch et al., 2019; R. Li et al., 2019). The X-<lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>chromosome DMC1 elevation is in a sense an extreme case of slower repair of <lb/>DSBs whose homologue is not PRDM9-bound, because no homologue exists in <lb/>this case. <lb/>However, we see a striking departure in the Zcwpw1 -/-mouse, where the <lb/>X-chromosome behaves similarly to the autosomes in terms of DMC1 vs. SPO11 <lb/>signal strength (Figure 7C). Moreover, we also see a simple linear relationship <lb/>between DMC1 and SPO11 binding in this mouse. These data imply the <lb/>relationship between DMC1 removal and PRDM9 binding is eliminated in this <lb/>mouse, so PRDM9 (whether because ZCWPW1 directly aids the process, or <lb/>indirectly) appears unable to &quot;assist&quot; in homology search in this mouse. Indeed, <lb/>the data imply a widespread perturbation of DSB repair in this mouse, with <lb/>autosomal DMC1 foci persisting as long as those on the X-chromosome. In the <lb/>previously studied Hop2 -/-mouse (Khil et al., 2012; Petukhova et al., 2003; <lb/>Smagulova et al., 2011), we identified a very similar pattern (Supplementary <lb/>Figure 19): in this mouse, DMC1 is loaded onto ssDNA, but DSBs are not repaired <lb/>at all, indicating that DSB repair pathways in Zcwpw1 -/-mice are profoundly altered. <lb/>These results are consistent with, and extend, our microscopy observations <lb/>(Figure 4) that many DSBs persist in the Zcwpw1 -/-mouse, and some may never <lb/>repair. We are unable to say whether DSB repair involves the homologue or not in <lb/>this mouse, but the partial synapsis we observe suggests some repair does likely <lb/>occur. To further understand DMC1 persistence at individual hotspots, we <lb/>estimated the relative DMC1 heat of 9,318 autosomal hotspots in the Zcwpw1 -/-<lb/>mouse, compared to the WT mouse (Methods). Via linear regression, by far the <lb/>best individual predictor of this ratio among H3K4me3, WT DMC1, and SPO11 was <lb/>the level of H3K4me3 (r=0.55, p&lt;10 -15 ; Supplementary Figure 20, while r=0.57 <lb/>when using all 3 predictors together). The average DMC1 ratio changes around 9-<lb/>fold from the most weakly to the most strongly H3K4me3-marked hotspots. <lb/>Therefore, if DMC1 signal changes are indeed explained by slower DSB <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>processing in the Zcwpw1 -/-mouse at hotspots bound strongly by PRDM9, then <lb/>this implies a very strong effect. Whatever the cause, the overall strong correlation <lb/>implies perturbation of DMC1 behaviour is widespread, rather than impacting any <lb/>small subset of hotspots. Moreover, it appears to be mainly controlled by local <lb/>levels of PRDM9 histone modification, in keeping with the evidence that ZCWPW1 <lb/>recognizes this mark at PRDM9-bound sites, on either the broken or (identical) <lb/>homologous chromosome. <lb/>ZCWPW1 binds CpG dinucleotides <lb/>In addition to the strong PRDM9-dependent ZCWPW1 peaks described earlier, <lb/>there are many locations in HEK293T cells at which ZCWPW1 binds, typically more <lb/>weakly, and independently of PRDM9. Indeed, we identified over 800,000 <lb/>ZCWPW1 peaks. Surprisingly, a large proportion of these binding sites overlap Alu <lb/>repeats (Figure 8A and Supplementary Figure 21) (of which there are 1.1 million <lb/>in the human genome (Deininger, 2011)). The weakest ZCWPW1 peaks overlap <lb/>Alus most frequently, whilst the strongest peaks are depleted of Alus relative to <lb/>chance overlap (Figure 8A). <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 8. ZCWPW1 binds CpG-rich sequences such as Alu repeats. (A) Fraction <lb/>of overlap of ZCWPW1 binding peaks with Alus, ordered by enrichment in <lb/>ZCWPW1 binding. ZCWPW1 peaks are binned into 25 bins with equal number of <lb/>data points, and means of both enrichment and overlap are plotted. Solid ribbon <lb/>shows prediction from GAM logistic model. Dotted line shows overall means. (B) <lb/>Rate of overlap of Alu repeats with ZCWPW1 peaks, for Alus with different <lb/>numbers of CpG dinucleotides. (C) The probability of a 300bp window overlapping <lb/>a ZCWPW1 peak increases with increasing CpG count in that window. Windows <lb/>overlapping (by 10bp or more) Alus, other repeats, or CpG islands have been <lb/>excluded. Methylation status of NA is for windows with 0 CpGs. Methylated regions <lb/>are those with a methylated to unmethylated reads ratio of &gt;0.75, and <lb/>unmethylated &lt;0.25 (Methods) (D) Relative proportion of peaks with given <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>numbers of CpGs +/-150bp from peak center. ZCWPW1 peaks are enriched in <lb/>CpGs compared to random peak locations. &apos;Meth&apos;, methylated; &apos;UnMeth&apos;, <lb/>unmethylated; NA, not applicable. <lb/>Because Alus are rich in CpGs (containing &gt;23% of human CpG dinucleotides, <lb/>with deamination depleting CpGs in older Alus (Luo et al., 2014)), we tested if <lb/>binding correlates with CpG presence/absence. Indeed, the binding of ZCWPW1 <lb/>to Alus depends on the presence of CpGs, which are mainly methylated <lb/>(Gaysinskaya et al., 2018): Alus with no CpGs were bound at a rate lower than by <lb/>chance, but almost all Alus containing 10-20 CpGs are bound (Figure 8B). This <lb/>dependence is not Alu-specific: even outside genomic repeats, 300-bp regions with <lb/>zero CpGs have negligible probability of overlapping a ZCWPW1 binding site, while <lb/>the overlap probability rises to &gt;50% for regions containing 10 or more CpGs, <lb/>suggesting CpGs are essential for PRDM9-independent ZCWPW1 binding (Figure <lb/>8C,D and Supplementary Figure 22). ZCWPW1 appears to have greater affinity <lb/>for methylated CpG pairs, but retains some affinity even for non-methylated <lb/>regions. This binding mode was unexpected a priori, and does not appear to be <lb/>easily explained by patterns of H3K4me3/H3K36me3 in the genome, which do not <lb/>concentrate as strongly in these regions. <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>Here we exploited previous work on single-cell transcript profiling of mouse testis, <lb/>which has established spatio-temporal (and likely functional) components of co-<lb/>expressed genes (Jung et al., 2019), to identify co-factors relevant to PRDM9 <lb/>function in specification of recombination hotspots and DSB repair during meiosis. <lb/>We show that the histone methylation reader ZCWPW1, which is both highly co-<lb/>expressed and co-evolving with PRDM9, is recruited by PRDM9 to its binding sites, <lb/>likely mediated through the recognition of the dual H3K4me3-H3K36me3 histone <lb/>mark PRDM9 deposits. <lb/>While we find co-evolution of ZCWPW1 with PRDM9, consistent with <lb/>proteins functioning in the same pathway, this appears to depend on particular <lb/>domains. ZCWPW1 shows weaker conservation among species outside the CW <lb/>and PWWP domains, suggesting these are of high importance, and co-occurs with <lb/>PRDM9 in species where the latter possesses a SET domain predicted to retain <lb/>catalytic activity for H3K4me3/H3K36me3, which the domains of ZCWPW1 are <lb/>predicted to recognise, strongly suggesting a partnership totally dependent on this <lb/>recognition. This co-occurrence can persist, even in species where PRDM9 is not <lb/>believed to position DSBs, suggesting the co-operation between these proteins <lb/>does not completely depend on this aspect of PRDM9&apos;s function. Interestingly, <lb/>such a SET domain of PRDM9 mainly occurs when PRDM9 possesses a SSXRD <lb/>domain, which in other proteins (Banito et al., 2018) recruits CXXC2 which binds <lb/>to CpG islands -whether this connects to our observation of a potential CpG-<lb/>binding domain in ZCWPW1, and CpG-binding behaviour ex-vivo, remains to be <lb/>explored. <lb/>Others have recently reported phenotyping of Zcwpw1 -/-mice (M. Li et al., <lb/>2019), and although our KO is different, we observe similar patterns of infertility in <lb/>males, and results consistent with gradual fertility decline in females, towards <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>sterility from 8 months onwards. Why females deficient for ZCWPW1 are (at least <lb/>initially) fertile is unknown, but resembles sexual dimorphism in loss-of-function <lb/>mutants for other meiotic genes involved in homologous recombination, where <lb/>females exhibit a milder fertility phenotype (Cahoon and Libuda, 2019; Morelli and <lb/>Cohen, 2005; Zhang et al., 2019). However we observe a distinct intracellular <lb/>localisation of ZCWPW1 from that reported by (M. Li et al., 2019): while we also <lb/>detect ZCWPW1 as a diffuse nuclear signal across the nucleus (though excluding <lb/>the chromocenters) and localisation to the XY body in pachytene, we see an <lb/>additional signal in mid-pachytene to diplotene cells at the ends of the <lb/>synaptonemal complex. This might reflect the specificity of our polyclonal antibody, <lb/>which is raised against the full-length mouse protein vs a monoclonal antibody <lb/>raised against a C-terminal region, hence recognising a wider spectrum of <lb/>ZCWPW1. Given that the Zcwpw1 -/-mouse arrests in early pachytene, it is not <lb/>possible to test later stages, so a caveat is that we cannot completely exclude off-<lb/>target antibody recognition. If accurate, the late-stage localisation of ZCWPW1 at <lb/>subtelomeric regions resembles other proteins (Speedy A, CDK2, TFR1, SUN1, <lb/>TERB1/2, MAJIN, and KASH), which form a complex tethering the telomeres to <lb/>the nuclear envelope to facilitate chromosome movement and pairing -essential <lb/>for synapsis and fertility (Ashley et al., 2001; Ding et al., 2007; Horn et al., 2013; <lb/>Shibuya et al., 2014; Tu et al., 2017). However, no evidence of impaired telomeric <lb/>attachment was reported in the other Zcwpw1 -/-, based on normal localisation of <lb/>TRF1 (M. Li et al., 2019). <lb/>We find, using an ex vivo system, that ZCWPW1 is strongly recruited to <lb/>PRDM9-bound sites, in an allele-specific manner, dependent on the level of <lb/>H3K4me3 and H3K36me3 that PRDM9 deposits, and most likely due to recognition <lb/>of these marks by the CW and PWWP domains of ZCWPW1. Li and colleagues <lb/>(M. Li et al., 2019) showed co-immunoprecipitation of H3K4me3 with ZCWPW1, <lb/>but our results imply that PRDM9 recruits ZCWPW1 much more strongly than <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>H3K4me3 alone, further suggesting that the combination of histone marks is key <lb/>for ZCWPW1&apos;s recognition of PRDM9 sites. Indeed in cells with PRDM9, the <lb/>strongest ZCWPW1 binding sites are almost all PRDM9-bound sites. <lb/>Although it has been suggested that ZCWPW1 might recruit the DSB <lb/>machinery (M. Li et al., 2019; Spruce et al., 2019), our data imply DSB formation <lb/>and positioning are largely unaffected by loss of ZCWPW1 and occur at PRDM9-<lb/>bound hotspots. Moreover DMC1, RAD51 and RPA2 loading also appear normal <lb/>(Figure 7A and (M. Li et al., 2019)), but asynapsis and failure to remove DMC1 <lb/>imply a profound downstream impact. Indeed most hotspots show perturbed DMC1 <lb/>heats consistent with DSB repair delays proportional to their cis H3K4me3 levels, <lb/>i.e. driven by expected WT ZCWPW1 recruitment levels at each hotspot <lb/>(Supplementary Figure 15). ZCWPW1 therefore offers a (thus far) unique protein, <lb/>linking PRDM9 binding with its downstream functions (Davies et al., 2016; Hinch <lb/>et al., 2019; R. Li et al., 2019) in aiding rapid DSB processing/repair at hotspots <lb/>whose homologue is bound by PRDM9. <lb/>PRDM9 is thought to aid homology search/chromosome pairing by such <lb/>binding to the homologous chromosome, and hybrids where hotspots are highly <lb/>&quot;asymmetric&quot; (i.e. the homologues are not bound at the sites where DSBs occur, <lb/>due to evolutionary hotspot erosion) show multiple features identical to Zcwpw1 -/-<lb/>mice. These include asynapsis (particularly of shorter chromosomes with fewer <lb/>DSBs), persistent DMC1 foci (at the asymmetric hotspots), and complete sterility <lb/>in males only. In Zcwpw1 -/-mice, we infer that the level of PRDM9 binding to the <lb/>homologue now makes no difference to DSB persistence, so these mice generally <lb/>behave exactly as if all hotspots are completely asymmetric. Thus, a parsimonious <lb/>explanation of our findings is that ZCWPW1 functions by attaching to PRDM9-<lb/>bound sites, so as to recognize the homologous chromosome at DSB sites. This <lb/>might e.g. lead to their recruitment to the chromosomal axis (where DMC1 foci are <lb/>found), for potential use as the homologous repair template in DSB repair, perhaps <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>mediated by the SCP-1-like domain identified in some orthologous copies. Given <lb/>we observe ZCWPW1 throughout the nucleus in early meiosis, such recruitment <lb/>would likely be transient in nature. Alternatively, ZCWPW1&apos;s part in mediating <lb/>PRDM9&apos;s downstream roles might also depend (or even, depend only) on it binding <lb/>the chromosome on which DSBs occur. <lb/>Given that we still observe some synapsis, similar to Prdm9 -/-mice, we <lb/>suggest that a &quot;back-up&quot; mechanism, which is independent of PRDM9 binding <lb/>level, is acting to attempt homology search/chromosome pairing in Zcwpw1 -/-mice. <lb/>Some such mechanism is necessary, to repair DSBs happening within a subset of <lb/>hotspots that are asymmetric due to naturally occurring variation (as seen in e.g. <lb/>humans and heterozygous mice). If our observed &gt;9-fold changes in relative DMC1 <lb/>levels for strongly vs. weakly bound hotspots purely reflect increased DMC1 <lb/>persistence, it might be this mechanism is greatly slower than the PRDM9-<lb/>dependent pathway for wild-type mice. In turn, this could explain many -or all -of <lb/>the downstream phenotypes in these mice, as consequences of delayed homology <lb/>search. <lb/>The simplest explanation of our observation that ZCWPW1 binds in a CpG <lb/>dependent manner ex vivo is that these sites might be directly bound by a methyl-<lb/>CpG binding domain (MBD) putatively observed in the human, mouse, and <lb/>coelacanth Zcwpw1, among others. Alternatively, recruitment might be indirect, <lb/>with ZCWPW1 forming a complex with an MBD containing protein, e.g. SETDB1 <lb/>which is expressed in HEK293 cells, co-expressed with ZCWPW1 and PRDM9 <lb/>(Jung et al., 2019; Schultz et al., 2002), and interacts with several other identified <lb/>PRDM9 partner proteins (Mulligan et al., 2008; Parvanov et al., 2017). Given the <lb/>precisely regulated developmental changes in methylation status, <lb/>ZCWPW1/PRDM9 protein abundance, and chromatin during meiosis <lb/>(Gaysinskaya et al., 2018; Seisenberger et al., 2013) it is unclear whether <lb/>ZCWPW1 will also weakly bind Alus in vivo. However, if CpG dinucleotides do <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>retain weak in vivo ZCWPW1 binding affinity, and given that CpG methylation is <lb/>associated with transposons, it is interesting to speculate whether ZCWPW1 might <lb/>play a role in germline transposon recognition, silencing, or facilitate repair of DSBs <lb/>occurring within transposable elements. <lb/>Zcwpw1 possesses a paralogue, Zcwpw2, which is also co-expressed in <lb/>testis with Prdm9 (although at a lower level), possesses both CW and PWWP <lb/>domains, and has been shown to be able to recognise H3K4me3 at least (Liu et <lb/>al., 2016). Further studies are required to investigate what function if any Zcwpw2 <lb/>has in meiosis. One interesting possibility is that Zcwpw2, rather than Zcwpw1, <lb/>might act to help position DSBs -if so, its low abundance relative to Zcwpw1 would <lb/>be analogous to the low number of DSBs per meiosis (~300) relative to the number <lb/>of PRDM9 binding sites. <lb/>In this study we have shown that Zcwpw1 co-evolves with Prdm9, binds to <lb/>sites marked by PRDM9, and is required for the proper processing, removal of <lb/>DMC1, and repair of DSBs. How exactly it mediates repair, if for example by <lb/>recruitment of other proteins, remains to be determined. This study also further <lb/>demonstrates that genes co-expressed with PRDM9 represent a rich source of <lb/>undiscovered meiotic genes, with important functional implications for <lb/>recombination, meiosis progression and ultimately fertility. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Orthologue Alignment <lb/>We identified ZCWPW1 orthologues across species using four data sources: first, <lb/>we used BlastP (blast.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov), against the full-length human reference <lb/>ZCWPW1 sequence (identifier NP_060454.3, against nr_v5 database) storing the <lb/>top 1000 hits using the default parameters (set 1). Secondly, we downloaded the <lb/>two <lb/>sets <lb/>of <lb/>Ensembl <lb/>identified <lb/>ZCWPW1 <lb/>orthologues <lb/>(against <lb/>ENSMUSG00000037108.13; ensembl.org, 105 orthologues), and identified NCBI <lb/>ZCWPW1 protein orthologues (146 species, www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov). Initial <lb/>examination of identified orthologues revealed conservation among orthologues <lb/>mainly of the ZW and PWWP domains; therefore, to find additional orthologues <lb/>sequences we performed tBLASTn (against the nr/nt nucleotide collection 17 th July <lb/>2019; top 1000 hits) to identify orthologues in the NCBI nucleotide database, to the <lb/>partial sequence (amino acids 256-339 of the reference sequence NP_060454.3), <lb/>corresponding to the ZW and PWWP domains of ZCWPW1. Protein sequences <lb/>were then aligned against full-length human ZCWPW1 (NP_060454.3) using <lb/>BLASTP2.9 (Altschul et al., 2005, 1997) We obtained taxonomy information from <lb/>the <lb/>folder <lb/>https://ftp.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pub/taxonomy/new_taxdump/, <lb/>for <lb/>comparisons among species and between ZCWPW1 and PRDM9. <lb/>Previous work has identified highly conserved &quot;KWR&quot; and &quot;PWWP&quot; <lb/>patterns among ZW and PWWP domains, respectively (Fahu He et al., 2010; Qin <lb/>and Min, 2014). We thus identified an initial set of &quot;clear&quot; ZCWPW1 orthologues, <lb/>and then used these to identify further less precise matches. &quot;Clear&quot; orthologues <lb/>are defined as proteins within set 1 containing perfect matches to both these <lb/>sequences, and such that in the NCBI alignment, at least 39% of each sequence <lb/>aligns to the human protein, and conversely. This second step is required to avoid <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>spurious matches to e.g. ZCWPW2, which overlaps 19% of ZCWPW1, by requiring <lb/>&gt;2-fold this match length; although several ZCWPW2 copies are in our initial list, <lb/>no gene annotated as most similar to ZCWPW2 attains the 39% overlap. For <lb/>proteins within the &quot;clear&quot; set, we identified the longest alignment for each given <lb/>species, resulting in 136 species with a likely ZCWPW1 orthologue. This initial <lb/>screen identified three groups of fish, placental mammals, marsupials, <lb/>monotremes and reptiles as likely possessing ZCWPW1, similar to our final <lb/>conclusions. Moreover, it defined amino acids 247-428 in the human reference <lb/>sequence as being conserved in the alignment (at most 1 sequence not aligning), <lb/>including the annotated ZCW and PWWP domains. <lb/>Using this initial set, we identified additional orthologous sequences and <lb/>refined our results, by identifying conserved bases within ZCWPW1. Specifically, <lb/>we divided the 136 species into major clades, as in (Baker et al., 2017), and gave <lb/>each sequence a weighting so that the overall weight for each clade was the same <lb/>(so e.g. each Placental mammal sequence was downweighted as this clade was <lb/>over-represented). Within the consistently aligned region 247-428, we calculated <lb/>the overall weighted probability of each of the 20 amino acids, or a gap (adding 10 -<lb/>5 to exclude zero weights). This identified 31 completely conserved amino acids, <lb/>and 78 amino acids whose entropy was below 1 (equivalent to 2 amino acids, <lb/>having equal probability, so implying one amino acid present &gt;50% of the time). <lb/>Finally, we defined ZCWPW1 orthologues as those sequences matching at least <lb/>90% of those 31 perfectly conserved bases which were aligned, and aligning to at <lb/>least 50% of these bases (this last condition allows for inclusion of incomplete <lb/>sequencing or protein assembly). We note that while this 90% condition is arbitrary, <lb/>by definition all annotated orthologues exceed this threshold, while thresholds <lb/>below ~70-80% are exceeded by orthologues of ZCWPW2 among other genes, <lb/>offering some justification. Nonetheless, it is worth pointing out that our analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>does not rule out the existence of more poorly conserved ZCWPW1 copies in more <lb/>distantly related species. This approach identified a final set of 167 genes, which <lb/>we annotated as likely ZCWPW1 orthologues and used for the majority of results. <lb/>For each ZCWPW1 orthologue, we also identified the taxonomic relationship of the <lb/>closest species possessing such a PRDM9 copy (Supplementary Table 1). We <lb/>also reciprocally annotated each PRDM9 copy previously identified (Baker et al., <lb/>2017) according to the closest species also possessing ZCWPW1 <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). <lb/>Our analyses revealed a relationship between ZCWPW1 predicted <lb/>functional domains and PRDM9 histone modifications. Therefore, we identified <lb/>additional potential conserved sites by identifying perfectly conserved bases <lb/>among those species possessing both ZCWPW1 and PRDM9 orthologues, and <lb/>where three key SET domain catalytic amino acids within PRDM9 are intact, <lb/>meaning PRDM9 is predicted to have normal histone modification activity (Baker <lb/>et al., 2017). This identified a slightly larger number of conserved amino acids (37). <lb/>Only eight of these varied in any of the 167 species with a potential ZCWPW1 <lb/>orthologue: 260, 404 and 411 (in two Xenopus frogs, with 411 also in white-headed <lb/>capuchin), 19 and 22 (in three canines), 25 (in Ocelot gecko), 257 (in Anolis lizard <lb/>and in Wombat), 325 (in elephantfish). While these changes might alter ZCWPW1 <lb/>function, the true behaviour of ZCWPW1 is uncertain in these cases, though it is <lb/>interesting that canids and frogs represent clades that all appear to have lost <lb/>PRDM9, and possess multiple, clustered, amino acid changes. <lb/>Domain Search <lb/>pDomThreader (Lobley et al., 2009), was used via the PSIPRED server <lb/>(http://bioinf.cs.ucl.ac.uk/psipred/) on the following uniProt amino acid <lb/>sequences <lb/>(Q9H0M4|ZCPW1_HUMAN, <lb/>Q6IR42|ZCPW1_MOUSE, <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>E2RFJ2|E2RFJ2_CANLF, <lb/>M3XJ39_LATCH, <lb/>A0A3S5ZP38_BOVIN, <lb/>M3WDY6_FELCA, and G3ULT5|G3ULT5_LOXAF) all of which identified a <lb/>match to 1ub1A00 in the C terminal section after the PWWP domain, except <lb/>in LOXAF in which this match was slightly below the p-value threshold of <lb/>0.001. <lb/>SCP1 prediction used NCBI conserved domain search server <lb/>(https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/Structure/cdd/wrpsb.cgi?) with the uniProt <lb/>amino <lb/>acid <lb/>sequences <lb/>Q9H0M4|ZCPW1_HUMAN <lb/>and <lb/>Q6IR42|ZCPW1_MOUSE. <lb/>Mice and genotyping <lb/>KO mice for Zcwpw1 (C57BL/6N-Zcwpw1em1(IMPC)Tcp) were generated by the <lb/>Toronto Centre for Phenogenomics (Canada). A 1485-bp deletion on chromosome <lb/>5 spanning exons 5 to 7 of Zcwpw1 (chr5:137799545-13780101029) was <lb/>engineered <lb/>by <lb/>CRISPR/Cas9 <lb/>using <lb/>guide <lb/>RNAs <lb/>5&apos;-<lb/>GACTGCACTCACGGCCATCT-3&apos;. The frameshift deletion introduces a stop <lb/>codon in Exon 8, leading to a predicted unstable short truncated 492bp transcript. <lb/>Mice were genotyped at the Zcwpw1 locus using the following primers, and <lb/>standard <lb/>cycling <lb/>conditions: <lb/>KO <lb/>allele-Forward, <lb/>5&apos;-<lb/>CACAGGCTCATGTATGTTTGTCTC-3&apos;; <lb/>KO <lb/>allele-Reverse, <lb/>5&apos;-<lb/>CTGCTTCGTCCTCTTTCCTTATCTC-3&apos;; <lb/>WT <lb/>allele-Forward, <lb/>5&apos;-<lb/>TGCCACCACACTTCATTTGT-3&apos;; <lb/>WT <lb/>allele-Reverse <lb/>CCTGTTTCCTTCCCAACTCA-3&apos;. The deletion was verified by direct Sanger <lb/>sequencing of the KO genotyping PCR product (Source Bioscience, UK), following <lb/>purification with the QIAquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen). Sequence analysis <lb/>was carried out using Chromas LITE (version 2.1.1). <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<body>KO mice for Prdm9 were described previously (Hayashi et al., 2005; Mihola <lb/>et al., 2019) and obtained from the RIKEN BioResource Research Center in Japan <lb/>(strain name B6.129P2-Prdm9&lt;tm1Ymat&gt;, strain number RBRC05145). Mice <lb/>were genotyped at the Prdm9 locus using the following primers, and standard <lb/>cycling conditions: WT allele-Forward 5&apos;-AGGAATCTTCCTTCCTTGCTGTCG-3&apos;; <lb/>WT allele-Reverse 5&apos;-ATTTCCCTGTATCTTCTTCAGGACT-3&apos;; KO allele-Reverse <lb/>5&apos;-CGCCATTCAGGCTGCGCAACTGTT-3&apos;. <lb/>All animal experiments received local ethical review approval from the <lb/>University of Oxford Animal Welfare and Ethical Review Body (Clinical Medicine <lb/>board) and were carried out in accordance with the UK Home Office Animals <lb/>(Scientific Procedures) Act 1986. <lb/>Fertility measurements <lb/>Fertility was assessed in mice ranging from 9 to 12 weeks of age, either by mating <lb/>with WT littermates and recording the average litter size and frequency, or by <lb/>measuring paired testes weight (normalized to lean body weight), sperm count (per <lb/>paired epididymides) and chromosome synapsis rate (by immunostaining of <lb/>pachytene spermatocytes) in males. Lean body weight was measured using the <lb/>EchoMRI-100 Small Animal Body Composition Analyzer. <lb/>Immunostaining of spermatocytes <lb/>Mouse testis chromosome spreads were prepared using surface spreading (Barchi <lb/>et al., 2008; Peters et al., 1997) and immunostained as previously described <lb/>(Davies et al., 2016) The following primary antibodies were used: custom <lb/>ZCWPW1 rabbit antiserum (1:100), mouse anti-SYCP3 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology <lb/>sc-74569, D-1) or biotinylated rabbit anti-SYCP3 (Novus NB300-232), rabbit anti-<lb/></body>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<body>DMC1 (Santa Cruz Biotechnology sc-74569, D-1), rabbit anti-HORMAD2 (Santa <lb/>Cruz Biotechnology sc-82192), mouse anti-RAD51 (Abcam ab88572), rabbit anti-<lb/>RPA2 (Abcam ab10359), mouse (Millipore 05-636, clone JBW301) or chicken <lb/>(Orbit orb195374, discontinued) anti-phospho γ-H2AX and Alexa Fluor 488-, 647-<lb/>or 594-conjugated secondary antibodies against rabbit, mouse or chicken IgG <lb/>(ThermoFisher Scientific), as well as avidin 647 (ThermoFisher Scientific) were <lb/>used to detect the primary antibodies. Images were acquired using either a BX-51 <lb/>upright wide-field microscope equipped with a JAI CVM4 B&amp;W fluorescence CCD <lb/>camera and operated by the Leica Cytovision Genus software, or a Leica DM6B <lb/>microscope for epifluorescence, equipped with a DFC 9000Gt B&amp;W fluorescence <lb/>CCD camera, and operated via the Leica LASX software. Image analysis was <lb/>carried out using Fiji (ImageJ-win64). <lb/>FISH <lb/>Following immunostaining of spermatocytes, telomeres were labelled using the <lb/>Telomere PNA FISH Kit/Cy3 (Agilent), following the manufacturer&apos;s instructions, <lb/>but without protease treatment. For the identification of chromosome 18, BAC <lb/>RP24-144B10 (CHORI, BACPAC Resource Center) was labelled with the Abbot <lb/>Molecular Nick Translation kit, and applied to the immunostained spermatocytes. <lb/>The hybridisation and signal detection were carried out using standard techniques. <lb/>Plasmids <lb/>Constructs encoding full-length human (h) or chimp (c) PRDM9 with a C-terminal <lb/>V5 or N-terminal YFP tag for expression in mammalian cells (pLENTI CMV/TO <lb/>Puro DEST backbone vector, Addgene plasmid # 17293; Campeau et al., 2009) <lb/>were described previously (Altemose et al., 2017). Constructs encoding full-length <lb/></body>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<body>human (h) and mouse (m) ZCWPW1 for expression in mammalian cells were <lb/>purchased from Genescript (hZCWPW1 cDNA with a C-terminal HA tag in <lb/>pCDNA3.1; clone ID OHu16813) and Origene (mZCWPW1 cDNA with a FLAG-<lb/>Myc dual tag in pCMV6-Entry; clone ID MR209594), respectively. For expression <lb/>in E. Coli, full-length mZCWPW1 cDNA was subcloned into the pET22b(+) vector <lb/>(Novagen) with a C-terminal poly-His tag. <lb/>ZCWPW1 antibody production <lb/>pET22b-mZCWPW1-His construct was transformed into BL21 (DE3) E.Coli cells <lb/>(Invitrogen). Bacterial cultures were grown to a density with O.D600~0.7, and <lb/>expression of recombinant His-tagged ZCWPW1 protein was induced overnight at <lb/>20°C by addition of IPTG to 0.5mM. The protein was purified using Talon metal <lb/>affinity resin, according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions (Takara). Further <lb/>purification was carried out by size exclusion chromatography (Superdex HiLoad <lb/>200 16/60, GE Life Sciences). Western Blot validation was carried out as described <lb/>previously (Altemose et al., 2017), using mouse anti-human ZCWPW1 (SIGMA <lb/>SAB1409478) and mouse anti-polyhistidine (SIGMA H1029). The purified protein <lb/>was used to immunize 2 rabbits (Eurogentec, Belgium), and the resulting immune <lb/>antisera were tested against the recombinant antigen by ELISA (Eurogentec), and <lb/>the endogenous protein in mouse testes from WT and KO mice (data not shown), <lb/>alongside the preimmune sera. <lb/>Cell line, transfection and immunofluorescence staining <lb/>Human embryonic kidney (HEK) 293T cells were cultured and transfected using <lb/>Fugene HD as previously described (Altemose et al., 2017). High and comparable <lb/>expression of the target proteins was verified by immunofluorescence staining of <lb/>duplicate transfected cultures before proceeding to ChIP. PRDM9 expression was <lb/></body>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body>visualized either directly from live cells through YFP fluorescence, or by <lb/>immunofluorescence staining of fixed cells using rabbit anti-V5 (Abcam ab9116) <lb/>as described previously (Altemose et al., 2017). ZCWPW1-HA was detected by <lb/>immunostaining as above, using rabbit anti-HA (Abcam ab9110, 1:100). The <lb/>fraction of cells co-expressing ZCWPW1-HA and PRDM9-V5 was determined by <lb/>co-staining with both antibodies, as above (Supplementary Figure 11). <lb/>ChIP-seq <lb/>DMC1 ChIP-seq data from WT B6 mouse testis were generated previously (Brick <lb/>et al., 2012). H3K4me3 ChIP-seq data was generated previously (Davies et al., <lb/>2016). <lb/>ChIP <lb/>ChIP against ZCWPW1-HA, (h/cPRDM9-V5) was carried out from transfected <lb/>HEK293T cells as previously described (Davies et al., 2016); (Altemose et al., <lb/>2017) were crosslinked for 10min in 1% formaldehyde, the reaction was quenched <lb/>for 5min by the addition of glycine to a final concentration of 125mM, and the cells <lb/>were washed twice in cold PBS. The cell pellet was resuspended in cold sonication <lb/>buffer (50mM Tris-HCl pH8, 10mM EDTA, 1% SDS) supplemented with protease <lb/>inhibitors (Complete, Roche), and chromatin was sheared to an average size of <lb/>200-500bp by sonication for 35 cycles (30s ON/30s OFF) using a Bioruptor Twin <lb/>(Diagenode). After centrifugation for 10min at 20,000g, 4°C, the sonicate was pre-<lb/>cleared for 2h at 4°C with 65μl of Dynabeads™ M-280 sheep anti-rabbit IgG (Life <lb/>Technologies) and a 1% input chromatin sample was set aside. The rest of the <lb/>sample was diluted 10 fold in ChIP buffer (16.7mM Tris pH8 1.2mM EDTA, 167mM <lb/>NaCl, 1.1% Triton X-100) supplemented with protease inhibitors, and incubated <lb/>overnight at 4°C with 5μl of either Abcam rabbit antibody: anti-HA (ab9110), anti-<lb/></body>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>H3K4me3 (ab8580), anti-H3K36me3 (ab9050). Immunocomplexes were washed <lb/>once with each of low salt buffer (20 mM Tris pH8, 150 mM NaCl, 1% Triton X-<lb/>100, 0.1% SDS, 2mM EDTA), high salt buffer (20 mM Tris pH8, 500 mM NaCl, 1% <lb/>Triton X-100, 0.1% SDS, 2mM EDTA), LiCl buffer (10mM Tris pH8, 0.25M LiCl, 1% <lb/>NP-40, 1% sodium deoxycholate, 1mM EDTA) and TE buffer (10mM Tris pH8, <lb/>1mM EDTA) and eluted from the beads in 100 mM NaHCO3, 1% SDS for 30 min <lb/>at 65°C with shaking. Both input and ChIP samples were reverse crosslinked <lb/>overnight at 65°C in the presence of 200mM NaCl, and proteins were digested for <lb/>90 min at 45°C by addition of proteinase K (0.3ug/ul final concentration). DNA was <lb/>purified using the MinElute reaction cleanup kit (QIAGEN), and quantified using <lb/>the dsDNA HS assay kit and a Qubit® 2.0 Fluorometer (Invitrogen). <lb/>ChIP against DMC1 was performed from Zcwpw1 -/-testes using the <lb/>published method by (Khil et al., 2012) with some modifications listed here. <lb/>Chromatin shearing was carried out in 20mM Tris-HCl pH8, 2mM EDTA, 0.1% SDS <lb/>using a Bioruptor Pico sonicator (Diagenode) for 4 cycles of 15s ON/45s OFF. ChIP <lb/>was performed in 10mM Tris-HCl pH8, 1mM EDTA, 0.1% Sodium Deoxycholate, <lb/>1% Triton X-100, 500mM NaCl using 5μg of mouse anti-DMC1 2H12/4 (Novus <lb/>NB100-2617) pre-bound to 50μl of Dynabeads™ M-280 sheep anti-mouse IgG <lb/>(Life Technologies) . <lb/>Sequencing <lb/>ZCWPW1 ChIP and input libraries from transfected cells were prepared by the <lb/>Oxford Genomics Centre at the Wellcome Centre for Human Genetics (Oxford, <lb/>UK) using the Nextera DNA Library Prep Kit and established Illumina protocols, <lb/>and sequenced on a HiSeq 4000 platform (75bp paired end reads, 48 million <lb/>reads/sample). DMC1 ChIP libraries from Zcwpw1 -/-testes were prepared and <lb/>sequenced as described previously (Davies et al., 2016) on an Illumina HiSeq2500 <lb/>platform (Rapid Run, 51bp paired end reads, 110 million reads/sample). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<body>Read Mapping <lb/>For the HEK293 experiments, reads were mapped to either hg38 (NCBI&apos;s <lb/>GCA_000001405.15_GRCh38_no_alt_plus_hs38d1_analysis_set.fna.gz) using <lb/>bwa mem (version 0.7.17-r1188) (Li, 2013). Duplicates were removed using <lb/>picard&apos;s markDuplicates (version 2.20.4-SNAPSHOT). Unmapped, mate <lb/>unmapped, non primary alignment, failing platform, and low MAPQ reads were <lb/>removed using samtools with parameters &quot;-q 30 -F 3852 -f 2 -u&quot; (version 1.9 (using <lb/>htslib 1.9)). Other unmapped reads and secondary alignments were removed using <lb/>samtools fixmate. Fragment position bed files were created using bedtools <lb/>bamtobed (v2.28.0). <lb/>For the DMC1 mouse experimental data, we processed the data following the <lb/>algorithm provided by (Khil et al., 2012) to map the reads to the mouse mm10 <lb/>reference genome (Lunter and Goodson, 2011), and obtain type I reads. <lb/>Peak Calling <lb/>We called DMC1 peaks, as described previously (Davies et al., 2016). For the <lb/>HEK293 experiments, peaks for ZCWPW1, PRDM9, H3K4me3, and H3k36me3 <lb/>were called using a peak caller previously described (Davies et al., 2016) and <lb/>available at https://github.com/MyersGroup/PeakCaller. Single base peaks were <lb/>called with parameters pthresh 10 -6 and peakminsep 250 on 22 autosomes. For <lb/>each experiment, we used available IP replicates, and sequenced input DNA to <lb/>estimate background, in calling peaks. Most of our analyses refer to these peaks, <lb/>except that Figures 5A and B plot the change in ZCWPW1 occupancy following <lb/>PRDM9 transfection, for either the chimp or human PRDM9 alleles. To estimate <lb/></body>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			<body>ZCWPW1 levels with vs. without PRDM9, we called ZCWPW1 peaks in HEK293T <lb/>cells also transfected with PRDM9 as before, but now replacing the &quot;input&quot; lane <lb/>with the IP data for ZCWPW1 in cells not transfected with PRDM9. Supplementary <lb/>Figure 13 also uses this measure, of ZCWPW1 recruitment attributable to PRDM9 <lb/>binding, to predict DMC1 levels, while Supplementary Figure 21 (right panel) <lb/>checks that changes in ZCWPW1 occupancy occur largely at PRDM9-bound sites. <lb/>We analysed previously published H3K4me3 and SPO11 read data (Davies et al., <lb/>2016; Lange et al., 2016). <lb/>Enrichment Profiles for HEK293T experiments <lb/>Peaks were filtered if: center within 2.5kb of PRDM9 independent H3K4me3 <lb/>(promoters), input coverage &lt;=5, in top 5 by likelihood, greater than 99.9 percentile <lb/>input coverage. For human PRDM9 peaks the PRDM9 motif position (Altemose et <lb/>al., 2017) was inferred using the getmotifs function in MotifFinder within the 300bp <lb/>region around the peak (with parameters alpha=0.2, maxits=10, seed=42, <lb/>stranded_prior=T), and peaks were recentered and stranded at these locations. <lb/>Peaks within 4kb of one another are removed to avoid double counting. Mean <lb/>coverage was calculated with bwtool 1.0 using the aggregate command with <lb/>parameters &quot;-fill=0 -firstbase&quot; at a width of +/-2kb. Each profile was normalised by <lb/>the total coverage of all of the fragments as well as by the input profile. Random <lb/>profiles were created using bedtools random with 10,000 locations, with seed <lb/>72346, and were also filtered such that non were within 4kb of one another. <lb/>DSB Profiles <lb/>Mapped type 1 reads were filtered by removing non-canonical chromosomes (with <lb/>underscores in names), sex chromosomes, and mitochondrial reads. Bedgraphs <lb/></body>

			<page>43 <lb/></page>

			<body>were converted to bigWig format using UCSC bedGraphToBigWig v4. Profiles <lb/>were created using bwtool 1.0 using the aggregate command with parameters <lb/>5000:2000 and -fill=0. B6 wild type hotspot locations were filtered to remove non-<lb/>autosomal chromosomes, retain only B6 allele hotspots, and remove hotspots with <lb/>PRDM9-independent H3K4me3. Prdm9 -/-hotspots were filtered to remove X <lb/>chromosome. Motif centered coordinates were used for Wild type hotspots. To <lb/>normalise background signal, the mean signal between -5000 and -3000 was <lb/>subtracted from each strand-mouse combination. Mean coverage was normalised <lb/>by the sum of coverage over each strand-mouse combination across both WT and <lb/>KO locations. <lb/>Mapping of Alu CpGs <lb/>Alu locations were downloaded from UCSC tables and filtered for Alu repeats with <lb/>a width between 250 and 350bp. DNA sequence was extracted from the genome <lb/>(Ensembl 95 h38 primary assembly) at these locations using the bedtools getfasta <lb/>command and CpG dinucleotides were counted using &apos;stringr::str_locate_all&apos; <lb/>command in R. <lb/>DMC1 Prediction using ZCWPW1 and PRDM9 binding strength <lb/>PRDM9-dependent ZCWPW1 was force-called at the human PRDM9 peaks. <lb/>DMC1 sites are from (Pratto et al., 2014) (GSE59836) and were subsetted to &apos;AorB&apos; <lb/>autosomal peaks with a width less than 3kb. These peaks were then trimmed to a <lb/>maximum of 800bp before overlapping with PRDM9 peaks to create a binary target <lb/>variable. Regions with input coverage &lt;=5 in either predictor were removed in <lb/>addition to outliers with input &gt; 200 and or Zcwpw1 enrichment &gt;10. Chromosomes <lb/></body>

			<page>44 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>1,3, and 5 were used as the test data with the remaining autosomes being the <lb/>training data. <lb/>Heatmaps <lb/>Regions were extracted from bigWig using bwtool matrix -fill=0 -decimals=1 -tiled-<lb/>averages=5, and width parameters 2000. Coverage was normalised by total <lb/>coverage (scaled by 10 10 ). A pseudocount of 1 was added to both input and <lb/>sample, and the sample was then normalised by the input for each region. Values <lb/>outside the quantile range 0.01-0.99 were thresholded. The profile plots are <lb/>created by taking the ratio of the mean coverage of the sample and input <lb/>separately. Ordering of the regions was determined by the mean coverage of a <lb/>200bp window centered on the peak center. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>45 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank the High-Throughput Genomics Group at the Wellcome Centre for <lb/>Human Genetics (funded by Wellcome Trust grant 203141/Z/16/Z) for the <lb/>generation of sequencing data. We also thank Dr. Benjamin Bishop and Prof. <lb/>Christian Siebold in the Division of Structural Biology (Wellcome Centre for Human <lb/>Genetics, Oxford) for their help with the purification of recombinant mouse <lb/>ZCWPW1 (size exclusion) towards antibody production.</div> 

			<div type="funding">Funding: This work was <lb/>supported by a Wellcome Trust Investigator Award to S.R.M. (098387/Z/12/Z &amp; <lb/>212284/Z/18/Z) and Wellcome Trust PhD Studentship to D.W. (109109/Z/15/Z). <lb/>Graphical abstract was created with BioRender.com. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>S.R.M. designed the study; E.B carried out cloning, cell culture experiments, bred <lb/>the mice and collected fertility measures; D.M. performed immunostaining of <lb/>spermatocytes and FISH for protein expression and synapsis analysis; E.B <lb/>performed ZCWPW1 ChIP-seq in human cells and G.Z. performed DMC1 ChIP-<lb/>seq in mouse testis; E.B, D.W, D.M, A.G.H (DMC1 ChIP-seq) and S.R.M analysed <lb/>the data; E.B, D.W and S.R.M prepared the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Materials &amp; Correspondence <lb/>Code is available at ww.github.com/MyersGroup/Zcwpw1. Other requests should <lb/>be addressed to S.R.M. <lb/></div>

			<page>46 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Allen JW, Latt SA. 1976. In vivo BrdU-33258 Hoechst analysis of DNA replication <lb/>kinetics and sister chromatid exchange formation in mouse somatic and <lb/>meiotic cells. Chromosoma 58:325-340. doi:10.1007/bf00292841 <lb/>Altemose N, Noor N, Bitoun E, Tumian A, Imbeault M, Chapman JR, Aricescu <lb/>AR, Myers SR. 2017. A map of human PRDM9 binding provides evidence for <lb/>novel behaviors of PRDM9 and other zinc-finger proteins in meiosis. Elife 6. <lb/>doi:10.7554/eLife.28383 <lb/>Altschul SF, Madden TL, Schäffer AA, Zhang J, Zhang Z, Miller W, Lipman DJ. <lb/>1997. Gapped BLAST and PSI-BLAST: a new generation of protein <lb/>database search programs. Nucleic Acids Res 25:3389-3402. <lb/>doi:10.1093/nar/25.17.3389 <lb/>Altschul SF, Wootton JC, Gertz EM, Agarwala R, Morgulis A, Schäffer AA, Yu Y-<lb/>K. 2005. Protein database searches using compositionally adjusted <lb/>substitution matrices. FEBS J 272:5101-5109. doi:10.1111/j.1742-<lb/>4658.2005.04945.x <lb/>Ashley T, Walpita D, de Rooij DG. 2001. Localization of two mammalian cyclin <lb/>dependent kinases during mammalian meiosis. J Cell Sci 114:685-693. <lb/>Aymard F, Bugler B, Schmidt CK, Guillou E, Caron P, Briois S, Iacovoni JS, <lb/>Daburon V, Miller KM, Jackson SP, Legube G. 2014. Transcriptionally active <lb/>chromatin recruits homologous recombination at DNA double-strand breaks. <lb/>Nat Struct Mol Biol 21:366-374. doi:10.1038/nsmb.2796 <lb/>Baker Z, Schumer M, Haba Y, Bashkirova L, Holland C, Rosenthal GG, <lb/>Przeworski M. 2017. Repeated losses of PRDM9-directed recombination <lb/>despite the conservation of PRDM9 across vertebrates. Elife 6. <lb/>doi:10.7554/eLife.24133 <lb/>Banito A, Li X, Laporte AN, Roe J-S, Sanchez-Vega F, Huang C-H, Dancsok AR, <lb/>Hatzi K, Chen C-C, Tschaharganeh DF, Chandwani R, Tasdemir N, Jones <lb/>KB, Capecchi MR, Vakoc CR, Schultz N, Ladanyi M, Nielsen TO, Lowe SW. <lb/>2018. The SS18-SSX Oncoprotein Hijacks KDM2B-PRC1.1 to Drive <lb/>Synovial Sarcoma. Cancer Cell. doi:10.1016/j.ccell.2018.07.006 <lb/>Barchi M, Roig I, Di Giacomo M, de Rooij DG, Keeney S, Jasin M. 2008. ATM <lb/>promotes the obligate XY crossover and both crossover control and <lb/>chromosome axis integrity on autosomes. PLoS Genet 4:e1000076. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1000076 <lb/>Barski A, Cuddapah S, Cui K, Roh T-Y, Schones DE, Wang Z, Wei G, Chepelev <lb/>I, Zhao K. 2007. High-resolution profiling of histone methylations in the <lb/>human genome. Cell 129:823-837. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2007.05.009 <lb/>Baudat F, Buard J, Grey C, Fledel-Alon A, Ober C, Przeworski M, Coop G, de <lb/>Massy B. 2010. PRDM9 Is a Major Determinant of Meiotic Recombination <lb/>Hotspots in Humans and Mice. Science. doi:10.1126/science.1183439 <lb/>Bhattacharyya T, Gregorova S, Mihola O, Anger M, Sebestova J, Denny P, <lb/>Simecek P, Forejt J. 2013. Mechanistic basis of infertility of mouse <lb/>intersubspecific hybrids. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 110:E468-77. <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.1219126110 <lb/>Brick K, Smagulova F, Khil P, Camerini-Otero RD, Petukhova GV. 2012. Genetic <lb/>recombination is directed away from functional genomic elements in mice. <lb/>Nature 485:642-645. doi:10.1038/nature11089 <lb/>Brown MS, Grubb J, Zhang A, Rust MJ, Bishop DK. 2015. Small Rad51 and <lb/>Dmc1 Complexes Often Co-occupy Both Ends of a Meiotic DNA Double <lb/>Strand Break. PLoS Genet 11:e1005653. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1005653 <lb/>Cahoon CK, Libuda DE. 2019. Leagues of their own: sexually dimorphic features <lb/>of meiotic prophase I. Chromosoma. doi:10.1007/s00412-019-00692-x <lb/>Capra JA, Singh M. 2007. Predicting functionally important residues from <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>47 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>sequence conservation. Bioinformatics 23:1875-1882. <lb/>doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btm270 <lb/>Carithers LJ, Ardlie K, Barcus M, Branton PA, Britton A, Buia SA, Compton CC, <lb/>DeLuca DS, Peter-Demchok J, Gelfand ET, Guan P, Korzeniewski GE, <lb/>Lockhart NC, Rabiner CA, Rao AK, Robinson KL, Roche NV, Sawyer SJ, <lb/>Segrè AV, Shive CE, Smith AM, Sobin LH, Undale AH, Valentino KM, <lb/>Vaught J, Young TR, Moore HM, GTEx Consortium. 2015. A Novel <lb/>Approach to High-Quality Postmortem Tissue Procurement: The GTEx <lb/>Project. Biopreserv Biobank 13:311-319. doi:10.1089/bio.2015.0032 <lb/>Carvalho S, Vítor AC, Sridhara SC, Martins FB, Raposo AC, Desterro JMP, <lb/>Ferreira J, de Almeida SF. 2014. SETD2 is required for DNA double-strand <lb/>break repair and activation of the p53-mediated checkpoint. Elife 3:e02482. <lb/>doi:10.7554/eLife.02482 <lb/>Davies B, Hatton E, Altemose N, Hussin JG, Pratto F, Zhang G, Hinch AG, <lb/>Moralli D, Biggs D, Diaz R, Preece C, Li R, Bitoun E, Brick K, Green CM, <lb/>Camerini-Otero RD, Myers SR, Donnelly P. 2016. Re-engineering the zinc <lb/>fingers of PRDM9 reverses hybrid sterility in mice. Nature 530:171-176. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nature16931 <lb/>Deininger P. 2011. Alu elements: know the SINEs. Genome Biol 12:236. <lb/>doi:10.1186/gb-2011-12-12-236 <lb/>Diagouraga B, Clément JAJ, Duret L, Kadlec J, de Massy B, Baudat F. 2018. <lb/>PRDM9 Methyltransferase Activity Is Essential for Meiotic DNA Double-<lb/>Strand Break Formation at Its Binding Sites. Mol Cell 69:853-865.e6. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.molcel.2018.01.033 <lb/>Ding X, Xu R, Yu J, Xu T, Zhuang Y, Han M. 2007. SUN1 is required for telomere <lb/>attachment to nuclear envelope and gametogenesis in mice. Dev Cell <lb/>12:863-872. doi:10.1016/j.devcel.2007.03.018 <lb/>Gaysinskaya V, Miller BF, De Luca C, van der Heijden GW, Hansen KD, Bortvin <lb/>A. 2018. Transient reduction of DNA methylation at the onset of meiosis in <lb/>male mice. Epigenetics Chromatin 11:15. doi:10.1186/s13072-018-0186-0 <lb/>Gregorova S, Gergelits V, Chvatalova I, Bhattacharyya T, Valiskova B, <lb/>Fotopulosova V, Jansa P, Wiatrowska D, Forejt J. 2018. Modulation of <lb/>Prdm9-controlled meiotic chromosome asynapsis overrides hybrid sterility in <lb/>mice. Elife 7. doi:10.7554/eLife.34282 <lb/>Hayashi K, Yoshida K, Matsui Y. 2005. A histone H3 methyltransferase controls <lb/>epigenetic events required for meiotic prophase. Nature 438:374-378. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nature04112 <lb/>He F, Muto Y, Inoue M, Kigawa T, Shirouzu M, Terada T, Yokoyama S, RIKEN <lb/>Structural Genomics/Proteomics Initiative. 2010. Complex structure of the zf-<lb/>CW domain and the H3K4me3 peptide. doi:10.2210/pdb2rr4/pdb <lb/>He F, Umehara T, Saito K, Harada T, Watanabe S, Yabuki T, Kigawa T, <lb/>Takahashi M, Kuwasako K, Tsuda K, Matsuda T, Aoki M, Seki E, Kobayashi <lb/>N, Güntert P, Yokoyama S, Muto Y. 2010. Structural insight into the zinc <lb/>finger CW domain as a histone modification reader. Structure 18:1127-1139. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.str.2010.06.012 <lb/>Hinch AG, Zhang G, Becker PW, Moralli D, Hinch R, Davies B, Bowden R, <lb/>Donnelly P. 2019. Factors influencing meiotic recombination revealed by <lb/>whole-genome sequencing of single sperm. Science 363. <lb/>doi:10.1126/science.aau8861 <lb/>Hong EL, Shinohara A, Bishop DK. 2001. Saccharomyces cerevisiae Dmc1 <lb/>protein promotes renaturation of single-strand DNA (ssDNA) and <lb/>assimilation of ssDNA into homologous super-coiled duplex DNA. J Biol <lb/>Chem 276:41906-41912. doi:10.1074/jbc.M105563200 <lb/>Horn HF, Kim DI, Wright GD, Wong ESM, Stewart CL, Burke B, Roux KJ. 2013. <lb/>A mammalian KASH domain protein coupling meiotic chromosomes to the <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>48 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>cytoskeleton. J Cell Biol 202:1023-1039. doi:10.1083/jcb.201304004 <lb/>Huang Y, Gu L, Li G-M. 2018. H3K36me3-mediated mismatch repair <lb/>preferentially protects actively transcribed genes from mutation. J Biol Chem <lb/>293:7811-7823. doi:10.1074/jbc.RA118.002839 <lb/>Ji Z, Sheng Y, Miao J, Li X, Zhao H, Wang J, Cheng C, Wang X, Liu K, Zhang K, <lb/>Xu L, Yao J, Shen L, Hou J, Zhou W, Sun J, Li L, Gao W-Q, Zhu HH. 2019. <lb/>The histone methyltransferase Setd2 is indispensable for V(D)J <lb/>recombination. Nature Communications. doi:10.1038/s41467-019-11282-x <lb/>Johansson F, Toh H. 2010. A comparative study of conservation and variation <lb/>scores. BMC Bioinformatics 11:388. doi:10.1186/1471-2105-11-388 <lb/>Jung M, Wells D, Rusch J, Ahmad S, Marchini J, Myers SR, Conrad DF. 2019. <lb/>Unified single-cell analysis of testis gene regulation and pathology in five <lb/>mouse strains. Elife 8. doi:10.7554/eLife.43966 <lb/>Khil PP, Smagulova F, Brick KM, Camerini-Otero RD, Petukhova GV. 2012. <lb/>Sensitive mapping of recombination hotspots using sequencing-based <lb/>detection of ssDNA. Genome Res 22:957-965. doi:10.1101/gr.130583.111 <lb/>Lange J, Yamada S, Tischfield SE, Pan J, Kim S, Zhu X, Socci ND, Jasin M, <lb/>Keeney S. 2016. The Landscape of Mouse Meiotic Double-Strand Break <lb/>Formation, Processing, and Repair. Cell 167:695-708.e16. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cell.2016.09.035 <lb/>Lee J-H, Skalnik DG. 2008. Wdr82 is a C-terminal domain-binding protein that <lb/>recruits the Setd1A Histone H3-Lys4 methyltransferase complex to <lb/>transcription start sites of transcribed human genes. Mol Cell Biol 28:609-<lb/>618. doi:10.1128/MCB.01356-07 <lb/>Lee J-H, Skalnik DG. 2005. CpG-binding protein (CXXC finger protein 1) is a <lb/>component of the mammalian Set1 histone H3-Lys4 methyltransferase <lb/>complex, the analogue of the yeast Set1/COMPASS complex. J Biol Chem <lb/>280:41725-41731. doi:10.1074/jbc.M508312200 <lb/>Li F, Mao G, Tong D, Huang J, Gu L, Yang W, Li G-M. 2013. The histone mark <lb/>H3K36me3 regulates human DNA mismatch repair through its interaction <lb/>with MutSα. Cell 153:590-600. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2013.03.025 <lb/>Li H. 2013. Aligning sequence reads, clone sequences and assembly contigs with <lb/>BWA-MEM. arXiv [q-bioGN]. <lb/>Li M, Huang T, Li M-J, Zhang C-X, Yu X-C, Yin Y-Y, Liu C, Wang X, Feng H-W, <lb/>Zhang T, Liu M-F, Han C-S, Lu G, Li W, Ma J-L, Chen Z-J, Liu H-B, Liu K. <lb/>2019. The histone modification reader ZCWPW1 is required for meiosis <lb/>prophase I in male but not in female mice. Science Advances. <lb/>doi:10.1126/sciadv.aax1101 <lb/>Li R, Bitoun E, Altemose N, Davies RW, Davies B, Myers SR. 2019. A high-<lb/>resolution map of non-crossover events reveals impacts of genetic diversity <lb/>on mammalian meiotic recombination. Nat Commun 10:3900. <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41467-019-11675-y <lb/>Liu Y, Tempel W, Zhang Q, Liang X, Loppnau P, Qin S, Min J. 2016. Family-wide <lb/>Characterization of Histone Binding Abilities of Human CW Domain-<lb/>containing Proteins. J Biol Chem 291:9000-9013. <lb/>doi:10.1074/jbc.M116.718973 <lb/>Lobley A, Sadowski MI, Jones DT. 2009. pGenTHREADER and <lb/>pDomTHREADER: new methods for improved protein fold recognition and <lb/>superfamily discrimination. Bioinformatics 25:1761-1767. <lb/>doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp302 <lb/>Lu L-Y, Yu X. 2015. Double-strand break repair on sex chromosomes: challenges <lb/>during male meiotic prophase. Cell Cycle 14:516-525. <lb/>doi:10.1080/15384101.2014.998070 <lb/>Lunter G, Goodson M. 2011. Stampy: a statistical algorithm for sensitive and fast <lb/>mapping of Illumina sequence reads. Genome Res 21:936-939. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>49 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>doi:10.1101/gr.111120.110 <lb/>Luo Y, Lu X, Xie H. 2014. Dynamic Alu methylation during normal development, <lb/>aging, and tumorigenesis. Biomed Res Int 2014:784706. <lb/>doi:10.1155/2014/784706 <lb/>Marchler-Bauer A, Bryant SH. 2004. CD-Search: protein domain annotations on <lb/>the fly. Nucleic Acids Res 32:W327-31. doi:10.1093/nar/gkh454 <lb/>McDaniel SL, Strahl BD. 2017. Shaping the cellular landscape with Set2/SETD2 <lb/>methylation. Cell Mol Life Sci 74:3317-3334. doi:10.1007/s00018-017-2517-<lb/>x <lb/>Mihola O, Pratto F, Brick K, Linhartova E, Kobets T, Flachs P, Baker CL, <lb/>Sedlacek R, Paigen K, Petkov PM, Camerini-Otero RD, Trachtulec Z. 2019. <lb/>Histone methyltransferase PRDM9 is not essential for meiosis in male mice. <lb/>Genome Res 29:1078-1086. doi:10.1101/gr.244426.118 <lb/>Moens PB, Kolas NK, Tarsounas M, Marcon E, Cohen PE, Spyropoulos B. 2002. <lb/>The time course and chromosomal localization of recombination-related <lb/>proteins at meiosis in the mouse are compatible with models that can resolve <lb/>the early DNA-DNA interactions without reciprocal recombination. J Cell Sci <lb/>115:1611-1622. <lb/>Morelli MA, Cohen PE. 2005. Not all germ cells are created equal: aspects of <lb/>sexual dimorphism in mammalian meiosis. Reproduction 130:761-781. <lb/>doi:10.1530/rep.1.00865 <lb/>Mulligan P, Westbrook TF, Ottinger M, Pavlova N, Chang B, Macia E, Shi Y-J, <lb/>Barretina J, Liu J, Howley PM, Elledge SJ, Shi Y. 2008. CDYL bridges REST <lb/>and histone methyltransferases for gene repression and suppression of <lb/>cellular transformation. Mol Cell 32:718-726. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.molcel.2008.10.025 <lb/>Myers S, Bowden R, Tumian A, Bontrop RE, Freeman C, MacFie TS, McVean G, <lb/>Donnelly P. 2010. Drive against hotspot motifs in primates implicates the <lb/>PRDM9 gene in meiotic recombination. Science 327:876-879. <lb/>doi:10.1126/science.1182363 <lb/>Neale MJ, Keeney S. 2006. Clarifying the mechanics of DNA strand exchange in <lb/>meiotic recombination. Nature 442:153-158. doi:10.1038/nature04885 <lb/>Parvanov ED, Petkov PM, Paigen K. 2010. Prdm9 Controls Activation of <lb/>Mammalian Recombination Hotspots. Science. doi:10.1126/science.1181495 <lb/>Parvanov ED, Tian H, Billings T, Saxl RL, Spruce C, Aithal R, Krejci L, Paigen K, <lb/>Petkov PM. 2017. PRDM9 interactions with other proteins provide a link <lb/>between recombination hotspots and the chromosomal axis in meiosis. Mol <lb/>Biol Cell 28:488. doi:10.1091/mbc.E16-09-0686 <lb/>Peters AH, Plug AW, van Vugt MJ, de Boer P. 1997. A drying-down technique for <lb/>the spreading of mammalian meiocytes from the male and female germline. <lb/>Chromosome Res 5:66-68. <lb/>Petukhova GV, Romanienko PJ, Daniel Camerini-Otero R. 2003. The Hop2 <lb/>Protein Has a Direct Role in Promoting Interhomolog Interactions during <lb/>Mouse Meiosis. Developmental Cell. doi:10.1016/s1534-5807(03)00369-1 <lb/>Pfister SX, Ahrabi S, Zalmas L-P, Sarkar S, Aymard F, Bachrati CZ, Helleday T, <lb/>Legube G, La Thangue NB, Porter ACG, Humphrey TC. 2014. SETD2-<lb/>dependent histone H3K36 trimethylation is required for homologous <lb/>recombination repair and genome stability. Cell Rep 7:2006-2018. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.celrep.2014.05.026 <lb/>Powers NR, Parvanov ED, Baker CL, Walker M, Petkov PM, Paigen K. 2016. The <lb/>Meiotic Recombination Activator PRDM9 Trimethylates Both H3K36 and <lb/>H3K4 at Recombination Hotspots In Vivo. PLoS Genet 12:e1006146. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1006146 <lb/>Pratto F, Brick K, Khil P, Smagulova F, Petukhova GV, Camerini-Otero RD. 2014. <lb/>DNA recombination. Recombination initiation maps of individual human <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>50 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>genomes. Science 346:1256442. doi:10.1126/science.1256442 <lb/>Qin S, Min J. 2014. Structure and function of the nucleosome-binding PWWP <lb/>domain. Trends Biochem Sci 39:536-547. doi:10.1016/j.tibs.2014.09.001 <lb/>Rona GB, Eleutherio ECA, Pinheiro AS. 2016. PWWP domains and their modes <lb/>of sensing DNA and histone methylated lysines. Biophys Rev 8:63-74. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s12551-015-0190-6 <lb/>Schultz DC, Ayyanathan K, Negorev D, Maul GG, Rauscher FJ 3rd. 2002. <lb/>SETDB1: a novel KAP-1-associated histone H3, lysine 9-specific <lb/>methyltransferase that contributes to HP1-mediated silencing of euchromatic <lb/>genes by KRAB zinc-finger proteins. Genes Dev 16:919-932. <lb/>doi:10.1101/gad.973302 <lb/>Sehorn MG, Sigurdsson S, Bussen W, Unger VM, Sung P. 2004. Human meiotic <lb/>recombinase Dmc1 promotes ATP-dependent homologous DNA strand <lb/>exchange. Nature 429:433-437. doi:10.1038/nature02563 <lb/>Seisenberger S, Peat JR, Hore TA, Santos F, Dean W, Reik W. 2013. <lb/>Reprogramming DNA methylation in the mammalian life cycle: building and <lb/>breaking epigenetic barriers. Philos Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci <lb/>368:20110330. doi:10.1098/rstb.2011.0330 <lb/>Shibuya H, Ishiguro K-I, Watanabe Y. 2014. The TRF1-binding protein TERB1 <lb/>promotes chromosome movement and telomere rigidity in meiosis. Nat Cell <lb/>Biol 16:145-156. doi:10.1038/ncb2896 <lb/>Smagulova F, Gregoretti IV, Brick K, Khil P, Camerini-Otero RD, Petukhova GV. <lb/>2011. Genome-wide analysis reveals novel molecular features of mouse <lb/>recombination hotspots. Nature 472:375-378. doi:10.1038/nature09869 <lb/>Soh YQS, Junker JP, Gill ME, Mueller JL, van Oudenaarden A, Page DC. 2015. <lb/>A Gene Regulatory Program for Meiotic Prophase in the Fetal Ovary. PLoS <lb/>Genet 11:e1005531. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1005531 <lb/>Spruce C, Dlamini S, Ananda G, Bronkema N, Tian H. 2019. HELLS and PRDM9 <lb/>form a Pioneer Complex to Open Chromatin at Meiotic Recombination <lb/>Hotspots. bioRxiv. <lb/>Tarsounas M, Morita T, Pearlman RE, Moens PB. 1999. RAD51 and DMC1 form <lb/>mixed complexes associated with mouse meiotic chromosome cores and <lb/>synaptonemal complexes. J Cell Biol 147:207-220. <lb/>doi:10.1083/jcb.147.2.207 <lb/>Thibault-Sennett S, Yu Q, Smagulova F, Cloutier J, Brick K, Camerini-Otero RD, <lb/>Petukhova GV. 2018. Interrogating the Functions of PRDM9 Domains in <lb/>Meiosis. Genetics 209:475-487. doi:10.1534/genetics.118.300565 <lb/>Tu Z, Bayazit MB, Liu H, Zhang J, Busayavalasa K, Risal S, Shao J, <lb/>Satyanarayana A, Coppola V, Tessarollo L, Singh M, Zheng C, Han C, Chen <lb/>Z, Kaldis P, Gustafsson J-Å, Liu K. 2017. Speedy A-Cdk2 binding mediates <lb/>initial telomere-nuclear envelope attachment during meiotic prophase I <lb/>independent of Cdk2 activation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 114:592-597. <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.1618465114 <lb/>Uhlén M, Fagerberg L, Hallström BM, Lindskog C, Oksvold P, Mardinoglu A, <lb/>Sivertsson Å, Kampf C, Sjöstedt E, Asplund A, Olsson I, Edlund K, Lundberg <lb/>E, Navani S, Szigyarto CA-K, Odeberg J, Djureinovic D, Takanen JO, Hober <lb/>S, Alm T, Edqvist P-H, Berling H, Tegel H, Mulder J, Rockberg J, Nilsson P, <lb/>Schwenk JM, Hamsten M, von Feilitzen K, Forsberg M, Persson L, <lb/>Johansson F, Zwahlen M, von Heijne G, Nielsen J, Pontén F. 2015. <lb/>Proteomics. Tissue-based map of the human proteome. Science <lb/>347:1260419. doi:10.1126/science.1260419 <lb/>Wagner EJ, Carpenter PB. 2012. Understanding the language of Lys36 <lb/>methylation at histone H3. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 13:115-126. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrm3274 <lb/>Zhang J, Fujiwara Y, Yamamoto S, Shibuya H. 2019. Publisher Correction: A <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>51 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>meiosis-specific BRCA2 binding protein recruits recombinases to DNA <lb/>double-strand breaks to ensure homologous recombination. Nat Commun <lb/>10:986. doi:10.1038/s41467-019-08995-4 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
