<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Effects of a novel three-dimensional grid intrauterine device on <lb/>the uterus, steroid receptor and PAX2 of rhesus macaques <lb/>Mei-Hua Zhang 1 † , Li-Ping Zhai 2 † , Ling Yu 1 , Xia Song 1 , Jian-Chun Yu 1* , Yi <lb/>Qiu 1* <lb/>1. Key Laboratory of Birth Regulation and Control Technology of National Health <lb/>Commission of China, Key Laboratory for Imp roving Birth Outcome Technique, <lb/>Maternal and Child Health Care Hospital of Shandong Province, 238 East Road <lb/>of Jingshi, Jinan, Shandong 250014, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/>2. Shandong Provincial Institute of Control of Endemic Disease, East Road of <lb/>Jingshi, Jinan, Shandong 250014, People&apos;s Republic of China <lb/> Intrauterine devices (IUDs) is the most effective methods of the reversible and <lb/>long-acting contraception. 1) To develop a novel three-dimensional grid intrauterine <lb/>device (3-DGIUD) with nickel-titanium (Ni-Ti) and silicone rubber. 2) To observe the <lb/>effect of the 3-DGIUD on contraceptive efficacy and the change of uterus, <lb/>endometrial sex steroid receptor, PAX2 in rhesus macaques (Macaca mulatta). The <lb/>materials of the 3-DGIUD were the nitinol wire and the silicone rubber. The frame of <lb/>the 3-DGIUD was three-dimensional and grid-like. Twenty adult female rhesus <lb/>macaques were divided into the 3-DGIUD group (placing the 3-DGIUD, n=9), the <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>sham operation group (no placing the 3-DGIUD, n=9) and the control group (n=2). <lb/>On the 10 th -day after surgery, the 3-DGIUD group and the sham operation group <lb/>macaques were caged together with male macaques (female: male = 1:1). The uterus, <lb/>3-DGIUD and pregnancy of 18 female rhesus monkeys were examined by abdominal <lb/>ultrasound every month. The endometrium pathological examination was carried out <lb/>and the expression of PAX2 and hormone receptor (ER, PR) was detected by <lb/>immunohistochemical staining. After 3-DGIUD was placed in case group for 3 and 12 <lb/>months, only 1 of female macaque was pregnant in 9. The contraceptive effective rate <lb/>was 88.9% (8/9). The 3-DGIUD in the uterus of macaques was observed by <lb/>ultrasound. In the sham operation group, 9 macaques were pregnant (9/9). There was <lb/>significant difference in uterine size of the 3-DGIUD group between pre-placement <lb/>and after surgery for 3 and 12 months (P&lt;0.05). The endometrial epithelium was <lb/>intact, just a small number of glands vacuoles and a few neutrophils infiltration <lb/>around the 3-DGIUD. The expression of endometrial ER, PR and PAX2 in 3-DGIUD <lb/>group on 12 months after surgery was similar to those in control macaque. The <lb/>3-DGIUD has a good contraceptive effect on female macaques, and has no significant <lb/>affection on the expression of endometrial steroid receptor and PAX2 in rhesus <lb/>monkeys. <lb/>Key words: three-dimensional grid intrauterine device (3-DGIUD); contraception; <lb/>sex steroid receptor; PAX2; rhesus macaques <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<front>43 <lb/>44 <lb/>Short Title: Novel 3-DGIUD on uterus <lb/></front>
			
			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<front>† These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* Corresponding author: <lb/>Jian-Chun Yu, E-mail: yujchun@163.com <lb/>Yi Qiu, E-mail: qiuyi987@sina.com <lb/>This work was supported financially by grant of &quot;the National Key Research and <lb/>Development Plan&quot; (2016YFC1000903). <lb/></front>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Appliance of contraceptives is the cornerstone of prevention for unintended <lb/>pregnancy. The rate of unintended pregnancy in the United States is 51% and 45% in <lb/>2011 and in 2008, respectively [1]. In China, more than 20% of teenager and <lb/>unmarried women are pregnant every year [2], and the rate of undergoing repeat <lb/>abortions and non-use of contraception in these adolescents is 39% and 68%, <lb/>respectively [3]. Long-acting reversible contraceptive (LARC) methods could help <lb/>reduce the high rate of unintended pregnancy. Among all available contraceptive <lb/>methods, the failure rate of IUD is less than 1%, which is almost ideal and the most <lb/>popular contraceptive method in the world [4,5]. IUDs are the most common forms <lb/>for millions of women, particularly in mediate postpartum women [6-8]. Current data <lb/>shows that more than 10% of childbearing aged women are using IUDs worldwide [4]. <lb/>In China, IUDs are utilized by 48%-51% women of childbearing aged in 2010-2015 <lb/>[5,8]. The rate of IUD use in American Muslim women are 21.2% [9]. In breast <lb/>cancer women, the rate of IUDs use is 72.1% [10]. <lb/>Although female contraceptive methods such as sterilization, IUDs and hormonal <lb/>contraception are very effective in preventing unintended pregnancy, some women <lb/>can&apos;t use them due to health condition or side effects. IUDs may cause side effects to <lb/>some women. Migration, especially uterine perforations, expulsion, increased <lb/>menstrual blood loss, pain, and uterus or pelvic inflammatory and risk of extrauterine <lb/>pregnancy after IUD insertion are frequently occurred on patients [11,12]. IUD <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>migrated into bladder is a rare and serious complication [13]. On the other hand, the <lb/>burst release of the cupric ion (Cu 2+ ) of cooper containing IUDs (Cu-IUDs) is an <lb/>important side effect particularly in the first month. The Cu-IUDs, <lb/>levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system (LNG-RIS) and implants are LARC. <lb/>Excessive Cu 2+ may cause toxic effect on the cell and increase bleeding and pain <lb/>[14-16]. The LNG-RIS can increase irregular bleeding and/or spotting days <lb/>particularly after 3 months of use [17,18]. In addition, the shape, size and weight of <lb/>IUDs also have a great impact on contraceptive effects and side effects. The increase <lb/>in menstrual volume caused by IUD seems to be related to the size of the device. The <lb/>greater the size and weight of the IUD, the greater the amount of menstrual blood loss <lb/>is. 11,12 Relationships between the size of the IUD and the size of the uterine cavity are <lb/>also considered to be a factor in the expulsion of the IUD [12]. <lb/>Inducing local inflammatory reaction in the endometrium is the major effect of all <lb/>IUDs. The inflammatory response can be enhanced by Cu-IUDs. Cu+ is released from <lb/>Cu-IUDs and reached in a concentration in the luminal fluids of the genital tract that <lb/>is toxic for spermatozoa and embryos [19]. Cu-IUDs are usually associated with <lb/>menorrhagia. As a local foreign body reaction, Cu-IUDs can cause certain <lb/>morphological changes in the endometrium and infiltration of monocytes as well as a <lb/>few plasma cells during the proliferative phase of the cycle [20]. The ovulation <lb/>dysfunction hemorrhage may be related to morphological and biochemical changes in <lb/>the IUD use. The LNG-RIS has profound morphological effects upon the <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>endometrium, which may lead to a large number of decidualization of endometrial <lb/>stromal cells, atrophy of the glandular and surface epithelium and vascular <lb/>morphology change [21,22]. Irregular bleeding is still a common reason for the <lb/>discontinuation of progestin-only contraception [21]. Down-regulation of sex steroid <lb/>receptors is found in all cellular components with endometrial exposure to LNG-RIS <lb/>[22]. Paired box 2 (PAX2) is a member of paired box family and is an oncogene <lb/>involved in the development of endometrial cancer. Recent studies have demonstrated <lb/>that occurrence of PAX2 loss expression in endometrial hyperplasia increases with <lb/>malignant progression, and PAX2 gene is required for embryonic uterine <lb/>development, during endometrial carcinogenesis [23-25]. No study has been found <lb/>in the effect of IUDs as the contraceptive method on endometrial sex steroid receptors <lb/>and PAX2 expression in uterus of rhesus macaques. <lb/>We have reported that the main contraceptive mechanism effect of the <lb/>three-dimensional reticular IUD (3-DRIUD) in rats, and observed that the larger the <lb/>physical space occupied by the intrauterine device, the less the pregnancy [26]. In <lb/>present study, we designed and manufactured a novel three-dimensional grid <lb/>intrauterine device (3-DGIUD) with nickel-titanium (nitinol) wire and silicone rubber <lb/>for rhesus macaques, and investigated the changes in the uterus and endometrium of <lb/>macaques after the 3-DGIUD placement. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>Materials of the new 3-DGIUD and inserter for rhesus macaques <lb/>The frame of the 3-DGIUD was composed of nitinol wire (with a diameter of 0.05 <lb/>mm) and covered with a layer of silicone rubber. Design the structure of the <lb/>3-DGIUD was according to the size and shape of the rhesus macaque&apos;s uterus. The <lb/>shape of the 3-DGIUD for rhesus macaques was three-dimensional in nature and had <lb/>a reticular grid shape. Its height (H), upper width (D), lower width (d) and thickness <lb/>were 0.6-1.2 cm, 0.4-0.6 cm and 0.2-0.4 cm, respectively (Figure 1 A, B and D). The <lb/>weight of the 3-DGIUD was 0.015-0.020 g. A layer of silicon-boron coupling agent <lb/>was covered on the surface of the 3-DGIUD, and finally multi-layer coating method <lb/>was used with silica gel, and the 3-DGIUD coated with silica gel was vulcanized. The <lb/>3-DGIUD was placed in the external casing tube of the inserter (Figure 1 C). Figure 1 <lb/>shows photographs of the 3-DGIUD for rhesus macaques. <lb/>The material of the inserter of the 3-DGIUD for rhesus macaques was stainless <lb/>steel. Inserters of the 3-DGIUD were composed of an external casing tube (diameter <lb/>2.0 mm) and an internal needle core (push-rod) (diameter 1.8 mm) (Figure 1 C). <lb/>Animals <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Rhesus macaques were from the Fujian Provincial Non-human Primate Animal <lb/>Experimental Center. All procedures were performed in accordance with &quot;Guidelines <lb/>for the Care and Use of Experimental Animals in Fujian Province&quot;, and approved by <lb/>the Animal Care and Use Committee of Fujian Provincial Institute for Family <lb/>Planning Science and Technology. In December 2016, twenty adult female rhesus <lb/>macaques were divided into 3 groups, 9 macaques were in the 3-DGIUD group, 9 cases <lb/>were taken as the sham operation group, and the other 2 cases were taken as control <lb/>group (without surgery). The license number of the Animal Care and Use was SYXK <lb/>(Min) 2015-0007 and SCXK (Min) 2015-0002. All macaques were single cage <lb/>(stainless steel) with standard feeding. The indoor temperature of the animal was <lb/>22~25°C, the relative humidity was 60~70%, artificial lighting was 12h/d, and the air <lb/>was ventilated. <lb/>Surgical procedures <lb/>The surgical procedures were carried out under sterile technique. Macaques were <lb/>sedated with ketamine, atropine sulfate (0.02 mL/kg intramuscular injection) and <lb/>ketamine hydrochloride (0.1-0.2 mL/kg intramuscular injection in a 50 mg/mL <lb/>aqueous solution), the abdominal regions were shaved and the animals were <lb/>positioned in the supine position. The lower abdominal region was disinfected with <lb/>70% ethanol and iodine tincture and covered with sterilized drapes, and then surgical <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>midline lower abdominal incision was performed and the uterus was exposed (Figure <lb/>2 A and B). The external dimensions of the uterus were measured with a sterilized <lb/>caliper (Figure 2 B). Then a catheter was inserted into the uterus (Figure 2 C). The <lb/>3-DGIUD was placed into the uterine cavity with a catheter for 9 macaques <lb/>(3-DGIUD group). The sham surgery was performed for another 9 macaques (only <lb/>the catheter inserted into the uterine cavity, without the 3-DGIUD placement). Then <lb/>the incision of the uterus was sutured with absorbable sutures (Figure 2 D), and <lb/>macaques received prophylactic antibiotics (Cefazolin, 30 mg/kg). <lb/>Treatment phase and ultrasonography <lb/>On the 10 th -day after operation, 18 female macaques in the 3-DGIUD group (n=9) and <lb/>the sham operation group (n=9) were coupled with fertile male macaques (1:1) to <lb/>observe the effect of contraception of the 3-DGIUD. Two macaques in the 3-DGIUD <lb/>group and one macaque in control group (No. 1, without surgery) were <lb/>hysterectomized at third-month. On 12 months after the 3-DGIUD placement, 6 <lb/>macaques in the 3-DGIUD group and 1 macaque in control group (No. 2, without <lb/>surgery) undergo hysterectomy. <lb/>Abdominal ultrasound was performed for 18 macaques in the 3-DGIUD group and <lb/>the sham operation group every month, to check the uterus, 3-DGIUD and pregnancy. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>For ultrasonography, we used an X300PE (Siemens, Germany) machine with a <lb/>3.5-MHz (VS 13-5, Siemens) probe. <lb/>After hysterectomy, the uterus was used for histology and immunohistochemistry <lb/>and morphological studies. Several cross-sections (about 2 mm thick) were cut <lb/>freehand from the lumen to the myometrial border with a razor blade under <lb/>stereomicrocope magnification. These slices were processed further to assess <lb/>histological development, steroid receptor immunocytochemistry and markers (PAX2) <lb/>of proliferation. Steroid receptors (estrogen and progestin receptor, ER and PR), and <lb/>PAX2 described as below. <lb/>Histology and immunohistochemistry <lb/>Pathological examination was carried out to the endometrium. Samples for histology <lb/>were fixed with a mixture of 2% glutaraldehyde and 3% paraformaldehyde, embedded <lb/>in glycol methacrylate (GMA), sectioned, and stained with hematoxylin and eosin <lb/>(HE). The expression of ER, PR and PAX2 were detected by immunohistochemistry <lb/>of endometrium on 12 months after surgery. For immunohistochemistry, briefly, <lb/>paraffin-embedded tissue sections were de-paraffinized with xylene and dehydrated <lb/>through graded ethanol, and then their endogenous peroxidase activity was quenched <lb/>with 3% hydrogen peroxide for 30 min. Antigen retrieval used 10 mM sodium citrate <lb/>buffer for 2 min. Sections were washed with PBS (phosphate-buffered saline) and <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>blocked with goat serum for 15 min. Sections were incubated with blocking serum for <lb/>20 min and then with the primary monoclonal anti-ER (1D-5; detects ER alpha, <lb/>Biogenex, San Ramon, CA, USA) and anti-PR (JZB-39; courtesy of Geoffrey Greene, <lb/>University of Chicago, detects PR-A and PR-B), and both were incubated overnight at <lb/>4 °C, washed, and then were incubated for 20 min at room temperature with <lb/>respective biotinylated goat anti-mouse/rabbit secondary antibody and biotinylated <lb/>horseradish peroxidase complex both in the Ultra Sensitive™ SP (Mouse/Rabbit) IHC <lb/>Kit (Maixin Bio). For PAX2, Sections were dried for 1 h at 65 °C before treatment <lb/>procedure of deparaffinization, rehydration and epitope retrieval in the Pre-Treatment <lb/>Module, PT-LINK (DAKO) at 95 °C for 20 min in 50 × Tris/EDTA buffer, pH 9.0. <lb/>Before staining the sections, endogenous peroxidase was blocked. The antibodies <lb/>used were against 6H2.1. After incubation, the reaction was visualized with the stain <lb/>used: PAX2, clone: Z-RX2. Sections were counter-stained with hematoxylin. <lb/>Appropriate negative controls including no primary antibody were also tested. The <lb/>sections were incubated with DAB (3,3&apos;-diaminobenzidine tetrahydrochloride) for <lb/>5 min (Maixin Bio), washed under tap water and counterstained with hematoxylin to <lb/>facilitate identification of cellular elements. The section was cover-slipped. Finally, <lb/>the slides were observed by microscopy (Olympus). <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>The statistical analysis of the study was performed using an IBM SPSS (Version 22.0. <lb/>Armonk, NY: IBM Corp.). Data were shown as the mean ± SD. Parametric data were <lb/>analyzed statistically using Student&apos;s t-tests. The exact Pearson Chi-Square test <lb/>(Fisher&apos;s Exact Test)was used for the pregnant rate. The difference was considered <lb/>statistically significant for P values &lt;0.05. <lb/>Results <lb/>Uterine corpus measurement results before operation and during surgery <lb/>The weight, uterine corpus measurement (during surgery) and ultrasonography <lb/>(before operation) were shown in Table 1. The mean weight and mean age of the <lb/>3-DGIUD group (n=9) and the sham operation group (n=9) were 6.4 ± 1.0 kg and <lb/>129.6 ± 1.6 months, and 6.5 ± 0.8 kg and 130.8 ± 8.4 months, respectively, no <lb/>significant differences were found between both groups. The weight and age of <lb/>another 2 female control macaques (without operation) were 5.9 kg and 127 months <lb/>and 6.9 kg and 132 months, respectively. In longitudinal section, the uterus was <lb/>shaped like an inverted pear (Figure 3 A and B), whereas in transverse section, it was <lb/>triangular, with a well-defined border by ultrasound. The 3-DGIUD in the uterus <lb/>shown strong echo, and longitudinal and transverse section were 8 × 6 × 3 mm (large) <lb/>(Figure 3 C and D) and 6 × 4 × 2 mm (small) (Figure 3 E). The mean size of uterine <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>corpus of height, width and thickness during operation measured by caliper was 28.1 <lb/>± 1.0 mm, 21.7 ± 2.5 mm and 17.3 ± 2.6 mm in the 3-DGIUD group, and 28.7 ± 0.8 <lb/>mm, 22.8 ± 2.8 mm and 17.3 ± 1.6 mm in control group (t=0.533, 1.153 and 0.000, <lb/>and P=0.609, 0.282 and 1.000); the size of uterine corpus by ultrasound in <lb/>longitudinal section and in transverse section was 28.12 ± 2.26 mm, 19.49 ± 2.11 mm <lb/>and 21.77 ± 2.43 mm in the 3-DGIUD group, and 29.63 ± 2.25 mm, 19.24 ± 1.67 mm <lb/>and 21.33 ± 2.27 mm in control group (t=1.240, 0.297 and 0.589, and P=0.250, 0.787 <lb/>and 0.572), respectively. <lb/>Pregnancy and uterine measurement of rhesus macaques on 3 months and 12 <lb/>months after surgery <lb/>The large type of the 3-DGIUD was placed in 7 rhesus macaques and the small type <lb/>was placed in 2 cases. After 3 months, the 3-DGIUD loss and pregnancy were found <lb/>in one macaque (1/9, 11.1%), and this 3-DGIUD was small type. In the sham <lb/>operation group, 6 and 3 macaques on 3 and 12 months after surgery were pregnant <lb/>(Figure 3 F), respectively, and there was significant difference comparing with the <lb/>3-DGIUD group (x 2 = 5.844, P = 0.05 and x 2 = 14.400, P = 0.000). Uterine <lb/>measurement on 3 months and 12 months after surgery is shown in Table 2. <lb/>Changes in the histology <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>No pelvic infection occurred in 18 rhesus macaques on 3 and 12 months after surgery. <lb/>After hysterectomy, the uterus was cut open. It can be seen that the 3-DGIUD did not <lb/>adhere to surrounding tissues or embed into myometrium (Figure 4 A). The <lb/>endometria in the without operation macaque (No. 1, control) were typically straight <lb/>tubular glands in a normal stroma (Figure 4 B). Pathological examination of uterus on <lb/>3 months after the 3-DGIUD placement: Endometrial epithelium was intact (Figure 4 <lb/>C and D), interstitial cells were edema, short fusiform and dense. A small number of <lb/>glands were curved and vacuole. The spiral artery was hyperplasia on 3 months after <lb/>3-DGIUD placement (Figure 4 C). After the 3-DGIUD placement for 12 months, <lb/>endometrial monolayer columnar epithelium was mostly intact, focal epithelial cells <lb/>were loss with focal hemorrhage, and a few neutrophils infiltration were observed. <lb/>Some glands secreted vacuoles. The vitreous degeneration was found in the basal <lb/>layer and the superficial muscle layer; and the interstitial spiral arterioles developed <lb/>well (Figure 4 D). <lb/>Changes in the immunohistochemistry <lb/>There was no difference in cell distribution and staining intensity of the expression of <lb/>ER, PR and PAX2 between non-surgical rhesus macaque (No.2, control group) and <lb/>the 3-DGIUD placement group. The Figure 5 illustrates representative examples of <lb/>the ER, PR and PAX2 immunostaining of uterine sections of normal endometrium <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>(No. 2, control) (Figure 5 A, C and E) and the 3-DGIUD group (Figure 5 B, D and F). <lb/>The positive ER, PR and PAX2 were shown in the nuclear and cytoplasmic <lb/>immunostaining of endometrial glands. ER, PR and PAX2 expression status in <lb/>endometrium was normal (Figure 5 B, D and F). No loss, increase and decrease of <lb/>ER, PR and PAX2 protein expression were found. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Principal findings of the study <lb/>We designed the shape of the 3-DGIUD by using nitinol wire, performed rhesus <lb/>macaque experiments, and investigated the changes in the uterus of rhesus macaques <lb/>in this study. The uterine shape and size of the rhesus macaque were similar to human <lb/>(only smaller than human). Macaques (non-human primate animal) may be the best <lb/>animal model for experiment of IUDs. We explored that the weight and uterine size of <lb/>macaques increased on 3 months and 12 months after the 3-DGIUD placement. <lb/>Changes in endometrial epithelium by the local oppression of the 3-DGIUD were <lb/>observed. No alterations were found in the expression of endometrial ER, PR and <lb/>PAX2 after the 3-DGIUD placement. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Results of the study in the context of other observations <lb/>Materials of the frame of IUDs: The frame of currently used IUD is made of <lb/>stainless steel and plastic, and included copper or additional hormones [27,28]. The <lb/>Cu (CuT380A) IUD is the only non-hormonal LARC device approved by the United <lb/>States Food and Drug Administration (FDA) [29]. The Cu 2+ of Cu-IUD-releasing <lb/>such as small T-shaped devices which made of flexible plastic, can kill sperm. The <lb/>Cu-IUD is a LARC (up to twelve years), however some women discontinue use due <lb/>to undesired side effects such as pain or cramping and complaints of heavy bleeding <lb/>[14-16,28]. The high rate of amenorrhea is often seen with the higher progestin <lb/>devices [30,31]. In present study, the frame of the new 3-DGIUD is made of nitinol <lb/>wire and silicone rubber. The nitinol wire is no toxic and used widely in clinical such <lb/>as orthopedics, bone and cardiovascular stents. The nitinol frame was covered with <lb/>silicone rubber, to prevent the 3-DGIUD from adhering to the endometrium. The <lb/>metal copper and progestin are not used for the 3-DGIUD. These may avoid side <lb/>effect of copper and hormone IUDs. <lb/>Efficacy and side effects of IUDs: Proper installation of IUD or IUD system will <lb/>reduce adverse effects and improve acceptability, resulting in enhanced continuation <lb/>of the IUD use [32]. Cramping pain, erratic bleeding or menorrhagia and expulsion of <lb/>IUDs may be caused by the dimensional incompatibility. In the present study, the <lb/>small type of 3-DGIUD was expulsion in one macaque at 3 months. The remaining 8 <lb/>macaques, no pregnancy occurred after surgery. Therefore, the size of IUD is too <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>small, easy to fall off, leading to pregnancy. On the other hand, menorrhagia, <lb/>dislocation or expulsion and contraceptive efficacy may be affected by the shape and <lb/>the weight of IUDs. If the shape is too large or the weight is too heavy of the IUD, <lb/>severe compression will be caused. The rigidity of the inserted tube may also be <lb/>linked to risks [33,34]. In the present study, we improved the shape of IUDs. The <lb/>three-dimensional structure for macaques replaced the two-dimensional structure of <lb/>the commonly used IUDs. The weight of the 3-DGIUD&apos;s frame was light. The space <lb/>of uterine cavity was occupied by the 3-DGIUD and embryo implantation was <lb/>interfered. Nitinol has a memory function, and can restore to the designed shape at <lb/>body temperature. It has a good flexibility, may be conformed to the contraction and <lb/>activity of the uterus, and avoided uterine perforation. <lb/>The contraceptive efficacy is very important for IUDs. Wu et al. reported [35] that <lb/>the LNG-IUS placed in 3 monkeys, expulsion of device is found in one monkey. In <lb/>human women, the expulsion rate of postpartum IUD varies according to the <lb/>placement time, delivery method, and the type of IUDs, ranging from 1.9% to 29.7% <lb/>[36-39], while removal rates are 3.6% to 19.3% due to associate side effects <lb/>(bleeding, pain and discharge) [36,38]. <lb/>Clinical implications of the study <lb/>Effects of IUDs on the uterus: Wang et al. [40] reported that the chronic endometrial <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>inflammation of histologic features occurs after placement a bare copper wire to <lb/>contraception in the uterus of rhesus macaques. The chronic and non-specific <lb/>endometrial inflammation may be one of contraceptive effects of the Cu-IUD. The <lb/>strong local inflammatory response is induced by LNG-IUS for the transplant <lb/>recipients as in the healthy control [41]. <lb/>The detection of ER, PR and PAX2 expression can be used to predict the <lb/>response of endometrial hyperplasia and cancer for IUD use: Two studies <lb/>reported that IUD has nothing to do with the increased risk of breast cancer [42,43], <lb/>whereas other studies reported that IUDs are associated with an increased risk of <lb/>breast cancer [44,45]. In the LNG-IUS used patients, the recurrence and formation of <lb/>endometrial polyp may be inhibited through lowering the expression of ER and PR <lb/>[46]. The LNG-IUS can reduce the expression of ER and PR in endometrium and <lb/>inhibit endometrial proliferation [47]. When the conservative treatment with LNG <lb/>-IUS failed, the expression of PR and ER of these patients were higher [48]. The <lb/>complete down-regulation of PR and ER expression in uterine glands and stroma is <lb/>caused by the LNG-IUS in human endometrial hyperplasia [49]. The LNG released <lb/>locally from the IUD has a depressive effect on the ER and PR, which may contribute <lb/>to the contraceptive effect of this type of IUD and may also be the causes of <lb/>LNG-IUS-induced irregular bleeding and amenorrhoea [50]. In this study, PAX2 <lb/>expression was normal, and there was no decrease, loss or over-expression after <lb/>placement 3-DGIUD. PAX2 is a downstream gene in the steroid hormone receptor <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>signal pathway. It is over-expressed in endometrial cancer and benign endometrial <lb/>hyperplasia [51]. Recently, Monte et al. [23] and Quick et al. [25] reported that PAX2 <lb/>deficiency in up to 77% of endometrial adenocarcinoma and 71% of patients with <lb/>atypical endometrial hyperplasia. As an oncogene involves in the development of <lb/>endometrial cancer, the expression of PAX2 is increased in the neoplastic lesion <lb/>progresses from a premalignant state to endometrial cancer. Knock-down of PAX2 <lb/>may lead to the decrease of cell viability, invasion and migration, while PAX2 <lb/>over-expression causes to the opposite effects. PAX2 acts as a tumor suppressor in <lb/>proliferative and self-renewing endometrial epithelial cells [23]. <lb/>Research implications <lb/>Unanswered questions: Birth control plays pivotal roles in the reduction of maternal, <lb/>infant, and child mortality. As the main method of contraception, IUD is the focus of <lb/>clinical research. Questions relating to the risks of IUD use remain unanswered. The <lb/>material, size and shape of the IUD have significant impacts on contraceptive <lb/>efficacy, and side effects may be avoided or decreased by changes in the shape and <lb/>materials of IUDs. The size of IUDs is too small to be expelled [33,34]. In the present <lb/>study, a small type of 3-DGIUD was expelled from the uterus after 3 months. <lb/>Proposals for future research: Contraceptive effectiveness and side effects of <lb/>IUDs should be studied by improvement of the material and the shape of IUDs. The <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>material IUDs must be non-toxic and to fit for the uterus. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, despite the 3-DGIUD was developed for macaques, it is likely that <lb/>improvement of the shape and the materials for currently used IUD of human <lb/>according to this study. The 3-DGIUD was non-toxic and had good contraceptive <lb/>effectiveness for macaques. <lb/></body>

			<div type="funding">Funding Statement <lb/>The author(s) received no specific funding for this work. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability <lb/>All relevant data are within the paper and its Supporting Information files. <lb/></div>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1]. Finer LB, Zolna MR. Declines in unintended pregnancy in the United States, 2008-2011. N <lb/>Engl J Med. 2016;374(9):843-852. <lb/>[2]. Ding R, Guo C, Song X, Zheng X. Male knowledge, attitude and practice and partner <lb/>pregnancy among Chinese unmarried youth. PLoS One. 2019;14(3):e0214452. <lb/>[3]. Liu J, Wu S, Xu J, Temmerman M, Zhang WH; INPAC Group. Is repeat abortion a public <lb/>health problem among Chinese adolescents? A cross-sectional survey in 30 provinces. Int J <lb/>Environ Res Public Health. 2019;16(5). pii: E794. <lb/>[4]. Dina B, Peipert LJ, Zhao Q, Peipert JF. Anticipated pain as a predictor of discomfort with <lb/>intrauterine device placement. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2018;218(2):236.e1-236.e9. <lb/>[5]. Huang Z, Gao Y, Wen W, Li H, Zheng W, Shu XO, Beeghly-Fadiel A. Contraceptive <lb/>methods and ovarian cancer risk among Chinese women: A report from the Shanghai women&apos;s <lb/>health study. Int J Cancer. 2015;137(3):607-614. <lb/>[6]. Bednarek PH, Creinin MD, Reeves MF, Cwiak C, Espey E, Jensen JT; Post-Aspiration IUD <lb/>Randomization (PAIR) Study Trial Group. Immediate versus delayed IUD insertion after <lb/>uterine aspiration. N Engl J Med 2011;364:2208-2217. <lb/>[7]. Eggebroten JL, Sanders JN, Turok DK. Immediate postpartum intrauterine device and implant <lb/>program outcomes: a prospective analysis. Am J Obstet Gynecol. 2017;217(1):51.e1-51.e7. <lb/>[8]. Wang C. Trends in contraceptive use and determinants of choice in China: 1980-2010. <lb/>Contraception. 2012;85:570-579. <lb/>[9]. Shabaik SA, Awaida JY, Xandre P, Nelson AL. Contraceptive beliefs and practices of <lb/>American Muslim women. J Womens Health (Larchmt). 2019;22. <lb/>[10]. Hamy AS, Abuellellah H, Hocini H, Coussy F, Gorins A, Serfaty D, Tournant B, Perret F, <lb/>Bonfils S, Giacchetti S, Cuvier C, Espie M. Contraception after breast cancer: a retrospective <lb/>review of the practice among French gynecologists in the 2000&apos;s. Eur J Gynaecol Oncol. <lb/>2014;35(2):149-153. <lb/>[11]. Hubacher D, Chen PL, Park S. Side effects from the copper IUD: do they decrease over <lb/>time? Contraception. 2009;79(5):356-562. <lb/>[12]. GoldstuckND, Wildemeersch D. Role of uterine forces in intrauterine device embedment, <lb/>perforation, and expulsion. Int J Womens Health. 2014; 6: 735-744. <lb/>[13]. Sano M, Nemoto K, Miura T, Suzuki Y. Endoscopic treatment of intrauterine device <lb/>migration into the bladder with stone formation. Endourol Case Rep. 2017;3(1):105-107. <lb/>[14]. Mathew MS, Davis J , Joseph K . Green synthesis of a plant-derived protein protected copper <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>quantum cluster for intrauterine device application. Analyst. 2018;143(16):3841-3849. <lb/>[15]. Ramakrishnan R, B B, Aprem AS. Controlled release of copper from an intrauterine device <lb/>using a biodegradable polymer. Contraception. 2015;92(6):585-588. <lb/>[16]. Zhang S, Li Y, Yu P, Chen T, Zhou W, Zhang W, Liu J. In vitro release of cupric ion from <lb/>intrauterine devices: influence of frame, shape, copper surface area and indomethacin. Biomed <lb/>Microdevices. 2015;17(1):19. <lb/>[17]. Beckert V, Ahlers C, Frenz AK, Gerlinger C, Bannemerschult R, Lukkari-Lax E. Bleeding <lb/>patterns with the 19.5 mg LNG-IUS, with special focus on the first year of use: implications <lb/>for counselling. Eur J Contracept Reprod Health Care. 2019;24(4):251-259. <lb/>[18]. Papaikonomou K, Kopp Kallner H, Söderdahl F, Gemzell-Danielsson K. Mifepristone <lb/>treatment prior to insertion of a levonorgestrel releasing intrauterine system for improved <lb/>bleeding control -a randomized controlled trial. Hum Reprod. 2018;33(11):2002-2009. <lb/>[19]. Ortiz ME, Croxatto HB, Bardin CW. Mechanisms of action of intrauterine devices. <lb/>ObstetGynecolSurv. 1996;51(12 Suppl):S42-51. <lb/>[20]. Reinprayoon D, Taneepanichskul S, Niruthisard S, Suwajanakon S. Uterine histopathologic <lb/>changes after Cu-Fix intrauterine device insertion. Contraception. 1999;59(1):63-65. <lb/>[21].Critchley HO, Wang H, Jones RL, Kelly RW, Drudy TA, Gebbie AE, Buckley CH, McNeilly <lb/>AS, Glasier AF. Morphological and functional features of endometrial decidualization fo <lb/>llowing long-term intrauterine levonorgestrel delivery. Hum Reprod. 1998;13(5):1218-1224. <lb/>[22]. Guttinger A, Critchley HO. Endometrial effects of intrauterine levonorgestrel. <lb/>Contraception. 2007;75(6 Suppl):S93-98. <lb/>[23]. Monte NM, Webster KA, Neuberg D, Dressler GR, Mutter GL. Joint loss of PAX2 and <lb/>PTEN expression in endometrial precancers and cancer. Cancer Res. 2010;70(15):6225-6232. <lb/>[24]. Joiner AK, Quick CM, Jeffus SK. Pax2 expression in simultaneously diagnosed WHO and <lb/>EIN classification systems. Int J Gynecol Pathol. 2015;34(1):40-6. <lb/>[25]. Quick CM, Laury AR, Monte NM, Mutter GL. Utility of PAX2 as a marker for diagnosis of <lb/>endometrial intraepithelial neoplasia. Am J Clin Pathol. 2012;138(5):678-684. <lb/>[26]. Qiu Y, Wang LG, Zhang MH, Zhang YP, Zhang AD, Yang DT. A new experimental <lb/>three-dimensional, reticular intrauterine device (3-DRIUD) composed of nitinol and silicone <lb/>rubber. Contraception. 2013;88(1):31-36. <lb/>[27]. Gemzell-Danielsson K, Schellschmidt I, Apter D. A randomized, phase II study describing <lb/>the efficacy, bleeding profile, and safety of two low-dose levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine <lb/>contraceptive systems and Mirena. FertilSteril. 2012;97:616-622. <lb/>[28]. Costescu DJ. Levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine systems for long-acting contraception: <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>current perspectives, safety, and patient counseling. Int J Womens Health. 2016;8:589-598. <lb/>[29]. Sanders JN, Adkins DE, Kaur S, Storck K, Gawron LM, Turok DK. Bleeding, cramping, and <lb/>satisfaction among new copper IUD users: A prospective study. PLoS One. <lb/>2018;13(11):e0199724. <lb/>[30]. Nelson AL. LNG-IUS 12: a 19.5 levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system for prevention <lb/>of pregnancy for up to five years. Expert Opin Drug Deliv. 2017;14(9):1131-1140. <lb/>[31]. Parks C, Peipert JF. Eliminating health disparities in unintended pregnancy with long-acting <lb/>reversible contraception (LARC). Am J Obstet Gy necol. 2016;214(6):681-688. <lb/>[32]. Wildemeersch D, Hasskamp T, Nolte K, Jandi S, Pett A, Linden S, van Santen M, Julen O. <lb/>A multicenter study assessing uterine cavity width in over 400 nulliparous women seeking <lb/>IUD insertion using 2D and 3D sonography. Eur J ObstetGynecolReprod Biol. <lb/>2016;206:232-238. <lb/>[33]. Toumi O, Ammar H, Ghdira A, et al. Pelvic abscess complicating sigmoid colon perforation <lb/>by migrating intrauterine device: a case report and review of the literature. Int J Surg Case <lb/>Rep 2018;42:60-63. <lb/>[34]. Harrison-Woolrych M, Ashton J, Coulter D. Uterine perforation on intrauterine device <lb/>insertion: is the incidence higher than previously reported? Contraception 2003;67:53-56. <lb/>[35]. Wu C, Xia W, Wu X, Li R, Huang X, Yan Y, Huang D. Effect of domestically-made <lb/>levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine device on the endocrine system and menstruation in <lb/>monkeys. J Tongji Med Univ. 1996;16(2):117-120. <lb/>[36]. Makins A, Taghinejadi N, Sethi M, Machiyama K, Munganyizi P, Odongo E, Divakar H, <lb/>Fatima P, Thapa K, Perera G, Arulkumaran S. FIGO postpartum intrauterine device initiative: <lb/>Complication rates across six countries. Int J Gynaecol Obstet. 2018;143 Suppl 1:20-27. <lb/>[37]. Jatlaoui TC, Whiteman MK, Jeng G, Tepper NK, Berry-Bibee E, Jamieson DJ, Marchbanks <lb/>PA, Curtis KM. Intrauterine Device Expulsion After Postpartum Placement: A Systematic <lb/>Review and Meta-analysis. Obstet Gynecol. 2018;132(4):895-905. <lb/>[38]. Schnyer AN, Jensen JT, Edelman A, Han L. Do menstrual cups increase risk of IUD <lb/>expulsion? A survey of self-reported IUD and menstrual hygiene product use in the United <lb/>States. Eur J Contracept Reprod Health Care. 2019;23:1-5. <lb/>[39]. Kumar S, Srivastava A, Sharma S, Yadav V, Mittal A, Kim YM, Nash-Mercado A, <lb/>Reijneveld SA, Sood B. One-year continuation of postpartum intrauterine contraceptive <lb/>device: findings from a retrospective cohort study in India. Contraception. <lb/>2019;99(4):212-216. <lb/>[40]. Wang YY, Hu SF, Rao M, Xia XP, Xia W, Zhu CH. Antifertility effectiveness of a novel <lb/>polymer matrix composite and its influence on the endometrium in rhesus macaques (Macaca <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>mulatta). Contraception. 2019;100(2):132-136. <lb/>[41]. Kim CR, Martinez-Maza O, Magpantay L, Magyar C, Gornbein J, Rible R, Sullivan P. <lb/>Immunologic evaluation of the endometrium with a levonorgestrel intrauterine device in solid <lb/>organ transplant women and healthy controls. Contraception. 2016;94(5):534-540. <lb/>[42]. Backman T, Rauramo I, Jaakkola K, Inki P, Vaahtera K, Launonen A, Koskenvuo M. Use of <lb/>the <lb/>levonorgestrel-releasing <lb/>intrauterine <lb/>system <lb/>and <lb/>breast <lb/>cancer. Obstet <lb/>Gynecol. 2005;106(4):813-817. <lb/>[43]. Fu Y, Zhuang Z. Long-term effects of levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system on <lb/>tamoxifen-treated breast cancer patients: a meta-analysis. Int J Clin Exp Pathol. <lb/>2014;7(10):6419-6429. <lb/>[44]. Lyytinen HK, Dyba T, Ylikorkala O, Pukkala EI. A case-control study on hormone therapy <lb/>as a risk factor for breast cancer in Finland: intrauterine system carries a risk as well. Int J <lb/>Cancer. 2010;126(2):483-9. <lb/>[45]. Soini T, Hurskainen R, Grenman S, Maenpaa J, Paavonen J, Joensuu H, Pukkala E. <lb/>Levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine system and the risk of breast cancer: A nationwide <lb/>cohort study. Acta Oncol. 2016;55(2):188-192. <lb/>[46]. Wu X, Liu X, Jin X, Xu X. Effects of levonorgestrel intrauterine system on the expressions <lb/>of estrogen receptor, progesterone receptor and insulin-like growth factor-1. Zhonghua Yi Xue <lb/>Za Zhi. 2014;94(35):2763-2765. <lb/>[47]. Weng M, Li L, Feng S, Xie M, Hong S. Effects of levonorgestrel-releasing intrauterine <lb/>system on endometrial estrogen and progesterone receptors in patients with endometrial <lb/>hyperplasia. Nan Fang Yi Ke Da Xue Xue Bao. 2012 Sep;32(9):1350-1354. <lb/>[48]. Reyes HD, Carlson MJ, Devor EJ, Zhang Y, Thiel KW, Samuelson MI, McDonald M, Yang <lb/>S, Stephan JM, Savage EC, Dai D, Goodheart MJ, Leslie KK. Down regulation of FOXO1 <lb/>mRNA levels predicts treatment failure in patients with endometrial pathology conservatively <lb/>managed <lb/>with <lb/>progestin-containing <lb/>intrauterine <lb/>devices. <lb/>Gynecol <lb/>Oncol. <lb/>2016;140(1):152-160. <lb/>[49]. Vereide AB, Kaino T, Sager G, Arnes M, Ørbo A. Effect of levonorgestrel IUD and oral <lb/>medroxyprogesterone acetate on glandular and stromal progesterone receptors (PRA and <lb/>PRB), and estrogen receptors (ER-alpha and ER-beta) in human endometrial hyperplasia. <lb/>Gynecol Oncol. 2006;101(2):214-223. <lb/>[50]. Critchley HO, Wang H, Kelly RW, Gebbie AE, Glasier AF. Progestin receptor isoforms and <lb/>prostaglandin dehydrogenase in the endometrium of women using a levonorgestrel-releasing <lb/>intrauterine system. Hum Reprod. 1998;13(5):1210-1217. <lb/>[51]. Harshman LA, Brophy PD. PAX2 in human kidney malformations and <lb/>disease. PediatrNephrol. 2012;27:1265-1275 <lb/>26 <lb/>527 <lb/>528 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Tables in text <lb/>Table 1. The weight and uterine size by ultrasound before and during surgery <lb/>Weight <lb/>Uterine size (mm) * <lb/>Ultrasound (mm) * <lb/>No. (kg) height width thickness <lb/>longitudinal transverse 3-DGIUD <lb/>1 <lb/>6.45 <lb/>22 <lb/>18 <lb/>15 <lb/>26.6 18.8 <lb/>20.9 <lb/>yes <lb/>2 <lb/>5.50 <lb/>28 <lb/>24 <lb/>16 <lb/>27.3 18.5 <lb/>18.5 <lb/>yes <lb/>3 <lb/>8.50 <lb/>32 <lb/>22 <lb/>17 <lb/>27.5 20.8 <lb/>21.2 <lb/>yes <lb/>4 <lb/>6.10 <lb/>26 <lb/>22 <lb/>15 <lb/>26.9 16.6 <lb/>18.2 <lb/>yes <lb/>5 <lb/>6.10 <lb/>29 <lb/>20 <lb/>17 <lb/>29.6 18.8 <lb/>23.4 <lb/>yes <lb/>6 <lb/>7.10 <lb/>27 <lb/>22 <lb/>18 <lb/>30.6 20.6 <lb/>23.5 <lb/>yes <lb/>7 <lb/>6.85 <lb/>32 <lb/>24 <lb/>21 <lb/>32.5 220 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>yes <lb/>8 <lb/>5.25 <lb/>25 <lb/>18 <lb/>15 <lb/>25.9 16.8 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>yes <lb/>9 <lb/>5.75 <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>22 <lb/>26.2 22.5 <lb/>25.1 <lb/>yes <lb/>10 6.30 <lb/>28 <lb/>24 <lb/>16 <lb/>28.6 18.2 <lb/>22.0 <lb/>no <lb/>11 7.20 <lb/>28 <lb/>22 <lb/>17 <lb/>30.8 20.7 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>no <lb/>12 7.32 <lb/>32 <lb/>25 <lb/>18 <lb/>32.8 20.8 <lb/>21.7 <lb/>no <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>13 6.20 <lb/>25 <lb/>22 <lb/>16 <lb/>27.8 19.0 <lb/>18.0 <lb/>no <lb/>14 5.90 <lb/>28 <lb/>20 <lb/>18 <lb/>28.8 20.7 <lb/>19.0 <lb/>no <lb/>15 6.25 <lb/>31 <lb/>26 <lb/>19 <lb/>29.5 20.1 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>no <lb/>16 5.30 <lb/>27 <lb/>21 <lb/>15 <lb/>27.5 16.1 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>no <lb/>17 6.33 <lb/>26 <lb/>20 <lb/>17 <lb/>27.8 17.5 <lb/>20.0 <lb/>no <lb/>18 8.10 <lb/>33 <lb/>23 <lb/>20 <lb/>33.5 20.1 <lb/>24.3 <lb/>no <lb/>*Measured the uterine corpus, not included the cervix. The number 1-9 was in the <lb/>experimental group (3-DGIUD) and the number 10-18 was in the sham operation. <lb/>Table 2. Weight and uterine size of macaques on 3 and 12 months after surgery <lb/>During operation <lb/>After 3 Months After 12 Months <lb/>Weight (kg) <lb/>6.4 ± 1.1 (8) <lb/>6.7 ± 1.0 (8) a <lb/>6.8 ± 1.2 (6) b <lb/>Uterine corpus (mm) <lb/>Height <lb/>27.5 ± 4.0 (6) <lb/>31.3 ± 5.1 (6) c <lb/>Width <lb/>21.5 ± 1.0 (6) <lb/>23.2± 3.2 (6) d <lb/>Thickness <lb/>16.7 ± 2.7 (6) <lb/>18.7 ± 2.3 (6) e <lb/>29 <lb/>Ultrasound (mm) <lb/>Before operation <lb/>Longitudinal-1 <lb/>28.3 ± 2.4 (8) <lb/>29.1 ± 2.3 (8) f <lb/>Longitudinal-2 <lb/>19.9 ± 1.9 (8) <lb/>20.0 ± 2.1 (8) g <lb/>Transverse <lb/>22.2 ± 2.1 (8) <lb/>28.5 ± 2.1 (8) h <lb/>Notes: The number in brackets is the rhesus macaques (n). Superscript letter a-e was <lb/>compared with during operation and f-h was compared with before operation; a t = <lb/>1.991, P = 0.087, b t = 4.812, P = 0.005; c t = 3.557, P = 0.016; d t = 7.906, P = 0.001; e <lb/>t = 5.477, P = 0.003; f t = 7.112, P = 0.000; g t = 2.333, P = 0.052; h t = 6.563, P = <lb/>0.000. Fisher&apos;s Exact Test. <lb/>Figure legends <lb/>Figure 1. Design and manufacture of the novel three-dimensional grid intrauterine <lb/>device (3-DGIUD) for rhesus macaques. (A) Designed map of 3-DGIUD. (B) Actual <lb/>3-DGIUD, two types, large and small. (C) Inserters with the 3-DGIUD for rhesus <lb/>macaques. (D) Measured 3-DGIUD size. <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Placement of 3-DGIUD. (a) The lower abdominal incision. (b) Measuring <lb/>the uterine size. (c) A catheter inserted into the uterine cavity. (d) After placement of <lb/>3-DGIUD, the incision in the uterus was sutured. <lb/>Figure 3. The uterine ultrasound of rhesus macaques. (A) and (B), before surgery, the <lb/>longitudinal section and the transverse section. (C) and (D), one month and 3 months <lb/>after surgery, strong echo of the large type of 3-DGIUD. (E), the small type of <lb/>3-DGIUD in the uterine cavity. (F), pregnancy, fetal in the uterus. <lb/>Figure 4. The 3-DGIUD and endometrial histology of macaques. (A), the 3-DGIUD <lb/>in the uterine cavity. (B), the uterine histology of the control (No.1, non-operation <lb/>macaque) (20 × magnifications). (C), the uterine histology of macaque on 3 months <lb/>after the 3-DGIUD placement (20 × magnifications). (D), the uterine histology of <lb/>macaque on 12 months after the 3-DGIUD placement (25 × magnifications). <lb/>Figure 5. Uterine immunohistochemistry of the ER, PR and PAX2 on 12 months after <lb/>surgery. (A), (C) and (E), non-operation macaque (No. 2, control). (B), (D) and (F), <lb/>the 3-DGIUD group macaque. (A) and (B), the ER immunostaining, both were <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>599 <lb/>similar. (C) and (D), the PR immunostaining, both were similar. (E) and (F), the <lb/>600 <lb/>PAX2 immunostaining, both were similar. All were 25 × magnifications. </body>


	</text>
</tei>
