<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Design of Experiments for Fine-Mapping Quantitative <lb/>Trait Loci in Livestock Populations <lb/>Dörte Wittenburg * , Sarah Bonk † , Michael Doschoris * , Henry Reyer ‡ <lb/>December 17, 2019 <lb/> * Leibniz Institute for Farm Animal Biology, Institute of Genetics and Biometry, 18196 <lb/>Dummerstorf, Germany <lb/> † University Medicine Greifswald, Department of Psychiatry and Psychotherapy, 17475 <lb/>Greifswald, Germany <lb/> ‡ Leibniz Institute for Farm Animal Biology, Institute of Genome Biology, 18196 Dum-<lb/>merstorf, Germany <lb/></front>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Running title: Experimental design <lb/>Keywords: Single nucleotide polymorphism, statistical power, target region, SNP-BLUP, <lb/>linkage disequilibrium <lb/>Corresponding author: <lb/>Dörte Wittenburg <lb/>Leibniz Institute for Farm Animal Biology <lb/>Institute of Genetics and Biometry <lb/>Wilhelm-Stahl-Allee 2 <lb/>18196 Dummerstorf, Germany <lb/>Phone +49 38208 68930 <lb/>Email wittenburg@fbn-dummerstorf.de <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>Abstract <lb/>Single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) which capture a significant impact on <lb/>a trait can be identified with genome-wide association studies. High linkage disequi-<lb/>librium (LD) among SNPs makes it difficult to identify causative variants correctly. <lb/>Thus, often target regions instead of single SNPs are reported. Sample size has not <lb/>only a crucial impact on the precision of parameter estimates, it also ensures that a <lb/>desired level of statistical power can be reached. We study the design of experiments <lb/>for fine-mapping of signals of a quantitative trait locus in such a target region. <lb/>A multi-locus model allows to identify causative variants simultaneously, to state <lb/>their positions more precisely and to account for existing dependencies. Based on <lb/>the commonly applied SNP-BLUP approach, we determine the z-score statistic for <lb/>locally testing non-zero SNP effects and investigate its distribution under the al-<lb/>ternative hypothesis. This quantity employs the theoretical instead of observed <lb/>dependence between SNPs; it can be set up as a function of paternal and maternal <lb/>LD for any given population structure. <lb/>We simulated multiple paternal half-sib families and considered a target region of <lb/>1 Mbp. A bimodal distribution of estimated sample size was observed, particu-<lb/>larly if more than two causative variants were assumed. The median of estimates <lb/>constituted the final proposal of optimal sample size; it was consistently less than <lb/>sample size estimated from single-SNP investigations which was used as a baseline <lb/>approach. The second mode pointed to inflated sample sizes and could be explained <lb/>by blocks of varying linkage phases leading to negative correlations between SNPs. <lb/>Optimal sample size increased almost linearly with number of signals to be identified <lb/>but depended much stronger on the assumption on heritability. For instance, three <lb/>times as many samples were required if heritability was 0.1 compared to 0.3. These <lb/>results enable the resource-saving design of future experiments for fine-mapping of <lb/>candidate variants in structured and unstructured populations. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>1 Introduction <lb/>Genomewide association studies (GWAS) help exploring the relationship between genetic <lb/>and phenotypic variation. Genetic variation is often expressed in terms of genomic markers <lb/>such as single nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs). Identified variants may or may not be <lb/>part of known genes. In a candidate-gene approach, variants are then assigned to the <lb/>closest known gene and their functional importance can be studied further (e.g., Reyer <lb/>et al., 2015). The functional meaning of a variant may be differently interpreted if, due to <lb/>statistical uncertainty, it was identified a few kbp upstream or downstream of its position. <lb/>In general, it could be a complicated task to detect single loci as reported by Sahana et al. <lb/>(2014) in a study on udder health in dairy cattle. Instead of identifying important SNPs <lb/>for clinical mastitis, only target regions were found. For instance, a window of about 1 Mbp <lb/>length was detected on BTA6. A statistical reason for this complication lies in the high <lb/>multicollinearity among predictor variables due to linkage and linkage disequilibrium (LD) <lb/>between SNPs (e.g., Hampel et al., 2018). Region-based aggregation tests in biologically <lb/>relevant regions (e.g., genes; Lee et al., 2014) or fine-mapping approaches in independent <lb/>partitions of the genome (Schaid et al., 2018) have been suggested as powerful options. To <lb/>eventually unravel which of the variants in a target region might be truly related to the <lb/>trait, a follow-up experiment is recommended. The experimental design should account <lb/>for the dependence between SNPs to ensure sufficient statistical power. This will be <lb/>reflected in the sample size required. Statistical tools for the design of experiments (e.g., <lb/>QUANTO; Gauderman &amp; Morrison, 2007) could not provide this until now. However, the <lb/>denser the SNP chip is, the higher will be the correlation between SNPs. For instance, <lb/>the target region on BTA6 of Sahana&apos;s paper covers 17 SNPs using a 50k SNP panel, 192 <lb/>SNPs based on a 700k SNP panel and 21 796 SNPs in case of DNA sequence (Sahana <lb/>et al., 2014; Schnabel, 2018). <lb/>In theory, it can be determined what sample size is needed for discovering a new variant <lb/>in a single-locus model at a given power, e.g., 80 %. Such investigations are based on <lb/>ANOVA (one way classification; Luo, 1998) and can also account for a hypothetical degree <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>of LD between causative variant and SNP (Pritchard &amp; Przeworski, 2001; Khatkar et al., <lb/>2008). Proposals for an optimum experimental design have been made for mapping of a <lb/>quantitative trait locus (QTL) in different population structures (e.g., F2, backcross or <lb/>daughter design; Weller, 2001). However, it is not clear what sample size is required to <lb/>distinguish multiple independent signals of a QTL using dense marker data. <lb/>Moreover, the power of association analysis depends not only on sample size and popula-<lb/>tion parameters (e.g., heritability) but also on the underlying statistical model. Among <lb/>myriad options for whole genome regression models, SNP-BLUP is an obvious choice for <lb/>estimating genetic effects captured by all SNPs simultaneously. Also because of its direct <lb/>relationship to GBLUP (e.g., Gualdrón Duarte et al., 2014), it is widely used in live-<lb/>stock (e.g., Koivula et al., 2012; Mucha et al., 2015) and beyond (e.g., Maier et al., 2015; <lb/>Kristensen et al., 2018). Being enormously relevant in practice, it has been upgraded to <lb/>comprise information of individuals with and without genotypic data in the framework of <lb/>single-step methods (Taskinen et al., 2017; Aguilar et al., 2019). Though directly or indi-<lb/>rectly estimated SNP effects are tested for being significantly different from zero (Aguilar <lb/>et al., 2019), reports on statistical power of the underlying study design are lacking. <lb/>This paper addresses the question how to design a follow-up experiment based on a <lb/>SNP-BLUP approach knowing that the predictor variables are so highly correlated. Our <lb/>objective is the theoretical inference of optimal sample size to fine-map a QTL signal or <lb/>to find evidence for multiple independent signals in a specified chunk of DNA. Eventually, <lb/>it should be possible to detect variants at their actual position with high power. This <lb/>paper concentrates on the case study of paternal half-sib families which is a typical family <lb/>structure in livestock (e.g., dairy cattle). But the methodology developed enables sample <lb/>size calculation for any population structure (e.g. full siblings, half siblings, mixture of <lb/>both, unrelated individuals). Given the number of families, SNPs, signals of QTL and <lb/>heritability, the optimal sample size is then presented as overall number of progeny. We <lb/>validated our approach using simulated data. Furthermore, publicly available bovine HD <lb/>SNP chip data helped verifying that the simulated linkage blocks resemble the genome <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>structure in dairy cattle. A discussion of our achievements complements this study. <lb/>2 Material and methods <lb/>The design of experiment requires a statistical model that combines phenotype with geno-<lb/>type data. Here, we assume a multiple-SNP approach that considers information of as <lb/>many SNPs as desired simultaneously. For comparing the outcome with a conventionally <lb/>used approach, a single-SNP model is specified. <lb/>2.1 Multi-SNPs model <lb/>For a joint association analysis of p SNPs, a regression model is fitted to a phenotype <lb/>y = (y 1 , . . . , y n ) of n individuals, <lb/>y = Xβ + e . <lb/>The n × p design matrix X contains the genotype codes: X j,k ∈ {1, 0, −1} for j = 1, . . . , n <lb/>and k = 1, 2, . . . , p. The columns of X and the vector y are centered within family and <lb/>scaled afterwards. This way, the model becomes independent of allele frequency. The <lb/>residual error term is e ∼ N (0, I n σ 2 <lb/>e ). Then the coefficient vector β is estimated using a <lb/>ridge regression approach as <lb/>β = (X X + λI p ) <lb/>−1 X y . <lb/>This step requires a penalty term λ which is practically obtained via cross-validation or <lb/>REML approach. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Next, we investigate a multiple testing problem. For each SNP k, k = 1, . . . , p, it is tested <lb/>H 0 : β k = 0 vs. H A : β k = 0 <lb/>(2.1) <lb/>with a suitable test statistic <lb/>T k = <lb/>β k <lb/>SD( β k ) <lb/>. <lb/>(2.2) <lb/>The calculation of power π requires the distribution of T k under H A , then <lb/>π(µ k ) = Pr(T k ≥ q 1−α/2 ) + Pr(T k &lt; q α/2 ) , <lb/>where q 1−α/2 and q α/2 denote the upper and lower threshold, respectively, of the distri-<lb/>bution of T k under H 0 with respect to a type-I error α. Due to the ridge approach, <lb/>requirements for fulfilling a t distribution do not hold (Searle, 1971, p. 57). Hence the <lb/>distribution of T k is approximated as normal and the distribution mean µ k is obtained <lb/>from the expectation and variance of the estimator β k . The moments are <lb/>E( β) = (X X + λI p ) <lb/>−1 X Xβ , <lb/>V ( β) = (X X + λI p ) <lb/>−1 X X (X X + λI p ) <lb/>−1 σ 2 <lb/>e . <lb/>The central point of our investigation is to substitute the correlation matrix 1 <lb/>n X X to <lb/>be observed in the progeny generation by the theoretical correlation matrix R. The <lb/>calculation of R requires a genetic map and genetic information of parents; its derivation <lb/>is shown in Appendix A. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Then the mean becomes <lb/>µ k = <lb/>√ <lb/>n <lb/>1 <lb/>σe (R + λ <lb/>n I p ) −1 Rβ k <lb/>(R + λ <lb/>n I p ) −1 R(R + λ <lb/>n I p ) −1 <lb/>k,k <lb/>. <lb/>(2.3) <lb/>Under H 0 µ k = 0. In order to calculate the optimal sample size, the experimenter has <lb/>to specify a set of parameters: number of SNPs (p) in the investigated window of DNA, <lb/>number of QTL signals to be detected (η), proportion of variance explained by the window <lb/>(h 2 ) and number of families (e.g., N sires). The input parameters for statistical power <lb/>calculation are inferred from this experimental set-up: <lb/>1. R requires haplotypes of N sires (plus genetic map and maternal LD in general). <lb/>2. We assume that all variants corresponding to the QTL signals contribute equally to <lb/>the genetic variance. Hence the relative effect size is determined at η QTL signals <lb/>as <lb/>β l <lb/>σ e <lb/>= <lb/>h 2 <lb/>η(1 − h 2 ) <lb/>for l in the set of QTL signals . <lb/>The remaining β&apos;s are 0. <lb/>3. The shrinkage parameter is derived corresponding to Hoerl et al. (1975), <lb/>λ = p <lb/>σ 2 <lb/>e <lb/>β β <lb/>= p <lb/>1 − h 2 <lb/>h 2 . <lb/>This is a rough approximation assuming linkage equilibrium between variants cor-<lb/>responding to the QTL signals. <lb/>We circumvent doing any assumption about the unknown positions of QTL signals by <lb/>taking a random sample of η positions. Then the optimal sample size is calculated over <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>a range of n (e.g., 1 − 5 000) employing the method of bisection. The minimum n that <lb/>exceeds a power of 80 % is selected as &quot;optimal&quot; and denoted as n opt . In order to get a <lb/>reliable estimate of optimal sample size, sampling is repeated 100 times, and the median <lb/>of n opt is suggested as final n * <lb/>opt . The overall type-I error was α = 0.01. <lb/>2.2 Single-SNP model <lb/>For comparison, we consider a single SNP k ∈ {1, . . . , p} in a sliding window over the <lb/>target region. Using the parameter definitions as above, the linear model in its simplest <lb/>form is <lb/>y = X k β k + e . <lb/>Then the regression coefficient is estimated via ordinary least squares as <lb/>β k = (X k X k ) <lb/>−1 X k y . <lb/>The null hypothesis testing problem (2.1) and the corresponding test statistic (2.2) also <lb/>apply in the single-SNP analysis. The test statistic is t-distributed with n − 1 degrees of <lb/>freedom and non-centrality parameter δ k (Searle, 1971, pp. 110), <lb/>δ k = <lb/>β k <lb/>σ e <lb/>√ <lb/>n . <lb/>This approach neglects any impact of the other SNPs in the target region on y. Thus, <lb/>a reduced pointwise error level (α k ) has to be employed to keep the overall type-I error <lb/>at α. Knowing the effective number of independent tests (M eff ), a suitable type-I-error <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>correction is <lb/>α k = α/M eff . <lb/>In accordance with the simpleM method of Gao et al. (2008), we suggest using R in-<lb/>stead of 1 <lb/>n X X for calculating M eff . More precisely, the number of eigenvalues of R that <lb/>contribute at least 99.5 % to the sum of all eigenvalues yields M eff . <lb/>2.3 Data and validation study <lb/>The software R version 3.6.1 (R Core Team, 2019) was employed in this study. Unless <lb/>otherwise stated, we implemented own R scripts. <lb/>Population genetic data were simulated using the R package AlphaSimR version 0.11.0 <lb/>(Faux et al., 2016). In total, 300 SNPs were spread in a chunk of DNA of 1 cM length. <lb/>This corresponds approximately to 1 Mbp. Five traits were simulated simultaneously, one <lb/>for each number of QTL signals affecting the trait, η = 1, . . . , 5. In case of multiple <lb/>QTL signals, effect sizes were equal. The founder population comprised 2 000 individuals <lb/>and constitutes the parent generation. Other population parameters were kept at default <lb/>settings. As the data simulation yielded no consistent pattern of SNP dependence, the <lb/>simulation of the parent population was repeated 100 times. The maternal LD in terms of <lb/>r 2 between adjacent SNPs was on average 0.45 and reflects high multicollinearity. In each <lb/>repetition, N = 10 sires were selected depending on their phenotype. Then, haplotypes <lb/>of all selected sires, or a subset thereof if N = 1 or N = 5, and 1 000 females were used <lb/>to set up the R matrix. Few loci with no variation were disregarded. Optimal sample <lb/>size was estimated based on R. Using the same parent generation, N males were selected <lb/>as sires of half-siblings in the progeny generation. The number of dams was determined <lb/>according to optimal sample size required. The simulation of the progeny generation was <lb/>also repeated 100 times to estimate and test SNP effects for validation purposes; this <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>yielded 100 × 100 data sets in total. The total heritability was h 2 ∈ {0.1, 0.2, 0.3}. For <lb/>each h 2 , data sets were simulated independently. <lb/>Additionally, to explore a direct relationship between assumed positions of QTL signals <lb/>and n opt , we selected arbitrarily a single repetition of simulation with h 2 = 0.1 and N = 10. <lb/>For this particular data set, we determined n opt for each SNP position (i.e., assuming one <lb/>QTL signal) and for all possible SNP pairs (i.e., assuming two QTL signals). <lb/>The R package asreml version 3.0 (Butler et al., 2009) was used for association analysis. <lb/>Other suitable R packages, such as rrBLUP (Endelman, 2011) or ridge (Cule et al., <lb/>2011), had difficulties to converge or produced almost zero variance components due to <lb/>the high multicollinearity of predictor variables. The multi-SNP model was applied to <lb/>all simulated scenarios as described in Section 2.1. Unlike in Section 2.2, the single-<lb/>SNP model considered an additional factor u ∼ N (0, Aσ 2 <lb/>a ) that accounts for background <lb/>genetic effects due to the relationship between individuals. This was modeled similarly, <lb/>e.g., in EMMAX (Kang et al., 2010) but we used the numerator relationship matrix A for <lb/>computational convenience. The pointwise testing of SNP effects was followed by p-value <lb/>correction according to Benjamini &amp; Hochberg (1995). P -values from the multi-SNP <lb/>model were not altered. The outcome was used to assess sensitivity and specificity of the <lb/>multi-SNP and single-SNP model. For this, a window of 0.01 cM to both sides of a QTL <lb/>signal (covering 2-3 SNPs) was specified in order to accept a significant SNP as a true <lb/>positive result. Then, the true-positive rate (TPR) reflected sensitivity. Specificity was <lb/>obtained as 1− the false-positive rate (FPR), and ROC curves were produced from TPR <lb/>and FPR. <lb/>To evaluate how realistically the simulation of genetic data worked, empirical HD SNP <lb/>chip data from the Dryad repository have been used (Bermingham et al., 2013). These <lb/>data included 1 151 dairy cows with no pedigree specification. We selected an arbitrary <lb/>window on BTA7 comprising 300 SNPs on 1.16 Mbp and phased haplotypes of all animals <lb/>using AlphaPhase (Hickey et al., 2011). We selected randomly 10 animals and marked <lb/>them as sires in order to set up a matrix R. Because of the high SNP density, genetic <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>distances were approximated linearly, i.e., 1 Mbp ≈ 1 cM. Maternal LD was roughly <lb/>approximated from haplotype frequencies of all animals. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">2.4 Data availability <lb/>R scripts used to simulate and analyze data are available upon request. The empirical <lb/>bovine HD SNP chip data are accessible through the Dryad repository https://doi. <lb/>org/10.5061/dryad.519bm (Bermingham et al., 2013). <lb/></div>

			<body>3 Results <lb/>The optimal sample size suggested by the single-SNP model required the effective number <lb/>of independent tests which was on average M eff = 53 if h 2 = 0.1 and rather constant for <lb/>R set up from N = 1, 5 or 10 sires (h 2 = 0.2: M eff = 54; h 2 = 0.3: M eff = 56). Hence <lb/>results are reported for M eff based on N = 10. Table 1 presents the median of n * <lb/>opt <lb/>from 100 repetitions of simulation. The median increased almost linearly with number <lb/>of QTL signals but reduced with increasing heritability, and it was rather unaffected <lb/>by the number of families. As an example, 127 individuals were required to fine-map <lb/>a single QTL signal based on the multi-SNP model if h 2 = 0.1. Almost twice as much <lb/>were required to distinguish two signals if h 2 = 0.1 or only 34 individuals were required <lb/>to detect a single signal correctly when h 2 = 0.3 instead of h 2 = 0.1. Optimal sample <lb/>size suggested by the multi-SNP model was 17 % to 39 % less than estimated from the <lb/>single-SNP model. Supplemental Figure D.1 visualizes the dependence of optimal sample <lb/>size estimated from the single-SNP model on heritability. It also shows that a much larger <lb/>sample was required if QTL heritability was less than 0.2. <lb/>In case of h 2 = 0.1, the distribution of n opt is represented in Figure 1; a separate panel is <lb/>shown for each number of QTL signals to be detected. Based on 100 × 100 estimates of <lb/>n opt , we derived a bimodal distribution of optimal sample size in the multi-SNP model. <lb/>The median of n opt was consistently less than sample size estimated from single-SNP in-<lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>vestigations. With increasing heritability, the first mode approached the median of n opt <lb/>but was still less than optimal sample size based on the single-SNP model, see Supple-<lb/>mental Figures D.2 (h 2 = 0.2) and D.3 (h 2 = 0.3). The second mode appeared due to <lb/>strong negative correlations between SNPs. Particularly this outcome was observed when <lb/>all possible pairs of SNPs were evaluated for detecting two QTL signals in a single repeti-<lb/>tion of simulation. Figure 2(a) shows the correlation matrix for a single data set. Those <lb/>entries of R have been selected that belonged to 10 % of the highest estimates of sample <lb/>size, i.e., n opt ≥ 864 (h 2 = 0.1). Correspondingly, Figure 2(b) indicates that, with few <lb/>exceptions, negative correlations caused this outcome. The separation of SNP dependence <lb/>into maternal and paternal contribution revealed further insight, and most often negative <lb/>maternal LD was the driving term (Supplemental Fig. D.4). An additional inspection <lb/>of any relationship between assumed positions of a single QTL signal and n opt was not <lb/>conclusive. Neither extreme maternal allele frequency nor missing sire heterozygosity led <lb/>to obviously increased n opt for detecting one QTL signal (Figure 3). <lb/>The association analysis of data sets of optimal sample size was validated in terms of <lb/>sensitivity and specificity of testing SNP effects. The shape of ROC curves was similar <lb/>for all investigated simulation scenarios. As an example, if N = 10 and η = 2, the median <lb/>of n * <lb/>opt was 273, and the outcome is displayed in Figure 4. The analysis showed superiority <lb/>of the multi-SNP model over the single-SNP model. In general, it was observed that the <lb/>smaller n * <lb/>opt was estimated, the larger both TPR and FPR turned out for the single-SNP <lb/>model. The multi-SNP model performed rather robust against changes in sample size. <lb/>However, the flat appearance of the ROC curve complicates fine-mapping of QTL signals <lb/>based on the suggested multi-SNP approach. For instance, a TPR of 80 % is accompanied <lb/>with a FPR larger than 20 %. <lb/>Blocks of varying linkage phases, as shown in Figure 2, might be an artifact of data <lb/>simulation. Based on empirical bovine HD SNP chip data, a possible R matrix was set <lb/>up, see Figure 5. The blocking structure was less pronounced. Using this R for estimating <lb/>n * <lb/>opt led to results being similar to the simulation study for one and two QTL signals but <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>larger samples were required to detect more QTL signals: n * <lb/>opt was 123 (1 signal), 288 (2 <lb/>signals), 516 (3 signals), 800 (4 signals) and 1 342 (5 signals) if h 2 = 0.1. The number of <lb/>repetitions of randomly drawing the positions of QTL signals did not substantially affect <lb/>the final n * <lb/>opt . For instance, the median deviated less than 4 % if n opt was calculated 1 000 <lb/>instead of 100 times. <lb/>4 Discussion <lb/>Our investigation contributes to the design of powerful experiments for fine-mapping of <lb/>causative variant(s) in a genomic target region. We incorporated the expected dependence <lb/>among SNPs in this region and estimated optimal sample size based on a SNP-BLUP ap-<lb/>proach. The outcome was compared to a single-SNP model. Negative correlations between <lb/>SNPs, which were mainly due to negative maternal LD, caused essentially inflated sample <lb/>size estimates. In case of positive correlations, the majority of sample size estimates was <lb/>less than sample size estimated from the single-SNP approach. The less the heritability, <lb/>the higher the deviation between models was. <lb/>4.1 Population parameters <lb/>Our approach is applicable to any population structure. The matrix K of covariance be-<lb/>tween SNPs can be set up for any kind of family stratification by adapting the derivations <lb/>of the Appendix or, in case of unrelated individuals, by using population LD in K. <lb/>Due to the way of model parametrization (columns X k have been scaled), the dependence <lb/>on allele frequency has been excluded. For instance, in a random mating population, <lb/>the column-scaling term is 2p k (1 − p k ) with allele frequency p k at SNP k. Likewise, <lb/>a scaling term can be derived for half-sib families as the square root of Equation (A.3) <lb/>by investigating maternally and paternally inherited SNP alleles separately. Results of <lb/>association analyses suggested that there was no clear relationship between high n opt and <lb/>maternal allele frequency or sire heterozygosity (Figure 3). However, regions with large <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>or low variation have to be taken into account when selecting sires for fine-mapping of <lb/>QTL signals in a follow-up experiment. The lower sire heterozygosity or maternal minor <lb/>allele frequency is, the lower the relative effect size β k on the model scale will be and, <lb/>consequently, higher n * <lb/>opt is required in order to detect QTL signals. To investigate this, <lb/>we employed the relationship X k β k = X <lb/>(o) <lb/>k β <lb/>(o) <lb/>k <lb/>at SNP k. Here X <lb/>(o) <lb/>j,k is the allele count <lb/>at SNP k for individual j, and β <lb/>(o) <lb/>k is the coefficient on the observed genotype scale, i.e. <lb/>β <lb/>(o) <lb/>k = β k s k with scaling term s k = V (X j,k ). The relationship between allele frequency <lb/>and optimal sample size for detecting one QTL signal based on the single-SNP model is <lb/>presented in Supplemental Figure D.5. Extreme alleles, roughly spoken with major allele <lb/>frequency &gt; 0.95, require drastically increased sample size. <lb/>Hence the suggested optimal sample size is divided into N sires which are selected for most <lb/>heterogeneity in the target region. The actual number of sires is of minor importance. <lb/>The choice of individuals depends on the objectives of the follow-up study. Sires can be <lb/>chosen independently from the GWAS population in order to confirm and fine-map QTL <lb/>signal(s). However, if the initial study indicated the presence of rare variants, sires under <lb/>suspicion should be re-used. Selective genotyping is an option to increase power (Weller, <lb/>2001) but this might have negative impact on reproducibility of the study design (Lee <lb/>et al., 2014). In our investigation of paternal half-sib families, mothers are treated as <lb/>random samples from a dam population. Thus, the choice of dams for future matings is <lb/>not addressed here but is definitely an issue for other family designs. <lb/>Being equally important for fine-mapping of QTL signals is the positive correlation be-<lb/>tween SNPs. Positive correlatedness is a matter of genotype coding. Coding has to be <lb/>consistent throughout the target region to avoid unnecessary sign changes in correlation. <lb/>We employed coding in terms of counting the major allele in the population. But in re-<lb/>gions of intermediate frequency, the coding might not be appropriate and hence a dynamic <lb/>approach of coding the SNP alleles can circumvent negative correlations. A strategy on <lb/>this is worth further investigation. <lb/>Power calculations are needed to quantify and judge the prospects of identifying causative <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>variants with a hypothesized effect size in a particular population. In practice, however, <lb/>experiments are usually not planned to obtain maximum power but data are regularly <lb/>collected for purposes of breeding as a standard routine. Thus, experimental designs being <lb/>theoretically optimal could be compared with available field data to understand the possi-<lb/>ble shortcomings of such data and to understand differences between theoretical/expected <lb/>and actually achieved power. Based on the results, decisions can be made whether the <lb/>amount of data is sufficient or, in case of underpowered experiments, more data should <lb/>be acquired. <lb/>4.2 Necessity of fine-mapping of QTL signals using an appro-<lb/>priate design <lb/>The QTL databases of livestock species (Hu et al., 2012) contain information on several <lb/>thousands QTL for a wide range of traits. This shows that the variability of most of <lb/>the traits studied has a polygenic origin, with multiple QTL contributing to the overall <lb/>genetic variance. Despite the number of QTL, only a handful of causal mutations could be <lb/>detected and verified in the different livestock species (Andersson &amp; Georges, 2004). This <lb/>is partly due to the fact that GWAS show considerable weaknesses in the fine-mapping of <lb/>QTL signals which are related to the SNP panel requirements for a genomewide distribu-<lb/>tion and high LD to neighboring markers (Schaid et al., 2018). Accordingly, these SNPs <lb/>are usually indicative of a large genomic region that likely comprises the unmeasured <lb/>causal SNP but does not provide information about the causal variant itself. Statisti-<lb/>cal methods for fine-mapping have been designed to overcome these issues and perform <lb/>fine-mapping using the available SNP information from a SNP-chip or GBS (summarized <lb/>by Schaid et al., 2018). However, even these methods require a high SNP density in the <lb/>region of interest, which favors a targeted sequencing strategy that enable the dissection <lb/>of QTL regions and increase the chance of detecting causal variants (Mamanova et al., <lb/>2010). Major factors to be considered for designing a targeted sequencing study are ef-<lb/>fect size, the number of causal SNPs, local LD structure and sample size (Schaid et al., <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>2018). The approach proposed in this study incorporates information on η, h 2 and R <lb/>derived from the data to estimate the optimal sample size (n * <lb/>opt ) and thus provides all the <lb/>information needed to design a fine-mapping experiment. <lb/>Currently, several fine-mapping studies are based on imputation strategies or the integra-<lb/>tion of results with functional enrichment analysis to identify promising candidate genes <lb/>and QTNs (e.g., Jiang et al., 2019; Cai et al., 2019; Liu et al., 2019). These approaches <lb/>largely depend on imputation accuracy and the status of genome annotation, thus lim-<lb/>iting the ability to detect causal variants, especially those with a low allele frequency <lb/>(Dadaev et al., 2018). Specific examples for the fine-mapping of important genomic re-<lb/>gions with a resequencing strategy are still rare nowadays. Fraser et al. (2018) focused <lb/>in their study on collagenous lectins in horses by resequencing 658kb DNA consisting of <lb/>different candidate genes and regulatory regions. Therefore, a case-control design with <lb/>pooled samples was used and with this approach 113 variants were identified, which dif-<lb/>fered between the groups. Although the results are promising, the authors concluded <lb/>that a large-scale genotyping of individual samples is necessary for deeper insights. In <lb/>this context, and considering that targeted sequencing for a reasonable set of samples is <lb/>becoming increasingly affordable, an accurate estimate of sample size is advisable. <lb/>4.3 Other random effects <lb/>Association analysis of empirical data with certain pedigree structure requires an addi-<lb/>tional model term to account for genetic effects beyond the target window (Zu). Then <lb/>u = (u 1 , . . . , u n ), u ∼ N (0, Gσ 2 <lb/>u ), is the vector of individual genetic effects with suitable <lb/>relationship matrix G. The calculation of optimal sample size should consider the pres-<lb/>ence of additional random effects (genetic or environmental) for the design of experiments. <lb/>For instance, the coefficients of the single-SNP model could be estimated via BLUE. This <lb/>affects sample size calculation because the variance of the estimator β k , <lb/>V ( β k ) = X k V −1 X k <lb/>−1 <lb/>with V = ZZ σ 2 <lb/>u + I n σ 2 <lb/>e , <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>has impact on the distribution of the test statistic. Accounting for V in the denominator <lb/>of test statistic increases the denominator of non-centrality parameter. However, in order <lb/>to keep it simple, it would be sufficient to increase σ 2 <lb/>e or reduce h 2 appropriately without <lb/>any other alterations. <lb/>It is possible to consider other kinds of genetic effects with the proposed methods. For <lb/>instance, exploring dominance genetic effects requires only one modification. Instead of <lb/>coding SNP genotypes for additive effects via X j,k ∈ {1, 0, −1}, genotypes can be coded <lb/>as X j,k ∈ {0, 1, 0} to account for dominance effects. The covariance between dominance <lb/>effects has been worked out by Bonk et al. (2016). Feeding the Equation (2.3) with the <lb/>corresponding dominance correlation matrix will provide estimates of optimal sample size <lb/>to fine-map QTL signals with dominance effect. <lb/>5 Conclusion <lb/>For planning the design of experiment, we recommend a multi-SNP approach which con-<lb/>siders the expected dependence among SNPs. Compared to a conventional approach, <lb/>this leads to a reduced estimate of sample size and thus promises a more efficient use of <lb/>animal resources. The benefit depends strongly on heritability: the lower heritability, the <lb/>more resources can be saved. In general, optimal sample size increases almost linearly <lb/>with the number of QTL signals to be detected. This study constitutes a framework for <lb/>the design of experiments in specific populations that may be characterized by family <lb/>stratification. It will help differentiating independent signals in QTL regions that can be <lb/>further examined for cellular and molecular properties. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The project was funded by the German Research foundation (DFG, WI 4450/1-1). Spe-<lb/>cial thanks are given to N. Reinsch (Leibniz Institute for Farm Animal Biology, Dummer-<lb/>storf), J. Hartung (University of Hohenheim, Stuttgart) and V. Liebscher (University of <lb/></div>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Greifswald), who contributed invaluable ideas to the project, and to C. Gaynor (Roslin <lb/>Institute, Edingburgh) for giving handy insight into AlphaSimR. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contribution <lb/>DW developed the theory, implemented the statistical methods, performed the analysis, <lb/>and wrote the manuscript. SB contributed to the research on covariance between SNPs, <lb/>MD was involved in theoretical investigations. HR contributed to the discussion. All <lb/>authors have read and approved the final manuscript. The authors declare that they have <lb/>no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Abecasis, G. R., Cardon, L. R. &amp; Cookson, W. (2000), A general test of association <lb/>for quantitative traits in nuclear families. The American Journal of Human Genetics <lb/>66(1), 279-292. <lb/>Aguilar, I., Legarra, A., Cardoso, F., Masuda, Y., Lourenco, D. &amp; Misztal, I. (2019), <lb/>Frequentist p-values for large-scale-single step genome-wide association, with an appli-<lb/>cation to birth weight in american angus cattle. Genetics Selection Evolution 51(1), <lb/>28. <lb/>Andersson, L. &amp; Georges, M. (2004), Domestic-animal genomics: deciphering the genetics <lb/>of complex traits. Nature Reviews Genetics 5(3), 202. <lb/>Benjamini, Y. &amp; Hochberg, Y. (1995), Controlling the false discovery rate: a practical and <lb/>powerful approach to multiple testing. Journal of the Royal statistical society: series B <lb/>(Methodological) 57(1), 289-300. <lb/>Bermingham, M. L., Bishop, S. C., Woolliams, J. A., Pong-Wong, R., Allen, A. R., <lb/>McBride, S. H., McDowell, S. W. J., Skuce, R. A., Ryder, J. J., Wright, D. M. &amp; <lb/>Glass, E. J. (2013), Data from: Genome-wide association study identifies novel loci <lb/>associated with resistance to bovine tuberculosis. Dryad, Dataset URL https://doi. <lb/>org/10.5061/dryad.519bm. <lb/>Bonk, S., Reichelt, M., Teuscher, F., Segelke, D. &amp; Reinsch, N. (2016), Mendelian sam-<lb/>pling covariability of marker effects and genetic values. Genetics Selection Evolution <lb/>48(1), 36. <lb/>Butler, D., Cullis, B. R., Gilmour, A. &amp; Gogel, B. (2009), ASReml-R reference manual. <lb/>The State of Queensland, Department of Primary Industries and Fisheries, Brisbane . <lb/>Cai, Z., Guldbrandtsen, B., Lund, M. S. &amp; Sahana, G. (2019), Weighting sequence variants <lb/>based on their annotation increases the power of genome-wide association studies in <lb/>dairy cattle. Genetics Selection Evolution 51(1), 20. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Cule, E., Vineis, P. &amp; De Iorio, M. (2011), Significance testing in ridge regression for <lb/>genetic data. BMC Bioinformatics 12, 372. <lb/>Dadaev, T., Saunders, E. J., Newcombe, P. J., Anokian, E., Leongamornlert, D. A., Brook, <lb/>M. N., Cieza-Borrella, C., Mijuskovic, M., Wakerell, S., Al Olama, A. A. et al. (2018), <lb/>Fine-mapping of prostate cancer susceptibility loci in a large meta-analysis identifies <lb/>candidate causal variants. Nature communications 9(1), 2256. <lb/>Endelman, J. B. (2011), Ridge regression and other kernels for genomic selection with R <lb/>package rrBLUP. The Plant Genome 4(3), 250-255. <lb/>Faux, A.-M., Gorjanc, G., Gaynor, R. C., Battagin, M., Edwards, S. M., Wilson, D. L., <lb/>Hearne, S. J., Gonen, S. &amp; Hickey, J. M. (2016), AlphaSim: software for breeding <lb/>program simulation. The plant genome 9(3). <lb/>Fraser, R. S., Arroyo, L. G., Meyer, A. &amp; Lillie, B. N. (2018), Identification of genetic vari-<lb/>ation in equine collagenous lectins using targeted resequencing. Veterinary immunology <lb/>and immunopathology 202, 153-163. <lb/>Gao, X., Starmer, J. &amp; Martin, E. R. (2008), A multiple testing correction method for <lb/>genetic association studies using correlated single nucleotide polymorphisms. Genetic <lb/>Epidemiology 32, 361-369. <lb/>Gauderman, J. &amp; Morrison, J. (2007), QUANTO Version 1.2. University of Southern Cali-<lb/>fornia, Department of Preventive Medicine, URL http://biostats.usc.edu/Quanto. <lb/>html, retrieved June 10, 2015. <lb/>Gualdrón Duarte, J. L., Cantet, R. J., Bates, R. O., Ernst, C. W., Raney, N. E. &amp; <lb/>Steibel, J. P. (2014), Rapid screening for phenotype-genotype associations by linear <lb/>transformations of genomic evaluations. BMC Bioinformatics 15(1), 246, URL https: <lb/>//doi.org/10.1186/1471-2105-15-246. <lb/>Hampel, A., Teuscher, F., Gomez-Raya, L., Doschoris, M. &amp; Wittenburg, D. (2018), Esti-<lb/></listBibl>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>mation of recombination rate and maternal linkage disequilibrium in half-sibs. Frontiers <lb/>in Genetics 9, 186. <lb/>Hickey, J. M., Kinghorn, B. P., Tier, B., Wilson, J. F., Dunstan, N. &amp; van der Werf, <lb/>J. H. (2011), A combined long-range phasing and long haplotype imputation method <lb/>to impute phase for snp genotypes. Genetics Selection Evolution 43(1), 12. <lb/>Hoerl, A. E., Kennard, R. W. &amp; Baldwin, K. F. (1975), Ridge regression: some simula-<lb/>tions. Communications in Statistics 4(2), 105-123. <lb/>Hu, Z.-L., Park, C. A., Wu, X.-L. &amp; Reecy, J. M. (2012), Animal QTLdb: an improved <lb/>database tool for livestock animal QTL/association data dissemination in the post-<lb/>genome era. Nucleic acids research 41(D1), D871-D879. <lb/>Jiang, J., Cole, J. B., Freebern, E., Da, Y., VanRaden, P. M. &amp; Ma, L. (2019), Functional <lb/>annotation and bayesian fine-mapping reveals candidate genes for important agronomic <lb/>traits in Holstein bulls. Communications Biology 2(1), 212. <lb/>Kang, H. M., Sul, J. H., Service, S. K., Zaitlen, N. A., Kong, S.-y., Freimer, N. B., Sabatti, <lb/>C., Eskin, E. et al. (2010), Variance component model to account for sample structure <lb/>in genome-wide association studies. Nature genetics 42(4), 348. <lb/>Khatkar, M. S., Nicholas, F. W., Collins, A. R., Zenger, K. R., Cavanagh, J. A., Barris, <lb/>W., Schnabel, R. D., Taylor, J. F. &amp; Raadsma, H. W. (2008), Extent of genome-wide <lb/>linkage disequilibrium in Australian Holstein-Friesian cattle based on a high-density <lb/>SNP panel. BMC genomics 9(1), 187. <lb/>Koivula, M., Strandén, I., Su, G. &amp; Mäntysaari, E. A. (2012), Different methods to <lb/>calculate genomic predictions-comparisons of blup at the single nucleotide polymor-<lb/>phism level (snp-blup), blup at the individual level (g-blup), and the one-step approach <lb/>(h-blup). Journal of dairy science 95(7), 4065-4073. <lb/>Kristensen, P. S., Jahoor, A., Andersen, J. R., Cericola, F., Orabi, J., Janss, L. L. &amp; <lb/>Jensen, J. (2018), Genome-wide association studies and comparison of models and <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>cross-validation strategies for genomic prediction of quality traits in advanced winter <lb/>wheat breeding lines. Frontiers in plant science 9, 69. <lb/>Lee, S., Abecasis, G. R., Boehnke, M. &amp; Lin, X. (2014), Rare-variant association analysis: <lb/>study designs and statistical tests. The American Journal of Human Genetics 95(1), <lb/>5-23. <lb/>Liu, Z., Wang, T., Pryce, J. E., MacLeod, I. M., Hayes, B. J., Chamberlain, A. J., Van-<lb/>der Jagt, C., Reich, C. M., Mason, B. A., Rochfort, S. et al. (2019), Fine-mapping <lb/>sequence mutations with a major effect on oligosaccharide content in bovine milk. Sci-<lb/>entific reports 9(1), 2137. <lb/>Luo, Z. (1998), Detecting linkage disequilibrium between a polymorphic marker locus and <lb/>a trait locus in natural populations. Heredity 80(2), 198. <lb/>Maier, R., Moser, G., Chen, G.-B., Ripke, S., Absher, D., Agartz, I., Akil, H., Amin, <lb/>F., Andreassen, O. A., Anjorin, A. et al. (2015), Joint analysis of psychiatric disorders <lb/>increases accuracy of risk prediction for schizophrenia, bipolar disorder, and major <lb/>depressive disorder. The American Journal of Human Genetics 96(2), 283-294. <lb/>Mamanova, L., Coffey, A. J., Scott, C. E., Kozarewa, I., Turner, E. H., Kumar, A., <lb/>Howard, E., Shendure, J. &amp; Turner, D. J. (2010), Target-enrichment strategies for <lb/>next-generation sequencing. Nature methods 7(2), 111. <lb/>Mucha, S., Mrode, R., MacLaren-Lee, I., Coffey, M. &amp; Conington, J. (2015), Estimation <lb/>of genomic breeding values for milk yield in uk dairy goats. Journal of dairy science <lb/>98(11), 8201-8208. <lb/>Pritchard, J. K. &amp; Przeworski, M. (2001), Linkage disequilibrium in humans: models and <lb/>data. The American Journal of Human Genetics 69(1), 1-14. <lb/>R Core Team (2019), R: A Language and Environment for Statistical Computing. R Foun-<lb/>dation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, URL https://www.R-project. <lb/>org/. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Reyer, H., Hawken, R., Murani, E., Ponsuksili, S. &amp; Wimmers, K. (2015), The genetics of <lb/>feed conversion efficiency traits in a commercial broiler line. Scientific reports 5, 16387. <lb/>Sahana, G., Guldbrandtsen, B., Thomsen, B., Holm, L.-E., Panitz, F., Brøndum, R. F., <lb/>Bendixen, C. &amp; Lund, M. S. (2014), Genome-wide association study using high-density <lb/>single nucleotide polymorphism arrays and whole-genome sequences for clinical mastitis <lb/>traits in dairy cattle. Journal of dairy science 97(11), 7258-7275. <lb/>Schaid, D. J., Chen, W. &amp; Larson, N. B. (2018), From genome-wide associations to <lb/>candidate causal variants by statistical fine-mapping. Nature Reviews Genetics 19(8), <lb/>491-504. <lb/>Schnabel, R. (2018), ARS-UCD1.2 cow genome assembly: Mapping of all existing <lb/>variants. URL https://www.animalgenome.org/repository/cattle/UMC_bovine_ <lb/>coordinates/, retrieved Sep 21, 2018. <lb/>Searle, S. (1971), Linear models. John Wiley and Sons, Inc. <lb/>Taskinen, M., Mäntysaari, E. A. &amp; Strandén, I. (2017), Single-step snp-blup with on-<lb/>the-fly imputed genotypes and residual polygenic effects. Genetics Selection Evolution <lb/>49(1), 36. <lb/>Weller, J. (2001), Quantitative trait loci analysis in animals. CABI Publishing. <lb/>Wittenburg, D., Teuscher, F., Klosa, J. &amp; Reinsch, N. (2016), Covariance between geno-<lb/>typic effects and its use for genomic inference in half-sib families. G3: Genes, Genomes, <lb/>Genetics 6, 2761-2772. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">A Appendix: Derivation of correlation matrix <lb/>We study the dependence between pairs of SNPs, each with two alleles A and B, in a pop-<lb/>ulation consisting of N paternal half-sib families. Let X j,k be the genotype code at SNP <lb/>k ∈ {1, . . . , p} of individual j ∈ {1, . . . , n} being progeny of sire s and dam d. Homozy-<lb/>gous genotypes A/A and B/B are coded as 1 and -1, respectively, and the heterozygous <lb/>genotype A/B is indicated as 0. The family-specific, i.e. sire-specific, covariance between <lb/>SNP k and l of individual j is, according to Bonk et al. (2016) and Wittenburg et al. <lb/>(2016), <lb/>K s <lb/>k,l = E(X j,k X j,l |S s ) − E(X j,k |S s )E(X j,l |S s ) <lb/>= D d <lb/>k,l + D s <lb/>k,l <lb/>a function of maternal and paternal contribution and depends on the sire diplotype S s . <lb/>The D d <lb/>k,l denotes the LD of maternal gametes in a dam population. The sire term depends <lb/>on the phase of paternal haplotypes and recombination rate (θ k,l ). It is determined as <lb/>D s <lb/>k,l = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>1 <lb/>4 (1 − 2θ k,l ) , <lb/>for sire with haplotypes A-A and B-B <lb/>− 1 <lb/>4 (1 − 2θ k,l ) , for sire with haplotypes A-B and B-A <lb/>0 , <lb/>else . <lb/>(A.1) <lb/>To achieve the covariance between a pair of SNPs, we employ conditioning on families, <lb/>E(X j,k X j,l ) = <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>Pr(S s )E(X j,k X j,l |S s ) <lb/>E(X j,k ) = <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>Pr(S s )E(X j,k |S s ) <lb/>cov(X j,k , X j,l ) = <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k X j,l |S s ) − <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k |S s ) <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,l |S s ) <lb/></div>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">with family weights w s = ns <lb/>n and N <lb/>s=1 n s = n. The aim is now to derive an expression <lb/>that depends on already known terms. For instance, using <lb/>E(X j,k X j,l |S s ) = K s <lb/>k,l + E(X j,k |S s )E(X j,l |S s ) <lb/>yields <lb/>E(X j,k X j,l ) = <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s K s <lb/>k,l + E(X j,k |S s )E(X j,l |S s ) . <lb/>We exploit the separation into independently inherited maternal and paternal SNP alleles: <lb/>X j,k = X j,k,s + X j,k,d , where X j,k,s and X j,k,d take a value of 1 <lb/>2 if the A allele was inherited <lb/>but − 1 <lb/>2 otherwise. Then <lb/>E(X j,k |S s ) = E(X j,k,d |S s ) + E(X j,k,s |S s ) <lb/>E(X j,k,d |S s ) = E(X j,k,d ) = p k − <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>where p k denotes the maternal allele frequency at SNP k. Furthermore, <lb/>E(X j,k,s |S s ) = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>1 <lb/>2 , <lb/>for sire genotype A/A <lb/>0 , <lb/>for sire genotype A/B <lb/>− 1 <lb/>2 , for sire genotype B/B . <lb/>(A.2) <lb/></div>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Putting it all together, <lb/>K k,l = <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s (D d <lb/>k,l + D s <lb/>k,l ) <lb/>+ <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s p k − <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ E(X j,k,s ) <lb/>(p l − <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ E(X j,l,s ) <lb/>− <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s p k − <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ E(X j,k,s ) <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s (p l − <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>+ E(X j,l,s ) . <lb/>This can be reduced to <lb/>K k,l = D d <lb/>k,l + <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s D s <lb/>k,l + <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k,s )E(X j,l,s ) <lb/>− <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k,s ) <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,l,s ) <lb/>and evaluated using the sire-specific terms in (A.1) and (A.2). <lb/>Now the variance of genotype codes at SNP k is derived explicitly -it also serves as a <lb/>scaling term in a regression model for association analysis. The second moment of the <lb/>paternally inherited SNP allele is constant E(X 2 <lb/>j,k,s |S s ) = 1 <lb/>4 for all s. Hence <lb/>V (X j,k,s ) = <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>− <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k,s |S s ) <lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>Then, the variance at SNP k is <lb/>V (X j,k ) = V (X j,k,d ) + V (X j,k,s ) <lb/>= p k (1 − p k ) + <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>− <lb/>N <lb/>s=1 <lb/>w s E(X j,k,s |S s ) <lb/>2 <lb/>= K k,k . <lb/>(A.3) <lb/>Finally, the correlation matrix R = {R k,l } k,l=1,...,p is calculated by scaling the entries <lb/></div>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">correspondingly, <lb/>R k,l = <lb/>K k,l <lb/>K k,k K l,l <lb/>. <lb/>Note that the covariance based on non-centered genotype codes (as derived above) is <lb/>identical to the one based on centered genotype codes (as used in Section Material and <lb/>methods). Centering is used to study within-family genetic effects, and it allows the direct <lb/>estimation of allele substitution effects (Abecasis et al., 2000). <lb/></div>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body>B Tables <lb/></body>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 Median of optimal sample size for detecting different number of QTL signals from 100 repetitions of simulations. Results are based on the <lb/>multi-SNP approach * <lb/>(N = 1, 5, 10 families) or single-SNP approach. ( * <lb/>In each repetition, sample size was repeatedly determined for randomly drawn <lb/>QTL positions and the median was calculated.) <lb/>QTL <lb/>h 2 <lb/>= 0.1 <lb/>h 2 <lb/>= 0.2 <lb/>h 2 <lb/>= 0.3 <lb/>N = 1 N = 5 N = 10 single <lb/>N = 1 N = 5 N = 10 single <lb/>N = 1 N = 5 N = 10 single <lb/>1 <lb/>128 <lb/>126 <lb/>127 <lb/>195 <lb/>57 <lb/>58 <lb/>57 <lb/>91 <lb/>34 <lb/>33 <lb/>34 <lb/>56 <lb/>2 <lb/>275 <lb/>269 <lb/>273 <lb/>382 <lb/>125 <lb/>126 <lb/>122 <lb/>175 <lb/>73 <lb/>70 <lb/>73 <lb/>106 <lb/>3 <lb/>421 <lb/>426 <lb/>436 <lb/>569 <lb/>214 <lb/>201 <lb/>205 <lb/>259 <lb/>126 <lb/>120 <lb/>120 <lb/>155 <lb/>4 <lb/>613 <lb/>540 <lb/>584 <lb/>756 <lb/>291 <lb/>288 <lb/>281 <lb/>342 <lb/>177 <lb/>170 <lb/>170 <lb/>204 <lb/>5 <lb/>763 <lb/>713 <lb/>685 <lb/>943 <lb/>385 <lb/>349 <lb/>344 <lb/>426 <lb/>228 <lb/>208 <lb/>207 <lb/>253 <lb/></body>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<body>C Figures <lb/></body>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<body>n = 195 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>1 QTL <lb/>n = 382 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>2 QTL <lb/>n = 569 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>3 QTL <lb/>n = 756 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>4 QTL <lb/>n = 943 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>5 QTL <lb/>Figure 1 Distribution of optimal sample size. Violinplot of n opt vs. number of half-sib families for <lb/>different numbers of QTL signals in a multi-SNP model. The parent generation was simulated 100 <lb/>times and 100 random draws of positions of QTL signals were analyzed in each run, h 2 = 0.1. The <lb/>diamond indicates the median of n opt and the blue line marks the results based on a single-SNP <lb/>model. <lb/></body>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>correlation <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>correlation <lb/>(b) <lb/> Figure 2 Dependence between SNPs in a single simulated data set with N = 10 sires. (a) Correlation <lb/>matrix R, (b) entries selected from R which belong to 10 % highest sample size (n opt ≥ 864). All <lb/>possible SNP pairs were evaluated to detect two QTL signals (h 2 = 0.1). <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<body>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>qq q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>position (Morgan) <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>(a) <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>qq <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>qq <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>qq <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>qq q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>qq q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q qq q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>position (Morgan) <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>qq <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>qq q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>qq q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q qq q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>sire heterozygosity <lb/>maternal allele frequency <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 3 Relationship of optimal sample size with genome position. (a) Optimal sample size for <lb/>detecting one QTL signal was estimated based on the multi-SNP model (h 2 = 0.1). All possible <lb/>SNP positions were evaluated. (b) Sire heterozygosity and maternal allele frequency at each SNP <lb/>position. Values for SNPs that belong to 10 % highest sample size (n opt ≥ 194) are indicated by a <lb/>star. Results are based on a single simulated data set with N = 10 sires. <lb/></body>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>ROC curve <lb/>results_opt_2QTL_N10 <lb/>1 − specificity (FPR) <lb/>sensitivity (TPR) <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q qq <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q q q qq <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>Ridge <lb/>GWAS <lb/>Figure 4 Sensitivity and specificity of testing SNP effects. ROC curve is based on 100 × 100 <lb/>repeated simulations of genotypes and phenotypes in progeny generation comprising N = 10 half-sib <lb/>families (two QTL signals, h 2 = 0.1). Optimal sample size suggested by the multi-SNP model was <lb/>considered for setting up the progeny generation. <lb/></body>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−1.0 <lb/>−0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>correlation <lb/>(a) <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>number of QTL <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 5 Empirical bovine HD SNP chip data. (a) Correlation matrix for a randomly selected window <lb/>containing 300 SNPs on BTA7. (b) Violinplot of n opt vs. number of QTL signals to be detected. <lb/>The diamond indicates the median of n opt and the blue dots mark the results based on a single-SNP <lb/>model, N = 10 and h 2 = 0.1. <lb/></body>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">D Supplemental Figures <lb/></div>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">h2 <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>800 <lb/>1000 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>h² = 0.1 <lb/>n = 197 (1 QTL) <lb/>n = 387 (2 QTL) <lb/>n = 576 (3 QTL) <lb/>n = 766 (4 QTL) <lb/>n = 955 (5 QTL) <lb/>h² = 0.2 <lb/>n = 92 (1 QTL) <lb/>n = 176 (2 QTL) <lb/>n = 260 (3 QTL) <lb/>n = 344 (4 QTL) <lb/>n = 429 (5 QTL) <lb/>Figure D.1 Optimal sample size estimated from the single-SNP model and depending on heritability. <lb/>Pointwise type-I error was corrected using the simpleM method. <lb/></div>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">n = 91 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>1 QTL <lb/>n = 175 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>2 QTL <lb/>n = 259 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>3 QTL <lb/>n = 342 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>4 QTL <lb/>n = 426 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>5 QTL <lb/>Figure D.2 Distribution of optimal sample size. Violinplot of n opt vs. number of half-sib families <lb/>for different numbers of QTL signals in a multi-SNP model. The parent generation was simulated <lb/>100 times and 100 random draws of positions of QTL signals were analyzed in each run, h 2 = 0.2. <lb/>The diamond indicates the median of n opt and the blue line marks the results based on a single-SNP <lb/>model. <lb/></div>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">n = 56 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>1 QTL <lb/>n = 106 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>2 QTL <lb/>n = 155 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>3 QTL <lb/>n = 204 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>4 QTL <lb/>n = 253 <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>1 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>number of half−sib families <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>5 QTL <lb/>Figure D.3 Distribution of optimal sample size. Violinplot of n opt vs. number of half-sib families <lb/>for different numbers of QTL signals in a multi-SNP model. The parent generation was simulated <lb/>100 times and 100 random draws of positions of QTL signals were analyzed in each run, h 2 = 0.3. <lb/>The diamond indicates the median of n opt and the blue line marks the results based on a single-SNP <lb/>model. <lb/></div>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>pat. LD <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>pat. LD <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>mat. LD <lb/>(c) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>locus 1 <lb/>locus 2 <lb/>−0.2 <lb/>−0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>mat. LD <lb/>(d) <lb/>Figure D.4 Separation of dependence between SNPs in a single simulated data set with N = 10 sires. <lb/>(a) Paternal covariance, (b) entries selected from paternal covariance which belong to 10 % highest <lb/>sample size (n opt ≥ 864), (c) maternal covariance, (d) entries selected from maternal covariance <lb/>which belong to 10 % highest sample size. All possible SNP pairs were evaluated to detect two QTL <lb/>signals (h 2 = 0.1). <lb/></div>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">allele frequency <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>q <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>heritability <lb/>optimal sample size <lb/>Figure D.5 Dependence of optimal sample size on major allele frequency (p). The relative effect <lb/>size on the observed genotype level was fixed at 0.5 and multiplied by 2p(1 − p). Optimal sample <lb/>size was estimated based on a single-SNP model. <lb/></div>

			<page>42 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
