<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Deep Evolutionary History of the Phox and Bem1 (PB1) Domain <lb/>Across Eukaryotes <lb/>Sumanth Kumar Mutte 1 and Dolf Weijers 1, * <lb/>1 Laboratory of Biochemistry, Wageningen University, Stippeneng 4, 6708WE, Wageningen, <lb/>the Netherlands <lb/>Sumanth Kumar Mutte: Sumanth.mutte@wur.nl <lb/>* Corresponding author (Dolf Weijers): dolf.weijers@wur.nl <lb/>2 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Protein oligomerization is a fundamental process to build complex functional modules. <lb/>Domains that facilitate the oligomerization process are diverse and widespread in nature <lb/>across all kingdoms of life. One such domain is the Phox and Bem1 (PB1) domain, which is <lb/>functionally (relatively) well understood in the animal kingdom. However, beyond animals, <lb/>neither the origin nor the evolutionary patterns of PB1-containing proteins are understood. <lb/>While PB1 domain proteins have been found in other kingdoms, including plants, it is unclear <lb/>how these relate to animal PB1 proteins. <lb/>To address this question, we utilized large transcriptome datasets along with the proteomes of <lb/>a broad range of species. We discovered eight PB1 domain-containing protein families in <lb/>plants, along with three each in Protozoa and Chromista and four families in Fungi. Studying <lb/>the deep evolutionary history of PB1 domains throughout eukaryotes revealed the presence of <lb/>at least two, but likely three, ancestral PB1 copies in the Last Eukaryotic Common Ancestor <lb/>(LECA). These three ancestral copies gave rise to multiple orthologues later in evolution. <lb/>Tertiary structural models of these plant PB1 families, combined with Random Forest based <lb/>classification, indicated family-specific differences attributed to the length of PB1 domain <lb/>and the proportion of β-sheets. <lb/>This study identifies novel PB1 families and reveals considerable complexity in the protein <lb/>oligomerization potential at the origin of eukaryotes. The newly identified relationships <lb/>provide an evolutionary basis to understand the diverse functional interactions of key <lb/>regulatory proteins carrying PB1 domains across eukaryotic life. <lb/>3 <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>Phylogeny, protein oligomerization, plants, animals, homology modeling, random forest <lb/></front>

			<body>BACKGROUND <lb/>Protein-protein interaction is a basic and important mechanism that brings proteins <lb/>together in a functional module and thus allows the development of higher-order <lb/>functionalities. One of the versatile interaction domains that brings this modularity through <lb/>either dimerization or oligomerization is the PB1 domain. Initially, the two animal proteins, <lb/>p40 Phox and p67 Phox , were shown to interact through a novel motif that contains a stretch of <lb/>negatively charged amino acids [1]. In the same study, it was also shown that the yeast CELL <lb/>DIVISION CONTROL 24 (Cdc24) protein contains the same motif as found in p40 Phox , and <lb/>hence named as PC motif (for p40 Phox and Cdc24; Nakamura et al. 1998). Later, the BUD <lb/>EMERGENCE 1 (Bem1) protein in yeast was also found to have this motif, after which it has <lb/>been renamed as PB1 domain (for Phox and Bem1). The PB1 domain of Bem1 in yeast is <lb/>required for the interaction with Cdc24 to maintain cell polarity [2]. Later, in mammals, <lb/>many protein families were identified that contain a PB1 domain [3]. In plants, the PB1 <lb/>domain was initially recognised as domain III/IV in the auxin repressor proteins <lb/>AUXIN/INDOLE-3-ACETIC-ACID (Aux/IAAs) [4]. Later, the domains III/IV were found <lb/>to form a fold similar to (and hence renamed as) the PB1 domain, with a wider presence in <lb/>multiple gene families in plants [5-7]. <lb/>The PB1 domain ranges from 80-100 amino acids in length and exhibits a Ubiquitin <lb/>β-grasp fold with five β-sheets and two α-helices [8,9]. The first half of the domain represents <lb/>a positively charged face, with a conserved Lysine (K) in β1. The latter half of the domain <lb/>represents a negatively charged face, with D-x-D/E-x-D/E as core (OPCA motif; Müller et al. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>2006). Based on the presence/absence of these important residues/motifs, the PB1 domains <lb/>are divided into three types. If the PB1 domain contains only the conserved OPCA motif but <lb/>not the Lysine, it is considered as a type-1 (or type-A) PB1 domain. If there is only Lysine <lb/>but not OPCA motif, it is a type-2 (or type-B) domain. If the PB1 domain contains both <lb/>Lysine and the OPCA motifs, it is referred as type-1/2 (or type-AB). Various proteins that <lb/>harbour a PB1 domain undergo dimerization or oligomerization, where the positive face of <lb/>one PB1 domain interacts with the negative face of another in a head-to-tail fashion [3,8]. <lb/>Hence, depending on the type of PB1 domain they interact with, there can be either <lb/>homotypic or heterotypic PB1 interactions. <lb/>All the eukaryotes are divided into five kingdoms: Protozoa, Chromista, Fungi, <lb/>Animalia and Plantae. PB1 domain-containing proteins have been relatively well studied in <lb/>Animalia, when compared to the other kingdoms. At least nine gene families have been <lb/>shown to encode a PB1 domain [10]. Animal genomes encode proteins that contain all three <lb/>types of PB1 domains: type-1 -NEUTROPHIL CYTOSOL FACTOR 4 (NCF4/p40 Phox ), <lb/>MITOGEN-ACTIVATED PROTEIN KINASE KINASE 5 (M2K5) and NEXT TO BRCA 1 <lb/>(NBR1); type-2 -NEUTROPHIL CYTOSOL FACTOR 2 (NCF2/p67 Phox ), PARTITIONING <lb/>DEFECTIVE 6 (Par6) and MITOGEN-ACTIVATED PROTEIN KINASE KINASE <lb/>KINASE 2/3 (M3K2/3); type-1/2 -SEQUESTOSOME-1 (SQSTM1/p62) , ATYPICAL <lb/>PROTEIN KINASE C (aPKC) and TRK-FUSED GENE (TFG). A systematic analysis <lb/>through yeast two-hybrid and pull-down assays revealed various homotypic and heterotypic <lb/>interactions among these PB1 domains [3]. The p67 Phox upon its interaction with p40 Phox <lb/>activates the phagocyte NADPH oxidase that is important for innate immunity in mammals <lb/>[11]. The Par6-aPKC complex establishment through PB1 is essential for cell polarity in <lb/>mammals and insects [12]. This complex, along with Par3, also regulates the formation of <lb/>junctions through apical-basal polarity in mammalian epithelial cells [13]. p62 acts as a <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>crucial scaffolding protein playing important roles in autophagy, apoptosis and inflammation <lb/>[14]. <lb/>The PB1 domain of M3K2/3 interacts with M2K5 to activate ERK5 mediated <lb/>signalling in response to growth factors and osmotic stress [15]. TFG PB1 domain is involved <lb/>in transforming activity by forming the TFG-TrkA (Tyrosine Kinase A) fusion [16]. NBR1 <lb/>interacts with p62 through PB1 which is required for targeting p62 to sarcomeres [3]. Few <lb/>non-canonical PB1 interactions were also observed, for example, in p40 Phox PB1 and PX <lb/>domains undergo intramolecular interaction, disruption of which is required to activate the <lb/>NADPH oxidase [17]. In yeast, interaction of both the PB1 domain containing proteins, <lb/>Bem1 and Cdc24 is critical for the cell polarity establishment at both budding and mating [2]. <lb/>The NADPH OXIDASE REGULATOR (NoxR) plays a central role fungal morphogenesis, <lb/>growth and development through NADPH oxidation pathway [18]. <lb/>The best-studied PB1 domains in plants are from the AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR <lb/>(ARF) transcription factors and their AUXIN/INDOLE-3-ACETIC-ACID (Aux/IAA) <lb/>inhibitors. Both the homotypic and heterotypic interactions among and between these gene <lb/>families is relatively well established [19]. The structural basis for these interactions has also <lb/>been scrutinized in detail [8,20]. Both ARFs and Aux/IAAs are involved in auxin-dependent <lb/>gene regulation through the Nuclear Auxin Pathway, that controls various growth and <lb/>developmental processes (reviewed in Weijers and Wagner 2016). Another PB1 domain <lb/>containing protein, AtNBR1, an Arabidopsis ortholog of animal NBR1, is involved in <lb/>autophagy and was shown to homo-polymerize through its PB1 domain [5]. Joka2, an <lb/>AtNBR1 orthologue of tobacco, can also homodimerize through its PB1 domain [7]. <lb/>Moreover, this study also revealed non-canonical interaction of the PB1 domain with the C-<lb/>terminal UBA domain within the same protein [7]. Homotypic interactions through PB1 <lb/>domains of NIN-LIKE PROTEINS OF PLANTS (NLPs) are required to induce nitrate-<lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>dependent gene expression [22,23]. Interestingly, like AtNBR1/Joka2, the PB1 domain of <lb/>NLP also undergoes non-canonical interaction with the HQ domain of TEOSINTE <lb/>BRANCHED 1, CYCLOIDEA, PCF DOMAINS CONTAINING PROTEIN 20 (TCP20) <lb/>[22]. Another study identified a novel unclassified PB1 domain-containing protein PAL OF <lb/>QUIRKY (POQ) that undergoes non-canonical interaction with QUIRKY (QKY) [24]. <lb/>However, the structural or mechanistic basis of these non-canonical interactions are yet to be <lb/>elucidated. <lb/>Even though PB1 domain proteins are well defined and their mechanical basis is <lb/>relatively well established in animals (reviewed in Sumimoto et al. 2007; Burke and Berk <lb/>2015), their evolutionary histories are essentially unknown. Moreover, it is unclear how many <lb/>PB1 domain-containing gene families are present in other kingdoms. Deep evolution has <lb/>been relatively well studied for ARF and Aux/IAA gene families [26] and to a certain extent <lb/>for NLPs [27], but the presence and the evolution of other PB1 domains, if any, in plants and <lb/>unicellular eukaryotes is obscure. Hence, the current study is designed to address several <lb/>important questions related to the distribution and ancestry of PB1 domains in the eukaryotic <lb/>tree of life: (1) How many PB1 domain-containing gene families are present in the kingdoms <lb/>Protozoa, Chromista, Fungi and Plantae? (2) What is the origin of the PB1 domain? How <lb/>many copies of PB1 were present in the Last Eukaryotic Common Ancestor (LECA)? (3) <lb/>How have PB1-containing proteins diversified/multiplied in evolution across multiple <lb/>kingdoms? (4) What are the sequence/structural patterns specific to each family of PB1s and <lb/>how to classify them? <lb/>To answer these questions, we have utilized the large transcriptome datasets in <lb/>Chromista and Plantae and the (almost) complete proteomes from Fungi and Animalia. We <lb/>found that the PB1 domains have a deep evolutionary origin with at least two copies in <lb/>LECA. Moreover, we find that the PB1 domain is associated with a variety of domains, <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>ranging from DNA-binding domains to Kinases and membrane-binding domains. Further, a <lb/>detailed sequence analysis of PB1 domains in Plantae revealed that these are poorly <lb/>conserved among various families in general, with few residues being specific to each family. <lb/>Taken together, this study provides the first evolutionary framework of the PB1 domains <lb/>across the eukaryotes. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Identification and evolution of PB1 domain-containing proteins in various kingdoms: <lb/>Animalia. -Based on literature, we extracted protein sequences of all PB1 domain-<lb/>containing proteins in the human genome from the Uniprot database. Nine gene families were <lb/>found to encode the PB1 domains as a part of their protein architecture (Fig. 1a). aPKC and <lb/>M3K2/3 both contain PB1 and Kinase domains in their N-and C-terminus, respectively. <lb/>Whereas, aPKC contains an extra diacylglycerol-binding (kDAG) domain in the middle. <lb/>NCF2/p67 Phox and NCF4/p40 Phox both contains SRC Homology 3 (SH3) and PB1 domains in <lb/>the C-terminus, where NCF2 contains Tetratricopeptides and NCF4 contains Phox <lb/>homologous domain (PX) in their N-terminus (Fig. 1a). The other three protein families, <lb/>Par6, TFG and p62/SQSTM1, are in general shorter than other PB1 domain-containing <lb/>proteins, with a PB1 domain in the amino-end. p62 contains a Ubiquitin-associated domain <lb/>(UBA), whereas Par6 contains a PSD95-Dlg1-Zo1 (PDZ) domain in the carboxy-end (Fig. <lb/>1a). The full name or description of all the domains along with a link to the InterPro domain <lb/>database are provided online (see Additional file 1: Table S1). <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>PB1 sequences from all the above-mentioned proteins were used as queries to retrieve <lb/>orthologues from ten species across various phyla in Animalia (see Additional file 4 for the <lb/>list of species used). Retrieved orthologous sequences were used in a phylogenetic analysis <lb/>along with the respective human counterparts. The PB1 domain-based phylogeny reflected <lb/>the monophyly of each gene family (Fig. 2 and Additional file 1: Fig. S2). PB1 domains of <lb/>M3K2-M3K3 and aPKC-M2K5 form paralogous pairs, indicating the common ancestry of <lb/>PB1 for each pair at the emergence of the kingdom Animalia. Interestingly, the paralog <lb/>Figure 1: Domain architecture of various PB1 domain containing proteins across the <lb/>five eukaryotic kingdoms. Panels show he complement of PB1-containing proteins in <lb/>Animalia (A), Protozoa (B), Chromista (C), Fungi (D) and Plantae (E). NBR1/p62 in (A) <lb/>and (B) indicate the presence of both NBR1 and p62 with all the domains as their orthologs <lb/>along with multiple partial domain combinations. DBD in (C) represents the DNA binding <lb/>domain, which is a combination of both B3 and dimerization domain (DD). Abbreviation <lb/>and the corresponding InterPro database link of all the domains are provided in Additional <lb/>file 1: Table S1. PB1 domains that are identified in only one sequence and/or one species <lb/>are provided in the Additional file 1: Fig. S1. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>ous pairs M3K2-M3K3 and aPKC-M2K5 PB1 domains are closer to the respective <lb/>orthologues from other kingdoms than the other PB1 domains in the same kingdom, <lb/>Animalia. A similar trend is observed with NBR1, however, surprisingly NCF2/p67 Phox is <lb/>placed as the sister clade to the NBR1. p62 do not show any close relationship with other PB1 <lb/>domains, neither paralogous nor orthologous, from the same kingdom or the other kingdoms <lb/>(Fig. 2 and Additional file 1: Fig. S2). In a similar way, Par6 and TFG also appear to be <lb/>Animalia-specific clades (Fig. 2 and Fig. 3). <lb/>Protozoa. -From UniProt, at least six reference proteomes and other individual Protozoan <lb/>sequences from various species across different phyla in Protozoa were used to identify the <lb/>PB1 domains (see Additional file 4). Few PB1 domain-containing proteins were identified <lb/>along with a large number of partial (or truncated) proteins with either only a PB1 domain or <lb/>a large unknown flanking sequence (Fig. 1 and Additional file 1: Fig. S1). Among the (full <lb/>length) PB1 domain-containing proteins, orthologs of Animalia M3K2/3 as well as Plantae <lb/>Phox were identified, and named as Kinase and Phox respectively (Fig. 1b and Additional file <lb/>1: Fig. S2). Unlike the animals, the Protozoan kinases also contain WD40 repeats at their C-<lb/>terminus. Moreover, the PB1 domain is also adjacent to kinase domain (Fig. 1b). Orthologues <lb/>of the NBR1 with all the four (known) domains were also found, along with the sequences of <lb/>various domain combinations i.e. either PB1 with Zn-finger, with the NBR1 Central domain, <lb/>or with the UBiquitin Associated (UBA) domains (Fig. 1). We also identified many PB1 <lb/>domain-containing proteins either associated with a Sterile Alpha Motif (SAM), Per-Arnt-<lb/>Sim (PAS), EF-hand or Cystathionine Beta Synthase (CBS) domains (Additional file 1: Fig. <lb/>S1). However, the majority of these are identified in only one sequence or one species, and <lb/>also represented in polyphyletic groups spread across the phylogenetic tree, making it <lb/>difficult to classify them into a certain clade (Additional file 1: Fig. S2). <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2: Unrooted tree with representative Fungi, Animalia and Plantae PB1 <lb/>domains. Early branches that are well-supported (bootstrap &gt;75) are indicated in grey. <lb/>Orthologs from each kingdom are represented with each colour as indicated: Fungi in <lb/>&apos;orange&apos;, Animalia in &apos;purple&apos; and Plantae in &apos;green&apos;. The groups outlined with dotted <lb/>lines indicated as LECA-1, LECA-2 and LECA-3 represent the probable ancestral copies <lb/>in LECA corresponding to Kinase, Phox and NBR1 groups respectively. Another <lb/>phylogenetic tree with all the five kingdoms is presented in the Additional file 1: Fig. S2 <lb/>as a schematic and full version with taxa names and domain information of both the trees <lb/>are available online (Additional file 2 and Additional file 3). <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Chromista. -To identify the PB1 domains in Chromista, all the transcriptomes from the <lb/>MMETSP database were used (see Additional file 4). Well-annotated fungal (Bem1 and <lb/>Cdc24), plant (Arabidopsis and Marchantia) and animal (Human and Mouse) PB1 sequences <lb/>were used to query the database, and processed the data with the pipeline developed <lb/>previously [26]. Two gene families, Kinase and NBR1 were identified in Chromista, with a <lb/>similar domain architecture, being orthologous to the respective gene families in Animalia <lb/>(Fig. 1c and Additional file 1: Fig. S2). Interestingly, like Protozoan kinase proteins, these <lb/>carry WD40 repeats too, however, the PB1 domain is far to the N-terminus as in Plantae or <lb/>Animalia (Fig. 1c). Orthologues of NBR1 are identified as multiple (partial) proteins <lb/>represented as polyphyletic groups, similar to Protozoa (Additional file 1: Fig. S2). However, <lb/>as a third gene family, we identified the CBS domain-containing proteins, where the PB1 <lb/>domain is associated in their carboxy terminus (Fig. 1c). Few other PB1 domain proteins <lb/>were identified as single copies in only one species that host either a Tetratricopeptide (TPR) <lb/>repeat or an EF-hand domain, which were also represented in polyphyletic groups <lb/>(Additional file 1: Fig. S1 and Additional file 1: Fig. S2). <lb/>Fungi. -For Fungi, we have selected the 12 reference proteomes from MycoCosm database <lb/>(see Additional file 4). Well-annotated plant and animal PB1 sequences were used as query <lb/>sequences. Four PB1 domain containing protein families were identified (Fig. 1d). The <lb/>widely known Bem1 and Cdc24, were identified as a monophyletic paralogous pair in our <lb/>study (Fig. 2). Along with the PB1 domain, Bem1 contains SH3 and PX domains, whereas <lb/>Cdc24 contains Dbl homology (DH) and Plextrin homology (PH) domains. Interestingly, <lb/>NCF4/p40 Phox , the animal ortholog of Bem1, contains PX in N-terminus, unlike in the middle <lb/>as in Bem1 (Fig. 1d). CBS domain containing proteins (referred as Mug70) were also <lb/>identified, with a similar domain architecture like in other kingdoms (Fig. 1d). Further, <lb/>NoxR, an ortholog of Animalia and Plantae Phox, was also identified as a sister clade to this <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>pair (Fig. 2 and Additional file 1: Fig. S2). In summary, all the four gene families form a <lb/>respective individual monophyletic group with all the paralogs, indicating their presence <lb/>across major phyla in Fungi (Fig. 2 and Fig. 3). It is worth noting that an ortholog of p62 and <lb/>a PB1 domain associated with a SAM domain were identified. However, each was found in <lb/>only one species and a single copy (Additional file 1: Fig. S1). Hence, we discarded them for <lb/>further analysis as they are considered of low confidence and may not represent any phylum <lb/>or the kingdom itself. <lb/>Plantae. -To identify all the PB1 domains in the kingdom Plantae (Fig. 1e), we have <lb/>adapted a similar pipeline as mentioned above [26], using 485 transcriptomes, that belong to <lb/>multiple phyla in the kingdom Plantae, from the OneKP database (Matasci et al. 2014; see <lb/>Additional file 4). We identified eight gene families that encode for PB1 domain-containing <lb/>Figure 3: Summary of <lb/>various PB1 domain-<lb/>containing <lb/>proteins <lb/>across key species in <lb/>Animalia, Fungi and <lb/>Plantae. Filled and empty <lb/>circles represent presence <lb/>and absence, respectively, <lb/>of the orthologous genes <lb/>for the family mentioned <lb/>on the top in the <lb/>corresponding species. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>proteins in plants (Fig. 1e). Among these, NBR1 and Kinase orthologues are placed in the <lb/>same clade as their counterparts from other kingdoms, and also contain the same domain <lb/>architecture as their animal orthologs (Fig. 1e and Fig. 2). ARF and Aux/IAA families form a <lb/>distinct monophyletic clade indicating a common ancestry at the base of the Streptophytes. <lb/>ARFs contain a B3 and Dimerization domains (together referred as DNA-binding domain <lb/>(DBD)) at the N-terminus and a PB1 domain at the C-terminus, like the Aux/IAAs. In <lb/>addition to a PB1 domain, Aux/IAAs also contain an EAR-motif and a degron motif <lb/>(Domain-I and -II respectively; Fig. 1e). Phox proteins, having the same domains as animal <lb/>counterparts, form a sister clade to the respective orthologous proteins from other kingdoms <lb/>(Fig. 2). CBS domain-containing proteins were also identified in plants, placed in the same <lb/>clade as fungal Mug70. Kinase-derived, ARF, Aux/IAA and NLP are Plantae specific <lb/>families that are not identified in any other kingdom (Fig. 3). All these plant-specific gene <lb/>families were discovered before, except Kinase-derived, which has only a PB1 domain in its <lb/>N-terminus with a large flanking sequence without any known domains. It is worth <lb/>mentioning that the Kinase-derived PB1 domains, resemble the Kinase PB1 domains and <lb/>appears to have been duplicated in the phylum &apos;Magnoliophyta&apos; (Angiosperms; Fig. 2 and <lb/>Fig. 3). NLPs contain an RWP-RK domain, in association with the PB1 domain and they are <lb/>placed as sister clade to the CBS domain containing proteins (Fig. 1e and Fig. 2). <lb/>Interestingly, among all the families identified so far across all the kingdoms, there do not <lb/>appear to be any constraints on either the position of the PB1 domain in the protein, or the <lb/>category of domains it is associated with (DNA binding, Oligomerization, Phosphorylation <lb/>etc.; Fig. 1). An overview of all the identified gene families and their existence across the <lb/>major phyla in the kingdoms Animalia, Fungi and Plantae is summarized in Figure 3. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Ancestral copy number in LECA <lb/>To better understand the origin and evolutionary patterns of all the PB1 domains <lb/>across five kingdoms in eukaryotes, two phylogenetic trees were constructed using only the <lb/>PB1 domain protein sequences. One is based on the PB1 domains from only three kingdoms <lb/>(Animalia, Fungi and Plantae; Fig. 2), whereas another one is constructed based on all the <lb/>sequences from five kingdoms (Additional file 1: Fig. S2). The detailed versions of both the <lb/>phylogenetic trees are available online (Additional file 2 and Additional file 3). All the <lb/>previously mentioned pairs that form the monophyletic groups of individual families in each <lb/>kingdom are well supported with good bootstrap values (&gt;75), especially in Fungi, Animalia <lb/>and Plantae (Fig. 2). The branches representing PB1 domains in Protozoa and Chromista are <lb/>highly unreliable due to the polyphyletic nature and their random distribution across the <lb/>phylogenetic tree (Additional file 1: Fig. S2). Overall, the recently evolved clades in the <lb/>phylogeny that are either gene family-specific or kingdom-specific, are generally <lb/>monophyletic in nature. We have observed a decrease in the support of the split of early <lb/>branches (with poor bootstraps) in the phylogeny based on all the five kingdoms (Additional <lb/>file 1: Fig. S2 and Additional file 3). Monophyletic grouping, as well as the presence in <lb/>multiple kingdoms, support the notion that there would have been at least two common <lb/>ancestral copies of PB1 domains, each corresponding to Kinase and Phox orthologues across <lb/>eukaryotes. Even though the Plantae NBR1 PB1 domains, along with the animal orthologues <lb/>(and the similar proteins p62) are not monophyletic in origin, they are still placed in the <lb/>phylogeny as sister clades (Fig. 2). This distribution of orthologues from the various <lb/>kingdoms hint at a third common ancestor of PB1 in LECA. This analysis has failed to <lb/>predict the order of evolution because of the lack of sufficient phylogenetic signal due to <lb/>poorly conserved sequences, a relatively small domain (in general) and poor bootstraps in the <lb/>early branches in the tree with all five kingdoms. The use of bacterial outgroup sequences <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>could not improve resolution, leading to mixing in the phylogeny along with ingroup <lb/>sequences. Hence, no outgroup was used and the tree is unrooted. Because of these <lb/>drawbacks, this study could not identify the order of events, but could predict the copy <lb/>number in LECA, based on both the monophyletic nature of Kinase and Phox groups as well <lb/>as presence of NBR1 orthologous sister clades across multiple kingdoms. <lb/>(Dis)similarities in the plant PB1 domains <lb/>After identifying the majority, if not all, of the PB1 domain-containing proteins and <lb/>understanding their evolution patterns across major phyla in all five kingdoms in eukaryotes, <lb/>we further investigated the plant PB1 domains in detail at the amino acid level. To achieve <lb/>this, we gathered the PB1 domain sequences from four whole genome-sequenced land plants, <lb/>one species each from liverworts (Marchantia polymorpha), mosses (Physcomitrella patens), <lb/>basal angiosperms (Amborella trichopoda) and a core eudicot (Arabidopsis thaliana). All <lb/>PB1 domain protein sequences that belongs to the eight families identified were aligned, and <lb/>an individual sequence logo was derived for each family (Fig. 4). The well-conserved (group <lb/>of) residues across the majority of the families are the positive residues Lysine (K) in β1 and <lb/>Arginine (R) in β2 that together represent the positive surface. However, the Lysine of β1 that <lb/>makes contact with the OPCA motif on the negative face of another PB1, is not conserved in <lb/>Kinase and Kinase-derived PB1 domains, indicating that these could be type-1 PB1 domains <lb/>with only a conserved negative face (Fig. 4). In general, the negative face represented by the <lb/>OPCA motif is relatively well-conserved in all the gene families, despite a strong <lb/>conservation of three amino acids (QLP) just before the OPCA motif in Kinase and Kinase-<lb/>derived PB1 domains (Fig. 4). Interestingly, the Tyrosine (Y) in β3 is relatively well <lb/>conserved in all the gene families. Apart from these generally conserved residues across <lb/>multiple families, there are various single amino acids that are specifically conserved in each <lb/>gene family. For example, Tyrosine (Y) and Phenylalanine (F) of the α1, Glycine (G) in β4 <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>and Phenylalanine (F) in α2 are specific to ARF and Aux/IAA PB1 domains. In a similar <lb/>way, two Phenylalanine (F) in and before the β1 and a G-x-L-x-L-x-L motif in β5 are specific <lb/>to PB1 domains associated with CBS domains (Fig. 4). The Tryptophan (W) in β4 is specific <lb/>to NLPs. Despite NBR1 being a single-copy gene in the kingdom Plantae, there do not seem <lb/>to be any constrains on the domain itself, as there is less than 20% identity among them. This <lb/>provides a basic understanding of relaxed evolutionary pressure in the PB1 domain, <lb/>providing opportunities for many gene family-specific changes. This makes it difficult not <lb/>only to predict general sequence patterns that are important for function, but also to estimate <lb/>the domain properties specific to each family purely based on the primary sequence and its <lb/>poorly conserved amino acids. <lb/>Figure 4: Sequence logos based on the alignment of PB1 domains from the <lb/>representative land plants (Marchantia, Physco, Amborella and Arabidopsis). Secondary <lb/>structures (α-helices and β-sheets) represented on the top are based on the ARF5 structure <lb/>(PDB ID: 4CHK). Numbers represented in the braces next to the name of the gene family, <lb/>shows the number of sequences present in all these four species together, and also the <lb/>number of sequences used for that particular alignment logo. Amino acids are coloured <lb/>according to the group: &apos;PAGFLIMV&apos;, &apos;KRH&apos; and &apos;DE&apos; are shown in &apos;purple&apos;, &apos;blue&apos; and <lb/>&apos;red&apos; colours respectively. All other amino acids are shown in &apos;black&apos;. Stars at the bottom <lb/>represent the key residues on positive (blue) and negative (red) faces, corresponding to <lb/>Lysine and OPCA motif (D-x-D/E-x-D/E core) respectively. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Classification using Random Forests <lb/>Since there are no clear patterns to identify the gene family to which each PB1 <lb/>belongs to and because it is also not possible to identify important features of a specific PB1 <lb/>domain based on the sequence alignment, one might detect patterns based on the secondary <lb/>structure composition along with the amino acid properties. Random forest (RF) based <lb/>classification was performed with 28 amino acid descriptors as variables. After bootstrap <lb/>aggregating (bagging) all the decision trees from the RF, the mean out-of-bag (OOB) error <lb/>rate is only 6% which indicates the high reliability of the RF model (Fig. 5). The <lb/>classification error rate is the highest (~14%) for Kinase-derived and the least (~2%) for ARF <lb/>PB1 domains (Fig. 5a and Additional file 1: Table S3). On an average, the majority of PB1 <lb/>families were resolved well, indicating the high reliability of classification using these <lb/>descriptors. <lb/>The importance of each variable is evaluated through the mean decrease in accuracy <lb/>(MDA) and the mean decrease in Gini (MDG). Higher values of both MDA and MDG <lb/>indicate the most important variables. In this case, the top 10 important variables are shown <lb/>in Fig. 5b, with mHbeta being the most important variable to differentiate the different <lb/>classes of PB1 domains. Hydrophobic moment of β-sheets, mHbeta, indicates the strength of <lb/>periodicity in the hydrophobicity of the β-sheets, also indicating the formation of more β-<lb/>sheets (Eisenberg 1984). The next most important variables are composition of Proline (P) <lb/>and length of the PB1 domain (Fig. 5b). We further analysed how these three important <lb/>variables differ between the gene families (Fig. 5c). mHbeta is low for ARFs and Aux/IAAs, <lb/>slightly higher for Phox, but even higher for the rest of the gene families. On the other hand, <lb/>the composition of Proline (P) is lowest in CBS, but shows a very broad distribution in the <lb/>Kinase-derived family. However, the length of the PB1 domain is very constrained for <lb/>majority of the families (&gt;90 for NBR1 and &lt;90 for ARFs), except Aux/IAA and Kinase-<lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 5: Random forest (RF) classification of the plant PB1 families. (A) <lb/>Mean out-of-bag (OOB) error rate of 6% is reported for the classification of eight <lb/>plant PB1 families with individual classification error % as shown in bar chart (B) <lb/>Importance plots of 10 most important descriptors (variables). The predictive value <lb/>of each variable was expressed as the mean decrease in accuracy (black dots with <lb/>scale at bottom) and the mean decrease in Gini (blue dots at top), arranged from <lb/>most important (top) to the less important (bottom) variables. (C) Violin plots <lb/>showing the actual distribution of three most important variables across eight <lb/>families. mHbeta has no units; Composition of Proline is indicated as percentage; <lb/>and Length is the number of amino acids in the PB1 domain. <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>derived, and to a certain extent for Phox (Fig. 5c). To correlate the contribution of <lb/>mHbeta to the β-sheets in the secondary structure, we have performed homology modelling <lb/>of at least one randomly selected Arabidopsis orthologue and we indeed found that higher <lb/>mHbeta represents secondary structures with more β-sheets (Fig. 6). For example, IAA17 <lb/>shows ~18% of the residues in β-sheets, whereas CBS36500 has ~34%, correlating with <lb/>lower and higher mHbeta values observed for Aux/IAA and CBS PB1s, respectively (Fig. 6; <lb/>Additional file 1: Fig. S3). Taken together, these results clearly indicate that there is a <lb/>difference between the gene families that can be explained from the mHbeta, the composition <lb/>of Proline and by keeping the length unique/constrained for that respective family. <lb/>Figure 6: Representative (homology model) structures of one member from each <lb/>family in Arabidopsis. The identifiers were: ARF5 (PDB: 4CHK), IAA17 (PDB: <lb/>2MUK), At2G36500 (CBS), At1G04700 (Kinase), At2G01190 (KinaseDerived), NBR1, <lb/>NLP9 and Phox2. (A) Secondary structures shown in various colours: α-helices in <lb/>&apos;Cyan&apos;; β-sheets in &apos;red&apos; and turns in &apos;purple&apos;. Surface representation of the positive and <lb/>negative faces shown in (B) and (C) respectively. Hydrophobic amino acids <lb/>&apos;AGVILFMP&apos; are in &apos;Yellow&apos;; Polar residues &apos;NQTSCYW&apos; are in &apos;Grey&apos;; Positively <lb/>charged &apos;RKH&apos; are in &apos;Blue&apos; and Negatively charged &apos;DE&apos; are in &apos;Red&apos;. <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>DISCUSSION <lb/>The PB1 domain is widespread in nature, throughout all the kingdoms in the <lb/>eukaryotic tree of life. It is diversified to a great extent in organisms with complex body plans <lb/>like animals and even more in land plants (Fig. 1). As a result, the human genome encodes 13 <lb/>PB1 domain-containing proteins, whereas a simple model Angiosperm, Arabidopsis thaliana, <lb/>encodes more than 80 PB1 domain copies grouped into eight families (Fig. 3). The proteins <lb/>with a PB1 domain also feature various domains, representing a manifold association ranging <lb/>from DNA/protein binding, catalytic function, scaffolding to membrane association (Fig. 1). <lb/>However, the PB1 domain is (mostly) found at either terminus of the protein, preferably <lb/>facilitating these to perform their native function, scaffolding or oligomerization, without the <lb/>hindrance of other domains. <lb/>The evolutionary patterns of the PB1 domain showed that there are multiple families <lb/>shared across multiple kingdoms (Fig. 2). Kinase and NBR1 are present in all the five <lb/>kingdoms, while Phox is found in four kingdoms (except Chromista) with a similar domain <lb/>architecture (Fig. 1). The phylogenetic placement of Kinase and Phox PB1 domains and their <lb/>orthologs indicate the presence of two ancestral copies in LECA and presumably a third copy <lb/>might be represented by the NBR1 and/or p62 group. It is known that orthologous proteins <lb/>may perform similar functions by interacting with similar proteins across kingdoms. An <lb/>example of common functionality of orthologous domains across multiple kingdoms is the <lb/>recently studied DIX domain in plant cell polarity protein SOSEKI (van Dop et al., in <lb/>revision). The DIX head-to-tail oligomerization domain is conserved across multiple <lb/>kingdoms (e.g. DISHEVELLED in animals; DIX-like in protozoans), and functions in cell <lb/>polarity by forming oligomers in plants and animals. In a similar way, the PB1 orthologs <lb/>across multiple kingdoms may share common functionality in similar pathways. One such is <lb/>the PB1 domain containing protein NBR1, which serves as an autophagy cargo receptor in <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>both plants and animals, where homodimerization of the PB1 domain is also conserved as a <lb/>part of its function [5,29]. Phox orthologues in animals (p67 Phox ) and fungi (NoxR) play a key <lb/>role in NADPH oxidation pathway by interacting with the membrane associated proteins <lb/>(gp91 Phox and NoxA/B respectively) as well as through PB1 domain with p40 Phox and Cdc24 <lb/>respectively [18,30]. Similarly, in Arabidopsis, Phox4 was shown to interact with membrane-<lb/>associated proteins KNOLLE, SYP22 and PEN1, which belong to the SNARE family [31]. <lb/>However, it is unknown which PB1 domain protein interacts with Phox4 PB1 in plants. <lb/>Discovering these unknown interactions may provide a link to the existence of an NADPH <lb/>oxidation pathway in plants controlled by PB1-dependent interactions. <lb/>Apart from the proteins that are shared across multiple kingdoms, some are specific to <lb/>each kingdom (Fig. 3). ARF, Aux/IAA and NLP families are specific to plants, whereas TFG, <lb/>Par6, M2K5 and aPKC are specific to animals. ARFs and Aux/IAAs are involved the Nuclear <lb/>Auxin Pathway, controlling transcriptional regulation of downstream targets with multiple <lb/>functions in response to the phytohormone auxin (reviewed in Weijers and Wagner 2016). <lb/>NLPs are master regulators of nitrate-inducible gene regulation in higher plants [23]. On the <lb/>other hand, animal Par6 and aPKC PB1 domains are known to interact with each other <lb/>playing a key role in cell polarity [32]. Thus, as far as can be inferred, these kingdom-specific <lb/>PB1 domain-containing proteins appear to regulate processes that are specific to that <lb/>kingdom. <lb/>It is interesting to see that the key interacting PB1 domains have also evolved in pairs. <lb/>Some such pairs are: aPKC-M2K5 (Animalia), Bem1-Cdc24 (Yeast), ARF-Aux/IAA <lb/>(Plantae) (Fig. 2). The interacting pairs (for example ARF-Aux/IAA) seem to maintain pairs <lb/>of amino acids specific to those classes (Fig. 4). Hence, based on this &apos;paired&apos; conservation <lb/>pattern, it is enticing to speculate that the Kinase and Kinase-derived PB1&apos;s might form <lb/>interacting pairs (Fig. 4). Despite the overall poor sequence conservation, it is clear that PB1 <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>domains are maintaining a flexible (global β-grasp fold) yet specific (local conserved <lb/>residues) sequence context in each family may provide specificity in function. Adding to the <lb/>complexity in specificity of each interaction, the PB1 domains can also undergo non-<lb/>canonical interactions. In plants, PAL OF QUIRKY (POQ), a Kinase-derived PB1 domain, <lb/>interacts with QUIRKY [24]. The PB1 domain of NLP interacts with HQ domain of TCP20 <lb/>[22]. In animals, the M2K5 PB1 interacts with ERK5, among many others [10]. However, the <lb/>structural and/or mechanistic basis of any of these interactions is currently unknown. <lb/>In various kingdoms, the PB1 domain-containing proteins have expanded to various <lb/>complexities/copies. For example, NBR1 in plants is (mostly) a single copy gene, where <lb/>ARFs and Aux/IAAs are represented by large gene families with more than 20 copies <lb/>(Additional file 1: Table S2). This clearly shows varying duplication rates in different gene <lb/>families. However, whether it is a single-or a multi-copy gene family, there is hardly any <lb/>conservation in the PB1 domain among the members of the same gene family outside of key <lb/>residues: Lysine in β1, Tyrosine in β3 and the OPCA motif (Fig. 4). Despite their low <lb/>conservation, all the PB1 domain families identified in plants can potentially form a β-grasp <lb/>ubiquitin fold (Fig. 6). Thus, for the PB1 domain it is evident that sequence conservation <lb/>seems to be a less important factor than maintaining the overall β-grasp structure itself. <lb/>This poor sequence conservation is never a bottleneck to identify the most important <lb/>features, as there are efficient machine learning based classification programs like Random <lb/>Forests (RF). RF has been very successful in classification with highly correlated variables at <lb/>low error rate [33]. The classification error rate is as low as 2% (in ARFs), but up to 14% in <lb/>Kinase-derived, which could be due to the broader distribution of all three most important <lb/>variables. This clearly defines that the more specific the variables are, the lower the error rate <lb/>is. RF also provides the relative importance of each variable with the precision. Hydrophobic <lb/>moment of β-sheets, mHbeta, the most important variable in our case, is low for Aux/IAA but <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>high for CBS, correlating with the increased β-sheets in CBS (Fig. 6). How this increase of β-<lb/>sheets could bring a change in function needs to be elucidated. Another interesting <lb/>observation is that there is a clear difference between some variables being very constrained <lb/>for each family. For example, the length of the PB1 domain is always above 90 amino acids <lb/>in the NBR1 family, where as it is always below 90 for ARFs. Hence, it is evident that PB1 <lb/>domains are constrained in different ways to maintain the uniqueness of that family. <lb/>Moreover, using more (specific) parameters in future, one should be able to distinguish PB1 <lb/>domains to a much broader extent, even across multiple kingdoms, and including homo-and <lb/>heterotypic interactions. <lb/>Apart from DIX and PB1 domains, the SAM domain also undergoes head-to-tail <lb/>oligomerization, but this domain is structurally different from both others [34]. It is unclear <lb/>why the PB1 domains are much more widespread and preferred for (head-to-tail) <lb/>oligomerization, compared to DIX or SAM domains. The latter are only limited to few <lb/>families and few members in each family. One reason could be that, as discussed above, the <lb/>PB1 domain is highly flexible in nature contributed by a wide range of (non)-canonical <lb/>interactions and its diverse evolutionary patterns. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Search for PB1 Domains in Animalia, Protozoa and Fungi <lb/>To study the PB1 domains in the kingdom Animalia, based on the literature, we first <lb/>extracted all the PB1 domain sequences of Human proteome from the UniProt database <lb/>(https://www.uniprot.org/proteomes/). To find other PB1 domains, we then used ten <lb/>proteomes from the kingdom across various phyla (see Additional file 4). A protein database <lb/>has been created with all these proteomes and queried this database with the PB1 domain <lb/>sequences from already known plant (Arabidopsis and Marchantia) and animal (Human) <lb/>species. BLASTP module in NCBI BLAST 2.7.1+ [35] was employed for this search and <lb/>InterPro domain database v5.30-69.0 (https://www.ebi.ac.uk/interpro/) was used for domain <lb/>identification in the BLAST hits. All the sequences that have a PB1 domain have been used <lb/>for further phylogenetic analysis. <lb/>A similar procedure was used to obtain the PB1 sequences from Protozoa and Fungi. <lb/>However, the proteomes of twelve fungi across multiple phyla have been obtained from <lb/>MycoCosm database at JGI (see Additional file 4; https://mycocosm.jgi.doe.gov). For the <lb/>Protozoa, we have used the six reference proteomes from UniProt (see Additional file 4). <lb/>Identification of the PB1 domains in Chromista and Plantae <lb/>To identify the PB1 domains in the kingdom Plantae, we employed a large <lb/>transcriptome resource, 1000 plant transcriptomes (OneKP) database [28,36]. Out of nearly <lb/>1300 transcriptomes in the database, we have used 485 transcriptomes in this study, covering <lb/>all the phyla in the kingdom Plantae. We have adapted a protocol that was developed earlier <lb/>[26]. In brief, the query PB1 sequences from Arabidopsis were searched against each <lb/>transcriptome, where the resulting scaffold hits were translated using TransDecoder (v2.0.1; <lb/>https://transdecoder.github.io). All these translated sequences were checked for the presence <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body>of PB1 domains using InterProScan [37] and only those protein sequences with a PB1 <lb/>domain identified were used for further analysis. In a similar way, for Chromista, we have <lb/>employed another transcriptome dataset, Marine Micro Eukaryote Transcriptome Sequencing <lb/>Project (MMETSP) database [38]. We have used all the available transcriptomes and adapted <lb/>a similar protocol as mentioned above (see Additional file 4). <lb/>Phylogeny construction and visualization <lb/>Using all the PB1 sequences that were identified in all the five kingdoms of <lb/>eukaryotes, we performed the phylogenetic analysis (see Additional file 5). The protein <lb/>sequences were aligned with MAFFT G-INS-i algorithm using default parameters (v7; [39]). <lb/>Alignment was cleaned up further, where the positions with more than 20% gaps were <lb/>removed with trimAl, prior to phylogeny construction [40]. ModelFinder (accessed through <lb/>IQtree) indicated &apos;LG&apos; as the best model of evolution, of all the 462 models tested [41]. <lb/>Further, the Maximum Likelihood (ML) method, employed in the IQtree program was used <lb/>for the phylogenetic tree construction, with 1000 rapid bootstrap replicates and tree branches <lb/>tested by SH-aLRT method [42]. The resulting tree was manually curated further for some <lb/>misplaced taxa. In a similar way, another phylogenetic tree was generated using the PB1 <lb/>sequences only from three kingdoms (Animalia, Fungi and Plantae). An unrooted version of <lb/>both the trees were visualized in Additional file 2 and Additional file 3. <lb/>Alignment of the plant PB1 domains <lb/>To understand the PB1 domains in the plant kingdom further, we have taken the PB1 <lb/>sequences of all the eight families from four species (Marchantia, Physcomitrella, Amborella <lb/>and Arabidopsis), aligned them using ClustalOmega [43]. After the alignment, the domains <lb/>from each family were separated and a sequence logo was generated using All the gene <lb/>identifiers from these four species are available in Additional file 1: Table S2. LogOddsLogo <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body>server was used for logo generation, with the colour codes for specific amino acids <lb/>(https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/ CBBresearch/Yu/logoddslogo/proteins.cgi). Amino acid <lb/>groups &apos;PAGFLIMV&apos;, &apos;KRH&apos; and &apos;DE&apos; were shown in purple, blue and red colours <lb/>respectively. All other amino acids were shown in black colour. <lb/>Random forest (RF) based plant PB1 classification <lb/>The Random Forest (RF) method was used to identify key amino acid descriptors to <lb/>differentiate and classify each of the PB1 domains into eight plant PB1 families [33]. To <lb/>make this classification an extensive one, we extracted all the PB1 domains from Plaza <lb/>Monocots database v4.5, that includes species from all the major phyla in Embryophytes <lb/>[44]. Since the size of each family is different, and to make the analysis uniform and <lb/>comparable, we have extracted 100 PB1 sequences randomly for each gene family (except 78 <lb/>for NBR1 as it is a single copy gene). We have used 28 amino acid descriptors (variables) <lb/>calculated either with &apos;protr&apos; or &apos;peptides&apos; R packages [45,46]. Among these, 20 variables <lb/>correspond to the composition of 20 amino acids, and the remaining eight correspond to the <lb/>general parameters such as length, molecular weight, hydrophobicity, net charge, isoelectric <lb/>point (pI), aliphatic index, hydrophobic moment of alpha and beta sheets. We used <lb/>&apos;RandomForest&apos; R package to build a maximum of 500 decision trees with 5 variables being <lb/>tried at each step (www.r-project.org; [47]). Confusion matrix and variable importance plots <lb/>showing mean decrease in accuracy and gini were obtained. Descriptive plots and other <lb/>graphs shown were obtained using &apos;ggplot2&apos; R package. Additional file 6 provides the <lb/>complete R script that has been used for the RF analysis. <lb/>Homology modelling <lb/>Homology modelling for the eight selected members in Arabidopsis, one each from <lb/>each plant PB1 family were performed using Phyre2 webserver &apos;normal&apos; mode [48]. The <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body>identifiers of the PB1 sequences used were: ARF5 (PDB: 4CHK), IAA17 (PDB: 2MUK), <lb/>At2G36500 (CBS), At1G04700 (Kinase), At2G01190 (Kinase-derived), NBR1, NLP9 and <lb/>Phox2. Obtained homology models were visualized in PyMol software (Schrodinger Inc., <lb/>USA). <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">DECLARATIONS <lb/>Ethics approval and consent to participate <lb/>Not applicable <lb/>Consent for publication <lb/>Not applicable <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of data and materials <lb/>All data generated or analyzed during this study are included in this published article and its <lb/>supplementary information files. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This research was supported by a VICI grant to D.W., from the Netherlands Organization for <lb/>Scientific Research (NWO; 865.14.001). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>S.K.M. and D.W. conceived the research. S.K.M. performed analysis. D.W supervised the <lb/>research and acquired funding. S.K.M. and D.W. discussed and interpreted the results and <lb/>wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors would like to thank the 1000 plant transcriptomes (OneKP) and Marine Micro <lb/>Eukaryotic Transcriptome Sequencing Project (MMETSP) consortiums for providing <lb/></div>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">essential data resources for the scientific community, and Francois Parcy and Mariann Bienz <lb/>for their comments on the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Nakamura R, Sumimoto H, Mizuki K, Hata K, Ago T, Kitajima S, et al. The PC motif: A <lb/>novel and evolutionarily conserved sequence involved in interaction between p40(phox) and <lb/>p67(phox), SH3 domain-containing cytosolic factors of the phagocyte NADPH oxidase. Eur J <lb/>Biochem. 1998;251:583-9. <lb/>2. Ito T, Matsui Y, Ago T, Ota K, Sumimoto H. Novel modular domain PB1 recognizes pc <lb/>motif to mediate functional protein-protein interactions. EMBO J. 2001;20:3938-46. <lb/>3. Lamark T, Perander M, Outzen H, Kristiansen K, Øvervatn A, Michaelsen E, et al. <lb/>Interaction Codes within the Family of Mammalian Phox and Bem1p Domain-containing <lb/>Proteins. J Biol Chem. 2003;278:34568-81. <lb/>4. Hagen G, Guilfoyle T. Auxin-responsive gene expression: genes, promoters and regulatory <lb/>factors. Plant Mol Biol. 2002;49:373-85. <lb/>5. Svenning S, Lamark T, Krause K, Johansen T. Plant NBR1 is a selective autophagy <lb/>substrate and a functional hybrid of the mammalian autophagic adapters NBR1 and <lb/>p62/SQSTM1. Autophagy. 2011;7:993-1010. <lb/>6. Guilfoyle TJ, Hagen G. Getting a grasp on domain III/IV responsible for Auxin Response <lb/>Factor-IAA protein interactions. Plant Sci. 2012;190:82-8. <lb/>7. Zientara-Rytter K, Sirko A. Significant role of PB1 and UBA domains in multimerization <lb/>of Joka2, a selective autophagy cargo receptor from tobacco. Front Plant Sci. 2014;5:1-13. <lb/>8. Korasick DA, Westfall CS, Lee SG, Nanao MH, Dumas R, Hagen G, et al. Molecular basis <lb/>for AUXIN RESPONSE FACTOR protein interaction and the control of auxin response <lb/>repression. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2014;111:5427-32. <lb/>9. Müller S, Kursula I, Zou P, Wilmanns M. Crystal structure of the PB1 domain of NBR1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>FEBS Lett. 2006;580:341-4. <lb/>10. Sumimoto H, Kamakura S, Ito T. Structure and function of the PB1 domain, a protein <lb/>interaction module conserved in animals, fungi, amoebas, and plants. Sci STKE. <lb/>2007;2007:1-16. <lb/>11. Lambeth JD. NOX enzymes and the biology of reactive oxygen. Nat Rev Immunol. <lb/>2004;4:181-9. <lb/>12. Suzuki A. The PAR-aPKC system: lessons in polarity. J Cell Sci. 2006;119:979-87. <lb/>13. Joberty G, Petersen C, Gao L, Macara IG. The cell-polarity protein Par6 links Par3 and <lb/>atypical protein kinase C to Cdc42. Nat Cell Biol. 2000;2:531-9. <lb/>14. MOSCAT J, DIAZMECO M, WOOTEN M. Signal integration and diversification <lb/>through the p62 scaffold protein. Trends Biochem Sci. 2007;32:95-100. <lb/>15. Nakamura K, Johnson GL. PB1 Domains of MEKK2 and MEKK3 Interact with the <lb/>MEK5 PB1 Domain for Activation of the ERK5 Pathway. J Biol Chem. 2003;278:36989-92. <lb/>16. Roccato E, Pagliardini S, Cleris L, Canevari S, Formelli F, Pierotti MA, et al. Role of <lb/>TFG sequences outside the coiled-coil domain in TRK-T3 oncogenic activation. Oncogene. <lb/>2003;22:807-18. <lb/>17. Honbou K, Minakami R, Yuzawa S, Takeya R, Suzuki NN, Kamakura S, et al. Full-<lb/>length p40phox structure suggests a basis for regulation mechanism of its membrane binding. <lb/>EMBO J. 2007;26:1176-86. <lb/>18. Takemoto D, Kamakura S, Saikia S, Becker Y, Wrenn R, Tanaka A, et al. Polarity <lb/>proteins Bem1 and Cdc24 are components of the filamentous fungal NADPH oxidase <lb/>complex. Proc Natl Acad Sci. 2011;108:2861-6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>19. Piya S, Shrestha SK, Binder B, Stewart CN, Hewezi T. Protein-protein interaction and <lb/>gene co-expression maps of ARFs and Aux/IAAs in Arabidopsis. Front Plant Sci. 2014;5:1-<lb/>9. <lb/>20. Nanao MH, Vinos-Poyo T, Brunoud G, Thévenon E, Mazzoleni M, Mast D, et al. <lb/>Structural basis for oligomerization of auxin transcriptional regulators. Nat Commun. <lb/>2014;5:3617. <lb/>21. Weijers D, Wagner D. Transcriptional Responses to the Auxin Hormone. Annu Rev Plant <lb/>Biol. 2016;67:539-74. <lb/>22. Guan P, Ripoll J-J, Wang R, Vuong L, Bailey-Steinitz LJ, Ye D, et al. Interacting TCP <lb/>and NLP transcription factors control plant responses to nitrate availability. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci. 2017;114:2419-24. <lb/>23. Konishi M, Yanagisawa S. The role of protein-protein interactions mediated by the PB1 <lb/>domain of NLP transcription factors in nitrate-inducible gene expression. BMC Plant Biol. <lb/>2019;19:90. <lb/>24. Trehin C, Schrempp S, Chauvet A, Berne-Dedieu A, Thierry A-M, Faure J-E, et al. <lb/>QUIRKY interacts with STRUBBELIG and PAL OF QUIRKY to regulate cell growth <lb/>anisotropy during Arabidopsis gynoecium development. Development. 2013;140:4807-17. <lb/>25. Burke RM, Berk BC. The Role of PB1 Domain Proteins in Endothelial Cell Dysfunction <lb/>and Disease. Antioxid Redox Signal. 2015;22:1243-56. <lb/>26. Mutte SK, Kato H, Rothfels C, Melkonian M, Wong GK-S, Weijers D. Origin and <lb/>evolution of the nuclear auxin response system. Elife. 2018;7:e33399. <lb/>27. Mu X, Luo J. Evolutionary analyses of NIN-like proteins in plants and their roles in <lb/>nitrate signaling. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2019;76:3753-64. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>28. Matasci N, Hung L-H, Yan Z, Carpenter EJ, Wickett NJ, Mirarab S, et al. Data access for <lb/>the 1,000 Plants (1KP) project. Gigascience. 2014;3:17. <lb/>29. Kirkin V, McEwan DG, Novak I, Dikic I. A Role for Ubiquitin in Selective Autophagy. <lb/>Mol Cell. 2009;34:259-69. <lb/>30. Sumimoto H. Structure, regulation and evolution of Nox-family NADPH oxidases that <lb/>produce reactive oxygen species. FEBS J. 2008;275:3249-77. <lb/>31. Fujiwara M, Uemura T, Ebine K, Nishimori Y, Ueda T, Nakano A, et al. Interactomics of <lb/>Qa-SNARE in Arabidopsis thaliana. Plant Cell Physiol. 2014;55:781-9. <lb/>32. Hirano Y, Yoshinaga S, Takeya R, Suzuki NN, Horiuchi M, Kohjima M, et al. Structure <lb/>of a Cell Polarity Regulator, a Complex between Atypical PKC and Par6 PB1 Domains. J <lb/>Biol Chem. 2005;280:9653-61. <lb/>33. Breiman L. Random Forests. Mach Learn. 2001;45:5-32. <lb/>34. Bienz M. Signalosome assembly by domains undergoing dynamic head-to-tail <lb/>polymerization. Trends Biochem Sci. 2014;39:487-95. <lb/>35. Camacho C, Coulouris G, Avagyan V, Ma N, Papadopoulos J, Bealer K, et al. BLAST+: <lb/>architecture and applications. BMC Bioinformatics. 2009;10:421. <lb/>36. One Thousand Plant Transcriptomes Initiative. One thousand plant transcriptomes and the <lb/>phylogenomics of green plants. Nature. 2019;574:679-85. <lb/>37. Jones P, Binns D, Chang HY, Fraser M, Li W, McAnulla C, et al. InterProScan 5: <lb/>Genome-scale protein function classification. Bioinformatics. 2014;30:1236-40. <lb/>38. Keeling PJ, Burki F, Wilcox HM, Allam B, Allen EE, Amaral-Zettler LA, et al. The <lb/>Marine Microbial Eukaryote Transcriptome Sequencing Project (MMETSP): Illuminating the <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Functional Diversity of Eukaryotic Life in the Oceans through Transcriptome Sequencing. <lb/>Roberts RG, editor. PLoS Biol. 2014;12:e1001889. <lb/>39. Katoh K, Standley DM. MAFFT multiple sequence alignment software version 7: <lb/>Improvements in performance and usability. Mol Biol Evol. 2013;30:772-80. <lb/>40. Capella-Gutiérrez S, Silla-Martínez JM, Gabaldón T. trimAl: A tool for automated <lb/>alignment trimming in large-scale phylogenetic analyses. Bioinformatics. 2009;25:1972-3. <lb/>41. Kalyaanamoorthy S, Minh BQ, Wong TKF, Von Haeseler A, Jermiin LS. ModelFinder: <lb/>Fast model selection for accurate phylogenetic estimates. Nat Methods. 2017;14:587-9. <lb/>42. Nguyen LT, Schmidt HA, Von Haeseler A, Minh BQ. IQ-TREE: A fast and effective <lb/>stochastic algorithm for estimating maximum-likelihood phylogenies. Mol Biol Evol. <lb/>2015;32:268-74. <lb/>43. Sievers F, Higgins DG. Clustal Omega for making accurate alignments of many protein <lb/>sequences. Protein Sci. 2018;27:135-45. <lb/>44. Van Bel M, Diels T, Vancaester E, Kreft L, Botzki A, Van De Peer Y, et al. PLAZA 4.0: <lb/>An integrative resource for functional, evolutionary and comparative plant genomics. Nucleic <lb/>Acids Res. Oxford University Press; 2018;46:D1190-6. <lb/>45. Osorio D, Rondón-Villarreal P, Torres R. Peptides: A package for data mining of <lb/>antimicrobial peptides. R J. 2015;7:4-14. <lb/>46. Xiao N, Cao DS, Zhu MF, Xu QS. Protr/ProtrWeb: R package and web server for <lb/>generating various numerical representation schemes of protein sequences. Bioinformatics. <lb/>2015;31:1857-9. <lb/>47. Liaw A, Wiener M. Classification and Regression by randomForest. R News. 2002;2:18-<lb/>22. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>48. Kelley LA, Mezulis S, Yates CM, Wass MN, Sternberg MJE. The Phyre2 web portal for <lb/>protein modeling, prediction and analysis. Nat Protoc. 2015;10:845-58. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">ADDITIONAL FILES <lb/>Additional file 1: Supplementary figures and Supplementary tables <lb/>Additional file 2: Full phylogenetic tree based on species from three kingdoms, related to <lb/>Fig. 2 <lb/>Additional file 3: Full phylogenetic tree based on species from three kingdoms, related to <lb/>Additional file 1: Fig. S2 <lb/>Additional file 4: List of species used for the phylogenetic tree construction in all the five <lb/>kingdoms <lb/>Additional file 5: FASTA file of all the PB1 domain sequences used for phylogenetic tree <lb/>construction <lb/>Additional file 6: R script used for RandomForest classification</div> 


	</text>
</tei>
