<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>Providing new insights on the byphasic lifestyle of the predatory bacterium Bdellovibrio <lb/>bacteriovorus through genome-scale metabolic modeling. <lb/>Short title: Genome-scale metabolic modeling of B. bacteriovorus <lb/>Herencias C 1⸸ , Prieto MA 1, 2 and Nogales J 2,3 * <lb/>1 Microbial and Plant Biotechnology Department, Biological Research Center, CSIC, Madrid, <lb/>Spain. <lb/>2 Interdisciplinary Platform for Sustainable Plastics towards a Circular Economy-Spanish <lb/>National Research Council (SusPlast-CSIC), Madrid, Spain. <lb/>3 Department of Systems Biology, Centro Nacional de Biotecnología, CSIC, Madrid, Spain <lb/>⸸ Present address: Department of Microbiology, Hospital Universitario Ramon y Cajal, Instituto <lb/>Ramon y Cajal de Investigacion Sanitaria (IRYCIS), Madrid, Spain. <lb/>*Corresponding author. <lb/>Mailing address: <lb/>E-mail: j.nogales@csic.es <lb/>2 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>In this study we analyze the growth-phase dependent metabolic states of Bdellovibrio <lb/>bacteriovorus by constructing a fully compartmented, mass and charge-balanced genome-scale <lb/>metabolic model of this predatory bacterium (iCH457). Considering the differences between life <lb/>cycle phases driving the growth of this predator, growth-phase condition-specific models have <lb/>been generated allowing the systematic study of its metabolic capabilities. Using these <lb/>unprecedented computational tools, we have been able to analyze, from a system level, the <lb/>dynamic metabolism of the predatory bacteria as the life cycle progresses. We provide solid <lb/>computational evidences supporting potential axenic growth of B. bacteriovorus&apos;s in a rich <lb/>medium based its encoded metabolic capabilities. Our systems-level analysis confirms the <lb/>presence of &quot;energy-saving&quot; mechanisms in this predator as well as an abrupt metabolic shift <lb/>between the attack and intraperiplasmic growth phases. Our results strongly suggest that <lb/>predatory bacteria&apos;s metabolic networks have low robustness, likely hampering their ability to <lb/>tackle drastic environmental fluctuations, thus being confined to stable and predictable habitats. <lb/>Overall, we present here a valuable computational testbed based on predatory bacteria activity <lb/>for rational design of novel and controlled biocatalysts in biotechnological/clinical applications. <lb/>AUTHOR SUMMARY <lb/>Bacterial predation is an interspecific relationship widely extended in nature. Among other <lb/>predators, Bdellovibrio and like organism (BALOs) have received recently a great attention due <lb/>to the high potential applications such as biocontrol agent in medicine, agriculture, aquaculture <lb/>and water treatment. Despite the increasing interest in of this predatory bacterium its complex <lb/>lifestyle and growth conditions hamper the full exploitation of their biotechnological properties. <lb/>In order to overcome these important shortcomings, we provide here the first genome-scale <lb/>model of a predator bacterium constructed so far. By using the model as a computational <lb/>testbed, we provide solid evidences of the metabolic autonomy of this interesting bacterium in <lb/> 3 <lb/> term of growth, as well as its dynamic metabolism powering the biphasic life style of this <lb/>predator. We found a low metabolic robustness thus suggesting that Bdellovibrio is more niche-<lb/>specific than previously thought and that the environmental conditions governing predation may <lb/>be relatively uniform. Overall, we provide here a valuable computational tool largely facilitating <lb/>rational design of novel and controlled predator-based biocatalysts in biotechnological/clinical <lb/>applications. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Predation is a biological interaction where an individual, the predator, feeds on another, the <lb/>prey, to survive. Since predation has played a central role in the diversification and organization <lb/>of life, this system provides an interesting biological model from both an ecological and <lb/>evolutionary point of view. Predation is an example of coevolution where the predator and prey <lb/>promote reciprocal evolutionary responses to counteract the adaptation of each other [1]. This <lb/>interspecific relationship is widely extended in nature, including the microbial world where the <lb/>main predators are bacteriophages, protozoa and predatory bacteria [2]. Focusing on bacteria, <lb/>this group is composed, among others, by Bdellovibrio and like organisms (BALOs) which are <lb/>small, highly motile, and aerobic gram-negative predatory bacteria that prey on a wide variety <lb/>of other gram-negative bacteria. Originally discovered in soil [3], BALOs are ubiquitous in <lb/>nature. They can be found in terrestrial and aquatic habitats, bacterial biofilms, plants, roots, <lb/>animals and human feces [4] and lung microbiota [5]. B. bacteriovorus is the best characterized <lb/>member of the group of BALOs and the genome of different strains, including HD100, Tiberius <lb/>and 109J have been sequenced providing a reliable source of genetic information [6-8]. <lb/>B. bacteriovorus exhibits a biphasic growth cycle (Fig 1), including a free-swimming attack <lb/>phase (AP) and an intraperiplasmic growth phase (GP) inside the prey´s periplasm forming the <lb/>so-called bdelloplast structure. During AP, free living cells from extracellular environment are <lb/>in active search for new preys. After attachment, and once the predator-prey interaction is stable <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>and irreversible, the predator enters in the prey`s periplasm, where it grows and replicates DNA <lb/>during the GP using the cytoplasm of the prey cell as a source of nutrients and biomass building <lb/>blocks. When the prey is exhausted, B. bacteriovorus, grown as a filament, septs into several <lb/>daughter cells and, through its large array of hydrolytic enzymes, lyses the ghost-prey&apos;s outer <lb/>cell membrane and releases into the medium [9]. Interestingly, host-independent (HI) mutants <lb/>of Bdellovibrio strains have been developed under laboratory conditions. These HI predators are <lb/>able to grow axenically (without prey) in a rich-nutrient medium mimicking the dimorphic <lb/>pattern of elongated growth, division and differentiation [10]. It is worth noticing that the axenic <lb/>growth of these mutant strains is given by a mutation in the host interaction (hit) locus, which <lb/>has been described as being involved in regulatory and/or scaffold elements [11]. This argues in <lb/>favor of this mutation having no metabolic (enzymatic) impact. In fact, the main metabolism of <lb/>these HI derivatives should not have suffered changes with respect to the wild type Bdellovibrio <lb/>strains. <lb/>Fig 1. Lifecycle of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus HD100. 1) Prey location: B. bacteriovorus <lb/>moves towards prey-rich regions. 2) Attachment: the predator anchors to the host cell, which <lb/>leads to the infection. 3) Invasion: B. bacteriovorus enters the periplasm of the prey cell. 4 and <lb/>5) Growth in bdelloplast and development: the prey has a rounded appearance due to cell wall <lb/>modification and B. bacteriovorus grows in the periplasm and replicates its DNA. B. <lb/>bacteriovorus uses the prey cytoplasm as a source of nutrients. 6 and 7) Septation and <lb/>development: the predator septs when resources become limited and it matures into individual <lb/>attack phase cells. 8) Lysis: mature attack-phase cells lyse the cell wall of the bdelloplast, <lb/>initiating the search for fresh prey. The complete cycle takes about 4 h. <lb/>B. bacteriovorus&apos; extraordinary repertoire of susceptible preys allows for a wide range of <lb/>potential applications based on its predatory capability, such as biocontrol agent in medicine, <lb/>agriculture, aquaculture and water treatment [12-15]. Furthermore, it has been proposed as an <lb/>excellent source of valuable biotechnological enzymes and as a biological lytic tool for <lb/>intracellular products, due to its hydrolytic arsenal [4,16,17]. Moreover, regarding its unique <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>lifestyle it represents a good model for evolution studies focusing, for example, on the origin of <lb/>the eukaryotic cell [18,19]. Despite the interest that this predatory bacterium&apos;s potential <lb/>applications have recently aroused among the scientific community, its complex lifestyle and <lb/>growth conditions make it hard to implement metabolic and physiological studies. As a direct <lb/>consequence, to date, its physiology and metabolic capabilities remain an enigma to a large <lb/>extent [20]. Moreover, the potential of this predator to be used as a biotechnological chassis <lb/>depends on the quantity and quality of the available metabolic knowledge. Therefore, expanding <lb/>the knowledge of this predatory bacterium as a shuttle for the further full exploitation of its <lb/>unique biotechnological applications would require a reliable platform driving the rational <lb/>understanding of its characteristics. <lb/>Following this aim, the advent of genomic age and the subsequent large amount of derived <lb/>high-throughput data, have largely contributed to deeper understanding of microbial behavior, at <lb/>system level [21]. Specifically, genome-scale metabolic models (GEMs) are being used to <lb/>analyze bacterial metabolism under different environmental conditions [22,23]. GEMs are <lb/>structured representations of the metabolic capabilities of a target organism based on existing <lb/>biochemical, genetic and phenotypic knowledge which can be used to predict phenotype from <lb/>genotype [24]. <lb/>The application of Constraint-Based Reconstruction and Analysis (COBRA) approaches [25] <lb/>together with specific GEMs have been successfully applied for better understanding of <lb/>interspecies interactions such as mutualism, competition and parasitism providing important <lb/>insights into genotype-phenotype relationship [26]. Despite GEMs being powerful tools to <lb/>elucidate the metabolic capabilities of single systems, addressing the complex metabolism of <lb/>bacterial predators having biphasic growth-cycles such as B. bacteriovorus is challenging and <lb/>has remained elusive so far. <lb/>We provide here the first step toward the metabolic understanding at system level of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus by the reconstruction of its metabolism at genome-scale. We further use this <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>cutting edge computational platform as a test bed for the integration and contextualization of <lb/>transcriptomic and physiological data shedding light on the biphasic lifestyle of this predatory <lb/>bacterium. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Characteristics of B. bacteriovorus metabolic reconstruction <lb/>A genome-scale metabolic model (iCH457) including the metabolic content derived from <lb/>genome annotation and available biochemical information was created for B. bacteriovorus <lb/>HD100. iCH457 does not differentiate AP and GP, but it is a powerful tool for determining and <lb/>analyzing the potential metabolic capabilities of the system from a global perspective. All the <lb/>gene-protein-reaction associations (GPRs) included in the model were subject to a rigorous <lb/>manual curation process in order to ensure the quality of the final model (Fig. 2). Several open <lb/>reading frames (ORFs) were annotated de novo and/or re-annotated during the reconstruction <lb/>process. For instance, from the initial 75 ORFs included in the reconstruction draft belonging to <lb/>amino acid metabolism based on bioinformatics evidence, only 65 (87%) were finally included <lb/>according to bioinformatics and literature-based evidences. Moreover, during the manual <lb/>curation process, we confirmed (by sequence homology) the function of several genes related to <lb/>amino acids metabolism and the hydrolytic enzymes involved (Tables S4 and S5). For instance, <lb/>gene bd0950, annotated as an unspecific acetyltransferase, was specifically associated with an <lb/>UDP 2,3-diamino-2,3-dideoxy-D-glucose acyltransferase, while gene bd2095, wrongly <lb/>annotated as encoding for an acetyl-CoA C-acetyltransferase, was unequivocally re-annotated as <lb/>a 3-ketoacyl-CoA thiolase. <lb/>Fig 2. iCH457 metabolic model pipeline. A) The draft of metabolic reconstruction was based <lb/>on available metabolic models (iJN1411 and iJO1366), the genome sequence of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus HD100 and the automatic model Seed. Manual curation is required to accurately <lb/>fine-tune the information contained in the metabolic model and several steps of network <lb/>validation and analysis are required to finally obtain the metabolic model iCH457. B) <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Generation of condition-specific models: iCHAP and iCHGP. The general model iCH457 was <lb/>constrained based on nutrient availability (minimal and rich in silico media), biological role <lb/>(ATP production or biomass generation) and transcriptomic available data (Karunker et al., <lb/>2013)*. GIM 3 E algorithm was used to construct the condition-specific models. <lb/>iCH457 includes 457 ORFs, which represent 13 % of the coding genes in the genome, whose <lb/>gene products account for 705 metabolic and transport reactions (accounting for 70.5 % of the <lb/>model&apos;s total reactions). The model was completed with the inclusion of 296 non-gene <lb/>associated reactions (29.5 %) based on physiological and/or biochemical evidences supporting <lb/>their presence in B. bacteriovorus. For instance, reactions related to the ACP acyltransferase <lb/>(G3PAT) needed for glycerophospholipid biosynthesis were included based on the <lb/>physiological evidence provided by Nguyen and col. and Muller and col. [27,28]. Overall, <lb/>iCH457 accounts for a total of 1001 reactions and 955 metabolites distributed in three different <lb/>compartments: cytoplasm, periplasm and extracellular space. <lb/>Reactions from iCH457 fall into 12 main functional categories (Fig 3). It is noteworthy that cell <lb/>envelope metabolism seems to be the most represented group with a total of 222 reactions. In <lb/>this important group we found reactions involved in the metabolism of peptidoglycans, <lb/>lipopolysaccharides, glycerophospholipids, and murein. Across this group, catabolic reactions <lb/>including reactions involved in the degradation of peptidoglycan by specific carboxypeptidases <lb/>represent up to 37%. This high number of hydrolytic reactions present in iCH457 is consistent <lb/>with the important role of these enzymes in the degradation of the prey&apos;s cell wall to penetrate <lb/>into the periplasm, completion of the growth cycle and also in recycling the envelope <lb/>components [29]. <lb/>Fig 3. Distribution of the reactions of the system in 12 global functional categories. The <lb/>metabolites inside the rectangles correspond with the auxotrophies in the cofactor metabolism <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>(dark blue fraction) and the amino acid metabolism (brown fraction), respectively. Asterisks (*) <lb/>show the metabolite groups that contain auxotrophies. <lb/>In the past 15 years, GEMs have garnered considerable research attention and numerous <lb/>metabolic reconstructions have been generated for several organisms [30]. The metabolic <lb/>models within the δ-proteobacteria group are underrepresented among this phylum and only a <lb/>few of them have been constructed, for instance for Geobacter spp. and Desulfovibrio vulgaris <lb/>[31-33]. Thus, the model of B. bacteriovorus HD100, iCH457, represents a new model within <lb/>this group, which, as depicted in Table 1, provides a complete reconstruction of this important <lb/>bacterial group in terms of the metabolites and reactions included. Furthermore, other microbial <lb/>interactions have been recently modeled, such as the syntrophic association between <lb/>Desulfovibrio vulgaris Hildenborough and Methanococcus maripaludis S2 [32]. The metabolic <lb/>reconstruction of this interaction highlighted the potential use of in silico predictions to capture <lb/>growth parameters and community composition of bacterial communities. However, this is the <lb/>first metabolic model of a predatory bacterium. <lb/>Table 1. Comparison of the metabolic properties of iCH457 compared with other δ-<lb/>proteobacteria (Geobacter spp. and Desulfovibrio vulgaris) metabolic models and with the well-<lb/>establish metabolic reconstruction of P. putida (iJN1411) and E. coli (iJO1366). <lb/>iJN1411 <lb/>iJO1366 <lb/>Geobacter <lb/>metallirre-<lb/>ducens <lb/>Geobacter <lb/>sulfirreducens <lb/>Desulfovibrio <lb/>vulgaris <lb/>Hildenborough <lb/>iCH457 <lb/>Protein-<lb/>coding <lb/>Genes <lb/>5350 <lb/>4405 <lb/>3532 <lb/>3530 <lb/>3379 <lb/>3584 <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>196 <lb/>197 <lb/>Model-driven assessment of auxotrophies and biomass building block transport systems <lb/>198 <lb/>highlight the predatory lifestyle of B. bacteriovorus <lb/> 199 <lb/> During the reconstruction process, we identified several incomplete biosynthetic pathways <lb/> 200 <lb/> (amino acids, cofactors, and vitamins) that are consistent with the numerous auxotrophies <lb/>201 <lb/>previously reported for strain HD100 [6]. However, model-based analyses provide an integrated <lb/>202 <lb/>overview of the complete metabolic network of this predator, including metabolic gaps <lb/>203 <lb/>potentially responsible for the auxotrophies. This is because instead of analyzing just the main <lb/>204 <lb/>synthetic pathways, such in silico analyses consider the global metabolism, including alternative <lb/>205 <lb/>and/or secondary/accessory biosynthetic routes. <lb/>206 <lb/>In fact, model-based analyses identified up to 24 different auxotrophies. For instance, from the <lb/>207 <lb/>20 proteinogenic amino acids, external supply of 14 of them was required to achieve in silico <lb/>208 <lb/>growth, including arginine, asparagine, cysteine, glycine, histidine, methionine, leucine, <lb/>209 <lb/>isoleucine, valine, phenylalanine, tryptophan, threonine, serine and proline. In addition, external <lb/>210 <lb/>supply of several cofactors including riboflavin, nicotinamide, putrescine, folic acid, <lb/>211 <lb/>pantothenate, pyridoxal phosphate, biotin and lipoate was needed in order to achieve in silico <lb/>212 <lb/>growth (Fig 2A). <lb/>Genes (%) <lb/>1411 <lb/>(26%) <lb/>1366 <lb/>(31%) <lb/>747 (21%) <lb/>588 (17%) <lb/>744 (22%) <lb/>457 (13%) <lb/>Metabolites 2057 <lb/>1136 <lb/>769 <lb/>541 <lb/>1016 <lb/>956 <lb/>Reactions <lb/>2754 <lb/>2251 <lb/>697 <lb/>523 <lb/>951 <lb/>1001 <lb/>Reference <lb/>(Nogales et <lb/>al., 2017) <lb/>(Orth et <lb/>al., <lb/>2011) <lb/>(Sun et al., <lb/>2009) <lb/>(Mahadevan et <lb/>al., 2006) <lb/>(Flowers et al., <lb/>2018) <lb/>This work <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Concerning nucleosides monophosphate, we found that B. bacteriovorus has the ability to <lb/>synthetize de novo all these key biomass building blocks despite nucleosides derived from the <lb/>hydrolysis of prey having been traditionally suggested as a source of nucleic acids [34]. <lb/>Supporting this computational analysis, radiotracer studies showed that strain 109J mainly <lb/>utilized host nucleosides monophosphate during intraperiplasmic growth, however it was also <lb/>able to synthesize its own pool of nucleotides [35,36]. This phenomenon has been traditionally <lb/>explained in the context of an &quot;energy-saving&quot; mechanism. Similarly, this mechanism has also <lb/>been reported, and validated by our in silico analysis, for phospholipid assimilation and the <lb/>recycling of some unaltered or altered fatty acids from the prey. Thus, while model analysis <lb/>confirmed a complete and likely functional fatty acid de novo biosynthetic pathway, the direct <lb/>uptake of these biomass building blocks has been largely reported. This demonstrates a more <lb/>efficient incorporation of cellular components from the prey [27,37]. <lb/>Due to their lifestyle and the obligate requirement of obtaining essential biomass building <lb/>blocks from prey, the transport subsystem became an important key for the survival of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus. In fact, this category was found to be one of the most representative in terms of <lb/>number of reactions (161), highlighting their importance in cellular interchange. Although a <lb/>comprehensive analysis of the transport systems in the predator has been previously reported <lb/>[38], the predicted substrate specificity needs more experimental support. Remarkably, iCH457 <lb/>model accounts for 67 % of the annotated transport system reported in the genome. <lb/>It is worth emphasizing the case of peptide transporters; despite amino acids from protein <lb/>breakage having been suggested as major carbon and energy sources during the intraperiplasmic <lb/>growth of B. bacteriovorus [39], we noticed a significant lack of specific amino acid <lb/>transporters during the model reconstruction and functional validation process. Instead, we <lb/>found a large number of di-and tripeptide transporters, suggesting that the predator might be <lb/>taking up small peptides from the prey. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Overall, model-based analyses largely supported the presence of energy-saving mechanisms in <lb/>B. bacteriovorus targeting the biosynthesis of nucleotide monophosphates and phospholipids, <lb/>but not of amino acids or vitamins whose availability depends exclusively on the prey. <lb/>Likewise, detailed analysis of transport systems included in the model suggests B. <lb/>bacteriovorus&apos; ability to obtain oligopeptides through prey proteins cleavage and use them as its <lb/>main source of carbon, nitrogen and energy during GP. <lb/>iCH457 exhibits high accuracy predicting physiological states of B. bacteriovorus under <lb/>different nutrients scenarios <lb/>A model&apos;s capability of providing accurate predictions of empirically-supported knowledge of a <lb/>target organism&apos;s functional states is a key feature in order to assess the accuracy and <lb/>completeness of the final reconstruction. However, the obligate predatory lifestyle of B. <lb/>bacteriovoru and the complex environment provided by the prey, in terms of nutrients, prove <lb/>challenging when using classical validation workflows based on single nutrient sources. <lb/>Therefore, for iCH457 validation, we took advantage of spontaneous HI Bdellovibrio strains <lb/>developed under laboratory conditions. Such HI strains exhibit a similar lifecycle when growing <lb/>in a rich medium to the wild type strain growing inside the intraperiplasmic space of the prey <lb/>[40]. Indeed, because the HI phenotype has been attributed to putative regulatory and/or <lb/>scaffold mechanisms rather than to metabolic genes (enzymes) [41,42], these HI strains are <lb/>supposed to possess metabolic capabilities identical to those of the parental strains. Thus, for the <lb/>GEMs validation process, including potential carbon sources and biomass generation rates, we <lb/>decided to use data from HI Bdellovibrio strains for iCH457 validation. <lb/>Specifically, we validated the predictive capabilities of the iCH457 by comparing in silico <lb/>results with experimentally determined biomass production and growth rates of the HI strain B. <lb/>bacteriovorus 109 Davis [43]. The in silico growth rates were calculated using minimal medium <lb/>supplemented with selected carbon sources (S1 Text). iCH457 was very precise predicting <lb/>growth rate on five different carbon sources, with an accuracy close to 100% in the case of <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>glutamate, glutamine and succinate, and 70% for pyruvate and lactate (Fig 4A). The slight <lb/>discrepancies found between in silico predictions and in vivo results might be explained by an <lb/>incomplete formulation of biomass function or higher energy maintenance requirements under <lb/>the simulated conditions not accounted for in the current reconstruction. In addition, higher in <lb/>silico growth rates are often found due to the intrinsic nature and limitations of FBA. FBA <lb/>presumes a final evolution state in stark contrast with the potential scenario found in vivo which <lb/>could lack the proper adaptation to these metabolites as a primary carbon source [44]. Also, <lb/>FBA only predicts steady-state fluxes and does not account for any regulatory constraints, <lb/>which should play an important role in the uptake of substrates from the extracellular medium <lb/>[45]. Overall, our model predictions showed a significant accuracy that is comparable to other <lb/>high-quality genome-scale models already available [46]. <lb/>Fig 4. Evaluation of the metabolic capabilities of iCH457. A) Comparison of the growth <lb/>performance of the in silico iCH457 strain and a derivative strain of B. bacteriovorus 109 <lb/>Davis on different carbon sources. Experimental values of growth rate were calculated using <lb/>the mass doubling time previously compiled in Ishiguro et al. (Ishiguro, 1974). The in silico <lb/> growth rate was calculated with the minimal medium defined in Annex 4 supplemented with the <lb/>tested carbon source. B) Comparison of the biomass production predicted in silico with the <lb/>available experimental data performed with the prey-independent B. bacteriovorus 109 Davis <lb/>(Ishiguro, 1974). In vivo and in silico biomass data were expressed as Kendall&apos;s rank correlation <lb/>coefficient (τ = 0,88) for iCH457. GLU: glutamate, GLN: glutamine, PYR: pyruvate, LACT: <lb/>lactate, SUCC: succinate. <lb/>Beyond the availability to predict growth rates, it is valuable to assess the model&apos;s ability to <lb/>predict the maximum amount of biomass produced from known concentrations of given carbon <lb/>and energy sources. Similar high accuracy was found regarding the predictability of biomass <lb/>production between in silico and experimental data (Kendall`s coefficient τ = 0.88) (Fig 4B). It <lb/>is noteworthy that the in silico analysis provided in these evaluations largely confirmed the <lb/>prey-independent metabolic states, thus shedding light on the predator&apos;s potentially autonomous <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>metabolism. These results are in good agreement with the large amount of HI derivative strains <lb/>isolated previously [47] and the recent description of the metabolic response of AP cells in NB <lb/>medium to synthesize and secrete proteases [48]. Therefore, the obligate predatory lifestyle of <lb/>B. bacteriovorus should be questioned, at least from a metabolic point of view. <lb/>Overall, the high accuracy exhibited by iCH457 encourages us to use the model to characterize <lb/>and better understand the metabolic states that underline the biphasic growth cycle of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus. <lb/>Reaction essentiality towards understanding the predator´s lifestyle <lb/>It is well-known that the environmental conditions and natural habitat of a given bacterium <lb/>largely influence its evolutionary traits, including processes of genome expansion/reduction. <lb/>Therefore, and taking advantage of iCH457, it would be interesting to address from a <lb/>computational perspective whether the genome content of the predator has been influenced by <lb/>its complex lifestyle. We identified a set of essential reactions in iCH457. The network <lb/>reaction(s) associated with each gene was individually &quot;deleted&quot; by setting the flux to 0 and <lb/>optimizing for the biomass function. A reaction was defined as essential if after constrained it <lb/>the growth rate decreased to less than 10% of wild type model. To properly contextualize the <lb/>reaction essentiality analysis, we compared our results with those from some free-living <lb/>organisms such as P. putida KT2440 (iJN1411) [46], E. coli strain K-12 MG1655 (iJO1366) <lb/>and Geobacter metallireducens GS-15 (iAF987), as well as with other bacteria that also possess <lb/>intracellular stages during their growth cycles, such as Yersinia pestis CO92 (iPC815), <lb/>Salmonella enterica subsp. enterica serovar Typhimurium str. LT2 (STM_v1_0 model) and <lb/>Shigella flexneri (iSF1195). <lb/>This reaction essentiality analysis showed no significant correlation between the number of <lb/>essential reactions and the size of the metabolic network or the microorganism&apos;s lifestyle. The <lb/>number of essential reactions found ranged from 214 to 419, with Y. pestis and P. putida being <lb/>the organisms with lower and higher number of essential reactions, respectively. Moreover, the <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>number of these essential reactions for the δ-proteobacteria, B. bacteriovorus and G. <lb/>metallireducens, account for approximately 30% of the total reactions (Table 2 and Fig S1). <lb/>This rate could be related with the lack of a secondary metabolism in this bacterial group, which <lb/>should be explored in depth in order to increase the computational value of the results. <lb/>Table 2. Reaction essentiality of the metabolic models of different bacteria <lb/>E. coli P. putida G. metallireducens B. bacteriovorus Salmonella S. flexneri Y. pestis <lb/>Total <lb/>reactions 2583 2826 <lb/>1285 <lb/>1002 <lb/>2545 <lb/>2630 <lb/>1961 <lb/>Essential <lb/>reactions* 274 <lb/>404 <lb/>387 <lb/>305 <lb/>333 <lb/>264 <lb/>210 <lb/>% of <lb/>essential <lb/>rxn <lb/>10.6 14.6 <lb/>30.1 <lb/>30.2 <lb/>13.1 <lb/>10.3 <lb/>10.7 <lb/>*Exchange reactions were excluded <lb/>The comparison of the essential reactions of the free living organism and the intracellular <lb/>bacteria provided three main groups of essential reactions (exchange reactions were excluded <lb/>from the comparison) (Fig 5): i) shared essential reactions between free-living and intracellular <lb/>microorganisms (38 reactions), ii) free-living microorganisms&apos; exclusive essential reactions (27 <lb/>reactions), iii) intracellular microorganisms&apos; exclusive essential reactions (15 reactions). <lb/>Potentially, the 38 shared reactions would be part of the hypothetical essential metabolic <lb/>network. Overall, the reactions found in the shared essentiality group are related with cell <lb/>envelope, nucleotide, and cofactors (Table S6). <lb/>Fig 5. Comparison of the reaction essentiality of intracellular lifestyle and free-living <lb/>bacteria. <lb/>Among the essential reactions found exclusively in the group of free-living microorganisms, <lb/>none of them are present in the iCH457 metabolic model and they are mostly involved in cell <lb/>envelope biosynthesis. This result together with the predator&apos;s auxotrophies suggest the <lb/>adaptation of B. bacteriovorus to a non-free-living lifestyle, where the uptake of metabolites <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>becomes crucial to its survival. Moreover, numerous reactions involved in amino acid <lb/>metabolism are included in the group of free-living organisms, but not in the predator set, likely <lb/>due to the direct incorporation of these metabolites from the prey. <lb/>Analysis of the predator´s lifestyle using condition-specific models: Attack Phase (iCHAP) <lb/>and Growth Phase (iCHGP) models <lb/>B. bacteriovorus possesses a biphasic growth cycle, leading by an extracellular attack phase <lb/>(AP) and an intraperiplasmic growth phase (GP). It has been previously reported that these two <lb/>stages are clearly differentiated in terms of gene expression [49] and also in the biological role <lb/>[20], changes that must be strongly determined by the microenvironment. <lb/>B. bacteriovorus AP cells are exposed to extracellular environment with highly diluted <lb/>concentration of nutrients, but during GP the predator finds a very rich environment inside of <lb/>the prey. As a consequence, it is reasonable to assume that the predator could hardly find <lb/>nutrients during AP, which defines the search, attachment to and invasion of new preys as its <lb/>main biological objective under this scenario. It could be envisaged that, during this period, the <lb/>predator&apos;s metabolism is rerouted to obtaining energy, in terms of ATP, thus allowing flagellum <lb/>movement and facilitating the collision with prey cells thanks to its high velocity [50]. Once the <lb/>predator enters the prey periplasm it uses the cytoplasm as a source of nutrients to initiate GP. <lb/>Bacterial cytoplasm is a very crowded compartment where most of the components of a <lb/>microorganism are localized (30-40% of macromolecules and over 70% of proteins; [51]). Thus, <lb/>the cytoplasm is an extremely rich environment supporting growth and the completion of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus&apos; life cycle [52,53]. Consequently, it is reasonable to hypothesize that the main <lb/>aim of this phase is to grow, which implies a highly active metabolism (catabolism and <lb/>anabolism) supporting fast biomass generation. In fact, recent transcriptomic analyses have <lb/>shown a highly activated anabolism in this phase [49]. <lb/>To obtain a deeper understanding of this predatory bacterium in each phase of its life cycle, we <lb/>constructed two different condition-specific models. Overall, these GP and AP-condition <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>models were constructed by constraining iCH457 in terms of: i) nutrient availability, ii) <lb/>biological objective, and iii) gene expression profile. As a first step, based on the environmental <lb/>conditions, we defined two different in silico media: e.g., minimal and rich medium for AP and <lb/>GP, respectively (Text S1). Secondly, focusing on biological role, we used different biological <lb/>objectives for simulating AP and GP phases. Thus, under AP and GP, ATP production and <lb/>biomass production were selected as differential objective functions, respectively. Finally, in <lb/>order to constrain even more the solution space in each model, data from RNA-seq analyses <lb/>collected during AP and GP [49] were integrated into the metabolic model by using GIM3E <lb/>[54]. GIM3E is an algorithm which minimizes the use of reactions whose encoding gene <lb/>expression levels are under a certain threshold and finds a flux distribution consistent with the <lb/>target function (biomass generation for GP or ATP production for AP). Following this <lb/>workflow, we constructed two new models (iCHAP and iCHGP), mimicking AP and GP growth <lb/>phases, respectively (Fig 2B). <lb/>The number of reactions of each specific-condition model was significantly reduced (from 1001 <lb/>to 810 and 841 in AP and GP, respectively). This significant reduction involves reduced <lb/>solution spaces, and thus likely more accurate predictions. As could be inferred given the <lb/>difference in biological objectives in each phase, the condition-specific models were <lb/>significantly different regarding the specific metabolic content (Fig 2B and Table S7). For <lb/>instance, while we found several reactions only present during AP (67 reactions), including <lb/>reactions involved in glycerophospholipid degradation, the β-oxidation pathway and a large <lb/>number of reactions were only present in GP model (98 reactions) i.e. reactions responsible for <lb/>the biosynthesis of the cell envelope, nucleotides, fatty acids and lipids ( Table S7). In other <lb/>words, we found that while the unique enzymes present during AP were mainly involved in <lb/>energy production and cell survival, during GP the reactions were largely involved in anabolic <lb/>pathways including biosynthesis of biomass building blocks. <lb/>These reaction profiles gave way to the optimal pipeline for system exploration of the resulting <lb/>solution spaces using Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling; [55] thus it was possible to establish <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>potential differences in the metabolic states between AP and GP. Subsequently, we assessed the <lb/>most probable carbon flux distribution between the two condition-specific models to reveal <lb/>integrated information about the predator&apos;s metabolism (Fig 6). Thereby the behavior during AP <lb/>seems to follow a balanced oxidative metabolism aimed at energy production, including intense <lb/>flux across TCA and oxidative phosphorylation. On the contrary, no significant fluxes were <lb/>predicted across anaplerotic and biosynthetic pathways including gluconeogenesis, pentose <lb/>phosphate, and lipid biosynthesis, which suggests negligible participation of these metabolic <lb/>hubs during AP. Interestingly, a completely inverse metabolic scenario was predicted under GP. <lb/>Firstly, this specific model predicted key energetic metabolic pathways being partially inactive <lb/>during GP. For example, it is important to remark an incomplete performance of the TCA cycle <lb/>when several stages, including citrate synthase (CS), aconitase (ACONT), isocitrate <lb/>dehydrogenase (ICDH), and malate dehydrogenase (MDH) were predicted carrying no flux at <lb/>all. Instead, acetyl-CoA derived from amino acid catabolism was mainly funneled to lipid <lb/>biosynthesis. Reduction equivalents powering oxidative phosphorylation were produced, almost <lb/>exclusively, from glutamate metabolism via α-ketoglutarate dehydrogenase and succinate <lb/>dehydrogenase, thus ensuring ATP production. Finally, a very high flux through <lb/>gluconeogenesis from pyruvate was predicted, thus enabling the required building blocks for <lb/>nucleotide and cell envelope biosynthesis in this phase (Fig 6). Interestingly, this scenario <lb/>described for GP is fully compatible with the energy-saving mechanisms suggested for B. <lb/>bacteriovours. Therefore, the reuse of prey-derived biomass building blocks renders the role of <lb/>the TCA cycle as the main source of reducing equivalents powering the production of ATP <lb/>negligible. <lb/>Fig 6. Prediction of the carbon flux distribution in iCH457 metabolic network. Graphical <lb/>representation of the metabolic carbon fluxes during the life cycle of B. bacteriovorus HD100. <lb/>The numbers below each reaction represent the more probable flux in each phase (GP flux/AP <lb/>flux) as determined by Monte Carlo sampling analysis. The thick arrows highlight the carbon <lb/>flux distribution in GP compared with AP. The thin arrows highlight the reactions that are <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>active in AP compared with GP. As the major carbon sources are amino acids, alanine and <lb/>glutamate come directly from the breakdown of the dipeptides or from the single amino acids. <lb/>Eritrose 4 phosphate and glyceraldehyde 3 phosphate come from the degradation pathways of <lb/>serine and threonine. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Integrative approaches combining traditional and innovative technologies are currently being <lb/>addressed to establish the metabolic network of hot-spot microorganisms. This issue becomes <lb/>much more challenging when it refers to predatory microorganisms such as the bacterium B. <lb/>bacteriovorus, which exhibit a bi-phasic lifestyle. With the aim of elucidating the metabolic <lb/>network wired to predator physiology and lifestyle, we implemented a computational test-bed <lb/>that proved very useful in the assessment of our predator&apos;s phenotype-genotype relationships, <lb/>while providing new insight on how B. bacteriovorus&apos; metabolism operates at the systems level. <lb/>Complex B. bacteriovorus lifestyle has guided a significant genome streamlining process <lb/>and the acquisition of biosynthetic energy-saving mechanisms. <lb/>Comparison of the essential reactions between B. bacteriovorus and other intracellular lifecycle <lb/>bacteria and free-living microorganisms has revealed the loss of biosynthetic pathways (Table <lb/>S6, reactions exclusive to free-living microorganisms). This metabolic scenario is only possible <lb/>because the host/prey metabolic machinery provides the required biomass building blocks <lb/>during the intracellular stage of the growth cycle. Despite numerous auxotrophies having been <lb/>reported in specific genes [6], the metabolic model has allowed the functional contextualization <lb/>of these biosynthetic deficiencies within the network. For instance, model-based analyses <lb/>identified additional metabolic gaps which had remained unknown so far, while on the other <lb/>hand they provided alternative metabolic routes overcoming theoretical auxotrophies. Overall, <lb/>our analysis has shown a significantly higher number of auxotrophies than previously thought. <lb/>The loss of essential biosynthetic genes is a typical characteristic of bacteria existing in nutrient-<lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>rich environments, such as lactic acid bacteria, endosymbionts or pathogens [56]. In this sense, <lb/>although B. bacteriovorus HD100 possesses a relatively large genome, it could also be included <lb/>in this &quot;genome streamlining&quot; bacterial group because it directly employs whole molecules <lb/>from the cytoplasm of the prey [53,57,58]. With regard to the production of the biomass <lb/>building blocks, it is noteworthy that most amino acids suffer a total lack of biosynthesis <lb/>pathways. In contrast, B. bacteriovorus is fully equipped with the biosynthetic routes for <lb/>nucleotides and fatty acids. Keeping in mind the macromolecular composition of a prokaryotic <lb/>cell&apos;s cytoplasm as the natural growth niche of B. bacteriovorus (50 % proteins, 20 % RNA, 10 <lb/>% lipids, 20 % remaining components), it is easy to speculate why the oligopeptide transporter <lb/>systems are widely represented. While the factors driving de novo synthesis or the uptake of <lb/>biomass building blocks are still unknown, it is likely that these processes are extremely <lb/>regulated and only activated in the absence of intermediates. A significant flux feeding nucleic <lb/>acid biosynthesis was predicted (Fig 6). Thus, an important amount of nucleotides came from de <lb/>novo synthesis pathways. This would occur during in vivo conditions even in the presence of <lb/>nucleotides in the extracellular medium (prey´s cytoplasm). This high requirement of <lb/>nucleotides beyond the amount provided by the prey could justify the presence of a complete <lb/>nucleotide biosynthesis pathway in contrast with the scenario found in the biosynthesis of amino <lb/>acids and cofactors when multiple autotrophies were found. <lb/>In addition, the presence of these complete metabolic pathways determines the potential ability <lb/>of the predator to survive and grow without prey, as predicted by the model. Supplying the <lb/>model with a rich medium based on amino acids returned a simulation which provided key <lb/>information about growth and generation of biomass. Importantly, this potentially independent <lb/>growth might be associated with B. bacteriovorus&apos; role as a balancer of bacterial population <lb/>either in aquatic or soil environments, or in the intestine of healthy individuals, because survival <lb/>of predator cells is not uniquely dependent on the predation event [48]. <lb/>On the whole, our data support the hypothesis and suggest that the metabolic properties of B. <lb/>bacteriovorus are closer to those of the postulated minimal metabolic network. This low <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>robustness of the metabolic network suggests Bdellovibrio is more niche-specific than <lb/> previously thought and the environmental conditions governing predation may be relatively <lb/>uniform. However, in-depth studies of the metabolic capabilities of the predator are needed to <lb/>complete the metabolic network and obtain more reliable in silico predictions. <lb/>Nutrient availability and biological objective largely conditioned the metabolic shift from <lb/>iCHAP to iCHGP <lb/>The development of iCH457, iCHAP and iCHGP has provided a computational framework for a <lb/>better understanding of the physiological and metabolic versatility of BALOs and other <lb/>predatory bacteria. In addition, it has allowed the computational demonstration, in terms of flux <lb/>distribution, of the metabolic shift between the different phases. Through detailed analysis of <lb/>these specific-condition models it has been possible to conclude that during AP, B. <lb/>bacteriovorus invests most of its resources in ATP generation, presumably in order to fuel the <lb/>flagellum to search for new prey. In contrast, GP was characterized by the biosynthesis of <lb/>biomass building blocks. During this phase, several metabolic pathways become inactive, <lb/>allowing carbon flux distribution re-routing toward biosynthetic pathways. For instance, the <lb/>TCA cycle shifts from a completely operational state to an anaplerotic mode by inactivating the <lb/>decarboxilative branch including citrate synthase, aconitase and isocitrate dehydrogenase. In <lb/>parallel, glutamate was used as a main carbon and energy source. The metabolic switch in B. <lb/>bacteriovorus between the different growth phases has revealed an environmental adaptation of <lb/>this predator to tackle a rich medium, which would provide an explanation for the development <lb/>of HI strains. Overall, the carbon flux predictions were compatible with the complex lifestyle of <lb/>Bdellovibrio cells and provided an unprecedented overview of the metabolic shifting required to <lb/>move from AP to GP, as well as new knowledge about the connections within the predator&apos;s <lb/>metabolic network. <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body>Finally, the results obtained during this study contribute not only to increasing the available <lb/>metabolic knowledge of B. bacteriovorus, but also to providing a computational platform for the <lb/>full exploitation of this predator bacterium as a biotechnology workhorse in the near future. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Genome-scale metabolic network reconstruction: iCH457 <lb/>The genome-scale metabolic model of B. bacterivorous HD100 (iCH457) was constructed using <lb/>standardized protocols for metabolic reconstruction [22,59], and is detailed in Fig 2A. An initial <lb/>draft reconstruction was generated from the annotated genome of B. bacteriovorus HD100 <lb/>(GenBank number: BX842601.2) using the automatic application provided by Model Seed <lb/>server [60]. Additionally, the metabolic content of B. bacteriovorus was mapped with two <lb/>broadly used and high-quality GEMs belonging to E. coli (iJO1366; [61]) and P. putida <lb/>(iJN1411; [46]), generating additional drafts by using MrBac Server [62]. Once these models <lb/>were unified into a final reconstruction, we proceeded to a thorough manual curation of the <lb/>collected metabolic information. During this iterative process, the final inclusion of each <lb/>individual&apos;s biochemical reaction was assessed using genomic [6], metabolic, transporter and <lb/>GEMs databases, including: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG, [63]), <lb/>BRENDA [64], BIGG [65]. Transport reactions were also added by using the TransportDB <lb/>[66] database. Relevant reactions added during this process were listed in Supplementary Tables <lb/>(Added reactions I and II). Finally, we performed a manual gap filling step in order to connect <lb/>the network as much as possible and remove potential inconsistencies. B. bacteriovorus legacy <lb/>literature has been thoroughly consulted, ensuring high confidence in the metabolic content <lb/>included. When specific data for the HD100 strain were not available, information from <lb/>phylogenetically related organisms such as 109 Davis strain was used as previously suggested <lb/>[59]. The metabolites and reactions included in this metabolic model are listed in Tables S1 and <lb/>S2. <lb/>Model Analysis: Flux Balance Analysis (FBA) <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body>FBA is by far the most popular approach for analyzing constraint-based models and it is used in <lb/>many applications of GEMs. FBA uses optimization of an objective function to find a subset of <lb/>optimal states in the large solution space of possible states that is shaped by the mass balance <lb/>and capacity constraints. In FBA, the solution space is constrained by the statement of a steady-<lb/>state, under which each internal metabolite is consumed at the same rate as it is produced [45]. <lb/>The conversion into a mathematical format can be done automatically by parsing the <lb/>stoichiometric coefficients from the network reaction list e.g. using the COBRA toolbox [55]. <lb/>The dimensions of the stoichiometric matrix, S, are m by n, where m is the number of <lb/>metabolites in the reaction network and n is the number of reactions. Therefore, each column <lb/>represents a reaction and each row represents the stoichiometric participation of a specific <lb/>metabolite in each of the reactions. FBA was used to predict growth and flux distributions. FBA <lb/>is based on solving a linear optimization problem by maximizing or minimizing a given <lb/>objective function to a set of constraints. The foundations and applications of FBA have been <lb/>reviewed elsewhere [67,68]. A particular flux distribution of the network, v, indicates the flux <lb/>levels through each of the reactions. Based on the principle of conservation of mass and the <lb/>assumption of a steady state, the flux distribution through a reaction network can be <lb/>characterized by the following equation: S x v = 0 [45,69]. Constraints are placed on individual <lb/>reactions to establish the upper and lower bounds on the range of flux values that each of the <lb/>reactions can have. These constraints are described as follows: α 1 ≤v 1 ≤β 1 , where α1 is the lower <lb/>bound on flux v1, and β1 is the upper bound. If no information about flux levels is available, the <lb/>value of α 1 is set to zero for irreversible fluxes. In all other cases, α 1 and β 1 are left <lb/>unconstrained, thus allowing the flux to take on any value, whether positive or negative. <lb/>Biomass function <lb/>It is commonly assumed that the objective of living organisms is to divide and proliferate. Thus, <lb/>many metabolic network reconstructions have a so-called biomass function, in which all known <lb/>metabolic precursors of cellular biomass are grouped (e.g. amino acids, nucleotides, <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<body>phospholipids, vitamins, cofactors, energetic requirements, etc.). Since no detailed studies about <lb/>B. bacteriovorus biomass composition are available, the biomass composition from P. putida <lb/>[46] was used as a template for the biomass function of iCH457. However, data from B. <lb/>bacteriovorus were added when available (e.g. nucleotide composition -from genome <lb/>sequence). The detailed calculation of biomass composition is provided in Table S3. <lb/>Generation of growth phase-specific models: iCHAP and iCHGP <lb/>A given metabolic reconstruction is defined by the metabolic content contained in the genome <lb/>and thus is unique for the target organism. However, it is possible to construct different <lb/>condition-specific models by applying additional constraints such as condition-specific data <lb/>(including physiological), gen/protein expression and flux data, etc. <lb/>To construct condition-specific metabolic models we incorporated these additional constraints <lb/>to the model by means of a stepwise procedure including condition specific: i) biomass, ii) <lb/>nutrient availability and iii) gene expression data (Fig 2B). Firstly, the objective function was <lb/>adjusted to the biological role of AP and GP. ATP maintenance and biomass equations were <lb/>selected as objective functions for AP and GP, respectively. In addition, different in silico media <lb/>were designed for each phase, simulating the availability of nutrients in each growth phase (S1 <lb/>Text). Finally, available AP and GP gene expression datasets [49] were incorporated in order to <lb/>constrain even further the solution space us GIM3E [70]. GIM3E builds reduced models by <lb/>removing the reactions not available in the expression dataset while preserving model <lb/>functionality. It should be noted that GIM3E considers which genes are expressed or not, but <lb/>not the modifications in mRNA levels under different experimental conditions. A given gene <lb/>was considered expressed when its RNA levels in the RNA-seq analysis fell within the first <lb/>quartile, which is ≥ 10 RPKM using the available dataset [49]. <lb/>The distribution of possible fluxes in the specific-condition models was calculated using <lb/>Markov chain Monte Carlo sampling [55]. The median value from the distribution was used as <lb/>the reference flux value. <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Reactions essentiality analysis <lb/>In order to determine the effect of a single reaction deletion, all the reactions associated with <lb/>each gene in iCH457 were individually suppressed from the matrix S. FBA was used to predict <lb/>the mutation growth phenotype. The singleReactionDeletion function implemented in the <lb/>COBRA Toolbox [55] was used to simulate knockouts. A lethal deletion was defined as that <lb/>yielding &lt; 10% of the original model&apos;s growth rate values. The simulations for reaction <lb/>essentiality were performed using the rich in silico medium for iCH457 (Supporting <lb/>information). Reaction essentiality analysis has been performed for other bacteria: P. putida <lb/>KT2440 (iJN1411) [46], E. coli strain K-12 substrain MG1655 (iJO1366) [71], Geobacter <lb/>metallireducens GS-15 (iAF987) [72], Yersinia pestis CO92 (iPC815) [73], Salmonella enterica <lb/>subsp. enterica serovar Typhimurium str. LT2 (STM_v1_0 model) [65] and Shigella flexneri <lb/>(iSF1195) [65]. <lb/>The associations between essential reactions and each bacterium were represented building a <lb/>bipartite network. For visualization we use Gephi software (0.9.2). These essential reactions and <lb/>the bacterial models were clustered in a heatmap using the pheatmap (v. 1.0.12) package within <lb/>the R environment (http://www.R-project.org). <lb/>Software <lb/>The iCH457 model was analyzed with the COBRA Toolbox v2.0 within the MATLAB <lb/>environment (The MathWorks Inc.) [74]. Tomlab CPLEX and the GNU Linear Programming <lb/>Kit (http://www.gnu.org/software/glpk) were used for solving the linear programing problems. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTION: <lb/>M.A.P. and J.N. designed research. C.H. and J.N. performed the reconstruction. C.H. <lb/>performed the analysis. C.H, M.A.P and J.N analyzed data. C.H and J.N drafted the paper. All <lb/>the authors contributed to the final version. <lb/></div>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>This work was supported in part by the Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness <lb/>through funding provided to project BIO2014-59528-JIN, BIO2013-44878-R, Engicoin 760994 <lb/>and BIO2017-83448-R. <lb/>The authors thank Clive A. Dove for critical reading of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. <lb/>Thompson JN. The evolution of species interactions. Science. 1999;284: 2116-8. <lb/>doi:10.1126/science.284.5423.2116 <lb/>2. <lb/>Clarholm M. Microbes as predators or prey. Current perspectives on microbial ecology. <lb/>1984. <lb/>3. <lb/>Stolp H, Starr MP. Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus gen. etsp. n., a predatory, ectoparasitic, <lb/>and bacteriolytic microorganism. Antonie Van Leeuwenhoek. 1963;29: 217-248. <lb/>4. <lb/>Jurkevitch E, Davidov Y. Phylogenetic Diversity and Evolution of Predatory <lb/> Prokaryotes. ACS Division of Fuel Chemistry, Preprints. 2006. doi:10.1007/7171 <lb/>5. <lb/>Caballero JDD, Vida R, Cobo M, Máiz L, Suárez L, Galeano J, et al. Individual Patterns <lb/>of Complexity in Including Predator Bacteria , over a 1-Year Period. 2017;8: e00959-17. <lb/>doi:10.1128/mBio.00959-17 <lb/>6. <lb/>Rendulic S, Jagtap P, Rosinus A, Eppinger M, Baar C, Lanz C, et al. A predator <lb/>unmasked: life cycle of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus from a genomic perspective. Science. <lb/>2004;303: 689-92. doi:10.1126/science.1093027 <lb/>7. <lb/>Hobley L, Lerner TR, Williams LE, Lambert C, Till R, Milner DS, et al. Genome <lb/>analysis of a simultaneously predatory and prey-independent, novel Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>from the River Tiber, supports in silico predictions of both ancient and recent lateral gene <lb/>transfer from diverse bacteria. BMC Genomics. 2012;13: 670. doi:10.1186/1471-2164-13-670 <lb/>8. <lb/>Wurtzel O, Dori-Bachash M, Pietrokovski S, Jurkevitch E, Sorek R, Ben-Jacob E. <lb/>Mutation Detection with Next-Generation Resequencing through a Mediator Genome. PLoS <lb/>One. 2010;5. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0015628 <lb/>9. <lb/>Sockett RE. Predatory lifestyle of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. Annu Rev Microbiol. <lb/>2009;63: 523-39. doi:10.1146/annurev.micro.091208.073346 <lb/>10. <lb/>MARTA, EKSZTEJN, and, MAZAL, VARON. Elongation and Cell Division in <lb/>Bdellovibrio <lb/>bacteriovorus. <lb/>arch <lb/>micorbiol. <lb/>1977;144: <lb/>175-181. <lb/>doi:https://doi.org/10.1007/BF00410781 <lb/>11. <lb/>Capeness MJ, Lambert C, Lovering AL, Till R, Uchida K, Chaudhuri R, et al. Activity <lb/>of Bdellovibrio Hit Locus Proteins, Bd0108 and Bd0109, Links Type IVa Pilus <lb/>Extrusion/Retraction <lb/>Status <lb/>to <lb/>Prey-Independent <lb/>Growth <lb/>Signalling. <lb/>2013; <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0079759 <lb/>12. <lb/>Scherff RH. Control of bacterial blight of soybean by Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. <lb/>Phytopathology. 1973;63: 400-402. <lb/>13. <lb/>Loozen G, Boon N, Pauwels M, Slomka V, Rodrigues Herrero E, Quirynen M, et al. <lb/>Effect of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus HD100 on multispecies oral communities. Anaerobe. <lb/>Elsevier Ltd; 2015;35: 45-53. doi:10.1016/j.anaerobe.2014.09.011 <lb/>14. <lb/>Atterbury RJ, Hobley L, Till R, Lambert C, Capeness MJ, Lerner TR, et al. Effects of <lb/>orally administered Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus on the well-being and Salmonella colonization <lb/>of young chicks. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2011;77: 5794-5803. doi:10.1128/AEM.00426-11 <lb/>15. <lb/>Cao H, He S, Wang H, Hou S, Lu L, Yang X. Bdellovibrios, potential biocontrol <lb/>bacteria against pathogenic Aeromonas hydrophila. Vet Microbiol. Elsevier B.V.; 2012;154: <lb/>413-418. doi:10.1016/j.vetmic.2011.07.032 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>16. <lb/>Martínez V, de la Peña F, García-Hidalgo J, de la Mata I, García JL, Prieto MA. <lb/>Identification and biochemical evidence of a medium-chain-length polyhydroxyalkanoate <lb/>depolymerase in the Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus predatory hydrolytic arsenal. Appl Environ <lb/>Microbiol. 2012;78: 6017-26. doi:10.1128/AEM.01099-12 <lb/>17. <lb/>Martínez V, Herencias C, Jurkevitch E, Auxiliadora Prieto M. Engineering a predatory <lb/>bacterium as a proficient killer agent for intracellular bio-products recovery: The case of the <lb/>polyhydroxyalkanoates. Nat Publ Gr. 2016; doi:10.1038/srep24381 <lb/>18. <lb/>Margulis L. Archaeal-eubacterial mergers in the origin of Eukarya: phylogenetic <lb/>classification of life. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 1996;93: 1071-1076. <lb/>doi:10.1073/pnas.93.3.1071 <lb/>19. <lb/>Jurkevitch E. Predatory Behaviors in Bacteria-Diversity and Transitions. Microbe. <lb/>2007;2: 67-73. doi:10.1128/microbe.2.67.1 <lb/>20. <lb/>Lambert C, Hobley L, Chang C-Y, Fenton A, Capeness M, Sockett L. A predatory <lb/>patchwork: membrane and surface structures of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. [Internet]. <lb/>Advances in microbial physiology. 2009. doi:10.1016/S0065-2911(08)00005-2 <lb/>21. <lb/>Bordbar A, Monk JM, King ZA, Palsson BO. Constraint-based models predict <lb/>metabolic and associated cellular functions. Nat Rev Genet. 2014;15: 107-120. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nrg3643 <lb/>22. <lb/>Monk J, Nogales J, Palsson BO. Optimizing genome-scale network reconstructions. <lb/>Nature Biotechnology. 2014. doi:10.1038/nbt.2870 <lb/>23. <lb/>O &apos;brien EJ, Monk JM, Palsson BO. Using Genome-Scale Models to Predict Biological <lb/>Capabilities. Cell. 2015;161: 971-987. doi:10.1016/j.cell.2015.05.019 <lb/>24. <lb/>Nielsen J. Systems Biology of Metabolism. Annu Rev Biochem. 2017;86: 245-275. <lb/>doi:10.1146/annurev-biochem-061516-044757 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>25. <lb/>Heirendt L, Arreckx S, Pfau T, Mendoza SN, Richelle A, Heinken A, et al. Creation and <lb/>analysis of biochemical constraint-based models: the COBRA Toolbox v3.0. Nat Protoc. <lb/>2018;2: 1290-1307. doi:10.1038/nprot.2007.99 <lb/>26. <lb/>Lewis NE, Nagarajan H, Palsson BO. Constraining the metabolic genotype-phenotype <lb/>relationship using a phylogeny of in silico methods. Nat Rev Microbiol. Nature Publishing <lb/>Group; 2012;10: 291-305. doi:10.1038/nrmicro2737 <lb/>27. <lb/>Nguyen N-AT, Sallans L, Kaneshiro ES. The major glycerophospholipids of the <lb/>predatory and parasitic bacterium Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus HID5. Lipids. 2008;43: 1053-63. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s11745-008-3235-9 <lb/>28. <lb/>Müller FD, Beck S, Strauch E, Linscheid MW. Bacterial predators possess unique <lb/>membrane lipid structures. Lipids. 2011;46: 1129-40. doi:10.1007/s11745-011-3614-5 <lb/>29. <lb/>Lerner TR, Lovering AL, Bui NK, Uchida K, Aizawa SI, Vollmer W, et al. Specialized <lb/>peptidoglycan hydrolases sculpt the intra-bacterial niche of predatory Bdellovibrio and increase <lb/>population fitness. PLoS Pathog. 2012;8. doi:10.1371/journal.ppat.1002524 <lb/>30. <lb/>Oberhardt MA, Palsson BØ, Papin JA. Applications of genome-scale metabolic <lb/>reconstructions. Mol Syst Biol. 2009;5. doi:10.1038/msb.2009.77 <lb/>31. <lb/>Sun J, Sayyar B, Butler JE, Pharkya P, Fahland TR, Famili I, et al. Genome-scale <lb/>constraint-based modeling of Geobacter metallireducens. BMC Syst Biol. BioMed Central; <lb/>2009;3: 15. doi:10.1186/1752-0509-3-15 <lb/>32. <lb/>Stolyar S, Van Dien S, Hillesland KL, Pinel N, Lie TJ, Leigh JA, et al. Metabolic <lb/>modeling of a mutualistic microbial community. Mol Syst Biol. 2007;3: 92. <lb/>doi:10.1038/msb4100131 <lb/>33. <lb/>Flowers JJ, Richards MA, Baliga N, Meyer B, Stahl DA. Constraint-based modelling <lb/>captures the metabolic versatility of Desulfovibrio vulgaris. Environ Microbiol Rep. 2018;10: <lb/>190-201. doi:10.1111/1758-2229.12619 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>34. <lb/>Hespell RB, Miozzari GF, Rittenberg SC. Ribonucleic acid destruction and synthesis <lb/>during intraperiplasmic growth of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. J Bacteriol. 1975;123: 481-91. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=235752&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>35. <lb/>Ruby EG, McCabe JB, Barke JI. Uptake of intact nucleoside monophosphates by <lb/>Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus 109J. J Bacteriol. 1985;163: 1087-94. Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=219242&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>36. <lb/>Matin a, Rittenberg SC. Kinetics of deoxyribonucleic acid destruction and synthesis <lb/>during growth of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus strain 109D on pseudomonas putida and <lb/>escherichia <lb/>coli. <lb/>J <lb/>Bacteriol. <lb/>1972;111: <lb/>664-73. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=251338&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>37. <lb/>Kuenen JG, Rittenberg SC. Incorporation of long-chain fatty acids of the substrate <lb/>organism by Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus during intraperiplasmic growth. J Bacteriol. 1975;121: <lb/>1145-57. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=246047&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>38. <lb/>Barabote RD, Rendulic S, Schuster SC, Saier MH. Comprehensive analysis of transport <lb/>proteins encoded within the genome of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. Genomics. 2007;90: 424-<lb/>46. doi:10.1016/j.ygeno.2007.06.002 <lb/>39. <lb/>Hespell RB, Rosson R a, Thomashow MF, Rittenberg SC. Respiration of Bdellovibrio <lb/>bacteriovorus strain 109J and its energy substrates for intraperiplasmic growth. J Bacteriol. <lb/>1973;113: <lb/>1280-8. <lb/>Available: <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=251695&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>40. <lb/>Seidler RJ, Starr M. Isolation and Characterization of Host-Independent Bdellovibrios. J <lb/>Bacteriol. <lb/>1969;100: <lb/>769-785. <lb/>Available: <lb/>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC250157/pdf/jbacter00385-0249.pdf <lb/>41. <lb/>Cotter TW, Thomashow MF. Identification of a Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus genetic <lb/>locus, hit, associated with the host-independent phenotype. J Bacteriol. 1992;174: 6018-24. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=207666&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>42. <lb/>Roschanski N, Klages S, Reinhardt R, Linscheid M, Strauch E. Identification of genes <lb/>essential for prey-independent growth of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus HD100. J Bacteriol. <lb/>2011;193: 1745-1756. doi:10.1128/JB.01343-10 <lb/>43. <lb/>Ishiguro EE. Minimum nutritional requirements for growth of host-independent <lb/>derivatives of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus strain 109 Davis. Can J Microbiol. 1974;20: 263-265. <lb/>doi:10.1139/m74-041 <lb/>44. <lb/>Fong SS, Joyce AR, Palsson BØ. Parallel adaptive evolution cultures of Escherichia coli <lb/>lead to convergent growth phenotypes with different gene expression states. Genome Res. <lb/>2005;15: <lb/>1365-1372. <lb/>Available: <lb/>https://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/pmc/articles/PMC1240078/pdf/00151365.pdf <lb/>45. <lb/>Orth JD. What is flux balance analysis? Nat Biotechnol. 2010;28: 245-248. <lb/>doi:doi:10.1038/nbt.1614 <lb/>46. <lb/>Nogales J, Gudmundsson S, Duque E, Luis Ramos J, Putida P. Expanding the <lb/>computable reactome in Pseudomonas putida reveals metabolic cycles providing robustness. 2 3 <lb/>Running Head: Metabolic Robustness Cycles in. BioRxiv. 2017;May. doi:10.1101/139121 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>47. <lb/>Seidler RJ, Starr MP, Mandel M. Deoxyribonucleic acid characterization of <lb/>Bdellovibrios. <lb/>J <lb/>Bacteriol. <lb/>1969;100: <lb/>786-90. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=250158&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>48. <lb/>Dwidar M, Im H, Seo JK, Mitchell RJ. Attack-Phase Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus <lb/>Responses to Extracellular Nutrients Are Analogous to Those Seen During Late <lb/>Intraperiplasmic Growth. Microb Ecol. 2017; doi:10.1007/s00248-017-1003-1 <lb/>49. <lb/>Karunker I, Rotem O, Dori-Bachash M, Jurkevitch E, Sorek R. A Global <lb/>Transcriptional Switch between the Attack and Growth Forms of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. <lb/>PLoS One. 2013;8: e61850. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0061850 <lb/>50. <lb/>Erkin Kuru, 1 7, Carey Lambert, 2, Jonathan Rittichier, 3 7, et al. Fluorescent D -amino-<lb/> acids reveal bi-cellular cell wall modifications important for Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus <lb/>predation. Nat Microbiol. 2017; doi:doi: 10.1038/s41564-017-0029-y <lb/>51. <lb/>Zimmerman SB, Trach S 0. Estimation of Macromolecule Concentrations and Excluded <lb/>Volume Effects for the Cytoplasm of Escherichia coli. J Mol Bid. 1991;222: 599-620. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://ac.els-cdn.com/002228369190499V/1-s2.0-002228369190499V-<lb/>main.pdf?_tid=fe412f06-55c4-11e7-8e6b-<lb/>00000aab0f27&amp;acdnat=1497969202_40de091c7e85b960895c477a2b0bfa60 <lb/>52. <lb/>Zhang Y-HP. Substrate channeling and enzyme complexes for biotechnological <lb/>applications. Biotechnol Adv. 2011;29: 715-725. doi:10.1016/j.biotechadv.2011.05.020 <lb/>53. <lb/>Vendeville A s, Lariviere D, Fourmentin E. An inventory of the bacterial <lb/>macromolecular components and their spatial organization `. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2011;35: <lb/>395-414. doi:10.1111/j.1574-6976.2010.00254.x <lb/>54. <lb/>Becker SA, Palsson BO. Context-specific metabolic networks are consistent with <lb/>experiments. PLoS Comput Biol. 2008;4. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000082 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>55. <lb/>Schellenberger J, Que R, Fleming RMT, Thiele I, Orth JD, Feist AM, et al. Quantitative <lb/>prediction of cellular metabolism with constraint-based models: The COBRA Toolbox v2.0. Nat <lb/>Protoc. 2011;6: 1290-1307. doi:10.1038/nprot.2011.308 <lb/>56. <lb/>D&apos;Souza G, Waschina S, Pande S, Bohl K, Kaleta C, Kost C. LESS IS MORE: <lb/>SELECTIVE ADVANTAGES CAN EXPLAIN THE PREVALENT LOSS OF <lb/>BIOSYNTHETIC GENES IN BACTERIA. Evolution (N Y). 2014;68: 2559-2570. <lb/>doi:doi:10.1111/evo.12468 <lb/>57. <lb/>Rittenberg SC, Langley D. Utilization of nucleoside monophosphates per Se for <lb/>intraperiplasmic growth of Bdellovibrio bacteriovorus. J Bacteriol. 1975;121: 1137-44. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://www.pubmedcentral.nih.gov/articlerender.fcgi?artid=246046&amp;tool=pmcentrez&amp;renderty <lb/>pe=abstract <lb/>58. <lb/>Golding I, Cox EC. Physical nature of bacterial cytoplasm. Phys Rev Lett. 2006;96: 14-<lb/>17. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.96.098102 <lb/>59. <lb/>Thiele I, Palsson B. A protocol for generating a high-quality genome-scale metabolic <lb/>reconstruction. Nat Protoc. 2010;5: 93-121. doi:10.1038/nprot.2009.203.A <lb/>60. <lb/>Aziz RK, Devoid S, Disz T, Edwards RA, Henry CS, Olsen GJ, et al. SEED Servers: <lb/>High-Performance Access to the SEED Genomes, Annotations, and Metabolic Models. PLoS <lb/>One. 2012;7: 1-10. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0048053 <lb/>61. <lb/>Feist AM, Henry CS, Reed JL, Krummenacker M, Joyce AR, Karp PD, et al. A <lb/>genome-scale metabolic reconstruction for Escherichia coli K-12 MG1655 that accounts for <lb/>1260 ORFs and thermodynamic information. Mol Syst Biol. 2007;3: 121. <lb/>doi:10.1038/msb4100155 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>62. <lb/>Liao YC, Huang TW, Chen FC, Charusanti P, Hong JSJ, Chang HY, et al. An <lb/>experimentally validated genome-scale metabolic reconstruction of Klebsiella pneumoniae <lb/>MGH 78578, iYL1228. J Bacteriol. 2011;193: 1710-1717. doi:10.1128/JB.01218-10 <lb/>63. <lb/>Ogata H, Goto S, Sato K, Fujibuchi W, Bono H, Kanehisa M. KEGG: Kyoto <lb/>encyclopedia of genes and genomes. Nucleic Acids Res. 1999;27: 29-34. <lb/>doi:10.1093/nar/27.1.29 <lb/>64. <lb/>Placzek S, Schomburg I, Chang A, Jeske L, Ulbrich M, Tillack J, et al. BRENDA in <lb/>2017: New perspectives and new tools in BRENDA. Nucleic Acids Res. 2017;45: D380-D388. <lb/>doi:10.1093/nar/gkw952 <lb/>65. <lb/>King ZA, Lu J, Dräger A, Miller P, Federowicz S, Lerman JA, et al. BiGG Models: A <lb/>platform for integrating, standardizing and sharing genome-scale models. Nucleic Acids Res. <lb/>2016;44: D515-D522. doi:10.1093/nar/gkv1049 <lb/>66. <lb/>Elbourne LDH, Tetu SG, Hassan KA, Paulsen IT. TransportDB 2.0: A database for <lb/>exploring membrane transporters in sequenced genomes from all domains of life. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Res. 2017;45: D320-D324. doi:10.1093/nar/gkw1068 <lb/>67. <lb/>Bonarius HPJ, Schmid G, Tramper J. Flux analysis of underdetermined metabolic <lb/>networks: The quest for the missing constraints. Trends Biotechnol. 1997;15: 308-314. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0167-7799(97)01067-6 <lb/>68. <lb/>Varma A, Palsson B 0. Stoichiometric Flux Balance Models Quantitatively Predict <lb/>Growth and Metabolic By-Product Secretion in Wild-Type Escherichia coli W3110. Appl <lb/>Environ <lb/>Microbiol. <lb/>1994; <lb/>3724-3731. <lb/>Available: <lb/>http://cepac.cheme.cmu.edu/pasilectures/costas/varma-palsson94.pdf <lb/>69. <lb/>Varma A, Palsson B. Metabolic Capabilities of Escherichia coli: I. Synthesis of <lb/>biosynthetic precursors and cofactors. J ournal Theor Biol. 1993;165: 477-502. Available: <lb/>https://ac.els-cdn.com/S0022519383712026/1-s2.0-S0022519383712026-<lb/></listBibl>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>main.pdf?_tid=f7a7d5dc-6338-4d72-9aa4-<lb/>58e94bb72d4a&amp;acdnat=1521540528_c1a58e5d5350a4be70af328083507e3f <lb/>70. <lb/>Nogales J, Agudo L. A Practical Protocol for Integration of Transcriptomics Data into <lb/>Genome-Scale Metabolic Reconstructions. Hydrocarb Lipid Microbiol Protoc -Springer Protoc <lb/>Handbooks. 2015; 135-152. doi:10.1007/8623 <lb/>71. <lb/>Orth JD, Conrad TM, Na J, Lerman JA, Nam H, Feist AM, et al. A comprehensive <lb/>genome-scale reconstruction of Escherichia coli metabolism-2011. Mol Syst Biol. 2011;7: <lb/>535. doi:10.1038/msb.2011.65 <lb/>72. <lb/>Feist AM, Nagarajan H, Rotaru AE, Tremblay PL, Zhang T, Nevin KP, et al. <lb/>Constraint-Based Modeling of Carbon Fixation and the Energetics of Electron Transfer in <lb/>Geobacter <lb/>metallireducens. <lb/>PLoS <lb/>Comput <lb/>Biol. <lb/>2014;10: <lb/>1-10. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1003575 <lb/>73. <lb/>Charusanti P, Chauhan S, McAteer K, Lerman JA, Hyduke DR, Motin VL, et al. An <lb/>experimentally-supported genome-scale metabolic network reconstruction for Yersinia pestis <lb/>CO92. BMC Syst Biol. BioMed Central Ltd; 2011;5: 163. doi:10.1186/1752-0509-5-163 <lb/>74. <lb/>Hyduke D, Schellenberger J, Que R, Fleming R, Thiele I, Orth J, et al. PROTOCOL <lb/>EXCHANGE | COMMUNITY CONTRIBUTED COBRA Toolbox 2 . 0. Protoc Exch. 2011; 1-<lb/>30. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
