<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/> 1. GENERAL INFORMATION <lb/>Article Type: Research Paper <lb/>Title: High evolutionary potential in the chemical defenses of an aposematic Heliconius butterfly <lb/>Authors: Mattila, Anniina L. K. 1 ; Jiggins, Chris D. 2 ; Opedal, Øystein H. 1,3 ; Montejo-Kovacevich, Gabriela 2 ; <lb/>de Castro, Érika 2 ; McMillan, William O. 4 ; Bacquet, Caroline 5 ; Saastamoinen, Marjo 1,6 <lb/>Author affiliations: <lb/>1. Research Centre for Ecological Change, Organismal and Evolutionary Biology Research Programme, <lb/>University of Helsinki, Finland <lb/>2. Department of Zoology, University of Cambridge, UK <lb/>3. Department of Biology, Lund University, Sweden <lb/>4. Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute, Panama <lb/>5. Universidad Regional Amazónica de Ikiam, Tena, Ecuador <lb/>6. Helsinki Life Science Institute, University of Helsinki, Finland <lb/>Orcid ID: <lb/>Anniina L. K. Mattila: 0000-0002-6546-6528 <lb/>Chris D. Jiggins: 0000-0002-7809-062X <lb/>Øystein H. Opedal: 0000-0002-7841-6933 <lb/>Gabriela Montejo-Kovacevich: 0000-0003-3716-9929 <lb/>Érika de Castro: 0000-0002-4731-3835 <lb/>William O. McMillan: 0000-0003-2805-2745 <lb/>Caroline Bacquet: 0000-0002-1954-1806 <lb/>Marjo Saastamoinen: 0000-0001-7009-2527 <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>chemical defense -aposematism -mimicry -Heliconius -cyanogenic glucosides -evolvability <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<front>2. ABSTRACT <lb/>Chemical defences against predators underlie the evolution of aposematic coloration and mimicry, which <lb/>represent classic examples of adaptive evolution. Yet, unlike color patterns, little is known about the <lb/>evolutionary potential of chemical defences. Neotropical Heliconius butterflies exhibit incredibly diverse <lb/>warning color patterns and widespread mimicry. Their larvae feed exclusively on cyanogenic Passiflora vines, <lb/>can metabolize and sequester host plant toxins, as well as biosynthesize defensive cyanogenic toxins <lb/>themselves. Here, we investigate variation in biosynthesized toxicity both in wild populations along <lb/>environmental gradients and in common-garden broods and feeding treatments in Heliconius erato, together <lb/>demonstrating considerable intraspecific variation and evolutionary potential in this important chemical <lb/>defense trait. Toxicity varied markedly among wild populations from Central and South America. Within wild <lb/>populations, the distribution of toxicity was consistently skewed, indicative of automimic &quot;cheaters&quot; that may <lb/>exploit, and consequently deplete, the protection of the warning coloration. In a common-garden rearing design <lb/>comprising more than 300 butterflies across 20 broods, variation in host-plant nutritional quality or cyanogen <lb/>levels did not translate into differences in toxicity of butterflies feeding on these plants. Instead, toxicity had a <lb/>significant heritable genetic component, in part explained by maternal inheritance. The evolvability of toxicity <lb/>was high (eµ=1.55%), suggesting that toxicity can evolve rapidly. Through its link with the evolution of <lb/>warning color pattern mimicry, the high evolutionary potential of cyanogenic toxicity may have facilitated <lb/>diversification and ecological speciation in Heliconius, highlighting the importance of understanding the <lb/>evolution of chemical defense in aposematic and mimetic species. <lb/></front>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>3. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Chemical defenses are a common means for animals to gain protection against predators. Defensive chemicals <lb/>can be acquired from the larval or adult diet (sequestered) and/or biosynthesized de novo by the organism 1-3 . <lb/>Chemical defenses are often coupled with bright color patterns, which local predators learn to associate with <lb/>toxicity or unpalatability of the prey, a phenomenon known as aposematism 4 . This can also lead to mimicry <lb/>among co-occurring prey species, which can be either Batesian mimicry, where a palatable mimic exploits an <lb/>unpalatable model, or Müllerian mimicry, in which unpalatable species copy one another for mutual benefit <lb/>(reviewed by 5 ). However, because palatability can vary along a continuum 6 , the distinction between these <lb/>forms of mimicry is not always clear-cut, and theory suggests that an intermediate form of Müllerian mimicry, <lb/>known as quasi-Batesian mimicry, may also occur 7 . Quasi-Batesian mimicry occurs when a less well protected <lb/>species acts in a parasitic manner, diluting the protection of the better defended species 8,9 . Such a situation is <lb/>expected to be less common than simple Müllerian mimicry 10 , but empirical evidence from laboratory and <lb/>field experiments supports its existence 11,12 . These different mimicry relationships depend largely on <lb/>predictable differences in toxicity among mimetic species and individuals, and yield different predictions about <lb/>the origins of diversity in warning coloration and mimicry 8,13,14 . Although mimicry is one of the earliest and <lb/>best studied examples of Darwin´s theory of evolution by natural selection and some of evolution´s oldest <lb/>mathematical models 15 , many open questions remain concerning the evolution of chemical defenses <lb/>underlying aposematism and mimicry. <lb/>A key factor in defining mimicry relationships is the relative protection levels of individuals <lb/>and species, which varies with unpalatability and abundance 5,9,16 . This is because the effectiveness of a <lb/>warning signal depends on how often the predators encounter the signal 17 , and how memorable these <lb/>encounters are, i.e. the level of toxicity or unpalatability. Turner 6 and Speed 8 highlight the importance of <lb/>studying the geography of the palatability spectrum because of its high relevance in defining mimicry <lb/>relationships. Extensive variation in defensive toxins within and among prey populations has repeatedly been <lb/>demonstrated 18 , supporting the prediction that chemical defenses vary widely along a continuum 8,18-20 . The <lb/>levels of unpalatability of mimic species can range from equal to very uneven 1,19,21 , and species may be <lb/>protected by different chemical compounds 20,22 . Such variation has important implications for the dynamics <lb/>of mimicry, through e.g. leading to alternation between the different types of mimicry, which could in turn <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>influence convergent vs. advergent selection (where selective pressures cause phenotypic convergence of one <lb/>species on another, but not vice versa 9 ), and contribute to the observed diversity in mimicry systems 8,10 . <lb/>Chemical defense also varies within species and populations. The selection pressures acting <lb/>on chemical defense traits are expected to be complex, as chemically defended herbivores are often involved <lb/>in close coevolutionary arms races with their host plants, predators and parasitoids 6 . At the individual level, <lb/>there may be selection for optimizing the allocation of energy and resources between defense and other <lb/>functions because of the potentially high costs of production and maintenance of chemical defenses. This <lb/>could lead to energetic trade-offs 23,24 and automimicry (the occurrence of palatable &quot;cheaters&quot; in a <lb/>chemically defended population 18,25 ). These &quot;cheaters&quot; (automimics) benefit from the protection of their <lb/>warning coloration, without investing in energetically expensive chemical defenses 18 . A decrease in <lb/>population average unpalatability due to the occurrence of automimics or weakly defended individuals could <lb/>dilute the protection conveyed by the warning signal 18,26,27 , as in Batesian and quasi-Batesian mimicry. Host-<lb/>plant chemistry is likely to drive intraspecific variation in sequestered defensive compounds 1,2 , as <lb/>demonstrated in butterflies 28,29 . For species that biosynthesize defensive compounds de novo, the origin of <lb/>variation in defense levels is less clear. Sources of variation may include biotic factors such as the energy <lb/>and resources available for the expensive compound synthesis, as well as interactions (and potential trade-<lb/>offs) with life-history traits such as age, reproductive stage or immunological status 1,30 . An important <lb/>mechanism underlying defense variation is probably variation in the biochemical efficiency of sequestration <lb/>and biosynthesis of defensive chemicals, a trait that could itself evolve. However, little is known about <lb/>whether such variation is genetic or environmental in origin. Despite the central role of chemical defenses in <lb/>the evolution of aposematic and mimetic species, we know little about the evolutionary potential of these <lb/>traits. <lb/>Neotropical Heliconius butterflies, with their incredible diversity in wing coloration, are a well-<lb/>known example of aposematism and mimicry 31,32 . Heliconius larvae feed exclusively on passion vines <lb/>(Passiflora genus), with which they have radiated and speciated through a coevolutionary arms race 33,34 . <lb/>Passiflora are cyanogenic, and contain one or several of about 30 different cyanogenic glucoside (CNglc) <lb/>compounds 3 . Some of these CNglcs found in Passiflora can be sequestered by the larvae of most Heliconius <lb/>species 3,35 , and the chemical content of host plants can influence the level of sequestered defenses of the <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>butterfly 29 . However, the Heliconius genus represents a minority among Lepidopterans additionally capable <lb/>of biosynthesizing defensive compounds de novo 36 . Heliconius larvae and adult butterflies can biosynthesize <lb/>the CNglcs linamarin and lotaustralin from aliphatic amino acids 37 , but the sources of variation in biosynthesis <lb/>are less well known than those in host-plant dependent compound sequestration. The capacity of cyanogen <lb/>biosynthesis in Heliconius is thought to be related to the evolution of pollen feeding. This is because pollen <lb/>feeding allows the exploitation of amino acid sources during adulthood for reproduction and the uniquely long <lb/>adult life-span of these butterflies, and could thus free larval-acquired resources for purposes such as defense <lb/>38-41 <lb/>. Substantial variation in the amounts and types of cyanogens between different Heliconius species has <lb/>been documented, both within and between mimicry rings 3,19,41,42 . Some of this is explained by the level of <lb/>diet specialization, which is a major determinant of the relative roles of plant-CNglcs sequestration and de <lb/>novo biosynthesis, shown to be negatively correlated traits among Heliconius species 3,42 . In general, the more <lb/>specialized the species, the larger the role of sequestration and the higher the total level of CNglcs, while the <lb/>more generalist species acquire their defense compounds mostly from biosynthesis, and have on average lower <lb/>total cyanogen levels 3 . However, we know little about how cyanogenic toxicity varies within Heliconius <lb/>species or within populations, how it is influenced by environmental variation, and what is its potential to <lb/>evolve. <lb/>Here, we analyzed the evolutionary potential of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity in <lb/>Heliconius erato by estimating genetic variance components and evolvabilities of this important chemical <lb/>defense trait using a common-garden breeding design. The pedigree data consisted of 20 broods and altogether <lb/>more than 300 individuals. In addition, we analyzed natural variation in the cyanogenic content of the host <lb/>plant Passiflora biflora, and the contribution of larval diet (P. biflora with varying cyanogenic content and <lb/>overall nutritional quality) to the variation in butterfly biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity. Finally, we studied <lb/>variation in toxicity within and among natural populations of H. erato along environmental clines and among <lb/>populations originating from two regions of South and Central America. <lb/>4. RESULTS <lb/>Common-garden pedigree data comprising more than 300 Heliconius erato individuals revealed a significant <lb/>heritable genetic component and high evolvability in biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity (Fig. 1D). In <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>contrast, nutritional quality and cyanogenic toxicity in the host plant Passiflora biflora, which varied <lb/>significantly in response to full-factorial water availability treatments, had negligible impacts on the <lb/>biosynthesized toxicity level of the butterflies feeding on these plants. The distribution of biosynthesized <lb/>cyanogenic toxicity in natural H. erato populations sampled at wet, intermediate, and dry sites along a <lb/>rainfall gradient in Panama was consistently skewed, so that a large proportion of individuals had a <lb/>noticeably low level of toxicity compared with a smaller proportion of high-toxicity individuals (Fig. 1C). <lb/>Furthermore, a comparison of geographically distant natural populations of H. erato from Panama and <lb/>Ecuador showed that populations of the same species can have substantially different levels of <lb/>biosynthesized toxicity (Fig. 1B). Together, these results demonstrate the high level of intraspecific variation <lb/>and evolutionary potential in this important chemical defense trait of an aposematic and mimetic Heliconius <lb/>butterfly. <lb/>Figure 1. Natural variation and evolutionary potential of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity in <lb/>Heliconius erato. A) Top panel: Locations of the natural study populations in Central and South America <lb/>(Panama and Ecuador, respectively), with a more detailed map of study areas along the rainfall gradient <lb/>in Panama. Bottom panel: Experimental setups for common garden populations of H. erato and host <lb/>plant Passiflora biflora. B) Variation among natural populations in total-and total biosynthesized <lb/>cyanogenic (CNglc) toxin concentrations in P. biflora and H. erato, respectively. Small-case letters <lb/>indicate statistically significant differences between populations (Tukey HSD P&lt;0.05). C) Zero-truncated <lb/>kernel density distributions of total biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity in natural populations of H. erato <lb/>in Panama. D) Top panel: Expected % change in H. erato biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity through <lb/>generations assuming evolvability eµ =1.55% (measured value) and mean-scaled selection gradient βμ=1. <lb/>Bottom panel: Variance components of H. erato biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity (with S.E.) based on <lb/>pedigree data (see panel A). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Genetic variance in toxicity suggests high evolvability <lb/>The level of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity (concentrations of linamarin and lotaustralin, the two <lb/>cyanogenic compounds biosynthesized by Heliconius larvae and adults, analyzed with 1 H-NMR from <lb/>samples of adult individuals), varied two-fold among the 20 full-sib common-garden reared broods (range of <lb/>brood averages = 0.48% -0.88% of dry mass, Fig. 2A). Phenotypic variance components of cyanogenic <lb/>toxicity estimated with an animal model including the full pedigree as a random effect and fixed effects of <lb/>sex and feeding treatment (Model1) revealed a statistically significant genetic variance component (VG) for <lb/>total biosynthesized CNglcs concentration level (Fig. 1D, Table 1, Table S1), corresponding to a broad-sense <lb/>heritability (H 2 ) of 0.115. The genetic variance component was larger and statistically significant for the <lb/>concentration of linamarin compared to lotaustralin (H 2 = 0.139 for linamarin, H 2 = 0.067 for lotaustralin; <lb/>Table 1, Table S1). Heritabilities are useful measures of the resemblance between offspring and parents, but <lb/>are poor standardized measures of evolutionary potential 43 . As a measure of evolutionary potential, we <lb/>therefore computed mean-scaled evolvabilities (eµ) as eµ = VG/µ 2 , where µ is the trait mean, and which gives <lb/>the expected percent change in the trait mean per generation under a unit strength of selection 43,44 . The <lb/>broad-sense evolvability of total CNglcs concentration was eµ=1.55%, meaning that the trait mean is <lb/>expected to change by 1.55% per unit strength of selection in a generation (Fig. 1D). Evolvability was higher <lb/>for the concentration of linamarin compared to that of lotaustralin (eµ= 1.89% vs. eµ= 1.04%; Table 1, Table <lb/>S1). <lb/>Genetic variance component, <lb/>heritability and evolvability <lb/>Other variance components <lb/>(V/VP) <lb/>Total <lb/>phenotypic <lb/>variance <lb/>Model <lb/>type <lb/>Cyanogen <lb/>trait <lb/>Trait <lb/>mean <lb/>(µ) <lb/>No. <lb/>Obs. <lb/>No. <lb/>broods <lb/>VG <lb/>P VG <lb/>H 2 <lb/>(VG/VP) <lb/>eµ <lb/>(VG/µ 2 ); <lb/>% <lb/>Vmat/ <lb/>VP <lb/>Vtrm / <lb/>VP <lb/>Vsex/ <lb/>VP <lb/>VR/VP <lb/>VP <lb/>1 <lb/>Total CNglc % <lb/>0.772 322 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.0093 0.037 0.115 <lb/>1.555 <lb/>0.011 0.011 0.874 <lb/>0.080 <lb/>1 <lb/>Linamarin % <lb/>0.577 322 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.0063 0.020 0.139 <lb/>1.887 <lb/>0.001 0.013 0.848 <lb/>0.045 <lb/>1 <lb/>Lotaustralin % 0.195 322 <lb/>20 <lb/>0.0004 0.130 0.067 <lb/>1.039 <lb/>0.008 0.004 0.929 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>2 <lb/>Total CNglc % <lb/>0.772 322 <lb/>20 <lb/>1.0e-7 1.000 1.4e-6 1.7e-5 0.102 0.043 0.002 0.895 <lb/>0.073 <lb/>Table 1. Summary of variance components of Heliconius biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity <lb/>estimated with REML animal models. Vmat, Vtrm and Vsex are the variance components for maternal <lb/>effects, host plant feeding treatment and sex, respectively. See Table S1 for full model results. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>When including maternal identity as a second random effect in the animal model (Model2), <lb/>this maternal variance component explained most of the variance explained by the genetic variance <lb/>component in Model1, whereas VG became negligible, illustrating that the two random terms explain <lb/>essentially the same variance component (i.e. the among-family variance; Table 1, Table S1). Parent-<lb/>offspring regressions revealed that offspring CNglc concentration was positively associated with the CNglc <lb/>concentration of the mother (slope = 0.181 ± 0.071, t = 2.539, P = 0.012 for total CNglc concentration; Fig. <lb/>2C), while the association between fathers and offspring was negative and poorly supported statistically <lb/>(slope = -0.122 ± 0.083, t = -1.469, P = 0.143 for total CNglc concentration). In turn, the midparent-offspring <lb/>Figure 2. A) Variation in total biosynthesized CNglcs concentration (% dry mass) among full-sibling <lb/>broods of Heliconius erato by increasing maternal CNglc % (one pair of full-sib broods are paternal <lb/>half-siblings, in grey) B) Total biosynthesized CNglcs concentration (% dry mass) in newly-emerged <lb/>adult individuals fed with different Passiflora biflora host plant treatment types (see Fig. 1A) as <lb/>larvae. C) Parent-offspring regressions of total biosynthesized CNglcs concentration. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>regression was nearly flat (slope = 0.046 ± 0.107, t = 0.435, P = 0.664 for total CNglc concentration; Fig. <lb/>2C). These regression slopes (accounting for parent identity as a random factor) translate into a maternal-<lb/>effect coefficient for total CNglc concentration of m = 0.261 (95% confidence interval = -0.099, 0.614), <lb/>which implies the existence of considerable positive maternal effects in biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity. <lb/>The maternal effect coefficient was higher for linamarin level (mean m = 0.288, 95% C.I. -0.094, 0.687) than <lb/>lotaustralin level (mean m = 0.193, 95% C.I. -0.135, 0.520). <lb/>Butterflies reared on different host plant types (cultivated in a full-factorial combination of <lb/>plant origins and water availability treatments, see Fig. 1A) as larvae did not differ in biosynthesized <lb/>cyanogenic toxicity (Fig. 2B), and the host plant type explained a negligible proportion of variance in <lb/>toxicity level (Vtrm/VP = 0.011; Fig. 1D, Table 1, Table S1). This is despite the host plant types showing <lb/>highly significant differences in cyanogenic toxicity and plant quality indices representing nutritional values <lb/>(e.g. carbon-nitrogen balance; see Supplementary S3), which were measured because larval-acquired <lb/>nitrogenous resources have been proposed as an important source for cyanogen biosynthesis (Cardoso and <lb/>Gilbert 2013). The minor effect of the larval diet compared to the effect of family is also evident from a <lb/>simple linear model of total CNglcs concentration explained by maternal identity, sex, plant treatment, and <lb/>their two-way interactions, in which the effect of plant treatment was not statistically significant (F3, 228 = <lb/>1.335, P = 0.26), whereas the effect of maternal identity was (F19, 228 = 2.996, P&lt;0.001). Sex was also a <lb/>negligible source of variation in toxicity (Vsex/VP = 0.011; Fig. 1D, Table 1, Table S1). Despite the common-<lb/>garden conditions that all individuals experienced throughout their life cycle, the residual (unexplained) <lb/>variance component of CNglcs concentration remained large (Vres/VP = 0.874 for total CNglcs, Fig. 1D, <lb/>Table 1, Table S1). This large amount of unexplained variance is also demonstrated by a significant <lb/>difference in toxicity level between the parental and offspring generation (F1, 320 = 27.42, P &lt; 0.001 for total <lb/>CNglcs), despite the two generations sharing common garden conditions. <lb/>Wide natural variation in toxicity of butterflies and host plants <lb/>The distribution of biosynthesized CNglcs levels in the natural populations of H. erato sampled along an <lb/>environmental rainfall gradient in Panama was similar in the Dry, Intermediate and Wet populations (Fig. <lb/>1C): a large proportion of individuals had toxicity values in the low end of the toxicity range (e.g. 40% of <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>individuals had total CNglc concentrations falling within the lower 25% of toxicity values), while a small <lb/>proportion of individuals had a considerably higher toxicity level (e.g. 5% of individuals had total CNglc <lb/>concentrations within the highest 25% of toxicity values). Total CNglcs concentration and concentration of <lb/>linamarin did not differ detectably among the three Panamanian populations. However, the concentration of <lb/>lotaustralin differed among populations (F2, 89 = 7.97, P &lt; 0.001), with the Intermediate population having <lb/>higher concentrations than the two populations at the opposite extremes along the rainfall gradient. <lb/>The three populations along the altitudinal gradient in Ecuador differed markedly in <lb/>biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity from their Panamanian conspecifics: most Ecuadorian samples lacked <lb/>both linamarin and lotaustralin. Linamarin was detected in only 29% of samples, most of which originated <lb/>from the high-altitude site (75% of those with any signal), and the average biosynthesized cyanogen level in <lb/>these samples was very low (0.063%; Fig. 1B), which is below the minimum level observed in the <lb/>Panamanian populations. <lb/>The CNglc levels of the host plant Passiflora biflora differed significantly among the natural <lb/>populations along the rainfall gradient in Panama (F2, 48 = 3.65, P = 0.034; Fig. 1B). However, the cyanogen <lb/>level in Passiflora varied in a contrasting pattern to that <lb/>of H. erato, in which individuals from the Intermediate <lb/>population were most toxic on average (Fig. 1B). In the <lb/>plants, the Dry population had substantially lower <lb/>cyanogen levels compared with both the Intermediate and <lb/>Wet populations. Passibiflorin was the main compound <lb/>(93-95% of total CNglcs; Fig. 3) in all populations, with <lb/>the remaining proportion made up mainly of passibiflorin <lb/>triglycoside (5-6% of total CNglcs; Fig. 3). In addition, <lb/>15% of the samples from the Dry, and 9% from the <lb/>Intermediate populations contained traces of the CNglc <lb/>compound tetraphyllin A, which was not present in the <lb/>Wet population (Fig 3). <lb/>Figure 3. Average CNglc compound <lb/>compositions in natural Dry, <lb/>Intermediate and Wet populations of <lb/>the host plant Passiflora biflora in <lb/>Panama. Standard error bars are <lb/>shown for the total CNglcs <lb/>concentration. <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. DISCUSSION <lb/>High evolutionary potential of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity and its implications <lb/>We have shown for the first time that there is high evolvability in the biosynthesized chemical defenses of an <lb/>aposematic Heliconius butterfly. Our heritability estimate of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity (0.115 ± <lb/>0.086) is close to the average heritability value of physiological traits (0.12 ± 0.05) in a meta-analysis of a <lb/>wide range of traits and taxa 43 . Concerning evolvability, however, the estimated value for cyanogenic <lb/>toxicity is high (1.55 ± 0.89%) compared to the average value of physiological traits (0.49 ± 0.14%), as well <lb/>as the median evolvability of all studied traits across taxa (0.26 ± 0.03%; see 43 ). The evolvability of <lb/>eµ=1.55% means that the mean cyanogenic toxicity can be expected to change by 1.55% per unit strength of <lb/>selection per generation. This high estimate of evolvability implies that the trait has the potential to evolve <lb/>rapidly, especially in conditions of strong selection, also taking into account the short generation time <lb/>(usually one to two months) of these tropical butterflies. For example, assuming the species has six <lb/>generations per year, and increased cyanogenic toxicity is selected for with selection as strong as direct <lb/>selection on fitness (βμ= 100%, see 45 ), the trait mean has the potential to increase by 9.7% in just one year. <lb/>Studies of mimicry typically focus on the warning signal, namely the color pattern 31,32,46-48 . <lb/>However, contrasting selective agents could be acting on the defense trait associated with the warning signal, <lb/>both equally required for aposematism and mimicry. The complex selection regimes acting on chemical <lb/>defense, together with heritable genetic variation, could result in diverse patterns of adaptive evolution in <lb/>chemical defense traits, and influence the evolutionary trajectories of aposematic and mimetic species. This <lb/>is because evolutionary changes in chemical defense levels could alter mimetic relationships among groups <lb/>of species, including shifts between Müllerian, Batesian and quasi-Batesian relationships, which could in <lb/>turn influence advergent vs. convergent selection and contribute to the observed diversity in mimicry <lb/>systems 8,10,14 . <lb/>Heliconius butterflies are well known for rapid inter-and intraspecific diversification in their <lb/>color patterns 31,32 . Co-mimetic species have evolved numerous geographic races or sub-species 49 , of which <lb/>H. erato and H. melpomene present one of the most striking examples of the diversity of region-specific <lb/>color-pattern races. The origins of such diversity, and the role of Müllerian or other forms of mimicry in <lb/>creating this diversity, remain poorly understood 10,32,50-52 . The evolvability of cyanogenic toxicity <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body>demonstrated here suggests that local adaptation in chemical defense could have altered the nature of <lb/>relationships between species across geographic space, which may have played a role in the evolution of <lb/>wing pattern diversity. The capacity of Heliconius for defense compound biosynthesis could allow for <lb/>increased genetic control (and thus, increased evolvability) of chemical defenses compared with most other <lb/>chemically defended Lepidoptera which rely solely on host plant compound sequestration 36 . Furthermore, <lb/>evolutionary shifts in color pattern mimicry have been shown to result in reproductive isolation and <lb/>speciation in Heliconius 53,54 . Through influencing the evolution of color pattern mimicry, evolutionary <lb/>changes in chemical defenses could play a part in facilitating such ecological speciation. <lb/>Our results also indicate a central role for maternal effects in the inheritance of cyanogenic <lb/>toxicity. These effects could have a genetic and/or environmental basis in the mother. However, mothers <lb/>were raised in common garden conditions, and environmental variance is thus expected to be low. The <lb/>maternal effects could originate from e.g. epigenetic effects, direct transfer of toxins from mother to <lb/>offspring in eggs 37 , or other types of maternal influence on the offspring phenotype, beyond the contribution <lb/>of maternally transmitted genes 55-57 . Paternal effects were not observed, even though Heliconius males are <lb/>known to transfer a nuptial gift containing cyanogenic compounds to females at mating 58 . It is noteworthy <lb/>that the occurrence of a maternal effect of the type estimated here, defined simply as an effect of the mothers <lb/>phenotype on the offspring&apos;s phenotype (as in Falconer´s dilution model 55,56 ), could significantly strengthen <lb/>the response of the trait to selection. Walsh and Lynch 59 simulated the predicted selection response with <lb/>maternal effects under Falconer´s model, and demonstrated that for a trait with a maternal effect coefficient <lb/>of m = 0.25, which is comparable to the m = 0.261 found here for cyanogenic toxicity, the cumulative <lb/>response to selection would over time exceed that of a trait with m = 0 by as much as about 50% (with <lb/>heritability values remaining equal). This effect however is expected to dilute over generations and is not <lb/>straightforward to predict. Nevertheless, maternal effects could accelerate the high evolutionary potential of <lb/>cyanogenic toxicity, highlighting the potentially important role of chemical defense evolution in the <lb/>diversification and speciation of Heliconius. <lb/>Complex selection pressures in chemical defense: explaining defense variation in wild populations? <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>We found considerable variation in biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity both in common-garden laboratory <lb/>and wild population butterfly individuals. The extensive variation in host plant quality and toxicity had a <lb/>negligible influence on the cyanogenic toxicity level of the H. erato butterflies feeding on these plants in the <lb/>common garden. The relationship between larval diet and the level of sequestered compounds has been <lb/>demonstrated in many taxa, including Heliconius 29,42 . Here, we focused solely on the biosynthesized <lb/>cyanogenic compounds linamarin and lotaustralin, for which the sources of variation are less clear. <lb/>Heliconius erato is not capable of sequestering the cyanogenic compounds found in Passiflora biflora, its <lb/>major natural host plant and the host plant used in our experiment, because of the modified structure of those <lb/>compounds 3,35 , and we therefore expected only de novo biosynthesis of cyanogens in our common-garden <lb/>samples. The lack of a relationship between larval diet and biosynthesized cyanogens is still somewhat <lb/>surprising, as previous studies on Heliconius suggest that general larval nutrient intake (amino acids derived <lb/>from host plants) may be important for adult cyanogen biosynthesis 41 . In contrast, we found no significant <lb/>impact of host plant quality on butterfly biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity, despite the extensive variation <lb/>in overall nutritional values of the plants (e.g. carbon-nitrogen ratio). <lb/>Toxicity levels varied significantly among wild butterfly populations both between regions <lb/>and along environmental clines. The rainfall gradient along which populations were sampled is substantial, <lb/>and the habitat types vary from deciduous dry tropical forest to rainforest. The Ecuadorian populations, on <lb/>the other hand, inhabit a very different and geographically distant biotope along the eastern slope of the <lb/>Andes. These environmental clines are likely to differ in multiple biotic and abiotic factors potentially <lb/>relevant for chemical defense, including host plant and nectar/pollen availability and the community of <lb/>predators, a key candidate for a strong and dynamic selective force driving local adaptations in chemical <lb/>defense 14,18 . The field and experimental data indicate that quality variation within the main host plant species <lb/>P. biflora does not contribute to plastic responses in H. erato toxicity. However, in the case of wild-collected <lb/>samples the larval and adult diet is unknown (H. erato feeds on P. biflora, P. coriaceae and to a lesser extent <lb/>P. auriculata in the Canal Zone of Panama 60 , while the preferred host plants in Ecuador are not well <lb/>known). Some natural intraspecific variation found in biosynthesized toxicity could therefore originate from <lb/>variation in host plant species use, potentially influenced by a negative correlation between biosynthesis and <lb/>sequestration, which appears to occur from interspecific to individual levels 3,42,61 . Heliconius erato cannot <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body>sequester Passiflora cyanogens from P. biflora, but can do so from some of its other possible host plants 3 . <lb/>This could also help to explain the very low biosynthesized toxin levels in H. erato in Ecuador, where host <lb/>plant availability may differ. These populations could have specialized on a particular Passiflora host, <lb/>selecting for a major decrease in biosynthesis, and leading to local adaptation in the biosynthesized toxicity <lb/>level, in line with the demonstrated high evolutionary potential of this trait. Cases of zero levels of <lb/>biosynthesized cyanogens in Heliconius are rare, but previous observations of such species provide evidence <lb/>for their high levels of host plant specialization and plant defense compound sequestration 3,62 . Such adaptive <lb/>radiations of Heliconius driven by host plant niche use could also have been facilitated by the high <lb/>evolutionary potential in biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity leading to local adaptations in the sequestration-<lb/>biosynthesis balance. <lb/>In the case of the host plant Passiflora biflora, it is particularly notable that watering <lb/>treatments induced substantial differences in the cyanogen content and overall quality of the plants, and <lb/>corresponding variation in cyanogen content was observed also in the wild populations of P. biflora. This <lb/>adds to growing evidence of water availability as a major factor influencing toxin levels of cyanogenic <lb/>plants, many of which are of great economic importance (e.g. Eucalyptus 63 , cassava 64 , white clover 65 ). <lb/>Although here the cyanogen variation in P. biflora did not influence the studied chemical defense traits of H. <lb/>erato, water availability-induced variation in Passiflora and other cyanogenic plant species could have <lb/>important consequences for these plants as well as their associated species community, especially herbivores <lb/>feeding on them. This is particularly relevant when acknowledging that changes in precipitation are expected <lb/>to exert the most powerful selective forces in relation to global climate change 66 . <lb/>Patterns of within-population variation in toxicity: maximizing the proportion of &quot;cheaters&quot;? <lb/>All three butterfly populations along the rainfall gradient exhibited similar skewed distributions of <lb/>biosynthesized cyanogens. The majority of individuals in these populations had relatively low levels of <lb/>toxicity, whereas a smaller proportion had substantially higher levels, and the pattern was surprisingly <lb/>similar in all populations. Such a pattern could arise from e.g. age distributions, as some studies suggest that <lb/>Heliconius may accumulate cyanogenic toxins with age 40 . However, many individuals in the study <lb/>populations had near zero levels of toxicity, and thus, the pattern is also indicative of automimicry. <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Automimic &quot;cheaters&quot; exploit the protection given by their warning coloration, without investing in chemical <lb/>defenses themselves 18,25 . <lb/>An important assumption for automimicry to occur is that chemical defenses must be costly, <lb/>and there is thus selection for reducing individual-level toxicity, possibly through trade-offs with other <lb/>important energy-expensive traits. Costs of chemical defense in Heliconius are poorly known. There is <lb/>considerable evidence demonstrating costs of defense in other chemically-defended arthropods 18,24 . For the <lb/>&quot;cheaters&quot; not to take over the whole population, there must also be benefits of investing in chemical defense <lb/>(e.g. 67,68 ). These benefits are not always simple to demonstrate, as unpalatability may not be a linear <lb/>correlate of toxicity (e.g. 69 ), and it often varies widely particularly based on the predator community 14 . <lb/>However, empirical data on Heliconius imply direct benefits (surviving predator attacks) for chemically <lb/>defended individuals 70-72 , and indicate an increase in protection level especially when comparing low to <lb/>moderate cyanogenic toxicity levels 69 , applicable to observed cyanogen levels of H. erato 3,19 . <lb/>Theory suggests that the frequency of automimics in a population can reach an equilibrium <lb/>where the fitness of the &quot;cheaters&quot; (which pay reduced costs of defense but are more likely to be injured or <lb/>killed by predators) is equal to the fitness of the defended individuals (which pay more costs for defense but <lb/>have higher probability of surviving predator attacks) 67,68 . This could help explain the observed patterns of <lb/>variation in cyanogenic toxicity within natural populations of Heliconius erato, which may be indicative of <lb/>selection maximizing the frequency of automimics based on individual-level costs and benefits of chemical <lb/>defense. The occurrence of automimicry in Heliconius (also observed by 19 ) indicates that individual-level <lb/>costs of producing and maintaining cyanogenic toxicity could lead to decreases in population average <lb/>unpalatability. Future studies should investigate the entire range of both CNglcs and other chemical defense <lb/>compounds potentially interacting with biosynthesized CNglcs in producing the unpalatability level <lb/>perceived by relevant predators. An automimicry-related decrease in unpalatability could theoretically dilute <lb/>the protection conveyed by the warning signal against predators 18,26,27 , similarly as in Batesian and quasi-<lb/>Batesian mimicry, and influence the evolutionary trajectories of the species sharing the warning signal. <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body>6. CONCLUSION <lb/>We have shown in this analysis of biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity in a Heliconius butterfly that this <lb/>important chemical defense trait varies substantially within and among populations. This variation was <lb/>unrelated to nutritional quality and toxicity variation in its main Passiflora host. Instead, the results suggest <lb/>that larval host species availability and individual-level energy optimization may play more important roles <lb/>as selective agents acting on biosynthesized toxicity. We show that biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity has a <lb/>significant heritable genetic basis and substantial evolutionary potential, indicating that it can evolve rapidly <lb/>in response to the prevailing selection pressures. Despite the key role of chemical defense in mimicry <lb/>dynamics, adaptive changes in chemical defense levels are often somewhat overlooked as a mechanism of <lb/>evolution in aposematic and mimetic species, including the widely studied Heliconius butterflies. This study <lb/>is to date the most comprehensive analysis of the patterns of intraspecific chemical defense variation in wild <lb/>Heliconius populations, and the first to shed light on the evolutionary potential of this important trait. Our <lb/>results highlight the implications of adaptive evolution in chemical defense traits for the evolution of <lb/>Heliconius and other aposematic and mimetic species. <lb/>7. METHODS <lb/>Study sites and field collection of butterflies and host plants <lb/>Heliconius erato (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae) is a widespread neotropical butterfly typically occurring at the <lb/>edges of primary and secondary tropical rainforests. Heliconius erato demophoon butterflies and its typical <lb/>host plant P. biflora were collected from three populations in Panama along a steep rainfall gradient (Wet, <lb/>Intermediate and Dry study sites; Fig 1A, S4), and H. erato lativitta from High and Low altitude sites on the <lb/>Eastern slope of the Andes in Ecuador (Fig. 1A, S4). Butterflies were caught using a hand net and <lb/>transported live to the laboratory. All individuals caught from the Panamanian study areas (n = 92) were <lb/>sexed and weighed, and were preserved in 1 ml 100% MeOH (body excluding wings and one half of the <lb/>thorax) on the day of capture (males) or after allowing to oviposit in an insectary (females, see S4). At the <lb/>Ecuadorian sites, fertilised females were brought to a common environment, and the thorax of 21 F1 <lb/>individuals from each altitude were preserved in 1 ml 100% MeOH. <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body>Passiflora biflora leaf samples (one to four leaves pooled per plant individual, see S4) were <lb/>collected from the Panamanian Dry (n = 20), Int (n = 11) and Wet (n = 20) study areas (Fig. 1A), and <lb/>preserved fresh in 1ml 100% MeOH. In addition, 50 cm cuttings, all from different plant individuals, were <lb/>sampled from the Dry (n = 12) and Wet (n = 12) study areas for greenhouse cultivation. <lb/>Host plant greenhouse cultivation and treatments <lb/>Passiflora biflora were cultivated in the greenhouses at the University of Helsinki, Finland (75% relative <lb/>humidity; 8-20 hrs: 25°C, light; 20-8 hrs: 20°C, dark) in a soil mixture (50% compost, 20% coir, 15% perlite, <lb/>15% sand or gravel)(see S4 for details on cultivation methods and watering treatments). Standard (std)-<lb/>treated P. biflora were used as oviposition plants for the H. erato parental generation and larval diet for the <lb/>F1 families not included in feeding treatments. The P. biflora cuttings collected from the Dry and Wet study <lb/>areas in Panama were cultivated in a full-factorial combination of origins and water treatments, resulting in <lb/>the four host plant treatment types used in feeding treatments of H. erato (next section). Plants in the dry <lb/>treatment were kept at 75% relative humidity and watered two to three times weekly with about 1/3 of the <lb/>water volume compared to the wet treatment (constant water availability, relative humidity up to 100%), <lb/>such that the surface soil was allowed to dry and the leaves slightly droop between watering events. The dry <lb/>treatment thus aimed to mimic conditions of drought stress. <lb/>Butterfly rearing and breeding design <lb/>Laboratory H. erato populations descendent of the wild Dry population (transported live from Panama as <lb/>eggs, larvae and adult butterflies) were established at the University of Helsinki greenhouses (see S4 for <lb/>details on transport and rearing methods). Larvae were reared on std-type P. biflora. All butterflies were <lb/>individually marked, and were allowed to fly, mate, and oviposit freely in 2×2×2 m mesh cages with potted <lb/>std-type P. biflora and a standardized sugar solution diet provided ad libitum. The butterfly cages were <lb/>observed throughout the day for mating pairs, and mated females were moved to individual 2×2×2 m mesh <lb/>cages and allowed to oviposit on std-type P. biflora. Eggs of 14 females (eight mated with a known father, <lb/>average no. of full-sibs/family = 8, see Table S2) were collected, and hatched larvae fed with std-type P. <lb/>biflora until pupation. The offspring of six mated pairs (both parental identities known, average no. of full-<lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body>sibs/family = 29, Table S2) were included in the feeding treatments, where eggs from each mother were <lb/>divided equally into four groups and transferred onto each of the four P. biflora treatment types. F1 <lb/>individuals were collected within three days following emergence (unmated and unfed), were weighed and <lb/>preserved in 100% MeOH (body excluding wings and one-half of thorax). <lb/>Butterfly toxicity analyses with 1 H-NMR <lb/>The concentrations of the two cyanogenic compounds biosynthesized by Heliconius larvae and adults, <lb/>linamarin and lotaustralin, were analyzed from the butterfly samples using nuclear magnetic resonance ( 1 H-<lb/>NMR) with Bruker Avance III HD NMR spectrometer (Bruker BioSpin, Germany)(see S4 for details on <lb/>sample extraction and 1 H-NMR methods). The data were processed and analyzed using Bruker TopSpin <lb/>software. The peaks of CNglcs compounds were identified based on comparison of sample 1 H spectra with <lb/>the 1 H spectra of authentic reference samples of linamarin and lotaustralin. Note that we analyzed only the <lb/>biosynthesized cyanogenic compounds (not sequestered cyanogenic compounds nor other chemicals <lb/>potentially influencing unpalatability in Heliconius; see 32 ), and Heliconius &quot;cyanogenic toxicity&quot; or <lb/>&quot;toxicity&quot; refer here to biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity. Our study species has been considered generalist <lb/>or oligophagous on Passiflora, largely acquiring its cyanogenic toxicity through de novo biosynthesis of <lb/>CNglcs 42,60 , and the CNglc profile of its main host plant P. biflora, also used in our experimental setup, <lb/>consists of complex compounds which Heliconius larvae are unable to sequester 3,42 . <lb/>The values of CNglc concentrations in the wild-collected samples were normalized with a <lb/>square-root-transformation before applying ANOVA to test for population differences in R 3.4.4 73 . <lb/>Distributions of cyanogen traits were also explored by inspection of truncated weighted density distributions <lb/>(accounting for the skewness of data towards near-zero values) using the sm&quot; R package 74 . For the analyses <lb/>using common-garden data, untransformed values were used. <lb/>Host plant toxicity and quality analyses <lb/>The cyanogenic content of the Passiflora biflora samples was analyzed using liquid chromatography-mass <lb/>spectrometry (LC-MS/MS) with Agilent 1100 Series LC (Agilent Technologies, Germany) hyphenated to a <lb/>Bruker HCT-Ultra ion trap mass spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics, Germany) following the procedure of <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body>Castro et al. 3 (see S4 for details on sample extraction, spectrometry and analyses). Mass spectral data were <lb/>analyzed with the native data analysis software (Compass DataAnalyses, Bruker Daltonics). The P. biflora <lb/>CNglc compounds were detected and quantified following Castro et al. 3 . <lb/>Plant quality traits representing nutritional values of the greenhouse-cultivated P. biflora <lb/>treatment types were measured (average n = 63) with Dualex® Scientific+ leaf clip meter (Cerovic et al. <lb/>2012; S4). ANOVA including plant origin, treatment and their interaction was applied in R 3.4.4 73 to test for <lb/>differences in CNglcs and plant quality traits between the treatment groups. <lb/>Estimation of variance components, heritability, evolvability and maternal effects in Heliconius <lb/>biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity <lb/>The concentration of the two tested biosynthesized CNglcs, linamarin and lotaustralin were strongly <lb/>correlated with each other (r = 0.897, P&lt;0.001), and with the combined total concentration of biosynthesized <lb/>CNglcs (r = 0.94 for Lotaustralin, r = 0.99 for Linamarin, P&lt;0.001). Toxicity did not depend on adult mass <lb/>in either sex (F = 0.52, P = 0.471 for total CNglcs concentration; mass data available for n = 196 <lb/>individuals). Adult mass also did not differ between the feeding treatments (F=0.88, P= 0.480; model <lb/>including feeding treatment, sex and their interaction), and was not included as a variable in further analyses. <lb/>Variance components of Heliconius erato biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity were analyzed <lb/>by fitting linear mixed models applying the &quot;animal model&quot; framework 76,77 , in which the full pedigree <lb/>(relatedness matrix) is incorporated as an individual-level random effect. The models were fitted using <lb/>ASReml-R Version 4 78 , an R package that fits linear mixed models using Residual Maximum Likelihood <lb/>(REML) estimation. The two-generation pedigree consisted of 20 broods and their parents, and included <lb/>mother-offspring, father-offspring, full-sibling and paternal half-sibling relationships (n = 322 individuals, <lb/>Table S2). Of the 20 broods, six were included in the feeding treatments receiving four different P. biflora <lb/>types as larval diet (Table S2). Individuals of the parental generation were assumed to be unrelated. Because <lb/>our breeding design resulted mostly in full-sib families, we have limited power to distinguish additive-<lb/>genetic from other genetic variance components (dominance, epistasis, maternal/paternal effects). We thus <lb/>consider our genetic-variance estimate as a &apos;broad-sense&apos; genetic variance, although the estimate approaches <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body>the narrow-sense estimate more than a simple full-sib design due to the parent-offspring and half-sib <lb/>relations in the breeding design 79 . <lb/>Animal models were fitted separately for the three biosynthesized cyanogenic toxicity traits <lb/>(concentration of linamarin, lotaustralin and total CNglcs). The primary models (referred to as &quot;Animal <lb/>Model1&quot;) included the individual breeding value as a random effect, and the fixed effects of sex and feeding <lb/>treatment (variance explained by fixed effects computed using the method of Villemereuil et al. 80 ; see also <lb/>S4). &quot;Animal Model2&quot; included additionally the random effect of maternal identity. We computed broad-<lb/>sense heritabilities (H 2 ) as the proportion of the total phenotypic variance (VP) explained by the (broad-<lb/>sense) genetic variance component (VG). When calculating heritabilities we included the variance due to sex <lb/>in the total phenotypic variance, but we did not include the variance due to the treatment because this <lb/>component of the variance is unlikely to represent natural variation 80 . <lb/>The role of maternal effects in the evolution of cyanogenic toxicity was explored by <lb/>estimating maternal-effect coefficients following Falconer´s dilution model, which assumes that offspring <lb/>phenotype is a direct, linear function of maternal phenotype, beyond the contribution of maternally <lb/>transmitted genes 55-57 . Thus, the interpretation of this &apos;maternal effect&apos; is related to specific measured traits <lb/>(here, cyanogenic toxicity), and is different from the typical formulation of &apos;maternal environmental effects&apos; <lb/>(influence of the maternal environment on offspring traits). We estimated maternal effect coefficients (m) as <lb/>the difference in slope between a mother-offspring (mo) and a father-offspring (fo) regression, i.e. m = βmo -<lb/>βfo 55,56 . We fitted the parent-offspring regressions as linear mixed models with the lme4 R package 81 , <lb/>including family as a random factor and maternal or paternal toxicity phenotype as explanatory variables of <lb/>offspring toxicity phenotype. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>Datasets used in this study will be made available online at acceptance for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">8. ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>Personnel and researchers at the Smithsonian Tropical Research Institute (STRI Panama) and Ikiam at <lb/>Universidad Regional Amazónica (Ecuador) are acknowledged for help with permits and the field collection <lb/></div>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">of the study species. We are especially grateful to Marleny Rivera (STRI) for reliable and friendly assistance <lb/>in field sampling. Samples were processed at the Molecular Ecology Laboratory at the University of Helsinki <lb/>(UH), and analysed at the NMR facility at the Institute of Biotechnology (UH), which is supported by Biocenter <lb/>Finland and Helsinki Institute of Life Science (HiLIFE). Søren Bak and David Pattison (Department for Plant <lb/>and Environmental Sciences, University of Copenhagen) are acknowledged for collaboration on the LC-MS <lb/>analyses of Passiflora samples. Juha-Matti Pitkänen, Tuomas Niemi-Aro and Annukka Ruokolainen are <lb/>thanked for technical assistance, and Guillaume Minard, Anne Duplouy, Richard Wallbank, Richard Merrill, <lb/>Oscar Paneso, Krzysztof Kozak and Sophia Gripenberg for advice on study design and field work. Mika <lb/>Zagrobelny and Marcio Cardoso are thanked for advice on cyanogenic assays and Mika Zagrobelny also for <lb/>providing reference samples of the CNglcs compounds. Research and collecting permits were granted by the <lb/>Ministerio de Ambiente, Republica de Panama (Permit SE/AP-21-16) and the Ministerio del Ambiente, <lb/>Ecuador (under the Contrato Marco MAE-DNB-CM-2017-0058). Financial support was provided by the <lb/>Academy of Finland (Grant no. 286814 to A.M.), ERC (SpeciationGenetics 339873 to J.C.), NERC Doctoral <lb/>Training Partnership (NE/L002507/1 to G.M.K.), and Spanish Agency for International Development <lb/>Cooperation (AECID, grant number 2018SPE0000400194 to C.N.B.). The authors declare no conflicts of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>9. REFERENCES <lb/>1. Bowers, M. D. The evolution of unpalatibility and the cost of chemical defense in insects. in Insect <lb/>Chemical Ecology: An Evolutionary Approach 216-244 (Chapman Hall, 1992). <lb/>2. Opitz, S. E. W. &amp; Müller, C. Plant chemistry and insect sequestration. Chemoecology 19, 117 (2009). <lb/>3. de Castro, É. C. P. et al. Sequestration and biosynthesis of cyanogenic glucosides in passion vine <lb/>butterflies and consequences for the diversification of their host plants. Ecol. Evol. 9, 5079-5093 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>4. Ruxton, G. D., Sherratt, T. N. &amp; Speed, M. P. Avoiding Attack: The Evolutionary Ecology of Crypsis, <lb/>Warning Signals and Mimicry. (Oxford University Press, 2004). <lb/>5. Turner, J. R. G. The evolutionary dynamics of batesian and muellerian mimicry: similarities and <lb/>differences. Ecol. Entomol. 12, 81-95 (1987). <lb/>6. Turner, J. R. G. Mimicry: the palatability spectrum and its consequences. in The Biology of Butterflies <lb/>141-161 (Academic Press, 1984). <lb/>7. Speed, M. P. Muellerian mimicry and the psychology of predation. Anim. Behav. 45, 571-580 (1993). <lb/>8. Speed, M. P. Batesian, quasi-Batesian or Müllerian mimicry? Theory and data in mimicry Research. <lb/>Evol. Ecol. 13, 755-776 (1999). <lb/>9. Mallet, J. Causes and Consequences of a Lack of Coevolution in Müllerian mimicry. Evol. Ecol. 13, 777-<lb/>806 (1999). <lb/>10. Mallet, J. &amp; Joron, M. Evolution of Diversity in Warning Color and Mimicry: Polymorphisms, Shifting <lb/>Balance, and Speciation. Annu. Rev. Ecol. Syst. 30, 201-233 (1999). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>11. Speed, M. P., Alderson, N. J., Hardman, C. &amp; Ruxton, G. D. Testing Müllerian mimicry: an experiment <lb/>with wild birds. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci. 267, 725-731 (2000). <lb/>12. Rowland, H. M., Mappes, J., Ruxton, G. D. &amp; Speed, M. P. Mimicry between unequally defended prey <lb/>can be parasitic: evidence for quasi-Batesian mimicry. Ecol. Lett. 13, 1494-1502 (2010). <lb/>13. Joron, M. &amp; Mallet, J. L. Diversity in mimicry: paradox or paradigm? Trends Ecol. Evol. 13, 461-466 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>14. Briolat, E. S. et al. Diversity in warning coloration: selective paradox or the norm? Biol. Rev. 94, 388-<lb/>414 (2019). <lb/>15. Müller, F. Ituna and Thyridia: a remarkable case of in butterflies. Trans Entomol Soc Lond 1879, <lb/>20-29 (1879). <lb/>16. Lindström, L., Alatalo, R. V. &amp; Mappes, J. Imperfect Batesian mimicry-the effects of the frequency and <lb/>the distastefulness of the model. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B Biol. Sci. 264, 149-153 (1997). <lb/>17. Chouteau, M., Arias, M. &amp; Joron, M. Warning signals are under positive frequency-dependent selection <lb/>in nature. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 113, 2164-2169 (2016). <lb/>18. Speed, M. P., Ruxton, G. D., Mappes, J. &amp; Sherratt, T. N. Why are defensive toxins so variable? An <lb/>evolutionary perspective. Biol. Rev. 87, 874-884 (2012). <lb/>19. Arias, M. et al. Variation in cyanogenic compounds concentration within a Heliconius butterfly <lb/>community: does mimicry explain everything? BMC Evol. Biol. 16, 272 (2016). <lb/>20. Prudic, K. L., Timmermann, B. N., Papaj, D. R., Ritland, D. B. &amp; Oliver, J. C. Mimicry in viceroy butterflies <lb/>is dependent on abundance of the model queen butterfly. Commun. Biol. 2, 68 (2019). <lb/>Ritland, D. B. &amp; Brower, L. P. The viceroy butterfly is not a batesian mimic. Nature 350, 497 (1991). <lb/>22. Elias, M. &amp; Joron, M. Mimicry in Heliconius and Ithomiini butterflies: The profound consequences of an <lb/>adaptation. BIO Web Conf. 4, 00008 (2015). <lb/>23. Fordyce, J. A. &amp; Nice, C. C. Antagonistic, Stage-Specific Selection on Defensive Chemical Sequestration <lb/>in a Toxic Butterfly. Evolution 62, 1610-1617 (2008). <lb/>24. Lindstedt, C., Talsma, J. H. R., Ihalainen, E., Lindström, L. &amp; Mappes, J. Diet Quality Affects Warning <lb/>Coloration Indirectly: Excretion Costs in a Generalist Herbivore. Evolution 64, 68-78 (2010). <lb/>25. Brower, L. P., Pough, F. H. &amp; Meck, H. R. Theoretical Investigations of Automimicry, I. Single Trial <lb/>Learning. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 66, 1059-1066 (1970). <lb/>26. Gibson, D. O. How is Automimicry Maintained? in The Biology of Butterflies 163-165 (Academic Press, <lb/>1984). <lb/>27. Jones, R. S., Speed, M. P. &amp; Mappes, J. Parameterising a public good: how experiments on predation <lb/>can be used to predict cheat frequencies. Evol. Ecol. 30, 825-840 (2016). <lb/>28. Gardner, D. R. &amp; Stermitz, F. R. Host plant utilization and iridoid glycoside sequestration byEuphydryas <lb/>anicia (Lepidoptera: Nymphalidae). J. Chem. Ecol. 14, 2147-2168 (1988). <lb/>29. Hay-Roe, M. M. &amp; Nation, J. Spectrum of Cyanide Toxicity and Allocation in Heliconius erato and <lb/>Passiflora Host Plants. J. Chem. Ecol. 33, 319-329 (2007). <lb/>30. Smilanich, A. M., Dyer, L. A., Chambers, J. Q. &amp; Bowers, M. D. Immunological cost of chemical defence <lb/>and the evolution of herbivore diet breadth. Ecol. Lett. 12, 612-621 (2009). <lb/>31. Merrill, R. M. et al. The diversification of Heliconius butterflies: what have we learned in 150 years? J. <lb/>Evol. Biol. 28, 1417-1438 (2015). <lb/>32. Jiggins, C. D. The Ecology and Evolution of Heliconius Butterflies. (Oxford University Press, 2017). <lb/>33. Benson, W. W., Brown, K. S. &amp; Gilbert, L. E. Coevolution of Plants and Herbivores: Passion Flower <lb/>Butterflies. Evolution 29, 659-680 (1975). <lb/>34. de Castro, É. C. P., Zagrobelny, M., Cardoso, M. Z. &amp; Bak, S. The arms race between heliconiine <lb/>butterflies and Passiflora plants -new insights on an ancient subject. Biol. Rev. 93, 555-573 (2018). <lb/>35. Engler, H. S., Spencer, K. C. &amp; Gilbert, L. E. Preventing cyanide release from leaves. Nature 406, 144 <lb/>(2000). <lb/>36. Nishida, R. Sequestration of Defensive Substances from Plants by Lepidoptera. Annu. Rev. Entomol. 47, <lb/>57-92 (2002). <lb/>37. Nahrstedt, A. &amp; Davis, R. H. Occurrence, variation and biosynthesis of the cyanogenic glucosides <lb/>linamarin and lotaustralin in species of the Heliconiini (Insecta: Lepidoptera). Comp. Biochem. Physiol. <lb/>Part B Comp. Biochem. 75, 65-73 (1983). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>38. Gilbert, L. E. Pollen Feeding and Reproductive Biology of Heliconius Butterflies. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U. <lb/>S. A. 69, 1403-1407 (1972). <lb/>39. Boggs, C. L. Nutritional and Life-History Determinants of Resource Allocation in Holometabolous <lb/>Insects. Am. Nat. 117, 692-709 (1981). <lb/>40. Nahrstedt, A. &amp; Davis, R. H. Biosynthesis and quantitative relationships of the cyanogenic glucosides, <lb/>linamarin and lotaustralin, in genera of the Heliconiini (Insecta: Lepidoptera). Comp. Biochem. Physiol. <lb/>Part B Comp. Biochem. 82, 745-749 (1985). <lb/>41. Cardoso, M. Z. &amp; Gilbert, L. E. Pollen feeding, resource allocation and the evolution of chemical defence <lb/>in passion vine butterflies. J. Evol. Biol. 26, 1254-1260 (2013). <lb/>42. Engler-Chaouat, H. S. &amp; Gilbert, L. E. De novo Synthesis vs. Sequestration: Negatively Correlated <lb/>Metabolic Traits and the Evolution of Host Plant Specialization in Cyanogenic Butterflies. J. Chem. Ecol. <lb/>33, 25-42 (2007). <lb/>43. Hansen, T. F., Pélabon, C. &amp; Houle, D. Heritability is not Evolvability. Evol. Biol. 38, 258 (2011). <lb/>44. Hansen, T. F. &amp; Houle, D. Measuring and comparing evolvability and constraint in multivariate <lb/>characters. J. Evol. Biol. 21, 1201-1219 (2008). <lb/>45. Hereford, J., Hansen, T. F. &amp; Houle, D. Comparing strengths of directional selection: how strong is <lb/>strong? Evol. Int. J. Org. Evol. 58, 2133-2143 (2004). <lb/>46. Benson, W. W. Natural Selection for Miillerian Mimicry in Heliconius erato in Costa Rica. Science <lb/>936-939 (1972). <lb/>47. Mallet, J. &amp; Barton, N. H. Strong Natural Selection in a Warning-Color Hybrid Zone. Evolution 43, 421-<lb/>431 (1989). <lb/>48. Kapan, D. D. Three-butterfly system provides a field test of müllerian mimicry. Nature 409, 338-340 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>49. Supple, M. A. et al. Genomic architecture of adaptive color pattern divergence and convergence in <lb/>Heliconius butterflies. Genome Res. 23, 1248-1257 (2013). <lb/>50. Brower, A. V. Rapid morphological radiation and convergence among races of the butterfly Heliconius <lb/>erato inferred from patterns of mitochondrial DNA evolution. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 91, 6491-6495 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>51. Flanagan, N. S. et al. Historical demography of Müllerian mimicry in the neotropical Heliconius <lb/>butterflies. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. 101, 9704-9709 (2004). <lb/>52. Hines, H. M. et al. Wing patterning gene redefines the mimetic history of Heliconius butterflies. Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. 108, 19666-19671 (2011). <lb/>53. Mallet, J., McMillan, W. O. &amp; Jiggins, C. D. Mimicry and warning color at the boundary between <lb/>microevolution and macroevolution. in Endless Forms: Species and Speciation (Oxford University Press, <lb/>1998). <lb/>54. Jiggins, C. D., Naisbit, R. E., Coe, R. L. &amp; Mallet, J. Reproductive isolation caused by colour pattern <lb/>mimicry. Nature 411, 302-305 (2001). <lb/>55. Lande, R. &amp; Price, T. Genetic correlations and maternal effect coefficients obtained from offspring-<lb/>parent regression. Genetics 122, 915-922 (1989). <lb/>56. Lynch, M. &amp; Walsh, B. Maternal Effects. in Genetics and Analysis of Quantitative Traits 687-714 (Oxford <lb/>University Press, 1998). <lb/>57. Walsh, B. &amp; Lynch, M. Evolution and Selection of Quantitative Traits. (Oxford University Press, 2018). <lb/>58. Cardoso, M. Z. &amp; Gilbert, L. E. A male gift to its partner? Cyanogenic glycosides in the spermatophore of <lb/>longwing butterflies (Heliconius). Naturwissenschaften 94, 39-42 (2007). <lb/>59. Walsh, B. &amp; Lynch, M. Selection in the presence of heritable maternal effects. in Evolution and Selection <lb/>of Quantitative Traits 537-547 (2018). <lb/>60. Merrill, R. M., Naisbit, R. E., Mallet, J. &amp; Jiggins, C. D. Ecological and genetic factors influencing the <lb/>transition between host-use strategies in sympatric Heliconius butterflies. J. Evol. Biol. 26, 1959-1967 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>61. Pinheiro de Castro, É. C. et al. dynamics of cyanide defences in the life cycle of an aposematic <lb/>butterfly: Biosynthesis versus sequestration. Insect Biochem. Mol. Biol. 116, 103259 (2020). <lb/>62. Sculfort, O. et al. Variation of chemical compounds in wild Heliconiini reveals ecological factors <lb/>involved in the evolution of chemical defences in mimetic butterflies. (in prep.). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>63. Gleadow, R. M. &amp; Woodrow, I. E. Defense chemistry of cyanogenic Eucalyptus cladocalyx seedlings is <lb/>affected by water supply. Tree Physiol. 22, 939-945 (2002). <lb/>64. Vandegeer, R., Miller, R. E., Bain, M., Gleadow, R. M. &amp; Cavagnaro, T. R. Drought adversely affects tuber <lb/>development and nutritional quality of the staple crop cassava (Manihot esculenta Crantz). Funct. Plant <lb/>Biol. 40, 195-200 (2013). <lb/>65. Kooyers, N. J., Gage, L. R., Al-Lozi, A. &amp; Olsen, K. M. Aridity shapes cyanogenesis cline evolution in white <lb/>clover (Trifolium repens L.). Mol. Ecol. 23, 1053-1070 (2014). <lb/>66. Siepielski, A. M. et al. Precipitation drives global variation in natural selection. Science 355, 959-962 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>67. Ruxton, G. D. &amp; Speed, M. P. How can automimicry persist when predators can preferentially consume <lb/>undefended mimics? Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci. 273, 373-378 (2006). <lb/>68. Svennungsen, T. O. Holen, Ø. H. The evolutionary stability of automimicry. Proc. R. Soc. B Biol. Sci. <lb/>274, 2055-2063 (2007). <lb/>69. Chouteau, M., Dezeure, J., Sherratt, T. N., Llaurens, V. &amp; Joron, M. Similar predator aversion for natural <lb/>prey with diverse toxicity levels. Anim. Behav. 153, 49-59 (2019). <lb/>70. Boyden, T. C. Butterfly Palatability and Mimicry: Experiments with Ameiva Lizards. Evolution 30, 73-81 <lb/>(1976). <lb/>71. Pinheiro, C. E. G. Palatablility and escaping ability in Neotropical butterflies: tests with wild kingbirds <lb/>(Tyrannus melancholicus, Tyrannidae). Biol. J. Linn. Soc. 59, 351-365 (1996). <lb/>72. Pinheiro, C. E. G. &amp; Campos, V. C. The responses of wild jacamars (Galbula ruficauda, Galbulidae) to <lb/>aposematic, aposematic and cryptic, and cryptic butterflies in central Brazil. Ecol. Entomol. 44, 441-450 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>73. R Core Team. A language and environment for statistical computing. R Foundation for Statistical <lb/>Computing. (R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Austria, 2018). <lb/>74. Bowman, A. W. &amp; Azzalini, A. R package &apos;sm&apos;: nonparametric smoothing methods (version 2.2-5.5). <lb/>(2014). <lb/>75. Cerovic, Z. G., Masdoumier, G., Ghozlen, N. B. &amp; Latouche, G. A new optical leaf-clip meter for <lb/>simultaneous non-destructive assessment of leaf chlorophyll and epidermal flavonoids. Physiol. Plant. <lb/>146, 251-260 (2012). <lb/>76. Kruuk, L. E. B. Estimating genetic parameters in natural populations using the &apos;animal model&apos;. Philos. <lb/>Trans. R. Soc. Lond. B. Biol. Sci. 359, 873-890 (2004). <lb/>77. Wilson, A. J. et al. An ecologist&apos;s guide to the animal model. J. Anim. Ecol. 79, 13-26 (2010). <lb/>78. Butler, D. G., Cullis, B. R., Gilmour, A. R., Gogel, B. G. &amp; Thompson, R. ASReml-R Reference Manual <lb/>Version 4. (2017). <lb/>79. Lynch, M. &amp; Walsh, B. Resemblance Between Relatives. in Genetics and Analysis of Quantitative Traits <lb/>(Oxford University Press, 1998). <lb/>80. Villemereuil, P. de, Morrissey, M. B., Nakagawa, S. &amp; Schielzeth, H. Fixed-effect variance and the <lb/>estimation of repeatabilities and heritabilities: issues and solutions. J. Evol. Biol. 31, 621-632 (2018). <lb/>81. Bates, D., Mächler, M., Bolker, B. &amp; Walker, S. Fitting Linear Mixed-Effects Models using lme4. (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">10. AUTHOR INFORMATION <lb/>Contributions <lb/>A.M., M.S. and C.J. conceived the study. A.M., M.S. and G.M.K. conducted fieldwork. A.M. conducted <lb/>experimental work. A.M. and E.C. conducted laboratory work. A.M. and Ø.O. collated the dataset and <lb/>conducted the analyses. A.M. and C.J. wrote the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final <lb/>manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Corresponding author <lb/>Correspondence to Anniina L. K. Mattila (anniina.mattila@helsinki.fi) <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex">11. SUPPLEMENTARY ITEMS <lb/>S1. Table S1: Full results table of REML animal models. <lb/>S2. Table S2: Summary table of Heliconius erato broods. <lb/>S3. Cyanogenic toxicity and overall quality of Passiflora biflora host plant treatment groups. <lb/>S4. Supplementary Methods <lb/></div>

			<page>26 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
