<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Addiction Biology <lb/>HUMAN IMAGING STUDY <lb/>doi:10.1111/j.1369-1600.2010.00242.x <lb/>Brain activation patterns associated with cue <lb/>reactivity and craving in abstinent problem gamblers, <lb/>heavy smokers and healthy controls: an fMRI study <lb/>Anna E. Goudriaan <lb/>1,2 <lb/>, Michiel B. de Ruiter <lb/>1,3 <lb/>, Wim van den Brink <lb/>1,2 <lb/>, Jaap Oosterlaan <lb/>4 &amp; <lb/>Dick J. Veltman <lb/>1,3 <lb/>Department of Psychiatry, Academic Medical Center, University of Amsterdam,The Netherlands <lb/>1 <lb/>, Amsterdam Institute for Addiction Research, Amsterdam,The <lb/>Netherlands <lb/>2 <lb/>, Department of Psychiatry, VU University Medical Center, Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/>3 <lb/>, Department of Clinical Neuropsychology, VU University <lb/>Amsterdam, Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/>4 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Abnormal cue reactivity is a central characteristic of addiction, associated with increased activity in motivation, <lb/>attention and memory related brain circuits. In this neuroimaging study, cue reactivity in problem gamblers (PRG) was <lb/>compared with cue reactivity in heavy smokers (HSM) and healthy controls (HC). A functional magnetic resonance <lb/>imaging event-related cue reactivity paradigm, consisting of gambling, smoking-related and neutral pictures, was <lb/>employed in 17 treatment-seeking non-smoking PRG, 18 non-gambling HSM, and 17 non-gambling and non-smoking <lb/>HC. Watching gambling pictures (relative to neutral pictures) was associated with higher brain activation in occipito-<lb/>temporal areas, posterior cingulate cortex, parahippocampal gyrus and amygdala in PRG compared with HC and HSM. <lb/>Subjective craving in PRG correlated positively with brain activation in left ventrolateral prefrontal cortex and left <lb/>insula. When comparing the HSM group with the two other groups, no significant differences in brain activity induced <lb/>by smoking cues were found. In a stratified analysis, the HSM subgroup with higher Fagerström Test for Nicotine <lb/>Dependence scores (FTND M = 5.4) showed higher brain activation in ventromedial prefrontal cortex, rostral anterior <lb/>cingulate cortex, insula and middle/superior temporal gyrus while watching smoking-related pictures (relative to <lb/>neutral pictures) than the HSM subgroup with lower FTND scores (FTND M = 2.9) and than non-smoking HC. Nicotine <lb/>craving correlated with activation in left prefrontal and left amygdala when viewing smoking-related pictures in HSM. <lb/>Increased regional responsiveness to gambling pictures in brain regions linked to motivation and visual processing is <lb/>present in PRG, similar to neural mechanisms underlying cue reactivity in substance dependence. Increased brain <lb/>activation in related fronto-limbic brain areas was present in HSM with higher FTND scores compared with HSM with <lb/>lower FTND scores. <lb/>Keywords Addiction, cue reactivity, fMRI, impulse control disorder, nicotine dependence, pathological gambling. <lb/>Correspondence to: Anna E. Goudriaan, Department of Psychiatry, Academic Medical Center, P.O.Box 22660, 1100 DD Amsterdam, the Netherlands. <lb/>E-mail: a.e.goudriaan@amc.uva.nl <lb/>Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Terms and Conditions set out at http://wileyonlinelibrary.com/onlineopen#OnlineOpen_Terms <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Pathological gambling (PG) is a fairly common disorder <lb/>with an estimated point prevalence of approximately 1% <lb/>(Welte et al. 2001). PG often results in severe psychoso-<lb/>cial problems (Petry &amp; Kiluk 2002; Potenza et al. 2002). <lb/>Currently, PG is classified as an impulse control disorder, <lb/>but the diagnostic criteria closely resemble those of <lb/>substance dependence. In addition, recent studies have <lb/>shown neurobiological similarities between PG and sub-<lb/>stance dependence (Petry &amp; Kiluk 2002; Potenza et al. <lb/>2002; Goudriaan et al. 2004). As a consequence, some <lb/>authors have proposed to reclassify PG as a behavioural <lb/>addiction in DSM-V (Petry 2006; Potenza 2006). <lb/>Increased cue reactivity coupled with heightened <lb/>attention for addiction-related cues represents an impor-<lb/>tant mechanism in the development of addictive behav-<lb/>iors (Goldstein &amp; Volkow 2002) and may promote relapse <lb/></body>

			<front>Disclosure/Conflict of interest: None <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>in substance dependence (Cooney et al. 1997; Kosten <lb/>et al. 2006; Marissen et al. 2006). Functional imaging <lb/>studies using cue-exposure paradigms in nicotine, <lb/>alcohol and cocaine dependence have reported increased <lb/>ventral prefrontal, insular, amygdala, striatal, and tha-<lb/>lamic activity, brain regions associated with emotion <lb/>processing and motivational behavior. In addition, atten-<lb/>tional and cognitive control circuitry has been implicated <lb/>in neuroimaging cue reactivity studies, indicated by <lb/>increased dorsolateral prefrontal, anterior cingulate <lb/>cortex and parietal activation (Kilts et al. 2001; Tapert <lb/>et al. 2004; David et al. 2005; Kosten et al. 2006; McBride <lb/>et al. 2006; Franklin et al. 2007). <lb/>About 50% of pathological gamblers who try to quit <lb/>experience a relapse with seriously negative conse-<lb/>quences (Hodgins &amp; el Guebaly 2004), and other studies <lb/>indicate frequent relapses in treatment-seeking patho-<lb/>logical gamblers (Ledgerwood &amp; Petry 2006). Because <lb/>cue reactivity is a key mechanism in the development of <lb/>addictive disorders, and because it has been associated <lb/>with a higher risk of relapse in substance dependence <lb/>(Cooney et al. 1997; Kosten et al. 2006; Marissen et al. <lb/>2006), investigating the neurobiological mechanisms of <lb/>cue reactivity in this population is highly relevant. So far, <lb/>only two functional magnetic resonance imaging (fMRI) <lb/>studies on exposure to gambling-related cues in patho-<lb/>logical gamblers have been published (Potenza et al. <lb/>2003; Crockford et al. 2005). Both studies employed <lb/>video fragments of gambling-related and various control <lb/>scenes, but yielded inconsistent results. In the first study <lb/>among 10 pathological gamblers and 11 normal con-<lb/>trols, PG subjects revealed decreased, rather than <lb/>increased activation in the ventral anterior cingulate <lb/>cortex, orbitofrontal cortex, basal ganglia and thalamus <lb/>during gambling-associated versus control epochs. <lb/>Increased activation during viewing of gambling-related <lb/>material was found in the occipital lobe only (Potenza <lb/>et al. 2003). In the second study in 10 pathological gam-<lb/>blers and 10 healthy controls (HC) (Crockford et al. <lb/>2005), PG subjects showed higher brain activation in <lb/>response to gambling stimuli in the left occipital cortex, <lb/>left fusiform gyrus, right parahippocampal gyrus and <lb/>right prefrontal areas, compared with HC. <lb/>Thus, whereas these PG studies indicate increased <lb/>activation of brain regions involved in attention, memory <lb/>and visual processing, no evidence for abnormally <lb/>increased activity in limbic structures during processing <lb/>of gambling cues was found (e.g. increased activation in <lb/>amygdala), unlike neuroimaging studies on cue reactivity <lb/>in substance dependence (Kilts et al. 2004; Tapert et al. <lb/>2004; Kosten et al. 2006; McBride et al. 2006; Franklin <lb/>et al. 2007). Possible reasons for this discrepancy are the <lb/>use of videos instead of pictures and lack of power <lb/>because of small sample sizes. Furthermore, both studies <lb/>enrolled gamblers recruited through advertisements, and <lb/>neither study investigated whether treatment-seeking <lb/>problem gamblers (PRGs) would differ in cue reactivity to <lb/>gambling cues from normal controls. In an fMRI study <lb/>focusing on the processing of rewards in pathological <lb/>gamblers (Reuter et al. 2005), a blunted response to wins <lb/>versus losses was found in the limbic reward areas in <lb/>pathological gamblers versus HC. When presenting <lb/>pathological gamblers with gambling videos, the limbic <lb/>system may thus be relatively underactivated because of <lb/>a diminished response to gambling situations in which <lb/>money is gained. Given this blunted response to monetary <lb/>gains, the investigation of limbic activation to gambling <lb/>cues versus neutral cues that do not include monetary <lb/>gain may provide insight in cue reactivity to general gam-<lb/>bling cues. <lb/>In the present study, we wanted to address these issues <lb/>by investigating brain activation patterns to gambling or <lb/>smoking cues in chronic PRGs seeking treatment, heavy <lb/>smokers (HSM) and non-smoking non-gambling healthy <lb/>controls (HC). We employed an event-related picture <lb/>paradigm (George et al. 2001; Myrick et al. 2004; Smolka <lb/>et al. 2006) because this provides optimal flexibility with <lb/>regard to stimulus timing and avoids modeling problems <lb/>which may arise when analyzing video paradigm fMRI <lb/>data. In order to compare cue reactivity in PRG to cue <lb/>reactivity of a substance-dependent group, a comparison <lb/>group of HSM was included as well. An HSM control <lb/>group was chosen because the neurotoxic effects of nico-<lb/>tine are limited compared with those of other drugs of <lb/>abuse, such as alcohol (Sullivan 2003; Mudo, Belluardo <lb/>&amp; Fuxe 2007). Based on previous cue-reactivity studies in <lb/>substance dependence, we hypothesized that gambling <lb/>cues in PRG and smoking cues in HSM would elicit higher <lb/>brain reactivity compared with brain reactivity in healthy <lb/>non-smoking controls in brain regions associated with <lb/>emotion processing and motivational behavior such as <lb/>the amygdala, ventral striatum and ventral prefrontal <lb/>cortex, and in attention and cognitive control-related <lb/>brain areas such as the dorsal prefrontal cortex and ante-<lb/>rior cingulate cortex (ACC). In addition, the relation <lb/>between cue-related brain activity and subjective craving <lb/>in PRG and HSM was studied. We hypothesized that sub-<lb/>jective craving would be associated with increased activa-<lb/>tion in emotion and motivation-related brain areas in <lb/>PRG and HSM. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Subjects <lb/>Nineteen treatment-seeking PRG (four left-handed), 19 <lb/>HSM (three left-handed) and 19 non-smoking HC (one <lb/>left-handed), all males, participated in this study. For two <lb/></body>

			<page>492 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>PRG, one HSM and two HC, magnetic resonance imagine <lb/>(MRI) data could not be (completely) acquired because of <lb/>scanner failures. Therefore, 17 PRG, 18 HSM and 17 HC <lb/>constituted the three groups used for statistical analysis. <lb/>The PRG were recruited from two Dutch addiction treat-<lb/>ment centers. The HSM and the HC group were recruited <lb/>through advertisements in newspapers. <lb/>The main inclusion criterion for PRG was current <lb/>treatment for gambling problems. PRG were interviewed <lb/>with section T of the Diagnostic Interview Schedule <lb/>(Robins et al. 1998) to assess the diagnostic criteria for a <lb/>DSM-IV-TR diagnosis of PG. In addition, the South Oaks <lb/>Gambling Screen (SOGS; Lesieur &amp; Blume 1987) was <lb/>administered as a measure of problem gambling severity. <lb/>Two PRG failed to meet the criteria of a current DSM-<lb/>IV-TR PG diagnosis. However, because they did meet two <lb/>PG criteria currently, met PG criteria in the past and their <lb/>SOGS scores (7 and 8, respectively) were similar to the <lb/>PRG that did fulfill diagnostic criteria for PG (see Table 1; <lb/>mean SOGS score = 9.6 Ϯ 2.6), these PRG were included <lb/>in the analyses. All PRG were abstinent from gambling for <lb/>at least 1 week. HSM were included if they smoked at <lb/>least 15 cigarettes per day, and did not engage in gam-<lb/>bling activities more than twice a year. HSM were current <lb/>smokers who engaged in an experimental smoking cessa-<lb/>tion as part of this study. The Fagerström Test for Nicotine <lb/>Dependence (FTND) served as an indicator of nicotine <lb/>dependence severity (Heatherton et al. 1991). No <lb/>minimum score on the FTND was required for HSM. HSM <lb/>had to be overnight smoking abstinent, filled out ques-<lb/>tionnaires in the morning and were scanned in the <lb/>afternoon (16–18 hours abstinent). Abstinence was con-<lb/>firmed with a breath carbon monoxide measurement in <lb/>the morning, using a micro+ Smokerlyzer (Bedfont Scien-<lb/>tific, Ltd., Rochester, UK). HC never smoked, did not have <lb/>a history of problem gambling and did not engage in <lb/>gambling activities more than twice in the last year. <lb/>Exclusion criteria for all groups were: age under <lb/>18 years; difficulty reading Dutch; use of psychotropic <lb/>medication; a lifetime diagnosis of schizophrenia or psy-<lb/>chotic episodes; a 12-month diagnosis of manic disorder, <lb/>assessed with the respective sections of the Composite <lb/>International Diagnostic Interview (CIDI; Heatherton <lb/>et al. 1991; World Health Organization 1997); current <lb/>treatment for mental disorders other than those under <lb/>study; physical conditions known to influence cognition <lb/>or motor performance (e.g. multiple sclerosis, rheumatic <lb/>disease); positive urine screen for alcohol, amphetamines, <lb/>benzodiazepines, opioids or cocaine; consumption of <lb/>more than 21 units of alcohol per week. Groups were <lb/>mutually exclusive with regard to the psychiatric disorder <lb/>under study. For instance, PRG and HC did not smoke <lb/>(with the exception of one PRG who smoked less than five <lb/>cigarettes a day). Additional exclusion criteria for HC and <lb/>HSM, but not for PRG, were presence of anxiety disorders <lb/>(CIDI-section D), depression (CIDI-section E), obsessive– <lb/>compulsive disorder (CIDI-section K), post-traumatic <lb/>stress disorder (CIDI-section K) and attention-deficit/ <lb/>hyperactivity disorder (Conners ADHD Rating Scales; <lb/>Conners &amp; Sparrow 1999). PRG with these comorbid dis-<lb/>orders were not excluded, because problem gambling is <lb/>highly comorbid with these disorders. The severity of <lb/>depression symptoms was assessed with the Beck Depres-<lb/>sion Inventory (BDI-II; Beck et al. 1996). Problematic <lb/>alcohol use was screened with the Alcohol Use Disorders <lb/>Identification Test-Consumption (Bush et al. 1998). <lb/>In addition to the Cue Reactivity Task, a probabilistic <lb/>reversal learning task, a planning task and a stop signal <lb/>task were administered. Results from the reversal learn-<lb/>ing task and the planning task are reported elsewhere (de <lb/>Ruiter et al. 2009). The ethical review board of the Aca-<lb/>demic Medical Center approved the study and written <lb/>informed consent was obtained. Participants were reim-<lb/>bursed with €50 transferred to their bank account follow-<lb/>ing participation. <lb/>fMRI paradigm: Cue Reactivity Task <lb/>A picture two-choice response task was used (for <lb/>examples of pictures, see Fig. 1). Pictures were matched <lb/>for complexity as follows: an equal number of overview <lb/>pictures and detail pictures was selected for each condi-<lb/>tion (e.g. several persons gambling, smoking or talking, <lb/>versus detailed pictures of a hand at a slot machine, a <lb/>hand with a cigarette, a hand with a magazine). Second, <lb/>to match for picture complexity and comparability, all <lb/>pictures were taken in a similar naturalistic setting (e.g. <lb/>all pictures with multiple persons were taken with mul-<lb/>tiple objects in the background), only males were <lb/>included on pictures, and care was taken to match for <lb/>emotional expressions between the different pictures, by <lb/>including only photos with neutral face expressions. <lb/>Thirty gambling pictures, 30 smoking-related pictures, <lb/>30 neutral pictures and 30 low-level baseline pictures <lb/>were presented randomly, with the restriction that a <lb/>stimulus of the same stimulus category was not pre-<lb/>sented more than three times in a row. Low-level baseline <lb/>pictures with arrows pointing to the left or right were <lb/>presented, and a left or right response had to be given, in <lb/>order to be able to compare complex picture processing <lb/>compared with low-level visual processing. In the gam-<lb/>bling, smoking-related and neutral pictures, participants <lb/>had to press a response button with their left index finger <lb/>when a face was present in the picture and had to press a <lb/>response button with their right index finger when no <lb/>face was present. Fifty percent of all pictures within each <lb/>category contained a face. Each picture was presented for <lb/>a fixed period of 5 seconds, and participants were <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>493 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Demographic characteristics for problem gamblers, heavy smokers and healthy controls <lb/>Problem gamblers <lb/>(n <lb/>= 17) <lb/>Heavy smokers <lb/>(n <lb/>= 18) <lb/>Healthy controls <lb/>(n <lb/>= 17) <lb/>ANOVA, F test and significance <lb/>(P value, 2-tailed) <lb/>Age, mean (SD) <lb/>35.3 (9.4) <lb/>33.8 (9.1) <lb/>34.7 (9.7) <lb/>F(2,49) <lb/>= 0.11, P <lb/>= 0.89 <lb/>Education level, mean (SD) <lb/>4.1 (0.9) <lb/>4.1 (1.1) <lb/>4.3 (1.2) <lb/>F(2,49) <lb/>= 0.15, P <lb/>= 0.86 <lb/>Pathological Gambling Lifetime Diag <lb/>a <lb/>No. (%) <lb/>14 (82%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Pathological Gambling 12 M Diag <lb/>a <lb/>, No. (%) <lb/>11 (65%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>South Oaks Gambling Screen, 12 months, scale range 0–14; mean (SD) <lb/>9.6 (2.6) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Gambling-related debts in <lb/>€ (SD) <lb/>58.843,-(67.131,-) <lb/>– <lb/>– <lb/>Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence, mean (SD) <lb/>2.0 (-) <lb/>b <lb/>4.0 (1.5) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Mean n cigarettes/day (SD) <lb/>&lt;5 (-) <lb/>b <lb/>17.2 (3.8) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Breath carbon monoxide (BCO) levels in particles per million (SE) <lb/>2.2 (0.9) <lb/>9.0 (0.9) <lb/>2.0 (0.9) <lb/>F(2,51) <lb/>= 21.24, P <lb/>&lt; 0.001 <lb/>CIDI Anxiety 12 M Diag, No. (%) <lb/>3 (17%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>CIDI Depression 12 M Diag, No. (%) <lb/>3 (17%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Total comorbidity, No. (%) <lb/>4 (22%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Conners Adult ADHD Rating Scale, mean (SD) <lb/>52.5 (14.2) <lb/>46.1 (11.6) <lb/>44.5 (6.1) <lb/>F(2,49) <lb/>= 2.42, P <lb/>= 0.099 <lb/>Beck Depression Inventory, mean (SD) <lb/>11.1 (12.0) <lb/>4.4 (4.2) <lb/>3.8 (4.1) <lb/>F(2,49) <lb/>= 4.7, P <lb/>= 0.013 <lb/>Alcohol Use Disorders Identification Test—C <lb/>4.5 (2.7) <lb/>4.8 (2.6) <lb/>3.4 (2.1) <lb/>F(2,49) <lb/>= 1.7, P <lb/>= 0.19 <lb/>Gambling Urge Before Cue Reactivity Test <lb/>1.43 (.75) <lb/>1.18 (.33) <lb/>1.01 (.07) <lb/>See text <lb/>Gambling Urge After Cue Reactivity Test <lb/>1.76 (.70) <lb/>1.19 (.32) <lb/>1.02 (.10) <lb/>See text <lb/>Smoking Urge Before Cue Reactivity Test <lb/>1.28 (.66) <lb/>3.91 (1.27) <lb/>1.01 (.05) <lb/>See text <lb/>Smoking Urge After Cue Reactivity Test <lb/>1.37 (.86) <lb/>4.11 (1.36) <lb/>1.00 (.00) <lb/>See text <lb/>a <lb/>Pathological gambling was diagnosed with Diagnostic Interview Schedule Section T. <lb/>b <lb/>One gambler smoked less than five cigarettes a day. LT Diag <lb/>= Lifetime Diagnosis; 12 M Diag <lb/>= 12-Month Diagnosis; CIDI <lb/>= Composite <lb/>International Diagnostic Interview. <lb/></body>

			<page>494 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>requested to respond within this time period. When no <lb/>response was made after 5 seconds, the task proceeded. A <lb/>2.5-second blank screen was presented between each <lb/>picture. No feedback was given about right or wrong <lb/>responses. The scanning session lasted 15 minutes; each <lb/>of the gambling, smoking-related and neutral pictures <lb/>was presented once. Subjects were not encouraged to <lb/>respond as quickly as possible. The task was explained <lb/>and practiced outside the scanner using other pictures. <lb/>The performance parameter for the task was mean reac-<lb/>tion time to the pictures in each stimulus category. <lb/>Urge questionnaires <lb/>An 8-item gambling urge questionnaire, range 1–7 (MN <lb/>Potenza &amp; SS O&apos;Malley, unpublished data) and a 10-item <lb/>smoking urge questionnaire, range 1–7 (Tiffany &amp; Drobes <lb/>1991), were included to assess levels of gambling and <lb/>nicotine craving, respectively. Participants filled out the <lb/>urge questionnaires before and immediately after fMRI <lb/>scanning. <lb/>Imaging acquisition and preprocessing <lb/>Imaging data was obtained using a 3.0 Tesla Philips <lb/>Intera full-body fMRI scanner equipped with a standard <lb/>SENSE RF head coil (Quasar gradient system, Philips <lb/>Medical Systems BV, Eindhoven, the Netherlands) located <lb/>at the Academic Medical Center, Amsterdam. While par-<lb/>ticipants performed the task, T2*-weighted echo planar <lb/>images, sensitive to blood oxygenation level-dependent <lb/>(BOLD) contrast were acquired (35 axial slices, voxel size <lb/>3 ¥ 3 ¥ 3 mm, interslice gap 0.3 mm, matrix size <lb/>64 ¥ 64 mm, bandwidth 90 kHz, TE 35 ms, repetition <lb/>time 2.28 seconds), covering the entire brain except for <lb/>the inferior regions of the cerebellum. A sagittal <lb/>T1-weighed structural scan (voxel size 1 ¥ 1 ¥ 1 mm, <lb/>170 slices) was made in order to co-register it with the <lb/>fMRI data. Imaging analysis was done using SPM2 (Sta-<lb/>tistical Parametric Mapping; Wellcome Department of <lb/>Cognitive Neurology, London, UK). Images were slice-<lb/>timed, reoriented and realigned to the first volume. Next, <lb/>T1-coregistered volumes were normalized to an SPM T1-<lb/>template (using 12 linear parameters and a set of non-<lb/>linear cosine basis functions), and spatial smoothing was <lb/>performed using an 8 mm FWHM Gaussian kernel. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Group differences in demographic and clinical data were <lb/>analyzed using univariate analysis of variance (ANOVA) <lb/>and Tukey&apos;s post hoc tests. Group differences in educa-<lb/>tional level were analyzed using Pearson&apos;s chi-square <lb/>test. ANOVAs were used to analyze performance data <lb/>(mean reaction time) with group as between-subject <lb/>factor (PRG, HSM and HC), and stimulus category (gam-<lb/>bling versus neutral, smoking-related versus neutral, or <lb/>low-level baseline versus neutral) as within-subject <lb/>factor, using group contrasts. ANOVA was used to <lb/>analyze urge ratings (mean gambling urge, mean <lb/>smoking urge), with time (before and after task comple-<lb/>tion) as within-subject factor. All analyses were per-<lb/>formed two-tailed. <lb/>The mean FTND score in the HSM group was low <lb/>(M = 4.0; SD = 1.5) compared with FTND scores in <lb/>smokers reported in other fMRI cue reactivity studies <lb/>(Franklin et al. 2007, FTND = 4.8; McClernon et al. <lb/>2007, FTND = 6.4; McClernon, Kozink &amp; Rose 2008, <lb/>FTND = 6.5), and no nicotine dependence diagnoses were <lb/>available for the HSM, as in other studies (Brody et al. <lb/>Figure 1 Examples of gambling stimuli (left), smoking-related stimuli (middle) and neutral stimuli (right) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>495 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>2002). Therefore, exploratory analyses were done, <lb/>comparing HSM with high FTND scores (n = 10, FTND-<lb/>high group M = 5.4, SD = 0.5) to HSM with low FTND <lb/>scores (n = 8, FTND-low group: M = 2.9, SD = 1.0), after <lb/>a median split was made. In the PRG group, no split was <lb/>made between high or low severity PRG, because severity <lb/>of gambling problems in our sample, as assessed with the <lb/>SOGS, was comparable with severity reported in other <lb/>studies in treatment-seeking pathological gamblers. <lb/>The fMRI data were analyzed in the context of the <lb/>general linear model, using delta functions convolved with <lb/>a synthetic hemodynamic response function to model <lb/>responses to each stimulus type. For each comparison of <lb/>interest, single-subject contrast images were entered into <lb/>second-level (random effects) analyses. To investigate dif-<lb/>ferential processing of addiction relevant stimuli between <lb/>groups, one-way ANOVAs were performed and interaction <lb/>effects were computed for gambling versus neutral pic-<lb/>tures in the PRG versus the HC or HSM, and for smoking-<lb/>related versus neutral pictures in the HSM (HSM total <lb/>group; FTND-high group; FTND-low group) versus the <lb/>PRG or the HC. Main effects and interaction effects were <lb/>analyzed with one-way ANOVA implemented in SPM2 <lb/>and are reported with a cluster size restriction of 10 voxels <lb/>at P &lt; 0.05 corrected for multiple comparisons according <lb/>to the Family Wise Error method (Tiffany &amp; Drobes 1991; <lb/>Nichols &amp; Hayasaka 2003). Group interactions are <lb/>reported with a cluster size restriction of 5 voxels at <lb/>P &lt; 0.001, masked with the appropriate main effect. <lb/>Gambling or smoking-related pictures versus neutral <lb/>pictures were chosen for our main group-interaction con-<lb/>trast, because this contrast is most specific for the cue-<lb/>reactivity effect: reactivity to addiction specific cues <lb/>versus cues not related to addiction. The comparison of <lb/>addiction-related pictures versus baseline would include <lb/>various non-specific visual processes (such as stimulus <lb/>processing, object recognition) that are activated when <lb/>watching visually complex stimuli compared with very <lb/>simple visual stimuli (an arrow pointing to the left or <lb/>right). An interaction between addiction-related pictures <lb/>and baseline would therefore be less specific, because <lb/>visual processing would then interact with cue reactivity <lb/>effects. However, in addicted populations, it is important <lb/>to establish that baseline visual interpretation is similar <lb/>in both addicted persons and non-addicted groups. In <lb/>another study from our group, it was found that addicted <lb/>persons had a larger brain response to neutral pictures <lb/>compared with baseline (Zijlstra et al. 2009). Therefore, <lb/>we also present the contrast neutral versus baseline, to <lb/>demonstrate that neutral pictures generated similar acti-<lb/>vation patterns across groups. <lb/>In addition, the potential influence of left-handedness <lb/>on brain activity patterns was investigated by performing <lb/>all analyses with and without left-handed participants. <lb/>The activity patterns found after excluding left-handed <lb/>participants were very similar to those obtained when <lb/>including both left-and right-handed participants. <lb/>Therefore, in the Results section, we only present data <lb/>based on the whole sample. <lb/>Regression analyses were performed for the PRG and <lb/>HSM separately, to investigate whether brain activation in <lb/>response to addiction-related stimuli (gambling and <lb/>smoking stimuli, respectively) versus the neutral pictures <lb/>correlated with self-reported craving after scanning. <lb/>Regression analyses were also conducted to investigate <lb/>whether co-morbid ADHD [Conners Adult ADHD Rating <lb/>Scales (CAARS) scores] and depressive symptoms (BDI-II <lb/>scores) correlated with cue-reactivity-related brain acti-<lb/>vation (addiction-related pictures versus neutral pic-<lb/>tures). Because the PRG scored somewhat higher on the <lb/>CAARS, and much higher on the BDI-II than the other <lb/>two groups (see Table 1), these analyses were done sepa-<lb/>rately for each group. Four PRG had co-morbid psychiat-<lb/>ric disorders (anxiety and/or depression). Therefore, <lb/>group interactions including PRG were analyzed both <lb/>with and without these co-morbid participants. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Demographic and clinical results <lb/>Table 1 summarizes demographic and clinical character-<lb/>istics for the three groups. PRG had an average of almost <lb/>€60 000 in gambling-related debts. Breath carbon mon-<lb/>oxide levels were higher for the HSM, compared with PRG <lb/>and HC. PRG obtained higher scores on the CAARS and <lb/>BDI-II than both HSM and HC. <lb/>Results for performance data and craving ratings <lb/>Mean reaction times to gambling pictures (M: 1143 ms, <lb/>SD: 340) were longer than mean reaction times to <lb/>neutral pictures (M: 1006 ms, SD: 311), F(1,49) = 50.1, <lb/>P &lt; 0.0001; mean reaction times to smoking pictures (M: <lb/>929 ms, SD: 235) were shorter than mean reaction times <lb/>to neutral stimuli (F(1,49) = 12.9, P &lt; 0.0001; and <lb/>mean reaction times to the low level baseline condition <lb/>(M: 717 ms, SD: 169) were shorter than to the neutral <lb/>stimuli, F(1,49) = 80.3, P &lt; 0.0001, but no stimulus <lb/>type by group interactions were present (all group by <lb/>stimulus contrasts F values &lt; 1, NS). Accuracy was high; <lb/>mean number of errors summed across all conditions <lb/>was 1.2, and no differences in number of errors between <lb/>groups or conditions were found (F &lt; 1, NS). ANOVA <lb/>indicated that craving for smoking before scanning was <lb/>higher in the HSM compared with HC, F(1,34) = 87.4, <lb/>P &lt; 0.0001, and compared with PRG F(1,34) = 57.8, <lb/>P &lt; 0.0001. Craving did not differ between the FTND-<lb/>high group and the FTND-low group, F(1,17) &lt; 1, NS. <lb/></body>

			<page>496 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>No difference between smoking craving before and after <lb/>the cue reactivity task in the total group of HSM <lb/>F(1,17) = 1.42, P = 0.25, nor in the FTND-high group <lb/>versus the FTND-low group, F(1,16) = .29, P = 0.60 was <lb/>present. Craving for gambling was higher in PRG com-<lb/>pared with HSM and HC, F(2,51) = 6.92, P &lt; 0.002, and <lb/>a trend for increased gambling craving after the cue <lb/>reactivity task was observed in PRG, F(1,16) = 3.18, <lb/>P = 0.09, partial h <lb/>2 = 0.17 (defined as a large effect size, <lb/>Stevens 1996). <lb/>fMRI cue reactivity <lb/>Main effects (pictures versus baseline) <lb/>The main effects of viewing neutral pictures versus low-<lb/>level baseline pictures were observed in all three groups <lb/>mainly in the ventral visual stream (occipital lobe: <lb/>middle, inferior and lingual gyrus), as well as in areas <lb/>related to reward/motivation, and attention and <lb/>cognitive control; medial temporal lobe including <lb/>the amygdala, bilateral dorsolateral prefrontal cortex <lb/>(DLPFC), as well as bilateral posterior thalamus, see <lb/>Fig. 2, left panel. For gambling versus baseline pictures <lb/>and smoking-related versus baseline pictures, similar <lb/>regions were identified. In addition, we found bilateral <lb/>activation of the ventrolateral prefrontal cortex (VLPFC) <lb/>for gambling and smoking-related pictures versus base-<lb/>line pictures, as well as dorsomedial prefrontal cortex <lb/>activation for gambling pictures versus baseline pictures <lb/>(Fig. 2, middle and right panels, respectively). <lb/>Group interactions <lb/>For neutral pictures versus low-level baseline pictures, no <lb/>significant group interaction effects were observed. For <lb/>gambling pictures versus neutral pictures, we found <lb/>greater activation in left occipital cortex, bilateral para-<lb/>hippocampal gyrus, right amygdala and right DLPFC in <lb/>PRG relative to HC. Relative to the HSM, PRG showed <lb/>higher bilateral occipital cortex, bilateral parahippocam-<lb/>pal gyrus, bilateral amygdala, bilateral DLPFC and left <lb/>VLPFC activation when viewing gambling pictures versus <lb/>neutral pictures (Table 2 and Fig. 3). Similar group differ-<lb/>ences were observed when PRG with co-morbid psycho-<lb/>pathology were excluded, although differences in DLPFC <lb/>activation in PRG compared with HC, and differences in <lb/>activation in right amygdala and left DLPFC in PRG com-<lb/>pared with HSM ceased to be statistically significant. <lb/>No significant group by condition interactions were <lb/>observed for smoking pictures in HSM compared with <lb/>PRG or HC. Greater activation was present in the ventro-<lb/>medial prefrontal cortex (VMPFC) bilaterally, in the <lb/>Figure 2 Activation patterns across groups for neutral pictures versus low-level baseline pictures (top left panel), gambling pictures versus <lb/>low-level baseline pictures (top middle panel), smoking pictures versus low-level baseline pictures (top right panel), gambling pictures versus <lb/>neutral pictures (lower left panel), smoking-related pictures versus neutral pictures (lower right panel) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>497 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 2 <lb/>Cue Reactivity Task: BOLD activations for main effects (neutral/gambling/smoking-related pictures versus low-level baseline pictures); group interactions (gambling pictures versus neutral <lb/>pictures, and smoking-related pictures versus neutral pictures); correlations between BOLD activations and self-reported craving <lb/>Main effects <lb/>Neutral versus baseline <lb/>Gambling versus baseline <lb/>Smoking-related versus baseline <lb/>Gambling versus neutral <lb/>Smoking-related versus neutral <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>Prefrontal <lb/>Dorsolateral <lb/>-42 <lb/>9 <lb/>33 <lb/>7.43 <lb/>L <lb/>-42 <lb/>12 <lb/>33 <lb/>7.44 <lb/>L <lb/>-3 <lb/>54 <lb/>36 5.17 <lb/>42 <lb/>15 <lb/>30 <lb/>7.42 <lb/>R <lb/>54 <lb/>24 <lb/>30 <lb/>7.77 <lb/>R <lb/>42 <lb/>15 <lb/>33 <lb/>6.92 <lb/>L <lb/>-9 <lb/>27 <lb/>57 5.99 <lb/>Ventrolateral <lb/>L <lb/>-30 <lb/>33 <lb/>-9 <lb/>5.78 <lb/>-33 <lb/>33 <lb/>12 <lb/>6.59 <lb/>L <lb/>-33 <lb/>48 <lb/>6 3.87 <lb/>R <lb/>3 6 <lb/>3 6 <lb/>-6 <lb/>6.32 <lb/>36 <lb/>33 <lb/>-6 <lb/>7.52 <lb/>R <lb/>36 <lb/>33 <lb/>-6 <lb/>5.59 <lb/>Medial <lb/>R <lb/>3 <lb/>54 <lb/>0 4.75 <lb/>Temporal <lb/>Middle temporal <lb/>-33 <lb/>-18 <lb/>-21 <lb/>6.43 <lb/>L <lb/>-30 <lb/>-21 <lb/>-21 <lb/>6.53 <lb/>L <lb/>-30 -15 -15 <lb/>6.77 <lb/>L <lb/>-39 <lb/>6 <lb/>-15 4.83 <lb/>R <lb/>3 3 <lb/>-15 <lb/>-15 <lb/>7.29 <lb/>R <lb/>30 <lb/>-21 <lb/>-21 <lb/>7.22 <lb/>R <lb/>33 <lb/>-15 -15 <lb/>6.58 <lb/>Medial temporal <lb/>Parahippocampal gyrus <lb/>L <lb/>-27 <lb/>-33 <lb/>-21 <lb/>12.01 <lb/>L <lb/>-33 <lb/>-48 <lb/>-18 <lb/>7.90 <lb/>L <lb/>-24 -33 -18 <lb/>7.80 <lb/>L <lb/>-27 -45 -15 6.07 <lb/>R <lb/>2 7 <lb/>-48 <lb/>-15 <lb/>14.30 <lb/>R <lb/>33 <lb/>-48 <lb/>-18 <lb/>11.00 <lb/>R <lb/>36 <lb/>-48 -24 13.25 <lb/>R <lb/>33 <lb/>-45 -12 7.06 <lb/>Amygdala region <lb/>L <lb/>-21 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-18 <lb/>8.60 <lb/>L <lb/>-21 <lb/>-6 -15 <lb/>7.83 <lb/>R <lb/>2 4 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-18 <lb/>9.76 <lb/>R <lb/>21 <lb/>-6 -15 <lb/>7.81 <lb/>Occipital lobe <lb/>Occipital gyrus <lb/>-27 <lb/>-84 <lb/>-9 <lb/>15.35 <lb/>-24 <lb/>-84 <lb/>-6 <lb/>12.23 <lb/>-30 -84 <lb/>-9 14.24 <lb/>L <lb/>-36 -66 <lb/>27 5.48 <lb/>L <lb/>-45 -63 <lb/>33 5.86 <lb/>-39 <lb/>-78 <lb/>9 <lb/>13.68 <lb/>-33 <lb/>-72 <lb/>21 <lb/>8.90 <lb/>-36 -81 <lb/>12 13.65 <lb/>R <lb/>45 <lb/>-63 <lb/>30 5.49 <lb/>R <lb/>45 <lb/>-63 <lb/>39 4.80 <lb/>Fusiform gyrus <lb/>R <lb/>36 <lb/>-45 <lb/>-15 <lb/>10.39 <lb/>R <lb/>39 <lb/>-63 <lb/>-15 <lb/>10.28 <lb/>R <lb/>39 <lb/>-63 <lb/>-15 11.15 <lb/>R <lb/>60 <lb/>-54 <lb/>12 5.86 <lb/>R <lb/>60 <lb/>-36 <lb/>-3 5.12 <lb/>Occipital gyrus <lb/>27 <lb/>-84 <lb/>-9 <lb/>11.50 <lb/>24 <lb/>-84 <lb/>-15 <lb/>15.03 <lb/>24 <lb/>-84 -15 13.65 <lb/>24 <lb/>-81 <lb/>12 <lb/>8.41 <lb/>24 <lb/>-90 <lb/>12 <lb/>12.85 <lb/>24 <lb/>-90 <lb/>12 12.65 <lb/>Posterior thalamus <lb/>L <lb/>-18 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-3 <lb/>11.58 <lb/>L <lb/>-21 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-3 <lb/>10.21 <lb/>L <lb/>-21 -30 <lb/>-3 11.27 <lb/>R <lb/>1 8 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-3 <lb/>9 . 4 3 <lb/>R <lb/>2 1 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-3 <lb/>10.94 <lb/>R <lb/>21 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-3 <lb/>6.92 <lb/>Group Interactions <lb/>a <lb/>Gambling vs. Neutral Pictures Problem Gamblers <lb/>&gt; Healthy Controls <lb/>Problem Gamblers <lb/>&gt; Heavy Smokers <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>Prefrontal <lb/>L <lb/>-48 <lb/>9 <lb/>33 <lb/>3.64 <lb/>Dorsolateral <lb/>R <lb/>39 <lb/>7 <lb/>30 <lb/>3.22 <lb/>R <lb/>45 <lb/>0 <lb/>42 <lb/>4.31 <lb/>Ventrolateral <lb/>L <lb/>-42 <lb/>24 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.30 <lb/>Medial Temporal <lb/>Parahippocampal Gyrus <lb/>L <lb/>-18 <lb/>-24 <lb/>-21 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>L <lb/>-27 <lb/>-45 <lb/>-15 <lb/>4.04 <lb/>R <lb/>2 1 <lb/>-27 <lb/>-21 <lb/>3.52 <lb/>R <lb/>27 <lb/>-36 <lb/>-21 <lb/>4.01 <lb/>R <lb/>3 0 <lb/>-60 <lb/>-15 <lb/>3.45 <lb/>Amygdala <lb/>L <lb/>-21 <lb/>9 <lb/>-18 <lb/>3.54 <lb/>R <lb/>1 5 <lb/>0 <lb/>-15 <lb/>3.34 <lb/>R <lb/>15 <lb/>5 <lb/>-10 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>Occipital/Temporal junction <lb/>R <lb/>57 <lb/>-60 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.56 <lb/>Middle Occipital Gyrus <lb/>L <lb/>-33 <lb/>-78 <lb/>12 <lb/>3.40 <lb/>L <lb/>-33 <lb/>-78 <lb/>12 <lb/>4.89 <lb/>-39 <lb/>-72 <lb/>12 <lb/>R <lb/>27 <lb/>-72 <lb/>33 <lb/>3.20 <lb/>a <lb/>Group interaction are reported at P <lb/>&lt; 0.001 unless indicated otherwise. BOLD <lb/>= blood oxygenation level-dependent; MNI <lb/>= Montreal Neurological Institute. <lb/></body>

			<page>498 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>rostral ACC bilaterally and in the left VLPFC in the <lb/>FTND-high group compared with HC and in the <lb/>FTND-high group compared with the FTND-low <lb/>group. Similar effects were observed when comparing <lb/>the FTND-high group with PRG (see Table 3 and Fig. 4). <lb/>In addition, in the FTND-high group, activation in the <lb/>left precuneus, right insula and left middle and superior <lb/>temporal gyri was greater than in the FTND-low group. <lb/>No significant group by condition interactions were <lb/>observed in the FTND-low group compared with either <lb/>HC or PRG. <lb/>Figure 3 Group interaction: Areas highlighted for higher activation <lb/>in problem gamblers (PRG) versus the pooled sample of healthy <lb/>controls (HC) and heavy smokers (HSM) at coordinates -9, 0, -18. <lb/>Exclusion of PRG with co-morbid psychiatric disorders resulted in <lb/>similar results, although differences in dorsolateral prefrontal cortex <lb/>(DLPFC) in PRG compared with HC, and in right amygdala activation <lb/>and left DLPFC in PRG compared with HSM ceased to be statistically <lb/>significant. No significant relations between Beck Depression <lb/>Inventory-II, or Conners Adult ADHD Rating Scales scores and <lb/>blood oxygenation level-dependent response when viewing gam-<lb/>bling pictures versus neutral pictures were present in PRG, HSM or <lb/>HC <lb/>Figure 4 Group interaction: Areas highlighted for higher activation <lb/>in Fagerström Test for Nicotine Dependence (FTND)-high group <lb/>versus the pooled sample of FTND-low group, problem gamblers <lb/>(PRG) and healthy controls (HC) at coordinates 3, -51, 21. No <lb/>significant relations between Beck Depression Inventory-II, or <lb/>Conners Adult ADHD Rating Scales scores and blood oxygenation <lb/>level-dependent response when viewing smoking-related pictures <lb/>versus neutral pictures were present in the FTND-high group, <lb/>FTND-low group, PRG or HC <lb/>Table 3 Cue-reactivity task: BOLD activations for group interactions: smoking-related pictures versus neutral pictures. <lb/>Nicotine vs. Neutral <lb/>Pictures <lb/>FTND-high &gt; Healthy Controls <lb/>FTND-high &gt; FTND-low <lb/>FTND-high &gt; Problem Gamblers <lb/>L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value L/R <lb/>MNI coordinates <lb/>Z value <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>Prefrontal <lb/>Ventromedial <lb/>L <lb/>-12 <lb/>54 -3 3.61 <lb/>L <lb/>-12 <lb/>51 <lb/>-3 3.51 <lb/>L <lb/>-6 <lb/>66 15 3.46 <lb/>R <lb/>12 <lb/>51 <lb/>0 3.71 <lb/>R <lb/>9 <lb/>51 <lb/>6 3.95 <lb/>R <lb/>9 <lb/>60 15 3.30 <lb/>Ventrolateral <lb/>L <lb/>-33 <lb/>51 <lb/>6 3.83 <lb/>R <lb/>15 <lb/>51 <lb/>3 3.65 <lb/>Superior frontal gyrus <lb/>R <lb/>33 <lb/>42 <lb/>42 3.39 <lb/>rostral ACC <lb/>L <lb/>-6 <lb/>42 <lb/>9 3.79 <lb/>L <lb/>-6 <lb/>42 <lb/>9 3.88 <lb/>L <lb/>-6 <lb/>48 <lb/>3 4.07 <lb/>-3 <lb/>48 <lb/>6 3.54 <lb/>R <lb/>9 <lb/>42 <lb/>6 3.56 <lb/>R <lb/>6 <lb/>45 <lb/>6 3.68 <lb/>R <lb/>6 <lb/>42 <lb/>9 3.55 <lb/>Parietal <lb/>L <lb/>-9 -60 36 3.61 <lb/>L <lb/>-3 -48 33 3.65 <lb/>Middle temporal gyrus <lb/>L <lb/>-51 <lb/>6 -21 4.27 <lb/>Superior temporal gyrus <lb/>L <lb/>-45 <lb/>9 -15 3.52 <lb/>Insula <lb/>R <lb/>36 <lb/>9 <lb/>-9 3.44 <lb/>Precuneus <lb/>L <lb/>-6 -54 <lb/>36 3.56 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>499 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>Correlations between BOLD activation, subjective craving, <lb/>BDI-II and CAARS <lb/>Regression analyses indicated a positive relation between <lb/>subjective craving for gambling after scanning in PRG <lb/>and BOLD activation in the VLPFC, left anterior insula <lb/>and left caudate head when viewing gambling pictures <lb/>versus neutral pictures (see Table 2). A positive relation <lb/>between subjective craving for nicotine after scanning in <lb/>HSM and BOLD activation in the VLPFC and left <lb/>amygdala region during viewing of smoking-related pic-<lb/>tures versus neutral pictures was present (Table 4). <lb/>No significant relations between BDI-II or CAARS <lb/>scores and regional cerebral blood flow changes during <lb/>viewing gambling or smoking-related pictures versus <lb/>neutral pictures were present in PRG, HSM or HC. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>This is the first study investigating cue reactivity to <lb/>gambling stimuli in treatment-seeking PRG compared <lb/>with HSM and HC, using an fMRI event-related picture <lb/>paradigm. PRG showed higher brain activation compared <lb/>with HC and HSM when viewing gambling pictures (com-<lb/>pared with neutral pictures) in brain areas related to <lb/>visual information processing and memory (bilateral <lb/>occipital cortex, parahippocampal gyrus), and emotion <lb/>and motivation (amygdala region, VLPFC). Specifically, <lb/>upregulation of visual information processing areas has <lb/>been related to altered dopaminergic transmission in <lb/>neural systems implicated in substance dependence: (1) <lb/>an emotion/motivational and memory/learning circuit, <lb/>including orbitofrontal, subcallosal cortex, amygdala and <lb/>hippocampus; and (2) an attention/control circuit, <lb/>including dorsal prefrontal and ACC (Breiter &amp; Rosen <lb/>1999; Goldstein &amp; Volkow 2002; Kalivas &amp; Volkow <lb/>2005). Higher activation in PG in these visual informa-<lb/>tion processing areas may thus be related to a higher <lb/>saliency of gambling stimuli, through innervations of <lb/>dopamine pathways from the nucleus accumbens, <lb/>ventral tegmental area and limbic areas to this visual <lb/>system. Similar brain areas were found to be activated in <lb/>fMRI cue reactivity studies of smokers and alcohol-<lb/>dependent persons (George et al. 2001; Due et al. 2002; <lb/>Myrick et al. 2004). Higher activation of the amygdala <lb/>region and parahippocampal gyrus indicates that gam-<lb/>bling pictures activated the emotion/motivation and <lb/>memory-related circuitry more in PRG than in HSM and <lb/>HC. The parahippocampal gyrus is involved in processing <lb/>complex visual information, receives input from the <lb/>nucleus accumbens and amygdala, and is an important <lb/>afferent pathway to the hippocampus. Cue reactivity <lb/>studies of problem gambling, alcohol dependence and <lb/>nicotine dependence have also reported brain activation <lb/>in the parahippocampal gyrus (Crockford et al. 2005; <lb/>Smolka et al. 2006; Park et al. 2007). This study is the <lb/>first to show involvement of the amygdala region in a <lb/>cue-reactivity study in PRG, and to observe that activa-<lb/>tion in brain areas such as insular cortex and caudate <lb/>nucleus is associated with self-reported gambling <lb/>craving. These findings point to the persistent emotional <lb/>relevance of gambling stimuli in patients currently in <lb/>treatment for gambling problems. <lb/>All PRG were being treated for PG when they partici-<lb/>pated in the study, and reported an average duration of <lb/>gambling problems of 13 years (data not shown). The <lb/>two fMRI cue reactivity studies in PG present in the lit-<lb/>erature (Potenza et al. 2003; Crockford et al. 2005) <lb/>focused on community-recruited PRG, and did not report <lb/>amygdala, insular cortex or caudate nucleus activation. <lb/>The findings of this study suggest that cue reactivity in <lb/>chronic PRGs seeking treatment may be related more <lb/>strongly to brain reactivity in emotional and motivational <lb/>circuitries than cue reactivity in (non-chronic) PRGs who <lb/>are not in treatment. <lb/>Table 4 Cue Reactivity Task: correlations between BOLD activations and self-reported craving levels in problem gamblers and heavy <lb/>smokers <lb/>Positive <lb/>correlations <lb/>Regression analyses <lb/>Gambling versus neutral pictures with <lb/>gambling urge in problem gamblers <lb/>Smoking-related versus neutral pictures <lb/>with smoking urge in heavy smokers <lb/>L/R <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>Z value <lb/>L/R <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/>z <lb/>Z value <lb/>VLPFC <lb/>L <lb/>-39 <lb/>45 <lb/>-3 <lb/>4 . 3 2 <lb/>L <lb/>-36 <lb/>6 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.56 <lb/>dACC <lb/>L <lb/>-6 <lb/>2 7 <lb/>3 9 <lb/>3 . 3 1 <lb/>Anterior insula <lb/>L <lb/>-48 <lb/>21 <lb/>-3 <lb/>4.02 <lb/>Amygdala region <lb/>L <lb/>-18 <lb/>3 <lb/>-21 <lb/>3.51 <lb/>Caudate head <lb/>L <lb/>-15 <lb/>15 <lb/>6 <lb/>3.29 <lb/>Group interactions are reported at P &lt; 0.001 unless indicated otherwise. BOLD = blood oxygenation level-dependent; dACC = dorsal anterior cingulate <lb/>cortex; VLPFC = Ventrolateral prefrontal cortex. <lb/></body>

			<page>500 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<body>Differences in brain activation patterns to smoking <lb/>pictures between the FTND-high smokers and HC or <lb/>PRG were most consistently present in VLPFC, VMPFC <lb/>and rostral ACC, conforming with previous fMRI cue <lb/>reactivity studies in smokers (David et al. 2005; Lee et al. <lb/>2005; McClernon et al. 2005, 2008). The lack of an <lb/>effect of cue-reactivity in the FTND-low HSM group com-<lb/>pared with the PRG or the HC group is likely related to the <lb/>lower level of nicotine dependence in this subgroup. It <lb/>has been reported that FTND scores positively correlate <lb/>with regional brain reactivity to smoking cues (Smolka <lb/>et al. 2006; McClernon et al. 2008). Therefore, in future <lb/>studies, the selection of a more homogeneous group of <lb/>smokers, with a minimum score on the FTND or a formal <lb/>DSM-IV ND diagnosis would be advisable. <lb/>In addition to our findings of higher brain activation <lb/>in VMPFC and rostral ACC in the FTND-high smokers <lb/>compared with the other groups, we observed that <lb/>smoking urge in HSM correlated positively with activity <lb/>in brain areas related to emotion and reward/ <lb/>motivational processing (amygdala and VLPFC), areas <lb/>previously implicated in craving for smoking (David et al. <lb/>2005; McClernon et al. 2008). <lb/>Limitations <lb/>Although we observed increased brain activation in <lb/>response to gambling pictures in PRG and to smoking <lb/>cues in the FTND-high HSM group, viewing these pic-<lb/>tures elicited only a trend for higher self-reported craving <lb/>in PRG, whereas in HSM no effects of the cue reactivity <lb/>task on smoking urges were present. Changes in subjec-<lb/>tive craving before and after the task may have been <lb/>limited in our study because of the timing of the mea-<lb/>surement: a paper and pencil craving questionnaire was <lb/>filled out after leaving the scanner, when immediate <lb/>effects of the task on craving may have subsided. In future <lb/>research, computerized craving measures administered <lb/>in the scanner, halfway or immediately after the cue reac-<lb/>tivity task, are therefore preferable. <lb/>After recruiting the HSM group, it became clear that <lb/>FTND scores differed substantially within this group. <lb/>Therefore, post hoc comparisons were made between two <lb/>subgroups of HSM: an FTND-high group and an FTND-<lb/>low group. The differential findings in the FTND-high and <lb/>FTND-low groups imply that it is important to include a <lb/>measure of nicotine dependence severity in cue reactivity <lb/>studies in smokers, in addition to selecting smokers based <lb/>on the number of cigarettes they smoke. The group sizes <lb/>of the FTND subgroups were small (n = 10 and n = 8, <lb/>respectively), and therefore the results regarding these <lb/>subgroups have to be interpreted with caution. Studies in <lb/>larger groups of smokers differing in FTND scores should <lb/>be done to replicate these preliminary findings. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>This study demonstrates that viewing gambling pictures <lb/>(as opposed to neutral pictures) is related to greater brain <lb/>activation in visual processing, emotion-motivation and <lb/>attentional-control brain circuitry in treatment-seeking <lb/>PRG, compared with HC and HSM, and that this activa-<lb/>tion is positively related to gambling urges. These effects <lb/>are consistent with those observed in substance-<lb/>dependent persons (George et al. 2001; Myrick et al. <lb/>2004; Franklin et al. 2007). In the present study, we did <lb/>observe increased brain reactivity to smoking cues in <lb/>persons with FTND scores indicating moderate nicotine <lb/>dependence compared with HC, but did not find differ-<lb/>ences in persons with an FTND score indicating low nico-<lb/>tine dependence. Higher smoking urge in HSM was <lb/>associated with increased activity in reward and <lb/>emotion-related brain areas. Future research needs to <lb/>establish whether the long-term effects of gambling cues <lb/>on brain activation in PRG in treatment are related to <lb/>relapse in problem gambling. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This study was partly funded by a grant from the Nether-<lb/>lands Organization for Health Research and Development <lb/>(#31000056) of the Netherlands Organization for Scien-<lb/>tific Research (NWO) to A.G., D.V., J.O. and W.B, and by a <lb/>New Investigator grant (A.G., Veni grant) from the Dutch <lb/>Scientific Organization (NWO ZonMw, #91676084, <lb/>2007–10). Scanning costs were in part funded by the <lb/>Amsterdam Brain Imaging Platform. A.G., M.R., D.V., J.O. <lb/>and W.B. report no conflict of interests. We thank Jellinek <lb/>Amsterdam for their help in recruitment of problem <lb/>gamblers. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors Contribution <lb/>AG, MR, and DV take responsibility for the integrity of the <lb/>data and the accuracy of the data analysis. All authors <lb/>have had full access to all the data in the study. AG, MR, <lb/>JO, WB, and DV were responsible for the study concept <lb/>and design. MR was responsible for data acquisition. MR, <lb/>AG, and DV were responsible for statistical analysis and <lb/>interpretation of data. AG drafted the manuscript. MR, <lb/>JO, WB and DV provided critical revision of the manu-<lb/>script for important intellectual content. All authors criti-<lb/>cally reviewed content and approved final version for <lb/>publication. Preliminary data of this study were pre-<lb/>sented at the Human Brain Mapping Meeting June <lb/>15–19, 2008, Melbourne, Australia. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Beck AT, Steer RA, Ball R, Ranieri WF (1996) Comparison of <lb/>Beck Depression Inventories-IA and -II in Psychiatric Outpa-<lb/>tients. J Pers Assess 67:588–597. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>501 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Breiter HC, Rosen BR (1999) Functional magnetic resonance <lb/>imaging of brain reward circuitry in the human. Ann N Y <lb/>Acad Sci 877:523–547. <lb/>Brody AL, Mandelkern MA, London ED, Childress AR, Lee GS, <lb/>Bota RG, Ho ML, Saxena S, Baxter LR, Jr, Madsen D, Jarvik ME <lb/>(2002) Brain metabolic changes during cigarette craving. <lb/>Arch Gen Psychiatry 59:1162–1172. <lb/>Bush K, Kivlahan DR, McDonell MB, Fihn SD, Bradley KA <lb/>(1998) The AUDIT alcohol consumption questions (AUDIT-C): <lb/>an effective brief screening test for problem drinking. Ambu-<lb/>latory Care Quality Improvement Project (ACQUIP). Alcohol <lb/>Use Disorders Identification Test. Arch Intern Med 158:1789– <lb/>1795. <lb/>Conners CK, Sparrow MA (1999) Conners Adult ADHD Rating <lb/>Scales (CAARS). New York: Multihealth Systems. <lb/>Cooney NL, Litt MD, Morse PA, Bauer LO, Gaupp L (1997) <lb/>Alcohol cue reactivity, negative-mood reactivity, and relapse <lb/>in treated alcoholic men. J Abnorm Psychol 106:243– <lb/>250. <lb/>Crockford DN, Goodyear B, Edwards J, Quickfall J, el-Guebaly N <lb/>(2005) Cue-induced brain activity in pathological gamblers. <lb/>Biol Psychiatry 58:787–795. <lb/>David SP, Munafo MR, Johansen-Berg H, Smith SM, Rogers RD, <lb/>Matthews PM, Walton RT (2005) Ventral striatum/nucleus <lb/>accumbens activation to smoking-related pictorial cues in <lb/>smokers and nonsmokers: a functional magnetic resonance <lb/>imaging study. Biol Psychiatry 58:488–494. <lb/>de Ruiter MB, Veltman DJ, Goudriaan AE, Oosterlaan J, Sjoerds Z, <lb/>van den Brink W (2009) Response perseveration and ventral <lb/>prefrontal sensitivity to reward and punishment in male <lb/>problem gamblers and smokers. Neuropsychopharmacology <lb/>34:1027–1038. <lb/>Due DL, Huettel SA, Hall WG, Rubin DC (2002) Activation in <lb/>mesolimbic and visuospatial neural circuits elicited by <lb/>smoking cues: evidence from functional magnetic resonance <lb/>imaging. Am J Psychiatry 159:954–960. <lb/>Franklin TR, Wang Z, Wang J, Sciortino N, Harper D, Li Y, <lb/>Ehrman R, Kampman K, O&apos;Brien CP, Detre JA, Childress AR <lb/>(2007) Limbic activation to cigarette smoking cues indepen-<lb/>dent of nicotine withdrawal: a perfusion fMRI study. Neurop-<lb/>sychopharmacology 32:2301–2309. <lb/>George MS, Anton RF, Bloomer C, Teneback C, Drobes DJ, Lorb-<lb/>erbaum JP, Nahas Z, Vincent DJ (2001) Activation of prefron-<lb/>tal cortex and anterior thalamus in alcoholic subjects on <lb/>exposure tot alcohol-specific cues. Arch Gen Psychiatry <lb/>58:345–352. <lb/>Goldstein RZ, Volkow ND (2002) Drug addiction and its under-<lb/>lying neurobiological basis: neuroimaging evidence for the <lb/>involvement of the frontal cortex. Am J Psychiatry 159: <lb/>1642–1652. <lb/>Goudriaan AE, Oosterlaan J, de Beurs E, van Den Brink W <lb/>(2004) Pathological gambling: a comprehensive review of <lb/>biobehavioral findings. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 28:123– <lb/>141. <lb/>Heatherton TF, Kozlowski LT, Frecker RC, Fagerstrom KO (1991) <lb/>The Fagerstrom Test for Nicotine Dependence: a revision <lb/>of the Fagerstrom Tolerance Questionnaire. Br J Addict <lb/>86:1119–1127. <lb/>Hodgins DC, el Guebaly N (2004) Retrospective and prospective <lb/>reports of precipitants to relapse in pathological gambling. J <lb/>Consult Clin Psychol 72:72–80. <lb/>Kalivas PW, Volkow ND (2005) The neural basis of addiction: <lb/>a pathology of motivation and choice. Am J Psychiatry <lb/>162:1403–1413. <lb/>Kilts CD, Gross RE, Ely TD, Drexler KP (2004) The neural corre-<lb/>lates of cue-induced craving in cocaine-dependent women. <lb/>Am J Psychiatry 161:233–241. <lb/>Kilts CD, Schweitzer JB, Quinn CK, Gross RE, Faber TL, Muham-<lb/>mad F, Ely TD, Hoffman JM, Drexler KP (2001) Neural activity <lb/>related to drug craving in cocaine addiction. Arch Gen Psy-<lb/>chiatry 58:334–341. <lb/>Kosten TR, Scanley BE, Tucker KA, Oliveto A, Prince C, <lb/>Sinha R, Potenza MN, Skudlarski P, Wexler BE (2006) Cue-<lb/>induced brain activity changes and relapse in cocaine-<lb/>dependent patients. Neuropsychopharmacology 31:644– <lb/>650. <lb/>Ledgerwood DM, Petry NM (2006) What do we know about <lb/>relapse in pathological gambling? Clin Psychol Rev 26:216– <lb/>228. <lb/>Lee JH, Lim Y, Wiederhold BK, Graham SJ (2005) A functional <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging (FMRI) study of cue-induced <lb/>smoking craving in virtual environments. Appl Psychophysiol <lb/>Biofeedback 30:195–204. <lb/>Lesieur H, Blume SB (1987) The South Oaks Gambling Screen <lb/>(SOGS): a new instrument for the identification of pathologi-<lb/>cal gamblers. Am J Psychiatry 144:1184–1188. <lb/>McBride D, Barrett SP, Kelly JT, Aw A, Dagher A (2006) Effects of <lb/>expectancy and abstinence on the neural response to smoking <lb/>cues in cigarette smokers: an fMRI study. Neuropsychophar-<lb/>macology 31:2728–2738. <lb/>McClernon FJ, Hiott FB, Huettel SA, Rose JE (2005) Abstinence-<lb/>induced changes in self-report craving correlate with <lb/>event-related FMRI responses to smoking cues. Neuropsy-<lb/>chopharmacology 30:1940–1947. <lb/>McClernon FJ, Hutchison KE, Rose JE, Kozink RV (2007) DRD4 <lb/>VNTR polymorphism is associated with transient fMRI-BOLD <lb/>responses to smoking cues. Psychopharmacol (Berl) 194: <lb/>433–441. <lb/>McClernon FJ, Kozink RV, Rose JE (2008) Individual differences <lb/>in nicotine dependence, withdrawal symptoms, and sex <lb/>predict transient fMRI-BOLD responses to smoking cues. Neu-<lb/>ropsychopharmacology 33:2148–2157. <lb/>Marissen MA, Franken IH, Waters AJ, Blanken P, van den <lb/>Brink W, Hendriks VM (2006) Attentional bias predicts <lb/>heroin relapse following treatment. Addiction 101:1306– <lb/>1312. <lb/>Mudo G, Belluardo N, Fuxe K (2007) Nicotinic receptor agonists <lb/>as neuroprotective/neurotrophic drugs. Progress in molecular <lb/>mechanisms. J Neural Transm 114:135–147. <lb/>Myrick H, Anton RF, Li X, Henderson S, Drobes D, Voronin K, <lb/>George MS (2004) Differential brain activity in alcoholics and <lb/>social drinkers to alcohol cues: relationship to craving. Neu-<lb/>ropsychopharmacology 29:393–402. <lb/>Nichols T, Hayasaka S (2003) Controlling the familywise error <lb/>rate in functional neuroimaging: a comparative review. Stat <lb/>Methods Med Res 12:419–446. <lb/>Park MS, Sohn JH, Suk JA, Kim SH, Sohn S, Sparacio R (2007) <lb/>Brain substrates of craving to alcohol cues in subjects with <lb/>alcohol use disorder. Alcohol Alcohol 42:417–422. <lb/>Petry NM (2006) Should the scope of addictive behaviors be <lb/>broadened to include pathological gambling? Addiction 101 <lb/>(Suppl. 1):152–160. <lb/>Petry NM, Kiluk BD (2002) Suicidal ideation and suicide <lb/>attempts in treatment-seeking pathological gamblers. J Nerv <lb/>Ment Dis 190:462–469. <lb/>Potenza MN (2006) Should addictive disorders include non-<lb/>substance-related conditions? Addiction 101 (Suppl. 1):142– <lb/>151. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>502 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Anna E. Goudriaan et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Potenza MN, Fiellin DA, Heninger GR, Rounsaville BJ, Mazure <lb/>CM (2002) Gambling: an addictive behavior with health and <lb/>primary care implications. J Gen Intern Med 17:721–732. <lb/>Potenza MN, Steinberg MA, Skudlarski P, Fulbright RK, Lacadie <lb/>CM, Wilber MK, Rounsaville BJ, Gore JC, Wexler BE (2003) <lb/>Gambling urges in pathological gambling: a functional mag-<lb/>netic resonance imaging study. Arch Gen Psychiatry 60:828– <lb/>836. <lb/>Reuter J, Raedler T, Rose M, Hand I, Glascher J, Buchel C (2005) <lb/>Pathological gambling is linked to reduced activation of the <lb/>mesolimbic reward system. Nat Neurosci 8:147–148. <lb/>Robins L, Cottler L, Bucholz K, Compton W (1998) Diagnostic <lb/>Interview Schedule for DSM-IV (DIS-IV-Revision 11 Sep <lb/>1998). St. Louis, MO: Washington University, School of Medi-<lb/>cine, Department of Psychiatry. <lb/>Smolka MN, Buhler M, Klein S, Zimmermann U, Mann K, Heinz <lb/>A, Braus DF (2006) Severity of nicotine dependence modu-<lb/>lates cue-induced brain activity in regions involved in motor <lb/>preparation and imagery. Psychopharmacol (Berl) 184:577– <lb/>588. <lb/>Stevens J (1996) Applied Multivariate Statistics for the Social <lb/>Sciences, 3rd edn. Mahwah, NJ: Lawrence Erlbaum. <lb/>Sullivan EV (2003) Compromised pontocerebellar and cerebel-<lb/>lothalamocortical systems: speculations on their contribu-<lb/>tions to cognitive and motor impairment in nonamnesic <lb/>alcoholism. Alcohol Clin Exp Res 27:1409–1419. <lb/>Tapert SF, Brown GG, Baratta MV, Brown SA (2004) fMRI BOLD <lb/>response to alcohol stimuli in alcohol dependent young <lb/>women. Addict Behav 29:33–50. <lb/>Tiffany ST, Drobes DJ (1991) The development and initial vali-<lb/>dation of a questionnaire on smoking urges. Br J Addict <lb/>86:1467–1476. <lb/>Welte JW, Barnes G, Wieczorek W, Tidwell MC, Parker J (2001) <lb/>Alcohol and gambling pathology among U.S. adults: preva-<lb/>lence, demographic patterns and comorbidity. J Studies <lb/>Alcohol 62:706–712. <lb/>World Health Organization (1997) Composite International <lb/>Diagnostic Interview—Version 2.L. Geneva: World Health <lb/>Organization. <lb/>Zijlstra F, Veltman DJ, Booij J, van den Brink W, Franken IH <lb/>(2009) Neurobiological substrates of cue-elicited craving and <lb/>anhedonia in recently abstinent opioid-dependent males. <lb/>Drug Alcohol Depend 99:183–192. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Neuroimaging cue reactivity in problem gamblers and smokers <lb/></note>

			<page>503 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">© 2010 The Authors, Addiction Biology © 2010 Society for the Study of Addiction <lb/>Addiction Biology, 15, 491–503 </note>

	</text>
</tei>
