<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>G U I D E L I N E S <lb/>Suspected Anaphylactic Reactions Associated with <lb/>Anaesthesia <lb/>Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/>Membership of the Working Party: N J N Harper, Chairman; T Dixon; P Dugué; D M Edgar; <lb/>A Fay; H C Gooi; R Herriot; P Hopkins; J M Hunter; R Mirakian; R S H Pumphrey; <lb/>S L Seneviratne; A F Walls; P Williams; J A Wildsmith; P Wood. Ex Officio: A S Nasser 1 , <lb/>R K Powell 1 , R Mirakhur 2 , J Soar 3 , Executive Officers, AAGBI <lb/>1 British Society for Allergy and Clinical Immunology <lb/>2 Royal College of Anaesthetists <lb/>3 Resuscitation Council UK <lb/>

			This is a consensus document produced by expert members of a Working Party established by the Association of <lb/>Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland (AAGBI). It updates and replaces previous guidance published in <lb/>2003. <lb/>Summary <lb/>(1) The AAGBI has published guidance on manage-<lb/>ment of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia in 1990, <lb/>1995 and 2003. This 2008 update was necessary to <lb/>disseminate new information. <lb/>(2) Death or permanent disability from anaphylaxis in <lb/>anaesthesia may be avoidable if the reaction is <lb/>recognised early and managed optimally. <lb/>(3) Recognition of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia is <lb/>usually delayed because key features such as hypo-<lb/>tension and bronchospasm more commonly have a <lb/>different cause. <lb/>(4) Initial management of anaphylaxis should follow the <lb/>ABC approach. Adrenaline (epinephrine) is the <lb/>most effective drug in anaphylaxis and should be <lb/>given as early as possible. <lb/>(5) If anaphylaxis is suspected during anaesthesia, it is <lb/>the anaesthetist&apos;s responsibility to ensure the patient <lb/>is referred for investigation. <lb/>(6) Serum mast cell tryptase levels may help the <lb/>retrospective diagnosis of anaphylaxis: appropriate <lb/>blood samples should be sent for analysis. <lb/>(7) Specialist (allergist) knowledge is needed to inter-<lb/>pret investigations for anaesthetic anaphylaxis, <lb/>including sensitivity and specificity of each test <lb/>used. Specialist (anaesthetist) knowledge is needed <lb/>to recognise possible non-allergic causes for the <lb/>&apos;reaction&apos;. Optimal investigation of suspected reac-<lb/>tions is therefore more likely with the collaboration <lb/>of both specialties. <lb/>(8) Details of specialist centres for the investigation of <lb/>suspected anaphylaxis during anaesthesia may be <lb/>found on the AAGBI website http://www.aagbi. <lb/>org. <lb/>(9) Cases of anaphylaxis occurring during anaesthesia <lb/>should be reported to the Medicines Control <lb/>Agency and the AAGBI National Anaesthetic <lb/>Anaphylaxis Database. Reports are more valuable <lb/>if the diagnosis is recorded following specialist <lb/>investigation of the reaction. <lb/>(10) This guidance recommends that all Departments <lb/>of Anaesthesia should identify a Consultant Anaes-<lb/>thetist who is Clinical Lead for anaesthetic <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The AAGBI published its first guidelines on suspected <lb/>anaphylactic reactions in 1990. Subsequent revisions were <lb/>published in 1995 and 2003. The current guidelines <lb/></body>

			<front>Re-use of this article is permitted in accordance with the Creative <lb/>Commons Deed, Attribution 2.5, which does not permit commercial <lb/>exploitation. <lb/> Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>doi:10.1111/j.1365-2044.2008.05733.x <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>199 <lb/></page>

			<body>incorporate advice from a large number of clinical <lb/>immunologists, allergists and anaesthetists throughout <lb/>the UK. In common with the 1995 and the 2003 <lb/>editions, this report is published jointly with the British <lb/>Society for Allergy and Clinical Immunology (BSACI). <lb/>This document is intended to be concordant with, and <lb/>complementary to, the 2007 Scandinavian Clinical <lb/>Practice Guidelines, the 2008 Resuscitation Council <lb/>UK guidelines and the BSACI guidelines: Investigation <lb/>of suspected anaphylaxis during anaesthesia. <lb/>These guidelines apply only to suspected anaphylactic <lb/>reactions associated with anaesthesia and it is presupposed <lb/>that the patient is in the care of a trained anaesthetist. <lb/>Objectives <lb/>(1) To clarify the definitions used in allergy and <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/>(2) To review the epidemiology of anaesthesia-related <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/>(3) To provide advice on the recognition of anaesthetic <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/>(4) To make recommendations on the immediate man-<lb/>agement and initial investigation of suspected anaes-<lb/>thetic anaphylaxis. <lb/>(5) To make recommendations concerning the further <lb/>investigation of suspected anaesthetic anaphylaxis. <lb/>(6) To assist anaesthetists in obtaining access to a <lb/>specialist centre for comprehensive investigation of <lb/>suspected anaesthetic anaphylaxis. <lb/>(7) To assist anaesthetists to provide appropriate infor-<lb/>mation to the specialist centre. <lb/>(8) To make recommendations about the reporting and <lb/>collection of data on anaesthetic anaphylaxis in Great <lb/>Britain and Ireland. <lb/>Definitions <lb/>The term &apos;anaphylaxis&apos; has been used for all types of acute <lb/>life-threatening illness triggered by abnormal sensitivity <lb/>(hypersensitivity) to a trigger agent, and for apparently <lb/>spontaneous attacks with similar features (idiopathic <lb/>anaphylaxis). This has made it difficult to define. The <lb/>EAACI Nomenclature Committee proposed the follow-<lb/>ing broad definition [1]: <lb/>Anaphylaxis is a severe, life-threatening, generalized or <lb/>systemic hypersensitivity reaction. <lb/>Minor, localised or non-systemic reactions are outside <lb/>the definition of anaphylaxis. Anaphylaxis may be divided <lb/>into &apos;allergic anaphylaxis&apos; and &apos;non-allergic anaphylaxis&apos;. <lb/>The clinical features of allergic anaphylaxis and non-<lb/>allergic anaphylaxis may be identical. The EAACI com-<lb/>mittee proposed the term &apos;allergic anaphylaxis&apos; should be <lb/>used only when the reaction is mediated by an immuno-<lb/>logical mechanism (such as IgE, IgG, or complement <lb/>activation by immune complexes). An anaphylactic <lb/>reaction mediated by IgE antibodies, such as to amoxicillin, <lb/>is referred to as &apos;IgE-mediated allergic anaphylaxis&apos;. <lb/>The term &apos;anaphylactoid&apos; reaction had been introduced <lb/>for non-IgE-mediated anaphylactic reactions but the <lb/>EAACI committee has recommended this term should <lb/>no longer be used. This proposal has not been universally <lb/>accepted. An authoritative recent American practice <lb/>parameter [2] states: &apos;Anaphylaxis is defined … as a <lb/>condition caused by an IgE-mediated reaction [2]. <lb/>Anaphylactoid reactions are defined as those reactions <lb/>that produce the same clinical picture as anaphylaxis but <lb/>are not IgE mediated.&apos; In these guidelines we will follow <lb/>the European (EAACI) nomenclature. <lb/>Anaphylaxis is not a homogeneous process: the <lb/>pathways, mediators, time course and response to <lb/>treatment depend on the trigger agent, its route and <lb/>rate of administration, the nature of the patient&apos;s <lb/>hypersensitivity and the state of health of the patient, <lb/>including incidental pathology such as respiratory or <lb/>cardiovascular disease and the effects of concomitant <lb/>medication such as b-blockers and ACE inhibitors. <lb/>Although anaphylaxis commonly involves respiratory, <lb/>cutaneous and circulatory changes, variations such as <lb/>shock with gastrointestinal disturbance or shock alone <lb/>are possible. Alternatively, reactions may be fatal <lb/>without significant shock except as the terminal event <lb/>following respiratory arrest [3]. Angioedema and urti-<lb/>caria may be features of anaphylaxis but commonly <lb/>result from mechanisms other than anaphylaxis. <lb/>Intravascular volume redistribution is an important <lb/>component of anaphylactic shock. Cardiac output may <lb/>be decreased as a result of reduced coronary artery <lb/>perfusion pressure as well as impaired venous return. <lb/>Local release of mediators may cause coronary artery <lb/>spasm and there may be features of acute left or right <lb/>ventricular failure. Myocardial ischaemia with ECG <lb/>changes is expected within minutes of anaphylactic shock <lb/>becoming severe. <lb/>Asphyxia may be due to upper airway occlusion caused <lb/>by angioedema, or bronchospasm with mucus plugging of <lb/>the lower airways; the latter most commonly occurs in <lb/>patients taking daily treatment for asthma. Both these <lb/>processes may occur simultaneously in patients reacting to <lb/>foods, latex, b-lactam antibiotics or aspirin. <lb/>Anaphylaxis usually resolves in 2-8 h but secondary <lb/>pathology arising from the reaction or its treatment may <lb/>prolong this. Resolution is complete except when <lb/>cerebral hypoxia at the peak of the reaction has caused <lb/>significant brain damage, or when disordered clotting <lb/>leads to bleeding. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>200 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The involvement of the British Society for Allergy and <lb/>Clinical Immunology and the Clinical Immunology and <lb/>Allergy section of the British Society for Immunology is <lb/>gratefully acknowledged. In addition, the working party <lb/>wishes to acknowledge the assistance of the following: <lb/>Sr Alex Farragher Specialist Immunology Nurse <lb/>Mr Chris Hirst AAGBI Anaphylaxis website designer <lb/>Dr David Noble <lb/>Dr Martin Shields <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Johansson SGO, Bieber T, Dahl R, et al. Revised nomen-<lb/>clature for allergy for global use: Report of the Nomenclature <lb/>Review Committee of the World Allergy Organization, <lb/>October 2003. Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology 2004; <lb/>113: 832-6. <lb/>2 Joint Task Force on Practice Parameters. The diagnosis and <lb/>management of anaphylaxis: an updated practice parameter. <lb/>Journal of Allergy and Clinical Immunology 2005; 115: S483-523. <lb/>3 Pumphrey RSH. Lessons for management of anaphylaxis <lb/>from a study of fatal reactions. Clinical and Experimental Allergy <lb/>2000; 30: 1144-50. <lb/>Epidemiology <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Geographical variation <lb/>Most reports on anaesthesia-related anaphylaxis originate <lb/>from France, Australia, New Zealand and the United <lb/>Kingdom. Other case series have been described from <lb/>Scandinavia and the USA. The true incidence and their <lb/>associated morbidity and mortality remain poorly defined. <lb/>Both the accuracy and completeness of reporting is not <lb/>optimal. <lb/>10% of anaesthesia-related reactions reported to the UK <lb/>Medicines Control Agency (MCA) were fatal. These data <lb/>should be interpreted with caution because it is likely that <lb/>many less-severe reactions are not reported [1]. Reactions <lb/>that are accepted as side-effects of certain drugs, for <lb/>instance, histaminergic reactions due to atracurium and <lb/>mivacurium, may be under-reported. During a time <lb/>period of over 6 years only 361 reactions were reported <lb/>to the MCA. In a 2-year period 789 reactions were <lb/>reported in France in a comparable population where <lb/>there is a well-established culture of reporting anaesthesia-<lb/>related reactions [2]. <lb/>Based on studies in Australia and France, the incidence <lb/>of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia has been estimated at <lb/>between 1 in 10 000 and 20 000 [3, 4] The true <lb/>incidence of anaphylaxis during anaesthesia in the UK is <lb/>not known. By extrapolating the French and Australian <lb/>data to the UK, it is estimated that there are approxi-<lb/>mately 500 severe reactions in the UK each year. <lb/>Anaphylactic reactions are more common when drugs <lb/>are given intravenously. <lb/>In one large study an immune basis was demonstrated <lb/>in two-thirds of patients investigated for anaphylaxis [2]: <lb/>the remainder comprised non-allergic anaphylaxis and <lb/>mechanisms other than anaphylaxis. The tests currently <lb/>available for the diagnosis of anaesthetic anaphylaxis are <lb/>imperfect. Skin tests and blood tests have limited <lb/>sensitivity and specificity and their positive and negative <lb/>predictive value varies between drugs. <lb/>Patient characteristics (age, sex, ethnicity, <lb/>smoking etc) <lb/>Neuromuscular blocking drugs and latex appear to cause <lb/>anaphylaxis more commonly in female patients. There <lb/>appears to be a connection between smoking and <lb/>antibiotic anaphylaxis, possibly because smokers may <lb/>become sensitised by exposure to repeated courses of <lb/>antibiotics for respiratory tract infections. Individuals with <lb/>a history of atopy, asthma or allergy to some foods appear <lb/>to be at increased risk of latex allergy but not anaphylaxis <lb/>to neuromuscular blocking drugs or antibiotics [2, 5]. <lb/>Anaphylaxis associated with radiographic contrast media <lb/>appears to be associated with atopy [6]. Patients with <lb/>asthma or taking b-blocking drugs may suffer a more <lb/>severe reaction. Some of these reactions may be refractory <lb/>to conventional therapy. <lb/>Possible environmental sensitising agents <lb/>The prevalence of anaphylactic reactions to neuromuscular <lb/>blocking agents (NMBAs) is reported to be at least six times <lb/>more frequent in some countries [7, 8]: it is considerably <lb/>more common in Norway than in Sweden. Quaternary <lb/>ammonium ions (QAI) are proposed to be the allergenic <lb/>epitopes in NMBAs. Common environmental chemicals <lb/>such as toothpastes, washing detergents, shampoos, and <lb/>cough medicines share these allergenic epitopes with the <lb/>NMBAs [8]. Numerous possibilities exist for a predisposed <lb/>individual to become sensitised to QAIs and thus be at risk <lb/>of developing anaphylaxis to NMBAs during anaesthesia. <lb/>In a recent Scandinavian survey, use of certain cough <lb/>medicines was found to be the only significant difference in <lb/>environmental chemical exposure [8]. In Norway, but not <lb/>Sweden, cough syrups containing pholcodine are available <lb/>without prescription. IgE-antibodies to pholcodine were <lb/>seen in 6% of a general population (blood donors) in <lb/>Norway but not in Sweden (0%). <lb/>Muscle relaxants <lb/>Approximately 60% of cases of anaesthesia-related ana-<lb/>phylaxis are thought on the basis of skin tests to be due to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>201 <lb/></page>

			<body>neuromuscular blocking agents. Mivacurium and atra-<lb/>curium are associated with non-allergic anaphylaxis in <lb/>which release of mediators (notably histamine) from mast <lb/>cells exactly imitates allergic anaphylaxis. Cisatracurium, <lb/>although sharing a benzylisoquinolinium structure, is not <lb/>associated with non-allergic anaphylaxis, although several <lb/>cases of allergic anaphylaxis have been reported. It is <lb/>generally accepted that succinylcholine is the NMBA <lb/>most likely to be associated with allergic anaphylaxis, <lb/>although rocuronium has been implicated in a similar <lb/>number of cases in France. <lb/>The prevalence of sensitisation to NMBAs in the <lb/>community is higher than the incidence of reactions <lb/>would suggest. In one study, approaching 10% of the <lb/>general population exhibited skin reactivity to NMBAs, <lb/>an incidence that far exceeds the incidence of anaphy-<lb/>laxis on administration of these drugs during anaesthesia <lb/>[9]. A previous history of specific drug exposure is <lb/>not necessary, particularly for neuromuscular blocking <lb/>drugs. A history of previous exposure is found in fewer <lb/>than 50% of patients who are allergic to neuromuscular <lb/>blocking drugs. Conversely, an uneventful exposure <lb/>may sensitise an individual to subsequent administration <lb/>of the drug. <lb/>Cross-sensitivity between different NMBAs is relatively <lb/>common, probably because they share a quaternary <lb/>ammonium epitope. If anaphylaxis to an NMBA is <lb/>suspected, the patient should undergo skin prick testing <lb/>with all the NMBAs in current use. If a patient demon-<lb/>strates a positive skin prick test (SPT) to an NMBA, the <lb/>patient should be warned against future exposure to all <lb/>NMBAs if possible. If it is mandatory to use an NMBA <lb/>during anaesthesia in the future, it would seem appropriate <lb/>to permit the use of an NMBA which has a negative skin <lb/>test, accepting that a negative skin test does not guarantee <lb/>that anaphylaxis will not occur. <lb/>The apparent excess of cases of anaphylaxis to rocu-<lb/>ronium in some countries should be interpreted with <lb/>caution until much more data have been collected. Large <lb/>sample sizes are needed to estimate the true incidence: if <lb/>the true incidence is 1 in 5000, a sample size of 7 million <lb/>would be needed to have a 95% chance of being within <lb/>5% of the true value [10]. There is a need for further <lb/>epidemiological studies. <lb/>Latex <lb/>Latex hypersensitivity is the second most common cause <lb/>of anaesthesia-related anaphylaxis in many studies (up to <lb/>20% of cases). However, the incidence of anaphylaxis to <lb/>latex is considerably less than would be suggested by the <lb/>prevalence of positive skin tests or positive IgE tests. It <lb/>appears that the incidence may be waning, at least in some <lb/>countries; possibly as a result of a change or decline in the <lb/>use of latex gloves. Certain patient groups are more <lb/>susceptible to latex anaphylaxis (see Appendix II). <lb/>Antibiotics <lb/>Approximately 15% of anaesthesia-related anaphylactic <lb/>episodes are due to antibiotics. This proportion has <lb/>increased in recent years and may merely mirror increased <lb/>exposure to antibiotics in the community [2, 11]. The <lb/>pre-operative history is important. Although only a <lb/>minority of patients who report allergy to antibiotics <lb/>have a true allergy, the consequence of anaphylaxis to <lb/>intravenous antibiotics may be catastrophic, and self-<lb/>reporting should be taken seriously. Skin testing is only <lb/>approximately 60% predictive of clinical hypersensitivity. <lb/>Penicillins and cephalosporins which share the b-lactam <lb/>ring are responsible for approximately 70% of antibiotic-<lb/>induced anaphylaxis. Many antibiotics possess a b-lactam <lb/>ring: <lb/>• Benzylpenicillin, phenoxymethylpenicillin <lb/>• Flucloxacillin, temocillin <lb/>• Amoxicillin, ampicillin, co-amoxiclav <lb/>• Co-fluampicil <lb/>• Piperacillin, ticarcillin, <lb/>• Pivmecillinam HCl <lb/>• Cephalosporins <lb/>• Aztreonam <lb/>• Ertapenem, imipenem with cilastatin, meropenem <lb/>The structure of the side chains attached to the <lb/>b-lactam ring is also important in determining the <lb/>response of the immune system. First generation ceph-<lb/>alosporins and cefamandole share a similar side chain with <lb/>penicillin and amoxicillin. A recent meta-analysis sug-<lb/>gested that patients who are allergic to penicillin or <lb/>amoxicillin have a higher incidence of allergic reactions to <lb/>first generation cephalosporins and cefamandole, but not <lb/>other cephalosporins [12]. The issue is complicated <lb/>because the classification of cephalosporins relates to <lb/>their antimicrobial activity rather than their chemical <lb/>structure. <lb/>First generation cephalosporins <lb/>• Cefalexin (cephalexin)* <lb/>• Cephaloridine <lb/>• Cephalothin <lb/>• Cefazolin <lb/>• Cefradine (cephradine)* <lb/>• Cefadroxil * <lb/>Second generation cephalosporins <lb/>• Cefaclor* <lb/>• Cefamandole <lb/>• Cefuroxime* <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>202 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<body>Third generation cephalosporins <lb/>• Cefixime* <lb/>• Cefotaxime* <lb/>• Cefpodoxime* <lb/>• Ceftazidime* <lb/>• Ceftriaxone* <lb/>Fourth generation cephalosporins <lb/>• Cefepime <lb/>• Cefpirome <lb/>*Listed in the British National Formulary. <lb/>Local anaesthetics <lb/>Anaphylactic reactions to local anaesthetic drugs are very <lb/>uncommon. Local anaesthetic esters are more likely than <lb/>amides to provoke a Type lV allergic reaction. Preserva-<lb/>tives such as methyl-paraben or metabisulphites may be <lb/>responsible in some cases. It has been suggested that <lb/>inadvertent intravascular injection of a local anaesthetic or <lb/>the systemic absorption of adrenaline may be responsible <lb/>for many of the reported reactions. Reactions occurring <lb/>in the dental chair may also be associated with idiopathic <lb/>angioedema or latex allergy. <lb/>Opioids <lb/>Opioids are an uncommon cause of anaesthesia-related <lb/>anaphylaxis. Diagnosis is difficult and the true incidence is <lb/>unknown. Morphine, pethidine and codeine are well-<lb/>known to cause non-specific histamine release which <lb/>precludes diagnostic skin testing. The diagnosis of opioid <lb/>anaphylaxis often rests on a careful history and the <lb/>exclusion of other possibilities. Challenge testing may be <lb/>appropriate in some cases but may be performed only in <lb/>specialist centres. <lb/>Anaesthetic induction agents <lb/>Anaphylaxis to propofol is very uncommon. The antigenic <lb/>determinant may be the isopropyl groups. It has been stated <lb/>that patients with egg allergy or soy allergy should avoid <lb/>propofol but there is no strongly-supportive evidence. It <lb/>has been suggested that propofol anaphylaxis is more likely <lb/>if lignocaine is added to reduce pain on injection: there is <lb/>no evidence to support this suggestion. Anaphylaxis to <lb/>thiopental has become extremely uncommon, probably <lb/>reflecting the decline in its use. A small number of cases of <lb/>midazolam anaphylaxis have been reported. <lb/>Non-steroidal anti-inflammatory drugs (NSAIDs) <lb/>Several mechanisms may be responsible for reactions <lb/>to NSAIDs. Inhibition of the PGE 2 pathway leads to <lb/>excessive leukotriene synthesis and subsequent mediator <lb/>release, causing urticaria or bronchospasm. IgE-mediated <lb/>reactions may also occur in relation to some NSAIDs. <lb/>Fatal anaphylaxis has been described after oral adminis-<lb/>tration of NSAIDs. <lb/>Halogenated volatile anaesthetics <lb/>There are no published reports of anaphylaxis to <lb/>halogenated volatile anaesthetics. The rare fulminant <lb/>form of hepatitis associated with halothane has an <lb/>immune basis which is unrelated to anaphylaxis. <lb/>Colloids <lb/>Intravenous colloids are responsible for approximately 4% <lb/>of all peri-operative anaphylactic reactions. In one study, <lb/>gelatin solutions were responsible for 95% of the intra-<lb/>venous colloid reactions. It has been stated that the <lb/>incidence may be greater with the urea-linked gelatins <lb/>compared with the modified fluid gelatins. Intravenous <lb/>gelatin solutions should be avoided in patients with a <lb/>history of allergy to gelatin-containing vaccines. Ana-<lb/>phylaxis to intravenous dextrans has been reported, with <lb/>an incidence similar to the modified fluid gelatins. <lb/>Anaphylaxis to hydroxyethyl-starch is rare. <lb/>Antiseptics and disinfectants <lb/>Reactions to chlorhexidine have come into greater <lb/>prominence in recent years. There appears to be a <lb/>significant difference in incidence between countries [13]. <lb/>Reactions range from contact dermatitis to life-threaten-<lb/>ing anaphylaxis. Anaphylaxis has occurred when chlor-<lb/>hexidine was used as an antiseptic for urological and <lb/>gynaecological procedures as well as insertion of central <lb/>venous and epidural catheters. The chlorhexidine coating <lb/>of certain central venous catheters has been implicated in <lb/>such reactions. It is prudent to allow skin disinfectant to <lb/>completely dry before beginning an invasive procedure. <lb/>Anaphylaxis to polyvinylpyrrholidine as povidone-iodine <lb/>or as an excipient for oral medicines occurs but is rare. <lb/>Miscellaneous agents <lb/>Many agents to which patients may be exposed during <lb/>anaesthesia may be associated with anaphylaxis, including <lb/>aprotinin, protamine, heparins, radiological contrast <lb/>material, dyes and oxytocin. Anaphylaxis to glycopyrro-<lb/>nium and neostigmine may occur very rarely. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Axon AD, Hunter JM. Editorial III: Anaphylaxis and <lb/>anaesthesia -all clear now? British Journal of Anaesthesia 2004; <lb/>93: 501-4. <lb/>2 Mertes PM, Laxenaire MC, Alla F. Anaphylactic anaphy-<lb/>lactoid reactions occurring during anaesthesia in France in <lb/>1999-2000. Anesthesiology 2003; 99: 536-45. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>203 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>3 Fisher MM, Baldo BA. The incidence and clinical features <lb/>of anaphylactic reactions during anesthesia in Australia. <lb/>Annales Francaises d&apos;Anesthesie et de Reanimation 1993; 12: <lb/>97-104. <lb/>4 Laxenaire MC. Epidemiology of anesthetic anaphylactoid <lb/>reactions. Fourth multicenter survey (July 1994-December <lb/>1996). Annales Francaises d&apos;Anesthesie et de Reanimation 1999; <lb/>18: 796-809. <lb/>5 Laxenaire MC, Mertes PM. Anaphylaxis during anaesthesia. <lb/>Results of a two-year survey in France. British Journal of <lb/>Anaesthesia 2001; 87: 549-58. <lb/>6 Lang DM, Alpern MB, Visintainer PF, Smith ST. Increased <lb/>risk for anaphylactoid reaction from contrast media in <lb/>patients on beta-adrenergic blockers or with asthma. <lb/>Annals of Internal Medicine 1991; 115: 270-6. <lb/>7 Laake JH, Rottingen JA. Rocuronium and anaphylaxis -<lb/>a statistical challenge. Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandinavica <lb/>2001; 45: 1196-203. <lb/>8 Florvaag E, Johansson SG, Oman H, et al. Prevalence of <lb/>IgE antibodies to morphine. Relation to the high and low <lb/>incidences of NMBA anaphylaxis in Norway and Sweden, <lb/>respectively. Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandinavica 2005; 49: <lb/>437-44. <lb/>9 Porri F, Lemiere C, Birnbaum J, et al. Prevalence of <lb/>muscle relaxant sensitivity in a general population: <lb/>implications for a preoperative screening. Clinical and <lb/>Experimental Allergy 1999; 29: 72-5. <lb/>10 Fisher M, Baldo BA. Anaphylaxis during anaesthesia: current <lb/>aspects of diagnosis and prevention. European Journal of <lb/>Anaesthesiology 1994; 11: 263-84. <lb/>11 Moss J. Allergy to anesthetics. Anesthesiology 2003; 99: 521-3. <lb/>12 Pichichero ME, Casey JR. Safe use of selected cephalo-<lb/>sporins in penicillin-allergic patients: a meta-analysis. <lb/>Otolaryngology-Head and Neck Surgery 2007; 136: 340-7. <lb/>13 Garvey LH, Roed-Petersen J, Menne T, Husum B. <lb/>Danish Anaesthesia Allergy Centre -preliminary results. <lb/>Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandinavica 2001; 45: 1204-9. <lb/>Recognition and clinical diagnosis of anaphylaxis <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>In a closely monitored patient such as during anaesthesia, <lb/>when a fall in blood pressure, change in heart rate or <lb/>difficulty with ventilation are noticed, anaphylaxis is so <lb/>rarely the cause that inevitably treatment is given for <lb/>another diagnosis before anaphylaxis is recognised; the <lb/>response to this treatment has commonly delayed or even <lb/>prevented recognition of the true cause. It is therefore <lb/>probable that many grade I and II acute allergic reactions <lb/>to anaesthetic drugs are missed. Conversely, a cause other <lb/>than allergic anaphylaxis seems more likely in around <lb/>one-third of the patients referred to specialist centres for <lb/>investigation of suspected anaphylaxis during anaesthesia. <lb/>Previous history <lb/>Any clue that appropriately raises anticipation of anaphy-<lb/>laxis will be helpful. A previous history of reaction to <lb/>anaesthetic drugs, antibiotics, other drugs, chlorhexidine <lb/>or latex should obviously lead to appropriate avoidance. <lb/>Because it is always possible the wrong trigger factor <lb/>was identified, the exact details of exposure leading to <lb/>any previous reaction should be sought during the <lb/>pre-operative assessment. Cross-reactivity between non-<lb/>anaesthetic drugs such as pholcodine or environmental <lb/>chemicals containing quaternary ammonium groups such <lb/>as cosmetics and detergents has been proposed as the <lb/>source of sensitivity to opioids and muscle relaxants: a <lb/>history of cutaneous sensitivity to cosmetics or rashes <lb/>from cough medicines should raise caution. <lb/>Anaphylaxis to amoxicillin and cephalosporins is <lb/>commonest in asthmatic smokers who have had <lb/>multiple courses of these antibiotics without reacting: <lb/>the symptoms of anaphylaxis in such a patient are likely <lb/>to be initially misinterpreted (quite reasonably) as those <lb/>expected from anaesthesia in an asthmatic smoker. <lb/>Clinical features <lb/>Although anaesthesia-related anaphylaxis usually results <lb/>from intravenous drug administration, administration by <lb/>other routes, for example cutaneous, mucosal ⁄ vesical <lb/>peritoneal, intra-articular or intramuscular may be respon-<lb/>sible. Clinical features include hypotension, tachycardia or <lb/>bradycardia; cutaneous flushing, rash or urticaria; bron-<lb/>chospasm; hypoxia; angioedema and cardiac arrest. If an <lb/>adverse event such as hypotension or bronchospasm occurs <lb/>during anaesthesia it is appropriate to suspect anaphylaxis <lb/>unless there exists a significantly more likely cause. <lb/>Tachycardia is not invariable: bradycardia is seen in <lb/>approximately 10% of patients with allergic anaphylaxis <lb/>during anaesthesia. Hypotension is the sole clinical feature <lb/>in approximately 10% of patients and is likely to be <lb/>exaggerated in patients undergoing anaesthesia with neur-<lb/>axial blockade. Widespread flushing or urticaria is seen in <lb/>the majority of patients but the absence of cutaneous signs <lb/>does not exclude anaphylaxis. Bronchospasm may be more <lb/>common in patients with pre-existing asthma. <lb/>Clinical features <lb/>Allergic <lb/>anaphylaxis <lb/>(n = 518), n (%) <lb/>Non-allergic <lb/>anaphylaxis <lb/>(n = 271), n (%) <lb/>Cardiovascular <lb/>387 (74.7) <lb/>92 (33.9) <lb/>Arterial hypotension <lb/>90 (17.3) <lb/>50 (18.4) <lb/>Cardiovascular collapse <lb/>264 (50.8) <lb/>30 (11.1) <lb/>Bradycardia <lb/>7 (1.3) <lb/>2 (0.7) <lb/>Cardiac arrest <lb/>31 (5.9) <lb/>-<lb/>Bronchospasm <lb/>207 (39.8) <lb/>52 (19.2) <lb/>Cutaneous signs <lb/>374 (71.9) <lb/>254 (93.7) <lb/>Angioedema <lb/>64 (12.3) <lb/>21 (7.7) <lb/>Clinical features of allergic anaphylaxis and non-allergic anaphylaxis <lb/>occurring during anaesthesia in France between 1st Jan 1999 and 31st <lb/>Dec 2000. Mertes PM et al. Anesthesiology 2003; 99: 536-45. <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>204 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<body>The clinical features usually occur within a few minutes <lb/>but may be delayed by up to an hour. Substances to which the <lb/>clinical reaction may be delayed include latex, antibiotics, <lb/>intravenous colloids and Cidex OPA (used to disinfect <lb/>surgical instruments). However, an immediate response does <lb/>not exonerate these substances. The clinical features of <lb/>anaphylaxis to neuromuscular blocking agents usually <lb/>develop rapidly. Deflation of a surgical tourniquet may <lb/>induce anaphylaxis if the allergen has been sequestered in the <lb/>limb. <lb/>Immediate management <lb/>These management guidelines presuppose that the patient is in <lb/>the care of an appropriately-trained anaesthetist and full <lb/>resuscitation facilities and appropriate vital signs monitors are <lb/>available. <lb/>There is a wide spectrum of severity and combinations <lb/>of clinical features. Although management should be <lb/>tailored to the individual patient, there is consensus that <lb/>adrenaline should be given as early as possible. In addition <lb/>to having alpha-agonist activity, adrenaline is a valuable <lb/>beta-agonist which is inotropic and a bronchodilator, and <lb/>reduces further mediator release. <lb/>Other causes of hypotension or difficulty in ventilation <lb/>should be excluded, for example a misplaced tracheal tube <lb/>or equipment failure. <lb/>Immediate management <lb/>1 Use the ABC approach (Airway, Breathing, Circu-<lb/>lation). Team-working enables several tasks to be <lb/>accomplished simultaneously. <lb/>2 Remove all potential causative agents (including IV <lb/>colloids, latex and chlorhexidine) and maintain anaes-<lb/>thesia, if necessary, with an inhalational agent. <lb/>3 Call for help and note the time. <lb/>4 Maintain the airway and administer oxygen 100%. <lb/>Intubate the trachea if necessary and ventilate the lungs <lb/>with oxygen. <lb/>5 Elevate the patient&apos;s legs if there is hypotension. <lb/>6 If appropriate, start cardiopulmonary resuscitation <lb/>immediately according to Advanced Life Support <lb/>Guidelines. <lb/>7 Administer adrenaline intravenously. An initial dose of <lb/>50 lg (0.5 ml of 1 : 10 000 solution) is appropriate <lb/>(adult dose). Several doses may be required if there is <lb/>severe hypotension or bronchospasm. <lb/>8 If several doses of adrenaline are required, consider <lb/>starting an intravenous infusion of adrenaline (adren-<lb/>aline has a short half-life). <lb/>9 Administer saline 0.9% or lactated Ringer&apos;s solution at <lb/>a high rate via an intravenous cannula of an appropriate <lb/>gauge (large volumes may be required). <lb/>Secondary management <lb/>1 Administer chlorphenamine 10 mg IV (adult dose). <lb/>2 Administer hydrocortisone 200 mg IV (adult dose). <lb/>3 If the blood pressure does not recover despite an <lb/>adrenaline infusion, consider the administration of an <lb/>alternative intravenous vasopressor according to the <lb/>training and experience of the anaesthetist, for example <lb/>metaraminol. <lb/>4 Treat persistent bronchospasm with an intravenous <lb/>infusion of salbutamol. If a suitable breathing-system <lb/>connector is available, a metered-dose inhaler may be <lb/>appropriate. Consider giving intravenous aminophyl-<lb/>line or magnesium sulphate. <lb/>5 Arrange transfer of the patient to an appropriate Critical <lb/>Care area. <lb/>6 Take blood samples (5-10 ml clotted blood) for Mast <lb/>Cell Tryptase as follows: <lb/>a Initial sample as soon as feasible after resuscitation has <lb/>started -do not delay resuscitation to take the sample. <lb/>b Second sample at 1-2 h after the start of symptoms. <lb/>c Third sample either at 24 h or in convalescence (for <lb/>example in a follow-up allergy clinic). This is a <lb/>measure of baseline tryptase levels as some individuals <lb/>have a higher baseline level. <lb/>d Ensure that the samples are labelled with the time <lb/>and date. <lb/>7 Liaise with the hospital laboratory (see Appendix lll: <lb/>Mast cell Tryptase). <lb/>Drug doses in children <lb/>Adrenaline <lb/>Intramuscular <lb/>&gt; 12 years: 500 lg IM (0.5 ml of a 1 : 1000 solution) <lb/>300 lg IM (0.3 ml of a 1 : 1000 solution) if the child is <lb/>small <lb/>6-12 years: 300 lg IM (0.3 ml of a 1 : 1000 solution) <lb/>Up to 6 years: 150 lg IM (0.15 ml of a 1 : 1000 <lb/>solution) <lb/>Intravenous <lb/>Intravenous adrenaline may be used in children in acute <lb/>areas such as operating theatres or intensive care units by <lb/>those familiar with its use and if IV access is already <lb/>available. Great care should be taken to avoid dose errors <lb/>when preparing drug dilutions. Prepare a syringe con-<lb/>taining 1 ml of 1 : 10 000 adrenaline for each 10 kg body <lb/>weight (0.1 ml.kg )1 of 1 : 10 000 adrenaline solution = <lb/>10 lg.kg )1 . Titrate to response, starting with a dose of <lb/>one-tenth of the contents of the syringe, i.e. 1 lg.kg )1 . <lb/>Often a child will respond to as little as 1 lg.kg )1 . In <lb/>smaller children, further dilution may be needed to allow <lb/>dose titration (check carefully for decimal point and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>205 <lb/></page>

			<body>concentration errors). The intramuscular route is pre-<lb/>ferred where there is no venous access or where <lb/>establishing venous access would cause a delay in drug <lb/>administration. <lb/>Hydrocortisone <lb/>&gt; 12 years: 200 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>6 to 12 years: 100 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>6 months to 6 years: 50 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>&lt; 6 months: 25 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>Chlorphenamine <lb/>&gt; 12 years: 10 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>6 to 12 years: 5 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>6 months to 6 years: 2.5 mg IM or IV slowly <lb/>&lt; 6 months: 250 lg.kg )1 IM or IV slowly <lb/>Later investigations to identify the causative <lb/>agent <lb/>Any patient who has a suspected anaphylactic reaction <lb/>associated with anaesthesia should be investigated fully, <lb/>but investigations should not interfere with the immediate <lb/>treatment of the patient. The anaesthetist who adminis-<lb/>tered the anaesthetic or the consultant anaesthetist in <lb/>charge of the patient is responsible for ensuring that the <lb/>reaction is investigated. <lb/>The patient should be referred to a specialist Allergy or <lb/>Immunology centre that has appropriate experience of <lb/>investigating this type of problem. Anaesthetic departments <lb/>should identify a lead anaesthetist for anaesthetic anaphylaxis. <lb/>Referral pathways should be agreed prospectively with the <lb/>appropriate specialist centre. <lb/>Criteria for referral to a specialist centre <lb/>for investigation <lb/>Patients in whom allergic or non-allergic anaphylaxis is <lb/>suspected should be referred to a specialist clinic for <lb/>investigation. A patient should be referred if there is any <lb/>of the following: <lb/>1 Unexplained cardiac arrest during anaesthesia. <lb/>2 Unexplained, unexpected hypotension (for example <lb/>a decrease of mean arterial pressure of more than <lb/>30 mmHg) which requires active treatment. <lb/>3 Unexplained, unexpected bronchospasm, particularly if <lb/>the bronchospasm is severe, causes a significant decrease <lb/>in oxygen saturation and is relatively resistant to <lb/>treatment. <lb/>4 Widespread rash, flushing or urticaria. <lb/>5 Angioedema. <lb/>A detailed analysis of events surrounding the suspected <lb/>anaphylactic reaction must be undertaken. The time of <lb/>onset of the reaction in relation to induction and other <lb/>events is the most important information. All drugs and <lb/>other agents to which the patient was exposed before and <lb/>during the anaesthetic as well as their timing in relation to <lb/>the reaction must be recorded. <lb/>Details sent to the specialist centre along with a letter of <lb/>referral must include: <lb/>• A legible photocopy of the anaesthetic record <lb/>• A legible photocopy of the recovery room chart <lb/>• Legible photocopies of drug charts <lb/>• A description of the reaction and time of onset in <lb/>relation to induction <lb/>• Details of blood tests sent and their timing in relation to <lb/>the reaction <lb/>• Contact details of the surgeon and the general practi-<lb/>tioner <lb/>A standard referral proforma is useful (see Appendix S1 in <lb/>Supporting Information). <lb/>Tests performed at the specialist centre <lb/>Skin tests <lb/>Patients should be referred for skin testing as soon as <lb/>possible after the clinical event. Skin testing can be <lb/>performed as soon as the patient has made a full clinical <lb/>recovery and the effects of any antihistamine given to <lb/>treat the reaction have fully worn off. Skin tests can <lb/>provide confirmation of sensitisation to a specific drug but <lb/>must be interpreted within the clinical context. There are <lb/>a variety of techniques and several different criteria are <lb/>used for positivity [1-4] so skin testing must be performed <lb/>by suitably trained and experienced personnel. <lb/>A histamine solution and physiological saline are used <lb/>as positive and negative controls respectively. Drugs with <lb/>anti-histamine activity must be discontinued a few days <lb/>before testing. There is no need to discontinue oral or <lb/>inhaled steroids. <lb/>Skin prick tests are usually done on the volar surface of <lb/>the forearm. A drop of the drug is placed on the skin and <lb/>the skin pricked through the drop with a lancet. The <lb/>results are read after 15-20 min. <lb/>Intradermal tests may be performed where skin prick <lb/>tests are negative. Although they are more sensitive, they <lb/>are less specific, more difficult to interpret and more likely <lb/>to precipitate a systemic reaction. Intradermal tests are <lb/>usually performed on the forearm or back. 0.02 to <lb/>0.05 ml of a dilute solution is injected intradermally and <lb/>the results read after 20-30 min. <lb/>Both skin prick tests and intradermal tests are widely <lb/>used in the diagnosis of IgE mediated allergic reactions <lb/>though the diagnostic value of a positive test for most <lb/>drugs is limited due to lack of subsequent challenge data. <lb/>If the mechanism is unknown a negative test is unreliable. <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>206 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<body>All drugs used during anaesthesia may be tested and <lb/>lists of non-irritant dilutions have been compiled for <lb/>both skin prick tests and intradermal tests [5]. Skin tests <lb/>are most useful for latex, beta lactam antibiotics and <lb/>NMBAs. They are also useful for induction agents, <lb/>protamine [6] and chlorhexidine. Intradermal testing <lb/>may be more reliable for propofol [2]. Skin tests are not <lb/>usually performed for opioids because false positive <lb/>results are common. However, skin prick testing appears <lb/>to be informative for the synthetic opioids fentanyl and <lb/>remifentanil. Skin tests are not useful for NSAIDs, <lb/>dextrans or iodinated radiological contrast media [6] <lb/>because anaphylaxis to these agents is not usually <lb/>IgE-mediated. <lb/>Patch tests are the mainstay of diagnosis for contact <lb/>allergic reactions and may be useful for diagnosing <lb/>exanthematous drug rashes but are not helpful in eliciting <lb/>the cause of suspected anaphylactic reactions occurring <lb/>during anaesthesia. <lb/>References <lb/>1 Pepys J, Pepys EO, Baldo BA, Whitwam JG. Anaphylac-<lb/>tic ⁄ anaphylactoid reactions to anaesthetic and associated <lb/>agents. Anaesthesia 1994; 49: 470-5. <lb/>2 Fisher MMcD, Bowey CJ. Intradermal compared with <lb/>prick testing in the diagnosis of anaesthetic allergy. British <lb/>Journal of Anaesthesia 1997; 79: 59-63. <lb/>3 Berg CM, Heier T, Wilhelmsen V, Florvaag E. Rocuronium <lb/>and cisatracurium-positive skin tests in non allergic volun-<lb/>teers: determination of drug concentration thresholds using <lb/>a dilution titration technique. Acta Anaesthesiologica Scandi-<lb/>navica 2003; 47: 576-82. <lb/>4 Leynadier F, Sansarricq M, Didier JM, Dry J. Prick tests in <lb/>the diagnosis of anaphylaxis to general anaesthetics. British <lb/>Journal of Anaesthesia 1987; 59: 683-9. <lb/>5 Prevention of allergic risk in Anaethesia. Societe Francaise <lb/>d&apos;Anesthesie et de Reanimation, 2001. http://www.sfar.org/ <lb/>allergiefr.html [accessed 8 October 2008]. <lb/>6 Fisher M, Baldo BA. Anaphylaxis during anaesthesia: current <lb/>aspects of diagnosis and prevention. European Journal of <lb/>Anaesthesiology 1994; 11: 263-84. <lb/>Blood tests <lb/>Appropriate further blood investigations depend on the <lb/>drug in question, and the experience of the specialised <lb/>laboratory service. Blood samples for specific IgE tests <lb/>may be taken at the time of the reaction, or soon <lb/>afterwards during that hospital admission. If the results are <lb/>negative these tests should be repeated when the patient is <lb/>seen at the specialist centre in case the initial results might <lb/>be falsely negative due to possible consumption of <lb/>relevant IgE antibodies during the reaction. The most <lb/>commonly used test for allergen-specific IgE uses target <lb/>allergen or drug bound onto a three-dimensional sponge-<lb/>like solid matrix or &apos;CAP&apos; and a fluorescent detection <lb/>system. The Radio-AllergoSorbent Test (RAST) uses a <lb/>radioactive detection system: it is now rarely used but the <lb/>name has persisted in common use. <lb/>Specific IgE antibodies against succinylcholine (thio-<lb/>choline ester) can be assayed in serum but the sensitivity is <lb/>relatively poor (30-60%). Tests for serum IgE antibodies <lb/>against other neuromuscular blocking drugs are not <lb/>available in the UK. Specific IgE antibodies against <lb/>several antibiotics can be assayed. These include amox-<lb/>icilloyl, ampicilloyl, penicilloyl G, penicilloyl V and <lb/>cefaclor, however the diagnostic value of these tests is less <lb/>well defined. Tests for specific antibodies against latex, <lb/>chlorhexidine and bovine gelatin are available. <lb/>The presence of drug-specific IgE in serum is evidence <lb/>of allergic sensitisation in that individual and provides a <lb/>possible explanation of the mechanism and specific drug <lb/>responsible for the reaction. It is not in itself proof that <lb/>the drug is responsible for the reaction. It is important <lb/>to emphasise that attribution of cause and effect is a <lb/>judgement made after considering all the clinical and <lb/>laboratory information relevant to the reaction. <lb/>Experimental tests <lb/>There is much research into ways of improving the in <lb/>vitro elucidation of anaphylaxis. In addition to tissue-<lb/>bound mast cells, circulating basophils are also involved in <lb/>anaphylaxis. During anaphylaxis, proteins such as CD63 <lb/>and CD203c become newly or increasingly expressed on <lb/>the surface of basophils. These can be detected by flow <lb/>cytometry which forms the basis of experimental drug-<lb/>induced basophil stimulation tests. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Appendix I <lb/>Frequently asked questions <lb/>Should I give a test dose of IV antibiotic? <lb/>No. Predictive testing would require serial challenges with <lb/>increasing doses, starting with a minuscule dose and allow-<lb/>ing at least 30 min between each dose. This approach is <lb/>impossible within the constraints of an operating list. <lb/>Should I avoid cephalosporins in a patient who gives a history <lb/>suggestive of penicillin allergy? <lb/>Most patients who give a history of a penicillin-related rash <lb/>are not allergic to cephalosporins. However, there are now <lb/>many suitable alternatives to cephalosporins and, unless <lb/>there are compelling bacteriological indications, it would <lb/>be appropriate to consider avoiding first and second <lb/>generation cephalosporins. If there is a convincing history <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>207 <lb/></page>

			<body>of penicillin-related anaphylaxis, the case for avoiding first <lb/>and second generation cephalosporins is stronger. <lb/>Should I use crystalloid or colloid in the immediate management <lb/>of anaphylaxis? <lb/>There is no evidence that one is better than the other. <lb/>If an IV colloid has already been given to the patient <lb/>before the appearance of clinical signs of anaphylaxis, it <lb/>should be discontinued and either replaced by crystal-<lb/>loid or replaced by a colloid of a different class; e.g. <lb/>replace a gelatin-based colloid with a starch-based <lb/>colloid. <lb/>Should I give an H2-blocking drug as part of the immediate <lb/>management of anaphylaxis? <lb/>There is no evidence to support the use of H2-blocking <lb/>drugs in this situation. <lb/>What should I do if a patient with a convincing history of cardio-<lb/>respiratory collapse during a previous anaesthetic presents for <lb/>emergency surgery without having been investigated for <lb/>anaphylaxis? <lb/>1 Covert cardiac or respiratory disease should be <lb/>sought in accordance with normal pre-operative <lb/>practice. <lb/>2 It may be possible to exclude latex allergy by taking a <lb/>detailed history from the patient. If this is impossible, a <lb/>latex-free environment should be provided. <lb/>3 Inhalational agents are likely to be safe unless the <lb/>previous collapse was due to malignant hyperthermia. <lb/>4 If previous records are available: <lb/>a It would be appropriate to avoid all drugs given <lb/>during the previous anaesthetic before the onset of <lb/>cardio-respiratory collapse, with the exception of <lb/>inhalational agents. <lb/>b If the patient received a neuromuscular blocking <lb/>drug before the collapse, then all neuromuscular <lb/>blocking drugs should be avoided if possible because <lb/>cross-sensitivity is common. <lb/>5 If previous records are not available: <lb/>a It would be appropriate to avoid all neuromuscular <lb/>blocking drugs if possible (the anaesthetist will need <lb/>to assess the balance of risks). <lb/>b Drugs used in local and regional anaesthesia are likely <lb/>to be safe; allergy to amide local anaesthetic drugs is <lb/>extremely rare. <lb/>c It would be appropriate to avoid chlorhexidine <lb/>preparations if possible; allergy to povidone iodine is <lb/>less common than allergy to chlorhexidine. <lb/>d The previous reaction may have been the result of <lb/>non-allergic anaphylaxis; it would be appropriate to <lb/>avoid drugs that are known to release histamine, for <lb/>example morphine. <lb/>6 There is no evidence that pre-treatment with hydro-<lb/>cortisone or histamine-blocking drugs will reduce the <lb/>severity of anaphylaxis. <lb/>What should I say to a patient who wishes to be screened for <lb/>anaesthetic allergy pre-operatively? <lb/>Unless there is a history suggestive of previous anaesthetic <lb/>anaphylaxis, pre-operative screening is of no value. The <lb/>sensitivity and specificity of skin tests and blood tests is <lb/>relatively low. If the pretest probability is very low, i.e. <lb/>there is no positive history, neither a negative test nor a <lb/>positive test is likely to be predictive of outcome. <lb/>Should I avoid propofol in patients who are allergic to eggs, soya or <lb/>nuts? <lb/>There is no published evidence indicating that propofol <lb/>should be avoided in patients who are allergic to eggs, <lb/>soya or nuts. Propofol contains purified egg phosphatide <lb/>and soya-bean oil. It is likely that the manufacturing <lb/>process removes or denatures the proteins responsible for <lb/>egg allergy and soya allergy. However, a cautious <lb/>approach would seem to be appropriate in patients with <lb/>egg allergy or soya allergy. <lb/>I don&apos;t have a specialist allergy centre nearby. Should I do my <lb/>own skin-testing? <lb/>The results of skin tests are very technique-dependent and <lb/>their interpretation requires specialist training and expe-<lb/>rience. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Appendix II <lb/>Latex allergy <lb/>Latex is a natural rubber derived from the sap of a tree <lb/>(Hevea brasiliensis) found in Asia which contains several <lb/>water-soluble proteins, designated Hev b 1-Hev b 13. <lb/>Patient contact with natural rubber latex (NRL) during <lb/>anaesthesia may occur via several routes including the <lb/>airway, mucous membranes, surgical wounds and par-<lb/>enteral injection. An anaphylactic reaction to NRL <lb/>during anaesthesia may be immediate, or may be <lb/>delayed for up to an hour. The clinical manifestations <lb/>of NRL anaphylaxis during anaesthesia tend to be less <lb/>severe than anaphylaxis due to neuromuscular blocking <lb/>drugs. <lb/> Classification of latex reactions <lb/>1 Systemic reaction: a Type 1 hypersensitivity reaction <lb/>involving specific IgE to Hev proteins, mostly to Hev b <lb/>5&amp;6. This is the most severe but least frequent reaction <lb/>and occurs in genetically predisposed individuals. The <lb/>symptoms consist of itching, swelling, rhinitis, asthma <lb/>and anaphylaxis. This allergy is life long. A proportion <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>208 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">of sensitized individuals also react to certain fruits cross <lb/>reacting with latex proteins. <lb/>2 Contact dermatitis: a delayed Type IV hypersensitivity <lb/>reaction consisting of an eczematous reaction starting <lb/>24-48 h after repeated skin or mucosal contact with <lb/>additives used during rubber production. This is a <lb/>T cell-mediated, non-life-threatening reaction. It may, <lb/>however, predispose the individual to a more severe <lb/>systemic reaction. <lb/>3 Clinical non-immune-mediated reaction: irritant der-<lb/>matitis resulting from a mild irritant effect of the <lb/>powder in the gloves and that of disinfectants, sweating <lb/>etc. This is the most frequent reaction, is limited to the <lb/>contact area and is characterised by itching, irritation <lb/>and blistering at the side of contact. <lb/>High risk individuals <lb/>Approximately 8% of the population is sensitized to latex <lb/>but only 1.4% of the population exhibits latex allergy. <lb/>The following groups are at increased risk: <lb/>• Patients with atopy <lb/>• Children undergoing multiple surgical procedures, <lb/>such as spina bifida, or children undergoing surgery at <lb/>a very young age <lb/>• Patients with severe dermatitis of their hands <lb/>• Healthcare professionals <lb/>• Patients with allergy to fruits; most frequently banana, <lb/>chestnut and avocado <lb/>• Industrial workers using protective gear <lb/>• Occupational exposure to latex <lb/>Pre-operative assessment <lb/>A history of pre-operative symptoms suggestive of latex <lb/>allergy is present in approximately a quarter of patients <lb/>who develop intra-operative NRL anaphylaxis. A thor-<lb/>ough history, including an occupational history, should <lb/>be part of the pre-operative assessment. It is useful to ask <lb/>specifically whether contact with balloons, condoms or <lb/>latex gloves provokes itching, rash or angioedema. <lb/>Pre-operative testing <lb/>If the clinical history is positive or equivocal, the patient <lb/>should be referred for testing before the surgical proce-<lb/>dure and surgery should proceed only in an emergency. <lb/>In the preoperative situation, it is particularly important <lb/>to exclude IgE-mediated sensitivity. The choice of test: <lb/>either a blood test for latex-specific IgE, or skin testing <lb/>may depend on local availability. Current tests have a <lb/>sensitivity of approximately 75-90%; skin prick testing <lb/>may be more sensitive than blood tests for specific IgE. It <lb/>is important that skin prick tests are performed by trained <lb/>staff. It may be appropriate to proceed to challenge testing <lb/>in some patients. <lb/>Peri-operative precautions <lb/>• If NRL allergy is diagnosed pre-operatively, avoidance <lb/>is mandatory. <lb/>• Care should be taken to avoid introducing additional, <lb/>unrelated hazards when latex precautions are imple-<lb/>mented in the operating theatre. <lb/>• Latex allergy should be recorded in the case-notes and <lb/>on the patient&apos;s wrist bracelet. <lb/>• The surgical team and the nursing and anaesthetic <lb/>support teams should be alerted. <lb/>• There is no evidence that premedication with an anti-<lb/>histamine or steroid is useful. <lb/>• The operating theatre should be prepared the night <lb/>before to avoid the release of latex particles and the <lb/>patient should be scheduled first on the list. Evidence is <lb/>limited regarding the need for this degree of caution in <lb/>operating theatres where all latex gloves are of the non-<lb/>powdered type. <lb/>• A &apos;Latex allergy&apos; notice should be placed on the doors <lb/>to the anaesthetic room and operating theatre. <lb/>• Staff traffic should be limited. <lb/>• Absolute use of synthetic gloves when preparing <lb/>equipment and during anaesthesia, surgery and post-<lb/>operative care. <lb/>• Non-essential equipment should be removed from the <lb/>vicinity of the patient. <lb/>• The anaesthetic and surgical areas must contain only <lb/>latex free products. <lb/>• Only latex-free dressings and tapes should be applied. <lb/>• Equipment in resuscitation boxes and trolleys must <lb/>contain only latex free material. <lb/>Postoperative investigation of possible latex anaphylaxis <lb/>If skin testing and specific IgE testing is negative or <lb/>equivocal in the presence of a suggestive history, it may <lb/>be appropriate for the patient to proceed to a provocation <lb/>test with the finger of a latex glove. This procedure must <lb/>be performed by trained staff and resuscitation facilities <lb/>must be available. Patch testing by an expert is useful in <lb/>the diagnosis of delayed (Type lV) hypersensitivity to <lb/>rubber. <lb/>Hospital Latex-Allergy Policy <lb/>It is recommended that all hospitals have a latex-allergy <lb/>policy which should address the following: <lb/>• A named clinical lead for latex allergy <lb/>• Instructions for accessing latex-allergy testing <lb/>• Latex allergy precautions in the ward and clinic settings <lb/>• Latex allergy precautions in the operating theatre <lb/>environment <lb/>• Avoidance of latex sensitization in employees <lb/>• Liaison with pharmacy and equipment-procurement <lb/>departments <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>209 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Further reading <lb/>Demaegd J, Soetens F, Herregods L. Latex allergy: a challenge <lb/>for anesthetists. Acta Anaesthesiologica Belgica 2006; 57: 127-<lb/>135. <lb/>Mari A, Scala E, D&apos;Ambrosio C, Breitenerder H, Wagner S. <lb/>Latex allergy with a cohort of non at risk subjects with <lb/>respiratory symptoms: prevalence of latex sensitization and <lb/>assessment of diagnostic tools. International Archives of Allergy <lb/>and Immunology 2007; 143: 135-143. <lb/>Bousquet J, Flahault A, Vandemplas O, Ameille J, et al. Natural <lb/>rubber latex allergy among health care workers: a systematic <lb/>review of the evidence. The Journal of Allergy and Clinical <lb/>Immunology 2006; 118: 447-54. <lb/>Mertes PM, Laxenaire MC, Alla F. Anaphylactic and anaphy-<lb/>lactoid reactions occurring during anesthesia in France in <lb/>1999-2000. Anesthesiology 2003; 99: 536-545. <lb/>Suli C, Lorini M, Mistrello G, Tedeschi A. Diagnosis of <lb/>latex hypersensitivity :comparison of different methods. <lb/>European Annals of Allergy and Clinical Immunology 2006; <lb/>38: 24-30. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Appendix III <lb/>Mast cell tryptase <lb/>1 Mast cells are found within many tissues including <lb/>lung, intestine and skin. Tryptase is a protease <lb/>enzyme which acts via widespread protease activated <lb/>receptors (PARs). There are two types of tryptase; a <lb/>and b, each of which has several subtypes. Mature <lb/>b-tryptase is stored in granules in mast cells and is <lb/>released during anaphylaxis by a calcium-dependent <lb/>mechanism. a-tryptase is secreted constitutively by <lb/>mast cells and is the form normally found in the <lb/>blood in health. a-tryptase is elevated in systemic <lb/>mastocytosis. Pro-b-tryptase is also secreted consti-<lb/>tutively by mast cells. <lb/>2 The normal functions of tryptase include modulation <lb/>of intracellular calcium ion and intestinal chloride ion <lb/>transport in addition to mediating relaxation of smooth <lb/>muscle in vascular endothelium and bronchial smooth <lb/>muscle. In inflammation, tryptase stimulates the release <lb/>of pro-inflammatory interleukins and stimulates fur-<lb/>ther tryptase secretion by neighbouring mast cells. <lb/>3 A variety of pathways may combine to produce <lb/>anaphylaxis, depending on the trigger and the suscep-<lb/>tibility of the patient. Typically anaphylaxis results <lb/>from mast cell activation, and typically this will cause <lb/>release of mast cell b-tryptase into the circulation. <lb/>4 Anaphylaxis may be caused by basophil or comple-<lb/>ment activation, both of which are not associated with <lb/>a rise in mast cell tryptase. A raised tryptase concen-<lb/>tration is therefore a marker of anaphylaxis, but <lb/>anaphylaxis does not always cause a raised concentra-<lb/>tion. The greater the rise in concentration, the greater <lb/>the probability this was caused by an anaphylactic <lb/>reaction but a normal concentration does not disprove <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/>5 A rise in serum tryptase simply indicates mast cell <lb/>degranulation and does not discriminate between <lb/>allergic and non-allergic anaphylaxis. It has been <lb/>stated that the rise in serum tryptase concentration <lb/>may be less marked in non-allergic anaphylaxis. <lb/>6 During anaphylaxis, tryptase peaks by approximately <lb/>1 h and its half-life in the circulation is about 2 h: the <lb/>concentration therefore falls rapidly following an <lb/>anaphylactic reaction. <lb/>7 The most widely used assay for tryptase is the Immuno-<lb/>CAP Ò fluorescence enzyme immunoassay (FEIA) <lb/>which measures the sum of a and b-tryptase concen-<lb/>trations. A raised resting concentration is usually due to <lb/>a-tryptase, secreted constitutively by the increased <lb/>numbers of mast cells in systemic mastocytosis. <lb/>8 Although the current tryptase assay has a high <lb/>specificity, its sensitivity is relatively low and some <lb/>cases of anaphylaxis may be missed. <lb/>9 The sensitivity and specificity of the tryptase assay <lb/>depends on the cut-off point that is chosen to indicate <lb/>anaphylaxis. Because there is a wide variation in the <lb/>base-line plasma concentration of tryptase, the change <lb/>in tryptase concentration is more helpful than the <lb/>absolute concentration in reaching a diagnosis. <lb/>10 Intravenous fluid replacement is usually required <lb/>during treatment of a reaction. This fluid will dilute <lb/>the blood and causes a fall in the concentration of <lb/>tryptase measured. This must be taken into account <lb/>when evaluating the measured concentration. <lb/>11 Following death, the circulation stops and tryptase is no <lb/>longer removed from the circulation; samples taken <lb/>postmortem are helpful in evaluating whether the termi-<lb/>nal events were related to anaphylaxis. A raised tryptase <lb/>concentration found at autopsy has lower predictive <lb/>value than a sample taken during life. b-tryptase may be <lb/>raised in trauma or myocardial infarction. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>Further reading <lb/>Fisher MM, Baldo BA. Mast cell tryptase in anaesthetic ana-<lb/>phylactoid reactions. British Journal of Anaesthesia 1998; 80: <lb/>26-29. <lb/>Enrique E, Garcia-Ortega P, Sotorra O, Gaig P, Richart C. <lb/>Usefulness of UniCAP Tryptase fluoroimmunoassay <lb/>in the diagnosis of anaphylaxis. Allergy 1999; 54: 602-606. <lb/>Payne V, Kam PCA. Mast cell tryptase: a review of its <lb/>physiology and clinical significance. Anaesthesia 2004; 59: <lb/>695-703. <lb/>Brown SGA, Blackman KE, Heddle RJ. Can serum mast cell <lb/>tryptase help diagnose anaphylaxis? Emergency Medicine <lb/>Australasia 2004; 16: 120-124. <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/></note>

			<page>210 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Appendix IV <lb/>Useful websites <lb/>http://www.aagbi.org <lb/>The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and <lb/>Ireland <lb/>http://www.bsaci.org <lb/>The British Society for Allergy and Clinical Immunology <lb/>http://www.immunology.org <lb/>The British Society for Immunology <lb/>http://www.resus.org.uk <lb/>Resuscitation Council UK <lb/>http://www.eaaci.net <lb/>The European Academy of Allergology and Clinical <lb/>Immunology <lb/>http://www.mhra.gov.uk <lb/>The Medicines and Healthcare products Regulatory <lb/>Agency <lb/>Supporting Information <lb/>Additional Supporting information may be found in the <lb/>online version of this article: <lb/>Appendix S1 Anaesthetic Anaphylaxis Referral Form. <lb/>Please note: Wiley-Blackwell are not responsible for the <lb/>content or functionality of any Supporting materials <lb/>supplied by the authors. Any queries (other than missing <lb/>material) should be directed to the corresponding author <lb/>for the article. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Anaesthesia, 2009, 64, pages 199-211 <lb/>Suspected anaphylactic reactions associated with anaesthesia <lb/>. ..................................................................................................................................................................................................................... <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Ó 2008 The Authors <lb/>Journal compilation Ó 2008 The Association of Anaesthetists of Great Britain and Ireland <lb/></note>

			<page>211 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
