<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>German Edition:D OI:10.1002/ange.201809108 <lb/>Polymers <lb/>International Edition:D OI:10.1002/anie.201809108 <lb/>Tracking Local Mechanical Impact in Heterogeneous Polymers with <lb/>Direct Optical Imaging <lb/>Georgy A. Filonenko,* Jody A. M. Lugger,Chong Liu, Ellen P. A. van Heeswijk, <lb/>Marco M. R. M. Hendrix, Manuela Weber,C hristian Müller,Emiel J. M. Hensen, <lb/>Rint P. Sijbesma, and Evgeny A. Pidko <lb/>Abstract: Structural heterogeneity defines the properties of <lb/>many functional polymers and it is often crucial for their <lb/>performance and ability to withstand mechanical impact. Such <lb/>heterogeneity,h owever,p oses at remendous challenge for <lb/>characterization of these materials and limits our ability to <lb/>design them rationally.H erein we present ap ractical method-<lb/>ology capable of resolving the complex mechanical behavior <lb/>and trackingm echanical impact in discrete phases of seg-<lb/>mented polyurethane-a typical example of as tructurally <lb/>complex polymer.U sing direct optical imaging of photo-<lb/>luminescence produced by as mall-molecule organometallic <lb/>mechano-responsive sensor we observe in real time how <lb/>polymer phases dissipate energy,r estructure,a nd breakdown <lb/>upon mechanical impact. Owing to its simplicity and robust-<lb/>ness,t his method has potential in describing the evolution of <lb/>complex soft-matter systems for whichglobal characterization <lb/>techniques fall short of providing molecular-level insight. <lb/></front>

			<body>Understanding the mechanisms that define mechanical <lb/>stability of polymers is crucial for designing robust materials <lb/>resistant to wear and failure.A lthough conventional macro-<lb/>scopic techniques such as rheology or dynamic mechanical <lb/>thermal analysis (DMTA) may be sufficient to characterize <lb/>most polymers,t he macroscopic picture provided by these <lb/>techniques often lacks molecular-level resolution. This limi-<lb/>tation is particularly valid for functional polymers that are <lb/>typically non-uniform and heterogeneous on multiple length <lb/>scales.T ou nderstand properties of materials composed of <lb/>several distinct or mixed phases ac onceptually different <lb/>characterization approach would be required. <lb/>Acomplex multi-phase material at the core of this work, is <lb/>ac hain-extended polyurethane (PU)-a copolymer com-<lb/>posed of flexible polyether or polyester &quot;soft&quot; blocks and <lb/>rigid &quot;hard&quot; blocks that form ah ydrogen-bonded crystalline <lb/>phase (Figure 1). [1] Theu biquity of PU in practical applica-<lb/>tions stems from the great variability of their properties, <lb/>which can be achieved by tuning the chemical nature and <lb/>relative content of different phases.S uch diversity,h owever, <lb/>comes at the expense of the drastically increased structural <lb/>complexity of PUs.A sac onsequence,alocal, phase-and <lb/>component-specific picture of their behavior under mechan-<lb/>ical stress remains at opic of intense debate eight decades <lb/>after the first PU was prepared. <lb/>Seeking to overcome the limitations of global character-<lb/>ization techniques lacking molecular-level resolution, several <lb/>force-responsive molecular probes have been developed over <lb/>the last decade.W ith few exceptions utilizing nanoparticle <lb/>moieties, [2] them ajority of such probes are small organic <lb/>fragments built into the polymer main chain. Upon exposure <lb/>to external force,t hese organic moieties,o ften termed as <lb/>mechanophores,c an undergo mechanochemical activation [3] <lb/>producing aspecific response,for example,luminescence [4] or <lb/>ac hange in absorbance and fluorescence characteristics. [5, 6] <lb/>Alternatively,am echanical stimulus can alter the arrange-<lb/>ment of fluorescent mechanophore within the polymer <lb/>matrix, which results in ad ramatic change of their emission <lb/>properties. [7] Thevast majority of these mechanophores relies <lb/>on transformations with no or limited reversibility.F or this <lb/>reason, common mechanophores can only probe the state of <lb/>the polymer system before and after the mechanical impact <lb/>while the dynamic evolution of the polymer system overtime <lb/>remains beyond their reach. <lb/>Herein we address this challenge and develop as imple <lb/>and straightforward methodology that allows the direct <lb/>monitoring of the real-lime evolution of discrete phases in <lb/>ac omplex polymer system under mechanical stress.I nstru-<lb/>mental to this work was the development of new robust <lb/>organometallic mechanophores that combine high aerial <lb/>stability and facile response with straightforward chemistry <lb/>for their incorporation into distinct phases of polyurethanes. <lb/>Relying on direct optical imaging as the primary analysis <lb/></body>

			<front>[*] Dr.G .A.Filonenko,D r. C. Liu, Prof. E. A. Pidko <lb/>Inorganic Systems Engineering group <lb/>Department of Chemical Engineering <lb/>Delft University of Technology <lb/>2629 HZ Delft (The Netherlands) <lb/>E-mail:g.a.filonenko@tudelft.nl <lb/>Dr.J .A.M.Lugger,Prof. R. P. Sijbesma <lb/>Institute for Complex Molecular Systems, Eindhoven University of <lb/>Technology <lb/>5600 MB Eindhoven (The Netherlands) <lb/>E. P. A. van Heeswijk, M. M. R. M. Hendrix, Prof. E. J. M. Hensen <lb/>Department of Chemical Engineering and Chemistry,Eindhoven <lb/>Universityo fT echnology <lb/>5600 MB Eindhoven (The Netherlands) <lb/>M. Weber,P rof. C. Müller <lb/>Institut fürChemie und Biochemie, Freie UniversitätBerlin <lb/>14195 Berlin (Germany) <lb/>Supportinginformation and the ORCID identification number(s) for <lb/>the author(s) of this article can be found under: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/anie.201809108. <lb/>2018 The Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp; Co. <lb/>KGaA. This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons AttributionL icense, which permits use, distribution and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly <lb/>cited. <lb/>Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/> 16385 <lb/> Angew.C hem. Int.E d. 2018, 57,1 6385 -16390 <lb/> 2018 The Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/></front>

			<body>technique,the methodology holds great potential for general <lb/>use in soft matter characterization. <lb/>Thep reparation of the new mechanophore and its <lb/>selective incorporation in PUs was the first objective of our <lb/>study.W eb ased our mechanophore design on an ew class of <lb/>recently developed phosphorescent complexes that were <lb/>shown to reversibly respond to mechanical stress (CuN 4 , <lb/>Figure 1b). [8,9] Themechanism governing their force-induced <lb/>response,depicted in Figure 1b,isconceptually different from <lb/>those found in common organic mechanophores. [9] Instead of <lb/>bond scission and related irreversible transformations,t hese <lb/>copper halide complexes vary their photoluminescence (PL) <lb/>via aforce-induced restriction of their intramolecular isomer-<lb/>ization that represents an on-radiative relaxation process. <lb/>Slower isomerization, induced by the restriction on the <lb/>polymer chain mobility under stress,r esults in brighter <lb/>phosphorescence with higher quantum yields and longer PL <lb/>lifetimes.F ast isomerization, that is typical for highly mobile <lb/>polymer chains results in lower PL intensities.T his response <lb/>mechanism would be suitable to track force-induced phe-<lb/>nomena in PUs in real time but falls short of being practically <lb/>useful due the poor air stability of the Cu I halide complexes. <lb/>Forp ractical reasons,the target stress-responsive mecha-<lb/>nophores based on the CuN 4 core should be robust enough to <lb/>withstand continuous exposure to air and UV light. A <lb/>common strategy for stabilizing Cu I towards oxidation is the <lb/>use of strong donor auxiliary ligands,for example,phosphines <lb/>or N-heterocyclic carbenes (NHC). To identify potential <lb/>mechanophores we evaluated as eries of Cu I complexes with <lb/>different NHC ligands using DFT calculations (S6 of Sup-<lb/>porting Information) targeting complexes with the isomer-<lb/>ization mechanism identical of that of previously described <lb/>Cu halides.S pecifically,w ea nalyzed how mechanophore <lb/>isomerization is influenced by substitution of the halide ligand <lb/>in the parent halide CuN 4 by NHC ligands with different <lb/>steric bulk. We identified one of the smallest known NHC <lb/>ligands derived from N,N&apos;-dimethylimidazolium carboxylate <lb/>(Figure 1) to be the suitable auxiliary ligand that would not <lb/>alter mechanophore isomerization mechanism and therefore <lb/>its force response.I nl ine with predicted behavior,r eference <lb/>complex 1,prepared to validate our analysis,indeed exhibits <lb/>isomerization dynamics identical to that of CuN 4 and remains <lb/>structurally similar to the parent complex according to the <lb/>single crystal X-ray diffraction data (see Figure 1C and <lb/>Section S5 of Supporting Information). This behavior,partic-<lb/>ularly important for mechanophore selection, suggests an <lb/>isomerization mechanism of 1 is identical to that of parent <lb/>halide mechanophores [9] involving intermediate formation of <lb/>4-coordinate Cu centers,t hus,b eing associative.F inally, <lb/>complex 1 is remarkably stable and withstands nearly <lb/>aw eek long exposure to air in dichloromethane solution, <lb/>making it suitable for further practical use as am echano-<lb/>phore. <lb/>We further incorporated this phosphorescent motif into <lb/>hard and soft phases of polyurethane samples.Inspired by the <lb/>strategy reported by Braun and co-workers [5] we developed <lb/>ao ne-pot protocol targeting the macrocyclic ligand L <lb/>(Figure 1) to prescribed locations.N amely,w ep re-formed <lb/>two building blocks depicted in Figure 1a&quot;soft&quot; one <lb/>terminated with polyether groups (pTHF) and a&quot; hard&quot; one <lb/>terminated with hexamethylene diisocyanate (HDI) extended <lb/>with 1,4-butanediol (BDO) to direct the mechanophore <lb/>precursor to soft or hard PU domains,r espectively.R espec-<lb/>tive PU samples were denoted as SP/HP for the type of PU <lb/>phase hosting mechanophore and given the index &quot;40&quot; <lb/>indicating the molar fraction of the BDO chain extender. <lb/>NMR spectroscopy confirmed the incorporation of preloaded <lb/>amounts of ligand L in all PUs and their identical composition <lb/>regardless of the phase labelled (See Supporting Informa-<lb/>Figure 1. Structure and properties of PU phases (A), working principles <lb/>of CuN 4 mechanophores (B) and building blocks used in this work <lb/>together with the solid-state structure of reference complex 1 (C). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/></note>

			<page>16386</page>

			<note place="footnote">www.angewandte.org 2018T he Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim Angew.C hem.I nt. Ed. 2018, 57,1 6385-16390 <lb/></note>

			<body>tion). FTIR spectroscopy confirmed no impact of mechano-<lb/>phore incorporation on the hard phase of SP40 samples and <lb/>indicated am arginal increase in the relative content of <lb/>disordered carbonyl groups in HP40 further confirming that <lb/>the labelling impacted specific synthetically targeted phases <lb/>(See Figure S29 in the Supporting Information). Size exclu-<lb/>sion chromatography indicated similar molecular weights of <lb/>all samples ranging from 70 to 90 kDa with nearly identical <lb/>polydispersity of 1.9-2.1. Finally,the polymer-bound ligand L <lb/>was complexed with Cu I following the procedure developed <lb/>for the synthesis of complex 1 to produce emissive polymers <lb/>with 1 HNMR spectra nearly identical to those of the <lb/>reference complex 1 (See Section S3 of Supporting Informa-<lb/>tion). Thel atter,i mportantly,c onfirms the identity of <lb/>mechanophore embedded in the PU material and suggests <lb/>no ligand exchange between mechanophore and polymer <lb/>matrix taking effect. <lb/>Copper-containing PU films fabricated by mold casting <lb/>were photoluminescent and emitted at around 580 nm upon <lb/>excitation with UV light. Importantly,t he emission of PU <lb/>films was identical to that of reference complex 1 in solution <lb/>but not in the solid state.This confirms that mechanophore in <lb/>the PU is well dispersed and not aggregated as the aggregates <lb/>would produce emission similar to that of crystalline 1, which <lb/>is significantly blue shifted to approximately 555 nm. Films of <lb/>Cu-HP samples incorporating the mechanophore in the hard <lb/>domain exhibit nearly three-fold longer PL lifetimes com-<lb/>pared to their soft phase labelled counterparts Cu-SP <lb/>suggesting that Cu-SP indeed contains mechanophore in the <lb/>phase with significantly higher chain mobility as expected <lb/>when the mechanophore is embedded in the soft phase of PU. <lb/>Once discrete phases of PU samples were labelled with <lb/>mechanophore,w ef ocused on tracking the differences in <lb/>force-induced behavior of those phases.T odothat, PU films <lb/>were subjected to uniaxial extension with simultaneous <lb/>detection of the photoluminescence intensity produced by <lb/>these films.F or tensile tests the isotropic PU films were pre-<lb/>stretched to 250 %o ft heir initial length to prevent necking <lb/>and associated changes in sample geometry during the <lb/>imaging experiment. <lb/>To observe both deformation and stress relaxation <lb/>kinetics we adopted the testing protocol (Figure 2) similar <lb/>to that used by Braun [5] and Boyce. [10] Namely,s amples were <lb/>extended with ac onstant rate of 5o r5 0% L 0 s À1 to produce <lb/>af ixed (7.5 MPa) increase in stress at each loading step <lb/>followed by a5second hold allowing for stress relaxation to <lb/>be monitored. Afterwards,t he loading/relaxation was <lb/>repeated until the sample failed. Ty pical curves produced in <lb/>these tests are depicted in Figure 2. <lb/>As expected, external stress applied to PUs reduces <lb/>mechanophore isomerization rate and leads to an increase of <lb/>the PL intensity during all tests.The evolution of PL response <lb/>during stress relaxation step,however, depended strongly on <lb/>the location of the phosphorescent probe and strain rates <lb/>applied during the elongation. Slow deformation of the Cu-<lb/>SP40 containing mechanophore in the soft phase produces an <lb/>immediate increase of PL intensity that further decays when <lb/>the sample is allowed to relax (Figure 2A). Simultaneously <lb/>with the decrease of the PL intensity,t he global mechanical <lb/>stress decreases.T he drop on the PL intensity of the soft <lb/>phase embedded mechanophore suggests that gradual redis-<lb/>tribution of local stresses within the PU sample from the soft <lb/>phase to the hard phase takes place during the relaxation <lb/>stage.W et herefore assume that even at low loading rates <lb/>deformation of the soft phase is impacted by the deformation <lb/>of the hard phase that accounts for decrease in the detected <lb/>PL response. <lb/>Interestingly,mechanophore localized in the hard domain <lb/>as in Cu-HP40 produces ad ifferent PL profile that contains <lb/>as hort plateau of approximately 1.2-1.8 sd uration that <lb/>precedes the PL decrease associated with the same stress <lb/>redistribution phenomena that we observed in Cu-SP40. <lb/>Because the appearance of plateau was specific to the hard <lb/>phase we assigned it to the reorientation of the hard phase <lb/>along the elongation direction that was observed experimen-<lb/>tally (See Figure 2and Figure 3and Supporting Information) <lb/>and reported for other common PUs. [1,11] Ac ommon feature <lb/>of slow deformation in either HP or SP samples is the <lb/>immediate increase of PL intensity in response to deforma-<lb/>tion that indicates an immediate restriction of the chain <lb/>mobility upon loading regardless of the mechanophore <lb/>location. <lb/>Fast deformation of the hard phase labelled Cu-HP40 <lb/>produces ad ramatically different PL response.U pon defor-<lb/>mation the PL intensity instantaneously drops while subse-<lb/>quent stress relaxation and associated decay of global <lb/>mechanical stress is accompanied by am ono-exponential <lb/>increase of PL intensity (Figure 2D). This sharply contrasts <lb/>the behavior of the PL probe in Cu-SP40 at the same <lb/>deformation rate (Figure 2C)w here no pronounced drop-<lb/>recovery behavior was observed. <lb/>Up to this point, our observations suggest that at high <lb/>deformation rates the hard phase restructures differently with <lb/>mechanophore becoming highly mobile upon mechanical <lb/>impact and being slowly immobilized over time.Importantly, <lb/>the extent of plastic deformation in Cu-HP40-5/50 is negli-<lb/>gible and the distinctly different hard phase behavior takes <lb/>place within the same range of applied stresses and strains to <lb/>those registered throughout all tests (see expansions in <lb/>Figure 2). Taken together,t hese data suggest that observed <lb/>PL response differences in Cu-HP40-5/50 are specific to the <lb/>hard phase of PU and stem solely from the elongation rate <lb/>dependence.H aving observed such ap rofound difference in <lb/>the PL response for Cu-HP40 we further aimed at assigning <lb/>these differences to physical events taking place in PUs under <lb/>stress.T his would ultimately allow linking the data provided <lb/>by our methodology to the knowledge framework developed <lb/>for PUs using conventional characterization techniques. <lb/>Them ajor structural change occurring in PUs upon <lb/>deformation is associated with the reorientation and segmen-<lb/>tation of the crystalline hard phase. [1, 11] Using linear dichroism <lb/>IR spectroscopy we found that slow deformation of Cu-HP40 <lb/>leads to al arge increase of hard phase orientation along the <lb/>stretching direction. Theo rder parameter in that case <lb/>increases from the initial value of 0.37 for pre-stretched <lb/>samples before tensile tests to approximately 0.7 (Figure 2, <lb/>top). Thei ncrease of the order parameter is in line with the <lb/>expected behavior of PUs,w hich are known to produce <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/></note>

			<page>16387 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Angew.C hem. Int.E d. 2018, 57,1 6385 -16390 <lb/>2018 The Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>www.angewandte.org <lb/></note>

			<body>oriented morphologies upon deformation though the slow <lb/>rotation of hard domains that orients them along the principal <lb/>deformation axis. [11] Theobserved mechanophore behavior in <lb/>the slow deformation experiment is indeed <lb/>consistent with this conventional deforma-<lb/>tion mechanism. Theincrease of PL inten-<lb/>sity and the following slow decay can, <lb/>therefore,b ea ssigned to two distinct <lb/>events in PUs upon deformation:1)restric-<lb/>tion of mobility of extended polymer <lb/>chains (increase of PL) and 2) rotation of <lb/>hard domains that allows for higher chain <lb/>mobility as the stress relaxation takes <lb/>effect (slow decrease of PL). <lb/>Aiming to identify the origin of adiffer-<lb/>ent PL response profile observed in the <lb/>case of fast deformation we extended our <lb/>structural studies to Cu-HP40-50 sample. <lb/>Interestingly,wef ound no apparent differ-<lb/>ence in the close range packing in Cu-<lb/>HP40-5/50 examined by wide angle X-ray <lb/>scattering (WAXS,s ee S7 in Supporting <lb/>Information). IR spectroscopy,s imilarly <lb/>indicated no detectible change in the over-<lb/>all hard phase composition in all Cu-HP40 <lb/>samples as evidenced by identical absorb-<lb/>ance in the characteristic regions for ure-<lb/>thane NH and C=Ov ibrations (Figure 3B <lb/>and section S7 in Supporting Information). <lb/>Theh ard phase alignment in Cu-HP40-50, <lb/>however was found to be strikingly differ-<lb/>ent from that of Cu-HP40-5.N amely,t he <lb/>fast deformation did not affect the hard <lb/>phase order parameter that remained at <lb/>the value of 0.37 after the tensile tests.This <lb/>suggests that hard domains in PU were <lb/>unable to rotate and re-orient upon the fast <lb/>deformation that resulted into aP Uw ith <lb/>an entirely different morphology.T his <lb/>notion is in part supported by atomic <lb/>force microscopy data (Figure S28 in the <lb/>Supporting <lb/>Information) <lb/>indicating <lb/>am ajor restructuring of the PU surface as <lb/>the PU samples are subjected to mechan-<lb/>ical impact. <lb/>Further structural differences in Cu-<lb/>HP40-5/50 were revealed by the 2D-SAXS <lb/>analysis depicted in Figure 3A.All samples <lb/>after the pre-stretch and tensile tests <lb/>exhibited at ypical 4-spot pattern often <lb/>referred to as &quot;chevron pattern&quot; common <lb/>among HDI-based PUs. [12] This scattering <lb/>pattern indicates the presence of two <lb/>groups of hard domains tilted at identical <lb/>angle with respect to the deformation <lb/>direction as depicted in Figure 3A.I n <lb/>contrast to the linear dichroism IR data <lb/>suggesting the reorientation of the ure-<lb/>thane functional groups in slow deforma-<lb/>tion experiments and the lack of thereof in fast deformation <lb/>tests,SAXS data indicates that hard domains in Cu-HP40-50 <lb/>produced by the fast loading are actually more ordered <lb/>Figure 2. Tensile test method, hard phase alignment characterization (top) and experimental <lb/>data (bottom, (A)-(D)). Stress (black lines) in uniaxial tension at two different elongation <lb/>rates and corresponding PL response curves (brown dots). Expansions show PL, stress and <lb/>strain profiles for three loading steps in the vicinity of 100 MPa region (curves in stress-<lb/>strain coordinates can be found in the Supporting Information). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/></note>

			<page>16388</page>

			<note place="footnote">www.angewandte.org 2018T he Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim Angew.C hem.I nt. Ed. 2018, 57,1 6385-16390 <lb/></note>

			<body>macroscopically (See Figure 3B). Namely,amore defined <lb/>&quot;chevron&quot; pattern is revealed by the azimuthal scattering <lb/>intensity distribution data and adetectible shift was observed <lb/>for the broad peak in SAXS profile at ca. 0.08 À1 corre-<lb/>sponding to the hard domain repeating unit. Altogether,these <lb/>findings confirm that deformation rate dependence of the <lb/>mechanophore response in Cu-HP40 indeed originates from <lb/>differences in hard phase deformation mechanism. <lb/>Our data consistently links the differences in PL response <lb/>to the development of distinct PU morphologies.F igure 3C <lb/>summarizes our proposed mechanism for their formation. In <lb/>line with previous observations and our structural character-<lb/>ization data, slow deformation allows for the rotation of hard <lb/>domains in PU and their alignment with the stretching <lb/>direction. This deformation has no major effect on the hard <lb/>phase morphology and preserves its macroscopic structure as <lb/>confirmed by 2D-SAXS.Asthe PL response in hard and soft <lb/>phase of Cu-SP/HP40 was similar at low elongation rates,we <lb/>assume that deformation is largely dominated by the soft <lb/>phase uncoiling and subsequent relaxation due to hard phase <lb/>rotation (Figure 3C). <lb/>In contrast to this,t he fast deformation regime is <lb/>apparently destructive for the hard phase of the PU at least <lb/>during the initial deformation step.T his interpretation is <lb/>supported by the sharp drop in the PL intensity during the fast <lb/>loading in Cu-HP40-50 that suggests that the mechanophore <lb/>is mobilized upon the impact. This can proceed either via <lb/>ap ull-out of individual hard segments containing the <lb/>mechanophore or ap artial breakdown of the hard phase <lb/>crystallites.I mportantly,r egardless of which of these phe-<lb/>nomena takes place,itdoes not induce hard domain rotation, <lb/>suggesting that mechanical impact restructures the hard phase <lb/>without allowing it to diffuse and reorient macroscopically. <lb/>Based on these considerations,wecome to conclusion that the <lb/>hard phase deformation should involve the scission of weak <lb/>hydrogen bonds between individual hard segments. <lb/>As the hydrogen bonds are non-covalent, they can form <lb/>and break reversibly, [13] allowing fragmented hard domains to <lb/>re-associate when deformation stops.T his behavior could <lb/>indeed be responsible for the recovery of PL response <lb/>observed during fast deformation experiments.C onsidering <lb/>that the recovery of PL signal in Cu-HP40-50 is strictly mono-<lb/>exponential we conclude that the PL response profile in fact <lb/>describes as ingle process that is likely crystallization of the <lb/>hard phase with an observed rate constant of 0.93 AE 0.1 s À1 <lb/>calculated from exponential PL recovery traces-a value <lb/>corresponding to aprocess lifetime in the order of one second. <lb/>Although highly unusual to occur at room temperature, <lb/>the hard phase crystallization is consistent with our exper-<lb/>imental data-in PUs crystallization is af ast process with <lb/>at ime scale of multiple seconds at room temperature. [14] <lb/>Direct analysis of non-isothermal crystallization kinetics of <lb/>Cu-HP40 performed using DSC,places an estimated crystal-<lb/>lization rate constant at 4.7 s À1 at 25 8 8C( S4 in Supporting <lb/>Information)-a value similar to that observed in imaging <lb/>experiments.A lthough the H-bond scission in PUs likely <lb/>impacts aminor fraction of the hard phase,our methodology <lb/>appears to have sufficient sensitivity to produce ar eadily <lb/>detectible response to these transient physical events that <lb/>otherwise remain undetected by techniques lacking temporal <lb/>or spatial resolution. <lb/>In conclusion, our work provides ad irect observation of <lb/>diverse and distinctly different phase behavior patterns within <lb/>as ingle polymer family and offers an unprecedented insight <lb/>into the mechanically induced evolution of complex polymer <lb/>system. Theresponse of robust mechanophores has been used <lb/>as ad iagnostic tool to identify the deformation mechanisms <lb/>leading to the development of distinct polymer morphologies <lb/>Figure 3. A) 2D SAXS data for top:isotropic and prestretched Cu-HP40 samples and bottom:ofCu-HP40-5 subjected to slow elongation and Cu-<lb/>HP40-50 subjected fast elongation. Measurements performed on samples recovered after tensile elongation tests depicted in Figure 2. B) Total <lb/>scattering intensity and azimuthal intensity distribution plots for scatteringdata depicted in panel (A) and IR spectroscopy data for these samples. <lb/>C) Proposed deformationm echanism of Cu-HP40 at slow and fast elongation regimes assigned to observed PL profiles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/></note>

			<page>16389 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Angew.C hem. Int.E d. 2018, 57,1 6385 -16390 <lb/>2018 The Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim <lb/>www.angewandte.org <lb/></note>

			<body>that can hardly be predicted using global characterization <lb/>techniques.S ince the response of new mechanophores <lb/>originates at the molecular level, it allows us to describe <lb/>force-induced phenomena locally.Atthe same time,the non-<lb/>destructive nature of mechanophore action allows these <lb/>dynamic phenomena to be tracked in real time.This method-<lb/>ology is efficient in dealing with the case of structural <lb/>complexity in polyurethanes.W e, therefore,see no limitation <lb/>for it to become acommon tool assisting materials scientists in <lb/>resolving soft matter complexity in the near future. <lb/>Experimental Section <lb/>Full synthesis and characterization data and testing methodology <lb/>description can be found in Supporting. CCDC 1849321 contains the <lb/>supplementary crystallographic data for this paper.These data can be <lb/>obtained free of charge from TheC ambridge Crystallographic Data <lb/>Centre. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This research was supported by the European Research <lb/>Council (ERC) under the European UnionsH orizon 2020 <lb/>research and innovation programme (grant agreement No. <lb/>725686). This work was sponsored by NWOE xact and <lb/>Natural Sciences for the use of supercomputer facilities.R.P.S. <lb/>thanks the Ministry of Education, Culture and Science of The <lb/>Netherlands for support (Gravity program 024.001.035)). <lb/>C.M. thanks the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (DFG) <lb/>for financial support. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>Theauthors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>Keywords: copper •l uminescence •mechanical properties • <lb/>molecular dynamics •p olymers <lb/></div>

			<front>Howt ocite: Angew.C hem. Int. Ed. 2018, 57,1 6385 -16390 <lb/>Angew.Chem. 2018, 130,16623 -16628 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>[1] C. Prisacariu, Polyurethane Elastomers:F romM orphology to <lb/>Mechanical Aspects,S pringer Vienna, Vienna 2011. <lb/>[2] a) X. Jin, M. Gçtz, S. Wille,Y .K.M ishra, R. Adelung,C . <lb/>Zollfrank, Adv.Mater. 2013, 25,1342;b)C.L.Choi, K. J. Koski, <lb/>A. C. K. Olson, A. P. Alivisatos, Proc.Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2010, <lb/>107,2 1306;c )S.N .R aja, A. C. K. Olson, K. Thorkelsson, A. J. <lb/>Luong,L .H sueh, G. Chang,B .G ludovatz, L. Lin, T. Xu, R. O. <lb/>Ritchie,A.P .Alivisatos, Nano Lett. 2013, 13,3915;d)S .N .Raja, <lb/>D. Zherebetskyy, S. Wu,P .E rcius,A .P owers,A .C.K.O lson, <lb/>D. X. Du, L. Lin, S. Govindjee,L .-W.W ang,T .X u, A. P. <lb/>Alivisatos,R.O .Ritchie, Nano Lett. 2016, 16,5060;e)S .Y in, Z. <lb/>Zhao,W .L uan, F. Yang, RSC Adv. 2016, 6,1 8126;f )A. <lb/>Stevenson, A. Jones,S .R aghavan, Nano Lett. 2011, 11,3 274. <lb/>[3] a) M. M. Caruso,D.A.Davis,Q.Shen, S. A. Odom, N. R. Sottos, <lb/>S. R. White,J .S.M oore, Chem. Rev. 2009, 109,5 755;b )K. <lb/>Imato,T .Kanehara, T. Ohishi, M. Nishihara, H. Yajima, M. Ito, <lb/>A. Takahara,H .O tsuka, ACSM acro Lett. 2015, 4,1 307;c )T . <lb/>Kosuge,K.Imato,R.Goseki, H. Otsuka, Macromolecules 2016, <lb/>49,5 903. <lb/>[4] a) Y. Chen, A. J. H. Spiering, S. Karthikeyan, G. W. M. Peters, <lb/>E. W. Meijer,R .P .S ijbesma, Nat. Chem. 2012, 4,5 59;b )Y . <lb/>Chen, R. P. Sijbesma, Macromolecules 2014, 47,3 797;c )E. <lb/>Ducrot,Y .Chen, M. Bulters,R .P .S ijbesma,C .C reton, Science <lb/>2014, 344,186. <lb/>[5] C. K. Lee,B .A.B eiermann, M. N. Silberstein, J. Wang,J .S. <lb/>Moore,N.R.Sottos,P .V .Braun, Macromolecules 2013, 46,3746. <lb/>[6] a) C. K. Lee,D .A.Davis,S .R.W hite,J .S .Moore,N .R.Sottos, <lb/>P. V. Braun, J. Am. Chem. Soc. 2010, 132,16107;b)G .OBryan, <lb/>B. M. Wong,J .R.McElhanon, ACSAppl. Mater.Interfaces 2010, <lb/>2,1 594;c )D .A.D avis,A .H amilton, J. Yang,L .D .C remar,D . <lb/>Va nGough, S. L. Potisek, M. T. Ong,P .V .Braun, T. J. Martinez, <lb/>S. R. White,J .S.Moore,N .R.Sottos, Nature 2009, 459,6 8. <lb/>[7] a) A. Pucci, R. Bizzarri, G. Ruggeri, Soft Matter 2011, 7,3 689; <lb/>B. R. Crenshaw,C.W eder, Macromolecules 2006, 39,9581;b)A. <lb/>Pucci, F. Di Cuia, F. Signori, G. Ruggeri, J. Mater.C hem. 2007, <lb/>17,7 83;c )C.C alvino,A .G uha, C. Weder, S. Schrettl, Adv. <lb/>Mater. 2018, 30,1 704603;d )Y .S agara, M. Karman,E .V erde-<lb/>Sesto,K.Matsuo,Y .Kim, N. Tamaoki, C. Weder, J. Am. Chem. <lb/>Soc. 2018, 140,1584. <lb/>[8] G. Filonenko,R .R.F ayzullin,J .R.K husnutdinova, J. Mater. <lb/>Chem. C 2017, 5,1638. <lb/>[9] G. A. Filonenko,J .R.K husnutdinova, Adv.M ater. 2017, 29, <lb/>1700563. <lb/>[10] H. J. Qi, M. C. Boyce, Mech. Mater. 2005, 37,817. <lb/>[11] I. Kimura, H. Ishihara, H. Ono,N .Y oshihara, S. Nomura, H. <lb/>Kawai, Macromolecules 1974, 7,3 55. <lb/>[12] R. S. Waletzko,L .T .J .K orley,B .D .P ate,E .L.T homas,P .T . <lb/>Hammond, Macromolecules 2009, 42,2041. <lb/>[13] Y. Yanagisawa,Y .Nan, K. Okuro,T .Aida, Science 2017,https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1126/science.aam7588. <lb/>[14] S. Irena, D. Irena, J. Polym. Sci. Polym. Symp. 1975, 53,1 87. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Manuscript received:A ugust 7, 2018 <lb/>Acceptedm anuscript online: September5 ,2 018 <lb/>Version of record online: October 9, 2018 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Angewandte <lb/>Chemie <lb/>Communications <lb/></note>

			<page>16390</page>

			<note place="footnote">www.angewandte.org 2018T he Authors. Published by Wiley-VCH Verlag GmbH &amp;C o. KGaA, Weinheim Angew.C hem.I nt. Ed. 2018, 57,1 6385-16390 </note>

	</text>
</tei>
