<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0007013v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 2 Jul 2000 <lb/>Measurements of the absolute value of the penetration depth in high-T c <lb/>superconductors using a tunnel diode resonator <lb/>R. Prozorov, R. W. Giannetta, A. Carrington, P. Fournier, 3 <lb/>R. L. Greene, 3 P. Guptasarma, D.G. Hinks, 4 and A. R. Banks <lb/>1 Loomis Laboratory of Physics, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, 1110 West Green St., Urbana, 61801 Illinois. <lb/>2 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Leeds, Leeds LS2 9JT, United Kingdom <lb/>3 Center for Superconductivity Research, Department of Physics, <lb/>University of Maryland, College Park, Maryland 20742 <lb/>4 Chemistry and Materials Science Division, Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois 60439 <lb/>5 Materials Research Laboratory, University of Illinois at Urbana-Champaign, <lb/>104 South Goodwin Ave, Urbana, 61801 Illinois. <lb/>(Dated: Submitted to Applied. Phys. Lett. June 30, 2000) <lb/>A method is presented to measure the absolute value of the London penetration depth, λ, from <lb/>the frequency shift of a resonator. The technique involves coating a high-Tc superconductor (HTSC) <lb/>with film of low -Tc material of known thickness and penetration depth. The method is applied <lb/>to measure London penetration depth in YBa2Cu3O 7−δ (YBCO) Bi2Sr2CaCu2O 8+δ (BSCCO) and <lb/>Pr1.85Ce0.15CuO 4−δ (PCCO). For YBCO and BSCCO, the values of λ(0) are in agreement with the <lb/>literature values. For PCCO λ ≈ 2790Å, reported for the first time. <lb/></front>

			<body>The London penetration depth, λ(T ), is a quantity <lb/>of fundamental importance. Its temperature, field, and <lb/>doping dependencies are directly related to the density <lb/>of quasiparticle energy states, knowledge of which is cru-<lb/>cial for testing models of pairing symmetry and mecha-<lb/>nisms of superconductivity 1 . λ(T ) is also a key param-<lb/>eter in determining the response and collective proper-<lb/>ties of the Abrikosov vortex lattice 2 . For single crys-<lb/>tals, measurements of the resonant frequency shift of a <lb/>microwave cavity 3,4,5,6 or tunnel diode oscillator 7,8,9,10 <lb/>provide the highest resolution for changes of the pene-<lb/>tration depth, ∆λ ≡ λ(T ) − λ(T min ), with respect to <lb/>temperature. For the sub-mm sized crystals typically <lb/>studied in high-T c work, resolution of better than 0.2Å <lb/>can be achieved 3,6,8,9 . However, the usual resonator ap-<lb/>proach has the disadvantage that it does not provide the <lb/>absolute magnitude of λ. This shortcoming arises from <lb/>various experimental uncertainties and is not an inher-<lb/>ent limitation of the resonator technique. As we show in <lb/>this paper, by suitably plating superconducting crystals <lb/>it is possible to exploit the extremely high sensitivity of <lb/>the resonator to changes in frequency and thus obtain an <lb/>absolute measurement of λ(T ). <lb/>The method described here permits a simultaneous <lb/>measurement of λ(T min ) and ∆λ(T ) on the same sam-<lb/>ple. The zero-temperature penetration depth, λ(0) can <lb/>be obtained by extrapolation to T = 0. Together, λ(0) <lb/>and ∆λ(T ) determine the normalized superfluid density <lb/>ρ s (T ) = (1 + ∆λ(T )/λ(0)) −2 , the quantity directly re-<lb/>lated to the electromagnetic response of the supercon-<lb/>ductor. This is a distinct advantage over the situation <lb/>in which these two quantities are obtained by different <lb/>groups using different samples and techniques. In addi-<lb/>tion, no new physical model is required to obtain λ(T ) <lb/>from the data, unlike the case with techniques such as <lb/>µSR or reversible magnetization. Our method has been <lb/>tested on single crystals of YBCO, BSCCO and PCCO <lb/>and compared with values of λ(T ) obtained from other <lb/>techniques. <lb/>It is first worth discussing why resonator methods can-<lb/>not normally determine the absolute penetration depth. <lb/>We focus on a lumped LC resonator but the ideas also <lb/>hold for a distributed device such as a microwave cavity. <lb/>In the absence of a superconducting sample the empty <lb/>resonant frequency is f 0 = 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>LC. When a supercon-<lb/>ducting sample is inserted into the resonator, the induc-<lb/>tance L decreases due to a decrease of the magnetic field <lb/>energy W m = LI 2 /2c 2 as a result of Meissner expulsion. <lb/>For a platelet sample of thickness 2d in the z− direction <lb/>and mean planar dimensions 2w × 2w in the x − y plane, <lb/>this leads to an increase of the frequency by an amount <lb/>∆f ≡ f (T ) − f (0) given by 9 , <lb/>∆f <lb/>f 0 <lb/>= <lb/>V s <lb/>2V 0 (1 − N ) <lb/>1 − <lb/>λ <lb/>R <lb/>tanh <lb/>R <lb/>λ <lb/>(1) <lb/>Here V s is the sample volume, V 0 is the effective volume <lb/>of the resonator, N is the demagnetization factor and the <lb/>field is applied along the z direction. R is the effective <lb/>sample dimension which depends upon field orientation <lb/>relative to the sample and sample geometry 9 . For the <lb/>standard &quot;Meissner&quot; configurations in which the field is <lb/>applied parallel to the surface of an infinite slab, N = 0 <lb/>and R = d. For the geometry used here, in which the AC <lb/>field is normal to the face of a platelet, R ≈ w/5 9 . <lb/>The measurement process is sketched in Fig. 1. The <lb/>superconducting sample is inserted into the resonator, re-<lb/>sulting in a change in frequency ∆f 0 . For typical HTSC <lb/>samples ∆f 0 10 4 Hz. In principle, if R were known pre-<lb/>cisely then one could use Eq. (1) together with the mea-<lb/>sured ∆f 0 to determine λ(0). Unfortunately, there are <lb/>several sources of error. First, the accuracy with which <lb/>∆f 0 can be determined is limited by repeatability. Ex-<lb/>tracting and inserting the sample in situ typically leads <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>empty resonator, =~10 Hz <lb/>f f 0 <lb/>7 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>static <lb/>uncertaintỹ <lb/>10 Hz <lb/>noisẽ <lb/>0.005 Hz <lb/>l(0) = 0 <lb/>l ¹ <lb/>(0) 0 <lb/>l(T&gt;0) <lb/>df <lb/>Df 0~ 10 Hz <lb/>4 <lb/>Df <lb/>±df 0 <lb/>FIG. 1: Frequency shifts encountered in resonance measure-<lb/>ments. The static uncertainty δf0 is usually greater than the <lb/>frequency shift due to finite λ(0). Relative frequency shift δf <lb/>is independent of δf0 and permits accurate measurements of <lb/>∆λ. <lb/>to an error of δf 0 ∼ 10 Hz out of a total ∆f ∼ 4 . <lb/>This &quot;static&quot; uncertainty is shown by the gray band in <lb/>Fig. 1. According to Eq. (1), the difference between <lb/>the perfect diamagnet and sample with finite λ is only <lb/>f 0 (1 − λ/R) ≈ 30 Hz for a typical YBCO crystal where <lb/>R ≥ 50 µm and λ(0) = 0.15 µm which is quite compara-<lb/>ble to the static uncertainty, δf 0 ≈ Hz. Furthermore, <lb/>extracting and inserting the sample gives the value of ∆f 0 <lb/>already reduced by finite λ(0). Other methods of estima-<lb/>tion of ∆f 0 such as measuring a ball made of a conven-<lb/>tional superconductor 7,8 or replicating an HTSC sample <lb/>using low-T c material 3 result even in greater uncertainty, <lb/>because in addition to an inevitable &quot;static&quot; uncertainty <lb/>between different runs there are additional uncertainties <lb/>related to differences between real sample and the sub-<lb/>stitute. Furthermore, realistic samples are irregular and <lb/>so have dimensions which are uncertain to much more <lb/>than λ(T ). They may also have large demagnetizing ef-<lb/>fects. Finally Eq. (1) itself involves approximations for <lb/>R that adds further error. It is therefore not feasible <lb/>to measure λ(T ) using resonator frequency shifts in the <lb/>straightforward manner outlined. Despite this limitation <lb/>on accuracy, the precision with which changes in λ can <lb/>be measured is much higher. This is illustrated in Fig. 1 <lb/>by the change ∆f upon warming the sample from low to <lb/>intermediate temperature. In this case the sample stays <lb/>fixed so the temperature-independent static uncertainty <lb/>is irrelevant. Only the oscillator noise matters, which is <lb/>typically 2000 times smaller than the static uncertainty. <lb/>It is therefore imperative to adopt a technique that keeps <lb/>the sample fixed. <lb/>Our method is illustrated in Fig. 2. The sample under <lb/>study is plated with a conventional low T c superconduc-<lb/>tor, in this case an Al film. The film thickness t should <lb/>be larger than λ(Al) but much smaller than the normal <lb/>state skin depth of Al (≈ 3 µm at the operating frequency <lb/>Al <lb/>HTSC <lb/>l(AL) <lb/>l(HTSC) + t <lb/>t <lb/>T &lt; T (Al) <lb/>c <lb/>T &gt; T (Al) <lb/>c <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>FIG. 2: Field penetration above and below transition temper-<lb/>ature of Al film. (a) T &lt; Tc(Al): magnetic field penetrates <lb/>only λ(Al). (b) T &gt; Tc(Al): magnetic field penetrates the Al <lb/>layer and HTSC superconductor λ(HT SC). <lb/>of 10 MHz). <lb/>Using λ = H −1 ∞ <lb/>0 B(x)dx we find that for T &lt; T c (Al) <lb/>the magnetic field penetrates to λ(T &lt; T c (Al)) = λ(Al)+ <lb/>exp (−t/λ(Al)) [λ(HT SC) − λ(Al)]. Above T c (Al) the <lb/>penetration depth is λ(T &gt; T c (Al)) = t + λ(HT SC). <lb/>Converting the frequency change ∆f = f (T &gt; T c (Al)) − <lb/>f (T &lt; T c (Al)) to a change in the effective penetration <lb/>depth, ∆λ, using Eq. (1), we obtain: <lb/>λ(HT SC) = λ(Al) + <lb/>∆λ − t <lb/>1 − exp (−t/λ(Al)) <lb/>(2) <lb/>The errors in this method arise from uncertainties in <lb/>the film thickness t, the resonator calibration constant <lb/>and λ(Al). Literature values for the effective penetra-<lb/>tion depth of aluminum films, λ(Al) ≈ λ L (Al) ξ(0)/ℓ <lb/>range from 400 to 600Å 13 . Here, the BCS coherence <lb/>length ξ(0) ≈ 16000Å, the mean free path, ℓ ≈ 1000Å <lb/>and the London penetration depth λ L (Al) ≈ 160Å. We <lb/>choose the commonly accepted value, λ(Al) ≈ 500 ± 100 <lb/>A. The Al film was 800 ± 50Å thick. Uncertainty in the <lb/>calibration constant gives an additional error of about <lb/>10Å giving a total error of approximately ±150Å. It <lb/>can be further reduced by choosing different coating ma-<lb/>terials, which will give additional independent reference <lb/>points and by varying the thickness of the coating layer. <lb/>Although it is clearly desirable to improve the accuracy, <lb/>an error of 150Å still results in only a 1% deviation <lb/>of ρ s over 20 K range for YBCO. A somewhat similar <lb/>measurement technique was used earlier to determine λ <lb/>in heavy fermion compounds 11,12 . In that experiment, a <lb/>flux trapped or screened by a thin Cd layer was used, but <lb/>owing to the much reduced sensitivity of SQUID mag-<lb/>netization measurements, it is not suitable for high-T c <lb/>materials. <lb/>λ(HT SC), was measured in three different super-<lb/>conductors: YBa Cu 3 O 7−δ (YBCO), Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ <lb/>0.0 0.4 0.8 1.2 1.6 <lb/>-500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>T c of <lb/>bulk Al <lb/>∆λ (Å ) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>-500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>∆λ (Å) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>

			FIG. 3: Penetration depth in single crystal YBCO calculated <lb/>from Eq. (2). Inset: Temperature range in which Al becomes <lb/>normal. <lb/>(BSCCO), and the electron-doped Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 4−δ <lb/>(PCCO). YBCO crystals were grown in yttria stabilized <lb/>zirconia crucibles as described 15 and annealed to achieve <lb/>maximal T c ≈ 93 K 15 . BSCCO samples where grown <lb/>using a floating zone process and had T c ≈ 89.5K 16 . <lb/>Single crystals of PCCO were grown using directional <lb/>solidification technique and annealed in argon to achieve <lb/>T c ≈ 22.5K 16 . The aluminum coating was applied with <lb/>a magnetron sputtering system with 5 cm rotated Al tar-<lb/>get ( 99.999 % purity). Sputtering was conducted in an <lb/>argon atmosphere and was homogeneous over 20 cm 2 . <lb/>The Al layer thickness, t, was calibrated using a Inficon <lb/>XTC 2 with 6 MHZ gold quartz crystal and later directly <lb/>measured using SEM edge imaging of a broken sample. <lb/>The measurement technique utilized a 10 MHz tunnel <lb/>diode oscillator whose specifications have been reported <lb/>previously 7,9 . Samples were mounted on a moveable sap-<lb/>phire stage whose temperature could be varied from 0.35 <lb/>to 100 K. The low base temperature was crucial in order <lb/>to obtain the full frequency shift due to the diamagnetism <lb/>of the Al film. <lb/>We first present experiments in YBCO single crystals. <lb/>Previous work has shown that λ(0) is anisotropic with <lb/>λ a (0) = 1600Å and λ b (0) = 800Å 6 . Since supercur-<lb/>rents for the H||c orientation flow along both a and b <lb/>axes, we obtain an average of λ a and λ b . Two crystals, <lb/>plated in separate evaporation runs, were measured. The <lb/>first is shown in Fig. 3. Note that contribution due to Al <lb/>film is subtracted using Eq. (2) and therefore the ∆λ(T ) <lb/>curve begins at negative values. Thus, at T = T c (Al), <lb/>λ(HT SC)(T c (Al)) is obtained. Linear extrapolation to <lb/>T = 0 yields λ(Y BCO) ≈ 1460Å. This value should be <lb/>compared to values obtained from µSR, 1405 ± 92Å 22 , <lb/>1550Å 23 , 1586 − 1699Å 24 ; polarized neutron reflectom-<lb/>etry, 1400 ± 100Å 25 ; magnetic susceptibility of grain -<lb/>aligned powder, 1400Å 26 and infrared spectroscopy, 1440 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>-500 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>3000 <lb/>3500 <lb/>PCCO <lb/>BSCCO <lb/>YBCO <lb/>∆λ (Å) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>FIG. 4: Penetration depth in (from bottom to top) YBCO, <lb/>BSCCO and PCCO single crystals. For YBCO and BSCCO <lb/>data were extrapolated using λ(T ) ∝ T , whereas for PCCO <lb/>λ(T ) ∝ T 2 dependence was used. <lb/>A 27 . Since T c (Al) is quite low and the Al plating in its <lb/>normal state is transparent to 10 MHz RF, it is possible <lb/>to monitor dλ(T )/dT of YBCO for T &gt; T c (Al). This is <lb/>an important check on the method since it is conceivable <lb/>that the Al coating might change the surface properties <lb/>of the cuprate enough to alter its penetration depth. The <lb/>slope dλ/dT ≈ 5.1Å/K. This slope is somewhat larger <lb/>than the value of 4.1Å/K reported previously 3,6,7 , but is <lb/>in agreement with our recent measurements conducted on <lb/>unplated samples in the H||ab configuration. The second <lb/>YBCO sample, shown in Fig. 4, gave λ(0) ≈ 1460Åand <lb/>dλ/dT ≈ 5.10Å/K, both within the estimated error with <lb/>the first sample. <lb/>The Inset to Fig. 3 shows details of the penetration <lb/>depth variation warming the sample above T c (Al). The <lb/>measured T c (Al) ≈ 1.69 K is significantly larger than the <lb/>bulk value T c (Al) ≈ 1.18 K 28 . This increase could be <lb/>due to proximity effects 29 , but could also be caused by <lb/>disorder and altered chemical composition of aluminum <lb/>film 28 . <lb/>Figure 4 summarizes the measurements for all three <lb/>cuprates. <lb/>For BSCCO-2212 crystal we obtained <lb/>λ(BSCCO) ≈ 2690Å, which can be compared to data <lb/>from: reversible magnetization, λ ≈ 2100Å 17 ; µSR, <lb/>λ ≈ 1800Å 18 ; and lower critical field measurements, <lb/>λ ≈ 2700Å 19 . It is clear that a fairly large disagreement <lb/>still exists over the value of λ(0) in this material. We <lb/>obtained a linear variation of λ(T ) with a dλ/dT ≈ 11.7 <lb/>A/K, compared to dλ/dT ≈ 10.5Å/K in previous mi-<lb/>crowave and µSR 20,21 . To within our current precision, <lb/>it appears that the Al plating has no effect on the elec-<lb/>trodynamics of the underlying cuprate superconductor. <lb/>The uppermost curve in Fig. 4 shows the results for <lb/>the electron-doped cuprate superconductor, PCCO. This <lb/>material has been cited as an example of a cuprate s-<lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>wave superconductor. Recent measurements with higher <lb/>resolution and lower temperatures have shown that <lb/>λ(T ) varies quadratically with temperature, indicative <lb/>of a nodal order parameter in the presence of impu-<lb/>rity scattering 10 . This is shown in the figure with <lb/>dλ/dT ≈ 4.38Å/K 2 . We find λ(0) ≈ 2790Å. The <lb/>only published value was obtained from measurements of <lb/>H c1 = Φ 0 /[4πλ(0) 2 ] ln κ which gave λ(0) ≈ 1000Å 30 . It <lb/>is difficult to reliably determine H c1 in thin crystals owing <lb/>to demagnetization and pinning surface barrier effects. <lb/>Our approach is arguably more reliable since no DC fields <lb/>or vortices are involved and we have obtained close agree-<lb/>ment with other methods in YBCO and BSCCO. <lb/>In conclusion, we have developed a new technique <lb/>to measure λ(T ) in high−T c superconductors. We ob-<lb/>tained λ(0) = 1390 and 1460Å for two YBCO crys-<lb/>tals, λ(0) = 2690Å for BSCCO, and λ(0) = 2790Å <lb/>for PCCO. All values are determined with the ±150Å <lb/>accuracy. The plating has no discernable effect on the <lb/>underlying temperature dependence of λ(T ). The accu-<lb/>racy of the method is limited principally by uncertainties <lb/>in the Al film thickness. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank P. J. Hirschfeld for pointing out Ref.[11,12]. <lb/>Work at Urbana was supported by the Science and Tech-<lb/>nology Center for Superconductivity Grant No. NSF-<lb/>DMR 91-20000. Work at Maryland was supported by <lb/>NSF Grant No. NSF-DMR 97-32736. Work at Argonne <lb/>was supported by U.S. DOE-BES Contract No. W-31-<lb/>109-ENG-38 and NSF-STCS Contract No. DMR 91-<lb/>20000 <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1 For example: J. F. Annett, N. D. Goldenfeld, and S. Renn, <lb/>in Physical Properties of High Temperature Superconduc-<lb/>tors II, edited by D. M. Ginsberg (World Scientific, New <lb/>Jersey, 1990). <lb/>2 For example, G. Blatter et. al., Rev. Mod. Phys. 66, 1125 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>3 W. N. Hardy et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, 3999 (1993). <lb/>S. M. Anlage et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 523 (1994). <lb/>5 A. Hosseini et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 81, 1298 (1998). <lb/>S. Kamal et al., Phys. Rev. B 58, R8933 (1998). <lb/>7 A. Carrington et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 4172 (1999). <lb/>A. Carrington et. al., Phys. Rev. B 59, R14173 (1999). <lb/>9 R. Prozorov et al., Phys. Rev. B, 62, 115 (2000). <lb/>R. Prozorov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. submitted (2000); <lb/>cond-mat/0002301. <lb/>11 F. Gross, K. Andres, and B. S. Chandrasekhar, Physica C <lb/>162-164, 419 (1989). <lb/>12 F. Groß-Alltag, B. S. Chandrasekhar, D. Einzel, P. J. <lb/>Hirschfeld, and K. Andres, Z. Phys. B 82, 243 (1991). <lb/>J. Romijn et. al. Phys. Rev. B 26, 3648 (1982); P. M. <lb/>Tedrow, G. Faraci, and R. Meservey, Phys. Rev. B 4, 74 <lb/>(1971); <lb/>14 P. Guptasarma and D. G. Hinks, Bull. Am. Phys. Soc. 42, <lb/>713 (1997). <lb/>S. E. Stupp and D. M. Ginsberg, in Physical Properties of <lb/>High Temperature Superconductors III, edited by D. M. <lb/>Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1992). <lb/>16 J. L. Peng et al., Physica C 177 79 (1991); M. Brinkman <lb/>et al., J. of Cryst. Growth 163 (1996). <lb/>V. G. Kogan et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, 1870 (1993). <lb/>S. L. Lee et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 3862 (1993). <lb/>M. Nideröst et. al. Phys. Rev. Lett. 81, 3231 (1998). <lb/>T. Jacobs et. al.,Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, 4516 (1995); <lb/>Shih-Fu Lee et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 735 (1996). <lb/>D. A. Bonn et. al., Phys. Rev. B 47, 11314 (1993). <lb/>23 J. L. Tallon et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 74, 1008 (1995). <lb/>J. E. Sonier et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 2875 (1997). <lb/>V. Lauter-Pasyuk et. al., Physica B 248, 166 (1998). <lb/>C. Panagopoulos, J. R. Cooper, and T. Xiang, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 57, 13422 (1998). <lb/>27 D. N. Basov et. al., Phys. Rev. B 49, 12165 (1994). <lb/>28 CRC Handbook of Chemistry and Physics, page 12-65, <lb/>edited by D. R. Lide, (CRC Press, London, 1999). <lb/>29 M. E. Farrell and M. F. Bishop, Phys. Rev. B 40, 10786 <lb/>(1989). <lb/>30 A. F. T. Hoekstra et. al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 4293 (1998); <lb/>A. F. Th. Hoekstra et. al., Physica C 282-287, 2265 <lb/>(1997). </listBibl>

	</text>
</tei>
