<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="art_fin"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Nonlinear stability of a Vlasov equation for magnetic <lb/>plasmas <lb/> Fr´édérique Charles, Bruno Després, Benoˆ t Perthame, Remi Sentis <lb/> To cite this version: <lb/> Frédérique Charles, Bruno Després, Benoˆ t Perthame, Remi Sentis. Nonlinear stability of <lb/>a Vlasov equation for magnetic plasmas. Kinetic and Related Models (KRM), 2013, 6 (2), <lb/>pp.269 -290. &lt;http://www.aimsciences.org/journals/displayArticlesnew.jsp?paperID=8318&gt;. <lb/> &lt;10.3934/krm.2013.6.269&gt;. &lt;hal-00689810&gt; <lb/> HAL Id: hal-00689810 <lb/>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-00689810 <lb/> Submitted on 20 Apr 2012 <lb/> HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access <lb/>archive for the deposit and dissemination of sci-<lb/>entific research documents, whether they are pub-<lb/>lished or not. The documents may come from <lb/>teaching and research institutions in France or <lb/>abroad, or from public or private research centers. <lb/>L&apos;archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est <lb/>destinée au dépôt et a la diffusion de documents <lb/>scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, <lb/>´ emanant des etablissements d&apos;enseignement et de <lb/>recherche français oú etrangers, des laboratoires <lb/>publics ou privés. <lb/></titlePage> 
			
			<front>Nonlinear stability of a Vlasov equation for magnetic plasmas <lb/> Frédérique Charles  * † <lb/> Bruno Després  * ‡ <lb/> Benoît Perthame  * § <lb/> Rémi Sentis  ¶ <lb/> April 20, 2012 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> The mathematical description of laboratory fusion plasmas produced in Tokamaks is still challenging. Com-<lb/>plete models for electrons and ions, as Vlasov-Maxwell systems, are computationally too expensive because they <lb/>take into account all details and scales of magneto-hydrodynamics. In particular, for most of the relevant stud-<lb/>ies, the mass electron is negligible and the velocity of material waves is much smaller than the speed of light. <lb/>Therefore it is useful to understand simplified models. Here we propose and study one of those which keeps <lb/>both the complexity of the Vlasov equation for ions and the Hall effect in Maxwell&apos;s equation. Based on energy <lb/>dissipation, a fundamental physical property, we show that the model is nonlinear stable and consequently prove <lb/>existence. <lb/> Key words: Vlasov equations; Plasma physics; Kinetic averaging lemma; Maxwell&apos;s equations. <lb/> Mathematics Subject Classification: 35B35, 35L60, 82D10 <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> To describe the behavior of ions population in hot plasmas, it is very classical to address, at least at theoretical <lb/>level, a Vlasov equation coupled to a non-linear Poisson equation which defines the electrostatic field. When the <lb/>magnetic field B is an external datum, for the ion distribution function f (t, x, v) (at position x and velocity v), <lb/> one addresses the following system <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/>.[(−T  e  ln n  e  +v ∧ B) f ] = 0, <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ln n  e  = <lb/> f (v)dv−n  e  , <lb/> where n  e  = n  e  (t, x) is the electron density, T  e  is the mean electron temperature assumed to be constant and λ is the <lb/>Debye length (a characteristic constant of the plasma). This system is a classical one, indeed the electrostatic field <lb/>may be approximated by −T  e  ln n  e  (at least when the electron temperature is constant) and the Poisson equation <lb/>is nothing but the Gauss relation applied to this field (cf. [7] for example) <lb/>The mathematical understanding of this kind of kinetic system has made important progresses with the proof of <lb/>existence of global weak solutions in the large of the Vlasov-Maxwell system in [11] and of the Vlasov-Poisson system <lb/>[19, 25]. However, the mathematical description of laboratory fusion plasmas (such as those produced in Tokamaks) <lb/>with this kind of ion kinetic models is still a major challenge, in particular to deal with a time scale compatible with <lb/>the evolution equation for the magnetic field. As a matter of fact, complete systems of Vlasov-Maxwell type which <lb/>account for all scales of electro-dynamics are not relevant since the velocity of ion waves is much smaller than the <lb/>speed of light: it is well known that at the time scale of the ion population it is convenient to neglect the current <lb/>of displacement in the Maxwell equations (as in magneto-hydrodynamics models cf. [20, 21]), that is to say the <lb/>electric current J is assumed to satisfy <lb/> </body> 
			
			<front>*  UPMC-Paris06, CNRS UMR 7598, Laboratoire Jacques-Louis Lions, 4, pl. Jussieu F75252 Paris cedex 05. <lb/></front>  
			
			<front>†  Email: charles@ann.jussieu.fr <lb/></front>  
			
			<front>‡  Email: despres@ann.jussieu.fr <lb/></front>  
			
			<front>§  INRIA Rocquencourt EPI BANG. Email: benoit.perthame@upmc.fr <lb/></front>  
			
			<front>¶  CEA Bruyères-le-Chatel. Email: remi.sentis@CEA.FR <lb/></front> 
			
			<page>1 <lb/></page> 
			
			<body>J =  ∧ B. <lb/> The aim of this work is precisely to propose, justify and study a model which couples a kinetic equation for the <lb/>ions and an evolution equation for the magnetic field (as those used in magneto-hydrodynamics). The unknowns <lb/>are the ion particle density f (t, x, v), the magnetic field B(t, x) and the electron density n  e  (t, x) and they satisfy <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e  , <lb/> (a) <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> − ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  I  u  I  ∧ B <lb/> + ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> J ∧ B <lb/> + ∧ (η ∧ B) = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v · f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> · <lb/> − <lb/> T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e  + <lb/> J − n  I  u  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ B + v ∧ B <lb/> f <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(c) <lb/> · B = 0, <lb/>(d) <lb/> (1) <lb/>where the following notations are used <lb/> n  I  (t, x) = <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)dv <lb/> (the number density in ions), <lb/>(2) <lb/> n  I  (t, x)u  I  (t, x) = <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)vdv <lb/> (the macroscopic velocity of ions). <lb/>(3) <lb/>and η denotes a strictly positive bounded function corresponding to the plasma resistivity. <lb/>Notice firstly that the electric field E is given by the relation <lb/> n  e  E = −T  e  n  e  − n  I  u  I  ∧ B + J ∧ B + n  e  η ∧ B <lb/> (4) <lb/>which is one of the classical forms of the generalized Ohm law [7, 3, 2, 14] (it includes the term J ∧ B related to <lb/>the Hall effect); so, (1)-b) is exactly the Faraday equation  ∂B <lb/>∂t  + ∧ E = 0. <lb/> We have chosen here a rescaling, such that the ion mass is set to 1 and the electron and ion charge are also set <lb/>to 1. Moreover the scaling of the ion and electron density is such that the characteristic value of n  I  is equal to 1. So <lb/>with this scaling, the Debye length λ is defined by λ  2  = T  e  ε  0  where ε  0  is vacuum dielectric constant and equation <lb/>(1)-a) reads also as <lb/> −ε  0  T  e  ∆ ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e <lb/> which is Gauss relation applied to −T  e  ln n  e  , the dominant term in the electric field. In the rest of the paper, we <lb/>use the following notations <lb/> E  0  (t, x) = −T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> (J − n  I  u  I  ) ∧ B <lb/> and <lb/> F(t, x, v) = E  0  + v ∧ B. <lb/> (5) <lb/>Here F is the kinetic force field which appears in equation (1)-c). <lb/> Remark 1. It is fundamental to notice that the Debye length is a small quantity in many situations; it may be <lb/>proved that in the limit λ → 0 the solution n  e  to the non-linear Poisson equation satisfies n  e  → n  I  and many studies <lb/>have analyzed this singular limit in different contexts [4, 8, 18]. Then, if we make the approximation n  e  n  I  , the <lb/>Ohm law (4) leads to the classical formula <lb/> E + u  I  ∧ B = −T  e  ln n  I  + <lb/>1 <lb/> n  I <lb/> ( ∧ B) ∧ B + η ∧ B <lb/> and from (1), we recover formerly the following system <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> − ∧ (u  I  ∧ B) + ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  I <lb/> ( ∧ B) ∧ B) <lb/> + ∧ (η ∧ B) = 0, <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (E  lim  + v ∧ B)f <lb/> = 0, <lb/> n  I  (E  lim  + u  I  ∧ B) = −T  e  n  I  + ( ∧ B) ∧ B. <lb/> Despite its apparently simpler form than the system (1), it is not used in physical literature, up to our knowledge. <lb/>As a matter of fact even if the magnetic field is neglected, the equation <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (E  lim  + v ∧ B)f <lb/> = 0, n  I  E  lim  = −T  e  n  I <lb/>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			is probably ill-posed from a mathematical point of view (nevertheless [18] has noticed that using some arguments of <lb/>the paper [22], one may find a weak solution on a small time interval). Moreover it would be hard to give a meaning <lb/>of the quantity u  I  = <lb/> R  3  f (v)vdv/ <lb/> R  3  f (v)dv which appears in the magnetic equation (it is hardly possible to <lb/>derive a bound of n  I  away from below). Notice that this kind of model has been addressed in [16] and [1] but <lb/>the framework is a little different since a velocity diffusion term (of Fokker-Planck type) is accountered for in the <lb/>kinetic equation. <lb/>Back to (1), from a mathematical point of view, one can show that n  e  is naturally bounded away from zero due <lb/>to the nonlinear elliptic equation (1)-a and the quantity  nI <lb/>ne  u  I  = n  −1 <lb/> e <lb/> R  3  f (v)vdv may be defined in some Lebesgue <lb/>space. <lb/>Our study is aiming at the analysis of model (1) in a bounded domain; therefore we have to specify the boundary <lb/>and initial conditions. <lb/> Boundary conditions Let Ω be a bounded domain of R  3  of class C  1,1  . We consider the model (1) for v ∈ R  3  , <lb/> x ∈ Ω and t ≥ 0, with the following boundary conditions <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> n  x  · n  e  (t, x) = 0 <lb/> x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> (a) <lb/> n  x  ∧ B(t, x) = 0 <lb/> x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> (b) <lb/> f (x, v − 2(v · n  x  )n  x  ) = f (x, v), <lb/>v ∈ R  3  , x ∈ ∂Ω. <lb/> (c) <lb/> (6) <lb/>The zero flux boundary conditions (6)-a) on electrons enforces in (1)-a) the global neutrality of the plasma <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  e  dx = <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  i  dx. <lb/> The condition (b) on the magnetic field is the simplest one and a more realistic condition is discussed in section 4. <lb/>Our result will be still true with more realistic boundary condition, of impedance type for example, or also a non <lb/>homogeneous boundary condition such as <lb/> n  x  ∧ B(t, x) = n  x  ∧ B  imp  , x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> which is much more relevant in the context of confined plasmas in Tokamaks. Condition (6)-c) is the so-called <lb/>specular reflection; it implies the no-slip boundary condition <lb/> u  I  (t, x) · n  x  = 0, x ∈ ∂Ω. <lb/> (7) <lb/>Our main result is the following. <lb/> Theorem 1 (Nonlinear stability). Assume (14) and that the initial datum satisfy (11)–(13). From any bounded <lb/>family of solutions f  ε  , B  ε  , n  ε <lb/>e  to (1), (6) we can extract a subsequence that converges to a weak solution with finite <lb/>energy. Moreover, we have for all T &gt; 0, <lb/> B  ε  → B ∈ L  ∞  <lb/> 0, T ; L  2  (Ω) <lb/> ∩ L  2  <lb/> 0, T ; L  q  (Ω) <lb/> strongly, <lb/> q &lt; 6, <lb/> f  ε  → f ∈ L  ∞  <lb/> 0, T ; L  1  ∩ L  ∞  (Ω × R  3  )) <lb/> weakly, <lb/> J  ε  = ∧ B  ε  → J in L  2  ((0, T ) × Ω) weakly, <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e  → n  e  in L  q  ((0, T ) × Ω), strongly and for some constants 0 &lt; K  −  ≤ n  e  ≤ K  +  , <lb/>n  ε <lb/>I  u  ε <lb/>I  → n  I  u  I  ∈ (L  q  (0, T × Ω))  3  strongly, <lb/> for all q such that 1 ≤ q &lt; 5/4. <lb/> The first tool towards a mathematical analysis is to state the energy balance for the full system; this is performed <lb/>in section 2. It indicates that the magnetic resistivity in equation (1)-a) is useful (if not necessary) so as to control the <lb/>current J and subsequently the term J ∧ B describing to the Hall effect. Also the classical tools for elliptic equation <lb/>with Neumann boundary conditions will lead to control n  e  away from below. But more technical ingredients (namely <lb/>a kinetic averaging lemma in a L  q  space) are used in the proof in order to pass to the limit in the nonlinearities; <lb/>this is the purpose of section 3 and of several appendices. We come back on more realistic boundary conditions <lb/>in section 4 so as to include confinement. We also detail a constructive splitting procedure which can be used to <lb/>design an approximate solution with the same energy law. <lb/>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			2 Preliminaries <lb/> The first and major ingredient in our approach to nonlinear stability is the energy balance. We state it here together <lb/>with considerations on the physics sustaining the model. <lb/> 2.1 The energy balance <lb/> We now turn to the study of energy dissipation for the system (1) with homogeneous boundary conditions (6). We <lb/>introduce the ions kinetic energy and the magnetic energy <lb/> E  I  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx, <lb/> E  m  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> |B(t, x)|  2  dx, <lb/> as well as the free energy <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  (t) ln n  e  (t) − n  e  (t) + 1)dx and the total energy which reads as <lb/> E  tot  (t) = E  I  (t) + E  m  (t) + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> || ln n  e  (t)|  2  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  (t) ln n  e  (t) − n  e  (t) + 1)dx. <lb/> (8) <lb/>Notice that the integral <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> || ln n  e  (t)| <lb/> 2  dx corresponds to the electrostatic energy. We now establish the <lb/> Proposition 1 (Energy dissipation). Classical solutions to (1), (6) satisfy the energy dissipation relation <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  I  + E  m  + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> || (ln n  e  )|  2  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  ln n  e  − n  e  + 1) dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx. <lb/> (9) <lb/> Proof. Notice that, as usual, the free divergence condition (1)-(d) is not needed for the energy identity. We first <lb/>consider the ion kinetic energy. Using the specular reflection condition, we compute <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  I  = <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> F(t, x, v) · vdv <lb/> = <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> ( ∧ B) ∧ B + (v − <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> u  I  ) ∧ B − T  e  (ln n  e  ) <lb/> f <lb/> · vdvdx <lb/> = <lb/> Ω <lb/>  n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> J ∧ B − n  I  T  e  (ln n  e  ) <lb/> · u  I  dx. <lb/> Now, we turn to the magnetic energy and first recall the definition of E in (4). Thanks to a classical tensorial <lb/>identity, we find <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  m  = <lb/> Ω <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> · Bdx = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> ∧ E · Bdx = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> [E · ∧ B + · (E ∧ B)]dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> − <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> u  I  ∧ B + η ∧ B <lb/> · ( ∧ B) dx − <lb/> ∂Ω <lb/> n  x  · (E ∧ B)dx. <lb/> According to the boundary condition (6)-(b), we have n  x  · (E ∧ B) = −E · (n  x  ∧B) = 0, then the boundary integral <lb/>is zero. Now, thanks to identity J · (u  I  ∧ B) = −u  I  · (J ∧ B), we get <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  m  = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> u  I  · (J ∧ B)dx − <lb/> R  3 <lb/> η <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx. <lb/> At this stage, we have obtained <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> [E  i  + E  m  ] = <lb/> Ω <lb/> [(J ∧ B) − n  I  (ln n  e  )] · u  I  dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> u  I  · (J ∧ B)dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω  n  I  (ln n  e  ) · u  I  dx − <lb/> Ω  η <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx. <lb/> (10) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> To continue, we recall the conservation of mass on n  I <lb/> ∂n  I <lb/> ∂t <lb/> +  · (n  I  u  I  ) = 0. <lb/> Then, we may use the boundary condition (7) to obtain <lb/> − <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  I  (ln n  e  ) · u  I  dx = <lb/> Ω <lb/> (ln n  e  ) · (n  I  u  I  ) dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> (ln n  e  ) <lb/> ∂n  I <lb/> ∂t <lb/>dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> (ln n  e  ) <lb/> ∂n  e <lb/> ∂t <lb/> − λ  2  ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> ∆ (ln n  e  ) <lb/> dx <lb/> = − <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  (ln n  e  ) − n  e  ) dx <lb/> − λ  2  d <lb/>dt <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||(ln n  e  )|  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx <lb/> where we have used equation (1)-(a) once differentiated in time. <lb/>Altogether, we obtain the relation (9). <lb/> 2.2 Physical considerations <lb/> Let first focus on the momentum balance. To find it, we multiply the kinetic equation (1)-c) by v, integrate over <lb/> R  3  and define as usual [6] the ion pressure tensor P  I  through <lb/> · (v ⊗ vf (v))dv = · (n  I  u  I  ⊗ u  I  ) + · P  I  . <lb/> Then, we get <lb/> ∂(n  I  u  I  ) <lb/> ∂t <lb/> + · (n  I  u  I  ⊗ u  I  ) + · P  I  + T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  I  + <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  I  u  I  ∧ B − <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> J ∧ B − n  I  u  I  ∧ B = 0, <lb/> that is to say <lb/> ∂(n  I  u  I  ) <lb/> ∂t <lb/> + · (n  I  u  I  ⊗ u  I  ) + · P  I  + T  e  n  e  − J ∧ B = <lb/>(n  e  − n  I  ) <lb/> n  e <lb/> [T  e  n  e  + (n  I  u  I  − J) ∧ B] . <lb/> On the left hand side one recognizes the classical momentum equation which appears in the MHD modeling with <lb/>the magnetic pressure tensor. Let us stress that with the electric field E  0  introduced in (5) and according to (1)-a), <lb/>the r.h.s. term reads as follows <lb/> ε  0 <lb/> · E  0  + · <lb/> n  I  u  I  − J <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> E  0  = ε  0  · <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> |E  0  |  2  − E  0  ⊗ E  0 <lb/> + λ  2  E  0  · <lb/> n  I  u  I  − J <lb/> n  e  T  e <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> . <lb/> Thus we may see that this equation is in a conservative form only when the Debye length vanishes. This is due <lb/>to the asymptotic expansion motivating ( 1); we have chosen to keep energy dissipation and smoothness for n  e  to <lb/>the expense of momentum balance. In order to ensure exact conservation momentum, a possible route is to use a <lb/>modified Poisson equation as follows <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e  − λ  2  · <lb/> J − n  I  u  I <lb/> n  e  T  e <lb/> ∧ B <lb/> which corresponds to an approximation at the same order but which looses nice properties on n  e  . <lb/> Remark 2 (Electron momentum balance). We see that E  0  is equal to the electric field E up to the resistive part <lb/> η ∧ B. Let us stress that ( ∧ B)−n  I  u  I  = J − n  I  u  I  is the electron contribution to the electric current and (4) <lb/>may be interpreted as the electron momentum balance equation when using the massless electron approximation. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Remark 3 (Friction). In order to account for the friction between ions and electrons in the kinetic equation, we <lb/>could add a friction term to equation (1)-c) and arrive to <lb/> ∂f <lb/> ∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/>.(Ff ) = − <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (ηJf ) <lb/> (recall that the coefficient η is related to the collision frequency of electrons against ions). Also, for the sake of <lb/>compatibility, instead of equation (1)-a), the Poisson equation would read <lb/> λ  2  <lb/> − ∆ ln n  e  + <lb/>1 <lb/> T  e <lb/> (ηJ) <lb/> = n  I  − n  e  . <lb/> 3 Proof of the stability theorem <lb/> We give a family of initial conditions that satisfy <lb/> f  ε  (0, x, v) = f  in,ε  (x, v) ≥ 0, <lb/> f  in,ε  is bounded in L  1  ∩ L  ∞  (Ω × R  3  ), <lb/> (11) <lb/> B  ε  (0, x) = B  in,ε  (x), <lb/>  x  · B  in,ε  = 0. <lb/> (12) <lb/>From the Lemma 1 in Appendix A and the explanations in Appendix B we see that if E  I  (0) is uniformly bounded <lb/>then the free energy at initial time <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||  x  (ln n  ε <lb/>e  (0, x))| <lb/> 2  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e  (0, x) ln n  ε <lb/>e  (0, x)dx is also uniformly bounded. <lb/>Then we only need to assume that <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/> [E  I  (0) + E  m  (0)] &lt; ∞ <lb/> (13) <lb/>to have a total energy uniformly bounded for all time. Moreover we assume a control on resistivity as <lb/> 0 &lt; η  min  ≤ η ∈ L  ∞  (Ω). <lb/> (14) <lb/>Associated with such initial datum, we consider a sequence of strong solutions f  ε  , B  ε  , and n  ε <lb/>e  of (1) with boundary <lb/>conditions (6). <lb/> 3.1 A priori bounds <lb/> Before we begin the proof of Theorem 1, we recall several general a priori estimates that are used. The energy <lb/>bound (13) is of course at the heart of our analysis because it allows us to deduce directly from the estimate (9) the <lb/> Proposition 2 (Bounds derived from energy). Under the assumptions (11)–(14), the sequences f  ε  , B  ε  , and n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> satisfy <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/> sup <lb/> t∈[0,∞] <lb/> R  3 <lb/> Ω <lb/> f  ε <lb/>i  (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx &lt; ∞, <lb/> (15) <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/> sup <lb/> t∈[0,∞] <lb/> Ω <lb/> |B  ε  (t, x)|  2  dx &lt; ∞, <lb/> (16) <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/> sup <lb/> t∈[0,∞] <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||  x  (ln |n  ε <lb/>e  |)| <lb/> 2  + n  ε <lb/>e  ln |n  ε <lb/>e  | + n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> dx &lt; ∞. <lb/> (17) <lb/>Indeed, for (17), we use the fact that the map x ∈ R → x ln(x) − x is bound from below and thus all the terms <lb/>in (9) are bounded by the initial energy plus a constant. <lb/>This provides a control on the kinetic energy for the ion distribution that is essential to obtain further a priori <lb/>bounds <lb/> Proposition 3 (Estimates for the kinetic densities). For strong solutions one has f  ε  ∈ L  ∞  <lb/> 0, ∞; L  1  ∩ L  ∞  (Ω × R  3  ) <lb/> and <lb/> f  ε  (t, ·, ·)  p  = f  in,ε  (·, ·)  p  ∀t ≥ 0, ∀p ∈ [1, ∞], <lb/>n  ε <lb/>I  (t, ·)  5/3  ≤ Cf  in,ε  (·, ·)  2/5 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx <lb/>  3/5 <lb/> , <lb/> n  ε <lb/>I  u  ε <lb/>I  (t, ·)  5/4  ≤ Cf  in,ε  (·, ·)  1/5 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx <lb/>  4/5 <lb/> . <lb/> (18) <lb/>6 <lb/> The bounds of f  ε  follow immediately from the observation that div  v  F = 0. The bounds on n  ε <lb/>I  and n  ε <lb/>I  u  ε <lb/>I  follow <lb/>from interpolation inequalities that we recall in the Appendix A. <lb/>Next we use the L  5/3  integrability of n  I  to obtain <lb/> Proposition 4 (Estimates on the electron density). The electron density satisfies for some constants K  +  &gt; 0, <lb/> K  −  &gt; 0 (depending on the bounds stated as now) <lb/> 0 &lt; K  −  ≤ n  e  (t, x) ≤ K  +  . <lb/> (19) <lb/>This is an easy consequence of elliptic regularity and we give a proof in the Appendix B, it is just a combination <lb/>of Lemma 1 and Lemma 2. <lb/>We now come to the magnetic field. We have the following Proposition : <lb/> Proposition 5 (Estimate on the magnetic field). The family of magnetic fields satisfies for a uniform constant C <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/>  ∞ <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/>x ∧ B  ε <lb/> 2 <lb/> dxdt ≤ C, <lb/> sup <lb/> 0&lt;ε≤1 <lb/> B  ε   L  2 <lb/> 0,∞;L  6  (Ω) <lb/>  ≤ C. <lb/> (20) <lb/> Proof. The control in L  2  (0, ∞; H  curl  (Ω)), follows from the energy dissipation in Proposition 1. Then thanks to <lb/>Theorem 2, the family B  ε  is bounded in L  2  (0, ∞; H  1  (Ω)  3  ), and then, thanks to the Sobolev injections, the family <lb/> B  ε  is bounded in L  2  (0, ∞; L  6  (Ω)  3  <lb/> . We refer to Appendix C for precise statements and references. <lb/>Our last task is to show that we have enough bounds to define the electric and force fields. The four terms that <lb/>compose the electric field <lb/> E  ε  = −T  e  ln n  ε <lb/>e  − <lb/> n  ε <lb/>I  u  ε <lb/>I <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> ∧ B  ε  + <lb/> J  ε  ∧ B  ε <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> + η ∧ B  ε <lb/> are respectively uniformly bounded in the spaces <lb/> • T  e  ln n  ε <lb/>e  ∈ L  ∞ <lb/> t  (L  2 <lb/> x  ) (energy inequality), <lb/> • <lb/> n  ε <lb/>I  u  ε <lb/>I <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> ∧B  ε  ∈ L  2 <lb/> t  (L  30/29 <lb/> x <lb/> ); this follows from (18), (19) and (20) and the fact that, according to Hölder inequality, <lb/>we get the bound <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> [AB  30/29  ]  2  dt ≤ <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> [A  5/4  B  6  ]  2  dt ≤ sup <lb/> t <lb/> A <lb/> 2 <lb/>5/4 <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> [B  6  ]  2  dt. <lb/> • <lb/> J  ε  ∧ B  ε <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> ∈ L  1 <lb/> t  (L  3/2 <lb/> x  ) ∩ L  2 <lb/> t  (L  1 <lb/> x  ) from the Hölder inequality with (19) and the a priori estimates in Proposition 5. <lb/>By interpolation, we also find that <lb/> J  ε  ∧ B  ε <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> ∈ L  r <lb/>t  (L  p <lb/>x  ), <lb/>1 ≤ r ≤ 2, <lb/>1 <lb/> p <lb/> = <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3r <lb/> . <lb/> In particular <lb/> J  ε  ∧ B  ε <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> ∈ L <lb/> 20/11 <lb/> t <lb/> (L  30/29 <lb/> x <lb/> ). <lb/> • η ∧ B  ε  ∈ L  2 <lb/> t,x  (energy dissipation). <lb/>Therefore it is well defined and the four terms will have a weak limit in Lebesgue spaces. <lb/>For the kinetic force field, <lb/> F  ε  (t, x, v) := −T  e  ln n  ε <lb/>e  + <lb/> v − <lb/> n  ε <lb/>I <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> u  ε <lb/>I <lb/> ∧ B  ε  + <lb/> J  ε  ∧ B  ε <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e <lb/> , <lb/> the same integrability, locally uniformly in v, holds true because these are the same terms and thus they are bounded <lb/>as for the electric field at the exception of v ∧ B  ε  which is well defined thanks to (16). <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body> 3.2 Space-time compactness <lb/> The bounds mentioned before allow us to extract subsequences that converge weakly and our task is now to prove <lb/>several strong convergence results. <lb/>We first observe that, from Proposition 5 and (16), we may extract a subsequence, still denoted by B  ε  such that <lb/> B  ε  −→ <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> B strongly in L  p  (0, T ; L  q  (Ω)  3  <lb/> , 1 ≤ p &lt; 2, 1 ≤ q &lt; 6, and 1 ≤ p &lt; ∞, 1 ≤ q &lt; 2. <lb/> (21) <lb/>This is because (see Appendix C) thanks to our a priori estimates and Theorem 2, the field {B  ε  } is bounded in <lb/> L  1  (0, T, H  1  (Ω)  3  ), and then, thanks to Rellich Theorem, {B  ε  (t, ·)} is relatively compact in L  6  (Ω)  3  for all t ∈]0, T [). <lb/> Compactness in time then follows from the Simon-Lions-Aubin lemma (see [28]) because, as proved at the end of <lb/>section (3.1), we control L  r <lb/>t  (L  p <lb/>x  ) integrability of the electric field and <lb/> ∂B  ε <lb/> ∂t <lb/> = ∧ E  ε  . <lb/> According to the kinetic averaging lemma recalled in Appendix D, we know that after extraction of a subsequence, <lb/>for every test function ψ = ψ(v) compactly supported, there exists a weak limit f  *  of f  ε  such that <lb/> ψf  ε  → ψf  *   a.e. and ψvf  ε  → ψvf  *   a.e. <lb/> Now, since <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> | ψf  ε  |  5/3  dxdt and <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> | ψvf  ε  |  5/4  dxdt are uniformly bounded, according to classical inter-<lb/>polation arguments we have for given exponents q and r (with 1 &lt; q &lt; 5/3 and 1 &lt; r &lt; 5/4) <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> | ψf  ε  − ψf  *  |  q  dxdt → 0, and <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> | ψvf  ε  − ψvf  *  |  r  dxdt → 0. <lb/> Therefore we get <lb/> n  ε <lb/>I  −→ <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> n  I  , strongly in L  q  (0, T ; Ω), <lb/> (22) <lb/> n  I  u  ε <lb/>I  −→ <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> n  I  u  I  strongly in L  r  (0, T ; Ω)  3  . <lb/> (23) <lb/>Next for the electronic density we may extract a subsequence, still denoted n  ε <lb/>e  such that, <lb/> n  ε <lb/>e  −→ <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> n  e  a.e. and strongly in L  q  (0, T ; Ω)  3  . <lb/> (24) <lb/>This is a consequence of the bounds (17) and (19) and the strong convergence (22). <lb/> 3.3 Passing to the limit <lb/> We recall that a weak (distributional) solution to (1) is defined by testing against smooth test functions Ψ(t, x), <lb/> Φ(t, x, v) respectively for (1)-b) and (1)-c) and satisfying the corresponding boundary conditions as in (6). <lb/>After integration by parts, we obtain respectively for (1)-b) and (1)-c), the definitions <lb/> − <lb/> (0,T )×Ω <lb/>  ∂Ψ(t, x) <lb/>∂t <lb/> B  ε  + E  ε  (t, x) · ∧ Ψ(t, x) <lb/> dtdx = <lb/> Ω <lb/> B  in,ε  (x, v)Ψ(0, x), <lb/> (25) <lb/>and <lb/> − <lb/> (0,T )×Ω×R  3 <lb/>  ∂Φ(t, x, v) <lb/> ∂t <lb/> +v ·  x  Φ(t, x, v) + F  ε  (t, x, v) ·  v  Φ(t, x, v) <lb/> f  ε  (t, x, v)dtdxdv <lb/> = <lb/> Ω×R  3 <lb/> f  in,ε  (x, v)Φ(0, x, v). <lb/> (26) <lb/>The elliptic equation (1)-a) is more standard and does not yield difficulties, hence we do not consider it here. In <lb/>order to conclude the proof of Theorem 1, our purpose is to show that the limit as ε → 0 of the various unknowns <lb/> B  ε  , E  ε  (t, x), F  ε  and f  ε  still satisfy these equalities. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Additionally to the strong convergence results stated in (21)–(24), we are know other weak convergences for <lb/>functions of interest. Firstly, we have <lb/> J  ε  − <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> J in L  2  ((0, T ) × Ω)  3  . <lb/> This is enough to pass to the limit weakly in the electric fields because the nonlinear terms are always formed <lb/>of either strongly convergent terms or J  ε  multiplied by a term that converges strongly. As a conclusion, we have <lb/> E  ε  − <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> E in L  20/11  <lb/> 0, T ; L  30/29  (Ω) <lb/>  3  . <lb/> The same applies to the force field. However for later purposes, it is better to use the splitting <lb/> F  ε  = E  0,ε  + v ∧ B  ε  , <lb/> and to notice that, as before, <lb/> E  0,ε  − <lb/> ε→0 <lb/> E  0  in L  20/11  <lb/> 0, T ; L  30/29  (Ω) <lb/>  3 <lb/> while the other term converges strongly. <lb/>These observations allow us to pass to the weak limit in equations (1)-a) and (1)-b), on the electronic density <lb/>and on the magnetic field. <lb/>For passing to the weak limit in the third equation (1)-c), let us introduce two smooth test functions χ and ϕ <lb/> with compact support respectively in [0, T ) × Ω and in R  3  ; then we have to deal with two terms. The first one <lb/>which reads as <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> B  0,ε  ∧ v · <lb/> ∂ϕ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (v)χ(t, x)f  ε  (t, x, v)dtdxdv, <lb/> can be treated as usual because the magnetic field converges strongly as stated earlier. The second one reads as <lb/>follows <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> E  0,ε  · <lb/> ∂ϕ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (v)f  ε  (t, x)χ(t, x)dtdxdv = <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω <lb/> χ(t, x)E  0,ε  · ψf  ε  (t, x)dtdx <lb/> with ψ  i  =  ∂ϕ <lb/>∂vi  ; we need to use the kinetic averaging lemma which is stated in appendix D. It states that, after <lb/>extraction, velocity averages converge strongly <lb/> χ ψ  i  f  ε  (t, x) → χ ψ  i  f  *   in L  q  ([0, T ] × Ω) <lb/> for a given value of the index q, with 1 ≤ q &lt; p. Therefore they converge almost everywhere and this is enough to <lb/>pass to the weak-strong limit in the term <lb/>  T <lb/> 0 <lb/> Ω  χE  0,ε  · ψf  ε  dtdx. <lb/> This concludes the proof of the Theorem 1. <lb/> 4 Non homogeneous magnetic boundary condition <lb/> In view of applications to the physics of confined plasmas, it is worthwhile considering, instead of (6)-(b), a non <lb/>homogeneous boundary condition for the magnetic field <lb/> n  x  ∧ B(t, x) = n  x  ∧ B  imp  , x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> (27) <lb/>The imposed magnetic field B  imp  (x) is given and can be a function of time as well eventhough we restrict our <lb/>analysis to space dependency only. In order to introduce this boundary condition in the problem, we assume that <lb/> B  imp  can be defined globally as a smooth function in the closure of Ω. It turns out that a convenient regularity <lb/>assumption is <lb/> B  imp   1,∞  ≤ C. <lb/> (28) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> We will write B = B  imp  + B  pert  where B  pert  is the perturbation. Using these notations the system (1)-(a,b,c) is <lb/>rewritten as <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e  , <lb/> (a) <lb/> ∂B  pert <lb/> ∂t <lb/> − ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  I  u  I  ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) <lb/> + ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> (J  imp  + J  pert  ) ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) <lb/> + ∧ (η (J  imp  + J  pert  )) = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (− <lb/> T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e  + <lb/>(J  imp  + J  pert  ) − n  I  u  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  )) + v ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) <lb/> f <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(c). <lb/> (29) <lb/>where the total current is J = J  imp  + J  pert  with <lb/> J  imp  = ∧ B  imp  and J  pert  = ∧ B  pert  . <lb/> We now use the boundary conditions <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> n  x  · n  e  (t, x) = 0 <lb/> x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> (a) <lb/> n  x  ∧ B(t, x)  pert  = 0 <lb/> x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> (b) <lb/> f (x, v − 2(v · n  x  )n  x  ) = f (x, v), <lb/>v ∈ R  3  , x ∈ ∂Ω. <lb/> (c) <lb/> (30) <lb/>Let us define the perturbed magnetic energy and the total perturbed energy <lb/> E  pert <lb/> m  (t) = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> |B  pert  (t, x)|  2  dx, <lb/> E  pert <lb/>tot  = E  I  + E  pert <lb/> m <lb/> + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||  x  (ln n  e  )|  2  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  ln n  e  − n  e  + 1) dx ≥ 0. <lb/> The energy balance is modified by the imposed magnetic field and we have <lb/> Proposition 6. Classical solutions to (29)–(30) satisfy the perturbed energy dissipation relation <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  pert <lb/>tot  = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η <lb/>Jpert <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx + S <lb/> where the source is <lb/> S = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η J  imp  · J  pert  dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> J  imp  ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) · J  pert  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> J  imp  ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) · n  I  u  I  dx. <lb/> Proof. Performing the same manipulations as in the proof of the energy identity (9), we obtain <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  I  = <lb/> Ω <lb/>  n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> (J  imp  + J  pert  ) ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) − n  I  T  e  (ln n  e  ) <lb/> · u  I  dx. <lb/> Taking the scalar product of the magnetic equation against B  pert  and using the homogeneous boundary condition <lb/>(30)-(b), we obtain <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  pert <lb/> m <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> u  I  · (J  pert  ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  )) dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> (J  imp  + J  pert  ) ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) · J  pert  dx <lb/> − <lb/> R  3 <lb/> η (J  imp  + J  pert  ) · J  pert  dx <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> n  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> u  I  · (J  pert  ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  )) dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> 1 <lb/> n  e <lb/> J  imp  + ∧ (B  imp  + B  pert  ) · J  pert  dx − <lb/> R  3 <lb/> η (J  imp  + J  pert  ) · J  pert  dx <lb/> Therefore one gets <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> E  I  + E  pert <lb/>tot <lb/> = − <lb/> Ω <lb/> T  e  (ln n  e  ) · (n  I  u  I  )dx − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η <lb/>Jpert <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx + S <lb/> which is very similar to (10). The rest of the proof is unchanged. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proposition 7. There exists a constant K &gt; 0 depending only on the initial data and on the constant in (28) such <lb/>that the perturbed energy is bounded for all time t &lt; T  񮽙  = log <lb/> 1 + <lb/> C <lb/> 񮽙Jimp񮽙∞ <lb/> . <lb/>Remark 4. Our analysis of weak stability can easily be extended to this non-homogeneous boundary condition <lb/>for t &lt; T  񮽙  . This estimate expresses the interest of a good control on the imposed current. Indeed the smaller is <lb/> J  imp   ∞  , the greater T  񮽙  is. <lb/> Proof. (of proposition 7). We observe that the new terms in S are proportional to J  imp  . Therefore two cases occur. <lb/> First case: J  imp  = 0. This idealized case might be encountered in Tokamaks: for example if B  imp  = F θ <lb/> where θ is the toroidal angle and F is a constant. Physically it corresponds to an imposed exterior magnetic with <lb/>vanishing current [10]. The magnetic lines of B  imp  form a ring. In this case S = 0, so the perturbed energy <lb/>dissipation relation has the same form as (9). It turns out that the perturbed energy is bounded for all times, which <lb/>indeed corresponds to the claim since J  imp  = 0. <lb/> Second case: J  imp  񮽙 = 0. This situation is more realistic in Tokamaks, since the magnetic lines form an helix <lb/>or at least must be close to helicoidal geometry [10]. This is the general case. <lb/>Let σ &gt; 0 be a given positive number. The energy identity writes also <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/> e  −σt  E  pert <lb/>tot <lb/> = Re  −σt  , R = −σE  pert <lb/>tot  − <lb/> Ω <lb/> η <lb/>Jpert <lb/> 2 <lb/> dx + S. <lb/> (31) <lb/>Our goal is to control the source term S in R as much as possible by −σE  pert <lb/>tot  − ηJ  pert   2  and to control the <lb/>remaining part with a Gronwall technique. <lb/>Using the assumption (28), the fact that η is constant and the Hölder inequality between the conjugated spaces <lb/> L  5  (Ω) and L <lb/> 5 <lb/> 4  (Ω), we can write <lb/> |S| ≤ <lb/> α  1  J  pert   2  + α  2  J  pert   2  B  pert   2  + α  2  B  imp   5  n  I  u  I   5 <lb/>4 <lb/> + α  2  B  pert   5  n  I  u  I   5 <lb/>4 <lb/> J  imp   ∞ <lb/> with α  1  = η and α  2  = n  −1 <lb/> e   ∞  . Let &gt; 0 be an arbitrary real number. Then <lb/> α  1  J  pert   2  + α  2  J  pert   2  B  pert   2  ≤ <lb/> α  1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>+ <lb/>α  1  + α  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> J  pert   2 <lb/>2  + <lb/> α  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> B  pert   2 <lb/>2  . <lb/> The identity (34), written as n  I  u  I   5 <lb/>4 <lb/> ≤ α  4  E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I  , implies successively the controls <lb/> B  imp   5  n  I  u  I   5 <lb/>4 <lb/> ≤ α  3  E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I <lb/> B  pert   5  n  I  u  I   5 <lb/>4 <lb/> ≤ α  5  (B  pert   2  + J  pert   2  ) E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I  ≤ α  6 <lb/> E  pert <lb/> m <lb/>  1 <lb/>2  E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I  + <lb/>α  5 <lb/> 2 <lb/> J  pert   2 <lb/>2  + <lb/> α  5 <lb/> 2 <lb/> E <lb/> 8 <lb/>10 <lb/> I  . <lb/> So the right hand side in (31) is bounded by <lb/> R ≤ β  1  + β  2  E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I  + β  3 <lb/> E  pert <lb/> m <lb/>  1 <lb/>2  E <lb/> 4 <lb/>5 <lb/> I <lb/> for some constants β  1,2,3  . Since the electronic density is bounded and 0 ≤ E  I  + E  pert <lb/> m <lb/> ≤ E  pert <lb/>tot  by construction, we <lb/>also have <lb/> R ≤ γ  1  + γ  2 <lb/> E  pert <lb/>tot <lb/>  4 <lb/>5  + γ  3 <lb/> E  pert <lb/>tot <lb/>  13 <lb/>10 <lb/> for some constants γ  1,2,3  which do not depend on time. Since y <lb/> 4 <lb/>5  ≤ 1 + y <lb/> 13 <lb/>10  for positive y, we get the more compact <lb/>form <lb/> R ≤ δ  1  + δ  2 <lb/> E  pert <lb/>tot <lb/>  13 <lb/>10 <lb/> for some constants δ  1,2  which do not depend on time. <lb/>We see that the right hand side is more than linear with respect to E  pert <lb/>tot  due to the power  13 <lb/>10  . As a consequence <lb/>this inequality cannot prove that e  −σt  E  pert <lb/>tot  or E  pert <lb/>tot  is bounded for all time. <lb/>Next we wish to obtain a evaluation of the time of existence with respect to J  imp   ∞  . We set u(t) = e  −σt  E  pert <lb/>tot  . <lb/>One can simplify the inequality as <lb/> u   (t) ≤ <lb/> δ  1  + δ  2  u <lb/> 13 <lb/>10 <lb/> J  imp   ∞  e <lb/> 3σ <lb/>10  t  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 11 <lb/></page>

			<body> Rescaling of the time variable as dτ = J  imp   ∞  e <lb/> 3σ <lb/> 10  t  dt, that is <lb/> τ = <lb/>10 <lb/>3 <lb/> J  imp   ∞ <lb/> e <lb/> 3σ <lb/>10  t  − 1 <lb/> , <lb/> yields the inequality  d <lb/>dτ  u ≤ δ  1  + δ  2  u <lb/> 13 <lb/>10  . It is finally convenient to define v = δ  1  + δ  2  u <lb/> 13 <lb/>10  so that <lb/> v   (t) = δ  2 <lb/> 13 <lb/>10 <lb/> u <lb/> 3 <lb/>10  u   (t) which yields v   (t) ≤ δ  3  v <lb/> 3 <lb/>13  v = δ  3  v <lb/> 16 <lb/>13  . <lb/> Therefore −  d <lb/>dτ  v  −  3 <lb/>13  ≤ δ  4  =  3 <lb/>13  δ  3  . which implies v  −  3 <lb/>13  (0) − v  −  3 <lb/>13  (τ ) ≤ δ  4  τ . It yields <lb/> v <lb/> 3 <lb/>13  (τ ) ≤ <lb/> 1 <lb/> v <lb/> 3 <lb/>13  (0) − δ  4  τ <lb/> which is valid for τ &lt; τ  񮽙  =  v <lb/> 3 <lb/>13  (0) <lb/> δ4  . Going back to the time variable t, the solution is defined for t &lt; T  񮽙  where <lb/> 10 <lb/>3 <lb/> J  imp   ∞ <lb/> e <lb/> 3σ <lb/>10  T   − 1 <lb/> = τ  񮽙  . <lb/> The proof is complete. <lb/> 5 Construction of an approximate solution <lb/> In order to complete our theory, we now detail how to use the so-called splitting strategy, which is a constructive <lb/>method, for the design of an approximate solution to the system <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e  , <lb/> (a) <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> − ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ne  n  I  u  I  ∧ B <lb/> + ∧ (  1 <lb/> ne  J ∧ B)+ ∧ (η ∧ B) = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> (− <lb/> T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e  + <lb/> J − n  I  u  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ B) + v ∧ B <lb/> f <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(c). <lb/> (32) <lb/>The idea is clearly inspired from numerical methods. It consists of a convenient splitting strategy à la Strang, <lb/>together with the linearization and freezing of certain coefficients à la Temam. The main point is to decompose <lb/>the total system in simpler parts which are conceptually easier to solve or easier to analyse, preserving at the same <lb/>time the decay of the energy identity <lb/> E  tot  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> |B(t, x)|  2  dx + <lb/> λ  2 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||  x  (ln n  e  )| <lb/> 2  dx + <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  e  ln n  e  − n  e  + 1) dx. <lb/> Let ∆t &gt; 0 be a time step which is ultimately destinated to tend to zero. We consider that <lb/> f (t  k  ) and B(t  k  ) <lb/> are known at the beginning of the time step t  k  = k∆t. We restrict the presentation to the core of the method. This <lb/>constructive method also provides additional insights into the mathematical structure of the model. <lb/> 5.1 Vlasov-Poisson <lb/> One first solves during the time step ∆t <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ln n  e  = n  I  − n  e  , <lb/> (a) <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.f + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> − <lb/> T  e <lb/> n  e <lb/> n  e  f <lb/> = 0. <lb/>(c) <lb/> This is a non linear Vlasov-Poisson equation which can be considered as standard even if we know very little <lb/>mathematical literature about it. It is easy to show that regular solutions preserve the energy. This procedure <lb/>defines a new solution <lb/> f  񮽙  (t  k  + ∆t) and B  񮽙  (t  k  + ∆t) = B(t  k  ). <lb/></body>

			<page> 12 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.2 Magnetic part, first stage <lb/> For convenience we split the magnetic part of the equations in two stages, the first one which is fundamental, and <lb/>the second which deals with less involved terms. The first stage writes <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ∂B <lb/> ∂t <lb/> − ∧ <lb/> 1 <lb/> ne  n  I  u  I  ∧ B frozen <lb/> + ∧ (  1 <lb/> ne  J ∧ B frozen )+ ∧ (η ∧ B) = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> J <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ B frozen ) <lb/> f <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(c). <lb/> The initial data is provided by the previous step of the algorithm <lb/> f   (t  k  ) = f  񮽙  (t  k  + ∆t) et B   (t  k  ) = B  񮽙  (t  k  + ∆t). <lb/> The frozen magnetic field is <lb/> B frozen = B  񮽙  (t  k  + ∆t). <lb/> This frozen field is constant in time during the whole time step. This trick was first introduced by Temam in the <lb/>context of trilinear forms and Navier-Stokes equations for magnetic equations [26, 27], see also [15]. <lb/>One notices that equation b) is now a linear one, even if equation c) is still formerly non linear because it has a <lb/> n  e  dependence. However an explicit procedure allows to compute the solution. Indeed solutions of equation c) are <lb/>such that <lb/> ∂  t  n  I  = 0. <lb/> It means that n  I  and n  e  are frozen quantities <lb/> n  I  = n  I <lb/> frozen et n  e  = n  e <lb/> frozen . <lb/> One has <lb/> ∂  t  n  I  u  I  = J ∧ d, d = <lb/> n  I <lb/> frozen B frozen <lb/> n  e  frozen <lb/>which yields <lb/> n  I  u  I  = n  I  u  I  (t  k  ) + <lb/>  t <lb/>t  k <lb/> ∧ B(s)ds ∧ d. <lb/> It shows that n  I  u  I  integro-differential and linear with respect to B. Plugging this form of n  I  u  I  in equation <lb/>b), we end up with a linear equation for B. This linear integro-differential equation is well posed under general <lb/>assumptions. <lb/>Once the magnetic field is computed, we can report the current J in equation c) which is now easily solved with <lb/>the method of characteristics. It is immediate that, due to the resistive operator, the energy decreases during this <lb/>step. Since n  i  is constant, the electronic energy is constant. <lb/>The solution at the end of this stage is referred to as <lb/> f   (t  k  + ∆t) and B   (t  k  + ∆t) = B(t  k  ). <lb/> 5.3 Magnetic part, second stage <lb/> It remains to solve <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ∂B <lb/>∂t <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(b) <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> −n  I  u  I <lb/> n  e <lb/> ∧ B) + v ∧ B <lb/> f <lb/> = 0, <lb/>(c), <lb/> with prescribed initial data <lb/> f  •  (t  k  ) = f   (t  k  + ∆t) and B  •  (t  k  ) = B   (t  k  + ∆t). <lb/> Since the magnetic field is frozen <lb/> B = B frozen , <lb/></body>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			<body> equation c) is greatly simplified. Once again the ionic density n  I  and the electronic density n  e  are frozen <lb/> n  I  = n  I <lb/> frozen and n  e  = n  e <lb/> frozen . <lb/> A consequence is <lb/> ∂  t  n  I  u  I  = n  I  u  I  ∧ d, d = <lb/> − <lb/> n  I <lb/> frozen <lb/> n  e  frozen <lb/> + 1 <lb/> B frozen . <lb/> The solution of this linear equation is immediate. Therefore n  I  u  I  is known. And finally the method of characteristics <lb/>can be used to solve c). The energy is preserved during this second magnetic stage. <lb/> 5.4 Iterations <lb/> The previous procedure allows us to design an approximate solution <lb/> f (t  k  + ∆t) = f  •  (t  k  + ∆t) and B(t  k  + ∆t) = B  •  (t  k  + ∆t) <lb/> one time step after the other. With this procedure the total energy decreases and we can apply our stability analysis <lb/>for proving existence. <lb/> A Control on moments of f  I <lb/> Several type of controls on velocity moments of f  I  are available, see [23]. Here we recall one of the most fundamental <lb/>control in L  p  spaces based on the kinetic energy. <lb/> Lemma 1. Let f ∈ L  ∞ <lb/> t,x,v  ((0, T ) × Ω × R  3  ) ∩ L  ∞ <lb/> t  (0, T ; L  1 <lb/> x,v  (Ω × R  3  , |v|  2  dxdv). Define n  I  by (2) and n  I  u  i  by (3). <lb/> Then n  I  ∈ L  ∞ <lb/> t <lb/> 0, T ; L <lb/> 5/3 <lb/> x  (Ω) <lb/> , n  I  u  I  ∈ L  ∞ <lb/> t <lb/> 0, T ; L <lb/> 5/4 <lb/> x  (Ω) <lb/> and we have for all t ∈ [0, T ], <lb/> n  I  (t, ·)  5/3  ≤ Cf (t, ·, ·)  ∞ <lb/> 2/5 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx <lb/>  3/5 <lb/> , <lb/> (33) <lb/> n  I  (t, ·)u  I   5/4  ≤ C   f (t, ·, ·)  ∞ <lb/> 1/5 <lb/> Ω <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dvdx <lb/>  4/5 <lb/> . <lb/> (34) <lb/> Proof. We only recall the proof of the result on n  I  . Let R &gt; 0. We have <lb/> n  I  (t, x) = <lb/> |v|≤R <lb/> f (t, x, v)dv + <lb/> |v|≥R <lb/> f (t, x, v)dv <lb/> ≤ CR  3  f (t, ·, ·)  ∞  + <lb/>1 <lb/> R  2 <lb/> |v|≤R <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dv. <lb/> Then by minimization over R we get <lb/> n  I  (t, x) ≤ C f (t, ·, ·)  2/5 <lb/> ∞ <lb/> R  3 <lb/> f (t, x, v)|v|  2  dv <lb/>  3/5 <lb/> and after integration we obtain the claim. <lb/> B Uniform lower bound on n  e <lb/> The purpose of this section is to prove several properties that we have used throughout the paper for the elliptic <lb/>equation <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −λ  2  ∆ ln n  e  + n  e  = n  I  , <lb/>x ∈ Ω, <lb/> ∂n  e <lb/> ∂ν <lb/> = 0, <lb/> x ∈ ∂Ω, <lb/> with a right hand side data satisfying n  I  ≥ 0, <lb/> n  I  = M  initial  &gt; 0 and n  I  ∈ L  5/3  . <lb/>We are going to prove the estimate <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<body> Lemma 2. Let n  I  ∈ L  ∞  (0, T ; L  5/3  ∩ L  1  (Ω)) and n  e  a strong solution to the above equation, then we have the <lb/>two-sided control <lb/> 0 &lt; K  −  (n  I   5/3  ) ≤ n  e  ≤ K  +  (n  I   5/3  ), <lb/> (35) <lb/> for some continuous positive functions K  ±  (·) with K  +  &gt; 1 increasing, K  −  decreasing. <lb/> We also recall that integration of the equation gives the electric neutrality relation <lb/> n  e   1  = n  I   1  . <lb/> We can now explain why the total energy (8) is well defined for weak solutions and also at initial time. From <lb/>the lower and upper bound in (35), we conclude that n  e  ln n  e  ∈ L  1  (Ω). Also, multiplying the equation by ln n  e  , we <lb/>find <lb/> λ <lb/> Ω <lb/> ||  x  ln n  e  | <lb/> 2  dx = <lb/> Ω <lb/> (n  I  − n  e  ) ln n  e  ≤ 2 ln K  +  n  I   1  . <lb/> Proof. Then, we argue in two steps. Firstly, we multiply the equation by n <lb/> 2/3 <lb/> e <lb/> and integrate by parts. The Hölder <lb/>inequality gives <lb/> 2λ  2 <lb/> 3 <lb/> ||n  e  |  2 <lb/> n <lb/> 1/3 <lb/> e <lb/> + <lb/> n  5/3 <lb/> e <lb/> = <lb/> n  I  n  2/3 <lb/> e <lb/> ≤ n  I   5/3  n  e  <lb/> 2/3 <lb/>5/3  , <lb/> from which we conclude the bound <lb/> n  e   5/3  ≤ n  I   5/3  . <lb/> Secondly we use the elliptic regularity theory to conclude that ln n  e  − ln n  e   Ω  ∈ W  2,p  , 1 ≤ p ≤ 5/3 and thus <lb/> ln n  e  − ln n  e   Ω  ∈ L  q  , <lb/> ∀q &gt; 1, <lb/>1 <lb/> q <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> p <lb/> − <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/> , <lb/> where φ  Ω  denotes the average of the L  1  (Ω) function φ over Ω. Finally, because  2 <lb/>3  &gt;  3 <lb/>5  we conclude from the <lb/>Morrey estimates [13] that <lb/> ln n  e  − ln n  e   Ω   ∞  ≤ C(n  I   5/3  ). <lb/> The result follows immediately thanks to the control of ln n  e   Ω  through (35). <lb/> C Compactness of the magnetic field <lb/> We have also used the Sobolev injection for Maxwell equations and we recall it in this appendix. We introduce the <lb/>following spaces <lb/> H  curl  (Ω) = {b ∈ L  2  (Ω)  3  / ∧ b ∈ L  2  (Ω)  3  }, <lb/> H  div  (Ω) = {b ∈ L  2  (Ω)  3  / · b ∈ L  2  (Ω)  3  }, <lb/> X  N  (Ω) = {b ∈ H  curl  (Ω) ∩ H  div  (Ω) / b ∧ n = 0 on ∂Ω}. <lb/> (36) <lb/>We recall the following result (see [9]) <lb/> Theorem 2. Assume that the domain Ω is of class C  1,1  . Then the space X  N  (Ω) is continuously imbedded in <lb/> H  1  (Ω)  3  . <lb/> D Kinetic averaging lemma <lb/> We recall here one result of the theory of averaging lemmas for kinetic equations. When f (t, x, v) is solution of <lb/>a kinetic equation, it cannot be more regular that the initial data or the right hand-side. However, averages in <lb/>velocity gain regularity. Recall that the macroscopic quantity f ψ is defined as <lb/> f ψ(t, x) = <lb/> R  d <lb/> f (t, x, v)ψ(v)dv <lb/> where ψ is a given function in C  ∞ <lb/> c  (R  d  ) (i.e. smooth with compact support), the averaging lemmas aim at proving <lb/>compactness properties on f ψ. The first version of these averaging Lemma has been established by Golse, Lions <lb/></body>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body> Perthame and Sentis [17] for f ∈ L  2 <lb/> t,x,v  solution of the equation ∂  t  f + v ·  x  f = S with S ∈ L  2 <lb/> t,x,v  : it was proved <lb/>that locally in time f ψ ∈ H <lb/> 1/2 <lb/> t,x  . This version has been then be extended (by complex interpolation) for the L  p <lb/> framework, 1 &lt; p &lt; ∞ in [12]. Moreover, more complex versions have been proved by Di Perna, Lions and Meyer <lb/>[12], who treat the case where S is the k-th derivative in velocity with a fractional derivative in x strictly less than <lb/>one. <lb/>We use here a version proved by Perthame and Sougadinis [24] (the equality is the exponent is due to Bouchut <lb/>[5]) which expresses an optimal gain of regularity (a full derivative) <lb/> Theorem 3. Let 1 &lt; q &lt; ∞ and f, g = (g  1  , ..., g  d  ) belong to L  q <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) and satisfy <lb/> ∂f <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v ·  x  f = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/>. <lb/> (I − ∆  t,x,v  )  1/2  g <lb/> . <lb/> (37) <lb/> Then f ψ ∈ L  q <lb/>t,x  (R  1+3  ) and there exists C(p, ψ) such that <lb/> f ψ  q  ≤ C(q, ψ)f  1−α <lb/> q <lb/> g  α <lb/>q <lb/> for a positive exponent α ≤  1 <lb/>2  min(  1 <lb/> q  , 1 −  1 <lb/> q  ). <lb/> In fact this theorem also proves strong compactness, which is the way we use it in our context. Consider a <lb/>truncation function χ = χ(t, x) with suppχ ⊂ (0, T ] × Ω which is fixed in this paragraph. Define the sequence of <lb/>functions w  ε  as w  ε  = χF  ε  f  ε  and z  ε  = Zf  ε  , with Z = <lb/> ∂χ <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v.  x  χ. They satisfy in R  1+3+3 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> (χf  ε  ) + v ·  x  (χf  ε  ) = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/>.w  ε  + z  ε  . <lb/> (38) <lb/>We know that w  ε  is bounded in L  1  ∩ L  p <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) for some p &gt; 1 (here p = 30/29) and z  ε  and χf  ε  are bounded <lb/>in L  1  ∩ L  ∞ <lb/> t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ). <lb/> We are going to prove the following result for an exponent q (with 1 &lt; q &lt; p). <lb/> Lemma 3. Consider, after extraction, the weak limit f  *  in L  p <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) of the sequence f  ε  weakly then <lb/> ρ  ε <lb/>ψ  = χf  ε  ψ → ρ  * <lb/> ψ  = χf  *  ψ, strongly in L  q <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ). <lb/> (39) <lb/> Proof. We first define <lb/> g  ε  = (I − ∆  x,t,v  )  −1/2  w.  ε <lb/> By regularizing effects the family g  ε  is compact in L  1 <lb/> t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) : indeed g  ε  is given by a convolution product <lb/>between w  ε  and the fundamental solution of (I − ∆  x,t,v  )  −1/2  . Moreover g  ε  is bounded in L  p <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) and then, <lb/>by interpolation argument, it is compact in L  q <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ) for some q (with 1 &lt; q &lt; p). Since the family {χf  ε  } is <lb/>uniformly bounded in L  q <lb/>t,x,v  as well as z  ε  , the theorem recalled above (the term z  ε  can be written as a v -derivative <lb/>without loss of generality) applied to χf  ε  allows to claim that the following bound holds <lb/> ρ  ε <lb/>ψ   q  ≤ C(q, ψ)Cg  ε   α <lb/>q  . <lb/> Then, there exists a subsequence f  ε  , w  ε  and functions f  *  , ρ  * <lb/> ψ  , g  *  , w  *  such that <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> f  ε  f  *  , <lb/> w  ε  w  *  weakly in L  p <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ), <lb/> ρ  ε <lb/>ψ  ρ  * <lb/> ψ <lb/> weakly in L  q <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ), <lb/> g  ε  → g  *  strongly in L  q <lb/>t,x,v  (R  1+3+3  ). <lb/> and g  *  = (I − ∆  x,t,v  )  −1/2  w  *  . Of course we have also, passing to the weak limit, <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂t <lb/> + v ·  x  )(χf  * <lb/> = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> · w  *  + Zf  * <lb/> = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> · ((I − ∆  x,t,v  )  1/2  g  *  ) + Zf  *  . <lb/></body>

			<page> 16 <lb/></page>

			<body> We combine this with (38) and we get <lb/> ( <lb/> ∂ <lb/> ∂t <lb/> + v ·  x  )[χf  ε  − χf  *  ] = <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂v <lb/> · ((I − ∆  x,t,v  )  1/2  (g  ε  − g  *  )) + Z(f  ε  − f  *  ). <lb/> And according to the previous theorem (the term Z(f  ε  − f  *  ) can be written as a v-derivative also) once again we <lb/>see that <lb/> χf  ε  ψ − χf  *  ψ  q  ≤ C(q, ψ) · g  ε  − g  *   α <lb/>q  f  ε  − f  *   (1−α) <lb/> q <lb/> . <lb/> That is to say, the property (39) holds. <lb/></body>
			
			<back>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Acheritogaray, M. and Degond, P. and Frouvelle, A. and Liu J.-G. Kinetic formulation and global existence <lb/>for the Hall-Magneto-hydrodynamics system. Kinetic and Related Models 4, N  o  4, p. 901–918 (2011). <lb/>[2] Blum J. <lb/> Numerical simulation and optimal control in plasma physics with application to Tokamaks. <lb/> Wiley/Gauthier-Vilars Series in Modern Applied Mathematics, (1989). <lb/>[3] Braginskii S.I. Transport Processes in a Plasma. In Reviews of Plasma Physics, Vol.1, Consultants Bureau, <lb/>New York, p. 205–311 (1965). <lb/>[4] Brezis, H. and Golse, F. and Sentis, R. Analyse asymptotique de l&apos;équation de Poisson couplée à la relation de <lb/>Boltzmann. Quasi-neutralité dans les plasmas. Note C. R. Ac. Sciences, série I, Paris, 321, p. 953–959 (1995). <lb/>[5] Bouchut, F. and Golse, F. and Pulvirenti, M. Kinetic equations and asymptotic theory. Series in Appl. Math., <lb/>Gauthiers-Villars, (2000). <lb/>[6] Cercignani, C. and Illner R. and Pulvirenti, M. The mathematical theory of dilute gases. Applied Math. <lb/>Sciences 106, Springer–Verlag, Berlin (1994). <lb/>[7] Chen, F. Introduction to plasma physics and controlled fusion. Springer New-York (1984). <lb/>[8] Crispel, P. and Degond, P. and Vignal, M.H. Quasi-neutral fluid models for current-carrying plasmas. Journal <lb/>of Computational Physics, 205, Issue 2, p. 408–438 (2005). <lb/>[9] Dautray, R. and Lions, J.-L. Mathematical analysis and numerical methods for sciences and technology. Springer <lb/>(1990). <lb/>[10] Després, B. and Sart, R. Reduced resistive MHD in Tokamaks with general density, M2AN (online) february <lb/>2012. <lb/>[11] DiPerna, R. J. and Lions, P.-L. Global weak solutions of Vlasov-Maxwell systems. Comm. Pure Appl. Math. <lb/> 42, p. 729–757, (1989). <lb/>[12] DiPerna, R. J. and Lions, P.-L. and Meyer, Y. Lp regularity of velocity averages. Annales de l&apos;Institut <lb/>HenriPoincaré. Analyse non linéaire, 8, N  o  3-4, p. 271–287, Elsevier (1991). <lb/>[13] Evans, L. C. Partial Differential Equations. Graduate Studies in Mathematics, 19, American Mathematical <lb/>Society (1998). <lb/>[14] Freidberg, J. P lasma physics and fusion energy. Cambridge (2007). <lb/>[15] Gerbeau, J.F. and Le Bris, C. and Lelièvre T., Mathematical methods for the magnetohydrodynamics of liquid <lb/>metals, Oxford University Press, USA (2006). <lb/>[16] Ghendrih, P. and Hauray, M. and Nouri, A. D erivation of a gyrokinetic model. Existence and uniqueness of <lb/>specific stationary solution. Kinetic and Related Models 2, N  o  4, p. 707–725 (2009). <lb/>[17] Golse, F. and Lions, P.-L. and Perthame, B. and Sentis, R. Regularity of the moments of the solution of a <lb/>transport equation. J. Funct. Anal. 76, p. 110–125, (1988). <lb/>[18] Han Kwan, D. Quasineutral limit of the Vlasov-Poisson system with massless electrons. Comm. Partial <lb/>Differential Equations, 36, p. 1385–1425 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [19] Lions, P.-L. and Perthame, B. Propagation of moments and regularity for the 3-dimensional Vlasov-Poisson <lb/>System. Inventiones Math. 105, p. 415-430, (1991). <lb/>[20] Lütjens, H. and Luciani, J.-F. The XTOR code for nonlinear 3D simulations of MHD instabilities in tokamak <lb/>plasmas. Journal of Computational Physics, 227, issue 14, p. 6944–6966, (2008). <lb/>[21] Lütjens, H. and Luciani, J.-F. XTOR-2F: A fully implicit Newton-Krylov solver applied to nonlinear 3D <lb/>extended MHD in tokamaks. Journal of Computational Physics, 229, Issue 21, p. 8130–8143, (2010). <lb/>[22] Mouhot, C. and Villani, C. On Landau damping. Acta Mathematica, 207, p. 29–201 (2011). <lb/>[23] Perthame, B. Mathematical Tools for Kinetic Equations. Bull. Amer. Math. Soc. 41, p.205–244, (2004). <lb/>[24] Perthame, B. and Souganidis, P.E. A limiting case for velocity averaging. Annales Scientifiques de l&apos; école <lb/>Normale Supérieure, 31, N  o  4, p. 591–598,Elsevier (1998). <lb/>[25] Pfaffelmoser K., Global classical solutions of the Vlasov-Poisson system. J. Differential Equations, 95, p. <lb/>281–303 (1992). <lb/>[26] Temam, R. Remarks on a free boundary value problem arising in plasma physics, Comm. Partial Differential <lb/>Equations 2 (1977), 6, 563-585. <lb/>[27] Temam, R. N avier-Stokes Equations, Theory and Numerical Analysis, North-Holland (1979). <lb/>[28] Simon, J. Compact sets in the space L  p  (0, T ; B). Ann. Mat. Pura ed Appl., 146, p. 65–96 (1987). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 </page>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
