<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_Bouvet_12129"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		
			<titlePage> This is an author-deposited version published in: http://oatao.univ-toulouse.fr/ <lb/>Eprints ID: 12129 <lb/> To link to this article: DOI: 10.1016/j.compositesa.2014.09.024 <lb/>URL: http://dx.doi.org/10.1016/j.compositesa.2014.09.024 <lb/> To cite this version:  Abdulhamid, Hakim and Bouvet, Christophe and <lb/>Michel, Laurent and Aboissière, Jacky and Minot, Clément Influence of <lb/>internally dropped-off plies on the impact damage of asymmetrically <lb/>tapered laminated CFRP. (2015) Composites Part A: Applied Science and <lb/>Manufacturing, vol. 68. pp. 110-120. ISSN 1359-835X <lb/> Open Archive Toulouse Archive Ouverte (OATAO) <lb/> OATAO is an open access repository that collects the work of Toulouse researchers and <lb/>makes it freely available over the web where possible. <lb/>Any correspondence concerning this service should be sent to the repository <lb/>administrator: staff-oatao@inp-toulouse.fr <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> Influence of internally dropped-off plies on the impact damage <lb/>of asymmetrically tapered laminated CFRP <lb/> Hakim Abdulhamid a,b,⇑ , Christophe Bouvet a , Laurent Michel a , Jacky Aboissière b , Clément Minot b <lb/> a  Université de Toulouse; INSA, UPS, Mines ALBI, ISAE; ICA (Institut Clément Ader), ISAE (Institut Supérieur de l&apos;Aéronautique et de l&apos;Espace), 10, avenue Edouard Belin, <lb/>BP 54032-31055 Toulouse Cedex 4, France <lb/> b  Sogeti High Tech, Avenue Escadrille Normandie Niemen, Parc du Millénaire, 31703 Blagnac, France <lb/> a r t i c l e i n f o <lb/> Keywords: <lb/> A. Carbon fibre <lb/>B. Impact behaviour <lb/>C. Damage mechanics <lb/>Ply drop-off <lb/> a b s t r a c t <lb/> This paper presents an experimental study of low velocity impact response of carbon/epoxy asymmetri-<lb/>cally tapered laminates. The tests are realised at energy between 10 and 30 J on two types of layup with <lb/>multiple terminated plies. The type and localisation of damage are analysed using C-scan and <lb/>micrographs. Then, the data is compared with the response of corresponding respective plain laminate. <lb/>The effects of some tapering parameters (taper angle, drop-off disposition and configuration) on the <lb/>impact damage mechanisms are also investigated. Very similar impact damage phenomena are found <lb/>between tapered and plain laminates. The presence of material discontinuity due to the resin pocket <lb/>affects less the damage mechanism than the structural difference between the thick and the thin sections. <lb/></front> 
			
			<body>1. Introduction <lb/> In order to achieve optimum weight reduction of a structure <lb/>like thin walled or beam structural elements, part thickness needs <lb/>to be tailored according to local loads distribution. In composite <lb/>structures, thickness tapering cannot be achieved in a continuous <lb/>way. Plies must be terminated or dropped off at discrete location <lb/>over the part. Additionally, as an effect of the manufacturing pro-<lb/>cess, a triangular-shape resin-rich pocket is generally present at <lb/>the end of a dropped ply. Effects of those geometry and material <lb/>discontinuities on the damage mechanism under static and fatigue <lb/>loadings have already been significantly studied [1–7]. In the <lb/>tapered region, ply drop-off generates high inter-laminar stress <lb/>concentration [3,8] since the load carried by the dropped plies <lb/>must be transferred to continuous plies through the inter-plies <lb/>resin layers and the resin-rich pocket. This stress concentration <lb/>triggers premature failure initiated by matrix cracking and delam-<lb/>ination [4–7,9]. Both tensile and compressive strength are reduced <lb/>when compared with the corresponding strengths of the thin sec-<lb/>tion [10]. For instance, Curry and Johnson [4] found that the com-<lb/>pressive strength ratio between the thin section and the tapered <lb/>specimen is equal to the ratio of compliance between the thin <lb/>and the thick section. Under fatigue loading, Weiss et al. [11] <lb/>reported that the propagation of delamination initiated at the resin <lb/>pocket nearest to the thin section leads to the final rupture of the <lb/>specimen. <lb/>Another important element in composite structures design is <lb/>the &apos;&apos;impact damage tolerance&apos;&apos; (i.e. the capacity to sustain load <lb/>in presence of damage). Here, it is worth noting the difference with <lb/>&apos;&apos;impact damage resistance&apos;&apos; which is more the concern for high <lb/>energy impact. In fact, low velocity/low energy impact loading is <lb/>likely to happen during the lifecycle of a given structure. Minor <lb/>impact events like maintenance tool drop or in-service debris <lb/>impact on the runway are likely to happen. Many studies have <lb/>shown how dangerous out-of-plane loading can be to composite <lb/>laminates [12–17]. In fact, impact loading creates complex internal <lb/>damage, generally considered as matrix cracking, delamination <lb/>and fibre rupture. Even in the absence of visible external damage, <lb/>the internal damage can propagate far beyond the impact point <lb/>and significantly reduces the resistance of the structure below <lb/>design loads. For thin composite laminates, the energy threshold <lb/>for BVID (Barely Visible Impact Damage) at which external damage <lb/>is detectable, generally corresponds already to a substantial loss in <lb/>the plate compression strength [18]. <lb/>Many authors have highlighted the importance of interactions <lb/>between matrix cracking and delamination onset and propagation <lb/>on the impact damage mechanism [12,19–21]. Since, the ply <lb/>drop-off discontinuity is found to be prone to damage, it is therefore <lb/>justified to investigate its response to impact loading. In literature, <lb/></body>

			<front> ⇑  Corresponding author at: Université de Toulouse; INSA, UPS, Mines ALBI, ISAE; <lb/>ICA (Institut Clément Ader), ISAE (Institut Supérieur de l&apos;Aéronautique et de <lb/>l&apos;Espace), 10, Avenue Edouard Belin, BP 54032-31055 Toulouse Cedex 4, France. <lb/> E-mail address: hakim.abdulhamid@isae.fr (H. Abdulhamid). <lb/></front>

			<body>there are not many reports concerning the study of impact damage <lb/>of ply drop-off. To the authors&apos; knowledge, only one study done by <lb/>Kairouz and Ball [22] is available in the open literature. They have <lb/>tested T300/914C asymmetrically tapered specimens with <lb/>6.88 mm and 6.02 mm thickness respectively in the thick and thin <lb/>sections. One sub-laminate of three plies, situated near the non-<lb/>impacted side is terminated at the mid-length of the specimen. They <lb/>presented the evolution of delamination area for energy between <lb/>14 J and 42 J and concluded on the vulnerability regarding the initi-<lb/>ation of delamination of the 3 plies drop-off using the stress field <lb/>from a 2D bending numerical simulation. However, that unique <lb/>study remains limited and there is a need for a more in-depth <lb/>understanding of the subject. In this work, specimens with multiple <lb/>dropped plies are considered to match with industrial type <lb/>structures. Firstly, the location of delaminated interfaces and their <lb/>propagation are discussed with regards to the tapered region. Sec-<lb/>ondly, results of plain and tapered laminates are compared. And <lb/>finally, the effects on the damage mechanism of drop-off disposi-<lb/>tion, configuration and the taper angle are analysed. <lb/> 2. Experimental setup <lb/> 2.1. Material and specimens <lb/> Two tapered laminate layups (A and B) are considered in this <lb/>study. Both specimens have the same range of thickness: 6 mm <lb/>(A) and 6.25 mm (B) in the thick and 4 mm in the thin sections. <lb/>This range of thickness is a classical characteristic of aircraft fuse-<lb/>lage. For such application, one side of the structure needs to be flat <lb/>and smooth to provide good aerodynamic properties. This require-<lb/>ment has led to choose a specimen geometry with only one tapered <lb/>side as shown in Fig. 1. Test specimens are 250 mm long and the <lb/>tapering starts at 125 mm from the edge of the thin section <lb/>(Fig. 1). This size is 100 mm longer compared with the standard-<lb/>ized 100 Â 150 mm 2 specimen commonly used in low velocity <lb/>impact because some space needs to be allocated for the attach-<lb/>ment of tabs at each end of the specimen in anticipation of future <lb/>CAI tests. During the CAI tests, tabs will compensate for the thick-<lb/>ness difference between thick and thin sections. <lb/>In this work, the dropped-plies of the specimens are inter-<lb/>spersed with continuous plies. Such configuration of ply drop-off <lb/>presents a good resistance under static loadings according to the <lb/>work of Vizzini and Lee [8] and is advocated by the aeronautical <lb/>regulation [23]. The specimens are made from 0.25 mm thick <lb/>T700GC/M21 carbon-epoxy unidirectional prepreg tapes manufac-<lb/>tured by HEXCEL <lb/> 
			
			Ò <lb/> . The mechanical properties of the material <lb/>obtained from experimental testing [24,25] are provided in Table 1. <lb/>In the case of type A specimens, 8 in 24 plies are dropped-off. All <lb/>the terminated plies are oriented in the 0° longitudinal direction of <lb/>the laminate. In this layup, the number of potential interface of <lb/>delamination is reduced by grouping plies by pairs. The layup in <lb/>the thin section is chosen to be the same as a previously studied <lb/>plain plate [26] to enable the comparison of damage. For type B <lb/>specimens, the layup contains 25 plies, 9 of which are dropped-<lb/>off. It was designed following AIRBUS composite design rules <lb/>[23]. Plies with all orientations (0, 45, À45, 90) are terminated. <lb/>Compared with type A specimens, the number of ply interfaces is <lb/>increased by separating some plies of the same orientation. Also, <lb/>there are some partially dropped groups of plies (Fig. 2(a)) which <lb/>are obtained by terminating only one ply in a group of two or three <lb/>plies of the same orientation. To assess the damage vulnerability of <lb/>tapered laminates, for both layups, plain laminate with the corre-<lb/>sponding thin section layup is also considered. <lb/>Regarding the parametric study, two taper angles are tested: a <lb/>steep slope of 17% and a shallow slope of 10%. Since ply thickness <lb/>is 2.5 mm, the step spacing is then respectively equal to 1.5 and <lb/>2.5 mm. To modify the drop-off configuration in layup A, the groups <lb/>of plies are dropped-off in two different manners: in a staggered <lb/>way (Fig. 2(b)) for A st specimens and simultaneously (Fig. 2(c)) for <lb/>A si . For type B layup, two configurations B 1 and B 2 are also manufac-<lb/>tured by changing the order of dropping the plies. The nomencla-<lb/>ture of the tapered specimens is presented in Table 2. It is defined <lb/>as the type (A st , A st , B 1 , B 2 ) followed by the drop-off spacing <lb/>(1.5, 2.5) in subscript. The plain laminates are respectively desig-<lb/>nated as A P and B P . Detailed descriptions of the layups are provided <lb/>in Table 3. <lb/>The consistency of the taper angle is ensured by controlling the <lb/>step spacing between terminated plies with a microscopic screw <lb/>driven ruler during layup; no mould was placed against the <lb/>tapered face during the curing process. After the manufacturing <lb/>process, the transition zone was observed under a microscope to <lb/>assess the state of the drop-off. A triangular shape resin pocket is 
			
			<lb/>observed at the end of dropped plies, except for those close to a <lb/>90° ply. For such plies, the 90° ply material migrates inside the <lb/>pocket. Curry and Johnson [4] have also reported similar <lb/>observation for their specimens. <lb/> Fig. 1. Impact boundary conditions. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/> Table 1 <lb/> Mechanical properties of T700GC/M21 [24,25]. <lb/> q <lb/> Density <lb/>1600 kg/m 3 <lb/> E T <lb/> 1 <lb/> Tensile Young&apos;s modulus in fibre direction <lb/>130 GPa <lb/> E C <lb/> 1 <lb/> Compressive Young&apos;s modulus in fibre direction <lb/>100 GPa <lb/> E  2 <lb/> Transverse Young&apos;s modulus <lb/>7.7 GPa <lb/> G  12 <lb/> Shear modulus <lb/>4.8 GPa <lb/> m  12 <lb/> Poisson&apos;s ratio <lb/>0.33 <lb/> e  T0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Tensile failure strain in fibre direction <lb/>0.016 <lb/> e  C0 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Compressive failure strain in fibre direction <lb/> À0.0125 <lb/> r  T0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> Transverse tensile strength <lb/>60 MPa <lb/> r  0 <lb/>12 <lb/> 
			
			In-plane shear strength <lb/> 110 MPa <lb/>
			 
			 2.2. Test procedure <lb/> Impact tests were performed using a drop weight testing rig. A <lb/>guided 4 kg-mass with a hemispherical indenter of 16 mm <lb/>diameter is dropped from a specific height onto the specimen <lb/>placed below. Specimens were impacted on the flat face; the <lb/>opposite side being simply supported by a tapered base with a <lb/>rectangular opening of 75 Â 125 mm 2 . This boundary condition is <lb/>very similar to the Airbus standard AITM 1-0010 [27] defined for <lb/>plain specimens. The impact target is the centre of the specimen <lb/>which is located at the end of the thin section. The schematic <lb/>diagram of the test setup is provided in Fig. 1. <lb/>Regarding the test measurement, a piezoelectric sensor is <lb/>attached to the impactor to measure the impact force history and <lb/>an optical sensor is placed at the level of the specimen to measure <lb/>the initial impact velocity. Also, the deflection of the non-impacted <lb/>face is measured using another optical sensor positioned below the <lb/>specimen. All the data is acquired and recorded at a sampling rate <lb/>of 200 kHz. The initial velocity and impact force history were then <lb/>used to compute the evolution of velocity and displacement of the <lb/>indenter throughout the test. A detailed description of the integra-<lb/>tion and data processing procedure is available in [28]. Post-impact <lb/>damage analysis was conducted using C-scan techniques and <lb/>microscopic observations. <lb/> 3. Results <lb/> 3.1. Force curves <lb/> Force versus displacement curves of four different specimens <lb/>impacted at 30 J are plotted in Fig. 3 for comparison. Tapered <lb/>specimens (A st <lb/>1.5 and B 1 <lb/>1.5 ) curves are very similar to the respective <lb/>corresponding thin section plain laminate (A P or B P ). The impact <lb/>phases, from the damage mechanism point of view, are reflected in <lb/>the changes of the force–displacement curve. Similarly to composite <lb/>plain laminates, three major phases can be distinguished. The first <lb/>phase corresponds mainly to the linear dynamic response of the sys-<lb/>tem: impactor and plate. It lasts until the onset of first severe dam-<lb/>age – in this case, delamination – when the force reaches around <lb/>4 kN. The second phase of the impact is characterized by the propa-<lb/>gation of ply interfaces delamination. This propagation is as stable as <lb/>for plain specimen given the strong similarity between the curves. <lb/>The final phase is characterized by a drastic drop in the force which <lb/>is commonly associated with fibre rupture. It happens shortly before <lb/>the return of the indenter. <lb/> 3.2. Global results <lb/> A summary of the impact results for tapered and plain speci-<lb/>mens is presented in Table 4. For each test, data is presented in <lb/>terms of: the impact and absorbed energies, the maximum filtered <lb/>impact force and the maximum deflection of the plate during the <lb/>test. Also provided are the projected delaminated area obtained <lb/> Fig. 2. Drop-off configurations (a – partially dropped-off, b – staggered drop-off, c – <lb/>simultaneously dropped). (For interpretation of the references to colour in this <lb/>figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/> Table 2 <lb/> Tapered specimens nomenclature. <lb/>Layups <lb/>Configurations <lb/>Step spacing (mm) <lb/>Nomenclature <lb/>A <lb/>Staggered <lb/>1.5 <lb/>A st <lb/>1.5 <lb/> Simultaneous <lb/>5 <lb/>A si <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 3 <lb/>A si <lb/>1.5 <lb/> B <lb/>1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>B 1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>B 1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>B 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 1.5 <lb/>B 2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> Table 3 <lb/> Specimens layup. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this table legend, the reader is referred to the web <lb/>version of this article.) <lb/> Layup A <lb/>[45 2 0 2 <lb/> -45 2 0 2 <lb/> 90 2 <lb/> 0 2 ] s <lb/>
			
			termination order -<lb/>2 nd -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1 st <lb/> Layup B <lb/>[45 -45 90 0 0 0 45 45 90 -45 -45 0 0 1/2 ] s <lb/> termination order <lb/>for B 1 <lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>3 rd 1 st --4 th -<lb/>-<lb/>2 nd <lb/> -<lb/>-5 th <lb/> termination order <lb/>for B 2 <lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>1 st 5 th --4 th -<lb/>-<lb/>2 nd <lb/> -<lb/>-3 rd <lb/> Fig. 3. Force–displacement curves for specimens impacted at 30 J. (For interpre-<lb/>tation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the <lb/>web version of this article.) <lb/>
			
			from the C-scan image and the residual indentation measured with <lb/>a stereo-correlation system at least 48 h after the test. In all, 20 <lb/>tests have been realised and the results are fairly repeatable from <lb/>one test to another. Some tests are performed twice in order to <lb/>provide a specimen for microscopic observation. <lb/>For the plain laminates impacted at 30 J, absorbed energy is <lb/>comparable between A P and B P , 65% and 62% of the initial energy <lb/>respectively. However, the projected delaminated area is 60% <lb/>lower for B P compared with A P as a result of the higher number <lb/>of plies interfaces in B P layup. As the number of interface increases, <lb/>smaller projected area is needed to dissipate the impact initial <lb/>energy. For both cases, the maximum impact force of the specimen <lb/>is reached because there is a sudden drop of the peak force for B P <lb/> and a plateau for A P (Fig. 3). <lb/>In the cases of tapered laminates, the tests are performed for a <lb/>range of increasing nominal energy of 10, 20 and 30 J. For low <lb/>impact energies (10 and 20 J), the damage consists mainly of dif-<lb/>fused matrix cracking and ply interface delamination. For those <lb/>cases, the absorbed energy is around 40% of the impact energy. <lb/>At 30 J, a severe drop in the plate stiffness due to fibre rupture is <lb/>observed and the absorbed energy increases up to 65–70%. Fur-<lb/>thermore, the dissipated energy of steeper specimens (A 1.5 , B 1.5 ) <lb/>is slightly higher compared with the shallower ones (A 2.5 , B 2.5 ) <lb/>but they still remain in the same range as for plain specimens. <lb/>Regarding the delamination of tapered specimens, the damage area <lb/>of A specimens remains higher (around 50%) compared with B <lb/>specimens. This observation is consistent with the data of plain <lb/>laminates. However when comparing specimens A and B, impacted <lb/>at 30 J, with their respective plain laminate, the damage area is <lb/>quite similar for type A specimens. This is contrary to type B results <lb/>where the damage area is increased up to 60% for tapered speci-<lb/>mens (Fig. 4(a)). <lb/>Permanent indentation is an important parameter to compare <lb/>with the BVID (0.25–0.5 mm) and to assess the impact damage <lb/>tolerance of composite plates. For tapered specimens it ranges <lb/>from 0.07 to 0.4 mm. At 30 J, an important scattering of the <lb/>indentation is observed for the B tapered specimens (Fig. 4(b)) <lb/>and the values are smaller compared with the corresponding <lb/>plain laminates. <lb/> 3.3. Internal damage <lb/> NDT such as Ultrasonic system is widely used to identify the <lb/>impact damage in CFRP laminates. It can provide information <lb/>regarding both the damage area and through thickness localisation <lb/>of material discontinuities like interfaces debonding. However, in <lb/>the presence of ply drop-off, the ultrasonic wave signal can be dis-<lb/>turbed by material discontinuities and plies inclination which <lb/>makes it problematic to localise deep delamination. In the case of <lb/>pristine specimen for example, it was difficult for the transceiver <lb/>to record the reflected signal in the tapered region from both sides <lb/>of the specimen. Another difficulty inherent to tapered specimen is <lb/>the identification of the delaminated interface. Depending on the <lb/>interface location in the thickness, its position may change on <lb/>either side of the tapered region. Therefore, a particular interface <lb/>can be represented by two different colours in the C-scan image, <lb/>or a given colour may represent two different interfaces which <lb/>makes the interpretation not straightforward. <lb/>In Fig. 5, a detailed C-scan image of specimen A st <lb/>1.5 is presented. <lb/>In this case for example, two different colours represent the <lb/>interfaces between the group of plies 4/5 [0, 90] and 8/9 [90, 0]. To <lb/>facilitate the interpretation, delamination profile in the transition <lb/>zone is represented next to the C-scan. The scan is carried out from <lb/>the impacted face, in a rectangle area of 150 Â 100 mm 2 , centred at <lb/>the impact point. Plies drop-off are represented by the horizontal <lb/>dotted lines situated in the middle of the image. The dashed red line <lb/>rectangle represents the impact boundary condition. The thick sec-<lb/>tion is situated below the dotted lines and the thin one is in the <lb/>upper part of the image. <lb/>Globally, the orientation of delaminated interfaces is governed <lb/>by the same rule as for plain laminates: i.e. delamination propa-<lb/>gates in the direction of the underlying ply. The conic evolution <lb/>of delamination throughout the thickness, generally observed in <lb/>plain laminates, is still verified apart from the propagation in the <lb/>transverse direction of the specimen. The identified delamination <lb/>profile shows that interfaces between continuous plies are more <lb/>critical. Although a 1 mm thick 0° terminated sub-laminate (plies <lb/>drop-off (1)) is present at the mid-thickness, it does not trigger <lb/>any delamination. Otherwise, there would have been another <lb/> Table 4 <lb/> Specimen results summary. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this table legend, the reader is referred to the <lb/>web version of this article.) <lb/> Specimens <lb/> (1) <lb/>Impact <lb/>Energy <lb/>Delaminated <lb/>Area (2) <lb/>Dissipated <lb/>Energy <lb/>Maximum <lb/>Force <lb/>Maximum <lb/>Deflection <lb/>Permanent <lb/>Indentation <lb/>A si <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 10.3 J <lb/>594 mm² <lb/>3.9 J (37 %) <lb/>6.6 kN <lb/>3.0 mm <lb/>0.09 mm <lb/>A si <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 10.5 J <lb/>684 mm² <lb/>4.5 J (43 %) <lb/>6.6 kN <lb/>3.1 mm <lb/>0.09 mm <lb/>A si <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 20.4 J <lb/>1828 mm² <lb/>11 J (53 %) <lb/>7.5 kN <lb/>4.7 mm <lb/>0.16 mm <lb/>A st <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 19.9 J <lb/>1800 mm² <lb/>8.9 J (44 %) <lb/>8.0 kN <lb/>4.6 mm <lb/>0.23 mm <lb/>A si <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 20.6 J <lb/>2288 mm² <lb/>11.8 J (57 %) <lb/>7.5 kN <lb/>4.6 mm <lb/>0.20 mm <lb/> A  P <lb/> 3 0 . 1 J <lb/>2 8 2 7 m m ² <lb/> 1 9 . 8 J ( 6 5 % ) <lb/>7 . 8 k N <lb/>6 . 0 m m <lb/>0 . 4 0 m m <lb/> A si <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 30.6 J <lb/>2655 mm² <lb/>19.7 J (64 %) <lb/>8.2 kN <lb/>6.1 mm <lb/>0.29 mm <lb/>A st <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 29.1 J <lb/>2730 mm² <lb/>18.7 J (65 %) <lb/>8.4 kN <lb/>5.9 mm <lb/>0.40 mm <lb/>B 1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 10.3 J <lb/>421 mm² <lb/>4.6 J (45 %) <lb/>6.4 kN <lb/>2.9 mm <lb/>0.07 mm <lb/>B 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 10.1 J <lb/>540 mm² <lb/>4.0 J (40 %) <lb/>6.4 kN <lb/>3.0 mm <lb/>0.07 mm <lb/>B 1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 10.3 J <lb/>387 mm² <lb/>5.9 J (58 %) <lb/>6.3 kN <lb/>2.9 mm <lb/>0.08 mm <lb/>B 2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 9.7 J <lb/>343 mm² <lb/>4.6 J (48 %) <lb/>6.4 kN <lb/>2.8 mm <lb/>0.07 mm <lb/>B 1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 20.4 J <lb/>1106 mm² <lb/>10.4 J (51 %) <lb/>8.9 kN <lb/>4.3 mm <lb/>0.13 mm <lb/>B 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 20.3 J <lb/>999 mm² <lb/>9.0 J (44 %) <lb/>9.0 kN <lb/>4.3 mm <lb/>0.12 mm <lb/> B P <lb/> 30.2 J <lb/>1178 mm² <lb/>18.8 J (62%) <lb/>9.4 kN <lb/>5.4 mm <lb/>0.47 mm <lb/> B 1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 30.6 J <lb/>1357 mm² <lb/>20.3 J (66 %) <lb/>9.5 kN <lb/>5.5 mm <lb/>0.31 mm <lb/>B 2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/> 30.5 J <lb/>1911 mm² <lb/>14.3 J (47 %) <lb/>11.5 kN <lb/>5.2 mm <lb/>0.19 mm <lb/>B 1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 31.1 J <lb/>1596 mm² <lb/>21.5 J (69 %) <lb/>10.6 kN <lb/>5.4 mm <lb/>0.24 mm <lb/>B 2 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> 30.9 J <lb/>1734 mm² <lb/>23.6 J (76 %) <lb/>10.8 kN <lb/>5.5 mm <lb/>0.24 mm <lb/> Note: (1) the subscripts 1.5 and 2.5 correspond to the spacing between the ends of two successive dropped-off plies. (2) <lb/> Area of projected delamination is computed from C-scan image. <lb/>
			
			 interface between the interfaces 4/5 [0, 90] shown in green and the <lb/>ones shown in yellow 8/9 [90, 0]. <lb/>The micrograph of specimen A st <lb/>1.5 , in Fig. 6a, provides a compre-<lb/>hensive view of internal defects. The cutting plane is parallel to the <lb/>longitudinal direction of the plate and passes through the impact <lb/>point. Dense matrix cracking characterized by both small and big <lb/>cracks are found below the indenter and farther in the thin section. <lb/>Nevertheless, in the transition zone, the cracks are much less dense <lb/>and consist of large trans-laminar failure that pilots the interface <lb/>jump of delamination. The presence of multiple plies fibre rupture <lb/>below the indenter correlates with the drop in the force curve in <lb/>Fig. 3. Apart from the interface between the groups of plies 11/ <lb/>12 [0, À45] situated near the non-impacted face, all the delaminat-<lb/>ed interfaces involve continuous plies (Fig. 6(a)). The micrograph <lb/>confirms the absence of any damage around the 0° terminated <lb/>mid-thickness sub-laminate observed in the C-scan. Even though <lb/>the ply drop-off is quite far from the impact point, the absence <lb/>of any cracks around it induces that it is less critical to impact <lb/>load. <lb/>For B 1 <lb/>
			
			1.5 specimens, the interpretation of the C-scan (Fig. 7) is <lb/>much more complicated due to the existence of a higher number <lb/>of ply interfaces and their proximity. Identification of interfaces <lb/>using only the C-scan data is less accurate and it was conducted with <lb/>information from micrographs. In order to lighten the view, only <lb/>large delaminations are identified on the C-scan. These delamina-<lb/>tions are found in the interfaces of both continuous and partially <lb/>dropped plies. Despite the presence of dropped-off plies of different <lb/>orientation, it is not possible to distinguish the most critical one in <lb/>terms of delamination. It is only observed that, in the thin section, <lb/>the largest delaminations propagate toward the 90° transverse direc-<lb/>tion and that in the transition region they propagate toward the 45° <lb/>and À45° directions of the specimen. <lb/>
			
			The micrograph in Fig. 8 presents internal damage of B 1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/> specimen impacted at 30 J. Three cross sections (A–A, B–B and <lb/> Fig. 4. (a) – Evolution of delamination area. (b) – Evolution of permanent indentation. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is <lb/>referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/> Fig. 5. C-scan from the impacted side of specimen A st <lb/>1.5 impacted at 30 J. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web <lb/>version of this article.) <lb/>
			
			 C–C) are considered. The central image is the micrograph obtained at <lb/>the section B–B. The zooms in Fig. 8(a–c) and (e) are schematic <lb/>diagrams of local damage at different sections to show the evolution <lb/>of damage in the transverse direction. <lb/>For this specimen, multiple matrix cracks and fibre ruptures are <lb/>observed below the indenter (Fig. 8(d)). In the transition zone <lb/>(Fig. 8(d)), there are some trans-laminar matrix cracks located far <lb/>from the impact point. Those matrix cracks which pilot the inter-<lb/>face jump of delamination are found in the proximity of ply <lb/>drop-off. However, there is no crack observed in the resin pocket. <lb/>Therefore, it is the inclination of ply due to the presence of a ply <lb/>drop-off that generates additional out-of-plane shear responsible <lb/>for crack initiation. Regarding the delamination, in addition to <lb/>the ones identified in the C-scan, there are some smaller delamin-<lb/>ations involving dropped plies. Actually, the presence of partially <lb/>dropped layers has led to small delamination between two plies <lb/>of the same orientation like the 0/0 (Fig. 8(a)-ii) and À45/À45 <lb/> (Fig. 8(e)-ii). This type of [h/h] interface delamination has not yet <lb/>been reported in the case of impact damage. The micrograph <lb/>shows that it does not propagate much farther and switches to a <lb/>neighbour [h/b] interface. <lb/>The analysis of delamination around ply drop-off at different <lb/>cross-sections reveals that the delamination does not initiate at <lb/>the ply drop-off (Fig. 8(e)). Dropped ply interfaces delaminate only <lb/>when delamination of continuous plies interface reaches the resin <lb/>pocket (Fig. 8(a), (b) and (e)) and that the orientation of the under-<lb/>lying ply is toward the resin pocket. To illustrate this idea, let&apos;s <lb/>consider the zone represented in Fig. 8(a). In Fig. 8(a)-ii, obtained <lb/>from cross-section B–B, the delamination of [90, 0] interface <lb/>reaches the resin pocket (1). Since its propagation is in the longitu-<lb/>dinal direction of the specimen, this delamination can progress and <lb/>trigger a delamination between the continuous and terminated 0° <lb/>plies. However, at 45° from the impact point, Fig. 8(a)-i obtained <lb/>from cross section C–C, there is no delamination near the resin <lb/>pocket (1) and this layer is not damaged. <lb/> 4. Discussion <lb/> 4.1. Comparison with plain laminate <lb/> Based on the force–displacement curves and the C-scan images, <lb/>damage from tapered and plain laminates is compared to <lb/> Fig. 6. Micrograph of (a) – A st <lb/>
			 
			 1.5 specimen, (b) – A P⁄ specimen [26]. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of <lb/>this article.) <lb/>
			 
			 investigate the effect of the tapering in the damage mechanism. <lb/>Note that plain laminate specimens are impacted at 30 J only. <lb/>Regarding the force–displacement curves (Fig. 9), the response of <lb/>tapered laminates are compared to the corresponding thin section <lb/>plain laminate. For both specimens, the presence of the tapering <lb/>does not modify the critical force for the onset of first damage. <lb/>Nonetheless, the appearance of major fibre rupture seems to be <lb/>affected by the tapering, but it is difficult to draw a conclusion <lb/>given the scattering of composite materials. The existence of major <lb/>fibre rupture, recorded on the force–displacement curve, affects <lb/>significantly the value of permanent indentation as it was already <lb/>reported by He et al. [29]. Besides that, permanent indentation <lb/>increases with the value of additional deflection recorded after <lb/>the fibre rupture during the impact. This additional deflection cor-<lb/>responds to the difference between the maximum displacement of <lb/>the impactor and its displacement at major fibre rupture as <lb/>presented in Fig. 11(a). Fig. 11(b) shows the correlation between <lb/>permanent indentation and additional deflection of specimens <lb/>impacted at 30 J. Consequently, the variation of onset of fibre rup-<lb/>ture and additional deflection after rupture explain the variation of <lb/>permanent indentation between plain and tapered laminates. <lb/>Although permanent indentation of tapered laminates is found to <lb/>be lower compared to plain laminates, it is not possible to highlight <lb/>a tendency of the effect of the tapering angle on fibre rupture or <lb/>permanent indentation. <lb/>As regards to delamination in Fig. 10, the same interfaces are <lb/>affected between plain laminates and the thin section of tapered <lb/>laminates. For type A specimens particularly, delamination shape <lb/>is comparable with a slightly larger propagation in the 90° trans-<lb/>verse direction of tapered specimens. Nonetheless, for type B spec-<lb/>imens, differences in delamination shape are clearly visible. They <lb/>are mainly observed in the first interfaces, especially for the ones <lb/>that propagate in the transverse direction. As a result of the ply <lb/>drop-offs, delamination is no more confined in a small area around <lb/>the impact point as it should be for type B plain laminate layup <lb/>because it has many ply interfaces. Additionally, some new <lb/>interfaces [h/h] involving partially dropped plies are also delami-<lb/>nated for tapered B specimens. <lb/>For A P specimen, a micrograph from Bouvet et al. [26] is also <lb/>available in Fig. 6(b). This specimen is named A P⁄ . The damage <lb/>was created by quasi-static indentation test under the impact <lb/>boundary conditions. The maximum deflection was 6.10 mm <lb/>which is equivalent to the displacement of a 30 J impact on tapered <lb/>specimen. For T700GC/M21, Bouvet et al. [26] have demonstrated <lb/>that quasi-static indentation and low velocity impact give very <lb/>similar damage. Note the strong similarity existing between the <lb/>two specimens in terms of matrix cracks, delamination and fibre <lb/>rupture. <lb/> 4.2. Effects of the tapering parameters <lb/> The effects of three drop-off parameters: step spacing, configu-<lb/>ration and disposition are investigated in this section. The compar-<lb/>ison of the force–displacement curves of various specimens <lb/>(Fig. 9(a) and (b)) shows that those three parameters have no signif-<lb/>icant effect either on the onset of damage or on the curve evolution. <lb/>The only observed variation is related to the instant and the severity <lb/>of tensile fibre rupture at the third phase of the impact loading <lb/>between steep and shallow tapered specimens. For example, for <lb/>specimens B 1 <lb/>1.5 and B 2 <lb/>1.5 impacted at 30 J, there is a sudden 4 kN loss <lb/>when the impact force reaches 10.5 kN due to simultaneous fibre <lb/>rupture in multiple plies (Fig. 9). Nonetheless, specimens with shal-<lb/>low angle reveal less severe loss, i.e. B 1 <lb/>2.5 presents a 1.5 kN drop at <lb/>9.5 kN and B 2 <lb/>2.5 has no force drop until 11.5 kN. Yet, it is difficult to <lb/>draw a clear conclusion with the small number of tests and the scat-<lb/>tering of composite material. <lb/>Regarding the delamination, its evolution with respect to the <lb/>impact energy is presented for all specimens in Fig. 10. The com-<lb/>parison of A 1.5 with A 2.5 specimens shows that the propagation of <lb/>delaminations toward the transverse direction is more pronounced <lb/>for steep specimens. This comparison is only valid when impact <lb/>energy is not enough to lead to major fibre rupture (10 and 20 J). <lb/> Fig. 7. C-scan from the impacted side of specimen B 1 <lb/>1.5 impacted at 30 J. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web <lb/>version of this article.) <lb/>
			 
			 Fig. 8. Micrograph of B 1 <lb/>1.5 specimen impacted at 30 J. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/> Fig. 9. Evolution of force–displacement curves for (a) – type A specimens, (b) – for type B specimens. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the <lb/>reader is referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/>
			 
			 In fact, a steeper angle gives a smaller length of the transition zone <lb/>and therefore the speed of delamination propagation toward the <lb/>thick section is likely reduced earlier. As a result, more energy is <lb/>available to be dissipated by delamination propagation through <lb/>the transverse direction. <lb/>Concerning the disposition of ply drop-offs, Weiss et al. [11] <lb/>showed that the order of dropping plies is an important parameter <lb/>in the fatigue strength of tapered laminates. However, in this <lb/>study, there is not any significant influence observed on the impact <lb/>damage mechanism (Fig. 10). Even though there seems to be some <lb/>differences in the delaminated interfaces of the transition zone <lb/>between B 1 and B 2 , those differences concern mainly the first <lb/>interfaces close to the impact side and can be explained by the <lb/>order in adding new plies in the layup. <lb/> Fig. 10. Evolution of interface delamination for specimens A and B (C-scan from the impacted side). (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the <lb/>reader is referred to the web version of this article.) <lb/>
			 
			 Fig. 11. Permanent indentation versus additional deflection after major fibre rupture. (For interpretation of the references to colour in this figure legend, the reader is referred <lb/>to the web version of this article.) <lb/>
			 
			 For the case of type A specimens, where the group of two plies <lb/>were dropped in two different manners: simultaneous (A si <lb/>1.5 ) and <lb/>stagger (A st <lb/>1.5 ), a noticeable difference is observed on the delamina-<lb/>tion area. At 20 J impact energy, despite both configurations have <lb/>the same tapering slope, the delamination area is 25% higher when <lb/>the group of plies is dropped simultaneously (A st <lb/>1.5 ). The propagation <lb/>in the specimen transverse direction is the most affected by this <lb/>modification. When two plies are dropped simultaneously, the <lb/>neighbouring continuous plies are highly curved. As a result, the load <lb/>passing through the inter-plies resin in the transition region is <lb/>higher which explains the increase in delamination area. <lb/> 4.3. Tapered specimens damage mechanism <lb/> The synthesis of information gathered in this study allows <lb/>establishing the impact damage mechanism of tapered laminates. <lb/>At low impact energy, as the micrographs have confirmed the <lb/>absence of damage at ply drop-off, first damage must take place <lb/>within the continuous plies in terms of matrix cracking. This leads <lb/>to the delamination of the interfaces of continuous plies as found <lb/>in the C-scan of low energy impacted specimens (Fig. 10). Delam-<lb/>ination propagates in both the thin and thick sections at more or <lb/>less the same rate in all directions. The shape and the propagation <lb/>of delamination are governed by the same rules as for plain spec-<lb/>imens. Resin pocket is only damaged if a delamination reaches <lb/>its location and that the conditions of delamination propagation <lb/>are fulfilled. Then, when delamination reaches the end of the tran-<lb/>sition region near the thick section, its propagation toward that <lb/>direction is slowed down. The deceleration is due to the increase <lb/>in local bending stiffness as more new plies are loaded. Simulta-<lb/>neously, the propagation in the transverse direction accelerates <lb/>and the damage can reach the boundary conditions in presence <lb/>of enough impact energy. Finally, major fibre rupture appears at <lb/>the end of the impact load below the indenter. <lb/>The observation of micrographs reveals that ply drop-off resin <lb/>pocket is less critical to damage than normal ply interface during <lb/>impact. Even though, the resin pocket creates stress concentration, <lb/>as it is located far enough from the impact point, the stress increase <lb/>is not high enough to trigger any crack. The resin pocket is only <lb/>damaged when delamination reaches its position and even then <lb/>the crack does not propagate much far away as the stress concen-<lb/>tration is confined near to the indenter. To understand this phe-<lb/>nomenon, consider the stress field in a bending of a simply <lb/>supported plate; the highest shear and normal stresses responsible <lb/>for matrix cracking is localised below the indenter. This notion of <lb/>confinement of the critical area explains the difference of resilience <lb/>of tapered laminates when subjected to traction/compression load-<lb/>ing and impact loading. In a traction/compression test, excluding <lb/>the boundary effects, the stress is constant across the width of <lb/>the specimen and therefore the first damage will be triggered by <lb/>the stress concentration at the resin pocket. In the case of impact, <lb/>as the location of ply drop-offs is quite far from the indenter, the <lb/>stress concentration is not high enough to create cracks. Conse-<lb/>quently, two main effects of the ply drop-off regarding delamina-<lb/>tion are observed: first, the creation of trans-laminar cracks in <lb/>the neighbour plies that pilots the jump of delamination interface <lb/>and second, the increase of delamination parallel to the ply drop-<lb/>off axis which is essentially attributed to the structural effects of <lb/>the thickness variation. <lb/> 5. Conclusion <lb/> Impacts tests have been conducted on two typical tapered <lb/>layups with a thickness varying from 4 mm to 6.25 mm. Some <lb/>taper parameters like drop-offs disposition, configuration and <lb/>taper-angle were varied to investigate any effects on the damage. <lb/>The impact energy level ranges from 10 to 30 J. Impact damage <lb/>assessment was realised using C-scan and micrographs. The results <lb/>show that the global response of a tapered specimen is quite <lb/>similar to the response of a plain specimen in terms of the <lb/>force–displacement curve. The effects of ply drop-offs on the <lb/>delamination shape is limited when the layup has few number of <lb/>ply interfaces (A specimens). However in presence of laminate <lb/>with many interfaces (B specimens); ply drop-off generates larger <lb/>delamination area compared to plain laminates. In both cases, the <lb/>overall delamination shape is elliptical with the major axis parallel <lb/>to the ply drop-off. At high impact energy, the propagation of <lb/>delamination is biased toward the thin section. Microscopic obser-<lb/>vations have shown that cracks do not necessarily initiate at the <lb/>resin pocket. This behaviour is attributed to the confinement and <lb/>complexity of the stress state in the impact loading. However, <lb/>ply drop-off can trigger trans-laminar matrix cracking in the neigh-<lb/>bour plies that can modify the propagation of delamination. The <lb/>presence of partially dropped group of plies leads to small delam-<lb/>ination between plies of the same orientation. The variation of the <lb/>tapering angle and the order of adding new ply do not affect much <lb/>the final damage of the specimen. However, delamination area <lb/>increases when groups of plies are terminated simultaneously. <lb/>Compared to plain laminates, permanent indentation of tapered <lb/>laminates is reduced due to the delay in fibre rupture. From a <lb/>damage tolerance point of view, this difference can make tapered <lb/>laminates more critical to impact. In the future, this research will <lb/>be pursued to investigate the compression after impact of tapered <lb/>laminates. Additionally, numerical analysis will be carried out to <lb/>investigate the impact behaviour of tapered laminates, more spe-<lb/>cifically predicting the onset and growth of damage in matrix <lb/>cracking, delamination and fibre rupture. <lb/> 
			 
			 <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement <lb/> The authors gratefully acknowledge SOGETI HIGH TECH for the <lb/>financial support of this Ph.D. program. <lb/></div>
		 
		 </body>
		 
		 <back>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] Cui W, Wisnom MR, Jones M. New model to predict static strength of tapered <lb/>laminates. Composites 1995;26:141–6. <lb/>[2] He K, Hoa S, Ganesan R. The study of tapered laminated composite structures: <lb/>a review. Compos Sci Technol 2000;60:2643–57. <lb/>[3] Hitchen SA, Kemp RMJ. The effect of stacking sequence on impact damage in a <lb/>carbon fibre/epoxy composite. Composites 1995;26:207–14. <lb/>[4] Curry JM, Johnsont ER. Effect of dropped plies on the strength of graphite-<lb/>epoxy laminates. AIAA J 1992;30(2):449–56. <lb/>[5] Wisnom MR, Dixon R, Hill G. Delamination in asymmetrically tapered <lb/>composites loaded in tension. Compos Struct 1996;35:309–22. <lb/>[6] Murri GB, O&apos;Brien TK, Carl Q R. Fatigue life methodology for tapered composite <lb/>flexbeam laminates. Am Helicopter Soc Forum 1997. <lb/>[7] Xing YM, Yun H, Dai FL. An experimental study of failure mechanisms in <lb/>laminates with dropped plies. Compos Sci Technol 1999;59:1527–31. <lb/>[8] Vizzini AJ, Lee SW. Damage analysis of composite tapered beams. J Am <lb/>Helicopter Soc 1995;40:43. <lb/>[9] Wisnom MR, Jones MI, Cui W. Failure of tapered composites under static and <lb/>fatigue tension loading. AIAA J 1995;33:911–8. <lb/>[10] Steeves CA, Fleck NA. Compressive strength of composite laminates with <lb/>terminated internal plies. Compos Part A Appl Sci Manuf 2005;36:798–805. <lb/>[11] Weiss a, Trabelsi W, Michel L, Barrau JJ, Mahdi S. Influence of ply-drop location <lb/>on the fatigue behaviour of tapered composites laminates. Proc Eng <lb/>2010;2:1105–14. <lb/>[12] Abrate S. Impact on composite structures. Cambridge University Press; 2005. <lb/>[13] De Freitas M, Reis L. Composite failure: mechanisms on composite specimens <lb/>compression after impact. Compos Struct 1998;42:365–73. <lb/>[14] Hongkarnjanakul N, Bouvet C, Rivallant S. Validation of low velocity impact <lb/>modelling on different stacking sequences of CFRP laminates and influence of <lb/>fibre failure. Compos Struct 2013;106:549–59. <lb/>[15] González EV, Maimí P, Camanho PP, Turon a, Mayugo Ja. Simulation of drop-<lb/>weight impact and compression after impact tests on composite laminates. <lb/>Compos Struct 2012;94:3364–78. <lb/>[16] Reis L, de Freitas M. Damage growth analysis of low velocity impacted <lb/>composite panels. Compos Struct 1997;38:509–15. <lb/> [17] Rivallant S, Bouvet C, Hongkarnjanakul N. Failure analysis of CFRP laminates <lb/>subjected to compression after impact: FE simulation using discrete interface <lb/>elements. Compos Part A Appl Sci Manuf 2013;55:83–93. <lb/>[18] Richardson MOW, Wisheart MJ. Review of low velocity impact properties of <lb/>composite materials. Compos Part A Appl Sci Manuf 1996;27:1123–31. <lb/>[19] Bouvet C, Castanié B, Bizeul M, Barrau J-J. Low velocity impact modelling in <lb/>laminate composite panels with discrete interface elements. Int J Solids Struct <lb/>2009;46:2809–21. <lb/>[20] Allix O, Blanchard L. Mesomodeling of delamination: towards industrial <lb/>applications. Compos Sci Technol 2006;66:731–44. <lb/>[21] Renault M. Compression après impact d&apos;une plaque stratifiée carbone époxyde <lb/>– etude expérimentale et modélisation éléments finis associée. 1994. <lb/>[22] Kairouz KC, Ball J. Impact of ply drops. Beijing, China: ICCM; 2001. <lb/>[23] Airbus Industrie. Reference structure design principles for A350 XWB: <lb/>composite design principles, vol. 2. Blagnac; 2008. <lb/>[24] Guillon D. Etude des mécanismes d&apos;absorption d&apos;énergie lors de l&apos;écrasement <lb/>progressif de structures composites à base de fibre de carbone. Ph.D. DMSM <lb/>ISAE. Université de Toulouse; 2008. <lb/>[25] Prombut P. Caractérisation de la propagation de delaminage des stratifies <lb/>composites multidirectionnels. Ph.D. DMSM ISAE. Université de Toulouse; <lb/>2007. <lb/>[26] Bouvet C, Hongkarnjanakul N, Rivallant S, Barrau J-J. Discrete modelling of <lb/>inter-and intra-laminar failure for impact in composites. In: Abrate S, Castanié <lb/>B, Rajapakse YDS, editors. Dyn. fail. compos. sandw. struct., vol. <lb/>192. Dordrecht: Springer Netherlands; 2013. p. 339–92. <lb/>[27] Airbus Industrie Test Method 1-0010. Fiber reinforced plastics determination <lb/>of compression strength after impact. Blagnac Cedex: Airbus Industrie <lb/>Engineering Directorate; 1999. p. 15. <lb/>[28] Petit S, Bouvet C, Bergerot A, Barrau J-J. Impact and compression after impact <lb/>experimental study of a composite laminate with a cork thermal shield. <lb/>Compos Sci Technol 2007;67:3286–99. <lb/>[29] He W, Guan Z, Li X, Liu D. Prediction of permanent indentation due to impact <lb/>on laminated composites based on an elasto-plastic model incorporating fiber <lb/>failure. Compos Struct 2012. </listBibl>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
