<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cell Death and Differentiation (2011) 18, 1944–1947 <lb/>&amp; 2011 Macmillan Publishers Limited All rights reserved 1350-9047/11 <lb/>www.nature.com/cdd <lb/>Meeting Report <lb/>International EMBO Molecular Medicine Workshop <lb/>2011 on &apos;Cell Death and Disease&apos; <lb/>A Hague* <lb/>,1 and LS Dickens <lb/>2 <lb/>Cell Death and Differentiation (2011) 18, 1944–1947; doi:10.1038/cdd.2011.108; published online 26 August 2011 <lb/>Obergurgl, Austria, 10–14 March 2011 <lb/>Superbly organised by Andreas Villunger, this friendly and <lb/>lively meeting took place by the ski slopes of Obergurgl. <lb/>The third in a series of cell death conferences held in this <lb/>Tyrolean village, the speakers focused on their recent findings <lb/>in the classic and alternative cell death signalling pathways <lb/>and provided insights into how these pathways modulate <lb/>cancer and immune signalling. <lb/></front>

			<body>miRNAs, Synthetic Lethality and Cancer <lb/>Carlo Croce (Columbus, OH, USA) took us from early <lb/>chromosome breakpoint analysis of tumours, which paved <lb/>the way for the cloning of human oncogenes such as Bcl-2 and <lb/>c-Myc, and illustrated that microRNA sequences can be <lb/>similarly identified. Global miRNA signatures of indolent and <lb/>aggressive subsets of CLL and solid tumours revealed some <lb/>commonality between multiple cancer types. miRNAs are <lb/>attractive tumour therapies and provide useful blood biomar-<lb/>kers for early tumour detection. As miRNAs have multiple <lb/>targets, the challenge will be to identify these and establish <lb/>their contribution to malignant transformation. The importance <lb/>of miRNAs in cancer was further demonstrated by Jean <lb/>Christophe Marine (Leuven, Belgium) who showed that in a <lb/>mouse model of retinoblastoma, monoallelic loss of the <lb/>miRNA-processing enzyme Dicer1 accelerated tumour <lb/>progression. Further studies indicated that Dicer1 loss is <lb/>synthetically lethal with p53 inactivation, in cells where the <lb/>retinoblastoma protein is inactivated. Identification of micro-<lb/>RNAs, downstream of Dicer1, that are responsible for <lb/>synthetic lethality in p53-deficient cells may highlight key <lb/>therapeutic targets to selectively treat retinoblastoma. <lb/>Daniel Murphy (Wü rzburg, Germany) presented data from <lb/>a synthetic lethal siRNA screen, which identified two kinases <lb/>from the AMP-activated protein kinase (AMPK) family as <lb/>potential targets in Myc-overexpressing tumours. Depletion of <lb/>either kinase resulted in apoptosis in vitro and therapeutic <lb/>efficacy in a Myc-driven mouse model of hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma. Thus, small molecule inhibition of AMPK-related <lb/>kinases may prove effective against tumours overexpressing <lb/>Myc. However, care should be taken when using rapamycin-<lb/>based therapies, as rapamycin rescued cells depleted of <lb/>either kinase from Myc-induced lethality. Jochen Prehn <lb/>(Dublin, Ireland) provided further caution, as he implicated <lb/>AMPK as a key switch in the decision between cell survival <lb/>and death. Transient AMPK activation protects against <lb/>apoptosis through the activation of GLUT transporters and <lb/>stimulation of glucose metabolism. However, prolonged <lb/>AMPK activation can lead to apoptosis via Bim and Bmf. <lb/>Therefore, identifying what determines whether AMPK has a <lb/>protective or destructive effect will have important implications <lb/>for a range of human diseases. <lb/>The p53 Family <lb/>Following DNA damage, cells either undergo cell cycle arrest <lb/>or apoptosis. As p53 is stabilised in both situations, additional <lb/>factors must determine which response prevails. Ulrich <lb/>Maurer (Freiburg, Germany) showed that in response to <lb/>DNA damage, glycogen synthase kinase-3, through <lb/>phosphorylation of Tip60, regulates p53 acetylation and <lb/>p53-dependent Puma expression. This mechanism may <lb/>provide a link between phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase signal-<lb/>ling and the p53-mediated decision for life or death. <lb/>Gerry Melino (Leicester, UK) provided new data on p63 in <lb/>ear development. p63 null mice have supernumary auditory <lb/>hair cells, and patients with p63 mutations and the syndrome <lb/>ectrodactyly, ectodermal dysplasia and cleft lip/palate have a <lb/>reduced number of cochlea coils. Gerry also described how <lb/>the p53 family of proteins might protect the female germline; <lb/>p63 is involved in follicle maturation, p73 in blastocyst <lb/>development, and p53 controls implantation. Andreas Strasser <lb/>(Melbourne, Australia) explained that mouse oocytes respond <lb/>to DNA damage by apoptotic cell death, requiring Puma and <lb/>Noxa. Puma/Noxa double knockout (DKO) oocytes are <lb/>protected against this type of death, but progeny are <lb/>developmentally normal and fertile. Although much emphasis <lb/>is placed on p53 as a tumour suppressor, Puma/Noxa DKO <lb/>mice do not get tumours, nor do Puma/p21 DKO mice. <lb/></body>

			<front>1 School of Oral and Dental Sciences, University of Bristol, Lower Maudlin Street, Bristol BS1 2LY, UK and <lb/>2 MRC Toxicology Unit, Hodgkin Building, PO Box 138, <lb/>University of Leicester, Lancaster Road, Leicester LE1 9HN, UK <lb/>*Corresponding author: A Hague, School of Oral and Dental Sciences, University of Bristol, Lower Maudlin Street, Bristol BS1 2LY, UK. Tel: þ 44 117 342 4114; <lb/>Fax: þ 44 117 342 4428; Email: a.hague@bristol.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<body>Consistent with this, Alexander Egle (Salzburg, Austria) <lb/>showed that Puma/p21 DKO mice were resistant to develop-<lb/>ing thymic lymphomas after repeated doses of non-lethal <lb/>irradiation. This tumour-resistant phenotype appeared to be <lb/>related to differential regulation of cell cycle and DNA-damage <lb/>repair in irradiated haemopoietic stem cells versus wild-type <lb/>counterparts. <lb/>Tumour Evasion of the Immune Response and <lb/>Chemotherapy <lb/>Thomas Brunner (Konstanz, Germany) reported that gluco-<lb/>corticoid synthesis by colon cancer cells might assist them in <lb/>escaping immune surveillance. Intestinal cells produce <lb/>cortisol through stimulation of the nuclear receptor, liver <lb/>receptor homolog-1 (LRH-1), and steroidogenic enzymes. <lb/>LRH-1 was restricted to the crypt base in normal colon, but <lb/>exhibited uniform expression in colonic tumours. Secretion of <lb/>cortisol by human colon cancer cells likely suppresses <lb/>activation of infiltrating T cells as well as inducing their death, <lb/>as these functions were inhibited with 11-b hydroxylase <lb/>inhibitor. <lb/>Jan Paul Medema (Amsterdam, The Netherlands) <lb/>expanded on his work showing that high Wnt activity <lb/>functionally designates a chemotherapy-resistant, CD133-<lb/>positive &apos;cancer stem cell&apos; (CSC) population among colon <lb/>tumours. Class I histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors can <lb/>induce differentiation of CSCs and sensitise them to che-<lb/>motherapy. Therefore, even apoptosis-resistant CSCs might <lb/>be targeted by combination treatments involving HDAC <lb/>inhibitors. <lb/>Autophagy, Metabolism and Disease <lb/>Xin Lu (Oxford, UK) considered the role of ASPP2 in epithelial <lb/>tumours, where it exhibits reduced expression (e.g., in breast, <lb/>lung and hepatocellular carcinoma) and is a haploinsufficient <lb/>tumour suppressor. She showed a p53-independent function <lb/>of ASPP2 in maintaining tight junction integrity and cell <lb/>polarity through regulating localisation of the tight junction <lb/>protein, PAR3. She also proposed a link between cell polarity <lb/>and autophagy. <lb/>Jennifer Martinez (Memphis, TN, USA) showed that <lb/>phagocytosis of apoptotic, necrotic or necroptotic cells <lb/>caused Atg7 and Beclin-1-dependent LC3 translocation to <lb/>the phagosome. Thus, LC3-associated phagocytosis is <lb/>utilised to efficiently remove dying cells and limit autoimmune <lb/>responses. <lb/>Inê s Castro (Leicester, UK) showed that autophagy <lb/>degrades defective mitochondria, with an accumulation of <lb/>unfolded proteins, via the PINK1/Parkin pathway. Both Pink1 <lb/>and Parkin mutant flies exhibit an atypical wing posture due to <lb/>abnormal mitochondria in the indirect flight muscles. A similar <lb/>phenotype was observed upon mitochondrial accumulation of <lb/>unfolded ornithine transcarbamylase (OTC). Furthermore, <lb/>these mutant flies had locomotor defects. Parkin suppressed <lb/>mitochondrial dysfunction and locomotor defects caused by <lb/>OTC accumulation by promoting autophagy, a process <lb/>involving the Drosophila orthologue of mammalian p62, <lb/>Ref(2)P. Inê s suggested that defects in the regulation of <lb/>mitochondrial quality by the PINK1/Parkin/Ref(2)P pathway <lb/>may be relevant to the aetiology of Parkinson&apos;s disease. <lb/>Seamus Martin (Dublin, Ireland) explained how mutant <lb/>Ras <lb/>V12 induced Noxa in normal human ovarian epithelial cells, <lb/>leading to caspase-independent cell death with features of <lb/>autophagy. shNoxa or shPuma restored colony forming <lb/>efficiency upon switching on Ras <lb/>V12 ; moreover, A1 and <lb/>Mcl-1, which are efficient binders of Noxa, blocked cell death <lb/>more efficiently than Bcl-2 or Bcl-xL. Furthermore, shBeclin-1 <lb/>and siAtg5 both conferred protection. Beclin-1 binds Bcl-xL, <lb/>Mcl-1 and Bcl-2, the first two of which dissociate from Beclin-1 <lb/>when Ras <lb/>V12 is switched on; Puma displaces Bcl-xL from <lb/>Beclin-1, and Noxa displaces Mcl-1 from Beclin-1. This <lb/>mechanism may serve to limit the oncogenic potential of <lb/>deregulated Ras signals. <lb/>Cristina Muñ oz-Pinedo (Barcelona, Spain) analysed cell <lb/>death induced by inhibition of glycolysis by glucose depriva-<lb/>tion or treatment with 2-deoxyglucose (2-DG), a non-<lb/>metabolisable glucose analogue. As tumours have increased <lb/>glycolytic flux, such approaches may target tumour cells for <lb/>cell death. In rhabdomyosarcoma cells, interesting differ-<lb/>ences were noted between the two methods of inhibiting <lb/>glycolysis; glucose withdrawal resulted in necrosis, whereas <lb/>2-DG induced caspase-dependent apoptosis associated with <lb/>decreased Mcl-1 and increased Noxa. Clearly, understanding <lb/>the consequences of anti-glycolytic treatments will be crucial <lb/>in predicting tumour response. <lb/>The Bcl-2 Family in Immunity <lb/>Eric Eldering (Amsterdam, The Netherlands) described how <lb/>TCR or BCR clonal diversity is regulated by the Mcl-1/Noxa <lb/>rheostat. Antigen stimulation induces Noxa, the ablation of <lb/>which leads to lower antigen affinity and greater clonal <lb/>diversity in the T-cell response. Noxa null mice take longer <lb/>to recover from infection, indicating that Noxa has a role in <lb/>ensuring the most effective clones of the adaptive immune <lb/>system survive. Eleonora Ottina (Innsbruck, Austria) showed <lb/>evidence that A1 may be important in positive selection of <lb/>thymocytes, B-cell maturation and granulopoiesis. <lb/>Cytotoxic lymphocytes cosecrete perforin and granzyme B <lb/>to induce death of target cells. Jamie Lopez (Melbourne, <lb/>Australia) showed that perforin likely forms a pore to permit <lb/>granzyme B entry. However, detailed kinetic analysis showed <lb/>only a small window of opportunity for granzymes to gain entry <lb/>into the target cell before plasma membrane repair. <lb/>The Bcl-2 Family in Cancer <lb/>Suzanne Cory (Melbourne, Australia) discussed how in-<lb/>creased Mcl-1 is a mechanism for resistance to the BH3 <lb/>mimetic, ABT-737. Mcl-1 siRNA or Noxa overexpression can <lb/>enhance its effectiveness. ABT-737 was also discussed by <lb/>Martin Schuler (Essen, Germany) as a co-treatment to <lb/>overcome resistance to EGFR antibody-based therapy. A <lb/>novel use of ABT-737, outside of cancer treatment, was <lb/>introduced by Douglas Fairlie (Melbourne, Australia). Douglas <lb/>suggested that BH3 mimetics could be employed to treat <lb/>schistosomiasis by targeting pro-survival Bcl-2 orthologues in <lb/>the schistosome, resulting in parasite death. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Meeting Report <lb/></note>

			<page>1945 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cell Death and Differentiation <lb/></note>

			<body>The concept of direct activator BH3 proteins acting by <lb/>&apos;Mode 1&apos; and sensitiser BH3 proteins acting via &apos;Mode 2&apos; was <lb/>discussed by Doug Green (Memphis, TN, USA). Doug <lb/>proposed that Mode 2 is more efficient and is engaged at <lb/>higher stresses, whereas Mode 1 is more easily derepressed. <lb/>Peter Czabotar (Melbourne, Australia) used an alternative <lb/>approach to investigate the interactions of the Bcl-2 family. <lb/>Met74E Bax cannot bind anti-apoptotic Bcl-2 family members, <lb/>but can oligomerise; it reduces the colony forming ability of <lb/>Bax/Bak DKO mouse embryonic fibroblasts and sensitises <lb/>cells to ABT-737 more effectively than wild-type Bax. This <lb/>suggests that anti-apoptotic proteins provide some restraint <lb/>on Bax, suppressing a &apos;Mode 2&apos;-type of death. <lb/>Cell Signalling from Soluble Intracellular Complexes <lb/>Peter Vandenabeele (Ghent, Belgium) described TNF signal-<lb/>ling and necroptosis, a RIP kinase-mediated form of <lb/>programmed necrosis. RIP kinases are crucial in determining <lb/>the TNF response: knockdown of RIPK1 prevented necrosis, <lb/>but sensitised to apoptosis, whereas knockdown of RIPK3 led <lb/>to protection against both forms of cell death. The cytopro-<lb/>tective importance of RIPK3 was illustrated by comparing <lb/>RIPK3 knockout and wild type mice injected with TNF; in wild <lb/>type mice, TNF induces systemic inflammatory response <lb/>syndrome, but RIPK3 knockout mice were completely <lb/>protected. Andrew Oberst (Memphis, TN, USA) discussed <lb/>how caspase-8 and c-FLIP L protect against TNF-induced <lb/>necroptosis. This was achieved by caspase-8 and c-FLIP L <lb/>forming a catalytically active complex that inhibited the stable <lb/>formation of a RIPK1/RIPK3/FADD complex. Therefore, <lb/>c-FLIP L can protect against both apoptosis and necroptosis. <lb/>Martin Leverkus (Heidelberg, Germany) and Pascal Meier <lb/>(London, UK) reported on an intracellular complex containing <lb/>caspase-8, c-FLIP, FADD and RIPK1 termed the &apos;Ripopto-<lb/>some&apos;. This is formed in the absence of cIAPs and can be <lb/>recruited to different platforms such as those formed by death <lb/>receptors or Toll-like receptor-3 (TLR3). Martin showed that <lb/>upon ligation of TLR-3, the complex was recruited to the <lb/>adaptor protein TRIF and both apoptosis and necroptosis <lb/>were induced. Pascal reported that treating cells with SMAC <lb/>mimetics or etoposide results in reduced levels of IAPs, <lb/>facilitating ripoptosome formation and c-FLIP recruitment. <lb/>John Silke (Melbourne, Australia) showed that the IAP family <lb/>modulates RIPK1 recruitment to the TNFR1 platform and, by <lb/>analysing cIAP1/cIAP2 or cIAP1/XIAP DKO mice, illustrated <lb/>that this critically regulates RIPK1-and TNFR1-mediated <lb/>death in vivo. <lb/>David Wallach (Rehovot, Israel) discussed the mitochon-<lb/>drial-associated RIG-1 complex, a ribonucleic acid sensor, to <lb/>which caspase-8 and RIPK1 are recruited in response to viral <lb/>infection. The RIG-1 complex activates IRF3, which drives <lb/>transcription of type I interferons. The complex is stabilised by <lb/>RIPK1 ubiquitination and dissociated by caspase-8-mediated <lb/>cleavage of RIPK1. Therefore, caspase-8 can restrict RIG-1 <lb/>signalling without compromising its initial activation. Caspase-<lb/>8 knockdown in basal epidermal keratinocytes leads to fatal <lb/>inflammation associated with enhanced phosphorylation of <lb/>IRF3. Hence, this work revealed a further function for <lb/>caspase-8 in restricting inflammation. <lb/>Maria Andree (Cologne, Germany) discussed XIAP <lb/>as a key regulator of immune responses to intracellular <lb/>infection, for example by Shigella flexneri. XIAP serves <lb/>to regulate the NOD1 signalling cascade, induce <lb/>NF-kB activation and upregulate IL-8 secretion. Shigella <lb/>dampens the pro-apoptotic response to infection by selective <lb/>release of SMAC from mitochondria, thus inhibiting XIAP. <lb/>Philipp Jost (Munich, Germany) described how cytokine <lb/>secretion in macrophages following activation of NOD2 <lb/>depends (in part) on XIAP, whereas Mads Gyrd-Hansen <lb/>(Copenhagen, Denmark) proposed that the E3 ligase <lb/>activity of XIAP was required for its potentiation of NF-kB <lb/>activation. Interestingly, X-linked lymphoproliferative disease <lb/>is associated with XIAP mutations and defects in NF-kB <lb/>activation. <lb/>Cell Signalling from Membrane-Associated Complexes <lb/>Arton Philip Kater (Amsterdam, The Netherlands) studied <lb/>the lymph node microenvironment that is postulated to <lb/>favour chemoresistant CLL. He reported that BAFF and <lb/>APRIL, two TNF receptor ligands, are abundantly expressed <lb/>and accelerate tumorigenesis in a mouse model of <lb/>CLL, suggesting a rationale for targeting the TNF-receptor <lb/>pathway. <lb/>Henning Walczak (London, UK) described the identification <lb/>of the linear ubiquitin chain assembly complex (LUBAC) as a <lb/>novel component of the TNF-receptor signalling complex <lb/>(TNF-RSC). Recruitment of LUBAC to the TNF-RSC is <lb/>apparent within seconds and is dependent on TRADD, <lb/>TRAF2/5 and cIAP1/2. LUBAC consists of HOIL-1, HOIP <lb/>and Sharpin, which together form an E3 ligase that creates <lb/>linear ubiquitin chains stabilising TNF-RSC and enhancing <lb/>recruitment of the NEMO-IKK and TAB/TAK complexes. <lb/>Sharpin is mutated in mice with chronic proliferative dermatitis <lb/>and the skin lesions in these mice can be prevented by TNF <lb/>knockout. Therefore, Henning proposed that Sharpin <lb/>prevents TNF-induced inflammation by balancing the output <lb/>of TNF signal transduction. This may open new therapeutic <lb/>avenues for the treatment of autoimmunity. <lb/>Laura Dickens (Leicester, UK) described a novel structural <lb/>model of the TRAIL DISC, derived from mass spectrometry <lb/>analysis of the proteins present in the affinity-purified <lb/>complex. This analysis suggested that the relative abundance <lb/>of proteins within the DISC does not fit with current <lb/>hypotheses. Laura challenged existing views of the DISC <lb/>structure and left delegates considering the challenges of <lb/>redrawing the TRAIL DISC. <lb/>Inna Lavrik (Heidelberg, Germany) addressed the <lb/>contribution of DED-proteins in the CD95 DISC. In each HeLa <lb/>cell, there are around 250 000 molecules of caspase-8, but <lb/>only 530 molecules of c-FLIP S and 320 molecules of c-FLIP L . <lb/>Therefore, c-FLIP affinity for the DISC is much higher than <lb/>that of caspase-8. c-FLIP L can act in a pro-apoptotic or anti-<lb/>apoptotic manner depending on DISC stoichiometry, the <lb/>amount of c-FLIP S/R and the extent of CD95 stimulation. Also <lb/>cleaved c-FLIP L (p43) can disable, promote or inhibit NF-kB <lb/>activation depending on whether its levels are low, medium or <lb/>high, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Meeting Report <lb/></note>

			<page>1946 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cell Death and Differentiation <lb/></note>

			<body>Closing Remarks <lb/>As the meeting concluded, the weather closed in, resulting in <lb/>cancellation of the 3rd Apoptosis Ski Slalom competition. <lb/>Prizes were awarded to PhD students who gave exceptional <lb/>short talks: Inê s Castro, Eleonora Ottina and Maria Andree. <lb/>Congratulations to them, and a big thank you to the <lb/>organisers, sponsors and participants who made the meeting <lb/>outstanding. <lb/>Conflict of Interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. This meeting was an EMBO Molecular Medicine <lb/>Workshop and was also sponsored by BD, Biozym, eBioscience, Eppendorf, Genentech, <lb/>Invitrogen, Microsynth, VWR, Innsbruck Biocenter and Cell Death and Differentiation. <lb/>We would like to thank the speakers who gave us permission to include unpublished work <lb/>and apologise to those whose work we were unable to include due to space limitations. We <lb/>would also like to thank Professor Marion MacFarlane for her helpful comments. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Meeting Report <lb/></note>

			<page>1947 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Cell Death and Differentiation </note>


	</text>
</tei>
