<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_Chirouze_HESS2014gilles"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>doi:10.5194/hess-18-1165-2014 <lb/>© Author(s) 2014. CC Attribution 3.0 License. <lb/> Hydrology and <lb/>Earth System <lb/>Sciences <lb/> Open Access <lb/>

			Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance <lb/>methods to retrieve surface evapotranspiration and water stress <lb/>of irrigated fields in semi-arid climate <lb/> J. Chirouze  1  , G. Boulet  1  , L. Jarlan  1  , R. Fieuzal  1  , J. C. Rodriguez  2  , J. Ezzahar  3  , S. Er-Raki  4  , G. Bigeard  1  , O. Merlin  1  , <lb/>J. Garatuza-Payan  5  , C. Watts  2  , and G. Chehbouni  1 <lb/>1 Centre d&apos;Etudes Spatiales de la Biosphère, UPS, CNRS, CNES, IRD – UMR5126, Toulouse, France <lb/> 2 Universidad de Sonora, Hermosillo, Sonora, México <lb/> 3 Centre National de l&apos;Energie, des Sciences et des Techniques Nucléaires, Kénitra, Morocco <lb/> 4 LP2M2E, Département de physique, Faculté des Sciences et Techniques, Université Cadi Ayyad, Marrakech, Morocco <lb/> 5 Instituto Tecnológico de Sonora, Ciudad Obregón, Sonora, México <lb/> Correspondence to: G. Boulet (gilles.boulet@cesbio.cnes.fr) <lb/>Received: 18 December 2012 – Published in Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci. Discuss.: 21 January 2013 <lb/>Revised: 11 February 2014 – Accepted: 15 February 2014 – Published: 27 March 2014 <lb/> Abstract. Instantaneous evapotranspiration rates and surface <lb/>water stress levels can be deduced from remotely sensed <lb/>surface temperature data through the surface energy bud-<lb/>get. Two families of methods can be defined: the contex-<lb/>tual methods, where stress levels are scaled on a given im-<lb/>age between hot/dry and cool/wet pixels for a particular veg-<lb/>etation cover, and single-pixel methods, which evaluate la-<lb/>tent heat as the residual of the surface energy balance for <lb/>one pixel independently from the others. Four models, two <lb/>contextual (S-SEBI and a modified triangle method, named <lb/>VIT) and two single-pixel (TSEB, SEBS) are applied over <lb/>one growing season (December–May) for a 4 km × 4 km ir-<lb/>rigated agricultural area in the semi-arid northern Mexico. <lb/>Their performance, both at local and spatial standpoints, are <lb/>compared relatively to energy balance data acquired at seven <lb/>locations within the area, as well as an uncalibrated soil– <lb/>vegetation–atmosphere transfer (SVAT) model forced with <lb/>local in situ data including observed irrigation and rainfall <lb/>amounts. Stress levels are not always well retrieved by most <lb/>models, but S-SEBI as well as TSEB, although slightly bi-<lb/>ased, show good performance. The drop in model perfor-<lb/>mance is observed for all models when vegetation is senes-<lb/>cent, mostly due to a poor partitioning both between tur-<lb/>bulent fluxes and between the soil/plant components of the <lb/>latent heat flux and the available energy. As expected, con-<lb/>textual methods perform well when contrasted soil moisture <lb/>and vegetation conditions are encountered in the same im-<lb/>age (therefore, especially in spring and early summer) while <lb/>they tend to exaggerate the spread in water status in more ho-<lb/>mogeneous conditions (especially in winter). Surface energy <lb/>balance models run with available remotely sensed prod-<lb/>ucts prove to be nearly as accurate as the uncalibrated SVAT <lb/>model forced with in situ data. <lb/> </front>
			
			<body>1 Context and objectives <lb/> Evapotranspiration is the largest water loss component of <lb/>continental surfaces (Oki and Kanae, 2006; Shiklomanov, <lb/>1998). In semi-arid areas, more than 80 % of the annual avail-<lb/>able water is lost through evapotranspiration (Chehbouni et <lb/>al., 2008a). In most countries, and especially the least devel-<lb/>oped ones, irrigation consumes the largest amount of water. <lb/>It often represents more than 80 % of all uses (World Water <lb/>Assessment Programme, 2012). In many cases, water use ef-<lb/>ficiency is lower than 50 %. For countries facing water short-<lb/>age, or likely to suffer from more frequent drought spills <lb/>under climate change scenarios, there is a great need to ra-<lb/>tionalize this use, and therefore to monitor more closely the <lb/>different terms of the water budget (Oki and Kanae, 2006). <lb/>Among them, evapotranspiration is of major importance. <lb/></body>
			
			<front>Published by Copernicus Publications on behalf of the European Geosciences Union. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1166 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			<body>Although the water budget can be fairly easily monitored <lb/>by the farmer at plot scale, it is much more difficult for re-<lb/>gional authorities or national planners to monitor water allo-<lb/>cation and use at the relevant scales, i.e., the irrigated perime-<lb/>ter and the basin scales. To do so, remote sensing data is in-<lb/>creasingly used, because it allows for the description of the <lb/>surface at most scales ranging from plot to region, at a tem-<lb/>poral scale no greater than a few weeks, which is particularly <lb/>important to follow the growth of vegetation. <lb/>There are many methods that compute evapotranspiration <lb/>with the help of remote sensing data (Courault et al., 2005). <lb/>Some methods rely only on the atmospheric demand through <lb/>different radiation and atmospheric variables derived from <lb/>remote sensing (Venturini et al., 2008). Since evapotranspi-<lb/>ration depends largely on the availability of water, which is <lb/>often greater in the root zone than at the soil surface, sur-<lb/>face losses depend mostly on the intensity of transpiration. <lb/>Many methods, especially those designed for irrigated agri-<lb/>culture, which is usually not short of water, compute a poten-<lb/>tial or reference evapotranspiration rate and weight the latent <lb/>heat flux by the amount of vegetation present for each pixel, <lb/>through the use of a vegetation index such as the NDVI (nor-<lb/>malized differential vegetation index; Cleugh et al., 2007). <lb/>But these methods are of little help when vegetation suffers <lb/>from water stress, which means that they have little applica-<lb/>bility for operational management of irrigation water when <lb/>the objective is to prevent stress. <lb/>Since evaporation is the most efficient way to dissipate ex-<lb/>tra energy at the surface, there is a tight coupling between <lb/>water availability and surface temperature under water stress <lb/>conditions. Therefore, the use of information in the thermal <lb/>infrared (TIR) domain (3–15 µm) is an appropriate way to <lb/>assess actual evaporation and soil moisture status at rele-<lb/>vant space and timescales (Boulet et al., 2007; Hain et al., <lb/>2009). Methods to estimate evapotranspiration from satellite <lb/>data in the TIR domain are reviewed in Kalma et al. (2008) <lb/>and Kustas and Anderson (2009). Estimates of instantaneous <lb/>evaporation rates at the time of the satellite overpass can be <lb/>converted into daily values through the use of extrapolation <lb/>algorithms based on the diurnal self-preservation of quan-<lb/>tities like the evaporative fraction, i.e., the ratio between the <lb/>latent heat flux and the available energy (Delogu et al., 2012). <lb/>TIR-based methods to compute instantaneous evapotran-<lb/>spiration can be broadly divided into two families: contextual <lb/>and single-pixel methods. Contextual methods cover all ap-<lb/>proaches based on the simultaneous presence, at the time of <lb/>acquisition, of hot/dry and cold/wet pixels within the satel-<lb/>lite image, for a sufficiently large range of vegetation covers <lb/>or surface states. The latter are usually inferred in other opti-<lb/>cal wavelengths so that for given vegetation type/extent or a <lb/>given value of the scaling surface parameter one can securely <lb/>associate contrasted temperature patterns with contrasted soil <lb/>moisture conditions. Those methods use synchronous infor-<lb/>mation of several pixels of a given image. Each intermedi-<lb/>ate temperature for a given vegetation class is then scaled <lb/>to these extremes to provide an intermediate water stress <lb/>condition. <lb/>On the other hand, single-pixel methods mostly solve the <lb/>surface energy budget for each pixel independently from the <lb/>others. They are more sensitive to absolute errors in surface <lb/>temperature estimates (Cammalleri et al., 2012; Norman et <lb/>al., 2000). However, one usually expects that they are well <lb/>adapted to uniform landscapes with fairly homogeneous veg-<lb/>etation and surface water conditions, such as natural land-<lb/>scapes or rain-fed monoculture, for which contextual meth-<lb/>ods are likely to fail. They are also more adapted to the use <lb/>of low-resolution data. For the latter indeed, pixels are mixed <lb/>and often cover many individual plots with contrasted lev-<lb/>els of NDVI and soil moisture. The resulting conditions tend <lb/>to blur into average effective moisture/vegetation character-<lb/>istics at the pixel scale. They are therefore applied to produce <lb/>global maps of evapotranspiration (Jiménez et al., 2011). <lb/>Contextual models, which use temperature differences in-<lb/>stead of absolute values, are less sensitive to absolute errors <lb/>in surface temperature estimates. But they rely on the as-<lb/>sumption that all soil moisture conditions are present within <lb/>one image for a large enough range of vegetation fraction <lb/>cover. This hypothesis can be sometimes misleading (Choi <lb/>et al., 2009; Gonzalez-Dugo et al., 2009). For instance, just <lb/>after rainfall or after a long dry-down, this assumption can <lb/>be challenged for natural landscapes or rain-fed agriculture. <lb/>Moreover, wet bare soils or fully stressed vegetation are not <lb/>always present on a single image, especially in irrigated agri-<lb/>cultural areas with sufficient water supply. <lb/>Many studies have tested the performance of these mod-<lb/>els at various scales, from very high (Gomez et al., 2005; <lb/>Jacob et al., 2002; Long and Singh, 2012; Minacapilli et al., <lb/>2009; Su et al., 2005; Timmermans et al., 2007) to low spa-<lb/>tial resolution (Jia et al., 2003; McCabe and Wood, 2006; Su <lb/>et al., 2007; Verstraeten et al., 2005; Yang and Wang, 2011). <lb/>But in most cases, those studies lack the temporal represen-<lb/>tativeness of a surface evolution during a full growing season <lb/>(Choi et al., 2009; French et al., 2005; Gonzalez-Dugo et al., <lb/>2009; van der Kwast et al., 2009; Li et al., 2005, 2008; Long <lb/>and Singh, 2012; Ma et al., 2011; McCabe and Wood, 2006; <lb/>Minacapilli et al., 2009; Su et al., 2005, 2007). A nonexhaus-<lb/>tive list of validation and intercomparison studies of surface <lb/>energy budget (SEB) models is shown in Table 1. Depending <lb/>on the experiments, root mean square differences (RMSD) <lb/>for instantaneous retrievals of turbulent fluxes range from <lb/>40 W m  −2  (Gonzalez-Dugo et al., 2009; Jia et al., 2003; Li et <lb/>al., 2008; Long and Singh, 2012; McCabe and Wood, 2006; <lb/>Verstraeten et al., 2005) to more than 150 W m  −2  (Choi et <lb/>al., 2009; Li et al., 2005; Oku et al., 2007). Understanding of <lb/>the reasons for such a wide range of performance is crucial <lb/>in order to implement thermal data in automated operational <lb/>algorithms. <lb/>Amongst well-known models, two algorithms emerge in <lb/>the &quot; single-pixel models &quot; category: TSEB (two-source en-<lb/>ergy balance; Norman et al., 1995) and SEBS (surface <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1167 <lb/></page>

			Table 1. Nonexhaustive review of validation exercises of instantaneous models. One site covers less than 30 × 30 low-resolution pixels, <lb/>1 station covers less than 10 high-resolution pixels. <lb/>Publication <lb/>Model(s) <lb/>Resolution <lb/>Precision on λE <lb/> Spatial and temporal <lb/>(W m  −2  ) <lb/>coverage <lb/>Anderson et al. <lb/>TSEB <lb/>10 m to 10 km (airborne) <lb/>– <lb/>1 station on 1 site, 1 flight <lb/>(2011) <lb/>Choi et al. (2009) <lb/>TSEB, <lb/>60 m (LANDSAT 7) <lb/>RMSD 50–150 <lb/>14 stations on 1 site, 2 dates <lb/>METRIC, <lb/>TRIM <lb/>French et al. (2005) TSEB, <lb/>15–90 m (ASTER) <lb/>Bias 10–80 <lb/>8 stations on 1 site, 1 date <lb/>SEBAL <lb/>Galleguillos et al. <lb/>S-SEBI, <lb/>90 m (ASTER) <lb/>– <lb/>Comparison with SVAT <lb/>(2011) <lb/>WDI <lb/>(Hydrus 1-D) and 1 station <lb/>on 1 site <lb/>Gomez et al. (2005) S-SEBI <lb/>20 m (airborne) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 90 <lb/>7 stations on 1 site, 19 dates <lb/>Gonzalez-Dugo et <lb/>TSEB, <lb/>120–60 m (Landsat 5 &amp; 7) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 50 <lb/>12 stations on 1 site, 3 dates <lb/>al. (2009) <lb/>METRIC <lb/>Jia et al. (2003) <lb/>SEBS, <lb/>1 km (ATSR-2) <lb/>RMSD 10–40 (BR) 11 stations on 1 site, <lb/>SEBI <lb/>11 dates, 1 scintillometer <lb/>Li et al. (2005) <lb/>TSEB <lb/>120–60 m (Landsat 5 &amp; 7, <lb/>RMSD 40–120 <lb/>5 stations on 1 site, 4 dates <lb/>aircraft) <lb/>Li et al. (2008) <lb/>TSEB <lb/>120 m (Landsat 5) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 40 <lb/>3 stations on 1 site, 3 dates <lb/>Long and Singh <lb/>TTME <lb/>90–60 m (ASTER &amp; Landsat) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 50 <lb/>12 stations, 1 site, 4 images <lb/>(2012) <lb/>Ma et al. (2011) <lb/>SEBS <lb/>90 m (ASTER) <lb/>Bias &gt; 80 <lb/>3 stations on 1 site, 4 dates <lb/>McCabe and <lb/>SEBS <lb/>990–1020 m (aggregated <lb/>RMSD 60 (HR) <lb/>7 stations on 1 site, 1 date <lb/>Wood (2006) <lb/>ASTER &amp; Landsat + MODIS) −80 (BR) <lb/>Minacapilli et al. <lb/>TSEB, <lb/>15 m (airborne) <lb/>– <lb/>1 date <lb/>(2009) <lb/>SEBAL <lb/>Oku et al. (2007) <lb/>SEBS <lb/>5–7 km (GMS-5) <lb/>RMSD &gt; 100 <lb/>Su et al. (2007) <lb/>SEBS <lb/>1 km (MODIS) <lb/>RMSD 40–60 <lb/>2 dates, sites CEOP EOP-1 <lb/>Su et al. (2005) <lb/>SEBS <lb/>30 m (LANDSAT 7) &amp; 20 km <lb/>RMSD 30 (HR) <lb/>1 date, 8 stations on 8 sites <lb/>(GOES, MODIS) <lb/> −140 (BR) <lb/>Timmermans et al. <lb/>TSEB, <lb/>6–12 m (airborne) <lb/>RMSD 60–70 <lb/>2 stations on 1 site, <lb/>(2007) <lb/>SEBAL <lb/>5 airborne flights <lb/>Van der Kwast et <lb/>SEBS <lb/>90 m (ASTER) <lb/>– <lb/>6 stations on 1 site, 1 date <lb/>al. (2009) <lb/>Verstraeten et al. <lb/>S-SEBI <lb/>1.1 km (NOAA/AVHRR) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 40 <lb/>13 stations on 13 sites, <lb/>(2005) <lb/>AVHRR series <lb/>Yang and Wang <lb/>S-SEBI <lb/>1 km (MODIS) <lb/>Only evaporative <lb/>12 stations, 12 sites, <lb/>(2011) <lb/>fraction evaluated <lb/>16 dates <lb/>Jacob et al. (2002) <lb/>SEBAL <lb/>20 m (airborne) <lb/>RMSD ∼ 85 <lb/>7 stations, 1 site, <lb/> ∼ 15 airborne flights <lb/> energy balance system; Su, 2002); amongst the contextual <lb/>approaches, one can cite the popular S-SEBI (simplified sur-<lb/>face energy balance index; Roerink et al., 2000) and &quot; trian-<lb/>gle &quot; or &quot; trapezoidal &quot; (Moran et al., 1994) approaches, for <lb/>the most simple ones, or two complex but widely used meth-<lb/>ods, SEBAL (surface energy balance algorithm for land; <lb/>Bastiaanssen et al., 1998) and METRIC (mapping evapo-<lb/>transpiration at high resolution with internalized calibration; <lb/>Allen et al., 2007). <lb/>Due to the limited availability of high-resolution images, <lb/>these models have not yet been tested for a wide range <lb/>of climates and landscapes, spanning various climatic and <lb/>
			
			 <note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1168 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/> </note>
			
			vegetation conditions. Indeed, it is difficult to build a com-<lb/>prehensive yet exhaustive protocol to validate the SEB mod-<lb/>els with enough data in space and time. The main reason is <lb/>that observations of turbulent fluxes are available for long-<lb/>term applications, but for a few locations only, and except <lb/>for intensive international campaigns, no more than one or <lb/>two points within each image. <lb/>Soil–vegetation–atmosphere transfer (SVAT) models, <lb/>however, are able to simulate the surface temperature from <lb/>irrigation and rainfall inputs. In the case of local-scale appli-<lb/>cations where all water-related variables are well known (i.e., <lb/>water inputs, initial soil moisture, etc.), they are expected to <lb/>perform better than surface energy balance methods. How-<lb/>ever, since information about irrigation at regional scale is <lb/>very difficult to assess, those models are difficult to imple-<lb/>ment in large irrigated perimeters. Because surface tempera-<lb/>ture is related to water stress (Hain et al., 2009), one can con-<lb/>strain model prediction through the assimilation of the ob-<lb/>served surface temperature into SVAT models (Coudert and <lb/>Ottlé, 2007; Olioso et al., 2005) and compensate for errors <lb/>in water inputs estimates. Even for most hydrological mod-<lb/>els with daily time steps, which do not simulate the equi-<lb/>librium surface temperature, a remotely sensed evapotran-<lb/>spiration product could be used in an assimilation scheme <lb/>(McCabe et al., 2008; Schuurmans et al., 2003). Again, even <lb/>if most SVAT models are able to assimilate directly the sur-<lb/>face temperature, it is often hard to specify model errors, <lb/>observation errors, and, particularly, spatial model error co-<lb/>variance when assimilating surface temperature images into <lb/>distributed SVAT models. If contextual models show robust <lb/>and reliable performance, the TIR-based evapotranspiration <lb/>products could be assimilated either in SVAT or hydrological <lb/>models by providing additional information about distributed <lb/>constraints of studied areas. <lb/>The main objective of this paper is to test the relative per-<lb/>formance of four TIR-based instantaneous evapotranspira-<lb/>tion and water stress simulation models (two contextual and <lb/>two single-pixel) to retrieve surface fluxes and water stress <lb/>levels from remote sensing data over an intensive irrigated <lb/>perimeter in semi-arid land throughout the main agricultural <lb/>season. It is a necessary preliminary study before assimilat-<lb/>ing evapotranspiration products and their relative error in dis-<lb/>tributed SVAT models, which is our ultimate goal beyond the <lb/>scope of this study. The performance of those four models <lb/>will be assessed through data collected at seven flux stations <lb/>and compared to outputs of an uncalibrated SVAT model <lb/>forced with in situ vegetation, climate and irrigation input <lb/>data measured at those seven stations. <lb/> 2 Material and methods <lb/>2.1 The surface energy balance for estimating <lb/>evapotranspiration <lb/> The first three models (SEBS, TSEB and S-SEBI) compute <lb/>evapotranspiration as the residual of the energy balance, writ-<lb/>ten as follows: <lb/> λE = R  n  − H − G, <lb/> (1) <lb/>where R  n is the net radiation, H the sensible heat flux, λE <lb/> the latent heat flux and G the soil heat flux, all expressed in <lb/>watts per square meter (W m  −2  ). <lb/>Models differ primarily in the partitioning of available en-<lb/>ergy R  n  − G into turbulent fluxes H and λE, and secondly <lb/>on the way they compute the available energy. <lb/> 2.1.1 Available energy <lb/> There are many different ways in the literature to estimate the <lb/>net radiation R  n and soil heat flux G as well as their compo-<lb/>nents from remote sensing data. However, in our model in-<lb/>tercomparison, we focus more precisely on the way available <lb/>energy is partitioned between latent heat flux λE and sensi-<lb/>ble heat flux H . That is why we made the choice to use the <lb/>same formulation of R  n and G for the three models requir-<lb/>ing available energy R  n  − G estimates in the computation of <lb/>evapotranspiration. Starting from the same basis, it will be <lb/>easier to analyze the different model behaviors. <lb/>The general formulation of net radiation is: <lb/> R  n  = (1 − α) · R  sw  + ε · <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> R  lw  − σ · T  4 <lb/>0 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (2) <lb/> R  sw and R  lw are the shortwave and longwave incoming radi-<lb/>ation (respectively), T  0 the surface temperature, α and ε are <lb/>the albedo and the emissivity of the surface (respectively) <lb/>and σ the Stefan–Boltzmann constant. For all SEB models, <lb/>the emissivity value of the surface is fixed at 0.98 for the <lb/>whole scene and for each date. <lb/>The amount of available formulation in the literature to <lb/>estimate the soil heat flux is much larger than for the net ra-<lb/>diation (for example, see Bastiaanssen, 2000; Norman et al., <lb/>1995; Roerink et al., 2000; Santanello and Friedl, 2003; and <lb/>Su, 2002). It has been shown that for a fixed time around <lb/>midday, G can be considered as proportional to the net ra-<lb/>diation, the proportionality factor being determined by the <lb/>surface vegetation and soil properties. <lb/>We tested each formulation of G proposed in the three SEB <lb/>models (Norman et al., 1995; Roerink et al., 2000; Su, 2002), <lb/>which require an estimate of the ground heat flux, as well <lb/>as the Bastiaanssen (2000) formulation implemented in the <lb/>METRIC model. The latter proved to be the most accurate, <lb/>with a RMSD of 57 W m  −2  when applied to the current data <lb/>set (which will be detailed later in the paper) whereas the <lb/>other formulations showed RMSD greater than 90 W m  −2  . <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1169 <lb/></page>

			Thus we chose to implement it for all methods. Its formula-<lb/>tion is detailed in Eq. (3). <lb/> G = R  n  T  0  × (0.0038 + 0.0074 α) × (1 − 0.98 NDVI 4  ) (3) <lb/> 2.1.2 Single-pixel models <lb/> Both single-pixel models compute turbulent exchanges be-<lb/>tween the source at the aerodynamic level and the reference <lb/>level z where atmospheric forcing data is available, usually <lb/>just a few meters above the crop height. Heat transfers are <lb/>based on the Monin–Obukhov similarity theory in the atmo-<lb/>spheric boundary layer (ABL). Bulk ABL similarity func-<lb/>tions proposed by Brutsaert (1999) describe the wind and <lb/>temperature profiles in the turbulent environment (Eqs. 4, 5; <lb/>see Brutsaert, 1999; and Su, 2002). <lb/> T  aero  − T  a  = <lb/> H <lb/> ρ C  p <lb/> × <lb/> 1 <lb/> k u  * <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ln <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> z − d  0 <lb/> z  0h <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> − 񮽙  h <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> z − d  0 <lb/> L <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> + 񮽙  h <lb/> z  0h <lb/> L <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> H <lb/> ρ C  p <lb/> × r  a <lb/> (4) <lb/> u = <lb/> u  * <lb/> k <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ln <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> z − d  0 <lb/> z  0m <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> − 񮽙  m <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> z − d  0 <lb/> L <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> + 񮽙  m <lb/> z  0m <lb/> L <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (5) <lb/> r  a is the aerodynamic resistance to heat transfer at the <lb/>surface–atmosphere interface, u is the wind velocity at <lb/>level z, k = 0.4 is the von Karman constant, d  0 is the dis-<lb/>placement height (d 0  ≈ h  c  × 2 / 3, h  c being the crop height), <lb/>and z  0m is the roughness height for momentum transfer <lb/>(d 0  ≈ h  c  × 0.123). T  a and T  aero are the temperature of the air <lb/>at reference and aerodynamic levels (respectively), ρ is the <lb/>density of the air, C  p is the heat capacity of air and z  0h is the <lb/>roughness height for heat transfer. 񮽙  m and 񮽙  h are the sta-<lb/>bility correction functions for momentum and sensible heat <lb/>transfer and L is the Monin–Obukhov length (Su, 2002). <lb/>If one agrees in general that Eq. (4) provides a fairly robust <lb/>estimate of the aerodynamic resistance to heat transfer r  a , <lb/>estimating the aerodynamic temperature remains a difficult <lb/>issue (Kustas and Anderson, 2009). There is currently no way <lb/>to measure this temperature directly, and models rely usually <lb/>on the only available data, the surface temperature obtained <lb/>by satellite imagery. The difference between the two single-<lb/>pixel models will thus lie in the approximation made in order <lb/>to relate T  aero to the radiometric surface temperature T  0 . <lb/> The surface energy balance system (SEBS) model <lb/> SEBS (Su, 2002) computes the latent heat flux as the residual <lb/>of the energy balance for a mixed pixel. The particularity <lb/>of the SEBS model resides in two points. First, it proposes <lb/>a new formulation of the difference between the roughness <lb/>for heat transfer z  0h (Eqs. 6–7) and momentum z  0m , which <lb/>allows one to replace T  aero by T  0 in Eq. (4): <lb/> z  0h  = <lb/> z  0m <lb/> exp <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k B  −1 <lb/> 񮽙 , <lb/> (6) <lb/>where: <lb/> k B  −1  = A  1  × f  2 <lb/>c  + A  2  × f  c  f  s  + k B  −1 <lb/> s  × f  2 <lb/>s  . <lb/> (7) <lb/>The first term A  1 describes the full canopy aerodynamic <lb/>properties (Choudhury and Monteith, 1988), k B  −1 <lb/> s <lb/> is rep-<lb/>resentative of the bare-soil properties and the A  2 term takes <lb/>into account the interactions between the vegetation and the <lb/>bare soil. f  c is the canopy coverage fraction and f  s = 1 − f  c . <lb/>The other specificity of SEBS lies in the retrieval of the <lb/>latent heat flux. Once the sensible heat flux is computed using <lb/>Eq. (4) the model ensures that the retrieved latent heat flux <lb/>is bounded by two theoretical, extreme conditions under the <lb/>given climate forcing (null and potential evapotranspiration <lb/>rates, Eqs. 8 and 9, respectively). This is achieved through the <lb/>substitution of any outlier with the corresponding theoretical <lb/>minimum (Eq. 8) or maximum (Eq. 9): <lb/> λE  dry  = 0, <lb/>(8) <lb/> λE  wet  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> R  n  − G − <lb/> ρ C  p  (e  s  − e) <lb/>r  ew  γ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> / <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 1 + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>γ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (9) <lb/> λE  dry and λE  wet are the latent heat fluxes in those extreme <lb/>dry and wet conditions. e and e  s are respectively the actual <lb/>and saturation vapor pressure, γ is the psychrometric con-<lb/>stant, 񮽙 is the slope of saturation vapor pressure curve at <lb/>temperature T  a and r  ew is the aerodynamic resistance for wet <lb/>conditions. <lb/> The two-source energy balance (TSEB) model <lb/> TSEB computes two separate energy budgets for the soil <lb/>and the vegetation, and estimates evaporation and transpi-<lb/>ration (respectively) as residual terms of the energy balance <lb/>(see Eqs. 10 and 11). Net radiation is computed according <lb/>to Eq. (2). It is then partitioned based on fraction cover into <lb/>the two main components, the net radiation of the canopy <lb/> R  n,c , and the bare-soil R  n,s (Norman et al., 1995) respec-<lb/>tively. Both energy balance equations read <lb/> R  n,c  = H  c  + λE  c  , <lb/> (10) <lb/> R  n,s  = H  s  + λE  s  + G. <lb/> (11) <lb/> H  s and λE  s are the sensible and latent heat flux at the <lb/>soil–atmosphere interface and H  c and λE  c the fluxes at <lb/>the canopy–atmosphere interface (partitioning of the energy <lb/>budget is summarized in Fig. 1). <lb/>Similarly to Eq. (1), both latent heat flux components λE  s <lb/> and λE  c can be retrieved as residuals of both energy bal-<lb/>ance equations provided that the soil (T s ) and vegetation (T c ) <lb/>component surface temperatures are known. The &quot; trick &quot; to <lb/>get two unknowns out of one single piece of information <lb/>(mixed-pixel temperature) is to assume that in many cases <lb/>the vegetation is unstressed and transpires at a potential rate <lb/> λE  c , which is obtained with a Priestley–Taylor formulation <lb/>(see Eq. 12). <lb/> λE  c  = 1.3 f  g <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 + γ <lb/> R  n,c  , <lb/> (12) <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1170 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			Fig. 1. Scheme of the resistance network of TSEB following <lb/>Norman et al. (1995). <lb/> where f  g is the green fraction of leaf area index (LAI). Here, <lb/>LAI is retrieved from the NDVI and is thus considered as <lb/>green LAI. As a consequence, f  g is set to one in our appli-<lb/>cation. Fraction cover is estimated from LAI with a Beer– <lb/>Lambert law using a fixed extinction coefficient of 0.4. This <lb/>first computation of λE  c gives us a first guess of H  c , as a <lb/>residual of the energy budget of the canopy (Eq. 10). The <lb/>canopy temperature T  c can be deduced from the canopy&apos;s <lb/>sensible heat flux H  c through a formulation similar to Eq. (4). <lb/>The total sensible heat flux H is <lb/> H = H  s  + H  c  = ρ C  p <lb/> T  s  − T  a <lb/> r  a  + r  s <lb/> + ρ C  p <lb/> T  c  − T  a <lb/> r  a <lb/> , <lb/> (13) <lb/>where the resistance r  s takes into consideration the resistance <lb/>to heat transfer in the boundary layer immediately above the <lb/>soil surface. <lb/>Equation (14) (Norman et al., 1995) links canopy and soil <lb/>temperatures to the observed radiometric temperature T  0 and <lb/> f  c and allows one to calculate T  s : <lb/> T  0  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> f  c  T  4 <lb/>c  + (1 − f  c  ) T  4 <lb/>s <lb/> 񮽙  1/4 <lb/> . <lb/> (14) <lb/>Combining Eqs. (11) and (13) gives H  s and λE  s . If λE  s is <lb/>positive then a balance is reached. If λE  s  &lt; 0, the assumption <lb/>that the vegetation transpires at a potential rate is no longer <lb/>valid, the soil is considered as dry and λE  s set to zero and the <lb/>other parameters are computed from Eqs. (11), (13) and (14). <lb/> λE  c is obtained as a residual of Eq. (10). If λE  c is negative <lb/>then soil and vegetation are dry and λE  c is set to zero. Then <lb/> H  c = R  n,c and Eqs. (13) and (14) lead to a new H  s . G is com-<lb/>puted as the residual of the energy balance for the bare soil <lb/>(and thus differs in this specific case from the other models). <lb/> 2.1.3 Contextual models <lb/>The simplified surface energy balance index (S-SEBI) <lb/>model <lb/> The S-SEBI (Roerink et al., 2000) model is based on the ob-<lb/>servation that for homogeneous atmospheric conditions over <lb/>a scene, the scatter plot between surface temperature T  0 and <lb/>surface albedo α is bounded by two theoretical lines cor-<lb/>responding to extreme soil moisture conditions (see Fig. 2, <lb/>upper panels). The method then considers for each pixel α <lb/> the corresponding extreme conditions (with the same avail-<lb/>able energy) with the respective surface temperatures T  hot <lb/> and T  cold . Those conditions correspond respectively to dry <lb/>(λE min = 0, H = H  max ) and wet (λE = λE  max , H  min = 0) ar-<lb/>eas where all the available energy is used to evaporate. The <lb/>evaporative fraction is then computed using those extreme <lb/>temperatures according to <lb/> 񮽙 = <lb/> λE <lb/> R  n  − G <lb/> = <lb/> R  n  − G − H <lb/>R  n  − G <lb/> = <lb/> H  max  − H <lb/>H  max <lb/> . <lb/> (15) <lb/>From Eq. (4), we can deduce that, for a given range of albedo, <lb/>the wet boundary conditions (H = 0) implies T  cold  ≈ T  a . So if <lb/>we replace T  a by T  cold , we can deduce from Eqs. (4) and (15) <lb/>the following formulation of the evaporative fraction: <lb/> 񮽙 = <lb/> T  hot  (α) − T  0 <lb/> T  hot  (α) − T  cold  (α) <lb/>. <lb/> (16) <lb/>The turbulent fluxes H and λE are then deduced from the <lb/>evaporative fraction (Eq. 16) and an estimate of the available <lb/>energy (Eq. 2). <lb/> A vegetation index-temperature trapezoid method <lb/>(VIT) <lb/> Similarly, Moran et al. (1994) proposed a method for retriev-<lb/>ing λE on large areas by combining information on the tem-<lb/>perature difference, 񮽙T = T  0  − T  a , and vegetation extent. In <lb/>the original method, the Penman–Monteith equation is ap-<lb/>plied to calculate equilibrium surface-to-air temperature dif-<lb/>ferences (T 0  − T  a ) in four extreme conditions of soil mois-<lb/>ture and vegetation cover (well watered and fully stressed <lb/>canopies, wet and dry bare soils). Four theoretical vertices <lb/>of a trapezoid in the T  0 /VI (VI for vegetation index) space <lb/>are obtained (see Fig. 2, lower left panel). The other assump-<lb/>tion is that T  0  − T  a is linearly related to the vegetation cover, <lb/>which itself is linearly related to the vegetation index used <lb/>by Moran et al. (1994), the soil-adjusted vegetation index <lb/>(SAVI). This allows straight lines to be drawn between the <lb/>vertices 1 and 3 and the vertices 2 and 4. The third assump-<lb/>tion that us allows to link this graphic representation to the <lb/>water status of the surface is that, for uniform available en-<lb/>ergy, vapor pressure deficit of the air and aerodynamic resis-<lb/>tance values, T  s  − T  a and T  c  − T  a , are linearly dependent on <lb/>evaporation and transpiration, respectively. The land surface <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1171 <lb/></page>

			Fig. 2. Upper panels: ASTER surface temperature vs. FORMOSAT-2 albedo scatter plot and dry and hot regression law determined with the <lb/>SPLIT method in S-SEBI. The points&apos; colors correspond to the value of FORMOSAT-2 NDVI for each pixel. Lower panels: FORMOSAT-2 <lb/>NDVI vs. ASTER surface temperature scatter plot and the trapezoid determined with the SPLIT method in VIT. For both methods, the plots <lb/>are made for 10 March and 6 May. <lb/> temperature T  0 being directly linked to T  s and T  c , the linear <lb/>relation between T  0 and evapotranspiration is established as <lb/>follows: <lb/>WDI = <lb/> 񮽙T − 񮽙T  min <lb/> 񮽙T  max  − 񮽙T  min <lb/> , <lb/> (17) <lb/>where WDI is the water deficit index; 񮽙T , 񮽙T  min and 񮽙T  max <lb/> are respectively the surface-to-air temperature difference at <lb/>points C (actual case), A (well watered case) and B (stressed <lb/>case). Graphically, it corresponds to the ratio of the dis-<lb/>tances AC and AB. WDI can be assimilated to surface water <lb/>stress. Other applications of the VIT method also use NDVI <lb/>or fraction cover instead of SAVI. <lb/>In our case, a preliminary study had shown that the the-<lb/>oretical vertices calculated with the Moran et al. (1994) ap-<lb/>proach were not usable. Actually, the theoretical trapezoid <lb/>did not include all the situations present in the images (not <lb/>shown). Thus, pixels with unrealistic values of WDI were <lb/>present, i.e., either with negative values or values larger than <lb/>one. We then chose to make an assumption similar to the one <lb/>made in the S-SEBI method, which is that the variety of rel-<lb/>ative moisture conditions present in the image is sufficient <lb/>to assess, if not the four extreme points, at least the bounding <lb/>linear relationships (lines 1–3 and 2–4) corresponding to well <lb/>watered cold points and stressed hot ones. We thus decided <lb/>to derive the four vertices graphically and not theoretically <lb/>by drawing the bounding trapezoid for each 񮽙T –NDVI scat-<lb/>ter plot. Since we have a flat study zone of limited extent, we <lb/>consider that a single air temperature measurement at 10 m <lb/>is representative of the whole area. We can then work on the <lb/>NDVI–T 0 scatter plots directly. <lb/> 2.1.4 Method to retrieve water status extremes in <lb/>contextual models <lb/> Various methods to retrieve linear relationships correspond-<lb/>ing to extreme boundary conditions between surface tem-<lb/>perature and albedo (S-SEBI) or NDVI (VIT) have been <lb/>tested (not shown). They are either manual or automatic, with <lb/>different levels of complexity. An entirely manual method <lb/>would allow the user to take into account qualitative a priori <lb/>information on the surface (type of cultivated crop, sewing, <lb/>harvesting and irrigations dates, etc.) to decide whether ex-<lb/>tremes correspond to target situations (for instance, wet bare <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1172 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			soils or dense vegetation under water stress) or anecdotic out-<lb/>liers. However, manual methods are not appropriate for inte-<lb/>gration into operational automated retrieval algorithms. That <lb/>is why we chose to use the automatic method presented in <lb/>Verstraeten et al. (2005) and named SPLIT method. In this <lb/>method, a classification of albedo values is performed. We <lb/>chose a subdivision in ten classes of albedo values for each <lb/>image. For each class, the median of the 5 % maximum and <lb/>the median of the 5 % minimum surface temperature values <lb/>are identified, then the least square method is applied to those <lb/>median values to retrieve each bounding linear relation. In <lb/>our application of the VIT and S-SEBI methods, we infer <lb/>the bounding relationships on a subset of the original image, <lb/>corresponding to our area of interest (4 km × 4 km). This is <lb/>justified by the fact that our landscape is an irrigated agri-<lb/>cultural area, which is by nature heterogeneous but holds a <lb/>fairly uniform distribution of this heterogeneity (in terms of <lb/>land cover and irrigation practices). <lb/> 2.1.5 The soil–vegetation–atmosphere transfer (SVAT) <lb/>model <lb/> In this study we use the outputs of the interactive canopy <lb/>radiative exchange (ICARE) SVAT model as a reference or <lb/>benchmarking tool to relate the SEB models&apos; performance. <lb/>ICARE is a classic dual-source SVAT model that solves both <lb/>water and energy balance of the surface. It is forced with <lb/>climatic and vegetation growth data. The main differences <lb/>between the SVAT model and the SEB models reside in two <lb/>points. <lb/>First, the water balance module simulates the evolution of <lb/>soil moisture for two soil layers (shallow surface and root <lb/>zone) using the force–restore method (Noilhan and Planton, <lb/>1989): <lb/> 񮽙  ∂w  s <lb/> ∂t  =  C  1 <lb/> ρ  w  d  1 <lb/> (P + I − E  s  ) −  C  2 <lb/> τ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> w  s  − w  eq <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂w  2 <lb/> ∂t  =  P + I − E  s  − E  c <lb/> ρ  w  d  2 <lb/> (18) <lb/>where w  s and w  2 are respectively the surface layer and root <lb/>zone volumetric soil moisture, P the precipitation rate, I the <lb/>irrigation rate, E  s the soil evaporation rate, E  c the plant tran-<lb/>spiration rate, d  1 and d  2 the thickness of surface layer and <lb/>root zone respectively set at 0.05 and 1 m for all crops, τ <lb/> the diurnal time period (1 day) and ρ  w the density of wa-<lb/>ter. C  1 and C  2 are coefficients estimated following the ISBA <lb/>model (Noilhan and Mahfouf, 1996) depending on soil tex-<lb/>ture (pedotransfer functions) and w  eq is an equilibrium soil <lb/>surface moisture representing the case where capillarity and <lb/>gravity forces compensate each other. E  s and E  c are com-<lb/>puted with a coupled two-source energy balance equation <lb/>(Shuttleworth and Wallace, 1985); and they depend respec-<lb/>tively on a surface resistance to evaporation (a function of <lb/>surface soil moisture, Passerat de Silans, 1986) and a stom-<lb/>atal resistance (a function of root zone soil moisture, Noilhan <lb/>and Planton, 1989). Surface and root zone temperatures in <lb/>the soil are also computed using the force–restore method <lb/>based on a classical heat diffusion law. As any dynamic <lb/>model, initial conditions for the surface and the root zone <lb/>temperature and moisture levels are required. In our applica-<lb/>tion, initial conditions are taken from in situ measurements <lb/>at each station. <lb/>Second, contrary to SEB models, the surface temperature <lb/>is not an input but an output of the SVAT model. Direct infor-<lb/>mation about soil moisture is absent from the SEB models, <lb/>in opposition to the SVAT model, which is forced by rain <lb/>(null over the season in our case) and irrigation time series. <lb/>Next is the computation of the radiation budget. The model <lb/>used by ICARE is not forced by a remotely sensed albedo <lb/>value but computes its own broadband albedo with a multi-<lb/>ple reflections model and fixed values of soil and vegetation <lb/>broadband reflectances; and it is likely to introduce differ-<lb/>ences in the computation of the net radiation. Finally, the soil <lb/>heat flux G is not calculated as a fraction of the net radiation <lb/>but as a residual of the energy budget; and it provides an up-<lb/>per boundary condition to the heat diffusion law between the <lb/>soil layers. Soil texture was determined from in situ measure-<lb/>ments at each station and the main physical parameters of soil <lb/>were estimated following ISBA&apos;s own pedotransfer functions <lb/>(Noilhan and Mahfouf, 1996, Appendix A4). Estimation of <lb/>the available energy differs significantly from the SEB mod-<lb/>els. A more detailed presentation of the model is available in <lb/>Gentine et al. (2007). <lb/>As any complex physically based SVAT model, ICARE re-<lb/>quires a large set of input parameters describing the different <lb/>properties of the surface (soil and vegetation). Those parame-<lb/>ters need to be calibrated in order to obtain consistent results. <lb/>However, we chose to run the model in its most standardized <lb/>version, with literature or measured values, when available. <lb/>Vegetation parameters such as leaf aerodynamic properties <lb/>were determined using standard values from the literature. <lb/>In situ measured input data for vegetation includes vegeta-<lb/>tion height and green and dry LAIs, respectively. Total LAI <lb/>is used to compute fraction cover and within canopy aerody-<lb/>namic resistances, whereas green LAI weights the stomatal <lb/>resistance. The only soil parameter that has been calibrated <lb/>was the soil resistance to evaporation r  ss , because soil tex-<lb/>ture and composition are almost uniform over the whole area. <lb/>This choice was also made because future implementation of <lb/>data assimilation in ICARE would provide a way to calibrate <lb/>the model. Therefore, we wished to compare the SEB models <lb/>to a SVAT model running with the most &quot; standard &quot; set of pa-<lb/>rameters possible. The formulation of r  ss is given in Eq. (19) <lb/>from Passerat de Silans (1986). w  s is the soil water content <lb/>index and w  sat the soil saturation soil water content index. <lb/> A  rss and B  rss are therefore the only two empirical constants <lb/>that have been calibrated. <lb/> r  ss  = exp <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  rss  − B  rss <lb/> w  s <lb/> w  sat <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (19) <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1173 <lb/></page>

			The calibration of A  rss and B  rss has been done simultane-<lb/>ously on the sole northeastern wheat eddy covariance (EC) <lb/>station (wheat(1), see Sect. 2.2.1) when the surface was al-<lb/>most bare using a multicriteria approach on two observed <lb/>variables: the latent heat flux and the surface (5 cm) soil <lb/>moisture. The minimum value of the sum of the relative ab-<lb/>solute difference of these two variables, scaled by their mean <lb/>value, was searched systematically for all parameters com-<lb/>binations within the 0–20 range. Results of this calibration <lb/>lead to values of 12 and 19 for A  rss and B  rss (respectively). <lb/>The minimum stomatal resistance, which is a very sensitive <lb/>parameter for the estimation of latent heat flux, has been set <lb/>to 100 s m  −1  (Gentine et al., 2007; Martin et al., 1999). <lb/>The SVAT model has been run at each station at a half hour <lb/>time step for the whole growing season, except for the chili <lb/>pepper station. The latter was covered by a white cap dur-<lb/>ing half of the season, which is not accounted for by ICARE. <lb/>Since irrigation patterns are not known with enough preci-<lb/>sion, ICARE is not run spatially to produce maps, but locally <lb/>at each flux station. <lb/> 2.2 Site and data acquisition <lb/>2.2.1 Site description <lb/> This study was conducted in the Yaqui Valley (27.4  •  N, <lb/>109.9  •  W), in the state of Sonora, northwestern Mexico. With <lb/>an area of 225 000 ha, bordered on the southwest by the <lb/>Sea of Cortez and on the northeast by the Sierra Madre, <lb/>it is the largest agricultural district of the state. The main <lb/>cultivated crop is winter wheat. The climate is semi-arid <lb/>with an average annual potential evapotranspiration of about <lb/>2233 mm (1971–2000 average; Servicio Meteorológico Na-<lb/>cional, México, http://smn.cna.gob.mx), far greater than the <lb/>average annual precipitation, which is 290 mm (1981–2000 <lb/>average; see http://smn.cna.gob.mx/observatorios/historica/ <lb/>obregon.pdf). Rainfall is brought essentially during the mon-<lb/>soon season (from June to September) with only 42.8 mm of <lb/>precipitation from January to June. About 90 % of the water <lb/>consumption in the valley comes from irrigation (Chehbouni <lb/>et al., 2008b). The estimation of water losses by evapotran-<lb/>spiration is consequently a key factor in the management of <lb/>water at the regional scale. <lb/>From December 2007 to May 2008, an international <lb/>cooperative experiment was carried out over a square of <lb/>4 km × 4 km, located south of the city of Ciudad Obregón <lb/>(center of the zone: 27.263  •  N, 109.892  •  W). Around 50 % <lb/>of the cultivated crops are wheat. The remaining part is di-<lb/>vided between broccoli, beans, chili pepper, potatoes, chick-<lb/>pea, safflower, orange and corn. Seven micro-meteorological <lb/>stations equipped with an EC flux measurement system were <lb/>installed in different fields. Their location is shown in Fig. 3. <lb/> Fig. 3. Satellite view of the studied zone with respective positions of <lb/>the EC stations (Imagerie © 2012 Cnes/Spot Image, DigitalGlobe, <lb/>Données cartographiques © 2012 Google, INEGI). <lb/> 2.2.2 Automated data acquisition <lb/> Meteorological data were acquired at a height of 10 m from a <lb/>weather station installed at the center of the zone. It provided <lb/>measurements of wind speed and direction (R. M. Young <lb/>anemometer), air temperature and moisture (Vaisala humid-<lb/>ity and temperature sensor). Missing data were replaced with <lb/>a combination of the meteorological data also available at <lb/>each EC station. Data were acquired with half hourly time <lb/>steps from 27 December 2007 to 13 May 2008. <lb/>At each of the seven sites, the net radiation was acquired <lb/>using CNR1 (Kipp &amp; Zonen, stations (1), (3) and (7)) and <lb/>Q7.1 (REBS, stations (2), (4), (5) and (6)) radiometers. The <lb/>soil heat flux was estimated with HUKSEFLUX HFP-01 <lb/>plates buried at 0.05 m at the top and bottom of the fur-<lb/>row (when applicable). Surface temperature was measured <lb/>at each site with Apogee infrared radiometers at nadir, at 2m <lb/>height (which corresponds to a footprint radius of 0.66 m). <lb/>Soil moisture was acquired at 0.05 and 0.3 m depths using <lb/>a CS616 TDR (time domain reflectometer, Campbell Scien-<lb/>tific Inc., UT, USA). Those data were acquired at a sampling <lb/>interval of 10 s then averaged and recorded every 30 min. <lb/>Latent and sensible heat fluxes were measured with KH20 <lb/>fast response hygrometers (Campbell) and Campbell CSAT3 <lb/>or RM Young 81000 3D sonic anemometers at a frequency <lb/>of 10 Hz. <lb/> 2.2.3 Discontinuous measurements <lb/> In addition to the data acquired by the automatic stations, in <lb/>situ measurements of vegetation properties were also carried <lb/>out. Crop height and LAI were measured at various dates <lb/>during the whole study, every week on average. They were <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1174 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			linearly interpolated between two successive dates to pro-<lb/>vide input data for ICARE. LAI was estimated from destruc-<lb/>tive measurements as well as hemispherical photographs for <lb/>23 fields representative of the various land use types. Gravi-<lb/>metric soil moisture profiles at each station were carried <lb/>out each week. Those measurements allowed us to cali-<lb/>brate the CS616 TDR installed at each station. Soil texture <lb/>was analyzed at each site at the beginning of the study pe-<lb/>riod. Surface (0–5 cm) soil moisture was acquired spatially <lb/>with ThetaProbe sensors (Delta-T) every week also at some <lb/>200 locations from December to May. <lb/> 2.2.4 Remote sensing data <lb/> Seven ASTER (Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission <lb/>and Reflection Radiometer; http://asterweb.jpl.nasa.gov/) <lb/>images were acquired in the thermal infrared domain from <lb/>December 2007 to May 2008. The resolution of the land <lb/>surface temperature product (AST08; https://lpdaac.usgs. <lb/>gov/products/aster_productstable/ast08) is 90 m and is atmo-<lb/>spherically corrected. <lb/>FORMOSAT-2 is an earth observation satellite launched <lb/>in 2004 by the National Space Organization of Taiwan. It <lb/>provides high-resolution (8 m) images of a particular area ev-<lb/>ery day at 09:30 LT (local time) for four bands (blue, green, <lb/>red and near infrared) and with the same view angle. More <lb/>details can be found in Chern et al. (2008). For our study, <lb/>26 cloud-free images were obtained from 27 December 2007 <lb/>to 13 May 2008, which represents a regular acquisition fre-<lb/>quency of on average 1 image every 5 days (see Fieuzal and <lb/>al., 2011, for more details). Remote Sensing products such <lb/>as NDVI derived from FORMOSAT-2 data were linearly in-<lb/>terpolated to the date of the ASTER acquisition date. <lb/> 2.3 Data processing <lb/>2.3.1 Flux data <lb/> The turbulent fluxes from the EC stations were processed of-<lb/>fline. A post-processing software (EC Pack) developed by the <lb/>Meteorology and Air Quality group at Wageningen Univer-<lb/>sity (http://wwWmet.wau.nl/) was applied. A detailed expla-<lb/>nation of the correction procedure is available in Van Dijk et <lb/>al. (2004). <lb/>After rejection of inconsistent data due to instability or <lb/>malfunction of the instruments, erroneous values of H and <lb/> λE were still present. The closure of the energy balance was <lb/>not achieved most of the time, with a residual at the half <lb/>hourly time step comprised between 24 and 38 % of total <lb/>available energy, depending on the station. This error is in <lb/>the upper range of what can be found in the literature (Twine <lb/>et al., 2000; Wilson et al., 2002). The gap in energy clo-<lb/>sure is often partly due to instrumental limitations. Indeed, <lb/>although they acquire wind speed and specific humidity fluc-<lb/>tuations at high frequencies, EC systems still miss part of the <lb/>energy fluctuations occurring at very high frequencies, lead-<lb/>ing to an underestimation of turbulent fluxes. Estimation of <lb/>the soil heat flux can also be questioned for row crops since <lb/>it is derived from a simple average of values measured at the <lb/>top and bottom of the furrow, corrected for the soil energy <lb/>storage through the use of a thermocouple buried at 5 cm. In <lb/>addition, the malfunctioning of some instruments was iden-<lb/>tified during the Yaqui 2008 experiment, especially Krypton <lb/>hygrometers of stations (2) and (4) and the CNR1 sensor of <lb/>station (1). Finally, differences of energy closure issues be-<lb/>tween the stations result both from the variability of observed <lb/>surface properties, like crop geometry, and differences be-<lb/>tween the various instrumental setups (brand, provenance, <lb/>and maintenance history). At station (1), the CNR1, com-<lb/>pared to those installed at other stations, proved to underesti-<lb/>mate the incoming solar radiation component of the radiation <lb/>budget. This term has been replaced with a mean value of <lb/>measurements at other stations. Surface energy balance clo-<lb/>sure was forced using two different methods. In the case of <lb/>stations (2) and (4) where the KH20 did not work, we chose <lb/>to trust the estimation of H by the sonic anemometer and <lb/>to discard the measurements of λE. The corrected λE was <lb/>computed as the residual of the energy balance R  n  − G − H . <lb/>For stations (1), (3) and (6), the regression slope between <lb/>available energy and the sum of turbulent fluxes was larger <lb/>than 0.65, therefore both fluxes can be considered as consis-<lb/>tent. The &quot; Bowen-ratio closure &quot; method is then used (Barr et <lb/>al., 1994; Blanken et al., 1997). The estimation of the Bowen <lb/>ratio H /λE is considered as correct and the fluxes are ad-<lb/>justed to close the energy balance. The safflower station (7) <lb/>had both problems with the turbulent and soil heat fluxes so <lb/>we excluded its data from the study. Finally, we did not suc-<lb/>ceed in integrating the drip irrigation data of the chili pepper <lb/>station (5) into ICARE, therefore this station has not been <lb/>used in the intercomparison. The dates and EC station num-<lb/>bers for which data were used in the intercomparison are re-<lb/>ported in Table 2. <lb/> 2.3.2 Remote sensing data <lb/> The observed distributed radiometric surface temperature <lb/>used in this paper is the AST08 product from the ASTER <lb/>sensor. The seven images were downloaded from the Earth <lb/>Observing System Data Gateway. The overpass time is <lb/>around 11:00 LT and the dates of the images are 30 Decem-<lb/>ber 2007, 23 February, 10 March, 11 April, 27 April, 6 and <lb/>13 May 2008. The resolution of this product is 90 m and the <lb/>scenes are around 60 km × 60 km. The surface temperature <lb/>is retrieved by the temperature and emissivity separation al-<lb/>gorithm (Gillespie et al., 1998; Schmugge et al., 1998). The <lb/>absolute registration of the images has been done based on <lb/>a FORMOSAT-2 8 m resolution image (Merlin et al., 2010). <lb/>The extracted sub-images of the 4 km× 4 km study zone were <lb/>then resampled by bi-cubic interpolation at a resolution of <lb/>100 m for future model comparison. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1175 <lb/></page>

			Table 2. EC stations used to compute performance statistics at each date. Correspondence of numbers and stations : (1) wheat (east), (2) wheat <lb/>(west), (3) broccoli/beans, (4) chickpea, (5) chili pepper, (6) potatoes/sorghum and (7) safflower. <lb/>Observed data <lb/>Date <lb/>30 Dec 2007 23 Feb 2008 10 Mar 2008 11 Apr 2008 27 Apr 2008 6 May 2008 13 May 2008 <lb/> R  n <lb/> – <lb/>1–4 <lb/>1–4 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1, 2, 4, 6 <lb/> G <lb/> – <lb/>1, 2, 4 <lb/>1–4 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>2–4, 6 <lb/> H <lb/> 3 <lb/>1–3 <lb/>1–3 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/> λE <lb/> 3 <lb/>1, 2, 4 <lb/>1, 2 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, 6 <lb/>1–4, <lb/> α <lb/> 3 <lb/>1, 3 <lb/>1, 3, 7 <lb/>1, 3, 7 <lb/>1, 3, 7 <lb/>1, 3, 7 <lb/>1, 7 <lb/> T  0 <lb/> – <lb/>1–5 <lb/>1–5, 7 <lb/>1–5, 7 <lb/>1–7 <lb/>1–7 <lb/>1, 2, 4–7 <lb/> The error in the ASTER T  0 product is classically around <lb/>1.5 K (Jacob et al., 2008; Sabol et al., 2009). <lb/>The 26 FORMOSAT-2 images were registered using <lb/>GPS ground control points and reprojected in the UTM <lb/>WGS (Universal Transverse Mercator World Geodetic Sys-<lb/>tem) 1984 12 N coordinate system. Then an atmospheric <lb/>correction was applied (Hagolle et al., 2008). Finally, <lb/>the 4 km × 4 km study area was extracted and re sam-<lb/>pled at 100 m resolution by aggregation (averaging) of <lb/>FORMOSAT-2 pixels. <lb/>Although the ASTER platform provides more bands in <lb/>the near (NIR) and shortwave infrared (SWIR) domain than <lb/>FORMOSAT-2, which would suggest that a more consistent <lb/>shortwave broadband albedo can be computed, a dysfunction <lb/>of the SWIR sensor occurred on four of the seven available <lb/>ASTER dates. This made calculus of an ASTER albedo im-<lb/>possible on those dates and FORMOSAT-2 data were chosen <lb/>in order to keep a homogeneous albedo over the whole study <lb/>and not multiply the sources of error. Albedo was computed <lb/>as a linear combination of bands 3 (red) and 4 (near infrared) <lb/>of FORMOSAT-2, according to Courault et al. (2008): <lb/> α = 0.645 ρ  red  + 0.382 ρ  NIR  . <lb/> (20) <lb/>The NDVI was also calculated from bands 3 and 4 of <lb/>FORMOSAT-2. <lb/>A remotely sensed LAI was computed from NDVI using a <lb/>single relationship (Clevers, 1989) for the whole study area <lb/>(Eq. 21): <lb/>LAI = − <lb/> 1 <lb/> k <lb/> ln <lb/> 񮽙 NDVI  ∞ − NDVI <lb/>NDVI  ∞ − NDVI soil <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (21) <lb/>This relationship between LAI and NDVI was calibrated us-<lb/>ing values of hemispherical LAI retrieved for all 23 fields <lb/>during the growing season with a minimal RMSD crite-<lb/>rion (Fieuzal et al., 2011). The calibrated extinction fac-<lb/>tor k is 1.13 and the asymptotical values of NDVI are <lb/>NDVI  ∞  = 0.97 and NDVI soil = 0.05. NDVI  ∞  and NDVI soil <lb/> are the NDVI values for a fully developed canopy and a <lb/>bare soil respectively. We found that a single relationship was <lb/>valid for all crops with a satisfying accuracy. <lb/> Table 3. Performance statistics of the models for the four compo-<lb/>nents of the energy balance (in W m  −2  ). <lb/>RMSD <lb/>CV <lb/>Bias <lb/>(RMSD) <lb/> R  n <lb/> TSEB/SEBS/S-SEBI <lb/>42.5 <lb/>7.1 <lb/> −1.6 <lb/> ICARE <lb/>69.0 <lb/>11.4 <lb/>3.16 <lb/> G <lb/> TSEB <lb/>60.4 <lb/>55.0 <lb/> −9.1 <lb/> SEBS/S-SEBI <lb/>57.4 <lb/>52.2 <lb/> −7.8 <lb/> ICARE <lb/>96.1 <lb/>87.8 <lb/>37.4 <lb/> H <lb/> TSEB <lb/>131.4 <lb/>62.2 −77.7 <lb/> SEBS <lb/>136.4 <lb/>64.6 −41.1 <lb/> S-SEBI <lb/>133.6 <lb/>63.2 −20.1 <lb/> ICARE <lb/>99.3 <lb/>49.1 <lb/>25.8 <lb/> λE <lb/> TSEB <lb/>122.1 <lb/>43.0 <lb/>82.4 <lb/>SEBS <lb/>130.6 <lb/>46.0 <lb/>40.0 <lb/>S-SEBI <lb/>116.5 <lb/>41.0 <lb/>28.8 <lb/>ICARE <lb/>130.9 <lb/>42.2 −72.1 <lb/> Finally, vegetation height was interpolated spatially and <lb/>temporally from discontinuous measurements based on <lb/>NDVI time series to provide input data for the SEB models. <lb/> 3 Results <lb/> First, the biophysical variables (surface temperature, albedo) <lb/>extracted from the ASTER and FORMOSAT2 images (re-<lb/>spectively) at each station are compared to the available mea-<lb/>surements at the seven locations. Single-pixel values were se-<lb/>lected since land use and most conditions (vegetation height <lb/>etc) are fairly homogeneous within each field and EC stations <lb/>are located at the center of those fields. Then, the available <lb/>instantaneous energy components (net radiation and soil heat <lb/>flux) and the turbulent fluxes at the time of the satellite over-<lb/>pass are compared to station values, with a special insight <lb/>on water stress. The statistical results for the four models are <lb/>summarized in Table 3. Finally, the patterns deduced from <lb/>the models for the entire 4 km × 4 km square are analyzed <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1176 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			Fig. 4. ASTER (left panel) and ICARE (right panel) versus in situ <lb/>radiometric surface temperature at each station at ASTER overpass <lb/>dates. Color code: red: LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: <lb/>0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> by comparison with available information on moisture lev-<lb/>els, vegetation type, etc. <lb/> 3.1 Analysis of remotely sensed input data <lb/> Measurements of albedo were made on three sites ((1), (3) <lb/>and (7), see Table 2 for dates) by CNR1 sensors. Compari-<lb/>son of FORMOSAT-2 against in situ albedo values shows a <lb/>mean bias of around 4.4 % and a coefficient of variation of <lb/>the RMSD, noted CV(RMSD) (ratio of the root mean square <lb/>difference and the average value) of 10 %. Those results are <lb/>quite acceptable with respect to previous studies (Bsaibes et <lb/>al., 2009; Courault et al., 2008; Jacob and Olioso, 2005), <lb/>which document CV(RMSD) values between 3 and 15 %. <lb/>Extraction of ASTER and ICARE surface temperature val-<lb/>ues at each EC station&apos;s pixel are shown in Fig. 4. We com-<lb/>pared our ground data to ASTER values of temperature at <lb/>the coordinates of the EC stations (Fig. 1). Brightness sur-<lb/>face temperature of the Apogee sensors was corrected for <lb/>emissivity and reflected atmospheric radiation using a classi-<lb/>cal emissivity–NDVI relationship (Van de Griend and Owe, <lb/>1993). Dates and stations at which surface temperature is <lb/>available are displayed in Table 2. The absolute error on tem-<lb/>perature is around 3.5K and clearly exceeds the values re-<lb/>ported in the literature, but this can be explained by the dif-<lb/>ference between the footprint of the instruments (less than <lb/>1 m of diameter) and the pixel size (100 × 100 m) as well as <lb/>the representativeness of the surface temperature when the <lb/>surface is heterogeneous. Moreover, large temperature val-<lb/>ues are encountered in this semi-arid region. A mean bias <lb/>around 0.9  •  C appeared in the estimation of T  0 . Despite those <lb/>results, the mean bias was different for each station (from <lb/> −0.2 to 3.9  •  C), thus no global correction was applied to <lb/>AST08. ICARE proves to be less accurate with a RMSD of <lb/>5.4  •  C and a mean bias of 1.8  •  C. ASTER seems to be less ac-<lb/>curate for intermediate LAIs (between 0.8 and 1.2) where it <lb/>seems to overestimate the surface temperature. This error can <lb/>be attributed to the larger representative area of ASTER pix-<lb/>els than the Apogee footprint: ASTER can &quot; see &quot; more bare <lb/> Fig. 5. Computed versus measured net radiation for the SEBS, <lb/>TSEB and S-SEBI (left panel) and ICARE (right panel). Color code: <lb/>red: LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; <lb/>navy-blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> soil (which is hotter than the canopy) than the in situ instru-<lb/>ment. Larger errors for ICARE radiometric temperatures can <lb/>be interpreted as a consequence of model error in the en-<lb/>ergy balance resolution. The radiative surface temperature in <lb/>ICARE is determined as a linear combination of the aerody-<lb/>namic canopy and soil temperatures (Model RTM-TIR0 of <lb/>Merlin and Chehbouni, 2014), which are all computed from <lb/>the resolution of the energy budget at each source (soil and <lb/>canopy). <lb/> 3.2 Surface energy balance components <lb/> Scatter plots of modeled (SEB and ICARE) versus observed <lb/>(measured) net radiation are displayed in Fig. 5. The estima-<lb/>tion of the available energy by the three SEB models gives <lb/>results often encountered in the literature with a RMSD of <lb/>around 42 W m  −2  (&lt; 10 % of the mean value) for the com-<lb/>puted R  n and of 57 W m  −2  for G. Almost no bias is observed <lb/>in net radiation. <lb/>Net radiation is better retrieved by the SEB models than <lb/>ICARE. ICARE net radiation flux shows a coefficient of vari-<lb/>ation of the RSMD CV(RMSD) of 11 %, which, while still <lb/>being a reasonable error, can be explained by the differences <lb/>between the surface temperature and albedo used by the var-<lb/>ious algorithms. Indeed, in the SVAT model, albedo is com-<lb/>puted using soil and dry/green vegetation albedos (respec-<lb/>tively set at 0.15, 0.35 and 0.22 in our case, which correspond <lb/>to rough estimates observed during the experiment). The <lb/>ICARE albedo was not calibrated, thus it was not expected <lb/>to obtain optimal results for each crop (∼ 20 % CV(RMSD) <lb/>on albedo for wheat and chickpea crops, ∼ 55 % for beans). <lb/>On the contrary, the formula used to calculate the broadband <lb/>albedo from FORMOSAT-2 bands has been calibrated on a <lb/>large area with a substantial variety of crops (Courault et <lb/>al., 2008). It gets a CV(RMSD) lower than 10 % for wheat <lb/>and beans and of around 17 % for chickpea, with a global <lb/>CV(RMSD) of 9.6 % (against 35.7 % for ICARE). This gap <lb/>can be explained by the fact that we did not use remotely <lb/>

			<note place="footnote"> Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/> www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1177 <lb/></page>

			Fig. 6. Computed versus measured soil heat flux for SEB mod-<lb/>els (left panel) and ICARE (right panel). The only point dif-<lb/>fering between TSEB and the other SEB methods has been re-<lb/>ported as a white-faced triangle, the Bastiaanssen (2000) esti-<lb/>mation being reported as a red-faced triangle. Color code: red: <lb/>LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-<lb/>blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> sensed albedo data to calibrate the albedo parameterization <lb/>of ICARE. <lb/>The results of the calculation of the soil heat flux for each <lb/>model has been displayed in Fig. 6. Because of the structure <lb/>of the TSEB algorithm, which computes G as the residual of <lb/>the soil energy balance when the surface is totally stressed, <lb/>estimation of G by TSEB differs from SEBS and S-SEBI <lb/>only by one point. Thus, we did not plot results for TSEB <lb/>on a separate graph and just reported that point on the left <lb/>plot in Fig. 6 as a white triangle. For the SEB methods, an <lb/>effect of saturation is clearly noticeable for bare soils and <lb/>quasi-bare soils (red dots). This means that not only the max-<lb/>imum ratio of G over R  n but also the dynamic range for low <lb/>LAI values should be larger than what is suggested by Basti-<lb/>aanssen et al. (2000). The red dots group (group 1 in Fig. 6) <lb/>shows an overestimation of the soil heat flux by the selected <lb/>model. It corresponds to the end of the senescence period and <lb/>the harvesting time of wheat. At that time, vegetation is still <lb/>dense and standing, but dry. Since the formulation is based <lb/>on NDVI, and therefore represents the amount of shading <lb/>due to green vegetation only, shading is largely underesti-<lb/>mated. A series of green and yellow dots (intermediate and <lb/>low LAIs, group 2 in Fig. 6) corresponding to the same sta-<lb/>tion (beans) are constantly overestimated with a bias around <lb/>50 W m  −2  . No particular overestimation of net radiation or <lb/>surface temperature was observed at this location. We can <lb/>assume that this bias comes in a large extent from the mea-<lb/>surements. However, the models largely underestimate the <lb/>flux for high values of measured G. The third group of out-<lb/>liers (Fig. 6) comes from the chickpea station. Even if the <lb/>four points at the far right of the figure correspond to dates <lb/>where R  n was greatly underestimated (∼ 100 W m  −2  at each <lb/>date), it sums up with an underestimation of the 񮽙 = G/R  n <lb/> factor by the models. At the station, 񮽙 values estimated from <lb/>observations ranged between 0.3 and 0.45 whereas the model <lb/>computes values between 0.2 and 0.3. Although all in situ <lb/> Fig. 7. Simulated versus measured sensible heat flux H for <lb/>every station at ASTER overpass dates. Color code: red: <lb/>LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-<lb/>blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> values seem high for the study area (other stations give 񮽙 val-<lb/>ues of around 0.3 for bare soil), the maximum of this factor <lb/>encountered in the literature can be as high as 0.35 (Kustas <lb/>and Daughtry, 1990; Monteith, 1973; Norman et al., 1995). <lb/>In our case, the formulation of 񮽙cannot reach those values, <lb/>and rarely exceeds 0.3. <lb/>Greater scattering is observed in ICARE with a larger <lb/>RMSD (96 versus 57 W m  −2  for the other models). Since the <lb/>soil heat flux is determined by ICARE as the residual of the <lb/>energy budget at the soil interface, those errors are mainly <lb/>due to the absorption by G of the various errors made during <lb/>the estimation of both net radiation and turbulent fluxes. <lb/>Scatter plots of simulated versus measured turbulent fluxes <lb/>are presented in Figs. 7 and 8 for H and λE, respectively. <lb/>TSEB has a systematic tendency to underestimate H (and <lb/>thus overestimate λE) with a strong bias of 82 W m  −2  . In <lb/>Fig. 7, strong underestimation of H at low LAIs can be ob-<lb/>served. Underestimation of H for intermediate LAI values <lb/>can be due to errors in the ASTER temperature. At high <lb/>LAIs, we observe in most cases an overestimation of λE(see <lb/> Fig. 8) certainly related to an overestimation of the canopy <lb/>transpiration (Eq. 12), since TSEB&apos;s initial assumption is that <lb/>the vegetation always transpires at the potential rate. <lb/>In terms of absolute error, SEBS shows a similar per-<lb/>formance (Table 3). There is a great underestimation of H <lb/> for quasi-bare soils. Since the remotely sensed temperature <lb/>is rarely underestimated, and given the fact that vegetation <lb/>height is well constrained by in situ measurements, H un-<lb/>derestimation is likely to be due to an overestimation of the <lb/>excess resistance k B  −1  at low LAIs. This is in agreement <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1178 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			Fig. 8. Simulated versus measured latent heat flux λE for <lb/>every station at ASTER overpass dates. Color code: red: <lb/>LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-<lb/>blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> with the current findings published in the literature (Boulet <lb/>et al., 2012; Gokmen et al., 2012). The few overestimations <lb/>of H observed for moderate LAIs (between 0.4 and 1) come <lb/>from an underestimation of the aerodynamic resistance, in <lb/>some cases combined with an overestimation of the surface <lb/>temperature by a few degrees. <lb/>S-SEBI showed the best performance (among the SEB <lb/>models) in the computation of λE with RMSD of <lb/>116 W m  −2  . Opposite mean biases of −20 and 29 W m  −2 <lb/> have been observed on H and λE, respectively. A large un-<lb/>derestimation of H occurs during senescence for the wheat <lb/>plots. The vegetation is stressed but still dense and surface <lb/>temperature and albedo are not as high as for bare-soil pix-<lb/>els. Senescence can be observed on the upper-right scatter <lb/>plot of Fig. 2. Senescent wheat corresponds to yellow points <lb/>with albedos between 0.2 and 0.3 and temperatures between <lb/>35 and 45  •  C. They are located in the middle of the scatter <lb/>plot because of the low surface temperatures induced by tur-<lb/>bulent heat exchanges still going on above the canopy. <lb/>ICARE performs better than the other three models in the <lb/>computation of H but falls behind in the estimation of λE <lb/> with a RMSD of respectively 99 and 130 W m  −2  . Contrary to <lb/>SEB models, it tends to underestimate λE and overestimate <lb/> H with biases of respectively −72 and +26 W m  −2  . <lb/> 3.3 Water stress <lb/> For hydrological applications, it is important to test not <lb/>only the performance in estimating ETR (evapotranspira-<lb/>tion) when water is not limiting (potential evapotranspi-<lb/>ration being relatively easy to compute from NDVI and <lb/> Fig. 9. Scatter plots of water stress at each station for TSEB, <lb/>SEBS, S-SEBI, VIT method and ICARE. Values calculated <lb/>for ASTER overpass dates. Color code: red: LAI &lt; 0.4; <lb/>yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-blue: <lb/>1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> meteorological information) but during periods of water <lb/>shortage as well. This is why we concentrate in this section <lb/>on the assessment of the relative water stress of the surface. <lb/>Of course, for agronomical applications, it is more interesting <lb/>to get information about the water status of the plant. How-<lb/>ever, SEB models, TSEB excepted, only estimate evapotran-<lb/>spiration rates for the surface as a whole. Even in TSEB, the <lb/>simulated vegetation component of the latent heat flux does <lb/>not always represent transpiration. Indeed, when the vegeta-<lb/>tion is partially stressed, the soil evaporation term is set to <lb/>zero and the transpiration term represents the evapotranspi-<lb/>ration of the whole surface, excluding the case where the soil <lb/>still evaporates at a very low rate. We computed a surface <lb/>water stress at each measurement point for each date where <lb/>ASTER data were available. Results are shown in Fig. 9. The <lb/>definition of surface water stress reported here is the same as <lb/>the one introduced as WDI for the VIT method (Eq. 17): <lb/>water_stress = 1 − <lb/> λE <lb/>λE  max <lb/> . <lb/> (22) <lb/>In Eq. (22), λE  max is the maximum (potential) latent heat <lb/>flux achievable for one particular pixel. Each SEB method <lb/>uses its own potential conditions in order to compute actual <lb/>evapotranspiration (Penman–Monteith in SEBS, Priestley– <lb/>Taylor in TSEB and the available energy in S-SEBI). In or-<lb/>der to assess the capacity of each model to retrieve water <lb/>stress (which can be later on used as a proxy for total root <lb/>zone soil moisture, cf. Hain et al., 2009), it appears only <lb/>natural to consider water stress as an output of the models <lb/>and to use their own version of potential conditions. In or-<lb/>der to compute an in situ water stress, we used a two-source <lb/>potential evapotranspiration model, which was the clos-<lb/>est estimate amongst common models (Penman–Monteith, <lb/>Priestley–Taylor), when compared to λE measurements at <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/> www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1179 <lb/></page>

			Fig. 10. Stress frequency histograms and maps for the whole area on 10 March. <lb/> each EC station for a short period following irrigation (not <lb/>shown). Since potential evapotranspiration and average sur-<lb/>face stress were not routine outputs of ICARE, we chose to <lb/>run the SVAT model with a low continuous irrigation in order <lb/>to obtain its own λE  pot . <lb/>In terms of water stress, ICARE would be expected to <lb/>show good results, since it is the only model that is not forced <lb/>with surface temperature (which is indirectly related to soil <lb/>moisture) but directly with a time series of rain and irriga-<lb/>tion, which control soil moisture and therefore stress levels. <lb/>However, a significant overestimation of water stress is ob-<lb/>servable at medium and high LAIs. This seems to be due <lb/>to the water balance module (force–restore), which tends to <lb/>quickly dry the upper soil layer with bursts of λE  s on days <lb/>immediately following irrigation. <lb/>TSEB globally underestimates stress, which is in agree-<lb/>ment with the general overestimation of λE seen in Fig. 8, <lb/>but it has a lower scattering and number of outliers than the <lb/>other three SEB models. Additionally, it performs quite well <lb/>for low stressed vegetation. <lb/>SEBS has a strong tendency to underestimate stress for <lb/>low LAI, which is related to the overestimation of the surface <lb/>aerodynamic resistance for bare soil discussed in Sect. 3.2. A <lb/>group of points with large water stress values when stress is <lb/>expected to be absent is, as explained in Sect. 3.2, mostly a <lb/>consequence of an underestimation of the k B  −1  factor, and <lb/>thus of the surface aerodynamic resistance. <lb/>The contextual models, as expected, dispatch all stress lev-<lb/>els between extremes and produce a large spread of stress <lb/>levels. Around observed medium stress values (0.5), S-SEBI <lb/>and VIT simulate lower than observed stress values (red <lb/>dots, LAI &lt; 0.4). This is directly due to the observed sur-<lb/>face temperatures at those locations, which are not high <lb/>enough for the T (α) relation to detect a significant stress. <lb/>The corresponding points are in the lower part of the scat-<lb/>ter plot so S-SEBI simulates evaporative fractions over 0.5 <lb/>when measured values lie around 0.3 or 0.4. Two yellow <lb/>points with intermediate LAIs (0.4–0.8) present overesti-<lb/>mated stress values. This is due, for the one in the upper part <lb/>of the diagram (chickpea, on 10 March), to an overestimation <lb/>of the ASTER temperature of around 7  •  C (one must keep <lb/>in mind that the ASTER pixel is bigger than the EC instru-<lb/>ment footprint and includes more bare soil with higher tem-<lb/>peratures). The one in the lower part of the diagram (beans, <lb/>27 April) seems to be due to a high surface temperature of <lb/>the whole bean field (around 40  •  C), which is consistent with <lb/>the station measurement, while the crop is still growing and <lb/>well irrigated. Figure 10 shows an example of how contextual <lb/>methods are dependent on the surface properties of the stud-<lb/>ied area. In the case of the VIT method, pixels with stressed <lb/>and well developed vegetation (i.e., isolated pixels with high <lb/>NDVI and high surface temperature values) seem to be lack-<lb/>ing in the area, which is consistent with the agricultural prac-<lb/>tices: the whole zone being irrigated, stress is normally ab-<lb/>sent in the growing period. The boundaries drawn from the <lb/>scatter of points shown in Fig. 2 are therefore misinterpreted <lb/>as stressed for various pixels with high NDVI values located <lb/>near the top-right edge of the trapezoid, while those points <lb/>correspond to unstressed crops. However, stress is underes-<lb/>timated for some pixels classified as bare soils, which cor-<lb/>responds to pixels with low NDVI and a lower temperature <lb/>than the observed maximum. If some straw is left on the <lb/>ground after harvesting or if the bare-soil properties are dif-<lb/>ferent (e.g., higher albedo), evaporation is reduced. But since <lb/>the temperature is in the lower range, the pixel is not located <lb/>close enough to the bottom-right corner of the trapezoid to <lb/>detect a strong reduction in evaporation. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1180 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			Table 4. Mean values of turbulent flux and water stress on the whole area at two dates of ASTER overpass. <lb/>10 March <lb/>6 May <lb/>TSEB <lb/>SEBS S-SEBI VIT <lb/>TSEB <lb/>SEBS S-SEBI VIT <lb/> H  mean (W m  −2  ) <lb/>101.31 154.21 <lb/>173.00 <lb/>– <lb/>230.13 289.66 <lb/>209.39 <lb/>– <lb/> λE  mean (W m  −2  ) 425.57 372.67 <lb/>353.88 <lb/>– <lb/>272.70 207.76 <lb/>288.02 <lb/>– <lb/>Water stress <lb/>0.13 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>0.35 0.38 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.56 <lb/>0.44 0.40 <lb/> 3.4 Spatial variability <lb/> In this section we move from the local to the spatial stand-<lb/>point. Model intercomparison at a local scale allows us to as-<lb/>sess their performance and draw specific behaviors but not <lb/>to assess how they represent the spatial variability at the <lb/>perimeter scale. In Fig. 11, we plotted frequency histograms <lb/>for turbulent fluxes and remote sensing data (albedo, NDVI, <lb/>surface temperature) on 10 March for the whole area. At this <lb/>time of the year, most crops are well developed and green. On <lb/>the histograms, TSEB and SEBS have a similar response: low <lb/> H and high λE peaking around the potential rate. However, <lb/>as expected for a contextual model, S-SEBI shows a large <lb/>spread of values, which in this case does not seem to be rep-<lb/>resentative of the real situation. As seen before, TSEB tends <lb/>to simulate large values of latent heat flux for green land-<lb/>scapes. This is due to the starting hypothesis of the algorithm, <lb/>which states that vegetation is transpiring at the potential rate <lb/>given by the Priestley–Taylor formulation. This result is ob-<lb/>served as well in Table 4, where arithmetical means of turbu-<lb/>lent flux and water stress over the whole area are displayed. <lb/>TSEB λE  mean is higher than the other two (425 W m  −2  ), the <lb/>smallest being S-SEBI with a λE  mean of 354 W m  −2  . The re-<lb/>sults in terms of stress are shown in Fig. 10. Both contex-<lb/>tual models compute a larger amount of stressed areas than <lb/>the other models. This is expected since they distribute stress <lb/>values on the whole 0–1 interval. It is particularly true for <lb/>the beans and chili pepper fields (heavily stressed fields in <lb/>the northeastern 2 km × 2 km square, see Fig. 3). The sur-<lb/>face temperature of those fields being high, the contextual <lb/>models interpret them as stressed, whereas both crops are in <lb/>an early growing stage and thus well irrigated. The reason <lb/>of those high temperatures can be related to a large surface <lb/>aerodynamic resistance (low LAIs and crop height) and to <lb/>the effect of rows (large surfaces of bare soil are observed <lb/>between crop rows by ASTER because the plant has yet to <lb/>develop itself horizontally) rather than low water availability <lb/>for plants. Single-pixel models compute surface water stress <lb/>using theoretical potential rates taking into account LAI and <lb/>thus tend to minimize this problem. This also shows the lim-<lb/>itations of the use of a surface water stress to assess informa-<lb/>tion about plant stress. Both models have mean water stress <lb/>values of around 0.35 whereas single-pixel models compute <lb/>low mean stress values (0.11 for SEBS, 0.13 for TSEB). Con-<lb/>trarily to TSEB, SEBS computes very high stress values (null <lb/> Fig. 11. Frequency histograms of simulated turbulent-calculated <lb/>fluxes and remote sensing parameters on 10 March. On the T  0 his-<lb/>togram, the value of air temperature T  a is indicated as a green line. <lb/> evapotranspiration) for two orchard fields in the southeastern <lb/>2 km × 2 km part of the research area. Those sparse canopies <lb/>have large amounts of intercropping bare soils with large <lb/>temperatures. Both fields are irrigated, which means that the <lb/>average surface stress is sensitive to fraction cover. For this <lb/>land use type, one can question the validity of the de facto <lb/>parameterizations of k B  −1  and fraction cover from mean <lb/>NDVI values, which have been built for herbaceous vegeta-<lb/>tion. TSEB seems to better accommodate the contrasted wa-<lb/>ter status of those fields with its two-source energy balance. <lb/>In Fig. 10, as well, SEBS shows medium peaks of stress <lb/>at the edge of many fields. Similar patterns are observed on <lb/>NDVI (not shown) and thus LAI, and correspond to roads be-<lb/>tween the fields lowering the average NDVI of the surround-<lb/>ing pixels. Similar but more subtle edge effects are observed <lb/>on VIT stress maps. Although it was expected that the VIT <lb/>method would be the most sensitive to variations of NDVI, <lb/>

			<note place="footnote"> Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/> www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1181 <lb/></page>

			Fig. 12. Stress frequency histograms and maps for the whole area on 6 May. <lb/> it seems that the k B  −1  parameterization in SEBS induces a <lb/>high sensitivity of the model to vegetation cover. <lb/>On 6 May both well watered and stressed vegetation were <lb/>present in the area. As expected, in heterogeneous condi-<lb/>tions, contextual models react consistently to variations of <lb/>the surface water status (see Fig. 12). TSEB, S-SEBI and <lb/>VIT show very similar results in terms of patterns and stress <lb/>distribution as well as mean stress value. Again, SEBS distin-<lb/>guishes itself from the others with a higher mean stress value <lb/>(see Table 4) and a very different distribution of stress values <lb/>over the area. Its difficulty to accommodate the hot bare-soil <lb/>fractions is discussed below. <lb/> 4 Discussion <lb/> Considering that we are looking for a possible assimilation of <lb/>thermal data into SVAT or, more largely, hydrological mod-<lb/>els, SEB models – which provide information on the water <lb/>status of the surface combining TIR, visible/NIR and mete-<lb/>orological data – seem like a decent lead. Understanding of <lb/>their respective errors and robustness depending on surface <lb/>and climatic conditions of the area is crucial. <lb/> 4.1 Performance intercomparison <lb/> Models have shown fairly high errors in the computation of <lb/>turbulent fluxes (RMSD over 100 W m  −2  for the SEB meth-<lb/>ods), but it remains in the upper limit of what has already <lb/>been published (see Table 1). Although part of those errors <lb/>can be attributed to remote sensing uncertainties, most com-<lb/>ponents of the energy budget are often large in semi-arid <lb/>lands at low latitudes. In addition, fluxes are measured and <lb/>simulated near midday, close to the peak in incoming so-<lb/>lar radiation, and instantaneous energy flux values are also <lb/>large. It is therefore not surprising that RMSD values are in <lb/>the upper range of the literature. Moreover, the Yaqui exper-<lb/>iment was a &quot; one shot &quot; program carried out over a single <lb/>cereal growing season and thus could not benefit from the <lb/>experience in data understanding and correction that long-<lb/>term projects like FLUXNET (http://fluxnet.ornl.gov/) can <lb/>provide. Flux data quality is therefore also questionable. <lb/>In addition to the general performance of the models over <lb/>the whole season, we had a closer look at their performance <lb/>over different crop types and at different dates. ICARE per-<lb/>formed better than the other methods over wheat and chick-<lb/>pea fields, showing RMSD on turbulent fluxes lower by 20– <lb/>70 W m  −2  than the others. It could be expected for wheat <lb/>fields since the calibration of the soil resistance to evapora-<lb/>tion and minimum stomatal resistance has been made over <lb/>those crops. In addition, a fairly strong bias is present on <lb/>the net radiation calculated by the three SEB methods, which <lb/>tends to worsen their performance. However, over potatoes, <lb/>sorghum, broccoli and beans, the three SEB models perform <lb/>better, particularly over sorghum where the three models <lb/>present RMSD of around 70–90 W m  −2  . Despite the higher <lb/>global performance of ICARE than the energy balance mod-<lb/>els, it seems that SEB models can give better results for some <lb/>specific vegetation types. This can be partly due to their <lb/>relative simplicity compared to ICARE, which needs a fair <lb/>amount of surface parameters difficult to assess precisely. It <lb/>could be expected that the SEB methods that use remotely <lb/>observed surface temperature and albedo would be more con-<lb/>sistent than the more complex SVAT model that internally <lb/>calculates those parameters from user-defined properties of <lb/>the soil and vegetation. <lb/>Another observation made during this experiment is that <lb/>the relative error in surface temperature computation by <lb/>ICARE seems to compensate the error made for the turbulent <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1182 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			fluxes. Indeed, the situation where ICARE is not accurate in <lb/>surface temperature but has a very acceptable error in H and <lb/> λE is not uncommon and it questions the relevance of as-<lb/>similation of thermal data alone in SVAT models in order <lb/>to improve its performance in turbulent flux determination. <lb/>For instance, on 6 May, there is a 7  •  C difference between <lb/>the simulated and the observed surface temperatures for the <lb/>wheat (1) station, while errors in turbulent heat flux are lower <lb/>than 50 W m  −2  . On 6 March, there is also a 7  •  C tempera-<lb/>ture difference for the chickpea flux station while the sensible <lb/>heat is correct (corresponding error is 10 W m  −2  ) and the la-<lb/>tent heat is underestimated by more than 70 W m  −2  . In those <lb/>cases, correcting the model estimations based on thermal in-<lb/>formation may not be sufficient to correctly force ICARE <lb/>into the right partition between the various components of <lb/>the energy balance. <lb/> 4.2 Models&apos; structures and improvements <lb/> One big issue of the SEB models in their original formulation <lb/>is that they have difficulties to account for the senescence <lb/>phenomenon. For contextual methods, senescent vegetation <lb/>has a lower temperature than stressed green vegetation (for <lb/>VIT), due to a higher reflection of the incoming solar energy, <lb/>and than bare, sandy soil (for S-SEBI), due to a higher crop <lb/>height that enhances turbulent heat exchange at the surface. <lb/>Since senescent vegetation pixels do not appear in extreme <lb/>temperature conditions, those models do not detect very large <lb/>stress values. RMSD on senescent pixels was found to be <lb/>40 W m  −2  higher than for green ones. <lb/>SEBS tends to overestimate evapotranspiration for low <lb/>LAIs. This seems to be mostly due to the bare-soil compo-<lb/>nent of the k B  −1  factor that generates very high surface aero-<lb/>dynamic resistances and thus very low H values. RMSDs <lb/>of 170 and 240 W m  −2  are observed on latent and sensible <lb/>heat fluxes (respectively) for pixels with LAI lower than 0.2. <lb/>Solutions to this problem have been proposed. They consist <lb/>in either using another empirical factor in order to compute <lb/>turbulent fluxes (Boulet et al., 2012), including information <lb/>about soil moisture in the k B  −1  (Gokmen et al., 2012) or <lb/>lowering the soil component of the k B  −1  (Chen et al., 2013). <lb/>Implementation of the Boulet et al. (2012) formulation leads <lb/>to performance similar to the original SEBS but tends to <lb/>overcorrect errors on λE with a lower bias of −70 W m  −2 <lb/> (against +40 W m  −2  for Su, 2002). Overestimations of H <lb/> at intermediate LAIs (0.4 &lt; LAI &lt; 1) seems to confirm the <lb/>limitations of one-source methods and the advantage of us-<lb/>ing two-source approaches. Even if the new formulation of <lb/>the k B  −1  factor introduced by Su (2002) was meant to add <lb/>information about soil–plant interactions, the corresponding <lb/>term in Eq. (8) seems to be underestimated. The generated <lb/>error is lower than for bare soil but still needs to be noted, <lb/>with a RMSD of around 130 W m  −2  on H against 83 W m  −2 <lb/> for pixels with LAI larger than 1. <lb/>A major issue was encountered in TSEB during the senes-<lb/>cence period in the partitioning of net radiation between soil <lb/>and vegetation. The model has various new versions that <lb/>modify the partitioning of net radiation between the soil and <lb/>the vegetation for row crops, for instance, but we kept the <lb/>original formulation by Norman et al. (1995). RMSD was <lb/>found higher for senescent pixels than for bare soil and green <lb/>ones (144, 106 and 109 W m  −2  , respectively). Indeed, the <lb/>LAI used in this study is computed from NDVI and is there-<lb/>fore a green LAI. However, during senescence, part of the <lb/>canopy becomes yellow when drying. For crops like wheat, <lb/>vegetation is fully yellow before harvesting. Our version of <lb/>TSEB assimilates this part of vegetation as bare soil since it <lb/>is not taken into account in the green LAI. It results in a great <lb/>overestimation of the soil component of the net radiation for <lb/>TSEB. Since the soil heat flux is bounded by a maximum <lb/>fraction of R  n,s and the soil sensible heat flux is well con-<lb/>strained by the soil temperature mostly (which is in turn well <lb/>defined by T  0 and T  c ), the residual soil latent heat flux is the <lb/>most sensitive to big variations in R  n,s . It translates into a <lb/>large overestimation of λE  s , and by consequence of λE. In <lb/>order to integrate information about total and dry LAI into <lb/>TSEB, we made the coarse assumption that during the senes-<lb/>cence period, and until the harvesting date, the global LAI <lb/>was constant and equal to its maximum value LAI max . Global <lb/>LAI extracted from the FORMOSAT-2 time series was used <lb/>to compute the fraction cover during senescence and thus to <lb/>better partition R  n . We then calculated the green fraction f  g <lb/> according to Norman et al. (1995) with the new definition of <lb/>global LAI: <lb/> f  g  = <lb/> LAI green <lb/> LAI global <lb/> = <lb/> LAI green <lb/> LAI max <lb/> . <lb/> (23) <lb/>This approximation is not very accurate since the leaf&apos;s sur-<lb/>face decreases while drying, leading to a gradual decrease of <lb/>global LAI over the senescence period. However it is suffi-<lb/>cient to greatly improve the repartition of net radiation and <lb/>thus the estimation of λE and water stress. Results on λE <lb/> and net radiation with this new formulation of LAI are com-<lb/>pared to the initial version of the model in Fig. 13. Large <lb/>variations are observed between the two formulations on <lb/>soil and canopy net radiation, with differences as large as <lb/>500 W m  −2  . This influences greatly the energy balance at the <lb/>soil–atmosphere interface and produces smaller R  n,s values. <lb/>As a result, RMSD on λE is reduced by 10 W m  −2  and the <lb/>bias is lowered to 19 W m  −2  (against 82 W m  −2  with the ini-<lb/>tial formulation). The computation of water stress is also im-<lb/>proved with a very low positive bias of 0.03 against −0.1 <lb/> in the previous version (not shown). One must also stress <lb/>that since we use global LAI in the computation of surface <lb/>aerodynamic resistances, it tends to lower both r  a and r  s by <lb/>adding more roughness to the surface and thus to favor sensi-<lb/>ble heat transfer at the soil interface over λE  s . Thus, integrat-<lb/>ing information about dry vegetation could greatly improve <lb/>the performance of TSEB in senescent cases when vegetation <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/> >www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1183 <lb/></page>

			Fig. 13. Comparison of TSEB and observed λE fluxes with f  g = 1 <lb/>(top left panel) and with f  g taking into account the drying of leaves <lb/>(top, right), and corresponding values of the net radiation compo-<lb/>nents for the vegetation (R n,c , bottom left panel) and the soil (R  n,s  , <lb/>bottom right panel) with f  g = 1 (x axis) and with f  g taking into ac-<lb/>count the drying of leaves (y axis), respectively. Color code: red: <lb/>LAI &lt; 0.4; yellow: 0.4 ≤ LAI &lt; 0.8; green: 0.8 ≤ LAI &lt; 1.2; navy-<lb/>blue: 1.2 ≤ LAI &lt; 2.0; black: LAI ≥ 2.0. <lb/> height is reconstructed using LAI or NDVI time series. In our <lb/>case, many cloud-free FORMOSAT-2 images were available, <lb/>allowing us to follow each phenological stage of the vegeta-<lb/>tion and thus estimate the maximum LAI precisely. How-<lb/>ever, even if we hope that high-resolution images acquired <lb/>frequently enough will be easier to afford in the near future, <lb/>such clear-sky conditions over the whole growth season seem <lb/>almost impossible to find in temperate or tropical regions and <lb/>it would make the calibration of f  g much more delicate. <lb/>Comparing behaviors of TSEB and ICARE is also inter-<lb/>esting since they are both dual-source models. They partition <lb/>radiative energy between soil and vegetation in fairly differ-<lb/>ent ways. In the original TSEB formulation, global net ra-<lb/>diation is distributed between soil and vegetation based on <lb/>fraction cover whereas ICARE computes two separate net <lb/>radiations from LAI, soil and vegetation albedo, and emis-<lb/>sivity, using a multireflection and transmission network, as <lb/>proposed by Shuttleworth and Wallace (1985). The original <lb/>TSEB method for net radiation can be criticized because it <lb/>bypasses the effects of the vegetation&apos;s transmissivity and <lb/>longwave radiation exchanges between soil and vegetation <lb/>(emission of radiation from one layer to another). In Tang et <lb/>al. (2011), a more physical way to calculate R  n is used, tak-<lb/>ing into account those two phenomena, and delivers better <lb/>performance than a MODIS-based R  n (RMSD = 24 versus <lb/>44 W m  −2  on a MODIS pixel). However, this method re-<lb/>quires estimates of vegetation and soil albedos, as well as <lb/>the vegetation transmission factor, which can be quite diffi-<lb/>cult if studying a very heterogeneous zone. The method used <lb/>in ICARE considers all radiation exchanges between the two <lb/>layers (vegetation and bare soil), including transmission and <lb/>multiple reflections, but it assumes that the vegetation cover <lb/>is homogeneous. It is not adapted to row crops (see Colaizzi <lb/>et al., 2012 for recent formulations of net radiation for row <lb/>crops). As long as FORMOSAT-2 images are available, the <lb/>method used in this paper seems to be the most accurate for <lb/>estimating R  n independently of the heterogeneity of the sur-<lb/>face or regional topographic features. Furthermore, the as-<lb/>similation of this net radiation into the ICARE SVAT model <lb/>could be studied in order to calibrate vegetation and soil ra-<lb/>diative properties. <lb/>In the partitioning of the soil and vegetation latent heat flux <lb/>components, the two methods have also very different behav-<lb/>iors. Underestimation of λE by ICARE during the growing <lb/>period is due to the quick drying of the first layer of soil, re-<lb/>sulting in very low λE  s . However, since ICARE takes into <lb/>account the dry part of the vegetation through green and <lb/>dry LAIs, it performs better during senescence, with realistic <lb/>low λE  c values, whereas TSEB maintains a potential rate for <lb/>the vegetation. As a consequence, canopy temperature sim-<lb/>ulated by TSEB is almost equal to the air temperature while <lb/>the soil temperature computed by the model rises towards <lb/>ASTER surface temperature values. On the contrary, ICARE <lb/>distributes both temperatures around the computed surface <lb/>temperature. Although the partition of radiation sounds more <lb/>realistic with TSEB (subject to some changes about dry LAI), <lb/>the soil–vegetation partition between turbulent fluxes seems <lb/>to make more sense for ICARE, mostly because of the strong <lb/>initial hypothesis on vegetation water status in TSEB. After <lb/>correction, TSEB seems to be the most accurate of all four <lb/>SEB models after reconstitution of total fluxes, but its soil– <lb/>canopy distribution of latent heat and estimates of component <lb/>temperatures remains questionable. <lb/> 4.3 Determination of distributed water stress <lb/> We focus here on the intercomparison of stress patterns sim-<lb/>ulated by all four SEB models. In order to remain as concise <lb/>as possible, we chose not to discuss model results on every <lb/>ASTER image but to focus on the dates that can represent <lb/>the most significant cases encountered in this study. Differ-<lb/>ences were particularly important for two dates that represent <lb/>contrasted vegetation cover and soil moisture patterns: one, <lb/>10 March, when the quasi-totality of the area is green and <lb/>irrigated (and thus the spatial variability of water availabil-<lb/>ity is relatively low) and the other, 6 May, when wheat has <lb/>been harvested and thus the major part of the area is under <lb/>water stress whereas many crops are still growing and irri-<lb/>gated (and thus the spatial variability of water availability <lb/>is fairly high). We decided to focus on these two dates. In <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1184 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>
			
			Table 5. Double-entry table of coefficient of determination R  2 <lb/> (lower-left part) and RMSD (upper-right part) between the SEB <lb/>models and their standard deviation σ on 10 March. <lb/>RMSD <lb/> σ <lb/> TSEB SEBS S-SEBI VIT <lb/> R  2 <lb/> TSEB <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.28 0.14 <lb/>SEBS <lb/>0.43 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.26 0.18 <lb/>S-SEBI <lb/>0.94 <lb/>0.46 <lb/>0.06 0.26 <lb/>VIT <lb/>0.91 <lb/>0.58 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.27 <lb/> Tables 5 and 6 coefficients of determination R  2 and RMSD <lb/>values of the simulated water stress by the different models <lb/>are displayed, as well as their standard deviation σ over the <lb/>whole area. As expected for contextual models, which dis-<lb/>tribute stress over the whole 0–1 interval, S-SEBI and VIT <lb/>show higher σ values than single-pixel models on 10 March. <lb/>The quasi-totality of crops are green and well developed and <lb/>stress should be almost absent of the scene. We enlarged the <lb/>target area (from 4 km × 4 km to the whole FORMOSAT-<lb/>2 image) hoping to encounter truly stressed pixels, but the <lb/>slight change in the resulting bounding relationships did not <lb/>modify this finding (not shown). This tends to confirm that <lb/>our sample zone is representative of the whole irrigation <lb/>perimeter. For that date, the missing extremes should be in-<lb/>ferred from theoretical boundaries and not derived from the <lb/>images alone. For a later date in spring (on 6 May when <lb/>wheat is mostly senescent), TSEB and contextual models <lb/>are in good agreement with each other, showing equivalent <lb/> σ values, and low RMSDs between models (a difference of <lb/>around 0.1 between TSEB and contextual models, 0.04 be-<lb/>tween S-SEBI and VIT). <lb/>TSEB, S-SEBI and VIT show a strong correlation with <lb/>each other on both dates but with a narrower interval of dis-<lb/>tribution than for contextual models, which can explain their <lb/>differences in terms of mean values and standard deviation. <lb/>In May, the correlation between TSEB and the contextual <lb/>models is a bit lower than in March but the pattern shown in <lb/>Figs. 10 and 12, as well as the mean value and standard devi-<lb/>ation, are very similar. It shows that in the case of contrasted <lb/>conditions, simpler contextual models reproduce quite faith-<lb/>fully the general behavior of a more complex model like <lb/>TSEB, which is already used in operational algorithms at <lb/>continental scales and thus whose performance is trusted. On <lb/>the contrary, SEBS seems to behave very differently from the <lb/>other three models during the whole season in terms of stress <lb/>distribution, with a low standard deviation in winter as well <lb/>as in spring. It has a very low correlation with the other three <lb/>models and the patterns and histograms displayed in Figs. 10 <lb/>and 12 are very distinct from the others. One possible expla-<lb/>nation could be that SEBS is more sensitive to vegetation <lb/>properties due to its use of the k B  −1  parameterization of <lb/>the roughness length for heat exchange in the aerodynamic <lb/> Table 6. Double-entry table of coefficient of determination R  2 <lb/> (lower-left part) and RMSD (upper-right part) between the SEB <lb/>models and their standard deviation σ on 6 May. <lb/>RMSD <lb/> σ <lb/> TSEB SEBS S-SEBI VIT <lb/> R  2 <lb/> TSEB <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.13 0.25 <lb/>SEBS <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>0.25 0.18 <lb/>S-SEBI <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.04 0.22 <lb/>VIT <lb/>0.78 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.23 <lb/> resistance. The resulting roughness is very sensitive to the <lb/>vegetation height, which is very difficult to retrieve spatially. <lb/>Thus a lot of approximations are made using a priori values <lb/>based on in situ qualitative knowledge in order to distribute <lb/>crop heights over the whole area. The contextual models do <lb/>not need this information and TSEB is strongly driven by <lb/>fraction cover and surface temperature in his architecture, <lb/>which enables it to by-pass some crop height determination <lb/>issues. <lb/> 5 Summary and conclusions <lb/> Performance and structure particularities of two contextual <lb/>and two single-pixel methods to retrieve energy fluxes at <lb/>the surface using thermal remote sensing data have been lo-<lb/>cally compared with in situ measurements and outputs of <lb/>a complete SVAT model (ICARE) during a whole cereal-<lb/>growth season. In terms of energy fluxes, TSEB, SEBS and <lb/>S-SEBI showed comparable results with RMSD on λE rang-<lb/>ing from 117 (S-SEBI) to 131 W m  −2  (SEBS). These re-<lb/>sults are in the same range as the uncalibrated ICARE SVAT <lb/>model forced with in situ data (RMSD = 131 W m  −2  on λE) <lb/> but with an opposite behavior in the repartition of turbulent <lb/>fluxes. ICARE tends to underestimate the evapotranspiration <lb/>whereas the SEB methods overestimate it. TSEB and ICARE <lb/>are the two models that estimate water stress with the best <lb/>accuracy. However, TSEB performs better at high LAIs (low <lb/>stress) and shows difficulties in detecting stress during senes-<lb/>cence, whereas ICARE has a strong tendency to overestimate <lb/>stress for green vegetation but is more accurate than TSEB at <lb/>low LAIs. SEBS performs poorly for senescent and bare-soil <lb/>situations and contextual models present a lot of dispersion. <lb/>Corrections for TSEB and SEBS have been suggested in or-<lb/>der to account for their respective limitations in processing <lb/>dry vegetation and low LAI cases. <lb/>From the spatial standpoint, general behaviors of the mod-<lb/>els have been described. SEBS distinguishes itself from the <lb/>others in its way of incorporating and processing vegetation <lb/>data, resulting in a singular distribution of stress. However, <lb/>for dates with a strong contrast in surface soil moisture, con-<lb/>textual models have shown mean stress values and stress <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/> www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1185 <lb/></page>

			 patterns very similar to TSEB, whereas for dates with uni-<lb/>form surface moisture (winter and summer times mostly), <lb/>they tend to accentuate extreme values of water stress. This <lb/>was expected since they are self-calibrated and thus distribute <lb/>the values between fully stressed and potential conditions for <lb/>the whole image. In this paper, we used an automatic deter-<lb/>mination of the empirical laws driving contextual models. A <lb/>manual selection was also tested but did not produce better <lb/>or worse statistics (not shown). However, a user-monitored <lb/>determination of the bounding curves might still be the only <lb/>way to decide whether extremes correspond to target situa-<lb/>tions (for instance, wet bare soils or dense vegetation under <lb/>water stress) or meaningless outliers. <lb/>This work has been carried out as a preliminary study of <lb/>the SEB models in order to assess if thermal remote sens-<lb/>ing data could yield valuable information to assimilate into <lb/>a land surface or hydrological model. Results have shown <lb/>that the single-pixel SEB models, after various modifica-<lb/>tions, can provide relevant information about water stress, <lb/>especially during the growing period where ICARE tends to <lb/>overestimate stress. By combining data assimilation of sur-<lb/>face temperature, water stress index and broadband albedo <lb/>in a Kalman ensemble assimilation scheme, both perfor-<lb/>mance amelioration (by adjusting soil water content) and cal-<lb/>ibration of ICARE could be done (see Er-raki et al., 2008; <lb/>Cammalleri and Ciraolo, 2012; Merlin et al., 2014). Further-<lb/>more, as current environmental and water use issues require a <lb/>more regional point of view, distributed SVAT models could <lb/>be an interesting tool, but very difficult to implement be-<lb/>cause of the lack of knowledge in subsurface characteristics <lb/>of wide areas. Assimilation of thermal data could be a way to <lb/>calibrate those models with a limited amount of information <lb/>about the surface. Finally, it seems that contextual and single-<lb/>pixel approaches could be merged in order to take advantage <lb/>of the increased accuracy of the later in homogeneous con-<lb/>ditions (winter and summer times) while keeping the uncer-<lb/>tainty reduction of the former for very contrasted landscapes. <lb/> 
			 
			 <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements. Funding from the French space agency <lb/>(Centre National d&apos;Etudes Spaciales, CNES) for the MiSTIGRI <lb/>(MicroSatellite for Thermal Infrared Ground surface Imaging) <lb/>phase A study, as well as the FORMOSAT acquisition, the <lb/>MISTRALS (Mediterranean Integrated STudies at Regional And <lb/>Local Scales) SICMed (Continental Surfaces and Interfaces in <lb/>the Mediterranean area) program, the European FP7 SIRIUS, <lb/>the PLEIADES (Participatory multi-Level EO-assisted tools for <lb/>Irrigation water management and Agricultural Decision-Support) <lb/>program as well as the IRD (Institut de Recherche pour le <lb/>Développement), the ITSON (Instituto Tecnológico de SONora), <lb/>the University of Sonora and the Cadi Ayyad University (Mo-<lb/>rocco) in the setting up of the &quot; Yaqui experiment &quot; are gratefully <lb/>acknowledged. <lb/>Edited by: N. Romano <lb/>The publication of this article is <lb/>financed by CNRS-INSU. <lb/></div>
		 
		 </body>
		 
		 <back>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> Allen, R. G., Tasumi, M., and Trezza, R.: Satellite-Based Energy <lb/>Balance for Mapping Evapotranspiration with Internalized Cali-<lb/>bration (METRIC) – Model, J. Irrig. Drain. Eng., 133, 380–394, <lb/>doi:10.1061/(ASCE)0733-9437(2007)133:4(380), 2007. <lb/>Anderson, M. C., Kustas, W. P., Norman, J. M., Hain, C. R., <lb/>Mecikalski, J. R., Schultz, L., González-Dugo, M. P., Cammal-<lb/>leri, C., d&apos;Urso, G., Pimstein, A., and Gao, F.: Mapping daily <lb/>evapotranspiration at field to continental scales using geostation-<lb/>ary and polar orbiting satellite imagery, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., <lb/>15, 223–239, doi:10.5194/hess-15-223-2011, 2011. <lb/>Barr, A. G., King, K. M., Gillespie, T. J., Hartog, G., and Neumann, <lb/>H. H.: A comparison of bowen ratio and eddy correlation sensi-<lb/>ble and latent heat flux measurements above deciduous forest, <lb/>Bound.-Lay. Meteorol., 71, 21–41, doi:10.1007/BF00709218, <lb/>1994. <lb/>Bastiaanssen, W. G. M.: SEBAL-based sensible and latent heat <lb/>fluxes in the irrigated Gediz Basin, Turkey, J. Hydrol., 229, 87– <lb/>100, doi:10.1016/S0022-1694(99)00202-4, 2000. <lb/>Bastiaanssen, W. G. M., Menenti, M., Feddes, R. A., and Holtslag, <lb/>A. A. M.: A remote sensing surface energy balance algorithm for <lb/>land (SEBAL), 1. Formulation, J. Hydrol., 212–213, 198–212, <lb/>1998. <lb/>Blanken, P. D., Black, T. A., Yang, P. C., Neumann, H. H., Nesic, Z., <lb/>Staebler, R., den Hartog, G., Novak, M. D., and Lee, X.: Energy <lb/>balance and canopy conductance of a boreal aspen forest: Par-<lb/>titioning overstory and understory components, Journal of Geo-<lb/>physical Research, 102, 28915, doi:10.1029/97JD00193, 1997. <lb/>Boulet, G., Chehbouni, A., Gentine, P., Duchemin, B., Ezzahar, J., <lb/>and Hadria, R.: Monitoring water stress using time series of ob-<lb/>served to unstressed surface temperature difference, Agr. Forest <lb/>Meteorol., 146, 159–172, doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2007.05.012, <lb/>2007. <lb/>Boulet, G., Olioso, A., Ceschia, E., Marloie, O., Coudert, B., Ri-<lb/>valland, V., Chirouze, J., and Chehbouni, G.: An empirical ex-<lb/>pression to relate aerodynamic and surface temperatures for use <lb/>within single-source energy balance models, Agr. Forest Meteo-<lb/>rol., 161, 148–155, doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2012.03.008, 2012. <lb/>Brutsaert, W.: Aspects of bulk atmospheric boundary layer simi-<lb/>larity under free-convective conditions, Rev. Geophys., 37, 439– <lb/>451, doi:10.1029/1999RG900013, 1999. <lb/>Bsaibes, A., Courault, D., Baret, F., Weiss, M., Olioso, A., Ja-<lb/>cob, F., Hagolle, O., Marloie, O., Bertrand, N., Desfond, V., and <lb/>Kzemipour, F.: Albedo and LAI estimates from FORMOSAT-2 <lb/>data for crop monitoring, Remote Sens. Environ., 113, 716–729, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2008.11.014, 2009. <lb/>Cammalleri, C. and Ciraolo, G.: State and parameter up-<lb/>date in a coupled energy/hydrologic balance model using <lb/>ensemble Kalman filtering, J. Hydrol., 416-417, 171–181, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.jhydrol.2011.11.049, 2012. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1186 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>
			
			Cammalleri, C., Anderson, M. C., Ciraolo, G., D&apos;Urso, G., Kus-<lb/>tas, W. P., La Loggia, G., and Minacapilli, M.: Applications <lb/>of a remote sensing-based two-source energy balance algo-<lb/>rithm for mapping surface fluxes without in situ air tem-<lb/>perature observations, Remote Sens. Environ., 124, 502–515, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2012.06.009, 2012. <lb/>Chehbouni, A., Escadafal, R., Duchemin, B., Boulet, G., Simon-<lb/>neaux, V., Dedieu, G., Mougenot, B., Khabba, S., Kharrou, H., <lb/>Maisongrande, P., Merlin, O., Chaponnière, A., Ezzahar, J., Er-<lb/>Raki, S., Hoedjes, J., Hadria, R., Abourida, A., Cheggour, A., <lb/>Raibi, F., Boudhar, A., Benhadj, I., Hanich, L., Benkaddour, A., <lb/>Guemouria, N., Chehbouni, A. H., Lahrouni, A., Olioso, A., Ja-<lb/>cob, F., Williams, D. G., and Sobrino, J. A.: An integrated mod-<lb/>elling and remote sensing approach for hydrological study in arid <lb/>and semi-arid regions: the SUDMED Programme, Int. J. Remote <lb/>Sens., 29, 5161–5181, doi:10.1080/01431160802036417, 2008a. <lb/>Chehbouni, A., Hoedjes, J., Rodriguez, J.-C., Watts, C., Garatuza-<lb/>Payan, J., Jacob, F., and Kerr, Y.: Using remotely sensed data <lb/>to estimate area-averaged daily surface fluxes over a semi-arid <lb/>mixed agricultural land, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 148, 330–342, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2007.09.014, 2008b. <lb/>Chen, X., Su, Z., Ma, Y., Yang, K., Wen, J., and Zhang, Y.: An <lb/>Improvement of Roughness Height Parameterization of the Sur-<lb/>face Energy Balance System (SEBS) over the Tibetan Plateau, J. <lb/>Appl. Meteorol. Clim., 52, 607–622, doi:10.1175/JAMC-D-12-<lb/>056.1, 2013. <lb/>Chern, J.-S., Ling, J., and Weng, S.-L.: Taiwan&apos;s second re-<lb/>mote sensing satellite, Acta Astronautica, 63, 1305–1311, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.actaastro.2008.05.022, 2008. <lb/>Choi, M., Kustas, W. P., Anderson, M. C., Allen, R. G., <lb/>Li, F., and Kjaersgaard, J. H.: An intercomparison of <lb/>three remote sensing-based surface energy balance algorithms <lb/>over a corn and soybean production region (Iowa, U.S.) <lb/>during SMACEX, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 149, 2082–2097, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2009.07.002, 2009. <lb/>Choudhury, B. and Monteith, J.: A four-layer model for the heat <lb/>budget of homogeneous land surfaces, Q. J. Roy. Meteorol. Soc., <lb/>114, 373–398, 1988. <lb/>Cleugh, H. A., Leuning, R., Mu, Q., and Running, S. <lb/>W.: Regional evaporation estimates from flux tower and <lb/>MODIS satellite data, Remote Sens. Environ., 106, 285–304, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2006.07.007, 2007. <lb/>Clevers, J.: The Application of a Weighted Infrared-Red Vegeta-<lb/>tion Index for Estimating Leaf-Area Index by Correcting for soil-<lb/>moisture, Remote Sens. Environ., 29, 25–37, doi:10.1016/0034-<lb/>4257(89)90076-x, 1989. <lb/>Colaizzi, P. D., Evett, S. R., Howell, T. A., Li, F., Kustas, W. P., and <lb/>Anderson, M. C.: Radiation Model for Row Crops: I. Geometric <lb/>View Factors and Parameter Optimization, Agronomy J., 104, <lb/>225–240, doi:10.2134/agronj2011.0082, 2012. <lb/>Coudert, B. and Ottlé, C.: An improved SVAT model calibra-<lb/>tion strategy based on the optimisation of surface temper-<lb/>ature temporal dynamics, Geophys. Res. Lett., 34, L04402, <lb/>doi:10.1029/2006GL028778, 2007. <lb/>Courault, D., Seguin, B. and Olioso, A.: Review on estimation of <lb/>evapotranspiration from remote sensing data: From empirical to <lb/>numerical modeling approaches, Irrig. Drain. Syst., 19, 223–249, <lb/>doi:10.1007/s10795-005-5186-0, 2005. <lb/>Courault, D., Bsaibes, A., Kpemlie, E., Hadria, R., Hagolle, O., <lb/>Marloie, O., Hanocq, J.-F., Olioso, A., Bertrand, N., and Des-<lb/>fonds, V.: Assessing the Potentialities of FORMOSAT-2 Data for <lb/>Water and Crop Monitoring at Small Regional Scale in South-<lb/>Eastern France, Sensors, 8, 3460–3481, doi:10.3390/s8053460, <lb/>2008. <lb/>Delogu, E., Boulet, G., Olioso, A., Coudert, B., Chirouze, J., <lb/>Ceschia, E., Le Dantec, V., Marloie, O., Chehbouni, G., and <lb/>Lagouarde, J.-P.: Reconstruction of temporal variations of evap-<lb/>otranspiration using instantaneous estimates at the time of <lb/>satellite overpass, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 16, 2995–3010, <lb/>doi:10.5194/hess-16-2995-2012, 2012. <lb/>Er-Raki, S., Chehbouni, A., Hoedjes, J., Ezzahar, J., Duchemin, <lb/>B., and Jacob, F.: Improvement of FAO-56 method for olive <lb/>orchards through sequential assimilation of thermal infrared-<lb/>based estimates of ET, Agr. Water Manage., 95, 309–321, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.agwat.2007.10.013, 2008. <lb/>Fieuzal, R., Duchemin, B., Jarlan, L., Zribi, M., Baup, F., Merlin, <lb/>O., Hagolle, O., and Garatuza-Payan, J.: Combined use of opti-<lb/>cal and radar satellite data for the monitoring of irrigation and <lb/>soil moisture of wheat crops, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 15, 1117– <lb/>1129, doi:10.5194/hess-15-1117-2011, 2011. <lb/>French, a. N., Jacob, F., Anderson, M. C., Kustas, W. P., Timmer-<lb/>mans, W., Gieske, a., Su, Z., Su, H., McCabe, M. F., Li, F., <lb/>Prueger, J., and Brunsell, N.: Surface energy fluxes with the Ad-<lb/>vanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Reflection radiometer <lb/>(ASTER) at the Iowa 2002 SMACEX site (USA), Remote Sens. <lb/>Environ., 99, 55–65, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2005.05.015, 2005. <lb/>Galleguillos, M., Jacob, F., Prévot, L., French, A., and Lagacherie, <lb/>P.: Comparison of two temperature differencing methods to esti-<lb/>mate daily evapotranspiration over a Mediterranean vineyard wa-<lb/>tershed from ASTER data, Remote Sens. Environ., 115, 1326– <lb/>1340, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2011.01.013, 2011. <lb/>Gentine, P., Entekhabi, D., Chehbouni, A., Boulet, G., <lb/>and Duchemin, B.: Analysis of evaporative fraction di-<lb/>urnal behaviour, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 143, 13–29, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2006.11.002, 2007. <lb/>Gillespie, A., Rokugawa, S., Matsunaga, T., Cothern, J. S., Hook, <lb/>S., and Kahle, A. B.: A temperature and emissivity separation <lb/>algorithm for Advanced Spaceborne Thermal Emission and Re-<lb/>flection Radiometer (ASTER) images, IEEE T. Geosci. Remote, <lb/>36, 1113–1126, doi:10.1109/36.700995, 1998. <lb/>Gokmen, M., Vekerdy, Z., Verhoef, A., Verhoef, W., Batelaan, <lb/>O., and van der Tol, C.: Integration of soil moisture in <lb/>SEBS for improving evapotranspiration estimation under wa-<lb/>ter stress conditions, Remote Sens. Environ., 121, 261–274, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2012.02.003, 2012. <lb/>Gomez, M., Olioso, a, Sobrino, J., and Jacob, F.: Retrieval of evap-<lb/>otranspiration over the Alpilles/ReSeDA experimental site using <lb/>airborne POLDER sensor and a thermal camera, Remote Sens. <lb/>Environ., 96, 399–408, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2005.03.006, 2005. <lb/>Gonzalez-Dugo, M. P., Neale, C. M. U., Mateos, L., Kustas, W. <lb/>P., Prueger, J. H., Anderson, M. C., and Li, F.: A compari-<lb/>son of operational remote sensing-based models for estimating <lb/>crop evapotranspiration, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 149, 1843–1853, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2009.06.012, 2009. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote"> J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note>

			<page>1187 <lb/></page>

			Hagolle, O., Dedieu, G., Mougenot, B., Debaecker, V., Duchemin, <lb/>B., and Meygret, A.: Correction of aerosol effects on multi-<lb/>temporal images acquired with constant viewing angles: Appli-<lb/>cation to Formosat-2 images, Remote Sens. Environ., 112, 1689– <lb/>1701, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2007.08.016, 2008. <lb/>Hain, C. R., Mecikalski, J. R., and Anderson, M. C.: Retrieval of <lb/>an Available Water-Based Soil Moisture Proxy from Thermal <lb/>Infrared Remote Sensing, Part I: Methodology and Validation, <lb/>J. Hydrometeorol., 10, 665–683, doi:10.1175/2008JHM1024.1, <lb/>2009. <lb/>Jacob, F. and Olioso, A.: Derivation of diurnal courses of albedo <lb/>and reflected solar irradiance from airborne POLDER data <lb/>acquired near solar noon, J. Geophys. Res., 110, D10104, <lb/>doi:10.1029/2004JD004888, 2005. <lb/>Jacob, F., Olioso, A., Gu, X. F., Su, Z., and Seguin, B.: Mapping sur-<lb/>face fluxes using airborne visible, near infrared, thermal infrared <lb/>remote sensing data and a spatialized surface energy balance <lb/>model, Agronomie, 22, 669–680, doi:10.1051/agro:2002053, <lb/>2002. <lb/>Jacob, F., Schmugge, T., Olioso, A., French, A., Courault, D., <lb/>Ogawa, K., Petitcolin, F., Chehbouni, G., Pinheiro, A., and Priv-<lb/>ette, J.: Modeling and Inversion in Thermal Infrared Remote <lb/>Sensing over Vegetated Land Surfaces, in: Advances in Land Re-<lb/>mote Sensing, edited by: Liang, S., Springer Netherlands, 245– <lb/>291, 2008. <lb/>Jia, L., Su, Z., van den Hurk, B., Menenti, M., Moene, A., De Bruin, <lb/>H. A., Yrisarry, J. J. B., Ibanez, M., and Cuesta, A.: Estimation <lb/>of sensible heat flux using the Surface Energy Balance System <lb/>(SEBS) and ATSR measurements, Phys. Chem. Earth A/B/C, 28, <lb/>75–88, doi:10.1016/S1474-7065(03)00009-3, 2003. <lb/>Jiménez, C., Prigent, C., Mueller, B., Seneviratne, S. I., Mc-<lb/>Cabe, M. F., Wood, E. F., Rossow, W. B., Balsamo, G., Betts, <lb/>A. K., Dirmeyer, P. A., Fisher, J. B., Jung, M., Kanamitsu, <lb/>M., Reichle, R. H., Reichstein, M., Rodell, M., Sheffield, J., <lb/>Tu, K., and Wang, K.: Global intercomparison of 12 land <lb/>surface heat flux estimates, J. Geophys. Res., 116, D02102, <lb/>doi:10.1029/2010JD014545, 2011. <lb/>Kalma, J. D., McVicar, T. R., and McCabe, M. F.: Estimating Land <lb/>Surface Evaporation: A Review of Methods Using Remotely <lb/>Sensed Surface Temperature Data, Surv. Geophys., 29, 421–469, <lb/>doi:10.1007/s10712-008-9037-z, 2008. <lb/>Kustas, W. and Anderson, M.: Advances in thermal infrared remote <lb/>sensing for land surface modeling, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 149, <lb/>2071–2081, doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2009.05.016, 2009. <lb/>Kustas, W. and Daughtry, C.: Estimation of the soil heat flux/net <lb/>radiation ratio from spectral data, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 49, 205– <lb/>223, 1990. <lb/>Li, F., Kustas, W., Prueger, J., Neale, C., and Jackson, T.: Utility <lb/>of remote sensing-based two-source energy balance model under <lb/>low-and high-vegetation cover conditions, J, Hydrometeorol., 6, <lb/>878–891, 2005. <lb/>Li, F., Kustas, W. P., Anderson, M. C., Prueger, J. H., and Scott, <lb/>R. L.: Effect of remote sensing spatial resolution on interpreting <lb/>tower-based flux observations, Remote Sens. Environ., 112, 337– <lb/>349, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2006.11.032, 2008. <lb/>Long, D. and Singh, V. P.: A Two-source Trapezoid Model for Evap-<lb/>otranspiration (TTME) from satellite imagery, Remote Sens. En-<lb/>viron., 121, 370–388, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2012.02.015, 2012. <lb/>Ma, W., Ma, Y., Hu, Z., Su, Z., Wang, J., and Ishikawa, H.: Estimat-<lb/>ing surface fluxes over middle and upper streams of the Heihe <lb/>River Basin with ASTER imagery, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 15, <lb/>1403–1413, doi:10.5194/hess-15-1403-2011, 2011. <lb/>Martin, M., Dickinson, R. E., and Yang, Z.-L.: Use of a Coupled <lb/>Land Surface General Circulation Model to Examine the <lb/>Impacts of Doubled Stomatal Resistance on the Water Re-<lb/>sources of the American Southwest, J. Climate, 12, 3359–3375, <lb/>doi:10.1175/1520-0442(1999)012&lt;3359:UOACLS&gt;2.0.CO;2, <lb/>1999. <lb/>McCabe, M. F. and Wood, E. F.: Scale influences on the <lb/>remote estimation of evapotranspiration using multiple <lb/>satellite sensors, Remote Sens. Environ., 105, 271–285, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2006.07.006, 2006. <lb/>McCabe, M. F., Wood, E. F., Wójcik, R., Pan, M., Sheffield, J., Gao, <lb/>H., and Su, H.: Hydrological consistency using multi-sensor re-<lb/>mote sensing data for water and energy cycle studies, Remote <lb/>Sens. Environ., 112, 430–444, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2007.03.027, <lb/>2008. <lb/>Merlin, O. and Chehbouni, A.: Different approaches in esti-<lb/>mating heat flux using dual angle observations of radia-<lb/>tive surface temperature, Int. J. Remote Sens., 25, 275–289, <lb/>doi:10.1080/0143116031000116408, 2004. <lb/>Merlin, O., Duchemin, B., Hagolle, O., Jacob, F., Coudert, B., <lb/>Chehbouni, G., Dedieu, G., Garatuza, J., and Kerr, Y.: Disaggre-<lb/>gation of MODIS surface temperature over an agricultural area <lb/>using a time series of Formosat-2 images, Remote Sens. Envi-<lb/>ron., 114, 2500–2512, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2010.05.025, 2010. <lb/>Merlin, O., Chirouze, J., Olioso, A., Jarlan, L., Chehbouni, G., <lb/>and Boulet, G.: An image-based four-source surface energy bal-<lb/>ance model to estimate crop evapotranspiration from solar re-<lb/>flectance/thermal emission data (SEB-4S), Agr. Forest Meteo-<lb/>rol., 184, 188–203, doi:10.1016/j.agrformet.2013.10.002, 2014. <lb/>Minacapilli, M., Agnese, C., Blanda, F., Cammalleri, C., Ciraolo, <lb/>G., D&apos;Urso, G., Iovino, M., Pumo, D., Provenzano, G., and Rallo, <lb/>G.: Estimation of actual evapotranspiration of Mediterranean <lb/>perennial crops by means of remote-sensing based surface en-<lb/>ergy balance models, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 13, 1061–1074, <lb/>doi:10.5194/hess-13-1061-2009, 2009. <lb/>Monteith, J.: Principles of environmental physics, Edward Arnold, <lb/>London, 1973. <lb/>Moran, M., Clarke, T., Inoue, Y., and Vidal, A.: Estimating crop <lb/>water deficit using the relation between surface-air temperature <lb/>and spectral vegetation index, Remote Sens. Environ., 49, 246– <lb/>263, doi:10.1016/0034-4257(94)90020-5, 1994. <lb/>Noilhan, J. and Mahfouf, J.-F.: The ISBA land surface pa-<lb/>rameterisation scheme, Global Planet. Change, 13, 145–159, <lb/>doi:10.1016/0921-8181(95)00043-7, 1996. <lb/>Noilhan, J. and Planton, S.: A Simple Parameterization <lb/>of Land Surface Processes for Meteorological Models, <lb/>Mon. Weather Rev., 117, 536–549, doi:10.1175/1520-<lb/>0493(1989)117&lt;0536:ASPOLS&gt;2.0.CO;2, 1989. <lb/>Norman, J. M., Kustas, W. P., and Humes, K. S.: Source approach <lb/>for estimating soil and vegetation energy fluxes in observations <lb/>of directional radiometric surface temperature, Agr. Forest Mete-<lb/>orol., 77, 263–293, doi:10.1016/0168-1923(95)02265-Y, 1995. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/ <lb/>Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/></note>

			<page> 1188 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Chirouze et al.: Intercomparison of four remote-sensing-based energy balance methods <lb/></note> 
			
			Norman, J. M., Kustas, W. P., Prueger, J. H., and Diak, G. R.: <lb/>Surface flux estimation using radiometric temperature: A dual-<lb/>temperature-difference method to minimize measurement errors, <lb/>Water Resour. Res., 36, 2263–2274, 2000. <lb/>Oki, T., and Kanae, S.: Global Hydrological Cycles and <lb/>World Water Resources, Science, 313, 1068–1072, <lb/>doi:10.1126/science.1128845, 2006. <lb/>Oku, Y., Ishikawa, H., and Su, Z.: Estimation of Land Surface Heat <lb/>Fluxes over the Tibetan Plateau Using GMS Data, J. Appl. Me-<lb/>teorol. Clim., 46, 183–195, doi:10.1175/JAM2456.1, 2007. <lb/>Olioso, A., Inoue, Y., and Ortega-Farias, S.: Future directions for <lb/>advanced evapotranspiration modeling: Assimilation of remote <lb/>sensing data into crop simulation models and SVAT models, Ir-<lb/>rig. Drain., 19, 377–412, 2005. <lb/>Passerat de Silans, A.: Transferts de masse et de chaleur dans un sol <lb/>stratifié soumis à une excitation atmosphérique naturelle (com-<lb/>paraison modèles-expérience), Institut National Polytechnique <lb/>de Grenoble, Grenoble, 1986. <lb/>Roerink, G., Su, Z., and Menenti, M.: S-SEBI: A simple re-<lb/>mote sensing algorithm to estimate the surface energy bal-<lb/>ance, Phys. Chem. Earth B, 25, 147–157, doi:10.1016/S1464-<lb/>1909(99)00128-8, 2000. <lb/>Sabol, D. E., Gillespie, A. R., Abbott, E., and Yamada, G.: Remote <lb/>Sensing of Environment Field validation of the ASTER Temper-<lb/>ature – Emissivity Separation algorithm, Remote Sens. Environ., <lb/>113, 2328–2344, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2009.06.008, 2009. <lb/>Santanello, J. A. and Friedl, M. A.: Diurnal Covariation in Soil <lb/>Heat Flux and Net Radiation, J. Appl. Meteorol., 42, 851–862, <lb/>doi:10.1175/1520-0450(2003)042&lt;0851:DCISHF&gt;2.0.CO;2, <lb/>2003. <lb/>Schmugge, T., Hook, S., and Coll, C.: Recovering surface tempera-<lb/>ture and emissivity from thermal infrared multispectral data, Re-<lb/>mote Sens. Environ., 65, 121–131, 1998. <lb/>Schuurmans, J. M., Troch, P. A., Veldhuizen, A. A., Bastiaanssen, <lb/>W. G., and Bierkens, M. F. P.: Assimilation of remotely sensed <lb/>latent heat flux in a distributed hydrological model, Adv. Water <lb/>Resour., 26, 151–159, 2003. <lb/>Shiklomanov, I.: World water resources: a new appraisal and <lb/>assessment for the 21st century, UNESCO, Paris, available <lb/>from: http://www.vliz.be/imis/imis.php?refid=11667 (last ac-<lb/>cess: 23 April 2013), 1998. <lb/>Shuttleworth, W. and Wallace, J.: Evaporation from sparse crops – <lb/>An energy combination theory, Q. J. Roy. Meteorol. Soc., 111, <lb/>839–855, doi:10.1256/smsqj.46909, 1985. <lb/>Su, H., McCabe, M., and Wood, E.: Modeling evapotranspira-<lb/>tion during SMACEX: Comparing two approaches for local-and <lb/>regional-scale prediction, J. Hydrometeorol., 6, 910–922, 2005. <lb/>Su, H., Wood, E., McCabe, M., and Su, Z.: Evaluation of remotely <lb/>sensed evapotranspiration over the CEOP EOP-1 reference sites, <lb/>J. Meteorol. Soc. Jpn., 85, 439–459, 2007. <lb/>Su, Z.: The Surface Energy Balance System (SEBS) for estima-<lb/>tion of turbulent heat fluxes, Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 6, 85–100, <lb/>doi:10.5194/hess-6-85-2002, 2002. <lb/>Tang, R., Li, Z.-L., Jia, Y., Li, C., Sun, X., Kustas, W. P., <lb/>and Anderson, M. C.: An intercomparison of three remote <lb/>sensing-based energy balance models using Large Aperture <lb/>Scintillometer measurements over a wheat–corn production <lb/>region, Remote Sensing of Environment, 115, 3187–3202, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.rse.2011.07.004, 2011. <lb/>Timmermans, W. J., Kustas, W. P., Anderson, M. C., and French, <lb/>A. N.: An intercomparison of the Surface Energy Balance Al-<lb/>gorithm for Land (SEBAL) and the Two-Source Energy Balance <lb/>(TSEB) modeling schemes, Remote Sens. Environ., 108, 369– <lb/>384, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2006.11.028, 2007. <lb/>Twine, T. E., Kustas, W. P., Norman, J. M., Cook, D. R., Houser, <lb/>P. R., Meyers, T. P., Prueger, J. H., Starks, P. J., and Wesely, M. <lb/>L.: Correcting eddy-covariance flux underestimates over a grass-<lb/>land, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 103, 279–300, doi:10.1016/S0168-<lb/>1923(00)00123-4, 2000. <lb/>Van de Griend, A. A. and Owe, M.: On the Relationship between <lb/>Thermal Emissivity and the Normalized Difference Vegetation <lb/>Index for Natural Surfaces, Int. J. Remote Sens., 14, 1119–1131, <lb/>1993. <lb/>van der Kwast, J., Timmermans, W., Gieske, A., Su, Z., Olioso, <lb/>A., Jia, L., Elbers, J., Karssenberg, D., and de Jong, S.: Eval-<lb/>uation of the Surface Energy Balance System (SEBS) applied <lb/>to ASTER imagery with flux-measurements at the SPARC 2004 <lb/>site (Barrax, Spain), Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 13, 1337–1347, <lb/>doi:10.5194/hess-13-1337-2009, 2009. <lb/>Van Dijk, A., Moene, A. and De Bruin, H.: The principles <lb/>of surface flux physics: theory, practice and descrip-<lb/>tion of the ECPACK library, Wageningen, the Nether-<lb/>lands, available from: http://wwWmaq.wur.nl/NR/rdonlyres/ <lb/>3C2D48B3-2D23-4EE7-BA70-342863EBF822/60091/ir2004_ <lb/>01v13.pdf (last access: 1 March 2013), 2004. <lb/>Venturini, V., Islam, S., and Rodriguez, L.: Estimation of evapora-<lb/>tive fraction and evapotranspiration from MODIS products us-<lb/>ing a complementary based model, Remote Sens. Environ., 112, <lb/>132–141, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2007.04.014, 2008. <lb/>Verstraeten, W. W., Veroustraete, F., and Feyen, J.: Estimating evap-<lb/>otranspiration of European forests from NOAA-imagery at satel-<lb/>lite overpass time: Towards an operational processing chain for <lb/>integrated optical and thermal sensor data products, Remote <lb/>Sens. Environ., 96, 256–276, doi:10.1016/j.rse.2005.03.004, <lb/>2005. <lb/>Wilson, K., Goldstein, A., Falge, E., Aubinet, M., Baldocchi, D., <lb/>Berbigier, P., Bernhofer, C., Ceulemans, R., Dolman, H., Field, <lb/>C., Grelle, A., Ibrom, A., Law, B., Kowalski, A., Meyers, T., <lb/>Moncrieff, J., Monson, R., Oechel, W., Tenhunen, J., Valen-<lb/>tini, R., and Verma, S.: Energy balance closure at FLUXNET <lb/>sites, Agr. Forest Meteorol., 113, 223–243, doi:10.1016/S0168-<lb/>1923(02)00109-0, 2002. <lb/>World Water Assessment Programme: The United Nations World <lb/>Water Development Report 4: Managing Water under Uncer-<lb/>tainty and Risk, United Nat., edited by: Andrzejwski, C., Cullen, <lb/>A., Dash, B., Franek, A., Kelty, M., McDonald, D., Smith, M., <lb/>Wauchope, S., and P. Publishing, UNESCO, Paris, 2012. <lb/>Yang, J. and Wang, Y.: Estimating evapotranspiration frac-<lb/>tion by modeling two-dimensional space of NDVI/albedo <lb/>and day–night land surface temperature difference: A <lb/>comparative study, Adv. Water Resour., 34, 512–518, <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.advwatres.2011.01.006, 2011. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Hydrol. Earth Syst. Sci., 18, 1165–1188, 2014 <lb/>www.hydrol-earth-syst-sci.net/18/1165/2014/</note> 

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
