<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Targeted Neuronal Activation of the <lb/>Gastrointestinal Tract Shapes the Environment <lb/>of the Gut in Mice <lb/>Bryan B. Yoo 1* , Jessica A. Griffiths 1 , Peter Thuy-Boun 2+ , Victor Cantu 3+ , Kelly Weldon 4,5,+ , <lb/>Collin Challis 1 , Michael J. Sweredoski 1 , Ken Y. Chan 1# , Taren M. Thron 1 , Gil Sharon 1 , <lb/>Annie Moradian 1% , Gregory Humphrey 3 , Qiyun Zhu 3 , Justin Shaffer 3 , Dennis W. Wolan 2 , <lb/>Pieter C. Dorrestein 3,4,5 , Rob Knight 3,5,6,7 , Viviana Gradinaru 1 , and Sarkis K. Mazmanian 1* <lb/>1 <lb/>Division of Biology &amp; Biological Engineering, California Institute of Technology, Pasadena, California, <lb/>USA, 91125 <lb/>2 <lb/>Departments of Molecular Medicine and Integrative Structural and Computational Biology, The Scripps <lb/>Research Institute, 10550 North Torrey Pines Road, La Jolla, CA 92037, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Pediatrics, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>4 <lb/>Collaborative Mass Spectrometry Innovation Center, Skaggs School of Pharmacy and Pharmaceutical <lb/>Sciences, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>5 <lb/>UCSD Center for Microbiome Innovation, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>6 <lb/>Department of Computer Science and Engineering, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, <lb/>USA <lb/>7 <lb/>Department of Engineering, University of California San Diego, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>+ <lb/>These authors contributed equally <lb/># <lb/>Present Address: Stanley Center for Psychiatric Research, Broad Institute, Massachusetts Institute of <lb/>Technology, Cambridge, MA, 02142, USA <lb/>% Present Address: Precision Biomarker Labs, Cedars-Sinai, 8700 Beverly Blvd. Davis 2904, Los <lb/>Angeles, CA 90048 <lb/>*Corresponding Author. Email: byoo@caltech.edu (B.B.Y); sarkis@caltech.edu (S.K.M) <lb/>was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/> SUMMARY <lb/>The enteric nervous system (ENS) integrates cues from the brain and from local signals in the <lb/>gut to coordinate responses that shape the intestinal milieu. Tools to study, and knowledge of, <lb/>the ENS lag behind brain research. Herein, we deploy novel recombinant adeno-associated <lb/>viral (rAAV) vectors with enhanced tropism for the gut to map and activate enteric neurons with <lb/>spatial and temporal resolution. rAAV-mediated fluorescent labelling coupled with whole-tissue <lb/>clearing methods in the small intestine and colon of mice enables efficient and thorough <lb/>characterization of the neuronal architecture of the ENS. We also delivered &apos;designer receptors <lb/>exclusively activated by designer drugs&apos; (DREADDs) to specifically activate gut neurons that <lb/>express choline acetyltransferase (ChAT + ) and tyrosine hydroxylase (TH + ). Targeted activation <lb/>of ChAT + or TH + neuronal populations associated with the gastrointestinal (GI) tract altered the <lb/>intestinal transcriptome of mice, host and microbial proteome, metagenome, and fecal <lb/>metabolome. We reveal previously unknown and broad roles for neurons in modulating <lb/>intestinal physiology, mucosal immunity, and gut microbiome structure, and propose novel <lb/>interactions for the ENS such as regulating fungal colonization and shaping of bile acid profiles. <lb/>Experimental tools and rich datasets with multi-parameter characterization of the gut ecosystem <lb/>may enable further study of the ENS. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>The gastrointestinal (GI) tract consists of diverse cells (e.g., immune, epithelial, endothelial, <lb/>endocrine, muscle, neuronal, and even microbial) that coordinate physiology within the gut <lb/>(Furness, 2006) and throughout the entire body (Rao and Gershon, 2016). The mammalian gut <lb/>receives and transmits neuronal signals from over 100,000 extrinsic nerve fibers that originate <lb/>from the sympathetic (SNS) and parasympathetic (PNS) nervous systems (Grundy and <lb/>Brookes, 2011). The GI tract is also innervated by an expansive network of intrinsic neurons, <lb/>collectively termed the enteric nervous system (ENS), that has over 100 million neurons <lb/>organized into distinct compartments within the GI tract, namely the myenteric plexus and <lb/>submucosal plexus (Furness et al., 2014). In recent years, extrinsic and intrinsic innervation of <lb/>the GI tract has been implicated in various host responses, from digestion (Schneider et al., <lb/>2019), to immunity (Gabanyi et al., 2016; Muller et al., 2014), to complex behaviors (Bravo et <lb/>al., 2011) in mice. Specific interactions between neurons of the GI tract and various other cell <lb/>types emphasize the diverse and expansive roles of the ENS. For example, neural pathways in <lb/>the gut regulate nutrient sensation through intestinal enteroendocrine cells (Kaelberer et al., <lb/>2018), affect the epithelial barrier and mucosal immunity (Jarret et al., 2020; Seillet et al., 2020; <lb/>Talbot et al., 2020), and dynamically interface with the microbiome (Lai et al., 2019; Matheis et <lb/>al., 2020). While neurons in the central nervous system (CNS) interact with multiple cell types, <lb/>broad exposure of the ENS to a changing external environment (e.g., diet, microbiome, <lb/>xenobiotics, etc.) create interactions distinct from those in the brain. <lb/>With the goal of demystifying complex interactions in the GI tract, we employed and optimized <lb/>powerful experimental tools, originally developed for brain research, to explore the architecture <lb/>of the ENS and the functional consequence of neuronal activation of the GI tract. Adeno-<lb/>associated viruses (AAVs) have been characterized for their ability to efficiently deliver various <lb/>genes to eukaryotic cells (Kotterman and Schaffer, 2014), and have been deployed in research, <lb/>biotechnology, and medical settings (Samulski and Muzyczka, 2014). Using an engineered AAV <lb/>capsid variant, AAV-PHP.S, that was selected for having enhanced tropism to the ENS of mice <lb/>(Chan et al., 2017), we achieved broad expression of genetically encoded fluorescent reporters <lb/>and neural activators in the gut. Further, we delivered a fluorescent calcium reporter <lb/>(GCaMP6F) into enteric neurons to measure ENS activity in live animals. Adding to the wealth <lb/>of immunohistochemical characterization of the ENS (Furness, 2012), we coupled advanced <lb/>tissue clearing technologies with AAV-mediated labelling of cells to present methodological <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>improvements to traditional approaches that allowed broad surveyance of ENS architecture in <lb/>intact GI tissue and the ability to directly measure in vivo neuronal activity in the gut. <lb/>Beyond characterization, we sought to investigate the effects of activating specific neuronal <lb/>subsets on the gut environment. Choline acetyltransferase (ChAT) and tyrosine hydroxylase <lb/>(TH) are the rate limiting enzymes in acetylcholine and catecholamine biosynthesis, <lb/>respectively, are are key chemical mediators of neurotransmission in the brain and the <lb/>periphery. However, the extent to which these neuronal populations impact complex GI <lb/>physiologies beyond motility and secretory function remain less studied. Accordingly, we <lb/>transduced GI neurons of mice with chemogenetic modulators (Wess et al., 2013) in discrete <lb/>cell populations to achieve cell-specific control of ChAT and TH neurons. We discovered that <lb/>stimulating neural activity in the GI tract alters the transcriptional and proteomic landscape of <lb/>the intestines, with complementing alterations to the gut metagenome and the gut metabolome. <lb/>We report diverse and expansive effects of directed neuronal activation on epithelial biology, <lb/>mucosal immunity, angiogenesis, and muscle physiology, among other outcomes. We observe <lb/>expansions and contractions of fungal and bacterial taxa. Of the many molecular changes, we <lb/>highlight dramatic effects on the conversion of primary to secondary bile acids, products of <lb/>mouse and bacterial co-metabolism that have been widely implicated in health and disease (de <lb/>Aguiar Vallim et al., 2013; Fiorucci et al., 2018; Hofmann and Eckmann, 2006; Long et al., 2017; <lb/>Sakai et al., 1980). The experimental tools and multi-parameter datasets introduced in this <lb/>Resource may help advance technologies and understanding of neurogastroenterology and the <lb/>complex environment of the gut. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Targeted Neuronal Labeling Enables Extensive, High-Resolution Imaging of the ENS in <lb/>Mice <lb/>Various morphologic features of the ENS have been characterized (Furness, 2006). However, <lb/>resolving the broad architectural features of neurons in the gut with current imaging methods, <lb/>primarily using immunohistochemistry (IHC), are limited by several physical obstacles of the GI <lb/>tract: large area (~40cm long in a mouse), gut motility / tissue pliability (i.e., with or without <lb/>luminal contents, relaxed vs. contracted smooth muscle), and 3-dimensional biogeography (i.e., <lb/>longitudinal and cross-sectional analysis). Furthermore, the ENS is localized within two distinct <lb/>plexuses of the GI tract and studies have often characterized myenteric neurons by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>microdissection of the longitudinal muscle / myenteric plexus tissue layer (Fried and <lb/>Gulbransen, 2015), a manipulation of the tissue that disassociates axons from their destination <lb/>in 3-dimensional space and overlooks the organization of submucosal neurons. <lb/>To overcome these limitations, we labelled all neurons of the ENS of living mice with <lb/>recombinant adeno-associated viruses (rAAVs) expressing fluorescent proteins, and employed <lb/>tissue clearing techniques to enhance visualization of intact GI tissue. The AAV capsid variant <lb/>AAV-PHP.S was used since it has been optimized for systemic delivery in mice (Deverman et <lb/>al., 2016) and characterized for its increased tropism to the peripheral nervous system, <lb/>specifically the ENS (Chan et al., 2017). We first looked to compare the general infectivity of <lb/>AAV-PHP.S to AAV9 which has been used in the past for viral delivery to the ENS (Benskey et <lb/>al., 2015). Similar to the Chan et al. study, the cargo for both AAVs was the gene encoding a <lb/>nuclear localized green fluorescent protein expressed under the strong, ubiquitous CAG <lb/>promoter. Following a single intravenous (i.v.) systemic injection of the AAVs, AAV-PHP.S <lb/>efficiently transduced cells throughout the GI tract and exhibited greater infectivity of cells <lb/>throughout layers of the GI tract as seen by increased cellular expression of nuclear localized <lb/>CAG-GFP (Figure 1A).Gene products driven by the human Synapsin 1 (hSYN1) promoter have <lb/>previously been shown to restrict expression to neurons (Jackson et al., 2016; Kügler et al., <lb/>2003) and minimize expression in peripheral targets such as the dorsal root ganglia (Haenraets <lb/>et al., 2017). We packaged fluorescent proteins genes under the hSYN1 promoter into AAV-<lb/>PHP.S, delivered them systemically, and found that 90% (±1.5%) of cells in the ENS labelled <lb/>with antibodies against Protein Gene Product 9.5 (PGP9.5), a pan-neuronal protein, co-<lb/>localized with virally labelled neurons in the small intestines and colon (Figure 1B). <lb/>Tremendous efforts to characterize the circuitry and neurochemistry of the GI nervous system <lb/>have been made to date (Furness, 2012). However, the physical length of the GI tract makes <lb/>thorough characterization of the ENS by IHC both intractable and costly. With AAV-mediated <lb/>labeling, a single systemic injection of AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-mNeonGreen at 10 12 viral genomes <lb/>(vg) was sufficient to label expansive regions of ENS as seen in the colon and small intestines <lb/>(Figures 1C, S1A and S1B). This minimizes the technical variability inherent to IHC staining of <lb/>numerous tissue sections, and enables uniform imaging of millimeters of tissue at micron <lb/>resolution across many samples. Pan tissue labeling revealed spatial diversity of ENS such as <lb/>architectural differences of ganglia proximal and distal to the mesentery (insets in Figure 1C), <lb/>helping orient images relative to each other facilitating 3-dimensional tissue reconstruction. <lb/>Indeed, coupling viral-labeling with tissue clearing methods, such as a sorbitol-based clearing <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>method (ScaleS) (Hama et al., 2015; Treweek et al., 2015; Yang et al., 2014), we were able to <lb/>preserve the structure of intestinal tissue. Imaging intact tissue, rather than sectioned slides, <lb/>engendered a global view of the ENS including extrinsic nerve processes to the ENS (Figures <lb/>S1A and S1B), how ENS architecture changes in association with Peyer&apos;s patches (small <lb/>intestinal lymphoid tissues) (Figures S1C and S1D), and revealed different patterns of ENS <lb/>ganglionic morphology when tissue is fixed with or without luminal contents (Figures S1E-S1G). <lb/>When three separate viruses each encoding a distinct fluorescent protein (PHP.S:hSYN1-<lb/>mTurquoise2, PHP.S:hSYN1-mNeonGreen, or PHP.S:hSYN1-mRuby2 [together AAV-<lb/>PHP.S:hSYN1-XFP]) are delivered together at a combined dose of 10 12 vg, stochastic and <lb/>combinatorial viral transduction of cells resulted in multi-color labelling of neurons. Labeling of <lb/>neighboring cells with different colors demarcated cellular boundaries (Figure 1D) and <lb/>morphologies (Figure 1E) much more clearly than IHC, and allowed unambiguous assignment <lb/>of axons to specific cell bodies from which they emanate. This approach is also tunable by the <lb/>design of genetic promoters for different cell types, for example labeling of enteric glial cell <lb/>bodies with virally-expressed tdTomato driven by the glial fibrillary acidic protein (GFAP) <lb/>promoter (Figure 1F). <lb/>Lastly, passive clarity technique (PACT) (Hama et al., 2015; Treweek et al., 2015; Yang et al., <lb/>2014), a tissue clearing technique, also facilitated imaging of both myenteric and submucosal <lb/>neurons within the same image stack captured by confocal microscopy (Figure 1G), an <lb/>important feature of ENS phenotyping that is difficult to attain with current methods. Advances <lb/>provided by this method allow direct imaging of the ENS in intact GI tissue via whole mount <lb/>microscopy, eliminating the need to microdissect distinct layers of the GI tract and prepare thin <lb/>sections that make spatial orientation and full reconstruction of different regions challenging. <lb/>Obviating the need for microdissection also reduces mechanically-introduced artifacts to tissue. <lb/>Together, this cell labelling approach provides an effective and economical method to label the <lb/>ENS at high resolution, with cell specificity, with spatial positioning throughout the tissue, and is <lb/>widely deployable without the need for genetically-engineered mouse strains. While we <lb/>demonstrate the versatility of our method, the remainder of this study focuses on investigating <lb/>neurons in the gut. <lb/>Characterizing and Quantifying ENS Architecture <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>The small intestine and colon display similar, divergent and synergistic functions, and the ENS <lb/>is presumed to play critical roles in regulating various gut physiologies (Hansen, 2003). <lb/>However, it remains poorly understood how the cellular architecture of the ENS contributes to <lb/>GI function, and broad, simultaneous characterization of the myenteric and submucosal <lb/>plexuses has remained elusive (Foong et al., 2014; Sang and Young, 1998; Steele et al., 1991). <lb/>To expand on existing studies mapping the murine ENS, wild-type mice were transduced with <lb/>AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-XFP via a single i.v. injection to broadly label enteric neurons in the gut <lb/>(Figure 2A). Viral infection uniform throughout the SI and colon (Figure S2A), outside of a small <lb/>~1.5cm section of the medial colon that, for unknown reasons, was consistently not well <lb/>transduced and was therefore excluded from further study. Seven regions of the SI and two <lb/>regions of the colon were sampled proximally to distally, and tissue cleared by ScaleS. Tissue <lb/>regions were approximately 1cm in length and sampled every 2 to 3 cm. General ENS <lb/>architecture was explored by quantifying the number of neurons and ganglia, as well as the size <lb/>of ganglia (i.e., the number of neurons in each ganglion) in the myenteric and submucosal <lb/>plexuses (Figures 2B-2G), normalized to the number of crypts to control for inherent variabilities <lb/>within tissues. Importantly, no differences were found in crypt diameter along the GI tract <lb/>(Figure S2B). We saw that in the SI, the number of neurons and ganglia generally increased <lb/>toward the distal portions of the myenteric plexus compared to proximal regions, while the <lb/>converse was true for neurons and ganglia in the submucosal plexus (i.e., lower numbers in <lb/>distal relative to proximal regions) (Figures 2B and 2C). Additionally, the size of the ganglia (i.e., <lb/>the number of neurons per ganglia) increased in the distal regions of the SI myenteric plexus, a <lb/>feature not observed in the submucosal plexus (Figure 2D). While neuronal numbers were <lb/>similar in the proximal and distal regions of the colonic neural plexuses (Figure 2E), the number <lb/>of myenteric ganglia increased (Figure 2F) while the size of each ganglion decreased in the <lb/>distal colon (Figure 2G). Interestingly, submucosal neurons in the proximal colon were localized <lb/>to the natural folds the tissue (Figure 2A, dotted lines in lower right panel), and these ganglia <lb/>appear smaller in the distal colon. We conclude that combining viral labelling with tissue clearing <lb/>enables exceptionally broad analysis of both myenteric and submucosal neurons throughout the <lb/>gut, uncovering biogeographic features of ENS architecture in mice. Applying these histological <lb/>methodologies to characterize the ENS in the context of different diseases, microbial states, and <lb/>genetic models will initiate further expand our understanding of neurogastroenterology and <lb/>present new hypotheses of the role of the ENS in health. <lb/>Measuring Neuronal Activity in the ENS <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>We next developed a method to directly assess the activity of specific neurons in the ENS of live <lb/>mice. Existing approaches to measure intracellular calcium flux, a surrogate for neuronal firing, <lb/>in the ENS include ex vivo preparations of intestinal tissue (Hennig et al., 2015)or surgically <lb/>implanting an abdominal window to obtain in vivo ENS calcium recordings (Rakhilin et al., 2016; <lb/>2019). These techniques carry significant limitations as they involve extensive manipulation of <lb/>tissue to obtain access to the longitudinal muscle and myenteric plexus layer, require physical <lb/>separation of the ENS from its extrinsic neural connectivity, are technically challenging, and <lb/>involve intricate surgical procedures. <lb/>The expression of a genetically-encoded calcium indicator, GCaMP6F (Chen et al., 2013), <lb/>driven by the CAG promoter was targeted to the ENS via systemic viral delivery with AAV-<lb/>PHP.S. Mice were anesthetized, intestines removed from the peritoneum, and unstimulated <lb/>calcium transients in the proximal colon were recorded in individual neurons by in vivo confocal <lb/>microscopy (Figure 2H and Supplemental Video 1). Neurons in myenteric ganglia were <lb/>determined by their size and those that displayed robust changes in fluorescence intensity were <lb/>chosen at random for analysis. Enteric glial cells do not appear to show calcium fluxes in this <lb/>model. Measuring neuronal calcium flux over time revealed an average spike rate of 29.1 <lb/>spikes/minute with an interquartile range of 19.0 -37.7 spikes/minute (min.=7.0 spikes/min., <lb/>max.=63.0 spikes/min) (Figure 2I). Time between calcium spikes was calculated for each cell, <lb/>and the average peak interval was 2.6 seconds with an interquartile range of 1.6 -3.2 seconds <lb/>(min.=1.0 seconds, max.=8.6 seconds) (Figure 2J). Heatmaps (Figure 2K) and traces (Figure <lb/>2L) constructed from GCaMP6F fluorescence intensities further display the heterogeneity of <lb/>neuronal firing among and within cells (i.e., tonic vs. phasic, small vs. large fluorescence delta, <lb/>duration of spike). These data highlight the heterogeneity of ENS activity and underscores the <lb/>granularity and resolution of our method in achieving single cell measurements of neuronal <lb/>activity. Moreover, AAV-mediated delivery of GCaMP6F to the ENS and the imaging techniques <lb/>performed highlight the relative ease of data acquisition without the prerequisite of genetic <lb/>mouse models. Such application can expand the accessibility of ENS research, having broad <lb/>implications to future studies of neurogastroenterology in the context of health and disease. <lb/>Profiling Neuronal Subpopulations of the ENS in Mice <lb/>A deeper understanding of ENS biology requires knowledge of the location and function of <lb/>specific populations of neurons. Neuronal subsets can be defined by the neurotransmitters they <lb/>produce, and are often demarcated by the rate limiting enzymes required for individual <lb/>neurotransmitter production. Choline acetyltransferase (ChAT) and tyrosine hydroxylase (TH) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>are the rate limiting enzymes in acetylcholine and catecholamine biosynthesis, respectively. In <lb/>the GI tract, acetylcholine is a major excitatory neurotransmitter mainly studied for its role in <lb/>motility and secretomotor function whereas the role of intrinsically produced catecholamines is <lb/>less studied (Furness, 2012; Mittal et al., 2017). Although ChAT + and TH + neurons are intrinsic <lb/>to the GI tract, they have yet to be systematically characterized and interrogated for their role(s) <lb/>in GI physiology. We employed ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre animals, where the Cre-recombinase <lb/>(Cre) is expressed under the control of each respective gene promoter. Technically, genetic <lb/>constructs can be engineered to have the payload transgene in a double-floxed inverse <lb/>orientation (DIO), such that the transgene is flipped and expressed (and protein translated) in a <lb/>Cre-dependent manner; in other words, AAV&apos;s can be delivered to specifically to have <lb/>transgenes expressed in TH+ or ChAT+ neurons. <lb/>Accordingly, we transduced ChAT-Cre or TH-Cre mice with AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-XFP and <lb/>cleared tissues via ScaleS to visualize these specific neuronal subpopulations. Remarkably, the <lb/>cells labelled in each mouse strain occupied spatially distinct layers of the GI tract, with ChAT + <lb/>neurons localized to the myenteric plexus whereas TH + neurons were primarily found in the <lb/>submucosal plexus (Figure 3A). Upon quantification, there are more ChAT + than TH + neurons in <lb/>all assayed regions of the SI (Figure S2C), an increase largely due to higher cell numbers in the <lb/>myenteric plexus (Figure 3B). However, there were more TH + submucosal neurons in the small <lb/>intestines than ChAT + mice (Figure 3C), and this spatial disparity was accentuated when <lb/>calculating the ratio of myenteric-to-submucosal neurons (Figure S2D). Furthermore, densities <lb/>of myenteric neurons increased distally in the SI of TH-Cre mice (Figure 3B, SI-1 vs SI-<lb/>10/13/15, p &lt; 0.01; SI-4 vs SI-10/13/15 p &lt; 0.05), though still lower than neuronal numbers in <lb/>ChAT-Cre mice. In the colon, the ratio of myenteric and submucosal neurons did not differ <lb/>between ChAT + and TH + cells (Figure S2D). Our findings validate results from previous IHC <lb/>studies (Anlauf et al., 2003), but expand on the methods and throughput of quantification and <lb/>normalization such that global characterization is made possible. For example, the large number <lb/>of existing neuron-specific Cre-expressing mouse lines and disease models affords tremendous <lb/>opportunities for future use of this versatile system. These data reveal that spatial localization of <lb/>enteric neurons is determined by neuronal subpopulation, suggesting that these mouse models <lb/>could be utilized to interrogate the functional differences between neuronal cell types. <lb/>Activation of ChAT + and TH + Neurons in the GI Tract Alters the Intestinal Transcriptome <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>The unique spatial organization of ChAT + and TH + neurons suggests potentially distinct <lb/>functional properties, which can be investigated through cell-specific activation of each neuronal <lb/>subpopulation. ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice were infected with Cre-dependent genetic <lb/>constructs encoding activating &apos;Designer Receptors Exclusively Activated by Designer Drugs&apos; or <lb/>DREADDs (AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-hM3Dq-mRuby2). hM3Dq is a modified neurotransmitter <lb/>receptor that is designed to induce neuronal activation when exposed to Compound 21 (C21), a <lb/>&quot;designer drug&quot; that activates only this receptor (Thompson et al., 2018). Accordingly, C21 <lb/>induces a long calcium transient in a Cre-expressing neuron, as shown by the gradual increase <lb/>in GCaMP6F fluorescence in an intestinal explant (Figure 3D), validating the approach. <lb/>ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice were infected with activating DREADDs or a control virus <lb/>expressing a reporter protein instead (AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-mRuby2). C21 was <lb/>administered intraperitoneally (i.p.), once daily for 10 consecutive days to all mice (Figure 3E). <lb/>One hour following the last C21 injection, 1cm of tissue from the distal SI and proximal colon <lb/>was harvested, and gene expression profiled by QuantSeq, a quantitative 3&apos; mRNA-sequencing <lb/>technology. In neurons, the rapid and transient expression of immediate early genes (IEGs) is <lb/>widely used as a measure of increased neural activity (Wu et al., 2017). Accordingly, the IEGs <lb/>Fos, Egr1, Jun, Klf2 (Figures 3F-3I) were among the most significantly upregulated transcripts in <lb/>the SI and colon of both ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice harboring the activating DREADD (Figure <lb/>3J). Moreover, IEGs are known to be upregulated during growth and differentiation of highly <lb/>active cell types such as immune cells (Bahrami and Drabløs, 2016; Ramirez-Carrozzi et al., <lb/>2009), smooth muscle cells (Miano et al., 1993), and intestinal epithelial cells (Flandez et al., <lb/>2008). <lb/>In the distal SI, DREADD activation produced similar numbers of differentially expressed genes <lb/>(DEGs; p adj. &lt;0.05) in ChAT-Cre mice (162 DEGs) (Figure 3F) and TH-Cre mice (165 DEGs) <lb/>(Figure 3H). Interestingly however, ~73% of the DEGs were upregulated upon ChAT-Cre <lb/>activation (118 up, 44 down) and only ~42% of the DEGs were upregulated upon TH-Cre <lb/>activation (69 up, 96 down). This parallels the number of upregulated IEGs in the distal SI of <lb/>ChAT-Cre mice (29 IEGs) compared to those in TH-Cre mice (2 IEGs) (Figure 3J), with a few <lb/>IEGs (i.e., Hbegf, Soca3, Mcl1) actually being downregulated in TH-Cre mice (Figure 3H). As <lb/>previously mentioned, acetylcholine is a major excitatory neurotransmitter released from <lb/>cholinergic neurons, however their role in gene regulation has not been extensively <lb/>characterized. Furthermore, prior studies have reported that TH+ neurons are sparsely <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>distributed in the small intestine (Li et al., 2011) which could contribute towards the observed <lb/>decrease of upregulated genes, but as will described shortly, it appears there the gene <lb/>ontologies of regulated transcripts are functionally distinct. Similar proportions of transcripts <lb/>were upregulated in the proximal colon of both ChAT-Cre (253 DEGs-169 up, 84 down) (Figure <lb/>3G) and TH-Cre mice (192 DEGs -130 up, 62 down) (Figure 3I). <lb/>Gene Set Enrichment Analysis (GSEA) was employed to identify differences in gene ontology <lb/>(GO) annotations between treatment groups (Figures 3K-N and Table S1), providing insight into <lb/>cellular function. Notably, the most highly enriched GO term in the distal SI of ChAT-Cre mice <lb/>was &quot;regulation of smooth muscle cell proliferation&quot; (Figure 3K), whereas in TH-Cre mice it was <lb/>the &quot;response to bacteria&quot; (Figure 3M). In the proximal colon, we observed more similarity in GO <lb/>pathways between ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice following DREADD-mediated activation (Figures <lb/>3L and 3N). These gene expression profiles support the implication that spatial localization may <lb/>drive distinct transcriptomic signatures depending on the neurons activated (see Figures 3A-<lb/>3C), i.e., ChAT + neurons in the myenteric plexus of the SI are adjacent to muscle cells, while <lb/>TH + neurons in the distal SI are enriched in the submucosal plexus that neighbor epithelial and <lb/>immune cells which respond to bacteria. Both neuronal subsets are abundant in the myenteric <lb/>plexus of the colon (see Figure 3B). Also, the pathways upregulated where neurons exist in both <lb/>myenteric and submucosal plexuses, portray a wider breadth of changes than activation of TH + <lb/>neurons, with ChAT + neuronal activation impacting diverse cellular functions that take place in <lb/>the GI tract, involving endothelial, epithelial, immune, and adipose cells (Figure 3L and Table <lb/>S1). While recent studies have employed single-cell RNAseq technologies to profile <lb/>transcriptomes of ENS neurons (Drokhlyansky et al., 2020) the power to selectively activate <lb/>specific enteric neurons will open new avenues to interrogate the dynamic interplay between <lb/>cells of various lineages in the gut. <lb/>Neural Activation in the Gut Alters the Proteome of Mice and their Microbiota <lb/>Molecules from the mouse, gut microbes, and diet converge and interact in the GI tract <lb/>(Albenberg and Wu, 2014). To determine how activation of specific neuronal subsets impacts <lb/>the gut environment, we performed untargeted label-free proteomics on cell-free supernatants <lb/>of cecal contents from ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, with and without neuronal activation by <lb/>DREADDs. Cecal contents were assayed because the molecular changes that occur in the <lb/>upper GI tract will accrue in the cecum and will determine the environment that microbes in the <lb/>colon are exposed to. Material from the cecum (a compartment at the juncture of the SI and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>colon) were collected one hour following the final C21 treatment (see Figure 3E), and analyzed <lb/>by liquid chromatography / tandem mass spectrometry (LC-MS/MS). Interestingly, the <lb/>abundance of Niemann-Pick C1-Like 1 protein (NPCL1) is increased in the cecum of activated <lb/>ChAT-Cre mice. NPCL1 is expressed on the apical surface of enterocytes (Jia et al., 2011) and <lb/>is an integral protein involved in the absorption of free cholesterol from the lumen, the precursor <lb/>of bile acids. Goblet-cell related proteins also trended upwards, specifically Mucin-19 (MUC19) <lb/>and Zymogen granule 16 (ZG16) (Figure 4A), a protein localized to secretory granules <lb/>(Rodríguez-Piñeiro et al., 2013). Conversely, one of the most highly downregulated proteins <lb/>was an aldehyde dehydrogenase (Q3U367) encoded by the Aldh9A1 gene, which is involved in <lb/>the catalytic conversion of putrescine to gamma-aminobutyric acid (GABA) (Matsushima et al., <lb/>1986). Little is known about the role of GABA in the ENS and studies have alluded that they <lb/>may have a excitatory role (Hyland and Cryan, 2010), contrary to its inhibitory role in the brain. It <lb/>is intriguing to speculate that the induced cholinergic signaling in this activation model may lead <lb/>to the downregulation of non-cholinergic excitatory signaling pathways in the GI tract. <lb/>Pancreatic digestive enzymes were the most significantly upregulated proteins in cecal contents <lb/>of ChAT-activated mice (Figure 4A). These include chymopasin (CTRL), chymotrypsinogen 1 <lb/>(CTRB1), and pancreatic lipase related protein 2 (PNLIPRP2). Accordingly, network analysis of <lb/>upregulated proteins revealed that KEGG pathways associated with digestion represent the <lb/>majority of the network (Figure 4B). This novel finding is consistent with evidence that <lb/>cholinergic, viscerofugal neurons send signals from the GI tract to other organs of the digestive <lb/>system, including the pancreas (Furness et al., 2014). <lb/>Activation of TH + neurons also altered the luminal proteome of the cecum. Interestingly, 88% <lb/>(52/59) of the differentially abundant proteins (p adj. &lt;0.25, p nom&lt; 0.021) are distinct from those <lb/>identified in activated ChAT-Cre mice (p adj. &lt;0.25, p nom&lt; 0.042). Also 90% of these proteins were <lb/>upregulated (53/59), whereas only 18% of proteins in ChAT-Cre mice were upregulated <lb/>(20/112), suggesting that activation of distinct neuronal subsets is associated with largely <lb/>distinct changes in GI function. We observed signatures of increased protein-protein interactions <lb/>in cecal contents of activated TH-Cre mice, evidenced by more network nodes and connections <lb/>(Figures 4C and 4D). When TH + neurons are activated, Filamin B (FLNB) and spectrin beta <lb/>chain, non-erythrocytic 1 (SPTB2) were two of the most significantly enriched proteins (Figure <lb/>4C), and both are associated with the intestinal brush border and membrane vesicles (Donowitz <lb/>et al., 2007; McConnell et al., 2011). Accordingly, vesicle-mediated transport was a major <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>protein network we identified (Figure 4D) and relatedly, coatomer proteins also trended upward <lb/>(COPA and COPB2) (Figure 4C). Other enriched protein interaction networks that emerged <lb/>were associated with the immune system, metabolic pathways, and ribosomes (Figure 4D). For <lb/>example, immune related proteins such as immunoglobulin A (IgA) (in ChAT-Cre) and IgG2b <lb/>and complement component C3 (in TH-Cre) trended upward (Figure 4A and 4C), results that <lb/>are in accord with the immune-related biological processes identified by gene expression after <lb/>neuronal activation (see Figure 3). <lb/>Perhaps the most intriguing observation was the strong depletion of acidic mammalian chitinase <lb/>(CHIA) upon activation of TH + neurons (Figure 4C). Chitin is a natural polysaccharide that <lb/>comprises a major component of fungal cell walls (Latgé, 2007). Intestinal chitinases are poorly <lb/>studied in mice and CHIA has not been investigated for its role in regulating fungal populations. <lb/>Because our samples contain host and microbial proteins, this result prompted us to search our <lb/>dataset against microbial protein databases. Remarkably, the decrease in CHIA abundance <lb/>following TH + neuron activation was accompanied by a large bloom in the proportion of fungal-<lb/>associated peptides in the microbiome (representing ~59% of peptides mapped to any microbe) <lb/>(Figure 4E). In contrast, fungal peptides represented only ~0.4% of enriched peptides in the <lb/>lumen of activated ChAT-Cre mice (Figure 4F). We propose that reduction of chitinase <lb/>production by activated TH + cells is directly associated with the observed dramatic increase in <lb/>fungal proteins, and if true, would represent a novel circuit by which mice regulate fungal loads <lb/>in the gut. <lb/>Taken together, profiling the gut luminal proteome upon neuronal activation revealed intriguing <lb/>molecular dynamics occurring at the interface of the GI tract and the environment, and provided <lb/>initial glimpses into processes such as digestion and novel host-microbe interactions. Neuron-<lb/>mediated responses in the gut are likely vast and complex, and continued research promises to <lb/>uncover the breadth of changes that can result from activation of specific neuronal <lb/>subpopulations in the ENS. <lb/>Activation of ENS Neurons Reshapes the Gut Microbiome <lb/>Given the observed changes in the gut proteome, including proteins of microbial origin, we <lb/>reasoned that neuronal activation in the ENS may impact the composition and community <lb/>structure of the gut microbiome. For example, digestive enzymes alter the luminal nutrient <lb/>composition, altering metabolism for the host (Whitcomb and Lowe, 2007) and the gut <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>microbiome (Nishiyama et al., 2018). Also, changes to the intestinal immune response affect the <lb/>localization, diversity and abundance of microbial species in the GI tract (Donaldson et al., <lb/>2018; 2015; Zhang et al., 2015). While future work will be required to determine how ENS <lb/>activation impacts gut bacterial communities, we profiled the microbiome via shotgun <lb/>metagenomics from a longitudinal collection of fecal samples prior to and following ChAT + or <lb/>TH + neuron activation (pre-C21 samples, and at days 1, 5, and 9 after initial C21 dose) and <lb/>cecal contents (10 days after initial dose) (see Figure 3E). In ChAT-Cre mice, Faith&apos;s <lb/>phylogenetic diversity (i.e., alpha-diversity) decreased dramatically by day 9 in the feces and <lb/>also in the terminal cecum sample (day 10) (Figure 5A), an outcome supported by the large <lb/>number of microbial taxa that are less abundant in samples from ChAT + neuron activated mice <lb/>(Figures S3 and S4). In contrast, TH-Cre mice displayed similar phylogenetic diversity after <lb/>activation, though there is a trend toward decreased diversity from pre-C21 to day 5 that <lb/>recovers by day 9 in the feces (Figure 5A). In concordance with signatures of increased protein <lb/>digestion in ChAT-Cre mice (see Figure 4B), heightened fecal protease activity has been <lb/>associated with reduced microbiome diversity (Carroll et al., 2013). The composition of microbial <lb/>communities was determined using weighted UniFrac (i.e., beta-diversity): distances were <lb/>calculated and principle coordinate analyses (PCoA) were performed. There is separation <lb/>between control and activated animal groups in the feces and cecal contents of ChAT-Cre mice, <lb/>a shift that was largely absent in samples from TH-Cre mice (Figure 5B-5G). Interestingly, over <lb/>the experimental time course, Verrucomicrobia were significantly enriched in activated ChAT-<lb/>Cre mice (Figure 5H). To discover differentially abundant bacterial taxa, we used linear <lb/>discriminant analysis effect size (LEfSe) (Segata et al., 2011) and then visualized the data into <lb/>cladograms depicting the phylogenetic relationship of differentially abundant taxa (Figure 5I and <lb/>5K). Family level changes to cecal bacterial communities are displayed in Figures 5J and 5L for <lb/>ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, respectively. The bacterial species Akkermansia muciniphila <lb/>appears to drive the increase in Verrucomicrobia in activated ChAT-Cre mice (Figure 5M) but <lb/>not in TH-Cre mice (Figure 5N). A. muciniphila metabolizes host-derived mucus as a nutrient <lb/>source (Derrien et al., 2004; Van Herreweghen et al., 2017), consistent with the increase in <lb/>luminal mucin proteins (MUC19) or digestive enzymes in activated ChAT-Cre mice (see Figure <lb/>4A). A. muciniphila is implicated in many diseases, such as obesity (Everard et al., 2013; Plovier <lb/>et al., 2017), multiple sclerosis (Cekanaviciute et al., 2017; Jangi et al., 2016), and seizures <lb/>(Olson et al., 2018). Various additional associations can be postulated for ENS -microbiome <lb/>interactions from this dataset. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Beyond species assignment, metagenomic analysis reveals gene families and pathways that <lb/>are differentially abundant in the microbiome. Only ChAT-Cre mice showed activation-mediated <lb/>changes in beta-diversity of both gene families and pathways (Figures 5O-5R), and these shifts <lb/>occurred in the cecum and feces collected 9 days after activation. The most distinguishing <lb/>features were highly represented in the control groups and downregulated in activated ChAT-<lb/>Cre mice. The families and pathways that distinguish the groups (Figures S4C and S4D) were <lb/>mainly associated with bacterial activity, such as nucleotide biosynthesis and metabolism, and <lb/>protein translation and transport. The downregulation of these gene families and pathways in <lb/>activated ChAT-Cre mice supports the corresponding decreases in bacterial alpha-diversity (see <lb/>Figure 5A). We conclude that neuronal activation actively reshapes the gut microbiome at <lb/>community-, species-, and genetic-level resolutions, with considerable differences in effects <lb/>between ChAT + or TH + subpopulations. Potential mechanisms that mediate influences by the <lb/>ENS on gut bacterial composition include altered intestinal motility, regulation of immune <lb/>response, control of mucus production, shifts in metabolism / nutrient availability, among others. <lb/>Metabolomic Changes in the Gut Upon Neural Stimulation <lb/>Having characterized outcomes of neuronal activation on DNA (microbial metagenome), RNA <lb/>(host transcriptome), and protein (host and microbial proteome), we reasoned that a major <lb/>impact of these changes may manifest in the profile of gut metabolites. Mouse and microbial co-<lb/>metabolism represents an intimate and intertwined relationship with implications to health. Via <lb/>untargeted metabolomics using LC-MS/MS, we assayed detailed molecular changes in cecal <lb/>contents and feces following neuronal activation in the gut. In ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, we <lb/>observed a strong, activation-dependent clustering of metabolome profiles in cecal samples <lb/>taken one hour following the last C21 injection (Figures 6A and 6B). In longitudinal fecal <lb/>samples of ChAT-Cre mice, we observed separation of metabolomes between control and <lb/>activated groups by day 5 of C21 injection, a state that persisted until day 9 (Figures 6C-6F). In <lb/>TH-Cre fecal samples, data were plotted on axes that minimized experimental bias from an <lb/>apparent batch effect (see Methods), revealing differences between metabolomes of control and <lb/>TH + neuronal activation over time (Figures 6G-6J). Furthermore, there is clear separation in <lb/>cecal metabolites in ChAT-Cre versus TH-Cre mice, upon activation (Figures S5A and S5B), <lb/>and such separation occurs in the feces by Day 9 of the activation time course (Figures S5C-<lb/>S5F). Thus, targeted activation of ChAT + and TH + neurons in the ENS strongly influences the <lb/>global gut metabolome. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>The Global Natural Products Social Molecular Networking (GNPS) (Wang et al., 2016) tool is an <lb/>open-access mass spectroscopy repository and analysis pipeline that we employed to visualize <lb/>and contextualize our data. Molecular networks were generated based on MS2 spectral <lb/>similarities of small molecules and their analogs by querying both unannotated and annotated <lb/>features (via spectral matches against all public reference spectral libraries and the purchased <lb/>NIST17 CID library). In the cecal contents of ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, metabolic networks <lb/>consisting of both annotated and unannotated molecules were revealed (Figures 6K and 6L). <lb/>Annotated, non-networked metabolites were chosen for their differential abundance in either <lb/>control or activated samples. Specifically, in TH-Cre mice, there were strongly increased non-<lb/>networked metabolites in activated mice whose closest spectral matches are linoelaidic acid (ID: <lb/>626), oleanolic acid methyl ester (ID: 378), and coproporphyrin I (ID: 739). Metabolites that <lb/>spectrally resemble xanthine (ID: 259), genistein (ID: 846), and trans-Ferulic acid (ID: 707) were <lb/>decreased upon activation (Figure 6K and Table S2). <lb/>In both ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, the molecular networks largely consisted of level 3 <lb/>annotations (based on the Metabolomics Standards Initiative (MSI) (Sumner et al., 2007)) of <lb/>compounds belonging to the bile acid molecular family and their conjugates, as well as <lb/>unannotated analogs. Primary bile acids are host (mouse) derived chemicals from cholesterol <lb/>biosynthesis, which are subsequently metabolized by gut bacteria into secondary bile acids <lb/>(Aries et al., 1969; Sakai et al., 1980). Interestingly, metabolites with their closest spectral match <lb/>to the primary bile acid cholic acid (ID: 108, 114, 215, 219, 221, 224, 259) were significantly <lb/>enriched in the cecum of activated ChAT-Cre mice (Figures 6L-6N and Table S2). Additional <lb/>metabolites that closely resemble the spectra of tauro-conjugated primary bile acids trended <lb/>upwards, such as taurocholic acid (ID: 234, 238) and taurohyocholic acid (ID: 235). Conversely, <lb/>features with spectral matches to the family of secondary bile acids and bile acid metabolites <lb/>such as ursodeoxycholic acid (ID: 13), deoxycholic acid (ID: 100), beta-hyodeoxycholic acid (ID: <lb/>1, 143) and 12-ketodeoxycholic acid (ID: 19, 138) were decreased in ChAT + -activated mice <lb/>(Figures 6L-6N). These data suggest that activation of ChAT + neurons may modulate primary <lb/>bile acids secretion, either directly or indirectly, and/or their metabolism to secondary bile acids <lb/>via the observed decrease in microbial alpha-diversity observed in ChAT-Cre mice (see Figure <lb/>5A). <lb/>While additional examples of host-microbial co-metabolism were detected (Table S2), the <lb/>intriguing pathway alterations in bile acids following activation of ChAT + neurons may have <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>critical influences on various host physiologies and health. For example, bile acids and their <lb/>metabolites have historically been studied for their essential role in digesting dietary fats and <lb/>regulating the absorption of lipids (de Aguiar Vallim et al., 2013) and thus have been a <lb/>pharmacological target for nonalcoholic fatty liver diseases (e.g., NASH) (Gottlieb and Canbay, <lb/>2019). Bile acids regulate intestinal immune responses (Fiorucci et al., 2018; Ichikawa et al., <lb/>2012; Vavassori et al., 2009) and the production of neurotransmitters by gut enterochromaffin <lb/>cells (Yano et al., 2015). Expression of bile salt hydrolases and hydratases increases the fitness <lb/>of both commensal and pathogenic bacteria (Begley et al., 2005; Delpino et al., 2007; Hofmann <lb/>and Eckmann, 2006; Jones et al., 2008; Sannasiddappa et al., 2017). Recently, taurocholate, a <lb/>bile acid that induces expression of virulence genes in enteric pathogens, and its metabolism by <lb/>the human microbiota has been linked to susceptibility and resistance to infection (Alavi et al., <lb/>2020). These extensive and important functions attributed to bile acids had not previously been <lb/>known to be regulated by ChAT + neurons in the gut, a discovery herein that may have broad <lb/>implications on nutrition, metabolism, immunity, neurotransmission, and infection. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Modern systems neuroscience is primarily and appropriately focused on studying structures and <lb/>functions of cells within the brain, a complexity that is being interrogated through the advent of <lb/>novel tools that go beyond characterization and are able to activate and inhibit specific neuronal <lb/>functions with precision. Curiously, many disorders of the brain are associated with <lb/>gastrointestinal symptoms (Bhavsar et al., 2013; Cersosimo et al., 2013; Del Giudice et al., <lb/>1999; Pfeiffer, 2003; Valicenti-McDermott et al., 2008). While mechanisms linking the gut and <lb/>the brain, and their consequences to health, are an active area of study, the impact of neuronal <lb/>activation within the ENS on organs and tissues throughout the body has largely been <lb/>unexplored. Knowledge of many aspects of neuronal architecture and function within the gut <lb/>remain rudimentary (Carabotti et al., 2015; Furness et al., 2014). Historically, and paradoxically, <lb/>early pioneers of neuroscience in the 20 th century used the ENS as a model for studying the <lb/>nervous system, an approach that fell out of favor in lieu of brain research. Accordingly, our <lb/>understanding of brain function, while still limited, has outpaced research into the neuronal <lb/>systems of the gut. The current study embarked on adapting and optimizing recent tools <lb/>developed for brain research to explore the gut environment. To date, broad histological <lb/>characterization of the ENS has been restricted by the limitations of antibody-based labeling <lb/>approaches (Walsh and Zemper, 2019). Viral-mediated expression allows for vast infectivity of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>enteric neurons with a single systemic injection, without the use of transgenic animals, and <lb/>facilitates histology of large, complex, and dynamic tissues such as the small intestine and colon <lb/>of mice. The delivery of neuron-specific activation tools to the gut enables precise interrogation <lb/>of ENS function with remarkable spatial and temporal resolution. <lb/>Using a viral delivery system with enhanced tropism for the ENS to achieve cell-specific <lb/>expression of fluorescent proteins, merged with the power of tissue clearing approaches that <lb/>allow 3D preservation of tissue, we report neuronal architectures of the myenteric plexus and <lb/>submucosal plexus within the same tissue preparation. The ability to simultaneously image <lb/>these neuronal compartments enabled thorough analysis of the ENS is a robust and <lb/>reproducible manner. Furthermore, in assaying specific neuronal sub-populations, namely <lb/>ChAT + and TH + neurons, longitudinally variances along the gut and within each plexus were <lb/>identified. This finding suggests differences in functions between neurons of different classes. <lb/>Further, delivery of a calcium-based activity marker allowed recording of ENS neuronal firings in <lb/>live, anesthetized animals. These early discoveries highlight the tremendous complexity of the <lb/>ENS, and equip researchers with tools and approaches to further dissect structure-function <lb/>relationships within the gut nervous system. Future deployment of these technologies can <lb/>enable efforts to map neuronal innervations into and out of the gut, providing insights into how <lb/>the ENS networks with tissues throughout the body. <lb/>The AAV systems we used are versatile in terms of the cargo they can deliver to the ENS, a <lb/>feature that was leveraged to express activating DREADDs in specific neuronal subpopulations. <lb/>Although the activation paradigm used in this study is inherently an artificial system, it provides <lb/>a versatile framework to study the cellular and molecular interactions in the GI tract that are <lb/>mediated by the ENS and impact health and disease. We reveal that chronic activation of <lb/>ChAT + or TH + neurons in the ENS of mice altered the intestinal transcriptome and impacted <lb/>gene expression in pathways associated with gut motility, angiogenesis, absorption, epithelial <lb/>cell function, mucosal immunity / anti-microbial responses, among others. Upon targeted <lb/>activation of ChAT + or TH + neurons in the gut, we observed changes in genetic signatures <lb/>reminiscent of numerous cell types, highlighting the integration of signals from neurons to a <lb/>variety of other cells in the gut. Single-cell analysis may further refine connections between the <lb/>ENS and the varied lineages of intestinal cells that collaborate to coordinate gut functions. <lb/>Ostensibly, extensive exposure to the outside environment requires that the intestines are <lb/>charged with myriad of responsibilities including digestion and absorption of dietary nutrients, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>exclusion of xenobiotics, protection from enteric infection, and partnership with the gut <lb/>microbiome. Indeed, we observed differences in the compositional profile of the gut microbiome <lb/>between mice with activation of ChAT + versus TH + neurons, at the proteomic and metagenomic <lb/>levels. Of note, others have shown that deletion of ChAT in enteric neurons leads to microbiome <lb/>dysbiosis (Johnson et al., 2018). Our study does not resolve how ENS activation reshapes the <lb/>gut microbial community structure, which may involve altered colonic motility, changes in mucus <lb/>production, and / or modulation of mucosal immune responses. One interesting host-microbial <lb/>interaction appears to emerge upon activation of TH + cells, which leads to a dramatic decrease <lb/>in anti-fungal chitinase (CHIA) protein expression and a concomitant bloom in fungi, suggesting <lb/>that neuronal circuits regulate fungal populations in the gut. Several other hypotheses can be <lb/>proposed based on our dataset for potential mechanisms by which the ENS can affect the gut <lb/>microbiome, largely through changes to the luminal molecular environment, and also the <lb/>possible consequences of these interactions. <lb/>The human gut microbiome possesses the metabolic capacity of the liver, and thus changes to <lb/>both mouse gut physiology and the microbiome predictably have major influences on the gut <lb/>metabolome. In a striking example of mutualism, we report widespread changes to the pool of <lb/>intestinal bile acids, molecules produced via host-microbial co-metabolism. Activation of ChAT + <lb/>neurons impact expression of NPCL1 which is involved in cholesterol transport, and cholesterol <lb/>is the substrate for production of primary bile acids by mammals, which are then metabolized <lb/>exclusively by the gut microbiome into secondary bile acids. Bile acids play critical roles in fat <lb/>absorption (de Aguiar Vallim et al., 2013), gut motility (Kirwan et al., 1975), hormonal signaling <lb/>(Watanabe et al., 2006) and immune functions (Fiorucci et al., 2018), and changes in their <lb/>profiles have been associated with various disorders including neurological conditions (McMillin <lb/>and DeMorrow, 2016). While additional work is required to determine how the ENS affects <lb/>levels and constitution of the bile acid pool, understanding the processes that regulate synthesis <lb/>of secondary bile acids may conceivably have implications on a number of organ systems <lb/>throughout the body. <lb/>In the brain, experiential stimuli motivate neural plasticity and learning, and this defines the <lb/>network by which information is propagated from one neuron to another, resulting in <lb/>physiological or behavioral outputs (Bruel-Jungerman et al., 2016). Similarly in the GI tract, the <lb/>ENS adapts and responds to incredibly diverse molecular cues from the environment and must <lb/>do so throughout the entire length and surface area of the intestines-the largest and most <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>expansive internal organ with a rich network of neurons termed the &quot;second brain&quot; (Gershon, <lb/>2015). Exposures to molecules from the diet or the microbiome may modulate ENS function, <lb/>along with extrinsic signals from outside the gut, a topic not covered here but of great <lb/>significance. As a companion to ongoing brain research, the novel experimental tools, empiric <lb/>datasets, and conceptual advances provided by this Resource study may stimulate research <lb/>into the enteric nervous system, an endeavor with broad consequences to human health. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We thank members in the Mazmanian&apos;s laboratory for discussions throughout the research and <lb/>critical reading of the manuscript. We thank Dr. Andres Collazo and Caltech&apos;s Biological <lb/>Imaging Facility for training access to microscopy capabilities and the Caltech Proteome <lb/>Exploration Laboratory for access to LC-MS/MS capabilities. This work was supported by grants <lb/>from the Heritage Medical Research Institute, Emerald Foundation, Caltech Center for <lb/>Environmental and Microbial Interactions (CEMI), Aligning Science Across Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>Foundation, the National Institutes of Health (GM007616 and DK078938), and the Department <lb/>of Defense (PD160030). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>B.B.Y. and S.K.M. designed experiments. B.B.Y performed experiments. J.A.G., K.Y.C., C.C. <lb/>(supervised by V.G.) helped in AAV-mediated ENS characterization. J.A.G. performed analysis <lb/>of GCaMP6F fluorescence. P.T.B (supervised by D.W.W.), M.J.S., A.M. performed acquisition <lb/>and analysis of proteomic data. V.C., G.H., G.S., Q.Z., J.S., and (supervised by R.K.) performed <lb/>acquisition and analysis of metagenomic data. K.W. (supervised by P.C.D.) performed <lb/>acquisition and analysis of metabolomic data. T.M.T. assisted in animal-related work. B.B.Y. <lb/>and S.K.M wrote the manuscript with input from all authors. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>MAIN FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Figure 1. Advantages of Viral labeling in the ENS <lb/>(A) Viral-mediated expression of nuclear localized (NLS) GFP driven by the ubiquitous CAG <lb/>promoter. Quantification of virally labelled cells in AAV9 vs. AAV-PHP.S in the longitudinal <lb/>muscle, myenteric plexus, and circular muscle of the stomach. (N=4-5 mice, each data point <lb/>represents the average from 3 representative fields). <lb/>(B) Representative images of SI and colon in mice infected with AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-TdTomato <lb/>and immunolabelled with the pan-neuronal antibody, PGP9.5. Inset: quantification of the ratio of <lb/>TdTomato + cells / PGP9.5 + cells (N=3 mice, each data point represents the average from 3 <lb/>representative fields). <lb/>(C) Tiled, whole mount microscopy showing widespread labelling in the proximal colon (&gt;1cm of <lb/>tissue) from a single injection (10 12 VGs-vector containing AAVs). Yellow inset highlights regions <lb/>opposite from the mesenteric attachment; pink inset highlights a central region of the tissue. <lb/>(D) Left: Antibody-labelled myenteric plexus of the proximal colon. Right: Viral-mediated <lb/>multicolor labelling of a comparable region. AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-<lb/>(mTurq2/mNeonGreen/mRuby2) (AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-XFP, 3e 11 VGs each). <lb/>(E) High resolution confocal microscopy showing cell morphology when labelled with AAV-<lb/>PHP.S:hSYN1-(mTurq2/mNeonGreen/mRuby2) vs. traditional IHC with PGP9.5. <lb/>(F) Left: IHC with anti-PGP9.5 and anti-GFAP Right: Viral expression of AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-<lb/>mNeonGreen and AAV-PHP.S-GFAP-TdTomato <lb/>(G) PaCT tissue clearing coupled with multicolor labelling of the intestine, showing structural <lb/>and anatomical resolution in Z. <lb/>Figure 2. Quantifying ENS Architecture and Measuring ENS Activity with GCaMP6F <lb/>(A) Representative images from proximal and distal regions of the SI and colon from AAV-<lb/>PHP.S:hSYN1-XFP infected mice. Dotted lines demarcate the rugae (folds) in the proximal <lb/>large intestines. <lb/>(B-G) Quantification of neurons in 7 regions from the SI, and 2 regions from the colon, sampled <lb/>proximally to distally (N=3-4 mice per group, per intestinal region. Data points are averages <lb/>from 2-3 images per mouse, per region; *: p&lt;0.05, **: p&lt;0.01, ***: p&lt;0.001, ****: p&lt;0.001, 2-way <lb/>ANOVA with Sidak&apos;s multiple comparisons test) <lb/>(H) Experimental setup to capture GCaMP6F fluorescence in a live, anesthetized animal. <lb/>(I) Frequency distribution of calcium spike rate and (J) peak interval (Data was collected from <lb/>N=68 cells from 3 mice). <lb/>(K) Heatmap of GCaMP6F fluorescence (∆F/F) over time. Each row represents fluorescent time <lb/>course of a single cell. Data was cutoff at 83.64 seconds. <lb/>(L) Representative GCaMP6F fluorescent traces. <lb/>Figure 3. Characterizing Enteric ChAT-Cre + and TH-Cre + Neurons and Assaying <lb/>Activation-Mediated Transcriptomic Changes <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(A) Representative images from cross-sections (x-section), myenteric, and submucosal <lb/>plexuses in ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice infected with AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-XFP. <lb/>(B) Density of neurons in the myenteric plexus and (C) submucosal plexus of ChAT-Cre and <lb/>TH-Cre mice (N=3 mice, each data point represent the average from 3 representative fields, <lb/>ChAT-Cre vs. TH-Cre mice were compared using two-way ANOVAs with Sidak&apos;s correction for <lb/>multiple comparisons for the SI and LI independently; Comparison of different regions in the SI <lb/>of ChAT-Cre or TH-Cre mice were analyzed using one-way ANOVAs with Tukey&apos;s correction for <lb/>multiple comparisons) <lb/>(D) Fluorescence time course of GCaMP6F in an ex vivo preparation of ChAT-Cre SI following <lb/>C21 administration. <lb/>(E) Experimental paradigm-10 consecutive days of C21 injections, with feces sampled in <lb/>between and tissue and cecal contents collected at the end. <lb/>(F-I) Volcano plots of differentially expressed genes in DREADD Activated vs Control, in (F) <lb/>ChAT-Cre distal SI, (G) ChAT proximal colon, (H) TH-Cre distal SI, and (I) TH-Cre proximal <lb/>colon. (Dotted vertical: Fold Change (FC)=+/-1.5; Dotted horizontal: p adj. &lt;0.05. Annotated <lb/>transcripts are IEGs and are highlighted in green. N=10 mice per group) <lb/>(J) Fold changes of upregulated IEGs (p adj. &lt;0.05) as defined by Wu et al. 2017 (J-M) Gene set <lb/>enrichment analysis of gene ontology (GO) terms for (K) ChAT-Cre distal SI, (L) ChAT proximal <lb/>colon, (M) TH-Cre distal SI, and (N) TH-Cre proximal colon. <lb/>Figure 4. ENS Activation Alters Host and Microbe-Derived Luminal Proteins <lb/>(A) Volcano plot of differentially expressed host proteins identified in the cecal contents of <lb/>Activated ChAT (N=8) vs. Control ChAT mice (N=9 mice), 1 hour after C21 administration. <lb/>(B) STRING network analysis of host proteins that were more abundant in ChAT-activated mice <lb/>(p nom.&lt; 0.2). <lb/>(C) Proteomic volcano plots of TH-activated vs. TH-control mice (N=7 mice per group) after C21 <lb/>administration (D) STRING network analysis of upregulated host proteins in TH-activated mice <lb/>(p nom.&lt; 0.2). <lb/>(E-F) Unipept metaproteomic analysis of upregulated microbial proteins (p nom.&lt; 0.2) in activated <lb/>(E) TH and (F) ChAT-Cre mice (N=7-9 mice per group). <lb/>Figure 5. ENS Activation Alters the Microbiome <lb/>(A) Faith&apos;s phylogenetic diversity of feces and cecal contents over 10 days of neural activation in <lb/>ChAT-and TH-Cre mice. Pre (1 day before first injection), Post +1/5/9 (1, 5, 9 days after first <lb/>injection), Post +10 (Cecal contents collected at experimental endpoint) (**p&lt;0.01, ***p&lt;0.001 <lb/>determined by Kruskal-Wallis one-way ANOVA). <lb/>(B-G) Weighted UniFrac principle coordinate analysis (PCoA) of Activated vs. Control in ChAT-<lb/>and TH-Cre mice with PERMANOVA p-values and pseudo-F statistics analyses were performed <lb/>in QIIME2 as done previously (Bolyen et al., 2019). <lb/>(H) Stacked bar graph showing phylum-level changes in relative abundance, 5 and 9 days post-<lb/>injection in feces and 10 days post-injection in cecal contents. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(I-L) Cecal Microbiome LDA Effect Size (LEfSe) Analysis: (I,K) Cladograms showing differential <lb/>phylogenetic clusters and (J,L) LDA plots of family-level differences between Activated and <lb/>Control mice (Cutoff: log 10 (LDA Score)&gt;2 or &lt;-2) in (I,J) ChAT-Cre and (K,L) TH-Cre mice. <lb/>(M-N) Changes in relative abundance of Akkermansia muciniphila in feces and cecal contents of <lb/>(M) ChAT-Cre and (N) TH-Cre mice. (n=11-14 mice per group, per time point; red=Control, <lb/>green=hM3Dq-Activated, *p&lt;0.05, **p&lt;0.01, significance determined by multiple t-tests with <lb/>Holm-Sidak correction for multiple comparisons) <lb/>(O-R) Beta-diversity of bacterial gene families and pathways in the (O-Q) cecum and (P-R) post-<lb/>9 feces of control and activated mice. Beta-diversity was determined with Robust Aitchison <lb/>Principle Component Anaylsis (PCA) and analyzed using the DEICODE toolbox. The direction <lb/>of defining features is indicated with colored arrows. The colors of the arrows represent different <lb/>gene families and pathways and their length and direction is indicative of the influence that each <lb/>feature has on the separation of control and activated groups. These gene families and <lb/>pathways are annotated by the color of the feature arrow (Figure S4C and S4D). <lb/>Figure 6. ENS Activation Alters the Host and Microbe-Derived Luminal Metabolites <lb/>(A) Canberra PoCA of the cell-free, luminal metabolome of control (red) and activated (green) <lb/>cecal contents in ChAT-Cre and (B) TH-Cre mice. Statistical analyses were performed in <lb/>QIIME2 as done previously (Bolyen et al., 2019) and axes for data visualization were chosen to <lb/>minimize experimental biases (See Methods). <lb/>(C-J) Fecal metabolome assayed at different timepoints before and after C21 administration in <lb/>(C-F) ChAT-Cre and (G-J) TH-Cre mice. Axes for data visualization were chosen to minimize <lb/>experimental biases (See Methods). <lb/>(K) Metabolic networks constructed from identified cecal metabolites in TH-Cre and (L) ChAT-<lb/>Cre mice. Each node is labelled with an ID number, corresponding to annotations, mass-to-<lb/>charge ratios, retention times, fold changes, and significance values found in Table S2. Each <lb/>node is colored by its upregulation (green) or downregulation (red) in activated groups. IDs in <lb/>bold text have an annotation in GNPS and are colored by classes class of metabolite (primary <lb/>bile acids, secondary bile acids, and other metabolites). <lb/>(M) Fold-changes of specific bile acids identified to be upregulated (green bars) and <lb/>downregulated (red bars) in activated ChAT-Cre mice. <lb/>(N) Annotations of bile acids highlighted in (M). Metabolite IDs corresponding to annotated <lb/>primary bile acids (blue type) and secondary bile acids (red type). Metabolite IDs are distinct by <lb/>genotype (N=12-14 for each group analyzed, *: p&lt;0.05, **: p&lt;0.01, ***: p&lt;0.001, ****: p&lt;0.0001) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTAL FIGURE LEGENDS <lb/>Supplemental Figure 1. Viral Labeling Enables a Holistic Understanding of the ENS <lb/>(Related to Figure 1) <lb/>(A-D) Tiled images of the ENS in the mouse SI. Mice are infected with AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-XFP <lb/>(B) Inset of panel (A) showing extrinsic nerves and neurons connecting to intrinsic ganglia of the <lb/>ENS (D) Inset of panel (C) showing alterations to ENS architecture surrounding intestinal <lb/>lymphoid follicles such as Peyer&apos;s patches (E-F) Tiled image of the ENS in the colon with insets <lb/>showing how the (F) absence or (G) presence of luminal contents changes the appearance of <lb/>neuronal density in the ENS. <lb/>Supplemental Figure 2. Similar Viral Transduction Along the GI Tract (Related to Figure 2 <lb/>and Figure 3B and 3C) <lb/>(A) Quantification (qPCR) of AAV transduction in different regions of the mouse SI and colon (B) <lb/>Diameter (μm) of intestinal crypts in SI and colon (N=3-4 mice per group) (C) Quantification of <lb/>total neurons normalized by the number of crypts (D) Quantification of myenteric : submucosal <lb/>cell ratio in ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice. This data is an alternate representation of what is seen <lb/>in Figure 3B and 3C (N=3 mice, each data point represents the average from 3 representative <lb/>fields; ChAT-Cre vs. TH-Cre mice were compared using two-way ANOVAs with Sidak&apos;s <lb/>correction for multiple comparisons for the SI and LI independently). <lb/>Supplemental Figure 3. Annotated changes to gut bacteria (Related to Figure 5) <lb/>(A,B) Species-levels differences in cecal bacteria corresponding to main text Figure 5I-5L. (A) <lb/>ChAT-Cre and (B) TH-Cre ceca, day 10 after initial C21 injection. <lb/>Supplemental Figure 4. ENS Activation-Mediated Changes in Feces (Related to Figure 5) <lb/>LEfSe Cladograms for feces on (A) Day 9 of ChAT-Cre mice and (B) Day 5 of TH-Cre mice. <lb/>Annotations are labelled in the tables below the cladogram (C and D) Microbial gene family and <lb/>pathway annotations for the defining features labelled on the DEICODE PCoA plots in Figure <lb/>5O-5R. Colors in ID column refer to the color of feature arrows labelled in main figure. <lb/>Supplemental Figure 5. Class Differences in ChAT-Cre vs. TH-Cre Metabolites Upon <lb/>Activation (Related to Figure 6) <lb/>Canberra PCoA analysis comparing activation-mediated changes to the (A-B) cecal and (C-F) <lb/>fecal metabolome in ChAT-Cre versus TH-Cre mice (A) Cecal metabolome of control mice (B) <lb/>Cecal metabolome of activated mice (C) Pre-C21 feces of control and (D) activated mice (E) <lb/>Fecal metabolome during activation time course for control and (F) activated mice. <lb/>Supplemental Table 1. Gene Set Enrichement Analysis of Gene Ontology (GO) Terms <lb/>(Related to Figure 3) <lb/>Gene set enrichment analysis of gene ontology (GO) terms that are upregulated in the distal SI <lb/>and proximal colon of activated ChAT-and TH-Cre mice. <lb/>Supplemental Table 2. Extended GNPS annotations of Metabolite Network Nodes <lb/>(Related to Figure 6) <lb/>Extended annotations for networked (bold), MS/MS spectra in cecal luminal contents-<lb/>corresponds to Figure 6K and 6L in ChAT-Cre and TH-Cre mice, respectively. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>METHODS <lb/>Mice <lb/>All mouse experiments were performed in accordance with the NIH Guide for the Care and Use <lb/>of Laboratory Animals using protocols approved by the Institutional Animal Care and Use <lb/>Committee at the California Institute of Technology. TH-Cre (from Viviana Gradinaru at Caltech. <lb/>Originally from Ted Ebendal B6.129X1-Thtm1(cre)Te/Kieg) (Lindeberg et al., 2004) and ChAT-<lb/>Cre mice (Jackson Laboratories, Bar Harbor, ME-Stock# 028861) were obtained from Jackson <lb/>Laboratories, and homozygous Cre-mice were bred to wild-type mice to yield male and female <lb/>heterozygous Cre-mice used for our studies. Wildtype specific pathogen free (SPF), C57BL/6 <lb/>(Jackson Laboratories, Bar Harbor, ME Stock #000664) males and females were used for <lb/>breeding and experiments. <lb/>Virus Production <lb/>Virus was produced using methods described in Challis et. al. (Challis et al., 2019) Briefly, <lb/>human embryonic kidney (HEK293T) cells were triple-transfected with pUCmini-iCAP-AAV-<lb/>PHP.S, pHelper Plasmid, and one of the following pAAV genomes (CAG-NLS-GFP, hSYN1-<lb/>tDTomato, GFAP-tDTomato, hSYN1-mRuby2, hSYN1-DiO-mRuby2, hSYN1-mNeonGreen, <lb/>hSYN1-DiO-mNeonGreen, hSYN1-mTurquoise2, hSYN1-DiO-mTurquoise2, hSYN1-DiO-<lb/>hM3Dq-mRuby2, CAG-GCaMP6F). Cells were grown in DMEM + Glutamax + Pyruvate (Gibco, <lb/>Gaithersburg, MD-Stock# 10569-010) + 5% FBS + non-essential amino acids (Gibco, <lb/>Gaithersburg, MD-Stock# 11140-050), penicillin-streptomycin (Gibco, Gaithersburg, MD-<lb/>Stock# 15070-063). Virus is precipitated from cells and supernatant with an 8% PEG solution <lb/>(wt/vol), and purified by ultracentrifugation using 15%, 25%, 40%, 60% stacked iodixanol <lb/>gradients. <lb/>Systemic Delivery of AAV-Titers <lb/>Mice were anesthetized using 2% isoflurane. Virus was titered to 10 12 VGs, resuspended to a <lb/>volume of 100µl with sterile PBS, and injected retro-orbitally. <lb/>Quantitative PCR of Viral Abundance <lb/>AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-mNeonGreen was delivered systemically to WT mice at 6-8 weeks of age. <lb/>3-4 weeks following viral infection, 1cm of proximal, medial, and distal SI and colon were <lb/>harvested and flash frozen in TRIzol (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham, MA-Cat. No. <lb/>15596018) and RNA was extracted per manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Viral ssDNA is present in <lb/>the RNA fraction. Contaminating RNA was eliminated with RNase treatment (ThermoFisher <lb/>Scientific, Waltham, MA-Cat. No. AM228) per manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Quantitative PCR <lb/>was performed on viral DNA with primers against WPRE (Forward: 5&apos;-<lb/>GGCTGTTGGGCACTGACAAT-3&apos;; Reverse: 5&apos;-CCGAAGGGACGTAGCAGAAG-3&apos;) and values <lb/>were normalized to ubiquitous mitochondrial gene, mtRNR2 (Forward: 5&apos;-<lb/>CCGCAAGGGAAAGATGAAAA-3&apos;; Reverse: 5&apos;-TCGTTTGGTTTCGGGGTTTC-3&apos;). Plotted <lb/>relative abundances are mean values across three regions sampled in either SI or colon. <lb/>Neural activation of the GI tract <lb/>TH-Cre and ChAT-Cre mice are used for these experiments. &quot;Activated&quot; mice are infected with <lb/>AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-hM3Dq-mRuby2 and &quot;Control Mice&quot; are infected with AAV-<lb/>PHP.S:hSYN1-DIO-mRuby2. This is to control for both AAV-PHP.S-mediated expression and <lb/>the effects of Compound 21 dihydrochloride (C21) (HelloBio, Princeton, NJ-HB6124). C21 was <lb/>injected intraperitoneally at a dose of 3mg/kg in both activated and control mice. Mice for time <lb/>course experiments were single-housed in sterile cages with autoclaved water following first <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>C21 administration (C21 administered for 10 consecutive days). Injections of C21 were <lb/>administered at the same time every day (10AM). <lb/>Tissue preparation, immunohistochemistry, Imaging, and Quantification <lb/>100mg/kg of pentobarbital (Euthasol -Virbac, Carros, France) was administered IP, and tissues <lb/>were perfused with 30mL of phosphate buffer solution (PBS) and next with cold 4% <lb/>paraformaldehyde (PFA) in PBS. GI tract was post-fixed in 4% PFA overnight at 4 o C, and stored <lb/>in PBS + 0.025% sodium azide. Tissues that underwent subsequent immunohistochemistry <lb/>were made transparent by use of the passive CLARITY technique (PACT) (Treweek et al., <lb/>2015). Briefly, perfused and fixed tissues were embedded with polymerized 4% (wt/vol) <lb/>acrylamide, and lipids were eliminated using 8% (wt/vol) SDS solution. Tissues were blocked in <lb/>3% donkey serum and permeabilized with PBS + 0.3% Triton (PBST). Primary antibodies were <lb/>incubated in PBST for 48 hours and washed with PBST for 24 hours (replacing wash 3 times). <lb/>Tissues were next incubated in secondary antibodies (and DAPI) for 24 hours and washed in <lb/>PBS for 48 hours, intermittently replacing the wash solution with fresh PBS. Primary antibodies <lb/>used were rabbit PGP9.5 (1:300; Millipore Sigma AB1761-I) and chicken GFAP (1:500, <lb/>BioLegend Cat #829401). Secondary antibodies used were goat anti-chicken Alexa 647 (Life <lb/>Technologies A-21450) and donkey anti-rabbit Alexa 568 (Life Technologies A10042). Tissues <lb/>imaged just for virally expressed, endogenous fluorescence were made transparent using <lb/>sorbitol-based optical clearing method, ScaleS (Hama et al., 2015). Tissues were mounted in <lb/>respective mounting mediums (RIMS and Scales S4), on a glass slide with a 0.5mm spacer <lb/>(iSpacer, SunJin Lab Co.). Images were acquired on Zeiss LSM 780 or 880, and microscope, <lb/>laser settings, contrast, and gamma remained constant across images that were directly <lb/>compared. All confocal images were taken with the following objectives: Fluar 5× 0.25 M27 <lb/>Plan-Apochromat 10× 0.45 M27 (work-ing distance 2.0 mm) and Plan-Apochromat 25× 0.8 <lb/>Imm Corr DIC M27 multi-immersion. Neurons in each ganglion were counted by counting cells <lb/>that are of a distinct color. Large intestinal ganglia were defined as distinct if separated by a <lb/>width of 3 or fewer neurons. <lb/>Live, in vivo, imaging (GCaMP6F), Video Processing, and Analysis <lb/>AAV-PHP.S-CAG-GCaMP6F (10 12 VGs) was delivered systemically to WT C57. 3-4 weeks after <lb/>infection, mice were anesthetized with 2% isoflurane on a heating pad (Kent Scientific, <lb/>Torrington, CT-DCT15) with plastic sleeve covers (Kent Scientific, Torrington, CT-DCT1520P). <lb/>The abdominal cavity was surgically opened to expose the intestines. The proximal colon was <lb/>identified, and this portion was placed on top of a stack of 4-6 glass microscopy slides <lb/>(depending on size of animal) (VWR, Radnor PA-Cat. No. 48300-026). Tissue was secured <lb/>onto glass slide with a biorthogonal silicon elastomer (Kwik-Sil) (World Precision Instruments, <lb/>Sarasota, FL-KWIK-SIL), and a glass coverslip. Elastomer stiffens within 1 minute of <lb/>application and coverslip must be held steadily to ensure a flat imaging surface. Anesthetized <lb/>mouse is placed under an upright confocal microscope (Zeiss LSM 880). Using a 10X objective, <lb/>GCaMP6F fluorescence was taken at 5Hz (1 image every 200ms). Periods of movement of <lb/>tissue and luminal contents is normal during live imaging. Cell tracking was performed in 2D by <lb/>using TrackMate ImageJ plugin (https://imagej.net/TrackMate) and fluorescence intensity was <lb/>recorded from cells. Average background was determined by taking the fluorescence of a region <lb/>of interest that did not contain a cell, over the duration of the video. Background was subtracted <lb/>from cell fluorescence intensities. <lb/>Spike Detection <lb/>Data sets of fluorescent values recorded at a rate of 0.206 s from GCaMP6F-expressing <lb/>unstimulated neurons in the myenteric plexus of the proximal large intestine and analyzed with <lb/>the MLspike software for Matlab downloaded from GitHub (https://github.com/MLspike/spikes) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(Deneux et al., 2016). MLspike determines a new baseline to subtract from the raw fluorescence <lb/>data to allow accurate modelling. The software uses a version of the Viterbi algorithm to obtain <lb/>the most probable spike train. From the model, fluctuating baseline, model-estimated spike <lb/>train, and most probable spike times were extracted. Polynomial coefficients (p 2 ) were changed <lb/>from 0.5 to 0.55 and (p 3 ) from 0.01 to 0.03 for GCaMP6F fluorescence as recommended <lb/>(Deneux et al., 2016). The minimum range for baseline (b min ) was changed from 0.7 to 0.5 as <lb/>determined by observed fluorescence values. <lb/>GCaMP6F Fluorescence in Ex Vivo Intestinal Preparation <lb/>Small intestinal tissue was quickly harvested from ChAT-Cre mice, flushed and placed in <lb/>oxygenated (95% O2, 5% CO2), ice cold Krebs-Henseleit solution for 1 hour followed by 15 min <lb/>at room temperature. A segment was cut along the mesenteric attachment, and pinned flat <lb/>(mucosa facing down) on a Sylgard-lined recording chamber (Warner Instruments, PH1) in <lb/>oxygenated Krebs-Henseleit solution. C21 was added at 10nM and GCaMP6F fluorescence <lb/>was detected on an upright microscope (Zeiss, Oberkochen, Germany-Examiner D1). <lb/>3&apos; mRNA-sequencing <lb/>Tissue collection and RNA extraction <lb/>Mice were cervically dislocated and the GI tract was removed. 1cm of tissue above and below <lb/>the cecum were dissected and cleaned to represent tissue from the distal SI and proximal colon, <lb/>respectively. Tissue was homogenized in TRIzol (ThermoFisher Scientific, Waltham. MA-Cat. <lb/>No. 15596018) solution using bead-based homogenizing methods, and total RNA was extracted <lb/>using chloroform per manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Library Preparation, Sequencing, and Analysis <lb/>The cDNA libraries were prepared using the QuantSeq 3&apos;mRNA-Seq Library Prep Kit FWD for <lb/>Illumina (Lexogen, Greenland, NH) supplemented with UMI (unique molecular index) as per the <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Briefly, total RNA was reverse transcribed using oligo (dT) primers. <lb/>The second cDNA strand was synthesized by random priming, in a manner that DNA <lb/>polymerase is efficiently stopped when reaching the next hybridized random primer, so only the <lb/>fragment closed to the 3&apos; end gets captured for later indexed adapter ligation and PCR <lb/>amplification. UMIs were incorporated to the first 6 bases of each read, followed by 4 bases of <lb/>spacer sequences. UMIs are used to eliminate possible PCR duplicates in sequencing datasets <lb/>and therefore facilitate unbiased gene expression profiling. The basic principle behind the UMI <lb/>deduplication step is to collapse reads with identical mapping coordinates and UMI sequences. <lb/>This step helps increase the accuracy of sequencing read counts for downstream analysis of <lb/>gene expression levels. The processed libraries were assessed for its size distribution and <lb/>concentration using Bioanalyzer High Sensitivity DNA Kit (Agilent Technologies, Santa Clara, <lb/>CA-Cat. No. 5067-4626 and -4627). Pooled libraries were diluted to 2 nM in EB buffer (Qiagen, <lb/>Hilden, Germany, Cat. No. 19086) and then denatured using the Illumina protocol. The libraries <lb/>were pooled and diluted to 2 nM using 10 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.5 and then denatured using the <lb/>Illumina protocol. The denatured libraries were diluted to 10 pM by pre-chilled hybridization <lb/>buffer and loaded onto an Illumina MiSeq v3 flow cell for 150 cycles using a single-read recipe <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Single-end 75bp reads (max 4.5M reads) were <lb/>obtained. De-multiplexed sequencing reads were generated using Illumina BaseSpace. <lb/>UMI specific workflows that were developed and distributed by Lexogen were used to extract <lb/>reads that are free from PCR artifacts (i.e., deduplication). First, the umi2index tool was used to <lb/>add the 6 nucleotide UMI sequence to the identifier of each read and trims the UMI from the <lb/>start of each read. This generates a new FASTQ file, which is then processed through trimming <lb/>and alignment. Second, after the quality and polyA trimming by BBDuk (Website-<lb/>https://jgi.doe.gov/data-and-tools/bbtools/bb-tools-user-guide/bbduk-guide/) and alignment by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>HISAT2 (version 2.1.0) (Kim et al., 2015) , the mapped reads are collapsed according to the <lb/>UMI sequence of each read. Reads are collapsed if they have the same mapping coordinates <lb/>(CIGAR string) and identical UMI sequences. Collapsing reads in this manner removes PCR <lb/>duplicates. Read counts were calculated using HTSeq (Anders et al., 2015) by supplementing <lb/>Ensembl gene annotation (GRCm38.78). Raw read counts were run through ShinySeq to obtain <lb/>differentially expressed genes and downstream gene ontology analyses (Sundararajan et al., <lb/>2019). <lb/>Proteome Preparation <lb/>Protein extraction <lb/>Mice were sacrificed 45 minutes after C21 administration and cecal contents were isolated and <lb/>resuspended in 400μl of phosphate buffered solution, and centrifuged at x20,000g to spin down <lb/>cells and lysate. Protein was isolated from resulting supernatant using Wessel-Flüegge&apos;s <lb/>methanol/chloroform extraction method (Wessel and Flügge, 1984). Briefly, MeOH and <lb/>chloroform was added to sample at a 4:1 and 1:1 ratio, respectively. Next, water dH2O was <lb/>added at a 3:1 ratio, samples were vortexed and centrifuged at x20,000g. Resulting precipitated <lb/>protein was collected and washed with methanol. Precipitated protein was centrifuged and was <lb/>left to air dry, and stored in -20C until protein digestion. <lb/>In-solution Protein Digestion and Desalting <lb/>Precipitated protein sample was denatured in 40μl of 8M Urea (100mM Tris-HCl pH8.5). To <lb/>reduce disulfide bonds, 1.25μl of 100mM Tris(2-carboxyethyl)Phosphine was added and <lb/>incubated at room temperature (RT) for 20 minutes. Then 1.8μl of 250mM iodoactaminde was <lb/>added and incubated at RT in the dark to alkylate cysteines. The first step of digestion was <lb/>initiated by adding 1μl of 0.1µg/μl of Lysyl endopeptidase. After four-hour incubation. Urea <lb/>concentration was adjusted to 2M by adding 120μl of 100mM Tris-HCl pH8.5. The second step <lb/>of digestion was initiated by adding 2.5μl of 2µg/μl trypsin plus 1.6μl of 100mM CaCl2 for trypsin <lb/>activity enhancement and incubating overnight in the dark. Formic acid was added to stop <lb/>trypsing digestion. The digested peptides were desalted by HPLC using C8 peptide microtrap <lb/>(Microm Bioresources). Peptides were lyophilized and diluted to 200 ng/µl in 0.2% formic acid <lb/>prior to LC-MS/MS analysis. <lb/>LC-MS/MS <lb/>Samples were analyzed on a Q Exactive HF Orbitrap mass spectrometer coupled to an EASY <lb/>nLC 1200 liquid chromatographic system (Thermo Scientific, San Jose, CA). Approximately 200 <lb/>ng of peptides were loaded on a 50 μm I.D. × 25 cm column with a 10 μm electrospray tip <lb/>(PicoFrit from New Objective, Woburn, MA) in-house-packed with ReproSil-Pur C18-AQ 1.9 μm <lb/>(Dr. Maisch, Ammerbuch, Germany). Solvent A consisted of 2% MeCN in 0.2% FA and solvent <lb/>B consisted of 80% MeCN in 0.2% FA. A non-linear 60 minute gradient from 2% B to 40% B <lb/>was used to separate the peptides for analysis. The mass spectrometer was operated in a data-<lb/>dependent mode, with MS1 scans collected from 400-1650 m/z at 60,000 resolution and MS/MS <lb/>scans collected from 200-2000 m/z at 30,000 resolution. Dynamic exclusion of 45 s was used. <lb/>The top 12 most abundant peptides with charge states between 2 and 5 were selected for <lb/>fragmentation with normalized collision energy of 28. <lb/>Peptide and Protein Identification <lb/>Thermo .raw files were converted to .ms1 and .ms2 files using RawConverter 1.1.0.18 (He et <lb/>al., 2015) operating in data dependent mode and selecting for monoisotopic m/z. Tandem mass <lb/>spectra (.ms2 files) were identified by database search method using the Integrated Proteomics <lb/>Pipeline 6.5.4 (IP2, Integrated Proteomics Applications, Inc., <lb/>http://www.integratedproteomics.com). Briefly, databases containing forward and reverse <lb/>(decoy) (Elias and Gygi, 2007; Peng et al., 2003) peptide sequences were generated from in <lb/>silico trypsin digestion of either the mouse proteome (UniProt; Oct. 2, 2019) or protein <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>sequences derived from large comprehensive public repositories (ComPIL 2.0) (Park et al., <lb/>2018). Tandem mass specta were matched to peptide sequences using the <lb/>ProLuCID/SEQUEST (1.4) (Xu et al., 2015; 2006) software package. The validity of spectrum-<lb/>peptide matches were assessed using the SEQUEST-defined parameters XCorr (cross-<lb/>correlation score) and DeltaCN (normalized difference in cross-correlation scores) in the <lb/>DTASelect2 (2.1.4) (Cociorva et al., 2007; Tabb et al., 2002) software package. Search settings <lb/>were configured as follows: (1) 5ppm precursor ion mass tolerance, (2) 10ppm fragment ion <lb/>mass tolerance, (3) 1% peptide false discovery rate, (4) 2 peptide per protein minimum, (5) 600-<lb/>6000Da precursor mass window, (6) 2 differential modifications per peptide maximum <lb/>(methionine oxidation: M+15.994915 Da), (7) unlimited static modications per peptide (cysteine <lb/>carbamidomethylation: C+57.02146 Da), and (8) the search space included half-and fully tryptic <lb/>(cleavage C-terminal to K and R residues) peptide candidates with unlimited (mouse database, <lb/>custom metagenomic shotgun database) or 2 missed cleavage events (ComPIL 2.0). <lb/>Differential Analysis of Detected Proteins using Peptide-Spectrum Matches (Spectral <lb/>Counts) <lb/>Detected proteins were grouped by sequence similarity into &quot;clusters&quot; using CD-HIT 4.8.1 (Fu et <lb/>al., 2012; Li and Godzik, 2006; Li et al., 2001) at the following similarity cut-offs: 65%, 75%, <lb/>85%, and 95%. The following is an example command line input: &quot;cd-hit -i fastafile.fasta -o <lb/>outputfile -c 0.65 -g 1 -d 0&quot;. Tandem mass spectra identified as peptides (peptide spectrum <lb/>matches, PSMs) were mapped to CD-HIT generated clusters. PSMs mapping to &gt;1 cluster were <lb/>discarded. Cluster-PSM tables were generated and differential analysis was performed in <lb/>DESeq2 (1.25.13) (Love et al., 2014). Briefly, count data (PSMs) were modeled using the <lb/>negative binomial distribution, and the mean-variance relationship was estimated. Variance was <lb/>estimated using an information sharing approach whereby a single feature&apos;s (or cluster&apos;s) <lb/>variance was estimated by taking into account variances of other clusters measured in the same <lb/>experiment. Feature significance calling and ranking were performed using estimated effect <lb/>sizes. Multiple testing correction was performed by Benjamini-Hochberg method within the <lb/>DESeq2 package. Volcano plots were generated in Prism (GraphPad). <lb/>Differential Analysis of Detected Proteins using Ion Intensity (Precursor Intensity) <lb/>Detected proteins were grouped into &quot;clusters&quot; by sequence similarity using CD-HIT 4.8.1 (Fu et <lb/>al., 2012; Li and Godzik, 2006; Li et al., 2001) at the following similarity cut-offs: 65%, 75%, <lb/>85%, and 95%. The following is an example command line input: &quot;cd-hit -i fastafile.fasta -o <lb/>outputfile -c 0.65 -g 1 -d 0&quot;. Using the Census software package (Park et al.; 2008) (Integrated <lb/>Proteomics Pipeline 6.5.4), peptide ion intensities were calculated from .ms1 files. Peptide ion <lb/>intensities were assigned to their parent peptide, then parent peptides were mapped to their <lb/>appropriate CD-HIT generated clusters. Ion intensities belonging to parent peptides that map to <lb/>&gt;1 CD-HIT cluster were discarded. Cluster-ion intensity tables were generated. <lb/>Ion intensity data were analyzed using the DEP package (Zhang et al., 2018) operating <lb/>in R. Intensity values were automatically Log2 transformed in DEP. The cluster list was <lb/>subsequently filtered with the &apos;filter_proteins&apos; function such that clusters with missing values <lb/>above a 65% threshold were discarded. Remaining intensities were further transformed by the <lb/>&apos;normalize_vsn&apos; function (Huber et al., 2002). Missing data in remaining clusters were imputed <lb/>using a mixed approach. Clusters where either the control or treatment group contained only <lb/>null entries were classified as &apos;missing not at random&apos; (MNAR) and imputed with 0 values. All <lb/>other groups were treated as &apos;missing at random&apos; (MAR) and imputed using the maximum <lb/>likelihood method (&apos;MLE&apos;) (Gatto and Lilley, 2012). Note that for a given cluster, missing values <lb/>for treatment groups were imputed separately by treatment group. Differential expression <lb/>analyses were performed on filled-in cluster-ion intensity tables using the &apos;test_diff&apos; function <lb/>(Ritchie et al., 2015) and multiple testing correction was performed using the &apos;add_rejections&apos; <lb/>function. <lb/>Network Analysis using STRING Database <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Upregulated proteins with a nominal p-value&lt;0.2 were searched against protein-protein <lb/>interactions in the STRING database (http://www.string-db.org) where high confidence <lb/>interactions were selected for. Briefly, the STRING database sources protein-protein <lb/>interactions from primary databases consisting of genomic context predictions, high-throughput <lb/>lab experiments, (conserved) co-expression, automated textmining, and pervious knowledge in <lb/>databases (Szklarczyk et al., 2019). <lb/>Metaproteome Analysis using Unipept <lb/>Upregulated tryptic, microbial peptide sequences with nominal p-value cutoff of p&lt;0.2 were <lb/>input into Unipept (http://unipept.ugent.be) (Gurdeep Singh et al., 2019; Mesuere et al., 2015), <lb/>equating leucine and isoleucine and filtering duplicate peptides. Briefly, Unipept indexes tryptic <lb/>peptide sequences from the UniProtKB and details peptides with NCBI&apos;s taxonomic database. <lb/>Lowest common ancestor is calculated for each tryptic peptide. <lb/>Metagenome Preparations <lb/>Fecal Collection <lb/>AAV-PHP.S:hSYN1-hM3Dq-mRuby2 (10 12 VGs) was delivered systemically to TH-Cre and <lb/>ChAT-Cre mice. 3-4 week after infection, C21 (3mg/kg) was administered daily for 10 <lb/>consecutive days. Fecal pellets were collected in sterile containers one day before initial C21 <lb/>dose, and between doses thereafter. <lb/>Fecal sample DNA extraction and Library Preparation <lb/>DNA was extracted with the Qiagen MagAttract PowerSoil DNA kit as previously described <lb/>(Marotz et al 2017) . Our standard protocol is optimized for an input quantity of 1 ng DNA per <lb/>reaction. Prior to library preparation, input DNA is transferred to a 384-well plate and quantified <lb/>using a PicoGreen fluorescence assay (ThermoFisher, Inc). Input DNA is then normalized to <lb/>1 ng in a volume of 3.5 μL of molecular-grade water using an Echo 550 acoustic liquid-<lb/>handling robot (Labcyte, Inc). Enzyme mixes for fragmentation, end repair and A-tailing, ligation, <lb/>and PCR are prepared and added in approximately 1:8 scale volumes using a Mosquito HV <lb/>micropipetting robot (TTP Labtech). Fragmentation is performed at 37 °C for 20 min, followed <lb/>by end repair and A-tailing at 65 °C for 30 min. <lb/>Sequencing adapters and barcode indices are added in two steps, following the iTru adapter <lb/>protocol (Glenn et al., 2019). Universal adapter &quot;stub&quot; adapter molecules and ligase mix are first <lb/>added to the end-repaired DNA using the Mosquito HV robot and ligation performed at 20 °C <lb/>for 1 h. Unligated adapters and adapter dimers are then removed using AMPure XP magnetic <lb/>beads and a BlueCat purification robot (BlueCat Bio). 7.5 μL magnetic bead solution is added to <lb/>the total adapter-ligated sample volume, washed twice with 70% EtOH, and then resuspended <lb/>in 7 μL molecular-grade water. <lb/>Next, individual i7 and i5 are added to the adapter-ligated samples using the Echo 550 robot. <lb/>Because this liquid handler individually addresses wells, and we use the full set of 384 unique <lb/>error-correcting i7 and i5 indices, we are able to generate each plate of 384 libraries without <lb/>repeating any barcodes, eliminating the problem of sequence misassignment due to barcode <lb/>swapping (Costello et al., 2018; Sinha et al., 2017). To ensure that libraries generated on <lb/>different plates can be pooled if necessary, and to safeguard against the possibility of <lb/>contamination due to sample carryover between runs, we also iterate the assignment of i7 to i5 <lb/>indices each run, such that each unique i7:i5 index combination is only repeated once every <lb/>147,456 libraries. 4.5 μL of eluted bead-washed ligated samples is added to 5.5 μL of PCR <lb/>master mix and PCR-amplified for 15 cycles. The amplified and indexed libraries are then <lb/>purified again using magnetic beads and the BlueCat robot, resuspended in 10 μL water, and <lb/>9 μL of final purified library transferred to a 384-well plate using the Mosquito HV liquid-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>handling robot for library quantitation, sequencing, and storage. 384 samples are then <lb/>normalized based on a PicoGreen fluorescence assay. <lb/>Shallow shotgun metagenome sequencing and diversity analysis <lb/>The Illumina data for each HiSeq lane was uploaded to Qiita, a tool with standardized pipelines <lb/>for processing and analyzing metagenomic data (Gonzalez et al., 2018). Adapter sequences <lb/>were removed from the reads using the Atropos v.1.1.15 (Didion et al., 2017) command (from <lb/>the qp-shogun 0.1.5 pipeline) and the trimmed sequences were downloaded from Qiita. The <lb/>reads for each sample were filtered of any potential mouse contamination using Bowtie2 v.2-<lb/>2.2.3 (Langmead and Salzberg, 2012). The filtered reads were then aligned to the Web of Life <lb/>(WoL) reference phylogeny (Zhu et al., 2019) with Bowtie2 using an adapted SHOGUN pipeline <lb/>(Hillmann et al., 2018). The WoL contains 10,575 bacterial and archaeal genomes with each <lb/>genome representing an OTU. Sequencing reads that did not map to a single reference genome <lb/>as well as reads that mapped to multiple genomes were not included in the analysis. If an OTU <lb/>had a relative abundance less than 0.01% in a given sample, the OTU was not included for that <lb/>sample. Additionally, OTUs with fewer than 5 assigned reads were not considered. The samples <lb/>were rarefied to a depth of 12,750 reads and those with fewer than the rarefaction depth were <lb/>excluded. The QIIME2 v.2019.7 (Bolyen et al., 2019) DEICODE plugin was used to calculate <lb/>the Aitchison distances, a compositional beta diversity metric, and perform Robust Aitchison <lb/>PCA to create biplots that visualize relationships between features and samples (Martino et al., <lb/>2019). The QIIME2 diversity plugin was used to calculate the other alpha-and beta-diversity <lb/>metrics used in this study. <lb/>Metagenomic based functional profiling <lb/>The filtered reads were also analyzed using HUMAnN2 v2.8.1 (Franzosa et al., 2018) to <lb/>establish functional profiles for the samples. HUMAnN2 is a pipeline that begins by using <lb/>MetaPhlAn 2 to compile custom databases of reference genomes based on the species <lb/>detected in a sample (Truong et al., 2015). HUMAnN2 then maps the filtered onto these custom <lb/>databases and the reads that do not map to any of the references are then subjected to a <lb/>translated search against UniProt Reference Clusters or UniRef (Suzek et al., 2007). Here, the <lb/>UniRef90 database was used for the translated search and installed according to the HUMAnN2 <lb/>documentation. The results from both the search performed using the custom reference <lb/>genome database and the search against the UniRef90 database were combined and the gene <lb/>families identified in each sample were reported in units of read per kilobase (RPKs) to account <lb/>for gene length. HUMAnN2 also compared the gene families found in a sample with the <lb/>MetaCyc pathways database (Caspi et al., 2018) and output a table reporting the pathway <lb/>abundances found in each sample. After rarefying gene family tables to a depth of 166,000 <lb/>RPKs and using a depth of 22,600 for pathway abundances, the QIIME2 diversity and <lb/>DEICODE plugins were used to calculate alpha-and beta-diversity metrics. <lb/>Metabolomics Preparations <lb/>Sample Preparation <lb/>Frozen fecal and cecal samples were transported on dry ice for metabolomics analysis. The <lb/>samples were weighed out and an extraction solvent (1:1 methanol to water with an internal <lb/>standard of 1 µM sulfamethazine) was added at a 1:10 milligram to microliter ratio. The samples <lb/>were then homogenized using a TissueLyser II (Qiagen) for 5 minutes at 25 hertz followed by a <lb/>15 minute centrifugation at 14,000 rpm. From the supernatant, 120 µL were transferred to a 96 <lb/>deepwell plate (Eppendorf) and then these samples were lyophilized using a CentriVap <lb/>Benchtop Vacuum Concentrator (Labconco) and stored at -80℃. Upon the time for data <lb/>acquisition, the lyophilized plates were resuspended in a 1:1 methanol to water solvent spiked <lb/>with 1 µM of sulfadimethoxine. The plates were vortexed for 2 minutes, centrifuged at 14,000 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>rpm for 15 minutes and 120 µL of the supernatant was transferred to a 96 well autosampler <lb/>plate(Eppendorf). Plates were stored at 4 °C prior to LCMS analysis. <lb/>Data Acquisition <lb/>The untargeted metabolomics analysis was completed using an ultra-high performance liquid <lb/>chromatography system (Thermo Dionex Ultimate 3000 UHPLC) coupled to ultra-high resolution <lb/>quadrupole time of flight (qTOF) mass spectrometer (Bruker Daltonics MaXis HD). A <lb/>Phenomenex Kinetex column (C18 1.7 μm, 2.1 mm x 50 mm) was used for chromatographic <lb/>separation. An injection volume of 5 µL was used per sample and a flow-rate of 0.500 mL was <lb/>used throughout the analysis. The mobile phase consisted of solvent A: 100% LC-MS grade <lb/>water spiked with 0.1% formic acid and solvent B: 100% LC-MS grade acetonitrile spiked with <lb/>0.1% formic acid. The chromatographic gradient was as follows: 0.0-1.0 min, 5% B; 1.0-<lb/>9.0 min, 5-100% B; 9.0-11.0 min, 100% B; 11.0-11.5 min, 100-5% B; 11.5-12.5 min, 5% B. <lb/>The data was collected using electrospray ionization in positive mode. Sample data was saved <lb/>as .d file folders. <lb/>Data Processing <lb/>The raw .d data files were converted to mzXML format using Bruker Compass DataAnalysis 4.1 <lb/>software. The resulting .mzXML file, the original .d file folders, and basic prep information sheet <lb/>were stored on the UC San Diego MassIVE data repository under the accession number <lb/>MSV000084550. For the MS1 level feature detection, the open-source software MZmine version <lb/>2.51 was used. The parameters used are as follows: 1) Mass Detection (Centroid, Noise Level <lb/>MS1 1E3, MS2 1E2); 2) ADAP Chromatogram Builder (Min Group size in # of scans=3, Group <lb/>Intensity Threshold= 3E3, Min Highest Intensity=1E3, m/z tolerance 0.01 m/z or 10.0 ppm); 3) <lb/>Chromatogram Deconvolution (Local Minimum Search&gt;Chromatographic Threshold 0.01%, <lb/>Minimum in RT range 0.50 min, &lt;Minimum Relative Height 0.01%, Minimum Absolute Height <lb/>3E3, Min Ratio of Peak Top/Edge 2, Peak Duration Range 0.05-0.50 min; m/z Calculation Auto, <lb/>m/z range for MS2 pairing 0.01 Da, and RT Range for MS2 Pairing 0.1 min); Isotopic Peaks <lb/>Grouper (m/z Tolerance 0.01 m/z or 10.0 ppm, Retention Time Tolerance 0.3 min, Maximum <lb/>Charge 4, Representative Ion Most Intense); Join Aligner (m/z Tolerance 0.01 m/z or 10.0 ppm, <lb/>Weight for m/z 75, Retention Time Tolerance 0.3 min, Weight for RT 25); Gap-Filling Peak <lb/>Finder (Intensity Tolerance 20%, m/z Tolerance 0.005 m/z or 10.0 ppm, Retention Time <lb/>Tolerance 0.2 min). The resulting feature table was saved as a .csv file and .mgf file for use in <lb/>GNPS and MetaboAnalyst. <lb/>Molecular Networking and Statistical Analysis <lb/>Molecular networking was performing using the feature networking tool available on the Global <lb/>Natural Products Social Molecular Networking portal (GNPS) accessed via the following link: <lb/>https://gnps.ucsd.edu/ProteoSAFe/index.jsp?params=%7B%22workflow%22:%22FEATURE-<lb/>BASED-MOLECULAR-<lb/>NETWORKING%22,%22library_on_server%22:%22d.speclibs;%22%7D. <lb/>The annotations obtained using this workflow fall under MSI level 2 or 3 and were used for <lb/>feature analysis (Sumner et al., 2007). Briefly, level 2 compounds are putatively annotated <lb/>meaning they are not identified using chemical reference standards but rather based on <lb/>physical properties and/or spectral similarities to available spectral libraries (publicly available <lb/>and purchased NIST17 CID). Level 3 compounds are putatively characterized classes of <lb/>compounds identified similarly to level 2 compounds. The feature based molecular networking <lb/>workflow on GNPS (Nothias et al., 2019) was utilized in order to analyze the spectra associated <lb/>with the feature tables produced using the open source software Mzmine version 2.51 (Pluskal <lb/>et al., 2010). The .mgf and .csv outputs from MZmine v2.51 were used to run the workflow. The <lb/>GNPS workflow parameters used we as follows: Precursor Ion Mass 0.02 Da, Fragment Ion <lb/>Mass Tolerance 0.02 Da, Min Pairs Cos 0.7, Minimum Matched Fragments 6, Maximum Shift <lb/>Between Precursors 500 Da, Network TopK 10, Maximum Connected Component Size (Beta) <lb/>100, and the files were row sum normalized. Default parameters were used for the rest of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>settings. The visualizations and statistical analyses were performed using QIIME 2 v.2019.10 <lb/>(Bolyen et al., 2019), MetaboAnalyst and Cytoscape v3.7.2. All PCoA axes in Figure 6 and S5 <lb/>were individually plotted in QIIME 2 and due to a batch effect between subsequent plates run on <lb/>the mass spectrometer-axes that minimized experimental biases were determined and chosen <lb/>for graphical representation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Alavi, S., Mitchell, J.D., Cho, J.Y., Liu, R., Macbeth, J.C., and Hsiao, A. (2020). Interpersonal <lb/>Gut Microbiome Variation Drives Susceptibility and Resistance to Cholera Infection. Cell 181, <lb/>1533-1546.e13. <lb/>Albenberg, L.G., and Wu, G.D. (2014). Diet and the intestinal microbiome: associations, <lb/>functions, and implications for health and disease. Gastroenterology 146, 1564-1572. <lb/>Anders, S., Pyl, P.T., and Huber, W. (2015). HTSeq--a Python framework to work with high-<lb/>throughput sequencing data. Bioinformatics 31, 166-169. <lb/>Anlauf, M., Schäfer, M.K.H., Eiden, L., and Weihe, E. (2003). Chemical coding of the human <lb/>gastrointestinal nervous system: cholinergic, VIPergic, and catecholaminergic phenotypes. The <lb/>Journal of Comparative Neurology 459, 90-111. <lb/>Aries, V., Crowther, J.S., Drasar, B.S., and Hill, M.J. (1969). Degradation of bile salts by human <lb/>intestinal bacteria. Gut 10, 575-576. <lb/>Bahrami, S., and Drabløs, F. (2016). Gene regulation in the immediate-early response process. <lb/>Advances in Biological Regulation 62, 37-49. <lb/>Begley, M., Sleator, R.D., Gahan, C.G.M., and Hill, C. (2005). Contribution of three bile-<lb/>associated loci, bsh, pva, and btlB, to gastrointestinal persistence and bile tolerance of Listeria <lb/>monocytogenes. Infect. Immun. 73, 894-904. <lb/>Benskey, M.J., Kuhn, N.C., Galligan, J.J., Garcia, J., Boye, S.E., Hauswirth, W.W., Mueller, C., <lb/>Boye, S.L., and Manfredsson, F.P. (2015). Targeted gene delivery to the enteric nervous <lb/>system using AAV: a comparison across serotypes and capsid mutants. Mol. Ther. 23, 488-<lb/>500. <lb/>Bhavsar, A.S., Verma, S., Lamba, R., Lall, C.G., Koenigsknecht, V., and Rajesh, A. (2013). <lb/>Abdominal manifestations of neurologic disorders. Radiographics 33, 135-153. <lb/>Bolyen, E., Rideout, J.R., Dillon, M.R., Bokulich, N.A., Abnet, C.C., Al-Ghalith, G.A., Alexander, <lb/>H., Alm, E.J., Arumugam, M., Asnicar, F., et al. (2019). Reproducible, interactive, scalable and <lb/>extensible microbiome data science using QIIME 2. Nat Biotechnol 37, 852-857. <lb/>Bravo, J.A., Forsythe, P., Chew, M.V., Escaravage, E., Savignac, H.M., Dinan, T.G., <lb/>Bienenstock, J., and Cryan, J.F. (2011). Ingestion of Lactobacillus strain regulates emotional <lb/>behavior and central GABA receptor expression in a mouse via the vagus nerve. Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences 108, 16050-16055. <lb/>Bruel-Jungerman, E., Davis, S., and Laroche, S. (2016). Brain Plasticity Mechanisms and <lb/>Memory: A Party of Four. Neuroscientist 13, 492-505. <lb/>Carabotti, M., Scirocco, A., Maselli, M.A., and Severi, C. (2015). The gut-brain axis: interactions <lb/>between enteric microbiota, central and enteric nervous systems. Ann Gastroenterol 28, 203-<lb/>209. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Carroll, I.M., Ringel-Kulka, T., Ferrier, L., Wu, M.C., Siddle, J.P., Bueno, L., and Ringel, Y. <lb/>(2013). Fecal protease activity is associated with compositional alterations in the intestinal <lb/>microbiota. PloS One 8, e78017. <lb/>Caspi, R., Billington, R., Fulcher, C.A., Keseler, I.M., Kothari, A., Krummenacker, M., <lb/>Latendresse, M., Midford, P.E., Ong, Q., Ong, W.K., et al. (2018). The MetaCyc database of <lb/>metabolic pathways and enzymes. Nucleic Acids Res 46, D633-D639. <lb/>Cekanaviciute, E., Yoo, B.B., Runia, T.F., Debelius, J.W., Singh, S., Nelson, C.A., Kanner, R., <lb/>Bencosme, Y., Lee, Y.K., Hauser, S.L., et al. (2017). Gut bacteria from multiple sclerosis <lb/>patients modulate human T cells and exacerbate symptoms in mouse models. Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. U.S.a. 114, 10713-10718. <lb/>Cersosimo, M.G., Raina, G.B., Pecci, C., Pellene, A., Calandra, C.R., Gutiérrez, C., Micheli, <lb/>F.E., and Benarroch, E.E. (2013). Gastrointestinal manifestations in Parkinson&apos;s disease: <lb/>prevalence and occurrence before motor symptoms. J. Neurol. 260, 1332-1338. <lb/>Challis, R.C., Ravindra Kumar, S., Chan, K.Y., Challis, C., Beadle, K., Jang, M.J., Kim, H.M., <lb/>Rajendran, P.S., Tompkins, J.D., Shivkumar, K., et al. (2019). Systemic AAV vectors for <lb/>widespread and targeted gene delivery in rodents. Nature Protocols 14, 379-414. <lb/>Chan, K.Y., Jang, M.J., Yoo, B.B., Greenbaum, A., Ravi, N., Wu, W.-L., Sánchez-Guardado, L., <lb/>Lois, C., Mazmanian, S.K., Deverman, B.E., et al. (2017). Engineered AAVs for efficient <lb/>noninvasive gene delivery to the central and peripheral nervous systems. Nat. Neurosci. 20, <lb/>1172-1179. <lb/>Chen, T.-W., Wardill, T.J., Sun, Y., Pulver, S.R., Renninger, S.L., Baohan, A., Schreiter, E.R., <lb/>Kerr, R.A., Orger, M.B., Jayaraman, V., et al. (2013). Ultrasensitive fluorescent proteins for <lb/>imaging neuronal activity. Nature 499, 295-300. <lb/>Cociorva, D., L Tabb, D., and Yates, J.R. (2007). Validation of Tandem Mass Spectrometry <lb/>Database Search Results Using DTASelect. Current Protocols in Bioinformatics 16. <lb/>Costello, M., Fleharty, M., Abreu, J., Farjoun, Y., Ferriera, S., Holmes, L., Granger, B., Green, <lb/>L., Howd, T., Mason, T., et al. (2018). Characterization and remediation of sample index swaps <lb/>by non-redundant dual indexing on massively parallel sequencing platforms. BMC Genomics <lb/>19, 332-10. <lb/>de Aguiar Vallim, T.Q., Tarling, E.J., and Edwards, P.A. (2013). Pleiotropic roles of bile acids in <lb/>metabolism. Cell Metabolism 17, 657-669. <lb/>Del Giudice, E., Staiano, A., Capano, G., Romano, A., Florimonte, L., Miele, E., Ciarla, C., <lb/>Campanozzi, A., and Crisanti, A.F. (1999). Gastrointestinal manifestations in children with <lb/>cerebral palsy. Brain Dev. 21, 307-311. <lb/>Delpino, M.V., Marchesini, M.I., Estein, S.M., Comerci, D.J., Cassataro, J., Fossati, C.A., and <lb/>Baldi, P.C. (2007). A bile salt hydrolase of Brucella abortus contributes to the establishment of a <lb/>successful infection through the oral route in mice. Infect. Immun. 75, 299-305. <lb/>Deneux, T., Kaszas, A., Szalay, G., Katona, G., Lakner, T., Grinvald, A., Rózsa, B., and <lb/>Vanzetta, I. (2016). Accurate spike estimation from noisy calcium signals for ultrafast three-<lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>dimensional imaging of large neuronal populations in vivo. Nature Communications 7, 12190-<lb/>17. <lb/>Derrien, M., Vaughan, E.E., Plugge, C.M., and de Vos, W.M. (2004). Akkermansia muciniphila <lb/>gen. nov., sp. nov., a human intestinal mucin-degrading bacterium. International Journal of <lb/>Systematic and Evolutionary Microbiology 54, 1469-1476. <lb/>Deverman, B.E., Pravdo, P.L., Simpson, B.P., Kumar, S.R., Chan, K.Y., Banerjee, A., Wu, W.-<lb/>L., Yang, B., Huber, N., Pasca, S.P., et al. (2016). Cre-dependent selection yields AAV variants <lb/>for widespread gene transfer to the adult brain. Nat Biotechnol 34, 204-209. <lb/>Didion, J.P., Martin, M., and Collins, F.S. (2017). Atropos: specific, sensitive, and speedy <lb/>trimming of sequencing reads. PeerJ 5, e3720. <lb/>Donaldson, G.P., Ladinsky, M.S., Yu, K.B., Sanders, J.G., Yoo, B.B., Chou, W.C., Conner, <lb/>M.E., Earl, A.M., Knight, R., Bjorkman, P.J., et al. (2018). Gut microbiota utilize immunoglobulin <lb/>A for mucosal colonization. Science 360, 795-800. <lb/>Donaldson, G.P., Lee, S.M., and Mazmanian, S.K. (2015). Gut biogeography of the bacterial <lb/>microbiota. Nat Rev Micro 14, 20-32. <lb/>Donowitz, M., Singh, S., Salahuddin, F.F., Hogema, B.M., Chen, Y., Gucek, M., Cole, R.N., <lb/>Ham, A., Zachos, N.C., Kovbasnjuk, O., et al. (2007). Proteome of murine jejunal brush border <lb/>membrane vesicles. J. Proteome Res. 6, 4068-4079. <lb/>Drokhlyansky, E., Smillie, C.S., Van Wittenberghe, N., Ericsson, M., Griffin, G.K., Eraslan, G., <lb/>Dionne, D., Cuoco, M.S., Goder-Reiser, M.N., Sharova, T., et al. (2020). The Human and <lb/>Mouse Enteric Nervous System at Single-Cell Resolution. Cell 182, 1606-1622.e1623. <lb/>Elias, J.E., and Gygi, S.P. (2007). Target-decoy search strategy for increased confidence in <lb/>large-scale protein identifications by mass spectrometry. Nat. Methods 4, 207-214. <lb/>Everard, A., Belzer, C., Geurts, L., Ouwerkerk, J.P., Druart, C., Bindels, L.B., Guiot, Y., Derrien, <lb/>M., Muccioli, G.G., Delzenne, N.M., et al. (2013). Cross-talk between Akkermansia muciniphila <lb/>and intestinal epithelium controls diet-induced obesity. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.a. 110, 9066-<lb/>9071. <lb/>Fiorucci, S., Biagioli, M., Zampella, A., and Distrutti, E. (2018). Bile Acids Activated Receptors <lb/>Regulate Innate Immunity. Frontiers in Immunology 9, eaao1605-eaao1617. <lb/>Flandez, M., Guilmeau, S., Blache, P., and Augenlicht, L.H. (2008). KLF4 regulation in intestinal <lb/>epithelial cell maturation. Experimental Cell Research 314, 3712-3723. <lb/>Foong, J.P.P., Tough, I.R., Cox, H.M., and Bornstein, J.C. (2014). Properties of cholinergic and <lb/>non-cholinergic submucosal neurons along the mouse colon. The Journal of Physiology 592, <lb/>777-793. <lb/>Franzosa, E.A., McIver, L.J., Rahnavard, G., Thompson, L.R., Schirmer, M., Weingart, G., <lb/>Lipson, K.S., Knight, R., Caporaso, J.G., Segata, N., et al. (2018). Species-level functional <lb/>profiling of metagenomes and metatranscriptomes. Nat. Methods 15, 962-968. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Fried, D.E., and Gulbransen, B.D. (2015). In situ Ca2+ imaging of the enteric nervous system. <lb/>JoVE. <lb/>Fu, L., Niu, B., Zhu, Z., Wu, S., and Li, W. (2012). CD-HIT: accelerated for clustering the next-<lb/>generation sequencing data. Bioinformatics 28, 3150-3152. <lb/>Furness, J.B. (2012). The enteric nervous system and neurogastroenterology. Nature Reviews <lb/>Gastroenterology and Hepatology 9, 286-294. <lb/>Furness, J.B., Callaghan, B.P., Rivera, L.R., and Cho, H.-J. (2014). The Enteric Nervous <lb/>System and Gastrointestinal Innervation: Integrated Local and Central Control. In The Enteric <lb/>Nervous System, (New York, NY: Springer New York), pp. 39-71. <lb/>Furness, J.B. (2006). The Enteric Nervous System (Wiley-Blackwell). <lb/>Gabanyi, I., Muller, P.A., Feighery, L., Oliveira, T.Y., Costa-Pinto, F.A., and Mucida, D. (2016). <lb/>Neuro-immune Interactions Drive Tissue Programming in Intestinal Macrophages. Cell 164, <lb/>378-391. <lb/>Gatto, L., and Lilley, K.S. (2012). MSnbase-an R/Bioconductor package for isobaric tagged <lb/>mass spectrometry data visualization, processing and quantitation. Bioinformatics 28, 288-289. <lb/>Gershon, M.D. (2015). The Enteric Nervous System: A Second Brain. Hospital Practice 34, 31-<lb/>52. <lb/>Glenn, T.C., Nilsen, R.A., Kieran, T.J., Sanders, J.G., Bayona-Vásquez, N.J., Finger, J.W., <lb/>Pierson, T.W., Bentley, K.E., Hoffberg, S.L., Louha, S., et al. (2019). Adapterama I: universal <lb/>stubs and primers for 384 unique dual-indexed or 147,456 combinatorially-indexed Illumina <lb/>libraries (iTru &amp; iNext). PeerJ 7, e7755. <lb/>Gonzalez, A., Navas-Molina, J.A., Kosciolek, T., McDonald, D., Vázquez-Baeza, Y., <lb/>Ackermann, G., DeReus, J., Janssen, S., Swafford, A.D., Orchanian, S.B., et al. (2018). Qiita: <lb/>rapid, web-enabled microbiome meta-analysis. Nat. Methods 15, 796-798. <lb/>Gottlieb, A., and Canbay, A. (2019). Why Bile Acids Are So Important in Non-Alcoholic Fatty <lb/>Liver Disease (NAFLD) Progression. Cells 8. <lb/>Grundy, D., and Brookes, S. (2011). Neural Control of Gastrointestinal Function. Colloquium <lb/>Series on Integrated Systems Physiology: From Molecule to Function 3, 1-134. <lb/>Gurdeep Singh, R., Tanca, A., Palomba, A., Van der Jeugt, F., Verschaffelt, P., Uzzau, S., <lb/>Martens, L., Dawyndt, P., and Mesuere, B. (2019). Unipept 4.0: Functional Analysis of <lb/>Metaproteome Data. J. Proteome Res. 18, 606-615. <lb/>Haenraets, K., Foster, E., Johannssen, H., Kandra, V., Frezel, N., Steffen, T., Jaramillo, V., <lb/>Paterna, J.-C., Zeilhofer, H.U., and Wildner, H. (2017). Spinal nociceptive circuit analysis with <lb/>recombinant adeno-associated viruses: the impact of serotypes and promoters. Journal of <lb/>Neurochemistry 142, 721-733. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Hama, H., Hioki, H., Namiki, K., Hoshida, T., Kurokawa, H., Ishidate, F., Kaneko, T., Akagi, T., <lb/>Saito, T., Saido, T., et al. (2015). ScaleS: an optical clearing palette for biological imaging. Nat. <lb/>Neurosci. 18, 1518-1529. <lb/>Hansen, M.B. (2003). The enteric nervous system II: Gastrointestinal functions. Pharmacol. <lb/>Toxicol. 92, 249-257. <lb/>He, L., Diedrich, J., Chu, Y.-Y., and Yates, J.R. (2015). Extracting Accurate Precursor <lb/>Information for Tandem Mass Spectra by RawConverter. Anal. Chem. 87, 11361-11367. <lb/>Hennig, G.W., Gould, T.W., Koh, S.D., Corrigan, R.D., Heredia, D.J., Shonnard, M.C., and <lb/>Smith, T.K. (2015). Use of Genetically Encoded Calcium Indicators (GECIs) Combined with <lb/>Advanced Motion Tracking Techniques to Examine the Behavior of Neurons and Glia in the <lb/>Enteric Nervous System of the Intact Murine Colon. Front. Cell. Neurosci. 9, 13819. <lb/>Hillmann, B., Al-Ghalith, G.A., Shields-Cutler, R.R., Zhu, Q., Gohl, D.M., Beckman, K.B., Knight, <lb/>R., and Knights, D. (2018). Evaluating the Information Content of Shallow Shotgun <lb/>Metagenomics. mSystems 3, 457. <lb/>Hofmann, A.F., and Eckmann, L. (2006). How bile acids confer gut mucosal protection against <lb/>bacteria. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 103, 4333-4334. <lb/>Huber, W., Heydebreck, von, A., Sültmann, H., Poustka, A., and Vingron, M. (2002). Variance <lb/>stabilization applied to microarray data calibration and to the quantification of differential <lb/>expression. Bioinformatics 18 Suppl 1, S96-S104. <lb/>Hyland, N.P., and Cryan, J.F. (2010). A Gut Feeling about GABA: Focus on GABA(B) <lb/>Receptors. Front Pharmacol 1, 124. <lb/>Ichikawa, R., Takayama, T., Yoneno, K., Kamada, N., Kitazume, M.T., Higuchi, H., Matsuoka, <lb/>K., Watanabe, M., Itoh, H., Kanai, T., et al. (2012). Bile acids induce monocyte differentiation <lb/>toward interleukin-12 hypo-producing dendritic cells via a TGR5-dependent pathway. <lb/>Immunology 136, 153-162. <lb/>Jackson, K.L., Dayton, R.D., Deverman, B.E., and Klein, R.L. (2016). Better Targeting, Better <lb/>Efficiency for Wide-Scale Neuronal Transduction with the Synapsin Promoter and AAV-PHP.B. <lb/>Front. Mol. Neurosci. 9, 116. <lb/>Jangi, S., Gandhi, R., Cox, L.M., Li, N., Glehn, von, F., Yan, R., Patel, B., Mazzola, M.A., Liu, <lb/>S., Glanz, B.L., et al. (2016). Alterations of the human gut microbiome in multiple sclerosis. <lb/>Nature Communications 7, 12015-11. <lb/>Jarret, A., Jackson, R., Duizer, C., Healy, M.E., Zhao, J., Rone, J.M., Bielecki, P., Sefik, E., <lb/>Roulis, M., Rice, T., et al. (2020). Enteric Nervous System-Derived IL-18 Orchestrates Mucosal <lb/>Barrier Immunity. Cell 180, 50-63.e12. <lb/>Jia, L., Betters, J.L., and Yu, L. (2011). Niemann-pick C1-like 1 (NPC1L1) protein in intestinal <lb/>and hepatic cholesterol transport. Annu. Rev. Physiol. 73, 239-259. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Johnson, C.D., Barlow-Anacker, A.J., Pierre, J.F., Touw, K., Erickson, C.S., Furness, J.B., <lb/>Epstein, M.L., and Gosain, A. (2018). Deletion of choline acetyltransferasein enteric neurons <lb/>results in postnatal intestinal dysmotility and dysbiosis. The FASEB Journal 32, 4744-4752. <lb/>Jones, B.V., Begley, M., Hill, C., Gahan, C.G.M., and Marchesi, J.R. (2008). Functional and <lb/>comparative metagenomic analysis of bile salt hydrolase activity in the human gut microbiome. <lb/>Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.a. 105, 13580-13585. <lb/>Kaelberer, M.M., Buchanan, K.L., Klein, M.E., Barth, B.B., Montoya, M.M., Shen, X., and <lb/>Bohórquez, D.V. (2018). A gut-brain neural circuit for nutrient sensory transduction. Science <lb/>361, eaat5236. <lb/>Kim, D., Langmead, B., and Salzberg, S.L. (2015). HISAT: a fast spliced aligner with low <lb/>memory requirements. Nat. Methods 12, 357-360. <lb/>Kirwan, W.O., Smith, A.N., Mitchell, W.D., Falconer, J.D., and Eastwood, M.A. (1975). Bile acids <lb/>and colonic motility in the rabbit and the human. Gut 16, 894-902. <lb/>Kotterman, M.A., and Schaffer, D.V. (2014). Engineering adeno-associated viruses for clinical <lb/>gene therapy. Nat Rev Genet 15, 445-451. <lb/>Kügler, S., Kilic, E., and Bähr, M. (2003). Human synapsin 1 gene promoter confers highly <lb/>neuron-specific long-term transgene expression from an adenoviral vector in the adult rat brain <lb/>depending on the transduced area. Gene Ther 10, 337-347. <lb/>Lai, N.Y., Musser, M.A., Pinho-Ribeiro, F.A., Baral, P., Jacobson, A., Ma, P., Potts, D.E., Chen, <lb/>Z., Paik, D., Soualhi, S., et al. (2019). Gut-Innervating Nociceptor Neurons Regulate Peyer&apos;s <lb/>Patch Microfold Cells and SFB Levels to Mediate Salmonella Host Defense. Cell 180, 33-<lb/>49.e22. <lb/>Langmead, B., and Salzberg, S.L. (2012). Fast gapped-read alignment with Bowtie 2. Nat. <lb/>Methods 9, 357-359. <lb/>Latgé, J.P. (2007). The cell wall: a carbohydrate armour for the fungal cell. Molecular <lb/>Microbiology 66, 279-290. <lb/>Li, W., and Godzik, A. (2006). Cd-hit: a fast program for clustering and comparing large sets of <lb/>protein or nucleotide sequences. Bioinformatics 22, 1658-1659. <lb/>Li, W., Jaroszewski, L., and Godzik, A. (2001). Clustering of highly homologous sequences to <lb/>reduce the size of large protein databases. Bioinformatics 17, 282-283. <lb/>Li, Z., Chalazonitis, A., Huang, Y.Y., Mann, J.J., Margolis, K.G., Yang, Q.M., Kim, D.O., Cote, <lb/>F., Mallet, J., and Gershon, M.D. (2011). Essential Roles of Enteric Neuronal Serotonin in <lb/>Gastrointestinal Motility and the Development/Survival of Enteric Dopaminergic Neurons. <lb/>Journal of Neuroscience 31, 8998-9009. <lb/>Lindeberg, J., Usoskin, D., Bengtsson, H., Gustafsson, A., Kylberg, A., Söderström, S., and <lb/>Ebendal, T. (2004). Transgenic expression of Cre recombinase from the tyrosine hydroxylase <lb/>locus. Genesis 40, 67-73. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Long, S.L., Gahan, C.G.M., and Joyce, S.A. (2017). Interactions between gut bacteria and bile <lb/>in health and disease. Mol. Aspects Med. 56, 54-65. <lb/>Love, M.I., Huber, W., and Anders, S. (2014). Moderated estimation of fold change and <lb/>dispersion for RNA-seq data with DESeq2. Genome Biol 15, 1-21. <lb/>Martino, C., Morton, J.T., Marotz, C.A., Thompson, L.R., Tripathi, A., Knight, R., and Zengler, K. <lb/>(2019). A Novel Sparse Compositional Technique Reveals Microbial Perturbations. mSystems <lb/>4, 813. <lb/>Matheis, F., Muller, P.A., Graves, C.L., Gabanyi, I., Kerner, Z.J., Costa-Borges, D., Ahrends, T., <lb/>Rosenstiel, P., and Mucida, D. (2020). Adrenergic Signaling in Muscularis Macrophages Limits <lb/>Infection-Induced Neuronal Loss. Cell 180, 64-78.e16. <lb/>Matsushima, S., Hori, S., and Matsuda, M. (1986). Conversion of 4-aminobutyraldehyde to <lb/>gamma-aminobutyric acid in striatum treated with semicarbazide and kainic acid. Neurochem. <lb/>Res. 11, 1313-1319. <lb/>McConnell, R.E., Benesh, A.E., Mao, S., Tabb, D.L., and Tyska, M.J. (2011). Proteomic <lb/>analysis of the enterocyte brush border. American Journal of Physiology -Gastrointestinal and <lb/>Liver Physiology 300, G914-G926. <lb/>McMillin, M., and DeMorrow, S. (2016). Effects of bile acids on neurological function and <lb/>disease. Faseb J. 30, 3658-3668. <lb/>Mesuere, B., Debyser, G., Aerts, M., Devreese, B., Vandamme, P., and Dawyndt, P. (2015). <lb/>The Unipept metaproteomics analysis pipeline. Proteomics 15, 1437-1442. <lb/>Miano, J.M., Miano, J.M., Vlasic, N., Vlasic, N., TOTA, R.R., Tota, R.R., STEMERMAN, M.B., <lb/>and Stemerman, M.B. (1993). Smooth muscle cell immediate-early gene and growth factor <lb/>activation follows vascular injury. A putative in vivo mechanism for autocrine growth. <lb/>Arterioscler. Thromb. 13, 211-219. <lb/>Mittal, R., Debs, L.H., Patel, A.P., Nguyen, D., Patel, K., O&apos;Connor, G., Grati, M., Mittal, J., Yan, <lb/>D., Eshraghi, A.A., et al. (2017). Neurotransmitters: The Critical Modulators Regulating Gut-<lb/>Brain Axis. J. Cell. Physiol. 232, 2359-2372. <lb/>Muller, P.A., Koscsó, B., Rajani, G.M., Stevanovic, K., Berres, M.-L., Hashimoto, D., Mortha, A., <lb/>Leboeuf, M., Li, X.-M., Mucida, D., et al. (2014). Crosstalk between Muscularis Macrophages <lb/>and Enteric Neurons Regulates Gastrointestinal Motility. Cell 158, 1210. <lb/>Nishiyama, H., Nagai, T., Kudo, M., Okazaki, Y., Azuma, Y., Watanabe, T., Goto, S., Ogata, H., <lb/>and Sakurai, T. (2018). Supplementation of pancreatic digestive enzymes alters the composition <lb/>of intestinal microbiota in mice. Biochem. Biophys. Res. Commun. 495, 273-279. <lb/>Nothias, L.F., Petras, D., Schmid, R., Dührkop, K., Rainer, J., Sarvepalli, A., Protsyuk, I., Ernst, <lb/>M., Tsugawa, H., Fleischauer, M., et al. (2019). Feature-based Molecular Networking in the <lb/>GNPS Analysis Environment. bioRxiv 38, 812404. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Olson, C.A., Vuong, H.E., Yano, J.M., Liang, Q.Y., Nusbaum, D.J., and Hsiao, E.Y. (2018). The <lb/>Gut Microbiota Mediates the Anti-Seizure Effects of the Ketogenic Diet. Cell 173, 1728-<lb/>1741.e13. <lb/>Park, S.K.R., Jung, T., Thuy-Boun, P.S., Wang, A.Y., John R Yates, I., and Wolan, D.W. (2018). <lb/>ComPIL 2.0: An Updated Comprehensive Metaproteomics Database. J. Proteome Res. 18, <lb/>616-622. <lb/>Park, S.K., Venable, J.D., Xu, T., and Yates, J.R. (2008). A quantitative analysis software tool <lb/>for mass spectrometry-based proteomics. Nat. Methods 5, 319-322. <lb/>Peng, J., Elias, J.E., Thoreen, C.C., Licklider, L.J., and Gygi, S.P. (2003). Evaluation of <lb/>multidimensional chromatography coupled with tandem mass spectrometry (LC/LC-MS/MS) for <lb/>large-scale protein analysis: the yeast proteome. J. Proteome Res. 2, 43-50. <lb/>Pfeiffer, R.F. (2003). Gastrointestinal dysfunction in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Lancet Neurol 2, 107-<lb/>116. <lb/>Plovier, H., Everard, A., Druart, C., Depommier, C., Van Hul, M., Geurts, L., Chilloux, J., <lb/>Ottman, N., Duparc, T., Lichtenstein, L., et al. (2017). A purified membrane protein from <lb/>Akkermansia muciniphila or the pasteurized bacterium improves metabolism in obese and <lb/>diabetic mice. Nature Medicine 23, 107-113. <lb/>Pluskal, T., Castillo, S., Villar-Briones, A., and Oresic, M. (2010). MZmine 2: Modular framework <lb/>for processing, visualizing, and analyzing mass spectrometry-based molecular profile data. <lb/>BMC Bioinformatics 11. <lb/>Rakhilin, N., Barth, B., Choi, J., Muñoz, N.L., Kulkarni, S., Jones, J.S., Small, D.M., Cheng, Y.-<lb/>T., Cao, Y., LaVinka, C., et al. (2016). Simultaneous optical and electrical in vivo analysis of the <lb/>enteric nervous system. Nature Communications 7, 31. <lb/>Rakhilin, N., Garrett, A., Eom, C.-Y., Chavez, K.R., Small, D.M., Daniel, A.R., Kaelberer, M.M., <lb/>Mejooli, M.A., Huang, Q., Ding, S., et al. (2019). An intravital window to image the colon in real <lb/>time. Nature Communications 10, 5647-10. <lb/>Ramirez-Carrozzi, V.R., Braas, D., Bhatt, D.M., Cheng, C.S., Hong, C., Doty, K.R., Black, J.C., <lb/>Hoffmann, A., Carey, M., and Smale, S.T. (2009). A Unifying Model for the Selective Regulation <lb/>of Inducible Transcription by CpG Islands and Nucleosome Remodeling. Cell 138, 114-128. <lb/>Rao, M., and Gershon, M.D. (2016). The bowel and beyond: the enteric nervous system in <lb/>neurological disorders. Nature Reviews Gastroenterology and Hepatology 13, 517-528. <lb/>Ritchie, M.E., Phipson, B., Wu, D., Hu, Y., Law, C.W., Shi, W., and Smyth, G.K. (2015). limma <lb/>powers differential expression analyses for RNA-sequencing and microarray studies. Nucleic <lb/>Acids Res 43, e47-e47. <lb/>Rodríguez-Piñeiro, A.M., Bergström, J.H., Ermund, A., Gustafsson, J.K., Schütte, A., <lb/>Johansson, M.E.V., and Hansson, G.C. (2013). Studies of mucus in mouse stomach, small <lb/>intestine, and colon. II. Gastrointestinal mucus proteome reveals Muc2 and Muc5ac <lb/>accompanied by a set of core proteins. American Journal of Physiology -Gastrointestinal and <lb/>Liver Physiology 305, G348-G356. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Sakai, K., Makino, T., Kawai, Y., and Mutai, M. (1980). Intestinal microflora and bile acids. Effect <lb/>of bile acids on the distribution of microflora and bile acid in the digestive tract of the rat. <lb/>Microbiol. Immunol. 24, 187-196. <lb/>Samulski, R.J., and Muzyczka, N. (2014). AAV-Mediated Gene Therapy for Research and <lb/>Therapeutic Purposes. Annu Rev Virol 1, 427-451. <lb/>Sang, Q., and Young, H.M. (1998). The identification and chemical coding of cholinergic <lb/>neurons in the small and large intestine of the mouse. Anat. Rec. 251, 185-199. <lb/>Sannasiddappa, T.H., Lund, P.A., and Clarke, S.R. (2017). In Vitro Antibacterial Activity of <lb/>Unconjugated and Conjugated Bile Salts on Staphylococcus aureus. Front. Microbio. 8, 1581. <lb/>Schneider, S., Wright, C.M., and Heuckeroth, R.O. (2019). Unexpected Roles for the Second <lb/>Brain: Enteric Nervous System as Master Regulator of Bowel Function. Annu. Rev. Physiol. 81, <lb/>235-259. <lb/>Segata, N., Izard, J., Waldron, L., Gevers, D., Miropolsky, L., Garrett, W.S., and Huttenhower, <lb/>C. (2011). Metagenomic biomarker discovery and explanation. Genome Biol 12, R60. <lb/>Seillet, C., Luong, K., Tellier, J., Jacquelot, N., Shen, R.D., Hickey, P., Wimmer, V.C., <lb/>Whitehead, L., Rogers, K., Smyth, G.K., et al. (2020). The neuropeptide VIP confers anticipatory <lb/>mucosal immunity by regulating ILC3 activity. Nat Immunol 21, 168-177. <lb/>Sinha, R., Stanley, G., Gulati, G.S., Ezran, C., Travaglini, K.J., Wei, E., Chan, C.K.F., Nabhan, <lb/>A.N., Su, T., Morganti, R.M., et al. (2017). Index switching causes &quot;spreading-of-signal&quot; among <lb/>multiplexed samples in Illumina HiSeq 4000 DNA sequencing. 29, 1072-29. <lb/>Steele, P.A., Brookes, S.J., and Costa, M. (1991). Immunohistochemical identification of <lb/>cholinergic neurons in the myenteric plexus of guinea-pig small intestine. Neuroscience 45, <lb/>227-239. <lb/>Sumner, L.W., Amberg, A., Barrett, D., Beale, M.H., Beger, R., Daykin, C.A., Fan, T.W.M., <lb/>Fiehn, O., Goodacre, R., Griffin, J.L., et al. (2007). Proposed minimum reporting standards for <lb/>chemical analysis Chemical Analysis Working Group (CAWG) Metabolomics Standards <lb/>Initiative (MSI). Metabolomics 3, 211-221. <lb/>Sundararajan, Z., Knoll, R., Hombach, P., Becker, M., Schultze, J.L., and Ulas, T. (2019). Shiny-<lb/>Seq: advanced guided transcriptome analysis. BMC Res Notes 12, 432-435. <lb/>Suzek, B.E., Huang, H., McGarvey, P., Mazumder, R., and Wu, C.H. (2007). UniRef: <lb/>comprehensive and non-redundant UniProt reference clusters. Bioinformatics 23, 1282-1288. <lb/>Szklarczyk, D., Gable, A.L., Lyon, D., Junge, A., Wyder, S., Huerta-Cepas, J., Simonovic, M., <lb/>Doncheva, N.T., Morris, J.H., Bork, P., et al. (2019). STRING v11: protein-protein association <lb/>networks with increased coverage, supporting functional discovery in genome-wide <lb/>experimental datasets. Nucleic Acids Res 47, D607-D613. <lb/>Tabb, D.L., McDonald, W.H., and Yates, J.R. (2002). DTASelect and Contrast: tools for <lb/>assembling and comparing protein identifications from shotgun proteomics. J. Proteome Res. 1, <lb/>21-26. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Talbot, J., Hahn, P., Kroehling, L., Nguyen, H., Li, D., and Littman, D.R. (2020). Feeding-<lb/>dependent VIP neuron-ILC3 circuit regulates the intestinal barrier. Nature 579, 575-580. <lb/>Thompson, K.J., Khajehali, E., Bradley, S.J., Navarrete, J.S., Huang, X.P., Slocum, S., Jin, J., <lb/>Liu, J., Xiong, Y., Olsen, R.H.J., et al. (2018). DREADD Agonist 21 Is an Effective Agonist for <lb/>Muscarinic-Based DREADDs in Vitro and in Vivo. ACS Pharmacol Transl Sci 1, 61-72. <lb/>Treweek, J.B., Chan, K.Y., Flytzanis, N.C., Yang, B., Deverman, B.E., Greenbaum, A., Lignell, <lb/>A., Xiao, C., Cai, L., Ladinsky, M.S., et al. (2015). Whole-body tissue stabilization and selective <lb/>extractions via tissue-hydrogel hybrids for high-resolution intact circuit mapping and <lb/>phenotyping. Nature Protocols 10, 1860-1896. <lb/>Truong, D.T., Franzosa, E.A., Tickle, T.L., Scholz, M., Weingart, G., Pasolli, E., Tett, A., <lb/>Huttenhower, C., and Segata, N. (2015). MetaPhlAn2 for enhanced metagenomic taxonomic <lb/>profiling. Nat. Methods 12, 902-903. <lb/>Valicenti-McDermott, M.D., McVicar, K., Cohen, H.J., Wershil, B.K., and Shinnar, S. (2008). <lb/>Gastrointestinal symptoms in children with an autism spectrum disorder and language <lb/>regression. Pediatr. Neurol. 39, 392-398. <lb/>Van Herreweghen, F., Van den Abbeele, P., De Mulder, T., De Weirdt, R., Geirnaert, A., <lb/>Hernandez-Sanabria, E., Vilchez-Vargas, R., Jauregui, R., Pieper, D.H., Belzer, C., et al. <lb/>(2017). In vitro colonisation of the distal colon by Akkermansia muciniphila is largely mucin and <lb/>pH dependent. Benef Microbes 8, 81-96. <lb/>Vavassori, P., Mencarelli, A., Renga, B., Distrutti, E., and Fiorucci, S. (2009). The bile acid <lb/>receptor FXR is a modulator of intestinal innate immunity. J Immunol 183, 6251-6261. <lb/>Walsh, K.T., and Zemper, A.E. (2019). The Enteric Nervous System for Epithelial Researchers: <lb/>Basic Anatomy, Techniques, and Interactions With the Epithelium. Cellular and Molecular <lb/>Gastroenterology and Hepatology 8, 369-378. <lb/>Wang, M., Carver, J.J., Phelan, V.V., Sanchez, L.M., Garg, N., Peng, Y., Nguyen, D.D., <lb/>Watrous, J., Kapono, C.A., Luzzatto-Knaan, T., et al. (2016). Sharing and community curation of <lb/>mass spectrometry data with Global Natural Products Social Molecular Networking. Nat <lb/>Biotechnol 34, 828-837. <lb/>Watanabe, M., Houten, S.M., Mataki, C., Christoffolete, M.A., Kim, B.W., Sato, H., Messaddeq, <lb/>N., Harney, J.W., Ezaki, O., Kodama, T., et al. (2006). Bile acids induce energy expenditure by <lb/>promoting intracellular thyroid hormone activation. Nature 439, 484-489. <lb/>Wess, J., Nakajima, K., and Jain, S. (2013). Novel designer receptors to probe GPCR signaling <lb/>and physiology. Trends Pharmacol. Sci. 34, 385-392. <lb/>Wessel, D., and Flügge, U.I. (1984). A method for the quantitative recovery of protein in dilute <lb/>solution in the presence of detergents and lipids. Analytical Biochemistry 138, 141-143. <lb/>Whitcomb, D.C., and Lowe, M.E. (2007). Human pancreatic digestive enzymes. Dig. Dis. Sci. <lb/>52, 1-17. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Wu, Y.E., Pan, L., Zuo, Y., Li, X., and Hong, W. (2017). Detecting Activated Cell Populations <lb/>Using Single-Cell RNA-Seq. Neuron 96, 313-329.e316. <lb/>Xu, T., Park, S.K., Venable, J.D., Wohlschlegel, J.A., Diedrich, J.K., Cociorva, D., Lu, B., Liao, <lb/>L., Hewel, J., Han, X., et al. (2015). ProLuCID: An improved SEQUEST-like algorithm with <lb/>enhanced sensitivity and specificity. J Proteomics 129, 16-24. <lb/>Xu, T., Venable, J.D., Park, S.K., Cociorva, D., Lu, Q.B., Liao, L., Wohlschlegel, J., Hewel, J., <lb/>Yates, J.R., and Conciorva, D. (2006). ProLuCID, a fast and sensitive tandem mass spectra-<lb/>based protein identification program. <lb/>Yang, B., Treweek, J.B., Kulkarni, R.P., Deverman, B.E., Chen, C.-K., Lubeck, E., Shah, S., <lb/>Cai, L., and Gradinaru, V. (2014). Single-Cell Phenotyping within Transparent Intact Tissue <lb/>through Whole-Body Clearing. Cell 158, 945-958. <lb/>Yano, J.M., Yu, K., Donaldson, G.P., Shastri, G.G., Ann, P., Ma, L., Nagler, C.R., Ismagilov, <lb/>R.F., Mazmanian, S.K., and Hsiao, E.Y. (2015). Indigenous Bacteria from the Gut Microbiota <lb/>Regulate Host Serotonin Biosynthesis. Cell 161, 264-276. <lb/>Zhang, H., Sparks, J.B., Karyala, S.V., Settlage, R., and Luo, X.M. (2015). Host adaptive <lb/>immunity alters gut microbiota. Isme J 9, 770-781. <lb/>Zhang, X., Smits, A.H., van Tilburg, G.B., Ovaa, H., Huber, W., and Vermeulen, M. (2018). <lb/>Proteome-wide identification of ubiquitin interactions using UbIA-MS. Nature Protocols 13, 530-<lb/>550. <lb/>Zhu, Q., Mai, U., Pfeiffer, W., Janssen, S., Asnicar, F., Sanders, J.G., Belda-Ferre, P., Al-<lb/>Ghalith, G.A., Kopylova, E., McDonald, D., et al. (2019). Phylogenomics of 10,575 genomes <lb/>reveals evolutionary proximity between domains Bacteria and Archaea. Nature Communications <lb/>10, 5477-14. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder. All rights reserved. No reuse allowed without permission. <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint (which <lb/>this version posted April 13, 2021. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.04.12.439539 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint </note>


	</text>
</tei>
