<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Presynaptic autophagy is coupled to the synaptic <lb/>vesicle cycle via ATG-9 <lb/>Authors: Sisi Yang 1 , Daehun Park 1,2 , Laura Manning 1 , Sarah E. Hill 1 , Mian Cao 1,2 , <lb/>Zhao Xuan 1 , Ian Gonzalez 1 , Lin Shao 1 , Ifechukwu Okeke 5 , Pietro De Camilli 1,2,4 <lb/>and Daniel A. Colón-Ramos 1,3* <lb/>Affiliations: <lb/>1 <lb/>Program in Cellular Neuroscience, Neurodegeneration and Repair, Departments <lb/>of Neuroscience and Cell Biology, Yale University School of Medicine, 333 Cedar <lb/>Street, SHMB-156, New Haven, CT 06511, USA <lb/>2 <lb/>Howard Hughes Medical Institute, Yale University School of Medicine, New <lb/>Haven, CT 06510, USA <lb/>3 <lb/>Instituto de Neurobiología, Recinto de Ciencias Médicas, Universidad de Puerto <lb/>Rico, 201 Boulevard del Valle, San Juan 00901, Puerto Rico <lb/>4 <lb/>Kavli Institute for Neuroscience, Yale University School of Medicine, New <lb/>Haven, CT 06510, USA <lb/>5 <lb/>Department of Molecular and Cell Biology, University of California, Berkeley, <lb/>Berkeley, CA 94720, USA <lb/>*Correspondence to: <lb/>Daniel A. Colón-Ramos, Ph.D. <lb/>Department of Neuroscience <lb/>Department of Cell Biology <lb/>Yale University School of Medicine <lb/>333 Cedar Street <lb/>SHM B 163D <lb/>New Haven, CT 06510 <lb/>Email: daniel.colon-ramos@yale.edu <lb/>Twitter: @dacolon <lb/>. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/>Highlights <lb/>In C. elegans, ATG-9 is delivered to presynaptic sites in vesicles generated <lb/>from the trans-Golgi network via AP-3-dependent budding <lb/>ATG-9 vesicles undergo activity-dependent exo-endocytosis at presynaptic <lb/>sites <lb/>Mutations in endocytic proteins, including a mutation associated with <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease, result in abnormal ATG-9 accumulation at clathrin-rich <lb/>foci <lb/>Abnormal accumulation of ATG-9 at clathrin-rich foci is associated with <lb/>defects in activity-dependent presynaptic autophagy <lb/>Keywords <lb/>Autophagy, endocytosis, neuronal activity, synaptic vesicle cycle, ATG-9, AP-3, <lb/>Golgi apparatus, synaptojanin-1/UNC-26, clathrin, Parkinson&apos;s disease <lb/>. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<front>Summary <lb/>Autophagy is a cellular degradation pathway essential for neuronal health <lb/>and function. Autophagosome biogenesis occurs at synapses, is locally regulated <lb/>and increases in response to neuronal activity. The mechanisms that couple <lb/>autophagosome biogenesis to synaptic activity remain unknown. In this study we <lb/>determine that trafficking of ATG-9, the only transmembrane protein in the core <lb/>autophagy pathway, links the synaptic vesicle cycle with autophagy. ATG-9 <lb/>positive vesicles in C. elegans are generated from the trans-Golgi network via AP3-<lb/>dependent budding, and delivered to presynaptic sites. At presynaptic sites, ATG-<lb/>9 undergoes exo-endocytosis in an activity-dependent manner. Mutations that <lb/>disrupt endocytosis, including one associated with Parkinson&apos;s disease, result in <lb/>abnormal ATG-9 accumulation at clathrin-rich synaptic foci and defects in activity-<lb/>dependent presynaptic autophagy. Our findings uncover regulated key steps of <lb/>ATG-9 trafficking at presynaptic sites, and provide evidence that ATG-9 exo-<lb/>endocytosis couples autophagosome biogenesis at presynaptic sites with the <lb/>activity-dependent synaptic vesicle cycle. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Macroautophagy (herein called autophagy) is an evolutionarily conserved <lb/>cellular degradative process that is essential for neuronal physiology and survival <lb/>(Son et al., 2012, Stavoe and Holzbaur, 2019, Azarnia Tehran et al., 2018, Kulkarni <lb/>et al., 2018, Liang and Sigrist, 2018, Menzies et al., 2017, Vijayan and Verstreken, <lb/>2017, Menzies et al., 2015, Tsukada and Ohsumi, 1993, Yorimitsu and Klionsky, <lb/>2005). Neurons are particularly vulnerable to dysfunctional organelles and <lb/>damaged proteins due to their post-mitotic nature, their polarized morphology and <lb/>their high metabolic activity states during neuronal stimulation. Autophagy is <lb/>regulated to cater to these neurophysiological needs. For example, local <lb/>autophagosome biogenesis occurs near synapses and autophagosome <lb/>biogenesis is coupled to the neuronal activity state (Bunge, 1973, Soukup et al., <lb/>2016, Maday et al., 2012, Stavoe et al., 2016, Katsumata et al., 2010, Shehata et <lb/>al., 2012, Hill et al., 2019). Disruption of synaptic autophagy has been associated <lb/>with the accumulation of damaged proteins and organelles, synaptic dysfunction <lb/>and neurodegenerative diseases, including Parkinson&apos;s disease (Hoffmann et al., <lb/>2019, Hill et al., 2019, Lynch-Day et al., 2012, Zavodszky et al., 2014, Karabiyik et <lb/>al., 2017, Cheung and Ip, 2009). <lb/>Molecules that regulate synaptic transmission and function, including <lb/>proteins involved in synaptic vesicle exo-endocytosis, were reported to regulate <lb/>autophagy at presynaptic sites (Soukup et al., 2016, George et al., 2016, <lb/>Vanhauwaert et al., 2017, Murdoch et al., 2016, Kononenko et al., 2017, Binotti et <lb/>al., 2015). For example, in Drosophila, endophilin A, a protein mainly known for its <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>role in endocytosis, was proposed to directly regulate autophagosome formation <lb/>by inducing curved membranes that can recruit autophagic machinery (Soukup et <lb/>al., 2016, Milosevic et al., 2011). Synaptojanin 1, a phosphoinositide phosphatase <lb/>implicated in the endocytic recycling of synaptic vesicles (Cremona et al., 1999, <lb/>Verstreken et al., 2003, Harris et al., 2000), was also reported to play roles in the <lb/>control of synaptic autophagy in zebrafish and Drosophila (Vanhauwaert et al., <lb/>2017, George et al., 2016). Recent studies have revealed links between these <lb/>canonical endocytic proteins and early-onset parkinsonism (EOP), suggesting a <lb/>relationship between the synaptic vesicle cycle (which is tied to synaptic activity), <lb/>autophagy and neurodegenerative diseases (Vidyadhara et al., 2019, Trinh and <lb/>Farrer, 2013, Alegre-Abarrategui and Wade-Martins, 2009, Bandres-Ciga et al., <lb/>2019, Schreij et al., 2016, Quadri et al., 2013, Krebs et al., 2013). Yet, the <lb/>mechanistic links underlying the coupling between synaptic activity and <lb/>autophagosome formation remain unknown. <lb/>In this study we examined the dynamics of ATG-9, the only transmembrane <lb/>protein of the core autophagy machinery, at synapses of C. elegans and <lb/>mammalian neurons. ATG-9 is thought to promote local autophagosome <lb/>biogenesis through its role as a lipid scramblase that cooperates with the lipid <lb/>transport protein ATG2 in the nucleation of the isolation membrane in nascent <lb/>autophagosomes (Karanasios et al., 2016, Reggiori et al., 2005, Reggiori et al., <lb/>2004, Sawa-Makarska et al., 2020, Guardia et al., 2020, Matoba et al., 2020, <lb/>Matoba and Noda, 2020, Maeda et al., 2020, Gomez-Sanchez et al., 2018). We <lb/>find that at synapses, ATG-9 links the synaptic vesicle cycle to autophagy. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Specifically, we observe that in C. elegans neurons, ATG-9 is delivered to <lb/>presynaptic sites in vesicles generated by the trans-Golgi network (TGN) via AP-<lb/>3-dependent budding. At presynaptic sites, ATG-9 positive vesicles undergo exo-<lb/>endocytosis in a synaptic activity-dependent manner. Mutants that disrupt synaptic <lb/>endocytic traffic, including a synaptojanin 1/unc-26 allele that mimics a Parkinson <lb/>disease mutation, result in abnormal accumulation of ATG-9 in clathrin-rich foci, <lb/>and defects in activity-dependent synaptic autophagy. Mutations that affect <lb/>autophagosome biogenesis also result in abnormal accumulations of ATG-9 in <lb/>clathrin-rich foci, further suggesting a relation between endocytic trafficking of <lb/>ATG-9 and nucleation of autophagosomes at presynaptic sites. In mammalian <lb/>hippocampal neurons, mutations in endocytic proteins similarly result in abnormal <lb/>ATG9 accumulation in nerve terminals, indicating conserved mechanisms of ATG-<lb/>9 trafficking at synapses. Collectively our studies identify the regulated dynamics <lb/>of ATG-9 trafficking at presynaptic sites and provide insight into mechanisms that <lb/>couple the synaptic vesicle cycle (related to synaptic activity) to presynaptic <lb/>autophagy. <lb/>Results <lb/>In C. elegans ATG-9 is transported to synapses in vesicles generated in the <lb/>trans-Golgi network (TGN) via AP-3-dependent budding. <lb/>Autophagy occurs at presynaptic sites in response to synaptic activity, and <lb/>transmembrane protein ATG-9 plays a critical role in local synaptic autophagy <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(Stavoe et al., 2016, Hill et al., 2019, Soukup et al., 2016, Wang et al., 2015, <lb/>Shehata et al., 2012). To understand the dynamics of ATG-9 at presynaptic sites, <lb/>we first examined the in vivo localization of ATG-9 in the AIY interneurons of C. <lb/>elegans. AIYs are a pair of bilaterally symmetric interneurons which display a <lb/>stereotypical distribution of presynaptic specializations along their neurites ((White <lb/>et al., 1986, Colon-Ramos et al., 2007); (Figures 1A-1B)). Simultaneous <lb/>visualization of the presynaptic marker mCherry::RAB-3 and ATG-9::GFP revealed <lb/>that ATG-9 localization in neurons is discrete, compartmentalized and enriched at <lb/>subcellular structures in the cell body and at presynaptic regions ((Stavoe et al., <lb/>2016); (Figures 1C-1F, 1C&apos;)). <lb/>To identify ATG-9 positive structures at synapses, we performed post-<lb/>embedding immunogold electron microscopy of transgenic animals expressing <lb/>ATG-9::GFP, by using antibodies directed against GFP. We observed that the <lb/>majority of the immunogold particles (75%) localized to the presynaptic areas <lb/>occupied by synaptic vesicles, with occasional localization of gold particles on the <lb/>plasma membrane (&lt;10%) (Figures 1G, S1A-S1D). However, the distribution of <lb/>immunogold particles was generally non-homogeneous in the synaptic vesicle-<lb/>positive areas. Accordingly, comparison by light microscopy with the localization <lb/>of mCherry::RAB-3 and of a well-established synaptic vesicle integral membrane <lb/>protein, SNG-1::BFP, revealed strong colocalization between mCherry::RAB-3 <lb/>and SNG-1::BFP, but subtle differences between the colocalization of these two <lb/>proteins and ATG-9::GFP (Figures 1H-1K), consistent with ATG-9 being enriched <lb/>on a subpopulation of vesicles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>To determine the site of ATG-9 localization within the cell soma, we co-<lb/>expressed either ATG-9::mCherry or ATG-9::GFP with other organelle markers <lb/>(Reggiori et al., 2005, Karanasios et al., 2016, van der Vaart and Reggiori, 2010, <lb/>Puri et al., 2013). We observed that ATG-9::GFP was concentrated at sites that <lb/>overlapped with trans-Golgi marker TGN-38::mCherry and that ATG-9::mCherry <lb/>was directly adjacent to the medial/cis-Golgi marker AMAN-2::GFP, but did not <lb/>overlap with other organelles markers (Figures 1L-1R, 1L&apos;, S1E-S1K). These <lb/>findings, which are consistent with observations from yeast and mammalian culture <lb/>cells (Noda, 2017, Webber et al., 2007, Ohashi and Munro, 2010), indicate a trans-<lb/>Golgi-specific enrichment of ATG-9 in the neuronal cell body. <lb/>The trans-Golgi network (TGN) is where vesicles destined for transport to <lb/>distinct subcellular locations are packaged. Coat protein complexes such as <lb/>members of the heterotetrameric family of adaptor proteins (APs) regulate this <lb/>process by sorting cargoes into distinct vesicular carriers (Park and Guo, 2014, <lb/>Nakatsu and Ohno, 2003, Mattera et al., 2017, Badolato and Parolini, 2007, <lb/>Dell&apos;Angelica et al., 1997). In vertebrate, AP-4 is particularly important in exporting <lb/>transmembrane protein ATG9A from the Golgi apparatus, leading to neurological <lb/>disorders (Yamamoto et al., 2012, De Pace et al., 2018, Mattera et al., 2017). In <lb/>C. elegans and other invertebrates, however, no orthologues of AP-4 have been <lb/>characterized. Which proteins are then required for the biogenesis of ATG-9 <lb/>positive vesicles? <lb/>We tested mutants for AP complexes UNC-101/AP-1, DPY-23/AP-2 and <lb/>AP-3 (Park and Guo, 2014, Nakatsu and Ohno, 2003) and did not observe <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>abnormal localization of ATG-9 in loss-of-function alleles of unc-101(m1)/ap-1 or <lb/>dpy-23(e840)/ap-2 (data not shown). However, a putative null allele for apb-<lb/>3(ok429), a gene encoding a subunit of the AP-3 complex, displayed a reduction <lb/>of ATG-9 at synapses (Figures 1S-1U, 1X). The AP-3 complex comprises four <lb/>subunits -apb-3/β3-adaptin, apd-3/δ-adaptin, apm-3/μ3 and aps-3/σ3. Putative <lb/>null alleles for the three AP-3 complex subunits (apb-3/β3-adaptin, apm-3/μ3, apd-<lb/>3/δ-adaptin) resulted in enrichment of ATG-9 at the cell body (Figure 1Y). <lb/>Interestingly, these alleles did not affect the localization of the synaptic vesicle <lb/>proteins SNG-1 or RAB-3 to presynaptic sites, suggesting that the observed <lb/>decrease of ATG-9 at synapses is not due to a general problem in synaptic vesicle <lb/>biogenesis (Figures 1V-1W, 1Z, S1L-S1O). Together, our findings reveal that in <lb/>vivo in C. elegans neurons, enrichment of ATG-9 at presynaptic sites results from <lb/>AP-3 mediated export of ATG-9 positive vesicles at the TGN. <lb/>ATG-9 undergoes exo-endocytosis at presynaptic sites. <lb/>The concentration of ATG-9 on vesicles at presynaptic sites and its <lb/>occasional localization in the axonal plasma membrane raised the possibility that <lb/>this protein may be a component of vesicles that undergo exo-endocytosis. To <lb/>address this possibility, we imaged ATG-9 synaptic localization in C. elegans <lb/>neurons in mutants with disrupted exo-endocytic traffic at presynaptic sites (Harris <lb/>et al., 2000, Watanabe et al., 2014, Sudhof, 1995, Saheki and De Camilli, 2012) <lb/>(Figure 2A). We observed that endocytic mutants unc-26(e205)/synaptojanin 1, <lb/>unc-57(ok310)/endophilin A, unc-11(e47)/AP180 and temperature-sensitive dyn-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/> The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>1(ky51) displayed defects in ATG-9 localization at synapses (Figures 2B-2H). For <lb/>example, in the AIY interneuron presynaptic-rich region (termed Zone 2; (Colon-<lb/>Ramos et al., 2007)), the ATG-9::GFP signal is predominantly concentrated in a <lb/>homogenous manner across this presynaptic area (Figures 1E, 1K, 2B-2B&apos;, 2C). <lb/>However, in all the endocytic mutants examined, most animals display abnormal <lb/>accumulation of ATG-9::GFP into multiple subsynaptic foci (Figures 2D-2H, 2SA-<lb/>B). To quantify the genetic expressivity of the phenotype, we defined an index for <lb/>ATG-9 mislocalization (briefly, the index was defined as the number of local signal <lb/>peaks divided by their width, see STAR Methods). We found that in the endocytic <lb/>mutants there was a significant difference in the subsynaptic localization of ATG-<lb/>9, with ATG-9 abnormally enriched at discrete foci within the presynaptic regions <lb/>(Figure 2K). <lb/>Are endocytic proteins acting cell autonomously in neurons to regulate <lb/>ATG-9 subsynaptic localization? To address this question, we focused on UNC-<lb/>26/synaptojanin-1. Expressing unc-26 cDNA cell specifically in the AIY <lb/>interneurons of unc-26(e205) mutants rescued ATG-9 defects at the synapse, <lb/>indicating that UNC-26 acts cell autonomously in neurons to prevent abnormal <lb/>ATG-9 accumulation at subsynaptic foci (Figures S2C-S2E). <lb/>If the accumulation of ATG-9 at abnormal foci in endocytic mutants is due <lb/>to abnormal endocytic traffic, then mutants in exocytosis should suppress this <lb/>phenotype. To test this hypothesis, we examined putative null alleles unc-<lb/>13(s69)/Munc13 and unc-18(e81)/Munc18, which encode essential components <lb/>of synaptic vesicle exocytosis (Hata et al., 1993, Richmond et al., 1999). Single <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>mutants of unc-13(s69) and unc-18(e81) did not disrupt ATG-9 localization <lb/>(Figures S2A, S2F-S2G). Importantly, double mutants of unc-13(s69);unc-<lb/>26(e205) and unc-18(e81);unc-26(s1710) suppressed the unc-26/synaptojanin 1 <lb/>phenotype, indicating that the accumulation of ATG-9 at abnormal foci depends on <lb/>synaptic vesicle exocytosis (Figures 2I-2K, S2A). <lb/>Our genetic perturbations in C. elegans are consistent with ATG-9 positive <lb/>vesicles undergoing exo-endocytosis at presynaptic sites. To better examine this, <lb/>we imaged ATG-9 dynamics in a loss-of-function allele of phosphofructokinase <lb/>1/pfk-1.1(gk922689). The absence of phosphofructokinase, like the absence of <lb/>other glycolytic proteins, results in impaired synaptic vesicle endocytosis during <lb/>transient hypoxia (Jang et al., 2016). Through the use of a microfluidic device that <lb/>allows precise control of transient cycles of normoxia and hypoxia, we can <lb/>temporally control the endocytic reaction (Jang et al., 2020). We examined ATG-9 <lb/>localization in the synaptic Zone 3 region (Figure L-L&apos;), in which we can observe <lb/>discrete and interspersed presynaptic specializations (compare to the Zone 2 <lb/>region (Figure 2B-B&apos;), which consists of one large and continuous presynaptic <lb/>area). Visualization of ATG-9 in the Zone 3 region enabled us to determine local <lb/>ATG-9 dynamics due to transient inhibition of endocytosis. We observed that in <lb/>pfk-1.1(gk922689) mutants, transient inhibition of endocytosis during transient <lb/>hypoxia correlated with changes in ATG-9 localization: namely, ATG-9 relocalized <lb/>from discrete presynaptic clusters in the synaptic Zone 3 region, to a more diffuse <lb/>distribution, consistent with what would be expected if ATG-9 were trapped at the <lb/>plasma membrane due to short-term defects in endocytosis. Conversely, removing <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>the endocytic block by shifting to normoxia rescued the localization of ATG-9 to <lb/>the presynaptic clusters (Figures 2L-2M). Together, our data indicate that ATG-9 <lb/>positive vesicles undergo exo-endocytosis at presynaptic sites by using the <lb/>synaptic vesicle cycling machinery. <lb/>ATG-9 mislocalization phenotypes are enhanced under conditions that <lb/>increase AIY activity-state. <lb/>We next examined if the mislocalization phenotype of ATG-9 could be <lb/>modified based on physiologically relevant stimuli known to increase the activity <lb/>state of the neuron, and known to increase synaptic autophagy (Hill et al., 2019). <lb/>AIY neurons in C. elegans are part of the thermotaxis circuit, which allows animals <lb/>to navigate towards their cultivation temperature, and the activity state of AIY <lb/>increases based on the cultivation temperature at which the organism is reared <lb/>(Clark et al., 2006, Hawk et al., 2018). At higher cultivation temperatures, AIY <lb/>displays increases in activity-dependent synaptic autophagy (Hill et al., 2019). <lb/>We observed that the penetrance of the ATG-9 phenotype in unc-<lb/>26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutants similarly varied depending on the cultivation <lb/>temperature of the animals. At higher cultivation temperatures, known to increase <lb/>the activity state of AIY and synaptic autophagy, we observed a higher percentage <lb/>of unc-26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutant animals displaying abnormal ATG-9 foci <lb/>at synapses (Figure 2N). Moreover, temperature-dependent increases of <lb/>abnormal ATG-9 foci in unc-26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutant animals were <lb/>suppressed by the exocytosis mutant unc-13(s69) (Figure 2N). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/> The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Biochemical evidence that ATG9 travels to and from the plasma membrane. <lb/>Our results are consistent with published evidence that ATG-9 can be <lb/>exposed at the cell surface and then re-internalized by endocytosis in mammalian <lb/>fibroblastic cells, as revealed by immunocytochemistry following perturbation of a <lb/>critical endocytic factor, dynamin, either pharmacologically or by dominant <lb/>interference (Puri et al., 2013, Feng and Klionsky, 2017, Zhou et al., 2017). To <lb/>obtain direct biochemical evidence for ATG9 exo-endocytosis, we performed cell <lb/>surface biotinylation experiments (with Sulfo-NHS-LC-Biotin) in tamoxifen-<lb/>inducible dynamin 1 and 2 double knock-out (DKO) mouse fibroblasts (Ferguson <lb/>et al., 2009). A pool of ATG9A, and of transferrin receptor as a control, was <lb/>detected at the plasma membrane in control fibroblasts, and these pools were <lb/>enhanced (Figures 3A-3C) in fibroblasts where the expression of dynamin 1 and 2 <lb/>had been suppressed by tamoxifen (Figures S3A-S3B), providing biochemical <lb/>evidence that ATG-9 travels to and from the plasma membrane, and that its <lb/>internalization depends on endocytic proteins. <lb/>In unc-26/synaptojanin 1 mutants, ATG-9 accumulates at presynaptic, <lb/>clathrin-rich sites. <lb/>What are the subsynaptic foci where ATG-9 is enriched in endocytic <lb/>mutants? We first examined if ATG-9 accumulated with synaptic vesicles proteins <lb/>in such foci. Defects in the endocytic pathway result in the redistribution of synaptic <lb/>vesicle membrane proteins to the plasma membrane and endocytic intermediates, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>which is reflected in a less clustered localization of intrinsic and peripheral synaptic <lb/>vesicle proteins in neurites (Harris et al., 2000, Verstreken et al., 2003, Ferguson <lb/>et al., 2007, Raimondi et al., 2011, Milosevic et al., 2011). Consistent with these <lb/>findings, RAB-3::mCherry and SNG-1::GFP displayed diffuse localization in unc-<lb/>26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutants (Figures S3C-S3F). These phenotypes are <lb/>distinct from the ones observed for ATG-9, as SNG-1::BFP in unc-26(s1710) <lb/>mutants failed to localize similarly to ATG-9::GFP at subsynaptic foci (Figures 3D-<lb/>3F, 3M). Our data indicate that while ATG-9 undergoes exo-endocytosis at the <lb/>synapse in an activity dependent manner, mutations in endocytic proteins affect <lb/>ATG-9 and a bona fide synaptic vesicle protein differently. <lb/>We next examined if ATG-9 was abnormally localized to immature <lb/>autophagosomes. Simultaneous imaging of ATG-9::mCherry and of the <lb/>autophagosome marker, GFP::LGG-1/Atg8/GABARAP (Alberti et al., 2010, Manil-<lb/>Segalen et al., 2014, Wu et al., 2015, Stavoe et al., 2016, Hill et al., 2019) in the <lb/>unc-26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutants did not reveal enrichment on the same <lb/>compartments. However, they sometimes appeared adjacent to each other <lb/>(Figures 3G-3I, 3M). <lb/>Synaptojanin plays conserved roles in clathrin-mediated endocytosis, and <lb/>in C. elegans, Drosophila and vertebrates, mutations in synaptojanin result in the <lb/>accumulation of clathrin-coated, abnormal endocytic intermediates (Harris et al., <lb/>2000, Verstreken et al., 2003, Cremona et al., 1999, Kim et al., 2002). We <lb/>examined the relationship between ATG-9 and clathrin by simultaneously imaging <lb/>ATG-9::GFP and BFP::CHC-1/Clathrin Heavy Chain in the AIY interneurons of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>wild-type animals and unc-26(s1710)/synaptojanin 1 mutant animals. We found <lb/>that in the unc-26(s1710) mutants, CHC-1 localized to abnormal foci at synapses <lb/>(Figures 3K, S3G) and it colocalized well with ATG-9 (Figures 3J-3M). Based on <lb/>previous findings (Harris et al., 2000, Cremona et al., 1999, Verstreken et al., <lb/>2003), these clathrin-rich foci at the synapses probably represent abnormal <lb/>endocytic intermediates (Figures 3J-3M). <lb/>To sum up, ATG-9 accumulates at presynaptic clathrin-rich structures in <lb/>unc-26/synaptojanin 1 mutants. <lb/>In autophagy mutants, ATG-9 accumulates into endocytic intermediates at <lb/>presynaptic sites. <lb/>The critical role of ATG-9 in autophagy predicts that disruption of autophagy <lb/>should impact ATG-9 localization (Reggiori et al., 2004, Sekito et al., 2009, Lu et <lb/>al., 2011). Thus, we also examined ATG-9 localization in mutants with disrupted <lb/>autophagy (Figure 4A). In loss-of-function alleles unc-51(e369)/ATG1, epg-<lb/>9(bp320)/Atg101, atg-13(bp414)/epg-1 and epg-8(bp251)/Atg14 (Crawley et al., <lb/>2019, Liang et al., 2012, Huang et al., 2013) that affect early steps of <lb/>autophagosome initiation, we observed abnormal focal accumulation of ATG-9 at <lb/>presynaptic sites (Figures 4B-4G). Similar to unc-26 mutants, the abnormal focal <lb/>accumulation of ATG-9::GFP in epg-9(bp414) autophagy mutants co-localized <lb/>with clathrin heavy chain BFP::CHC-1 (Figures 4I-4K). <lb/>Is the abnormal localization of ATG-9 in early autophagy mutants affected <lb/>under conditions of increased synaptic activity state and autophagy? We examined <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>ATG-9 in epg-9(bp414) mutants reared at 15°C, 20°C and 25°C, and found that <lb/>the penetrance of the ATG-9 phenotype in the AIY interneurons of epg-9(bp414) <lb/>mutants varied according to the cultivation temperature of the animals (which <lb/>relates to the activity state of the AIY interneuron (Clark et al., 2006, Hawk et al., <lb/>2018); (Figure 4H)). The effects of temperature on the abnormal localization of <lb/>ATG-9 to foci in autophagy mutants are similar to those observed for ATG-9 in <lb/>endocytic mutants (Figure 4H and Figure 2N). <lb/>To then relate changes in ATG-9 localization at the synapse with activity-<lb/>dependent increases in synaptic autophagy, we examined LGG-1/Atg8/GABARAP <lb/>puncta in mutant backgrounds that affect exo-endocytosis at the synapse. <lb/>Consistent with the previous findings (Hill et al., 2019, Hawk et al., 2018), we <lb/>observed the average number of LGG-1 puncta increased when the wild type <lb/>animals were cultivated at 25°C, a condition known to increase the activity state of <lb/>the AIY neurons (Hawk et al., 2018) and synaptic autophagy (Hill et al., 2019) <lb/>(Figure 4L, S4A-S4C). Inhibiting exocytosis (in unc-13(s69) mutants) or disrupting <lb/>the autophagy pathway (in atg-9(wy56) mutants) eliminated the capacity of the <lb/>neuron to increase synaptic autophagy in response to increases in the cultivation <lb/>temperature (Figure 4L, S4C). We observed higher numbers of LGG-1 puncta <lb/>under basal conditions in unc-26(s1710) mutants (Figures S4C). The LGG-1 <lb/>puncta in unc-26(s1710) mutants could not be suppressed by autophagy mutants, <lb/>suggesting the increased LGG-1 puncta were not bona-fide functional <lb/>autophagosomes (Figures S4C). Moreover, the LGG-1 puncta in unc-26(s1710) <lb/>mutants did not increase in response to cultivation temperatures that increase the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>activity state of the neuron (Figures 4L, S4C). Our findings are consistent with <lb/>previous studies that provide evidence that synaptojanin 1 is important for <lb/>autophagosome formation when inducing autophagy (Vanhauwaert et al., 2017). <lb/>We extend these studies, now demonstrating a link between exo-endocytic traffic <lb/>of ATG-9 at presynaptic sites, and activity-dependent presynaptic autophagy. <lb/>Abnormal accumulation of ATG9A in nerve terminals of mammalian neurons <lb/>with mutations in endocytic proteins. <lb/>We next investigated whether the effect of perturbation of endocytosis on ATG9A <lb/>dynamics in nerve terminals is conserved at mammalian synapses. To this end, <lb/>we explored the localization of ATG9A in nerve terminals of hippocampal neuronal <lb/>cultures of mice double KO for dynamin 1 and 3 (the two neuronally enriched <lb/>dynamin isoforms) and KO for synaptojanin 1 (SJ1) (the neuronally enriched <lb/>synaptojanin isoform) (Raimondi et al., 2011, Cremona et al., 1999, Ferguson and <lb/>De Camilli, 2012). Synapses of both genotypes are characterized by a massive <lb/>accumulation of synaptic vesicle endocytic intermediates, endocytic pits in the <lb/>case of dynamin mutants and clathrin coated vesicles in the case of synaptojanin <lb/>1 mutants. This accumulation is reflected in a very robust clustering in presynaptic <lb/>terminals of immunoreactive signal for endocytic factors, including clathrin, clathrin <lb/>adaptors and their accessory proteins such as amphiphysin 2 (Raimondi et al., <lb/>2011, Hayashi et al., 2008, Ferguson et al., 2007, Milosevic et al., 2011). <lb/>Accordingly, anti-amphiphysin 2 immunofluorescence revealed a much stronger <lb/>synaptic staining in dynamin 1 and 3 DKO neurons, and in SJ1 KO neurons, than <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>in controls (Figures 5). Importantly, anti-ATG9A immunofluorescence also <lb/>revealed a striking accumulation of this protein at a subset of mutant synapses <lb/>relative to WT synapses (Figures 5A-5B, 5E-5F). Such hot spots of ATG9A <lb/>colocalized with amphiphysin 2 immunoreactivity, confirming the synaptic <lb/>localization of anti-ATG9A (Figure 5). However, the number of synaptic puncta <lb/>were more numerous for amphiphysin 2 than for ATG9A, suggesting a <lb/>heterogeneous localization of ATG9A at synapses, or a different impact of the <lb/>perturbation of dynamin and SJ1 on ATG9A in different neurons. <lb/>A mutation in unc-26/synaptojanin 1 associated with early-onset <lb/>Parkinsonism (EOP) leads to abnormal focal accumulation of ATG-9 in <lb/>presynaptic nerve terminals. <lb/>ATG-9 links autophagy, endocytosis and neuronal activity at synapses. <lb/>Abnormal function of these processes, which are crucial for maintaining neuronal <lb/>health and homeostasis, have been implicated in Parkinson&apos;s disease (Vidyadhara <lb/>et al., 2019, Anglade et al., 1997, Lynch-Day et al., 2012). A missense mutation at <lb/>an evolutionarily conserved position in the PI4P phosphatase domain of Sac1 <lb/>domain of SJ1 (R258Q) is associated with early-onset Parkinsonism (Quadri et al., <lb/>2013, Krebs et al., 2013). Introduction of the same mutation in mouse and <lb/>Drosophila was reported to affect endocytic trafficking and autophagosome <lb/>maturation at synapses (Cao et al., 2017, Vanhauwaert et al., 2017). The mutant <lb/>position, which impairs the catalytic activity of the Sac1 domain, is conserved in C. <lb/>elegans (R216Q) (Figure 6A). Does this mutation also affect ATG9A localization <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>at synapses? We addressed this question both in neuronal cultures of previously <lb/>described homozygous knock-in mice with the PD mutation (SJ1 RQ KI mice) (Cao <lb/>et al., 2017) and in C. elegans in which we engineered the homozygous <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease mutation (R216Q) via CRISPR-Cas9. <lb/>Immunofluorescence staining of endogenous ATG9A in hippocampal <lb/>cultures generated from SJ1 RQ KI mice revealed abnormal ATG9A accumulations <lb/>that colocalized with focal enrichment of amphiphysin 2 foci at synapses (Figures <lb/>6B-6E, 6I) and were similar to those observed in SJ1 KO neurons (Figures 5E-5H). <lb/>As in the case of dynamin 1 and 3 DKO synapses and of SJ1 KO synapses <lb/>(Hayashi et al., 2008, Raimondi et al., 2011), such accumulations were typically <lb/>more prominent in inhibitory presynaptic GABA-ergic nerve terminals -as revealed <lb/>by immunostaining for vGAT (Figures 6F-6H, 6F&apos;-6H&apos;), which generally have higher <lb/>levels of tonic activity. <lb/>Likewise, in unc-26 (R216Q) mutant C. elegans, ATG-9::GFP was <lb/>abnormally localized to subsynaptic foci which resembled those observed in unc-<lb/>26(e205)/SJ1 null alleles -and accordingly were enriched in clathrin -albeit with a <lb/>lower penetrance, consistent with partial loss of function (Figures 6J-6M, S5H-<lb/>S5J). <lb/>We also observed that the unc-26(R216Q) allele, contrary to the loss-of-<lb/>function allele, did not produce obvious changes in the localization of the synaptic <lb/>vesicle proteins SNG-1 or RAB-3 at presynaptic regions (Figures S5A-S5G), <lb/>showing that unc-26 (R216Q) differentially affects ATG-9 localization and synaptic <lb/>vesicle protein localization. These findings are consistent with Drosophila studies <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>indicating that the unc-26(R216Q) Parkinson&apos;s disease mutation impairs <lb/>autophagy at the synapse (Vanhauwaert et al., 2017), and are extended to show <lb/>an impact of the mutation on ATG-9 trafficking at presynaptic sites. <lb/>Another Sac domain-containing protein, Sac2/INPP5F (Fig. 6A), is located <lb/>within a Parkinson&apos;s disease risk locus identified by genome-wide association <lb/>studies (Blauwendraat et al., 2019, Nalls et al., 2014). We examined two putative <lb/>null alleles of SAC-2 in C. elegans, sac-2(gk927434) and sac-2(gk346019), for <lb/>phenotypes in ATG-9 localization. While single mutants of sac-2 do not affect ATG-<lb/>9 localization (data not shown), sac-2(gk927434);unc-26(s1710) and sac-<lb/>2(gk346019);unc-26(s1710) double mutants enhance the abnormal localization of <lb/>ATG-9 in unc-26(s1710) single null allele, suggesting that sac-2 and unc-<lb/>26/synaptojanin 1 function synergistically in mediating ATG-9 trafficking at <lb/>synapses (Figures 6N-6P). Our observations are consistent with previous findings <lb/>showing that Sac2 and synaptojanin 1 have overlapping roles in the endocytic <lb/>pathway at synapses (Cao et al., 2020). Importantly, our findings indicate that <lb/>lesions associated with early onset Parkinsonism in endocytic mutants result in <lb/>abnormal ATG-9 accumulation, suggesting a possible link between this condition, <lb/>ATG-9 traffic at synapses and autophagy. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In C. elegans, ATG-9 exits the Golgi complex in an AP-3 dependent <lb/>manner. We had previously shown that ATG-9, the only intrinsic transmembrane <lb/>protein of the autophagy machinery, is transported by UNC-104/KIF1A to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>presynaptic nerve terminals, where it plays a critical role for synaptic <lb/>autophagosome formation (Stavoe et al., 2016). Here we show that AP-3 is a <lb/>critical component of the coat that sorts ATG-9 in the vesicles targeted to <lb/>presynaptic sites in C. elegans. The C. elegans AP-3 protein complex is <lb/>structurally and mechanistically related to the mammalian AP-4 complex, which in <lb/>vertebrates is required for signal-mediated transport of ATG9 from the TGN to the <lb/>peripheral cytoplasm (Rout and Field, 2017, Dell&apos;Angelica, 2009). Invertebrates, <lb/>including C. elegans, do not have AP-4 complexes. Whether AP-3 has a role for <lb/>ATG-9 export from the Golgi complex in mammalian cells remains to be explored. <lb/>ATG-9 enriched vesicles at the synapse might represent a distinct <lb/>subpopulation of vesicles. In nerve terminals, as shown by our EM analyses, the <lb/>bulk of ATG-9 is localized in small vesicles. Interestingly, while one cannot identify <lb/>molecularly distinct vesicle populations based on size and morphological <lb/>appearance in EM, immunogold staining suggests a predominant concentration of <lb/>ATG-9 on a subpopulation of vesicles. Likewise, fluorescent microscopy revealed <lb/>only partial overlap in nerve terminals between the distribution of ATG-9 and of the <lb/>intrinsic membrane protein of synaptic vesicles, SNG-1/synaptogyrin. Consistent <lb/>with these findings, ATG-9 was identified by mass spectrometry in a synaptic <lb/>vesicle fraction obtained by immunopurification of vesicles positive for the synaptic <lb/>vesicle protein synaptophysin or by differential and Ficoll density gradient <lb/>centrifugation (Boyken et al., 2013, Chantranupong et al., 2020), suggesting <lb/>compositional overlap between ATG-9 vesicles and bona fide synaptic vesicles. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Synaptically-localized ATG-9 positive vesicles undergo exo-endocytosis. <lb/>We demonstrate that their exocytosis is unc-13/unc-18-dependent, and that their <lb/>endocytosis is affected by dyn-1/dynamin, unc-26/synaptojanin, unc-57/endophilin <lb/>and unc-11/AP180, all genes required for synaptic vesicle endocytosis. In unc-26 <lb/>mutants, ATG-9 predominantly accumulates in foci which are also enriched in <lb/>clathrin. The observation that loss-of-function mutations of unc-13/unc-18 <lb/>suppress the abnormal distribution of ATG-9 in endocytic mutants shows that such <lb/>redistribution is the result of abnormal endocytosis after exocytosis. Consistent <lb/>with these findings in C. elegans, in mice a robust accumulation of ATG-9 was <lb/>detected in a subpopulation of neurons that harbor loss-of-function mutations in <lb/>the genes that encode neuronal isoforms of dynamin and synaptojanin. These <lb/>findings are also consistent with studies in non-neuronal mammalian cells showing <lb/>an accumulation of ATG9 at the plasma membrane upon perturbation of dynamin-<lb/>dependent endocytosis, as detected by fluorescence microscopy (Puri et al., 2013, <lb/>Puri et al., 2014, Popovic and Dikic, 2014) or a cell surface biotinylation assay (this <lb/>study). <lb/>The exo-endocytosis of ATG-9 at synapses reveals a link between synaptic <lb/>vesicle traffic and autophagy. We observe that disruptions in the synaptic vesicle <lb/>cycle, or autophagy, similarly result in abnormal accumulation of ATG-9 at the <lb/>plasma membrane and in clathrin-rich presynaptic foci. We interpret these clathrin-<lb/>rich foci to be endocytic intermediates onto which ATG-9 gets trapped in the <lb/>endocytic and autophagy mutants. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>A missense mutation in the endocytic protein synaptojanin in C. elegans <lb/>(corresponding to human R258Q associated with early-onset parkinsonism (EOP)) <lb/>results in abnormal accumulation of ATG-9 in clathrin-rich synaptic foci. <lb/>Synaptojanin contains two phosphatase domains: an inositol 5-phosphatase <lb/>domain which has been associated with most of the roles of synaptojanin in the <lb/>endocytic trafficking of synaptic vesicles, and an inositol 4-phosphate Sac1 <lb/>phosphatase domain, which can dephosphorylate to some extent also PI3P and <lb/>PI(3,5)P2, and whose precise physiological function is less understood. The <lb/>R258Q mutation, which selectively abolishes the activity of the Sac1 phosphatase <lb/>domain, was shown to impair presynaptic endocytic flow, more prominently at <lb/>inhibitory synapses, which have generally higher tonic activity (Cao et al., 2017), <lb/>and also impair autophagy (Vanhauwaert et al., 2017). Our findings are consistent <lb/>with an impact of the EOP mutation on autophagy, as we demonstrate that ATG-<lb/>9 is mislocalized at synapses both in C. elegans harboring the homologous unc-<lb/>26(R216Q) lesion and in the R258Q mutant mice. In Drosophila, the corresponding <lb/>EOP mutation in synaptojanin also resulted in neurodegeneration (Vanhauwaert <lb/>et al., 2017). In view of the role of autophagy in the control of nerve terminal health <lb/>and homeostasis, the defect in autophagy may contribute to the <lb/>neurodegeneration leading to EOP. <lb/>Together, our data support a model whereby ATG-9 couples the synaptic <lb/>exo-endocytosis and autophagy (Figure 7). ATG-9 is critical for autophagosome <lb/>biogenesis, and by trafficking via exo-endocytosis at presynaptic sites, ATG-9 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>could coordinate synaptic autophagy with synaptic vesicle recycling, linking <lb/>synaptic autophagy to the activity state of the neuron. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank Erik Jorgensen (Department of Biology, the University of Utah), <lb/>Kang Shen (Department of Biology, Stanford University) and Hong Zhang <lb/>(Department of Cell Biology, University of Massachusetts Medical School) for <lb/>providing strains and constructs. We thank Center for Cellular and Molecular <lb/>Imaging, Electron Microscopy Facility at Yale Medical School for assistance with <lb/>the work presented here, and Yumei Wu, Irina Kolotuev, David Hall, Maike <lb/>Kittelmann and Szi-chieh Yu for advice on immunoelectron microscopy <lb/>experiments. We thank current and past members of the Colón-Ramos lab for <lb/>help, advice and insightful comments on the project. We thank the Caenorhabditis <lb/>Genetics Center (funded by NIH Office of Research Infrastructure Programs P40 <lb/>OD010440) for C. elegans strains. S.Y. was supported by China Scholarship <lb/>Council-Yale World Scholars Program. I.O. summer research was supported by <lb/>Howard Hughes Medical Institute Exceptional Research Opportunities Program <lb/>(HHMI ExROP) and Yale BioMed Amgen Scholars Program. Research in the <lb/>P.D.C. lab was supported by the NIH (NS36251 and DA18343), the Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>Foundation, the Kavli Foundation, MJFF (ASAP-000580) and a fellowship from the <lb/>National Research Foundation of Korea to D.P. (2019R1A6A3A03031300). <lb/>Research in the D.A.C.-R. lab was supported by NIH R01NS076558, <lb/>DP1NS111778 and by an HHMI Scholar Award. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: S.Y., S.H. and D.A.C.-R.; methodology: S.Y., L.M., S.H., M.C., <lb/>L.S. and D.A.C.-R.; software: L.S.; investigation in C. elegans: S.Y., L.M., S.H., <lb/>Z.X., I.G. and I.O.; investigation in mammalian cells: D.P. and M.C.; formal <lb/>analysis: S.Y., L.M. and D.P.; writing -original draft: S.Y., L.M., P.D.C. and D.A.C.-<lb/>R.; writing -review and editing: S.Y., L.M., S.H., Z.X., L.S., D.P., M.C., P.D.C. and <lb/>D.A.C.-R.; visualization: S.Y., L.M., D.P. and D.A.C.-R.; supervision, project <lb/>administration and funding acquisition: P.D.C. and D.A.C.-R.. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Disclosure <lb/>P.D.C. is a member of the scientific advisory board of Casma Therapeutics. <lb/></div>

			<body>Figure Legends <lb/>Fig 1. In C. elegans ATG-9 is transported to synapses in vesicles generated <lb/>in the trans-Golgi network (TGN) via AP-3-dependent budding. <lb/>(A) Schematic of the head of C. elegans, including pharynx (grey region) and the <lb/>two bilaterally symmetric AIY interneurons (in black dashed box) with presynaptic <lb/>regions (magenta). The synaptic-rich region is highlighted with an orange dashed <lb/>square and cell bodies with a blue dashed square. In axis, A, anterior; P, posterior; <lb/>L, left; R, right; D, dorsal; V, ventral. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(B) Schematic of a single AIY interneuron with cell body (in blue dashed square) <lb/>and presynaptic regions (magenta and black arrowheads, and synaptic-rich region <lb/>highlighted with an orange dashed square). <lb/>(C) Schematic of a cell body in the AIY interneurons, with ATG-9 localization <lb/>represented in green. <lb/>(C&apos;) Representative confocal micrograph of ATG-9::GFP localization at the cell <lb/>body of AIY in a wild-type animal (as in C, and blue dashed box in B). <lb/>(D-F) Representative confocal micrographs of RAB-3::mCherry (pseudo-colored <lb/>magenta) (D), ATG-9::GFP (E) and a merged channels (F) in the synaptic regions <lb/>of a representative wild-type AIY interneuron. The arrows and the dashed box <lb/>highlight the presynaptic specializations. <lb/>(G) Immunogold electron microscopy of transgenic animals with panneuronal <lb/>expression of ATG-9::GFP, with antibodies directed against GFP. Note that the <lb/>majority of immunogold particles localize to the presynaptic areas occupied by <lb/>synaptic vesicles, but not to all synaptic vesicle (see Supplementary Fig 1). Blue <lb/>line, outline of neurons. Dense projections, shaded in orange. &quot;m&quot;, mitochondria. <lb/>SV, examples of synaptic vesicles. Yellow arrows point to examples of <lb/>immunogold particles. <lb/>(H) Schematic of synaptic-rich region in the AIY interneurons <lb/>(I-K) Representative confocal micrographs of RAB-3::mCherry (pseudo-colored <lb/>magenta) (I), SNG-1::BFP (pseudo-colored cyan) (J) and ATG-9::GFP (K) at <lb/>synaptic-rich region (corresponding to H, also orange dashed box in B) in wild <lb/>type. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/> The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(L) Schematic of the AIY interneuron cell body with Golgi labeled (as grey puncta), <lb/>(L&apos;) Schematic of the Golgi apparatus with medial/cis-Golgi-specific protein AMAN-<lb/>2 (magenta) and trans-Golgi-specific protein TGN-38 (red). <lb/>(M-O) Confocal micrographs of AMAN-2::GFP (pseudo-colored magenta) (M), <lb/>ATG-9::mCherry (pseudo-colored green) (N) and merged channels (O) in the cell <lb/>body of AIY. <lb/>(P-R) Confocal micrographs of TGN-38::mCherry (pseudo-colored magenta) (P), <lb/>ATG-9::GFP (Q) and merged channels (R) in the cell body of AIY. <lb/>(S) Schematic of an AIY interneuron with ATG-9 (green). Pre-synaptic-rich region <lb/>(Zone 2) is highlighted by orange rectangle. <lb/>(T-U) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP at Zone 2 in wild type (T) and apb-<lb/>3(ok429) mutants (U). <lb/>(V-W) Confocal micrographs of SNG-1::GFP (pseudo-colored magenta) at Zone 2 <lb/>in wild type (V) and apb-3(ok429) mutants (W). <lb/>(X) Quantification of ATG-9::GFP enrichment at Zone 2 of AIY neurons in wild-type <lb/>and apb-3(ok429) mutant animals. Error bars correspond to standard error of the <lb/>mean (SEM). **p&lt;0.01 by Welch&apos;s t test between wild-type and mutant <lb/>animals. Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>(Y) Quantification of the ratio of ATG-9 intensity at cell body / synapses of AIY <lb/>neurons in wild-type, apb-3(ok429), apm-3(gk771233) and apd-3(gk805642) <lb/>mutant animals. Error bars represent standard error of the mean (SEM). *p&lt;0.05, <lb/>**p&lt;0.01 and ****p&lt;0.0001 (between wild type and the mutants) by ordinary one-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons test between wild-type and the <lb/>mutant groups. Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>(Z) Quantification of ratio of SNG-1 intensity at cell body / synapses of AIY neurons <lb/>in wild-type and apb-3(ok429) mutant animals. &quot;ns&quot;: not significant (between wild <lb/>type and the mutants) by Welch&apos;s t test between wild-type and mutant animals. <lb/>Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>Scale bars 5µm in (C&apos;); 5µm in (D) for (D)-(F); 200nm in (G); 2µm in (I) for (I)-(K); <lb/>2µm in (M) for (M)-(R); 2µm in (T) for (T)-(W). <lb/>Fig 2. ATG-9 undergoes exo-endocytosis at presynaptic sites. <lb/>(A) Schematic of the proteins required for the synaptic vesicle cycle examined in <lb/>this study, with vertebrate and C. elegans gene names (Saheki and De Camilli, <lb/>2012, Watanabe et al., 2014, Gan and Watanabe, 2018). <lb/>(B-B&apos;&apos;) Schematic of ATG-9 localization in AIY neurons (B), enlargement of the <lb/>synaptic-rich region of Zone 2 (B&apos;). <lb/>(C-J) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP at AIY Zone 2 in wild type (C), unc-<lb/>26(e205) (D), unc-57(ok310) (E) and unc-11(e47) (F) mutants, temperature-<lb/>sensitive dyn-1(ky51) mutants in the permissive temperature 20°C (G), in the <lb/>restrictive temperature 25°C (H), unc-13(s69);unc-26(e205) (I) and unc-<lb/>18(e81);unc-26(s1710) (J) double mutants. <lb/>(K) Quantification of the index of ATG-9 mislocalization (see STAR Methods) in <lb/>wild type, unc-26(s1710), unc-57(ok310), unc-11(e47) mutants, unc-13(s69);unc-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>26(e205) and unc-18(e81);unc-26(s1710) double mutants. Error bars show <lb/>standard error of the mean (SEM). &quot;ns&quot; (not significant), **p&lt;0.01 and ***p&lt;0.001 <lb/>(between wild type and the mutants) by ordinary one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s <lb/>multiple comparisons test between wild-type and the mutant groups. Each dot in <lb/>the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>(L, L&apos;) Schematic of ATG-9 localization in AIY neurons (L), enlargement of the <lb/>distal part of the neurite with synaptic clusters of Zone 3 (L&apos;). <lb/>(M) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP (pseudo-colored black) at AIY Zone 3 in <lb/>pfk-1.1(gk922689) mutants prehypoxia/normoxia (left panels), after 10min of <lb/>transient hypoxia (middle panels) and another iteration of 10min of normoxia (right <lb/>panels). Corresponding fluorescence intensity is shown below the line scan image. <lb/>(N) Quantification of the percentage of animals displaying two (or more) ATG-9 <lb/>subsynaptic foci at AIY Zone 2 in unc-26(s1710) mutants raised at indicated <lb/>temperatures. Higher temperatures in AIY result in increased activity state, and <lb/>autophagy (Clark et al., 2006, Hawk et al., 2018, Hill et al., 2019). unc-13(s69);unc-<lb/>26(e205) double mutants were also raised at 25°C and quantified. The number of <lb/>animals examined in each condition is indicated by &quot;n&quot;. Error bars show standard <lb/>error of the mean (SEM). ****p&lt;0.0001 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>Scale bars 2µm in (C) for (C)-(J); 5µm in (M) <lb/>Fig 3. In unc-26/synaptojanin 1 mutants, ATG-9 accumulates at presynaptic, <lb/>clathrin-rich sites <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(A-C) Surface levels of ATG9A and transferrin receptor (TfR) in control and <lb/>dynamin 1 and 2 conditional double knock-out (Dyn1/2 CKO) fibroblasts. <lb/>(A) Immunoblots (IB) for transferrin receptor (TfR) and ATG9A of total cell extracts <lb/>and of material recovered by streptavidin affinity purification following surface <lb/>biotinylation. <lb/>(B and C) Quantification of surface / total levels of ATG9 and TfR in Dyn1/2 CKO <lb/>fibroblasts relative to the control cells (CTL). Error bars show standard error of the <lb/>mean (SEM). *p&lt;0.05 and **p&lt;0.01 by Student&apos;s t test. <lb/>(D-F) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP (D), SNG-1::BFP (pseudo-colored <lb/>magenta) (E) and merged channels (F) at AIY Zone 2 in unc-26(s1710) mutants. <lb/>(G-I) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::mCherry (pseudo-colored green) (G), <lb/>GFP::LGG-1 (pseudo-colored magenta) (H) and merged channels (I) in unc-<lb/>26(s1710) mutants. <lb/>(J-L) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP (J), BFP::clathrin heavy chain (CHC-<lb/>1) (pseudo-colored magenta) (K) and merged (L) in unc-26(s1710) mutants. <lb/>(M) Percentage of ATG-9 foci that colocalize with LGG-1, the synaptic-vesicle <lb/>associated transmembrane protein Synaptogyrin/SNG-1 and CHC-1 puncta. The <lb/>number of foci examined in each condition are indicated by the &quot;n&quot;. Error bars show <lb/>standard error of the mean (SEM). **p&lt;0.01 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>Scale bars 2µm in (D) for (D)-(L). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig 4. In autophagy mutants, ATG-9 accumulates into endocytic <lb/>intermediates at presynaptic sites. <lb/>(A) Schematic of the autophagosome biogenesis pathway. ATG-9 cycles between <lb/>ATG-9 reservoirs and pre-autophagosomal structures (PAS) during <lb/>autophagosome biogenesis (Reggiori et al., 2004, Yamamoto et al., 2012, Suzuki <lb/>et al., 2001). <lb/>(B-F) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP at AIY Zone 2 in wild type (B), unc-<lb/>51(e369)/Atg1 (C), epg-9(bp320)/Atg101 (D), atg-13(bp414)/epg-1 (E), and epg-<lb/>8(bp251)/Atg14 (F) mutants. <lb/>(G) Quantification of percentage of animals displaying one (or more) ATG-9 <lb/>subsynaptic foci at AIY Zone 2 in wild type and indicated autophagy mutants. The <lb/>number of animals examined in each condition is indicated by &quot;n&quot;. Error bars show <lb/>standard error of the mean (SEM). &quot;ns&quot; (not significant), *p&lt;0.05 and ****p&lt;0.0001 <lb/>(between wild type and the mutants) by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>(H) Quantification of the percentage of animals with one (or more) ATG-9 <lb/>subsynaptic foci at AIY Zone 2 in epg-9(bp320)/Atg101 mutants raised at indicated <lb/>temperatures. The number of animals examined in each condition is indicated by <lb/>the numbers on the bars. Error bars show standard error of the mean (SEM). <lb/>*p&lt;0.01 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>(I-K) Representative confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP (I), BFP::CHC-1 <lb/>(pseudo-colored magenta) (J) and merged channels (K) at AIY Zone 2 in epg-<lb/>9(bp320)/Atg101 mutants. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(L) Quantification of the relative number of LGG-1 puncta in the AIY neurites at <lb/>20°C and at 25°C for 4 hours in wild type, unc-13(e450), atg-9(wy56) and unc-<lb/>26(s1710) mutants. As primary interneurons in the thermotaxis circuit of C. <lb/>elegans, AIY activity state is found to increase when animals are raised at 25°C <lb/>for 4 hours, compared with animals at 20°C (Clark et al., 2006, Hawk et al., 2018, <lb/>Biron et al., 2006). For every genotype, the average number of LGG-1 puncta at <lb/>25°C was normalized to the observed average at 20°C to visualize the difference <lb/>between different neuronal activity state in each genotype. The average number <lb/>before normalization can be seen in Supplementary Figure 4. &quot;ns&quot; (not significant) <lb/>and ***p&lt;0.001 (between 20°C and 25°C in each genotype) by Welch&apos;s t test. <lb/>Scale bars 2µm in (B) for (B)-(F); 2µm in (I) for (I)-(K). <lb/>Fig 5. Abnormal accumulation of ATG9A in nerve terminals of mammalian <lb/>neurons with mutations in endocytic proteins. <lb/>(A-D) Representative images showing immunoreactivity for ATG9A (A and B) and <lb/>amphiphysin2 (C and D) in DIV17 hippocampal neuronal cultures from wild type <lb/>(WT) (A and C) and dynamin 1/3 double KO (Dyn1/3 KO) (B and D) newborn mice. <lb/>(E-H) Representative images showing immunoreactivity for ATG9A (E and F) and <lb/>amphiphysin2 (G and H) in DIV23 hippocampal neuronal cultures from wild type <lb/>(WT) (E and G) and synaptojanin1 KO (SJ1 KO) (F and H) newborn mice. <lb/>Scale bars 20µm in (C), (D), (G), (H) for (A)-(H). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig 6. A mutation in unc-26/synaptojanin 1 associated with early-onset <lb/>Parkinsonism (EOP) leads to abnormal focal accumulation of ATG-9 in <lb/>presynaptic nerve terminals. <lb/>(A) Domain structures of Sac2/sac-2 and Synaptojanin 1/unc-26. The mutated <lb/>residue associated with EOP is conserved (highlighted in yellow). <lb/>(B-E) Representative images showing immunoreactivity for ATG9A (B and C) and <lb/>amphiphysin2 (D and E) in DIV23 hippocampal neuronal cultures from newborn <lb/>wild type (WT) mice (B and D) and mice harboring a EOP associated mutation in <lb/>the synaptojanin1 (SJ1 RQ KI) gene (C and E). <lb/>(F-H, F&apos;-H&apos;) Representative images showing immunoreactivity for vesicular GABA <lb/>transporter (vGAT) (F), ATG9A (G) and amphiphysin2 (H) in DIV19 hippocampal <lb/>neuronal cultures from SJ1 RQ KI newborn mice. (F&apos;-H&apos;) enlarged images of squared <lb/>regions in (F-H). <lb/>(I) Quantification of relative ATG9A intensity in nerve terminals of wild type (WT), <lb/>SJ1 RQ KI and SJ1KO hippocampal neuronal cultures. n = 3 independent cultures. <lb/>Error bars show standard error of the mean (SEM). **p&lt;0.01 by Student&apos;s t test. <lb/>(J) Quantification of abnormal ATG9 localization in unc-26(R216Q) and unc-<lb/>26(e205) worm mutants. The bars show C. elegans that display two (or more) <lb/>ATG-9 subsynaptic foci at Zone 2 in wild type. The number of animals examined <lb/>in each condition is indicated by &quot;n&quot;. Error bars show standard error of the mean <lb/>(SEM). **p&lt;0.01 and ****p&lt;0.0001 (between wild type and the mutants, and <lb/>between the two mutant groups) by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>(K) Schematic of an AIY interneuron with presynaptic sites (in red and <lb/>arrowheaded) and Zone 2 highlighted by dashed square. <lb/>(L-O) Representative confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP at AIY Zone 2 in wild <lb/>type (L), unc-26(R216Q) (M) mutants, unc-26(s1710) (N) and sac-<lb/>2(gk346019);unc-26(s1710) (O) mutants. <lb/>(P) Quantification of the percentage of animals displaying two (or more) ATG-9 <lb/>subsynaptic foci at AIY Zone 2 in wild type, unc-26(s1710), sac-2(gk927434);unc-<lb/>26(s1710) and sac-2(gk346019);unc-26(s1710) mutants. The number of animals <lb/>examined in each condition is indicated by the numbers on the bars. Error bars <lb/>show standard error of the mean (SEM). ****p&lt;0.0001 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact <lb/>test. <lb/>Scale bars 20µm in (D) for (B) and (D); 20µm in (E) for (C) and (E); 20µm in (H) <lb/>for (F)-(H); 5µm in (H&apos;) for (F&apos;)-(H&apos;); 2µm in (L) for (L)-(M); 2µm in (N) for (N)-(O) <lb/>Fig 7. ATG-9 traffic in neurons: a model from origin in the cell body to local <lb/>traffic at the synapse <lb/>Schematic model of ATG-9 trafficking in C. elegans neurons. ATG-9 vesicles <lb/>originate from the trans-Golgi network via AP-3-dependent budding (C. elegans <lb/>lacks distinct AP-3 and AP-4 adaptors). ATG-9 vesicles undergo anterograde <lb/>transport to the synapses, which depends on the kinesin UNC-104/KIF1A (Stavoe <lb/>et al., 2016). Once ATG-9 vesicles reach the presynaptic region, they undergo <lb/>exo-endocytosis. In mutants that disrupt endocytosis, or in autophagy mutants, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>ATG-9 accumulates into clathrin-enriched synaptic foci, and activity-dependent <lb/>presynaptic autophagy is compromised. Similar mechanisms operate at <lb/>mammalian nerve terminals. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Fig S1, related to Fig 1. ATG-9 localizes to a subset of vesicles at synapses <lb/>and does not extensively colocalize with ER or mitochondrial markers at cell <lb/>body; RAB-3 is not affected by APB-3. <lb/>(A-B) Immunogold electron microscopy of nerve terminals transgenic worms <lb/>expressing ATG-9::GFP, and done with antibodies directed against GFP. Note that <lb/>immunogold particles are enriched at specific presynaptic areas. The similar <lb/>localization of immunoreactivity in closely adjacent sections (A) and (B) speaks <lb/>against the possibility that the non-homogenous distribution of gold particles in the <lb/>terminal may be a labeling artifact. Blue line, outline of the nerve terminals. Dense <lb/>projections are shaded in orange. &quot;m&quot;, mitochondria. <lb/>(C) Quantification of the percentage of immunogold particles on indicated <lb/>subcellular structures (vesicles, plasma membrane or mitochondria, reported as <lb/>the percent of total particles in the portion of the neurite visible in the section). <lb/>(D) Quantification of the number of immunogold particles on subcellular structures <lb/>(vesicles, plasma membrane or mitochondria) divided by area occupied by the <lb/>cellular structures (µm 2 ). <lb/>(E) Schematic of a cell body and organelles in the AIY interneurons. <lb/>(F-H) Confocal micrographs of SP12::GFP (ER marker) (F), ATG-9::mCherry (G) <lb/>and merged channels (H) at the cell body of AIY. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">(I-K) Confocal micrographs of TOMM-20::GFP (mitochondrial marker) (I), ATG-<lb/>9::mCherry (J) and merged channels (K) at cell body of AIY. <lb/>(L) Schematic of an AIY interneuron with RAB-3 localization (red), and synaptic-<lb/>rich region of Zone 2 in orange dashed box. <lb/>(M-O) Confocal micrographs of RAB-3::mCherry at Zone 2 in wild type (M) and <lb/>apb-3(ok429) mutants (N), and quantification (O). Error bars show standard error <lb/>of the mean (SEM). &quot;ns&quot;: not significant by Welch&apos;s t test between wild-type and <lb/>mutant animals. Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>Scale bars 200nm in (A) for (A)-(B) and in inset; 5µm in (F) for (F)-(K); 2µm in (M) <lb/>for (M)-(N) <lb/>Fig S2, related to Fig 2. Endocytosis regulates ATG-9 localization at <lb/>synapses. <lb/>(A) Quantification of the percentage of animals displaying two (or more) ATG-9 foci <lb/>at AIY Zone 2 synapses in wild type and endo-exocytic mutants. The number of <lb/>animals examined in each condition is indicated by &quot;n&quot;. Error bars show standard <lb/>error of the mean (SEM). ***p&lt;0.001 and ****p&lt;0.0001 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact <lb/>test. <lb/>(B) Mean intensity of ATG-9 at AIY Zone 2 in wild type and unc-26(s1710) mutants. <lb/>Error bars show standard error of the mean (SEM). *p&lt;0.05 (between wild type <lb/>and the mutants) by Welch&apos;s t test. Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single <lb/>animal. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">(C-D) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP in the AIY Zone 2 for unc-26(e205) <lb/>(C) mutants, unc-26(e205) mutants with UNC-26 cDNA rescue array cell-<lb/>specifically expressed in AIY (D). <lb/>(E) Quantification of the percentage of animals displaying one (or more) ATG-9 <lb/>foci at the synapse-rich AIY Zone 2 in wild type, unc-26(s1710) mutants and unc-<lb/>26(s1710) mutants with an UNC-26 cDNA rescue array cell-specifically expressed <lb/>in AIY. The number of animals examined in each condition is indicated by the &quot;n&quot;. <lb/>Error bars show standard error of the mean (SEM). &quot;ns&quot; (not significant), <lb/>****p&lt;0.0001 by two-tailed Fisher&apos;s exact test. <lb/>(F-G) Confocal micrographs of ATG-9::GFP in the AIY Zone 2 in unc-13(s69) (F) <lb/>and unc-18(e81) (G) mutants. <lb/>Scale bars 2µm in (C) for (C)-(D); 2µm in (F) for (F)-(G) <lb/>Fig S3, related to Fig 3. Defects of synaptic vesicle clusters and clathrin <lb/>heavy chain (CHC-1) in unc-26 mutants as compared to wild type. <lb/>(A) Immunoblots (IB) for dynamins in the Dyn1/2 CKO fibroblast, and controls. <lb/>(B) Quantification of the dynamin levels in Dyn1/2 CKO fibroblasts relative to a <lb/>tubulin control, in Dyn1/2 CKO and the control cells (CTL). n = 3 independent <lb/>experiments. Error bars show standard error of the mean (SEM). **p&lt;0.01 by <lb/>Student&apos;s t test. <lb/>(C-E) Confocal micrographs of RAB-3::mCherry (pseudo-colored green) in wild <lb/>type (C) and unc-26(s1710) mutants (D), and SNG-1::GFP (E) in the unc-<lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">26(s1710) mutants. Note that like ATG-9, synaptic vesicle associated protein RAB-<lb/>3 concentrates near synaptic sites in wild type animals (arrows, compare to Figure <lb/>1), but unlike ATG-9, these synaptic vesicle proteins become diffusely localized in <lb/>unc-26(s1710) mutants (consistent with observations from (Harris et al., 2000, <lb/>Verstreken et al., 2003, Ferguson et al., 2007, Raimondi et al., 2011, Milosevic et <lb/>al., 2011)). <lb/>(F) Quantification of the distribution of RAB-3 in wild type and unc-26(s1710) <lb/>mutants for the synaptic region in C and D, and as described (STAR Methods). <lb/>**p&lt;0.01 (between wild type and the mutants) by Welch&apos;s t test. Each dot in the <lb/>scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>(G) Quantification of CHC-1 clusters intensity at synapses per AIY neuron in wild <lb/>type and unc-26 (s1710) mutants, and as described (STAR Methods). *p&lt;0.05 <lb/>(between wild type and the mutants) by Welch&apos;s t test. Each dot in the scatter plot <lb/>represents a single animal. The method described in STAR Methods. <lb/>Fig S4, related to Fig 4. Activity-dependent autophagy at presynaptic sites. <lb/>(A-B) Confocal micrographs of cytoplasmic mCherry and eGFP::LGG-1 at AIY <lb/>Zone 2 in wild type (A) and unc-26(s1710) mutants (B). Yellow dashed lines in AIY <lb/>emphasize the synaptic region, with the yellow dashed box emphasizing the <lb/>synaptic-rich AIY Zone 2 region of AIY, and the white dashed line, the asyntaptic <lb/>region. The arrow points to autophagosomes (as visualized with eGFP::LGG-1 <lb/>(Alberti et al., 2010, Manil-Segalen et al., 2014, Wu et al., 2015, Stavoe et al., <lb/>2016, Hill et al., 2019)). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">(C) Quantification of the average number of LGG-1 puncta in the AIY neurites at <lb/>20°C and at 25°C for 4 hours in wild type, unc-13(e450), atg-9(wy56), unc-<lb/>26(s1710) and unc-26(s1710);atg-9(wy56) mutants. The number of animals <lb/>examined in each condition is indicated by the numbers on the bars. *p&lt;0.05 and <lb/>****p&lt;0.0001 by ordinary one-way ANOVA with Dunnett&apos;s multiple comparisons <lb/>test between wild-type and the mutant groups. <lb/>Scale bars 5µm in (A) for (A)-(B). <lb/>Fig S5, related to Fig 6. The lesion associated with EOP does not affect <lb/>localization of synaptic vesicle proteins. <lb/>(A) Schematic of an AIY interneuron. <lb/>(B) Quantification of the distribution of SNG-1 at Zone 3 in wild type and unc-<lb/>26(R216Q) mutants as described (STAR Methods). Error bars show standard error <lb/>of the mean (SEM). &quot;ns&quot; (not significant) (between wild type and the mutants) by <lb/>Welch&apos;s t test. Each dot in the scatter plot represents a single animal. <lb/>(C-G) Representative confocal micrographs of RAB-3::mCherry at Zone 3 in wild <lb/>type (C), unc-26(R216Q) (D), unc-26(s1710) (E) mutants; SNG-1::GFP in wild type <lb/>(F) and unc-26(R216Q) (G) mutants. The arrowheads denote the clusters at Zone <lb/>3. The brackets denote the diffuse RAB-3 localization at Zone 3. <lb/>(H-J) Representative confocal micrographs of BFP::CHC-1 (pseudo-colored <lb/>magenta) (H), ATG-9::GFP (I) and merged channels (J) at Zone 2 in unc-<lb/>26(R216Q) mutants. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Scale bars 5µm in (C) for (C)-(G); 2µm in (H) for (H)-(J); <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">STAR Methods <lb/>CONTACT INFORMATION <lb/>Further information and requests for resources and reagents should be directed to <lb/>and will be fulfilled by the Lead Contact, Daniel A. Colón-Ramos (daniel.colon-<lb/>ramos@yale.edu). <lb/></div>

			<body>EXPERIMENTAL MODEL AND SUBJECT DETAILS <lb/>C. elegans Strains and Genetics <lb/>Worms were raised on nematode growth media plates at 20°C or room <lb/>temperature using OP50 Escherichia coli as a food source (Brenner, 1974). <lb/>Animals were analyzed as larva 4 (L4) stage hermaphrodites. For wild-type <lb/>nematodes, C. elegans Bristol strain N2 was used. For a full list of strains used in <lb/>the study, please see the KEY RESOURCES TABLE. <lb/>Molecular Biology and Transgenic Lines <lb/>C. elegans transgenic strains were created by injecting pSM vector-derived <lb/>plasmids (listed on KEY RESOURCES TABLE) by standard injection techniques <lb/>with co-injection markers punc-122::gfp and punc-122:rfp. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>The cDNA constructs (UNC-26, TGN-38, clathrin heavy chain (CHC-1)) generated <lb/>were amplified from a cDNA pool of a mixed population of C. elegans. Detailed <lb/>sub-cloning information is available upon request. <lb/>METHOD DETAILS <lb/>C. elegans CRISPR Transgenics <lb/>To introduce the lesion in unc-26/synaptojanin 1 associated with early-onset <lb/>Parkinsonism (EOP), we used CRISPR-Cas9 to substitute CGA with CAA, and <lb/>generate the homozygous mutation R216Q. CRISPR transgenic strain was <lb/>generated by precision genome editing method using CRISPR-Cas9 and linear <lb/>repair templates, as previously described (Paix et al., 2017) and using the targeted <lb/>gene crRNA (GGCACUCGAUUCAACGUAC) and repair template ssODN <lb/>(GACGTGTTGCTCTAATATCTCGTCTAAGTTGTGAGCGTGTCGGCACTCGAT <lb/>TCAACGTACAAGGAGCCAATTATCTCGGAAATGTGGCTAATTTCGTCGAGAC <lb/>TGAGCAATTGTTGCTTTT) <lb/>Cell Autonomy and Rescue of unc-26 <lb/>The unc-26 mutant phenotype was rescued by cell specifically expressing the wild <lb/>type unc-26 cDNA under AIY-specific ttx-3 promoter fragment (Colon-Ramos et <lb/>al., 2007). <lb/>Fluorescence Microscopy and Confocal Imaging <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>We imaged C. elegans by using 60x CFI Plan Apo VC, NA 1.4, oil objectives on <lb/>an UltraView VoX spinning disc confocal microscope and on a NikonTi-E stand <lb/>(PerkinElmer) with a Hammamatsu C9100-50 camera. C. elegans were <lb/>immobilized on a 2% agarose pad with 10mM levamisole (Sigma). Images were <lb/>processed with Volocity software or Fiji. <lb/>Inhibiting Oxidative Phosphorylation Using a microfluidic-hydrogel device <lb/>To inhibit oxidative phosphorylation by hypoxia, a reusable microfluidic <lb/>polydimethylsiloxane (PDMS) microfluidic device was used, as described (Jang et <lb/>al., 2020) while imaging ATG-9::GFP localization in pfk-1.1(gk922689);olaIs34 <lb/>(pttx-3::atg-9::gfp and pttx-3::mCherry::rab-3). Normoxic and hypoxic conditions <lb/>were applied to animals for 10 min sequentially by alternating the flow of air and <lb/>nitrogen gas, respectively. As a positive control, synaptic vesicle protein RAB-3 <lb/>was also imaged as reported (Jang et al., 2016) (Figure 2M). <lb/>Electron Microscopy <lb/>Worms were prepared by high pressure freeze and freeze substitution as <lb/>described (Rostaing et al., 2004, Manning and Richmond, 2015, Kolotuev et al., <lb/>2012). Briefly, ~10-20 worms at the L4 stage were loaded into carriers coated <lb/>lightly with hexadecane (Specimen carrier Type A and B, Technotrade <lb/>International) with 20% BSA and E. coli for high-pressure freezing (Leica EM HPM <lb/>010). After freezing, samples were transferred to an AFS machine for freeze <lb/>substitution (Leica EM AFS2) using a custom made workbox submerged in liquid <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/> The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>nitrogen. Samples were incubated in .1% uranyl acetate in anhydrous acetone as <lb/>follows: -90C for 48 hours, temperature raised to -50C over 8 hours, held at -50C <lb/>for 12 hours. Next, samples were washed with ethanol several times over 2 hours <lb/>and incubated in graded concentrations of HM20 resin (Lowicryl HM20, Electron <lb/>Microscopy Sciences) in ethanol (3 hours at 25% HM20 in EtOH, 3 hours in 50%, <lb/>16h in 75%, 6 hours in 100% HM20). Finally, worms were embedded in HM20 <lb/>resin at -50C within the AFS chamber. To facilitate embedding, we used a custom-<lb/>made aluminum chamber similar to that described in (Kolotuev, 2014). Carriers <lb/>containing the worms were inverted onto a small square of Aclar (Sigma) and <lb/>manipulated using fine needle tips to dissociate worms from the planchette. Worms <lb/>were then placed onto a small drop of HM20 within a double-sided adhesive <lb/>frames (Thermo Scientific) sandwiched between squares of Aclar. Thin embedding <lb/>at this step was critical to see the transparent worms later during sectioning. <lb/>Samples were cured under UV light for 48 hours at -50C, brought to room <lb/>temperature over 14 hours, and remained under UV light for another 24 hours at <lb/>room temperature. <lb/>To facilitate sectioning, fixed worms were cut from the embedded square and glued <lb/>onto thin plastic blocks made using Epon resin in a Chang mold (EMS). Worms <lb/>were trimmed (Diatome Trim 45) and sectioned (Diatome 4.0 Ultra) on a Leica UC7 <lb/>(Leica) until the desired area was identified. 500 nm thick sections were collected <lb/>and stained with toluidine blue to check for the desired ROI. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>The nerve ring and AIY Zone 2 were identified using anatomical landmarks <lb/>described in the original C. elegans connectome (White et al., 1986). The nerve <lb/>ring is located in the head of the animal and forms a ring of densely packed neurites <lb/>around the pharynx. AIY Zone 2 synapses are positioned in a ventral bundle of <lb/>neurites just posterior to the nerve ring. These synapses reside at the ventral base <lb/>of the neurite bundle and form a unique humped shape with multiple dense <lb/>projections. The left and right process of AIY contact one another at the posterior <lb/>end of Zone 2 synapses. Chemical synapses in C. elegans are defined by the <lb/>presence of presynaptic dense projection in the neurite. <lb/>50 nm thick sections were collected from at least one animal per genotype on <lb/>nickel slot grids covered with Formvar (EMS). When possible, serial sections were <lb/>collected. Antibody staining was performed within one day. Grids were incubated <lb/>for 10 minutes in .15% glycine and .1M ammonium chloride in PBS, followed by <lb/>incubation in blocking solution (1% BSA and 1% CWFS gelatin in PBS) for 10 <lb/>minutes. Grids were then incubated in anti-GFP primary antibody diluted in 2 parts <lb/>PBS and 1 part blocking solution overnight at 4C (ab6556 1:20, Abcam) After <lb/>washing in PBS four times over 15 minutes, grids were incubated in Protein A Gold <lb/>conjugated to 10 nm particles diluted in 2 parts PBS and 1 part blocking solution <lb/>(1:75, University Medical Center Utrecht) for 30 minutes. Grids were washed again <lb/>in PBS four times over 15 minutes, followed by 5 minutes incubation in 1% <lb/>glutaraldehyde in PBS (EMS), and three quick washes on water. After drying, grids <lb/>were post stained with Reynold&apos;s lead citrate for 4 minutes, 2.5% uranyl acetate <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>for 4 minutes, and lead citrate for 1 minute and allowed to dry at least 1 hour before <lb/>imaging. <lb/>Images were acquired on a FEI Tecnai Biotwin (FEI) equipped with a SIS Morada <lb/>11 megapixel CCD camera and a TALOS L120 (Thermo Fisher) equipped with a <lb/>Ceta 4k x 4k CMOS camera. For serial sections, images were aligned in z using <lb/>the TrakEM2 plugin in FIJI. <lb/>Hippocampal Neuron Culture <lb/>Mice were maintained on the C57BL6/129 hybrid genetic background. <lb/>Heterozygous mice were mated to generate homozygous knockout or knock-in <lb/>with their littermate controls. For neuronal cultures, P0 pups were genotyped by <lb/>PCR and then hippocampi were dissected. Tissues were digested for 20 min in a <lb/>papain/HBSS solution (20 U/ml) containing DNase (20 μg/ml). Cells were <lb/>dissociated by trituration and then plated onto poly-d-lysine coated coverslips. <lb/>After 3 hours incubation, the plating medium was exchanged to complete <lb/>neurobasal medium (2% B-27 and 0.5 mM L-glutamine in neurobasal medium). <lb/>Cells were maintained at 37°C in a 5% CO2 humidified incubator and the 30% of <lb/>cultured medium was replaced with new complete neurobasal medium at 4, 7 and <lb/>14 days in vitro (DIV). All adult mice for breeding were maintained on a 12 hours <lb/>light/dark cycle with standard mouse chow and water ad libitum. All research and <lb/>animal care procedures were approved by the Yale University Institutional Animal <lb/>Care and Use Committee. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Immunofluorescence <lb/>Cultured hippocampal neurons were briefly washed in a pre-warmed tyrode (136 <lb/>mM NaCl, 2.5 mM KCl, 2 mM CaCl2, 1.3 mM MgCl2, 10 mM HEPES and 10 mM <lb/>glucose) and then fixed with 4% PFA in 4% sucrose-containing 0.1M PB buffer <lb/>(pH7.3) for 15 min at RT. After fixation, cells were washed in PBS and incubated <lb/>with blocking buffer (3% BSA, 0.2% Triton X-100 in PBS) for 30 min at RT. Primary <lb/>(1 hour) and secondary antibody (45 min) incubations were subsequently <lb/>performed in the blocking buffer at RT. After washing, samples were mounted on <lb/>slides with Prolong Gold antifade reagent (Invitrogen). <lb/>Dynamin Conditional Knockout <lb/>For the tamoxifen inducible KO, Dynamin 1/2 conditional knockout (CKO) cells <lb/>(Ferguson et al., 2009) were treated with 2 μM 4-hydroxy-tamoxifen for 2 days and <lb/>then further incubated with 300 nM 4-hydroxy-tamoxifen for 3 days. Depletion of <lb/>total dynamin levels was confirmed by western blotting. <lb/>Surface Biotinylation <lb/>Control and dynamin 1/2 conditional KO cells were washed three times with ice-<lb/>cold PBS and incubated with ice-cold EZ-Link Sulfo-NHS-LC-Biotin (0.25 mg/ml) <lb/>in PBS for 30 min at 4 °C to label the surface proteins. Unbound biotins were <lb/>quenched and removed by 50 mM glycine in ice-cold PBS for 10 min at 4 °C. After <lb/>washout, cells were lysed with 1% triton X-100 lysis buffer (20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>1% triton X-100, 10% glycerol, 137 mM NaCl, 2 mM EDTA, 1 mM PMSF, 10 mM <lb/>leupeptin, 1.5 mM pepstatin and 1 mM aprotinin) and centrifuged at 14,000 g for <lb/>20 min at 4°C. The supernatants were collected, and protein concentrations were <lb/>determined by the BCA Protein Assay Kit. Same amount of lysates (600 μg) were <lb/>incubated with NeutraAvidin particles for 2 hours at 4 °C to pull-down the <lb/>biotinylated proteins. Particles were washed three times by lysis buffer, eluted with <lb/>2x sample buffer and boiling (5 min) and the eluates were processed for SDS-<lb/>PAGE and western blotting. The level of proteins were quantified by densitometry <lb/>using Fiji. <lb/>QUANTIFICATION AND STATISTICAL ANALYSIS <lb/>C. elegans AIY Quantifications <lb/>Presynaptic Enrichment <lb/>Morphologically, AIY can be divided into four segments, consistent with the C. <lb/>elegans EM reconstructions (White et al., 1986): the cell body; a proximal <lb/>asynaptic region termed Zone 1; a ~5µm synaptic-rich region termed Zone 2, <lb/>located at the turn of the neuron into the nerve ring; and Zone 3, which is the distal <lb/>part of the neurite located at the nerve ring. <lb/>ATG-9 or RAB-3 enrichment at synapses was quantified in the integrated <lb/>transgenic line olaIs34, expressing pttx-3::atg-9::gfp and pttx-3::mCherry::rab-3 in <lb/>the wild type and apb-3(ok429) mutants. Fluorescence intensity at Zone 2 was <lb/>quantified in Fiji (Schindelin et al., 2012) in maximal projection confocal <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>micrographs. ATG-9 (or RAB-3) enrichment at synapses represents Zone 2 signal <lb/>subtracted by average cytoplasmic signal at the cell body (Figures 1X and S1O). <lb/>Ratio of ATG-9 intensity of cell body/synapses was quantified in olaIs34 in the wild <lb/>type, apb-3(ok429), apm-3(gk771233) and apd-3(gk805642) mutants. In maximal <lb/>projection confocal micrographs, fluorescence intensities were measured, <lb/>background-subtracted (from cytoplasmic signal in the cell body) and averaged for <lb/>different subcellular regions (using an identically-sized oval-shaped object). The <lb/>&apos;Ratio between ATG-9 intensity at the cell body and synapses&apos; represents signal <lb/>of ATG-9 intensity (after the processing) at the cell body divided by the intensity <lb/>(after the processing) at Zone 2 (as shown in the equation below; Figure 1Y). <lb/>𝑇ℎ𝑒 𝑟𝑎𝑡𝑖𝑜 = <lb/>𝐴𝑇𝐺 − 9 𝑖𝑛𝑡𝑒𝑛𝑠𝑖𝑡𝑦 𝑎𝑡 𝑐𝑒𝑙𝑙 𝑏𝑜𝑑𝑦 − 𝑐𝑦𝑡𝑜𝑝𝑙𝑎𝑠𝑚𝑖𝑐 𝑏𝑎𝑐𝑘𝑔𝑟𝑜𝑢𝑛𝑑 <lb/>𝐴𝑇𝐺 − 9 𝑖𝑛𝑡𝑒𝑛𝑠𝑖𝑡𝑦 𝑎𝑡 𝑧𝑜𝑛𝑒 2 − 𝑐𝑦𝑡𝑜𝑝𝑙𝑎𝑠𝑚𝑖𝑐 𝑏𝑎𝑐𝑘𝑔𝑟𝑜𝑢𝑛𝑑 <lb/>To quantify ratio of SNG-1 intensity of cell body/synapses, we used the <lb/>extrachromosomal line olex4060 in the wild type and apb-3(ok429) mutants. <lb/>Maximal projection confocal micrographs were taken on SNG-1 and measured as <lb/>the intensity at Zone 2 by segmented line scans and the intensity at the cell body <lb/>by the oval selections of the whole cell body. The ratio of SNG-1 intensity between <lb/>cell body and synapses was reported as the intensity of SNG-1 at cell body divided <lb/>by the intensity of SNG-1 at Zone 2 (Figure 1Z). <lb/>Penetrance of ATG-9:GFP Subsynaptic Foci at the Presynaptic Region <lb/>To quantify the penetrance of ATG-9 subsynaptic foci at the presynaptic region <lb/>(Zone 2), we used integrated transgenic strain olaIs34 and olaIs33 in the wild type <lb/>and mutant background animals. For the temperature sensitive allele dyn-1(ky51) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>and the wild-type animals, animals were held at either 20°C (permissive) or 25°C <lb/>(non-permissive) for 3 days (or longer) prior to examination at the L4 stage. Other <lb/>mutants were kept at 20°C except for unc-26(s1710) and epg-9(bp320) <lb/>temperature experiments. <lb/>The penetrance of ATG-9 subsynaptic foci was quantified as percentage of <lb/>animals showing subsynaptic foci of ATG-9:GFP at Zone 2. Mutant phenotype was <lb/>defined as two or more than two subsynaptic foci of ATG-9::GFP at Zone 2 in <lb/>endocytic mutants, or one or more than one subsynaptic foci in autophagy <lb/>mutants. A Leica DM500B compound fluorescent microscope was used to <lb/>visualize and screen the worm in different genetic backgrounds (Figures 2N, S2A, <lb/>S2E, 4G-4H, 6J, 6P). <lb/>Expressivity of ATG-9::GFP Subsynaptic Foci at the Presynaptic Region <lb/>To quantify expressivity of ATG-9 subsynaptic foci at the presynaptic region (Zone <lb/>2), we obtained the plot profiles for individual presynaptic region (Zone 2) through <lb/>segmented line scans using Fiji. An algorithm in MATLAB was designed to identify <lb/>peaks along the line scans of Zone 2. The index of ATG-9 mislocalization at <lb/>presynaptic region is defined as the number of peaks divided by the width of peaks <lb/>at Zone 2 in each individual animal. In endocytic mutants, two populations of <lb/>mutant phenotype were identified: ATG-9 is dim and diffuse at Zone 2; ATG-9 <lb/>displays subsynaptic foci at Zone 2. Only endocytic mutants that display <lb/>subsynaptic foci were quantified for the expressivity (Figure 2K). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Code <lb/>available: <lb/>https://github.com/yangsisi76/Quantify-distribution-of-cell-<lb/>structures. <lb/>Mean Intensity of ATG-9 at Zone 2 <lb/>To measure the level of ATG-9 at presynaptic regions, we obtained the fluorescent <lb/>value for individual presynaptic region (Zone 2) through segmented line scans <lb/>using Fiji. All settings for the confocal microscope and camera were kept identical <lb/>between the wild type and unc-26(s1710) mutants. Mean fluorescent value of <lb/>animals in the two genotypes was calculated by Fiji (Figure S2B). <lb/>RAB-3 and SNG-1 Enrichment at Zone 3 <lb/>To quantify the distribution and enrichment of synaptic proteins, such as RAB-3 <lb/>and SNG-1, we used methods as described (Dittman and Kaplan, 2006, Jang et <lb/>al., 2016). Briefly, fluorescent values for the RAB-3 (SNG-1) in AIY neurons were <lb/>obtained through segmented line scans using Fiji. A sliding window of 2µm was <lb/>used to identify all the fluorescent peak and trough values for Zone 3 in each <lb/>individual neuron. The synaptic enrichment was calculated as %DF/F as described <lb/>(Jang et al., 2016, Dittman and Kaplan, 2006, Bai et al., 2010). In short, all the <lb/>identified fluorescent peak and trough values (Fpeak and Ftrough) were averaged and <lb/>used to calculate the %DF/F (100 x (Fpeak -Ftrough)/ Ftrough) (Bai et al., 2010, Dittman <lb/>and Kaplan, 2006, Jang et al., 2016). All settings for the confocal microscope and <lb/>camera were kept identical between the wild type and unc-26(s1710) mutants <lb/>(Figures S3F and S5B). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Percentage of ATG-9 Subsynaptic Foci that Colocalize with the Subsynaptic <lb/>Structures <lb/>To quantify the percentage of ATG-9 subsynaptic foci that colocalize with the <lb/>subsynaptic structures (LGG-1 and CHC-1), we observed the transgenic lines <lb/>olaex1360;olaIs44 <lb/>(pttx-3::gfp::lgg-1, <lb/>pttx-3::mCherry::atg-9) <lb/>and <lb/>olaex4290;olaIs34 (pttx-3::bfp::chc-1, pttx-3::atg-9::gfp). Confocal maximal <lb/>projections were used, and percentage colocalization was calculated as the <lb/>percentage of ATG-9 subsynaptic foci that colocalize with examined organelle <lb/>markers (Figure 3M). <lb/>Activity-dependent Autophagy <lb/>To measure the synaptic autophagosomes in AIY, animals with olaIs35 in the wild-<lb/>type, unc-13(e450), atg-9(wy56), unc-26(s1710) and unc-26(s1710);atg-9(wy56) <lb/>mutant backgrounds were grown in 20°C and then shifted to 25°C for 4 hours and <lb/>assessed for number of LGG-1 puncta in the neurite of AIY under a Leica DM <lb/>5000B compound microscope (Hill et al., 2019). To show the comparison between <lb/>20°C and 25°C, the number of LGG-1 puncta at 25°C in each genotype was <lb/>normalized by the number at 20°C (Figure 4L). Results before normalization are <lb/>reported in Figure S4C. <lb/>Immuno-EM <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>To quantify the distribution of ATG-9 positive particles, animals with olaex2264 <lb/>(punc-14::atg-9::GFP) in the wild type were used. Quantifications were performed <lb/>in FIJI. Cross-sectional area: an image of a 40nm section. Particles were counted <lb/>using the Cell Counter plugin. Occasionally, a Gaussian Blur processing filter was <lb/>applied in FIJI to help visualize structures in the image. Staining specificity, <lb/>calculated as a signal to noise ratio of particle density in neuronal tissue divided <lb/>by particle density in nearby E coli in the section, was &gt;20 for all samples. Particles <lb/>were considered localized near vesicles, plasma membrane, or mitochondria if the <lb/>distance from the gold particle to that structure was &lt;20 nm. This distance was <lb/>chosen based on estimates of the size of GFP, a GFP antibody, and protein A <lb/>crystal structures. To measure the area occupied by vesicles, a freehand shape <lb/>was drawn around an apparent cluster of vesicles occupying most or all vesicles <lb/>in the neurite. To measure area occupied by plasma membrane, the perimeter of <lb/>the neurite was multiplied by 40, which accounts for the rough measured width of <lb/>the plasma membrane plus the 20 nm radius in which a particle may be localized <lb/>nearby (Figures 1G, S1A-S1D). <lb/>Quantification of Immunoreactivity in Hippocampal Neuron Culture and <lb/>GFP::CHC-1 in C. elegans <lb/>Quantification of ATG9 and CHC-1 clustering was performed using Fiji as <lb/>previously described (Cao et al., 2020). Briefly, the same threshold was applied to <lb/>all images after background subtraction and then &apos;analyze particles&apos; function of Fiji <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>was used to obtain the raw intensity values of masked regions (Figures S3G and <lb/>6I). <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis and data plotting were conducted with Prism 7 software. We <lb/>used Fisher&apos;s exact test to determine statistical significance of categorical data in <lb/>contingency table, such as the penetrance of ATG-9 phenotype in AIY. 95% <lb/>confidence intervals were calculated by Wilson/Brown method and used for error <lb/>bars. For the continuous data, ordinary one-way ANOVA with Tukey&apos;s multiple <lb/>comparisons test, Welch&apos;s t test and Student&apos;s t test were used to determine its <lb/>statistical significance. The error bar represents the standard error of the mean <lb/>(SEM). The p value for significant differences is reported in the figure legends. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>Reference: <lb/>ALBERTI, A., MICHELET, X., DJEDDI, A. &amp; LEGOUIS, R. 2010. The <lb/>autophagosomal protein LGG-2 acts synergistically with LGG-1 in dauer <lb/>formation and longevity in C. elegans. Autophagy, 6, 622-33. <lb/>ALEGRE-ABARRATEGUI, J. &amp; WADE-MARTINS, R. 2009. Parkinson disease, <lb/>LRRK2 and the endocytic-autophagic pathway. Autophagy, 5, 1208-10. <lb/>ANGLADE, P., VYAS, S., JAVOY-AGID, F., HERRERO, M. T., MICHEL, P. P., <lb/>MARQUEZ, J., MOUATT-PRIGENT, A., RUBERG, M., HIRSCH, E. C. &amp; AGID, <lb/>Y. 1997. Apoptosis and autophagy in nigral neurons of patients with Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>disease. Histol Histopathol, 12, 25-31. <lb/>AZARNIA TEHRAN, D., KUIJPERS, M. &amp; HAUCKE, V. 2018. Presynaptic <lb/>endocytic factors in autophagy and neurodegeneration. Curr Opin Neurobiol, 48, <lb/>153-159. <lb/>BADOLATO, R. &amp; PAROLINI, S. 2007. Novel insights from adaptor protein 3 <lb/>complex deficiency. J Allergy Clin Immunol, 120, 735-41; quiz 742-3. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>BAI, J. H., HU, Z. T., DITTMAN, J. S., PYM, E. C. G. &amp; KAPLAN, J. M. 2010. <lb/>Endophilin Functions as a Membrane-Bending Molecule and Is Delivered to <lb/>Endocytic Zones by Exocytosis. Cell, 143, 430-441. <lb/>BANDRES-CIGA, S., SAEZ-ATIENZAR, S., BONET-PONCE, L., BILLINGSLEY, <lb/>K., VITALE, D., BLAUWENDRAAT, C., GIBBS, J. R., PIHLSTROM, L., GAN-OR, <lb/>Z., INTERNATIONAL PARKINSON&apos;S DISEASE GENOMICS, C., COOKSON, M. <lb/>R., NALLS, M. A. &amp; SINGLETON, A. B. 2019. The endocytic membrane <lb/>trafficking pathway plays a major role in the risk of Parkinson&apos;s disease. Mov <lb/>Disord, 34, 460-468. <lb/>BINOTTI, B., PAVLOS, N. J., RIEDEL, D., WENZEL, D., VORBRUGGEN, G., <lb/>SCHALK, A. M., KUHNEL, K., BOYKEN, J., ERCK, C., MARTENS, H., CHUA, J. <lb/>J. &amp; JAHN, R. 2015. The GTPase Rab26 links synaptic vesicles to the autophagy <lb/>pathway. Elife, 4, e05597. <lb/>BIRON, D., SHIBUYA, M., GABEL, C., WASSERMAN, S. M., CLARK, D. A., <lb/>BROWN, A., SENGUPTA, P. &amp; SAMUEL, A. D. 2006. A diacylglycerol kinase <lb/>modulates long-term thermotactic behavioral plasticity in C. elegans. Nat <lb/>Neurosci, 9, 1499-505. <lb/>BLAUWENDRAAT, C., HEILBRON, K., VALLERGA, C. L., BANDRES-CIGA, S., <lb/>VON COELLN, R., PIHLSTROM, L., SIMON-SANCHEZ, J., SCHULTE, C., <lb/>SHARMA, M., KROHN, L., SIITONEN, A., IWAKI, H., LEONARD, H., NOYCE, A. <lb/>J., TAN, M., GIBBS, J. R., HERNANDEZ, D. G., SCHOLZ, S. W., JANKOVIC, J., <lb/>SHULMAN, L. M., LESAGE, S., CORVOL, J. C., BRICE, A., VAN HILTEN, J. J., <lb/>MARINUS, J., EEROLA-RAUTIO, J., TIENARI, P., MAJAMAA, K., TOFT, M., <lb/>GROSSET, D. G., GASSER, T., HEUTINK, P., SHULMAN, J. M., WOOD, N., <lb/>HARDY, J., MORRIS, H. R., HINDS, D. A., GRATTEN, J., VISSCHER, P. M., <lb/>GAN-OR, Z., NALLS, M. A., SINGLETON, A. B., TEAM, A. R. &amp; IPDGC 2019. <lb/>Parkinson&apos;s disease age at onset genome-wide association study: Defining <lb/>heritability, genetic loci, and alpha-synuclein mechanisms. Movement Disorders, <lb/>34, 866-875. <lb/>BOYKEN, J., GRONBORG, M., RIEDEL, D., URLAUB, H., JAHN, R. &amp; CHUA, J. <lb/>J. E. 2013. Molecular Profiling of Synaptic Vesicle Docking Sites Reveals Novel <lb/>Proteins but Few Differences between Glutamatergic and GABAergic Synapses. <lb/>Neuron, 78, 285-297. <lb/>BRENNER, S. 1974. The genetics of Caenorhabditis elegans. Genetics, 77, 71-<lb/>94. <lb/>BUNGE, M. B. 1973. Fine structure of nerve fibers and growth cones of isolated <lb/>sympathetic neurons in culture. J Cell Biol, 56, 713-35. <lb/>CAO, M., WU, Y., ASHRAFI, G., MCCARTNEY, A. J., WHEELER, H., <lb/>BUSHONG, E. A., BOASSA, D., ELLISMAN, M. H., RYAN, T. A. &amp; DE CAMILLI, <lb/>P. 2017. Parkinson Sac Domain Mutation in Synaptojanin 1 Impairs Clathrin <lb/>Uncoating at Synapses and Triggers Dystrophic Changes in Dopaminergic <lb/>Axons. Neuron, 93, 882-896 e5. <lb/>CAO, M. A., PARK, D., WU, Y. M. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2020. Absence of <lb/>Sac2/INPP5F enhances the phenotype of a Parkinson&apos;s disease mutation of <lb/>synaptojanin 1. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United <lb/>States of America, 117, 12428-12434. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>CHANTRANUPONG, L., SAULNIER, J. L., WANG, W., JONES, D. R., PACOLD, <lb/>M. E. &amp; SABATINI, B. L. 2020. Rapid purification and metabolomic profiling of <lb/>synaptic vesicles from mammalian brain. Elife, 9. <lb/>CHEUNG, Z. H. &amp; IP, N. Y. 2009. The emerging role of autophagy in Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>disease. Mol Brain, 2, 29. <lb/>CLARK, D. A., BIRON, D., SENGUPTA, P. &amp; SAMUEL, A. D. T. 2006. The AFD <lb/>sensory neurons encode multiple functions underlying thermotactic behavior in <lb/>Caenorhabditis elegans. Journal of Neuroscience, 26, 7444-7451. <lb/>COLON-RAMOS, D. A., MARGETA, M. A. &amp; SHEN, K. 2007. Glia promote local <lb/>synaptogenesis through UNC-6 (netrin) signaling in C-elegans. Science, 318, <lb/>103-106. <lb/>CRAWLEY, O., OPPERMAN, K. J., DESBOIS, M., ADRADOS, I., BORGEN, M. <lb/>A., GILES, A. C., DUCKETT, D. R. &amp; GRILL, B. 2019. Autophagy is inhibited by <lb/>ubiquitin ligase activity in the nervous system. Nature Communications, 10. <lb/>CREMONA, O., DI PAOLO, G., WENK, M. R., LUTHI, A., KIM, W. T., TAKEI, K., <lb/>DANIELL, L., NEMOTO, Y., SHEARS, S. B., FLAVELL, R. A., MCCORMICK, D. <lb/>A. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 1999. Essential role of phosphoinositide metabolism in <lb/>synaptic vesicle recycling. Cell, 99, 179-88. <lb/>DE PACE, R., SKIRZEWSKI, M., DAMME, M., MATTERA, R., MERCURIO, J., <lb/>FOSTER, A. M., CUITINO, L., JARNIK, M., HOFFMANN, V., MORRIS, H. D., <lb/>HAN, T. U., MANCINI, G. M. S., BUONANNO, A. &amp; BONIFACINO, J. S. 2018. <lb/>Altered distribution of ATG9A and accumulation of axonal aggregates in neurons <lb/>from a mouse model of AP-4 deficiency syndrome. PLoS Genet, 14, e1007363. <lb/>DELL&apos;ANGELICA, E. C. 2009. AP-3-dependent trafficking and disease: the first <lb/>decade. Curr Opin Cell Biol, 21, 552-9. <lb/>DELL&apos;ANGELICA, E. C., OHNO, H., OOI, C. E., RABINOVICH, E., ROCHE, K. <lb/>W. &amp; BONIFACINO, J. S. 1997. AP-3: an adaptor-like protein complex with <lb/>ubiquitous expression. EMBO J, 16, 917-28. <lb/>DITTMAN, J. S. &amp; KAPLAN, J. M. 2006. Factors regulating the abundance and <lb/>localization of synaptobrevin in the plasma membrane. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, <lb/>103, 11399-404. <lb/>FENG, Y. C. &amp; KLIONSKY, D. J. 2017. Autophagic membrane delivery through <lb/>ATG9. Cell Research, 27, 161-162. <lb/>FERGUSON, S. M., BRASNJO, G., HAYASHI, M., WOLFEL, M., COLLESI, C., <lb/>GIOVEDI, S., RAIMONDI, A., GONG, L. W., ARIEL, P., PARADISE, S., <lb/>O&apos;TOOLE, E., FLAVELL, R., CREMONA, O., MIESENBOCK, G., RYAN, T. A. &amp; <lb/>DE CAMILLI, P. 2007. A selective activity-dependent requirement for dynamin 1 <lb/>in synaptic vesicle endocytosis. Science, 316, 570-574. <lb/>FERGUSON, S. M. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2012. Dynamin, a membrane-remodelling <lb/>GTPase. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol, 13, 75-88. <lb/>FERGUSON, S. M., RAIMONDI, A., PARADISE, S., SHEN, H., MESAKI, K., <lb/>FERGUSON, A., DESTAING, O., KO, G., TAKASAKI, J., CREMONA, O., E, O. <lb/>T. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2009. Coordinated actions of actin and BAR proteins <lb/>upstream of dynamin at endocytic clathrin-coated pits. Dev Cell, 17, 811-22. <lb/>GAN, Q. &amp; WATANABE, S. 2018. Synaptic Vesicle Endocytosis in Different <lb/>Model Systems. Front Cell Neurosci, 12, 171. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>GEORGE, A. A., HAYDEN, S., STANTON, G. R. &amp; BROCKERHOFF, S. E. 2016. <lb/>Arf6 and the 5&apos;phosphatase of synaptojanin 1 regulate autophagy in cone <lb/>photoreceptors. Bioessays, 38 Suppl 1, S119-35. <lb/>GOMEZ-SANCHEZ, R., ROSE, J., GUIMARAES, R., MARI, M., PAPINSKI, D., <lb/>RIETER, E., GEERTS, W. J., HARDENBERG, R., KRAFT, C., UNGERMANN, C. <lb/>&amp; REGGIORI, F. 2018. Atg9 establishes Atg2-dependent contact sites between <lb/>the endoplasmic reticulum and phagophores. J Cell Biol, 217, 2743-2763. <lb/>GUARDIA, C. M., CHRISTENSON, E. T., ZHOU, W., TAN, X. F., LIAN, T., <lb/>FARALDO-GOMEZ, J. D., BONIFACINO, J. S., JIANG, J. &amp; BANERJEE, A. <lb/>2020. The structure of human ATG9A and its interplay with the lipid bilayer. <lb/>Autophagy, 1-2. <lb/>HARRIS, T. W., HARTWIEG, E., HORVITZ, H. R. &amp; JORGENSEN, E. M. 2000. <lb/>Mutations in synaptojanin disrupt synaptic vesicle recycling. Journal of Cell <lb/>Biology, 150, 589-599. <lb/>HATA, Y., SLAUGHTER, C. A. &amp; SUDHOF, T. C. 1993. Synaptic vesicle fusion <lb/>complex contains unc-18 homologue bound to syntaxin. Nature, 366, 347-51. <lb/>HAWK, J. D., CALVO, A. C., LIU, P., ALMORIL-PORRAS, A., ALJOBEH, A., <lb/>TORRUELLA-SUAREZ, M. L., REN, I., COOK, N., GREENWOOD, J., LUO, L. <lb/>J., WANG, Z. W., SAMUEL, A. D. T. &amp; COLON-RAMOS, D. A. 2018. Integration <lb/>of Plasticity Mechanisms within a Single Sensory Neuron of C. elegans Actuates <lb/>a Memory. Neuron, 97, 356-+. <lb/>HAYASHI, M., RAIMONDI, A., O&apos;TOOLE, E., PARADISE, S., COLLESI, C., <lb/>CREMONA, O., FERGUSON, S. M. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2008. Cell-and stimulus-<lb/>dependent heterogeneity of synaptic vesicle endocytic recycling mechanisms <lb/>revealed by studies of dynamin 1-null neurons. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 105, <lb/>2175-80. <lb/>HILL, S. E., KAUFFMAN, K. J., KROUT, M., RICHMOND, J. E., MELIA, T. J. &amp; <lb/>COLON-RAMOS, D. A. 2019. Maturation and Clearance of Autophagosomes in <lb/>Neurons Depends on a Specific Cysteine Protease Isoform, ATG-4.2. <lb/>Developmental Cell, 49, 251-+. <lb/>HOFFMANN, S., ORLANDO, M., ANDRZEJAK, E., BRUNS, C., TRIMBUCH, T., <lb/>ROSENMUND, C., GARNER, C. C. &amp; ACKERMANN, F. 2019. Light-Activated <lb/>ROS Production Induces Synaptic Autophagy. J Neurosci, 39, 2163-2183. <lb/>HUANG, S., JIA, K., WANG, Y., ZHOU, Z. &amp; LEVINE, B. 2013. Autophagy genes <lb/>function in apoptotic cell corpse clearance during C. elegans embryonic <lb/>development. Autophagy, 9, 138-149. <lb/>JANG, S., NELSON, J. C., BEND, E. G., RODRIGUEZ-LAUREANO, L., <lb/>TUEROS, F. G., CARTAGENOVA, L., UNDERWOOD, K., JORGENSEN, E. M. <lb/>&amp; COLON-RAMOS, D. A. 2016. Glycolytic Enzymes Localize to Synapses under <lb/>Energy Stress to Support Synaptic Function. Neuron, 90, 278-291. <lb/>JANG, S., XUAN, Z., LAGOY, R. C., JAWERTH, L. M., GONZALEZ, I. J., <lb/>SINGH, M., PRASHAD, S., KIM, H. S., PATEL, A., ALBRECHT, D. R., HYMAN, <lb/>A. A. &amp; COLON-RAMOS, D. A. 2020. Phosphofructokinase Relocalizes into <lb/>Subcellular Compartments with Liquid-like Properties In Vivo. Biophys J. <lb/>KARABIYIK, C., LEE, M. J. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. 2017. Autophagy impairment <lb/>in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Essays Biochem, 61, 711-720. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>KARANASIOS, E., WALKER, S. A., OKKENHAUG, H., MANIFAVA, M., <lb/>HUMMEL, E., ZIMMERMANN, H., AHMED, Q., DOMART, M. C., COLLINSON, <lb/>L. &amp; KTISTAKIS, N. T. 2016. Autophagy initiation by ULK complex assembly on <lb/>ER tubulovesicular regions marked by ATG9 vesicles. Nature Communications, <lb/>7. <lb/>KATSUMATA, K., NISHIYAMA, J., INOUE, T., MIZUSHIMA, N., TAKEDA, J. &amp; <lb/>YUZAKI, M. 2010. Dynein-and activity-dependent retrograde transport of <lb/>autophagosomes in neuronal axons. Autophagy, 6, 378-85. <lb/>KIM, W. T., CHANG, S. H., DANIELL, L., CREMONA, O., DI PAOLO, G. &amp; DE <lb/>CAMILLI, P. 2002. Delayed reentry of recycling vesicles into the fusion-<lb/>competent synaptic vesicle pool in synaptojanin 1 knockout mice. Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America, 99, 17143-<lb/>17148. <lb/>KOLOTUEV, I. 2014. Positional correlative anatomy of invertebrate model <lb/>organisms increases efficiency of TEM data production. Microsc Microanal, 20, <lb/>1392-403. <lb/>KOLOTUEV, I., BUMBARGER, D. J., LABOUESSE, M. &amp; SCHWAB, Y. 2012. <lb/>Targeted ultramicrotomy: a valuable tool for correlated light and electron <lb/>microscopy of small model organisms. Methods Cell Biol, 111, 203-22. <lb/>KONONENKO, N. L., CLASSEN, G. A., KUIJPERS, M., PUCHKOV, D., <lb/>MARITZEN, T., TEMPES, A., MALIK, A. R., SKALECKA, A., BERA, S., <lb/>JAWORSKI, J. &amp; HAUCKE, V. 2017. Retrograde transport of TrkB-containing <lb/>autophagosomes via the adaptor AP-2 mediates neuronal complexity and <lb/>prevents neurodegeneration. Nat Commun, 8, 14819. <lb/>KREBS, C. E., KARKHEIRAN, S., POWELL, J. C., CAO, M., MAKAROV, V., <lb/>DARVISH, H., DI PAOLO, G., WALKER, R. H., SHAHIDI, G. A., BUXBAUM, J. <lb/>D., DE CAMILLI, P., YUE, Z. Y. &amp; PAISAN-RUIZ, C. 2013. The Sac1 Domain of <lb/>SYNJ1 Identified Mutated in a Family with Early-Onset Progressive Parkinsonism <lb/>with Generalized Seizures. Human Mutation, 34, 1200-1207. <lb/>KULKARNI, A., CHEN, J. &amp; MADAY, S. 2018. Neuronal autophagy and <lb/>intercellular regulation of homeostasis in the brain. Curr Opin Neurobiol, 51, 29-<lb/>36. <lb/>LIANG, Q. Q., YANG, P. G., TIAN, E., HAN, J. H. &amp; ZHANG, H. 2012. The C. <lb/>elegans ATG101 homolog EPG-9 directly interacts with EPG-1/Atg13 and is <lb/>essential for autophagy. Autophagy, 8, 1426-1433. <lb/>LIANG, Y. &amp; SIGRIST, S. 2018. Autophagy and proteostasis in the control of <lb/>synapse aging and disease. Curr Opin Neurobiol, 48, 113-121. <lb/>LU, Q., YANG, P., HUANG, X., HU, W., GUO, B., WU, F., LIN, L., KOVACS, A. <lb/>L., YU, L. &amp; ZHANG, H. 2011. The WD40 repeat PtdIns(3)P-binding protein <lb/>EPG-6 regulates progression of omegasomes to autophagosomes. Dev Cell, 21, <lb/>343-57. <lb/>LYNCH-DAY, M. A., MAO, K., WANG, K., ZHAO, M. &amp; KLIONSKY, D. J. 2012. <lb/>The role of autophagy in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Cold Spring Harb Perspect Med, 2, <lb/>a009357. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>MADAY, S., WALLACE, K. E. &amp; HOLZBAUR, E. L. 2012. Autophagosomes <lb/>initiate distally and mature during transport toward the cell soma in primary <lb/>neurons. J Cell Biol, 196, 407-17. <lb/>MAEDA, S., YAMAMOTO, H., KINCH, L. N., GARZA, C. M., TAKAHASHI, S., <lb/>OTOMO, C., GRISHIN, N. V., FORLI, S., MIZUSHIMA, N. &amp; OTOMO, T. 2020. <lb/>Structure, lipid scrambling activity and role in autophagosome formation of <lb/>ATG9A. Nat Struct Mol Biol. <lb/>MANIL-SEGALEN, M., LEFEBVRE, C., JENZER, C., TRICHET, M., <lb/>BOULOGNE, C., SATIAT-JEUNEMAITRE, B. &amp; LEGOUIS, R. 2014. The C. <lb/>elegans LC3 acts downstream of GABARAP to degrade autophagosomes by <lb/>interacting with the HOPS subunit VPS39. Dev Cell, 28, 43-55. <lb/>MANNING, L. &amp; RICHMOND, J. 2015. High-Pressure Freeze and Freeze <lb/>Substitution Electron Microscopy in C. elegans. Methods Mol Biol, 1327, 121-40. <lb/>MATOBA, K., KOTANI, T., TSUTSUMI, A., TSUJI, T., MORI, T., NOSHIRO, D., <lb/>SUGITA, Y., NOMURA, N., IWATA, S., OHSUMI, Y., FUJIMOTO, T., <lb/>NAKATOGAWA, H., KIKKAWA, M. &amp; NODA, N. N. 2020. Atg9 is a lipid <lb/>scramblase that mediates autophagosomal membrane expansion. Nat Struct Mol <lb/>Biol. <lb/>MATOBA, K. &amp; NODA, N. N. 2020. Secret of Atg9: lipid scramblase activity <lb/>drives de novo autophagosome biogenesis. Cell Death Differ. <lb/>MATTERA, R., PARK, S. Y., DE PACE, R., GUARDIA, C. M. &amp; BONIFACINO, J. <lb/>S. 2017. AP-4 mediates export of ATG9A from the trans-Golgi network to <lb/>promote autophagosome formation. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A, 114, E10697-<lb/>E10706. <lb/>MENZIES, F. M., FLEMING, A., CARICASOLE, A., BENTO, C. F., ANDREWS, <lb/>S. P., ASHKENAZI, A., FULLGRABE, J., JACKSON, A., JIMENEZ SANCHEZ, <lb/>M., KARABIYIK, C., LICITRA, F., LOPEZ RAMIREZ, A., PAVEL, M., PURI, C., <lb/>RENNA, M., RICKETTS, T., SCHLOTAWA, L., VICINANZA, M., WON, H., ZHU, <lb/>Y., SKIDMORE, J. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. 2017. Autophagy and <lb/>Neurodegeneration: Pathogenic Mechanisms and Therapeutic Opportunities. <lb/>Neuron, 93, 1015-1034. <lb/>MENZIES, F. M., FLEMING, A. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. 2015. Compromised <lb/>autophagy and neurodegenerative diseases. Nat Rev Neurosci, 16, 345-57. <lb/>MILOSEVIC, I., GIOVEDI, S., LOU, X., RAIMONDI, A., COLLESI, C., SHEN, H., <lb/>PARADISE, S., O&apos;TOOLE, E., FERGUSON, S., CREMONA, O. &amp; DE CAMILLI, <lb/>P. 2011. Recruitment of endophilin to clathrin-coated pit necks is required for <lb/>efficient vesicle uncoating after fission. Neuron, 72, 587-601. <lb/>MURDOCH, J. D., ROSTOSKY, C. M., GOWRISANKARAN, S., ARORA, A. S., <lb/>SOUKUP, S. F., VIDAL, R., CAPECE, V., FREYTAG, S., FISCHER, A., <lb/>VERSTREKEN, P., BONN, S., RAIMUNDO, N. &amp; MILOSEVIC, I. 2016. <lb/>Endophilin-A Deficiency Induces the Foxo3a-Fbxo32 Network in the Brain and <lb/>Causes Dysregulation of Autophagy and the Ubiquitin-Proteasome System. Cell <lb/>Rep, 17, 1071-1086. <lb/>NAKATSU, F. &amp; OHNO, H. 2003. Adaptor protein complexes as the key <lb/>regulators of protein sorting in the post-Golgi network. Cell Structure and <lb/>Function, 28, 419-429. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>NALLS, M. A., PANKRATZ, N., LILL, C. M., DO, C. B., HERNANDEZ, D. G., <lb/>SAAD, M., DESTEFANO, A. L., KARA, E., BRAS, J., SHARMA, M., SCHULTE, <lb/>C., KELLER, M. F., AREPALLI, S., LETSON, C., EDSALL, C., STEFANSSON, <lb/>H., LIU, X., PLINER, H., LEE, J. H., CHENG, R., INTERNATIONAL <lb/>PARKINSON&apos;S DISEASE GENOMICS, C., PARKINSON&apos;S STUDY GROUP <lb/>PARKINSON&apos;S RESEARCH: THE ORGANIZED, G. I., ANDME, GENEPD, <lb/>NEUROGENETICS RESEARCH, C., HUSSMAN INSTITUTE OF HUMAN, G., <lb/>ASHKENAZI JEWISH DATASET, I., COHORTS FOR, H., AGING RESEARCH <lb/>IN GENETIC, E., NORTH AMERICAN BRAIN EXPRESSION, C., UNITED <lb/>KINGDOM BRAIN EXPRESSION, C., GREEK PARKINSON&apos;S DISEASE, C., <lb/>ALZHEIMER GENETIC ANALYSIS, G., IKRAM, M. A., IOANNIDIS, J. P., <lb/>HADJIGEORGIOU, G. M., BIS, J. C., MARTINEZ, M., PERLMUTTER, J. S., <lb/>GOATE, A., MARDER, K., FISKE, B., SUTHERLAND, M., XIROMERISIOU, G., <lb/>MYERS, R. H., CLARK, L. N., STEFANSSON, K., HARDY, J. A., HEUTINK, P., <lb/>CHEN, H., WOOD, N. W., HOULDEN, H., PAYAMI, H., BRICE, A., SCOTT, W. <lb/>K., GASSER, T., BERTRAM, L., ERIKSSON, N., FOROUD, T. &amp; SINGLETON, <lb/>A. B. 2014. Large-scale meta-analysis of genome-wide association data <lb/>identifies six new risk loci for Parkinson&apos;s disease. Nat Genet, 46, 989-93. <lb/>NODA, T. 2017. Autophagy in the context of the cellular membrane-trafficking <lb/>system: the enigma of Atg9 vesicles. Biochemical Society Transactions, 45, <lb/>1323-1331. <lb/>OHASHI, Y. &amp; MUNRO, S. 2010. Membrane Delivery to the Yeast <lb/>Autophagosome from the Golgi-Endosomal System. Molecular Biology of the <lb/>Cell, 21, 3998-4008. <lb/>PAIX, A., FOLKMANN, A. &amp; SEYDOUX, G. 2017. Precision genome editing <lb/>using CRISPR-Cas9 and linear repair templates in C. elegans. Methods, 121, 86-<lb/>93. <lb/>PARK, S. Y. &amp; GUO, X. 2014. Adaptor protein complexes and intracellular <lb/>transport. Biosci Rep, 34. <lb/>POPOVIC, D. &amp; DIKIC, I. 2014. TBC1D5 and the AP2 complex regulate ATG9 <lb/>trafficking and initiation of autophagy. EMBO Rep, 15, 392-401. <lb/>PURI, C., RENNA, M., BENTO, C. F., MOREAU, K. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. <lb/>2013. Diverse autophagosome membrane sources coalesce in recycling <lb/>endosomes. Cell, 154, 1285-99. <lb/>PURI, C., RENNA, M., BENTO, C. F., MOREAU, K. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. <lb/>2014. ATG16L1 meets ATG9 in recycling endosomes: additional roles for the <lb/>plasma membrane and endocytosis in autophagosome biogenesis. Autophagy, <lb/>10, 182-4. <lb/>QUADRI, M., FANG, M., PICILLO, M., OLGIATI, S., BREEDVELD, G. J., <lb/>GRAAFLAND, J., WU, B., XU, F., ERRO, R., AMBONI, M., PAPPATA, S., <lb/>QUARANTELLI, M., ANNESI, G., QUATTRONE, A., CHIEN, H. F., BARBOSA, <lb/>E. R., INTERNATIONAL PARKINSONISM GENETICS, N., OOSTRA, B. A., <lb/>BARONE, P., WANG, J. &amp; BONIFATI, V. 2013. Mutation in the SYNJ1 gene <lb/>associated with autosomal recessive, early-onset Parkinsonism. Hum Mutat, 34, <lb/>1208-15. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>RAIMONDI, A., FERGUSON, S. M., LOU, X., ARMBRUSTER, M., PARADISE, <lb/>S., GIOVEDI, S., MESSA, M., KONO, N., TAKASAKI, J., CAPPELLO, V., <lb/>O&apos;TOOLE, E., RYAN, T. A. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2011. Overlapping role of dynamin <lb/>isoforms in synaptic vesicle endocytosis. Neuron, 70, 1100-14. <lb/>REGGIORI, F., SHINTANI, T., NAIR, U. &amp; KLIONSKY, D. J. 2005. Atg9 cycles <lb/>between mitochondria and the pre-autophagosomal structure in yeasts. <lb/>Autophagy, 1, 101-109. <lb/>REGGIORI, F., TUCKER, K. A., STROMHAUG, P. E. &amp; KLIONSKY, D. J. 2004. <lb/>The Atg1-Atg13 complex regulates Atg9 and Atg23 retrieval transport from the <lb/>pre-autophagosomal structure. Developmental Cell, 6, 79-90. <lb/>RICHMOND, J. E., DAVIS, W. S. &amp; JORGENSEN, E. M. 1999. UNC-13 is <lb/>required for synaptic vesicle fusion in C-elegans. Nature Neuroscience, 2, 959-<lb/>964. <lb/>ROSTAING, P., WEIMER, R. M., JORGENSEN, E. M., TRILLER, A. &amp; <lb/>BESSEREAU, J. L. 2004. Preservation of immunoreactivity and fine structure of <lb/>adult C. elegans tissues using high-pressure freezing. J Histochem Cytochem, <lb/>52, 1-12. <lb/>ROUT, M. P. &amp; FIELD, M. C. 2017. The Evolution of Organellar Coat Complexes <lb/>and Organization of the Eukaryotic Cell. Annu Rev Biochem, 86, 637-657. <lb/>SAHEKI, Y. &amp; DE CAMILLI, P. 2012. Synaptic vesicle endocytosis. Cold Spring <lb/>Harb Perspect Biol, 4, a005645. <lb/>SAWA-MAKARSKA, J., BAUMANN, V., COUDEVYLLE, N., VON BULOW, S., <lb/>NOGELLOVA, V., ABERT, C., SCHUSCHNIG, M., GRAEF, M., HUMMER, G. &amp; <lb/>MARTENS, S. 2020. Reconstitution of autophagosome nucleation defines Atg9 <lb/>vesicles as seeds for membrane formation. Science, 369. <lb/>SCHINDELIN, J., ARGANDA-CARRERAS, I., FRISE, E., KAYNIG, V., <lb/>LONGAIR, M., PIETZSCH, T., PREIBISCH, S., RUEDEN, C., SAALFELD, S., <lb/>SCHMID, B., TINEVEZ, J. Y., WHITE, D. J., HARTENSTEIN, V., ELICEIRI, K., <lb/>TOMANCAK, P. &amp; CARDONA, A. 2012. Fiji: an open-source platform for <lb/>biological-image analysis. Nat Methods, 9, 676-82. <lb/>SCHREIJ, A. M., FON, E. A. &amp; MCPHERSON, P. S. 2016. Endocytic membrane <lb/>trafficking and neurodegenerative disease. Cell Mol Life Sci, 73, 1529-45. <lb/>SEKITO, T., KAWAMATA, T., ICHIKAWA, R., SUZUKI, K. &amp; OHSUMI, Y. 2009. <lb/>Atg17 recruits Atg9 to organize the pre-autophagosomal structure. Genes Cells, <lb/>14, 525-38. <lb/>SHEHATA, M., MATSUMURA, H., OKUBO-SUZUKI, R., OHKAWA, N. &amp; <lb/>INOKUCHI, K. 2012. Neuronal Stimulation Induces Autophagy in Hippocampal <lb/>Neurons That Is Involved in AMPA Receptor Degradation after Chemical Long-<lb/>Term Depression. Journal of Neuroscience, 32, 10413-10422. <lb/>SON, J. H., SHIM, J. H., KIM, K. H., HA, J. Y. &amp; HAN, J. Y. 2012. Neuronal <lb/>autophagy and neurodegenerative diseases. Exp Mol Med, 44, 89-98. <lb/>SOUKUP, S. F., KUENEN, S., VANHAUWAERT, R., MANETSBERGER, J., <lb/>HERNANDEZ-DIAZ, S., SWERTS, J., SCHOOVAERTS, N., VILAIN, S., <lb/>GOUNKO, N. V., VINTS, K., GEENS, A., DE STROOPER, B. &amp; VERSTREKEN, <lb/>P. 2016. A LRRK2-Dependent EndophilinA Phosphoswitch Is Critical for <lb/>Macroautophagy at Presynaptic Terminals. Neuron, 92, 829-844. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>STAVOE, A. K. H., HILL, S. E., HALL, D. H. &amp; COLON-RAMOS, D. A. 2016. <lb/>KIF1A/UNC-104 Transports ATG-9 to Regulate Neurodevelopment and <lb/>Autophagy at Synapses. Developmental Cell, 38, 171-185. <lb/>STAVOE, A. K. H. &amp; HOLZBAUR, E. L. F. 2019. Axonal autophagy: Mini-review <lb/>for autophagy in the CNS. Neurosci Lett, 697, 17-23. <lb/>SUDHOF, T. C. 1995. The synaptic vesicle cycle: a cascade of protein-protein <lb/>interactions. Nature, 375, 645-53. <lb/>SUZUKI, K., KIRISAKO, T., KAMADA, Y., MIZUSHIMA, N., NODA, T. &amp; <lb/>OHSUMI, Y. 2001. The pre-autophagosomal structure organized by concerted <lb/>functions of APG genes is essential for autophagosome formation. EMBO J, 20, <lb/>5971-81. <lb/>TRINH, J. &amp; FARRER, M. 2013. Advances in the genetics of Parkinson disease. <lb/>Nature Reviews Neurology, 9, 445-454. <lb/>TSUKADA, M. &amp; OHSUMI, Y. 1993. Isolation and characterization of autophagy-<lb/>defective mutants of Saccharomyces cerevisiae. FEBS Lett, 333, 169-74. <lb/>VAN DER VAART, A. &amp; REGGIORI, F. 2010. The Golgi complex as a source for <lb/>yeast autophagosomal membranes. Autophagy, 6, 800-801. <lb/>VANHAUWAERT, R., KUENEN, S., MASIUS, R., BADEMOSI, A., <lb/>MANETSBERGER, J., SCHOOVAERTS, N., BOUNTI, L., GONTCHARENKO, <lb/>S., SWERTS, J., VILAIN, S., PICILLO, M., BARONE, P., MUNSHI, S. T., DE <lb/>VRIJ, F. M., KUSHNER, S. A., GOUNKO, N. V., MANDEMAKERS, W., <lb/>BONIFATI, V., MEUNIER, F. A., SOUKUP, S. F. &amp; VERSTREKEN, P. 2017. The <lb/>SAC1 domain in synaptojanin is required for autophagosome maturation at <lb/>presynaptic terminals. EMBO J, 36, 1392-1411. <lb/>VERSTREKEN, P., KOH, T. W., SCHULZE, K. L., ZHAI, R. G., HIESINGER, P. <lb/>R., ZHOU, Y., MEHTA, S. Q., CAO, Y., ROOS, J. &amp; BELLEN, H. J. 2003. <lb/>Synaptojanin is recruited by Endophilin to promote synaptic vesicle uncoating. <lb/>Neuron, 40, 733-748. <lb/>VIDYADHARA, D. J., LEE, J. E. &amp; CHANDRA, S. S. 2019. Role of the <lb/>endolysosomal system in Parkinson&apos;s disease. Journal of Neurochemistry, 150, <lb/>487-506. <lb/>VIJAYAN, V. &amp; VERSTREKEN, P. 2017. Autophagy in the presynaptic <lb/>compartment in health and disease. J Cell Biol, 216, 1895-1906. <lb/>WANG, T., MARTIN, S., PAPADOPULOS, A., HARPER, C., MAVLYUTOV, T., <lb/>NIRANJAN, D., GLASS, N., COOPER-WHITE, J., SIBARITA, J. B., CHOQUET, <lb/>D., DAVLETOV, B. &amp; MEUNIER, F. 2015. Control of autophagosome axonal <lb/>retrograde flux by presynaptic activity unveiled using botulinum neurotoxin type-<lb/>A. Journal of Neurochemistry, 134, 165-165. <lb/>WATANABE, S., TRIMBUCH, T., CAMACHO-PEREZ, M., ROST, B. R., <lb/>BROKOWSKI, B., SOHL-KIELCZYNSKI, B., FELIES, A., DAVIS, M. W., <lb/>ROSENMUND, C. &amp; JORGENSEN, E. M. 2014. Clathrin regenerates synaptic <lb/>vesicles from endosomes. Nature, 515, 228-33. <lb/>WEBBER, J. L., YOUNG, A. R. J. &amp; TOOZE, S. A. 2007. Atg9 trafficking in <lb/>mammalian cells. Autophagy, 3, 54-56. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>WHITE, J. G., SOUTHGATE, E., THOMSON, J. N. &amp; BRENNER, S. 1986. The <lb/>structure of the nervous system of the nematode Caenorhabditis elegans. Philos <lb/>Trans R Soc Lond B Biol Sci, 314, 1-340. <lb/>WU, F., WATANABE, Y., GUO, X. Y., QI, X., WANG, P., ZHAO, H. Y., WANG, <lb/>Z., FUJIOKA, Y., ZHANG, H., REN, J. Q., FANG, T. C., SHEN, Y. X., FENG, W., <lb/>HU, J. J., NODA, N. N. &amp; ZHANG, H. 2015. Structural Basis of the Differential <lb/>Function of the Two C. elegans Atg8 Homologs, LGG-1 and LGG-2, in <lb/>Autophagy. Mol Cell, 60, 914-29. <lb/>YAMAMOTO, H., KAKUTA, S., WATANABE, T. M., KITAMURA, A., SEKITO, T., <lb/>KONDO-KAKUTA, C., ICHIKAWA, R., KINJO, M. &amp; OHSUMI, Y. 2012. Atg9 <lb/>vesicles are an important membrane source during early steps of <lb/>autophagosome formation. Journal of Cell Biology, 198, 219-233. <lb/>YORIMITSU, T. &amp; KLIONSKY, D. J. 2005. Autophagy: molecular machinery for <lb/>self-eating. Cell Death Differ, 12 Suppl 2, 1542-52. <lb/>ZAVODSZKY, E., SEAMAN, M. N., MOREAU, K., JIMENEZ-SANCHEZ, M., <lb/>BREUSEGEM, S. Y., HARBOUR, M. E. &amp; RUBINSZTEIN, D. C. 2014. Mutation <lb/>in VPS35 associated with Parkinson&apos;s disease impairs WASH complex <lb/>association and inhibits autophagy. Nat Commun, 5, 3828. <lb/>ZHOU, C., MA, K., GAO, R., MU, C., CHEN, L., LIU, Q., LUO, Q., FENG, D., <lb/>ZHU, Y. &amp; CHEN, Q. 2017. Regulation of mATG9 trafficking by Src-and ULK1-<lb/>mediated phosphorylation in basal and starvation-induced autophagy. Cell Res, <lb/>27, 184-201. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>D <lb/>V <lb/>L <lb/>R <lb/>P <lb/>A <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>E <lb/>WT <lb/>F merge <lb/>AIY <lb/>Presynaptic regions <lb/>WT <lb/>RAB-3 <lb/>D <lb/>Presynaptic <lb/>regions <lb/>B <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>C <lb/>C&apos; <lb/>WT <lb/>* <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>apb-3 <lb/>U ATG-9 <lb/>H <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>S <lb/>X <lb/>Y <lb/>Z <lb/>T <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>apb-3 <lb/>SNG-1 <lb/>W <lb/>SNG-1 <lb/>V <lb/>WT <lb/>WT <lb/>H <lb/>WT <lb/>Presynaptic <lb/>region <lb/>WT <lb/>WT <lb/>J <lb/>K <lb/>WT <lb/>I <lb/>RAB-3 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>SNG-1 <lb/>G <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>WT <lb/>N <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>WT <lb/>O <lb/>merge <lb/>WT <lb/>M AMAN-2 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>Q <lb/>WT <lb/>merge <lb/>R <lb/>WT <lb/>TGN-38 <lb/>P <lb/>WT <lb/>Golgi <lb/>L <lb/>TGN-38 <lb/>AMAN-2 <lb/>L&apos; <lb/>Golgi <lb/>trans <lb/>medial/cis <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>a p b -3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Ratio of SNG-1 intensity at <lb/>cell body / synapses (A.U.) <lb/>ns <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>a p b -3 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>2500 <lb/>ATG-9 enrichment <lb/>at synapses (A.U.) <lb/>** <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>a p b -3 <lb/>a p m <lb/>-3 <lb/>a p d -3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Ratio of ATG-9 intensity at <lb/>cell body / synapses (A.U.) <lb/>**** * <lb/>** <lb/>SV <lb/>u n c -2 6 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>1 5 <lb/>C <lb/>( n = 2 7 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>2 0 <lb/>C <lb/>( n = 5 3 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>2 5 <lb/>C <lb/>( n = 3 1 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 ; u n c -1 3 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>2 5 <lb/>C <lb/>( n = 1 9 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>ATG-9:GFP puncta (!2) <lb/>at zone 2 of AIY <lb/>(percent of animals) <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>A <lb/>unc-11/AP180 <lb/>unc-57/Endophilin A <lb/>dyn-1/dynamin 1 <lb/>unc-26/Synaptojanin 1 <lb/>clathrin <lb/>Exocytosis <lb/>Endocytosis <lb/>unc-13/Munc13 <lb/>unc-18/Munc18 <lb/>N <lb/>K <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>15 C 20 C 25 C <lb/>zone 2 <lb/>B&apos; <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>B <lb/>* <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>C <lb/>unc-57(ok310) <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>E <lb/>unc-26(e205) <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>D <lb/>unc-18;unc-26 <lb/>J <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>unc-13;unc-26 <lb/>I <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>unc-11(e47) <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>20 C <lb/>dyn-1(ky51) <lb/>。 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>H <lb/>25 C <lb/>dyn-1(ky51) <lb/>。 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>u n c -2 6 <lb/>( s 1 7 1 0 ) <lb/>u n c -5 7 ( o k 3 1 0 ) <lb/>u n c -1 1 ( e 4 7 ) <lb/>u n c -1 3 ; u n c -2 6 <lb/>u n c -1 8 ; u n c -2 6 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>Index of ATG-9 <lb/>mislocalization <lb/>** <lb/>*** <lb/>*** <lb/>ns ns <lb/>M <lb/>zone 3 <lb/>L&apos; <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>L <lb/>* <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>F int (U.A.) <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>normoxia <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>normoxia <lb/>hypoxia <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>F int (U.A.) <lb/>normoxia <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>LGG-1 <lb/>merge <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>I <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Surface <lb/>(biotinylation) <lb/>Total <lb/>(5% input) <lb/>IB: TfR <lb/>IB: ATG9A <lb/>C <lb/>T L <lb/>D <lb/>y n 1 / 2 <lb/>C <lb/>K <lb/>O <lb/>Size <lb/>C <lb/>T L <lb/>D <lb/>y n 1 / 2 <lb/>C <lb/>K <lb/>O <lb/>Surface ATG9A <lb/>(Surface / Total) <lb/>D <lb/>y n 1 / 2 <lb/>C <lb/>K <lb/>O <lb/>C <lb/>T L <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>Surface TfR <lb/>(Surface / Total) <lb/>C <lb/>T L <lb/>D <lb/>y n 1 / 2 <lb/>C <lb/>K <lb/>O <lb/>C <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>D <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>SNG-1 <lb/>E <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>merge <lb/>F <lb/>L G <lb/>G <lb/>-1 <lb/>( n = 2 9 ) <lb/>S N <lb/>G <lb/>-1 <lb/>( n = 3 6 ) <lb/>C <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>-1 <lb/>( n = 1 4 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>Percentage of colocalization <lb/>(ATG-9 foci and <lb/>indicated structures) <lb/>** <lb/>J <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>ATG-9 K <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>CHC-1 <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>merge <lb/>L <lb/>M <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4 <lb/>A <lb/>PAS <lb/>epg-8/Atg14 <lb/>unc-51/Atg1 <lb/>PI3K <lb/>Kinase complex <lb/>ATG-13/EPG-1 <lb/>EPG-9/Atg101 <lb/>Induction <lb/>Nucleation <lb/>Isolation <lb/>membrane <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>reservoirs <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>( n = 1 0 7 ) <lb/>u n c -5 1 / A <lb/>t g 1 ( e 3 6 9 ) ( n = 5 6 ) <lb/>e p g -9 / A <lb/>t g 1 0 1 ( b p 3 2 0 ) ( n = 3 7 ) <lb/>a t g -1 3 / e p g -1 ( b p 4 1 4 ) ( n = 3 7 ) <lb/>e p g -8 / A <lb/>t g 1 4 ( b p 2 5 1 ) ( n = 2 8 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>ATG-9:GFP puncta (!1) <lb/>at zone 2 of AIY <lb/>(percent of animals) <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>* <lb/>H <lb/>e p g -9 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>1 5 <lb/>C <lb/>e p g -9 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>2 0 <lb/>C <lb/>e p g -9 <lb/>m <lb/>u t a n t s <lb/>i n <lb/>2 5 <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>ATG-9:GFP puncta (!1) <lb/>at zone 2 of AIY <lb/>(percent of animals) <lb/>60 <lb/>107 <lb/>50 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>15 C <lb/>20 C <lb/>25 C <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>。 <lb/>G <lb/>L <lb/>K merge <lb/>epg-9/Atg101 <lb/>ATG-9 J CHC-1 <lb/>epg-9/Atg101 <lb/>epg-9/Atg101 <lb/>I <lb/>epg-8/Atg14 <lb/>F <lb/>epg-9/Atg101 <lb/>D <lb/>atg-13/epg-1 <lb/>E <lb/>unc-51/Atg1 <lb/>C <lb/>B ATG-9 <lb/>WT <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>Elongation, <lb/>Closure, <lb/>Maturation <lb/>and Fusion <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>u n c -1 3 ( e 4 5 0 ) <lb/>a t g -9 ( w <lb/>y 5 6 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 ( s 1 7 1 0 ) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>Relative ave. LGG-1 puncta <lb/>in AIY neurite <lb/>20C <lb/>25C 4hrs <lb/>55 44 <lb/>40 34 <lb/>74 53 <lb/>35 74 <lb/>*** <lb/>ns <lb/>ns <lb/>ns <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>G <lb/>F <lb/>H <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>Sac <lb/>5-Phosphotase Proline-Rich <lb/>Homo sapiens and mouse <lb/>Caenorhabditis elegans <lb/>R216Q <lb/>R258Q <lb/>A <lb/>Synaptojanin 1/unc-26 <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>Sac <lb/>PH <lb/>Sac2/sac-2 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>unc-26(s1710) <lb/>N <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>sac-2;unc-26 <lb/>O <lb/>Figure 6 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>M <lb/>L <lb/>WT <lb/>Presynaptic <lb/>regions <lb/>K <lb/>* <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>( n = 5 1 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 ( R <lb/>2 1 6 Q <lb/>) ( n = 6 0 ) <lb/>u n c -2 6 ( e 2 0 5 ) ( n = 1 0 6 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>ATG-9:GFP puncta ( 2) <lb/>at zone 2 of AIY <lb/>(percent of animals) <lb/>**** <lb/>**** <lb/>** <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>u n c -2 6 ( s 1 7 1 0 ) <lb/>s a c -2 ( g k 9 2 7 4 3 4 ) ; u n c -2 6 ( s 1 7 1 0 ) <lb/>s a c -2 ( g k 3 4 6 0 1 9 ) ; u n c -2 6 ( s 1 7 1 0 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>ATG-9:GFP puncta ( 2) <lb/>at zone 2 of AIY <lb/>(percent of animals) <lb/>**** <lb/>99 <lb/>65 <lb/>49 <lb/>31 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>WT <lb/>unc-26(R216Q) <lb/>P <lb/>S J 1 R Q <lb/>K <lb/>I <lb/>S J 1 K <lb/>O <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>** <lb/>Relative ATG9 intensity <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>N.S <lb/>I <lb/>J <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>F&apos; <lb/>G <lb/>G&apos; <lb/>H <lb/>H&apos; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">. <lb/>CC-BY-NC-ND 4.0 International license <lb/>available under a <lb/>(which was not certified by peer review) is the author/funder, who has granted bioRxiv a license to display the preprint in perpetuity. It is made <lb/>The copyright holder for this preprint <lb/>this version posted December 28, 2020. <lb/>; <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.12.28.424508 <lb/>doi: <lb/>bioRxiv preprint <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 7 <lb/>Mut <lb/>WT <lb/>Local ATG-9 traffic at synapse <lb/>Cell Body <lb/>Presynaptic <lb/>Region <lb/>Golgi <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>Clathrin <lb/>AV <lb/>AV <lb/>Clathrin <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>ATG-9 <lb/>vesicle <lb/>nucleus </body>


	</text>
</tei>
