<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>research papers <lb/>Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/>doi:10.1107/S0907444910019554 865 <lb/>Acta Crystallographica Section D <lb/>Biological <lb/>Crystallography <lb/>ISSN 0907-4449 <lb/>Structure of the N-terminal fragment of Escherichia <lb/>coli Lon protease <lb/>Mi Li, a,b Alla Gustchina, a <lb/>Fatima S. Rasulova, c Edward E. <lb/>Melnikov, d Michael R. Maurizi, c <lb/>Tatyana V. Rotanova, d Zbigniew <lb/>Dauter e and Alexander <lb/>Wlodawer a * <lb/>a <lb/>Protein Structure Section, Macromolecular <lb/>Crystallography Laboratory, National Cancer <lb/>Institute at Frederick, Frederick, <lb/>MD 21702-1201, USA, b Basic Research <lb/>Program, SAIC-Frederick, Frederick, MD 21702, <lb/>USA, c Laboratory of Cell Biology, National <lb/>Cancer Institute, Bethesda, MD 20892, USA, <lb/>d Shemyakin-Ovchinnikov Institute of <lb/>Bioorganic Chemistry, Russian Academy of <lb/>Sciences, Moscow 117997, Russia, and <lb/>e <lb/>Synchrotron Radiation Research Section, <lb/>Macromolecular Crystallography Laboratory, <lb/>NCI, Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, <lb/>IL 60439, USA <lb/>Correspondence e-mail: wlodawer@nih.gov <lb/># 2010 International Union of Crystallography <lb/>Printed in Singapore -all rights reserved <lb/> The structure of a recombinant construct consisting of <lb/>residues 1-245 of Escherichia coli Lon protease, the proto-<lb/>typical member of the A-type Lon family, is reported. This <lb/>construct encompasses all or most of the N-terminal domain of <lb/>the enzyme. The structure was solved by SeMet SAD to 2.6 A <lb/>resolution <lb/>utilizing trigonal crystals that contained one <lb/>molecule in the asymmetric unit. The molecule consists of <lb/>two compact subdomains and a very long C-terminal -helix. <lb/>The structure of the first subdomain (residues 1-117), which <lb/>consists mostly of -strands, is similar to that of the shorter <lb/>fragment previously expressed and crystallized, whereas the <lb/>second subdomain is almost entirely helical. The fold and <lb/>spatial relationship of the two subdomains, with the exception <lb/>of the C-terminal helix, closely resemble the structure of <lb/>BPP1347, a 203-amino-acid protein of unknown function from <lb/>Bordetella parapertussis, and more distantly several other <lb/>proteins. It was not possible to refine the structure to <lb/>satisfactory convergence; however, since almost all of the Se <lb/>atoms could be located on the basis of their anomalous <lb/>scattering the correctness of the overall structure is not in <lb/>question. The structure reported here was also compared with <lb/>the structures of the putative substrate-binding domains of <lb/>several proteins, showing topological similarities that should <lb/>help in defining the binding sites used by Lon substrates. <lb/> Received 29 April 2010 <lb/>Accepted 25 May 2010 <lb/>PDB Reference: N-terminal <lb/>fragment of Lon protease, <lb/>3ljc. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Lon proteases were the first well characterized enzymes that <lb/>contained both protease and ATPase domains. Studies of <lb/>the enzymatic properties of Escherichia coli Lon protease <lb/>(EcLon) established the general properties of the whole <lb/>family of such proteins (Goldberg et al., 1994; Gottesman et al., <lb/>1997; Melnikov et al., 2000). The enzymatic function of Lon <lb/>proteases is to couple ATP hydrolysis to structural disruption <lb/>and processive degradation of proteins into peptides <lb/>consisting of 5-12 amino acids. As determined by electron <lb/>microscopy (Park et al., 2006), EcLon forms hexamers of <lb/>identical 784-amino-acid polypeptide chains (Amerik et al., <lb/>1990; Goldberg et al., 1994). Although a crystal structure of the <lb/>full-length enzyme is not yet available, a number of structures <lb/>of fragments of EcLon and its orthologs from other organisms <lb/>have been reported (Botos, Melnikov, Cherry, Khalatova et al., <lb/>2004; Botos, Melnikov, Cherry, Tropea et al., 2004; Botos et al., <lb/>2005; Garcia-Nafria et al., 2010; Im et al., 2004; Li et al., 2005). <lb/>Each subunit of EcLon contains three functional domains <lb/>(Amerik et al., 1990; Gottesman et al., 1995; Rotanova et al., <lb/>2006); however, the number of separately folded structural <lb/>subdomains is most likely to be larger. EcLon was classified as <lb/>a member of the LonA family, all of which have been shown <lb/>to consist of tandem N-terminal, ATPase and proteolytic <lb/>domains (Rotanova et al., 2004). The central region of LonA <lb/>proteases, named the A domain, is an ATPase belonging to the <lb/>AAA + superfamily (Neuwald et al., 1999). The proteolytically <lb/>active C-terminal region, or P domain, defines a unique serine <lb/>protease family and has a serine-lysine catalytic dyad (Botos, <lb/>Melnikov, Cherry, Tropea et al., 2004; Rotanova et al., 2003, <lb/>2004). <lb/>The defining feature of the LonA family in bacteria is its <lb/>N-terminal domain, which is around 300-350 amino acids in <lb/>length and is differentiated by sequence conservation and <lb/>presumed functional properties. The N domain is divided into <lb/>two or more subdomains (Li et al., 2005) and is also predicted <lb/>to include an extended coiled coil (CC; amino acids $175-280 <lb/>in EcLon; Ebel et al., 1999; Lee et al., 2004; Melnikov et al., <lb/>2008). The CC segment joins the two parts of the N domain <lb/>comprising residues 1 to $200 to a small helical subdomain <lb/>($280-300) that is the final link to the A domain. The CC <lb/>segment contains a region (amino acids 233-240) that is <lb/>sensitive to proteolytic digestion (Melnikov et al., 2008). By <lb/>analogy with other ATP-dependent proteases, the N-terminal <lb/>domain of LonA is predicted to participate in recognition and <lb/>binding of target proteins or their adaptors (Ebel et al., 1999; <lb/>Iyer et al., 2004; Rotanova et al., 2004). Previously, only the <lb/>first $120 residues of the N-terminal domain have been <lb/>characterized in structural terms (Li et al., 2005). We have now <lb/>crystallized and solved the structure of a longer construct <lb/>consisting of residues 1-245 of EcLon (Lon-N245), which <lb/>extends just beyond the proteolytically sensitive region of the <lb/>CC segment. Because it is not certain that the protease-<lb/>sensitive region precisely defines a subdomain border, we will <lb/>refer to the part of the N domain purified and crystallized in <lb/>this study as the Lon-N245 fragment. <lb/>2. Materials and methods <lb/>2.1. Protein expression, purification and crystallization <lb/>To obtain a construct expressing Lon-N245, a clone of intact <lb/>E. coli Lon from plasmid pLon500 (Maurizi et al., 1985) was <lb/>moved to the pET30a vector using a two-step procedure. A <lb/>fragment of lon with an internal BstBI deletion was amplified <lb/>by PCR and inserted into the vector. The BstBI-deleted <lb/>portion of Lon was then restored by cutting and ligation. Prior <lb/>to restoration of the fragment, a silent mutation was intro-<lb/>duced into the BstBI fragment using the QuikChange proce-<lb/>dure to eliminate an internal NdeI site. The Lon-N245 reading <lb/>frame was amplified by PCR using the pET30a lon clone as a <lb/>template, placing a stop codon after codon 245 and providing <lb/>NdeI and XhoI restriction sites for cleavage and ligation into <lb/>pBAD33 under the control of the arabinose regulon. A further <lb/>modification was made by cleavage of the NdeI site and liga-<lb/>tion of a short synthetic duplex encoding a tandem array of six <lb/>histidines in frame immediately following the initiator <lb/>methionine. For expression of His 6 -Lon-N245, the plasmid was <lb/>transformed into E. coli MG1655 carrying a lon deletion and <lb/>cells were grown in LB medium. To incorporate seleno-<lb/>methionine (SeMet) into the expressed protein, the plasmid <lb/>was transformed into E. coli B834 cells (Novagen). Trans-<lb/>formed cells were grown in the defined medium recommended <lb/>by the supplier initially with limiting methionine (10 mg ml À1 ) <lb/>to an A 600 of 0.8. SeMet (30 mg ml À1 ) was added to the <lb/>medium and Lon-N245 expression was induced by the addi-<lb/>tion of 0.2% arabinose for 4 h, after which the cells were <lb/>harvested and stored frozen. <lb/>Cells containing SeMet-modified His 6 -Lon-N245 were <lb/>suspended in 4 ml buffer [50 mM Tris-HCl pH 8.0, 0.1 M KCl, <lb/>10%(v/v) glycerol] per gram of cells and the suspension was <lb/>passed once through a French pressure cell at 138 MPa. After <lb/>clarifying the extract by centrifugation at 30 000g for 45 min, <lb/>the supernatant solution was passed over a Talon metal-<lb/>chelate affinity column and His 6 -Lon-N245 was eluted with a <lb/>gradient from 0.02 to 1.0 M imidazole in the same buffer. <lb/>Unbound His 6 -Lon-N245 was loaded back onto a fresh Talon <lb/>column after adding KCl to 0.5 M and the protein was eluted <lb/>as before in buffer containing 0.5 M KCl. Fractions containing <lb/>His 6 -Lon-N245 were combined and run over a Superdex 200 <lb/>column equilibrated with 50 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.5, 0.4 M KCl, <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <page>866</page>

            <note place="footnote">Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment <lb/>Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/></note>

            <body>Table 1 <lb/>Data-collection and refinement statistics. <lb/>Values in parentheses are for the last shell. <lb/>Data set 1 <lb/>Data set 2 <lb/>Data collection <lb/>Wavelength (A ˚) <lb/>0.9756 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Space group <lb/>P3 2 21 <lb/>P3 2 21 <lb/>Unit-cell parameters (A ˚) <lb/>a = b = 91.69, <lb/>c = 81.97 <lb/>a = b = 91.58, <lb/>c = 81.86 <lb/>Resolution (A ˚) <lb/>30-2.8 <lb/>30-2.6 <lb/>No. of reflections (unique/total) <lb/>10106 (81603) <lb/>12507 (107497) <lb/>Completeness (%) <lb/>99.9 (99.7) <lb/>99.6 (96.3) <lb/>I/(I) <lb/>35.6 (2.3) <lb/>33.5 (2.5) <lb/>R merge (%) <lb/>7.2 (73.3) <lb/>5.3 (53.3) <lb/>Refinement <lb/>No. of molecules in asymmetric unit <lb/>1 <lb/>No. of protein atoms <lb/>1897 <lb/>No. of solvent molecules <lb/>0 <lb/>Average B factor (A ˚2) <lb/>96.3 <lb/>R cryst (%) <lb/>23.5 <lb/>R free (3% of reflections) (%) <lb/>28.2 <lb/>R.m.s. deviations from ideality <lb/>Bond lengths (A ˚) <lb/>0.011 <lb/>Bond angles ( ) <lb/>1.31 <lb/>Table 2 <lb/>Twinning analysis of the data sets. <lb/>Twinning analysis <lb/>Data set 1 Data set 2 <lb/>Theoretical <lb/>nontwinned <lb/>Theoretical <lb/>twinned <lb/>hI 2 i/hIi 2 acentric <lb/>2.087 <lb/>2.055 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>hI 2 i/hIi 2 centric (h0l) <lb/>3.310 <lb/>3.284 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>hE 2 À 1i acentric <lb/>0.747 <lb/>0.735 <lb/>0.736 <lb/>0.541 <lb/>hE 2 À 1i centric (h0l) 1.120 <lb/>1.066 <lb/>0.968 <lb/>0.736 <lb/>N(z), z &lt; 0.1 acentric 0.091 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>0.018 <lb/>N(z), z &lt; 0.1 centric <lb/>0.228 <lb/>0.253 <lb/>0.248 <lb/>0.095 <lb/>h|L|i <lb/>0.492 <lb/>0.493 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.375 <lb/>hL 2 i <lb/>0.325 <lb/>0.327 <lb/>0.333 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>h|H|i <lb/>0.466 <lb/>0.468 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>hH 2 i <lb/>0.302 <lb/>0.308 <lb/>0.333 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>10%(v/v) glycerol. The fractions of the <lb/>highest purity were combined, concentrated <lb/>using a Centricon-10 membrane and <lb/>dialyzed before setting up for crystallization. <lb/>Crystals of SeMet-His 6 -Lon-N245 were <lb/>obtained using the hanging-drop vapor-<lb/>diffusion method. The sample was con-<lb/>centrated to 10 mg ml À1 in 20 mM Tris-HCl <lb/>buffer pH 7.5 also containing 1 mM EDTA, <lb/>0.4 M NaCl and 10% glycerol. The well <lb/>solution contained 0.6 M magnesium <lb/>formate in 0.1 M bis-tris buffer pH 5.5. The <lb/>hanging drop was prepared by mixing 4 ml <lb/>sample with 4 ml well solution. Crystals <lb/>could be observed overnight and grew to a <lb/>length of more than 1 mm in about 10 d. <lb/>2.2. Data collection and processing <lb/>Two data sets were collected on the SER-<lb/>CAT beamline 22ID at APS, Argonne <lb/>National Laboratory from the trigonal <lb/>crystals of the SeMet derivative of Lon-<lb/>N245 at 100 K using a MAR 300 CCD <lb/>detector. The first set was collected at a <lb/>wavelength of 0.9756 A ˚, close to the Se <lb/>absorption edge, and included data <lb/>extending to a resolution of 2.8 A ˚. The <lb/>second, 2.6 A ˚data set was collected at a <lb/>wavelength of 1.000 A ˚. Both data sets were <lb/>processed with HKL-2000 (Otwinowski &amp; <lb/>Minor, 1997) and the resulting statistics of <lb/>data processing are shown in Table 1. <lb/>Owing to problems encountered subse-<lb/>quently in structure refinement (see below), <lb/>these data were analyzed in detail in order <lb/>to verify that the crystals were not subject to <lb/>twinning or other crystallographic artifacts. <lb/>Diffraction data from both crystals merged <lb/>well in point groups 321 and 3, but not in <lb/>point group 622. Regular absences among <lb/>the 00l reflections clearly demonstrated the <lb/>presence of a threefold screw axis. The <lb/>symmetry of these crystals was therefore consistent with either <lb/>the true or partially merohedrally twinned space groups P3 1 21 <lb/>or P3 2 21 or perfectly twinned P3 1 or P3 2 . Several tests for <lb/>twinning were performed and Table 2 shows the results <lb/>obtained from phenix.xtriage (Zwart et al., 2005). The results <lb/>for both data sets agree well with the statistics expected for <lb/>nontwinned crystals. Moreover, the clear difference between <lb/>the statistics obtained for acentric and potentially centric (h0l) <lb/>reflections for the 321 point group confirm the presence of <lb/>twofold axes and therefore exclude the possibility that these <lb/>crystals display perfectly twinned symmetry in space groups <lb/>P3 1 or P3 2 . It is known that the simultaneous occurrence of <lb/>merohedral twinning and translational pseudosymmetry may <lb/>neutralize the effect of either of these phenomena on the <lb/>intensity statistics. However, the highest native Patterson <lb/>peaks obtained from the data sets have heights of 6.8 and 6.0% <lb/>of the origin maximum, precluding the presence of such <lb/>effects. <lb/>2.3. Structure solution and refinement <lb/>The structure of Lon-N245 was solved by single-wavelength <lb/>anomalous diffraction of crystals of selenomethionine-<lb/>containing protein. Data from the 2.8 A ˚set 1 were used to <lb/>search for Se sites with the programs SHELXD/E (Sheldrick, <lb/>2008). 11 of the 12 expected Se sites (not counting the <lb/>N-terminal methionine, which was expected to be disordered) <lb/>were located and served as input into the program auto-<lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/>Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment</note> 
            
            <page>867 <lb/></page>

            <body>Figure 1 <lb/>The final 2F o À F c electron-density maps of Lon-N245. (a) Representative density in the <lb/>N-terminal subdomain. (b) Representative density in the C-terminal subdomain. The maps <lb/>were contoured at the 1.5 level and selected residues are labeled. <lb/>SHARP (Global Phasing Ltd, Cambridge) for refinement, <lb/>phase calculation and extension and density modification <lb/>using both data sets 1 and 2. The final phases had an FOM of <lb/>0.53 for the acentric reflections and 0.38 for the centric <lb/>reflections when space group P3 2 21 was selected. The scores <lb/>from density modification were 0.94 for space group P3 2 21 and <lb/>0.32 for P3 1 21, unambiguously proving the former to be <lb/>correct. The resulting electron-density map exhibited good <lb/>density for the C-terminal subdomain of Lon-N245 (residues <lb/>123-245), showing a very clear long helix (residues 189-245) as <lb/>well as four shorter helical segments. However, the electron <lb/>density for the N-terminal subdomain was quite poor. The <lb/>C-terminal subdomain was built both manually with the <lb/>program Coot (Emsley &amp; Cowtan, 2004) as well as auto-<lb/>matically with the program Buccaneer (Cowtan, 2006). Since <lb/>the N-terminal subdomain could not be traced based on the <lb/>experimental map alone, the previously solved structure of the <lb/>EcLon N-terminal subdomain (residues 1-119; Lon-N119; Li <lb/>et al., 2005) was used to assist in model building. Two different <lb/>approaches were attempted. First, the structure of Lon-N119 <lb/>was manually rotated and translated into the position where <lb/>the S atoms of Met25, Met44, Met51 and Met80 overlapped <lb/>with the Se sites located by SHELXD and SHARP. The <lb/>resulting model was inspected in Coot, showing good crystal <lb/>packing with no collisions between the symmetry-related <lb/>molecules. The second approach involved molecular-replace-<lb/>ment analysis with the program Phaser (McCoy, 2007) using <lb/>Lon-N119 as a search model. Such runs were not successful <lb/>against the original data with no partial model, but succeeded <lb/>when the coordinates of the C-terminal subdomain were used. <lb/>For the C-terminal subdomain itself a molecular-replacement <lb/>run resulted in a Z score of 27.1 and an LLG of 598, whereas <lb/>the Z score was lowered to 19.7 and the LLG increased to 790 <lb/>after the N-terminal subdomain was added. The solution from <lb/>the Phaser run compared well with the manually inserted <lb/>N-terminal subdomain resulting from the first approach <lb/>above, verifying the correctness of locating this part of the <lb/>structure. A post-mortem check of the anomalous difference <lb/>Fourier map confirmed the positions of all 12 Se atoms, but the <lb/>peak heights on this map differed considerably, which was in <lb/>general agreement with the varying refined B factors of the Se <lb/>atoms and the occupancies of the peaks in the SHELXD <lb/>substructure solution (Table 3). <lb/>The structure was rebuilt and refined with Coot and <lb/>REFMAC5 (Murshudov et al., 1997) using the higher resolu-<lb/>tion data set 2. Throughout the refinement the electron <lb/>density for the N-terminal subdomain remained poor and the <lb/>conventional approach for refinement that utilized rigid-body <lb/>and positional refinement, annealing and TLS could not lower <lb/>R free below 30%. Since at this stage we started to suspect that <lb/>the reasons for such behavior arose from the mobility of the <lb/>protein molecule, especially its N-terminal subdomain, we <lb/>used the normal-mode-based refinement algorithm for the <lb/>final refinement cycles, as implemented in the programs <lb/>ENM-CALC (Lu et al., 2006) and REFMAC-NM. Such an <lb/>approach involves rigid-body refinement, rebuilding with Coot <lb/>and subsequent normal-mode refinement. After the latter <lb/>refinement, positional refinement that included TLS, but with <lb/>no refinement of B factors, was conducted with REFMAC. <lb/>The procedures were repeated in several rounds of rebuilding <lb/>and refinement, significantly improving the statistics (Table 1). <lb/>The final model of Lon-N245 consists of residues 7-245; the <lb/>His tag and the first six residues at the N-terminus are disor-<lb/>dered. In view of the limited resolution of the diffraction data <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <page>868</page>

            <note place="footnote">Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment <lb/>Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/></note>

            <body>Table 3 <lb/>Peak heights (in map units) in the anomalous difference Fourier map <lb/>calculated with refined phases, refined B factors of the Se atoms and <lb/>relative occupancies of peaks in the SHELXD substructure solution. <lb/>SeMet residue <lb/>Peak height () <lb/>B factor (A ˚2) <lb/>Occupancy <lb/>25 <lb/>9.0 <lb/>92 <lb/>0.959 <lb/>44 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>95 <lb/>-<lb/>51 <lb/>6.7 <lb/>112 <lb/>0.559 <lb/>80 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>77 <lb/>0.500 <lb/>173 <lb/>12.3 <lb/>56 <lb/>0.893 <lb/>186 <lb/>10.3 <lb/>58 <lb/>0.907 <lb/>197 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>49 <lb/>0.842 <lb/>199 <lb/>12.8 <lb/>58 <lb/>0.743 <lb/>200 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>54 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>221 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>67 <lb/>0.501 <lb/>234 <lb/>7.7 † <lb/>88 <lb/>0.568 † <lb/>244 <lb/>9.2 <lb/>59 <lb/>0.965 <lb/> † This peak is shifted to the special position on the twofold axis between two symmetry-<lb/>equivalent Se234 atoms. <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>An anomalous difference map showing the experimentally determined <lb/>location of the Se atoms in the crystals of Lon-N245 superimposed on the <lb/>backbone trace of the protein, with SeMet residues shown as sticks. The <lb/>map was calculated with the phases calculated from the final model after <lb/>deletion of Se atoms and was contoured at the 3.0 level. <lb/>and the less-than-optimal quality of the electron-density maps <lb/>(Fig. 1) we did not attempt to model any solvent. The coor-<lb/>dinates and structure factors have been deposited in the <lb/>Protein Data Bank (PDB) with accession code 3ljc. <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>3.1. Analysis of the correctness of the structure <lb/>Since the electron-density maps were less than fully satis-<lb/>factory and some nonstandard procedures were utilized <lb/>during refinement, it was necessary to analyze the resulting <lb/>structure very carefully in order to verify its correctness. The <lb/>geometry of the refined model is satisfactory considering the <lb/>limited resolution of the diffraction data. The Ramachandran <lb/>plot for the final structure obtained with the program <lb/>PROCHECK (Laskowski et al., 1993) showed 84.4% of the <lb/>residues in the core region and 15.6% in the additionally <lb/>allowed region, with none in the generously allowed or <lb/>disallowed regions. The positions of the anomalous scatterers <lb/>determined from the SHELXD analysis are in good agree-<lb/>ment with the final model (Fig. 2, Table 3), further supporting <lb/>the general correctness of the structure as currently inter-<lb/>preted, although the values for the R factors are higher than <lb/>expected and the values of the B factors are also quite high. <lb/>3.2. Description of the molecule <lb/>Analysis of multiple sequence alignments suggested that <lb/>LonA N domains might consist of two or more independently <lb/>folded subdomains with a boundary at around residue 119 <lb/>(EcLon numbering). Indeed, crystals of Lon-N119 have been <lb/>obtained and its structure has been solved in two different <lb/>crystal forms, yielding 14 crystallographically independent <lb/>views of this fragment of the molecule (Li et al., 2005). With <lb/>the exception of some parts of the loops that exhibited limited <lb/>conformational variability, all of the independent structures <lb/>agreed well with each other. However, in Lon-N245 this <lb/>region was quite difficult to trace and the electron density for <lb/>parts of the molecule was still poor in the current structure <lb/>even at the conclusion of the refinement process. <lb/>The structure of the N-terminal subdomain of Lon-N245 <lb/>predominantly consists of -strands (Fig. 3). The first two, 1 <lb/>(9-16) and 2 (26-31), are followed by the sole prominent <lb/>helix present in this subdomain, 1 (34-45). Strand 3 (49-54) <lb/>leads to a very irregular wide loop, which is followed by the <lb/>helical turn 2 made by residues 65-67. The remainder of the <lb/>subdomain is made of a long strand 4 (71-82), the even <lb/>longer 5 (88-105) and the terminal strand 6 that starts at <lb/>residue 109 and ends at 123, forming a linker to the second, <lb/>helical subdomain. Strands 1, 3, 4 and part of strand 5 <lb/>form a mixed -sheet, while strands 2, the rest of strand 5 <lb/>and strand 4 form an antiparallel sheet that is almost exactly <lb/>perpendicular to the former. Finally, a third antiparallel sheet <lb/>is formed by strands 1, 6 and 5. <lb/>The C-terminal subdomain is all-helical (Fig. 3), with helix <lb/>3 (124-145) followed by helices 4 (149-159), 5 (162-172), <lb/>6 (181-185) and finally the very long helix 7 (189-245). The <lb/>length of the latter helix is $85 A ˚and helices 6 and 7 <lb/>belong to the predicted CC region of EcLon. These five <lb/>helices, up to and including residues 189-207 of 7, form a <lb/>compact bundle with up-down-up-down-up topology. Owing <lb/>to crystal packing, helix 7 makes extensive contacts with its <lb/>symmetry mate from another molecule. <lb/>3.3. Comparison with other structures <lb/>We have previously noted that the structure of Lon-N119 <lb/>exhibits significant similarity to the structure deposited in the <lb/>PDB with accession code 1zbo but not described in further <lb/>detail (F. Forouhar, W. Yong, K. Conover, T. B. Acton, G. T. <lb/>Montelione, L. Tong &amp; J. F. Hunt, unpublished work). These <lb/>coordinates represent a hypothetical protein from Bordetella <lb/>parapertussis, BPP1347, that is annotated as having unknown <lb/>function. This structure was solved at a resolution of 2.6 A ˚and <lb/>the asymmetric unit contains two identical molecules with 197 <lb/>visible residues each. Similarly to Lon-N245, a molecule of <lb/>BPP1347 consists of two subdomains that are connected by a <lb/>single extended linker. Superposition of Lon-N245 on mole-<lb/>cule A of BPP1347 with the program SSM (Krissinel &amp; <lb/>Henrick, 2004) resulted in an r.m.s. deviation of 2.35 A ˚for 154 <lb/>C pairs belonging to both subdomains. A similar super-<lb/>position with the program ALIGN (Cohen, 1997) resulted in <lb/>an r.m.s. deviation of 2.15 A ˚for 161 C pairs, whereas super-<lb/>position with DALI (Holm &amp; Sander, 1993) resulted in an <lb/>r.m.s. deviation of 3.3 A ˚for 175 pairs (Z score 17.2). Thus, not <lb/>only are the individual subdomains of Lon-N245 and BPP1347 <lb/>similar to each other but their mutual disposition is also <lb/>practically the same (Fig. 4), despite their very low sequence <lb/>homology (only 34 residues are identical in the aligned <lb/>segments). This result could not have happened by chance and <lb/>offers independent support for the correctness of the structure <lb/>of Lon-N245. <lb/>BPP1347 is a representative of a large diverse family of <lb/>proteins or domains of larger proteins, previously named LAN <lb/>(Iyer et al., 2004). The conserved-domains database on the <lb/>NCBI site (http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/) identified these <lb/>proteins as members of COG2802, a conserved domain related <lb/>to the N-terminal region of LonA. The regions of homology <lb/>within the COG correspond to regions of similarity between <lb/>EcLon-N207 and BBP1347. <lb/>The search for related structures with DALI did not identify <lb/>any other proteins with a similar overall fold, although the <lb/>helical part of the structure appeared to exhibit some simi-<lb/>larity to a fragment of phenylalanine-ammonia lyase 1 (PDB <lb/>code 1w27; Ritter &amp; Schulz, 2004). Although the Z score of 7.2 <lb/>is comparatively high, the alignment of 111 residues (of the <lb/>690 present in each molecule of phenylalanine-ammonia lyase <lb/>1) resulted in an r.m.s. deviation of 4.7 A ˚and a sequence <lb/>identity of 10%, indicating that the apparent similarity is not <lb/>significant. A number of structures of tyrosine aminomutase <lb/>could be aligned with Z scores of 5.4-5.7, again exhibiting no <lb/>significant similarity in the amino-acid sequence. <lb/>However, the overall architecture of Lon-N245 shows some <lb/>similarity to the architecture of the response regulator RssB <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/> Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment</note> 

            <page>869 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Studemann et al., 2003) from E. coli and <lb/>Pseudomonas aeruginosa. Structures of this <lb/>protein have been deposited in the PDB <lb/>with accession codes 3eq2 and 3f7a, <lb/>respectively, but have not otherwise been <lb/>described (I. Levchenko, R. A. Grant, R. T. <lb/>Sauer &amp; T. A. Baker, unpublished work). <lb/>RssB is a targeting factor for the ATP-<lb/>dependent protease ClpXP and, reminiscent <lb/>of Lon-N245, its structure contains a very <lb/>long -helix. However, in the case of RssB <lb/>the helix connects two widely separated <lb/>compact domains, neither of which resem-<lb/>bles the two compact subdomains of Lon-<lb/>N245. Considering that the latter molecule <lb/>contains only a fragment of a larger protease <lb/>and that the fragment studied here is <lb/>followed by the C-terminal part of the N-<lb/>terminal fragment, which is predicted to <lb/>form a small mostly helical globular subdo-<lb/>main that then joins the ATPase domain, the <lb/>topological similarity does not seem to be <lb/>completely far-fetched. Incidentally, similar <lb/>to the case described here, the refinement of <lb/>the structures of RssB also presented <lb/>significant crystallographic difficulties, with <lb/>much lower resolution of diffraction data <lb/>and much higher values of the final R <lb/>factors. This fact may indicate that the <lb/>presence of a long exposed helix might <lb/>make the protein more flexible and thus <lb/>make the crystals less able to diffract to high <lb/>resolution. <lb/>3.4. Function of the N-terminal domain of <lb/>LonA proteases <lb/>Direct evidence that the N domain of Lon <lb/>plays a role in substrate discrimination <lb/>comes from several directions. Deletion of <lb/>up to 250 residues from the N-terminus of <lb/>Lon from Mycobacterium smegmatis <lb/>(Roudiak &amp; Shrader, 1998), E. coli <lb/>(Melnikov et al., 2008) or Brevibacils <lb/>thermoruber (Chir et al., 2009) led to &gt;90% <lb/>loss of ATP-dependent protein-degrading <lb/>activity without affecting the peptidase or <lb/>ATPase activities to a significant degree. <lb/>These results suggest that the loss of the <lb/>N-terminus causes a defect in protein-<lb/>substrate interaction which might arise from <lb/>impaired oligomerization of the truncated <lb/>enzyme (Chir et al., 2009; Melnikov et al., <lb/>2008). In a separate study (FSR, G. G. <lb/>Leffers, S. Gottesman and MRM, unpub-<lb/>lished work) it has been found that deletion <lb/>of a portion of the N-terminus abrogates the <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <page>870</page> 

            <note place="footnote">Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment <lb/>Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/></note>

            <body>Figure 4 <lb/>Comparison of the backbone trace of Lon-N245 (blue) with the hypothetical B. parapertussis <lb/>protein BB1347 (yellow). <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>Stereoview of the crystal structure of Lon-N245. The elements of the secondary structure are <lb/>colored magenta for -strands, blue for -helices and brown for coils. <lb/>ability of EcLon to degrade RcsA and overexpression of N-<lb/>terminal fragments of various lengths in Lon + E. coli cells can <lb/>block the degradation of RcsA. These results also support the <lb/>model postulating that the N-terminus of EcLon plays a role in <lb/>recognizing RcsA. It has also been reported (Ebel et al., 1999) <lb/>that a point mutation Glu240Lys of EcLon led to a specific <lb/>defect in the ability to degrade RcsA in vivo but had no effect <lb/>on another physiological substrate, SulA, suggesting that this <lb/>region of the N-terminus might be involved in substrate <lb/>recognition or in a specific interaction needed to process a <lb/>subset of substrates. Partial proteolysis of Lon by trypsin, <lb/>chymotrypsin or glutamyl endopeptidase V8 resulted in clea-<lb/>vage near Glu240 in the 233-240 segment of the enzyme <lb/>(Melnikov et al., 2008; Patterson et al., 2004; Vasilyeva et al., <lb/>2002), indicating that this portion of the N-terminus is exposed <lb/>and perhaps somewhat flexible in the native structure. One <lb/>might suppose that the Glu240Lys mutation could disrupt the <lb/>long helix observed in the Lon-N245 crystal and/or prevent <lb/>formation of a predicted coiled coil to which this helix <lb/>contributes. <lb/>A potential protein target-LonA interaction region can be <lb/>identified by examining the nonrandom distribution of highly <lb/>conserved residues within the fragments of LonA proteases <lb/>which correspond to Lon-N245 (Fig. 5). A deep hydrophobic <lb/>cleft found on the edge of the N-terminal subdomain where it <lb/>joins the C-terminal subdomain is made up of highly con-<lb/>served residues. Highly conserved mostly hydrophobic resi-<lb/>dues continue from the cleft across the inside surface of the <lb/>junction between the pommel and the shaft joint and then <lb/>extend all along the shaft. Given the known affinity of Lon for <lb/>unfolded regions of proteins rich in aromatic residues (Gur &amp; <lb/>Sauer, 2008), this conserved surface covering the deep cleft <lb/>appears to be an ideal site at which such target regions in Lon <lb/>substrates could interact. <lb/>Whereas helices as long as the C-terminal helix of Lon-<lb/>N245 (residues 189-245) and almost completely super-<lb/>imposable with it are not uncommon among known protein <lb/>structures, they are usually found in coiled coils (for example, <lb/>in the GTPase-activating protein Git1; PDB code 2w6a; <lb/>Schlenker &amp; Rittinger, 2009). However, despite the very low <lb/>r.m.s.d. of only 0.8 A ˚for 56 residues superimposed in this <lb/>particular case, such a resemblance is most likely just to be a <lb/>result of the helix being quite regular. With the sequence <lb/>identity as low as 4%, there is no reason to believe that such <lb/>apparent structural similarity would be biologically significant. <lb/>A helix of a comparable length was also seen in the middle of <lb/>ClpB and Hsp104 subunits (Lee et al., 2003), where it forms a <lb/>part of a CC region that spans compact protein domains. The <lb/>CC region may act as a &apos;molecular crowbar&apos; (Glover &amp; <lb/>Lindquist, 1998) to disrupt local structural elements in protein <lb/>aggregates and thus help untangle and solubilize aggregated <lb/>proteins. It was recently postulated that coiled coils and their <lb/>surrounding regions in EcLon and bacterial ClpB exhibit a <lb/>topological similarity (Rotanova &amp; Melnikov, 2010). However, <lb/>this postulate needs to be further verified in structural terms. <lb/>ATP-dependent proteases interact with substrates in <lb/>several modes. Recognition and capture are thought to occur <lb/>in two primary steps: an initial binding event followed by a <lb/>second step that results in overall tighter binding that requires <lb/>ATP hydrolysis to disrupt. In some cases, either the first or the <lb/>second step (or both) can be specific (Gottesman &amp; Maurizi, <lb/>1992). SspB-mediated substrate binding to ClpXP involves the <lb/>adaptor-substrate complex interacting with the N domains of <lb/>ClpX followed by binding of the C-terminal two amino acids <lb/>to a site within the ATPase domain of ClpX (Bolon et al., <lb/>2004). A similar model holds for ClpS-mediated degradation <lb/>with ClpAP, except that the specific binding of the N-terminus <lb/>of the substrate to ClpS is followed by a nonspecific inter-<lb/>action of an unstructured region of the protein with a still-<lb/>unknown site in ClpA (Erbse et al., 2006; Wang et al., 2008). In <lb/>LonA, the substrate-recognition sites have not been directly <lb/>identified, but a similar model of bipartite interaction of <lb/>substrates has been proposed and one site is likely to be <lb/>located within the axial channel of the hexamer (Gur &amp; Sauer, <lb/>2009). The second site is likely to be within the N-terminal <lb/>fragment or at least to include a part of it. Such a bipartite <lb/>mode of interaction implies that the N-terminal fragment of <lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/>Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment</note>

            <page>871 <lb/></page>

            <body>Figure 5 <lb/>Conservation of the amino-acid sequence among the N domains of LonA <lb/>proteins. The two views of the cudgel-shaped Lon-N245 are related by <lb/>$180 rotation around the vertical axis. A surface rendering shows highly <lb/>conserved residues around a putative substrate-binding cleft in the <lb/>pommel and along the long helical shaft extending toward the <lb/>C-terminus. The color gradient shows a descending order of conservation: <lb/>from darkest blue (identical) through light blue, green, yellow and orange <lb/>to darkest red (nonconserved). Conservation scores were obtained with <lb/>the program ConSurf 2005 (Glaser et al., 2003; Landau et al., 2005) using a <lb/>multiple sequence alignment of 250 Lon sequences as input. The <lb/>alignment was generated with the ClustalW program at the EMBL-EBI <lb/>website (http://www.ebi.ac.uk/Tools/clustalw/). This figure was prepared <lb/>with PyMOL (DeLano, 2002). <lb/>LonA is dynamic and can help to position bound substrates so <lb/>that the degradation determinants or degrons have access to <lb/>the axial channel. The elongated structure of the nearly <lb/>complete N-terminal fragment presented here indicates that <lb/>even slight movement of its C-terminal subdomain about the <lb/>point of attachment to the A domain will result in dramatic <lb/>movement of the N-terminal subdomain (residues 1-119) and <lb/>the first helical region (residues 120-220). Such a wide range <lb/>of movement suggests that those portions undergo a sweeping <lb/>motion that could survey the area for unfolded proteins or <lb/>that could be used to exert disruptive forces on bound proteins <lb/>that it encounters. Higher resolution structures that include <lb/>both the N-terminal fragment and the A domain are needed to <lb/>put such a model of the modes of action on firmer footing. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank Gerald G. Leffers (NCI) for constructing the <lb/>pET30a clone of E. coli Lon with the synonymous mutation <lb/>eliminating the endogenous NdeI restriction enzyme site. We <lb/>acknowledge the use of beamline 22-ID of the Southeast <lb/>Regional Collaborative Access Team (SER-CAT), located at <lb/>the Advanced Photon Source, Argonne National Laboratory. <lb/>Use of the APS was supported by the US Department of <lb/>Energy, Office of Science, Office of Basic Energy Sciences <lb/>under Contract No. W-31-109-Eng-38. This work was <lb/>supported in part by a grant from the Russian Foundation for <lb/>Basic Research (Project No. 08-04-00977) to TVR, by the <lb/>Intramural Research Program of the NIH, National Cancer <lb/>Institute, Center for Cancer Research and by Federal funds <lb/>from the National Cancer Institute, National Institutes of <lb/>Health under Contract HHSN261200800001E. The content of <lb/>this publication does not necessarily reflect the views or <lb/>policies of the Department of Health and Human Services, nor <lb/>does the mention of trade names, commercial products or <lb/>organizations imply endorsement by the US Government. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Amerik, A. Y., Antonov, V. K., Ostroumova, N. I., Rotanova, T. V. &amp; <lb/>Chistyakova, L. G. (1990). Bioorgan. Khim. 16, 869-880. <lb/>Bolon, D. N., Wah, D. A., Hersch, G. L., Baker, T. A. &amp; Sauer, R. T. <lb/>(2004). Mol. Cell, 13, 443-449. <lb/>Botos, I., Melnikov, E. E., Cherry, S., Khalatova, A. G., Rasulova, <lb/>F. S., Tropea, J. E., Maurizi, M. R., Rotanova, T. V., Gustchina, A. &amp; <lb/>Wlodawer, A. (2004). J. Struct. Biol. 146, 113-122. <lb/>Botos, I., Melnikov, E. E., Cherry, S., Kozlov, S., Makhovskaya, O. V., <lb/>Tropea, J. E., Gustchina, A., Rotanova, T. V. &amp; Wlodawer, A. <lb/>(2005). J. Mol. Biol. 351, 144-157. <lb/>Botos, I., Melnikov, E. E., Cherry, S., Tropea, J. E., Khalatova, A. G., <lb/>Rasulova, F., Dauter, Z., Maurizi, M. R., Rotanova, T. V., <lb/>Wlodawer, A. &amp; Gustchina, A. (2004). J. Biol. Chem. 279, 8140-<lb/>8148. <lb/>Chir, J.-L., Liao, J.-H., Lin, Y.-C. &amp; Wu, S.-H. (2009). Biochem. <lb/>Biophys. Res. Commun. 382, 762-765. <lb/>Cohen, G. E. (1997). J. Appl. Cryst. 30, 1160-1161. <lb/>Cowtan, K. (2006). Acta Cryst. D62, 1002-1011. <lb/>DeLano, W. L. (2002). The PyMOL Molecular Viewer. San Carlos, <lb/>California, USA: DeLano Scientific. <lb/>Ebel, W., Skinner, M. M., Dierksen, K. P., Scott, J. M. &amp; Trempy, J. E. <lb/>(1999). J. Bacteriol. 181, 2236-2243. <lb/>Emsley, P. &amp; Cowtan, K. (2004). Acta Cryst. D60, 2126-2132. <lb/>Erbse, A., Schmidt, R., Bornemann, T., Schneider-Mergener, J., <lb/>Mogk, A., Zahn, R., Dougan, D. A. &amp; Bukau, B. (2006). Nature <lb/>(London), 439, 753-756. <lb/>Garcia-Nafria, J., Ondrovicova, G., Blagova, E., Levdikov, V. M., <lb/>Bauer, J. A., Suzuki, C. K., Kutejova, E., Wilkinson, A. J. &amp; Wilson, <lb/>K. S. (2010). Protein Sci. 19, 987-999. <lb/>Glaser, F., Pupko, T., Paz, I., Bell, R. E., Bechor-Shental, D., Martz, E. <lb/>&amp; Ben Tal, N. (2003). Bioinformatics, 19, 163-164. <lb/>Glover, J. R. &amp; Lindquist, S. (1998). Cell, 94, 73-82. <lb/>Goldberg, A. L., Moerschell, R. P., Chung, C. H. &amp; Maurizi, M. R. <lb/>(1994). Methods Enzymol. 244, 350-375. <lb/>Gottesman, S. &amp; Maurizi, M. R. (1992). Microbiol. Rev. 56, 592-<lb/>621. <lb/>Gottesman, S., Wickner, S., Jubete, Y., Singh, S. K., Kessel, M. &amp; <lb/>Maurizi, M. (1995). Cold Spring Harb. Symp. Quant. Biol. 60, <lb/>533-548. <lb/>Gottesman, S., Wickner, S. &amp; Maurizi, M. R. (1997). Genes Dev. 11, <lb/>815-823. <lb/>Gur, E. &amp; Sauer, R. T. (2008). Genes Dev. 22, 2267-2277. <lb/>Gur, E. &amp; Sauer, R. T. (2009). Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 106, 18503-<lb/>18508. <lb/>Holm, L. &amp; Sander, C. (1993). J. Mol. Biol. 233, 123-138. <lb/>Im, Y. J., Na, Y., Kang, G. B., Rho, S.-H., Kim, M.-K., Lee, J. H., <lb/>Chung, C. H. &amp; Eom, S. H. (2004). J. Biol. Chem. 279, 53451-<lb/>53457. <lb/>Iyer, L. M., Leipe, D. D., Koonin, E. V. &amp; Aravind, L. (2004). J. Struct. <lb/>Biol. 146, 11-31. <lb/>Krissinel, E. &amp; Henrick, K. (2004). Acta Cryst. D60, 2256-2268. <lb/>Landau, M., Mayrose, I., Rosenberg, Y., Glaser, F., Martz, E., Pupko, <lb/>T. &amp; Ben Tal, N. (2005). Nucleic Acids Res. 33, W299-W302. <lb/>Laskowski, R. A., MacArthur, M. W., Moss, D. S. &amp; Thornton, J. M. <lb/>(1993). J. Appl. Cryst. 26, 283-291. <lb/>Lee, A. Y.-L., Hsu, C.-H. &amp; Wu, S.-H. (2004). J. Biol. Chem. 279, <lb/>34903-34912. <lb/>Lee, S., Sowa, M. E., Watanabe, Y. H., Sigler, P. B., Chiu, W., Yoshida, <lb/>M. &amp; Tsai, F. T. (2003). Cell, 115, 229-240. <lb/>Li, M., Rasulova, F., Melnikov, E. E., Rotanova, T. V., Gustchina, A., <lb/>Maurizi, M. R. &amp; Wlodawer, A. (2005). Protein Sci. 14, 2895-2900. <lb/>Lu, M., Poon, B. &amp; Ma, J. (2006). J. Chem. Theory Comput. 2, 464-<lb/>471. <lb/>Maurizi, M. R., Trisler, P. &amp; Gottesman, S. (1985). J. Bacteriol. 164, <lb/>1124-1135. <lb/>McCoy, A. J. (2007). Acta Cryst. D63, 32-41. <lb/>Melnikov, E. E., Andrianova, A. G., Morozkin, A. D., Stepnov, A. A., <lb/>Makhovskaya, O. V., Botos, I., Gustchina, A., Wlodawer, A. &amp; <lb/>Rotanova, T. V. (2008). Acta Biochim. Pol. 55, 281-296. <lb/>Melnikov, E. E., Tsirulnikov, K. B. &amp; Rotanova, T. V. (2000). <lb/>Bioorgan. Khim. 26, 530-538. <lb/>Murshudov, G. N., Vagin, A. A. &amp; Dodson, E. J. (1997). Acta Cryst. <lb/>D53, 240-255. <lb/>Neuwald, A. F., Aravind, L., Spouge, J. L. &amp; Koonin, E. V. (1999). <lb/>Genome Res. 9, 27-43. <lb/>Otwinowski, Z. &amp; Minor, W. (1997). Methods Enzymol. 276, 307-326. <lb/>Park, S.-C., Jia, B., Yang, J.-K., Van, D. L., Shao, Y. G., Han, S. W., <lb/>Jeon, Y.-J., Chung, C. H. &amp; Cheong, G.-W. (2006). Mol. Cells, 21, <lb/>129-134. <lb/>Patterson, J., Vineyard, D., Thomas-Wohlever, J., Behshad, R., Burke, <lb/>M. &amp; Lee, I. (2004). Biochemistry, 43, 7432-7442. <lb/>Ritter, H. &amp; Schulz, G. E. (2004). Plant Cell, 16, 3426-3436. <lb/>Rotanova, T. V., Botos, I., Melnikov, E. E., Rasulova, F., Gustchina, <lb/>A., Maurizi, M. R. &amp; Wlodawer, A. (2006). Protein Sci. 15, 1815-<lb/>1828. <lb/>Rotanova, T. V. &amp; Melnikov, E. E. (2010). In the press. <lb/>Rotanova, T. V., Melnikov, E. E., Khalatova, A. G., Makhovskaya, <lb/>O. V., Botos, I., Wlodawer, A. &amp; Gustchina, A. (2004). Eur. J. <lb/>Biochem. 271, 4865-4871. <lb/>Rotanova, T. V., Melnikov, E. E. &amp; Tsirulnikov, K. B. (2003). Bioorg. <lb/>Khim. 29, 97-99. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

			<page>872</page>

            <note place="footnote">Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment <lb/> Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Roudiak, S. G. &amp; Shrader, T. E. (1998). Biochemistry, 37, 11255-<lb/>11263. <lb/>Schlenker, O. &amp; Rittinger, K. (2009). J. Mol. Biol. 386, 280-289. <lb/>Sheldrick, G. M. (2008). Acta Cryst. A64, 112-122. <lb/>Studemann, A., Noirclerc-Savoye, M., Klauck, E., Becker, G., <lb/>Schneider, D. &amp; Hengge, R. (2003). EMBO J. 22, 4111-4120. <lb/>Vasilyeva, O. V., Kolygo, K. B., Leonova, Y. F., Potapenko, N. A. &amp; <lb/>Ovchinnikova, T. V. (2002). FEBS Lett. 526, 66-70. <lb/>Wang, K. H., Oakes, E. S., Sauer, R. T. &amp; Baker, T. A. (2008). J. Biol. <lb/>Chem. 283, 24600-24607. <lb/>Zwart, P. H., Grosse-Kunstleve, R. W. &amp; Adams, P. D. (2005). CCP4 <lb/>Newsl. 44, contribution 10. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">research papers <lb/></note>

            <note place="footnote">Acta Cryst. (2010). D66, 865-873 <lb/>Li et al. Lon protease N-terminal fragment</note>

            <page>873 </page>

	</text>
</tei>
