<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_ddn286"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Putative direct and indirect Wnt targets identified <lb/>through consistent gene expression changes <lb/>in APC-mutant intestinal adenomas <lb/>from humans and mice <lb/> Stefania Segditsas 1,Ã,  {  , Oliver Sieber 1,  {  , Maesha Deheragoda 2 , Phil East 3 , Andrew Rowan 1 , <lb/>Rosemary Jeffery 4 , Emma Nye 5 , Susan Clark 6 , Bradley Spencer-Dene 5 , Gordon Stamp 5 , <lb/>Richard Poulsom 4 , Nirosha Suraweera 7 , Andrew Silver 7 , Mohammad Ilyas 8 and Ian Tomlinson 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Molecular and Population Genetics Laboratory, 2 Histopathology Laboratory, 3 Bioinformatics and Biostatistics, <lb/> 4 <lb/> In Situ Hybridisation Service and 5 Experimental Pathology Laboratory, London Research Institute, Cancer Research <lb/>UK, 44, Lincoln&apos;s Inn Fields, London WC2A 3PX, UK, 6 Polyposis Registry, St Mark&apos;s Hospital, Watford Road, Harrow <lb/>HA1 3UJ, UK, 7 Colon Cancer Genetics, Institute of Cell and Molecular Science, Bart&apos;s and the London Medical School, <lb/>Whitechapel, London, UK and 8 Department of Histopathology, University of Nottingham, Queen&apos;s Medical Centre, <lb/>Nottingham, UK <lb/> Received August 13, 2008; Revised and Accepted September 6, 2008 <lb/>

			In order to identify new genes with differential expression in early intestinal tumours, we performed mRNA <lb/>(messenger ribonucleic acid) expression profiling of 16 human and 63 mouse adenomas. All individuals <lb/>had germline APC mutations to ensure that tumorigenesis was driven by &apos;second hits&apos; at APC. Using strin-<lb/>gent filtering to identify changes consistent between humans and mice, we identified 60 genes up-regulated <lb/>and 151 down-regulated in tumours. For 22 selected genes—including known Wnt targets—expression differ-<lb/>ences were confirmed by qRT – PCR (quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction). Most, but <lb/>not all, differences were also present in colorectal carcinomas. In situ analysis showed a complex picture. <lb/>Expression of up-regulated genes in adenomas was usually uniform/diffuse (e.g. ITGA6) or prominent in <lb/>the tumour core (e.g. LGR5); in normal tissue, these genes were expressed at crypt bases or the transit ampli-<lb/>fying zone. Down-regulated genes were often undetectable in adenomas, but in normal tissue were expressed <lb/>in mesenchyme (e.g. GREM1/2) or differentiated cells towards crypt tops (e.g. SGK1). In silico analysis of <lb/>TCF4-binding motifs showed that some of our genes were probably direct Wnt targets. Previous studies, <lb/>mostly focused on human tumours, showed partial overlap with our &apos;expression signature&apos;, but 37 genes <lb/>were unique to our study, including TACSTD2, SEMA3F, HOXA9 and IER3 (up-regulated), and TAGLN, <lb/>GREM1, GREM2, MAB21L2 and RARRES2 (down-regulated). Combined analysis of our and published <lb/>human data identified additional genes differentially expressed in adenomas, including decreased BMPs <lb/>(bone morphogenetic proteins) and increased BUB1/BUB1B. Several of the newly identified, differentially <lb/>expressed genes represent potential diagnostic or therapeutic targets for intestinal tumours. <lb/></front> 
			
			<front> Ã <lb/> To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: þ44 2072692884; Fax: þ44 2072693093; Email: stefania.segditsas@cancer.org.uk <lb/> † The authors wish it to be known that, in their opinion, the first two authors should be regarded as joint First Authors. <lb/> # 2008 The Author(s) <lb/> This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by-nc/2.0/uk/) which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<front> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/> 3864–3875 <lb/> doi:10.1093/hmg/ddn286 <lb/>Advance Access published on September 9, 2008 <lb/></front>

			<body> INTRODUCTION <lb/> To the limit of its current resolution, genetic evidence suggests <lb/>that most early colorectal adenomas in humans, and intestinal <lb/>adenomas in the equivalent mouse models, have developed <lb/>solely as a result of bi-allelic inactivation of the APC gene. <lb/>Gene expression changes in these early tumours can therefore <lb/>be taken as candidate Wnt signalling targets, being driven <lb/>directly or indirectly by the increase in beta-catenin-mediated <lb/>signalling that loss of APC function causes. <lb/>The normal intestinal crypt is subject to a gradient of extrinsic <lb/>Wnt signalling, with a maximum at the crypt base where the stem <lb/>cells almost certainly reside, and a minimum at the top of the <lb/>crypt or villus where fully differentiated cells are shed into the <lb/>gut lumen. Three categories of putative Wnt target gene have <lb/>been suggested (1). The first type of gene is expressed primarily <lb/>in the proliferating or transit amplifying cells of the normal crypt, <lb/>and includes established Wnt targets such as MYC. The second <lb/>type of gene—e.g. MMP7 and the cryptdins—is a marker of <lb/>Paneth cell differentiation in the small bowel. The third type of <lb/>gene principally shows expression in the bases of normal intesti-<lb/>nal crypts, perhaps in the crypt stem cells. There are probably <lb/>several reasons for these differences in expression patterns, <lb/>including the actions of other signalling pathways such as the <lb/>Eph/Efn, Bmp and Delta/Notch systems. Although colorectal <lb/>tumours generally show over-expression of Wnt targets, it is <lb/>not clear whether their molecular phenotypes most closely <lb/>resemble normal cells with type 1, 2 or 3 gene expression. <lb/>Understanding the full transcriptional programme of Wnt sig-<lb/>nalling and its downstream effects is important. Proven transcrip-<lb/>tional Wnt targets include MYC, CCND1, CD44 and AXIN2. <lb/> Genes with reduced levels of expression may also be found in <lb/>regions of high physiological Wnt signalling or in colorectal <lb/>tumours. Many of these down-regulated transcripts are likely to <lb/>be genes involved in the functioning of differentiated cells. <lb/>Examples include genes/proteins involved in the absorption of <lb/>nutrients (e.g. lipoprotein lipases and alkaline phosphatases) or <lb/>in instructing cell differentiation (e.g. HATH1 that is involved <lb/>in cell fate direction towards the secretory lineage). <lb/>There has been a handful of previous studies that aimed to <lb/>identify the transcriptional programme driven by Wnt signal-<lb/>ling. Most of these studies have been based on messenger ribo-<lb/>nucleic acid (mRNA) expression microarray analysis. The <lb/>methods and systems used have been very variable, and <lb/>have included inactivation of Wnt in colorectal cancer <lb/>(CRC) cell lines, activation of Wnt in cell lines from normal <lb/>intestinal epithelium and study of colorectal tumours (benign <lb/>and malignant) from humans. Most studies have been <lb/>focused on human tumours. Perhaps unsurprisingly, there <lb/>has been considerable variation between studies in their detec-<lb/>tion of known Wnt targets and in their identification of new <lb/>targets. Thus, despite some notable successes, it has some-<lb/>times proved difficult to distinguish signal from noise. Reichl-<lb/>ing et al. (2) undertook transcriptional profiling of 14 Apc Min <lb/> mouse adenomas and found 114 differentially expressed <lb/>genes, excluding known Wnt targets. When analysis of <lb/>CRCs was added, differential expression of genes such as <lb/> Igfbp5, Lcn2, Ly6d, N4wbp4 (PMEPA1), S100c and Sox4 <lb/> was found. Van der Flier et al. (1) expressed dominant-<lb/>negative TCF4 or TCF1 in CRC cell lines DLD1 and <lb/>LS174T. Changes were confirmed in 32 human adenomas <lb/>and 25 CRCs. Consistently down-regulated genes (putative <lb/>positive Wnt targets) included AXIN2, MYC, ASCL2, LGR5/ <lb/>GPR49, HIG2, BMP4 and SOX4. Kaiser et al. (3) compared <lb/>gene expression profiles in embryonic colon and colorectal <lb/>tumours and found significant resemblances between them. <lb/>Sabates-Bellver et al. (4) undertook transcriptome profiling <lb/>of human colorectal adenomas from 32 patients. After micro-<lb/>enrichment for epithelium, 319 possible positive and negative <lb/>Wnt targets were identified by expression profiling. Of these, <lb/>144 genes displayed significantly altered expression on verifi-<lb/>cation. The KIAA1199 gene was particularly highly expressed <lb/>(60-fold increased). Gaspar et al. (5) studied 42 polyps from <lb/>13 patients (eight APC- and five MYH-mutant) with three <lb/>normal samples for comparison. Duodenal adenomas from <lb/>three Apc 1638N  mice and two wild-type mice were also ana-<lb/>lysed. Approximately 10% of 18 000 genes were differentially <lb/>expressed in humans and, after analysis of the mouse samples, <lb/>a 166-gene signature (100 up, 66 down) was derived, yet this <lb/>included only a few known Wnt targets. Immunohistochemis-<lb/>try was used to validate CD44, ANXA1, CCNA2 and <lb/>MARCKSL1. <lb/>We aimed to identify mRNAs that were consistently differ-<lb/>entially expressed between early adenomas and morphologi-<lb/>cally normal tissue from both humans and mice. We <lb/>therefore collected a much larger sample of mouse tumours <lb/>for analysis than previous studies had done. In order to <lb/>utilize a relatively homogeneous system and to ensure that <lb/>tumorigenesis was driven by &apos;second hits&apos; at APC, we <lb/>focused on individuals with known germline APC mutations, <lb/>either humans with familial adenomatous polyposis (FAP) or <lb/>mice with the Apc Min(R850X)  mutation. Adenomas were early <lb/>lesions (,5 mm diameter, tubular morphology, mildly dys-<lb/>plastic), and a small number of sporadic human CRCs was <lb/>analysed alongside them. Using stringent criteria, we ident-<lb/>ified a number of genes that are differentially expressed in <lb/>early colorectal tumours and represent strong candidates as <lb/>direct or indirect targets of Wnt signalling. We discuss these <lb/>data in the light of previous studies. <lb/> RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/> Expression profiling and verification <lb/> Using a stringent significance threshold of P , 0.005 after <lb/>Benjamini– Hochberg false discovery rate (FDR) correction, <lb/>we identified 220 genes that were significantly up-regulated <lb/>and 548 that were significantly down-regulated by at least <lb/>2-fold when comparing normal tissue and large-bowel adeno-<lb/>mas from human FAP patients. If multiple probes from one <lb/>gene were present on the array, we scored that gene as differ-<lb/>entially expressed if any probe fulfilled our criteria, although <lb/>in no case were two different probes from the same gene sig-<lb/>nificantly altered in opposite directions. The 768 genes are <lb/>shown in Supplementary Material, Table S1. The list included <lb/>several genes that have been described as direct or indirect <lb/>targets of Wnt signalling, including CCND1, CD44, CLU, <lb/>EPH receptors, LGR5/GPR49, MMP7, MYC and SFRP1. <lb/> Absent from the list, because they were not significantly <lb/>differentially expressed, were known Wnt targets such as <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3865 <lb/></page>

			AXIN, conductin (AXIN2) and c-Jun. The most strongly <lb/>up-regulated gene was CDH3 (P-cadherin), which was over-<lb/>expressed 35-fold. <lb/> We then compared the list of human genes with genes that <lb/>passed the same thresholds in three series of large and small <lb/>bowel adenomas from Min mice on the C57BL/6J background <lb/>(see Materials and Methods). In line with our stringent selec-<lb/>tion process, initial filtering required .95% of all mouse <lb/>probes from all three series of polyps to show changes in <lb/>the same direction as the human changes. Evidently, this strat-<lb/>egy will have excluded some genuine direct or indirect Wnt <lb/>targets, especially those-specific to each species or to different <lb/>regions of the bowel, or those with sub-optimal probes on the <lb/>arrays. Other genes, such as CD44, showed 10% of discor-<lb/>dant probes, presumably as a result of isoform-specific <lb/>expression in the two species. TCF4 and CLU (clusterin) <lb/>showed an unusual pattern, with universal up-regulation in <lb/>mice, but down-regulation in all human tumours. <lb/>We then excluded all genes for which no mouse probe <lb/>showed significantly changed expression at P , 0.005. In <lb/>practice, this selection largely excluded genes with few <lb/>probes on the arrays and for which there was consequently <lb/>low confidence in the expression changes being consistent in <lb/>humans and mice. This reduced the list to a &apos;gene expression <lb/>signature&apos; of 60 up-regulated and 151 down-regulated genes <lb/>(Table 1). This gene set included the up-regulated targets <lb/> CCND1, EPHB2, EPHB3, LGR5, MMP7 and MYC and the <lb/>down-regulated SFRP1. The most up-regulated gene was <lb/> TACSTD2 (18-fold in humans, 82-fold in mouse) and the <lb/>most down-regulated were CCL19 (25-fold in humans) and <lb/> Cnn1 (33-fold in mouse). The genes performed no evident <lb/>common function (apart from being in the Wnt pathway in <lb/>some cases), although some related genes were present in <lb/>the list, an example being GREM1 and GREM2. <lb/> In order to validate the expression array data, we then selected <lb/>for quantitative reverse transcription polymerase chain reaction <lb/>(qRT–PCR) analysis a mixture of 22 differentially expressed <lb/>genes showing up-or down-regulation (described later), includ-<lb/>ing some known Wnt targets and some potentially novel <lb/>targets. These genes were studied in additional sets of up to 19 <lb/>FAP large bowel adenomas, seven sporadic human CRCs, 14 <lb/>Min mouse small bowel adenomas, and 19 Min mouse large <lb/>bowel adenomas. Actual sample numbers studied for each gene <lb/>varied according to the quantity of mRNA extracted from each <lb/>lesion (see Materials and Methods). Pre hoc, our criteria were <lb/>to reject any gene for which any of the sample sets showed an <lb/>expression change in the opposite direction to that found by <lb/>microarray analysis and also to exclude any gene that did not <lb/>show a significant expression difference (at P , 0.05 to reflect <lb/>fewer tests) in any sample type. In practice, almost all genes <lb/>passed these thresholds. We successfully validated the array <lb/>data for the following up-regulated genes: MMP7, LGR5, <lb/>MYC, CCND1, ITGA6, PHLDA1, CXCL3, IER3, TGIF, <lb/>SEMA3F, SOX4, TACSTD2 and HOXA9. However, ETS2 was <lb/>only over-expressed in adenomas, and actually significantly <lb/>under-expressed in two of the three CRCs investigated. For <lb/>down-regulated genes, we validated under-expression of SGK1, <lb/>GNA11, SFRP1, RARRES2, HPGD and MAB21L2. However, <lb/>whilst GREM1 and GREM2 were under-expressed in adenomas, <lb/>these two genes showed increased expression in CRCs. In <lb/>summary, all targets were successfully verified in adenomas, <lb/>but in a small number of cases, gene expression levels changed <lb/>on progression to carcinoma. <lb/> In situ analysis of gene expression <lb/> We then undertook in situ hybridization (ISH) of mRNAs using <lb/>normal intestinal epithelium and adenomas from FAP patients <lb/>and Min mice, in order to determine the topographical <lb/>expression patterns of a subset of the consistently changed <lb/>genes. Although it is difficult to make truly quantitative com-<lb/>parisons between gene expression levels using ISH, it is possible <lb/>to make semi-quantitative comparisons using the beta-actin <lb/>control probe, to assess the gradient of expression of any gene <lb/>along the crypt axis, and to assess the cell types in which <lb/>genes are principally expressed. In some cases, expression <lb/>levels were low and reliable ISH data could not be obtained. <lb/>However, clear results were obtained in the following cases. <lb/>We first analysed some established Wnt targets. MYC and <lb/> EPHB2 were strongly expressed in the transit amplifying <lb/>zone of normal crypts (type 1 genes), and throughout the epi-<lb/>thelium of adenomas. MMP7 was strongly expressed only at <lb/>the bases of normal crypts, but strongly or moderately diffu-<lb/>sely in adenoma epithelium; expression appeared to be par-<lb/>ticularly strong in Paneth cells, but was not restricted to this <lb/>lineage and MMP7 could therefore be classed as of mixed <lb/>type 2/3. CD44 was moderately/strongly expressed at the <lb/>crypt bases (and in villus cores of normal small bowel epi-<lb/>thelium), and strongly in adenomas (type 3). CCND1 <lb/>(assessed using immunohistochemistry) was principally <lb/>expressed in the transit amplifying zone of normal crypts <lb/>and widely in adenomas, with the strongest expression near <lb/>the crypt tops. <lb/> LGR5 encodes an orphan G-protein coupled receptor and <lb/>was originally identified as a Wnt target in CRC cell lines. <lb/>It was shown to be up-regulated in hepatocellular carcinomas <lb/>carrying beta-catenin mutations (6) and in colorectal and <lb/>ovarian tumours (7). It has been reported as being expressed-<lb/>specifically in crypt base columnar (CBC) cells, between the <lb/>Paneth cells, by Barker et al. (8). On this basis, coupled <lb/>with lineage tracing, LGR5 has been proposed as a crypt <lb/>stem (or progenitor) cell marker. We too found LGR5 to be <lb/>a type 3 gene, with expression restricted to the crypt bases, <lb/>especially the CBC cells, in both large and small bowel. In <lb/>adenomas, LGR5 was generally present in patches of variable <lb/>size that comprised about two-thirds of the total area of the <lb/>lesion (Fig. 1A), more extensive than reported by Barker <lb/> et al. (8). In general, these areas were close to the adenoma <lb/>core, consistent with retention of some normal crypt hierarchy, <lb/>some differentiation towards the surface of early adenomas, <lb/>and a &apos;bottom-up&apos; model of adenoma pathogenesis. <lb/> SGK1 encodes a kinase involved in the control of ion trans-<lb/>port. It was expressed at the tops of normal crypts (Fig. 1B) <lb/>and on villi, but was absent from all adenomas and carci-<lb/>nomas. Naishiro et al. (9) had found decreased expression of <lb/> SGK1 mRNA in a rat intestinal epithelial cell line that <lb/>expressed a stable form of beta-catenin. Immunohistochemis-<lb/>try by Naishiro et al. (9) did not confirm the mRNA expression <lb/>data, but in our hands, SGK1 antibodies have proved unsuita-<lb/>ble for use in fixed material. Interestingly, SGK1 expression <lb/>

			<page> 3866 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			Table 1. Early intestinal adenoma &apos;expression signature&apos; <lb/>Direction Human <lb/>Mouse <lb/>Gene symbol <lb/>Gaspar et al. Van der <lb/>Flier et al. <lb/> adenomas <lb/>Sabates-Bellver et al. Hatzis et al. Our <lb/>Wnt <lb/>Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value <lb/> Up <lb/>17.65 <lb/>0.0001 82.22 <lb/>0.0010 TACSTD2  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>10.91 <lb/>0.0000 11.05 <lb/>0.0000 DUSP4 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>8.62 <lb/>0.0000 36.12 <lb/>0.0010 MMP7  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>7.60 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>0.0010 SERPINB5 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>7.40 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.95 <lb/>0.0010 GDF15 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>7.37 <lb/>0.0007 49.64 <lb/>0.0010 CXCL3  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>5.92 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>4.56 <lb/>0.0010 GPR49/LGR5  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>5.89 <lb/>0.0000 28.15 <lb/>0.0010 CXCL1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>5.84 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>1.16 <lb/>0.0010 FABP6 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>4.99 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.0010 SLC12A2 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>4.33 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.29 <lb/>0.0010 ITGA6  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>3.99 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>3.03 <lb/>0.0010 EPHB3 <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>3.91 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>7.72 <lb/>0.0001 FLJ20315 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>3.88 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.0010 HYAL1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>3.47 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>0.0010 EPHB2 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>3.10 <lb/>0.0034 <lb/>2.22 <lb/>0.0005 DDX31 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.99 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>4.47 <lb/>0.0010 SEMA3F  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.95 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>0.0010 HOXA9  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.90 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>8.43 <lb/>0.0010 PHLDA1  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.82 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>7.91 <lb/>0.0010 SOX4  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.79 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>2.28 <lb/>0.0010 ETS2  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.74 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>9.95 <lb/>0.0005 C9orf26 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.73 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.0010 CCT2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.72 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>1.42 <lb/>0.0041 FLJ10458 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>2.39 <lb/>0.0010 S100A11 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>0.0001 GTF2IRD1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.53 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>4.64 <lb/>0.0024 TRIM29 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.48 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>0.0010 APG-1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.46 <lb/>0.0027 <lb/>2.95 <lb/>0.0010 MYC  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>2.45 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>0.0010 CGI-07 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.41 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>2.95 <lb/>0.0010 TGIF  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>2.41 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0012 SH3BP4 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>2.37 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.59 <lb/>0.0010 ABCE1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.37 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>1.98 <lb/>0.0010 SLC39A8 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>2.34 <lb/>0.0040 <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0010 ZNF22 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.33 <lb/>0.0018 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>0.0001 FAIM <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.31 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>0.0010 RGNEF <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.29 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>3.05 <lb/>0.0010 CCND1  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Up <lb/>2.25 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>9.25 <lb/>0.0010 IER3  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.22 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0002 SOX9 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.16 <lb/>0.0019 <lb/>2.21 <lb/>0.0010 MEP50 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.16 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>1.51 <lb/>0.0010 CDC2 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0132 TOPK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>3.00 <lb/>0.0260 RHOBTB3 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.12 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>3.37 <lb/>0.0000 PLEK2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.11 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.43 <lb/>0.0010 BTG3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.11 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>1.82 <lb/>0.0010 SLC39A6 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.10 <lb/>0.0032 <lb/>1.40 <lb/>0.0010 HSPD1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.10 <lb/>0.0017 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>0.0010 TRIP6 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.09 <lb/>0.0022 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>0.0010 DTYMK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.07 <lb/>0.0048 <lb/>1.37 <lb/>0.0010 NPM1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.07 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>0.0010 GCSH <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.06 <lb/>0.0034 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>0.0010 IPO7 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.04 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>0.0010 RRS1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.04 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>1.50 <lb/>0.0010 CKAP2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>0.0010 RCN2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>2.44 <lb/>0.0001 AASDHPPT <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0032 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.0010 PMPCB <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.01 <lb/>0.0018 <lb/>4.13 <lb/>0.0010 TM4SF12 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Up <lb/>2.00 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>3.07 <lb/>0.0011 DUSP14 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>24.75 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>0.0010 CCL19 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>16.47 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.79 <lb/>0.0010 CCL21 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>12.82 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>0.0010 FY <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>11.47 <lb/>0.0004 33.20 <lb/>0.0010 CNN1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>10.25 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>3.49 <lb/>0.0010 CXCL12 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/> Continued <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3867 <lb/></page>

			Table 1. Continued <lb/> Direction Human <lb/>Mouse <lb/>Gene symbol <lb/>Gaspar et al. Van der <lb/>Flier et al. <lb/> adenomas <lb/>Sabates-Bellver et al. Hatzis et al. Our <lb/>Wnt <lb/>Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value <lb/> Down <lb/>9.31 <lb/>0.0000 17.72 <lb/>0.0010 TNA <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>8.97 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.98 <lb/>0.0010 CXCL13 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>8.92 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>2.81 <lb/>0.0010 GCG <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>8.59 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>0.0010 MAP4K1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>7.92 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.0010 RTN1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>7.81 <lb/>0.0014 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.0010 CCL22 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>7.67 <lb/>0.0001 10.94 <lb/>0.0010 TAGLN  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>7.66 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>8.91 <lb/>0.0010 ADH1B <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>7.06 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>0.0008 PPP1R16B <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>6.96 <lb/>0.0000 12.96 <lb/>0.0010 TNXB <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>6.69 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>7.60 <lb/>0.0010 GREM2  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Too low <lb/>Down <lb/>6.65 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.18 <lb/>0.0010 RASGRP2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.90 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>6.70 <lb/>0.0010 MYLK <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.85 <lb/>0.0042 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>0.0003 CRYBA2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.81 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>4.65 <lb/>0.0010 ABCG2 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.59 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>0.0010 CCR7 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.36 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>8.46 <lb/>0.0010 CA1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>5.28 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>3.35 <lb/>0.0010 HLA-DQA1 /// <lb/>HLA-DQA2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.14 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.52 <lb/>0.0010 ADAMDEC1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.11 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>0.0010 CD22 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>5.06 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.11 <lb/>0.0463 CA7 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.83 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.83 <lb/>0.0067 SCGN <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.82 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.92 <lb/>0.0010 RHOH <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.76 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>5.75 <lb/>0.0010 CHGA <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.74 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.14 <lb/>0.0010 SFRP1  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.72 <lb/>0.0034 <lb/>3.73 <lb/>0.0010 MAB21L2  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.71 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.67 <lb/>0.0010 INSM1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.69 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>0.0307 P2RX5 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.69 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>0.0010 LSP1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.69 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.51 <lb/>0.0010 RARRES2  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.64 <lb/>0.0019 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>0.0018 BRDG1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.62 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.27 <lb/>0.0218 KIAA0657 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.60 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>2.01 <lb/>0.0010 BCHE <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.35 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>0.0010 FOLR2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.31 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>5.56 <lb/>0.0019 PDE2A <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.29 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>0.0010 CD7 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.10 <lb/>0.0037 <lb/>1.45 <lb/>0.0010 ANPEP <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.07 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>0.0010 DSIPI <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.04 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>0.0010 TNFRSF17 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.01 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.0010 RAC2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>4.00 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.44 <lb/>0.0010 NR3C1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.99 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>0.0010 GREM1  Ã <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Too low <lb/>Down <lb/>3.96 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>0.0010 XLKD1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.96 <lb/>0.0012 <lb/>1.66 <lb/>0.0010 AIF1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.92 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>1.91 <lb/>0.0010 LTB <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.84 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>0.0010 CD79A <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.82 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.70 <lb/>0.0010 POU2AF1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>3.81 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>0.0007 DKFZP434C171 N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.81 <lb/>0.0000 33.73 <lb/>0.0010 CES1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.81 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.86 <lb/>0.0010 HSPB2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.80 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>0.0010 CD48 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.76 <lb/>0.0014 <lb/>1.46 <lb/>0.0010 PCSK2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.72 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.0010 KLF2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>3.68 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.28 <lb/>0.0003 OLFML3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.65 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>2.21 <lb/>0.0010 CD79B <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.49 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>5.22 <lb/>0.0010 PTPRR <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.47 <lb/>0.0009 <lb/>1.54 <lb/>0.0010 SELL <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.42 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.22 <lb/>0.0010 HLA-DRB1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.41 <lb/>0.0022 <lb/>5.30 <lb/>0.0010 CCL5 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.40 <lb/>0.0018 <lb/>1.71 <lb/>0.0010 LRMP <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.35 <lb/>0.0009 <lb/>1.55 <lb/>0.0005 TTID <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.31 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>2.45 <lb/>0.0010 KCTD12 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.29 <lb/>0.0001 12.81 <lb/>0.0015 ITIH5 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/> Continued <lb/>

			<page> 3868 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			Table 1. Continued <lb/> Direction Human <lb/>Mouse <lb/>Gene symbol <lb/>Gaspar et al. Van der <lb/>Flier et al. <lb/> adenomas <lb/>Sabates-Bellver et al. Hatzis et al. Our <lb/>Wnt <lb/>Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value <lb/> Down <lb/>3.28 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.0010 COL13A1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.22 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.70 <lb/>0.0010 GIMAP4 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.17 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>1.14 <lb/>0.0010 WASPIP <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.15 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>0.0005 MAP1B <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>3.14 <lb/>0.0004 11.87 <lb/>0.0001 TRPM6 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.13 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>0.0010 AKAP12 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.07 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>3.79 <lb/>0.0010 FXYD1 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.04 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>5.83 <lb/>0.0010 PCK1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.03 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>5.68 <lb/>0.0007 RODH <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>3.02 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>1.25 <lb/>0.0010 MS4A1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.99 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.62 <lb/>0.0010 CD74 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.98 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2.63 <lb/>0.0010 CEACAM1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.96 <lb/>0.0035 22.47 <lb/>0.0010 CA4 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.95 <lb/>0.0000 22.17 <lb/>0.0001 DPYD <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.94 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.41 <lb/>0.0019 SLAMF8 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.94 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.22 <lb/>0.0010 HLA-DRB3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.91 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>0.0010 GMFG <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.84 <lb/>0.0009 <lb/>2.64 <lb/>0.0010 TCF21 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.84 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>0.0010 L1CAM <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.80 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.78 <lb/>0.0010 EDN3 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.79 <lb/>0.0023 <lb/>8.91 <lb/>0.0010 ADH1C /// <lb/>ADH1A /// <lb/>ADH1B <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.79 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.87 <lb/>0.0010 ZBTB16 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.76 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>0.0010 PALM2-AKAP2 N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.76 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>2.52 <lb/>0.0010 EDG2 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.75 <lb/>0.0026 <lb/>6.75 <lb/>0.0005 LOC63928 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.75 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.16 <lb/>0.0010 ITGB2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.74 <lb/>0.0036 <lb/>4.29 <lb/>0.0000 OSR2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.73 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.04 <lb/>0.0010 SEP06 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.72 <lb/>0.0019 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>0.0105 BC008967 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.70 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>2.54 <lb/>0.0010 GNA11  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.69 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.82 <lb/>0.0010 IL6R <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.69 <lb/>0.0025 <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0010 PLTP <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.67 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>4.34 <lb/>0.0010 CCL8 <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.66 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0010 SLC4A4 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.61 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>0.0010 PTPRCAP <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.61 <lb/>0.0019 <lb/>1.20 <lb/>0.0010 NNMT <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.61 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.41 <lb/>0.0010 IL7R <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.60 <lb/>0.0017 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>0.0010 CD8A <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>0.0010 RASSF2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>1.33 <lb/>0.0010 CD19 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.59 <lb/>0.0006 <lb/>1.55 <lb/>0.0152 HOM-TES-103 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.58 <lb/>0.0025 10.77 <lb/>0.0010 HPGD  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.57 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>5.71 <lb/>0.0010 UPP1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.52 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>8.17 <lb/>0.0001 MGC4172 <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.51 <lb/>0.0007 <lb/>2.98 <lb/>0.0010 BTK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.49 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>0.0010 HLA-DQB2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.49 <lb/>0.0032 <lb/>1.64 <lb/>0.0010 LAT <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.46 <lb/>0.0050 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>0.0010 MFAP5 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.46 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>2.71 <lb/>0.0010 SGK1  Ã <lb/> Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.45 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.13 <lb/>0.0006 SAMSN1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.44 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.65 <lb/>0.0010 FCGRT <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.43 <lb/>0.0021 <lb/>1.66 <lb/>0.0010 PER1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.41 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>1.30 <lb/>0.0010 PPAP2B <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.41 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>2.03 <lb/>0.0010 RECK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.41 <lb/>0.0042 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>0.0010 C1QA <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.39 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>4.99 <lb/>0.0010 HLA-DMB <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.38 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>6.46 <lb/>0.0025 CLDN15 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.37 <lb/>0.0042 11.61 <lb/>0.0010 KCNMB1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.36 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>6.55 <lb/>0.0031 BENE <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.36 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>0.0010 AQP1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.34 <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>1.21 <lb/>0.0010 ITK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.30 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>0.0010 CD2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/> Continued <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3869 <lb/></page>

			has actually been reported as being increased in other cancer <lb/>types (10,11) and recently, Dehner et al. (12) found SGK1 to <lb/>be up-regulated in the CRC cell line HCT116 when Wnt sig-<lb/>nalling was increased by knock-down of APC. However, we <lb/>have found that SGK1 expression in colorectal carcinomas is <lb/>very low, consistent with its role in ion transport which <lb/>suggests that higher expression is expected at the top of the <lb/>crypt and on the villus. Intestinal stem cells, adenomas and <lb/>CRCs would not be expected to express SGK1, consistent <lb/>with our data. <lb/> GNA11 is a G-protein of essentially uncertain function in <lb/>the gut. It is probably involved in transmembrane signalling <lb/>and may act as an activator of phospholipase C. Down-<lb/>regulation of the gene has been demonstrated in breast <lb/>cancers (13). GNA11 showed moderate expression in normal <lb/>epithelium, without any clear gradient or obvious restriction <lb/>of expression. Expression was universally down-regulated in <lb/>adenomas (Fig. 1C). <lb/> ETS2 is a transcription factor that recognizes the core con-<lb/>sensus deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) sequence GGAA/T <lb/>upstream of target genes. ETS2 was expressed at the base <lb/>and in the lower third of the transit amplifying zone of <lb/>normal crypts. Adenomas investigated by ISH showed gener-<lb/>ally increased expression, with a subtle falling-off of levels <lb/>towards the tops of crypts (Fig. 1D). Interestingly, Sussan <lb/> et al. (14) showed that trisomy 21 repressed intestinal tumori-<lb/>genesis largely through ETS2 over-expression. In line with this <lb/>effect, ETS2 may play a role in promoting apoptosis (15), and <lb/>intestinal adenomas exhibit increased rates of apoptosis (our <lb/>unpublished data). ETS2 is over-expressed in several types <lb/>of cancer, although out of the three sporadic colorectal <lb/>carcinomas we investigated by qRT–PCR, only one showed <lb/>3.5-fold up-regulation of the gene, while the other two <lb/>showed decreased expression (1.6 and 9.0-fold respectively), <lb/>suggesting that its functional effects may be context-dependent. <lb/> GREM1 and GREM2 were expressed at relatively low levels <lb/>in the sub-epithelial myofibroblasts and muscularis mucosa of <lb/>the normal intestinal epithelium. Expression was not detect-<lb/>able in adenomas. These proteins are secreted bone morpho-<lb/>genetic protein (BMP) antagonists that are 55% identical to <lb/>each other within a 173 amino acid core. An SNP near <lb/> GREM1 is associated with increased risk of CRC in humans <lb/>(16). The pattern of Gremlin expression in normal tissue <lb/>(Fig. 1E) partially resembles that detected previously by <lb/>Kosinski et al. (17) who compared gene expression in the <lb/>tops and bottoms of crypts. It is also strongly suggestive of <lb/>a BMP gradient along the crypt, with levels highest at the <lb/>top and lowest near the stem cells at the bottom. However, <lb/>we and others (18,19) have found increased Gremlin <lb/>expression in cancers, apparently at odds with decreased <lb/>expression in our adenomas. It is possible that these obser-<lb/>vations reflect a decreased ratio of muscularis mucosa to epi-<lb/>thelium in benign lesions, but a tendency for malignancies to <lb/>acquire their own Gremlin expression—and perhaps a <lb/>mesenchyme-like phenotype—in order to maintain a stem <lb/>cell-like state independent of the surrounding tissues. <lb/> ITGA6 is a member of the integrin alpha subunit family <lb/>involved in cell adhesion and signalling. Up-regulation of <lb/>the gene has been identified in oesophageal adenocarcinomas <lb/>(20) and was found to be necessary for survival of a highly <lb/>tumorigenic sub-population of breast cancer cells, through <lb/>roles in adhesion and/or signalling (21). ITGA6 mRNA <lb/> Table 1. Continued <lb/> Direction Human <lb/>Mouse <lb/>Gene symbol <lb/>Gaspar et al. Van der <lb/>Flier et al. <lb/> adenomas <lb/>Sabates-Bellver et al. Hatzis et al. Our <lb/>Wnt <lb/>Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value Fold <lb/>change <lb/> P-value <lb/> Down <lb/>2.30 <lb/>0.0022 <lb/>2.36 <lb/>0.0010 CD3Z <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.29 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>1.58 <lb/>0.0008 BACH2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.21 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>3.42 <lb/>0.0010 NR5A2 <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.19 <lb/>0.0040 <lb/>1.15 <lb/>0.0010 CD160 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.19 <lb/>0.0028 <lb/>8.32 <lb/>0.0010 PCSK1N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.17 <lb/>0.0021 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0235 CHRNA3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.16 <lb/>0.0009 <lb/>1.68 <lb/>0.0010 HCK <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.14 <lb/>0.0042 <lb/>3.28 <lb/>0.0010 <lb/>– <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.13 <lb/>0.0003 <lb/>1.29 <lb/>0.0010 MXI1 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.10 <lb/>0.0020 <lb/>1.91 <lb/>0.0000 PDLIM2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.08 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>1.34 <lb/>0.0010 CSF1R <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.06 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>1.48 <lb/>0.0010 HOXD4 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.05 <lb/>0.0013 <lb/>1.88 <lb/>0.0010 CXCL9 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Y <lb/>Down <lb/>2.04 <lb/>0.0012 <lb/>9.81 <lb/>0.0005 FLJ21934 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.03 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>5.44 <lb/>0.0010 SLC26A2 <lb/>Y <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.03 <lb/>0.0006 17.87 <lb/>0.0004 CLIC5 <lb/>Y <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0047 <lb/>2.58 <lb/>0.0061 FLJ11000 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0012 12.55 <lb/>0.0010 CHGB <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.02 <lb/>0.0022 <lb/>1.60 <lb/>0.0010 EZH1 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.00 <lb/>0.0022 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>0.0010 GZMA <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Down <lb/>2.00 <lb/>0.0011 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>0.0010 KCNH2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/> The table shows genes with consistent expression across all of our human and mouse series. Genes investigated further are indicated by asterisk mark. <lb/>Data from the &apos;signatures&apos; of the three other similar studies are shown for each gene in our list (Y ¼ present in other signature, N ¼ not present). The <lb/>promoter TCF-binding data of Hatzis et al. are also shown similarly, and finally the results of our experiment to determine whether the genes are direct <lb/>Wnt targets. <lb/>

			<page> 3870 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			expression was essentially absent in normal intestine, but there <lb/>was strong up-regulation throughout adenomatous epithelium <lb/>(Fig. 1F). <lb/> RARRES2 showed an unusual change between normal tissue <lb/>and adenomas. In the normal crypt, expression was concen-<lb/>trated around the base (Fig. 1G). Although there was a net <lb/>decrease in RARRES2 expression in adenomas, it became <lb/>more widespread, involving the whole epithelium at a low <lb/>level (Fig. 1H). RARRES2 is a retinoic acid receptor, although <lb/>its function is poorly described. <lb/> Comparison and pooled analysis with other studies <lb/> We compared our data with those of three relatively large <lb/>studies that have been published (1,4,5), although one of <lb/>these studies (1) only reported genes that were up-regulated <lb/>when Wnt was activated. Of our 60 þ 151 &apos;gene signature&apos;, <lb/>19% of genes were present in the Gaspar data set (1859 <lb/>genes with FDR , 0.005), 18% in the van der Flier data set <lb/>(160 up-regulated genes with FDR , 0.05) and 14% in the <lb/>Sabates-Bellver data (genes with .4-fold expression differ-<lb/>ence and FDR , 0.01). By way of comparison, 16% of the <lb/>genes reported by van der Flier et al. were also present in <lb/>the list of Gaspar et al. The following up-regulated genes <lb/>were present in our list and at least two of the other lists: <lb/> GPR49/LGR5, EPHB3, PHLDA1, SOX4 and ETS2. A further <lb/>17 up-regulated genes, including MYC and CCND1, were <lb/>present in our list and in one other list. For our down-regulated <lb/>genes, 44 (including GNA11 and SGK1) were present in at <lb/>least one of the other two studies, and seven (MYLK, <lb/> SFRP1, IL6R, HPGD, MGC4172, NR5A2 and SLC26A2) <lb/> were listed in all three studies. Thirty-seven genes were <lb/>unique to our list, including the following that were confirmed <lb/>by qRT – PCR: TACSTD2, SEMA3F, HOXA9 and IER3 (all <lb/>up), and TAGLN, GREM1, GREM2, MAB21L2 and <lb/> RARRES2 (all down). <lb/> Figure 1. In situ hybridization analysis of selected genes showing differential expression in APC-mutant adenomas and normal tissue. Representative images <lb/>(human adenomas unless otherwise stated) of ISH (Â20 magnification) for Gpr49/Lgr5 (mouse adenoma shown, A), SGK1 (B), GNA11 (C), ETS2 (D), GREM2 <lb/> (normal tissue only, E), ITGA6 (F) and RARRES2 (normal tissue, G and adenoma, H). Left panels of each pair are Giemsa-stained sections. Right panels are <lb/>dark-field images highlighting autoradiographic silver. Solid lines on Giemsa-stained images delineate tumour tissue. White solid arrows on dark field images <lb/>illustrate gene expression in tumour tissue. Dashed arrows indicate gene expression in normal tissue. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3871 <lb/></page>

			Since our sequential filtering strategy favours-specificity at <lb/>potentially great cost in sensitivity, we also undertook a <lb/>pooled analysis of our human data and the publicly available <lb/>results of Sabates-Bellver et al. (4) who used an Affymetrix <lb/>platform which was compatible with our analysis. A combined <lb/>analysis of our data from human FAP adenomas with those of <lb/>Sabates-Bellver was performed, with the caveat that APC <lb/> mutation status was not characterized in the Sabates-Bellver <lb/>sample set. The 1676 genes with a .2-fold difference in <lb/>expression, using a FDR threshold of 0.001 and after correc-<lb/>tion for variation between experiments, are shown in Sup-<lb/>plementary Material, Table S3. The combined analysis <lb/>confirmed most of the putative Wnt targets reported in this <lb/>study and previously. In addition, the following targets were <lb/>of note and were supported in both studies. CDH3, highly <lb/>expressed in our human data but not universally so in mouse <lb/>tumours and not reported in all other studies, was strongly sup-<lb/>ported by the combined analysis. Similarly, KIAA1199 <lb/> reported as a possible Wnt target by Sabates-Bellver et al., <lb/> was also over-expressed in our study and supported by the <lb/>combined analysis. BMP expression, with the exception of <lb/> BMP4, was generally decreased, despite the decrease in <lb/>expression of the BMP antagonists GREM1 and GREM2. <lb/> This may favour a stem cell phenotype, but appears to be a <lb/>paradoxical result, and may be secondary to changes in the <lb/>Gremlins. Hypoxia pathway components, such as carbonic <lb/>anhydrases, were also generally decreased. Other previously <lb/>unreported, but potentially interesting targets included the <lb/>spindle assembly checkpoint genes BUB1 and BUB1B, <lb/> which were over-expressed; given that APC has a proposed <lb/>(though controversial) role in chromosomal instability <lb/>through chromosome mis-segregation, it is possible that <lb/>BUB1/BUB1B are over-expressed in response to mitotic <lb/>checkpoint activation (22). <lb/> Differential expression and TCF-binding <lb/> In order to test whether some of our differentially expressed <lb/>genes were direct Wnt targets, we searched using Fuzznuc <lb/>from Emboss for the presence of putative TCF4-binding <lb/>sites (WWCAAWG) in the 10 kb upstream of the translation <lb/>start site of each transcript in humans (data from https:// <lb/>www.ensembl.org/). We examined whether genes with signifi-<lb/>cant expression differences in human tumours tended to have <lb/>more upstream TCF4 sequences than genes without such <lb/>differences.-specifically, in a logistic regression analysis, we <lb/>set as the dependent variable whether a gene was significantly <lb/>differentially expressed and used as independent variables: (i) <lb/>distance from the translation start site in 500 bp bins, (ii) mean <lb/>number of TCF4-binding motifs in each bin over all genes, <lb/>and (iii) local GC content in that bin. The mean number of <lb/>TCF4 sequences was significantly higher (P ¼ 0.001) for <lb/>significantly differentially expressed genes (mean ¼ 0.68 per <lb/>gene) than other genes (mean ¼ 0.62), even after stratifying <lb/>for local GC content. There was overall no effect of distance <lb/>from translation start site on motif frequency, although it <lb/>was notable that the first 500 bp upstream, which was <lb/>GC-rich and hence least likely to have TCF4-binding motifs <lb/>that occurred by chance, showed the highest difference <lb/>between significantly and non-significantly differentially <lb/>expressed genes (means 0.46 and 0.39 binding sites per gene <lb/>respectively, P , 0.0001, Wilcoxon test). <lb/>We tested whether some-specific members of our Wnt <lb/>&apos;signature&apos; were likely to be direct targets. We used the <lb/>CRC cell line RKO in which Wnt signalling is not active <lb/>and, owing to reported issues of toxicity if beta-catenin is <lb/>over-expressed in these cells, we activated Wnt signalling <lb/>using LiCl, an inhibitor of GSK3-beta. New protein synthesis <lb/>was inhibited using cycloheximide. We found that GREM1 <lb/> and GREM2 were already expressed at very low levels prior <lb/>to Wnt activation, consistent with their origins from <lb/>non-epithelial cells. LGR5 showed 2.1-fold increased <lb/>expression, consistent with it being a direct positive Wnt <lb/>target. However, all of the other genes tested (CXCL3, <lb/> ETS2, GNA11, ITGA6, PHLDA1, SEMA3F, SGK1, <lb/>TACSTD2) showed less than the conventional threshold of <lb/>1.5-fold change in mRNA levels, suggesting that they are <lb/>not direct positive or negative Wnt targets. <lb/>We then determined whether our &apos;Wnt signature&apos; genes had <lb/>been detected as possible targets of TCF4/beta-catenin binding <lb/>using chromatin immunoprecipitation assays in the study of <lb/>Hatzis et al. (23). We examined the top 2148 genes reported <lb/>by Hatzis et al., containing a total of 6868 high-confidence <lb/>binding sites. Of the 21 most strongly over-expressed genes <lb/>in our human tumours (Table 1), 11 had high-confidence <lb/>TCF4 -binding sites (TACSTD2, DUSP4, GDF15, CXCL3, <lb/>SLC12A2, ITGA6, EPHB3, EPHB2, SEMA3F, PHLDA1 and <lb/> ETS2). In all, 16/60 over-expressed genes, but only 18/151 <lb/>under-expressed genes, were associated with binding sites <lb/>(P ¼ 0.0086, x  2 <lb/>1 <lb/> test). Whilst the possibility of direct negative <lb/>Wnt targets cannot be excluded, this result confirms that Wnt <lb/>activation generally leads to increased direct target expression. <lb/>It also suggests that some positive Wnt target genes—such as <lb/> TACSTD2 and SEMA3F, which were not over-expressed when <lb/>we activated Wnt in the absence of new protein synthesis— <lb/>may contain TCF4-binding sites that are not involved in <lb/>causing increased gene expression in vivo. <lb/> Concluding remarks <lb/> Using high-stringency filtering, we have identified a set of 60 <lb/>up-regulated and 151 down-regulated genes that show consist-<lb/>ent expression differences between intestinal adenomas and <lb/>normal tissue from humans and mice. This list includes <lb/>known Wnt targets. The remaining &apos;novel&apos; genes are potential <lb/>Wnt targets, mostly of the indirect type, but many are likely to <lb/>be indirectly influenced by Wnt or by the cellular composition <lb/>of adenomas compared with normal epithelium. All genes <lb/>tested that were differentially expressed by microarray analy-<lb/>sis were confirmed by qRT – PCR. However, ISH showed that <lb/>the actual localization of the differentially expressed mRNAs <lb/>was highly variable. In situ analysis is therefore very import-<lb/>ant when examining genes with differential expression in early <lb/>intestinal tumours. <lb/>It is notable that the several studies to identify putative Wnt <lb/>targets using mRNA expression analysis in colorectal tumours <lb/>have found only limited overlap. Inevitably, some &apos;targets&apos; are <lb/>false-positives, but the differences also reflect the use of <lb/>different samples and mechanisms of Wnt activation, and <lb/>different methods of analysis. For example, we deliberately <lb/>

			<page> 3872 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote"> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			excluded some differentially expressed genes for which <lb/>mRNA splicing appeared to be altered between normal and <lb/>tumour tissues, since comparison between the levels of these <lb/>genes is extremely difficult. Overall, our study seems compar-<lb/>able with the three other most similar studies in the field <lb/>(1,4,5) in that there was considerable, but incomplete, <lb/>overlap for a core set of 20– 30 genes that are generally <lb/>accepted as differentially expressed under Wnt-ON and <lb/>Wnt-OFF conditions. Many other real targets were probably <lb/>present in our list, the stringency of our filtering being <lb/>reflected in the fact that only 37 of our 215 differentially <lb/>expressed genes were not detected by any of the other three <lb/>studies. This assertion was confirmed by our pooled analysis <lb/>with the Sabates-Bellver data (4), in which ,25% of the <lb/>genes in our 60 þ 151 &apos;gene signature&apos; genes were rendered <lb/>absent from the combined data using a filter of FDR , 0.001. <lb/>In summary, the identification of genes with expression <lb/>changes in early colorectal adenomas helps to identify the <lb/>mechanisms of colorectal tumorigenesis and to provide poten-<lb/>tial targets for prevention and therapy. It is essential that a <lb/>multi-stage approach is taken to this work, both for validation <lb/>and so that different strands of evidence can be incorporated, <lb/>including expression profiling and the discovery of TCF4/ <lb/>beta-catenin-binding sites. In this study, we have reported <lb/>our own expression profiling data and some new early and <lb/>consistent changes in human and mouse intestinal adenomas. <lb/>We have also undertaken comparative and pooled analyses <lb/>that between them have enabled us to propose new direct or <lb/>indirect Wnt targets with some confidence. Several of the <lb/>newly identified, differentially expressed genes represent <lb/>potential diagnostic or therapeutic targets for intestinal <lb/>tumours. <lb/> MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/> Microarray expression analysis <lb/> Initially, three &apos;classical&apos; FAP patients carrying germline <lb/>mutations (Q163X, S1190X and delATnt2396) in the APC <lb/> gene were identified. Sixteen snap-frozen adenomas (all with <lb/>previously characterized somatic APC mutations) were col-<lb/>lected from these patients; all lesions were mildly dysplastic <lb/>adenomas of ,0.5 cm diameter derived from different sites <lb/>within the large bowel. Eight snap-frozen samples of normal <lb/>bowel were collected from the same three patients and two <lb/>additional FAP cases. mRNA was extracted from each <lb/>sample with the GenElute mammalian total RNA miniprep <lb/>kit (Sigma, RTN70) All subsequent steps in the microarray <lb/>expression analysis were carried out by the Cancer Research <lb/>UK GeneChip Microarray Service. Briefly, after quality <lb/>control, the RNAs were reverse-transcribed to double stranded <lb/>complementary DNA (cDNAs) and biotin-labelled comp-<lb/>lementary RNA (cRNA) was amplified by in vitro transcrip-<lb/>tion with T7 RNA polymerase. cRNAs were then hybridized <lb/>to HGU133A Affymetrix Chips. Full protocols are available <lb/>at http://bioinformatics.picr.man.ac.uk/mbcf/protocols.jsp <lb/>For Apc Min/þ  (Min) mice, three series of small-or large-<lb/>bowel adenomas and normal intestinal epithelium were <lb/>studied. All samples were removed at autopsy and snap-<lb/>frozen. For series 1, mRNA was extracted and cRNA prepared <lb/>from 24 small-bowel adenomas and 24 normal samples from <lb/>six mice as described earlier; samples from each mouse <lb/>were pooled, before hybridization to 12 Affymetrix <lb/>MOE430_2 arrays using the manufacturer&apos;s protocols. For <lb/>series 2, tissue was homogenized using the FastRNA Kit <lb/>(Q-Biogene) and total RNA prepared using the RNEasy kit <lb/>(Qiagen). RNAs from up to five tumours or normal epithelium <lb/>from eight individual mice were pooled before hybridization <lb/>to the Affymetrix MG_U74Av2 arrays using the manufac-<lb/>turer&apos;s protocols; this resulted in the following pools being <lb/>analysed – two tumours and two normal from the large <lb/>bowel, and four tumours and two normal from the small <lb/>bowel. For series 3, samples were prepared as for series 1; <lb/>RNAs from nine small bowel adenomas and from six <lb/>normal epithelial samples were each hybridized to Affymetrix <lb/>MOE430_2 arrays. <lb/> Quantitative reverse transcription polymerase <lb/>chain reaction <lb/> In order to provide further evidence of the changes identified <lb/>by expression microarrays, mRNA was extracted from snap-<lb/>frozen human FAP samples (on average, eight normal <lb/>samples, 10 adenoma samples and four colorectal carcinoma <lb/>samples were investigated for each gene) and Apc Min/þ <lb/> mouse samples (on average, 32 normal and 29 tumour <lb/>samples) with GenElute mammalian total RNA miniprep kit <lb/>(Sigma, RTN70) and converted to cDNA with First Strand <lb/>cDNA synthesis kit (Amersham biosciences) according to <lb/>the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. cDNAs were purified using the <lb/>QIAquick PCR purification kit (Qiagen, 28104) and 30 ng of <lb/>cDNA were used for each reaction. TaqMan Gene Expression <lb/>Assays (Applied Biosystems) were used for each gene of inter-<lb/>est. Details are available from the authors on request. Absolute <lb/>quantification qRT –PCR was performed on the ABI 7900HT <lb/>(Applied Biosystems) according to the manufacturer&apos;s instruc-<lb/>tions and data were analysed with the comparative Ct method <lb/>(with GAPDH serving as endogenous Control) as described in <lb/>Applied Biosystems&apos;s User Bulletin No. 2. <lb/>For analysis of target mRNA expression in RKO, cells were <lb/>seeded and left to grow to 80% confluence. The cells were <lb/>then treated with the protein synthesis inhibitor cycloheximide <lb/>(60 ug/ml, Sigma) for 2 h, before addition of 20 mM LiCl (test) <lb/>or KCl (Control). No-treatment and cycloheximide-only <lb/>samples were also analysed. The cells were incubated for <lb/>24 h and RNAs were then extracted from pelleted cells <lb/>using the GenElute total mammalian RNA kit (RTN-70, <lb/>Sigma). RNAs were reverse transcribed into cDNA using the <lb/>AffinityScript TM QPCR cDNA Synthesis Kit (Stratagene), <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. cDNAs were puri-<lb/>fied using the QIAquick PCR purification kit (QIAGEN) and <lb/>used (30 ng per reaction) to assess expression of the putative <lb/>Wnt target genes CXCL3, ETS2, GNA11, GREM1, GREM2, <lb/>ITGA6, LGR5, PHLDA1, RARRES2, SEMA3F, SGK1 and <lb/> TACSTD2 with TaqMan Gene Expression Assays (details <lb/>available on request), according to manufacturer&apos;s protocol. <lb/>Each sample was run in duplicate and the data obtained <lb/>were analysed using the comparative Ct method (as described <lb/>in Applied Biosystems User Bulletin No. 2), using GAPDH as <lb/>an endogenous Control and comparing LiCl-with KCl-treated <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3873 <lb/></page>

			cells. The fold change in mRNA expression levels was calcu-<lb/>lated as 2  2ddCt  . <lb/> In situ hybridization <lb/> Isotopic ISH was performed essentially as previously described <lb/>(24) on the following genes: MYC, EPHB2, MMP7, CD44, <lb/>GPR49/LGR5, SGK1, GNA11, ETS2, GREM2, ITGA6 and <lb/> RARRES2. Briefly, templates for riboprobe synthesis were gen-<lb/>erated by amplifying from cDNA PCR products of 500 bp, <lb/>spanning exon – exon boundaries, and cloning them into the <lb/>vector pGEM3Z. All templates were sequenced prior to ribop-<lb/>robe synthesis. Details of primers used and correspondence <lb/>between ISH probes and TaqMan Gene Expression Assays <lb/>are shown in Supplementary Material, Table S3. Riboprobes <lb/>were generated by in vitro transcription using the RNA poly-<lb/>merase Sp6 and hybridized to 4 mm sections, cut from eight <lb/>formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded specimens. A beta-actin <lb/>probe was generated and used as a hybridization control. <lb/> Data analysis <lb/> Raw gene expression data were imported into the GeneSpring <lb/>program and the Mas5 algorithm was used to average across <lb/>the different probes per gene present in each array. Data for <lb/>each chip were normalized by median-centering (i.e. to the <lb/>median of all values on a given array). Data were included <lb/>if a probeset was present in at least one sample probe set <lb/>per data series. Differential expression was defined as exceed-<lb/>ing a specified fold change in either direction with a specified <lb/>degree of confidence; in general, higher fold-changes and <lb/>lower P-values or FDRs were specified for the initial screens <lb/>than for the verification experiments. For meta-analysis of <lb/>our own data and those of others, signal intensity estimates <lb/>for the extra data sets were Mas5 generated and the data <lb/>median centred as for our own human data set. Since both <lb/>data sets were from Affymetrix arrays, probesets with identi-<lb/>cal IDs were identified and analysed. Tumour and experiment <lb/>effect variance was modelled using ANOVA. Differential <lb/>probe sets between the adenoma and normal cases were <lb/>identified using a 0.001 FDR correcting for any experiment <lb/>effect across the samples. The analysis was carried out using <lb/>the Limma and Affy packages from Bioconductor 2.2 within <lb/>R 2.7.0. <lb/> 
			
		</body>

		<back>
			
			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL <lb/> Supplementary Material is available at HMG Online. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/> We are grateful to colleagues who supplied tissue, to those <lb/>involved in animal husbandry and to several groups who <lb/>undertook vital aspects of the expression microarray analysis. <lb/></div> 
			
			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. <lb/></div> 
			
			<div type="annex">FUNDING <lb/> The study was funded by Cancer Research UK. Funding to pay <lb/>the Open Access publication charges for this article was pro-<lb/>vided by Cancer Research UK. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/> 1. Van der Flier, L.G., Sabates-Bellver, J., Oving, I., Haegebarth, A., De Palo, M., <lb/>Anti, M., Van Gijn, M.E., Suijkerbuijk, S., Van de Wetering, M., Marra, G. <lb/> et al. (2007) The intestinal Wnt/TCF signature. Gastroenterology, 132, <lb/> 628–632. <lb/>2. Reichling, T., Goss, K.H., Carson, D.J., Holdcraft, R.W., Ley-Ebert, C., <lb/>Witte, D., Aronow, B.J. and Groden, J. (2005) Transcriptional profiles of <lb/>intestinal tumors in Apc(Min) mice are unique from those of embryonic <lb/>intestine and identify novel gene targets dysregulated in human colorectal <lb/>tumors. Cancer Res., 65, 166–176. <lb/>3. Kaiser, S., Park, Y.K., Franklin, J.L., Halberg, R.B., Yu, M., Jessen, W.J., <lb/>Freudenberg, J., Chen, X., Haigis, K., Jegga, A.G. et al. (2007) <lb/>Transcriptional recapitulation and subversion of embryonic colon <lb/>development by mouse colon tumor models and human colon cancer. <lb/> Genome Biol., 8, R131. <lb/>4. Sabates-Bellver, J., Van der Flier, L.G., de Palo, M., Cattaneo, E., Maake, C., <lb/>Rehrauer, H., Laczko, E., Kurowski, M.A., Bujnicki, J.M., Menigatti, M. et al. <lb/> (2007) Transcriptome profile of human colorectal adenomas. Mol. Cancer <lb/>Res., 5, 1263–1275. <lb/>5. Gaspar, C., Cardoso, J., Franken, P., Molenaar, L., Morreau, H., Moslein, G., <lb/>Sampson, J., Boer, J.M., de Menezes, R.X. and Fodde, R. (2008) <lb/>Cross-species comparison of human and mouse intestinal polyps reveals <lb/>conserved mechanisms in adenomatous polyposis coli (APC)-driven <lb/>tumorigenesis. Am. J. Pathol., 172, 1363–1380. <lb/>6. Yamamoto, Y., Sakamoto, M., Fujii, G., Tsuiji, H., Kenetaka, K., Asaka, M. <lb/>and Hirohashi, S. (2003) Overexpression of orphan G-protein-coupled <lb/>receptor, Gpr49, in human hepatocellular carcinomas with beta-catenin <lb/>mutations. Hepatology, 37, 528–533. <lb/>7. McClanahan, T., Koseoglu, S., Smith, K., Grein, J., Gustafson, E., Black, S., <lb/>Kirschmeier, P. and Samatar, A.A. (2006) Identification of overexpression of <lb/>orphan G protein-coupled receptor GPR49 in human colon and ovarian <lb/>primary tumors. Cancer Biol. Ther., 5, 419–426. <lb/>8. Barker, N., van Es, J.H., Kuipers, J., Kujala, P., van den Born, M., <lb/>Cozijnsen, M., Haegebarth, A., Korving, J., Begthel, H., Peters, P.J. et al. <lb/> (2007) Identification of stem cells in small intestine and colon by marker <lb/>gene Lgr5. Nature, 449, 1003–1007. <lb/>9. Naishiro, Y., Yamada, T., Idogawa, M., Honda, K., Takada, M., Kondo, T., <lb/>Imai, K. and Hirohashi, S. (2005) Morphological and transcriptional <lb/>responses of untransformed intestinal epithelial cells to an oncogenic <lb/>beta-catenin protein. Oncogene, 24, 3141–3153. <lb/>10. Chung, E.J., Sung, Y.K., Farooq, M., Kim, Y., Im, S., Tak, W.Y., Hwang, Y.J., <lb/>Kim, Y.I., Han, H.S., Kim, J.C. et al. (2002) Gene expression profile analysis <lb/>in human hepatocellular carcinoma by cDNA microarray. Mol. Cells, 14, <lb/> 382–387. <lb/>11. Leong, M.L., Maiyar, A.C., Kim, B., O&apos;Keeffe, B.A. and Firestone, G.L. <lb/>(2003) Expression of the serum-and glucocorticoid-inducible protein <lb/>kinase, Sgk, is a cell survival response to multiple types of environmental <lb/>stress stimuli in mammary epithelial cells. J. Biol. Chem., 278, <lb/> 5871– 5882. <lb/>12. Dehner, M., Hadjihannas, M., Weiske, J., Huber, O. and Behrens, J. <lb/>(2008) Wnt signaling inhibits forkhead box O3a-induced transcription and <lb/>apoptosis through up-regulation of serum-and glucocorticoid-inducible <lb/>kinase 1. J. Biol. Chem., 283, 19201–19210. <lb/>13. Asada, K., Miyamoto, K., Fukutomi, T., Tsuda, H., Yagi, Y., Wakazono, K., <lb/>Oishi, S., Fukui, H., Sugimura, T. and Ushijima, T. (2003) Reduced <lb/>expression of GNA11 and silencing of MCT1 in human breast cancers. <lb/> Oncology, 64, 380–388. <lb/>14. Sussan, T.E., Yang, A., Li, F., Ostrowski, M.C. and Reeves, R.H. (2008) <lb/>Trisomy represses Apc(Min)-mediated tumours in mouse models of <lb/>Down&apos;s syndrome. Nature, 451, 73–75. <lb/>15. Wolvetang, E.J., Wilson, T.J., Sanij, E., Busciglio, J., Hatzistavrou, T., <lb/>Seth, A., Hertzog, P.J. and Kola, I. (2003) ETS2 overexpression in <lb/>transgenic models and in Down syndrome predisposes to apoptosis via the <lb/>p53 pathway. Hum. Mol. Genet., 12, 247–255. <lb/> 3874 <lb/> Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/> 16. Jaeger, E., Webb, E., Howarth, K., Carvajal-Carmona, L., Rowan, A., <lb/>Broderick, P., Walther, A., Spain, S., Pittman, A., Kemp, Z. et al. (2008) <lb/>Common genetic variants at the CRAC1 (HMPS) locus on chromosome <lb/>15q13.3 influence colorectal cancer risk. Nat. Genet., 40, 26–28. <lb/>17. Kosinski, C., Li, V.S., Chan, A.S., Zhang, J., Ho, C., Tsui, W.Y., Chan, T.L., <lb/>Mifflin, R.C., Powell, D.W., Yuen, S.T. et al. (2007) Gene expression patterns <lb/>of human colon tops and basal crypts and BMP antagonists as intestinal stem <lb/>cell niche factors. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 104, 15418–15423. <lb/>18. Sneddon, J.B., Zhen, H.H., Montgomery, K., van de Rijn, M., Tward, A.D., <lb/>West, R., Gladstone, H., Chang, H.Y., Morganroth, G.S., Oro, A.E. et al. <lb/> (2006) Bone morphogenetic protein antagonist gremlin 1 is widely expressed <lb/>by cancer-associated stromal cells and can promote tumor cell proliferation. <lb/> Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA, 103, 14842–14847. <lb/>19. Namkoong, H., Shin, S.M., Kim, H.K., Ha, S.A., Cho, G.W., Hur, S.Y., <lb/>Kim, T.E. and Kim, J.W. (2006) The bone morphogenetic protein <lb/>antagonist gremlin 1 is overexpressed in human cancers and interacts with <lb/>YWHAH protein. BMC Cancer, 6, 74. <lb/>20. Hourihan, R.N., O&apos;Sullivan, G.C. and Morgan, J.G. (2003) Transcriptional <lb/>gene expression profiles of oesophageal adenocarcinoma and normal <lb/>oesophageal tissues. Anticancer Res., 23, 161–165. <lb/>21. Cariati, M., Naderi, A., Brown, J.P., Smalley, M.J., Pinder, S.E., Caldas, C. <lb/>and Purushotham, A.D. (2008) Alpha-6 integrin is necessary for the <lb/>tumourigenicity of a stem cell-like subpopulation within the MCF7 breast <lb/>cancer cell line. Int. J. Cancer, 122, 298–304. <lb/>22. Fodde, R., Smits, R. and Clevers, H. (2001) APC, signal transduction <lb/>and genetic instability in colorectal cancer. Nat. Rev. Cancer, 1, 55–67. <lb/>23. Hatzis, P., van der Flier, L.G., van Driel, M.A., Guryev, V., Nielsen, F., <lb/>Denissov, S., Nijman, I.J., Koster, J., Santo, E.E., Welboren, W. et al. <lb/> (2008) Genome-wide pattern of TCF7L2/TCF4 chromatin occupancy in <lb/>colorectal cancer cells. Mol. Cell. Biol., 28, 2732– 2744. <lb/>24. Poulsom, R., Longcroft, J.M., Jeffery, R.E., Rogers, L.A. and Steel, J.H. <lb/>(1998) A robust method for isotopic riboprobe in situ hybridisation to localise <lb/>mRNAs in routine pathology specimens. Eur. J. Histochem., 42, 121–132. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2008, Vol. 17, No. 24 <lb/></note>

			<page> 3875 </page>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
