<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/>4290–4296 <lb/>doi:10.1093/hmg/ddr340 <lb/>Advance Access published on August 11, 2011 <lb/>Large common deletions associate with <lb/>mortality at old age <lb/>Maris Kuningas 1, * , Karol Estrada 2 , Yi-Hsiang Hsu 4,5 , Kannabiran Nandakumar 4 , <lb/>André G. Uitterlinden 1,2,6 , Kathryn L. Lunetta 7 , Cornelia M. van Duijn 1,6 , David Karasik 4 , <lb/>Albert Hofman 1,6 , Joanne Murabito 8,9 , Fernando Rivadeneira 2,6 , Douglas P. Kiel 4 <lb/>and Henning Tiemeier 1,3,6 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Epidemiology, <lb/>2 Department of Internal Medicine and <lb/>3 <lb/>Department Psychiatry, Erasmus Medical <lb/>Center, Rotterdam, CA 3000, The Netherlands <lb/>4 <lb/>Hebrew Senior Life Institute for Aging Research and Harvard Medical <lb/>School, Boston, MA 02131, USA, <lb/>5 <lb/>Molecular and Integrative Physiological Sciences Program, Harvard School of <lb/>Public Health, Boston, MA 02115, USA, <lb/>6 <lb/>Netherlands Genomics Initiative (NGI)-sponsored Netherlands Consortium <lb/>for Healthy Aging (NCHA), Leiden, RC 2300, The Netherlands, <lb/>7 <lb/>Department of Biostatistics, Boston University School <lb/>of Public Health, Boston, MA 02118, USA, <lb/>8 Sections of General Internal Medicine, Preventive Medicine, Cardiology <lb/>and Neurology, Department of Medicine, Boston University School of Medicine, Boston, MA 02118, USA and <lb/>9 <lb/>The <lb/>National Heart Lung and Blood Institute&apos;s Framingham Heart Study, Framingham, MA 01702-5827, USA <lb/>Received February 15, 2011; Revised July 1, 2011; Accepted August 1, 2011 <lb/>Copy-number variants (CNVs) are a source of genetic variation that increasingly are associated with human <lb/>disease. However, the role of CNVs in human lifespan is to date unknown. To identify CNVs that influence <lb/>mortality at old age, we analyzed genome-wide CNV data in 5178 participants of Rotterdam Study (RS1) <lb/>and positive findings were evaluated in 1714 participants of the second cohort of the Rotterdam Study <lb/>(RS2) and in 4550 participants of Framingham Heart Study (FHS). First, we assessed the total burden of <lb/>rare (frequency &lt;1%) and common (frequency &gt;1%) CNVs for association with mortality during follow-up. <lb/>These analyses were repeated by stratifying CNVs by type and size. Secondly, we assessed individual <lb/>common CNV regions (CNVR) for association with mortality. We observed that the burden of common but <lb/>not of rare CNVs influences mortality. A higher burden of large (≥500 kb) common deletions associated <lb/>with 4% higher mortality [hazard ratio (HR) per CNV 1.04, 95% confidence interval (CI) 1.02 – 1.07, P 5 <lb/>5.82 3 10 <lb/>25 ] in the 11 442 participants of RS1, RS2 and FHS. In the analysis of 312 individual common <lb/>CNVRs, we identified two regions (11p15.5; 14q21.3) that associated with higher mortality in these cohorts. <lb/>The 11p15.5 region (combined HR 1.59, 95% CI 1.31 – 1.93, P 5 2.87 3 10 <lb/>26 ) encompasses 41 genes, of <lb/>which some have previously been related to longevity, whereas the 14q21.3 region (combined HR 1.57, <lb/>95% CI 1.19 – 2.07, P 5 1.53 3 10 <lb/>23 ) does not encompass any genes. In conclusion, the burden of large <lb/>common deletions, as well as common CNVs in 11p15.5 and 14q21.3 region, associate with higher mortality. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>It has long been observed that human lifespan has a genetic <lb/>component (heritability 25– 30%) (1 – 3), but to date only <lb/>few genes have been identified to influence it. The recent <lb/>genome-wide association studies (GWASs) relating single <lb/>nucleotide polymorphisms (SNPs) to longevity have provided <lb/>only modest additional information (4,5). These studies were <lb/>well powered to detect the association of common SNPs <lb/>with longevity, suggesting that either rare variants or other <lb/>types of genetic variation might be at play. Recently, the <lb/>genome-wide study of copy number variations (CNVs) has <lb/>become feasible and thereby also the study of CNVs in <lb/>relation to human lifespan. <lb/> </body>

			<front>* <lb/>To whom correspondence should be addressed. Tel: +31 107043488; Fax: +31 107044657; Email: m.kuningas@erasmusmc.nl <lb/># The Author 2011. Published by Oxford University Press. All rights reserved. <lb/>For Permissions, please email: journals.permissions@oup.com <lb/></front>

			<body>CNVs are caused by chromosomal rearrangements that <lb/>result in the loss (deletion) or gain (duplication) of stretches <lb/>of DNA sequence, and they represent a significant source of <lb/>genetic variation in the human genome (6). The mechanisms <lb/>through which CNVs can lead to phenotypic effects include <lb/>among others gene interruption, gene fusion and changes in <lb/>gene expression. Differences in gene expression can result <lb/>from a dose effect for genes that are within a deletion or du-<lb/>plication, or from altered expression through disruption of <lb/>regulatory elements (7 – 9). Gene interruption, on the other <lb/>hand, can lead to gene inactivation, whereas gene fusion <lb/>caused by genomic rearrangements between different genes <lb/>or their regulatory sequences can generate a gene with a <lb/>new and unexpected function (7 – 9). It has been noticed that <lb/>CNVs can be detrimental, beneficial or have no phenotypic <lb/>consequences at all (10). <lb/>In humans, CNVs have been shown to cause sporadic and <lb/>Mendelian diseases (10), but recent evidence implicates <lb/>CNVs also in a variety of complex traits (11– 15). In these <lb/>studies, individual CNVs and the total burden of rare CNVs <lb/>have been analyzed. Analyzing the burden of rare CNVs (fre-<lb/>quency ,1%) enables to estimate the combined effect of rare <lb/>variants. Through this approach, the burden of rare CNVs has <lb/>been identified as a possible cause of schizophrenia (14), <lb/>autism (11), bipolar disorder (16), amyotrophic lateral <lb/>sclerosis (17,18) and obesity (19). Likewise, lifespan could <lb/>be affected by the combined effect of rare CNVs, but the <lb/>same could hold true for the combined effect of common <lb/>CNVs. Common CNVs are individually likely to have small <lb/>or moderate phenotypic effects, but in combination they <lb/>might result in considerable phenotypic effects. Such effects <lb/>can reliably be assessed with moderate sample sizes. To <lb/>date, however, common CNVs have typically been analyzed <lb/>separately for their association with various traits. It has <lb/>been found that individual common CNVs (frequency .5%) <lb/>associate with Crohn&apos;s disease, rheumatoid arthritis, type 1 <lb/>diabetes and type 2 diabetes (15). Most of these common <lb/>CNVs are tagged by SNPs, and have therefore been indirectly <lb/>studied with GWASs (6,15). Nevertheless, as not all CNVs are <lb/>tagged by common SNPs, the study of individual common <lb/>CNVs remains important. The same hold true for the evalu-<lb/>ation of their combined effect, i.e. CNV burden. <lb/>In this study, we assessed the impact of CNVs on mortality <lb/>in two ways: first as individuals&apos; total burden of rare and <lb/>common CNVs, and second, by searching for common indi-<lb/>vidual CNV regions. We hypothesized that a higher burden <lb/>of CNVs, either rare or common, is associated with higher <lb/>mortality. In addition, we expected to identify novel <lb/>genomic locations that influence lifespan by analyzing individ-<lb/>ual common CNV regions (CNVRs). The study was carried <lb/>out in the first cohort (RS1) of the prospective population-<lb/>based Rotterdam study (RS), and positive findings were repli-<lb/>cated in the second cohort of RS (RS2) and in the Framingham <lb/>Heart Study. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>We analyzed the total burden of CNVs that were present in <lb/>,1% (rare CNVs) or in .1% (common CNVs) of the RS1 <lb/>study population separately. Altogether, 95% of these partici-<lb/>pants carried at least one rare CNV, whereas 99% carried at <lb/>least one common CNV (Supplementary Material, <lb/>Table S1). Per individual we observed a median number of <lb/>three rare and six common CNVs (Supplementary Material, <lb/>Table S1). Among common CNVs, no very large (≥1 Mb) <lb/>deletions or duplications were observed. <lb/>First, we investigated the effect of the total burden of rare <lb/>and common CNVs on mortality in RS1. Of the 5178 partici-<lb/>pants, 2716 (53%) died during a median follow-up period of <lb/>15 years (Table 1). For the total burden of rare CNVs, no asso-<lb/>ciations with mortality were observed (Table 2). This result <lb/>did not change when the rare CNV burden was analyzed sep-<lb/>arately for deletions and duplications, or CNV size (Table 2). <lb/>In contrast, for the burden of common CNVs, we observed that <lb/>Table 1. Characteristics of the participating studies <lb/>RS1 <lb/>(Discovery <lb/>cohort) <lb/>RS2 <lb/>(Replication <lb/>cohort 1) <lb/>FHS <lb/>(Replication <lb/>cohort 2) <lb/>n <lb/>5178 <lb/>1714 <lb/>4550 <lb/>Female (n, %) <lb/>3111 (60%) <lb/>933 (54%) <lb/>2411 (53%) <lb/>Age at baseline <lb/>(median, IQR) <lb/>(in years) <lb/>68.2 (62.0– 75.3) 62.1 (59.0–69.8) 40.0 (34.0–48.0) <lb/>Follow-up <lb/>(median, IQR) <lb/>(in years) <lb/>15.2 (8.84– 16.5) 7.94 (7.47–8.59) 30.5 (29.0–32.4) <lb/>Mortality (n, %) 2716 (53%) <lb/>223 (13%) <lb/>1180 (26%) <lb/>Table 2. Association between mortality and the burden of rare and common <lb/>CNVs in 5178 participants of RS1 <lb/>Rare CNVs <lb/>Common CNVs <lb/>HR (95% CI) <lb/>P-value HR (95% CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>Deletions and duplications <lb/>All segments <lb/>1.00 (0.98– 1.01) 0.64 <lb/>0.99 (0.98– 1.01) 0.25 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥100 kb <lb/>0.98 (0.95– 1.01) 0.10 <lb/>0.99 (0.96– 1.02) 0.52 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥500 kb <lb/>0.99 (0.90– 1.08) 0.80 <lb/>1.09 (1.02– 1.18) 0.017 <lb/> * <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥1 Mb <lb/>0.92 (0.76– 1.11) 0.37 <lb/>– <lb/>– <lb/>Deletions <lb/>All segments <lb/>1.00 (0.99– 1.02) 0.68 <lb/>0.99 (0.98– 1.01) 0.27 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥100 kb <lb/>0.99 (0.96– 1.02) 0.46 <lb/>0.99 (0.95– 1.04) 0.70 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥500 kb <lb/>0.96 (0.84– 1.10) 0.59 <lb/>1.17 (1.05– 1.30) 0.005 <lb/> * <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥1 Mb <lb/>0.77 (0.54– 1.09) 0.14 <lb/>– <lb/>– <lb/>Duplications <lb/>All segments <lb/>0.98 (0.95– 1.01) 0.18 <lb/>0.99 (0.97– 1.02) 0.68 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥100 kb <lb/>0.97 (0.92– 1.01) 0.12 <lb/>0.99 (0.95– 1.03) 0.66 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥500 kb <lb/>1.02 (0.90– 1.15) 0.75 <lb/>1.04 (0.94– 1.14) 0.50 <lb/>Segments <lb/>≥1 Mb <lb/>1.03 (0.81– 1.30) 0.82 <lb/>– <lb/>– <lb/>Sex and age at baseline adjusted Cox proportional hazard regression; estimates <lb/>indicate HRs per one extra CNV; HR-hazard ratio; CI-confidence interval. <lb/> * P-value , 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>4291 <lb/></page>

			<body>a higher burden of deletions which are .500 kb is associated <lb/>with 17% higher mortality in RS1 (HR 1.17, 95% CI 1.05 – <lb/>1.30, P ¼ 5.0 × 10 <lb/>23 ) (Table 2). Similar associations were <lb/>also observed in RS2 (HR 1.58, 95% CI 0.58 – 4.25, P ¼ <lb/>0.37) and FHS (HR 1.04, 95% CI 1.02 – 1.06, P ¼ 4.3 × <lb/>10 <lb/>24 <lb/>). In the overall meta-analysis of the 11442 participants <lb/>of RS1, RS2 and FHS, a 4% increase in mortality (HR 1.04, <lb/>95% CI 1.02– 1.07, P ¼ 5.82 × 10 <lb/>25 <lb/>) was observed. <lb/>Next, we examined the association of individual CNVRs <lb/>that have a frequency .1% with mortality. In defining <lb/>CNVRs, overlapping CNVs within a region were merged, <lb/>and the outermost boundaries of those CNVs were taken. <lb/>This approach yielded 312 CNVRs with an average size of <lb/>847 kb (range 1.70 kb – 14.5 Mb), of which nine were asso-<lb/>ciated with mortality in RS1 (Table 3). From these, the asso-<lb/>ciation with mortality was most consistently replicated for <lb/>two CNVRs (11p15.5 and 14q21.3) in RS2 and FHS. The <lb/>14q21.3 CNVR (size 65.4 kb) contains only deletions and <lb/>does not encompass any genes (Supplementary Material, <lb/>Fig. S1). The closest gene is c14orf28, which is located <lb/>116 kb downstream. This deletion is present in 1% of the par-<lb/>ticipants and it contributes to higher mortality as observed in <lb/>the 11 442 participants of RS1, RS2 and FHS (combined HR <lb/>1.57, 95% CI 1.19– 2.07, P ¼ 1.53 × 10 <lb/>23 <lb/>) (Table 3). The <lb/>second, 11p15.5, CNVR (size 794 kb) contains both duplica-<lb/>tions and deletions, and encompasses 41 genes (Fig. 1; Supple-<lb/>mentary Material, Table S2). Approximately 2% of the <lb/>examined populations carries either a deletion or a duplication <lb/>in this region, and these carriers have higher mortality com-<lb/>pared with non-carriers, as observed in 11 442 participants <lb/>of RS1, RS2 and FHS (combined HR 1.59, 95% CI 1.31 – <lb/>1.93, P ¼ 2.87 × 10 <lb/>26 ) (Table 3). <lb/>Within the RS1 discovery cohort, we repeated all analyses <lb/>for CNVRs with a frequency .5%. This did not reveal any <lb/>significant associations (data not shown). In addition, to test <lb/>whether the association between higher mortality and the <lb/>burden of deletions .500 kb in RS1 is accounted for by the <lb/>11p15.5 and 14q21.3 CNVRs, we repeated the initial analysis <lb/>with adjusting for these two CNVRs. This adjustment did not <lb/>essentially change the initial estimate. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this genome-wide CNV analysis we observed in RS1 and <lb/>replicated in RS2 and FHS that a higher burden of deletions <lb/>larger than 500 kb associates with 4% higher mortality. In add-<lb/>ition, we identified two common CNV regions (CNVRs) that <lb/>associate with higher mortality as well. One of these <lb/>CNVRs (11p15.5) is located in a gene-rich region, whereas <lb/>the other (14q21.3) does not encompass any genes. <lb/>In this study we expected that the higher burden of CNVs, <lb/>either rare or common would be associated with higher mortal-<lb/>ity. For the burden of rare CNVs, we observed no significant <lb/>associations. It is likely that rare CNVs are highly detrimental <lb/>and that carriers of these do not reach old age. Therefore, we <lb/>speculate that the rare CNVs observed in this study of older <lb/>individuals have negligible functional consequences. Alterna-<lb/>tively, they could have moderate phenotypic effects, but due to <lb/>power limitations, we were unable to detect these associations, <lb/>Table 3. Association between mortality and common individual CNVRs <lb/>CNVR <lb/>Locus <lb/>Type <lb/>RS1 (Discovery) <lb/>RS2 (Replication 1) <lb/>FHS (Replication 2) <lb/>Overall <lb/>Size (KB) Freq. HR (95% CI) <lb/>Freq. HR (95% CI) <lb/>Freq. HR (95% CI) <lb/>n <lb/>HR (95% CI) <lb/>P– value <lb/>chr3:37957465–37961253 <lb/>3p22.2 <lb/>DEL <lb/>3.79 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>1.47 (1.12–1.92) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>NA <lb/>5178 1.47 (1.12– 1.92) 5.30 <lb/>× 10 <lb/>23 * <lb/>chr14:21310636– 22074550 <lb/>14q11.2 <lb/>DEL/DUP <lb/>763.9 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.84 (0.74–0.96) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0.02 <lb/>1.15 (0.81–1.63) <lb/>9728 0.87 (0.78– 0.97) 0.014 <lb/> * <lb/>chr11:280233 –1074362 <lb/>11p15.5 <lb/>DEL/DUP <lb/>794.1 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>1.33 (1.05–1.68) 0.02 <lb/>2.23 (1.15–4.35) 0.01 <lb/>2.38 (1.59–3.54) 11 442 1.59 (1.31– 1.93) 2.87E–06 <lb/> * <lb/>chr9:5257043 –5354592 <lb/>9p24.1 <lb/>DEL/DUP <lb/>97.6 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1.46 (1.06–2.01) 0.01 <lb/>0.41 (0.06–2.90) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>6892 1.42 (1.04– 1.93) 0.027 <lb/> * <lb/>chr14:44254784– 44320168 <lb/>14q21.3 <lb/>DEL <lb/>65.4 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1.49 (1.04–2.12) 0.01 <lb/>2.49 (1.02–6.05) 0.01 <lb/>1.47 (0.87–2.50) 11 442 1.57 (1.19– 2.07) 1.53E–03 <lb/> * <lb/>chr4:160924547– 162509675 <lb/>4q32.1 <lb/>DEL <lb/>1585.1 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.84 (0.71–0.98) 0.15 <lb/>0.74 (0.50–1.09) 0.05 <lb/>1.31 (1.03–1.65) 11 442 0.93 (0.82– 1.06) 0.276 <lb/>chr3:192542016– 192564038 <lb/>3q28 <lb/>DEL <lb/>22.0 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>1.13 (1.01–1.27) 0.06 <lb/>1.17 (0.68–2.01) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>6892 1.13 (1.01– 1.27) 0.037 <lb/> * <lb/>chr14:104197399–106066496 14q32.33 DEL/DUP 1869.1 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>1.23 (1.02–1.48) 0.03 <lb/>1.25 (0.64–2.43) 0.15 <lb/>0.76 (0.64–0.90) 11 442 0.95 (0.83– 1.07) 0.378 <lb/>chr11:50021328– 51385578 <lb/>11p11.12 DEL/DUP 1364.3 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>1.17 (1.02–1.34) NA <lb/>NA <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1.20 (0.73–1.97) <lb/>9728 1.16 (1.02– 1.33) 0.024 <lb/> * <lb/>Sex and age at baseline adjusted Cox proportional hazard regression; reference category includes participants with no respective CNVR; freq., frequency; HR, hazard ratio; CI, confidence interval; NA, not <lb/>applicable due to frequency lower than 1%. <lb/> * <lb/>P , <lb/>0.05. <lb/></body>

			<page>4292 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. The 11p15.5 CNV region. The chromosome (chr)11:280233 –1074362 region (794 kb) contains overlapping deletions (red) and duplications (blue), <lb/>which were merged into a CNVR. The lines for duplications and deletions represent RS1 individuals who carry these CNVs. Within this region, 41 RefSeq genes <lb/>are located. The breakdown of linkage disequilibrium between SNPs within this region and Database of Genomic Variants entries from other studies are shown at <lb/>the bottom part of the figure. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>4293 <lb/></page>

			<body>leading to a potential false-negative result. Common CNVs are <lb/>likely to contribute to moderate phenotypic effects, but due to <lb/>their higher frequency their combined effect is more easily <lb/>detectable. Here, we observed that individuals with a higher <lb/>burden of common large deletions have 4% higher mortality. <lb/>This association could not be explained by the two individual <lb/>common CNVRs (11p15.5 and 14q21.3) that also associated <lb/>with higher mortality. This suggests that not only the <lb/>number of CNVs, but also the combination of CNVs that an <lb/>individual carries may have an influence on the risk of <lb/>mortality. <lb/>In this study, we tested 312 common individual CNVRs, of <lb/>which two (11p15.5 and 14q21.3) were consistently associated <lb/>with higher mortality across the three populations. Consider-<lb/>ing the low number of CNVRs tested and the level of signifi-<lb/>cance these associations reached, we are confident that these <lb/>loci represent true findings. Furthermore, both of these <lb/>CNVRs have been reported by the Database of Genomic Var-<lb/>iants (DGV, http://projects.tcag.ca/variation/). The 11p15.5 <lb/>CNV is located in a gene-rich region and it encompasses 41 <lb/>genes. Some of these genes have been associated with cardio-<lb/>vascular disease (CVD; PKP3) (20), cancer (HRAS, RNH1, <lb/>TALDO1) (21– 23), insulin resistance (PNPLA2) (24) and lon-<lb/>gevity (HRAS) (25,26). In the HRAS gene, a 3&apos; variable <lb/>number of tandem repeat allele was observed to be less fre-<lb/>quent in centenarians compared with young controls (25), <lb/>and in an other independent study, a haplotype was shown <lb/>to enhance the effect of APOE on exceptional survival (26). <lb/>However, even though there is prior evidence for the influence <lb/>of HRAS gene on human lifespan, other genes in this region or <lb/>in close proximity might also be of relevance. Especially when <lb/>taking into account that the 11p15.5 region is located nearby <lb/>genes (SIRT3, TH, INS and IGF2) that are consider to be <lb/>prominent candidate genes for human longevity (27– 29). <lb/>Based on our results, we cannot conclude the independence <lb/>or uniform effect of the CNV events spanning this region, <lb/>where specific evaluation of the CNV breaking points is <lb/>needed. The other, 14q21.3, CNVR encompasses no genes, <lb/>making functional implications less clear cut. The closest <lb/>gene to that region is c14orf28, which is located 116 kb down-<lb/>stream. Recently, it was demonstrated that the expression of <lb/>c14orf28 is altered in schizophrenia and bipolar disorder <lb/>samples relative to controls (30), implicating this gene in <lb/>dopamine-signaling pathway. Although the 14q21.3 deletion <lb/>is located far upstream, it could influence the transcription <lb/>of c14orf28 gene. Another alternative functional consequence <lb/>of the 14q21.3 deletion includes a disruption of highly evolu-<lb/>tionarily conserved DNA region with functions either in <lb/>chromosome assembly or in DNA replication (31). <lb/>In this study, we called CNVs common, when they were <lb/>present in .1% of the study population (i.e. polymorphism). <lb/>Under this definition, we were able to observe significant asso-<lb/>ciations for CNVs that have a relatively low frequency <lb/>(11p15.5 2%; 14q21.3 1%). In several other studies, different <lb/>cut-off criteria for determining common CNVs have been <lb/>used. One of these criteria includes frequency .5% (15). <lb/>When we applied this criterion, no significant associations <lb/>with CNVRs and mortality were observed. Previously it has <lb/>been demonstrated that most of the CNVs with a frequency <lb/>.5% are well tagged by SNPs and have indirectly been <lb/>studied in GWASs (6,15). Hence, the lack of associations <lb/>with CNVRs with frequency .5% in this study is in line <lb/>with the lack of genome-wide significant associations <lb/>between SNPs and longevity. On the other hand, in this <lb/>study, we were powered enough to study CNVs that are rare <lb/>but not extremely rare, representing frequencies for which <lb/>very large samples sizes would be needed in GWASs. <lb/>The current study has several strengths. One of these is the <lb/>availability of genome-wide CNV data within a large <lb/>population-based cohort, implying unbiased phenotyping. In <lb/>addition, the participants of this study have been followed <lb/>for mortality for a relatively long period of time, yielding a <lb/>high number of events to study. Also, by making use of RS2 <lb/>and FHS cohorts, we were able to validate the CNV events <lb/>and their frequency in different cohorts and across different <lb/>genotyping array types. Furthermore, we were able to replicate <lb/>the associations observed in RS1. A strength but also a draw-<lb/>back of the study is the use of high-density SNP arrays for <lb/>detecting CNVs. These arrays enable high genomic resolution, <lb/>but they have been designed to target unique non-duplicated <lb/>regions of the human genome. Therefore, not all regions in <lb/>the genome are equally well covered, especially those which <lb/>are prone to genomic rearrangements (32). Consequently, <lb/>some genomic regions were not assessed and remain to be <lb/>studied. In addition, we observed CNVs in the same <lb/>genomic regions with different frequencies in different study <lb/>populations. This is likely to stem from the genotype data <lb/>used, since if SNPs for some reason do not pass quality <lb/>control, it affects CNV inference (33). Despite these limita-<lb/>tions, we identified CNVRs that associate with higher mortal-<lb/>ity across three study populations. The use of specific CNV <lb/>arrays in the future would enable a more comprehensive <lb/>assessment of the relationship between CNVs and lifespan. <lb/>In conclusion, in this study, we found that the burden of <lb/>large common deletions, as well as common CNVs in the <lb/>11p15.5 and 14q21.3 regions, contribute to higher mortality <lb/>at old age. <lb/>SUBJECTS AND METHODS <lb/>Study populations <lb/>This study is embedded in the RS and the FHS. The RS is an <lb/>ongoing population-based study of risk factors for chronic dis-<lb/>eases in the elderly. Detailed information on design, objectives <lb/>and methods has been presented elsewhere (34). The current <lb/>study included 5178 participants of the RS1 and 1714 partici-<lb/>pants of RS2 for whom genome-wide CNV data were avail-<lb/>able. All participants of the RS were followed for mortality <lb/>until 1 January 2009. Altogether 2716 (53%) of the 5178 par-<lb/>ticipants in RS1 and 223 (13%) of the 1714 participants RS2 <lb/>died during the follow-up period (Table 1). The Medical <lb/>Ethics Committee of the Erasmus Medical Center approved <lb/>the RS and written informed consent was obtained from all <lb/>participants. The FHS was initiated to study the determinants <lb/>of CVD and other major illnesses. The original cohort was <lb/>recruited in 1948 and the offspring of the original cohort par-<lb/>ticipants and offspring spouses were enrolled in 1971 (35– 38). <lb/>DNA was obtained for genetic studies in the 1990s from sur-<lb/>viving original cohort and offspring participants. The time at <lb/></body>

			<page>4294 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/></note>

			<body>which DNA was obtained is considered the baseline examin-<lb/>ation for these analyses. For the current study, genetic infor-<lb/>mation and data on mortality were available for 4550 <lb/>participants. <lb/>CNV detection <lb/>In RS, CNVs were inferred from the genome-wide genotype <lb/>data of the RS participants. The genome-wide genotyping <lb/>was performed with Illumina 550K array (Illumina, San <lb/>Diego, CA, USA) in individuals of European descent <lb/>(sample call rate ≥97.5%). Individuals with excess of auto-<lb/>somal heterozygosity mismatch between genotypic and pheno-<lb/>typic gender, and outliers identified by the identity-by-state <lb/>clustering analysis, were excluded. For CNV detection, log <lb/>R ratio (LRR) signal intensity and B allele frequency (BAF) <lb/>were extracted using BeadStudio 3.1.3 (Illumina). A hidden-<lb/>Markov model, implemented in the software QuantiSNP <lb/>(32), was used to make CNV calls. For each CNV call, a <lb/>log Bayes factor was computed as a measure of confidence. <lb/>A correction for local difference in GC content is implemented <lb/>in the algorithm, which enables to adjust for irregularities in <lb/>signal intensity. Samples with a mean autosomal LRR SD <lb/>.0.35 or a BAF SD .0.15 were excluded, as well as CNV <lb/>calls that spanned the centromere. In addition, all CNV calls <lb/>with a log Bayes factor value ,10, a CNV size ,1 kb or <lb/>CNVs with only one consecutive SNP in the CNV event, <lb/>were excluded. For samples with an LRR SD between 0.3 <lb/>and 0.35, a stricter confidence threshold was applied <lb/>(BAF ¼ 15). Finally, samples with an excess of CNV calls <lb/>[expressed as upper quartile + 1.5 × (inter-quartile range)] <lb/>were also excluded. In FHS, genotyping was performed <lb/>using the Affymetrix genome wide array 5.0 for 8735 indivi-<lb/>duals. The raw CEL files were read, normalized and CNVs <lb/>called using Affymetrix power tools and the PennCNV soft-<lb/>ware. A total of 112 746 CNVs were obtained from the ana-<lb/>lysis. Extensive quality control of data was done using <lb/>several measures. CNVs that did not adhere to a one or <lb/>more of these criteria were excluded. <lb/>Generation of CNV-burden and CNVR datasets <lb/>The data on total CNV burden and on specific CNVRs per in-<lb/>dividual was estimated by using PLINK v1.07 software (39). <lb/>In estimating the total CNV burden, CNVs that overlapped <lb/>by at least 50% of their length with another CNV were consid-<lb/>ered to co-localize and counted once. For CNVRs, completely <lb/>non-redundant CNVRs were constructed by merging overlap-<lb/>ping CNVs and taking the outermost boundaries of those <lb/>CNVs. These datasets were generated for deletions and dupli-<lb/>cations combined and separated. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>The association between mortality and the burden of CNVs and <lb/>individual CNVRs was calculated with Cox proportional hazard <lb/>regression, adjusted for age at baseline and sex. All association <lb/>analyses were performed with SPSS version 17 (SPSS Inc., <lb/>Chicago, IL, USA) statistical software. Results were combined <lb/>in a meta-analysis using the inverse variance method to combine <lb/>effect size estimates from each sample (40). <lb/>SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Material is available at HMG online. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank Pascal Arp, Mila Jhamai, Marijn Verkerk, Lizbeth <lb/>Herrera and Marjolein Peters for their help in creating the <lb/>GWAS database. The authors are grateful to the study partici-<lb/> pants, the staff from the Rotterdam Study and the participating <lb/>general practitioners and pharmacists. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest statement. None declared. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">FUNDING <lb/>This work was supported by the Research Institute for <lb/>Diseases in the Elderly (grant number 014-93-015; RIDE2); <lb/>and the Netherlands Genomics Initiative (NGI)/Netherlands <lb/>Organization for Scientific Research (NWO) project (grant <lb/>number 050-060-810; NCHA), Erasmus Medical Center and <lb/>Erasmus University, Rotterdam; Netherlands Organization <lb/>for the Health Research and Development (ZonMw); the <lb/>Research Institute for Diseases in the Elderly (RIDE); the <lb/>Ministry of Education, Culture and Science; the Ministry for <lb/>Health, Welfare and Sports; the European Commission <lb/>(DG XII); and the Municipality of Rotterdam. The generation <lb/>and management of GWAS genotype data for the Rotterdam <lb/>Study are supported by the Netherlands Organization of Scien-<lb/>tific Research NWO Investments (grant numbers <lb/>175.010.2005.011, 911-03-012 and 017-106-370 VIDI to <lb/>H.T.). The FHS was funded by grants from the US National <lb/>Institute for Arthritis, Musculoskeletal and Skin Diseases <lb/>and National Institute on Aging (R01 AR/AG 41398 D.P.K.; <lb/>R01 AR 050066 D.K.; R01 AG 29451 J.M. and K.L.L.) and <lb/>Hebrew SeniorLife Men&apos;s Associate. The Framingham Heart <lb/>Study of the National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute of <lb/>the National Institutes of Health and Boston University <lb/>School of Medicine were supported by the National Heart, <lb/>Lung, and Blood Institute&apos;s Framingham Heart Study (N01-<lb/>HC-25195) and its contract with Affymetrix, Inc. for genotyp-<lb/>ing services (N02-HL-6-4278). Analyses reflect intellectual <lb/>input and resource development from the Framingham Heart <lb/>Study investigators participating in the SNP Health Associ-<lb/>ation Resource (SHARe) project. A portion of this research <lb/>was conducted using the Linux Cluster for Genetic Analysis <lb/>(LinGA-II) funded by the Robert Dawson Evans Endowment <lb/>of the Department of Medicine at Boston University School <lb/>of Medicine and Boston Medical Center. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Hjelmborg, J.W., Iachine, I., Skytthe, A., Vaupel, J.W., McGue, M., <lb/>Koskenvuo, M., Kaprio, J., Pedersen, N.L. and Christensen, K. (2006) <lb/>Genetic influence on human lifespan and longevity. Hum. Genet., 119, <lb/>312– 321. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 <lb/></note>

			<page>4295 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>2. Mitchell, B.D., Hsueh, W.C., King, T.M., Pollin, T.I., Sorkin, J., <lb/>Agarwala, R., Schaffer, A.A. and Shuldiner, A.R. (2001) Heritability of <lb/>life span in the Old Order Amish. Am. J. Med. Genet., 102, 346–352. <lb/>3. Gudmundsson, H., Gudbjartsson, D.F., Frigge, M., Gulcher, J.R. and <lb/>Stefansson, K. (2000) Inheritance of human longevity in Iceland. Eur. J. <lb/>Hum. Genet., 8, 743–749. <lb/>4. Newman, A.B., Walter, S., Lunetta, K.L., Garcia, M.E., Slagboom, P.E., <lb/>Christensen, K., Arnold, A.M., Aspelund, T., Aulchenko, Y.S., <lb/>Benjamin, E.J. et al. (2010) A meta-analysis of four genome-wide <lb/>association studies of survival to age 90 years or older: the Cohorts for <lb/>Heart and Aging Research in Genomic Epidemiology Consortium. J. <lb/>Gerontol. A Biol. Sci. Med. Sci., 65A, 478– 487. <lb/>5. Sebastiani, P., Solovieff, N., Puca, A., Hartley, S.W., Melista, E., <lb/>Andersen, S., Dworkis, D.A., Wilk, J.B., Myers, R.H., Steinberg, M.H. <lb/>et al. (2010) Genetic signatures of exceptional longevity in humans. <lb/>Science, 22, 404– 415. <lb/>6. McCarroll, S.A., Kuruvilla, F.G., Korn, J.M., Cawley, S., Nemesh, J., <lb/>Wysoker, A., Shapero, M.H., de Bakker, P.I.W., Maller, J.B., Kirby, A. <lb/>et al. (2008) Integrated detection and population-genetic analysis of SNPs <lb/>and copy number variation. Nat. Genet., 40, 1166–1174. <lb/>7. Stranger, B.E., Forrest, M.S., Dunning, M., Ingle, C.E., Beazley, C., <lb/>Thorne, N., Redon, R., Bird, C.P., de Grassi, A., Lee, C. et al. (2007) <lb/>Relative impact of nucleotide and copy number variation on gene <lb/>expression phenotypes. Science, 315, 848–853. <lb/>8. Feuk, L., Carson, A.R. and Scherer, S.W. (2006) Structural variation in <lb/>the human genome. Nat. Rev. Genet., 7, 85– 97. <lb/>9. Henrichsen, C.N., Chaignat, E. and Reymond, A. (2009) Copy number <lb/>variants, diseases and gene expression. Hum. Mol. Genet., 18, R1–R8. <lb/>10. Zhang, F., Gu, W., Hurles, M.E. and Lupski, J.R. (2009) Copy number <lb/>variation in human health, disease, and evolution. Annu. Rev. Genomics <lb/>Hum. Genet., 10, 451– 481. <lb/>11. Glessner, J.T., Wang, K., Cai, G., Korvatska, O., Kim, C.E., Wood, S., <lb/>Zhang, H., Estes, A., Brune, C.W., Bradfield, J.P. et al. (2009) Autism <lb/>genome-wide copy number variation reveals ubiquitin and neuronal <lb/>genes. Nature, 459, 569–573. <lb/>12. Mefford, H.C., Muhle, H., Ostertag, P., von Spiczak, S., Buysse, K., <lb/>Baker, C., Franke, A., Malafosse, A., Genton, P., Thomas, P. et al. (2010) <lb/>Genome-wide copy number variation in epilepsy: novel susceptibility loci <lb/>in idiopathic generalized and focal epilepsies. PLoS Genet., 6, e1000962. <lb/>13. Glessner, J.T., Reilly, M.P., Kim, C.E., Takahashi, N., Albano, A., <lb/>Hou, C., Bradfield, J.P., Zhang, H., Sleiman, P.M.A., Flory, J.H. et al. <lb/>(2010) Strong synaptic transmission impact by copy number variations in <lb/>schizophrenia. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 107, 10584– 10589. <lb/>14. The International Schizophrenia Consortium (2008) Rare chromosomal <lb/>deletions and duplications increase risk of schizophrenia. Nature, 455, <lb/>237– 241. <lb/>15. The Wellcome Trust Case Control Consortium (2010) Genome-wide <lb/>association study of CNVs in 16,000 cases of eight common diseases and <lb/>3,000 shared controls. Nature, 464, 713 –720. <lb/>16. Zhang, D., Cheng, L., Qian, Y., Alliey-Rodriguez, N., Kelsoe, J.R., <lb/>Greenwood, T., Nievergelt, C., Barrett, T.B., McKinney, R., Schork, N. <lb/>et al. (2009) Singleton deletions throughout the genome increase risk of <lb/>bipolar disorder. Mol. Psychiatry, 14, 376–380. <lb/>17. Cronin, S., Blauw, H.M., Veldink, J.H., van Es, M.A., Ophoff, R.A., <lb/>Bradley, D.G., van den Berg, L.H. and Hardiman, O. (2008) Analysis of <lb/>genome-wide copy number variation in Irish and Dutch ALS populations. <lb/>Hum. Mol. Genet., 17, 3392–3398. <lb/>18. Blauw, H.M., Al-Chalabi, A., Andersen, P.M., van Vught, P.W., <lb/>Diekstra, F.P., van Es, M.A., Saris, C.G., Groen, E.J., van Rheenen, W., <lb/>Koppers, M. et al. (2010) A large genome scan for rare CNVs in <lb/>amyotrophic lateral sclerosis. Hum. Mol. Genet., 19, 4091– 4099. <lb/>19. Bochukova, E.G., Huang, N., Keogh, J., Henning, E., Purmann, C., <lb/>Blaszczyk, K., Saeed, S., Hamilton-Shield, J., Clayton-Smith, J., <lb/>O&apos;Rahilly, S. et al. (2010) Large, rare chromosomal deletions associated <lb/>with severe early-onset obesity. Nature, 463, 666 –670. <lb/>20. Talmud, P.J., Drenos, F., Shah, S., Shah, T., Palmen, J., Verzilli, C., <lb/>Gaunt, T.R., Pallas, J., Lovering, R., Li, K. et al. (2009) Gene-centric <lb/>association signals for lipids and apolipoproteins identified via the <lb/>HumanCVD BeadChip. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 85, 628– 642. <lb/>21. Boulalas, I., Zaravinos, A., Karyotis, I., Delakas, D. and Spandidos, D.A. <lb/>(2009) Activation of RAS family genes in urothelial carcinoma. J. Urol., <lb/>181, 2312– 2319. <lb/>22. Vogel, U., Olsen, A., Wallin, H., Overvad, K., Tjonneland, A. and <lb/>Nexo, B.A. (2005) Effect of polymorphisms in XPD, RAI, ASE-1 and <lb/>ERCC1 on the risk of basal cell carcinoma among Caucasians after age <lb/>50. Cancer Detect. Prev., 29, 209–214. <lb/>23. Basta, P.V., Bensen, J.T., Tse, C.K., Perou, C.M., Sullivan, P.F. and <lb/>Olshan, A.F. (2008) Genetic variation in Transaldolase 1 and risk of <lb/>squamous cell carcinoma of the head and neck. Cancer Detect. Prev., 32, <lb/>200–208. <lb/>24. Johansson, L.E., Johansson, L.M., Danielsson, P., Norgren, S., <lb/>Johansson, S., Marcus, C. and Ridderstrale, M. (2009) Genetic variance in <lb/>the adiponutrin gene family and childhood obesity. PLoS One, 4, e5327. <lb/>25. Bonafè, M., Barbi, C., Olivieri, F., Yashin, A., Andreev, K.F., <lb/>Vaupel, J.W., De Benedictis, G., Rose, G., Carrieri, G., Jazwinski, S.M. <lb/>et al. (2002) An allele of HRAS1 3 <lb/>′ variable number of tandem repeats is <lb/>a frailty allele: implication for an evolutionarily-conserved pathway <lb/>involved in longevity. Gene, 286, 121–126. <lb/>26. Jazwinski, S.M., Kim, S., Dai, J., Li, L., Bi, X., Jiang, J.C., Arnold, J., <lb/>Batzer, M.A., Walker, J.A., Welsh, D.A. et al. (2010) HRAS1 and LASS1 <lb/>with APOE are associated with human longevity and healthy aging. Aging <lb/>Cell, 9, 698– 708. <lb/>27. Lescai, F., Blanche, H., Nebel, A., Beekman, M., Sahbatou, M., <lb/>Flachsbart, F., Slagboom, E., Schreiber, S., Sorbi, S., Passarino, G. et al. <lb/>(2009) Human longevity and 11p15.5: a study in 1321 centenarians. Eur. <lb/>J. Hum. Genet., 17, 1515– 1519. <lb/>28. Bellizzi, D., Rose, G., Cavalcante, P., Covello, G., Dato, S., De Rango, F., <lb/>Greco, V., Maggiolini, M., Feraco, E., Mari, V. et al. (2005) A novel <lb/>VNTR enhancer within the SIRT3 gene, a human homologue of SIR2, is <lb/>associated with survival at oldest ages. Genomics, 85, 258–263. <lb/>29. De Luca, M., Rose, G., Bonafè, M., Garasto, S., Greco, V., Weir, B.S., <lb/>Franceschi, C. and De Benedictis, G. (2001) Sex-specific longevity <lb/>associations defined by Tyrosine Hydroxylase– Insulin–Insulin Growth <lb/>Factor 2 haplotypes on the 11p15.5 chromosomal region. Exp. Gerontol., <lb/>36, 1663–1671. <lb/>30. Zhan, L., Kerr, J.R., Lafuente, M.J., Maclean, A., Chibalina, M.V., <lb/>Liu, B., Burke, B., Bevan, S. and Nasir, J. (2011) Altered expression and <lb/>coregulation of dopamine signalling genes in schizophrenia and bipolar <lb/>disorder. Neuropathol. Appl. Neurobiol., 37, 206– 219. <lb/>31. Ludwig, M.Z. (2002) Functional evolution of noncoding DNA. Curr. <lb/>Opin. Genet. Dev., 12, 634–639. <lb/>32. Carter, N.P. (2007) Methods and strategies for analyzing copy number <lb/>variation using DNA microarrays. Nat. Genet., 39(7 Suppl):S16 –S21. <lb/>33. Alkan, C., Coe, B.P. and Eichler, E.E. (2011) Genome structural variation <lb/>discovery and genotyping. Nat. Rev. Genet., 12, 363–376. <lb/>34. Hofman, A., Breteler, M., van Duijn, C., Janssen, H., Krestin, G., <lb/>Kuipers, E., Stricker, B., Tiemeier, H., Uitterlinden, A., Vingerling, J. <lb/>et al. (2009) The Rotterdam Study: 2010 objectives and design update. <lb/>Eur. J. Epidemiol., 24, 553– 572. <lb/>35. Dawber, T.R., Kannel, W.B. and Lyell, L.P. (1963) An approach to <lb/>longitudinal studies in a community: the Framingham Study. Ann. N. Y. <lb/>Acad. Sci., 107, 539 –556. <lb/>36. Dawber, T.R., Meadors, G.F. and Moore, F.E. Jr. (1951) Epidemiological <lb/>approaches to heart disease: the Framingham Study. Am. J. Public Health <lb/>Nations Health, 41, 279–281. <lb/>37. Feinleib, M., Kannel, W.B., Garrison, R.J., McNamara, P.M. and Castelli, <lb/>W.P. (1975) The Framingham offspring study. Design and preliminary <lb/>data. Prev. Med., 4, 518–525. <lb/>38. Kannel, W.B., Feinleib, M., McNamara, P.M., Garrison, R.J. and <lb/>Castelli, W.P. (1979) An investigation of coronary heart disease in <lb/>families. The Framingham offspring study. Am. J. Epidemiol., 110, <lb/>281–290. <lb/>39. Purcell, S., Neale, B., Todd-Brown, K., Thomas, L., Ferreira, M.A., <lb/>Bender, D., Maller, J., Sklar, P., de Bakker, P.I., Daly, M.J. et al. (2007) <lb/>PLINK: a tool set for whole-genome association and population-based <lb/>linkage analyses. Am. J. Hum. Genet., 81, 559–575. <lb/>40. Willer, C.J., Li, Y. and Abecasis, G.R. (2010) METAL: fast and efficient <lb/>meta-analysis of genomewide association scans. Bioinformatics, 26, <lb/>2190– 2191. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4296 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Human Molecular Genetics, 2011, Vol. 20, No. 21 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
