<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_EJM_CavitationModelsComparison"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> A comparative study of cavitation models in a Venturi <lb/>flow <lb/> Boris Charì ere  a  , Jean Decaix  b  , Eric Goncalv es  a, § <lb/> a <lb/> LEGI -University of Grenoble, 1025 rue de la Piscine, 38400 St Martin d&apos;Heres, France <lb/> b <lb/> University of Applied Sciences, Western Switzerland, CH-1950 Sion <lb/> Abstract <lb/> This paper presents a numerical study of an aperiodic cavitation pocket <lb/>developing in a Venturi flow. The mass transfer between phases is driven <lb/>by a void ratio transport equation model. A new free-parameter closure <lb/>relation is proposed and compared with other formulations. The re-entrant <lb/>jet development, void ratio profiles and pressure fluctuations are analyzed to <lb/>discern results accuracy. Comparisons with available experimental data are <lb/>done and good agreement is achieved. <lb/> Keywords: Cavitation, Mass transfer, Homogeneous model, RANS <lb/>simulation <lb/> Nomenclature <lb/> c <lb/> speed of sound <lb/> C  p  , C  v <lb/> thermal capacities <lb/> E <lb/> total energy <lb/> e <lb/> internal energy <lb/>  § <lb/> Corresponding author <lb/> Email address: eric.goncalves@legi.grenoble-inp.fr (Eric Goncalv es ) <lb/> Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/>January 8, 2014 <lb/></front>

			<body> k <lb/> turbulent kinetic energy <lb/> P <lb/> static pressure <lb/> P  vap <lb/> vapour pressure <lb/> P  r  , P  rt <lb/> molecular and turbulent Prandtl numbers <lb/> Q <lb/> total heat flux <lb/> Re  L <lb/> Reynolds number based on the length L <lb/> T <lb/> temperature <lb/> u, v <lb/> velocity components <lb/> V <lb/> vector velocity <lb/> w <lb/> conservative variables <lb/> Y <lb/> mass fraction of gas <lb/>˙ <lb/> m <lb/> mass transfer <lb/> AE <lb/> void fraction <lb/> ∞ <lb/> ratio of thermal capacities <lb/> &quot; <lb/> dissipation rate <lb/> ∏, ∏  t <lb/> molecular and turbulent thermal conductivity <lb/> µ, µ  t <lb/> molecular and eddy viscosity <lb/> Ω <lb/> density <lb/> Ω  I <lb/> interfacial density <lb/> ae <lb/> cavitation number <lb/> ø <lb/> total stress tensor <lb/> ! <lb/> specific dissipation <lb/>()  l <lb/> liquid value <lb/>()  v <lb/> vapour value <lb/>()  v <lb/> viscous <lb/>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			()  t <lb/> turbulent <lb/> 1. Introduction <lb/> Cavitation is the formation of vapour cavities within a given liquid due to <lb/>pressure drop. It may be observed in various engineering systems such as <lb/>hydraulic constructions, aeronautics, aerospace, power systems and turbo-<lb/>machinery. The cavitation development may be the origin of several nega-<lb/>tive eAEects, such as noise, vibrations, performance alterations, erosion and <lb/>structural damages. This makes cavitation an important issue in design and <lb/>operation, which should be controlled, or at least well understood. <lb/>Among the cavitation types that may develop, partial cavitation pockets <lb/>are often observed in hydraulic machines and is known to be responsible for <lb/>severe damage. Cavitating venturis are one of the simplest case to study <lb/>such cavities, both experimentally and numerically. This kind of cavitation <lb/>is characterized by a partial vapour cavity that detaches from the solid body <lb/>and extends downstream with the existence of a re-entrant jet. The dynamic <lb/>of these cavitation sheets, the interaction between cavitation and turbulence, <lb/>the behaviour of the turbulent boundary layer are not yet well known and <lb/>understood. <lb/>Although the numerical modelling of such cavitation has received a great <lb/>deal of attention, it is still a very di±cult and challenging task to simulate <lb/>such complex unsteady two-phase flow with an acceptable accuracy. Cavitat-<lb/>ing flows are challenging to model, since they are turbulent with a complex <lb/>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			interaction with two-phase structures, highly dynamic and involve non equi-<lb/>librium thermodynamic states. Several numerical models have been devel-<lb/>oped to investigate such cavitating flows, especially with one-fluid Reynolds-<lb/>Averaged Navier-Stokes (RANS) solvers. The homogeneous mixture model <lb/>treats the cavitating flows as a mixture of two fluids behaving as one. These <lb/>models are based on the assumption of local kinematic equilibrium between <lb/>phases (the local velocity is the same for both phases), local thermal and <lb/>mechanic equilibrium between the two components (local temperature and <lb/>pressure equality between phases). These models are composed by three <lb/>conservation laws for mixture quantities (mass, momentum and total en-<lb/>ergy). This model cannot reproduce strong thermodynamic non equilibrium <lb/>eAEects but, because of its simplicity, it is often used for numerical simulations <lb/>[1, 2, 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, 8]. <lb/>By assuming that one pure phase is on a metastable state, a supplementary <lb/>mass equation or void fraction equation is added. Various formulations of <lb/>four-equation model have been expressed. A very popular formulation has <lb/>been developed to simulate turbulent cavitating flows [9, 10, 11, 12, 13, 14]. <lb/>The main di±culty is related to the formulation of the source term and the <lb/>tunable parameters involved for the vaporization and condensation processes. <lb/>Moreover, these models are not thermodynamically well-posed [15]. Another <lb/>popular model devoted to ebullition problems uses a relaxation term (Ho-<lb/>mogeneous Relaxation Model). The source term involves a relaxation time <lb/>estimated from experimental data [16] or with an optimization problem on <lb/>the mixture entropy [17]. An original formulation was recently proposed for <lb/>the mass transfer between phases assuming its proportionality with the diver-<lb/>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			gence of the mixture velocity. This model was validated on various inviscid <lb/>and turbulent applications [18, 19]. <lb/>The present work is devoted to the numerical study of a partial cavitation <lb/>pocket appearing on a venturi geometry. For this test case, a transitional be-<lb/>haviour is observed between a stable pocket and a periodic cycles pocket. <lb/>A particular emphasis is placed on the comparison of various void ratio <lb/>transport equation models and their ability to capture the re-entrant jet <lb/>phenomenon. An in-house finite-volume code solving a four-equation RANS <lb/>compressible system was developed [19]. A new cavitation model is investi-<lb/>gated using a mixture of stiAEened gas equation of state (EOS). The formula-<lb/>tion does not involve any tunable parameter. Validation and comparisons are <lb/>done with experimental measurements (time-averaged void ratio and veloc-<lb/>ity profiles, RMS wall pressure fluctuations). A comparison is proposed with <lb/>OpenFOAM simulations in which the Kunz&apos;s void ratio transport equation <lb/>model is considered. The opensource software OpenFOAM was used and <lb/>validated in cavitating flows by various authors [20, 21, 22]. <lb/>In this paper, we will first review the theoretical formulation, including phys-<lb/>ical models, equation of state and elements of the numerical methods. This <lb/>is followed by sets of results on a Venturi geometry and discussions. <lb/> 2. The LEGI&apos;s numerical tool <lb/> The code is based on the solving of the one-fluid compressible RANS system <lb/>with transport-equation turbulence models. <lb/>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			2.1. Reynolds-Averaged Navier-Stokes compressible equations <lb/> The compressible one-fluid RANS equations are used, coupled with a one-<lb/>or two-equation turbulence model. For low Mach number applications, an <lb/>inviscid preconditioner is introduced. These equations can be expressed as: <lb/> P  °1 <lb/> c <lb/> @w <lb/> @t <lb/> + div (F  c  ° F  v  ) = S <lb/> (1) <lb/> w = <lb/> 0 <lb/> B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>@ <lb/> Ω <lb/>ΩV <lb/>ΩE <lb/>AE <lb/>Ωk <lb/>Ω™ <lb/> 1 <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/> ; F  c  = <lb/> 0 <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>@ <lb/> ΩV <lb/>ΩV ≠ V + pI <lb/> (ΩE + p)V <lb/> AEV <lb/>ΩkV <lb/>Ω™V <lb/> 1 <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/> ; F  v  = <lb/> 0 <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>@ <lb/> 0 <lb/> ø  v  + ø  t <lb/> (ø  v  + ø  t  ).V ° Q  v  ° Q  t <lb/> 0 <lb/>(µ + µ  t  /ae  k  ) grad k <lb/> (µ + µ  t  /ae  ™  ) grad ™ <lb/> 1 <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/> where w denotes the conservative variables and the void ratio, F  c  and F  v <lb/> the convective and viscous flux densities and S the source terms, which con-<lb/>cern the void ratio equation and the turbulent transport equations. The <lb/>expression of the preconditioning matrix P  c  is given in [19]. k is the mixture <lb/>turbulent kinetic energy (TKE) and ™ is a mixture turbulent variable. In <lb/>multiphase flow, the divergence of the fluctuating phase velocity is not zero <lb/>[23]. Therefore, supplementary terms appear in the mixture TKE equation <lb/>(pressure-dilation term, dilatational dissipation rate), which are not taken <lb/>into account in the present paper. <lb/>The exact expression of the eddy-viscosity µ  t  and the source terms depends <lb/>on the turbulence model as well as constants ae  k  and ae  ™  . <lb/>The total stress tensor ø is evaluated using the Stokes hypothesis, Newton&apos;s <lb/>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			law and the Boussinesq assumption. The total heat flux vector Q is obtained <lb/>from the Fourier law involving a turbulent thermal conductivity ∏  t  with the <lb/>constant Prandtl number hypothesis. <lb/> ø = ø  v  + ø  t  = (µ + µ  t  ) <lb/> ∑ <lb/> ( grad V + ( grad V )  t  ) ° <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>( div V )I <lb/> ∏ <lb/> + <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/> ΩkI <lb/> Q = Q  v  + Q  t  = ° (∏ + ∏  t  ) grad T with ∏  t  = <lb/> µ  t  C  p <lb/> P  rt <lb/> (2) <lb/>In pure phases, the viscosity is assumed to be constant. The mixture viscosity <lb/>is defined as the arithmetic mean of the liquid and vapour viscosities: <lb/> µ(AE) = AEµ  V  + (1 ° AE)µ  L <lb/> (3) <lb/>The mixture thermal conductivity ∏ is also defined as the arithmetic mean <lb/>of the liquid and vapour values: <lb/> ∏(AE) = AE <lb/> µ  V  C  p  V <lb/> P  r  V <lb/> + (1 ° AE) <lb/> µ  L  C  p  L <lb/> P  r  L <lb/> (4) <lb/>The turbulent Prandtl number P  rt  is set to 1. <lb/>To close the system, an equation of state (EOS) is necessary to link the <lb/>pressure and the temperature to the internal energy and the density. For the <lb/>pure phases, we used the convex stiAEened gas EOS: <lb/> P (Ω, e) = (∞ ° 1)Ω(e ° q) ° ∞P  1 <lb/> (5) <lb/> P (Ω, T ) = Ω(∞ ° 1)C  v  T ° P  1 <lb/> (6) <lb/> T (Ω, h) = <lb/> h ° q <lb/>C  p <lb/> (7) <lb/>where ∞ = C  p  /C  v  is the heat capacity ratio, C  p  and C  v  are thermal capacities, <lb/> q the energy of the fluid at a given reference state and P  1  is a constant <lb/>reference pressure. <lb/>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			2.2. A void ratio transport equation <lb/> A void ratio equation can be expressed as [24]: <lb/> @AE <lb/> @t <lb/> + div (AEV ) = (K + AE) div V + <lb/>˙ <lb/> m <lb/> Ω  I <lb/> (8) <lb/> K = <lb/> √ <lb/> Ω  l  c  2 <lb/> l  ° Ω  v  c  2 <lb/> v <lb/> Ω  l  c  2 <lb/> l <lb/> 1°AE <lb/> +  Ω  v  c  2 v <lb/> AE <lb/> ! <lb/> ; <lb/> Ω  I  = <lb/> √  c  2 <lb/> v <lb/> AE <lb/> + <lb/> c  2 <lb/> l <lb/> 1°AE <lb/> Ω  l  c  2 <lb/> l <lb/> 1°AE <lb/> +  Ω  v  c  2 v <lb/> AE <lb/> ! <lb/> (9) <lb/>where ˙ <lb/> m is the mass transfer between phases and Ω  I  the interfacial density . <lb/>By assuming that the mass transfer is proportional to the divergence of the <lb/>velocity, it is possible to build a family of models in which the mass transfer <lb/>˙ <lb/> m is expressed as [18] <lb/>˙ <lb/> m = <lb/> Ω  l  Ω  v <lb/> Ω  l  ° Ω  v <lb/> µ <lb/> 1 ° <lb/> c  2 <lb/> c  2 <lb/> wallis <lb/> ∂ <lb/> div V <lb/> (10) <lb/>where c  wallis  is the propagation velocity of acoustic waves without mass trans-<lb/>fer [25]. This speed of sound is expressed as a weighted harmonic mean of <lb/>speeds of sound of each phase: <lb/>1 <lb/> Ωc  2 <lb/> wallis <lb/> = <lb/> AE <lb/>Ω  v  c  2 <lb/> v <lb/> + <lb/>1 ° AE <lb/>Ω  l  c  2 <lb/> l <lb/> (11) <lb/>A first model was built using the speed of sound associated with a sinu-<lb/>soidal barotropic EOS [18, 19]. In the following, this model will be named <lb/>4-equation barotropic model. It involves one tunable parameter c  baro  inter-<lb/>preted as the minimum value of the speed of sound in the mixture. For all <lb/>simulations the value was set to 0.5 m/s. <lb/> 2.3. A new cavitation model <lb/> The new model is based on a mixture of stiAEened gas EOS. By assuming <lb/>the pressure equilibrium between phases, an expression for the pressure can <lb/>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			be deduced, function of the void ratio AE and the vapour mass fraction Y = <lb/> AEΩ  v  /Ω: <lb/>P (Ω, e, AE, Y ) = (∞(AE) ° 1)Ω(e ° q(Y )) ° ∞(AE)P  1  (AE) <lb/>( 1 2 ) <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞(AE) ° 1 <lb/>= <lb/> AE <lb/>∞  v  ° 1 <lb/>+ <lb/>1 ° AE <lb/>∞  l  ° 1 <lb/>(13) <lb/> q(Y ) = Y q  v  + (1 ° Y )q  l <lb/> (14) <lb/> P  1  (AE) = <lb/> ∞(AE) ° 1 <lb/> ∞(AE) <lb/> ∑ <lb/> AE <lb/>∞  v <lb/> ∞  v  ° 1 <lb/> P  v <lb/> 1  + (1 ° AE) <lb/>∞  l <lb/> ∞  l  ° 1 <lb/> P  l <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∏ <lb/> (15) <lb/>By assuming the thermal equilibrium between phases, the mixture tempera-<lb/>ture is expressed as: <lb/> T (Ω, h, Y ) = <lb/> h  l  ° q  l <lb/> C  p  l <lb/> = <lb/> h  v  ° q  v <lb/> C  p  v <lb/> = <lb/> h ° q(Y ) <lb/> C  p  (Y ) <lb/>(16) <lb/> C  p  (Y ) = Y C  p  v  + (1 ° Y )C  p  l <lb/> (17) <lb/>The speed of sound in the mixture can be expressed as a function of the <lb/>enthalpy of each phase (see Appendix A): <lb/> Ωc  2  = <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ ° 1 <lb/> ∑ Ω  v  Ω  l <lb/> (Ω  l  ° Ω  v  ) <lb/>(h  v  ° h  l  ) <lb/> ∏ <lb/> (18) <lb/>Enthalpies of pure phase h  l  and h  v  are computed with the mixture temper-<lb/>ature T . <lb/>The mass transfer term is activated when the local pressure P is smaller than <lb/>the vapour pressure P  vap  . This model will be named 4-equation SG model. <lb/>It does not involve any tunable parameter. <lb/> 2.4. The turbulence model <lb/> Various turbulence models are considered: the Smith k ° ` model (KL) [26], <lb/>the one-equation Spalart-Allmaras model (SA) [27] and the Jones-Launder <lb/>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			 k ° &quot; model (KE) [28]. For a correct simulation of the re-entrant jet, the <lb/>Reboud eddy-viscosity limiter is added [29, 30, 31]. For comparisons with <lb/>the OpenFOAM solver, the Menter k ° ! SST model [32] is used, assuming <lb/>the validity of the Bradshaw assumption in a two-phase turbulent boundary <lb/>layer. <lb/> 2.5. Wall functions <lb/> For the modelling of flow close to the wall, a two-layer wall law approach is <lb/>used: <lb/> u  +  = y  + <lb/> if y  +  &lt; 11.13 <lb/> u  +  = <lb/>1 <lb/> ∑ <lb/> ln y  +  + 5.25 if y  +  &gt; 11.13 <lb/> u  +  = <lb/> u <lb/>U  ø <lb/> ; <lb/> y  +  = <lb/> yU  ø <lb/> ∫  w <lb/> ; U  2 <lb/> ø  = <lb/> ø  w <lb/> Ω  w <lb/> (19) <lb/>where ∑ = 0.41 is the von Karman constant and the subscript &apos;w&apos; is used for <lb/>a wall value. <lb/>We assume that wall functions are similar in a two-phase flow and in a <lb/>single-phase flow. For unsteady flows, the existence of a wall law is assumed <lb/>to be valid at each instant. These assumptions have been studied in [33] and <lb/>comparisons were proposed with a thin boundary layer approach. <lb/> 2.6. Numerics <lb/> The numerical simulations are carried out using an implicit CFD code based <lb/>on a finite-volume discretization. For the mean flow, the convective flux <lb/>density vector on a cell face is computed with the Jameson-Schmidt-Turkel <lb/>scheme [34]. The artificial viscosity includes a second-order dissipation term <lb/>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			 D  2  and a fourth-order dissipation term D  4  , which involve two tunable pa-<lb/>rameters k  (2)  and k  (4)  . <lb/>The viscous terms are discretized by a second-order space-centered scheme. <lb/>For the turbulence transport equations, the upwind Roe scheme [35] is used <lb/>to obtain a more robust method. The second-order accuracy is obtained by <lb/>introducing a flux-limited dissipation [36]. <lb/>Time integration is achieved using the dual time stepping approach and a <lb/>low-cost implicit method consisting in solving, at each time step, a system <lb/>of equations arising from the linearization of a fully implicit scheme. The <lb/>derivative with respect to the physical time is discretized by a second-order <lb/>formula. <lb/>The numerical treatment of boundary conditions is based on the use of the <lb/>preconditioned characteristic relationships. More details are given in [19]. <lb/> 3. The OpenFOAM code <lb/> The OpenFOAM code is an open source code distributed by ESI Group. It <lb/>is based on an orientated object framework [37]. It provides a large variety of <lb/>RANS turbulence models and cavitation models. For cavitation modelling, <lb/>two ways are available: either to use an equation of state for the mixture or <lb/>to use a transport equation for the volume fraction of liquid. The last one is <lb/>retained for the present simulation. <lb/> 3.1. Cavitation model <lb/> The cavitation model reads: <lb/> @AE  l <lb/> @t <lb/> + u  j <lb/> @AE  l <lb/> @x  j <lb/> = S <lb/> (20) <lb/>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			where AE  l  is the volume fraction of liquid and S is the mass source term. <lb/>Following Kunz development [10], the source term is expressed as the sum of <lb/>a vaporisation term m  v  and a condensation term m  c  : <lb/> S = m  v  + m  c <lb/> (21) <lb/>with: <lb/> m  c  = <lb/> Ω <lb/>Ω  l  Ω  v <lb/> C  c <lb/> Ω  v <lb/> t  1 <lb/> AE  2 <lb/> Llim <lb/> max (P ° P  vap  ; 0) <lb/>max (P ° P  vap  ; 0.01 P  vap  ) <lb/>(22) <lb/> m  v  = <lb/> Ω <lb/>Ω  l  Ω  v <lb/> C  v <lb/> Ω  v <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> Ω  l  U  2 <lb/> 1  t  1 <lb/> min (P ° P  vap  ; P  0  ) <lb/>( 2 3 ) <lb/> C  c  , C  v  , U  1  and t  1  are constant set by the user, whereas P  0  and AE  Llim  are <lb/>included to avoid non physical values. Usually U  1  is set to the freestream <lb/>value, and t  1  represents a relaxation time not well defined in the literature. <lb/>For the present computations, the following values are specified: <lb/> C  c  = 10 ; C  v  = 8000 ; U  1  = 10.8 m/s ; t  1  = 0.005 s <lb/> (24) <lb/>The model uncertainty should be analyzed using non-intrusive stochastic <lb/>methods as presented in [38]. <lb/> 3.2. The turbulence model <lb/> The k ° ! SST model proposed by Menter [32] is used to solve the turbulent <lb/>kinetic energy and the specific dissipation with the standard values of the <lb/>diAEerent parameters. <lb/> 3.3. Numerics <lb/> The time derivatives are computed with the backward second order scheme. <lb/>Excepted for the volume fraction of liquid, the convective flux are discretised <lb/>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			with the Total Variation Diminishing (TVD) scheme named &apos;limitedLinear&apos; <lb/>specific to OpenFOAM with the parameter set to 1. <lb/>Whereas the momentum equation and the Poisson equation are treated im-<lb/>plicitly, the equation for the volume fraction of liquid is treated explicitly and <lb/>separately. To maintain the boundedness of the liquid volume fraction, the <lb/>Multidimensional Universal Limiter for Explicit Solution (MULES) is used <lb/>and a counter-gradient is introduced to reduce the diAEusion of the interface <lb/>and enhanced the numerical stability. The convective flux of the transport <lb/>equation for the volume fraction of liquid is computed with the van Leer <lb/>scheme. <lb/>The set of equation is solved using a prediction-correction approach coupling <lb/>the SIMPLE and PISO algorithm. <lb/> 4. Experimental and numerical parameters <lb/> 4.1. Experimental conditions <lb/> The Venturi was tested in the cavitation tunnel of the CREMHyG (Centre <lb/>d&apos;Essais de Machines Hydrauliques de Grenoble). It is characterized by a <lb/>divergence angle of 4  ±  , illustrated in Figure 1. The edge forming the throat <lb/>of the Venturi is used to fix the separation point of the cavitation cavity. <lb/>This geometry is equipped with five probing holes to allow various mea-<lb/>surements such as the local void ratio, instantaneous local speed and wall <lb/>pressure (Figure 1). The velocity is evaluated as the most probable value <lb/>and the void ratio is obtained from the signal of the double optical probe <lb/>using a post-processing algorithm. The relative uncertainty on the void ratio <lb/>measurement was estimated at roughly 15% [39]. <lb/>
			
			<page>13 <lb/></page> 
			
			The selected operating point is characterized by the following physical pa-<lb/>rameters [39]: <lb/> U  inlet  = 10.8 m/s, the inlet velocity <lb/> ae  inlet  = <lb/> P  inlet  ° P  vap <lb/> 0.5ΩU  2 <lb/> inlet <lb/> &apos; 0.55, the cavitation parameter in the inlet section <lb/> T  ref  &apos; 293K, the reference temperature <lb/> L  ref  =252 mm, the reference length <lb/> Re  L  ref  = <lb/> U  inlet  L  ref <lb/> ∫ <lb/> = 2.7 10  6  , the Reynolds number <lb/>With these parameters, a cavity length L ranging from 70 mm to 85 mm was <lb/>obtained. The experimental views for this geometry show a relatively stable <lb/>cavity behaviour (see Fig. 2). The attached cavity length corresponding to <lb/>the end of the re-entrant jet is around 30-35 mm. For this geometry, no <lb/>periodic cycles with large shedding were observed. <lb/> 4.2. Mesh and numerical parameters <lb/> The grid is a H-type topology. It contains 251 nodes in the flow direction <lb/>and 62 nodes in the orthogonal direction. A special contraction of the mesh <lb/>is applied in the main flow direction just after the throat to better simulate <lb/>the two-phase flow area. The y  +  values of the mesh, at the center of the first <lb/>cell, vary between 12 and 27 for a non cavitating computation. <lb/>Unsteady computations are performed with the dual time stepping method <lb/>and are started from the non cavitating numerical solution. The numerical <lb/>parameters are: <lb/>-the dimensionless time step, ¢t  §  = <lb/> ¢tU  inlet <lb/> L  ref <lb/> = 4.88 10  °3 <lb/> -sub-iterations of the dual time stepping method, 100 <lb/>
			
			<page>14 <lb/></page> 
			
			- the CFL number, 0.2 <lb/>-Jacobi iterations for the implicit stage, 15 <lb/>-the two coe±cients of the artificial dissipation, k  (2)  = 1 and k  (4)  = 0.045. <lb/> 5. Computational results <lb/> Various computations were performed by varying the cavitation model and <lb/>the turbulence model, summarized in Table (1). The goal was to obtain a <lb/>sheet whose time-averaged attached and total length varied around 30-35 <lb/>mm and 75-85 mm, respectively. The time of simulation is between 2 and <lb/>3 s. <lb/> 5.1. Limitation of the eddy viscosity <lb/> A key point to compute the unsteadiness of the cavitation pocket is linked to <lb/>the over-production of eddy viscosity by standard turbulence models. Previ-<lb/>ous simulations based on a three-equation model illustrated the importance <lb/>of using an eddy-viscosity limiter to capture the re-entrant jet dynamics [30]. <lb/>In this study, the Reboud limiter is added to the turbulence model. The <lb/>eAEect of this limiter using the Spalart-Allmaras is showed in Figure 3 where <lb/>are plotted the contours of the density gradient modulus (Schlieren-like vi-<lb/>sualizations). When the turbulent viscosity is reduced by the correction, the <lb/>length of attached cavity reaches the experimental value around 0.35 m and <lb/>vapour clouds appear. <lb/>We observed the same eAEect for other turbulence models and results are not <lb/>presented. <lb/>
			
			<page>15 <lb/></page> 
			
			5.2. Turbulence models comparison <lb/> Computations are done using the four-equation barotropic model associated <lb/>to three turbulence models in which the Reboud limiter is added. All nu-<lb/>merical values are obtained by a time-averaged statistical treatment over a <lb/>simulation time of 2 s. <lb/>Fig. 4 presents the void ratio and velocity profiles from stations 3 to 5. At <lb/>stations 1 and 2, inside the attached cavity, all simulations provide the same <lb/>results in close agreement with the experimental data and are not presented. <lb/>At station 3, the re-entrant jet is observed on the velocity measurement. All <lb/>simulations indicate a recirculating behaviour with a re-entrant jet extend-<lb/>ing through half the sheet thickness. For the void ratio profiles, the three <lb/>simulations give very close results. <lb/>At station 4 and 5 the whole of simulation capture the re-entrant jet charac-<lb/>terized by negative velocitites close to the wall. As regard to the void ratio <lb/>profiles, we observe an over-estimation at station 4 using the k ° ¡ models <lb/>and a better estimation using the Spalart-Allmaras model. At station 5, the <lb/> k ° ` turbulence model overestimates a little the length of the cavity. <lb/>The dimensionless wall pressure distribution  P °P  vap <lb/> Pvap <lb/> is plotted in Figure 5 <lb/>versus the distance x ° x  inlet  . The first five data are located inside the cavity <lb/>(where the void ratio and velocity profiles are measured). All models provide <lb/>a pressure distribution similar to the experimental measurements upstream <lb/>of the re-compression. <lb/>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			The Root Mean Square (RMS) wall pressure fluctuations are plotted in Fig-<lb/>ure 6 versus the distance x ° x  inlet  . The pressure fluctuation is divided by <lb/>the time-averaged pressure P av. Experimental data indicate an augmenta-<lb/>tion of pressure fluctuations at the end of the sheet cavity. All simulations <lb/>predict a peak of pressure fluctuations located close to the experimental ab-<lb/>scissa. The magnitude of the peak is overestimated by the computations, <lb/>but with the lack of experimental values in this area the comparison cannot <lb/>be precise. Nevertheless, downstream the cavity, the pressure fluctuations <lb/>are over-predicted using the Spalart-Allmaras and k ° &quot; turbulence models. <lb/>This phenomenon has already been observed in a previous study and can be <lb/>corrected by modifying the source term in the void ratio equation [19]. <lb/>The dynamic of cavitation pocket is also studied with the iso-lines of the Q-<lb/>criterion. Positive values of the Q-criterion, defined as the second invariant <lb/>of the velocity gradient tensor  @u  i <lb/> @x  j <lb/> [40], <lb/> Q = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> &quot; µ @u  i <lb/> @x  i <lb/> ∂  2 <lb/> ° <lb/> @u  i <lb/> @x  j <lb/> @u  j <lb/> @x  i <lb/> # <lb/> (25) <lb/>are used to identify vortices and local rotational areas. A dimensionless quan-<lb/>tity is built using the inlet velocity and the reference length. Iso-lines levels <lb/>vary between 0.005 and 0.1. The results are illustrated in Figure 7. For <lb/>all turbulence models, the shear layer creates vortical clouds of cavitation, <lb/>which are convected by the mean flow. No significant discrepancies on the <lb/>flow dynamic are noticeable between the three simulations. <lb/>To conclude, similar results have been obtained with the three turbulence <lb/>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			models associated to an eddy viscosity limiter. The re-entrant jet is well <lb/>estimated but vapour ratio tends to be overestimated especially in the re-<lb/>circulating area (station 3 and 4). The influence of the turbulence model is <lb/>weak for this partial cavitation pocket. <lb/>In the next part, a mixture of stiAEened gas EOS is proposed to replace the <lb/>barotropic EOS and to investigate the cavitation model influence. <lb/> 5.3. Cavitation models comparison <lb/> For this study, the Spalart-Allmaras turbulence model is chosen and the two <lb/>formulations of 4-equation model are compared. <lb/>The dynamic of the cavitation sheets is proposed in Figure 8 where the con-<lb/>tours of the density gradient modulus are presented at two diAEerent times. <lb/>Both simulations propose similar dynamics and the generation of vapour <lb/>cloud shedding are clearly illustrated. <lb/>A more precise comparison is led by studying void ratio and velocity profiles, <lb/>which are presented in Figure 9 from stations 3 to 5. At region of attached <lb/>cavity sheet (stations 1 and 2), both simulations provide a well estimation of <lb/>the cavity thickness and results are not presented. <lb/>DiAEerences appear at station 3 where the four-equation SG cavitation model <lb/>provides a better prediction of the void ratio profile characterized by a sig-<lb/>nificant decrease close to the wall. However, by comparison with the exper-<lb/>imental data and the four-equation barotropic velocity profiles, this model <lb/>underestimates the recirculating flow in this area. At stations 4 and 5 the <lb/>four-equation SG cavitation model also reproduces the re-entrant jet on the <lb/>
			
			<page>18 <lb/></page> 
			
			half bottom of the cavity but it over-predicts the vapour ratio in the remain-<lb/>ing part. The wall value of the void ratio is better simulated with the new <lb/>model. <lb/>As it can be observed in Figure 10 both models give a time-averaged wall <lb/>pressure distribution in good agreement with the experimental data. The <lb/>Root Mean Square (RMS) wall pressure fluctuations are plotted in Figure 11. <lb/>Both models predict a similar peak intensity at the same location. It appears <lb/>that the four-equation SG cavitation model provides a better estimation of <lb/>the pressure fluctuations decrease in the re-compression area. <lb/>This study reveals that the four-equation SG cavitation is well adapted to <lb/>simulate the behaviour of the cavitation pocket especially in the closure part <lb/>of the cavity. Moreover, this model presents the large advantage to not <lb/>involve tunable parameters. In the next part, this model will be used to <lb/>compare the LEGI&apos;s and OpenFOAM softwares. <lb/> 5.4. Comparison with OpenFOAM simulations <lb/> Comparisons between the LEGI solver and OpenFOAM are proposed on a <lb/>similar mesh using the k ° ! SST turbulence model. The considered cavita-<lb/>tion models are the 4-equation SG model and the Kunz model, respectively. <lb/>The time of simulation is about 2 s. <lb/>Time-averaged void ratio and velocity profiles are presented in Figure 12 from <lb/>stations 1 to 5. Inside the attached cavity sheet, at stations 1 and 2, the both <lb/>solvers estimate a well cavity thickness and composition. At stations 3 and <lb/>
			
			<page>19 <lb/></page> 
			
			4, the LEGI solver provides a better prediction of the void ratio decrease <lb/>due to the presence of a mixture in this area. The OpenFOAM computation <lb/>over-predicts the vapour quantity inside the cavity (95% instead of 70% at <lb/>station 3 and 90% instead of 30% at station 3). Moreover, the thickness of <lb/>the cavity is under-estimated and a pure liquid phase is simulated close to <lb/>the wall. At station 5, both the cavity thickness and the re-entrant jet are <lb/>badly simulated by the OpenFOAM software. Although the re-entrant phe-<lb/>nomenon is well observed in experiments, the OpenFOAM simulation does <lb/>not reproduce the recirculation area. <lb/>The time-averaged wall pressure distributions are compared in Figure 13. <lb/>The two models present a diAEerent re-compression area respectively located <lb/>downstream the experimental measures with the LEGI solver and upstream <lb/>with the OpenFOAM solver. The rate of re-compression is also under-<lb/>estimated by the OpenFOAM solver. <lb/>A study of the Root Mean Square (RMS) wall pressure fluctuations is pro-<lb/>posed in Figure 14. The peak of fluctuations position is varying among the <lb/>case. The OpenFOAM solver provides a maximum of fluctuations located <lb/>upstream the closure area of the cavity sheet (x ° x  i  º 0.2 in experiments), <lb/>whereas it is predicted downstream by the LEGI solver. <lb/>To conclude, the topology of the cavitation pocket marks large discrepancies <lb/>between the two softwares, especially as regards the re-entrant jet develop-<lb/>ment. Maybe a better calibration of the production and evaporation con-<lb/>
			
			<page>20 <lb/></page> 
			
			stants appearing in the mass transfer formulation should improve the results <lb/>for this test case. <lb/> 6. Conclusion <lb/> An aperiodic partial cavitation pocket has been studied in a 2D venturi con-<lb/>figuration by numerical one-fluid unsteady RANS simulations. Numerical <lb/>results have been compared with experimental data concerning the void ra-<lb/>tio, streamwise velocity, wall pressure and wall pressure fluctuations. <lb/>First, calculations have been carried out with an in-house code. The one-fluid <lb/>RANS equations have been successively coupled with the Smith k ° `, the <lb/>Spalart-Allmaras, the Jones-Launder k ° &quot; and the Menter k ° ! SST tur-<lb/>bulence models. Two cavitation models using an explicit formulation of the <lb/>mass transfer between phases have also been compared: the first one based <lb/>on a barotropic EOS and the second one based on a mixture of stiAEened gas <lb/>EOS. Comparisons revealed that similar results were obtained using diAEerent <lb/>turbulence models when an eddy viscosity limiter is introduced. For this test <lb/>case, the turbulence model influence is weak. Then, a cavitation model com-<lb/>parison was performed using the Spalart-Allmaras turbulence model. The <lb/>new four-equation model has improved the re-entrant jet simulation down-<lb/>stream the attached cavity by diminishing the void ratio values close to the <lb/>wall. A better estimation of the pressure fluctuations is also provided by this <lb/>model. A very positive point is the free-parameter formulation of the source <lb/>term, which avoids poisonous calibration problems. <lb/>Secondly, simulations has been carried out with the OpenFOAM software us-<lb/>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			ing another formulation of void ratio transport equation cavitation models. <lb/>Calculations were performed on a similar mesh using the Menter SST tur-<lb/>bulence model. Large discrepancies appeared between the two solvers and <lb/>the OpenFOAM simulations were not able to reproduce the re-entrant jet <lb/>phenomenon. Maybe it is due to a calibration problem of the mass transfer <lb/>model involving two tunable parameters. The new LEGI model is therefore <lb/>very attractive to simulate such partial cavitation pockets. <lb/>Additional works are in progress to pursue comparative analyses between <lb/>turbulence and cavitation models and to extend the formulation with ther-<lb/>modynamic eAEects. <lb/> Appendix <lb/> Appendix A: the speed of sound in a mixture of stiAEened gas <lb/> Starting from the usual thermodynamic relation <lb/> de = T ds + <lb/> P <lb/> Ω  2  dΩ <lb/> or <lb/> d(Ωe) = ΩT ds + hdΩ <lb/> (26) <lb/>And with the diAEerential of Ωe: <lb/> d(Ωe) = <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∂ <lb/> P <lb/> dΩ + <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/>@P <lb/> ∂ <lb/> Ω <lb/> dP <lb/> (27) <lb/>We can obtain the diAEerential of the pressure P : <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/>@P <lb/> ∂ <lb/> Ω <lb/> dP = ΩT ds + <lb/> ∑ <lb/> h ° <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∂ <lb/> P <lb/> ∏ <lb/> dΩ <lb/> (28) <lb/>We deduce an expression of the speed of sound: <lb/> c  2  = <lb/> µ @P <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∂ <lb/> s <lb/> = <lb/> h ° <lb/> ≥ <lb/> @Ωe <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ¥ <lb/> P <lb/> °  @Ωe <lb/>@P <lb/> ¢ <lb/> Ω <lb/> (29) <lb/>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			With the stiAEened gas EOS, we have: <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/> @P <lb/> ∂ <lb/> Ω <lb/> = AE <lb/> µ @Ω  v  e  v <lb/> @P <lb/> ∂ <lb/> Ω <lb/> + (1 ° AE) <lb/> µ @Ω  l  e  l <lb/> @P <lb/> ∂ <lb/> Ω <lb/> = <lb/>1 <lb/> ∞ ° 1 <lb/> µ @Ωe <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∂ <lb/> P <lb/> = <lb/> @ <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∑ <lb/> AE <lb/> µ P <lb/> ∞  v  ° 1 <lb/>+ Ω  v  q  v  + <lb/> ∞  v  P  v <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∞  v  ° 1 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> + (1 ° AE) <lb/> µ P <lb/> ∞  l  ° 1 <lb/>+ Ω  l  q  l  + <lb/> ∞  l  P  l <lb/> 1 <lb/> ∞  l  ° 1 <lb/> ∂∏ <lb/> = <lb/> Ω  l  h  l  ° Ω  v  h  v <lb/> Ω  v  ° Ω  v <lb/> Finally, the speed of sound is: <lb/> Ωc  2  = Ω <lb/> µ @P <lb/>@Ω <lb/> ∂ <lb/> s <lb/> = (∞ ° 1) <lb/> ∑ Ω  v  Ω  l <lb/> (Ω  l  ° Ω  v  ) <lb/>(h  v  ° h  l  ) <lb/> ∏ <lb/> (30) <lb/></body>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> [1] D. Schmidt, C. Rutland, M. Corradini, A fully compressible, two-<lb/>dimensional model of small, high-speed, cavitating nozzles, Atomization <lb/>and Sprays 9 (1999) 255–276. <lb/>[2] T. Liu, B. Khoo, W. Xie, Isentropic one-fluid modelling of unsteady <lb/>cavitating flow, Journal of Computational Physics 201 (1) (2004) 80– <lb/>108. <lb/>[3] T. Barberon, P. Helluy, Finite volume simulation of cavitating flows, <lb/>Computers &amp; Fluids 34 (7) (2005) 832–858. <lb/>[4] E. Sinibaldi, F. Beux, M. Salvetti, A numerical method for 3D barotropic <lb/>flows in turbomachinery, Flow Turbulence Combustion 76 (2006) 371– <lb/>381. <lb/>[5] S. Schmidt, I. Sezal, G. Schnerr, Compressible simulation of high-speed <lb/>hydrodynamics with phase change, in: European Conference on Com-<lb/>putational Fluid Dynamics ECCOMAS 2006, Delft, The Netherlands, <lb/>2006. <lb/>[6] W. Xie, T. Liu, B. Khoo, Application of a one-fluid model for large <lb/>scale homogeneous unsteady cavitation: The modified Schmidt model, <lb/>Computers &amp; Fluids 35 (2006) 1177–1192. <lb/>[7] E. Goncalves, R. F. Patella, Numerical simulation of cavitating flows <lb/>with homogeneous models, Computers &amp; Fluids 38 (9) (2009) 1682– <lb/>1696. <lb/>[8] M. Bilanceri, F. Beux, M. Salvetti, An implicit low-diAEusive HLL scheme <lb/>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			with complete time linearization: application to cavitating barotropic <lb/>flows, Computers &amp; Fluids 39 (2010) 1990–2006. <lb/>[9] C. Merkle, J. Feng, P. Buelow, Computation modeling of the dynam-<lb/>ics of sheet cavitation, in: 3  rd  International Symposium on Cavitation <lb/>CAV1998, Grenoble, France, 1998. <lb/>[10] R. Kunz, D. Boger, D. Stinebring, T. Chyczewski, J. Lindau, H. Gibel-<lb/>ing, S. Venkateswaran, T. Govindan, A preconditioned Navier-Stokes <lb/>method for two-phase flows with application to cavitation prediction, <lb/>Computers &amp; Fluids 29 (8) (2000) 849–875. <lb/>[11] G. Schnerr, J. Sauer, Physical and numerical modeling of unsteady cav-<lb/>itation dynamics, in: 4th Int. Conference on Multiphase Flow ICMF01, <lb/>New Orleans, USA, 2001. <lb/>[12] I. Senocak, W. Shyy, A pressure-based method for turbulent cavitating <lb/>flow computations, Journal of Computational Physics 176 (2) (2002) <lb/>363–383. <lb/>[13] A. Singhal, M. Athavale, H. Li, Y. Jiang, Mathematical basis and vali-<lb/>dation of the full cavitation model, Journal of Fluids Engineering 124 (3) <lb/>(2002) 617–624. <lb/>[14] Y. Utturkar, J. Wu, G. Wang, W. Shyy, Recent progress in modelling of <lb/>cryogenic cavitation for liquid rocket propulsion, Progress in Aerospace <lb/>Sciences 41 (2005) 558–608. <lb/>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			[15] E. Goncalves, R. F. Patella, Constraints on equation of state for cavitat-<lb/>ing flows with thermodynamic eAEects, Applied Math. and Computation <lb/>217 (2011) 5095–5102. <lb/>[16] P. Downar-Zapolski, Z. Bilicki, L. Bolle, J. Franco, The non-equilibrium <lb/>relaxation model for one-dimensional flashing liquid flow, Int. Journal <lb/>of Multiphase Flow 22 (3) (1996) 473–483. <lb/>[17] P. Helluy, N. Seguin, Relaxation models of phase transition flows, Math-<lb/>ematical Modelling and Numerical Analysis 40 (2) (2006) 331–352. <lb/>[18] E. Goncalves, Numerical study of expansion tube problems: Toward the <lb/>simulation of cavitation, Computers &amp; Fluids 72 (2013) 1–19. <lb/>[19] E. Goncalves, B. Charriere, Modelling for isothermal cavitation with a <lb/>four-equation model, International Journal of Multiphase Flow 59 (2014) <lb/>54–72. <lb/>[20] R. Bensow, G. Bark, Simulating cavitating flows with LES in openfoam, <lb/>in: V ECCOMAS CFD, Lisbon, Portugal, June 2010. <lb/>[21] S. Park, S. Rhee, Computational analysis of turbulent super-cavitating <lb/>flow around a two-dimensional wedge-shaped cavitator geometry, Com-<lb/>puters &amp; Fluids 70 (2012) 73–85. <lb/>[22] Z. Shang, Numerical investigations of supercavitation around blunt bod-<lb/>ies of submarine shape, Applied Mathematical Modelling 37 (2013) <lb/>8836–8845. <lb/>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			[23] J. Decaix, E. Goncalves, Compressible eAEects modelling in turbulent <lb/>cavitating flows, European J. of Mechanics B/Fluids 39 (2013) 11–31. <lb/>[24] R. Saurel, F. Petitpas, R. Abgrall, Modelling phase transition in <lb/>metastable liquids: application to cavitating and flashing flows, Journal <lb/>of Fluid Mechanics 607 (2008) 313–350. <lb/>[25] G. Wallis, One-dimensional two-phase flow, New York: McGraw-Hill <lb/>(1967). <lb/>[26] B. Smith, A near wall model for the k°l two equation turbulence model, <lb/>in: AIAA 94–2386, 25  sh  Fluid Dynamics Conference – Colorado Springs, <lb/>Colorado, 1994. <lb/>[27] P. Spalart, S. Allmaras, A one-equation turbulence model for aerody-<lb/>namic flows, La Recherche Aérospatiale (1) (1994) 5–21. <lb/>[28] W. Jones, B. Launder, The prediction of laminarization with a two-<lb/>equation model of turbulence, Int. J. Heat and Mass Transfer 15 (1972) <lb/>301–314. <lb/>[29] J.-L. Reboud, B. Stutz, O. Coutier, Two-phase flow structure of cavita-<lb/>tion: experiment and modelling of unsteady eAEects, in: 3  rd  International <lb/>Symposium on Cavitation CAV1998, Grenoble, France, 1998. <lb/>[30] E. Goncalves, Numerical study of unsteady turbulent cavitating flows, <lb/>European Journal of Mechanics B/Fluids 30 (1) (2011) 26–40. <lb/>[31] J. Decaix, E. Goncalves, Time-dependent simulation of cavitating flow <lb/>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			 with k ° ` turbulence models, Int. Journal for Numerical Methods in <lb/>Fluids 68 (2012) 1053–1072. <lb/>[32] F. Menter, Two-equation eddy-viscosity turbulence models for engineer-<lb/>ing applications, AIAA Journal 32 (8) (1994) 1598–1605. <lb/>[33] E. Goncalves, J. Decaix, Wall model and mesh influence study for partial <lb/>cavities, European Journal of Mechanics B/Fluids 31 (1) (2012) 12–29. <lb/>[34] A. Jameson, W. Schmidt, E. Turkel, Numerical solution of the Euler <lb/>equations by finite volume methods using Runge-Kutta time stepping <lb/>schemes, in: AIAA Paper 81–1259, 1981. <lb/>[35] P. Roe, Approximate Riemann solvers, parameters vectors, and diAEer-<lb/>ence schemes, Journal of Computational Physics 43 (1981) 357–372. <lb/>[36] S. Tatsumi, L. Martinelli, A. Jameson, Flux-limited schemes for the <lb/>compressible Navier-Stokes equations, AIAA Journal 33 (2) (1995) 252– <lb/>261. <lb/>[37] H. Weller, G. Tabor, H. Jasak, C. Fureby, A tensorial approach to <lb/>computational continuum mechanics using objected-oriented techniques, <lb/>Computers in Physics 12 (1998) 620–631. <lb/>[38] M. Rodio, P. Congedo, Robust analysis of cavitating flows in Venturi <lb/>tube, European J. of Mechanics B/Fluids in press. <lb/>[39] S. Barre, J. Rolland, G. Boitel, E. Goncalves, R. F. Patella, Experiments <lb/>and modelling of cavitating flows in Venturi: attached sheet cavitation, <lb/>European Journal of Mechanics B/Fluids 28 (2009) 444–464. <lb/>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			[40] J. Hunt, C. Wray, P. Moin, Eddies, streams, and convergence zones in <lb/>turbulent flows, Tech. rep., Center for Turbulence Research, CTR-S88 <lb/>(1988). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1: Unsteady computations, 4  ±  Venturi. <lb/> cav. model turb. model <lb/> ae  inlet  attached and total sheet length (m) <lb/>4-eqt baro SA <lb/>0.59 <lb/>0.09 -0.11 <lb/>4-eqt baro SA + Reboud 0.60 <lb/>0.035 -0.076 <lb/>4-eqt baro KL + Reboud 0.61 <lb/>0.038 -0.085 <lb/>4-eqt baro KE + Reboud 0.61 <lb/>0.029 -0.078 <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>SA + Reboud 0.575 <lb/>0.038 -0.085 <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>KW SST <lb/>0.595 <lb/>0.030 -0.10 <lb/>4-eqt Foam KW SST <lb/>0.585 <lb/>0.070 <lb/>
			
			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			Figure 1: Schematic view of the 4  ±  Venturi profile. <lb/>

			<page> 31 <lb/></page>

			Figure 2: Photograph of the cavitation pocket. <lb/>

			<page> 32 <lb/></page>

			Figure 3: Contours of the density gradient modulus, without limiter (top) and with limiter <lb/>(bottom). <lb/>

			<page> 33 <lb/></page>

			alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/> SA <lb/>KL <lb/>KE <lb/>EXPE <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> SA <lb/>KL <lb/>KE <lb/>EXPE <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> Figure 4: Time-averaged velocity (right) and void ratio (left) profiles from station 3 to 5, <lb/>4-equation barotropic model. <lb/>

			<page> 34 <lb/></page>

			x-x  i (m) <lb/>(P-Pvap)/Pvap <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> 0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>SA <lb/>KL <lb/>KE <lb/> Figure 5: Dimensionless time-averaged wall pressure evolution, 4-equation barotropic <lb/>model. <lb/>

			<page> 35 <lb/></page>

			 x-x  i (m) <lb/>P&apos; rms / Pav <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>SA <lb/>KL <lb/>KE <lb/> Figure 6: RMS wall pressure fluctuations, 4-equation barotropic model. <lb/>

			<page> 36 <lb/></page>

			 x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.04 <lb/> SA model <lb/> x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.04 <lb/> KL model <lb/>KE model <lb/> Figure 7: Isolines of the dimensionless Q-criterion. Turbulence models comparison, 4-<lb/>equation barotropic model. <lb/>

			<page> 37 <lb/></page>

			x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Grad-rho: 5000 21111.1 37222.2 53333.3 69444.4 85555.6 101667 117778 133889 150000 <lb/> x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Grad-rho: 5000 21111.1 37222.2 53333.3 69444.4 85555.6 101667 117778 133889 150000 <lb/> x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Grad-rho: 5000 21111.1 37222.2 53333.3 69444.4 85555.6 101667 117778 133889 150000 <lb/> x(m) <lb/> y(m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>Grad-rho: 5000 21111.1 37222.2 53333.3 69444.4 85555.6 101667 117778 133889 150000 <lb/> Figure 8: Density gradient modulus (kg.m  °4  ) for 4-eqt SG model (left) and 4-eqt <lb/>barotropic model (right) <lb/>

			<page> 38 <lb/></page>

			alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/> 4-eqt baro <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>EXPE <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> 4-eqt baro <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>EXPE <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> Figure 9: Time-averaged velocity (right) and void ratio (left) profiles from station 3 to 5, <lb/>4-equation models comparison. <lb/>

			<page> 39 <lb/></page>

			 x-x  i (m) <lb/>(P-Pvap)/Pvap <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> 0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>4-eqt baro <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/> Figure 10: Dimensionless time-averaged wall pressure evolution, 4-equation models com-<lb/>parison. <lb/>

			<page> 40 <lb/></page>

			x-x  i (m) <lb/>P&apos; rms / Pav <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>4-eqt baro <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/> Figure 11: RMS wall pressure fluctuations, 4-equation models comparison. <lb/>

			<page> 41 <lb/></page>

			alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.0015 <lb/>0.002 <lb/> 4-eqt SG <lb/>OpenFOAM <lb/>EXPE <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.0005 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.0015 <lb/>0.002 <lb/> 4-eqt SG <lb/>OpenFOAM <lb/>EXPE <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> alpha <lb/> y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> U (m/s) <lb/>y (m) <lb/> 0 <lb/> 5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.004 <lb/>0.006 <lb/>0.008 <lb/>0.01 <lb/> Figure 12: Time-averaged velocity (right) and void ratio (left) profiles from station 1 to <lb/>5, LEGI solver versus openFOAM. <lb/>

			<page> 42 <lb/></page>

			x-x  i (m) <lb/>(P-Pvap)/Pvap <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> 0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>openFOAM <lb/> Figure 13: Dimensionless time-averaged wall pressure evolution, LEGI solver versus open-<lb/>FOAM. <lb/>

			<page> 43 <lb/></page>

			x-x  i (m) <lb/>P&apos; rms / Pav <lb/> 0.15 <lb/> 0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/> EXPE <lb/>4-eqt SG <lb/>openFOAM <lb/> Figure 14: RMS wall pressure fluctuations, LEGI solver versus openFOAM. <lb/></body>

			<page> 44 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
