<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>AUTOPHAGY <lb/>COPII vesicles and the <lb/>expansion of the phagophore <lb/>A new study has identified the proteins that adapt COPII vesicles to the <lb/>needs of starving cells. <lb/>CATHERINE RABOUILLE <lb/></front>

			<body>W <lb/>hen a cell is starving, it can recycle <lb/>cytoplasmic elements that are dis-<lb/>pensable or faulty to obtain the <lb/>amino acids and nutrients it needs to survive. <lb/>This process, known as autophagy, is orches-<lb/>trated by more than 40 different proteins <lb/>(Mizushima et al., 2011). It starts with the for-<lb/>mation of the phagophore, a flat membrane-<lb/>bound structure that expands and engulfs the <lb/>components destined for digestion. Although <lb/>the membrane of many organelles -including <lb/>the Golgi apparatus -can be the source of the <lb/>phagophore, the structure appears to largely <lb/>emerge from the endoplasmic reticulum (ER). It <lb/>has recently also become clear that the early <lb/>expansion of the phagophore requires vesicles <lb/>coated with a protein complex called <lb/>COPII, hereafter referred to as COPII <lb/>vesicles (reviewed in van Leeuwen et al., 2018). <lb/>Cells with plenty of nutrients grow by produc-<lb/>ing proteins, and COPII vesicles are essential in <lb/>this process. They bud from ER exit sites and <lb/>transport newly synthesized proteins to the <lb/>Golgi and many other membrane compart-<lb/>ments. An array of molecules works together on <lb/> the membrane at the ER exit sites to form these <lb/>vesicles. Indeed, the transmembrane ER protein <lb/>Sec12 and the small GTPase Sar1 help to recruit <lb/>the Sec23/Sec24 complex that will create the <lb/>inner coat of the vesicle, while another complex, <lb/>Sec13/31, will then form the outer coat (Gomez-<lb/>Navarro and Miller, 2016). However, while <lb/>starving cells require COPII vesicles for <lb/>autophagy, cells deprived of nutrients reduce <lb/>their protein secretion (Jeong et al., <lb/>2018; Zacharogianni et al., 2014): in this con-<lb/>text, how can these vesicles be specifically gen-<lb/>erated to help expand the phagophore? <lb/>Several complementary models have been <lb/>put forward to explain how this could be possi-<lb/>ble. Some propose that once the COPII vesicles <lb/>have formed at the ER exit sites, they are redir-<lb/>ected away from the Golgi and towards the <lb/>nascent phagophore (Rao et al., 2016; <lb/>Tan et al., 2013; Davis et al., 2016; <lb/>Wang et al., 2015). Another model suggests <lb/>that in starving mammalian cells, instead of <lb/>being redirected, COPII vesicles bud from a dif-<lb/>ferent place altogether. Indeed, during starva-<lb/>tion, COPII vesicles emerge from a membrane <lb/>between the ER and the Golgi, the ER-Golgi <lb/>intermediate compartment (ERGIC). Autophagy <lb/>activates an enzyme, the kinase ULK1, which <lb/>drives this change by helping to relocate the <lb/>COPII protein Sec12 to the ERGIC (Ge et al., <lb/>2017). Once the vesicles have budded from this <lb/>structure, they go on to expand the phagophore <lb/>(Ge et al., 2015). Now, in eLife, Michele Pagano <lb/>and colleagues at New York University School of <lb/>Medicine, IBioBA in Buenos Aires and other <lb/>institutes in the United States and Argentina -<lb/>including Yeon-Tae Jeong as first author -report <lb/></body>

			<front>Copyright Rabouille. This article is <lb/>distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution <lb/>License, which permits unrestricted <lb/>use and redistribution provided that <lb/>the original author and source are <lb/>credited. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>Related research article Jeong YT, Simo-<lb/>neschi D, Keegan S, Melville D, Adler NS, <lb/>Saraf A, FlorensL, Washburn MP, Cavasotto <lb/>CN, Fenyo ¨D, Cuervo AM, Rossi M, Pagano <lb/>M. 2018. The ULK1-FBXW5-SEC23B nexus <lb/>controls autophagy. eLife 7:e42253. DOI: <lb/>10.7554/eLife.42253 <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Rabouille. eLife 2019;8:e44944. DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.44944 <lb/>1 of 3 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">INSIGHT <lb/></note>

			<body>results that support and expand this last model <lb/>(Jeong et al., 2018). <lb/>Combining state-of-the-art biochemistry with <lb/>imaging, Jeong et al. show that COPII vesicles <lb/>do indeed bud from the ERGIC during autoph-<lb/>agy. But the experiments also reveal that the <lb/>inner coat of these vesicles is different. When <lb/>cells are growing, an enzyme known as FBXW5 <lb/>tags Sec23B for destruction, and the protein is <lb/>then degraded slowly, but constantly. Under <lb/>these conditions, the remaining Sec23B proteins <lb/>may bind Sec24 and help form COPII vesicles <lb/>destined for secretion, but this is likely a small <lb/>contribution. <lb/>The study by Jeong et al. further reveals that <lb/>when starvation activates ULK1, the enzyme <lb/>then phosphorylates Sec23B to produce Sec23B-<lb/>P, which is impervious to FBXW5; Sec23B-P <lb/>starts to accumulate and bind to Sec24A and <lb/>Sec24B -but not Sec24C or Sec24D. The <lb/>Sec23B-P/Sec24AB complex then relocates to <lb/>the ERGIC (possibly as a direct consequence of <lb/>the phosphorylation of Sec23B), and it forms <lb/>COPII vesicles specifically destined to fuel the <lb/>growth of the phagophore. The beauty of these <lb/>experiments is thus to show that certain COPII <lb/>subunits have a clear, dedicated role during <lb/>autophagy, with Sec23B-P/Sec24AB playing a <lb/>key part in forming the vesicles required in this <lb/>process (Figure 1). It remains to be examined <lb/>whether Sec23B-P/Sec24AB also helps transport <lb/>proteins to the Golgi under starvation condi-<lb/>tions, when general secretion is reduced and the <lb/>complex is efficiently brought to the ERGIC. <lb/>While it is likely that the complex is specific to <lb/>autophagy, this would need to be further <lb/>investigated. <lb/>The work by Jeong et al. also helps to better <lb/>grasp how ULK1 controls the use of COPII pro-<lb/>teins during autophagy: the kinase helps to relo-<lb/>cate the machinery from ER exit sites to the <lb/>ERGIC, while also tweaking the nature of the <lb/>vesicles&apos; inner coat to fuel the early expansion of <lb/>the phagophore. These results add to work at <lb/>Berkeley, which showed how ULK1 participates <lb/>in bringing Sec12 to the ERGIC, initiating the <lb/>formation of COPII vesicles (Ge et al., 2015; <lb/>Ge et al., 2017). In yeast, ULK1 also contributes <lb/>to the recruitment of a protein that, once acti-<lb/>vated, will direct COPII vesicles to the phago-<lb/>phore assembly site (Wang et al., 2013). Next, <lb/>it will be interesting to learn how the enzyme <lb/>acts on other components of the ER exit sites -<lb/>including Sec16, a ULK1 substrate during peri-<lb/>ods of growth (Joo et al., 2016). <lb/>Figure 1. Autophagy starts with the production of special COPII vesicles. When cells are <lb/>growing (top), the E3 ligase FBXW5, which is associated with Cul1 and SKP1, tags Sec23B <lb/>(pink circle) with ubiquitin (Ub). This labels Sec23B for destruction by the cell. Starvation kick-<lb/>starts autophagy, whereby the cell recycles certain components in order to obtain amino <lb/>acids and nutrients. It also activates ULK1, a kinase that phosphorylates Sec23B (red circle) <lb/>on Serine 186, thus preventing FBXW5 from tagging it for destruction. Instead, Sec23B-P <lb/>associates with Sec24AB (green) to form a complex that is not recruited to the endoplasmic <lb/>reticulum exit sites (ERES; gray line), but to the ER-Golgi intermediate compartment (ERGIC; <lb/>black line). Another COPII protein, Sec12 (light blue), has also been relocated to this <lb/>structure. This creates special COPII vesicles (dark blue) that bud to fuel the growth of the <lb/>phagophore (violet structure) and autophagic activity. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Rabouille. eLife 2019;8:e44944. DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.44944 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Insight <lb/>Autophagy COPII vesicles and the expansion of the phagophore <lb/></note>

			<front>Catherine Rabouille is in the Hubrecht Institute, <lb/>Utrecht, and the Department of Biomedical Science of <lb/>Cells &amp; Systems, UMCG, Groningen, Netherlands <lb/>c.rabouille@hubrecht.eu <lb/>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3663-9717 <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests: The author declares that no <lb/>competing interests exist. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Davis S, Wang J, Zhu M, Stahmer K, Lakshminarayan <lb/>R, Ghassemian M, Jiang Y, Miller EA, Ferro-Novick S. <lb/>2016. Sec24 phosphorylation regulates <lb/>autophagosome abundance during nutrient <lb/>deprivation. eLife 5:e21167. DOI: https://doi.org/10. <lb/>7554/eLife.21167, PMID: 27855785 <lb/>Ge L, Zhang M, Schekman R. 2014. <lb/>Phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase and COPII generate LC3 <lb/>lipidation vesicles from the ER-Golgi intermediate <lb/>compartment. eLife 3:e04135. DOI: https://doi.org/10. <lb/>7554/eLife.04135, PMID: 25432021 <lb/>Ge L, Wilz L, Schekman R. 2015. Biogenesis of <lb/>autophagosomal precursors for LC3 lipidation from the <lb/>ER-Golgi intermediate compartment. Autophagy 11: <lb/>2372-2374. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1080/15548627. <lb/>2015.1105422, PMID: 26565421 <lb/>Ge L, Zhang M, Kenny SJ, Liu D, Maeda M, Saito K, <lb/>Mathur A, Xu K, Schekman R. 2017. Remodeling of ER-<lb/>exit sites initiates a membrane supply pathway for <lb/>autophagosome biogenesis. EMBO Reports 18:1586-<lb/>1603. DOI: https://doi.org/10.15252/embr.201744559, <lb/>PMID: 28754694 <lb/>Gomez-Navarro N, Miller E. 2016. Protein sorting at <lb/>the ER-Golgi interface. The Journal of Cell Biology <lb/>215:769-778. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb. <lb/>201610031, PMID: 27903609 <lb/>Jeong YT, Simoneschi D, Keegan S, Melville D, Adler <lb/>NS, Saraf A, Florens L, Washburn MP, Cavasotto CN, <lb/>Fenyo ¨D, Cuervo AM, Rossi M, Pagano M. 2018. The <lb/>ULK1-FBXW5-SEC23B nexus controls autophagy. eLife <lb/>7:e42253. DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.42253, <lb/>PMID: 30596474 <lb/>Joo JH, Wang B, Frankel E, Ge L, Xu L, Iyengar R, Li-<lb/>Harms X, Wright C, Shaw TI, Lindsten T, Green DR, <lb/>Peng J, Hendershot LM, Kilic F, Sze JY, Audhya A, <lb/>Kundu M. 2016. The noncanonical role of ULK/ATG1 in <lb/>ER-to-Golgi trafficking is essential for cellular <lb/>homeostasis. Molecular Cell 62:982. DOI: https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.molcel.2016.05.030, PMID: 27315557 <lb/>Mizushima N, Yoshimori T, Ohsumi Y. 2011. The role <lb/>of Atg proteins in autophagosome formation. Annual <lb/>Review of Cell and Developmental Biology 27:107-<lb/>132. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1146/annurev-cellbio-<lb/>092910-154005, PMID: 21801009 <lb/>Rao Y, Perna MG, Hofmann B, Beier V, Wollert T. <lb/>2016. The Atg1-kinase complex tethers Atg9-vesicles <lb/>to initiate autophagy. Nature Communications 7: <lb/>10338. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1038/ncomms10338, <lb/>PMID: 26753620 <lb/>Tan D, Cai Y, Wang J, Zhang J, Menon S, Chou HT, <lb/>Ferro-Novick S, Reinisch KM, Walz T. 2013. The EM <lb/>structure of the TRAPPIII complex leads to the <lb/>identification of a requirement for COPII vesicles on <lb/>the macroautophagy pathway. PNAS 110:19432-<lb/>19437. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>1316356110, PMID: 24218626 <lb/>van Leeuwen W, van der Krift F, Rabouille C. 2018. <lb/>Modulation of the secretory pathway by amino-acid <lb/>starvation. The Journal of Cell Biology 217:2261-2271. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201802003, PMID: 2 <lb/>9669743 <lb/>Wang J, Menon S, Yamasaki A, Chou HT, Walz T, <lb/>Jiang Y, Ferro-Novick S. 2013. Ypt1 recruits the Atg1 <lb/>kinase to the preautophagosomal structure. PNAS <lb/>110:9800-9805. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas. <lb/>1302337110, PMID: 23716696 <lb/>Wang J, Davis S, Menon S, Zhang J, Ding J, Cervantes <lb/>S, Miller E, Jiang Y, Ferro-Novick S. 2015. Ypt1/Rab1 <lb/>regulates Hrr25/CK1d kinase activity in ER-Golgi traffic <lb/>and macroautophagy. The Journal of Cell Biology 210: <lb/>273-285. DOI: https://doi.org/10.1083/jcb.201408075, <lb/>PMID: 26195667 <lb/>Zacharogianni M, Aguilera-Gomez A, Veenendaal T, <lb/>Smout J, Rabouille C. 2014. A stress assembly that <lb/>confers cell viability by preserving ERES components <lb/>during amino-acid starvation. eLife 3:04132. <lb/>DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.04132 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Rabouille. eLife 2019;8:e44944. DOI: https://doi.org/10.7554/eLife.44944 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Insight <lb/>Autophagy COPII vesicles and the expansion of the phagophore </note>

	</text>
</tei>
