<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>AAS Open Research <lb/>Open Peer Review <lb/>Discuss this article <lb/>(0) <lb/>Comments <lb/>OPEN LETTER <lb/>Model framework for governance of genomic research and <lb/>biobanking in Africa -a content description [version 1; referees: <lb/>3 approved] <lb/>Aminu Yakubu <lb/>, Paulina Tindana , Alice Matimba , Katherine Littler , <lb/>Nchangwi Syntia Munung , Ebony Madden , Ciara Staunton , Jantina De Vries 5 <lb/>Department of Health Planning, Research &amp; Statistics, Federal Ministry of Health, Abuja, Nigeria <lb/>Navrongo Health Research Centre, Ghana Health Service, Navrongo, Ghana <lb/>Wellcome Genome Campus Advanced Courses and Scientific Conferences, Cambridge, UK <lb/>Global Policy, Wellcome Trust, London, UK <lb/>Department of Medicine, University of Cape Town, Cape Town, South Africa <lb/>Division of Genomic Medicine, National Human Genome Research Institute, National Institutes of Health, Rockville, MD, USA <lb/>Law Department, Middlesex University, London, UK <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Genomic research and biobanking are expanding globally, with a promise to <lb/>fast-track the research needed to improve approaches to disease treatment <lb/>and prevention through scientific collaborations such as the Human Heredity <lb/>and Health in Africa (H3Africa) initiative. Integral to this type of research is the <lb/>availability of samples and data for research. The need for broad access brings <lb/>along a host of ethical concerns, including those related to privacy and <lb/>confidentiality, as well as fairness and equity in access and capacity to utilise <lb/>these samples between scientists from the high income and low income <lb/>countries. Addressing these concerns while promoting genomic research, <lb/>especially in Africa, requires the implementation of a sound governance <lb/>framework. In this paper, we describe the contents of a Framework for Best <lb/>Practice for Genomics Research and biobanking in Africa that was developed, <lb/>under the auspices of the H3Africa initiative. This framework is broad enough to <lb/>be used and adapted by African countries to facilitate the development of <lb/>country-specific guidelines and to help improve the conduct and governance of <lb/>genomics research. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>genomics research, biobanking, governance <lb/></front>

			1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>

			<front>Referee Status: <lb/>Invited Referees <lb/>version 1 <lb/>published <lb/>18 Apr 2018 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>report <lb/>report <lb/>report <lb/>, University of <lb/>Kieran O&apos;Doherty <lb/>Guelph, Canada <lb/>, University of Guelph, <lb/>Kim Chuong <lb/>Canada <lb/>1 <lb/>, Vanderbilt <lb/>Ellen Wright Clayton <lb/>University Medical Center (VUMC), USA <lb/>2 <lb/>, University of Tasmania, <lb/>Don Chalmers <lb/>Australia <lb/>3 <lb/>18 Apr 2018, :13 (doi: <lb/>) <lb/>First published: <lb/>1 <lb/>10.12688/aasopenres.12844.1 <lb/>18 Apr 2018, :13 (doi: <lb/>) <lb/>Latest published: <lb/>1 <lb/>10.12688/aasopenres.12844.1 <lb/>v1 <lb/></front>

			<page>Page 1 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<front>AAS Open Research <lb/>Aminu Yakubu ( <lb/>) <lb/>Corresponding author: <lb/>yakubu.aminu@gmail.com <lb/>: Conceptualization, Writing -Original Draft Preparation, Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Conceptualization, <lb/>Author roles: Yakubu A <lb/>Tindana P <lb/>Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>Matimba A <lb/>Littler K <lb/>Munung NS <lb/>: Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Writing -Review &amp; Editing; <lb/>: Conceptualization, Writing -Review &amp; Editing <lb/>Madden E <lb/>Staunton C <lb/>De Vries J <lb/>No competing interests were disclosed. <lb/>Competing interests: <lb/>Yakubu A, Tindana P, Matimba A <lb/>How to cite this article: <lb/>et al. Model framework for governance of genomic research and biobanking in <lb/>AAS Open Research 2018, :13 (doi: <lb/>) <lb/>Africa -a content description [version 1; referees: 3 approved] <lb/>1 <lb/>10.12688/aasopenres.12844.1 <lb/>© 2018 Yakubu A <lb/>. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>, which <lb/>Copyright: <lb/>et al <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution Licence <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>This work is supported by the Human Heredity and Health in Africa (H3Africa) in Partnership with the African Academy of <lb/>Grant information: <lb/>Sciences. The Framework drafting meeting was supported by a grant from the Wellcome Trust (WT201245/Z/16/Z). During the development of this <lb/>Framework, Jantina de Vries was supported by the RHDGen grant, a H3Africa grant funded by the Wellcome Trust (WT099313MA) and the <lb/>Stigma in African Genomics grant funded by the National Human Genome Research Institute of the National Institutes of Health under Award <lb/>Number U01HG008226. <lb/>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>18 Apr 2018, :13 (doi: <lb/>) <lb/>First published: <lb/>1 <lb/>10.12688/aasopenres.12844.1 <lb/></front>

			<page>Page 2 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The complete mapping of the human genome 1 brought along <lb/>with it possibilities to better understand human health and its <lb/>determinants which would help improve the way diseases and <lb/>health conditions are managed. Since then, the number of genomic <lb/>research studies and the need for biobanking has been growing <lb/>globally 2-4 , with a steady increase in the number of such studies <lb/>being conducted on the African continent 5 . Further scaling <lb/>up genomics research with samples and data from diverse <lb/>African populations 6 has great value considering that only a small <lb/>portion of human diversity is found outside Africa 7 . Towards <lb/>addressing this gap, a $76 million initiative referred to as <lb/>the Human Heredity and Health in Africa Initiative (H3Africa) <lb/>was funded jointly by the National Institutes of Health in <lb/>the US and Wellcome Trust in the UK 3 . In order to fast-track <lb/>realization of the benefits inherent in genomics research, the <lb/>global community agreed to principles of &apos;open science&apos;, which <lb/>promotes the value of sharing and reuse of data and samples as <lb/>a critical component of the contemporary scientific landscape 8-10 . <lb/>Although this has the strong potential to facilitate scientific dis-<lb/>covery, it also raises a number of ethical concerns which includes <lb/>appropriate model of consent that will allow for such sharing of <lb/>data and samples while upholding participant autonomy 11-14 ; <lb/>issues of withdrawal of consent 15,16 ; ownership of samples <lb/>and data 17-20 ; privacy and confidentiality 15,21-23 ; and benefit <lb/>sharing 24-26 . Such issues are not peculiar to African countries, but <lb/>require a different lens in further elucidating the contextual con-<lb/>cerns in African settings. Furthermore, there are concerns about <lb/>trust 27 and fairness in research collaborations 10,28 , increased <lb/>vulnerability of research participants due to lower socio-<lb/>economic levels, a history of exploitation of local populations <lb/>and researchers 29 , and cultural issues that all must be considered <lb/>in the governance of genomics research and biobanking in <lb/>Africa. <lb/>In addition to these ethical concerns, regulatory frameworks for <lb/>health research in Africa are either non-existent, or where they <lb/>exist, do not respond to the specific concerns raised by genom-<lb/>ics research and biobanking 10,23,30 . Towards addressing this gap, <lb/>the H3Africa Initiative considered it expedient to develop an <lb/>ethics framework describing best practice for genomics research <lb/>and biobanking. Described in terms of core principles and <lb/>elements, the Framework considered African political history <lb/>of exploitations from the West and accounts of ethical <lb/>concerns in conducting genomics research and biobanking 30-33 <lb/>to inform the choice of these core principles and elements. The <lb/>phenomenon of &quot;parachute research&quot; -where fully equipped <lb/>research teams from other countries arrive at the site where <lb/>research is needed, conduct their research independently of <lb/>others, and then leave, has been long cited as a challenge for <lb/>genuine collaborative research in Africa as well as other devel-<lb/>oping countries in the world. That such practices are not <lb/>part of the past was highlighted during the recent Ebola epidemic <lb/>in some West African countries where international research-<lb/>ers are said to have carted specimens away from the affected <lb/>countries without any form of oversight or recourse to local <lb/>regulations or regulators 29 . A permutation of these practices <lb/>is where African researchers are reduced to the role of data and <lb/>sample collectors, without genuine attempts to ensure their <lb/>involvement beyond such functions. One way to remedy such <lb/>practices is by fostering sustainable capacity building for <lb/>African intellectual leadership in the conceptualization, design, <lb/>implementation and reporting of locally appropriate studies 30,34,35 <lb/>-this is one of the core elements of the framework described <lb/>here. It is also one of the main goals of the H3Africa initiative <lb/>including support for equipment and infrastructure to enable <lb/>researchers to develop biobanks and conduct large-scale genomics <lb/>studies. <lb/>The aim of this framework is to guide governance, address sam-<lb/>ple and data sharing concerns, as well as to serve as a resource <lb/>for countries to develop their local regulations. The process <lb/>of engagement that led to the development of this framework is <lb/>reported in another manuscript. This paper highlights the key <lb/>contents of this framework and plans for its implementation <lb/>across the African continent. <lb/>An overarching philosophical basis <lb/>In developing this ethics framework, it was important for key <lb/>stakeholders to identity the overarching philosophical basis that <lb/>should guide the development of ethical best practice for genomic <lb/>research and biobanking. The issues of unfair research collabora-<lb/>tion, lack of trust in research collaborations with scientists from <lb/>the &quot;West&quot; and the related scepticisms among experts and com-<lb/>munity representatives 30,36-38 were key considerations. These <lb/>remain genuine concerns that need to be addressed to promote <lb/>inclusion of Africans in genomics research as the field progresses <lb/>and the world benefits from its outcomes 6 . To ensure that African <lb/>patients and researchers partake in genomic research to optimal <lb/>benefit, we thought it important to adopt a normative basis from <lb/>African cultural philosophy. &quot;Ubuntu&quot; is a largely South African <lb/>worldview that focuses on the interrelatedness of humans in their <lb/>quest for mutual co-existence and is one such African philosophy <lb/>that was initially selected as a foundation for the framework 39 . <lb/>However, given its strong historical links to an era of struggle <lb/>in apartheid South Africa and several accounts limiting it as a <lb/>southern African philosophy, its acceptance during our con-<lb/>sultations as a philosophical basis for the framework met with <lb/>some resistance from stakeholders in other parts of Africa. <lb/>Instead, upon consultation we agreed that the framework should <lb/>adopt a more generic communal or solidarity-based worldview. <lb/>Such a worldview recognises that individuals are shaped by <lb/>their relations to people around them and emphasizes respect-<lb/>ful and harmonious relationships between them. In the African <lb/>research context, we agreed that a communitarian perspective <lb/>would place central importance on reciprocity, consultation and <lb/>accountability as key ethical values. <lb/>Core Principles and Elements <lb/>The framework proposes a set of five core principles that ought <lb/>to underpin guidance for genomic research and biobanking <lb/>initiatives in Africa. Whilst these principles are not new, they need <lb/>to keep of being emphasized to address particular concerns of <lb/>African communities and scientists regarding trust and unfair-<lb/>ness in research collaborations. A number of these principles have <lb/>been echoed in a parallel initiative, the San Code of Ethics, which <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 3 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>seeks to define how researchers ought to conduct their work when <lb/>dealing with the San population in South Africa 40,41 . The five core <lb/>principles of our framework emphasize the need for research <lb/>to: a) be sensitive and respectful of African values and cultures; <lb/>b) be designed primarily to benefit the African people, while <lb/>acknowledged it may equally benefit the global population; <lb/>c) ensure genuine and active intellectual participation of African <lb/>investigators and other stakeholders in research and in dissemi-<lb/>nation of findings; and d) promote relationships characterised <lb/>by respect, fairness, equity and reciprocity. As core principles, <lb/>these aspects are non-negotiable and should be incorporated in <lb/>the design and conduct of genomics research and biobanking <lb/>initiatives in Africa. <lb/>Key elements of the Framework for Best Practice <lb/>In addition to these core principles, the Framework also describes <lb/>ten key areas that need to be addressed in order to ensure that <lb/>the core principles elucidated in the framework are realised. <lb/>They include: African intellectual leadership; Consent; Com-<lb/>munity engagement; Ethics review; Avoidance of group harm <lb/>and stigma; Benefit sharing; Capacity building; International <lb/>collaboration and export of samples; Feedback of individual <lb/>genetic findings; and Good governance. These core elements <lb/>are not mutually exclusive. For instance, high-level capacity <lb/>building is key to ensuring African intellectual leadership. <lb/>Highlights of the key elements of the framework <lb/>Because sample and data sharing are essential to genomics <lb/>research and biobanking, it is important that the consent proc-<lb/>ess allows sharing and re-use whilst still respecting participant <lb/>choice. While there are several models of informed consent that <lb/>may support genomics research 42 , our framework promotes the <lb/>use of broad consent. It is important to differentiate this from <lb/>blanket consent, which is consent for sharing and use of data and <lb/>specimen without any restrictions. Broad consent as under-<lb/>stood in the framework allows for &quot;use of samples and/or data <lb/>for unspecified future studies, but with conditions. These con-<lb/>ditions can involve, for instance a restriction on the types of <lb/>studies or diseases that samples/data can be used for; a speci-<lb/>fied oversight and approval process for future use; ongoing <lb/>consultation with sample donors about future use, if possible; <lb/>and a process allowing participants to withdraw samples or <lb/>data from the storage facility that holds them&quot;. Although debates <lb/>about appropriate consent models for genomics and biobank-<lb/>ing continue, there is growing consensus that it may be the &apos;best <lb/>compromise&apos; consent model 43 . In their critical presentation of the <lb/>outcomes of a workshop which aimed to identify the appropri-<lb/>ate consent model for collection of biospecimen for use in future <lb/>research, Grady et al. (2015) submitted that broad con-<lb/>sent was considered &quot;ethically appropriate, and preferable <lb/>to lack of consent for the majority of biospecimen collec-<lb/>tion for future research uses&quot; 42 . Furthermore, Tindana and De <lb/>Vries (2016) in their paper on the perspectives of broad consent <lb/>for genomics research in LMICs concluded that there are no <lb/>a priori reasons against the use of broad consent for genom-<lb/>ics research in Africa 44 . Empirical research conducted since <lb/>then suggests that participants may also be supportive of broad <lb/>consent if done sensitively and respectfully 45-47 . The proposed <lb/>framework for acceptable broad consent includes initial <lb/>consent, oversight of future research projects, and, when feasi-<lb/>ble, mechanisms for maintaining contact and communication with <lb/>specimen donors. There is, however, an agreement among most <lb/>proponents of broad consent that for optimal participant protec-<lb/>tion, whenever broad consent is used in genomics research to <lb/>allow for future research use, it needs to be accompanied with a <lb/>mechanism that promotes accountability and equity 48 in sharing <lb/>specimen and/or data with other researchers while also <lb/>ensuring that participants&apos; choice are respected 42,44 . <lb/>The Framework considers that genuine community engage-<lb/>ment is a key component of ensuring best practice in genom-<lb/>ics research and biobanking in Africa, not in the least because it <lb/>promotes respect for community values and perspectives and <lb/>maximizes the social value of research 49 . Community engage-<lb/>ment is one way to ensure that research conduct is aligned with <lb/>a communitarian worldview. Furthermore, genuine commu-<lb/>nity engagement is proposed as a condition for the use of broad <lb/>consent 42,44 . Community engagement should take place along <lb/>the entire spectrum of research activities, from initial planning <lb/>phases and data collection, to include the return of general study <lb/>findings when projects end. <lb/>The framework recommends that all primary genomic research <lb/>and biobanking studies must be reviewed by a competent research <lb/>ethics review committee based in the country where samples are <lb/>collected or stored. Research ethics review fulfils an important <lb/>role in promoting ethical best practice and is key to the protec-<lb/>tion of research participants Such a role is very important in the <lb/>African research that takes place in the context of a high bur-<lb/>den of disease, poor access to basic necessities and healthcare, <lb/>low average income and literacy levels as well as unfamiliar-<lb/>ity of most of the people with biomedical research generally and <lb/>genomic research specifically. A particular challenge is the lim-<lb/>ited capacity of research ethics committees in Africa to review <lb/>genomics research and biobanking projects 50,51 . Using a matrix <lb/>that maps the various elements of this framework against impor-<lb/>tant issues that ethics committees are recommended to consider, <lb/>Table 1 is proposed as a practical tool for ethics committees to <lb/>provide oversight for good governance in genomics research and <lb/>biobanking. <lb/>The avoidance of group harm or stigma is considered impor-<lb/>tant particularly in the African research context where research-<lb/>ers may work with members of many different population groups, <lb/>each characterised by their own language, culture and belief <lb/>systems, some of which may be marginalised or discriminated <lb/>against. Research may also involve groups of people suffering <lb/>from stigmatised conditions or outlawed or stigmatising behav-<lb/>iours, phenotypes or lifestyles. In such a context, the reporting of <lb/>genomic research results could aggravate existing stigma or mar-<lb/>ginalisation. An example is the way in which genomic research <lb/>on the San included findings that were considered potentially <lb/>stigmatising 41 . In this example, Namibian San leaders were <lb/>approached for participation in genomics research 52 , without <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 4 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Checklist for Ethics Committee Review of Governance Arrangements in Proposed Genomics Research Studies. <lb/>Element <lb/>Explanation <lb/>Criteria <lb/>African intellectual <lb/>leadership <lb/>The substantive contribution of scientists based at African <lb/>institutions <lb/>Intellectual leadership or co-leadership of scientists at African institutions <lb/>Broad consent <lb/>Consent for the use of samples and/or data for unspecified <lb/>future studies subject to conditions <lb/>Must be fully informed and voluntary <lb/>Participants must be informed about the manner and extent to which they may withdraw <lb/>from the study <lb/>Must be supported by community engagement <lb/>Must be supported by a good governance framework <lb/>Must be subject to ethical review <lb/>Community <lb/>engagement (CE) <lb/>The process of informing, consulting and actively involving <lb/>relevant communities that have a legitimate interest in the <lb/>research process <lb/>Must be an integral part of each research project <lb/>Goals and process of CE must be clearly defined, planned and designed collaboratively <lb/>This must be done at the start of the research <lb/>CE must be evaluated <lb/>Ethics review <lb/>Ethics review promotes ethical conduct of research while <lb/>providing assurances to the public that their welfare is being <lb/>well taken care of as they contribute to knowledge and <lb/>development <lb/>Every genomic research and biobanking study must be subject to ethics review <lb/>Re-use of samples must be subject to review by a designated committee <lb/>The use of samples must be subject to a sample access committee <lb/>The use of data must be subject to data access committee review <lb/>Avoiding group harm <lb/>or stigma <lb/>The reporting of genomic research results has the potential to <lb/>aggravate existing stigma or marginalization, or punishment <lb/>Donors and research ethics comittees must be told about any risk of group harm or stigma <lb/>with the use or re-use of samples <lb/>Stigma related concerns about the sharing of genomic samples and data should be subject <lb/>to stakeholder engagement <lb/>Where there are stigma related concerns, individuals from the countries and/or institutions <lb/>where obtained should be considered <lb/>Descriptors that may be perceived to be stigmatizing or prejudicial must be avoided <lb/>Benefit sharing <lb/>Benefit sharing regulates that benefits and burdens are <lb/>distributed fairly and it is therefore key to ensuring that <lb/>research collaboration is fair <lb/>Genomics research may likely yield intangible benefits like knowledge generation and <lb/>capacity building, some of which may only translate into tangible benefits in future <lb/>generations. General study results can count as one study benefit and should be fed back <lb/>to communities in which research is conducted. This is essential to maintaining trust and <lb/>can be incorporated in community engagement activities. <lb/>If there is a realistic expectation of tangible benefit to a group, a benefit sharing plan must <lb/>be agreed to after stakeholder engagement <lb/>Consideration must be given to how genomic and biobanking research may confer benefits <lb/>on participants <lb/>Capacity building <lb/>Genomic research and biobanking conducted in Africa <lb/>should lead to substantive building of research capacity, <lb/>including both human resources and research infrastructure <lb/>A capacity building plan must be included as part of each research project <lb/>This must include infrastructure, personnel and administrative capacity building <lb/>International <lb/>collaboration and <lb/>export of samples <lb/>International collaboration and export of samples should <lb/>promote the goals of reducing global health inequality and <lb/>exploitation and strengthening the research system in the <lb/>country where the samples were collected <lb/>Export of samples must be subject to ethics review <lb/>Exportation of samples and collaboration must help build local capacity <lb/>Exportation of samples must be indicated in the consent documents <lb/>Exportation of samples must be subject to materials transfer agreements <lb/>Feedback of <lb/>individual genetic <lb/>research results <lb/>The feedback of findings in the African context considering <lb/>difficulties of validating research findings in a diagnostic <lb/>facility, the absence of healthcare workers trained in genetics <lb/>that could provide feedback, and limited validation of <lb/>genomic research findings in African populations <lb/>There is a need for wide stakeholder engagement to determine when feedback of findings <lb/>should be provided and a plan on how this would be applied. <lb/>Good governance <lb/>Good governance helps build and maintain public trust and <lb/>ensure transparency of genomic and biobanking research <lb/>Governance framework must include oversight on the use and reuse of samples <lb/>There must be compliance with local, national and international guidelines and regulations <lb/>Entities controlling access to samples must be comprised of members primarily residing on <lb/>the African continent <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 5 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>involvement of San political leadership or individuals with expe-<lb/>rience in science who could have properly explained the research <lb/>project and who could have helped the research team in design-<lb/>ing more appropriate consent processes. Whilst presented inter-<lb/>nationally as an example of &apos;best practice&apos; for the involvement of <lb/>&apos;indigenous&apos; African populations 53 , this project, as well as its <lb/>inconsiderate presentation of research results, was perceived <lb/>as deeply offensive by the Namibian and South African San <lb/>Councils and led to the development of the San Code for Ethics <lb/>referenced earlier. <lb/>Because of this and other experiences, the framework requires <lb/>researchers to be mindful of whether and how groups are <lb/>identified in genomics research, and how research results are <lb/>reported. Importantly, the framework suggests that commu-<lb/>nity engagement may be one way to alleviate the potential for <lb/>stigma. Genuine intellectual leadership by senior African <lb/>researchers and their meaningful involvement in the prepara-<lb/>tion of manuscripts is equally important to ensure the respectful <lb/>engagement with African populations and the responsible <lb/>reporting of study findings. <lb/>In terms of benefit sharing, the framework proposes that <lb/>genomics research and biobanking may bring intangible <lb/>benefits in the form of general study results, social recogni-<lb/>tion, knowledge production and translation of relevant knowl-<lb/>edge to healthcare practice. Whilst there may be some tangible <lb/>benefits emanating from genomics research and biobanking in the <lb/>form of (patentable) innovations or technologies, these are rare <lb/>and should not be the focus of benefit sharing discussions. The <lb/>framework describes, first, that it is imperative that research-<lb/>ers ensure that intangible benefits accrue to researchers and <lb/>communities and they should be aware of this. It also describes <lb/>that researchers should be mindful not to raise unrealistic expecta-<lb/>tions, and to clearly describe to communities and individuals the <lb/>nature of potential benefits they can expect and those that they <lb/>cannot. <lb/>Capacity building for African scientists is one of the cen-<lb/>tral elements of the framework, and has been identified as one <lb/>of the primary benefits emanating out of ongoing research <lb/>endeavours such as H3Africa 25,54 . Building a critical mass <lb/>of scholars in genomics and biobanking is essential to ensure <lb/>the sustainability of these research approaches in Africa. <lb/>Similarly, such a critical mass is needed to ensure that this <lb/>research can be conducted by African research teams and under <lb/>African intellectual leadership in the future, provided that capac-<lb/>ity is built along the entire academic hierarchy and includes <lb/>junior scientists as well as more senior ones. Importantly, <lb/>capacity building would need to focus not just on training in <lb/>genomics science and bioinformatics, but also in grants admin-<lb/>istration, contract negotiation, ethics and in transferable skills <lb/>such as grant writing which enables sustainability of the <lb/>genomics research. The expectation is that broad capacity build-<lb/>ing would ensure that research is responsive to the health needs <lb/>of Africans, is sensitive to African ethical, legal and social <lb/>issues, and that there is a strong avenue for the implementation <lb/>of relevant research findings into national health policy and <lb/>clinical practice. <lb/>With regard to the export of samples to other countries, the <lb/>framework acknowledges that this is often viewed as problem-<lb/>atic by research ethics committees and other regulators, not in <lb/>the least because it is viewed as perpetuating inequality. For <lb/>this reason, the framework proposes that export should only be <lb/>permitted where researchers can outline how their work will <lb/>contribute to reducing global health inequality and what measures <lb/>they have put in place to strengthen the research system in the <lb/>country where the samples were collected. One example would <lb/>be where junior and senior African students and researchers <lb/>are meaningfully involved in all aspects of the research process, <lb/>including aspects that happen in non-African laboratories and <lb/>universities. Material Transfer Agreements are fundamental to <lb/>underpin the fair export of samples, and guidance offered for <lb/>instance by the <lb/>Whilst the framework offers some guidance on the feedback <lb/>of individual genetic research results, it mainly proposes <lb/>a range of questions that need to be considered in determin-<lb/>ing whether and under which conditions the return of research <lb/>results may be appropriate in the African research context. <lb/>Given the complexity of the issues, the H3Africa Consortium <lb/>is developing a policy guiding researchers in how to decide <lb/>which results to feedback, which expands on the summary <lb/>guidance given in the framework. <lb/>Lastly, implementing a good governance regime is recom-<lb/>mended in order to tie all these elements together towards <lb/>optimal protection of participant in genomics research and <lb/>biobanking. This should be a mechanism that provides oversight <lb/>for re-use of samples and data sharing in line with the princi-<lb/>ples and elements set out in the framework. Such oversight is <lb/>expected to among other things, ensure that decisions to provide <lb/>access to sample and data for secondary use are sensitive <lb/>to the need to promote genomics scholarship from African <lb/>scientists and facilitate preferential use of data and access to <lb/>samples for such scientists for a reasonable period of time. <lb/>Such a preferential use provision is expected to further support <lb/>African scientists, who may have challenges in engaging with <lb/>the data and specimen available as fast as their counterparts <lb/>due to systemic challenges such as poor power supply, poor <lb/>access to academic databases for research, poor access to fast <lb/>and reliable internet and so forth; or infrastructural challenges <lb/>such as the availability of databases with comparable secu-<lb/>rity protections that will allow for sharing data across coun-<lb/>tries and continents. In making these decisions however, it is <lb/>important to find an appropriate balance between over-<lb/>protection, which may hinder good science with potential <lb/>benefit to humanity derivable from it. Typically, such a govern-<lb/>ance regime is achieved through the establishment of Sample <lb/>Access Committees and Data Access Committee 55 . However, <lb/>each country that seeks to use the framework, as a guide may <lb/>have to develop a structure that works best considering local <lb/>peculiarities. <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 6 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>Implementation mechanisms and amendments <lb/>The next step in our quest to consolidate and harmonize standards <lb/>for African genomics research and biobanking is to engage broadly <lb/>around the framework, and to develop template guidelines for <lb/>adaptation. <lb/>Firstly, the framework provides the basis for further discus-<lb/>sions and engagement with professional organisations, regulators <lb/>and ethics committees across Africa. Through our consultation <lb/>processes, we have built up a rich network of contacts with reg-<lb/>ulators and ethics committees at local, regional and national <lb/>levels across the continent, and we are liaising with all of these <lb/>to create awareness of the minimal standards described in the <lb/>Framework. We are also liaising with professional science <lb/>organisations including for instance the African Academy of <lb/>Sciences (AAS), to explore how that organisation can take a <lb/>leadership role in advancing ethical standards of genomics <lb/>research and biobanking on the continent. <lb/>In terms of ensuring the incorporation of the standards outlined <lb/>in the Framework into research practice, we are prepar-<lb/>ing more detailed guidelines that expand on the items in the <lb/>Framework. This resource will be publicly available for use <lb/>by ethics committees across the continent, and the hope is <lb/>that ethics committees and national ethics councils will adapt <lb/>and adopt the guidelines so that they become the gold standard <lb/>for national regulation of genomics and biobanking. In order to <lb/>ensure that they do, we will continue our engagement activities <lb/>with committees and national councils. In addition, we are <lb/>increasingly involved in offering training to national and local <lb/>ethics committees, which are invaluable in ensuring awareness <lb/>of the Framework and guidelines emanating from them. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Disclaimer <lb/>The views expressed in this article are those of the author(s). <lb/>Publication in AAS Open Research does not imply endorsement by <lb/>the AAS. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>No data are associated with this article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>No competing interests were disclosed. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Grant information <lb/>This work is supported by the Human Heredity and Health in <lb/>Africa (H3Africa) in Partnership with the African Academy of <lb/>Sciences. The Framework drafting meeting was supported by <lb/>a grant from the Wellcome Trust (WT201245/Z/16/Z). Dur-<lb/>ing the development of this Framework, Jantina de Vries was <lb/>supported by the RHDGen grant, a H3Africa grant funded <lb/>by the Wellcome Trust (WT099313MA) and the Stigma in African <lb/>Genomics grant funded by the National Human Genome <lb/>Research Institute of the National Institutes of Health under <lb/>Award Number U01HG008226. <lb/>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The development of the Framework was initiated and driven <lb/>by the H3Africa Working Group on Ethics. All authors are part <lb/>of the task force assigned by this Working Group to develop the <lb/>Framework. They are reporting on the Framework on behalf of <lb/>the Working Group. The process involved consultations with <lb/>funding institutions -NIH and Wellcome Trust, stakeholders <lb/>involved in genomics research and biobanking -the Bridging <lb/>Biobanking and Biomedical Research across Europe and Africa <lb/>(B3Africa) initiative and the Academy of Science of South <lb/>Africa, as well as selected ethics committee members from <lb/>Botswana, Uganda and Ethiopia. Akin Abayomi, Adamu <lb/>Addissie, Julius Ecuru, Mark Guyer, Mary Kasule, Michael <lb/>Pepper and Godfrey Tangwa, Ebony Madden, Patricia Marshall, <lb/>Odile Ouwe Missi Oukem-Boyer provided comments through <lb/>the H3A Working Group on Ethics. Clement Adebamowo and <lb/>Michele Ramsay provided extensive comments through the <lb/>H3Africa Steering Committee. The following provided com-<lb/>ments at some stage in the development of the Framework: Anne-<lb/>Marie Tassé and Emily Kirby of the Public Population Project <lb/>in Genomics and Society (P3G); Maimuna Mendy, Jane <lb/>Reichel, Erisa Mwaka of B3Africa and BCNet; M&apos;an Zawati and <lb/>Bartha Maria Knoppers of the Centre of Genomics and Policy <lb/>of McGill University; Doris Schroeder, Roger Chennels, Klaus <lb/>Leisinger and Michelle Singh of the Trust Project; Col-<lb/>leagues from the Global Emerging Pathogens Treatment (GET) <lb/>Consortium; Thaddeus Metz of the Philosophy Department of the <lb/>University of Witwatersrand; Victoria de Menhil of the Broad <lb/>Institute; Ilina Singh of the Department of Psychiatry of the <lb/>University of Oxford. <lb/>The Framework for the Responsible Sharing of Genomic and <lb/>Health-Related Data developed by the Global Alliance for <lb/>Genomics and Health (GA4GH) was a key resource as well as <lb/>the OECD Guidelines on Human Biobanks and Genetic Research <lb/>Databases, the Wellcome Trust Framework on the Feedback <lb/>of Health-Related Findings in Research, the EC report &apos;Global <lb/>Governance of Science&apos;, the EC report &apos;Ethical and Regula-<lb/>tory Challenges to Science and Research Policy at the Global <lb/>Level&apos; and country-specific ethics guidelines from 22 African <lb/>countries, some of which were specific to genomic research and <lb/>biobanking 56 . <lb/>A number of professionals and experts from organisations <lb/>across Africa, Europe and the United States contributed to the <lb/>development of the Framework -all are duly acknowledged in <lb/>the Framework and this paper. <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 7 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Collins FS, Morgan M, Patrinos A: The Human Genome Project: lessons from <lb/>large-scale biology. Science. 2003; 300(5617): 286-90. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>2. <lb/>McCarthy JJ, McLeod HL, Ginsburg GS: Genomic medicine: a decade of <lb/>successes, challenges, and opportunities. Sci Transl Med. 2013; 5(189): 189sr4. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>3. <lb/>H3Africa Consortium, Rotimi C, Abayomi A, et al.: Research capacity. Enabling <lb/>the genomic revolution in Africa. Science. 2014; 344(6190): <lb/>1346-1348. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>4. <lb/>International HapMap Consortium: The International HapMap Project. Nature. <lb/>2003; 426(6968): 789-96. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>5. <lb/>Gurdasani D, Carstensen T, Tekola-Ayele F, et al.: The African Genome Variation <lb/>Project shapes medical genetics in Africa. Nature. 2015; 517(7534): 327-32. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>6. <lb/>Bentley AR, Callier S, Rotimi CN: Diversity and inclusion in genomic research: <lb/>why the uneven progress? J Community Genet. 2017; 8(4): 255-266. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>7. <lb/>Tishkoff SA, Reed FA, Friedlaender FR, et al.: The genetic structure and history <lb/>of Africans and African Americans. Science. 2009; 324(5930): 1035-44. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>8. <lb/>Marshall E: Bermuda rules: community spirit, with teeth. Science. 2001; <lb/>291(5507): 1192. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>9. <lb/>Toronto International Data Release Workshop Authors, Birney E, Hudson TJ, et al.: <lb/>Prepublication data sharing. Nature. 2009; 461(7261): 168-70. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>10. de Vries J, Tindana P, Littler K, et al.: The H3Africa policy framework: negotiating <lb/>fairness in genomics. Trends Genet. 2015; 31(3): 117-9. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>11. Boddington P, Curren L, Kaye J, et al.: Consent forms in genomics: the <lb/>difference between law and practice. Eur J Health Law. 2011; 18(5): <lb/>491-519. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>12. McGuire AL, Beskow LM: Informed consent in genomics and genetic research. <lb/>Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet. 2010; 11: 361-81. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>13. Wendler D: Broad versus blanket consent for research with human biological <lb/>samples. Hastings Cent Rep. 2013; 43(5): 3-4. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>14. Nnamuchi O: H3Africa: An Africa exemplar? Exploring its framework on <lb/>protecting human research participants. Dev World Bioeth. 2017; n/a-n/a. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>15. Kaye J: The tension between data sharing and the protection of privacy in <lb/>genomics research. Annu Rev Genomics Hum Genet. 2012; 13(1): 415-431. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>16. Lowenthal J, Hull SC: Framing the &quot;Right to Withdraw&quot; in the Use of <lb/>Biospecimens for iPSC Research. Ethics in Biology, Engineering and Medicine: <lb/>An International Journal. 2013; 4(1): 1-14. <lb/>Publisher Full Text <lb/>17. Hawkins AK, O&apos;Doherty KC: &quot;Who owns your poop?&quot;: insights regarding <lb/>the intersection of human microbiome research and the ELSI aspects of <lb/>biobanking and related studies. BMC Med Genomics. 2011; 4: 72. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>18. Haga SB, Beskow LM: Ethical, legal, and social implications of biobanks for <lb/>genetics research. Adv Genet. 2008; 60: 505-44. <lb/> PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>19. Caulfield T, Rachul C, Nelson E: Biobanking, consent, and control: a survey <lb/>of Albertans on key research ethics issues. Biopreserv Biobank. 2012; 10(5): <lb/>433-8. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>20. de Vries J, Abayomi A, Brandful J, et al.: A perpetual source of DNA or <lb/>something really different: ethical issues in the creation of cell lines for <lb/>African genomics research. BMC Med Ethics. 2014; 15(1): 60. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>21. Heeney C, Hawkins N, de Vries J, et al.: Assessing the privacy risks of data <lb/>sharing in genomics. Public Health Genomics. 2011; 14(1): 17-25. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>22. McGuire AL, Gibbs RA: Genetics. No longer de-identified. Science. 2006; <lb/>312(5772): 370-371. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>23. Nnamuchi O: Biobank/Genomic Research in Nigeria: Examining Relevant <lb/>Privacy and Confidentiality Frameworks. J Law Med Ethics. 2015; 43(4): <lb/>776-786. <lb/>PubMed Abstract <lb/>24. Dauda B, Dierickx K: Benefit sharing: an exploration on the contextual <lb/>discourse of a changing concept. BMC Med Ethics. 2013; 14: 36. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>25. Dauda B, Joffe S: The benefit sharing vision of H3Africa. Dev World Bioeth. <lb/>2018. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>26. Simm K: Benefit-sharing: an inquiry regarding the meaning and limits of the <lb/>concept in human genetic research. Genomics Soc Policy. 2005; 1(2): 29. <lb/>Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>27. Moodley K, Singh S: &quot;It&apos;s all about trust&quot;: reflections of researchers on the <lb/>complexity and controversy surrounding biobanking in South Africa. BMC <lb/>Med Ethics. 2016; 17(1): 57. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>28. O&apos;Daniel J, Haga SB: Public perspectives on returning genetics and genomics <lb/>research results. Public Health Genomics. 2011; 14(6): 346-55. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>29. Heymann DL, Liu J, Lillywhite L: Partnerships, Not Parachutists, for Zika <lb/>Research. N Engl J Med. 2016; 374(16): 1504-1505. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>30. Staunton C, Moodley K: Challenges in biobank governance in Sub-Saharan <lb/>Africa. BMC Med Ethics. 2013; 14: 35. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>31. de Vries J, Bull SJ, Doumbo O, et al.: Ethical issues in human genomics <lb/>research in developing countries. BMC Med Ethics. 2011; 12(1): 5. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>32. Wonkam A, Tekendo CN, Sama DJ, et al.: Initiation of a medical genetics service <lb/>in sub-Saharan Africa: experience of prenatal diagnosis in Cameroon. Eur J <lb/>Med Genet. 2011; 54(4): e399-404. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>33. Wright KM, Bomblies K: Evolutionary genetics: inheritance of a complex <lb/>pollination syndrome. Curr Biol. 2013; 23(12): R525-7. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>34. MacDonald NE, Bortolussi R, Pemba S, et al.: Supporting research leadership in <lb/>Africa. Lancet Glob Health. 2016; 4(6): e362. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>35. Davies J, Mullan Z: Research capacity in Africa--will the sun rise again? Lancet <lb/>Glob Health. 2016; 4(5): e287. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>36. Bylstra Y, Lysaght T, Thrivikraman J, et al.: Ethical frameworks for obtaining <lb/>informed consent in tumour profiling: an evidence-based case for Singapore. <lb/>Hum Genomics. 2017; 11(1): 31. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>37. Sieber J: Data Sharing in Historical Perspective. J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics. <lb/>2015; 10(3): 215-216. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>38. Tangwa GB: Giving voice to African thought in medical research ethics. Theor <lb/>Med Bioeth. 2017; 38(2): 101-110. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>39. Swanson D: Ubuntu: An African contribution to (re)search for/with a &apos;humble <lb/>togetherness&apos;. Journal of Contemporary Issues in Education. 2007; 2(2): 15. <lb/>Publisher Full Text <lb/>40. Callaway E: South Africa&apos;s San people issue ethics code to scientists. Nature. <lb/>2017; 543(7646): 475-476. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>41. Chennells R, Steenkamp A: International Genomics Research Involving the <lb/>San People. In Ethics Dumping: Case Studies from North-South Research <lb/>Collaborations. D. Schroeder, et al., Editors. Springer International Publishing: <lb/>Cham. 2018; 15-22. <lb/>Reference Source <lb/>42. Grady C, Eckstein L, Berkman B, et al.: Broad Consent for Research With <lb/>Biological Samples: Workshop Conclusions. Am J Bioeth. 2015; 15(9): 34-42. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>43. Jao I, Kombe F, Mwalukore S, et al.: Involving Research Stakeholders in <lb/>Developing Policy on Sharing Public Health Research Data in Kenya: Views <lb/>on Fair Process for Informed Consent, Access Oversight, and Community <lb/>Engagement. J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics. 2015; 10(3): 264-277. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>44. Tindana P, de Vries J: Broad Consent for Genomic Research and Biobanking: <lb/>Perspectives from Low-and Middle-Income Countries. Annu Rev Genomics <lb/>Hum Genet. 2016; 17(1): 375-393. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>45. Sanderson SC, Brothers KB, Mercaldo ND, et al.: Public Attitudes toward <lb/>Consent and Data Sharing in Biobank Research: A Large Multi-site <lb/>Experimental Survey in the US. Am J Hum Genet. 2017; 100(3): 414-427. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>46. Tindana P, Molyneux S, Bull S, et al.: &apos;It is an entrustment&apos;: Broad consent for <lb/>genomic research and biobanks in Sub-Saharan Africa. Dev World Bioeth. 2017. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>Page 8 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>47. Warner TD, Weil CJ, Andry Cm, et al.: Broad Consent for Research on <lb/>Biospecimens: The Views of Actual Donors at Four U.S. Medical Centers. <lb/>J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics. 2018; 13(2): 115-124. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>48. Bull S: Review: Ensuring global equity in open research. Wellcome Trust. <lb/>2016. <lb/>Reference Source <lb/>49. Participants in the Community Engagement and Consent Workshop, Kilifi, Kenya, <lb/>March 2011: Consent and community engagement in diverse research <lb/>contexts. J Empir Res Hum Res Ethics. 2013; 8(4): 1-18. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>50. Ramsay M, de Vries J, Soodyall H, et al.: Ethical issues in genomic research <lb/>on the African continent: experiences and challenges to ethics review <lb/>committees. Hum Genomics. 2014; 8: 15. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>51. Barchi F, Matlhagela K, Jones N, et al.: &quot;The keeping is the problem&quot;: A <lb/>qualitative study of IRB-member perspectives in Botswana on the collection, <lb/>use, and storage of human biological samples for research. BMC Med Ethics. <lb/>2015; 16: 54. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>52. Schuster SC, Miller W, Ratan A, et al.: Complete Khoisan and Bantu genomes <lb/>from southern Africa. Nature. 2010; 463(7283): 943-947. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>53. Hayes V: Indigenous genomics. Science. 2011; 332(6030): 639. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text <lb/>54. Munung NS, Mayosi BM, de Vries J: Equity in international health research <lb/>collaborations in Africa: Perceptions and expectations of African researchers. <lb/>PLoS One. 2017; 12(10): e0186237. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/>55. H3Africa Consortium: H3Africa Consortium Data Sharing, Access and Release <lb/>Policy. 2014. <lb/>Reference Source <lb/>56. de Vries J, Munung SN, Matimba A, et al.: Regulation of genomic and biobanking <lb/>research in Africa: a content analysis of ethics guidelines, policies and <lb/>procedures from 22 African countries. BMC Med Ethics. 2017; 18(1): 8. <lb/>PubMed Abstract | Publisher Full Text | Free Full Text <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>Page 9 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/>AAS Open Research <lb/></note>

			1. <lb/>2. <lb/>3. <lb/>4. <lb/>1. <lb/>2. <lb/>3. <lb/>4. <lb/>5. <lb/>

			<div type="annex">Open Peer Review <lb/>Current Referee Status: <lb/>Version 1 <lb/>26 June 2018 <lb/>Referee Report <lb/>doi:10.21956/aasopenres.13910.r26458 <lb/>Don Chalmers <lb/>Centre for Law and Genetics, Faculty of Law, University of Tasmania, Hobart, Tas, Australia <lb/>This is a very well written and valuable account of the development of an ethical governance framework <lb/>for genomic research and biobanking in Africa. <lb/>I strongly recommend indexing for the following reasons <lb/>The article sets a clear context for the H3Africa and the development of an autochthonous African <lb/>model of consent for sharing genomic data and samples which respects autonomy; consent; <lb/>ownership of samples and data; privacy and confidentiality; and, benefit sharing. <lb/>The article makes a valuable contribution to the continuing development of an overarching African <lb/>philosophical basis for a &quot;.. framework …[with]a more generic communal or solidarity-based <lb/>worldview&quot;. This is different, as is the focus on the &quot;..central importance on reciprocity, consultation <lb/>and accountability&apos;. This draws a clear distinction between the proposed African model and <lb/>conventional western participant-focused ethical approaches, which can accompany &quot;parachute <lb/>research&quot;, mentioned in the Introduction. <lb/>The article details the elements of this African best-practice genomics and biobanking framework <lb/>based on &quot;African intellectual leadership; Consent; Community engagement; Ethics review; <lb/>Avoidance of group harm and stigma; Benefit sharing; Capacity building; International <lb/>collaboration and export of samples; Feedback of individual genetic findings; and Good <lb/>governance. <lb/>The implementation agenda for the H3Africa framework is briefly set out. Specifically noted is <lb/>future engagement with professional organisations, regulators and ethics committees before <lb/>drafting more detailed guidelines and engagement activities with ethics committees and national <lb/>councils. <lb/>I have some suggestions for the authors <lb/>The brief mention of the principle of &quot;ubuntu&quot; is interesting and is there any more recent discussion <lb/>since the footnote 35 2007 reference? <lb/>In the section on &quot;Core Principles and elements&apos;, the authors mention &apos;five core principles&quot; but only <lb/>list four (a to d). They need to add the fifth <lb/>The authors highlight the elements of their proposed framework (see 3 above) but do not include <lb/>any discussion on the principle of &quot;African intellectual leadership&quot;. <lb/>There has been a working connection between the H3Africa and the GA4GH and a reference <lb/>could be included to this at: <lb/>. <lb/>https://www.ga4gh.org/news/ffY_2As3q-iv39gB2Un4Bw.article <lb/>In the acknowledgements, the authors list the key resources of the Global Alliance for Genomics <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 10 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">AAS Open Research <lb/>4. <lb/>5. <lb/>could be included to this at: <lb/>. <lb/>https://www.ga4gh.org/news/ffY_2As3q-iv39gB2Un4Bw.article <lb/>In the acknowledgements, the authors list the key resources of the Global Alliance for Genomics <lb/>and Health (GA4GH) Framework for the Responsible Sharing of Genomic and Health-Related <lb/>; the OECD <lb/>, 2009 the <lb/>Data <lb/>Guidelines on Human Biobanks and Genetic Research Databases <lb/>Wellcome Trust <lb/>, 2014 the <lb/>Framework on the feedback of health-related findings in research <lb/>European Commission&apos;s reports on <lb/>, 2009 and <lb/>Global Governance of Science <lb/>Ethical and <lb/>l 2012 and the 22 <lb/>Regulatory Challenges to Science and Research Policy at the Global Leve <lb/>African country-specific ethics guidelines. <lb/>These global collaborations and interactions are worthy of reference and comment in the text at the <lb/>section &quot;Key elements of the Framework for Best Practice&apos;. This records that the authors are <lb/>striking out on a path for Africa but one informed by international developments and collaborations. <lb/>Declaration of interest I have met Littler K and De Vries J but have never published with either. <lb/>Is the rationale for the Open Letter provided in sufficient detail? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Does the article adequately reference differing views and opinions? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Are all factual statements correct, and are statements and arguments made adequately <lb/>supported by citations? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Is the Open Letter written in accessible language? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Where applicable, are recommendations and next steps explained clearly for others to follow? <lb/>Yes <lb/>No competing interests were disclosed. <lb/>Competing Interests: <lb/>I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that <lb/>it is of an acceptable scientific standard. <lb/>25 June 2018 <lb/>Referee Report <lb/>doi:10.21956/aasopenres.13910.r26476 <lb/>Ellen Wright Clayton <lb/>Center for Biomedical Ethics and Society, Vanderbilt University Medical Center (VUMC), Nashville, TN, <lb/>USA <lb/>This is an important paper setting forth guiding principles for genomics research in Africa. The document <lb/>is clear and well written and will be quite helpful for the work of putting concrete mechanisms in place that <lb/>protect the interests of individuals and communities while building local capacity and advancing research <lb/>to improve health. <lb/>I have only one substantive comment, which is that it would be helpful to say more about what the authors <lb/>mean by community engagement, specifying to what extent and on what topics the community should <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 11 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">AAS Open Research <lb/>mean by community engagement, specifying to what extent and on what topics the community should <lb/>have input. This is often a contested issue. <lb/>My other comments are minor: <lb/>Under core principles, there is an extra &quot;of&quot; on the second line. <lb/>I saw only four principles, not five. <lb/>On line 9 under consent process, I assume that &quot;it&quot; refers to broad consent. If so, that should be stated <lb/>explicitly. <lb/>Under avoidance of group harm, there should not be a comma after note 52. <lb/>Is the rationale for the Open Letter provided in sufficient detail? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Does the article adequately reference differing views and opinions? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Are all factual statements correct, and are statements and arguments made adequately <lb/>supported by citations? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Is the Open Letter written in accessible language? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Where applicable, are recommendations and next steps explained clearly for others to follow? <lb/>Yes <lb/>No competing interests were disclosed. <lb/>Competing Interests: <lb/>I have read this submission. I believe that I have an appropriate level of expertise to confirm that <lb/>it is of an acceptable scientific standard. <lb/>21 June 2018 <lb/>Referee Report <lb/>doi:10.21956/aasopenres.13910.r26442 <lb/>, <lb/>Kieran O&apos;Doherty <lb/>Kim Chuong <lb/>Department of Psychology, University of Guelph, Guelph, ON, Canada <lb/>This article describes an ethics framework for genomics research and biobanking in Africa, which is <lb/>valuable in the African public health context and to address global health inequality. The article is <lb/>well-written and concise in its summary of the core principles and key elements of the framework. We see <lb/>the contribution of the framework in the context of ELS implications of genomics and biobanks in its <lb/>emphasis on the need for research to be sensitive and respectful of diverse cultures, values and belief <lb/>systems of African populations. Also of significance is the goal to enhance capacity building and genuine <lb/>intellectual participation of African researchers and stakeholders in genomics research. The authors of <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 12 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">AAS Open Research <lb/>intellectual participation of African researchers and stakeholders in genomics research. The authors of <lb/>this article are to be commended for this important work. <lb/>Overall, the manuscript will make an important contribution. We have only minor suggestions for <lb/>improvement. Although the key elements of the framework are well-presented, the authors do not address <lb/>potential challenges that may be encountered while applying those key elements. We realise that the <lb/>purpose of the article is to lay out the framework, and so does not address implementation issues. <lb/>However, some additional detail may be good to add, in particular in the context of community <lb/>engagement, which the authors emphasize as a key component for ensuring best practice in genomics <lb/>research and biobanking in Africa. However, it is not clear from the framework what the authors mean by <lb/>&quot;genuine community engagement&quot;. There is a rich literature on engaging community members in research <lb/>and the values and challenges of doing so. Community engagement goes beyond the meaningful <lb/>involvement of African researchers to include individuals from the broader population and specific groups, <lb/>and will need to address issues such as power dynamics between researchers who are considered <lb/>experts and community members. <lb/>Other issues: <lb/>On p. 3. The authors mention that &quot;The process of engagement that led to the development of this <lb/>framework is reported in another manuscript.&quot; A reference to this manuscript should be provided. <lb/>The paragraph on export of samples to other countries is incomplete (p. 6). <lb/>The &quot;implementation mechanisms and amendments&quot; section (p. 7) describes the next steps for raising <lb/>awareness and engaging health organisations and national councils with the framework. It would be great <lb/>to have more detail regarding future evaluation of the framework and the Working Group&apos;s engagement <lb/>activities. <lb/>Is the rationale for the Open Letter provided in sufficient detail? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Does the article adequately reference differing views and opinions? <lb/>Partly <lb/>Are all factual statements correct, and are statements and arguments made adequately <lb/>supported by citations? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Is the Open Letter written in accessible language? <lb/>Yes <lb/>Where applicable, are recommendations and next steps explained clearly for others to follow? <lb/>Yes <lb/>No competing interests were disclosed. <lb/>Competing Interests: <lb/>We have read this submission. We believe that we have an appropriate level of expertise to <lb/>confirm that it is of an acceptable scientific standard. <lb/></div>

			<page>Page 13 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 <lb/>AAS Open Research <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 14 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">AAS Open Research 2018, 1:13 Last updated: 26 JUN 2018 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
