<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cognition and Behavior <lb/>Sexually Dimorphic Vasopressin Cells Modulate <lb/>Social Investigation and Communication in <lb/>Sex-Specific Ways <lb/>Nicole Rigney, 1 Jack Whylings, 1 Michihiro Mieda, 2 Geert de Vries, 1 and Aras Petrulis 1 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1523/ENEURO.0415-18.2019 <lb/>1 Georgia State University, Atlanta, GA 30303, and 2 Kanazawa University, Kanazawa, Ishikawa, Japan 920-1192 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The neuropeptide arginine vasopressin (AVP) has long been implicated in the regulation of social behavior and <lb/>communication, but precisely which AVP cell groups are involved is largely unknown. To address whether the <lb/>sexually dimorphic AVP cell group in the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis (BNST) is important for social <lb/>communication, we deleted BNST AVP cells by viral delivery of a Cre-dependent caspase-3 cell-death construct <lb/>in AVP-iCre-positive mice using AVP-iCre negative littermate as controls, and assessed social, sexual, aggressive <lb/>and anxiety-related behaviors. In males, lesioning BNST AVP cells reduced social investigation of other males and <lb/>increased urine marking (UM) in the presence of a live female, without altering ultrasonic vocalizations (USVs), <lb/>resident-intruder aggression, copulatory behavior, anxiety, or investigation of females or their odor cues. In <lb/>females, which have significantly fewer AVP cells in the BNST, these injections influenced copulatory behavior but <lb/>otherwise had minimal effects on social behavior and communication, indicating that these cells contribute to sex <lb/>differences in social behavioral function. <lb/>Key words: bed nucleus of the stria terminalis; mice; sex differences; social behavior; social communication; <lb/>vasopressin <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Social behavior and communication show profound sex <lb/>differences in many species (Darwin, 1871; Bradbury and <lb/>Vehrencamp, 1998), and in humans, dysfunction in social <lb/>behavior and communication is prominent in chronic, de-<lb/>bilitating, and pervasive psychopathologies (Insel, 2010) <lb/>that show sex differences in prevalence and clinical out-<lb/>come (Halladay et al., 2015), such as autism (Schultz, <lb/>2005). One reasonable hypothesis is that sex differences <lb/>in the underlying neural circuitry contribute to sexually <lb/>differentiated function and dysfunction in social behavior <lb/></body>

			<front>Received October 26, 2018; accepted January 2, 2019; First published <lb/>January 15, 2019. <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/>Author contributions: A.P. and G.d.V. designed research; N.R. and J.W. <lb/>performed research; M.M. contributed unpublished reagents/analytic tools; <lb/>N.R. also designed experiment and analyzed data; N.R., A.P., and G.d.V. wrote <lb/>the paper. <lb/>Significance Statement <lb/>Despite over thirty years of indirect evidence implicating sexually-dimorphic arginine vasopressin (AVP) cells <lb/>within the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis (BNST) in the control of social and anxiety-related behavior in <lb/>mammals, the function of these cells has never been directly tested. Here, we show that deletion of these <lb/>cells in male, but not female, mice reduce investigation of same-sex conspecifics and alter social commu-<lb/>nication without changing aggressive and anxiety-related behaviors. Although AVP cell deletion in the BNST <lb/>did not alter male copulatory behavior, it impaired female sexual behavior. These results indicate that <lb/>sexually-dimorphic AVP cells in the BNST drive specific aspects of sexually-differentiated social investiga-<lb/>tion, behavior, and communication. <lb/>New Research <lb/>January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 1-20 <lb/></front>

			<body>and communication. A particularly well-positioned circuit <lb/>in this respect is the arginine vasopressin (AVP) innerva-<lb/>tion of the brain, which shows marked sex differences <lb/>across many species, including humans (Goodson and <lb/>Bass, 2001; De Vries and Panzica, 2006; de Vries, 2008). <lb/>Research across taxa confirms an important role for AVP <lb/>in social behavior. For example, AVP has been implicated <lb/>in aggression, pair bonding, maternal behavior, and com-<lb/>munication across vertebrates (Goodson and Bass, 2001; <lb/>Albers, 2012). However, the anatomy of AVP projections <lb/>suggests that AVP control of social behavior is complex <lb/>and, in most cases, the anatomic substrate of AVP&apos;s <lb/>control of social behavior is unclear (Kelly and Goodson, <lb/>2013a; Ludwig and Stern, 2015; Dumais and Veenema, <lb/>2016). In most animals, AVP is synthesized in several cell <lb/>groups, each of which projecting to distinct brain areas <lb/>(De Vries and Boyle, 1998; Rood and De Vries, 2011; <lb/>Rood et al., 2013). AVP cells in the medial amygdala (MeA) <lb/>and bed nucleus of the stria terminalis (BNST) contribute <lb/>to the most pronounced sex differences in AVP innerva-<lb/>tion in brain (De Vries and Boyle, 1998). For example, male <lb/>rats and mice have about two to three times as many AVP <lb/>cells as females in these nuclei and the projections of <lb/>these cells to areas such as lateral septum (LS) are denser <lb/>as well (van Leeuwen et al., 1985; Rood and De Vries, <lb/>2011; Rood et al., 2013; Otero-Garcia et al., 2014). <lb/>Various studies suggest that AVP cells in the BNST and <lb/>MeA modulate pro-social as well as antagonistic behav-<lb/>iors. In birds, for example, partial knock-down of AVP <lb/>gene expression in the BNST reduces prosocial vocaliza-<lb/>tions and social interactions in birds while increasing <lb/>male-male aggression (Kelly et al., 2011; Kelly and Good-<lb/>son, 2013a,b). Evidence for involvement of AVP projec-<lb/>tions from the BNST and MeA in social behavior in <lb/>mammals is less direct. For example, the density of AVP <lb/>fibers in BNST and MeA projection areas and c-Fos acti-<lb/>vation in AVP cells in the BNST correlate negatively with <lb/>aggression in male mice and rats (Compaan et al., 1993; <lb/>Everts et al., 1997; Ebner et al., 2000; Beiderbeck et al., <lb/>2007; Veenema et al., 2010) but positively with prosocial <lb/>behavior (Goodson et al., 2009; Ho et al., 2010). In addi-<lb/>tion, injecting specific V1a receptor agonists or boosting <lb/>V1a receptor expression in target areas of AVP cells in the <lb/>BNST and MeA promotes affiliation in voles (Wang et al., <lb/>1994; Liu et al., 2001; Pitkow et al., 2001; Lim and Young, <lb/>2004; Lim et al., 2004) and social recognition and active <lb/>social behaviors in rats (Dantzer et al., 1988; Veenema <lb/>et al., 2012). In rats, where AVP release in the septum, one <lb/>of the most prominent projection areas of BNST and MeA <lb/>AVP cells (De Vries and Buijs, 1983; De Vries and Panzica, <lb/>2006), correlates positively with intermale aggression in a <lb/>resident-intruder test, a behavioral response could be <lb/>blocked by retro-dialysis of an AVP antagonist (Veenema <lb/>et al., 2010). None of these results, however, can be tied <lb/>with certainty to AVP cells in the BNST and MeA, as all <lb/>these areas receive AVP input from other sources as well, <lb/>most importantly the PVN (Rood et al., 2013). In addition, <lb/>AVP released dendritically from neurosecretory neurons in <lb/>the hypothalamus may reach these areas as well (Ludwig <lb/>and Stern, 2015). To directly test the hypothesis that AVP <lb/>cells in the BNST modulate social behavior, we injected <lb/>an adeno-associated virus (AAV) with a Cre-dependent, <lb/>genetically modified executioner caspase-3 complex <lb/>(Yang et al., 2013; Unger et al., 2015) into the BNST of <lb/>adult AVP-iCreϩ and AVP-iCre-(Mieda et al., 2015) male <lb/>and female mice, which specifically deleted AVP cells in <lb/>the area, and tested the effects of these deletions on <lb/>social investigation, courtship ultrasonic vocalizations <lb/>(USVs; Chabout et al., 2015), and territorial urine marking <lb/>(UM; Arakawa et al., 2008b), all aspects of mouse com-<lb/>munication known to show pronounced sex differences <lb/>(Crawley, 2012; Lehmann et al., 2013; Wöhr, 2014). <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Animals and husbandry <lb/>All mice were maintained at 22°C on a 12/12 h reverse <lb/>light/dark cycle with food and water available ad libitum, <lb/>housed in individually ventilated cages (Animal Care Sys-<lb/>tems), and provided with corncob bedding, a nestlet <lb/>square, and a housing tube. All animal procedures were <lb/>performed in accordance with the Georgia State Univer-<lb/>sity animal care committee regulations and the National <lb/>Institutes of Health Guide for the Care and Use of Labo-<lb/>ratory Animals. <lb/>Subjects <lb/>Founding AVP-iCre mice were obtained from Dr. Michi-<lb/>hiro Mieda (Kanazawa University, Japan). These mice <lb/>were generated using a bacterial artificial chromosome <lb/>(BAC) that expressed codon-improved Cre recombinase <lb/>(Shimshek et al., 2002) under the transcriptional control of <lb/>the AVP promoter (AVP-iCre mice). In these animals, iCre <lb/>expression is found in the BNST and the MeA, as well as <lb/>in hypothalamic areas (Mieda et al., 2015). Subjects were <lb/>derived by crossing heterozygous iCreϩ mutants to wild-<lb/>type C57Bl/6J mice and genotyped (ear punch) by poly-<lb/>merase chain reaction (PCR) at 21-24 d of age <lb/>(Transnetyx). Both iCreϩ and iCre-littermates were used <lb/>in behavioral experiments. All subject mice were singly-<lb/>housed for a minimum of one week. <lb/>Stimulus animals <lb/>CD1(ICR) (Charles River Laboratories) mice were used <lb/>as stimuli for behavioral testing and to provide male and <lb/>female subjects with social experience because strain <lb/>differences between subjects and stimulus mice increase <lb/>social investigation (Gheusi et al., 1994). Mice were used <lb/>at 9 -16 weeks of age and were novel and unrelated to the <lb/>subject to which they were exposed. <lb/></body>

			<front>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health Grant R21 <lb/>MH111104. <lb/>Acknowledgements: We thank Carol Wilber, Leah Krevitt, Meira Robbins, <lb/>Dorena Nguyen, and Sean Bevacqua for their assistance collecting behavioral <lb/>data and Jonathan Boykin for programming assistance in R. <lb/>Correspondence should be addressed to Nicole Rigney at nrigney1@ <lb/>student.gsu.edu. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1523/ENEURO.0415-18.2019 <lb/>Copyright © 2019 Rigney et al. <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution 4.0 International license, which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium provided that the original work is <lb/>properly attributed. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Female stimulus mice were group-housed, ovariecto-<lb/>mized, and implanted with an estradiol capsule (GDXϩE), <lb/>and given two sexual experiences before testing. Two <lb/>groups of stimulus males were used for behavioral test-<lb/>ing. Mice that were used as subordinate mice in the home <lb/>cage aggression tests and for providing aggressive expe-<lb/>rience to subjects, were group housed, gonadectomized <lb/>(GDX), and subjected to two aggressive encounters with a <lb/>dominant male. Mice in the second group, which provided <lb/>sexual experience to female subjects and served as sex-<lb/>ual partners during copulatory tests and as stimulus ani-<lb/>mal in the three-chamber social test, were singly-housed, <lb/>GDX, and implanted with testosterone (GDXϩT), and <lb/>given two sexual experiences before testing. <lb/>Viral vector <lb/>AVP driven-, Cre-expressing-BNST neurons were ab-<lb/>lated using an AAV (AAV-flex-taCasp3-TEVp; serotype <lb/>2/1; 3 ϫ 10 12 IU/ml; University of North Carolina at Chapel <lb/>Hill Vector Core) that encodes, in a Cre-dependent fash-<lb/>ion, a mutated pro-caspase-3 and its activator (TEVp; Fig. <lb/>1A). This system activates an apoptotic signaling cas-<lb/>cade, cleaving multiple structural and regulatory proteins <lb/>critical for cell survival and maintenance (Yang et al., <lb/>2013) and thereby inducing far less inflammation than <lb/>other lesion approaches (Morgan et al., 2014). <lb/>Surgery <lb/>All surgeries were conducted using 1.5-3% isoflurane <lb/>gas anesthesia in 100% oxygen; 3 mg/kg of carprofen <lb/>was given before surgery to reduce pain. <lb/>Stereotaxic surgery <lb/>Mice were positioned in a stereotaxic frame (David Kopf <lb/>Instruments) with ear and incisor bars holding bregma and <lb/>lambda level. After a midline scalp incision, a hand oper-<lb/>ated drill was used to make holes in the skull exposing the <lb/>dura. For all subjects, 500 nl of AAV-flex-taCasp3-TEVp <lb/>was delivered bilaterally to the BNST (coordinates: AP <lb/>-0.01 mm; ML Ϯ0.75 mm; DV 4.8 mm; Paxinos and <lb/>Franklin, 2012) at a rate of 100 nl/min using a 5-l Ham-<lb/>ilton syringe with a 30-gauge beveled needle mounted on <lb/>a stereotaxic injector. Following virus delivery, the syringe <lb/>was left in place for 15 min and slowly withdrawn from the <lb/>brain. <lb/>Gonadectomy and hormone treatment <lb/>Testes were cauterized and removed at the ductus <lb/>deferens via a midline abdominal incision. SILASTIC cap-<lb/>sules (1.5-cm active length; 1.02-mm inner diameter, <lb/>2.16-mm outer diameter; Dow Corning Corporation) were <lb/>filled with crystalline T (Sigma) and inserted subcutane-<lb/>ously between the scapulae after gonadectomy; this pro-<lb/>cedure leads to physiologic levels of T (Barkley and <lb/>Goldman, 1977; Matochik et al., 1994). To further reduce <lb/>aggression in stimulus animals (Beeman, 1947), some <lb/>males were GDX, but did not receive a T implant (GDX). <lb/>The ovaries of stimulus female mice were removed by <lb/>cauterization at the uterine horn and attendant blood <lb/>vessels. SILASTIC capsules (0.7-cm active length; <lb/>1.02-mm inner diameter, 2.16-mm outer diameter; Dow <lb/>Corning Corporation) containing estradiol benzoate (E; <lb/>diluted 1:1 with cholesterol) were implanted subcutane-<lb/>ously in the scapular region immediately following ovari-<lb/>ectomy (GDXϩE; Bakker et al., 2002; Ström et al., 2012). <lb/>To induce sexual receptivity, stimulus females were in-<lb/>jected subcutaneously with 0.1 ml of progesterone (500 <lb/>g dissolved in sesame oil, Sigma) 4 h preceding sexual <lb/>experience, urine collection, and behavioral testing (Vey-<lb/>rac et al., 2011). <lb/>Social experience <lb/>As opposite-sex sexual experience and attaining com-<lb/>petitive status (&quot;social dominance&quot;) promote male and <lb/>female communicative behaviors (Lumley et al., 1999; <lb/>Roullet et al., 2011), mice received social experience over <lb/>five consecutive days (sexual encounters on days 1 and 4, <lb/>aggressive encounters on days 2 and 5, and no encoun-<lb/>ters on day 3). <lb/>Sexual experience <lb/>Subjects were given two opportunities to interact with <lb/>either a stimulus female (for male subjects) or a stimulus <lb/>male (for female subjects). A sexually-experienced stim-<lb/>ulus mouse was placed in the subject&apos;s home cage and <lb/>removed 5 min after one ejaculation or 90 min in the <lb/>absence of ejaculation. Subjects that did not show ejac-<lb/>ulation (two iCre-males) or did not elicit ejaculation (one <lb/>iCreϩ female) on either trial were removed from further <lb/>testing. <lb/>Aggressive experience <lb/>Male subjects were exposed to two interactions with <lb/>subordinate males treated with 40 l of GDXϩT male <lb/>urine applied to their backs. Gonadectomy, group hous-<lb/>ing, and social defeat of our subordinates reduce offen-<lb/>sive aggression in mice, while GDXϩT male urine <lb/>provides subjects with a male urinary cue that elicits <lb/>offensive aggression (Beeman, 1947; Connor and Win-<lb/>ston, 1972; Van Loo et al., 2001). Subordinate stimulus <lb/>males were placed in the subject&apos;s home cage and re-<lb/>moved after the subject&apos;s first offensive attack (biting) <lb/>within a 10-min period. All subject males attacked the <lb/>intruder male stimulus by the second encounter, and all <lb/>subordinate stimulus males displayed submissive behav-<lb/>ior, defined as defensive postures (e.g., on-back), fleeing, <lb/>and non-social exploring (Koolhaas et al., 2013). Female <lb/>subjects were exposed to a female intruder; however, this <lb/>did not elicit any attacks from either animal. <lb/>Experimental procedure <lb/>All testing occurred within the first 6 h of the dark cycle <lb/>under red light illumination, with the exception of the <lb/>elevated plus maze (EPM). All tests were scored by an <lb/>experimenter blind to the genotype of the subject. Three <lb/>to four weeks after viral injections, subjects were habitu-<lb/>ated to the testing room and apparatus by handling and <lb/>placing mice (for 5 min) in the three-chamber apparatus <lb/>(see below) each day for 3 d. On experimental days, <lb/>subjects were adapted to the experimental room for 15 <lb/>min before testing. First, we tested mice on an EPM to <lb/>test for anxiety-related behavior (Lister, 1987). Mice were <lb/>then tested in the three-chamber apparatus over six con-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. AVP histology and experiment timeline. A, Cre-dependent AAV (AAV-flex-taCasp3-TEVp) and location of bilateral BNST <lb/>injection site; coordinates: AP -0.01 mm; ML Ϯ0.75 mm; DV 4.8 mm; modified from Paxinos and Franklin (2012). Timeline of <lb/>experimental manipulations. B, Example images of fluorescent in situ hybridization (ISH)-labeled BNST AVP cells and boxplot of cell <lb/>number. Within the BNST, a significant decrease in AVP cell label was observed in both iCreϩ male and female mice compared to <lb/>iCre-control animals (males: p ϭ 0.00014; females: p ϭ 0.0025). iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 11) males and iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ <lb/>(n ϭ 8) females. C, Example images of fluorescent ISH-labeled accessory nucleus-AVP cells and boxplot of cell number. No significant <lb/>AVP cell loss was observed between iCreϩ and iCre-subjects (males: p ϭ 0.98; females: p ϭ 0.89). iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ <lb/>11) males and iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 8) females. D, Example images of fluorescent ISH-labeled PVN and boxplot of image <lb/>intensity (arbitrary units). iCreϩ and iCre-subjects did not differ in PVN signal intensity (males: t (20) ϭ 0.66, p ϭ 0.947; females: p ϭ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>secutive days with a day off on the fourth day. Lastly, odor <lb/>discrimination, copulatory, and aggressive behavior were <lb/>measured in the subject&apos;s home cage (Fig. 1A). Female <lb/>subjects were tested irrespective of estrous cycle day, <lb/>except during copulation testing, when they were in be-<lb/>havioral estrus. Prior research indicates minimal effects of <lb/>estrous cycle on female mouse communicative behavior <lb/>(Maggio and Whitney, 1985; Coquelin, 1992; Moncho-<lb/>Bogani et al., 2004). Following testing, subjects were <lb/>killed and their brain tissue was processed for in situ <lb/>hybridization to detect AVP expression in BNST and <lb/>nearby hypothalamic areas. <lb/>Social behavior <lb/>USV, UM, and social investigation were recorded in an <lb/>acrylic three-chamber apparatus (Crawley, 2007; Ara-<lb/>kawa et al., 2008a; Moy et al., 2009; Harvard Apparatus; <lb/>dimensions: 20.3 ϫ 42 ϫ 22 cm). Instead of a solid floor, <lb/>the apparatus was placed on absorbent paper (Nalgene <lb/>Versi-dry paper, Thermo Fisher Scientific) so as to accu-<lb/>rately measure UM. Animals were also tracked using <lb/>motion detection software (ANY-maze, San Diego Instru-<lb/>ments, RRID:SCR_014289). During testing with stimulus <lb/>animals, subjects had access to either a stimulus animal <lb/>in a cage [8 cm (D), 18 cm (H); 3-mm diameter steel bars, <lb/>7.4 mm spacing] or an empty cage placed at opposite <lb/>corners of the outermost chambers of the apparatus. For <lb/>testing with social odors, subjects had access to 50 l of <lb/>fresh urine from a stimulus animal or 50-l saline pipetted <lb/>onto a clean piece of filter paper (3 cm 2 ), that was taped <lb/>on the outside of cages. The location of stimulus and the <lb/>&quot;clean&quot; cage were counterbalanced across animals. After <lb/>placing the subject in the center of the middle chamber, <lb/>we measured, across a 5-min trial, close investigation of <lb/>clean and stimulus cages, distance traveled throughout <lb/>the apparatus, time spent in the stimulus and clean cage <lb/>chambers as well as USVs and UMs. After testing, the <lb/>apparatus and cages were thoroughly cleaned with 70% <lb/>ethanol and allowed to dry before further testing. In all <lb/>cases, urine stimulus from one sex was presented first <lb/>followed by a live stimulus of that same sex; this order <lb/>was then repeated for the opposite sex. In this fashion, <lb/>mice experienced first weak (urine) then stronger social <lb/>stimuli (stimulus animal; the order of male and female <lb/>stimuli presentation was counterbalanced. <lb/>Investigation and USVs <lb/>Close investigation was defined as time spent sniffing <lb/>within 2 cm of the stimulus or clean cage; climbing on the <lb/>cage was not scored as investigation. USVs were de-<lb/>tected using a condenser microphone connected to an <lb/>amplifier (UltraSoundGate CM16/CMPA, 10 -200 kHz, fre-<lb/>quency range) placed 4 cm inside the apparatus and <lb/>directly above the center compartment. USVs were sam-<lb/>pled at 200 kHz (16-bit) with target frequency set to 70 <lb/>kHz (UltraSoundGate 116Hb, Avisoft Bioacoustics). Re-<lb/>cordings were then analyzed using a MATLAB (Math-<lb/>Works, RRID:SCR_001622) plug-in that automates USV <lb/>analysis (Van Segbroeck et al., 2017). Using this program, <lb/>sonograms were generated by calculating the power <lb/>spectrum on Hamming windowed data and then trans-<lb/>formed into compact acoustic feature representations <lb/>(Gammatone Filterbank). Each 200-ms window containing <lb/>the maximum USV syllable duration was then clustered, <lb/>via machine learning algorithms, into USV syllable types <lb/>(repertoire units) based on time-frequency USV shape. <lb/>Repertoire units that appeared as background noise were <lb/>discarded. We counted the number of all USV produced <lb/>by each subject. USV syllable types were identified from a <lb/>subset of males (iCre-n ϭ 6; iCreϩ n ϭ 7) using criterion <lb/>previously described: short, composite, downward, up-<lb/>ward, 1 frequency jump, modulated, multiple frequency <lb/>jumps, u-shape, flat, chevron (Hanson and Hurley, 2012). <lb/>UM <lb/>Following testing, the substrate sheet was allowed to <lb/>dry for 1 h and then sprayed with ninhydrin fixative (LC-<lb/>NIN-16; Tritech Forensics Inc.) to visualize urine marks <lb/>(Meyer, 1957; Lehmann et al., 2013). After 24 h, sheets <lb/>were imaged (Sony DSC-S700 camera), binarized and <lb/>analyzed using a computer-aided imaging software (Im-<lb/>ageJ, RRID:SCR_003070). UM was measured as the total <lb/>area (cm 2 ) of visualized ninhydrin urine marks in the entire <lb/>arena. Urine marks that were larger than 6 cm 2 and di-<lb/>rected toward corners were counted as eliminative <lb/>&quot;pools&quot; and were counted separately (Bishop and Chev-<lb/>ins, 1987). <lb/>Copulatory and aggressive behavior <lb/>To measure copulatory behavior, the stimulus mouse <lb/>was placed in the subject&apos;s home cage and then removed <lb/>5 min after one ejaculation had occurred or if 90 min had <lb/>elapsed without copulation. The latency and total time <lb/>investigating the anogenital region, latency to mount, per-<lb/>centage of females that were mounted, percentage of <lb/>male ejaculations, and number of mount rejections (fe-<lb/>male kicking male off during mounting attempt) in female <lb/>subjects was recorded. To measure territorial aggression, <lb/>subordinate stimulus males were placed in the subject&apos;s <lb/>home cage and then removed after the subject&apos;s first <lb/>offensive attack (biting) within a 10-min period; the latency <lb/>to first bite was recorded. <lb/>continued <lb/>0.29). iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 10) males and iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 8) females. E, Example images of Nissl-stained BNST <lb/>tissue and boxplot of cell number. No difference in BNST cell number between iCreϩ and iCre-subjects was observed (males: p ϭ <lb/>0.439; females: p ϭ 0.44). iCre-(n ϭ 6) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 9) males and iCre-(n ϭ 8) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 6) females. In boxplots, dots indicate <lb/>individual data points, bold horizontal lines illustrate the median, the areas above and below the lines show the 1st/3rd quartile. The <lb/>vertical bars range from the minimal to the maximal values excluding outliers (Ϯ1.35 SDs from interquartile range). Images were taken <lb/>at 10ϫ for fluorescent material and 20ϫ for Nissl-stained tissue. Scale bar ϭ 50 m; ‫ءء‬ indicates significant effect of genotype, p Ͻ <lb/>0.005. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Odor discrimination <lb/>We used a habituation-discrimination procedure on a <lb/>subset of subjects to test whether they could distinguish <lb/>between social odors (Baum and Keverne, 2002). Sub-<lb/>jects were given five consecutive 2-min presentations of <lb/>an odor stimulus with one min intervals between presen-<lb/>tations. Subjects were first presented with deionized wa-<lb/>ter, followed by two non-social odors (100% almond, <lb/>lemon, or vanilla extract, Frontier Natural Products), and <lb/>then two urine samples (one from each sex) within their <lb/>home cage. The sequence of odor presentation was <lb/>counterbalanced within non-social or social odor cate-<lb/>gory. Each odor stimulus (30 l) was placed onto a clean <lb/>piece of filter paper (3 cm 2 ) taped to an empty food <lb/>hopper such that subjects could contact the urine sam-<lb/>ples. Time spent sniffing within 2 cm of the filter paper <lb/>was recorded. Food hoppers were cleaned with 70% <lb/>ethanol and allowed to dry between each odor presenta-<lb/>tion. <lb/>EPM <lb/>The EPM consisted of two open arms (30 ϫ 5 cm) and <lb/>two closed arms (30 ϫ 25 ϫ 5 cm) crossed perpendicu-<lb/>larly and raised 60 cm above the floor. Subjects were <lb/>placed at the arm intersection facing the open arm and <lb/>were allowed to habituate to the apparatus for 1 min; <lb/>subjects were then observed for an additional 5 min. <lb/>Animals were tracked by ANY-maze so that measure-<lb/>ments of time spent in open and closed arms were re-<lb/>corded automatically whereas the number of risk <lb/>assessment behaviors (stretch-attend posture, head-<lb/>dips) were manually scored from video (Cole and Rodg-<lb/>ers, 1993). <lb/>Urine collection <lb/>Pooled urine samples were collected from stimulus <lb/>females induced into estrus and from stimulus males (five <lb/>to eight mice per sample). Estrous state was verified by <lb/>color, swelling, and expanded size of vaginal opening <lb/>(Caligioni, 2009). To collect urine, mice were picked up by <lb/>the tail base and held by dorsal neck skin; this method <lb/>was often sufficient to induce urination. If the mouse did <lb/>not urinate, stroking its belly from an anterior to posterior <lb/>direction stimulated bladder voiding. Each mouse pro-<lb/>vided 15-50 l of urine that was pooled into a 1.5-ml <lb/>Eppendorf tube. Urine samples were used fresh within 1 h <lb/>of collection to prevent chemosignal degradation (Roullet <lb/>et al., 2011). <lb/>Histology and in situ hybridization <lb/>Following testing, subjects were killed via CO 2 asphyx-<lb/>iation. Brains were extracted and flash frozen via submer-<lb/>sion in 2-methyl-2-butanol (Sigma) for 10 -20 s and stored <lb/>at Ϫ80°C until sectioned. Coronal sections (20 m) were <lb/>cut with a cryostat (Leica CM3050 S, Leica Biosystems) <lb/>into three series and stored at Ϫ80°C. All tissue was <lb/>handled in a RNase-free environment. Tissue was post-<lb/>fixed in paraformaldehyde, followed by a wash in 2ϫ <lb/>saline-sodium citrate (SSC) and acetylation in a trietha-<lb/>nolamine/acetic anhydride solution, rinsed in dH 2 O, <lb/>washed in acetone/methanol solutions (1:1), and again in <lb/>2ϫ SSC. Tissue was first incubated at 65°C in hybridiza-<lb/>tion buffer (50% deionized formamide, 1% yeast tRNA, <lb/>10% dextran sulphate, 1ϫ Denhardt&apos;s solution, 5% 20ϫ <lb/>SSC) for 30 min before probe application. Riboprobes <lb/>were developed from linearized PK Bluescript SK(ϩ) with <lb/>inserted mouse-vasopressin gene (NM_027106.4, Gen-<lb/>script) using digoxygenin (DIG)-conjugated uracil. Ribo-<lb/>probe synthesized from this plasmid was added to <lb/>hybridization buffer at a concentration of 100 ng/100 l <lb/>and denatured at 90°C for 5 min. Tissue was then hybrid-<lb/>ized at 65°C for 24 h in a humid chamber. The tissue was <lb/>then subjected to two 10-min washes in 2ϫ SSC at room <lb/>temperature followed by a 15-min digestion with RNase A <lb/>(10 g/ml in 2ϫ SSC) at 37°C. This was followed by a <lb/>30-min 2ϫ SSC wash at 56°C and two 10-min 2ϫ SSC <lb/>washes at room temperature. The tissue was then <lb/>quenched in 1% H 2 O 2 in 1ϫ SSC for 15 min, rinsed twice <lb/>in 1ϫ SSC with 0.1% Tween followed by one 5-min TBS <lb/>(20 mM Tris and 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.6) wash. Blocking <lb/>solution (normal sheep serum and bovine caesin) was <lb/>applied and tissue was incubated for 30 min followed by <lb/>a 2-h, room temperature incubation with anti-DIG-HRP <lb/>(1:200, Roche Applied Sciences). Unbound antibody was <lb/>washed away with three 10-min washes in TBS-T (0.05% <lb/>Tween in TBS). DIG-labeled probe signal was amplified <lb/>and visualized using a TSA Plus Fluorescein kit (PerkinEl-<lb/>mer) by incubating sections in a 1:50 dilution of the Flu-<lb/>orescein working solution for 12 min followed by three <lb/>10-min washes in TBS. Tissue was then cover-slipped <lb/>using Prolong Gold (Life Technologies) for subsequent <lb/>imaging and tissue analysis. Tissue processed using <lb/>sense RNA probe generated no specific labeling. A subset <lb/>of brain sections was Nissl stained to determine whether <lb/>viral vector injections resulted in a non-specific loss of <lb/>BNST cells. <lb/>Tissue analysis <lb/>Bilateral images were taken at 10ϫ magnification using <lb/>a Zeiss Axio Imager.M2 microscope (Carl Zeiss Microim-<lb/>aging), which transferred fluorescent images (FITC <lb/>contrast reflector) to image analysis software (Stereo In-<lb/>vestigator, MicroBrightField, RRID:SCR_002526). Imag-<lb/>ing domains (2 mm 2 ) were placed with reference to <lb/>anatomic landmarks (ventricles, fiber tracts; Paxinos and <lb/>Franklin, 2012). Fluorescently labeled AVP mRNA-<lb/>expressing cells were counted in the BNST in both hemi-<lb/>spheres and averaged over three sections covering the <lb/>extent of the AVP cell population in the BNST. In addition, <lb/>we counted nearby accessory AVP mRNA expressing <lb/>cells (Rood and De Vries, 2011) as well as average label <lb/>intensity for AVP mRNA in the paraventricular nucleus of <lb/>the hypothalamus (PVN; ImageJ) to determine any possi-<lb/>ble off-target effects of our injections. Although we <lb/>counted AVP mRNA-expressing cells in the PVN as well, <lb/>AVP mRNA label intensity was chosen as the preferred <lb/>method for quantification due to the difficulty of discrim-<lb/>inating between overlapping AVP cells in PVN. Lastly, we <lb/>Nissl stained and imaged BNST tissue at 20ϫ magnifica-<lb/>tion to confirm no significant cell loss. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 Statistical analysis <lb/>Figure <lb/>Data structure <lb/>Type of test <lb/>Sample size <lb/>Statistical data <lb/>1B, AVP cell count in <lb/>BNST <lb/>Normal distribution Independent samples t test Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 11 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: p ϭ 0.00014 (two-tailed), t ϭ 4.57, df ϭ 22; <lb/>Cohen&apos;s d ϭ 2.64 <lb/>Females: p ϭ 0.0025 (two-tailed), t ϭ 3.58, df ϭ 19; <lb/>Cohen&apos;s d ϭ 2.02 <lb/>1C, AVP cell count in <lb/>nearby accessory area <lb/>Normal distribution Independent samples t test Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 11 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: p ϭ 0.987 (two-tailed) t ϭ -0.16, df ϭ 22 <lb/>Females: p ϭ 0.89 (two-tailed) t ϭ -0.15, df ϭ 19 <lb/>1D, AVP fluorescent <lb/>intensity (au) in the <lb/>PVN and cell count in <lb/>the PVN <lb/>Normal distribution Independent samples t test Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Intensity (au) measurement: <lb/>Males: p ϭ 0.947 (two-tailed), t ϭ 0.66, df ϭ 20 <lb/>Females: p ϭ 0.289 (two-tailed) t ϭ -1.10, df ϭ 19 <lb/>Cell counts: <lb/>Males: p ϭ 0.514 (two-tailed) t ϭ 0.66, df ϭ 20 <lb/>Females: p ϭ 0.82 (two-tailed) t ϭ 0.79, df ϭ 19 <lb/>1E, Nissl cell count in <lb/>BNST <lb/>Normal distribution Independent samples t test Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 6 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 9 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 8 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 6 <lb/>Males: p ϭ 0.439 (two-tailed), t ϭ 0.79, df ϭ 13 <lb/>Females: p ϭ 0.44 (two-tailed), t ϭ -0.80, df ϭ 12 <lb/>2A,B, social investigation <lb/>(live animal condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>two repeated measure <lb/>[sex of stimulus, <lb/>location of stimulus (two <lb/>levels)], followed by <lb/>independent samples t <lb/>test with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 11 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 261.34, p ϭ 1.0792E-13 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 0.62 , p ϭ 0.438 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 5.89, p ϭ 0.024 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 10.71, p ϭ <lb/>0.003 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 59.35, p <lb/>ϭ 1.0976E-7 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) <lb/>ϭ 11.16, p ϭ 0.003 <lb/>Investigation of female stimulus: p ϭ 1.0 (two-tailed) t <lb/>ϭ -0.70, df ϭ 22 <lb/>Investigation of male stimulus: p ϭ 0.004 (two-tailed) t <lb/>ϭ 3.75, df ϭ 22; Cohen&apos;s d ϭ 1.52 <lb/>Investigation of clean stimulus in female condition: p ϭ <lb/>0.70 (two-tailed) t ϭ -1.40, df ϭ 22 <lb/>Investigation of clean stimulus in male condition: p ϭ <lb/>1.0 (two-tailed) t ϭ -0.92, df ϭ 22 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 55.92, p ϭ 4.4965E-7 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 1.60 , p ϭ 0.29 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 2.16, p ϭ 0.161 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 11.58, p ϭ <lb/>0.001 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 3.12, p ϭ <lb/>0.09 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) <lb/>ϭ 0.004, p ϭ 0.94 <lb/>Investigation of female stimulus: p ϭ 0.33 (two-tailed) t <lb/>ϭ 1.82, df ϭ 19 <lb/>Investigation of male stimulus: p ϭ 0.51 (two-tailed) t <lb/>ϭ 0.67, df ϭ 19 <lb/>Investigation of clean stimulus in female condition: p ϭ <lb/>0.58 (two-tailed) t ϭ 0.57, df ϭ 19 <lb/>Investigation of clean stimulus in male condition: p ϭ <lb/>0.06 (two-tailed) t ϭ -2.69, df ϭ 19 <lb/>2C,D, social investigation <lb/>(urine condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>two repeated measure <lb/>[sex of stimulus, <lb/>location of stimulus (two <lb/>levels)] <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 <lb/>AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 11 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 <lb/>AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 117.39, p ϭ 2.7526E-10 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 0.07 , p ϭ 0.79 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 1.31, p ϭ 0.26 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.05, p ϭ <lb/>0.003 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 59.35, p <lb/>ϭ 0.82 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,22) <lb/>ϭ 0.22, p ϭ 0.64 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 60.33, p ϭ 2.5924E-7 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 2.9 , p ϭ 0.10 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 1.48, p ϭ 0.161 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 1.16, p ϭ 0.30 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 4.27, p ϭ <lb/>0.53 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ LOCATION OF STIMULUS(1,19) <lb/>ϭ 2.91, p ϭ 0.10 <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 Continued <lb/>Figure <lb/>Data structure <lb/>Type of test <lb/>Sample size <lb/>Statistical data <lb/>Table 2, social <lb/>investigation (time spent <lb/>in zones, live animal <lb/>condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>two repeated measure <lb/>[sex of stimulus, <lb/>location of zone (two <lb/>levels)] <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 15.68, p ϭ 0.001 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 0.0002 , p ϭ 0.99 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 1.33, p ϭ 0.26 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.01, p ϭ 0.922 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 14.30, p ϭ <lb/>0.001 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.13, <lb/>p ϭ 0.72 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 1.56, p ϭ 0.23 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 1.70 , p ϭ 0.21 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 2.32, p ϭ 0.14 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 2.21, p ϭ 0.15 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 6.73, p ϭ 0.017 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 0.04, <lb/>p ϭ 0.85 <lb/>Table 2, social <lb/>investigation (distance <lb/>traveled, live animal <lb/>condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>one repeated measure <lb/>(sex of stimulus) <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 2.16, p ϭ 0.16 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 3.48, p ϭ 0.33 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.01, p ϭ 0.92 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 0.000043, p ϭ 0.96 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 3.47, p ϭ 0.08 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 0.01, p ϭ 0.91 <lb/>Not shown, social <lb/>investigation (time spent <lb/>in zones, urine condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>two repeated measure <lb/>[sex of stimulus, <lb/>location of zone (two <lb/>levels)] <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.07, p ϭ 0.80 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 3.21 , p ϭ 0.08 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.52, p ϭ 0.48 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.75, p ϭ 0.40 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.26, p ϭ 0.61 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,22) ϭ 0.56, <lb/>p ϭ 0.82 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 1.14, p ϭ 0.30 F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ <lb/>4.28 , p ϭ 0.54 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 0.66, p ϭ 0.43 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 5.10, p ϭ 0.12 <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ 0.19, p ϭ 0.67 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS ϫ ZONE LOCATION(1,19) ϭ <lb/>0.0003, p ϭ 0.99 <lb/>Not shown, social <lb/>investigation (distance <lb/>traveled, urine condition) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>one repeated measure <lb/>(sex of stimulus), <lb/>followed by independent <lb/>samples t test with <lb/>Bonferroni correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.73, p ϭ 0.79 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 2.85, p ϭ 0.11 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.70, p ϭ 0.41 <lb/>Females: <lb/>F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 0.15, p ϭ 0.70 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 7.6, p ϭ 0.012 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,19) ϭ 0.33, p ϭ 0.57 <lb/>distance traveled in male urine condition: p ϭ 0.05 <lb/>(two-tailed), t ϭ -2.42, df ϭ 19 <lb/>distance traveled in male urine condition: p ϭ 0.19 <lb/>(two-tailed), t ϭ -1.93, df ϭ 19 <lb/>3A,B, UM (live animal <lb/>condition) <lb/>Males: normal <lb/>distribution <lb/>Females: <lb/>non-normal <lb/>Males: mixed model <lb/>analysis with one <lb/>between-subject factor <lb/>(genotype) and one <lb/>repeated measure (sex <lb/>of stimulus), followed by <lb/>independent samples t <lb/>test with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Females: Mann-Whitney U <lb/>test, independent <lb/>samples with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 52.62, p ϭ 0.00000029 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 23.72, p ϭ .000072 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 21.02, p ϭ 0.000145 <lb/>UM to female stimulus: p ϭ 0.000112 (two-tailed) t ϭ <lb/>-4.6, df ϭ 22; Cohen&apos;s d ϭ 2.04 <lb/>UM to male stimulus: p ϭ 0.16 (two-tailed) t ϭ -1.45, <lb/>df ϭ 22 <lb/>Females: <lb/>UM to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.15 <lb/>(two-tailed), U ϭ 20 <lb/>UM to male stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.32 (two-<lb/>tailed), U ϭ 32 <lb/>3C,D, UM (urine condition) Males: normal <lb/>distribution <lb/>Females: <lb/>non-normal <lb/>Males: mixed model <lb/>analysis with one <lb/>between-subject factor <lb/>(genotype) and one <lb/>repeated measure (sex <lb/>of stimulus) <lb/>Females: Mann-Whitney U <lb/>test, independent <lb/>samples with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.53, p ϭ 0.48 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 12.51, p ϭ 0.002 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ SEX OF STIMULUS(1,22) ϭ 0.16, p ϭ 0.70 <lb/>Females: <lb/>UM to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.467 <lb/>(two-tailed), U ϭ 52 <lb/>UM to male stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.858 (two-<lb/>tailed), U ϭ 32 <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 Continued <lb/>Figure <lb/>Data structure <lb/>Type of test <lb/>Sample size <lb/>Statistical data <lb/>4A,B, USVs (live animal <lb/>condition) <lb/>Non-normal <lb/>Mann-Whitney U test, <lb/>independent samples <lb/>with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: USV to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ <lb/>1.0 (two sided), U ϭ 64 <lb/>USV to male stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.334 (two <lb/>sided), U ϭ 47 <lb/>Females: USV with male stimulus across genotype: p <lb/>ϭ 0.16 (two-tailed), U ϭ 52 <lb/>USV to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.18 <lb/>(two-tailed), U ϭ 58 <lb/>4E,F, USVs (live animal <lb/>condition), syllable type <lb/>Non-normal/ <lb/>homogenous <lb/>Mann-Whitney U test, <lb/>independent samples <lb/>with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 6 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 7 <lb/>Males: USV syllable type (all two-tailed): <lb/>short: p ϭ 0.14, U ϭ 10, composite: p ϭ 1.0, U ϭ 22, <lb/>downward: p ϭ 0.63, U ϭ 17, <lb/>upward: p ϭ 0.63, U ϭ 17, 1 frequency jump: p ϭ <lb/>0.45, U ϭ 15, modulated: p ϭ 0.37, U ϭ 27, <lb/>multiple frequency jumps: p ϭ 0.63, U ϭ 24.5, u-<lb/>shape: p ϭ 0.83, U ϭ 19.5, flat: p ϭ 0.73, U ϭ 18, <lb/>chevron: p ϭ 0.08, U ϭ 39 <lb/>4C,D, USVs (urine <lb/>condition) <lb/>Non-normal <lb/>Mann-Whitney U test, <lb/>independent samples <lb/>with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: USV to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ <lb/>0.77 (two sided), U ϭ 60 <lb/>USV to male stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.50 (two <lb/>sided), U ϭ 52 <lb/>Females: USV with male stimulus across genotype: p <lb/>ϭ 0.49 (two sided), U ϭ 58 <lb/>USV to female stimulus across genotype: p ϭ 0.26 <lb/>(two sided), U ϭ 60 <lb/>5A,B, EPM (open/closed <lb/>arm measurements) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>one repeated measure <lb/>(open/closed arm) <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F OPEN/CLOSED ARM(1,22) ϭ 51.74, p ϭ 7.826E-7 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 0.36 , p ϭ 0.52 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ OPEN/CLOSED ARM(1,22) ϭ 2.81, p ϭ 0.11 <lb/>Females: F OPEN/CLOSED ARM(1,19) ϭ 189.41, p ϭ <lb/>2.477E-11 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 0.30 , p ϭ 0.60 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ OPEN/CLOSED ARM(1,19) ϭ 1.30, p ϭ 0.59 <lb/>5C,D, EPM (additional <lb/>anxiety measurements) <lb/>Normal distribution Mixed model analysis with <lb/>one between-subject <lb/>factor (genotype) and <lb/>one repeated measure <lb/>(stretch attends/head <lb/>dips) <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: F STRETCH ATTENDS/HEAD DIPS(1,22) ϭ 262.1, p ϭ <lb/>1.0479E-13 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,22) ϭ 0.68 , p ϭ .42 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ STRETCH ATTENDS/HEAD DIPS(1,22) ϭ 3.90, p ϭ <lb/>0.16 <lb/>Females: F STRETCH ATTENDS/HEAD DIPS(1,19) ϭ 33.82, p ϭ <lb/>0.000016 <lb/>F GENOTYPE(1,19) ϭ 2.03 , p ϭ 0.17 <lb/>F GENOTYPE ϫ STRETCH ATTENDS/HEAD DIPS(1,19) ϭ 0.80, p ϭ <lb/>0.382 <lb/>6A,B, sex behavior <lb/>(latency to mount, number <lb/>of female rejections) <lb/>Normal distribution Independent samples t test <lb/>with Bonferroni <lb/>correction <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: latency to mount: p ϭ 0.31 (two-tailed), t ϭ <lb/>1.04, df ϭ 22 <lb/>Females: latency to be mounted: p ϭ 0.03 (two-tailed), <lb/>t ϭ -0.52, df ϭ 19 <lb/>number of rejections: p ϭ 0.61 (two-tailed), t ϭ -0.52, <lb/>df ϭ 19 <lb/>6C,D, sex behavior <lb/>(percent mounted) <lb/>NA <lb/>Pearson&apos;s 2 <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: Pearson&apos;s 2 : p ϭ 0.34 <lb/>Females: Pearson&apos;s 2 : p ϭ 1.2797E-27 <lb/>7A, aggressive behavior <lb/>(latency) <lb/>Non-normal <lb/>Mann-Whitney U test, <lb/>independent samples <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: latency to attack across genotype: p ϭ 0.955 <lb/>(two sided), U ϭ 60 <lb/>Females: NA <lb/>7B, aggressive behavior <lb/>(percent attacking) <lb/>NA <lb/>Pearson&apos;s 2 <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 10 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 13 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 8 <lb/>Males: Pearson&apos;s 2 : p ϭ 0.85 (two sided) <lb/>Females: NA <lb/>8A,B, odor discrimination <lb/>Normal distribution Paired samples t test with <lb/>Bonferroni correction <lb/>between odors <lb/>Males: AVP-iCre-ϭ 11 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 5 <lb/>Females: AVP-iCre-ϭ 5 AVP-iCreϩ ϭ 7 <lb/>Males (all two-tailed, iCre-df ϭ 10, iCreϩ df ϭ 4): <lb/>water (3) vs almond (1): t ϭ 5.132, p ϭ 0.0004 (iCre-), <lb/>t (4) ϭ 5.261, p ϭ 0.006 (iCreϩ) <lb/>almond (3) vs coconut (1): t ϭ 1.21, p ϭ 0.20 (iCre-), <lb/>t ϭ 1.725, p ϭ 0.16 (iCreϩ) <lb/>coconut (3) vs male urine (1): t ϭ 11.41, p Ͻ 0.00001 <lb/>(iCre-), t ϭ 6.675, p ϭ 0.003 (iCreϩ) <lb/>male urine (3) vs female urine (1): t ϭ 7.936, p ϭ <lb/>0.00001 (iCre-), t ϭ 8.313, p ϭ 0.001 (iCreϩ) <lb/>Females (all two-tailed, iCre-df ϭ 10, iCreϩ df ϭ 4): <lb/>water (3) vs almond (1): t ϭ 1.431, p ϭ 0.226 (iCre-), <lb/>t ϭ 1.56, p ϭ 0.218 (iCreϩ) <lb/>almond (3) vs coconut (1): t ϭ 2.250, p ϭ 0.09 (iCre-), <lb/>t ϭ 2.10, p ϭ 0.10 (iCreϩ) <lb/>coconut (3) vs male urine (1): t ϭ 6.197, p ϭ 0.003 <lb/>(iCre-), t ϭ 7.454, p ϭ 0.0003 (iCreϩ) <lb/>male urine (3) vs female urine (1): t ϭ 7.071, p ϭ 0.002 <lb/>(iCre-), t ϭ 5.211, p ϭ 0.002 (iCreϩ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Statistical analysis <lb/>All data were analyzed and graphed in R (3.4.4; R Core <lb/>Team, 2017). Histology, social investigation, movement, <lb/>UM (in male subjects), odor discrimination, and EPM <lb/>data met the assumptions of parametric statistical tests. <lb/>Therefore, we analyzed histologic data with t tests and <lb/>data on social investigation, movement (distance traveled, <lb/>time in chambers containing stimulus and clean cages) <lb/>and male UM with mixed-model ANOVAs [between-<lb/>subject factor: genotype (iCreϩ, iCre-); within-subject <lb/>factors: sex of stimulus (male, female); preference for <lb/>stimulus (stimulus, clean) followed by t tests assessing <lb/>genotype effects]. Total distance traveled within the ap-<lb/>paratus was analyzed using a mixed-model ANOVA <lb/>(between-subject factor: genotype; within-subject factor: <lb/>sex of stimulus) as was time spent in open/closed arms in <lb/>the EPM test (between-subject factor: genotype; within-<lb/>subject factor: arm); effects of genotype on additional <lb/>anxiety behaviors (stretch-attend, head-dips) were ana-<lb/>lyzed using t tests. We determined whether subjects <lb/>could discriminate between odors by comparing odor <lb/>investigation on the last trial for one odor and odor investi-<lb/>gation on the first trial of the subsequent odor using paired t <lb/>tests. The number of female UMs, USVs, USV syllable type, <lb/>measures of copulatory behavior, and aggression behavior <lb/>were not normally distributed and could not be transformed, <lb/>therefore, we analyzed genotype effects using pairwise <lb/>Mann-Whitney U tests. Differences in proportion of animals <lb/>engaging in copulatory/aggressive behaviors across geno-<lb/>type was assessed using 2 tests. All post hoc pairwise <lb/>comparisons report Bonferroni-corrected p values and Co-<lb/>hen&apos;s d for effect size when statistically significant. Results <lb/>were considered significant if p Ͻ 0.05. All statistical tests <lb/>are presented in Table 1. <lb/>Results <lb/>Histology <lb/>Injection of a viral vector encoding a Cre-dependent <lb/>cell-death construct into the BNST highly effectively re-<lb/>duced AVP cell numbers in both iCreϩ males and fe-<lb/>males, which had only 10% of the number found in iCre-<lb/>subjects (males: t (22) ϭ 4.57, p ϭ 0.00014, d ϭ 2.64; <lb/>females: t (19) ϭ 3.58, p ϭ 0.0025, d ϭ 2.02; Fig. 1B), <lb/>without significantly reducing the number of nearby ac-<lb/>cessory AVP mRNA-expressing cells (males: t (22) ϭ -0.16, <lb/>p ϭ 0.98; females: t (19) ϭ -0.15, p ϭ 0.89; Fig. 1C) or total <lb/>level of AVP mRNA label in the PVN (males: t (20) ϭ 0.66, p <lb/>ϭ 0.947; females: t (19) ϭ -1.10, p ϭ 0.29; Fig. 1D), sug-<lb/>gesting that there were no significant off-target effects. <lb/>We also observed no difference in the number of AVP <lb/>mRNA-expressing cells in the PVN between genotype <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>e <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>r <lb/>U <lb/>: <lb/>s <lb/>u <lb/>l <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>S <lb/>l <lb/>a <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>A <lb/>: <lb/>s <lb/>u <lb/>l <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>S <lb/>male <lb/>subject <lb/>female <lb/>subject <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>** <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>iCre− stimulus <lb/>iCre− clean <lb/>iCre+ stimulus <lb/>iCre+ clean <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>Figure 2. BNST AVP cell ablations in iCreϩ males reduced male-male social investigation. Boxplot and individual data points of time spent <lb/>investigating male or female animals or their urine versus clean control stimuli within the three-chamber apparatus. A, B, Time spent <lb/>investigating either a caged female versus a clean cage or a caged male versus clean cage. A, iCre-(males: n ϭ 13, females: n ϭ 13) and <lb/>iCreϩ mice (males: n ϭ 11, females: n ϭ 8) differed in preference for investigating the stimulus depending on the sex of stimulus (p ϭ 0.003). <lb/>Post hoc analysis revealed iCreϩ males significantly decreased investigation of the male animal compared to iCre-littermates p ϭ 0.004. <lb/>B, iCre-and iCreϩ females did not differ in investigation (p ϭ 0.94). C, D, Time spent investigating either female urine or male urine versus <lb/>saline control placed on filter paper. iCre-and iCreϩ subjects did not differ in their investigation of female or male urine. C, Male subjects: <lb/>p ϭ 0.64. D, Female subjects: p ϭ 0.10. Note scale difference in animal investigation time between male and female subjects; ‫ءء‬ indicates <lb/>significant effect of genotype, p ϭ 0.004. Boxplot representations as in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>10 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>(males: t (20) ϭ 0.66, p ϭ 0.514; females: t (19) ϭ 0.79, p ϭ <lb/>0.82; Table 1). In addition, Nissl-stained tissue from a <lb/>subset of subjects revealed no overall cell loss in the <lb/>BNST (males: t (13) ϭ 0.79, p ϭ 0.439; females: t (12) ϭ <lb/>-0.80, p ϭ 0.44 (Fig. 1E). Two iCreϩ males and two iCreϩ <lb/>females were removed from the analysis as their AVP cell <lb/>numbers in the BNST were Ͼ3 standard deviations above <lb/>the mean, which we interpreted as off-target injections. <lb/>Two additional iCreϩ females were removed due to uni-<lb/>lateral AVP cell loss in the PVN. <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations in iCre؉ males reduced <lb/>male-male social investigation <lb/>Mice from both genotypes investigated female stimulus <lb/>animals more than male stimulus animals (males subjects: <lb/>F (1,22) ϭ 261.34, p Ͻ 0.00001; female subjects: F (1,19) ϭ <lb/>55.92, p Ͻ 0.00001) and had similar overall levels of <lb/>investigation (male subjects: F (1,22) ϭ 0.62, p ϭ 0.438; <lb/>female subjects: F (1,19) ϭ 1.60, p ϭ 0.29). However, iCre-<lb/>and iCreϩ males differed in preference for investigating <lb/>the stimulus animal depending on the sex of stimulus <lb/>(F (1,22) ϭ 11.16, p ϭ 0.003). Post hoc comparisons re-<lb/>vealed that iCreϩ males significantly decreased investi-<lb/>gation of male animals compared to iCre-littermates (t (22) <lb/>ϭ 3.75, p ϭ 0.004, d ϭ 1.52; Fig. 2A) but not female <lb/>stimulus animals (t (22) ϭ -0.70, p ϭ 1.0), while ablation of <lb/>these cells in females did not affect social investigation <lb/>(F (1,19) ϭ 0.004, p ϭ 0.94; Fig. 2B). <lb/>Males of both genotypes investigated female urine more <lb/>than male urine (F (1,22) ϭ 117.39, p Ͻ 0.00001), whereas female <lb/>subjects investigated male urine more than female urine (F (1,19) <lb/>ϭ 60.33, p Ͻ 0.00001). iCreϩ mice did not investigate urine <lb/>Table 2. Table of median (interquartile range) distance traveled and time spent in stimulus or clean cage chamber <lb/>Male subjects <lb/>Female subjects <lb/>iCre-<lb/>iCreϩ <lb/>iCre-<lb/>iCreϩ <lb/>Stimulus <lb/>Female <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Male <lb/>Female <lb/>Male <lb/>Distance traveled (m) <lb/>0.33 (0.22-0.54) <lb/>0.32 (0.16-0.5) <lb/>0.34 (0.19-0.48) <lb/>0.29 (0.13-0.44) <lb/>0.28 (0.08-0.38) <lb/>0.23 (0.01-0.47) <lb/>0.35 (0.16-0.42) <lb/>0.34 (0.04-0.5) <lb/>Time in stimulus chamber (s) <lb/>185 (129-248) <lb/>127 (78-195) <lb/>175 (111-229) <lb/>97 (15-209) <lb/>174 (102-246) <lb/>147 (30-227) <lb/>155.75 (23-198) <lb/>119 (91-155) <lb/>Time in clean chamber (s) <lb/>86 (45-122) <lb/>127 (73-155) <lb/>90 (49-158) <lb/>130 (67-231) <lb/>90 (43-176) <lb/>113 (52-240) <lb/>106 (48-170) <lb/>136 (74-282) <lb/>iCre-and iCreϩ mice did not differ in distance traveled, time spent in animal stimulus, or clean stimulus chambers. <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>area <lb/>(cm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>area <lb/>(cm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>area <lb/>(cm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>*** <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>area <lb/>(cm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>female <lb/>male <lb/>iCre− <lb/>iCre+ <lb/>e <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>r <lb/>U <lb/>: <lb/>s <lb/>u <lb/>l <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>S <lb/>l <lb/>a <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>A <lb/>: <lb/>s <lb/>u <lb/>l <lb/>u <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>S <lb/>male <lb/>subject <lb/>female <lb/>subject <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Figure 3. BNST AVP cell ablations in iCreϩ males increased UM to females. Boxplot and individual data points of UM in presence <lb/>of males or females or their urine within the three-chamber apparatus. A, iCre-(males: n ϭ 13, females: n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ mice <lb/>(males: n ϭ 11, females: n ϭ 8) differed in UM depending on the sex of stimulus (p ϭ 0.00015). Post hoc analysis revealed iCreϩ males <lb/>significantly increased UM to the female stimulus compared to iCre-littermates (p ϭ 0.000112). B, iCre-and iCreϩ females did not <lb/>differ in UM to stimulus animals [p ϭ 0.32 (males), p ϭ 0.15 (females)]. C, D, UM with either female urine or male urine present. iCre-<lb/>and iCreϩ subjects did not differ in UM to female or male urine. C, Male subjects: p ϭ 0.70. D, Female subjects: p ϭ 0.467 (female <lb/>stimulus), p ϭ 0.858 (male stimulus); ‫ءءء‬ indicates significant effect of genotype, p ϭ 0.00015. Boxplot representations as in <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>differently from iCre-littermates (males: F (1,22) ϭ 0.22, p ϭ 0.64; <lb/>females: F (1,19) ϭ 2.91, p ϭ 0.10; Fig. 2C,D). <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations in iCre؉ animals did not <lb/>alter the amount or spatial distribution of activity <lb/>Overall, mice of both genotypes traveled similar dis-<lb/>tances throughout the three-chamber apparatus (males: <lb/>F (1,22) ϭ 3.48, p ϭ 0.33; females: F (1,19) ϭ 3.47, p ϭ 0.08); <lb/>this pattern did not differ when presented with female or <lb/>male stimulus animals (males: F (1,22) ϭ 0.01, p ϭ 0.92; <lb/>females: F (1,19) ϭ 0.01, p ϭ 0.91). There were no differences <lb/>between genotypes in the amount of time mice spent in the <lb/>stimulus and clean chamber zones (males: F (1,22) ϭ 0.13, p ϭ <lb/>0.72; females: F (1,19) ϭ 0.04, p ϭ 0.85; Table 2). <lb/>Figure 4. BNST AVP cell ablations in iCreϩ animals did not alter USVs. Boxplot and individual data points of USV in presence of a <lb/>male or female or their urine within the three-chamber apparatus. A, B, iCre-(males: n ϭ 13, females: n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ mice (males: <lb/>n ϭ 11, females: n ϭ 8) did not differ by genotype in USV production. A, Male subjects: p ϭ 1.0 (female stimulus), p ϭ 0.33 (male <lb/>stimulus). B, Female subjects: p ϭ 0.18 (female stimulus), p ϭ 0.16 (male stimulus). C, D, USV with either female urine or male urine <lb/>present. iCre-and iCreϩ subjects did not differ in USVs to female or male urine. C, Male subjects: p ϭ 0.77 (female stimulus), p ϭ <lb/>0.5 (male stimulus). D, Female subjects: p ϭ 0.26 (female stimulus), p ϭ 0.49 (male stimulus). E, USV emitted by male mice were <lb/>gammatone-transformed (200-ms window) and divided into 10 categories of calls based on spectrographic parameters. F, Male USV <lb/>syllable type (iCre-n ϭ 6; iCreϩ n ϭ 7). BNST-AVP ablations did not change the percentage of USV syllable types produced between <lb/>genotypes. Boxplot representations as in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>BNST AVP cell ablated iCre؉ males increased UM to <lb/>females <lb/>Male mice UM more in the presence of females than <lb/>males (F (1,22) ϭ 52.62, p Ͻ 0.00001. iCre-and iCreϩ <lb/>males differed in overall UM (F (1,22) ϭ 23.72, p ϭ 0.00007) <lb/>and UM depending on the sex of stimulus (F (1,22) ϭ 21.02, <lb/>p ϭ 0.00015). Post hoc comparisons revealed that iCreϩ <lb/>males significantly increased UM to the female stimulus <lb/>compared to iCre-littermates (t (22) ϭ 4.6, p ϭ 0.000112, <lb/>d ϭ 2.04; Fig. 3A) but not to the male stimulus (t (22) ϭ 1.45, <lb/>p ϭ 0.16). iCre-and iCreϩ females did not differ in UM in <lb/>the presence of males (U ϭ 32, p ϭ 0.32) or females (U ϭ <lb/>20, p ϭ 0.15; Fig. 3A). Neither male nor female subjects <lb/>differed in UM to urine depending on the sex of stimulus <lb/>[male subjects: F (1,22) ϭ 1.16, p ϭ 0.70; female subjects: U <lb/>ϭ 52, p ϭ 0.467 (female stimulus), U ϭ 32, p ϭ 0.858 <lb/>(male stimulus)]. Only one male (iCreϩ) pooled urine in the <lb/>male condition, therefore we did not analyze pooled urine. <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations in iCre؉ animals did not <lb/>alter USVs <lb/>The total number of USVs emitted when iCre-and <lb/>iCreϩ mice were placed with female (male subjects: U ϭ <lb/>64, p ϭ 1.0; female subjects: U ϭ 58, p ϭ 0.18) or male <lb/>animals did not differ by genotype (male subjects: U ϭ 47, <lb/>p ϭ 0.33; female subjects: U ϭ 52, p ϭ 0.16; Fig. 4A,B). <lb/>Mice from both genotypes also did not differ in USVs to <lb/>female urine (male subjects: U ϭ 60, p ϭ 0.77; female <lb/>subjects: U ϭ 53, p ϭ 0.26) or male urine (male subjects: <lb/>U ϭ 52, p ϭ 0.5; female subjects: U ϭ 60, p ϭ 0.49; Fig. <lb/>4C,D). Additionally, BNST AVP cell ablations did not <lb/>change the percentage of USV syllable types produced <lb/>between male genotypes (short: U ϭ 10, p ϭ 0.14, com-<lb/>posite: U ϭ 22, p ϭ 1.0, downward: U ϭ 17, p ϭ 0.63, <lb/>upward: U ϭ 17, p ϭ 0.63, 1 frequency jump: U ϭ 15, p <lb/>ϭ 0.45, modulated: U ϭ 27, p ϭ 0.37, multiple frequency <lb/>jumps: U ϭ 24.5, p ϭ 0.63, u-shape: U ϭ 19.5, p ϭ 0.83, <lb/>flat: U ϭ 18, p ϭ 0.73, chevron: U ϭ 39, p ϭ 0.08; Fig. <lb/>4E,F). <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations in iCre؉ animals did not <lb/>influence anxiety-like behavior <lb/>All mice spent less time in the open arm than the closed <lb/>arm of the EPM (male subjects: F (1,22) ϭ 51.74, p Ͻ <lb/>0.000001; female subjects: F (1,19) ϭ 89.41, p Ͻ 0.000001). <lb/>iCre-and iCreϩ mice did not differ in the time spent in <lb/>either arm of the EPM (male subjects: F (1,22) ϭ 2.81, p ϭ <lb/>0.11; female subjects: F (1,19) ϭ 1.30, p ϭ 0.59; Fig. 5A,B). <lb/>Additionally, both genotypes did not differ in frequency of <lb/>stretch attend postures or head dips (male subjects: F (1,22) <lb/>ϭ 3.90, p ϭ 0.16; female subjects: F (1,19) ϭ 0.80, p ϭ 0.38; <lb/>Fig. 5C,D). <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations in iCre؉ animals did not <lb/>alter male copulatory behavior but did reduce <lb/>mounting of females <lb/>iCreϩ and iCre-males mounted females with similar <lb/>latencies and did not differ in the percentage of subjects <lb/>male <lb/>subject <lb/>female <lb/>subject <lb/>C <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>time (s) <lb/>open arms <lb/>closed arms <lb/>open arms <lb/>closed arms <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/># stretch attends <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/># head dips <lb/>iCre− <lb/>iCre+ <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/># stretch attends <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/># head dips <lb/>D <lb/>Figure 5. BNST AVP cell ablations in iCreϩ animals did not influence anxiety-like behavior. Boxplot and individual data points of time <lb/>spent in the open and closed arms within the EPM, number of stretch attends, and number of head dips. A, B, iCre-(males: n ϭ 13, <lb/>females: n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ mice (males: n ϭ 11, females: n ϭ 8) did not differ by genotype in time spent in open and closed arms. <lb/>A, Male subjects: p ϭ 0.11. B, Female subjects: p ϭ 0.59. C, D, iCre-mice (males: n ϭ 13, females: n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ mice (males: <lb/>n ϭ 11, females: n ϭ 8) did not differ by genotype in number of stretch attends or head dips. C, Male subjects: p ϭ 0.16. D, Female <lb/>subjects: p ϭ 0.38. Boxplot representations as in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>13 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>mounting and/or ejaculating (t (22) ϭ 1.04, p ϭ 0.31; Fig. <lb/>6A,C). However, it took longer for males to mount iCreϩ <lb/>females (U ϭ 22, p ϭ 0.03) and fewer iCreϩ females were <lb/>mounted overall as compared to iCre-females ( 2 (2), p Ͻ <lb/>0.000001). However, female iCreϩ mice did not reject <lb/>stimulus males more frequently than did iCre-females <lb/>(t (19) ϭ 0.52, p ϭ 0.61). One iCreϩ female was removed <lb/>during the sex behavior test and sex behavior analysis <lb/>because the stimulus male attacked the female. <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablation did not alter territorial <lb/>aggression <lb/>The proportion of male subjects that attacked the sub-<lb/>ordinate intruder in their home cage did not differ between <lb/>genotypes ( 2 (2), p ϭ 0.85) nor did they differ in attack <lb/>latency (U ϭ 60, p ϭ 0.955; Fig. 7A,B). Female subjects <lb/>did not attack female intruders. <lb/>BNST AVP cell ablations did not change the ability to <lb/>discriminate between social odors <lb/>Males and females of both genotypes were able to <lb/>discriminate between male and female urine odors [males: <lb/>t (10) ϭ 7.936, p ϭ 0.00001 (iCre-), t (4) ϭ 8.313, p ϭ 0.001 <lb/>(iCreϩ); females: t (4) ϭ 7.071, p ϭ 0.002 (iCre-), t (6) ϭ <lb/>5.211, p ϭ 0.002 (iCreϩ)] and could distinguish between <lb/>non-social and social odors [males: t (10) ϭ 11.41, p Ͻ <lb/>0.00001 (iCre-), t (4) ϭ 6.675, p ϭ 0.003 (iCreϩ); females: <lb/>t (4) ϭ 6.197, p ϭ 0.003 (iCre-), t (6) ϭ 7.454, p ϭ 0.0003 <lb/>(iCreϩ)]. However, subjects&apos; ability to discriminate be-<lb/>tween non-social odors was not robust (Fig. 8A,B). Al-<lb/>though both iCreϩ and iCre-males discriminated <lb/>between water and almond odor, females did not, and no <lb/>subjects discriminated between the two non-social odors <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We found that deletion of the sexually dimorphic AVP <lb/>cell group in the BNST significantly affected social behav-<lb/>ior in males, reducing social investigation of other males <lb/>and increasing UM in the presence of a female. In fe-<lb/>males, which have significantly fewer AVP BNST cells, <lb/>similar deletions minimally affected social behavior and <lb/>communication. This is the first time that direct alteration <lb/>of a male-biased, sexually-dimorphic population of neu-<lb/>male <lb/>subject <lb/>female <lb/>subject <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>latency (min) <lb/>* <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>latency (min) <lb/>iCre− <lb/>iCre+ <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>no ejaculation <lb/>ejaculation <lb/>ejaculation <lb/>mounted <lb/>not mounted <lb/>not <lb/>mounted <lb/>mounted <lb/>iCre-female subject <lb/>iCre+ female subject <lb/>iCre-male subject <lb/>iCre+ male subject <lb/>1 12 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 3 <lb/>2 6 <lb/>Figure 6. BNST AVP cell ablations in iCreϩ animals did not alter male copulatory behavior but did reduce mounting of females. <lb/>Boxplot and individual data points of male subject&apos;s latency to mount a female (A) or female subject&apos;s latency to be mounted (B). Pie <lb/>chart summarizing proportion of male subjects that ejaculated (C) or the proportion of female subjects mounted by a male (D) with <lb/>number of subjects in each category indicated. A, C, iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 11) male mice did not differ by genotype in their <lb/>latency to mount females or in the percentage of subjects ejaculating. B, D, iCreϩ (n ϭ 8) female mice were mounted at longer <lb/>latencies (p ϭ 0.03) and proportionally less (p Ͻ 0.000001) than iCre-(n ϭ 13) females; ‫ء‬ indicates significant effect of genotype, <lb/>p ϭ 0.03. Boxplot representations as in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>14 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>ropeptidergic cells has caused a sex difference in mam-<lb/>malian social responses. While several studies have <lb/>directly tested the social function of sexually-dimorphic <lb/>cell populations (Yang et al., 2013; Scott et al., 2015; <lb/>Unger et al., 2015; Wei et al., 2018), only one has found a <lb/>strong sex difference in social behavior tied to an ana-<lb/>tomic sexual dimorphism, in this case a female-biased <lb/>one (Scott et al., 2015). Our results indicate that sex <lb/>differences in AVP cells in the BNST contributes to sex-<lb/>ually dimorphic components of social communication. <lb/>Our experiments do not allow us to conclude that re-<lb/>moval of AVP production in the BNST, by and of itself, <lb/>caused the behavioral effects observed in this study. <lb/>Lesioning AVP cells also removed all other neuroactive <lb/>substances co-expressed by these cells, for example, <lb/>galanin (Miller et al., 1993), which also has been impli-<lb/>cated in control of social behavior (Wu et al., 2014). <lb/>Consequently, our behavioral results may be due to <lb/>depletion of AVP, or of co-transmitters from BNST pro-<lb/>jections, or both. Our finding of reduced male-male inves-<lb/>tigation following BNST AVP cell deletion, however, is <lb/>strikingly similar to the effects of RNA interference for the <lb/>homologous peptide arginine vasotocin (AVT) in the BNST <lb/>of territorial finches (Kelly and Goodson, 2013b) and sug-<lb/>gests that this effect is mainly due to a reduction of AVP <lb/>signal from the BNST. <lb/>Our cell deletion approach is, by design, permanent, <lb/>and so behavioral effects may reflect molecular, cellular, <lb/>and anatomic adjustments or compensations to chronic <lb/>depletion of AVP cells in the BNST. Indeed, long-term <lb/>pharmacological reduction of V1a receptor activity in the <lb/>LS, a key target of AVP cells in the BNST (De Vries and <lb/>Panzica, 2006), produces different changes in behavior <lb/>than acute receptor blockade (Liebsch et al., 1996; Everts <lb/>and Koolhaas, 1999). A lack of an effect on a behavior, <lb/>therefore, does not exclude involvement of these cells in <lb/>that behavior. Nevertheless, our findings of male-specific <lb/>alterations in social interactions and communication fol-<lb/>lowing deletion of AVP cells in the BNST strongly indicate <lb/>that in males these cells are critical for these functions. <lb/>One of the strongest effects of deletion of AVP cells in <lb/>the BNST was the reduction of same-sex social investi-<lb/>gation, which we found in males but not in females. <lb/>Importantly, this reduction was not due to a lack of gen-<lb/>eral social interest, as investigation of females was <lb/>unchanged. It was not due to changes in general chemo-<lb/>sensory function or motor behavior either, as odor habit-<lb/>uation or discrimination of non-social odors and detection <lb/>of social odors (male or female urine) was unaffected and <lb/>measures of general activity were also not changed. This <lb/>reduction can also not be explained by a general increase <lb/>in anxiety-like behaviors, because the lesions did not <lb/>affect behavior in the anxiogenic EPM. Instead, it sug-<lb/>gests that one function of AVP cells in the BNST is to <lb/>generate male-typical approach, investigation, and as-<lb/>sessment of potential territorial competitors (Oldfield <lb/>et al., 2015), which is consistent with the observation that <lb/>knocking down AVT mRNA in the BNST of territorial birds <lb/>reduces social contact with other males (Kelly and Good-<lb/>son, 2013b), and that overexpression of V1a receptors <lb/>(Landgraf et al., 2003) or AVP injections (Koolhaas et al., <lb/>1991) in the LS, a key target for AVP projections from the <lb/>BNST (De Vries and Panzica, 2006), increases active <lb/>male-male interactions and aggressive behavior in rats. <lb/>Indeed, retrodialysis of V1aR antagonist into the LS of <lb/>male rats blocks further territorial aggression during re-<lb/>peated resident-intruder tests (Veenema et al., 2010). Our <lb/>finding that deleting AVP cells in the BNST reduced in-<lb/>vestigation of potential competitors is consistent with <lb/>these findings. Our failure to see a change in aggressive <lb/>behavior is not. One explanation for this apparent discrep-<lb/>ancy is that AVP from other sources contribute to stimu-<lb/>lating effects on aggressive behavior in areas such as the <lb/>LS. For example, AVP cells in the MeA show similar <lb/>dimorphisms as BNST cells and project to overlapping <lb/>areas (De Vries and Panzica, 2006). Lesioning both cell <lb/>iCre− <lb/>iCre+ <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>7.5 <lb/>10.0 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>latency (min) <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>attack <lb/>no <lb/>attack <lb/>no <lb/>attack <lb/>attack <lb/>iCre-male subject <lb/>iCre+ male subject <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>Figure 7. BNST AVP cell ablation did not alter territorial aggression. A, Boxplot and individual data points of male subject&apos;s latency <lb/>to attack a subordinate intruder male. iCre-(n ϭ 13) and iCreϩ (n ϭ 11) male mice did not differ by genotype in latency to attack the <lb/>intruder (p ϭ 0.955). B, Pie chart summarizing proportion of male subjects that attacked the subordinate intruder in their home cage <lb/>with number of subjects in each category indicated. Subjects did not differ between genotypes (p ϭ 0.85). Boxplot representations <lb/>as in Figure 1. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>groups may be necessary to identify all behaviors in which <lb/>these sexually dimorphic cell groups are critically in-<lb/>volved. Nevertheless, AVP cells in the BNST appear to be <lb/>required for the proactive investigation of credible social <lb/>threats rather than for offensive aggression per se. <lb/>Ablation of AVP cells in the BNST of male, but not <lb/>female, mice strongly increased UM toward females, sug-<lb/>gesting that these cells normally suppress male scent <lb/>marking toward females. This increase in UM is not due to <lb/>excessive eliminative urination because it was not ob-<lb/>served toward male stimuli nor was it manifested as an <lb/>increase in pooled urine. It is possible that this increase is <lb/>simply due to increased proximity and interest in females. <lb/>However, males with deletions of AVP cells in the BNST <lb/>did not differ from control animals in time spent investi-<lb/>gating female stimuli, making this explanation less likely. <lb/>Although UM strongly depends on chemosensory pro-<lb/>cessing (Maruniak et al., 1986; Labov and Wysocki, 1989), <lb/>the increase in UM by lesioned males was not driven <lb/>primarily by female urine cues because marking to female <lb/>urine was not increased, suggesting that other cues, che-<lb/>mosensory as well as non-chemosensory, may drive this <lb/>increase in scent marking. Given the metabolic costs of <lb/>urination (Gosling et al., 2000) and the increased risks <lb/>associated with attraction of aggressive competitors and <lb/>predators toward urine marks (Desjardins et al., 1973; <lb/>Figure 8. BNST AVP cell ablations did not change the ability to discriminate between social odors. Time spent investigating water, <lb/>almond or coconut extract, male urine, or female urine. A, Males and B, females of both genotypes were able to discriminate between <lb/>male and female urine odors [A, males: p ϭ 0.00001 (iCreϪ), p ϭ 0.001 (iCreϩ); B, females: p ϭ 0.002 (iCreϪ), p ϭ 0.002 (iCreϩ)] <lb/>and could distinguish between non-social and social odors [males: p Ͻ 0.00001 (iCreϪ), p ϭ 0.003 (iCreϩ); p ϭ 0.003 (iCreϪ), p ϭ <lb/>0.0003 (iCreϩ)]. However, subjects&apos; ability to discriminate between non-social odors was not robust. Although both iCreϩ and iCreϪ <lb/>males discriminated between water and almond odor, females did not, and no subjects discriminated between the two non-social <lb/>odors. Data are expressed as mean (Ϯ) SEM; trial numbers are given on the x-axis; ‫ء‬ indicates significant difference (all p Ͻ 0.005) <lb/>between investigation of odors, irrespective of genotype. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>16 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Roberts et al., 2001), UM should be strongly regulated so <lb/>that signaling occurs in only specific social contexts. The <lb/>present results indicate that the BNST-AVP cells may be <lb/>a key part of the neural system that adaptively regulates <lb/>this critical signaling behavior. <lb/>Although AVP/AVT has been implicated in the produc-<lb/>tion of vocalizations across taxa (Goodson and Bass, <lb/>2001), deleting the AVP cells in the BNST did not signifi-<lb/>cantly alter the production of USVs in a reproductive <lb/>context. This is consistent with the few studies examining <lb/>male courtship vocalizations (in birds) that report no effect <lb/>of central infusions of AVT or V1a antagonists on female-<lb/>directed singing (Goodson and Adkins-Regan, 1999; <lb/>Goodson and Evans, 2004) or got mixed results from <lb/>antisense knock-down of BNST-AVP, with one study find-<lb/>ing no effect (Kelly et al., 2011) and another observing <lb/>decreased singing (Kelly and Goodson, 2013b). Most <lb/>other studies supporting a role for AVP/AVT in vocaliza-<lb/>tions have not identified the relevant neuroanatomical <lb/>source of the peptide or its locus of action (Wilczynski <lb/>et al., 2017) or tended to focus on stress-related or ag-<lb/>gressive vocalizations across development (Winslow and <lb/>Insel, 1993; Bleickardt et al., 2009; Iijima et al., 2014; <lb/>Lukas and Wöhr, 2015; Paul et al., 2016; Freeman et al., <lb/>2018). <lb/>Our study also points to a limited, sexually dimorphic <lb/>role of BNST AVP cells in reproductive behavior. Removal <lb/>of these cells in males did not alter copulatory behavior, <lb/>which is consistent with the absence of copulatory defi-<lb/>cits in whole-animal knock-outs of V1a or V1b receptors <lb/>(Wersinger et al., 2004, 2007). However, unexpectedly, <lb/>ablating these cells in females delayed, and reduced the <lb/>number of times they were mounted by males. This effect <lb/>may represent reduced attractiveness of the female or an <lb/>increased rejection of the male. The latter possibility <lb/>seems less likely, as we did not detect any change in male <lb/>investigation toward lesioned females, nor did such fe-<lb/>males reject males more frequently. It is possible that <lb/>these females show decreases in cryptic proceptive <lb/>and/or receptive behaviors. Although AVP has been im-<lb/>plicated in female rat sexual behavior, the pattern of prior <lb/>results is opposite to our findings: in rats, AVP reduced, <lb/>whereas V1a receptor antagonists increased, female sex-<lb/>ual behavior in rats (Södersten et al., 1983; Pedersen and <lb/>Boccia, 2006). However, as in these studies peptides <lb/>were injected into the lateral ventricle, it is unclear with <lb/>what AVP system they interacted. <lb/>Although central AVP has been repeatedly implicated in <lb/>the generation of anxiety states (Ebner et al., 2002; Biel-<lb/>sky et al., 2004; Raggenbass, 2008), we did not observe <lb/>changes in anxiety-like behavior of lesioned males or <lb/>females in a non-social anxiogenic environment (Hogg, <lb/>1996). This is somewhat surprising because AVP in the <lb/>LS, an important target of the BNST AVP cells (De Vries <lb/>and Panzica, 2006), controls anxious states. For example, <lb/>injections of AVP or V1aR antagonists, or V1aR knock-<lb/>down within LS all support the idea that AVP is anxiogenic <lb/>at this site (Landgraf et al., 1995; Liebsch et al., 1996; <lb/>Beiderbeck et al., 2007). However, since large lesions of <lb/>BNST have no effect on anxiety-like behavior in the EPM <lb/>task either (Treit et al., 1998), it may simply mean that, as <lb/>with aggressive behavior, AVP cells in the BNST are not <lb/>critically involved in anxiety-like behaviors, and that AVP <lb/>derived from other sources, such as the PVN or the <lb/>amygdala (Rood et al., 2013), also drive AVP&apos;s anxiogenic <lb/>action in the septum and elsewhere. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>A growing body of literature indicates that vasopressin <lb/>plays a sexually dimorphic role in control of social and <lb/>anxiety-related behaviors. In humans, for example, intra-<lb/>nasal vasopressin stimulates reciprocation of cooperation <lb/>in males and conciliatory behavior in females, while acti-<lb/>vating brain areas implicated in reward, social bonding, <lb/>arousal and memory in males, but not in females (Rilling <lb/>et al., 2014). In hamsters, hypothalamic injections of va-<lb/>sopressin stimulate aggression in males, while reducing it <lb/>in females (Terranova et al., 2016). In mice, a genetic <lb/>knock-out of the vasopressin V1a receptor gene reduces <lb/>anxiety-related behaviors in males, but not in females <lb/>(Bielsky et al., 2004, 2005). In rats, a V1a antagonist <lb/>reduces social play in males while increasing them in <lb/>females when injected intracerebroventricularly, but has <lb/>the exact opposite effect when injected into the septum <lb/>(Veenema et al., 2013). Although, these studies clearly <lb/>point at a sexually dimorphic role of vasopressin and its <lb/>cognate receptor in behavior, they do not identify which <lb/>AVP system is involved, and the opposite effects in play <lb/>behavior, depending on the area injected, suggests that <lb/>more than one system may be involved. By targeting a <lb/>specific AVP cell group directly, our study has identified <lb/>the sexually dimorphic AVP cells in the BNST as contrib-<lb/>uting to sex differences in social behavior, and has shown <lb/>the feasibility of following a similar approach in identifying <lb/>the contributions of other AVP systems in the brain as <lb/>well. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Albers HE (2012) The regulation of social recognition, social com-<lb/>munication and aggression: vasopressin in the social behavior <lb/>neural network. Horm Behav 61:283-292. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Arakawa H, Arakawa K, Blanchard DC, Blanchard RJ (2008a) A new <lb/>test paradigm for social recognition evidenced by urinary scent <lb/>marking behavior in C57BL/6J mice. Behav Brain Res 190:97-104. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Arakawa H, Blanchard DC, Arakawa K, Dunlap C, Blanchard RJ <lb/>(2008b) Scent marking behavior as an odorant communication in <lb/>mice. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 32:1236 -1248. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bakker J, Honda S-I, Harada N, Balthazart J (2002) The aromatase <lb/>knock-out mouse provides new evidence that estradiol is required <lb/>during development in the female for the expression of sociosex-<lb/>ual behaviors in adulthood. J Neurosci 22:9104 -9112. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Barkley MS, Goldman BD (1977) The effects of castration and Silas-<lb/>tic implants of testosterone on intermale aggression in the mouse. <lb/>Horm Behav 9:32-48. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Baum MJ, Keverne EB (2002) Sex difference in attraction thresholds <lb/>for volatile odors from male and estrous female mouse urine. Horm <lb/>Behav 41:213-219. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Beeman EA (1947) The relation of the interval between castration and <lb/>first encounter to the aggressive behavior of mice. Anat Rec <lb/>99:570. Medline <lb/>Beiderbeck DI, Neumann ID, Veenema AH (2007) Differences in <lb/>intermale aggression are accompanied by opposite vasopressin <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>17 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>release patterns within the septum in rats bred for low and high <lb/>anxiety. Eur J Neurosci 26:3597-3605. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bielsky IF, Hu SB, Szegda KL, Westphal H, Young LJ (2004) Pro-<lb/>found impairment in social recognition and reduction in anxiety-<lb/>like behavior in vasopressin V1a receptor knockout mice. <lb/>Neuropsychopharmacology 29:483-493. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bielsky IF, Hu SB, Young LJ (2005) Sexual dimorphism in the vaso-<lb/>pressin system: lack of an altered behavioral phenotype in female <lb/>V1a receptor knockout mice. Behav Brain Res 164:132-136. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bishop MJ, Chevins PF (1987) Urine odours and marking patterns in <lb/>territorial laboratory mice (Mus musculus). Behav Processes 15: <lb/>233-248. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bleickardt CJ, Mullins DE, Macsweeney CP, Werner BJ, Pond AJ, <lb/>Guzzi MF, Martin FDC, Varty GB, Hodgson RA (2009) Character-<lb/>ization of the V1a antagonist, JNJ-17308616, in rodent models of <lb/>anxiety-like behavior. Psychopharmacology 202:711-718. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline <lb/>Bradbury JW, Vehrencamp SL (1998) Principles of animal commu-<lb/>nication, Ed 2. Sunderland, MA: Sinauer Associates, Oxford Uni-<lb/>versity Press. <lb/>Caligioni CS (2009) Assessing reproductive status/stages in mice. <lb/>Curr Protoc Neurosci Appendix 4:Appendix 4I. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Chabout J, Sarkar A, Dunson DB, Jarvis ED (2015) Male mice song <lb/>syntax depends on social contexts and influences female prefer-<lb/>ences. Front Behav Neurosci 9:76. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Cole JC, Rodgers RJ (1993) An ethological analysis of the effects of <lb/>chlordiazepoxide and bretazenil (Ro 16-6028) in the murine ele-<lb/>vated plus-maze. Behav Pharmacol 4:573-580. Medline <lb/>Compaan JC, Buijs RM, Pool CW, De Ruiter AJ, Koolhaas JM (1993) <lb/>Differential lateral septal vasopressin innervation in aggressive and <lb/>nonaggressive male mice. Brain Res Bull 30:1-6. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/>Connor JL, Winston H (1972) Genetic analysis of conditioned emo-<lb/>tional responses in the mouse (Mus musculus L.). J Comp Physiol <lb/>Psychol 81:37-44. Medline <lb/>Coquelin A (1992) Urine-marking by female mice throughout their <lb/>reproductive cycle. Horm Behav 26:255-271. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Crawley JN (2007) Mouse behavioral assays relevant to the symp-<lb/>toms of autism. Brain Pathol 17:448 -459. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Crawley JN (2012) Translational animal models of autism and neu-<lb/>rodevelopmental disorders. Dialogues Clin Neurosci 14:293-305. <lb/>Medline <lb/>Dantzer R, Koob GF, Bluthé RM, Le Moal M (1988) Septal vasopres-<lb/>sin modulates social memory in male rats. Brain Res 457:143-147. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Darwin C (1871) The descent of man, and selection in relation to sex. <lb/>Princeton, NJ: Princeton University Press. <lb/>Desjardins C, Maruniak JA, Bronson FH (1973) Social rank in house <lb/>mice: differentiation revealed by ultraviolet visualization of urinary <lb/>marking patterns. Science 182:939 -941. CrossRef Medline <lb/>De Vries GJ (2008) Sex differences in vasopressin and oxytocin <lb/>innervation of the brain. Prog Brain Res 170:17-27. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>De Vries GJ, Buijs RM (1983) The origin of the vasopressinergic and <lb/>oxytocinergic innervation of the rat brain with special reference to <lb/>the lateral septum. Brain Res 273:307-317. CrossRef Medline <lb/>De Vries GJ, Boyle PA (1998) Double duty for sex differences in the <lb/>brain. Behav Brain Res 92:205-213. CrossRef Medline <lb/>De Vries GJ, Panzica GC (2006) Sexual differentiation of central <lb/>vasopressin and vasotocin systems in vertebrates: different mech-<lb/>anisms, similar endpoints. Neuroscience 138:947-955. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Dumais KM, Veenema AH (2016) Vasopressin and oxytocin receptor <lb/>systems in the brain: sex differences and sex-specific regulation of <lb/>social behavior. Front Neuroendocrinol 40:1-23. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Ebner K, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (2000) A single social <lb/>defeat experience selectively stimulates the release of oxytocin, <lb/>but not vasopressin, within the septal brain area of male rats. Brain <lb/>Res 872:87-92. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Ebner K, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (2002) Forced swim-<lb/>ming triggers vasopressin release within the amygdala to modulate <lb/>stress-coping strategies in rats. Eur J Neurosci 15:384 -388. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Everts HG, Koolhaas JM (1999) Differential modulation of lateral <lb/>septal vasopressin receptor blockade in spatial learning, social <lb/>recognition, and anxiety-related behaviors in rats. Behav Brain Res <lb/>99:7-16. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Everts HG, De Ruiter AJ, Koolhaas JM (1997) Differential lateral <lb/>septal vasopressin in wild-type rats: correlation with aggression. <lb/>Horm Behav 31:136 -144. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Freeman AR, Hare JF, Anderson WG, Caldwell HK (2018) Effects of <lb/>arginine vasopressin on Richardson&apos;s ground squirrel social and <lb/>vocal behavior. Behav Neurosci 132:34 -50. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Gheusi G, Bluth R-M, Goodall G, Dantzer R (1994) Social and indi-<lb/>vidual recognition in rodents: methodological aspects and neuro-<lb/>biological bases. Behav Processes 33:59 -87. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Goodson JL, Adkins-Regan E (1999) Effect of intraseptal vasotocin <lb/>and vasoactive intestinal polypeptide infusions on courtship song <lb/>and aggression in the male zebra finch (Taeniopygia guttata). J <lb/>Neuroendocrinol 11:19 -25. Medline <lb/>Goodson JL, Bass AH (2001) Social behavior functions and related <lb/>anatomical characteristics of vasotocin/vasopressin systems in <lb/>vertebrates. Brain Res Brain Res Rev 35:246 -265. Medline <lb/>Goodson JL, Evans AK (2004) Neural responses to territorial chal-<lb/>lenge and nonsocial stress in male song sparrows: segregation, <lb/>integration, and modulation by a vasopressin V1 antagonist. Horm <lb/>Behav 46:371-381. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Goodson JL, Kabelik D, Schrock SE (2009) Dynamic neuromodula-<lb/>tion of aggression by vasotocin: influence of social context and <lb/>social phenotype in territorial songbirds. Biol Lett 5:554 -556. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Gosling LM, Roberts SC, Thornton EA, Andrew MJ (2000) Life history <lb/>costs of olfactory status signalling in mice. Behav Ecol Sociobiol <lb/>48:328 -332. CrossRef <lb/>Halladay AK, Bishop S, Constantino JN, Daniels AM, Koenig K, <lb/>Palmer K, Messinger D, Pelphrey K, Sanders SJ, Singer AT, Taylor <lb/>JL, Szatmari P (2015) Sex and gender differences in autism spec-<lb/>trum disorder: summarizing evidence gaps and identifying emerg-<lb/>ing areas of priority. Mol Autism 6:36. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Hanson JL, Hurley LM (2012) Female presence and estrous state <lb/>influence mouse ultrasonic courtship vocalizations. PLoS One <lb/>7:e40782. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Hogg S (1996) A review of the validity and variability of the elevated <lb/>plus-maze as an animal model of anxiety. Pharmacol Biochem <lb/>Behav 54:21-30. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Ho JM, Murray JH, Demas GE, Goodson JL (2010) Vasopressin cell <lb/>groups exhibit strongly divergent responses to copulation and <lb/>male-male interactions in mice. Horm Behav 58:368 -377. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline <lb/>Iijima M, Yoshimizu T, Shimazaki T, Tokugawa K, Fukumoto K, <lb/>Kurosu S, Kuwada T, Sekiguchi Y, Chaki S (2014) Antidepressant <lb/>and anxiolytic profiles of newly synthesized arginine vasopressin <lb/>V1B receptor antagonists: TASP0233278 and TASP0390325. Br J <lb/>Pharmacol 171:3511-3525. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Insel TR (2010) The challenge of translation in social neuroscience: a <lb/>review of oxytocin, vasopressin, and affiliative behavior. Neuron <lb/>65:768 -779. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Kelly AM, Goodson JL (2013a) Functional significance of a phyloge-<lb/>netically widespread sexual dimorphism in vasotocin/vasopressin <lb/>production. Horm Behav 64:840 -846. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Kelly AM, Goodson JL (2013b) Behavioral relevance of species-<lb/>specific vasotocin anatomy in gregarious finches. Front Neurosci <lb/>7:242. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Kelly AM, Kingsbury MA, Hoffbuhr K, Schrock SE, Waxman B, <lb/>Kabelik D, Thompson RR, Goodson JL (2011) Vasotocin neurons <lb/>and septal V1a-like receptors potently modulate songbird flocking <lb/>and responses to novelty. Horm Behav 60:12-21. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>18 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Koolhaas JM, Moor E, Hiemstra Y, Bohus B (1991) The testosterone-<lb/>dependent vasopressinergic neurons in the medial amygdala and <lb/>lateral septum: Involvement in social behaviour of male rats. In <lb/>Vasopressin, (Jard S, Jamison R, eds), pp 213-219. Paris/London: <lb/>INSERM/John Libbey Eurotext Ltd. <lb/>Koolhaas JM, Coppens CM, de Boer SF, Buwalda B, Meerlo P, <lb/>Timmermans PJ (2013) The resident-intruder paradigm: a stan-<lb/>dardized test for aggression, violence and social stress. J Vis Exp <lb/>(77):e4367. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Labov JB, Wysocki CJ (1989) Vomeronasal organ and social factors <lb/>affect urine marking by male mice. Physiol Behav 45:443-447. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Landgraf R, Gerstberger R, Montkowski A, Probst JC, Wotjak CT, <lb/>Holsboer F, Engelmann M (1995) V1 vasopressin receptor anti-<lb/>sense oligodeoxynucleotide into septum reduces vasopressin <lb/>binding, social discrimination abilities, and anxiety-related behav-<lb/>ior in rats. J Neurosci 15:4250 -4258. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Landgraf R, Frank E, Aldag JM, Neumann ID, Sharer CA, Ren X, <lb/>Terwilliger EF, Niwa M, Wigger A, Young LJ (2003) Viral vector-<lb/>mediated gene transfer of the vole V1a vasopressin receptor in the <lb/>rat septum: improved social discrimination and active social be-<lb/>haviour. Eur J Neurosci 18:403-411. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lehmann ML, Geddes CE, Lee JL, Herkenham M (2013) Urine scent <lb/>marking (USM): a novel test for depressive-like behavior and a <lb/>predictor of stress resiliency in mice. PLoS One 8:e69822. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline <lb/>Liebsch G, Wotjak CT, Landgraf R, Engelmann M (1996) Septal <lb/>vasopressin modulates anxiety-related behaviour in rats. Neurosci <lb/>Lett 217:101-104. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lim MM, Young LJ (2004) Vasopressin-dependent neural circuits <lb/>underlying pair bond formation in the monogamous prairie vole. <lb/>Neuroscience 125:35-45. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lim MM, Hammock EAD, Young LJ (2004) The role of vasopressin in <lb/>the genetic and neural regulation of monogamy. J Neuroendocri-<lb/>nol 16:325-332. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lister RG (1987) The use of a plus-maze to measure anxiety in the <lb/>mouse. Psychopharmacology 92:180 -185. Medline <lb/>Liu Y, Curtis JT, Wang Z (2001) Vasopressin in the lateral septum <lb/>regulates pair bond formation in male prairie voles (Microtus <lb/>ochrogaster). Behav Neurosci 115:910 -919. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Ludwig M, Stern J (2015) Multiple signaling modalities mediated by <lb/>dendritic exocytosis of oxytocin and vasopressin. Philos Trans R <lb/>Soc Lond B Biol Sci 370:20140182. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lukas M, Wöhr M (2015) Endogenous vasopressin, innate anxiety, <lb/>and the emission of pro-social 50-kHz ultrasonic vocalizations <lb/>during social play behavior in juvenile rats. Psychoneuroendocri-<lb/>nology 56:35-44. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lumley LA, Sipos ML, Charles RC, Charles RF, Meyerhoff JL (1999) <lb/>Social stress effects on territorial marking and ultrasonic vocaliza-<lb/>tions in mice. Physiol Behav 67:769 -775. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Maggio JC, Whitney G (1985) Ultrasonic vocalizing by adult female <lb/>mice (Mus musculus). J Comp Psychol 99:420 -436. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Maruniak JA, Wysocki CJ, Taylor JA (1986) Mediation of male mouse <lb/>urine marking and aggression by the vomeronasal organ. Physiol <lb/>Behav 37:655-657. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Matochik JA, Sipos ML, Nyby JG, Barfield RJ (1994) Intracranial <lb/>androgenic activation of male-typical behaviors in house mice: <lb/>motivation versus performance. Behav Brain Res 60:141-149. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Meyer H (1957) The ninhydrin reaction and its analytical applications. <lb/>Biochem J 67:333-340. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Mieda M, Ono D, Hasegawa E, Okamoto H, Honma K-I, Honma S, <lb/>Sakurai T (2015) Cellular clocks in AVP neurons of the SCN are <lb/>critical for interneuronal coupling regulating circadian behavior <lb/>rhythm. Neuron 85:1103-1116. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Miller MA, Kolb PE, Raskind MA (1993) Extra-hypothalamic vaso-<lb/>pressin neurons coexpress galanin messenger RNA as shown by <lb/>double in situ hybridization histochemistry. J Comp Neurol 329: <lb/>378 -384. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Moncho-Bogani J, Lanuza E, Lorente MJ, Martinez-Garcia F (2004) <lb/>Attraction to male pheromones and sexual behaviour show differ-<lb/>ent regulatory mechanisms in female mice. Physiol Behav 81:427-<lb/>434. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Morgan CW, Julien O, Unger EK, Shah NM, Wells JA (2014) Turning <lb/>on caspases with genetics and small molecules. Methods Enzymol <lb/>544:179 -213. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Moy SS, Nadler JJ, Young NB, Nonneman RJ, Grossman AW, <lb/>Murphy DL, D&apos;Ercole AJ, Crawley JN, Magnuson TR, Lauder JM <lb/>(2009) Social approach in genetically engineered mouse lines <lb/>relevant to autism. Genes Brain Behav 8:129 -142. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/>Oldfield RG, Harris RM, Hofmann HA (2015) Integrating resource <lb/>defence theory with a neural nonapeptide pathway to explain <lb/>territory-based mating systems. Front Zool 12:S16. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Otero-Garcia M, Martin-Sanchez A, Fortes-Marco L, Martínez-Ricós <lb/>J, Agustin-Pavón C, Lanuza E, Martínez-García F (2014) Extending <lb/>the socio-sexual brain: arginine-vasopressin immunoreactive cir-<lb/>cuits in the telencephalon of mice. Brain Struct Funct 219:1055-<lb/>1081. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Paul MJ, Peters NV, Holder MK, Kim AM, Whylings J, Terranova JI, <lb/>de Vries GJ (2016) Atypical social development in vasopressin-<lb/>deficient brattleboro rats. eNeuro 3:ENEURO.0150-15.2016. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Paxinos G, Franklin K (2012) The mouse brain in stereotaxic coordi-<lb/>nates, Ed 4. San Diego, CA: Academic Press. <lb/>Pedersen CA, Boccia ML (2006) Vasopressin interactions with oxy-<lb/>tocin in the control of female sexual behavior. Neuroscience 139: <lb/>843-851. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Pitkow LJ, Sharer CA, Ren X, Insel TR, Terwilliger EF, Young LJ <lb/>(2001) Facilitation of affiliation and pair-bond formation by vaso-<lb/>pressin receptor gene transfer into the ventral forebrain of a mo-<lb/>nogamous vole. J Neurosci 21:7392-7396. CrossRef Medline <lb/>R Core Team (2013). R: A language and environment for statistical <lb/>computing. R Foundation for Statistical Computing, Vienna, Aus-<lb/>tria. <lb/>Raggenbass M (2008) Overview of cellular electrophysiological ac-<lb/>tions of vasopressin. Eur J Pharmacol 583:243-254. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Rilling JK, Demarco AC, Hackett PD, Chen X, Gautam P, Stair S, <lb/>Haroon E, Thompson R, Ditzen B, Patel R, Pagnoni G (2014) Sex <lb/>differences in the neural and behavioral response to intranasal <lb/>oxytocin and vasopressin during human social interaction. Psy-<lb/>choneuroendocrinology 39:237-248. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Roberts SC, Gosling LM, Thornton EA, McClung J (2001) Scent-<lb/>marking by male mice under the risk of predation. Behav Ecol <lb/>12:698 -705. CrossRef <lb/>Rood BD, De Vries GJ (2011) Vasopressin innervation of the mouse <lb/>(Mus musculus) brain and spinal cord. J Comp Neurol 519:2434 -<lb/>2474. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Rood BD, Stott RT, You S, Smith CJW, Woodbury ME, De Vries GJ <lb/>(2013) Site of origin of and sex differences in the vasopressin <lb/>innervation of the mouse (Mus musculus) brain. J Comp Neurol <lb/>521:2321-2358. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Roullet FI, Wöhr M, Crawley JN (2011) Female urine-induced male <lb/>mice ultrasonic vocalizations, but not scent-marking, is modulated <lb/>by social experience. Behav Brain Res 216:19 -28. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/>Schultz RT (2005) Developmental deficits in social perception in <lb/>autism: the role of the amygdala and fusiform face area. Int J Dev <lb/>Neurosci 23:125-141. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Scott N, Prigge M, Yizhar O, Kimchi T (2015) A sexually dimorphic <lb/>hypothalamic circuit controls maternal care and oxytocin secre-<lb/>tion. Nature 525:519 -522. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Shimshek DR, Kim J, Hübner MR, Spergel DJ, Buchholz F, Casanova <lb/>E, Stewart AF, Seeburg PH, Sprengel R (2002) Codon-improved <lb/>Cre recombinase (iCre) expression in the mouse. Genesis 32:19 -<lb/>26. CrossRef Medline <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>19 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Södersten P, Henning M, Melin P, Ludin S (1983) Vasopressin alters <lb/>female sexual behaviour by acting on the brain independently of <lb/>alterations in blood pressure. Nature 301:608 -610. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Ström JO, Theodorsson A, Ingberg E, Isaksson IM, Theodorsson E <lb/>(2012) Ovariectomy and 17␤-estradiol replacement in rats and <lb/>mice: a visual demonstration. J Vis Exp. Advance online publica-<lb/>tion. Retrieved June 12, 2012. doi:10.3791/4013 <lb/>Terranova JI, Song Z, Larkin TE 2nd, Hardcastle N, Norvelle A, Riaz <lb/>A, Albers HE (2016) Serotonin and arginine-vasopressin mediate <lb/>sex differences in the regulation of dominance and aggression by <lb/>the social brain. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 113:13233-13238. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Treit D, Aujla H, Menard J (1998) Does the bed nucleus of the stria <lb/>terminalis mediate fear behaviors? Behav Neurosci 112:379 -386. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Unger EK, Burke KJ Jr, Yang CF, Bender KJ, Fuller PM, Shah NM <lb/>(2015) Medial amygdalar aromatase neurons regulate aggression <lb/>in both sexes. Cell Rep 10:453-462. CrossRef Medline <lb/>van Leeuwen FW, Caffe AR, De Vries GJ (1985) Vasopressin cells in <lb/>the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis of the rat: sex differences <lb/>and the influence of androgens. Brain Res 325:391-394. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Van Loo PL, Mol JA, Koolhaas JM, Van Zutphen BF, Baumans V <lb/>(2001) Modulation of aggression in male mice: influence of group <lb/>size and cage size. Physiol Behav 72:675-683. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Van Segbroeck M, Knoll AT, Levitt P, Narayanan S (2017) MUPET-<lb/>Mouse Ultrasonic Profile ExTraction: A Signal Processing Tool for <lb/>Rapid and Unsupervised Analysis of Ultrasonic Vocalizations. <lb/>Neuron 94:465-485.e5. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Veenema AH, Beiderbeck DI, Lukas M, Neumann ID (2010) Distinct <lb/>correlations of vasopressin release within the lateral septum and <lb/>the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis with the display of intermale <lb/>aggression. Horm Behav 58:273-281. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Veenema AH, Bredewold R, De Vries GJ (2012) Vasopressin regu-<lb/>lates social recognition in juvenile and adult rats of both sexes, but <lb/>in sex-and age-specific ways. Horm Behav 61:50 -56. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Veenema AH, Bredewold R, De Vries GJ (2013) Sex-specific modu-<lb/>lation of juvenile social play by vasopressin. Psychoneuroendocri-<lb/>nology 38:2554 -2561. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Veyrac A, Wang G, Baum MJ, Bakker J (2011) The main and acces-<lb/>sory olfactory systems of female mice are activated differentially <lb/>by dominant versus subordinate male urinary odors. Brain Res <lb/>1402:20 -29. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wang Z, Smith W, Major DE, De Vries GJ (1994) Sex and species <lb/>differences in the effects of cohabitation on vasopressin messen-<lb/>ger RNA expression in the bed nucleus of the stria terminalis in <lb/>prairie voles (Microtus ochrogaster) and meadow voles (Microtus <lb/>pennsylvanicus). Brain Res 650:212-218. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wei YC, Wang SR, Jiao ZL, Zhang W, Lin JK, Li XY, Li SS, Zhang X, <lb/>Xu XH (2018) Medial preoptic area in mice is capable of mediating <lb/>sexually dimorphic behaviors regardless of gender. Nat Commun <lb/>9:279. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wersinger SR, Kelliher KR, Zufall F, Lolait SJ, O&apos;Carroll A-M, Young <lb/>W 3rd (2004) Social motivation is reduced in vasopressin 1b <lb/>receptor null mice despite normal performance in an olfactory <lb/>discrimination task. Horm Behav 46:638 -645. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wersinger SR, Caldwell HK, Martinez L, Gold P, Hu S-B, Young WS <lb/>3rd (2007) Vasopressin 1a receptor knockout mice have a subtle <lb/>olfactory deficit but normal aggression. Genes Brain Behav 6:540 -<lb/>551. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wilczynski W, Quispe M, Muñoz MI, Penna M (2017) Arginine vaso-<lb/>tocin, the social neuropeptide of amphibians and reptiles. Front <lb/>Endocrinol 8:186. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Winslow JT, Insel TR (1993) Effects of central vasopressin adminis-<lb/>tration to infant rats. Eur J Pharmacol 233:101-107. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Wöhr M (2014) Ultrasonic vocalizations in Shank mouse models for <lb/>autism spectrum disorders: detailed spectrographic analyses and <lb/>developmental profiles. Neurosci Biobehav Rev 43:199 -212. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Wu Z, Autry AE, Bergan JF, Watabe-Uchida M, Dulac CG (2014) <lb/>Galanin neurons in the medial preoptic area govern parental be-<lb/>haviour. Nature 509:325-330. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Yang CF, Chiang MC, Gray DC, Prabhakaran M, Alvarado M, Juntti <lb/>SA, Unger EK, Wells JA, Shah NM (2013) Sexually dimorphic <lb/>neurons in the ventromedial hypothalamus govern mating in both <lb/>sexes and aggression in males. Cell 153:896 -909. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>20 of 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">January/February 2019, 6(1) e0415-18.2019 <lb/>eNeuro.org </note>


	</text>
</tei>
