<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Sensory and Motor Systems <lb/>Gas Anesthesia Impairs Peripheral Auditory <lb/>Sensitivity in Barn Owls (Tyto alba) <lb/>Nadine Thiele, 1 and Christine Köppl 1,2 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1523/ENEURO.0140-18.2018 <lb/>1 Department of Neuroscience, School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Carl von Ossietzky University Oldenburg, <lb/>26129 Oldenburg, Germany and 2 Cluster of Excellence &quot;Hearing4all&quot; and Research Center Neurosensory Science, <lb/>Carl von Ossietzky University Oldenburg, 26129 Oldenburg, Germany <lb/>Visual Abstract <lb/>&lt; 1 .5 <lb/>k H z <lb/>1 .5 -3 <lb/>k H z <lb/>3 -4 .5 <lb/>k H z <lb/>4 .5 -6 <lb/>k H z <lb/>&gt; 6 k H z <lb/>Ket-terminal <lb/>Isofl-terminal <lb/>CF bin <lb/>Threshold re age-matched CAP (dB) <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/> 0 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-20 <lb/>-30 <lb/>-40 <lb/>-50 <lb/>Frequency (kHz) <lb/>) <lb/>L <lb/>P <lb/>S <lb/>B <lb/>d <lb/>( <lb/>d <lb/>l <lb/>o <lb/>h <lb/>s <lb/>e <lb/>r <lb/>h <lb/>t <lb/>R <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>-1 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-3 <lb/>-4 <lb/>Time (ms) <lb/>) <lb/>V <lb/>µ <lb/>( <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>u <lb/>t <lb/>i <lb/>l <lb/>p <lb/>m <lb/>a <lb/>R <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>Ket-ABR <lb/>Isofl-ABR <lb/>Sevofl-ABR <lb/>Auditory nerve single-unit recordings were obtained from two groups of young barn owls (age, between <lb/>posthatching days 11 and 86) in terminal experiments under two different anesthetic regimes: ketamine (6 -11 <lb/>mg/kg) plus xylazine (ϳ2 mg/kg); or isoflurane (1-1.5%) in oxygen, delivered via artificial respiration. In a second <lb/>series of minimally invasive experiments, auditory brainstem responses (ABRs) were recorded in the same four <lb/>Significance Statement <lb/>Anesthesia and analgesia are necessary for most invasive experiments. Their effects are also a concern for <lb/>studying normal neural and sensory functions. We show a significant deterioration of hearing sensitivity of <lb/>the auditory nerve under gas anesthesia (isoflurane or sevoflurane), compared with injection anesthesia with <lb/>ketamine/xylazine, in barn owls. This generalizes similar findings across birds and mammals, and suggests <lb/>that while inhalants are widely recommended as safe and easy-to-use anesthetics in veterinary contexts, <lb/>they should only be used with great caution in auditory neurophysiology, even at the most peripheral level. <lb/>Future important questions are whether the deterioration of sensitivity at the periphery generalizes to other <lb/>senses and what the precise mechanisms are that determine the species-specific extent of sensitivity loss. <lb/> New Research <lb/>September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 1-14 <lb/>adult barn owls (Tyto alba; age, between 5 and 32 months) under three different anesthetic protocols: ketamine <lb/>(10 mg/kg) plus xylazine (3 mg/kg), isoflurane (1-1.5%), and sevoflurane (2-3%) in carbogen. Finally, the ABR <lb/>measurements on adult owls were repeated in terminal experiments including more invasive procedures such as <lb/>artificial respiration and higher isoflurane dosage. The main finding was a significant deterioration of auditory <lb/>sensitivity in barn owls under gas anesthesia, at the level of the auditory nerve (i.e., a very peripheral level of the <lb/>auditory system). The effect was drastic in the young animals that experienced threshold elevations in auditory <lb/>nerve single-unit responses of Ն20 dB. ABR thresholds assessed repeatedly in experiments on adult owls were <lb/>also significantly higher under isoflurane and sevoflurane, on average by 7 and 15 dB, compared with ketamine/ <lb/>xylazine. This difference already occurred with minimal dosages and was reversibly enlarged with increased <lb/>isoflurane concentration. Finally, there was evidence for confounding detrimental effects associated with artificial <lb/>respiration over many hours, which suggested oxygen toxicity. <lb/>Key words: auditory brainstem response; avian; bird; isoflurane; ketamine; physiology <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Anesthesia and analgesia are necessary components of <lb/>most invasive physiological experiments. Yet, their very <lb/>site of action, the nervous system, is a constant concern <lb/>for neuroscientists who strive to study normal neural and <lb/>sensory functions. Different anesthetic agents act on dif-<lb/>ferent neural targets and for some common anesthetic <lb/>agents these are known in considerable detail at the <lb/>molecular level (Lukasik and Gillies, 2003; Sonner et al., <lb/>2003; Rudolph and Antkowiak, 2004). However, due to <lb/>the highly interactive nature of the intact nervous system, <lb/>it remains difficult to predict their effect on a given neu-<lb/>ronal population under in vivo conditions (Antkowiak, <lb/>2001; Vahle-Hinz and Detsch, 2002; Windels, 2006). <lb/>In the present study, the anesthetic regime was <lb/>changed during an ongoing experimental series on the <lb/>development of auditory nerve responses in the barn owl <lb/>(Tyto alba). Previous auditory research in several labora-<lb/>tories had successfully used a combined ketamine/xyla-<lb/>zine or ketamine/diazepam injection anesthesia in both <lb/>adult and young owls (Cohen and Knudsen, 1995; Köppl, <lb/>1997; Keller and Takahashi, 2005; Bremen et al., 2007; <lb/>Köppl and Nickel, 2007). Nevertheless, a change to iso-<lb/>flurane inhalant anesthesia was recommended by the <lb/>consulting veterinarians, citing animal welfare concerns <lb/>(Varner et al., 2004). Isoflurane and related inhalants (ha-<lb/>logenated ethers, e.g., sevoflurane and desflurane; Cam-<lb/>pagna et al., 2003), are commonly recommended as the <lb/>first choice for veterinary procedures on a wide variety of <lb/>species, including birds (Korbel, 1998; Gunkel and Lafor-<lb/>tune, 2005; Lierz and Korbel, 2012; Raftery, 2013). Fre-<lb/>quently cited advantages are the rapid and easy control of <lb/>anesthetic depth, stable anesthetic state for lengthy pro-<lb/>cedures, and rapid recovery (Keegan, 2005). <lb/>Although no specific reports were available about the <lb/>effects of isoflurane on neural responses in birds, there <lb/>was no reason to expect a deterioration in auditory nerve <lb/>responses with gas anesthetic agents relative to ket-<lb/>amine/xylazine. In starlings and chickens, halothane, an-<lb/>other inhalant anesthetic, and ketamine/xylazine were <lb/>tested and compared for their effects on cochlear re-<lb/>sponses. Both types of anesthesia were found to act in an <lb/>equally depressive fashion on otoacoustic emissions (pro-<lb/>duced by the hair cells of the inner ear; Kettembeil et al., <lb/>1995). Similarly, the effects of ketamine or isoflurane on <lb/>auditory nerve responses in the Tokay gecko were mod-<lb/>erately depressive and differed little from each other <lb/>(Dodd and Capranica, 1992). In a bat, isoflurane had no <lb/>adverse effects on otoacoustic emissions (Drexl et al., <lb/>2004), suggesting that it could even be preferable to <lb/>ketamine, depending on the species. Unfortunately, it <lb/>became clear during the course of this study that the <lb/>change to isoflurane correlated with degraded hearing <lb/>sensitivity in the barn owl. Studies in several mammalian <lb/>species subsequently reported similar effects on cochlear <lb/>responses (Stronks et al., 2010; Cederholm et al., 2012; <lb/>Ruebhausen et al., 2012). In order to directly compare <lb/>different anesthetic agents and protocols, including pro-<lb/>longed anesthesia and artificial respiration, which are <lb/>common in invasive neurophysiology, a dedicated series <lb/>of experiments on adult barn owls was finally carried out. <lb/>In addition to ketamine/xylazine and isoflurane, the more <lb/>recently introduced inhalant sevoflurane was then also <lb/>included for testing. Sevoflurane shows a pharmacology <lb/>similar to isoflurane, but induction and recovery from <lb/>anesthesia are even more rapid and, as an additional <lb/>benefit, it is less of an irritant to the respiratory tract <lb/>(O&apos;Keeffe and Healy, 1999; Preckel and Bolten, 2005; <lb/>Flaherty, 2009; Burns, 2014). <lb/></body>

			<front>Received April 9, 2018; accepted October 5, 2018; First published November <lb/>2, 2018. <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/>Author contributions: C.K. designed research; N.T. and C.K. performed <lb/>research; N.T. and C.K. analyzed data; N.T. and C.K. wrote the paper. <lb/>This work was supported by Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft Grants KO <lb/>1143/11-1 and 11-2; and Bundesministerium für Bildung und Forschung Grant <lb/>01GQ1505B, as part of the German-USA Collaboration in Computational <lb/>Neuroscience &quot;Field Potentials in the Auditory System.&quot; <lb/>Acknowledgments: We thank Mark Konishi for the generous gift of the <lb/>software &quot;xdphys,&quot; custom written in his laboratory and used in the single-unit <lb/>recordings; and Rainer Beutelmann for the development and continuing sup-<lb/>port of custom-written software used for the ABR measurements. We also <lb/>thank STELS-OL (Scientific and Technical English Language Services, Olden-<lb/>burg, Germany) for English language editing. <lb/>Correspondence should be addressed to Christine Köppl, Cluster of Excel-<lb/>lence &quot;Hearing4all,&quot; Research Center Neurosensory Science, and Department <lb/>of Neuroscience, School of Medicine and Health Sciences, Carl von Ossietzky <lb/>University, 26129 Oldenburg, Germany. E-mail: Christine.Koeppl@uol.de. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1523/ENEURO.0140-18.2018 <lb/>Copyright © 2018 Thiele and Köppl <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution 4.0 International license, which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium provided that the original work is <lb/>properly attributed. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Materials and Methods <lb/>Experiments were carried out over a time span of sev-<lb/>eral years, using two different laboratories and different <lb/>recording techniques. The two experimental series will be <lb/>referred to as young owls and adult owls. In young owls, <lb/>compound action potential (CAP) and auditory nerve <lb/>single-unit recordings were carried out. In adult owls, <lb/>auditory brainstem responses (ABRs) were recorded. <lb/>Within each group, different anesthetic protocols will be <lb/>abbreviated as follows: ketamine-terminal and isoflurane-<lb/>terminal (young owls); and ketamine-ABR, isoflurane-<lb/>ABR, sevoflurane-ABR, and ABR-terminal (adult owls). <lb/>Experimental animals <lb/>All animal procedures were performed in accordance <lb/>with the German Animal Welfare Act and were approved <lb/>by local authorities (permits AZ 209.1/211-2531-113/03 <lb/>and AZ 33.12 42502-13/1154). In the first experimental <lb/>series, 21 young barn owls of undetermined (either) sex, <lb/>18 T. alba and 3 Tyto furcata (formerly classified as T. alba <lb/>pratincola) were used. Their hatching dates were not al-<lb/>ways known to the specific day, therefore the develop-<lb/>mental stage was determined according to the study by <lb/>Köppl et al. (2005) and was expressed as the number of <lb/>days posthatching; the stage ranged from postnatal day <lb/>11 (P11) to P86. Barn owls are altricial and fledge from the <lb/>nest fully grown at about P65 (Köppl et al., 2005). The <lb/>ABR was recorded in four adult barn owls (T. alba), two <lb/>females and two males, between 5 and 32 months of age <lb/>and weighing between 310 and 390 g. <lb/>Anesthesia and homeostasis <lb/>All animals were deprived of food for ϳ12 h before the <lb/>initiation of anesthesia. Young owls received initial doses <lb/>of 10 mg/kg ketamine hydrochloride (Ketavet, Pharmacia) <lb/>and 3 mg/kg xylazine hydrochloride (Rompun, BayerVital), <lb/>injected intramuscularly. Young owls in the ketamine-<lb/>terminal group were maintained by supplementing ket-<lb/>amine and xylazine as needed, usually every 30 -40 min <lb/>during the surgical stage and every 40 -60 min during <lb/>electrophysiological recordings, at dosages of 6 -11 and <lb/>1.7-2.5 mg/kg, respectively. Young owls in the isoflurane-<lb/>terminal group were maintained on ketamine and xylazine <lb/>only for preliminary surgery, during which the trachea was <lb/>cut in the neck region and intubated, and the abdominal <lb/>air sac was exposed and opened. A one-way respiration <lb/>system was then connected (Burger and Lorenz, 1960; <lb/>Schwartzkopff and Brémond, 1963), delivering gases at a <lb/>constant pressure to the tracheal tube and providing an <lb/>outlet through a short tube inserted into the air sac. <lb/>Spontaneous breathing immediately ceased under artifi-<lb/>cial respiration in all cases. In most experiments, pure <lb/>oxygen was delivered with 1-1.5% isoflurane (Rhodia <lb/>Organique Fine or Essex Tierarznei) added by a vaporizer <lb/>(Vapor 19.3, Dräger), at a volume of 150 -400 ml/min, <lb/>depending on the size of the animal. In three experiments, <lb/>carbogen (95% oxygen and 5% carbon dioxide) was used <lb/>instead of pure oxygen. Respiratory gases were humidi-<lb/>fied via a wash bottle with distilled water before being <lb/>delivered to the animal. All young owls in the isoflurane-<lb/>terminal group also received analgesic injections of 20 -50 <lb/>mg/kg metamizole-sodium (Vetalgin, Intervet) at irregular <lb/>intervals of 2-8 h. <lb/>Each adult barn owl was tested under three different <lb/>anesthetic protocols, applied on separate days in a ran-<lb/>domized sequence, with 1 week of recovery in between. <lb/>Breathing was unaided in all cases. For the ketamine-ABR <lb/>condition, owls received an initial dose of 10 mg/kg ket-<lb/>amine hydrochloride (bela-pharm) and 3 mg/kg xylazine <lb/>hydrochloride (Medistar Arzneimittelvertrieb), i.m. Mainte-<lb/>nance doses of 1.6 -5 mg/kg ketamine and 0.6 -1.8 mg/kg <lb/>xylazine were given as needed, typically every 30 min. For <lb/>the isoflurane-ABR condition, anesthesia was both initi-<lb/>ated and maintained on isoflurane only. A concentration <lb/>of 0.5-1.5% isoflurane (CP-Pharma Handelsgesellschaft) <lb/>was added to carbogen (used to minimize the danger of <lb/>apnea) by a vaporizer (Fortec, Cyprane Kneighley) and <lb/>delivered via a custom-built respiration mask, at a volume <lb/>of 1 L/min. For the sevoflurane-ABR condition, 2-3% <lb/>sevoflurane (Ecuphar; vaporizer, Harvard Apparatus) in <lb/>carbogen was delivered. At the conclusion of each exper-<lb/>iment, the owl received a single dose of ϳ0.03 mg/kg <lb/>meloxicam (Boehringer Ingelheim Vetmedica), a non-<lb/>steroidal anti-inflammatory drug, for the recovery phase. <lb/>In a fourth and terminal experiment, ABR measurements <lb/>were repeated under different, sequentially applied pro-<lb/>tocols that included conditions closer to those of the <lb/>terminal experiments on young owls. The sequence al-<lb/>ways began with ketamine/xylazine injection anesthesia, <lb/>applied as before. The trachea was cut in the neck region <lb/>and intubated, in preparation for later artificial respiration. <lb/>However, breathing was still unaided for the first series of <lb/>measurements. After that, the abdominal air sac was <lb/>opened, and a one-way artificial respiration system with <lb/>pure oxygen (400 ml/min) was instigated, as in young <lb/>owls. After the completion of another series of ABR mea-<lb/>surements, ketamine/xylazine anesthesia was discontin-<lb/>ued and the anesthesia was switched to isoflurane, added <lb/>to the oxygen respiration at different concentrations (1%, <lb/>2%, and back to 1%) to investigate the effect of dosage <lb/>on the ABR. <lb/>All animals were killed by an overdose of sodium pen-<lb/>tobarbital (ϳ100 mg/kg) at the conclusion of the terminal <lb/>experiment. <lb/>The depth of anesthesia was constantly monitored via a <lb/>combined EKG and muscle potential recording between <lb/>needle electrodes inserted into muscles of one wing and <lb/>the contralateral leg. Body temperature was held constant <lb/>at 39°C by a feedback-controlled heating blanket (Har-<lb/>vard Systems) wrapped around the body of the animal, <lb/>with the probe inserted into the cloaca. The head temper-<lb/>ature of young barn owls was monitored separately by a <lb/>small thermoprobe placed in the throat. Barn owls be-<lb/>come homeothermic at ϳ3 weeks posthatching (Shaw-<lb/>yer, 1998), and individuals older than ϳP25 maintained a <lb/>constant head temperature at 37-38°C, under these con-<lb/>ditions. In younger animals, the unassisted head cooled <lb/>significantly relative to the body, and a heat lamp was <lb/>added to maintain head temperature at 35-38°C during <lb/>recordings. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Surgery <lb/>The heads of young barn owls were held firmly via an <lb/>individual head band modeled from plaster-of-Paris. For <lb/>CAP recordings, the round window of the inner ear on one <lb/>side was exposed. For single-unit recordings from the <lb/>auditory nerve, the brainstem was exposed by aspirating <lb/>part of the cerebellum. Note that in these experiments, the <lb/>surgical openings also vented the middle-ear space. This <lb/>avoids the buildup of negative middle-ear pressure under <lb/>anesthesia, which significantly reduces auditory sensitiv-<lb/>ity (for review, see Larsen et al., 2016). <lb/>For ABR measurements of adult owls, the beak of the <lb/>owl was fixed in a custom-built holder. To prevent the <lb/>buildup of negative middle-ear pressure under anesthesia <lb/>(Larsen et al., 2016), a sterile 27 gauge cannula was <lb/>inserted through the skull into the middle-ear cavity for <lb/>ventilation during ABR measurements. <lb/>Sound stimulation and electrophysiological <lb/>recordings <lb/>All CAP and single-unit recording measurements took <lb/>place in a custom-built double-walled sound-attenuating <lb/>chamber, and ABR measurements took place in a double-<lb/>walled chamber (model 1203A, Industrial Acoustics). In-<lb/>dividually calibrated acoustic stimuli were presented <lb/>through a custom-built miniature earphone and micro-<lb/>phone system sealed into the ear canal ipsilateral to the <lb/>recording electrode (ER-2 earphone, Etymotic Research; <lb/>FG-23329 microphone for ABR recordings, Knowles). <lb/>For CAP recordings in young owls, a silver wire elec-<lb/>trode, insulated except for a small bead melted at its tip, <lb/>was placed onto the round window membrane, and a <lb/>grounded reference electrode (Ag/AgCl pellet) was placed <lb/>under the skin near the incisions made in the head. Elec-<lb/>trode signals were amplified by a Tucker-Davis Technol-<lb/>ogies (TDT) DB4 amplifier, used at 10,000ϫ to 100,000ϫ <lb/>amplification, 0.1 or 0.2 kHz high-pass filtering, and 15 <lb/>kHz low-pass filtering (12 dB/octave Butterworth filters). <lb/>Signals were then fed to a TDT AD1 analog-to-digital <lb/>converter that was connected via an O1 optical interface <lb/>to an AP2 signal processor interface in a personal com-<lb/>puter. The same interface was used to synthesize the <lb/>acoustic stimuli, which were then antialiased (FT6-2, <lb/>TDT), variably attenuated (PA4, TDT), and fed to the ear-<lb/>phone. Stimuli were tone pips of 20 ms duration, including <lb/>1 ms cosine-shaped rise and fall times (2 ms at 500 Hz) <lb/>and were delivered at rates of 5/s. Stimuli had a fixed <lb/>starting phase and equal numbers of stimulus presenta-<lb/>tions with opposite starting phase were averaged (in total, <lb/>32 or 64). Stimulus generation and CAP recording were <lb/>conducted under the control of TDT software (SigGen and <lb/>BioSig). <lb/>For auditory nerve single unit recordings in young owls, <lb/>glass microelectrodes filled with 3 M KCL and with imped-<lb/>ances typically between 30 and 50 M⍀ were placed over <lb/>the brainstem under visual control and then remotely <lb/>advanced by a precision microdrive (inchworm 6000ULN, <lb/>Burleigh). A grounded reference electrode (Ag/AgCl pellet) <lb/>was placed under the skin near the incisions made on the <lb/>head. Signals were amplified and filtered (767 electrome-<lb/>ter, World Precision Instruments, TDT PC1 module), ac-<lb/>tion potentials were threshold discriminated (SD1, TDT), <lb/>and the resulting TTL pulses were fed to a TDT AP2 <lb/>interface board, via an event timer (model ET1, TDT) and <lb/>an analog-to-digital converter (model DD1 TDT). As <lb/>above, the same interface was used to synthesize the <lb/>acoustic stimuli, which were then antialiased (FT6-2, <lb/>TDT), variably attenuated (PA4, TDT), and fed to the ear-<lb/>phone. Stimulus generation and recording of the TTL <lb/>pulses was under the control of custom-written software. <lb/>ABR in adult owls was recorded between two subcu-<lb/>taneous platinum electrodes (Grass Technologies), one <lb/>placed on the vertex and one next to the left ear canal. <lb/>Signals were amplified 1000ϫ by an ISO 80 amplifier <lb/>(World Precision Instruments), band-pass filtered be-<lb/>tween 0.1 and 10 kHz, and digitized by a Hammerfall DSP <lb/>Multiface II Interface Card (RME Audio). Stimuli were tone <lb/>bursts with 10 ms duration and 1 ms rise/fall time, and <lb/>delivered at a rate of 7 bursts/s, generated by the same <lb/>interface and fed to the earphone via a TDT HB7 Head-<lb/>phone Buffer. ABR responses were averaged over 300 <lb/>stimulus repetitions. Stimulus generation and ABR re-<lb/>cording were conducted under the control of software <lb/>custom-written in MATLAB (MathWorks). <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>CAP responses in young owls were recorded to fre-<lb/>quencies of 500 Hz and 1 to 10 kHz in 1 kHz steps. At <lb/>each frequency, responses to a range of randomly pre-<lb/>sented levels were recorded, generally in 5 dB incre-<lb/>ments, and decreased to 3 dB near threshold. CAP <lb/>amplitude was defined as the difference between the first <lb/>negative peak N1 and the following most prominent pos-<lb/>itive peak. Thresholds were derived from linear regression <lb/>fits through the initial segment of the curve (four to six <lb/>data points collected at the lowest stimulus levels), as the <lb/>level eliciting a 5 V response. <lb/>For auditory nerve single units recorded in young owls, <lb/>the frequency-threshold curves were derived from re-<lb/>sponses to a matrix of tone bursts of 50 ms duration, <lb/>presented randomly at different frequencies and levels, <lb/>three times each, at a rate of five stimuli per second; the <lb/>threshold criterion was, on average, 20 spikes/s above <lb/>spontaneous rate. The spontaneous rate was estimated <lb/>from the same datasets, either by counting spikes in <lb/>the 50 ms window immediately before each stimulus <lb/>(ketamine-terminal group) or from randomly inserted silent <lb/>trials (isoflurane-terminal group). A new measure of rela-<lb/>tive sensitivity was defined that normalizes for the known <lb/>threshold changes that occur with age that have been <lb/>quantified for ketamine/xylazine anesthetized owls (Köppl <lb/>and Nickel, 2007). Age-typical CAP thresholds can be <lb/>derived for any desired age at 11 standard frequencies <lb/>between 0.5 and 10 kHz, from the published fits of the <lb/>CAP threshold as a function of posthatching age (Köppl <lb/>and Nickel, 2007, their Fig. 8, plus data for five frequen-<lb/>cies not shown). By linear interpolation between frequen-<lb/>cies, age-typical CAP thresholds were then calculated <lb/>for any desired frequency. The difference between the <lb/>threshold of a single unit at characteristic frequency (CF) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>and the corresponding CAP threshold at that age and <lb/>frequency was taken as a measure of relative sensitivity. <lb/>In ABR recordings from adult owls, a standard set of six <lb/>frequencies was tested, at 1, 2, 4, 6, 8, and 10 kHz. At <lb/>each frequency, responses to a range of randomly pre-<lb/>sented levels were recorded, generally in 5 dB incre-<lb/>ments, and decreased to 3 dB near threshold (with few <lb/>exceptions). ABR thresholds were identified visually, and <lb/>peak-to-peak amplitude and peak latency were read out <lb/>with the use of a custom MATLAB script (Fig. 1, example). <lb/>To eliminate the audiogram threshold variation for graph-<lb/>ical summaries comparing the different anesthetic proto-<lb/>cols, ABR thresholds were normalized to the respective <lb/>individual value in the ketamine-ABR condition or the <lb/>ketamine condition in the ABR-terminal experiment. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analyses were carried out with the use of <lb/>PASW Statistics version 18.0.2 or SPSS Statistics ver-<lb/>sions 24 and 25 (IBM). Nonparametric measures and tests <lb/>were used throughout (Table 1). A p value of Յ0.01 was <lb/>the criterion for a significant difference. In case of multiple <lb/>post hoc comparisons, a Bonferroni adjustment of the <lb/>criterion p value was applied by dividing 0.01 by the <lb/>number of pairwise tests required. For example, if three <lb/>pairwise post hoc tests were performed, the Bonferroni-<lb/>corrected criterion p value was 0.003333. <lb/>Results <lb/>Single-unit auditory nerve thresholds were less <lb/>sensitive under isoflurane than under <lb/>ketamine/xylazine <lb/>A total of 57 auditory nerve fibers were recorded in the <lb/>ketamine-terminal condition, from owls aged P17 to P36, <lb/>and 360 auditory nerve fibers in the isoflurane-terminal <lb/>condition, from owls aged P11 to P86. As absolute sen-<lb/>sitivity is known to change within these age brackets <lb/>(Köppl and Nickel, 2007), the difference between the <lb/>threshold of a single unit and the CAP threshold typical for <lb/>that age and frequency was defined as a measure of relative <lb/>sensitivity (see Materials and Methods). This eliminated the <lb/>known maturational changes of auditory thresholds, allow-<lb/>ing for the identification of other factors influencing hearing <lb/>sensitivity. There was a significant difference in relative sen-<lb/>sitivity between auditory nerve fibers recorded under the two <lb/>anesthetic protocols (Table 1, References 1). Median values <lb/>were Ϫ2.4 dB for the isoflurane-terminal condition and <lb/>Ϫ26.5 dB for the ketamine-terminal condition (Fig. 2A). This <lb/>difference held across frequencies when tested separately <lb/>for different characteristic frequencies, binned into 1.5-kHz-<lb/>wide bands. Median relative thresholds for the isoflurane-<lb/>terminal condition were between 17 and 26 dB higher than <lb/>those recorded under the ketamine-terminal condition <lb/>(Table 1, References 2-5, Fig. 2B; note that for CFs Ͼ6 kHz, <lb/>the sample for the ketamine-terminal group was insuf-<lb/>ficient for a meaningful test). <lb/>CAP thresholds were less sensitive under isoflurane <lb/>than under ketamine/xylazine <lb/>CAP thresholds were obtained in only one young owl in <lb/>this study. Nevertheless, this case is included here as it <lb/>validated the principal assumption that CAP and single-<lb/>unit thresholds are tightly correlated. Single-unit data and <lb/>CAP recordings were obtained in the same individual, <lb/>aged P32, under isoflurane anesthesia. The median <lb/>single-unit sensitivity relative to the animal&apos;s own CAP <lb/>audiogram was Ϫ23 dB (n ϭ 7; CFs, 2.6 -4.4 kHz), while <lb/>it was ϩ10.2 dB relative to the age-matched CAP thresh-<lb/>old under ketamine/xylazine anesthesia (Köppl and <lb/>Nickel, 2007). This individual thus represented a drastic <lb/>case of threshold loss (Fig. 3). Furthermore, the direct <lb/>reference of single-unit thresholds to the animal&apos;s own <lb/>CAP thresholds supports the notion derived from the <lb/>population data that single-unit thresholds fall, on aver-<lb/>age, ϳ20 dB below the CAP thresholds obtained under <lb/>comparable conditions. This is typical for birds in general <lb/>(Köppl and Gleich, 2007). <lb/>Spontaneous discharge rates and frequency tuning <lb/>were much less affected <lb/>As a measure of discharge activity of auditory nerve <lb/>single units, spontaneous rates were evaluated for effects <lb/>of the anesthetic protocol. First, data were examined for <lb/>confounding age-related maturation of spontaneous rate. <lb/>There was evidence for lower spontaneous rates in very <lb/>young owls, aged P11 to P14, but no further changes in <lb/>animals older than that (Table 1, References 6 -16). To <lb/>minimize maturation effects, the comparison between the <lb/>anesthetic groups was therefore restricted to owls aged <lb/>P17 and older. In these groups, spontaneous rates were <lb/>significantly lower in the isoflurane-terminal group <lb/>(Table 1, Reference 17, Fig. 4A). Median values were 40 <lb/>spikes/s in the ketamine-terminal group and 33.3 spikes/s <lb/>in the isoflurane-terminal group. Since spontaneous rates <lb/>are, in addition, known to vary with CF (Köppl, 1997), the <lb/>data were further examined separately, for 1.5-kHz-wide <lb/>CF bands. Here, the difference between the anesthetic <lb/>Fig. 1. Example of a typical ABR recording from an adult owl. <lb/>Shown is an average response to 300 stimuli at 2 kHz, 51 dB <lb/>SPL. Only wave I was analyzed. Amplitude was defined as the <lb/>difference between the first positive (AmpMax) and following <lb/>negative (AmpMin) peak. Latency was defined as the latency of <lb/>the first positive peak (Tmax). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1: List of statistical tests <lb/>Reference <lb/>number <lb/>Data structure <lb/>Parameter tested <lb/>Type of test <lb/>p value <lb/>Figure <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 57) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 351) <lb/>Single-unit threshold (relative to age-matched <lb/>CAP audiograms) <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2A <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 5) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 49) <lb/>Single-unit threshold (relative to age-matched <lb/>CAP audiograms) <lb/>CF Ͻ1.5 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.004 <lb/>2B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 14) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 76) <lb/>Single-unit threshold (relative to age-matched <lb/>CAP audiograms) <lb/>CF 1.5-3 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 20) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 89) <lb/>Single-unit threshold (relative to age-matched <lb/>CAP audiograms) <lb/>CF 3-4.5 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 17) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 86) <lb/>Single-unit threshold (relative to age-matched <lb/>CAP audiograms) <lb/>CF 4.5-6 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>2B <lb/>Five independent samples (age groups): <lb/>P11 to P14 (n ϭ 99) <lb/>P17 (n ϭ 35) <lb/>P21 to 32 (n ϭ 87) <lb/>P35 to P40 (n ϭ 17) <lb/>P51 to P86 (n ϭ 38) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P11 to P14 (n ϭ 99) <lb/>P17 (n ϭ 35) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P11to P14 (n ϭ 99) <lb/>P21 to P32 (n ϭ 87) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.001 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P11 to P14 (n ϭ 99) <lb/>P35 to P40 (n ϭ 17) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.003 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P11 to P14 (n ϭ 99) <lb/>P51 to P86 (n ϭ 38) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P17 (n ϭ 35) <lb/>P21 to P32 (n ϭ 87) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.346 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P17 (n ϭ 35) <lb/>P35 to P40 (n ϭ 17) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.992 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P17 (n ϭ 35) <lb/>P51 to P86 (n ϭ 38) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.614 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P21 to 32 (n ϭ 87) <lb/>P35 to P40 (n ϭ 17) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.467 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P21 to P32 (n ϭ 87) <lb/>P51 to P86 (n ϭ 38) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.718 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>P35 to P40 (n ϭ 17) <lb/>P51 to P86 (n ϭ 38) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate <lb/>Mann-Whitney Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.826 <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 56) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 260) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate, <lb/>all ages ՆP17 <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.005 <lb/>4A <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 5) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 29) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate, <lb/>all ages ՆP17 and CF Ͻ1.5 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.575 <lb/>4B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 14) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 30) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate, <lb/>all ages ՆP17 and CF 1.5-3 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.035 <lb/>4B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 19) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 62) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate, <lb/>all ages ՆP17 and CF 3-4.5 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.858 <lb/>4B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 17) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 88) <lb/>Single-unit spontaneous discharge rate, <lb/>all ages ՆP17 and CF 4.5-6 kHz <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.264 <lb/>4B <lb/>Two independent samples: <lb/>ketamine-terminal (n ϭ 53) <lb/>isoflurane-terminal (n ϭ 327) <lb/>Single-unit Q10 dB <lb/>Mann-Whitney <lb/>0.098 <lb/>(Continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>regimes did not hold for any CF band (Fig. 4B, Table 1, <lb/>References 18 -21; note that for CFs Ͼ6 kHz, the sample <lb/>for the ketamine-terminal group was insufficient for a <lb/>meaningful test). Together, isoflurane thus appeared to <lb/>have a mildly depressive effect on spontaneous rates <lb/>when compared with data from ketamine/xylazine-ane-<lb/>sthetized juvenile owls. <lb/>The quality of frequency tuning, expressed as Q 10dB , <lb/>was not consistently affected by the anesthetic protocol. <lb/>An overall comparison of Q 10dB values between the ket-<lb/>amine-terminal and the isoflurane-terminal groups re-<lb/>vealed no significant difference (Table 1, Reference 22). <lb/>ABR thresholds were less sensitive with gas <lb/>anesthesia compared with ketamine/xylazine <lb/>Four adult owls were tested under three anesthetic <lb/>protocols each: ketamine-ABR, isoflurane-ABR, and sevo-<lb/>flurane-ABR. Importantly, the sequence of testing was <lb/>randomized and different for each owl. ABR audiograms <lb/>showed a similar overall shape for all conditions, suggest-<lb/>ing that the basic relationship between ABR threshold and <lb/>frequency was not affected (Fig. 5A). However, thresholds <lb/>differed significantly between the conditions (Table 1, <lb/>Reference 23). Specifically, thresholds in the ketamine-<lb/>ABR condition were significantly lower than thresholds <lb/>Table 1: Continued <lb/>Reference <lb/>number <lb/>Data structure <lb/>Parameter tested <lb/>Type of test <lb/>p value <lb/>Figure <lb/>23 <lb/>Three dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>ketamine-ABR <lb/>isoflurane-ABR <lb/>sevoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Friedman <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>5 <lb/>24 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>ketamine-ABR <lb/>isoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>5 <lb/>25 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>ketamine-ABR <lb/>sevoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>5 <lb/>26 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>isoflurane-ABR <lb/>sevoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.076 <lb/>5 <lb/>27 <lb/>Six independent samples: <lb/>1/2/4/6/8/10 kHz <lb/>(n ϭ 4 each) <lb/>ABR threshold difference: isoflurane-ABRϪ <lb/>ketamine-ABR condition <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>0.406 <lb/>5B <lb/>28 <lb/>Six independent samples: <lb/>1/2/4/6/8/10 kHz <lb/>(n ϭ 4 each) <lb/>ABR threshold difference: sevoflurane-ABRϪ <lb/>ketamine-ABR condition <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis <lb/>0.472 <lb/>5B <lb/>29 <lb/>Three dependent samples (n ϭ 16): <lb/>ketamine-ABR <lb/>isoflurane-ABR <lb/>sevoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR amplitudes 10 dB above threshold <lb/>Friedman <lb/>0.068 <lb/>30 <lb/>Three dependent samples (n ϭ 16): <lb/>ketamine-ABR <lb/>isoflurane-ABR <lb/>sevoflurane-ABR <lb/>ABR latencies 10 dB above threshold <lb/>Friedman <lb/>0.646 <lb/>31 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>ABR-terminal, ketamine <lb/>ABR-terminal, ketamine ϩ oxygen <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>0.163 <lb/>32 <lb/>Three dependent samples (n ϭ 11): <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane <lb/>ABR-terminal, 2% isoflurane <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane repeat <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Friedman <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>6A <lb/>33 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 11): <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane <lb/>ABR-terminal, 2% isoflurane <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.003 <lb/>6A <lb/>34 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 11): <lb/>ABR-terminal, 2% isoflurane <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane repeat <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.003 <lb/>6A <lb/>35 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 11): <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane repeat <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>Bonferroni corrected <lb/>0.262 <lb/>6A <lb/>36 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>ABR-terminal, ketamine ϩ oxygen <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>0.004 <lb/>37 <lb/>Two dependent samples (n ϭ 24): <lb/>isoflurane-ABR (normalized <lb/>compared with ketamine) <lb/>ABR-terminal, 1% isoflurane <lb/>(normalized compared with ketamine) <lb/>ABR threshold <lb/>Wilcoxon <lb/>&lt;0.001 <lb/>Column 1 shows the serial number used to refer to specific tests throughout the article. Column 2 defines the samples, and column 3 the tested parameter. <lb/>Column 4 lists the specific nonparametric test used, and column 5 shows the resulting p value, which is highlighted in bold type if the null hypothesis was re-<lb/>jected. Note that the criterion p value was 0.01, or lower if a Bonferroni correction was applied, as indicated in Column 4. Finally, column 6 refers to the rele-<lb/>vant figure, if applicable. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>for either the isoflurane-or sevoflurane-ABR condition <lb/>(Table 1, References 24 and 25). There was no significant <lb/>difference between ABR thresholds obtained with the two <lb/>anesthetic gases (Table 1, Reference 26). Threshold dif-<lb/>ferences to the respective threshold in the ketamine-ABR <lb/>condition showed no significant frequency dependence <lb/>(Table 1, References 27 and 28, Fig. 5B). Overall, thresh-<lb/>olds under isoflurane showed a median elevation of 7 dB, <lb/>thresholds under sevoflurane showed a median elevation <lb/>of 15 dB compared with the ketamine-ABR condition (Fig. <lb/>5C). <lb/>The amplitude and latency of ABR wave I were unaf-<lb/>fected by the anesthesia protocol. Of course, amplitude <lb/>increased and latency decreased with increasing sound <lb/>level. Therefore, this comparison was carried out at a <lb/>relative level of 10 dB above the respective ABR threshold <lb/>(Table 1, References 29 and 30). <lb/>In a final, terminal experiment, each adult owl was <lb/>tested with more invasive protocols to assess confound-<lb/>ing factors such as artificial respiration and variable inhal-<lb/>ant concentration. There was no significant change in <lb/>ABR thresholds after switching from unassisted breathing <lb/>through a tracheotomy to artificial respiration with oxygen, both <lb/>still under ketamine/xylazine anesthesia (Table 1, Reference <lb/>31). Next, the anesthetic protocol was switched to isoflurane <lb/>and stepped from 1% to 2% and back to 1%, with a minimum <lb/>equilibration time of 15 min before measurements were ob-<lb/>tained after a change in gas concentration. This revealed <lb/>a significant effect of isoflurane dosage (Table 1, Refer-<lb/>ence 32, Fig. 6A). Increasing isoflurane from 1% to 2% <lb/>resulted in a significant rise of ABR thresholds (Table 1, <lb/>Reference 33, Fig. 6A), which was reversible upon a return <lb/>to 1% (Table 1, References 34 and 35, Fig. 6A). Note that, <lb/>unfortunately, the full sequence of tests could be com-<lb/>pleted for only two owls. At the point of the initial switch <lb/>to 1% isoflurane, the full sample from all four owls could <lb/>still be obtained and showed a significant elevation of <lb/>thresholds relative to the ketamine condition with artificial <lb/>respiration tested immediately before (Table 1, Reference <lb/>36), thus confirming the principal effect observed in the <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 2. Auditory nerve single-unit thresholds were severely ele-<lb/>vated under isoflurane. A, Box plot showing thresholds (normal-<lb/>ized to the age-matched CAP) for auditory nerve fibers recorded <lb/>under ketamine/xylazine and isoflurane, respectively. B, The <lb/>same data, separated into 1.5-kHz-wide CF bands, for the two <lb/>anesthetic conditions. Empty boxes represent data for the <lb/>ketamine-terminal conditions, and hatched boxes represent data <lb/>for the isoflurane-terminal condition. Note that thresholds under <lb/>isoflurane were significantly higher. Boxes and whiskers indicate <lb/>the interquartile ranges and 1.5 times the interquartile ranges, <lb/>respectively. Horizontal lines within boxes indicate medians, and <lb/>circular symbols indicate outliers that lie beyond 1.5 times the <lb/>interquartile range. <lb/>Fig. 3. CAP thresholds were severely elevated under isoflurane. <lb/>CAP threshold audiogram of an individual aged P32, under <lb/>isoflurane anesthesia (solid line). For comparison, the average <lb/>CAP audiogram for P32 owls under ketamine/xylazine anesthe-<lb/>sia is also shown (dashed line; after Köppl and Nickel, 2007). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>previous ABR experiments with the same individuals. As <lb/>the terminal experiments progressed, however, an unex-<lb/>plained, gradual, and irreversible loss of sensitivity oc-<lb/>curred at different times for different owls that, in addition, <lb/>appeared to affect the higher frequencies more (Fig. 6B). <lb/>Some thresholds exceeded the maximum SPL of the <lb/>sound system, such that the sample gradually diminished <lb/>(Fig. 6B). The cause for this deterioration, which appeared <lb/>unrelated to the anesthetic protocol is unknown and will <lb/>be discussed below in the section about confounding <lb/>factors. Importantly, we observed no changes to the fre-<lb/>quency of heart beat or the shape of the EKG waveform <lb/>that might correlate with the loss of sensitivity. <lb/>Interaction with type of respiration <lb/>The above observations suggested significant factors <lb/>that influence auditory sensitivity, in addition to the anes-<lb/>thetic agent. This prompted us to compare thresholds <lb/>obtained with two types of respiration, both under isoflu-<lb/>rane anesthesia. Indeed, thresholds in the isoflurane-ABR <lb/>condition and the ABR-terminal-isoflurane 1% condition, <lb/>both normalized to the respective ketamine thresholds, <lb/>differed significantly (Table 1, Reference 37). The main <lb/>difference was the type of respiration: unassisted breath-<lb/>ing of 0.5-1.5% isoflurane delivered in carbogen versus <lb/>artificial respiration with 1% isoflurane delivered in pure <lb/>oxygen. In the condition we normalized to, owls always <lb/>breathed normal room air unassisted. While both isoflu-<lb/>rane conditions resulted in a threshold loss (as already <lb/>shown above), the loss was relatively greater when <lb/>breathing carbogen unaided, by a median of 1 dB. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The main finding of the present study was a significant <lb/>deterioration of auditory sensitivity in barn owls under gas <lb/>anesthesia. The effect was drastic in young animals that, <lb/>compared with age-matched individuals that were anes-<lb/>thetized with a combination of ketamine and xylazine, <lb/>experienced threshold elevations in auditory nerve single-<lb/>unit responses of Ն20 dB. Consistent with this, ABR <lb/>thresholds assessed repeatedly in experiments on adult <lb/>owls were also significantly lower under ketamine/xyla-<lb/>zine anesthesia, compared with gas anesthesia with both <lb/>isoflurane and sevoflurane. Importantly, this difference <lb/>already occurred with minimal dosages and was revers-<lb/>ibly enlarged with increased isoflurane concentration. Fi-<lb/>nally, there was evidence for confounding detrimental <lb/>effects associated with the respiration mode. <lb/>Reports of anesthetic effects on peripheral auditory <lb/>responses across species <lb/>Evidence that inhalant anesthetics adversely affect co-<lb/>chlear sensitivity has accumulated in recent years for <lb/>mammals also. In the guinea pig, isoflurane was shown to <lb/>have a dose-dependent depressive effect on several au-<lb/>ditory evoked potentials [CAP, cochlear microphonic (CM) <lb/>potential, and ABR; Stronks et al., 2010). Thresholds, <lb/>amplitudes, and neural latencies were all negatively af-<lb/>fected. The effects were most pronounced at higher fre-<lb/>quencies Ն8 kHz, where CAP thresholds were elevated <lb/>by ϳ10-15 dB. Stronks et al. (2010) referenced the mea-<lb/>surements obtained under isoflurane to the awake condi-<lb/>tion, which does not necessarily suggest that isoflurane <lb/>acts worse than other anesthetics. In rat and mouse, ABR <lb/>thresholds were directly compared between anesthesia <lb/>with isoflurane and with ketamine/xylazine, and they were <lb/>found to be relatively elevated under isoflurane (Ceder-<lb/>holm et al., 2012; Ruebhausen et al., 2012). Furthermore, <lb/>in the gerbil, ABR thresholds under ketamine/xylazine <lb/>were not significantly different from those in the awake <lb/>condition (Smith and Mills, 1989). Together, these studies <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 4. Auditory nerve spontaneous discharge rates were mildly <lb/>depressed by isoflurane. A, Box plot showing overall spontane-<lb/>ous discharge rates for auditory nerve fibers recorded under <lb/>ketamine/xylazine and isoflurane, respectively. The rates under <lb/>isoflurane were significantly lower. B, The same data, separated <lb/>into 1.5-kHz-wide CF bands, for the two anesthetic conditions. <lb/>Empty boxes represent data for the ketamine-terminal condi-<lb/>tions, and hatched boxes represent data for the isoflurane-<lb/>terminal condition. Boxes and whiskers indicate the interquartile <lb/>ranges and 1.5 times the interquartile ranges, respectively. Hor-<lb/>izontal lines within boxes indicate medians, and circular symbols <lb/>and stars indicate outliers that lie beyond 1.5 times (circles) or <lb/>beyond 3 times (stars) the interquartile range. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>strongly support a differentially detrimental action of the <lb/>gas anesthetic, very similar to the present findings in the <lb/>barn owl. <lb/>However, there is clearly also species-specific variation <lb/>in the sensitivity to different anesthetics, and gas anes-<lb/>thetics do not fare universally worst. In the starling, a small <lb/>songbird, CAP amplitudes were depressed under halo-<lb/>thane anesthesia, at concentrations as low as 0.5%, com-<lb/>pared with the awake state (Kettembeil et al., 1995). The <lb/>same study, however, observed equally depressive ef-<lb/>fects of ketamine/xylazine and halothane anesthesia on <lb/>otoacoustic emissions, which reflect the responses of <lb/>sensory hair cells, in both starlings and chickens. Since <lb/>neural responses were not obtained under ketamine/xy-<lb/>lazine, it thus remained unclear whether they might be <lb/>differentially affected. In a systematic comparison of au-<lb/>ditory nerve single-unit responses under different anes-<lb/>thetic protocols in a lizard, the Tokay gecko, Dodd and <lb/>Capranica (1992) found significantly elevated thresholds <lb/>under both isoflurane and ketamine, compared with pen-<lb/>tobarbital anesthesia. Thus, in the gecko, too, ketamine <lb/>had similarly degrading effects compared with isoflurane, <lb/>albeit comparatively highly dosed at 440 mg/kg (Dodd <lb/>and Capranica, 1992). Furthermore, in the Tokay gecko, in <lb/>contrast to the present study in the owl, auditory nerve <lb/>discharge rates were also severely and differentially de-<lb/>pressed under the different anesthetic conditions: the <lb/>highest rates were observed under pentobarbital, fol-<lb/>lowed by ketamine, with isoflurane having the lowest rates <lb/>(Dodd and Capranica, 1992). <lb/>Finally, there is conflicting evidence regarding the ef-<lb/>fects of gas anesthetics on the responses of sensory hair <lb/>cells, specifically the outer hair cells of the mammalian <lb/>cochlea, measured as otoacoustic emissions. In humans, <lb/>several studies reported a selectively depressive effect of <lb/>gas anesthetics on evoked emissions (Ferber-Viart et al., <lb/>1998; Ropposch et al., 2014; Gungor et al., 2015). How-<lb/>ever, it is currently unclear whether this is a truly pharma-<lb/>cological effect on the cochlea or may be a secondary <lb/>consequence of changes in arterial blood pressure. In a <lb/>bat species, isoflurane was shown to have the opposite <lb/>effect (i.e., increased emission amplitudes; Drexl et al., <lb/>2004). It was suggested that this may reflect disinhibition <lb/>through inactivation of the olivocochlear efferent input <lb/>(see also next section). <lb/>Possible mechanisms of isoflurane and sevoflurane <lb/>action <lb/>The mechanisms that produce general anesthesia at <lb/>the systems level are still poorly understood (Rudolph and <lb/>Antkowiak, 2004; Ishizawa, 2007). The cellular sites of <lb/>action commonly involve ion channels and neurotransmit-<lb/>ter receptors that are widely expressed in the CNS and <lb/>should thus act at all levels. Nevertheless, as a general <lb/>rule, a gradual effect is observed, such that higher-level <lb/>cognitive functions are impaired at lower anesthetic con-<lb/>centrations than motor functions, early visual processing, <lb/>or basic homeostatic physiology (Campagna et al., 2003; <lb/>Rudolph and Antkowiak, 2004; Ishizawa, 2007). This sug-<lb/>gests that while the cellular sites of action may be similar, <lb/>higher centers tend to show the combined result of direct <lb/>anesthetic action and cumulative effects in neural net-<lb/>works. This also promotes the common assumption that <lb/>general anesthesia, when appropriately dosed, should not <lb/>significantly affect primary sensory processes. Therefore, <lb/>the pronounced effect of isoflurane and sevoflurane at the <lb/>most peripheral levels of the auditory system, the hair <lb/>cells and auditory nerve, is surprising. <lb/>Isoflurane and probably all inhalant anesthetics belong-<lb/>ing to the halogenated alkanes and ethers, such as halo-<lb/>thane and sevoflurane, have several known target sites of <lb/>action, all of which are predicted to suppress neural ac-<lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 5. ABR thresholds were elevated under gas anesthesia. A, Box plot showing ABR thresholds as a function of frequency, for the same <lb/>four adult individuals, tested with different anesthetic protocols in successive experiments. B, The same data, with thresholds now <lb/>normalized to the values at the respective frequency for the ketamine-ABR condition; as a visual reference, the dashed line indicates the <lb/>reference condition. Note that the minor variation across frequencies was not significant (Table 1, References 27 and 28). Therefore, C then <lb/>shows an overall comparison between anesthetic conditions. Thresholds for either the isoflurane-ABR or sevoflurane-ABR condition were <lb/>significantly higher than thresholds for the ketamine-ABR condition (Table 1, References 24 and 25). Thresholds for the ketamine-ABR <lb/>condition are shown as empty boxes, for the isoflurane-ABR condition as hatched boxes, and for the sevoflurane-ABR condition as gray <lb/>boxes. Boxes and whiskers indicate the interquartile ranges and 1.5 times the interquartile ranges, respectively. Horizontal lines within <lb/>boxes indicate medians. There were no outliers beyond 1.5 times the interquartile ranges. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>10 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>tivity (for review, see Campagna et al., 2003; Rudolph and <lb/>Antkowiak, 2004; Burns, 2014). They suppress excitatory <lb/>transmission through the inhibition of glutamate recep-<lb/>tors, both the NMDA and AMPA subtypes, and through <lb/>inhibition of nicotinic acetylcholine (ACh) receptors. Con-<lb/>versely, they enhance inhibitory transmission through the <lb/>potentiation of GABA A and glycine receptors. In contrast, <lb/>the sites of ketamine and xylazine action are more re-<lb/>stricted. Ketamine predominantly inhibits NMDA-type glu-<lb/>tamate receptors and nicotinic ACh receptors, both <lb/>normally excitatory (Rudolph and Antkowiak, 2004). Xyla-<lb/>zine is a known agonist of the ␣ 2 -adrenergic receptor <lb/>(Lierz and Korbel, 2012), which is best known for mediat-<lb/>ing the inhibition of sympathetic activity of the autonomic <lb/>nervous system. <lb/>Considering these anesthetic profiles, where are the <lb/>potential sites of action at the cochlear level? Glutamate <lb/>receptors of all ionotropic subtypes are typically found on <lb/>the afferent terminals connecting to vertebrate hair cells <lb/>(Eatock and Lysakowski, 2006). In the mammalian co-<lb/>chlea, the functionally predominant receptors are those of <lb/>the AMPA subtype (Ruel et al., 2007; Glowatzki et al., <lb/>2008). Assuming the same for birds, isoflurane and sevoflu-<lb/>rane are indeed predicted to have a potentially larger direct <lb/>impact on auditory afferents than ketamine. However, in the <lb/>present study, the observed effect was curiously specific to <lb/>auditory thresholds and affected discharge rates only mildly. <lb/>This is not obviously compatible with a general suppressive <lb/>effect on the auditory afferents. <lb/>There is currently no evidence for the inhibitory neu-<lb/>rotransmitters GABA and glycine in the avian cochlea (for <lb/>review, see Köppl, 2011), so these are not likely to be <lb/>potential mediators of the observed threshold shifts in <lb/>birds. Remaining possible sites of action are the cholin-<lb/>ergic terminals of efferent fibers to the cochlear hair cells <lb/>(Köppl, 2011). Indeed, an inhibitory effect of isoflurane on <lb/>these has been indirectly suggested for mammals (Drexl <lb/>et al., 2004). Depending on the subtypes of efferents <lb/>activated, such an enhancement could conceivably me-<lb/>diate a suppressive effect on auditory nerve afferents. <lb/>However, the pharmacology of the hair cell ACh receptor <lb/>is of an unusual nicotinic subtype (Katz et al., 2011), and <lb/>there have been no direct tests for interactions with any <lb/>anesthetic agent. <lb/>In summary, selectively depressive effects of gas anes-<lb/>thetics relative to ketamine on cochlear neural responses <lb/>are consistent with their wider spectrum of known cellular <lb/>interaction sites, specifically their inhibitory action on <lb/>ionotropic glutamate receptors. However, the specific <lb/>pattern of a drastic threshold shift without a comparable <lb/>effect on discharge rates or frequency tuning, does not fit <lb/>any straightforward predictions. Importantly, it may point <lb/>to additional, confounding effects associated with pro-<lb/>longed and invasive protocols. <lb/>Confounding factors <lb/>The anesthetic agents were not the only difference <lb/>between the experimental groups in our initial study with <lb/>young barn owls. Young owls of the isoflurane-terminal <lb/>group were artificially respirated with oxygen or carbogen, <lb/>B <lb/>A <lb/>Fig. 6. A, Isoflurane dose dependence of ABR thresholds. Box <lb/>plot showing thresholds for different isoflurane concentrations <lb/>tested sequentially in ABR-terminal experiments. Thresholds un-<lb/>der 2% isoflurane were significantly elevated relative to those <lb/>under both 1% conditions (Table 1, References 32-35). B, Grad-<lb/>ual threshold deterioration with time in terminal ABR experi-<lb/>ments. Shown are ABR thresholds normalized to the values for <lb/>the initial ketamine/xylazine condition (animal breathing air un-<lb/>aided), separated according to frequency, for all conditions <lb/>tested sequentially. Note that the number of data points contrib-<lb/>uting to each box now varies; upward arrows indicate data that <lb/>dropped out because the threshold exceeded the limit of the <lb/>sound system and thus could not be determined. Note also that <lb/>high frequencies appear to be affected more. Thresholds ob-<lb/>tained under ketamine ϩ artificial oxygen respiration are shown <lb/>as empty boxes, for the 1% isoflurane condition as hatched blue <lb/>boxes, for the 2% isoflurane condition as hatched yellow boxes, <lb/>and for the repeated 1% isoflurane condition as hatched ma-<lb/>genta boxes. Boxes and whiskers indicate the interquartile <lb/>ranges and 1.5 times the interquartile ranges, respectively. Hor-<lb/>izontal lines within boxes indicate medians. There were no out-<lb/>liers beyond 1.5 times the interquartile ranges. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>while the ketamine-terminal group breathed normal air <lb/>unaided. Therefore, in the follow-up study on adult owls, <lb/>each individual was tested repeatedly under otherwise <lb/>identical conditions. This confirmed the specific, detri-<lb/>mental effect of gas anesthesia. However, the threshold <lb/>difference relative to ketamine anesthesia was smaller for <lb/>the group of adult owls, opening several possibilities for <lb/>confounding effects. These were addressed in the termi-<lb/>nal experiments with adult owls. <lb/>Similar to previous studies (Kettembeil et al., 1995; <lb/>Stronks et al., 2010), it was shown that the inhalant an-<lb/>esthetic elevated peripheral auditory thresholds in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner. Thus, dosage is a likely confounding <lb/>factor in experiments using more invasive procedures, <lb/>such as single-unit recordings, which tend to require <lb/>higher anesthetic dosages. <lb/>Mode of respiration is another possible confounding <lb/>factor that was tested. Breathing carbogen unassisted <lb/>appeared to result in additional sensitivity losses, over <lb/>and above those related to isoflurane anesthesia, when <lb/>compared with artificial respiration with pure oxygen. We <lb/>had chosen carbogen (as opposed to pure oxygen) in the <lb/>experiments where the owls breathed the isoflurane mix-<lb/>ture unassisted, to minimize the danger of apnea. CO 2 is <lb/>known to be an important respiratory regulator, and low <lb/>partial pressure of CO 2 (p CO2 ) tends to depress respiration <lb/>(Powell, 2015). Our results, however, suggest that this <lb/>was misguided and instead resulted in a slight additional <lb/>loss of sensitivity. An obvious explanation for this effect is <lb/>lacking. We do not consider hypoxia very likely, since <lb/>carbogen still contains 95% oxygen (i.e., a concentration <lb/>far above normal air). Similarly, artificial respiration with <lb/>pure oxygen is unlikely to cause hypoxia but still appeared <lb/>to cause a decline in auditory sensitivity over time. While <lb/>no consistent, immediate deterioration associated with <lb/>the switch to artificial oxygen respiration was found, un-<lb/>explained drastic threshold losses occurred beyond 4 -5 h <lb/>in adult owls receiving artificial oxygen respiration. This is <lb/>reminiscent of the significant further deterioration within 1 <lb/>h reported for mice under isoflurane (but not ketamine) <lb/>anesthesia, breathing oxygen unaided (Cederholm et al., <lb/>2012). Such a time-dependent deterioration could also <lb/>have been a confounding factor for the auditory nerve <lb/>single-unit thresholds reported here, as these measure-<lb/>ments typically only began with a substantial delay after <lb/>anesthetic induction, due to prolonged surgery. Together, <lb/>these observations point to additional, detrimental changes <lb/>in the long term that would not be observed in short-term <lb/>experiments such as minimally invasive ABR measurements <lb/>or most veterinary procedures. Importantly, there were no <lb/>indications from our EKG monitor that the state of the ani-<lb/>mals may have been compromised. <lb/>Interestingly, a study (Jaensch et al., 2001a,b) exposing <lb/>awake budgerigars to pure oxygen over variable times, <lb/>from 3 h to 3 d, found indicators of oxygen stress by <lb/>reactive oxygen species from the shortest exposure and, <lb/>with longer exposure, additional evidence of pulmonary <lb/>inflammation due to oxygen toxicity. Although their birds <lb/>showed no outward signs, the authors concluded that &quot;in <lb/>a clinical setting, elevated inhalant oxygen tensions <lb/>should be provided to birds with caution, especially if <lb/>prolonged or repeated exposure is anticipated.&quot; This sug-<lb/>gests that there is a point where the delivery of pure <lb/>oxygen changes from being beneficial to damaging. This <lb/>point may well be reached earlier in healthy subjects, as <lb/>typically used in a neurophysiological research setting, <lb/>compared with veterinary patients. Data on respiratory or <lb/>other metabolic parameters, such as arterial partial pres-<lb/>sure of O 2 , p CO2 , or blood pressure and pH, would thus be <lb/>desirable but were not monitored in any of the auditory <lb/>studies. Unfortunately, they are known to be difficult to <lb/>obtain for small birds with body weights Ͻ400 g (Des-<lb/>marchelier et al., 2007; Lierz and Korbel, 2012). <lb/>General implications for invasive neurophysiology <lb/>The above findings suggest that despite their advan-<lb/>tages regarding animal welfare, isoflurane and related <lb/>inhalant anesthetics are not the first choice for experi-<lb/>ments in sensory and neurophysiology. The present arti-<lb/>cle focused on auditory physiology; however, there is <lb/>similar evidence, for example, for the visual cortex (Mi-<lb/>chelson and Kozai, 2018). Researchers should be aware <lb/>that sensory responses may already be depressed at the <lb/>most peripheral levels, as now shown clearly for the au-<lb/>ditory nerve. Effects on peripheral responses must also be <lb/>expected to propagate through brain nuclei. Indeed, re-<lb/>ports of reduced sensitivity and neural activity under iso-<lb/>flurane anesthesia in mammalian auditory cortex (Cheung <lb/>et al., 2001; Noda and Takahashi, 2015) are plausibly <lb/>explained by the extent of peripheral effects observed <lb/>here and in other studies. One should also be aware, <lb/>however, that the brain is not organized along one-<lb/>dimensional hierarchies. For example, the auditory sys-<lb/>tems of both birds and mammals show a multitude of <lb/>ascending and descending interconnections (Smith and <lb/>Spirou, 2002; Bolhuis et al., 2010). This makes it difficult <lb/>to predict to what extent a given peripheral impairment <lb/>will be evident in higher-order responses. Direct actions of <lb/>inhalants on higher-order neurons may add to any inher-<lb/>ited effects. <lb/>The degradation of auditory sensitivity was dose de-<lb/>pendent in the present and previous studies. In order to <lb/>minimize the detrimental effects of inhalant anesthetics, <lb/>their dosage should therefore be individually adjusted as <lb/>low as possible. In the veterinary literature, one recom-<lb/>mended way to reduce the dose further is to administer a <lb/>combination of isoflurane (or related inhalants) and nitrous <lb/>oxide (Korbel, 1998). However, regarding sensory re-<lb/>sponses, we caution that this may trade one evil for an <lb/>even worse one. Sloan et al. (2010) compared ABR, as <lb/>well as somatosensory and visual evoked responses in <lb/>the baboon, measured under anesthesia with different <lb/>proportionate mixtures of isoflurane and nitrous oxide. <lb/>They found evidence for a synergistic action of the two <lb/>agents (i.e., the combination produced more drastic ef-<lb/>fects on the sensitivity and latency of the responses than <lb/>predicted from a simple addition of the individual effects <lb/>of isoflurane and nitrous oxide). Consistent with that, <lb/>Anderson and Young (2004) found that adding nitrous <lb/>oxide in order to reduce the isoflurane necessary did not <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<body>avoid the depressive effects on sensitivity, discharge rate, <lb/>and extent of inhibition in cat dorsal cochlear nucleus <lb/>units. <lb/>Finally, there was clear evidence for additional detri-<lb/>mental effects on auditory sensitivity related to the modes <lb/>of respiration. While it may seem trivial that adequate <lb/>respiration needs to be provided, the observed effects <lb/>could not simply be traced to hypoxia. Instead, we ob-<lb/>tained tentative evidence for oxygen toxicity developing <lb/>over time and, furthermore, observed an unexplained de-<lb/>terioration when the owls breathed carbogen. Whether <lb/>these effects occur only in conjunction with isoflurane, or <lb/>may at least be exacerbated by it, remains to be shown. <lb/>Our results suggest that for prolonged experiments with <lb/>healthy experimental animals, normal air is the best op-<lb/>tion. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Anderson MJ, Young ED (2004) Isoflurane/N2O anesthesia sup-<lb/>presses narrowband but not wideband inhibition in dorsal cochlear <lb/>nucleus. Hear Res 188:29 -41. CrossRef <lb/>Antkowiak B (2001) How do general anaesthetics work? Naturwis-<lb/>senschaften 88:201-213. Medline <lb/>Bolhuis JJ, Okanoya K, Scharff C (2010) Twitter evolution: converg-<lb/>ing mechanisms in birdsong and human speech. Nat Rev Neurosci <lb/>11:747-759. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Bremen P, Poganiatz I, Campenhausen M, Wagner H (2007) Sensi-<lb/>tivity to interaural time difference and representation of azimuth in <lb/>central nucleus of inferior colliculus in the barn owl. J Comp <lb/>Physiol A 193:99 -112. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Burger RE, Lorenz FW (1960) Artificial respiration in birds by unidi-<lb/>rectional air flow. Poultry Sci 39:236 -237. CrossRef <lb/>Burns P (2014) Isoflurane &amp; sevoflurane: mechanics &amp; effects. Clin <lb/>Brief 23-26. Available at https://www.cliniciansbrief.com/article/ <lb/>isoflurane-sevoflurane-mechanics-effects <lb/>Campagna JA, Miller KW, Forman SA (2003) Mechanisms of actions <lb/>of inhaled anesthetics. N Engl J Med 348:2110 -2124. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Cederholm JM, Froud KE, Wong AC, Ko M, Ryan AF, Housley GD <lb/>(2012) Differential actions of isoflurane and ketamine-based an-<lb/>aesthetics on cochlear function in the mouse. Hear Res 292:71-<lb/>79. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Cheung SW, Nagarajan SS, Bedenbaugh PH, Schreiner CE, Wang X, <lb/>Wong A (2001) Auditory cortical neuron response differences un-<lb/>der isoflurane versus pentobarbital anesthesia. Hear Res 156:115-<lb/>127. CrossRef <lb/>Cohen YE, Knudsen EI (1995) Binaural tuning of auditory units in the <lb/>forebrain archistriatal gaze fields of the barn owl: local organization <lb/>but no space map. J Neurosci 15:5152-5168. Medline <lb/>Desmarchelier M, Rondenay Y, Fitzgerald G, Lair S (2007) Monitoring <lb/>of the ventilatory status of anesthetized birds of prey by using <lb/>end-tidal carbon dioxide measured with a microstream capnom-<lb/>eter. J Zoo Wildl Med 38:1-6. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Dodd F, Capranica RR (1992) A comparison of anesthetic agents and <lb/>their effects on the response properties of the peripheral auditory <lb/>system. Hear Res 62:173-180. CrossRef <lb/>Drexl M, Henke J, Kössl M (2004) Isoflurane increases amplitude and <lb/>incidence of evoked and spontaneous otoacoustic emissions. <lb/>Hear Res 194:135-142. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Eatock RA, Lysakowski A (2006) Mammalian vestibular hair cells. In: <lb/>Vertebrate hair cells (Eatock RA, Fay RR, Popper AN, eds), pp <lb/>348 -442. New York: Springer. <lb/>Ferber-Viart C, Preckel MP, Dubreuil C, Banssillon V, Duclaux R <lb/>(1998) Effect of anesthesia on transient evoked otoacoustic emis-<lb/>sions in humans: a comparison between propofol and isoflurane. <lb/>Hear Res 121:53-61. Medline <lb/>Flaherty D (2009) Anaesthetic drugs. In: Anaesthesia for veterinary <lb/>nurses (Welsh L, ed), pp 121-161. Chichester, UK: Wiley-<lb/>Blackwell. <lb/>Glowatzki E, Grant L, Fuchs P (2008) Hair cell afferent synapses. Curr <lb/>Opin Neurobiol 18:389 -395. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Gungor G, Bozkurt-Sutas P, Gedik O, Atas A, Babazade R, Yilmaz M <lb/>(2015) Effects of sevoflurane and desflurane on otoacoustic emis-<lb/>sions in humans. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol 272:2193-2199. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Gunkel C, Lafortune M (2005) Current techniques in avian anesthe-<lb/>sia. Semin Avian Exotic Pet Med 14:263-276. CrossRef <lb/>Ishizawa Y (2007) Mechanisms of anesthetic actions and the brain. J <lb/>Anesth 21:187-199. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Jaensch S, Cullen L, Raidal SR (2001a) Normobaric hyperoxic stress <lb/>in budgerigars: enzymic antioxidants and lipid peroxidation. Comp <lb/>Biochem Physiol C Toxicol Pharmacol 128:173-180. CrossRef <lb/>Jaensch S, Cullen L, Morton L, Raidal SR (2001b) Normobaric hy-<lb/>peroxic stress in budgerigars: non-enzymic antioxidants. Comp <lb/>Biochem Physiol C Toxicol Pharmacol 128:181-187. CrossRef <lb/>Katz E, Elgoyhen AB, Fuchs PA (2011) Cholinergic inhibition of hair <lb/>cells. In: Auditory and vestibular efferents (Ryugo D, Fay RR, <lb/>Popper AN, eds), pp 103-133. New York: Springer. <lb/>Keegan RD (2005) Inhalant anesthetics: the basics. In: Recent ad-<lb/>vances in veterinary anesthesia and analgesia: companion animals <lb/>(Gleed RD, Ludders JW, eds). Ithaca, NY: International Veterinary <lb/>Information Service. <lb/>Keller CH, Takahashi TT (2005) Localization and identification of <lb/>concurrent sounds in the owl&apos;s auditory space map. J Neurosci <lb/>25:10446 -10461. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Kettembeil S, Manley GA, Siegl E (1995) Distortion-product otoa-<lb/>coustic emissions and their anaesthesia sensitivity in the European <lb/>Starling and the chicken. Hear Res 86:47-62. Medline <lb/>Köppl C (1997) Frequency tuning and spontaneous activity in the <lb/>auditory nerve and cochlear nucleus magnocellularis of the barn <lb/>owl, Tyto alba. J Neurophysiol 77:364 -377. CrossRef <lb/>Köppl C (2011) Evolution of the octavolateral efferent system. In: <lb/>Auditory and vestibular efferents (Ryugo D, Fay RR, Popper AN, <lb/>eds), pp 217-259. New York: Springer. <lb/>Köppl C, Gleich O (2007) Evoked cochlear potentials in the barn owl. <lb/>J Comp Physiol A Neuroethol Sens Neural Behav Physiol 193:601-<lb/>612. CrossRef <lb/>Köppl C, Nickel R (2007) Prolonged maturation of cochlear function <lb/>in the barn owl after hatching. J Comp Physiol A Neuroethol Sens <lb/>Neural Behav Physiol 193:613-624. CrossRef <lb/>Köppl C, Futterer E, Nieder B, Sistermann R, Wagner H (2005) <lb/>Embryonic and posthatching development of the barn owl (Tyto <lb/>alba): reference data for age determination. Dev Dyn 233:1248 -<lb/>1260. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Korbel R (1998) Vergleichende Untersuchungen zur Inhalationsanäs-<lb/>thesie mit Isofluran (Forene) und Sevofluran (SEVOrane) bei <lb/>Haustauben (Columba livia Gmel., 1789, var. domestica) und Vor-<lb/>stellung eines Referenz-Narkoseprotokolls für Vögel. Tierärztliche <lb/>Praxis 26:211-223. <lb/>Larsen ON, Christensen-Dalsgaard J, Jensen KK (2016) Role of <lb/>intracranial cavities in avian directional hearing. Biol Cybern 110: <lb/>319 -331. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Lierz M, Korbel R (2012) Anesthesia and analgesia in birds. J Exotic <lb/>Pet Med 21:44 -58. CrossRef <lb/>Lukasik VM, Gillies RJ (2003) Animal anaesthesia for in vivo magnetic <lb/>resonance. NMR Biomed 16:459 -467. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Michelson NJ, Kozai TDY (2018) Isoflurane and ketamine differen-<lb/>tially influence spontaneous and evoked laminar electrophysiology <lb/>in mouse V1. J Neurophyiol. Advance online publication. Retrieved <lb/>October 27, 2018. doi:10.1152/jn.00299.2018. <lb/>Noda T, Takahashi H (2015) Anesthetic effects of isoflurane on the <lb/>tonotopic map and neuronal population activity in the rat auditory <lb/>cortex. Eur J Neurosci 42:2298 -2311. CrossRef Medline <lb/>O&apos;Keeffe NJ, Healy TEJ (1999) The role of new anesthetic agents. <lb/>Pharmacol Ther 84:233-248. Medline <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>13 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Powell FL (2015) Respiration. In: Sturkie&apos;s avian physiology, Vol6 <lb/>(Scanes CG, ed), pp 301-336. Amsterdam: Elsevier. <lb/>Preckel B, Bolten J (2005) Pharmacology of modern volatile anaes-<lb/>thetics. Best Pract Res Clin Anaesthesiol 19:331-348. Medline <lb/>Raftery A (2013) Avian anaesthesia. In Pract 35:272-278. CrossRef <lb/>Ropposch T, Walch C, Avian A, Mausser G, Spary M (2014) Effects <lb/>of the depth of anesthesia on distortion product otoacoustic emis-<lb/>sions. Eur Arch Otorhinolaryngol 271:2897-2904. CrossRef Med-<lb/>line <lb/>Rudolph U, Antkowiak B (2004) Molecular and neuronal substrates <lb/>for general anaesthetics. Nat Rev Neurosci 5:709 -720. CrossRef <lb/>Medline <lb/>Ruebhausen MR, Brozoski TJ, Bauer CA (2012) A comparison of the <lb/>effects of isoflurane and ketamine anesthesia on auditory brains-<lb/>tem response (ABR) thresholds in rats. Hear Res 287:25-29. <lb/>CrossRef Medline <lb/>Ruel J, Wang J, Rebillard G, Eybalin M, Lloyd R, Pujol R, Puel JL <lb/>(2007) Physiology, pharmacology and plasticity at the inner hair <lb/>cell synaptic complex. Hear Res 227:19 -27. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Schwartzkopff J, Brémond JC (1963) Méthode de dérivation des <lb/>potentiels cochléaires chez lЈoiseau. J Physiol Paris 55:495-518. <lb/>Shawyer CR (1998) The barn owl. Chelmsford, UK: Arlequin. <lb/>Sloan T, Sloan H, Rogers J (2010) Nitrous oxide and isoflurane are <lb/>synergistic with respect to amplitude and latency effects on sen-<lb/>sory evoked potentials. J Clin Monit Comput 24:113-123. Cross-<lb/>Ref Medline <lb/>Smith DI, Mills JH (1989) Anesthesia effects: auditory brain-stem <lb/>response. Electroencephal Clin Neurophysiol 72:422-428. Medline <lb/>Smith PH, Spirou GA (2002) From the cochlea to the cortex and <lb/>back. In: Integrative functions in the mammalian auditory pathway <lb/>(Oertel D, Fay RR, Popper AN, eds), pp 6 -71. New York: Springer <lb/>Verlag. <lb/>Sonner JM, Antognini JF, Dutton RC, Flood P, Gray AT, Harris RA, <lb/>Homanics GE, Kendig J, Orser B, Raines DE, Trudell J, Vissel B, <lb/>Eger EI (2003) Inhaled anesthetics and immobility: mechanisms, <lb/>mysteries, and minimum alveolar anesthetic concentration. Anesth <lb/>Analg 97:718 -740. Medline <lb/>Stronks HC, Aarts MCJ, Klis SFL (2010) Effects of isoflurane on <lb/>auditory evoked potentials in the cochlea and brainstem of guinea <lb/>pigs. Hear Res 260:20 -29. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Vahle-Hinz C, Detsch O (2002) What can in vivo electrophysiology in <lb/>animal models tell us about mechanisms of anaesthesia? Br J <lb/>Anaesth 89:123-142. Medline <lb/>Varner J, Clifton KR, Broderson R, Wyatt RD (2004) Lack of efficacy <lb/>of injectable ketamine with xylazine or diazepam for anesthesia in <lb/>chickens. Lab Anim 33:36 -39. CrossRef Medline <lb/>Windels F (2006) Neuronal activity: from in vitro preparation to be-<lb/>having animals. Mol Neurobiol 34:1-25. Medline <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">New Research <lb/></note>

			<page>14 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September/October 2018, 5(5) e0140-18.2018 <lb/>eNeuro.org </note>


	</text>
</tei>
