<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9908383v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 26 Aug 1999 <lb/>Universal relationship between the penetration depth and the <lb/>normal-state conductivity in YBaCuO. <lb/>A. Pimenov 1 , A. Loidl 1 , B. Schey 1 , B. Stritzker 1 , G. Jakob 2 , H. Adrian 2 , A. V. Pronin 3 , <lb/>and Yu. G. Goncharov <lb/>1 Institut für Physik, Universität Augsburg, 86135 Augsburg, Germany <lb/>Institut für Physik, Universität Mainz, 55099 Mainz, Germany <lb/>3 Institute of General Physics, Russian Acad. Sci., 117942 Moscow, Russia <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The absolute values of the conductivity in the normal state σ n and of <lb/>the low temperature penetration depths λ(0) were measured for a number <lb/>of different samples of the YBaCuO family. We found a striking correlation <lb/>between σ n and λ −2 regardless of doping, oxygen reduction or defects, thus <lb/>providing a simple method to predict the superconducting penetration depth <lb/>and to have an estimate of the sample quality by measuring the normal-state <lb/>conductivity. <lb/></front>

			<body>The superconducting penetration depth, λ(0), is one of the most important electrody-<lb/>namic properties of the high-temperature superconductors and provides direct information <lb/>about the spectral weight of the superconducting condensate [1]. In the normal state the low <lb/>frequency electrodynamics can be characterized by the absolute value of the conductivity <lb/>σ n (ν, T ). At not too high frequencies, σ n (ν, T ) is in a good approximation a real function <lb/>of frequency. Because λ(0) and σ n (0, T ) both involve a Fermi-surface averaging and depend <lb/>on the same amplitude factors e 2 N(0)υ 2 <lb/>F [2], they may be expected to be connected to each <lb/>other. <lb/>In order to investigate possible correlations experimentally, we have carried out <lb/>submillimeter-wave (100 GHz ¡ ν ¡1100 GHz) transmission experiments on different thin <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ films. Optimally doped films on different substrates were obtained by laser <lb/>ablation and by magnetron sputtering. One film was oxygen reduced after the measurement <lb/>and then remeasured under identical conditions. Transmission experiments in the frequency <lb/>range 100-1100 GHz were performed utilizing a set of backward-wave oscillators. The mea-<lb/>surements were performed in a Mach-Zehnder interferometer arrangement [3] which allows <lb/>both, the measurements of transmission and phase shift. The properties of the substrates <lb/>were determined in separate experiments. Utilizing the Fresnel optical formulas for the <lb/>complex transmission coefficient for a double layer system, the complex conductivity was <lb/>determined from the observed spectra without any approximations. It is important to note, <lb/>that the absolute values of the conductivity could be deduced directly from the experiment. <lb/>The penetration depth was calculated from the conductivity data via λ = c/ωk, with k <lb/>being the imaginary part of the complex refractive index k = Im[i(σ 1 + iσ 2 )/ε ω] 1/2 . This <lb/>expression for λ gives the usual microwave result λ = (µ 0 ωσ 2 ) −1/2 in the limit σ 1 ≪ |σ 2 | and <lb/>reduces to the expression for the skin depth in the normal state (σ ≫ |σ 2 |). <lb/>The submillimeter properties of YBa Cu 3 O 7−δ films for a fixed frequency ν = 450 GHz <lb/>(15 cm −1 ) are summarized in the Table 1. In addition, some details of the film preparation, <lb/>the weight of the superconducting condensate (ω <lb/>p,s = c 2 /λ(0) 2 ), and the effective scattering <lb/>rate (Eq. 1) are given. The detailed submillimeter-wave data for the samples No.1,3,5 were <lb/>published previously [5-7]. The data in Tab.1 are represented in the order of decreasing <lb/>absolute values of the conductivities at 100 K. Comparing the conductivity column with the <lb/>penetration depth column, the correlation between these two quantities becomes obvious. <lb/>
			With the exception of the sample No.4, the penetration depth increases with decreasing <lb/>conductivities. We note that the scattering of data for different samples may be connected <lb/>with experimental difficulties in measuring the absolute values of conductivity and penetra-<lb/>tion depth. In addition, in spite of substantial progress in prepairing good quality YBaCuO <lb/>films [4], the details of deposition process still may influence the experimental results. <lb/>To check the possible correlation between σ n and λ in more detail, the normal state con-<lb/>ductivity and the superconducting penetration depth were analyzed on the basis of published <lb/>data available up to now. The results of this analysis are summarized in Fig. 1. In order to <lb/>simplify the analysis only results on YBaCuO based materials were considered. To compare <lb/>the absolute values of the conductivity for different samples the characteristic temperature <lb/>of T =100 K was chosen. It is well known [8] that the resistivity even of oxygen reduced <lb/>or doped cuprates is to a reasonable approximation linear for temperatures between 100 K <lb/>and 300 K. A linear temperature scaling was therefore used, if the results were reported at <lb/>temperatures different from T =100 K. Taking into account the relatively strong scattering <lb/>of the data for different samples, this procedure certainly introduces no substantial errors. <lb/>Fig. 1 represents the data as measured by different experimental methods. In addition to <lb/>the thin film results by THz transmission technique [9-15], mutual inductance data [16,17] <lb/>and single crystal data [18-22] are shown. The remarkable feature of Fig. 1 is that the <lb/>majority of experimental points closely follows the dashed line, which is the best fit to our <lb/>data according to the expression λ(0) −2 /µ 0 = σ n /τ , with 1/τ = 22 THz. Fig. 1 thus suggest <lb/>that the absolute value of the conductivity in the normal state is approximately proportional <lb/>to the spectral weight of the superconducting condensate ω <lb/>p,s or to the inverse square of the <lb/>penetration depth λ(0) −2 . <lb/>In the following we would like to suggest rather simple arguments to understand this rela-<lb/>tion. Within the isotropic approximation the real part of the conductivity can be written as <lb/>σ n = ε 0 ω 2 <lb/>p,n τ , where τ −1 is the quasiparticle scattering rate and ε 0 ω 2 <lb/>p,n is the spectral weight <lb/>of the Drude peak. For a number of high temperature cuprates in the normal conducting <lb/>state the characteristic scattering rate has been shown to increase linear in temperature fol-<lb/>lowing h/τ ≈ 2k B T [23]. Assuming the value ∆ = 2k B T C for the energy gap [24], one obtains <lb/>the approximation for the ratio of mean free path to the coherence length, ℓ/ξ = πτ ∆/ℏ ≈ 3. <lb/>As the scattering rate decreases even stronger than linearly below T C [1], at low tempera-<lb/>tures the high-T C superconductors are in the clean limit and the spectral weight of a Drude <lb/>peak (ε 0 ω 2 <lb/>p,n = ne 2 /m * ) is expected to fully condense into the delta function at T =0K. <lb/>This conclusion is supported by the Drude-analysis of the frequency dependent conductivity <lb/>of YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ [5] and by a comparison of the conductivity spectral weights at infrared <lb/>frequencies [25]. In the clean limit the following expression holds <lb/>1 <lb/>µ 0 λ(0) 2 = ε 0 ω 2 <lb/>p,s = ε 0 ω <lb/>p,n = σ n /τ <lb/>(1) <lb/>
			The Eq.(1) thus suggests the possible explanation of the correlation in Fig. 1: obviously <lb/>defects (doping, sample quality) and oxygen concentration change only the density of states <lb/>at the Fermi-level, N(0), or the effective number of charge carriers, ω 2 <lb/>p,s and ω 2 <lb/>p,n , and do not <lb/>affect the effective scattering rate τ −1 . Theoretical calculations of the normal-state prop-<lb/>erties using spin-fluctuation scattering [26], Fermi-surface nesting [27] or phenomenological <lb/>marginal Fermi-liquid approach [28] result in the quasiparticle scattering rate, which is not <lb/>dependent on N(0), but is approximately proportional to temperature. Therefore, within a <lb/>reasonable approximation, τ −1 may be supposed to be unsensitve to the level of defects. As <lb/>long as the sample is in the clean limit, the complete Drude spectral weight ω 2 <lb/>p,n condenses <lb/>into the superconducting delta function retaining the correlation between the normal and <lb/>the superconducting state given by Eq. (1). <lb/>Interestingly, the Ni-and Zn-doped samples of Ulm et al. [17] and the Pr doped samples of <lb/>Brorson et al. [9] still follow the correlation of Fig.1, except for the samples with the highest <lb/>doping levels (6% Ni, 40% Pr, or 4% Zn doping). The different behavior of heavily doped <lb/>samples is probably due to the fact, that they are no more in the clean limit. Therefore a <lb/>substantial portion of the &quot;normal&quot; spectral weight is not condensed into the delta function <lb/>at low temperatures and the penetration depth λ(0) = c/ω p,s is substantially higher than <lb/>the value estimated from Eq. (1), λ(0) = c/ω p,n . In addition Fig. 1 shows that Zn doping <lb/>has the strongest effect on the electrodynamic properties of high-T C &apos;s compared to Ni or Pr. <lb/>Similar conclusion has been drawn on the basis of the microwave data by Bonn et al. [29]. <lb/>Although simple arguments, presented above, give an idea to understand the observed <lb/>correlation, we cannot exclude other possible explanations. E.g. even the application of <lb/>Fermi-liquid picture to high-temperature superconductors is still an intensively discussed <lb/>problem [2,30]. Further on and especially concerning optimally doped YBCO films, the <lb/>extrinsic effects may also play an important role in determining the conductivity values. The <lb/>influence of weak links on the surface impedance of granular superconductors was discussed <lb/>in detail by Halbritter [31]. <lb/>The scattering rate 1/τ = 22 THz, as deduced from the dashed line in Fig. 1, leads <lb/>to the following expression at T =100 K: h/τ = 1.7k B T . This relation is similar to h/τ ≈ <lb/>2k B T [23] cited above. On the basis of the above presented discussion we may conclude, <lb/>that the scattering rate h/τ = 1.7k B T is to a good approximation independent of doping, <lb/>oxygen depletion and defects. Hence, the proportionality between λ(0) −2 and σ n provides <lb/>a simple possibility to characterize the superconducting properties of the YBaCuO samples <lb/>by measuring the normal state conductivity by e.g. standard four point method. On the <lb/>basis of data, presented in Fig.1 the penetration depth of a certain sample is given by the <lb/>approximate expression <lb/>λ(0)[nm] = 190/ σ n (100K)[10 4 Ω −1 cm −1 ] = 19 • ρ n (100K)[µΩ • cm] <lb/>(2) <lb/>Eq. (2) describes 80% of all penetration depth data in Fig. 1 with deviations well <lb/>below 25%. Finally it should be noted, that most points of Fig.1 represent thin-film data. <lb/>The applicability of Eq. (2) for single crystals should be checked in more detail in further <lb/>investigations. <lb/>In conclusion, we have measured the conductivity and the penetration depth of a variety <lb/>of YBaCuO samples and compared our results to published data. We have plotted the <lb/>low temperature penetration depth as a function of the normal-state conductivity, where <lb/>the absolute values for both parameters were available on the same sample. In this plot <lb/>we observe a correlation λ −2 ∽ σ n . This observation allows the estimate of the penetration <lb/>depth of a given YBaCuO sample by measuring its normal state conductivity. In the normal <lb/>conducting state we find universal scattering rate h/τ = 1.7k B T independent of defects, <lb/>oxygen concentration and doping. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">This research was partly supported by the BMBF under the contract number 13N6917/0 <lb/>(EKM). <lb/></div>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] Bonn D. A. and Hardy W. N., in Physical Properties of high Temperature Superconduc-<lb/>tors V, Ed. by D. M. Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1996). p. 7. <lb/>[2] Hensen S., Müller G., Rieck C. T. and Scharnberg K., Phys. Rev. B56 (1997) 6237. <lb/>[3] Volkov A. A., Goncharov Yu. G., Kozlov G. V., Lebedev S. P. and Prochorov A. M., <lb/>Infrared Phys. 25 (1985) 369; G. V. Kozlov and A. A. Volkov in Millimeter and Sub-<lb/>millimeter Wave Spectroscopy of Solids, Ed. by G. Grüner (Springer, Berlin, 1998), <lb/>p.51. <lb/>[4] Lemberger T. R., in Physical Properties of high Temperature Superconductors III, Ed. <lb/>by D. M. Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1992). p. 471. <lb/>[5] Pimenov A., Loidl A., Jakob G. and Adrian H., Phys. Rev. B59 (1999) 4390. <lb/>[6] Pimenov A., Pronin A. V., Schey B., Stritzker B. and Loidl A., Physica B244 (1998) <lb/>49. <lb/>[7] Pimenov A., Loidl A., Jakob G. and Adrian H., cond-mat/9901039 . <lb/>[8] Iye Y., in Physical Properties of high Temperature Superconductors III, Ed. by D. M. <lb/>Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1992), p. 285. <lb/>[9] Brorson S. D., Buhleier R., Trofimov I. E., White J. O., Ludwig Ch., Balakirev F. F., <lb/>Habermeier H.-U. and Kuhl J., J. Opt. Soc. Am. B13 (1996) 1979 . <lb/>[10] Feenstra B. J., Klaassen F. C., van der Marel D., Barber Z. H., Pinaya R. P. and <lb/>Decroux M., Physica C278 (1997) 213 . <lb/>[11] Ludwig Ch., Jiang Q., Kuhl J. and Zegenhagen J., Physica C269 (1996) 249. <lb/>[12] Nagashima T., Harada S., Hangyo M. and Nakashima S., Physica C293 (1997) 283. <lb/>[13] Dähne U., Amrein T., Goncharov Y., Klein N., Kozlov G., Schultz L., Tellmann N. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>and Urban K., Physica C235-240 (1994) 2066; Dähne U., Goncharov Y., Klein N., <lb/>Tellmann N., Kozlov G. and Urban K., J. Supercond. 8 (1995) 129. <lb/>[14] Nuss M. C., Mankiewich P. M., O&apos;Malley M. L.,. Westerwick E. H and Littlewood P. <lb/>B., Phys. Rev. Lett. 66 (1991) 3305. <lb/>[15] de Vaulchier L. A., Vieren J. P., Guldner Y., Bontemps N., Combescot R., Lemaître <lb/>Y. and Mage J. C., Europhys. Lett. 33 (1996) 153; Djordjevic S., de Vaulchier L. A., <lb/>Bontemps N., Vieren J. P., Guldner Y., Moffat S., Preston J., Castel X., Guilloux-Viry <lb/>M. and Perrin A., Eur. Phys. J. B5 (1998) 847. <lb/>[16] Fiory A. T., Hebard A. F., Eick R. H., Mankiewich P. M., Howard R. E. and O&apos;Malley <lb/>M. L., Phys. Rev. Lett. 65 (1990) 3441. <lb/>[17] Ulm E. R., Kim J.-T., Lemberger T. R., Foltyn S. R. and Wu X., Phys. Rev. B51 <lb/>(1995) 9193; Kim J.-T., Lemberger T. R., Foltyn S. R. and Wu X., Phys. Rev. B49 <lb/>(1994) 15970; Sumner M. J., Kim J.-T. and Lemberger T. R., Phys. Rev. B47 (1993) <lb/>12248. <lb/>[18] Basov D. N., Liang R., Bonn D. A., Hardy W. N., Dabrowski B., Quijada M., Tanner <lb/>D. B., Rice J. P., Ginsberg D. M. and Timusk T., Phys. Rev. Lett. 74 (1995) 598. <lb/>[19] ZhangK., Bonn D. A., Kamal S., Liang R., Baar D. J., Hardy W. N., Basov D. and <lb/>Timusk T., Phys. Rev. Lett. 73 (1994) 2484. <lb/>[20] Kitano H., Shibauchi T., Uchinokura K., Maeda A., Asaoka H. and Takei H., Phys. <lb/>Rev. B51 (1995) 1401. <lb/>[21] Sonier J. E., Kiefl R. F., Brewer J. H.,. Bonn D. A, Carolan J. F., Chow K. H., Dosanjh <lb/>P., Hardy W. N., Liang R., MacFarlane W. A., Mendels P., Morris G. D., Riseman T. <lb/>M. and Schneider J. W., Phys. Rev. Lett. (1994) 744; Liang R., Dosanjh P., Bonn <lb/>D. A., Baar D. J., Carolan J. F. and Hardy W. N., Physica C195 (1992) 51. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[22] Kamal S., Liang R., Hosseini A., Bonn D.A. and Hardy W. N., Phys. Rev. B58 (1998) <lb/>8933. <lb/>[23] Tanner D. B. and Timusk T. in Physical Properties of high Temperature Superconductors <lb/>III, Ed. by D. M. Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1992), p. 363. <lb/>[24] Panagopoulos Ch. and Xiang T., Phys. Rev. Lett., 81 (1998) 2336. <lb/>[25] Tanner D. B., Liu H. L., Quijada M. A., Zibold A. M., Berger H., Kelley R. J., Onellion <lb/>M., Chou F. C., Johnston D. C., Rice J. P., Ginsberg D. M. and Markert J. T., Physica <lb/>B244 (1998) 1. <lb/>[26] Hirschfeld P. J., Putikka W. O., and Scalapino D. J., Phys. Rev. B50 (1994) 10250. <lb/>[27] Virosztek A. and Ruvalds J., Phys. Rev. B42 (1990) 4064. <lb/>[28] Littlewood P. B. and Varma C. M., J. Appl. Phys. (1991) 4979. <lb/>[29] Bonn D.A., Kamal S., Zhang K., Liang R., Baar D. J., Klein E. and Hardy W. N., <lb/>Phys. Rev. B50 (1994) 4051. <lb/>[30] Shulga D. V., Dolgov O. V., and Maksimov E. G., Physica C178 (1991) 266. <lb/>[31] Halbritter J., J. Supercond. 8 (1995) 691. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>No. T C [K] Preparation <lb/>Substrate <lb/>d <lb/>[nm] <lb/>σ n <lb/>[10 4 Ω −1 cm −1 ] <lb/>λ <lb/>[nm] <lb/>ω 2 <lb/>p,s <lb/>[eV 2 ] <lb/>τ -1 <lb/>[THz] <lb/>Ref. <lb/>1 <lb/>89.5 magnetron sputt. NdGaO 3 81 <lb/>1.51 <lb/>1.71 22.8 [4] <lb/>2 <lb/>91.3 magnetron sputt. LaAlO 3 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>204 0.952 19.1 <lb/>3 <lb/>85.9 <lb/>laser ablation <lb/>MgO <lb/>85 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>243 0.671 16.8 [5] <lb/>4 <lb/>89 magnetron sputt. NdGaO 3 75 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>215 0.857 26.9 <lb/>5 <lb/>56.5 <lb/>No.1 reduced NdGaO 3 81 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>279 0.509 17.0 [6] <lb/>6 <lb/>91 <lb/>laser ablation NdGaO 3 70 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>292 0.464 24.6 <lb/>Table 1. Submillimeter-wave properties of YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ films at ν = 450 GHz. The <lb/>normal state conductivity σ n and the superconducting penetration depth λ are given at <lb/>temperatures 100 K and 6 K respectively. The spectral weight of the superconducting <lb/>condensate ω 2 <lb/>p,s and the effective scattering rate 1/τ were calculated using Eq. (1). <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

        	<body>Figure caption. <lb/>Fig. 1. Low temperature (T K) penetration depth λ of different YBCO samples as <lb/>a function of the normal-state conductivity σ n at T =100 K. Dashed line is drawn according <lb/>to the expression λ(0) −2 /µ 0 = σ n /τ using 1/τ = 22THz. The characters in the symbols <lb/>correspond to: <lb/>Rhombs -single crystal data: <lb/>B -Basov et al. [18] and Zhang et al. [19]; K -Kitano et al. [20]; K1 -Kamal et al. [22]; <lb/>S -Sonier et al. [21]. <lb/>Circles -optimally doped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ films: <lb/>closed circles -this work, Table 1; B -Brorson et al. [9]; D -Dähne et al. [13]; F -Fiory <lb/>et al. [16]; L -Ludwig et al. [11]; N -Nagashima et al. [12] (λ is taken at T =40 K); N1 -<lb/>Nuss et al. [14]; V -de Vaulchier et al. [15]. <lb/>Squares -oxygen reduced YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ films: <lb/>closed square -this work, Table 1; L -Ludwig et al. [11]. <lb/>Down triangles -doped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ films: <lb/>B -Brorson et al. [9] (20%, 30%, and 40% Pr -doped films); F -Feenstra et al. [10] <lb/>(DyBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ ); U -Ulm et al. [17] (2%, 4% and 6% Ni doped and 2% and 4% Zn doped <lb/>films). Dotted lines are guide to the eye. Arrows indicate the increasing doping direction.<lb/>
        	0.1 <lb/>1000 <lb/>K <lb/>K <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>S <lb/>K1 <lb/>K1 <lb/>L <lb/>L <lb/>U <lb/>U <lb/>U <lb/>U <lb/>U <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>L <lb/>B <lb/>N1 <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>K1 <lb/>crystals <lb/>films opt. <lb/>films red. <lb/>films dop. <lb/>Fig. 1, Pimenov et al. <lb/>D <lb/>N i d o p e d <lb/>P r d o p e d <lb/>Z n d o p e d <lb/>F <lb/>V <lb/>τ -1 <lb/>= 2 2 T H z <lb/>YBaCuO <lb/>λ [nm] <lb/>σ 1 (100 K) [10 <lb/>4 Ω <lb/>-1 cm <lb/>-1 ] </body>


	</text>
</tei>
