<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		
			<front>Europhys. Lett., 58 (4), pp. 589-595 (2002) <lb/>EUROPHYSICS LETTERS <lb/>15 May 2002 <lb/>Absence of pseudogap <lb/>in heavily overdoped Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ <lb/>from tunneling spectroscopy of break junctions <lb/>L. Ozyuzer 1,2 , J. F. Zasadzinski 1,3 , K. E. Gray , <lb/>C. Kendziora 4 and N. Miyakawa <lb/>1 Materials Science Division, Argonne National Laboratory -Argonne IL 60439, USA <lb/>Department of Physics, Izmir Institute of Technology -TR-35437 Izmir, Turkey <lb/>3 Physics Division, Illinois Institute of Technology -Chicago IL 60616, USA <lb/>4 Naval Research Laboratory -Washington DC 20375, USA <lb/>5 Department of Applied Physics, Science University of Tokyo -Tokyo, Japan <lb/>(received 29 September 2001; accepted in final form 21 February 2002) <lb/>PACS. 74.72.-h -High-Tc compounds. <lb/>PACS. 74.50.+r -Proximity effects, weak links, tunneling phenomena, and Josephson effects. <lb/>PACS. 74.62.Dh -Effects of crystal defects, doping and substitution. <lb/>Abstract. -We report tunneling spectroscopy of superconductor-insulator-superconductor <lb/>break junctions on heavily overdoped Bi2Sr2CaCu2O 8+δ with Tc = 56 K. At T <lb/>Tc, the <lb/>junction conductances display well-defined quasiparticle peaks at ±2∆ and in some cases a <lb/>Josephson current at zero bias. Gap values as small as ∆ = 10.5 meV have been observed <lb/>leading to 2∆/kTc near the BCS limit for d x 2 −y 2 pairing. Temperature dependence of the <lb/>gap magnitude, ∆(T ), follows the BCS relation and both the quasiparticle gap and Josephson <lb/>current vanish for T &gt; Tc. Above Tc, the tunneling conductance shows a flat background <lb/>without any indication of a pseudogap near the Fermi level. <lb/></front>

			<body>High-temperature superconductors (HTSs) have emerged with properties that are very <lb/>different from those found in conventional superconductors. One such property of the under-<lb/>doped phase is the presence of a pseudogap observed well above T c , up to a characteristic <lb/>temperature T *, that has been detected by a number of experimental techniques, such as <lb/>in-plane resistivity, angle-resolved photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES), specific heat, and <lb/>NMR [1,2]. One reason why the presence of the pseudogap garners a lot of attention is that it <lb/>might be related to the phenomenon of superconductivity in HTSs. Numerous theories have <lb/>been proposed to explain the origin of the pseudogap in the underdoped phase, such as pairing <lb/>fluctuation theory, spin-charge separation scenario, phase fluctuations [3-6]. <lb/>While it is generally accepted that the pseudogap is a property of the underdoped phase, <lb/>it is still debatable whether it is also present in the overdoped region. Whereas T * can be <lb/>determined in various experiments (e.g., a change in slope of in-plane resistivity vs. T ) a <lb/>corresponding direct measurement of a pseudogap in the density of states is not always avail-<lb/>able. For overdoped HTSs, none of the experimental techniques listed earlier have detected a <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">c EDP Sciences <lb/></note>

			<page>590 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">EUROPHYSICS LETTERS <lb/></note>

			<body>clear pseudogap [1]. Some results from scanning tunneling microscopy (STM) [7,8] and planar <lb/>tunnel [9] junctions have suggested that the pseudogap exists at all hole doping concentrations <lb/>in Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ (Bi-2212). In contrast, another STM study in the ab-plane of Bi-2212 <lb/>does not show any gap-like feature in the overdoped phase [10]. These conflicting observations <lb/>hinder our understanding of the pseudogap and demand further tunneling investigations of <lb/>the overdoped phase of Bi-2212. One reason for the conflict might be that the doping level of <lb/>Bi-2212 in the region of the junction is not the same as in the bulk. Miyakawa et al. [11] have <lb/>demonstrated a clear relationship between the energy gap (∆) and hole concentration and <lb/>therefore the measured gap provides important information on the local doping level. Here <lb/>we report measurements of heavily overdoped crystals (T c = 56 K) that exhibit a ∆ value as <lb/>low as 10.5 meV, much smaller than the optimal doped value of 38 meV and clearly in the <lb/>overdoped state. <lb/>The break junction method can be used to measure the superconductor-insulator-supercon-<lb/>ductor (SIS) tunneling conductance in conventional and HTSs. One advantage of this method <lb/>is that the junction can be fabricated at low temperatures so that it is unexposed to air. The <lb/>SIS tunneling spectroscopy is not only capable of measuring quasiparticle excitations but also <lb/>the Cooper pairs in the form of the Josephson current, I c , which is purely a superconducting <lb/>phenomenon. This capability provides an important advantage since I c (T ) → 0 defines the <lb/>junction T c . In other words, the phase coherence temperature can be identified by measuring <lb/>the temperature dependence of the critical current. <lb/>Single crystals of Bi-2212 were grown by a self-flux technique in a strong thermal gradient <lb/>to stabilize the direction of solidification. Overdoping was accomplished using stainless-steel <lb/>cells sealed with the sample immersed in liquid oxygen [12]. The critical temperature of the <lb/>samples was determined from the magnetization which showed sharp transitions. Tunneling <lb/>measurements were done with a point contact apparatus [13]. The Bi-2212 crystal is cleaved <lb/>along the ab-plane and mounted on a substrate so that the tip approaches along the c-axis. <lb/>A novel method is used to form the SIS break junctions. A differential micrometer-driven <lb/>Au tip approaches the sample at LHe temperature and superconductor-insulator-normal-<lb/>metal (SIN) junctions are first formed. These conductances exhibit quasiparticle peaks at <lb/>eV ∼ ±∆ and clearly show the standard dip and hump features above ∆ in the occupied part <lb/>of the DOS [7, 11]. Further increasing the force of the tip leads to an Ohmic contact (less <lb/>than 10 ohm) with the crystal and a mechanical bond. A Bi-2212 piece is easily dislodged by <lb/>cleaving along the double Bi-O layer. As a result of this process, an SIS junction forms between <lb/>the Bi-2212 piece and the rest of the crystal. The SIS conductances show quasiparticle peaks at <lb/>±2∆ that are consistent with the ∆ value obtained from the SIN junctions. Additionally, the <lb/>SIS conductances also show a symmetric dip, hump and background, and also the presence <lb/>of a Josephson current. The magnitude of this current generally decreases as the junction <lb/>resistance increases. <lb/>Figure 1(a) shows the temperature dependence of the tunneling conductance for junction <lb/># 1 on the heavily overdoped Bi-2212. The 4.2 K data show a tunneling conductance of <lb/>a Bi-2212 break junction with sharp quasiparticle peaks at ±2∆, a weak Josephson current <lb/>peak at zero bias, and the dip and hump features above ±2∆. One of the distinct features of <lb/>this junction is the relatively flat background. This is different than the typical SIS conduc-<lb/>tances found from optimally doped [14] and overdoped [15] Bi-2212 that show a decreasing <lb/>background up to ±350 meV. For SIS junctions at low temperatures, the thermal smearing <lb/>is minimal and the quasiparticle peaks can be used to estimate the energy gap size, which <lb/>is 14 meV for the 4.2 K spectra in fig. 1(a), giving a coupling ratio 2∆/kT c ∼ 5.8. A set <lb/>of temperature-dependent data for another SIS break junction (junction # 2) of Bi-2212 is <lb/>shown in fig. 1(b). Although the junction resistance in fig. 1(b) is approximately the same <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">L. Ozyuzer et al.: Absence of pseudogap in heavily overdoped Bi-2212 <lb/></note>

			<page>591 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>-150-100 -50 0 50 100 150 <lb/>dI/dV(mS) <lb/>Voltage(mV) <lb/>T=4.2 K <lb/>T=15 K <lb/>T=30 K <lb/>T=39 K <lb/>T=48 K <lb/>T=50 K <lb/>T=55 K <lb/>T=59 K <lb/>T=67 K <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>-150-100 -50 0 50 100 150 <lb/>dI/dV(mS) <lb/>dI/dV(mS) <lb/>T=41 K <lb/>T=44 K <lb/>T=48 K <lb/>T=51 K <lb/>T=61 K <lb/>T=4.2 K <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>(b) <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>-300-200-100 0 100 200 <lb/>dI/dV (mS) <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>(c) <lb/>T=10 K <lb/>T=31 K <lb/>T=50 K <lb/>T=63 K <lb/>T=74 K <lb/>T=78 K <lb/>T=81 K <lb/>T=72 K <lb/>Fig. 1 -The temperature evolution of the tunneling conductance for overdoped Bi-2212 with bulk <lb/>Tc = 56 K, (a) junction # 1 and (b) junction # 2; (c) underdoped Bi-2212 with bulk Tc = 77 K [11]. <lb/>The tunneling conductances (except for 4.2 K) are shifted upward for clarity. Note that the scale at <lb/>higher temperatures is different for (b). <lb/>as in fig. 1(a), we do not observe the Josephson current. This discrepancy may be due to a <lb/>slightly different junction orientation or possibly due to the smaller energy gap which is esti-<lb/>mated from the 4.2 K data to be 10.5 meV. To the best of our knowledge fig. 1(b) shows the <lb/>smallest gap ever found in the Bi-2212 system. The energy gap magnitude found from tunnel-<lb/>ing is consistent with that observed in recent ARPES measurements around (π,0) on similar <lb/>crystals [16]. Using the bulk T c , the coupling ratio 2∆/kT c is 4.35, which is very close to the <lb/>BCS mean field d x 2 −y 2 -wave (d-wave) prediction of 4.28. The decrease in gap size and T c with <lb/>increasing hole doping in the overdoped phase is consistent with recent experiments [11,14,17] <lb/>and the phase diagram of HTSs. <lb/>As the temperature increases towards T c , the tunneling conductances of fig. 1(a) and <lb/>fig. 1(b) show several notable changes. Most importantly, all traces of a superconducting gap, <lb/>or any other type of gap, have disappeared for temperatures above the bulk T c . Additionally, <lb/>the magnitude of the Josephson current peak in fig. 1(a) diminishes until it vanishes around T c . <lb/>This is further evidence that the junction T c is the same as the bulk value. Both figures show <lb/>no presence of any depression above T c such as is observed in underdoped Bi-2212 [7,11]. Note <lb/>the increased sensitivity of the vertical scale in fig. 1(b) for the higher-temperature data. For <lb/>comparison, we show some previously published data on underdoped Bi-2212 [11] in fig. 1(c). <lb/>The superconducting gap is washed out around the bulk T c = 77 K of the crystal but a weak <lb/>depression in the conductance remains which is consistent with a pseudogap. The absence <lb/>of any pseudogap in our present measurements is consistent with recent ARPES studies [16] <lb/>on the same type of samples. In that study, the midpoint of the spectral weight peak shifted <lb/>to the Fermi level at T c , showing no evidence of the pseudogap that is seen in optimally <lb/>doped or underdoped Bi-2212 [1]. Thus, there are now two measurements which show that <lb/>the pseudogap disappears in heavily overdoped Bi-2212. <lb/>Considering other studies, STM measurements of overdoped Bi-2212 with T c ∼ 74 K have <lb/></body>

			<page>592 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">EUROPHYSICS LETTERS <lb/></note>

			<body>0.85 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>Normalized Conductance <lb/>T=48 K <lb/>D =9 meV <lb/>G=13 meV <lb/>(b) <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.96 <lb/>0.97 <lb/>0.98 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>-100 <lb/>-50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>D =6 meV <lb/>G=18 meV <lb/>D =5 meV <lb/>G=20 meV <lb/>D =4 meV <lb/>G=18 meV <lb/>D =3 meV <lb/>G=20 meV <lb/>T=55 K <lb/>Normalized Conductance <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>(c) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>-150 -100 -50 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 100 150 <lb/>Normalized Conductance <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>D=14 meV <lb/>G=0.2 meV <lb/>a=0.4 <lb/>d-wave SIS at 4.2 K <lb/>(a) <lb/>Fig. 2 -(a) Normalized conductance of SIS junction (dots), which is given in fig. 1(a). The data <lb/>corresponds to 4.2 K and normalized by a constant. The solid line is a SIS-generated d-wave fit <lb/>which includes the smearing factor Γ and a directionality function f (θ). (b) and (c) Normalized <lb/>conductance of SIS junctions (dots) for 48 K and 55 K, which is given in fig. 1(a). The solid line in <lb/>(b) is SIS-generated pure d-wave fit which only includes the smearing factor Γ. The solid lines in (c) <lb/>show different attemps to fit the data. <lb/>reported the observation of a pseudogap above T c [7]. Since STM is a local probe, there is a <lb/>possibility that it does not reflect the bulk T c of the sample and therefore it is important to <lb/>consider the energy gap magnitude. Both refs. [7] and [8] present energy gaps in the range <lb/>35-40 meV in addition to the pseudogap behavior. This gap magnitude is consistent with <lb/>optimally doped or slightly overdoped samples and thus the doping level at the junction is not <lb/>well established. In a more recent study, SIS break junctions of underdoped and overdoped <lb/>Bi-2212 with T c = 82 K were fabricated using an STM by M. Oda et al. [18]. Both sets of <lb/>data exhibited a pseudogap above T c ; however, the overdoped tunneling conductance showed a <lb/>smaller gap which fills in at a much lower temperature than underdoped and thus T * is closer <lb/>to T c . Taken together the tunneling studies have established that the pseudogap persists with <lb/>overdoping down to T c = 82 K, but is absent when T c = 56 K. <lb/>A natural question might be whether there is any change in the pairing symmetry as-<lb/>sociated with the loss of a pseudogap. One may assume that increasing hole doping makes <lb/>the Bi-2212 normal-state more Fermi-liquid-like, leading possibly to an s-wave BCS super-<lb/>conductor. There are ARPES observations that suggest s-wave BCS behavior in the heavily <lb/>overdoped phase [19]. However, the tunneling subgap conductance shapes at low tempera-<lb/>tures in figs. 1(a) and (b) are not consistent with the s-wave BCS theory prediction which <lb/>is supposed to be flat near zero bias. Here what we observed is that the d-wave-like sub-<lb/>gap structure persists at the T c = 56 K overdoped Bi-2212. Figure 2 shows the normalized <lb/>tunneling conductance of SIS break junction # 1 at 4.2 K (dots) which is given in fig. 1(a). <lb/>Since the tunneling conductance is flat above T c , the data have been normalized by a con-<lb/>stant. The fit is generated using a d-wave gap function, ∆ = ∆ cos(2θ), in the BCS DOS, <lb/>N s (E, θ) = (E − iΓ)/ (E − iΓ) 2 − ∆(θ) 2 . Here, Γ is a smearing parameter to account for <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">L. Ozyuzer et al.: Absence of pseudogap in heavily overdoped Bi-2212 <lb/></note>

			<page>593 <lb/></page>

			<body>quasiparticle lifetime. The SIS conductance is calculated by <lb/>dI <lb/>dV <lb/>= c <lb/>d <lb/>dV <lb/>f (θ)N s (E, θ)N s (E + eV, θ)[F (E) − F (E + eV )]dEdθ , <lb/>where c is a proportionality constant. F (E) is the Fermi function. The formula also includes a <lb/>directionality function f (θ)=1+α cos(4θ) which corresponds to a preferred tunneling along the <lb/>d-wave lobes. Here α is the directionality strength, which is assumed temperature independent <lb/>(α = 0.4) [15]. The fit (solid line in fig. 2(a)) shows good agreement in the subgap region <lb/>with the experimental data. Thus there appears to be no change of symmetry away from <lb/>d-wave. However for |eV | &gt; 2∆ the data deviate from the BCS d-wave fit, exhibiting broader <lb/>peak widths and the dip feature. In general, these features are compensating which allows <lb/>conservation of states; however, the data in fig. 2(a) lead to an integrated area out to 150 meV <lb/>which is about 6% above the BCS d-wave fit. We attribute the discrepancy to the inability to <lb/>accurately know the background conductance at 4.2 K. The broad peaks and dip feature are <lb/>observed throughout the doping range and have been attributed to strong-coupling effects [20]. <lb/>The weak temperature dependence of quasiparticle peak position has been observed in <lb/>the bare STM tunneling conductance on underdoped, optimally doped and overdoped Bi-<lb/>[7]. Analysis of the underdoped data has been carried out by Franz and Millis [21] using <lb/>the classical phase fluctuation model. What they find in their model fit to the tunneling <lb/>conductance of underdoped Bi-2212 data is that the gap is decreasing until 3/4 of T c , and <lb/>sharply increases near T c . This unusual effect seems to be tied to the presence of a pseudogap. <lb/>In the present study, we show that the gap magnitude for heavily overdoped Bi-2212 shows <lb/>no anomalies near T c but continues to decrease and appears to close near the bulk T c value. <lb/>Figures 2(b) and (c) shows the d-wave fit for T c = 48 K and 55 K. The tunneling conductance <lb/>in the fig. 2(b) displays peak values near 30 meV, however, the best fit for fig. 2(b) corresponds <lb/>to ∆ = 9 meV and Γ = 13 meV, so the energy gap is smaller than obtained value at 4.2 K. For <lb/>K, we plot fits using different ∆ and Γ values in fig. 2(c) to prove that the gap is very small <lb/>around T c . The data are in good agreement with a fit using ∆ = 4 meV and Γ = 18 meV. <lb/>These results show the energy gap magnitude reduces with increasing temperature as indicated <lb/>in fig. 3 and appears to close at the bulk T c . <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>16 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>2 0 <lb/>3 0 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>5 0 <lb/>6 0 <lb/>∆(Τ), Γ(Τ) (meV) <lb/>Normalized Josephson Strength <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>Γ(T) <lb/>∆(T) <lb/>Fig. 3 -Graph obtained from analyzing fig. 1(a) temperature dependence of superconducting gap <lb/>∆(T ) (squares), quasiparticle scattering rate Γ(T ) (circles), and Josephson strength, IcRn (diamonds) <lb/>normalized by IcRn (4.2 K). Here, the Josephson current Ic is estimated from the peak in conductance <lb/>at zero bias. The full curve represents the BCS superconducting gap ∆(T ). <lb/></body>

			<page>594 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">EUROPHYSICS LETTERS <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 4 -The temperature and 2∆ vs. hole concentration for Bi-2212. The dashed area is the measured <lb/>T * by different experimental techniques (see ref. [18]). The circles are our data that were published <lb/>before [11]. The diamond is the present work. <lb/>Figure 3 presents the various parameters derived from fig. 1(a). The solid line corresponds <lb/>to the temperature dependence of s-wave BCS superconductor energy gap which is similar to <lb/>the d-wave BCS [22] behavior. Filled squares are energy gap magnitude, filled circles are Γ. <lb/>The T -dependence of the gap magnitude follows the BCS prediction, although the increased <lb/>smearing due to the scattering rate Γ prevents exact determination of the gap magnitude <lb/>around T c . <lb/>As discussed before, one of the advantages of SIS tunnel junctions is the possible Josephson <lb/>current which can be used to determine T c of the superconductor. Even if there is a pairing <lb/>above T c , such as preformed pairs [5], any Josephson current that might persist above T c , <lb/>would be extremely weak. Therefore, we use the tunneling conductance peak (a more sensi-<lb/>tive measurement) to obtain the Josephson strength I c R n . In fig. 3, diamonds correspond to <lb/>normalized Josephson strength which vanishes around bulk T c of the crystal, the same tem-<lb/>perature where the quasiparticle gap vanished. These two measurements point to the absence <lb/>of superconducting pairing and Cooper pairs above the bulk T c of heavily overdoped Bi-2212. <lb/>We now combine in fig. 4 these results along with our previously published data and <lb/>the phase diagram for Bi-2212 as suggested in ref. [18]. Figure 4 shows that our energy <lb/>gap values lie within the experimentally determined region of T * over a wide doping range. <lb/>Here T * is obtained from various experimental techniques including SIS break junctions using <lb/>STM [18]. Extrapolating T * to the overdoped phase suggests that T c and T * are very close <lb/>and might even merge in the overdoped region. This might be the reason that we do not <lb/>observe a pseudogap in our tunneling studies. The implication of the doping dependence of <lb/>superconducting energy gap and T * is that they are intimately related. The simplest notion <lb/>is that T * represents the mean-field temperature for pairing, whereas T c defines when long-<lb/>range phase coherence is established. However, if the two temperatures were distinct over the <lb/>entire doping range, then that would suggest that T * corresponds to physics distinct from <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">L. Ozyuzer et al.: Absence of pseudogap in heavily overdoped Bi-2212 <lb/></note>

			<page>595 <lb/></page>

        	<body>superconductivity. Our present result suggests that there is a particular doping value where <lb/>the two temperature scales merge and this provides further support for pseudogap models <lb/>based on superconducting fluctuations [4, 7]. <lb/>In summary, we have performed break junction tunneling spectroscopy on heavily over-<lb/>doped Bi-2212. The tunneling conductance displays a flat background above T c without any <lb/>indication of pseudogap near the Fermi level. In addition, the energy gap magnitude reaches <lb/>a value as low as 2∆/kT c = 4.35, very close to the BCS value for d-wave superconductors. <lb/>The quasiparticle gap appears to close at the same temperature that the Josephson current <lb/>disappears. Taken together, the results suggest a merging of the temperature scales for pairing <lb/>and phase coherence. This occurs at a region of hole concentration where the strong-coupling <lb/>ratio approaches the BCS limit. This gives further support for the ideas that the pseudogap <lb/>associated with T * is due to some type of precursor superconductivity.<lb/></body>  

        	*  *  * <lb/>

        	<div type="acknowledgement">This work was partially supported by US Department of Energy, Division of Basic Energy <lb/>Sciences-Material Sciences under Contract No. W-31-109-ENG-38. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] Ding H. et al., Nature (London), 382 (1996) 51; Loeser A. G. et al., Science, 273 (1996) 325. <lb/>[2] Loram J. et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 71 (1993) 1740; Warren W. W. et al., Phys. Rev. Lett., 62 <lb/>(1989) 1193. <lb/>[3] Chen Q., Kosztin I., Janko B. and Levin K., Phys. Rev. Lett., 81 (1998) 4708. <lb/>[4] Lee P. A and Wen X.-G., Phys. Rev. Lett., 78 (1997) 4111. <lb/>[5] Emery V. and Kivelson S. A., Nature (London), 374 (1995) 434. <lb/>[6] Timusk T. and Statt B., Rep. Prog. Phys., 62 (1999) 61. <lb/>[7] Renner Ch., Revaz B., Genoud J.-Y., Kadowaki K. and Fisher O., Phys. Rev. Lett., 80 <lb/>(1998) 149. <lb/>[8] Matsuda A., Sugita S. and Watanabe T., Phys. Rev. B, 60 (1999) 1377. <lb/>[9] Tao H. J., Lu F. and Wolf E. L., Physica C, 282-287 (1997) 1507. <lb/>[10] Gupta, A. K. and Ng K.-W., Phys. Rev. B, 58 (1998) R8901. <lb/>[11] Miyakawa N., Zasadzinski J. F., Ozyuzer L., Guptasarma P., Hinks D. G., Kendziora <lb/>C. and Gray K. E., Phys. Rev. Lett., 83 (1999) 1018. <lb/>[12] Kendziora C., Kelley R. J., Skelton E. and Onellion M., Physica C, 257 (1996) 74. <lb/>[13] Ozyuzer L., Zasadzinski J. F. and Gray K. E., Cryogenics, 38 (1998) 911. <lb/>[14] DeWilde Y., Miyakawa N., Guptasarma P., Iavarone M., Ozyuzer L., Zasadzinski J. <lb/>F., Romano P., Hinks D. G., Kendziora C., Crabtree G. W. and Gray K. E., Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett., 80 (1998) 153. <lb/>[15] Ozyuzer L., Zasadzinski J. F., Kendziora C. and Gray K. E., Phys. Rev. B, 61 (2000) <lb/>3629. <lb/>[16] Yusof Z., Wells B. O., Valla T., Fedorov A. V., Johnson P. D., Li Q., Kendziora C., <lb/>Jian S. and Hinks D. G., cond-mat/0104367. <lb/>[17] Renner C., Revaz B., Genoud J.-Y. and Fisher O., J. Low Temp. Phys., 105 (1996) 1083. <lb/>[18] Oda M., Dipasupil R. M., Momono N. and Ido M., submitted to Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>[19] Kelley R. J., Quitmann C., Onellion M., Berger H., Almeras P., and Margaritondo <lb/>G., Science, 271 (1996) 1255. <lb/>[20] Zasadzinski J. F., Ozyuzer L., Miyakawa N., Gray K. E., Hinks D. G. and Kendziora <lb/>C., Phys. Rev. Lett., 87 (2001) 067005. <lb/>[21] Franz M. and Millis A. J., Phys. Rev. B, 58 (1998) 14572. <lb/>[22] Won H. and Maki K., Phys. Rev. B, 49 (1994) 1397. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
