<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
        
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9504062v1 14 Apr 1995 <lb/>Linear Temperature Variation of the Penetration Depth in <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ Thin Films <lb/>L.A. de Vaulchier, J.P. Vieren, Y. Guldner, N. Bontemps <lb/>Laboratoire de Physique de la Matière Condensée, Ecole Normale Supérieure, 24 rue Lhomond, <lb/>Paris Cedex 05, France <lb/>R. Combescot <lb/>Laboratoire de Physique Statistique, Ecole Normale Supérieure, 24 rue Lhomond, 75231 Paris <lb/>Cedex 05, France <lb/>Y. Lemaître and J.C. Mage <lb/>Laboratoire Central de Recherches, Thomson-CSF,Domaine de Corbeville, 91404 Orsay Cedex, <lb/>France <lb/>(Received May 10, 2019) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We have measured the penetration depth λ(T ) on YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 thin films <lb/>from transmission at 120, 330 and 510 GHz, between 5 and 50 K. Our data <lb/>yield simultaneously the absolute value and the temperature dependence of <lb/>λ(T ). In high quality films λ(T ) exhibits the same linear temperature depen-<lb/>dence as single crystals, showing its intrinsic nature, and λ(0) = 1750Å. In a <lb/>lower quality one, the more usual T 2 dependence is found, and λ(0) = 3600Å. <lb/>This suggests that the T 2 variation is of extrinsic origin. Our results put the <lb/>d-wave like interpretation in a much better position. <lb/>1 <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25.Gz, 74.25.Nf, 74.72.Bk, 74.76.Bz</front> <lb/>Typeset using REVT E X <lb/>

			<body>The puzzling properties of high-T c superconductors have stimulated recently extensive <lb/>experimental and theoretical work in order to determine the actual symmetry of the order <lb/>parameter. While in the BCS weak coupling theory, the penetration depth λ(T ) varies as <lb/>exp(−∆/k B T ), a quadratic behavior λ(T ) ∼ T 2 was reported by many groups in YBCO <lb/>thin films [1-3]. Recently, in very high quality YBCO single crystals, a linear temperature <lb/>dependence was measured up to 40 K [4-6]. Such a variation, never observed so far in <lb/>YBCO thin films [7], is consistent with the occurrence of nodes in the gap and may suggest <lb/>a d-wave pairing mechanism [8]. However other possible interpretations have been raised, <lb/>both theoretically and experimentally, e.g. a possible proximity effect with a normal metal <lb/>layer [6,9], or the sensitivity of a conventional BCS type λ(T ) to the oxygenation of the <lb/>samples [10,11]. Several reasons for the discrepancy observed between thin films and single <lb/>crystals may be invoked: (i) within the framework of d-wave pairing, scattering due to im-<lb/>purities or defects may change the linear temperature dependence into a quadratic one in <lb/>thin films [12], where such defects would be more numerous. However T c should then also <lb/>be affected, which is not the case [4,13]. (ii) weak links, more likely to be present in thin <lb/>films, may yield an effective penetration depth (larger than the intrinsic one) with a different <lb/>temperature dependence [14,15]. The penetration depth λ has been essentially measured <lb/>in both single crystals and thin films by using surface impedance techniques at a single <lb/>frequency [2,4]. Such measurements actually measure the variation ∆λ(T ) = λ(T ) − λ(0), <lb/>but without the knowledge of λ(0) on each sample, comparing the temperature dependence <lb/>of various samples may not be significant. This paper reports for the first time, from high <lb/>frequency transmission data, both an unambiguous linear temperature dependence of λ(T ) <lb/>on high quality YBCO thin films, which is quantitatively the same as in single crystals [4], <lb/>and simultaneously λ(0) ∼ 1750Å. We observe a quadratic temperature dependence on a <lb/>lower quality sample, and λ(0) ∼ 3600Å. We suggest that this T 2 dependence in thin films <lb/>is not a consequence of strong scattering (in contrast with Zn or Ni doped materials [16]) <lb/>but is of extrinsic origin. The intrinsic dependence of λ(T ) at low temperature is linear. <lb/>This linear dependence points plainly toward the existence of low energy excitations, but our <lb/></body>

            <page>3 <lb/></page>

            <body>results alone do not allow to identify them. A natural and popular explanation is that they <lb/>are due to nodes in the gap arising from unconventional pairing of d-wave type [1,4,5], an <lb/>interpretation also conveyed by SQUID experiments [17,18]. Our results provide support to <lb/>d-wave pairing, because they show a linear behavior in films, but also because they eliminate <lb/>the uncomfortable need to explain the T 2 dependence by impurity scattering at the unitary <lb/>limit [12]. <lb/>The experimental transmission set-up uses carcinotron tubes as powerful, stable mi-<lb/>crowave sources and oversized waveguides in order to change easily the frequency (120 to <lb/>GHz) [19,20]. We took an extreme care to lower microwave leakages down to 60 dB. The <lb/>transmitted signal is detected by a helium cooled InSb bolometer. Measurements have been <lb/>performed by slowly varying the temperature between 5 and 110 K at fixed frequencies. The <lb/>transmission of the substrate was checked to vary by less than 1 % between 5 and 110 K. <lb/>We have screened the samples from stray magnetic field, so that the residual field is less <lb/>than 0.5 Gauss. For a film of thickness d (smaller than the skin depth in the normal state <lb/>or the penetration depth in the superconducting state) deposited onto a substrate of index <lb/>n, the transmission writes [21]: <lb/>T = <lb/>1 <lb/>1 + σdZ 0 <lb/>1+n <lb/>2 <lb/>(1) <lb/>
            where σ = σ 1 − iσ 2 is the complex conductivity of the film, Z 0 the impedance of free space <lb/>and Z = 1/σd the impedance of the film. If in the energy and temperature range of interest <lb/>σ 2 (T ) ≫ σ 1 (T ) and σ 2 dZ 0 <lb/>1+n ≫ 1, we can write: <lb/>T <lb/>T 110 <lb/>= µ 2 <lb/>0 ω 2 λ 4 (T ) σ 2 <lb/>110 <lb/>(2) <lb/>where σ 110 is the normal 110 K conductivity of the film. We choose to normalize the trans-<lb/>mission at 110 K because the ratio thus obtained is experimentally more reliable than the <lb/>absolute value of the transmission. For simplicity we assumed σ 110 dZ 0 <lb/>1+n <lb/>≫ 1 in (2). Thus, <lb/>the measurement of T/T 110 yields an absolute value of λ(T ). The uncertainties on the λ(T ) <lb/></body>

            <page>4 <lb/></page>

            <body>value which arise when neglecting the interferences within the film and/or the substrate, and <lb/>the effect of the finite film thickness with respect to λ(T ) have been estimated: the trans-<lb/>mission is fairly insensitive to the interference effects at our frequencies as can be shown <lb/>by comparing a complete expression for T to (1). Moreover, no significant change of the <lb/>transmitted energy could be observed in the most sensitive range 440-550 GHz [20]. The <lb/>finite film thickness, yields an approximate 80Å overestimate of λ(T ) for d/λ(T ) ∼ 0.5. <lb/>σ 2 (ω, T ) ≫ σ 1 (ω, T ) holds at low temperature (T ≤ 20 K) for all frequencies, but should <lb/>break down at 40 K [5,22,23]. Indeed, σ 1 (35 GHz, 40 K) ∼ 2 × 10 7 Ω −1 m −1 , a value likely <lb/>larger than σ 2 (300 GHz). However we expect a strong decrease of σ 1 (T ) at 300 GHz [22-24]. <lb/>It is essential that we define the criteria we use in order to sort out the films that we <lb/>investigate. Our films are epitaxially grown either by laser ablation on MgO [25] or by <lb/>sputtering on LaAlO 3 [26]. They have a narrow transition (∆T c ≤ 1 K). T c is 86-92 K, <lb/>depending on the substrate. In previous papers, the correlation between the film quality in <lb/>terms of transmission, width of the rocking curve and surface resistance has been established <lb/>[19,20,27]. This led us to select the films either from their surface resistance: R S ≤ 0.5 mΩ <lb/>at 77 K and 10 GHz, or the width of their rocking curve ∆θ ≤ 0.5 • . The characteristics of <lb/>our samples are listed in Table I. Two types of films have been intentionally investigated. <lb/>The first film (A1) is of poor quality with respect to the above criteria. The two others <lb/>(B1 and B2) display either a low surface resistance or a narrow rocking curve. We show in <lb/>Fig. 1 and Fig. 2 the normalized transmission of the A1 and B2 films respectively. Strong <lb/>differences are observed, in particular for the residual transmission in the superconducting <lb/>state. At T ≤ 0.5 T c , the transmission increases as ω 2 in sample B2, as expected from (2) <lb/>and as shown in the inset of Fig. 2. In sample A1, the data can be analyzed by adding a <lb/>constant T to the ω 2 term [28]. We estimate T 0 from the 10 K data (see inset of Fig. 1). We <lb/>compute λ(T ) from (2) for the three frequencies, assuming that T 0 in the case of A1, does <lb/>not depend on temperature or frequency. The result of this analysis is shown on Fig. 3 and <lb/>Fig. 4, for the samples A1 and B2. The 120, 330 and 510 GHz curves collapse, up to 40 K <lb/>

            for sample A1 and up to 55 K for sample B2. This confirms that the frequency dependent <lb/>part of the transmission varies as ω 2 , and that σ 2 (ω, T ) ≫ σ (ω, T ) in these temperature <lb/>ranges. λ(0) is found to be 1750 ± 160Å for B2 and 3600 ± 200Å for A1. The uncertainty <lb/>on λ(0) depends mostly on the accuracy on the σ 110 measurement, which is limited by the <lb/>uncertainty on the film thickness (±100Å) and by the Van der Pauw technique. Finally <lb/>the most striking result is the temperature dependence of λ(T ). For sample A1, we find <lb/>as shown in the inset, a clear T 2 dependence, a fairly common result for thin films [1-3], <lb/>associated with a very large value for λ(0). In contrast, for sample B2, we find a linear <lb/>temperature dependence up to 50 K along with a much shorter λ(0). Such a linear behavior <lb/>was similarly observed in film B1. <lb/>We now discuss the implications of these results. We believe that they demonstrate <lb/>clearly the extrinsic origin of the T 2 dependence found previously in thin films. Indeed they <lb/>agree with a phenomenological expression λ 2 (T ) = λ 2 <lb/>intr (T )+λ 2 <lb/>extr (T ) as proposed by Hylton <lb/>et al., with λ extr being for example the contribution of weak links (but our conclusions are <lb/>obviously independent of this specific expression). When λ extr is the dominating contribu-<lb/>tion as in our film A1 it may produce the T 2 dependence which is likely to change from <lb/>sample to sample. Indeed, the data of Porch et al. (see inset of Fig. 3) are not the same as <lb/>ours. On the other hand, for good enough films, λ extr gets negligible and we find the intrinsic <lb/>behavior for λ(T ) which is linear, and is expected to be unchanged from films to crystals. <lb/>The YBCO single crystals results of Hardy et al. are reported on Fig. 4, shifted to our λ(0) <lb/>value. The excellent agreement between the two sets of data confirms the intrinsic nature <lb/>of λ in film B2. We remark that the agreement between λ(T ) in two completely unrelated <lb/>samples is a very strong result since, except for a coincidence, it eliminates any extrinsic <lb/>explanation like poor surface effects or pair breaking due to magnetic impurities [10], for the <lb/>interpretations of the linear dependence. However the nature of the low energy excitations <lb/>is still unknown [29,30] and it is also not yet clear whether they are linked to the planes or to <lb/>the chains. Furthermore, the T 2 dependence appears in a film where the penetration depth <lb/></body>

            <page>6 <lb/></page>

            <body>is large. Our λ intr (0) is much shorter. It is larger though than λ ab (0) = 1450-1490Å derive <lb/>by µSR [31], and consistent with λ a (0) = 1600Å provided by infrared reflectance data [32]. <lb/>We believe that most techniques do not provide as a straightforward determination as ours. <lb/>Our results offer a solution to a previous uncomfortable situation arising in the d-wave <lb/>interpretation of the experimental results for λ(T ). Indeed in order to explain the T 2 behav-<lb/>ior in films together with the linear dependence in single crystals, theoretical calculations <lb/>had to call for a high impurity concentration in films. But this implies a significant differ-<lb/>ence between T c for films and crystals which is not observed. The proposed escape [33] was <lb/>to assume that the impurity concentration was rather low with a scattering very near the <lb/>unitary limit, a very specific hypothesis. In this case T c could be little changed by impurities <lb/>while the low T behavior of λ(T ) would be much more affected. Since our results show that <lb/>the T 2 behavior is extrinsic, e.g. due to weak links [20], all the results become coherent with <lb/>a reasonably low content of ordinary scatterers. <lb/>In order to interpret quantitatively our results, it is convenient to make use of the sim-<lb/>plified two-dimensional model of d-wave like pairing introduced by Xu et al. [12], where the <lb/>gap has a linear dependence near the nodes and is constant elsewhere: |∆(θ)| = µ∆ 0 θ for <lb/>0 ≤ θ ≤ 1/µ and |∆(θ)| = ∆ 0 for 1/µ ≤ θ ≤ π/4, θ being the angle with respect to the <lb/>node position on the Fermi surface and the rest of ∆(θ) being obtained by symmetry. The <lb/>density of states is taken as constant. This model contains the essential physical ingredients <lb/>to represent a general order parameter with d-wave symmetry, except for the possible effect <lb/>of Van Hove singularities. The slope of λ(T ) at T = 0 is given by 2 ln 2/µ∆ 0 , however when <lb/>∆ 0 is calculated with a weak coupling assumption, the result can only be made to agree with <lb/>experiment up to 20 K and it does not reproduce the remarkable linear behavior up to 55 K. <lb/>A simple way to account for this feature is to incorporate strong coupling effects. This is <lb/>justified on theoretical ground [8] and is also consistent with experiments since for example <lb/></body>

            <page>7 <lb/></page>

            <body>tunneling data give an effective gap larger than what is expected from BCS theory. If we <lb/>take 2∆ 0 /T c = 7 (a typical tunneling value), we obtain the solid curve on Fig. 4 which agrees <lb/>quite well with our experimental results. This gives further support to this interpretation. <lb/>In summary, although our results cannot be taken as a proof for d-wave pairing, they put <lb/>at least this interpretation in a much better position. <lb/>We are deeply indebted to M. Guilloux-Viry, C. Le Paven-Thivet and A. Perrin from <lb/>the Laboratoire de Chimie Inorganique et Moléculaire, Université de Rennes, for providing <lb/>us with well characterized thin films. We thank P. Monod for his critical reading of the <lb/>manuscript. This work has been supported by EEC Contract 93-2027.IL and by the New <lb/>Energy and Industrial Technology Development Organization (NEDO). Both laboratories <lb/>Physique de la Matière Condensée and Physique Statistique are associated to CNRS and <lb/>Universities Paris VI and Paris VII. <lb/></body>

            <page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] J. Annett, N. Goldenfeld and S.R. Renn, Phys. Rev. B 43, 2778 (1991). <lb/>[2] A. Porch et al., to appear in the Proceedings of the Applied Superconductivity Confer-<lb/>ence (1994), to be published in the IEEE Trans. on Applied Supercond. (1995). <lb/>[3] Z. Ma et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 781, (1993). <lb/>[4] W.N. Hardy et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, 3999 (1993). <lb/>[5] Kuan Zhang et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 73, 2484 (1994). <lb/>[6] J. Mao et al., submitted to Phys. Rev. B , (1994). <lb/>[7] M.R. Beasley, same issue as [2], reports a linear temperature dependence on one TlBa-<lb/>CaCuO thin film. <lb/>[8] P. Monthoux, A.V. Balatsky and D. Pines, Phys. Rev. Lett. 67, 3448 (1991). <lb/>[9] M.S. Pambianchi, J. Mao and S.M. Anlage, Phys. Rev. B 50, 13659 (1994). <lb/>[10] V.S. Kresin, to be published in J. Supercond. Proceedings of the Workshop on High-T c <lb/>Superconductors: Physical Properties and Mechanisms (5-11 Jan. 1995, Miami, USA). <lb/>[11] Y.Y. Xue et al., same issue as [10]. <lb/>[12] D. Xu, K. Yip and J.A. Sauls, to be published in Phys. Rev. B , (1994). <lb/>[13] M. Prohammer and J.P. Carbotte, Phys. Rev. B 43, 5370 (1991). <lb/>[14] T.L. Hylton et al., Appl. Phys. Lett. 53, 1343 (1988). <lb/>[15] J. Halbritter, J. Appl. Phys. 71, 339 (1992). <lb/>[16] D.A. Bonn et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 4051 (1994). <lb/>[17] D.A. Wollman et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. bf 71, 2134 (1993). <lb/>[18] C.C. Tsuei et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. bf 73, 593 (1994). <lb/>9 <lb/>[19] L.A. de Vaulchier et al., Physica C 235-240, 1083 (1994). <lb/>[20] L.A. de Vaulchier et al., to be published in Phys. Rev. B , (1995). <lb/>[21] R.E. Glover and M. Tinkham, Phys. Rev. 108, 243 (1957). <lb/>[22] D.A. Bonn et al., Phys. Rev. B 47, (1993). <lb/>[23] R. Buhleier et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 9672 (1994). <lb/>[24] U. Dähne et al., Physica C 235-240, 2066 (1994). <lb/>[25] M. Guilloux-Viry et al., Mat. Sc. Eng. B 18, 115 (1993). <lb/>[26] Y. Lemaitre et al., Physica C 235-240, 643 (1994). <lb/>[27] C. Thivet et al., submitted to Physica C, (1994). <lb/>[28] One possible origin for the extra transmission T could be holes in the film: indeed <lb/>observations with the optical microscope show in film A1 few holes of 100 µm typical <lb/>size which may give rise to excess transmission. <lb/>[29] A.M. Neminsky and P.N. Nikolaev, Physica C 212, 389 (1993). <lb/>[30] G.M. Eliashberg, G.V. Klimovitch and Rylyakov, J. Supercond. 4, 393 (1991). <lb/>[31] J.E. Sonier et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 72, 744 (1994). <lb/>[32] D.N. Basov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 74, 598 (1995). <lb/>[33] P.J. Hirschfeld and N. Goldenfeld, Phys. Rev. B 48, 4219 (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURES <lb/>FIG. 1. 110 K normalized transmission versus temperature for the YBCO A1 film. The inset <lb/>shows the ω 2 law of the normalized transmission at 10 K. <lb/>FIG. 2. 110 K normalized transmission versus temperature for the YBCO B2 film. The inset <lb/>shows the ω 2 law of the normalized transmission at 10 K. <lb/>FIG. 3. Temperature dependence of λ(T ) for the YBCO A1 film. The T 2 law (see inset) is <lb/>characteristic of a poor quality film. The bold squares represent the 8 GHz Porch et al. [2] data <lb/>points shifted to our λ(0) value. <lb/>FIG. 4. Temperature dependence of λ(T ) for the YBCO B2 film. The bold squares represent <lb/>the Hardy et al. [4] data points on a single crystal (shifted to our λ(0) value). The solid line is a <lb/>comparison with a d-wave like, strong coupling calculation, with 2∆ 0 = 7 k B T c (see text). <lb/>11 <lb/>TABLES <lb/>TABLE I. Characteristics of the YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 thin films. d is their thickness and ∆θ the rocking <lb/>curve width. R S (77 K, 10 GHz) has been corrected for the film thickness. <lb/>Sample <lb/>d [Å] <lb/>T c [K] <lb/>∆θ [ • ] <lb/>R S [mΩ] <lb/>σ 110 [µΩcm] <lb/>A1 <lb/>1200 <lb/>86 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>∼ 10 <lb/>130 <lb/>B1 <lb/>1400 <lb/>88 <lb/>0.42 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>B2 <lb/>1000 <lb/>92 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>80 <lb/> 0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 GHz <lb/>GHz <lb/>GHz <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>T <lb/>6 [ K ] <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>M [ 10 &quot; rad s` ] <lb/>6 =10 K <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>T <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>GHz <lb/>330 GHz <lb/>510 GHz <lb/>6 [ K ] <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>T <lb/>0 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>6 =10 K <lb/>T <lb/>/ <lb/>T <lb/>M [ 10 &quot; rad s` ] <lb/>3500 <lb/>4000 <lb/>4500 <lb/>5000 <lb/>5500 <lb/>6000 <lb/>25 <lb/>45 <lb/>65 <lb/>85 <lb/>120 GHz <lb/>330 GHz <lb/>510 GHz <lb/>Porch et al. <lb/>l <lb/>[ <lb/>Å <lb/>] <lb/>6 [ K ] <lb/>3600 <lb/>3700 <lb/>3800 <lb/>3900 <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 1200 1600 <lb/>l <lb/>[ <lb/>Å <lb/>] <lb/>6 [ K ] <lb/>% <lb/># <lb/>&apos; <lb/>!! <lb/>!% <lb/># <lb/># <lb/>&quot;# <lb/>$# <lb/>&amp;# <lb/>120 GHz <lb/>330 GHz <lb/>510 GHz <lb/>Hardy et al. <lb/>l <lb/>[ <lb/>Å <lb/>] <lb/>6 [ K ] <lb/>1750 <lb/>1800 <lb/>1850 <lb/>1900 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>l <lb/>[ <lb/>Å <lb/>] <lb/>6 [ K ] </body>

	</text>
</tei>
