<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_fermeture"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Empirical Natural Closure Relation for Short Fiber <lb/>Suspension Models <lb/> E. Prulière 1 , A. Ammar 1* , F. Chinesta 2 <lb/> 1  Laboratoire de Rhéologie, INPG, UJF, CNRS (UMR 5520) <lb/>1301 rue de la piscine, BP 53 Domaine universitaire <lb/>38041 Grenoble Cedex 9, France <lb/>pruliere@ujf-grenoble.fr <lb/>* Amine.Ammar@ujf-grenoble.fr (corresponding author) <lb/> 2 LMSP UMR 8106 CNRS-ENSAM-ESEM <lb/>151 Boulevard de l&apos;Hôpital, F-75013 Paris, France <lb/>francisco.chinesta@paris.ensam.fr <lb/>ABSTRACT. This work focuses on the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation that governs the <lb/>evolution of the fibers orientation distribution. To reduce the computing time, that equation is solved <lb/>along some flow trajectories in order to extract the significant information of the solution from the <lb/>application of the Karhunen-Loève decomposition. Now, from this information one could solve the <lb/>Fokker-Planck equation everywhere in the flow domain or simply adjust a closure relation that becomes <lb/>optimal for such flow, solving the evolution of some orientation moments which require a less amount of <lb/>computation. This paper focuses on this last strategy. For this purpose we start introducing the <lb/>Karhunen-Loève decomposition that is applied later to automatically extract the main solution <lb/>characteristics for adjusting empirically a natural closure relation. <lb/>KEYWORDS: Short fiber suspensions; Closure relations; Numerical modeling; Model reduction; <lb/>Karhunen-Loève decomposition <lb/> Manuscript <lb/></front>

			<page> 2 <lb/></page>

			<body> 1. Introduction <lb/>1.1. Short Fiber Suspensions flow models <lb/> Numerical modeling of non-Newtonian flows usually involves the coupling between equations of motion, <lb/>which define an elliptic problem, and the fluid constitutive equation, which introduces an advection <lb/>problem related to the fluid history. In short fiber suspensions (SFS) models, the extra-stress tensor <lb/>depends on the fiber orientation whose evolution can be modeled from a transport problem. In all cases the <lb/>flow kinematics and the fiber orientation are coupled: the kinematics of the flow governs the fiber <lb/>orientation, and the presence and orientation of the fibers modify the flow kinematics. Thus, for example, in <lb/>a contraction flow of a dilute suspension, large recirculating areas appear (Lipscomb et al. (1988)). <lb/>If one uses SFS flows in material forming processes, the final fiber orientation state depends on the process <lb/>and exhibits flow-induced anisotropy. Thus, we need to compute the fiber orientation in order to predict the <lb/>final mechanical properties of the composite parts, which depend strongly on the fiber orientation. <lb/>Moreover, the numerical simulation of such flows becomes interesting if one wants to identify their <lb/>rheological parameters using some rheometric devices and an appropriate inverse technique. <lb/>The mechanical model governing the SFS flow is given by the following equations: (Batchelor (1970), <lb/>Hand (1962), Hinch and Leal (1975, 1976)) <lb/> • The momentum balance equation, when the inertia and mass terms are neglected, results <lb/> 0 <lb/> Divσ = <lb/> (1) <lb/>where  σ  is the stress tensor. <lb/> •  The mass balance equation for incompressible fluids <lb/> 0 <lb/> Divv = <lb/> (2) <lb/>where  v  represents the velocity field. <lb/>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			•  The constitutive equation for a dilute suspension of high aspect-ratio particles is given, with other <lb/>simplifying assumptions (Tucker (1991)), by <lb/> ( ) <lb/> { <lb/>} <lb/> 2 <lb/>: <lb/> p <lb/> pI <lb/>D N a D <lb/> σ <lb/> η <lb/> = − + <lb/>+ <lb/> (3) <lb/>where  p  denotes the pressure, I the unit tensor,  η  the viscosity which depends on the chosen model, <lb/> D the strain rate tensor,  p <lb/> N a scalar parameter depending on both the fiber concentration and the fiber <lb/>aspect ratio, &quot; : &quot; the tensorial product twice contracted (i.e. <lb/> kl <lb/>ijkl <lb/>ij <lb/> D <lb/>a <lb/>D <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 : <lb/>) and  a  the fourth order <lb/>orientation tensor defined by: <lb/> ( ) <lb/> a <lb/>d <lb/> ρ ρ ρ ρ ψ ρ ρ <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ ⊗ ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (4) <lb/>where  ρ  is the unit vector aligned in the fiber axis direction, &quot;  ⊗  &quot; denotes the tensorial product (i.e. <lb/> ( ) <lb/> j <lb/>i <lb/>ij <lb/> ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/> = <lb/> ρ <lb/>⊗ <lb/>ρ <lb/> ), and <lb/> ) <lb/>(  ρ <lb/>ψ <lb/> is the orientation distribution function satisfying the normality condition <lb/> ( ) <lb/>1 <lb/> d <lb/> ψ ρ ρ  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (5) <lb/>If  ( ) ( ) <lb/> ρ <lb/>− <lb/>ρ <lb/>δ <lb/> = <lb/> ρ <lb/>ψ <lb/> ˆ , with <lb/> ) <lb/>( <lb/> δ  the Dirac&apos;s distribution, all the orientation probability is concentrated in <lb/>the direction defined byρ , and the corresponding orientation tensor results <lb/> ρ <lb/>⊗ <lb/>ρ <lb/>⊗ <lb/>ρ <lb/>⊗ <lb/>ρ <lb/> = <lb/> ˆ <lb/>ˆ <lb/>ˆ <lb/>ˆ <lb/>ˆ <lb/> a <lb/> . <lb/>We can also define the second order orientation tensor as: <lb/> ( ) <lb/> a <lb/>d <lb/> ρ ρ ψ ρ ρ <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (6) <lb/>It is easy to verify that if <lb/>) <lb/>ˆ <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/> ρ <lb/>− <lb/>ρ <lb/>δ <lb/> = <lb/> ρ <lb/>ψ <lb/> , the fourth order orientation tensor can be written as <lb/> a a a <lb/> = ⊗ <lb/> (7) <lb/>whose components are defined by <lb/> kl <lb/>ij <lb/>ijkl <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>a = <lb/> . <lb/>For general expressions of <lb/>) <lb/>( ρ <lb/>ψ <lb/> the previous relation is not exact, and equation (7) becomes a closure <lb/>approximation known as the quadratic closure relation: <lb/> kl <lb/>ij <lb/>quad <lb/>ijkl <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> . However, other closure relations <lb/>are usually applied (Advani and Tucker (1990), Dupret et al. (1998)), among them we can consider the <lb/>linear closure relation: <lb/>
			
			<page>4 <lb/> </page>
			
			1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(4 <lb/>)(2 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(4 <lb/>) <lb/> lin <lb/> ijkl <lb/>ij kl <lb/>ik jl <lb/>il jk <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>ij kl <lb/>ik jl <lb/>il jk <lb/>kl ij <lb/>jl ik <lb/>jk il <lb/>d <lb/> a <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>N <lb/> δ δ δ δ δ δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/> = − <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> (8) <lb/>where  d <lb/> N  refers to the space dimension, i.e. <lb/> 2 in 2 <lb/>3 in 3 <lb/> d <lb/> D <lb/>N <lb/>D <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (9) <lb/>The hybrid closure relation <lb/> ( 1 <lb/>) <lb/> hyb <lb/>quad <lb/>lin <lb/>ijkl <lb/>ijkl <lb/>ijkl <lb/> a <lb/>f a <lb/>f a <lb/> = <lb/>+ − <lb/> (10) <lb/>where <lb/> ( )  det( ) <lb/> d <lb/> N <lb/>d <lb/> f <lb/>N <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> ; and finally, the natural closure relation (Dupret and Verleye (1999)) that <lb/>in the 2D case takes the form <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>det( )( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>6 <lb/>3 <lb/> nat <lb/>ijkl <lb/>ij kl <lb/>ik jl <lb/>il jk <lb/>ij kl <lb/>ik jl <lb/>il jk <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>aa <lb/>aa <lb/>aa <lb/> δ δ δ δ δ δ <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> (11) <lb/>The 3D isotropic orientation state is defined by the uniform distribution function <lb/> ( )  1 <lb/>4 <lb/> ρ <lb/>π <lb/> Ψ <lb/> = <lb/> (12) <lb/>and then, the second order orientation tensor related to that isotropic orientation state is <lb/> 3 <lb/> I <lb/>a = <lb/> (13) <lb/>It is easy to verify that for isotropic orientation distributions (2D or 3D) the linear closure becomes <lb/>exact. <lb/> •  If we consider spheroidal fibers immersed in a dilute suspension, we can describe the orientation <lb/>evolution by means of the Jeffery equation (Jeffery (1922)) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> : <lb/> d <lb/>k D <lb/>D <lb/>dt <lb/> ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ρ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/> = Ω + <lb/> − <lb/>⊗ <lb/> (14) <lb/>
			
			<page>5 <lb/></page>
			
			where  Ω  is the vorticity tensor, and  k  is a constant that depends on the fiber aspect ratio  r  (fiber <lb/>length to fiber diameter ratio): <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> k <lb/>r <lb/>r <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> + <lb/> (15) <lb/>On the other hand the evolution of the fiber orientation distribution  ψ  is governed by the Fokker-Planck <lb/>equation, <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>0 <lb/> d <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/>dt <lb/> ψ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ψ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> + <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂  񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (16) <lb/>where the material derivative is given by: <lb/> d <lb/>v Grad <lb/>dt <lb/>t <lb/> ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/> ∂ <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/> ∂ <lb/> (17) <lb/>Now, taking into account equations (6), (14) and (16), the equation that governs the evolution of the <lb/>second order orientation tensor can be deduced <lb/> ( ) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 2 : <lb/> d a <lb/>a a <lb/>k D a a D <lb/>a D <lb/>dt <lb/> = Ω − Ω + <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/> (18) <lb/>A similar equation can be derived for the evolution of the fourth order orientation tensor, which in this <lb/>case involves the sixth-order orientation tensor. <lb/>To take account of fiber interaction effects in semi-concentrated suspensions Folgar and Tucker (1984) <lb/>proposed the introduction of a diffusion term in the Fokker-Planck equation, i.e. <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> r <lb/> d <lb/>d <lb/>D <lb/>dt <lb/>dt <lb/> ψ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ψ ρ <lb/>ψ ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> + <lb/>= <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (19) <lb/>Fiber interaction being taken into account, the equation governing the evolution of  a  then yields: <lb/> ( ) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 2 : <lb/>4  r <lb/>d <lb/> d a <lb/>I <lb/>a a <lb/>k D a a D <lb/>a D <lb/>D a <lb/>dt <lb/>N <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = Ω − Ω + <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (20) <lb/>The Fokker-Planck formalism circumvents the necessity of using closure relations, but it induces some <lb/>difficulties related to its multidimensional character (the distribution function is defined in the physical and <lb/>the configuration spaces) and moreover advection terms are defined in both spaces. By these reasons the <lb/>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			number of works devoted to the treatment of the FP equation is relatively reduced (Lozinski and Chauvière <lb/>(2003); Chauvière and Lozinski (2004)). In these techniques, usually, to account for the multidimensional <lb/>character of the FP equation, a time-splitting is often considered to decouple the advection problem in <lb/>physical space and the advection-diffusion problem in the conformation space. The first problem can be <lb/>solved by a numerical method appropriate for hyperbolic partial differential equations (discontinuous <lb/>Galerkin, SUPG, …). Then, the advection-diffusion problem defined in the conformation space can be <lb/>treated using different implicit techniques (SUPG, wavelets-Galerkin, spectral techniques, …) preserving <lb/>stability, accounting for distribution relatively localized as well as periodic boundary conditions in the <lb/>conformation space. <lb/>In general we can solve the FP equation from its associated Ito stochastic differential equation for a large <lb/>set of realizations. The CONNFFESSIT method (Ottinger and Laso (1992)) was the first implementation of <lb/>the stochastic approach. The Brownian Configuration Fields (Hulsen et al. (1997)) can be considered as an <lb/>improvement of the CONNFFESSIT method. However, the control of the statistical noise is a major issue <lb/>in stochastic micro-macro simulations, problem that does not arise in the deterministic Fokker-Planck <lb/>approach. <lb/>This work focuses on the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation that governs the evolution of the fibers <lb/>orientation distribution. To reduce the computing time, that equation is solved along some flow trajectories <lb/>in order to extract the significant information of the solution from the application of the Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition. Now, from this information one could solve the Fokker-Planck equation everywhere in the <lb/>flow domain or simply adjust a closure relation that becomes optimal for such flow, solving the evolution <lb/>of some orientation moments which require a less amount of computation. Some antecedents exist <lb/>concerning closure relation fitting; see for example Parsheh et al. (2006) or Gillet-Chaulet et al. (2006). <lb/>The present paper focuses on the definition of an empirical natural closure approximation for each <lb/>particular flow. For this purpose we start introducing the Karhunen-Loève decomposition (Ryckelynck et <lb/>al. (2006)) that is applied later to automatically extract the main solution characteristics for adjusting <lb/>empirically a natural closure relation. <lb/>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			1.2. The Karhunen-Loève decomposition <lb/> We assume that the evolution of a certain field  ( ) <lb/> t <lb/> x <lb/>u , is known. In practical applications, this field is <lb/>expressed in a discrete form, that is, it is known at the nodes of a spatial mesh and for some times <lb/> ( )  p <lb/>i <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/> u <lb/>t <lb/>x <lb/>u <lb/> ≡ <lb/> , <lb/>. W e c a n a l s o w r i t e i n t r o d u c i n g a s p a t i a l i n t e r p o l a t i o n <lb/> ( ) ( <lb/>) <lb/> , <lb/> p <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> u x <lb/>u x t p t <lb/> ≡ <lb/> = Δ  , <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/> 1, , <lb/> p <lb/>P <lb/> ∀ ∈ 񮽙 <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/> 1, , <lb/> i <lb/>N <lb/> ∀ ∈ 񮽙 <lb/> . The main idea of the Karhunen-Loève (KL) decomposition is how to <lb/>obtain the most typical or characteristic structure  ( ) <lb/> x <lb/> φ <lb/> among these <lb/> ( )  p <lb/>x <lb/>u p <lb/> ∀ <lb/> , <lb/>. This is equivalent to <lb/>obtaining a function  ( ) <lb/> x <lb/> φ <lb/> that maximizes  α  . <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> p P i N <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>i N <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> x u x <lb/>x <lb/> φ <lb/>α <lb/>φ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (21) <lb/>The maximization leads to: <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> = <lb/>; <lb/> p P <lb/>j N <lb/>i N <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>j <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>i N <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> x u x <lb/>x u x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> φ <lb/>φ <lb/>α φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ∀ <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (22) <lb/>which can be rewritten in the form <lb/> ( ) ( ) ( ) ( ) <lb/>( ) ( ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> ; <lb/> j N p P <lb/>i N <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>j <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>p <lb/>i N <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> u x u x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> φ <lb/>φ <lb/>α φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ∀ <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (23) <lb/>Defining the vectors  a  such that its  i-component  is  ( ) <lb/> i <lb/> x <lb/>a <lb/> , Eq. (23) takes the following matrix form <lb/> ; <lb/> T <lb/>T <lb/> k <lb/>k <lb/> φ φ α φ φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ αφ <lb/> = <lb/> ∀ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> (24) <lb/>where the two points correlation matrix is given by <lb/> ( ) ( ) <lb/> ( ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/> p P <lb/>p P <lb/>T <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>ij <lb/>p <lb/>p <lb/> k <lb/>u x u x <lb/>k <lb/>u u <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> = <lb/> ⇔ = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (25) <lb/>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			which is symmetric and positive definite. If we define the matrix  Q  containing the discrete field history: <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> P <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/> u u <lb/>u <lb/>u u <lb/>u <lb/>Q <lb/>u u <lb/>u <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (26) <lb/>is easy to verify that the matrix  k  in Eq. (25) results: <lb/> T <lb/> k Q Q <lb/> = <lb/> (27) <lb/> 1.3  &quot; A posteriori &quot; reduced modeling <lb/> If some direct simulations are carried out, we can determine  ( ) <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/>[ <lb/>] <lb/> P <lb/>p <lb/>N <lb/>i <lb/>u <lb/>t <lb/>x <lb/>u <lb/> p <lb/>i <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∈ <lb/> ∀ <lb/>∈ <lb/>∀ <lb/>≡ <lb/> , <lb/>and <lb/>from <lb/>these <lb/>the <lb/> n <lb/> eigenvectors <lb/>related <lb/>to <lb/>the <lb/> n-highest <lb/> eigenvalues <lb/> ( ) <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/>[ <lb/>] <lb/> n <lb/>k <lb/>N <lb/>i <lb/>x i <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/> , <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∈ <lb/>∀ <lb/>∈ <lb/>∀ <lb/>φ <lb/> = <lb/> φ <lb/> that are expected to contain the most information about the <lb/>problem solution. For this purpose we solve the eigenvalue problem defined by Eq. (24) retaining all the <lb/>eigenavules belonging to the interval defined by the highest eigenvalue and that value divided by a large <lb/>enough value ( <lb/> 8 <lb/> 10 in our simulations). In practice  n  is much lower than  N.  Thus, we can try to use these  n <lb/> eigenfunctions for approximating the solution of a problem slightly different to the one that has served to <lb/>define  ( )  p <lb/>i <lb/>p <lb/>i <lb/> u <lb/>t <lb/>x <lb/>u <lb/> ≡ <lb/> , <lb/>. F o r t h i s p u r p o s e w e n e e d t o d e f i n e t h e m a t r i x  B <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> n <lb/>n <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>n <lb/> x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>B <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/>x <lb/> φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (28) <lb/>Now, if we consider the linear system of equations resulting from the discretization of a partial differential <lb/>equation (PDE) in the form <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( 1) <lb/> m <lb/>m <lb/> K U <lb/>F <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/> (29) <lb/>where the superscript refers to the time step, then, assuming that the unknown vector contains the nodal <lb/>degrees of freedom, it can be expressed as: <lb/>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/> i n <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> U <lb/>B <lb/> ζ φ <lb/>ζ <lb/> = <lb/> = <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (30) <lb/>Eq. (29) results <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( 1) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( 1) <lb/> m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/> K U <lb/>F <lb/>K B <lb/>F <lb/> ζ <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> (31) <lb/>and by multiplying both terms by  T <lb/> B  it results <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( 1) <lb/> T <lb/>m <lb/>T <lb/>m <lb/> B K B <lb/>B F <lb/> ζ <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/> (32) <lb/>which proves that the final system of equations is of low order, i.e. the dimension of <lb/> T <lb/> B K B  is <lb/> n <lb/>n ×  , <lb/>with <lb/> N <lb/>n &lt;&lt;  , and the dimensions of both <lb/> ( ) <lb/> m <lb/> ζ  and <lb/> ( 1) <lb/> T <lb/>m <lb/> B F <lb/> −  are <lb/> 1 <lb/> × <lb/> n  . <lb/> Remark 1.  Equation (32) can be also derived introducing the approximation (30) into the PDE Galerkin <lb/>form. <lb/> 2. Simulating complex flows <lb/> We consider the use of a decoupled strategy which solves the flow kinematics (from the orientation state <lb/>known at the previous iteration or time step), and then the orientation state can be updated using the velocity <lb/>field just computed. The flow kinematics can be solved accurately by using standard discretization <lb/>techniques as for example the finite element method. This paper focuses on the resolution of the orientation <lb/>problem which involves some specific difficulties. <lb/> 2.1 Extracting the solution structure <lb/> One possibility for reducing the computing time associated with the resolution of the Fokker-Planck <lb/>equation (18) consists of decoupling the resolution of the purely advection problem in the physical space <lb/>and the advection-diffusion defined in the conformation space. Now, the first problem can be accurately <lb/>integrated using the method of characteristics along some nodal trajectories, being the one defined in the <lb/>conformation space discretized using some stabilized finite element strategy for accounting its advection <lb/>character. The model reduction described later will operate only on the conformation space discretization. <lb/>

			<page>1 0 <lb/></page>

			We briefly summarize this strategy in the 2D case, the 3D case being a direct extension. In that case the <lb/>Fokker-Planck equation can be written using polar coordinates as: <lb/> , , <lb/> ( , , ) <lb/>( , , ) <lb/>( , , ) <lb/> r <lb/> x t <lb/> d x t <lb/>d <lb/>x t <lb/>x t <lb/>D <lb/>dt <lb/>dt  ϕ <lb/> ψ ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ψ ϕ <lb/>ψ ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> + <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/>∂ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (33) <lb/>where <lb/> , , <lb/> x t <lb/> d <lb/>dt  ϕ <lb/> ϕ <lb/> is computed from the Jeffery equation (13): <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 12 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/> 0 <lb/>-sin <lb/>cos <lb/>cos <lb/>0 <lb/>cos <lb/>sin <lb/>sin <lb/>cos <lb/>cos <lb/>-<lb/>cos <lb/>sin <lb/>sin <lb/>sin <lb/> D <lb/>D <lb/>d <lb/>k D <lb/>D <lb/>dt <lb/>D <lb/>D <lb/>k <lb/>D <lb/>D <lb/> ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/> Ω <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/> −Ω <lb/>− <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (34) <lb/>By multiplying the second equation by cosϕ , the first one by sinϕ and subtracting the first one from the <lb/>second one, it results: <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/> 12 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/> 0 <lb/>cos <lb/>s i n <lb/>c o s <lb/>0 <lb/>sin <lb/>cos <lb/>+ <lb/>sin <lb/>cos <lb/>sin <lb/> d <lb/>dt <lb/>D <lb/>D <lb/>k <lb/>D <lb/>D <lb/> ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/> Ω <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = − <lb/> + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> −Ω <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (35) <lb/>where the components of both the vorticity and the strain rate tensor could depend on the physical <lb/>coordinates  x  and time  t. <lb/> Applying a stabilized finite element discretization of Eq. (33) in the conformation space (  ϕ  ) it results <lb/>(taking into account the solution periodicity in the angular coordinate): <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>* <lb/>0 <lb/> r <lb/> d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>dt <lb/>dt <lb/>dt <lb/>D <lb/>d <lb/> π <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/>π <lb/> ψ <lb/>ϕ ψ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ψ ψ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ϕ <lb/>ψ ψ ϕ <lb/>ϕ ϕ <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂ 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> ∂ ∂ <lb/> = − <lb/>∂ ∂ <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (36) <lb/>

			<page>1 1 <lb/></page>

			The weighting function <lb/> * <lb/> ψ  is approximated as  ψ  whereas <lb/> * <lb/> ψ  is approximated in a different way in order <lb/>to account for the advection character of the differential operation. Different alternatives exist, out of the <lb/>scope of the present work. In our simulations a SUPG (streamline upwind Petrov Galerkin) stabilization <lb/>has been used. Finally, after introducing the different finite element interpolations and perform the <lb/>numerical integration the following linear system is obtained: <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/> K <lb/> K <lb/>F <lb/>K K <lb/>K F <lb/> ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/> • <lb/> • <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> = <lb/>+  񮽙  = <lb/>+ <lb/>  (37) <lb/>In this equation vector  F  accounts for the normality condition of the orientation distribution that is <lb/>enforced using a Lagrange multiplier technique. <lb/>Now, for integrating in the physical domain we use the method of characteristics by its simplicity and high <lb/>accuracy. For this purpose, we assume that we are looking for the solution along the streamline related to <lb/>point  X  where at the initial time  t=0  the orientation distribution is known. <lb/>Now, the orientation distribution updating is given by: <lb/> 1 <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> ( ; , 0) <lb/>( ; , 0) ( ( ; , 0), ) <lb/>( ( ; , 0), ) <lb/>( ( ; , 0), ) <lb/>( ( ; , 0), ) <lb/> n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/> x t X t <lb/>x t X t <lb/>v x t X t <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>x t X t <lb/>t <lb/>x t X t <lb/>t <lb/>K K <lb/>x t X t <lb/>t <lb/>F <lb/>t <lb/> ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> − <lb/> = = <lb/>= + <lb/>= <lb/> Δ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> + <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/> Δ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (38) <lb/>where <lb/> 1 <lb/> ( ; , 0) <lb/> n <lb/> x t X t <lb/> + <lb/> = <lb/> denotes the position that at time <lb/> 1 <lb/> n <lb/> t  +  occupies a fluid volume located at point <lb/> X  at time  t=0. <lb/> Using this simple uncoupled strategy one can compute the evolution of the fiber orientation distribution <lb/>along some nodal trajectories identified by the parameter  l.  Those distributions could be stored at some <lb/>time steps (snapshots) leading to the following eigenvalue problems: <lb/> [ <lb/>] <lb/> ( ) <lb/>(l) <lb/>( ) (l) <lb/> ; <lb/>1 , , <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/> Q Q <lb/>l <lb/>L <lb/> φ <lb/>αφ <lb/> = <lb/> ∈ 񮽙 <lb/> (39) <lb/>with <lb/>
			
			<page>1 2 <lb/></page> 
			
			1 <lb/>2 <lb/>( ) 1 <lb/>( ) 1 <lb/>( ) 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>( ) 2 <lb/>( ) 2 <lb/>( ) 2 <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> l <lb/> l <lb/>l <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/> P <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>P <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>P <lb/>l <lb/>N <lb/>l <lb/>N <lb/>l <lb/>N <lb/> Q <lb/> ψ <lb/> ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (40) <lb/>where (l) denotes the nodal trajectory,  l <lb/> P  the number of the selected distributions along each trajectory <lb/>(snapshots), and  L  is the total number of nodal trajectories where the Fokker-Planck equation has been <lb/>integrated, of course,  L <lb/>N <lb/> &lt;&lt;  , with  N  the total number of nodes used to discretize the physical domain <lb/>where the flow is defined and  c <lb/> N  the number of nodes used in the conformation space discretization (  ϕ  ). <lb/>Now, from the solution of Eq. (39) we can compute the most significant eignfunctions allowing to write: <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> l <lb/> i n <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>i <lb/>l <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> t <lb/>t <lb/>B <lb/>t <lb/> ψ <lb/>ζ <lb/>φ <lb/>ζ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> ≈ <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (41) <lb/>Vector  ψ  has  c <lb/> N  components that are in fact the values of the distribution function at the nodes used to <lb/>discretize the conformation domain (the unit circle or the unit surface in the 2D or 3D case respectively). <lb/>Now we will define a global reduced approximation basis  B  from the different reduced approximation <lb/>bases <lb/> ( ) <lb/> l <lb/> B  . For this purpose, we proceed as follows: <lb/> • <lb/> (1) <lb/> B B <lb/> = <lb/> , <lb/> 1 <lb/> n n <lb/> =  and  l=1 <lb/> •  While  l L <lb/> ≤ <lb/> o <lb/> 1 <lb/> l l <lb/> ← + <lb/> o <lb/> 0 <lb/> i = <lb/> o  While <lb/> l <lb/> i n <lb/> ≤ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 1 <lb/> i i <lb/> ← + <lb/> 񮽙  If <lb/> ( ) <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/> n <lb/>T <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>j <lb/>j <lb/> TOL <lb/> φ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ φ <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> − <lb/> &gt; <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ( ) <lb/> l <lb/>i <lb/> B <lb/>B  φ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> =  񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 1 <lb/> n n <lb/> ← + <lb/>
			
			<page> 1 3 <lb/></page>

			that is, we update the reduced approximation basis introducing only vectors that are not too close to the <lb/>existing ones (for a given tolerance  TOL). <lb/> The final reduced approximation basis consists of the  n  vectors contained in matrix  B  , and it could be <lb/>expected that that basis represents accurately all the orientation distributions in the whole flow domain. <lb/>In order to accelerate the computation it could be interesting to solve the equation governing the evolution <lb/>of the second order orientation equation instead of the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation, along all <lb/>the nodal trajectories, but as previously argued this approach involves the introduction of an appropriate <lb/>closure relation allowing the expression of the fourth order orientation tensor from the expression of the <lb/>second order one. <lb/> Remark 2.  It is also possible to derive an evolution equation for the fourth order orientation tensor that <lb/>involves the sixth order one, and also requires the definition of an appropriate closure relation. Despite <lb/>that, this strategy could be more appealing because the constitutive equation directly uses the fourth order <lb/>orientation tensor, and the procedure described in this work could be applied for deriving this closure <lb/>relation, from now on we only consider the evolution problem related to the second order tensor and the <lb/>associated closure problem. <lb/>Now, we denote by <lb/> [ <lb/> ] <lb/> ; <lb/>1, , <lb/> j <lb/> j <lb/>n <lb/> φ  ∈  񮽙 <lb/> the  n  approximation vectors contained in matrix  B  , that are <lb/>expected to describe accurately the evolution of the orientation distribution solution along any flow <lb/>streamline, i.e. <lb/> 0 <lb/>1 <lb/> ( ( ; , 0)) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> x t x t <lb/>t <lb/>B t <lb/> ψ <lb/>ζ φ <lb/>ζ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> = <lb/> ≈ <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (42) <lb/>where <lb/> 0 <lb/> ( ; , 0) <lb/> x t x t =  denotes the position at time  t  of a fluid particle located at 0 <lb/> x  at time <lb/> 0 <lb/> t =  . <lb/>Taking into account the expressions of the second and fourth order orientation tensors, given by Eqs. (6) <lb/>and (4) respectively, it results: <lb/>

			<page>1 4 <lb/></page>

			( 2) <lb/>0 <lb/>( 2) <lb/>(2 ) <lb/>1 <lb/> ( ( ; , 0)) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> a x t x t <lb/>t a <lb/>A t <lb/> ζ <lb/> ζ <lb/> = <lb/> = <lb/> = <lb/> ≈ <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (43) <lb/>and <lb/> ( 4) <lb/>0 <lb/>( 4) <lb/>(4 ) <lb/>1 <lb/> ( ( ; , 0)) <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> a x t x t <lb/>t a <lb/>A t <lb/> ζ <lb/>ζ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> = <lb/> ≈ <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (44) <lb/>where ( 2)  a  and ( 4)  a  denote the vector form of the second and fourth order orientation tensors <lb/>respectively, being ( 2) i <lb/> a  and ( 4) i <lb/> a  the vector forms of the tensors defined by the integrals: <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> ( ) <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/> a <lb/>d <lb/> π <lb/> ρ ρ ρ ρ φ ϕ ϕ <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ ⊗ ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> with <lb/> cos <lb/>sin <lb/> ϕ <lb/>ρ <lb/>ϕ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> =  񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (45) <lb/>and <lb/> 2 <lb/>0 <lb/> ( ) <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/> a <lb/>d <lb/> π <lb/> ρ ρ φ ϕ ϕ <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (46) <lb/>We would mention that the value of ( ) <lb/> i <lb/> φ ϕ  at point  ϕ  can be determined by standard interpolation from <lb/>the nodal values of  i <lb/> φ  contained in the vector  i <lb/> φ  . Finally, matrix ( 2)  A  and ( 4)  A  are built from vectors <lb/> ( 2) i <lb/> a  and ( 4) i <lb/> a  which defines their different columns. <lb/> 2.2 Natural closure relation <lb/> Any closure approximation of the fourth order orientation tensor can be written using the Caley-Hamilton <lb/>theorem as well as partial normalization and symmetry (see Dupret and Verleye, 1999), in the general form: <lb/> 6 <lb/>( 4) <lb/>(4) i <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>( 4) <lb/>(4) i <lb/>1 <lb/> in 3D <lb/>in 2D <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> a <lb/>w <lb/>a <lb/>w <lb/> β <lb/>β <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (47) <lb/>where <lb/>
			
			<page>1 5 <lb/></page> 
			
			( 4) 1 <lb/>( 4) 2 <lb/>( 4) 3 <lb/>2 <lb/>( 4) 4 <lb/>2 <lb/>( 4) 5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>( 4) 6 <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/> w S I I <lb/>w S I a <lb/>w S a a <lb/>w S I a <lb/>w S a a <lb/>w S a <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> ⊗ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (48) <lb/>and where ( ) <lb/> S <lb/> refers to the symmetric component. <lb/>All the coefficients  i <lb/> β  are not independent due to the normalization conditions. Thus, we have in 3D <lb/> 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>3 <lb/>6 <lb/> 10 1 0 <lb/>1 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 7 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 6 <lb/>4( <lb/>) <lb/>6 <lb/>0 0 4 <lb/>7 <lb/>5 <lb/>2(3 4 ) <lb/>0 <lb/> D <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>D <lb/>P D <lb/>D <lb/> β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/> − <lb/> = − <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> + <lb/> − <lb/> (49) <lb/>and in 2D <lb/> 1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/> 8 1 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/> P <lb/> β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> = − <lb/> + <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> (50) <lb/>where <lb/> det( ) <lb/> P <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> and <lb/> ( ) <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 2 <lb/> 1 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> D <lb/>Tr a <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> (with  Tr  () the tensor trace). <lb/>From now on, and for the sake of generality, we consider the 3D case. Thus, Eq. (49) can be written in the <lb/>matrix form: <lb/> u <lb/>d <lb/> f <lb/>g <lb/>h <lb/> β <lb/>β <lb/> = <lb/>+ <lb/> (51) <lb/>Eq. (47) results: <lb/> 1 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>( 4) <lb/>(4) i <lb/>1 <lb/> 0 <lb/>=W <lb/> i <lb/>u <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/> f g <lb/>f h <lb/>a <lb/>w <lb/>W <lb/>W <lb/>W <lb/>W <lb/>I <lb/>W <lb/> β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (52) <lb/>Now, considering Eq. (52) for the  n  couples of tensors <lb/> ,  i <lb/>i <lb/> a a <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> extracted from the most significant <lb/>distribution functions (as explained in the previous section), one could be interested in determining the <lb/>optimal value of <lb/> d <lb/> β  , that is close to the procedure used by Dupret and Verleye to derive the natural <lb/>

			<page>1 6 <lb/></page>

			closure relation, but they considered only the distribution related to an initial isotropic distribution of <lb/>infinite slender fibers, without diffusion effects and in a simple shear flow. <lb/> 2.3 Local natural closure relation <lb/> For computing the unknown beta coefficients we proceed by using a moving least square technique. For this <lb/>purpose we define the approximation error <lb/> ( <lb/> ) <lb/> 2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>(2) <lb/>( 2) <lb/>(4) <lb/>1 <lb/> ( <lb/>, ) <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>d <lb/>i <lb/> J a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a W <lb/>W <lb/> ε <lb/> β <lb/>δ <lb/>γ <lb/>β <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (53) <lb/>where the weighting coefficient  i <lb/> γ  scales with  i <lb/> λ  related to the eigenfunction  i <lb/> φ  that was used for <lb/>computing tensors <lb/> i <lb/> a  and  i <lb/> a  . The window function  ( ) <lb/> d <lb/> ε <lb/> δ <lb/> is introduced for increasing the weight of <lb/>closer couples <lb/> ,  i <lb/>i <lb/> a a <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> in the error expression. In our simulations we have considered the following <lb/>window function: <lb/> ( ) <lb/> 2 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>with <lb/> d <lb/>d <lb/> d <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/> ε <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/> δ <lb/>δ <lb/>δ <lb/>ε <lb/>ε <lb/>π <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> − 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 񮽙 <lb/> (54) <lb/>Now, the optimality condition implies <lb/> ( <lb/>)  T <lb/>( 2) <lb/>(2) <lb/>(4) <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/> 0 2 <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i d <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/> J <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>W <lb/>a W <lb/>W <lb/> ε <lb/> δ <lb/>γ <lb/>β <lb/>β <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = = <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (55) <lb/>that is: <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/> T <lb/>(2) <lb/>( 2) <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>T <lb/>( 2) <lb/>(2) <lb/>( 4) <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>i <lb/>i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>W W <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>W <lb/>a W <lb/> ε <lb/>ε <lb/> δ <lb/>γ <lb/>β <lb/>δ <lb/>γ <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/>− <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (56) <lb/>or <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/> 1 <lb/>T <lb/>( 2) <lb/>(2) <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>T <lb/>(2) <lb/>( 2) <lb/>( 4) <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/> i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>d <lb/>i <lb/>i n <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>W W <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>W <lb/>a W <lb/> ε <lb/>ε <lb/> β <lb/>δ <lb/>γ <lb/>δ <lb/>γ <lb/> − <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/>× <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> × <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> (57) <lb/>

			<page>1 7 <lb/></page>

			which allows to compute at each ( 2)  a  the closure relation coefficients  d <lb/> β  and then from Eq. (51)  u <lb/> β <lb/> which defined completely the closure relation: <lb/> ( 4) <lb/>(2) <lb/>( 2) <lb/> =W( <lb/>) ( <lb/>) <lb/> a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/> β <lb/> = <lb/> (58) <lb/> Remark 3.  If one consider a unit window function, i.e. <lb/> ( ) 1 <lb/> d <lb/> ε <lb/> δ <lb/> =  , it results a global least squares <lb/>approximation that implies that closure coefficient does not depend anymore on ( 2)  a  . <lb/> 3. Numerical tests <lb/>3.1 Simple shear flow <lb/> We consider a 2D simple shear flow whose kinematics is defined by <lb/> ( , 0) <lb/> T <lb/> v <lb/>y <lb/> γ <lb/> • <lb/> = <lb/> being the shear rate <lb/> 1 <lb/> γ <lb/> • <lb/> =  . The fiber suspension is characterized by fibers whose shape factor leads to <lb/> 0.8 <lb/> k = <lb/> and the <lb/>diffusion coefficient was set to <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> r <lb/> D = <lb/> . The orientation distribution (assumed 2D) is discretized using <lb/>the SUPG finite element method on the mesh associated with the conformation space that consists of <lb/> 200 <lb/> c <lb/> N  = <lb/> nodes uniformly distributed in [0, 2 [ <lb/> π  . <lb/>When the Fokker-Plank equation is integrated along a trajectory from the isotropic initial state until <lb/>reaching the steady state characterized by a small enough variation between two consecutive time steps, that <lb/>is: <lb/> 6 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/> ( ) <lb/>( ) 10 <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/> n <lb/>n <lb/> t <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/> ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/>ψ <lb/> − <lb/> + <lb/> − <lb/>≤ <lb/>− <lb/> and the Karhunen-Loève decomposition is applied to the snapshots selected during the orientation <lb/>distribution evolution (around 20), the modes depicted in figure 1 are then obtained. <lb/>We can notice that the linear combination of only 5 orientation distributions (the ones depicted in figure 1) <lb/>are enough to represent accurately the evolution of the orientation distribution along the considered <lb/>streamline. It is also important to remark that these functions have not a full physical meaning, because, for <lb/>

			<page>1 8 <lb/></page>

			example, they take negative values. However their linear combination can reproduce perfectly the evolution <lb/>of the distribution function coming from the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation. However, in the <lb/>procedure described in the previous section the second moment of those distributions (second order <lb/>orientation tensor) is calculated, and due to the characteristics of those distributions the derived tensors <lb/>have not a unit trace. Despite this fact one could continue to apply the procedure proposed in the previous <lb/>section ignoring those physical or conceptual difficulties. <lb/>Other possibility to avoid these modes without a full physical meaning, consists of assuming that the <lb/>orientation distribution can be written everywhere on the considered streamline as a linear combination of <lb/>some orientation distributions (snapshots), for example, those were used for applying the Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition. In order to avoid the consideration of two distributions too close, one could start with the <lb/>initial distribution, adding a new distribution to the reduced approximation basis only when it is far enough <lb/>from all the functions defining the reduced approximation basis. The advantage of this approach is that all <lb/>the modes used for approximating the orientation distribution evolutions are real physical distributions and <lb/>consequently the associated second order orientation tensors are perfectly defined from all points of view. <lb/>Figure 2 shows the different modes defined on the same streamline by using the just described strategy. We <lb/>can notice the smoothness, periodicity, definite positive and normality of those distributions that define the <lb/>reduced approximation basis which also contains 5 functions. <lb/>Finally, one could consider a last possibility related to the snapshot proper orthogonal decomposition. This <lb/>technique is based on finding the significant modes from the application of the Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition, but assuming that those modes can be written as a linear combination of the  snap <lb/> N <lb/> snapshot <lb/>that were used to define the decomposition. The main advantage of this strategy derives from the fact that it <lb/>is easy to prove that theses modes result from the eigenproblem defined by <lb/> ( ) <lb/> T <lb/> Q Q <lb/> λ <lb/> ϒ = ϒ <lb/> (59) <lb/>whose size is  snap <lb/>snap <lb/> N <lb/>N <lb/> × <lb/> instead of  c <lb/>c <lb/> N N <lb/> ×  , and where only the eigenvectors related to large enough <lb/>eigenvalues are retained, <lb/> 8 <lb/>1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> i <lb/> λ <lb/>λ <lb/> − <lb/> &gt; <lb/> , 1 <lb/> λ  being the highest eigenvalue. From those eigenvectors the <lb/>

			<page>1 9 <lb/></page>

			reduced approximation modes are computed using the fact that those modes are linear combination of the <lb/>snapshots, i.e.: <lb/> [ <lb/> ] <lb/> , i 1, , <lb/> i <lb/> i <lb/> Q <lb/>n <lb/> φ  = ϒ <lb/>∈  񮽙 <lb/> (60) <lb/>The most significant modes  i <lb/> φ  related to the eigenvectors  i <lb/> ϒ  through <lb/> i <lb/>i <lb/> Q <lb/> φ  = ϒ  are depicted in figure <lb/>3. <lb/>In any case, these three numerical schemes offer three reduced approximation basis that can be used to <lb/>define the natural closure according to the procedure defined in the previous section. <lb/>In order to compare these different strategies, we have computed the reference second order orientation <lb/>tensor from the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation, and then the different orientation tensors using the <lb/>closures proposed in the previous section. The reference and approximated second order orientation <lb/>tensors were compared at different times, for different values of the diffusion coefficients, using the <lb/>following error measure: <lb/> ref <lb/>aprox <lb/> E a <lb/>a <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> (61) <lb/>Table 1 groups the different computed errors at the end of the evolution process. We can notice that when <lb/>the diffusion coefficient is small enough the standard natural closure relation works perfectly because we <lb/>are close to the hypothesis under which it was derived. However, when the diffusion coefficient is <lb/>increased, the solution accuracy is degraded. On the other hand, the adaptive natural closure that we have <lb/>defined works perfectly for any diffusion coefficient, except for the too small values that induce numerical <lb/>difficulties in the finite element discretization of the Fokker-Planck equation in the conformation space. We <lb/>must mention that due to the fact that the Karhunen-Loève and the Snapshot Karhunen-Loève natural <lb/>closures are built from modes (approximation functions) that have not a full physical meaning we have <lb/>preferred using a global least square technique. Moreover, the global least squares fitting can be applied <lb/>without a significant impact on the solution accuracy and with a considerable computing time reduction. <lb/> 3.2 Extensional flow <lb/>

			<page> 2 0 <lb/></page>

			We consider a 2D extensional flow whose kinematics is defined by <lb/> ( , <lb/>) <lb/> T <lb/> v <lb/>x <lb/>y <lb/> ε <lb/> ε <lb/> • <lb/> • <lb/> = <lb/> − <lb/> being the <lb/>elongation rate <lb/> 1 <lb/> ε <lb/> • <lb/> =  . The fiber suspension is characterized by fibers whose shape factor leads to <lb/> 0.8 <lb/> k  = <lb/> . The orientation distribution (assumed 2D) is discretized using the SUPG finite element method <lb/>on the mesh associated with the conformation space that consists of <lb/> 200 <lb/> c <lb/> N  = <lb/> nodes uniformly <lb/>distributed in [0, 2 [ <lb/> π  . <lb/>Figures 4 and 5 depict the time evolution of the error defined in Eq. (61) for <lb/> 0.01 <lb/> r <lb/> D  = <lb/> and <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> r <lb/> D  = <lb/> respectively, where only the snapshot natural closure is compared with the standard natural one. We can <lb/>notice the superior accuracy of the snapshot natural closure for both diffusion coefficients. <lb/> 3.3 Driven cavity flow model: an example of complex flow <lb/> In this section we consider the complex flow generated in a driven cavity <lb/> ] [ ] [ <lb/> 0,1 0,1 <lb/> Ω = <lb/> × <lb/> that involves <lb/>a short fiber suspension characterized by the same material parameters that in the previous tests. The <lb/>velocity <lb/>is <lb/>prescribed <lb/>on <lb/>the <lb/>domain <lb/>boundary <lb/>according <lb/>to: <lb/> ( <lb/>) <lb/> 0, <lb/>( <lb/>1, ) <lb/>( , <lb/>0) 0 <lb/> v x <lb/>y v x <lb/>y v x y <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>= = <lb/> and <lb/> ( <lb/>) ( <lb/>) <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>max <lb/> , <lb/>1 <lb/>16 <lb/>(1 ) , 0 <lb/> T <lb/> v x y <lb/>v x <lb/>x <lb/> = <lb/>= <lb/> − <lb/> . The <lb/>velocity field is then solved by assuming a Newtonian behavior and by applying a standard mixed finite <lb/>element formulation where the velocity and pressure approximations verify the LBB stability condition. The <lb/>Fokker-Planck equation governing the evolution of the fiber orientation distribution function is then solved <lb/>along some closed streamlines, where the periodicity condition of that distribution function was imposed as <lb/>described in Ammar and Chinesta (2005). From the computed orientation distribution function, the <lb/>characteristic modes are extracted by using the technique previously described based on the application of <lb/>the Karhunen-Loève decomposition, allowing to fit the empirical natural closure introduced in section 2.3 <lb/>using the snapshot natural closure strategy previously introduced. Now, the evolution equation associated <lb/>with the second order orientation tensor is solved by assuming different closure relations: linear, quadratic, <lb/>hybrid, natural and the empirical natural one. <lb/>

			<page>2 1 <lb/></page>

			If the Fokker-Planck equation is solved in the whole domain considering a fine enough mesh, the fiber <lb/>distribution function can be computed everywhere without addressing any closure relation. Thus, the second <lb/>order orientation tensor related to the just computed distribution function can be used as reference solution <lb/>for comparison purposes. <lb/>The error between the computed second order orientation tensor and the reference solution coming from the <lb/>solution of the Fokker-Planck equation is reported in Table 2. <lb/>From the previous results we can conclude that in the case of real complex flows it is difficult to conclude <lb/>about the net superiority of a particular closure relation. In this kind of flows there are regions in which <lb/>advection terms dominate the diffusion ones (as for example in the neighborhood of the upper wall in the <lb/>driven cavity flow) whereas in others regions diffusion terms dominate the advection ones. The contrast <lb/>between these two competitive behaviors increases as the diffusion coefficient decreases because for high <lb/>enough diffusion coefficients the spatial gradients of the orientation field are quite reduced. <lb/> 4. Conclusions <lb/> This work focused on the resolution of the Fokker-Planck equation that governs the evolution of the fiber <lb/>orientation distribution. To reduce the computing time, that equation is solved along some flow trajectories <lb/>in order to extract the significant information of the solution from the application of the Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition. This extraction has been made using three different strategies: (i) the standard Karhunen-<lb/>Loève decomposition; (ii) the simple use of some snapshots of the orientation distribution evolution (linear <lb/>independence is checked during the basis construction) and (iii) applying the snapshot-Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition that makes optimal the snapshot basis. From this reduced approximation bases we adjust a <lb/>closure relation that becomes optimal for such flow, that allows solving the evolution of some orientation <lb/>moments which require a less amount of computation. The accuracy of the proposed approach has been <lb/>illustrated in some numerical examples concerning some simple flows, and seems to be an appealing <lb/>strategy when the salient diffusion effects have an unfavourable effect on the natural closure approximation. <lb/>Thus, a mixed strategy combining the natural closure in the regions where the orientation is dominated by <lb/>
			
			<page>2 2 <lb/></page>
			
			advection terms and the adjustable one when the diffusion effects becomes important could be nice <lb/>candidate to be considered when fast and accurate solutions are desired. <lb/> </body>
			
			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/> S.G. Advani, Ch.L.Tucker III. Closure approximations for three-dimensional structure tensors. J. Rheol., <lb/>34, 367-386, (1990). <lb/>A. Ammar, F. Chinesta. A particle strategy for solving the Fokker-Planck equation governing the fiber <lb/>orientation distribution in steady recirculating flows involving short fiber suspensions. Lectures Notes on <lb/>Computational Science and Engineering, Springer, 43, 1-16, (2005). <lb/>G.K Batchelor. Slender-body theory for particles of arbitrary cross-section in Stokes flow. J. Fluid Mech., <lb/>44, 419-440, (1970). <lb/>C. Chauviere, A. Lozinski. Simulation of dilute polymer solutions using a Fokker-Planck equation. <lb/>Computers and Fluids., 33, 687-696 (2004). <lb/>F. Dupret, V. Verleye. Modelling the flow of fiber suspensions in narrows gaps. In Advances in the Flow <lb/>and Rheology of Non-Newtonian Fluids. D.A. Siginer, D. De Kee and R.P. Chabra editors, Rheology <lb/>Series, Elsevier, 1347-1398, (1999). <lb/>F.P. Folgar, Ch.L. Tucker III. Orientation behavior of fibers in concentrated suspensions. J. Reinf. Plast. <lb/>Comp., 3, 98-119, (1984). <lb/>F. Gillet-Chaulet, O. Gagliardini, J. Meyssonnier, T. Zwinger, J. Ruokolainen. Flow-induced anisotropy in <lb/>polar ice and related ice-sheet flow modelling. J. Non-Newtonian Fluid Mech., 134, 33-43, (2006). <lb/>G.L. Hand. A theory of anisotropic fluids. J. Fluid Mech., 13, 33-46, (1962) <lb/>E.J. Hinch, L.G. Leal. Constitutive equations in suspension mechanics. Part I. J. Fluid Mech., 71, 481-495, <lb/>(1975). <lb/>E.J. Hinch, L.G. Leal. Constitutive equations in suspension mechanics. Part II. J. Fluid Mech., 76, 187-208, <lb/>(1976). <lb/>M.A. Hulsen, A.P.G. van Heel, B.H.A.A. van den Brule. Simulation of viscoelastic flows using Brownian <lb/>configuration fields. J. Non-Newtonian Fluid Mech., 70, 79-101, (1997). <lb/>G.B. Jeffrey. The motion of ellipsoidal particles immersed in viscous fluid. Proc. R. Soc. London, Ser. A <lb/>102, 161-179, (1922). <lb/>G.G. Lipscomb, M.M. Denn, D.H. Hur, D.V. Boger. The flow of fiber suspensions in complex geometries. <lb/>J. Non-Newtonian Fluid Mech., 26, 297-325, (1988). <lb/>A. Lozinski, C. Chauviere. A fast solver for Fokker-Planck equation applied to viscoelastic flows <lb/>calculations: 2D FENE model. J. Computational Physics, 189, 607-625, (2003). <lb/>H.C. Öttinger, M. Laso. Smart polymers in finite element calculation. Int Congr. on Rheology, Brussel, <lb/>Belgium (1992). <lb/>M. Parsheh, M.L. Brown, C.K. Aidun, Investigation of closure approximations for fiber orientation <lb/>distribution in contracting turbulent flow. J. Non-Newtonian Fluid Mech., 136, 38-49, (2006). <lb/>

			<page>2 3 <lb/></page>

			D. Ryckelynck, F. Chinesta, E. Cueto, A. Ammar. On the a priori model reduction: overview and recent <lb/> developments. Archives of Computational Methods in Engineering, 13/1, 91-128, (2006). <lb/>Ch.L. Tucker III. Flow regimes for fiber suspensions in narrow gap. J. Non-Newtonian Fluid Mech., 39, <lb/>239-268, (1991). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>2 4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Diffusion <lb/>Natural <lb/>Closure <lb/>KL -Natural <lb/>Closure <lb/>Snapshot <lb/>Natural Closure <lb/>Snapshot-KL <lb/>Natural Closure <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.0139 <lb/>0.0095 <lb/>0.0091 <lb/>0 . 0 3 5 5 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.0046 <lb/>0.0196 <lb/>0.0113 <lb/>0 . 0 4 7 1 <lb/> Table 1.  Error of the different closure approximations: standard natural closure (Dupret and Verleye, 1999) <lb/>and the adaptive natural closure described in section 2 using the three different reduced approximation <lb/>bases just defined: the first one using the modes coming from the direct application of the Karhunen-Loève <lb/>decomposition, the second one using some appropriate snapshots and the last one based on the use of the <lb/>snapshot Karhune-Loève decomposition. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Diffusion <lb/>Linear <lb/>Quadratic <lb/>Hybrid <lb/>Natural <lb/>Empirical <lb/>Natural <lb/>1 <lb/>0.0031 <lb/>0.0704 <lb/>0.0062 <lb/>0.0019 <lb/>0.0008 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.1992 <lb/>0.1516 <lb/>0.0800 <lb/>0.0353 <lb/>0.0289 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>1.1286 <lb/>0.1452 <lb/>0.1048 <lb/>0.1216 <lb/>0.1126 <lb/> Table 2.  Error of the different closure approximations: linear, quadratic, hybrid, standard natural closure <lb/>(Dupret and Verleye, 1999) and the snapshot natural closure described in section 2. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 6 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 1.  Significant modes related to the evolution of the orientation distribution function along a <lb/>streamline computed from the Karhunen-Loève decomposition. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 2.  Reduced approximation modes related to the evolution of the orientation distribution function <lb/>along a flow streamline. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 3.  Significant modes related to the snapshot – Karhunen-Loève techniques. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure 4.  Error evolution in an elongational flow for <lb/> 0.01 <lb/> r <lb/> D  = <lb/> 3 0 <lb/> Figure 5.  Error evolution in an elongational flow for <lb/> 0.1 <lb/> r <lb/> D  = </body>


	</text>
</tei>
