<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_French_in_Auvergne"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
				
			<titlePage>French in Auvergne (Centre) : a speaker from <lb/>Clermont-Ferrand <lb/> Damien Chabanal, J. Durand, Corinne Ratier <lb/> To cite this version: <lb/> Damien Chabanal, J. Durand, Corinne Ratier. French in Auvergne (Centre) : a speaker from <lb/>Clermont-Ferrand. Oxford University Press. varieties of spoken French, Oxford University <lb/>Press, pp.5-15, 2015. &lt;hal-01062222&gt; <lb/> HAL Id: hal-01062222 <lb/>https://hal.archives-ouvertes.fr/hal-01062222 <lb/> Submitted on 10 Sep 2014 <lb/> HAL is a multi-disciplinary open access <lb/>archive for the deposit and dissemination of sci-<lb/>entific research documents, whether they are pub-<lb/>lished or not. The documents may come from <lb/>teaching and research institutions in France or <lb/>abroad, or from public or private research centers. <lb/>L&apos;archive ouverte pluridisciplinaire HAL, est <lb/>destinée au dépôt et a la diffusion de documents <lb/>scientifiques de niveau recherche, publiés ou non, <lb/>´ emanant des etablissements d&apos;enseignement et de <lb/>recherche français oú etrangers, des laboratoires <lb/>publics ou privés. <lb/></titlePage>

			<front> French in Auvergne (Centre): <lb/>a speaker from Clermont-Ferrand <lb/> Damien Chabanal, Jacques Durand and Corinne Ratier <lb/> A paraître dans l&apos;ouvrage « varieties of spoken french », Oxford University Press <lb/></front> 
			
			<body>0. Introduction <lb/> This extract has been chosen to illustrate the variety of French in the Auvergne region, <lb/>more precisely in Clermont-Ferrand in the Puy de Dôme department, the town where our <lb/>selected speaker was born and lives. Linguistically, Clermont-Ferrand is part of North Occitan <lb/>(see Bec 1963: 7-8) but we are not aware of any published work on the variety of <lb/>contemporary spoken French in this part of France apart from the thumbnail phonological <lb/>sketch of a Clermont-Ferrand speaker in Walter (1982: 169). Clermont-Ferrand, with a <lb/>population of over 140 000 inhabitants and its famous Michelin factories, is usually <lb/>considered as the capital of Massif Central. It is an important university town since there are <lb/>37 000 students, according to its Mairie&apos;s official website. Indeed, our chosen speaker is a <lb/>student whose French is at first sight a good example of a levelled variety (see Armstrong and <lb/>Pooley 2010) but, which on closer inspection of the phonology, still shows a number of <lb/>regional features. <lb/> 1. Sociolinguistic profile and recording situation <lb/> The speaker we focus on is a young woman MM (PFC code: 63mm1), who was 22 years <lb/>old at the time of the recording. She was born in Clermont-Ferrand in 1988. She has always <lb/>lived in the area apart from two years spent in Paris for her studying. During her stay in Paris <lb/>she did her second year correspondence course in psychology while working at the same time. <lb/>Back in the Puy de Dôme she joined a school training students for a Diplôme d&apos;État <lb/>d&apos;Éducateur Spécialisé (DEES). <lb/>The recording was made at the very beginning of her first year course and the extract is <lb/>chosen from an informal conversation between MM and her mother which took place in <lb/>September 2010 in the family house. <lb/> 2. Content analysis and lexicon <lb/>  MM tells her mother about her course which just started the day before the conversation, <lb/>her teachers and their expectations. The style, outside the precise references to education and <lb/>psychology, is informal. MM starts by describing her first teacher as un mec trop bizarre (l. <lb/>1, &apos;a very strange guy&apos;) where the use of the adverb trop to mean &apos;très&apos; is typical of the <lb/>younger generations in hexagonal French. The teacher&apos;s strangeness seems to derive from his <lb/>appearance (his long hair possibly seen as a sign of marginality in a professional context) but <lb/>also from his attitude and approach (the way he walks and prods students with repeated <lb/>questions). Every word used by a student has to be justified as to what lies behind it: Et <lb/>chaque mot que tu dis, il te dit : &apos;Mais tu sous-entends quoi ?&apos; (l. 7-8). The word marrant to <lb/>characterize the whole experience means &apos;funny&apos; and like its English equivalent is ambiguous <lb/>between the sense of &apos;peculiar&apos; and that of &apos;mirth provoking&apos;. Although the mother wonders if <lb/>this teacher is a psychologist, the daughter describes him as an éduc which is short for <lb/> éducateur (l. 12), a teacher of children with special needs. The strategy of truncating common <lb/>words is very frequent in hexagonal French and also illustrated within this extract by fac (l. <lb/>
			
			41) short for faculté (= university in this context) and prof (used by the mother, l. 52) short for <lb/> professeur (= teacher). <lb/>If this teacher&apos;s style is somewhat idiosyncratic, he is nevertheless said to be extremely <lb/>knowledgeable - il a un sacré niveau (l. 14, lit. &apos;he has an incredible level&apos;), where the use of <lb/> sacré as an intensificator is typical of informal speech. This remark allows MM to move on <lb/>to the course as such and its contents. MM stresses repeatedly how intensive the course is and <lb/>how much is expected of the students although they have no assignments as such (on a pas de <lb/>devoirs en soi, l. 19). <lb/>With a great deal of colloquial expressions, MM explains that she has to get stuck into <lb/>completing all her index cards (il faut que je me tape à faire toutes mes fiches, l. 23-24), read <lb/>lots of books (bouquins familiar for livres, l. 37) and attend &apos;millions&apos; of classes (une tonne <lb/>de cours, l. 31) on educational and psychological matters such as la séparation (l. 58, <lb/>&apos;divorce&apos;) and l&apos;hospitalisme (l. 58, &apos;hospitalism&apos; which can be defined as a type of mental <lb/>illness which affects children who have been prematurely separated from their mothers and <lb/>institutionalised). <lb/> Throughout the conversation, MM stresses the high level achieved by their teachers. <lb/>During the afternoon session, the students had a woman (une fille, lit. &apos;a girl&apos;, l. 39) who is <lb/> super sympa (l. 39, lit. super friendly) and who was initially a teacher of children with special <lb/>needs but then went to University and became a formatrice (an educationalist involved in the <lb/>training of future teachers). This woman is described as a militante, a term used to describe <lb/>activists involved in political or civil rights movements. In this context, it is likely that the <lb/>description applies to a person involved in the feminist movement but to establish the precise <lb/>reference of the phrase one would have to know more about the &apos;political&apos; or &apos;ideological&apos; <lb/>outlook of the speaker. <lb/>Many of the lexical choices are tightly integrated into the grammar used by MM and <lb/>would deserve more comments than is possible here. The relaxed register used by MM is <lb/>often typical of her generation but many of the lexical and grammatical features are typical of <lb/>colloquial speech. Although they are often branded &apos;très familier&apos;, and even &apos;populaire&apos; or <lb/>&apos;vulgaire&apos;, it is well known that all speakers use such words or constructions in informal <lb/>everyday conversation. Two obvious examples are the use of vachement (l. 57) to mean <lb/>&apos;beaucoup&apos; or &apos;très&apos;, a well-established feature of informal French, and the frequent use of <lb/> 
			
			machin (l. 32, 41, 66), a vague noun which like English &apos;thingummy&apos; or &apos;thingamabob&apos; <lb/>allows the speaker to refer to something or someone when you cannot remember or cannot be <lb/>bothered to find the proper word or name for them. The vagueness of the referent is <lb/>emphasized by et tout meaning &apos;and all&apos; (l. 32, 41). On the other hand, in l&apos;hospitalisme <lb/>machin (l. 66), machin appears to be used as a modifier with vague reference (&apos;any type of <lb/>hospitalism&apos;). The use of se taper is particularly interesting in this extract. <lb/>In colloquial usage, se taper is usually followed by a complement noun phrase and <lb/>means &apos;to get landed with&apos; (e.g. je me suis tapé toute la vaisselle = &apos;I got landed with (doing) <lb/>all the dishes&apos;). Here, however, the verb is followed by a verb phrase introduced by à: se <lb/>taper à faire toutes les fiches = &apos;to get landed with completing all the index cards&apos;. All these <lb/>examples illustrate the difficulty of defining registers in a rigid way. However we deal with <lb/>this question, it is essential not to look at all the features of spoken French present in the <lb/>extracts selected in this volume from a prescriptive point of view. Rather than seeing them as <lb/>illustrating a vulgar level of speech full of mistakes, we must learn to see them as typical of <lb/>spoken interaction between people who know each other well (see Blanche-Benveniste 2000: <lb/>35-63). <lb/> 3. Syntactic and discursive features <lb/> As emphasized above, this extract provides a striking illustration of informal speech. For <lb/>lack of space, we will not deal with features such as hesitations (there are 28 &apos;euh&apos; in the <lb/>extract), repetitions, reformulations, unfinished sentences or self-corrections which are typical <lb/>of spontaneous spoken interaction (see Rossi-Gensane, 2010, Ch. 6). Among features worth <lb/>examining, we will start with some comments on (i) ne in negative structures, (ii) the use of <lb/>personal pronouns, (iii) the use of tenses and moods, and then move on to some general <lb/>observations regarding the structure of this extract. <lb/>i) In one interpretation, ne is systematically omitted from all negative sentences in this <lb/>extract: cf. Non il est pas psychologue (l. 10-11), tu peux pas lire b/ dix bouquins (l. 37), vous <lb/>les lisez pas tous (l. 45), Si tu veux c&apos;est pas ça (l. 51). But it should be remembered that when <lb/>the pronoun on is used immediately a vowel initial word (e.g on a rien), it is impossible <lb/>according to most authorities to know whether the speaker used ne or not: on n&apos;a rien or on a <lb/>rien. In the relevant examples in this extract (cf. on a pas de devoirs en soi, on a rien de, <lb/> &lt;LM: Ouais.) on a rien à préparer (l. 19-20)), we have deliberately chosen not to include ne <lb/> in our transcriptions in line with the other clear examples where ne was indeed systematically <lb/>absent. It can&apos;t however be excluded that the speaker intended a ne which is not audible! <lb/>(ii) Unsurprisingly MM refers to herself as je (reinforced by moi, l. 60), and mother and <lb/>daughter use tu to refer to each other. It will be noticed that in reported speech (which there is <lb/>a great deal of in the extract), the teacher appears to use tu (or the oblique form toi) to address <lb/>the student which is not universal in higher education in France: e.g. Alors pour toi qu&apos;est-ce <lb/>que veut dire éducateur (l. 3-4), Oui mais tu sous-entends quoi par accompagner ? (l. 6-7). <lb/>The use of &apos;tu&apos; by a teacher when speaking to students probably depends on factors such as <lb/>age, &apos;political&apos; or &apos;ideological&apos; stance, outlook on life and the type of higher education <lb/>establishment one is dealing with. The reader will notice that many of the tu forms used by <lb/>MM are &apos;generic&apos; in value, often interpretable as on or nous but occasionally vaguer in <lb/>reference: e.g. Et chaque mot que tu dis (l. 7). It would appear that this &apos;generic&apos; use of tu is <lb/>currently replacing vous in hexagonal French (e.g. Et chaque mot que vous dites would have <lb/>been possible). The pronoun on is also very frequent and can either be replaced by nous or has <lb/>a generic value in line with its etymology (= homme). <lb/> (iii) As in many other extracts in this book, the tenses used are the indicative present, the <lb/>imperfect, the &apos;passé composé&apos;. Note that there are no futures but that MM uses aller + Vinf : <lb/>e.g. je vais continuer à lire mes fiches régulièrement (l. 63). The subjunctive, whose death has <lb/>frequently but rather imprudently been predicted for spoken French, is well-attested. It is <lb/>systematically triggered by the impersonal verb falloir: e.g. le problème c&apos;est qu&apos;il faut que ça <lb/>soit des notions qui soient acquises, c&apos;est-à-dire qu&apos;on f/faut qu&apos;on les apprenne ces notions <lb/> (l. 20-23). The absence of dummy subject il is in fact quite frequent before faut: cf. c&apos;est-à-<lb/>dire qu&apos;on f/faut qu&apos;on les apprenne ces notions (l. 22-23), Ah mais ce livre il est <lb/>indispensable &lt;LM: (XXXX)&gt; faut absolument que vous lisiez (l. 35-36), l e s notions <lb/>principales que tu vois en cours &lt;LM: Voilà.&gt; faut que tu les aies acquises (l. 55-56), nous <lb/> faut qu&apos;on sache ce que c&apos;est l&apos;hospitalisme (l. 66-67). In faut que tu les aies acquises (l. 56), <lb/>
			
			the reader should note the agreement form acquises (feminine plural) triggered by a direct <lb/>object complement if it precedes the auxiliary verb avoir (here les which stands for les <lb/>notions principales). This type of agreement is getting rarer and rarer in speech, even among <lb/>cultivated speakers (see Rouayrenc 2010: 150). <lb/>This shows that registers are not watertight modules and that characteristics of colloquial <lb/>speech can coexist with more formal features. <lb/>At a more general level, word-order and sentence-structure also seem to be in line with <lb/>the conversational register. Most of the utterances are statements but the few questions used <lb/>either by the speaker or her mother deserve some brief comments. The question (Alors pour <lb/>toi,) qu&apos;est-ce que veut dire éducateur? (l. 3-4) corresponds to the more formal written form <lb/> que veut dire éducateur?. It shows the spread of Qu&apos;est-ce-que into QU-questions. The QU-<lb/>element stays in situ in the other reported speech question: Oui mais tu sous-entends quoi par <lb/>accompagner? (l. 6-7), instead of the normative form Oui mais qu&apos;est-ce que tu sous-entends <lb/>par accompagner ?. As for the YES-NO question used by the mother (Et tu as des devoirs?, l. <lb/>17-18), it uses the declarative order rather than an inverted form (Et as-tu des devoirs?) as is <lb/>generally the case in hexagonal spoken French. <lb/>Many of the statements are built around a nucleus made up of a pronoun-subject + verb + <lb/>optional complement (il arrive vers toi; il s&apos;avance, tu parles, etc.) with possible internal <lb/>expansions (other pronouns, negation, etc.). But it must be remembered that these basic <lb/>predicational nuclei (e.g. je le sais, l. 59) are announced by thematically salient phrases which <lb/>can themselves be placed after discursive markers, as illustrated by an utterance like: Donc <lb/>moi déjà, tout ce que j&apos;ai, toute la séparation, l&apos;hospitalisme tout ça je le sais (l. 56-59). <lb/> A connective like donc (or alors) can be argued to provide a temporal or causal frame to <lb/>the reporting of events but other discourse markers such as tu vois (l. 1), tu sais (l. 9), si tu <lb/>veux (l. 51, 52) show how the speaker involves the addressee (her mother) by maintaining the <lb/>channel of communication and allowing her, a least in theory, to disagree with what is being <lb/>said. Many modern specialists emphasize that these discourse markers are essential to the co-<lb/>construction of discourse. <lb/>4. Phonetic and phonological features <lb/> The pronunciation of our speaker (MM) is interesting in that its segmental system (in <lb/>particular, its oral vowel system, see 4.1) is typical of southern varieties of French; on the <lb/>other hand, as far as schwa is concerned the features which we have identified (see 4.2) are <lb/>typical of northern varieties of French. <lb/>4.1 Vowel system <lb/> Let us focus first of all on the oral vowels but leave aside the high vowels /i, y, u/ as there <lb/>are no striking differences between the system used by MM and that of most other varieties of <lb/>hexagonal French. On the other hand, the non-high vowels deserve our attention. First of all, <lb/>like typical southern French speakers MM has only one /a/ phoneme. She does not distinguish <lb/>a front and a back vowel even in the reading aloud of minimal pairs such as patte vs. pâte in <lb/>the word list. Secondly, the mid-vowels are reducible to three phonemes which we will <lb/>represent here as /E/, /Ø/ and /O/. The capital letters for the underlying phonemes are assumed <lb/>to range over two values in each case [e, o, ø] in open syllables and [ɛ, oe, ɔ] in closed <lb/>syllables. This is generally referred to as the &apos;loi de position&apos; (see Ch. 13 and Coquillon &amp; <lb/>Durand 2010). It will be noticed for instance that all –ais, -ait endings which are mid-low [ɛ] <lb/>in some northern varieties are pronounced with an [e]: e.g Mais il/tu sais c&apos;est marrant <lb/>comme il fait alors il, il marchait comme ça (l. 10), disait (l. 28), était (l. 42). The full <lb/>distribution of the mid-high vs. mid-low allophones of /E/, / Ø/ and /O/ is not attested in this <lb/>extract but the reader can verify that the &apos;loi de position&apos; is respected in the word-list and the <lb/>reading aloud of the text. Thus, chaude and chose in the text are both pronounced with an [ɔ]. <lb/>The nasal vowels used by MM do not have a typical southern realization (i.e. oral or <lb/>slightly nasalised vowel followed by a nasal appendix). Nevertheless, unlike modern speakers <lb/>of Parisian French, she appears to make an opposition between /ɛ̃ / and /oẽ /: compare the <lb/>pronunciation of un in the first line of this extract with that of bien: j&apos;ai eu euh, un mec trop <lb/>bizarre mais pff bien tu vois. It also seems to us that this true of the word-list and the text: <lb/>compare brun with brin which are differentiated although not in a minimal pair-context <lb/>triggering a more artificial pronunciation. If we are correct, this speaker has four nasal <lb/>vowels: /ɛ̃ , oẽ , ɑ̃ , ɔ̃ /. <lb/>4.2 Schwa <lb/>As far as schwa is concerned, the patterns of deletion are aligned on those typical in <lb/>northern varieties of French. Starting with polysyllabic words, the word-final position <lb/>corresponds to an absence of schwa: e.g. je vais quand mêm(e) fair(e) mes fich(e)s (l. 61). In <lb/>word-internal position, unless there is a preceding complex cluster, schwa is deleted: e.g. <lb/> malheureus(e)ment (l. 24), feuill(e)tez (l. 46), vach(e)ment (l. 57), régulièr(e)ment (l. 63). <lb/>Within word-initial syllables, the deletion of schwa exhibits variability. A consonant-cluster <lb/>at the end of the preceding word blocks schwa-deletion: on a pas d(e) devoir (l. 19), je vais <lb/>jus(te) relire mon cours (l. 60). A vowel-final preceding word seems to favour deletion, <lb/>
			
			particularly with some frequent lexical items: les ch(e)veux (l. 2), la s(e)maine (l. 25). <lb/>However, note the presence of schwa in est repartie en fac (l. 41). There are two few <lb/>examples in this conversation to extract a full generalization. <lb/>Moving to monosyllables, this speaker seems to delete schwas as a matter of routine. <lb/>There are however some blocking contexts. The maintenance of a schwa may be triggered by <lb/>discourse planning factors: e.g. hesitation (remplies de, de dates) or a position at the end of an <lb/>unfinished sentence (vous essayez de. (l. 46)). Emphasis can also favour retention despite a <lb/>vowel on the left (e.g. mais ce livre l. 35). <lb/>A consonant at the end of the preceding word may appear to block deletion (cf. une <lb/>bibliographie donc de tous les livres, l. 43), which would traditionally be described in terms <lb/>of Grammont&apos;s famous &apos;loi des trois consonnes&apos; (i.e. avoid deleting a schwa if this results in a <lb/>cluster of three consonants or more ([kdt] in the above example). But note that the nature of <lb/> the consonant is highly relevant. Whereas &apos;donc&apos; ends in a plosive [k], a final [ʁ] does not <lb/>have the same effect and schwas are absent in the following examples despite the creation of <lb/>clusters of three consonants: prévoir l(e) soir ([ʁls], l. 26), histoir(e) d(e) l&apos;éducation ([ʁdl], l. <lb/>31), sur l(e) sujet ([ʁls], l. 44). In the same way, if a monosyllable is at the beginning of a <lb/>rhythmic group the schwa may be maintained (que les notions principales, l. 50) but note the <lb/>presence here of a plosive [k]. By contrast, in common clitics beginning with a fricative such <lb/>as je or ce, deletion seems to be automatic (C(e) matin (l. 1), J(e) sais pas comment (l. 48)). <lb/>4.3 Liaison <lb/> There are few contexts in the selected extract allowing for an extensive study of liaison. <lb/>Categorical liaisons as defined in the PFC project (see Ch. 28) are realized. Here the examples <lb/>are reduced to liaison between a clitic and the following item (e.g. on [n]a (l. 14), elle nous <lb/>[z]a données (l. 43)), Det + N (un [n]éduc, l. 12) and the set phrase tout-à-fait [tutafe] (l. 11). <lb/>There are a few contexts which are considered as variable in the recent literature and in all <lb/>such cases liaison is not realized: e.g. c&apos;est // un éduc (l. 12), c&apos;est // impressionnant (l. 49). <lb/>The reading aloud of the PFC text is therefore useful for a better understanding of this <lb/>speaker&apos;s system and of the possible role of register. Interestingly, the higher register <lb/>normally triggered by reading aloud is only detectable in the behaviour of the form est of the <lb/>verb être: est [t]en grand émoi, est [t]en revanche. In all other variable contexts, liaison is <lb/>absent: e.g. plural noun + adjective (e.g. circuits // habituels), avoir + past participle (ont // <lb/>eu), verb + complement (préparent // une journée chaude), and so forth. MM provides a good <lb/>example of the fact that adjective + noun is no longer an obligatory context of liaison: she <lb/>realized grand émoi without liaison but grand honneur, a more frequent combination, with <lb/>liaison. <lb/>This discrepancy has been much discussed in the PFC literature (e.g. Durand &amp; Lyche <lb/>2008, and Ch. 28). Overall, it can be said that MM realizes variable liaisons in a sparing <lb/>manner and limits herself to the frequent but restricted categorical contexts described in Ch. <lb/>28. <lb/> 4.4 Other features <lb/> The behaviour of the consonants in this extract does not require specific comments in an <lb/>overview such as this one. On the other hand, the reader should note quite a lot of reductions <lb/>and simplifications typical of fast informal speech. Thus, in the string si tu veux, the vowel /i/ <lb/>is dropped ([styvø]). The personal pronoun je can be reduced to [ʃ] through loss of the schwa <lb/>and devoicing of the [ʒ] by assimilation to a following voiceless consonant (a [t] in the <lb/>following example): faut que je trouve [fokʃtχuv] (l. 48). This example also illustrates the <lb/>fact that deletions of schwas can produce sequences of three consonants. Note that this [ʃ] can <lb/>absorb a following [s] as in je suis [ʃɥi] (l.11), je sais pas [ʃepa] (l. 48). Finally, the <lb/>pronunciation of expliquer as [ɛsplike] in sans les réexpliquer (l. 65) is often considered as a <lb/>feature of southern French but it is well attested in other northern varieties of French. <lb/></body> 
			
			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/> Armstrong, Nigel and Pooley, Tim (2010). Social and Linguistic Change in European <lb/>French. Basingstoke: Palgrave Macmillan. <lb/>Bec, Pierre (1963). La langue occitane. Paris: Presses Universitaires de France. <lb/>Blanche-Benveniste, Claire (2000) Approches de la langue parlée en français. Paris: <lb/>Ophrys. <lb/>Durand, Jacques &amp; Coquillon, Annelise (2010). Le français méridional : éléments de <lb/>synthèse.  In: S.  Detey, J. Durand, B. Laks &amp; C. Lyche (eds). Les variétés du français <lb/>parlé dans l&apos;espace francophone. Ressources pour l&apos;enseignement. Paris : Ophrys. pp. <lb/>185-197. <lb/>Durand, Jacques &amp; Lyche, Chantal (2008) French liaison in the light of corpus data. <lb/> Journal of French Language Studies. 18/1: 33-66. <lb/>Rossi-Gensane, Nathalie (2010). Oralité, syntaxe et discours. In S. Detey, J. Durand, <lb/>B. Laks &amp; Chantal Lyche (eds) Les variétés du français parlé dans l&apos;espace francophone. <lb/>Ressources pour l&apos;enseignement. Paris: Ophrys. <lb/>Rouayrenc, Catherine (2010). Le français oral. Vol. 1, Les composantes de la chaîne <lb/>parlée. Paris : Belin. <lb/>Walter, Henriette (1982). Enquête phonologique et variétés régionales du français. <lb/> Paris: PUF. </listBibl>

	</text>
</tei>
