<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_Hadbi_11990"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> COMPARISON BETWEEN SYSTEM DESIGN OPTIMIZATION <lb/>STRATEGIES FOR MORE ELECTRIC AIRCRAFT NETWORKS <lb/> Djamel Hadbi * , ** , Nicolas Retière * , Frederic Wurtz * , Xavier Roboam ** , Bruno Sareni ** <lb/> * Univ. Grenoble Alpes, G2Elab, F-38000 Grenoble, France, CNRS, G2Elab, F-38000 Grenoble, France <lb/>firstname.lastname@g2elab.grenoble-inp.fr <lb/> ** Université de Toulouse, LAPLACE, UMR CNRS-INPT-UPS, 2 rue Camichel, 31071 Toulouse, France <lb/>firstname.lastname@laplace.univ-tlse.fr <lb/> Abstract. Nowadays, embedded aircraft system contains electrical devices which must cooperate in safe and light <lb/>weight network. For designing such systems, different local strategies have been developed but no global <lb/>optimization has been performed so far. In this paper, we present and compare three strategies applied to the sizing <lb/>of a whole network of more electric aircraft: a simplified case study with only two components is considered to <lb/>illustrate methodological issues. The quality of the solution found from each method is compared, with regards to <lb/>the  &quot; cost of the collaborative approach &quot; and the volume of data generation. This comparison should provide system <lb/>designers an evaluation of the applicability of these methods according to the nature of the design problem. <lb/> Keywords: system design, integrated design, multilevel optimization, embedded electrical system. <lb/></front>

			<body> INTRODUCTION <lb/> Modern engineering products are becoming increasingly complex, particularly in industries such as <lb/>railway, aerospace and automotive [1], [2]. Conventionally, expertise and classical analysis methods, especially <lb/>those based on simulations are used, aided by optimization methods in some part of the process. Each sub-<lb/>system is designed separately by his manufacturer using his own model and process: this method is called <lb/> &quot; mechanistic approach &quot; . Another approach called  &quot; simultaneous design &quot; may be developed to integrate all the <lb/>components of a system into a single optimization. This extreme approach requires full cooperation for best <lb/>results [2]. Another diametrically opposite approach enables to design a system with a minimal collaboration. <lb/>This method called Extended Pareto Fronts was developed for the design of a railway application [3]. Industrial <lb/>design imposes other constraints, integration of a large scale multidisciplinary system, privacy issues and <lb/>decision level are fundamental criteria to elaborate feasible and efficient system design method [2]. <lb/> I. <lb/>DESIGN MODEL OF A SIMPLIFIED STUDIED CASE <lb/> Figure 1. Design of an actuator by Extended Pareto Front Method <lb/> Extended Pareto Front Method (EPFM) is based on the decomposition of a system in several devices, <lb/>each of them being previously optimized separately, only coupled by global variables (i. e. I, f, V in the figure <lb/>1). It intends to limit the communication of data between the suppliers. Only Extended Pareto Optimal Fronts <lb/>(space solution) are provided by suppliers to the system designer. First, a necessary condition has to be checked: <lb/>in a suitable decomposition, the system objective function has to be calculated by means of the objective <lb/>functions of sub-problems. If so, a classification of all problem variables allows identifying global variables that <lb/>describe couplings on the system. In the above example, there are N=3 couplings variables, i.e. current (I), <lb/>frequency (f) and voltage (V) of the bus, completed by O=2 objective functions for weight (W) and device <lb/>efficiency (K). So a N+O-dimension solution space is built for each component of the system. Gathering the <lb/>Extended Pareto Fronts of all amenities, the system manufacturer shall be able to make tradeoffs within the sets <lb/>of solutions in order to obtain the best solution at the system level. Of course, not any combination of equipment <lb/>is possible; the manufacturer must be careful of the consistency of coupling variables that ensure the <lb/>compatibility of the chosen amenities. <lb/> II. <lb/> DESIGN OF A SIMPLIFIED EMBEDDED ELECTRIC NETWORK <lb/> Figure 2. An example of a simplified embedded electric network <lb/> Embedded electric networks contain a high number of sources and loads connected to several buses: the <lb/>issue is then to analyze applicability of optimization methods to this class of complex system. In our study, <lb/>related to the development of strategies for system design, we initially relied on a  &quot; simplified &quot;  network, which is <lb/>voluntary limited to a single load in order to establish and compare optimization methods. It consists of a single <lb/>generating channel, connected with a unique non-linear load. This channel includes a generator, a rectifier and an <lb/>output filter. The load comprises an actuator, an inverter and an input filter. We investigate the design of this <lb/>channel (especially the filtering device sizing) using the three approaches previously presented: the optimization <lb/>goal is to minimize the whole network weight in compliance with quality standards; (current and voltage <lb/>harmonics are limited to a maximum threshold in a frequency band). Let us note that this case study consists of a <lb/>single objective optimization for which the previous method (EPFM) of course remains applicable. <lb/> III. <lb/>QUALITATIVE COMPARISON OF RESULTS <lb/> As shown in the figure 2 (left part), the values of the objective function obtained by two collaborative <lb/>methods, the simultaneous design approach and Extended Pareto Front Method are better than the value of the <lb/>objective function obtained with a conventional method ( &quot; mechanistic approach &quot; ) based on expertise and <lb/>classical analysis methods. <lb/>Collaboration level and calculation cost are conflicting characteristics as illustrated of the right part of <lb/>figure 2: higher is the collaboration level, lower the necessary computational cost to reach the perfect solution. <lb/>The mapping of the space solution of a sub-problem grows exponentially with the number of coupling variables <lb/>(if there are P values of M input global variable, P M optimizations are done). High level of collaboration means <lb/>that subsystem manufacturers need to share and communicate their models for the design process. So it&apos;s easy <lb/> for the system integrator to improve the whole system generating a small amount of data. On the other side, a <lb/>low level of collaboration means that each subsystem designer keeps its design secret, so that he must provide <lb/>more data to aircraft manufacturer to enable him finding the optimal combination of subsystems. <lb/>. <lb/> Figure 3. Comparison of optimization approaches in terms of objective function and costs (collaboration vs <lb/>computation cost) <lb/> CONCLUSION <lb/> Through our work, we managed to check out conditions are necessary to elaborate a design strategy for <lb/>complex system: collaboration and data generation. Thanks to this, we have proposed a multilevel collaborative <lb/>design strategy while limiting the data exchanged by the designer of system components which is a requirement <lb/>for industrial systems such as embedded networks. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> REFERENCES <lb/> [1] F. Moussouni-Messad,  &quot; Multi-level and multi-objective design optimization tools for handling complex systems &quot; , these (PHD) de <lb/>l&apos;Ecole Centrale de Lille 2009. <lb/> [2] X. Roboam &amp; al, &quot; Integrated design by optimization of electrical energy systems&apos;&apos;, edited by ISTE Wiley, 2012, ISBN 978-1-84821-<lb/> 389-0. <lb/>[3] H. Nguyen-Huu , N. Retière, F. Wutz, &quot; A new approach for building the global Pareto border of an electromagnetic system by using <lb/> the Pareto borders of each sub-component of the system &quot; , IEEE-CEFC 2008 (International Conference on Electromagnetic Field <lb/>Computation), ID: OC1-4 in proceeding of the conference. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<body>0,6 <lb/> 0,8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1,2 <lb/> W <lb/> tot (kg) <lb/> Simultaneous desigh aproach <lb/>Extended Pareto Front Method <lb/>Mechanistic approach <lb/> ma comb atio of subsy <lb/> Collaboration level <lb/>Optimization cost <lb/> Simultaneous design approach <lb/>E. P. F. M. <lb/>Mechanistic <lb/>Approach <lb/>High <lb/>Medium <lb/>Minimal <lb/>1 2 <lb/>2 x P M</body> 

	</text>
</tei>
