<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_HCII07-LongSteph"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Computer-supported creativity: <lb/>Evaluation of a tabletop mind-map application <lb/> Stéphanie Buisine 1 , Guillaume Besacier 2 , Marianne Najm 1 , <lb/>Améziane Aoussat 1 , and Frédéric Vernier 2 <lb/> 1 <lb/> ENSAM-LCPI, 151 boulevard de l Hôpital, 75013 Paris, FRANCE <lb/>Corresponding author: stephanie.buisine@paris.ensam.fr <lb/> 2 <lb/>  LIMSI-CNRS, BP 133, 91403 Orsay Cedex, FRANCE <lb/> Abstract. The aim of this study is to investigate the usability and usefulness of <lb/>interactive tabletop technologies to support group creativity. We implemented a <lb/>tabletop interface enabling groups of 4 participants to build mind-maps (a tool <lb/>for associative thinking). With 24 users in a within-group design, we compared <lb/>its use to traditional paper-and-pencil mind-mapping sessions. The results <lb/>showed no difference in idea production, but the tabletop condition <lb/>significantly improved both subjective and collaborative dimensions, especially <lb/>by leading to better-balanced contributions from the group members. <lb/> Keywords: Creativity, Mind-map, Tabletop device. <lb/> </front>
			
			<body>1 Creativity in industrial applications <lb/> Creativity is a high-level cognitive process which has given rise to researches in <lb/>various fields such as Psychology [4, 16], Engineering [7, 9] or Human-Computer <lb/>Interaction [3, 6, 14, 15]. Creativity applies to artistic work (e.g. fine arts, literature, <lb/>architecture, music), educative domain (e.g. early-learning and playing activities), <lb/>scientific skills (e.g. problem resolution, discoveries, epistemological breakthroughs), <lb/>and industrial applications (e.g. creation of product functions, stylistic design of <lb/>artifacts). <lb/>In this paper we consider creativity in industrial applications, for example when <lb/>some people design a product with new innovative functions (e.g. a mobile phone <lb/>including a positioning system) or search some applications to a new technology (e.g. <lb/>portable MP3 players). Understanding and supporting this kind of creativity is not <lb/>only an interesting research challenge: it also bears a strong potential for enhancing <lb/>industrial innovation and market opportunities. <lb/> 2 Enhancing creativity <lb/> To improve creativity, a wide-spread practice in companies is the group <lb/>brainstorming. Although creativity fundamentally remains an individual capacity, it <lb/> proves to be influenced by the subject s environment: in this respect, collective <lb/>creativity phenomena are often observed when group emulation improves the <lb/>expression of onee s own creative potential. This is especially true for industrial <lb/>creativity which can benefit from multiple, or even multidisciplinary viewpoints. <lb/>To further improve these collective creativity sessions, methodological toolkits [7, <lb/>9] have been formalized to structure the reflection and manage groups dynamics. <lb/>Consulting services specialized in creative problem solving also appeared to help <lb/>companies conduct creativity sessions and apply these methodologies. <lb/>Moreover, computer applications have been developed to support industrial <lb/>creativity 1 . According to Shneiderman [14], the existing software solutions can be <lb/>categorized into three approaches: inspirational tools (e.g. favoring visualization, free <lb/>association, or sources of inspiration), structural tools (e.g. databases, simulations, <lb/>methodical techniques of reasoning), and situational tools (e.g. based on the social <lb/>context, enabling peer-consultation, or dissemination). Lubart [8] adopted a <lb/>classification grounded on the role played by the computer in the creative process: <lb/>systems assisting the user in the management of creative projects (computer as <lb/>nanny), those supporting communication and collaboration within a team (computer <lb/>as pen-pal), systems implementing creativity enhancement techniques (computer as <lb/>coach) and those contributing to the idea production (computer as colleague). <lb/>In this context, our goal is to investigate the capacity of a tabletop computer (as a <lb/>physical device and as a digital interface) to support collaborative creativity related to <lb/>industrial issues. <lb/> 3 Tabletop systems <lb/> Fig. 1. Example of a tabletop system using MERL DiamondTouch device [5]. <lb/> Tabletop systems (see Fig. 1) are multi-user horizontal interfaces for interactive <lb/>shared displays. They implement around-the-table interaction metaphors allowing co-<lb/>located collaboration and face-to-face conversation in a social setting [12, 13]. <lb/>

			<note place="footnote"> 1 <lb/> For example Goldfire Innovator (www.invention-machine.com) or ThoughtOffice <lb/>(www.ideacenter.com). <lb/></note>

			Tabletop systems are used in various application contexts such as games, photo <lb/>browsing, map exploration, planning tasks, classification tasks, interactive exhibit <lb/>medium for museums, drawing, etc. [11]. Such systems being likely to favor <lb/>collaboration by providing around-the-table visualization facilities, they could be <lb/>thought of for supporting creativity sessions: in this respect they would fall into both <lb/>inspirational and situational creativity tools [14] or play pen-pal and coach roles [8] in <lb/>the creative process. Indeed, some tabletop systems were previously considered for <lb/>supporting creativity [17, 18] but their actual benefits were not experimentally <lb/>measured. To assess the usability and usefulness of tabletops in the context of <lb/>creativity sessions, we believe that it is necessary to compare their use with a control <lb/>condition relying on traditional paper-and-pencil tools. In the following section, we <lb/>introduce a creativity application we have developed for tabletop display in order to <lb/>conduct such an experiment. <lb/> 4 Our tabletop mind-map application <lb/> 4.1 Mind-maps as a collective creativity tool <lb/> Fig. 2. Example mind-map. <lb/> In general, creativity methodological framework [7] support a two-step process: first, <lb/>diverging by producing a vast number of ideas, then converging by selecting a few of <lb/>them to be further developed. Mind-maps [2] are used in the diverging step. The <lb/>mind-map principle is based on associative logics and is used for defining the <lb/>problem to address. The field to explore is written in a central box and the participants <lb/>express their free associations to this concept. Those ideas are written in new boxes <lb/>placed as a crown around the central concept (see Fig. 2). A second association level <lb/>is then built from the primary ideas, etc. Because the second level of association is not <lb/>directly related to the initial problem, new-original research directions can appear and <lb/>the realms of possibility grow. Mind-mapping can be performed individually or in a <lb/>group session. In the latter case, the session has to be managed by an animator whose <lb/> role is to coordinate speech turns and ensure that the group agrees on every idea. <lb/>Many software solutions 2 for desktop computers have been developed to support <lb/>mind-mapping, but none is adapted to tabletop interaction. This is why we <lb/>implemented our own tool. <lb/> 4.2 Implementation <lb/> Fig. 3. Example mind-map created with our tabletop application. <lb/> Implementation of Tabletop Mind-Maps (TMM, see Fig. 3) was conducted with the <lb/>DiamondSpin toolkit [13]. TMM was also based on our previous experience with a <lb/>hierarchy view, namely the Personal Digital Historian (PDH) application [12], which <lb/>is dedicated to organizing family pictures according to a hierarchy of people and <lb/>concepts present in the pictures. <lb/>A TMM session starts with a root label forced to be in center. The root displays the <lb/>field to explore, which is important to keep in mind, so we duplicated the label along <lb/>a symmetry axis to have it more readable from every point of view around the table. <lb/>The mind-map is then built top-down when users create new nodes with double-<lb/>tap-and-drop interaction. This concatenation of double-tap and drag-and-drop <lb/>appeared to be natural and easy to perform with direct manipulation. The double-tap <lb/>creates a new node in the sub-hierarchy of the tapped node, while the drag-and-drop <lb/>specifies the new node position. The background color of the node represents its level <lb/>in the hierarchy (green for 1 st level, blue for 2 nd level ). <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">2 <lb/> A complete list of mind-mapping software is available at www.mind-mapping.org, the market <lb/>leader being MindManager (www.mindjet.com). <lb/></note> 
			
			TMM nodes are editable. The choice of a label being a collaborative activity in <lb/>mind-mapping, this aspect had to be reproduced in TMM: we chose to allow text <lb/>input only from a single source, i.e. a physical wireless keyboard with a particular <lb/>focus management. Indeed, in a tabletop system there can be more than one focused <lb/>or selected element, as the users interact seamlessly together or in parallel. We made <lb/>the keyboard focus persistent until the Enter key is pressed. While the text is being <lb/>keyed, users can create new nodes or select other ones (e.g. to check for possible <lb/>redundant nodee s name) without interfering with the edition. The font color of the <lb/>node represents the user who created it. <lb/>Nodes of the hierarchy are freely relocatable on the table. The nodes of a sub-<lb/>hierarchy will also follow their parent node when the latter is moved on. The <lb/>orientation of the nodes is adjusted online while they are being moved on so that the <lb/>text is always oriented outwards to be readable by the nearest user. Moreover, users <lb/>can rotate the whole display if they want to change the view without changing the <lb/>arrangement of the hierarchy. <lb/>Finally, we introduced a means of creating a temporary view of a sub-hierarchy. A <lb/>given node becomes the new central root, all the items outside of its sub-hierarchy <lb/>being temporarily hidden. <lb/> 5 Experimental study <lb/> This experiment was designed to evaluate the use of a tabletop interactive application <lb/>for mind-mapping by comparing it with a control paper-and-pencil condition. <lb/> 5.1 Method <lb/>Participants. 6 groups of 4 participants took part in the experiment. Each group <lb/>included students, professors and/or employees. We excluded groups only composed <lb/>of students in order to avoid too much familiarity among participants and simulate <lb/>more realistic conditions of creativity sessions. Overall, userss age ranged from 20 to <lb/>52 years old (mean = 28.7; SD = 7.9) and each group was composed of 2 male and 2 <lb/>female participants. <lb/> Materials. For the tabletop condition, we used MERL DiamondTouch [5]: the <lb/>participants were seated around the table with the experimenter sitting aside on a <lb/>highchair. The participants interacted on TMM display with finger-input to create, <lb/>edit or move the mind-map items. The experimenter typed down the content of the <lb/>nodes using the wireless keyboard. <lb/>In the control condition the participants were seated in front of a paperboard with <lb/>the experimenter standing beside it. The experimenter used a marker pen to build the <lb/>mind-map and write down its content according to the participants indications. <lb/> Procedure. Each group had to build 2 mind-maps on different topics: 1 in the <lb/>tabletop condition and 1 in the control condition. The topics were related to the <lb/> sectors of Media and Leisure : such topics simulate potential reflection for e.g. <lb/>companies trying to find a way to diversify, searching an application for a new <lb/>technology or trying to find new markets. These 2 topics were chosen so as to be <lb/>equivalent in level of abstraction and width of scope. The order of conditions and the <lb/>assignment of topics were counterbalanced across the whole sample (see Table 1). <lb/> Table 1. Counterbalancement of conditions: For each group (A to F), this table defines the <lb/>order of the 2 conditions (Tabletop and Control) and the topic addressed in each case (Media <lb/>and Leisure sectors). <lb/>Group ID <lb/>First mind-map <lb/>Second mind-map <lb/>A <lb/>Tabletop: Media <lb/> C o n t r o l : Leisure <lb/> B <lb/>Tabletop: Leisure <lb/> C o n t r o l : Media <lb/> C <lb/>Tabletop: Media <lb/> C o n t r o l : Leisure <lb/> D <lb/>Control: Media <lb/> T a b l e t o p : Leisure <lb/> E <lb/>Control: Leisure <lb/> Tabletop: Media <lb/> F <lb/>Control: Media <lb/> T a b l e t o p : Leisure <lb/> To conduct the session, the experimenter first asks the general question What <lb/>does leisure (resp. media) make you think of? The participants freely suggest some <lb/>ideas and concepts associated to the target sector, and the experimenter writes down <lb/>the ideas the group agrees on. Once the first level of the mind-map is completed, the <lb/>same process is repeated for the second level by focusing on first-level ideas one by <lb/>one (( What does xxx make you think of? ). In this experiment the mind-maps were <lb/>limited to 2 levels and the time to build them to 10 minutes. The differences between <lb/>tabletop and control conditions in building the mind-maps are summarized in Table 2. <lb/> Table 2. Differences between tabletop and control conditions in the process of mind-mapping. <lb/>Factor <lb/>Description <lb/>Spatial position of participants <lb/>Around the table vs. in front of the paperboard <lb/>Creation of new boxes <lb/>By the participants in the tabletop condition vs. by the <lb/>experimenter in the control condition <lb/>Modification / suppression of a <lb/>box <lb/>Allowed in tabletop but not in control condition <lb/>Spatial arrangement of items <lb/>Online modifications allowed in tabletop but not in control <lb/>condition <lb/>Rotation of the mind-map <lb/>Allowed in tabletop but not in control condition <lb/>Focus on a first-level idea <lb/>Explicit in tabletop (making the rest of the mind-map <lb/>disappear) vs. implicit in control condition (whole map <lb/>always displayed) <lb/> The tabletop condition was preceded by a familiarization phase for demonstrating <lb/>the tablee s functionalities to the participants. Both tabletop and control conditions <lb/>were then video-recorded. At the end of the experiment, users had to fill in a <lb/>questionnaire to assess the following dimensions: efficiency, usability, usefulness of <lb/>the tabletop system, satisfaction, and comparison with the control condition. Users <lb/>had to quantify their impressions on 7-point scales and were particularly prompted to <lb/> complete with free qualitative comments. The whole experiment lasted about 1 hour <lb/>for each group. <lb/> 5.2 Data analysis <lb/> Inferential analyses were performed by means of ANOVAs using SPSS software. <lb/>Three dimensions were investigated: the performance in mind-mapping, the <lb/>subjective experience of users, and the collaborative behaviors. <lb/> Performance. We chose to assess the performance dimension from the <lb/>exhaustiveness of the outcome. As we lack absolute standards to evaluate a mind-map <lb/>in itself, we decided to aggregate the mind-maps of the 6 groups for the same topic <lb/>and take this as a reference to be compared to each mind-map. We rated the <lb/>exhaustiveness of the mind-maps by considering both the total number of ideas and <lb/>the number of categories of ideas in comparison to the reference. <lb/> Subjective experience. This dimension was computed from the questionnaire ratings. <lb/>The analysis processed on these data also accounted for users gender and category <lb/>(student, professor or employee). <lb/> Collaboration. The participantss collaborative behaviors were annotated from the <lb/>video-recordings of the sessions. We collected the following behaviors: assertions <lb/>(e.g. giving an idea), information requests, action requests, answers to questions, <lb/>expression of opinions, communicative gestures related to the task, and off-task talks. <lb/>The communicative gestures variable includes e.g. pointing to the map, interrupting <lb/>s.o. or requesting the speech turn by a gesture, which can be observed in both <lb/>conditions. In the tabletop condition, it also includes gesture-inputs on the table, with <lb/>the exclusion of creation / edition / suppression actions which we did not consider as <lb/>communicative gestures. <lb/>We first analyzed the raw behavioral data for each participant, and then we <lb/>converted them into percentages in order to assess the respective contribution of each <lb/>participant in the group. Such an index finally enabled us to compute the difference <lb/>between the actual collaboration pattern of each group and a theoretical perfectly-<lb/>balanced pattern (each one of the 4 participants would contribute 25%). <lb/> 5.3 Results <lb/>Performance. No significant difference appeared between tabletop and control <lb/>conditions on our index of exhaustiveness of mind-maps (F(1/5) = 0.92, NS). <lb/> Subjective experience. There was no significant effect of the condition (tabletop vs. <lb/>control) on easiness (F(1/20) &lt; 0.1, NS) and efficiency (F(1/20) = 1.02, NS) of mind-<lb/>map building. However, the tabletop was rated as significantly more pleasant to use <lb/>(F(1/20) = 10.43, p = 0.004), enabling a more pleasant communication between <lb/> participants (F(1/20) = 5.01, p = 0.037), more efficient group work (F(1/20) = 3.56, <lb/>p = 0.074) and more pleasant group work (F(1/20) = 4.23, p = 0.053) see Fig. 4. <lb/>Users gender and category had no influence on any of the previous results. <lb/> 1 <lb/> 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/> Pleasantness <lb/>Communication <lb/>pleasantness <lb/>Group efficiency <lb/>Group <lb/>pleasantness <lb/>Subhective ratings <lb/> Tabletop <lb/>Control <lb/> Fig. 4. Subjective ratings of participants for the tabletop and control conditions. <lb/> Collaboration. The variables expression of opinionn and off-task talkk comprised <lb/>too many missing values to be analyzed. The other raw behavioral data showed no <lb/>significant difference in the absolute number of any of the variables, except for the <lb/>communicative gestures category: tabletop led to more communicative gestures than <lb/>control condition (F(1/22) = 3.59, p = 0.071). <lb/> Tabletop condition <lb/>Control condition <lb/>Tabletop condition <lb/>Control condition <lb/> Fig. 5. Collaboration patterns in tabletop (left) and control (right) conditions: this graph <lb/>represents the average contribution of the 4 participants ranked on a leader / follower scale. <lb/>This figure illustrates that the contributions of the participants were significantly better <lb/>balanced in the tabletop condition (p = 0.013). <lb/> The analysis of collaboration patterns showed that participants verbal <lb/>contributions (sum of all behaviors without communicative gestures) were <lb/>significantly better balanced in tabletop than in control condition (F(1/22) = 7.35, <lb/>p = 0.013) i.e. they were significantly closer to the theoretical perfectly-balanced <lb/>pattern. Fig. 5 presents the average collaboration patterns in both conditions: to obtain <lb/> this figure, we ranked the participants of each group from the one who contributed the <lb/>most (the leader) to the one who contributed the least (the follower) and averaged the <lb/>data for the 6 groups. The same result applies for communicative gestures: the <lb/>gestural contributions were significantly better balanced in tabletop than in control <lb/>condition (F(1/22) = 8.94, p = 0.007). <lb/> 6 Conclusion and future work <lb/> The tabletop condition significantly improved both subjective and collaborative <lb/>dimensions of mind-mapping. First of all, the participants found that the tabletop <lb/>system was more pleasant to use, improved group communication and collaboration <lb/>efficiency. These effects on userss impressions could be explained e.g. by the spatial <lb/>position of participants favoring social interaction, the attraction of a new technology, <lb/>and/or the more active involvement of participants in this condition. <lb/>Moreover, the behavioral analysis showed that the tabletop system enabled a better <lb/>collaboration: while the control condition showed strong leaders and followers, in the <lb/>tabletop condition the participants collaborated in a better-balanced way. Some <lb/>benefits of a tabletop system compared to a wall display or a desktop computer were <lb/>previously observed by Rogers and Lindley [10] but their setting was noticeably <lb/>different from ours: their tabletop device supported only single-touch interaction <lb/>(with a pen) and a single viewpoint (so that the participants had to sit side by side and <lb/>not around the table). They observed more interaction and role changing (swapping <lb/>the possession of the input device) in the tabletop condition: it proved easier and more <lb/>natural to change roles because of the use of a direct input device (a pen has to be <lb/>placed directly on the display whereas a mouse controls the pointer from a distance) <lb/>and because of the physical proximity of the participants to this input device (higher <lb/>in the tabletop than in the wall display condition). In our experiment the collaborative <lb/>benefits cannot be explained by any of these reasons because all 4 participants had the <lb/>same role and interaction capacity. We could tentatively explain our results by the <lb/>spatial position of people around the table, which can facilitate idea exchange, or by <lb/>the attraction of a new technology, which could prompt the participants to interact <lb/>with the tabletop interface and thus to give new ideas. The second hypothesis is less <lb/>likely because it may have resulted in higher performance in idea generation. <lb/>Therefore we hypothesize that the collaborative benefits we observed come from the <lb/>around-the-table placement of people. This assumption will be tested with a new <lb/>control condition where the participants will have to build a paper-and-pencil mind-<lb/>map around a table. This new experiment will also complete the data about the <lb/>subjective preferences expressed in the present study. <lb/>Finally, despite all the advantages of our tabletop application (subjective <lb/>engagement, better collaboration, active involvement of users, focus on first-level <lb/>ideas, flexibility of the mind-map displayy ), the experimental results showed no <lb/>significant difference in the quality of outcomes between tabletop and control <lb/>conditions. In the next steps of the project, we intend to focus more deeply on the <lb/>performance dimension and search a way to improve it. We should develop a more <lb/>accurate analysis of mind-map process and outcome to better understand the idea <lb/> production mechanism. We also plan to test the influence of innovative interaction <lb/>styles (see e.g. the paper metaphor [1]) on idea production and organization. <lb/>The global experimental process followed in this study (comparison of tabletop <lb/>and traditional paper-and-pencil condition, variables collected ) is currently being <lb/>applied to other creativity tools such as brainstorming on sticky notes in order to <lb/>investigate whether the present results apply to other situations of group creativity. <lb/> 
			
		</body>

		<back>
			
			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/> This study was supported by the ANR-RNTL DigiTable project (www.digitable.fr). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Besacier, G., Rey, G., Najm, M., Buisine, S., Vernier, F.: Paper metaphor for tabletop <lb/>interaction design. HCII&apos;07 Human Computer Interaction International, Lecture Notes in <lb/>Computer Science, Springer (2007). <lb/>2. Buzan, T.: The Mind Map Book. Penguin Books (1991). <lb/>3. Candy, L., Hori, K.: The digital muse: HCI in support of creativity. Interactions, 10, (2003) <lb/>44-54. <lb/>4. Csikszentmihalyi, M.: Creativity: Flow and the psychology of discovery and invention. <lb/>Harper Perennial, New York (1996). <lb/>5. Dietz, P.H., Leigh, D.: DiamondTouch: A multi-user touch technology. UIST&apos;01 <lb/>International Conference on User Interface Software and Technology, ACM Press (2001) <lb/>219-226. <lb/>6. Farooq, U.: Eureka! Past, present, and future of creativity research in HCI. ACM <lb/>Crossroads, 12, (2005) 6-11. <lb/>7. Isaksen, S.G., Dorval, K.B., Treffinger, D.J.: Creative approaches to problem solving: A <lb/>framework for change. Kendall Hunt (2000). <lb/>8. Lubart, T.: How can computers be partners in the creative process. International Journal of <lb/>Human-Computer Studies, 63, (2005) 365-369. <lb/>9. Osborn, A.F.: Applied Imagination. Principles and procedures of creative problem-solving. <lb/>Charles Scribner&apos;s Sons (1953). <lb/>10. Rogers, Y., Lindley, S.: Collaborating around vertical and horizontal large interactive <lb/>displays: Which way is best? Interacting with Computers, 16, (2004) 1133-1152. <lb/>11. Scott, S.D., Carpendale, S. (Eds.): Interacting with digital tabletops. Special issue of IEEE <lb/>Computer Graphics and Applications, vol. 26 (2006). <lb/>12. Shen, C., Lesh, N., Vernier, F.: Personal Digital Historian: Story sharing around the table. <lb/>Interactions, 10, (2003) 15-22. <lb/>13. Shen, C., Vernier, F., Forlines, C., Ringel, M.: DiamondSpin: An extensible toolkit for <lb/>around-the-table interaction. CHI&apos;04 International Conference on Human Factors in <lb/>Computing Systems, ACM Press (2004) 167-174. <lb/>14. Shneiderman, B.: Creating creativity: User interfaces for supporting innovation. ACM <lb/>Transactions On Computer-Human Interaction (TOCHI), 7, (2000) 114 -138. <lb/>15. Shneiderman, B., Fischer, G., Czerwinski, M., Resnick, M., Myers, B.: Creativity support <lb/>tools: Report from a U.S. National Science Foundation sponsored workshop. International <lb/>Journal of Human-Computer Interaction, 20, (2006) 61-77. <lb/>16. Sternberg, R.J.: Handbook of Creativity. Cambridge University Press (1998). <lb/>17. Streitz, N.A., Geißler, J., Holmer, T., Konomi, S.: I-LAND, an interactive landscape for <lb/>creativity and innovation. CHI 99 International Conference on Human Factors in <lb/>Computing Systems, ACM Press (1999) 120-127. <lb/>18. Warr, A., OO Neill, E.: Public Social Private Design (PSPD). CHI 06 International <lb/>Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems, ACM Press (2006) 1499-1504. </listBibl>

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
