<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Iran J Parasitol: Vol. 13, No. 4, Oct-Dec 2018, pp.648-654 <lb/> 648 <lb/> Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/> Short Communication <lb/>The Taxonomic Position and Phylogenetic Relationship between <lb/>Digramma interrupta and Ligula intestinalis Based on <lb/>Morphological and Molecular Diagnosis <lb/>Emad AHMADIARA 1 , *Seyed Hossein HOSSEINI 1 , Fatemeh JALOUSIAN 1 , Hossein Ali <lb/>EBRAHIMZADEH MOUSAVI 2 <lb/> 1. Dept. of Parasitology, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran <lb/>2. Dept. of Aquatic Animal Health, School of Veterinary Medicine, University of Tehran, Tehran, Iran <lb/>Received <lb/>10 Oct 2017 <lb/>Accepted 04 Feb 2018 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: The position of Digramma interrupta remains disputable as it was <lb/>raised by Cholodkovsky from Ligula alternans. This study aimed to survey the evolu-<lb/>tionary relationships and the taxonomic position of D. interrupta and L. intestinalis. It <lb/>also intended to support or reject the validity of D. interrupt as an independent ge-<lb/>nus and its correlation with L. intestinalis on the basis of their morphological charac-<lb/>teristics and a study on molecular data. <lb/>Methods: Overall, 1301 fish varieties, including 883 Alburnoides bipunctatus and 418 <lb/>Abramis brama, were collected from north and north-western parts of Iran. A. <lb/>bipunctatus samples were obtained from fresh water sources of the Maragheh dam <lb/>(northwest) and the Ramesar Lake (north). Moreover, samples of A. brama were <lb/>captured from the Aras Dam (northwest) and the Bandar-e-Anzali lagoon (north). <lb/>PCR was used to generate a fragment spanning two independent ITS-inclusive <lb/>parts: ITS1-5.8S and ITS2 with two pairs of primers. <lb/>Results: Nucleotide variation between L. intestinalis and D. interrupta samples <lb/>amounts to about 3% to 7%. Between samples of L. intestinalis and GenBank data, <lb/>and also between D. interrupta specimens and GenBank data, the diversity was seen <lb/>for about 1% to 3%. Moreover, about 1% to 4% nucleotide variation was seen only <lb/>in L. intestinalis samples caught from the same host, which could be supplementary <lb/>to the presence of a species and/or strains in this genus. <lb/>Conclusion: Maybe D. interrupta was just a rare diplogonadic form of the Ligula <lb/>species, not a different genus and not synonymous with the Ligula genus, but only <lb/>another species of the Ligula genus. <lb/>Keywords: <lb/> Ligula intestinalis, <lb/>Digramma interrupta, <lb/>Morphology, <lb/>Molecular diagnosis, <lb/>Iran <lb/> * Correspondence <lb/>Email: <lb/>hhoseini@ut.ac.ir <lb/>Iranian Society of Parasitology <lb/>http://isp.tums.ac.ir <lb/>Iran J Parasitol <lb/>Open access Journal at <lb/>http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/>Tehran University of Medical <lb/>Sciences Publication <lb/>http://tums.ac.ir <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Ahmadiara et al.: The Taxonomic Position and Phylogenetic Relationship between … <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<page>649 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>embers of diphyllobothridae are <lb/>the most significant cestoda that <lb/>infect fish as the intermediated <lb/>host in the plerocercoid phase (1). This family <lb/>has significant genera like Ligula intestinalis, and <lb/>Digramma interrupta is distributed all around the <lb/>world. <lb/>The position of D. interrupta in <lb/>diphyllobothridae family remains disputable <lb/>since it was raised by Cholodkovsky from L. <lb/>alternans. Morphological differences, with one <lb/>set of reproductive organs in L. intestinalis and <lb/>two sets of this in D. interrupta, present the <lb/>most important differences between them. <lb/>However, the morphological features are not <lb/>completely reliable to distinguish genus from <lb/>each other (2). <lb/>One of the aims of this study was support or <lb/>reject the validity of D. interrupta and its corre-<lb/>lation with L. intestinalis on the basis of mor-<lb/>phological characteristics and a study of mo-<lb/>lecular data based on entire internal tran-<lb/>scribed spacer of the ribosomal DNA (ITS <lb/>rDNA) that contains ITS1-5.8S and ITS2. In <lb/>addition, this study intends to assess the ge-<lb/>netic diversity of L. intestinalis or D. interrupta <lb/>from different hosts and geographical regions. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Samples collection <lb/>Overall, 1301 fish varieties, including 883 <lb/>Alburnoides bipunctatus (A. bipunctatus) and 418 <lb/>Abramis brama (A. brama), were collected from <lb/>north and north-western parts of Iran. A. <lb/>bipunctatus samples were obtained from fresh <lb/>water sources of the Maragheh dam (north-<lb/>west) and the Ramesar Lake (north). Moreo-<lb/>ver, samples of A. brama were captured from <lb/>the Aras Dam (northwest) and the Bandar-e-<lb/>Anzali lagoon (north) (Fig. 1). The samples <lb/>were put into ice boxes and immediately trans-<lb/>ferred to the laboratory; they were isolated <lb/>from body cavities of infectious fish and pre-<lb/>served either by being placed in 96% ethanol <lb/>or being stored at -20 °C for morphological <lb/>and molecular analysis. <lb/>Morphological characterizations <lb/>The samples&apos; terminal segments were <lb/>stained with aceto-carmine and mounted with <lb/>the Canada balsam. The specimens were iden-<lb/>tified as L. intestinalis and D. interrupta by using <lb/>characters that are suitable for species identifi-<lb/>cation according to taxonomic keys (3). <lb/>Fig. 1: Localities in Iran where specimens of Ligula intestinalis and Digramma interrupta were collected <lb/>The morphological characterization of <lb/>plerocercoid was completed by observing <lb/>them under a light microscope equipped with <lb/>the camera lucida. Then, for having an accu-<lb/>M <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Iran J Parasitol: Vol. 13, No. 4, Oct-Dec 2018, pp.648-654 <lb/></note>

			<page>650 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<body>rate survey, we draw the schematic character-<lb/>istics of the specimens, and transferred them <lb/>onto talk paper and scanned for more accurate <lb/>analysis (Figs. 2-5). <lb/>Fig. 2: Cross section of Digramma interrupta with two sets of reproductive organs <lb/>Fig. 3: Cross section of Ligula intestinalis with one set of reproductive organ <lb/>Fig. 4: Longitudinal sections of Digramma interrupta with two rows of reproductive organ <lb/>Fig. 5: Longitudinal sections of Ligula intestinalis with one row of reproductive organ <lb/>DNA extraction <lb/>Deoxyribonucleic acid (DNA) was extracted <lb/>by using a DNA isolation kit (Qiagen, Ger-<lb/>many) according to the manufacturer&apos;s in-<lb/>structions. <lb/>PCR amplification <lb/>PCR was used to generate a fragment span-<lb/>ning two ITS-inclusive independent parts, <lb/>namely ITS1-5.8S and ITS2 with two pairs of <lb/>specific primers. These primers were designed <lb/>by Vector NTI11. The first for the 891bp <lb/>fragment comprised ITS1-5.8S, and second <lb/>for the 421bp sequence-long inclusive ITS2 <lb/>locus (Table 1). The PCR product was puri-<lb/>fied by using the PCR purification kit (Qiagen, <lb/>Germany). The sequencing was performed <lb/>from both sites of each PCR products by <lb/>Kawsar Biotech Company in Iran on the basis <lb/>of the Sanger method (1977). The sequences <lb/>were analyzed by using the Chromas version <lb/>1.3 software and CLC Main Workbench 5, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ahmadiara et al.: The Taxonomic Position and Phylogenetic Relationship between … <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<page>651 <lb/></page>

			<body>and they were compared with samples regis-<lb/>tered in GenBank by using the &apos;Basic Local <lb/>Alignment Search Tool&apos; (BLAST) program. <lb/>The phylogenetic tree was designed by MEGA <lb/>version 5.0 software. <lb/>Results <lb/>All isolates morphologically derived from A. <lb/>bipunctatus were distinguished from L. <lb/>intestinalis, and all specimens of A. brama were <lb/>determined to be D. interrupta. From 883 spec-<lb/>imens of A. bipunctatus and 418 collected sam-<lb/>ples of A. brama, 558 (63.19%) and 67 fishes <lb/>(16%) were infected, respectively (Table 2). <lb/>After blast, the data, according to the ITS <lb/>locus, 13 isolates were determined from D. <lb/>interrupta and 10 samples were determined L. <lb/>intestinalis. All the molecular results were coor-<lb/>dinated with the morphological outcome. <lb/>Table 1: Primer 1 (DigIr F 5&apos; &amp; DigIr R 5&apos;) for <lb/>891bp fragment consist of ITS1, 5.8S and ITS2; <lb/>Primer 2 (Ligir2F 5&apos;&amp; Ligir2R 5&apos;) for 421bp se-<lb/>quence long include ITS2 locus <lb/>Primer 1, product size: 890bp <lb/>DigIr F 5&apos; -CACGTTCCGTCTA TATGCGC-3&apos; <lb/>DigIr R 5&apos;-GGCAGCATCTCGCTTAAATG -3&apos; <lb/>Primer 2, product size:421bp <lb/>Ligir2F 5&apos; -TGGCGGGAAAACTCGGGCTT-3&apos; <lb/>Ligir2R 5&apos; -GCCGCCAACCACCAACAG -3&apos; <lb/>All 13 D. interrupta samples were registered in <lb/>the GenBank under accession numbers <lb/>KC900982-KC900994. Ten samples were re-<lb/>ferred to as L. intestinalis registered in the Gen-<lb/>Bank under accession numbers KC900972-<lb/>KC900981. Nucleotide variation between the <lb/>L. intestinalis and D. interrupta samples was <lb/>about 3% to 7%. <lb/>Table 2: Sampling localities and coordinates of Alburnoides bipunctatus and Abramis brama in this study <lb/>Sampled fish <lb/>Province <lb/>Locality <lb/>Geographical <lb/>position <lb/>Rate of <lb/>infection <lb/>Plerocercoid <lb/>detected <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>East Azerbaijan <lb/>Maragheh Dam <lb/>Northwest <lb/>63.19% <lb/>L. intestinalis <lb/>A. brama <lb/>West Azerbaijan <lb/>Aras Dam <lb/>Northwest <lb/>16% <lb/>D. interrupta <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>Guilan <lb/>Bandare-E-Anzali lagoon <lb/>North <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>A. brama <lb/>Mazandaran <lb/>Ramesar lake <lb/>North <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Between L. intestinalis samples in this survey <lb/>and the GenBank samples, and also between <lb/>D. interrupta samples and the GenBank sam-<lb/>ples, nucleotide variation was about 1% to 3%. <lb/>Finally, L. intestinalis samples were caught in <lb/>Iran from the same host and nucleotide varia-<lb/>tions of about 1% to 4% were seen among <lb/>them wonderfully. <lb/>The results of the genealogy tree based on <lb/>the ITS2 locus display that two clades were <lb/>obvious. One containing L. intestinalis and D. <lb/>interrupta samples from present study with five <lb/>isolates of this other L. intestinalis and D. <lb/>interrupta that registered in GenBank, while <lb/>another clade contains genus Schistocephalus <lb/>solidus that is available in GenBank. All sam-<lb/>ples caught in this study, including 10 isolates <lb/>of L. intestinalis and 11 isolates of D. interrupta, <lb/>along with five isolates from GenBank were <lb/>located in the same clade and so we could call <lb/>them monophyletic. S. solidus is located in a <lb/>different clade (Table 3, Fig. 6). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Studies on the distribution of D. interrupta <lb/>and L. intestinalis in Iran showed that most <lb/>such reports have been from the northwest <lb/>and western parts, while only a few reports <lb/>came from the northern area (4, 5). In this <lb/>study, none of the collected samples from the <lb/>northern part was infected, but, in contrast, <lb/>the infection rate was remarkably up in the <lb/>north-western part of country. Host specificity <lb/>and isolated lineages by geography were the <lb/>results of adjustment to local host fauna (6). <lb/>Moreover, L. intestinalis is remarkably host-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Iran J Parasitol: Vol. 13, No. 4, Oct-Dec 2018, pp.648-654 <lb/></note>

			<page>652 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<body>specific remarkably in Kenya (7). According to <lb/>the result of this study, infection with plero-<lb/>cercoid was highly correlated with habitat in <lb/>northwest Iran. <lb/>Table 3: Phylogenetic data collection to assess relationships between Ligula intestinalis and Digramma interrupta <lb/>No. Sample name <lb/>Locality <lb/>Host <lb/>Accession no. <lb/>1 <lb/>L. intestinalis 1 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900972.1 <lb/>2 <lb/>L. intestinalis 2 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900973.1 <lb/>3 <lb/>L. intestinalis 3 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900974.1 <lb/>4 <lb/>L. intestinalis 4 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900975.1 <lb/>5 <lb/>L. intestinalis 5 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900976.1 <lb/>6 <lb/>L. intestinalis 6 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900977.1 <lb/>7 <lb/>L. intestinalis 7 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900978.1 <lb/>8 <lb/>L. intestinalis 8 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900979.1 <lb/>9 <lb/>L. intestinalis 9 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900980.1 <lb/>10 <lb/>L. intestinalis 10 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. bipunctatus <lb/>KC900981.1 <lb/>11 <lb/>D. interrupta 1 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900982.1 <lb/>12 <lb/>D. interrupta 2 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900983.1 <lb/>13 <lb/>D. interrupta 3 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900984.1 <lb/>14 <lb/>D. interrupta5 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900986.1 <lb/>15 <lb/>D. interrupta 6 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900987.1 <lb/>16 <lb/>D. interrupta 7 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900988.1 <lb/>17 <lb/>D. interrupta 8 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900989.1 <lb/>18 <lb/>D. interrupta 10 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900991.1 <lb/>19 <lb/>D. interrupta 11 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900992.1 <lb/>20 <lb/>D. interrupta 12 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900993.1 <lb/>21 <lb/>D. interrupta 13 <lb/>Iran <lb/>A. brama <lb/>KC900994.1 <lb/>22 <lb/>S. solidus <lb/>Norway <lb/>Gasterosteus aculeatus <lb/>AY549508.1 <lb/>23 <lb/>L. intestinalis <lb/>Turkey <lb/>Silurus glanis <lb/>AY549516.1 <lb/>24 <lb/>L. intestinalis <lb/>Turkey <lb/>Chalcaburnus sp <lb/>AY549517.1 <lb/>25 <lb/>L. colymbi <lb/>Poland <lb/>Gavia stellata <lb/>EU241090.1 <lb/>26 <lb/>D. interrupta <lb/>Russia <lb/>Hemiculter lucidus <lb/>EU241114.1 <lb/>27 <lb/>D. interrupta <lb/>Russia <lb/>Hemiculter lucidus <lb/>EU241117.1 <lb/>Fig. 6: Maximum likelihood phylogenetic tree of Ligula intestinalis and Digramma interrupta based on ITS2 sequences. <lb/>Phylogenetic trees were obtained by comparing the ITS2 query sequences of L. intestinalis and D. interrupta with <lb/>those of other Cestoda species available in GenBank based on maximum parsimony. Similar topology was observed <lb/>among the trees obtained by distance-based (NJ) tree building methods in phylogenetic analysis using MEGA7 <lb/>software. The species included in the maximum parsimony analysis mainly clustered into two major clades and <lb/>Schistocephalus solidus (Pseudophyllidea: Diphyllobothriidae) rooted as an out-group and indicates its evolutionary <lb/>relationships <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Ahmadiara et al.: The Taxonomic Position and Phylogenetic Relationship between … <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<page>653 <lb/></page>

			<body>Climatic conditions in the north-western <lb/>part of the country are more conducive to <lb/>these parasites, while another probable reason <lb/>could be the neighborhood of Turkey. Since <lb/>Turkey is a good source of pollution by Ligu-<lb/>lidae plerocercoid, maybe water imported <lb/>from Turkey can be attributed to infection of <lb/>water by plerocercoid in northwest Iran (8). <lb/>Another reason could be migratory birds that <lb/>could transmit the infection in nearby loca-<lb/>tions in two adjacent countries. <lb/>Host specificity probably exists in Iran be-<lb/>cause D. interrupta was detected only from A. <lb/>brama, in Russia (9). In addition, similar to a <lb/>survey (5), results from northwest Iran <lb/>showed detection of plerocercoid of L. <lb/>intestinalis from A. bipunctatus. However, the <lb/>morphological difference could be used to <lb/>detect the genus and species from each other, <lb/>but it is not enough and an accurate meter is <lb/>needed for distinguishing the species and line-<lb/>age from each other. Therefore, over the last <lb/>two decades, molecular studies have helped <lb/>scientists to improve and revise their infor-<lb/>mation about the taxonomical status of para-<lb/>sites and their phylogeny. <lb/>Despite various studies on the epidemiologi-<lb/>cal aspect of this Cestoda, any molecular char-<lb/>acterization is not found in Iran and also in <lb/>the entire Middle East zone. Thus, there is <lb/>lack of sufficient information about the mo-<lb/>lecular characteristics of this Pseudophyllidean <lb/>Cestoda in this zone. It confirms the necessity <lb/>of a study on molecular and morphological <lb/>features of this genus, and another genus of <lb/>this family, as well as their true taxonomical <lb/>station in this region. <lb/>Liao and Liang (10) watched in Digramma the <lb/>transitional reproductive organ structure. A <lb/>single set of reproductive organs was located <lb/>at the anterior end of the larva in the carassian <lb/>intermediate hosts and also two rows of this <lb/>were located at the posterior end. Sexual di-<lb/>morphism was reported in D. interrupta in A. <lb/>brama the reproductive organs found in <lb/>one row, whereas two rows occur in those <lb/>from carp (9). Maybe D. interrupta was just a <lb/>rare diplogonadic form of the Ligula species <lb/>(2). In L. intestinalis dimorphism with some of <lb/>them debating on the potential existence of <lb/>this species in the Ligula genus. For example, <lb/>based on ITS region and 28S rRNA, verified <lb/>that plerocercoid of L. intestinalis specimens <lb/>from Rutilus and Gobio may represent different <lb/>strains or species (11). Despite recognition of <lb/>species based on morphological features ap-<lb/>propriate for the discrimination between two <lb/>genera (3), the morphological specification of <lb/>them is not reliable and raises much confusion <lb/>concerning D. interrupta validity because of the <lb/>transitional shape of reproductive organs in <lb/>the proglottids of these two genera. <lb/>In the present study, D. interrupta exhibited <lb/>identical sequences with L. intestinalis with <lb/>about 1% heterology based on the ITS1-5.8S <lb/>regions analysis, whereas a high degree of ge-<lb/>netic diversity of about 3% to 7% has seen <lb/>based on the ITS2 locus. The present study <lb/>also suggests that ITS2, unlike ITS1-5.8S se-<lb/>quences, can act as a useful genetic marker. <lb/>There is not any yardstick for identifying <lb/>species or genus borders by using the result of <lb/>the DNA-sequence distinction, with a value of <lb/>divergence based on ITS2 sequences, D. <lb/>interrupta is almost different from L. intestinalis. <lb/>Therefore, with nucleotide variation levels be-<lb/>tween L. intestinalis and D. interrupta specimens, <lb/>besides morphological differences, it cannot <lb/>be verified whether D. interrupta is a synonym <lb/>of the genus L. intestinalis, against the theory of <lb/>some researchers (10, 11). <lb/>On the other hand, they are different genera <lb/>because of low levels of nucleotide variation <lb/>and unstable morphological difference be-<lb/>tween them. Maybe polymorphism seen in L. <lb/>intestinalis and D. interrupta is present only in <lb/>some global locations (10, 12). Besides low <lb/>levels of nucleotide variation (else two sam-<lb/>ples that have 6% and 7% diversity, the other <lb/>differences would amount to (3% to 4%), we <lb/>reach and verify the theory that maybe D. <lb/>interrupta was just a rare diplogonadic form of <lb/>the Ligula species (2) not a different genus and <lb/>not synonymous with the Ligula genus, but <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Iran J Parasitol: Vol. 13, No. 4, Oct-Dec 2018, pp.648-654 <lb/></note>

			<page>654 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Available at: http://ijpa.tums.ac.ir <lb/></note>

			<body>only another species of the Ligula genus. Phy-<lb/>logenetic tree results have displayed differ-<lb/>ences between clade A and clade B, verifying <lb/>that the effect of geography in speciation and <lb/>its effect on molecular structures. L. intestinalis <lb/>and D. interrupta samples were different from <lb/>samples registered in GenBank. Eleven sam-<lb/>ples of D. interrupta and eight samples of L. <lb/>intestinalis were located in a common cluster so <lb/>that it may be support the analogy of this ge-<lb/>nus. Moreover, the discrepancy amount of 1% <lb/>to 4%, shown in the sequence of L. intestinalis <lb/>samples, were compared with each other in <lb/>the same host that could supplement the pres-<lb/>ence of a species and/or strains in this genus <lb/>much like results derived by other researchers <lb/>(12,13). <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>ITS2 may be one of the most useful markers <lb/>used to distinguish L. intestinalis from D. <lb/>interrupta. It can also be used to detect the var-<lb/>iations within L. intestinalis. Further, D. <lb/>interrupta may be another species of the Ligula <lb/>genus. On the other hand, they could not be <lb/>different genera because of low levels of nu-<lb/>cleotide variation arising from the possibility <lb/>of polymorphism and therefore D. interrupta is <lb/>another species of the Ligula genus. Its possi-<lb/>ble presence as a species and/or strains in the <lb/>Ligula genus is based on host specificity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors thank Dr. Iraj Mobedi for help-<lb/>ful advice and his kind assistance in designing <lb/>the schematic. Moreover, we are grateful of <lb/>University of Tehran for supporting this re-<lb/>search. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that there is no conflict <lb/>of interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. <lb/>Williams H, Jones A. Parasitic worms of fish <lb/>Taylor &amp; Francis, 1994. London. <lb/>2. <lb/>Luo HY, Nie P, Yao WJ, Wang GT, Gao Q. Is <lb/>the genus Digramma synonymous to the genus <lb/>Ligula (Cestoda: Pseudophyllidea)? Parasitol <lb/>Res. 2003; 89(5):419-21. <lb/>3. <lb/>Chubb JC, Pool DW, Veltkamp CJ. A key to <lb/>the species of cestodes (tapeworms) parasitic in <lb/>British and Irish freshwater fishes. J Fish Biol. <lb/>1987; 31:517-543. <lb/>4. <lb/>Jalali B, Barzegar M. Fish Parasites in Zarivar <lb/>Lake. J Agric Sci Technol. 2006; 8: 47-58. <lb/>5. <lb/>Hajirostamloo M. The occurrence and parasite <lb/>host of Ligula intestinalis in Sattarkhan Lake <lb/>(East Azerbaijan-Iran). J Anim Vet Adv. 2008; <lb/>7: 221-225. <lb/>6. <lb/>Bouzid W, Stefka J, Hypsa V, Lek S, Scholz T, <lb/>Legal L, Ben Hassine OK, Loot G. Geography <lb/>and host specificity: Two forces behind the ge-<lb/>netic structure of the freshwater fish parasite <lb/>Ligula intestinalis (Cestoda: Diphyllobothriidae). <lb/>Int J Parasitol. 2008; 38(12):1465-79. <lb/>7. <lb/>Britton JR, Jackson, MC, Harper, DM. Ligula <lb/>intestinalis (Cestoda: Diphyllobothriidae) in <lb/>Kenya: a field investigation into host specificity <lb/>and behavioral alterations. Parasitol. 2009; 136: <lb/>1367-73. <lb/>8. <lb/>Yavuzcan H, Korkmaz AS, Zencir O. The <lb/>infection of tench (Tincatinca) with Ligula <lb/>intestinalis plerocercoid in Lake Beysehir Turkey. <lb/>Bull Eur Assn Fish. 2003; 23: 223-227. <lb/>9. <lb/>Dubinina MN. Tapeworms (Cestoda, Liguli-<lb/>dae) of the fauna of the USSR Amerind, New <lb/>Delhi. 1980; 237-260. <lb/>10. Li J, Liao X. The taxonomic status of Di-<lb/>gramma (Pseudophyllidae: Ligulidae) inferred <lb/>from DNA sequences. J Parasitol. 2003; 89: <lb/>792-799. <lb/>11. Olson PD, Littlewood DT, Griffiths D, Ken-<lb/>nedy CR, Arme C. Evidence of the existence <lb/>of separate strains or species of Ligula in <lb/>Lough Neagh, Northern Ireland. J Helminthol. <lb/>2002; 76(2):171-4. <lb/>12. Arme C, Owen RW. Occurrence and patholo-<lb/>gy of Ligula intestinalis infections in British <lb/>fishes. J Parasitol. 1968; 54(2):272-80. <lb/>13. Arme C. Ligulosis in two cyprinid hosts: Ruti-<lb/>lus and Gobio. Helmintholgia. 1997; 34: 191-<lb/>196. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
