<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
        
        <titlePage>High-pressure oxygen-induced bulk superconductivity in 1222 structure Tl-Pb-Sr-<lb/>Eu(Ce)-Cu-O <lb/>Z. Iqbal, A. P. B. Sinha, D. E. Morris, J. C. Barry, G. J. Auchterlonie, and B. L. Ramakrishna <lb/>Citation: Journal of Applied Physics 70, 2234 (1991); doi: 10.1063/1.349414 <lb/>View online: http://dx.doi.org/10.1063/1.349414 <lb/>View Table of Contents: http://scitation.aip.org/content/aip/journal/jap/70/4?ver=pdfcov <lb/>Published by the AIP Publishing <lb/>Articles you may be interested in <lb/>Oxygen-induced internal pressure in superconductors <lb/>Low Temp. Phys. 41, 879 (2015); 10.1063/1.4936225 <lb/>High-pressure structural and elastic properties of Tl2O3 <lb/>J. Appl. Phys. 116, 133521 (2014); 10.1063/1.4897241 <lb/>Superconductivity and microstructure of n-type Ln1.85Ce0.15CuO4−y (Ln=Pr, Sm, Eu) produced under <lb/>high-pressure sintering <lb/>Appl. Phys. Lett. 62, 3037 (1993); 10.1063/1.109131 <lb/>Bulk superconductivity with T c (zero) up to 95 K in a Tl0.5Pb0.5Ca0.9Ce0.1Sr2Cu2 oxide with an <lb/>Y1Ba2Cu3O y -like structure <lb/>Appl. Phys. Lett. 54, 2464 (1989); 10.1063/1.101536 <lb/>Crystal structure of the high T c (107 K) superconducting phase in Pb-Bi-Sr-Ca-Cu-O <lb/>Appl. Phys. Lett. 54, 2157 (1989); 10.1063/1.101516 <lb/>Reuse of AIP Publishing content is subject to the terms at: https://publishing.aip.org/authors/rights-and-permissions. Download to IP: 130.102.82.20 On: Wed, 05 <lb/>Oct 2016 05:48:35 <lb/>I<lb/></titlePage> 

        <front>High-pressure oxygen-induced bulk superconductivity <lb/>in 1222 structure <lb/>I <lb/>TI-Pb-Sr-Eu(Ce)-Cu-0 <lb/>Z. lqbal <lb/>Allied-Signal Inc., Research and Technology, Morrfsfown, New Jersey 07962 <lb/>A. P. B. Sinha and D. E. Morris <lb/>Morris Research Inc., Berkeley, Califbrnid &apos;94704 <lb/>J. C. Barry and G. J. Auchterlonie <lb/>Electron Microscope Center, University of Queens&amp;d, Brisbane, Australia <lb/>B. L. Ramakrishna <lb/>Department of Chemistry, Arizona State University, Tempe. Arizona 85287 <lb/>(Received 4 March 1991; accepted for publication 4 May 1991) <lb/>A primarily single phase compound of composition (T1c.sPbc.s ) Srz ( Euz _ &amp;!e,) Cua09 (where <lb/>x ranges from (0.1 to 0.17) has been synthesized in the so-called 1222 structure. Bulk <lb/>superconductivity near 40 K is induced via oxygen doping in 100 bar of oxygen at 550 &quot;C!. The <lb/>material has been structurally characterized by diffraction and high-resolution lattice <lb/>imaging techniques. The lattice images reveal the presence of some intergrowths of a 1212 <lb/>structure nonsuperconducting (Tle,Pb&amp;Sr2EuCu207 <lb/>phase in the bulk 1222 <lb/>structure of the parent compound and indications of periodicity that suggest the possible <lb/>existence of a new, composite structure 2434 phase. <lb/></front>

		<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Recently Bi-and Tl-based compounds of composition <lb/>(Bi or Tl),(Sr or Ba)z(Ln,L,Ce,)C.u2010 <lb/>(where Ln is <lb/>Sm, Eu, or Gd) have been successfully synthesized by <lb/>Tokura et al.&apos; In these so-called 2222~structure cuprates, <lb/>adjacent CuO, layers are separated by a Lnz _ ,Ce,o2 flu-<lb/>orite block and are alternately offset in the a direction. The <lb/>Bi-based compounds display bulk superconductivity after <lb/>annealing in 80 bar O2 at 550-600 &quot;C for 10 h. The transi-<lb/>tion temperature initially reported was about 25 K but this <lb/>has been recently improved to 40 K by optimizing &apos;the <lb/>synthesis and annealing conditions.2 Superconductivity has <lb/>so far not been found under these conditions in the Tl-s <lb/>based 2222 compound,&apos; and in the Tl-0 monolayer Tl-Ba-<lb/>Ln(Ce)-Cu-0 <lb/>1222 compound, which has been synthe-<lb/>sized by Martin et al3 <lb/>The discovery of superconductivity in the Tl-Sr-Ca-<lb/>Cu-0 system with T, at 20 K (Ref. 4) and its optimization <lb/>via Ce doping to a bulk T, of 65 K (Ref. 5), and the <lb/>discovery <lb/>of <lb/>superconductivity <lb/>in <lb/>isostructural <lb/>(Tlo,SPbO.s)Sr&amp;!aCuzO, with a Tc of 85 K (Ref. 6) [tihich <lb/>has now been raised to 105 K (Ref. 7) by Y doping at the <lb/>Ca sites], suggested that the synthesis of the related com-<lb/>pounds of composition ( Tle,Pbc.5) Sr2( Ln, _ &amp;e;)C!u209 <lb/>having the 1222 structure may be possible. Phases of for-<lb/>mula (Tli -,Pb,) (Sri -,LaJ2(Lnl <lb/>-yCe )2CuZ09 in the <lb/>1222 structure were indeed synthesized,&apos;but found to be <lb/>nonsuperconducting. In this paper we report the synthesis, <lb/>in essentially single phase form, of a new compound of <lb/>composition ( TlcsPbc.s) SrZ( Eu, _ ,Ce,) CuZ09 having the <lb/>1222 structure [abbreviated here as (Tl,Pb)-12221, and its <lb/>doping under high 0, pressure to give a bulk superconduc-<lb/>tor with a T, onset near 40 K. This i.s the, first report, to our <lb/>knowledge, of superconductivity <lb/>in the (Tl,Pb)-1222 <lb/>structure cuprates; superconductivity at 25 K has however <lb/>been reported by Maeda et al.&apos; in a (Pb,Cu)-1222 cuprate <lb/>of composition (Pb,Cu) ( Sr,Eu)Z( Eu,Ce)2Cu20Z. The gen-<lb/>eral features of the structure and microstructure of the <lb/>(Tl,Pb)-1222 compound have also been determined. by <lb/>powder x-ray dilIraction, selected area electron diffraction, <lb/>and high-resolution lattice imaging. <lb/>SYNTHESlS <lb/>The best specimens of (Tl,Pb)-1222 were obtained <lb/>with a-nominal content of Ce in the above-given formula of <lb/>x = 0.2: The samples were prepared in two steps. A matrix <lb/>of nominal composition Sr2( Euc.&amp;!ect ) &amp;uZO, was first <lb/>prepared from a well-ground precursor mixture of SrO, <lb/>EuzO3, Ce&amp;, and CuO, which was fired in air at 950 &quot;C! for <lb/>16 h. The matrix powder was then mixed with a stoichio-<lb/>metric amount of PbO and B 10% excess by weight of <lb/>T1203, followed by pelletization. The pellet was placedin-<lb/>sidea gold tube, which was closed by crimping on one side <lb/>and by spot welding on the other side. The gold tube was <lb/>pushed into a furnace at 925 &quot;C under flowing O2 and held <lb/>at this temperature for 6 h. At the end of this period the <lb/>furnace was opened and the sample allowed to cool rapidly <lb/>(down to 30 &quot;C in about 30 min) under flowing OF <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>The, powder x-ray (Ct.&amp;a: radiation) diffraction pat-<lb/>tern (measured using a Rigaku diffractometer) of the as-<lb/>prepared material is shown in Fig. 1. Except for unreacted <lb/>CeOZ and a small amount of an impurity phase (see dis-<lb/>cussion below) indicated by crosses in Fig. 1, the diffrac-<lb/>tion lines can be indexed to the same structure (tetra-<lb/></body>

        <page>2234 <lb/></page> 

        <note place="footnote">J. Appl. Phys. 70 (4), 15 August 1991 <lb/>0021-8979/91/042234-04$03.00 <lb/>@ 1991 American Institute of Physics<lb/></note> 

        <page>2234 <lb/></page> 

        <note place="footnote">Reuse of AIP Publishing content is subject to the terms at: https://publishing.aip.org/authors/rights-and-permissions. Download to IP: 130.102.82.20 On: Wed, 05 <lb/>Oct 2016 05:48:35 <lb/></note>

		<body>h <lb/>P 16161-<lb/>2 <lb/>s <lb/>s <lb/>12121-<lb/>% <lb/>.% <lb/>: <lb/>I <lb/>8080-<lb/>t <lb/>4040-<lb/>gonal, <lb/>space group <lb/>I4/mmm) <lb/>reported <lb/>for the <lb/>(Tlr -$&apos;b,) (Srt -..La,) (Lnt -,Ce,)@r20g <lb/>compounds by <lb/>Mochiku et aL8 <lb/>Selected area electron diffraction patterns yielded av-<lb/>erage lattice parameters a z b = 3.91 A and c = 29.98 A. <lb/>A representative high resolution lattice image obtained us-<lb/>ing a JEOL 4000 FX electron microscope is shown in Fig. <lb/>2 together with the corresponding electron diffraction pat-<lb/>FIG. 2. [X0] lattice image of a Tle5PbO&amp;Eu2 -xCexCuz09 (x(0.1 to <lb/>0.17) microcrystal. Inset on the left shows the corresponding selected <lb/>area diffraction pattern. Inset at the center shows a computer simulated <lb/>image. <lb/>FIG. 1. Powder x-ray diffraction (CIA&amp;) <lb/>of a typical as-synthesized sample of <lb/>TlasPbO.sSr,Euz _ .$e,Cu,O, (x(0.1 to <lb/>0.17). $ symbols refer to reflections due <lb/>to impurity. <lb/>tern and image simulation. The image is in the [loo] pro-<lb/>jection and shoivs the layer sequence of the structure. Us; <lb/>ing the structural parameters reported by Mochiku et al.,&apos; <lb/>a simulated image in good agreement with the structure is <lb/>obtained (inset, Fig. 2). The structure proposed for the <lb/>(Tl,Pb)-1222 compound is shown in Fig. 3. An important <lb/>feature of the structure is a MiO, fluorite block (where M&apos; <lb/>in our sample is Eu doped by Ce) which separates the <lb/>O(4) <lb/>P <lb/>TIO <lb/>c---------MO <lb/>c <lb/>I;-<lb/>--<lb/>TlO <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>FIG. 3. Proposed structure of the Tlo.sPbO.sSrzEuz _ $exCuz09 (x(0.1 to <lb/>0.17) compound. The Tl layer is composed of Tla,,Pb,s and M&apos; is Eu <lb/>doped with Ce. <lb/></body>

        <page>2235 <lb/></page> 

        <note place="footnote">J. Appl. Phys., Vol. 70, No. 4, 15 August 1991 <lb/>lqbal et al.</note> <lb/>

        <page>2235 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">Reuse of AIP Publishing content is subject to the terms at: https://publishing.aip.org/authors/rights-and-permissions. Download to IP: 130.102.82.20 On: Wed, 05 <lb/>Oct 2016 05:48:35 <lb/></note>

        <body>CuO? layers of the structure. As evident from the lattice <lb/>6 <lb/>image, the Cu atoms in consecutive Cu02 layers down the <lb/>c axis are offset in the a direction by (a + b)/2 (where a <lb/>and b are 2-dimensional unit cell vectors for the pseudo-<lb/>tetragonal Cu02 sheet). The charge reservoir layer is a <lb/>single Tl-0 plane in which half the Tl ions are replaced by <lb/>Pb ions. Because of the strongly oxidizing synthesis condi-<lb/>tions used, the oxidation states of Tl and Pb are likely to be <lb/>+ 3 and + 4, respectively. An oxidation state of + 4 has <lb/>been determined for Pb in the 77 K &quot;12 13&quot; superconduc-<lb/>tor of composition Pbo.sSrBal.zYo.,Cao.3CU307 + 6 (Ref. <lb/>10) prepared under similar conditions. In addition, the <lb/>lattice images from some of the microcrystals show inter-<lb/>growths of the single M&apos; layer (Tl,Pb)-1212 phase of com-<lb/>position (TlcSPbo.JSr,EuCuzO-/. In some of the crystal-<lb/>lites the (TI,Pb)-1212 intergrowths display some degree of <lb/>periodicity, indicating the possible existence of a new com-<lb/>posite phase; namely, a (TI,Pb)-2434 compound consisting <lb/>of an alternating fluorite block and single M&apos; layer primi-<lb/>tive unit cell. In the YBa,Cu,Os (Y-124) compound, for <lb/>example, similar periodic intergrowths of the YBa@@7 <lb/>(Y-123) <lb/>phase can occur to give a composite <lb/>Y2Ba4Cu701s (Y-247) phase.&apos; * Preliminary x-ray diffrac-<lb/>tion data indicate the formation of a (semiconducting) <lb/>(Tl,Pb)-2434 compound from a stoichiometric mixture of <lb/>the oxides under similar conditions as described above. <lb/>Results of doping experiments and detailed characteriza-<lb/>tion of this phase will be published elsewhere. In addition <lb/>to (Tl,Pb)-1212 intergrowths, some isolated crystallites of <lb/>the (Tl,Pb)-12 12 phase were also detected. X-ray reflec-<lb/>tions associated with an impurity phase in Fig. 1 are there-<lb/>fore likely to be due to this compound. This was also <lb/>confirmed <lb/>by <lb/>synthesizing <lb/>nearly <lb/>pure <lb/>(Tlc5Pb0.5)Sr2EuCuz07, which was found to be nonsuper-<lb/>conducting down to 4 K in the as-prepared form as well as <lb/>on 6-bar O2 annealing. <lb/>Analytical transmission electron microscopy using en-<lb/>ergy dispersive spectroscopy with an intrinsic germanium <lb/>high-angle x-ray detector was used to determine the atomic <lb/>compositions of a series of crystallites from various prep-<lb/>arations. Most of the crystallites corresponded to a <lb/>Tl(Pb)-Sr-Eu-Cu <lb/>1222 composition in which the Tl:Pb ra-<lb/>tio is 1:l. Ce was barely detectable in 80% of the crystal-<lb/>lites, consistent with the observation of unreacted crystal-<lb/>line Ce02 in the product. However, 20% of the grains did <lb/>contain Ce with x near 0.17. <lb/>Four-probe dc resistance measurements of the as-pre-<lb/>pared (Tl,Pb)-1222 product shows semiconducting behav-<lb/>ior (Fig. 4) consistent with the observations of Tokura et <lb/>al. in Tl-2222 and Mochiku et al8 in related compounds. <lb/>However, a sample annealed at 550 &quot;C for 24 h under 6 <lb/>bars of O2 in a high pressure bomb indicates reduced semi-<lb/>conducting behavior and a resistance drop with an onset <lb/>near 22 K, as evident from Fig. 41 Zero-field-cooled <lb/>SQUID magnetic susceptibility data shown in Fig. 5 rep-<lb/>resent results for the 6-bar 02-annealed sample and a 100-<lb/>bar 02-annealed sample processed for 5 h at 550 &quot;C! in a <lb/>commercial high-pressure O2 furnace.&quot; Magnetic suscep-<lb/>tibility data for an as-prepared sample shows no indication<lb/></body> 

        <page>2236 <lb/></page>

        <note place="footnote">J. Appl. Phys., Vol. 70, No. 4, 15 August 1991<lb/></note> 

        <body>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>g3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>120 <lb/>160 <lb/>200 <lb/>240 <lb/>260 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>FIG. 4. Normalized four-probe dc resistivity (using I-mh measuring <lb/>current) as a function of temperature for an as-synthesized sample (curve <lb/>and <lb/>6-bars Orannealed <lb/>sample <lb/>f;)~,,Pbo,,Sr2J&amp; _xCexCuzOg (x(0.1 to 0.17). <lb/>(curve 6) <lb/>of <lb/>of diamagnetism consistent with the resistivity data. The <lb/>6-bar O,-annealed sample shows an approximately 3%-<lb/>volume diamagnetic fraction with diamagnetic onset near <lb/>20 K, consistent with the observed drop in resistance. The <lb/>lOO-bar.02-annealed sample clearly shows an enhancement <lb/>of the diamagnetic volume fraction to nearly 20% and an <lb/>increase of the diamagnetic onset T, to near 40 K. Field-<lb/>cooled Meissner fractions in this and similarly prepared <lb/>samples were found to be greater than 10% by volume, <lb/>indicating the occurrence of bulk superconductivity. How-<lb/>ever, on annealing the sample under 200 bars of O2 at <lb/>550 &quot;C! for 10 h, the diamagnetic fraction is sizably re-<lb/>duced. No changes are observed in the x-ray diffraction <lb/>patterns of the high 02-pressure annealed samples of <lb/>(Tl,Pb)-1222 indicating that doping affects only the oxy-<lb/>gen sublattice. Samples annealed at 100 bars of O2 show <lb/>Temperature <lb/>(K) <lb/>FIG. 5. Zero-field-cooled dc SQUID data at 10 Oe as a function of tem-<lb/>perature for: (A) 6-bars 02-annealed sample and (B) lCO-bar <lb/>Oz-annealed sample of Tle,Pbo.,Sr2Eu2 _ ,CexCu209 (x(0.1 to 0.17). <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">lqbal et a/. <lb/></note>

		<page>2236 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Reuse of AIP Publishing content is subject to the terms at: https://publishing.aip.org/authors/rights-and-permissions. Download to IP: 130.102.82.20 On: Wed, 05 <lb/>Oct 2016 05:48:35 <lb/></note>

		<body>decreased resistance and sizable drops near T,, but zero <lb/>resistance down to -12 K (the limit of our resistance <lb/>data) was not observed, although large Meissner fractions <lb/>were found in these samples. In addition, the temperature <lb/>dependence of the resistance remained weakly semicon-<lb/>ducting, suggesting that the grain boundary regions are not <lb/>optimally doped in the ceramic samples. <lb/>The oxygen content of the Tl-based cuprates cannot be <lb/>determined either by iodometric titration or thermogravi-<lb/>metric methods. Also, neutron diffraction experiments are <lb/>complicated by strongly neutron absorbing rare earth ele-<lb/>ments in the (Tl,Pb)-1222 compounds. Nevertheless, the <lb/>oxygen content can be qualitatively estimated on the basis <lb/>of the expected oxidation state of the constituent ions; thus, <lb/>for (T10.sPbo.5)SrzCaCuzO~, the 0 content is estimated to <lb/>be 6.75, assuming that Pb is + 4 and Cu is + 2. In order <lb/>to achieve the oxygen level of 7 for the layered oxygen-<lb/>deficient perovskite 1212 structure, the compound has to <lb/>be oxygen doped to form Cu + 3, which leads to supercon-<lb/>ductivity when the doping reaches a value near the semi-<lb/>conductor-to-metal transition phase boundary. The results <lb/>of Barry et al6 for (T1,,5Pbo.5)Sr2CaCu207 have shown <lb/>that this doping level is achieved at l-bar O2 to give a T, <lb/>near 85 K. However, some samples showed a resistance <lb/>drop at 105 K, which, in the light of the more recent <lb/>results on electron doping via Y + 3 substitution at the <lb/>Ca + &apos; sites,7 sugg ests that the as-synthesized samples were <lb/>somewhat overdoped, and that an optimally doped sample <lb/>would have a T, near 105 K. In the case of <lb/>(Tlo.sPbo.s)SrzEuz _ XCe,Cu209 similar charge counting <lb/>(neglecting Ce) yields an 0 content of 8.75, whereas for <lb/>(TlesPbo,s)SrZEuCu207, the 0 content is 7.25. Both these <lb/>compounds are semiconducting in the as-prepared (l-bar-<lb/>0,) state-the (Tl,Pb)-1222 compound appears to remain <lb/>hole deficient under conditions of ambient pressure oxygen <lb/>synthesis, whereas ( Tlo.sPbo.s) Sr2EuCu207 is overdoped <lb/>under these circumstances. The hole deficiency is removed <lb/>in the (Tl,Pb) -1222 compound by high pressure (to about <lb/>loo-bar-02) oxygen annealing, but doping with oxygen at <lb/>interstitial sites occurs at pressures above 200-bar-O2 lead-<lb/>ing to a decrease in the superconducting volume fraction. <lb/>Note that the T, of 40 K for (Tl,Pb)-1222, Bi-2222, and <lb/>(Pb,Cu)-1222 corresponds to that of a typical single <lb/>CuOZ <lb/>layer <lb/>cuprate <lb/>such <lb/>as the <lb/>T-structure <lb/>La2 _ ,Sr,CuO$ compound. This suggests that in the 1222 <lb/>and 2222 cuprates the CuOZ sheets are effectively indepen-<lb/>dent since they are separated by Mao, fluorite blocks. <lb/></body>

		<listBibl>&apos;Y. Tokura, T. Arima, H. Takagi, S. Uchida, T. Ishigaki, H. Asano, R. <lb/>Beyers, A. I. Nazzal, P. Lacorre, and J. B. Torrance, Nature (London) <lb/>342, 890 (1989). <lb/>&apos;T. Arima, Y. Tokura, H. Takagi, S. Uchida, R. Beyers, and J. B. Tor-<lb/>rance, Physica C 168, 79 ( 1990). <lb/>&apos;C. Martin, D. Bourgault, M. Hervieu, C. Michel, J. Provost, and B. <lb/>Raveau, Mod. Phys. Lett. B 3, 933 (1989). <lb/>4Z. Z. Sheng, A. M. Hermann, D. C. Vier, S. Schultz, S. B. Osero-ff, D. <lb/>J. George, and R. M. Hazen, Phys. Rev. B 38, 7074 (1988). <lb/>&apos;Z. Iqbal, B. L. Ramakrishna, and J. C. Barry, Physica C 169, 396 <lb/>(1990). <lb/>6J. C. Barry, Z. Iqbal, B. L. Ramakrishna, R. Sharma, H. Eckhardt, and <lb/>F. Reidinger, J. Appl. Phys. 65, 5207 (1989), and references therein. <lb/>&apos;R. S. Liu, J. M. L&amp;g, S. F. Wu, Y. T. Huang, P. T. Wu, and L. J. <lb/>Chen, Physica C 159, 385 (1989). <lb/>&quot;T. Mochiku, T. Nagashima, Y. Saito, M. Watahiki, H. Asano, and Y. <lb/>Fukai, Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. 29, L588 (1990). <lb/>&apos;T. Maeda, K. Sakuyama, S. Koriyama, A. Ichinose, H. Yamauchi, and <lb/>S. Tanaka, Physica C 169, 133 (1990). <lb/>*OX. X. Tang and D. E. Morris, Phys. Rev. B (in press). <lb/>&quot;D. E. Morris, N. G. Asmar, J. Y. T. Wei, J. H. Nickel, R. L. Sid, J. S. <lb/>Scott, and J. E. Post, Phys. Rev. B 40, 11406 (1989). <lb/>&apos;2Morris Research Inc., 1918 University Ave., Berkeley, CA 947041 <lb/></listBibl>

		<page>2237 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">J. Appl. Phys., Vol. 70, No. 4, 15 August 1991 <lb/>lqbal et a/. <lb/></note>

		<page>2237 <lb/></page>

		<note place="footnote">Reuse of AIP Publishing content is subject to the terms at: https://publishing.aip.org/authors/rights-and-permissions. Download to IP: 130.102.82.20 On: Wed, 05 <lb/>Oct 2016 05:48:35 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
