<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E <lb/>MiR-15a/16-1 deficiency induces IL-10-producing CD19 + <lb/>TIM-1 + cells in tumor microenvironment <lb/>Xiaoqin Jia 1,2 | Hao Liu 3 | Chong Xu 1 | Sen Han 1 | Yating Shen 1 | Xin Miao 1 | <lb/>Xiangyu Hu 1 | Zhijie Lin 1,2 | Li Qian 1,2 | Zhengbing Wang 3 | Weijuan Gong 1,2,4,5,6 <lb/>1 Department of Basic Medicine, Institute of <lb/>Translational Medicine, Medical College, <lb/>Yangzhou University,Yangzhou,P.R. China <lb/>2 Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Experimental &amp; <lb/>Translational Non-coding RNA Research, <lb/>Yangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>3 Department of General Surgery, Subei <lb/>People&apos;s Hospital of Jiangsu Province, <lb/>Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>4 Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Integrated <lb/>Traditional Chinese and Western Medicine <lb/>for Prevention and Treatment of Senile <lb/>Diseases, Yangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>5 Jiangsu Key Laboratory of Zoonosis, <lb/>Yangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>6 Jiangsu Co-innovation Center for <lb/>Prevention and Control of Important Animal <lb/>Infectious Diseases and Zoonoses, <lb/>Yangzhou, P.R. China <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Weijuan Gong, Department of Basic <lb/>Medicine, Institute of Translational Medicine, <lb/>Medical College, Yangzhou University, <lb/>Yangzhou, P.R. China. <lb/>Email: wjgong@yzu.edu.cn <lb/>and <lb/>Zhengbing Wang, Department of General <lb/>Surgery, Subei People&apos;s Hospital of Jiangsu <lb/>Province, Yangzhou University, Yangzhou, <lb/>P.R. China. <lb/>Email: wzhb403@163.com <lb/>Funding information <lb/>National Natural Science Foundation of <lb/>China, Grant/Award Number: 81273214, <lb/>81471547, 81671547, 81873867; <lb/>Innovation Project for Graduate Students in <lb/>Jiangsu Province, Grant/Award Number: <lb/>SJZZ16_0267; Natural Science Foundation <lb/>of Jiangsu Province, Grant/Award Number: <lb/>BK 20180925 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>IL-10-producing B cells (B10) are associated with autoimmune diseases, infection <lb/>and tumours. MiR-15a/16 as a tumour-suppressive gene is down-regulated in several <lb/>tumours, such as chronic lymphocytic leukaemia, pituitary adenomas and prostate <lb/>carcinoma. Here, increased frequency of IL-10-producing CD19 + Tim-1 + cells was <lb/>seen in both aged miR-15a/16 −/− mice (15-18 months) with the onset of B cell leu-<lb/>kaemia and young knockout mice (8-12 weeks) transplanted with hepatic cancer <lb/>cells. CD19 + Tim-1 + cells down-regulated the function of effector CD4 + CD25 low T <lb/>cells ex vivo dependent on IL-10 production, and adoptive transfer of CD19 + Tim-<lb/>1 + cells promoted tumour growth in mice. IL-10 production by CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>was involved with the STAT3 activation. Bioinformatics analysis shows that miR-16 <lb/>targets the 3′-untranslating region (3′-UTR) of STAT3 mRNA. Overexpression of <lb/>miR-16 in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells inhibited STAT3 transcription and its protein expres-<lb/>sion. Thus, the loss of miR-15a/16 promoted induction of regulatory CD19 + Tim-1 + <lb/>cells in tumour microenvironment. These results confirmed that miR-15a/16 could <lb/>be used in tumour therapy due to its inhibition of tumour and regulatory B cells. <lb/>K E Y W O R D S <lb/>CD19, IL-10, miR-15a/16, Tim-1, tumor <lb/>Xiaoqin Jia and Hao Liu contributed equally to this article. <lb/>----------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------------<lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, <lb/>provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>© 2018 The Authors. Journal of Cellular and Molecular Medicine published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd and Foundation for Cellular and Molecular Medicine. <lb/>Received: 15 January 2018 | Revised: 30 August 2018 | Accepted: 26 October 2018 <lb/>DOI: 10.1111/jcmm.14037 <lb/>J Cell Mol Med. 2019;23:1343-1353. <lb/>wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/jcmm | 1343 <lb/></front>

			<body>1 | INTRODUCTION <lb/>The IL-10-secreting B cells (B10), as one of the important regulatory <lb/>B (Breg) cells, are associated with autoimmune diseases, infections <lb/>and tumours. B10 cells can directly inhibit macrophage activation, <lb/>down-regulate its secretion of NO and related inflammatory cytoki-<lb/>nes (TNF-α, IL-1, IL-6, IL-8, IL-12), and also reduce the phagocytosis <lb/>of macrophages. 1,2 Breg cells can inhibit antigen presentation and <lb/>expression of costimulatory molecules and cytokines of dendritic <lb/>cells (DCs). The Th1/Th17 effector cells are also regulated by Breg <lb/>cells to down-regulate the local inflammatory response. In addition, <lb/>Breg cells can also induce classical Treg and Tr1 cells to promote <lb/>immune-regulatory activity. 3,4 <lb/>So far, three subsets of IL-10-secreting B cells have been identi-<lb/>fied, namely, CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi , 5,6 CD19 + Tim +7 and <lb/>CD19 + FcγIIb hi8 cells. After being stimulated with Tim-1 antibody, <lb/>45% of CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi cells up-regulated Tim-1 expression and <lb/>secreted IL-10, whereas 8% of them could express Tim-1 and had <lb/>potential IL-10 secretion ability in non-CD5 + CD1d hi B cells, which <lb/>suggested that these two phenotypic Breg cells could not replace <lb/>each other. 7 A unique phenotype of CD19 hi FcγIIb hi B cells, which is <lb/>induced by regulatory DCs, also produces IL-10 to inhibit effector <lb/>CD4 + T cells. 8 The engagement of BCR is thought to play a role in <lb/>the early stage, whereas the activation of CD40 and Toll-like recep-<lb/>tors (TLRs) plays a role in the late stage of Breg cell differentiation. <lb/>Several signalling proteins, such as Erk, p38, glycogen synthase <lb/>kinase 3-β (GSK3-β), Smad, Signal transducers and activators of tran-<lb/>scription (STATs), mammalian target of rapamycin (mTOR) and <lb/>nuclear factor-kappa B (NF-κB), are involved in IL-10 production. 9-11 <lb/>The miR-15a/16 gene complex is located in the intron of the <lb/>DLEU2 gene in the human 13q14 region, which is recognized as a <lb/>tumour-suppressor gene. 12 The deletion of this gene region is closely <lb/>related not only with chronic B lymphocytic leukaemia, but also with <lb/>various solid tumours such as melanoma, colorectal cancer, prostate <lb/>cancer, breast cancer and bladder cancer. 13 The target genes of miR-<lb/>15a/16 include Bcl-2, WT-1, WNT3A, MCA1, MCL1 and CCDN1, <lb/>which are involved in tumour apoptosis. 14 MiR-15a/16 can also inhi-<lb/>bit vascular endothelial growth factor (VEGF) secretion and play <lb/>anti-angiogenesis activity. 15 Here, we showed that the deficiency of <lb/>miR-15a/16 was associated with induction of IL-10-producing Breg <lb/>cells under tumour microenvironment by up-regulating STAT3 <lb/>expression. <lb/>2 | MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>2.1 | Reagents and mice <lb/>MiR-15a/16 −/− mice (C57BL/6) were obtained from the Jackson Lab-<lb/>oratory (Sacramento, CA). All animal experiments were approved by <lb/>the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of Yangzhou <lb/>University (Yangzhou, China). The murine liver cancer cell line (H22) <lb/>was obtained from ATCC. Antibodies for flow cytometry were pur-<lb/>chased from either BioLegend (San Diego, CA) or eBioscience (San <lb/>Diego, CA): CD19 (1D3), B220 (RA3-6B2), CD5 (53-7.3), Tim-1 <lb/>(RMT1-4), FcγIIb (AT130-2), IL-10 (JES5-16E3), CD1d (1B1), CD4 <lb/>(RM4-5), CD69 (H1.2F3) and IFN-γ (XMG1.2). Antibodies for Wes-<lb/>tern blot were from Cell Signaling Technology (Boston, MA): STAT3 <lb/>(4904P), STAT3-pY705 (9145S) and STAT3-pS727 (94994T). <lb/>2.2 | ELISA <lb/>Splenic B cells (5 × 10 5 ) isolated either from miR-15a/16 −/− or wild-<lb/>type (WT) mice (C57BL/6) by magnetic sorting beads (Miltenyi) were <lb/>cultured in complete RPMI 1640 medium. For 24 or 48 hours, cell <lb/>supernatants were collected, and IL-10 concentrations were mea-<lb/>sured according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol (BioLegend). Serum <lb/>IL-10 levels of miR-15a/16 knock-out (KO) or wild-type (WT) mice <lb/>were also determined by the same kit. <lb/>2.3 | Flow cytometric intracellular staining <lb/>Intracellular cytokine production was determined using a staining kit <lb/>(eBioscience). For IL-10 detection, B lymphocytes were cultured in <lb/>the presence of Brefeldin A (10 μg/mL) for 4 hours at 37°C. For <lb/>IFN-γ measurement, lymphocytes were stimulated with PMA (50 ng/ <lb/>mL)/ionomycin (5 μg/mL) in the presence of Brefeldin A for 4 hours <lb/>at 37°C. After lymphocytes were stained with surface markers, they <lb/>were fixed, permeabilized, stained with cytokine or isotype antibody <lb/>and analysed by flow cytometry. <lb/>2.4 | Coculture of B and T cells <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were isolated from spleens of WT or KO mice which <lb/>were pre-transplanted with H22 cells by flow cytometry. CD4 + CD25 high <lb/>or CD4 + CD25 low cells from normal mice (C57BL/6) were also sorted out <lb/>by flow cytometry. Then, two lymphocyte subsets were mixed in a 1:1 <lb/>ratio and cultured overnight. The mixed lymphocytes were collected, <lb/>and CD69 expression and IFN-γ secretion were analysed in <lb/>CD4 + CD25 high or CD4 + CD25 low cells as described above. <lb/>2.5 | In vivo mouse tumour models <lb/>When H22 cells (2 × 10 6 ) were subcutaneously injected into mice <lb/>(n = 3), CD19 + Tim-1 + or CD19 + Tim-1 − cells (5 × 10 5 ) sorted form <lb/>KO mice were injected into the tail veins of tumour-bearing mice <lb/>every day. Tumour diameters were also documented every day. On <lb/>day 30, mice were sacrificed and tumour tissues were isolated. <lb/>2.6 | Western blot <lb/>Proteins of CD19 + Tim-1 + cells either from miR-15a/16 −/− or WT <lb/>mice were extracted after the lysis buffer (KeyGen, Nanjing, China) <lb/>was added into cells. After being separated on SDS-PAGE gels and <lb/>transferred onto polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes, pro-<lb/>teins were stained with first and secondary antibodies sequentially. <lb/>The blotting signal was developed using an ECL kit (KeyGen) and <lb/>analysed with the Gel-Pro32 software. <lb/></body>

			<page>1344 | <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>2.7 | Lentivirus infection <lb/>Lentivirus-expressing miR-16-1 (LV-miR-16) and a control lentivirus <lb/>(LV-control) were provided by GeneChem (Shanghai, China). <lb/>The transfection procedure was the same as in the previous <lb/>study. 16 <lb/>2.8 | Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) <lb/>As CD19 + Tim-1 + cells from miR-15a/16 −/− mice were transfected <lb/>with the LV-miR-16 lentivirus for 72 hours, RNA was extracted by <lb/>the TRIzol reagent (Life Technologies; Carlsbad, CA), and cDNA was <lb/>generated by a QuantiTect ® reverse transcription kit (QIAGEN <lb/>GmbH; Hilden, Germany). The amplification of cDNA was conducted <lb/>using the QuantiNova ™ SYBR ® Green PCR Kit (QIAGEN) on ABI <lb/>7500 (PE Applied Biosystems, Carlsbad, CA, USA). Primer pairs for <lb/>STAT3 were 5′-CACCCAACAGCCGCCGTAGT and 5′-TCCATTCA-<lb/>GATCCTGCATGTCTCC. <lb/>2.9 | Statistical analysis <lb/>Differences between the two groups were analysed by Student&apos;s t <lb/>test. Data were evaluated by one-way ANOVA followed by Dun-<lb/>nett&apos;s test between control and various stimulation groups. Signifi-<lb/>cant differences were indicated when *P &lt; 0.05, **P &lt; 0.01, and <lb/>***P &lt; 0.001. <lb/>3 | RESULTS <lb/>3.1 | Increased IL-10-producing B cells in the aged <lb/>knockout (KO) mice with leukaemia <lb/>The miR-15a/16 −/− mice spontaneously develop B cell leukaemia at <lb/>the age of 15-18 months with a penetrance of 60%. 17 First, B cell <lb/>frequencies in spleens of KO or WT mice in the age of 15-<lb/>18 months or 8-12 weeks were analysed. The aged KO mice (15-<lb/>18 months) were verified to have B cell leukaemia as shown in the <lb/>Figure S1. As expected, B cell frequency and absolute number are <lb/>significantly enhanced in the aged KO mice (15-18 months) (Fig-<lb/>ure 1A,B). No changes of B cells were observed in young KO mice <lb/>(8-12 weeks), compared with WT mice. B cells from spleens of KO <lb/>or WT mice at different ages were isolated and cultured ex vivo for <lb/>24 or 48 hours. In aged mice, IL-10 concentrations of supernatants <lb/>from KO mice-derived B cells were significantly higher than those <lb/>from WT mice-derived B cells. We did not observe any significant <lb/>differences of IL-10 concentration of B cell supernatants from young <lb/>mice (Figure 1C). IL-10 production by B cells from aged KO mice <lb/>was confirmed by intracellular staining of flow cytometry, as shown <lb/>in Figure 1D. Multi-colour fluorescence labelling was used to analyse <lb/>surface markers of CD19 + IL-10 + cells. KO mice-derived CD19 + IL-<lb/>10 + cells displayed the increased expression of Tim-1 and the similar <lb/>expression of CD1d and FcγIIb, as compared with WT mice (Fig-<lb/>ure 1E). Serum IL-10 level of aged KO mice was also higher than <lb/>that of aged WT mice and young KO mice (Figure 1F). Thus, there <lb/>was a B cell population with IL-10-producing activity in the aged KO <lb/>mice. <lb/>3.2 | Increased CD19 + Tim-1 + cells in the aged KO <lb/>mice with leukaemia <lb/>Three Breg cell populations with IL-10 production (CD19 + Tim-1 + , <lb/>CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi , CD19 + FcγIIb hi ) were detected in both aged and <lb/>young KO mice. In the aged KO mice (15-18 months), splenic <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cell frequency was significantly increased compared <lb/>with WT mice at the same age. No significant changes of splenic <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cell frequency were observed in young mice (Fig-<lb/>ure 2A). These CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were able to secrete IL-10 as <lb/>detected by flow cytometry (Figure 2B). The frequency of CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cells was positively correlated with serum IL-10 level (Fig-<lb/>ure 2C). However, the CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi cell frequency did not <lb/>vary obviously in aged or young KO mice (Figure 2D). CD19 + <lb/>FcγIIb hi cells also showed no significant changes between KO and <lb/>WT mice at different ages (Figure 2E). Therefore, CD19 + Tim-1 + <lb/>cells with IL-10 production were induced in aged KO mice bearing B <lb/>cell leukaemia. <lb/>3.3 | Increased CD19 + Tim-1 + cells in young KO <lb/>mice pre-transplanted with tumour cells <lb/>Considering IL-10-secreting B cells and leukaemic B cells in the aged <lb/>B cell-leukaemia bearing miR-15a/16 −/− mice (15-18 months) could <lb/>not be discriminated clearly, we determined whether CD19 + Tim-1 + <lb/>cells could be induced in young KO mice (8-12 weeks) bearing with <lb/>solid tumours. Hepatic cancer cells (H22) were subcutaneously trans-<lb/>planted into back of KO or WT mice. Tumour growth was up-regu-<lb/>lated in KO mice indicated by tumour size (Figure 3A). After 14 days <lb/>of H22 transplantation, Breg cells of KO or WT mice were analysed. <lb/>Compared with that in tumour-bearing WT mice, the splenic CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cell frequency was significantly increased in tumour-bearing <lb/>KO mice (Figure 3B,C). Frequency of CD19 + IL-10 + Tim-1 + cells was <lb/>also increased in KO mice (Figure 3D). Similarly, no significant <lb/>changes of splenic CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi and CD19 + FcγIIb hi cells were <lb/>observed in the two groups of mice (Figure 3E). The representative <lb/>results of CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi and CD19 + FcγIIb hi cells detected by <lb/>flow cytometry were shown in Figure S2. Simultaneously, CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cell frequencies in tumour tissues (Figure 3F) and peripheral <lb/>blood (Figure 3G) were significantly increased in KO mice. Because <lb/>sufficient CD19 + CD5 + cells infiltrated in tumour tissues can&apos;t be <lb/>acquired for analysis of distinct CD1d expression levels, we only <lb/>quantified the frequency of CD19 + CD5 + cells in tumour tissues and <lb/>peripheral blood (Figure S3). As shown in Figures 3F,G, there were <lb/>no significant differences of CD19 + CD5 + and CD19 + FcγIIb hi cell <lb/>frequencies in tumour tissues and peripheral blood between two <lb/>strains of mice. Therefore, CD19 + Tim-1 + cells with IL-10 production <lb/>could be also induced in young KO mice transplanted with tumour <lb/>cells. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/>| </note>

			<page>1345 <lb/></page>

			<body>F I G U R E 1 Enhanced IL-10-producing B cells in the aged (15-18 months) KO mice. (A, B) Detection of CD19 + B220 + cells of spleens from <lb/>both aged and young (8-12 weeks) mice by flow cytometry. (C) After CD19 + cells were isolated by magnetic beads and cultured ex vivo, cell <lb/>supernatants were collected, and IL-10 concentrations were measured with an ELISA kit. (D) Intracellular IL-10 of B cells from the aged mice <lb/>was detected by flow cytometry. (E) Expression of Tim-1, CD1d and FcγIIb on CD19 + IL-10 + cells detected by flow cytometry after multicolour <lb/>fluorescence labelling. (F) Serum IL-10 levels of aged and young KO or WT mice. **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001; ns, no significance. <lb/></body>

			<page>1346 | <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>F I G U R E 2 Analysis of regulatory B cell subsets in the aged (15-18 months) KO mice. CD19 + Tim-1 + (A), CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi (D), and <lb/>CD19 + FcγIIb hi (E) cell frequencies in spleens were detected by flow cytometry. (B) IL-10 production by CD19 + Tim-1 + were determined by <lb/>intracellular staining of flow cytometry. (C) Correlation analysis of CD19 + Tim-1 + cell frequency with serum IL-10. **P &lt; 0.01; ns, no <lb/>significance <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/>| </note>

			<page>1347 <lb/></page>

			<body>F I G U R E 3 Analysis of Breg cell subsets in young (8-12 weeks) KO mice bearing with transplanted tumours. (A) Tumour growth curve in KO <lb/>and WT mice after H-22 cells (5 × 10 6 ) were subcutaneously injected. (B, C) CD19 + Tim-1 + cell frequencies in spleens were detected by flow <lb/>cytometry. (D) Il-10 + Tim-1 + cells frequency gated on CD19 + cell was determined by intracellular staining of flow cytometry. (E) Splenic <lb/>CD19 + CD5 + CD1d hi and CD19 + FcγIIb hi cell frequencies of tumour-bearing mice. CD19 + Tim-1 + , CD19 + CD5 + and CD19 + FcγIIb hi cell <lb/>frequencies of tumour tissues (F) and peripheral blood (G). *P &lt; 0.05; ns, no significance <lb/></body>

			<page>1348 | <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>F I G U R E 4 Immune-regulatory function mediated by CD19 + Tim-1 + cells via IL-10 production. (A, C) Variations of CD69 expression of IL-2-<lb/>stimulated CD4 + T cells from healthy C57BL/6 mice after in coculture with CD19 + Tim-1 + cells at a ratio of 1:1 (with/without IL-10 <lb/>neutralizing antibody, 10 μg/mL). (B, C) IFN-γ production by CD4 + T cells was detected by intracellular staining of flow cytometry after being <lb/>incubated with CD19 + Tim-1 + cells. (D) Growth curve of transplanted H22 cells after adoptive transfer of CD19 + Tim-1 + or CD19 + Tim-1 − <lb/>cells. (E) Stripped tumour tissues from mice. Each experiment was repeated at least thrice. *P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/>| </note>

			<page>1349 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.4 | Regulatory activity of CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>depends on IL-10 production <lb/>CD4 + CD25 high cells are generally regarded as regulatory T cells, and <lb/>CD4 + CD25 low cells as effector T cells. When CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>were incubated with IL-2-stimulating CD4 + cells, CD69 expression <lb/>was significantly down-regulated on CD4 + CD25 low cells, but no <lb/>changes on CD4 + CD25 high cells (Figure 4A,C). Moreover, IFN-γ <lb/>production was sharply inhibited in CD4 + CD25 low cells after these <lb/>T cells were cocultured with CD19 + Tim-1 + cells (Figure 4B,C). The <lb/>suppressive activity of Tim-1 + B-cells from KO mice was also higher <lb/>than that of WT mice (Figure 4B,C). Thus, CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>exerted immune-regulatory effects through inhibiting activity of <lb/>effector T cells. When IL-10 neutralizing antibodies were added into <lb/>the B-T cell coculture system, the inhibitory effect of CD69 and <lb/>IFN-γ expression was almost reversed (Figure 4A-C), demonstrating <lb/>that Breg cells mediated the regulatory effect via IL-10 secretion. <lb/>Next, CD19 + Tim-1 + or CD19 + Tim-1 − cells from KO mice were <lb/>adoptively transferred into mice pre-injected with H22 cells every <lb/>3 days and lasted for 30 days. As expected, the transfer of CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cells significantly promoted tumour growth in vivo <lb/>(Figure 4D,E). <lb/>3.5 | STAT3 contributes to IL-10 production of <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>STAT3 activation is involved in IL-10 production of immune cells. <lb/>STAT3 levels of CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were checked in tumour-bear-<lb/>ing KO and WT mice. STAT3 mRNA levels were higher in CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cells of KO mice than those of WT mice (Figure 5A). Total <lb/>STAT3, STAT3-pY705 and STAT3-pS727 were all increased in <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells of tumour-bearing KO mice (Figure 5B,C). <lb/>When the STAT3 inhibitor (Stattic) was treated with KO mice-<lb/>derived CD19 + Tim-1 + cells, IL-10 production and Tim-1 expression <lb/>are both blocked (Figure 5D,E). The result indicated that the <lb/>increased STAT3 activity contributed to IL-10 production by <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells. <lb/>3.6 | MiR-16 over-expression in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells <lb/>inhibits STAT3 <lb/>Next, we determined whether miR-15a/16 directly down-regulated <lb/>the STAT3 mRNA level. By using bioinformatics analysis, miR-16, not <lb/>miR-15a, was found to directly bind with the 3′-untranslated region <lb/>(UTR) of STAT3 mRNA (Figure 6A). After KO mice-derived CD19 + <lb/>Tim-1 + cells were transfected with miR-16-containing lentivirus, miR-<lb/>16 expression levels were verified and shown in Figure 6B. At the <lb/>same time, the transcription of STAT3 was significantly inhibited <lb/>(Figure 6C). Western blot results also confirmed that STAT3 was <lb/>down-regulated in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells by being transfected with the <lb/>miR-16-containing lentivirus (Figure 6D). Therefore, overexpression <lb/>of miR-16 in KO mice-derived CD19 + Tim-1 + cells suppressed <lb/>STAT3 expression. <lb/>4 | DISCUSSION <lb/>The microRNA cluster of miR-15a/miR-16-1 (miR-15a/16) located <lb/>at 13q14.2 of the chromosome is regarded as a tumour-suppres-<lb/>sive gene. The loss of the gene cluster is involved in the develop-<lb/>ment of cancers such as chronic lymphocytic leukaemia (CLL), <lb/>pituitary adenomas, and prostate carcinoma. 13,14 Here, we deter-<lb/>mined that the loss of miR-15a/16 was associated with induction <lb/>of IL-10-producing B cells under tumour microenvironment. Breg <lb/>cells could down-regulate biologic activities of effector CD4 + T <lb/>cells and promote tumour growth with the characteristic pheno-<lb/>type of CD19 + Tim + . IL-10 production by B cells was dependent <lb/>on the STAT3 activation, and overexpression of miR-16 resulted <lb/>in inhibition of STAT3 and suppression of CD19 + Tim-1 + cells. We <lb/>described that Tim-1 + Breg cells with immune-suppressive activity <lb/>for tumour evasion was involved with the loss of the miR-15a/16 <lb/>gene cluster. <lb/>In humans, malignant cells from 90% of patients with CLL are <lb/>able to produce IL-10. These IL-10-competent CLL cells also express <lb/>cell surface phenotypes similar to nonmalignant B10 cells, indicating <lb/>a functional relationship between CLL and B10 cells. 18 We could not <lb/>discriminate B10 cells and leukemic B cells in the aged miR-15a/16 −/ <lb/>− mice (15-18 months) bearing B cell leukaemia. When the young <lb/>miR-15a/16 −/− mice (8-12 week) were transplanted with hepatic can-<lb/>cer cells, IL-10-producing CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were significantly <lb/>increased. In this case, as there is no B cell leukaemia in mice, IL-10-<lb/>producing CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were induced instead. No obvious <lb/>changes in IL-10-producing CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were observed in <lb/>healthy young miR-15a/16 −/− mice, suggesting that this Breg subset <lb/>was only induced in tumour microenvironment. Breg cells could be <lb/>recruited to the tumour and thereby attenuate anti-tumour immune <lb/>responses. <lb/>To date, the detailed molecular mechanisms of Breg development <lb/>in the tumour microenvironment remain unknown. Some tumour <lb/>cell-derived factors, such as leukotriene B4, 19 TNF-α, 20 placental <lb/>growth factor 21 and IL-21 secreted by local T cells, 22 have been rec-<lb/>ognized as Breg-induced factors. In addition, cell membrane mole-<lb/>cules (CD40L 23 or PD-1 24 ) of tumours are involved in Breg <lb/>development. The differentiation of Breg cells mainly depends on <lb/>the engagement of BCR and CD40. 25,26 In human B cells, STAT3 <lb/>and Erk activation induced by TLR controls IL-10 expression. 27 The <lb/>inhibition of STAT3 blocked IL-10 expression by CD19 + Tim-1 + cells, <lb/>suggesting that using STAT3 inhibitors in tumour patients also <lb/>retards B10 cell development. <lb/>Ectopic expression of miR-15a and miR-16-1 has been shown to <lb/>up-regulate 265 genes and down-regulate 3307 genes. 28 We found <lb/>that eight nucleotides of miR-16 are complementary to bases 295-<lb/>324 at the 3′-end of the STAT3 cDNA. The overexpression of miR-<lb/>16 led to the down-regulation of STAT3 mRNA and protein levels in <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells from KO mice. Whether miR-16 regulates <lb/>STAT3 expression through direct binding of its 3′-UTR needs further <lb/>study. It could be inferred that the STAT3 expression regulated by <lb/>miR-16 was not as strong as that by other miR-16 prominent target <lb/></body>

			<page>1350 | <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<body>F I G U R E 5 STAT3 activity contributes to IL-10 production by CD19 + Tim-1 + cells. (A) STAT3 mRNAs of CD19 + Tim-1 + cells from both <lb/>mice were measured by reverse transcription and real-time PCR. (B) Total STAT3, STAT3-pY705, and STAT3-pS727 levels were determined by <lb/>Western blot. (C) Statistical analysis of STAT3 expression in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells from both mice. Variations of IL-10 (D) and Tim-1 (E) <lb/>expression in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells treated with the STAT3 inhibitor (Stattic). Each experiment was repeated at least thrice. *P &lt; 0.05; <lb/>***P &lt; 0.001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<page>| 1351 <lb/></page>

			<body>genes (eg, BCL-2, MCL1, CCND1 and WNT3A). 13,14 In addition, <lb/>although we analysed the activity of miR-16 in B10 cell develop-<lb/>ment, the role of miR-15a (belonging to the same microRNA family) <lb/>could not be excluded. <lb/>In summary, deficiency of the microRNA cluster of miR-15a/16 <lb/>promoted the induction of IL-10-producing CD19 + Tim-1 + cells in <lb/>mice. The development of regulatory CD19 + Tim-1 + cells was <lb/>dependent on STAT3 activation. Overexpression of miR-16 inhibited <lb/>STAT3 expression. Considering that microRNAs target many genes, <lb/>this study confirmed that miR-15/16 could be used pharmaceutically <lb/>in tumour therapy. 29,30 <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>This work was supported by the National Natural Science Founda-<lb/>tion (No. 81671547, No. 81471547, No. 81273214, No. 81873867) <lb/>of China, Natural Science Foundation of Jiangsu Province (BK <lb/>20180925), Innovation Project for Graduate Students in Jiangsu Pro-<lb/>vince (SJZZ16_0267), the &quot;Six peaks&quot; Talent Project, and the &quot;333&quot; <lb/>Talent Project in Jiangsu Province. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">CONF LICT OF I NTEREST <lb/>All authors have declared there are no financial conflicts of interest <lb/>with regard to this work. <lb/></div>

			<front>O R C I D <lb/>Weijuan Gong <lb/>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-8543-1314 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>R E F E R E N C E S <lb/>1. Sarvaria A, Madrigal JA, Saudemont A. B cell regulation in cancer <lb/>and anti-tumor immunity. Cell Mol Immunol. 2017;14:662-674. <lb/>2. Mauri C, Menon M. Human regulatory B cells in health and disease: <lb/>therapeutic potential. J Clin Invest. 2017;127:772-779. <lb/>3. Gorosito Serrán M, Fiocca Vernengo F, Beccaria CG, et al. The <lb/>regulatory role of B cells in autoimmunity, infections and cancer: <lb/>perspectives beyond IL10 production. FEBS Lett. 2015;589:3362-<lb/>3369. <lb/>4. Lykken JM, Candando KM, Tedder TF. Regulatory B10 cell develop-<lb/>ment and function. Int Immunol. 2015;27:471-477. <lb/>5. Yanaba K, Bouaziz J-D, Haas KM, et al. A regulatory B cell subset <lb/>with a unique CD1d hi CD5 + phenotype controls T cell dependent <lb/>inflammatory responses. Immunity. 2008;28:639-650. <lb/>6. Xing C, Ma N, Xiao H, et al. Critical role for thymic <lb/>CD19 ± CD5 ± CD1d hi IL-10 ± regulatory B cells in immune homeostasis. <lb/>J Leukoc Biol. 2015;97:547-556. <lb/>7. Ding Q, Yeung M, Camirand G, et al. Regulatory B cells are identified <lb/>by expression of TIM-1 and can be induced through TIM-1 ligation <lb/>to promote tolerance in mice. J Clin Invest. 2011;121:3645-3656. <lb/>8. Qian L, Qian C, Chen Y, et al. Regulatory dendritic cells program B <lb/>cells to differentiate into CD19 hi FcγIIb hi regulatory B cells through <lb/>IFN-β and CD40L. Blood. 2012;120:581-591. <lb/>9. Bankó Z, Pozsgay J, Szili D, et al. Induction and differentiation of IL-<lb/>10-producing regulatory B cells from healthy blood donors and <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis patients. J Immunol. 2017;198:1512-1520. <lb/>10. Menon M, Blair PA, Isenberg DA, et al. A regulatory feedback <lb/>between plasmacytoid dendritic cells and regulatory B cells is aber-<lb/>rant in systemic lupus erythematosus. Immunity. 2016;44:683-697. <lb/>11. Yanaba K, Bouaziz JD, Matsushita T, et al. The development and <lb/>function of regulatory B cells expressing IL-10 (B10 cells) requires <lb/>antigen receptor diversity and TLR signals. J Immunol. <lb/>2009;182:7459-7472. <lb/>12. Pekarsky Y, Croce CM. Role of miR-15/16 in CLL. Cell Death Differ. <lb/>2015;22:6-11. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>F I G U R E 6 Overexpression of miR-16 <lb/>down-regulates STAT3. (A) Bioinformatics <lb/>analysis of complementary sequences <lb/>between miR16 and 3′-UTR of STAT3 <lb/>mRNA. (B) miR-16 expression of <lb/>CD19 + Tim-1 + cells determined by RT-PCR. <lb/>(C) After CD19 + Tim-1 + cells were <lb/>transfected by the lentivirus containing <lb/>miR-16, STAT3 mRNA was detected by <lb/>RT-PCR. (D) Variations of STAT3 protein <lb/>levels in CD19 + Tim-1 + cells detected by <lb/>Western blot after the miR-16 lentivirus <lb/>transfection. Each experiment was <lb/>repeated at least thrice. *P &lt; 0.05; <lb/>***P &lt; 0.001 <lb/></body>

			<page>1352 | <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>13. Aqeilan RI, Calin GA, Croce CM. MiR-15a and miR-16-1 in cancer: <lb/>discovery, function and future perspectives. Cell Death Differ. <lb/>2010;17:215-220. <lb/>14. Cui J. MiR-16 family as potential diagnostic biomarkers for cancer: a <lb/>systematic review and meta-analysis. Int J Clin Exp Med. <lb/>2015;8:1703-1714. <lb/>15. Sun CY, She XM, Qin Y, et al. miR-15a and miR-16 affect the angio-<lb/>genesis of multiple myeloma by targeting VEGF. Carcinogenesis. <lb/>2013;34:426-435. <lb/>16. Jia X, Li X, Shen Y, et al. MiR-16 regulates mouse peritoneal macro-<lb/>phage polarization and affects T-cell activation. J Cell Mol Med. <lb/>2016;20:1898-1990. <lb/>17. Klein U, Lia M, Crespo M, et al. The DLEU2/miR-15a/16-1 cluster <lb/>controls B cell proliferation and its deletion leads to chronic lympho-<lb/>cytic leukemia. Cancer Cell. 2010;17:28-40. <lb/>18. Dilillo DJ, Weinberg JB, Yoshizaki A, et al. Chronic lymphocytic leu-<lb/>kemia and regulatory B cells share IL-10 competence and immuno-<lb/>suppressive function. Leukemia. 2012;27:170-182. <lb/>19. Bichi R, Shinton SA, Martin ES, et al. Human chronic lymphocytic <lb/>leukemia modeled in mouse by targeted TCL1 expression. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci USA. 2002;99:6955-6960. <lb/>20. Wejksza K, Lee-Chang C, Bodogai M, et al. Cancer-produced <lb/>metabolites of 5-lipoxygenase induce tumor-evoked regulatory B <lb/>cells via peroxisome proliferator-activated receptor α. J Immunol. <lb/>2013;190:2575-2584. <lb/>21. Schioppa T, Moore R, Thompson RG, et al. B regulatory cells and <lb/>the tumor-promoting actions of TNF-α during squamous carcinogen-<lb/>esis. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. 2011;108:10662-10667. <lb/>22. Lindner S, Dahlke K, Sontheimer K, et al. Interleukin 21-induced <lb/>granzyme B-expressing B cells infiltrate tumors and regulate T cells. <lb/>Cancer Res. 2013;73:2468-2479. <lb/>23. Zhou X, Su YX, Lao XM, et al. CD19 + IL-10 + regulatory B cells affect <lb/>survival of tongue squamous cell carcinoma patients and induce rest-<lb/>ing CD4 + T cells to CD4 + Foxp3 + regulatory T cells. Oral Oncol. <lb/>2016;53:27-35. <lb/>24. Xiao X, Lao XM, Chen MM, et al. PD-1 hi identifies a novel regulatory <lb/>B-cell population in human hepatoma that promotes disease progres-<lb/>sion. Cancer Discov. 2016;6:546-559. <lb/>25. Watanabe R, Ishiura N, Nakashima H, et al. Regulatory B cells (B10 <lb/>cells) have a suppressive role in murine lupus: CD19 and B10 cell <lb/>defciency exacerbates systemic autoimmunity. J Immunol. <lb/>2010;184:4801-4809. <lb/>26. Tedder TF. B10 cells: a functionally defined regulatory B cell subset. <lb/>J Immunol. 2015;194:1395-1401. <lb/>27. Liu BS, Cao Y, Huizinga TW, et al. TLR-mediated STAT3 and ERK <lb/>activation controls IL-10 secretion by human B cells. Eur J Immunol. <lb/>2014;44:2121-2129. <lb/>28. Calin GA, Cimmino A, Fabbri M, et al. MiR-15a and miR-16-1 cluster <lb/>functions in human leukemia. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. <lb/>2008;105:5166-5171. <lb/>29. Pekarsky Y, Balatti V, Croce CM. BCL2 and miR-15/16: from gene <lb/>discovery to treatment. Cell Death Differ. 2018;25:21-26. <lb/>30. Mohr A, Renaudineau Y, Bagacean C, et al. Regulatory B lymphocyte <lb/>functions should be considered in chronic lymphocytic leukemia. <lb/>Oncoimmunology. 2016;5:e1132977. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">S U P P O R T I N G I N F O R M A T I O N <lb/>Additional supporting information may be found online in the <lb/>Supporting Information section at the end of the article. <lb/></div>

			<front>How to cite this article: Jia X, Liu H, Xu C, et al. MiR-15a/ <lb/>16-1 deficiency induces IL-10-producing CD19 + TIM-1 + cells <lb/>in tumor microenvironment. J Cell Mol Med. 2019;23:1343-<lb/>1353. https://doi.org/10.1111/jcmm.14037 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">JIA ET AL. <lb/>| </note>

			<page>1353</page>


	</text>
</tei>
