<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Assessing enablement in clinical practice: a systematic <lb/>review of available instrumentsj ep_1332 1301..1308 <lb/> Catherine Hudon MD MSc CMFC, 1 Denise St-Cyr Tribble RN PhD, 2 France Légaré MD PhD FCMF, 3 <lb/> Gina Bravo PhD, 4 Martin Fortin MD MSc FCMF 5 and José Almirall MD PhD 6 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Associate Professor, Department of Family Medicine, Université de Sherbrooke, Sherbrooke, Québec, Canada <lb/> 2 <lb/> Full Professor, School of Nursing Science, Université de Sherbrooke, Sherbrooke, Québec, Canada <lb/> 3 <lb/> Associate Professor, Department of Family Medicine, Université Laval, Québec, Québec, Canada <lb/> 4 <lb/> Full Professor, Department of Community Health Sciences, Université de Sherbrooke, Sherbrooke, Québec, Canada <lb/> 5 <lb/> Full Professor, Department of Family Medicine, Université de Sherbrooke, Sherbrooke, Québec, Canada <lb/> 6 <lb/> Research Assistant, Centre de santé et de services sociaux de Chicoutimi, Chicoutimi, Québec, Canada <lb/> Keywords <lb/> empowerment, enablement, instruments, <lb/>professional practice, questionnaires, <lb/>systematic review <lb/> Correspondence <lb/> Catherine Hudon <lb/>305 St-Vallier <lb/>Chicoutimi <lb/>Québec <lb/>Canada G7H 5H6 <lb/>E-mail: catherine.hudon@usherbrooke.ca <lb/>Re-use of this article is permitted in <lb/>accordance with the Terms and Conditions <lb/>set out at http://wileyonlinelibrary.com/ <lb/>onlineopen#OnlineOpen_Terms <lb/>Accepted for publication: 10 August 2009 <lb/>doi:10.1111/j.1365-2753.2009.01332.x <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Rationale, aims and objectives Enablement is an intervention by which the health care <lb/>provider recognizes, promotes and enhances patients&apos; ability to control their health and life. <lb/>An abundant health literature suggests that enablement is associated with good outcomes. <lb/>In this review, we aimed at identifying and comparing instruments that assess enablement <lb/>in the health care context. <lb/> Method We conducted a systematic literature review using Medline, Embase, Cochrane, <lb/>Cinahl and PsycINFO databases, 1980 through March 2009, with specific search strategy <lb/>for each database. Citations were included if they reported: (1) development and/or vali-<lb/>dation of an instrument; (2) evaluation of enablement in a health care context; and (3) <lb/>quantitative results following administration of the instrument. The quality of each main <lb/>retained citation was assessed using a modified version of the Standards for Reporting of <lb/>Diagnostic Accuracy. <lb/> Results Of 3135 citations identified, 53 were retrieved for detailed evaluation. Four <lb/>articles were included. Two instruments were found: the Patient Empowerment Scale (PES) <lb/>and the Empowering Speech Practices Scale (ESPS). Both instruments assessed enable-<lb/>ment in hospital setting, one from the inpatient&apos;s perspective (PES) and the other from both <lb/>perspectives (ESPS). <lb/> Conclusion Two instruments assess enablement in hospital setting. No instrument is <lb/>currently available to assess enablement in an ambulatory care context. <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> Enablement is an intervention by which the health care provider <lb/>recognizes, promotes and enhances people&apos;s ability to control their <lb/>health and life [1–4]. St-Cyr Tribble et al. propose, in accordance <lb/>with recent reviews on the topic [1–4], a model of enablement <lb/>regrouping the following dimensions: contributing to the therapeu-<lb/>tic relationship, building on the person&apos;s point of view, facilitating <lb/>the learning experience, encouraging and supporting the decision-<lb/>making process, building on the person&apos;s strengths and helping to <lb/>broaden the person&apos;s possibilities [3]. <lb/>Enablement is in continuity with the patient-centred model <lb/>[5,6] because it shares many dimensions with this last model <lb/>(contributing to the therapeutic relationship, building on the per-<lb/>son&apos;s point of view, encouraging and supporting the decision-<lb/>making process and facilitating the learning experience). The term <lb/>&apos;empowerment&apos; is often used to talk about enablement [7–10]. <lb/>However, this term (empowerment) may be confusing because it <lb/>can also represent the patient&apos;s outcome after the enablement <lb/>intervention [2,4,11]. <lb/>Abundant health literature suggests that strategies based on <lb/>enablement are associated with good outcomes [12], which <lb/>include a more effective decision-making process, a better man-<lb/>agement of disease complications and adoption of healthier behav-<lb/>iours [13]. However, despite these potential relevant outcomes, <lb/>the World Health Organization stressed the lack of patients&apos; <lb/></body>

			<front> Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice ISSN 1356-1294 <lb/></front>

			<front> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd, Journal of Evaluation in Clinical Practice 16 (2010) 1301–1308 <lb/></front>

			<page> 1301 <lb/></page>

			<body> enablement by health care providers in the long-term care of <lb/>chronic diseases [12]. A primary step in developing and evaluating <lb/>strategies to improve enablement is to have a reliable and valid <lb/>measure of enablement in the health care context. As our capacity <lb/>to measure it grows, we will be in a better position to estimate the <lb/>real effects of enablement on patients&apos; health, and more broadly, <lb/>on the health care system [14]. We could also be able to design <lb/>effective strategies to improve enablement. <lb/>In this study, we aimed at identifying and comparing instru-<lb/>ments used to assess enablement in the health care context. <lb/> Methods <lb/> Search strategy and articles selection <lb/> Covering all available years from 1980 to March 2009, we con-<lb/>ducted an electronic literature search of the following databases: <lb/>Medline (1980–), Embase (1980–), Cochrane (1991–), Cinahl <lb/>(1982–) and PsycINFO (1980–), without any language restriction. <lb/>An information specialist was consulted to help develop, update <lb/>and run specific strategies for each databases. The following <lb/>MeSH terms and keywords were used: &apos;Power (psychology)&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Empowerment&apos;, &apos;Empowering&apos;, &apos;Enablement&apos;, &apos;Questionnaires&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Process assessment&apos;, &apos;Quality assessment&apos;, &apos;Psychometrics&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Scale&apos;, &apos;Instrument construction&apos;, &apos;Instrument validation&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Instrument scaling&apos;, &apos;Validation studies&apos;, &apos;Nursing assessment&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Reliability&apos;, &apos;Validity&apos;, &apos;Test validity&apos;, &apos;Test reliability&apos;, &apos;Test <lb/>construction&apos;, &apos;Factor analysis&apos;, &apos;Rating scale&apos;, &apos;Instrument&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Measurement&apos;, &apos;Assessment&apos;, &apos;Tool&apos;, &apos;Health Care Services&apos;, <lb/>&apos;Continuum of Care&apos;, &apos;Long Term Care&apos;, &apos;Mental Health Ser-<lb/>vices&apos;, &apos;Palliative Care&apos;, &apos;Primary Health Care&apos;. We also examined <lb/>additional relevant articles that potentially included an eligible <lb/>instrument from the reference lists of the collected articles (hand <lb/>searching). <lb/>All searches were transferred to a reference database (Ref-<lb/>works). Refworks gave the opportunity to group similar (not nec-<lb/>essarily identical) citations. Similar citations were then checked to <lb/>remove manually the identical ones (citations indexed on more <lb/>than one database). The titles and abstracts were read one by one <lb/>(CH). We excluded the citation at this stage if it was obvious that <lb/>it did not satisfy our inclusion criteria. We retained other citations <lb/>for complete reading. Two authors (CH and JA) independently <lb/>appraised the full text of identified retained papers to identify <lb/>potentially eligible articles. Discrepancies between the two <lb/>reviewers were resolved by consensus. First authors of included <lb/>studies were contacted to identify uncovered articles. <lb/> Inclusion and exclusion criteria <lb/> Citations were retained if they satisfied all of the following criteria: <lb/>(1) development and/or validation of an instrument; (2) evaluation <lb/>of enablement (often called &apos;empowerment&apos;) defined as an inter-<lb/>vention by which the health care provider recognizes, promotes <lb/>and enhances patients&apos; abilities to control their health and lives; <lb/>and (3) quantitative results following administration of the instru-<lb/>ment. We did not search for articles measuring only a sub-concept <lb/>or a dimension of enablement (patient-centred care, shared deci-<lb/>sion making, participation and information, etc.). Articles includ-<lb/>ing only a subscale on enablement were not retained. <lb/> Assessment of study quality <lb/> We assessed the quality of the first article published (considered as <lb/>the main article) for each instruments selected, using a modified <lb/>version of the Standards for Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy <lb/>(STARD) [15–17]. The STARD is an outgrowth of the Consoli-<lb/>dated Standards of Reporting Trials initiative [18], adopted by <lb/>many of the leading biomedical journals and journals in psychol-<lb/>ogy [19]. The STARD has already been successfully used in a <lb/>similar systematic review by a member of our team (F. L.) [20]. <lb/>From the initial STARD that contained 25 items [15–17], 15 items <lb/>were kept and judged appropriate to evaluate questionnaires. <lb/>Using this modified scale (15 items), two researchers (CH and JA) <lb/>independently determined a global quality score for each article. <lb/>The scores were then compared and a consensus was reached. <lb/> Data extraction <lb/> The following data were extracted for each instrument included: <lb/>[21] name of the instrument as given by the original author, first <lb/>author of the instrument and year of publication, discipline of the <lb/>first author, main purpose (measurement aim, clinical domain and <lb/>context of use envisioned by author, including the person who <lb/>completed the instrument), description of the instrument (number <lb/>of dimensions and items), response scale, development proce-<lb/>dures, conceptual/theoretical foundation and psychometric prop-<lb/>erties. Special attention was given to face and content validity [19]. <lb/>Face validity indicates whether the instrument appears to be <lb/>assessing the construct of interest. Content validity is the extent to <lb/>which all dimensions of the measured concept are represented <lb/>in the instrument [19]. Data extraction was completed by two <lb/>members of the team (CH and JA) and disagreements were <lb/>resolved by consensus. <lb/> Results <lb/> Articles included <lb/> Figure 1 shows the number of citations found at each stage of the <lb/>selection process. The search strategies identified 3800 citations, <lb/>from which 3135 were kept after removing duplicates. Fifty-three <lb/>were read completely and evaluated. Among these articles, eight <lb/>were not about the development or validation of an instrument <lb/>[22–29]; six were about concepts other than enablement or <lb/>empowerment [30–35], 31 did not measure a professional inter-<lb/>vention [36–66] and five included only a subscale on enablement <lb/>[67–71]. Hand searching and correspondence with authors added <lb/>another relevant article [72]. <lb/>Four articles covering two instruments were included in this <lb/>review. The identified instruments were: the Patient Empowerment <lb/>Scale (PES) [72,73] and the Empowering Speech Practices Scale <lb/>(ESPS) [74,75]. <lb/> Quality assessment <lb/> Overall, the quality of the studies was fair: 8 and 9 out of 15 <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/></body> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/> C. Hudon et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1302 <lb/></page>

			<body> Characteristics of instruments <lb/> Tables 2 and 3 summarize both included instruments. Both instru-<lb/>ments (PES and ESPS) were based on conceptual frameworks <lb/>developed from studies conducted by the same authors (as the <lb/>instrument development). <lb/>The PES evaluated patient&apos;s perception, whereas ESPS was <lb/>completed by both patient and nurse with parallel questionnaires, <lb/>thus representing both perceptions of the consultation. Both instru-<lb/>ments targeted inpatients. Both instruments used a 3-point Likert <lb/>response scale. The PES contained 40 items and the ESPS con-<lb/>tained 44 items. <lb/>The PES was studied among specific patient populations <lb/>(elderly inpatients), while ESPS was validated among a more <lb/>diverse group of patients. Both studies involved nurses and were <lb/>conducted in Europe. <lb/> Discussion <lb/> To the best of our knowledge, this is the first review to <lb/>identify and compare instruments used to measure enablement <lb/>in a health care context. Two instruments were identified. The <lb/>PES is a 40-item instrument to assess inpatient&apos;s perception <lb/>of enablement. The ESPS, a 44-item instrument, assesses <lb/>enablement in hospital setting, from the patients&apos; and nurses&apos; <lb/>perspectives. <lb/>Both instruments were based on conceptual frameworks devel-<lb/>oped from studies conducted by the original authors of the instru-<lb/>ment. Basing instrument development on conceptual framework <lb/>may increase the content validity of the instrument [76–78]. <lb/>However, it is relevant to start with a critical review of the litera-<lb/>ture to have a more valid conceptual model [79,80]. As suggested <lb/>by Streiner and Norman [19], recent reviews and empirical <lb/>research [1–4] could be used in further attempts to improve these <lb/>instruments (PES and ESPS) or elaborate new ones. <lb/>The enablement model [1,3,4] and the patient-centred model <lb/>[5,81] share many common dimensions (contributing to the thera-<lb/>peutic relationship, building on the person&apos;s point of view, encour-<lb/>aging and supporting the decision-making process and facilitating <lb/>the learning experience), raising the question &apos;Is it the same <lb/>concept?&apos; Our view is that the enablement process is necessarily <lb/> Total citations identified: 3800 <lb/>Citations retrieved for detailed evaluation by two authors: 53 <lb/>Duplicate: 665 <lb/>Relevant articles: 3 (2 instruments) <lb/>And citations added with hand searching: 1 <lb/>Included articles: 4 (2 instruments) <lb/>Citations screened for evaluation: 3135 <lb/>Exclusion criteria: <lb/> • Not about development or validation of an instrument: 8 <lb/> • Concepts other than enablement: 6 <lb/> • Outside the therapeutic relationship: 31 <lb/> • Including only a sub-scale on enablement: 5 <lb/> Figure 1 Number of citations identified <lb/>through the stages of the systematic review. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">C. Hudon et al. <lb/> Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1303 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table 1 Quality assessment of the main studies included, based on the modified version of Standards for Reporting of Diagnostic Accuracy <lb/>Section and topic <lb/>Item <lb/>Patient <lb/>Empowerment <lb/>Scale [72,73] <lb/>Empowering <lb/>Speech Practices <lb/>Scale [74,75] <lb/>Title/abstract <lb/>Identify the article as a study concerning a measuring instrument. <lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> Introduction <lb/>State the research question or study aims, like developing or validating a measuring <lb/>instrument. <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> Methods <lb/>Participants <lb/>Describe the study population: The inclusion and exclusion criteria, setting and <lb/>locations where the data were collected. <lb/> + <lb/> 0 <lb/>Describe the method of recruitment of the participants. <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> Describe participant sampling: Was the study population a consecutive series of <lb/>participants? If not, specify how participants were further selected. <lb/>0 <lb/> + <lb/> Test methods <lb/>Describe technical specifications of material and methods involved, including how and <lb/>when measurements were taken, and/or cite references for measuring instrument. <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> Describe relevant information for the readers concerning the measuring instrument <lb/>(scale available in the text). <lb/> + <lb/> 0 <lb/>Statistical methods Describe methods for calculating or comparing measures of reliability, validity and the <lb/>statistical methods used to quantify uncertainty (e.g. 95% confidence intervals). <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Results <lb/>Participants <lb/>Report when study was done, including beginning and ending dates of recruitment. <lb/>0 <lb/> + <lb/> Report demographic characteristics of the study population (e.g. age, sex, <lb/>employment, recruitment centres). <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> Report the number of participants satisfying the criteria for inclusion (a flow diagram <lb/>is strongly recommended). <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Test results <lb/>Report distribution of severity of the situation being assessed. <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Estimates <lb/>Report estimates of accuracy and measures of statistical uncertainty (e.g. 95% <lb/>confidence intervals). <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Report how indeterminate results, missing responses and outliers on the measuring <lb/>instrument were handled. <lb/>0 <lb/> + <lb/> Discussion <lb/>Discuss the clinical applicability of the study findings. <lb/> + <lb/>+ <lb/> Total score <lb/>8/15 <lb/>9/15 <lb/> Table 2 Characteristics of the two instruments included <lb/>Name of the <lb/>instrument (First author, <lb/>year of publication) <lb/>Origin of first <lb/>author, country <lb/>Main purpose (Measurement <lb/>aim, clinical domain and context <lb/>of use envisioned by author) <lb/>Description (number <lb/>of dimensions and items) <lb/>Response <lb/>scale <lb/>Patient <lb/>Empowerment <lb/>Scale (Faulkner, <lb/>2001) [72,73] <lb/>Department of <lb/>Community <lb/>Ageing <lb/>Rehabilitation <lb/>Education and <lb/>Research, UK <lb/>To assess inpatients&apos; enablement <lb/>in hospital environments. <lb/>3 dimensions in the empowerment <lb/>subscale (20 items): promoting patient <lb/>independence, awareness of patients&apos; <lb/>needs and promoting information <lb/>exchange <lb/>3-point <lb/>Likert <lb/>Completed by the patient after at <lb/>least 3 days of hospitalization. <lb/>3 dimensions in the disempowerment <lb/>subscale (20 items): impeding patient <lb/>collaboration in care planning, <lb/>domination and indifference to patients&apos; <lb/>needs. <lb/>Empowering <lb/>Speech <lb/>Practices Scale <lb/>(Kettunen, <lb/>2006) [74,75] <lb/>Research Center <lb/>for Health <lb/>Promotion, <lb/>Finland <lb/>To assess enablement of dyadic <lb/>counselling in hospital setting. <lb/>2 dimensions (44 items): professionally <lb/>led conversation and patient&apos;s requests <lb/>for additional clarification. <lb/>3-point <lb/>Likert <lb/>Completed by the inpatient and the <lb/>nurse (by way of the same <lb/>statements, parallel questionnaires) <lb/>after the counselling encounter. <lb/></body> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/> C. Hudon et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1304 <lb/></page>

			<body> Table  3  Development  and psychometric properties of the two instruments included <lb/> Instrument <lb/> Origins and development <lb/> Conceptual framework <lb/> Validity <lb/> Reliability <lb/> Patient <lb/> Empowerment <lb/> Scale [72,73] <lb/> 38 registered nurses were asked to nominate empowering and disempowering acts <lb/> relevant to interactions between staff and elderly patients. Further acts were <lb/> obtained following a literature review. <lb/> Constructed on the basis <lb/> of a conceptual model <lb/> of empowerment and <lb/> disempowerment derived <lb/> from the literature and <lb/> empirical results. <lb/> Face validity: Patients and <lb/> nurses were consulted. <lb/> Internal <lb/> consistency: <lb/> Cronbach alpha <lb/> from 0.75 to <lb/> 0.87 for the <lb/> empowerment <lb/> subscale and <lb/> 0.65 to 0.88 <lb/> for the <lb/> disempowerment <lb/> subscale. <lb/> Content validity: The scale is <lb/> coherent with the conceptual <lb/> model developed, but does <lb/> not take into account all the <lb/> literature on empowerment. <lb/> Construct validity: Factor <lb/> analysis (not detailed in the <lb/> article). <lb/> The resulting lists of 98 acts for each disposition were hypothetically judged by older <lb/> hospitalized people as to the extent they would be either &apos;control giving&apos; <lb/> (empowering acts,  n <lb/> =  20) or &apos;control taking&apos; (disempowering acts,  n <lb/> =  20) if <lb/> personally experienced. The 20 highest scoring acts in each category were <lb/> incorporated into the Patient Empowerment Scale. <lb/> The instrument was tested on 102 elderly (65 years or older) patients from three <lb/> hospitals (inpatients for at least 3 days) in Central England (acute medicine, <lb/> surgery and elderly care rehabilitation). <lb/> Empowering <lb/> Speech <lb/> Practices Scale <lb/> [74,75] <lb/> The first stage was a conversation of counselling encounters. <lb/> Constructed on the basis of <lb/> a conceptual model of <lb/> empowerment derived <lb/> from a case study by the <lb/> authors. <lb/> Face validity: Patients and <lb/> nurses were consulted. <lb/> Internal <lb/> consistency: <lb/> Cronbach alpha <lb/> for global <lb/> score: 0.88 and <lb/> for subscales: <lb/> 0.52 to 0.83. <lb/> Content validity: This scale <lb/> simultaneously includes <lb/> items related to the <lb/> enablement process and <lb/> outcomes <lb/> Construct validity: Factor <lb/> analysis confirms two factors <lb/> accounting for 59% of the <lb/> variance. Average loading <lb/> for professionally led <lb/> conversation: 0.80 and <lb/> patient&apos;s requests for <lb/> additional clarification: 0.84. <lb/> At the second stage, the study was used to design a questionnaire containing 65 <lb/> statements. <lb/> At the third stage, interviews were conducted where five patients and five nurses <lb/> assessed their videotaped counselling sessions by means of the instrument. The <lb/> statements were reduced to 58. <lb/> At the fourth stage, the revised instrument was tested by four patients on a hospital <lb/> ward. <lb/> Finally, 127 counselling situations involving adult patients (56 women and 54 men; <lb/> mean age <lb/> =  54.9 years) were evaluated with nurses (mean age <lb/> =  41.7; average <lb/> experience <lb/> =  13.8) on 17 wards and polyclinics providing care to adult patients in <lb/> Finland. This left a total of 44 statements. <lb/></body> 
			
			<note place="headnote">C. Hudon et al. <lb/> Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1305 <lb/></page>

			<body> patient-centred but a patient-centred intervention does not <lb/>always correspond to an enablement intervention. Indeed, build-<lb/>ing on the person&apos;s strengths is central to the enablement model <lb/>[1,82–85]. <lb/>Another question that could be raised is &apos;How is the enablement <lb/>concept positioned among other concepts such as shared decision <lb/>making, patient participation . . .&apos; As stressed in our enablement <lb/>model (see Introduction), these last concepts could be considered <lb/>as sub-concepts of enablement. Our hypothesis is that improving <lb/>many aspects of the interaction between the patient and the health <lb/>care provider (referring to the dimensions of our enablement <lb/>model) is maybe more effective than improving only one or two <lb/>aspects. <lb/>The PES evaluates patient&apos;s perception, while ESPS considers <lb/>patient and professional&apos;s points of view. Some authors argued that <lb/>both points of view have to be taken into account to evaluate <lb/>professional&apos;s practices, because interaction of these points of <lb/>view is determinant in the intervention process [11,86]. Other <lb/>studies demonstrated stronger relationship between patient&apos;s per-<lb/>ceptions and various outcomes. For example, in one study, per-<lb/>ceived empowering care by patients was the most important <lb/>predictor of their quality of life [87]. Stewart et al. evaluated <lb/>patient-centredness, a concept regrouping many dimensions of <lb/>enablement. They demonstrated that the patient&apos;s perception was a <lb/>better predictor of certain outcomes at the end of a 2-month period <lb/>than that of a trained person scoring an instrument from the audio-<lb/>tape of the encounter. One of their conclusions was that the patient <lb/>outcomes will be affected only when the doctor&apos;s patient-<lb/>centeredness reaches a level that the patient notices [5]. This <lb/>conclusion may be true for enablement as well. Further studies are <lb/>needed to evaluate this hypothesis. <lb/>The existing instruments are cross-sectional measures to assess <lb/>enablement (PES and ESPS). It is appropriate when considering <lb/>patients provided with medical care in an inpatient context. <lb/>However, in an ambulatory care setting, because the interaction <lb/>between a patient and a health care provider (his or her family <lb/>doctor for example) may evolve over time, the enablement inter-<lb/>vention may develop on a longitudinal basis [88,89]. Therefore, <lb/>one has to wonder, before using these instruments in such a <lb/>context, whether they are appropriate to measure an inherently <lb/>longitudinal process. This perspective must be kept in mind while <lb/>developing or improving instruments to assess enablement in an <lb/>ambulatory care context. <lb/> Limitation of the study <lb/> One of the main limitations of a review is its inability to include all <lb/>of the relevant literature and unpublished material. We acknowl-<lb/>edge that some eligible articles may have been missed during the <lb/>search stage. However, our search strategy was adapted for differ-<lb/>ent databases, was developed with an information specialist and <lb/>favoured an exhaustive literature review. Our hand search and <lb/>correspondence with experts were other ways to help us identify <lb/>uncovered articles. We did not include articles in which enable-<lb/>ment was part of a larger concept, such as quality of care, because <lb/>of the risk of missing such subscales. Scales measuring sub-<lb/>concepts of enablement (shared decision making for example) or <lb/>measuring enablement as a sub-concept of another construct <lb/>could, however, be used in a pool of items in further instrument <lb/>development. <lb/> Conclusion <lb/> Two instruments (PES and ESPS) were identified that measure <lb/>enablement in the health care context. Both instruments assess <lb/>enablement in hospital setting, one from the patient&apos;s perspective <lb/>(PES) and the other from both the patient&apos;s and the nurse&apos;s per-<lb/>spective (ESPS). To date, there is no tool available to the clinicians <lb/>or researchers to assess enablement in an ambulatory care context. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> We are grateful for the support of the Department of Family <lb/>Medicine at the University of Sherbrooke. We thank also Mrs <lb/>Tania Fayad for her editorial assistance with the preparation and <lb/>revision of this paper. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Virtanen, H., Leino-Kilpi, H. &amp; Salantera, S. (2007) Empowering <lb/>discourse in patient education. Patient Education and Counseling, 66, <lb/>140–146. <lb/>2. Ouschan, R., Sweeney, J. C. &amp; Johnson, L. W. (2000) Dimensions of <lb/>patient empowerment: implications for professional services market-<lb/>ing. Health Marketing Quarterly, 18 (1–2), 99–114. <lb/>3. St-Cyr Tribble, D., Gallagher, F., Bell, L., et al. (2008) Empowerment <lb/>interventions, knowledge translation and exchange: perspectives of <lb/>home care professionals, clients and caregivers. BMC Health Services <lb/>Research, 8, 177. <lb/>4. Aujoulat, I., D&apos;Hoore, W. &amp; Deccache, A. (2007) Patient empower-<lb/>ment in theory and practice: polysemy or cacophony? Patient Educa-<lb/>tion and Counseling, 66, 13–20. <lb/>5. Stewart, M. A., Belle Brown, J. B., Weston, W. W., McWhinney, I. R., <lb/>McWilliam, C. L. &amp; Freeman, T. R. (2003) In Patient-Centered Medi-<lb/>cine: Transforming the Clinical Method, 2nd edn. Cornwall: Radcliffe <lb/>Medical Press Ltd. <lb/>6. Mead, N. &amp; Bower, P. (2000) Patient-centredness: a conceptual frame-<lb/>work and review of the empirical literature. Social Science &amp; Medi-<lb/>cine, 51, 1087–1110. <lb/>7. Clay, T. (1992) Education and empowerment: securing nursing&apos;s <lb/>future. International Nursing Review, 39, 15–19. <lb/>8. Hawks, J. H. (1992) Empowerment in nursing education: concept <lb/>analysis and application to philosophy, learning and instruction. <lb/> Journal of Advanced Nursing, 17, 609–618. <lb/>9. Rodwell, C. M. (1996) An analysis of the concept of empowerment. <lb/> Journal of Advanced Nursing, 23, 305–313. <lb/>10. Ellis-Stoll, C. (1998) A concept analysis on the process of empower-<lb/>ment. ANS. Advances in Nursing Science, 21, 62–68. <lb/>11. St-Cyr Tribble, D., Gallagher, F., Paul, D. &amp; Archambault, J. (2003) <lb/>Les Pratiques D&apos;empowerment En Première Ligne. Compréhension Et <lb/>Évaluation De L&apos;efficacité Des Interventions Infirmières Et Psychoso-<lb/>ciales Conduites Auprès De Parents: Rapport De Recherche. Sher-<lb/>brooke: CSSS-IUGS. <lb/>12. World Health Organization (2002) Innovative care for chronic condi-<lb/>tions. Building blocks for action. Available at: http://www.who.int/ <lb/>diabetesactiononline/about/icccglobalreport.pdf (last accessed 24 July <lb/>2009). <lb/>13. World Health Organization (2006) What is the evidence on effective-<lb/>ness of empowerment to improve health? The Regional Office for <lb/>Europe of the World Health Organization. Available at: http:// <lb/>www.euro.who.int/Document/E88086.pdf (last accessed 24 July <lb/>2009). <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/> C. Hudon et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1306 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 14. Loukanova, S., Molnar, R. &amp; Bridges, J. F. P. (2007) Promoting patient <lb/>empowerment in the healthcare system: highlighting the need for <lb/>patient-centered drug policy. Expert Review of Pharmacoeconomics &amp; <lb/>Outcomes Research, 7, 281–289. <lb/>15. Bossuyt, P. M. &amp; Reitsma, J. B. (2003) The STARD initiative. Lancet, <lb/> 361, 7. <lb/>16. Bossuyt, P. M., Reitsma, J. B., Bruns, D. E., et al. (2003) The STARD <lb/>statement for reporting studies of diagnostic accuracy: explanation and <lb/>elaboration. Annals of Internal Medicine, 138, w1–w12. <lb/>17. Meyer, G. J. (2003) Guidelines for reporting information in studies of <lb/>diagnostic test accuracy: the STARD initiative. Journal of Personality <lb/>Assessment, 81, 191–193. <lb/>18. Altman, D. G., Schilz, K. F., Moher, D., et al. (2001) The revised <lb/>CONSORT statement for reporting randomized trials : explanation and <lb/>elaboration. Annals of Internal Medicine, 134, 663–694. <lb/>19. Streiner, D. L. &amp; Norman, G. R. (2008) In Health Measurement <lb/>Scales: A Practical Guide to Their Development and Use, 4th edn. <lb/>Oxford: Oxford University Press. <lb/>20. Légaré, F., Moher, D., Elwyn, G., LeBlanc, A. &amp; Gravel, K. (2007) <lb/>Instruments to assess the perception of physicians in the decision-<lb/>making process of specific clinical encounters: a systematic review. <lb/> BMC Medical Informatics and Decision Making, 7, 30. <lb/>21. McDowell, I. (2006) In Measuring Health. A Guide to Rating Scales <lb/>and Questionnaires, 3rd edn. New York: Oxford University Press. <lb/>22. Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J. &amp; Maxwell, M. (1995) Care of patients <lb/>with selected health problems in fundholding practices in Scotland in <lb/>1990 and 1992: needs, process and outcome. The British Journal of <lb/>General Practice, 45, 121–126. <lb/>23. Pawlikowska, T. R., Nowak, P. R., Szumilo-Grzesik, W. &amp; Walker, J. <lb/>J. (2002) Primary care reform: a pilot study to test the evaluative <lb/>potential of the Patient Enablement Instrument in Poland. Family <lb/>Practice, 19, 197–201. <lb/>24. Kilian, R., Lindenbach, I., Löbig, U., Uhle, M., Petscheleit, A. &amp; <lb/>Angermeyer, M. C. (2003) Indicators of empowerment and disempow-<lb/>erment in the subjective evaluation of the psychiatric treatment process <lb/>by persons with severe and persistent mental illness: a qualitative and <lb/>quantitative analysis. Social Science &amp; Medicine, 57, 1127–1142. <lb/>25. Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. &amp; Maxwell, M. (2004) Quality, core values <lb/>and the general practice consultation: issues of definition, measure-<lb/>ment and delivery. Family Practice, 21, 458–468. <lb/>26. Cottrell, R. P. F. &amp; Langzettel, M. (2005) Identifying dimensions of <lb/>empowerment in consumers of psychiatric services. Occupational <lb/>Therapy in Mental Health, 21, 13–38. <lb/>27. Gagnon, J. &amp; Grenier, R. (2004) Élaboration et validation <lb/>d&apos;indicateurs de la qualité des soins relatifs à l&apos;empowerment dans un <lb/>contexte de maladie complexe à caractère chronique. Recherche En <lb/>Soins Infirmiers, 76, 50–67. <lb/>28. van Uden-Kraan, C. F., Drossaert, C. H., Taal, E., Seydel, E. R. &amp; van <lb/>de Laar, M. A. (2009) Participation in online patient support groups <lb/>endorses patients&apos; empowerment. Patient Education and Counseling, <lb/> 74, 61–69. <lb/>29. Williamson, K. M. (2007) Home health care nurses&apos; perceptions of <lb/>empowerment. Journal of Community Health Nursing, 24, 133–153. <lb/>30. Johnson, P. T. &amp; Johnson, C. W. (1991) Power assessment inventory: <lb/>tool development. Applied Nursing Research: ANR, 4, 141–146. <lb/>31. Leddy, S. K. (1996) Development and psychometric testing of the <lb/>Leddy Healthiness Scale. Research in Nursing &amp; Health, 19, 431–440. <lb/>32. Maly, R. C., Frank, J. C., Marshall, G. N., DiMatteo, M. R. &amp; Reuben, <lb/>D. B. (1998) Perceived efficacy in patient-physician interactions <lb/>(PEPPI): validation of an instrument in older persons. Journal of the <lb/>American Geriatrics Society, 46, 889–894. <lb/>33. Coyle, J. &amp; Williams, B. (2001) Valuing people as individuals: devel-<lb/>opment of an instrument through a survey of person-centerdness in <lb/>secondary care. Journal of Advanced Nursing, 36, 450–459. <lb/>34. McDowell, J., Courtney, M., Edwards, H. &amp; Shortridge-Baggett, L. <lb/>(2005) Validation of the Australian/English version of the Diabetes <lb/>Management Self-Efficacy Scale. International Journal of Nursing <lb/>Practice, 11, 177–184. <lb/>35. Wensing, M., Vingerhoets, E. &amp; Grol, R. (2001) Functional status, <lb/>health problems, age and comorbidity in primary care patients. Quality <lb/>of Life Research, 10, 141–148. <lb/>36. Gagnon, M., Hébert, R., Dubé, M. &amp; Dubois, M. F. (2006) Develop-<lb/>ment and validation of an instrument measuring individual empower-<lb/>ment in relation to personal health care: the Health Care <lb/>Empowerment Questionnaire (HCEQ). American Journal of Health <lb/>Promotion, 20, 429–435. <lb/>37. Haughney, J., Cotton, P., Rosen, J. P., Rosen, J. P., Morrison, K. &amp; <lb/>Price, D. (2007) The use of a modification of the Patient Enablement <lb/>Instrument in asthma. Primary Care Respiratory Journal, 16, 89–92. <lb/>38. Dempsey, I. (1995) The enabling practices scale: the development of <lb/>an assessment instrument for disability services. Australia and New <lb/>Zealand Journal of Developmental Disabilities, 20, 67–73. <lb/>39. Klakovich, M. (1995) Development and psychometric evaluation of <lb/>the reciprocal empowerment scale. Journal of Nursing Measurement, <lb/> 3, 127–143. <lb/>40. Rissel, C., Perry, C. &amp; Finnegan, J. (1996) Toward the assessment of <lb/>psychological empowerment in health promotion: initial tests of valid-<lb/>ity and reliability. Journal of the Royal Society of Health, 116, 211– <lb/>218. <lb/>41. Rogers, E. S., Chamberlin, J., Ellison, M. L. &amp; Crean, T. (1997) A <lb/>consumer-constructed scale to measure empowerment among users of <lb/>mental health services. Psychiatric Services (Washington, DC), 48, <lb/>1042–1047. <lb/>42. Bolton, B. &amp; Brookings, J. (1998) Development of a measure of <lb/>intrapersonal empowerment. Rehabilitation Psychology, 43, 131–142. <lb/>43. Brookings, J. B. &amp; Bolton, B. (2000) Confirmatory factor analysis of <lb/>a measure of intrapersonal empowerment. Rehabilitation Psychology, <lb/> 45 (3), 292–298. <lb/>44. Corrigan, P. W., Faber, D., Rashid, F. &amp; Leary, M. (1999) The con-<lb/>struct validity of empowerment among consumers of mental health <lb/>services. Schizophrenia Research, 38, 77–84. <lb/>45. Wowra, S. A. &amp; McCarter, R. (1999) Validation of the empowerment <lb/>scale with an outpatient mental health population. Psychiatric Services <lb/>(Washington, DC), 50, 959–961. <lb/>46. Anderson, R. M., Funnell, M. M., Fitzgerald, J. T. &amp; Marrero, D. G. <lb/>(2000) The Diabetes Empowerment Scale: a measure of psychosocial <lb/>self efficacy. Diabetes Care, 23, 739–743. <lb/>47. Speer, P. W. &amp; Peterson, N. A. (2000) Instrument development. Psy-<lb/>chometric properties of an empowerment scale: testing cognitive, <lb/>emotional, and behavioral domains. Social Work Research, 24, 109– <lb/>118. <lb/>48. Anderson, R. M., Fitzgerald, J. T., Gruppen, L. D., Funnell, M. M. &amp; <lb/>Oh, M. S. (2003) The Diabetes Empowerment Scale-Short Form <lb/>(DES-SF). Diabetes Care, 26, 1641–1642. <lb/>49. Shiu, A. T., Wong, R. Y. &amp; Thompson, D. R. (2003) Development of <lb/>a reliable and valid Chinese version of the diabetes empowerment <lb/>scale. Diabetes Care, 26, 2817–2821. <lb/>50. Le Bossé, Y., Dufort, F. &amp; Vandette, L. (2004) L&apos;évaluation de <lb/>l&apos;empowerment des personnes: développement d&apos;une mesure <lb/>d&apos;indices psychosociologiques du pouvoir d&apos;agir (MIPPA). Canadian <lb/>Journal of Community Mental Health, 23, 91–114. <lb/>51. Hancer, M. (2005) Dimensions of the Turkish version of the <lb/>Psychological Empowerment Scale. Psychological Reports, 97, 645– <lb/>650. <lb/>52. Hansson, L. &amp; Björkman, T. (2005) Empowerment in people with a <lb/>mental illness: reliability and validity of the Swedish version of an <lb/>empowerment scale. Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences, 19, <lb/>32–38. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote"> C. Hudon et al. <lb/> Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1307 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> 53. Hochwälder, J. &amp; Bergsten Brucefors, A. (2005) A psychometric <lb/>assessment of a Swedish translation of Spreitzer&apos;s empowerment <lb/>scale. Scandinavian Journal of Psychology, 46, 521–529. <lb/>54. Johnson, D. M., Worell, J. &amp; Chandler, R. K. (2005) Assessing psy-<lb/>chological health and empowerment in women: the personal progress <lb/>scale revised. Women Health, 41, 109–129. <lb/>55. Shiu, A. T., Li, S. M. &amp; Thompson, D. R. (2005) The concurrent <lb/>validity of the Chinese version of the Diabetes Empowerment Scale. <lb/> Diabetes Care, 28, 498–499. <lb/>56. Bulsara, C., Styles, I., Ward, A. M. &amp; Bulsara, M. (2006) The psy-<lb/>chometrics of developing the patient empowerment scale. Journal of <lb/>Psychosocial Oncology, 24, 1–16. <lb/>57. Mikky, I. F. (2006) Development of the Client Empowerment Scale <lb/>(CES). PhD Dissertation. University of Connecticut. <lb/>58. Peterson, N. A., Lowe, J. B., Hughey, J., Reid, R. J., Zimmerman, M. <lb/>A. &amp; Speer, P. W. (2006) Measuring the intrapersonal component of <lb/>psychological empowerment: confirmatory factor analysis of the <lb/>sociopolitical control scale. American Journal of Community Psychol-<lb/>ogy, 38, 287–297. <lb/>59. Shiu, A. T., Martin, C. R., Thompson, D. R. &amp; Wong, R. Y. (2006) <lb/>Psychometric properties of the Chinese version of the diabetes <lb/>empowerment scale. Psychology, Health &amp; Medicine, 11, 198–208. <lb/>60. Leksell, J., Funnell, M., Sandberg, G., Smide, B., Wiklund, G. &amp; <lb/>Wikblad, K. (2007) Psychometric properties of the Swedish Diabetes <lb/>Empowerment Scale. Scandinavian Journal of Caring Sciences, 21, <lb/>247–252. <lb/>61. Stratic, E., Mirabella, F., Degli Espositi, M. &amp; Morosini, P. (2007) <lb/>Psychometric properties of the SESM, Italian version of the &apos;Con-<lb/>sumer constructed scale to measure empowerment among users of <lb/>mental health services&apos; (Rodgers et al. 1997). Epidemiologia E Psi-<lb/>chiatria Sociale, 16, 256–264. <lb/>62. Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J. &amp; Maxwell, M. (1997) Measuring quality <lb/>in general practice. Pilot study of needs, process and outcome <lb/>measure. The Journal of the Royal College of General Practitioners. <lb/>Occasional Paper, 75, i–xii, 1–32. <lb/>63. Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J., Maxwell, M. &amp; Walker, J. J. (1998) A <lb/>comparison of a Patient Enablement Instrument (PEI) against two <lb/>established satisfaction scales as an outcome measure of primary care <lb/>consultations. Fam Practice, 15, 165–171. <lb/>64. Price, D., Haughney, J., Rosen, J. P., Morrison, K. &amp; Howie, J. (2003) <lb/>Validation of a modified patient enablement instrument in asthma <lb/>[abstract]. The European Respiratory Journal, 22 (suppl 45), <lb/>P1701. <lb/>65. Castelein, S., van der Gaag, M., Bruggeman, R., van Busschbach, J. T. <lb/>&amp; Wiersma, D. (2008) Measuring empowerment among people with <lb/>psychotic disorders: a comparison of three instruments. Psychiatric <lb/>Services, 59, 1338–1342. <lb/>66. Klima, C., Vonderheid, S. &amp; Norr, K. (2007) Measuring empowerment <lb/>in pregnancy: the pregnancy-related empowerment scale [Abstract]. <lb/> Journal of Midwifery &amp; Women&apos;s Health, 52, 531. <lb/>67. Howie, J. G., Heaney, D. J., Maxwell, M., Walker, J. J. &amp; Freeman, G. <lb/>K. (2000) Developing a &apos;consultation quality index&apos; (CQI) for use in <lb/>general practice. Family Practice, 17, 455–461. <lb/>68. Kim, S. C., Boren, D. &amp; Solem, S. L. (2001) The Kim Alliance Scale: <lb/>development and preliminary testing. Clinical Nursing Research, 10, <lb/>314–331. <lb/>69. Chanter, C., Ashmore, S. &amp; Mandair, S. (2005) Improving the patient <lb/>experience in general practice with the General Practice Assessment <lb/>Questionnaire (GPAQ). Quality in Primary Care, 13, 225–232. <lb/>70. Mercer, S. W. &amp; Howie, J. G. (2006) CQI-2 – a new measure of <lb/>holistic interpersonal care in primary care consultations. The British <lb/>Journal of General Practice, 56, 262–268. <lb/>71. Jaturapatporn, D., Hathirat, S., Manataweewat, B., et al. (2006) Reli-<lb/>ability and validity of a Thai version of the General Practice Assess-<lb/>ment Questionnaire (GPAQ). Journal of the Medical Association of <lb/>Thailand, 89, 1491–1496. <lb/>72. Faulkner, M. (2001) A measure of patient empowerment in hospital <lb/>environments catering for older people. Journal of Advanced Nursing, <lb/> 34, 676–686. <lb/>73. Faulkner, M. (2001) Empowerment and disempowerment: models of <lb/>staff/patient interaction. NT Research, 6, 936–950. <lb/>74. Kettunen, T., Liimatainen, L., Villberg, J. &amp; Perko, U. (2006) Devel-<lb/>oping empowering health counselling measurement preliminary <lb/>results. Patient Education and Counseling, 64, 159–166. <lb/>75. Kettunen, T., Poskiparta, M. &amp; Liimatainen, L. (2001) Empowering <lb/>counselling – a case study: nurse–patient encounter in a hospital. <lb/> Health Education Research, 16, 227–238. <lb/>76. Clark, L. A. &amp; Watson, D. (1995) Constructing validity: basic issues in <lb/>objective scale development. Psychological Assessment, 7, 309–319. <lb/>77. Strickland, O. L. (2003) Using factor analysis for validity assessment: <lb/>practical considerations. Journal of Nursing Measurement, 11, 203– <lb/>205. <lb/>78. Griffin, S. J., Kinmonth, A. L., Veltman, M. W. M., Gillard, S., Grant, <lb/>J. &amp; Stewart, M. (2004) Effect on health-related outcomes of inter-<lb/>ventions to alter the interaction between patients and practitioners : a <lb/>systematic review of trials. Annals of Family Medicine, 2, 595–608. <lb/>79. Rodgers, B. L. (2000) Concept analysis: an evolutionary view. In <lb/>Concept Development in Nursing: Foundations, Techniques and <lb/>Applications, 2nd edn (eds B. L. Rodgers &amp; K. A. Knafl), pp. 77–102. <lb/>Philadelphia, PA: Saunders. <lb/>80. Walker, L. O. &amp; Avant, K. C. (1995) Strategies for Theory Construc-<lb/>tion in Nursing East Norwalk, CT: Appleton &amp; Lange. <lb/>81. Mead, N. &amp; Bower, P. (2002) Patient-centred consultations and out-<lb/>comes in primary care : a review of the literature. Patient Education <lb/>and Counseling, 48, 51–61. <lb/>82. Gibson, C. H. (1991) A concept analysis of empowerment. Journal of <lb/>Advanced Nursing, 16, 354–361. <lb/>83. Cowger, C. D. (1994) Assessing client strengths : clinical assessment <lb/>for client empowerment. Social Work, 39, 262–268. <lb/>84. Illmann, J. (2000) Patient power. Nursing Times, 96, 28–30. <lb/>85. Poskiparta, M., Liimatainen, L., Kettunen, T. &amp; Karhila, P. (2001) <lb/>From nurse-cenered health counseling to empowermental health coun-<lb/>selling. Patient Education and Counseling, 45, 69–79. <lb/>86. Guba, E. &amp; Lincoln, Y. (1989) Fourth Generation Evaluation. <lb/>Newbury Park, CA: Sage. <lb/>87. Tu, Y. C., Wang, R. H. &amp; Yeh, S. H. (2006) Relationship between <lb/>perceived empowerment care and quality of life among elderly resi-<lb/>dents within nursing homes in Taiwan: a questionnaire survey. Inter-<lb/>national Journal of Nursing Studies, 43, 673–680. <lb/>88. McKay, B., Forbes, J. A. &amp; Bourner, K. (1990) Empowerment in <lb/>general practice: the trilogies of caring. Australian Family Physician, <lb/> 19, 513–520. <lb/>89. Toofany, S. (2007) Empowering older people. Nursing Older People, <lb/> 19, 12–14. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote"> Instruments measuring enablement in clinical practice <lb/> C. Hudon et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote"> © 2010 Blackwell Publishing Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page> 1308 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
