<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Household, neighbourhood and service <lb/>provider risk factors for piped drinking-water <lb/>intermittency in urban and peri-urban <lb/>Zambia: A cross-sectional analysis <lb/>Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee ID <lb/>1,2 <lb/>*, Andrew A. Channon 3☯ , Robert E. S. Bain ID <lb/>4 <lb/>, James <lb/>A. Wright ID <lb/>1☯ <lb/>1 Geography and Environmental Science, University of Southampton, Southampton, United Kingdom, <lb/>2 WaterAid, London, United Kingdom, 3 Social Statistics and Demography, University of Southampton, <lb/>Southampton, United Kingdom, 4 UNICEF Middle East and North Africa, Amman, Jordan <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* mairthomas-poseee@wateraid.org <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Given nearly one third of sub-Saharan Africa&apos;s population lack access to an improved water <lb/>source that is available when needed, service continuity restricts access to safely managed <lb/>services. Household surveys, water regulators, and utilities all gather data on service conti-<lb/>nuity, but few studies have integrated these disparate datasets to quantify continuity-related <lb/>risk factors and inequalities. This study aimed to assess the added value of utility and regu-<lb/>lator data for international monitoring by assessing factors affecting piped water availability <lb/>in urban and peri-urban Zambia. Household &apos;user&apos; data from the 2018 Demographic and <lb/>Health Survey (n = 3047) were spatially linked to provider data from an international utility <lb/>database and regulator reports. Multilevel modelling quantified provider-related and socio-<lb/>economic risk factors for households reporting water being unavailable for at least one day <lb/>in the previous fortnight. 47% (95% CI: 45%, 49%) of urban and peri-urban households <lb/>reported water being unavailable for at least one full day, ranging from 18% (95% CI: 14%, <lb/>23%) to 76% (95% CI: 70%, 81%) across providers. Controlling for provider, home owner-<lb/>ship (odds ratio (OR) = 1.31; p &lt;0.01), speaking Luvale, Kaonde, Lunda (OR = 2.06; p <lb/>&lt;0.05) or Tonga (OR = 1.78; p &lt;0.1) as an ethnicity proxy, and dry season interview dates <lb/>(OR = 1.91; p &lt;0.05) were associated with household-reported interruptions. Households <lb/>using a neighbour&apos;s tap (OR = 1.33; p &lt;0.1) and in mid-wealth neighbourhoods (OR = 4.31; <lb/>p &lt;0.1) were more likely to report interruptions. For every $1000 increase in utility-level GDP <lb/>per capita, the odds of an interruption were 0.51 times less (p&lt;0.01). Substantial inequalities <lb/>in drinking-water availability were found between provider coverage areas. Spatial integra-<lb/>tion of user, provider and regulator data enriches analysis, providing a finer-scale perspec-<lb/>tive than otherwise possible. However, wider use of utility or regulator data requires <lb/>investment in monitoring of small-scale community supply intermittency and utility coverage <lb/>area data. <lb/>PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/>1 / 26 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Thomas-Possee MLH, Channon AA, Bain <lb/>RES, Wright JA (2024) Household, neighbourhood <lb/>and service provider risk factors for piped drinking-<lb/>water intermittency in urban and peri-urban <lb/>Zambia: A cross-sectional analysis. PLOS Water <lb/>3(2): e0000127. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal. <lb/>pwat.0000127 <lb/>Editor: Sara Marks, Eawag, SWITZERLAND <lb/>Received: March 23, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: October 4, 2023 <lb/>Published: February 5, 2024 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Thomas-Possee et al. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The original <lb/>contributions presented in the study are publicly <lb/>available. The data can be found at the following: <lb/>Service provider data can be accessed at: https:// <lb/>database.ib-net.org/countries_results?ctry= <lb/>29&amp;years=2018&amp;type=report&amp;ent=country&amp;mult= <lb/>true&amp;report=1&amp;table=true&amp;chart= <lb/>false&amp;chartType=column&amp;lang=EN&amp;exch=1. 2018 <lb/>DHS data is available on application via the public <lb/>repository: https://dhsprogram.com/methodology/ <lb/>survey/survey-display-542.cfm. Regulator data is <lb/>openly available and can be extracted from the <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The sixth Sustainable Development Goal (SDG) aims to &apos;ensure the availability and sustainable <lb/>management of water and sanitation for all&apos; by 2030 [1]. The accompanying target 6.1, is to <lb/>achieve universal and equitable access to safe and affordable drinking-water. The associated <lb/>indicator, 6.1.1, measures progress towards this target via the proportion of the population <lb/>using safely managed drinking-water services, requiring that drinking-water from an <lb/>improved service be available when needed [2]. Additionally, the World Health Organization <lb/>(WHO) outlines a global drinking-water availability benchmark which recommends that a <lb/>minimum of 50 litres/capita/day (LPCD) is needed to meet domestic needs, including wash-<lb/>ing, personal hygiene and cleaning [3, 4]. <lb/>Between 2000 and 2020 the proportion of the sub-Saharan African (SSA) population using <lb/>improved drinking-water sources that were available when needed increased from 41% to 59% <lb/>[5]. Over the same period, the population in SSA using piped water doubled from 185 to 380 mil-<lb/>lion. However, coverage of piped water services in urban areas has not kept up with population <lb/>growth, declining from 65% to 59% between 2000 and 2020 [5]. In 2015, an estimated 116 million <lb/>people in Africa were supplied by an unreliable piped water system prone to interruptions [6]. <lb/>Water services that are not available when needed may result in damage to water service infra-<lb/>structure, compromise water safety [7], adversely impact health [8, 9], and lead to additional <lb/>household expenditure on water storage, treatment and purchasing supplementary water [10], <lb/>with the latter often sourced from informal service providers and unimproved services [11]. <lb/>The transition from the Millennium Development Goals (MDGs) to the SDGs saw the spe-<lb/>cific addition of water availability to the international agenda, resulting in new demand for <lb/>data sources for monitoring [12]. Multiple sources, including household surveys (hereafter <lb/>&apos;user data&apos;), utility companies (hereafter &apos;provider data&apos;) and government regulators [13], hold <lb/>data on water service intermittency. Historically household survey questions on the availability <lb/>of drinking water services have not been harmonised, thus different countries may not use <lb/>consistent question and response wording. This complex data landscape is further exacerbated <lb/>by the challenges of measuring water availability, for which methods vary between studies <lb/>[14]. Metrics used include hours of service a day alongside service in the last week or month, <lb/>using household or per capita consumption per day, or the number of interruptions or break-<lb/>ages in a given time period [15]. In 2018, the Joint Monitoring Programme (JMP) of the WHO <lb/>and United Nations Children&apos;s Fund (UNICEF), who are responsible for international moni-<lb/>toring of SDG target 6.1, published a core question, &apos;In the last month, has there been any time <lb/>when your household did not have sufficient quantities of drinking-water when needed?&apos;, for <lb/>greater harmonisation and incorporation into household surveys for availability monitoring. <lb/>Since this is a new question and household surveys are implemented only every three to five <lb/>years, availability of internationally comparable survey data remains patchy. <lb/>As a result of patchy data and the use of multiple metrics of availability, national and inter-<lb/>national monitoring has been reliant on numerous data sources, presenting challenges for data <lb/>integration. Under the MDGs, monitoring was primarily dependent on household surveys <lb/>and census data [16], whereas more recently under the SDGs, there has been a shift towards <lb/>using information from regulators of providers alongside these more traditional sources [17]. <lb/>Regulators often produce annual reports which benchmark levels of service between different <lb/>providers. An additional data source concerning piped water service levels is available directly <lb/>from service provider records [18]. Many service providers report their performance data to <lb/>the International Benchmarking Network for Water and Sanitation Utilities (IBNET). At pres-<lb/>ent, IBNET provides the most systematic international data on provider reported water avail-<lb/>ability [18]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<front>following report: https://www.nwasco.org.zm/ <lb/>index.php/media-center/publications/water-supply-<lb/>and-sanitation-sector-reports. All code and publicly <lb/>available data has been provided as supplementary <lb/>materials to allow full transparency and replication <lb/>of the analysis that has been undertaken. <lb/>Funding: This research was supported by a South <lb/>Coast Doctoral Training Partnership (SCDTP) PhD <lb/>award, awarded to M.L.H.T-P., from the UK <lb/>Economic and Social Research Council (Grant No. <lb/>ES/P000673/1). This funding body had no role in <lb/>study design, data collection and analysis, decision <lb/>to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>To date, most studies that have sought to quantify risk factors for interruptions in water ser-<lb/>vices have focused almost exclusively on household surveys [19-21]. In comparing provider <lb/>and user data, one study conducted bespoke household surveys within four case study provider <lb/>coverage areas (PCAs) in Kenya and Ghana [11], whilst a second compared user-reported and <lb/>provider-reported service continuity at regional level in Peru [18]. However, since many <lb/>household surveys are now georeferenced [22], the new household survey question on service <lb/>continuity provides an opportunity for spatial integration of household reports of water service <lb/>interruptions with related statistics reported by service providers and regulators. Such spatial <lb/>integration would enable more detailed assessment of household versus regulator-or pro-<lb/>vider-reported service continuity for consistency, alongside evaluation of provider-level risk <lb/>factors for household-reported interruptions such as supply-side service management <lb/>indicators. <lb/>Barriers inhibiting household access to uninterrupted water services may exacerbate urban-<lb/>rural and socio-economic disparities that are evident in drinking-water services. In 2020, only <lb/>13% of the rural SSA population used services that were safely managed compared to 54% of <lb/>the urban population [5]. With the SDGs seeking to &apos;leave no one behind&apos;, identifying and <lb/>addressing drivers of inequalities in water, sanitation and hygiene (WASH) services is critical. <lb/>In a city-scale study of Lilongwe, Malawi, water rationing of the formal water system led to <lb/>more irregular supply in low-income informal settlements [23], highlighting one driver of <lb/>such inequalities. However, whilst wealth quintile was associated with rural household access <lb/>to continuous water in Bangladesh and Pakistan [19], there is little evidence on urban or per-<lb/>urban inequalities in household access to continuous piped water in addition to such inequali-<lb/>ties at city or PCA scale. <lb/>The primary objective of this study was therefore to assess the added value of utility and <lb/>regulator data in estimating piped water availability and quantifying risk factors for piped <lb/>water intermittency and related inequalities. As secondary objectives, the study aims to assess <lb/>whether household survey data are sufficient in isolation to quantify water availability and <lb/>related risk factors, alongside identifying barriers to more widespread integrated analyses of <lb/>household survey, utility, and regulatory data sets. Data on water service availability from <lb/>users, providers and regulators were first mapped to identify a suitable case study country to <lb/>examine risk factors for user-reported interruptions in piped water services in SSA. Since <lb/>Africa shows the least progress towards SDG 6 [5], and Zambia had near contemporaneous <lb/>data from users, providers and regulators that could be spatially linked, it was selected as the <lb/>case study. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Ethical approval <lb/>Ethical approval for the use of all data was received from the University of Southampton Ethics <lb/>Committee (Submission ID # 55516) on 10th March 2020. <lb/>Study country selection <lb/>A systematic secondary data audit (S1 Fig; S1-S3 Tables) was undertaken via the JMP&apos;s 2019 <lb/>country files [24] and IBNET database [25] to identify an African Union (AU) member state <lb/>for which household survey or population census data, government regulator data and water <lb/>providers all report at least one water availability metric (i.e. a measure of the quantity of <lb/>household water supplied, or continuity of water service provision) covering the same year(s). <lb/>To facilitate subsequent multi-level analysis, countries eligible for inclusion required <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>household survey or census data geographically disaggregated to sub-provincial level and pro-<lb/>vider or regulator data disaggregated to at least province level or equivalent coverage area. <lb/>Half of AU member states (n = 27) lacked relevant household survey or census data on <lb/>availability and were excluded (Fig 1). Of the remaining 27 that had user data, only five had <lb/>user, provider and regulator data that each captured water availability. For each of the five <lb/>shortlisted countries, the three data streams were mapped using ArcMap 10.7.1. This <lb/>Fig 1. Available data for each of the 54 African Union member states. (GADM 2018 base layer available at: https://gadm.org/index.html). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>determined whether subsequent integration of the three data streams was possible. Zambia <lb/>was the only country where the administrative geography of drinking-water supply was suffi-<lb/>ciently simple to facilitate spatial linkage of household survey and provider data since PCA <lb/>(which are also used by the regulator) coincided with province boundaries. All three Zambian <lb/>data sources also covered the same year (S1 Table). <lb/>Study site <lb/>Located in southern-central Africa, Zambia is a landlocked country with a 2019 population of <lb/>nearly 19 million [26]; 45% live in urban areas [27]. Zambia&apos;s trans-boundary catchment areas <lb/>result in fluctuations of surface water availability because of the varying water demands of <lb/>neighbouring states [28]. Renewable water resources are affected by inconsistent seasonal rain-<lb/>fall, characterised by periodic drought [29]. Mismanagement and rapid urban growth have <lb/>also caused considerable stress on groundwater resources [30]. <lb/>Urban and peri-urban piped drinking-water is supplied to over six million people by 11 <lb/>commercial Water and Sewerage Companies (WSCs) [31]. Approximately 4,656,375 piped <lb/>water connections supply drinking-water in 91 towns (S4 Table). In total, an estimated 46% of <lb/>the urban population have a safely managed water service, that is available when needed [32]. <lb/>In rural Zambia, 35% have an unimproved service compared to 9% of the urban population <lb/>[32]. The National Water Supply and Sanitation Council (NWASCO), a statutory body, is <lb/>responsible for regulating water and sanitation services across Zambia [33]. <lb/>Data sources and availability metrics <lb/>We used three main data sources in our study: <lb/>1. User data: nationally representative data from the Zambian Demographic and Health Sur-<lb/>vey (DHS) was used. This was implemented as a multi-stage cluster household survey from <lb/>18 th July 2018 to 24 th January 2019 [34]. Interviews were undertaken concurrently across all <lb/>provinces, using a stratified two-stage sample design [34]. We used geospatial data, geore-<lb/>ferenced to cluster level (comprising groups of approximately 25 households, selected at <lb/>random from a given census enumeration area). Cluster locations are provided as the mean <lb/>GPS coordinates for all participating households within each cluster, displaced within 2km <lb/>(for urban areas) to retain anonymity [35]. No sampling clusters were displaced outside of <lb/>their administrative district. To assess drinking-water availability, participating households <lb/>are asked &apos;In the last two weeks, was the water from your main source not available for at <lb/>least one full day?&apos;. <lb/>2. Provider data: To assess provider-level risk factors for reported interruptions, provider-<lb/>reported availability of piped services for all 11 WSCs was obtained from the IBNET data-<lb/>base for 2017, the most recent year available [36]. This includes metrics of availability, such <lb/>as continuity of service, as yearly average hours of service per day (hrs/day) [37], and yearly <lb/>average residential consumption in LPCD [38]. Details of non-revenue water, the difference <lb/>in water supplied and sold as a percentage of net water supplied [39], which inherently <lb/>affects service availability [40, 41] were also of interest as these reflect illegal use of piped <lb/>networks and water that has been stolen or leaked from the system. <lb/>3. Regulator data: since 2001, NWASCO have also annually reported on each WSC&apos;s perfor-<lb/>mance based on nine key indicators [33]. The annual average duration of water service <lb/>(hours/day) at the customer connection, and the average amount of water consumed in <lb/>LPCD were extracted from the publicly available 2018 NWASCO report [42] for each <lb/>WSC. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Household inclusion criteria and data integration <lb/>With less than 5% of rural households using piped drinking-water services [5], provider and <lb/>regulator data from NWASCO do not cover rural areas [43]. Given this, 8,117 households in <lb/>347 rural clusters (comprising 16% of households nationally reporting piped water as their <lb/>drinking-water source) were excluded (Fig 2). 47 households in two clusters which had miss-<lb/>ing GPS coordinates were also excluded. Provider service area boundaries for regulator and <lb/>Fig 2. Flowchart, showing reasons for excluding households participating in the 2018 Zambian Demographic and Health <lb/>Survey from analysis (n = number of households). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>provider data were derived through aggregation of district administrative boundaries for Zam-<lb/>bia from the Global Administrative Areas (GADM) database [44] and spatially joined to DHS <lb/>household clusters in ArcMap 10.7.1. The final dataset therefore included information on the <lb/>provider and regulator perspective of water availability at the PCA level (henceforth &apos;provider-<lb/>level&apos;) and the user perspective at household-level. <lb/>Households that did not drink piped water (whether from a connection in dwelling, yard/ <lb/>plot, neighbour or public tap/standpipe) were excluded (n = 1574) as they were not asked <lb/>about water service continuity [45], as were those who did not know about their piped water <lb/>continuity (n = 46) (Fig 2). <lb/>Outcome and explanatory variables <lb/>A binary outcome variable &apos;user reported availability of piped water&apos; was defined as respon-<lb/>dents reporting at least one full day of interruptions in the two weeks prior to being surveyed. <lb/>Explanatory variables at the household-, cluster-and provider-level were chosen to represent <lb/>socio-economic, water source, or neighbourhood characteristics that could constitute risk fac-<lb/>tors for piped water interruptions (S5 and S6 Tables). Household cluster-level variables were <lb/>created by aggregating data on households within each DHS cluster. <lb/>In modelling user-reported availability of piped water, the following household-level <lb/>explanatory variables were included: <lb/>• Since different types of connection are prone to different types of interruptions [46], type of <lb/>piped service (piped into dwelling, piped to neighbour, piped to yard/plot or public tap/ <lb/>standpipe) was included as a covariate. Users may also consume more water if it is piped to <lb/>the yard or home, than if located further afield, such as at a neighbour&apos;s or a public tap/ <lb/>standpipe [47]. <lb/>• The DHS&apos;s urban/rural wealth index was used as a household wealth variable. This considers <lb/>assets and services owned by rural populations alongside those owned by urban populations <lb/>[48]. Wealth relates to the type of piped service used [49] and affects household vulnerability <lb/>to interruptions. The wealthier pay tariffs more regularly, are less exposed to illegal connec-<lb/>tions or pipeline breakages, can afford to consume more water [50] and purchase storage <lb/>tanks which may protect from interruptions [51]. <lb/>• Month of interview was included as a proxy for seasonal water shortages [52]. Lower bore-<lb/>hole yields seasonally restrict groundwater-fed piped systems, while lower reservoir levels <lb/>seasonally affect piped networks drawing on surface waters [53]. Date of interview was <lb/>grouped into categories to align with the April-September dry season in 2018/19 [54] (dry <lb/>season: &apos;September 2018&apos;; &apos;July-August 2018&apos;, rainy season: &apos;October-November 2018&apos;; <lb/>&apos;December 2018-January 2019&apos;). <lb/>• Belonging to a minority ethnic group may restrict water access, since for example, locations <lb/>of public standpipes and household connections to mains services often disproportionately <lb/>favour majority ethnic groups [55]. Native language (English, Bemba, Lozi, Tonga, Kaonde/ <lb/>Lunda/Luvale or other) was therefore included as a proxy for ethnicity. <lb/>• Household size was included as it correlates with water consumption [51, 56], including <lb/>depletion rates of household stored water, ultimately affecting continuity. It also relates to <lb/>choice of service type [57, 58]. <lb/>• Home ownership relates to the choice of water service and ability to cope with piped water <lb/>interruptions. For example, home-owners can choose to invest in a water tank as an <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>important coping strategy [59]. Home ownership as reported by the men&apos;s and women&apos;s <lb/>DHS questionnaire respondents was included. <lb/>At DHS household cluster level, we included the following variables: <lb/>• Degree of urbanisation (classified as: urban centres/cities; urban clusters/towns/suburbs; <lb/>rural localities; and unpopulated) was included as a systematic review found lower reported <lb/>availability in rural settings [15]. This DHS variable was derived from 2015 settlement data <lb/>from the Global Human Settlement Layer (GHSL) project [60]. <lb/>• Since recently urbanised areas may have water infrastructure that has undergone develop-<lb/>ment and is less prone to maintenance-related interruptions, we included change in urbani-<lb/>sation (less urbanised; more urbanised; no change), based on the difference in GHSL <lb/>settlement class between 1990 and 2015. <lb/>• Neighbourhood wealth was included to reflect societal factors such as crime levels and disad-<lb/>vantaged communities [61], which in turn affect neighbourhood water infrastructure and <lb/>local capacity to cope with water intermittency. Cluster-level averages of the DHS&apos;s urban/ <lb/>rural wealth index were created. <lb/>• Newer neighbourhoods are less likely to have water infrastructure that is prone to failure, <lb/>due to general aging of materials and poor upkeep [11, 62] and neighbourhoods comprising <lb/>newly arrived migrants may lack sufficient social cohesion to lobby for services [63]. The <lb/>men&apos;s and women&apos;s DHS questionnaires ask respondents their length of residence in their <lb/>current home. As a proxy for the age of a cluster&apos;s neighbourhood and social cohesion, we <lb/>calculated the maximum length of residency for any men or women within a given cluster. <lb/>Water service provider-level variables were as follows: <lb/>• Since local economic development affects investment in WASH infrastructure [46, 64], we <lb/>calculated GDP per capita at the service provider level. 2015 provincial GDP [65] data were <lb/>converted to GDP per capita using 2015 provincial population statistics [66] (S7 Table), esti-<lb/>mating this via areal interpolation for those service provider areas that did not match to pro-<lb/>vincial boundaries. <lb/>• Non-revenue water was included to account for leakage or illegal use of piped networks [40, <lb/>41]. 2017 IBNET data which comprised the difference between water supplied and water <lb/>sold that is &apos;lost&apos; before it reaches the consumer, expressed as a percentage of net water sup-<lb/>plied [39]. <lb/>• Provider and regulator availability-reported average service hours expressed as hrs/day <lb/>and LCPCD were used and treated as continuous variables. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Stata 16.1 was used for all analysis [67]. Initially, provider, regulator and user-reported avail-<lb/>ability were compared through scatter plots and calculation of Pearson&apos;s correlation coeffi-<lb/>cients. The LPCD measures reported by providers and the regulator were also assessed against <lb/>the WHO benchmark of �50 LPCD to estimate the proportion of population within each <lb/>PCA not meeting this benchmark. <lb/>Descriptive and bivariate analysis for the outcome and explanatory variables, and associated <lb/>95% confidence intervals (CIs) and chi-square tests, used household survey weights [68] and <lb/>accounted for the complex survey design. Collinearity and missingness were examined for the <lb/>explanatory variables. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Comparison of a single-level unconditional model and a two-level variance components <lb/>model quantified the clustering in the dataset, confirming the appropriateness of multilevel <lb/>models. Households (level 1) were nested in household clusters (level 2). Two final models <lb/>were specified. Model 1 included significant household and household cluster level variables, <lb/>and accounted for provider-level variation using dummy variables, as the small number of <lb/>PCAs (&lt;25) made it inappropriate to include the PCA as a level [69]. Model 2 included signifi-<lb/>cant household, household cluster and provider explanatory variables. Backward elimination <lb/>with a significance threshold of p = 0.05 was used for both models and type of piped service <lb/>was retained as a control, despite not reaching this level of significance. An interaction term <lb/>was considered when a valid hypothesis existed and was subsequently deemed meaningful. <lb/>Survey weights were not used in the multilevel models, since the DHS only make weights avail-<lb/>able at the household level due to concerns about disclosure risk [70]. Therefore, they were <lb/>unavailable at the household cluster or provider level, as was required for this analysis. Lastly, <lb/>random effects were added to the two models to calculate the proportion of variance within <lb/>household clusters that could not be attributed to observed variables. <lb/>Issues of multicollinearity were found between regulator-and provider-reported LPCD or <lb/>service hours/day. Analysis found regulator and provider reporting for the same year (2017) to <lb/>be very similar for LPCD, and identical for hrs/day (see section entitled &apos;Data Sources and <lb/>Availability Metrics&apos;). Detailed analysis found a clear relationship between regulator LPCD in <lb/>2017 and 2018 (S2 Fig). LPCD was therefore used as the measure of availability. When com-<lb/>paring regulator and provider perspectives during initial descriptive analysis, 2017 data was <lb/>used for consistencies of the year. For all modelling however, to eliminate multicollinearity, <lb/>only 2018 regulator data was used as it matched the year of user-reported availability and <lb/>reflected the provider perspective. <lb/>Results <lb/>Comparison of provider, regulator and user availability <lb/>In 2017, regulator records for service continuity (hrs/day) perfectly matched the provider data <lb/>reported to IBNET. No utilities reported a continuous service for 24 hrs/day, with households <lb/>receiving piped water for 18.4 hrs/day on average. The regulator and providers reported simi-<lb/>lar quantities of water supplied (in LPCD). Reported quantities were positively correlated (r s = <lb/>0.86, p&lt;0.001), though higher average LPCD was reported by providers (S16 Table). <lb/>2018 regulator-reported service continuity (hrs/day) is associated with user-reported avail-<lb/>ability at PCA level (χ(4) = 56.04, p&lt;0.001). Where the regulator reported continuity of 20 <lb/>hrs/day, 54% of users reported interruptions. 2018 regulator LPCD and user-reported avail-<lb/>ability were associated (χ(9) = 220.63, p&lt;0.001), with evidence of a significant weak positive <lb/>correlation (r s = 0.05, p = 0.007). Where the regulator reported supplying �50 LPCD and sub-<lb/>sequently met the WHO benchmark, 55% of users reported an interruption to their supply. <lb/>User-reported availability by provider coverage areas <lb/>Overall, 47% (95% CI: 44%, 49%) of users reported experiencing at least one full day of inter-<lb/>ruptions in the two weeks prior to being surveyed in 2018. The proportion of households <lb/>reporting an interruption ranged from 77% (95% CI: 71%, 82%) in Kafubu WSC to 19% (95% <lb/>CI: 15%, 24%) in Lukanga WSC (S8 Table). Fig 3 shows 2018 user-reported availability along-<lb/>side regulator/provider-reported hrs/day. Only six of 177 household clusters had no household <lb/>reports of piped water interruptions. Lusaka WSC supplied piped drinking-water to 44% of <lb/>households in the sample. Southern WSC supplied a further 14% of sampled households. All <lb/>other WSCs provided drinking-water to between 2% and 9% of sampled households. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Bivariate analysis of user-reported water availability <lb/>1398 of 3047 households included in analysis reported an interruption to their service, with <lb/>the proportions of such households varying seasonally and by respondent&apos;s native language <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>Neither household wealth, household size, home ownership nor type of piped service were <lb/>statistically significantly related to service interruptions (p&gt;0.05). Month of interview was sig-<lb/>nificantly associated with interruptions to drinking-water service (p&lt;0.05), as was native lan-<lb/>guage (p&lt;0.05). As expected, type of piped service was significantly associated with household <lb/>wealth (p&lt;0.01). 68% of households in the richest wealth quintile had a piped service into <lb/>their dwelling, compared to 2% in the poorest wealth quintile. 45% of those in the poorest <lb/>wealth quintile used a public standpipe/tap compared to less than 1% in the richest wealth <lb/>quintile. <lb/>At the household cluster level, only degree of urbanisation and maximum length of resi-<lb/>dency were significantly associated with interruptions (p&lt;0.01) (Table 2). The relationship <lb/>was non-linear, with reported water interruptions lowest at 32.2% for clusters with a <lb/>Fig 3. Household and regulator/provider-reported availability of piped water in Zambia (2018). (Key to Utilities/Water and Sewerage Companies (WSC): <lb/>NWWSC -North Western WSC; MWSC-Mulonga WSC; NWSC-Nkana WSC; KWSC-Kafubu WSC; LGWSC-Lukanga WSC; LPWSC-Luapula WSC; <lb/>CWSC-Chambeshi WSC; ESWC-Eastern WSC; LWSC-Lusaka WSC; SWSC-Southern WSC; WWSC-Western WSC) (GADM 2018 base layer available at: <lb/>https://gadm.org/index.html). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Proportion of urban Zambian households reporting a piped water service interruption in the preceding <lb/>fortnight, by socio-economic characteristic (n = 3047). <lb/>User Characteristics <lb/>Weighted Percentages (%) of Households (n) <lb/>Reporting an Interruption <lb/>Chi squared (df), p-<lb/>value <lb/>Household Size <lb/>3.54 (4), 0.47 <lb/>1 person <lb/>42.6 (108) <lb/>2-3 people <lb/>48.2 (358) <lb/>4-6 people <lb/>47.2 (618) <lb/>7-9 people <lb/>46.7 (250) <lb/>10+ people <lb/>40.3 (64) <lb/>Native Language <lb/>52.69 (8), &lt;0.001** <lb/>English <lb/>25.8 (21) <lb/>Bemba <lb/>50.3 (597) <lb/>Lozi <lb/>49.1 (117) <lb/>Lunda, Kaonde, Luvale <lb/>50.8 (137) <lb/>Tonga <lb/>44.6 (142) <lb/>Other <lb/>44.1 (384) <lb/>Household Wealth <lb/>0.84 (4), 0.93 <lb/>Poorest <lb/>45.5 (236) <lb/>Poorer <lb/>44.3 (244) <lb/>Middle <lb/>47.0 (273) <lb/>Richer <lb/>48.8 (298) <lb/>Richest <lb/>47.1 (347) <lb/>Home Ownership <lb/>6.19 (2), 0.05 <lb/>At least partly owns house <lb/>50.8 (477) <lb/>Does not own <lb/>45.0 (855) <lb/>No information <lb/>43.0 (66) <lb/>Type of piped service <lb/>1.40 (2), 0.50 <lb/>Piped into dwelling <lb/>47.7 (322) <lb/>Piped to yard/plot or Public tap/ <lb/>standpipe <lb/>47.0 (793) <lb/>Piped to neighbour <lb/>44.7 (283) <lb/>Month of Interview (Season) <lb/>17.56 (3), 0.001** <lb/>July-August 2018 (Dry) <lb/>49.8 (653) <lb/>September 2018 (Dry) <lb/>43.8 (275) <lb/>October-November 2018 (Rainy) <lb/>47.2 (349) <lb/>December 2018-January 2019 <lb/>(Rainy) <lb/>32.6 (121) <lb/>Provider <lb/>245.87 (10), 0.93 <lb/>Chambeshi WSC <lb/>57.3 (148) <lb/>Eastern WSC <lb/>38.1 (78) <lb/>Kafubu WSC <lb/>77.0 (166) <lb/>Luapula WSC <lb/>58.2 (59) <lb/>Lukanga WSC <lb/>18.7 (52) <lb/>Lusaka WSC <lb/>42.4 (377) <lb/>Mulongo WSC <lb/>58.8 (73) <lb/>Nkana WSC <lb/>53.3 (121) <lb/>North Western WSC <lb/>48.2 (105) <lb/>Southern WSC <lb/>41.9 (135) <lb/>Western WSC <lb/>42.7 (84) <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>maximum length of residency of 31-40 years. At the provider level, GDP per capita, regulator-<lb/>and provider-reported service continuity, regulator-and provider-reported LPCD and non-<lb/>revenue water were all associated with service interruptions (p&lt;0.01). <lb/>User-reported inequalities in water availability by provider <lb/>Table 3 presents the socio-economic differences in household characteristics of those reporting <lb/>interruptions to their service, by provider. Ratios of those reporting an interruption are used <lb/>as a measure of inequality within each PCA. <lb/>Inequalities in those experiencing an interruption between providers are sometimes large, <lb/>though not necessarily significant, when considering a range of household characteristics. <lb/>Between PCAs, inconsistencies often existed in which household group reported the most <lb/>interruptions. In 82% of PCAs more one-person households experienced interruptions than <lb/>households with &gt;10 members. <lb/>In all PCAs, more households using a public standpipe or a service in their yard experi-<lb/>enced interruptions than those with a service in their dwelling. In Luapula WSC for example, <lb/>households using a public standpipe or a service in their yard were 8.9 times more likely to <lb/>experience an interruption. Households that at least partly owned their home were more likely <lb/>to report an interruption than those that did not, in all but one PCA. Variation exists in the <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>User Characteristics <lb/>Weighted Percentages (%) of Households (n) <lb/>Reporting an Interruption <lb/>Chi squared (df), p-<lb/>value <lb/>Total households reporting an <lb/>interruption: <lb/>46.7 (1398) <lb/>Note: n is an unweighted count <lb/>* p&lt;0.05 <lb/>**p&lt;0.01 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.t001 <lb/>Table 2. Association between household-reported availability and household cluster level and provider level <lb/>explanatory variables in urban Zambia (n = 3047). <lb/>Explanatory variable <lb/>Chi-squared (df) <lb/>p-value <lb/>Household Cluster Level Factors <lb/>Neighbourhood wealth <lb/>1.4 (2) <lb/>0.50 <lb/>Maximum length of residency <lb/>53.9 (3) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Change in urbanisation <lb/>1.4 (2) <lb/>0.49 <lb/>Degree of urbanisation <lb/>15.6 (3) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Water service provider-level Factors <lb/>GDP per capita at service provider level <lb/>245.9 (10) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Regulator hrs/day <lb/>56.0 (4) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Provider hrs/day <lb/>144.3 (6) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Regulator LPCD <lb/>220.6 (9) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Provider LPCD <lb/>245.9 10) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Non-Revenue Water <lb/>214.7 (10) <lb/>&lt;0.001** <lb/>Note <lb/>* p&lt;0.05 <lb/>**p&lt;0.01 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>magnitude of this inequality (Table 3). In 55% of PCAs, the richest households experienced <lb/>interruptions more than the poorest. Differences in household interruptions between those <lb/>speaking the majority and minority language are consistent between each PCA. Households <lb/>interviewed in the drier months of July-August were more likely to report an interruption <lb/>than those interviewed in wetter December-January, regardless of PCA. <lb/>Some patterns of socioeconomic inequalities in households reporting an interruption may <lb/>be mediated by PCA characteristics. In urbanised PCAs, the gap between households speaking <lb/>the majority language that report an interruption, compared to the minority language, is nar-<lb/>rower than for less urbanised PCAs. For both home ownership and household wealth, the rich-<lb/>est PCAs had the greatest inequalities in service interruption risk. Conversely, when <lb/>comparing households using a yard or public tap versus those with water piped to their dwell-<lb/>ing, or those speaking the majority versus minority language, the richest PCAs had the smallest <lb/>differences in those reporting an interruption. <lb/>Table 3. User-reported inequalities in piped water interruptions, by provider. <lb/>Provider <lb/>Percentage (%) (weighted) difference of households reporting an <lb/>interruption between population sub-groups with differing socio-<lb/>economic characteristics <lb/>Ratio of households reporting an interruption between population sub-<lb/>groups with differing socio-economic characteristics <lb/>Partly <lb/>Owns <lb/>Home <lb/>versus <lb/>Does <lb/>not <lb/>Own <lb/>Richest <lb/>versus <lb/>Poorest <lb/>HHs <lb/>One <lb/>person <lb/>versus <lb/>&gt;10 <lb/>people <lb/>HHs <lb/>Yard/ Public <lb/>Standpipe <lb/>versus <lb/>Supply in <lb/>Dwelling <lb/>Interviewed in <lb/>Dry (July/ <lb/>Aug) versus <lb/>Rainy Season <lb/>(Dec/Jan) <lb/>Majority <lb/>versus <lb/>Minority <lb/>Language <lb/>in WSC <lb/>Area <lb/>Partly <lb/>Owns <lb/>Home / <lb/>Does <lb/>not <lb/>Own <lb/>Richest / <lb/>Poorest <lb/>HHs <lb/>One <lb/>person / <lb/>&gt;10 <lb/>people <lb/>HHs <lb/>Yard/ <lb/>Public <lb/>Standpipe / <lb/>Supply in <lb/>Dwelling <lb/>Interviewed in <lb/>Dry (July/ <lb/>Aug) / Rainy <lb/>Season (Dec/ <lb/>Jan) <lb/>Majority / <lb/>Minority <lb/>Language <lb/>in WSC <lb/>Area <lb/>Chambeshi <lb/>WSC <lb/>4.8 <lb/>-29.5 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>21.4 <lb/>16.5 <lb/>93.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>65.8 <lb/>Eastern <lb/>WSC <lb/>20.6 <lb/>-2.5 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>25.4 <lb/>7.6 <lb/>84.5 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>28.8 <lb/>Kafubu <lb/>WSC <lb/>32.3 <lb/>20.8 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>19.2 <lb/>45.2 <lb/>63.1 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>2.9 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>6.3 <lb/>45.4 <lb/>Luapula <lb/>WSC <lb/>15.7 <lb/>-7.5 <lb/>-5.4 <lb/>62.6 <lb/>32.6 <lb/>84.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>8.9 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>Lukanga <lb/>WSC <lb/>19.5 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>49.0 <lb/>53.8 <lb/>41.9 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>14.1 <lb/>Lusaka <lb/>WSC <lb/>39.0 <lb/>21.0 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>44.9 <lb/>48.8* <lb/>46.5 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>2.1 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>-* <lb/>116.1 <lb/>Mulongo <lb/>WSC <lb/>39.2 <lb/>19.3 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>55.9 <lb/>29.8 <lb/>73.7 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>4.1 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>69.4 <lb/>Nkana <lb/>WSC <lb/>44.0 <lb/>15.4 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>55.9 <lb/>55.6* <lb/>62.8* <lb/>4.0 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>5.8 <lb/>-* <lb/>-* <lb/>North <lb/>Western <lb/>WSC <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>17.9 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>40.1 <lb/>52.0 <lb/>53.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>3.3 <lb/>10.1 <lb/>44.4 <lb/>Southern <lb/>WSC <lb/>18.0 <lb/>-19.5 <lb/>10.7 <lb/>16.2 <lb/>63.4 <lb/>47.6* <lb/>1.7 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>-* <lb/>Western <lb/>WSC <lb/>21.6 <lb/>-31.1 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>12.0 <lb/>29.6 <lb/>71.8* <lb/>2.4 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>-* <lb/>Negative difference values and ratios below 1.0 indicate lower reported interruptions in the first population sub-group named in column heading. Counts and weighted <lb/>percentages of the number of households reporting an interruption for each inequality are presented in S9-S14 Tables. S15 Table &amp; S3 Fig present household cluster <lb/>inequalities in water availability by provider. <lb/>*Household did not report an interruption in one of the socio-economic categories being compared. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Multi-level logistic regression <lb/>Table 4 includes the multi-level logistic regression results for two models. Model 1 includes <lb/>selected household and household cluster factors that explain inequalities in piped-water inter-<lb/>ruptions with provider accounted for via dummy variables. Model 2 shows the association <lb/>between socioeconomic characteristics at the household, household cluster and provider-level <lb/>and the likelihood of households reporting an interruption. <lb/>When provider is accounted for in model 1, type of piped service is not significant, whereas <lb/>in model 2 it is. Households using a neighbour&apos;s water had 33% greater odds of reporting an <lb/>interruption than those with water piped to their dwelling (p&lt;0.1). In model 1, households <lb/>interviewed at the peak of the dry season had 1.91 times the odds of an interruption than those <lb/>interviewed in the middle of the rainy season (p&lt;0.05). In model 2, households interviewed <lb/>outside the wettest months of December-January had 2-3 times the odds of experiencing an <lb/>interruption (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>In both models, household ownership is significantly associated with experiencing an inter-<lb/>ruption. The odds of experiencing an interruption were 1.31-1.32 times higher for those that <lb/>at least partly owned their home (p&lt;0.001). Availability of services varies significantly with <lb/>household native language. In both models, those who speak Luvale/Kaonde/Lunda have <lb/>greater odds of experiencing an interruption than English speaking households (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>When accounting for provider, compared to English speaking households, Tonga speakers <lb/>were 1.78 times more likely to have an interruption (p&lt;0.1) whereas in model 2, Bemba speak-<lb/>ing households had 1.88 time the odds (p&lt;0.1). <lb/>Households in neighbourhoods classed as having mid-level wealth had 4.31 times the odds <lb/>of experiencing an interruption than those in poor neighbourhoods (p&lt;0.01) (model 2). <lb/>Neighbourhood wealth was found to interact with regulator-reported service availability. <lb/>Compared to poor clusters, for every one litre increase in regulator reported LPCD, house-<lb/>holds in mid-wealth clusters had 3% lower odds of reporting an interruption (p&lt;0.05). <lb/>GDP per capita is the only provider-level factor associated with household availability <lb/>(model 2). For each $1000 increase in GDP per capita, the odds of reporting an interruption <lb/>are 0.51 times less (p&lt;0.01). GDP per capita at service provider level interacts with regulator-<lb/>reported LPCD. For every one unit increase in regulator-reported LPCD and GDP per capita <lb/>at service provider level, the odds of having an interruption were 1.02 times greater (p&lt;0.01). <lb/>Substantial variations between providers are evident when controlling for home ownership, <lb/>type of piped service, month of interview and native language (model 1). When comparing the <lb/>odds of households reporting an interruption to areas supplied by Lusaka WSC, households <lb/>supplied by Lukanga WSC had 64% lower odds of experiencing an interruption (p&lt;0.05) <lb/>whilst in Nkana the odds were 2.24 times higher (p&lt;0.05) and Mulongo WSC 3.77 times <lb/>higher (p&lt;0.05). Similarly, in Chambeshi WSC the odds of having an interruption were 2.43 <lb/>times higher (p&lt;0.05) and in Luapula they were 2.89 (p&lt;0.05). In Kafubu WSC, households <lb/>have eightfold increased odds of reporting experiencing an interruption than those whose pro-<lb/>vision is from Lusaka WSC (p&lt;0.01). <lb/>The variability in households&apos; likelihood of experiencing an interruption that was not <lb/>explained by the household and household cluster factors used in the multilevel models was exam-<lb/>ined through the Intra-Class Correlation (ICC). The ICC for model 1 shows that 27% of the <lb/>remaining unexplained variation in reported interruptions lies between household clusters, whilst <lb/>73% lies within household clusters. In model 2, 31% of the variation lies between clusters whereas <lb/>69% is within clusters. These results suggest that between a quarter and a third of the likelihood of <lb/>experiencing an interruption is related to the cluster that someone lives in, with the remainder <lb/>due to the specific household, after accounting for the variables within the models. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 4. Multi-level logistic regression analysis of user-reported interruptions to piped water services in the urban and peri-urban population of Zambia, 2018 <lb/>(n = 3047, groups = 177). <lb/>Model 1 a <lb/>Model 2 b <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>Std.Err. <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>Std.Err. <lb/>Intercept <lb/>0.18*** <lb/>0.089 <lb/>0.08*** <lb/>0.05 <lb/>Household-level Factors <lb/>Native Language (ref.: English) <lb/>Bemba <lb/>1.53 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>1.88* <lb/>0.60 <lb/>Luvale, Kaonde, Lunda <lb/>2.06** <lb/>0.74 <lb/>2.30** <lb/>0.81 <lb/>Lozi <lb/>1.81 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>1.85 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>Other <lb/>1.60 <lb/>0.52 <lb/>1.77 <lb/>0.57 <lb/>Tonga <lb/>1.78* <lb/>0.62 <lb/>1.73 <lb/>0.59 <lb/>Month of Interview (season) (ref.: Dec 2018-Jan 2019 (Rainy)) <lb/>Sept 2018 (Dry) <lb/>1.64 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>2.95*** <lb/>1.12 <lb/>Oct-Nov 2018 (Rainy) <lb/>1.61 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>2.36** <lb/>0.80 <lb/>July-Aug 2018 (Dry) <lb/>1.91** <lb/>0.61 <lb/>2.51*** <lb/>0.84 <lb/>Type of piped service (ref.: Piped into dwelling) <lb/>Piped to yard/plot or Public tap/standpipe <lb/>1.20 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>1.24 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>Piped to neighbour <lb/>1.32 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>1.33* <lb/>0.21 <lb/>Home ownership (ref: Does not own) <lb/>At least partly owns <lb/>1.31*** <lb/>0.13 <lb/>1.32*** <lb/>0.13 <lb/>No information <lb/>1.10 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>Provider-level Dummy Variable <lb/>Provider (ref.: Lusaka WSC) <lb/>Chambeshi WSC <lb/>2.43** <lb/>0.94 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Eastern WSC <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Kafubu WSC <lb/>8.02*** <lb/>3.40 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Luapula WSC <lb/>2.89** <lb/>1.45 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Lukanga WSC <lb/>0.36** <lb/>0.15 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Mulongo WSC <lb/>3.77** <lb/>1.85 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Nkana WSC <lb/>2.24* <lb/>0.90 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>North Western WSC <lb/>1.39 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Southern WSC <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Western WSC <lb/>1.18 <lb/>0.54 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Household cluster-level Factors <lb/>Neighbourhood Wealth (ref.: Poor) <lb/>Middle <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>4.31* <lb/>3.29 <lb/>Rich <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>3.22 <lb/>2.31 <lb/>Provider-level Factors <lb/>Regulator LPCD <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1.01 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>GDP per Capita at Service Provider Level <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.51*** <lb/>0.11 <lb/>Regulator LPCD x Neighbourhood Wealth (ref.: Poor) <lb/>Middle <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.97** <lb/>0.01 <lb/>Rich <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.98* <lb/>0.01 <lb/>Regulator LPCD x GDP per Capita at Service Provider Level <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1.02*** <lb/>0.01 <lb/>Random-effects Parameters <lb/>Between PSU variance <lb/>1.21 <lb/>0.19 <lb/>1.47 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>Intraclass Correlation Coefficient (ICC) <lb/>Intra-PSU correlation coefficient <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Discussion <lb/>Insights into equalities in piped water continuity through integrated <lb/>analysis of survey, regulator, and provider data sets <lb/>Integrated analysis of utility, regulator, and household survey data provides some insights into <lb/>inequalities and risk factors for piped water continuity in urban Zambia that would not be <lb/>apparent from analysing any one data set in isolation. There are few statistically significant <lb/>inequalities at the household level (S17 Table, Model 2) and significant cluster-and provider-<lb/>level predictors. After controlling for household characteristics, this nationally representative <lb/>analysis of urban DHS data highlights provider-level inequality in service continuity (Fig 3) <lb/>[13]. 19% of households reported an interruption in Lukanga, compared to 77% in Kafubu <lb/>WSC (Table 1), with Kafubu, Mulongo, and several other WSCs having significantly higher <lb/>odds of household-reported interruptions relative to Lusaka after controlling for household <lb/>characteristics (Table 4). Similarly, a study [18] comparing DHS with IBNET for Peruvian <lb/>regions also found high inter-provider and inter-province intermittency, with lower house-<lb/>hold-reported intermittency in Lima, the capital, than most other regions. Whilst there is <lb/>some tentative evidence in our models that such provider-level variation in water continuity <lb/>may relate to utility operational indicators such as LPCD, this variation is also associated with <lb/>regional socio-economic variation such as in GDP per capita (Table 4). <lb/>Alongside provider-level patterns, variation in household-reported water continuity is evi-<lb/>dent at the household and household cluster level (Tables 2 &amp; 4). Regulatory reports and pro-<lb/>vider performance databases such as IBNET do not differentiate the level of service provided <lb/>to different household groups within their PCAs. However, it is known that ethnic minorities, <lb/>the poor, and other disadvantaged groups may receive poorer quality services [13]. In this <lb/>analysis, we integrated PCA boundaries with household survey data to examine such inequali-<lb/>ties. We find some evidence of urban inequalities in the availability of piped water services in <lb/>relation to ethnicity (measured via native language), home ownership and seasonality, but not <lb/>household wealth. We find no significant evidence that such inequalities vary between PCAs. <lb/>Key findings concerning household-and cluster-level risk factors were as follows: <lb/>• We found native English speakers less likely to report interruptions compared to respon-<lb/>dents speaking all other native languages. This could reflect the regional distribution of eth-<lb/>nicity in relation to service availability. Ethnicity is an important factor contributing to water <lb/>inequalities globally, with indigenous populations comprising 15% of the world&apos;s poor [1]. <lb/>• Households in mid-wealth clusters were less likely to experience an interruption than those <lb/>in poor clusters. This could reflect households in wealthier neighbourhoods adopting <lb/>Table 4. (Continued) <lb/>Model 1 a <lb/>Model 2 b <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>Std.Err. <lb/>Odds Ratio <lb/>Std.Err. <lb/>Log likelihood <lb/>-1787.03 <lb/>-1799.69 <lb/>Deviance <lb/>3574.00 <lb/>3599.00 <lb/>*** p&lt;0.01 <lb/>** p&lt;0.05 <lb/>* p&lt;0.1; PSU: Primary Sampling Unit (household clusters) <lb/>a <lb/>Only significant household and household cluster level variables, plus provider dummy variable <lb/>b Only significant household, household cluster level and provider variables <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127.t004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>protective measures against interruptions [10, 71] and having greater capacity to address ser-<lb/>vice network failures. <lb/>• Counter to our hypothesis, we found households who owned their home were more likely to <lb/>experience interruptions than those that did not. <lb/>• Households using a neighbour&apos;s piped water also had higher odds of experiencing an inter-<lb/>ruption than those with water piped to their dwelling. This could reflect household reluc-<lb/>tance to sell their water to neighbours during times of water scarcity. <lb/>• As suggested by other authors [18], reported water continuity varied seasonally, with house-<lb/>holds interviewed in peak rainy season having lower odds of reporting an interruption <lb/>(Tables 1 and 4). <lb/>Although multi-country analyses suggest exposure to microbially contaminated or inade-<lb/>quately chlorinated water is often greater among poorer households [72, 73], we found Zam-<lb/>bian households in both poor and wealthy clusters were more exposed to water interruptions <lb/>relative to those in mid-wealth clusters. Criteria concerning availability and water safety may <lb/>therefore affect socio-economic inequalities in access to safely managed water services. <lb/>Comparability and consistency of survey versus provider and regulatory <lb/>data <lb/>It is clear the data landscape is complex, which is exacerbated by the contrasting approaches to <lb/>measuring availability [14, 15]. The extent of our analysis has been limited due to the use of <lb/>two very different metrics of availability: regulator and provider reported yearly mean service <lb/>hours or LPCD, whilst DHS household survey respondents reported service interruptions in <lb/>the past fortnight. <lb/>Despite this, we find household survey reporting is correlated with provider/regulator <lb/>reporting (S17 Table). Differences existed between provider and regulator reporting depend-<lb/>ing on the metric in question, however generally they are highly consistent with one another <lb/>(S16 Table). This is as expected given NWASCO regulator reports use provider data, but the <lb/>use of regulator data is preferable for monitoring, given regulator independence from service <lb/>provision and incentives for providers to report higher service continuity [11]. <lb/>In linking household survey, regulator and provider data sets to evaluate their consistency, <lb/>we adopted a different approach to a previous study in Peru [18]. This study aggregated data <lb/>for PCAs to region level and compared household-and regulator-reported metrics at the <lb/>region level. In contrast, we used multi-level modelling to assess whether contextual provider-<lb/>or regulator-reported water continuity metrics were associated with household-level reports of <lb/>service interruptions. Our approach thus enables simultaneous evaluation of provider-level <lb/>versus household-level risk factors for supply interruptions, whilst avoiding the known prob-<lb/>lems of areal aggregation [74]. Particularly for larger service providers, our approach also pro-<lb/>vides insights into intra-provider socio-economic inequalities in access to an uninterrupted <lb/>water service via household reports collected independent of the service provider (Table 2). <lb/>Limitations affecting Zambia study <lb/>This analysis only captures household respondents who report an interruption of at least one <lb/>full day in the two weeks prior to being surveyed. As such, recall bias will likely exist in the <lb/>user data [75] whereby respondents may fail to remember or misremember interruptions in <lb/>their service. For example, respondents using a 2-week recall period systematically under-<lb/>reported child diarrhoea relative to a 1-week period [76]. Additionally, respondents who <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>spend more time away from their homes may be unaware of short duration outages. Thus, <lb/>there are likely to be households who experience shorter-and longer-term service interrup-<lb/>tions, that are not captured in household survey data. Source of drinking-water and water used <lb/>for other purposes form inputs to the DHS wealth index, but not reported supply interrup-<lb/>tions. This complicates WASH inequality analyses [77] and could have increased collinearity <lb/>between the wealth index and source type in our models, but we did not find empirical evi-<lb/>dence for this. <lb/>The quality of provider and regulator data depends greatly on the accuracy of the data <lb/>reported by each WSC [14]. Data supplied by providers may be of limited reliability as they <lb/>may lack any form of independent verification [78]. <lb/>Between datasets, definitional differences existed in the classification of urban/rural areas <lb/>[31, 34]. Households were excluded based on the DHS urban/rural classification, despite the <lb/>regulator or provider potentially classifying them as urban. Additionally, given the DHS used a <lb/>2010 rural/urban classification [34, 79], it is likely that some rural areas may have become <lb/>urbanised. The issue of differing classifications is exacerbated by the use of GHSL population <lb/>data to create cluster-level locality and change in urbanisation variables. GHSL data uses a <lb/>finer spatial scale classification [80] that differs to the DHS classification. Thus, despite exclud-<lb/>ing all rural households from the analysis, inconsistencies between datasets are evident. For <lb/>both variables, some household clusters are classified as rural or unpopulated areas, despite the <lb/>DHS classifying them as urban. This could also be a result of the DHS&apos;s displacement of house-<lb/>hold cluster locations [35], though the effect is likely minimal as GPS clusters were not dis-<lb/>placed across province boundaries and WSCs are coincident with provinces. <lb/>The higher-level explanatory variables for wealth also have limitations. The neighbourhood <lb/>wealth variable was calculated by aggregating household-level DHS wealth index values to <lb/>household cluster level. This will however mean that closely located extreme differences in <lb/>wealth are unaccounted for. The provincial wealth variable used provincial GDP data that is <lb/>based on where industries produce their goods or where their head office is located. Therefore, <lb/>the data may not be a true representation of wealth in each PCA [65]. <lb/>Additional explanatory variables were considered for analysis, including &apos;voice&apos; [9], gender <lb/>of the person collecting water [81], storage tank ownership [82] and blue water scarcity [83]. <lb/>In all instances, inclusion was not possible as there was either no available data, limited vari-<lb/>ability across Zambia or reasonable proxies did not exist. <lb/>Barriers to methodological transferability <lb/>Our integrated analysis of household survey and water utility databases highlights data-related <lb/>barriers at present to methodological transferability at both international and national level. In <lb/>the context of Zambia, comparison has been made possible by a relatively simple data land-<lb/>scape, where PCAs largely coincide with DHS regions. At present, exploring inequalities else-<lb/>where via this methodology would only be possible in countries where household surveys have <lb/>measured service interruptions and for WSCs serving large populations, with known geo-<lb/>graphic coverage areas. Given that household survey cluster coordinates are randomly dis-<lb/>placed to preserve confidentiality [22], misallocation of households to providers is more likely <lb/>where PCAs are small. Thus, our approach is more suited to countries with several large-scale <lb/>water service providers, as opposed to countries dominated by small-scale providers or a single <lb/>national provider (e.g. Ghana Water Company Limited). Elsewhere, the availability of data <lb/>from all three streams is currently restricted to eastern and southern Africa (Fig 1 and S1 Fig; <lb/>S1-S3 Tables), but analysis will become possible in more countries as data availability <lb/>increases. By 2030, the data landscape may change considerably with greater availability of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>household survey data on water service continuity, from government via regulators, from utili-<lb/>ties as service providers and potentially other new forms of data such as via social media or <lb/>sensors [84]. Therefore, whilst the current transferability of methods is reliant on present-day <lb/>data availability, as monitoring expands, the applicability and transferability of this analysis <lb/>may broaden. <lb/>Within Zambia, data were only available for urban and peri-urban services from the pro-<lb/>vider and regulator, which limited the scope of this analysis to include only the urban and <lb/>peri-urban third of the Zambian population. Compared to user data which has national cover-<lb/>age, both datasets only include the population served by large-scale reporting commercial utili-<lb/>ties and may exclude services from small-scale private schemes/companies [85], micro-<lb/>operators managing delegated services [86], and community-managed piped services [18]. <lb/>Implications for international monitoring <lb/>The JMP only makes estimates for safely managed drinking-water when there are data avail-<lb/>able on water quality and at least one other element (accessibility or availability) that repre-<lb/>sents at least half of the population in question (e.g. country) [87]. The development of <lb/>methods which could help to reach this criterion threshold, for example by using data from <lb/>multiple perspectives, will be critical in better analysing WASH for international agendas such <lb/>as the SDGs. Improvements in data, coupled with a standardised process by which data are <lb/>processed to give nationally representative and internationally comparable insights into drink-<lb/>ing-water availability are needed, especially in order to understand inequalities between popu-<lb/>lation groups [16]. <lb/>Definitions of provider-reported average service hours requires further clarity. For exam-<lb/>ple, does it represent the hours a pump in a piped network is operated or the average duration <lb/>of service households receive? Several suggestions have been made to address this, such as reg-<lb/>ular random household surveys by providers or the use of sensors to detect outages [18]. At <lb/>present, provider reporting of hrs/day is unclear and it is unknown what the number of days <lb/>between service is. <lb/>We recommend further smaller scale studies of drinking-water availability. Whilst our anal-<lb/>ysis bears similarities to Rawas et al. [18] in its regional/provincial analysis, future work that <lb/>resonates more closely with Bellaubi et al.&apos;s [11] finer scale case study analysis would give <lb/>more detailed understanding of the availability of piped services. To achieve this, we recom-<lb/>mend providers and regulators report availability for smaller geographical units so that house-<lb/>holds can be better matched with provider jurisdictions. This would also be enhanced by <lb/>utilities providing their service areas as coverage area boundaries to IBNET to facilitate data <lb/>integration. Additionally, a future multi-country study could potentially explore other IBNET-<lb/>derived management indicators (e.g. concerning staff training or adequacy infra-structure <lb/>investment [88]) alongside those relating to service availability. However, care would be <lb/>needed to control for other regional covariates that could explain water service continuity, <lb/>such as regional GDP. <lb/>Greater uptake of the JMP&apos;s expanded WASH questions by national statistical agencies via <lb/>household surveys, such as the DHS, would facilitate further, more widespread evaluation of <lb/>regulator and provider data concerning water availability. Alongside the DHS question ana-<lb/>lysed in our study, these expanded questions also include asking households &apos;how many hours <lb/>per day is water supplied on average?&apos; [2]. Whilst uptake such questions depends on survey <lb/>implementation resources and national priorities [15], it would enable direct comparison with <lb/>regulator and provider reporting of service availability via a metric common to all data <lb/>sources. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Conclusion <lb/>This study demonstrates the additional insights into risk factors associated with piped drink-<lb/>ing-water availability by incorporating utility and regulatory data into household survey analy-<lb/>sis for urban and peri-urban Zambia. At household and household cluster (neighbourhood) <lb/>level, when adjusting for confounders through multi-level modelling, inequalities are minimal. <lb/>Wealth was the only neighbourhood risk factor found to influence service availability. At the <lb/>household level, home ownership, month of interview, native language and type of service had <lb/>a modest effect. At provider-level, inequalities between PCAs were found in household report-<lb/>ing of interruptions to services. <lb/>Our analysis builds on existing assessments of drinking-water services [11, 18] by including <lb/>the additional perspective of the regulator. We find correlations between user, provider and <lb/>regulator reports of service availability, but direct comparison is difficult, due to variations in <lb/>availability metrics used. Limited data availability also restricts more widespread, integrated <lb/>analyses of these data in rural areas and across SSA. Moving forward, greater availability of <lb/>water service continuity data from all three data sources should enable assessment of socio-<lb/>economic and geographic inequalities in access to uninterrupted water services and potential <lb/>for understanding how water management indicators relate to household-related interruptions <lb/>in a wider set of countries. However, more widespread, integrated use of utility or regulator <lb/>data requires investment in government monitoring of intermittency in small-scale commu-<lb/>nity supplies to better understand rural service access. It also requires investment in utility cov-<lb/>erage area map layers to facility spatial data integration with household surveys. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Flowchart showing inclusion criteria for identifying study country, with reasons <lb/>for excluding African Union member states. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Scatterplot showing the similarities between 2017 and 2018 regulator reported <lb/>LPCD. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Provider inequalities compared to differences in household socioeconomic charac-<lb/>teristics, for households that reported experiencing an interruption to their piped water <lb/>service. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Year of all available data streams for the 13 shortlisted countries. Colour depicts <lb/>the data stream with dark green = regulator data, mid-green = user data and light <lb/>green = provider data; black box indicates where data for all three streams is available for the <lb/>same year. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Table. Metrics of availability used by all available data streams for the 13 shortlisted <lb/>countries. Colour depicts the data stream with dark green = regulator data, mid-green = user <lb/>data and light green = provider data; black box indicates where the same metric of availability <lb/>is used for multiple data streams for a given country. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Table. Level of disaggregation for all available data streams for the 13 shortlisted coun-<lb/>tries. Colour depicts the data stream with dark green = regulator data, mid-green = user data <lb/>and light green = provider data; black box indicates where the same metric of availability is <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">used for multiple data streams for a given country. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S4 Table. Commercial Water Supply Company (WSC) connections and population ser-<lb/>viced in 2018. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S5 Table. Outcome and explanatory variables, and their sources, included in the multi-<lb/>level model analysis. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S6 Table. DHS household and men&apos;s survey questions relating to source and continuity of <lb/>drinking-water supply and socio-economic characteristics. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S7 Table. GDP and GDP per capita based on 2015 current prices, in Zambian Kwacha <lb/>(ZKW) and US Dollars (US$) for WSC coverage areas. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S8 Table. Proportion of households reporting a full day&apos;s interruption in their piped water <lb/>supply in the preceding fortnight, per provider, with 95% confidence intervals. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S9 Table. User-reported inequalities, by month of interview, in piped-water interruptions <lb/>by provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S10 Table. User-reported inequalities, by type of supply, in piped-water interruptions by <lb/>provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S11 Table. User-reported inequalities, by household size, in piped-water interruptions by <lb/>provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S12 Table. User-reported inequalities, by household wealth, in piped-water interruptions <lb/>by provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S13 Table. User-reported inequalities, by tenure, in piped-water interruptions by provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S14 Table. User-reported inequalities, by native language, in piped-water interruptions by <lb/>provider. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S15 Table. User-reported inequalities in piped-water interruptions by provider: The per-<lb/>centage (weighted) of households, by household cluster characteristics, reporting an inter-<lb/>ruption to their supply in each PCA. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S16 Table. Assessment of average annual piped water service delivery in urban and peri-<lb/>urban Zambia in 2017/18 (n = 3047 HHs). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S17 Table. Exploration of clustering in reported service interruptions through comparison <lb/>of a single-level unconditional model with a two-level variance components model <lb/>(n = 3047). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Data. <lb/>(7Z) <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee, Andrew A. Channon, Robert E. S. Bain, James <lb/>A. Wright. <lb/>Data curation: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee. <lb/>Formal analysis: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee. <lb/>Funding acquisition: Andrew A. Channon, James A. Wright. <lb/>Investigation: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee, Andrew A. Channon, James A. Wright. <lb/>Methodology: Andrew A. Channon, James A. Wright. <lb/>Project administration: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee. <lb/>Supervision: Andrew A. Channon, Robert E. S. Bain, James A. Wright. <lb/>Visualization: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Mair L. H. Thomas-Possee. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Andrew A. Channon, Robert E. S. Bain, James A. Wright. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. UN Water. Sustainable Development Goal 6: Synthesis Report on Water and Sanitation. United <lb/>Nations. New York, USA; 2018. <lb/>2. WHO, UNICEF. Core questions on water, sanitation and hygiene for household surveys: 2018 update. <lb/>New York, NY, USA.; 2018. <lb/>3. Howard G, Bartram J. Domestic Water Quantity, Service Level and Health. World Health Organization. <lb/>Geneva, Switzerland; 2003. <lb/>4. Howard G, Bartram J, Williams A, Overbo A, Fuente D, Geere J-A. Domestic water quantity, service <lb/>level and health, second edition. World Health Organization. Geneva, Switzerland; 2020. <lb/>5. WHO, UNICEF. Progress on household drinking water, sanitation and hygiene 2000-2020: five years <lb/>into the SDGs. Geneva, Switzerland; 2021. <lb/>6. Bivins AW, Sumner T, Kumpel E, Howard G, Cumming O, Ross I, et al. Estimating infection risks and <lb/>the global burden of diarrheal disease attributable to intermittent water supply using QMRA. Environ-<lb/>mental Science and Technology. 2017; 51: 7542-7551. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est.7b01014 PMID: <lb/>28582618 <lb/>7. Kumpel E, Nelson KL. Comparing microbial water quality in an intermittent and continuous piped water <lb/>supply. Water Research. 2013; 47: 5176-5188. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.watres.2013.05.058 PMID: <lb/>23866140 <lb/>8. Lechtenfeld T. Why does piped water not reduce diarrhea for children? Evidence from urban Yemen. <lb/>Courant Research Centre: Poverty, Equity and Growth-Discussion Papers. Go ¨ttingen: Georg-August-<lb/>Universita ¨t Go ¨ttingen, Courant Research Centre-Poverty, Equity and Growth (CRC-PEG); 2012. <lb/>9. Majuru B, Suhrcke M, Hunter PR. How Do Households Respond to Unreliable Water Supplies? A Sys-<lb/>tematic Review. International Journal of Environmental Health Research. 2016; 13. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3390/ijerph13121222 PMID: 27941695 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>10. Pattanayak SK, Yang J-C, Whittington D, Bal Kumar KC. Coping with unreliable public water supplies: <lb/>Averting expenditures by households in Kathmandu, Nepal. Water Resources Research. 2005; 41: 1-<lb/>11. https://doi.org/10.1029/2003WR002443 <lb/>11. Bellaubi F, Visscher JT. Water service delivery in Kenya and Ghana: an area-based assessment of <lb/>water utility performance. Water International. 2014; 39: 952-968. https://doi.org/10.1080/02508060. <lb/>2015.985976 <lb/>12. Yu W, Wardrop NA, Bain RES, Lin Y, Zhang C, Wright JA. A Global Perspective on Drinking-Water and <lb/>Sanitation Classification: An Evaluation of Census Content. Hills RK, editor. PLOS ONE. 2016; 11: <lb/>e0151645. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pone.0151645 PMID: 26986472 <lb/>13. WHO, UNICEF. Progress on household drinking water, sanitation and hygiene 2000-2017. Special <lb/>focus on inequalities. New York, USA.; 2019. <lb/>14. Majuru B, Suhrcke M, Hunter PR. Reliability of water supplies in low and middle income countries: A <lb/>structured review of definitions and assessment criteria. Journal of Water, Sanitation and Hygiene for <lb/>Development. 2018; 8: 142-164. https://doi.org/10.2166/washdev.2018.174 <lb/>15. Thomas MLH, Channon AA, Bain RES, Nyamai M, Wright JA. Household-Reported Availability of <lb/>Drinking Water in Africa: A Systematic Review. Water. 2020; 12: 2603. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>w12092603 <lb/>16. Bartram J, Brocklehurst C, Fisher M, Luyendijk R, Hossain R, Wardlaw T, et al. Global Monitoring of <lb/>Water Supply and Sanitation: History, Methods and Future Challenges. International Journal of Environ-<lb/>mental Research and Public Health. 2014; 11: 8137-8165. https://doi.org/10.3390/ijerph110808137 <lb/>PMID: 25116635 <lb/>17. WHO, UNICEF. Progress on Drinking Water, Sanitation and Hygiene Update and SDG Baselines. <lb/>Geneva, Switzerland; 2017. <lb/>18. Rawas F, Bain R, Kumpel E. Comparing utility-reported hours of piped water supply to households&apos; <lb/>experiences. npj Clean Water. 2020; 3: 1-9. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41545-020-0053-y <lb/>19. DuChanois RM, Liddle ES, Fenner RA, Jeuland M, Evans B, Cumming O, et al. Factors Associated <lb/>with Water Service Continuity for the Rural Populations of Bangladesh, Pakistan, Ethiopia, and Mozam-<lb/>bique. Environmental Science and Technology. 2019; 53: 4355-4363. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.est. <lb/>8b07173 PMID: 30917279 <lb/>20. Smiley SL. Water Availability and Reliability in Dar es Salaam, Tanzania. The Journal of Development <lb/>Studies. 2016; 52: 1320-1334. https://doi.org/10.1080/00220388.2016.1146699 <lb/>21. Majuru B, Jagals P, Hunter PR. Assessing rural small community water supply in Limpopo, South <lb/>Africa: Water service benchmarks and reliability. Science of The Total Environment. 2012; 435: 479-<lb/>486. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2012.07.024 PMID: 22885354 <lb/>22. Perez-Haydrich C, Warren JL, Burgert CR, Emch ME. Guidelines on the use of DHS GPS data. Spatial <lb/>Analysis Reports No. 8. Calverton, Maryland, USA; 2013 Sep. <lb/>23. Alda-Vidal C, Kooy M, Rusca M. Mapping operation and maintenance: an everyday urbanism analysis <lb/>of inequalities within piped water supply in Lilongwe, Malawi. Urban Geography. 2017; 39: 104-121. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/02723638.2017.1292664 <lb/>24. JMP. Downloads Index-Country Files. 2021 [cited 23 Jan 2020]. Available: https://washdata.org/data/ <lb/>downloads#WLD <lb/>25. IBNET. The International Benchmarking Network. 2021 [cited 23 Feb 2022]. Available: https://www.ib-<lb/>net.org/ <lb/>26. World Bank. Population, total-Zambia. In: Washington D.C., USA [Internet]. 2019 [cited 22 Sep 2020]. <lb/>Available: https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.POP.TOTL?locations=ZM&amp;view=chart <lb/>27. World Bank. Urban population (% of total population)-Zambia. In: Washington D.C., USA [Internet]. <lb/>2019 [cited 22 Sep 2020]. Available: https://data.worldbank.org/indicator/SP.URB.TOTL.IN.ZS? <lb/>locations=ZM <lb/>28. Hamududu BH, Ngoma H. Impacts of climate change on water resources availability in Zambia: implica-<lb/>tions for irrigation development. Environment, Development and Sustainability. 2020; 22: 2817-2838. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s10668-019-00320-9 <lb/>29. Libanda B, Zheng M, Ngonga C. Spatial and temporal patterns of drought in Zambia. Journal of Arid <lb/>Land. 2019; 11: 180-191. https://doi.org/10.1007/s40333-019-0053-2 <lb/>30. Lapworth DJ, Stuart ME, Pedley S, Nkhuwa DCW, Tijani MN. A review of urban groundwater use and <lb/>water quality challenges in Sub-Saharan Africa. British Geological Survey Open Report OR/17/056; <lb/>2017. <lb/>31. NWASCO. Urban and Peri-urban Water Supply and Sanitation Sector Report 2018. Lusaka, Zambia: <lb/>National Water Supply and Sanitation Council; 2018. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>32. WHO, UNICEF, JMP. JMP: Zambia Drinking Water Statistics. In: New York, USA [Internet]. 2018 [cited <lb/>23 Sep 2020]. Available: https://washdata.org/data/household#!/zmb <lb/>33. NWASCO. Annual Report 2018. Lusaka, Zambia: National Water Supply and Sanitation Council; <lb/>2018. <lb/>34. Zambia Statistics Agency M of H (MOH) Z, ICF. Zambia Demographic and Health Survey 2018. Lusaka, <lb/>Zambia, and Rockville, Maryland, USA; 2019. <lb/>35. Burgert CR, Colston J, Roy T, Zachary B. Geographic displacement procedure and georeferenced data <lb/>release policy for the Demographic and Health Surveys. DHS Spatial Analysis Reports No. 7. ICF Inter-<lb/>national, Calverton, Maryland, USA; 2013. <lb/>36. IBNET. Country Profile Zambia. 2020 [cited 23 Sep 2020]. Available: https://database.ib-net.org/ <lb/>country_profile?ctry=29&amp;years=2019,2018,2017,2016,2015&amp;type=report&amp;ent=country&amp;mult= <lb/>true&amp;table=true&amp;chart=false&amp;chartType=column&amp;lang=en&amp;exch=1 <lb/>37. IBNET. Zambia Utility Company Continuity of Supplies. 2017 [cited 12 Oct 2020]. Available: https:// <lb/>database.ib-net.org/utilities_results?uid=22094,20,22095,125,24382,22099,121,122,123,22096,126, <lb/>22097,127,22098,124&amp;years=2017&amp;type=indicator&amp;ent=utility&amp;mult=true&amp;report=1&amp;indicator= <lb/>34&amp;table=true&amp;chart=true&amp;chartType=column&amp;lang=EN&amp;exch=1 <lb/>38. IBNET. Zambia Utility Company Total Water Consumption (LPCD). 2017 [cited 12 Oct 2020]. Available: <lb/>https://database.ib-net.org/utilities_results?uid=22094,20,22095,125,24382,22099,121,122,123, <lb/>22096,126,22097,127,22098,124&amp;years=2017&amp;type=indicator&amp;ent=utility&amp;mult=true&amp;report= <lb/>1&amp;indicator=7&amp;table=true&amp;chart=true&amp;chartType=column&amp;lang=EN&amp;exch=1 <lb/>39. IBNET. Non revenue water. 2021 [cited 21 Oct 2020]. Available: https://www.ib-net.org/toolkit/ibnet-<lb/>indicators/non-revenue-water/ <lb/>40. Simukonda K, Farmani R, Butler D. Intermittent water supply systems: causal factors, problems and <lb/>solution options. Urban Water Journal. 2018; 15: 488-500. https://doi.org/10.1080/1573062X.2018. <lb/>1483522 <lb/>41. Liemberger R, Wyatt A. Quantifying the global non-revenue water problem. Water Science and Tech-<lb/>nology: Water Supply. 2019; 19: 831-837. https://doi.org/10.2166/ws.2018.129 <lb/>42. NWASCO. Urban and Peri-Urban WSS Sector Reports. In: National Water Supply and Sanitation <lb/>Council [Internet]. 2020 [cited 23 Sep 2020]. Available: http://www.nwasco.org.zm/index.php/media-<lb/>center/publications/urban-and-peri-urban-wss-sector-reports <lb/>43. National Water Supply and Sanitation Council. Water Sector Overview. In: National Water Supply and <lb/>Sanitation Council [Internet]. 2023 [cited 22 Mar 2023]. Available: https://www.nwasco.org.zm/index. <lb/>php/regulated-sector/water-sector-overview <lb/>44. GADM. Zambia Administrative Boundaries. 2020 [cited 23 Sep 2020]. Available: https://gadm.org/ <lb/>download_country_v3.html <lb/>45. Croft TN, Marshall AMJ, Allen CK. Guide to DHS Statistics: DHS-7. Maryland, USA; 2018. <lb/>46. Luh J, Bartram J. Drinking water and sanitation: progress in 73 countries in relation to socioeconomic <lb/>indicators. Bulletin of the World Health Organization. 2016; 94: 111-121. https://doi.org/10.2471/BLT. <lb/>15.162974 PMID: 26957676 <lb/>47. Cassivi A, Guilherme S, Bain R, Tilley E, Owen E, Waygood D, et al. Drinking water accessibility and <lb/>quantity in low and middle-income countries: A systematic review. International Journal of Hygiene and <lb/>Environmental Health. 2019; 222: 1011-1020. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijheh.2019.06.011 PMID: <lb/>31320308 <lb/>48. Rutstein SO. The DHS Wealth Index: Approaches for Rural and Urban Areas. Calverton, Maryland, <lb/>USA; 2008. <lb/>49. Zoungrana TD. The effect of wealth on the choice of household drinking water sources in West Africa. <lb/>International Journal of Finance &amp; Economics. 2020; ijfe.1903. https://doi.org/10.1002/ijfe.1903 <lb/>50. Kayaga S, Franceys R. Costs of urban utility water connections: Excessive burden to the poor. Utilities <lb/>Policy. 2007; 15: 270-277. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jup.2007.06.002 <lb/>51. Dungumaro EW. Socioeconomic differentials and availability of domestic water in South Africa. Physics <lb/>and Chemistry of the Earth. 2007; 32: 1141-1147. <lb/>52. Kelly E, Shields KF, Cronk R, Lee K, Behnke N, Klug T, et al. Seasonality, water use and community <lb/>management of water systems in rural settings: Qualitative evidence from Ghana, Kenya, and Zambia. <lb/>Science of the Total Environment. 2018; 628-629: 715-721. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2018. <lb/>02.045 PMID: 29454211 <lb/>53. Simukonda K, Farmani R, Butler D. Causes of intermittent water supply in Lusaka City, Zambia. Water <lb/>Practice and Technology. 2018; 13: 335-345. https://doi.org/10.2166/wpt.2018.046 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>54. International Research Institute of Climate and Society, World Bank. World Bank Climate Variability <lb/>Tool: Precipitation Plots. 2021 [cited 12 May 2021]. Available: http://iridl.ldeo.columbia.edu/maproom/ <lb/>Global/World_Bank/Climate_Variability/ <lb/>55. Jackson K. Diversity and the Distribution of Public Goods in Sub-Saharan Africa. Journal of African Eco-<lb/>nomics. 2013; 22: 437-462. <lb/>56. Arouna A, Dabbert S. Determinants of domestic water use by rural households without access to private <lb/>improved water sources in Benin: A Seemingly Unrelated Tobit Approach. Water Resources Manage-<lb/>ment. 2010; 24: 1381-1398. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11269-009-9504-4 <lb/>57. Armand L, Fotue T, Sikod F. Determinants of the households&apos; choice of drinking water source in Camer-<lb/>oon. Journal of Sustainable Development in Africa. 2012; 14: 86-97. <lb/>58. Mulenga JN, Bwalya BB, Kaliba-Chishimba K. Determinants and inequalities in access to improved <lb/>water sources and sanitation among the Zambian households. International Journal of Development <lb/>and Sustainability. 2017; 6: 746-762. <lb/>59. Staddon C, Rogers J, Warriner C, Ward S, Powell W. Why doesn&apos;t every family practice rainwater har-<lb/>vesting? Factors that affect the decision to adopt rainwater harvesting as a household water security <lb/>strategy in central Uganda. Water International. 2018; 43: 1114-1135. https://doi.org/10.1080/ <lb/>02508060.2018.1535417 <lb/>60. Pesaresi M, Freire S. GHS-SMOD R2016A -GHS settlement grid, following the REGIO model 2014 in <lb/>application to GHSL Landsat and CIESIN GPW v4-multitemporal (1975-1990-2000-2015). In: Euro-<lb/>pean Commission, Joint Research Centre (JRC) [Internet]. 2016 [cited 12 Oct 2020]. Available: https:// <lb/>data.jrc.ec.europa.eu/dataset/jrc-ghsl-ghs_smod_pop_globe_r2016a <lb/>61. Winter S, Dreibelbis R, Barchi F. Context matters: a multicountry analysis of individual-and neighbour-<lb/>hood-level factors associated with women&apos;s sanitation use in sub-Saharan Africa. Tropical Medicine &amp; <lb/>International Health. 2018; 23: 173-192. https://doi.org/10.1111/tmi.13016 PMID: 29172229 <lb/>62. Robles-Velasco A, Corte ´s P, Muñuzuri J, Onieva L. Prediction of pipe failures in water supply networks <lb/>using logistic regression and support vector classification. Reliability Engineering and System Safety. <lb/>2020; 196: 106754. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ress.2019.106754 <lb/>63. Kennedy-Walker R, Amezaga JM, Paterson CA. The impact of community social dynamics on achiev-<lb/>ing improved sanitation access for the urban poor: The case of Lusaka, Zambia. Habitat Int. 2015; 50: <lb/>326-334. https://doi.org/10.1016/J.HABITATINT.2015.09.004 <lb/>64. Felice E. The Misty Grail: The Search for a Comprehensive Measure of Development and the Reasons <lb/>for GDP Primacy. Development and Change. 2016; 47: 967-994. https://doi.org/10.1111/dech.12257 <lb/>65. Republic of Zambia Central Statistical Office. Research Paper on Provincial Gross Domestic Product. <lb/>Lusaka, Zambia; 2017. <lb/>66. Republic of Zambia Central Statistical Office. Zambia in Figures 2018. Lusaka, Zambia; 2018. <lb/>67. StataCorp. Stata Statistical Software: Release 16. College Station, TX: StataCorp LLC.; 2019. <lb/>68. Pfeffermann D, Skinner CJ, Holmes DJ, Goldstein H, Rasbash J. Weighting for unequal selection prob-<lb/>abilities in multilevel models. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society Series B: Statistical Methodology. <lb/>1998; 60: 23-40. https://doi.org/10.1111/1467-9868.00106 <lb/>69. Snijders TAB. Power and sample size in multilevel modeling. In: Everitt BS, Howell DC, editors. Ency-<lb/>clopedia of Statistics in Behavioral Science. Chichester, UK: Wiley; 2005. pp. 1570-1573. <lb/>70. Elkasabi M, Ren R, Pullum TW. DHS Methodology Reports 27. Multilevel Modeling Using DHS Sur-<lb/>veys: A Framework to Approximate Level-Weights. Rockville, Maryland, USA; 2020. <lb/>71. Oageng I, Power Mmopelwa G. Water consumption patterns in a rural setting in Ngamiland district, <lb/>Botswana: the case of the Boro village. Journal of Water Sanitation and Hygiene for Development. <lb/>2014; 4: 720-726. https://doi.org/10.2166/washdev.2014.065 <lb/>72. Yang H, Bain R, Bartram J, Gundry S, Pedley S, Wright J. Water Safety and Inequality in Access to <lb/>Drinking-water between Rich and Poor Households. Environmental Science &amp; Technology. 2013; 47: <lb/>11222-1230. https://doi.org/10.1021/es303345p PMID: 23276231 <lb/>73. Bain R, Johnston R, Khan S, Hancioglu A, Slaymaker T. Monitoring Drinking Water Quality in Nationally <lb/>Representative Household Surveys in Low-and Middle-Income Countries: Cross-Sectional Analysis of <lb/>27 Multiple Indicator Cluster Surveys 2014-2020. Environmental Health Perspectives. 2021; 129: <lb/>097010. https://doi.org/10.1289/EHP8459 PMID: 34546076 <lb/>74. Nelson JK, Brewer CA. Evaluating data stability in aggregation structures across spatial scales: revisit-<lb/>ing the modifiable areal unit problem. Cartography and Geographic Information Science. 2017; 44: 35-<lb/>50. <lb/>75. Boerma JT, Sommerfeltb AE. Demographic and health surveys (DHS): contributions and limitations. <lb/>World health statistics quarterly. 1993; 46: 222-226. PMID: 8017081 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>76. Overbey KN, Schwab KJ, Exum NG. Comparison of 1-week and 2-week recall periods for caregiver-<lb/>reported diarrhoeal illness in children, using nationally representative household surveys. International <lb/>Journal of Epidemiology. 2019; 48: 1228-1239. https://doi.org/10.1093/ije/dyz043 PMID: 30907423 <lb/>77. Rheingans R, Anderson JD, Luyendijk R, Cumming O. Measuring disparities in sanitation access: does <lb/>the measure matter? Tropical Medicine &amp; International Health. 2014; 19: 2-13. https://doi.org/10.1111/ <lb/>tmi.12220 PMID: 24851256 <lb/>78. UNICEF. Drinking Water: Equity, safety and sustainability. In: United Nations International Children&apos;s <lb/>Emergency Fund. New York, USA [Internet]. UNICEF/WHO. Geneva, Switzerland; 2021 [cited 14 Jun <lb/>2021]. Available: https://data.unicef.org/resources/drinking-water-equity-safety-and-sustainability-<lb/>2011-thematic-report/ <lb/>79. Elkasabi M, Thomas MLH. Zambia DHS 2018: Classification of rural/urban. In: The DHS Program User <lb/>Forum [Internet]. 2020 [cited 15 Mar 2023]. Available: https://userforum.dhsprogram.com/index.php?t= <lb/>msg&amp;goto=20391&amp;&amp;srch=zambia+rural#msg_20391 <lb/>80. Dijkstra L, Poelman H. A harmonised definition of cities and rural areas: the new degree of urbanisation <lb/>Working Papers. Brussels, Belgium; Luxembourg City, Luxembourg; 2014. <lb/>81. Jeil EB, Abass K, Ganle JK. &quot;We are free when water is available&quot;: Gendered livelihood implications of <lb/>sporadic water supply in Northern Ghana. Local Environment. 2020; 25: 320-335. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1080/13549839.2020.1744118 <lb/>82. Guragai B, Takizawa S, Hashimoto T, Oguma K. Effects of inequality of supply hours on consumers&apos; <lb/>coping strategies and perceptions of intermittent water supply in Kathmandu Valley, Nepal. Science of <lb/>The Total Environment. 2017; 599-600: 431-441. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.scitotenv.2017.04.182 <lb/>PMID: 28482301 <lb/>83. McNally A, Verdin K, Harrison L, Getirana A, Jacob J, Shukla S, et al. Acute Water-Scarcity Monitoring <lb/>for Africa. Water. 2019; 11: 1968. https://doi.org/10.3390/W11101968 <lb/>84. Thomson P, Hope R, Foster T. GSM-enabled remote monitoring of rural handpumps: A proof-of-con-<lb/>cept study. Journal of Hydroinformatics. 2012; 14: 829-839. https://doi.org/10.2166/hydro.2012.183 <lb/>85. NWASCO. Water Providers. In: National Water Supply and Sanitation Council [Internet]. Lusaka, Zam-<lb/>bia; 2021 [cited 4 Aug 2021]. Available: http://www.nwasco.org.zm/index.php/regulated-sector/water-<lb/>providers <lb/>86. Castro V, Morel A. Can delegated management help water utilities improve services to informal settle-<lb/>ments? Waterlines. 2008; 27: 289-306. <lb/>87. WHO, UNICEF. WASH in the 2030 Agenda New global indicators for drinking water, sanitation and <lb/>hygiene. Geneva, Switzerland; 2017. <lb/>88. IBNET. IBNET Indicators. 2023 [cited 14 Mar 2023]. Available: https://www.ib-net.org/toolkit/ibnet-<lb/>indicators/ <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS WATER <lb/>Risk factors for urban intermittent piped drinking-water <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Water | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pwat.0000127 February 5, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 26 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
