<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Mutational signature dynamics indicate SARS-<lb/>CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity is driven by host <lb/>antiviral molecules <lb/>Kieran D. Lamb ID <lb/>1,2☯ <lb/>, Martha M. Luka 1,2☯ , Megan Saathoff 1 , Richard J. Orton 1 , My V. <lb/>T. Phan 3,4 , Matthew Cotten 1,3,4,5 , Ke YuanID 2,6,7 *, David L. RobertsonID 1 * <lb/>1 Medical Research Council -University of Glasgow Centre for Virus Research, School of Infection and <lb/>Immunity, Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom, 2 School of Computing Science, University of Glasgow, <lb/>Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom, 3 Medical Research Council/Uganda Virus Research Institute and <lb/>London School of Hygiene &amp; Tropical Medicine Uganda Research Unit, Entebbe, Uganda, 4 College of Health <lb/>Solutions, Arizona State University, Phoenix, Arizona, United States of America, 5 Complex Adaptive <lb/>Systems Initiative, Arizona State University, Scottsdale, Arizona, United States of America, 6 School of <lb/>Cancer Sciences, University of Glasgow, Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom, 7 Cancer Research UK <lb/>Scotland Institute, Glasgow, Scotland, United Kingdom <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* Ke.Yuan@glasgow.ac.uk (KY); David.L.Robertson@glasgow.ac.uk (DLR) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The COVID-19 pandemic has been characterised by sequential variant-specific waves <lb/>shaped by viral, individual human and population factors. SARS-CoV-2 variants are defined <lb/>by their unique combinations of mutations and there has been a clear adaptation to more <lb/>efficient human infection since the emergence of this new human coronavirus in late 2019. <lb/>Here, we use machine learning models to identify shared signatures, i.e., common underly-<lb/>ing mutational processes and link these to the subset of mutations that define the variants of <lb/>concern (VOCs). First, we examined the global SARS-CoV-2 genomes and associated <lb/>metadata to determine how viral properties and public health measures have influenced the <lb/>magnitude of waves, as measured by the number of infection cases, in different geographic <lb/>locations using regression models. This analysis showed that, as expected, both public <lb/>health measures and virus properties were associated with the waves of regional SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 reported infection numbers and this impact varies geographically. We attribute this to <lb/>intrinsic differences such as vaccine coverage, testing and sequencing capacity and the <lb/>effectiveness of government stringency. To assess underlying evolutionary change, we <lb/>used non-negative matrix factorisation and observed three distinct mutational signatures, <lb/>unique in their substitution patterns and exposures from the SARS-CoV-2 genomes. Signa-<lb/>tures 1, 2 and 3 were biased to C!T, T!C/A!G and G!T point mutations. We hypothe-<lb/>sise assignments of these mutational signatures to the host antiviral molecules APOBEC, <lb/>ADAR and ROS respectively. We observe a shift amidst the pandemic in relative mutational <lb/>signature activity from predominantly Signature 1 changes to an increasingly high proportion <lb/>of changes consistent with Signature 2. This could represent changes in how the virus and <lb/>the host immune response interact and indicates how SARS-CoV-2 may continue to gener-<lb/>ate variation in the future. Linkage of the detected mutational signatures to the VOC-defining <lb/>amino acids substitutions indicates the majority of SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity is <lb/>PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/>1 / 26 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Lamb KD, Luka MM, Saathoff M, Orton <lb/>RJ, Phan MVT, Cotten M, et al. (2024) Mutational <lb/>signature dynamics indicate SARS-CoV-2&apos;s <lb/>evolutionary capacity is driven by host antiviral <lb/>molecules. PLoS Comput Biol 20(1): e1011795. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 <lb/>Editor: Roger Dimitri Kouyos, University of Zurich, <lb/>SWITZERLAND <lb/>Received: July 12, 2023 <lb/>Accepted: January 3, 2024 <lb/>Published: January 25, 2024 <lb/>Peer Review History: PLOS recognizes the <lb/>benefits of transparency in the peer review <lb/>process; therefore, we enable the publication of <lb/>all of the content of peer review and author <lb/>responses alongside final, published articles. The <lb/>editorial history of this article is available here: <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 <lb/>Copyright: © 2024 Lamb et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: Computational code <lb/>is available at https://github.com/kieran12lamb/ <lb/>SARS-CoV2_Mutational_Signatures GISAID data <lb/>accessions are available at doi.org/10.55876/gis8. <lb/></front>

		<body>likely to be associated with the action of host antiviral molecules rather than virus replication <lb/>errors. <lb/></body>

		<!-- new element never seen before -->
		<front>Author summary <lb/>We show that both public health measures and virus properties are associated with the <lb/>rise and fall of regional SARS-CoV-2 reported infection numbers with regional differences <lb/>attributable to the extent of vaccine usage and the effectiveness of public health measures. <lb/>In our mutational signature analysis, using non-negative matrix factorisation, we detected <lb/>three distinct mutational signatures that can be putatively attributed to the action of spe-<lb/>cific host antiviral molecules. Interestingly, we observe a shift in mutational signature <lb/>activity from predominantly Signature 1 changes to an increasingly high proportion of <lb/>changes consistent with Signature 2. These mutation patterns influence SARS-CoV-2&apos;s <lb/>evolutionary capacity, the available genetic variation that selection can act on, and so can <lb/>be linked to the mutations defining the variants of concern responsible for the distinct <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 infection waves. The dominant types of nucleotide substitutions involved <lb/>indicate that much of the mutation and hence variation come from the action of the host <lb/>immune response rather than replication errors since the virus has an error correction <lb/>system. <lb/></front>

		<body>Introduction <lb/>The COVID-19 pandemic began in late 2019 following a zoonotic spillover event of a SARS-<lb/>related coronavirus, subsequently named SARS-CoV-2, in Wuhan, China [1, 2]. The extensive <lb/>and rapid global spread of this new human coronavirus and its detrimental impact on human <lb/>health has rendered it among the most significant pandemics in recent history [3]. Different <lb/>geographical regions of the world have reported varied infection patterns that are attributed to <lb/>differences in population demographics and health care systems, diverse government <lb/>responses [4, 5], the emergence of more transmissible variants [6, 7] and other viral, human <lb/>and population factors. Since its emergence, SARS-CoV-2 has undergone significant genetic <lb/>change such that numerous variants, i.e., distinct genotypes, have been identified [8], many <lb/>with altered phenotypic properties [9]. <lb/>The World Health Organization (WHO) and other public health bodies have broadly classi-<lb/>fied variants that pose an increased risk to global public health (due to increased transmissibil-<lb/>ity, increased virulence or decrease in the effectiveness of public health measures relative to <lb/>2019/early 2020 SARS-CoV-2 variants) as variants of concern (VOCs) and variants of interest <lb/>(VOIs) [10]. The early SARS-CoV-2 variants to emerge in 2019 and the more transmissible <lb/>+S:D614G variant followed by the VOCs (Alpha, Beta, Gamma, Delta and currently Omicron) <lb/>have driven significant and sequential &quot;waves&quot; of SARS-CoV-2 infections internationally. The <lb/>emergence of each variant showing a clear geographical link [11-13]. <lb/>Viral mutations arise from a diverse set of processes (principally viral polymerase replica-<lb/>tion errors and host anti-viral editing processes), which can be identified by the characteristic <lb/>mutational signatures that they leave on the genome [14, 15]. Such characterisation of domi-<lb/>nant mutational processes is routinely used in cancer genomics [16]. The catalogue of SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 nucleotide changes show distinct mutational patterns suggestive of a role for host <lb/>antiviral mutational processes in introducing changes in the viral RNA [17, 18]. These <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<front>221201qs, doi.org/10.55876/gis8.230406qg and <lb/>doi.org/10.55876/gis8.230406fb. <lb/>Funding: The authors acknowledge funding from <lb/>the Medical Research Council (MRC, <lb/>MC_UU_12014/12 to DLR, MC_UU_00034/5 to <lb/>DLR and a Doctoral Training Programme in <lb/>Precision Medicine studentship for KDL, MR/ <lb/>N013166/1 to KY and DLR), the Wellcome Trust <lb/>(220977/Z/20/Z to MC, KY, DLR), the UK <lb/>Department for International Development (DFID) <lb/>under the MRC/DFID Concordat agreement <lb/>(MC_PC_20010 to MC), Engineering and Physical <lb/>Sciences Research Council (EPSRC, EP/R018634/ <lb/>1 to KY), and the European Union&apos;s Horizon 2020 <lb/>research and innovation programme project <lb/>PANCAIM (101016851 to KY). The funders had no <lb/>role in study design, data collection and analysis, <lb/>decision to publish, or preparation of the <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>processes potentially dominate in SARS-CoV-2 evolution because point mutations introduced <lb/>in replication are mostly corrected by the action of a proofreading enzyme. <lb/>The generation of virus diversity, the key to virus persistence by generating novel variation <lb/>and thus evolutionary capacity, is multi-faceted [19], yet our understanding of the relative <lb/>importance of underlying mutational processes linked to the action of host anti-viral mole-<lb/>cules is still very limited. Given that SARS-CoV-2 continues to develop new variants, many <lb/>associated with sets of previously observed (convergent) and novel mutations [9], it is critical <lb/>that we improve our understanding of the mechanisms and sources of evolutionary change. <lb/>Along with routine surveillance of SARS-CoV-2 infections, there has been an unprece-<lb/>dented global sequencing effort resulting in databases containing many millions of genome <lb/>sequences, in particular GISAID [20]. Here we examined this data to describe the global <lb/>molecular epidemiology and evolution of SARS-CoV-2. Using regression models we first <lb/>examined how viral properties and public health measures have influenced the magnitude of <lb/>infection waves in different geographic locations. Satisfied that SARS-CoV-2 variants have <lb/>been an important driver of infections we then used non-negative matrix factorisation to char-<lb/>acterise the mutational processes involved in the generation of variants and their changing pat-<lb/>terns of activity over time. <lb/>Results <lb/>Characterising the SARS-CoV-2 waves regionally <lb/>This first part of the study reports on global SARS-CoV-2 data from 24/12/2019 to 28/01/ <lb/>2022 only as limited public health measures were in place after this time. We observed 1,544 <lb/>distinct SARS-CoV-2 lineages from 7,348,178 sequences. 88% of the infections in the global <lb/>pandemic during this time frame were caused by a subset of 13 Pango and WHO variants <lb/>(S1 Table). While there are geographical differences there is a clear dominance of a subset of <lb/>variants and replacement of these through time (Fig 1). This &quot;wave&quot; infection pattern was <lb/>evident in all geographic locations. Although biased by testing rates, Europe and the Ameri-<lb/>cas had the highest infection rates, reporting up to 450 cases per million population per day <lb/>(Fig 1). The emergence or introduction of VOCs coincided with a steep increase in infection <lb/>rates globally. For example, cases in Asia showed a steep rise in February 2021, which peaked <lb/>in May 2021 (Fig 1, panel Asia). During this period, Alpha and Delta comprised greater than <lb/>75% of the SARS-CoV-2 cases identified in the sequence data. Africa and Oceania on the <lb/>other hand displayed overall sustained low case numbers. Despite this, Beta dominated the <lb/>second wave in parts of Africa while Alpha dominated the third Oceanic wave. After its <lb/>emergence in March 2021, Delta spread to become the predominant variant across all conti-<lb/>nents. The Omicron variant of concern was first identified in South Africa in late November <lb/>2021 and, by January 2022, it had rapidly become the predominant cause of infections world-<lb/>wide (Fig 1). <lb/>Covariates of the waves <lb/>We investigated the degree to which public health measures and viral properties explain conti-<lb/>nent-specific reported cases of infection. Correlation analysis at the global level showed a sig-<lb/>nificant correlation between infection rates and the predictor variables: government <lb/>stringency, vaccination, previous infection burden, virus diversity and fitness (S2 Table). <lb/>Regression analysis revealed that the impact of the predictor variables on the magnitude of <lb/>reported cases were found across all continents. We classified significance levels as follows: no <lb/>significance for p-values greater than 0.05, weak significance for p-values between 0.05 and <lb/>0.001, and high significance for p-values less than 0.001. Our findings indicated that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>government stringency had a weakly significant impact in Asia, Europe, and South America, <lb/>but a strongly significant impact in Africa, Oceania, and North America. Virus fitness, previ-<lb/>ous infection burden, and vaccination demonstrated a strongly significant impact across all <lb/>continents. Virus diversity was strongly correlated with high infection numbers in Europe and <lb/>Fig 1. Continent-level SARS-CoV-2 lineage dynamics and pandemic curves. Lines show a 14-day rolling average of reported SARS-CoV-2 cases. <lb/>Bars show the biweekly proportions of common lineages and are coloured by lineage. The white space shows the proportion of sequences from <lb/>other (non-majority) lineages. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>North America, with a weaker association in Africa, Asia, Oceania, and South America. The R <lb/>squared values, indicating the proportion of variance explained by our model, were greater <lb/>than 0.5 for all continents, ranging from 0.66 in Oceania to 0.79 in Africa (S3 Table). Gener-<lb/>ally, our predictions closely resembled the rise and fall of SARS-CoV-2 infection case numbers <lb/>(Fig 2). <lb/>For country-level analysis, we included 29 countries from six continents based on the com-<lb/>pleteness of data (availability of sequence data in every 14 day bin). Pandemic plots were visu-<lb/>alised using biweekly bins and multiple linear regression was fitted using the same approach. <lb/>Different countries had varying lineage dynamics as illustrated in S1 Fig. The five predictor <lb/>variables had varying impacts on infection rates across countries (S2 Fig). Despite some differ-<lb/>ences related to the population level processes investigated here, there is a clear variant replace-<lb/>ment process taking place. As the generation of novel variants is fundamentally a mutation <lb/>dependent process we next investigated the underlying patterns of mutations being generated <lb/>through time. The goodness of fit varied among countries, with the R squared varying from <lb/>0.28 (Japan) to 0.96 (Australia), with a median of 0.69 (S4 Table). Though our model success-<lb/>fully captured the general infection wave patterns in many countries, it struggled to capture <lb/>short-term data spikes in specific instances, such as in Belgium (November 2020), India (May <lb/>2021), Indonesia (August 2021) and Japan (September 2021) (S2 Fig). <lb/>Fig 2. Association of SARS-CoV-2 infection rates and predictor variables globally. A. Pearson&apos;s correlation matrix of infection rate and predictor <lb/>variables. Positive correlations are denoted in orange and negative correlations in blue and colour intensity is directly proportional to coefficient value. <lb/>B. Model fitting using multiple linear regression. Black solid lines show a 14-day rolling average of adjusted SARS-CoV-2 cases. Pink solid lines show <lb/>fitted mean response values of infection rates with predictor values as input. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Identifying putative mutational processes contributing to changes in <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>New variants of concern have displaced viral lineages that were previously dominant in the <lb/>population in different geographical regions and in some cases globally (Fig 1). This behaviour <lb/>has been observed with the original variants of concern (Alpha, Beta and Gamma) and then <lb/>globally with the Delta and Omicron lineages. We investigated whether these variant wave <lb/>events (periods of time where infections are dominated by a single variant) were linked to the <lb/>activity of specific mutational processes. Each of the variants of interest/concern has evolved <lb/>independently such that detecting the patterns of mutations in the SARS-CoV-2 sequence data <lb/>allows us to observe which processes are most active and could be contributing to the emer-<lb/>gence of variants. <lb/>Mutations were called using inferred references for each of the Pango lineages, which we <lb/>call tree-based referencing (S3 Fig). The SARS-CoV-2 alignment of 13,278,844 sequences up to <lb/>26/10/2022 was used. Of these 13 million sequences 2,195,182 sequences were selected as they <lb/>contained 5,726,144 newly arisen mutations. Cytosine to thymine mutations (C!T) were the <lb/>most common and were the primary substitution category for most weeks where sequences <lb/>were recorded. Note, SARS-CoV-2 has an RNA genome but we refer to uracil as a thymine to <lb/>match pre-existing DNA mutational signature notations. <lb/>Three signatures were identified with distinct substitution patterns using non-negative <lb/>matrix factorisation (NMF) (Fig 3 and S5 Fig). Signature 1 is heavily biased towards C!T <lb/>mutations. Signature 1 had a high probability of ACA, ACT and TCT contexts (adjacent nucle-<lb/>otides in the 5&apos; and 3&apos; direction of the mutated site), consistent with what was earlier reported <lb/>by Simmonds et al. [17] as highly mutated contexts for C!T substitutions in SARS-CoV-2. <lb/>Signature 2 is predominantly adenine to guanine (A!G), guanine to adenine (G!A) and thy-<lb/>mine to cytosine (T!C) mutations. The proportion of A!G and T!C mutations is approxi-<lb/>mately equal in this signature, which is indicative of a double-stranded mutational process. <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 mutations at adenine positions on the negative strand will be counted as thymine <lb/>mutations due to the negative strand being used to replicate positive sense RNA, with the <lb/>mutated A!G now pairing with a cytosine on the +sense RNA and replacing the original thy-<lb/>mine [21, 22]. Signature 3 is predominantly composed of guanine to thymine (G!T) <lb/>substitutions. <lb/>The dynamics of mutational processes through the pandemic <lb/>By using the available SARS-CoV-2 sequences we can measure the mutational signature activ-<lb/>ity across time as long as our samples are aggregated using time series annotations. Signature <lb/>exposures (Fig 4) show that Signature 1 remained the most prominent signature throughout <lb/>the pandemic, although following the emergence of Signature 2 its activity reduced propor-<lb/>tionally. Absolute exposure values (Fig 4B) show that Signature 1 does not appear to reduce its <lb/>exposure, rather Signature 2 increases its exposure. Signature 2 establishes itself as a substantial <lb/>signature after December 2020. It continues to expand after October 2021, just prior to the <lb/>emergence of the Delta VOC. Signature 3 is by far the least active of the three signatures but <lb/>remains consistent until after January-February 2022 when it begins to drop towards zero. <lb/>This is around the time Omicron began to emerge as the dominant VOC. <lb/>Combined signature activity reached a peak between July and October 2021 (Fig 4B) coin-<lb/>ciding with the peak number of unique mutations (Fig 5A and 5B). This is around the time the <lb/>mutational signature dynamics appear to be shifting, with Signature 2 contributing more <lb/>unique mutations. We can see that this also coincides with the Delta VOC wave, which, <lb/>between May 2021 and January 2022, was the lineage group showing the greatest number of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>newly acquired mutations (Fig 5). Delta was the first VOC to dominate on a global scale, out-<lb/>competing other VOCs like Alpha, Beta and Gamma in their regions of circulation. Omicron <lb/>similarly repeated this phenomenon, almost entirely replacing Delta globally within weeks of <lb/>its emergence (Fig 5B). We also see a marked decrease in the activity of Signature 3 following <lb/>Omicron&apos;s establishment as the dominant variant. A similar decrease in G!T mutations was <lb/>Fig 3. Mutational signatures extracted from the SARS-CoV-2 genome sequences by non-negative matrix factorisation. Signatures are patterns of probabilities for <lb/>each category of substitution in a three nucleotide context. Each bar represents a context and is coloured by the substitution category of the mutation that occurs there. <lb/>Each signature may represent a distinct mutational process. Signature 1 is heavily biased towards cytosine to thymine (C!T) mutations, particularly in 3&apos; CpG <lb/>contexts TCG, CCG and ACG. Signature 2 from SARS-CoV-2 is predominantly adenine to guanine (A!G), guanine to adenine (G!A) and thymine to cytosine <lb/>mutations (T!C). Signature 3 is strongly guanine to thymine (G!T), a pattern that is thought to be caused by the action of guanine oxidation by reactive oxygen <lb/>species. Signatures are shown normalised against the tri-nucleotide composition of the SARS-CoV-2 genome. Non-normalised forms in the context of the SARS-CoV-<lb/>2 genome composition are shown in S5 Fig. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>also observed by Bloom et al. [23] and Ruis et al. [24]. This is different to Delta, where there <lb/>was an increase in Signature 3 following its emergence. These Signature 3 changes become par-<lb/>ticularly apparent when we begin to look at signature activities within variant-defined subsets <lb/>of the data. <lb/>Signature dynamics spatially and by variant <lb/>After observing changes in signature activity during transitions between dominant variants, <lb/>we next investigated the differences between signature activities in variant-defined subsets of <lb/>the data as well as in continent-defined subsets. We used the globally extracted signatures to <lb/>extract exposures from the subsets using a non-negative least squares regression to retain the <lb/>non-negativity constraint. This allowed for the measurement of signature activity in each of <lb/>the subsets of interest. <lb/>Fig 4. Signature exposure plots showing the activities of the extracted mutation signatures over the duration of the COVID-19 pandemic. A. <lb/>Shows the percentage activity of the signatures during a given week of the pandemic, with each colour representing a different signature. B. Shows the <lb/>signature activities as their absolute values at each epidemic week. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Signature 1 was the most active in almost all the variant-defined subsets as was expected <lb/>from the global activity. Signature 3 was most active in the Delta subset as well as during the <lb/>Delta wave in the continent-defined subsets (Fig 5). The non-VOC, Beta and Omicron subsets <lb/>appear to be the least impacted by Signature 3 with almost zero activity in Omicron. Signature <lb/>2 also shows low activity in the non-VOC subset but is very active in the other VOC subsets, in <lb/>particular Alpha, where it appears to be the most active, overtaking the Signature 1 process. <lb/>Continent-defined subsets of the data also consistently showed the high activity of Signa-<lb/>ture 1. Signature 2 begins to consistently appear in all continents after 2020, with only small <lb/>bursts of activity being detected before this (Fig 5D), again consistent with what we see in the <lb/>global data. Signature 3 activity also follows the pattern of the global activity, appearing most <lb/>prominently during the Delta wave. <lb/>Bridging the gap between mutation signatures and amino acid <lb/>substitutions <lb/>Stratifying non-synonymous nucleotide substitutions by their association with mutational sig-<lb/>natures should provide insights into how these mutational processes affect viral proteins. <lb/>Exposures were calculated by stratifying nucleotide mutations by whether they were synony-<lb/>mous or non-synonymous substitutions for each dataset (Fig 6A). The unattributed exposure <lb/>Fig 5. A. Counts of unique SARS-CoV-2 mutations for each epidemic week, with colours representing which continent the mutations came from. B. <lb/>Counts of unique mutations per week that are part of the mutational signature substitution-context features (i.e., no indel mutations included). Colours <lb/>represent which lineage/group of lineages the mutations belong to. C. Ridgeline plot showing the exposure of mutational signatures in SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>variant-defined subsets. Exposures are coloured by the signature they have been attributed to. D. Ridgeline plot showing the exposure of mutational <lb/>signatures in SARS-CoV-2 continent-defined subsets. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig 6. A. Exposures for each of the SARS-CoV-2 mutational signatures for both synonymous and non-synonymous stratified datasets. Synonymous exposures are <lb/>below 0 on the y-axis, while non-synonymous exposures are above 0. Each area represents signature exposures across epidemic weeks, with colours representing which <lb/>signature the exposures are attributed to. B. Non-synonymous and synonymous mutations in the tree-based references of identified variants of concern. Signature 1 <lb/>produces the majority of both synonymous and non-synonymous substitutions in all lineages. Signature 3 mutations are more often non-synonymous substitutions in <lb/>the lineages of concern, with most lineages having few to no changes. Signature 2 non-synonymous mutations appear to have increased in the Omicron lineages (BA.1 <lb/>and BA.2). C. Variant of concern associated non-synonymous mutations coloured by the mutational signature with the greatest likelihood of causing the change. D. <lb/>Variant of concern synonymous mutations coloured by the putative mutational process that caused the change. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>was calculated using the model error for mutational categories not contained within any of the <lb/>extracted mutational signatures. The majority of non-synonymous substitutions can be <lb/>described by the observed mutational signatures. Signature 1 likely produces most of the non-<lb/>synonymous mutations, however, Signature 3 is an almost exclusively non-synonymous signa-<lb/>ture, with particularly high activity during the Delta wave of infections. Signature 2 appears to <lb/>produce predominantly synonymous mutations. <lb/>Using the tree-based references, we can also look at individual lineage reference sequences <lb/>to observe which mutational processes have probably produced their specific amino acid sub-<lb/>stitution set. The tree-based references were used since they are equivalent to a high-quality <lb/>representative sequence and because many of the early real sequences contain sequencing <lb/>errors. For each variant of concern, mutations were assigned to a signature by calculating the <lb/>maximum likelihood of the mutation and its context being produced by each of the three <lb/>extracted signatures. Using the trinucleotide context C[C ! T]G as an example, the likelihood <lb/>function is P(C[C ! T]G j Signature), which corresponds to the probability bars for CT-CCT <lb/>in the extracted signatures. Mutations that contained substitution-context pairs not found <lb/>within any of the mutational signatures were labeled as &quot;unattributed&quot;. <lb/>The Alpha VOC tree-based reference sequence contains eleven Signature 1 changes, six Sig-<lb/>nature 2 changes and a single Signature 3 change. Signature 1 changes account for 39% of all <lb/>substitutions within the Alpha tree-reference sequence, with 75% of these mutations being <lb/>non-synonymous substitutions. Signature 1 was frequently active prior to the Alpha VOC&apos;s <lb/>emergence. The activity plots (Fig 4) show that this was the case for much of the pandemic, <lb/>particularly prior to the Alpha&apos;s emergence around September 2020. It should be noted that <lb/>while Signature 1 mutations are by far the most frequent, only one is found within the Spike <lb/>protein (producing the S:T716I change). Signature 3 only had one change, which was non-syn-<lb/>onymous appearing in ORF:8. Signature 2 mutations were non-synonymous substitutions <lb/>83% of the time, with three Spike mutations relating to the process including S:D614G, which <lb/>is present within all known variants of concern. <lb/>The Beta VOC emerged around the same time as Alpha (Autumn 2020) and is defined by a <lb/>smaller set of mutations. A greater proportion of Signature 1 mutations are non-synonymous <lb/>substitutions in Beta (66%). Signature 2 mutations resulted in S:D215G and S:E484K, the latter <lb/>reported to help the virus evade neutralising antibodies [25]. Signature 3 mutations most likely <lb/>produced S:K417N in spike, which is also reported to aid in antibody evasion [25, 26] similar <lb/>to S:E484K. <lb/>Gamma also emerged in Autumn 2020 and has 33 different defining substitutions. Signa-<lb/>ture 1 mutations account for 11 of these with 54% being non-synonymous. Four are present in <lb/>Spike including S:L18F, S:P26S, S:H655Y and S:T1027I. Signature 2 mutations resulted in six <lb/>amino acid substitutions, with only 75% of changes being non-synonymous. Three of the five <lb/>mutations in non-synonymous substitutions occurred in Spike. Signature 3 mutations in the <lb/>Gamma lineage were all non-synonymous except for a single synonymous substitution in <lb/>ORF1a/b. <lb/>Delta was the first VOC to dominate worldwide and replace almost every other lineage in <lb/>all regions. The initial Delta sequence (Pango lineage B.1.617.2) contains six Signature 1 muta-<lb/>tions. 66% of these changes were non-synonymous and none occurred within Spike. Signature <lb/>2 mutations were all non-synonymous and displaced throughout the virus ORFs including <lb/>ORF1a/b, S and M. Signature 3 mutations in Delta are found in non-coding regions and N, <lb/>with the N mutations both being non-synonymous. <lb/>Omicron is the most recent VOC to emerge, quickly replacing Delta globally. Omicron dif-<lb/>fers from earlier VOCs with a much greater number of Spike mutations relative to the other <lb/>ORFs. The first identified Omicron variant B.1.1.529 has 40 substitutions of which 32 are non-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>synonymous changes. This is almost double that of Delta, which only had 18. Seven of these <lb/>substitutions were Signature 1 changes, two were Signature 3 and ten were Signature 2 <lb/>changes. There are four non-synonymous ORF1a/b mutations despite this ORF being substan-<lb/>tially longer than SARS-CoV-2&apos;s other ORFs. Only one Spike substitution was synonymous <lb/>out of the 21 total changes. This number is even greater when looking at the major Omicron <lb/>variants BA.1 and BA.2. BA.1 had 31 non-synonymous substitutions in Spike alone while BA.2 <lb/>had 28. Between these three Omicron variants, only two Spike substitutions are non-synony-<lb/>mous out of a total of 40. Nine of the 40 changes are from Signature 1, 2 are from Signature 3 <lb/>and 12 are from Signature 2. This means 23/40 of the changes appear to come from these three <lb/>mutational processes. 20 of the 40 substitutions observed in these variants were present in the <lb/>receptor-binding domain (RBD) of Omicron, with nine of these changes thought to help Omi-<lb/>cron evade the immune response or increase its transmissibility [27]. Of these beneficial RBD <lb/>changes, three are potentially the result of Signature 1 activity, 9 are Signature 2 and one is <lb/>from Signature 3. The high density of Signature 2 RBD amino acid changes in a variant that <lb/>has emerged as Signature 2 exposure increased suggests that the mutational process behind <lb/>Signature 2 may have contributed to the emergence of the Omicron variant. <lb/>Signature exposures and highly mutated sequences in wastewater data <lb/>Similar trends over time in exposures are seen when the mutational signatures are applied to <lb/>publicly available wastewater data. Although the trend is seen at a lower resolution than global <lb/>data, Signature 1 and Signature 3 are gradually replaced by Signature 2 (Fig 7A). Although, Sig-<lb/>nature 2 is not quite as strong as in the global data (Fig 4). This suggests trends in mutational <lb/>processes can be monitored using wastewater, not only sequencing of the infected population. <lb/>Additionally, at time periods where a high level of virus diversity is expected, there are highly <lb/>mutated sequences present in the wastewater (Fig 7C). This suggests cryptic sequences in <lb/>wastewater may be used to observe potential upcoming variants, similar to how known <lb/>sequences have been back-traced to particular buildings using wastewater [28]. <lb/>As chronic SARS-CoV-2 infections are implicated as a major contributor to VOC evolution <lb/>[29, 30], it may be possible to parse highly-mutated cryptic sequences of interest from chronic <lb/>infections out of wastewater data in the interest of detecting potential VOCs. Unfortunately, <lb/>this is problematic to deconvolve as sequencing data for immunocompromised and chroni-<lb/>cally infected individuals is sparse. When sequences from known chronic infections are exam-<lb/>ined, the distribution of mutation types is consistent with global data, with Signature 1 <lb/>mutations dominating as expected for samples from January 2022 (Fig 7B). Although, due to <lb/>the low number of chronic infections for comparison this result is not very conclusive, it does <lb/>demonstrate how mutational patterns can be potentially detected in this type of data. Studying <lb/>these types of infections, and underlying mutational processes, will be important to under-<lb/>stand better the origins of the sets of mutations that contribute to the generation of VOCs. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we investigated SARS-CoV-2 lineage dynamics and identified temporal variables <lb/>that are associated with increased numbers of infection cases. Both public health measures and <lb/>virus properties were associated with the sequential waves of regional SARS-CoV-2 infections <lb/>cases. These predictors have varying impact in different geographical locations. As more of the <lb/>global population&apos;s immune system becomes sensitised to existing SARS-CoV-2 variants, <lb/>either through previous infection or vaccination, the virus has and will continue to undergo <lb/>changes that enable reinfections. The continued emergence of new variants is thus expected. <lb/>In some regions, government stringency had limited significant impact on patterns of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>infection. This could be due to differences in implementation strategies and support, other <lb/>competing predictor variables, as well as behavioural changes in citizens as a response to the <lb/>restrictions. <lb/>Our analysis highlights the significant role of vaccination in influencing reported COVID-<lb/>19 case patterns across all continents, even in regions with lower vaccination coverage like <lb/>Africa. Despite Africa&apos;s lower vaccination rates, the continent has seen a relatively low-level of <lb/>sustained transmission. This phenomenon might be attributed to factors such as the younger <lb/>median age of the population, lower population density, immune priming due to prevalent <lb/>Fig 7. A. Signature exposures per month from wastewater sequences show similar trends in mutational processes as the global data, although at a lower <lb/>resolution and, interestingly, with a lower Signature 2 exposure. B. Substitutions in SARS-CoV-2 consensus sequences from infections of <lb/>immunocompromised individuals contain mutation types corresponding with patterns observed in the distinct signatures. Of note, there are more <lb/>synonymous mutations present in the chronic infection data than in the global sequences, although it is important to note the sample size for <lb/>immunocompromised infections is low. C. Mutation counts in wastewater sequences for bi-yearly time periods. Highly mutated sequences cluster to <lb/>the right especially during the 2021 July-December time period, as would be expected when Omicron was emerging. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795.g007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>infectious diseases, and limited testing capacity [31]. The weak impact of viral diversity on <lb/>reported cases in Asia and South America may be explained by the emergence and dominance <lb/>of variants such Delta and Gamma in the regions, respectively. For instance, the Delta variant, <lb/>initially identified in Asia, quickly became the predominant strain, overshadowing other line-<lb/>ages before spreading globally. Overall, the predictor variables significantly contributed to <lb/>explaining the rise and fall of infection numbers across different continents, accounting for <lb/>more than half of the variance in reported cases. The differences in the regression effectiveness <lb/>can be attributed to intrinsic differences among continents, such as variations in vaccine cov-<lb/>erage, testing and sequencing capabilities, and the effectiveness of government stringency <lb/>measures. <lb/>While our model effectively captured the general trends of infection waves, it struggled to <lb/>accurately represent peaks within short time-frames in some countries. This discrepancy <lb/>might be attributed to the omission of certain predictor variables, like mass gatherings, which <lb/>are known to contribute to viral super-spreading events [32]. <lb/>In utilizing the OWID and OxCGRT datasets, which are arguably among the most compre-<lb/>hensive for addressing our research objectives, we note some limitations. First, there were dis-<lb/>crepancies in parameter definitions, such as varying case classifications across regions. Second, <lb/>positive tests are commonly labeled based on their reporting date rather than &quot;date-of-event&quot; <lb/>[33]. Lastly, the cases reported in these datasets may not be fully representative of the actual <lb/>disease burden. Although the Human Development Index (HDI) of a country can act as a <lb/>proxy to bridge the gap between reported cases and the true disease burden, it does not fully <lb/>capture the entire complexity. <lb/>The extracted signatures from the global SARS-CoV-2 dataset show clear and distinct pat-<lb/>terns describing mutational processes acting on the viral genome. The most prominent of <lb/>these signatures, Signature 1 (Fig 3 and S5 Fig), shows a marked bias towards C!T mutations, <lb/>a signal indicative of the APOBEC family of cytidine deaminases [17, 18]. APOBEC enzymes <lb/>have been shown to cause extensive C!T editing of DNA and RNA in human and viral <lb/>genomes. However, it is not yet clear whether they are the cause of this pronounced C!T bias <lb/>in SARS-CoV-2 despite a number of other studies also observing other APOBEC-like muta-<lb/>tional patterns [34-37]. Cytosines flanked by either an adenine or thymine in both the 3&apos; and <lb/>5&apos; direction appear to be the most pronounced targets of Signature 1. APOBEC editing was <lb/>shown to have contexts outside of the traditional TpC when structural features of the nucleic <lb/>acid such as hairpin loops are present [38]. Outside of structural features, APOBEC3A is <lb/>thought to be the predominant cause for TpC changes and is found to be expressed in lung tis-<lb/>sue [39]. ApC changes are considered to be caused by APOBEC1, which in cell models was <lb/>shown to efficiently edit SARS-CoV-2 RNA [39]. APOBEC1 is found predominately in the <lb/>liver and small intestine, tissues reported to be infected by SARS-CoV-2 [39, 40]. 3&apos; CpG nucle-<lb/>otide contexts are the most targeted, in particular TCG, CCG and ACG. CpG suppression is a <lb/>well-known dinucleotide bias. In RNA viruses, this appears to be a result of selective pressures <lb/>exerted from the presence of host CpG sensing molecules such as Zinc-finger Antiviral Protein <lb/>(ZAP). ZAP relies on host CpG suppression to allow it to specifically target non-host genomic <lb/>material (such as viral RNA) with higher CpG content [41]. This allows viruses with lower <lb/>CpG content to better evade restriction by ZAP since it more closely resembles the host CpG <lb/>composition. While ZAP does not induce C!T changes, it may help explain why C!T sites <lb/>in a CpG 3&apos; context are preferentially edited relative to other 3&apos; contexts. ZAP has been shown <lb/>to restrict SARS-CoV-2 despite pre-existing CpG depletion [42]. ZAP isoforms have been <lb/>shown to prevent necessary translational frame-shifting for SARS-CoV-2 ORF1b protein pro-<lb/>duction. [43]. The non-normalised form of Signature 1 (S5 Fig) shows that when tri-nucleotide <lb/>bias is not accounted for 3&apos; CpG&apos;s are lower than the normalised signatures, yet 5&apos; TpC and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>ApC contexts remain the most prevalent(S5 Fig). The most targeted contexts do shift to ACA, <lb/>ACT and TCT, likely reflecting their comparatively high abundance within the SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>genome relative to 3&apos;CpG contexts. These non-normalised contexts are consistent with what <lb/>was earlier reported by Simmonds et al. [17]). <lb/>Signature 2 (Fig 3 and S5 Fig) has a nearly identical proportion of A!G and T!C muta-<lb/>tions. These are a known target of the ADAR family of adenine deaminases. ADAR enzymes <lb/>typically operate on double-stranded RNA and convert adenine into inosine [21, 22]. Inosine <lb/>forms base pairs with cytosine, which after another round of replication causes guanine to <lb/>replace the inosine and complete the A!G change. As ADAR operates on both strands of <lb/>dsRNA, the mutational signature resulting from the process is expected to contain an equal <lb/>proportion of A!G and T!C mutations, which is the case for Signature 2 [21]. Signature 2 <lb/>also contains a number of G!A mutations, which could be caused by low-level C!T activity <lb/>on the negative sense RNA strand. Due to the cellular strand biases present between the posi-<lb/>tive and negative sense RNA [36], C!T mutational processes acting on ssRNA are much less <lb/>likely to produce a mutation on the negative strand (resulting in G!A substitutions) than <lb/>C!T changes on the positive strand. The negative strand will only be present during the repli-<lb/>cation phase of the virus while the positive strand will be present both on cell entry and on exit <lb/>as the new viral particles are packaged to infect further cells. This could explain why the nega-<lb/>tive sense Signature 1 changes are present in Signature 2, since it may be operating at a similar <lb/>level to Signature 2 on the negative strand. The non-normalised form of Signature 2 (S5 Fig) <lb/>does have different targeted contexts, just as with Signature 1. However, the main attribute of <lb/>Signature 2 is its equal contributions of A!G and T!C substitutions, which still remain <lb/>equal. <lb/>Signature 3 (Fig 3 and S5 Fig) is dominated by G!T substitutions. A putative mechanism <lb/>for this is Reactive Oxygen Species(ROS) in the cell. Increases in oxidative stress as part of a <lb/>ROS &apos;burst&apos; have been associated with viruses during the early stages of infection [34, 44]. Gua-<lb/>nine nucleotides are known to be vulnerable to oxidation, with the product 7,8-dihydro-8-oxo-<lb/>2&apos;-deoxyguanine (oxoguanine) pairing with adenine bases rather than cytosine [44, 45]. Similar <lb/>to inosine causing A!G changes, this change to oxoguanine will result in a G!T mutation <lb/>after a replication cycle. The lack of C!A changes in the signature also suggests that the mech-<lb/>anism is most active on the positive single-stranded RNA rather than the negative single-<lb/>stranded RNA. The initial positive single-stranded RNA is found in the cytoplasm, meaning it <lb/>can be easily accessed by ROS and other mechanisms of mutation. Viral replication is thought <lb/>to take place within membrane-bound environments that aim to protect the RNA. The pres-<lb/>ence of double-stranded RNA within these environments strongly suggests that this is the case <lb/>[46] and may explain the relative lack of negative strand mutations in SARS-CoV-2 signatures. <lb/>The non-normalised G!T signature (S5 Fig) seems to display a context preference of TpG and <lb/>ApG nucleotides, although this contextual bias is changed to CpG and ApG following normali-<lb/>sation. These contextual biases mean that the signature could be some other as yet unknown <lb/>editing mechanism on the viral RNA, although normalisation changing this context so heavily <lb/>suggests that this bias perhaps has more to do with genome composition. The increased CpG <lb/>context shift post-normalisation could also be another ZAP-induced effect, where CpG deple-<lb/>tion is selected for to help the virus evade ZAP. Curiously, this G!T bias has been observed in <lb/>other coronaviruses, but not widely among RNA viruses [47]. ROS has a verified cancer muta-<lb/>tional signature [15, 48] although the context preferences do not match the signatures (normal-<lb/>ised or non-normalised) observed here. However, there are a multitude of differences between <lb/>viral RNA and human DNA that make these signatures difficult to compare. <lb/>It is important to note that while SARS-CoV-2 does have an error correction mechanism <lb/>resulting in fewer replicase-induced errors, this mechanism will not catch all changes. A <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>number of the mutations picked up from the set of sequences (and included in our mutational <lb/>signatures) will be derived from replication errors. However, the clear and repeatable extrac-<lb/>tion of the signatures indicates that despite this potential contamination, the extracted signa-<lb/>tures do appear to be predominantly other mutational processes. While a replication error-<lb/>associated mutational signature may be identified in future, this signature is too diffuse to <lb/>identify as a distinct process. Similarly, a high proportion of mutations are not accounted for <lb/>by the extracted mutational signatures. These mutations were not present in large enough <lb/>quantities to enable effective extraction from the data. Future methods may be able to tease out <lb/>the more subtle mutational mechanisms that almost certainly exist to induce these less com-<lb/>mon mutation types. <lb/>Signature activities clearly change in both the global dataset and in the various subsets of <lb/>the data for VOCs and continents. In the global data (Fig 4) Signature 1 is dominant through-<lb/>out the pandemic. Signature 2 only begins to appear around November 2020, after which it <lb/>appears consistently active for the remainder of the pandemic. This is approximately when <lb/>variant of concern lineages began to emerge, as well as the beginning of the first vaccine roll-<lb/>outs. This is particularly apparent in the Alpha subset where Signature 2 is the most highly <lb/>active mutational process (Fig 5), with a large depletion of Signature 1 activity as well. <lb/>Alpha was shown to increase sub-genomic RNA expression of several immune-antagonist <lb/>viral proteins including nucleocapsid (N), ORF9b and ORF6 [49-52]. N is thought to shield <lb/>dsRNA from detection by RNA sensors, which trigger downstream antiviral response path-<lb/>ways [49, 52-54]. ORF9b antagonises TOM70, a protein required for the activation of mito-<lb/>chondrial antiviral-signalling proteins (MAVS) [49] while ORF6 inhibits the transportation to <lb/>the nucleus of inflammatory transcription factors [55]. Combined, the cumulative immune <lb/>inhibition may have resulted in an observable change in the mutational processes that we <lb/>observe within the Alpha lineage. Beta and Gamma (both VOCs that emerged around the <lb/>same time as Alpha) gained amino acid substitutions that helped evade the immune system <lb/>primarily via antigenic change. Alpha&apos;s reliance on attenuating immune pathways rather than <lb/>antibody binding may be why we see a different signature exposure pattern in this VOC rela-<lb/>tive to the others. This could be due to the attenuated pathways being involved in signalling for <lb/>the mutational processes behind Signatures 1 and 3, while not inhibiting Signature 2 as much. <lb/>This Alpha pattern is not observed in the other VOC datasets, although Delta and Omicron <lb/>have a high level of Signature 2 exposure as well, despite Signature 1 remaining the dominant <lb/>process in those subsets. Signature 3 appears to be most prominently found in the Delta subset <lb/>and remains consistently at low levels in the global data until January 2022 when it appears to <lb/>disappear almost entirely. The Omicron subset has little to no exposure for Signature 3 and <lb/>this happens to be the VOC almost exclusively circulating after January 2022. Why Omicron <lb/>appears to have so little Signature 3 exposure is unclear, although unlike previous VOCs, Omi-<lb/>cron differs in its preference of cell entry mechanism. Previous variants of the virus typically <lb/>enter the cell using membrane fusion, where the viral membrane fuses with the cell membrane <lb/>via the action of ACE-2 receptor binding and TMPRSS2 cleavage of the spike protein. Omi-<lb/>cron instead favours an endosomal route of entry whereby the viral particle binds to the cell <lb/>using ACE-2 and is enveloped by endocytosis into the cell. Cleavage of the spike protein then <lb/>occurs via the action of Cathepsin L, which allows for the release of the viral RNA into the <lb/>cytoplasm of the now-infected cell [56, 57]. <lb/>Signature transitions from Signature 1 to Signature 2 changes occur from December 2020 <lb/>onwards in the global dataset and appears consistently in the VOC and continent-defined sub-<lb/>sets around this time point as well. Alpha underwent a major shift to Signature 2 mutations <lb/>early in its time as a VOC, although Signature 1 returned as the predominant set of changes <lb/>towards the end of its wave of infections. The non-VOC subset appears to be the least impacted <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>by Signature 2 changes. However, this can mostly be explained by the number of non-VOC <lb/>sequences quickly declining after the emergence of the VOC lineages. Delta underwent a dra-<lb/>matic increase in Signature 2 and Signature 3 exposure from July 2021, with Signature 2 <lb/>becoming the predominant signature towards the end of Deltas wave. Signature 2 changes <lb/>continue into Omicrons introduction, although it does decrease after the initial BA.1 wave <lb/>from December 2021 to March 2022. It seems clear that while Signature 1 mutations have <lb/>dominated in contributing to the evolutionary capacity of SARS-CoV-2 throughout the pan-<lb/>demic, this mutational environment is beginning to change. Such shifts in mutational pro-<lb/>cesses are potentially evidence of changing interactions between the viruses and the immune <lb/>systems of the hosts they circulate within. For example, changes in population-level immunity <lb/>via vaccination or previous infections may influence the mutations that we observe in the data. <lb/>Changing mutational process activity in consensus sequences from infections is unlikely to <lb/>fully reflect the true activity of each process, but they are likely to show which processes are <lb/>contributing mutations that eventually make it into circulating viruses. <lb/>All variants of concern we assessed show predominantly non-synonymous mutations and <lb/>all mutational signatures are associated with more non-synonymous than synonymous <lb/>changes. More synonymous substitutions in the lineage references were found in ORF1a/b, <lb/>which is expected due to it being the longest ORF. However, this pattern is not observed with <lb/>non-synonymous mutations as these are mainly located in the spike protein (Fig 6C and 6D). <lb/>This is consistent with spike being under intense immune pressure since it is the main glyco-<lb/>protein for SARS-CoV-2. As such, spike must change in order to escape the host immune <lb/>response, while maintaining its main function of binding and entry into host cells. Signature 1 <lb/>changes are the predominant source of mutations in all SARS-CoV-2 VOCs that we analysed, <lb/>followed by unattributed mutations, Signature 2 changes and Signature 3 changes. Signature 3 <lb/>changes were unlikely to be synonymous mutations with only Beta, Gamma and Delta con-<lb/>taining very few such changes (Fig 6D). This is also reflected in the global synonymous/non-<lb/>synonymous exposures where Signature 3 appears completely inactive in the synonymous <lb/>mutation subset (Fig 6A). Signature 2 exposure appears the most likely to be synonymous <lb/>mutations (Fig 6A) but this does not seem to be observed in the VOC lineages where most Sig-<lb/>nature 2 changes are non-synonymous mutations (Fig 6B). <lb/>In conclusion, mutational signature analysis reveals important processes contributing to <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 genetic variation and serves as a tool to track the dominant changes over time <lb/>and to generate hypotheses about the main mechanistic processes in play. Specifically, host <lb/>antiviral molecules as opposed to replication errors appear to be a the main generator of muta-<lb/>tions (confirming earlier computational studies), a result that requires experimental confirma-<lb/>tion. Despite limitations in potential biases, our findings contribute to a better understanding <lb/>of the complex dynamics driving the evolution of SARS-CoV-2 and the emergence of VOCs. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Data <lb/>The findings of this study are based on metadata associated with 13,281,213 sequences avail-<lb/>able on GISAID up to October 26, 2022 and accessible at doi.org/10.55876/gis8.221201qs. <lb/>Sequences were filtered to remove records from non-human hosts, with lengths less than <lb/>20,000 nucleotides, non-assigned lineages, with greater than 30% unknown bases, sequences <lb/>reported to be collected before 24/12/2019 and those with excessive mutations/deletions. The <lb/>cutoff for filtering out hypermutated sequences was 175 mutations in coding regions or more <lb/>than 69 different deletions, the cutoffs were manually determined after evaluation of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>mutation/deletion distribution and selecting the point where sequence counts were consis-<lb/>tently observed in single digits, this resulted in 1,852 sequences being filtered out. <lb/>Publicly available daily SARS-CoV-2 cases, tests performed and total vaccinations per capita <lb/>were obtained from OWID [58] in September 2022. Prior to February 2023, the OWID data <lb/>was piped from the Johns Hopkins University COVID-19 dashboard [33, 59]. Country-level <lb/>government stringency indices were downloaded from OxCGRT [60]. Government stringency <lb/>indices are composed of nine indicators: school closure, workplace closure, cancellation of <lb/>public events, stay at home order, public information campaigns, restrictions on public gather-<lb/>ings, public transport, internal movement and international travel. The index on a given day <lb/>ranges from 0 to 100 and is calculated as the mean of the nine indicators, with higher indices <lb/>indicating stricter regulations. If responses vary at sub-national levels, the index at the strictest <lb/>level is used [60]. <lb/>Wastewater findings are based on metadata associated with 1,343 sequences available on <lb/>GISAID and accessible at doi.org/10.55876/gis8.230406qg. Wastewater sequences were down-<lb/>loaded from the &apos;wastewater data&apos; section of GISAID in December 2022. <lb/>Sequences for immunocompromised individuals were downloaded from GISAID in <lb/>November 2022. Analysis of this was based on the metadata associated with 34 sequences avail-<lb/>able on GISAID and accessible at doi.org/10.55876/gis8.230406fb. Sequences were chosen <lb/>based on the known list of sequences used in [30]. Sequences were aligned to the COVID refer-<lb/>ence genome before use. <lb/>Design <lb/>Predictors of SARS-CoV-2 reported cases were explored using a linear model at both country <lb/>and continent levels. We collected continuous dependent variables reported on a daily basis. <lb/>These were classified into two groups: (i) public health measures (government stringency, test-<lb/>ing capacity and vaccination), (ii) viral properties (diversity and fitness). We examined the <lb/>data for completeness of predictive variables. In instances of missing vaccination data, we <lb/>interpreted this as no vaccinations having been given. This was a reasonable assumption for <lb/>periods prior to the vaccine rollouts in the respective countries. With the exception of vaccina-<lb/>tions, variables with less than 70% of the countries reporting data were not included. The num-<lb/>ber of SARS-CoV-2 diagnostic tests performed was excluded as a predictor due to missing <lb/>data. We determined the previous burden by summing the adjusted new cases per capita over <lb/>the past 90 days. Prior infection significantly reduces the risk of a subsequent infection, with a <lb/>reduction in risk of up to 95% in the initial three months [61]. This was included as a predictor <lb/>variable in the linear model. <lb/>Amino acid substitutions were defined against the Wuhan-Hu-1 sequence. Building on <lb/>findings from Obermeyer et al., we extracted a list of previously identified fitness-associated <lb/>mutations [62]. Each fit mutation within a sequence was counted and the counts were normal-<lb/>ized to the number of sequences per geographical location. Virus fitness was therefore defined <lb/>as the sum of the frequencies of previously identified [62] amino acid substitutions that <lb/>increase SARS-CoV-2 fitness divided by the sum of total genomes and the log of total muta-<lb/>tions per location. <lb/>Virus Fitness ¼ <lb/>weekly sum of fit mutations <lb/>total seqs per week þ logðtotal mutations per weekÞ <lb/>Diversity was calculated by dividing distinct lineages by the total number of genomes in a <lb/>given week. Sequences reported in GISAID were assumed to be representative of the diversity <lb/>of infections for that continent/country. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Linear model <lb/>We employed a linear regression model, described by Heo et al. [63], to adjust reported cases <lb/>per country using the Human Development Index (HDI), which encompasses not just eco-<lb/>nomic growth but also reflects a country&apos;s capacity for per capita testing. Countries with higher <lb/>HDI levels, typically high-income nations, conducted more tests per million people, often lead-<lb/>ing to more confirmed cases compared to nations with lower HDI levels. Adjusted daily cases <lb/>were smoothed using a 14-days rolling average to limit possible noise and identify simplified <lb/>changes over time. For continent-level analysis, data from all contributing countries was used <lb/>to fit the linear model. To ensure that countries with a large number of cases didn&apos;t artificially <lb/>inflate the results, each country&apos;s influence on the continent-level OxCGRT index was adjusted <lb/>based on its percent contribution to the continent&apos;s 14-day average daily case tally. <lb/>Pearson&apos;s correlation was used to test for correlation among the variables. Multiple linear <lb/>regression was fitted to evaluate the relationship between infection rate (adjusted daily cases <lb/>per capita) as the outcome and the public health measures and viral properties as predictors <lb/>within the different continents. The regression models were fitted on data from 01 April 2020 <lb/>onwards, as (sequence) data addition remained stable after this. The country-level analysis was <lb/>carried out for countries with less than 50 days of missing genome data using a similar <lb/>approach. <lb/>Pandemic plots <lb/>Case numbers and sequence data were aggregated by their respective continents, a 14-day roll-<lb/>ing average was used to smooth out daily infection rates and categorical variables were sum-<lb/>marised by counts. Proportions of lineages were calculated in 14-days bins and the most <lb/>common lineages were visualised per continent. <lb/>Tree-based referencing <lb/>The rapid evolution of SARS-CoV-2 means that the majority of viral sequences are distinct <lb/>from the early pandemic reference genome Wuhan-Hu-1 [64]. Continuing to count mutations <lb/>against the early reference sequence can result in mutations being allocated the wrong substi-<lb/>tution category (i.e., A!T instead of a C!T) where sites have mutated multiple times. Azgari <lb/>et al. [35] tackled this issue by building a tree of clustered sequences to remove ancestral muta-<lb/>tions. However, we utilise the available SARS-CoV-2 tree generated as part of the Pango [8] <lb/>nomenclature to generate a reference sequence for each defined lineage. This means that <lb/>sequences from the lineage B.1 are compared against a generated reference sequence for the B <lb/>lineage rather than the Wuhan-1 sequence (See S3 Fig for diagrammatic description). <lb/>One reference sequence was generated for each of the Pango lineages in the alignment. A <lb/>nucleotide was included in the generated Pango reference if it exceeded a frequency threshold <lb/>of greater than 75% of the samples from the lineage. If this threshold was not reached, the ref-<lb/>erence nucleotide of the nearest parental lineage was used (i.e., if a mutation in B.1 is ambigu-<lb/>ous, the nucleotide from the B lineage reference at that position is used). Building intermediate <lb/>references also meant that counting inherited mutations could be avoided. Since mutations <lb/>were identified relative to their nearest parental Pango lineage, inherited mutations are not <lb/>counted because, relative to this sequence, there hasn&apos;t been a mutation. Mutations are also <lb/>only counted once per lineage set of sequences so that mutations that are observed many times <lb/>due spread of the virus rather than acquisition by a mutational process are not over-counted. <lb/>This means that convergent amino acid substitutions can be observed between lineage sets, <lb/>although they may be undercounted within a lineage. However, this is necessary since it is very <lb/>difficult to identify convergence within similar sequences (especially at a global scale). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Overcounting of the mutations results in mutational signatures that reflect the circulating pre-<lb/>dominant lineages rather than the mutational processes producing the mutations in those <lb/>lineages. <lb/>Pseudo-sampling <lb/>Mutations were binned into categories composed of their substitution type (e.g., cytosine ! <lb/>thymine = CT) and their mutation context. The mutation context is the mutated base and <lb/>the nucleotides at the 5&apos; and 3&apos; positions of the mutated base. There are a total of 192 types <lb/>of substitution-context matchings that can appear (12 possible single nucleotide changes x <lb/>four possible nucleotide 5&apos; x four possible nucleotide 3&apos;). Every sequence produces a single <lb/>count vector of mutation category counts, with the total count matrix becoming the muta-<lb/>tional catalogue of the virus. On average, a single SARS-CoV-2 genome sequence has very <lb/>few new mutations. As extracting mutational signatures when mutation counts are low is <lb/>unlikely to produce meaningful results, we define each sample as a time-point (all of the <lb/>sequences collected in an epidemic week) and decompose signatures from the counts at <lb/>each time-point rather than from each sequence. This shrinks the mutational catalogue of <lb/>the virus from millions of samples down to less than 200 samples, one for each Epidemic <lb/>Week. <lb/>Non-negative matrix factorisation <lb/>NMF (non-negative matrix factorisation) [65, 66] was used to split the mutational catalogue <lb/>into two sub-matrices. One matrix represents the mutational signatures, the other matrix rep-<lb/>resents the exposure of the signatures. These matrices were used to reconstruct the original <lb/>mutational catalogue with some degree of error. To verify the validity of the identified signa-<lb/>tures, NMF was performed 100 times for each value of N, with N representing the number of <lb/>signatures to extract from the mutational catalogue. For this analysis, N was set to 2, . . ., 10. <lb/>For each NMF run, a new mutational catalogue was generated using bootstrap re-sampling of <lb/>the original matrix and removal of any mutational categories that did not account for more <lb/>than 0.5% of mutations. Mutational categories are pseudo-sampled down into epidemic week <lb/>matrices that NMF was run on. The signatures were then clustered together using K-means <lb/>clustering, with the cluster means forming the new signatures. Clusters were then assessed <lb/>using the silhouette score to determine the clustering quality. Clusters with high silhouette <lb/>scores are well separated from other clusters and are dense and well-formed. Cosine similarity <lb/>was used to determine if the signature was reliably extracted from the cluster. The cosine simi-<lb/>larity was calculated between signatures extracted from the whole mutational catalogue and <lb/>the cluster means of the signature clusters. A higher cosine similarity indicates that the cluster <lb/>mean shows a similar pattern to the initial mutational signature. Following the best practices <lb/>in Islam et al. [66], an N value of three was selected due to the reduction of the reconstruction <lb/>error plateauing around three and the marked decrease in silhouette score for signatures <lb/>greater than 3. The average cosine similarity between signatures and clusters was consistently <lb/>above 0.95 for each cluster and had an average of 0.98 for all three clusters when clustering was <lb/>repeated 100 times. Silhouette scores for each cluster were above 0.95, suggesting excellent sep-<lb/>aration and density of clusters (S5 Table and S9 Fig). Signatures can therefore be reliably <lb/>extracted from the bootstrapped catalogues, are robust and thus are unlikely to be artefacts. <lb/>Counts of mutations were normalised by the tri-mer composition of the SARS-CoV-2 refer-<lb/>ence sequence (dividing the counts by the number of contexts in the reference sequence). <lb/>Composition biased versions of the signatures were then produced by rescaling the signatures <lb/>using tri-mer composition. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<body>Non-negative least squares regression <lb/>A non-negative least squares (NNLS) Regression was used to produce positive exposure <lb/>weights for each of the signatures in each of the datasets. The non-negativity of the regression <lb/>ensures that the weights of the signatures continue to represent an additive process. The NNLS <lb/>weights can then represent the exposures of the signatures on each dataset. <lb/>Consensus lineage and continent signatures <lb/>Mutational catalogues were constructed for each continent and each of the Variant of Concern <lb/>(VOC) lineages (Alpha, Beta, Gamma, Delta and Omicron). The global signatures were then <lb/>used to extract exposures for each of the mutational catalogues to determine how processes <lb/>varied between each mutational catalogue subset. VOC sequence sets were filtered so that <lb/>weeks with fewer than 100 sequences were excluded. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Country-level SARS-CoV-2 lineage dynamics. Solid bars show the biweekly propor-<lb/>tions of the common lineages. Bars are coloured by lineage and white space shows the propor-<lb/>tion of sequences from other lineages. The countries included in this analysis is based on <lb/>temporal data completeness. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Model-fitting of country-level SARS-CoV-2 reported cases. Black solid lines show a <lb/>14-day rolling average of adjusted SARS-CoV-2 cases. Pink solid lines show fitted mean <lb/>response values of infection rates with predictor values as input and grey shaded areas high-<lb/>light the confidence intervals. The countries included in this analysis is based on temporal data <lb/>completeness. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S3 Fig. Diagrammatic depiction of how tree-based referencing works. Each Pango lineage <lb/>has a reference generated for it. Arrows show which sequences use which reference sequence, <lb/>with the arrow tip indicating the reference. For example, sequences from the B.1 lineage are <lb/>compared against the reference for the B lineage so that B.1 lineage-defining mutations can be <lb/>counted. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S4 Fig. Graphical description of the methods for NMF extraction of mutational signatures. <lb/>For every value of N signatures, the mutational signatures are extracted 100 times for boot-<lb/>straped and pseudo-sampled datasets. Once this has been completed, signatures are clustered <lb/>into N clusters and the stability and density of those clusters are evaluated using the silhouette <lb/>score. Signatures that have silhouette scores above 0.95 are evaluated as stable signatures. The <lb/>cluster means become the extracted signatures. The best set of N signatures is selected by pick-<lb/>ing the value of N that best minimises the reconstruction error and has the best silhouette score <lb/>(with a minimum of 0.95). A further evaluation is the cosine similarity of the clustered signa-<lb/>ture means with the signatures extracted by completing NMF on the original pseudo-sampled <lb/>dataset. Again, signatures must have a cosine similarity of at least 0.95 to be considered. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S5 Fig. Non-normalised mutational signatures for SARS-CoV-2. Signatures were extracted <lb/>using normalised counts calculated by dividing the mutation counts by the count of the tri-<lb/>nucleotide context of the mutation context (Fig 4). These signatures were then multiplied <lb/>post-analysis by the tri-nucleotide composition of the reference sequence to produce the non-<lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">normalised signatures shown here. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S6 Fig. Counts of unique substitutions per week of the pandemic. Areas are coloured by <lb/>substitution category. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S7 Fig. Counts of unique substitutions per week of the pandemic for each VOC category. <lb/>Areas are coloured by substitution category. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S8 Fig. Counts of unique substitutions per week of the pandemic for each continent cate-<lb/>gory. Areas are coloured by substitution category. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S9 Fig. Signature evaluation metrics. The number of signatures was selected at N = 3 since <lb/>this produced an &quot;elbow&quot; for the reconstruction error while having a suitable silhouette score <lb/>greater than 0.95. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Proportion of common lineages/variants globally. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S2 Table. Correlation between infection rate and predictor variables across different conti-<lb/>nents. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S3 Table. Effect of public health measures (government stringency and vaccination) and <lb/>viral properties (diversity and fitness) on infection rates at continent level. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S4 Table. Effect of public health measures (government stringency and vaccination) and <lb/>viral properties (diversity and fitness) on infection rates at national levels. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/>S5 Table. Evaluation Results for Signature with N = 3. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We gratefully acknowledge all data contributors, i.e., the authors and their originating labora-<lb/>tories responsible for obtaining the specimens and their submitting laboratories for generating <lb/>the genetic sequence and metadata and sharing via the GISAID Initiative, on which this <lb/>research is based. For the purpose of open access, the author has applied a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution (CC BY) licence to any Author Accepted Manuscript version arising. We thank <lb/>Spyros Lytras, Francesca Young, Sejal Modha, Andres Gomez and Procheta Sen for their help-<lb/>ful comments throughout the process of writing and preparing this manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Kieran D. Lamb, Ke Yuan, David L. Robertson. <lb/>Data curation: Richard J. Orton. <lb/>Formal analysis: Kieran D. Lamb, Martha M. Luka, Megan Saathoff. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Funding acquisition: Matthew Cotten, Ke Yuan, David L. Robertson. <lb/>Investigation: Kieran D. Lamb, Martha M. Luka, Ke Yuan, David L. Robertson. <lb/>Methodology: Kieran D. Lamb, Ke Yuan. <lb/>Resources: Kieran D. Lamb. <lb/>Software: Kieran D. Lamb. <lb/>Supervision: My V. T. Phan, Matthew Cotten, Ke Yuan, David L. Robertson. <lb/>Visualization: Kieran D. Lamb. <lb/>Writing -original draft: Kieran D. Lamb, Martha M. Luka, Megan Saathoff. <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: Kieran D. Lamb, Martha M. Luka, My V. T. Phan, Matthew Cot-<lb/>ten, Ke Yuan, David L. Robertson. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Yang X, Yu Y, Xu J, Shu H, Xia J, Liu H, et al. Clinical course and outcomes of critically ill patients with <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 pneumonia in Wuhan, China: a single-centered, retrospective, observational study. The <lb/>Lancet Respiratory Medicine. 2020; 8:475-481. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2213-2600(20)30079-5 <lb/>PMID: 32105632 <lb/>2. Li Q, Guan X, Wu P, Wang X, Zhou L, Tong Y, et al. Early Transmission Dynamics in Wuhan, China, of <lb/>Novel Coronavirus-Infected Pneumonia. New England Journal of Medicine. 2020; 382:1199-1207. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1056/NEJMoa2001316 PMID: 31995857 <lb/>3. Petersen E, Koopmans M, Go U, Hamer DH, Petrosillo N, Castelli F, et al. Comparing SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>with SARS-CoV and influenza pandemics. The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2020; 20:e238-e244. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30484-9 PMID: 32628905 <lb/>4. da Silva Filipe A, Shepherd JG, Williams T, Hughes J, Aranday-Cortes E, Asamaphan P, et al. Geno-<lb/>mic epidemiology reveals multiple introductions of SARS-CoV-2 from mainland Europe into Scotland. <lb/>Nature Microbiology 2020; 6:112-122. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-020-00838-z PMID: <lb/>33349681 <lb/>5. Dewi A, Nurmandi A, Rochmawati E, Purnomo EP, Rizqi MD, Azzahra A, et al. Global policy responses <lb/>to the COVID-19 pandemic: proportionate adaptation and policy experimentation: a study of country <lb/>policy response variation to the COVID-19 pandemic. Health Promotion Perspectives. 2020; 10:359. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.34172/hpp.2020.54 PMID: 33312931 <lb/>6. Kirby T. New variant of SARS-CoV-2 in UK causes surge of COVID-19. The Lancet Respiratory medi-<lb/>cine. 2021; 9:e20-e21. https://doi.org/10.1016/S2213-2600(21)00005-9 PMID: 33417829 <lb/>7. Lauring AS, Hodcroft EB. Genetic Variants of SARS-CoV-2-What Do They Mean? JAMA. 2021; <lb/>325:529-531. PMID: 33404586 <lb/>8. Rambaut A, Holmes EC, O&apos;Toole A ´ine, Hill V, McCrone JT, Ruis C, et al. A dynamic nomenclature pro-<lb/>posal for SARS-CoV-2 lineages to assist genomic epidemiology. Nature Microbiology 2020; 5:1403-<lb/>1407. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-020-0770-5 PMID: 32669681 <lb/>9. Harvey WT, Carabelli AM, Jackson B, Gupta RK, Thomson EC, Harrison EM, et al. SARS-CoV-2 vari-<lb/>ants, spike mutations and immune escape. Nature Reviews Microbiology 2021; 19:409-424. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1038/s41579-021-00573-0 PMID: 34075212 <lb/>10. WHO. Coronavirus Disease (COVID-19) Situation Reports; 2022. Available from: https://www.who.int/ <lb/>emergencies/diseases/novel-coronavirus-2019/situation-reports. <lb/>11. Tegally H, Wilkinson E, Giovanetti M, Iranzadeh A, Fonseca V, Giandhari J, et al. Detection of a SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 variant of concern in South Africa. Nature 2021; 592:438-443. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-<lb/>021-03402-9 PMID: 33690265 <lb/>12. Bugembe DL, Phan MVT, Ssewanyana I, Semanda P, Nansumba H, Dhaala B, et al. Emergence and <lb/>spread of a SARS-CoV-2 lineage A variant (A.23.1) with altered spike protein in Uganda. Nature Micro-<lb/>biology 2021; 6:1094-1101. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-021-00933-9 PMID: 34163035 <lb/>13. Mlcochova P, Kemp SA, Dhar MS, Papa G, Meng B, Ferreira IATM, et al. SARS-CoV-2 B.1.617.2 Delta <lb/>variant replication and immune evasion. Nature. 2021; 599:7883. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-<lb/>03944-y PMID: 34488225 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Alexandrov LB, Stratton MR. Mutational signatures: the patterns of somatic mutations hidden in cancer <lb/>genomes. Current opinion in genetics &amp; development. 2014; 24:52-60. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.gde. <lb/>2013.11.014 PMID: 24657537 <lb/>15. Alexandrov LB, Nik-Zainal S, Wedge DC, Aparicio SAJR, Behjati S, Biankin AV, et al. Signatures of <lb/>mutational processes in human cancer. Nature 2013; 500:415-421. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nature12477 PMID: 23945592 <lb/>16. Forbes SA, Beare D, Boutselakis H, Bamford S, Bindal N, Tate J, et al. COSMIC: Somatic cancer <lb/>genetics at high-resolution. Nucleic Acids Research. 2017; 45:D777-D783. https://doi.org/10.1093/nar/ <lb/>gkw1121 PMID: 27899578 <lb/>17. Simmonds P. Rampant C!U Hypermutation in the Genomes of SARS-CoV-2 and Other Coronavi-<lb/>ruses: Causes and Consequences for Their Short-and Long-Term Evolutionary Trajectories. mSphere. <lb/>2020; 5. https://doi.org/10.1128/mSphere.00408-20 PMID: 32581081 <lb/>18. Ratcliff J, Simmonds P. Potential APOBEC-mediated RNA editing of the genomes of SARS-CoV-2 and <lb/>other coronaviruses and its impact on their longer term evolution. Virology. 2021; 556:62. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.virol.2020.12.018 PMID: 33545556 <lb/>19. Sanjua ´n R, Domingo-Calap P. Mechanisms of viral mutation. Cellular and molecular life sciences. <lb/>2016; 73:4433-4448. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-016-2299-6 PMID: 27392606 <lb/>20. Shu Y, McCauley J. GISAID: Global initiative on sharing all influenza data-from vision to reality. <lb/>Eurosurveillance. 2017; 22(13). https://doi.org/10.2807/1560-7917.ES.2017.22.13.30494 PMID: <lb/>28382917 <lb/>21. Picardi E, Mansi L, Pesole G. Detection of A-to-I RNA Editing in SARS-COV-2. Genes 2021; 13:41. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3390/genes13010041 PMID: 35052382 <lb/>22. Ringlander J, Fingal J, Kann H, Prakash K, Rydell G, Andersson M, et al. Impact of ADAR-induced edit-<lb/>ing of minor viral RNA populations on replication and transmission of SARS-CoV-2. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences of the United States of America. 2022; 119:e2112663119. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1073/pnas.2112663119 PMID: 35064076 <lb/>23. Bloom JD, Beichman AC, Neher RA, Harris K. Evolution of the SARS-CoV-2 Mutational Spectrum. <lb/>Molecular Biology and Evolution. 2023; 40(4). https://doi.org/10.1093/molbev/msad085 PMID: <lb/>37039557 <lb/>24. Ruis C, Peacock TP, Polo LM, Masone D, Alvarez MS, Hinrichs AS, et al. Mutational spectra distinguish <lb/>SARS-COV-2 replication niches. 2022. https://doi.org/10.1101/2022.09.27.509649 <lb/>25. Wang P, Nair MS, Liu L, Iketani S, Luo Y, Guo Y, et al. Antibody resistance of SARS-CoV-2 variants <lb/>B.1.351 and B.1.1.7. Nature 2021; 593:130-135. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-021-03398-2 PMID: <lb/>33684923 <lb/>26. Wang Z, Schmidt F, Weisblum Y, Muecksch F, Barnes CO, Finkin S, et al. mRNA vaccine-elicited anti-<lb/>bodies to SARS-CoV-2 and circulating variants. Nature 2021; 592:616-622. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41586-021-03324-6 PMID: 33567448 <lb/>27. Ou J, Lan W, Wu X, Zhao T, Duan B, Yang P, et al. Tracking SARS-CoV-2 Omicron diverse spike gene <lb/>mutations identifies multiple inter-variant recombination events. Signal Transduction and Targeted <lb/>Therapy 2022; 7:1-9. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-022-00992-2 PMID: 35474215 <lb/>28. Shafer MM, Gregory D, Bobholz MJ, Roguet A, Haddock Soto LA, Rushford C, et al. Tracing the origin <lb/>of SARS-CoV-2 Omicron-like Spike sequences detected in wastewater. medRxiv. 2022; https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1101/2022.10.28.22281553 <lb/>29. Chaguza C, Hahn AM, Petrone ME, Zhou S, Ferguson D, Breban MI, et al. Accelerated SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>intrahost evolution leading to distinct genotypes during chronic infection. Cell Reports Medicine. 2023; <lb/>p. 100943. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xcrm.2023.100943 PMID: 36791724 <lb/>30. Harari S, Tahor M, Rutsinsky N, Meijer S, Miller D, Henig O, et al. Drivers of adaptive evolution during <lb/>chronic SARS-CoV-2 infections. Nature Medicine. 2022; 28(7):1501-1508. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41591-022-01882-4 PMID: 35725921 <lb/>31. Bamgboye EL, Omiye JA, Afolaranmi OJ, Davids MR, Tannor EK, Wadee S, et al. COVID-19 Pan-<lb/>demic: Is Africa Different? Journal of the National Medical Association. 2021; 113:324. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.jnma.2020.10.001 PMID: 33153755 <lb/>32. Herng LC, Singh S, Sundram BM, Zamri ASSM, Vei TC, Aris T, et al. The effects of super spreading <lb/>events and movement control measures on the COVID-19 pandemic in Malaysia. Scientific Reports. <lb/>2022; 12. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-022-06341-1 PMID: 35140319 <lb/>33. Dong E, Ratcliff J, Goyea TD, Katz A, Lau R, Ng TK, et al. The Johns Hopkins University Center for Sys-<lb/>tems Science and Engineering COVID-19 Dashboard: data collection process, challenges faced, and <lb/>lessons learned; The Lancet Infectious Diseases, 22(12), e370-e376. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-<lb/>3099(22)00434-0 PMID: 36057267 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>34. Graudenzi A, Maspero D, Angaroni F, Piazza R, Ramazzotti D. Mutational signatures and heteroge-<lb/>neous host response revealed via large-scale characterization of SARS-CoV-2 genomic diversity. <lb/>ISCIENCE. 2021; 24:102116. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.isci.2021.102116 PMID: 33532709 <lb/>35. Azgari C, Kilinc Z, Turhan B, Circi D, Adebali O, Castilletti C, et al. The Mutation Profile of SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>Is Primarily Shaped by the Host Antiviral Defense. Signal Transduction and Targeted Therapy 2022 <lb/>7:1. 2021. https://doi.org/10.3390/v13030394 PMID: 33801257 <lb/>36. Giorgio SD, Martignano F, Torcia MG, Mattiuz G, Conticello SG. Evidence for host-dependent RNA <lb/>editing in the transcriptome of SARS-CoV-2. Science Advances. 2020; 6:5813-5830. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1126/sciadv.abb5813 PMID: 32596474 <lb/>37. Yi K, Kim SY, Bleazard T, Kim T, Youk J, Ju YS. Mutational spectrum of SARS-COV-2 during the global <lb/>pandemic. Experimental &amp; Molecular Medicine. 2021; 53(8):1229-1237. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s12276-021-00658-z PMID: 34453107 <lb/>38. Langenbucher A, Bowen D, Sakhtemani R, Bournique E, Wise JF, Zou L, et al. An extended APO-<lb/>BEC3A mutation signature in cancer. Nature Communications. 2021; 12. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>s41467-021-21891-0 PMID: 33707442 <lb/>39. Kim K, Calabrese P, Wang S, Qin C, Rao Y, Feng P, et al. The Roles of APOBEC-mediated RNA Edit-<lb/>ing in SARS-CoV-2 Mutations, Replication and Fitness. bioRxiv. 2021.12.18.473309. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1101/2021.12.18.473309 <lb/>40. Trypsteen W, Cleemput JV, van Snippenberg W, Gerlo S, Vandekerckhove L. On the whereabouts of <lb/>SARS-CoV-2 in the human body: A systematic review. PLOS Pathogens. 2020; 16:e1009037. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1009037 PMID: 33125439 <lb/>41. Takata MA, Gonc ¸alves-Carneiro D, Zang TM, Soll SJ, York A, Blanco-Melo D, et al. CG dinucleotide <lb/>suppression enables antiviral defence targeting non-self RNA. Nature. 2017; 550(7674):124-127. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nature24039 PMID: 28953888 <lb/>42. Nchioua R, Kmiec D, Mu ¨ller JA, Conzelmann C, Groß R, Swanson CM, et al. Sars-cov-2 is restricted by <lb/>zinc finger antiviral protein despite preadaptation to the low-cpg environment in humans. mBio. 2020; <lb/>11(5):1-19. https://doi.org/10.1128/mBio.01930-20 <lb/>43. Zimmer MM, Kibe A, Rand U, Pekarek L, Ye L, Buck S, et al. The short isoform of the host antiviral pro-<lb/>tein ZAP acts as an inhibitor of SARS-CoV-2 programmed ribosomal frameshifting. Nature Communica-<lb/>tions. 2021; 12(1):1-15. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-021-27431-0 PMID: 34893599 <lb/>44. Mourier T, Sadykov M, Carr MJ, Gonzalez G, Hall WW, Pain A. Host-directed editing of the SARS-CoV-<lb/>2 genome. Biochemical and Biophysical Research Communications. 2021; 538:35-39. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1016/j.bbrc.2020.10.092 PMID: 33234239 <lb/>45. Li Z, Wu J, DeLeo CJ. RNA damage and surveillance under oxidative stress. IUBMB Life. 2006; <lb/>58:581-588. https://doi.org/10.1080/15216540600946456 PMID: 17050375 <lb/>46. V&apos;kovski P, Kratzel A, Steiner S, Stalder H, Thiel V. Coronavirus biology and replication: implications for <lb/>SARS-CoV-2. Nature Reviews Microbiology 2020; 19:155-170. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-020-<lb/>00468-6 PMID: 33116300 <lb/>47. Simmonds P, Ansari MA. Extensive C-&gt;U transition biases in the genomes of a wide range of mamma-<lb/>lian RNA viruses; potential associations with transcriptional mutations, damage-or host-mediated editing <lb/>of viral RNA. PLoS Pathogens. 2021; 17. https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1009596 PMID: 34061905 <lb/>48. Kucab JE, Zou X, Morganella S, Joel M, Nanda AS, Nagy E, et al. A Compendium of Mutational Signa-<lb/>tures of Environmental Agents. Cell. 2019; 177(4):821-836.e16. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.cell.2019.03. <lb/>001 PMID: 30982602 <lb/>49. Thorne LG, Bouhaddou M, Reuschl AK, Zuliani-Alvarez L, Polacco B, Pelin A, et al. Evolution of <lb/>enhanced innate immune evasion by SARS-CoV-2. Nature. 2022; 602:487-495. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1038/s41586-021-04352-y PMID: 34942634 <lb/>50. Carabelli AM, Peacock TP, Thorne LG, Harvey WT, Hughes J, de Silva TI, et al. SARS-CoV-2 variant <lb/>biology: immune escape, transmission and fitness; Nat Rev Microbiol 21, 162-177 (2023). https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41579-022-00841-7 PMID: 36653446 <lb/>51. Markov PV, Ghafari M, Beer M, Lythgoe K, Simmonds P, Stilianakis NI, et al. The evolution of SARS-CoV-<lb/>2; Nat Rev Microbiol 21, 361-379 (2023). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41579-023-00878-2 PMID: 37020110 <lb/>52. Liu G, Gack MU. SARS-CoV-2 learned the &apos;Alpha&apos;bet of immune evasion; Nature Immunology. 2022; <lb/>23:351-353. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41590-022-01148-8 PMID: 35194206 <lb/>53. Chen K, Xiao F, Hu D, Ge W, Tian M, Wang W, et al. Sars-cov-2 nucleocapsid protein interacts with rig-<lb/>i and represses rig-mediated ifn-β production. Viruses. 2021; 13. <lb/>54. Catanzaro M, Fagiani F, Racchi M, Corsini E, Govoni S, Lanni C. Immune response in COVID-19: <lb/>addressing a pharmacological challenge by targeting pathways triggered by SARS-CoV-2; Sig Trans-<lb/>duct Target Ther 5, 84 (2020). https://doi.org/10.1038/s41392-020-0191-1 PMID: 32467561 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 / 26 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>55. Miorin L, Kehrer T, Sanchez-Aparicio MT, Zhang K, Cohen P, Patel RS, et al. SARS-CoV-2 Orf6 hijacks <lb/>Nup98 to block STAT nuclear import and antagonize interferon signaling; Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences, 117(45), 28344-28354. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.2016650117 PMID: <lb/>33097660 <lb/>56. Willett BJ, Grove J, MacLean OA, Wilkie C, Lorenzo GD, Furnon W, et al. SARS-CoV-2 Omicron is an <lb/>immune escape variant with an altered cell entry pathway. Nature Microbiology 2022; 7:1161-1179. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41564-022-01143-7 PMID: 35798890 <lb/>57. Jackson CB, Farzan M, Chen B, Choe H. Mechanisms of SARS-CoV-2 entry into cells. Nature Reviews <lb/>Molecular Cell Biology 2021; 23:3-20. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41580-021-00418-x PMID: 34611326 <lb/>58. Ritchie H, Mathieu E, Rode ´s-Guirao L, Appel C, Giattino C, Ortiz-Ospina E, et al. Coronavirus Pan-<lb/>demic (COVID-19). Our World in Data. 2020;. <lb/>59. Dong E, Du H, Gardner L. An interactive web-based dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time; The <lb/>Lancet Infectious Diseases Volume 20, Issue 5, May 2020, Pages 533-534 https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>S1473-3099(20)30120-1 PMID: 32087114 <lb/>60. Hale T, Angrist N, Goldszmidt R, Kira B, Petherick A, Phillips T, et al. A global panel database of pan-<lb/>demic policies (Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker). Nature Human Behaviour 2021; <lb/>5:529-538. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41562-021-01079-8 PMID: 33686204 <lb/>61. Nordstro ¨m P, Ballin M, Nordstro ¨m A. Risk of SARS-CoV-2 reinfection and COVID-19 hospitalisation in <lb/>individuals with natural and hybrid immunity: a retrospective, total population cohort study in Sweden. <lb/>The Lancet Infectious Diseases. 2022; 22:781-790. https://doi.org/10.1016/S1473-3099(22)00143-8 <lb/>PMID: 35366962 <lb/>62. Obermeyer F, Jankowiak M, Barkas N, Schaffner SF, Pyle JD, Yurkovetskiy L, et al. Analysis of 6.4 mil-<lb/>lion SARS-CoV-2 genomes identifies mutations associated with fitness. Science. 2022; 376:1327-<lb/>1332. https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abm1208 PMID: 35608456 <lb/>63. Heo MH, Kwon YD, Cheon J, Kim KB, Noh JW. Association between the Human Development Index <lb/>and Confirmed COVID-19 Cases by Country. Healthcare (Switzerland). 2022; 10. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>3390/healthcare10081417 PMID: 36011075 <lb/>64. Wu F, Zhao S, Yu B, Chen YM, Wang W, Song ZG, et al. A new coronavirus associated with human <lb/>respiratory disease in China. Nature 2020; 579:265-269. https://doi.org/10.1038/s41586-020-2008-3 <lb/>PMID: 32015508 <lb/>65. Lee DD, Seung HS. Learning the parts of objects by non-negative matrix factorization. Nature 1999; <lb/>401:788-791. https://doi.org/10.1038/44565 PMID: 10548103 <lb/>66. Islam SMA, Dı ´az-Gay M, Wu Y, Barnes M, Vangara R, Bergstrom EN, et al. Uncovering novel muta-<lb/>tional signatures by de novo extraction with SigProfilerExtractor. Cell Genomics. 2022; 2(11):100179. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.xgen.2022.100179 PMID: 36388765 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PLOS COMPUTATIONAL BIOLOGY <lb/>Mutational processes and SARS-CoV-2&apos;s evolutionary capacity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Computational Biology | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.pcbi.1011795 January 25, 2024 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 / 26 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
