<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9903023v2 [cond-mat.supr-con] 24 Mar 1999 <lb/>Anisotropic resistivity of the antiferromagnetic <lb/>insulator Bi 2 Sr 2 ErCu 2 O 8 <lb/>T Kitajima, T Takayanagi, T Takemura and I Terasaki † <lb/>Department of Applied Physics, Waseda University, Tokyo 169-8555, Japan <lb/>Abstract. The anisotropic resistivities of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 single crystals were <lb/>measured and analyzed from 4.2 to 500 K with special interest taken in the parent <lb/>antiferromagnetic insulator with x=1.0. Although the resistivity is semiconducting <lb/>along both the in-plane and out-of-plane directions, the temperature dependences are <lb/>found to be significantly different. As a result, the resistivity ratio for x=1.0 exhibits <lb/>a broad maximum near room temperature. The electric conduction in the parent <lb/>antiferromagnetic insulators is different from that in other semiconductors, and is as <lb/>unconventional as that in high-temperature superconductors. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Anisotropic transport properties in the normal state are one of the most striking features <lb/>of high-temperature superconductors (HTSC&apos;s) [1]. The metallic in-plane resistivity <lb/>(ρ ab ) accompanied by the non-metallic out-of-plane resistivity (ρ c ) enhances ρ c /ρ ab at <lb/>low temperature (T ) [2, 3], whereas ρ c /ρ ab is independent of T for conventional metals. <lb/>The enhancement of ρ c /ρ ab is often called &apos;confinement&apos; [4], and can be a key to the <lb/>elucidation of the mechanism of high-temperature superconductivity. We have studied <lb/>the anisotropic transport properties of slightly overdoped YBa 2 Cu 3 O y crystals [5, 6]. <lb/>Although their resistivities ρ c and ρ ab are both metallic, the anisotropy is difficult to <lb/>understand within the Fermi liquid theory. <lb/>The next question is that of whether ρ c /ρ ab is anomalous for a parent <lb/>antiferromagnetic (AF) insulator, whose resistivities ρ c and ρ ab are semiconducting. <lb/>To our knowledge, very little investigation has been done on ρ c /ρ ab . Thio et al. [7] <lb/>have found that ρ c /ρ ab for La 2 CuO 4 decreases with decreasing T below 200 K, which <lb/>is significantly incompatible with ρ c /ρ ab for HTSC&apos;s. Since it does not saturate near <lb/>200 K, a higher-temperature measurement is needed. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> † To whom correspondence should be addressed. E-mail address: terra@mn.waseda.ac.jp <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Characterization of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 single crystals. Note that the <lb/>actual composition ratio is represented by setting Cu = 2. <lb/>Nominal Actual Composition <lb/>Size <lb/>c-axis <lb/>x <lb/>Bi : Sr : Ca : Er : Cu <lb/>(mm 3 ) <lb/>( Å) <lb/>0 <lb/>1.9 : 1.9 : 1.2 : 0 : 2 <lb/>0.6×1×0.02 30.85 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1.6 : 1.8 : 1.2 : 0.1 : 2 1×1.2×0.02 30.90 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.6 : 1.9 : 1.0 : 0.5 : 2 <lb/>1×1×0.004 <lb/>30.32 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2.0 : 2.1 : 0 : 0.6 : 2 <lb/>1×1.2×0.004 30.33 <lb/>For studying ρ c /ρ ab over a wide temperature range, Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x R x Cu 2 O 8 (R: rare-<lb/>earth) is most suitable for the following reasons: (i) Oxygens for x=0 are chemically <lb/>stable up to 600 K in air where ρ ab remains &quot;T -linear&quot; [8]. (ii) When x reduces from 1 <lb/>to 0, the doping level varies from that of a parent AF insulator to that of a (slightly) <lb/>overdoped superconductor [9]. (iii) All of the Cu sites are equivalent, and only the <lb/>CuO 2 plane is responsible for the electric conduction. Here we report on measurements <lb/>and analyses of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 single crystals with x=0, 0.1, 0.5, and 1.0. We <lb/>have found that ρ c /ρ ab for a parent AF insulator (x=1.0) is quite unique; it increases <lb/>with T below 100 K, takes a broad maximum near 300 K, and decreases above room <lb/>temperature. This obviously indicates that a parent AF insulator exhibits a quite <lb/>different conduction mechanism from conventional semiconductors. <lb/>2. Experimental <lb/>Single crystals of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 were grown by a self-flux method [10]. Powders <lb/>of Bi 2 O 3 , SrCO 3 , CuO, CaCO 3 , and Er 2 O 3 of 99.9 % purity were mixed, well ground <lb/>in an Al 2 O 3 crucible, heated at 900 • C [1020 • C] for 10 h, and slowly cooled down to <lb/>760 • C [820 • C] by 2 • C/h for x=0 [x =0]. Since the single crystals were very thin along <lb/>the c axis, the thickness was measured with a scanning electron microscope (SEM). <lb/>The actual compositions were measured through inductively coupled plasma emission <lb/>spectroscopy. The x-ray diffraction pattern showed no trace of impurities, and the c-axis <lb/>lattice parameter for x=0 was evaluated to be 30.85 Å, which agrees with the value in <lb/>the literature [10, 11]. The measured compositions, sizes, and c-axis lattice parameters <lb/>are listed in table 1. We should note that crystals grown by a flux method are produced <lb/>with little stress, owing to the slow cooling rate near thermal equilibrium. In fact, we did <lb/>not observe any serious cracks in the SEM images of our samples. In order to examine <lb/>the influence of inhomogeneity and disorder on the resistivity, we made measurements <lb/>for more than 30 samples including ones grown from different batches. The measured <lb/>resistivities were reproducible enough to warrant the discussion in this paper. <lb/>The resistivity was measured with a dc current I in a four-probe configuration along <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>10 -4 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>ρ <lb/>ab (Ωcm) <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1-x Er x Cu 2 O 8 <lb/>x=0 <lb/>x=0.1 <lb/>x=1 <lb/>x=0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>10 6 <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>ρ <lb/>c (Ωcm) <lb/>x=0 <lb/>x=0.1 <lb/>x=1 <lb/>x=0.5 <lb/>0 100 200 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 1 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>ρ/ρ <lb/>300 K <lb/>x=1.0 <lb/>ρ ab <lb/>ρ c <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 1. (a) The in-plane resistivity ρ ab and (b) out-of-plane resistivity ρ c of single <lb/>crystals of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 . ρ ab and ρ c for x=1.0 normalized at 300 K are <lb/>plotted as functions of temperature in the inset. <lb/>the in-plane direction (I ⊥ c), and in a ring configuration along the out-of-plane direction <lb/>(I c). We used two measurement systems below and above room temperature. From <lb/>4.2 to 300 K, the samples were slowly (100 K/h) cooled in a liquid-He cryostat, where T <lb/>was monitored through a cernox resistance thermometer. Above 300 K, the samples are <lb/>slowly (50-100 K/h) heated in air in a cylinder furnace with a Pt resistance thermometer. <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>Figures 1(a) and 1(b) show ρ ab and ρ c of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 single crystals, <lb/>respectively. The magnitudes of ρ ab and ρ c increase with x, showing that the hole <lb/>concentration is reduced by the Er substitution. As is seen in the literature, ρ c is four or <lb/>five orders of magnitude lager than ρ ab for all the samples. For superconducting samples <lb/>(x=0 and 0.1), metallic ρ ab and semiconducting ρ c are observed above T c . Reflecting <lb/>the slightly overdoped nature of x=0, T c (∼84 K) for the x=0 sample is lower than T c <lb/>(∼87 K) for x=0.1. These results attest to the quality of our crystals. <lb/>Both ρ ab and ρ c for x=1.0 are semiconducting, but they exhibit different T <lb/>dependences. Above room temperature, where ρ ab decreases gradually in comparison <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>ρ <lb/>c (T)/ρ <lb/>c (450 K) <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1-x Er x Cu 2 O 8 <lb/>x=0 <lb/>x=0.1 <lb/>x=0.5 <lb/>x=1.0 <lb/>ρ <lb/>ab (T)/ρ <lb/>ab (450 K) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 -4 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 2 <lb/>x <lb/>ρ <lb/>at 450K (Ωcm) <lb/>ρ c <lb/>ρ ab <lb/>Figure 2. The anisotropic resistivity ratios ρ c /ρ ab of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 single <lb/>crystals normalized at 450 K. Inset: The magnitudes of ρ ab and ρ c at 450 K are plotted <lb/>as functions of x. Note that each symbol represents the resistivity of a different sample <lb/>measured to check the reproducibility (see text). <lb/>with ρ c , ρ c /ρ ab decreases with increasing T . On the other hand, ρ ab becomes insulating <lb/>more rapidly than ρ c , as shown in the inset of figure 1 where the resistivities are <lb/>normalized at 300 K. Thus ρ c /ρ ab decreases with decreasing T below 300 K. These <lb/>results are not understandable on the basis of conventional theories. In the framework <lb/>of a band picture, anisotropy is mainly determined by effective masses, implying that <lb/>the T dependence of ρ is independent of the direction. In the case of a hole doped in <lb/>the AF background, the situations are nearly the same. In fact, a nearly T -independent <lb/>ρ c /ρ ab has been observed for La 2 NiO 4 [12] and Bi 2 M 3 Co 2 O 9 (M=Ca, Sr and Ba) [13]. <lb/>The magnitude of ρ c /ρ ab for a parent AF insulator is much more difficult to evaluate <lb/>than that for a superconductor, in that it is an exponentially varying quantity divided <lb/>by another exponentially varying quantity. Since we are interested in the T dependence <lb/>of ρ c /ρ ab , we normalize ρ c /ρ ab at 450 K in figure 2. As for the magnitude, we show ρ ab <lb/>and ρ c in the inset of figure 2, in which each symbol corresponds to a different sample. <lb/>From the inset one can see that the magnitude of ρ c /ρ ab at 450 K is nearly independent <lb/>of x. Accordingly the normalization at 450 K will not adversely affect the discussion <lb/>below. <lb/>We would like to point out three features in figure 2. First, ρ c /ρ ab changes smoothly <lb/>with x above room temperature; It increases with decreasing T , and the T dependence is <lb/>steeper for larger x (smaller hole concentration). If one looked at ρ c /ρ ab only above room <lb/>temperature, one could not distinguish a parent AF insulator from a superconductor. <lb/>Thus we may say that the holes are confined in a parent AF insulator as well as in <lb/>HTSC. In this context the former is as unconventional as the latter. Secondly, ρ c /ρ ab <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>Hole concentration per Cu <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1-x R x Cu 2 O 8 <lb/>T max R=Er <lb/>T c R=Er <lb/>T N R=Y <lb/>T c R=Y <lb/>Fig. 3 Kitajima et al. <lb/>AF <lb/>SC <lb/>Figure 3. The phase diagram of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x R x Cu 2 O 8 (R=Er and Y). AF and <lb/>SC represent the antiferromagnetic order and the superconducting phase, respectively. <lb/>T max (the temperature at which ρ c /ρ ab takes a maximum), T N (the Néel temperature), <lb/>and T c (the superconducting transition temperature) are plotted as a function of hole <lb/>concentration. T N and T c for R=Y are taken from Refs. [15] and [17]. The hole <lb/>concentration is estimated from the room-temperature thermopower, as is proposed in <lb/>Ref. [16]. The error bars in T max represent the variation from sample to sample. <lb/>for x=1.0 and 0.5 decreases with decreasing T below 100 K, which is consistent with <lb/>ρ c /ρ ab of La 2 CuO 4 [7]. The decrease of ρ c /ρ ab as T →0 could be understood from the <lb/>three-dimensional (3D) nature of the localization [14]. Thirdly, ρ c /ρ ab for x=1.0 and <lb/>0.5 takes a maximum at a certain temperature T max , which is very close to the Néel <lb/>temperature T N . (For x=0.5, a tiny fraction of a superconducting phase causes a small <lb/>drop of resistivity near 90 K, which obscures the position of T max .) <lb/>The localized f spins of Er 3+ make it difficult to measure T N of Cu 2+ for x=1.0 and <lb/>0.5. Instead, we will compare T N of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Y x Cu 2 O 8 [15], and we plot T c , T N and <lb/>T max in the electronic phase diagram of Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x R x Cu 2 O 8 in figure 3. We estimated <lb/>the hole concentration using an empirical relation to the thermopower [16], which we <lb/>measured with the same samples for R=Er (not shown here), and used Ref. [17] for <lb/>R=Y. T max is found to lie around the AF boundary. Since no structural transitions and <lb/>no phase separations are reported for Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x R x Cu 2 O 8 [9], it would be natural to <lb/>relate T max to the AF transition. <lb/>The confinement behavior above T N favors some theories based on the two-<lb/>dimensional (2D) spin fluctuation, which exists in parent AF insulators above T N [18] <lb/>and in HTSC&apos;s above T c as well [19]. We therefore propose that holes are confined in a <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>CuO 2 plane in the presence of the 2D spin fluctuation, which occurs irrespective of doping <lb/>levels. As the 3D AF order grows below T N , the confinement becomes less effective. A <lb/>recent numerical analysis of the bilayer t − J model has also led to the assertion that <lb/>ρ c is substantially modified in the presence of the 2D spin fluctuation [20]. We further <lb/>note that a similar case is seen for a layered ferromagnet La 2−x Sr 1+x Mn 2 O 7 [21]. For <lb/>100 K &lt; T &lt; 250 K, this compound is in a 2D ferromagnetic state, and exhibits a <lb/>non-metallic ρ c together with a metallic ρ ab . Once the 3D ferromagnetic order appears <lb/>below 100 K, ρ c becomes metallic to behave in a 3D-like manner. We believe that the <lb/>out-of-plane conduction in parent AF insulators includes essentially the same physics <lb/>as for La 2−x Sr 1+x Mn 2 O 7 ; the only difference is as regards whether the material is an <lb/>antiferromagnetic insulator or a ferromagnetic metal. <lb/>4. Summary <lb/>We prepared Bi 2 Sr 2 Ca 1−x Er x Cu 2 O 8 , single crystals for x=0, 0.1, 0.5 and 1.0 and <lb/>measured the in-plane and out-of-plane resistivities (ρ ab and ρ c ) from 4.2 to 500 K. The <lb/>present study has revealed that ρ c /ρ ab for a parent antiferromagnetic insulator (x = 1.0) <lb/>strongly depends on temperature, and that the enhancement of ρ c /ρ ab with decreasing T <lb/>is observed above room temperature. In this sense, parent antiferromagnetic insulators <lb/>are as unconventional as high-temperature superconductors. Their ratios ρ c /ρ ab take <lb/>maxima at a certain temperature near the Néel temperature, and we propose that the <lb/>confinement in the CuO 2 plane is operative in the two-dimensional spin-fluctuation <lb/>regime regardless of the doping level. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors would like to thank T Itoh, T Kawata, K Takahata and Y Iguchi for <lb/>collaboration. They also wish to express their appreciation to S Kurihara and S Saito <lb/>for fruitful discussions and valuable comments. One of the authors (I T) is indebted <lb/>to S Tajima for the collaboration at a preliminary stage of this work. This work was <lb/>partially supported by Waseda University Grant for Special Research Projects (97A-565, <lb/>98A-618). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] For a recent review of the anisotropic charge dynamics, see Cooper S L and Gray K E 1994 Physical <lb/>Properties of the High Temperature Superconductors IV, edited by Ginsberg D M (Singapore: <lb/>World Scientific) p. 61 <lb/>[2] Takenaka K, Mizuhashi K, Takagi H and Uchida S 1994 Phys. Rev. B50 6534 <lb/>[3] Nakamura Y and Uchida S 1993 Phys. Rev. B47 8369 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[4] Anderson P W 1997 The Theory of Superconductivity in the High-T c Cuprates (Princeton: <lb/>Princeton University Press) <lb/>[5] Terasaki I, Sato Y, Miyamoto S, Tajima S and Tanaka S 1995 Phys. Rev. B52 16246 <lb/>[6] Terasaki I, Sato Y and Tajima S 1996 Phys. Rev. B55 15300 <lb/>[7] Thio T, Chen C Y, Freer B S, Gabbe D R, Jenssen H P, Kastner M A, Picone P J, Preyer N W <lb/>and Birgeneau R J 1990 Phys. Rev. B41 231 <lb/>[8] Martin S, Fiory A T, Fleming R M, Schneemeyer L F and Waszczak J V 1988 Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>60 2194 <lb/>[9] Quitmann C, Andrich D A, Jarchow C, Fleuster M, Beschoten B, Güntherodt G, Moshchalkov V <lb/>V, Mante G and Manzke R 1992 Phys. Rev. B46 11813 <lb/>[10] Kendziora C, Forro L, Mandrus D, Hartge J, Stephens P, Mihaly L, Reeder R, Moecher D, Rivers <lb/>M and Sutton S 1992 Phys. Rev. B45 13025 <lb/>[11] Ilyushin A S, Shi L, Leonyuk L I, Mustafa B M, Nikanorova I A, Red&apos;ko S V, Jia Y, Vetkin A G, <lb/>Zhou G, Zubov I V 1993 J. Mater. Res. 8 1791 <lb/>[12] Rao C N R, Buttrey D J, Otsuka N, Ganguly P, Harrison H R, Sandberg C J and Honig J M 1984 <lb/>J. Solid State. Chem. 51 266 <lb/>[13] Watanabe Y, Tui D C, Birminghem J T, Ong N P and Tarascon J M 1991 Phys. Rev. B43 3026 <lb/>[14] Shkolovskii B I 1977 Sov. Phys. Semicond. 11 1253 <lb/>[15] Nishida N, Okuma S, Miyatake H, Tamegai T, Iye Y, Yoshizaki R, Nishiyama K, Nagamine K, <lb/>Kadono R and Brewer J H 1990 Physica C168 23 <lb/>[16] Obertelli S D, Cooper J R, and Tallon J L 1992 Phys. Rev. B46 14928 <lb/>[17] Mandrus D, Forro L, Kendziora C and Mihaly L 1991 Phys. Rev. B44 2418 <lb/>[18] Shirane G, Endoh Y, Birgeneau R J, Kastner M A, Hidaka Y, Oda M, Suzuki M and Murakami <lb/>T 1987 Phys. Rev. Lett. 59 1613 <lb/>[19] Yamada K, Lee C H, Kurahashi K, Wada J, Wakimoto S, Ueki S, Kimura H, Endoh Y, Hosoya S, <lb/>Shirane G, Birgeneau R J, Greven M, Kastner M A and Kim Y J 1998 Phys. Rev. B57 6165 <lb/>[20] Eder R, Ohta Y and Maekawa S 1995 Phys. Rev. B51 3265 <lb/>[21] Kimura T, Tomioka Y, Kuwahara H, Asamitsu A, Tamura M and Tokura Y 1996 Science 274 <lb/>1698 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
