<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0201165v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 11 Jan 2002 <lb/>Oxygen-isotope effect on the in-plane penetration depth in underdoped <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ as revealed by muon-spin rotation <lb/>R. Khasanov (1,2) , A. Shengelaya (1) , K. Conder (3) , E. Morenzoni (2) , I. M. Savić (4) , and H. Keller (1) <lb/>(1) Physik-Institut der Universität Zürich, CH-8057 Zürich, Switzerland <lb/>(2) Paul Scherrer Institut, CH-5232 Villigen PSI, Switzerland <lb/>(3) Laboratory for Neutron Scattering, ETH Zürich and PSI Villigen, CH-5232 Villigen PSI, Switzerland <lb/>Faculty of Physics, University of Belgrade, 11001 Belgrade, Yugoslavia <lb/>The oxygen-isotope ( 16 O/ 18 O) effect (OIE) on the in-plane penetration depth λ ab (0) in under-<lb/>doped Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ was studied by muon-spin rotation. A pronounced OIE on λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) <lb/>was observed with a relative isotope shift of ∆λ −2 <lb/>ab /λ −2 <lb/>ab = −5(2)% for x = 0.3 and -9(2)% for <lb/>x = 0.4. It arises mainly from the oxygen-mass dependence of the in-plane effective mass m * <lb/>ab . <lb/>The OIE exponents of Tc and of λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) exhibit a relation that appears to be generic for cuprate <lb/>superconductors. <lb/>PACS numbers: 76.75.+i, 74.72.-h, 82.20.Tr, 71.38 <lb/></front> 

			<body>The pairing mechanism responsible for high-<lb/>temperature superconductivity remains elusive in <lb/>spite of the fact that many models have been pro-<lb/>posed since its discovery. A fundamental question is <lb/>whether lattice effects are relevant for the occurrence of <lb/>high-temperature superconductivity. In order to clarify <lb/>this point a large number of isotope-effect studies were <lb/>performed since 1987 [1]. The first oxygen-isotope effect <lb/>(OIE) studies on the transition temperature T c were <lb/>performed on optimally doped samples, showing no <lb/>significant isotope shift [2]. However, later experiments <lb/>revealed a small but finite dependence of T c on the <lb/>oxygen-isotope mass M O [3, 4, 5, 6], as well as on <lb/>the copper-isotope mass M Cu [7, 8]. Moreover, a <lb/>general trend in the dependence of the OIE exponent <lb/>α O = −d ln T c /d ln M O on the doping level was found <lb/>which appears to be generic for all cuprate supercon-<lb/>ductors [1, 5, 8, 9, 10]: In the underdoped region α O <lb/>is large, even exceeding the conventional BCS-value <lb/>α = 0.5 and becomes small in the optimally doped and <lb/>overdoped regime. <lb/>There is increasing evidence that a strong electron-<lb/>phonon coupling is present in cuprate superconductors, <lb/>which may lead to the formation of polarons (bare charge <lb/>carriers accompanied by local lattice distortions) [11, 12]. <lb/>One way to test this hypothesis is to demonstrate that <lb/>the effective mass of the supercarriers m * depends on <lb/>the mass M of the lattice atoms. This is in contrast to <lb/>conventional BCS superconductors, where only the &apos;bare&apos; <lb/>charge carriers condense into Cooper pairs, and m * is es-<lb/>sentially independent of M . For cuprate superconductors <lb/>(clean limit) the in-plane penetration depth λ ab is simply <lb/>given by λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) ∝ n s /m * <lb/>ab , where n s is the superconduct-<lb/>ing charge carrier density, and m * <lb/>ab is the in-plane effec-<lb/>tive mass of the superconducting charge carriers. This <lb/>implies that the OIE on λ ab is due to a shift in n s and/or <lb/>m * <lb/>ab : <lb/>∆λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)/λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) = ∆n s /n s − ∆m * <lb/>ab /m * <lb/>ab . <lb/>(1) <lb/>Therefore a possible mass dependence of m * <lb/>ab can be <lb/>tested by investigating the isotope effect on λ ab , provided <lb/>that the contribution of n s to the total isotope shift is <lb/>known. <lb/>Previous OIE studies of the penetration depth in <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ [13], La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 [10, 14, 15], and <lb/>Bi 1.6 Pb 0.4 Sr 2 Ca 2 Cu 3 O 10+δ [16] indeed showed a pro-<lb/>nounced oxygen-mass dependence on the supercarrier <lb/>mass. However, in all these experiments the penetration <lb/>depth was determined indirectly from the onset of magne-<lb/>tization [13, 16], from the Meissner fraction [10, 14], and <lb/>from magnetic torque measurements [15]. The muon-<lb/>spin rotation (µSR ) technique is a direct and accurate <lb/>method to determine the penetration depth λ in type II <lb/>superconductors. In this Letter, we report µSR measure-<lb/>ments of in-plane penetration depth λ ab in underdoped <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (x = 0.3 and 0.4) with two differ-<lb/>ent oxygen isotopes ( 16 O and 18 O). A large OIE on λ ab <lb/>was observed which mainly arises from the oxygen-mass <lb/>dependence of m * <lb/>ab . <lb/>Polycrystalline samples of Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (x = <lb/>0.3 and x = 0.4) were prepared by standard solid state <lb/>reaction [17]. Oxygen isotope exchange was performed <lb/>during heating the samples in O 2 gas. In order to en-<lb/>sure the same thermal history of the substituted ( 18 O) <lb/>and not substituted ( O) sample, two experiments (in <lb/>O 2 and 18 O 2 ) were always performed simultaneously. <lb/>The exchange and back exchange processes were car-<lb/>ried out at 600 o C during 25 h, and then the samples <lb/>were slowly cooled (20 o C/h) in order to oxidize them <lb/>completely. The O content in the samples, as deter-<lb/>mined from a change of the sample weight after the iso-<lb/>tope exchange, was found to be 78(2)% for both sam-<lb/>ples. The total oxygen content of the samples was deter-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>mined using high-accuracy volumetric analysis [17]. To <lb/>examine the quality of the samples low-field (1mT, field-<lb/>cooled) SQUID magnetization measurements were per-<lb/>formed (see Fig. 1). For both concentrations the T c onset <lb/>for the 16 O samples was higher than for O with nearly <lb/>the same transition width. An oxygen back exchange of <lb/>the 18 O sample (x = 0.4) resulted within error in almost <lb/>the same magnetization curve as for the O sample, <lb/>confirming that the back exchange is almost complete. <lb/>The results of the OIE on T c are summarized in Table <lb/>I. Taking into account an isotope exchange of 78%, we <lb/>found α O = 0.22(4) for x = 0.3 and α O = 0.37(5) for <lb/>x = 0.4, in agreement with previous results [9, 18]. <lb/>50 <lb/>52 <lb/>54 <lb/>56 <lb/>58 <lb/>60 <lb/>62 <lb/>64 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>36 <lb/>38 <lb/>40 <lb/>42 <lb/>44 <lb/>46 <lb/>48 <lb/>50 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>DT <lb/>c <lb/>DT <lb/>c <lb/>= -1.3(1) K <lb/>x=0.3 <lb/>16 <lb/>O <lb/>18 <lb/>O <lb/>M <lb/>DT <lb/>c <lb/>= -1.7(1) K <lb/>x=0.4 <lb/>16 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>18 <lb/>O <lb/>16 <lb/>O <lb/>M <lb/>T (K) <lb/>FIG. 1: Section near Tc of the low-field (1mT, field-cooled) <lb/>magnetization curves (normalized to the value at 10K) for <lb/>Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ (x = 0.3 and 0.4). <lb/>The µSR experiments were performed at the Paul <lb/>Scherrer Institute (PSI), Switzerland, using the πM3 µSR <lb/>facility. The samples consisted of sintered pellets ( 12 mm <lb/>in diameter, 3 mm thick) which were mounted on a <lb/>Fe 2 O 3 sample holder in order to reduce the background <lb/>from muons not stopping in the sample. The polycrys-<lb/>talline Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ samples were cooled from <lb/>far above T c in a magnetic field of 200 mT perpendic-<lb/>ular to the sample disk. Time-differential µSR spec-<lb/>troscopy was employed, from which one can deduce the <lb/>probability distribution of the local magnetic field p(B) <lb/>of the vortex state by measuring the time evolution of <lb/>the muon-spin polarization [19]. In a powder sample the <lb/>magnetic penetration depth λ can be extracted from the <lb/>muon-spin depolarization rate σ(T ) ∝ 1/λ 2 (T ), which <lb/>probes the second moment ∆B 2 1/2 of p(B) in the mixed <lb/>state [19, 20]. For highly anisotropic layered supercon-<lb/>ductors (like the cuprate superconductors) λ is mainly <lb/>determinated by the in-plane penetration depth λ ab [20]: <lb/>σ(T ) ∝ 1/λ 2 <lb/>ab (T ) ∝ n s /m * <lb/>ab . <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>O <lb/>16 <lb/>O <lb/>18 <lb/>x = 0.3 <lb/>σ (µs ) <lb/>-1 <lb/>FIG. 2: Temperature dependence of the µSR depolarization <lb/>rate σ of Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ for x = 0.3, measured in a <lb/>field 200 mT (field-cooled). <lb/>The depolarization rate σ was extracted from the <lb/>µSR time spectra using a Gaussian relaxation func-<lb/>tion R(t) = exp[−σ 2 t 2 /2]. <lb/>Figure 2 shows the <lb/>temperature dependence of the measured σ for the <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ samples with x = 0.3. Similar re-<lb/>sults were obtained for the samples with x = 0.4. It is ev-<lb/>ident that the values of σ for 18 O are systematically lower <lb/>than those for O. As expected for a type II supercon-<lb/>ductor in the mixed state, σ continuously increases below <lb/>T c with decreasing temperature [20]. The sharp increase <lb/>of σ below ≃ 10 K is due to antiferromagnetic ordering <lb/>of the Cu(2) moments [21]. Above T c a small tempera-<lb/>ture independent depolarization rate σ nm ≃ 0.15 µs −1 is <lb/>seen, arising from the nuclear magnetic moments of Cu <lb/>and Pr. Therefore, the total σ is determined by three <lb/>contributions: a superconducting (σ sc ), an antiferromag-<lb/>netic (σ af m ), and a small nuclear magnetic dipole (σ nm ) <lb/>contribution. Because σ af m is only present at low tem-<lb/>peratures, data points below 10 K were not considered in <lb/>the analysis. The superconducting contribution σ sc was <lb/>then determined by subtracting σ nm measured above T c <lb/>from σ. In Fig. 3 we show the temperature dependence <lb/>of σ sc for the Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ samples with x = 0.3 <lb/>and 0.4. It is evident that for both concentrations a re-<lb/>markable oxygen isotope shift on T c as well as on σ sc is <lb/>present. <lb/>The data in Fig. 3 were fitted to the power law <lb/>σ sc (T )/σ sc (0) = 1−(T /T c ) n [20] with σ sc (0) and n as free <lb/>parameters, and T c fixed. The values of T c were taken <lb/>from the magnetization measurements (see Table I). The <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>x = 0.3 <lb/>x = 0.4 <lb/>λ <lb/>ab (T) / <lb/>λ <lb/>ab (0) ( O) <lb/>-2 <lb/>-2 <lb/>18 <lb/>σ <lb/>sc (T) (µs ) <lb/>-1 <lb/>O <lb/>16 <lb/>18 O <lb/>18 O <lb/>O <lb/>16 <lb/>O <lb/>16 <lb/>18 O <lb/>FIG. 3: Temperature dependence of depolarization rate σsc <lb/>in Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ for x = 0.3 and 0.4 (200 mT, field-<lb/>cooled). On the right axis the normalized in-plane pene-<lb/>tration depth λ −2 <lb/>ab (T )/λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)( 18 O) is plotted for comparison <lb/>with Ref. [15]. The solid lines correspond to fits to the power <lb/>law σsc(T )/σsc(0) = 1 − (T /Tc) n . <lb/>values of σ sc (0) obtained from the fits are listed in Table <lb/>I and are in agreement with previous results [21]. The <lb/>exponent n was found to be n = 2.0(1) for x = 0.3 and <lb/>n = 1.5(1) for x = 0.4, which is typical for underdoped <lb/>YBCO [20]. Moreover, n is within error the same for <lb/>16 O and 18 O. This implies that σ sc has nearly the same <lb/>temperature dependence for the two isotopes (see Fig. 3). <lb/>In order to proof that the observed OIE on λ ab (0) are in-<lb/>trinsic, the 18 O sample with x = 0.4 was back exchanged <lb/>( 18 O → 16 O). As seen in Fig. 3, the data points of this <lb/>sample (cross symbols) indeed coincide with those of the <lb/>16 O sample. From the values of σ sc (0) listed in Table <lb/>I the relative isotope shift of the in-plane penetration <lb/>depth ∆λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)/λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) = [σ 18O <lb/>sc (0) − σ 16O <lb/>sc (0)]/σ 16O <lb/>sc (0) <lb/>was determined. Taking into account an isotope ex-<lb/>change of 78%, one finds ∆λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)/λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) = −5(2)% <lb/>and -9(2)% for x = 0.3 and 0.4, respectively (Table I). <lb/>For the OIE exponent β O = −d ln λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)/d ln M O , one <lb/>readily obtains β O = 0.38(12) for x = 0.3 and β O = <lb/>0.71(14) for x = 0.4 (Table I). This means that in un-<lb/>derdoped Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ the OIE on λ −2 <lb/>ab as well <lb/>as on T c increase with increasing Pr doping x (decreas-<lb/>TABLE <lb/>I: <lb/>Summary <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>OIE <lb/>results <lb/>for <lb/>Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ extracted from the experimental <lb/>data (see text for an explanation). <lb/>O <lb/>18 O <lb/>x Tc <lb/>σsc(0) <lb/>Tc <lb/>σsc(0) <lb/>αO <lb/>∆λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) <lb/>λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) <lb/>βO <lb/>[K] <lb/>[µs −1 ] <lb/>[K] <lb/>[µs −1 ] <lb/>[%] <lb/>0.3 60.6(1) 1.63(2) 59.3(1) 1.57(2) 0.22(4) -5(2) 0.38(12) <lb/>0.4 45.3(1) 1.01(2) 43.6(1) 0.94(2) 0.37(5) -9(2) 0.71(14) <lb/>0.4 45.1(1) a 1.01(4) a <lb/>a results for the back-exchange ( 18 O→ 16 O) sample <lb/>ing T c ). This finding is in excellent agreement with <lb/>the recent magnetic torque measurements on underdoped <lb/>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 [15]. <lb/>According to Eq. (1) the observed ∆λ −2 <lb/>ab (0)/λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) is <lb/>due to a shift of n s and/or m * <lb/>ab . For La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 <lb/>several independent experiments [10, 14, 15] have shown <lb/>that the change of n s during the exchange proce-<lb/>dure is negligibly small. <lb/>In the present work we <lb/>provide further evidence: (i) The fully oxygenated <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ samples (δ ≃ 0) were all prepared <lb/>under identical conditions, either in a 16 O 2 or 18 O 2 at-<lb/>mosphere [17], and the Pr content x did not change. <lb/>It is very unlikely that n s changes significantly upon <lb/>18 O substitution, and after the back-exchange ( 18 O→ <lb/>16 O) the same results are obtained (see Figs. 1, 3 and <lb/>Table I). (ii) According to a model [22] that describes <lb/>the suppression of T c in Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ , the num-<lb/>ber of supercarriers decreases linearly with increasing <lb/>x in the range of 0.05 &lt; x &lt; 0.5, and consequently <lb/>∆n s /n s = −∆x/x. Moreover, for 0.1 &lt; x &lt; 0.5 the <lb/>transition temperature T c decreases linearly with x, with <lb/>∆T c /∆x ≃ −150 K/Pr atom [9]. Combining this two <lb/>relations one obtains: ∆T c ≃ −150 • x • ∆n s /n s . As-<lb/>suming that the observed OIE on λ −2 <lb/>ab is only due to a <lb/>change of n s (∆m * <lb/>ab /m * <lb/>ab ≃ 0), one can estimate the cor-<lb/>responding shift of T c . For x = 0.3 and x = 0.4 one finds <lb/>∆T c ≃ −1.8(4) K and −4.2(6) K, respectively. The ex-<lb/>perimental values, however, are much lower (see Fig. 1): <lb/>∆T c = −1.3(1) K (x = 0.3) and ∆T c = −1.7(1) K <lb/>(x = 0.4). We thus conclude that any change in n s dur-<lb/>ing the exchange procedure must be small, and that the <lb/>change of λ ab is mainly due to the OIE on the in-plane <lb/>effective mass m * <lb/>ab with ∆m * <lb/>ab /m * <lb/>ab ≃ 5(2) % and 9(2) % <lb/>for x = 0.3 and x = 0.4, respectively. This implies that <lb/>the effective supercarrier mass m * <lb/>ab in this cuprate su-<lb/>perconductor depends on the oxygen mass of the lattice <lb/>atoms, which is not expected for a conventional phonon-<lb/>mediated BSC superconductor. <lb/>In Fig. 4 the exponent β O versus the exponent α O for <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ is plotted. For comparison we <lb/>also included the recent magnetic torque results of un-<lb/>derdoped La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 [15]. It is evident that these <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>exponents are linearly correlated: β O = A • α O + B. <lb/>A best fit yields A = 1.8(4) and B = −0.01(12), so <lb/>that β O ≃ A • α O . This empirical relation appears to <lb/>be generic for cuprate superconductors. Quantitatively <lb/>one can understand this behavior in terms of an empiri-<lb/>cal relation between T c and the µSR depolarization rate <lb/>σ sc (0) [23, 24]. It was shown [24] that for most fami-<lb/>lies of cuprate superconductors the simple parabolic re-<lb/>lation T c = 2σ(1 − σ/2) describes the experimental data <lb/>rather well (here T c = T c /T m <lb/>c , σ = σ sc (0)/σ m <lb/>sc (0), and <lb/>T m <lb/>c and σ m <lb/>sc (0) are the transition temperature and de-<lb/>polarization rate of the optimally doped system). Using <lb/>this parabolic Ansatz, one readily obtains the linear re-<lb/>lation between β O and α O : β O /α O = 1 + 1/2 [(1 − (1 − <lb/>T c ) 1/2 )/(1 − T c ) 1/2 ]. In the heavily underdoped regime <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>α O <lb/>β <lb/>O <lb/>Y 1-x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7 (µSR) <lb/>La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 (torque) <lb/>FIG. 4: Plot of the OIE exponents βO versus αO for <lb/>Y1−xPrxBa2Cu3O 7−δ (x = 0.3 and 0.4) and La2−xSrxCuO4 <lb/>(x = 0.080 and 0.086) from [15]. The dashed line represents <lb/>a best fit to the empirical relation βO = A • αO + B. <lb/>(T c → 0) β O /α O → 1. For the underdoped samples <lb/>shown in Fig. 4 the reduced critical temperature T c is <lb/>in the range 0.5 to 0.7, yielding β O /α O = 1.2 − 1.4, in <lb/>agreement with A = 1.8(4) obtained from the experi-<lb/>mental data. Very recently, it was pointed out [25] that <lb/>the unusual doping dependence of the OIE on T c and on <lb/>λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) naturally follows from the doping driven 3D-2D <lb/>crossover and the 2D quantum superconductor to insu-<lb/>lator transition in the underdoped limit. It is predicted <lb/>that in the underdoped regime β O /α O → 1, which is <lb/>consistent with the parabolic Ansatz. <lb/>In summary, we performed µSR measurements of <lb/>the in-plane penetration depth λ ab in underdoped <lb/>Y 1−x Pr x Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (x = 0.3, 0.4) for samples with two <lb/>different oxygen isotopes ( 16 O and 18 O). A pronounced <lb/>OIE on both the transition temperature T c and λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) <lb/>was observed, which increases with decreasing T c . The <lb/>isotope shift on λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) is attributed to a shift in the in-<lb/>plane effective mass m * <lb/>ab . For x = 0.3 and 0.4 we find <lb/>∆m * <lb/>ab /m * <lb/>ab = −5(2)% and -9(2)%, respectively. Further-<lb/>more, an empirical relation between the OIE exponents <lb/>β O and α O was found that appears to be generic for vari-<lb/>ous classes of cuprate superconductors. The OIE on m * <lb/>ab <lb/>implies that the superconducting carriers have polaronic <lb/>character, and that lattice effects play an essential role in <lb/>the occurrence of high-temperature superconductivity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgment">We are grateful to G.M. Zhao, T. Schneider, and <lb/>K.A. Müller for many fruitful discussions and to A. Am-<lb/>ato, U. Zimmermann, and D. Herlach from PSI for tech-<lb/>nical support during the µSR experiments. This work <lb/>was partly supported by the Swiss National Science Foun-<lb/>dation.</div> <lb/>

			<listBibl>[1] For a review, see J.P. Franck, in Physical Properties High <lb/>Temperature Superconductors IV, edited by D.M Gins-<lb/>berg (World Scientific, Singapore, 1994), pp. 189-293. <lb/>[2] B. Batlogg et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 58, 2333 (1987). <lb/>[3] B. Batlogg et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 59, 912 (1987). <lb/>[4] M. Cardona et al., Solid State Commun. 67, 789 (1988). <lb/>[5] M.K. Crawford at al., Phys. Rev. B 41, 282 (1990). <lb/>[6] D. Zech et al., Nature (London) 371, 681 (1994). <lb/>[7] J.P. Franck, S. Harker, and J.H. Brewer, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>71, 283 (1993). <lb/>[8] G.M. Zhao et al., Phys. Rev. B 54, 14956 (1996). <lb/>[9] J.P. Franck, J. Jung, and M. A.-K. Mohamed, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 44, 5318 (1991). <lb/>[10] G.M. Zhao et al., J. Phys.: Condens Matter 10, 9055 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[11] A.S. Alexandrov and N.F. Mott, Int. J. Mod. Phys. 8, <lb/>2075 (1994). <lb/>[12] K.A. Müller, Physica C 341-348, 11 (2000). <lb/>[13] G.M. Zhao and D.E. Morris, Phys. Rev. 51, 16487 <lb/>(1995). <lb/>[14] G.M. Zhao et al., Nature (London) 385, 236 (1997). <lb/>[15] J. Hofer et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, 4192 (2000). <lb/>[16] G.M. Zhao et al., Phys. Rev. B 63, 220506-1 (2001). <lb/>[17] K. Conder, Mater. Sci. Eng. R32, 41-102 (2001). <lb/>[18] G.M. Zhao et al., Phys. Rev. B 54, 14982 (1996). <lb/>[19] S.L. Lee, in Muon Science, ed. by S.L. Lee, S.H. Kilcoyne, <lb/>and R. Cywinski, IOP Publishing, Bristol and Philadel-<lb/>phia, pp. 149-171 (1999), and references therein. <lb/>[20] P. Zimmerman et al., Phys. Rev. B 52, 541 (1995). <lb/>[21] C.L. Seaman et al., Phys. Rev. B 42, 6801 (1990). <lb/>[22] A. Liechtenstien and I. Mazin, Phys. Rev. Lett. 74, 1000 <lb/>(1995). <lb/>[23] Y. Uemura et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 62, 2317 (1989). <lb/>[24] T. Schneider and H. Keller, Phys. Rev. Lett. 69, 3374 <lb/>(1992). <lb/>[25] T. Schneider and H. Keller, Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, 4899 <lb/>(2001) . </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
