<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0112448v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 25 Dec 2001 <lb/>Quasiparticle Excitation in the Superconducting Pyrochlore <lb/>Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 Probed by Muon Spin Rotation <lb/>Ryosuke Kadono * , Wataru Higemoto, Akihiro Koda, Yu Kawasaki 1 , Masashi <lb/>Hanawa 2 , and Zenji Hiroi 2 <lb/>Institute of Materials Structure Science, High Energy Accelerator Research Organization (KEK), <lb/>Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-0801 <lb/>Graduate School of Engineering Science, Osaka University, Toyonaka, Osaka 560-8531 <lb/>2 Institute for Solid State Physics, University of Tokyo, Kashiwa, Chiba 277-8581 <lb/>(Received September 12, 2001) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The quasiparticle excitations in the mixed state of Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 have been <lb/>studied by means of muon spin rotation/relaxation (µSR). The tempera-<lb/>ture dependence of the magnetic penetration depth (λ) is consistent with <lb/>a nearly isotropic superconducting order parameter, although a slight dis-<lb/>crepancy which is dependent on the details in the analysis may be present. <lb/>This is also supported by the relatively weak field dependence of λ. <lb/> * Also at School of Mathematical and Physical Science, The Graduate University for Advanced <lb/>Studies <lb/></front>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>A class of metal oxides isostructural to mineral pyrochlore has been attracting consid-<lb/>erable attention because they exhibit a wide variety of interesting physical properties. [1] <lb/>The pyrochlore has a general formula of A 2 B 2 O 7 , consisting of BO 6 octahedra and eightfold <lb/>coordinated A cations, where A and B are transition metals and/or rare-earth elements. In <lb/>particular, the B sublattice can be viewed as a three-dimensional network of corner-sharing <lb/>tetrahedra, providing a testing ground for studying the role of geometrical frustration in sys-<lb/>tems which have local spins at B sites with antiferromagnetic (AFM) correlation. [2] Such <lb/>systems are known to remain frustrated even when the exchange interaction is ferromagnetic <lb/>(FM), provided that the spin correlation has local Ising anisotropy. [3] Recent studies have <lb/>revealed a rich variety of phenomena seemingly related to the geometrical frustration, such <lb/>as the occurrence of a spin-glass (SG) phase in R 2 Mo 2 O 7 with R=Y, Tb and Dy [4,5], the <lb/>unusual behavior of ordinary and anomalous Hall coefficients in the same compound with <lb/>R=Nd, Sm and Gd [6,7], and the &quot;spin-ice&quot; phase in R Ti 2 O 7 with R=Dy and Ho. [3,8] <lb/>Although metallic pyrochlores comprise a minority subgroup of the pyrochlore family, <lb/>they consist of distinct members such as Tl 2 Mn 2 O 7 , which exhibits colossal magnetoresis-<lb/>tance. [9,10] Moreover, the recently revealed superconductivity in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 , a 5d transition <lb/>metal pyrochlore [11,12], demonstrates that the pyrochlores provide a fertile field for elec-<lb/>tronic correlation adjacent to the perovskite compounds. In this context, it is noteworthy <lb/>that LiV 2 O 4 , a cubic spinel compound in which the V sublattice is isostructural to the B <lb/>sublattice in pyrochlore, behaves similarly to a heavy fermion metal. [13] <lb/>It is reported that Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 falls into the bulk superconducting state below T c ≃ 1 ∼ <lb/>2 K, as confirmed by a large jump of specific heat ∆C c as well as large diamagnetism <lb/>due to the Meissner effect associated with the occurrence of zero resistivity. [11] The dc <lb/>magnetization curve indicates that the superconductivity is of type II with the upper critical <lb/>field close to 0.29 T at 0 K. [14] The ratio ∆C c /γT c (with γ being the Sommerfeld constant) <lb/>is reported to be 1.15, which is smaller than the predicted value of 1.43 for isotropic BCS <lb/>superconductors. Unfortunately, these measurements were performed only above 0.4 K and <lb/>are thus inconclusive in determining the detailed characteristics of superconductivity in <lb/>

			Cd Re 2 O 7 . In this Letter, we report on the quasiparticle excitations in the mixed state of <lb/>Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 studied by muon spin rotation/relaxation (µSR). The magnetic penetration depth <lb/>λ, which reflects the population of normal electrons (&quot;quasiparticles&quot;) in the superconductive <lb/>state, is determined microscopically by measuring the muon spin relaxation due to the <lb/>spatial inhomogeneity of magnetic induction in the flux line lattice (FLL). We show that <lb/>the temperature dependence of λ is more or less consistent with the prediction based on the <lb/>BCS superconductors with an isotropic gap, although a slight discrepancy is suggested by <lb/>the detailed analysis. <lb/>The µSR experiments on both single-crystal and polycrystalline Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 were per-<lb/>formed on the M15 beamline at the TRIUMF muon facility which provides a beam of nearly <lb/>100% spin-polarized positive muons of momentum 28.6 MeV/c. The specimen was mounted <lb/>on the coldfinger of a He-4 He dilution refrigerator and cooled from a temperature above <lb/>T c after setting the magnetic field at every field point (i.e., field-cooling) to eliminate the <lb/>effect of flux pinning. The field and temperature scan data were obtained at T = 0.2 K and <lb/>at H = 0.1 T, respectively. Muons were implanted into the specimen (measuring about 10 <lb/>mm×10 mm and 1 mm thick) after being passed through a beam collimator. The initial <lb/>muon spin polarization was perpendicular to the magnetic field H and thus to the FLL in <lb/>the superconducting state. <lb/>Since the muons stop randomly along the length scale of the FLL, the muon spin pre-<lb/>cession signalP (t) provides a random sampling of the internal field distribution B(r), <lb/>P (t) ≡ P x (t) + iP y (t) = <lb/>∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/>n(B) exp(iγ µ Bt)dB, <lb/>(0.1) <lb/>n(B) = <lb/>dr <lb/>dB <lb/>, <lb/>(0.2) <lb/>where γ µ is the muon gyromagnetic ratio (=2π×135.53 MHz/T), and n(B) is the spectral <lb/>density for muon precession determined by the local field distribution. These equations indi-<lb/>cate that the real amplitude of the Fourier-transformed muon precession signal corresponds <lb/>to the local field distribution n(B). The local field distribution can be approximated as the <lb/>sum of magnetic induction from isolated vortices in the London model to yield <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>B(r) = B 0 <lb/>K <lb/>e −iK•r e −K 2 ξ 2 <lb/>v <lb/>1 + K 2 λ 2 + O(K 2 <lb/>x , K 2 <lb/>y ) <lb/>, <lb/>(0.3) <lb/>where K is a translation of the vortex reciprocal lattice, B 0 (≃ H) is the average internal <lb/>field, λ is the London penetration depth, and ξ v is the cutoff parameter. The term O(K 2 <lb/>x , K 2 <lb/>y ) <lb/>denotes the nonlocal effect in which the electromagnetic response kernel Q(K) generating <lb/>the supercurrent around the vortex depends on K. While this term is eliminated in the <lb/>conventional BCS superconductors with isotropic s-wave pairing, it becomes important for <lb/>the moe complex order parameters such as anisotropic s-wave or d-wave (e.g., d x −y 2 ). The <lb/>London penetration depth in the FLL state is related to the second moment ∆B 2 = <lb/>(B(r) − B 0 ) 2 of the field distribution reflected in the µSR line shape (where <lb/>means the <lb/>spatial average). In polycrystalline samples, a Gaussian distribution of local fields is a good <lb/>approximation, whereP <lb/>(t) ≃ exp(−σ 2 t 2 /2) exp(iγ µ Ht), <lb/>(0.4) <lb/>σ = γ µ ∆B 2 . <lb/>(0.5) <lb/>For the case of ideal triangular FLL with isotropic effective carrier mass m * and a cutoff <lb/>K ≈ 1.4/ξ v provided by the numerical solution of the Ginsburg-Landau theory, the London <lb/>penetration depth λ (with O(K 2 <lb/>x , K 2 <lb/>y ) = 0) can be deduced from σ using the following <lb/>relation [15-17], <lb/>σ [µs −1 ] = 4.83 × 10 4 (1 − h)λ −2 [nm], <lb/>(0.6) <lb/>where h = H/H c2 . While the above form is valid for h &lt; 0.25 or h &gt; 0.7, a more useful <lb/>approximation valid for an arbitrary field is [17] <lb/>σ [µs −1 ] = 4.83 × 10 4 (1 − h)[1 + 3.9(1 − h) 2 ] 1/2 λ −2 [nm]. <lb/>(0.7) <lb/>In both cases, λ is related to the superconducting carrier density n s as <lb/>λ 2 = <lb/>m * c 2 <lb/>4πn s e 2 , <lb/>(0.8) <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>indicating that λ is enhanced upon the reduction of n s due to the quasiparticle excitations. <lb/>For simplicity, we adopt eq. (0.6) for the following analysis. <lb/>In a preliminary analysis, we found that the spin relaxation rate due to the FLL formation <lb/>is less than 0.1 µs −1 which is typically of the same order of magnitude as that due to <lb/>static random local fields from nuclear magnetic moments. This means that the additional <lb/>relaxation due to 111,113 Cd and 185,187 Re nuclear moments must be considered for the proper <lb/>estimation of λ in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 . To this end, the following equation was used in the actual <lb/>fitting analysis of the time spectra, <lb/>P (t) = exp[−(σ 0 t) ν + σ 2 t 2 /2)] exp(iγ µ Ht), <lb/>(0.9) <lb/>where σ 0 is the relaxation rate due to the nuclear moments and ν is the power of relaxation. <lb/>The parameters σ 0 and ν were evaluated by fitting the time spectra above T c with σ set to <lb/>zero, yielding σ 0 ≃ 0.057(1) µs −1 and ν ≃ 1.0 in the polycrystalline specimen at H = 0.1 T. <lb/>Then, σ due to the formation of FLL below T c was deduced by analyzing data with σ 0 and <lb/>ν being fixed to the above values. A similar analysis was performed for the data obtained <lb/>for the single crystals. <lb/>Figure 1(a) shows the temperature dependence of σ in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 at H = 0.1 T. Upon the <lb/>onset of FLL formation, σ exhibits a gradual increase with decreasing temperature just below <lb/>T c (0.1 T) ∼ 0.7 K at this field. According to the empirical two-fluid model approximately <lb/>valid for conventional BCS superconductors, we have <lb/>λ(t) = λ(0) <lb/>1 <lb/>√ <lb/>1 − t 4 , <lb/>(0.10) <lb/>which leads to <lb/>σ(t) = σ(0)(1 − t 4 ), <lb/>(0.11) <lb/>where t ≡ T /T c (0.1 T). The fitting analysis by the same formula with an arbitrary power, <lb/>σ(t) = σ(0)(1 − t β ), <lb/>(0.12) <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>with T c as a free parameter yields β = 2.8(5) and T c = 0.65(3) K. We also found that <lb/>T c = 0.62(1) K when β = 4 is assumed, which is slightly lower than the value T c ≃ 0.7 K <lb/>estimated from the specific heat measurement for this field. Although the difference is not <lb/>obvious between these cases (solid curve for β = 2.8 and the dashed curve for β = 4) in <lb/>Fig. 1(a), we note that the reduced χ 2 for the former is almost two times smaller (better) than <lb/>the latter. Taking H c2 = 0.29 T, the penetration depth extrapolated to T = 0 (λ(0, 0.1 T)) <lb/>is 700(8) nm, leading to the Ginsburg-Landau parameter κ ≃ 21 with ξ ≃ 34 nm estimated <lb/>from H c2 (0). Thus, it is concluded that Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 is a typical type II superconductor with <lb/>large λ, which is consistent with the results of magnetization measurement. [11] <lb/>The finding that β ≃ 2.8 may indicate that the deviation ∆λ = λ(t)−λ(0) ∝ T β exhibits <lb/>a tendency predicted for the case of line nodes (d-wave pairing) with some disorder (i.e., <lb/>dirty limit), where ∆λ ∝ T 2 . [18] Such a temperature dependence has actually been observed <lb/>in high-T c (YBCO) cuprates. [19,20] Compared with the case of isotropic gap ∆k = ∆ 0 , the <lb/>quasiparticle excitations are enhanced along nodes (|∆k| = 0) to reduce average n s , leading <lb/>to the enhancement of λ. However, the result of the fitting analysis also suggests that the <lb/>discrepancy may be attributed to experimental uncertainty including the precise value of <lb/>T c . Thus, we are led to conclude that the order parameter in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 is mostly isotropic <lb/>with a possibility of residual weak anisotropy as suggested by the slightly reduced value of <lb/>β. <lb/>As shown in Fig. 2(a), σ decreases with increasing external field, where the general <lb/>field dependence is determined by the increasing contribution of normal vortex cores and <lb/>the stronger overlap of field distribution around the cores which are described by the term <lb/>(1−h) in eq.(0.6). The fitting analysis by eq.(0.6) with H c2 and λ(H = 0) as free parameters <lb/>yields H c 2 = 0.37(5) T and λ(H = 0) = 796(12) nm at 0.2 K. Since the deduced value of H c2 <lb/>is consistent with that obtained from the magnetization measurement (≃ 0.29 T), we can <lb/>conclude that the observed field dependence of λ is mostly due to the vortex core/overlap <lb/>effect, except for the fields below ∼0.06 T where a slightly steeper reduction of σ is suggested. <lb/>The penetration depth deduced for each field using eq.(0.6) with H c2 = 0.37 T is plotted in <lb/>Fig. 2(b). In order to evaluate the relative strength of the pair-breaking effect, it is useful <lb/>to introduce a dimensionless parameter η to describe the field dependence of λ with the <lb/>following simple linear relation, <lb/>λ = λ(0.2K, h)[1 + ηh], <lb/>(0.13) <lb/>where h ≡ H/H c2 (0.2K) with H c2 (0.2K) = 0.37 T. From the analysis of data in Fig. 2(b) by <lb/>eq. (0.13), we find that η = 0.38(14) with λ(0.2K, 0) = 741(5) nm for 0 ≤ H ≤ 0.06 T. <lb/>In general, the field dependence of λ is enhanced by two different mechanisms, i.e., the <lb/>nonlinear effect in the semiclassical Doppler shift of the quasiparticle energy levels due to <lb/>the supercurrent around the vortex cores, and the nonlocal effect which further modifies <lb/>the quasiparticle excitation spectrum in the momentum space. In particular, the nonlocal <lb/>effect is important in the system with line nodes because the coherence length is inversely <lb/>proportional to the order parameter, such that ξ 0 (k) =hv F /π∆k. The divergence of ξ 0 along <lb/>the nodal directions |∆k| = 0 means that the response of quasiparticles near the nodes is <lb/>highly nonlocal. <lb/>It is predicted that η ≪ 1 for the isotropic s-wave pairing because the finite gap prevents <lb/>the shifted levels of quasiparticle excitations from being occupied at low temperatures. This <lb/>is supported, for example, by the recent observation in CeRu , in which η ≃ 0 over the <lb/>field region 0 ≤ h ≤ 0.5 where the system behaves more or less as a conventional BCS <lb/>superconductor with isotropic s-wave pairing. [21] On the other hand, stronger field depen-<lb/>dence is predicted for the case of d-wave or anisotropic s-wave pairing due to the excess <lb/>population of quasiparticles in the region where |∆k| is small or zero. Typical examples <lb/>for the d-wave pairing are those of high-T c cuprates in which η is reported to be 5∼6.6 for <lb/>YBCO. [22] Meanwhile, in the case of an s-wave superconductor YNi 2 B 2 C in which strong <lb/>anisotropy for ∆k is suggested experimentally [23], η ≃ 1 is reported from a µSR study. [24] <lb/>The comparison of these earlier results with our result suggests that the anisotropy of the <lb/>order parameter in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 is considerably smaller than YNi 2 B 2 C. <lb/>Finally, we comment that the recent observation of a clear coherence peak below T c in <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>the 187 Re NQR measurement [25] does not necessarily indicate the absence of anisotropy <lb/>in the order parameter. In the case of the anisotropic energy gap, the magnitude of the <lb/>coherence peak depends on the mean free path l. The coherence peak is enhanced in a <lb/>certain condition of l where quasiparticles probe only a limited region of the Fermi surface. <lb/>Thus, while the actual value of l is difficult to estimate because of the semimetallic character <lb/>of this compound, the NQR result does not completely rule out the presence of anisotropy <lb/>in general. <lb/>In summary, we have investigated the quasiparticle excitations in the mixed state of <lb/>Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 by µSR. The temperature and field dependence of the London penetration depth <lb/>indicates that the basic feature is consistent with the isotropic order parameter for BCS <lb/>s-wave pairing, although there remains a certain subtlety suggested by the small deviation <lb/>from the theoretical prediction which may be better understood by considering a weak <lb/>anisotropy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgment">We would like to thank the staff of TRIUMF for their technical support during the <lb/>experiment. This work was partially supported by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research <lb/>on Priority Areas and a Grant-in-Aid for Creative Scientific Research from the Ministry of <lb/>Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology of Japan. <lb/></div>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] M. A. Subramanian, G. Aravamudan and G. V. Subba Rao: Prog. Solid St. Chem. <lb/>(1983) 55 . <lb/>[2] A. P. Ramirez: Annu. Rev. Mater. Sci. 24 (1994) 453. <lb/>[3] M. J. Harris, S. T. Bramwell, D. F. McMorrow, T. Zeiske and K. W. Godfrey: Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 79 (1997) 2554. <lb/>[4] S. R. Dunsiger, R. F. Kiefl, K. H. Chow, B. D. Gaulin, M. J. P. Gingras, J. E. Greedan, <lb/>A. Keren, K. Kojima, G. M. Luke, W. A. MacFarlane, N. P. Raju, J. E. Sonier, Y. J. <lb/>Uemura and W. D. Wu: Phys. Rev. B 54 (1996) 9019. <lb/>[5] J. S. Gardner, B. D. Gaulin, S. H. Lee, C. Broholm, N. P. Raju and J. E. Greedan: <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. (1999) 211. <lb/>[6] Y. Taguchi and Y. Tokura: Phys. Rev. B 60 (1999) 10280. <lb/>[7] T. Katsufuji, H. Y. Hwang and S.-W. Cheong: Phys. Rev. Lett. 84 (2000) 1998. <lb/>[8] A. P. Ramirez, A. Hayashi, R. J. Cava, R. Siddharthan and B. S. Shastry: Nature <lb/>(1999) 333. <lb/>[9] Y. Shimakawa, Y. Kubo and T. Manako: Nature (1996) 53. <lb/>[10] Y. Shimakawa, Y. Kubo, T. Manako, Y. V. Sushko, D. N. Argyriou and J. D. Jorgensen: <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 55 (1999) 6399. <lb/>[11] M. Hanawa, Y. Muraoka, T. Tayama, T. Sakakibara, J. Yamaura and Z. Hiroi: Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 87 (2001) 187001. <lb/>[12] R. Jin, J. He, S. McCall, C. S. Alexander, F. Drymiotis and D. Mandrus: Phys. Rev. B <lb/>64 (2001) 180503. <lb/>[13] S. Kondo, D. C. Johnston, C. A. Swenson, F. Borsa, A. V. Mahajan, L. L. Miller, T. <lb/>Gu, A. I. Goldman, M. B. Maple, D. A. Gajewski, E. J. Freeman, N. R. Dilley, R. P. <lb/>Dickey, J. Merrin, K. Kojima, G. M. Luke, Y. J. Uemura, O. Chmaissem and J. D. <lb/>Jorgensen: Phys. Rev. Lett.78 (1997) 3729. <lb/>[14] Z. Hiroi and M. Hanawa: to be published in J. Phys. Chem. Solid. <lb/>[15] P. Pincus, A.C. Gossard, V. Jaccarino and J.H. Wernick: Phys. Rev. Lett. 13 (1964) <lb/>21. <lb/>[16] G. Aeppli, R. J. Cava, E. J. Ansaldo, J. H. Brewer, S. R. Kreitzman, G. M. Luke, D. R. <lb/>Noakes and R. F. Kiefl: Phys. Rev. B 35 (1987) 7129. <lb/>[17] E. H. Brandt: Phys. Rev. B 37 (1988) 2349. <lb/>[18] P. J. Hirschfeld and N. Goldenfeld: Phys. Rev. B 48 (1993) 4219. <lb/>[19] D. A. Bonn, S. Kamal, K. Zhang, R. Liang, D. J. Baar, E. Klein and W. N. Hardy: <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 50 (1994) 4051. <lb/>[20] J. E. Sonier, J. H. Brewer, R. F. Kiefl, D. A. Bonn, S. R. Dunsiger, W. N. Hardy, R. <lb/>Liang, W. A. MacFarlane, R. I. Miller and T. M. Riseman: Phys. Rev. Lett. (1997) <lb/>2875. <lb/>[21] R. Kadono, W. Higemoto, A. Koda, K. Ohishi, T. Yokoo, J. Akimitsu, M. Hedo, Y. <lb/>Inada, Y. Onuki, E. Yamamoto and Y. Haga: Phys. Rev. B (2001) 224520. <lb/>[22] J. E. Sonier, R. F. Kiefl, J. H. Brewer, D. A. Bonn, S. R. Dunsiger, W. N. Hardy, R. <lb/>Liang, W. A. MacFarlane, T. M. Riseman, D. R. Noakes and C. E. Stronach: Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 55 (1997) 11789. <lb/>[23] T. Yokoya, T. Kiss, T. Watanabe, S. Shin, M. Nohara, H. Takagi and T. Oguchi: Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 85 (2000) 4952. <lb/>[24] K. Ohishi, K. Kakuta, J. Akimitsu, W. Higemoto, R. Kadono, J. E. Sonier, A. N. Price, <lb/>R. I. Miller, R. F. Kiefl, M. Nohara, H. Suzuki and H. Takagi: submitted to Phys. Rev. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>B. <lb/>[25] O. Vyaselev, K. Kobayashi, K. Arai, J. Yamazaki, K. Kodama, M. Takigawa, M. Hanawa <lb/>and Z. Hiroi: to be published in J. Phys. Chem. Solid. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURES <lb/>FIG. 1. Temperature dependence of a) the muon spin relaxation rate σ due to flux line lattice <lb/>and b) the magnetic penetration depth λ, where solid circles are the data from the polycrystalline <lb/>specimen and open triangles are those from single crystals. Solid curves are results of fitting by a <lb/>relation σ ∝ 1/λ ∝ 1 − (T /T c ) β with β and T c being free parameters. Dashed curves are obtained <lb/>when β = 4 with T c as a free parameter. <lb/>FIG. 2. Magnetic field dependence of a) the muon spin relaxation rate σ due to flux line <lb/>lattice and b) the magnetic penetration depth λ. The solid line in a) is a result of fitting by <lb/>eq.(0.6) with H c2 being a free parameter. Dashed lines are obtained by fitting data with a relation <lb/>λ ∝ 1 + η(H/H c2 ) only for 0 ≤ H ≤ 0.06 T. <lb/></body>

			<page>12 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
