<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0308506v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 25 Aug 2003 <lb/> Typeset with jpsj2.cls &lt;ver.1.2&gt; <lb/>Letter <lb/>Unconventional Superconductivity and Nearly Ferromagnetic Spin Fluctuations in <lb/>Na x CoO 2 • yH 2 O <lb/>K. Ishida 1 * , Y. Ihara Y. Maeno 1 C. Michioka M. Kato 2 K. Yoshimura 2 K. Takada T. Sasaki H. <lb/>Sakurai and E. Takayama-Muromachi <lb/>1 Department of Physics, Graduate School of Science, Kyoto University, Kyoto 606-8502, Japan, <lb/>Department of Chemistry, Graduate School of Science, Kyoto University, Kyoto 606-8502, Japan <lb/>Advanced Materials Laboratory, National Institute for Materials Science, 1-1 Namiki, Tsukuba, Ibaraki, 305-0044, Japan <lb/>4 Superconducting Materials Center, National Institute for Materials Science, 1-1 Namiki, Tsukuba, Ibaraki 305-0044, Japan. <lb/>Co NQR studies were performed in recently discovered superconductor NaxCoO2•yH2O to <lb/>investigate physical properties in the superconducting (SC) and normal states. Two samples <lb/>from the same NaxCoO2 were examined, SC bilayer-hydrate sample with Tc ∼ 4.7 K and <lb/>non-SC monolayer-hydrate sample. From the measurement of nuclear-spin lattice relaxation <lb/>rate 1/T1 in the SC sample, it was found that the coherence peak is absent just below Tc and <lb/>that 1/T1 is proportional to temperature far below Tc. These results, which are in qualitatively <lb/>agreement with the previous result by Fujimoto et al., suggest strongly that unconventional <lb/>superconductivity is realized in this compound. In the normal state, 1/T1T of the SC sample <lb/>shows gradual increase below 100K down to Tc, whereas 1/T1T of the non-SC sample shows the <lb/>Korringa behavior in this temperature range. From the comparison between 1/T1T and χ bulk in <lb/>the SC sample, the increase of 1/T1T is attributed to nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations. These <lb/>remarkable findings suggest that the SC sample possesses nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations, <lb/>which are possibly related with the unconventional superconductivity in this compound. The <lb/>implication of this finding is discussed. <lb/>KEYWORDS: superconductivity, hydrous sodium cobalt oxide, NQR, spin fluctuations <lb/></front>

			<body>Superconductivity in Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O (x ∼ 0.35, y ∼ <lb/>1.3) with the transition temperature T c ∼ 5 K was dis-<lb/>covered quite recently by Takada et al. 1) Although T c is <lb/>by one-order of magnitude smaller than that in cuprate <lb/>superconductors, much attention have been paid for its <lb/>unique crystal structure of the 2-dimensional (2-D) layer <lb/>where superconductivity occurs. The CoO forms a 2-D <lb/>hexagonal layered structure, which is in contrast with <lb/>the tetragonal structure of cuprates. Due to the vacancy <lb/>of the Na atom, 0.65 holes are doped into the band in-<lb/>sulating state of low-spin Co 3+ (3d 6 in t 2g orbits), which <lb/>is regarded alternatively as 0.35-electron doping state in <lb/>the triangular lattice consisting of S = 1/2 of Co 4+ . One <lb/>may expect the unconventional superconductivity with <lb/>magnetic frustrations originating from the triangular lat-<lb/>tice. <lb/>For understanding superconducting (SC) properties, <lb/>determination of the pairing symmetry is one of the most <lb/>important issues. For the purpose, nuclear magnetic reso-<lb/>nance (NMR) and nuclear quadrupole resonance (NQR) <lb/>measurements are suitable because they give crucial in-<lb/>formation about the orbital and spin states of the SC <lb/>pairs from a microscopic point of view. In particular, <lb/>NQR technique is powerful when some impurity phases <lb/>are included in a sample, because NQR can spectroscopi-<lb/>cally detect only a concerned phase from the difference of <lb/>the electric field gradient (EFG) in each phase. Further-<lb/>more, by using the NMR and NQR techniques, nuclear-<lb/>spin lattice relaxation rate 1/T 1 can be measured, which <lb/>is related with low-energy spin dynamics in compounds. <lb/></body>

			<front>* E-mail address: kishida@scphys.kyoto-u.ac.jp <lb/></front>

			<body>Until now, there are three NMR and NQR reports on <lb/>Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O. 2-4) Two groups report that 1/T 1 T is en-<lb/>hanced just below T c . 2, 3) On the other hand, Fujimoto <lb/>et al. show that 1/T 1 decreases suddenly just below T c <lb/>and follows the Korringa behavior (T T = const. behav-<lb/>ior) far below T c . 4) Their observation on 1/T 1 can be <lb/>interpreted by the unconventional SC model with line-<lb/>node gap. Thus the results reported so far contradict <lb/>each other. To settle the controversy over the NMR and <lb/>NQR results in the SC state, further 1/T 1 studies are <lb/>highly desired. <lb/>In this paper, we show our 1/T 1 results measured inde-<lb/>pendently. Our measurement was performed in the wider <lb/>temperature range between 65mK and 200 K and on two <lb/>samples with different character. One of the samples is <lb/>SC bilayer-hydrate Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O with higher T c ∼ 4.7 <lb/>K than in the previous reports. 3, 4) The other is the non-<lb/>SC monolayer hydrate Na x CoO 2 •yH O due to partial <lb/>extraction of H O molecules between CoO layers. Our <lb/>1/T 1 result in the SC state is consistent with that by Fuji-<lb/>moto et al., i.e. absence of the coherence peak just below <lb/>T c and existence of the residual density of states far below <lb/>T c . 4) These are characteristic features of unconventional <lb/>superconductivity. In addition, we found the low-energy <lb/>spin-fluctuations in the SC sample, which is considered <lb/>as nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations. These results sug-<lb/>gest that unconventional superconductivity appears in <lb/>the metallic state with nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations, <lb/>which play an important role for the occurrence of super-<lb/>conductivity. <lb/>We used powder sample for our NQR measurements, <lb/>preparation of which was described in literatures. 1, 5) SC <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. <lb/>letter <lb/>Author Name <lb/></note> 

			<body>11.5 <lb/>12.0 <lb/>12.5 <lb/>13.0 <lb/>non -SC <lb/>monolayer <lb/>hydrate <lb/>Na x CoO 2 yH 2 O <lb/>Co -NQR Intensity ( arb. unit ) <lb/>Frequency ( MHz ) <lb/>Co NQR Spectrum <lb/>( 7 / 2 ⇔ 5 / 2 ) <lb/>SC T c ~ 4.7 K <lb/>bilayer hydrate <lb/>Fig. 1. Co-NQR spectra corresponding to ±5/2 ↔ ±7/2 tran-<lb/>sition in the SC bilayer-hydrate and non-SC monolayer-hydrate <lb/>samples. The spectra were obtained by frequency-swept method. <lb/>transition was confirmed by dc-susceptibility measure-<lb/>ment (χ bulk ). The non-SC sample was obtained by stor-<lb/>ing the SC sample in the vacuum space at room tem-<lb/>perature for three days. From X-ray measurement, the <lb/>c-axis lattice constant was found to 6.9Å, which cor-<lb/>responds to that in monolayer-hydrate sample. 5) The <lb/>bilayer-hydrate phase could not observed in the non-SC <lb/>sample at all. Since the non-SC sample was prepared <lb/>from the SC sample, Na content is equivalent in two sam-<lb/>ples. This is very important for considering the role of <lb/>H O layer, since the superconductivity appears in quite <lb/>narrow Na-concentration region. 6) <lb/>Figure 1 shows the Co-NQR spectra in the SC and non-<lb/>SC samples, which were obtained by frequency-swept <lb/>method. The Co-NQR spectra originate from Co (I <lb/>= 7/2) nuclear-level transition between ±5/2 ↔ ±7/2. <lb/>The SC sample shows a single peak at 12.35 MHz with <lb/>the linewidth of 0.4 MHz. The EFG frequency and the <lb/>asymmetric parameter are consistent with previous re-<lb/>ports. 3, 4) On the other hand, the non-SC sample shows <lb/>two sharp peaks at 12.1 and 12.35 MHz, together with <lb/>other small satellite peaks at lower and higher frequency <lb/>sides. It seems that all Co sites are crystallographycally <lb/>unique in the SC sample: the CoO 2 layer is sandwitched <lb/>by two hydrate layers. On the other hand, due to ex-<lb/>traction of one hydrate layer, some Co sites in the CoO <lb/>layer of the non-SC sample have a different local sym-<lb/>metry from those of the SC sample, e.g. the sharp peak <lb/>at 12.1 MHz arises from the Co site, in which one of the <lb/>hydrate molecules near Co is regularly replaced by Na, <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>-1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>3~ <lb/>T <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>Na x CoO 2 yH 2 O <lb/>SC bilayer hydrate <lb/>Co -NQR <lb/>T c ~ 4.7 K <lb/>T <lb/>3 <lb/>1 / T <lb/>1 ( sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>Fig. 2. Temperature dependence of 1/T 1 of the SC bilayer-<lb/>hydrate sample plotted in logarithmic scale. The dotted curve in <lb/>the SC state is the calculation using the 2-D line-node (∆(φ) = <lb/>cos(2φ) ) model with residual DOS induced by unitarity impuri-<lb/>ties. The appropriate fitting parameters are 2∆/k B Tc = 3.5 and <lb/>Nres/N 0 ∼ 0.32. <lb/>and the satellite peaks are from the Co sites, in which <lb/>two or three hydrate molecules are replaced by Na. For <lb/>identification of Co-NQR peaks in the non-SC sample, <lb/>further NQR studies are needed in different stoichiomet-<lb/>ric samples. <lb/>T 1 was measured at 12.35 MHz in the SC sample and <lb/>12.1 and 12.35 MHz in the non-SC sample, respectively. <lb/>At these peaks, the recovery of the nuclear magnetization <lb/>after saturation pulses can be fitted by the theoretical <lb/>curve 7) in whole temperature range except for very low <lb/>temperature below 300 mK. <lb/>First, we discuss temperature dependence of 1/T in <lb/>the SC state. Figure 2 shows temperature dependence <lb/>of 1/T 1 in logarithmic scale. 1/T 1 shows sharp decrease <lb/>below T c and crosses over to the Korringa behavior in low <lb/>temperatures, which is qualitatively in good agreement <lb/>with the result by Fujimoto et al. 4) <lb/>To see the behavior around T c in detail, we show in <lb/>Fig. 3 temperature dependence of 1/T 1 divided by T , <lb/>1/T 1 T of the SC sample below 10 K. For comparison, we <lb/>also plot bulk susceptibility showing SC transition. As <lb/>seen in the figure, 1/T T decreases just below T c deter-<lb/>mined by the susceptibility. It is obvious that the coher-<lb/>ence peak is absent below T c , which suggests that the <lb/>superconductivity should be classified to an unconven-<lb/>tional superconductor such as heavy-Fermion, cuprate, <lb/>ruthenate, and organic superconductors. <lb/>The whole temperature dependence in the SC state <lb/>can be understood by the 2-D line-node model with <lb/>∆(φ) = ∆ 0 cos(2φ) incorporated with residual density of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. <lb/>Letter <lb/>Author Name <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>H = 200 Oe <lb/>T c ~ 4.7 K <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>Na x CoO yH 2 O <lb/>SC bilayer Hydrate <lb/>Co -NQR <lb/>1 / T <lb/>1 <lb/>T ( sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>χ ( 10 <lb/>-9 <lb/>emu / mol ) <lb/>Fig. 3. Temperature dependence of 1/T T and χ bulk of the SC <lb/>bilayer-hydrate sample below 10 K. <lb/>states (N res ) ascribed to impurities and/or crystal imper-<lb/>fections. 8) The dotted lines in Fig. 2 is the calculation us-<lb/>ing the model with 2∆/k B T c = 3.5 and N res /N 0 ∼ 0.32, <lb/>where N 0 is the density of states at T = T c . We found <lb/>that N res /N 0 is smaller in the higher-T c samples than <lb/>those reported by Fujimoto et al. 4) (N res /N 0 ∼ 0.65 and <lb/>T c ∼ 3.9 K ). Similar tendency was already seen in uncon-<lb/>ventional superconductor Sr RuO 4 . 9) Based on the the-<lb/>oretical model by Hotta, 10) we can tentatively estimate <lb/>T c0 in a pure sample of this compound as 5.5 K. Due to <lb/>the presence of the residual density of states, we cannot <lb/>rule out the possibility of the isotropic gap ascribed to <lb/>D + iD state, but the most promising gap would be the <lb/>line-node gap with residual density of states induced by <lb/>unitarity impurities. 11) <lb/>Next we move on to the normal-state properties in <lb/>these compounds. Temperature dependence of 1/T 1 T of <lb/>SC and non-SC samples, which was measured at 12.35 <lb/>MHz, are shown in the main panel of Fig. 4, in which <lb/>the scale of T axis is in the logarithmic scale. 1/T 1 T <lb/>was also measured at 12.1MHz in the non-SC sample, <lb/>and the value of 1/T 1 T is 8.2 s −1 K −1 at 4.2 K, 10 % <lb/>smaller than 1/T 1 T at 12.35 MHz, and the temperature <lb/>dependence is the same as that at 12.35 MHz. As seen <lb/>in the figure, 1/T 1 T of the non-SC sample shows the <lb/>Korringa behavior from 100 K to 1.4 K, whereas 1/T T <lb/>of the SC sample increases with decreasing temperature <lb/>below 100K down to T c . The Korringa behavior is not <lb/>seen at all just above T c in the SC sample. It is obvious <lb/>that the low-energy spin-fluctuations are present in the <lb/>SC sample, which is not seen in the non-SC sample. <lb/>To understand the spin-fluctuation character, we com-<lb/>pare the behavior of 1/T 1 T with that of bulk susceptibil-<lb/>ity χ bulk . The inset of Fig. 4 shows the temperature de-<lb/>pendence of χ bulk in two samples. The gradual increase of <lb/>χ bulk in the SC sample is seen below K, where 1/T 1 T <lb/>also increases. On the other hand, χ bulk in the non-SC <lb/>sample shows a sharp increase below 50 K whereas 1/T 1 T <lb/>does not in this temperature range. It seems that the in-<lb/>crease of χ bulk in the SC and non-SC samples might be <lb/>different in origin, e.g. the sharp increase in the non-SC <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>non-SC monolayer hydrate <lb/>T c <lb/>SC bilayer hydrate <lb/>1 / T <lb/>1 <lb/>T ( sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>non-SC monolayer <lb/>SC bilayer hydrate <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>χ <lb/>bulk ( 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>emu / mol ) <lb/>χ <lb/>bulk ( 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>emu / mol ) <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>Fig. 4. Temperature dependence of 1/T 1 T in SC bilayer-hydrate <lb/>and non-SC monolayer-hydrate samples. The inset shows tem-<lb/>perature dependence of χ bulk . In the inset, χ bulk is normalized, <lb/>so that the value of χ bulk at 300 K is identical in two samples. <lb/>sample originates from local moments in some impurity <lb/>phases, but the gradual increase in the SC sample is in-<lb/>trinsic behavior in the compound. This possibility is also <lb/>suggested by the comparison between 1/T T and χ bulk <lb/>in the SC sample as shown later. <lb/>In general, 1/T 1 T is related with low-energy part of <lb/>the q-dependent dynamical susceptibility in compounds. <lb/>From the comparison between 1/T T and χ bulk or Knight <lb/>shift, we can have an important information about spin-<lb/>fluctuation character, since the latter are related with <lb/>the static susceptibility at q = 0, χ(0). If AFM corre-<lb/>lations are dominant, which is the case in cuprate su-<lb/>perconductors, dynamical susceptibility has peaks at the <lb/>AFM wave vector Q apart from q = 0, therefore 1/T T is <lb/>mainly determined by staggered susceptibility, χ(Q). 12) <lb/>In most cuprate superconductors, 1/T 1 T and χ bulk show <lb/>different behavior, i.e., 1/T 1 T is enhanced whereas χ bulk <lb/>decreases with deceasing temperature due to the develop-<lb/>ment of AFM correlations. 13) Such information played a <lb/>crucial role in identifying the existence of AFM spin fluc-<lb/>tuations in underdoped cuprate superconductor. On the <lb/>contrary, when FM correlations are dominant, the dy-<lb/>namical susceptibility shows a peak at q = 0, thus 1/T 1 T <lb/>is dominant by χ(0) component. In the SCR theory which <lb/>describes the magnetic properties in weakly or nearly <lb/>FM metallic state successfully, 1/T 1 T was suggested to <lb/>be proportional to χ(0). 14) This relation was confirmed <lb/>experimentally in nearly FM metallic compounds such <lb/>as Pd 15) and YCo 2 . 16) The nearly FM fluctuations orig-<lb/>inate from the high density of states of d-electron at the <lb/>Fermi level. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. <lb/>letter <lb/>Author Name <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>1 / T 1 T <lb/>1 / T <lb/>1 <lb/>T ( sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>χ bulk <lb/>χ <lb/>bulk ( 10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>emu / mol) <lb/>M <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 / T <lb/>1 <lb/>T ( sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>K <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>χ bulk ( 10 <lb/>-4 emu / mol) <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>Fig. 5. Temperature dependence of 1/T T and χ bulk up to 200 <lb/>K. The inset shows the plot of 1/T 1 T against χ bulk . <lb/>Figure 5 shows temperature dependence of 1/T 1 T in <lb/>the normal state up to 200 K, together with bulk suscep-<lb/>tibility χ bulk for comparison. It was found that 1/T T <lb/>shows a good linear relation with χ bulk , as seen in the <lb/>inset of Fig. 5. 17) The good linear scaling between 1/T 1 T <lb/>and χ bulk strongly suggests that upturn of χ bulk in the <lb/>SC sample below 100 K is intrinsic behavior in the com-<lb/>pound, not from impurity phases. The linear relation in <lb/>the inset of Fig. 5 also suggests that the spin fluctuations <lb/>seen in the SC sample is nearly ferromagnetic ones, and <lb/>that superconductivity would appear in the nearly FM <lb/>metallic state, which is a quite contrast situation where <lb/>cuprate superconductivity appears. The nearly FM state <lb/>is also suggested by the large Wilson ratio (3.33), where <lb/>the values of χ bulk and γ of specific-heat measurement <lb/>just above T c <lb/>18) are adopted for the estimation. <lb/>Until now, it was found that most unconventional su-<lb/>perconductors appearing in the paramagnetic state have <lb/>strong AFM spin fluctuations. Even in spin-triplet super-<lb/>conductors reported so far, i.e., UPt 3 <lb/>19) and Sr 2 RuO 4 , 20) <lb/>dominant spin fluctuations are not FM but AFM like. Re-<lb/>cently unconventional superconductivity was discovered <lb/>far below FM transition, which is considered as spin-<lb/>triplet superconductors in the FM state. 21, 22) However, <lb/>although the existence of FM fluctuations above T c has <lb/>not been identified in the FM superconductors due to dif-<lb/>ficulty of experiments, it is likely that FM fluctuations <lb/>are mostly quenched deep into the FM ordered phase. <lb/>There has been no report about superconductivity ap-<lb/>pearing in the predominance of FM fluctuations. Thus, as <lb/>far as we know, Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O reported here is the first <lb/>example that the superconductivity appears in the nearly <lb/>FM metallic state. In such a situation, spin-triplet super-<lb/>conductivity in analogy with superfluidity of He would <lb/>be the most promising state within possible SC pairing <lb/>states. To identify the spin state of SC pairs, Knight-<lb/>shift measurement in the SC state is most crucial. Quite <lb/>recently, Waki et al. reported that the Co-NMR spec-<lb/>trum in the aligned SC sample is unchanged on passing <lb/>through T c , 2) whereas Kobayashi et al. reported the de-<lb/>crease of the Knight shift in the non-aligned SC sam-<lb/>ple. 23) The Knight shift behavior in the SC state is now <lb/>controversial issue. The result of the former group sug-<lb/>gests a spin-triplet superconducting state which is con-<lb/>sistent with our NQR results. <lb/>In conclusion, we show by Co-NMR study that <lb/>unconventional superconductivity is realized in <lb/>Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O. The promising SC-gap would be <lb/>line-node one with residual density of states induced <lb/>by unitarity impurities. We found the low-energy spin-<lb/>fluctuations present only in the SC sample, which are <lb/>considered as nearly ferromagnetic fluctuations from the <lb/>comparison between 1/T 1 T and χ bulk . We suggest that <lb/>Na x CoO 2 •yH 2 O is a new type of superconductivity, in <lb/>which nearly FM spin fluctuations play the primary role <lb/>for the mechanism of superconductivity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank H.Yaguchi for experimental support, and H. <lb/>Ikeda, and K. Yamada for valuable discussions. One of <lb/>the authors (K.I.) thanks W. Higemoto, and R. Kadono <lb/>for valuable information. This work has been partially <lb/>supported by CREST of Japan Science and Technology <lb/>Corporation (JST) and the 21COE Research in Grant-<lb/>in-Aid for Scientific Research from the Ministry of Edu-<lb/>cation, Culture, Sport, Science and Technology of Japan <lb/>(MECSST), and by the Grants-in-Aid for Scientific Re-<lb/>search from Japan Society for Promotion of Science <lb/>(JSPS), and MECSST. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1) K. Takada et al., Nature (London) 422, (2003) 53. <lb/>2) T. Waki et al., cond-mat/0306036. <lb/>3) Y. Kobayashi et al., cond-mat/0305649. <lb/>4) T. Fujimoto et al., cond-mat/0307 <lb/>5) K. Takada et al., to be published in J. Solid State Chem. <lb/>6) R. E. Schaak et al., Nature 424, (2003) 527 <lb/>7) D. E. MacLaughlin, J. D. Williamson and J. Butterworth, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 4, (1971) 60. <lb/>8) K. Ishida et al., J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 62, (1993) 2803. <lb/>9) K. Ishida et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, (2000) 5387. <lb/>10) Y. Hotta, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 62, (1993) 274. <lb/>11) Y. Bang, M. J. Graf, and A. V. Balatsky, cond/mat 0307510. <lb/>12) For example, Y. Kitaoka et al., Physica C 170,(1990) 189. <lb/>13) M. Takigawa et al., Phys. Rev. B 43 43, (1991) 247. <lb/>14) T. Moriya, and K. Ueda, Solid State Commun. 15, (1974) 169. <lb/>15) M. Takigawa, and H. Yasuoka, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 51, 787 <lb/>(1982). <lb/>16) K. Yoshimura et al., J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 53, 503 (1984). <lb/>17) The intercept of the x axis gives the orbital Van-Vleck sus-<lb/>ceptibility in the compound, which is estimated as 2 ×10 −5 <lb/>emu / mol. This suggests that the dominant contribution is <lb/>from the spin susceptibility of the Co-d electrons <lb/>18) B. G. Ueland et al., cond/mat 0307106. <lb/>19) G. R. Stewart et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 52, (1984) 679. <lb/>20) Y. Maeno et al., Nature 372, (1996) 532. <lb/>21) S. S. Saxena et al., Nature 406, (2000) 587. <lb/>22) D. Aokiet al., Nature 413, (2001) 613. <lb/>23) Y. Kobayashi, M. Yokoi, and M. Sato, cond/mat 0306264 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
