<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific Data | <lb/>(2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>text-mined dataset of inorganic <lb/>materials synthesis recipes <lb/>Olga Kononova 1 , Haoyan Huo 1,2 , tanjin He 1,2 , Ziqin Rong 2 , tiago Botari 1,3 , <lb/>Wenhao Sun 2 , Vahe tshitoyan 2,4 &amp; Gerbrand Ceder 1,2 <lb/>Materials discovery has become significantly facilitated and accelerated by high-throughput ab-initio <lb/>computations. this ability to rapidly design interesting novel compounds has displaced the materials <lb/>innovation bottleneck to the development of synthesis routes for the desired material. as there is no a <lb/>fundamental theory for materials synthesis, one might attempt a data-driven approach for predicting <lb/>inorganic materials synthesis, but this is impeded by the lack of a comprehensive database containing <lb/>synthesis processes. To overcome this limitation, we have generated a dataset of &quot;codified recipes&quot; <lb/>for solid-state synthesis automatically extracted from scientific publications. The dataset consists of <lb/>19,488 synthesis entries retrieved from 53,538 solid-state synthesis paragraphs by using text mining <lb/>and natural language processing approaches. Every entry contains information about target material, <lb/>starting compounds, operations used and their conditions, as well as the balanced chemical equation <lb/>of the synthesis reaction. the dataset is publicly available and can be used for data mining of various <lb/>aspects of inorganic materials synthesis. <lb/></front>

			<body>Background &amp; Summary <lb/>The number of big-data-driven projects for materials discovery has been boosted significantly in the last decades <lb/>due to Materials Genome Initiative efforts 1 and growth of computational tools 2-6 . Building and maintaining of <lb/>large-volume databases has become a crucial step to provide scientific data for mining and modeling. Widely used <lb/>materials databases, such as the Inorganic Crystal Structure Database (ICSD) 7,8 , NIST Web-book 9 , the Pauling <lb/>File and its subsets 10,11 , have been manually constructed and curated over decades and store experimentally <lb/>obtained data for thousands of inorganic materials. Combining high-throughput computations with database <lb/>infrastructure has led to the establishment of large-scale databases with ab initio-calculated materials structures <lb/>and properties 12-16 . <lb/>At the same time, scientific publications have accumulated an enormous amount of information about <lb/>materials, but the data is presented in unstructured and arbitrary form which significantly obstructs its use in <lb/>data-driven research 17 . Early approaches to text-mining of materials data have been implemented by manual <lb/>extraction from a limited amount of articles 18 , and lab notebooks 19 . Development of text mining and natural <lb/>language processing (NLP) approaches have made it possible to implement various automated methodologies <lb/>for converting scientific text into structured data collections 20,21 . Among the most widely used NLP toolkits for <lb/>chemical text processing and information extraction are ChemDataExtractor 22 , OSCAR4 23 , ChemicalTagger 24 <lb/>and others 17,25 . <lb/>Most of the existing data extraction and mining developments have been applied to establish and predict <lb/>structure-property-function relationships for materials 26-29 . Only recently effort has been spent to create collec-<lb/>tions of materials synthesis data and using them to predict materials synthesis routes 19,30 . Kim et al. created pub-<lb/>licly available dataset of inorganic synthesis parameters for 30 different oxides systems extracted from literature 20 . <lb/>They used their data to provide guidelines for titania nanotubes synthesis 30 . AI-guided synthesis predictions for <lb/>organic molecules have already been applied successfully 31-33 , as organic reaction data is more widely presented <lb/>in well-structured and machine readable format 34,35 . <lb/>In this work, we provide fully auto-generated open-source dataset of 19,744 chemical reactions retrieved from <lb/>53,538 solid-state synthesis paragraphs. The data are collected using an automated extraction pipeline (Fig. 1) <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Department of Materials Science and Engineering, University of California, Berkeley, CA, 94720, USA. 2 Materials <lb/>Sciences Division, Lawrence Berkeley National Laboratory, Berkeley, CA, 94720, USA. 3 Present address: institute of <lb/>Mathematics and computer Sciences, University of São Paulo, São carlos, SP, Brazil. 4 Present address: Google LLc, <lb/>Mountain View, cA, USA. these authors contributed equally: Olga Kononova and Haoyan Huo. correspondence and <lb/>requests for materials should be addressed to G.c. (email: gceder@berkeley.edu) <lb/>Received: 3 July 2019 <lb/>Accepted: 3 September 2019 <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/>Data DESCRiptOR <lb/>OpEN <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>which converts unstructured scientific paragraphs describing inorganic materials synthesis into so-called &quot;cod-<lb/>ified recipe&quot; of synthesis. The pipeline utilizes a variety of text mining and NLP approaches to find information <lb/>about target materials, starting compounds, synthesis steps and conditions in the text, and to process them into <lb/>chemical equation. The dataset is publicly available in JSON format. Digitizing and systemizing the large corpus <lb/>of existing solid-state chemistry literature enables us to make a first step toward development of data-driven <lb/>approaches for understanding inorganic materials synthesis and synthesizability. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Content acquisition. Scientific publications used in this work are journal articles published by Springer, <lb/>Wiley, Elsevier, the Royal Society of Chemistry, the Electrochemical Society, and the American Chemical Society, <lb/>from which we received permissions to download large amounts of web-content. For each publisher, we manually <lb/>identified all materials science related journals available for download. A web-scraping engine was built using the <lb/>scrapy (https://scrapy.org/) toolkit. Since the full-text articles published before 2000&apos;s are mostly in PDF format, <lb/>which complicates their parsing, we chose to process only papers in HTML/XML format published after the year <lb/>2000. The downloaded content includes the text of the article as well as its metadata such as journal name, article <lb/>title, article abstract, authors, etc. All data was stored in a document-oriented database implemented using a <lb/>MongoDB (www.mongodb.com) database instance. Because downloaded articles contain irrelevant markups, we <lb/>developed a customized library for parsing article markup strings into text paragraphs while keeping the structure <lb/>of paper and section headings. <lb/></body>

			<body>Paragraphs classification. To find paragraphs on solid-state synthesis, we used a two-step paragraph <lb/>classification approach described elsewhere 36 which consists of an unsupervised algorithm to cluster common <lb/>keywords in experimental paragraphs into &quot;topics&quot; and generate a probabilistic topic assignment for each para-<lb/>graph, followed by a random forest (RF) classifier trained on annotated paragraphs. The outsome of the RF is a <lb/>classification of the synthesis methodology in a paragraph as either solid-state synthesis, hydrothermal synthesis, <lb/>sol-gel precursor synthesis, or &quot;none of the above&quot;. The annotation set consisted of 1,000 paragraphs for each label. <lb/>Synthesis recipe extraction. A typical synthesis procedure in the solid-state chemistry literature con-<lb/>tains information about precursor and target materials, synthesis operations and operation conditions. These <lb/>items comprise a materials synthesis &quot;recipe&quot; and were extracted from a synthesis paragraph as shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>Our extraction pipeline consists of several algorithms which analyze a paragraph and identify information about <lb/>materials (final products and starting precursors), synthesis steps performed, and conditions associated with <lb/>those steps. Finally, target and starting materials as well as synthesis conditions are used to balance a chemical <lb/>equation representing the synthesis reaction. The next sections provide details on each step of the pipeline. <lb/>Material entities recognition (MER). To identify starting materials and final products mentioned in a synthesis <lb/>paragraph, we implemented a bi-directional long-short term memory neural network with a conditional random <lb/>Fig. 1 Schematic representation of synthesis &quot;recipes&quot; extraction pipeline. Top panel: The pipeline starts with <lb/>retrieval of HTML content from major publishers which is then parsed into a raw text. Next, paragraphs <lb/>describing synthesis are identified and classified according to synthesis type. Every paragraph is then processed <lb/>to extract synthesis &quot;recipe&quot;, i.e. materials, operations and conditions. The output is stored in a database for <lb/>further data mining. Bottom panel: Example of processing a synthesis paragraph into a &quot;recipe&quot;. The key <lb/>component of &quot;recipe&quot;, such as target and starting materials, synthesis steps and their conditions are found and <lb/>extracted from the paragraph by different text mining algorithms (see Methods). <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>field layer on top of it (BiLSTM-CRF) 37,38 which is able to recognize the meaning of a word based on both the <lb/>word itself and its context. Extraction was performed in two steps each executed by a different neural network: <lb/>first we identified all materials entities presented in the paragraph; next we replaced each material with a key-<lb/>word &quot;&lt;MAT&gt;&quot; and classified them as TARGET, PRECURSOR or OTHER material. Each word input for the <lb/>BiLSTM-CRF was represented as the combination of a word-level embedding from a Word2Vec model 39 trained <lb/>on ∼33,000 solid-state synthesis paragraphs, and a character-level embedding from a character lookup table. The <lb/>table was randomly initialized and then optimized during the training of the BiLSTM-CRF. As an additional fea-<lb/>ture in the word representation for the second neural network, we also included chemical information about each <lb/>material, i.e. number of metal/metalloid elements and a flag indicating whether the material contains C, H and O <lb/>elements only. This assisted in the differentiation of precursors and targets, as they tend to have different number <lb/>of metal/metalloid elements and are generally not organic compounds in our dataset. We manually annotated 834 <lb/>solid-state synthesis paragraphs from 750 papers by assigning each word token with the following tags: &quot;material&quot;, <lb/>&quot;target&quot;, &quot;precursor&quot;, and &quot;outside&quot; (not a material entity). The annotated dataset was randomly split into training/ <lb/>validation/test sets with 500/100/150 papers in each set. The model parameters were iteratively optimized on the <lb/>training set using early stopping regularization 40 to minimize overfitting, and the model with best performance <lb/>on the validation set was chosen. <lb/>Synthesis operations. We implemented an algorithm which combines neural network and sentence depend-<lb/>ency tree analysis to identify key steps of solid-state synthesis given in the paragraph. The neural network was <lb/>used to classify sentence tokens into 6 categories: NOT OPERATION, MIXING, HEATING, DRYING, <lb/>SHAPING, QUENCHING, which are the main operations in solid-state synthesis. To create tokens features, we <lb/>trained a Word2Vec model 39 on ∼20,000 synthesis paragraphs using the Gensim library 41 . For the Word2Vec <lb/>model training, the sentences of paragraphs were lemmatized, all the quantity tokens were replaced with a key-<lb/>word &lt;NUM&gt;, and all the chemical formulas were replaced with keyword &lt;CHEM&gt;. We also used the SpaCy <lb/>library 42 to grammatically parse each sentence and obtain linguistic features of token such as token&apos;s part of <lb/>speech and its dependency to a root token. The annotated set consisted of 100 solid-state synthesis paragraphs <lb/>(664 sentences) with manually assigned tokens labels. For training, validation and testing, the annotated set was <lb/>split into a 70/10/20 fraction, respectively. Next, we used the dependency tree to assign MIXING operations as <lb/>a SOLUTION MIXING if its lemma belongs to any solvent-based process (e.g &apos;disperse&apos; , &apos;dilute&apos; , &apos;dissolve&apos; , etc) <lb/>or has a solution environment (e.g. &apos;ethanol&apos; , &apos;water&apos; , &apos;alcohol&apos; , etc.) in its sub-tree. This was differentiated from a <lb/>MIXING operation which consists of grinding or milling in liquid environment, which was assigned the LIQUID <lb/>GRINDING label. <lb/>Mixing and heating conditions. For every HEATING operation, we extracted the values or range of values for <lb/>time, temperature, atmosphere corresponding to the operation, if they are mentioned in the same sentence. We <lb/>applied a regular expression approach to find the values of temperature and time, and a keyword-search to find <lb/>atmosphere. For any operation of type MIXING, we extracted corresponding mixing media and type of mix-<lb/>ing device, if they are mentioned in the same sentence. For this, we used the list of materials labeled by MER <lb/>as OTHER materials, as well as keyword-matching, to find potential device or media substances. The extracted <lb/>attributes were assigned to both the heating and mixing by using dependency sub-tree analysis. Throughout the <lb/>text, these attributes are referred as &quot;conditions&quot; of synthesis or operations. <lb/>Balancing equations. Every material entry was processed with a Material Parser, which converts the string rep-<lb/>resenting the material into a chemical formula and splits it into elements and stoichiometries. Balanced reactions <lb/>were obtained from parsed precursors and target materials by solving a system of linear equations. Variables <lb/>of the linear equations represent molar amounts of materials involved in a reaction, and each equation asserts <lb/>the conservation of a certain chemical element in the reaction. Besides precursor and target materials, we also <lb/>included a set of &quot;open&quot; compounds (i.e. the compounds that can be released or absorbed during solid-state syn-<lb/>thesis, such as O 2 , CO 2 , N 2 , etc.) which were inferred based on the compositions of precursor and target materials. <lb/>Whenever a target material was synthesized with a &quot;modifier&quot;, i.e. doping, stabilizing, substituting elements, a <lb/>note is assigned to the reaction: &quot;target &lt;target_name&gt; with additives &lt;element&gt; via &lt;precursor&gt;&quot;. To solve <lb/>symbolic equations for materials with variable amounts of chemical elements, we used the Gaussian elimination <lb/>routines in SymPy 43 . <lb/>Dataset generation. We scraped a total of 4,204,170 papers, which contained 6,218,136 paragraphs in the <lb/>experimental sections. The experimental sections were identified by using case-insensitive keyword matching in <lb/>section headings (i.e. &quot;experiment&quot;, &quot;synthesis&quot;, &quot;preparation&quot; and their morphological derivations). Plain text par-<lb/>agraphs were segmented into sentences and tokenized into words using the ChemDataExtractor tokenizer 22 . After <lb/>classification, 188,198 paragraphs were found to describe inorganic synthesis, such as solid-state, hydrothermal, <lb/>sol-gel, co-precipitation syntheses, with 53,538 corresponding to solid-state synthesis. These 53,538 paragraphs <lb/>and their corresponding abstracts were processed to extract materials, operations, conditions and balance chem-<lb/>ical equation as described above. <lb/>Data Records <lb/>The complete dataset of 19,488 solid-state synthesis reactions is provided as a single JSON file, and it is pub-<lb/>licly available at https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.9722159.v3 44 . Each record corresponds to a single chemical <lb/>reaction built from a paragraph describing inorganic material synthesis, and is represented as a JSON object in a <lb/>top-level list. If a paragraph reports synthesis of several materials or a material with variable substituted elements, <lb/>the corresponding reactions are split into separate data records. Aside from a balanced chemical equation, the <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>metadata for each reaction include: DOI of the paper from which the reaction is extracted and a snippet of the <lb/>corresponding synthesis paragraph (50 first and 50 last characters to facilitate its lookup), chemical information <lb/>about target and precursor materials used in the reaction, operations and conditions for heating and mixing steps <lb/>to synthesize the target material. The details of the data format are given in Table 1. <lb/>The chemical equation for the reaction is stored as a string as well as a list of pairs: chemical substance (mate-<lb/>rial) and stoichiometric coefficient (amount). The reactants and products are listed in the left_side and <lb/>right_side, respectively. If in the original paper the target compound was synthesized with variable substi-<lb/>tuted elements, the element used in the particular reaction is given in element_substitution. <lb/>The metadata for target and precursors used to construct and balance the chemical equation are represented <lb/>by a data structure with the following properties: <lb/>• material_string: string of material as given in the original paragraph before being parsed into chemical <lb/>composition. <lb/>• material_formula: chemical formula associated with the material (given originally or constructed <lb/>empirically by parser). <lb/>• composition: chemical composition of the material derived from its formula. Aside from single com-<lb/>pound materials, we found that a large portion of the materials (predominantly target materials) are compos-<lb/>ites, mixtures, solid solutions or alloys, written as sequence of ratio-compound pairs. Therefore, a chemical <lb/>composition entity is represented by a list of dictionaries where each item is associated with a compound <lb/>found in the materials formula. The ratio of each compound in the material is given in amount, its chemical <lb/>composition (i.e. element and its fraction) is given in elements. If a material is one compound, the list has <lb/>only one item and amount = 1.0. If a material is hydrate, the water is added into the composition list with <lb/>the amount corresponding to the amount of water molecules (if specified). <lb/>• additives: list of additive elements (i.e. elements used for doping, stabilization, substitution) resolved <lb/>from material string. <lb/>• elements_vars: lists all variable elements and their corresponding values found in the materials. <lb/>• amounts_vars: lists all variable elements ratios and their corresponding values found in the material for-<lb/>mula. The values of each variable are given as a structure with values listing specific variable&apos;s values, and <lb/>max_value/min_value values if range is given in the paragraph. <lb/>YellowGreen Data description <lb/>Data Key Label <lb/>Data Type <lb/>DOI of the original paper <lb/>doi <lb/>string <lb/>Snippet of the raw text <lb/>paragraph_string <lb/>string <lb/>Chemical equation <lb/>reaction <lb/>Object (dict): <lb/>-element_substitution: <lb/>-left_side: list of Objects a <lb/>-right_side: list of Objects a <lb/>Chemical equation in string format <lb/>reaction_string <lb/>string <lb/>Target material data <lb/>target <lb/>Object (dict): <lb/>-material_string: string, <lb/>-material_formula: string, <lb/>-composition: list of Objects b , <lb/>-additives: list of strings <lb/>-elements_vars: {var: list of strings} <lb/>-amounts_vars: {var: list of Objects c } <lb/>-oxygen_deficiency: boolean <lb/>-mp_id: string <lb/>List of target formulas obtained after variables substitution targets_string <lb/>list of strings <lb/>Precursor materials data <lb/>precursors <lb/>list of Objects (See target) <lb/>Sequence of synthesis steps and corresponding conditions operations <lb/>list of Objects (dict): <lb/>-token: string, <lb/>-type: string <lb/>-conditions: Object <lb/>-heating_temperature: list of Objects d <lb/>-heating_time: list of Objects d , <lb/>-heating_atmosphere: list of strings <lb/>-mixing_device: list of strings <lb/>-mixing_media: list of strings <lb/>Table 1. Format of each data record: description, key label, data type. a {amount: float, material: string}. <lb/>b {formula: string, elements: {element: amount of element}, amount: string}. c {max_value: float, <lb/>min_value: float, values: list of floats}. d {max_value: float, min_value: float, values: list of floats, <lb/>units: string}. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>• oxygen_deficiency: yes/no attribute which reflects if material was synthesized with unspecified oxygen <lb/>stoichiometry. <lb/>• mp_id: ID of the lowest-energy polymorph entry in Materials Project database (materialsproject.org) if it is <lb/>presented there. <lb/>To facilitate querying of the dataset, the targets_string field contains all target material formulas <lb/>obtained by substituting amounts_vars in the material_formula. <lb/>The sequence of synthesis steps for the reaction (if specified in the paragraph) is listed as a data structure with <lb/>the following fields: original token from the text (token), its type (type) as assigned by classification algorithm <lb/>(see Methods) and conditions used at this step (conditions). If the synthesis step has type HEATING then <lb/>temperature, time and atmosphere conditions are provided in the conditions attribute. Temperature and time <lb/>are given as values if discrete values are given, or max_value/min_value if a is given. If the synthesis <lb/>step is of the MIXING type then the mixing device and mixing media are specified in the conditions attribute. <lb/>technical Validation <lb/>Extraction accuracy. The overall extraction yield of the pipeline is 28%, meaning that out of 53,538 sol-<lb/>id-state paragraphs, only 15,144 of them produce a balanced chemical reaction. As a test of the full extraction <lb/>pipeline, we randomly pulled 100 paragraphs from the set of paragraphs classified as solid-state synthesis, and <lb/>checked them against completeness of the extracted data. Out of the 100 paragraphs, we found 30 that did not <lb/>contain a complete set of starting materials and final products, meaning that a human expert would not be able <lb/>to reconstruct a reaction from these paragraphs. The remaining 70 paragraphs could potentially contribute to <lb/>the dataset as they provide all information about starting materials and final products. Inspections of those 70 <lb/>paragraphs showed that 42 potential reactions were not reconstructed due to an incomplete or overcomplete set <lb/>of extracted precursor/target materials, or a failure to parse chemical composition, which makes it impossible to <lb/>balance the reaction. The former loss originates from the lower re-call of the MER algorithm which we traded in <lb/>for higher precision, while the parsing problem occurs due to complicated notation used for a materials entity. <lb/>Evaluation of the dataset records accuracy was performed by randomly pulling 100 entries and manually check-<lb/>ing each extracted field against the original paragraph. The calculated precision, recall and F1-score for every attrib-<lb/>ute of the data entry is given in Table 2. Overall, we achieved a high accuracy in extraction of targets (precision <lb/>97%), precursors (F1-score 99%), operations (F1-score 90%) and balancing reactions (precision 95%). The lower <lb/>accuracy of the heating conditions (F1-score &lt; 90%) is mostly caused by the cases where the heating step is missed <lb/>by the operations extraction algorithm. The retrieval of the mixing conditions show relatively poor accuracy with <lb/>F1-score 65%. This is largely due to misidentification by MER of the device material or media substance used for <lb/>mixing, as well as because those conditions are often not mentioned in same sentence as the mixing procedure. <lb/>This analysis leads us to a conclusion that at the chemistry level (correct precursors, targets, reactions), the <lb/>accuracy of the dataset is 93%. When including all operations and their conditions, the accuracy of having all <lb/>recipe items (chemistry, operations and attributes of the operations) extracted and assigned correctly is 51%, <lb/>which is low due to low performance in extraction the mixing attributes. For many solid-state recipes, specifics <lb/>of mixing the precursors is of less importance, so this extraction failure is less critical. When considering only <lb/>correctness of the recipe without conditions for heating and mixing (i.e. chemistry, operations and reactions), the <lb/>accuracy rises to 64%. <lb/>It is worth noting that for this dataset we aimed to achieve higher precision of the data extraction in expense <lb/>of lower recall (i.e. better miss the data record, rather than provide the wrong one), therefore the extraction rate <lb/>is low. Yet, constructing the balanced chemical equation sets up additional constraints on targets and precursors, <lb/>and helps to reduce potential errors that may have been caused by composition parsing. This results in a skew of <lb/>the metrics toward higher accuracy for identification of targets and precursors, as compared to operations. <lb/>Dataset mining. In order to test the diversity of the entries representing the dataset, we first obtained a list of <lb/>unique materials (targets and precursors) and reactions. The dataset contains 13,009 unique targets, 1,845 unique <lb/>Data attribute <lb/>Precision <lb/>Recall <lb/>F1 score <lb/>Materials <lb/>-targets <lb/>0.97 <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>-precursors <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>Operations <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>Heating conditions <lb/>-temperature <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>-time <lb/>0.90 <lb/>0.88 <lb/>0.89 <lb/>-atmosphere <lb/>0.89 <lb/>0.86 <lb/>0.87 <lb/>Mixing conditions <lb/>-mixing media <lb/>0.62 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>-mixing device <lb/>0.82 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>Balanced reactions <lb/>0.95 <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>Table 2. Performance of data extraction for dataset entries. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>precursors and 16,290 unique reactions. The almost 10-fold lower variety of precursors compared to targets can <lb/>be explained by the fact that in general researchers operate with a set of common well-established precursors. <lb/>Table 3 represents the ten most frequent targets, precursors and reactions in the dataset. The target compounds <lb/>neatly capture the types of materials most often studied in the last two decades via solid-state synthesis. These are <lb/>lithium ion battery cathode materials (LiFePO 4 , LiMn 2 O 4 and LiNi 0.5 Mn 1.5 O 4 ), as well as perovskites for multifer-<lb/>rorics, LEDs and CMOS applications (BaTiO 3 , BiFeO 3 , SrTiO 3 , Y 3 Al 5 O 12 ). It is possible that this &quot;top-ten&quot; materi-<lb/>als list is biased by the set of publishers that gave us permission to access their scientific corpus. For example, The <lb/>American Physical Society was not included and may have brought other compounds to the list. <lb/>Next, we evaluate the chemical space covered by the dataset. For each chemical element, we computed the <lb/>amount of the reactions which include the given element in the target. The results are mapped in Fig. 2 in the <lb/>yellow-to-green gradient frame at the top of each element box. The database is dominated by target materials <lb/>containing Ti, Sr, Ba, La, Fe -&gt;3,000 reactions include these targets with these elements. This is also reflected in <lb/>the list of the ten most frequent target materials appearing in the dataset (Table 3). The next-most prevalent targets <lb/>are materials with Li, Ca, Nb, Mn, Bi -2,000-3,000 reactions with these elements in targets. The least common ele-<lb/>ments are Au, Pt, Os, Be -&lt;13 reactions in the dataset contain these elements. The rare and radioactive elements <lb/>such as francium, radium, technetium or promethium are not presented in the target materials of the dataset. <lb/>We also examined the co-occurrence of chemical elements and the most typical counter-ions in precursor <lb/>materials, and determined the average firing temperature used with each of these precursors. Here, we operation-<lb/>ally define the firing temperature as the temperature used during the last heating step in the sequence of synthesis <lb/>operations. The results are shown in Fig. 2 as bar-graphs for each element. The color of the bar correspond to a <lb/>specific counter-ion. The pure element as precursor is shown in magenta. The length of the bar denotes the aver-<lb/>age firing temperature. <lb/>With this representation, we observe that the dataset accurately depicts known aspects of solid-state chemis-<lb/>try. For example, alkali and transition metal cations are often introduced into a reaction via a variety of precur-<lb/>sors, including binary oxides, nitrides, sulfides, etc; or simple salts such as carbonates, phosphates, and nitrates. <lb/>At the same time, some of the cations in precursor compounds can be found only in the form of oxides or pure <lb/>elements (e.g. Be, Sc, Hf, Ru, Os, Rh, Pb, Nb, Pt, Au, …). <lb/>In solid-state synthesis, the counter-ion governs the melting or decomposition temperature of the precursor <lb/>and may determine when the precursor becomes active during synthesis. The distribution of firing temperatures <lb/>in Fig. 2 agrees very well with this statement and illustrates how different precursors are used in different temper-<lb/>ature regimes during solid-state synthesis. For example, the blue bars have in general larger length (high average <lb/>temperature) than red ones, because transition metal borides, carbides and nitrides often have higher reaction <lb/>temperatures than their corresponding oxides, due to the refractory nature of their precursors. On the other <lb/>hand, the green bars are relatively shorter (lower average firing temperature) than red ones, because, compared to <lb/>oxides and complex oxide anions (carbonates, phosphates, etc), synthesis with hydroxides, oxalates, and acetates <lb/>facilitate lower temperature reactions as they are often homogeneously mixed by precipitation from solution. <lb/>This data-driven temperature analysis is based on precursor, and we acknowledge that reaction temperatures <lb/>also depend on the thermal stability and reactivity of the target compounds. Nonetheless, the figure provides a <lb/>semi-quantitative starting point for the researchers: If a target material decomposes at relatively low temperature, <lb/>it may be better to choose a precursor that tends to become active at lower temperature. <lb/>In order to demonstrate the diversity of synthesis routes represented in the dataset, we sorted the sequence of <lb/>synthesis steps according to the following pre-defined patterns (table in Fig. 3): <lb/>• one-step synthesis consists of only solid mixing/grinding operations and at most one heating steps (final fir-<lb/>ing) without regrinding, <lb/>• synthesis with grinding in a liquid media to homogenize (without dissolution) the starting materials in any <lb/>liquid media, <lb/>• solution-based synthesis contains any type of dissolution of starting materials in solvent, <lb/>• synthesis with intermediate heat has one or more heating steps (not including drying after mixing with liquid <lb/>part) before final firing of the materials. <lb/>Targets <lb/>Precursors <lb/>Reactions <lb/>LiFePO 4 <lb/>TiO 2 <lb/>BaCO 3 + TiO 2 = BaTiO 3 + CO 2 <lb/>LiMn 2 O 4 <lb/>SrCO 3 <lb/>3CuO + 4TiO 2 + CaCO 3 = CaCu 3 Ti 4 O 12 + CO 2 <lb/>BaTiO 3 <lb/>BaCO 3 <lb/>0.5Bi 2 O 3 + 0.5Fe 2 O 3 = BiFeO 3 <lb/>BiFeO 3 <lb/>La 2 O 3 <lb/>SrCO 3 + TiO 2 = SrTiO 3 + CO 2 <lb/>CaCu 3 Ti 4 O 12 <lb/>CaCO 3 <lb/>2Li 2 CO 3 + 5TiO 2 = Li 4 Ti 5 O 12 + 2CO 2 <lb/>SrTiO 3 <lb/>Bi 2 O 3 <lb/>TiO 2 + CaCO 3 = CaTiO 3 + CO 2 <lb/>Li 4 Ti 5 O 12 <lb/>Fe 2 O 3 <lb/>Nb 2 O 5 + ZnO = ZnNb 2 O 6 <lb/>Y 3 Al 5 O 12 <lb/>Nb 2 O 5 <lb/>6Fe2O3 + BaCO3 = BaFe12O19 + CO2 <lb/>CaTiO 3 <lb/>Li 2 CO 3 <lb/>Li 2 CO 3 + TiO 2 = Li 2 TiO 3 + CO 2 <lb/>LiNi 0.5 Mn 1.5 O 4 <lb/>Na 2 CO 3 <lb/>0.5Li 2 CO 3 + 0.333Co 3 O 4 + 0.083O 2 = LiCoO 2 + 0.5CO 2 <lb/>Table 3. Ten most common targets, precursors and reactions present in the dataset. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>First, we found that different synthesis types are represented in the database almost evenly (top pie-chart in <lb/>Fig. 3): 26% of materials are synthesized in one-step, 25% of the syntheses routes are done with intermediate heat-<lb/>ing step(s) before finial firing, 21% of the syntheses contain grinding (homogenizing) in liquid, and 14% require <lb/>dissolving of precursors in solvent. The rest of the recipes (14%) either do not contain any detailed synthesis <lb/>procedure (6%), or the pathway is more complex (8%). <lb/>Since the choice of counter-ion used in a precursor often depends strongly on the synthesis method, we sur-<lb/>veyed which type of synthesis is common for a specific ion in precursor. We queried a subset of reactions which <lb/>include the given counter-ion in a precursor compound, and calculated the fraction of each synthesis type in <lb/>this subset. The resulting pie-charts are shown in Fig. 3. The emerging picture is consistent with known aspects <lb/>of solid-state synthesis. For example, in the precipitation of solids during synthesis, the precursor is dissolved <lb/>in the solution. As shown in Fig. 3, the solution-based synthesis (orange fraction) often uses soluble precursors <lb/>with nitrates, acetates, and organic (CH-containing) radicals. Some counter-ions are more amenable to one-step <lb/>synthesis than others, for example, chlorides, sulfides, and hydrides do not require much additional processing. <lb/>On the other hand, relatively stable precursors such as oxides and carbonates are processed in a variety of ways, <lb/>often requiring intermediate heating and grinding. This is probably due to the common formation of reaction <lb/>impurities and non-equilibrium intermediates during reaction sequences 45,46 . <lb/>The extraction pipeline we developed allows for automatic processing of scientific paragraphs and identifying <lb/>key information about solid-state synthesis from there. However, the pipeline still suffers from some issues with <lb/>the text mining. First, most of the errors down the pipeline are introduced due to incorrect tokenization of the <lb/>paragraphs and sentences. Although the ChemDataExtractor 22 tokenizer significantly outperforms other NLP <lb/>packages on chemistry-related texts, it still fails to correctly process large mixtures and solid solutions formulas as <lb/>well as chemical names consisting of multiple words. We attribute this issue to the fact that ChemDataExtractor <lb/>was trained on organic chemical entities, and using it for the recognition of inorganic tokens requires modifi-<lb/>cation of the algorithms. Secondly, no established template or pattern exists for describing synthesis procedure <lb/>which results in significant amount of ambiguity and difficulty when a synthesis method is interpreted even <lb/>by an expert 47 . This requires development of more advanced text extraction models considering the features of <lb/>Fig. 2 Map of chemical space covered by the dataset. For each element, the frame colored in a yellow-to-green <lb/>gradient represents the total amount of reactions that produce a target compound containing the element. <lb/>The bar graph below each element shows the list of ions paired with the element in precursor compounds. The <lb/>length of the bar corresponds to the firing temperature averaged over all the reactions using the given precursor <lb/>(i.e. element + counter-ion). The elements occurring in five and less targets are faded in grey. &quot;Ac&quot; stands for <lb/>acetate radical CH 3 COO − in the compound formula. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/>(2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>scientific text flow. Third, although the dataset was generated from the paragraphs describing solid-state synthesis <lb/>(as defined by a classification algorithm), it also contains reactions for solution-based precursors synthesis, such <lb/>as sol-gel (Fig. 3). However, these entries mostly dropped out later in the pipeline, because the majority of them <lb/>uses organic precursors with complex radicals, and balancing such chemical equations becomes complicated. <lb/>Lastly, we found that most of the materials studied and synthesized after 2000&apos;s are often modified (e.g. doped, ele-<lb/>ments substituted) compounds, mixtures, glasses or solid solutions. Parsing such materials into composition and <lb/>building balanced reaction equations is not straightforward. For some compounds with doped and substituted <lb/>elements, we included the information about modifying elements and corresponding precursors in the reaction <lb/>string (see Methods). One of the ways to reconstruct reactions for mixtures, solid solutions, alloys, etc. is to split <lb/>the entire material into compounds and match them with the corresponding precursors. Rather than fully resolve <lb/>it, we choose to setup a flexible data structure which allows for its further development by the user. <lb/>Fig. 3 Correspondence between choice of synthesis route and precursors counter-ions. The top table gives an <lb/>example of the four synthesis types defined: one-step synthesis, solution-based, synthesis with intermediate <lb/>heating steps, synthesis including grinding of precursors in liquid media. The pie-charts on the right displays <lb/>the fraction of each synthesis route in the dataset. The donuts-like charts represent the fractions of the four <lb/>synthesis routes (given in table) for each counter-ions used in precursors. &quot;Ac&quot; stands for acetate radical <lb/>CH 3 COO − in the compound formula. &quot;Org&quot; stands for organic radical (-CH-) in the compound formula. <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<body>Usage Notes <lb/>The dataset is provided in a single file in JSON format. It can be read using all major programming languages, <lb/>including Python, Matlab, R, Wolfram Mathematica. No specific technical setup is required as a dependency. <lb/>The dataset can be easily queried by target and precursor compound(s), their compositions and Materials <lb/>Project IDs, type of operations used in synthesis, conditions and reaction. As an example, Fig. 4 illustrates the <lb/>utility of the dataset in conducting rapid literature review of different synthesis procedures within a single chem-<lb/>ical space. It displays the result of a query for reactions to a target with Li, Mn and O in the composition. This <lb/>example provides a birds-eye perspective of the various solid-state synthesis routes to target LMO compounds in <lb/>this space using the dataset. The generated subset can be further queried by precursors types, as well as by type of <lb/>heating/mixing conditions. <lb/>Although the dataset is provided as a static snapshot 44 , we plan to update it on a regular basis. The updates will <lb/>be posted at the github repository at https://github.com/CederGroupHub/text-mined-synthesis_public. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Code availability <lb/>The scripts utilized to classify paragraphs and extract recipes as well as to perform the data analysis are home-<lb/>written codes which are publicly available at the github repository https://github.com/CederGroupHub/text-<lb/>mined-synthesis_public with acknowledgement of the current paper. The underlying machine-learning libraries <lb/>used in this project are all open-source: Tensorflow (www.tensorflow.org), Keras (keras.io), SpaCy (spacy.io) 42 , <lb/>gensim (radimrehurek.com) 41 and scikit-learn (scikit-learn.org) 48 ChemDataExtractor (chemdataextractor.org) 22 . <lb/></div>

			<body>4 Graphical representation of dataset entries queried for the Li-Mn-O system. Examples of the subset <lb/>entries: target LMO material, synthesis reaction and route. The DOIs are provided for reference. The triangle <lb/>shows the distribution of the LMO materials on the phase diagram. The circles size and color are scaled <lb/>according to the number of reaction in the dataset with the given target material. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Holden, J. Materials Genome Initiative for global competitiveness. Tech. Rep., National Science and Technology Council, https://www. <lb/>mgi.gov/sites/default/files/documents/materials_genome_initiative-final.pdf (2011). <lb/>2. Curtarolo, S. et al. The high-throughput highway to computational materials design. Nat. Mater 12, 191-201 (2013). <lb/>3. Schleder, G. R., Padilha, A. C. M., Acosta, C. M., Costa, M. &amp; Fazzio, A. From DFT to machine learning: recent approaches to <lb/>materials science-a review. J. Phys. Mater 2, 032001 (2019). <lb/>4. Butler, K. T., Davies, D. W., Cartwright, H., Isayev, O. &amp; Walsh, A. Machine learning for molecular and materials science. Nature 559, <lb/>547-555 (2018). <lb/>5. Lookman, T., Balachandran, P. V., Xue, D. &amp; Yuan, R. Active learning in materials science with emphasis on adaptive sampling using <lb/>uncertainties for targeted design. npj Comput. Mater 5, 21 (2019). <lb/>6. Rickman, J., Lookman, T. &amp; Kalinin, S. Materials informatics: From the atomic-level to the continuum. Acta Mater 168, 473-510 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>7. Bergerhoff, G. &amp; Brown, I. D. Crystallographic Databases (Allen, F. H. et al. (Hrsg.) Chester, International Union of Crystallography, <lb/>1987). <lb/>8. Belsky, A., Hellenbrandt, M., Karen, V. L. &amp; Luksch, P. New developments in the Inorganic Crystal Structure Database (ICSD): <lb/>accessibility in support of materials research and design. Acta Crystallogr. B 58, 364-369 (2002). <lb/>9. Linstrom, P. &amp; Mallard, W. (eds) NIST Chemistry WebBook, NIST Standard Reference Database Number 69 (National Institute of <lb/>Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg MD, 20899, 2019). <lb/>10. Blokhin, E. &amp; Villars, P. The PAULING FILE Project and Materials Platform for Data Science: From Big Data Toward Materials <lb/>Genome, 1-26. Handbook of Materials Modeling (Springer, Cham, 2018). <lb/>11. Villars, P. &amp; Cenzual, K. Pearson&apos;s Crystal Data: Crystal Structure Database for Inorganic Compounds (on DVD) (Release 2018/19). <lb/>ASM InternationalÂ ® , Materials Park, Ohio, USA. <lb/>12. Jain, A. et al. Commentary: The Materials Project: A materials genome approach to accelerating materials innovation. APL Mater 1, <lb/>011002 (2013). <lb/>13. Saal, J. E., Kirklin, S., Aykol, M., Meredig, B. &amp; Wolverton, C. Materials design and discovery with high-throughput density <lb/>functional theory: The Open Quantum Materials Database (OQMD). JOM 65, 1501-1509 (2013). <lb/>14. Curtarolo, S. et al. AFLOWLIB.ORG: A distributed materials properties repository from high-throughput ab initio calculations. <lb/>Comp. Mater Sci 58, 227-235 (2012). <lb/>15. Draxl, C. &amp; Scheffler, M. NOMAD: The FAIR concept for big data-driven materials science. MRS Bulletin 43, 676-682 (2018). <lb/>16. O&apos;Mara, J., Meredig, B. &amp; Michel, K. Materials data infrastructure: A case study of the Citrination platform to examine data import, <lb/>storage, and access. JOM 68, 2031-2034 (2016). <lb/>17. Krallinger, M., Rabal, O., Lourenço, A., Oyarzabal, J. &amp; Valencia, A. Information retrieval and text mining technologies for <lb/>chemistry. Chem. Rev. 117, 7673-7761 (2017). <lb/>18. Ghadbeigi, L., Harada, J. K., Lettiere, B. R. &amp; Sparks, T. D. Performance and resource considerations of Li-ion battery electrode <lb/>materials. Energy Environ. Sci. 8, 1640-1650 (2015). <lb/>19. Raccuglia, P. et al. Machine-learning-assisted materials discovery using failed experiments. Nature 533, 73-76 (2016). <lb/>20. Kim, E. et al. Machine-learned and codified synthesis parameters of oxide materials. Sci. Data 4, 170127 (2017). <lb/>21. Court, C. J. &amp; Cole, J. M. Auto-generated materials database of Curie and Néel temperatures via semi-supervised relationship <lb/>extraction. Sci. Data 5, 180111 (2018). <lb/>22. Swain, M. C. &amp; Cole, J. M. ChemDataExtractor: A toolkit for automated extraction of chemical information from the scientific <lb/>literature. J. Chem. Inf. Model. 56, 1894-1904 (2016). <lb/>23. Jessop, D. M., Adams, S. E., Willighagen, E. L., Hawizy, L. &amp; Murray-Rust, P. OSCAR4: a flexible architecture for chemical text-<lb/>mining. J. Cheminformatics 3, 41 (2011). <lb/>24. Hawizy, L., Jessop, D. M., Adams, N. &amp; Murray-Rust, P. ChemicalTagger: A tool for semantic text-mining in chemistry. J. <lb/>Cheminformatics 3, 17 (2011). <lb/>25. Eltyeb, S. &amp; Salim, N. Chemical named entities recognition: A review on approaches and applications. J. Cheminformatics 6, 17 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>26. Hautier, G., Fischer, C. C., Jain, A., Mueller, T. &amp; Ceder, G. Finding nature&apos;s missing ternary oxide compounds using machine <lb/>learning and density functional theory. Chem. Mater 22, 3762-3767 (2010). <lb/>27. Sun, W. et al. Thermodynamic routes to novel metastable nitrogen-rich nitrides. Chem. Mater 29, 6936-6946 (2017). <lb/>28. Xiao, Y., Miara, L. J., Wang, Y. &amp; Ceder, G. Computational screening of cathode coatings for solid-state batteries. Joule 3, 1252-1275 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>29. Zunger, A. Inverse design in search of materials with target functionalities. Nat. Rev. Chem. 2, article number 0121 (2018). <lb/>30. Kim, E. et al. Materials synthesis insights from scientific literature via text extraction and machine learning. Chem. Mater 29, <lb/>9436-9444 (2017). <lb/>31. Segler, M. H. S., Preuss, M. &amp; Waller, M. P. Planning chemical syntheses with deep neural networks and symbolic ai. Nature 555, <lb/>604-610 (2018). <lb/>32. Duvenaud, D. K. et al. Convolutional networks on graphs for learning molecular fingerprints. In Cortes, C., Lawrence, N. D., Lee, D. <lb/>D., Sugiyama, M. &amp; Garnett, R. (eds) Advances in Neural Information Processing Systems 28, 2224-2232 (Currant Associates, Inc., <lb/>2015). <lb/>33. Ley, S. V., Fitzpatrick, D. E., Ingham, R. J. &amp; Myers, R. M. Organic synthesis: March of the machines. Angew. Chem. Int. Edit 54, <lb/>3449-3464 (2015). <lb/>34. Goodman, J. Computer software review: Reaxys. J. Chem. Inf. Model. 49, 2897-2898 (2009). <lb/>35. Kim, S. et al. PubChem 2019 update: improved access to chemical data. Nucleic Acids Res 47, D1102-D1109 (2018). <lb/>36. Huo, H. et al. Semi-supervised machine-learning classification of materials synthesis procedures. npj Computational Materials 5, 62 <lb/>(2019). <lb/>37. Hochreiter, S. &amp; Schmidhuber, J. Long short-term memory. Neural Comput. 9, 1735-1780 (1997). <lb/>38. Lample, G., Ballesteros, M., Subramanian, S., Kawakami, K. &amp; Dyer, C. Neural architectures for named entity recognition. In <lb/>Proceedings of the 2016 Conference of the North American Chapter of the Association for Computational Linguistics: Human Language <lb/>Technologies, 260-270 (Association for Computational Linguistics, San Diego, California, 2016). <lb/>39. Mikolov, T., Sutskever, I., Chen, K., Corrado, G. S. &amp; Dean, J. Distributed representations of words and phrases and their <lb/>compositionality. In Burges, C. J. C., Bottou, L., Welling, M., Ghahramani, Z. &amp; Weinberger, K. Q. (eds) Advances in Neural <lb/>Information Processing Systems 26, 3111-3119 (Curran Associates, Inc., 2013). <lb/>40. Prechelt, L. Early Stopping -But When?, 53-67 (Springer Berlin Heidelberg, Berlin, Heidelberg, 2012). <lb/>41. Řehůřek, R. &amp; Sojka, P. Software framework for topic modelling with large corpora. In Proceedings of the LREC 2010 Workshop on <lb/>New Challenges for NLP Frameworks, 45-50 (ELRA, Valletta, Malta, 2010). <lb/>42. Honnibal, M. &amp; Johnson, M. An improved non-monotonic transition system for dependency parsing. In Proceedings of the 2015 <lb/>Conference on Empirical Methods in Natural Language Processing, 1373-1378 (Association for Computational Linguistics, Lisbon, <lb/>Portugal, 2015). <lb/>43. Meurer, A. et al. Sympy: symbolic computing in python. PeerJ Comput. Sci. 3, e103 (2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific Data | <lb/> (2019) 6:203 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41597-019-0224-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificdata <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificdata/ <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>44. Kononova, O. et al. Text-mined dataset of inorganic materials synthesis recipes. figshare. https://doi.org/10.6084/ <lb/>m9.figshare.9722159.v3 (2019). <lb/>45. Bor-Rong, Chen. et al. Understanding crystallization pathways leading to manganese oxide polymorph formation. Nature <lb/>Communications 9(1), (2018). <lb/>46. Shoemaker, D. P. et al. In situ studies of a platform for metastable inorganic crystal growth and materials discovery. Proceedings of <lb/>the National Academy of Sciences 111(30), 10922-10927 (2014). <lb/>47. Kim, E., Huang, K., Kononova, O., Ceder, G. &amp; Olivetti, E. Distilling a materials synthesis ontology. Matter (2019). <lb/>48. Pedregosa, F. et al. Scikit-learn: Machine learning in Python. J. Mach. Learn. Res. 12, 2825-2830 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">acknowledgements <lb/>Funding to support this work was provided by the Energy &amp; Biosciences Institute through the EBI-Shell program, <lb/>Office of Naval Research (ONR) Award #N00014-14-1-0444, the National Science Foundation under Grant <lb/>No. 5710003959 and the Assistant Secretary of Energy Efficiency and Renewable Energy, Vehicle Technologies <lb/>Office, U.S. Department of Energy under Contract #DE-AC02-05CH11231. We thank Anna Sackmann (Science <lb/>Data and Engineering Librarian at UC Berkeley) for helping us to obtain Text and Data Mining agreements <lb/>with the specified publishers. We also thank Prof. Elsa Olivetti, Edward Kim, Alexander Van Grootel, Zach <lb/>Jensen and Nicolas Mingione for the valuable collaboration and help with content acquisition and HTML/XML <lb/>markups parser development, as well as Chris Bartel, Ram Balachandran, and Padmini Rajagopalan for valuable <lb/>discussions. Lastly, we thank all CEDER group member for their help with data annotation and manual checks <lb/>of the data. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">author contributions <lb/>O.K. developed the Materials Parser, operations and conditions extraction algorithms, analyzed the data, wrote <lb/>manuscript. H.H. curated papers and paragraphs databases, developed paragraphs classifier and balancing <lb/>equations algorithm, performed manual data inspection, accuracy evaluation and final dataset preparation. T.H. <lb/>developed materials entity recognition algorithm, analyzed the data. Z.R. developed web scraper and performed <lb/>content acquisition. T.B. developed HTML/XML markups parser. W.S. analyzed the data, manually inspected <lb/>the dataset. V.T. curated and updated papers and paragraphs databases. G.C. developed approach, supervised the <lb/>project, wrote manuscript. All authors discussed the results and contributed to the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">additional information <lb/>Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/ <lb/>applies to the metadata files associated with this article. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2019 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
