<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0106521v1 [cond-mat.str-el] 26 Jun 2001 <lb/>Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/>Hironori Sakai 1,2 , Kazuyoshi Yoshimura 1 , Hiroyuki Ohno 1 , <lb/>Harukazu Kato , Shinsaku Kambe 2 , Russell E. Walstedt 2 , <lb/>Tatsuma D. Matsuda 2 , Yoshinori Haga 2 , <lb/>and YoshichikaŌnuki 2,3 <lb/>1 Department of Chemistry, Graduate School of Science, Kyoto University, Kyoto <lb/>606-8502, JAPAN <lb/>Advanced Science Research Center, Japan Atomic Energy Research Institute, <lb/>Tokai, Ibaraki 319-1195, JAPAN <lb/>3 Graduate School of Science, Osaka University, Toyonaka, Osaka 560-0043, JAPAN <lb/>Abstract. We make the first report that a metallic pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 , <lb/>exhibits type II superconductivity at 1.1 K. The pyrochlore oxide is known to be <lb/>a geometrical frustrated system, which includes the tetrahedral network of magnetic <lb/>ions. A large number of compounds are classified in the family of pyrochlore oxides, and <lb/>these compounds exhibit a wide variety of physical properties ranging from insulator <lb/>through semiconductor and from bad metal to good metal. Until now, however, <lb/>no superconductivity has been reported for frustrated pyrochlore oxides. The bulk <lb/>superconductivity of this compound is confirmed by measurements of the resistivity and <lb/>the a. c. magnetic susceptibility. The H c2 , which is extrapolated to 0 K, is estimated as <lb/>about 0.8 T, using the resistivity measurements under aplied field. The plot of H c2 vs T <lb/>indicates that the Cooper pairs are composed of rather heavy quasiparticles. This fact <lb/>suggests that frustrated heavy electrons become superconducting in this compound. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.10, 74.60, 74.70 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>Recently the subject of geometrical frustration in strongly correlated electron <lb/>systems has attracted considerable interest. The ground states of these systems are <lb/>expected to be highly degenerate. Such high degeneracies lead to thermodynamic <lb/>instability at low temperatures. Lifting these degeneracies makes possible the production <lb/>of exotic quantum ground states, such as spin-liquid, heavy fermion, and unconventional <lb/>superconductivity. <lb/>The pyrochlore oxide, which has a general formula A 2 B 2 O 6 O&apos;, contains a tetrahedral <lb/>network of A or B cations, leading to geometrical frustration. The A cations are eight-<lb/>fold coordinated with six O and two O&apos; anions and are located within distorted cubes, <lb/>while the smaller B cations are six-fold coordinated and are located within distorted <lb/>octahedra of which the six bond lengths from the central B cation to the corner O anion <lb/>are equal. The corner-sharing BO 6 octahedra compose a three-dimensional network as <lb/>shown in Fig. 1a. The sublattice of B cations composes a three-dimensional corner-<lb/>shared tetrahedral network, namely, the pyrochlore lattice as shown in Fig.1b. If <lb/>the A cations are non-magnetic and the B cations are magnetic, the B-spin magnetic <lb/>couplings are strongly frustrated under a nearest-neighbor antiferromagnetic exchange <lb/>interaction. For the case of localized electron spin moments, theoretical studies of the <lb/>Heisenberg model on the pyrochlore lattice have suggested that the ground state of such <lb/>an insulator would be long-range magnetic order[1], spin-freezing[2], or quantum spin <lb/>liquid[3]. The geometrical frustration plays a crucial role even in the case of itinerant <lb/>electrons in the pyrochlore lattice. Indeed, the metallic spinel oxide LiV 2 O 4 , which has <lb/>a pyrochlore lattice of vanadium, has been reported to show heavy fermion behavior at <lb/>low temperatures due to the geometrical frustration[4]. <lb/>A large number of compounds are classified in the family of pyrochlore oxides, and <lb/>these compounds exhibit a wide variety of physical properties ranging from insulator <lb/>through semiconductor and from bad metal to good metal[5]. Until now, however, <lb/>no superconductivity has been reported for frustrated pyrochlore oxides. Here, we <lb/>make the first report that a metallic cubic pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 , exhibits type II <lb/>superconductivity at 1.1 K. <lb/>Polycrystalline samples of Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 were prepared by solid state reaction. A <lb/>stoichiometric mixture of CdO, ReO 3 , and Re metal was pelletized, and put into an <lb/>alumina Tammann tube. The pellet in the Tammann tube was further inserted into <lb/>an evacuated silica tube and preheated at 300˚C for several hours in order to avoid a <lb/>vaporization of the starting materials. Then, the pellet was heated at 1000˚C for several <lb/>hours. The powder XRD pattern measured at room temperature was identified as the <lb/>cubic pyrochlore structure with a lattice parameter a=10.221Å, which is consistent with <lb/>the previous report[6]. <lb/>The direct current (d. c.) electrical resistivity of the sintered sample of Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/>was measured using a standard four-probe technique in the temperature range of 0.3 to <lb/>300 K under applied field from 0 to 2 T. Low-temperature measurements below 1.9 K <lb/>were performed using a 3 He refrigerator. Figure 2 shows the temperature dependence <lb/>of the d.c. electrical resistivity of Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 under zero applied field. The electrical <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>resistivity shows a steep descent below T * ∼ 200 K. This anomaly at T * was observed <lb/>in the d.c. magnetic susceptibility measurement as well. The origin of this anormaly <lb/>has not been identified. The electrical resistivity drops to zero sharply at the onset <lb/>superconducting temperature T c =1.1 K, and shows effectively zero resistivity below <lb/>1.05 K. Changes of driving electric current density produced slight differences in the <lb/>resistivity below 1.7 K, an effect which may be due to the superconductivity of a small <lb/>amount of impurity rhenium metal (T c =1.7 K). The superconductivity transition at 1.1 <lb/>K is not due to filamentary superconductivity of Re, since the observed critical field is <lb/>much larger than the critical field of Re (0.02 T), as will be described below. The large <lb/>residual resistivity of 4 × 10 −3 Ω•cm may suggest a low carrier density of this system. <lb/>From band calculations, it is pointed out that the system has a very small density of <lb/>states at the Fermi level, which is located within the 5d-band and in the valley between <lb/>the very flat bands of the rhenium 5d electrons[7]. However, the electronic specific heat <lb/>coefficient has been found to be large, i. e., γ=13.3 mJ/Re mol• K 2 [8], indicating that <lb/>heavy quasiparticles are formed due to the spin-frustration in this compound. <lb/>The alternating current (a. c.) magnetic susceptibility was measured by a mutual-<lb/>inductance method at a magnetic field of 2×10 −5 T in the temperature range of 0.3 to <lb/>1.8 K. As shown in Fig. 3, a strong diamagnetic signal (χ&apos;) has been observed below <lb/>1.06 K, which corresponds to the end-point transition temperature of the electrical <lb/>resistivity measurement. The dissipative component χ&quot; shows only a small peak around <lb/>T c , indicating no weak superconducting link between superconducting grains. The <lb/>superconducting volume fraction was estimated roughly as ∼ 50 % at 0.3 K. From this <lb/>experiment, a bulk superconducting state has been strongly confirmed in Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/>below 1.1 K. <lb/>To estimate the superconducting critical field, the magnetic field dependence <lb/>of T c has been determined by resistivity measurements. As the magnetic field was <lb/>applied, the sample maintained zero resistivity until the field reached H c2 . At H c2 <lb/>the superconductivity was quenched abruptly as shown in Fig.4. The value of the upper <lb/>critical field, which is extrapolated to zero temperature in the plot of H c2 vs T (Fig. 4, <lb/>inset) using the WHH model[9], is estimated as H c2 (0)=0.8 T. The superconducting <lb/>coherence length, ξ is expressed as <lb/>φ 0 <lb/>2πH c2 (T ) (where φ 0 is the fluxoid quantum). The <lb/>Pippard coherence length, ξ 0 =h v F <lb/>π∆(0) (where v F is the Fermi velocity, and ∆(0) is <lb/>the superconducting energy gap at T =0 K) was obtained as about 300Å using the <lb/>relation, ξ(T ) = 0.74ξ 0 <lb/>1− T <lb/>Tc <lb/>for a clean superconductor. This compound is considered to <lb/>be a clean superconductor, since the mean free path l is estimated as ∼ 4 × 10 −8 <lb/>m &gt; ξ 0 , using the Drude relation, ρ =h (3π 2 ) <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>e 2 l n − 2 <lb/>3 with resistivity ρ ∼ 4 × 10 −5 Ω• <lb/>m and carrier concentration n ∼ 1 × 10 24 m −3 which is a typical value for metallic <lb/>pyrochlore compounds. The observed large initial slope of H c2 , i.e., 1 <lb/>Tc <lb/>dH c2 <lb/>dT <lb/>T =Tc <lb/>∼ <lb/>1 T/K 2 , indicates that the Cooper pairs are composed of rather heavy quasiparticles, <lb/>since 1 <lb/>Tc <lb/>dH c2 <lb/>dT <lb/>T =Tc <lb/>is proportional to the square of effective mass m * 2 , in agreement with <lb/>the large γ value. This fact suggests, indeed, that frustrated heavy electrons become <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>superconducting in this compound. <lb/>Generally, superconductivity due to a magnetic interaction competes with magnetic <lb/>frustration, since no particular magnetic excitation for a superconducting attractive <lb/>channel exists due to the frustration. The present study gives the first example of <lb/>coexistence of magnetic frustration and superconductivity. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Anderson P W 1956 Phys. Rev. 1008 <lb/>[2] Villain J 1979 Z. Phys. B 33 31 <lb/>[3] Reimers J N 1992 Phys. Rev. B 45 7287 <lb/>[4] Kondo S et al 1997 Phys. Rev. Lett. 3729 <lb/>[5] Subramanian M A, Aravamudan G and Subba Rao G V 1983 Prog. Solid State Chem. 15 55 <lb/>[6] Donohue P C, Longo J M, Rosenstein R D, and Katz L 1965 Inorg. Chem. 1153 <lb/>[7] Harima H et al private communication <lb/>[8] Blacklock K and White H W 1979 J.Chem.Phys 71 5287 <lb/>[9] Werthamer N R, Helfand E, and Hohenberg P C 1966 Phys. Rev. 295 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>BO 6 octahedron <lb/>A cation <lb/>B cation <lb/>O&apos; anion <lb/>Fig. 1 H. Sakai et al. <lb/>Figure 1. Crystal structure of pyrochlore oxide. Figure 1a is drawn on a basis of the <lb/>network of BO 6 octahedra. Figure 1b shows the pyrochlore lattice of B cations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>5000 <lb/>0 <lb/>ρ ( µΩ • cm ) <lb/>1.8 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>J = 0.008 A/cm 2 <lb/>J = 0.23 A/cm 2 <lb/>J = 0.08 A/cm 2 <lb/>2.5x10 <lb/>4 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>ρ ( µΩ • cm ) <lb/>300 <lb/>200 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>Fig. 2 H. Sakai et al. <lb/>Figure 2. Temperature dependence of d. c. electrical resistivity for Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 in the <lb/>temperature range of 0.8 to 1.8 K. The inset shows the data in the range of 0.3 to 300 <lb/>K. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.5 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>χ&apos; <lb/>ac , <lb/>χ&apos;&apos; <lb/>ac ( arb. units ) <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>χ&apos; ac <lb/>χ&apos;&apos; ac <lb/>Fig. 3 H. Sakai et al. <lb/>Figure 3. Temperature dependence of a.c. magnetic susceptibility for Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 . χ&apos; <lb/>and χ&quot; represent the real part and the imaginary part, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Superconductivity in a pyrochlore oxide Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>5000 <lb/>0 <lb/>ρ ( µΩ • cm ) <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>H ( T ) <lb/>T = 0.42 K <lb/>T = 0.49 K <lb/>T = 0.62 K <lb/>T = 0.69 K <lb/>T = 0.79 K <lb/>T = 0.90 K <lb/>T = 1.01 K <lb/>T = 1.10 K <lb/>T = 0.38 K <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>H <lb/>C2 ( T ) <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>T ( K ) <lb/>Fig. 4 H. Sakai et al. <lb/>Figure 4. Magnetic field dependence of the resistivity for Cd 2 Re 2 O 7 . The inset shows <lb/>the plot of H c2 vs T . </body>


	</text>
</tei>
