<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0202251v2 [cond-mat.str-el] 7 Oct 2002 <lb/>Superconductivity and Quantum Criticality in CeCoIn <lb/>V. A. Sidorov, * M. Nicklas, P. G. Pagliuso, J. L. Sarrao, Y. Bang, A. V. Balatsky, and J. D. Thompson <lb/>Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NM 87545 <lb/>(Dated: October 29, 2018) <lb/>Electrical resistivity measurements on a single crystal of the heavy-fermion superconductor <lb/>CeCoIn5 at pressures to 4.2 GPa reveal a strong crossover in transport properties near P * ≈ 1.6 GPa, <lb/>where Tc is a maximum. The temperature-pressure phase diagram constructed from these data pro-<lb/>vides a natural connection to cuprate physics, including the possible existence of a pseudogap. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.70.Tx, 74.62.Fj, 75.30.Mb, 75.40.-s <lb/></front>

			<body>The relationship between unconventional superconduc-<lb/>tivity and quantum criticality is emerging as an im-<lb/>portant issue in strongly correlated materials, includ-<lb/>ing cuprates, organics and heavy-fermion intermetallics <lb/>[1, 2]. In each of these, either Nature or an externally <lb/>imposed parameter, such as pressure or chemical substi-<lb/>tutions, tunes some magnetic order to a T = 0 transi-<lb/>tion where quantum fluctuations introduce new excita-<lb/>tions that control thermodynamic and transport proper-<lb/>ties over a broad range of temperature-parameter phase <lb/>space. A frequent, but controversial [3], assumption is <lb/>that these same excitations may mediate Cooper pair-<lb/>ing in the anisotropic superconductivity that appears <lb/>in the vicinity of a quantum-critical point (QCP). In-<lb/>deed, the effective potential generated by proximity to a <lb/>quantum-critical spin-density wave [4] also can lead [5] <lb/>to anisotropic superconductivity. <lb/>Though the issue of quantum criticality and super-<lb/>conductivity came to prominence in the context of the <lb/>cuprates (see, eg [6]), there have been several recent ex-<lb/>amples of this interplay in heavy-fermion compounds [7]. <lb/>Like the cuprates, unconventional superconductivity in <lb/>these Ce-based heavy-fermion materials develops out of <lb/>a distinctly non-Fermi-liquid normal state that evolves <lb/>in proximity to a continuous T = 0 antiferromagnetic <lb/>transition; but unlike the cuprates, this state can be ac-<lb/>cessed cleanly by applied hydrostatic pressure and with-<lb/>out introducing extrinsic disorder associated with chemi-<lb/>cal substitutions. In addition to chemical inhomogeneity <lb/>in the cuprates, a further &apos;complication&apos; is the existence <lb/>of a pseudogap state above T c for dopings less than opti-<lb/>mal [8]. Whether evolution of the pseudogap with dop-<lb/>ing produces another QCP near the optimal T c in the <lb/>cuprates is an open question as is the origin of the pseu-<lb/>dogap [9]. Thus far, a pseudogap has not been detected in <lb/>canonical quantum-critical heavy-fermion systems, such <lb/>as CeIn 3 or CePd 2 Si 2 under pressure, but this may not <lb/>be too surprising. In these cases, superconductivity ap-<lb/>pears only at very low temperatures, less than 0.4 K, and <lb/>over a narrow window of pressures (≤ 0.8 GPa) centered <lb/>around the pressure where T N extrapolates to zero. In <lb/>analogy to the cuprates, we would expect a pseudogap in <lb/>these Ce compounds to exist only over a narrow temper-<lb/>ature window, 0.1 − 0.2 K above T c , and in a fraction of <lb/>the narrow pressure window, which certainly would make <lb/>detection of a pseudogap difficult. <lb/>CeCoIn 5 offers the possibility of making a connec-<lb/>tion between other Ce-based heavy-fermion materials <lb/>and the cuprates. Bulk, unconventional superconduc-<lb/>tivity is present in CeCoIn 5 at atmospheric pressure <lb/>[10, 11, 12, 13] and develops out of a heavy-fermion nor-<lb/>mal state in which the resistivity is approximately linear <lb/>in temperature. Application of a magnetic field suffi-<lb/>cient to quench superconductivity reveals a specific heat <lb/>diverging as −T ln T and associated low-temperature en-<lb/>tropy consistent with its huge zero-field specific heat <lb/>jump at T c (∆C/γT c = 4.5). Together, these proper-<lb/>ties suggest that CeCoIn 5 may be near an antiferromag-<lb/>netic quantum-critical point at P = 0. Its isostructural, <lb/>antiferromagnetic relative CeRhIn becomes a pressure-<lb/>induced unconventional superconductor near 1.6 GPa, <lb/>with a T c = 2.1 K close to that of CeCoIn 5 at P = 0 <lb/>[14, 15]. This and other similarities between CeCoIn at <lb/>P = 0 and CeRhIn 5 at P = 1.6 GPa reinforce specula-<lb/>tion [16, 17] that the nearby antiferromagnetic QCP in <lb/>CeCoIn may be at an inaccessible slightly negative pres-<lb/>sure. The 1.7% smaller cell volume of CeCoIn compared <lb/>to that of CeRhIn is consistent with this view. We have <lb/>studied the effect of pressure on the electrical resistivity <lb/>and superconductivity of CeCoIn 5 and find striking cor-<lb/>relations between them that are reminiscent of cuprate <lb/>behaviors. <lb/>Four-probe AC resistivity measurements, with current <lb/>flowing in the tetragonal basal plane, were made on a <lb/>single crystal of CeCoIn grown from excess In flux. Hy-<lb/>drostatic pressures to 5 GPa were generated in a toroidal <lb/>anvil cell [18] in which a boron-epoxy gasket surrounds <lb/>a teflon capsule filled with a glycerol-water mixture (3:2 <lb/>volume ratio) that served as the pressure transmitting <lb/>fluid. Pressure inside the capsule was determined at room <lb/>temperature and at low temperatures from the pressure-<lb/>dependent electrical resistivity and T c of Pb, respectively <lb/>[19]. The width of superconducting transition of Pb did <lb/>not exceed 15 mK, indicating good hydrostatic conditions <lb/>and providing an estimate of the pressure-measurement <lb/>uncertainty, ±0.04 GPa. <lb/>The response of ρ(T ) to pressure over a broad temper-<lb/>ature scale [16, 17] is typical of many Ce-based heavy-</body>

			<page><lb/>2</page>

			<body><lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>Sidorov et al. <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>CeCoIn <lb/>5 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>2.87 <lb/>2.16 <lb/>1.35 GPa <lb/>ρ (µΩ cm) <lb/>T(K) <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>3.43 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>3.15 <lb/>2.87 <lb/>2.16 <lb/>1.69 <lb/>ρ / <lb/>ρ(T <lb/>+ <lb/>c <lb/>) <lb/>T(K) <lb/>0 <lb/>1.35 <lb/>FIG. 1: Effect of pressure on the low-temperature resistivity <lb/>and superconducting Tc of CeCoIn5. The inset shows the <lb/>resistivity ρ normalized by ρ(T + <lb/>c ) up to 10 K. <lb/>fermion compounds and reflects a systematic increase in <lb/>the energy scale of spin fluctuations. Most interesting is <lb/>the low-temperature response (Fig. 1) where T c and the <lb/>resistivity just above T c (ρ(T + <lb/>c )) decrease rapidly with <lb/>pressures P &gt; 1.35 GPa. We have analyzed the low tem-<lb/>perature resistivity, plotted over a broader temperature <lb/>scale in the inset of Fig. 1, by either fitting to a form <lb/>ρ(T ) = ρ 0 + AT n , with ρ 0 , A and n fitting parameters, <lb/>or from plots of (ρ(T ) − ρ 0 )/T n . A drawback to the for-<lb/>mer approach is that parameters can be sensitive to the <lb/>temperature range chosen for fitting. The more sensitive <lb/>and revealing approach is the latter in which ρ 0 and n are <lb/>adjusted to give the best horizontal line. This procedure <lb/>requires one less parameter, A, which is provided directly <lb/>by the magnitude of (ρ(T ) − ρ 0 )/T n . Representative ex-<lb/>amples of this approach are plotted in Fig. 2. Parameters <lb/>obtained from these plots are well defined and agree, typ-<lb/>ically to 10% or better, with parameter values extracted <lb/>from straightforward fits. As indicated by arrows on the <lb/>lowest pressure curve in Fig. 2, (ρ(T ) − ρ 0 )/T n deviates <lb/>from the horizontal trend at a temperature T pg well above <lb/>the onset of superconductivity. This departure implies <lb/>either a decrease in the scattering rate or increase in car-<lb/>rier density. Resistivity measurements at P = 0 and in a <lb/>magnetic field (6 T) greater than H c2 (0) find [20] a sim-<lb/>ilar departure of (ρ(T ) − ρ 0 )/T n from a T -independent <lb/>curve at T pg =3 K. Thus, T pg does not originate from su-<lb/>perconducting fluctuations or from trace amounts of free <lb/>indium. We also note that this behavior was present in <lb/>previous measurements on other single crystals CeCoIn <lb/>but was missed in inspections of ρ versus T curves [16]. <lb/>We will return to a discussion of T pg later. <lb/>Values of ρ 0 , n and A obtained from these plots are <lb/>summarized in Figs. 3a and b. There is an unmis-<lb/>takable crossover in the pressure dependence of ρ and <lb/>12345 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>T C <lb/>T C <lb/>T pg <lb/>1.35 GPa <lb/>CeCoIn 5 <lb/>T FL <lb/>3.43 <lb/>2.87 <lb/>( <lb/>ρ -<lb/>ρ <lb/>0 ) / T <lb/>n <lb/>( <lb/>µΩ cm K <lb/>-n <lb/>) <lb/>T(K) <lb/>FIG. 2: Representative plots of (ρ(T ) − ρ0)/T n vs T . At <lb/>low pressures, (ρ(T ) − ρ0)/T n is constant from Tpg ≈ (1.15 ± <lb/>0.05)Tc to about 10 K. At the higher pressures, there is a <lb/>well-defined range below TF L where (ρ − ρ0) ∝ T 2 is Fermi-<lb/>liquid like. The resistive onset of superconductivity, defined <lb/>by the intersection of linear extrapolations of ρ(T ) from above <lb/>and below Tc, is denoted by dashed vertical arrows. At the <lb/>highest pressures, the gradual rounding just above Tc is due <lb/>to a broadened transition (see Fig. 3) and not to Tpg <lb/>n at P * ≈ 1.6 GPa. Below P * , n = 1.0 ± 0.1 for <lb/>T pg ≤ T ≤ 10 K. This value of n is expected for a 2-<lb/>dimensional, antiferromagnetic quantum-critical system <lb/>[21] and is not too surprising given the layered crys-<lb/>tal structure [22] and anisotropy in electronic states of <lb/>CeCoIn [10, 23]. At pressures greater than P * , n rapidly <lb/>approaches the Fermi-liquid value of 2.0, which holds <lb/>from just above T c to T F L (see Fig. 2). Though not <lb/>shown in either Fig. 2 or 3a, at these higher pressures n <lb/>assumes a value of 1.5±0.1, characteristic of a 3-D antifer-<lb/>romagnetic QCP, in a temperature interval from slightly <lb/>greater than T F L to as high as ∼ 60 K. For P ≥ P * , ρ 0 <lb/>decreases reversibly by an order of magnitude to a very <lb/>small value of about 0.2 µΩcm. Clearly, pressure does not <lb/>remove impurities from the sample; the large decrease in <lb/>ρ 0 must be due to a pressure-induced change in inelas-<lb/>tic scattering processes. Theories of electronic transport <lb/>in quantum-critical systems show [24, 25] that impurity <lb/>scattering can be strongly enhanced by quantum-critical <lb/>fluctuations. This sensitivity provides a natural expla-<lb/>nation for a decrease in scattering with increasing pres-<lb/>sure, if there is a crossover near P * from quantum-critical <lb/>(P &lt; P * ) to a Fermi-liquid-like state for (P &gt; P * ). Such <lb/>a crossover is suggested by the pressure variation of n. <lb/>Experimental values of the T n -coefficient of resistiv-<lb/>ity, plotted in Fig. 3b, also decrease strongly with in-<lb/>creasing pressure for P &lt; <lb/>∼ P * . For comparison, we show <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>CeCoIn 5 <lb/>ρ = ρ 0 + AT <lb/>n <lb/>a <lb/>ρ <lb/>0 ( <lb/>µΩ cm ) <lb/>n <lb/>b <lb/>A ( <lb/>µΩ cm K <lb/>-n <lb/>) <lb/>γ (mJ / mol Ce K <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>c <lb/>∆T <lb/>C / T <lb/>C <lb/>P(GPa) <lb/>FIG. 3: (a) Values of ρ0 and n obtained from plots as shown in <lb/>Fig. 2. (b) Temperature coefficient of resistivity, A, associated <lb/>with values of n given in the top panel, and specific heat <lb/>coefficient γ measured directly (P &lt; 1.5 GPa) and, for P &gt; 2 <lb/>GPa , inferred from the T 2 coefficient of ρ(T ). See text for <lb/>details. (c) Superconducting transition width normalized by <lb/>Tc. ∆Tc and Tc are the half-width of the resistive transition <lb/>width and resistive midpoint, respectively. Solid lines in all <lb/>cases are guides to the eye. <lb/>the variation of the electronic specific heat divided by <lb/>temperature (C/T ≡ γ) at 3 K for pressures less than <lb/>1.5 GPa [26] and, at higher pressures, we plot values of γ <lb/>inferred from the empirical relationship A = 1 × 10 −5 γ 2 , <lb/>where A is the T 2 -coefficient of resistivity, followed by <lb/>several heavy-fermion compounds [27]. Though a T <lb/>coefficient proportional to γ 2 is expected for a Landau <lb/>Fermi-liquid [6], it is not obvious a priori why A(P ) ap-<lb/>proximately tracks the directly measured γ at low pres-<lb/>sures, but this seems to be the case. In any event, both <lb/>A(P ) and γ(P ) exhibit qualitatively different magnitudes <lb/>and functional dependencies above and below P * . The <lb/>dramatic differences in γ(P ) at low and high pressures <lb/>suggest that either the empirical relationship is invalid <lb/>and underestimates γ in the high-pressure regime by at <lb/>least two orders of magnitude or there is a very rapid <lb/>crossover in the density of low-energy excitations in the <lb/>vicinity of P * . In the Fermi-liquid-like state above P * , <lb/>we would expect the temperature scale T F L (see Fig. 2) <lb/>P* <lb/>P <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>PG <lb/>FL <lb/>NFL <lb/>AFM <lb/>SC <lb/>T <lb/>P <lb/>0 <lb/>1234 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>T FL <lb/>T pg <lb/>a <lb/>CeCoIn 5 <lb/>SC <lb/>n = 1.5 ± 0.1 <lb/>n ≈ 1 <lb/>n = 2 <lb/>T(K) <lb/>P(GPa) <lb/>FIG. 4: (a) Temperature-pressure phase diagram for CeCoIn5 <lb/>constructed from data shown in Figs. 2 and 3. (b) Schematic <lb/>T −P phase diagram. AFM: Néel state; PG: pseudogap state; <lb/>SC: unconventional superconducting state; FL: Fermi liquid; <lb/>NFL: non-Fermi-liquid. See text for details. <lb/>to be proportional to A −0.5 instead of the approximate <lb/>T F L ∝ <lb/>√ <lb/>A found experimentally. We do not understand <lb/>this discrepancy. Direct measurements of C/T at pres-<lb/>sures above P * would be valuable. <lb/>Finally, we note that the resistive transition to the su-<lb/>perconducting state is equally sensitive to the crossover <lb/>at P * . As shown in Fig. 3c, the relative transition width <lb/>∆T c /T c passes through a pronounced minimum near P * . <lb/>To some extent this behavior is accentuated by the pres-<lb/>sure variation of T c , but ∆T c itself is a minimum near P * . <lb/>It is as if the optimally homogeneous state is singular in <lb/>the vicinity of P * . <lb/>From the data presented above, we construct a <lb/>temperature-pressure phase diagram for CeCoIn given <lb/>in Fig. 4a. This phase diagram is more like that of <lb/>the cuprates around optimal doping than the canonical <lb/>behavior of heavy-fermion systems exemplified, for ex-<lb/>ample, by CeIn or CePd 2 Si 2 [7]. There is no obvious <lb/>long-range ordered state in CeCoIn 5 at atmospheric or <lb/>higher pressures. Rather, in view of its relationship to <lb/>CeRhIn 5 , a reasonable speculation is that the antiferro-<lb/>magnetic QCP of CeCoIn 5 is at a slightly negative pres-<lb/>sure. The resistivity exponent n and specific heat (ref. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>[26]) are those of a non-Fermi-liquid up to P * where T c <lb/>is a maximum. Beyond P * , T c drops rapidly and param-<lb/>eters characterizing electronic transport are qualitatively <lb/>different, Fermi-liquid-like at temperatures just above T c <lb/>and those of a 3-D quantum-critical antiferromagnetic <lb/>state at higher temperatures. <lb/>The generic T −P phase diagram in Fig. 4b provides <lb/>a broader perspective of our experimental observations <lb/>and their relationship to CeRhIn 5 . In the spirit of this <lb/>diagram, the non-Fermi-liquid transport and thermody-<lb/>namic properties of CeCoIn 5 below P * are controlled <lb/>by an antiferromagnetic QCP at the inaccessible nega-<lb/>tive pressure denoted by P c in Fig. 4. We have chosen <lb/>P c to correspond approximately to the critical pressure <lb/>at which superconductivity appears in CeRhIn . Spin-<lb/>lattice relaxation measurements on CeRhIn identify [28] <lb/>a pseudogap whose signature first appears at pressures <lb/>slightly less than P c and at a temperature of ∼5 K and <lb/>then decreases toward T c with increasing pressure until <lb/>its signature is lost at P &gt; <lb/>∼ P c . If we associate the tem-<lb/>perature T pg (P ) in Fig. 4a with a resistive signature for a <lb/>pseudogap and extrapolate T pg (P ) in CeCoIn to slightly <lb/>negative pressures, there is a natural connection between <lb/>our observations and properties of CeRhIn . Neither <lb/>the 1/T 1 T measurements on CeRhIn 5 nor our transport <lb/>measurements on CeCoIn 5 permits definitive statements <lb/>about the origin or nature of the pseudogap [29]. We <lb/>note, however, that 4-fold anisotropy of the thermal con-<lb/>ductivity in the basal plane of CeCoIn persists [12] to <lb/>3.2 K ≈ T pg at atmospheric pressure. If this in-plane <lb/>modulation of the normal-state thermal conductivity is <lb/>due to the presence of a pseudogap, it implies d-wave <lb/>symmetry. <lb/>The schematic phase diagram, Fig. 4b, reflects the rela-<lb/>tionship among various phases of CeCoIn and CeRhIn 5 <lb/>and is similar to the T -doping phase diagram of the <lb/>cuprates. This diagram and experimental data from <lb/>which it is inferred indicate that the physics of heavy-<lb/>fermion systems may be more closely related to that of <lb/>the cuprates than previously appreciated. Aside from the <lb/>structural layering in CeCoIn 5 and CeRhIn 5 and their <lb/>relatively high T c &apos;s, they are similar in many respects <lb/>to other Ce-based heavy-fermion materials in which su-<lb/>perconductivity develops near a QCP. Further study <lb/>of CeCoIn , in parallel with the cuprates and other <lb/>pressure-induced heavy-fermion superconductors, holds <lb/>promise for bridging our understanding of the inter-<lb/>relationship between unconventional superconductivity <lb/>and quantum criticality across these interesting classes <lb/>of correlated matter. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank R. Movshovich for helpful discussions. VS <lb/>acknowledges S. M. Stishov for his support during the <lb/>initial stage of this research. Work at Los Alamos was <lb/>performed under the auspices of the US Department of <lb/>Energy. <lb/></div>

			<front>* Permanent address: Institute for High Pressure Physics, <lb/>Russian Academy of Sciences, Troitsk, Russia. <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>[1] J. Orenstein and A. J. Millis, Science 288, 468 (2000); S. <lb/>Sachdev, ibid. 288, 475 (2000). <lb/>[2] A. Y. Chubukov, D. Pines, and J. Schmalian, cond-<lb/>mat/0201140. <lb/>[3] P. W. Anderson, Physica B 318, 28 (2002). <lb/>[4] P. Coleman and C. Pepin, Physica B 312-313, 383 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>[5] P. Monthoux, A. V. Balatsky, and D. Pines, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 67, 3448 (1991). <lb/>[6] C. M. Varma, Z. Nussinov, and W. van Saarloos, Phys. <lb/>Rep. 361, 267 (2002). <lb/>[7] N. D. Mathur et al., Nature 394, 39 (1998). <lb/>[8] T. Timusk and B. Statt, Rep. Prog. Phys. 62, 61 (1999). <lb/>[9] See, for example, C. M. Varma, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 3538 <lb/>(1999); A. Sokol and D. Pines, Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 2813 <lb/>(1993); S. Chakravarty et al., Phys. Rev. B 63, 094503 <lb/>(2001); Ar. Abanov, A.V. Chubukov, and J. Schmalian, <lb/>Europhys. Lett. 55, 369 (2001); and refernces therein. <lb/>[10] C. Petrovic et al., J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 13, L337 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[11] R. Movshovich et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, 5152 (2001). <lb/>[12] K. Izawa et al.,Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 057002 (2001). <lb/>[13] Y. Kohori et al., Phys. Rev. B 64, 134526 (2001). <lb/>[14] H. Hegger et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 84, 4986 (2000). <lb/>[15] R. A. Fisher et al., Phys. Rev. B 65, 224509 (2002). <lb/>[16] M. Nicklas et al., J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 13, L905 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[17] H. Shishido et al., J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 71, 162 (2002). <lb/>[18] L. G. Khvostantsev, V. A. Sidorov, and O. B. Tsiok, <lb/>in: Properties of Earth and Planetary Materials at High <lb/>Pressures and Temperatures, Ed. by M.H. Manghnani <lb/>and T. Yagi, Geophysical Monograph 101, American <lb/>Geophysical Union, 1998, p.89. <lb/>[19] A. Eiling and J. S. Schilling, J. Phys. F: Metal Phys. 11, <lb/>623 (1981). <lb/>[20] R. Movshovich, private communication. <lb/>[21] S. Sachdev, Quantum Phase Transitions (Cambridge <lb/>University Press, Cambridge, 1999). <lb/>[22] E. G. Moshopoulou et al., J. Solid State Chem. 158, 25 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[23] R. Settai et al., J. Phys.: Condens. Matter 13, L627 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>[24] A. Rosch, Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 4280 (1999). <lb/>[25] K. Miyake and O. Narikiyo, J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 71, 867 <lb/>(2002). <lb/>[26] G. Sparn, et al. Physica B 312-313, 138 (2002); E. <lb/>Lengyel et al. High Pressure Res. 22, (2002). In these <lb/>references, for H ≥ Hc2(0) C/T = − ln T persists to <lb/>P = 1.48 GPa, but the rate of divergence decreases with <lb/>increasing P . <lb/>[27] K. Kadowaki and S. B. Woods, Solid State Comm. 58, <lb/>507 (1986). <lb/>[28] S. Kawasaki et al., Phys. Rev. B 65, 020504 (2001). <lb/>[29] There is no obvious evidence for a pseudogap at P = 0 in <lb/>specific heat or magnetic susceptibility data for CeCoIn5, <lb/>possibly because the signature is expected to be weak and <lb/>the temperature range between Tpg and Tc is limited to <lb/>no more than 1.1 K. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
