<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0303278v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 14 Mar 2003 <lb/>APS/123-QED <lb/>Superconductivity of the Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 spin ladder system : Are the <lb/>superconducting pairing and the spin-gap formation of the same origin? <lb/>Naoki Fujiwara, * Nobuo Môri, † and Yoshiya Uwatoko <lb/>Institute for Solid State Physics, University of Tokyo, <lb/>5-1-5 Kashiwanoha, Kashiwa, Chiba 277-8581,Japan <lb/>Takehiko Matsumoto <lb/>National Institute for Materials Science, Tsukuba 305-0047, Japan <lb/>Naoki Motoyama and Shinichi Uchida <lb/>Department of Superconductivity, University of Tokyo, <lb/>7-3-1 Hongo, Bunkyo-ku, Tokyo 113-8656, Japan <lb/>(Dated: July 17 2002) <lb/>Pressure-induced superconductivity in a spin-ladder cuprate Sr2Ca12Cu24O41 has not been studied <lb/>on a microscopic level so far although the superconductivity was already discovered in 1996. We have <lb/>improved high-pressure technique with using a large high-quality crystal, and succeeded in studying <lb/>the superconductivity using Cu nuclear magnetic resonance (NMR). We found that anomalous <lb/>metallic state reflecting the spin-ladder structure is realized and the superconductivity possesses <lb/>a s-wavelike character in the meaning that a finite gap exists in the quasi-particle excitation: At <lb/>pressure of 3.5GPa we observed two excitation modes in the normal state from the relaxation rate <lb/>T −1 <lb/>1 . One gives rise to an activation-type component in T −1 <lb/>1 , and the other T -linear component <lb/>linking directly with the superconductivity. This gapless mode likely arises from free motion of <lb/>holon-spinon bound states appearing by hole doping, and the pairing of them likely causes the <lb/>superconductivity. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25. Ha, 74.72. Jt,74.70. -b <lb/></front>

			<body>Sr 14−x Ca x Cu 24 O 41 (x=11.5-13.5) is a spin-ladder sys-<lb/>tem in which superconducting state is realized by apply-<lb/>ing pressure [1]. The system possesses a structural unit <lb/>of the Cu 2 O 3 two-leg ladder [2], and holes are transferred <lb/>from the CuO chain unit by substituting Ca for Sr. The <lb/>dopant hole density can be controlled over a wide range <lb/>from 0.07 (x=0) to 0.24 (x=14) per ladder Cu [3]. It <lb/>is known from theoretical investigations that the ground <lb/>state of undoped system is a quantum spin liquid and <lb/>this state persists even in highly doped region [4-6]. The <lb/>spin gap has been observed by a number of works in <lb/>the present ladder system. The decrease of the spin gap <lb/>for the Ca substitution was observed in the NMR mea-<lb/>surements [7-9], although no change was observed in the <lb/>neutron scattering [10]. The relationship and interplay <lb/>between the spin gap and the superconductivity in the <lb/>hole-doped ladder system is of central concern [4-6, 11] <lb/>as is the case with high-T c cuprates in underdoped region <lb/>[12]. <lb/>The superconducting state is realized when high pres-<lb/>sure of 3-8GPa is applied for highly doped compounds <lb/>(x≥10) [3]. Pressure plays a role of stabilizing the metal-<lb/>lic state and suppressing anisotropy within the ladder <lb/>plane. In fact, the temperature (T ) dependence of the <lb/>resistivity in the direction perpendicular to the plane ρ c <lb/></body>

			<front> * Email: naokif@issp.u-tokyo.ac.jp <lb/> † Department of Physics, Faculty of Science, Saitama University, <lb/>255 Simookubo, Saitama 338-8581, Japan <lb/></front>

			<body>which is insulating at low pressures turns to be meallic <lb/>as pressure increases [13, 14]. The ratio of the resistiv-<lb/>ities along the rungs and the legs, ρ a /ρ c goes up to 80 <lb/>at ambient pressure, but is reduced below 30 at 3.5GPa <lb/>[13]. <lb/>The superconductivity has been studied on a macro-<lb/>scopic level by the resistivity and AC susceptibility mea-<lb/>surements because these measurements are performable <lb/>with a small amount of sample and cubic-anvil pressure <lb/>cell is available to reach high pressure [1, 13-15]. A <lb/>clamp-type pressure cell is much more convenient and <lb/>available to various methods in which a larger sample <lb/>volume is needed. However, usual clamp-type pressure <lb/>cell is made of CuBe alloy and the maximum pressure is <lb/>3GPa at most. Hence, microscopic study of the super-<lb/>conductivity has not been performed so far although the <lb/>superconductivity was discovered in 1996. Mayaffre et <lb/>al. made NMR measurements under high pressure up to <lb/>3GPa for the field (H) perpendicular to the plane, crystal <lb/>b axis and suggested that the spin gap is suppressed by <lb/>applying pressure [16, 17]. However, the measurements <lb/>were in fact done not in the superconducting state but in <lb/>the normal state above T c . <lb/>In the present work, we have used a clamp-type pres-<lb/>sure cell made of Ni alloy and performed NMR measure-<lb/>ment at pressures more than 3GPa by applying the field <lb/>parallel to the leg direction, crystal c axis. This enabled <lb/>us to study the superconducting state on a microscopic <lb/>level for the first time and to investigate pairing symme-<lb/>try as well as the relation between the spin gap and the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>61.5 <lb/>61.4 <lb/>61.3 <lb/>61.2 <lb/>61.1 <lb/>61.0 <lb/>60.9 <lb/>Frequency (MHz) <lb/>7.0 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>3.5Gpa <lb/>H // c axis <lb/>0T <lb/>5T <lb/>6T <lb/>7T <lb/>12 <lb/>8 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>H(T) <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>T(K) <lb/>FIG. 1: Resonance frequency of a NMR probe attached to a <lb/>pressure cell. The frequency changes at the superconducting <lb/>state. The onset corresponds to the upper critical field. Inset <lb/>shows Hc − Tc curve obtained from the onset of the frequency <lb/>at each field. Solid line is a guide for the eyes. <lb/>superconductivity. <lb/>Single crystal of Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 with a volume of <lb/>4x2x1mm was prepared for the measurements. The <lb/>clamp-type pressure cell with an effective sample space <lb/>of φ4 x 20mm was used for the measurement. The ap-<lb/>pearance of the superconductivity was confirmed by mea-<lb/>suring resonance frequency of a NMR probe attached to <lb/>the pressure cell. The resonance frequency is roughly <lb/>given as f ∝ 1/ <lb/>√ <lb/>LC where L and C represent induc-<lb/>tance and variable capacitance of the NMR probe, re-<lb/>spectively. The sample is contained in a coil and the <lb/>onset of superconductivity is detected by the change of <lb/>the resonant frequency, i.e. the change of L value. This <lb/>method corresponds to AC susceptibility measurement. <lb/>The T dependence of the frequency at several fields is <lb/>shown in Fig. 1. If we probe the temperature at which <lb/>the resonance frequency starts to change against H, this <lb/>gives H c2 vs. T c characteristics as is shown in the inset. <lb/>For high-T c cuprates, the temperature has been identi-<lb/>fied as irreversibility temperature T irr [18]. T irr gives <lb/>a borderline between creeping and freezing of flux lines <lb/>(FL) which are formed through the planes for the H per-<lb/>pendicular to the plane. In the present case flux lines are <lb/>self-trapped between the planes since the field is applied <lb/>parallel to the plane, and thus such a creep is hardly <lb/>expected. <lb/>63 Cu-NMR signals for the ladder site can be separated <lb/>from those for the chain site since nuclei of these sites <lb/>possess different quadrupole coupling [8, 19]. We have <lb/>reported NMR spectra under pressure measured by us-<lb/>ing the present crystal in Ref. 20. The NMR spectra <lb/>at 3.5GPa were almost the same with those at ambient <lb/>pressure. One signal corresponding to the central transi-<lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>10 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>1/T <lb/>1 (sec <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>4 6 8 <lb/>10 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 6 8 <lb/>100 <lb/>2 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>T <lb/>6.2T Tc=2.8K <lb/>5.0T Tc=3.4K <lb/>3.5GPa <lb/>Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 <lb/>H // c axis <lb/>10 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>4 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>FIG. 2: Nuclear ratice relaxation rate 1/T1 for 63 Cu nuclei. <lb/>A solid line shows Korringa relation expressed by Eq. (2). <lb/>1/T1 at low temperatures around Tc is expanded in the inset. <lb/>tion (I= -1/2⇔ 1/2) of 63 Cu nuclei was observed for the <lb/>ladder site and the relaxation rate (T −1 <lb/>1 ) was measured <lb/>at 70.0MHz which corresponds to 6.2T. T c at this field <lb/>is about 2.8K as is seen from the inset of Fig. 1. The T <lb/>dependence of T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>is shown in Fig. 2. The spin gap is <lb/>observed even under high pressure as an activated T de-<lb/>pendence of T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>at temperatures higher than 30K, i.e., <lb/>T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>∝ exp(−∆ spin /T ). <lb/>(1) <lb/>The value of ∆ spin is estimated to be 173K. It should be <lb/>noted that the spin gap is seen in the state in which the <lb/>charge transport is metallic [13]. <lb/>By contrast, T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>below 30K is dominated by a term <lb/>showing T -linear dependence followed by a peak devel-<lb/>oped below T c . The onset and the position of the peak <lb/>shift to higher temperature with decreasing the magnetic <lb/>field to 5.0T (open squares in Fig. 2). If the T -linear <lb/>component originates from extrinsic source, it should be <lb/>persistent in the superconducting state. However, T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>measured at low temperatures obviously goes below the <lb/>T -linear line shown in the figure. Then, such a case is <lb/>excluded. As for the peak the possibility of vortex mo-<lb/>tion might be pointed out. The vortex motion has been <lb/>observed from T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>of ligand sites in high-T c cuprates <lb/>such as YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 [21] or HgBa 2 CuO 4+δ [22] when <lb/>the H is applied perpendicular to the plane. The FL <lb/>is self-trapped between the planes for the H parallel to <lb/>the plane, and thus the effect is hardly expected in the <lb/>present case. In fact, the effect disappears when the H is <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>applied parallel to the planes in HBCO system [22]. Fur-<lb/>thermore, T −1 <lb/>1 /γ 2 <lb/>N (γ N : nuclear gyromagnetic ratio ) at <lb/>the peak is 80 or 25 times larger than those for YBCO <lb/>or HBCO, respectively. The value is too large to explain <lb/>the peak due to vortex motion. Hence, we conclude that <lb/>the peak of T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>and the T -linear component have the <lb/>same origin in the electric state and/or spin fluctuations. <lb/>The peak can be assigned to a superconducting coherence <lb/>peak and the T -linear dependence of T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>to Korringa-<lb/>type behavior, <lb/>T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>∝ bT <lb/>(2) <lb/>where the value of b is about 6.1 (sec −1 K −1 ). The ob-<lb/>servation of the clear peak implies that a finite gap ex-<lb/>ists in the quasi-particle excitation at all wave vectors. <lb/>In the meaning that there exist no nodes in the pairing <lb/>symmetry, the superconductivity possesses a s-wavelike <lb/>character. <lb/>The spin gap is also observed in 63 Cu-NMR shift (K) <lb/>at relevant temperatures. The shift shows H −2 -linear <lb/>dependence because large quadrupole effect acts on 63 Cu <lb/>nuclei. The values free from the quadrupole effect are <lb/>obtained by plotting K vs. H −2 and extrapolating to <lb/>zero field [23]. The values at high temperatures are shown <lb/>in Fig. 3. The shift is given as a sum of two components, <lb/>the orbital and the spin parts (K = K orb + K spin ) and <lb/>the spin part is proportional to the spin susceptibility. <lb/>The T dependence of K at high temperatures fits well <lb/>the theoretical curve for a spin-ladder system [24], <lb/>K(T ) = K 0 + <lb/>K 1 <lb/>√ <lb/>T <lb/>exp(−∆ spin /T ). <lb/>(3) <lb/>The gap ∆ spin obtained from the fit is 217K and is com-<lb/>parable with that estimated from T −1 <lb/>1 . The value of <lb/>K 0 is estimated to be 0.25%. The main contribution <lb/>of K 0 comes from K orb comparable with that for high-<lb/>T c cuprates (K 0 of YBCO, for example, is 0.28% [25].) <lb/>The paramagnetic contribution corresponding to the Ko-<lb/>rringa term in T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>(Eq. (2)) should be included in K 0 . <lb/>The shift in the low temperature region around T c is <lb/>shown in Fig. 4. The raw data at several fields are also <lb/>plotted in the figure since T c depends on the fields. As <lb/>seen from the figure, no appreciable change is seen at T c . <lb/>The paramagnetic contribution in K 0 should be consid-<lb/>erably small so that a change at T c might be difficult to <lb/>detect within the present experimental accuracy. <lb/>We have observed from T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>and K unexpected fea-<lb/>tures in both normal and superconducting states. At <lb/>pressure of 3.5GP we observed two excitation modes in <lb/>the normal metallic state; one gives rise to the gapless T -<lb/>linear component in T −1 <lb/>1 ( T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>∝ bT ) which links directly <lb/>with the superconductivity, and the other the activation-<lb/>type component expressed in Eq. (1). The persistence of <lb/>the spin gap at high pressures suggests that quasi-one-<lb/>dimensional spin-charge dynamics is preserved in the nor-<lb/>mal state although pressure increases coupling or hopping <lb/>between the ladders. In the case of conventional metals <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Shift (%) <lb/>250 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>H // c axis <lb/>3.5GPa <lb/>Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 <lb/>FIG. 3: NMR shift of Cu nuclei for the ladder sites at high <lb/>temperatures. Solid curve represents values calculated by Eq. <lb/>(3) in the text. <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Shift (%) <lb/>4.0 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>3.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>Tc <lb/>70MHz 6.2T <lb/>76MHz 6.7T <lb/>84MHz 7.4T <lb/>Extrapolation <lb/>(H=0T) <lb/>H // c axis <lb/>Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 <lb/>FIG. 4: NMR shift of 63 Cu nuclei for the ladder sites at <lb/>low temperatures around Tc. The raw data which show the <lb/>H −2 -linear dependence due to the quadrupole effect are also <lb/>plotted in the figure. <lb/>the gapless T -linear component arises from paramagnetic <lb/>free electrons, however, such a term is hardly expected in <lb/>the present system unless peculiarity of the ladder struc-<lb/>ture is regarded, because majority of spins falls into the <lb/>spin-singlet state due to the existence of the large spin <lb/>gap ∆ spin at low temperatures. <lb/>Since the system is metallic under high pressure, the <lb/>system should be treated in k space. However, mi-<lb/>croscopic snapshot in real space saves to understand <lb/>the existence of the T -linear component as well as the <lb/>activation-type component. The snapshot in real space <lb/>

			A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>FIG. 5: (A) Illustration of spin and charge configuration at <lb/>high temperatures. Ellipses show spin dimmers on the rung. <lb/>Some of them are in the triplet states at high temperatures. <lb/>Rectangle implies the holon-spinon bound states. They move <lb/>independently in the ladder. (B) Illustration at intermediate <lb/>temperatures. A spin within the holon-spinon bound state is <lb/>free and paramagnetic. Spin dimmers in the ellipses are in <lb/>the singlet state at this temperature region. (C) Illustration <lb/>at the superconducting state. Two spins within the bound <lb/>state form the pairing. <lb/>can be described as follows: The ground state of the un-<lb/>doped ladders is understood as overlap of spin dimmers <lb/>on the rung [4]. Hole doping implies breaking of spin dim-<lb/>mers on the rung and gives rise to holon-spinon bound <lb/>state [26]. At high temperatures singlet-triplet spin ex-<lb/>citation in the spin dimmers away from the bound state <lb/>dominates, which causes the activated behavior of T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>as is illustrated in Figs. 5A. At intermediate tempera-<lb/>tures majority of the spin dimmers falls into the singlet <lb/>ground state, but the spin in the bound states moves <lb/>rather freely and contributes to the gapless T -linear com-<lb/>ponent in T −1 <lb/>1 (Figs. 5B). The superconductivity would <lb/>be realized by the pairing of two bound states as illus-<lb/>trated in Figs. 5C. In this viewpoint, the spin-gap for-<lb/>mation observed from T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>at high temperatures does not <lb/>contribute to the pairing formation of the superconduc-<lb/>tivity. The pairing force is expected to be magnetic since <lb/>the system is a strongly correlated electron system, how-<lb/>ever, we cannot exclude the possibility that conventional <lb/>phonon coupling plays some roles in the pairing. <lb/>Finally, it should be noted that the normal state in the <lb/>present system is free from large antiferromagnetic fluc-<lb/>tuation unlike high-T c cuprates. T −1 <lb/>1 <lb/>in typical high-T c <lb/>cuprates such as YBCO systems is expressed as a + bT <lb/>above T c where T -independent term a represents the an-<lb/>tiferromagnetic fluctuation (a ∼ 3x10 3 (sec −1 ) and b ∼ 6 <lb/>(sec −1 K −1 ) for YBCO) [27]. The antiferromagnetic fluc-<lb/>tuation is extremely suppressed due to the existence of <lb/>the spin gap in the present system, which might explain <lb/>why high T c is not realized in this system although the <lb/>structure is quite similiar to high-T c cuprates. <lb/>In conclusion, we have succeeded in obtaining mi-<lb/>croscopic information of the superconducting state in <lb/>Sr 2 Ca 12 Cu 24 O 41 by applying pressure up to 3.5GPa. In <lb/>this material, we observed two excitation modes in the <lb/>normal state. One gives rises to the activation-type com-<lb/>ponent in T −1 <lb/>1 , the other T -linear component linking di-<lb/>rectly with the superconductivity. The superconductiv-<lb/>ity possesses a s-wavelike character in the meaning that <lb/>a finite gap exists in the quasi-particle excitation. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Authors wish to thank Profs. H. Fukuyama, K. Ya-<lb/>mada, M. Imada and M. Takigawa and Drs. S. Fujimoto, <lb/>H. Kontani, and K. Kojima for fruitful discussion. The <lb/>present work was partially supported by Grant-in-Aid for <lb/>the Ministry of Education, Science and Culture, Japan, <lb/>and by grants of Ogasawara Foundation for the Promo-<lb/>tion of Science and Engineering, Japan and Simadzu Sci-<lb/>ence Foundation, Japan. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] M. Uehara, et al., J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 65, 2764 (1996) <lb/>[2] Z.Hiroi, et al., J. Solid. State. Chem., 95 (1991) <lb/>[3] T. Osafune, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 78 1980 (1997) <lb/>[4] E. Dagotto, J. Riera, and D. Scalapino, Phys. Rev. B45 <lb/>5644 (1992) <lb/>[5] T. M. Rice, S. Gopalan and M. Sigrist, Europhys. Lett. <lb/>23 445 (1993) <lb/>[6] M. Sigrist, T. M. Rice, F. C. Zhang, Phys. Rev. B49 <lb/>(1994) <lb/>[7] K. Kumagai, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 78 1992 (1997) <lb/>[8] K. Magishi, et al., Phys. Rev. B57 11533 (1998) <lb/>[9] T. Imai, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 81 220(1998) <lb/>[10] S. Katano, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 82 636 (1999) <lb/>[11] H. Kontani and K. Ueda, Phys. Rev. Lett. 5619 (1998) <lb/>[12] See for example, H. Yasuoka, et al., Strong Correlation <lb/>and Superconductivity, Springer, Berlin 254(1989): <lb/>Rossat-Mignod,et al., Dynamics of Magnetic fluctuations <lb/>in HighTc materials, Plemum Press, New York, 35 1990 <lb/>[13] T. Nagata, et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 81 1091 (1998) <lb/>[14] N. Motoyama, et al., Phys. Rev. B55 R3386 (1997) <lb/>[15] T. Nakanishi, et al., Physica B281 282 (2000) <lb/>[16] H. Mayaffre,et al., Science 279 (1998) <lb/>[17] Y. Piskunov, et al. has recently extended the work of <lb/>Ref. [16]. They measured NMR under high pressure up to <lb/>3.6GPa for the field parallel to the b axis. Y. Piskunov,et <lb/>al., Eur. Phys. J. B13 417 (2000): Eur. Phys. J. B 24 443 <lb/>(2001) <lb/>[18] A.P.Melozemoff, et al., Phys. Rev. B 7203 (1988) <lb/>[19] M. Takigawa,et al., Phys. Rev. B57 1124 (1998) <lb/>[20] N. Fujiwara,et al., J. Phys. and Chem. Solids B63 1103 <lb/>(2002) <lb/>[21] M. Corti,et al., Phys. Rev. B 9469 (1996) <lb/>[22] B. J. Suh,et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 1928 (1996) <lb/>[23] M. H. Kohen and F. Rief, Solid State Physics 321(1957) <lb/>[24] M. Troyer, et al., Phys. Rev. B50 13515 (1994) <lb/>[25] S. E. Barrett,et al., Phys. Rev. B41 6283 (1990) <lb/>[26] H. Tsunetsugu, et al., Phys. Rev. B49 R16078(1994) <lb/>[27] See for example, D. M. Ginsberg, Physical properties of <lb/>high temperature superconductors II, World Scientific 5 <lb/>269 (1990) </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
