<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0607671v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 26 Jul 2006 <lb/>Role of pair-breaking and phase fluctuations in c-axis tunneling in <lb/>underdoped Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ <lb/>C.J. van der Beek, a P. Spathis, a S. Colson, a P. Gierlowski, b M. Gaifullin, c Yuji Matsuda, d <lb/>P.H. Kes e <lb/>a Laboratoire des Solides Irradiés, Ecole Polytechnique, 91128 Palaiseau, France <lb/>b Institute of Physics of the Polish Academy of Sciences, 32/46 Aleja Lotnikow, 02-668 Warsaw, Poland <lb/>c National Institute for Material Science, 1-2-1, Sengen, Ibaraki, Tsukuba, Japan <lb/>d Department of Physics, Kyoto University, Sakyo-ku, Kyoto 606-8502, Japan <lb/>e Kamerlingh Onnes Laboratorium, Rijksuniversiteit Leiden, P.O. Box 9506, 2300 RA Leiden, The Netherlands <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The Josephson Plasma Resonance is used to study the c-axis supercurrent in the superconducting state of under-<lb/>doped Bi2Sr2CaCu2O 8+δ with varying degrees of controlled point-like disorder, introduced by high-energy electron <lb/>irradiation. As disorder is increased, the Josephson Plasma frequency decreases proportionally to the critical tem-<lb/>perature. The temperature dependence of the plasma frequency does not depend on the irradiation dose, and is in <lb/>quantitative agreement with a model for quantum fluctuations of the superconducting phase in the CuO2 layers. <lb/>Key words: Disorder, Interlayer coupling, Josephson Plasma Resonance, Quantum fluctuations <lb/>PACS: 74.40.+k, 74.50.+r, 74.62.-c, 74.62.Dh <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>From the d-wave symmetry of the order pa-<lb/>rameter of cuprate superconductors, one expects <lb/>an enhanced sensitivity of c-axis transport in the <lb/>superconducting state to disorder, due to the en-<lb/>hancement of the quasiparticle density of states <lb/>along the gap node directions, and due to impurity <lb/>assisted hopping [1]. Both mechanisms lead to as yet <lb/>unobserved T 2 -dependences of the c-axis superfluid <lb/>density ρ c <lb/>s at low T , with coefficients that strongly <lb/>depend on the scattering rate Γ. On the other hand, <lb/>underdoped cuprates are sufficiently disordered <lb/>for (quantum) fluctuations of the order parameter <lb/>phase to play a prominent role [2], leading to a T -<lb/>linear behavior of ρ c <lb/>s . Here, we report on the effect <lb/>of controlled point disorder on interlayer tunneling <lb/>of Cooper pairs in underdoped Bi Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ . <lb/>2. Experimental details <lb/>Single-crystalline <lb/>rods <lb/>of <lb/>underdoped <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ were grown using the travel-<lb/>ling solvent floating zone technique under 25 mBar <lb/>oxygen partial pressure [3]. The samples used for <lb/>the study, with T c ≈ K, were cleaved from the <lb/>same crystalline piece. The crystals were then ir-<lb/>radiated with 2.5 MeV electrons using the van der <lb/>Graaf accelerator of the Laboratoire des Solides <lb/>Irradiés. The irradiation produces homogeneously <lb/>distributed Frenkel pairs, which have previously <lb/>been identified as strong scattering centers [4]. <lb/>The Josephson Plasma Resonance (JPR) fre-<lb/>quency f JP R of the crystals was then measured <lb/>using the cavity perturbation technique, exploiting <lb/>T M 01n harmonic modes to access different frequen-<lb/>cies [6], and the bolometric technique using a waveg-<lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Preprint submitted to Elsevier Science <lb/>7 July 2018 <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>× 10 <lb/>18 e <lb/>-cm <lb/>-2 <lb/>6 × 10 <lb/>19 e <lb/>-cm <lb/>-2 <lb/>7.7 × 10 <lb/>18 e <lb/>-cm <lb/>-2 <lb/>5.3 × 10 <lb/>17 e <lb/>-cm <lb/>-2 <lb/>unirradiated <lb/>f <lb/>JPR <lb/>(T)/f <lb/>JPR <lb/>(0) <lb/>T / T c <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>f <lb/>JPR <lb/>2 <lb/>(0) ( GHz 2 <lb/>) <lb/>T c ( K ) <lb/>(a) <lb/>Fig. <lb/>1. <lb/>JPR <lb/>frequency <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>e − -irradiated <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ crystals, normalized to the JPR fre-<lb/>quency at T → 0, versus reduced temperature. <lb/>uide in the T E 01 travelling wave mode [5]. The <lb/>latter technique allows for swept-frequency mea-<lb/>surements, necessary to elucidate the weak f JP R (T ) <lb/>dependence at low T [5]. Note that f 2 <lb/>JP R is propor-<lb/>tional to the c-axis critical current j c <lb/>c and to the <lb/>c-axis superfluid density: f 2 <lb/>JP R = j c <lb/>c s/2πǫ 0 ǫ r Φ 0 = <lb/>c 2 /4π 2 ǫ r λ 2 <lb/>c ∝ ρ c <lb/>s , with ǫ r the low-frequency dielec-<lb/>tric constant and λ c is the c-axis penetration depth. <lb/>3. Results and Discussion <lb/>Sharp JPR resonant peaks were measured for all <lb/>samples under study. Both T c and f JP R (T → 0) <lb/>decrease with irradiation dose. The sensitivity of <lb/>f JP R to even weak additional disorder contradicts <lb/>the model of coherent interlayer Cooper pair tun-<lb/>neling [7]. Within the framework of a d-wave BCS <lb/>model, the measured proportionality between f <lb/>JP R <lb/>and T c can be understood as resulting either from <lb/>(i) the dependence of the interlayer Josephson cur-<lb/>rent j c <lb/>c ∝ ∆σ qp on the gap magnitude ∆ and the <lb/>quasiparticle conductivity σ qp [8], or (ii) from the <lb/>decrease of the in-plane superfluid density due to <lb/>strong phase fluctuations. <lb/>The origin of the temperature and disorder-<lb/>dependence of f JP R can be pinpointed using <lb/>Fig. 1(b). Normalising all results to f JP R (T → 0) <lb/>and plotting these versus reduced temperature, re-<lb/>veals a common T -dependence independent of disor-<lb/>der. This contradicts the prediction of Ref. [1] that <lb/>ρ s should follow different powers of T depending on <lb/>the ratio of T , ∆, and Γ. However, it agrees with a <lb/>dominant role of quantum phase fluctuations. Then, <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>Eq. (1) <lb/>5.3×10 17 e -cm -2 <lb/>3×10 18 e -cm -2 <lb/>7.7×10 18 e -cm -2 <lb/>6×10 19 e -cm -2 <lb/>f <lb/>JPR <lb/>2 <lb/>(T) <lb/>λ <lb/>c <lb/>2 <lb/>(0) <lb/>f <lb/>JPR <lb/>2 <lb/>(0) <lb/>λ <lb/>c <lb/>2 <lb/>(T) <lb/>1 -<lb/>~ 1 -<lb/>T / T c <lb/>f JPR <lb/>2 <lb/>(T) <lb/>4α k <lb/>B <lb/>T <lb/>2 C 2 <lb/>σ k B <lb/>T <lb/>f JPR <lb/>2 (0) <lb/>σ ε 0 <lb/>s <lb/>3 <lb/>ε 0 <lb/>s <lb/>= 1 -( ) -<lb/>( ) 2 <lb/>ε 0 s/ k B = 400 K (Ref. [3]) <lb/>α = 0.5 [ Jacobs et al., PRL 75, 4516 (1995)] <lb/>σ = σs = 3.7 e 2 /h i.e. ρ = 1 mΩcm <lb/>C 2 = 10 <lb/>Fig. <lb/>2. <lb/>JPR <lb/>frequency <lb/>of <lb/>the <lb/>e − -irradiated <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ crystals, plotted as 1−f 2 <lb/>J P R (T )/f 2 <lb/>J P R (0) <lb/>in order to bring out the low temperature T -dependence. <lb/>The line is a fit to Eq. 1 [9] with parameters as indicated. <lb/>f <lb/>JP R (T ) <lb/>f 2 <lb/>JP R (0) <lb/>≈ 1 − <lb/>4αk B T <lb/>ε 0 sσ <lb/>− C 2 <lb/>2σ <lb/>3 <lb/>k B T <lb/>ε 0 s <lb/>2 <lb/>(1) <lb/>where α = (∂ε 0 s/∂T ) T →0 , ε 0 = Φ 0 /4πµ 0 λ 2 <lb/>ab with <lb/>λ ab the in-plane penetration depth, s is the CuO 2 <lb/>layer spacing, and σ = σs is the CuO plane sheet <lb/>conductivity [9]. The temperature dependence of the <lb/>JPR frequency arises from the temperature of the in-<lb/>plane phase stiffness ε 0 . Figure 2 shows that Eq. (1) <lb/>describes the results very satisfactorily. <lb/>Summarizing, the temperature-and disorder de-<lb/>pendence of the c-axis Cooper pair tunnel current <lb/>in underdoped Bi Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ is well described <lb/>assuming a strong effect of quantum phase fluctua-<lb/>tions. A d-wave model without fluctuations cannot <lb/>account for the T -dependence of c-axis coupling. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] T. Xiang and J.M. Wheatley, Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 4632 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[2] L.B. Ioffe and A. Millis, Science 285, 1241 (1999). <lb/>[3] Ming Li et al. Phys. Rev. B 66, 024502 (2002). <lb/>[4] F. Rullier-Albenque et al., Europhys. Lett. 50, 81 <lb/>(2000). <lb/>[5] M.B. Gaifullin et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 3928 (1999). <lb/>[6] S. Colson et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 137002 (2003). <lb/>[7] Yu. Latyshev et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 5345 (1999). <lb/>[8] Y. Sun and K. Maki, Phys. Rev. B 51, 6059 (1995). <lb/>[9] A. Paramekanti, Phys. Rev. B 65, 104521 (2002). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
