<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0404196v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 8 Apr 2004 <lb/>&quot;Spin-Flop&quot; Transition and Anisotropic Magnetoresistance in Pr 1.3−x La 0.7 Ce x CuO 4 : <lb/>Unexpectedly Strong Spin-Charge Coupling in Electron-Doped Cuprates <lb/>A. N. Lavrov, 1 H. J. Kang, 2, 3 Y. Kurita, 1, * T. Suzuki, 1, * Seiki Komiya, <lb/>J. W. Lynn, S.-H. Lee, 4 Pengcheng Dai, 2, 3, † and Yoichi Ando 1, ‡ <lb/>1 Central Research Institute of Electric Power Industry, Komae, Tokyo 201-8511, Japan <lb/>2 Department of Physics and Astronomy, The University of Tennessee, Knoxville, Tennessee 37996-1200, USA <lb/>3 Condensed Matter Sciences Division, Oak Ridge National Laboratory, Oak Ridge, Tennessee 37831-6393, USA <lb/>4 NIST Center for Neutron Research, National Institute of Standards and Technology, Gaithersburg, Maryland 20899, USA <lb/>(Dated: November 5, 2018) <lb/>We use transport and neutron-scattering measurements to show that a magnetic-field-induced <lb/>transition from noncollinear to collinear spin arrangement in adjacent CuO2 planes of lightly <lb/>electron-doped Pr1.3−xLa0.7CexCuO4 (x = 0.01) crystals affects significantly both the in-plane <lb/>and out-of-plane resistivity. In the high-field collinear state, the magnetoresistance (MR) does not <lb/>saturate, but exhibits an intriguing four-fold-symmetric angular dependence, oscillating from being <lb/>positive at B [100] to being negative at B [110]. The observed MR of more than 30% at low tem-<lb/>peratures induced by a modest modification of the spin structure indicates an unexpectedly strong <lb/>spin-charge coupling in electron-doped cuprates. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25.Fy, 75.25.+z, 74.20.Mn, 74.72.Jt <lb/></front>

			<body>High-T c superconductivity (SC) in cuprates emerges <lb/>as the parent antiferromagnetic (AF) insulator is doped <lb/>with charge carriers, either holes or electrons. Despite <lb/>this apparent symmetry with respect to doping, it still <lb/>remains unclear whether the mechanism of SC in both <lb/>cases is the same. It is generally believed that in the <lb/>hole-doped cuprates, the SC pairing originates from an <lb/>interplay between the doped holes and AF spin correla-<lb/>tions. Indeed, many observations, including a fast sup-<lb/>pression of the Néel order by doped holes [1] which results <lb/>in the &quot;spin-glass&quot; state [1, 2, 3], and a strong tendency to <lb/>form spin-charge textures -&quot;stripes&quot; [4], point to a very <lb/>strong coupling between the charge and spin degrees of <lb/>freedom. <lb/>The behavior of doped electrons looks, however, much <lb/>different. Electron doping suppresses the AF order at vir-<lb/>tually the same slow rate as the substitution of magnetic <lb/>Cu 2+ ions with non-magnetic Zn 2+ [5, 6], and does not <lb/>induce any incommensurability in the spin correlations <lb/>[7]. This has been taken as evidence that the electrons <lb/>merely dilute the spin system [1, 5, 6]. Apparently, if the <lb/>charge transport and spin correlations are actually de-<lb/>coupled in the electron-doped cuprates, the SC pairing <lb/>should have a non-magnetic origin as well. A recent dis-<lb/>covery of the magnetic-field induced AF order in super-<lb/>conducting Nd 2−x Ce x CuO 4 [8, 9] has shown, however, <lb/>that antiferromagnetism and superconductivity may be <lb/>closely related in these compounds. <lb/>To probe the spin-charge coupling, one can determine <lb/>how the charge transport responds to such relatively <lb/>weak changes in the spin structure as spin-flop or meta-<lb/>magnetic transitions. In hole-doped La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 , <lb/>for instance, the conductivity changes by up to several <lb/>times [10, 11]. In this Letter, we use neutron scat-<lb/>tering and magnetoresistance (MR) measurements to <lb/>study the effect of magnetic field on the spin structure <lb/>and anisotropic conductivity of lightly electron-doped <lb/>Pr 1.3−x La 0.7 Ce x CuO 4 (PLCCO) single crystals. We find <lb/>that both the in-plane and out-of-plane resistivity (ρ ab <lb/>and ρ c ) are surprisingly sensitive to spin reorientation, <lb/>with ∆ρ ab /ρ ab exceeding 30% at low temperatures -the <lb/>same scale as in hole-doped La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 [11]. This re-<lb/>sult indicates that in electron-doped cuprates the charge <lb/>transport exhibits a similar degree of coupling to mag-<lb/>netism as in the hole-doped ones, and therefore the su-<lb/>perconductivity in both systems may have a universal <lb/>origin. <lb/>High-quality PLCCO single crystals with x = 0.01 <lb/>(mosaicity &lt; 1 • ) were grown by the traveling-solvent <lb/>floating-zone technique and annealed at ≈ 860 • C in <lb/>pure argon to remove excess oxygen. The partial sub-<lb/>stitution of Pr with La was used to stabilize the crys-<lb/>tal growth, without introducing significant lattice distor-<lb/>tions [12]. Neutron scattering measurements were per-<lb/>formed on the BT-2 and SPINS triple-axis spectrome-<lb/>ters at the NIST Center for Neutron Research. We la-<lb/>bel wavevectors Q = (q x , q y , q z ) inÅ −1 as (H, K, L) = <lb/>(q x a/2π, q y a/2π, q z c/2π) in the reciprocal lattice units <lb/>(r.l.u.) suitable for the tetragonal unit cell of PLCCO <lb/>(space group I4/mmm, a = 3.964 and c = 12.28Å <lb/>are in-plane and out-of-plane lattice paramters, respec-<lb/>tively). In this notation, [100]/[010] and [110]/[110] are <lb/>along the Cu-O-Cu bond direction and the diagonal Cu-<lb/>Cu direction, respectively. The experimental details are <lb/>described in Refs. [8, 9]. <lb/>Resistivity measurements were carried out by the ac <lb/>four-probe method on the same crystal used for neu-<lb/>tron measurements. It was cut and polished into suitable <lb/>shapes: 3.1 × 1 × 0.45 mm 3 for ρ ab and ≈ 1 × 1 × 1 mm 3 <lb/>for ρ c . The MR was measured by sweeping the magnetic <lb/>

            FIG. 1: Field-induced transition from noncollinear to col-<lb/>linear spin arrangement in Pr2CuO4. (a) Zero-filed non-<lb/>collinear spin structure; only Cu spins are shown. (b) -(c) <lb/>Collinear spin-flop states induced by (b) a magnetic field ap-<lb/>plied along the Cu-Cu direction; (c) a magnetic field tilted <lb/>from [010]; and (d) B [010]. <lb/>field between ±14 T at fixed temperatures stabilized by <lb/>a capacitance sensor with an accuracy of ∼ 1 mK. <lb/>The peculiar spin structure of Pr 2 CuO 4 (PCO) is in-<lb/>teresting in its own right. While a strong intraplane ex-<lb/>change drives the AF spin ordering within CuO 2 planes, <lb/>all the isotropic exchange interactions between the planes <lb/>are perfectly canceled out due to the body-centered <lb/>tetragonal crystal symmetry. The three-dimensional or-<lb/>dering [Fig. 1(a)] that sets in below the Néel temperature <lb/>T N = 250 − 285 K [13, 14, 16] is governed by weak pseu-<lb/>dodipolar (PD) interactions, which favor a noncollinear <lb/>orientation of spins in adjacent planes (alternating along <lb/>the [100] and [010] directions) [13, 14, 15, 16]. A unique <lb/>feature of the interplane PD interaction is that its energy <lb/>does not change if the spin sublattices of adjacent CuO <lb/>50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>Pr 1.3-x La 0.7 Ce x CuO 4 <lb/>x = 0.01 <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 1) <lb/>(a) <lb/>M Cu <lb/>M Pr <lb/>Moment (arb. units) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 3) <lb/>Intensity (counts/15 sec) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>FIG. 2: (a) Temperature dependence of the Cu 2+ and Pr 3+ <lb/>moments in PLCCO (x = 0.01). (b) Integrated intensity <lb/>of the ( 1 <lb/>2 , 1 <lb/>2 , 1) and ( 1 <lb/>2 , 1 <lb/>2 , 3) magnetic peaks. The ordered <lb/>moments are estimated by normalizing the magnetic intensity <lb/>to the weak (1,1,0) nuclear Bragg peak without considering <lb/>the absorption and extinction effects [9]. The solid lines are <lb/>power-law fits describing the contribution of Cu spins [13]. <lb/>0.96 0.98 1.00 1.02 1.04 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>1.92 1.96 2.00 2.04 2.08 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>_ <lb/>T = 5 K <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 1) <lb/>(a) <lb/>B = <lb/>0.5 T <lb/>1.0 T <lb/>1.5 T <lb/>2.0 T <lb/>2.5 T <lb/>3.0 T <lb/>4.0 T <lb/>5.0 T <lb/>7.0 T <lb/>B // [110] <lb/>Intensity (10 <lb/>3 <lb/>counts/10 sec) <lb/>H (r.l.u.) <lb/>(c) <lb/>T = <lb/>K <lb/>30 K <lb/>41 K <lb/>56 K <lb/>75 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>150 K <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 1) <lb/>Intensity (counts/10 sec) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 2) <lb/>H (r.l.u.) <lb/>(d) (1/2, 1/2, 2) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>FIG. 3: (a), (b) Effect of the B [110] field on ( <lb/>2 , 1 <lb/>2 , 1) and <lb/>( 1 <lb/>2 , 1 <lb/>2 , 2) magnetic peaks at 5 K. (c), (d) Field dependence <lb/>of the integrated intensity at various temperatures. We note <lb/>that the critical field for spin-flop transition in PLCCO is <lb/>lower than that of PCO [13]. <lb/>planes rotate in opposite directions [14, 15, 16]. Such a <lb/>continuous spin rotation can be induced by a magnetic <lb/>field parallel to Cu-Cu direction, which easily converts <lb/>the noncollinear structure of Fig. 1(a) into a collinear <lb/>one with spins along the [110] direction [Fig. 1(b)]. Note <lb/>that while these diagonal directions are hard spin axes in <lb/>the non-collinear phase, they become the easy axes in the <lb/>collinear one. A perfectly aligned field B [010] causes a <lb/>first-order transition directly to the spin-flop phase [Fig. <lb/>1(d)], while at intermediate field directions the magnetic <lb/>field first induces a transition into the collinear phase <lb/>[Fig. 1(c)], and then smoothly rotates the spins to align <lb/>them perpendicular to the field [16]. <lb/>The neutron diffraction measurements at zero field on <lb/>the (1/2, 1/2, L) magnetic Bragg peaks (L = 0, 1, 2, 3, 4) <lb/>show that in our PLCCO (x = 0.01) the Cu 2+ spins <lb/>order into the same non-collinear structure as in pure <lb/>PCO, albeit at a somewhat lower T N ≈ 229 K (Fig. 2). <lb/>The reduced T N is probably due to a partial substitution <lb/>of Pr 3+ with non-magnetic La 3+ , as well as to doped <lb/>electrons. Similar to PCO [13], the Pr 3+ ions in PLCCO <lb/>can be polarized by the ordered Cu 2+ moment. Upon <lb/>cooling below 100-150 K, the exchange field of the Cu 2+ <lb/>spins induces a small (up to ∼ 0.1 µ B ) ordered moment <lb/>

            0 50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>-15 -10 -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>-15 -10 -5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>ρ <lb/>c (Ωcm) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>ρ ab <lb/>ρ c <lb/>(a) <lb/>ρ <lb/>ab (mΩcm) <lb/>(b) <lb/>10 K <lb/>20 K <lb/>T = 5 K <lb/>74 K <lb/>30 K <lb/>Pr 1.3-x La 0.7 Ce x CuO 4 <lb/>x = 0.01 <lb/>B // Cu-Cu <lb/>40 K <lb/>∆ρ <lb/>c <lb/>/ρ <lb/>c (%) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>55 K <lb/>(c) <lb/>K <lb/>55 K <lb/>40 K <lb/>30 K <lb/>20 K <lb/>10 K <lb/>T = 5 K <lb/>B// Cu-Cu <lb/>∆ρ <lb/>ab <lb/>/ρ <lb/>ab (%) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>40 K 55 K 74 K <lb/>FIG. 4: (a) In-plane and out-of-plane resistivity of PLCCO (x = 0.01) single crystals. The MR in ρc (b) and ρ ab (c) measured <lb/>for the in-plane magnetic field B [110]. <lb/>on the Pr 3+ ions (Fig. 2). <lb/>Figure 3 shows the effect of a B [110] field on the <lb/>(1/2, 1/2, 1) and (1/2, 1/2, 2) magnetic peaks at vari-<lb/>ous temperatures. Upon increasing the magnetic field, <lb/>the peak intensity changes, indicating a continuous non-<lb/>collinear to collinear phase transition. Indeed, for the <lb/>collinear spin arrangement [Fig. 1(b)], the magnetic in-<lb/>tensity vanishes at (1/2, 1/2, L) with L = 1, 3, 5. As can <lb/>be seen in Figs. 3(c) and 3(d), the critical field for the <lb/>non-collinear to collinear (&quot;spin-flop&quot;) transition, B c , in-<lb/>creases from less than 0.5 T at 150 K to ∼2 T at 5 <lb/>K. In comparison, the first-order spin-flop transition for <lb/>B [010] was reported to take place at several time larger <lb/>fields [16] and a c-axis aligned field does not change the <lb/>noncollinear spin structure [9]. <lb/>The transport properties of lightly electron-doped <lb/>PLCCO differ from those of its hole-doped analog LSCO <lb/>or YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6+x (YBCO). In contrast to hole-doped <lb/>cuprates [11, 17, 18], the doping of 1% of electrons into <lb/>the CuO 2 planes appears to be insufficient to induce <lb/>metallic in-plane conduction in PLCCO, and both ρ ab <lb/>and ρ c grow upon cooling below room temperature [Fig. <lb/>4(a)]. It is worth noting also that lightly doped PLCCO <lb/>turns out to be one of the most anisotropic cuprates with <lb/>ρ c /ρ ab ∼ 8000 at room temperature -an order of mag-<lb/>nitude larger than in LSCO and YBCO [11, 18]. <lb/>In further contrast to hole-doped cuprates [11, 18], no <lb/>anomaly is detected at the Néel transition in PLCCO ei-<lb/>ther in the in-plane or out-of-plane resistivity. At a first <lb/>glance, this supports the view that the charge motion in <lb/>electron-doped PLCCO is virtually decoupled from spin <lb/>correlations, and one therefore would expect the conduc-<lb/>tivity to ignore the spin reorientation sketched in Fig. <lb/>1. Surprisingly, the experiment shows that this is not <lb/>the case, and instead of being field-independent, both <lb/>ρ ab and ρ c exhibit a considerable increase upon transi-<lb/>tion into the collinear state [Figs. 4(b) and 4(c)]. We <lb/>have confirmed that this MR is of the spin origin and <lb/>contains no orbital terms, since no difference was ob-<lb/>served in ∆ρ ab /ρ ab for fields applied parallel or perpen-<lb/>dicular to the current. Moreover, ∆ρ ab /ρ ab and ∆ρ c /ρ c <lb/>demonstrate a remarkable similarity both in magnitude <lb/>and in field dependence, in spite of the huge resistivity <lb/>anisotropy. Finally, no MR anomaly is observed when a <lb/>c-axis aligned field is applied, consistent with the absence <lb/>of a spin-flop transition for such field orientation [9]. <lb/>The MR behavior in Fig. 4 is clearly reminiscent of <lb/>that in LSCO [11], though there are two important dif-<lb/>ferences. First is the sign of the anomalous MR, which is <lb/>always positive in PLCCO, but negative in LSCO. Sec-<lb/>ond, the MR features in LSCO and YBCO become dis-<lb/>cernible as soon as the AF order is established, but in <lb/>PLCCO they appear at temperatures much lower that <lb/>T N (at T &lt; 70 − 100 K), and quickly gain strength upon <lb/>decreasing temperature (Fig. 4). The latter indicates <lb/>that some other factors, such as magnetic moments of <lb/>Pr 3+ or a structural instability [19], that come into play <lb/>at low temperature, may be relevant to the observed MR. <lb/>A comparison of the neutron and resistivity data re-<lb/>veals one more interesting feature, namely, the transi-<lb/>tions observed by these two probes do not match each <lb/>other [inset to Fig. 5(a)]. One can see that the charge <lb/>transport ignores the initial spin rotation, and the steep-<lb/>est resistivity variation is observed at B c , where the <lb/>collinear structure is established. Although B c changes <lb/>substantially with temperature [Fig. 5(a)], the apparent <lb/>shift in the transitions holds consistently, with the peak <lb/>in dρ/dB roughly coinciding with the end of the transi-<lb/>tion observed by neutron scattering. <lb/>As the magnetic field deviates from the Cu-Cu direc-<lb/>tion [Fig. 1(c)], the spin-flop transition shifts towards <lb/>higher fields, reaching ultimately B c ∼ 12 T for B [010]; <lb/>the MR behavior for these two field orientations is com-<lb/>pared in Figs. 5(b) and 5(c) [20]. It becomes immediately <lb/>clear from these figures that the step-like increase of the <lb/>resistivity upon the transition to the collinear state does <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>-12 -8 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>-12 -8 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>12 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>(a) <lb/>ρ ab <lb/>ρ c <lb/>B // Cu-Cu <lb/>B <lb/>c (T) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>* <lb/>B c <lb/>* <lb/>B c <lb/>(b) <lb/>B // Cu-O-Cu <lb/>T = 5 K <lb/>∆ρ <lb/>ab <lb/>/ρ <lb/>ab (%) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>* <lb/>B c <lb/>(c) <lb/>T=T <lb/>B // Cu-O-Cu <lb/>B // Cu-Cu <lb/>B // Cu-Cu <lb/>T = 5 K <lb/>∆ρ <lb/>c <lb/>/ρ <lb/>c (%) <lb/>B (T) <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>90 <lb/>120 <lb/>150 <lb/>180 <lb/>210 <lb/>240 270 <lb/>300 <lb/>330 <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>T = 30 K <lb/>∆ρ <lb/>c , <lb/>∆I <lb/>B (T) <lb/>FIG. 5: (a) The critical field Bc determined from peaks in dρ ab /dB and dρc/dB for B [110]. In the inset to (a), the <lb/>normalized field dependence of ρc (•) is compared with that of the ( 1 <lb/>2 , 1 <lb/>2 , 1)-peak intensity (•). ∆ρ ab /ρ ab (b) and ∆ρc/ρc (c) <lb/>for two directions of the in-plane magnetic field. The angular dependence of the high-field MR is sketched in the inset to (c). <lb/>not make a complete story. Regardless of the field direc-<lb/>tion within the ab plane, the resistivity exhibits roughly <lb/>the same increase at the spin-flop transition, but then (at <lb/>B &gt; B * <lb/>c ) it keeps changing without any sign of satura-<lb/>tion [Figs. 5(b) and 5(c)]. Even more surprising is that <lb/>this high-field MR changes its sign depending on the field <lb/>direction, as is schematically drawn in the inset to Fig. <lb/>5(c). One can conceive a spin structure upon rotating <lb/>the high magnetic field within the ab plane in the follow-<lb/>ing way: the spins always keep the collinear arrangement <lb/>and rotate as a whole, being almost perpendicular to the <lb/>magnetic field (Fig. 1). Our data show that the resistiv-<lb/>ity goes down as the spin direction approaches one of the <lb/>two equivalent spin easy axes (Cu-Cu directions) and in-<lb/>creases at the spin hard axes (Cu-O-Cu directions) [inset <lb/>to Fig. 5(c)]. Note that the resistivity changes are rather <lb/>large, ∆ρ ab /ρ ab reaches ≈ 18% at T = 5 K and exceeds <lb/>32% at 2.5 K, indicating that the magnetic field B [100] <lb/>can effectively localize the doped electrons. <lb/>Apparently, the fascinating MR oscillations in Fig. 5 <lb/>cannot originate from simple &quot;spin-valve&quot; effects, since <lb/>at high fields the spin structure always stays collinear, <lb/>and all that changes is the relative orientation of spins <lb/>with respect to the crystal axes. The MR may be related <lb/>to 2D spin fluctuations that were found to survive far <lb/>above B c , as manifested in the diffuse neutron scattering <lb/>[21], or to some unusual coupling of the charge trans-<lb/>port with low-energy spin dynamics. Though the exact <lb/>mechanism of the revealed MR features still remains to <lb/>be understood, what is certain is that the charge carriers <lb/>in electron-doped cuprates appear to have a remarkably <lb/>strong coupling with the spin order, which should play an <lb/>important role in determining their physical properties. <lb/>Upon preparing this paper, we became aware of similar <lb/>MR features observed for Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 4 [22], which <lb/>gives evidence that the strong spin-charge coupling sur-<lb/>vives up to much higher electron-doping levels, that are <lb/>relevant for the superconducting state. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank K. Segawa and Shiliang Li for technical as-<lb/>sistance. This work was in part supported by the US <lb/>NSF DMR-0139882 and DOE under contract No. DE-<lb/>AC-00OR22725 with UT/Battelle, LLC. <lb/></div>

			<front> * Also at Department of Physics, Tokyo University of Sci-<lb/>ence, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 162-8601, Japan. <lb/> † Electronic address: daip@ornl.gov <lb/> ‡ Electronic address: ando@criepi.denken.or.jp <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>[1] M. A. Kastner, R. J. Birgeneau, G. Shirane, and Y. En-<lb/>doh, Rev. Mod. Phys. 70, 897 (1998). <lb/>[2] Ch. Niedermayer et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 3843 (1998). <lb/>[3] A. N. Lavrov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 017007 (2001). <lb/>[4] J. M. Tranquada et al., Nature 375, 561 (1995). <lb/>[5] B. Keimer et al., Phys. Rev. B 45, 7430 (1992). <lb/>[6] G. M. Luke et al., Phys. Rev. B 42, 7981 (1990). <lb/>[7] K. Yamada et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 137004 (2003). <lb/>[8] H. J. Kang et al., Nature 423, 522 (2003). <lb/>[9] M. Matsuura et al., Phys. Rev. B 68, 144503 (2003). <lb/>[10] T. Thio et al., Phys. Rev. B 38, 905 (1988). <lb/>[11] Y. Ando et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 90, 247003 (2003). <lb/>[12] M. Fujita et al., Phys. Rev. B 67, 014514 (2003). <lb/>[13] I. W. Sumarlin et al., Phys. Rev. B 51, 5824 (1995). <lb/>[14] D. Petitgrand et al., Phys. Rev. B 59, 1079 (1999). <lb/>[15] R. Sachidanandam et al., Phys. Rev. B 56, 260 (1997). <lb/>[16] V. P. Plakhty et al., Europhys. Lett. 61, 534 (2003). <lb/>[17] Y. Ando et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 87, 017001 (2001). <lb/>[18] A. N. Lavrov et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 83 (1999) 1419. <lb/>[19] V. P. Plakhty et al., Solid State Commun. 103, 683 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>[20] For the case of B [010], the transition field is extremely <lb/>sensitive to the crystal alignment; just a few degrees tilt-<lb/>ing of the ρ ab sample in Fig. 5(b) notably shifted the tran-<lb/>sition to low fields, as compared with the better aligned <lb/>ρc sample in Fig. 5(c). <lb/>[21] D. Petigrand et al., App. Phys. A. 74, S853 (2002). <lb/>[22] P. Fournier et al., cond-mat/0309144. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
