<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:0708.0921v2 [cond-mat.supr-con] 8 May 2008 <lb/>Evidence for gap anisotropy in CaC 6 from directional point-contact spectroscopy <lb/>R.S. Gonnelli, 1 D. Daghero, 1 D. Delaude, 1 M. Tortello, 1 G.A. Ummarino, <lb/>V.A. Stepanov, 2 J.S. Kim, 3 R.K. Kremer, 3 A. Sanna, 4 G. Profeta, 5 and S. Massidda <lb/>1 Dipartimento di Fisica and CNISM, Politecnico di Torino, 10129 Torino, Italy <lb/>2 P.N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, 119991 Moscow, Russia <lb/>3 Max-Planck-Institut für Festkörperforschung, D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany <lb/>4 Institut für Theoretische Physik, Freie Universität Berlin, Arnimallee 14, D-14195 Berlin, Germany <lb/>5 CNISM -Dipartimento di Fisica, Università degli studi dell&apos;Aquila, Italy <lb/>6 SLACS-INFM/CNR and Dipartimento di Fisica, Università degli Studi di Cagliari, Italy <lb/>We present the first results of directional point-contact spectroscopy in high quality CaC6 samples <lb/>both along the ab plane and in the c-axis direction. The superconducting order parameter ∆(0), <lb/>obtained by fitting the Andreev-reflection (AR) conductance curves at temperatures down to 400 <lb/>mK with the single-band 3D Blonder-Tinkham-Klapwijk model, presents two different distributions <lb/>in the two directions of the main current injection, peaked at 1.35 and 1.71 meV, respectively. By <lb/>ab-initio calculations of the AR conductance spectra, we show that the experimental results are in <lb/>good agreement with the recent predictions of gap anisotropy in CaC6. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.50.+r, 74.45.+c, 74.70.Ad <lb/></front>

			<body>The discovery of a relatively &quot;high-T c &quot; superconduc-<lb/>tivity in graphite intercalated with Ca [1, 2], Yb [1] and, <lb/>very recently, Sr [3, 4] has strongly revived the inter-<lb/>est in the Graphite Intercalated Compounds (GICs) and <lb/>their physics. The Ca-intercalated graphite, CaC 6 , with <lb/>its &quot;record&quot; T c of about 11.5 K, in particular, has been <lb/>the subject of various theoretical and experimental in-<lb/>vestigations in the past two years (for a short review of <lb/>the initial results see [5]). One of the most important <lb/>questions, however, is still not clear: what is the mag-<lb/>nitude and anisotropy of its superconducting gap? The <lb/>first experiments (STM, penetration depth, specific heat) <lb/>on CaC 6 have evidenced a single, apparently isotropic, s-<lb/>wave gap with a ratio 2∆/k B T c of the order of the BCS <lb/>value [6, 7, 8]. Recent tunnel spectroscopy results, on the <lb/>other hand, claimed the presence of an isotropic gap with <lb/>a magnitude more than 40% higher than that reported <lb/>earlier [9]. The spread of gap values measured up to now <lb/>range between 1.6 meV [6] and 2.3 meV [9]. The im-<lb/>portant point is that all these experiments have either <lb/>probed a bulk property [8] or a directional one along <lb/>the c-axis direction [6, 7, 9]. As pointed out in Ref.6, <lb/>the presence of anisotropic or two-gap superconductivity <lb/>in CaC 6 cannot be ruled out until tunneling or point-<lb/>contact measurements are performed also along the ab <lb/>direction. On the other hand, recent first-principles den-<lb/>sity functional calculations of the superconducting prop-<lb/>erties of CaC 6 have supported the presence of a moder-<lb/>ately anisotropic gap which varies between 1.1 and 2.3 <lb/>meV, depending on the k-point and the π or interlayer <lb/>(IL) sheet of the Fermi surface (FS) involved [10]. Such <lb/>an anisotropy can be revealed by directional spectroscopy <lb/>measurements performed along both c and ab direction. <lb/>In this paper we present the results of point-contact <lb/>Andreev-reflection (PCAR) spectroscopy performed on <lb/>high-quality bulk samples of CaC 6 [8]. By using a spe-<lb/>cial technique to realize the contacts, that proved very <lb/>successful and effective in the case of MgB 2 [11, 12], we <lb/>were able to perform directional PCAR spectroscopy at <lb/>very low temperature both along the ab plane and the <lb/>c-axis direction. Two different gap distributions in the <lb/>two directions can reproducibly be extracted from the ex-<lb/>perimental data. When compared to the results of new <lb/>first-principles calculations these findings unequivocally <lb/>prove the anisotropy of the superconducting gap in CaC 6 . <lb/>The high-quality CaC 6 bulk samples used for our mea-<lb/>surements were synthesized by reacting highly oriented <lb/>pyrolytic graphite (with a spread of the c axis orienta-<lb/>tion ≤ 0.4 • ) for several weeks at 350 • C with a molten <lb/>alloy of Li and Ca [8]. The resulting CaC 6 samples have <lb/>a shiny golden surface. They are very sensitive to air and <lb/>moisture which rapidly damage the sample surfaces. X-<lb/>ray analysis has shown mainly the CaC 6 reflections with <lb/>a small (&lt; 5%) contribution from impurity phases. Fur-<lb/>ther details on the characterization of the samples may be <lb/>found in Ref. 8. All samples used for PCAR spectroscopy <lb/>(size ≈ 1×1×0.2 mm 3 ) were selected to have a very sharp <lb/>superconducting transition (∆T c (10% − 90%) = 0.1 K) <lb/>with the onset at T c = 11.4 K. <lb/>The point contacts were made by using a non-<lb/>conventional technique we called &quot;soft&quot; PCAR spec-<lb/>troscopy [11, 12]. Instead of using the standard metallic <lb/>tip, a very small (∅ ≃ 50 µm) drop of Ag conductive <lb/>paint, put on the etched or freshly cleaved surfaces of <lb/>the sample is used as a counterelectrode. Such contacts <lb/>are particularly stable both in time and towards tem-<lb/>perature variations and they allow to inject the current <lb/>mainly perpendicular to the contact plane. A fine tuning <lb/>of the junction characteristics at low temperature can be <lb/>done by applying short voltage or current pulses. Fur-<lb/>ther details on the technique can be found in Refs. 11, 13. <lb/>Due to the mentioned high sensitivity of CaC 6 samples&apos; <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>1.05 <lb/>1.10 <lb/>¡ <lb/>¢ <lb/>£ <lb/>¤ <lb/>¥ <lb/>¦ <lb/> § <lb/>ab plane <lb/>(a) <lb/>-0.30 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>+ 0.41 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>+ 0.31 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>Conductance (Ω <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>0.60 <lb/>0.65 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.85© <lb/>c axis <lb/>(b) <lb/>-0.02 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>-0.03 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>-0.13 Ω <lb/>−1 <lb/>Conductance (Ω <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>FIG. 1: (Color online) (a) Raw point-contact conductance <lb/>curves of various ab-plane contacts at 4.2 K. For clarity the <lb/>curves are vertically shifted of the amount shown close to each <lb/>curve. (b) The same as in (a) but for various contacts with <lb/>current injection mainly along the c axis. In each panel a <lb/>sketch of the contact geometry is also shown. <lb/>surface to air, the room-temperature preparation of the <lb/>contact was done inside a sealed glove bag filled with <lb/>pure He gas or in a glove box with Ar atmosphere. Af-<lb/>ter the contact was made the junction was very rapidly <lb/>transferred to the cryostat in a sealed container. Con-<lb/>tacts were made either on the flat ab-plane surface or on <lb/>the narrow lateral side of the samples. Referring to the <lb/>main direction of current injection, we call them c-axis <lb/>and ab-plane contacts, respectively (see insets of Fig. 1). <lb/>The conductance curves, dI/dV vs. V , were obtained <lb/>by numerical differentiation of the measured I −V curves <lb/>and subsequently normalized by dividing them by the <lb/>normal-state conductance measured at T ≥ T c . For this <lb/>reason, in all the contacts, we therefore carefully studied <lb/>the temperature dependence of the conductance in order <lb/>to determine the critical temperature of the junction, i.e. <lb/>the &apos;Andreev critical temperature&apos;, T A <lb/>c . In an overall of <lb/>different contacts, T A <lb/>c was found to be 11.3 ± 0.1 K, in <lb/>best agreement with the bulk T c &apos;s of the samples and in <lb/>contrast with a previous report [6]. This fact proves the <lb/>high quality of samples and surfaces in the contact re-<lb/>gion. For simplicity, we will therefore refer to the critical <lb/>temperatures of the contacts as T c in the following. <lb/>Fig. 1 shows several raw conductance curves as func-<lb/>tion of bias voltage measured both in ab-plane contacts <lb/>(a) and in c-axis ones (b) at 4.2 K. The curves show clear <lb/>Andreev-reflection (AR) features, an almost flat conduc-<lb/>tance (at V &gt; 8 − 10 meV) and no dips that usually <lb/>are a sign of the failure in reaching the conditions for <lb/>pure ballistic conduction in the contact [14, 15]. The <lb/>normal resistance R N of all the good contacts is between <lb/>0.75 and 6.4 Ω. By knowing the mean free paths and <lb/>the residual resistivities of CaC 6 along the ab plane and <lb/>in the c-axis direction, i.e. ℓ ab = 74 nm, ℓ c = 4.7 nm, <lb/>ρ 0,ab = 0.8 µΩ•cm and ρ 0,c = 24 µΩ•cm [16, 17] we can <lb/>apply the Sharvin formula for the contact resistance in <lb/>the ballistic regime in order to determine the contact <lb/>radius a = (4ρ 0 ℓ/3πR N ) 0.5 [15]. The condition for full <lb/>ballistic transport (a ≪ ℓ) is totally verified in ab-plane <lb/>contacts, where a ab ≈ 6 − 18 nm. In c-axis junctions, <lb/>where a c ≈ 14 − 24 nm but the conductance curves do <lb/>not show any sign of heating [13], the presence of at least <lb/>30 parallel contacts in the junction area is expected. <lb/>After normalization, the conductance curves were <lb/>fitted to the modified 3D Blonder-Tinkham-Klapwijk <lb/>(BTK) model [18, 19, 20]. In the single-band form it con-<lb/>tains three fitting parameters: The gap ∆, the barrier-<lb/>height parameter Z and the broadening Γ which accounts <lb/>for both intrinsic (quasiparticle lifetime) and extrinsic <lb/>phenomena that broaden the AR conductance [19]. <lb/>In order to increase the experimental resolution of our <lb/>measurements we decided to perform part of the PCAR <lb/>experiments at very low temperature in a Quantum De-<lb/>sign measurement system (PPMS) with 3 He insert. <lb/>Fig. 2 (a) shows the normalized conductance curves <lb/>(circles) of a typical ab-plane contact at various temper-<lb/>atures from 400 mK up to T c . At any temperature the <lb/>single-band 3D BTK model fits the data very well (solid <lb/>lines). At the lowest T , the values of the fitting param-<lb/>eters are: ∆ = 1.44 meV, Γ = 0.61 meV and Z = 0.75. <lb/>In panel (c) we display the order parameter ∆ obtained <lb/>from the data given in (a). Its temperature dependence <lb/>almost perfectly follows the BCS-like expression (solid <lb/>line) with 2∆(0)/k B T c = 2.98 which is sensibly smaller <lb/>than expected from BCS theory. <lb/>In Fig. 2 (b) and (d) we report the same data for a <lb/>c-axis contact. As for the ab-plane case, the curves are <lb/>well fitted by the single-band 3D BTK model which gives <lb/>at 400 mK: ∆ = 1.7 meV, Γ = 0.84 meV and Z = 0.97. <lb/>The temperature dependence of ∆ is very close to the <lb/>expected BCS one with a ratio 2∆(0)/k B T c = 3.48, in <lb/>best agreement with the weak-coupling BCS value. <lb/>It is worth noticing that the Z values observed in c-<lb/>axis contacts (between 0.74 and 1.01) are systematically <lb/>greater than those of ab-plane contacts (between 0.48 <lb/>and 0.75). According to the 3D BTK model [20], this <lb/>difference can be explained by the different Fermi veloc-<lb/>ities of CaC in the ab plane (v ab = 0.54 × 10 6 m/s) and <lb/>along c axis (v c = 0.29 × 10 6 m/s), thus confirming the <lb/>directionality of our point contacts. <lb/>The AR curves shown in Fig. 1 and 2 are rather <lb/>small in amplitude, as already observed in all the &quot;soft&quot; <lb/>PCAR measurements on MgB 2 and related compounds <lb/>[11, 12, 13], resulting in Γ values substantially greater <lb/>than those expected for the quasiparticle lifetime. As re-<lb/>cently observed in lithographically fabricated Cu-Pt-Pb <lb/>nanocontacts [21], this additional broadening can be ex-<lb/>plained by the presence of pair-breaking effects induced <lb/>by the scattering in a thin disordered layer present at the <lb/>NS interface. This is the case of our point contacts, due <lb/>to a disordered layer on the surface of Ag grains that also <lb/>makes the residual resistivity of the paint be five orders <lb/>of magnitude greater than in pure Ag. <lb/>The reproducibility of the PCAR data was very good. <lb/>Most of the contacts, obtained both in 4 He and in 3 He <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 10 12 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 (a) <lb/>Order parameter <lb/>∆ (meV) <lb/>Normalized conductance <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0.4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>10.5 <lb/>11 <lb/>ab-plane <lb/>Normalized conductance <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 10 12 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>(c) <lb/>2∆/k B T C =2.98 <lb/>ab-plane <lb/>BCS fit <lb/>-10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>(b) <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0.4 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>c-axis <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>(d) <lb/>2∆/k B T C =3.48 <lb/>c-axis <lb/>BCS fit <lb/>FIG. 2: (Color online) Normalized dI/dV vs. V curves at different temperatures down to 400 mK in an ab-plane contact (a) <lb/>and in a c-axis one (b) (open circles). Solid lines: best-fit curves given by the single-band 3D BTK model. Panels (c) and <lb/>(d) show the temperature dependency of the order parameter ∆ (full circles) in the ab-plane direction and in the c-axis one, <lb/>respectively, as determined from the BTK fits shown in (a) and (b). Solid lines are the BCS-like fits. <lb/>cryostat, show dI/dV curves and temperature dependen-<lb/>cies of quality similar to that presented in Fig. 2. In <lb/>15 ab-plane contacts the order parameter ∆(0) ranged <lb/>between 1.1 meV and 1.7 meV with the distribution <lb/>shown in Fig. (a). In 14 c-axis contacts ∆(0) ranged <lb/>between 1.3 meV and 1.94 meV with the distribution <lb/>shown in Fig. 3 (b). The figure also shows the Gaussian <lb/>curves that best fit the distributions. They are peaked at <lb/>∆ ab (0)=1.35 meV and ∆ c (0)=1.71 meV and show stan-<lb/>dard deviations s ab =0.14 meV and s c =0.08 meV, respec-<lb/>tively. The results in c-axis direction are in very good <lb/>agreement with the gap values previously reported in <lb/>Ref. 6, 7. A minority of contacts (3 in ab-plane and <lb/>3 in c-axis direction) have shown gap values between 2.1 <lb/>and 2.4 meV, similarly to the results of Ref. 9. <lb/>The complex microscopical nature of our point con-<lb/>tacts leaves some uncertainty about the true direction <lb/>of current injection, particularly in the case of contacts <lb/>on the side faces of the sample (i.e. ab-plane contacts) <lb/>where, due to the intrinsic inhomogeneity of the cleaved <lb/>surface, current injection along c axis is also possible. <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>(a) <lb/>Frequency Counts <lb/>Order parameter ∆ (meV) <lb/>ab plane <lb/>1.3 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>1.9 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>c axis <lb/>(b) <lb/>Frequency Counts <lb/>Order parameter ∆ (meV) <lb/>FIG. 3: (Color online) Distributions of the different ∆(0) val-<lb/>ues measured in ab-plane contacts (a) and in c-axis ones (b) <lb/>at 4.2 K (red) and at 400 mK (light red). Dash black lines <lb/>are the fits of the total distribution to a Gaussian curve. <lb/>However, the clear difference observed between the most <lb/>probable ∆(0) values in ab-plane and c-axis contacts pro-<lb/>vides strong evidence for a gap anisotropy in CaC 6 . <lb/>In order to compare our results with the theoretical <lb/>predictions of gap anisotropy in CaC 6 [10] we calcu-<lb/>lated the Andreev-reflection conductance curves by first-<lb/>principles methods. We have a SN junction where S = <lb/>CaC 6 and N = Ag. Let&apos;s label with the suffix i = 1,2,3 <lb/>the three sheets of the CaC 6 Fermi surface (FS) (π and <lb/>interlayer (IL) bands). If n is the unitary vector in the <lb/>direction of the injected current, v ik,n = v ik • n are the <lb/>corresponding components of the Fermi velocities in the <lb/>superconductor at wave vector k for band i-th. Tak-<lb/>ing into account that Ag has a quasi-spherical FS and <lb/>an almost constant Fermi velocity v N = v ik , the corre-<lb/>sponding quantity in the normal metal will be v N,n = v N . <lb/>Following Refs. 22, 23 we finally obtain the total AR con-<lb/>ductance as: <lb/>σ(E, n) = <lb/>i σ ikn (E) <lb/>v 2 <lb/>ik,n <lb/>v ik [v ik,n +vN] 2 FSi <lb/>i <lb/>v 2 <lb/>ik,n <lb/>v ik [v ik,n +vN] 2 FSi <lb/>(1) <lb/>where: FSi is the integral over the i-th FS, i.e. <lb/>v ik,n <lb/>2 <lb/>v ik [v ik,n +vN] 2 FSi = v ik,n &gt;0 <lb/>v 2 <lb/>ik,n <lb/>[v ik,n +vN] 2 δ(E ik )d 3 k. <lb/>σ ikn (E) is the BTK conductance of the i-th band ex-<lb/>pressed in terms of the quantities N q <lb/>ik (E) = E/ <lb/>p <lb/>E 2 <lb/>− ∆ 2 <lb/>ik <lb/>and N p <lb/>ik (E) = ∆ ik / <lb/>p <lb/>E 2 <lb/>− ∆ 2 <lb/>ik (whose real parts are the <lb/>quasiparticle and the pair density of states in the same <lb/>band, respectively) and of Z n values. ∆ ik is the gap value <lb/>for band i-th at point k over the FS, recently calculated <lb/>from first principles [10]. The values of Z n used in the <lb/>calculation are taken similar to those of the curves shown <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>T = 0.4 K <lb/>T = 0 K <lb/>T = 0 K <lb/>a axis <lb/>(a) <lb/>exp <lb/>Γ = 0.6 meV <lb/>Γ = 0 <lb/>Normalized conductance <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>BTK fit <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>Γ = 0 <lb/>Γ = 0.8 meV <lb/>exp <lb/>T = 0.4 K <lb/>T = 0 K <lb/>T = 0 K <lb/>c axis <lb/>(b) <lb/>Normalized conductance <lb/>Voltage (mV) <lb/>BTK fit <lb/>FIG. 4: (Color online) Theoretical AR conductances calcu-<lb/>lated at T = 0 by Eq. (1). (a) Current injected along the <lb/>a axis with Z = 0.75 and Γ = 0 (black) and Γ = 0.6 (red); <lb/>(b) current injected along the c axis with Z = 1 and Γ = 0 <lb/>(black) and Γ = 0.8 (red). Experimental curves at 400 mK <lb/>are shown for comparison (blue circles). <lb/>in Fig. 2, i.e. Z ab = 0.75 and Z c = 1. The explicit ex-<lb/>pression of σ ikn (E) can be found in Ref. 20. <lb/>The results of the calculations given by Eq. (1) are <lb/>shown at T = 0 K and for a-and c-axis directions (top <lb/>curves in Fig. 4 (a) and (b)). The conductance calcu-<lb/>lated along the b direction is almost identical to the one <lb/>in a direction. At T = 0 the topology of the CaC 6 FS <lb/>and the calculated anisotropy of the π and IL gaps re-<lb/>sult in a sizeable anisotropy of the AR conductance. In <lb/>ab direction, it exhibits a sharp peak (related to the π <lb/>gap) at about 1.38 meV and a broad shoulder (mainly <lb/>related to the IL gap) at about 1.9 meV. In c direction, <lb/>as expected from the shape of the FS, the role of the IL <lb/>(Ca) gap becomes more important and the conductance <lb/>shows two distinct peaks with almost the same height. <lb/>However, for Γ = 0 even at T = 0 K these anisotropic <lb/>features are rapidly smeared out. The middle curves of <lb/>Fig. 4(a) and (b) show the effect on the theoretical con-<lb/>ductances of a broadening similar to that observed at <lb/>very low T in the experimental curves of Fig. 2. The con-<lb/>ductances become similar to single-gap ones and can be <lb/>perfectly fitted by single-gap 3D BTK curves, as shown <lb/>in Fig. 4 (black dash lines). The use of more complex <lb/>fitting models (anisotropic or two-band BTK) that we <lb/>tested on our data does not improve the fit substantially, <lb/>as already pointed out in Ref. 6, 9. In Fig. 4 the ex-<lb/>perimental ab-plane and c-axis conductances measured <lb/>at 400 mK are included too (circles) in order to show <lb/>the remarkable agreement with the theoretical curves for <lb/>the same level of broadening. Although this broadening <lb/>washes out the fine anisotropic structures of the conduc-<lb/>tance, a clear sign of the underlying gap anisotropy is <lb/>still present since the 3D BTK fit of the theoretical con-<lb/>ductances gives different order parameters in the two di-<lb/>rections, ∆ = 1.5 meV (Γ = 0.65 meV, Z = 0.765) for <lb/>a-axis direction and ∆ = 1.7 meV (Γ = 0.92 meV, Z = <lb/>1.015) for c-axis one. The c-axis value is in perfect agree-<lb/>ment with the experimental results (both single curves at <lb/>400 mK and the peak of the distribution of the 14 dif-<lb/>ferent contacts). In the ab-plane case, the experimental <lb/>∆ values from the curves at 400 mK and from the peak <lb/>of the distribution of Fig. 3 (a) (ranging from 1.3 meV <lb/>to 1.44 meV) are smaller than the value obtained from <lb/>the fit of the theoretical conductance. This discrepancy <lb/>could be ascribed to a possible slight overestimation of <lb/>the small π gap (and, maybe, an underestimation of the <lb/>large IL gap associated with Ca FS) in the theoretical <lb/>calculations. This fact appears reasonable if one consid-<lb/>ers that the first-principle calculations of Ref. [10] led to <lb/>an underestimation of T c of about 17 %. <lb/>In conclusion, the first directional PCAR measure-<lb/>ments in CaC 6 carried out also at T = mK both <lb/>along the ab-plane and the c-axis direction give strong <lb/>and reproducible evidence of the predicted anisotropic <lb/>nature of the superconducting gap in this GIC. New first-<lb/>principles calculations of the expected anisotropy in the <lb/>AR conductance curves fully support this conclusion and <lb/>indicate that the actual gap anisotropy in CaC 6 could be <lb/>even slightly greater than theoretically predicted. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank Lilia Boeri, O.V. Dolgov, E.K.U. Gross and <lb/>I.I. Mazin for useful discussions. This work was done <lb/>within the projects: PRIN (No. 2006021741) and Cy-<lb/>bersar (cofunded by MUR under PON). V.A.S. acknowl-<lb/>edges the support of RFBR (Proj. No. 06-02-16490). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] T. E. Weller et al., Nature Phys. 1, 39 (2005). <lb/>[2] N. Emery et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 95, 087003 (2005). <lb/>[3] J. S. Kim et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 99, 027001 (2007). <lb/>[4] M. Calandra and F. Mauri, Phys. Rev. B 74, 094507 <lb/>(2006). <lb/>[5] I. I. Mazin et al., Physica C 460-462, 116 (2007). <lb/>[6] N. Bergeal et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, 077003 (2006). <lb/>[7] G. Lamura et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 107008 (2006). <lb/>[8] J. S. Kim et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 96, 217002 (2006). <lb/>[9] C. Kurter et al., Phys. Rev. B 76, 220502 (2007). <lb/>[10] A. Sanna et al., Phys. Rev. B 75, 020511(R) (2007). <lb/>[11] R.S. Gonnelli et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 89, 247004 (2002). <lb/>[12] R.S. Gonnelli et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 97, 037001 (2006). <lb/>[13] D. Daghero et al., Phys. Rev. B 74, 174519 (2006). <lb/>[14] Goutam Sheet, S. Mukhopadhyay, and P. Raychaudhuri, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 69, 134507 (2004). <lb/>[15] Y.G. Naidyuk, I.K. Yanson, Point-Contact Spectroscopy, <lb/>Springer Series in Solid-State Sciences, Vol. 145, 2004. <lb/>[16] J. S. Kim, unpublished results. <lb/>[17] A. Gauzzi et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 98, 067002 (2007). <lb/>[18] G.E. Blonder, M. Tinkham and T.M. Klapwijk, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 25, 4515 (1982). <lb/>[19] A. Plecenik et al., Phys. Rev. B 49, 10016 (1994). <lb/>[20] S. Kashiwaya et al., Phys. Rev. B 53, 2667 (1996). <lb/>[21] P. Chalsani et al., Phys. Rev. B 75, 094417 (2007). <lb/>[22] I.I Mazin, Phys. Rev. Lett. 83, 1427 (1999). <lb/>[23] A. Brinkman et al., Phys. Rev. B 65, 180517(R) (2002). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
