<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_Mori_et_al_Bone"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<front> DU145 human prostate cancer cells express functional Receptor Activator of NF-κ κ κ <lb/>κB: <lb/> New insights in the prostate cancer bone metastasis process. <lb/> Mori K. 1, 2, * , Le Goff B. 1, 2 , Charrier C. 1, 2 , Battaglia S. 1, 2 , Heymann D. 1, 2,* , Rédini F. 1, 2 <lb/> 1. INSERM, ERI 7, Nantes, F-44035 France <lb/>2. Université de Nantes, Nantes atlantique universités, Laboratoire de Physiopathologie de la <lb/>Résorption Osseuse et Thérapie des Tumeurs Osseuses Primitives, EA3822, Nantes, F-44035 <lb/>France <lb/> Correspondence and reprint request to: <lb/> Dr. D. HEYMANN or Dr K. MORI Université de Nantes EA 3822 ; INSERM ERI 7, <lb/>Physiopathologie de la Résorption Osseuse et Thérapie des Tumeurs Osseuses Primitives. <lb/>Faculté de Médecine, 1 rue Gaston Veil, 44035, Nantes cedex 1, France <lb/>Tel: +33 2 40 41 28 45 <lb/>Fax: +33 2 40 41 28 60 <lb/>e-mail: dominique.heymann@univ-nantes.fr or kanchi@belle.shiga-med.ac.jp <lb/>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			Abstract <lb/> Prostate cancer metastases to bone are observed in around 80% of prostate cancer patients and <lb/>represent the most critical complication of advanced prostate cancer, frequently resulting in <lb/>significant morbidity and mortality. As the underlying mechanisms are not fully characterized, <lb/>understanding the biological mechanisms that govern prostate cancer metastases to bone at the <lb/>molecular level should lead to the determination of new potential therapeutic targets. Receptor <lb/>Activator of NF-κB ligand (RANKL)/RANK/Osteoprotegerin (OPG) are the key regulators of <lb/>bone metabolism both in normal and pathological condition, including prostate cancer bone <lb/>metastases. In the present study, we demonstrated that human prostate cancer cell lines, DU145 <lb/>and PC3 express biologically functional RANK. Indeed, soluble human RANKL (shRANKL, <lb/>100ng/ml) treatment induced ERK 1/2, p38 and IκB phosphorylations in these cells. shRANKL <lb/>administration also promoted DU145 and PC3 prostate cancer cell invasion in vitro. Whereas <lb/>human OPG (hOPG) administration alone (100ng/ml) had no marked effect, combined <lb/>association of both agents abolished the RANKL-induced DU145 cell invasion. As RANKL <lb/>had no direct effect on DU145 cell proliferation, the observed effects were indeed related to <lb/>RANKL-induced cell migration. DU145 human prostate cancer cells promoted <lb/>osteoclastogenesis of osteoclast precursors generated from mouse bone marrow. Moreover, <lb/>DU145 cells produced soluble factor(s) that up-regulate the proliferation of MC3T3-E1 <lb/>pre-osteoblasts through the activation of the ERK 1/2 and STAT3 signal transduction pathways. <lb/>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			This stimulation of pre-osteoblast proliferation resulted in an increased local RANKL <lb/>expression that can activate both osteoclast/osteoclast precursors and prostate cancer cells, thus <lb/>facilitating prostate cancer metastasis development in bone. We confirm that RANKL is a <lb/>factor that facilitates metastasis to bone by acting as an activator of both osteoclasts and <lb/>RANK-positive prostate cancer cells in our model. Furthermore, the present study provides the <lb/>evidence that blocking RANKL-RANK interaction offer new therapeutic approach not only at <lb/>the level of bone resorbing cells, but also by interfering with RANK-positive prostate cancer <lb/>cells in the prostate cancer bone metastasis development. <lb/>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			Key words: RANK, RANKL, prostate cancer, migration, bone metastasis <lb/></front>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> Prostate cancer is the most common malignancy diagnosed in males and is currently <lb/>the major leading cause of cancer death among men [1, 2]. Prostate cancer metastases to bone <lb/>are observed in around 80% of prostate cancer patients and represent the most critical <lb/>complication of advanced prostate cancer, frequently resulting in significant morbidity and <lb/>mortality [1, 2]. Unlike other solid tumors that are associated with osteolytic bone metastases, <lb/>prostate cancer bone metastases stimulate an overall increase in both bone remodelling and <lb/>bone volume [3]. In contrast, recent findings strongly suggest the importance of osteoclast <lb/>function [4-9]; however the mechanisms underlining these processes are not fully determined. <lb/>Therefore, understanding the biological mechanisms that govern prostate cancer metastases to <lb/>bone at the molecular level and elucidation of the interactions among the factors involved <lb/>should lead to the determination of new potential therapeutic targets. <lb/>Receptor activator of NF-κB ligand (RANKL)/RANK/Osteoprotegerin (OPG) <lb/>represent the key regulators of bone metabolism both in normal and pathological condition, <lb/>including prostate cancer bone metastases [10, 11]. RANKL has been shown to both activate <lb/>mature osteoclasts and mediate osteoclastogenesis in the presence of macrophage-colony <lb/>stimulating factor (M-CSF) [12, 13]. RANKL is preferentially expressed on committed <lb/>pre-osteoblastic cells, whereas its specific receptor RANK is expressed on hematopoietic <lb/>osteoclast precursors [14, 15]. OPG also produced by osteoblast lineage cells acts as a decoy <lb/>
			
			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			receptor and inhibits osteoclast formation, function and survival by preventing the binding of <lb/>RANKL to its receptor RANK [10]. Recent data strongly revealed the significant involvement <lb/>of the RANKL/RANK/OPG system in metastatic bone cancer diseases, including prostate <lb/>cancer bone metastases [16]. Indeed, current studies have disclosed that blocking <lb/>RANKL-RANK interaction prevents the progression of prostate cancer in bone [6-9]. <lb/>Furthermore, an increased expression of OPG and RANKL were reported in prostate cancer <lb/>bone metastases [17, 18]. As OPG is also a decoy receptor for TNF-related apoptosis-inducing <lb/>ligand (TRAIL), it exerts inhibitory effect on TRAIL-induced cancer cell apoptosis and OPG <lb/>thus represents a survival factor for prostate cancer cells [19]. RANK expressed on <lb/>osteoclast/osteoclast precursors has been largely described as a key receptor that control <lb/>osteoclast differentiation, activity and survival [12, 14, 15, 20]. However, we and others have <lb/>demonstrated the expression of functional RANK at the surface of tumor cells that develop in <lb/>bone, including a mouse osteosarcoma cell line, POS-1 [21, 22]. These recent findings bring <lb/>new insights in the vicious cycle theory between bone resorbing cells and cancer cells [23]. <lb/>Indeed, it has been suggested that cancer cells produce soluble factors that activate directly <lb/>(RANKL) or indirectly via osteoblasts (Parathyroid Hormone-related Protein, Interleukin 8…) <lb/>osteoclast differentiation and maturation [24]. During the bone resorption, osteoclasts liberate <lb/>growth factors stocked in the mineralized bone matrix (Insulin-like Growth Factor-1, <lb/>Transforming Growth Factor-β, Fibroblast Growth Factor …) that can further activate cancer <lb/>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			cell proliferation [25]. This vicious cycle has been proposed to explain the tumor development <lb/>in bone sites. <lb/>Previous studies reported that OPG expression by prostate cancer cells [8] and more <lb/>recently RANK expression by cancer cells [21, 22], these all findings therefore led us to <lb/>elucidate the molecular mechanisms underlying prostate cancer bone metastases and the <lb/>therapeutic relevance of RANKL/RANK/OPG triad in these processes, using DU145 and PC3 <lb/>human prostate cancer cell lines. <lb/> Materials and Methods <lb/> Cell culture <lb/> Huma n pr osta te ca nce r c e ll line s ( DU145 a nd PC3) w ere obtained from the <lb/>American Type Culture Collection (ATCC, USA). MC3T3-E1, a mouse calvaria-derived <lb/>pre-osteoblast cell line was obtained from the RIKEN Cell Bank (Tsukuba, Japan). DU145 <lb/>and MC3T3-E1 were cultured in Dulbecco&apos;s Modified Eagle&apos;s Medium (DMEM) (Bio <lb/>Whittaker, Verviers, Belgium) and PC3 in F12 medium (Invitrogen, Eragny, France), <lb/>respectively supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS, Hyclone, France), at 37°C in a <lb/>humidified atmosphere (5% CO 2 / 95% air). <lb/> Characterization of human prostate cancer cell lines <lb/>

			<page> 8 <lb/></page>

			- RNA extraction and RT-PCR analysis <lb/> Total RNA was extracted from human prostate cancer cell lines using TRIzol reagent <lb/>(Invitrogen) following manufacturer&apos;s recommendation. First, RNA (5µg) was reverse <lb/>transcribed (RT) into cDNA using 400 U MMLV-RT (Invitrogen) and 0.5µg random primers <lb/>(Promega, Madison, USA). Two microliters of the RT products were subjected to PCR using <lb/>1.25 U of Ampli Taq Gold (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, USA) and upstream and <lb/>downstream primers (20pmol each) to determine the expression of human OPG (hOPG) <lb/>[5&apos;-gctaacctcaccttcgag-3&apos; (sense), 5&apos;-tgattggacctggttacc-3&apos; (anti-sense)], human RANK <lb/>(hRANK) [5&apos;-ttaagccagtgcttcacggg-3&apos; (sense), 5&apos;-acgtagaccacgatgatgtcgc-3&apos; (anti-sense)], <lb/>human RANKL (hRANKL) [5&apos;-gccagtgggagatgttag-3&apos; (sense), 5&apos;-ttagctgcaagttttccc-3&apos; <lb/>(anti-sense)], <lb/>human <lb/>interleukin <lb/>(hIL)-6 <lb/>[5&apos;-aaagaggcactggcagaaaa-3&apos; <lb/>(sense), <lb/>5&apos;-aaagctgcgcagaatgagat-3&apos; (anti-sense)], hIL-11 [5&apos;-ctgagcctgtggccagata-3&apos; (sense), <lb/>5&apos;-gcccagtcaagtgtcaggtg-3&apos; <lb/>(anti-sense)], <lb/>human <lb/>oncostatin <lb/>M <lb/>(hOSM) <lb/>[5&apos;-ataggcagctgctcgaaaga-3&apos; (sense), 5&apos;-actgagtgcatgaagcgatg-3&apos; (anti-sense)], human <lb/>leukemia <lb/>inhibitory <lb/>factor <lb/>(hLIF) <lb/>[5&apos;-accagatcaggagccaactg-3&apos; <lb/>(sense), <lb/>5&apos;-gttgacagcccagcttcttc-3&apos; (anti-sense)] and 18S [5&apos;-tcaagaacgaaagtcggaggtc-3&apos; (sense), <lb/>5&apos;-ttattgctcaatctcgggtggct-3&apos; (anti-sense)]. The thermal cycle profile was as follows: <lb/>denaturation for 30 seconds at 95°C, annealing for 30 seconds at 58°C (hRANKL), 60°C <lb/>(hOPG) and 62°C (hIL-6, hIL-11, hOSM, hLIF and 18S) respectively, or 4 minutes at 68°C <lb/>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			(hRANK), and extension for 60 seconds at 72°C. After the number of PCR cycles was <lb/>increased, a plot was done for each sample and the cycle values corresponding to the linear part <lb/>of the amplification curve were determined and used to quantify the messages versus the 18S <lb/>signal determined in the same way. The cycle number used was 40 cycles for hRANK, <lb/>hRANKL, hOPG, hIL-11, and hOSM, 35 cycles for hIL-6 and hLIF, and 20 cycles for 18S, <lb/>respectively. The PCR products were electrophoresed on 1% agarose gel containing ethidium <lb/>bromide. The mRNA levels of each gene were standardized to 18S levels. <lb/> -Immunocytochemistry <lb/> The analysis of RANK expression at the protein level on prostate cancer cells was <lb/>performed by cytospin preparation and immunocytochemistry staining. After trypsin treatment, <lb/>cells were suspended in phosphate buffered saline (PBS, Bio Whittaker) at 400 x 10 3 cells/ml, <lb/>centrifuged for 4 minutes at 600 rpm on glass slides (Cytocentrifugeuse Shandon Cytospin 3, <lb/>Thermo Electron Corporation, France) and fixed by acetone. The cytospin slides were then <lb/>stained by immunocytochemistry. Endogenous peroxidase activity was blocked using 3% H 2 O 2 <lb/> in distilled water, then the slides were incubated with a human anti-RANK monoclonal <lb/>antibody (1:5 dilution, Santa Cruz Biotechnology, CA, USA) overnight at 4˚C, then with a <lb/>biotin-labelled secondary antibody (1:200 dilution, Rockland immunohistochemicals Inc., <lb/>Gilbertsville, PA, USA). Cytospin slides were then subjected to avidin-conjugated peroxidase <lb/>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			(Sigma-Aldrich, St. Louis, MO, USA). Finally, peroxidase activity was detected using a <lb/>commercially available kit (AEC staining kit, Sigma-Aldrich), and the sections were <lb/>counterstained with hematoxylin. Negative control slides were prepared by incubating sections <lb/>with PBS instead of the primary antibody. <lb/> Signal transduction analyses by Western Blot <lb/> DU145 and PC3 cells were grown in a 6-multiwell plate until 70-80% of confluence in <lb/>their respective growth medium. Then, DU145 and PC3 cells were washed three times with <lb/>their respective culture medium and cultured in serum-free respective culture medium for 24 <lb/>hours before being incubated for 2, 5, 10, 15, 30, 60 and 120 minutes in the absence or presence <lb/>of 100ng/ml soluble hRANKL (shRANKL, kindly provided by Amgen Inc., Thousand Oaks, <lb/>USA). Both cells were then lysed in ice-cold buffer (NaCl 150mM, Tris 50mM, Nonidet P-40 <lb/>1%, sodium deoxycholate 0.25%, NaF 1mM, NaVO 4 1mM, leupeptine 10mg/ml, aprotinin <lb/>10mg/ml, PMSF 0.5mM). Total amount of proteins was determined in each sample using a <lb/>bicinchominic acid (BCA, Sigma) based procedure. Briefly, 10µl of cellular lysis or standard <lb/>bovine serum albumin (BSA) solution were added to 200µl of reagent (Copper II solution 1/50 <lb/>diluted in bicinchominic acid) and incubated for 30 minutes at 37°C. Optic density (OD) was <lb/>determined at 570 nm as well as the protein concentration compared to the standard curve using <lb/>a Wallac 1420 VICTOR 2 ™ multilabel counter (Perkin Elmer, MA, USA). The same amounts <lb/>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			of proteins were resolved on 10% SDS-polyacrylamide gel electrophoresis (PAGE), and <lb/>transferred to a poly vinydilene fluorure (PVDF) membrane (Millipore, Bedford, MA, USA). <lb/>The levels of phosphorylated forms of ERK 1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), p38 (Thr180/Tyr182), IκB <lb/>(Ser32) (Cell Signaling Technologies, Beverly, MA, USA), and total forms of ERK 1/2 (Cell <lb/>Signaling Technologies), p38 (R&amp;D systems, MN, USA), IκB (Tebu-bio, Le Perray en <lb/>Yvelines, France) were detected by respective specific antibodies (Ozyme, Saint-Quentin en <lb/>Yvelines, France) in PBS, 0.05% Tween 20, 3% BSA, and revealed using the BM <lb/>Chemiluminescence Western Blotting Substrate (Roche Applied Science, IN, USA). <lb/> Migration analyses by slit assay <lb/> DU145 and PC3 cells were seeded at the density of 40 x 10 3 cells per well into a <lb/>24-multiwell plate, and cultured in their respective culture medium supplemented with 1% FBS. <lb/>At the time of confluence, both cells were incubated in the absence or presence of shRANKL (5 <lb/>and 100ng/ml) for 24 hours. Then, a slit was made horizontally with a white tip at the centre of <lb/>each confluent well, the medium was changed after gentle rinse and cells were cultured for 24 <lb/>hours with or without shRANKL (5 and 100ng/ml). hOPG (kindly provided by Amgen Inc., <lb/>100ng/ml) alone or combined by pre-incubation with shRANKL (shRANKL:hOPG ratio of <lb/>1:5) were used in the same manner. Cell invasion on the slit of the confluent well was assessed <lb/>in each condition by light microscopy. The effect of a MEK/ERK inhibitor (UO126, 10µM), a <lb/>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			p38 inhibitor (SB 203580, 10µM) and a NF-κB translocation inhibitor (SN 50, 18µM) <lb/>(Calbiochem, CA, USA) were tested in the same experimental conditions. These inhibitors <lb/>were added 2 hours before the incubation with shRANKL or hOPG and maintained during the <lb/>culture period at the indicated concentration. <lb/> Time lapse assay <lb/> DU145 cells were seeded at the density of 40 x 10 3 cells per well into a 6-multiwell <lb/>plate, and cultured in DMEM supplemented with 1% FBS, in the absence or presence of <lb/>100ng/ml shRANKL. Phase-contrast photographs (Leica, Germany) were taken every 10 <lb/>minutes during 24 hours and edited using the Metamorph software. The number of cell <lb/>divisions was then manually counted and the percentage of cell division was determined <lb/>according to the following formula: number of cell division/original cell number x 100 (%). To <lb/>control DU145 cell invasion, a slit assay was performed as previously described using a <lb/>6-multiwell plate and DU145 cells invasion on the slit was monitored during 24 hours (Leica). <lb/>To measure the magnitude of RANKL-induced cell invasion on the slit, each slit was divided <lb/>into three sections and the cell invasion of each section was determined during 24 hours. The <lb/>total invaded areas of the three sections were statistically compared between each group. <lb/> Cell proliferation assays <lb/>

			<page> 13 <lb/></page>

			 - XTT test <lb/> DU145 cells were seeded at the density of 2 x 10 3 cells per well into a 96-multiwell <lb/>plate, and cultured for 72 hours in DMEM supplemented with 0.5% FBS in the absence or <lb/>presence of shRANKL (5, 50, 100ng/ml). The medium was changed every 24 hours and the cell <lb/>proliferation was determined by a XTT based method, using Cell Proliferation Kit II (Sigma) <lb/>following to the supplier&apos;s recommendations. In brief, at the end of the culture, 50µl of XTT <lb/>reagent were added in each well, and incubated 6 hours at 37°C. Then, OD was determined at <lb/>450 nm using a Wallac 1420 VICTOR 2 ™ multilabel counter. <lb/> -Trypan blue exclusion <lb/> Trypan blue exclusion was used to quantify the viable cells. DU145 cells were seeded <lb/>into a 24-multiwell plate (5 x 10 3 cells/well) and cultured in DMEM supplemented with 0.5 to <lb/>10% FBS in the absence or presence of 100ng/ml shRANKL, then the viable cell number was <lb/>counted at day 1, 4 and 7. <lb/> Human prostate cancer cell effects on bone cells <lb/> -Conditioned medium (CM) <lb/> DU145 cells (10 4 cells/cm 2 ) were grown in a 25cm 2 flask until reaching 70-80% confluence <lb/>in DMEM supplemented with 10% FBS. Then, cells were washed three times with PBS and the <lb/>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			medium was changed to serum-free DMEM in the presence or absence of 100ng/ml shRANKL. <lb/>After 24 hours, conditioned medium (CM) was collected and centrifuged at 1000rpm for 10 <lb/>minutes and stored at -80°C until use. The same volume of serum-free DMEM incubated in the <lb/>same conditions without cells was used as a control CM (CT CM). <lb/> -Osteoclastogenesis <lb/> Osteoclast precursors were generated from 4-5 weeks-old swiss male mice (Janvier, <lb/>Le Genest Saint Isle, France). Briefly, bone marrow cells isolated from mice tibiae and femora <lb/>were suspended in α-MEM (Invitrogen) supplemented with 10% FBS and 1% non-essential <lb/>amino acid (NEAA) (Invitrogen) and cultured in the presence of 5ng/ml mouse M-CSF (R&amp;D <lb/>systems). After 24 hours, non-adherent cells were collected and used as osteoclast precursors. <lb/>They were seeded into a 24-multiwell plate (10 6 cells/well) in α-MEM supplemented with 10% <lb/>FBS and 1% NEAA in the presence or absence of 100ng/ml shRANKL, 12ng/ml mouse <lb/>M-CSF, with or without DU145 cells (10 3 cells/well). Direct or separate co-cultures were <lb/>performed using 24 well format-culture chambers (Cell Culture Insert, BD Falcon, NJ, USA). <lb/>Half of medium was changed every 72 hours. After 7 days, cells were fixed and stained for <lb/>tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP) using Acid Phosphatase kit (Sigma-Aldrich) <lb/>following the manufacturer&apos;s recommendation, and the number of TRAP-positive <lb/>multinucleated cells (&gt; 3 nuclei) were counted by light microscopy. To identify the RANKL <lb/>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			effect through RANK-positive DU145 cells, increased concentration of shRANKL (200ng/ml) <lb/>was also tested in the same experimental condition. <lb/> -Pre-osteoblast cell proliferation assay <lb/> The mouse pre-osteoblast MC3T3-E1 cells were seeded into a 96-multiwell plate (2.8 <lb/>x 10 3 cells/well) and cultured for 72 hours in CT CM or CM from DU145 cells incubated with <lb/>or without 100ng/ml shRANKL supplemented with 5% FBS. The medium was changed every <lb/>48 hours and the cell proliferation was determined using a XTT based method as described <lb/>above. As an additional experiment, MC3T3-E1 cells were cultured with or without suramin <lb/>(50-500µg/ml, Sigma), a pan growth factor blocker. MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation was <lb/>measured by direct cell counting using the trypan blue exclusion method, as suramin interferes <lb/>with cell proliferation assays based on mitochondrial enzyme activity [26]. Further, to <lb/>determine which soluble factor mainly involves in MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation induced by CM <lb/>from DU145, neutralizing inhibitors were tested. According to the results of RT-PCR and <lb/>western blot, we have tested anti-mouse IL-6 receptor antibody (10µg/ml) and anti-human LIF <lb/>antibody (10µg/ml) (R&amp;D systems). Anti-goat IgG (10µg/ml, R&amp;D systems) was used as <lb/>negative control. These antibodies were pre-incubated with MC3T3-E1 cells or CM from <lb/>DU145 according to the antibodies for 1 hour before the experiment and maintained during the <lb/>culture period at the indicated concentration. <lb/>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			-Signal transduction analyses by Western Blot <lb/> MC3T3-E1 cells were seeded (10 4 cells/cm 2 ) into a 6-multiwell plate in DMEM supplemented <lb/>with 10% FBS. At 70-80% of confluence, MC3T3-E1 cells were washed three times with <lb/>DMEM, cultured in serum-free DMEM for 24 hours, and then the cells were incubated for 30 <lb/>minutes with CT CM. MC3T3-E1 cells were then incubated for 2, 5, 10, 15 and 30 minutes in <lb/>the presence or absence of CM from DU145 cells. After the treatments, cell lysates were <lb/>prepared as described above ( § signal transduction analyses) and subjected to western blot <lb/>analyses. The induction of the phosphorylated forms of ERK 1/2 (Thr202/Tyr204), p38 <lb/>(Thr180/Tyr182), signal transducer and activator of transduction (STAT)1 (Tyr701), STAT3 <lb/>(Tyr705) (Cell Signaling Technologies), STAT5 (ZYMED Laboratories, Invitrogen <lb/>immunodetection, San Francisco, CA, USA) and Akt (Ser473) (Cell Signaling Technologies) <lb/>were determined as well as total forms of ERK 1/2 (Cell Signaling Technologies), p38 (R&amp;D <lb/>systems), STAT1, STAT3, STAT5 (BD Biosciences, CA, USA) and Akt (Cell Signaling <lb/>Technologies). <lb/> -Alkaline Phosphatase (ALP) activity <lb/> Alkaline phosphatase (ALP) activity was determined in MC3T3-E1 cells as previously <lb/>reported [27] with slight modifications. Briefly, MC3T3-E1 cells were seeded into a <lb/>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			24-multiwell plate (5 x 10 3 cells/well) and cultured for 7 days in CT CM or CM from DU145 <lb/>cells supplemented with 5% FBS and 50µg/ml ascorbic acid (Sigma). At the end of the culture <lb/>period, cells were lysed in ice-cold buffer [NaCl 150mM, Tris 50mM, Nonidet P-40 1%, <lb/>sodium deoxycholate 0.25%, NaF 1mM, leupeptine 10mg/ml, aprotinin 10mg/ml, PMSF <lb/>0.5mM]. ALP activity was determined by Enzyline PAL kit (BioMérieux, Marcy l&apos;Etoile, <lb/>France) according to the supplier&apos;s recommendations. <lb/> - Mineralization assay <lb/> Alizarin red-S staining was used to detect the mineralized nodule formation in vitro as <lb/>previously reported [27] with slight modifications. Briefly, mouse bone marrow cells were <lb/>cultured in the absence or presence of DU145 cells for 14 days in α-MEM containing 10 -8 M <lb/>dexamethasone (Sigma), 50µg/ml ascorbic acid (Sigma) and 10mM Na-β-glycerophosphate <lb/>(Sigma) was also added for the last 7 days of the culture. Adherent cells were washed with PBS, <lb/>and then fixed in ice-cold 70% ethanol for 1 hour. The fixed cells were washed with distilled <lb/>water and incubated with alizarin red-S (Merck KGaA, Darmstadt, Germany, 40mM, pH 7.4) <lb/>for 10 minutes at room temperature. After extensive washing, the presence of mineralized <lb/>nodes was revealed by light microscopy. <lb/> Statistical analysis <lb/>

			<page> 18 <lb/></page>

			Represented data are the results of three independent studies at least. Mann-Whitney&apos;s <lb/> U test was used to assess differences in experimental groups. P values less than 0.05 were <lb/>considered statistically significant. <lb/> Results <lb/> Human prostate cancer cell lines DU145 and PC3 express RANK and OPG <lb/> The expression of the molecular triad RANKL/RANK/OPG was analysed in both <lb/>DU145 and PC3 human prostate cancer cell lines. RT-PCR analyses revealed that both cell <lb/>lines were positive for RANK and OPG but negative for RANKL at the transcript level (Figure <lb/>1). We further analyzed major cytokines expressions that involving tumor-bone cells <lb/>cross-talks through STAT3 signal transduction pathway. Both cell lines were positive for IL-6 <lb/>and LIF; however negative for IL-11 and OSM at the transcript level (Figure 1). <lb/>Immunocytochemical analyses confirmed the positive RANK expression at the protein level in <lb/>DU145 and PC3 human prostate cancer cell lines, mainly at the cell membrane level (Figure 2). <lb/> RANKL induces ERK 1/2, p38 and Iκ  κ κ <lb/>κB  phosphorylation in RANK-expressing prostate <lb/>cancer cells <lb/>

			<page> 19 <lb/></page>

			As RANK expression was confirmed at the protein level, we further studied its <lb/>functionality by western blot which signalling pathways were activated when RANK-positive <lb/>prostate cancer cells were incubated with 100ng/ml shRANKL. Represented results in Figure <lb/>3A showed an acute activation of ERK 1/2, p38 and IκB phosphorylation respectively after 5, 2 <lb/>and 15 minutes incubation as compared to the corresponding total forms in DU145 cells. <lb/>shRANKL treatment (100ng/ml) also induced acute activation of ERK 1/2 phosphorylation in <lb/>PC3 cells after 2 minutes incubation; however the magnitude was lower than that of in DU145 <lb/>cells (Figure 3B). These results revealed that RANKL is able to activate signal transduction <lb/>pathways in RANK-expressing prostate cancer cells as well as its receptor (RANK) on these <lb/>cells is functional. <lb/> RANKL stimulates DU145 and PC3 cell migration <lb/> In a second set of experiments, we studied whether RANKL could induce biological <lb/>activity in RANK-positive prostate cancer cells, DU145 and PC3. Migration experiments <lb/>showed that shRANKL treatment significantly promoted DU145 cell invasion on the slit made <lb/>in the DU145 confluent well compared to that of the control group in a dose-dependent manner <lb/>(Figures 4A, b and c compared to a). Whereas treatment with 100ng/ml hOPG alone has no <lb/>marked effect on cell invasion (Figure 4A, d compared to a), the combined association of hOPG <lb/>with shRANKL at a shRANKL:hOPG ratio of 1:5 (pre-incubated) abolished the <lb/>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			shRANKL-induced cell invasion on the slit (Figure 4A, e). Several inhibitors of signal <lb/>transduction pathways were then used to determine which pathway was involved in this effect. <lb/>Among the specific inhibitors tested, only UO126, a MEK/ERK inhibitor partially inhibited <lb/>RANKL-induced cell invasion (Figure 4A, g compared to f), whereas other inhibitors tested <lb/>showed no significant effects (data not shown). shRANKL treatment also induce PC3 cell <lb/>invasion on the slit made in the PC3 confluent well compared to the control group (Figure 4A, i <lb/>compared to h); however DU145 cells were more sensitive for RANKL treatment. Thus, further <lb/>analyses were performed using DU145 cells. The invasion magnitude was further quantified by <lb/>slit time lapse assay using DU145 cells. The areas of the slit invaded during 24 hours by DU145 <lb/>cells were significantly increased in the presence of 100ng/ml shRANKL compared to the <lb/>control group (respectively 1.19x10 5 ± 0.135x10 5 µm 2 and 1.04x10 5 ± 0.0588x10 5 µm 2 , p=0.02, <lb/>Figure 4B). <lb/> RANKL does not influence DU145 cell proliferation <lb/> Additional experiments were performed to see whether RANKL-induced stimulation <lb/>of DU145 cell invasion could be the consequence of an up-regulated cell proliferation. Neither <lb/>XTT assay nor manual cell counting could demonstrate any significant difference of DU145 <lb/>cell proliferation after shRANKL treatment (100ng/ml). These results were corroborated by the <lb/>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			absence of significant difference in the percentage of cell division quantified by the time lapse <lb/>assay (50.3% vs 52.4%, p=0.56). <lb/> DU145 cells produce soluble factor(s) that stimulate osteoclastogenesis <lb/> Co-cultures of DU145 cells with osteoclast precursors generated from mouse bone <lb/>marrow cells were used to analyse the influence of prostate cancer cells on osteoclastogenesis. <lb/>We demonstrated that DU145 prostate cancer cells up-regulated osteoclastogenesis around <lb/>20% despite the presence of culture chambers or not (p&lt;0.05) (Figure 5). The similar results <lb/>observed with direct contact or separate co-culture in chambers revealed that cell-cell contact is <lb/>not necessary for osteoclastogenesis induced by DU145 cells. The induction of multinucleated <lb/>osteoclasts was not observed in the absence of shRANKL even the TRAP-positive <lb/>mononuclear cells were scarcely observed. Increased shRANKL treatment (200ng/ml) has <lb/>same effect of DU145 cell-induced osteoclastogenesis compared to 100ng/ml shRANKL <lb/>treatment (Figure 5). <lb/> DU145 effects on the MC3T3-E1 mouse pre-osteoblastic cell line <lb/>-Soluble factor(s) produced by DU145 cells stimulate MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation <lb/> When CM from DU145 cells was added to MC3T3-E1 cells, it induced a significant <lb/>up-regulation of pre-osteoblastic cell proliferation by more than 100% (p&lt;0.001, Figure 6A). <lb/>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			CM from DU145 cells incubated with shRANKL has similar effect on MC3T3-E1 cell <lb/>proliferation (Figure 6A). Suramin, a pan-growth factor blocker, significantly abrogated the <lb/>stimulation of MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation induced by CM from DU145 cells in a <lb/>dose-dependent manner (Figure 6B). These results demonstrated that prostate cancer cells <lb/>produce growth factor(s) that are able to stimulate the pre-osteoblast cell proliferation. Among <lb/>neutralizing inhibitors used, anti-mouse IL-6 receptor antibody partially abrogated CM from <lb/>DU145-induced MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation (Figure 6C). <lb/> - Conditioned medium from DU145 cells activates the ERK 1/2 and STAT3 signal <lb/>transduction pathways in pre-osteoblast cells <lb/> We further studied which signal transduction pathways were activated in the DU145 <lb/>cell-induced stimulation of pre-osteoblast cells proliferation. When MC3T3-E1 cells were <lb/>incubated in the presence of CM from DU145 cells, a huge activation of ERK 1/2 and STAT3 <lb/>phosphorylations were observed after 2 and 15 minutes, respectively (Figure 7). <lb/> -Conditioned medium from DU145 cells does not modulate ALP activity and mineralized <lb/>nodule formation in pre-osteoblasts <lb/> To see whether soluble factor(s) produced by DU145 prostate cancer cells can <lb/>modulate osteoblast activity, ALP activity and mineralization assays were studied in <lb/>

			<page>23 <lb/></page>

			MC3T3-E1 cells. CM from DU145 cells treatment modified neither ALP activity nor <lb/>mineralized nodule formation in MC3T3-E1 cells (data not shown). <lb/>These overall data demonstrated that DU145 human prostate cancer cells are able to <lb/>modulate bone cells behaviour by inducing osteoclastogenesis and stimulating pre-osteoblast <lb/>proliferation through the activation of ERK 1/2 and STAT3 signal transduction pathways. <lb/> Discussion <lb/> The present study was designed to better characterize the involvement of the <lb/>RANKL-RANK axis in the regulation of bone cells-prostate cancer cells interactions. First, we <lb/>demonstrated the functional RANK expression at the surface of DU145 and PC3 human <lb/>prostate cancer cells. The functionality of this receptor was further evidenced as the shRANKL <lb/>administration promoted human prostate cancer cell invasion in vitro, which was the result of <lb/>the increased cell migration rather than the increased cell proliferation. <lb/>Second, we demonstrated that DU145 cells produced soluble factor(s) that act on cells <lb/>in bone microenvironment by enhancing mouse pre-osteoblast cell proliferation and inducing <lb/>osteoclastogenesis. These overall results clearly demonstrate the complex cross-talks between <lb/>bone cells and cancer cells during prostate tumor development in bone. <lb/>Because DU145 cells have shown better response to RANKL treatment compared to <lb/>PC3 cells (signal transduction analysis and migration assay), we performed further analyses <lb/>using DU145 cells. DU145 cells were known to brain metastatic cell line; however an in vivo <lb/> model of prostate cancer growth in bone by intratibial inoculation of DU145 cells has been <lb/>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			established [28]. In this model, an increase in number of osteoclasts cells was observed similar <lb/>to PC3 cell model; it is therefore rational to analyze prostate cancer cells-bone cells interaction <lb/>using this cell line. <lb/>RANK expressed at the surface of osteoclasts is the essential signalling receptor for <lb/>osteoclast differentiation [12, 14, 15, 20]. However its expression is not restricted to this cell <lb/>type, as it was also observed in other tissue including mammary gland [29], lung [20], brain <lb/>[20], kidney [20] and hypertrophic chondrocytes [15]. Recently, functional RANK expression <lb/>on tumor cells was reported by our laboratory [21] and others [22, 30]. Indeed, we have recently <lb/>reported the expression of functional RANK in POS-1 mouse osteosarcoma cells [21]. In these <lb/>RANK-expressing cells, RANKL induced the expression of BMP-2 and slightly inhibited <lb/>osteosarcoma cell proliferation [21]. Moreover, RANK expression was confirmed in other <lb/>osteosarcoma cell lines from human origin (MG63, Saos-2 and MNNG-HOS) together with <lb/>some human osteosarcoma specimens in both at the transcript and protein levels (Mori K et al. <lb/> submitted). In addition, Jones et al. have more recently reported the expression of functional <lb/>RANK on human breast cancer (MDA-MB231, Hs578T, MCF7), human prostate cancer <lb/>(LNCaP, DU145) and mouse melanoma (B16F10) cell lines [30]. As we demonstrated <lb/>RANKL-induced RANK-positive DU145 cell migration in the present study, Jones et al. also <lb/>observed RANKL-triggered migration of RANK-expressing human epithelial cancer cells and <lb/>melanoma cells. <lb/>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			The biological functionality of RANK has been also revealed through the activation <lb/>including ERK 1/2, p38 and IκB pathways, the most reported pathways in the literature [31], in <lb/>response to RANKL. However, the result of RANKL-induced migration of DU145 cells is only <lb/>partially mediated by the MEK/ERK pathway suggesting the involvement of other down stream <lb/>signalling pathways that remain to be determined. <lb/>Although both DU145 and PC3 human prostate cancer cells did not express RANKL <lb/>at the transcript level in our in vitro condition, RANKL is abundant in bone environment, thus <lb/>being able to bind to RANK expressed on prostate cancer cells in a paracrine (soluble RANKL) <lb/>and/or juxtacrine (membranous RANKL) manner. Therefore, RANKL has two potential targets <lb/>in this tumoral bone environment (Figure 8): one is osteoclasts/osteoclast precursors and the <lb/>other is RANK-positive prostate cancer cells. RANKL through its binding to RANK expressed <lb/>on osteoclast/osteoclast precursors increases osteoclastic activity leading to bone degradation <lb/>that allows the release of tumor-supportive growth factors stocked in the bone matrix. These <lb/>factors stimulate the vicious cycle that takes place between osteolytic process and tumor <lb/>development in bone site [32]. The bone degradation may also provide enough space for <lb/>subsequent RANK-positive prostate cancer cell migration enhanced by RANKL. Thus, RANK <lb/>expressed on both osteoclasts and prostate cancer cells in tumoral bone microenvironment has a <lb/>propensity for prostate cancer bone metastasis development by synergic effect. Indeed, despite <lb/>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			its overall osteoblastic profile, recent evidences suggested the significant involvement of <lb/>osteolytic lesion preceding osteoblastic prostate cancer bone metastasis development [4-9]. <lb/>The RANKL/RANK/OPG triad represents the key regulator of bone metabolism in <lb/>both normal and pathological condition [10]. Recent findings strongly suggested the significant <lb/>involvement of this triad as therapeutic targets in prostate cancer bone metastasis [6-9, 11, 30]. <lb/>Indeed, it has been reported that two cytokines, OPG and soluble RANK (sRANK)-Fc blocked <lb/>RANKL activity and significantly diminished prostate cancer progression in bone tissue [6, 7, <lb/>9]. In these studies, the effect of such cytokines is indirect on tumor progression as OPG or <lb/>sRANK-Fc did not exert direct effect on tumor growth and viability in vitro. Moreover, Zhang <lb/> et al. failed to demonstrate OPG-/sRANK-Fc-induced tumor cell growth inhibition in <lb/>non-osseous tissue (subcutaneous) in vivo [6, 7]. These results suggested that the tumor cell <lb/>growth inhibition induced by OPG or sRANK-Fc was mediated via the bone microenvironment <lb/>rather than the direct effect on tumor cells [6, 7]. The results of the present study provide the <lb/>evidence that RANKL can directly affects RANK-positive prostate cancer cells by inducing <lb/>their migration. To reveal visible RANKL-induced prostate cancer cell migration, it is <lb/>necessary to provide enough space where they can migrate. In bone tissue, RANKL can activate <lb/>osteoclasts/osteoclast precursors that initiate bone degradation, providing such space for tumor <lb/>cell migration. Thus, the previously reported OPG-/sRANK-Fc-induced tumor growth <lb/>inhibition might be partially due to the direct effect on the RANK-positive prostate cancer cells <lb/>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			by reducing RANKL-induced tumor cell migration. Therefore, a therapeutic approach using <lb/>exogenous OPG or sRANK-Fc administration may be suggested even if they don&apos;t affect cell <lb/>proliferation or survival, because these agents could inhibit tumor cell migration. This effect <lb/>could be additional to the direct inhibition of bone resorption, leading to a resultant decrease of <lb/>tumor growth. <lb/>Alternatively, we investigated the role of prostate cancer cells on osteoclast and <lb/>osteoblast cells. Using osteoclast precursors generated from mouse bone marrow cells, we <lb/>demonstrated that DU145 cells secreted soluble factor(s) that increase RANKL-mediated <lb/>osteoclastogenesis by around 20%. However, Inoue et al. have reported that DU145 cells can <lb/>significantly induce osteoclastogenesis through RANKL-dependent and -independent <lb/>pathways [5]. The likely explanation of this discrepancy between their results and ours may be <lb/>due to the different culture condition. In the present study, increased number of TRAP-positive <lb/>multinucleated osteoclasts was observed in direct co-culture compared to separate co-culture <lb/>using culture chamber. Different microenvironment caused by culture chamber in our system <lb/>(i.e., fluid stress, CO 2 supply etc,) was suspected the reason for this discrepancy. Indeed, it has <lb/>been reported that oscillatory fluid flow-induced shear stress modify RANKL/OPG ratio and <lb/>resulted in a decrease in osteoclast formation [33]. Interestingly, it was able to observe that CM <lb/>from DU145 cells significantly up-regulated MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation and activated ERK <lb/>1/2 and STAT3 signal transduction pathways without marked change in MC3T3-E1 cell <lb/>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			differentiation. No marked effect of RANKL via RANK-positive DU145 cell on pre-osteoblast <lb/>proliferation and osteoclastogenesis was observed. As suramin, a pan growth factor blocker, <lb/>inhibited MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation induced by CM from DU145 cells, it can be suggested <lb/>that DU145 cells produce more than one kind of growth factor that up-regulate MC3T3-E1 <lb/>proliferation. Therefore, further studies are performed to identify the pre-osteoblast <lb/>proliferation promoting factor(s) secreted by DU145 cells. The results of pre-osteoblastic cell <lb/>proliferation assay with neutralizing inhibitors indicated that IL-6 secreted by DU145 cells has <lb/>a partial role in DU145-induced MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation, however further studies are <lb/>needed to identify other pre-osteoblast proliferation promoting factor(s) secreted by DU145 <lb/>cells. IL-6 has long been considered as an osteoresorptive factor; however recent data indicate <lb/>that IL-6 could influence osteoblastic cells, especially in the presence of soluble IL-6 receptor <lb/>[34, 35]. It has been reported that DU145 notably augmented the secretion of soluble IL-6 <lb/>receptor in certain condition [36]. Interestingly, it has been reported that IL-6 contribute <lb/>prostate cancer cell growth and IL-6 blockade achieved prostate cancer growth inhibition [37, <lb/>38]. Thus, IL-6 blockade is able to interfere with the vicious cycle in tumoral bone environment <lb/>by not only induce prostate tumor regression, but also inhibit prostate cancer cell-induced <lb/>pre-osteoblast cell proliferation. <lb/>Furthermore, it has been recently reported that CM from DU145 cells increases the <lb/>local RANKL/OPG ratio by stimulating RANKL expression without any change in OPG&apos;s [5]. <lb/>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			Thus DU145 cells may stimulate both osteoclast and RANK-positive prostate cancer cells in <lb/>tumoral bone environment by increasing local RANKL expression, resulting in activation of <lb/>the vicious cycle (Figure 8). <lb/>These findings are all consistent with a high trend of prostate cancer metastases to <lb/>bone. Since Paget has suggested his &quot; seed and soil &quot; theory [39], the factors involved have been <lb/>unknown for a long time. However, the unique anatomical structure of bone marrow vessels has <lb/>been suggested to represent one of the factors that contribute to &quot; seed &quot; tumor cells into bone <lb/>environment. A positive correlation has been reported between constant expressions of RANK <lb/>with decreased/absent expression of RANKL and a high metastatic phenotype in breast <lb/>carcinoma [40]. Taken together, we suggest that RANK-positive cells are starving RANKL and <lb/>preferentially attracted by RANKL rich bone environment, where RANKL acts as a &apos;soil&apos; <lb/>factor that facilitates bone metastases development by activating both kinds of RANK-positive <lb/>cells (osteoclast/osteoclast precursors and prostate cancer cells). However, further studies are <lb/>needed to determine how RANKL is involved in the recruitment of RANK-positive tumor cells <lb/>to bone environment. <lb/>In conclusion, the present study reveals the evidence that blocking RANKL-RANK <lb/>interaction offer new therapeutic approach not only at the level of bone resorbing cells, but also <lb/>by interfering with RANK-positive prostate cancer cells in the bone metastasis development. <lb/>

			</body>
			
			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/> This work was supported by INSERM, The Région des Pays de la Loire and by a grant from the <lb/>West Committee of the Ligue Contre le Cancer. Kanji Mori received a personal fellowship <lb/>from the Ligue Nationale Contre le Cancer. <lb/></div>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Landis SH, Murray T, Bolden S, Wingo PA. Cancer statistics, 1999. CA Cancer J Clin 1999; <lb/>49: 8-31. <lb/>2. Mundy GR. Metastasis to bone: causes, consequences and therapeutic opportunities. Nat Rev <lb/>Cancer 2002; 2: 584-93. <lb/>3. Clarke NW, McClure J, George NJ. Morphometric evidence for bone resorption and <lb/>replacement in prostate cancer. Br J Urol 1991; 68: 74-80. <lb/>4. Garnero P, Buchs N, Zekri J, Rizzoli R, Coleman RE, Delmas PD. Markers of bone turnover <lb/>for the management of patients with bone metastases from prostate cancer. Br J Cancer 2000; <lb/>82: 858-64. <lb/>5. Inoue H, Nishimura K, Oka D, Nakai Y, Shiba M, Tokizane T, Arai Y, Nakayama M, <lb/>Shimizu K, Takaha N, Nonomura N, Okuyama A. Prostate cancer mediates osteoclastogenesis <lb/>through two different pathways. Cancer Lett 2005; 223: 121-8. <lb/>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			6. Zhang J, Dai J, Qi Y, Lin DL, Smith P, Strayhorn C, Mizokami A, Fu Z, Westman J, Keller <lb/>ET. Osteoprotegerin inhibits prostate cancer-induced osteoclastogenesis and prevents prostate <lb/>tumor growth in the bone. J Clin Invest 2001; 107: 1235-44. <lb/>7. Zhang J, Dai J, Yao Z, Lu Y, Dougall W, Keller ET. Soluble receptor activator of nuclear <lb/>factor κB Fc diminishes prostate cancer progression in bone. Cancer Res 2003; 63: 7883-90. <lb/>8. Corey E, Brown LG, Kiefer JA, Quinn JE, Pitts TE, Blair JM, Vessella RL. Osteoprotegerin <lb/>in prostate cancer bone metastasis. Cancer Res 2005; 65: 1710-8. <lb/>9. Whang PG, Schwarz EM, Gamradt SC, Dougall WC, Lieberman JR. The effects of RANK <lb/>blockade and osteoclast depletion in a model of pure osteoblastic prostate cancer metastasis in <lb/>bone. J Orthop Res 2005; 23: 1475-83. <lb/>10. Théoleyre S, Wittrant Y, Tat SK, Fortun Y, Rédini F, Heymann D. The molecular triad <lb/>OPG/RANK/RANKL: involvement in the orchestration of pathophysiological bone <lb/>remodeling. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev 2004; 15: 457-75. <lb/>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			11. Hofbauer LC, Neubauer A, Heufelder AE. Receptor activator of nuclear factor-kappaB <lb/>ligand and osteoprotegerin: potential implications for the pathogenesis and treatment of <lb/>malignant bone diseases. Cancer 2001; 92: 460-70. <lb/>12. Kong YY, Yoshida H, Sarosi I, Tan HL, Timms E, Capparelli C, Morony S, <lb/>Oliveira-dos-Santos AJ, Van G, Itie A, Khoo W, Wakeham A, Dunstan CR, Lacey DL, Mak <lb/>TW, Boyle WJ, Penninger JM. OPGL is a key regulator of osteoclastogenesis, lymphocyte <lb/>development and lymph-node organogenesis. Nature 1999; 397: 315-23. <lb/>13. Burgess TL, Qian Y, Kaufman S, Ring BD, Van G, Capparelli C, Kelley M, Hsu H, Boyle <lb/>WJ, Dunstan CR, Hu S, Lacey DL. The ligand for osteoprotegerin (OPGL) directly activates <lb/>mature osteoclasts. J Cell Biol 1999; 145: 327-38. <lb/>14. Lacey DL, Timms E, Tan HL, Kelley MJ, Dunstan CR, Burgess T, Elliott R, Colombero A, <lb/>Elliott G, Scully S, Hsu H, Sullivan J, Hawkins N, Davy E, Capparelli C, Eli A, Qian YX, <lb/>Kaufman S, Sarosi I, Shalhoub V, Senaldi G, Guo J, Delaney J, Boyle WJ. Osteoprotegerin <lb/>ligand is a cytokine that regulates osteoclast differentiation and activation. Cell 1998; 93: <lb/>165-76. <lb/>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			15. Hsu H, Lacey DL, Dunstan CR, Solovyev I, Colombero A, Timms E, Tan HL, Elliott G, <lb/>Kelley MJ, Sarosi I, Wang L, Xia XZ, Elliott R, Chiu L, Black T, Scully S, Capparelli C, <lb/>Morony S, Shimamoto G, Bass MB, Boyle WJ. Tumor necrosis factor receptor family member <lb/>RANK mediates osteoclast differentiation and activation induced by osteoprotegerin ligand. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 1999; 96: 3540-5. <lb/>16. Wittrant Y, Théoleyre S, Chipoy C, Padrines M, Blanchard F, Heymann D, Rédini F. <lb/>RANKL/RANK/OPG: new therapeutic targets in bone tumors and associated osteolysis. <lb/>Biochimica Biophysica Acta 2004; 1704: 49-57. <lb/>17. Brown JM, Corey E, Lee ZD, True LD, Yun TJ, Tondravi M, Vessella RL. Osteoprotegerin <lb/>and rank ligand expression in prostate cancer. Urology 2001; 57: 611-6. <lb/>18. Brown JM, Vessella RL, Kostenuik PJ, Dunstan CR, Lange PH, Corey E. Serum <lb/>osteoprotegerin levels are increased in patients with advanced prostate cancer. Clin Cancer Res <lb/>2001; 7: 2977-83. <lb/>19. Holen I, Croucher PI, Hamdy FC, Eaton CL. Osteoprotegerin (OPG) is a survival factor for <lb/>human prostate cancer cells. Cancer Res 2002; 62: 1619-23. <lb/>

			<page>35 <lb/></page>

			20. Nakagawa N, Kinosaki M, Yamaguchi K, Shima N, Yasuda H, Yano K, Morinaga T, <lb/>Higashio K. RANK is the essential signaling receptor for osteoclast differentiation factor in <lb/>osteoclastogenesis. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 1998; 253: 395-400. <lb/>21. Wittrant Y, Lamoureux F, Mori K, Riet A, Kamijo A, Heymann D, Rédini F. RANKL <lb/>directly induces bone morphogenetic protein-2 expression in RANK-expressing POS-1 <lb/>osteosarcoma cells. Int J Oncol 2006; 28: 261-9. <lb/>22. Tometsko M, Armstrong A, Miller R, Jones J, Chaisson M, Branstetter D, Dougall W. <lb/>RANK Ligand directly induces osteoclastogenic, angiogenic, chemoattractive and invasive <lb/>factors on RANK-expressing human cancer cells MDA-MB-231 and PC3. J Bone Miner Res <lb/>2004; 19: S25. <lb/>23. Chirgwin JM, Guise TA. Molecular mechanisms of tumor-bone interactions in osteolytic <lb/>metastases. Crit Rev Eukaryot Gene Expr 2000; 10: 159-78. <lb/>24. Chirgwin JM, Mohammad KS, Guise TA. Tumor-bone cellular interactions in skeletal <lb/>metastases. J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact 2004; 4: 308-18. <lb/>

			<page>36 <lb/></page>

			25. Guise TA, Chirgwin JM. Transforming growth factor-beta in osteolytic breast cancer bone <lb/>metastases. Clin Orthop Relat Res 2003; 415 (suppl): S32-8. <lb/>26. Hansen MB, Nielsen SE, Berg K. Re-examination and further development of a precise and <lb/>rapid dye method for measuring cell growth/cell kill. J Immunol Methods 1989; 119: 203-10. <lb/>27. Chipoy C, Berreur M, Couillaud S, Pradal G, Vallette F, Colombeix C, Rédini F, Heymann <lb/>D, Blanchard F. Downregulation of osteoblast markers and induction of the glial fibrillary <lb/>acidic protein by oncostatin M in osteosarcoma cells require PKCdelta and STAT3. J Bone <lb/>Miner Res 2004; 19: 1850-61. <lb/>28. Fisher JL, Schmitt JF, Howard ML, Mackie PS, Choong PF, Risbridger GP. An in vivo <lb/>model of prostate carcinoma growth and invasion in bone. Cell Tissue Res 2002; 307: 337-45. <lb/>29. Srivastava S, Matsuda M, Hou Z, Bailey JP, Kitazawa R, Herbst MP, Horseman ND. <lb/>Receptor activator of NF-kappaB ligand induction via Jak2 and Stat5a in mammary epithelial <lb/>cells. J Biol Chem 2003; 278: 46171-8. <lb/>

			<page>37 <lb/></page>

			30. Jones DH, Nakashima T, Sanchez OH, Kozieradzki I, Komarova SV, Sarosi I, Morony S, <lb/>Rubin E, Sarao R, Hojilla CV, Komnenovic V, Kong YY, Schreiber M, Dixon SJ, Sims SM, <lb/>Khokha R, Wada T, Penninger JM. Regulation of cancer cell migration and bone metastasis by <lb/>RANKL. Nature 2006; 440: 692-6. <lb/>31. Lee ZH, Kim HH. Signal transduction by receptor activator of nuclear factor kappa B in <lb/>osteoclasts. Biochem Biophys Res Commun 2003; 305: 211-4. <lb/>32. Guise TA. The vicious cycle of bone metastases. J Musculoskelet Neuronal Interact 2002; <lb/>2: 570-2. <lb/>33. Kim CH, You L, Yellowley CE, Jacobs CR. Oscillatory fluid flow-induced shear stress <lb/>decreases osteoclastogenesis through RANKL and OPG signaling. Bone 2006 Epub. <lb/>34. Kwan Tat S, Padrines M, Theoleyre S, Heymann D, Fortun Y. IL-6, RANKL, <lb/>TNF-alpha/IL-1: interrelations in bone resorption pathophysiology. Cytokine Growth Factor <lb/>Rev 2004; 15: 49-60. <lb/>

			<page>38 <lb/></page>

			35. Franchimont N, Wertz S, Malaise M. Interleukin-6: An osteotropic factor influencing bone <lb/>formation? Bone 2005; 37: 601-6. <lb/>36. Mori S, Murakami-Mori K, Bonavida B. Dexamethasone enhances expression of <lb/>membrane and soluble interleukin-6 receptors by prostate carcinoma cell lines. Anticancer Res <lb/>1998; 18: 4403-8. <lb/>37. Chung TD, Yu JJ, Spiotto MT, Bartkowski M, Simons JW. Characterization of the role of <lb/>IL-6 in the progression of prostate cancer. Prostate 1999; 38: 199-207. <lb/>38. Smith PC, Hobisch A, Lin DL, Culig Z, Keller ET. Interleukin-6 and prostate cancer <lb/>progression. Cytokine Growth Factor Rev 2001; 12: 33-40. <lb/>39. Paget S. The distrubution of secondary growths in cancer of the breast. Lancet 1889; 1: <lb/>571-2. <lb/>40. Bhatia P, Sanders MM, Hansen MF. Expression of receptor activator of nuclear <lb/>factor-kappaB is inversely correlated with metastatic phenotype in breast carcinoma. Clin <lb/>Cancer Res 2005; 11: 162-5. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>39 <lb/></page>

			<body> Figure legends <lb/>Figure 1. Human prostate cancer cells DU145 and PC3 express OPG, RANK, IL-6 and <lb/>LIF at the transcriptional level. The expression of Receptor Activator of NF-κB Ligand <lb/>(RANKL), RANK, osteoprotegerin (OPG), interleukin (IL)-6, IL-11, oncostatin M (OSM) and <lb/>leukemia inhibitory factor (LIF) was analyzed in human prostate cancer cells DU145 and PC3 <lb/>by semi-quantitative RT-PCR according to the condition described in the Materials and <lb/>Methods section. <lb/> Figure 2. Immunodetection of RANK in human prostate cancer cell lines DU145 and PC3. <lb/> Immunocytochemistry of RANK in DU145 (A) and PC3 (C) cells is represented together with <lb/>respective negative controls (B, D). Original magnification: x400. <lb/> Figure 3. RANKL induces signal transduction pathways in RANK-positive DU145 and <lb/>PC3 cells. At 70-80% of confluence, DU145 and PC3 cells were serum starved for 24 hours, <lb/>then incubated for the indicated times in the absence or presence of 100ng/ml soluble human <lb/>RANKL. Aliquots of whole cell lysates were analyzed by immunoblotting for phospho-ERK <lb/>1/2, p38 and Iκ-B, and the corresponding total forms, as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section. (A) DU145 cells, (B) PC3 cells. <lb/>

			<page>40 <lb/></page>

			Figure 4. RANKL increases DU145 cell migration via the MEK/ERK pathway. (A) <lb/> Treatment of DU145 cells with soluble human RANKL (shRANKL, 5, 100ng/ml) promoted <lb/>cell invasion on the slit made in the DU145 confluent wells in a dose-dependent manner (a-c). <lb/>The effects of human OPG (hOPG) alone or in association with shRANKL (shRANKL:hOPG <lb/>ratio of 1:5) were studied following the same experimental condition (d, e). Several inhibitors <lb/>of signal transduction pathways were tested in the same way [UO126, a MEK/ERK inhibitor <lb/>(10µM); SB 203580, a p38 inhibitor (10µM) and SN 50, a NF-κB translocation inhibitor <lb/>(18µM)]. Only UO126 partially inhibited RANKL-induced stimulation of DU145 cell <lb/>migration (f, g). Treatment of PC3 cells with 100ng/ml shRANKL also promoted cell invasion <lb/>on the slit made in the PC3 confluent well (h, i); however the magnitude was smaller than that <lb/>of DU145. (B) Kinetic study of the RANKL-induced DU145 cell migration. The kinetic of <lb/>DU145 cell invasion was quantified and compared in the absence and presence of 100ng/ml <lb/>shRANKL by slit time lapse assay. The results are the mean of total invaded areas of three <lb/>distinct sections on the slit per 24 hours. *p=0.02, Mann-Whitney&apos;s U test. <lb/> Figure 5. Soluble factor(s) secreted by DU145 cells promote osteoclastogenesis. Osteoclast <lb/>precursors were generated from mouse bone marrow as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section. They were incubated for 7 days in the absence or presence of DU145 cells (10 3 cells for <lb/>10 6 osteoclast precursors) in direct contact or separate condition using culture chambers in <lb/>

			<page>41 <lb/></page>

			different soluble human RANKL concentrations (0-200ng/ml). *p&lt;0.05 (with DU145 cells vs <lb/>without DU145 cells), Mann-Whitney&apos;s U test. <lb/> Figure 6. Conditioned medium from DU145 cells significantly up-regulates the <lb/>MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation. (A) The mouse pre-osteoblast MC3T3-E1 cells were cultured <lb/>for 72 hours in control conditioned medium (CT CM) or CM from DU145 cells in the presence <lb/>or absence of 100ng/ml soluble human RANKL as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section. Cell proliferation was determined using a XTT based method. *p&lt;0.001 (CM from <lb/>DU145 cells vs CT CM), Mann-Whitney&apos;s U test. (B) The effect of suramin, a pan growth <lb/>factor blocker was studied on MC3T3-E1 cell proliferation by trypan blue exclusion. <lb/>**p&lt;0.001 (CM from DU145 cells vs others), Mann-Whitney&apos;s U test. CT CM: control <lb/>conditioned medium, CM: CM from DU145 cells, S50: suramin 50µg/ml, S100: suramin <lb/>100µg/ml. (C) Anti-mouse IL-6 receptor antibody (10µg/ml) and anti-human LIF antibody <lb/>(10µg/ml) were tested as described in the Materials and Methods section. Anti-mouse IL-6 <lb/>receptor antibody partially, but significantly abrogated DU145-induced MC3T3-E1 cell <lb/>proliferation.  †p=0.05 (CM from DU145 cells with anti-mouse IL-6 receptor antibody vs other <lb/>CM from DU145 group), Mann-Whitney&apos;s U test. <lb/>

			<page>42 <lb/></page>

			Figure 7. Soluble factor(s) secreted by DU145 cells induce phospho-ERK 1/2 and <lb/>phospho-STAT3 activation in MC3T3-E1 cells. At 70-80% of confluence, MC3T3-E1 cells <lb/>were washed three times with DMEM and cultured in serum-free DMEM for 24 hours, and then <lb/>incubated for 30 minutes with control conditioned medium (CT CM). MC3T3-E1 cells were <lb/>then incubated for 2, 5, 10, 15 and 30 minutes in the presence or absence of CM from DU145 <lb/>cells. After the treatments, cell lysates were prepared as described in the Materials and Methods <lb/>section and subjected to western blot analyses. <lb/> Figure 8. Schematic representation of the putative interactions between prostate cancer <lb/>cells and osteoblastic/osteoclastic cells in tumoral bone microenvironment. <lb/> RANK-positive prostate tumor cells preferentially target bone microenvironment where is rich <lb/>in RANKL. In tumoral bone environment, RANKL produced by osteoblasts and bone stromal <lb/>cells has two potential targets: osteoclast/osteoclast precursors and prostate cancer cells. <lb/>RANKL acts as a &apos;soil&apos; factor that facilitates prostate cancer metastasis development in bone by <lb/>activating both kinds of RANK-positive cells. <lb/>: RANKL, <lb/>: RANK, <lb/>: OPG, X: <lb/>soluble factor(s) produced by prostate cancer cells. <lb/> Figure  1 <lb/> 18S <lb/> RANK <lb/> RANKL <lb/> OPG <lb/> PC3 <lb/> DU145 <lb/> LIF <lb/> OSM <lb/> IL-11 <lb/> IL-6 <lb/> DU145 <lb/> PC3 <lb/> Figure  2 <lb/> PC3 <lb/> DU145 <lb/> RANK <lb/> Control <lb/> C <lb/> A <lb/> B <lb/> D <lb/> Figure  3A <lb/> Phospho-INB <lb/> Total-INB <lb/> Total-p38 <lb/> Phospho-p38 <lb/> Phospho-ERK 1/2 <lb/> Total-ERK 1/2 <lb/> 0 2 5 10 15 30 60 120 <lb/> Time (min.) <lb/> DU145 cells <lb/> shRANKL 100ng/ml <lb/> Figure 3B <lb/> 0 2 5 10 15 30 60 120 <lb/> Time (min.) <lb/> PC3 cells <lb/> shRANKL 100ng/ml <lb/> Phospho-ERK 1/2 <lb/> Total-ERK 1/2 <lb/> Figure  4A <lb/> 0H <lb/> 0H <lb/> 24H <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> 0ng/ml <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> 100ng/ml <lb/> h <lb/> i <lb/> PC3 cells <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> 0ng/ml <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> 5ng/ml <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> 100ng/ml <lb/> 24H <lb/> c <lb/> a <lb/> b <lb/> hOPG <lb/> 100ng/ml <lb/> shRANKL 100ng/ml <lb/> +UO126 10µM <lb/> shRANKL 50ng/ml <lb/> +hOPG 250ng/ml <lb/> d <lb/> e <lb/> f <lb/> g <lb/> shRANKL 0ng/ml <lb/> +UO126 10µM <lb/> DU145 cells <lb/> 0H <lb/> 24H <lb/> CT <lb/> RANKL <lb/> 0 <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> 1.2 <lb/> CT <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> Invaded areas on the slit (x10 5 µm2) <lb/> * <lb/> Figure 4B <lb/> Figure  5 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 200 <lb/> 400 <lb/> 600 <lb/> 800 <lb/> 1000 <lb/> 1200 <lb/> 1400 <lb/> Osteoclasts <lb/> / <lb/> well <lb/> Direct co-culture <lb/> * <lb/> Separate co-culture <lb/> ** <lb/> DU145 <lb/> - + <lb/> + <lb/>

			<page> -<lb/></page>

			Figure  6 <lb/> B <lb/> 0 <lb/> 4 <lb/> CT CM <lb/> CM <lb/> CM+S50 <lb/> CM+S100 <lb/> Days <lb/> 1 <lb/> 7 <lb/> ** <lb/> 1.0 <lb/> 0.6 <lb/> 0.4 <lb/> 1.4 <lb/> 0 <lb/> Cell number (x10 6 ) <lb/> * <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> 0,000 <lb/> 0,200 <lb/> 0,400 <lb/> 0,600 <lb/> 0,800 <lb/> 1,000 <lb/> 1,200 <lb/> OD 450 nm <lb/> CT CM <lb/> CM <lb/> (DU145) <lb/> shRANKL <lb/> (100ng/ml) <lb/> A <lb/> C <lb/> 0.000 <lb/> 0.200 <lb/> 0.400 <lb/> 0.600 <lb/> 0.800 <lb/> 1.000 <lb/> 1.200 <lb/> 1.400 <lb/> CT <lb/> CT CT <lb/> CM <lb/> CM CT <lb/> IL-6R <lb/> LIF <lb/> CM <lb/> (DU145) <lb/> CT CM <lb/>  †  † <lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> -<lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> Goat IgG <lb/> IL-6R <lb/> LIF <lb/> -<lb/> -<lb/> -<lb/> + <lb/> -<lb/> -<lb/>  † <lb/> Figure  7 <lb/> 0 <lb/> 2 <lb/> 5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 15 <lb/> 30 <lb/> Time (min.) <lb/> Phospho-STAT3 <lb/> Total-STAT3 <lb/> CM from DU145 cells <lb/> Phospho-ERK 1/2 <lb/> Total-ERK 1/2 <lb/> Figure  8 <lb/> Osteoblastic <lb/> Stromal Cells <lb/> Active <lb/> Osteoclast <lb/> Bone microenvironment <lb/> Osteoclast <lb/> Precursor <lb/> Tumor-supportive <lb/> growth factors <lb/> Tumor cell <lb/> migration <lb/> X <lb/> Pre-osteoblast cells <lb/> proliferation <lb/> Prostate cancer cells <lb/> Osteoblastic <lb/> Stromal Cells <lb/> osteoclastogenesis </body>


	</text>
</tei>
