<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Multiscale Agent-Based and Hybrid Modeling of the Tumor <lb/>Immune Microenvironment <lb/>Kerri-Ann Norton #1,2,* , Chang Gong #1 , Samira Jamalian #1 , and Aleksander S. Popel 1,3 <lb/>1 Department of Biomedical Engineering, School of Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, <lb/>Baltimore, MD 21205, USA <lb/>2 Computer Science Program, Department of Science, Mathematics, and Computing, Bard <lb/>College, Annandale-on-Hudson, NY 12504, USA <lb/>3 Department of Oncology and the Sidney Kimmel Comprehensive Cancer Center, School of <lb/>Medicine, Johns Hopkins University, Baltimore, MD 21205, USA <lb/># These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Multiscale systems biology and systems pharmacology are powerful methodologies that are <lb/>playing increasingly important roles in understanding the fundamental mechanisms of biological <lb/>phenomena and in clinical applications. In this review, we summarize the state of the art in the <lb/>applications of agent-based models (ABM) and hybrid modeling to the tumor immune <lb/>microenvironment and cancer immune response, including immunotherapy. Heterogeneity is a <lb/>hallmark of cancer; tumor heterogeneity at the molecular, cellular, and tissue scales is a major <lb/>determinant of metastasis, drug resistance, and low response rate to molecular targeted therapies <lb/>and immunotherapies. Agent-based modeling is an effective methodology to obtain and <lb/>understand quantitative characteristics of these processes and to propose clinical solutions aimed <lb/>at overcoming the current obstacles in cancer treatment. We review models focusing on intra-<lb/>tumor heterogeneity, particularly on interactions between cancer cells and stromal cells, including <lb/>immune cells, the role of tumor-associated vasculature in the immune response, immune-related <lb/>tumor mechanobiology, and cancer immunotherapy. We discuss the role of digital pathology in <lb/>parameterizing and validating spatial computational models and potential applications to <lb/>therapeutics. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>multiscale systems biology; computational biology; quantitative systems pharmacology (QSP); <lb/>immuno-oncology; immunotherapy; immune checkpoint inhibitor; mathematical modeling <lb/>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution (CC BY) license (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/). <lb/>* <lb/>Correspondence: knorton@bard.edu; Tel.: +845-752-2307. <lb/>Author Contributions: All authors conceptualized the work, participated in draft preparation, and editing and finalizing the <lb/>manuscript. K.A.N., C.G., and S.J. contributed equally to the paper. <lb/>Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/>HHS Public Access <lb/>Author manuscript <lb/>Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/>Published in final edited form as: <lb/>Processes (Basel). 2019 January ; 7(1): . doi:10.3390/pr7010037. <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>In recent years it has become increasingly evident that studying the tumor microenvironment <lb/>(TME), in addition to studying cancer cell transformation, is crucial to understanding tumor <lb/>growth, progression and dissemination. TME is a complex and heterogeneous milieu where <lb/>cancer cells and stromal cells (including immune cells and other cells resident in the tissue) <lb/>interact with each other and with the extracellular matrix (ECM), Figure 1. One of the <lb/>critical elements of the TME is the tumor&apos;s interaction with the host immune system. <lb/>Hanahan and Weinberg described evasion of the immune system as one of the hallmarks of <lb/>cancer [1]. The importance of the stromal microenvironment in tumor progression was also <lb/>recognized in the classical paper by Paget [2]. It has become clear that the tumor stromal <lb/>component, and specifically, the host immune system, contributes to tumor growth, and new <lb/>therapeutics are now being aimed at altering the immune system as a cancer target (see <lb/>reviews [3,4]). <lb/>The cellular components of the TME can vary in different regions of the tumor [5], as well <lb/>as between patients and even between tumors in a single patient [6]. Each of these cellular <lb/>components has its own behavior in terms of migration, proliferation, differentiation, <lb/>apoptosis, adhesion, and response to treatment. Cancer is so difficult to treat partly because <lb/>of this degree of complexity that results in a highly unpredictable tumor behavior, partially <lb/>due to the complex microenvironment [7], emphasizing the pressing need for personalized <lb/>treatment for individual patients. Mathematical and computational modeling techniques <lb/>provide a powerful tool in understanding the TME and predicting cancer progression [8]. <lb/>Below, we provide a brief overview of the role of the immune system in cancer and <lb/>introduce computational approaches to study the tumor immune microenvironment (TIME). <lb/>2. Immune System Biology and Cancer <lb/>The immune system consists of two major parts: the innate immune system, and the adaptive <lb/>immune system. The innate immune system is the body&apos;s immediate defense against foreign <lb/>antigens. The immunity via the innate immune system is nonspecific and short-lived, <lb/>whereas the adaptive immune response is a late-stage immune response that is highly <lb/>specific and can provide long-lasting defense [9]. The innate immune cells have pattern <lb/>recognition receptors that recognize entities that are non-self and then induce an <lb/>inflammatory response. The innate immune response is immediate, although some studies <lb/>suggest these cells also have the capability for memory [10], and may be followed by an <lb/>adaptive immune response [11]. The adaptive immune response is more specific than the <lb/>innate immune response and can be antibody-mediated or cell-mediated, with T-and B-cells <lb/>as the key cell types driving this response [12]. T-cells are a type of lymphocyte that matures <lb/>in the thymus, with several different subtypes that play a distinct function in immune <lb/>response [13]. Cytotoxic T-cells kill cancer cells [13], T-helper cells assist other cell types <lb/>during the immune response, and T-regulatory cells (Treg) play an important role in <lb/>immunological tolerance. In the case of cancer, in addition to normal antigens (self), cancer <lb/>cells express antigens unique to the tumor, which can result in an immune response. The <lb/>computational models discussed in this review will largely focus on the adaptive immune <lb/>system. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>Although the immune system is well equipped to eliminate abnormal cells, cancer cells have <lb/>several ways to evade the immune system. For example, cancer cells can become invisible to <lb/>the immune system by downregulating major histocompatibility complex (MHC) class-I <lb/>receptors on their cell surface, and in turn, not presenting the mutation associated antigen for <lb/>detection by T-cell receptors. Cancer cells attract regulatory T-cells (Treg) [14] and myeloid-<lb/>derived suppressor cells (MDSC) [15] to the tumors; an abundance of these cell types results <lb/>in an immunosuppressive environment [16]. Furthermore, receptors such as CTLA-4 on <lb/>Treg can bind to CD80 and CD86 on T-cells and antigen presenting cells (APC), which <lb/>inhibits co-stimulation of these cells, and results in T-cell suppression. Treg can further <lb/>inhibit the adaptive immune response by interfering with B-cell function and releasing <lb/>immunosuppressive cytokines such as IL-10. In fact, under certain conditions, the immune <lb/>response can contribute to tumor growth instead of inhibiting it [17]. Another way that <lb/>tumors escape detection is through chronic inflammation [18]. During chronic inflammation, <lb/>T-cells eventually lose their effectiveness over the course of the infection, called T-cell <lb/>exhaustion [19]. T-cell exhaustion is also frequently found in the tumor microenvironment <lb/>through the PD-L1/PD-1 pathway [20]. PD-1 blockage enhances T-cell and NK (Natural <lb/>Killer) cell activity in tumors [21,22]. Several immune checkpoint inhibitors are currently <lb/>being used in treatments of patients with cancer [23,24]. <lb/>Innate immune cells, such as macrophages, neutrophils, and eosinophils, have also been <lb/>shown to decrease or enhance tumor growth depending on their polarization state. <lb/>Macrophages have a great deal of plasticity but are usually classified in one of two types: an <lb/>M1-type that is immuno-enhancing, and an M2-type which is immuno-suppressing; though <lb/>there is a spectrum of states between M1 and M2 [25]. Studies have shown that high <lb/>numbers of tumor-associated macrophages (TAM) can lead to a worse clinical outcome [26]. <lb/>TAM have been shown to promote tumor growth by increasing vascularization, cancer cell <lb/>migration, cancer cell survival, and immuno-suppression [27]. Macrophages are recruited to <lb/>hypoxic areas of the tumor [28], and aid in tumor progression [26,29]. Cancer cells recruit <lb/>macrophages through Colony Stimulating Factor 1 (CSF1), and high CSF1 concentrations <lb/>are correlated with poor prognoses [30]. Macrophages can be converted to TAM within the <lb/>tumor by secreted factors, such as c-c chemokine receptor type-2 (CCR2) [31], which causes <lb/>them to exhibit an M2-like phenotype [32]; this conversion of macrophages leads to a <lb/>distinct subpopulation [33]. TAM secretion of c-c chemokine ligand type-18 (CCL18) can <lb/>enable the epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition of breast cancer cells [34,35]. These TAM <lb/>have also been shown to be associated with invasion, extravasation and metastasis [36-38]. <lb/>Thus, M2-type macrophages are currently being targeted with therapeutics for tumor <lb/>treatment [39]. Neutrophils are less abundant in tumors, but they are becoming more <lb/>recognized for their duel role in the immune response to cancer [40]. Eosinophils are also <lb/>commonly found within tumors [41], and have been found to enhance T-cell infiltration [42]. <lb/>These cells also have a duel role in the immune response, and can promote or suppress <lb/>tumor growth [43]. There is a complex interaction between cancer cells and the immune <lb/>system. Thus, it is important to understand the conditions in which tumors are eliminated or <lb/>enhanced by the immune system. <lb/>As is evident from the complex mechanisms of immune response and immune evasion <lb/>described above, modeling the immune system is a challenging task [44]. For the specific <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>case of cancer, immune cells can be found within the TME, the lymphatic system and the <lb/>lymph nodes, resulting in spatial complexity. Molecular and cellular components themselves <lb/>are complex and have patient specific features such as unique lymphocyte antigen receptors. <lb/>In addition, different functions of the immune system occur at different time scales, ranging <lb/>from minutes to years. For example, intracellular signaling occurs in minutes, whereas <lb/>memory cells exist on the order of years. Revealing this complexity across different scales as <lb/>discussed above is very challenging or impossible to achieve in an experimental setting. <lb/>Thus, computational modeling platforms provide a powerful tool to complement <lb/>experimental measurements for better understanding of the immune system in cancer. In the <lb/>following section, we provide an overview of the current computational modeling <lb/>approaches for the study of cancer. <lb/>3. Overview of Computational Modeling Methodologies including Agent-<lb/>Based Modeling <lb/>Computational modeling has provided great insight into studying intra-tumor heterogeneity <lb/>[45] and the interplay between the tumor and the microenvironment [46]. Modeling has the <lb/>benefit of providing a quantitative time-and cost-effective means to study the physical and <lb/>chemical interactions in tumor initiation and growth. Modeling efforts complement <lb/>experimental platforms by providing an understanding of clonal dynamics and <lb/>microenvironmental cues over time. There are several ways to classify mathematical/ <lb/>computational models in general, and cancer models in particular. One is deterministic vs. <lb/>stochastic; another is continuum vs. discrete models. Deterministic models have an end state <lb/>that does not change as long as the initial conditions remain the same, whereas stochastic <lb/>models have randomness included, resulting in differences in end states, even with the same <lb/>initial conditions. Continuum models treat cells as concentrations of cell types, whereas <lb/>discrete models (such as agent-based or particle models) consider discrete cells; the cell <lb/>behaviors, including interactions between cells, can be described as deterministic or <lb/>stochastic. A multiscale setting (called a hybrid model, illustrated in Figure 2) can include <lb/>both approaches, i.e., the discrete modeling of cells and continuous modeling of molecular <lb/>species, such as oxygen, growth factors, chemokines, microRNAs, and drugs, but <lb/>appropriate linking and calibration of such hybrid models should be performed. For <lb/>continuum-based models, temporal ordinary differential equations (ODE) and spatio-<lb/>temporal partial differential equations (PDE) have been used to model the immune response <lb/>in cancer, e.g., [47-53]; here, we focus on discrete agent-based models (ABM) and hybrid <lb/>models. <lb/>From another standpoint, the models that describe the immune system can be broadly <lb/>categorized into top-down and bottom-up, and previous reviews have focused on <lb/>computational modeling of the immune system [44,54]. The top-down approach models <lb/>populations of cells, not single entities, and uses the mean behavior at the macroscopic level. <lb/>ODE and PDE models are examples of this type of modeling where individual interactions <lb/>are not simulated. Stochastic differential equation models are also a part of this class. On the <lb/>other hand, the bottom-up approach focuses on the microscopic level. The model tracks each <lb/>agent (e.g., a cell) and its interactions with the surrounding environment, and emergent <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>behavior arises from all the entities and their local behavior. Features such as stochastic <lb/>behavior, spatial distribution, and heterogeneity of entities are inherent to bottom up models, <lb/>and thus, easier to capture with this approach. Drawbacks of these models are that they <lb/>require more computational power because they track individual agents and their <lb/>interactions over time and space; also, there are computational limitations on the number of <lb/>agents that can be considered; it is thus impossible to consider an entire organ or patient. <lb/>Therefore, both approaches will need to be combined to achieve both spatial cellular and <lb/>sub-cellular resolutions and whole patient pharmacokinetics and pharmacodynamics. <lb/>Agent-based models are an example of a bottom-up approach with applications in <lb/>immunology and immune related diseases such as cancer [55]. An agent-based model is a <lb/>discrete mathematical and computational framework that is capable of capturing emergent <lb/>behavior of its interacting agents, defined as large-scale spatio-temperal patterns resulting <lb/>from local spatial interactions between agents. The behavior and function of these agents are <lb/>driven by the information they sense in their local environment and the rules of the agent-<lb/>based model. Some of the characteristics that separate agent-based models apart from other <lb/>rule-based modeling systems (in which outcomes are based on a set of rules that govern <lb/>decisions) are that (1) they are spatial, (2) they incorporate agents that interact with other <lb/>agents and their environment, (3) they may incorporate stochasticity, (4) they are modular, <lb/>and (5) they produce emergent behavior [56]. These models allow the individual agents to <lb/>adapt to their local environment (i.e., agents are adaptive instead of reactive), and take part <lb/>in local interactions with other agents [57]. These result in complex aggregate behavior <lb/>stemming from simple rules and emergent properties from agent interactions. Agent-based <lb/>models can be lattice-based or lattice-free, depending on whether agents reside and move on <lb/>a (regular or irregular) spatially discretized lattice, or have their locations and velocities <lb/>represented by continuous variables, usually governed by forces in the environment. For <lb/>example, in lattice-based ABM, agents are placed on a lattice structure that defines the <lb/>locations of cells and their neighbors for cellular interactions. There are several model types <lb/>that, although they are not explicitly characterized as agent-based, are reviewed here for <lb/>completeness; those include cellular automata, Potts models, and Petri net models. <lb/>Agent-based models are particularly suitable for capturing spatially-varying events and <lb/>heterogeneities [58], and for understanding the immune system&apos;s function. With this aim in <lb/>mind, several investigators have developed agent-based models of diseases with involvement <lb/>of the immune system. Several ABM have simulated the immune system&apos;s involvement in <lb/>maintaining homeostasis and disease conditions, such as bacterial infections [59], fungal <lb/>infections [60], abnormal systemic inflammatory response [61], ulceration [62], allergens <lb/>[63], ischemia [64], tuberculosis [65], sepsis [66], and wound healing [67]. For cancers, such <lb/>models include tumor growth and invasion [68], as well as specific cancer types such as <lb/>hepatocellular carcinoma [69], breast cancer [70], melanoma [71], colorectal [72], lung <lb/>cancer [73,74], and metastasis [75]. Software packages have been developed based on the <lb/>ABM framework to study the immune system; these include ImmSim [76-79], Immunogrid <lb/>[80,81], Simmune [82], Cycell [83], and PhysiCell [84]. <lb/>Now we discuss the latest agent-based and hybrid models that investigate the effects of the <lb/>immune system on cancer progression and immunotherapy, see Table 1. In order to be <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>included in the review, the work needs to have an immune component, a tumor component, <lb/>and include ABM. We limited our focus to papers that were published within the last ten <lb/>years. However, we also included some studies on diseases other than cancer where we feel <lb/>that the methodology is relevant and could be applied to cancer; we also refer to a few <lb/>general software tools that can be readily adapted to cancer. <lb/>We break the review into the following sections, although there may be significant overlap: <lb/>(1) <lb/>Models focusing on immune-related tumor mechanobiology <lb/>(2) <lb/>Models focusing on tumor-associated vasculature in the immune response <lb/>(3) <lb/>Models focusing on tumor-associated lymphatics and lymph nodes <lb/>(4) <lb/>Models focusing on tumor immunotherapy <lb/>(5) <lb/>Models focusing on tumor-enhancing immune cells <lb/>(6) <lb/>Models focusing on intra-tumor heterogeneity <lb/>3.1. Models Focusing on Tumor Mechanobiology <lb/>Changes in the tumor extracellular matrix (ECM) have been known to contribute to tumor <lb/>progression and metastasis [85], with several computational models focusing on <lb/>investigating glioma invasion [86-88], but less is known about its contribution to immune <lb/>response. Computational modeling has been used to shed light on the interactions between <lb/>the ECM and the immune system in cancer dynamics. A hybrid agent-based model was used <lb/>to investigate the role of cellular adhesion to the ECM in tumor and immune system <lb/>dynamics [89]. Frascoli et al. found that the greater the motility of the cancer cells, the more <lb/>likely they will escape from immunotherapy. They also found that intermediate levels of <lb/>adhesion in general led to less successful outcomes, but these results were variable. <lb/>Kather et al. used ABM to investigate the combination of adoptive cell transfer and therapy <lb/>that permeabilized the fibrotic stromal component in colorectal cancer [72]. Adoptive cell <lb/>transfer is a therapeutic strategy that aims to increase the number of immune cells to <lb/>strengthen immuno-surveillance and counter tumor development. Kather et al. simulated <lb/>various conditions of immune surveillance. In their model, T-cell killing of tumor cells <lb/>occurred in a purely stochastic manner, with killing probability representing the effect of <lb/>tumor specificity, immunogenicity, stimulatory and inhibitory effects all in one parameter. <lb/>An immune rich environment promoted immune escape, but tumor growth slowed in a <lb/>lymphocyte deprived environment. Tumor control was observed in a subgroup of tumors <lb/>with less stroma and a high numbers of immune cells. They found that high levels of fibrosis <lb/>and low numbers of lymphocytes reduced overall survival. Their findings were validated <lb/>with data from colorectal cancer patients, where low density stroma and high lymphocyte <lb/>level correlated with better overall survival. In this study, Kather et al. simulated the effect of <lb/>immunotherapy by boosting the number of immune cells by 2-8 fold. Therapy was intended <lb/>to enhance fibrotic stromal permeability; this was implemented by modifying the <lb/>corresponding parameter by a factor of 4% to 16%. The model predicted that optimal tumor <lb/>eradication requires a combination of therapeutics aiming at both activating adaptive <lb/>immune system and stromal depletion. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>3.2. Models Focusing on Tumor-Associated Vasculature in the Immune Response <lb/>Tumor-associated vasculature is an important aspect of the tumor-immune complex because <lb/>it not only provides oxygen and nutrients for the tumor to grow, but it is also the source of <lb/>tumor dissemination via circulating tumor cells (CTC), and recruitment for many immune <lb/>cells, such as monocytes/macrophages and T-cells. Studies have aimed to provide a better <lb/>understanding of these processes [90,91]. An ABM of Early Metastasis (ABMEM) <lb/>framework was used to model the interactions between tumor cells, platelets, neutrophils, <lb/>and endothelial cells [92]. Receptor binding to Mac-1 (macrophage antigen-1) by <lb/>endothelial cells, platelets, or tumor cells leads to reactive oxygen species (ROS) production <lb/>by neutrophils. Uppal et al. examined two types of platelet inhibition: inhibition of <lb/>thromboxane, inhibition of adenosine diphosphate (ADP) receptors and inhibition of both <lb/>[92]. They found that thromboxane inhibition alone resulted in the best outcome. <lb/>Alfonso et al. developed an agent-based model of immune cell-epithelial cell interactions in <lb/>breast lobular epithelium [93]. The model investigated the effect of menstrual cycle length <lb/>and hormone status on inflammatory response to cell turnover in breast tissue. Blood vessels <lb/>were homogeneously distributed in the intra-and interlobular stroma. The model accounts <lb/>for myoepithelial and luminal cells. Cellular processes (i.e., epithelial cell proliferation, cell <lb/>death via effector cells, programmed cell death, removal of dead cells, immune cell motility, <lb/>and inhibition of effector cells by regulatory cells) are modeled as stochastic events. Effector <lb/>CD8+ cells are the only cells responsible for killing of damaged epithelial cells. Regulatory <lb/>CD4+ and CD8+ cells act by inducing inactivation of effector dependent response. <lb/>Chemokines from damaged epithelial cells activate the immune cells. Immune cells become <lb/>ineffective when such chemokines are absent, or due to the suppression via regulatory cells. <lb/>The outcome of the model identified novel prognostic information for breast cancer, such as <lb/>the number of immune clusters being associated with the degree of epithelial damage. <lb/>3.3. Models Focusing on Tumor-Associated Lymphatics and Lymph Nodes <lb/>Reddy developed the first mathematical model of the lymphatic system in 1977 [94]. In <lb/>recent years, various computational modeling approaches have been used to study the <lb/>lymphatic vessels [95-99] and lymph nodes [100-102] in general, and in the application to <lb/>infectious disease [103,104], and simulating fluid and chemokine transport in the lymphatic <lb/>system as it relates to health and disease conditions [105]. Agent-based models have more <lb/>recently been used to simulate various processes that occur during an adaptive immune <lb/>response in a lymph node. Meyer-Hermann developed an ABM of germinal centers of the <lb/>lymph node [106,107]. The authors studied B-cell germinal center reactions and how they <lb/>contribute to germinal center deregulation [106]. They expanded this model to study B-cell <lb/>affinity maturation in the lymph node germinal centers [108]. They found that competition <lb/>for T-cell rescue and increased refractory time leads to a more robust affinity maturation. <lb/>A series of studies on modeling of T-cell behavior in the lymph node have been conducted <lb/>by Bogle and Dunbar [44,109-112]. They modeled T-cell trafficking, activation, and <lb/>proliferation in the lymph node paracortex using an agent-based approach. The model <lb/>included chemokine and cytokine gradients. Using this lattice-based approach, they were <lb/>able to model the movement and behavior of T-cells in the lymph node paracortex [112]. In <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>the next step, they expanded the agent-based model of the lymph node paracortex in three <lb/>dimensions to include T-cells and dendritic cells (DC). The model allows simulation of a <lb/>large number of T-cells at physiologic densities. The virtual lymph node can shrink or swell, <lb/>depending on the dynamics of cell trafficking. The model was able to simulate T-cell <lb/>activation in agreement with in-vivo observations, and provide new understanding on T-cell-<lb/>DC interactions. Not all the parameters of the model were experimentally measured; thus, <lb/>the model can be refined by more accurate measurement of those parameters [110]. Next, <lb/>the authors built on their previous models to simulate T-cell ingress and egress, as well as <lb/>chemotaxis in the lymph node, by incorporating new numerical methods. The new model <lb/>allows simulation of expansion and contraction of T-cells in the lymph node paracortex <lb/>during an immune response. The ability to model chemotaxis could be useful in studying <lb/>other biological processes involving chemotaxis [111]. <lb/>Moreau et al. constructed a virtual lymph node using agent-based modeling to study T-cell <lb/>activation by synapses (long-lasting contacts) and kinapses (transient interactions) [113]. <lb/>The model incorporated T-cell migration and T-cell-DC interactions. Additionally, virtual <lb/>fluorescence-activated cell sorting (FACs) profiles were obtained from modeling by <lb/>visualizing T-cell proliferation. This virtual lymph node model provides new opportunities <lb/>for understanding the mechanisms of T-cell regulation in infection or vaccine application <lb/>[113]. <lb/>The ABM developed for studies of the lymphatic system thus far mainly focus on the lymph <lb/>node, and in particular, T-cell processes. Folcik et al. developed the basic immune simulator <lb/>(BIS), which is an agent-based platform that includes parenchymal tissue, secondary <lb/>lymphoid tissue and the lymphatic/humoral circulation [114]. Using agent-based and hybrid <lb/>models, lymph node dynamics are studied in the context of infectious diseases and cancer. <lb/>Kim and Lee used a hybrid model to study the efficacy of preventative cancer vaccines. The <lb/>model comprised two compartments for interactions of tumor and immune cells at the tissue <lb/>site and in the draining lymph nodes [115]. Jacob et al. developed a three-compartment <lb/>ABM that includes lymph nodes, blood vessels, and organ/tissue. The model was used to <lb/>study immune response against viruses in these compartments [116]. Marino et al. <lb/>developed a hybrid model where the lymph node and blood compartment were simulated <lb/>using ordinary differential equations and the lung compartment was simulated using agents. <lb/>They focused on the formation of granulomas in the lung, which are organized structures of <lb/>immune cells in the lung, and are a hallmark of infection. The model focused on the <lb/>recruitment of APCs in the lymph node from the lung for Mycobacterium tuberculosis (Mtb, <lb/>the causative bacterium of TB) infection [117]. In another study, they investigated the role of <lb/>DC in Mtb infection [118]. The growth and dissemination of bacteria were highly affected <lb/>by CD8+ and CD4+ T-cell proliferation rates and DC migration. Such multiscale models <lb/>allow the study of tissue level dynamics during adaptive immune response [118], and <lb/>although they focus on infectious disease, many of the components and processes involved <lb/>in anti-cancer immunity and adaptive immunity against infection are shared. For example, T-<lb/>cells specific to tumor antigens are primed and expanded in a similar fashion to that in which <lb/>T-cells specific to foreign antigens are during their response to infection; the immune <lb/>suppressive mechanisms that cancer cells hijack to evade immune surveillance are also <lb/>deployed during an immune response against infection to prevent excessive tissue damage. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>Since the body reacts similarly in response to an infection as it does in response to cancer <lb/>(e.g., activation of similar signaling pathways), cancer models can heavily borrow from this <lb/>literature. <lb/>3.4. Models Focusing on Tumor Immunotherapy <lb/>A variety of cancer immunotherapy strategies exist that range from boosting the overall <lb/>immune response to specifically targeting cancer immunity. Some examples of <lb/>immunotherapies are treatment vaccines, adoptive cell transfer, and immune checkpoint <lb/>inhibitor treatments. Agent-based and hybrid models are developed to help understand these <lb/>therapies when applied separately or in combination with other cancer treatments. One type <lb/>of therapy that has been explored is cancer vaccines. Therapeutic cancer vaccines treat <lb/>existing cancers by delivering immunogenic and tumor specific antigens to the patient to <lb/>induce cellular and/or humoral anti-tumor immunity. Pennisi et al. have developed several <lb/>hybrid models investigating the immune system effects on tumors. They developed a hybrid <lb/>model to study the development of lung metastases from mammary carcinoma [75]. Pennisi <lb/>et al. also developed a hybrid model MetastaSim to simulate the protection against lung <lb/>metastases in mouse using Triplex cell vaccine [73]. In this simulation, macrophages could <lb/>capture tumor-associated antigen and immunocomplexes, breaking them down and <lb/>eliminating them from the system. This vaccine elicited a combination of three stimuli: the <lb/>p185neu antigen expressed by the HER2/neu gene, allogeneic major histocompatibility <lb/>complex (MHC) molecules, and IL-12 which enhances antigen presentation. Using this <lb/>model, after calibration and validation, the authors were able to evaluate different protocols <lb/>of vaccine administration. The simulation results suggested that in order to maximize <lb/>protection while reducing the number of administrations, the vaccination strategy should <lb/>include a significant dosage early on and a few recalls afterwards. <lb/>Dreau et al. developed an ABM model of solid tumor progression to understand the <lb/>interplay between solid tumor growth, tumor vascular growth, and the host&apos;s immune system <lb/>[119]. The model includes tumor and immune cells, vasculature, tumor cell proliferation, <lb/>and immune system response. Their model supported immunotherapy as an effective cancer <lb/>treatment in individuals with functioning immune systems. They concluded that a strong <lb/>immune response limits tumor growth in a way that cannot be achieved under a weaker <lb/>immune response. Another study focused on the role of T-cells in the effectiveness of <lb/>response to immunotherapy in B-16 melanoma [120]. The model includes macrophages, <lb/>DC, tumor vasculature, and interactions between these components. It was found that early <lb/>entry of T-cells effectively eliminated the tumor and was dependent on CD137 (a co-<lb/>stimulatory protein that helps in tumor rejection [121]) expression in tumor vasculature. <lb/>Oncolytic virus therapy is a strategy that utilizes viral infection to kill cancer cells, but not <lb/>normal cells, with the potential of enhancing T-cell recruitment to the tumor and increasing <lb/>their access to cancer cells. Several computational models have examined the conditions of <lb/>success for this type of therapeutic in silico [122]. Walker et al. developed an agent-based <lb/>model of pancreatic tumors to study the synergy between chimeric antigen receptor (CAR) <lb/>T-cell therapy and oncolytic virus therapy [123]. CAR T-cell therapy is one type of adoptive <lb/>cell transfer treatment involving genetically engineered T-cells specifically targeting cancer <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>cells, and has been the subject of several computational models [124]. The agent-based <lb/>model recapitulates treatment mechanisms including cancer specific CAR T-cell recruitment <lb/>to the tumor site via vasculature and the injection and spread of oncolytic virus. Rohrs et al. <lb/>demonstrated the ability of the model to track the dynamics of cancer cells and stromal cells <lb/>in space in the presence of the treatment combinations; optimization of the combination <lb/>therapy requires more accurate calibration [124]. <lb/>Immune checkpoint inhibitors are used in cancer immunotherapy that enhances anti-tumor <lb/>immune response by targeting cancer immune evasion mechanisms. In many cancer types, <lb/>tumor neoantigens are sufficiently immunogenic to promote the expansion of antitumor <lb/>immune cells [125]; however, these immune cells are not functional due to the inhibitory <lb/>signals from molecules adaptively induced during cancer development [24,126]. Among <lb/>them, one of the most prominent mechanisms is PD-1/PD-L1 interaction, where T-cells are <lb/>suppressed through PD-1 signaling upon contact with induced PD-L1 in the tumor <lb/>microenvironment. Gong et al. developed an ABM of tumor-immune interaction in 3D to <lb/>study the spatio-temporal dynamics of cancer cells and cytotoxic T-cells [127]. In this study, <lb/>the inhibitor to the checkpoint molecules were modeled as a factor which modulates the <lb/>parameter governing the suppression of tumor specific T-cells by PD-L1+ cancer cells. They <lb/>found that patient responsiveness to such therapy could be associated with the level of <lb/>mutational burden of the cancer and antigen strength among patients. They also found that <lb/>tumor growth is insensitive to the vascular density of the tumor core. From these results, a <lb/>scoring method was proposed to predict anti-PDL1 treatment efficacy in patients. <lb/>3.5. Models Focusing on Tumor-Enhancing Immune Cells <lb/>While the immune system has evolved to kill off tumor cells, there are many ways in which <lb/>cancer cells can avoid immune detection. In addition, there is mounting evidence that <lb/>immune cells can stimulate tumor growth under certain conditions. Several agent-based <lb/>models have focused on understanding the tumor-enhancing contributions of the immune <lb/>system. Enderling and colleagues explored the interactions between tumor cell death and the <lb/>immune system using a cellular automata model focused on the interplay between cancer <lb/>stem cells and the immune system [128]. They showed that immune system-induced tumor <lb/>cell death led to stem cell selection, and thus, more aggressive tumors [128,129]. In this <lb/>model, even though immune cells effectively killed off tumor cells, they also affected <lb/>progenitor cells. This resulted in the creation of a space for cancer stem cells to proliferate <lb/>and produce more cancer stem cells. This ultimately resulted in a larger stem cell population <lb/>and a more aggressive tumor. <lb/>Several studies have specifically focused on the tumor-enhancing contribution of immune <lb/>cells, such as tumor-associated macrophages (TAM). Macrophages are one of the most <lb/>abundant immune cells found in tumors, but their population is heterogeneous [130]. M1-<lb/>type macrophages have been shown to be tumor inhibiting, whereas M2-type macrophages <lb/>have been shown to be tumor enhancing [26]. One model looked at the transition from the <lb/>M1 to M2 macrophage phenotype on tumor growth and then predicted targeted therapies <lb/>[131]. Knútsdóttir et al. used a hybrid model to investigate epidermal growth factor (EGF) <lb/>and macrophage colony-stimulating factor 1 (CSF-1) signaling between macrophages and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>cancer cells during macrophage aggregation [132]. They found that CSF-1/CSFR1 autocrine <lb/>signaling affects the ratio of tumor cells to macrophages during tumor growth. In a further <lb/>study, they found that the macrophage/tumor cell ratio was most sensitive to the strength of <lb/>EGF signaling, but usually maintained a 1:3 ratio [133]. <lb/>Another ABM of triple-negative breast cancer examined the tumor enhancing effects of <lb/>macrophages [134]. Norton et al. investigated the interplay between tumor growth, blood <lb/>vessel recruitment and macrophage recruitment through tumor vasculature. They observed <lb/>that while macrophages increase tumor growth, excessive macrophage recruitment <lb/>conversely leads to a decrease in tumor growth due to the inhibition of proliferation resulting <lb/>from overcrowding. <lb/>3.6. Models Focusing on Intra-Tumor Heterogeneity <lb/>Intra-tumor heterogeneity and the characteristics of the tumor microenvironment are found <lb/>to have important implications in the outcome of disease progression [135]. Patients often <lb/>have varied responses to treatment because each patient is unique in their genome, <lb/>microbiome, disease history, lifestyle, and environment. The case of tumors is especially <lb/>complex, because this heterogeneity is observed not only between tumors, but also between <lb/>subpopulations of cells from the same tumor, resulting in different response to drugs [136]. <lb/>While capturing this degree of heterogeneity may be difficult in experiments and clinical <lb/>trials, especially the temporal dynamics of spatial heterogeneity, computational models are <lb/>especially suited to tackling this challenge. This section focuses on the models that have <lb/>aimed to capture intra-tumor heterogeneity. <lb/>A 2D agent-based model was used to study the interactions between an avascular tumor and <lb/>immune cells (NK cells and cytotoxic T-cells) [137]. They examined the effects of cancer <lb/>cell proliferation on overall tumor growth under two conditions: the first, where cancer cells <lb/>do not consider the microenvironment when deciding when to proliferate, and the second, <lb/>where they proliferate based on the number of healthy cells surrounding them. Tumor-<lb/>immune cell interaction can have three outcomes: tumor cell death, immune cell death, or no <lb/>cell death based on the state of the tumor. The predicted growth of the tumor was then <lb/>compared to a xenograft tumor growth. Spatial heterogeneity was also examined in a <lb/>different model where cancer cells use glycolysis instead of oxidative phosphorylation to <lb/>increase their energy production. In order to study how this increased energy production <lb/>affects the surrounding stroma, a combination of computational modeling and in vitro/in <lb/>vivo experiments was used [138]. They used agent-based modeling to understand tumor <lb/>growth in a vascularized area of the tumor. They found that tumors develop spatial patterns <lb/>where macrophages and tumor cells coexisted in areas with high levels of oxygen, but that <lb/>only tumor cells survived in ischemic regions. They then used an in vitro tissue-mimetic <lb/>system to create the directional gradients for oxygen and lactate, which also allowed for the <lb/>co-culture of tumor cells and macrophages. <lb/>Figueredo et al. created a series of hybrid models to study the interplay between the immune <lb/>system (including macrophages) and tumor cells [139,140]. An agent-based on-lattice model <lb/>for tumors was created using Chaste (Cancer, Heart and Soft Tissue Environment), part of <lb/>the Virtual Physiological Human (VPH) Toolkit; the model consists of three layers: a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>diffusible layer, a cellular layer, and a subcellular layer [141]. The diffusible layer consists <lb/>of diffusible species such as oxygen, the cellular layer consists of normal cells, tumor cells, <lb/>and macrophages, and the subcellular layer governs apoptosis and cell-cycle in each cell. In <lb/>this model, macrophages were M1-like, they supported the immune system, and aided <lb/>immunotherapies. They investigated the growth of the tumor under oxygen-dependent <lb/>proliferation. They found that the emergent behavior of agent-based models allowed for the <lb/>generation of additional tumor architectures over other modeling methodologies [142]. <lb/>4. Discussion and Emerging Applications <lb/>The immune system is made up of many interacting components that together drive a <lb/>complex spatio-temporal behavior during immune response. Thus, agent-based modeling is <lb/>particularly suitable for understanding the immune systems function in health and in disease <lb/>conditions such as cancer. Here, we reviewed the latest agent-based and hybrid models that <lb/>investigate the contributions of the immune system to cancer growth and the effect of <lb/>immunotherapy. In this context, we focused on models of immune-related tumor <lb/>mechanobiology, tumor-associated vasculature, tumor-associated lymphatics, tumor <lb/>immunotherapies, tumor-enhancing immune cells, and finally, models focusing on intra-<lb/>tumor heterogeneity. Overall, ABM can generate novel hypotheses to be validated and <lb/>refined by future experiments. Development and refinement of multiscale agent-based <lb/>models along with experiments through an iterative process can improve our understanding <lb/>of biological processes in cancer and lead to the identification of novel prognostic and <lb/>predictive biomarkers that can improve therapies and help design and interpret the results of <lb/>clinical trials [143]. <lb/>Models investigating the tumor-enhancing effects of the immune system can provide useful <lb/>insights into managing tumor-immune interactions. Since the tumor microenvironment can <lb/>be very heterogeneous, care must be taken to appropriately model cell-cell interactions <lb/>between cancer, stromal, and immune cells, the extracellular matrix, and the secreted factors. <lb/>Accurate data from in vitro and in vivo experiments must be used to understand the <lb/>transition from tumor-inhibiting to tumor-enhancing immune cell types. In addition, since <lb/>immune cells such as macrophages and T-cells are usually recruited to the tumor by secreted <lb/>factors, an evolving tumor vasculature is necessary to accurately model these processes. <lb/>Agent-based models of the tumor enhancing effects of the immune system can help us better <lb/>understand how to prevent or revert the immune system back into a tumor-inhibiting <lb/>phenotype. Thus, these models will help improve immunotherapies for cancer treatment. <lb/>One limitation of the immunotherapy studies mentioned above is that although the models <lb/>are quantitative in many aspects, the modules governing drug delivery and response is <lb/>relatively qualitative or semi-quantitative in nature. This could potentially be resolved by <lb/>combining spatio-temporal agent-based models with traditional model types, such as <lb/>Physiologically Based Pharmacokinetic (PBPK) models to track drug distribution in <lb/>different physiological compartments, and pharmacodynamic (PD) models for individual <lb/>cellular agents to represent effects of drugs on target cells [144]. Such hybrid quantitative <lb/>systems pharmacology (QSP) models can be utilized not only as a platform for basic science <lb/>research, but also as a potential complement to the clinical research and drug discovery <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>pipeline. A schematic of such a hybrid model based on the research in our own group is <lb/>presented in Figure 3. Compared with continuous models, the discretely represented agents <lb/>allow the flexibility to track intra-tumor heterogeneity, such as tumor neoantigen profile, T-<lb/>cell clonality and local expression of immune checkpoint molecules with preferred levels of <lb/>granularity. By running multiple simulations in parallel using different parameter values and <lb/>initial conditions accounting for genetic background and environmental exposure, the <lb/>models can represent cohorts of patients with desired population scale heterogeneity. These <lb/>properties render agent-based and hybrid models a powerful platform for conducting virtual <lb/>clinical trials. <lb/>Computer models provide large-scale predictive power by allowing us to simulate clinical <lb/>trials with sufficient details to study response to various conditions. Using these models, it is <lb/>possible to test and predict drug failures in simulations rather than in patients, which could <lb/>result in improved drug design, reduced risks and side effects, and can dramatically decrease <lb/>costs of drug development. Importantly, models can predict how the immune-tumor system <lb/>evolves during the course of the treatment [136]. The challenge is that available data for <lb/>individual patients is limited. To address this problem, machine learning approaches can be <lb/>used to build statistical models based on available patient data, and these models can be <lb/>employed to simulate virtual populations to predict the effects of therapies [145]. These <lb/>approaches have already been expanded to identify biomarkers and find important mutations <lb/>that affect response to treatment with drugs in cancer cell lines [146-148]. <lb/>Mechanistic models are another suitable approach that provides large-scale predictive <lb/>capabilities based on the available information on the interactions between various <lb/>components of a biological system. These models can be discrete or continuous. A certain <lb/>type of model is chosen based on the application and availability of the data [149,150]. <lb/>Depending on the type of the model, predictions can be made for the behavior of the <lb/>signaling system in a qualitative, semi-quantitative or quantitative manner. For example, for <lb/>quantitative predictions of signaling and regulatory gene networks, continuous variables <lb/>need to be modeled on continuous time scales using ODEs [151]. <lb/>Such detailed modeling requires knowledge of important biological reactions at every step. <lb/>This can only be achieved in several iterative steps that include the implementation of <lb/>various components such as signaling events and defining values for related parameters and <lb/>appropriate initial conditions. In recent years, numerous models have been developed that <lb/>simulate individual signaling pathways [152-154]. The challenge is that these models often <lb/>do not fully capture crosstalk mechanisms that are crucial in predicting patient response to <lb/>treatment, as each drug perturbs multiple biological processes. ODE-based models can be <lb/>combined with agent-based models to capture the dynamics of the system being modeled in <lb/>a more complex fashion. Stochasticity is one of the main advantages of agent-based models, <lb/>as it applies to biological processes [155]. In comparison to ODE models that make <lb/>predictions of concentrations and other events over time, ABM allows the study of each <lb/>agent, as it interacts with other agents in their proximity and the ways in which that affects <lb/>the large-scale behavior. These models, however, are computationally more expensive. There <lb/>are also challenges in validating results from ABM due to insufficient spatio-temporal data <lb/>on tumor development [156]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>One aspect that is typically missing from mechanistic knowledge-based models including <lb/>QSP and ABM is an input from high-throughput data, genomic or proteomic; such data can <lb/>inform the models and can supplement the data obtained at the cellular and tissue levels <lb/>[157]. Examples include immune landscape information from different sources including <lb/>patients&apos; databases such as TCGA (The Cancer Genome Atlas) [33,158,159]. Another <lb/>source of &quot;Big Data&quot; for parameterization and validation of the models, including ABM, <lb/>will be the emerging methodologies of digital pathology, such as using multiplex <lb/>immunofluorescence (mIF) of patients&apos; biopsies and resected tumors, with subsequent <lb/>analysis of cellular and molecular spatial patterns. Steps in this direction are already <lb/>underway [160]. Another source of data is image-based, using microCT, confocal, <lb/>multiphoton, and super resolution microscopy, both ex vivo and in vivo; examples include <lb/>imaging entire tumor vasculature with subsequent computer simulation of blood flow and <lb/>molecular transport [161,162]. <lb/>In addition to modeling approaches used to simulate response to treatment, virtual patients <lb/>are a key component of virtual clinical trials. A virtual population has the characteristics of <lb/>the original patient population but also includes individual diversity, usually comprising <lb/>parameter sets weighted by a clinical or response distribution [163]. This diversity allows <lb/>testing a broad range of responses that can be missed in a clinical trial. In contrast to <lb/>traditional clinical trials that can only be performed after costly and lengthy development, in <lb/>silico trials could be performed at every stage of the drug development. In silico design of <lb/>treatments can be conducted with data-driven or mechanistic-based (knowledge-based) <lb/>approaches [164]. It should be noted that in silico clinical trials require integration of data at <lb/>different scales via a multi-model approach using virtual patients. Similar to a traditional <lb/>clinical trial, rigorous statistical approaches are needed at various steps of virtual clinical <lb/>trials. The ability to test treatment via in silico clinical trials can significantly reduce the cost <lb/>and increase the efficacy of drug development. <lb/>The main challenge in the way of predictive models for virtual clinical trials is the <lb/>availability of input data for the model for each patient. Detailed knowledge about the <lb/>situation at the start of the simulation can significantly affect the predictive power of that <lb/>model. Such input information is being generated at a growing rate and a lower cost. <lb/>Furthermore, proteomic data enable the modeling of interactions of different subgroups of <lb/>cells from the same tumor with each other as well as immune cells and other stromal cells, <lb/>allowing modeling tumors for individual patients. Computational models can make <lb/>predictions for the optimal treatments, making it safer, faster, and cheaper to complement <lb/>current clinical trials. These models will improve by continuous comparison of predicted <lb/>and actual response to therapy. Additionally, as more detailed information on biological <lb/>parameters and disease mechanisms become available, the accuracy of the models will <lb/>increase. <lb/>Currently, only 1 in 10s of clinical trials results in drugs that make it to the market [165]. <lb/>The process takes 10-12 years, costing billions of dollars, sometimes with low effectiveness <lb/>when used by real patients [136]. Although virtual clinical trials with virtual patients and <lb/>virtual cohorts cannot replace clinical trials, they can inform design of such trials to improve <lb/>success rates and increase the efficacy of the process of drug development. Virtual trials can <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>also better address the need for personalized therapy [166]. Finally, combining agent-based <lb/>models and data-driven artificial intelligence (AI) methods (e.g., machine learning, <lb/>including deep learning), we can better understand the gap between preclinical findings and <lb/>clinical outcomes. <lb/>In summary, in silico modeling and specifically agent-based modeling are powerful tools of <lb/>cancer systems biology and cancer immune systems biology. Combined with novel <lb/>measurement methodologies and increasing amounts and sophistication of data available <lb/>from clinical trials, they should bring a better mechanistic understanding and predictive <lb/>capabilities of therapeutic interventions in cancer, including immunotherapies. The field is <lb/>ripe for conducting predictive virtual clinical trials as a prerequisite to clinical trials in <lb/>patients. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was supported by the National Institutes of Health grants R01CA138264, U01CA212007 and <lb/>R01CA196701 and American Cancer Society postdoctoral fellowship PF-13-174-01-CSM (KAN). The authors <lb/>thank Amanda Figueroa for her expert drawing of Figure 1. The authors thank Mohammad Jafarnejad and Richard <lb/>Sove for critical comments on the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Hanahan D; Weinberg RA Hallmarks of cancer: The next generation. Cell 2011, 144, 646-674. <lb/>[PubMed: 21376230] <lb/>2. Paget S The distribution of secondary growths in cancer of the breast. Lancet 1889, 133, 571-573. <lb/>3. Wei SC; Duffy CR; Allison JP Fundamental mechanisms of immune checkpoint blockade therapy. <lb/>Cancer Discern. 2018, 8, 1069-1086. <lb/>4. Chen DS; Mellman I Elements of cancer immunity and the cancer-Immune set point. Nature 2017, <lb/>541, 321-330. [PubMed: 28102259] <lb/>5. Quail DF; Joyce JA Microenvironmental regulation of tumor progression and metastasis. Nat. Med <lb/>2013, 19, 1423-1437. [PubMed: 24202395] <lb/>6. Ansell SM; Vonderheide RH Cellular composition of the tumor microenvironment. Am. Soc. Clin. <lb/>Oncol. Educ. B 2013, 33, e91-e97. <lb/>7. Pitt JM; Marabelle A; Eggermont A; Soria JC; Kroemer G; Zitvogel L Targeting the tumor <lb/>microenvironment: Removing obstruction to anticancer immune responses and immunotherapy. <lb/>Ann. Oncol 2016, 27, 1482-1492. [PubMed: 27069014] <lb/>8. Crespo I; Coukos G; Doucey M; Xenarios I Modelling approaches to discovery in the tumor <lb/>microenvironment. J. Cancer Immunol. Ther 2018, 1, 23-37. <lb/>9. Netea MG; Joosten LAB; Latz E; Mills KHG; Natoli G; Stunnenberg HG; O&apos;Neill LAJ; Xavier RJ <lb/>Trained immunity: A program of innate immune memory in health and disease. Science 2016, 352, <lb/>aaf1098. [PubMed: 27102489] <lb/>10. Netea MG; Quintin J; Van Der Meer JWM Trained immunity: A memory for innate host defense. <lb/>Cell Host Microbe 2011, 9, 355-361. [PubMed: 21575907] <lb/>11. Kumar H; Kawai T; Akira S Pathogen recognition by the innate immune system. Int. Rev. Immunol <lb/>2011, 30, 16-34. [PubMed: 21235323] <lb/>12. Gajewski TF; Schreiber H; Fu Y-X Innate and adaptive immune cells in the tumor <lb/>microenvironment. Nat. Immunol 2013, 14, 1014-1022. [PubMed: 24048123] <lb/>13. Dykes SS; Hughes VS; Wiggins JM; Fasanya HO; Tanaka M; Siemann D Stromal cells in breast <lb/>cancer as a potential therapeutic target. Oncotarget 2018, 9, 23761-23779. [PubMed: 29805773] <lb/>14. Chaudhary B; Elkord E Regulatory T cells in the tumor microenvironment and cancer progression: <lb/>Role and therapeutic targeting. Vaccines 2016, 4, 28. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>15. Fleming V; Hu X; Weber R; Nagibin V; Groth C; Altevogt P; Utikal J; Umansky V Targeting <lb/>myeloid-derived suppressor cells to bypass tumor-induced immunosuppression. Front. Immunol <lb/>2018, 9, 398. [PubMed: 29552012] <lb/>16. Beyer M; Schultze JL Regulatory T cells in cancer. Blood 2006, 108, 804-811. [PubMed: <lb/>16861339] <lb/>17. De Visser KE; Eichten A; Coussens LM Paradoxical roles of the immune system during cancer <lb/>development. Nat. Rev. Cancer 2006, 6, 24-37. [PubMed: 16397525] <lb/>18. Palucka AK; Coussens LM The basis of oncoimmunology. Cell 2016, 164, 1233-1247. [PubMed: <lb/>26967289] <lb/>19. Blank C; Mackensen A Contribution of the PD-L1/PD-1 pathway to T-cell exhaustion: An update <lb/>on implications for chronic infections and tumor evasion. Cancer Immunol. Immunother 2007, 56, <lb/>739-745. [PubMed: 17195077] <lb/>20. Jiang Y; Li Y; Zhu B T-cell exhaustion in the tumor microenvironment. Cell Death Dis. 2015, 6, <lb/>e1792. [PubMed: 26086965] <lb/>21. Seifert AM; Zeng S; Zhang JQ; Kim TS; Cohen NA; Beckman MJ; Medina BD; Maltbaek JH; Loo <lb/>JK; Crawley MH; et al. PD-1/PD-L1 blockade enhances T-cell activity and antitumor efficacy of <lb/>Imatinib in gastrointestinal stromal tumors. Clin. Cancer Res 2017, 23, 454-465. [PubMed: <lb/>27470968] <lb/>22. Oyer JL; Gitto SB; Altomare DA; Copik AJ PD-L1 blockade enhances anti-tumor efficacy of NK <lb/>cells. Oncoimmunology 2018, 7, e1509819. [PubMed: 30377572] <lb/>23. Abdel-Wahab N; Shah M; Lopez-Olivo MA; Suarez-Almazor ME Use of immune checkpoint <lb/>inhibitors in the treatment of patients with cancer and preexisting autoimmune disease: A <lb/>systematic review. Ann. Intern. Med 2018, 168, 121-130. [PubMed: 29297009] <lb/>24. Sharma P; Allison JP Immune checkpoint targeting in cancer therapy: Toward combination <lb/>strategies with curative potential. Cell 2015, 161, 205-214. [PubMed: 25860605] <lb/>25. Raggi F; Pelassa S; Pierobon D; Penco F; Gattorno M; Novelli F; Eva A; Varesio L; Giovarelli M; <lb/>Bosco MC Regulation of human macrophage M1-M2 polarization balance by hypoxia and the <lb/>triggering receptor expressed on myeloid cells-1. Front. Immunol 2017, 8, 1097. [PubMed: <lb/>28936211] <lb/>26. Choi J; Gyamfi J; Jang H; Koo JS The role of tumor-associated macrophage in breast cancer <lb/>biology. Histol. Histopathol 2018, 33, 133-145. [PubMed: 28681373] <lb/>27. Seager RJ; Hajal C; Spill F; Kamm RD; Zaman MH Dynamic interplay between tumour, stroma <lb/>and immune system can drive or prevent tumour progression. Converg. Sci. Phys. Oncol 2017, 3, <lb/>034002. [PubMed: 30079253] <lb/>28. Tripathi C; Tewari BN; Kanchan RK; Baghel KS; Nautiyal N; Shrivastava R; Kaur H; Bhatt MLB; <lb/>Bhadauria S Macrophages are recruited to hypoxic tumor areas and acquire a pro-angiogenic M2-<lb/>polarized phenotype via hypoxic cancer cell derived cytokines Oncostatin M and Eotaxin. <lb/>Oncotarget 2014, 5, 5350-5368. [PubMed: 25051364] <lb/>29. Williams CB; Yeh ES; Soloff AC Tumor-associated macrophages: Unwitting accomplices in breast <lb/>cancer malignancy. NPJ Breast Cancer 2016, 2, 15025. [PubMed: 26998515] <lb/>30. Luo H; Tu G; Liu Z; Liu M; Noy R; Pollard JWW Tumor-associated macrophages: From <lb/>mechanisms to therapy. Immunity 2014, 41, 49-61. [PubMed: 25035953] <lb/>31. Hollmén M; Roudnicky F; Karaman S; Detmar M Characterization of macrophage-Cancer cell <lb/>crosstalk in estrogen receptor positive and triple-negative breast cancer. Sci. Rep 2015, 5, 9188. <lb/>[PubMed: 25776849] <lb/>32. Sousa S; Brion R; Lintunen M; Kronqvist P; Sandholm J; Mdnkkdnen J; Kellokumpu-Lehtinen P-<lb/>L; Lauttia S; Tynninen O; Joensuu H; et al. Human breast cancer cells educate macrophages <lb/>toward the M2 activation status. Breast Cancer Res. 2015, 17, 101. [PubMed: 26243145] <lb/>33. Gubin MM; Esaulova E; Ward JP; Malkova ON; Runci D; Wong P; Noguchi T; Arthur CD; Meng <lb/>W; Alspach E; et al. High-dimensional analysis delineates myeloid and lymphoid compartment <lb/>remodeling during successful immune-checkpoint cancer therapy. Cell 2018, 175, 1014-1030. <lb/>[PubMed: 30343900] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>34. Su S; Liu Q; Chen J; Chen J; Chen F; He C; Huang D; Wu W; Lin L; Huang W; et al. A Positive <lb/>feedback loop between mesenchymal-like cancer cells and macrophages is essential to breast <lb/>cancer metastasis. Cancer Cell 2014, 25, 605-620. [PubMed: 24823638] <lb/>35. Burger GA; Danen EHJ; Beltman JB Deciphering epithelial-Mesenchymal transition regulatory <lb/>networks in cancer through computational approaches. Front. Oncol 2017, 7, 162. [PubMed: <lb/>28824874] <lb/>36. Mitchem JB; Brennan DJ; Knolhoff BL; Belt BA; Zhu Y; Sanford DE; Belaygorod L; Carpenter D; <lb/>Collins L; Piwnica-Worms D; et al. Targeting tumor-infiltrating macrophages decreases tumor-<lb/>initiating cells, relieves immunosuppression, and improves chemotherapeutic responses. Cancer <lb/>Res. 2013, 73, 1128-1141. [PubMed: 23221383] <lb/>37. Qian B; Deng Y; Im JH; Muschel RJ; Zou Y; Li J; Lang RA; Pollard JW A distinct macrophage <lb/>population mediates metastatic breast cancer cell extravasation, establishment and growth. PLoS <lb/>ONE 2009, 4, e6562. [PubMed: 19668347] <lb/>38. Lohela M; Casbon A-J; Olow A; Bonham L; Branstetter D; Weng N; Smith J; Werb Z Intravital <lb/>imaging reveals distinct responses of depleting dynamic tumor-associated macrophage and <lb/>dendritic cell subpopulations. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 2014, 111, E5086-E5095. [PubMed: <lb/>25385645] <lb/>39. Ngambenjawong C; Cieslewicz M; Schellinger JG; Pun SH Synthesis and evaluation of multivalent <lb/>M2pep peptides for targeting alternatively activated M2 macrophages. J. Control. Release 2016, <lb/>224, 103-111. [PubMed: 26772876] <lb/>40. Mishalian I; Granot Z; Fridlender ZG The diversity of circulating neutrophils in cancer. <lb/>Immunobiology 222, 82-88. [PubMed: 26874580] <lb/>41. Davis BP; Rothenberg ME Eosinophils and cancer. Cancer Immunol. Res 2014, 2, 1-8. [PubMed: <lb/>24778159] <lb/>42. Hämmerling GJ; Carretero R; Beckhove P; Salgado OC; Sektioglu IM; Garbi N Eosinophils <lb/>orchestrate cancer rejection by normalizing tumor vessels and enhancing infiltration of CD8+ T <lb/>cells. Nat. Immunol 2015, 16, 609-617. [PubMed: 25915731] <lb/>43. Sakkal S; Miller S; Apostolopoulos V; Nurgali K Eosinophils in cancer: Favourable or <lb/>unfavourable? Curr. Med. Chem 2016, 23, 650-666. [PubMed: 26785997] <lb/>44. Shinde SB; Kurhekar MP Review of the systems biology of the immune system using agent-based <lb/>models. IET Syst. Biol 2018, 12, 83-92. [PubMed: 29745901] <lb/>45. Altrock PM; Liu LL; Michor F The mathematics of cancer: Integrating quantitative models. Nat. <lb/>Rev. Cancer 2015, 15, 730-745. [PubMed: 26597528] <lb/>46. Rejniak KA; McCawley LJ Current trends in mathematical modeling of tumor-microenvironment <lb/>interactions: A survey of tools and applications. Exp. Biol. Med 2010, 235, 411-423. <lb/>47. Eftimie R; Bramson JL; Earn DJD Interactions between the immune system and cancer: A brief <lb/>review of non-spatial mathematical models. Bull. Math. Biol 2011, 73, 2-32. [PubMed: 20225137] <lb/>48. Alemani D; Pappalardo F; Pennisi M; Motta S; Brusic V Combining cellular automata and lattice <lb/>Boltzmann method to model multiscale avascular tumor growth coupled with nutrient diffusion <lb/>and immune competition. J. Immunol. Methods 2012, 376, 55-68. [PubMed: 22154892] <lb/>49. Bellomo N; Delitala M From the mathematical kinetic, and stochastic game theory to modelling <lb/>mutations, onset, progression and immune competition of cancer cells. Phys. Life Rev 2008, 5, <lb/>183-206. <lb/>50. Eladdadi A; de Pillis L; Kim P Modelling tumour-immune dynamics, disease progression and <lb/>treatment. Lett. Biomath 2018, 5, S1-S5. <lb/>51. Dritschel H; Waters SL; Roller A; Byrne HM A mathematical model of cytotoxic and helper T cell <lb/>interactions in a tumour microenvironment. Lett. Biomath 2018, 5, S36-S68. <lb/>52. Nikolopoulou E; Johnson LR; Harris D; Nagy JD; Stites EC; Kuang Y Tumour-immune dynamics <lb/>with an immune checkpoint inhibitor. Lett. Biomath 2018, 5, S137-S159. <lb/>53. Salgia R; Mambetsariev I; Hewelt B; Achuthan S; Li H; Poroyko V; Wang Y; Sattler M Modeling <lb/>small cell lung cancer (SCLC) biology through deterministic and stochastic mathematical models. <lb/>Oncotarget 2018, 9, 26226-26242. [PubMed: 29899855] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>54. Konstorum A; Vella AT; Adler AJ; Laubenbacher RC Addressing current challenges in cancer <lb/>immunotherapy with mathematical and computational modelling. J. R. Soc. Interface 2017, 14, <lb/>20170150. [PubMed: 28659410] <lb/>55. Chiacchio F; Pennisi M; Russo G; Motta S; Pappalardo F Agent-based modeling of the immune <lb/>system: NetLogo, a promising framework. BioMed Res. Int 2014, 907171. [PubMed: 24864263] <lb/>56. An G; Mi Q; Dutta-Moscato J; Vodovotz Y Agent-based models in translational systems biology. <lb/>Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Syst. Biol. Med 2009, 1, 159-171. [PubMed: 20835989] <lb/>57. Chavali AK; Gianchandani EP; Tung KS; Lawrence MB; Peirce SM; Papin JA Characterizing <lb/>emergent properties of immunological systems with multi-cellular rule-based computational <lb/>modeling. Trends Immunol. 2008, 29, 589-599. [PubMed: 18964301] <lb/>58. Shi ZZ; Wu C-H; Ben-Arieh D Agent-based model: A surging tool to simulate infectious diseases <lb/>in the immune system. Open J. Model. Simul 2014, 02, 12-22. <lb/>59. Segovia-Juarez JL; Ganguli S; Kirschner D Identifying control mechanisms of granuloma <lb/>formation during M. tuberculosis infection using an agent-based model. J. Theor. Biol 2004, 231, <lb/>357-376. [PubMed: 15501468] <lb/>60. Tokarski C; Hummert S; Mech F; Figge MT; Germerodt S; Schroeter A; Schuster S; Linde J; Hu G <lb/>Agent-based modeling approach of immune defense against spores of opportunistic human <lb/>pathogenic fungi. Front. Microbiol 2012, 3, 129. [PubMed: 22557995] <lb/>61. Dong X; Foteinou PT; Calvano SE; Lowry SF; Androulakis IP Agent-based modeling of <lb/>endotoxin-induced acute inflammatory response in human blood leukocytes. PLoS ONE 2010, 5, <lb/>e9249. [PubMed: 20174629] <lb/>62. Solovyev A; Mi Q; Tzen YT; Brienza D; Vodovotz Y Hybrid equation/agent-based model of <lb/>ischemia-induced hyperemia and pressure ulcer formation predicts greater propensity to ulcerate in <lb/>subjects with spinal cord injury. PLoS Comput. Biol 2013, 9, e1003070. [PubMed: 23696726] <lb/>63. Santoni D; Pedicini M; Castiglione F Implementation of a regulatory gene network to simulate the <lb/>TH1/2 differentiation in an agent-based model of hypersensitivity reactions. Bioinformatics 2008, <lb/>24, 1374-1380. [PubMed: 18413328] <lb/>64. Bailey AM; Lawrence MB; Shang H; Katz AJ; Peirce SM Agent-based model of therapeutic <lb/>adipose-derived stromal cell trafficking during ischemia predicts ability to roll on p-selectin. PLoS <lb/>Comput. Biol 2009, 5, e1000294. [PubMed: 19247427] <lb/>65. D&apos;Souza RM; Lysenko M; Marino S; Kirschner D; Souza RMD; Arbor A Data-parallel algorithms <lb/>for agent-based model simulation of tuberculosis on graphics processing units In Proceedings of <lb/>the 2009 Spring Simulation Multiconference, San Diego, CA, USA, 22-27 3 2009. <lb/>66. Song SO; Hogg J; Peng ZY; Parker R; Kellum JA; Clermont G Ensemble models of neutrophil <lb/>trafficking in severe sepsis. PLoS Comput. Biol 2012, 8, e1002422. [PubMed: 22412365] <lb/>67. Mi Q; Riviere B; Clermont G; Steed DL; Vodovotz Y Agent-based model of inflammation and <lb/>wound healing: Insights into diabetic foot ulcer pathology and the role of transforming growth <lb/>factor-β1 Wound Repair Regen. 2007, 15, 671-682. [PubMed: 17971013] <lb/>68. Alarcón T; Byrne HM; Maini PK A mathematical model of the effects of hypoxia on the cell-cycle <lb/>of normal and cancer cells. J. Theor. Biol 2004, 229, 395-411. [PubMed: 15234206] <lb/>69. Hoehme S; Bertaux F; Weens W; Grasl-Kraupp B; Hengstler JG; Drasdo D Model prediction and <lb/>validation of an order mechanism controlling the spatiotemporal phenotype of early hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma. Bull. Math. Biol 2018, 80, 1134-1171. [PubMed: 29568983] <lb/>70. Bianca C; Pennisi M The triplex vaccine effects in mammary carcinoma: A nonlinear model in <lb/>tune with SimTriplex. Nonlinear Anal. Real World Appl 2012, 13, 1913-1940. <lb/>71. Wang J; Zhang L; Jing C; Ye G; Wu H; Miao H; Wu Y; Zhou X Multi-scale agent-based modeling <lb/>on melanoma and its related angiogenesis analysis. Theor. Biol. Med. Model 2013, 10, 41. <lb/>[PubMed: 23800293] <lb/>72. Kather JN; Poleszczuk J; Suarez-Carmona M; Krisam J; Charoentong P; Valous NA; Weis CA; <lb/>Tavernar L; Leiss F; Herpel E; et al. In silico modeling of immunotherapy and stroma-targeting <lb/>therapies in human colorectal cancer. Cancer Res. 2017, 77, 6442-6452. [PubMed: 28923860] <lb/>73. Pennisi M; Pappalardo F; Motta S Agent based modeling of lung metastasis-immune system <lb/>competition In Lecture Notes in Computer Science (Including Subseries Lecture Notes in <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics); Springer: Berlin/Heidelberg, <lb/>Germany, 2009; Volume 5666, pp. 1-3. <lb/>74. Jagiella N; Muller B; Muller M; Vignon-Clementel IE; Drasdo D Inferring growth control <lb/>mechanisms in growing multi-cellular spheroids of NSCLC cells from spatial-temporal image <lb/>data. PLoS Comput. Biol 2016, 12, e1004412. [PubMed: 26866479] <lb/>75. Pennisi M; Pappalardo F; Palladini A; Nicoletti G; Nanni P; Lollini P-L; Motta S Modeling the <lb/>competition between lung metastases and the immune system using agents. BMC Bioinform. <lb/>2010, 11, S13. <lb/>76. Bezzi M; Celada F; Ruffo S; Seiden PE The transition between immune and disease states in a <lb/>cellular automaton model of clonal immune response. Phys. A Stat. Mech. Its Appl 1997, 245, <lb/>145-163. <lb/>77. Baldazzi V; Castiglione F; Bernaschi M An enhanced agent based model of the immune system <lb/>response. Cell Immunol. 2006, 244, 77-79. [PubMed: 17416357] <lb/>78. Bernaschi M; Castiglione F Design and implementation of an immune system simulator. Comput. <lb/>Biol. Med 2001, 31, 303-331. [PubMed: 11535199] <lb/>79. Celada F; Seiden PE A computer model of cellular interactions in the immune system. Immunol. <lb/>Today 1992, 13, 56-62. [PubMed: 1575893] <lb/>80. Emerson A; Rossi E ImmunoGrid -the virtual human immune system project. Stud. Heal. Technol. <lb/>Inf 2007, 126, 87-92. <lb/>81. Halling-Brown M; Pappalardo F; Rapin N; Zhang P; Alemani D; Emerson A; Castiglione F; <lb/>Duroux P; Pennisi M; Miotto O; et al. ImmunoGrid: Towards agent-based simulations of the <lb/>human immune system at a natural scale. Philos. Trans. R. Soc. A Math. Phys. Eng. Sci 2010, 368, <lb/>2799. <lb/>82. Perelson AS; Ribeiro RM Modeling the within-host dynamics of HIV infection. BMC Biol. 2013, <lb/>11, 96. [PubMed: 24020860] <lb/>83. Warrender C; Forrest S; Koster F Modeling intercellular interactions in early Mycobacterium <lb/>infection. Bull. Math. Biol 2006, 68, 2233-2261. [PubMed: 17086496] <lb/>84. Ghaffarizadeh A; Heiland R; Friedman SH; Mumenthaler SM; Macklin P PhysiCell: An open <lb/>source physics-based cell simulator for 3-D multicellular systems. PLOS Comput. Biol 2018, 14, <lb/>e1005991. [PubMed: 29474446] <lb/>85. Gilkes DM; Semenza GL; Wirtz D Hypoxia and the extracellular matrix: Drivers of tumour <lb/>metastasis. Nat. Rev. Cancer 2014, 14, 430-439. [PubMed: 24827502] <lb/>86. Alfonso JCL; Talkenberger K; Seifert M; Klink B; Hawkins-Daarud A; Swanson KR; Hatzikirou <lb/>H; Deutsch A The biology and mathematical modelling of glioma invasion: A review. J. R. Soc. <lb/>Interface 2017, 14, 20170490. [PubMed: 29118112] <lb/>87. Massey SC; Rockne RC; Hawkins-Daarud A; Gallaher J; Anderson ARA; Canoll P; Swanson KR <lb/>Simulating PDGF-driven glioma growth and invasion in an anatomically accurate brain domain. <lb/>Bull. Math. Biol 2018, 80, 1292-1309. [PubMed: 28842831] <lb/>88. Juliano J; Gil O; Hawkins-Daarud A; Noticewala S; Rockne RC; Gallaher J; Massey SC; Sims PA; <lb/>Anderson ARA; Swanson KR; et al. Comparative dynamics of microglial and glioma cell motility <lb/>at the infiltrative margin of brain tumours. J. R. Soc. Interface 2018, 15, 20170582. [PubMed: <lb/>29445035] <lb/>89. Frascoli F; Flood E; Kim PS A model of the effects of cancer cell motility and cellular adhesion <lb/>properties on tumour-immune dynamics. Math. Med. Biol 2016, 34, dqw004. <lb/>90. Noonan DM; De Lerma Barbaro A; Vannini N; Mortara L; Albini A Inflammation, inflammatory <lb/>cells and angiogenesis: Decisions and indecisions. Cancer Metastasis Rev. 2008, 27, 31-40. <lb/>[PubMed: 18087678] <lb/>91. Tian L; Goldstein A; Wang H; Ching Lo H; Sun Kim I; Welte T; Sheng K; Dobrolecki LE; Zhang <lb/>X; Putluri N; et al. Mutual regulation of tumour vessel normalization and immunostimulatory <lb/>reprogramming. Nature 2017, 544, 250-254. [PubMed: 28371798] <lb/>92. Uppal A; Wightman SC; Ganai S; Weichselbaum RR; An G Investigation of the essential role of <lb/>platelet-tumor cell interactions in metastasis progression using an agent-based model. Theor. Biol. <lb/>Med. Model 2014, 11, 17. [PubMed: 24725600] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>93. Alfonso JCL; Schaadt NS; Schbnmeyer R; Brieu N; Forestier G; Wemmert C; Feuerhake F; <lb/>Hatzikirou H In-silico insights on the prognostic potential of immune cell infiltration patterns in <lb/>the breast lobular epithelium. Sci. Rep 2016, 6, 33322. [PubMed: 27659691] <lb/>94. Reddy NP; Krouskop TA; Newell PH A computer model of the lymphatic system. Comput. Biol. <lb/>Med 1977, 7, 181-197. [PubMed: 891141] <lb/>95. Jamalian S; Jafarnejad M; Zawieja SD; Bertram CD; Gashev AA; Zawieja DC; Davis MJ; Moore <lb/>JE Demonstration and analysis of the suction effect for pumping lymph from tissue beds at <lb/>subatmospheric pressure. Sci. Rep 2017, 7, 12080. [PubMed: 28935890] <lb/>96. Jamalian S; Davis MJ; Zawieja DC; Moore JE Network scale modeling of lymph transport and its <lb/>effective pumping parameters. PLoS ONE 2016, 11, e0148384. [PubMed: 26845031] <lb/>97. Jamalian S; Bertram CD; Richardson WJ; Moore JE Parameter sensitivity analysis of a lumped-<lb/>parameter model of a chain of lymphangions in series. Am. J. Physiol. Circ. Physiol 2013, 305, <lb/>H1709-H1717. <lb/>98. Wilson JT; van Loon R; Wang W; Zawieja DC; Moore JE Determining the combined effect of the <lb/>lymphatic valve leaflets and sinus on resistance to forward flow. J. Biomech 2015, 48, 3584-3590. <lb/>[PubMed: 26315921] <lb/>99. Roose T; Swartz MA Multiscale modeling of lymphatic drainage from tissues using <lb/>homogenization theory. J. Biomech 2012, 45, 107-115. [PubMed: 22036032] <lb/>100. Jafarnejad M; Zawieja DC; Brook BS; Nibbs RJB; Moore JE A novel computational model <lb/>predicts key regulators of chemokine gradient formation in lymph nodes and site-specific roles <lb/>for CCL19 and ACKR4. J. Immunol 2017, 299, ji1700377. <lb/>101. Jafarnejad M; Woodruff MC; Zawieja DC; Carroll MC; Moore JE Modeling lymph flow and fluid <lb/>exchange with blood vessels in lymph nodes. Lymphat. Res. Biol 2015, 13, 234-247. [PubMed: <lb/>26683026] <lb/>102. Cooper LJ; Heppell JP; Clough GF; Ganapathisubramani B; Roose T An image-based model of <lb/>fluid flow through lymph nodes. Bull. Math. Biol 2016, 78, 52-71. [PubMed: 26690921] <lb/>103. Marino S; Gideon HP; Gong C; Mankad S; McCrone JT; Lin PL; Linderman JJ; Flynn JAL; <lb/>Kirschner DE Computational and empirical studies predict mycobacterium tuberculosis-specific <lb/>T cells as a biomarker for infection outcome. PLoS Comput. Biol 2016, 12, e1004804. [PubMed: <lb/>27065304] <lb/>104. Gong C; Linderman JJ; Kirschner D Harnessing the heterogeneity of T cell differentiation fate to <lb/>fine-tune generation of effector and memory T cells. Front. Immunol 2014, 5, 57. [PubMed: <lb/>24600448] <lb/>105. Margaris KN; Black RA Modelling the lymphatic system: Challenges and opportunities. J. R. <lb/>Soc. Interface 2012, 9, 601-612. [PubMed: 22237677] <lb/>106. Meyer-Hermann M A mathematical model for the germinal center morphology and affinity <lb/>maturation. J. Theor. Biol 2002, 216, 273-300. [PubMed: 12183119] <lb/>107. Meyer-Hermann ME; Maini PK Cutting edge: Back to &quot;one-way&quot; germinal centers. J. Immunol <lb/>2005, 174, 2489-2493. [PubMed: 15728453] <lb/>108. Meyer-Hermann ME; Maini PK; Iber D An analysis of B cell selection mechanisms in germinal <lb/>centers. Math. Med. Biol. A J. IMA 2006, 23, 255-277. <lb/>109. Bogle G; Dunbar PR T cell responses in lymph nodes. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Syst. Biol. Med <lb/>2010, 2, 107-116. [PubMed: 20836014] <lb/>110. Bogle G; Dunbar PR Agent-based simulation of T-cell activation and proliferation within a lymph <lb/>node. Immunol. Cell Biol 2010, 88, 172-179. [PubMed: 19884904] <lb/>111. Bogle G; Dunbar PR On-lattice simulation of T cell motility, chemotaxis, and trafficking in the <lb/>lymph node paracortex. PLoS ONE 2012, 7, e45258. [PubMed: 23028887] <lb/>112. Bogle G; Dunbar PR Simulating T-cell motility in the lymph node paracortex with a packed <lb/>lattice geometry. Immunol. Cell Biol 2008, 86, 676-687. [PubMed: 18711399] <lb/>113. Moreau HD; Bogle G; Bousso P A virtual lymph node model to dissect the requirements for T-<lb/>cell activation by synapses and kinapses. Immunol. Cell Biol 2016, 94, 680-688. [PubMed: <lb/>27089942] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>114. Folcik VA; An GC; Orosz CG The Basic Immune Simulator: An agent-based model to study the <lb/>interactions between innate and adaptive immunity. Theor. Biol. Med. Model 2007, 4, 39. <lb/>[PubMed: 17900357] <lb/>115. Kim PS; Levy D; Lee PP Modeling and simulation of the immune system as a self-regulating <lb/>network. Methods Enzymol. 2009, 467, 79-109. [PubMed: 19897090] <lb/>116. Jacob C; Sarpe V; Gingras C; Feyt RP Swarm-based simulations for immunobiology: What can <lb/>agent-based models teach us about the immune system? In Intelligent Systems Reference <lb/>Library; Springer: Berlin/Heidelberg, Germany, 2011; Volume 11, pp. 29-64. <lb/>117. Marino S; El-Kebir M; Kirschner D A hybrid multi-compartment model of granuloma formation <lb/>and T cell priming in Tuberculosis. J. Theor. Biol 2011, 280, 50-62. [PubMed: 21443879] <lb/>118. Marino S; Kirschner D A multi-compartment hybrid computational model predicts key roles for <lb/>dendritic cells in Tuberculosis infection. Computation 2016, 4, 39. [PubMed: 28989808] <lb/>119. Dréau D; Stanimirov D; Carmichael T; Hadzikadic M An agent-based model of solid tumor <lb/>progression In Lecture Notes in Computer Science (Including Subseries Lecture Notes in <lb/>Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics); Springer: Berlin/Heidelberg, <lb/>Germany, 2009; Volume 5462, pp. 187-198. <lb/>120. Pappalardo F; Forero IM; Pennisi M; Palazon A; Melero I; Motta S Simb16: Modeling induced <lb/>immune system response against B16-melanoma. PLoS ONE 2011, 6, e26523. [PubMed: <lb/>22028894] <lb/>121. Sanchez-Paulete AR; Labiano S; Rodriguez-Ruiz ME; Azpilikueta A; Etxeberria I; Bolaños E; <lb/>Lang V; Rodriguez M; Aznar MA; Jure-Kunkel M; et al. Deciphering CD137 (4-1BB) signaling <lb/>in T-cell costimulation for translation into successful cancer immunotherapy. Eur. J. Immunol <lb/>2016, 46, 513-522. [PubMed: 26773716] <lb/>122. Santiago DN; Heidbuechel JPW; Kandell WM; Walker R; Djeu J; Engeland CE; Abate-Daga D; <lb/>Enderling H Fighting cancer with mathematics and viruses. Viruses 2017, 9, 239. <lb/>123. Walker R; Navas PE; Friedman SH; Galliani S; Karolak A; MacFarlane F; Noble R; Poleszczuk J; <lb/>Russell S; Rejniak KA; et al. Enhancing synergy of CAR T cell therapy and oncolytic virus <lb/>therapy for pancreatic cancer. bioRxiv 2016, 055988. <lb/>124. Rohrs JA; Zheng D; Graham NA; Wang P; Finley SD Computational model of chimeric antigen <lb/>receptors explains site-specific phosphorylation kinetics. Biophys. J 2018, 115, 1116-1129. <lb/>[PubMed: 30197180] <lb/>125. Schumacher TN; Schreiber RD Neoantigens in cancer immunotherapy. Science 2015, 348, 69-74. <lb/>[PubMed: 25838375] <lb/>126. Sharma P; Allison JP The future of immune checkpoint therapy. Science 2015, 348, 56-61. <lb/>[PubMed: 25838373] <lb/>127. Gong C; Milberg O; Wang B; Vicini P; Narwal R; Roskos L; Popel AS A computational <lb/>multiscale agent-based model for simulating spatio-temporal tumour immune response to PD1 <lb/>and PDL1 inhibition. J. R. Soc. Interface 2017, 14, 20170320. [PubMed: 28931635] <lb/>128. Hillen T; Enderling H; Hahnfeldt P The tumor growth paradox and immune system-mediated <lb/>selection for cancer stem cells. Bull. Math. Biol 2013, 75, 161-184. [PubMed: 23196354] <lb/>129. Enderling H; Hlatky L; Hahnfeldt P Immunoediting: Evidence of the multifaceted role of the <lb/>immune system in self-metastatic tumor growth. Theor. Biol. Med. Model 2012, 9, 31. [PubMed: <lb/>22838395] <lb/>130. Dehne N; Mora J; Namgaladze D; Weigert A; Brüne B Cancer cell and macrophage cross-talk in <lb/>the tumor microenvironment. Curr. Opin. Pharmacol 2017, 35, 12-19. [PubMed: 28538141] <lb/>131. Wells DK; Chuang Y; Knapp LM; Brockmann D; Kath WL; Leonard JN Spatial and functional <lb/>heterogeneities shape collective behavior of tumor-immune networks. PLoS Comput. Biol 2015, <lb/>11, e1004181. [PubMed: 25905470] <lb/>132. Knútsdóttir H; Pálsson E; Edelstein-Keshet L Mathematical model of macrophage-facilitated <lb/>breast cancer cells invasion. J. Theor. Biol 2014, 357, 184-199. [PubMed: 24810842] <lb/>133. Knutsdottir H; Condeelis JS; Palsson E 3-D individual cell based computational modeling of <lb/>tumor cell-macrophage paracrine signaling mediated by EGF and CSF-1 gradients. Integr. Biol <lb/>2016, 8, 104-119. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>134. Norton KA; Jin K; Popel AS Modeling triple-negative breast cancer heterogeneity: Effects of <lb/>stromal macrophages, fibroblasts and tumor vasculature. J. Theor. Biol 2018, 452, 56-68. <lb/>[PubMed: 29750999] <lb/>135. Marusyk A; Almendro V; Polyak K Intra-tumour heterogeneity: A looking glass for cancer? Nat. <lb/>Rev. Cancer 2012, 12, 323-334. [PubMed: 22513401] <lb/>136. Lehrach H Virtual clinical trials, an essential step in increasing the effectiveness of the drug <lb/>development process. Public Health Genom. 2015, 18, 366-371. <lb/>137. Pourhasanzade F; Sabzpoushan S; Alizadeh AM; Esmati E An agent-based model of avascular <lb/>tumor growth: Immune response tendency to prevent cancer development. Simulation 2017, 93, <lb/>641-657. <lb/>138. Carmona-Fontaine C; Bucci V; Akkari L; Deforet M; Joyce JA; Xavier JB Emergence of spatial <lb/>structure in the tumor microenvironment due to the Warburg effect. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA <lb/>2013, 110, 19402-19407. [PubMed: 24218566] <lb/>139. Figueredo GP; Aickelin U; Siebers PO Systems dynamics or agent-based modelling for immune <lb/>simulation? In Proceedings of the Lecture Notes in Computer Science (Including Subseries <lb/>Lecture Notes in Artificial Intelligence and Lecture Notes in Bioinformatics); Springer: Berlin/ <lb/>Heidelberg, Germany, 2011; Volume 6825, pp. 81-94. <lb/>140. Figueredo GP; Siebers P-O; Aickelin U Investigating mathematical models of immuno-<lb/>interactions with early-stage cancer under an agent-based modelling perspective. BMC <lb/>Bioinform. 2013, 14, S6. <lb/>141. Figueredo GP; Joshi TV; Osborne JM; Byrne HM; Owen MR On-lattice agent-based simulation <lb/>of populations of cells within the open-source Chaste framework. Interface Focus 2013, 3, <lb/>20120081. [PubMed: 24427527] <lb/>142. Figueredo GP; Siebers PO; Owen MR; Reps J; Aickelin U Comparing stochastic differential <lb/>equations and agent-based modelling and simulation for early-stage cancer. PLoS ONE 2014, 9, <lb/>e95150. [PubMed: 24752131] <lb/>143. Yankeelov TE; An G; Saut O; Luebeck EG; Popel AS; Ribba B; Vicini P; Zhou X; Weis JA; Ye <lb/>K; et al. Multi-scale modeling in clinical oncology: Opportunities and barriers to success. Ann. <lb/>Biomed. Eng 2016, 44, 2626-2641. [PubMed: 27384942] <lb/>144. Cosgrove J; Butler J; Alden K; Read M; Kumar V; Cucurull-Sanchez L; Timmis J; Coles M <lb/>Agent-based modeling in systems pharmacology. CPT Pharmacometrics Syst. Pharmacol 2015, <lb/>4, 615-629. [PubMed: 26783498] <lb/>145. Rieger TR; Allen RJ; Bystricky L; Chen Y; Colopy GW; Cui Y; Gonzalez A; Liu Y; White RD; <lb/>Everett RA; et al. Improving the generation and selection of virtual populations in quantitative <lb/>systems pharmacology models. Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol 2018, 139, 15-22. [PubMed: <lb/>29902482] <lb/>146. Barretina J; Caponigro G; Stransky N; Venkatesan K; Margolin AA; Kim S; Wilson CJ; Lehár J; <lb/>Kryukov GV; Sonkin D; et al. The Cancer Cell Line Encyclopedia enables predictive modelling <lb/>of anticancer drug sensitivity. Nature 2012, 483, 603-607. [PubMed: 22460905] <lb/>147. Garnett MJ; Edelman EJ; Heidorn SJ; Greenman CD; Dastur A; Lau KW; Greninger P; <lb/>Thompson IR; Luo X; Soares J; et al. Systematic identification of genomic markers of drug <lb/>sensitivity in cancer cells. Nature 2012, 483, 570-575. [PubMed: 22460902] <lb/>148. Rubio-Perez C; Tamborero D; Schroeder MP; Antolin AA; Deu-Pons J; Perez-Llamas C; Mestres <lb/>J; Gonzalez-Perez A; Lopez-Bigas N In silico prescription of anticancer drugs to cohorts of 28 <lb/>tumor types reveals targeting opportunities. Cancer Cell 2015, 27, 382-396. [PubMed: <lb/>25759023] <lb/>149. Anderson ARA; Maini PK Mathematical oncology. Bull. Math. Biol 2018, 80, 945-953. <lb/>[PubMed: 29679280] <lb/>150. Sun X; Hu B Mathematical modeling and computational prediction of cancer drug resistance. <lb/>Brief. Bioinform 2017, 19, 1382-1399. <lb/>151. Arney K Improving brain-cancer therapies through mathematical modelling. Nature 2018, 561, <lb/>S52-S53. [PubMed: 30258162] <lb/>152. Barua D; Hlavacek WS Modeling the effect of APC truncation on destruction complex function in <lb/>colorectal cancer cells. PLoS Comput. Biol 2013, 9, e1003217. [PubMed: 24086117] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<listBibl>153. Klinger B; Sieber A; Fritsche-Guenther R; Witzel F; Berry L; Schumacher D; Yan Y; Durek P; <lb/>Merchant M; Schafer R; et al. Network quantification of EGFR signaling unveils potential for <lb/>targeted combination therapy. Mol. Syst. Biol 2014, 9, 673. <lb/>154. Kirouac DC; Du JY; Lahdenranta J; Overland R; Yarar D; Paragas V; Pace E; McDonagh CF; <lb/>Nielsen UB; Onsum MD Computational modeling of ERBB2-amplified breast cancer identifies <lb/>combined ErbB2/3 blockade as superior to the combination of MEK and AKT inhibitors <lb/>(Science Signaling 6:288 (ra68)). Sci. Signal 2014, 7, er5. <lb/>155. Carbo A; Bassaganya-Riera J; Pedragosa M; Viladomiu M; Marathe M; Eubank S; Wendelsdorf <lb/>K; Bisset K; Hoops S; Deng X; et al. Predictive computational modeling of the mucosal immune <lb/>responses during Helicobacter pylori infection. PLoS ONE 2013, 8, e73365. [PubMed: <lb/>24039925] <lb/>156. Zand R; Abedi V; Hontecillas R; Lu P; Noorbakhsh-Sabet N; Verma M; Leber A; Tubau-Juni N; <lb/>Bassaganya-Riera J Development of synthetic patient populations and in silico clinical trials In <lb/>Accelerated Path to Cures; Springer International Publishing AG: Basel, Switzerland, 2018; pp. <lb/>57-77. <lb/>157. Edelman LB; Eddy JA; Price ND In silico models of cancer. Wiley Interdiscip. Rev. Syst. Biol. <lb/>Med 2010, 2, 438-459. [PubMed: 20836040] <lb/>158. Jerby-Arnon L; Shah P; Cuoco MS; Rodman C; Su M-J; Melms JC; Leeson R; Kanodia A; Mei <lb/>S; Lin J-R; et al. A cancer cell program promotes T cell exclusion and resistance to checkpoint <lb/>blockade. Cell 2018, 175, 984-997.e24. [PubMed: 30388455] <lb/>159. Thorsson V; Gibbs DL; Brown SD; Wolf D; Bortone DS; Ou Yang T-H; Porta-Pardo E; Gao GF; <lb/>Plaisier CL; Eddy JA; et al. The immune landscape of cancer. Immunity 2018, 48, 812-830.e14. <lb/>[PubMed: 29628290] <lb/>160. Gong C; Anders RA; Zhu Q; Taube JM; Green B; Cheng W; Bartelink IH; Vicini P; Wang B; <lb/>Popel AS Quantitative Characterization of CD8+ T Cell Clustering and Spatial Heterogeneity in <lb/>Solid Tumors. Front Oncol. 2018, 8, 649. [PubMed: 30666298] <lb/>161. D&apos;Esposito A; Sweeney PW; Ali M; Saleh M; Ramasawmy R; Roberts TA; Agliardi G; <lb/>Desjardins A; Lythgoe MF; Pedley RB; et al. Computational fluid dynamics with imaging of <lb/>cleared tissue and of in vivo perfusion predicts drug uptake and treatment responses in tumours. <lb/>Nat. Biomed. Eng 2018, 2, 773-787. <lb/>162. Stamatelos SK; Kim E; Pathak AP; Popel AS A bioimage informatics based reconstruction of <lb/>breast tumor microvasculature with computational blood flow predictions. Microvasc. Res 2014, <lb/>91, 8-21. [PubMed: 24342178] <lb/>163. Kirouac DC How do we &quot;validate&quot; a QSP model? CPT Pharmacometrics Syst. Pharmacol 2018, <lb/>7, 547-548. [PubMed: 29761661] <lb/>164. Gadkar K; Kirouac D; Parrott N; Ramanujan S Quantitative systems pharmacology: A promising <lb/>approach for translational pharmacology. Drug Discov. Today Technol 2016, 21-22, 57-65. <lb/>165. Workman P; Draetta GF; Schellens JHM; Bernards R How much longer will we put up with <lb/>100,000 cancer drugs? Cell 2017, 168, 579-583. [PubMed: 28187281] <lb/>166. Zhang X; Li Y; Pan X; Xiaoqiang L; Mohan R; Komaki R; Cox JD; Chang JY Intensity-<lb/>modulated proton therapy reduces the dose to normal tissue compared with intensity-modulated <lb/>radiation therapy or passive scattering proton therapy and enables individualized radical <lb/>radiotherapy for extensive stage IIIB non-small-cell lung canc. Int. J. Radiat. Oncol. Biol. Phys <lb/>2010, 77, 357-366. [PubMed: 19660879] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>Figure 1. <lb/>The Tumor Microenvironment (TME). The tumor microenvironment consists of different <lb/>types of cells (cancer and stromal including immune cells), the extracellular matrix (ECM), <lb/>and the myriad molecules such as chemokines, cytokines, microRNAs, and growth factors. <lb/>Cancer cells (including cancer stem cells and progenitor cells), the tumor vessels (blood <lb/>vessels and lymphatic vessels), immune cells (including tumor-associated macrophages <lb/>(TAM) and T-cells (cytotoxic and regulatory), myeloid-derived suppressor cells (MDSC), <lb/>natural killer cells (NK cell), neutrophils and other stromal components (including the <lb/>extracellular matrix and cancer-associated fibroblasts (CAF)) are shown. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>Figure 2. <lb/>Using hybrid models to study immuno-oncology. While agent-based models are ideal tools <lb/>to recapitulate the spatio-temporal dynamics of cancer cells and the tumor <lb/>microenvironment at the tissue scale, the mechanisms at other biological scales can be <lb/>efficiently embodied using other types of mathematical representations; however, agent-<lb/>based models (ABM) can also be used at any scale. Such multi-scale hybrid models increase <lb/>the flexibility in model construction, improve computational performance, and enhance <lb/>model credibility by allowing comparison between model output and a wide range of <lb/>experimental and clinical observations <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<body>Figure 3. <lb/>Diagram of a multi-compartment hybrid model capturing tumor development and anti-tumor <lb/>immune response. Dynamics of cells and pharmacokinetics of drug (e.g., antibody) in the <lb/>lymphatics, tumor-draining lymph node, central (blood) and peripheral compartments are <lb/>modeled using ordinary differential equation systems. Spatial dynamics of cells and <lb/>molecules in the tumor compartment are captured using agent-based model and partial <lb/>differential equations. Death of cancer cells produces antigens which drive maturation of <lb/>APC and their migration to the tumor draining LN, where CD8+ and CD4+ T-cells go <lb/>through priming and proliferation before they enter blood circulation and extravasate to the <lb/>tumor microenvironment. Effector CD8+ T-cells can be further activated and expanded when <lb/>they encounter tumor antigens. These cytotoxic cells kill cancer cells and also release <lb/>various cytokines, including IL2 which drives further proliferation of T-cells, and IFNγ <lb/>which is proinflammatory and induces PD-L1 expression on cancer cells. PD-L1 can then <lb/>bind to PD-1 molecules on cytotoxic T-cells, resulting in T-cell exhaustion. Both PD-L1 and <lb/>PD-1 molecules are potential targets for immune checkpoint blockade antibodies. <lb/>Regulatory cell types in the ABM include Treg and MDSC, which can inhibit cytotoxic T <lb/>lymphocytes (CTL) through different mechanisms. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. <lb/></note>

			Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Norton et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 27 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. <lb/>Summary of Section 3: ABM and hybrid models discussed in each section. <lb/>3.1. Models <lb/>Focusing on <lb/>Immune-Related <lb/>Tumor <lb/>Mechanobiology <lb/>3.2 Models Focusing on <lb/>Tumor-Associated <lb/>Vasculature in the <lb/>Immune Response <lb/>3.3 Models Focusing on Tumor-<lb/>Associated Lymphatics <lb/>3.4 Models Focusing on <lb/>Tumor Immunotherapy <lb/>3.5 Models Focusing on Tumor-<lb/>Enhancing Immune Cells <lb/>3.6 Models Focusing on Intra-<lb/>Tumor Heterogeneity <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Study <lb/>Ref <lb/>Cellular <lb/>adhesion <lb/>to ECM <lb/>(Frascoli <lb/>et al. <lb/>2016) <lb/>[89] <lb/>Early metastasis <lb/>(Uppal <lb/>et al. <lb/>2017) <lb/>[92] <lb/>Germinal <lb/>centers of <lb/>LN <lb/>(Meyer-Hermann et <lb/>al. 2002, 2005) [106-<lb/>108] <lb/>Lung met in <lb/>mammary <lb/>carcinoma <lb/>(Pennisi et <lb/>al. 2009) <lb/>[73] <lb/>Cancer stem <lb/>cell-immune <lb/>cell <lb/>interaction <lb/>(Hillen 2013) <lb/>(Enderling 2012) <lb/>[128,129] <lb/>Tumor, NK <lb/>cell, <lb/>cytotoxic T-<lb/>cell <lb/>interactions <lb/>(Pourhasanzade <lb/>et al. 2017) <lb/>[137] <lb/>Adoptive <lb/>cell <lb/>transfer <lb/>in <lb/>colorectal <lb/>cancer <lb/>(Kather <lb/>et al. <lb/>2017) <lb/>[72] <lb/>Immune-<lb/>epithelial cell <lb/>interactions in <lb/>breast <lb/>epithelium <lb/>(Alfonso <lb/>et al. <lb/>2016) <lb/>[93] <lb/>T-cell <lb/>behavior in <lb/>LN <lb/>(Bogle et al. 2010, <lb/>2012, 2008) [109-<lb/>113] <lb/>Effect of <lb/>vaccine on lung <lb/>metastasis <lb/>(Pennisi et <lb/>al. 2010) <lb/>[75] <lb/>Effect of M1 <lb/>and M2 <lb/>macrophages <lb/>on tumor <lb/>growth <lb/>(Wells 2015) [131] <lb/>Effect of <lb/>stroma on <lb/>tumor <lb/>spatial <lb/>patterns <lb/>(Carmona-<lb/>Fontaine et al. <lb/>2013) [138] <lb/>T-cell <lb/>activation in <lb/>virtual LN <lb/>(Moreau, 2016) [113] <lb/>Immunotherapy <lb/>in solid tumors <lb/>(Dréau et <lb/>al. 2009) <lb/>[119] <lb/>Signaling <lb/>between <lb/>macrophages <lb/>and cancer <lb/>cells <lb/>(Knútsdóttir et al. <lb/>2014, 2016) <lb/>[132,133] <lb/>Immune <lb/>cell, <lb/>macrophage, <lb/>tumor cell <lb/>interactions <lb/>(Figueredo <lb/>2011, 2013) <lb/>[139,140] <lb/>Model of <lb/>LN to study <lb/>cancer <lb/>vaccines <lb/>(Kim et al. 2009) <lb/>[100] <lb/>Role of T-cells <lb/>in response to <lb/>immunotherapy <lb/>(Pappalardo <lb/>et al. 2011) <lb/>[120] <lb/>Effect of <lb/>macrophages <lb/>on TNBC <lb/>tumor <lb/>growth <lb/>(Norton et al. <lb/>2018) [134] <lb/>Tumors <lb/>under <lb/>oxygen-<lb/>dependent <lb/>proliferation <lb/>(Figueredo <lb/>2013, 2014) <lb/>[141,142] <lb/>Immune <lb/>response <lb/>against <lb/>viruses <lb/>(Jacob et al. 2011) <lb/>[116] <lb/>Effect of <lb/>different <lb/>therapies on <lb/>pancreatic <lb/>tumors <lb/>(Walker et <lb/>al. 2016) <lb/>[123] <lb/>Recruitment <lb/>of APCs in <lb/>the LN from <lb/>lung <lb/>(Marino et al. 2011) <lb/>[117] <lb/>Spatio-<lb/>temporal <lb/>dynamics of <lb/>tumor-immune <lb/>cell interactions <lb/>(Gong et al. <lb/>2017) [127] <lb/>T-cell <lb/>trafficking <lb/>and <lb/>proliferation <lb/>(Marino et al. 2016) <lb/>[118] <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Processes (Basel). Author manuscript; available in PMC 2019 January 28. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
