<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>NIH Public Access <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/>Published in final edited form as: <lb/>Forum Health Econ Policy. 2010 ; 13(2): . doi:10.2202/1558-9544.1204. <lb/>The Effect of Massachusetts&apos; Health Reform on Employer-<lb/>Sponsored Insurance Premiums * <lb/>John F. Cogan * , R. Glenn Hubbard † , and Daniel Kessler ‡ <lb/>* Stanford University, cogan@stanford.edu <lb/> † Graduate School of Business of Columbia University, rgh1@columbia.edu <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/> ‡ Stanford University, fkessler@stanford.edu <lb/>Abstract <lb/>In this paper, we use publicly available data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -<lb/>Insurance Component (MEPS-IC) to investigate the effect of Massachusetts&apos; health reform plan on <lb/>employer-sponsored insurance premiums. We tabulate premium growth for private-sector <lb/>employers in Massachusetts and the United States as a whole for 2004 – 2008. We estimate the <lb/>effect of the plan as the difference in premium growth between Massachusetts and the United <lb/>States between 2006 and 2008—that is, before versus after the plan—over and above the <lb/>difference in premium growth for 2004 to 2006. We find that health reform in Massachusetts <lb/>increased single-coverage employer-sponsored insurance premiums by about 6 percent, or $262. <lb/>Although our research design has important limitations, it does suggest that policy makers should <lb/>be concerned about the consequences of health reform for the cost of private insurance. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>health reform <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>In April 2006, Massachusetts enacted legislation designed to provide nearly universal <lb/>coverage to its residents. The Massachusetts Health Reform Plan involved several <lb/>components (McDonough et al. 2008): an individual mandate, an employer pay-or-play <lb/>requirement, subsidies for low-and moderate-income people, an insurance exchange <lb/>(coupled with other insurance market reforms), changes in insurance regulations, and an <lb/>expansion of the Massachusetts Medicaid program. These changes were phased in <lb/>throughout 2007. <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>Much has been written about the Plan, both favorable (e.g., Long and Stockley 2009) and <lb/>critical (e.g., Tanner 2009). Because the Plan&apos;s main components are the same as those of the <lb/>new health reform law, the effects of the Plan provide a window onto the country&apos;s future. <lb/>Yet, despite this, no study has carefully examined the Plan&apos;s effects on employer-sponsored <lb/></body>

			<front>* John F. Cogan is the Leonard and Shirley Ely Senior Fellow at the Hoover Institution at Stanford University; R. Glenn Hubbard is <lb/>Dean and Russell L. Carson Professor of Finance and Economics (Graduate School of Business) and Professor of Economics at <lb/>Columbia University and Research Associate at the National Bureau of Economic Research (NBER); and Daniel Kessler is Professor <lb/>(Graduate School of Business and Law School) and Senior Fellow (Hoover Institution) at Stanford University and Research Associate <lb/>at NBER. Kessler gratefully acknowledges funding from the National Institutes on Aging through the NBER. All errors or <lb/>misstatements are our own. <lb/>Copyright © 2010 The Berkeley Electronic Press. All rights reserved. <lb/></front>

			<body>insurance premiums. This omission is significant because, in 2008, 58.5 percent of <lb/>Americans obtained coverage from their employer (DeNavas-Walt et al. 2009). <lb/>The Plan&apos;s effect on premiums is theoretically indeterminate. On the one hand, the Plan <lb/>might lead to lower premiums for employer-sponsored insurance. The creation of an <lb/>insurance exchange could reduce transaction costs, especially for small employers. In <lb/>addition, the individual and employer mandates, by expanding coverage, could reduce cost-<lb/>shifting from the uninsured. On the other hand, the Plan might lead to higher premiums. If <lb/>the supply of health services is upward-sloping, then the expansion in the demand for health <lb/>services induced by the plan would lead prices of health services to increase, and premiums <lb/>to follow prices. Any expansion of regulation through the exchange could exacerbate this <lb/>effect. <lb/>The Plan&apos;s effect on small firms relative to their larger counterparts is indeterminate as well. <lb/>One of the consequences of the Plan was the merger of the nongroup/individual and small <lb/>group insurance markets, which was predicted to increase small group rates by 1–1.5 percent <lb/>(Gorman Actuarial et al. 2006). However, other features of the Plan, such as the insurance <lb/>exchanges, may have benefitted small firms disproportionately and therefore have offset this <lb/>effect. <lb/>In this note, we use publicly-available data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -<lb/>Insurance Component (MEPS-IC) to investigate the issue empirically. We tabulate premium <lb/>growth for private-sector employers in Massachusetts and the United States as a whole for <lb/>2004–2008. We estimate the effect of the Plan as the difference in premium growth between <lb/>Massachusetts and the United States between 2006 and 2008 --that is, before versus after <lb/>the Plan --over and above the difference in premium growth for 2004 to 2006. In doing so, <lb/>we control not only for differences in the level of premiums in Massachusetts versus the rest <lb/>of the country, but also for preexisting differences in premium growth that may be due to <lb/>factors unrelated to reform. <lb/>We calculate the effect of reform on single-coverage and family premiums, and on <lb/>premiums for small firms (&lt; 50 employees). In addition, to better account for possible <lb/>economic and demographic differences between Massachusetts and the rest of the country, <lb/>we also compare premium growth in the Boston Metropolitan Statistical Area (MSA) to <lb/>premium growth in the 19 largest other MSAs. Massachusetts as a whole is <lb/>characteristically different from the United States, in that its residents have higher incomes <lb/>and are more concentrated in urban areas. To the extent that these differences affected <lb/>premium growth for reasons unrelated to health reform, the United States would not be a <lb/>good &quot;control&quot; for Massachusetts in the analysis above. Our comparison of the Boston MSA <lb/>only to other large MSAs provides an alternative estimate that, at least in part, addresses this <lb/>concern. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Table 1 presents our analysis of single-coverage premiums. The top panel compares <lb/>premiums in Massachusetts to those in the United States. The first column presents the <lb/>growth in premiums for the 2006 to 2008 period, before versus after Massachusetts&apos; <lb/>adoption of its health reform Plan. Premiums for single coverage at private sector employers <lb/>rose by 8.7 percent in Massachusetts, as compared to 6.5 percent in the United States as a <lb/>whole. A simple estimate of the effect of the Plan, then, would be the difference between 8.7 <lb/>and 6.5, or 2.2 percent. <lb/>This simple calculation, however, does not account for the fact that Massachusetts may have <lb/>had a different preexisting trend in premiums from the rest of the country. The second <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cogan et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>column shows that it did: premiums in Massachusetts grew 3.7 percent more slowly than <lb/>premiums nationwide from 2004 to 2006. Thus, the differential growth in Massachusetts <lb/>versus the United States between 2006 and 2008, as compared to the growth from 2004 to <lb/>2006, is 5.9 percent --our estimate of the effect of the Plan. On the base of Massachusetts&apos; <lb/>2006 premiums of $4,448, this amounts to $262. <lb/>The middle panel of the table presents analogous calculations that compare the Boston/ <lb/>Cambridge/Quincy, MA/NH MSA to the 19 largest other MSAs. Comparing the premium <lb/>growth in the Boston MSA to the country&apos;s other large MSAs yields an estimate of the effect <lb/>of the Plan of 5.5 percent – almost identical to the one above. <lb/>The bottom panel presents calculations for small private-sector employers only. It shows <lb/>that the premiums for this group grew 6.8 percent more in Massachusetts versus the United <lb/>States between in 2006–08 as compared to 2004–06 --0.9 percent greater than the 5.9 <lb/>percent differential growth rate for all private-sector employers. This finding is consistent <lb/>with other analysts&apos; predictions, as discussed above. <lb/>Table 2 presents our analysis of family premiums. As in Table 1, the top panel compares <lb/>Massachusetts to the United States. It shows that premiums in Massachusetts grew 4.1 <lb/>percent more rapidly from 2006 to 2008 than premiums in the nation as a whole. However, <lb/>in the two years before health reform, family insurance premiums were already growing 2.7 <lb/>percent faster in Massachusetts than in the rest of the country. Our estimate of the effect of <lb/>reform is therefore the difference between these numbers, 1.5 percent. This finding is <lb/>surprising, in light of the fact that the Plan required that fully insured family policies offer <lb/>coverage to children for two years after loss of dependent status, or until they turn 26, <lb/>whichever comes first. Previously, family policies could cease covering dependents when <lb/>they were no longer full-time students (McDonough et al. 2008). <lb/>In the Boston MSA, however, family premiums grew far more rapidly: from 2006–08, by <lb/>21.7 percent, or 8.2 percent more than premiums in the nineteen largest other MSAs. This <lb/>rapid growth does not appear to be due to preexisting differential trends: from 2004–06, <lb/>premiums in Boston grew only 0.1 percent more than in the other large MSAs. The fact that <lb/>family premiums in Boston rose much more than in the Commonwealth as a whole suggests <lb/>that the composition of families may have been changing differently across the state. <lb/>Small employers in the Commonwealth as a whole also experienced very high family <lb/>premium growth contemporaneous with health reform. In particular, family premiums for <lb/>employers with less than 50 employees grew 9.4 percent more from 2006–08 in <lb/>Massachusetts than the United States. By comparison, Massachusetts had 5 percent lower <lb/>premium growth in the small-group market from 2004–06. Thus, the differential <lb/>Massachusetts/US growth in small-group premiums from 2006–08, over and above the <lb/>growth from 2004–06, was 14.4 percent. At least by this measure, health reform in <lb/>Massachusetts imposed a very large burden on small businesses and their employees. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>As the country begins to implement health reform, the experience of Massachusetts has <lb/>become increasingly relevant. Even though the Massachusetts reform is little more than two <lb/>years old, data on its effects offer important lessons for the nation as a whole. <lb/>In this note, we use publicly available data from the Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -<lb/>Insurance Component to calculate the effect of health reforms on premium growth from <lb/>2006–08 in Massachusetts relative to the United States, and the Boston MSA relative to the <lb/>19 largest other MSAs. We control for the 2004–06 trends in premiums in order to account <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cogan et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>for any preexisting differences in health care cost growth between Massachusetts and the <lb/>rest of the country. <lb/>We find that health reform in Massachusetts increased single-coverage employer-sponsored <lb/>insurance premiums by about 6 percent in aggregate, and by about 7 percent for firms with <lb/>fewer than 50 employees. The effect of reform on family premiums is less uniform. If <lb/>Massachusetts is compared to the nation as a whole, reform had a modest 1.5 percent effect <lb/>on family premiums. However, in the Boston MSA, and among employees of small firms, <lb/>the effect of reform on family premiums was much greater. Family premiums grew by about <lb/>8 percent more in Boston than in the 19 largest other MSAs from 2006–08, as compared to <lb/>2004–06. For small employers, the differential Massachusetts/US growth in small-group <lb/>premiums from 2006–08, over and above the growth from 2004–06, was 14.4 percent. <lb/>This premium growth is unlikely to be due to changes in cost-sharing. To investigate this <lb/>possibility, we tabulated trends in single-coverage insurance-policy deductibles and <lb/>copayments in Massachusetts and the United States over the study period (not in any <lb/>exhibit).1 We found that deductibles fell slightly, and copayments rose slightly, in <lb/>Massachusetts versus the rest of the country. The average deductible in Massachusetts fell <lb/>approximately $12 relative to the United States from 2006–08, as compared to 2004–06; the <lb/>average copayment for an office visit rose approximately $1 in Massachusetts relative to the <lb/>nation as a whole from 2006–08, relative to 2004–06. Of course, these calculations are not <lb/>definitive, as they only measure two (out of many) dimensions of the extent of cost sharing <lb/>of an insurance policy. Nonetheless, the small magnitude of these changes suggest that <lb/>changes in cost sharing would be unlikely to explain the differential Massachusetts/U.S. <lb/>increase in premiums due to reform. <lb/>Our analysis has at least three important limitations. First, if relative premium growth in <lb/>Massachusetts follows a random process around a long-run mean, then using the pre-reform <lb/>trend as a control for the post-reform period could lead our estimates to overstate the true <lb/>effect of reform. In other words, if there were regression to the mean in relative premiums, <lb/>then the negative 2004–06 trend would lead to high 2006–08 growth, even in the absence of <lb/>reform. Second, the publicly available MEPS-IC tables do not contain sufficient information <lb/>to calculate standard errors for our estimates. Third, we have only calculated the short-run <lb/>effect of reform; long-run effects may be smaller or larger. For example, if the increase in <lb/>premiums is due to the short-run inelasticity of supply of health services, then the long-run <lb/>effect of reform on premiums would decline as supply expands. <lb/>Although the data do not permit firm conclusions about the effect of the Massachusetts Plan <lb/>on premiums, they do suggest that policy makers should be concerned about the <lb/>consequences of health reform for the cost of private insurance. In addition, this note shows <lb/>how researchers seeking to evaluate the effects of the new health reform law can use the <lb/>Massachusetts experience as a roadmap to guide their analyses. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Long SK, Stockley K. Massachusetts Health Reform: Employer Coverage from Employees&apos; <lb/>Perspective. Health Affairs. 2009; 29:w1079–w1087. [PubMed: 19797331] <lb/>McDonough JE, Rosman B, Butt M, Tucker L, Howe LK. Massachusetts Health Reform <lb/>Implementation: Major Progress and Future Challenges. Health Affairs. 2008; 27:w285–w297. <lb/>[PubMed: 18522949] <lb/>1 See MEPS-IC tables II.F.1, II.F.2, II.F.4, II.F.5 available at http://www.meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/survey_comp/Insurance.jsp <lb/>Cogan et al. <lb/>Page 4 <lb/>Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>Tanner, M. Massachusetts Miracle or Massachusetts Miserable: What the Failure of the &apos;Massachusetts <lb/>Model&apos; Tells Us About Health Care Reform. Vol. 112. Washington: Cato Institute Briefing Paper; <lb/>2009. <lb/>DeNavas-Walt, C.; Proctor, BD.; Smith, JC. Income, Poverty, and Health Insurance Coverage in the <lb/>United States: 2008. Washington: US Census Bureau publication; 2009. p. P60-P236.available at <lb/>http://www.census.gov/prod/2009pubs/p60-236.pdf <lb/>Gorman Actuarial, DeWeese Consulting, and Health Strategies. Impact of Merging the Massachusetts <lb/>Non-Group and Small Group Insurance Markets. 2006 December 26. available at <lb/>http://www.mass.gov/Eoca/docs/doi/Legal_Hearings/NonGrp_SmallGrp/Fin <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Cogan et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/> NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Cogan et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Employer-sponsored single-coverage health insurance premiums Massachusetts versus United States, and <lb/>Boston versus the 19 largest other MSAs, 2004–2008 <lb/>Premium <lb/>Growth <lb/>2006-08 <lb/>Premium <lb/>Growth <lb/>2004-06 <lb/>Differential <lb/>Growth <lb/>06-08 -04-06 <lb/>All private-sector employers <lb/>MA <lb/>8.7% <lb/>7.4% <lb/>1.3% <lb/>US <lb/>6.5% <lb/>11.1% <lb/>−4.6% <lb/>Difference <lb/>2.2% <lb/>−3.7% <lb/>5.9% <lb/>Boston MSA <lb/>11.9% <lb/>5.2% <lb/>6.7% <lb/> 19 largest other MSAs <lb/>8.8% <lb/>7.6% <lb/>1.2% <lb/> Difference <lb/>3.1% <lb/>−2.4% <lb/>5.5% <lb/>Small private-sector employers (&lt;50 employees) <lb/>MA <lb/>9.0% <lb/>9.7% <lb/>−0.7% <lb/>US <lb/>5.7% <lb/>13.2% <lb/>−7.5% <lb/>Difference <lb/>3.3% <lb/>−3.5% <lb/>6.8% <lb/>Source: Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -Insurance Component, tables II.C.1. and IX.B.2., 2004, 2006, 2008, available at <lb/>http://www.meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/survey_comp/Insurance.jsp <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/>NIH-PA Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Cogan et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 <lb/>Employer-sponsored family-coverage health insurance premiums Massachusetts versus United States, and <lb/>Boston versus the 19 largest other MSAs, 2004–2008 <lb/>Premium <lb/>Growth <lb/>2006-08 <lb/>Premium <lb/>Growth <lb/>2004-06 <lb/>Differential <lb/>Growth <lb/>06-08 -04-06 <lb/>All private-sector employers <lb/>MA <lb/>12.2% <lb/>16.4% <lb/>−4.2% <lb/>US <lb/>8.1% <lb/>13.7% <lb/>−5.7% <lb/>Difference <lb/>4.1% <lb/>2.7% <lb/>1.5% <lb/>Boston MSA <lb/>21.7% <lb/>7.4% <lb/>14.3% <lb/>19 largest other MSAs <lb/>13.5% <lb/>7.3% <lb/>6.2% <lb/>Difference <lb/>8.2% <lb/>0.1% <lb/>8.1% <lb/>Small private-sector employers (&lt;50 employees) <lb/>MA <lb/>14.7% <lb/>7.1% <lb/>7.6% <lb/>US <lb/>5.3% <lb/>12.1% <lb/>−6.8% <lb/>Difference <lb/>9.4% <lb/>−5.0% <lb/>14.4% <lb/>Source: Medical Expenditure Panel Survey -Insurance Component, tables II.D.1. and IX.B.2., 2004, 2006, 2008, available at <lb/>http://www.meps.ahrq.gov/mepsweb/survey_comp/Insurance.jsp. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Forum Health Econ Policy. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2012 January 4. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
