<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>The <lb/>Oncologist <lb/>® <lb/>Lung Cancer <lb/>Outcomes of Research Biopsies in Phase I Clinical Trials: <lb/>The MD Anderson Cancer Center Experience <lb/>HAZEM EL-OSTA, <lb/>a DAVID HONG, <lb/>a JENNIFER WHELER, <lb/>a SIQING FU, <lb/>a AUNG NAING, <lb/>a GERALD FALCHOOK, <lb/>a <lb/>MARSHALL HICKS, <lb/>b SIJIN WEN, <lb/>c APOSTOLIA M. TSIMBERIDOU, <lb/>a RAZELLE KURZROCK <lb/>a <lb/> Departments of <lb/>a <lb/>Investigational Cancer Therapeutics (Phase I Clinical Trials Program), <lb/>b <lb/>Diagnostic Imaging, <lb/>and <lb/>c <lb/>Biostatistics, The University of Texas MD Anderson Cancer Center, Houston, Texas, USA <lb/>Key Words. Drug development • Mandatory biopsy • Optional biopsy • Phase I clinical trial • Research biopsy <lb/>Disclosures: Hazem El-Osta: None; David Hong: None; Jennifer Wheler: None; Siqing Fu: None; Aung Naing: Research <lb/>funding/contracted research: National Institutes of Health; Gerald Falchook: None; Marshall Hicks: None; Sijin Wen: None; <lb/>Apostolia M. Tsimberidou: None; Razelle Kurzrock: None. <lb/>The content of this article has been reviewed by independent peer reviewers to ensure that it is balanced, objective, and free from <lb/>commercial bias. No financial relationships relevant to the content of this article have been disclosed by the independent peer <lb/>reviewers. <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background. Research biopsies are crucial for exploring <lb/>the impact of novel agents on putative targets. The cur-<lb/>rent study assesses the safety and success rate associated <lb/>with performing such biopsies. <lb/>Methods. We reviewed the medical records of 155 con-<lb/>secutive patients who had one or more research biopsies as <lb/>part of a phase I trial from September 2004 to October 2009. <lb/>Results. Of 281 research biopsies performed, 118 were <lb/>paired before and after treatment biopsies (total ‫؍‬ 236 bi-<lb/>opsies). The most common sites of biopsy were superficial <lb/>lymph node (19.9%), followed by liver (16.4%), and then <lb/>soft tissue (15.7%). Ultrasound-guided biopsies were the <lb/>most frequent type (53.7%). Among 142 patients who con-<lb/>sented for mandatory biopsy, 86.6% had the biopsy per-<lb/>formed, compared with 4.4% of 911 patients offered a <lb/>biopsy on an optional basis (p &lt; .0001). Biopsy was ob-<lb/>tained most frequently on industry-sponsored trials; lack <lb/>of funding on nonindustry trials was the most common <lb/>reason that biopsies were not obtained. Of 281 single biop-<lb/>sies, only 4 (1.4%) had complications: pneumothorax re-<lb/>quiring chest tube placement (n ‫؍‬ 2), infection requiring <lb/>admission (n ‫؍‬ 1), and arrhythmia with hypotension (n ‫؍‬ <lb/>1). All but one biopsy was successful in obtaining tissue. <lb/>No deaths were attributable to biopsy. <lb/>Conclusions. Our experience demonstrates that re-<lb/>search biopsies in early phase clinical trials are safe <lb/>(1.4% risk of serious complications), and a higher per-<lb/>centage of patients underwent mandatory biopsies <lb/>(86.6%) compared with that of the patients with op-<lb/>tional biopsies (4.4%). The Oncologist 2011;16:1292–1298 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Phase I trials play a major role in early drug development, <lb/>bringing investigational drugs from bench to bedside. Tra-<lb/>ditionally, phase I trials aim to define the safety, pharmaco-<lb/>kinetic profile, and recommended dose of novel drugs for <lb/>future phase II studies [1]. In addition, these trials describe <lb/></body>

			<front>Correspondence: David Hong, M.D., Department of Investigational Therapeutics, (Phase 1 Program)-Unit 455, Division of Cancer Med-<lb/>icine, MD Anderson Cancer Center, 1515 Holcombe Boulevard, Houston, Texas 77030, USA. Telephone: 713-563-5844; Pager: 713-<lb/>606-3113; Fax: 713-792-0305; e-mail: dshong@mdanderson.org Received February 21, 2011; accepted for publication June 16, 2011; <lb/>first published online in The Oncologist Express on August 22, 2011. ©AlphaMed Press 1083-7159/2011/$30.00/0 http://dx.doi.org/ <lb/>10.1634/theoncologist.2011-0043 <lb/> The Oncologist 2011;16:1292–1298 www.TheOncologist.com <lb/></front>

			<body>response signals, and in the era of targeted therapy, phar-<lb/>macodynamic properties such as target impact have be-<lb/>come increasingly important. Pharmacodynamic studies <lb/>provide proof-of-principle for the mechanism(s) of action <lb/>and biologic effect of novel drugs on target molecules. In-<lb/>corporating these endpoints into early phase I trials is a crit-<lb/>ical step toward developing targeted agents for patients who <lb/>are most likely to benefit [2, 3]. <lb/>These new strategies in oncology require collecting <lb/>samples from tumor or normal tissue before and after treat-<lb/>ment. Safety concerns and ethical controversies surround-<lb/>ing research biopsies have been voiced [4]. In particular, <lb/>there may be concerns regarding the risk of harm without a <lb/>clearly defined prospect of benefit. In light of the limited <lb/>published literature on this subject [5], we conducted a ret-<lb/>rospective review of the safety of research biopsies per-<lb/>formed on patients enrolled in phase I trials at MD <lb/>Anderson Cancer Center. <lb/>PATIENTS AND METHODS <lb/>Data Collection <lb/>We undertook an electronic chart review of 155 consecu-<lb/>tive patients enrolled in 45 phase I trials that included a <lb/>mandatory or optional biopsy for correlative studies in the <lb/>Department of Investigational Cancer Therapeutics (Phase <lb/>I Clinical Trials program) at The University of Texas MD <lb/>Anderson Cancer Center from September 2004 to October <lb/>2009. Patient information was analyzed that included age, <lb/>gender, performance status, body mass index, anticoagula-<lb/>tion intake, previous treatments on phase I trials, blood <lb/>chemistry panels (albumin, platelet, international normal-<lb/>ized ratio, activated partial thromboplastin time), and can-<lb/>cer types. We also systematically reviewed data regarding <lb/>how biopsy tissue was obtained, including site, method, <lb/>timing, type of needle used, and outcome (failure to obtain <lb/>tissue, serious complications), and characterized the clini-<lb/>cal trials (sponsored by industry or nonindustry trials, man-<lb/>datory or optional biopsies). Trials that were not sponsored <lb/>by industry included trials sponsored by the National Can-<lb/>cer Institute, National Comprehensive Cancer Network, or <lb/>no sponsor. The latter included mainly trials using FDA-<lb/>approved drugs in combination. We defined serious com-<lb/>plications as events that occurred during the first 4 weeks <lb/>after the biopsy procedure and required immediate surgical <lb/>or interventional procedures, or hospitalization. We defined <lb/>comorbidity as any medical condition that coexists with the <lb/>primary cancer such as hypertension, diabetes mellitus, <lb/>heart disease, and lung disease. This study and all biopsies <lb/>were done according to the guidelines of the MD Anderson <lb/>Cancer Center Institutional Review Board (IRB). <lb/>Statistics <lb/>Patient characteristics, biopsy features, and outcomes were <lb/>summarized using descriptive statistics and exploratory <lb/>data analysis. Categorical data were described using con-<lb/>tingency tables. Continuously scaled measures were sum-<lb/>marized with descriptive statistical measures [i.e., mean <lb/>(ϮSD) or median (range)]. The 95% confidence interval of <lb/>the risk of failure and complications of biopsies was esti-<lb/>mated based on binomial distributions. The Fisher&apos;s exact <lb/>test was used to examine the association between two cat-<lb/>egorical variables. A p-value Ͻ.05 denoted statistical sig-<lb/>nificance. Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS <lb/>17.0 software (SPSS, Chicago, IL) and SPLUS (Insightful <lb/>Corp., Seattle) and was verified by our statistician (S.W.). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Patient Demographics <lb/>Overall, 45 phase I trials, 13 investigator-initiated, and 32 <lb/>sponsored studies involving research biopsy on a manda-<lb/>tory or optional basis were identified. A total of 281 biop-<lb/>sies were performed in a total of 155 distinct patients and <lb/>163 protocol enrollees. It should be noted that the 163 pro-<lb/>tocol enrollees biopsied represent 155 distinct patients, be-<lb/>cause 8 patients who were biopsied enrolled on more than <lb/>one protocol and were biopsied on both protocols in which <lb/>they participated. These 155 distinct patients included 110 <lb/>patients who had at least one paired before and after treat-<lb/>ment biopsy (8 of whom had two paired biopsies on two dif-<lb/>ferent phase I studies). Therefore, there were 118 paired <lb/>before and after treatment biopsies, or a total of 236 biop-<lb/>sies that were part of a pair. In addition, there were 45 single <lb/>biopsies of which 42 were before treatment biopsies and 3 <lb/>were after treatment biopsies. The purpose of these biopsies <lb/>varied among protocols, and most protocols specified sev-<lb/>eral types of uses, which included immunohistochemistry <lb/>staining, mutation analysis, single-nucleotide polymor-<lb/>phism analysis, and messenger RNA profiling. <lb/>Demographic and laboratory data are shown in Tables 1 <lb/>and 2. Patient age ranged from 14 to 85 years, with a median <lb/>of 57 years. Eighty patients were men (51.6%). Eight pa-<lb/>tients (5.2%) had previous biopsies in the setting of phase I <lb/>trials, and 46 (29.7%) had been enrolled in earlier phase I <lb/>trials. Performance status was 0 to 1 in 156 of 163 cases <lb/>(95.7%). Comorbidity at the time of biopsy was confirmed <lb/>in 95 of 163 cases (58.3%): hypertension (n ϭ 71, 43.6%), <lb/>diabetes mellitus (n ϭ 24, 14.7%), thyroid dysfunction (n ϭ <lb/>17, 10.4%), dyslipidemia (n ϭ 18, 11%), heart disease (n ϭ <lb/>15, 9.2%), lung and kidney disease (n ϭ 4, 2.5% each), and <lb/>miscellaneous (n ϭ 15, 9.2%). The main types of tumors <lb/>were cutaneous (mainly melanoma) (n ϭ 30, 19.4%), gas-<lb/></body>

			<page>1293 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">El-Osta, Hong, Wheler et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.TheOncologist.com <lb/></note>

			<body>trointestinal (n ϭ 30, 19.4%), head and neck (n ϭ 17, <lb/>10.9%), thoracic (n ϭ 16, 10.3%), gynecologic (n ϭ 13, <lb/>8.4%), genitourinary (n ϭ 12, 7.7%), endocrine (mainly <lb/>thyroid) (n ϭ 10, 6.5%), breast (n ϭ 10, 6.5%), soft tissue <lb/>(mainly sarcoma) (n ϭ 9, 5.8%), and lymphatic (n ϭ 8, <lb/>5.1%) (Table 1). <lb/>Anticoagulation and Antiplatelet Agents <lb/>Eighteen (11%) patients were on anticoagulation therapy <lb/>prior to biopsy; 11 patients (6.7%) were on antiplatelet <lb/>agents. Eight (4.9%) of the 18 patients on anticoagulants <lb/>were on warfarin, whereas 9 (5.5%) were on enoxaparin <lb/>and 1 (0.6%) was on heparin. Typically, warfarin was held <lb/>for 5 days before the procedure, whereas enoxaparin was <lb/>held for 24 hours and aspirin was held for 3 days before the <lb/>procedure. <lb/>In only five cases, antiplatelet agents were not held prior <lb/>to procedure (superficial lymph node biopsy, n ϭ 2; skin <lb/>biopsy, n ϭ 1; breast biopsy, n ϭ 1; abdominal biopsy, n ϭ <lb/>Table 1. Demographics <lb/>Variable <lb/>Results <lb/>Median age (range) <lb/>57 years (14–85) <lb/>Gender <lb/>a <lb/>Male <lb/>80 (51.6%) <lb/>Female <lb/>75 (48.4%) <lb/>Cancer type <lb/>a <lb/>Cutaneous (mainly melanoma) <lb/>30 (19.4 %) <lb/>Gastrointestinal <lb/>30 (19.4 %) <lb/>Head and neck <lb/>17 (10.9 %) <lb/>Thoracic <lb/>16 (10.3 %) <lb/>Gynecologic <lb/>13 (8.4 %) <lb/>Genitourinary <lb/>12 (7.7 %) <lb/>Endocrine (mainly thyroid) <lb/>10 (6.5 %) <lb/>Breast <lb/>10 (6.5 %) <lb/>Soft tissue (mainly sarcoma) <lb/>9 (5.8 %) <lb/>Lymphatic <lb/>8 (5.1 %) <lb/>Previous treatment on phase I trials <lb/>a <lb/>46 (29.7 %) <lb/>Previous biopsy in the setting of <lb/>phase I trial <lb/>a <lb/>8 (5.1 %) <lb/>Anticoagulation <lb/>b <lb/>18 (11 %) <lb/>Antiplatelet agents <lb/>b <lb/>11 (6.7 %) <lb/>Performance status <lb/>b <lb/>0:55 (33.7 %) <lb/>1:101 (62 %) <lb/>2:6 (3.7 %) <lb/>3:1 (0.6 %) <lb/>a <lb/>By number of patients (the denominator is the total <lb/>number of patients studied, which is 155). <lb/>b By number of protocol enrollees (the denominator is the <lb/>total number of protocol enrollees, which is 163 because <lb/>8 patients who were biopsied were enrolled on more than <lb/>one protocol and were biopsied on both protocols in <lb/>which they participated). <lb/>Table 2. Biopsy features <lb/>Number <lb/>Percentage <lb/>Method of biopsy <lb/>Ultrasound <lb/>151 <lb/>53.7% <lb/>CT scan <lb/>105 <lb/>37.4% <lb/>Punch <lb/>23 <lb/>8.2% <lb/>Other <lb/>2 (forceps) 0.7% <lb/>Total <lb/>281 <lb/>100% <lb/>Timing of biopsy <lb/>Before treatment <lb/>42 <lb/>25.8% <lb/>After treatment <lb/>3 <lb/>1.8% <lb/>Before and after treatment <lb/>118 <lb/>72.4% <lb/>Total <lb/>163 <lb/>100% <lb/>Site of biopsy <lb/>Superficial lymph node <lb/>56 <lb/>19.9% <lb/>Liver <lb/>46 <lb/>16.4% <lb/>Soft tissue <lb/>44 <lb/>15.7% <lb/>Lung/pleura <lb/>42 <lb/>14.9% <lb/>Abdominal/pelvis <lb/>35 <lb/>12.4% <lb/>Skin <lb/>23 <lb/>8.2% <lb/>Retroperitoneum <lb/>19 <lb/>6.8% <lb/>Kidney/adrenal <lb/>7 <lb/>2.5% <lb/>Breast <lb/>5 <lb/>1.8% <lb/>Mediastinum <lb/>4 <lb/>1.4% <lb/>Total <lb/>281 <lb/>100% <lb/>Needle gauge <lb/>14 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.8% <lb/>16 <lb/>30 <lb/>11.7% <lb/>18 <lb/>175 <lb/>68.3% <lb/>19 <lb/>13 <lb/>5.1% <lb/>20 <lb/>24 <lb/>9.4% <lb/>21 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.8% <lb/>22 <lb/>10 <lb/>3.9% <lb/>total <lb/>256 <lb/>a <lb/>100% <lb/>Mandatory versus optional <lb/>Mandatory <lb/>123 <lb/>75.5% <lb/>Optional <lb/>40 <lb/>24.5% <lb/>Total <lb/>163 <lb/>100% <lb/>Industry versus nonindustry <lb/>Industry-sponsored <lb/>120 <lb/>73.6% <lb/>Nonindustry-sponsored <lb/>43 <lb/>26.4% <lb/>Total <lb/>163 <lb/>100% <lb/>a This number reflect biopsies obtained using needle and <lb/>does not include punch biopsies (N ϭ 23) or biopsies by <lb/>forceps (N ϭ 2). <lb/></body>

			<page>1294 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research Biopsy in Phase I Clinical Trials <lb/></note>

			<body>1). Warfarin was not held before biopsy in one case of su-<lb/>perficial lymph node biopsy and one case of a subcutaneous <lb/>lesion, whereas enoxaparin was not held in one case of a <lb/>superficial lymph node biopsy. No significant after proce-<lb/>dure complications were encountered in the eight patients <lb/>in whom the anticoagulation or antiplatelet agents were not <lb/>held prior to the procedure, or in the patients in whom it was <lb/>held. <lb/>Biopsy Characteristics <lb/>The main sites of biopsy included superficial lymph node <lb/>(n ϭ 56, 19.9%), liver (n ϭ 46, 16.4%), soft tissue (n ϭ 44, <lb/>15.7%), lung and pleura (n ϭ 42, 14.9%), abdomen and pel-<lb/>vis (n ϭ 35, 12.4%), skin (n ϭ 23, 8.2%), retroperitoneum <lb/>(n ϭ 19, 6.8%), renal/adrenal (n ϭ 7, 2.5%), breast (n ϭ 5, <lb/>1.8%), and mediastinum (n ϭ 4, 1.4%). Ultrasound-guided <lb/>biopsy was the most frequent method for obtaining tissue <lb/>(n ϭ 151, 53.7%) followed by computed tomography– <lb/>guided (CT-guided) scan (n ϭ 105, 37.4%), punch skin bi-<lb/>opsy (n ϭ 23, 8.2%), and biopsy by forceps (n ϭ 2, 0.7%). <lb/>Needles of 18 gauge or above were used in most procedures <lb/>(n ϭ 224 of 256 biopsies, 87.5%). Most skin punch biopsies <lb/>were 3– 4 mm in diameter (17 of 23) (Table 2). <lb/>Of the patients biopsied, 59.5% (n ϭ 97) were on indus-<lb/>try-sponsored trials with mandatory biopsies; 14.1% (n ϭ <lb/>23) were on industry-sponsored trials with optional biop-<lb/>sies; 16% (n ϭ 26) were on nonindustry-sponsored trials <lb/>with mandatory biopsies; and 10.4% (n ϭ 17) were on non-<lb/>industry-sponsored trials with optional biopsies. In regard <lb/>to &quot; mandatory &quot; biopsies, industry-sponsored trials gener-<lb/>ally were inflexible about the mandatory requirement. <lb/>However, even when biopsies were considered &quot; manda-<lb/>tory &quot; in nonindustry-sponsored trials, many protocols al-<lb/>lowed enough flexibility so that patients or physicians <lb/>could opt out of the biopsy providing there was a valid med-<lb/>ical or logistical reason. Among 142 protocol enrollees on <lb/>studies with &quot; mandatory &quot; biopsies, biopsy was done in 123 <lb/>(86.6%). Among 911 protocol enrollees offered a biopsy on <lb/>an optional basis, biopsies were done in only 40 cases <lb/>(4.4%), which was significantly lower (p Ͻ .0001). Twen-<lb/>ty-six of 45 (57.8%) protocol enrollees considered for man-<lb/>datory biopsies per protocol on nonindustry-sponsored <lb/>trials had the biopsy performed compared to 97 of 97 pro-<lb/>tocol enrollees (100%) in industry-sponsored trials (p Ͻ <lb/>.0001). The reason for not having the mandatory research <lb/>biopsy done in the 19 patients was documented as follows: <lb/>14 cases due to lack of funding, 2 cases due to medical rea-<lb/>son, 2 cases due to patient&apos;s refusal of the procedure, and 1 <lb/>case due to absence of biopsiable lesion. Of the 355 enroll-<lb/>ees offered an optional biopsy in industry-sponsored trials, <lb/>23 had the biopsy done, compared to only 17 of 556 in non-<lb/>industry-sponsored trials (6.5% vs. 3.1%, p ϭ .019) (Table <lb/>3). The reasons for not doing the optional biopsies were not <lb/>specified in the research record or medical chart. <lb/>Features of Patients Having Mandatory and <lb/>Optional Biopsy <lb/>We analyzed and compared the clinical and demographic <lb/>profiles of patients having optional versus mandatory biop-<lb/>sies. Statistical analyses revealed that women, gynecologic <lb/>cancer, and breast cancer were more frequently represented <lb/>in the protocol enrollees who underwent biopsies on studies <lb/>with optional biopsies compared to those on studies with <lb/>mandatory biopsies. Indeed, among the 40 protocol enroll-<lb/>ees who underwent the biopsy on studies with optional bi-<lb/>opsy, 23 were women (57.5%), 8 had gynecologic cancer <lb/>(20%), and 6 had breast cancer (15%). Otherwise, among <lb/>the 123 protocol enrollees who underwent the biopsy on <lb/>studies with mandatory biopsy, 52 were women (42.3%), 5 <lb/>had gynecological cancer (4.1%), and 4 had breast cancer <lb/>(3.3%), with p-values of .10, .003, and .015, respectively. <lb/>The distribution of race between the two biopsy groups was <lb/>not statistically significant. <lb/>Table 3. Comparison of mandatory versus optional <lb/>biopsies <lb/>Biopsy <lb/>done <lb/>Biopsy <lb/>not <lb/>done <lb/>Total <lb/>% of <lb/>biopsy <lb/>done <lb/>All trials <lb/>a <lb/>Mandatory <lb/>123 <lb/>19 <lb/>142 <lb/>86.6% <lb/>Optional <lb/>40 <lb/>871 <lb/>911 <lb/>4.4% <lb/>163 <lb/>890 <lb/>1053 15.5% <lb/>Industry-sponsored <lb/>trials <lb/>b <lb/>Mandatory <lb/>97 <lb/>0 <lb/>97 <lb/>100% <lb/>Optional <lb/>23 <lb/>332 <lb/>355 <lb/>6.5% <lb/>120 <lb/>332 <lb/>452 <lb/>26.5% <lb/>Nonindustry-sponsored <lb/>trials <lb/>c <lb/>Mandatory <lb/>26 <lb/>19 <lb/>45 <lb/>57.8% <lb/>Optional <lb/>17 <lb/>539 <lb/>556 <lb/>3.1% <lb/>43 <lb/>558 <lb/>601 <lb/>7.2% <lb/>Industry versus <lb/>nonindustry <lb/>d <lb/>Industry <lb/>120 <lb/>332 <lb/>452 <lb/>26.5% <lb/>Nonindustry <lb/>43 <lb/>558 <lb/>601 <lb/>7.2 % <lb/>163 <lb/>890 <lb/>1053 15.5% <lb/>a p Ͻ .0001. <lb/>b p Ͻ .0001. <lb/>c p Ͻ .0001. <lb/>d p Ͻ .0001. <lb/></body>

			<page>1295 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">El-Osta, Hong, Wheler et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.TheOncologist.com <lb/></note>

			<body>Complications of Research Biopsies <lb/>Of a total of 281 distinct biopsies, only 4 serious complica-<lb/>tions occurred (1.4%). Serious complications included <lb/>pneumothorax requiring chest tube placement (n ϭ 2 of 42 <lb/>lung biopsies [4.8%]), skin infection requiring admission <lb/>(n ϭ 1), and supraventricular tachycardia associated with <lb/>hypotension requiring admission (n ϭ 1). No deaths were <lb/>directly related to biopsy. The two patients having pneumo-<lb/>thorax and the one patient who had arrhythmia all recovered <lb/>promptly. The one patient admitted for skin infection after <lb/>biopsy died soon thereafter from multiple complications re-<lb/>lated to cancer, which were not related to the biopsy proce-<lb/>dure. <lb/>Failure of Research Biopsies <lb/>Research biopsy was unsuccessful in obtaining tissue in <lb/>only one case. In that patient, an attempt was made to access <lb/>the hepatic lesion using ultrasound guidance. The needle <lb/>was advanced into the skin and soft tissues. However, be-<lb/>cause of poor visualization of the lesion, the procedure was <lb/>aborted. This patient had a subsequent successful pelvic bi-<lb/>opsy. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Assessing the effect of a drug on a specific molecular target <lb/>in tumor tissue and identifying biomarkers within tumor <lb/>cells that might correlate with response or resistance has <lb/>played an increasing role in the discovery of new drugs and <lb/>in advancing our understanding of cancer biology. Conse-<lb/>quently, the use of mandatory or optional research biopsies <lb/>and the ethics and safety of conducting research biopsies <lb/>has come to the fore in early clinical trial development. Our <lb/>study confirms that research biopsies are safe (1.4% serious <lb/>complication rate) similar to studies done in other patient <lb/>populations. The 1.4% risk of significant complications that <lb/>we observed is similar to the risk associated with diagnostic <lb/>biopsy [4, 6] and supports the results of Dowlati et al. [5] in <lb/>the research setting. Moreover, we have shown here, per-<lb/>haps for the first time, that mandatory biopsies have a much <lb/>higher success rate (86.6%) of obtaining necessary tissue <lb/>than optional biopsies (4.4%), and an even higher success <lb/>rate on protocols with minimal protocol flexibility concern-<lb/>ing mandatory biopsies (100%). <lb/>Ethical criteria related to medical research have been es-<lb/>tablished with the intention of protecting patients from <lb/>harm and exploitation and ensuring their autonomy and pri-<lb/>vacy [7]. There has been debate about the requirements for <lb/>research-related biopsy procedures, especially when &quot; man-<lb/>datory. &quot; Criticism has centered upon potential harm in the <lb/>absence of direct benefit to patient care [4], impact on pa-<lb/>tient autonomy, and issues related to unrealistic expecta-<lb/>tions from patients regarding benefit despite informed <lb/>consent [8 –11]. There are limited data about the risks asso-<lb/>ciated with research biopsies in the early clinical trials set-<lb/>ting for patients with advanced cancer. Our experience is <lb/>that single or sequential research biopsies in early phase <lb/>clinical trials can be performed safely and successfully <lb/>when adequate precautions are taken and experienced op-<lb/>erators are involved. Only 1.4% of our 155 patients had a <lb/>serious complication, and there were no deaths caused by <lb/>the biopsies. Three of the four serious complications were <lb/>reversible, and in the fourth case the patient died soon there-<lb/>after of progressive cancer. No bleeding was seen, perhaps <lb/>in part because of the policy of stopping anticoagulation or <lb/>antiplatelet agents for several days before the procedure. <lb/>Despite the high incidence of repeat thromboembolism in <lb/>this population, no associated morbidity emerged. Most of <lb/>our patients had a good performance status despite the ex-<lb/>tent of their disease, and this might have contributed to their <lb/>low biopsy morbidity. <lb/>Regarding technique, an 18-gauge needle biopsy was <lb/>used in most cases, but use of a 14-gauge needle has been <lb/>reported to be safe and to yield a greater amount of tissue [5, <lb/>12]. Of our patients, 53.7% had an ultrasound-guided bi-<lb/>opsy, and this method appeared as safe and effective as CT <lb/>scan-guided biopsies, but is significantly less expensive at <lb/>our institution. The highest risk in our study was in the sub-<lb/>set of patients who had lung biopsies. There were two cases <lb/>of pneumothorax requiring chest tubes out of a total of 42 <lb/>single lung biopsies (4.8%), a similar result from a previous <lb/>report in the literature [13]. In another reported multivariate <lb/>analysis of 660 CT-guided lung biopsies [14], the incidence <lb/>of pneumothorax requiring chest tube insertion was 1%. <lb/>This study showed that the risk factors for the highest rate of <lb/>pneumothorax were lesions Ͻ2 cm in size, a subpleural le-<lb/>sion depth from the point of pleural puncture to the nearest <lb/>edge of the lesion of 1–20 mm, and a less experienced op-<lb/>erator. Both of our two patients with this complication had <lb/>a lesion depth between 1 and 20 mm. <lb/>Several questions surrounding mandatory biopsies have <lb/>been raised in the literature. Does requiring a mandatory bi-<lb/>opsy better address the scientific question being explored in <lb/>a trial by increasing the number of collected specimens? Or <lb/>does such a requirement dissuade patients from enrolling <lb/>into clinical trials that require mandatory biopsies for re-<lb/>search purposes? Given the fact that only about 2%– 4% of <lb/>all adult patients with cancer enroll in clinical trials [15], <lb/>impact on study participation has not been well explored. In <lb/>a recent survey-based study, 36% of oncologists and IRB <lb/>members believed that requiring a research biopsy might <lb/>deter patients from participating in clinical trials, and many <lb/>believed that research biopsies should remain optional [16]. <lb/></body>

			<page>1296 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research Biopsy in Phase I Clinical Trials <lb/></note>

			<body>However, most oncologists and IRB members perceived <lb/>that requiring a patient to undergo a mandatory biopsy is <lb/>ethical [16]. Our data confirm that unless biopsies are man-<lb/>datory without protocol flexibility they are often not done. <lb/>Indeed, the rate of biopsies performed in such circum-<lb/>stances was 100% versus 57.8% for protocols where biop-<lb/>sies were &quot; mandatory &quot; but with protocol flexibility for <lb/>medical or logistical reasons. Most of these trials with pro-<lb/>tocol flexibility were investigator-initiated studies and al-<lb/>lowed patients to continue on study for logistical or medical <lb/>reasons at the discretion of the principal investigator even <lb/>though the patient was not able to undergo a biopsy. After <lb/>review of the research records and discussion with the re-<lb/>spective principal investigators, the most common reason <lb/>for not performing the biopsy was financial constraints of <lb/>the investigator and not the medical condition of the patient <lb/>or other logistical reasons, that is, in one National Cancer <lb/>Institute–Cancer Therapy Evaluation Program (NCI-CTEP)-<lb/>sponsored study, translational research funding was ended be-<lb/>fore all biopsies were performed. The latter data suggest that it <lb/>may be that adequate finances may be as or more important to <lb/>procuring a biopsy than the &quot; mandatory &quot; requirement. On the <lb/>basis of these results, it is not surprising that industry-spon-<lb/>sored trials were most rigid in their demand for biopsies and <lb/>most successful in their acquisition. <lb/>In contrast, only 4.4% of patients had biopsies per-<lb/>formed when they were optional. The research and medical <lb/>records in our study did not allow us to determine the rea-<lb/>sons for patients not undergoing a research biopsy. How-<lb/>ever, other investigators have also noted the low rate of <lb/>biopsies that are actually performed when offered on a vol-<lb/>untary basis, with reasons that include: (a) patient-related <lb/>factors, that is, hesitancy because of weighing the associ-<lb/>ated risk in the absence of direct benefit and the time com-<lb/>mitment [16]; (b) physician-related factors, that is, <lb/>physicians having a lower acceptability for risk and who are <lb/>hesitant because of any additional time that might be in-<lb/>curred before obtaining informed consent [17]; and (c) lo-<lb/>gistical factors, such as lack of funding. <lb/>It is interesting to note that the distribution of cancer <lb/>types seen in this cohort differs from the overall distribution <lb/>of cancer types seen in the phase I group, as reported in a <lb/>previous publication from our department [13]. Particu-<lb/>larly, there is more cutaneous cancer, mainly melanoma, in <lb/>our cohort versus those that have been previously reported, <lb/>which were primarily gastrointestinal malignancies. This <lb/>might be reflective of the ease and lower cost of skin-punch <lb/>biopsies in melanoma patients. <lb/>One weakness of our study was the lack of data on the tu-<lb/>mor yield associated with the biopsies; these data were not <lb/>available because most samples did not undergo pathology re-<lb/>view at our institution but instead were reviewed by the spon-<lb/>sor, and the results were not immediately available for this <lb/>study. However, this does not diminish the significance of our <lb/>findings on the safety and rate of obtained biopsies. <lb/>Although it is well established that the risk and purpose <lb/>of research biopsies must be effectively communicated to <lb/>the involved patients [18], whether or not trials should be <lb/>permitted to mandate biopsies is still a matter of debate, al-<lb/>though a consensus appears to have emerged that such a re-<lb/>quirement is ethical. It remains unclear if a negative impact <lb/>on protocol accrual might outweigh the advantages of get-<lb/>ting biopsy specimens. Further studies comparing accrual <lb/>rates between early studies that require mandatory biopsies <lb/>versus those that do not need to be considered are needed. In <lb/>addition, further exploration of why patients agree to op-<lb/>tional biopsies or decline participation in trials with man-<lb/>datory biopsies needs to be explored. We are currently <lb/>conducting a large survey of our phase I patients to deter-<lb/>mine which factors and characteristics influence a patient&apos;s <lb/>decision to participate in studies with biopsies. <lb/>Recent phase I studies, of BRAF inhibitors in BRAF <lb/>V600E mutated melanoma and anaplastic lymphoma ki-<lb/>nase inhibitors in EML-anaplastic lymphoma kinase trans-<lb/>located non–small cell lung cancer patients, have shown the <lb/>importance of predictive markers obtained from tissue in <lb/>selecting patients and increasing response rates [19 –21]. <lb/>These types of studies will likely be the model of future <lb/>phase I studies. The importance of selection by biomarker <lb/>testing in this model is clear, and biopsies are central to this <lb/>process [21]. In conclusion, our study shows that biopsies <lb/>done in a phase I setting are not only safe but should be <lb/>mandatory and gives further support to these selection-<lb/>based early trials. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>This research was supported in part by Grant RR024148 from <lb/>the National Center for Research Resources, a component of <lb/>the NIH Roadmap for Medical Research (http://nihroadmap. <lb/>nih.gov/clinicalresearch/overview-translational.asp). H.E.-O. <lb/>and D.H. contributed equally to this work. We thank Joann <lb/>Aaron for editorial assistance. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Conception/Design: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong, Jennifer Wheler <lb/>Provision of study material or patients: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong, <lb/>Jennifer Wheler, Siqing Fu, Aung Naing, Gerald Falchook, Marshall Hicks, <lb/>Sijin Wen, Apostolia M. Tsimberidou, Razelle Kurzrock <lb/>Collection and/or assembly of data: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong, Aung <lb/>Naing, Gerald Falchook, Marshall Hicks, Sijin Wen, Apostolia M. Tsimberidou, <lb/>Razelle Kurzrock <lb/>Data analysis and interpretation: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong, Jennifer <lb/>Wheler, Siqing Fu, Aung Naing, Gerald Falchook <lb/>Manuscript writing: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong <lb/>Final approval of manuscript: Hazem El-Osta, David Hong, Jennifer Wheler, <lb/>Siqing Fu, Aung Naing, Gerald Falchook, Marshall Hicks, Sijin Wen, <lb/>Apostolia M. Tsimberidou, Razelle Kurzrock <lb/></div>

			<page>1297 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">El-Osta, Hong, Wheler et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">www.TheOncologist.com <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 Horstmann E, McCabe MS, Grochow L et al. Risks and benefits of phase 1 <lb/>oncology trials, 1991 through 2002. N Engl J Med 2005;352:895–904. <lb/>2 Mandrekar SJ, Sargent DJ. Clinical trial designs for predictive biomarker <lb/>validation:theoretical considerations and practical challenges. J Clin Oncol <lb/>2009;27:4027– 4034. <lb/>3 Le Tourneau C, Lee JJ, Siu LL. Dose escalation methods in phase I cancer <lb/>clinical trials. J Natl Cancer Inst 2009;101:708 –720. <lb/>4 Peppercorn J, Shapira I, Collyar D et al. Ethics of mandatory research bi-<lb/>opsy for correlative end points within clinical trials in oncology. J Clin On-<lb/>col 2010;28:2635–2640. <lb/>5 Dowlati A, Haaga J, Remick SC et al. Sequential tumor biopsies in early <lb/>phase clinical trials of anticancer agents for pharmacodynamic evaluation. <lb/>Clin Cancer Res 2001;7:2971–2976. <lb/>6 West J, Card TR. Reduced mortality rates following elective, percutaneous <lb/>liver biopsies. Gastroenterology 2010;139:1230 –1237. <lb/>7 Stewart DJ, Whitney SN, Kurzrock R. Equipoise lost: ethics, costs, and the <lb/>regulation of cancer clinical research. J Clin Oncol 2010;28:2925–2935. <lb/>8 Helft PR, Daugherty CK. Are we taking without giving in return? The eth-<lb/>ics of research-related biopsies and the benefits of clinical trial participa-<lb/>tion. J Clin Oncol 2006;24:4793– 4795. <lb/>9 Daugherty C, Ratain MJ, Grochowski E et al. Perceptions of cancer patients <lb/>and their physicians involved in phase I trials. J Clin Oncol 1995;13:1062– <lb/>1072. <lb/>10 Nurgat ZA, Craig W, Campbell NC et al. Patient motivations surrounding <lb/>participation in phase I and phase II clinical trials of cancer chemotherapy. <lb/>Br J Cancer 2005;92:1001–1005. <lb/>11 Kodish E, Stocking C, Ratain MJ et al. Ethical issues in phase I oncology <lb/>research: a comparison of investigators and institutional review board <lb/>chairpersons. J Clin Oncol 1992;10:1810 –1816. <lb/>12 Plecha DM, Goodwin DW, Rowland DY et al. Liver biopsy: effects of bi-<lb/>opsy needle caliber on bleeding and tissue recovery. Radiology 1997;204: <lb/>101–104. <lb/>13 Jain RK, Lee JJ, Hong D et al. Phase I oncology studies: evidence that in the <lb/>era of targeted therapies patients on lower doses do not fare worse. Clin <lb/>Cancer Res 2010;16:1289 –1297. <lb/>14 Yeow KM, Su IH, Pan KT et al. Risk factors of pneumothorax and bleed-<lb/>ing:multivariate analysis of 660 CT-guided coaxial cutting needle lung bi-<lb/>opsies. Chest 2004;126:748 –754. <lb/>15 Murthy VH, Krumholz HM, Gross CP. Participation in cancer clinical tri-<lb/>als: race-, sex-, and age-based disparities. JAMA 2004;291:2720 –2726. <lb/>16 Agulnik M, Oza AM, Pond GR et al. Impact and perceptions of mandatory <lb/>tumor biopsies for correlative studies in clinical trials of novel anticancer <lb/>agents. J Clin Oncol 2006;24:4801– 4807. <lb/>17 Ranjan S, Chandra P, Prabhu S. Antidepressant-induced bruxism: need for <lb/>buspirone? Int J Neuropsychopharmacol 2006;9:485– 487. <lb/>18 Cox AC, Fallowfield LJ, Jenkins VA. Communication and informed con-<lb/>sent in phase 1 trials: a review of the literature. Support Care Cancer 2006; <lb/>14:303–309. <lb/>19 Kwak EL, Bang YJ, Camidge DR et al. Anaplastic lymphoma kinase inhi-<lb/>bition in non-small-cell lung cancer. N Engl J Med 2010;363:1693–1703. <lb/>20 Flaherty KT, Puzanov I, Kim KB et al. Inhibition of mutated, activated <lb/>BRAF in metastatic melanoma. N Engl J Med 2010;363:809 – 819. <lb/>21 Chabner BA. New results will change the paradigm for phase I trials and <lb/>drug approval. The Oncologist 2010;15:1023–1025. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>1298 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research Biopsy in Phase I Clinical Trials </note>


	</text>
</tei>
