<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Highlights <lb/>Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/>Xuyang Chang,Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux <lb/>• A novel geometry is proposed, which can buckle from an initial planar configuration into a complex 3D shape <lb/>under tensile load. More importantly, the parametrized closed-form solution of the deformed geometry is <lb/>obtained analytically. <lb/>• The mechanical analysis of the buckling and post-buckling behavior is also provided. <lb/>• This closed-form solution can be used to benchmark either a numerical simulation of buckling or a Stereo Digital <lb/>Image Correlation (Stereo-DIC) code. <lb/>Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/>Xuyang Chang a, * , Matthieu Vitse a,b and Stéphane Roux a <lb/>a Université Paris-Saclay, CentraleSupélec, ENS Paris-Saclay, CNRS, LMPS -Laboratoire de Mécanique Paris-Saclay, Avenue de <lb/>Science, Gif-sur-Yvette, 91190, , France <lb/>b SciViz, Paris, France <lb/>A R T I C L E I N F O <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>Elastic Buckling <lb/>Analytical solution <lb/>Geometrical instability <lb/>A B S T R A C T <lb/>Analytical solutions for elastic buckling and post-buckling geometries are scarce. The present <lb/>work presents such a solution for a sample geometry, initially planar, which buckles into a <lb/>complex 3D shape under tensile load. The assumptions are that the sample thickness is small, so <lb/>that flexural stiffness is low compared to in-plane strain stiffness, and hence the sample can be <lb/>considered inextensible. The initial geometry is composed of two disk angular sectors sharing <lb/>a common edge. Under tensile loading, the two radial edges of each sector tend to align so <lb/>that each half turns into two regular cone sectors. As the tensile load increases, the cone angle <lb/>progressively decreases, but the same generic form holds the sample extension all along the <lb/>tensile direction. Such a solution may be useful for validating numerical simulation tools, or <lb/>stereo-vision shape measurement procedures. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Buckling of elastic solids is a fundamental problem of high practical interest as it may limit the load-bearing <lb/>capacity of engineering structures Godoy (1999), and also because it may trigger the emergence of new shapes and <lb/>patterns in biology (from plant leaves to brain circumvolutions) Thompson (1942). <lb/>A considerable amount of work has been devoted to initially simple geometries such as plates or shells (cylinder, <lb/>sphere) where its closed-form solutions could be obtained Yamaki (1984). Buckling has also become a paradigm <lb/>for problems of non-linear complex systems. Notably, the formation of highly generic patterns such as wrinkles, <lb/>ridges, folds, or singular developable cones has been identified as a ubiquitous phenomenon with which post-buckled <lb/>thin plate geometries could be understood Ben Amar and Pomeau (1997); Chaïeb, Melo and Géminard (1998); <lb/>Cerda and Mahadevan (2003); Hamm, Roman and Melo (2004); Ouchi, Yang, Suo and Hayward (2018). Until <lb/>now, many applications of these instabilities involve surfaces that are patterned into regions with different material <lb/>properties Genzer and Groenewold (2006); Xu, Chen and Hayward (2014). Nevertheless, the geometrical nature of a <lb/>buckling instability also gives a wide range of relevance, as this instability may occur at a stage where materials are still <lb/>in their linear elastic domain, and hence, the buckled geometry is weakly dependent on the material, and the critical <lb/>load (the onset of buckling) varies in proportion to the elastic modulus. <lb/>However, despite the fact that the buckling behavior of elastic solids under load can often be anticipated, analytical <lb/>solutions are rather scarce. A notable exception is the &quot;tension-field theory&quot; which describes very thin elastic films, <lb/>which would buckle in compression when subject to a vanishing small compressive stress Reissner (1938); Stein and <lb/>Hedgepeth (1961); Mansfield (1969). This limit can be incorporated into an effective constitutive law that accounts for <lb/>this unilaterally Wang and Pipkin (1986); Steigmann (1990); Mahmood, Audoly and Roux (2018). Such a formulation <lb/>makes the problem of buckling amenable to new analytic or numerical tools. Yet, closed-form solutions are still mostly <lb/>restricted to elementary geometries. <lb/>In the present study, a particular geometry is introduced that leads to an analytic solution for buckling, and post-<lb/>buckling. It concerns thin elastic plates which exhibit a very low (vanishing) bending stiffness, so that in-plane strain <lb/>can be neglected. A notable property of the proposed geometry is that the initial state is planar, but the buckled and <lb/>post-buckled configurations are not. The full evolution of the geometry under displacement load (the onset of buckling, <lb/>and the post-buckling behavior) as well as the force-displacement relation are described analytically. <lb/></body>

			<front>⋆ This work has been supported by EikoSim, and the Ecole Normale Supérieure Paris-Saclay. <lb/> * Corresponding author <lb/>xuyang.chang@ens-paris-saclay.fr (X. Chang); stephane.roux@ens-paris-saclay.fr (.S. Roux) <lb/>https://gitlab.com/sciviz/blendic (M. Vitse) <lb/>ORCID(s): 0000-0002-8239-4714 (X. Chang); 0000-0002-4230-6396 (M. Vitse); 0000-0003-4885-6732 (.S. Roux) <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 1 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1: Geometry of the sample <lb/>The paper is organized as follows: in Section 2, the design of the initial geometry is provided along with its <lb/>progressive evolution as a function of the overall extension of the sample. In Section 3, mechanical analysis of the <lb/>buckling phenomenon is carried out over the proposed geometry to compute the tensile force as a function of the <lb/>sample extension. In Section 4, conclusions and perspectives are drawn. <lb/>2. Model <lb/>Let us consider a planar sample shown in Fig. 1 that consists of two disk sector ring sharing a common edge along <lb/>BC. The two sectors BCEA and CBFD are symmetric with respect to the midpoint between B and C. The disk radius is <lb/>denoted 1 . The midpoint along the outer circle is denoted E (resp. F) for the first (resp. second) sector. The geometry <lb/>is parametrized by the angle = ̂ = ̂ = ̂ = ̂ . <lb/>A thin elastic plate having the shape of the geometry shown in Fig. 1 is considered. In practice, to avoid stress <lb/>singularity at angular points B and C, two small circular holes centered in B and C can be cut out of the sample (for <lb/>instance, the inner circle radius can be chosen as say one-tenth of the external radius). The presence of such holes has <lb/>a negligible influence on the buckled shape solution, but limits the risk of plastification or tearing in the vicinity of <lb/>these points. &quot;Thin&quot; implies that the bending stiffness is small and in-plane stretch can be neglected. <lb/>In the following, the plate will be assumed to be in-extensible. The sample is under tensile load between points A and <lb/>D. <lb/>When &lt; ∕2, the segment AD lies inside the sample, and hence, because of inextensibility, it is not possible to stretch <lb/>this segment any further than its end-to-end length. In contrast, when &gt; ∕2, it is possible to deform the sample up <lb/>to the stage where ABCD is aligned onto a straight segment. This configuration is obviously an upper bound on the <lb/>maximum stretch that can be applied to the structure while violating inextensibility. <lb/>It is first assumed that the point-symmetry, with respect to the mid-point between B and C, is not broken in the buckled <lb/>configuration. Hence, the problem of geometrical description at each given load can be reduced to the upper section <lb/>ABCE. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2: Illustration of the deformed arc Γ (black curve). It consists of two parts AE and EC which are two arcs that <lb/>belong to the sphere centered in B, and belong to two cones whose apex is B and which are tangent to each other along <lb/>the BE line. Both cones and the sphere are drawn with transparent colors. <lb/>The arc AEC is initially located at a uniform distance to point B. Because the sample is assumed to be inextensible, <lb/>the deformed arc AEC, denoted as Γ , remains at a fixed distance from center B, i.e., it lies on the sphere of radius 1 <lb/>centered in B. Thus, the deformed (buckled) sample geometry is a conical surface whose apex is point B and ends on <lb/>the dielectrics Γ . Let us emphasize that the elastic energy of the buckled configuration can thus be inferred from the <lb/>curvature of the deformed arc Γ , and the least elastic energy corresponds to the smaller L2 norm of the arc curvature. <lb/>The arc length of Γ is 2 = 2 1 in the initial geometry, and because of inextensibility, it remains constant in the <lb/>deformed configuration. <lb/>Hence the problem reduces to finding an arc Γ along the sphere with a fixed arc length, such that its end-to-end <lb/>distance achieves a pre-defined value larger than the initial one (and obviously smaller or equal to 2 1 ) with the least <lb/>L2 norm of its curvature. <lb/>Among such curves that would minimize its curvature and elastic energy, one may consider circles whose radius can <lb/>only be smaller than 1 . However, a constant arc length 2 on such circles brings the end point closer to the starting <lb/>point and hence is not a feasible solution to the problem. Nevertheless, two such segments of two tangent circles having <lb/>the same radius allow to form a curve Γ that meets the desired objective of bringing point C closer to the symmetric <lb/>point of A with respect to B. Because the curvature remains constant, it corresponds to a minimum L2 norm of the arc <lb/>curvature and hence of the deformed plate. These simple observations provide a global and qualitative solution to the <lb/>buckling problem. To give further insight into the problem, the following gives an analytical characterization of the <lb/>deformed configuration. <lb/>2.1. First circle arc <lb/>Its length is half that of the initial Γ , hence = 1 . In the deformed configuration, its radius is , and hence the <lb/>polar angle around the cone axis is such that <lb/>= 1 . <lb/>The cone semi-angle is denoted as , and the associated stretching parameter, , reads as <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>(1) <lb/>Because the -axis is part of the cone, the cone axis is inclined at an angle from the -axis. This leads to the relation <lb/>= 1 sin( ) <lb/>(2) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>and thus <lb/>= <lb/>sin( ) <lb/>(3) <lb/>Conventionally, the axis can be oriented in the ( , ) plane, and hence its direction vector, , is written <lb/>1 = <lb/>⎛ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎜ <lb/>⎝ <lb/>sin( ) <lb/>0 <lb/>cos( ) <lb/>⎞ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎟ <lb/>⎠ <lb/>(4) <lb/>The projection of the first circle on its cone axis is the vector <lb/>1 , where = 1 cos( ) = <lb/>√ <lb/>2 <lb/>1 − 2 . Thus, choosing <lb/>the origin of the frame in B, the AE arc is parameterized with 0 ≤ ≤ , reads as <lb/>⎧ <lb/>⎪ <lb/>⎨ <lb/>⎪ <lb/>⎩ <lb/>= ( 1 ∕2) sin(2 )(1 − cos( )) <lb/>= 1 sin( ) sin( ) <lb/>= ( 1 ∕2)[(1 + cos(2 )) + (1 − cos(2 )) cos( )] <lb/>(5) <lb/>The end point E is obtained from the previous expression with = . <lb/>More compact writing of such an arc is obtained via quaternions to encode the 3D rotation. Indeed, the rotation <lb/>about the axis 1 , by an angle , is written 1 ( ) = (cos( ∕2), sin( ∕2) 1 ). Vectors in 3D, such as 1 , are 3 component <lb/>elements denoted with bold and italic fonts. Quaternions are written as 4D vectors, and denoted by bold but non-<lb/>italicised fonts. A vector 1 can be associated to the quaternion 1 = (0, 1 ) = (0, sin( ), 0, cos( )) with a null real <lb/>part (the first component of the quaternion). The rotation of the BA vector (written as a quaternion 0 = 1 (0, 0, 0, 1)), <lb/>about the axis 1 by an angle is obtained from <lb/>= 1 ( ). 0 . 1 ( ) <lb/>(6) <lb/>using the standard multiplication rules for quaternions, and where denotes the conjugate of . Using the above <lb/>presentation, the BE vector is obtained as the quaternion . <lb/>2.2. Second circle arc <lb/>The second part of the arc, is also a cone of similar semi-angle , and axis along 2 . The point E is part of this <lb/>second cone, and the two circles are tangent at this point. Thus 1 and 2 are symmetric with respect to the BE line. <lb/>The projection of 1 along the BE direction has a length 1 cos( ) 2 , and hence 1 + 2 = <lb/>cos( ) 2 . <lb/>Quaternions offer again a convenient expression for 2 as the rotation of 2 about the BE vector by an angle . <lb/>This rotation is written <lb/>= (1∕ 1 ) , and hence <lb/>2 = . 1 . <lb/>(7) <lb/>The second part of the arc, segment EC, is obtained from BE by a rotation about 2 by an angle − , for 0 ≤ ≤ . <lb/>This rotation is written 2 ( ) = (cos( ∕2), − sin( ∕2) 2 ), and the arc is described by the quaternion <lb/>= 2 ( ). . 2 ( ) <lb/>(8) <lb/>and hence vector BC is . <lb/>Now that the first half of the sample in its deformed configuration has been described as a function of the single <lb/>parameter , the second half is deduced by a mere point symmetry about the midpoint between B and C. This <lb/>completes the description of the full deformed geometry. As an illustration, 1 Figure 3 shows respectively the initial <lb/>reference geometry, the intermediary deformed configuration, the maximum deformed geometry (with a corresponding <lb/>parameter p = 1, 1.2, 1.45). Let us note that at the maximum deformed configuration (Figure 3 and Figure 4), points <lb/>A, B, C and D are all aligned with the -axis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">1 Using the provided closed-form solution, the visual rendering is achieved via the BlenDIC add-on for Blender software Vitse <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; P y D + v D B 2 6 7 h B 0 6 u G y L T n j G C p a z w = &quot; &gt; A A A C 1 H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R L x t S y 6 c V n B P q A t k k y n d W i a h M l E K L U r c e s P u N V v E v 9 A / 8 I 7 Y w o + E J 2 Q 5 M y 5 5 9 y Z e 6 8 f B y J R j v O S s 2 Z m 5 + Y X 8 o u F p e W V 1 b X i + k Y 9 i V L J e I 1 F Q S S b v p f w Q I S 8 p o Q K e D O W 3 B v 6 A W / 4 g 1 M d b 1 x z m Y g o v F C j m H e G X j 8 U P c E 8 R d R l c a 3 d k x 4 b H 7 R j M R m 7 h 5 P L Y s k p O 2 b Z P 4 G b g R K y V Y 2 K z 2 i j i w g M K Y b g C K E I B / C Q 0 N O C C w c x c R 2 M i Z O E h I l z T F A g b 0 o q T g q P 2 A F 9 + 7 R r Z W x I e 5 0 z M W 5 G p w T 0 S n L a 2 C F P R D p J W J 9 m m 3 h q M m v 2 t 9 x j k 1 P f b U R / P 8 s 1 J F b h i t i / f F P l f 3 2 6 F o U e j k 0 N g m q K D a O r Y 1 m W 1 H R F 3 9 z + V J W i D D F x G n c p L g k z 4 5 z 2 2 T a e x N S u e + u Z + K t R a l b v W a Z N 8 a Z v S Q N 2 v 4 / z J 6 j v l d 3 D 8 v 7 5 f q l y k o 0 6 j y 1 s Y 5 f m e Y Q K z l B F z c z 8 A Y 9 4 s u r W j X V r 3 X 1 I r V z m 2 c S X Z d 2 / A 7 W a l Y Q = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>5⇡ <lb/>16 <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; Y E a A k F t F s 5 l z l A 3 e C I 8 W f I o Y Z 8 o = &quot; &gt; A A A C x 3 i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k W o m 5 J I U Z d F N 7 q r Y B 9 Q i y T p t B 2 a Z E I y K Z b i w h 9 w q 3 8 m / o H + h X f G F N Q i O i H J m X P v O T P 3 X j f y e S I t 6 z V n L C w u L a / k V w t r 6 x u b W 8 X t n W Y i 0 t h j D U / 4 I m 6 7 T s J 8 H r K G 5 N J n 7 S h m T u D 6 r O W O z l W 8 N W Z x w k V 4 L S c R 6 w b O I O R 9 7 j l S U W l Z H t 4 W S 1 b F 0 s u c B 3 Y G S s h W X R R f c I M e B D y k C M A Q Q h L 2 4 S C h p w M b F i L i u p g S F x P i O s 5 w j w J p U 8 p i l O E Q O 6 L v g H a d j A 1 p r z w T r f b o F J / e m J Q m D k g j K C 8 m r E 4 z d T z V z o r 9 z X u q P d X d J v R 3 M 6 + A W I k h s X / p Z p n / 1 a l a J P o 4 1 T V w q i n S j K r O y 1 x S 3 R V 1 c / N L V Z I c I u I U 7 l E 8 J u x p 5 a z P p t Y k u n b V W 0 f H 3 3 S m Y t X e y 3 J T v K t b 0 o D t n + O c B 8 2 j i n 1 c q V 5 V S 7 W z b N R 5 7 G E f Z Z r n C W q 4 Q B 0 N 8 h 7 i E U 9 4 N i 4 N Y Y y N u 8 9 U I 5 d p d v F t G Q 8 f r l G Q Z g = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>u(t) <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; 5 3 z p y J D n Z y D w d j n 7 s 9 c T / x 7 x a N g = &quot; &gt; A A A C z H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w F R I R d S M U 3 b i S C v Y h t Z R k O q 2 h e Z F M h F K 6 9 Q f c 6 n e J f 6 B / 4 Z 1 x C m o R n Z D k z L n 3 n J l 7 r 5 c E f i Z s + 7 V g z M 0 v L C 4 V l 0 s r q 2 v r G + X N r U Y W 5 y n j d R Y H c d r y 3 I w H f s T r w h c B b y U p d 0 M v 4 E 1 v e C 7 j z X u e Z n 4 c X Y t R w j u h O 4 j 8 v s 9 c Q d R N 0 n X M U 9 O x 7 G 6 5 Y l u 2 W u Y s c D S o Q K 9 a X H 7 B L X q I w Z A j B E c E Q T i A i 4 y e N h z Y S I j r Y E x c S s h X c Y 4 J S q T N K Y t T h k v s k L 4 D 2 r U 1 G 9 F e e m Z K z e i U g N 6 U l C b 2 S B N T X k p Y n m a q e K 6 c J f u b 9 1 h 5 y r u N 6 O 9 p r 5 B Y g T t i / 9 J N M / + r k 7 U I 9 H G i a v C p p k Q x s j q m X X L V F X l z 8 0 t V g h w S 4 i T u U T w l z J R y 2 m d T a T J V u + y t q + J v K l O y c s 9 0 b o 5 3 e U s a s P N z n L O g c W A 5 R 9 b h 1 W G l e q Z H X c Q O d r F P 8 z x G F R e o o U 7 e I R 7 x h G f j 0 h D G 2 J h 8 p h o F r d n G t 2 U 8 f A B l 0 J F q &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>p 1 = 1.0 <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; g g 4 0 5 Q 4 7 n r f t r U C 2 6 Y Z U R 8 U N S t I = &quot; &gt; A A A C z H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V Z J S 1 I 1 Q d O N K K t i H 1 F K S d F q H 5 k U y E U r p 1 h 9 w q 9 8 l / o H + h X f G K a h F d E K S M + f e c 2 b u v W 7 s 8 1 R Y 1 m v O W F h c W l 7 J r x b W 1 j c 2 t 4 r b O 8 0 0 y h K P N b z I j 5 K 2 6 6 T M 5 y F r C C 5 8 1 o 4 T 5 g S u z 1 r u 6 F z G W / c s S X k U X o t x z L q B M w z 5 g H u O I O o m 7 l X M U 9 M u V 3 r F k l W 2 1 D L n g a 1 B C X r V o + I L b t F H B A 8 Z A j C E E I R 9 O E j p 6 c C G h Z i 4 L i b E J Y S 4 i j N M U S B t R l m M M h x i R / Q d 0 q 6 j 2 Z D 2 0 j N V a o 9 O 8 e l N S G n i g D Q R 5 S W E 5 W m m i m f K W b K / e U + U p 7 z b m P 6 u 9 g q I F b g j 9 i / d L P O / O l m L w A A n q g Z O N c W K k d V 5 2 i V T X Z E 3 N 7 9 U J c g h J k 7 i P s U T w p 5 S z v p s K k 2 q a p e 9 d V T 8 T W V K V u 4 9 n Z v h X d 6 S B m z / H O c 8 a F b K 9 l G 5 e l U t 1 c 7 0 q P P Y w z 4 O a Z 7 H q O E C d T T I O 8 A j n v B s X B r C m B j T z 1 Q j p z W 7 + L a M h w 9 s 9 p F t &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>p 2 = 1.2 <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; M o k M 6 B 6 h S 6 I M 1 4 2 j Z e 5 A D l D I M + Y = &quot; &gt; A A A C z n i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w F R K t 2 o 1 Q d O O y g n 1 A L S W Z T m t o X i S T Q i n F r T / g V j 9 L / A P 9 C + + M K a h F d E K S M + e e c 2 f u v U 7 k u Y k w z d e c t r C 4 t L y S X y 2 s r W 9 s b h W 3 d x p J m M a M 1 1 n o h X H L s R P u u Q G v C 1 d 4 v B X F 3 P Y d j z e d 4 a W M N 0 c 8 T t w w u B H j i H d 8 e x C 4 f Z f Z g q h 2 1 D 3 W z 3 X L K F d O u s W S a Z h q 6 f P A y k A J 2 a q F x R f c o o c Q D C l 8 c A Q Q h D 3 Y S O h p w 4 K J i L g O J s T F h F w V 5 5 i i Q N 6 U V J w U N r F D + g 5 o 1 8 7 Y g P Y y Z 6 L c j E 7 x 6 I 3 J q e O A P C H p Y s L y N F 3 F U 5 V Z s r / l n q i c 8 m 5 j + j t Z L p 9 Y g T t i / / L N l P / 1 y V o E + q i o G l y q K V K M r I 5 l W V L V F X l z / U t V g j J E x E n c o 3 h M m C n n r M + 6 8 i S q d t l b W 8 X f l F K y c s 8 y b Y p 3 e U s a s P V z n P O g c W R Y p 0 b 5 u l y q X m S j z m M P + z i k e Z 6 h i i v U U F c d f 8 Q T n r W a N t K m 2 v 2 n V M t l n l 1 8 W 9 r D B 8 c J k f E = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>p 3 = 1.485 <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; Y E a A k F t F s 5 l z l A 3 e C I 8 W f I o Y Z 8 o = &quot; &gt; A A A C x 3 i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k W o m 5 J I U Z d F N 7 q r Y B 9 Q i y T p t B 2 a Z E I y K Z b i w h 9 w q 3 8 m / o H + h X f G F N Q i O i H J m X P v O T P 3 X j f y e S I t 6 z V n L C w u L a / k V w t r 6 x u b W 8 X t n W Y i 0 t h j D U / 4 I m 6 7 T s J 8 H r K G 5 N J n 7 S h m T u D 6 r O W O z l W 8 N W Z x w k V 4 L S c R 6 w b O I O R 9 7 j l S U W l Z H t 4 W S 1 b F 0 s u c B 3 Y G S s h W X R R f c I M e B D y k C M A Q Q h L 2 4 S C h p w M b F i L i u p g S F x P i O s 5 w j w J p U 8 p i l O E Q O 6 L v g H a d j A 1 p r z w T r f b o F J / e m J Q m D k g j K C 8 m r E 4 z d T z V z o r 9 z X u q P d X d J v R 3 M 6 + A W I k h s X / p Z p n / 1 a l a J P o 4 1 T V w q i n S j K r O y 1 x S 3 R V 1 c / N L V Z I c I u I U 7 l E 8 J u x p 5 a z P p t Y k u n b V W 0 f H 3 3 S m Y t X e y 3 J T v K t b 0 o D t n + O c B 8 2 j i n 1 c q V 5 V S 7 W z b N R 5 7 G E f Z Z r n C W q 4 Q B 0 N 8 h 7 i E U 9 4 N i 4 N Y Y y N u 8 9 U I 5 d p d v F t G Q 8 f r l G Q Z g = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>u(t) <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; h r V 1 Z V U X + / C h L h M b D p q 2 x z r e c Y w = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I q i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 p e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a J z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / N R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H + t b j 0 8 = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>A <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; f p N p 0 q G J L M 9 4 5 + 3 9 c X b G f O c 7 3 8 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 6 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 8 b m K d + 5 Y J n g S X 8 l J y v q R N 4 r 5 k A e e J K p Z v y m V n Y q j l z 0 P X A P K M K u R l F 5 w j Q E S B M g R g S G G J B z C g 6 C n B x c O U u L 6 m B K X E e I 6 z n C P N d L m l M U o w y N 2 T N 8 R 7 X q G j W m v P I V W B 3 R K S G 9 G S h u H p E k o L y O s T r N 1 P N f O i v 3 N e 6 o 9 1 d 0 m 9 P e N V 0 S s x C 2 x f + l m m f / V q V o k h j j T N X C q K d W M q i 4 w L r n u i r q 5 / a U q S Q 4 p c Q o P K J 4 R D r R y 1 m d b a 4 S u X f X W 0 / E 3 n a l Y t Q 9 M b o 5 3 d U s a s P t z n P O g f V x x T y r V Z r V c q 5 t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 7 b u P U A = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>B <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; b n P Y h o G F R h 2 0 g h q b s E o M m t l h 8 / 8 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 8 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 c V 3 F O 3 c s E z y J r + Q k Z f 3 I G 8 V 8 y A N P E t W s 3 5 T K T s X R y 5 4 H r g F l m N V I S i + 4 x g A J A u S I w B B D E g 7 h Q d D T g w s H K X F 9 T I n L C H E d Z 7 j H G m l z y m K U 4 R E 7 p u + I d j 3 D x r R X n k K r A z o l p D c j p Y 1 D 0 i S U l x F W p 9 k 6 n m t n x f 7 m P d W e 6 m 4 T + v v G K y J W 4 p b Y v 3 S z z P / q V C 0 S Q 5 z p G j j V l G p G V R c Y l 1 x 3 R d 3 c / l K V J I e U O I U H F M 8 I B 1 o 5 6 7 O t N U L X r n r r 6 f i b z l S s 2 g c m N 8 e 7 u i U N 2 P 0 5 z n n Q P q 6 4 J 5 V q s 1 q u n Z t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 8 B u P U Q = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>C <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c R 3 e J 8 y u A R j G j O C N T / 0 e n 2 Y H G A k = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r K o i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / J 7 j 1 I = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>D <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; h r V 1 Z V U X + / C h L h M b D p q 2 x z r e c Y w = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I q i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 p e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a J z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / N R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H + t b j 0 8 = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>A <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; f p N p 0 q G J L M 9 4 5 + 3 9 c X b G f O c 7 3 8 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 6 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 8 b m K d + 5 Y J n g S X 8 l J y v q R N 4 r 5 k A e e J K p Z v y m V n Y q j l z 0 P X A P K M K u R l F 5 w j Q E S B M g R g S G G J B z C g 6 C n B x c O U u L 6 m B K X E e I 6 z n C P N d L m l M U o w y N 2 T N 8 R 7 X q G j W m v P I V W B 3 R K S G 9 G S h u H p E k o L y O s T r N 1 P N f O i v 3 N e 6 o 9 1 d 0 m 9 P e N V 0 S s x C 2 x f + l m m f / V q V o k h j j T N X C q K d W M q i 4 w L r n u i r q 5 / a U q S Q 4 p c Q o P K J 4 R D r R y 1 m d b a 4 S u X f X W 0 / E 3 n a l Y t Q 9 M b o 5 3 d U s a s P t z n P O g f V x x T y r V Z r V c q 5 t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 7 b u P U A = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>B <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; b n P Y h o G F R h 2 0 g h q b s E o M m t l h 8 / 8 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 8 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 c V 3 F O 3 c s E z y J r + Q k Z f 3 I G 8 V 8 y A N P E t W s 3 5 T K T s X R y 5 4 H r g F l m N V I S i + 4 x g A J A u S I w B B D E g 7 h Q d D T g w s H K X F 9 T I n L C H E d Z 7 j H G m l z y m K U 4 R E 7 p u + I d j 3 D x r R X n k K r A z o l p D c j p Y 1 D 0 i S U l x F W p 9 k 6 n m t n x f 7 m P d W e 6 m 4 T + v v G K y J W 4 p b Y v 3 S z z P / q V C 0 S Q 5 z p G j j V l G p G V R c Y l 1 x 3 R d 3 c / l K V J I e U O I U H F M 8 I B 1 o 5 6 7 O t N U L X r n r r 6 f i b z l S s 2 g c m N 8 e 7 u i U N 2 P 0 5 z n n Q P q 6 4 J 5 V q s 1 q u n Z t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 8 B u P U Q = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>C <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c R 3 e J 8 y u A R j G j O C N T / 0 e n 2 Y H G A k = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r K o i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / J 7 j 1 I = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>D <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; g J + L H Q I o 1 U V B j P Z z C v O r N Z U S u e M = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I o i s s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / T b j 1 M = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>E <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c t b m L E m Y D U 7 B q Z V I c D 7 i X Z U B Z S 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 0 W h u G z B P q A W S d J p D Z 0 8 y E y E U v Q H 3 O q 3 i X + g f + G d c Q p q E Z 2 Q 5 M y 5 9 5 y Z e 6 + f 8 l B I x 3 k t W A u L S 8 s r x d W 1 9 Y 3 N r e 3 S z m 5 b J H k W s F a Q 8 C T r + p 5 g P I x Z S 4 a S s 2 6 a M S / y O e v 4 4 w s V 7 9 y x T I R J f C U n K e t H 3 i g O h 2 H g S a K a 9 Z t S 2 a k 4 e t n z w D W g D L M a S e k F 1 x g g Q Y A c E R h i S M I c H g Q 9 P b h w k B L X x 5 S 4 j F C o 4 w z 3 W C N t T l m M M j x i x / Q d 0 a 5 n 2 J j 2 y l N o d U C n c H o z U t o 4 J E 1 C e R l h d Z q t 4 7 l 2 V u x v 3 l P t q e 4 2 o b 9 v v C J i J W 6 J / U s 3 y / y v T t U i M c S Z r i G k m l L N q O o C 4 5 L r r q i b 2 1 + q k u S Q E q f w g O I Z 4 U A r Z 3 2 2 t U b o 2 l V v P R 1 / 0 5 m K V f v A 5 O Z 4 V 7 e k A b s / x z k P 2 s c V 9 6 R S b V b L t X M z 6 i L 2 c Y A j m u c p a r h E A y 3 t / Y g n P F t 1 i 1 v C y j 9 T r Y L R 7 O H b s h 4 + A P c 7 j 1 Q = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>F <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; g J + L H Q I o 1 U V B j P Z z C v O r N Z U S u e M = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I o i s s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / T b j 1 M = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>E <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c t b m L E m Y D U 7 B q Z V I c D 7 i X Z U B Z S 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 0 W h u G z B P q A W S d J p D Z 0 8 y E y E U v Q H 3 O q 3 i X + g f + G d c Q p q E Z 2 Q 5 M y 5 9 5 y Z e 6 + f 8 l B I x 3 k t W A u L S 8 s r x d W 1 9 Y 3 N r e 3 S z m 5 b J H k W s F a Q 8 C T r + p 5 g P I x Z S 4 a S s 2 6 a M S / y O e v 4 4 w s V 7 9 y x T I R J f C U n K e t H 3 i g O h 2 H g S a K a 9 Z t S 2 a k 4 e t n z w D W g D L M a S e k F 1 x g g Q Y A c E R h i S M I c H g Q 9 P b h w k B L X x 5 S 4 j F C o 4 w z 3 W C N t T l m M M j x i x / Q d 0 a 5 n 2 J j 2 y l N o d U C n c H o z U t o 4 J E 1 C e R l h d Z q t 4 7 l 2 V u x v 3 l P t q e 4 2 o b 9 v v C J i J W 6 J / U s 3 y / y v T t U i M c S Z r i G k m l L N q O o C 4 5 L r r q i b 2 1 + q k u S Q E q f w g O I Z 4 U A r Z 3 2 2 t U b o 2 l V v P R 1 / 0 5 m K V f v A 5 O Z 4 V 7 e k A b s / x z k P 2 s c V 9 6 R S b V b L t X M z 6 i L 2 c Y A j m u c p a r h E A y 3 t / Y g n P F t 1 i 1 v C y j 9 T r Y L R 7 O H b s h 4 + A P c 7 j 1 Q = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>F <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; h r V 1 Z V U X + / C h L h M b D p q 2 x z r e c Y w = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I q i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 p e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a J z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / N R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H + t b j 0 8 = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>A <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; f p N p 0 q G J L M 9 4 5 + 3 9 c X b G f O c 7 3 8 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 6 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 8 b m K d + 5 Y J n g S X 8 l J y v q R N 4 r 5 k A e e J K p Z v y m V n Y q j l z 0 P X A P K M K u R l F 5 w j Q E S B M g R g S G G J B z C g 6 C n B x c O U u L 6 m B K X E e I 6 z n C P N d L m l M U o w y N 2 T N 8 R 7 X q G j W m v P I V W B 3 R K S G 9 G S h u H p E k o L y O s T r N 1 P N f O i v 3 N e 6 o 9 1 d 0 m 9 P e N V 0 S s x C 2 x f + l m m f / V q V o k h j j T N X C q K d W M q i 4 w L r n u i r q 5 / a U q S Q 4 p c Q o P K J 4 R D r R y 1 m d b a 4 S u X f X W 0 / E 3 n a l Y t Q 9 M b o 5 3 d U s a s P t z n P O g f V x x T y r V Z r V c q 5 t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 7 b u P U A = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>B <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; g J + L H Q I o 1 U V B j P Z z C v O r N Z U S u e M = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r I o i s s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / T b j 1 M = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>E <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c t b m L E m Y D U 7 B q Z V I c D 7 i X Z U B Z S 0 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 0 W h u G z B P q A W S d J p D Z 0 8 y E y E U v Q H 3 O q 3 i X + g f + G d c Q p q E Z 2 Q 5 M y 5 9 5 y Z e 6 + f 8 l B I x 3 k t W A u L S 8 s r x d W 1 9 Y 3 N r e 3 S z m 5 b J H k W s F a Q 8 C T r + p 5 g P I x Z S 4 a S s 2 6 a M S / y O e v 4 4 w s V 7 9 y x T I R J f C U n K e t H 3 i g O h 2 H g S a K a 9 Z t S 2 a k 4 e t n z w D W g D L M a S e k F 1 x g g Q Y A c E R h i S M I c H g Q 9 P b h w k B L X x 5 S 4 j F C o 4 w z 3 W C N t T l m M M j x i x / Q d 0 a 5 n 2 J j 2 y l N o d U C n c H o z U t o 4 J E 1 C e R l h d Z q t 4 7 l 2 V u x v 3 l P t q e 4 2 o b 9 v v C J i J W 6 J / U s 3 y / y v T t U i M c S Z r i G k m l L N q O o C 4 5 L r r q i b 2 1 + q k u S Q E q f w g O I Z 4 U A r Z 3 2 2 t U b o 2 l V v P R 1 / 0 5 m K V f v A 5 O Z 4 V 7 e k A b s / x z k P 2 s c V 9 6 R S b V b L t X M z 6 i L 2 c Y A j m u c p a r h E A y 3 t / Y g n P F t 1 i 1 v C y j 9 T r Y L R 7 O H b s h 4 + A P c 7 j 1 Q = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>F <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; b n P Y h o G F R h 2 0 g h q b s E o M m t l h 8 / 8 = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r / q u u n Q T L I K r k k h R l 8 W C u G z B P q A W S d J p H Z o X m Y l Q i v 6 A W / 0 2 8 Q / 0 L 7 w z T k E t o h O S n D n 3 n j N z 7 / X T k A v p O K 8 F a 2 F x a X m l u L q 2 v r G 5 t V 3 a 2 W 2 L J M 8 C 1 g q S M M m 6 v i d Y y G P W k l y G r J t m z I v 8 k H X 8 c V 3 F O 3 c s E z y J r + Q k Z f 3 I G 8 V 8 y A N P E t W s 3 5 T K T s X R y 5 4 H r g F l m N V I S i + 4 x g A J A u S I w B B D E g 7 h Q d D T g w s H K X F 9 T I n L C H E d Z 7 j H G m l z y m K U 4 R E 7 p u + I d j 3 D x r R X n k K r A z o l p D c j p Y 1 D 0 i S U l x F W p 9 k 6 n m t n x f 7 m P d W e 6 m 4 T + v v G K y J W 4 p b Y v 3 S z z P / q V C 0 S Q 5 z p G j j V l G p G V R c Y l 1 x 3 R d 3 c / l K V J I e U O I U H F M 8 I B 1 o 5 6 7 O t N U L X r n r r 6 f i b z l S s 2 g c m N 8 e 7 u i U N 2 P 0 5 z n n Q P q 6 4 J 5 V q s 1 q u n Z t R F 7 G P A x z R P E 9 R w y U a a G n v R z z h 2 b q w Q k t Y + W e q V T C a P X x b 1 s M H 8 B u P U Q = = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>C <lb/>&lt; l a t e x i t s h a 1 _ b a s e 6 4 = &quot; c R 3 e J 8 y u A R j G j O C N T / 0 e n 2 Y H G A k = &quot; &gt; A A A C x H i c j V H L S s N A F D 2 N r 1 p f V Z d u g k V w V R I p 6 r K o i M s W b C v U I k k 6 r U M n D z I T o R T 9 A b f 6 b e I f 6 F 9 4 Z 0 x B L a I T k p w 5 9 5 4 z c + / 1 E 8 G l c p z X g j U 3 v 7 C 4 V F w u r a y u r W + U N 7 f a M s 7 S g L W C W M T p l e 9 J J n j E W o o r w a 6 S l H m h L 1 j H H 5 3 q e O e O p Z L H 0 a U a J 6 w X e s O I D 3 j g K a K a Z z f l i l N 1 z L J n g Z u D C v L V i M s v u E Y f M Q J k C M E Q Q R E W 8 C D p 6 c K F g 4 S 4 H i b E p Y S 4 i T P c o 0 T a j L I Y Z X j E j u g 7 p F 0 3 Z y P a a 0 9 p 1 A G d I u h N S W l j j z Q x 5 a W E 9 W m 2 i W f G W b O / e U + M p 7 7 b m P 5 + 7 h U S q 3 B L 7 F + 6 a e Z / d b o W h Q G O T Q 2 c a k o M o 6 s L c p f M d E X f 3 P 5 S l S K H h D i N + x R P C Q d G O e 2 z b T T S 1 K 5 7 6 5 n 4 m 8 n U r N 4 H e W 6 G d 3 1 L G r D 7 c 5 y z o H 1 Q d Q + r t W a t U j / J R 1 3 E D n a x T / M 8 Q h 0 X a K B l v B / x h G f r 3 B K W t L L P V K u Q a 7 b x b V k P H / J 7 j 1 I = &lt; / l a t e x i t &gt; <lb/>D <lb/>Figure 3: Initial configuration ( = 1), intermediary deformation ( = 1.2) and maximum stretch ( = 1.485). The <lb/>has been chosen to be 5 ∕8. <lb/>Figure 4: Another point of view of the maximum stretch configuration ( = 1.485). The angle has been chosen to be <lb/>5 ∕8. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>3. Mechanical analysis <lb/>The above analysis of the deformed state has been reduced to a mere geometrical problem, and no mechanical <lb/>information has been obtained so far. <lb/>Let us first note that the parameterization with was convenient but difficult to assess experimentally. However, the <lb/>above description provides easy access to the extension Δ as a function of . It can also be noted that the maximum <lb/>stretch displacement, Δ <lb/>is easily obtained from the initial length | <lb/>| and the maximum one equal to 3 1 , so that <lb/>the dimensionless ratio Δ ∕Δ <lb/>will be used in the following to pair with the aforementioned stretching parameter <lb/>. Figure 5a shows the correspondence between and the elongation during the tensile test, Δ ∕Δ <lb/>, scaled by the <lb/>maximum stretch. <lb/>In terms of elastic energy, the deformed surface consists of four portions of cones with the same semi-angle. <lb/>The curvature of the cone is proportional to cot( )∕ , where designates the distance to either B or C, for the upper <lb/>(respectively lower) half of the specimen. The singularity in B or C is susceptible to create either damage or plastic <lb/>yielding, and hence in practice, drilling a small hole in B and in C will avoid these difficulties and still preserve the <lb/>validity of the solution. Along the outer edge, the curvature = cot( )∕ is spatially uniform. Its variation with the <lb/>relative extension in shown in Figure 5b. It allows to construct the total elastic energy as proportionnal to 2 , as shown <lb/>in Figure 6a. It is to be observed that for a small stretch of the specimen, the curvature behaves as (Δ ) 1∕2 , and <lb/>hence the elastic energy grows linearly with Δ . Its derivative provides a finite force at vanishing stretch which can be <lb/>interpreted as a buckling force, , below which the sample remains non-deformed. At maximum stretch, the tensile <lb/>force diverges, ∝ (Δ <lb/>− Δ ) −1∕2 . The tensile force versus stretch is shown in Figure 6b. <lb/>(a) Stretching parameter, = 2 ∕ <lb/>(b) Curvature <lb/>Figure 5: (a) Stretching parameter, = 2 ∕ , and (b) curvature, , are shown as a function of the dimensionless ratio <lb/>Δ ∕Δ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<body>(a) Total elastic energy, <lb/>(b) Tensile force scaled by critical buckling force, ∕ <lb/>Figure 6: (a) Elastic energy and (b) relative tensile force versus scaled elongation <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>This paper has introduced a simple sample planar geometry that buckles into a non-trivial shape in three dimensions <lb/>and whose evolution under load can be followed analytically up to a maximum elongation. <lb/>Although the problem was addressed in the framework of linear elasticity, it is worth emphasizing that the deformed <lb/>geometry would be identical for a wide category of hyper-elastic laws. Indeed, in the deformed geometry all elementary <lb/>angular sectors (centered either in B or in C) are subjected to the very same deformation as the segment of the cone <lb/>(with an identical cone semi-angle). Therefore whatever the hyper-elastic law, the elastic energy stored in such sectors <lb/>is identical. Thus, the relevance of the proposed deformed geometry for a more general constitutive law resumes to its <lb/>stability, or essentially the convexity of the hyper-elastic law. <lb/>One may fear that the high (singular) strains expected at the apex of the cones in the deformed geometry (close <lb/>to either B or C), may induce plastic strain, or even tearing. This is indeed very likely to occur. However, in practice, <lb/>cutting out two small disks centered in B and C from the sample would limit the most intense stresses, and still preserve <lb/>the validity of the solution. <lb/>Thus, the obtained solution appears to be quite robust, even with respect to the constitutive law of the material. <lb/>As such, it constitutes an interesting benchmark solution for numerical simulations of buckling, challenging large 3D <lb/>displacements, as well as stereo-vision systems for shape characterization and displacement measurements Strecha, <lb/>von Hansen, Van Gool, Fua and Thoennessen (2008); Keller, Enzweiler and Gavrila (2011); Hu and Mordohai (2012). <lb/>For the latter case, an experimental study is underway and will be reported in a forthcoming study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Buckling of a double sector thin elastic plate: Analytical solution <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">CRediT authorship contribution statement <lb/>Xuyang Chang: Conceptualization of this study, Visualization,Writing -Original draft preparation. Matthieu <lb/>Vitse: Software, Visualization. Stéphane Roux: Conceptualization of this study, Methodology, Writing -Original <lb/>draft preparation, Supervision. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Ben Amar, M., Pomeau, Y., 1997. Crumpled paper. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. Series A: Mathematical, Physical and Engineering <lb/>Sciences 453, 729-755. <lb/>Cerda, E., Mahadevan, L., 2003. Geometry and physics of wrinkling. Physical review letters 90, 074302. <lb/>Chaïeb, S., Melo, F., Géminard, J.C., 1998. Experimental study of developable cones. Physical review letters 80, 2354. <lb/>Genzer, J., Groenewold, J., 2006. Soft matter with hard skin: From skin wrinkles to templating and material characterization. Soft Matter 2, 310-. <lb/>doi:10.1039/B516741H. <lb/>Godoy, L.A., 1999. Theory of elastic stability: analysis and sensitivity. CRC Press. <lb/>Hamm, E., Roman, B., Melo, F., 2004. Dynamics of developable cones under shear. Physical Review E 70, 026607. <lb/>Hu, X., Mordohai, P., 2012. A quantitative evaluation of confidence measures for stereo vision. IEEE Transactions on Pattern Analysis and Machine <lb/>Intelligence 34, 2121-2133. doi:10.1109/TPAMI.2012.46. <lb/>Keller, C.G., Enzweiler, M., Gavrila, D.M., 2011. A new benchmark for stereo-based pedestrian detection, in: 2011 IEEE Intelligent Vehicles <lb/>Symposium (IV), pp. 691-696. doi:10.1109/IVS.2011.5940480. <lb/>Mahmood, O., Audoly, B., Roux, S., 2018. Cracks in tension-field elastic sheets. Physical review letters 121, 144301. <lb/>Mansfield, E., 1969. Tension field theory, a new approach which shows its duality with inextensional theory, in: Applied Mechanics. Springer, pp. <lb/>305-320. <lb/>Ouchi, T., Yang, J., Suo, Z., Hayward, R.C., 2018. Effects of stiff film pattern geometry on surface buckling instabilities of elastic bilayers. ACS <lb/>Applied Materials &amp; Interfaces 10, 23406-23413. URL: https://doi.org/10.1021/acsami.8b04916, doi:10.1021/acsami.8b04916, <lb/>arXiv:https://doi.org/10.1021/acsami.8b04916. pMID: 29956909. <lb/>Reissner, E., 1938. On tension field theory. Proc. of the 5th Int. Congr. for Applied Mechanics Harvard Univ. &amp; MIT , 88-92. <lb/>Steigmann, D.J., 1990. Tension-field theory. Proceedings of the Royal Society of London. A. Mathematical and Physical Sciences 429, 141-173. <lb/>Stein, M., Hedgepeth, J.M., 1961. Analysis of partly wrinkled membranes. National Aeronautics and Space Administration. <lb/>Strecha, C., von Hansen, W., Van Gool, L., Fua, P., Thoennessen, U., 2008. On benchmarking camera calibration and multi-view stereo for high <lb/>resolution imagery, in: 2008 IEEE Conference on Computer Vision and Pattern Recognition, pp. 1-8. doi:10.1109/CVPR.2008.4587706. <lb/>Thompson, D.W., 1942. On growth and form. volume 2. Cambridge university press Cambridge. <lb/>Vitse, M., . Blendic add-on for blender. Available at https://gitlab.com/sciviz/blendic. <lb/>Wang, W.B., Pipkin, A., 1986. Inextensible networks with bending stiffness. The Quarterly Journal of Mechanics and Applied Mathematics 39, <lb/>343-359. <lb/>Xu, B., Chen, D., Hayward, R.C., 2014. Mechanically gated electrical switches by creasing of patterned metal/elastomer bilayer films. Advanced <lb/>Materials 26, 4381-4385. URL: https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/abs/10.1002/adma.201400992, doi:https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1002/adma.201400992, arXiv:https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/pdf/10.1002/adma.201400992. <lb/>Yamaki, N., 1984. Elastic stability of circular cylindrical shells. Elsevier. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Xuyang Chang, Matthieu Vitse, Stéphane Roux: Preprint submitted to Elsevier <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 8 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
