<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Language and iconic gesture use in procedural discourse by speakers <lb/>with aphasia <lb/>Madeleine Pritchard a *, Lucy Dipper a , Gary Morgan a and Naomi Cocks b <lb/>a Division of Language and Communication Science, City University, London, UK; b School of <lb/>Psychology and Speech Pathology, Curtin University, Perth, Australia <lb/>(Received 16 April 2014; accepted 28 November 2014) <lb/>Background: Conveying instructions is an everyday use of language, and gestures are <lb/>likely to be a key feature of this. Although co-speech iconic gestures are tightly <lb/>integrated with language, and people with aphasia (PWA) produce procedural dis-<lb/>courses impaired at a linguistic level, no previous studies have investigated how PWA <lb/>use co-speech iconic gestures in these contexts. <lb/>Aims: This study investigated how PWA communicated meaning using gesture and <lb/>language in procedural discourses, compared with neurologically healthy people <lb/>(NHP). We aimed to identify the relative relationship of gesture and speech, in the <lb/>context of impaired language, both overall and in individual events. <lb/>Methods &amp; Procedures: Twenty-nine PWA and 29 NHP produced two procedural <lb/>discourses. The structure and semantic content of language of the whole discourses were <lb/>analysed through predicate argument structure and spatial motor terms, and gestures were <lb/>analysed for frequency and semantic form. Gesture and language were analysed in two key <lb/>events, to determine the relative information presented in each modality. <lb/>Outcomes &amp; Results: PWA and NHP used similar frequencies and forms of gestures, <lb/>although PWA used syntactically simpler language and fewer spatial words. This <lb/>meant, overall, relatively more information was present in PWA gesture. This finding <lb/>was also reflected in the key events, where PWA used gestures conveying rich <lb/>semantic information alongside semantically impoverished language more often than <lb/>NHP. <lb/>Conclusions: PWA gestures, containing semantic information omitted from the con-<lb/>current speech, may help listeners with meaning when language is impaired. This <lb/>finding indicates gesture should be included in clinical assessments of meaning-<lb/>making. <lb/>Keywords: aphasia; iconic gesture; procedural discourse; discourse; semantic weight <lb/></front>

			<body>When communicating, speakers present information to construct meaning (Halliday, 2004), <lb/>which involves spoken language but which is also likely to incorporate additional modalities, <lb/>including co-speech gesture. Moreover, everyday communication includes a range of differ-<lb/>ent discourses (Davidson, Worrall, &amp; Hickson, 2003), and the relative informational load <lb/>carried by spoken language and gesture will vary according to the genre of discourse being <lb/>produced (Cocks, Hird, &amp; Kirsner, 2007; Ulatowska, North, &amp; Macaluso-Haynes, 1981). In <lb/>evaluating the communication abilities of people with aphasia (PWA), it is therefore essential <lb/>to understand how gesture and spoken language share the communicative burden in different <lb/>discourse types. In this study, the focus is on procedural discourse. <lb/></body>

			<front>*Corresponding author. Email: madeleine.pritchard.1@city.ac.uk <lb/>Aphasiology, 2015 <lb/>Vol. 29, No. 7, 826-844, http://dx.doi.org/10.1080/02687038.2014.993912 <lb/>© 2014 The Author(s). Published by Taylor &amp; Francis. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives <lb/>License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/), which permits non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduc-<lb/>tion in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited, and is not altered, transformed, or built upon in any way. <lb/></front>

			<body>Variation in language form and content can be grammatical, lexical, and/or semantic <lb/>(Cocks, Dipper, Middleton, &amp; Morgan, 2011; Dipper, Cocks, Rowe, &amp; Morgan, 2011; <lb/>Kendon, 2004; Kita, 2000; Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003; Pritchard, Cocks, &amp; Dipper, 2013). For <lb/>example, in a study completed by Kita and Özyürek (2003), the shape of speakers&apos; gesture <lb/>was affected by their lexical choices of the verbs go, fly, or swing. Semantic differences <lb/>between topics are also likely to affect gesture: in a discourse involving a large amount of <lb/>spatial information, a large amount of spatial and/or motor meaning can be expected in <lb/>gesture (Hostetter, Alibali, &amp; Kita, 2007). <lb/>Aphasia and discourse <lb/>Evidence from naturalistic observation of older adults indicates that language to &quot;inform <lb/>and explain&quot; accounts for 12.3% of total communicative activity, making it one of the <lb/>most frequent everyday uses of language (Davidson et al., 2003). Giving instructions is <lb/>likely to be particularly important in contexts where an individual is unable to complete a <lb/>task themselves, such as adults who have difficulties completing activities of daily living <lb/>independently. For example, a speaker with mobility difficulties may instruct a support <lb/>worker how they like their tea made, or give idiosyncratic instructions for how to operate <lb/>their washing machine. Despite this, very limited research has explored how speakers <lb/>communicate when informing and explaining. <lb/>Procedural discourse is one example of language to inform and explain and was the <lb/>focus of the current study. These discourses are goal-orientated monologues, where a <lb/>speaker gives instructions on completing a procedure. Previous research has asked speak-<lb/>ers to describe how to make scrambled eggs, shop in a supermarket, change the wheel of a <lb/>car, and wrap a box in paper for a present (Brady, Armstrong, &amp; Mackenzie, 2006; Cocks <lb/>et al., 2007; Nicholas &amp; Brookshire, 1995; Shadden, Burnette, Eikenberry, &amp; Dibrezzo, <lb/>1991; Ulatowska, Weiss Doyel, Freedmam Stern, Macaluso-Haynes, &amp; North, 1983; <lb/>Ulatowska et al., 1981). Procedural tasks require a speaker to identify the main steps in <lb/>a process and communicate them clearly, which will involve spoken language as well as <lb/>additional modalities, especially gesture. Gesture may play a larger role in conveying <lb/>meaning when language is impaired, such as in adults with aphasia following stroke. <lb/>The research completed to date on procedural discourses indicates that they have <lb/>specific attributes, including structurally simpler language and particular grammatical <lb/>constructions, and that they contain more co-speech iconic gestures than other genres. <lb/>In comparison with fictional narratives, the procedural discourses produced by neurolo-<lb/>gically healthy people (NHP) tend to contain fewer t-units (defined as a clause plus any <lb/>dependent or relative clauses); contain less complex language overall; and contain fewer <lb/>subordinate clauses, which indicates an overall reduction in linguistic complexity <lb/>(Shadden et al., 1991; Ulatowska et al., 1981). <lb/>PWA use structurally less complex language than NHP consistently across a range of <lb/>genres, measured through sentence structures, predicate argument structures (PASs), t-units, <lb/>and clauses per t-unit (Berndt, Haendiges, Mitchum, &amp; Sandson, 1997; Cruice, Pritchard, &amp; <lb/>Dipper, 2014; Ulatowska et al., 1981, 1983; Webster, Franklin, &amp; Howard, 2007). This <lb/>reduction in complexity by PWA in comparison to NHP has also been shown to differ at a <lb/>single word and semantic level, which is likely to affect procedural discourse. First, for <lb/>example, PWA use fewer Correct Information Units (defined as any single word, intelligible, <lb/>informative, and relevant in context) in discourse than NHP (Nicholas &amp; Brookshire, 1993). <lb/>Second, PWA also use fewer types and tokens of spatial language in spatial tasks than NHP <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>827 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Johnson, Cocks, &amp; Dipper, 2013). Finally, speakers with aphasia and verb production deficits <lb/>also use verbs differently to speakers without verb production deficits, using a high level of <lb/>semantically &quot;light&quot; verbs containing little semantic information, such as come, go, make, <lb/>take, get, give, do, have, be, and put (Berndt et al., 1997). Overall, these findings create a <lb/>picture of PWA conveying less information in language, in a context where spoken language <lb/>may already be structurally less complex. This means that additional communicative mod-<lb/>alities are likely to become more important, raising questions about the role of gesture in such <lb/>discourses, and how aphasia affects this. <lb/>Gesture production <lb/>What do we mean when we talk about gesture, and why might it be affected by language <lb/>impairment? Iconic gestures are not formalised, occur alongside spoken language, and <lb/>reflect the semantic content of that language (Kendon, 2004; McNeill, 2000). The exact <lb/>nature of the relationship between speech and gesture is the subject of theoretical debate, <lb/>both in terms of where gesture and language interact and in terms of its function. <lb/>The Sketch Model (de Ruiter, 2000) asserts that gesture stems from conceptual <lb/>imagery in working memory. The Growth Point Hypothesis (McNeill, &amp; Duncan, 2000) <lb/>describes gesture and language arising at a common semantic level, and the Interface <lb/>Hypothesis (Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003) describes gesture interacting with spoken language <lb/>during lexical and clausal packaging. Finally, the Lexical Retrieval hypothesis describes <lb/>gesture in fluent speech arising at a conceptual level, but also being prompted by lexical <lb/>retrieval failure, which then results in visualisation in working memory that supports <lb/>lexical access (Krauss, Chen, &amp; Gottesman, 2000). <lb/>Consequently, each of these models can be used to explain why speakers with aphasia <lb/>might gesture more: for communicative reasons (de Ruiter, 2000; Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003; <lb/>McNeill &amp; Duncan, 2000), or to facilitate lexical access (Krauss et al., 2000). Moreover, <lb/>those models in which gesture serves a communicative role (de Ruiter, 2000; Kita &amp; <lb/>Özyürek, 2003; McNeill &amp; Duncan, 2000) can also explain how gesture and spoken <lb/>language together share the communicative burden in aphasia where, as well as the <lb/>prelinguistic plan and constraints on lexical and clausal packaging, the two modalities <lb/>must also negotiate spoken language production difficulties. <lb/>Gesture and spatial discourse <lb/>Speakers with no neurological impairments produce more gesture within procedural <lb/>discourse (Cocks et al., 2007; Feyereisen &amp; Havard, 1999), a finding that is likely to be <lb/>due to the spatial motor properties of the discourse. This gesture is likely to have a <lb/>communicative role, whether or not this is the speaker&apos;s intention, because listeners <lb/>comprehend spatial relationships more accurately when speakers gesture. Listeners&apos; <lb/>comprehension is particularly aided when the information is difficult to code in language <lb/>or relates to the relative position and size of objects (Beattie &amp; Shovelton, 1999; Graham <lb/>&amp; Argyle, 1975). There is also some evidence of a trade-off between gesture and <lb/>language: speakers who gesture spontaneously when describing spatial configurations <lb/>omit spatial information from their language, whilst those who don&apos;t gesture do not <lb/>(Melinger &amp; Levelt, 2004). These findings are compatible with proposals by McNeill <lb/>and Duncan (2000), and by de Ruiter (2000), that gesture and language interact, and that <lb/>spatial information can be packaged relatively efficiently in a gestural format. <lb/></body>

			<page>828 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Gesture and aphasia <lb/>Although no research to date has focused specifically on aphasia, gesture, and procedural <lb/>discourse, a body of research does outline how PWA use gesture in other discourses. It is <lb/>a well-established finding that PWA use more gesture in discourse than NHP (Carlomagno <lb/>&amp; Cristilli, 2006; Cicone, Wapner, Foldi, Zurif, &amp; Gardner, 1979; Feyereisen, 1983; <lb/>Hadar, Burstein, Krauss, &amp; Soroker, 1998; Herrmann, Reichle, Lucius-Hoene, <lb/>Wallesche, &amp; Johannsen-Horbache, 1988; Lanyon &amp; Rose, 2009; Orgassa, 2005). <lb/>However, frequency data are not clinically informative, as it does not tell us how a <lb/>speaker uses their gesture, nor how it contributes to their discourse. <lb/>A speaker&apos;s language profile is likely to affect their gesture, with speakers with less <lb/>impaired language producing gesture with more content. Mol, Krahmer, and van de <lb/>Sandt-Koenderman (2013) found that of 26 speakers with aphasia, those with mild <lb/>aphasia produced co-speech gestures that were more comprehensible than those with <lb/>severe aphasia. This indicates that gesture mirrors language, rather than compensates for <lb/>it. In contrast, other studies show that speakers with aphasia produce gestures that are <lb/>semantically similar to NHP (Carlomagno &amp; Cristilli, 2006) and gestures that differ in <lb/>content from speech (Dipper et al., 2011; Hogrefe, Ziegler, Wiesmayer, Weidinger, &amp; <lb/>Goldenberg, 2013), suggesting that the content of speech and gesture can depict different <lb/>information. <lb/>However, although gesture and language diverge, there is evidence they are not comple-<lb/>tely separate, and that speakers&apos; language profile affects the form and content of gesture. <lb/>Hogrefe, Ziegler, Weidinger, and Goldenberg (2012) found that speakers with severe aphasia <lb/>and good semantics produced a wider range of handshapes, and Cocks, Dipper, Pritchard, and <lb/>Morgan (2013) found that speakers with aphasia and good non-verbal semantic knowledge <lb/>produced gestures containing a high proportion of semantically rich manner information, <lb/>describing how something moves. Finally, PWA with good semantics also produce additional <lb/>gestures, linked to the lexical target, when experiencing word finding difficulty for objects <lb/>(Cocks et al., 2011, 2013; Pritchard et al., 2013). These studies indicate that the ability to <lb/>convey semantic information in gesture relies upon underlying retained semantic skills. <lb/>Even if speakers&apos; &quot;semantically dense&quot; gestures are not produced with purposely <lb/>communicative intent, as suggested by some models (Hadar et al., 1998), they are likely <lb/>to serve a pragmatic function, allowing a listener to gather additional meaning when a <lb/>speaker&apos;s language is impaired. This means that meaningful gestures have an important <lb/>role in contextual communication, regardless of the purpose they serve for the speaker: a <lb/>gesture being intended communicatively and being understood communicatively are two <lb/>separate entities (de Ruiter, 2000). Due to the clear potential for a listener gathering <lb/>meaning from both speech and gesture, there is likely to be considerable value in <lb/>considering the relative roles of speech and gesture in clinical language assessment, in <lb/>order that speakers&apos; contextual communication skills are acknowledged. <lb/>The current study <lb/>Although procedural discourse is important in daily interaction, it is not yet known how <lb/>PWA use gesture and language such discourses. The current study aimed to assess how <lb/>speakers present meaning in speech and gesture, by comparing the overall patterns of <lb/>spontaneous iconic gesture and language used by PWA and NHP in two procedural <lb/>discourses, and in two events within the discourses. Hypotheses were that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>829 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hypothesis 1. PWA would produce syntactically and semantically impoverished lan-<lb/>guage by comparison to NHP, in line with the findings of previous <lb/>research (Berndt et al., 1997; Cruice et al., 2014; Ulatowska et al., <lb/>1981, 1983; Webster et al., 2007); <lb/>Hypothesis 2. PWA would produce more gestures than NHP (Carlomagno &amp; Cristilli, <lb/>2006; Cicone et al., 1979; Feyereisen, 1983; Hadar et al., 1998; <lb/>Herrmann et al., 1988; Lanyon &amp; Rose, 2009; Orgassa, 2005); <lb/>Hypothesis 3. PWA gestures would contain information omitted from the concurrent <lb/>speech, in line with theoretical models, and previous research (de <lb/>Ruiter, 2000; Dipper et al., 2011; McNeill &amp; Duncan, 2000; Melinger <lb/>&amp; Levelt, 2004). <lb/>Method <lb/>Participants <lb/>Twenty-nine PWA (12 female, 17 male) and 29 NHP (18 female, 11 male) took part in the study, <lb/>recruited for a larger UK study on gesture production and aphasia (Cocks et al., 2013). <lb/>Participants lived in London and the South East of the UK. <lb/>All participants completed the Action Research Arm Test (Lyle, 1981), which tested <lb/>strength and range of movement in the upper limbs. Five PWA scored 0/57 for the right upper <lb/>limb and two scored 0/57 for the left upper limb, indicating complete paralysis of this limb. <lb/>One PWA scored 12/57 for the right upper limb and one scored 3/57 for the right upper limb, <lb/>indicating limited use. Those participants who had limited use or complete paralysis of one <lb/>upper limb had full use of the other upper limb. No participant with aphasia obtained scores <lb/>indicating limb apraxia on the Birmingham University Praxis Screen (Bickerton et al., 2006) <lb/>or Screen for Limb Apraxia (Poeck, 1986). Those participants who had limb paralysis <lb/>completed this assessment with their functional limb. These participants also used their <lb/>functional limb to gesture, with no differences in frequency or form to those participants <lb/>who had functional use of both limbs. <lb/>PWA were between 16 months and 32 years post-stroke, were recruited via community <lb/>stroke groups, and presented with a range of mild-to-moderate aphasia profiles as defined by <lb/>the Western Aphasia Battery-Revised (WAB-R) (Kertesz, 2006). The majority of speakers <lb/>presented with anomic aphasia (n = 16), followed by conduction aphasia (n = 6), Broca&apos;s <lb/>aphasia (n = 3), and Wernicke&apos;s aphasia (n = 4). No participants self-reported any difficulties <lb/>with speech such as verbal apraxia, nor was this noted during participation. All participants <lb/>spoke English as their first language and were excluded if they had any coexisting neurolo-<lb/>gical conditions or were unable to give informed consent to participate. Participants&apos; average <lb/>age was 60.9 years (SD = 14.85). Seven participants had completed tertiary level education, <lb/>21 had completed secondary school level education, and one had completed only junior level <lb/>education. Please refer to Table 1 for a summary of participants&apos; WAB scores and to Cocks <lb/>et al. (2013) for a more detailed description of participants&apos; language profiles. <lb/>NHP were matched for age (mean = 59.69, SD = 13.63). No participant presented with <lb/>any limb weakness or apraxia. NHP did not have a history of psychiatric disorder, <lb/>neurological illness or insult, nor any other serious medical condition. All NHP were <lb/>right-handed and all spoke English as a first language. <lb/>Ethical approval for the study was obtained from City University Ethics Committee. <lb/></body>

			<page>830 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Procedure <lb/>Participants were invited to take part in &quot;The describing events project&quot;, focusing upon the <lb/>impact of aphasia on discourse production. Data were collected at a university clinic, a day <lb/>centre, or participants&apos; own homes. Speakers produced discourses in response to the <lb/>questions &quot;can you tell me how you would wrap a box in paper for a present?&quot; (gift <lb/>wrapping procedure) and &quot;can you tell me how you would change the wheel of a car?&quot; <lb/>(wheel changing procedure). After the question was posed, participants were given positive <lb/>but neutral encouragement, such as nodding and smiling. Participants were considered to <lb/>have finished when they stopped talking for &gt;10 s or gave some indication of being finished, <lb/>for example, saying &quot;and that&apos;s it&quot;. Participants were filmed on a digital video camera, <lb/>placed approximately 1 m away from them, and positioned to obtain a front view. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Discourse analysis <lb/>Discourse analysis aimed to address Hypotheses 1 and 2, relating to overall patterns of gesture <lb/>and language use. All discourses were transcribed verbatim using MS Office Word and <lb/>Windows Media Player by the first author, a qualified Speech and Language Therapist <lb/>(SLT) with post-qualification experience of working with adults with aphasia. See <lb/>Appendix for example transcripts. Language was coded by hand in MS Office Word, collated <lb/>in MS Office Excel, and analysed for number of words, PAS (Webster et al., 2007), and <lb/>frequency of spatial motor terms (SMTs; Hostetter et al., 2007). The number of words, rather <lb/>than any other measure such as mean length of utterance, was used so that findings were <lb/>comparable with previous gesture frequency studies (e.g., Cocks et al., 2013; Sekine, Rose, <lb/>Foster, Attard, &amp; Lanyon, 2013). The PAS analysis tallied the number of internal arguments <lb/>used with each main verb. Examples of 0, 1, and 2 argument structures are given in Table 2. <lb/>Using the data, the average PAS score was calculated, using the formula (total number of <lb/>arguments produced/total number of predicates produced). The resulting figure describes the <lb/>average complexity of structures produced, termed &quot;mean PAS complexity&quot; by Webster et al. <lb/>Table 2. Examples of 0, 1, and 2 argument structures. <lb/>Number of arguments <lb/>Examples <lb/>0 <lb/>&quot;and then twist&quot; <lb/>1 <lb/>&quot;fold [the paper]&quot; <lb/>&quot;sellotape [that]&quot; <lb/>2 <lb/>&quot;you put [the box] [down]&quot; <lb/>&quot;drop [the jack] [down]&quot; <lb/>Table 1. Summary of participants&apos; WAB scores. <lb/>Aphasia subtype <lb/>N <lb/>Aphasia quotient (AQ) <lb/>Mean <lb/>Range <lb/>SD <lb/>Anomic <lb/>16 <lb/>83.7 <lb/>71.2-89.7 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>Conduction <lb/>6 <lb/>62.9 <lb/>40.1-80 <lb/>12.4 <lb/>Wernicke&apos;s <lb/>3 <lb/>63.3 <lb/>55.7-71.5 <lb/>4.3 <lb/>Broca&apos;s <lb/>4 <lb/>57.7 <lb/>40.1-69.6 <lb/>9.9 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>831 <lb/></page>

			<body>(2007). SMTs described how and where things moved and included actions (e.g., turn), <lb/>descriptors (e.g., tightly and opposite), and positional language (e.g., under). <lb/>Iconic gestures (as defined by McNeill, 2000), occurring concurrent to language or <lb/>within a word searching episode, were identified with the sound on, as this definition <lb/>encompasses gestures which have a formal relation to the semantic content of the <lb/>concurrent language. These were tagged using the programme EUDICO Linguistic <lb/>Annotator (Wittenburg, Brugman, Russel, Klassmann, &amp; Sloetjes, 2006). Gestures con-<lb/>tained at least a stroke phase (Kendon, 2004) and were coded as depicting semantic <lb/>features outlined in previous studies (Allen et al., 2007; Cocks et al., 2013; Kita &amp; <lb/>Özyürek, 2003; Pritchard et al., 2013), described in Cocks et al. (2011): <lb/>• Path: gesture describes the direction in which something moves; for example, the <lb/>thumb moves to the right alongside the speech &quot;you put the sellotape on&quot;. <lb/>• Manner: gesture describes some aspect of the way in which the action is completed; <lb/>for example, the hand makes a holding shape with the palm outward and then twists <lb/>90°to the left alongside the speech &quot;you need to do it up&quot;. <lb/>• Attribute: gesture describes some feature of the shape or size of the item; for <lb/>example, finger and thumb form a pincer grip approximately 5 cm apart to <lb/>demonstrate the size of the item alongside the speech &quot;take the wheel nut&quot;. <lb/>• Shape outline: hands trace or mould the shape of the object; for example, both <lb/>hands tracing the outline of a circle whilst saying &quot;wheel&quot;. <lb/>• Other: gesture is clearly iconic, but its relationship to co-speech is unclear. <lb/>Gestures that contained conflated information (e.g., manner and path information) were <lb/>counted twice: for example, once for path and once for manner. <lb/>Key event analysis <lb/>The key event analysis addressed Hypothesis 3, exploring how speakers used language and <lb/>gesture to describe two key events within the discourses. The key events were selected as they <lb/>are essential steps in the discourses, had been identified as such in previous work (Hostetter <lb/>et al., 2007), and were present in the discourses of most speakers. In the gift wrapping <lb/>procedure, the key event was the point where the paper is first folded over the box (fold event), <lb/>and in the wheel changing procedure, the key event was the point where the new wheel is put <lb/>onto the car (put event). Speakers who did not describe the event were omitted from this <lb/>analysis only. 1 The main verbs were coded based on semantic weight, with the verbs come, <lb/>go, make, take, get, give, do, have, be, and put coded as semantically light, and all others <lb/>coded as semantically heavy (Berndt et al., 1997; Hostetter et al., 2007). Gesture was <lb/>synchronised if it occurred anywhere within the clause describing the &quot;fold&quot; or &quot;put event&quot;, <lb/>so, for example, either where it occurred alongside the verb itself or whether it occurred <lb/>alongside the preposition in an argument phrase. This is because the majority of iconic <lb/>gestures occur alongside verbs in healthy speakers (Hadar &amp; Krauss, 1999), and the semantics <lb/>of the verb has been shown to directly influence the shape of a gesture (the verb &quot;swing&quot; in <lb/>Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003). There is not a corresponding heavy/light distinction made in gesture <lb/>categorisation, but gestures are commonly analysed for the same semantic components used <lb/>in language semantics -for example, path, and manner (Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003). In spoken <lb/>language, &quot;light&quot; verbs are highly frequent and convey basic information about events or <lb/>states such as the fact that something moved. The gestures most similar to this in terms of both <lb/></body>

			<page>832 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>frequency and paucity of semantics conveyed are path gestures. Therefore, in this &quot;gesture <lb/>weight&quot; analysis, &quot;path&quot; gestures were considered light, as the hand movement depicts <lb/>minimal semantic information describing the path of movement only. See Table 3 for <lb/>examples of light and heavy language and gesture. <lb/>Finally, the gesture and the language were considered together, to determine whether <lb/>one modality carried more semantic weight. For example, if a speaker said &quot;you do the <lb/>paper&quot; whilst producing a gesture depicting holding the paper and folding it over, the <lb/>language and gesture were coded as mismatched, as the semantics of the gesture indicated <lb/>manner of moment and attributes of the object being moved, whilst the lexical semantics <lb/>of the verb do did not. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>Data were analysed using IBM SPSS Statistics 21 software and compared using 2-tailed <lb/>t-tests, with significance set at p &lt; 0.05. Frequency of gestures, number of words per <lb/>gesture, and number of the internal arguments used by each group were completed using a <lb/>mixed analysis of variance, with group as the between-subjects variable and number of <lb/>arguments as the within-subject variable. Post hoc comparisons were completed using <lb/>2-tailed tests, with p &lt; 0.005, to adjust for multiple comparisons. Key event comparisons <lb/>between groups were completed using Fisher&apos;s exact tests, p &lt; 0.05. <lb/>Reliability <lb/>Coding was completed by an English-speaking SLT with post-qualification experience with <lb/>adults with aphasia. A second rater, also a qualified English speaking SLT with post-qualifica-<lb/>tion experience with adults with aphasia coded 10% of the data for language measures (word <lb/>count, PAS, SMTs, and verb semantic weight) and gestures (frequency and form). Interrater <lb/>reliability is reported in Table 4. Differences in coding were resolved through discussion. <lb/>Results <lb/>The following section will present speakers&apos; overall use of gesture and language in the <lb/>discourses and then the findings for the key events within each discourse in gesture, <lb/>language, and relative semantic weight. <lb/>Table 3. Examples of light and heavy language and gesture in the &quot;fold&quot; event. <lb/>Gesture <lb/>Language <lb/>Light <lb/>Participant moves hand to the left 30 cm <lb/>(describing path of movement only) <lb/>&quot;You do the paper over the box&quot; <lb/>Heavy <lb/>Participant&apos;s handshape depicts holding a <lb/>piece of paper and folding it over the box <lb/>(describing path, manner, and attribute) <lb/>&quot;You fold the paper over the box&quot; <lb/>Match <lb/>Participant&apos;s handshape depicts holding a <lb/>piece of paper, and folding it over the box <lb/>(describing path, manner, and attribute) <lb/>&quot;You fold the paper over the box&quot; <lb/>Mismatch <lb/>Participant moves hand to the left 30 cm <lb/>(describing path of movement only) <lb/>&quot;You fold the paper over the box&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>833 <lb/></page>

			<body>Procedural discourse analysis <lb/>Overall language <lb/>PWA produced significantly shorter discourses, using fewer words to describe both procedures <lb/>(wheel changing procedure, t(51) = 1.95, p &lt; 0.05; gift wrapping procedure, t(53) = 2.93, <lb/>p &lt; 0.05). Refer to Tables 5 and 6 for figures. <lb/>PAS <lb/>As predicted, PWA used fewer verbs in both the wheel changing procedure, t(54) = 3.59, <lb/>p &lt; 0.05, and gift wrapping procedure, t(51) = 3.48, p &lt; 0.05. This was reflected in lower <lb/>PAS scores for both the wheel changing procedure t(55) = 1.89, p &lt; 0.05, and gift <lb/>wrapping procedure, t(53) = 3.34, p &lt; 0.05. Refer to Tables 5 and 6 for figures. <lb/>Speakers in both groups used 0, 1, and 2 argument PASs. Each group behaved consistently <lb/>in the two discourse tasks: NHP used 2 argument structures most frequently, followed by 1 <lb/>argument and 0 argument structures, whilst PWA used 1 argument structures most frequently, <lb/>followed by 2 argument and 0 argument structures (see Figures 1 and 2). There was a significant <lb/>interaction between group and number of arguments used for the wheel changing procedure, F <lb/>(2) = 2.36, p &lt; 0.05, and gift wrapping procedure, F(2) = 2.26, p &lt; 0.05, indicating the two <lb/>groups had different levels of syntactic complexity. Post hoc comparisons indicated a significant <lb/>difference between 2 argument structures between groups for both discourses, with NHP using a <lb/>Table 5. Means of language and gesture used in the procedural discourses by PWA. <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Wheel changing procedure <lb/># words <lb/>90.03 <lb/>61.26 <lb/># verbs <lb/>9.36 <lb/>7.23 <lb/>PAS complexity <lb/>1.19 <lb/>0.57 <lb/># SMTs <lb/>16.74 <lb/>11.29 <lb/>% SMTs <lb/>19.3 <lb/>8.37 <lb/># gestures <lb/>7.61 <lb/>5.95 <lb/>Words per gesture <lb/>16.8 <lb/>21.05 <lb/>Gift wrapping procedure <lb/># words <lb/>69.34 <lb/>41.97 <lb/># Verbs <lb/>7.1 <lb/>5.62 <lb/>PAS complexity <lb/>1.14 <lb/>0.45 <lb/># SMTs <lb/>14.33 <lb/>9.98 <lb/>% SMTS <lb/>19.56 <lb/>10.25 <lb/># gestures <lb/>7.61 <lb/>6.96 <lb/>Words per gesture <lb/>19.33 <lb/>21.22 <lb/>Table 4. Interrater reliability analyses. <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Reliability level (%) <lb/>Transcription <lb/>94 <lb/>PAS <lb/>92.8 <lb/>SMTs <lb/>89 <lb/>Verb semantic weight <lb/>100 <lb/>Gesture coding <lb/>84.7 <lb/></body>

			<page>834 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>higher percentage of these structures (wheel changing procedure PWA, m = 38.18%, <lb/>SD = 27.45; NHP, m = 49.17%, SD = 22.16), t(55) = 2.34, p &lt; 0.005, gift wrapping procedure <lb/>(PWA m = 31.08%, SD = 25.34; NHP m = 44.55%, SD = 16.55), t(54) = 3.59, p &lt; 0.005. <lb/>SMTs <lb/>As predicted, PWA used fewer SMTs overall than NHP in both procedures: wheel <lb/>changing procedure, t(51) = 3.07, p &lt; 0.05, and gift wrapping procedure, t(53) = 3.38, <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Percentage frequency <lb/>Number of arguments <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 1. Gift wrapping procedure: PAS. <lb/>Table 6. Means of language and gesture used in the procedural discourses by NHP. <lb/>Mean <lb/>SD <lb/>Wheel changing procedure <lb/># words <lb/>119.22 <lb/>75.57 <lb/># verbs <lb/>15.55 <lb/>10.35 <lb/>PAS complexity <lb/>1.45 <lb/>0.35 <lb/># SMTs <lb/>29.31 <lb/>17.92 <lb/>% SMTs <lb/>23.56 <lb/>3.31 <lb/># gestures <lb/>6.55 <lb/>4.7 <lb/>Words per gesture <lb/>14.04 <lb/>10.34 <lb/>Gift wrapping procedure <lb/># words <lb/>100.09 <lb/>66.96 <lb/># Verbs <lb/>13.96 <lb/>7.31 <lb/>PAS complexity <lb/>1.42 <lb/>0.35 <lb/># SMTs <lb/>15.86 <lb/>14.73 <lb/>% SMTS <lb/>24.32 <lb/>7.14 <lb/># gestures <lb/>6.32 <lb/>4.44 <lb/>Words per gesture <lb/>21.43 <lb/>16.98 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>835 <lb/></page>

			<body>p &lt; 0.05. They also used fewer SMTs as a percentage of overall words used: wheel <lb/>changing procedure, t(51) = 2.2, p &lt; 0.05, and gift wrapping procedure, t(56) = 2.2, <lb/>p &lt; 0.05. Refer to Tables 5 and 6 for figures. <lb/>Overall gesture frequency and form <lb/>The frequency and form of participants&apos; gestures were analysed to test Hypothesis 2 <lb/>that PWA would produce more gestures than NHP and that these gestures would differ <lb/>in form from those produced by NHP. Contrary to expectations, there was no effect of <lb/>group or discourse on the frequency of gestures, F(2, 58) = 0.29, p &gt; 0.05. The <lb/>frequency of words per gesture was similar across both groups for both discourses, <lb/>F(2, 58) = 0.663, p &gt; 0.05. <lb/>Also contrary to expectations, across both tasks, both groups produced gestures <lb/>containing similar semantic information, indicated by no interaction between group and <lb/>semantic content of gesture, wheel changing procedure, F(4, 2.717) = 0.775, p &gt; 0.05, and <lb/>gift wrapping procedure F(4, 2.712) = 1.489, p &gt; 0.05. This is depicted in Figures 3 and 4. <lb/>Key event analysis <lb/>Key events were analysed, in order to test Hypothesis 3, that PWA gesture would differ <lb/>from their language. Patterns of language and gesture use were different in the two events. <lb/>Gift wrapping procedure: &quot;Fold&quot; event <lb/>28 NHP and 21 PWA used gesture and language to describe the fold event within the gift <lb/>wrapping procedure. The NHP group used a higher frequency of heavy verbs than PWA <lb/>(NHP = 26/28; PWA = 13/21, Fisher&apos;s exact p &lt; 0.05). Both groups used the verbs &quot;fold&quot; <lb/>and &quot;bring&quot; most frequently to describe this event (see Table 7). <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Percentage frequency <lb/>Number of arguments <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 2. Wheel changing procedure: PAS. <lb/></body>

			<page>836 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>Path <lb/>Manner <lb/>Attribute <lb/>Shape <lb/>Outline <lb/>Other <lb/>Percentage frequency <lb/>Semantic features of gestures <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 4. Wheel changing procedure: Percentage of gestures containing specific semantic features <lb/>of form. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>Path <lb/>Manner <lb/>Attribute <lb/>Shape <lb/>Outline <lb/>Other <lb/>Percentage frequency <lb/>Semantic features of gestures <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 3. Gift wrapping procedure: Percentage of gestures containing specific semantic features of <lb/>form. <lb/>Table 7. Gift wrapping procedure Fold event verbs used by speakers. <lb/>Group <lb/>Verb used <lb/>NHP (n = 28) <lb/>fold (16), wrap (5), bring (3), pull (1), put (1), place (1), lift (1) <lb/>PWA (n = 21) <lb/>fold (4), wrap (4), put (4), no verb used (3), negotiate (1), <lb/>get (1), is (1), wind (1), do (1), stick (1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>837 <lb/></page>

			<body>Most participants used semantically heavy gestures to describe this event (NHP = 28/ <lb/>28; PWA = 20/21, Fisher&apos;s exact, p &lt; 0.05). As shown in Figure 5, the majority of these <lb/>contained aspects of both path and manner. <lb/>There was a difference between groups in whether the information conveyed in speech <lb/>and gesture matched (Fisher&apos;s exact, p &lt; 0.05). NHP communicated similar information in <lb/>both modalities: 25/26 of participants used a semantically heavy verb with a semantically <lb/>rich gesture, for example, saying &quot;you fold it over&quot; [heavy verb], alongside a gesture that <lb/>demonstrated the size of the paper and the way it would be held whilst being folded <lb/>[heavy gesture]. In line with expectations, some speakers with aphasia presented different <lb/>information in speech and gesture. Just 11/21 of the gestures and language produced by <lb/>the PWA matched, with all mismatched speech and gesture combinations being a heavy <lb/>gesture used with a light verb. See Table 3 for an example of this. <lb/>Wheel changing procedure: &quot;Put&quot; event <lb/>Nineteen NHP and 17 PWA described the put event using gesture and language. Both <lb/>groups used &quot;put&quot; most frequently to describe this event (see Table 8). <lb/>As shown in Figure 6, the majority of gestures produced by all participants were <lb/>&quot;heavy&quot; gestures (NHP = 17/19; PWA = 17/17, Fisher&apos;s exact p &gt; 0.05), and the majority <lb/>of these contained aspects of both path and manner. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>Path <lb/>Manner <lb/>Attribute <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 5. Gift wrapping procedure Fold event: Percentage of participants&apos; gestures containing <lb/>features of path, attribute, and manner. <lb/>Table 8. Wheel changing procedure Put event verbs used by speakers. <lb/>Group <lb/>Verb used <lb/>NHP (n = 19) <lb/>put (10), do (2), change (2), place (2), stick (1), bring (1), <lb/>slot (1) <lb/>PWA (n = 17) <lb/>put (12), do (1), change (1), figure (1), replace (1), fix (1) <lb/></body>

			<page>838 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Both groups used similar patterns of language and gesture, with the content of <lb/>language and gesture differing (NHP mismatched = 12/19; PWA matched = 15/17, <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact, p &gt; 0.05). These mismatches were all semantically heavy gestures with <lb/>semantically light verbs. <lb/>In summary, PWA used language that was syntactically and semantically simpler <lb/>than NHP for their procedural discourses, whilst producing gestures that conveyed a <lb/>similar amount of semantic information to NHP. In the key event analysis, both groups <lb/>presented information similarly in the light put event, but differently in the fold event, <lb/>where PWA used gestures that were semantically heavy alongside semantically light <lb/>language. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This study investigated how PWA presented information using gesture and language in <lb/>procedural discourses, compared with NHP. The study aimed to identify the information <lb/>presented in gesture in the context of impaired language, both overall and in individual <lb/>events. This was completed with the dual purpose of informing clinical assessment of <lb/>communication and understanding the multimodal nature of language. Ours is the first <lb/>study that has focused on the relative roles played by gesture and language in the <lb/>procedural discourses of PWA. As predicted, and in line with previous research, PWA <lb/>used syntactically less complex language in the discourses. Contrary to our expectations <lb/>and the findings of previous studies, overall, PWA used gestures with semantically similar <lb/>forms to NHP. However, there were differences in the content of gesture and language <lb/>when describing the key events, for both NHP and PWA. Both groups produced gesture <lb/>and language that did not match, such as a semantically heavy gesture alongside a <lb/>semantically light verb. These findings are likely to be due to speakers&apos; lexical choices <lb/>and the spatial nature of the discourse and are informative for clinical practice. They also <lb/>contribute to the debate regarding the role of gesture in language production. <lb/>As hypothesised, and consistent with previous studies (Cruice et al., 2014; Johnson <lb/>et al., 2013; Ulatowska et al., 1981; Webster et al., 2007), PWA in the current study <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>90 <lb/>100 <lb/>Path <lb/>Manner <lb/>Attribute <lb/>PWA <lb/>NHP <lb/>Figure 6. Wheel changing procedure Put event: Percentage of participants&apos; gestures containing <lb/>features of path, attribute, and manner. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>839 <lb/></page>

			<body>produced syntactically and semantically less complex language in their discourses. <lb/>However, contrary to hypotheses and the majority of previous studies (Cicone et al., <lb/>1979; Cocks et al., 2013; Feyereisen, 1983; Hadar et al., 1998; Herrmann et al., 1988; <lb/>Lanyon &amp; Rose, 2009; Orgassa, 2005; Sekine et al., 2013), both groups used similar <lb/>quantities and types of gestures. The fact that both groups in this study used a comparable <lb/>number of gestures, but that PWA used fewer SMTs than NHP, indicates that PWA <lb/>presented more spatial motor information in gesture than in language. What is striking <lb/>in these findings is that PWA gesture was accurate despite their impoverished language. <lb/>Speakers from both groups presented information omitted from spoken language in <lb/>gesture, in line with our predictions. In the semantically heavy fold event, NHP produced <lb/>the same information in speech and language, whilst PWA omitted information in their <lb/>speech, and included it within their gesture. By contrast, in the semantically lighter put <lb/>event, both groups used spoken language containing limited information, alongside <lb/>gestures that contained more semantic information. There is an evidence base in the <lb/>literature about the semantic complexity of verbs used by PWA (Barde, Schwartz, &amp; <lb/>Boronat, 2006; Berndt et al., 1997; Faroqi-Shah &amp; Graham, 2011; Gordon, 2008), and the <lb/>verb put has been analysed as light by others (Gordon, 2008). To our knowledge, the same <lb/>variable has not been explored in gesture, and although there is not a corresponding <lb/>heavy/light distinction made in gesture categorisation, gestures are commonly analysed <lb/>for the same semantic components used in language semantics -for example, path, and <lb/>manner (Kita &amp; Özyürek, 2003). Path gestures display characteristics the most similar to <lb/>light verbs, in terms of being highly frequent and in terms of conveying sparse informa-<lb/>tion, such as the fact something moved. <lb/>This mismatch in information presented in gesture and speech could be explained <lb/>through the syntactic and semantic properties of the verb put, which contains meaning in <lb/>its arguments that may be conveyed in gesture. However, the fact that speakers with <lb/>aphasia also produced the same pattern of light language and heavy gesture in the heavy <lb/>fold event is likely to indicate that when speech contains limited information, spontaneous <lb/>co-speech gesture can carry some of the communicative load. This dissociation between <lb/>language and gesture is consistent with theoretical models (de Ruiter, 2000; McNeill &amp; <lb/>Duncan, 2000) and previous studies on spatial communication in NHP and in speakers <lb/>with aphasia (Dipper et al., 2011; Graham &amp; Argyle, 1975; Melinger &amp; Levelt, 2004). <lb/>With all communication, listeners gather meaning from speech, but also from addi-<lb/>tional modalities, and so gesture is a key element in procedural discourses, due to their <lb/>spatial content. The dissociation demonstrated within the current study, between speech <lb/>and gesture, indicates that it can be a normal pattern to communicate more information in <lb/>gesture than in language. Future research should focus on the relationship between <lb/>specific aspects of language semantics and gestures in specific events and different <lb/>discourse genres. <lb/>These findings are of importance clinically. First, there should be different expecta-<lb/>tions from speech and gesture, depending on genre, due to differences in lexical choices <lb/>and semantics. Second, it is likely that if a speaker with aphasia is not producing heavy <lb/>gestures in contexts where they would be expected, such as in procedures, this would be <lb/>an indication that their semantic system is impaired. Finally, in terms of clinical assess-<lb/>ment and intervention, both modalities need to be taken into account. Whilst a speaker <lb/>may not intentionally produce gesture to directly compensate for impaired language, the <lb/>use of semantically rich gesture alongside semantically impoverished language is likely to <lb/>be useful to the listener and may well contribute to the observation that some speakers <lb/></body>

			<page>840 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>with aphasia are able to communicate better than they talk (Holland, 1982). This finding is <lb/>likely to be specific to speakers&apos; language profile: PWA in this study had mild-to-<lb/>moderate aphasia, and produced gesture that was concurrent to language, not in its <lb/>place. Future research should explore the impact of language profile, such as aphasia <lb/>type, fluency, and severity, on language and gestures in discourses for different functions <lb/>and levels of complexity. <lb/>The current study confirmed previous findings that the language of speakers with <lb/>aphasia is impaired in form and content in procedural discourses. It also presented new <lb/>evidence that the gestures used by PWA in this discourse genre carry rich semantic <lb/>information and should be considered in clinical assessment. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors would like to acknowledge the contribution of Foteini Theocharopoulou, who worked <lb/>as a Research Assistant on the project. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work was supported by a City University London Pump Priming Grant and the Dunhill <lb/>Medical Trust [grant reference: R171/0710]. <lb/></div>

			<!-- notes are usually annotated foot notes -->
			<div type="annex">Note <lb/>1. Speakers omitted from this analysis either omitted the step entirely or described an alternative <lb/>process for completing the procedure (e.g., &quot;I create a sort of bag out of the paper and then put <lb/>the box inside it&quot;). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Allen, S., Özyürek, A., Kita, S., Brown, A., Furman, R., Ishizuka, T., &amp; Fujii, M. (2007). Language-<lb/>specific and universal influences in children&apos;s syntactic packaging of manner and path: A <lb/>comparison of English, Japanese, and Turkish. Cognition, 102, 16-48. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>cognition.2005.12.006 <lb/>Barde, L., Schwartz, M., &amp; Boronat, C. (2006). Semantic weight and verb retrieval in aphasia. Brain <lb/>and Language, 97, 266-278. doi:10.1016/j.bandl.2005.11.002 <lb/>Beattie, G., &amp; Shovelton, H. (1999). Do iconic hand gestures really contribute anything to the <lb/>semantic information conveyed by speech? An experimental investigation. Semiotica, 123, 1-<lb/>30. doi:10.1515/semi.1999.123.1-2.1 <lb/>Berndt, R., Haendiges, A., Mitchum, C., &amp; Sandson, J. (1997). Verb retrieval in aphasia. 2. <lb/>Relationship to sentence processing. Brain &amp; Language, 56, 107-137. doi:10.1006/ <lb/>brln.1997.1728 <lb/>Bickerton, W., Samson, D., Humphreys, G., Riddoch, M., Kumar, V., Mortensen, L., … Punt, D. <lb/>(2006). The development of Birmingham University Apraxia Screening Test. Abstracts of the <lb/>4th World Congress for Neurorehabilitation, 20, 179. <lb/>Brady, M., Armstrong, L., &amp; Mackenzie, C. (2006). An examination over time of language and <lb/>discourse production abilities following right hemisphere brain damage. Journal of <lb/>Neurolinguistics, 19, 291-310. doi:10.1016/j.jneuroling.2005.12.001 <lb/>Carlomagno, S., &amp; Cristilli, C. (2006). Semantic attributes of iconic gesture in fluent and non fluent <lb/>aphasic adults. Brain &amp; Language, 99, 102-103. doi:10.1016/j.bandl.2006.06.061. Retrieved <lb/>from http://www.sciencedirect.com/science/article/pii/S0093934X06001672 <lb/>Cicone, M., Wapner, W., Foldi, N., Zurif, E., &amp; Gardner, H. (1979). The relation between gesture <lb/>and language in aphasic communication. Brain &amp; Language, 8, 324-349. doi:10.1016/0093-<lb/>934X(79)90060-9 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>841 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Cocks, N., Dipper, L., Middleton, R., &amp; Morgan, G. (2011). The impact of aphasia on gesture <lb/>production: A case of conduction aphasia. International Journal of Language &amp; <lb/>Communication Disorders, 46, 423-436. doi:10.3109/13682822.2010.520813 <lb/>Cocks, N., Dipper, L., Pritchard, M., &amp; Morgan, G. (2013). The impact of impaired semantic <lb/>knowledge on spontaneous iconic gesture production. Aphasiology, 27, 1050-1069. <lb/>doi:10.1080/02687038.2013.770816 <lb/>Cocks, N., Hird, K., &amp; Kirsner, K. (2007). The relationship between right hemisphere damage and <lb/>gesture in spontaneous discourse. Aphasiology, 21, 299-319. doi:10.1080/02687030600911393 <lb/>Cruice, M., Pritchard, M., &amp; Dipper, L. (2014). Verb use in aphasic and non-aphasic personal <lb/>discourse: What is normal? Journal of Neurolinguistics, 28, 31-47. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>jneuroling.2013.12.002 <lb/>Davidson, B., Worrall, L., &amp; Hickson, L. (2003). Identifying the communication activities of older <lb/>people with aphasia: Evidence from naturalistic observation. Aphasiology, 17, 243-264. <lb/>doi:10.1080/729255457 <lb/>de Ruiter, J. (2000). The production of gesture and speech. In D. McNeill (Ed.), Language and <lb/>gesture (pp. 284-311). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Dipper, L., Cocks, N., Rowe, M., &amp; Morgan, G. (2011). What can co-speech gestures in aphasia tell <lb/>us about the relationship between language and gesture?: A single case study of a participant <lb/>with conduction aphasia. Gesture, 11, 123-147. doi:10.1075/gest.11.2.02dip <lb/>Faroqi-Shah, Y., &amp; Graham, L. (2011). Treatment of semantic verb classes in aphasia: Acquisition <lb/>and generalization effects. Clinical Linguistics &amp; Phonetics, 25, 399-418. doi:10.3109/ <lb/>02699206.2010.545964 <lb/>Feyereisen, P. (1983). Manual activity during speaking in aphasic subjects. International Journal of <lb/>Psychology, 18, 545-556. doi:10.1080/00207598308247500 <lb/>Feyereisen, P., &amp; Havard, I. (1999). Mental imagery and production of hand gestures while speaking <lb/>in younger and older adults. Journal of Nonverbal Behavior, 23, 153-171. doi:10.1023/ <lb/>A:1021487510204 <lb/>Gordon, J. (2008). Measuring the lexical semantics of picture description in aphasia. Aphasiology, <lb/>22, 839-852. doi:10.1080/02687030701820063 <lb/>Graham, J., &amp; Argyle, M. (1975). A cross-cultural study of the communication of extra-verbal <lb/>meaning by gesture. International Journal of Psychology, 10, 57-67. doi:10.1080/ <lb/>00207597508247319 <lb/>Hadar, U., Burstein, A., Krauss, R., &amp; Soroker, N. (1998). Ideational gestures and speech in brain damaged <lb/>subjects. Language &amp; Cognitive Processes, 13, 59-76. doi:10.1080/016909698386591 <lb/>Hadar, U., &amp; Krauss, R. (1999). Iconic gestures: The grammatical categories of lexical affiliates. <lb/>Journal of Neurolinguistics, 12, 1-12. doi:10.1016/S0911-6044(99)00001-9 <lb/>Halliday, M. (2004). An introduction to functional grammar. London: Edward Arnold. <lb/>Herrmann, M., Reichle, T., Lucius-Hoene, G., Wallesche, C., &amp; Johannsen-Horbache, H. (1988). <lb/>Non-verbal communication as a compensative strategy for severely non fluent aphasics? A <lb/>quantitative approach. Brain &amp; Language, 33, 41-54. doi:10.1016/0093-934X(88)90053-3 <lb/>Hogrefe, K., Ziegler, W., Weidinger, N., &amp; Goldenberg, G. (2012). Non-verbal communication in <lb/>severe aphasia: Influence of aphasia, apraxia, or semantic processing? Cortex, 48, 952-962. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.cortex.2011.02.022 <lb/>Hogrefe, K., Ziegler, W., Wiesmayer, S., Weidinger, N., &amp; Goldenberg, G. (2013). The actual and potential <lb/>use of gestures for communication in aphasia. Aphasiology, 27, 1070-1089. doi:10.1080/ <lb/>02687038.2013.803515 <lb/>Holland, A. (1982). Observing functional communication of aphasic adults. Journal of Speech and <lb/>Hearing Disorders, 47, 50-56. doi:10.1044/jshd.4701.50 <lb/>Hostetter, A., Alibali, M., &amp; Kita, S. (2007, August 1-4). Does sitting on your hands make you bite <lb/>your tongue? The effects of gesture inhibition on speech during motor descriptions. Paper <lb/>presented at the 29th meeting of the Cognitive Science Society, Nashville, TN. <lb/>Johnson, S., Cocks, N., &amp; Dipper, L. (2013). Use of spatial communication in aphasia. International <lb/>Journal of Language &amp; Communication Disorders, 48, 469-476. doi:10.1111/1460-6984.12022 <lb/>Kendon, A. (2004). Gesture: Visible action as utterance. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Kertesz, A. (2006). The Western Aphasia Battery WAB-R. London: Grune and Statton. <lb/>Kita, S. (2000). How representational gestures help speaking. In D. McNeil (Ed.), Language and <lb/>gesture. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>842 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Kita, S., &amp; Özyürek, A. (2003). What does cross-linguistic variation in semantic coordination of <lb/>speech and gesture reveal?: Evidence for an interface representation of spatial thinking and <lb/>speaking. Journal of Memory &amp; Language, 48, 16-32. doi:10.1016/S0749-596X(02)00505-3 <lb/>Krauss, R., Chen, Y., &amp; Gottesman, R. (2000). Lexical gestures and Lexical access: A process <lb/>model. In D. McNeill (Ed.), Language &amp; gesture. Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Lanyon, L., &amp; Rose, M. (2009). Do the hands have it? The facilitation effects of arm and hand <lb/>gesture on word retrieval in aphasia. Aphasiology, 23, 809-822. doi:10.1080/ <lb/>02687030802642044 <lb/>Lyle, R. (1981). A performance test for assessment of upper limb function in physical rehabilitation <lb/>treatment and research. International Journal of Rehabilitation Research, 4, 483-492. <lb/>doi:10.1097/00004356-198112000-00001 <lb/>McNeill, D. (Ed.). (2000). Introduction. In Language &amp; gesture (pp. 1-10). Cambridge: Cambridge <lb/>University Press. <lb/>McNeill, D., &amp; Duncan, S. (2000). Growth points in thinking-for-speaking. In D. McNeil (Ed.), <lb/>Language &amp; gesture (pp. 141-161). Cambridge: Cambridge University Press. <lb/>Melinger, A., &amp; Levelt, W. (2004). Gesture and the communicative intention of the speaker. <lb/>Gesture, 4, 119-141. doi:10.1075/gest.4.2.02mel <lb/>Mol, L., Krahmer, E., &amp; van de Sandt-Koenderman, M. (2013). Gesturing by speakers with aphasia: <lb/>How does it compare? Journal of Speech, Language &amp; Hearing Research, 56, 1224-1236. <lb/>doi:10.1044/1092-4388(2012/11-0159) <lb/>Nicholas, L., &amp; Brookshire, R. (1993). A system for quantifying the informativeness and efficiency <lb/>of the connected speech of adults with aphasia. Journal of Speech, Language &amp; Hearing <lb/>Research, 36, 338-350. doi:10.1044/jshr.3602.338 <lb/>Nicholas, L., &amp; Brookshire, R. (1995). Presence, completeness, and accuracy of main concepts in <lb/>the connected speech of non-brain-damaged adults and adults with aphasia. Journal of Speech, <lb/>Language &amp; Hearing Research, 38, 145-156. doi:10.1044/jshr.3801.145 <lb/>Orgassa, A. (2005). Co-speech gesture in anomic aphasia. Toegepaste Taalwetenschap in Artikelen, <lb/>73, 85-97. doi:10.1075/ttwia.73.09org <lb/>Poeck, K. (1986). The clinical examination for motor apraxia. Neuropsychologia, 24, 129-134. <lb/>doi:10.1016/0028-3932(86)90046-1 <lb/>Pritchard, M., Cocks, N., &amp; Dipper, L. (2013). Iconic gesture in normal language and word <lb/>searching conditions: A case of conduction aphasia. International Journal of Speech-<lb/>Language Pathology, 15, 524-534. doi:10.3109/17549507.2012.712157 <lb/>Sekine, K., Rose, M., Foster, A., Attard, M., &amp; Lanyon, L. (2013). Gesture production patterns in <lb/>aphasic discourse: In-depth description and preliminary predictions. Aphasiology, 27, 1031-<lb/>1049. doi:10.1080/02687038.2013.803017 <lb/>Shadden, B., Burnette, R., Eikenberry, B., &amp; Dibrezzo, R. (1991). All discourse tasks are not created <lb/>equal. In T. Prescott (Ed.), Clinical aphasiology (Vol. 20, pp. 327-341). Austin, TX: Pro-Ed. <lb/>Ulatowska, H., North, A., &amp; Macaluso-Haynes, S. (1981). Production of narrative and procedural <lb/>discourse in aphasia. Brain &amp; Language, 13, 345-371. doi:10.1016/0093-934X(81)90100-0 <lb/>Ulatowska, H., Weiss Doyel, A., Freedmam Stern, R., Macaluso-Haynes, S., &amp; North, A. (1983). <lb/>Production of procedural discourse in aphasia. Brain &amp; Language, 18, 315-341. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>0093-934X(83)90023-8 <lb/>Webster, J., Franklin, S., &amp; Howard, D. (2007). An analysis of thematic and phrasal structure in <lb/>people with aphasia: What more can we learn from the story of Cinderella? Journal of <lb/>Neurolinguistics, 20, 363-394. doi:10.1016/j.jneuroling.2007.02.002 <lb/>Wittenburg, P., Brugman, H., Russel, A., Klassmann, A., &amp; Sloetjes, H. (2006, May 24). ELAN: A <lb/>professional framework for multimodality research. Paper presented at the LREC 2006, fifth <lb/>international conference on Language Resources and Evaluation, Genoa. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Appendix <lb/>Wheel changing procedure: NHP <lb/>Well in theory yes erm you would need to find a jack from the boot you&apos;d need to find the jack socket <lb/>hole point jack point I think it&apos;s called er you&apos;d need to put insert the jack into that and do the lever and <lb/>make the car go up you&apos;d undo the oh no first of all you&apos;d have to rewind you&apos;d have to un loosen the <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Aphasiology <lb/></note>

			<page>843 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">bolts on the wheel first then jack it up then complete the loosening erm take the tyre off oh I haven&apos;t <lb/>mentioned the spare tyre get the spare tyre from the boot put it onto the car um yes then you&apos;d initially <lb/>tighten the screws put the car back onto the floor using the jack and and finish them off. <lb/>Wheel changing procedure: PWA <lb/>Er you get the jack out out out out the back of the car anyway I jack the tyre up and then I take get <lb/>the the the the erm sort of like gets the wheel off or or or the nuts off gets all the nuts off and takes <lb/>them out off to one side takes the the the the tyre off and he gets the tyre out and he takes it off off <lb/>off off off the rim and and he gets the thing out and er he he attempts to finish and to er that&apos;s all. <lb/>Gift wrapping procedure: NHP <lb/>First of all find a piece of paper that&apos;s large enough for the for the box and by doing a rough <lb/>calculation in your head you need to be certain that it&apos;s going to come on all four sides press the <lb/>piece of paper on the table put the box on the piece of paper then take the the the sides of the paper <lb/>bring them over to the top with your sellotape bring them over your piece of paper sellotape in the <lb/>other hand and stick on piece of the paper down repeat process then you need to fold the spare ends <lb/>in doing an elegant kind of fold on both sides more sellotape and then have I anything else oh yeah <lb/>both ends side yes box wrapped. <lb/>Gift wrapping procedure: PWA <lb/>Ok so I would find my scissors and sellotape and wrapping paper on the table put them on the table <lb/>and I would get the present put the paper out put the present on it and pull it all over it and put <lb/>sellotape on it maybe I might have had to cut the paper er then I would find the ribbons or pretty I <lb/>like wrapping up things and put that on and then write on it who it was to and tidy everything up put <lb/>the bits in the bin and put it all away. <lb/></div>

			<page>844 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. Pritchard et al. </note>


	</text>
</tei>
