<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_pcbi.1000473"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front> Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation Analysis <lb/>Incorporating Genomic Organisation, and Application to <lb/>Enterobacterial Plant Pathogens <lb/> Leighton Pritchard 1  *, Hui Liu 1 , Clare Booth 2 , Emma Douglas 1 , Patrice François 3 , Jacques Schrenzel 3 , <lb/>Peter E. Hedley 2 , Paul R. J. Birch 1,4 , Ian K. Toth 1  * <lb/> 1 Plant Pathology Programme, SCRI, Dundee, Scotland, United Kingdom, 2 Genetics Programme, SCRI, Dundee, Scotland, United Kingdom, 3 Genomic Research <lb/>Laboratory, Infectious Diseases Service, Geneva University Hospitals and the University of Geneva, Geneva, Switzerland, 4 Division of Plant Science, College of Life <lb/>Sciences, University of Dundee at SCRI, Dundee, Scotland, United Kingdom <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Microarray comparative genomic hybridisation (aCGH) provides an estimate of the relative abundance of genomic DNA <lb/>(gDNA) taken from comparator and reference organisms by hybridisation to a microarray containing probes that represent <lb/>sequences from the reference organism. The experimental method is used in a number of biological applications, including <lb/>the detection of human chromosomal aberrations, and in comparative genomic analysis of bacterial strains, but <lb/>optimisation of the analysis is desirable in each problem domain. We present a method for analysis of bacterial aCGH data <lb/>that encodes spatial information from the reference genome in a hidden Markov model. This technique is the first such <lb/>method to be validated in comparisons of sequenced bacteria that diverge at the strain and at the genus level: <lb/> Pectobacterium atrosepticum SCRI1043 (Pba1043) and Dickeya dadantii 3937 (Dda3937); and Lactococcus lactis subsp. lactis <lb/> IL1403 and L. lactis subsp. cremoris MG1363. In all cases our method is found to outperform common and widely used aCGH <lb/>analysis methods that do not incorporate spatial information. This analysis is applied to comparisons between commercially <lb/>important plant pathogenic soft-rotting enterobacteria (SRE) Pba1043, P. atrosepticum SCRI1039, P. carotovorum 193, and <lb/> Dda3937. Our analysis indicates that it should not be assumed that hybridisation strength is a reliable proxy for sequence <lb/>identity in aCGH experiments, and robustly extends the applicability of aCGH to bacterial comparisons at the genus level. <lb/>Our results in the SRE further provide evidence for a dynamic, plastic &apos;accessory&apos; genome, revealing major genomic islands <lb/>encoding gene products that provide insight into, and may play a direct role in determining, variation amongst the SRE in <lb/>terms of their environmental survival, host range and aetiology, such as phytotoxin synthesis, multidrug resistance, and <lb/>nitrogen fixation. <lb/> Citation: Pritchard L, Liu H, Booth C, Douglas E, François P, et al. (2009) Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation Analysis Incorporating Genomic <lb/>Organisation, and Application to Enterobacterial Plant Pathogens. PLoS Comput Biol 5(8): e1000473. doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473 <lb/> Editor: Weixiong Zhang, Washington University in Saint Louis, United States of America <lb/> Received February 5, 2009; Accepted July 16, 2009; Published August 21, 2009 <lb/> Copyright: ß 2009 Pritchard et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. <lb/> Funding: This work was supported by the Scottish Government Rural and Environment Research and Analysis Directorate (RERAD) [SCR/908/03, SCR/842/04]. JS <lb/>and PF were also supported by the European Union [COST C05.0103 to JS] and the Swiss National Science Foundation [3100A0-116075/1 to PF, 3100A0-112370/1 <lb/>to JS]. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/> Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. <lb/>* E-mail: lpritc@scri.ac.uk (LP); itoth@scri.ac.uk (IKT) <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> Microarray comparative genomic hybridisation (aCGH) provides <lb/>an estimate of the relative abundance of genomic DNA (gDNA) <lb/>taken from comparator and reference organisms by hybridisation to <lb/>a microarray containing probes that represent sequences from the <lb/>reference organism. This method has been used in a number of <lb/>biological applications, including the detection of human chromo-<lb/>somal aberrations [1,2]; comparisons of bacterial human pathogens <lb/>[3–10]; bacterial plant pathogens [11,12]; industrially-important <lb/>bacteria [13]; and comparative transcriptomics of Xenopus laevis [14]. <lb/>Numerous algorithms and software packages have been applied <lb/>to the analysis of this aCGH data in prokaryotes. The majority of <lb/>these partition reference organism sequences into two mutually <lb/>exclusive classes: sequences that are &apos;present&apos; and sequences that <lb/>are &apos;absent or divergent&apos; in the comparator organism [e.g. <lb/>5,12,15,16]. Observed hybridisation data are, in each case, <lb/>assumed to be reliable proxies for these classes. <lb/>In this manuscript we describe and apply an improved method <lb/>for analysis of aCGH data from bacterial genome comparisons. <lb/>This method incorporates spatial information about CDS location <lb/>on the reference genome in a hidden Markov model (HMM). This <lb/>spatial information is expected to capture pertinent biological and <lb/>evolutionary information, such as operon structure, and regions of <lb/>lateral gene transfer. Our approach differs from previously <lb/>proposed, and widely-used, methods applied to bacterial aCGH, <lb/>such as GACK and MPP, that consider hybridisation intensities of <lb/>each reference probe as measurements that are independent of <lb/>their genomic location [15,16], and is thus more similar to <lb/>methods such as ArrayLeaRNA [17], which incorporates <lb/>predicted operon structure into interpretations of microarray <lb/>expression data, for a restricted set of organisms. We compare the <lb/>relative performance of our method to commonly used bacterial <lb/>aCGH analysis algorithms and software. <lb/>We demonstrate that several assumptions of common bacterial <lb/>aCGH analysis methods concerning the relationship between <lb/></body>

			<front> PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></front>
			
			<page>1 <lb/></page>
			
			<front>August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></front>

			<body>observed hybridisation scores and ratios and the presence or <lb/>absence of a reference CDS in the comparator organism do not <lb/>always hold strongly, and that this is particularly the case for more <lb/>distantly-related organisms. Our data in particular do not support <lb/>a distinction between &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent or divergent&apos; classes of <lb/>sequence, but rather between those sequences in the reference <lb/>organism that do, and those that do not, have putative orthologues <lb/>in the comparator genome. We find that the HMM is a better <lb/>predictor of reference sequences that do not have a putative <lb/>orthologue in the comparator organism than the other methods <lb/>tested. <lb/>Spatial organisation of sequences on the reference genome has <lb/>previously been incorporated into methods applied to aCGH <lb/>analyses of copy number variation in human genomes. This has <lb/>been represented using HMM [18] and segmentation methods <lb/>[19]. Simple smoothing methods have also been used to identify <lb/>breakpoints in this data [20]. However, the problem domain of <lb/>human copy number aCGH (detecting copy number variation in a <lb/>known genome sequence) differs from the problem domain of <lb/>bacterial comparative genomic aCGH (identifying the presence or <lb/>absence of putative orthologues of known genes in a genome of <lb/>unknown sequence). To the best of our knowledge, this study <lb/>describes the first application of a method incorporating such <lb/>spatial information to aCGH for comparative genomics of <lb/>unsequenced bacteria, and the first demonstration of the <lb/>applicability of the technique as a whole across bacterial genera. <lb/> Pectobacterium atrosepticum (Pba), Pectobacterium carotovorum (Pcc), and <lb/> Dickeya spp. are plant pathogenic soft-rotting enterobacteria (SRE) <lb/>that share a common ancestor. Despite their many similarities, <lb/>these commercially significant pathogens differ in their host range, <lb/>geographical distribution, aetiology and environmental persistence <lb/>[21]. The molecular origins of these differences are not well <lb/>understood, but this ecological flexibility is likely indicative of a <lb/>dynamic, plastic genome with &apos;core&apos; and &apos;accessory&apos; components. <lb/>There are currently two publicly available annotated genomes for <lb/>these organisms: Pba strain SCRI1043 (Pba1043) [22], and Dickeya <lb/>dadantii strain 3937 (Dda3937; https://asap.ahabs.wisc.edu/; v6b). <lb/>The availability of these sequences has rapidly advanced our <lb/>understanding of these organisms, but broader comparisons are <lb/>expected to deliver greater insight into the evolution and function <lb/>of the SRE. <lb/>The major common virulence factors of the SRE are plant cell <lb/>wall degrading enzymes (PCWDE) that degrade the plant cell wall <lb/>to release nutrients in a so-called &apos;brute force&apos; attack [23–25]. Other <lb/>virulence factors include virulence-associated secretion systems, <lb/>siderophores, cell-surface polysaccharides and agglutinins [26,27]. <lb/>By contrast, bacterial plant pathogens such as Pseudomonas spp. <lb/>are associated with a biotrophic &apos;stealth&apos; interaction with the host. <lb/>These &apos;stealth&apos; pathogens employ mechanisms such as the type III <lb/>secretion system (T3SS) to translocate effectors into host cells. The <lb/>effectors modulate the host plant&apos;s biochemical responses, <lb/>implementing a wide array of strategies to circumvent host <lb/>immunity [28–31]. However, Pba1043, Dda3937, and other SREs <lb/>also encode a functioning T3SS and other gene products <lb/>associated with this &apos;stealth&apos; interaction, indicating a more <lb/>complex relationship with their hosts than simple &apos;brute-force&apos; <lb/>necrotrophy [22,32–36]. Key factors with a confirmed role in <lb/>virulence include type IV and type VI secretion systems, and the <lb/>phytotoxin coronafacic acid (CFA), which is synthesised by the cfa <lb/> gene cluster [22,37]. Other factors associated with persistence in, <lb/>and adaptation to, the wider environment have been identified, <lb/>such as genes associated with opine uptake, biofilm formation, <lb/>antibiotic production, and nitrogen fixation [22]. <lb/>In many bacteria, such genes associated with pathogenicity, and <lb/>other phenotypically-distinguishing characters, are frequently <lb/>associated with islands of horizontal gene transfer (HGT). This <lb/>gene complement is often variable between strains and species, <lb/>and is sometimes termed the &apos;accessory genome&apos;, in order to <lb/>distinguish it from the &apos;core genome&apos; that provides functionality <lb/>presumed to be essential to all related organisms [5,9,22,38–40]. <lb/>We expect that observed differences between the gene comple-<lb/>ments of SRE will reflect differences in their phenotypes, and <lb/>adaptations to their distinct environments, and that these <lb/>differences will be preferentially located in islands of genes in <lb/>their genomes. We use aCGH and apply our analysis method to <lb/>identify genomic islands in Pba1043 that do not have putative <lb/>orthologues in the unsequenced Pba strain SCRI1039 (Pba1039) <lb/>and Pcc strain SCRI193 (Pcc193), and in the sequenced Dda3937. <lb/> In this study, coding sequences (CDS) from Pba1043 that are <lb/>predicted by aCGH to be absent or divergent in Pba1039, Pcc193 <lb/> or Dda3937 are of interest because they may potentially contribute <lb/>to Pba1043-specific phenotypes, including host interactions. <lb/>Pairwise comparisons between Pba1043 and these three organisms <lb/>span a range of evolutionary distances since their most recent <lb/>common ancestor with Pba1043, and represent variation at strain, <lb/>species and genus levels. <lb/>Our results for the SRE support a hypothesis that the genomes <lb/>of SRE continue to be modified by the acquisition of genomic <lb/>islands, and the model of an &apos;accessory genome&apos; of niche-specific <lb/>functionality that is composed, at least in part, of horizontally-<lb/>acquired genomic islands. We identify major differences in the <lb/>CDS carried within the accessory genomes of SRE and, while <lb/>these recapitulate previous observations of major genomic islands <lb/>made using alternative approaches [22,38], we also find a number <lb/>of unexpected differences that provide insight into, and may play a <lb/>direct role in determining, variation amongst the SRE in terms of <lb/>their environmental survival, host range and aetiology. <lb/> Materials and Methods <lb/> Genome Sequences and Annotations <lb/> Annotated genome sequences were obtained from GenBank for <lb/> Pba1043 (accession: NC_004547), Lactococcus lactis subsp. lactis <lb/> Il1403 (accession: NC_002662), and L. lactis subsp. cremoris <lb/> MG1363 (accession: NC_009004). Equivalent data for Dda3937 <lb/> was obtained from ASAP (https://asap.ahabs.wisc.edu/; v6b). <lb/>CDS annotations from these sources were not modified for this <lb/>study. <lb/> Author Summary <lb/> We describe the first use of a method for the analysis of <lb/>bacterial microarray comparative genomic hybridisation <lb/>(aCGH) that includes information about the spatial <lb/>organisation of genes in the reference bacterium. We <lb/>demonstrate that using this information improves predic-<lb/>tive performance over standard bacterial aCGH methods in <lb/>discriminating between genes from the reference organ-<lb/>ism that either do or do not have putative orthologues in <lb/>the comparator organism. Our approach produces good <lb/>results on more distantly related bacteria than can <lb/>successfully be analysed by the standard methods. We <lb/>apply our analysis to comparisons between four commer-<lb/>cially-significant plant pathogenic bacteria, and identify <lb/>several regions of the genome that are likely to contribute <lb/>to their ability to cause disease, and to proliferate in the <lb/>environment, generating hypotheses for future experi-<lb/>ments. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>2 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			Identification of Putative Orthologues <lb/>Putative orthologues of bacterial CDS were identified using <lb/>reciprocal best hit (RBH) analyses. RBH were identified by using <lb/>each annotated CDS from the reference genome as the query in a <lb/>sequence search against the comparator genome, and vice versa. A <lb/>RBH was called when the best match to a query sequence had the <lb/>query sequence as its own best match in the reciprocal comparison <lb/>[see also 22,38]. For protein comparisons, FASTA 3.4t25 was <lb/>used, and BLASTN 2.2.11 was used for nucleotide comparisons. <lb/>Reciprocal best hits were interpreted as putative orthologues, and <lb/>converted to Boolean &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent&apos; states for model <lb/>development and training. We would usually employ a threshold <lb/>for RBH of a minimum of 30% identity over a minimum of 80% <lb/>of the sequence length for protein comparisons. However, for this <lb/>analysis we relaxed both criteria completely, and considered the <lb/>best hit in each direction without such a filter. The division of <lb/>CDS into &apos;present&apos;/&apos;absent&apos; classes on the basis of RBH without <lb/>these thresholds corresponds to a strict classifier for allocating <lb/>CDS to the &apos;absent&apos; class. <lb/>Under the usual circumstances in which we perform these <lb/>comparative analyses, we wish to exclude weak reciprocal matches <lb/>from the &apos;present&apos; set in order to avoid inappropriate attribute <lb/>transfer or assignment. In those cases, we would implement this <lb/>filter to minimise misallocation of CDS to the &apos;present/putative <lb/>orthologue&apos; class. <lb/>However, in the case of this aCGH analysis, as we note that <lb/>probes to reference organism sequences that have little or no <lb/>sequence identity to the comparator may still give very high <lb/>hybridisation strengths/ratios, we wish preferentially to avoid <lb/>misallocation of CDS to the &apos;absent&apos; class. Therefore, we aim in <lb/>effect to give each reference sequence every possible opportunity <lb/>to be classified as &apos;present&apos; as a putative orthologue in the <lb/>comparator on the basis of RBH. Any remaining reference CDS <lb/>that are classified as &apos;absent&apos; -even though no restrictions are <lb/>made on the basis of sequence identity or match overlap – have no <lb/>reciprocal similarity by BLAST to any sequence in the <lb/>comparator. <lb/> Microarray Data: Acquisition <lb/> Genomic DNA was extracted from bacterial cell cultures <lb/>(,10 10 cells) using the QIAGEN Genomic-tip 100/G (Qiagen) <lb/>as recommended and labelling was performed using modified <lb/>Bioprime DNA Labelling System (Invitrogen). Briefly, 2 mg gDNA <lb/>in 21 ml was added to 20 ml random primer reaction buffer mix <lb/>and denatured at boiling for 5 min prior to cooling on ice. To this, <lb/>5 ml modified 106 dNTP mix (1.2 mM each of dATP, dGTP, <lb/>dTTP; 0.6 mM dCTP; 10 mM Tris pH 8.0; 1 mM EDTA), 3 ml <lb/> of either Cy3 or Cy5 dCTP (1 mM) and 1 ml Klenow enzyme was <lb/>added and incubated for 16 h at 37uC. Labelled samples for each <lb/>array were combined (if applicable) and unincorporated dyes <lb/>removed using Qiaquick PCR Purification Kit (Qiagen) as <lb/>recommended, eluting twice with 1650 ml sterile water. Hybrid-<lb/>isations and washing were performed as recommended (Agilent <lb/>Protocol v5.5). Genomic DNA from Dda3937 was hybridised to a <lb/> Pba1043-specific microarray (ArrayExpress: E-TABM-600; man-<lb/>ufactured by Agilent, AMADID 012663) carrying 5219 unique <lb/>probes that represent 4450/4472 annotated CDS from the <lb/> Pba1043 genome [37,41]. Hybridisations were carried out in the <lb/>presence of Pba1043 reference gDNA, Pcc193 reference gDNA <lb/>and in the absence of a reference sample, and all hybridisations <lb/>were replicated three times. Scanning was performed with an <lb/>Agilent G2505B scanner using default settings and data extracted <lb/>using Agilent FE (AGFE) software v9.5.3. <lb/> Microarray Data: Processing <lb/> Raw hybridisation data was imported using MatLab (http:// <lb/>www.mathworks.com) from AGFE format output (Pba1043 array), <lb/>and from GEO (Lactococcus comparison data, entries: GSM229601, <lb/>GSM229602, GSM229603, GSM229604) [13]. GEO entries <lb/>229602 and 229604 were found to have the labels for channel 1 <lb/>and 2 inverted, and this was corrected in processing. Raw <lb/>hybridisation data was corrected for background signal, log-<lb/>transformed in base 2, then quantile-normalised. Median values <lb/>were calculated for replicate probes on each array, and then <lb/>between replicate arrays. Normalised hybridisation scores were <lb/>associated with a RBH result for each CDS. <lb/> Gaussian Mixture Models <lb/> Two-dimensional Gaussian mixture models were fitted in <lb/>MatLab to the paired hybridisation and RBH data using the <lb/>gmdistribution.fit function. The optimal number of fitted Gaus-<lb/>sians was estimated by the Bayesian Information Criterion (BIC), <lb/>considering a maximum of ten Gaussians. <lb/> Threshold Models <lb/> Threshold models were implemented such that each CDS with <lb/>a normalised array hybridisation score (or ratio) that fell below the <lb/>threshold was classified as &apos;absent&apos;; those with a normalised <lb/>hybridisation score above that value were classified as &apos;present&apos;. <lb/>These Boolean states were used for validation of threshold models, <lb/>and for training of HMMs. Threshold scores were taken at 100 <lb/>evenly-spaced values between the lowest and highest observed <lb/>values of hybridisation score (or ratio) for data exploration, and at <lb/>all observed normalised threshold values (exhaustively to explore <lb/>all partitions of the data) for rigorous comparisons with alternative <lb/>models. <lb/> Hidden Markov Model (HMM) Construction <lb/> First-order hidden Markov models were trained using MatLab&apos;s <lb/>hmmestimate function, given the Boolean &apos;present&apos;/&apos;absent&apos; states <lb/>derived from reciprocal best hit analysis ordered naturally along <lb/>the reference genome as a ground truth, and Boolean &apos;present&apos;/ <lb/>&apos;absent&apos; states derived from the threshold models as observed <lb/>emission states. The derived models represent the presence or <lb/>absence of a putative orthologue in the comparator sequence as <lb/>hidden states, in conjunction with the observed hybridisation score <lb/>being above or below the corresponding normalised hybridisation <lb/>score threshold, as the emitted states. The resulting models were <lb/>used to obtain predicted hidden states from hybridisation data <lb/>using the Viterbi algorithm implemented in MatLab&apos;s hmmviterbi <lb/>function, where input data were again ordered naturally according <lb/>to probe location on the reference genome. <lb/>HMMs used in this study were trained separately on the RBH <lb/>and hybridisation data for two comparisons: Pba1043 and <lb/> Dda3937; and Lactococcus lactis subspecies lactis IL1403 and cremoris <lb/> MG1363 [13]. <lb/> GACK and MPP <lb/> The packages GACK and MPP were obtained from their home-<lb/>pages (http://falkow.stanford.edu/whatwedo/software/software. <lb/>html; http://cbr.jic.ac.uk/dicks/software/mpp/index.html), and <lb/>used as recommended in their documentation [15,16]. Array <lb/>hybridisation data was converted to the appropriate input format in <lb/>each case using Python scripts. GACK binary and trinary data used <lb/>in this study was obtained at %EPP cutoffs of 0%, 50%, and 100%, <lb/>with all other settings at default values. MPP data used in this study <lb/>was obtained with default settings. <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>3 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			Model Validation <lb/> All predictive models were validated against the ground truth of <lb/>reciprocal best hit results for Pba1043 vs Dda3937 or the two Lactococcus <lb/> strains, as appropriate. All model output was obtained as Boolean <lb/>&apos;present&apos;/&apos;absent&apos; states, and validation statistics were obtained for <lb/>consistency tests using MatLab&apos;s classperf function (http://www. <lb/>mathworks.com/access/helpdesk/help/toolbox/bioinfo/ref/classperf. <lb/>html). Predictions of the absence of a reference CDS in the comparator <lb/>organism were taken to be &apos;positive&apos; for statistical classification <lb/>purposes. The optimal HMM and threshold models identified by the <lb/>validation process were used for subsequent predictions on Pba1039 <lb/> and Pcc193 hybridisation data. <lb/> Identification of Regions of Divergent Genome <lb/>Composition <lb/> The software package alien_hunter was downloaded from <lb/>http://www.sanger.ac.uk/Software/analysis/alien_hunter/ and used <lb/>to identify regions of divergent genome composition, with recom-<lb/>mended settings. This application implements an interpolated variable <lb/>order motif method derived from the base composition of the <lb/>chromosome to detect regions of nucleotide bias, and a second-order <lb/>HMM for change-point detection [42]. <lb/> Empirical Statistical Tests <lb/> Empirical statistical testing of the association of predicted <lb/>genomic islands with regions of divergent genome composition as <lb/>predicted by alien_hunter, and with regions of manually-<lb/>annotated HGT, was carried out using the following procedure, <lb/>implemented in a Python script. <lb/>The locations of genomic islands predicted by HMM, by <lb/>alien_hunter, and detailed in the NC_004547 annotation were <lb/>obtained. These were each considered to represent independent, <lb/>non-overlapping genomic regions. The location of each of the <lb/>alien_hunter and NC_004547 regions was shuffled one thousand <lb/>times, to produce two sets of non-overlapping arrangements of <lb/>each, representing a random distribution of the predicted islands. <lb/>A count of the number of HMM-predicted genomic islands that <lb/>overlapped with each of the shuffled sets was taken, as a measure <lb/>of the expected number of overlaps that would be obtained if the <lb/>islands were randomly placed on the genome. The observed count <lb/>overlap count of the HMM predictions with the alien_hunter and <lb/>annotated islands was tested for significance using a Z-statistic. <lb/>A similar procedure was followed for determining whether <lb/>individual genes were located preferentially within predicted <lb/>islands. In this case, the gene locations were taken as static, and <lb/>genomic island predictions shuffled as non-overlapping regions <lb/>1000 times. A Z-statistic was again used to calculate significance of <lb/>the count of genes observed to be coincident with predicted <lb/>genomic islands. <lb/> Results <lb/> Reciprocal Best Hit Analysis Indicates That Approximately <lb/>One Third of All Pba1043 CDS Are Absent in Dda3937 <lb/> The genomes of Pba1043 and Dda3937 have been sequenced <lb/>and annotated [22] (https://asap.ahabs.wisc.edu/; v6b). CDS <lb/>were defined to be common to both bacteria if a putative <lb/>orthologue to a Pba1043 CDS could be found in the Dda3937 <lb/> annotation. This was determined for each CDS at the amino acid <lb/>level by reciprocal best FASTA protein match, and at the <lb/>nucleotide level by reciprocal best BLASTN match [22]. Each <lb/>reciprocal best hit (RBH) result was considered to be a putative <lb/>orthologue (hereafter used interchangeably with &apos;orthologue&apos;) and, <lb/>as a direct and exhaustive sequence comparison, to be the best <lb/>estimate of the presence or absence of Pba1043 CDS in Dda3937 <lb/> available for method validation. The results were used as both <lb/>reference and training data for aCGH analysis algorithms, in a <lb/>consistency test approach similar to that used in [4]. <lb/>Of 4450 Pba1043 CDS represented by probes on the <lb/>microarray, 451 were found to have RBH to Dda3937 at both <lb/>nucleotide and amino acid sequence levels. In addition, 2369/ <lb/>4450 Pba1043 CDS made RBH at the amino acid level only, and <lb/>7/4450 CDS only at the nucleotide level. For Pba1043 1623/4450 <lb/>CDS therefore have no putative orthologue in Dda3937, and it <lb/>may be considered that approximately one third of the Pba1043 <lb/> genome is not common with Dda3937 (Figure S1). Very few <lb/> Pba1043 CDS were found to be orthologous at the nucleotide, but <lb/>not the protein level (a pattern suggestive of positive selection); <lb/>however, many were orthologous at the protein, but not at the <lb/>nucleotide, level (suggestive of neutral drift). The &apos;core&apos; of CDS <lb/>with both protein and nucleotide-level orthologues was found to <lb/>comprise only around 10% of the Pba1043 genome. <lb/> Array Hybridisation Intensities Have a Complex <lb/>Relationship with Sequence Identity for Pba1043 and <lb/> Dda3937 Orthologues <lb/> Genomic DNA from Dda3937 was hybridised to a Pba1043-<lb/> specific microarray in the presence, independently, of Pba1043 <lb/> reference gDNA and Pcc193 reference gDNA, and also in the <lb/>absence of a reference sample. Three overlapping populations of <lb/>raw hybridisation strengths were observed in each experiment <lb/>(Figure 1). This pattern was similar to that observed in similar <lb/>experiments [12], and comprised: a strongly-binding population of <lb/> Pba1043 probes that bind to Dda3937 gDNA with hybridisation <lb/>strength comparable to their binding to Pba1043 gDNA; a weakly-<lb/>binding population of probes with lower hybridisation strength to <lb/> Dda3937 than to Pba1043 gDNA; and a population with either no <lb/> Figure 1. Probability density function curves of log-trans-<lb/>formed raw probe hybridisation intensities for the hybridisa-<lb/>tion of  Dda3937  gDNA to a  Pba1043  microarray. Curves are <lb/>plotted for hybridisation of Dda3937 gDNA in the absence of reference <lb/>gDNA (red), and cohybridised with Pba1043 reference gDNA (green), or <lb/>cohybridised with Pcc193 comparator gDNA (blue). Three major <lb/>populations of probe intensities are seen: strong hybridisation (intensity <lb/>peak at approximately 14 log units), weak hybridisation (peaks at 8–10 <lb/>log units), and very weak to no hybridisation (less than 25 log units). <lb/>Three replicates are indicated for each experiment. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.g001 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			detectable, or very weak, hybridisation to Dda3937 gDNA <lb/>(Figure 1). <lb/>This observation does not support the assumption commonly <lb/>made in aCGH analysis methods that there are two populations of <lb/>probes in a typical experiment: &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent or divergent&apos; <lb/>[e.g. 3,8,11,15,16]. Notably, there is no a priori indication that any <lb/>of the three observed populations in Figure 1 comprise &apos;present&apos;, <lb/>&apos;absent&apos; or &apos;divergent&apos; sequences. <lb/>A linear, or at least monotonic, relationship between the <lb/>observed hybridisation score and the sequence identity of CDS in <lb/>the reference and comparator organisms has previously been <lb/>proposed or observed for aCGH experiments [13,43,44]. We did <lb/>not observe such a relationship. Our data indicated a complex <lb/>relationship between sequence identity and probe hybridisation <lb/>affinity (or log ratio), from which three major populations of <lb/>probes could readily be distinguished (Figure 2). Those probes <lb/>representing Pba1043 sequences that made RBH with greater than <lb/>30% amino acid sequence identity in Dda3937 were considered <lb/>here to be putative orthologues and therefore may only be classed <lb/>as either &apos;present&apos; or &apos;divergent&apos;, according to the scheme <lb/>commonly used in aCGH analyses [e.g. 5,12,15,16]. The &apos;absent&apos; <lb/>sequence set in that scheme corresponds to Pba1043 CDS with no <lb/>putative orthologue in the comparator organism. <lb/>In the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison, probes matching ortho-<lb/>logous sequences could be resolved into two distinct populations <lb/>on the basis of hybridisation strength using Gaussian mixture <lb/>models, but not on the basis of their sequence identities (Figure 2A). <lb/>In particular, the distribution of putative orthologues was bimodal <lb/>with respect to hybridisation score or ratio, but was unimodal with <lb/>respect to sequence identity. Sequence divergence was measured <lb/>in terms of sequence identity, and it was not possible to distinguish <lb/>between &apos;present&apos; and &apos;divergent&apos; orthologues using hybridisation <lb/>data. The commonly-used &apos;absent or divergent&apos; classification is the <lb/>union of the sets of &apos;absent&apos; and &apos;divergent&apos; sequences; our data <lb/>does not support this distinction between &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent or <lb/>divergent&apos; probe sets. <lb/>Those probes corresponding to Pba1043 CDS that were not <lb/>found to have putative orthologues in Dda3937 (i.e. that are <lb/>&apos;absent&apos;) were observed to have hybridisation ratios that ranged <lb/>from no measurable hybridisation to very strong hybridisation, <lb/>and to take values on the full range of hybridisation ratios spanned <lb/>by both &apos;present&apos; and &apos;divergent&apos; CDS. The distribution of <lb/>hybridisation ratios for probes representing putative orthologues <lb/>overlapped to a great extent that of probes corresponding to CDS <lb/>with no orthologue (Figure 2B). <lb/>Similar results were obtained for nucleotide sequence compar-<lb/>isons, and for raw hybridisation scores (Figure S2). As can be seen <lb/>from Figure S2, the observed relationship between sequence <lb/>identity and hybridisation affinity is qualitatively almost identical <lb/>whether obtained using hybridisation intensity (univariate) data, or <lb/>hybridisation ratio (bivariate) data. The complexity of this <lb/>relationship is therefore not due to the use of a log-ratio summary <lb/>of the hybridisation signal. <lb/>Taken together, these results indicated that a distinction might <lb/>reasonably be drawn between &apos;putatively orthologous&apos; and <lb/>&apos;putatively non-orthologous&apos; CDS on the basis of aCGH, but <lb/>not between &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent or divergent&apos; CDS. <lb/> An Optimal HMM-Based Predictive Model Predicts Which <lb/> Pba1043 CDS Have No Orthologue in Dda3937 Better <lb/>Than an Optimal Threshold Model <lb/> Analytical models for aCGH based on a single threshold that <lb/>partitions CDS into &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent or divergent&apos; classes have <lb/>previously been shown to perform acceptably well under some <lb/> Figure 2. Scatterplot of RBH sequence identity and CDS count <lb/>against hybridisation ratio. A) Scatterplot of putative orthologue <lb/>(RBH) protein sequence identity against log-transformed probe <lb/>hybridisation ratio for Dda3937 gDNA cohybridised with Pba1043 <lb/> reference gDNA, for all probes. Sequences with no orthologue are <lb/>allocated zero sequence identity. Probe population density contours <lb/>derived from Gaussian mixture modelling are superimposed, and the <lb/>corresponding Gaussian mixture components are distinguished by <lb/>coloured points. Three major populations of probes are seen: a strongly <lb/>hybridising population centred at hybridisation ratio 0 and %ID 0.87; a <lb/>weakly-hybridising population at hybridisation ratio 23 and %ID 0.82; <lb/>and Pba1043 sequences that have no putative orthologue (red points <lb/>along the x-axis). Strongly-and weakly-hybridising probe sets each <lb/>cover a range of sequence identities from 30% to 100%, and the probes <lb/>representing sequences with no orthologues cover a range of <lb/>hybridisation ratios from 27 to 3. B) Bar plot of the count of CDS by <lb/>hybridisation ratio, where CDS are divided into two classes: those with a <lb/>putative orthologue (blue), and those without a putative orthologue <lb/>(red), as found by RBH analysis. Both classes of CDS span a similar range <lb/>of observed hybridisation ratios and overlap significantly. The set of <lb/>CDS with no putative orthologue includes the majority of CDS in the <lb/>lowest bin of hybridisation ratio. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.g002 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			circumstances [e.g. 5,44–46]. However, while the data obtained in <lb/>this study did not support that particular interpretation of the <lb/>partitioning of sequences, a threshold approach may still <lb/>distinguish successfully between reference CDS that do and do <lb/>not have a putative orthologue in the comparator organism. <lb/>The influence of horizontal gene transfer has been in many <lb/>cases to introduce islands of genes whose collective function <lb/>distinguishes the recipient organism from its close relatives, as part <lb/>of the &apos;accessory&apos; genome [5,9,22,38,39,47]. One notable <lb/>influence of HGT on the reference genome is to confer collocation <lb/>of transferred genes in that genome; such transferred genes may <lb/>additionally be expected not to have an orthologue in a given <lb/>comparator genome. In particular, it would be expected that, <lb/>where a reference genome CDS has been acquired by HGT of a <lb/>genomic island, it and its neighbours are less likely to have an <lb/>orthologue in a comparator genome than another CDS randomly <lb/>selected from the reference genome. Similarly, prokaryotic genes <lb/>are frequently collected into operons, collocated groups of <lb/>sequences that often work towards a common function. Loss of <lb/>function may thus entail loss of a collocated set of genes. We <lb/>implemented a HMM that exploits this anticipated collocation of <lb/>sequences on the reference genome, particularly if they have no <lb/>orthologue in the comparator, in the expectation that taking into <lb/>account this spatial bias would improve predictive performance in <lb/>the presence of data noise, and in marginal cases that are difficult <lb/>to resolve with only a single threshold-based predictor. Such cases <lb/>might include genes with an unexpected level of redundancy in the <lb/>comparator organism, such as those with variable copy number <lb/>due to representation on plasmids [5]. <lb/>Threshold and HMM models (as defined in Materials and <lb/>Methods) were constructed for all hybridisation scores and ratios <lb/>observed in each array experiment, exhaustively enumerating all <lb/>such models that could be constructed from the data. All possible <lb/>outcomes of each method were thus obtained, facilitating general <lb/>claims concerning their performance on this data. In each <lb/>experiment, a threshold model could be obtained that performed <lb/>acceptably well when distinguishing between Pba1043 CDS that <lb/>do and do not have putative orthologues in Dda3937. However, <lb/>the optimally performing HMM outperformed the optimally <lb/>performing threshold model on measures of correct prediction rate <lb/>and specificity, in consistency tests for all such experiments <lb/>(Table 1). <lb/>It was observed that HMMs and threshold models constructed <lb/>from experiments involving reference gDNA performed significant-<lb/>ly better than those constructed from experiments where no <lb/>reference gDNA was used. Also, models built using log hybridisation <lb/>ratios performed better than those derived from single-channel raw <lb/>hybridisation scores (Table 1). Using log-transformed ratio data, the <lb/>threshold and HMM predictors predicted that similar total numbers <lb/>of CDS from Pba1043 did not have a putative orthologue in <lb/> Dda3937 (HMM: 1179; threshold: 1191; in silico analysis: 1630) but <lb/>differed in their classification of 372 (approximately 30%) of these <lb/>CDS. The predictions made by the two approaches differ <lb/>qualitatively, rather than quantitatively (Figure 3). The HMM <lb/>predictions appear to form larger contiguous islands of CDS on the <lb/>genome, while the threshold method predicts a greater number of <lb/>&apos;orphan&apos; CDS with no orthologue whose immediate neighbours are <lb/>predicted to have orthologues, and splits several large islands <lb/>(confirmed as single islands by in silico sequence comparison) into <lb/>several smaller fragments. <lb/>Additionally, the behaviour of each model is seen to differ as the <lb/>hybridisation ratio threshold varies from the minimum to <lb/>maximum observed value. Both models predict a mixture of <lb/>CDS with and without orthologues in the comparator at low <lb/>hybridisation ratios, but at high ratios the threshold model predicts <lb/>that all Pba1043 CDS are without an orthologue in Dda3937. At <lb/>high hybridisation ratio thresholds, the HMM assigns the majority <lb/>state for the data to all CDS (Figure S3). Also, &apos;blocks&apos; of <lb/>contiguous sequences with no orthologue in the comparator persist <lb/>to higher hybridisation ratios, using the HMM approach. <lb/> HMM-Based Predictors Validated on Pba1043:Dda3937 <lb/> and Lactococcus lactis aCGH Data Perform Better Than <lb/>GACK or MPP <lb/> Two packages for analysis of bacterial aCGH data are GACK <lb/>(perhaps the most widely-used such application) and MPP, <lb/>amongst a wide range of proposed alternative aCGH analysis <lb/>algorithms [10,15,16,48–52]. Nearly all of these methods make the <lb/>assumption that array probes partition into &apos;present&apos; and &apos;absent <lb/>or divergent&apos; classes, and that these classes are unimodal. It was <lb/>seen that this assumption is not met in the Pba1043:Dda3937 <lb/> comparison but, as for the threshold-based classification, it is likely <lb/>that these applications are able to segregate CDS from Pba1043 <lb/> that do have orthologues in Dda3937 from those that do not. <lb/>We applied GACK and MPP to the same log hybridisation ratio <lb/>data for the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison that was most <lb/>informative for both the HMM and threshold methods above. <lb/>In GACK it is possible to modify the required stringency of the <lb/>prediction by varying a parameter representing &apos;&apos;estimated <lb/>probability of presence&apos;&apos; (EPP). This may be set at values ranging <lb/>from 0% -indicating an expectation of statistical &apos;certainty&apos; that <lb/>CDS predicted to have no orthologue in the comparator organism <lb/>truly have no such orthologue -to 100% -indicating an <lb/>expectation of statistical &apos;certainty&apos; that CDS predicted to have <lb/>an orthologue in Dda3937 truly do have such an orthologue. <lb/>GACK was applied with EPP values of 0%, 50% and 100%, in <lb/>binary prediction mode. With these settings, GACK predicted that <lb/>84 (0% EPP), 344 (50% EPP) or 595 (100% EPP) CDS from <lb/> Pba1043 have no putative orthologue in Dda3937 (Figure S4). <lb/> Table 1. Consistency test validation statistics for Pba1043:Dda3937 aCGH comparisons. <lb/> Prediction method <lb/>Data used <lb/>Reference gDNA <lb/>Correct Positive Rate <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>Specificity <lb/> Threshold <lb/>hybridisation intensity <lb/>None <lb/>0.6672 <lb/>0.9592 <lb/>0.1620 <lb/>Threshold <lb/>hybridisation intensity <lb/> Pba1043 <lb/> 0.7587 <lb/>0.8943 <lb/>0.5239 <lb/>Threshold <lb/>log hybridisation ratio <lb/> Pba1043 <lb/> 0.7715 <lb/>0.8975 <lb/>0.5534 <lb/>HMM <lb/>hybridisation intensity <lb/>None <lb/>0.6952 <lb/>0.9585 <lb/>0.2399 <lb/>HMM <lb/>hybridisation intensity <lb/> Pba1043 <lb/> 0.7715 <lb/>0.9078 <lb/>0.5355 <lb/>HMM <lb/>log hybridisation ratio <lb/> Pba1043 <lb/> 0.7796 <lb/>0.9060 <lb/>0.5607 <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.t001 <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>6 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note> 
			
			Figure 3. Predictions of putative orthology for aCGH comparisons. Predictions of putative orthology for the Pba1043:Dda3937 aCGH <lb/>comparison using log-transformed hybridisation ratios, for both threshold (left) and HMM (right) methods, compared to the locations of known <lb/>orthologues obtained by in silico comparison (centre). CDS are in genomic order from top to bottom of the figure, and black bars indicate CDS from <lb/> Pba1043 with no orthologue in Dda3937. For the in silico comparison, a brighter copper tone indicates greater sequence identity for that orthologue. <lb/>The threshold and HMM results are similar, and broadly consistent with each other and the in silico analysis. The two prediction methods differ <lb/>qualitatively in that the HMM method tends to predict larger contiguous islands of CDS with no orthologue than the threshold method, which <lb/>predicts a greater number of CDS &apos;orphans&apos;, as illustrated by the inset that expands the region surrounding HAI2. This region contains the coronafacic <lb/>acid synthesis cfa gene cluster. The RBH comparisons for this island indicate two putative orthologues in Pba1043 and Dda3937, effectively breaking <lb/>the island into three smaller islands. The threshold method identifies five larger contiguous putative shared CDS, dividing the island into six smaller <lb/>regions. The HMM method identifies the island as a single large contiguous region, with no breaks. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.g003 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>7 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note> 
			
			MPP with default settings predicted that no Pba1043 CDS were <lb/>without a putative orthologue in Dda3937 – the majority state -and <lb/>thereby achieved a correct prediction rate of 0.65. Although GACK <lb/>obtained a correct prediction rate of 0.75 at 100% EPP, its sensitivity <lb/>was very low and, unlike the threshold and HMM methods, neither <lb/>GACK nor MPP identified a substantial proportion of the 1630 <lb/> Pba1043 CDS that do not have an orthologue in Dda3937. <lb/> Validation statistics for these analyses are shown in Table 2, and <lb/>indicate that the HMM outperformed both GACK and MPP on the <lb/> Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison in terms of sensitivity and total <lb/>number of correct predictions, although GACK obtained better <lb/>positive predictive rates at the expense of much reduced sensitivity. <lb/>It is possible that the less impressive performance of GACK and <lb/>MPP observed for the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison was due to <lb/>the relatively large evolutionary distance between these organisms, <lb/>or to the particular array configuration used in these experiments <lb/>(see Discussion). Most aCGH studies have hitherto focused on <lb/>variation at the subspecies level, and this is the domain on which <lb/>GACK and MPP have previously been and, it was assumed, were <lb/>intended to be, applied [5,9,13,15,16]. In order to compare the <lb/>performance of the HMM to GACK and MPP on a comparison of <lb/>sequenced bacteria with a more recent common ancestor, data for <lb/>aCGH between Lactococcus lactis subspecies lactis IL1403 and <lb/> cremoris MG1363 [13], employing an alternative array platform, <lb/>was obtained from the GEO public repository. The HMM <lb/>approach again outperformed both GACK and MPP in terms of <lb/>sensitivity, correct positive rate, and positive predictive rate on this <lb/>comparison data (Table 2). Although GACK more closely <lb/>approximated the number of non-orthologous sequences in its <lb/>predictions, its false positive rate was found to be rather high. <lb/> Comparison of HMM-Based, GACK and MPP Model <lb/>Performance on Pba1043:Pcc193 and Pba1043:Pba1039 <lb/> Data <lb/> Pcc193 and Pba1039 gDNA was hybridised to the Pba1043-<lb/> specific microarray, in separate experiments, using Pba1043 gDNA <lb/>as the reference in each. The distribution of log hybridisation <lb/>ratios was found to be approximately unimodal in both cases, <lb/>reflecting the relatively close evolutionary relationship between <lb/>these organisms (data not shown). <lb/>MPP, with default settings, was unable to fit curves to the <lb/>hybridisation data from the Pba1043:Pcc193 experiment, and so its <lb/>performance was not further assessed. The HMM trained on <lb/> Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison data predicted that 440 Pba1043 <lb/> CDS have no orthologue in Pcc193. GACK predicted that between <lb/>1187 (EPP: 0%) and 1846 (EPP: 100%) Pba1043 CDS have no <lb/>orthologue in Pcc193. As noted earlier, in silico sequence compar-<lb/>isons indicated that 1643 Pba1043 CDS have no orthologue in <lb/> Dda3937, whose most recent common ancestor with Pba1043 is <lb/>more ancient than that of Pba1043 and Pcc193. It would therefore <lb/>be expected that more Pba1043 CDS would have orthologues in <lb/> Pcc193, than in Dda3937. This implies that the GACK prediction <lb/>for the Pcc193 comparison at 100% EPP is an overprediction. There <lb/>was also a large discrepancy between the prediction count from <lb/>HMM and the most conservative GACK prediction at 0% EPP, in <lb/>that GACK predicted nearly three times as many CDS to be <lb/>without an orthologue in Pcc193 than did the HMM. <lb/>The Pba1043:Pba1039 comparison experiment was a comparison <lb/>between reference and comparator organisms at the strain level. The <lb/>HMM built from the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison data may be <lb/>inappropriate for analysis of more closely-related organisms, and so the <lb/>second HMM, trained separately on the Lactococcus comparison data, <lb/>was also tested. MPP predicted that 299 Pba1043 CDS have no orth-<lb/>ologue in Pba1039, and GACK predicted between 335 (EPP: 0%) and <lb/>637 (EPP: 100%) such CDS. The HMM built on the more divergent <lb/> Pba1039:Dda3937 comparison predicted 198, and the HMM built on <lb/>the more recently-diverged Lactococcus comparison predicted 255 such <lb/>CDS. The variation in prediction totals between the HMMs built on <lb/>the two distinct comparisons is not as great as the variation between the <lb/>HMM predictions and those made by GACK and MPP, and the <lb/>predictions made by the HMMs are each in close agreement, implying <lb/>that the HMM approach is reasonably robust to training set variation, <lb/>independent of the organism on which it was trained (Figure S5). <lb/>While no genome sequences were publicly available at the time of <lb/>submission to validate these particular predictions, some trends may <lb/>be inferred from this data. GACK appeared to predict a greater <lb/>number of CDS to be absent than did the HMM. This behaviour, <lb/>which potentially results in an increase in sensitivity at the expense <lb/>of specificity, has previously been reported by other groups [e.g. 5]. <lb/>Qualitatively, both GACK and MPP predicted a greater proportion <lb/> Table 2. Statistics for validation of aCGH analytical methods on Pba1043:Dda3937 and Lactococcus comparisons. <lb/> Analysis Method <lb/>Correct Prediction Rate <lb/>Positive Prediction Rate <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>Count <lb/> Pba1043:Dda3937 <lb/> 1630 <lb/>HMM (Pba1043:Dda3937) <lb/>0.7796 <lb/>0.7752 <lb/>0.5607 <lb/>1179 <lb/>GACK (0% EPP) <lb/>0.6512 <lb/>0.9642 <lb/>0.0497 <lb/>84 <lb/>GACK (50% EPP) <lb/>0.7011 <lb/>0.9360 <lb/>0.1975 <lb/>344 <lb/>GACK (100%EPP) <lb/>0.7355 <lb/>0.8807 <lb/>0.3214 <lb/>595 <lb/>MPP (BPP) <lb/>0.6337 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0 <lb/>MPP (EPP) <lb/>0.6337 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0 <lb/> Lactococcus lactis <lb/> 379 <lb/>HMM (Lactococcus) <lb/>0.8404 <lb/>0.7253 <lb/>0.1741 <lb/>91 <lb/>GACK (0% EPP) <lb/>0.8210 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0.0000 <lb/>0 <lb/>GACK (50% EPP) <lb/>0.7616 <lb/>0.2418 <lb/>0.1557 <lb/>244 <lb/>GACK (100%EPP) <lb/>0.7616 <lb/>0.2418 <lb/>0.1557 <lb/>244 <lb/>MPP (BPP) <lb/>0.8220 <lb/>1.0000 <lb/>0.0053 <lb/>2 <lb/>MPP (EPP) <lb/>0.8210 <lb/>0.5000 <lb/>0.0053 <lb/>4 <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.t002 <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			of &apos;orphan&apos; CDS, while the HMM favoured prediction of islands of <lb/>CDS with no orthologue in the comparator (Figure S5). This may <lb/>be a more biologically appropriate prediction mode. <lb/>We observed apparent overprediction, combined with reduced <lb/>sensitivity and diminished correct positive prediction rates for the <lb/>GACK and MPP methods, in comparison to the HMM approach. <lb/>We also found that variation in results between HMMs built on <lb/>alternative training sets is minor. Thus we proceeded to consider the <lb/>biological implications of aCGH results obtained for the Pectobacterium <lb/> and Dickeya species investigated, using only results obtained using the <lb/>HMM analysis model built from the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison. <lb/> The HMM-Based Predictive Model Predicts Genomic <lb/>Islands in Pba1043 That Correspond to Putative <lb/> Pectobacterium atrosepticum-Specific and <lb/> Pectobacterium-Specific &apos;Accessory&apos; Genomes <lb/> HMM analysis predicted 165 islands (1179 CDS) from Pba1043 <lb/> to have no orthologues in Dda3937, 60 islands (440 CDS) to have <lb/>no orthologues in Pcc193, and 17 islands (198 CDS) to have no <lb/>orthologues in Pba1039. This method also identified 16 islands <lb/>(169 CDS) that were unique to Pba1043 only, and a further 40 <lb/>islands (231 CDS) to be present only in Pba1043 and Pba1039. The <lb/>count of genomic islands and CDS with no orthologue in the <lb/>comparator diminished as the evolutionary distance from the last <lb/>common ancestor of Pba1043 to the comparator decreased. These <lb/>islands are illustrated in Figure 4 and Figure S6, and described in <lb/>detail in Tables S1, S2, S3, S4 and S5. <lb/>We considered those CDS that are present in Pba1043 but that <lb/>do not have orthologues in the most recently diverged organism in <lb/>this study: Pba1039, to reflect either recent acquisitions in Pba1043 <lb/> or recent losses in Pba1039. These CDS are a putative Pba1043-<lb/> specific &apos;accessory&apos; genome, and mostly comprise hypothetical <lb/>proteins and phage-related sequences, located in 17 islands on the <lb/> Pba1043 genome (Table S1; islands prefixed Pba1039I). <lb/>Fifty-six islands of Pba1043 CDS were predicted to be present <lb/>only in Pba1043, or to be common to both Pba strains, but not to <lb/>have orthologues in either Dda3937 or Pcc193. These are likely to <lb/>represent genes encoding functions that biochemically distinguish <lb/> Pba from its near evolutionary relatives. Such sequences included <lb/>CDS encoding coronafacic acid synthesis (cfa), phenazine antibiotic <lb/>synthesis (ehp), and various multidrug resistance genes. Several of <lb/>these CDS, in particular those for the synthesis of coronafacic acids <lb/>(CFA) have also previously been shown experimentally to contribute <lb/>to virulence in Pba1043 [22]. These CDS were predicted to be <lb/>components of the putative Pba-specific &apos;accessory&apos; genome, and <lb/>some examples are summarised in Table 3. A substantial minority of <lb/>these CDS were annotated only as hypothetical proteins in their <lb/>public sequence database submissions (Table S2). <lb/>One-hundred and sixty-eight islands of Pba1043 CDS were <lb/>predicted to have orthologues in both Pcc193 and Pba1039 but not <lb/>in Dda3937, and thus represent a putative Pectobacterium-specific <lb/> accessory genome. These islands are expected to include genes <lb/>encoding functions that distinguish pectobacteria from Dickeya <lb/> spp., and were found to contain CDS encoding PCWDE (pel and <lb/> peh), a syringomycin-like NRPS (syr), siderophore biosynthesis (pvc) <lb/>and octopine transport (occ). <lb/> Sixteen of Seventeen Previously Annotated, Horizontally <lb/>Acquired Islands from Pba1043 Are Coincident with <lb/>Islands of CDS with No Predicted Orthologue in Pcc193 <lb/> and/or Dda3937 <lb/> Seventeen putative horizontally acquired islands (HAI1-HAI17) <lb/>were identified in manual curation of the Pba1043 genome on the <lb/>basis of evidence such as divergent base composition and the <lb/>presence of flanking insertion sequences [22]. Of these, all but <lb/>HAI1 coincided with at least one island identified by aCGH, and <lb/>most include genes with putative or demonstrated roles in <lb/>pathogenesis and niche adaptation [38] (Table 4). <lb/>Two of these islands, HAI1 (capsular polysaccharide biosyn-<lb/>thesis) and HAI15 (type I secretion) were predicted to be entirely <lb/>or substantially conserved in all organisms examined in this study. <lb/>If the shared presence of each of these two islands is the result of <lb/>horizontal gene transfer, then the most parsimonious inference is <lb/>that acquisition occurred in a common ancestor of all three <lb/>species, rather than as independent transfer events in each <lb/>organism. <lb/>Two HAIs were predicted to have substantial orthologues only <lb/>within the pectobacteria: the portion of HAI2 that is homologous <lb/>with the SPI-7 pathogenicity island (PAI) flanking the coronafacic <lb/>acid synthesis genes (the cfa genes themselves have no orthologues in <lb/> Pcc193), and HAI6, which encodes a syringomycin-like NRPS. A <lb/>parsimonious explanation for this distribution might be that these <lb/>islands were acquired after the divergence of Dickeya and <lb/> Pectobacterium spp. but before the divergence of Pcc and Pba species; <lb/>alternatively, there may have been loss of these islands in the Dickeya <lb/> lineage. However, the PAI itself has been observed in several <lb/>unrelated bacterial genomes, and found to contain multiple <lb/>alternative functional &apos;payloads&apos; in those cases [53,54]. As the PAI <lb/>genes, but not their cfa &apos;cargo&apos; were predicted to be present in <lb/> Pcc193, it may be that there has been independent acquisition of this <lb/>sequence in Pba and Pcc, carrying alternative payloads in each case. <lb/>This may be determined by sequencing of that region in Pcc193. <lb/> Similarly, five HAIs (HAI3, HAI5, HAI10, HAI11 and HAI12) <lb/>were found only in the two Pba strains either substantially, or in <lb/>their entirety (Table 4; Table S2). These are expected to have been <lb/>acquired after the divergence of Pba from Pcc. Amongst the gene <lb/>functions carried by these HAIs are lipopolysaccharide biosynthe-<lb/>sis (rfb) and phenazine antibiotic synthesis (ehp). <lb/>A further five HAIs (HAI4, HAI7, HAI9, HAI13, and HAI17) <lb/>appeared to be substantially or entirely unique to Pba1043, but <lb/>these almost exclusively encode for phage-related sequences, and <lb/>hypothetical proteins. These were presumably recently acquired, <lb/>subsequent to the divergence of strain SCRI1043 from strain <lb/>SCRI1039. <lb/>HAI14, which putatively encodes nitrogen fixation function, is <lb/>anomalous in that it was predicted to have a substantial number of <lb/>orthologues in both Pba strains, and in Dda3937, but to have far <lb/>fewer orthologues in Pcc193. The most parsimonious explanation <lb/>for this distribution is that the common ancestor of Dickeya and <lb/> Pectobacterium possessed this capability for nitrogen fixation, and <lb/>that this has been progressively lost in the Pcc193 lineage. <lb/>Alternatively, nitrogen-fixing ability may have been acquired <lb/>independently in both Dickeya and Pba lineages. <lb/> Predicted Pba1043-Specific Genomic Islands Are <lb/>Associated with Regions of Divergent Genome <lb/>Composition <lb/> The software package alien_hunter [42] was used to identify <lb/>regions of putative HGT in the Pba1043 chromosome. An <lb/>empirical statistical method was used to determine whether there <lb/>was a significant association between Pba1043 CDS without <lb/>predicted orthologues in each comparator species and regions of <lb/>putative HGT as predicted by alien_hunter. <lb/>In total, alien_hunter identified regions of putative HGT <lb/>overlapping 731 CDS in Pba1043. These included 118/173 <lb/>CDS that were predicted by aCGH to be specific to Pba1043 (Z-<lb/>score 5.54; P,0.0001); 254/400 CDS predicted to be specific to <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>9 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			Pba strains (Z-score: 9.08, P,0.0001); 256/440 Pba1043 CDS <lb/>predicted to have no orthologue in Pcc193 (Z-score: 8.47, <lb/>P,0.0001); and 463/1179 CDS predicted to be have no <lb/>orthologue in Dda3937 (Z-score: 9.03, P,0.0001). This indicates <lb/>a significant tendency for Pba1043 CDS that are predicted to have <lb/>no orthologue in one or more comparator organisms to be located <lb/>within the regions of divergent base composition predicted by <lb/>alien_hunter. This is consistent with the hypothesis that the <lb/>composition of the &apos;accessory&apos; genome of Pba1043 is greatly <lb/>influenced by horizontal gene transfer. <lb/>A similar statistically significant association of predicted islands <lb/>of CDS in Pba1043 predicted to have no orthologue in at least one <lb/>comparator organism was observed with predicted regions of <lb/>putative HGT identified by alien_hunter. In total, 11/16 (Z-score: <lb/>3.86, P,0.0001) Pba1043-specific islands; 32/56 (Z-score: 6.29, <lb/>P,0.0001) Pba-specific islands; 32/60 (Z-score: 5.72, P,0.0001) <lb/>islands predicted to have no orthologue in Pcc193; and 50/165 (Z-<lb/>score: 2.39, P,0.01) islands predicted to have no orthologue in <lb/> Dda3937 were found to overlap with the regions of putative HGT <lb/>identified by alien_hunter. <lb/> Figure 4. Circular diagram of  Pba1043,  indicating predicted genomic islands. Circular diagram indicating, on the chromosome of Pba1043, <lb/> the locations of annotated horizontally-acquired islands (HAI); aCGH predictions of Pba1043 genomic islands that do not have orthologues in <lb/> Pba1039 (Pba1039I), Pcc193 (PccI), or Dda3937 (DdaI), or that are present only in Pba strains (PbaI); and predictions of divergent base composition <lb/>made by alien_hunter (labelled as IVOM). Chromosome features are coloured by functional classification. Predicted HAIs coincide with many of the <lb/>aCGH-predicted islands that themselves coincide with the predictions of divergent base composition made by alien_hunter. The DdaI islands are <lb/>numerous and distributed in clusters around the chromosome. Most islands not predicted to be found in Pcc193 are also not predicted to be found in <lb/> Dda3937. The diagram was constructed using GenomeDiagram [71]. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.g004 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			It is particularly notable that nearly three-quarters of all <lb/> Pba1043-specific islands also overlapped at least one region of <lb/>divergent base composition predicted by alien_hunter. This is <lb/>consistent with the proposal that these islands have been acquired <lb/>through lateral gene transfer subsequent to divergence of Pba1043 <lb/> and Pba1039 from their most recent common ancestor, suggesting <lb/>a dynamic genome plasticity that persists and distinguishes <lb/>between Pba strains [22]. <lb/> Table 3. Predicted genomic islands of potential functional importance. <lb/> Island <lb/>Locus tags <lb/>Genomic location <lb/>Putative phenotype, and representative genes <lb/> PbaI5 <lb/> ECA0487-ECA0491 <lb/> 563151-567396 <lb/>phosphonate metabolism (fom1, fom2, phnG) <lb/> PbaI7 <lb/> ECA0600-ECA0610 <lb/> 659712-682903 <lb/>coronafacic acid synthesis (cfa1-8B, cfl) <lb/> PbaI13 <lb/> ECA1420-ECA1441 <lb/> 1611940-1636204 <lb/>polysaccharide and O-antigen synthesis (rfb, nah) <lb/> PbaI14 <lb/> ECA1477-ECA1481 <lb/> 1673637-1678411 <lb/>transcriptional regulators <lb/>PbaI22 <lb/> ECA2068-ECA2073 <lb/> 2355814-2362568 <lb/>permease and transporter <lb/>PbaI27 <lb/> ECA2294-ECA2295 <lb/> 2599459-2602654 <lb/>glycosyl transferase <lb/>PbaI33 <lb/> ECA2693-ECA2705 <lb/> 3028797-3040751 <lb/>polyketide synthase, phenazine synthesis (ehpA-G, ehpR) <lb/> PbaI39 <lb/> ECA2933-ECA2936 <lb/> 3278434-3281122 <lb/>nitrogen fixation (nifQ) <lb/>PbaI41 <lb/> ECA2972-ECA2982 <lb/> 3322878-3332514 <lb/>multidrug efflux (emrE) <lb/>PbaI44 <lb/> ECA3446-ECA3450 <lb/> 3865038-3872587 <lb/>multidrug efflux (oprJ, mexBC, nfxB) <lb/> PbaI55 <lb/> ECA4452-ECA4455 <lb/> 4993334-5000237 <lb/>hemin storage (hms) <lb/>PectoI7 <lb/> ECA0149-ECA0163 <lb/> 169392-186544 <lb/>lipopolysaccharide synthesis (waa) <lb/>PectoI25-27 <lb/> ECA0516-ECA0615 <lb/> 590843-689677 <lb/>mobile element (SPI7-like) <lb/>PectoI50 <lb/> ECA1089-ECA1107 <lb/> 1217226-1255583 <lb/>cell wall enzymes (pel3, pehA), Type I secretion <lb/>PectoI61 <lb/> ECA1485-ECA1490 <lb/> 1680732-1681461 <lb/>syringomycin-like non-ribosomal peptide synthase (syrE) <lb/>PectoI82 <lb/> ECA2111-ECA2118 <lb/> 2398202-2426503 <lb/>type III effectors (dspE, hrpW), agglutinins (hecAB) <lb/>PectoI96 <lb/> ECA2430-ECA2438 <lb/> 2744003-2745227 <lb/>virulence regultors (rdgAB) <lb/>PectoI122 <lb/> ECA3116-ECA3122 <lb/> 3478243-3490068 <lb/>type I restriction <lb/>PectoI129 <lb/> ECA3370-ECA3387 <lb/> 3786824-3801913 <lb/>pyoverdine biosynthesis (pvc) <lb/>PectoI151 <lb/> ECA4078-ECA4084 <lb/> 4546706-4554057 <lb/>octopine transport (occQMP) <lb/>PectoI153 <lb/> ECA4109-ECA4119 <lb/> 4579773-4594107 <lb/>siderophore synthesis / receptor <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.t003 <lb/> Table 4. Horizontally acquired islands (HAI) previously identified in Pba1043. <lb/> HAI <lb/>Locus tags <lb/> Pba1039  Islands <lb/> Pcc193  Islands <lb/> Dda3937  Islands <lb/>Putative Phenotypes <lb/> HAI1 <lb/> ECA0499-ECA0510 <lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Capsular polysaccharide biosynthesis <lb/>HAI2 <lb/> ECA0516-ECA0614 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI6-PccI7 <lb/>DdaI24 <lb/>Polyketide phytotoxin cfa, SPI7 <lb/>HAI3 <lb/> ECA0665-ECA0678 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI8 <lb/>DdaI27 <lb/>Phage genes <lb/>HAI4 <lb/> ECA1054-ECA1067 <lb/> Pba1039I2-Pba1039I3 <lb/>PccI12 <lb/>DdaI44 <lb/>Phage genes/integrases <lb/>HAI5 <lb/> ECA1417-ECA1443 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI14 <lb/>DdaI55 <lb/>Exopolysaccharide and O-antigen biosynthesis (rfb, nah) <lb/> HAI6 <lb/> ECA1446-ECA1488 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI15 <lb/>DdaI56-DdaI58 <lb/>Syringomycin-like NRPS (syrE) <lb/>HAI7 <lb/> ECA1598-ECA1679 <lb/> Pba1039I4-Pba1039I6 <lb/>PccI18 <lb/>DdaI62 <lb/>Integrases, type IV secretion, arsenate resistance (ars) <lb/>HAI8 <lb/> ECA2045-ECA2182 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI24-PccI28 <lb/>DdaI76-DdaI84 <lb/>Type III secretion (hrp), agglutinins (hecAB) <lb/>HAI9 <lb/> ECA2598-ECA2637 <lb/> Pba1039I10-Pba1039I11 <lb/>PccI34-PccI35 <lb/>DdaI100-DdaI101 <lb/>P2 family prophage <lb/>HAI10 <lb/> ECA2694-ECA2705 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI36 <lb/>DdaI103 <lb/>Phenazine antibiotic biosynthesis (ehp) <lb/>HAI11 <lb/> ECA2750-ECA2759 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI37 <lb/>DdaI104 <lb/>Phage genes <lb/>HAI12 <lb/> ECA2850-ECA2879 <lb/> Pba1039I12 <lb/>PccI38-PccI40 <lb/>DdaI107-DdaI108 <lb/>Hypothetical, putative type VI substrate (vgrG) <lb/>HAI13 <lb/> ECA2889-ECA2921 <lb/> Pba1039I13 <lb/>PccI41 <lb/>DdaI109 <lb/>Putative integrated plasmid <lb/>HAI14 <lb/> ECA2922-ECA3000 <lb/> Pba1039I14 <lb/>PccI42-PccI44 <lb/>DdaI109-DdaI113 <lb/>Nitrogen fixation (nif) <lb/>HAI15 <lb/> ECA3262-ECA3270 <lb/> -<lb/>-<lb/>DdaI122 <lb/>Agglutination/adhesion (aggA) <lb/>HAI16 <lb/> ECA3378-ECA3460 <lb/> -<lb/>PccI45-PccI48 <lb/>DdaI124-DdaI128 <lb/>Multidrug resistance (mex-opr-nfxB) <lb/>HAI17 <lb/> ECA3695-ECA3742 <lb/> Pba1039I15 <lb/>PccI49-PccI51 <lb/>DdaI137-DdaI140 <lb/>Prophage <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.t004 <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			Several Predicted Genomic Islands Are Enhanced for CDS <lb/>with Reciprocal Best Hits in Plant-Associated Bacteria, But <lb/>Not in Animal-Pathogenic Enterobacteria <lb/> Each CDS in the Pba1043 chromosome was classified according <lb/>to whether a putative protein orthologue was found in completely <lb/>sequenced plant-associated bacteria (PAB), or in completely <lb/>sequenced animal-pathogenic enterobacteria (APE) [38]. Those <lb/>CDS that have at least one such orthologue in PAB, but none in <lb/>APE were considered potentially to encode a biochemical function <lb/>that is useful to a plant-associated lifestyle, but likely not to an <lb/>animal-associated lifestyle. A similar inference may be drawn for <lb/>CDS for which the Pba1043 sequence shares significantly greater <lb/>identity with its most similar PAB orthologue than it does with the <lb/>APE orthologue. As Pba1043 shares a more recent common <lb/>ancestor with APE such as Yersinia spp. and E. coli strains, such a <lb/>distribution of orthologous sequences may also imply acquisition <lb/>by HGT. <lb/>An empirical statistical test was performed to determine whether <lb/>genomic islands in Pba1043 identified by aCGH were enhanced <lb/>for such CDS. A significant enhancement was seen for 6/56 Pba-<lb/> specific islands, 6/60 islands with no orthologue in Pcc193, and 9/ <lb/>165 islands with no orthologue in Dda3937 (all tests Z-score.3.0; <lb/>P,0.001; Table S6). These islands may therefore represent <lb/>functions that are not only likely to have been acquired by lateral <lb/>gene transfer, but may also be specific to a plant-associated, and <lb/>not a generalist or animal-associated, lifestyle. Islands identified in <lb/>this way include PbaI7, which contains genes that encode for <lb/>coronafacic acid synthesis, and also a number of hypothetical <lb/>proteins (see Discussion). <lb/>This partitioning of sequences between &apos;core&apos; and &apos;accessory&apos; <lb/>regions of the bacterial genome, such that variable regions are <lb/>enhanced for strain-or niche-specific functions has also been <lb/>observed for other pathogenic bacteria, including P. syringae [9,39], <lb/>and appears to be a common strategy for the evolution of these <lb/>organisms. <lb/> Discussion <lb/> Array CGH Does Not Necessarily Distinguish between <lb/>&apos;Present&apos; and &apos;Absent or Divergent&apos; Sequences in a <lb/>Comparator Organism <lb/> Microarray comparative genomic hybridisation (aCGH) is a <lb/>valuable technique for rapidly, and relatively inexpensively, <lb/>obtaining comparative genomic data for bacterial strains in a <lb/>high-throughput manner. However, aCGH has inherent limitations <lb/>that restrict the applicability of the method, and the information <lb/>that can be obtained. Foremost is that an aCGH experiment is only <lb/>able to identify which reference probe sequences do or do not <lb/>hybridise well to gDNA from a comparator organism. In particular, <lb/>aCGH is unable positively to identify sequences that are present in <lb/>the comparator gDNA but that are absent from the reference or <lb/>otherwise unrepresented in the probe set. Thus aCGH is unable to <lb/>reflect sequences that are unique to the comparator organism. This <lb/>may be overcome to some degree by the use of arrays that contain <lb/>probes not only to the reference organism, but also to other related <lb/>organisms, as proposed in [5]. Here, the wider the scope of the <lb/>probes beyond the reference organism alone, the greater is the <lb/>theoretical coverage of sequences that may be present in the <lb/>comparator, but not in the reference organism. However, sequences <lb/>that are unique to the comparator still cannot be disclosed by this <lb/>approach unless they are present on the array. <lb/>It is commonly assumed that aCGH cannot distinguish between <lb/>sequences that are absent in the comparator gDNA, and those that <lb/>are merely sufficiently divergent that they cannot hybridise to the <lb/>array probe set [5,8, etc]. However, to some degree these <lb/>classifications are indistinguishable, as the statement that a <lb/>sequence is &apos;absent&apos; in a comparator can be equivalent to the <lb/>statement that there no significant sequence similarity. The use of <lb/>&apos;divergent&apos; as a classifier is ambiguous and potentially misleading <lb/>in these circumstances. It is also commonly assumed that the <lb/>assessment of &apos;absence or divergence&apos; reflects overall sequence <lb/>similarity, and that a relationship between hybridisation and <lb/>sequence similarity holds for intermediate levels of sequence <lb/>identity, such that intermediate hybridisation strengths reflect an <lb/>intermediate degree of sequence identity [13]. An important <lb/>observation made in [44] was that, even for closely-related <lb/>sequenced strains of Camplylobacter jejuni, the log ratio of each probe <lb/>was not sufficient to make a positive prediction of percentage <lb/>sequence identity. We confirm and extend this observation for <lb/>SRE with Agilent arrays. <lb/>It is often intuitively expected that microarray probes will <lb/>hybridise to comparator gDNA with a reduced signal, where the <lb/>comparator sequence is not identical with its homologue in the <lb/>reference. In all aCGH experiments hybridisation strength is a <lb/>measurement taken at the reference probe and not across the full <lb/>length of the sequence from either organism, unless the probe <lb/>covers the full length of the sequence. Where sequence identity is <lb/>not homogeneous across the full length of the sequence, or there is <lb/>similarity between the probe and a non-homologous sequence, this <lb/>expectation may break down. A comparable break down may <lb/>occur if there is the possibility of a confounding interaction <lb/>between hybridising reference and comparator gDNA to a probe. <lb/>Circumstances in which sequence divergence at the probe <lb/>hybridisation site is not representative of the overall divergence <lb/>across the sequence are highly likely to occur, and even under the <lb/>most favourable circumstances it is only possible to refer to the <lb/> apparent absence or divergence of sequences in the comparator <lb/>organism. <lb/>Most published approaches to interpretation of aCGH data <lb/>assume that probes which hybridise strongly to comparator gDNA <lb/>represent sequences that are present in the comparator organism, <lb/>while those probes that do not hybridise well represent sequences <lb/>that may be either absent or divergent in the comparator <lb/>[e.g.13,15,16]. By careful analysis of aCGH data for bacteria <lb/>with complete genome annotations, we have established that this <lb/>reasoning, while intuitively plausible, may lead to erroneous <lb/>conclusions. Our data support only a distinction between those <lb/>sequences that are, and those that are not, orthologous in the <lb/>comparator organism. In particular they do not support a <lb/>distinction between putatively orthologous sequences in terms of <lb/>their degree of sequence identity, using aCGH hybridisation data. <lb/>That is, the two sets of putatively orthologous sequences that <lb/>would be classified as &apos;present&apos; or merely &apos;divergent&apos; could not be <lb/>distinguished by us in terms of their hybridisation scores or ratios, <lb/>and therefore the two classes of &apos;present&apos; and &apos;divergent or absent&apos; <lb/>sequences could also not be distinguished. <lb/>We recognise that the array platform itself may be a significant <lb/>factor in the interpretation of hybridisation data. Our microarray <lb/>spots were designed with probes of 60 nt in length, one for each <lb/>CDS, and the L. lactis array data we studied was derived from arrays <lb/>spotted with amplicons of variable length from 80–800 bp [13]. <lb/>Previous aCGH studies have employed a number of alternative <lb/>array constructions, including gene-length cDNA probes, cDNA <lb/>probes of partial genes, but longer than 60 nt; Affymetrix arrays <lb/>with multiple short (25 nt) probes per spot; and Agilent arrays with <lb/>60 nt probes [10,12,14,55]. Our data demonstrate that conclusions <lb/>about the relationship between sequence identity and array <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>12 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			hybridisation drawn using a particular array technology do not <lb/>necessarily hold for alternative technologies. Measurement and <lb/>validation of this relationship is essential for correct interpretation of <lb/>aCGH data, and should be performed for each array platform. <lb/>Hybridisation binding strength or ratio data may also be <lb/>interpreted in terms of a thermodynamic model of probe binding <lb/>to the comparator organism gDNA, as an alternative to our <lb/>interpretation in terms of percentage sequence identity. This is a <lb/>useful technique when applied to resequencing of strains that are <lb/>very closely related to the reference, as deviations in hybridisation <lb/>strength may be accommodated within the thermodynamic model, <lb/>and sequence differences inferred from observed binding affinities, <lb/>in terms of that model; it may thus be a better approximator to <lb/>hybridisation strength than is sequence identity. However we do not <lb/>use it here as our aim is to infer putative orthology, defined in terms <lb/>of sequence identity, from hybridisation data. The appropriate <lb/>measure of putative orthology in this case is sequence identity, and <lb/>not inferred sequence composition based on a model of the <lb/>thermodynamic properties of probe binding. An interpretation of <lb/>measured hybridisation in terms of sequence identity, validated on <lb/>known sequence data, is therefore the most direct and appropriate <lb/>approach for this study. Also, a typical bacterial aCGH experiment <lb/>may involve a comparator organism that displays considerably <lb/>greater divergence than that which would normally be considered <lb/>for resequencing or other circumstances in which a thermodynamic <lb/>model would usually be applied. For example, in our genus-level <lb/>method validation only 807/10280 (less than 10%) of Pba array <lb/>probes make a best match (with BLASTN) to the Dda genome that <lb/>covers the probe to within 5 bp of its length. This significant <lb/>divergence is likely to induce significant uncertainty, and therefore <lb/>additional error, in the relationship between base composition as <lb/>inferred from a thermodynamic model, and the subsequent <lb/>assignment of putative orthology. <lb/> The HMM Predictor Robustly Extends the Working Range <lb/>of aCGH Analysis to Comparison of Bacteria at the Genus <lb/>Level <lb/> Array CGH has previously been applied, in the main, to closely <lb/>related organisms; in bacteria, this has usually involved comparisons <lb/>at the intra-or inter-species level [e.g.5,6,7,9,13,45,46,48,56]. In <lb/>principle, as hybridisation affinity is expected to be influenced by <lb/>sequence identity, and not by schemes of systematic classification, it <lb/>should be possible to extend the technique with some success to <lb/>comparisons between organisms with a more ancient last common <lb/>ancestor. In particular, DNA-DNA hybridisation studies of <lb/> Pba1043, Pcc193 and Dda3937, 16S rRNA analysis and phyloge-<lb/>netic considerations (data not shown) indicate genome-wide <lb/>sequence similarity that justifies the use of aCGH to compare the <lb/>genome complements of these organisms. In this study, we <lb/>successfully applied our analysis method to comparison data for <lb/> Pba1043 and Dda3937: bacteria that differed at the genus level. <lb/> Normalisation Methods for aCGH <lb/> It has been noted by other groups that a high degree of <lb/>sequence divergence between prokaryotes may obstruct aCGH <lb/>approaches, on the grounds that no strong assumption may be <lb/>made concerning the distribution of hybridisation ratios for a <lb/>Lowess normalisation step. Extension of aCGH to more distant <lb/>comparisons has previously been attempted by modification of the <lb/>normalisation method used on the array data, such as supervised <lb/>Lowess (S-LOWESS) [5,13]. However, we note that Lowess and <lb/>many other array normalisation methods employ a null hypothesis <lb/>which assumes that, for a significant proportion of probes, the <lb/>hybridisation strengths of reference and comparator sequences are <lb/>random variables drawn from the same distribution. This is a <lb/>reasonable assumption when applied to isogenic data, such as <lb/>bacterial mutants, these normalisation operations preserve differ-<lb/>ences in transcriptional expression while reducing systematic error, <lb/>as the applied correction of normalisation is valid for the great <lb/>majority of probes. It is not such a reasonable assumption for <lb/>aCGH. <lb/>Normalisation methods such as Lowess may be useful for <lb/>aCGH, on the condition that the reference and comparator <lb/>diverged sufficiently recently, as the proportion of probes that do <lb/>not conform to the underlying assumptions is likely to be small. <lb/>This restricts the applicability of aCGH when using these <lb/>normalisation approaches. However, in cases where the reference <lb/>and comparator organisms do not share such a recent common <lb/>ancestor, as for the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison in which a strict <lb/>majority of CDS do not have identifiable nucleotide RBH between <lb/>the organisms (Figure S1), the underlying assumptions of Lowess <lb/>normalisation fail for the majority of probes. <lb/>Subset modifications of Lowess have proven effective on within-<lb/>species strain comparisons, but require the prior identification of <lb/>conserved genes, and the assumption that the derived correction is <lb/>applicable even to the majority of divergent sequences [5,13]. <lb/>Therefore in this study we used the nonparametric normalisation <lb/>method of quantile normalisation (QN) to correct for systematic <lb/>errors. QN requires no prior assumptions concerning the <lb/>relatedness of reference and comparator sequences, and specifi-<lb/>cally makes no assumptions relating to sequence conservation. QN <lb/>asserts only that the distribution of probe strengths is comparable <lb/>across replicate arrays, which was established for our data in <lb/>Figure 1. <lb/>The results of our consistency test validation indicate that <lb/>measures of prediction quality for the interspecies Pba1043:Dda3937 <lb/> comparison, though lower than that for the interstrain Lactococcus <lb/> comparison, remain acceptable. <lb/> The HMM aCGH Analysis Method Performs Better than <lb/>GACK, MPP and Threshold Methods <lb/> Table 2 demonstrates that the HMM analysis method described <lb/>in this paper outperforms GACK, MPP and threshold methods in <lb/>identifying correctly those CDS in Pba1043 that do not have <lb/>orthologues in Dda3937, and also those CDS in L. lactis MG1363 <lb/>that do not have orthologues in IL1403. The consistency test of <lb/>performance on the Pba1043:Dda3937 comparison suggests that <lb/>GACK has a tendency to overpredict the number of reference <lb/>sequences that have no orthologue in the comparator, which <lb/>supports previous observations made using this method [5]. <lb/>The HMM approach applied herein makes one straightforward <lb/>improvement to the naı ve threshold cutoff classification in that it <lb/>incorporates information about the state of neighbouring CDS on <lb/>the genome. Spatial data has previously been incorporated into <lb/>methods applied to human copy number variation aCGH <lb/>[18,19,20], in which the reference and comparator sequences <lb/>may be assumed, accounting for noise, to be either so similar as to <lb/>be near-identical, variant in signal by whole-number ratios, or <lb/>absent altogether. Bacterial comparative genomic aCGH data also <lb/>represents sequences that may be nearly identical, occur as copy-<lb/>number variations, or absent altogether. However, the observed <lb/>degree of sequence variation in bacterial comparative genomics is <lb/>very high, and bacterial comparative data also has the potential to <lb/>include tens to thousands of sequences that may be orthologous or <lb/>paralogous, and to vary in terms of sequence identity at 50% of <lb/>their sequence or more. We have demonstrated that the <lb/>relationship between sequence identity and array hybridisation is <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			complex in this system, and while it was expected that using <lb/>information about spatial organisation would improve predictive <lb/>performance, as it has done in the human copy number aCGH <lb/>problem domain, the magnitude of this improvement was not <lb/>readily predictable. <lb/>The HMM applied here is first-order, and so is the simplest <lb/>such adaptation that could be applied. Further refinements of the <lb/>methodology may deliver enhanced predictive performance. <lb/>Although the resulting improvement in performance over a naı ve <lb/>threshold metric is not as striking as the improvement in relation to <lb/>GACK and MPP results, it is a consistently better predictor and <lb/>demonstrates that the incorporation of spatial information about <lb/>hybridisation scores improves predictive performance. The <lb/>qualitatively different predictions of the threshold and HMM <lb/>methods suggest that these approaches identify intersecting subsets <lb/>of true positives, and that an ensemble approach may be a <lb/>worthwhile progression of the method. <lb/>It is possible that a HMM with bivariate outcomes, or training <lb/>data (representing cy3 and cy5 intensities) might improve <lb/>predictive ability of the model. Other methods of identifying an <lb/>optimal path through the HMM than the Viterbi algorithm are <lb/>also available. However, our results demonstrate that a HMM <lb/>with univariate outcome, and using the Viterbi algorithm, <lb/>performs better than accepted and widely-used approaches on <lb/>bivariate signal data, and is sufficient to demonstrate that the <lb/>incorporation of spatial genomic information improves aCGH <lb/>prediction on bacterial genome sequences. <lb/>It might also be interesting to predict membership of one of the <lb/>populations (high, medium or low hybridisation putative ortholo-<lb/>gues) observed in Figure 1 for each probe. However, our interest in <lb/>this study was potential improvements in the prediction of putative <lb/>orthologues in comparator sequences using spatial information in <lb/>a HMM, and not optimisation of the predictive HMM. <lb/> Array CGH Results Obtained for Pba1043 Comparisons <lb/>Support a Model of &apos;Accessory&apos; Genome Acquisition by <lb/>Continuing, Dynamic Genomic Island Transfer <lb/> The improvement over threshold-based prediction seen with <lb/>the HMM suggests a detectable biological signal from the <lb/>collocation of sequences in the reference that do not have an <lb/>orthologue in the comparator, and supports the hypothesis that <lb/>the &apos;accessory&apos; genome is acquired in large part through genomic <lb/>islands, rather than individual genes. Accordingly, the number of <lb/>islands of Pba1043 CDS with no orthologue in the comparator <lb/>organism was seen to increase with evolutionary distance to a <lb/>common ancestor. At all evolutionary distances, the predicted <lb/>islands showed a statistically significant association with regions <lb/>of putative horizontal gene transfer, whether identified by <lb/>manual annotation or by the alien_hunter software. Further <lb/>statistically significant results were observed for the association of <lb/>these islands with sequences that were putatively orthologous to <lb/>sequences in plant-associated bacteria, but not in animal-<lb/>pathogenic enterobacteria. Taken together, this evidence is <lb/>strongly suggestive of the acquisition of functions specific to the <lb/>niche of these plant-associated enterobacteria by horizontal <lb/>transfer. <lb/>The identification of islands in Pba1043 that do not have <lb/>orthologues in Pba1039 is evidence that this process of lateral gene <lb/>transfer continues in the SRE. Most of the CDS in these islands <lb/>appeared to be phage-related or to encode hypothetical proteins <lb/>(Table 4). These may not themselves be critical to the phenotypic <lb/>differences between strains, but nevertheless indicate a dynamic <lb/>genome with the potential for acquisition of novel function. <lb/>However, comparisons at the species and genus level reveal major <lb/>differences in gene content that may reflect differences in the <lb/>abilities of each organism to persist in the environment <lb/>(particularly on plants), and to cause disease on susceptible host <lb/>plants. <lb/> Regions Identified as &apos;Accessory&apos; Genome Are Associated <lb/>with Virulence, Pathogenicity, and Persistence in Specific <lb/>Environmental Niches <lb/> Perhaps the most notable of the accessory islands is that which <lb/>includes the cfa genes encoding for coronafacic acid (CFA) <lb/>synthesis. The ability to synthesise this compound appears to be <lb/>limited to Pba, amongst the SRE. In the plant pathogen <lb/> Pseudomonas syringae, CFA is coupled to coronamic acid (CMA), <lb/>to produce the phytotoxin coronatine, which promotes disease <lb/>through manipulation of plant defences [57]. CFA has also been <lb/>demonstrated to be required for virulence in Pba1043, providing <lb/>the first evidence for the involvement of phytotoxins in soft rot <lb/>pathogenesis, although its precise role has yet to be determined <lb/>[22,36]. In Pba1043 the cfa gene cluster is carried on a <lb/>pathogenicity island highly similar to PAIs found in Pcc193 and <lb/>other bacterial pathogens. In other pathogens these lack the cfa <lb/> cluster, but in its place carry other genes with a range of functions, <lb/>some of which are known to contribute to disease development, <lb/>such as SPI-7 in Salmonella enterica serovar Typhi that carries the Vi <lb/>expolysaccharide cluster [53,54]. <lb/>Other putative phytotoxic PKS and NRPS, such as the PKS <lb/> ECA2694 and a syringomycin synthesis-like NRPS are observed to <lb/>be components of the &apos;accessory&apos; genomes of Pba and Pectobacter-<lb/>ium, respectively. Syringomycin is produced by strains of <lb/> Pseudomonas syringae, and is a virulence factor responsible for pore <lb/>formation and nutrient leakage through the host cell membrane <lb/>[57]. The structure of the compound produced by the putatively <lb/> Pectobacterium-specific NRPS, and any role it may play in virulence <lb/>are as yet unknown. <lb/>The type III secretion system (T3SS) and its translocated <lb/>effectors promote virulence by the manipulation of host plant <lb/>defence responses [29]. The T3SS structural apparatus encoded <lb/>by the hrp/hrc gene cluster appears to be conserved in all four <lb/>SRE tested. Our HMM predicts that a number of neighbouring <lb/>effector and helper proteins (e.g. dspEF and hrpW), and <lb/>agglutinins (hecAB) do not have orthologues in Dda3937 (island <lb/>DdaI80). However, sequence comparisons between the ge-<lb/>nomes of Pba1043 and Dda3937 indicate that this result is a false <lb/>positive, and the Pba1043 CDS do in fact have orthologues in <lb/> Dda3937. Such false positives may be caused or exacerbated by <lb/>a tendency to design microarray probes to divergent regions of <lb/>the reference gene. The distribution of these effectors may be <lb/>strain-dependent, as the EC16 strain of Dickeya appears not to <lb/>possess dspE or hrpW in the region flanking the hrp cluster <lb/>[58,59]. <lb/>Some putatively Pectobacterium-specific islands carry genes <lb/>encoding PCWDE that are not present in Dda3937, such as <lb/>pectate lyase (pel3) and polygalacturonase (pehA). These differences <lb/>in PCWDE complement may reflect corresponding differences in <lb/>environmental niche and/or host range [25]. Other islands carry <lb/>siderophores similar to pyoverdine and aerobactin, which appear <lb/>to be restricted to Pectobacterium spp. amongst the SRE tested. <lb/>Neither of these siderophores yet have a demonstrated association <lb/>with virulence in pectobacteria, but the siderophores chrysobactin <lb/>and achromobactin, which are not produced by Pba1043, are <lb/>known to be involved with virulence in Dda3937 [60,61]. <lb/>Several Pba-specific and Pectobacterium-specific islands contain <lb/>CDS encoding functions that are known or appear to be <lb/>associated with persistence in the environment, and particularly <lb/>

			<note place="headnote"> Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>14 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			on plant roots. These functions include phenazine antibiotic <lb/>production (ehp), multidrug resistance (emr, opr, mex, nfx), and <lb/>octopine uptake (occ; see Table 3). Phenazine has been shown to <lb/>target other microorganisms in competition for limited nutrient <lb/>resources in the rhizosphere [62,63]. Phenazine does not appear <lb/>to be produced by Pcc193 or Dda3937, but other antibiotics, such <lb/>as carbapenem, which is produced by some Pcc strains, may <lb/>provide equivalent function [64]. The multidrug resistance <lb/>proteins unique to Pba may provide protection against these <lb/>compounds. Octopines are tumour-derived compounds produced <lb/>by the plant using genes transferred during infection by <lb/> Agrobacterium tumefaciens. The resulting opines, including octopine, <lb/>are used as a source of nutrition by the bacterium. The octopine <lb/>uptake CDS, which we find to be putatively Pectobacterium-specific, <lb/> may reflect an ability to piggyback on Agrobacterium infection and <lb/>tumour formation [65]. This is an intriguing possibility when <lb/>taken in context with the observation of genes associated with <lb/>nitrogen fixation in Pba. <lb/> The region encoding putative nitrogen fixation function in <lb/> Pba1043 is unusual in that orthologues to key genes in this island <lb/>are found in Dda3937, and predicted to be present in Pba1039, but <lb/>not in Pcc193. This would appear to imply either that Pcc193 has <lb/>lost the capacity to fix nitrogen, or that at least one independent <lb/>acquisition event has occurred to confer this ability. Nitrogen <lb/>fixation is critical to the nitrogen cycle, and to the soil and <lb/>rhizosphere environments, in converting atmospheric nitrogen <lb/>into ammonium compounds that can then be converted by other <lb/>microorganisms into compounds that may be used by plants. The <lb/>apparent absence of this capability in Pcc193 suggests that the <lb/>ability to fix nitrogen is not essential for successful pathogenesis. <lb/>However, the ability to fix nitrogen may promote establishment <lb/>and persistence in the environment. <lb/> High-Throughput Sequencing Studies Also Support the <lb/>Broad Conclusions of Our aCGH Analysis <lb/> Our aCGH study indicated that HAIs in Pba1043 that were <lb/>previously identified through manual curation [22] were found to <lb/>be variably present in the SRE strains investigated (Table 4). A <lb/>recent study that used 454 sequencing to compare the genome of <lb/> Pba1043 to the pectobacteria PccWPP14 and P. braziliensis 1692 <lb/>(Pbr1692) also observed variation in the presence of these HAIs <lb/>amongst the pectobacteria [66]. HAI2, which in our analysis was <lb/>found to be present in Pba1043 and Pcc193, was found to be <lb/>entirely absent from PccWPP14 and Pbr1692, suggesting that its <lb/>occurrence is sporadic among the pectobacteria. Similarly <lb/>HAI17, which we predicted to be specific to Pba1043, was found <lb/>to be present in both PccWPP14 and Pbr1692. These observations <lb/>confirm the broad theme of our conclusions, that these <lb/>organisms, though related, have a dynamic, plastic genome <lb/>composition that results in large functional changes even at the <lb/>strain level. <lb/> What Are the Prospects for aCGH? <lb/> A recent study indicates that high-throughput sequencing (HTS; <lb/>serial analysis of gene expression: SAGE) provides advantages over <lb/>microarray technology for gene expression analysis, though the <lb/>false discovery rate appeared to be greater for SAGE [67]. There <lb/>are several additional disadvantages of aCGH that are overcome <lb/>by modern HTS methods such as 454 or Solexa/Illumina <lb/>sequencing. Aside from the question of whether probe hybridisa-<lb/>tion state is a reliable proxy of sequence identity, or even putative <lb/>orthology -questions that can be answered directly by sequencing <lb/>-unlike HTS, aCGH cannot disclose or describe novel sequences <lb/>in the comparator organism [68,69]. The cost of sequencing a <lb/>bacterial genome by these methods is falling rapidly at the time of <lb/>writing, and there may come a point where the cost of completely <lb/>sequencing a comparator genome is less than that of carrying out <lb/>the comparable aCGH experiment. Even before that point is <lb/>reached, the additional information that HTS provides may be <lb/>such that it justifies the additional cost of the technique. This area <lb/>is still moving rapidly, but it has been argued that, for some <lb/>approaches such as chromatin immunoprecipitation, microarray <lb/>and HTS experiments complement each other, and the same may <lb/>be true for aCGH [70]. <lb/> Supporting Information <lb/> Table S1  17 Pba1043 genomic islands predicted to have no <lb/>orthologues in Pba1039. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s001 (0.06 MB PDF) <lb/> Table S2  56 genomic islands predicted to have orthologues in <lb/>Pba1043 and Pba1039, but no orthologues in either of Pcc193 or <lb/>Dda3937. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s002 (0.10 MB PDF) <lb/> Table S3  60 Pba1043 genomic islands predicted to have no <lb/>orthologues in Pcc193, prefixed PccI. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s003 (0.10 MB PDF) <lb/> Table S4  165 Pba1043 genomic islands predicted to have no <lb/>orthologues in Dda3937, prefixed DdaI. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s004 (0.23 MB PDF) <lb/> Table S5  168 Pba1043 genomic islands predicted to have no <lb/>orthologues in Dda3937, but to have orthologues in both Pcc193 <lb/>and Pba1039, prefixed PectoI. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s005 (0.16 MB PDF) <lb/> Table S6  Islands of Pba1043 CDS predicted by aCGH to have <lb/>be Pba-specific (PbaI), or to have no orthologues in either Pcc193 <lb/>(PccI). <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s006 (0.05 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S1  Scatter plot of percentage sequence identity for <lb/>coding sequences in Pba1043 to Dda3937 by reciprocal best <lb/>FASTA and BLASTN analyses. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s007 (0.31 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S2  Scatterplots of putative orthologue (RBH) nucleotide <lb/>sequence identity. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s008 (1.54 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S3  Plot of predictions of the theshold and HMM <lb/>methods as the threshold is varied in the aCGH experiment with <lb/>Dda3937 against Pba1043 taking log transformed hybridisation <lb/>ratios. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s009 (0.23 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S4  Plots of CDS from the reference organisms predicted <lb/>to have or not to have a putative orthologue in the comparator <lb/>organisms. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s010 (0.10 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S5  Plot of the Pba1043 CDS with and without a <lb/>predicted orthologue in Pba1039 and Pcc193. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s011 (0.09 MB PDF) <lb/> Figure S6  Linear diagram indicating, on the chromosome of <lb/>Pba1043, locations of horizontally acquired islands, aCGH <lb/>predictions of genomic islands and predicted divergent base <lb/>composition by alien-hunter. <lb/>Found at: doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1000473.s012 (19.93 MB AI) <lb/>
		
		</body> 
		
		<back>
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>15 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank Brian Gettler and Yvan Charbonnier for their contribution in <lb/>developing software for microarray design, David Broadhurst for statistical <lb/>discussions, Micha Bayer for database support, and Peter Cock, Nicola <lb/>Holden and anonymous reviewers for helpful and constructive comments <lb/>on the manuscript. <lb/> Author Contributions <lb/> Conceived and designed the experiments: LP PRJB IKT. Performed the <lb/>experiments: LP HL CB ED PH. Analyzed the data: LP IKT. Contributed <lb/>reagents/materials/analysis tools: LP PF JS. Wrote the paper: LP HL PH <lb/>PRJB IKT. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Hu J, Gao J-B, Cao Y, Bottinger E, Zhang W (2007) Exploiting noise in array <lb/>CGH data to improve detection of DNA copy number change. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Res 35: e35. <lb/>2. Wang J, Mexa-Zepada LA, Kresse SH, Myklebost O (2004) M-CGH: analysing <lb/>microarray-based CGH experiments. BMC Bioinformatics 5: 74. <lb/>3. Fitzgerald JR, Sturdevant DE, Mackie SM, Gill SR, Musser JM (2001) <lb/>Evolutionary genomics of Staphylococcus aureus: insights into the origin of <lb/>methicillin-resistant strains and the toxic shock syndrome epidemic. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A 98: 8821–8826. <lb/>4. Porwollik S, Hong RM-Y, McClelland M (2002) Evolutionary genomics of <lb/> Salmonella: gene acquisitions revealed by microarray analysis. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci U S A 99: 8956–8961. <lb/>5. Witney AA, Marsden GL, Holden MTG, Stabler RA, Husain SE, et al. (2005) <lb/>Design, validation, and application of a seven-strain Staphylococcus aureus PCR <lb/>product microarray for comparative genomics. Appl Environ Microbiol 71: <lb/>7504–7514. <lb/>6. Koessler T, François P, Charbonnier Y, Huyghe A, Bento M, et al. (2006) Use of <lb/>oligoarrays for characterization of community-onset methicillin-resistant Staph-<lb/>ylococcus aureus. J Clin Microbiol 44: 1040–1048. <lb/>7. Lepage E, Brinster S, Caron C, Ducroix-Crepy C, Rigottier-Gois L, et al. (2006) <lb/>Comparative genomic hybridization analysis of Enterococcus faecalis: identification <lb/>of genes absent from food strains. J Bacteriol 188: 6858–6868. <lb/>8. Ben Zakour NL, Sturdevant DE, Even S, Guinane CM, Barbey C, et al. (2008) <lb/>Genome-wide analysis of ruminant Staphylococcus aureus reveals diversification of <lb/>the core genome. J Bacteriol 190: 6302–6317. <lb/>9. Sim SH, Yu Y, Lin CH, Karuturi RKM, Wuthiekanun V, et al. (2008) The core <lb/>and accessory genomes of Burkholderia pseudomallei: Implications for human <lb/>melioidosis. PLoS Pathog 4: e1000178. <lb/>10. Carter B, Wu G, Woodward MJ, Anjum MF (2008) A process for analysis of <lb/>microarray comparative genomics hybridisation studies for bacterial genomes. <lb/>BMC Genomics 9: 53. <lb/>11. Sarkar SF, Gordon JS, Martin GB, Guttman DS (2006) Comparative Genomics <lb/>of Host-Specific Virulence in Pseudomonas syringae. Genetics 174: 1041–1056. <lb/>12. Aittamaa M, Somervuo P, Pirhonen M, Mattinen L, Nissinen R, et al. (2008) <lb/>Distinguishing bacterial pathogens of potato using a genome-wide microarray <lb/>approach. Mol Plant Pathol 9: 705–717. <lb/>13. van Hijum SAFT, Baerends RJS, Zomer AL, Karsens HA, Martin-Requena V, <lb/>et al. (2008) Supervised Lowess normalization of comparative genome <lb/>hybridization data -application to lactococcal strain comparisons. BMC <lb/>Bioinformatics 9: 93. <lb/>14. Chain FJJ, Ilieve D, Evans BJ (2008) Single-species microarrays and comparative <lb/>transcriptomics. PLoS ONE 3: e3279. <lb/>15. Kim CC, Joyce EA, Chan K, Falkow S (2002) Improved analytical methods for <lb/>microarray-based genome-composition analysis. Genome Biol 3: RE-<lb/>SEARCH0065.1–0065.17. <lb/>16. Davey R, Savva G, Dicks J, Roberts IN (2007) MPP: a microarray-to-phylogeny <lb/>pipeline for analysis of gene and marker content datasets. Bioinformatics 23: <lb/>1023–1025. <lb/>17. Pin C, Reuter M (2007) Use of genomic DNA control features and predicted <lb/>operon structure in microarray data analysis: ArrayLeaRNA – a Bayesian <lb/>approach. BMC Bioinformatics 8: 455. <lb/>18. Fridlyand J, Snijders AM, Pinkel D, Albertson DG, Jain IN (2004) Hidden <lb/>Markov models approach to the analysis of array CGH data. J Multivar Anal 90: <lb/>132–153. <lb/>19. Picard F, Robin S, LeBarbier E, Daudin J-J (2007) A segmentation/clustering <lb/>model for the analysis of array CGH data. Biometrics 63: 758–66. <lb/>20. Budinska E, Gelnarova E, Schimek MG (2009) MSMAD: A computationally <lb/>efficient method for the analysis of noisy array CGH data. Bioinformatics 25: <lb/>703–713. <lb/>21. Perombelon MCM (2002) Potato diseases caused by soft rot erwinias: an <lb/>overview of pathogenesis. Plant Pathol 51: 1–12. <lb/>22. Bell KS, Sebaihia M, Pritchard L, Holden MTG, Hyman LJ, et al. (2004) <lb/>Genome sequence of the enterobacterial phytopathogen Erwinia carotovora subsp. <lb/> atroseptica and characterization of virulence factors. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>101: 11105–11110. <lb/>23. Barras F, van Gijsegem F, Chatterjee AK (1994) Extracellular enzymes and <lb/>pathogenesis of soft-rot Erwinia. Annu Rev Phytopathol 32: 201–234. <lb/>24. Py B, Barras F, Harris S, Robson N, Salmond GPC (1998) Extracellular <lb/>enzymes and their role in Erwinia virulence. Method Microbiol 27: 157–168. <lb/>25. Toth IK, Bell KS, Holeva MC, Birch PRJ (2003) Soft rot erwiniae: from genes to <lb/>genomes. Mol Plant Pathol 4: 17–30. <lb/>26. Hugouvieux-Cotte-Pattat N, Condemine G, Nasser W, Reverchon S (1996) <lb/>Regulation of pectinolysis in Erwinia chrysanthemi. Ann. Rev. Microbiol 50: <lb/>213–257. <lb/>27. Boughammoura A, Matzanke BF, Böttger L, Reverchon S, Lesuisse E, et al. <lb/>(2008) Differential role of ferritins in iron metabolism and virulence of the plant-<lb/>pathogenic bacterium Erwinia chrysanthemi 3937. J Bacteriol 190: 1518–1530. <lb/>28. Desveaux D, Singer AU, Dangl JL (2006) Type III effector proteins: <lb/>doppelgangers of bacterial virulence. Curr Opin Plant Biol 9: 376–382. <lb/>29. McCann HC, Guttman DS (2008) Evolution of the type III secretion system and <lb/>its effectors in plant-microbe interactions. New Phytol 177: 33–47. <lb/>30. Block A, Li G, Fu ZQ, Alfano JR (2008) Phytopathogen type III effector <lb/>weaponry and their plant targets. Curr Opin Plant Biol 11: 396–403. <lb/>31. Zhou J, Chai J (2008) Plant pathogenic bacterial type III effectors subdue host <lb/>responses. Curr Opin Microbiol 11: 179–185. <lb/>32. Bauer DW, Wei ZM, Beer SV, Collmer A (1995) Erwinia chrysanthemi harpin (Ech) <lb/>– an elicitor of the hypersensitive response that contributes to soft-rot <lb/>pathogenesis. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 8: 484–491. <lb/>33. Yang C-H, Gavilanes-Ruiz M, Okinaka Y, Vedel R, Berthuy I, et al. (2002) hrp <lb/> genes of Erwinia chrysanthemi 3937 are important virulence factors. Mol Plant <lb/>Microbe Interact 15: 472–480. <lb/>34. Lehtimä ki S, Rantakari A, Routtu J, Tuikkala A, Li J, et al. (2003) <lb/>Characterization of the hrp pathogenicity cluster of Erwinia carotovora subsp. <lb/> carotovora: high basal level expression in a mutant is associated with reduced <lb/>virulence. Mol Genet Genomics 270: 263–272. <lb/>35. Holeva MC, Bell KS, Hyman LJ, Avrova AO, Whisson SC, et al. (2004) Use of a <lb/>pooled transposon mutation grid to demonstrate roles in disease development for <lb/> Erwinia carotovora subsp. atroseptica putative type III secreted effector (DspE/A) <lb/>and helper (HrpN) proteins. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 17: 943–950. <lb/>36. Toth IK, Birch PRJ (2005) Rotting softly and stealthily. Curr Opin Plant Biol 8: <lb/>424–429. <lb/>37. Liu H, Coulthurst SJ, Pritchard L, Hedley PE, Ravensdale MR, et al. (2008) <lb/>Quorum sensing coordinates brute force and stealth modes of infection in the <lb/>plant pathogen Pectobacterium atrosepticum. PLoS Pathog 4: e1000093. <lb/>38. Toth IK, Pritchard L, Birch PRJ (2006) Comparative genomics reveals what <lb/>makes an enterobacterial plant pathogen. Annu Rev Phytopathol 44: 305–336. <lb/>39. Lindeberg M, Myers CR, Collmer A, Schneider DJ (2008) Roadmap to New <lb/>Virulence Determinants in Pseudomonas syringae: Insights from Comparative <lb/>Genomics and Genome Organization. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 21: 685–700. <lb/>40. Eswarappa SM, Janice J, Nagarajan AG, Balasundaram SV, Karnam G, et al. <lb/>(2008) Differentially Evolved Genes of Salmonella Pathogenicity Islands: Insights <lb/>into the Mechanism of Host Specificity in Salmonella. PLoS ONE 3: e3829. <lb/>41. Charbonnier Y, Gettler B, François P, Bento M, Renzoni A, et al. (2005) A <lb/>generic approach for the design of whole-genome oligoarrays, validated for <lb/>genomotyping, deletion mapping and gene expression analysis on Staphylococcus <lb/>aureus. BMC Genomics 6: 95. <lb/>42. Vernikos GS, Parkhill J (2006) Interpolated variable order motifs for <lb/>identification of horizontally acquired DNA: revisiting the Salmonella pathoge-<lb/>nicity islands. Bioinformatics 22: 2196–2203. <lb/>43. Dong Y, Glasner JD, Blattner FR, Triplett EW (2001) Genomic interspecies <lb/>microarray hybridization: rapid discovery of three thousand genes in the maize <lb/>endophyte, Klebsiella pneumoniae 342, by microarray hybridization with Escherichia <lb/>coli K-12 open reading frames. Appl Environ Microbiol 67: 1911–1921. <lb/>44. Taboada EN, Acedillo RR, Luebbert CC, Findlay WA, Nash JHE (2005) A new <lb/>approach for the analysis of bacterial microarray-based Comparative Genomic <lb/>Hybridization: insights from an empirical study. BMC Genomics 6: 78. <lb/>45. Nash JHE, Findlay WA, Luebbert CC, Mykytczuk OL, Foote SJ, et al. (2006) <lb/>Comparative genomics profiling of clinical isolates of Aeromonas salmonicida using <lb/>DNA microarrays. BMC Genomics 7: 43. <lb/>46. Earl AM, Losick R, Kolter R (2007) Bacillus subtilis genome diversity. J Bacteriol <lb/>189: 1163–1170. <lb/>47. Kunin V, Goldovsky L, Darzentas N, Ouzounis CA (2005) The net of life: <lb/>reconstructing the microbial phylogenetic network. Genome Res 15: 954–959. <lb/>48. Chan K, Baker S, Kim CC, Detweiler CS, Dougan G, et al. (2003) Genomic <lb/>comparison of Salmonella enterica serovars and Salmonella bongori by use of an S. <lb/>enterica serovar typhimurium DNA microarray. J Bacteriol 185: 553–563. <lb/>49. Hotopp JCD, Grifantini R, Kumar N, Tzeng YL, Fouts DE, et al. (2006) <lb/>Comparative genomics of Neisseria meningitidis: core genome, islands of horizontal <lb/>transfer and pathogen-specific genes. Microbiology 152: 3733–3749. <lb/>50. Peng J, Zhang X, Yang J, Wang J, Yang E, et al. (2006) The use of comparative <lb/>genomic hybridization to characterize genome dynamics and diversity among <lb/>the serotypes of Shigella. BMC Genomics 7: 218. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>16 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473 <lb/></note> 
			
			51. Pin C, Reuter M, Pearson B, Friis L, Overweg K, et al. (2006) Comparison of <lb/>different approaches for comparative genetic analysis using microarray <lb/>hybridization. Appl Microbiol Biotechnol 72: 852–859. <lb/>52. Paauw A, Caspers MPM, Schuren FHJ, Leverstein-van Hall MA, Delétoile A, et <lb/>al. (2008) Genomic diversity within the Enterobacter cloacae complex. PLoS ONE <lb/>3: e3018. <lb/>53. Mohd-Zain Z, Turner SL, Cerdeno-Tarraga AM, Lilley AK, Inzana TJ, et al. <lb/>(2004) Transferable antibiotic resistance elements in Haemophilus influenzae share a <lb/>common evolutionary origin with a diverse family of syntenic genomic islands. <lb/>J Bacteriol 186: 8114–8122. <lb/>54. Moreira LM, de Souza RF, Digiampietri LA, da Silva ACR, Setubal JC (2005) <lb/>Comparative analyses of Xanthomonas and Xylella complete genomes. Omics 9: <lb/>43–76. <lb/>55. Dziejman M, Balon EL, Boyd DH, Fraser CM, Heidelberg JF, et al. (2002) <lb/>Comparative genomic analysis of Vibrio cholerae: genes that correlate with cholera <lb/>endemic and pandemic disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 99: 1556–1561. <lb/>56. Stabler RA, Marsden GL, Witney AA, Li Y, Bentley SD, et al. (2005) <lb/>Identification of pathogen-specific genes through microarray analysis of <lb/>pathogenic and commensal Neisseria species. Microbiology 151: 2907–2922. <lb/>57. Bender CL, Alarcó n-Chaidez F, Gross DC (1999) Pseudomonas syringae <lb/> phytotoxins: mode of action, regulation, and biosynthesis by peptide and <lb/>polyketide synthetases. Microbiol Mol Biol Rev 63: 266–292. <lb/>58. Rojas CM, Ham JH, Deng W-L, Doyle JJ, Collmer A (2002) HecA, a member of <lb/>a class of adhesins produced by diverse pathogenic bacteria, contributes to the <lb/>attachment, aggregation, epidermal cell killing, and virulence phenotypes of <lb/> Erwinia chrysanthemi EC16 on Nicotiana clevelandii seedlings. Proc Natl Acad <lb/>Sci U S A 99: 13142–13147. <lb/>59. Rojas CM, Ham JH, Schechter LM, Kim JF, Beer SV, et al. (2004) The Erwinia <lb/>chrysanthemi EC16 hrp/hrc gene cluster encodes an active Hrp type III secretion <lb/>system that is flanked by virulence genes functionally unrelated to the Hrp <lb/>system. Mol Plant Microbe Interact 17: 644–653. <lb/>60. Enard C, Diolex A, Expert D (1988) Systemic virulence of Erwinia chrysanthemi <lb/> 3937 requires a functional iron assimilation system. J Bacteriol 170: 2419–2426. <lb/>61. Franza T, Mahém B, Expert D (2005) Erwinia chrysanthemi requires a second iron <lb/>transport route dependent of the siderophore achromobactin for extracellular <lb/>growth and plant infection. Mol Microbiol 55: 261–275. <lb/>62. Gurusiddaiah S, Weller DM, Sarkar A, Cook RJ (1986) Characterization of an <lb/>antibiotic produced by a strain of Pseudomonas fluorescens inhibitory to <lb/> Gaeumannomyces graminis var. tritici and Pythium spp.. Antimicrob Agents <lb/>Chemother 29: 488–495. <lb/>63. Thomashow LS, Weller DM (1988) Role of a phenazine antibiotic from <lb/> Pseudomonas fluorescens in biological control of Gaeumannomyces graminis var. tritici. <lb/> J Bacteriol 170: 3499–3508. <lb/>64. Coulthurst SJ, Barnard AML, Salmond GPC (2005) Regulation and biosynthesis <lb/>of carbapenem antibiotics in bacteria. Nat Rev Micro 3: 295–306. <lb/>65. Zhu J, Oger PM, Schrammeijer B, Hooykaas PJ, Farrand SK, et al. (2000) The <lb/>bases of crown gall tumorigenesis. J Bacteriol 182: 3885–3895. <lb/>66. Glasner JD, Marquez-Villavicencio M, Kim H-S, Jahn CE, Ma B, et al. (2008) <lb/>Niche-Specificity and the Variable Fraction of the Pectobacterium Pan-Genome. <lb/>Mol Plant Microbe Interact 21: 1549–1560. <lb/>67. &apos;t Hoen PAC, Ariyurek Y, Thygesen HH, Vreugdenhil E, Vossen RHAM, et al. <lb/>(2008) Deep sequencing-based expression analysis shows major advances in <lb/>robustness, resolution and inter-lab portability over five microarray platforms. <lb/>Nucleic Acids Res 36: e141. <lb/>68. Mardis ER (2008) The impact of next-generation sequencing technology on <lb/>genetics. Trends Genet 24: 133–141. <lb/>69. Pop M, Salzberg S (2008) Bioinformatics challenges of new sequencing <lb/>technology. Trends Genet 24: 142–149. <lb/>70. Coppée J-Y (2008) Do DNA microarrays have their future behind them? <lb/>Microbes Infect 10: 1067–1071. <lb/>71. Pritchard L, White JA, Birch RJ, Toth IK (2006) GenomeDiagram: a python <lb/>package for the visualization of large-scale genomic data. Bioinformatics 22: <lb/>616–617. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Microarray Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS Computational Biology | www.ploscompbiol.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>17 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">August 2009 | Volume 5 | Issue 8 | e1000473</note> 

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
