<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Submitted 14 September 2018 <lb/>Accepted 7 December 2018 <lb/>Published 29 January 2019 <lb/>Corresponding author <lb/>Pilar Sainz de Baranda, <lb/>psainzdebaranda@um.es <lb/>Academic editor <lb/>Antonio Palazón-Bru <lb/>Additional Information and <lb/>Declarations can be found on <lb/>page 10 <lb/>DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/>Copyright <lb/>2019 Cejudo et al. <lb/>Distributed under <lb/>Creative Commons CC-BY 4.0 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Age-related differences in flexibility in <lb/>soccer players 8-19 years old <lb/>Antonio Cejudo 1 , Francisco Javier Robles-Palazón 1 , Francisco Ayala 2 , <lb/>Mark De Ste Croix 3 , Enrique Ortega-Toro 1 , Fernando Santonja-Medina 4 and <lb/>Pilar Sainz de Baranda 1 <lb/>1 Department Physical Activity and Sport/Faculty of Sport Sciences/Campus of Excellence Mare Nostrum, <lb/>Universidad de Murcia, Murcia, Spain <lb/>2 School of Physical Education, Faculty of Sport, Health and Social Care, University of Gloucestershire, <lb/>Gloucester, United Kingdom <lb/>3 School of Sport and Exercise, University of Gloucestershire, Gloucester, United Kingdom <lb/>4 Virgen de la Arrixaca University Hospital/Faculty of Medicine/Campus of Excellence Mare Nostrum, <lb/>Universidad de Murcia, Murcia, Spain <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background. Muscle flexibility is a main component of health-related fitness and one <lb/>of the basic components of fitness for the performance in some sports. Sport and health <lb/>professionals require the flexibility profile of soccer to define quantitative aims in the <lb/>training of flexibility. The aim of this study was to identify age-related differences in <lb/>lower extremity flexibility in youth soccer players. <lb/>Methods. Seventy-two young male soccer players (age: 13.0 ± 3.1 y; body mass: <lb/>50.5 ± 15.3 kg; stature 158.2 ± 16.8 cm; BMI: 19.6 ± 2.6 kg/m 2 ) completed this <lb/>study. Measures of eleven passive hip (hip extension (HE), hip adduction with hip <lb/>flexed 90 • (HAD-HF90 • ), hip flexion with knee flexed (HF-KF) and extended (HF-KE), <lb/>hip abduction with hip neutral (HAB) and hip flexed 90 • (HAB-HF90 • ), hip external <lb/>(HER) and internal (HIR) rotation), knee (knee flexion (KF)) and ankle dorsiflexion <lb/>(ankle dorsiflexion with knee flexed (ADF-KF) and extended (ADF-KE)) ranges of <lb/>motion (ROM) were taken. Descriptive statistics were calculated for hip, knee and ankle <lb/>ROM measured separately by leg (dominant and non-dominant) and age-group (U10, <lb/>U12, U14, U16 and U19). The data was analysed using a one-way analysis of variance <lb/>(ANOVA) to examine the interaction of 11 ROM in the different players&apos; age-group. <lb/>Results. Generally, U10 and/or U12 soccer players obtain the highest mean value in <lb/>almost all ROM evaluated (U10: HAD-HF [39.6 • <lb/>± 4.3 • ], ADF-KE [32.3 • <lb/>± 4.1 • ], <lb/>HER [63.5 • <lb/>± 5.6 • ] and HAB-HF90 • [64.1 • <lb/>± 7.5 • ]; U12: HE [17.7 • <lb/>± 6.2 • ], HAB <lb/>[35.6 • <lb/>± 3.0], HIR [60.8 • <lb/>± 4.7 • ] and KF [133.8 • <lb/>± 7.1 • ]). Nonetheless, significant <lb/>differences between the players&apos; age-groups are just found in HAD-HF90 • (p = .042; <lb/>ES = .136), HAB (p = .001; ES = .252), HIR (p = .001; ES = .251), HER (p &lt; .001; <lb/>ES = .321) and HAB-HF90 • (p &lt; .001; ES = .376) ROM, showing a progressive and <lb/>irregular decrease in these ROM until the U19 team. <lb/>Conclusion. The findings of this study reinforce the necessity of prescribing exercises <lb/>aimed at improving HAD-HF90 • ROM in U16, HAB ROM in U14, HIR ROM in U16 <lb/>and U19, HER ROM in U12 and U19, and HAB-HF90 • ROM in U16 and U19 players <lb/>within everyday soccer training routines. <lb/>Subjects Orthopedics, Pediatrics <lb/>Keywords Football, Range of motion, Adolescence, Stretching, Age-group <lb/>How to cite this article Cejudo A, Robles-Palazón FJ, Ayala F, De Ste Croix M, Ortega-Toro E, Santonja-Medina F, Sainz de Baranda P. <lb/>2019. Age-related differences in flexibility in soccer players 8-19 years old. PeerJ 7:e6236 http://doi.org/10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Soccer is by far the world&apos;s most popular sport (Dvorak, Junge &amp; Graf-Baumann, 2004). <lb/>According to the survey conducted by the International Federation of Association Football <lb/>(FIFA) in 2006, more than 270 million participants played soccer in the world and most <lb/>of them were male players (90% of all registered players), with younger soccer players <lb/>comprising the greatest proportion (54.7%) (FIFA, 2006). <lb/>Soccer requires players to perform many repeated high intensity movements such as <lb/>sudden acceleration and deceleration, lots of changes of direction, jumping and landing <lb/>tasks, as well as many situations in which players are involved in tackling to keep or obtain <lb/>possession of the ball (Krustrup et al., 2010). Optimal performance in these actions depends <lb/>upon a variety of anthropometrical and physiological properties (Arnason et al., 2004; Pion <lb/>et al., 2015; Stolen et al., 2005). For example, body composition has been identified as <lb/>an important factor which could adjust the performance in soccer players across the <lb/>season due to the contribution that body fat and lean muscle mass have on some physical <lb/>abilities (Carling &amp; Orhant, 2010; Milanese et al., 2015). Likewise, some authors identified <lb/>endurance, repeated-sprint ability, velocity, agility and strength as the main properties and <lb/>optimal performance factors in this sport (Haugen, Tonnessen &amp; Seiler, 2013; Rebelo et al., <lb/>2014; Stolen et al., 2005; Wong et al., 2015). Nevertheless, it seems anthropometrical and <lb/>physiological demands are specific for each soccer player and depend on the participants&apos; <lb/>sex, position and age (Di Salvo et al., 2007; Le Gall et al., 2010; Oyón et al., 2016; Wong et <lb/>al., 2009). <lb/>Muscle flexibility is a main component of health-related fitness, and one of the basic <lb/>components of the performance in some sports (Kraemer &amp; Gómez, 2001); in soccer, <lb/>deficits in some ranges of motion might restrict specific technical skills and reduce players&apos; <lb/>performance (García-Pinillos et al., 2015; Mills et al., 2015; Nunome et al., 2006). Although <lb/>there is no consistent scientific evidence about the relationship between flexibility and <lb/>injury risk, it seems lower range of motion values in soccer players could also increase <lb/>the risk of some muscle injuries (Bradley &amp; Portas, 2007; Henderson, Barnes &amp; Portas, <lb/>2010; Witvrouw et al., 2003). In sport, it has been observed that flexibility is subject to <lb/>sex (Gómez-Landero, Vernetta &amp; López-Bedoya, 2013; Kibler &amp; Chandler, 2003), tactical <lb/>position (Oberg et al., 1984; Sporis et al., 2011), dominant laterality (Bittencourt et al., 2014; <lb/>Rahnama, Lees &amp; Bambaecichi, 2005) and competitive level (Rubini, Costa &amp; Gomes, 2007). <lb/>However, there are few articles where muscle flexibility was directly related to the age of <lb/>soccer players (Malina et al., 2007; Manning &amp; Hudson, 2009; Nikolaïdis, 2012; Vaeyens et <lb/>al., 2006). A general trend towards the flexibility reduction over ages has been reported by <lb/>previous studies conducted in non-athlete population (McKay et al., 2017). The knowledge <lb/>of flexibility changes in relation to the age of soccer players could show the variation of <lb/>this capability throughout the different phases of sport specialization, providing useful <lb/>information about the critical flexibility stages and the primary affected muscles to physical <lb/>trainers. Therefore, the aim of this study is to identify age-related differences in lower <lb/>extremity flexibility in young soccer players. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>2/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1 Demographic variables of the players of a soccer club (mean ± standard deviation). <lb/>U10 (n = 16) <lb/>U12 (n = 15) <lb/>U14 (n = 13) <lb/>U16 (n = 15) <lb/>U19 (n = 13) <lb/>Total (n = 72) <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>8.9 ± 0.9 <lb/>11.6 ± 0.5 <lb/>12.7 ± .7 <lb/>14.9 ± 0.7 <lb/>17.7 ± .8 <lb/>13.0 ± 3.1 <lb/>Body mass (kg) <lb/>33.5 ± 6.3 <lb/>39.7 ± 6.4 <lb/>52.1 ± 8.8 <lb/>62.0 ± 9.1 <lb/>70.2 ± 5.2 <lb/>50.5 ± 15.3 <lb/>Height (cm) <lb/>136.4 ± 6.7 <lb/>149.3 ± 8.3 <lb/>161.0 ± 8.7 <lb/>172.2 ± 7.7 <lb/>176.9 ± 5.5 <lb/>158.2 ± 16.8 <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>17.9 ± 2.21 <lb/>17.6 ± 1.1 <lb/>19.7 ± 2.3 <lb/>20.5 ± 1.8 <lb/>22.6 ± 1.8 <lb/>19.6 ± 2.6 <lb/>Notes. <lb/>BMI, body mass index. <lb/>MATERIALS &amp; METHODS <lb/>Participants <lb/>Seventy-two young soccer players completed this study. The participants were recruited <lb/>from five different teams (U10 = 16 players; U12 = 15 players; U14 = 13 players; U16 = <lb/>15 players; U19 = 13 players) of a youth soccer academy (Table 1). All the participants <lb/>were outfield players and participated regularly in sport (3-4 training sessions and 1 <lb/>match per week). Also, none of the participants were involved in systematic and specific <lb/>stretching regimes in the last 6 months, apart from the 1-2 sets of 8-10 s of static stretches <lb/>designated for the major muscles of the lower extremities (e.g., hamstrings, quadriceps, <lb/>adductors and triceps surae) that were performed daily during their pre-exercise warm-up <lb/>and post-exercise cool down phases. <lb/>The exclusion criterion was history of orthopaedic problems to the knee, thigh, hip, or <lb/>lower back in the last 3 months due to the fact that residual symptoms could have an impact <lb/>in the habitual players&apos; movement competency and/or lower extremity ROM profile. The <lb/>study was conducted at the end of the preseason phase of the year 2016. The time frame of <lb/>the study was selected to make sure that the players recruited to each team were definitive <lb/>and stable within the testing period. <lb/>Before any participation, experimental procedures and potential risks were fully <lb/>explained to both parents and children in verbal and written form, and written informed <lb/>consent was obtained. The experimental procedures used in this study were in accordance <lb/>with the Declaration of Helsinki and were approved by the Ethics and Scientific Committee <lb/>of the University of Murcia (Spain) (ID: 1551/2017). <lb/>Testing procedure <lb/>The passive hip extension (HE), hip adduction with hip flexed 90 • (HAD-HF90 • ), hip <lb/>flexion with knee flexed (HF-KF) and extended (HF-KE), hip abduction with hip neutral <lb/>(HAB) and hip flexed 90 • (HAB-HF90 • ), hip external (HER) and internal (HIR) rotation, <lb/>knee flexion (KF), ankle dorsiflexion with knee flexed (ADF-KF) and extended (ADF-KE) <lb/>ROM of the dominant and non-dominant leg were assessed following the methodology <lb/>previously described (Cejudo et al., 2014a) (Fig. 1). <lb/>These tests were selected because they have been considered appropriate by American <lb/>Medical Organizations, American Academy of Orthopedic Association (1965) and American <lb/>Medical Association (Gerhardt, Cocchiarella &amp; Lea, 2002) and included in manuals of <lb/>sports medicine and science (Magee, 2002; Palmer &amp; Epler, 2002) based on reliability and <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>3/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1 Lower extremity ranges of motion of the &apos;&apos;ROM-SPORT&apos;&apos; protocol. (A) Hip flexion with knee <lb/>flexed test (HF-KF); (B) Hip flexion with knee extended test (HF-KE); (C) Hip extension test (HE); (D) <lb/>Hip addution with hip flexed 90 • test (HAD-HF90 • ); (E) hip abduction with hip neutral test (HAB); (F) <lb/>hip abduction with hip flexed 90 • test (HAB-HF90 • ); (G) Hip internal rotation test (HIR); (H) Hip exter-<lb/>nal rotation test (HER); (I) Knee flexion test (KF); (J) Ankle dorsiflexion with knee extended test (ADF-<lb/>KE); (K) Ankle dorsiflexion with knee flexed test (ADF-KF). <lb/>Full-size DOI: 10.7717/peerj.6236/fig-1 <lb/>validity studies, anatomical knowledge, and extensive clinical and sport experience (Cejudo <lb/>et al., 2015a; Cejudo et al., 2015b; Cejudo et al., 2014b). In addition, the intra-operator <lb/>variability was analysed for each muscle flexibility measure using a test-retest design. <lb/>Before data collection, the reliability coefficient was evaluated on 20 healthy athletes. The <lb/>range of motion was measured twice with a 2-week interval. An interclass correlation <lb/>coefficient (ICC) and the minimal detectable change at 95% confidence interval (MDC 95 ) <lb/>were calculated from the results of subsequent measurements. Results of pre-and-post-<lb/>measurements showed a high reliability coefficient in all the tests (HF-KF [0.94], HF-KE <lb/>[0.97], HE [0.97], HAD-HF [0.97], HAB [0.95], HAB-HF90 • [0.96], HER [0.96], HIR <lb/>[0.96], KF [0.95], ADF-KE [0.95], and ADF-KF [0.95]). The MDC 95 for each flexibility <lb/>measure ranged from 3.7 • to 6.9 • (HF-KF [6.2 • ], HF-KE [6.1 • ], HE [3.7 • ], HAD-HF [5 • ], <lb/>HAB [5.5 • ], HAB-HF90 • [4.7 • ], HER [4.7 • ], HIR [4.1 • ], KF [6.9 • ], ADF-KE [4.7 • ], and <lb/>ADF-KF [5 • ]). <lb/>One week before the start of the study, all the soccer players completed a familiarization <lb/>session with the purpose of getting to know the correct technical execution of the <lb/>exploratory tests by means of the practical realization of each one of them. The dominant leg <lb/>was defined as the participant&apos;s preferred kicking leg. All tests were carried out by the same <lb/>two sport scientists (one conducted the tests and the other ensured proper testing position <lb/>of the participants throughout the assessment manoeuvre) under stable environmental <lb/>conditions. The sport scientists were blinded to the purpose of the study and to the test <lb/>results from previous testing sessions. <lb/>Prior to the testing session, all participants performed the dynamic warm-up designed by <lb/>Taylor et al. (2009). The overall duration of the entire warm-up was approximately 20 min. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>4/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>A 3-5 min rest interval between the end of the warm-up and beginning of the ROM <lb/>assessment was given to the soccer players because in a pilot study with 10 participants of <lb/>similar age and training status, sometime was required for practical reasons, like rehydrating <lb/>and drying their sweat prior to the ROM assessment. More importantly, it has been shown <lb/>that the effects elicited by the dynamic warm-up on muscle properties might last more <lb/>than 5 min (Ayala et al., 2016) and hence, decreases in ROM values within the 3-5 min <lb/>rest interval were not expected. <lb/>After the warm-up, soccer players were instructed to perform, in a randomised order, <lb/>two maximal trials of each ROM test for each leg, and the mean score for each test was used <lb/>in the analysis. Soccer players were examined wearing sports clothes and without shoes. A <lb/>30s rest was given between trials, legs and tests. <lb/>For the measurement, an ISOMED Unilevel inclinometer (Portland, Oregon) was used <lb/>with an extendable telescopic rod (Gerhardt, Cocchiarella &amp; Lea, 2002), a metal goniometer <lb/>with long arm (Baseline R Stainless) and &apos;&apos;lumbosant&apos;&apos; -lumbar support-to standardize the <lb/>lumbar curvature (Santonja, Ferrer &amp; Martínez, 1995; Sainz de Baranda et al., 2014). <lb/>Before each assessment session, the inclinometer was calibrated to 0 • with either the <lb/>vertical or horizontal axis. The angle between the longitudinal axis of the mobilized <lb/>segment was recorded (following its bisector) with the vertical or the horizontal (Cejudo et <lb/>al., 2014a; Gerhardt, Cocchiarella &amp; Lea, 2002). Regarding the assessment of hip abduction <lb/>movement, a metal goniometer of long arm (Baseline R Stainless) was used. <lb/>One or both of the following criteria determined the endpoint for each test: (a) an <lb/>examiner palpable or appreciated some compensation movement that increased the ROM <lb/>onset of pelvic rotation, and/or (b) the soccer player feeling a strong but tolerable stretch, <lb/>slightly before the occurrence of pain (Cejudo et al., 2014b). <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Prior to the statistical analysis, the distribution of raw data sets was checked using the <lb/>Kolmogorov-Smirnov test and demonstrated that all data had a normal distribution <lb/>(p &gt; .05). Descriptive statistics including means and standard deviations were calculated for <lb/>hip, knee and ankle ROM measurements, separately by leg (dominant and non-dominant). <lb/>Dependent sample t-tests were carried out to assess differences between the values of the <lb/>dominant and non-dominant sides. Also, data was analysed using a one-way analysis of <lb/>variance (ANOVA) to examine the interaction of 11 ROM at different youth teams. Post <lb/>hoc comparisons were made using the Bonferroni test for pair wise comparisons. Analysis <lb/>was completed using SPSS version 20 (SPSS Inc, Chicago, IL, USA). The effect sizes (ES) <lb/>of each variable were tested using eta squared (η2) between groups (.01 = small effect, .06 <lb/>= medium effect, and .14 = large effect (Cohen, 1988). Statistical significance was set at <lb/>p &lt; .05. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Statistical analysis reported no differences between dominant and non-dominant sides <lb/>for each ROM value, so the mean scores were used for comparing age-groups. Table 2 <lb/>shows the results of the 11 ROM variables of the ROM-SPORT protocol in soccer players, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>5/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2 Outfield based players&apos; descriptive values (mean ± SD) for 11 passive ranges of motion in the five categories analyzed (n = 72). <lb/>Range of <lb/>motion (grades) <lb/>U10 <lb/>(n = 16) <lb/>U12 <lb/>(n = 15) <lb/>U14 <lb/>(n = 13) <lb/>U16 <lb/>(n = 15) <lb/>U19 <lb/>(n = 13) <lb/>Total <lb/>(n = 72) <lb/>HE <lb/>16.8 • <lb/>± 8.1 • <lb/>17.7 • <lb/>± 6.2 • <lb/>12.4 • <lb/>± 4.9 • <lb/>12.3 • <lb/>± 8.1 • <lb/>11.4 • <lb/>± 6.0 • <lb/>14.3 • <lb/>± 7.2 • <lb/>HAD-HF90 • <lb/>39.6 • <lb/>± 4.3 •d <lb/>38.1 • <lb/>± 4.1 • <lb/>38.4 • <lb/>± 3.2 • <lb/>34.9 • <lb/>± 5.4 •a <lb/>36.2 • <lb/>± 4.8 • <lb/>37.5 • <lb/>± 4.6 • <lb/>ADF-KE <lb/>32.3 • <lb/>± 4.1 • <lb/>29.7 • <lb/>± 3.8 • <lb/>31.3 • <lb/>± 3.3 • <lb/>31.6 • <lb/>± 5.1 • <lb/>30.6 • <lb/>± 3.9 • <lb/>31.1 • <lb/>± 4.1 • <lb/>ADF-KF <lb/>36.4 • <lb/>± 4.0 • <lb/>34.8 • <lb/>± 4.1 <lb/>36.5 • <lb/>± 4.6 • <lb/>35.8 • <lb/>± 4.8 • <lb/>34.6 • <lb/>± 4.2 • <lb/>35.6 • <lb/>± 4.3 • <lb/>HAB <lb/>34.5 • <lb/>± 3.7 •c <lb/>35.6 • <lb/>±3.0 c,d <lb/>29.6 • <lb/>± 4.9 •a,b,e <lb/>31.5 • <lb/>± 4.5 •b <lb/>34.4 • <lb/>± 2.9 •c <lb/>33.2 • <lb/>± 4.4 • <lb/>HIR <lb/>55.7 • <lb/>± 8.5 • <lb/>60.8 • <lb/>± 4.7 •d,e <lb/>55.4 • <lb/>± 7.7 • <lb/>49.5 • <lb/>± 8.1 •b <lb/>49.6 • <lb/>± 8.4 •b <lb/>54.3 • <lb/>± 8.5 • <lb/>HER <lb/>63.5 • <lb/>± 5.6 •b,e <lb/>50.1 • <lb/>± 4.8 •a,d <lb/>55.7 • <lb/>± 12.7 • <lb/>61.2 • <lb/>± 5.6 •b,e <lb/>50.4 • <lb/>± 11.1 •a,d <lb/>56.4 • <lb/>± 9.8 • <lb/>HAB-HF90 • <lb/>64.1 • <lb/>± 7.5 •c,d,e <lb/>62.8 • <lb/>± 4.8 •c,d,e <lb/>55.3 • <lb/>± 5.4 •a,b <lb/>53.9 • <lb/>± 6.1 •a,b <lb/>53.3 • <lb/>± 6.8 •a,b <lb/>58.1 • <lb/>± 7.6 • <lb/>HF-KE <lb/>70.0 • <lb/>± 9.8 • <lb/>69.7 • <lb/>± 7.8 • <lb/>70.3 • <lb/>± 8.5 • <lb/>73.4 • <lb/>± 9.9 • <lb/>74.4 • <lb/>± 8.2 • <lb/>71.5 • <lb/>± 8.9 • <lb/>KF <lb/>130.8 • <lb/>± 15.1 • <lb/>133.8 • <lb/>± 7.1 • <lb/>127.0 • <lb/>± 9.1 • <lb/>124.8 • <lb/>± 10.6 • <lb/>120.4 • <lb/>± 16.4 • <lb/>127.6 • <lb/>± 12.7 • <lb/>HF-KF <lb/>136.8 • <lb/>± 9.1 • <lb/>135.2 • <lb/>± 5.6 • <lb/>136.3 • <lb/>± 3.7 • <lb/>131.4 • <lb/>± 6.8 • <lb/>136.9 • <lb/>± 7.3 • <lb/>135.3 • <lb/>± 7.0 • <lb/>Notes. <lb/>a Significantly different from U10 (p &lt; .05). <lb/>b Significantly different from U12 (p &lt; .05). <lb/>c Significantly different from U14 (p &lt; .05). <lb/>d Significantly different from U16 (p &lt; .05). <lb/>e Significantly different from U19 (p &lt; .05). <lb/>HE, hip extension test; HAD-HF90 • , hip adduction with hip flexed 90 • extended test; ADF-KE, ankle dorsiflexion with knee extended test; ADF-KF, ankle dorsiflexion with <lb/>knee flexed test; HAB, hip abduction test; HIR, hip internal rotation test; HER, hip external rotation test; HAB-HF90 • , hip abduction with hip flexed 90 • test; HF-KE, hip <lb/>flexion with knee extended test; KF, knee flexion test; HF-KF, hip flexion with knee flexed test. <lb/>differentiating the data between the 5 youth teams. Generally, U10 and/or U12 soccer <lb/>players obtained the highest mean value in almost all ROM evaluated (HE, HAD-HF, <lb/>ADF-KE, HAB, HIR, HER, HAB-HF90 • and KF). Nonetheless, significant differences <lb/>between the players&apos; age-group (large effect) are only found in HAD-HF90 • (F 4,67 = 2.629; <lb/>p = .042; ES = .136), HAB (F 4,67 = 5.642; p = .001; ES = .252), HIR (F 4,67 = 5.624; p = .001; <lb/>ES = 0.251), HER (F 4,67 = 7.930; p &lt; .001; ES = .321) and HAB-HF90 • (F 4,67 = 10.074; <lb/>p &lt; .001; ES = .376) ROM, showing a progressive and irregular decrease in these ROM <lb/>until the U19 team. On the contrary, the greatest mean value in the HF-KE (F 4,67 = .847; <lb/>p = .501; ES = .048) and HF-KF (F 4,67 = 1.674; p = .166; ES = .091) ROM is observed in <lb/>U19 players, but these differences are not statistically significant. <lb/>U10 players report the highest values in HAD-HF90 • , HER and HAB-HF90 • ROM. The <lb/>Bonferroni post hoc comparisons reflect statistical differences with U16 players (p = .035) <lb/>in HAD-HF90 • , U12 (p &lt; .001) and U19 (p = .001) players in HER, and U14 (p = .003), <lb/>U16 (p &lt; .001) and U19 (p &lt; .001) players in HAB-HF90 • . U12 players obtained the <lb/>highest ROM in HAB and HIR; the Bonferroni post hoc comparisons showed statistical <lb/>differences with U14 (p = .001) and U16 (p = .04) in HAB, and U16 (p = .001) and U19 <lb/>(p = .003) in HIR. The Bonferroni post hoc test also indicated significant differences <lb/>between U12 players and U14 (p = .019), U16 (p = .002) and U19 (p = .001) soccer players <lb/>in HAB-HF90 • ROM. Finally, the Bonferroni post hoc test showed significant differences <lb/>in U14 vs. U10 (p = .011) and U14 vs. U19 (p = .021) in HAB, and U16 vs. U12 (p = .005) <lb/>and U16 vs. U19 (p = 0.01) soccer players in HER (Fig. 2). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>6/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2 Age-related demands in flexibility in soccer players 8-19 years old. Statistically significant dif-<lb/>ferences between age group (p ≤ .040) with U10, U12, U14, U16, U19. (A) HAB: hip abduction with hip <lb/>neutral test; (B) HAB-HF90 • : hip abduction with hip flexed 90 • test; (C) HER: hip external rotation test; <lb/>(D) HIR: hip internal rotation test; (E) HAD-HF90 • : hip adduction with hip flexed 90 • test. <lb/>Full-size DOI: 10.7717/peerj.6236/fig-2 <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>The purpose of the current study was to identify age-related differences in lower extremity <lb/>flexibility in young soccer players. The principal results of this research indicated that the <lb/>U10 and U12 soccer players had the highest values in several (HE, HAD-HF, ADF-KE, <lb/>HAB, HIR, HER, HAB-HF90 • and KF), but not all (HF-KE and HF-KF) of the ROM <lb/>assessed in comparison with their counterpart older players. <lb/>Flexibility seems to decline with age (Medeiros, Araújo &amp; Araújo, 2013). Johns &amp; <lb/>Wright (1962) determined that the relative contributions of soft tissue to total resistance <lb/>encountered at a joint are as follows: joint capsules, 47%; muscle and its fascia, 41%; <lb/>tendons and ligaments, 10%; and skin, 2%. Evidence suggests that biological changes such <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>7/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>as tendon stiffening, joint capsule changes, or muscle changes could be responsible factors <lb/>for the age-related decrease in flexibility (Adams, O&apos;shea &amp; O&apos;shea, 1999). In this sense, <lb/>our data supports this statement showing a slight tendency to reduce the ROM during <lb/>different periods of soccer practice (specially in HE, HIR, HAB-HF90 • and HAD-HF90 • <lb/>ROM (Fig. 2)). A similar pattern in some of the hip ROM over the development phases <lb/>was previously reported by Manning &amp; Hudson (2009) who also found significant lower <lb/>ROM values in HE, HIR, HAB-HF90 • in senior soccer players compared to their equals&apos; <lb/>young players. The poor flexibility showed by older players in these ROM may also reflect <lb/>an adaptive response to playing soccer of soft tissue around the joints that improves <lb/>stability at the specific joint, or lack of attention to flexibility practices in training (Ostojić <lb/>&amp; Stojanović, 2007). Thus, training and repetition of specific soccer skills like kicking the <lb/>ball might explain the reduction of scores in HIR, HE and HAB-HF90o tests throughout <lb/>the different age-groups as a result of adaptation to this continuous contraction of external <lb/>hip rotator, hip flexor and hip adductor muscles. Indeed, these kicking adaptations would <lb/>be in agreement with the lower values found by López-Valenciano et al. (2019) in his recent <lb/>study in professional soccer players in HE (8.9 • ) and HIR (47.1 • ) ROM. Taking into <lb/>account that these reductions could predispose players to abnormal movement patterns <lb/>and increase the degeneration or capsular tightening in the hip joint (Manning &amp; Hudson, <lb/>2009), it is essential to perform stretching exercises aiming to improve the hip ROM. <lb/>On the contrary, older players have shown better values of ROM in HF-KF and, mainly, <lb/>in HF-KE. The HF-KE test assesses the flexibility of hamstring muscles. Some previous <lb/>studies have also shown similar increases in older soccer players&apos; hamstring flexibility in <lb/>comparison with their younger counterparts using the sit-and-reach test (Nikolaïdis, 2012; <lb/>Vaeyens et al., 2006). During the early childhood and adolescence ages the growth of bone <lb/>and muscle play important roles in force development, musculoskeletal loading and motor <lb/>control during childhood. Differential bone growth (femur) in relation to muscle length <lb/>can result in a decrease in flexibility (hamstring) and strength (De Ste Croix &amp; Korff, 2013). <lb/>In addition, these muscles have been the most studied muscle group by scientific literature, <lb/>given that they represent one of the most injured areas in sport, in general, and soccer, <lb/>in particular (Nogueira et al., 2017; Price et al., 2004). Several published injury prevention <lb/>programs include hamstring dynamic or static stretching exercises in order to increase <lb/>the flexibility in these muscles (DiStefano et al., 2009; Kiani et al., 2010). Perhaps, the great <lb/>incidence rates of hamstring injuries could explain an increase in the use of flexibility <lb/>training as a hamstring injury prevention strategy by the practitioners, allowing better <lb/>scores in HF-KE test in more trained athletes. Likewise, repetitive soccer skills as kicking <lb/>the ball where a hip flexion is performed accompanied by a knee almost full extended could <lb/>be a feasible reason to explain why older players present higher values in HF-KE ROM. <lb/>These adaptations in HF-KE ROM will be again in agreement with the results shown by <lb/>López-Valenciano et al. (2019) in professional soccer players (80.3 • HF-KE ROM). <lb/>Appropriate body status requires a minimum of flexibility to respond to the demands of <lb/>sport practise. Although there is no strong scientific evidence, flexibility appears to be also <lb/>necessary for sport performance in youth. In U16 soccer players, greater flexibility of the <lb/>lower back and upper thigh might discriminate players with high skill levels (Vaeyens et al., <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>8/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>2006); in young soccer players with an age range from 14 to 18 year olds, hamstring flexibility <lb/>was established as a key factor for performing football-specific skills, such as sprinting, <lb/>jumping, agility, and kicking (García-Pinillos et al., 2015). The efficacy of the traditional <lb/>stretching techniques (such as static, dynamic, PNF or ballistic) in the improvement of <lb/>ROM results have been reported in several studies (Ayala, Sainz de Baranda &amp; Cejudo, <lb/>2012; Ayala, Sainz de Baranda &amp; De Ste Croix, 2012; Ayala et al., 2013; Sainz de Baranda &amp; <lb/>Ayala, 2010); by the same token, new protocols as the combination of traditional techniques <lb/>with electrical stimulation (Piqueras-Rodríguez, Palazón-Bru &amp; Gil-Guillén, 2016) have <lb/>shown important enhancements in the flexibility of soccer players with reduced ROM. <lb/>Therefore, the inclusion of sport-specific flexibility work in training routines could help to <lb/>increase the ROM values and to improve sport performance. The appropriate stretching <lb/>protocols and work-loads have to be selected by the practitioners to increase flexibility and <lb/>to maintain it throughout the distinct stages of youth physical development, following the <lb/>recommendations proposed by Lloyd &amp; Oliver (2012). Specially, these exercises should be <lb/>aimed at young players with limited ROM; so it is essential to evaluate athletes&apos; flexibility <lb/>profile. On this matter, new predictive mobile apps have been published to determine <lb/>boy soccer players with a higher muscle (hamstring) ROM restriction which can be used <lb/>to make a simple and quickly assessment of our soccer teams (Piqueras-Rodríguez et al., <lb/>2016). <lb/>However, it is unclear what level of flexibility is optimum to improve performance and <lb/>to prevent injuries in soccer. Optimal values may vary between muscle groups and different <lb/>sports (Ostojić &amp; Stojanović, 2007; Sainz de Baranda et al., 2015); while a swimmer needs <lb/>higher values in the shoulder and ankle ROM, a dancer requires huge values in almost <lb/>all (upper and lower extremity) ROM. Even within the same sport, the optimal values <lb/>depend on the demands of the players&apos; position and age; the goalkeeper will need distinct <lb/>upper extremity ROM than the field player, and the differences in the movement patterns <lb/>developed by children and adolescents will possibly require diverse degrees of ROM (as <lb/>it happens with knee angular velocity in kicking (Kellis &amp; Katis, 2007). The current study <lb/>intends to analyse the flexibility differences between young soccer players in relation to <lb/>their chronological age. Due to the lack of flexibility normative values in youth soccer, <lb/>the flexibility profile derived from our results could be used as minimum objective scores <lb/>to achieve in each age-group. Nonetheless, and having into account that soccer success <lb/>is based on many different variables (Nikolaidis et al., 2014), it is necessary to publish <lb/>prospective cohort studies adopting holistic approaches for predicting the exact cut off <lb/>score in each physical skill that implies a higher sport performance and lower injury risk. <lb/>One of the principal limitations of this research was the sample size used in each group <lb/>(U10, U12, U14, U16 and U19); the limited number of players in each of the youth academy <lb/>teams hinders the athletes&apos; involvement. Other limitation could be that neither index of <lb/>maturity nor player position was assessed within the study. Future studies should analyse <lb/>possible differences in flexibility in regard to players&apos; maturational status and tactical <lb/>position. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>9/16 <lb/></page>

			<body>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>U10 and U12 soccer players display highest values in five of the ROM assessed (HAD-<lb/>HF90 • , HAB, HIR, HER, HAB-HF90 • ). On the contrary, older players (U19) showed <lb/>better ROM in HF-KE and HF-KF tests in comparison with their younger peers. The <lb/>ROM reductions in internal and external hip rotation and hip adduction and abduction <lb/>movements throughout the studied ages could explain an adaptive response of the muscles <lb/>involved in playing soccer. The ROM restriction could predispose players to abnormal <lb/>movement patterns and increase the risk of future injuries in the joints involved. Thus, the <lb/>findings of this study reinforce the necessity of prescribing exercises aimed at improving <lb/>HAD-HF90 • ROM in U16, HAB ROM in U14, HIR ROM in U16 and U19, HER ROM <lb/>in U12 and U19, and HAB-HF90 • ROM in U16 and U19 players within everyday soccer <lb/>training routines. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">ADDITIONAL INFORMATION AND DECLARATIONS <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This research was made possible by the Program of Human Resources Formation for Science <lb/>and Technology grant number 20326/FPI/2017 from the Seneca Foundation-Agency for <lb/>Science and Technology in the Region of Murcia (Spain). This study is part of the project <lb/>entitled &apos;&apos;Estudio del riesgo de lesión en jóvenes deportistas a través de redes de inteligencia <lb/>artificial&apos;&apos;, funded by the Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation (DEP2017-88775-P), <lb/>the State Research Agency (AEI) and the European Regional Development Fund (ERDF). <lb/>The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, <lb/>or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/> Grant Disclosures <lb/>The following grant information was disclosed by the authors: <lb/>Program of Human Resources Formation for Science and Technology: 20326/FPI/2017. <lb/>Seneca Foundation-Agency for Science and Technology in the Region of Murcia (Spain). <lb/>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation: DEP2017-88775-P. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing Interests <lb/>The authors declare there are no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>• Antonio Cejudo conceived and designed the experiments, performed the experiments, <lb/>analyzed the data, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the <lb/>paper, approved the final draft. <lb/>• Francisco Javier Robles-Palazón performed the experiments, prepared figures and/or <lb/>tables, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the final draft. <lb/>• Francisco Ayala performed the experiments, analyzed the data, contributed <lb/>reagents/materials/analysis tools, approved the final draft. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>10/16 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">• Mark De Ste Croix contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed <lb/>drafts of the paper, approved the final draft. <lb/>• Enrique Ortega-Toro analyzed the data, contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools, <lb/>approved the final draft. <lb/>• Fernando Santonja-Medina conceived and designed the experiments, contributed <lb/>reagents/materials/analysis tools, authored or reviewed drafts of the paper, approved the <lb/>final draft. <lb/>• Pilar Sainz de Baranda conceived and designed the experiments, contributed <lb/>reagents/materials/analysis tools, prepared figures and/or tables, authored or reviewed <lb/>drafts of the paper, approved the final draft. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Human Ethics <lb/>The following information was supplied relating to ethical approvals (i.e., approving body <lb/>and any reference numbers): <lb/>The experimental procedures used in this study were approved by the Ethics and <lb/>Scientific Committee of the University of Murcia (Spain) (ID: 1551/2017). <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data Availability <lb/>The following information was supplied regarding data availability: <lb/>The raw data is provided in the Dataset 1. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Supplemental Information <lb/>Supplemental information for this article can be found online at http://dx.doi.org/10.7717/ <lb/>peerj.6236#supplemental-information. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Adams K, O&apos;shea P, O&apos;shea KL. 1999. Aging: its effects on strength, power, flexibility, <lb/>and bone density. Strength &amp; Conditioning Journal 21(2):65-77. <lb/>American Academy of Orthopedic Association. 1965. Joint motion: method of measuring <lb/>and recording. Chicago: Park Ridge. <lb/>Arnason A, Sigurdsson SB, Gudmundsson A, Holme I, Engebretsen L, Bahr R. 2004. <lb/>Risk factors for injuries in football. The American Journal of Sports Medicine 32(1 <lb/>suppl):5S-16S DOI 10.1177/0363546503258912. <lb/>Ayala F, Sainz de Baranda P, Cejudo A. 2012. El entrenamiento de la flexibilidad: <lb/>técnicas de estiramiento. Revista Andaluza de Medicina del Deporte 5(3):105-112 <lb/>DOI 10.1016/S1888-7546(12)70016-3. <lb/>Ayala F, Moreno-Pérez V, Vera-García FJ, Moya M, Sanz-Rivas D, Fernández-<lb/>Fernández J. 2016. Acute and time-course effects of traditional and dynamic <lb/>warm-up routines in young elite junior tennis players. PLOS ONE 11(4):e0152790 <lb/>DOI 10.1371/journal.pone.0152790. <lb/>Ayala F, Sainz de Baranda P, De Ste Croix M. 2012. Estiramientos en el calentamiento: <lb/>diseño de rutinas e impacto sobre el rendimiento. Revista Internacional de Medicina y <lb/>Ciencias de la Actividad Física y del Deporte 12(46):349-368. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>11/16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Ayala F, Sainz de Baranda P, De Ste Croix M, Santonja F. 2013. Comparison of active <lb/>stretching technique in males with normal and limited hamstring flexibility. Physical <lb/>Therapy in Sport 14(2):98-104 DOI 10.1016/j.ptsp.2012.03.013. <lb/>Bittencourt N, Ocarino J, Sorrentino F, Jales F, Gabriel S, Mendonça L. 2014. Nor-<lb/>mative data for muscle flexibility in male soccer players. British Journal of Sports <lb/>Medicine 48(7):560-674 DOI 10.1136/bjsports-2014-093494.24. <lb/>Bradley P, Portas M. 2007. The relationship between preseason range of motion and <lb/>muscle strain injury in elite soccer players. Journal of Strength and Conditioning <lb/>Research 21(4):1155-1159 DOI 10.1519/R-20416.1. <lb/>Carling C, Orhant E. 2010. Variation in body composition in professional soccer <lb/>players: interseasonal and intraseasonal changes and the effects of exposure time and <lb/>player position. The Journal of Strength &amp; Conditioning Research 24(5):1332-1339 <lb/>DOI 10.1519/JSC.0b013e3181cc6154. <lb/>Cejudo A, Ayala F, Sainz de Baranda P, Santonja F. 2015b. Reliability of two methods of <lb/>clinical examination of the flexibility of the hip adductor muscles. The International <lb/>Journal of Sports Physical Therapy 10(7):976-983. <lb/>Cejudo A, Sainz de Baranda P, Ayala F, Santonja F. 2014a. Perfil de flexibilidad de la <lb/>extremidad inferior en jugadores de fútbol sala. Revista Internacional de Medicina y <lb/>Ciencias de la Actividad Física y el Deporte 14(55):509-525. <lb/>Cejudo A, Sainz de Baranda P, Ayala F, Santonja F. 2014b. A simplified version of <lb/>the weightbearing ankle lunge test: description and test-retest reliability. Manual <lb/>Therapy 36(2):278-285. <lb/>Cejudo A, Sainz de Baranda P, Ayala F, Santonja F. 2015a. Test-retest reliability <lb/>of seven common clinical tests for assessing lower extremity muscle flexibil-<lb/>ity in futsal and handball players. Physical Therapy in Sport 16(2):107-113 <lb/>DOI 10.1016/j.ptsp.2014.05.004. <lb/>Cohen JW. 1988. Statistical power analysis for the behavioral sciences. Hillsdale: Lawrence <lb/>Erlbaum Associates. <lb/>De Ste Croix M, Korff T. 2013. Paediatric biomechanics and motor control: theory and <lb/>application. London: Routledge. <lb/>Di Salvo V, Baron R, Tschan H, Calderon Montero FJ, Bachl N, Pigozzi F. 2007. Per-<lb/>formance characteristics according to playing position in elite soccer. International <lb/>Journal of Sports Medicine 28(3):222-227 DOI 10.1055/s-2006-924294. <lb/>DiStefano LJ, Padua DA, DiStefano MJ, Marshall SW. 2009. Influence of age, sex, <lb/>technique, and exercise program on movement patterns after an anterior cruciate <lb/>ligament injury prevention program in youth soccer players. The American Journal of <lb/>Sports Medicine 37(3):495-505 DOI 10.1177/0363546508327542. <lb/>Dvorak J, Junge A, Graf-Baumann T. 2004. Football is the most popular sport world-<lb/>wide. The American Journal of Sports Medicine 32:S3-S4 <lb/>DOI 10.1177/0363546503262283. <lb/>FIFA. 2006. FIFA big count 2006: 270 million people active in football. Available at <lb/>http:// www.fifa.com/ aboutfifa/ media/ newsid=529882.html. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>12/16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>García-Pinillos F, Ruiz-Ariza A, Moreno del Castillo R, Latorre-Román PÁ. 2015. <lb/>Impact of limited hamstring flexibility on vertical jump, kicking speed, sprint, <lb/>and agility in young football players. Journal of Sports Sciences 33(12):1293-1297 <lb/>DOI 10.1080/02640414.2015.1022577. <lb/>Gerhardt J, Cocchiarella L, Lea R. 2002. The practical guide to range of motion assessment. <lb/>Chicago: American Medical Association. <lb/>Gómez-Landero LA, Vernetta M, López-Bedoya J. 2013. Perfil motor del trampolín <lb/>gimnástico. Revisión taxonómica y nuevas propuestas de clasificación. Revista <lb/>Internacional de Ciencias del Deporte 30(9):60-78. <lb/>Haugen TA, Tonnessen E, Seiler S. 2013. Anaerobic performance testing of professional <lb/>soccer players 1995-2010. International Journal of Sports Physiology and Performance <lb/>8:148-156 DOI 10.1123/ijspp.8.2.148. <lb/>Henderson G, Barnes CA, Portas MD. 2010. Factors associated with increased propen-<lb/>sity for hamstring injury in English Premier League soccer players. Journal of Science <lb/>and Medicine in Sport 13:397-402 DOI 10.1016/j.jsams.2009.08.003. <lb/>Johns RJ, Wright V. 1962. Relative importance of various tissues in joint stiffness. Journal <lb/>of Applied Physiology 17(5):824-828 DOI 10.1152/jappl.1962.17.5.824. <lb/>Kellis E, Katis A. 2007. Biomechanical characteristics and determinants of instep soccer <lb/>kick. Journal of Sports Science &amp; Medicine 6(2):154-165. <lb/>Kiani A, Hellquist E, Ahlqvist K, Gedeborg R, Michaëlsson K, Byberg L. 2010. Preven-<lb/>tion of soccer-related knee injuries in teenaged girls. Archives of Internal Medicine <lb/>170(1):43-49 DOI 10.1001/archinternmed.2009.289. <lb/>Kibler WB, Chandler TJ. 2003. Range of movement in junior tennis player participating <lb/>in an injury risk modification program. Journal of Sports Science and Medicine <lb/>6(1):51-62. <lb/>Kraemer WJ, Gómez AL. 2001. Establisihing a solid fitness base. In: Foran B, ed. High-<lb/>performance sports conditioning. Champaign: Human Kinetics, 3-17. <lb/>Krustrup P, Aagaard P, Nybo L, Petersen J, Mohr M, Bangsbo J. 2010. Recreational <lb/>football as a health promoting activity: a topical review. Scandinavian Journal of <lb/>Medicine &amp; Science in Sports 20(s1):1-13 DOI 10.1111/j.1600-0838.2010.01108.x. <lb/>Le Gall F, Carling C, Williams M, Reilly T. 2010. Anthropometric and Fitness char-<lb/>acteristics of international, professional and amateur male graduate soccer player <lb/>from elite youth academy. Journal of Science and Medicine in Sport 13(1):90-95 <lb/>DOI 10.1016/j.jsams.2008.07.004. <lb/>Lloyd RS, Oliver JL. 2012. The youth physical development model: a new approach to <lb/>long-term athletic development. The Strength &amp; Conditioning Journal 34(3):61-72. <lb/>López-Valenciano A, Ayala F, Vera-García FJ, De Ste CM, Hernández-Sánchez S, Ruiz-<lb/>Pérez I, Cejudo A, Santonja F. 2019. Comprehensive profile of hip, knee and ankle <lb/>ranges of motion in professional football players. The Journal of Sports Medicine and <lb/>Physical Fitness 59(1):102-109. <lb/>Magee DJ. 2002. Orthopedic physical assessment. 4th edition, vol. 11. Philadelphia: W.B. <lb/>Saunders Company. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>13/16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Malina RM, Ribeiro B, Aroso J, Cumming S. 2007. Characteristics of youth soccer <lb/>players aged 13-15, years classified by skill level. British Journal of Sports Medicine <lb/>41(5):290-295 DOI 10.1136/bjsm.2006.031294. <lb/>Manning C, Hudson Z. 2009. Comparison of hip joint range of motion in profes-<lb/>sional youth and senior team footballers with age-matched controls: an indi-<lb/>cation of early degenerative change? Physical Therapy in Sport 10(1):25-29 <lb/>DOI 10.1016/j.ptsp.2008.11.005. <lb/>McKay MJ, Baldwin JN, Ferreira P, Simic M, Vanicek N, Burns J. 2017. Normative <lb/>reference values for strength and flexibility of 1,000 children and adults. Neurology <lb/>88(1):36-43 DOI 10.1212/WNL.0000000000003466. <lb/>Medeiros HBO, Araújo DSMS, Araújo CGS. 2013. Age-related mobility loss is <lb/>joint-specific: an analysis from 6,000 Flexitest results. Age 35(6):2399-2407 <lb/>DOI 10.1007/s11357-013-9525-z. <lb/>Milanese C, Cavedon V, Corradini G, De Vita F, Zancanaro C. 2015. Seasonal DXA-<lb/>measured body composition changes in professional male soccer players. Journal of <lb/>Sports Sciences 33(12):1219-1228 DOI 10.1080/02640414.2015.1022573. <lb/>Mills M, Frank B, Goto S, Blackburn T, Cates S, Clark M, Aguilar A, Fava N, Padua D. <lb/>2015. Effect of restricted hip flexor muscle length on hip extensor muscle activity and <lb/>lower extremity biomechanics in college-aged female soccer players. International <lb/>Journal of Sports Physical Therapy 10(7):946-954. <lb/>Nikolaïdis PT. 2012. Age-related differences of hamstring flexibility in male soccer play-<lb/>ers. Baltic Journal of Health and Physical Activity 4(2):110-115 <lb/>DOI 10.2478/v10131-012-0012-1. <lb/>Nikolaidis P, Ziv G, Lidor R, Arnon M. 2014. Inter-individual variability in soccer <lb/>players of different age groups playing different positions. Journal of Human Kinetics <lb/>40(1):213-225 DOI 10.2478/hukin-2014-0023. <lb/>Nogueira M, Laiginhas R, Ramos J, Costa O. 2017. Injuries in Portuguese amateur youth <lb/>football players: a six month prospective descriptive study. Acta Médica Portuguesa <lb/>30(12):840-847 DOI 10.20344/amp.8835. <lb/>Nunome H, Ikegami Y, Kozakai R, Apriantono T, Sano S. 2006. Segmental dynamics <lb/>of soccer instep kicking with the preferred and non-preferred leg. Journal of Sports <lb/>Science 24:529-541 DOI 10.1080/02640410500298024. <lb/>Oberg B, Ekstrand J, Möller M, Gillquist J. 1984. Muscle strength and flexibility <lb/>in different positions of soccer players. International Journal of Sports Medicine <lb/>5(4):213-216 DOI 10.1055/s-2008-1025908. <lb/>Ostojić SM, Stojanović MD. 2007. Range of motion in the lower extremity elite vs non-<lb/>elite soccer players. Serbian Journal of Sports Sciences 1(2):74-78. <lb/>Oyón P, Franco L, Rubio FJ, Valero A. 2016. Young women soccer players. Anthropo-<lb/>metric and physiological characteristics. Evolution in a sports season. Archivos de <lb/>Medicina del Deporte 33(1):24-28. <lb/>Palmer ML, Epler ME. 2002. Fundamentos de las técnicas de la evaluación muscu-<lb/>loesquelética. Barcelona: Paidotribo. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>14/16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Pion J, Segers V, Fransen J, Debuyck G, Deprez D, Haerens L, Vaeyens R, Philippaerts <lb/>R, Lenoir M. 2015. Generic anthropometric and performance characteristics among <lb/>elite adolescent boys in nine different sports. European Journal of Sport Science <lb/>15(5):357-366 DOI 10.1080/17461391.2014.944875. <lb/>Piqueras-Rodríguez F, Palazón-Bru A, Gil-Guillén VF. 2016. Effectiveness analysis of <lb/>active stretching versus active stretching plus low-frequency electrical stimulation <lb/>in children who play soccer and who have the short hamstring syndrome. Clinical <lb/>Journal of Sport Medicine 26(1):59-68 DOI 10.1097/JSM.0000000000000188. <lb/>Piqueras-Rodríguez F, Palazón-Bru A, Martínez-St John DRJ, Folgado-de la Rosa <lb/>DM, Gil-Guillén VF. 2016. A tool to quickly detect short hamstring syndrome <lb/>in boys who play soccer. International Journal of Sports Medicine 37(01):1-5 <lb/>DOI 10.1055/s-0036-1597544. <lb/>Price RJ, Hawkins RD, Hulse MA, Hodson A. 2004. The football association medical <lb/>research programme: an audit of injuries in academy youth football. British Journal <lb/>of Sports Medicine 38(4):466-471 DOI 10.1136/bjsm.2003.005165. <lb/>Rahnama N, Lees A, Bambaecichi E. 2005. Comparison of muscle strength and flexibility <lb/>between the preferred and non-preferred leg in English soccer players. Ergonomics <lb/>48(11-14):1568-1575 DOI 10.1080/00140130500101585. <lb/>Rebelo A, Brito J, Seabra A, Oliveira J, Krustrup P. 2014. Physical match performance <lb/>of youth football players in relation to physical capacity. European Journal of Sport <lb/>Science 14(sup1):S148-S156 DOI 10.1080/17461391.2012.664171. <lb/>Rubini EC, Costa A, Gomes P. 2007. The effects of stretching on strength performance. <lb/>Sports Medicine 37(3):213-224 DOI 10.2165/00007256-200737030-00003. <lb/>Sainz de Baranda P, Ayala F. 2010. Chronic flexibility improvement after 12 week of <lb/>stretching program utilizing the ACSM recommendations: hamstring flexibility. In-<lb/>ternational Journal of Sports Medicine 31(6):389-396 DOI 10.1055/s-0030-1249082. <lb/>Sainz de Baranda P, Cejudo A, Ayala F, Santonja F. 2015. Perfil óptimo de flexibilidad <lb/>del miembro inferior en jugadoras de fútbol sala. Revista Internacional de Medicina y <lb/>Ciencias de la Actividad Física y del Deporte 15(60):647-662. <lb/>Sainz de Baranda P, Rodríguez-Iniesta M, Ayala F, Santonja F, Cejudo A. 2014. <lb/>Determination of the criterion-related validity of hip joint angle test for estimating <lb/>hamstring flexibility using a contemporary statistical approach. Clinical Journal of <lb/>Sport Medicine 24(4):320-325 DOI 10.1097/JSM.0000000000000079. <lb/>Santonja F, Ferrer V, Martínez I. 1995. Exploración clínica del síndrome de isquiosurales <lb/>cortos. Selección 4(2):81-91. <lb/>Sporis G, Vucetic V, Jovanovic M, Jukic I, Omrcen D. 2011. Reliability and factorial <lb/>validity of flexibility tests for Team Sports: method paper. The Journal of Strength &amp; <lb/>Conditioning Research 25:1168-1176. <lb/>Stolen T, Chamari K, Castagna C, Wisloff U. 2005. Physiology of soccer. An update. <lb/>Sports Medicine 35:501-536 DOI 10.2165/00007256-200535060-00004. <lb/>Taylor KL, Sheppard JM, Lee H, Plummer N. 2009. Negative effect of static stretching <lb/>restored when combined with a sport specific warm-up component. Journal of <lb/>Science and Medicine in Sport 12(6):657-661 DOI 10.1016/j.jsams.2008.04.004. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>15/16 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Vaeyens R, Malina RM, Janssen M, Van Renterghem B, Bourgois J, Vrijens J, <lb/>Philippaerts RM. 2006. A multidisciplinary selection model for youth soccer: <lb/>the Ghent Youth Soccer Project. British Journal of Sports Medicine 40:928-934 <lb/>DOI 10.1136/bjsm.2006.029652. <lb/>Witvrouw E, Danneels L, Asselman P, D&apos;Have T, Cambier D. 2003. Muscle flexibility <lb/>as a risk factor for developing muscle injuries in male professional soccer players. The <lb/>American Journal of Sports Medicine 31(1):41-46 DOI 10.1177/03635465030310011801. <lb/>Wong DP, Hjelde GH, Cheng CF, Ngo JK. 2015. Use of the RSA/RCOD index to identify <lb/>training priority in soccer players. The Journal of Strength and Conditioning Research <lb/>29:2787-2793 DOI 10.1519/JSC.0000000000000953. <lb/>Wong PL, Chamari K, Dellal A, Wisloff U. 2009. Relationship between anthropometric <lb/>and physiological characteristics in youth soccer players. The Journal of Strength and <lb/>Conditioning Research 23(4):1204-1210 DOI 10.1519/JSC.0b013e31819f1e52. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Cejudo et al. (2019), PeerJ, DOI 10.7717/peerj.6236 <lb/></note>

			<page>16/16 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
