<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Excitation and Control of Plasma Wakefields by Multiple Laser Pulses <lb/>J. Cowley, 1 C. Thornton, 1 C. Arran, 1 R. J. Shalloo, 1 L. Corner, 1 G. Cheung, 1 C. D. Gregory, 2 <lb/>S. P. D. Mangles, 3 N. H. Matlis, 4 D. R. Symes, 2 R. Walczak, 1 and S. M. Hooker 1,* <lb/>1 John Adams Institute for Accelerator Science, University of Oxford, <lb/>Denys Wilkinson Building, Keble Road, Oxford OX1 3RH, United Kingdom <lb/>2 <lb/>Central Laser Facility, Rutherford Appleton Laboratory, Didcot OX11 0QX, United Kingdom <lb/>3 <lb/>John Adams Institute for Accelerator Science, Blackett Laboratory, Imperial College London, <lb/>London SW7 2AZ, United Kingdom <lb/>4 Deutsches Elektronen-Synchrotron (DESY), Notkestraße 85, Hamburg 22607, Germany <lb/>(Received 15 March 2017; revised manuscript received 31 May 2017; published 27 July 2017) <lb/>We demonstrate experimentally the resonant excitation of plasma waves by trains of laser pulses. We <lb/>also take an important first step to achieving an energy recovery plasma accelerator by showing that a <lb/>plasma wave can be damped by an out-of-resonance trailing laser pulse. The measured laser wakefields are <lb/>found to be in excellent agreement with analytical and numerical models of wakefield excitation in the <lb/>linear regime. Our results indicate a promising direction for achieving highly controlled, GeV-scale laser-<lb/>plasma accelerators operating at multikilohertz repetition rates. <lb/>DOI: 10.1103/PhysRevLett.119.044802 <lb/></front>

			<body>Particle accelerators lie at the heart of many areas of <lb/>science, technology, and medicine either through direct <lb/>application of the particle beams or by driving radiation <lb/>sources such as synchrotrons and free-electron lasers <lb/>(FELs). With conventional radio-frequency (RF) techno-<lb/>logy the electric field used to accelerate particles is <lb/>typically less than 100 MV m −1 , which is a significant <lb/>factor determining the size and cost of the machine. In <lb/>distinct contrast, plasma accelerators can generate gradients <lb/>of order 100 GV m −1 , which shrinks the length of the <lb/>acceleration stage by orders of magnitude. <lb/>In a plasma accelerator the acceleration field is generated <lb/>within a trailing plasma wakefield excited by displacement <lb/>of the plasma electrons by a driving laser pulse [1-4] or <lb/>particle bunch [5,6]. Laser-driven plasma accelerators have <lb/>made impressive progress [7] in recent years. They can now <lb/>generate electron beams with energies comparable to those <lb/>used in synchrotrons and FELs (a few GeV), but in <lb/>accelerator stages only a few centimetres long [8-10], <lb/>with bunch durations in the femtosecond range [11-13], <lb/>and with properties ideal for generating femtosecond <lb/>duration visible to x-ray pulses [14-20]. <lb/>In almost all recent work the plasma wakefield has been <lb/>driven by single laser pulses from high-power Ti:sapphire <lb/>chirped-pulse-amplification laser systems. Unfortunately, <lb/>these have very low wall-plug efficiency (&lt;0.1%) and <lb/>cannot readily operate at pulse repetition frequencies <lb/>much above f rep ¼ 10 Hz. At present, therefore, the driver <lb/>parameters severely restrict the number of potential appli-<lb/>cations of laser-plasma accelerators. <lb/>We recently reexamined [21] multipulse laser wakefield <lb/>acceleration (MP-LWFA) in which the wakefield is excited <lb/>by a train of low-energy laser pulses, rather than by a single, <lb/>high-energy pulse. If the pulses are spaced by the plasma <lb/>wavelength λ p0 ¼ 2πc=ω p0 , then the wakefields driven by <lb/>the pulses in the train add coherently, causing the plasma <lb/>wave amplitude to grow towards the back of the train. Here, <lb/>the plasma frequency is ω p0 ¼ 2π=T p0 ¼ ðn e0 e 2 =m e ϵ 0 Þ 1=2 , <lb/>where n e0 is the ambient electron density. We note that <lb/>Benedetti et al. [22] have studied an alternative scheme in <lb/>which the wakefield is driven by an incoherent combination <lb/>of laser pulses arranged longitudinally, or transversely, <lb/>within a single plasma period. <lb/>Using a train of low-energy laser pulses opens plasma <lb/>accelerators to novel laser technologies, such as fiber or <lb/>thin-disk lasers, which cannot directly deliver joule-level <lb/>short pulses, but which can provide lower-energy pulses <lb/>with f rep in the kilohertz range, whilst achieving wall-plug <lb/>efficiencies at least 2 orders of magnitude higher than <lb/>conventional solid-state lasers [23]. Our recent analysis <lb/>[21] showed that a MP-LWFA driven by a near-term laser <lb/>system of this type could drive wakefields with an accel-<lb/>erating field of 4.7 GV m −1 , with a dephasing-limited <lb/>energy gain of 0.75 GeV, and that with f rep ¼ 10 kHz <lb/>these could drive compact coherent and incoherent x-ray <lb/>sources with average brightnesses exceeding those available <lb/>from large scale, nonsuperconducting, RF accelerators. A <lb/>further advantage of MP-LWFA is that it provides a natural <lb/>architecture for &quot;energy recovery&quot;: the use of one or more <lb/>trailing laser pulses to remove (and potentially recycle) <lb/>energy remaining in the wakefield after particle acceleration. <lb/>Energy recovery is likely to be an important capability in <lb/>future plasma accelerators operating at high average powers. <lb/>In this Letter we present the first demonstration of <lb/>wakefield excitation by a laser pulse structure that is long <lb/>compared to the plasma period, and for which there is <lb/></body>

			<front>PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>0031-9007=17=119(4)=044802(6) <lb/>044802-1 <lb/>© 2017 American Physical Society <lb/></front>

			<body>sufficient control of the temporal profile to overcome <lb/>relativistic saturation. We also take an important first step <lb/>towards achieving energy recovery by showing that a <lb/>suitably delayed laser pulse can damp the plasma wave <lb/>driven by a leading pulse. We achieve this through <lb/>measurements of plasma waves by frequency domain <lb/>holography (FDH) and a new analysis method, temporally <lb/>encoded spectral shifting (TESS) [24]; we demonstrate that <lb/>these two analyses are in excellent agreement, and that our <lb/>results are well described by a linear response model of <lb/>wakefield excitation. <lb/>Since laser systems generating directly the pulse trains <lb/>required for MP-LWFA are still under development, this <lb/>first demonstration employed a Ti:sapphire laser-the <lb/>Gemini (Astra TA2) laser at the Rutherford Appleton <lb/>Laboratory-reconfigured to generate trains of laser pulses. <lb/>In its standard arrangement this laser delivers to target <lb/>approximately 600 mJ, 40 fs laser pulses with a center <lb/>wavelength λ 0 ¼ 800 nm at f rep ¼ 5 Hz. <lb/>Figure 1 shows schematically the experimental arrange-<lb/>ment employed (see Supplemental Material [25] for further <lb/>details of the experimental arrangement and analysis <lb/>methods). Single, temporally chirped pulses from the laser <lb/>system were converted into pulse trains by placing a <lb/>Michelson interferometer between the final laser amplifier <lb/>and its vacuum compressor, as discussed in Refs. [26,27]. <lb/>The Michelson acted as a spectral filter with a spectral <lb/>intensity transmission of the form TðωÞ ¼ cos 2 ðωΔx=2cÞ, <lb/>where Δx is the path difference between the Michelson <lb/>arms. With the compressor set for partial compression, <lb/>the modulated spectrum transmitted by the Michelson was <lb/>partially compressed to a train of pulses, with a temporal <lb/>spacing that could be controlled by adjusting the Michelson <lb/>and compressor. With the compressor set to give full <lb/>compression of an unmodulated input pulse, the output <lb/>of the combination comprised a pair of short (approxi-<lb/>mately 50 fs) pulses temporally separated by δτ ¼ Δx=c. <lb/>The temporal intensity profiles of the pulse trains were <lb/>determined by combining a model of the laser compressor <lb/>and pulse train Michelson with measurements of the pulse <lb/>train spectrum and single-shot autocorrelation (SSA) [27]. <lb/>The pulse train was directed to an f ¼ 1 m off-axis <lb/>paraboloid, used at f=18, which focused the pulses through <lb/>a hydrogen gas cell; this was 3 mm long, with entrance and <lb/>exit pinholes of 250 μm diameter. The spot size (1=e 2 <lb/>radius of the transverse intensity profile) of the focused <lb/>pulse trains was measured to be w 0 ¼ ð35 AE 5Þ μm. <lb/>Plasma wakefields driven by the pulse train were probed <lb/>by frequency domain holography [28]. In this method a <lb/>frequency-chirped probe pulse copropagates with the <lb/>plasma wave and a reference pulse located ahead of the <lb/>plasma wave. These diagnostic pulses are then interfered <lb/>in a spectrograph to give a spectral interferogram, with <lb/>spatial information in the nondispersed direction. When the <lb/>chirped probe pulse interacts with a plasma wave, each of <lb/>its frequency components experiences a phase shift that <lb/>depends on the local wakefield amplitude; after a length l <lb/>of plasma this phase shift can be written as ϕ p ðζÞ ¼ <lb/>ðω 0 =cÞl½ηðζÞ − η 0 , where ω 0 is the angular frequency <lb/>of the probe pulse, ζ ¼ t − l=c, ηðζÞ is the refractive index <lb/>of the plasma, and η 0 is the refractive index experienced by <lb/>the reference pulse. The spectrum of the combined trans-<lb/>mitted probe and reference pulses comprises spectral <lb/>fringes of angular frequency separation Δω ¼ 2π=Δt, <lb/>where Δt is the temporal separation of the probe and <lb/>reference pulses, modulated by a spectral phase ΔψðωÞ <lb/>that depends on the wakefield (for an example, see <lb/>Supplemental Material [25]). Frequency domain holo-<lb/>graphy uses well-known Fourier techniques to extract <lb/>ΔψðωÞ from the interferogram, and hence the temporal <lb/>phase shift caused by the plasma wave [28]. <lb/>In this work we also used a TESS analysis [24] of the <lb/>same data, which is applicable when the plasma wave is <lb/>sinusoidal. In this approach a Fourier transform of the <lb/>interferogram yields a sideband at t ¼ Δt and a series of <lb/>satellites at t¼Δtþmψ ð2Þ ω p0 where m ¼ AE1; AE2; AE3; … <lb/>and ψ ð2Þ is the group delay dispersion (GDD) of the probe <lb/>and reference pulses. The ratio of the amplitudes of the <lb/>satellites to the sideband can be shown to be [29] <lb/>r m ¼ <lb/>J m ðΔϕ p Þ <lb/>J 0 ðΔϕ p Þ <lb/>F ðmω p0 Þ <lb/>F ð0Þ <lb/>; <lb/>ð1Þ <lb/>where Δϕ p ¼ ðω 2 <lb/>p0 =2ω 0 Þðl=cÞðδn e0 =n e0 Þ is proportional <lb/>to the wake amplitude and <lb/>F ðmω p0 Þ ¼ <lb/>Z ∞ <lb/>0 <lb/>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi <lb/>S pr;inc ðω þ mω p0 Þ <lb/>q <lb/>ffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffiffi <lb/>S ref;inc ðωÞ <lb/>q <lb/>dω; ð2Þ <lb/>in which S pr;inc ðωÞ and S ref;inc ðωÞ are the spectra of the <lb/>incident probe and reference pulses. <lb/>FIG. 1. Schematic diagram of the experiment layout. The <lb/>propagation path of the driving pulse train is shown in red, <lb/>and that of the probe and reference beams is shown in blue. The <lb/>laser compressor and the components shown above the darker <lb/>base are located in the vacuum chamber; all other components are <lb/>mounted in air. <lb/>
				
			<note place="headnote">PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>044802-2 <lb/></note>
				
			A pair of λ ¼ 400 nm diagnostic pulses, with an adjust-<lb/>able temporal separation Δt, were generated by passing a <lb/>separately compressed and frequency-doubled fraction of <lb/>the main laser pulse through a Michelson interferometer. <lb/>These pulses were chirped and stretched to a duration of <lb/>around 1.5 ps by sending them through a 160 mm long <lb/>block of BK7 glass. The diagnostic pulses were propagated <lb/>colinearly with the driving pulse train by directing them <lb/>through a dichroic mirror; after propagating through the gas <lb/>cell they were separated from the pulse train by a second <lb/>dichroic mirror and imaged onto the entrance slit of a <lb/>spectrograph. <lb/>Figure 2 shows the results of FDH and TESS measure-<lb/>ments of the wakes driven by a single laser pulse. An <lb/>example wakefield retrieved by FDH is shown in Fig. 2(a): <lb/>the wake can be observed clearly, with a transverse extent <lb/>that is compatible with the focal spot size of the driving <lb/>laser, and with wave fronts that are only slightly curved, <lb/>which is consistent with a linear wakefield. The plasma <lb/>period, read directly from the plot, is found to be <lb/>T p0 ¼ ð90 AE 5Þ fs, which agrees with the expected value <lb/>of T p0 ¼ ð91 AE 2Þ fs for this cell pressure. <lb/>The wake in Fig. 2(a) can be observed up to ζ ≈ 2 ps <lb/>after the pump pulse, corresponding to approximately <lb/>20 plasma periods. This may be compared with the expected <lb/>time for the onset of ion motion T p;ion ¼ ðM=Zm e Þ 1=2 T p0 ≈ <lb/>43T p0 , where M is the ion mass and Z ¼ 1 is the ion charge. <lb/>For these conditions the characteristic time [30] for momen-<lb/>tum transfer by electron-ion collisions is approximately <lb/>τ ei ≈ 48T p0 . These processes are therefore unlikely to be the <lb/>sole cause of the apparent decay of the wakefield. An <lb/>additional reason is the variation of the plasma density along <lb/>the path of the probe pulse, especially near the entrance and <lb/>exit pinholes; in this case the number of measurable plasma <lb/>periods is approximately n e0 =ð2Δn e0 Þ, where Δn e0 is the <lb/>range of density. The data could therefore be fully explained <lb/>by a variation Δn e0 =n e0 ≈ 2.5%. Further work is necessary <lb/>to assess the roles of collisions and ion motion; however, we <lb/>note that our previous particle-in-cell simulations [21] show <lb/>(for a hydrogen pressure of 3.6 mbar) that linear growth of <lb/>the wake amplitude with N could be maintained for trains of <lb/>up to N ¼ 80. <lb/>Figure 2(b) shows, as a function of the cell pressure, a <lb/>waterfall plot of Fourier transforms of the spectral interfero-<lb/>grams. The sideband at t ¼ Δt ≈ 5.1 ps, corresponding to <lb/>the probe-reference separation, can be seen clearly, as can <lb/>the m ¼ AE1 TESS satellites; the separation of these <lb/>satellites, and also of a satellite to the DC peak at t ¼ 0, <lb/>follows closely that expected from the measured GDD of <lb/>the probe pulse and the plasma frequency calculated from <lb/>the initial gas pressure, assuming full ionization by the <lb/>driving laser pulse. The plasma periods determined from <lb/>the FDH and TESS analyses are compared in Fig. 2(c) and <lb/>are seen to be in excellent agreement with each other and <lb/>with the calculated plasma period. <lb/>Figure 3 shows, as a function of cell pressure, the relative <lb/>amplitude of the plasma waves driven by trains of N ¼ 1, <lb/>N ¼ 2, and N ≈ 7 pulses, as determined by TESS analyses. <lb/>In the linear regime the relative amplitude of the plasma <lb/>wave driven by a single driving pulse with Gaussian <lb/>transverse and temporal profiles is [31] <lb/>δn e <lb/>n e0 <lb/>¼ Aω p0 τ 0 <lb/>1 þ <lb/>2 <lb/>ffiffi ffi <lb/>2 <lb/>p <lb/>c <lb/>ω p0 w 0 <lb/>2 <lb/>exp <lb/>− <lb/>ðω p0 τ 0 Þ 2 <lb/>16 ln 2 <lb/>; ð3Þ <lb/>where τ 0 is the full-width at half maximum of the temporal <lb/>profile, and the parameter A is proportional to the peak <lb/>laser intensity. Figure 3(a) shows a fit of Eq. (3) to the data, <lb/>where A and τ 0 are taken as free parameters and ω p0 is <lb/>calculated from the gas pressure. The fit yields τ 0 ¼ <lb/>ð49 AE 8Þ fs, which is consistent with the value of τ 0 ¼ <lb/>ð46 AE 7Þ fs measured with the SSA. Figure 3(a) also shows <lb/>excellent agreement between the data and a fit to the <lb/>wakefield amplitude calculated for the measured temporal <lb/>intensity profile of the driving pulse, the only fitting <lb/>parameter being the parameter A. <lb/>From elementary considerations, in the linear regime the <lb/>relative amplitude of the wakefield behind a train of N <lb/>identical driving pulses spaced in time by δτ is <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>FIG. 2. FDH and TESS analyses of linear plasma wakefields <lb/>driven by a single laser pulse of energy approximately 270 mJ and <lb/>pulse duration ð46 AE 7Þ fs. (a) shows an example of the wakefield <lb/>recovered by FDH for a cell pressure of ð31 AE 1Þ mbar, where ζ ¼ <lb/>0 corresponds to the center of the pump pulse. In the panel above, the <lb/>solid line shows the amplitude of the wakefield averaged over the <lb/>range jrj ≤ 6 μm; the ticks on the y axis are at δn e =n e0 ¼ AE1%. <lb/>(b) shows a waterfall plot of Fourier transforms of the spectral <lb/>interferograms, where the magnitude of the Fourier transform is <lb/>plotted on a logarithmic scale. The solid white line shows the <lb/>expected position of the satellites calculated from the expected <lb/>plasma frequency. (c) shows, as a function of the gas pressure, the <lb/>plasma period determined by the FDH and TESS analyses. The <lb/>solid curve is the plasma period calculated assuming an electron <lb/>density equal to twice the density of hydrogen molecules. The error <lb/>bars are estimated from the uncertainty in determining the satellite <lb/>separation in (b) and the plasma period in (a). <lb/>
		
		
		<note place="headnote">PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>044802-3 <lb/></note>
		
		δn e <lb/>n e0 <lb/>N <lb/>¼ <lb/>δn e <lb/>n e0 <lb/>1 <lb/>sin ð 1 <lb/>2 Nω p0 δτÞ <lb/>sin ð 1 <lb/>2 ω p0 δτÞ <lb/>: <lb/>ð4Þ <lb/>Figure 3(b) shows the measured wake amplitude, as a <lb/>function of pressure, for a pair of laser pulses. Very clear <lb/>constructive and destructive interference of the two wake-<lb/>fields is observed, as expected. A fit to Eq. (4) yields <lb/>δτ ¼ ð407 AE 6Þ fs, which is in agreement with the values of <lb/>ð365 AE 40Þ and ð420 AE 20Þ fs measured by the SSA and <lb/>that deduced from interference fringes observed in the <lb/>spectrum of the two drive pulses. Better agreement with <lb/>the data is obtained if the pressure variation of the wake <lb/>amplitude is calculated from the SSA measurement of the <lb/>intensity profile of the driving pulses. For this fit the free <lb/>parameters were an overall scaling factor for the wake <lb/>amplitude, and a scaling factor α for the temporal axis of <lb/>the measured driving pulses, such that ζ → αζ; the fit <lb/>yields α ¼ 1.11 AE 0.02. An analysis of these data (see <lb/>Supplemental Material [25]) shows that the second (smaller) <lb/>laser pulse reduced the amplitude of the wakefield by <lb/>ð44 AE 8Þ%; this energy is removed from the plasma in <lb/>the form of blue-shifted photons in the trailing laser <lb/>pulse [32,33]. <lb/>Figure 3(c) shows the measured wake amplitude as a <lb/>function of the cell pressure for N ≈ 7 laser pulses. A <lb/>pronounced resonance is observed when the plasma period <lb/>matches the pulse spacing δτ. Also shown is a fit of Eq. (4) <lb/>for a train of N ¼ 7 identical pulses. Once again excellent <lb/>agreement between the data and analytical theory is <lb/>obtained, the fit yielding δτ ¼ ð116 AE 2Þ fs, which agrees <lb/>with the measured value. The solid line shows the variation <lb/>of the wake amplitude calculated for the measured pulse <lb/>train, the fit yielding α ¼ 1.04 AE 0.02. It is noticeable that <lb/>the pressure variation of the wake amplitude calculated for <lb/>the measured pulse train does not exhibit subsidiary <lb/>maxima; this difference is caused by the small variation <lb/>of the pulse spacing, and the presence of temporal wings, in <lb/>the measured pulse train. <lb/>We now place our results in context with earlier work. <lb/>The MP-LWFA approach is closely related to the plasma <lb/>beat-wave accelerator (PBWA) [1,34], in which two long <lb/>laser pulses of angular frequencies ω 1 and ω 2 ¼ ω 1 þ ω p0 <lb/>are combined to form a driving pulse modulated at ω p0 . <lb/>Beat-wave excitation of plasma waves [35-37], and their <lb/>application to accelerating electrons [38,39], have both <lb/>been demonstrated. <lb/>A well-known problem with PBWA is that the relativistic <lb/>increase in electron mass causes a loss of resonance between <lb/>the wakefield and the driver, leading to saturation of the <lb/>wake amplitude at the Rosenbluth-Liu limit [40]. A major <lb/>advantage of MP-LWFA is that this limit can be overcome <lb/>since the pulse spacing does not have to be constant within <lb/>the train. Indeed, MP-LWFA can be considered to be a <lb/>generalization of PBWA since, in addition, the properties of <lb/>each pulse (i.e., the energy, wavelength, duration, etc.) can, <lb/>in principle, be different. The MP-LWFA concept has been <lb/>investigated theoretically [41-49] but has not previously <lb/>been demonstrated experimentally. The idea of using a long <lb/>pulse with temporally nonuniform modulation to overcome <lb/>the Rosenbluth-Liu limit was proposed, within the context of <lb/>PBWA, by Deutsch et al. [50], who suggested using a pair of <lb/>frequency-chirped laser pulses. <lb/>Our results can be considered to be the first experimental <lb/>demonstration of MP-LWFA or of beat-wave excitation <lb/>with chirped laser pulses. In this first demonstration the <lb/>pulse spacing within the train was approximately constant <lb/>since the total available laser pulse energy was low; it <lb/>would be straightforward to maintain resonant excitation <lb/>with large amplitude wakefields by controlling the chirp <lb/>of one or both pulses, for example, by an acousto-optic <lb/>programmable filter [51]. Our results are important since <lb/>they are the first experimental demonstration of wakefield <lb/>excitation by a laser pulse structure that is long compared <lb/>to the plasma period, and which has sufficient control to <lb/>overcome relativistic saturation; as we have shown, this <lb/>approach also offers the potential for energy recovery. The <lb/>ability to deliver the driving laser energy over many plasma <lb/>periods allows the use of high-repetition-rate laser systems, <lb/>such as thin-disk [52] or fiber lasers [53], which cannot <lb/>straightforwardly generate high-energy short laser pulses. <lb/>These results, together with our earlier numerical analysis <lb/>of this scheme [21], indicate a route to achieving highly <lb/>controlled, GeV-scale laser-plasma accelerators operating <lb/>at multikilohertz repetition rates and driven by novel, <lb/>efficient laser technologies. In addition to stimulating <lb/>new work on the development of laser-plasma accelerators, <lb/>these results are of interest to those working on driving <lb/>plasma accelerators driven by trains of particle bunches <lb/>[54,55] or self-modulated proton beams [56,57]. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>(c) <lb/>FIG. 3. Relative wakefield amplitudes, as a function of gas cell <lb/>pressure, measured at delay ζ between the center of the pulse train <lb/>and the center of the probe pulse for a driving pulse train <lb/>comprising N pulses of measured pulse separation δτ and total <lb/>energy E where (a) N ¼ 1, E ¼ 270 mJ, ζ ¼ 2.2 ps; (b) N ¼ 2, <lb/>δτ ¼ ð420 AE 20Þ fs, E ¼ 160 mJ, ζ ¼ 2.5 ps; and (c) N ≈ 7, <lb/>δτ ¼ ð112 AE 6Þ fs, E ¼ 170 mJ, ζ ¼ 1.3 ps. Gray circles show <lb/>single measurements and red diamonds show the same data <lb/>averaged over pressure bins of width 4 mbar [(a) and (b)] or <lb/>2 mbar (c); the error bars are standard errors and the y axes are the <lb/>same for all plots. The insets show the measured driving pulse <lb/>trains. The dashed lines show fits of Eq. (4), and the solid lines <lb/>show the wake amplitudes calculated for the pulse trains shown in <lb/>the figure insets. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>044802-4 <lb/></note>

		<div type="acknowledgement">This work was supported by the UK Science and <lb/>Technology Facilities Council (STFC UK; Grant No. ST/ <lb/>J002011/1, ST/P002048/1, and 1507620); the Engineering <lb/>and Physical Sciences Research Council (Grant <lb/>Nos. 1378575 and 1093881); the Helmholtz Association <lb/>of German Research centers (Grant No. VH-VI-503); and <lb/>Effort sponsored by the Air Force Office of Scientific <lb/>Research, Air Force Material Command, USAF, under <lb/>Grant No. FA8655-13-1-2141. The U.S. Government is <lb/>authorized to reproduce and distribute reprints for <lb/>Governmental purpose notwithstanding any copyright nota-<lb/>tion thereon. <lb/></div>
		
		<front>* simon.hooker@physics.ox.ac.uk <lb/></front>
		
		<listBibl>[1] T. Tajima and J. M. Dawson, Phys. Rev. Lett. 43, 267 <lb/>(1979). <lb/>[2] V. Malka, J. Faure, Y. A. Gauduel, E. Lefebvre, A. Rousse, <lb/>and K. T. Phuoc, Nat. Phys. 4, 447 (2008). <lb/>[3] E. Esarey, C. B. Schroeder, and W. P. Leemans, Rev. Mod. <lb/>Phys. 81, 1229 (2009). <lb/>[4] P. A. Norreys, Nat. Photonics 3, 423 (2009). <lb/>[5] P. Chen, J. M. Dawson, R. W. Huff, and T. Katsouleas, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 54, 693 (1985). <lb/>[6] P. Muggli and M. J. Hogan, C.R. Phys. 10, 116 (2009). <lb/>[7] S. M. Hooker, Nat. Photonics 7, 775 (2013). <lb/>[8] W. P. Leemans, B. Nagler, A. J. Gonsalves, C. Toth, K. <lb/>Nakamura, C. G. R. Geddes, E. Esarey, C. B. Schroeder, and <lb/>S. M. Hooker, Nat. Phys. 2, 696 (2006). <lb/>[9] S. Kneip et al.P. Rajeev, J. Schreiber, M. Streeter, D. Urner, <lb/>J. Vieira, L. Silva, and Z. Najmudin, Phys. Rev. Lett. 103, <lb/>035002 (2009). <lb/>[10] X. Wang et al., Nat. Commun. 4, 2988 (2013). <lb/>[11] A. Buck, M. Nicolai, K. Schmid, C. M. S. Sears, A. Sävert, <lb/>J. M. Mikhailova, F. Krausz, M. C. Kaluza, and L. Veisz, <lb/>Nat. Phys. 7, 543 (2011). <lb/>[12] O. Lundh, J. Lim, C. Rechatin, L. Ammoura, A. Ben-Ismail, <lb/>X. Davoine, G. Gallot, J.-P. Goddet, E. Lefebvre, V. Malka, <lb/>and J. Faure, Nat. Phys. 7, 219 (2011). <lb/>[13] M. Heigoldt, A. Popp, K. Khrennikov, J. Wenz, S.-W. Chou, <lb/>S. Karsch, S. I. Bajlekov, S. M. Hooker, and B. Schmidt, <lb/>Phys. Rev. ST Accel. Beams 18, 121302 (2015). <lb/>[14] H.-P. Schlenvoigt, K. Haupt, A. Debus, F. Budde, O. Jackel, <lb/>S. Pfotenhauer, H. Schwoerer, E. Rohwer, J. G. Gallacher, <lb/>E. Brunetti, R. P. Shanks, S. M. Wiggins, and D. A. <lb/>Jaroszynski, Nat. Phys. 4, 130 (2008). <lb/>[15] M. Fuchs, R. Weingartner, A. Popp, Z. Major, S. Becker, J. <lb/>Osterhoff, I. Cortrie, B. Zeitler, R. Hoerlein, G. D. Tsakiris, <lb/>U. Schramm, T. P. Rowlands-Rees, S. M. Hooker, D. Habs, <lb/>F. Krausz, S. Karsch, and F. Gruener, Nat. Phys. 5, 826 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>[16] S. Kneip et al., Nat. Phys. 6, 980 (2010). <lb/>[17] S. Cipiccia et al., Nat. Phys. 7, 867 (2011). <lb/>[18] K. T. Phuoc, S. Corde, C. Thaury, V. Malka, A. Tafzi, J.-P. <lb/>Goddet, R. C. Shah, S. Sebban, and A. Rousse, Nat. <lb/>Photonics 6, 308 (2012). <lb/>[19] N. D. Powers, I. Ghebregziabher, G. Golovin, C. Liu, S. <lb/>Chen, S. Banerjee, J. Zhang, and D. P. Umstadter, Nat. <lb/>Photonics 8, 28 (2013). <lb/>[20] K. Khrennikov, J. Wenz, A. Buck, J. Xu, M. Heigoldt, L. <lb/>Veisz, and S. Karsch, Phys. Rev. Lett. 114, 195003 (2015). <lb/>[21] S. M. Hooker, R. Bartolini, S. P. D. Mangles, A. Tuennermann, <lb/>L. Corner, J. Limpert, A. Seryi, and R. Walczek, J. Phys. B <lb/>47, 234003 (2014). <lb/>[22] C. Benedetti, C. B. Schroeder, E. Esarey, and W. P. <lb/>Leemans, Phys. Plasmas 21, 056706 (2014). <lb/>[23] A. Klenke, S. Hädrich, T. Eidam, J. Rothhardt, M. Kienel, <lb/>S. Demmler, T. Gottschall, J. Limpert, and A. Tünnermann, <lb/>Opt. Lett. 39, 6875 (2014). <lb/>[24] N. H. Matlis, A. Maksimchuk, V. Yanovsky, W. P. Leemans, <lb/>and M. C. Downer, Opt. Lett. 41, 5503 (2016). <lb/>[25] See Supplemental Material http://link.aps.org/supplemental/ <lb/>10.1103/PhysRevLett.119.044802 for further details of the <lb/>experimental arrangement and analysis methods. <lb/>[26] A. S. Weling and D. H. Auston, J. Opt. Soc. Am. B 13, 2783 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[27] R. J. Shalloo, L. Corner, C. Arran, J. Cowley, G. Cheung, C. <lb/>Thornton, R. walczak, and S. M. Hooker, Nucl. Instrum. <lb/>Methods Phys. Res., Sect. A 829, 383 (2016). <lb/>[28] N. H. Matlis, S. Reed, S. S. Bulanov, V. Chvykov, G. <lb/>Kalintchenko, T. Matsuoka, P. Rousseau, V. Yanovsky, A. <lb/>Maksimchuk, S. Kalmykov, G. Shvets, and M. C. Downer, <lb/>Nat. Phys. 2, 749 (2006). <lb/>[29] C. A. Arran, N. H. Matlis, L. Corner, J. Cowley, G. Cheung, <lb/>C. D. Gregory, R. J. Shalloo, D. R. Symes, C. Thornton, R. <lb/>Walczak, and S. M. Hooker (to be published). <lb/>[30] L. J. Spitzer, Physics of Fully Ionized Gases (John Wiley &amp; <lb/>Sons, New York, 1962). <lb/>[31] F. Dorchies, F. Amiranoff, V. Malka, J. R. Marques, A. <lb/>Modena, D. Bernard, F. Jacquet, P. Mine, B. Cros, G. <lb/>Matthieussent, P. Mora, A. Solodov, J. Morillo, and Z. <lb/>Najmudin, Phys. Plasmas 6, 2903 (1999). <lb/>[32] C. D. Murphy et al., Phys. Plasmas 13, 033108 (2006). <lb/>[33] J. M. Dias, L. OliveiraeSilva, and J. T. Mendonca, Phys. <lb/>Rev. ST Accel. Beams 1, 031301 (1998). <lb/>[34] C. Joshi, W. B. Mori, T. Katsouleas, J. M. Dawson, and <lb/>J. M. Kindel, Nature (London) 311, 525 (1984). <lb/>[35] A. E. Dangor, A. Dymoke-Bradshaw, and A. E. Dyson, <lb/>Phys. Scr. T30, 107 (1990). <lb/>[36] C. E. Clayton, C. Joshi, C. B. C. Darrow, and D. Umstadter, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 54, 2343 (1985). <lb/>[37] F. Amiranoff, M. Laberge, J. R. Marques, F. Moulin, E. <lb/>Fabre, B. Cros, G. Matthieussent, P. Benkheiri, F. Jacquet, <lb/>J. Meyer, P. Mine, C. Stenz, and P. Mora, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>68, 3710 (1992). <lb/>[38] C. E. Clayton, K. A. Marsh, A. Dyson, M. Everett, A. LAL, <lb/>W. P. Leemans, R. Williams, and C. Joshi, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>70, 37 (1993). <lb/>[39] S. Y. Tochitsky, R. Narang, C. V. Filip, P. Musumeci, C. E. <lb/>Clayton, R. B. Yoder, K. A. Marsh, J. B. Rosenzweig, <lb/>C. Pellegrini, and C. Joshi, Phys. Rev. Lett. 92, 095004 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>[40] M. N. Rosenbluth and C. S. Liu, Phys. Rev. Lett. 29, 701 <lb/>(1972). <lb/>[41] K. Nakajima, Phys. Rev. A 45, 1149 (1992). <lb/>[42] V. I. Berezhiani and I. G. Murusidze, Phys. Scr. 45, 87 <lb/>(1992). <lb/>[43] D. Umstadter, E. Esarey, and J. Kim, Phys. Rev. Lett. 72, <lb/>1224 (1994). <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>044802-5 <lb/></note>

		<listBibl>[44] D. A. Johnson, R. A. Cairns, R. Bingham, and U. De <lb/>Angelis, Phys. Scr. T52, 77 (1994). <lb/>[45] S. Dalla and M. Lontano, Phys. Rev. E 49, R1819 (1994). <lb/>[46] G. Bonnaud, D. Teychenné, and J.-L. Bobin, Phys. Rev. E <lb/>50, R36 (1994). <lb/>[47] R. A. Cairns, D. Johnson, and R. Bingham, Laser Part. <lb/>Beams 13, 451 (1995). <lb/>[48] D. Umstadter, J. Kim, E. Esarey, E. Dodd, and T. Neubert, <lb/>Phys. Rev. E 51, 3484 (1995). <lb/>[49] E. I. Kalinnikova and V. D. Levchenko, Plasma Phys. Rep. <lb/>34, 290 (2008). <lb/>[50] M. Deutsch, B. Meerson, and J. E. Golub, Phys. Fluids B 3, <lb/>1773 (1991). <lb/>[51] F. Verluise, V. Laude, Z. Cheng, C. Spielmann, and P. <lb/>Tournois, Opt. Lett. 25, 575 (2000). <lb/>[52] T. Nubbemeyer, M. Kaumanns, M. Ueffing, M. Gorjan, A. <lb/>Alismail, H. Fattahi, J. Brons, O. Pronin, H. G. Barros, Z. <lb/>Major, T. Metzger, D. Sutter, and F. Krausz, Opt. Lett. 42, <lb/>1381 (2017). <lb/>[53] C. Jauregui, J. Limpert, and A. Tünnermann, Nat. Photonics <lb/>7, 861 (2013). <lb/>[54] P. Muggli, V. Yakimenko, M. Babzien, E. Kallos, and K. P. <lb/>Kusche, Phys. Rev. Lett. 101, 054801 (2008). <lb/>[55] E. Kallos, T. Katsouleas, W. D. Kimura, K. Kusche, P. <lb/>Muggli, I. Pavlishin, I. Pogorelsky, D. Stolyarov, and V. <lb/>Yakimenko, Phys. Rev. Lett. 100, 074802 (2008). <lb/>[56] A. Caldwell, K. Lotov, A. Pukhov, and F. Simon, Nat. Phys. <lb/>5, 363 (2009). <lb/>[57] A. Caldwell and K. V. Lotov, Phys. Plasmas 18, 103101 <lb/>(2011). <lb/></listBibl>

		<front>PRL 119, 044802 (2017) <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>week ending <lb/>28 JULY 2017 <lb/>044802-6 </front>

	</text>
</tei>
