<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Nutrition Research and Practice (2008), 2(2), 114-120 <lb/>ⓒ2008 The Korean Nutrition Society and the Korean Society of Community Nutrition <lb/>Construction of web-based nutrition education contents and searching engine for <lb/>usage of healthy menu of children* <lb/>Soon-Myung Hong <lb/>1 § <lb/>, Tae-Kyong Lee <lb/>2 <lb/>, Hea-Jung Chung <lb/>3 <lb/>, Hye-Kyung Park <lb/>4 <lb/>, Eun-Ju Lee <lb/>4 <lb/>, Hye-Seon Nam <lb/>4 <lb/>, <lb/>Soon-Im Jung <lb/>1 <lb/>, Jee-Ye Cho <lb/>1 <lb/>, Jin-Hee Lee <lb/>1 <lb/>, Gon Kim <lb/>5 and Min-Chan Kim <lb/>5 <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Food and Nutrition, University of Ulsan, Ulsan 680-749, Korea <lb/>2 <lb/>Department of Digital Information Design, University of Ulsan, Ulsan 680-749, Korea <lb/>3 <lb/>Department of Culinary Arts, Woosong University, Daejeon 300-718, Korea <lb/>4 <lb/>Nutritional Evaluation Division, Korea Food and Drug Administration, Seoul 122-704, Korea <lb/>5 <lb/>School of Computer Engineering &amp; Information Technology, University of Ulsan, Ulsan 680-749, Korea <lb/>Received March 21, 2008; March 28, 2008; Accepted April 25, 2008 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>A diet habit, which is developed in childhood, lasts for a life time. In this sense, nutrition education and early exposure to healthy menus in <lb/>childhood is important. Children these days have easy access to the internet. Thus, a web-based nutrition education program for children is an <lb/>effective tool for nutrition education of children. This site provides the material of the nutrition education for children with characters which are <lb/>personified nutrients. The 151 menus are stored in the site together with video script of the cooking process. The menus are classified by the <lb/>criteria based on age, menu type and the ethnic origin of the menu. The site provides a search function. There are three kinds of search conditions <lb/>which are key words, menu type and &quot;between&quot; expression of nutrients such as calorie and other nutrients. The site is developed with the operating <lb/>system Windows 2003 Server, the web server ZEUS 5, development language JSP, and database management system Oracle 10 g. <lb/>Key Words: Web-based nutrition program, healthy menu, nutrition education <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction 10) <lb/>Childhood is a critical time of human development. The most <lb/>common nutrition-related problems among children include <lb/>under-nutrition, iron-deficiency anemia, dental caries, high blood <lb/>lipid profile, overweight and obesity (Boyle, 2003). In 2003, the <lb/>Korea president announced the First Year of Children&apos;s Safety. <lb/>Since then, the government has promoted various polices in order <lb/>to enhance children&apos;s health. However, they appear to lack a <lb/>comprehensive vision or systematic development of action plans. <lb/>The eating habits which developed in childhood greatly affect <lb/>one&apos;s lifelong habits and health. Besides, the education to provide <lb/>information on food safety and nutrition has not been adequate. <lb/>Improper dietary habits and unhealthy life styles may have <lb/>resulted in a radical increase in producing number of overweight <lb/>and obese children and teenagers. The Korea National Health <lb/>&amp; Nutrition Survey 2005 revealed that over the past seven years, <lb/>there has been a significant 1.5-fold increase in the number of <lb/>overweight boys and girls under 18 years of age. And dietary <lb/>intakes of children were deficient in calcium and potassium. In <lb/>contrast, the intakes of protein and sodium were becoming <lb/>excessive (Department of Health and Welfare &amp; Korea Health <lb/>Industry Development Institute, 2006). <lb/>Nutrition education for children is valuable in changing dietary <lb/>behaviors and promoting health, considering that good eating <lb/>behavior formed in childhood would continue to later life. Some <lb/>off-line programs on menu planning and nutrition analysis have <lb/>been developed and used (Han, 1997; Hong, 1989; Hong, 1996; <lb/>Joni, 1983; Kang et al., 1999; Kolasa &amp; Miller, 1996). The use <lb/>of internet has become popular in Korea. Those who use internet <lb/>reached 75% in 2006; of those aged 6-19 years, 98.5% used <lb/>the internet (National Internet Development Agency of Korea <lb/>&amp; Ministry of Information Communication Republic of Korea, <lb/>2007). So, needs for web-based contents have been rapidly <lb/>increasing in educational fields. &quot;Diet and meal management&quot; <lb/>of lecture contents and software system for web-based nutritional <lb/>assessment and counseling (Youn, 2001) were researched. The <lb/>Korean Society of Community Nutrition, Nutrition Education <lb/>Center of Ulsan University, The Korean Food &amp; Nutrition <lb/>Society and KFDA are running internet-based nutrition education <lb/>programs. Some web-based programs for nutrition were deve-<lb/>loped (Han, 2000; Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; Her <lb/></body>

			<front>* This study was supported by Research Funds of Korea Food and Drug Administration. <lb/> § Corresponding Author: Soon-Myung Hong, Tel. 82-52-259-2374, Fax. 82-52-259-1496, Email. smhong@ulsan.ac.kr <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Soon-Myung Hong et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>115 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Web server system <lb/>Operating system <lb/>Windows 2003 server <lb/>Web server <lb/>Zeus <lb/>Language <lb/>JSP, JavaScript <lb/>Database <lb/>Oracle 10g <lb/>Table 2. Healthy menu DB classification <lb/>Healthy menu <lb/>Classification <lb/>Infant <lb/>Child <lb/>Adolescent <lb/>Total <lb/>Main dish <lb/>28 <lb/>29 <lb/>28 <lb/>85 <lb/>Side dish <lb/>15 <lb/>14 <lb/>15 <lb/>44 <lb/>Dessert <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>22 <lb/>Total <lb/>50 <lb/>51 <lb/>50 <lb/>151 <lb/>Menu type <lb/>Infant <lb/>Child <lb/>Adolescent <lb/>Total <lb/>Korean food <lb/>21 <lb/>18 <lb/>17 <lb/>56 <lb/>Western food <lb/>22 <lb/>22 <lb/>22 <lb/>66 <lb/>Chinese food <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>15 <lb/>Japanese food <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>Asian food <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>7 <lb/>10 <lb/>Total <lb/>50 <lb/>51 <lb/>50 <lb/>151 <lb/>&amp; Lee, 2003a; Her &amp; Lee, 2003b; Hong &amp; Kim, 2005; Kim <lb/>&amp; Yoon, 1999; Lee et al., 2002) and also a food exchange <lb/>program (Hong et al., 2004). But it is limited to adults and not <lb/>easy for an inexperienced person. Those of the program have <lb/>to be developed for wider groups of people. Needs for nutrition <lb/>education of children are increasing and related resources are <lb/>essential (Park et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). Internet could <lb/>be a useful route for children to provide nutrition information <lb/>and educational messages. Many kinds of topics or methods <lb/>might be effectively applied, in designing and planning nutrition <lb/>web-sites or planning education programs, for example cooking <lb/>or selecting snacks, flash animation with nutrition messages. <lb/>Nutrition web-sites for children should be constructed in a way <lb/>that children find the sites easily and search the contents for <lb/>fun (Ahn et al., 2007; Ahn &amp; Kim, 2007). So, we tried to make <lb/>kid-friendly web-based nutrition education searching system for <lb/>healthy menu recipe and easily learned nutrition information with <lb/>a lot of searching methods. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>The implementation of the system <lb/>This system is on the operating system the Windows 2003 <lb/>Server, which is Zeus. The languages for the development of <lb/>this site are Java Server Page and Java Script. It does not make <lb/>use of ActiveX and only uses HTML because the site with <lb/>ActiveX functions can be in operation with a particular browser. <lb/>The meal plan and nutrition evaluation go through complicated <lb/>procedures and calculation processes. This is why the deve-<lb/>lopment procedures are important. The site is based on MVC <lb/>Model2 (Model View Controller Pattern). The DBMS is Oracle <lb/>10 g. The content is shown in Table 1. <lb/>Construction of web contents <lb/>The web contents contain introductions of a home-page, the <lb/>menu of three age groups (infants, children and adolescents) and <lb/>menu search. The contents are menu pictures, cooking methods, <lb/>macro nutrients and sodium levels, video scripts of cooking <lb/>courses, close-up of menu pictures, exchange of weight and <lb/>printing. <lb/>The DB structure <lb/>The DB (Database) of the system consists of 4 segments. They <lb/>are healthy menu DB, food nutrient DB, nutrition intake guideline <lb/>DB and nutrient guideline DB. Healthy menu DB is developed <lb/>in the sub-project of this research. It is shown in Table 2. Food <lb/>nutrient DB is based on the 7th food table of 2006 of National <lb/>Rural Living Science Institute. Nutrition intake guideline DB is <lb/>based on the data of The Korean Nutrition Society 2005. Nutrient <lb/>Daily Value guideline DB is based on the data of KFDA 2007. <lb/>Menu searching method <lb/>Users can search by the title of a menu, ingredients, menu <lb/>types (main dish, dessert), ethnic food and each nutrient. With <lb/>those searching conditions, the screen can show recipe, video <lb/>script, food data of menu and nutrients. <lb/>Results <lb/>Contents and search function <lb/>The site of the department of nutritional evaluation in Korea <lb/>Food and Drug Administration (http://nutrition.kfda.go.kr) is Fig. <lb/>1, which is involved in a banner for children&apos;s healthy menus. <lb/>The contents of this children&apos;s healthy menus site are classified <lb/>into four groups. The first is introduction of this home page. <lb/>It explains the overall introduction of this site. The second page <lb/>contains the information of menus for infants, children and <lb/>adolescents (Fig. 2). This part contains all information which <lb/>users want to get by a search function. The third part provides <lb/>a search function so that users can find the information which <lb/>they need. The users specify search conditions. Types of the <lb/>conditions are menu name, raw material of a menu, types of <lb/>menus such as main dish, side dish and dessert, many kinds of <lb/>ethnic menu such as Korean food, Chinese food, Japanese food, <lb/>Western style food, Southeast Asian food, nineteen nutrients and <lb/>calories and so on. The fourth part, NutriEval, is like this site. <lb/>The NutriEval is another web-based program for meal plan <lb/>drafting and nutrition evaluation. It is an independent program <lb/>itself. It will be discussed in another chance. <lb/></body>

			<page>116 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 1. Home page of the department of nutritional evaluation, Korea Food and <lb/>Drug Administration (http://nutrition.kfda.go.kr) <lb/>Fig. 2. Page containing the information of menus for infants, children and <lb/>adolescents <lb/>Fig. 3. The introduction of home page <lb/>Fig. 4. Cali and Friends page <lb/>Introduction of home page <lb/>This introduction page summarizes the whole site. Fig. 3 is <lb/>the technical introduction of the home page. This is the page <lb/>which has links to the contents classified into eight groups. They <lb/>are &quot;Cali and Friends&quot;, &quot;Food Pyramid&quot;, &quot;Nutrition Safari&quot;, <lb/>&quot;Guideline of Diet Plan&quot;, &quot;Guideline of Nutrition Intake&quot;, <lb/>&quot;Guideline of Nutrition Ingredient&quot;, &quot;Nutrition Manifest&quot; and <lb/>&quot;NutriEval&quot;. <lb/>Cali and friends as nutrient nicknames <lb/>&quot;Cali&quot; means Calorie. Because this site is focused on children, <lb/>the terminology had better be familiar and easy to use and <lb/>pronounce for children. For this reason, some of the nutrients <lb/>are given an alias, gender and character. Children learn the <lb/>nutrients by playing with the alias. The aliases are &quot;Cali&quot;, <lb/>&quot;Carbo&quot;, &quot;Pro&quot;, &quot;Lipi&quot;, &quot;Mine&quot; and &quot;Vita&quot;. They are associated <lb/>with &quot;Calorie and Energy&quot;, &quot;Carbohydrate&quot;, &quot;Protein&quot;, &quot;Lipid, <lb/>Fats and Oil&quot;, &quot;Mineral&quot; and &quot;Vitamin&quot;, correspondingly. Fig. <lb/>4 is the &quot;Cali and Friends&quot; page. <lb/>Nutrition safari <lb/>In this page, children learn the importance of nutrients by a <lb/>&quot;safari tour&quot;. The contents consist of two parts. One is &quot;nutrition <lb/>café&quot; and the other is &quot;nutrition villages&quot;. Fig. 5 is the page <lb/>of the &quot;nutrition safari&quot;. <lb/>Nutrition café: Children learn what nutrients do in their bodies. <lb/>In addition to the functions of nutrients, the children learn the <lb/>reason why they have to eat well-balanced foods and how to <lb/>eat healthy foods. Fig. 6 is the page of &quot;Nutrition café&quot;. <lb/>Nutrition villages: There are eight villages. They are &quot;Carbo-<lb/>hydrate&quot;, &quot;Protein&quot;, &quot;Lipid&quot;, &quot;Mineral&quot;, &quot;Vitamin&quot;, &quot;Fiber&quot;, <lb/>&apos;Water&quot; and &quot;Calorie&quot;. Children learn what nutrients do in their <lb/>bodies by visiting the villages. They also learn the food in which <lb/>the nutrients are abundant. Fig. 7 is the page of &quot;Carbohydrate&quot; <lb/>village, one of the eight villages. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soon-Myung Hong et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>117 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 5. Nutrition safari page <lb/>Fig. 6. Nutrition café page <lb/>Fig. 7. Nutrition café page of &quot;Protein village&quot; <lb/>Fig. 8. Food tower page <lb/>Food tower <lb/>This page provides the amount and types of foods which are <lb/>consumed in a daily meal (Fig. 8). Each layer of the food guide <lb/>tower shows in turn to the upper step that nutrients should be <lb/>taken in lesser amounts. There are four layers. The function of <lb/>each layer&apos;s food type is explained. The symptom is also <lb/>explained when each layer&apos;s nutrition is over-eaten or is deficient <lb/>in a body. <lb/>Guideline of diet plan <lb/>This page gives the guidelines of diet plan for the age groups, <lb/>infants, children and adolescents (Fig. 9). For each age group, <lb/>there are seven recommendations by their age and critical <lb/>nutrition education and the characters which are the alias of <lb/>important nutrients. <lb/>Guideline of dietary reference intakes (DRIs) for Koreans <lb/>On this page, users will learn why guidelines of a diet plan <lb/>are so important (Fig. 10). There are four criteria in the guideline, <lb/>which are average, recommended, sufficient and upper limit <lb/>amount (DRIs, Korean Nutrition Society 2005). In the nutrition <lb/>intake table, users can find the most appropriate criteria of the <lb/>four criteria for them because those kinds of criteria are different <lb/>by the age, gender and nutrient needs. <lb/>Guideline of nutrients daily value (DV) <lb/>The guideline of nutrients is the representative value for each <lb/>ingredient. The value is applied to the all kinds of foods except <lb/>the group under the age of four, pregnant women and breast <lb/>feeding women. It is guideline of labeling of nutrient of processed <lb/>foods in terms of the percentile expression (Fig. 11) and it&apos;s <lb/>getting important for nutrition assessment and health care to <lb/>prevent an epidemiologic obesity trend. <lb/>Guideline of nutrition labeling <lb/>This page contains the information on the nutrition label (Fig. <lb/>12). The users learn why nutrition labeling is important, how <lb/></body>

			<page>118 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 9. Guideline page of diet plan <lb/>Fig. 10. Guideline page of dietary reference intakes (DRIs) <lb/>Fig. 11. Guideline of nutrients daily value (DV) <lb/>Fig. 12. Guideline of nutrition labeling <lb/>nutrition labeling with each food is interpreted and how the <lb/>nutrition amount is used for their health. <lb/>Menu search classification and recipe contents <lb/>This site contains menus for the infants, children and ado-<lb/>lescents. The menus are classified into groups by the criteria of <lb/>age, menu type, and ethnic origin of menu. The items of menu <lb/>type are main dish, side dish, dessert, etc. The items of ethnic <lb/>menus are Korean food, Chinese food, Japanese food, Western <lb/>style food, Southeast Asian food, etc. This information also is <lb/>searched by the search function. Fig. 13 is the page showing <lb/>the main dish for infants. There are screen scripts showing the <lb/>cooking process of a menu (Fig. 14). There is also a trans-<lb/>formation program which modifies the weights of raw materials <lb/>of a menu according to the change of weight of a certain raw <lb/>material of the menu. Fig. 15 shows a cooking course with video <lb/>script. <lb/>Search function <lb/>This site provides the search function which finds a menu under <lb/>a certain condition. It comes from 151 menus developed by the <lb/>sub-project in association with this research. The search <lb/>conditions are classified into three categories based on the <lb/>contents of the sub-expression. <lb/>The first one is the key word expression. The search content <lb/>expressions of the combination of the name of menu, name of <lb/>food materials, age group, menu type, menu style and nutrients. <lb/>The site accommodates the both the Korean and English names. <lb/>Fig. 16 is the menu search page whose search condition is <lb/>pumpkin. The second one is the &quot;between&quot; expression of the <lb/>lower bound and the upper bound of a certain nutrition ingredient <lb/>such as calorie and other nutrients. The absence of either of the <lb/>bound expressions means the value higher than the lower bound <lb/>value or the value lower than the upper bound. Fig. 17 is the <lb/>result of menu search. If we chose pumpkin as the title of menu, <lb/>we can the result of pumpkin menu and then, we can click wider <lb/>picture, recipe, video script, raw material of menu, nutrient and <lb/>specific capture. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soon-Myung Hong et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>119 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 13. Page showing main dish list for infants <lb/>Fig. 14. Menu recipe sample <lb/>Fig. 15. Menu recipe with Video script <lb/>Fig. 16. Menu search page whose search condition is a pumpkin <lb/>Fig. 17. Result of search of pumpkin <lb/>Discussion <lb/>This research aims to develop healthy menus during childhood <lb/>and making it available to the public. For this goal, the web-based <lb/>program is the most familiar and friendly interface to school <lb/>children. Some web-based programs for nutrition were developed <lb/>(Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; Hong &amp; Kim, 2005; <lb/>Lee et al., 2002), but web-based nutrition education programs <lb/>for children are very limited. Nutrition web-sites for children <lb/>should be constructed in a way which children find the sites <lb/>easily and search the contents while having fun (Ahn et al., 2007; <lb/>Ahn &amp; Kim, 2007). <lb/>We developed and composed this website to implement a <lb/>database program to store contents and search function. This <lb/>study has been focusing on a standardization of nutrient infor-<lb/>mation. To date, in the domestic environment, it is difficult to <lb/>find any research, organization or homepage that provides the <lb/>standards of nutrient expression. Therefore, we anticipate that <lb/>the constructed nutrient database system will make a contribution <lb/>to save nutrition information and to design criteria for sharing <lb/></body>

			<page>120 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Web-based nutrition education and healthy menu for children <lb/></note>

			<body>its information. In the introduction of this site, contents of DRIs <lb/>and Daily Value (DV) were added. Recently, restaurant nutrition <lb/>labeling was researched and it would become set in a legal term <lb/>(Hong &amp; Jeong, 2007) to prevent global tendency of high calorie <lb/>diet and out-going food. <lb/>The home page explains the site as a whole. This page has <lb/>links to the contents classified into eight nutrient groups. These <lb/>contents were considered for needs of nutrition education (Park <lb/>et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). Previous web-based nutrition <lb/>programs did not include them. So these kinds of trials will be <lb/>good education tools (Han &amp; Jeong, 2004; Her &amp; Lee, 2002; <lb/>Hong &amp; Kim, 2005). <lb/>This site contains menus for infants, children and adolescents. <lb/>The menus can be searched by many categories and have screen <lb/>scripts of the cooking process. There is also a transforming <lb/>program that modifies the weights of raw materials of menus <lb/>according to the change of weight of a certain raw material of <lb/>the menu. This site provides the search function for 151 healthy <lb/>menus for children in association with this research. <lb/>We tried to make the program from the children&apos;s viewpoints, <lb/>but some did not work properly. And the menu for the kids is <lb/>very limited. So we have to provide easier and a variety of menus <lb/>having more nutritious ingredients for the kids. This kind of effort <lb/>was organized for kid&apos;s easy access and attribute motive to learn <lb/>about food and nutrition. It will give better motive for education <lb/>needs of kids (Park et al., 2006; Shin et al., 2006). These kinds <lb/>of trials can be helpful for a future disease preventing program <lb/>and it could give knowledgeable information to the kids. We <lb/>hope that these kinds of web-based systems could be widely used <lb/>for nutrition education for kids and adults. <lb/></body>


			<back>

				<listBibl>Literature cited <lb/>Ahn Y, Kim HM, Seo JS, Yoon EY, Bea HJ &amp; Kim KW (2007). <lb/>Needs assessment for developing a nutrition information site for <lb/>elementary school children among elementary school dietitians. <lb/>Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 12:405-416. <lb/>Ahn Y &amp; Kim KW (2007). Study on utilization status of internet <lb/>and needs assessment for developing nutrition education programs <lb/>among elementary school children. Nutrition Research and Prac-<lb/>tice 1:341-348. <lb/>Boyle MA (2003). Community nutrition in action (3rd Eds), p.309-<lb/>311. Tomson wadsworth, USA <lb/>Department of Health and Welfare &amp; Korean Health Industry <lb/>Development Institute (2006). The Third Korea National Health &amp; <lb/>Nutrition Examination Survey (KNHANES III), 2005-Nutrition <lb/>Survey(1). Department of Health and Welfare, Seoul. Republic of <lb/>Korea <lb/>Han JS (1997). A computerized system for diagnosis and nutritional <lb/>assessment of dietary intakes : Recommended dietary allowances <lb/>for Koreans, 6 <lb/>th revision. Journal of the Korean Society of Food <lb/>science and Nutrition 26:726-732. <lb/>Han JS (2000). A system for nutritional assessment and diagnosis of <lb/>dietary intakes through internet. Journal of the Korean Society of <lb/>Food science and Nutrition 29:1177-1184. <lb/>Han JS &amp; Jeong JH (2004). A web-based internet program for <lb/>nutrition counseling and diet management of patient with diabetes <lb/>mellitus. Journal of the Korean Society of Food science and <lb/>Nutrition 33:114-122. <lb/>Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2003a). Utilization status of internet and dietary <lb/>information of school children in Gyeongnam and Jeonbuk areas. <lb/>Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 8:15-25. <lb/>Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2003b). Effect-evaluation of nutritional education <lb/>program using internet for school children. The Korean Journal <lb/>of Nutrition 36:500-507. <lb/>Her ES &amp; Lee KH (2002). Development of computer-aided nutri-<lb/>tional education program for the school children. The Korean <lb/>Journal of Nutrition 35:791-799. <lb/>Hong SM (1989). Development of computer programs for nutrition <lb/>counseling. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 22:275-289. <lb/>Hong SM (1996). Development status and application of software in <lb/>nutrition. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 29:1170-1174. <lb/>Hong SM &amp; Kim G (2005). System for nutrition counseling and <lb/>screening. Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 7:220-229. <lb/>Hong SM, Cho HS &amp; Kim G (2003). A basic study of food exchange <lb/>database construction and search system (ENECC/E-Food Exch-<lb/>ange) based on internet Journal of the Korean Dietetic Association <lb/>9:159-171. <lb/>Hong SM &amp; Jeong HJ (2007). Model development of nutrition labe-<lb/>ling on restaurant and fast-food, p.124-181. Korean Food &amp; Drug <lb/>Association report, Seoul. Republic of Korea <lb/>Joni Youngwirth (1983). The evolution of computers in dietetics: A <lb/>review, J Am Die Assoc 32:62-67. <lb/>Kang HJ, Kim KJ &amp; Kim I (1999). A study on the computerized <lb/>nutrition counseling program by food intake and exercise amount <lb/>checking. The Korean Jounal of Nutrition 32:598-607. <lb/>Kim YJ &amp; Yoon EY (1999). Development and evaluation of nutrition <lb/>education program through internet. Korean Journal of Community <lb/>Nutrition 4:546-553. <lb/>Kolasa KM &amp; Miller MG (1996). New developments in nutrition <lb/>education using computer technology. J Nutr Educ 28:7-14. <lb/>Lee JW, Seo JS, Kim KE &amp; Ly SY (2002). A needs assessment to <lb/>develop website contents on nutritional information and counseling <lb/>for teenagers. Korean Journal of Community Nutrition 7:664-674. <lb/>National Internet Development Agency of Korea &amp; Ministry of <lb/>Information Communication Republic of Korea (2007). 2006 <lb/>Survey on the computer and internet usage. http://isis.nida.or.kr/ <lb/>index_unssl. jsp. Accessed on 8/1/07. <lb/>Park YH, Kim HH, Shin KH, Shin EK, Bae IS &amp; Lee YK (2006). <lb/>A survey on practice of nutrition education and perception for <lb/>implementing nutrition education by nutrition teachers in ele-<lb/>mentary schools. The Korean Journal of Nutrition 39:403-416. <lb/>Shin EK, Shin KH, Kim HH, Park YH, Bae IS &amp; Lee YK (2006). <lb/>A survey on the needs educators, learners and parents for imple-<lb/>menting nutrition education by nutrition teachers in elementary <lb/>schools. Journal of the Korean Dietetic Association 12:89-101. <lb/>The Korean Nutrition Society (2005). Dietary Reference Intakes <lb/>(DRIs) for Koreans. Seoul. Republic of Korea <lb/>Youn SJ (2001). Implementation of WEB site for nutrition assessment <lb/>and management. Ministry of Health Welfare and Family Affairs <lb/>[Abstract]. </listBibl>
				
			</back>	


	</text>
</tei>
