<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Haptoglobin Genotype and Renal Function Decline in <lb/>Type 1 Diabetes <lb/>Tina Costacou, 1 Robert E. Ferrell, 2 Demetrius Ellis, 3 and Trevor J. Orchard 1 <lb/>OBJECTIVE-Haptoglobin (Hp) binds free Hb, inhibiting Hb-<lb/>induced oxidative damage. As oxidative stress has been associ-<lb/>ated with microvascular complications, we evaluated the <lb/>relationship between Hp genotype and microalbuminuria, mac-<lb/>roalbuminuria, end-stage renal disease (ESRD), and early renal <lb/>function decline in type 1 diabetes. <lb/>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS-Participants from the <lb/>Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study with DNA avail-<lb/>able were studied for the incidence of microalbuminuria (albu-<lb/>min excretion rate [AER] 20 -200 g/min), macroalbuminuria <lb/>(AER 200 g/min), ESRD (renal dialysis or transplantation), <lb/>and renal function decline (a decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 <lb/>from baseline estimated [by the Cockcroft-Gault equation] glo-<lb/>merular filtration rate [eGFR] in those with baseline eGFR 60 <lb/>ml/min per 1.73 m 2 ). <lb/>RESULTS-The proportions with the Hp 2/2, 2/1, and 1/1 <lb/>genotype were 43.4, 44.4, and 12.1%, respectively. During 18 years <lb/>of follow-up, the incidence of eGFR decline, microalbuminuria, <lb/>macroalbuminuria, and ESRD was 42.0, 40.5, 16.7, and 12.2%, <lb/>respectively. No significant univariate differences were ob-<lb/>served by Hp genotype. However, in multivariable Cox mod-<lb/>els, an twofold increased risk was observed for the Hp 2/2 <lb/>compared with the Hp 1/1 genotype for eGFR decline (hazard <lb/>ratio 1.79 [95% CI 1.06 -3.00]) and ESRD (2.74 [1.17-6.45]); no <lb/>significant associations were observed for microalbuminuria <lb/>or macroalbuminuria. <lb/>
			CONCLUSIONS-These data suggest that although Hp geno-<lb/>type is not associated with albuminuria per se, it may be an <lb/>independent determinant of early renal function decline and <lb/>progression to ESRD. Understanding these apparent contradic-<lb/>tory findings may provide further insight into the pathogenesis of <lb/>renal disease in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes 58:2904-2909, 2009 <lb/></front>

			<body>R <lb/>eactive oxygen species have been implicated in <lb/>both the etiology and progression of diabetes <lb/>complications, including nephropathy (1). <lb/>However, clinical trials assessing the impact <lb/>of antioxidant supplementation on micro-and macro-<lb/>vascular disease development have generally yielded <lb/>null results (2). <lb/>It has recently been proposed that the effectiveness of <lb/>an antioxidant regimen may be limited to susceptible <lb/>subgroups, such as individuals with the haptoglobin (Hp) <lb/>2/2 genotype (3). Hp is an acute-phase plasma 2 -<lb/>glycoprotein that, by binding to free Hb, inhibits Hb-<lb/>induced oxidative tissue damage (4). Once bound to Hp, <lb/>the Hp-Hb complex is cleared from circulation either at <lb/>the liver hepatocyte or through the scavenger receptor <lb/>CD163 present on monocytes and macrophages (5). In <lb/>humans, two common allele classes (Hp 1 and Hp 2 ) at the <lb/>Hp locus on chromosome 16q22 form three major geno-<lb/>types: Hp 1/1, Hp 2/1, and Hp 2/2 (4). Substantial evidence <lb/>supports a pathogenetic role of this polymorphism (6), <lb/>with the Hp 1 protein allele being more efficient in <lb/>preventing heme release from Hp-Hb complexes and pro-<lb/>moting uptake by the CD163 macrophage receptor (7-9) as <lb/>well as the antioxidant capacity of Hp 2 allele protein <lb/>product being restricted by its greater molecular mass (5) <lb/>and also associated with impaired reverse cholesterol <lb/>transport (7,10). Moreover, although Hp allele distribution <lb/>does not differ by diabetes status (6), the Hp 2 allele <lb/>protein product increases susceptibility to vascular com-<lb/>plications only in diabetes (11,12). Finally, daily vitamin E <lb/>supplementation in type 2 diabetes with the Hp 2/2 geno-<lb/>type significantly reduced cardiovascular event risk <lb/>(13,14). <lb/>We have previously shown that the Hp 2/2 genotype is a <lb/>determinant of the risk of cardiovascular disease also in <lb/>type 1 diabetes (15). In this article, we evaluated the <lb/>relationship between Hp genotype and both renal damage <lb/>(microalbuminuria and macroalbuminuria) and renal func-<lb/>tion (end-stage renal disease [ESRD] and early renal <lb/>function decline) in type 1 diabetes (n 486). <lb/>RESEARCH DESIGN AND METHODS <lb/>The Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study was based on a historical <lb/>cohort of incident cases of childhood-onset (17 years) type 1 diabetes, <lb/>diagnosed or seen within 1 year of diagnosis (1950 -1980) at Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital of Pittsburgh (16). The cohort has been shown to be representative <lb/>of the Allegheny County, Pennsylvania, type 1 diabetes population (17). <lb/>Subsequent to a first clinical assessment (1986 -1988, when average partici-<lb/>pant age and diabetes duration were 28 and 19 years, respectively), biennial <lb/>examinations were conducted for 10 years, with a further examination at 18 <lb/>years. The University of Pittsburgh Institutional Review Board approved the <lb/>study protocol. <lb/>Prior to each clinic visit, participants were sent questionnaires concerning <lb/>demographic, health care, self-care, and medical history information. Blood <lb/>pressure was measured with a random zero sphygmomanometer after a 5-min <lb/>rest (18). Hypertension was defined as 140/90 mmHg or use of anti-<lb/>hypertensive medication. Stable HbA 1 was measured by ion exchange chro-<lb/>matography (Isolab, Akron, OH) and subsequently by automated high-<lb/>performance liquid chromatography (Diamat; BioRad, Hercules, CA). The two <lb/>assays were highly correlated (r 0.95). HDL cholesterol was determined by <lb/>a precipitation technique with a modification (19) of the Lipid Research <lb/>Clinics method (20). Cholesterol and triglycerides were enzymatically mea-<lb/>sured (21,22). Non-HDL cholesterol was calculated as total minus HDL <lb/>cholesterol. White blood cell count was obtained using a counter S-plus IV and <lb/>fibrinogen using a biuret colorimetric procedure and a clotting method. <lb/></body>

			<front>From the 1 Department of Epidemiology, University of Pittsburgh, Pittsburgh, <lb/>Pennsylvania; the 2 Department of Human Genetics, University of Pitts-<lb/>burgh, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania; and the 3 Children&apos;s Hospital of Pittsburgh, <lb/>University of Pittsburgh School of Medicine, Pittsburgh, Pennsylvania. <lb/>Corresponding author: Tina Costacou, costacout@edc.pitt.edu. <lb/>Received 11 June 2009 and accepted 17 August 2009. Published ahead of <lb/>print at http://diabetes.diabetesjournals.org on 31 August 2009. DOI: <lb/>10.2337/db09-0874. <lb/>© 2009 by the American Diabetes Association. Readers may use this article as <lb/>long as the work is properly cited, the use is educational and not for profit, <lb/>and the work is not altered. See http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by <lb/>-nc-nd/3.0/ for details. <lb/>The costs of publication of this article were defrayed in part by the payment of page <lb/>charges. This article must therefore be hereby marked &quot;advertisement&quot; in accordance <lb/>with 18 U.S.C. Section 1734 solely to indicate this fact. <lb/>BRIEF REPORT <lb/>2904 <lb/>DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/></front>

			<body>Urinary albumin was measured by immunonephelometry (23), and creati-<lb/>nine was assayed by an Ectachem 400 Analyzer (Eastman Kodak, Rochester, <lb/>NY). Microalbuminuria was defined as albumin excretion rate (AER) of <lb/>20 -200 g/min (30 -300 mg per 24 h) and macroalbuminuria as AER 200 <lb/>g/min (300 mg per 24 h) in at least 2 of 3 validated timed urine collections. <lb/>In 10% of the samples, urine collections were deemed inadequate based on <lb/>creatinine excretion and albumin-to-creatinine ratio was used (microalbumin-<lb/>uria, 0.03-0.3 mg/mg; macroalbuminuria, 0.3 mg/mg) (24). ESRD onset was <lb/>defined as starting dialysis or undergoing renal transplantation. Early renal <lb/>function decline was defined as the incidence of a decline of 30 ml/min per <lb/>1.73 m 2 from baseline estimated glomerular filtration rate (eGFR) based on the <lb/>Cockcroft-Gault equation (25) among participants with normal or mildly <lb/>reduced renal function at study entry (stages I and II). <lb/>High molecular weight genomic DNA was isolated using the PureGene kit <lb/>(Gentra Systems, Minneapolis, MN), and Hp was genotyped by an amplifica-<lb/>tion method (26). Genotypes were assigned visually by comparison with <lb/>controls of known genotype and in a random sample showed excellent <lb/>agreement (97%) with an Eliza method (27). <lb/>Statistical analysis. Nonnormally distributed variables were logarithmically <lb/>transformed. Univariate associations were determined using the Student t test <lb/>and 2 or Fisher exact test, as appropriate. Cox proportional hazards models <lb/>with backward elimination were constructed to assess the multivariable <lb/>association between Hp genotype and the incidence of each outcome of <lb/>interest adjusting for traditional risk factors (including eGFR and AER levels <lb/>at study entry) and univariately significant variables. Survival time was <lb/>defined as the time in years from study entry to either an incident event or <lb/>censorship during the 18-year follow-up. Statistical analyses were conducted <lb/>using SAS (version 9.1; SAS Institute, Cary, NC). <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Of 658 study participants, DNA for Hp genotyping was <lb/>available for 486 (73.9%). Compared with those without <lb/>DNA available, individuals with DNA data had a shorter <lb/>diabetes duration and higher HbA 1 , blood pressure, non-<lb/>HDL cholesterol, serum creatinine, eGFR, and AER. The <lb/>distribution of the Hp genotype was 12.1% Hp 1/1, 44.4% Hp <lb/>2/1, and 43.4% Hp 2/2. Generally, no differences were <lb/>observed in participant characteristics by Hp genotype at <lb/>study entry with the exception of younger age and higher <lb/>non-HDL cholesterol in those with the Hp 2/2 compared <lb/>with the 2/1 genotype and lower insulin dose per weight in <lb/>those with the Hp 2/1 compared with the 1/1 genotype. <lb/>During 18 years of follow-up, 40.5% (n 111) developed <lb/>incident microalbuminuria, 16.7% (n 62) macroalbumin-<lb/>uria, and 12.2% (n 58) ESRD. Moreover, 188 (42.0%) <lb/>exhibited an early decline in renal function (30 ml/min <lb/>per 1.73 m 2 from baseline eGFR). Descriptive participant <lb/>characteristics by incidence of microalbuminuria and mac-<lb/>roalbuminuria are shown in Table 1 and by renal function <lb/>decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 and ESRD incidence in <lb/>Table 2. Generally, incident case subjects with both mi-<lb/>croalbuminuria and macroalbuminuria were more likely to <lb/>have higher levels of HbA 1 , non-HDL cholesterol, AER, and <lb/>inflammatory markers compared with those who remained <lb/>disease free. Incident case subjects with macroalbumin-<lb/>uria were also older at the time of diabetes onset com-<lb/>pared with noncase subjects and had a greater waist-to-hip <lb/>ratio. <lb/>Compared with noncase subjects, incident case subjects <lb/>with early renal function decline and ESRD were older, <lb/>TABLE 1 <lb/>Participant characteristics at study entry by subsequent microalbuminuria and macroalbuminuria status <lb/>Microalbuminuria <lb/>Macroalbuminuria <lb/>No <lb/>Yes <lb/>P <lb/>No <lb/>Yes <lb/>P <lb/>n <lb/>163 <lb/>111 <lb/>309 <lb/>62 <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>25.0 7.7 <lb/>25.8 8.3 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>26.2 8.1 <lb/>27.1 7.4 <lb/>0.43 <lb/>Age at onset (years) <lb/>8.5 4.2 <lb/>8.3 4.1 <lb/>0.64 <lb/>8.2 4.2 <lb/>9.3 3.3 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>Diabetes duration (years) <lb/>16.3 6.9 <lb/>17.6 7.6 <lb/>0.21 <lb/>18.0 7.6 <lb/>17.8 7.5 <lb/>0.83 <lb/>Follow-up time (years) <lb/>15.5 5.0 <lb/>7.3 4.8 <lb/>0.0001 15.2 5.0 <lb/>8.0 5.3 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Female subjects <lb/>50.9 (83) <lb/>55.9 (62) <lb/>0.42 <lb/>52.4 (162) <lb/>40.3 (25) <lb/>0.08 <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>23.1 3.2 <lb/>23.2 3.3 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>23.5 3.4 <lb/>23.6 3.1 <lb/>0.74 <lb/>Waist-to-hip ratio <lb/>0.81 0.06 <lb/>0.82 0.06 <lb/>0.27 <lb/>0.81 0.07 <lb/>0.84 0.07 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Ever smokers <lb/>28.8 (47) <lb/>31.5 (35) <lb/>0.63 <lb/>32.0 (99) <lb/>38.7 (24) <lb/>0.31 <lb/>HbA 1 (%) <lb/>9.7 (1.4) <lb/>10.8 (1.8) <lb/>0.0001 10.0 (1.6) <lb/>11.1 (2.0) <lb/>0.0002 <lb/>Insulin dose per weight* <lb/>0.81 (0.65-0.95) <lb/>0.80 (0.66-0.95) <lb/>0.77 <lb/>0.80 (0.63-0.94) <lb/>0.80 (0.60-0.98) <lb/>0.97 <lb/>Systolic blood pressure (mmHg) 106.9 10.7 <lb/>109.1 10.3 <lb/>0.10 108.8 11.4 <lb/>110.7 12.9 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>Diastolic blood pressure (mmHg) 67.9 8.4 <lb/>69.8 7.8 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>69.5 9.1 <lb/>70.8 9.1 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>3.7 (6) <lb/>3.6 (4) <lb/>1.00 † <lb/>5.5 (17) <lb/>9.7 (6) <lb/>0.21 <lb/>HDL cholesterol (mg/dl) <lb/>55.2 12.1 <lb/>54.0 9.8 <lb/>0.37 <lb/>54.5 11.4 <lb/>56.1 11.9 <lb/>0.38 <lb/>Non-HDL cholesterol (mg/dl) <lb/>116.0 25.5 <lb/>128.1 34.3 <lb/>0.002 122.9 30.2 <lb/>141.1 43.2 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>ACE/ARB use <lb/>1.3 (2) <lb/>0.9 (1) <lb/>1.00 † <lb/>1.0 (3) <lb/>1.7 (1) <lb/>0.52 † <lb/>Serum creatinine (mg/dl)* <lb/>0.80 (0.70-1.0) <lb/>0.80 (0.60-0.90) <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.80 (0.70-1.0) <lb/>0.90 (0.70-1.0) <lb/>0.39 <lb/>eGFR by Cockcroft-Gault <lb/>(ml/min per 1.73 m 2 ) <lb/>121.1 37.8 <lb/>124.6 38.7 <lb/>0.46 120.9 37.1 <lb/>125.0 43.5 <lb/>0.44 <lb/>AER (g/min)* <lb/>7.2 (5.1-10.1) <lb/>9.0 (6.2-11.6) <lb/>0.004 19.2 (5.9-16.1) <lb/>23.5 (9.5-71.3) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>White blood cell count <lb/>10 3 /mm 2 * <lb/>5.6 (4.8-6.6) <lb/>6.1 (5.2-7.2) <lb/>0.02 <lb/>5.8 (5.1-7.0) <lb/>6.7 (5.2-8.0) <lb/>0.005 <lb/>Fibrinogen (mg/dl)* <lb/>250.0 (200.0-300.0) 265.0 (220.0-300.0) 0.12 250.0 (210.0-305.0) 270.0 (240.0-310.0) 0.06 <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>77.4 (24) <lb/>22.6 (7) <lb/>81.4 (35) <lb/>18.6 (8) <lb/>2/1 <lb/>55.5 (71) <lb/>44.5 (57) <lb/>84.8 (145) <lb/>15.2 (26) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>59.1 (68) <lb/>40.9 (47) <lb/>0.08 <lb/>82.2 (129) <lb/>17.8 (28) <lb/>0.77 <lb/>Data are percent (n) or means SD unless otherwise indicated. The sample size for ACE/angiotensin receptor blocker medications was 270 <lb/>for the outcome of microalbuminuria (159 noncases and 111 incident cases) and 362 for the outcome of macroalbuminuria (302 noncases <lb/>and 60 incident cases). *The Wilcoxon two-sample test was used for nonnormally distributed variables; data are median (interquartile range). <lb/> †Fisher exact test. ARB, angiotensin receptor blocker. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T. COSTACOU AND ASSOCIATES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/>DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/></note>

			<page>2905 <lb/></page>

			<body>with higher systolic blood pressure, non-HDL cholesterol, <lb/>AER, and inflammatory marker levels and lower HDL <lb/>cholesterol. Incident case subjects with early renal func-<lb/>tion decline had an older age of diabetes onset and higher <lb/>BMI, HbA 1 , and eGFR and lower serum creatinine. Con-<lb/>versely, greater diabetes duration and higher levels of <lb/>diastolic blood pressure and serum creatinine but lower <lb/>insulin dose per kilogram body weight and eGFR were <lb/>observed in incident case subjects with ESRD compared <lb/>with noncase subjects. No univariate association, how-<lb/>ever, was observed between Hp and the incidence of other <lb/>renal outcomes at the 0.05 significance level. Hp genotype <lb/>was also not associated with all-cause mortality (P 0.80) <lb/>based on 82 (16.9%) deceased individuals. <lb/>Multivariable Cox proportional hazards models (Table <lb/>3) showed no association between the Hp genotype and <lb/>microalbuminuria or macroalbuminuria incidence. Con-<lb/>versely, adjusting for univariately significant risk factors, <lb/>an increased risk of an early renal function decline was <lb/>observed for individuals carrying the Hp 2/2 compared <lb/>with the Hp 1/1 genotype (hazard ratio 1.79 [95% CI <lb/>1.06 -3.00]). Similarly, the Hp 2/2 conferred over a twofold <lb/>increased risk of ESRD compared with the Hp 1/1 geno-<lb/>type (2.45 [1.05-5.73]). The risk associated with the Hp 2/1 <lb/>reached statistical significance for neither early renal <lb/>function decline nor ESRD incidence. <lb/>To examine the possibility of survival bias, we stratified <lb/>the cohort by diabetes diagnosis year (prior to or after <lb/>1965, wherein mortality was 40 vs. 13%, respectively). With <lb/>the exception of macroalbuminuria, a trend toward higher <lb/>incidence rates among the Hp 2/2 compared with the Hp <lb/>1/1 genotype was generally observed in those diagnosed <lb/>after 1965 (less subject to survival bias); however, none of <lb/>the stratified results were statistically significant (Table 4). <lb/>Similarly, when conducting cumulative incidence analyses <lb/>(including prevalent cases in outcomes), results demon-<lb/>strated nonsignificantly higher rates in those carrying the <lb/>Hp 2/2 compared with the Hp 1/1 genotype with the <lb/>exception of macroalbuminuria (Table 4). <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this cohort of subjects with type 1 diabetes, we failed to <lb/>show an association between the Hp genotype and either <lb/>microalbuminuria or macroalbuminuria incidence. How-<lb/>ever, although not univariately significant, approximately a <lb/>twofold increased risk emerged for outcomes assessing <lb/>TABLE 2 <lb/>Participant characteristics at study entry by a subsequent decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 from baseline eGFR and ESRD <lb/>A decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 from baseline <lb/>eGFR <lb/>ESRD <lb/>No <lb/>Yes <lb/>P <lb/>No <lb/>Yes <lb/>P <lb/>n <lb/>260 <lb/>188 <lb/>416 <lb/>58 <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>26.2 8.0 <lb/>27.8 7.3 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>26.6 7.8 <lb/>31.2 6.3 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Age at onset (years) <lb/>7.9 4.2 <lb/>9.0 3.8 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>8.4 4.1 <lb/>7.8 3.9 <lb/>0.29 <lb/>Diabetes duration (years) <lb/>18.3 7.3 <lb/>18.8 7.6 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>18.2 7.4 <lb/>23.4 7.1 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Follow-up time (years) <lb/>14.0 5.3 <lb/>6.5 4.8 <lb/>0.0001 15.2 3.9 <lb/>9.1 4.6 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Female subjects <lb/>45.8 (119) <lb/>54.3 (102) <lb/>0.08 <lb/>49.5 (206) <lb/>48.3 (28) <lb/>0.86 <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 ) <lb/>23.3 3.5 <lb/>24.3 3.0 <lb/>0.0008 23.6 3.3 <lb/>23.9 3.0 <lb/>0.48 <lb/>Waist-to-hip ratio <lb/>0.82 0.07 <lb/>0.83 0.07 <lb/>0.47 <lb/>0.82 0.07 <lb/>0.84 0.08 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>Ever smokers <lb/>33.5 (87) <lb/>38.8 (73) <lb/>0.24 <lb/>34.6 (144) <lb/>41.4 (24) <lb/>0.31 <lb/>HbA 1 (%) <lb/>8.5 (1.4) <lb/>9.0 (1.4) <lb/>0.0004 10.2 (1.7) <lb/>10.6 (1.9) <lb/>0.11 <lb/>Insulin dose per weight* <lb/>0.80 (0.62-0.94) <lb/>0.77 (0.64-0.94) <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.80 (0.64-0.94) <lb/>0.67 (0.57-0.80) <lb/>0.002 <lb/>Systolic blood pressure <lb/>(mmHg) <lb/>110.6 12.6 <lb/>113.4 14.9 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>110.7 12.8 <lb/>123.5 16.5 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Diastolic blood pressure <lb/>(mmHg) <lb/>71.1 10.5 <lb/>72.7 10.8 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>71.1 10.2 <lb/>77.9 12.4 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>9.6 (25) <lb/>13.8 (26) <lb/>0.17 <lb/>9.1 (38) <lb/>50.0 (29) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>HDL cholesterol (mg/dl) <lb/>55.2 12.4 <lb/>52.9 11.4 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>54.6 12.1 <lb/>50.2 10.4 <lb/>0.009 <lb/>Non-HDL cholesterol <lb/>(mg/dl) <lb/>127.5 34.2 <lb/>138.9 44.2 <lb/>0.003 128.8 34.9 <lb/>166.5 57.6 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>ACE/ARB use <lb/>1.6 (4) <lb/>2.2 (4) <lb/>0.47 † <lb/>1.5 (6) <lb/>13.8 (8) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Serum creatinine (mg/dl)* 0.90 (0.80-1.10) <lb/>0.70 (0.60-0.90) <lb/>0.0001 0.80 (0.70-1.0) <lb/>1.3 (0.90-1.80) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>eGFR by Cockcroft-Gault <lb/>(ml/min per 1.73 m 2 ) 105.3 23.4 <lb/>140.6 42.9 <lb/>0.0001 121.3 38.0 <lb/>77.7 40.8 <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>AER (g/min)* <lb/>10.6 (6.2-31.0) <lb/>19.6 (8.8-363.1) <lb/>0.0001 11.3 (6.8-46.7) <lb/>1,030.2 (281.5-1,877.8) 0.0001 <lb/>White blood cell count <lb/>10 3 /mm 2 * <lb/>6.1 (5.2-7.1) <lb/>6.2 (5.4-7.6) <lb/>0.10 <lb/>6.1 (5.2-7.2) <lb/>7.1 (5.9-8.9) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Fibrinogen (mg/dl)* <lb/>250.0 (210.0-310.0) 270.0 (240.0-350.0) <lb/>0.0007 270.0 (220.0-310.0) <lb/>310.0 (270.0-390.0) <lb/>0.0001 <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>64.8 (35) <lb/>35.2 (19) <lb/>87.9 (51) <lb/>12.1 (7) <lb/>2/1 <lb/>62.1 (128) <lb/>37.9 (78) <lb/>90.2 (193) <lb/>9.8 (21) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>51.6 (97) <lb/>48.4 (91) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>85.2 (172) <lb/>14.9 (30) <lb/>0.29 <lb/>Data are percent (n) or means SD unless otherwise indicated. The sample size for ACE/angiotensin receptor blocker medications was 437 <lb/>for a decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 from baseline eGFR (251 noncases and 186 incident cases) and 463 for the outcome of ESRD (405 <lb/>noncases and 58 incident cases). *The Wilcoxon two-sample test was used for nonnormally distributed variables; data are median <lb/>(interquartile range). †Fisher exact test. ARB, angiotensin receptor blocker. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HAPTOGLOBIN GENOTYPE AND RENAL FUNCTION IN TYPE 1 DIABETES <lb/></note>

			<page>2906 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/></note>

			<body>renal function decline and ESRD incidence after multiva-<lb/>riable adjustments. <lb/>Previous studies assessing the association between the <lb/>Hp phenotype and the presence or incidence of renal <lb/>disease have produced discrepant findings. In a small, <lb/>cross-sectional study of normotensive subjects with type 1 <lb/>or 2 diabetes, none of those with the Hp 1/1 phenotype <lb/>exhibited signs of nephropathy (0/18) compared with 27% <lb/>(10/37) of those with Hp 2/1 and 34% (19/55) of those with <lb/>Hp 2/2 (P 0.02) (6,28). Similar results were reported <lb/>from an Irish type 1 diabetes case-control study (29). <lb/>Conversely, a Japanese study of individuals with a long <lb/>duration (10 years) of type 2 diabetes did not observe an <lb/>increased risk associated with the common Hp phenotype <lb/>(P 0.43) (30). Similarly, we were also not able to detect <lb/>an association for either microalbuminuria or macroalbu-<lb/>minuria incidence in our cohort of individuals with a long <lb/>duration of type 1 diabetes, perhaps suggesting that at a <lb/>more advanced stage of diabetes, early Hp-susceptible <lb/>cases of microalbuminuria and macroalbuminuria may <lb/>have been excluded. Indeed, the cumulative incidence of <lb/>microalbuminuria (including both prevalent cases at study <lb/>entry and incident cases) appeared higher in our study <lb/>among participants carrying the Hp 2 allele, although <lb/>results did not reach statistical significance. However, <lb/>analogous findings were not observed for the cumulative <lb/>incidence of macroalbuminuria, suggesting that the Hp 2/2 <lb/>genotype is not a strong determining factor for progres-<lb/>sion to macroalbuminuria. <lb/>Despite the null associations for the incidence of pro-<lb/>teinuria, a strong relationship was noted between the Hp <lb/>2/2 genotype and the incidence of both an early decline in <lb/>renal function and ESRD. Unfortunately, we are not aware <lb/>of any published reports on the association between the <lb/>Hp genotype and renal function decline among individuals <lb/>with diabetes and thus cannot, at present, confirm these <lb/>findings. However, the possibility of a factor affecting the <lb/>incidence of renal dysfunction but not that of renal disease <lb/>per se raises the hypothesis that these are two different <lb/>disease entities, and thus factors contributing to their <lb/>development may be distinct. Indeed, almost a decade ago, <lb/>we suggested that in certain cases tubulopathy may pre-<lb/>cede glomerulopathy in type 1 diabetes and that even <lb/>microalbuminuria may be secondary to impaired tubular <lb/>reabsorption (31). More recently, research studies have <lb/>shown that reductions in eGFR do occur without preced-<lb/>ing microalbuminuria in those with diabetes (32-34). Im-<lb/>portantly, a pathophysiological mechanism has been <lb/>proposed that could account for the increased rate of renal <lb/>function decline among individuals with diabetes and the <lb/>TABLE 3 <lb/>Hazard ratios (95% CIs) from Cox proportional hazard models for the incidence of microalbuminuria, macroalbuminuria, eGFR <lb/>decline (decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 from baseline eGFR), and ESRD <lb/>Outcome <lb/>Crude <lb/>Model 1 <lb/>Model 2 <lb/>Model 3 <lb/>Microalbuminuria (n 270, 111 incident events) <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>2/1 <lb/>2.09 (0.95-4.59) <lb/>2.19 (0.996-4.80) <lb/>2.08 (0.95-4.56) <lb/>1.77 (0.80-3.92) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>1.84 (0.83-4.07) <lb/>1.95 (0.88-4.32) <lb/>1.67 (0.75-3.71) <lb/>1.34 (0.59-3.05) <lb/>A1C <lb/>1,147.803 <lb/>1,140.392 <lb/>1,106.418 <lb/>1,100.600 <lb/>Model 1 allowed for diabetes duration, sex, log AER, and eGFR <lb/>Model 2 allowed for variables in model 1 in addition to HbA 1 , systolic blood pressure, and HDL and non-HDL cholesterol <lb/>Model 3 allowed for variables in model 2 in addition to white blood cell count <lb/>Macroalbuminuria (n 364, 61 incident events) <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>2/1 <lb/>0.77 (0.35-1.70) <lb/>0.78 (0.35-1.72) <lb/>0.77 (0.35-1.72) <lb/>0.72 (0.33-1.60) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>0.84 (0.38-1.86) <lb/>0.78 (0.35-1.72) <lb/>0.78 (0.35-1.73) <lb/>0.73 (0.33-1.62) <lb/>A1C <lb/>686.874 <lb/>656.057 <lb/>640.020 <lb/>636.806 <lb/>Model 1 allowed for diabetes duration, sex, smoking status, waist-to-hip ratio, log AER, and eGFR <lb/>Model 2 allowed for variables in model 1 in addition to HbA 1 , systolic blood pressure, and HDL and non-HDL cholesterol <lb/>Model 3 allowed for variables in model 2 in addition to white blood cell count <lb/>A decline 30 ml/min per 1.73 m 2 from baseline eGFR (n 441, 187 incident events) <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>2/2 <lb/>1.59 (0.97-2.60) <lb/>1.30 (0.78-2.18) <lb/>1.38 (0.82-2.31) <lb/>1.38 (0.82-2.31) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>1.59 (0.97-2.60) <lb/>1.64 (0.99-2.73) <lb/>1.79 (1.06-3.00) <lb/>1.79 (1.06-3.00) <lb/>A1C <lb/>2,102.198 <lb/>1,897.376 <lb/>1,896.567 <lb/>1,896.567 <lb/>Model 1 allowed for diabetes duration, sex, BMI, log AER, and eGFR <lb/>Model 2 allowed for variables in model 1 in addition to HbA 1 , systolic blood pressure, and HDL and non-HDL cholesterol <lb/>Model 3 allowed for variables in model 2 in addition to fibrinogen <lb/>ESRD (n 467, 57 incident events) <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>1/1 <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>Referent <lb/>2/1 <lb/>0.72 (0.30-1.69) <lb/>1.14 (0.48-2.74) <lb/>1.24 (0.51-2.98) <lb/>1.32 (0.55-3.16) <lb/>2/2 <lb/>1.15 (0.50-2.61) <lb/>2.17 (0.93-5.04) <lb/>2.74 (1.17-6.45) <lb/>2.45 (1.05-5.73) <lb/>A1C <lb/>672.450 <lb/>522.184 <lb/>509.657 <lb/>508.736 <lb/>Model 1 allowed for diabetes duration, sex, smoking status, log AER, and eGFR <lb/>Model 2 allowed for variables in model 1 in addition to HbA 1 , hypertension, and HDL and non-HDL cholesterol <lb/>Model 3 allowed for variables in model 2 in addition to white blood cell count and fibrinogen <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">T. COSTACOU AND ASSOCIATES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/>DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/></note>

			<page>2907 <lb/></page>

			<body>Hp 2/2 genotype (7), based on the recognition that renal <lb/>proximal tubule cells serve as a (secondary to CD163) <lb/>default mechanism for clearance of the Hp-Hb complex. <lb/>Because CD163-mediated clearance of the Hp-Hb complex <lb/>is impaired in subjects with diabetes and the Hp 2/2 <lb/>genotype, renal proximal tubule cells are used to a greater <lb/>extent, resulting in a dramatic increase in iron deposition, <lb/>oxidative stress, and hypertrophy. In fact, Hp 2/2 diabetic <lb/>mice have been shown to display significantly increased <lb/>glomerular and proximal tubular hypertrophy and greater <lb/>deposition of collagen type IV, smooth muscle actin, and <lb/>increased renal iron (35). Intriguingly, vitamin E adminis-<lb/>tration was shown to slow diabetic renal disease progres-<lb/>sion among the Hp 2/2 but not the Hp 1/1 mice. <lb/>In conclusion, we observed an association between the <lb/>Hp genotype and renal function decline in individuals with <lb/>long-standing type 1 diabetes. A caveat of this study is the <lb/>lack of independent replication of findings in another <lb/>cohort. Nevertheless, these results raise the possibility <lb/>that pharmacological administration of vitamin E, shown <lb/>to reduce cardiovascular disease outcomes in those with <lb/>type 2 diabetes with the Hp 2/2 genotype (13-14), may also <lb/>lead to reduced renal disease risk. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>This research was supported by the National Institutes of <lb/>Health Grant DK34818. <lb/>No potential conflicts of interest relevant to this article <lb/>were reported. <lb/>We thank all study participants for their invaluable <lb/>contributions as well as the Epidemiology of Diabetes <lb/>Complications Study staff. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Baynes JW, Thorpe SR. Role of oxidative stress in diabetic complications: <lb/>a new perspective on an old paradigm. Diabetes 1999;48:1-9 <lb/>2. Lonn E, Yusuf S, Hoogwerf B, Pogue J, Yi Q, Zinman B, Bosch J, Dagenais <lb/>G, Mann JF, Gerstein HC, HOPE Study, MICRO-HOPE Study. Effects of <lb/>vitamin E on cardiovascular and microvascular outcomes in high-risk <lb/>patients with diabetes: results of the HOPE study and MICRO-HOPE <lb/>substudy. Diabetes Care 2002;25:1919 -1927 <lb/>3. Levy AP. Application of pharmacogenomics in the prevention of diabetic <lb/>cardiovascular disease: mechanistic basis and clinical evidence for utili-<lb/>zation of the haptoglobin genotype in determining benefit from antioxidant <lb/>therapy. Pharmacol Ther 2006;112:501-512 <lb/>4. Langlois MR, Delanghe JR. Biological and clinical significance of hapto-<lb/>globin polymorphism in humans. Clin Chem 1996;42:1589 -1600 <lb/>5. Kristiansen M, Graversen JH, Jacobsen C, Sonne O, Hoffman HJ, Law SK, <lb/>Moestrup SK. Identification of the haemoglobin scavenger receptor. Na-<lb/>ture 2001;409:198 -201 <lb/>6. Asleh R, Levy AP. In vivo and in vitro studies establishing haptoglobin as <lb/>a major susceptibility gene for diabetic vascular disease. Vasc Health Risk <lb/>Manag 2005;1:19 -28 <lb/>7. Asleh R, Marsh S, Shilkrut M, Binah O, Guetta J, Lejbkowicz F, Enav B, <lb/>Shehadeh N, Kanter Y, Lache O, Cohen O, Levy NS, Levy AP. Genetically <lb/>determined heterogeneity in Hb scavenging and susceptibility to diabetic <lb/>cardiovascular disease. Circ Res 2003;92:1193-1200 <lb/>8. Asleh R, Guetta J, Kalet-Litman S, Miller-Lotan R, Levy AP. Haptoglobin <lb/>genotype-and diabetes-dependent differences in iron-mediated oxidative <lb/>stress in vitro and in vivo. Circ Res 2005;96:435-441 <lb/>9. Levy AP, Purushothaman KR, Levy NS, Purushothaman M, Strauss M, <lb/>Asleh R, Marsh S, Cohen O, Moestrup SK, Moller HJ, Zias EA, Benhayon D, <lb/>Fuster V, Moreno PR. Downregulation of the Hb scavenger receptor in <lb/>individuals with diabetes and the Hp 2-2 genotype: implications for the <lb/>response to intraplaque hemorrhage and plaque vulnerability. Circ Res <lb/>2007;101:106 -110 <lb/>10. Asleh R, Miller-Lotan R, Aviram M, Hayek T, Yulish M, Levy JE, Miller B, <lb/>Blum S, Milman U, Shapira C, Levy AP. Haptoglobin genotype is a regulator <lb/>of reverse cholesterol transport in diabetes in vitro and in vivo. Circ Res <lb/>2006;99:1419 -1425 <lb/>11. Levy AP, Hochberg I, Jablonski K, Resnick HE, Lee ET, Best L, Howard BV, <lb/>Strong Heart Study. Haptoglobin phenotype is an independent risk factor <lb/>for cardiovascular disease in individuals with diabetes: the Strong Heart <lb/>Study. J Am Coll Cardiol 2002;40:1984 -1990 <lb/>12. Suleiman M, Aronson D, Asleh R, Kapeliovich MR, Roguin A, Meisel SR, <lb/>Shochat M, Sulieman A, Reisner SA, Markiewicz W, Hammerman H, Lotan <lb/>R, Levy NS, Levy AP. Haptoglobin polymorphism predicts 30-day mortality <lb/>and heart failure in patients with diabetes and acute myocardial infarction. <lb/>Diabetes 2005;54:2802-2806 <lb/>13. Levy AP, Gerstein H, Lotan R, Ratner R, McQueen M, Lonn E, Pogue J. The <lb/>effect of vitamin E supplementation on cardiovascular risk in diabetic <lb/>individuals with different haptoglobin phenotypes. Diabetes Care 2004;27: <lb/>2767 <lb/>14. Milman U, Blum S, Shapira C, Aronson D, Miller-Lotan R, Anbinder Y, <lb/>Alshiek J, Bennett L, Kostenko M, Landau M, Keidar S, Levy Y, Khemlin A, <lb/>Radan A, Levy AP. Vitamin E supplementation reduces cardiovascular <lb/>events in a subgroup of middle-aged individuals with both type 2 diabetes <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>TABLE 4 <lb/>Incidence of renal outcomes by Hp genotype <lb/>Outcome incidence <lb/>n <lb/>Hp genotype <lb/>P <lb/>1/1 <lb/>2/1 <lb/>2/2 <lb/>Microalbuminuria <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>73 <lb/>11.1 (1) <lb/>46.3 (19) <lb/>47.8 (11) <lb/>0.14* <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>201 <lb/>27.3 (6) <lb/>43.7 (38) <lb/>39.1 (36) <lb/>0.37 <lb/>Total cohort <lb/>274 <lb/>22.6 (7) <lb/>44.5 (57) <lb/>40.9 (47) <lb/>0.08 <lb/>Cumulative incidence <lb/>483 <lb/>59.3 (35) <lb/>67.1 (145) <lb/>67.3 (140) <lb/>0.49 <lb/>Macroalbuminuria <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>112 <lb/>0.0 (0) <lb/>17.5 (11) <lb/>24.3 (9) <lb/>0.16* <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>259 <lb/>25.8 (8) <lb/>13.9 (15) <lb/>15.8 (19) <lb/>0.28 <lb/>Total cohort <lb/>371 <lb/>18.6 (8) <lb/>15.2 (26) <lb/>17.8 (28) <lb/>0.77 <lb/>Cumulative incidence <lb/>483 <lb/>40.7 (24) <lb/>32.9 (71) <lb/>38.0 (79) <lb/>0.40 <lb/>Early renal function decline <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>145 <lb/>47.1 (8) <lb/>34.3 (25) <lb/>50.9 (28) <lb/>0.15 <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>303 <lb/>29.7 (11) <lb/>39.9 (53) <lb/>47.4 (63) <lb/>0.13 <lb/>Total cohort <lb/>448 <lb/>35.2 (19) <lb/>37.9 (78) <lb/>48.4 (91) <lb/>0.06 <lb/>ESRD <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>162 <lb/>22.2 (4) <lb/>17.7 (14) <lb/>27.7 (18) <lb/>0.33* <lb/>Diabetes diagnosis 1965 <lb/>312 <lb/>7.5 (3) <lb/>5.2 (7) <lb/>8.8 (12) <lb/>0.50* <lb/>Total cohort <lb/>474 <lb/>12.1 (7) <lb/>9.8 (21) <lb/>14.9 (30) <lb/>0.29 <lb/>Cumulative incidence <lb/>483 <lb/>13.6 (8) <lb/>10.7 (23) <lb/>17.3 (36) <lb/>0.14 <lb/>Data are percent (n) unless otherwise indicated. *Fisher exact test. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HAPTOGLOBIN GENOTYPE AND RENAL FUNCTION IN TYPE 1 DIABETES <lb/></note>

			<page>2908 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/>diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>mellitus and the haptoglobin 2-2 genotype: a prospective double-blinded <lb/>clinical trial. Arterioscler Thromb Vasc Biol 2008;28:341-347 <lb/>15. Costacou T, Ferrell RE, Orchard TJ. Haptoglobin genotype: a determinant <lb/>of cardiovascular complication risk in type 1 diabetes. Diabetes 2008;57: <lb/>1702-1706 <lb/>16. Orchard TJ, Dorman JS, Maser RE, Becker DJ, Drash AL, Ellis D, LaPorte <lb/>RE, Kuller LH. Prevalence of complications of IDDM by sex and duration: <lb/>Pittsburgh Epidemiology of Diabetes Complications Study II. Diabetes <lb/>1990;39:1116 -1124 <lb/>17. Wagener DK, Sacks JM, LaPorte RE, Macgregor JM. The Pittsburgh Study <lb/>of insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus: risk for diabetes among relatives of <lb/>IDDM. Diabetes 1982;31:136 -144 <lb/>18. Borhani NO, Kass EH, Langford HG, Payne GH, Remington RD, Stamler J, <lb/>HDFP Cooperative Group. The hypertension detection and follow-up <lb/>program. Prev Med 1976;5:207-215 <lb/>19. Warnick GR, Albers JJ. Heparin-Mn2 quantitation of high-density-<lb/>lipoprotein cholesterol: an ultrafiltration procedure for lipemic samples. <lb/>Clin Chem 1978;24:900 -904 <lb/>20. National Institutes of Health and Department of Health. Lipid Research <lb/>Clinics Program. Washington, DC, US Government Printing Office, 1975 <lb/>21. Allain CC, Poon LS, Chan CS, Richmond W, Fu PC. Enzymatic determina-<lb/>tion of total serum cholesterol. Clin Chem 1974;20:470 -475 <lb/>22. Bucolo G, David H. Quantitative determination of serum triglycerides by <lb/>the use of enzymes. Clin Chem 1973;19:476 -482 <lb/>23. Ellis D, Buffone GJ. A new approach to the evaluation of proteinuric states. <lb/>Clin Chem 1977;23:666 -670 <lb/>24. Ellis D, Coonrod BA, Dorman JS, Kelsey SF, Becker DJ, Avner ED, Orchard <lb/>TJ. Choice of urine sample predictive of microalbuminuria in patients with <lb/>insulin-dependent diabetes mellitus. Am J Kidney Dis 1989;13:321-328 <lb/>25. Cockcroft DW, Gault MH. Prediction of creatinine clearance from serum <lb/>creatinine. Nephron 1976;16:31-41 <lb/>26. Koch W, Latz W, Eichinger M, Roguin A, Levy AP, Schö mig A, Kastrati A. <lb/>Genotyping of the common haptoglobin Hp 1/2 polymorphism based on <lb/>PCR. Clin Chem 2002;48:1377-1382 <lb/>27. Victor J, Cheong W, Chen JJS, Levy N, Miller-Lotan R, Levy AP, Blum S, <lb/>Orchard TJ, Evans RW, Costacou T, Hauth BA. Clinical results of a rapid <lb/>screening assay for haptoglobin 2-2: a cardiovascular disease risk marker <lb/>in diabetes (Abstract). Diabetes 2009;58(Suppl. 1):A176 <lb/>28. Levy AP, Roguin A, Hochberg I, Herer P, Marsh S, Nakhoul FM, Skorecki <lb/>K. Haptoglobin phenotype and vascular complications in patients with <lb/>diabetes. N Engl J Med 2000;343:969 -970 <lb/>29. Conway BR, Savage DA, Brady HR, Maxwell AP. Association between <lb/>haptoglobin gene variants and diabetic nephropathy: haptoglobin polymor-<lb/>phism in nephropathy susceptibility. Nephron Exp Nephrol 2007;105:e75-<lb/>e79 <lb/>30. Koda Y, Soejima M, Yamagishi S, Amano S, Okamoto T, Inagaki Y, Yamada <lb/>K, Kimura H. Haptoglobin genotype and diabetic microangiopathies in <lb/>Japanese diabetic patients. Diabetologia 2002;45:1039 -1040 <lb/>31. Ellis D, Forrest KY, Erbey J, Orchard TJ. Urinary measurement of <lb/>transforming growth factor-and type IV collagen as new markers of renal <lb/>injury: application in diabetic nephropathy. Clin Chem 1998;44:950 -956 <lb/>32. Kramer HJ, Nguyen QD, Curhan G, Hsu CY. Renal insufficiency in the <lb/>absence of albuminuria and retinopathy among adults with type 2 diabetes <lb/>mellitus. JAMA 2003;289:3273-3277 <lb/>33. Retnakaran R, Cull CA, Thorne KI, Adler AI, Holman RR, UKPDS Study <lb/>Group. Risk factors for renal dysfunction in type 2 diabetes: U.K. Prospec-<lb/>tive Diabetes Study 74. Diabetes 2006;55:1832-1839 <lb/>34. Costacou T, Ellis D, Fried L, Orchard TJ. Sequence of progression of <lb/>albuminuria and decreased GFR in persons with type 1 diabetes: a cohort <lb/>study. Am J Kidney Dis 2007;50:721-732 <lb/>35. Nakhoul FM, Miller-Lotan R, Awad H, Asleh R, Jad K, Nakhoul N, Asaf R, <lb/>Abu-Saleh N, Levy AP. Pharmacogenomic effect of vitamin E on kidney <lb/>structure and function in transgenic mice with the haptoglobin 2-2 <lb/>genotype and diabetes mellitus. Am J Physiol Renal Physiol 2009;296: <lb/>F830 -F838 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">T. COSTACOU AND ASSOCIATES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">diabetes.diabetesjournals.org <lb/>DIABETES, VOL. 58, DECEMBER 2009 <lb/></note>

			<page>2909 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
