<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, 5, 187-194 <lb/>187 <lb/>1570-159X/07 $50.00+.00 <lb/>©2007 Bentham Science Publishers Ltd. <lb/>Allosteric Modulators for mGlu Receptors <lb/>F. Gasparini * and W. Spooren <lb/>Novartis Institutes for BioMedical Research Basel, Neuroscience Research, WSJ-386.743, Postfach, CH-4002 Basel, Switzerland; F. <lb/>Hofmann-La Roche, CNS Research, Psychiatry Disease Area, Building 74-148, 4070 Basel, Switzerland <lb/>Abstract: The metabotropic glutamate receptor family comprises eight subtypes (mGlu1-8) of G-protein coupled receptors. mGlu recep-<lb/>tors have a large extracellular domain which acts as recognition domain for the natural agonist glutamate. In contrast to the ionotropic <lb/>glutamate receptors which mediate the fast excitatory neurotransmission, mGlu receptors have been shown to play a more modulatory <lb/>role and have been proposed as alternative targets for pharmacological interventions. The potential use of mGluRs as drug targets for <lb/>various nervous system pathologies such as anxiety, depression, schizophrenia, pain or Parkinson&apos;s disease has triggered an intense <lb/>search for subtype selective modulators and resulted in the identification of numerous novel pharmacological agents capable to modulate <lb/>the receptor activity through an interaction at an allosteric site located in the transmembrane domain. The present review presents the <lb/>most recent developments in the identification and the characterization of allosteric modulators for the mGlu receptors. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Since their identification in the mid eighties [56] and their sub-<lb/>sequent cloning [18,31] in the early nineties, the metabotropic glu-<lb/>tamate receptor (mGluR) family triggered an intensive search to-<lb/>ward the identification of pharmacological agents to determine the <lb/>role of the mGlu receptors in the nervous system physiology and <lb/>patho-physiology. To date eight of such receptors (mGlu1-8) have <lb/>been cloned and based on their amino-acids sequence, pharmacol-<lb/>ogy and second messenger coupling these receptors have been clus-<lb/>tered into three groups (I -III) [4]. mGlu receptors belong to the <lb/>family 3 GPCRs and as such have a large extracellular ligand rec-<lb/>ognition N-terminal domain and seven transmembrane-spanning <lb/>regions that are connected by three intra-cellular and three extracel-<lb/>lular loops with a number of conserved cysteine residues [16]. The <lb/>extracellular ligand recognition N-terminal domain has a so-called <lb/>bi-lobed structure (= Venus fly-trap function) that can adopt an <lb/>open or closed configuration in the absence or presence of an ago-<lb/>nist, respectively [41]. In addition, there are indications that in the <lb/>brain functional mGlu1 and mGlu5 receptors may predominantly <lb/>exist as homodimers [52]. Glutamate is the physiological agonist <lb/>for all mGlu receptors subtypes and as such the first selective <lb/>agents identified were glutamate analogs [54] and are acting at the <lb/>receptor by displacing Glutamate from its binding site located in the <lb/>N-terminal domain, the orthosteric site. As such those ligands are <lb/>named competitive agonists or antagonists. The structural analogy <lb/>to Glutamate, with the presence of a distal carboxylic acid to the <lb/>amino-acid functionality, strongly influence the properties of the <lb/>competitive ligands and limits considerably their capacity to cross <lb/>membranes by passive diffusion. As a consequence, these com-<lb/>pounds have a poor oral bioavailability, and do not readily cross the <lb/>blood-brain-barrier. A noticeable exception is illustrated by the <lb/>small molecular weight ligands, LY354740, LY379268 or <lb/>LY404039 [53] which display potent agonist activity at mGlu2/3 <lb/>receptors, are orally bioavailable, and enter the brain in preclinical <lb/>model [36,37] and have been developed throughout the clinic as <lb/>potential anti-panic agents [2]. <lb/>The difficulty to identify suitable glutamate analog with ade-<lb/>quate drug-like properties and subtype selectivity has been an im-<lb/>portant element that fostered the search for alternative structural <lb/>compound classes to inhibit or activate mGlu receptor function. <lb/>DISCOVERY <lb/>The identification of the allosteric modulators is intimately <lb/>linked with the development of in vitro assays allowing the charac-<lb/>terization of the functional activity of agents acting at the receptor. <lb/>For the Group I mGlu receptors, coupled to Gq type of G-proteins, <lb/>two cellular assays based on IP 3 turnover and measurements of <lb/>intracellular Ca 2+ concentration were developed (Fig. 1). <lb/></body>

			<front>*Address correspondence to this author at Novartis Institutes for BioMedi-<lb/>cal Research Basel, Neuroscience Research, WSJ-386.743, Postfach, CH-<lb/>4002 Basel, Switzerland; Tel: + 41 61 324 72 57; FAX: + 41 61 324 38 11; <lb/>E-mail: fabrizio.gasparini@novartis.com <lb/></front>

			<body>For the Group II and III mGlu receptors, which are coupled to <lb/>Gi type of G-proteins, functional assays involving GTP--35 S bind-<lb/>ing and determination of cAMP concentration changes were devel-<lb/>oped (Fig. 2). <lb/>The development of these functional assays and their adaptation <lb/>to a high throughput screening mode allowed the screening of large <lb/>chemical libraries and the identification of numerous ligands with <lb/>no structural analogies to the natural ligand Glutamate acting as <lb/>negative allosteric modulators (NAM) or as positive allosteric <lb/>modulators (PAM). <lb/>A number of excellent reviews describing in the mechanism of <lb/>action and the progresses in the allosteric modulator field have been <lb/>published [13,14,20,44,45,50,55]. Here, we would like to describe <lb/>the most recent developments in the identification and characteriza-<lb/>tion of allosteric ligands for the various mGluR subtypes. <lb/>GROUP I <lb/>mGluR1 NAM <lb/>CPCCOEt (1) was the first non glutamate antagonist described <lb/>for the mGlu1 receptor [1]. This agent has been a useful tool to <lb/>investigate the role of the mGluR1 subtype in vitro, however, its <lb/>limited potency (only low micromolar IC 50 ), its lack of bio-<lb/>availability and brain penetration did not allow a broad use in vivo. <lb/>Nevertheless, CPCCOEt was identified as non-competitive inhibitor <lb/>and allowed to unravel and characterize the allosteric binding site <lb/>located in the transmembrane domain [28]. A more potent com-<lb/>pound, BAY36-7620 (2) was subsequently described to interact at <lb/>the same allosteric binding site and to inhibit the receptor constitu-<lb/>tive activity [3]. The improved in vivo properties of BAY36-7620 <lb/>has allowed the detection of an early signal for analgesic and anti-<lb/>convulsant effect but also for an impaired acquisition of a spatial <lb/>memory task (Morris water maze) [9,58]. This effect on memory <lb/>was later confirmed with highly optimized compounds. However, <lb/>various issues including potency has limited an extensive charac-<lb/>terization using this compound for the use of exploring the potential <lb/>of mGlu1 receptor antagonists for the treatment of various CNS <lb/>disorders. The first described highly potent, selective and systemi-<lb/>cally active mGlu1 receptor antagonist is JNJ16259685 (3) [25]. <lb/>JNJ16259685 is a non competitive antagonist with IC 50 values of <lb/>3.2 and 1.2 nM in glutamate-induced calcium mobilization at rat <lb/>and human receptors, respectively. In addition, systemic application <lb/>of JNJ16259685 resulted in high receptor occupancy at low dosis. <lb/>Together these data provide evidence that JNJ16259685 is an excel-<lb/>lent tool to explore the potential of mGlu1 receptor antagonists as <lb/>therapeutics [25]. Steckler et al. [60] described anxiolytic-like <lb/>properties in punished licking behavior which appeared to have <lb/>synergistic effects with mGlu5 receptor antagonists. Nevertheless, <lb/>the effects seem different from those for mGlu5 receptor antago-<lb/>nists as prominent effects were only seen on conflict procedures but <lb/>not on task based spontaneous exploration. Effects were described <lb/>on locomotor activity as expected from the expression pattern in <lb/>cerebellar structures but following chronic application data suggest <lb/></body>

			<page>188 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 <lb/>Gasparini and Spooren <lb/></note>

			<body>tolerance to these motor disturbances. Subsequently, Steckler et al. <lb/>[61] described that JNJ16259685 impaired spatial acquisition proc-<lb/>esses, irrespective of spatial load, as well as spatial re-acquisition, <lb/>already at the lowest dose tested (0.63 mg/kg). Effects on spatial <lb/>retention performance were relatively mild in mice that had learned <lb/>to locate the position of the escape platform prior to treatment. <lb/>These data suggest that blockade of the mGlu1 receptor primarily <lb/>affects learning of new information, but leaves retention of spatial <lb/>information relatively unaffected. <lb/>Another potent and selective non-competitive mGlu1 antagonist <lb/>is A-841720 (4) [10]. At recombinant human and native rat <lb/>mGluR1 receptors, A-841720 inhibited agonist-induced calcium <lb/>mobilization, with IC 50 values of 10.7 and 1.0 nM, respectively, <lb/>while showing selectivity over other mGluR receptors. Intraperito-<lb/>neal injection of A-841720 potently reduced complete Freund&apos;s <lb/>adjuvant-induced inflammatory pain (ED 50 = 8 mg/kg) and mon-<lb/>oiodoacetate-induced joint pain (ED 50 = 15 mg/kg). A-841720 also <lb/>decreased mechanical allodynia observed in both the sciatic nerve <lb/>chronic constriction injury and L5-L6 spinal nerve ligation (SNL) <lb/>models of neuropathic pain (ED 50 = 10 and 9 mg/kg, respectively). <lb/>Electrophysiological studies demonstrated that systemic administra-<lb/>tion of A-841720 in SNL animals significantly reduced evoked <lb/>firing in spinal wide dynamic range neurons. Importantly, signifi-<lb/>cant motor side effects were observed at analgesic doses and A-<lb/>841720 also impaired cognitive function in the Y-maze and the <lb/>Water Maze tests with no therapeutic index. The analgesic effects <lb/>of a selective mGluR1 receptor antagonist are associated with mo-<lb/>tor and cognitive side effects. <lb/>Taken together, the lack of separation between efficacy and side <lb/>effects in pre-clinical models indicates that mGluR1 antagonism <lb/>may not provide an adequate therapeutic window for the develop-<lb/>ment of such antagonists as therapeutics in humans. <lb/>mGluR1 PAM <lb/>Knoflach et al. [23] were the first to describe two chemical <lb/>series, compounds 5, 6 and 7 (Fig. 3), capable to potently increase <lb/>agonist-mediated responses in cells expressing the rat mGlu1 recep-<lb/>tor and in rat brain tissues. All three compounds were shown to <lb/>enhance the binding affinity of agonists for the orthosteric site. In <lb/>cells recombinantely expressing high level of the receptor and in <lb/>which the receptor shows a significant level of constitutive activity, <lb/>all three compounds were found to elicit a response in the absence <lb/>of orthosteric agonist. No similar effect was seen in native systems. <lb/>From the mechanistically point of view these effects were explained <lb/>by an interaction of the compound with an active form of the recep-<lb/>tor and the stabilization thereof. Compounds 5 and 7, showed selec-<lb/>tivity over the rmGlu2, rmGlu4, rmGlu5, rmGlu8 and hGABA B <lb/>receptors whereas compound 6 displayed a weak activation of the <lb/>glutamate-induced activation at the rmGlu5 receptor. Interestingly, <lb/>when tested on the human mGlu1 receptor only compound 6 acted <lb/>as positive modulator, compounds 5 and 7 being devoid of activity. <lb/>Furthermore, using chimeric receptor constructs and site directed <lb/>mutagenesis, Knoflach et al. [23], could demonstrate that all three <lb/>compounds interact in the transmembrane domain in an overlapping <lb/>pocket compared to the mGluR1 NAMS. Recently, a series of <lb/>structurally different mGlu1 positive modulators obtained by <lb/>chemical derivatization of the mGluR5 PAM CDPPB (15, Fig. 3) <lb/>Fig. (1). Group I mGluRs signal transduction pathway. <lb/>Fig. (2). Group II and III mGluR signal transduction pathway. <lb/>[cAMP] determination <lb/>GTP-γ-35 S Binding <lb/>AC <lb/>= glutamate <lb/>β <lb/>γ <lb/>α i <lb/>GDP <lb/>GTP <lb/>GTP-γ-35 S <lb/>ATP <lb/>cAMP <lb/>[cAMP] determination <lb/>GTP-γ-35 S Binding <lb/>AC <lb/>= glutamate <lb/>β <lb/>γ <lb/>α i <lb/>GDP <lb/>GTP <lb/>GTP-γ-35 S <lb/>ATP <lb/>cAMP <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Allosteric Modulators for mGlu Receptors <lb/>Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 </note>

			<page>189 <lb/></page>

			<body>was described and characterized. In contrast to the compounds 5, 7 <lb/>and 8, the CDPPB series was shown to interact in the transmem-<lb/>brane domain with a different binding mode compared to the <lb/>mGluR1 allosteric negative modulators [8]. <lb/>So far, no in vivo activity has been reported on the effects of <lb/>mGlu1 receptor PAMs, but based on the negative effects of NAMs <lb/>on learning and memory [10,61] it can be hypothesized that en-<lb/>hancement of mGlu1 receptor activity through a selective PAM <lb/>could be beneficial to restore normal learning and memory proc-<lb/>esses. <lb/>mGluR5 NAM <lb/>2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-pyridine (MPEP), 8 is the proto-<lb/>typical allosteric mGlu5 receptor antagonist [12]. It is a potent, <lb/>selective and systemically active antagonist. At the human mGlu5a <lb/>receptor expressed in recombinant cells, MPEP completely inhibits <lb/>quisqualate-stimulated phosphoinositide (PI) hydrolysis with an <lb/>IC 50 value of 36 nM while having no agonist or antagonist activities <lb/>at other receptors up to 30 M. Schild&apos;s analysis indicated that <lb/>MPEP acts in a non-competitive manner. MPEP also inhibited to a <lb/>large extent constitutive receptor activity in cells transiently over-<lb/>expressing rat mGluR5, suggesting that MPEP may act as an in-<lb/>verse agonist [40]. <lb/>Using chimeras and single amino acid substitutions between <lb/>hmGluR1 and hmGluR5, binding of the mGluR5 radioligand [ 3 H]-<lb/>2-methyl-6-(3-methoxyphenyl)ethynyl pyridine (M-MPEP) it could <lb/>be determined that the amino acids Ala-810 (TMVII), Pro-655 and <lb/>Ser-658 (TMIII) of the mGlu5 receptor are necessary to mediate the <lb/>binding and the selectivity of the MPEP series of antagonists. Con-<lb/>versely, the introduction of these three amino-acids in the corre-<lb/>sponding reciprocal position of the hmGlu1 receptor led to a mutant <lb/>mGlu1 receptor capable to bind [ 3 H]-M-MPEP with low nanomolar <lb/>affinity [40]. Radioligand binding to these mutants was also inhib-<lb/>ited by 7-hydroxyiminocyclopropan [b]chromen-1a-carboxylic acid <lb/>ethyl ester (CPCCOEt), a structurally unrelated non-competitive <lb/>mGluR1 antagonist previously shown to interact within the TM <lb/>region of the mGlu1 receptor [28]. These results indicate that MPEP <lb/>and CPCCOEt bind to overlapping binding pockets in the TM re-<lb/>gion of group I mGluRs but interact with different non-conserved <lb/>residues. Several additional allosteric mGlu5 antagonists based on <lb/>the chemical structure of MPEP have been described and character-<lb/>ized, among those MTEP 9 a close derivative was also extensively <lb/>characterized [5,57]. <lb/>The identification of MPEP (2-methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-<lb/>pyridine allowed the exploration of the therapeutic potential of this <lb/>class of compounds. Subsequent behavior studies revealed that--<lb/>with the exception of benzodiazepines--mGlu5 receptor antagonists <lb/>exhibit the widest and most robust anxiolytic activity in preclinical <lb/>models seen to date [59]. <lb/>Fenobam <lb/>Fenobam [N-(3-chlorophenyl)-N&apos;-(4,5-dihydro-1-methyl-4-oxo-<lb/>1H-imidazole-2-yl)urea] (10) is an atypical anxiolytic agent, with <lb/>until recently an unknown molecular target, that has previously <lb/>been demonstrated both in rodents and human to exert robust anx-<lb/>iolytic-like activity. During a HTS screen at F. Hoffmann-La <lb/>Roche, Fenobam (McN-3377) was identified as a potent antagonist <lb/>at mGlu5 receptors [49]. Characterization revealed that Fenobam is <lb/>a selective and potent metabotropic glutamate mGlu5 receptor an-<lb/>tagonist acting at an allosteric modulatory site shared with 2-<lb/>methyl-6-phenylethynyl-pyridine (MPEP). Fenobam inhibited quis-<lb/>qualate-evoked intracellular calcium response mediated by human <lb/>mGlu5 receptor with IC 50 = 58 nM. It acted in a noncompetitive <lb/>manner, similar to MPEP and demonstrated inverse agonist proper-<lb/>ties, blocking 66% of the mGlu5 receptor basal activity (in an over <lb/>expressed cell line) with an IC 50 = 84 nM. [ 3 H]-Fenobam bound to <lb/>rat and human recombinant receptors with K d values of 54 and 31 <lb/>Fig. (3). mGluR1 allosteric modulators. <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>mGluR1 NAMs <lb/>mGluR1 PAM <lb/>1, CPCCOEt <lb/>2, BAY36-7620 <lb/>3, JNJ16259685 <lb/>(R199912) <lb/>4, A841720 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/></body>

			<page>190 </page>

			<note place="headnote">Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 <lb/>Gasparini and Spooren <lb/></note>

			<body>nM, respectively. MPEP inhibited [ 3 H]-fenobam binding to human <lb/>mGlu5 receptors with a Ki value of 6.7 nM, indicating a common <lb/>binding site shared by both allosteric antagonists. Fenobam exhibits <lb/>robust anxiolytic-like activity with efficacy comparable to MPEP in <lb/>the stress-induced hyperthermia model, Vogel conflict test, Geller-<lb/>Seifter conflict test, and conditioned emotional response with a <lb/>minimum effective dose of 10 to 30 mg/kg p.o. Furthermore, Feno-<lb/>bam is devoid of GABAergic activity, confirming previous reports <lb/>that Fenobam acts by a mechanism distinct from benzodiazepines. <lb/>The non-GABAergic activity of Fenobam, coupled with its robust <lb/>anxiolytic activity supports the potential of developing mGlu5 re-<lb/>ceptor antagonists with an improved therapeutic window over ben-<lb/>zodiazepines as novel anxiolytic agents. The confidence in mGlu5 <lb/>receptor antagonists as a treatment for anxiety is obviously strongly <lb/>supported by positive results in clinical trials with patients. There <lb/>are at least two positive trials that indicate that Fenobam is indeed <lb/>efficacious in man including a double blind placebo-controlled and <lb/>standardized (Diazepam) trial [42,43]. It was concluded from these <lb/>studies that Fenobam relieved symptoms of anxiety in broad spec-<lb/>trum psychoneurotic patients which may experience anxiety as <lb/>cognitive, dysphoric or motor autonomic. The anxiolytic activity is <lb/>differentiated from benzodiazepines and fenobam was safe and <lb/>induced less sedation and drowsiness. Clearly, these findings need <lb/>to be confirmed in upcoming clinical trials using highly optimized <lb/>mGlu5 receptor antagonists but provide great promise for future <lb/>studies. <lb/>mGluR5 PAM <lb/>In contrast to the high number of NAM for the mGlu5 receptor, <lb/>relatively few positive allosteric modulators have been described. <lb/>The first series of compounds is based on a benzaldazine core struc-<lb/>ture and the pharmacological activity is determined by the nature <lb/>and the position of the substituents [38]. In this series, DFB (3,3&apos;-<lb/>difluorobenzaldazine, 11, Fig. 5), acts as positive modulator and <lb/>induces a marked increase in glutamate potency (EC 50 ). Interest-<lb/>ingly, a change in the nature of the substituent with a replacement <lb/>of the two fluorine atoms by a methoxy group conferred an antago-<lb/>nistic activity to the resulting DMeOB (3,3&apos;-dimethoxyBenzaldazine, <lb/>12, Fig. 5) derivative. Another very subtle substitution change, <lb/>chlorine for the fluorine atoms, led to the identification of a ligand <lb/>with no functional activity at the receptor, DCB (3,3&apos;-dichloro-<lb/>benzaldazine, 13, Fig. 5). The DFB family of modulators is the first <lb/>to demonstrate the whole range of pharmacological activities from <lb/>activation to inactivation of the receptor as well as neutral/silent <lb/>receptor ligands. All active derivatives of this series are interacting <lb/>in the transmembrane domain in a similar but not identical binding <lb/>site to the mGluR5 NAMs of the MPEP structural family. Shortly <lb/>after, two novel, structurally unrelated series illustrated by the pro-<lb/>totypic compounds CPPHA (14) and CDPPB (15) were described <lb/>by the same research group [27,39]. Both compounds showed a <lb/>potent increase of agonist mediated receptor activation for both <lb/>human and rat receptors with no cross reactivity at the other mGluR <lb/>subtypes nor at other CNS receptors. No activation of the receptor <lb/>was seen when DFB or CPPHA were used in the absence of orthos-<lb/>teric agonist [39] whereas CDPPB alone was capable to induce <lb/>a receptor activation [22]. All three compounds had no effect on <lb/>the binding of the orthosteric ligand [ 3 H]-quisqualate [22,39] <lb/>whereas only DFB and CDPPB did inhibit the binding of [ 3 H]-<lb/>methoxy-PEP-y [5] a derivative of the allosteric negative modulator <lb/>MPEP. Despite intense medicinal chemistry efforts, neither the <lb/>DFB nor CPPHA series did not deliver suitable molecules for in <lb/>vivo evaluation in preclinical models. In contrast, derivatization of <lb/>the CDPPB series not only allowed the identification more potent <lb/>derivatives but also the identification of mGluR1 positive allosteric <lb/>modulators [8]. <lb/>Fig. (4). mGluR5 allosteric modulators. <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>OH <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>CN <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>8, MPEP <lb/>9, MPEP <lb/>10, Fenobam <lb/>mGluR5 NAMs <lb/>mGluR5 PAMs <lb/>11, DFB <lb/>14, CPPHA <lb/>15, CDPPB <lb/>12, DMeOB <lb/>13, DCB <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Allosteric Modulators for mGlu Receptors <lb/>Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 </note>

			<page>191 <lb/></page>

			<body>In vivo, CDPPB was evaluated in two behavioral models sensi-<lb/>tive to antipsychotic: the amphetamine-induced locomotor activity <lb/>and the amphetamine-induced disruption of prepulse inhibition <lb/>(PPI) in rat. In both models, CDPPB showed a dose dependent <lb/>beneficial effect without noticeable side-effects [22]. These results <lb/>demonstrated for the first time the in vivo activity of a selective <lb/>mGluR5 allosteric positive modulator and suggested a potential use <lb/>of these type of modulator as anti-psychotics. <lb/>GROUP II <lb/>mGluR2 NAM <lb/>Since the publication of two series of mGluR2 NAMs by Kol-<lb/>czewski et al. [24] and Wichmann et al. [63] no further develop-<lb/>ment nor structurally novel mGluR2 NAMs have been described to <lb/>date. These two series illustrated by the compounds 16 and 17 (Fig. <lb/>4) were shown to inhibit agonist stimulated GTP--[ 35 S] binding on <lb/>a rat mGluR2 transfected cell membranes with sub-micromolar <lb/>IC 50 . Both lead compounds were also shown to be selective over <lb/>mGluR1, mGluR4, mGluR5 and ionotropic GluRs but no data was <lb/>published for the selectivity over the mGluR3 or other CNS recep-<lb/>tors. Based on the effects achieved with orthosteric antagonists, it <lb/>could be speculated that mGluR2 NAMs could improve cognitive <lb/>and or memory disturbances [17]. <lb/>mGluR2 PAM <lb/>Among all mGlu receptor subtypes, the activation of the Group <lb/>II subtypes is by far the best studied thanks to the identification and <lb/>development by Eli Lilly of the orthosteric agonist LY354740 <lb/>[36,37]. This compound and its prodrug derivative (LY544344) <lb/>have been extensively characterized in preclinical model for anxiety <lb/>related disorders and subsequently developed in the clinic where <lb/>their use demonstrate the usefulness of activation of Group II recep-<lb/>tors for the treatment of anxiety related disorders [26]. This proof of <lb/>principle with LY354740 also confirms that activation of the <lb/>mGluR2,3 subtypes display therapeutic activity at doses which are <lb/>devoid of the side effects typically observed with agents interacting <lb/>with the ionotropic glutamate receptors. <lb/>The search for orthosteric ligands derived from the original <lb/>structure, LY354740, with similar pharmacological and drug-<lb/>like properties proved to be extremely difficult and prompted the <lb/>search for alternative structures. As for the Group I, the use of func-<lb/>tional assays combined with the screening of chemical libraries <lb/>allowed the identification of the first series of positive allosteric <lb/>modulators: the sulfonamide derivatives such as LY487379 (18) <lb/>[19]. LY487379 and analog compounds from the same chemical <lb/>class were shown to act as allosteric modulators with an activation <lb/>of the receptor only in the presence of an orthosteric agonist and no <lb/>displacement of the orthosteric antagonist LY341495. In contrast to <lb/>all known orthosteric agonists, LY487379 and its derivatives are <lb/>selective for the mGluR2 over the other seven mGluR subtypes <lb/>including the mGluR3 and over a binding battery of CNS relevant <lb/>receptor. In vivo, LY487379 or its derivatives demonstrated effi-<lb/>cacy in animal models for anxiety (Fear potentiated startle; Stress <lb/>induced hyperthermia) or for anti-psychotic activity (PCP induced <lb/>locomotor activity) [21]. A second series of compound was de-<lb/>scribed shortly after by a research group at Merck and exemplified <lb/>by the phenyl-tetrazolyl acetophenone derivative 19 (Fig. 5) <lb/>[7,46,47,48]. In vitro, this series of compounds showed a similar <lb/>profile to the LY487379 and in vivo the use of a more potent and <lb/>brain penetrable compound, BINA (20), confirmed the potential <lb/>anti-psychotic effects in animal models [11,15,48,51]. <lb/>Fig. (5). mGluR2 allosteric modulators. <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Cl <lb/>Cl <lb/>O <lb/>NMe 2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>CF 3 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>HN N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>HO <lb/>16 <lb/>mGluR2 NAMs <lb/>17 <lb/>mGluR2 PAMs <lb/>LY487379, 18 <lb/>19 <lb/>20, BINA <lb/></body>

			<page>192 </page>
			<note place="headnote">Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 <lb/>Gasparini and Spooren <lb/></note>

			<body>Taken together these results that mGluR2 selective modulators <lb/>constitute a potential alternative for a pharmacotherapeutic inter-<lb/>vention to the orthosteric non-selective mGluR2,-3 agonists. <lb/>GROUP III <lb/>mGluR4, 6, 7, 8 NAMs <lb/>Compared to the Group I and II mGluR, the pharmacology of <lb/>the Group III is the least developed with a lack of subtype selective <lb/>negative modulators. To our knowledge, only one series of com-<lb/>pounds claimed in a patent (WO02102807; EP1408042 A1) has <lb/>been described. Within this series compound 23 is described as a <lb/>selective allosteric negative modulator of the mGluR7 with an IC 50 <lb/>of 7 nM. <lb/>mGluR4 PAM <lb/>For the mGlu4 receptor, two compounds have been identified, <lb/>PHCCC, 21 [29] and SIB1893, 22 [33] both originally discovered <lb/>as antagonist for the mGlu1 and mGlu5 receptors, respectively. <lb/>MPEP, 8 was also identified as potentiator of the mGluR4 but at <lb/>very high concentrations (50-100 m) which are several order of <lb/>magnitude higher than the effective concentrations needed to inhibit <lb/>the mGlu5 receptor. <lb/>In rat brain slices, using CPCCC Valenti et al. [62] could dem-<lb/>onstrate that the mGlu4 receptor plays a key role in the Group III <lb/>mGluR modulation of the excitatory transmission in the substantia <lb/>nigra pars compacta (SNc), a key region involved in the nigral neu-<lb/>rodegeneration and the resulting movement disorders in Parkinson&apos;s <lb/>Disease. Unfortunately, the limiting drug-like properties of PHCCC <lb/>and the lack of more potent and selective mGluR4 PAM prevent the <lb/>validation in vivo in animal model of this putative use of mGluR4 <lb/>positive modulators. Additional potential pharmacotherapeutic uses <lb/>of mGluR4 modulators have been recently reviewed by Marino et <lb/>al. [30]. <lb/>mGluR7 PAM <lb/>As for the other members of the Group III receptors the lack of <lb/>suitable selective pharmacological tools slowed considerably the <lb/>study of the mGlu7 receptor. However, the generation and the char-<lb/>acterization of the mGluR7 knock-out mice indicated that amygdala <lb/>dependent functions such as conditioned fear, aversive responses <lb/>and responses to anxiety and stress related responses are altered <lb/>[6,32,35]. <lb/>The recent identification of a selective allosteric agonist, <lb/>AMN082 (24, Fig. 6) allowed the confirmation of the data obtained <lb/>with the mGluR7 null mice [34]. In vitro, AMN082 was shown to <lb/>potently activate the recombinantly expressed human mGlu7 recep-<lb/>tor with an EC 50 of 64 nM in the absence of orthosteric agonist. In <lb/>addition, AMN082 increases the orthosteric agonist (Glu, L-AP4) <lb/>induced receptor activation in analogy to the positive modulators at <lb/>the other mGluR subtypes. In vivo, AMN082 was shown to be <lb/>orally bioavailable, to penetrate into the brain and to modulate the <lb/>level of stress hormones (cortisol and ACTH) in wild type animal <lb/>but not in the mGluR7 ko mouse. Taken together this data demon-<lb/>strate that mGluR7 modulation could a valuable mechanism for the <lb/>pharmacotherapy of stress-related psychiatric disorders. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS/OUTLOOK <lb/>The ubiquitous distribution of glutamate in the brain sets off the <lb/>critical role of glutamate receptors in most major functions of the <lb/>CNS. Next to the ionotropic glutamate-gated ion channels, me-<lb/>tabotropic glutamate receptors modulate neuronal excitability, syn-<lb/>aptic transmission, and have various metabolic functions. Albeit <lb/>small, the Family III or Class C of G-protein-coupled receptors <lb/>have become the focal point for the discovery of new and exciting <lb/>modulators of glutamatergic neurotransmission. Exciting medicinal <lb/>chemistry that allowed the interaction of small molecules with re-<lb/>ceptors through soft touched allosteric modulation that modify <lb/>transmembrane signaling rather than compete for binding with the <lb/>natural agonist at orthosteric sites. Indeed, the mGlu receptors are <lb/>illustrative in the discovery of both positive and/or negative allos-<lb/>teric modulators that display a unique degree of subtype selectivity <lb/>within the highly conserved mGlu family of receptors. The combi-<lb/>nation of these pharmacological tools, in conjunction with genetic <lb/>approaches, has led to major advances in our understanding of the <lb/>roles of mGlu receptors in regulating of CNS function and animal <lb/>behavior. From cloning to the identification multiple receptors, sub-<lb/>type selective allosteric modulators and testing in double blind pla-<lb/>cebo controlled trials in less than 15 years is a remarkable story. <lb/>These developments provide us with the unique opportunity for <lb/>better treatments in a wide variety of neurological and psychiatric <lb/>disorders that include complicated disease states such as depression, <lb/>anxiety disorders, and schizophrenia. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] <lb/>Annoura, H., Fukunaga, A., Uesugi, M., Tatsuoka, T., Horikawa, Y. (1996) <lb/>A novel classof antagonists for metabotropic glutamate receptors, 7-<lb/>(hydroxyimino)cyclopropachromen-1a-carboxylates. Bioorg. Med. Chem. <lb/>Lett., 6, 763-766. <lb/>[2] <lb/>Bergink, V., Westenberg, H.G. (2005) Metabotropic glutamate II receptor <lb/>agonists in panic disorder: a double blind clinical trial with LY354740. Int. <lb/>Clin. Psychopharmacol., 20, 291-3. <lb/>[3] <lb/>Carroll, F.Y., Stolle, A., Beart, P.M., Voerste, A., Brabet, I., Mauler, F., Joly, <lb/>C., Antonicek, H., Bockaert, J., Muller, T., Pin, J.P., Prezeau, L. (2001) <lb/>BAY36-7620: a potent non-competitive mGlu1 receptor antagonist with in-<lb/>verse agonist activity. Mol. Pharmacol., 59, 965-73. <lb/>[4] <lb/>Conn, P.J., Pin, J.P. (1997). Pharmacology and functions of metabotropic <lb/>glutamatereceptors. Ann. Rev. Pharmacol. Toxicol., 37, 205-237. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Fig. (6). Group III allosteric modulators. <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>OH <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>22, SIB1893 <lb/>mGluR4 PAMs <lb/>21, PHCCC <lb/>mGluR7 NAM <lb/>23 <lb/>mGluR7 PAM <lb/>24, AMN082 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Allosteric Modulators for mGlu Receptors <lb/>Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 </note>

			<page>193 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[5] <lb/>Cosford, N.D., Tehrani, L., Roppe, J., Schweiger, E., Smith, N.D., Anderson, <lb/>J., Bristow, L., Brodkin, J., Jiang, X., McDonald, I., Rao, S., Washburn, M., <lb/>Varney, M.A. (2003) 3-[(2-Methyl-1,3-thiazol-4-yl)ethynyl]-pyridine: a po-<lb/>tent and highly selective metabotropic glutamate subtype 5 receptor antago-<lb/>nist with anxiolytic activity. J. Med. Chem., 46, 204-6. <lb/>[6] <lb/>Cryan, J.F., Kelly, P.H., Neijt, H.C., Sansig, G., Flor, P.J., van Der Putten, H. <lb/>(2003) Antidepressant and anxiolytic-like effects in mice lacking the group <lb/>III metabotropic glutamate receptor mGluR7. Eur. J. Neurosci., 17, 2409-17. <lb/>[7] <lb/>Cube, R.V., Vernier, J.M., Hutchinson, J.H., Gardner, M.F., James, J.K., <lb/>Rowe, B.A., Schaffhauser, H., Daggett, L., Pinkerton, A.B. (2005) 3-(2-<lb/>Ethoxy-4-{4-[3-hydroxy-2-methyl-4-(3-methylbutanoyl)phenoxy]butoxy} <lb/>phenyl)propanoic acid: a brain penetrant allosteric potentiator at the me-<lb/>tabotropic glutamate receptor 2 (mGluR2). Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 15, <lb/>2389-93. <lb/>[8] <lb/>de Paulis, T., Hemstapat, K., Chen, Y., Zhang, Y., Saleh, S., Alagille, D., <lb/>Baldwin, R.M., Tamagnan, G.D., Conn, P.J. (2006) Substituent effects of N-<lb/>(1,3-diphenyl-1H-pyrazol-5-yl)benzamides on positive allosteric modulation <lb/>of the metabotropic glutamate-5 receptor in rat cortical astrocytes. J. Med. <lb/>Chem., 49, 3332-44. <lb/>[9] <lb/>De Vry, J., Horvath, E., Schreiber, R. (2001) Neuroprotective and behavioral <lb/>effects of the selective metabotropic glutamate mGlu(1) receptor antagonist <lb/>BAY 36-7620. Eur. J. Pharmacol., 428, 203-14. <lb/>[10] <lb/>El-Kouhen, O.; Lehto, S.G., Pan, J.B., Chang, R., Baker, S.J., Zhong, C., <lb/>Hollingsworth, P.R., Mikusa, J. P., Cronin, E.A., Chu, K.L., McGaraughty, <lb/>S.P., Uchic, M.E., Miller, L.N., Rodell, N.M., Patel, M., Bhatia, P., Mezler, <lb/>M., Kolasa, T., Zheng, G.Z., Fox, G.B., Stewart, A.O., Decker, M.W., More-<lb/>land, R.B., Brioni, J.D., Honore, P. (2006) Blockade of mGluR1 receptor re-<lb/>sults in analgesia and disruption of motor and cognitive performances: ef-<lb/>fects of A-841720, a novel non-competitive mGluR1 receptor antagonist. Br. <lb/>J. Pharmacol., 149, 761-774. <lb/>[11] <lb/>Galici, R., Jones, C.K., Hemstapat, K., Nong, Y., Echemendia, N.G., Wil-<lb/>liams, L.C., de Paulis, T., Conn, P.J. (2006) Biphenyl-indanone A, a positive <lb/>allosteric modulator of the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 2, has <lb/>antipsychotic-and anxiolytic-like effects in mice. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther., <lb/>318, 173-85. <lb/>[12] <lb/>Gasparini, F., Lingenhohl, K., Stoehr, N., Flor, P.J., Heinrich, M., Vranesic, <lb/>I., Biollaz, M., Allgeier, H., Heckendorn, R., Urwyler, S., Varney, M.A., <lb/>Johnson, E.C., Hess, S.D., Rao, S.P., Sacaan, A.I., Santori, E.M., Velicelebi, <lb/>G., Kuhn, R. (1999) 2-Methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)-pyridine (MPEP), a potent, <lb/>selective and systemically active mGlu5 receptor antagonist. Neuropharma-<lb/>cology, 38, 1493-503. <lb/>[13] <lb/>Goudet, C., Gaven, F., Kniazeff, J., Vol, C., Liu, J., Cohen-Gonsaud, M., <lb/>Acher, F., Prezeau, L., Pin, J.P. (2004) Heptahelical domain of metabotropic <lb/>glutamate receptor 5 behaves like rhodopsin-like receptors. Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. USA, 101, 378-83. <lb/>[14] <lb/>Goudet, C., Kniazeff, J., Hlavackova, V., Malhaire, F., Maurel, D., Acher, F., <lb/>Blahos, J., Prezeau, L., Pin, J.P. (2005) Asymmetric functioning of dimeric <lb/>metabotropic glutamate receptors disclosed by positive allosteric modulators. <lb/>J. Biol. Chem., 280, 24380-5. <lb/>[15] <lb/>Govek, S.P., Bonnefous, C., Hutchinson, J.H., Kamenecka, T., McQuiston, <lb/>J., Pracitto, R., Zhao, L.X., Gardner, M.F., James, J.K., Daggett, L.P., Rowe, <lb/>B.A., Schaffhauser, H., Bristow, L.J., Campbell, U.C., Rodriguez, D.E., <lb/>Vernier, J.M. (2005) Benzazoles as allosteric potentiators of metabotropic <lb/>glutamate receptor 2 (mGluR2): efficacy in an animal model for schizophre-<lb/>nia. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 15, 4068-72. <lb/>[16] <lb/>Hermans, E., Challiss, R.A.J. (2001) Structural, signalling and regulatory <lb/>properties of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors: prototypic family C <lb/>G-protein-coupled receptors. Biochem. J., 359, 465-484. <lb/>[17] <lb/>Higgins, G.A., Ballard, T.M., Kew, J.N., Richards, J.G., Kemp, J.A., Adam, <lb/>G., Woltering, T., Nakanishi, S., Mutel, V. (2004) Pharmacological manipu-<lb/>lation of mGlu2 receptors influences cognitive performance in the rodent. <lb/>Neuropharmacology, 46, 907-17. <lb/>[18] <lb/>Houamed, K.M., Kijper, J.L., Gilbert, T.L., Haldeman, B.A., Mulvihill, E.R., <lb/>Almers, W., Hagen, F.S. (1991). Cloning, expression and gene structure of a <lb/>G protein-coupled glutamate receptor from rat brain. Science, 252, 1318-<lb/>1321. <lb/>[19] <lb/>Johnson, M.P., Baez, M., Jagdmann, G.E. Jr., Britton, T.C., Large, T.H., <lb/>Callagaro, D.O., Tizzano, J.P., Monn, J.A., Schoepp, D.D. (2003) Discovery <lb/>of allosteric potentiators for the metabotropic glutamate 2 receptor: synthesis <lb/>and subtype selectivity of N-(4-(2-methoxyphenoxy)phenyl)-N-(2,2,2-<lb/>trifluoroethylsulfonyl)pyrid-3-ylmethylamine. J. Med. Chem., 46, 3189-92. <lb/>[20] <lb/>Johnson, M.P., Nisenbaum, E.S. (2004) Large TH, Emkey R, Baez M, King-<lb/>ston AE. Allosteric modulators of metabotropic glutamate receptors: lessons <lb/>learnt from mGlu1, mGlu2 and mGlu5 potentiators and antagonists. Bio-<lb/>chem. Soc. Trans., 32, 881-7. <lb/>[21] <lb/>Johnson, M.P., Barda, D., Britton, T.C., Emkey, R., Hornback, W.J., <lb/>Jagdmann, G.E., McKinzie, D.L., Nisenbaum, E.S., Tizzano, J.P., Schoepp, <lb/>D.D. (2005) Metabotropic glutamate 2 receptor potentiators: receptor modu-<lb/>lation, frequency-dependent synaptic activity, and efficacy in preclinical <lb/>anxiety and psychosis model(s). Psychopharmacology, 179, 271-83. <lb/>[22] <lb/>Kinney, G.G., O&apos;Brien, J.A., Lemaire, W., Burno, M., Bickel, D.J., Clements, <lb/>M.K., Chen, T.B., Wisnoski, D.D., Lindsley, C.W., Tiller, P.R., Smith, S., <lb/>Jacobson, M.A., Sur, C., Duggan, M.E., Pettibone, D.J., Conn, P.J., Wil-<lb/>liams, D.L. Jr. (2005) A novel selective positive allosteric modulator of me-<lb/>tabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5 has in vivo activity and antipsy-<lb/>chotic-like effects in rat behavioral models. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther., 313, <lb/>199-206. <lb/>[23] <lb/>Knoflach, F., Mutel, V., Jolidon, S., Kew, J.N., Malherbe, P., Vieira, E., <lb/>Wichmann, J., Kemp, J.A. (2001) Positive allosteric modulators of me-<lb/>tabotropic glutamate 1 receptor: characterization, mechanism of action, and <lb/>binding site. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 98, 13402-7. <lb/>[24] <lb/>Kolczewski, S., Adam, G., Stadler, H., Mutel, V., Wichmann, J., Woltering, <lb/>T. (1999) Synthesis of heterocyclic enol ethers and their use as group 2 me-<lb/>tabotropic glutamate receptor antagonists. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 9, 2173-<lb/>6. <lb/>[25] <lb/>Lavreysen, H., Wouters, R., Bischoff, F., Nobrega Pereira, S., Langlois, X., <lb/>Blokland, S., Somers, M., Dillen, L., Lesage, A.S. J. (2004) JNJ16259685, a <lb/>highly potent, selective and systemically active mGlu1 receptor antagonist. <lb/>Neuropharmacology, 47, 961-972. <lb/>[26] <lb/>Levine, L., Gaydos, B., Sheehan, D., Goddard, A., Feighner, J., Potter, W., <lb/>Schoepp, D. (2002) The mGlu2/3 receptor agonist, LY354740, reduces panic <lb/>anxiety induced by a CO2 challenge in patients diagnosed with panic disor-<lb/>der. Neuropharmacology, 43, 294-295. <lb/>[27] <lb/>Lindsley, C.W., Wisnoski, D.D., Leister, W.H., O&apos;brien, J.A., Lemaire, W., <lb/>Williams, D.L. Jr., Burno, M., Sur, C., Kinney, G.G., Pettibone, D.J., Tiller, <lb/>P.R., Smith, S., Duggan, M.E., Hartman, G.D., Conn, P.J., Huff, J.R. (2004) <lb/>Discovery of positive allosteric modulators for the metabotropic glutamate <lb/>receptor subtype 5 from a series of N-(1,3-diphenyl-1H-pyrazol-5-<lb/>yl)benzamides that potentiate receptor function in vivo. J. Med. Chem., 47, <lb/>5825-8. <lb/>[28] <lb/>Litschig, S., Gasparini, F., Rueegg, D., Stoehr, N., Flor, P.J., Vranesic, I., <lb/>Prezeau, L., Pin. J.P., Thomsen, C., Kuhn, R. (1999) CPCCOEt, a noncom-<lb/>petitive metabotropic glutamate receptor 1 antagonist, inhibits receptor sig-<lb/>naling without affecting glutamate binding. Mol. Pharmacol., 55, 453-61. <lb/>[29] <lb/>Maj, M., Bruno, V., Dragic, Z., Yamamoto, R., Battaglia, G., Inderbitzin, <lb/>W., Stoehr, N., Stein, T., Gasparini, F., Vranesic, I., Kuhn, R., Nicoletti, F., <lb/>Flor, P.J. (2003) (-)-PHCCC, a positive allosteric modulator of mGluR4: <lb/>characterization, mechanism of action, and neuroprotection. Neuropharma-<lb/>cology, 45, 895-906. <lb/>[30] <lb/>Marino, M.J., Hess, J.F., Liverton, N. (2005) Targeting the metabotropic <lb/>glutamate receptor mGluR4 for the treatment of diseases of the central nerv-<lb/>ous system. Curr. Top. Med. Chem., 5, 885-95. <lb/>[31] <lb/>Masu, M., Tanabe, Y., Tsuchida, K., Shigemototo, R., Nakanishi, S. (1991). <lb/>Sequence and expression of a metabotropic glutamate receptor. Nature, 349, <lb/>760-765. <lb/>[32] <lb/>Masugi, M., Yokoi, M., Shigemoto, R., Muguruma, K., Watanabe, Y., San-<lb/>sig, G., van der Putten, H., Nakanishi, S. (1999) Metabotropic glutamate re-<lb/>ceptor subtype 7 ablation causes deficit in fear response and conditioned <lb/>taste aversion. J. Neurosci., 19, 955-63. <lb/>[33] <lb/>Mathiesen, J.M., Svendsen, N., Brauner-Osborne, H., Thomsen, C., Ramirez, <lb/>M.T. (2003) Positive allosteric modulation of the human metabotropic glu-<lb/>tamate receptor 4 (hmGluR4) by SIB-1893 and MPEP. Br. J. Pharmacol., <lb/>138, 1026-30. <lb/>[34] <lb/>Mitsukawa, K., Yamamoto, R., Ofner, S., Nozulak, J., Pescott, O., Lukic, S., <lb/>Stoehr, N., Mombereau, C., Kuhn, R., McAllister, K.H., van der Putten, H., <lb/>Cryan, J.F., Flor, P.J. (2005) A selective metabotropic glutamate receptor 7 <lb/>agonist: activation of receptor signaling via an allosteric site modulates stress <lb/>parameters in vivo. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA, 102, 18712-7. <lb/>[35] <lb/>Mitsukawa, K., Mombereau, C., Lotscher, E., Uzunov, D.P., van der Putten, <lb/>H., Flor, P.J., Cryan, J.F. (2006) Metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 7 <lb/>ablation causes dysregulation of the HPA axis and increases hippocampal <lb/>BDNF protein levels: implications for stress-related psychiatric disorders. <lb/>Neuropsychopharmacology, 31, 1112-22. <lb/>[36] <lb/>Monn, J.A., Valli, M.J., Massey, S.M., Wright, R.A., Salhoff, C.R., Johnson, <lb/>B.G., Howe, T., Alt, C.A., Rhodes, G.A., Robey, R.L., Griffey, K.R., Tiz-<lb/>zano, J.P., Kallman, M.J., Helton, D.R., Schoepp, D.D. (1997) Design, syn-<lb/>thesis, and pharmacological characterization of (+)-2-aminobicyclo[3.1.0] <lb/>hexane-2,6-dicarboxylic acid (LY354740): A potent, selective, and orally ac-<lb/>tive group 2 metabotropic glutamate receptor agonist possessing anticonvul-<lb/>sant and anxiolytic properties. J. Med. Chem., 40, 528-537. <lb/>[37] <lb/>Monn, J.A., Valli, M.J., Massey, S.M., Hansen, M.M., Kress, T.J., Wepsiec, <lb/>J.P., Harkness, A.R., Grutsch, J.L. Jr., Wright, R.A., Johnson, B.G., Andis, <lb/>S.L., Kingston, A., Tomlinson, R., Lewis, R., Griffey, K.R., Tizzano, J.P., <lb/>Schoepp, D.D. (1999) Synthesis, pharmacological characterization, and mo-<lb/>lecular modeling of heterobicyclic amino acids related to (+)-2-<lb/>aminobicyclo[3.1.0] hexane-2,6-dicarboxylic acid (LY354740): identifica-<lb/>tion of two new potent, selective, and systemically active agonists for group <lb/>II metabotropic glutamate receptors. J. Med. Chem., 42, 1027-40. <lb/>[38] <lb/>O&apos;Brien, J.A., Lemaire, W., Chen, T.B., Chang, R.S., Jacobson, M.A., Ha, <lb/>S.N., Lindsley, C.W., Schaffhauser, H.J., Sur, C., Pettibone, D.J., Conn, P.J., <lb/>Williams, D.L. Jr. (2003) A family of highly selective allosteric modulators <lb/>of the metabotropic glutamate receptor subtype 5. Mol. Pharmacol., 64, 731-<lb/>40. <lb/>[39] <lb/>O&apos;Brien, J.A., Lemaire, W., Wittmann, M., Jacobson, M.A., Ha, S.N., Wis-<lb/>noski, D.D., Lindsley, C.W., Schaffhauser, H.J., Rowe, B., Sur, C., Duggan, <lb/>M.E., Pettibone, D.J., Conn, P.J., Williams, D.L. Jr. (2004) A novel selective <lb/>allosteric modulator potentiates the activity of native metabotropic glutamate <lb/>receptor subtype 5 in rat forebrain. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther., 309, 568-77. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>194 </page>
			<note place="headnote">Current Neuropharmacology, 2007, Vol. 5, No. 3 <lb/>Gasparini and Spooren <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[40] <lb/>Pagano, A., Ruegg, D., Litschig, S., Stoehr, N., Stierlin, C., Heinrich, M., <lb/>Floersheim, P., Prezeau, L., Carroll, F., Pin, J.P., Cambria, A., Vranesic, I., <lb/>Flor, P.J., Gasparini, F., Kuhn, R. (2000) The non-competitive antagonists 2-<lb/>methyl-6-(phenylethynyl)pyridine and 7-hydroxyiminocyclopropan[b]chro-<lb/>men-1a-carboxylic acid ethyl ester interact with overlapping binding pockets <lb/>in the transmembrane region of group I metabotropic glutamate receptors. J. <lb/>Biol. Chem., 275, 33750-8. <lb/>[41] <lb/>Parmentier, M.L., Prezeau, L., Bockaert, J., Pin, J.P. (2002) A model for the <lb/>functioning of family 3 GPCRs. Trends Pharmacol. Sci., 23, 268-74. <lb/>[42] <lb/>Pecknold, J.C., McClure, D.J., Appeltauer, L. (1980) Fenobam in anxious <lb/>out-patients. Curr. Ther. Res., 27, 119-123. <lb/>[43] <lb/>Pecknold, J.C., McClure, D.J., Appeltauer, L., Wrzesinski, L., Allan, T. <lb/>(1982) nt of anxiety using fenobam (a nonbenzodiazepine) in a double-blind <lb/>standard (diazepam) placebo-controlled study. J Clin. Psychopharmacol., 2, <lb/>9-33. <lb/>[44] <lb/>Pin, J.P., Galvez, T., Prezeau, L. (2003) Evolution, structure, and activation <lb/>mechanism of family 3/C G-protein-coupled receptors. Pharmacol. Ther., <lb/>98, 325-54. <lb/>[45] <lb/>Pin, J.P., Kniazeff, J., Liu, J., Binet, V., Goudet, C., Rondard, P., Prezeau, L. <lb/>(2005) Allosteric functioning of dimeric class C G-protein-coupled receptors. <lb/>FEBS J., 272, 2947-55. <lb/>[46] <lb/>Pinkerton, A.B., Cube, R.V., Hutchinson, J.H., Rowe, B.A., Schaffhauser, <lb/>H., Zhao, X., Daggett, L.P., Vernier, J.M. (2004) Allosteric potentiators of <lb/>the metabotropic glutamate receptor 2 (mGlu2). Part 1: Identification and <lb/>synthesis of phenyl-tetrazolyl acetophenones. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 14, <lb/>5329-32. <lb/>[47] <lb/>Pinkerton, A.B., Cube, R.V., Hutchinson, J.H., James, J.K., Gardner, M.F., <lb/>Schaffhauser, H., Rowe, B.A., Daggett, L.P., Vernier, J.M. (2004) Allosteric <lb/>potentiators of the metabotropic glutamate receptor 2 (mGlu2). Part 2: 4-<lb/>thiopyridyl acetophenones as non-tetrazole containing mGlu2 receptor poten-<lb/>tiators. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 14, 5867-72. <lb/>[48] <lb/>Pinkerton, A.B., Cube, R.V., Hutchinson, J.H., James, J.K., Gardner, M.F., <lb/>Rowe, B.A., Schaffhauser, H., Rodriguez, D.E., Campbell, U.C., Daggett, <lb/>L.P., Vernier, J.M. (2005) Allosteric potentiators of the metabotropic gluta-<lb/>mate receptor 2 (mGlu2). Part 3: Identification and biological activity of in-<lb/>danone containing mGlu2 receptor potentiators. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., <lb/>15, 1565-71. <lb/>[49] <lb/>Porter, R.H., Jaeschke, G., Spooren, W., Ballard, T.M., Buttelmann, B., <lb/>Kolczewski, S., Peters, J.U., Prinssen, E., Wichmann, J., Vieira, E., Muhle-<lb/>mann, A., Gatti, S., Mutel, V., Malherbe, P. (2005) Fenobam: a clinically <lb/>validated nonbenzodiazepine anxiolytic is a potent, selective, and noncom-<lb/>petitive mGlu5 receptor antagonist with inverse agonist activity. J. Pharma-<lb/>col. Exp. Ther., 315, 711-21. <lb/>[50] <lb/>Ritzen, A., Mathiesen, J.M., Thomsen, C. (2005) Molecular pharmacology <lb/>and therapeutic prospects of metabotropic glutamate receptor allosteric <lb/>modulators. Basic Clin. Pharmacol. Toxicol., 97, 202-13. <lb/>[51] <lb/>Rodriguez, D., Bonnefous, C., Kamenecka, T., Vernier, J.M., Bristow, L., <lb/>Campbell, U. (2004) Attenuation of ketamine-induced hyperactivity re-<lb/>sponses in rats following administration of a novel metabotropic glutamate <lb/>receptor 2 selective positive modulator [abstract], in Proceedings of the An-<lb/>nual Meeting of the Society for Neuroscience. Abstract number 798.8, Dallas, <lb/>TX. Society for Neuroscience, Washington, DC. <lb/>[52] <lb/>Romano, C., Yang, W.L., O&apos;Malley, K.L. (1996) Metabotropic glutamate <lb/>receptor 5 is a disulfide-linked dimer. J. Biol. Chem., 271, 28612-28616. <lb/>[53] <lb/>Rorick-Kehn, L.M., Johnson, B.G., Burkey, J.L., Wright, R.A., Calligaro, <lb/>D.O., Marek, G.J., Nisenbaum, E.S., Catlow, J.T., Kingston, A.E., Giera, <lb/>D.D., Herin, M.F., Monn, J.A., McKinzie, D.L., Schoepp, D.D. (2007) <lb/>Pharmacological and pharmacokinetic properties of a structurally-novel, po-<lb/>tent, selective mGlu2/3 receptor agonist: In vitro characterization of <lb/>LY404039. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther., 321, 308-17. <lb/>[54] <lb/>Schoepp, D.D., Jane, D.E., Monn, J.A. (1999) Pharmacological agents acting <lb/>at subtypes of metabotropic glutamate receptors. Neuropharmacology, 38, <lb/>1431-76. <lb/>[55] <lb/>Shipe, W.D., Wolkenberg, S.E., Williams, D.L. Jr., Lindsley, C.W. (2005) <lb/>Recent advances in positive allosteric modulators of metabotropic glutamate <lb/>receptors. Curr. Opin. Drug Discov. Devel., 8, 449-57. <lb/>[56] <lb/>Sladeczek, F., Pin, J.P., Recasens, M., Bockaert, J., Weiss, S. (1985) Gluta-<lb/>mate stimulates inositol phosphate formation in striatal neurons. Nature, 317, <lb/>717-719. <lb/>[57] <lb/>Slassi, A., Isaac, M., Edwards, L., Minidis, A., Wensbo, D., Mattsson, J., <lb/>Nilsson, K., Raboisson, P., McLeod, D., Stormann, T.M., Hammerland, L.G., <lb/>Johnson, E. (2005) Recent advances in non-competitive mGlu5 receptor an-<lb/>tagonists and their potential therapeutic applications. Curr. Top. Med. Chem., <lb/>5, 897-911. <lb/>[58] <lb/>Spooren, W., Ballard, T., Gasparini, F., Amalric, M., Mutel, V., Schreiber, R. <lb/>(2003) Insight into the function of Group I and Group II metabotropic gluta-<lb/>mate (mGlu) receptors: behavioural characterization and implications for the <lb/>treatment of CNS disorders. Behav. Pharmacol., 14, 257-77. <lb/>[59] <lb/>Spooren, W., Gasparini, F. (2004) mGlu5 receptor antagonists: a novel class <lb/>of anxiolytics? Drug News Perspect., 17, 251-7. <lb/>[60] <lb/>Steckler, T., Lavreysen, H., Oliveira, A.M., Aerts, N., Van Craenendonck, <lb/>H., Prickaerts, J., Megens, A., Lesage, A.S. (2005) Effects of mGlu1 receptor <lb/>blockade on anxiety-related behaviour in the rat lick suppression test. Psy-<lb/>chopharmacology, 179, 198-206. <lb/>[61] <lb/>Steckler, T., Oliveira, A.F., Van Dyck, C., Van Craenendonck, H., Mateus, <lb/>A.M., Langlois, X., Lesage, A.S., Prickaerts, J. (2005) Metabotropic gluta-<lb/>mate receptor 1 blockade impairs acquisition and retention in a spatial Water <lb/>maze task. Behav. Brain Res., 164, 52-60. <lb/>[62] <lb/>Valenti, O., Mannaioni, G., Seabrook, G.R., Conn, P.J., Marino, M.J. (2005) <lb/>Group III metabotropic glutamate-receptor-mediated modulation of excita-<lb/>tory transmission in rodent substantia nigra pars compacta dopamine neu-<lb/>rons. J. Pharmacol. Exp. Ther., 313, 1296-304. <lb/>[63] <lb/>Wichmann, J., Adam, G., Kolczewski, S., Mutel, V., Woltering, T. (1999) <lb/>Structure-activity relationships of substituted 5H-thiazolo[3,2-a]pyrimidines <lb/>as group 2 metabotropic glutamate receptor antagonists. Bioorg. Med. Chem. <lb/>Lett., 9, 1573-6. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Received: February 19, 2007 <lb/>Accepted: April 5, 2007 </front>


	</text>
</tei>