<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1182 <lb/>Convergent synthesis of the tetrasaccharide <lb/>repeating unit of the O-antigen of <lb/>Shigella boydii type 9 <lb/>Abhishek Santra and Anup Kumar Misra * <lb/>Full Research Paper <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Address: <lb/>Bose Institute, Division of Molecular Medicine, P-1/12, C.I.T. Scheme <lb/>VII-M, Kolkata-700054, India; Fax: 91-33-2355 3886 <lb/>Email: <lb/>Anup Kumar Misra * -akmisra69@gmail.com <lb/>* Corresponding author <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>diarrhea; glycosylation; O-antigen; oligosaccharide; Shigella boydii <lb/>Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/>doi:10.3762/bjoc.7.137 <lb/>Received: 01 June 2011 <lb/>Accepted: 25 July 2011 <lb/>Published: 29 August 2011 <lb/>Associate Editor: S. Flitsch <lb/>© 2011 Santra and Misra; licensee Beilstein-Institut. <lb/>License and terms: see end of document. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>A convenient synthesis of the tetrasaccharide repeating unit of the O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9 has been achieved in excel-<lb/>lent yield using a [2 + 2] block glycosylation strategy. TEMPO-mediated selective oxidation of the primary alcohol of the tetra-<lb/>saccharide derivative 8 to the carboxylic group followed by deprotection of the functional groups furnished target tetrasaccharide 1 <lb/>as its 4-methoxyphenyl glycoside in high yield. <lb/></front>

			<page>1182 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1: Structure of the tetrasaccharide repeating unit of the O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9. <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Diarrhoeal disease is a common cause of death in the tropical <lb/>countries and it is the second mostly causing infant deaths <lb/>worldwide. Shigella is one of the well-studied human pathogens <lb/>that cause diarrhoeal disease and dysentery (e.g., shigellosis). <lb/>Among several types of Shigella species, Shigella dysenteriae is <lb/>the most virulent pathogen causing devastating health problems <lb/>in developing countries [1-3]. Shigella strains are classified into <lb/>four species: Shigella boydii, Shigella dysenteriae, Shigella <lb/>flexneri and Shigella sonnei [4]. Sometimes, these species are <lb/>also termed as Shigella subgroups A, B, C, and D. Based on the <lb/>O-antigens, the Shigella species are divided into multiple <lb/>serotypes [5]. In general, O-antigens of Shigella species are <lb/>acidic in nature because of the presence of acidic constituents <lb/>(e.g., uronic acid, pseudaminic acid etc. or lactic acid, pyruvic <lb/>acid etc.) in their structures [6,7]. Recently, L&apos;vov et al. <lb/>reported the structure of the O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9, <lb/>which is a tetrasaccharide repeating unit containing a <lb/>D-glucuronic acid moiety (Figure 1) [8]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1183 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2: Structure of the synthesized tetrasaccharide and its intermediates. <lb/>Development of effective therapeutics to control the infections <lb/>of drug-resistant bacterial strains is the thrust area in the medi-<lb/>cinal chemistry. Like other bacterial infections, emergence of <lb/>the drug resistant Shigella infections requires development of <lb/>the newer therapeutics than the earlier used anti-shigellosis <lb/>agents [9,10]. Because of the high antigenic nature of the <lb/>O-antigens, antibodies against the O-specific polysaccharide of <lb/>a particular Shigella strain have the potential to control Shigella <lb/>infections [11-14]. A number of reports have been cited earlier <lb/>to develop glycoconjugate based therapy to control Shigella <lb/>infections [15-19]. In order to develop a glycoconjugate based <lb/>therapeutic agent from the tetrasaccharide repeating unit of the <lb/>O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9, it is essential to perform <lb/>several immunochemical studies with the glycoconjugates <lb/>derived from this tetrasaccharide repeating unit. The large quan-<lb/>tity of the tetrasaccharide that is required for this purpose <lb/>cannot be accessible from a natural source. Therefore, chemical <lb/>synthesis is the only option for achieving this in large quantity. <lb/>As a first step towards the preparation of glycoconjugates, we <lb/>report herein a convergent chemical synthesis of the tetra-<lb/>saccharide as its 4-methoxyphenyl glycoside 1 corresponding to <lb/>the O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9 using a [2 + 2] block <lb/>glycosylation strategy (Figure 2). <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>The convergent synthesis of the target tetrasaccharide 1 as its <lb/>4-methoxyphenyl glycoside has been achieved applying a <lb/>number of recently developed elegant reaction methodologies. <lb/>A number of notable features are present in the synthetic <lb/>strategy, which are (a) convergent [2 + 2] block glycosylation; <lb/>(b) application of recently developed environmentally benign <lb/>reaction conditions for protecting group manipulations and <lb/>glycosylations such as, (i) O-acetylation using sulfamic acid <lb/>[20], (ii) regioselective ring opening of the benzylidene acetal <lb/>using a combination of triethylsilane and iodine [21], (iii) direct <lb/>one-pot conversion of O-acetyl group to O-benzyl group [22], <lb/>(iv) activation of glycosyl trichloroacetimidate and thioglyco-<lb/>side donors by perchloric acid supported on silica <lb/>(HClO 4 -SiO 2 ) [23-26], and late stage TEMPO mediated selec-<lb/>tive oxidation [27-29] of the primary hydroxy group to the <lb/>carboxylic group under phase transfer conditions without <lb/>affecting the secondary hydroxy groups; (c) use of <lb/>4-methoxyphenyl (PMP) group as anomeric protecting group <lb/>[30,31], which can be easily removed under oxidative condi-<lb/>tions for the preparation of glycoconjugate derivatives. The syn-<lb/>thesis of the target tetrasaccharide 1 was achieved by the stereo-<lb/>selective coupling of a D-maltose derived disaccharide deriva-<lb/>tive 2 and a disaccharide thioglycoside derivative 7 followed by <lb/>functional group manipulations of the resulting tetrasaccharide <lb/>derivative 8. For this purpose, suitably functionalized reaction <lb/>intermediates 2, 3, 4 and 7 were prepared from commercially <lb/>available reducing mono-and disaccharides utilizing a series of <lb/>reaction methodologies reported earlier. <lb/>4-Methoxyphenyl (4,6-O-benzylidene-α-D-glucopyranosyl)-<lb/>(1→4)-β-D-glucopyranoside (5) [32] was subjected to a <lb/>sequence of reactions involving acetylation using acetic anhy-<lb/>dride in the presence of sulfamic acid [20] followed by regio-<lb/>selective reductive ring opening of the benzylidene acetal using <lb/>a combination of triethylsilane and iodine [21] to furnish <lb/>4-methoxyphenyl (2,3-di-O-acetyl-6-O-benzyl-α-D-glucopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→4)-2,3,6-tri-O-acetyl-β-D-glucopyranoside (2) in <lb/>82% yield (Scheme 1). 3,4,6-Tri-O-acetyl-2-azido-2-deoxy-α-<lb/>D-glucopyranosyl trichloroacetimidate (3) [33] was allowed to <lb/>couple stereoselectively with ethyl 2,4-di-O-benzyl-1-thio-α-L-<lb/>rhamnopyranoside (4) [34] under Schmidt&apos;s reaction conditions <lb/>[35] using perchloric acid supported on silica (HClO 4 -SiO 2 ) <lb/>[23,24] as glycosylation activator to give ethyl (3,4,6-tri-O-<lb/>acetyl-2-azido-2-deoxy-α-D-glucopyranosyl)-(1→3)-2,4-di-O-<lb/>benzyl-1-thio-α-L-rhamnopyranoside (6) in 81% yield. Stereo-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1184 <lb/></page>

			<body>Scheme 1: Reagents: (a) acetic anhydride, sulfamic acid, 60 °C, 30 min, 91%; (b) Et 3 SiH, I 2 , 0-5 °C, 30 min, 82%. <lb/>Scheme 2: Reagents: (a) HClO 4 -SiO 2 , CH 2 Cl 2 , -15 °C, 1 h, 81%; (b) benzyl bromide, NaOH, n-Bu 4 NBr, THF, rt, 2 h, 91%. <lb/>Scheme 3: Reagents: (a) N-iodosuccinimide, HClO 4 -SiO 2 , -10 °C, 1 h, 82%; (b) 0.1 M CH 3 ONa, CH 3 OH, rt, 3 h; (c) (i) NaBr, TBAB, TEMPO, <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 , H 2 O, NaOCl, NaHCO 3 , 5 °C, 2 h; (ii) tert-butanol, 2-methylbut-2-ene, NaClO 2 , NaH 2 PO 4 , rt, 3 h; (d) (i) H 2 , 20% Pd(OH) 2 /C, CH 3 OH-EtOAc, <lb/>rt, 10 h; (ii) acetic anhydride, CH 3 OH, rt, 30 min, overall 64%. <lb/>selective formation of compound 6 was confirmed from its <lb/>spectral analysis (presence of signals at δ 5.35 (br s, H-1 C ), 4.95 <lb/>(d, J = 3.6 Hz, H-1 D ) in the 1 H NMR and signals at δ 92.8 <lb/>(C-1 D ), 81.0 (C-1 C ) in the 13 C NMR spectrum). Compound 6 <lb/>was transformed into disaccharide thioglycoside donor 7 in 91% <lb/>yield under a one-pot deacetylation-benzylation reaction condi-<lb/>tion [22] (Scheme 2). In this case, the thioethyl group acts as an <lb/>orthogonal anomeric protecting group since it acts as a glycosyl <lb/>acceptor in the case of compound 4 whereas compound 7 has <lb/>been used as the glycosyl donor in the next step. Iodonium ion <lb/>promoted stereoselective glycosylation of the disaccharide thio-<lb/>glycoside donor 7 with the disaccharide acceptor 2 in the pres-<lb/>ence of a combination of N-iodosuccinimide (NIS) and <lb/>HClO 4 -SiO 2 [25,26] furnished tetrasaccharide derivative 8 in <lb/>82% yield. Stereoselective formation of new α-glycosyl linkage <lb/>in compound 8 was confirmed from the 1D and 2D NMR spec-<lb/>tral analysis (presence of signals at δ 5.34 (d, J = 4.5 Hz, H-1 B ), <lb/>4.97 (d, J = 3.5 Hz, H-1 D ), 4.95 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, H-1 A ), 4.89 (d, <lb/>J = 2.0 Hz, H-1 C ) in the 1 H NMR and signals at δ 99.7 (C-1 A ), <lb/>98.8 (C-1 C ), 96.0 (C-1 B ), 93.9 (C-1 D ) in the 13 C NMR spec-<lb/>trum). Because of the presence of the non-participating benzyl-<lb/>oxy group in the C-2 position of the L-rhamnosyl moiety, <lb/>involved in the glycosylation reaction, a minor amount of <lb/>β-glycosyl linked product also formed (~6%) together with the <lb/>desired product 8, which was separated by the column chroma-<lb/>tography. The presence of the α-linkages in compound 8 was <lb/>further confirmed from the J C1-H1 values in the 1 H coupled <lb/>13 C NMR spectrum of compound 8. Appearance of J C1-H1 <lb/>172.0 Hz, 171.6 Hz, 170.5 Hz and 162.0 Hz values in the <lb/>anomeric region in the 1 H coupled 13 C spectrum unambiguous-<lb/>ly supported the presence of three α-linkages and one β-linkage <lb/>[36-38] in compound 8. Compound 8 was subjected to a reac-<lb/>tion sequence involving (a) deacetylation using 0.1 M sodium <lb/>methoxide in methanol; (b) TEMPO mediated selective oxi-<lb/>dation [27-29] of the primary hydroxy group leaving secondary <lb/>hydroxy groups unaffected in a phase transfer reaction condi-<lb/>tion and (c) removal of benzyl groups for cleavage of ethers and <lb/>reduction of the azido group to an amine by hydrogenation over <lb/>20% Pd(OH) 2 /C followed by N-acetylation to furnish target <lb/>tetrasaccharide 1 as its sodium salt and 4-methoxyphenyl glyco-<lb/>side in 64% yield (Scheme 3). Spectroscopic analysis of com-<lb/>pound 1 confirmed its formation (presence of signals at δ 5.20 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1185 <lb/></page>

			<body>(d, J = 3.6 Hz, H-1 B ), 4.93 (br s, H-1 D ), 4.89 (br s, H-1 C ), 4.82 <lb/>(d, J = 7.8 Hz, H-1 A ) in the 1 H NMR and signals at δ 103.3 <lb/>(C-1 A ), 102.8 (C-1 B ), 102.4 (C-1 C ), 96.7 (C-1 D ) in the <lb/>13 C NMR spectrum). <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, a convenient synthetic strategy has been de-<lb/>veloped for the synthesis of the tetrasaccharide repeating unit of <lb/>the O-antigen of Shigella boydii type 9 as its 4-methoxyphenyl <lb/>glycoside sodium salt using a [2 + 2] block synthetic strategy. <lb/>Use of a block glycosylation strategy and a late-stage selective <lb/>oxidation of the primary hydroxy group significantly reduced <lb/>the number of protection-deprotection steps. A number of <lb/>modified clean reaction methodologies have been applied for <lb/>the preparation of intermediates. HClO 4 -SiO 2 has been used as <lb/>an effective acid catalyst to activate glycosyl trichloroacetimi-<lb/>date derivative and thioglycoside in combination with NIS <lb/>avoiding the use of moisture sensitive protic acids. All inter-<lb/>mediate steps were high yielding and glycosylation steps were <lb/>stereoselective. <lb/>Experimental <lb/>General methods: All reactions were monitored by thin layer <lb/>chromatography over silica gel-coated TLC plates. The spots on <lb/>TLC plates were visualized by warming ceric sulfate (2% <lb/>Ce(SO 4 ) 2 in 2 N H 2 SO 4 )-sprayed plates on a hot plate. Silica <lb/>gel 230-400 mesh was used for column chromatography. 1 H <lb/>and 13 C NMR, DEPT 135, 2D COSY, HMQC and gated 1 H <lb/>coupled 13 C NMR spectra were recorded on Bruker Avance <lb/>DRX 500 and 600 MHz spectrometers using CDCl 3 and <lb/>CD 3 OD as solvents and TMS as internal standard unless other-<lb/>wise stated. Chemical shifts are expressed in δ ppm. ESIMS <lb/>were recorded on a Micromass Quattro mass spectrometer. <lb/>Elementary analysis was carried out on Carlo Erba-1108 <lb/>analyzer. Optical rotations were measured at 25 °C on a Jasco <lb/>P-2000 polarimeter. Commercially available grades of organic <lb/>solvents of adequate purity are used in all reactions. Silica <lb/>supported perchloric acid (HClO 4 -SiO 2 ) was prepared <lb/>following the earlier report [39]. <lb/>4-Methoxyphenyl (2,3-di-O-acetyl-6-O-benzyl-α-D-glucopy-<lb/>ranosyl)-(1→4)-2,3,6-tri-O-acetyl-β-D-glucopyranoside (2): <lb/>To a suspension of 4-methoxyphenyl (4,6-O-benzylidene-α-D-<lb/>glucopyranosyl)-(1→4)-β-D-glucopyranoside (5, 3.0 g, <lb/>5.59 mmol) in acetic anhydride (6.0 mL, 63.47 mmol) sulfamic <lb/>acid (100 mg, 1.0 mmol) was added and the reaction mixture <lb/>was allowed to stir at 60 °C for 30 min. The solvents were <lb/>removed under reduced pressure and the crude reaction mixture <lb/>was passed through a short pad of silica gel using <lb/>hexane-EtOAc (1:2) as eluant to give pure acetylated product <lb/>(3.8 g, 91%). To a solution of the acetylated product (3.5 g, <lb/>4.69 mmol) in CH 3 CN (15 mL) triethylsilane (1.5 mL, <lb/>9.39 mmol) and iodine (250 mg, 0.98 mmol) were added at <lb/>0-5 °C and the reaction mixture was allowed to stir at the same <lb/>temperature for 30 min. The reaction mixture was poured into <lb/>water and extracted with CH 2 Cl 2 (100 mL). The organic layer <lb/>was successively washed with satd. NaHCO 3 solution and <lb/>water, dried (Na 2 SO 4 ) and concentrated. The crude product was <lb/>purified over silica gel using hexane-EtOAc (2:1) as eluant to <lb/>give pure compound 2 (2.9 g, 82%). White solid; mp 60-62 °C; <lb/>[α] D <lb/>25 +43.2 (c 1.2, CHCl 3 ); IR (KBr): 3479, 1751, 1509, 1371, <lb/>1233, 1047, 830, 754 cm -1 ; 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 5.38 <lb/>(d, J = 4.0 Hz, 1H, H-1 B ), 5.28 (t, J = 9.0 Hz, 1H, H-3 A ), 5.21 <lb/>(t, J = 9.0 Hz, 1H, H-3 B ), 5.04 (t, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H, H-2 A ), 4.96 <lb/>(d, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H, H-1 A ), 4.80 (dd, J = 9.0, 4.0 Hz, 1H, H-2 B ), <lb/>4.60-4.54 (m, 2H, PhCH 2 ), 4.50 (d, J = 11.5 Hz, 1H, H-6 aA ), <lb/>4.22 (dd, J = 12.0 Hz, 5.0 Hz, 1H, H-6 bA ), 4.06 (t, J = 9.5 Hz, <lb/>1H, H-4 A ), 3.79-3.71 (m, 4H, H-4 B , H-5 A , H-5 B , H-6 aB ), 3.75 <lb/>(s, 3H, OCH 3 ), 3.63-3.61 (m, 1H, H-6 bB ), 2.07, 2.03, 2.00, 1.99 <lb/>(4 s, 15H, 5 COCH 3 ); 13 C NMR (125 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 170.1, <lb/>170.6, 170.5, 170.2, 169.6 (5 COCH 3 ), 155.6-114.5 (Ar-C), <lb/>99.6 (C-1 A ), 95.7 (C-1 B ), 75.4 (C-3 A ), 73.7 (PhCH 2 ), 72.3 <lb/>(C-4 A ), 72.1 (C-3 B ), 72.0 (C-2 A ), 71.9 (C-5 A ), 71.5 (C-5 B ), <lb/>70.0 (C-2 B ), 69.7 (C-4 B ), 68.8 (C-6 B ), 62.7 (C-6 A ), 55.6 <lb/>(OCH 3 ), 20.8, 20.7, 20.6, 20.5 (2 C) (5 COCH 3 ); ESIMS m/z: <lb/>771.2 [M + Na] + ; anal. calcd for C 36 H 44 O 17 (748.26): C, 57.75; <lb/>H, 5.92; found: C, 57.54; H, 6.15. <lb/>Ethyl (3,4,6-tri-O-acetyl-2-azido-2-deoxy-α-D-glucopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→3)-2,4-di-O-benzyl-1-thio-α-L-rhamnopyra-<lb/>noside (6): A solution of compound 3 (2.4 g, 5.04 mmol) and <lb/>compound 4 (1.5 g, 3.86 mmol) in anhydrous CH 2 Cl 2 (10 mL) <lb/>was cooled to -15 °C under argon. To the cooled reaction mix-<lb/>ture HClO 4 -SiO 2 (50.0 mg) was added and the reaction mix-<lb/>ture was allowed to stir at the same temperature for 1 h. The <lb/>reaction mixture was filtered through a bed of Celite ® and <lb/>concentrated under reduced pressure. The crude product was <lb/>purified over silica gel using hexane-EtOAc (3:1) as eluant to <lb/>furnish pure compound 6 (2.2 g, 81%). Yellow oil; [α] D <lb/>25 +63.3 <lb/>(c 1.2, CHCl 3 ); IR (neat): 2930, 2110, 1750, 1455, 1368, 1233, <lb/>1094, 1039, 755, 699 cm -1 ; 1 H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>δ 7.43-7.26 (m, 10H, Ar-H), 5.55 (t, J = 10.2 Hz, 1H, H-3 D ), <lb/>5.35 (br s, 1H, H-1 C ), 4.98 (t, J = 10.2 Hz, 1H, H-4 D ), 4.95 (d, <lb/>J = 3.6 Hz, 1H, H-1 D ), 4.91 (d, J = 11.4 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.74 <lb/>(d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.70 (d, J = 11.4 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), <lb/>4.64 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.15-4.13 (m, 1H, H-5 D ), <lb/>4.08-4.03 (m, 2H, H-5 C , H-6 aD ), 4.00 (dd, J = 9.6, 3.0 Hz, 1H, <lb/>H-3 C ), 3.93 (br s, 1H, H-2 C ), 3.88 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, H-6 bD ), <lb/>3.69 (t, J = 9.6 Hz, 1H, H-4 C ), 3.31 (dd, J = 10.8, 3.6 Hz, 1H, <lb/>H-2 D ), 2.61-2.56 (m, 2H, SCH 2 CH 3 ), 2.08, 2.05, 1.90 (3 s, 9H, <lb/>3 COCH 3 ), 1.36 (d, J = 6.0 Hz, 3H, CCH 3 ), 1.25 (t, J = 7.2 Hz, <lb/>3H, SCH 2 CH 3 ); 13 C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 170.5, 169.8, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1186 <lb/></page>

			<body>169.6 (3 COCH 3 ), 138.0-127.6 (Ar-C), 92.8 (C-1 D ), 81.0 <lb/>(C-1 C ), 79.4 (C-3 C ), 75.5 (PhCH 2 ), 74.6 (C-3 C ), 74.2 (C-2 C ), <lb/>71.8 (PhCH 2 ), 70.4 (C-3 D ), 68.4 (C-5 C ), 68.1 (C-4 D ), 67.3 <lb/>(C-5 D ), 61.5 (C-6 D ), 60.6 (C-2 D ), 25.4 (SCH 2 CH 3 ), 20.7, 20.6, <lb/>20.5 (3 COCH 3 ), 17.7 (CCH 3 ), 14.9 (SCH 2 CH 3 ); ESIMS m/z: <lb/>724.2 [M + Na] + ; anal. calcd for C 34 H 43 N 3 O 11 S (701.26): C, <lb/>58.19; H, 6.18; found: C, 58.0; H, 6.42. <lb/>Ethyl (2-azido-3,4,6-tri-O-benzyl-2-deoxy-α-D-glucopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→3)-2,4-di-O-benzyl-1-thio-α-L-rhamnopyra-<lb/>noside (7): To a solution of compound 6 (2.0 g, 2.85 mmol) in <lb/>THF (10 mL) powdered NaOH (1.0 g, 25 mmol), benzyl bro-<lb/>mide (2.1 mL, 17.6 mmol) and n-Bu 4 NBr (50 mg) were added <lb/>and the reaction mixture was allowed to stir at rt for 2 h. The <lb/>reaction mixture was poured into water and extracted with <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 (100 mL). The organic layer was washed with water, <lb/>dried (Na 2 SO 4 ) and concentrated under reduced pressure. The <lb/>crude product was purified over silica gel using hexane-EtOAc <lb/>(6:1) as eluant to give pure compound 7 (2.2 g, 91%). Yellow <lb/>oil; [α] D <lb/>25 +12.0 (c 1.2, CHCl 3 ); IR (neat): 3430, 3031, 2925, <lb/>2107, 1642, 1496, 1454, 1361, 1215, 1091, 1051, 1028, 751, <lb/>697 cm -1 ; 1 H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 7.45-7.07 (m, 25H, <lb/>Ar-H), 5.32 (br s, 1H, H-1 C ), 4.93 (d, J = 3.6 Hz, 1H, H-1 D ), <lb/>4.85 (br s, 2H, PhCH 2 ), 4.83 (d, J = 10.2 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.77 <lb/>(d, J = 10.8 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.74 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), <lb/>4.69 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.60 (d, J = 12.6 Hz, 1H, <lb/>PhCH 2 ), 4.55 (d, J = 10.2 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.48 (d, J = <lb/>10.8 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.35 (d, J = 12.6 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.07 <lb/>(t, J = 9.6 Hz, 1H, H-3 D ), 4.04-3.99 (m, 3H, H-3 C , H-5 C , <lb/>H-5 D ), 3.93 (br s, 1H, H-2 C ), 3.79 (t, J = 9.6 Hz, 1H, H-4 C ), <lb/>3.66 (t, J = 9.6 Hz, 1H, H-4 D ), 3.60 (dd, J = 10.8, 2.4 Hz, 1H, <lb/>H-6 aD ), 3.51 (dd, J = 10.8, 1.2 Hz, 1H, H-6 aD ), 3.40 (dd, J = <lb/>10.2, 3.6 Hz, 1H, H-2 D ), 2.60-2.50 (m, 2H, SCH 2 CH 3 ), 1.35 (d, <lb/>J = 6.0 Hz, 3H, CCH 3 ), 1.22 (t, J = 7.8 Hz, 3H, SCH 2 CH 3 ); <lb/>13 C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 137.7-127.5 (Ar-C), 93.2 <lb/>(C-1 D ), 81.1 (C-1 C ), 80.2 (C-3 D ), 79.8 (C-4 D ), 78.1 (C-4 C ), <lb/>75.9 (PhCH 2 ), 74.8 (PhCH 2 ), 74.5 (C-3 C ), 74.4 (C-2 C ), 73.3 <lb/>(PhCH 2 ), 71.8 (PhCH 2 ), 70.4 (C-5 C ), 68.3 (C-5 D ), 67.8 (C-6 D ), <lb/>63.0 (C-2 D ), 25.4 (SCH 2 CH 3 ), 17.8 (CCH 3 ), 14.9 (SCH 2 CH 3 ); <lb/>ESIMS m/z: 868.3 [M + Na] + ; anal. calcd for C 49 H 55 N 3 O 8 S <lb/>(845.37): C, 69.56; H, 6.55; found: C, 69.33; H, 6.80. <lb/>4-Methoxyphenyl (2-azido-3,4,6-tri-O-benzyl-2-deoxy-α-D-<lb/>glucopyranosyl)-(1→3)-(2,4-di-O-benzyl-α-L-rhamnopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→4)-(2,3-di-O-acetyl-6-O-benzyl-α-D-glucopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→4)-2,3,6-tri-O-acetyl-β-D-glucopyranoside (8): To <lb/>a solution of compound 2 (1.2 g, 1.60 mmol) and compound 7 <lb/>(1.6 g, 1.89 mmol) in anhydrous CH 2 Cl 2 (8 mL) MS 4Å (2.0 g) <lb/>was added and the reaction mixture was cooled to -10 °C. <lb/>To the cooled reaction mixture NIS (500.0 mg, 2.22 mmol) <lb/>and HClO 4 -SiO 2 (20.0 mg) were added and it was allowed to <lb/>stir for 1 h at same temperature. The reaction mixture was <lb/>filtered through a bed of Celite ® and washed with CH 2 Cl 2 <lb/>(100 mL). The organic layer was successively washed with 5% <lb/>aq. Na 2 S 2 O 3 , NaHCO 3 solution and water, dried (Na 2 SO 4 ) and <lb/>concentrated under reduced pressure. The crude product was <lb/>purified over silica gel using hexane-EtOAc (2:1) as eluant to <lb/>give pure compound 8 (2.0 g, 82%). White solid; mp 66-68 °C; <lb/>[α] D <lb/>25 +18.2 (c 1.2, CHCl 3 ); IR (KBr): 3428, 3032, 2932, 2108, <lb/>1753, 1508, 1455, 1368, 1230, 1044, 740, 698 cm -1 ; 1 H NMR <lb/>(600 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 7.35-7.05 (m, 30H, Ar-H), 6.91 (d, J = <lb/>9.0 Hz, 2H, Ar-H), 6.80 (J = 9.0 Hz, 2H, Ar-H), 5.34 (d, J = <lb/>4.5 Hz, 1H, H-1 B ), 5.29 (t, J = 10.0 Hz, 1H, H-3 A ), 5.27 (t, J = <lb/>9.0 Hz, 1H, H-3 B ), 5.04 (dd, J = 8.0 Hz each, 1H, H-2 A ), 4.97 <lb/>(d, J = 3.5 Hz, 1H, H-1 D ), 4.95 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H, H-1 A ), 4.89 <lb/>(d, J = 2.0 Hz, 1H, H-1 C ), 4.85-4.80 (m, 2H, PhCH 2 ), <lb/>4.78-4.75 (m, 3H, H-2 B , PhCH 2 ), 4.65 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, <lb/>PhCH 2 ), 4.60 (d, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.58-4.44 (m, 5H, <lb/>PhCH 2 ), 4.41 (dd, J = 12.5, 2.5 Hz, 1H, H-6 aA ), 4.35 (d, J = <lb/>12.0 Hz, 1H, PhCH 2 ), 4.21 (dd, J = 12.5, 2.5 Hz, 1H, H-6 bA ), <lb/>4.05-4.01 (2 t, J = 9.5 Hz each, 2H, H-3 D , H-4 C ), 3.98-3.92 (m, <lb/>2H, H-3c, H-5c), 3.90 (t, J = 10.0 Hz, 1H, H-4 D ), 3.81 (t, J = <lb/>8.5 Hz, 1H, H-4 A ), 3.77 (s, 3H, OCH 3 ), 3.76-3.74 (m, 1H, <lb/>H-4 B ), 3.72-3.71 (m, 1H, H-5 B ), 3.69-3.65 (m, 2H, H-5 A , <lb/>H-6 aB ), 3.63-3.61 (m, 1H, H-6 aD ), 3.58-3.55 (m, 3H, H-2 C , <lb/>H-5 D , H-6 bB ), 3.53-3.51 (m, 1H, H-6 bD ), 3.43 (dd, J = 10.0, 3.5 <lb/>Hz, 1H, H-2 D ), 2.04, 2.02, 2.01, 1.99, 1.95 (5 s, 15H, <lb/>5 COCH 3 ), 1.25 (d, J = 6.2 Hz, 3H, CCH 3 ); 13 C NMR <lb/>(150 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 170.7, 170.2 (2C), 169.8, 169.7 <lb/>(5 COCH 3 ), 155.7-114.5 (Ar-C), 99.7 (C-1 A ), 98.8 (C-1 C ), 96.0 <lb/>(C-1 B ), 93.9 (C-1 D ), 80.2 (C-3 D ), 79.4 (C-4 D ), 78.2 (C-5 A ), <lb/>77.2 (C-5 B ), 75.5 (PhCH 2 ), 75.4 (C-3 A ), 75.3 (PhCH 2 ), 74.8 <lb/>(PhCH 2 ), 74.3 (C-2 B ), 74.2 (C-4 C ), 73.7 (PhCH 2 ), 73.3 <lb/>(PhCH 2 ), 72.6 (2C, C-5 D , PhCH 2 ), 72.2 (C-4 A ), 72.1 (C-2 A ), <lb/>71.3 (C-4 B ), 70.7 (2C, C-3 C , C-5 C ), 70.4 (C-3 B ), 69.0 (C-2 C ), <lb/>67.9 (C-6 B ), 67.8 (C-6 D ), 63.3 (C-2 D ), 62.6 (C-6 A ), 55.6 <lb/>(OCH 3 ), 21.0, 20.9, 20.7, 20.6 (2C) (5 COCH 3 ), 17.9 (CCH 3 ); <lb/>ESIMS m/z: 1554.6 [M + Na] + ; anal. calcd for C 83 H 93 N 3 O 25 <lb/>(1531.61): C, 65.04; H, 6.12; found: C, 64.82; H, 6.36. <lb/>4-Methoxyphenyl (2-acetamido-2-deoxy-α-D-glucopyra-<lb/>nosyl)-(1→3)-(α-L-rhamnopyranosyl)-(1→4)-(α-D-glucopy-<lb/>ranosyl)-(1→4)-sodium β-D-glucopyranosid uronate (1): A <lb/>solution of compound 8 (1.3 g, 0.85 mmol) in 0.1 M CH 3 ONa <lb/>in CH 3 OH (25 mL) was allowed to stir at rt for 3 h and neutral-<lb/>ized with Dowex 50W X8 (H + ) resin. The reaction mixture was <lb/>filtered and concentrated under reduced pressure. To a solution <lb/>of the crude product in CH 2 Cl 2 (25 mL) and H 2 O (4 mL) were <lb/>sequentially added aq. NaBr (2 mL, 1 M), aq. TBAB (2.5 mL, <lb/>1 M), TEMPO (100.0 mg, 0.64 mmol), satd. NaHCO 3 solution <lb/>(10 mL) and 4% aq. NaOCl (15 mL) were added and the reac-<lb/>tion mixture was allowed to stir at 0-5 °C for 2 h. The reaction <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1187 <lb/></page>

			<body>mixture was neutralized with 1 N aq. HCl. To the reaction mix-<lb/>ture tert-butanol (25 mL), 2-methylbut-2-ene (20 mL, 2 M solu-<lb/>tion in THF), aq. NaClO 2 (1.5 g in 5 mL) and aq. NaH 2 PO 4 <lb/>(1.5 g in 5 mL) were added and the reaction mixture was stirred <lb/>at room temperature for 3 h. The reaction mixture was diluted <lb/>with satd. aq. NaH 2 PO 4 and extracted with CH 2 Cl 2 (150 mL). <lb/>The organic layer was washed with water, dried (Na 2 SO 4 ) and <lb/>concentrated to dryness. The crude product was passed through <lb/>a short pad of silica gel using EtOAc-toluene (2:1) as eluant. To <lb/>a solution of the oxidized product (800.0 mg) in <lb/>CH 3 OH-EtOAc (20 mL, 10:1 v/v) 20% Pd(OH) 2 /C (150.0 mg) <lb/>was added and the reaction mixture was allowed to stir at room <lb/>temperature under a positive pressure of hydrogen for 10 h. The <lb/>reaction mixture was filtered through a bed of Celite ® and evap-<lb/>orated to dryness. To a solution of the crude product in CH 3 OH <lb/>(10 mL) acetic anhydride (2 mL) was added and the solution <lb/>was kept at rt for 30 min. The solvents were removed under <lb/>reduced pressure and the product was passed through a <lb/>Sephadex ® LH-20 column using CH 3 OH-H 2 O (60 mL, 4:1 v/v) <lb/>as eluant to give pure compound 1 (450.0 mg, 64%). White <lb/>powder; [α] D <lb/>25 +14 (c 1.0, CH 3 OH); IR (KBr): 3428, 2937, <lb/>1621, 1366, 1152, 1087, 669 cm -1 ; 1 H NMR (600 MHz, <lb/>CD 3 OD) δ 7.04 (d, J = 9.0 Hz, 2H, Ar-H), 6.84 (d, J = 9.0 Hz, <lb/>2H, Ar-H), 5.20 (d, J = 3.6 Hz, 1H, H-1 B ), 4.93 (br s, 1H, <lb/>H-1 D ), 4.89 (br s, 1H, H-1 C ), 4.82 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H, H-1 A ), <lb/>4.03-3.98 (m, 2H, H-2 A , H-5 C ), 3.97-3.95 (m, 2H, H-2 C , <lb/>H-2 D ), 3.88-3.86 (m, 1H, H-6 aD ), 3.83-3.75 (m, 5H, H-3 A , <lb/>H-3 B , H-5 D , H-6 aB , H-6 bD ), 3.74 (s, 3H, OCH 3 ), 3.73-3.71 (m, <lb/>1H, H-4 A ), 3.70-3.67 (m, 2H, H-2 B , H-6 bB ), 3.64 (t, J = 9.6 Hz, <lb/>1H, H-3 D ), 3.56-3.50 (m, 4H, H-4 B , H-4 C , H-5 A , H-5 B ), <lb/>3.49-3.44 (m, 2H, H-3 C , H-4 D ), 2.02 (s, 3H, COCH 3 ), 1.30 (d, <lb/>J = 6.1Hz, 3H, CCH 3 ); 13 C NMR (150 MHz, CDCl 3 ) δ 175.0 <lb/>(COONa), 172.6 (NHCOCH 3 ), 156.7-115.5 (Ar-C), 103.3 <lb/>(C-1 A ), 102.8 (C-1 B ), 102.4 (C-1 C ), 96.7 (C-1 D ), 81.2 (C-3 D ), <lb/>79.5 (C-4 B ), 78.1 (C-3 A ), 77.7 (C-4 A ), 76.6 (C-5 A ), 74.6 <lb/>(C-3 C ), 74.2 (C-4 C ), 73.8 (C-2 B ), 73.6 (C-2 A ), 73.0 (C-5 D ), <lb/>72.0 (C-5 B ), 71.9 (C-4 D ), 70.8 (C-5 C ), 69.3 (C-2 C ), 62.1 <lb/>(C-6 B ), 62.0 (C-6 D ), 56.2 (OCH 3 ), 55.3 (C-2 D ), 23.1 <lb/>(NHCOCH 3 ), 18.1 (CCH 3 ); ESIMS m/z: 834.2 [M + H] + ; anal. <lb/>calcd for C 33 H 48 NNaO 22 (833.26): C, 47.54; H, 5.80; found: C, <lb/>47.72; H, 6.07. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting Information <lb/>Supporting Information File 1 <lb/>1D and 2D NMR spectra of compounds 2, 6, 7, 8 and 1. <lb/>[http://www.beilstein-journals.org/bjoc/content/ <lb/>supplementary/1860-5397-7-137-S1.pdf] <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>A. S. thanks CSIR, New Delhi for providing a Senior Research <lb/>Fellowship. This work was supported by Bose Institute, <lb/>Kolkata. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. von Seidlein, L.; Kim, D. R.; Ali, M.; Lee, H.; Wang, X.; Thiem, V. D.; <lb/>Canh, D. G.; Chaicumpa, W.; Agtini, M. D.; Hossain, A.; Bhutta, Z. A.; <lb/>Mason, C.; Sethabutr, O.; Talukder, K.; Nair, G. B.; Deen, J. L.; <lb/>Kotloff, K.; Clemens, J. PLoS Med. 2006, 1556-1569. <lb/>2. Wachsmuth, K.; Morris, G. K. In Shigella, Foodborne Bacterial <lb/>Pathogens; Doyle, M. P., Ed.; Marcel Dekker Inc: New York, 1989; <lb/>pp 447-462. <lb/>3. Gupta, A.; Polyak, C. S.; Bishop, R. D.; Sobel, J.; Mintz, E. D. <lb/>Clin. Infect. Dis. 2004, 38, 1372-1377. doi:10.1086/386326 <lb/>4. Liu, B.; Knirel, Y. A.; Feng, L.; Perepelov, A. V.; Senchenkova, S. N.; <lb/>Wang, Q.; Reeves, P. R.; Wang, L. FEMS Microbiol. Rev. 2008, 32, <lb/>627-653. doi:10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00114.x <lb/>5. Wathen-Grady, H. G.; Davis, B. R.; Morris, G. K. J. Clin. Microbiol. <lb/>1985, 21, 129-132. <lb/>6. Reeves, P. R.; Wang, L. Curr. Top. Microbiol. Immunol. 2002, 264, <lb/>109-135. <lb/>7. Knirel, Y. A.; Kochetkov, N. K. Biochemistry (Moscow) 1994, 59, <lb/>1325-1383. <lb/>8. L&apos;vov, V. L.; Musina, L. I.; Shashkov, A. S.; Ermakov, G. P.; <lb/>Dmitriev, B. A. Bioorg. Khim. 1987, 13, 1245-1255. <lb/>9. Kosek, M.; Yori, P. P.; Olortegui, M. P. Curr. Opin. Infect. Dis. 2010, 23, <lb/>475-480. doi:10.1097/QCO.0b013e32833da204 <lb/>10. Bhan, M. K.; Raj, P.; Srivastava, R.; Bhandari, N.; Kumar, R. <lb/>Indian Pediatr. 1988, 25, 804-805. <lb/>11. Klee, S. R.; Tzschaschel, B. D.; Singh, M.; Falt, I.; Lindberg, A. A.; <lb/>Timmis, K. N.; Guzman, C. A. Microb. Pathog. 1997, 22, 363-376. <lb/>doi:10.1006/mpat.1996.0127 <lb/>12. Kweon, M.-N. Curr. Opin. Infect. Dis. 2008, 21, 313-318. <lb/>doi:10.1097/QCO.0b013e3282f88b92 <lb/>13. Niyogi, S. K. J. Microbiol. 2005, 43, 133-143. <lb/>14. Oaks, E. V.; Turbyfill, K. R. Vaccine 2006, 24, 2290-2301. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.vaccine.2005.11.040 <lb/>15. Pozsgay, V.; Kubler-Kielb, J. ACS Symposium Ser. 2007, 960, <lb/>238-252. doi:10.1021/bk-2007-0960.ch014 <lb/>16. Phalipon, A.; Costachel, C.; Grandjean, C.; Thuizat, A.; Guerreiro, C.; <lb/>Tanguy, M.; Nato, F.; Vulliez-Le Normand, B.; Belot, F.; Wright, K.; <lb/>Marcel-Peyre, V.; Sansonetti, P. J.; Mulard, L. A. J. Immunol. 2006, <lb/>176, 1686-1694. <lb/>17. Pozsgay, V.; Coxon, B.; Glaudemans, C. P. J.; Schneerson, R.; <lb/>Robbins, J. B. Synlett 2003, 743-767. doi:10.1055/s-2003-38724 <lb/>18. Pozsgay, V. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 1998, 37, 138-142. <lb/>doi:10.1002/(SICI)1521-3773(19980202)37:1/2&lt;138::AID-ANIE138&gt;3.0 <lb/>.CO;2-T <lb/>19. Carlin, N. I.; Bundle, D. R.; Lindberg, A. A. J. Immunol. 1987, 138, <lb/>4419-4427. <lb/>20. Santra, A.; Guchhait, G.; Misra, A. K. Green Chem. 2011, 13, <lb/>1345-1351. doi:10.1039/c1gc15122c <lb/>21. Panchadhayee, R.; Misra, A. K. Synlett 2010, 1193-1196. <lb/>doi:10.1055/s-0029-1219798 <lb/>22. Madhusudan, S. K.; Agnihotri, G.; Negi, D. S.; Misra, A. K. <lb/>Carbohydr. Res. 2005, 340, 1373-1377. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.carres.2005.03.007 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Org. Chem. 2011, 7, 1182-1188. <lb/></note>

			<page>1188 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>23. Ludek, O. R.; Gu, W.; Gildersleeve, J. C. Carbohydr. Res. 2010, 345, <lb/>2074-2078. doi:10.1016/j.carres.2010.07.030 <lb/>24. Du, Y.; Wei, G.; Cheng, S.; Hua, Y.; Linhardt, R. J. Tetrahedron Lett. <lb/>2006, 47, 307-310. doi:10.1016/j.tetlet.2005.11.025 <lb/>25. Mukherjee, C.; Misra, A. K. Synthesis 2007, 683-692. <lb/>doi:10.1055/s-2007-965913 <lb/>26. Mukhopadhyay, B.; Collet, B.; Field, R. A. Tetrahedron Lett. 2005, 46, <lb/>5923-5925. doi:10.1016/j.tetlet.2005.06.119 <lb/>27. Huang, L.; Teumelsan, N.; Huang, X. Chem.-Eur. J. 2006, 12, <lb/>5246-5252. doi:10.1002/chem.200600290 <lb/>28. Mukherjee, C.; Misra, A. K. Glycoconjugate J. 2008, 25, 111-119. <lb/>doi:10.1007/s10719-007-9061-0 <lb/>29. Panchadhayee, R.; Misra, A. K. Tetrahedron: Asymmetry 2009, 20, <lb/>1550-1555. doi:10.1016/j.tetasy.2009.05.026 <lb/>30. Attolino, E.; Rising, T. W. D. F.; Heidecke, C. D.; Fairbanks, A. J. <lb/>Tetrahedron: Asymmetry 2007, 18, 1721-1734. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.tetasy.2007.06.026 <lb/>31. Werz, D. B.; Seeberger, P. H. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. 2005, 44, <lb/>6315-6318. doi:10.1002/anie.200502615 <lb/>32. Marmuse, L.; Nepogodiev, S. A.; Field, R. A. Tetrahedron: Asymmetry <lb/>2005, 16, 477-485. doi:10.1016/j.tetasy.2004.11.047 <lb/>33. Grundler, G.; Schmidt, R. R. Liebigs Ann. Chem. 1984, 1826-1847. <lb/>doi:10.1002/jlac.198419841108 <lb/>34. Sajtos, F.; Hajko, J.; Kover, K. E.; Liptak, A. Carbohydr. Res. 2001, <lb/>334, 253-259. doi:10.1016/S0008-6215(01)00196-3 <lb/>35. Schmidt, R. R. Angew. Chem., Int. Ed. Engl. 1986, 25, 212-235. <lb/>doi:10.1002/anie.198602121 <lb/>36. Bock, K.; Pedersen, C. Acta Chem. Scand., Ser. B 1975, 29, 258-264. <lb/>doi:10.3891/acta.chem.scand.29b-0181 <lb/>37. Duus, J. O.; Gotfredsen, C. H.; Bock, K. Chem. Rev. 2000, 100, <lb/>4589-4614. doi:10.1021/cr990302n <lb/>38. Crich, D.; Li, H. J. Org. Chem. 2002, 67, 4640-4646. <lb/>doi:10.1021/jo0108818 <lb/>39. Chakraborti, A. K.; Gulhane, R. Chem. Commun. 2003, 1896-1897. <lb/>doi:10.1039/b304178f <lb/>License and Terms <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>This is an Open Access article under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>The license is subject to the Beilstein Journal of Organic <lb/>Chemistry terms and conditions: <lb/>(http://www.beilstein-journals.org/bjoc) <lb/>The definitive version of this article is the electronic one <lb/>which can be found at: <lb/>doi:10.3762/bjoc.7.137 </front>


	</text>
</tei>