<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>HYPOTHESIS AND THEORY ARTICLE <lb/>published: 11 December 2013 <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fnint.2013.00092 <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development in children: <lb/>perspectives <lb/>Sylvette R. Wiener-Vacher , Derek A. Hamilton 2 and Sidney I. Wiener 3,4 * <lb/>Vestibular and Oculomotor Evaluation Unit, Department of Otorhinolaryngology, Robert Debré Pediatric Hospital, Paris, France <lb/>Department of Psychology, University of New Mexico, Albuquerque, NM, USA <lb/>3 Laboratoire de Physiologie de la Perception et de l&apos; Action, UMR-7152, Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique -Collège de France, Paris, France <lb/>Memolife Laboratory of Excellence, Paris Science and Letters University, Paris, France <lb/>Edited by: <lb/>Paul Smith, University of Otago <lb/>Medical School, New Zealand <lb/>Reviewed by: <lb/>Cynthia Darlington, University of <lb/>Otago, New Zealand <lb/>Paul Smith, University of Otago <lb/>Medical School, New Zealand <lb/>*Correspondence: <lb/>Sidney I. Wiener, Laboratoire de <lb/>Physiologie de la Perception et de <lb/>l&apos; Action, UMR-7152, Centre National <lb/>de la Recherche Scientifique -Collège <lb/>de France, 11 Place Marcelin <lb/>Berthelot, 75231 Paris Cedex 05, <lb/>France <lb/>e-mail: sidney.wiener@ <lb/>college-de-france.fr <lb/>Vestibular signals play an essential role in oculomotor and static and dynamic posturomotor <lb/>functions. Increasing attention is now focusing on their impact on spatial and non-spatial <lb/>cognitive functions. Movements of the head in space evoke vestibular signals that make <lb/>important contributions during the development of brain representations of body parts <lb/>relative to one another as well as representations of body orientation and position within <lb/>the environment. A central nervous system pathway relays signals from the vestibular <lb/>nuclei to the hippocampal system where this input is indispensable for neuronal responses <lb/>selective for the position and orientation of the head in space. One aspect of the <lb/>hippocampal systems&apos; processing to create episodic and contextual memories is its role in <lb/>spatial orientation and navigation behaviors that require processing of relations between <lb/>background cues.These are also impaired in adult patients with vestibular deficits. However <lb/>little is known about the impact of vestibular loss on cognitive development in children. <lb/>This is investigated here with a particular emphasis upon the hypothetical mechanisms and <lb/>potential impact of vestibular loss at critical ages on the development of respective spatial <lb/>and non-spatial cognitive processes and their brain substrates. <lb/>Keywords: ontogeny, development, vestibular, otolith, cognitive, navigation, human <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>How does loss of vestibular function at various ages of child-<lb/>hood impact on the development of complex spatial behaviors <lb/>and cognition? To respond to this, it is necessary to chart the <lb/>ontogeny of these behaviors and of the brain structures impli-<lb/>cated in their expression. Bilateral loss of vestibular function at <lb/>or close to birth results in motor developmental delays (Rine <lb/>et al., 2000; Whitney et al., 2009; Wiener-Vacher et al., 2012b). <lb/>Although vestibular loss can be compensated with a return to <lb/>normal postural and oculomotor functions, observations of such <lb/>children throughout childhood reveal that many of those with <lb/>complete vestibular loss exhibit learning disabilities and poorly <lb/>adapted strategies for overcoming their sensory deficit (Franco <lb/>and Panhoca, 2008). For example, the gaze and fixation prob-<lb/>lems associated with vestibular dysfunction can lead to reading <lb/>problems requiring specific therapy (Braswell and Rine, 2006). <lb/>Development of diverse cognitive functions could be impaired <lb/>in vestibular-deficient children through several possible mech-<lb/>anisms. For example, vestibular deficits can impair detecting <lb/>and distinguishing one&apos;s own movements from other movements <lb/>in the environment through both the visual and proprioceptive <lb/>systems. <lb/>It has also been hypothesized, similar to the &quot;critical <lb/>periods&quot; observed for visual system development, that other <lb/>cognitive functions also have limited developmental windows <lb/>when their underlying brain structures establish long-lasting <lb/>connectivity with repercussions for life. During movements, <lb/>sensorimotor loops transmit conflicting or inaccurate information <lb/>in vestibular-impaired patients and this could lead to faulty wiring <lb/>and deficits in cognitive function. This chain of events can be con-<lb/>ceptualized in a framework where high level brain representations <lb/>are built up from sensorimotor loop activity by intermediate rep-<lb/>resentations of emulated or imagined actions in the real world and <lb/>their anticipated outcomes. <lb/>Vestibular patients have difficulties in constructing and using <lb/>several types of brain representations of space. Adults with bilateral <lb/>vestibular lesions have hippocampal atrophy and suffer spatial and <lb/>non-spatial cognitive impairments (Schautzer et al., 2003; Brandt <lb/>et al., 2005). Do critical periods exist during development where <lb/>vestibular signals are required to establish normal hippocampal <lb/>circuitry permitting spatial navigation and other functions? To <lb/>address this issue, theoretical background will first be provided on <lb/>the forms of spatial navigation, noting how they are supported by <lb/>the diverse types of vestibular information. Next we will discuss the <lb/>hippocampal system, its spatial representations, its relations with <lb/>the vestibular system and its development, followed by a review of <lb/>developmental studies of performance in specially designed spatial <lb/>orientation tasks. The final section will tie this all together, leading <lb/>to specific predictions of the impact of vestibular damage on spatial <lb/>cognition at respective ages corresponding to milestones in brain <lb/>and cognitive development. This will be considered in terms of <lb/>early identification of the potential cognitive deficits deriving from <lb/>vestibular disorders, thus permitting better adapted therapy and <lb/>training programs. <lb/></body>

			<front>Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/>Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></front>

			<body>Vestibular inputs provide several types of information which <lb/>are respectively engaged for diverse corresponding sensorimotor <lb/>and cognitive processes (Potegal, 1982; Wiener and Berthoz, 1993; <lb/>Borel et al., 2008). The three pairs of semicircular canals and the <lb/>otolith organs provide complementary information about several <lb/>types of rotational and translational head movements involving <lb/>accelerations and, importantly, signal the direction of gravitational <lb/>force. The latter is fundamental to terrestrial life from birth since <lb/>postural adjustments and active movements invariably must take <lb/>gravity into account. The brain builds representations of verticality <lb/>based upon vestibular, somatosensory proprioceptive, and visual <lb/>information, constructing a &quot;geocentric&quot; reference frame (Borel <lb/>et al., 2008). Vestibular patients are thus handicapped in acquir-<lb/>ing information during active displacements in the environment <lb/>since sensory frames of reference (e.g., visual or proprioceptive; <lb/>Lacour et al., 1997; Isableu et al., 2010) must be established with-<lb/>out vestibular information. Furthermore, gravitational and other <lb/>vestibular information can be instrumental in timely acquisition <lb/>of fundamental spatial relationships of up vs. down, left vs. right, <lb/>front vs. back, etc. (Wiener-Vacher et al., 2012a). Infants first learn <lb/>these spatial relations with reference to their own body. Under-<lb/>standing spatial relations between the body parts is difficult for <lb/>vestibularly impaired infants, perhaps in part because propriocep-<lb/>tive information about gravity is not reinforced by otolithic gravity <lb/>sensation. This would then have a negative impact on understand-<lb/>ing other spatial relationships such as over/under, inside/outside, <lb/>within/without, interposition, etc. These patients would then <lb/>have difficulty applying these concepts for establishing coordinate <lb/>systems for representing the relative positions and orientations <lb/>between environmental features and their own relative position <lb/>and orientation to all of this. Furthermore, if concepts like &quot;close, <lb/>distant, superior, inferior, etc.&quot; are poorly understood, the child <lb/>could also have difficulty extending them to arithmetic and geom-<lb/>etry as well as to other non-spatial domains where sets and groups <lb/>are compared (e.g., syntax, biology, history). <lb/>The vestibular system also makes a vital contribution in helping <lb/>to distinguish visually perceived self-movements from movements <lb/>of objects in the environment. Vestibular inputs help to reconcile <lb/>diverse and conflicting signals including vision, proprioception <lb/>(and other somatic sensation) and internally generated motor <lb/>commands. For example, optic flow signals are generated when <lb/>the head moves slowly at a constant velocity, but they also occur <lb/>when the head is immobile by viewing clouds drifting across the <lb/>sky, movement of the environment as seen from a stroller or a car <lb/>window, by points of light projected by a rotating disco mirror <lb/>ball, by movements of crowds, while seated on an immobile train <lb/>when the train on the next track pulls away, etc. Difficulties in <lb/>reconciling self-movements from non-self-movements as well as <lb/>in selecting appropriate vertical and horizontal references can thus <lb/>lead to problems in postural and motor coordination, fine motor <lb/>control, and visual processing. Vestibular patients depend more <lb/>on vision and proprioception for determining the earth vertical <lb/>orientation and if an object taken to be a stable reference point <lb/>moves, this can lead to postural instability and disorientation. <lb/>Signals related to rotational and linear accelerations including <lb/>gravity can help stabilize and inform several types of movements. <lb/>Each of these is associated with cognitive processes that can lead to <lb/>distinctive types of problems in cases of vestibular impairments. <lb/>These movement types include: <lb/>(a) gaze stabilization during passive and active head and body <lb/>movements, <lb/>(b) maintaining equilibrium: stable head on neck and body pos-<lb/>ture during immobility and movements, both passive and <lb/>active, <lb/>(c) relative movements among body parts (head on neck, point-<lb/>ing, touching parts of head and body), <lb/>(d) locomotion, <lb/>(e) interaction with the environment (pushing, reaching, catch-<lb/>ing, ducking/avoidance, etc.). <lb/>Impairment or late development of these functions would <lb/>also deprive the patient of the sensorimotor feedback informa-<lb/>tion generated by these movements. For example, infants without <lb/>otolith function learn to walk later than controls (Wiener-Vacher <lb/>et al., 2012b) and fall more frequently. This developmental deficit <lb/>means that they do not receive timely and coordinated visual and <lb/>proprioceptive feedback associated with stable walking -informa-<lb/>tion that would be vital for building spatial representations. An <lb/>infant with a vestibular deficit, who typically walks very cautiously <lb/>and attentively, seeking mechanical support and maintaining a <lb/>rigid neck, is not able to learn as much about spatial relation-<lb/>ships in the environment, and thus will have less opportunity to <lb/>build internal representations of space. For example, distances are <lb/>often calibrated in numbers of paces, but this is not feasible for <lb/>these patients. One theoretical framework of how cognitive rep-<lb/>resentations emerge in the brain contends that sensorimotor loop <lb/>activity is internally simulated and re-represented in the absence <lb/>of the relevant sensory inputs and movement. This would lead to <lb/>anticipatory processes and the construction of yet higher level rep-<lb/>resentations. Since vestibular dysfunction would impair the many <lb/>sensorimotor processes described in the previous paragraphs, seri-<lb/>ous consequences can be expected in building representations and <lb/>cognitive processing in the corresponding functional domains. <lb/>Before reviewing the literature relevant to the question of the <lb/>developmental consequences of vestibular impairments, it is nec-<lb/>essary to re-emphasize that the semicircular canals and otolith <lb/>organs respectively provide fundamentally different information. <lb/>In particular, only the otoliths are specialized for detecting the <lb/>direction of gravity force crucial for establishing vertical ori-<lb/>entation and thus defining spatial reference frames in concert <lb/>with the axes of the rotational selectivity of the semicircu-<lb/>lar canals. In the vast majority of the literature, the patients <lb/>groups described as &quot;vestibular impaired&quot; were tested for semi-<lb/>circular canal function only. Thus it is possible that residual <lb/>otolith organ function remained in some reportedly vestibular-<lb/>deficient patients -and that some reportedly normal controls <lb/>had functional canals but no otolithic responses. Even for exper-<lb/>imental subjects who have had surgical labyrinthectomies or <lb/>neurectomies, it is advisable to perform comprehensive vestibu-<lb/>lar testing to verify that there is no residual function. A <lb/>second issue is that patients show a great deal of variabil-<lb/>ity in their degree of compensation due to unequal access to <lb/>adapted training or therapeutic life experiences. It is possible <lb/>that individuals may differ in central compensation processes <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>-evidence has been found for increases in volume in bilateral <lb/>connections between the vestibular nuclei, in proprioceptive <lb/>processing area of right gracile nucleus and the visual motion <lb/>processing area MT/V5 (zu Eulenburg et al., 2010). Further-<lb/>more some may simply learn more effectively to substitute other <lb/>cues such as visual field flow, various types of proprioceptive <lb/>cues, visceral enteroception, visual landmark cues, and vari-<lb/>ous vertical/horizontal cues. These caveats should be recalled <lb/>in interpreting results from the literature and in planning new <lb/>experiments. <lb/>TYPES OF NAVIGATION PROCESSING <lb/>Orienting cues can be considered in two categories by virtue of <lb/>whether they transmit information about self-motion or about <lb/>environmental characteristics. Self-motion cues come from the <lb/>vestibular system, enteroceptors (located in the abdomen), motor <lb/>efferent collaterals related to locomotion and orienting move-<lb/>ments, proprioception countering gravitational forces and also <lb/>transmitting traction or slippage of paws or feet against the <lb/>substrate during locomotion. Although the vestibular system is <lb/>only sensitive to rotational or linear acceleration of the head, <lb/>the brain mathematically integrates these inputs over time first <lb/>to provide velocity signals, and then again to detect the angle <lb/>rotated and the linear distance covered. These integrations are <lb/>subject to drift errors and are generally not reliable for dis-<lb/>placements lasting longer than about 10 s, requiring regular <lb/>corrective updates, for example, by consulting with visual cues. <lb/>Studies of animals passively displaced then required to return <lb/>to their nest show that rotations are taken in account more <lb/>than translations (Etienne et al., 1988). Another important self-<lb/>motion signal comes from optic field flow. This is the coherent <lb/>movement of the image of the entire visual field relative to the <lb/>eyes during head movements and it indicates the velocity of <lb/>the head in space. While optic flow derives from visual detec-<lb/>tion of environmental cues, it cannot be accurately described <lb/>as &quot;allocentric.&quot; In vestibular rehabilitation therapy, patients <lb/>learn to substitute the various visual and proprioceptive cues <lb/>described above. Finally, information about the environmental <lb/>layout comes chiefly from visual perceptions of objects, audition, <lb/>and in certain species, magnetic sense, echolocation, and other <lb/>exotic senses. <lb/>Diverse types of navigation strategies engage distinct cognitive <lb/>processes (Trullier et al., 1997). Firstly, in dead reckoning, or path <lb/>integration, the initial starting point is noted. Then while travel-<lb/>ing, the velocity is integrated over time to compute the distances <lb/>covered. Angular heading during these displacements is taken into <lb/>account by vectorial addition yielding the total displacement as a <lb/>result (and reversing this gives the return vector). Principal sources <lb/>of information are the self-motion cues described above, including <lb/>the vestibular sense. Correct estimation of the duration of time is <lb/>clearly crucial for this integration (Israël et al., 2004). <lb/>The body alignment and target approaching navigation strategy, <lb/>also referred to as beacon homing, piloting, or approach/avoidance, <lb/>involves moving toward (or away from) a cue or object in the <lb/>environment. In the guidance strategy (as defined by O&apos;Keefe <lb/>and Nadel, 1978), the animal maintains a certain egocentric <lb/>relationship with respect to a particular landmark or object. A <lb/>vestibular patient with oscillopsia (continual oscillation of the <lb/>visual field) might be expected to have difficulty with this. <lb/>The next categories of navigation strategy are more advanced <lb/>since they can be used to reach a known but not currently visible <lb/>goal and involve identification of and orienting relative to places. <lb/>A place is defined within a large-scale environment as a set of con-<lb/>tiguous locations that are equivalent with regard to action selection <lb/>(Trullier et al., 1997). A place can also be defined as the set of loca-<lb/>tions from which a set of landmarks or a landmark configuration <lb/>is perceived as identical or very similar. Thus implicit to this is a <lb/>capacity to make generalizations. The term place navigation refers <lb/>here to navigation toward a specific location based on its spatial <lb/>relationship to a constellation of exteroceptive cues, particularly <lb/>distant background visual cues. Other strategies such as piloting or <lb/>vector-based navigation (Pearce et al., 1998) can be distinguished <lb/>from place navigation in that no single cue is sufficient for place <lb/>navigation. <lb/>Returning to the types of navigation processes, in place <lb/>recognition-triggered responses, the origin and intermediate places <lb/>along the route each have an associated angle of departure and <lb/>distance to go to the next place. Topological navigation involves <lb/>three steps: (a) recognizing the place where one is currently sit-<lb/>uated; (b) orienting within this place; and (c) selecting in which <lb/>direction to move so as to reach its current goal. It is not necessary <lb/>to plan a sequence of subsequent movements, but only to select <lb/>the very next action. Metric navigation implies a veridical internal <lb/>map that is consulted for making the most efficient changes in <lb/>position. <lb/>VESTIBULAR DYSFUNCTION AND DEFICITS IN COGNITIVE <lb/>FUNCTIONS INCLUDING NAVIGATION <lb/>Vision is a primary sensory modality in humans for detecting <lb/>size, shape, distance, and layout information. Static and dynamic <lb/>visual acuities are impaired by vestibular deficits. The ability to <lb/>maintain a stable visual image while the head is moving, such as <lb/>during walking, is dependent upon visual and vestibular inputs <lb/>triggering eye movements opposing and compensating for head <lb/>movements. When vestibular function is normal, visual acuity is <lb/>similar whether the head is moving or stationary. The difference in <lb/>static and dynamic visual acuity (DVA) can be quantified using the <lb/>DVA test (Schubert et al., 2006). Adults and children with vestibu-<lb/>lar deficits have impaired DVA (Rine and Braswell, 2003; Herdman <lb/>et al., 2007). Vestibular deficits are characterized by an absence of <lb/>the vestibulo-ocular response which maintains gaze fixed on a tar-<lb/>get when the head is passively moved suddenly in the direction of <lb/>sensitivity of a vestibular receptor end organ. This is the basis of <lb/>the commonly used clinical head impulse test (HIT) for detecting <lb/>vestibular deficits (Halmagyi et al., 1994). Subjects with complete <lb/>vestibular loss complain of oscillopsia during movements -this <lb/>makes them dizzy and disoriented when they walk, run, drive, <lb/>and read. Indeed, Braswell and Rine (2006) reported that children <lb/>with vestibular deficits have poor DVA results and this is associ-<lb/>ated with significant reduction in reading acuity. Smooth pursuit <lb/>oculomotor activity can compensate for head rotations up to a <lb/>velocity of 100 • /s. However, above this speed only the vestibular <lb/>system can detect and compensate for movements, and this range <lb/>of sensitivity is needed for many activities of daily life. Indeed, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>walking induces much low amplitude but high acceleration and <lb/>velocity vibration and shaking of the head (as apparent in a movie <lb/>taken from a camera carried on one&apos;s shoulder) and the vestibular <lb/>system permits this to be transformed to a smooth continuum. <lb/>In addition to problems related to vision, vestibular deficits can <lb/>lead directly to difficulties in estimating angular and distance dis-<lb/>placement, presumably through path integration. Beritoff (1965) <lb/>observed navigation deficits in children and in experimental ani-<lb/>mals with no detectable semicircular canal function. In cases where <lb/>the animals were familiar with a trajectory to a reward site, in <lb/>the absence of vision, they no longer were able to go directly to <lb/>the learned reward site. When vision was restored, they resumed <lb/>taking the direct path. Children aged 10-12 years old were blind-<lb/>folded, led or carried along a trajectory then along the return <lb/>path. They were able to retrace the steps, while blindfolded chil-<lb/>dren with non-functioning labyrinths could not, even after several <lb/>trials. This is one of the rare studies examining cognitive deficits <lb/>in vestibular-impaired children; the following text examines the <lb/>literature concerning adults. These studies show that vestibular <lb/>patients have difficulties in detecting and estimating body dis-<lb/>placements in the dark. During goal-directed locomotion, these <lb/>patients make errors in trajectory (e.g., Borel et al., 2004; Cohen <lb/>and Sangi-Haghpeykar, 2011). Another test where they have diffi-<lb/>culty is reversing the trajectory along a triangular path or finding <lb/>a shortcut (Péruch et al., 1999, 2005; Glasauer et al., 2002; Guidetti <lb/>et al., 2007; for review, see Israël and Warren, 2005). <lb/>In experiments evaluating dead reckoning, rats were required <lb/>to make return trips to a hidden start location under dark <lb/>conditions (Wallace and Whishaw, 2003). The peak velocity <lb/>was observed at the point midway of this return trajectory <lb/>and the direction of this trajectory was highly accurate, sug-<lb/>gesting the computation of both the distance and direction <lb/>to return to a target point of origin, consistent with dead <lb/>reckoning. In similar experiments this team also demonstrated <lb/>that dead reckoning is impaired after chemical labyrinthectomy <lb/>(Wallace et al., 2002). <lb/>A great deal of contemporary understanding of place naviga-<lb/>tion and its neurobiological bases has come from research using <lb/>the Morris water maze task (Morris, 1981, 1984; Sutherland and <lb/>Dyck, 1984). In this task, rodents (typically rats) learn to navigate <lb/>to an escape platform submerged in a circular pool of cool, opaque <lb/>water. Because the circular pool provides only information about <lb/>radial distance from the border, animals learn to navigate to the <lb/>escape platform by way of reference to a constellation of visual <lb/>cues outside the pool. <lb/>Over the past 15 years, several laboratories have utilized com-<lb/>puterized, virtual, navigation tasks based on the Morris water <lb/>task to measure place navigation in humans (Astur et al., 1998; <lb/>Jacobs et al., 1998; Hamilton and Sutherland, 1999; Doeller <lb/>and Burgess, 2008; Doeller et al., 2008; Mueller et al., 2008; <lb/>Hamilton et al., 2009). The participants view an environment <lb/>from a first-person perspective and &quot;swim&quot; in the virtual space <lb/>using a keyboard or joystick. As in the Morris water maze, the <lb/>environment contains distal visual cues and the subject must nav-<lb/>igate to a hidden goal. These tasks have been shown to both engage <lb/>(Cornwell et al., 2008; Doeller and Burgess, 2008) and require <lb/>an intact hippocampus (Astur et al., 2002; Driscoll et al., 2003; <lb/>Hanlon et al., 2006). The computerized virtual Morris water task <lb/>(VMWT) has been used to characterize spatial memory deficits <lb/>in patients with developmental disturbances (e.g., fetal alcohol <lb/>syndrome, Hamilton et al., 2003) and psychiatric disorders (e.g., <lb/>schizophrenia, Hanlon et al., 2006). Hartley et al. (2003) found <lb/>fMRI activation in the hippocampus of human subjects during <lb/>a virtual wayfinding task. Human subjects performing a virtual <lb/>task requiring them to point to the origin of a trajectory along <lb/>two sides of a triangular path also show increased activation of <lb/>the hippocampus (Wolbers et al., 2007). Caloric vestibular stim-<lb/>ulation activates the hippocampus in humans (Vitte et al., 1996). <lb/>Although the head is fixed and thus there are no vestibular sig-<lb/>nals that are generated or required for this task, the relationship <lb/>between vestibular function and performance has been exam-<lb/>ined in several studies (Schautzer et al., 2003; Brandt et al., 2005; <lb/>Hufner et al., 2007). Patients with bilateral vestibular failure are <lb/>impaired at finding the hidden platform, but perform as well as <lb/>matched controls in navigating to the platform when it is visible. <lb/>Navigation deficits were far more subtle in unilateral vestibular-<lb/>deficient patients, and only appeared in patients with right, but <lb/>not left, vestibular failure (Hufner et al., 2007). Structural analyses <lb/>via magnetic resonance imaging revealed that hippocampal vol-<lb/>umes were significantly decreased in bilateral vestibular patients <lb/>(Brandt et al., 2005), whereas major volumetric reductions in <lb/>unilateral patients were limited to gray matter reductions in <lb/>the cerebellum, temporal neocortex, thalamus, and area MT/V5 <lb/>(Hufner et al., 2009). <lb/>Vestibular patients are also impaired in object-based mental <lb/>transformations, another example of a cognitive task performed <lb/>with the head immobile and thus in the absence of self-movement <lb/>cues that would engage the vestibular system (Péruch et al., 2011) <lb/>The experimental groups were Menière&apos;s patients after unilateral <lb/>vestibular neurectomy, patients with bilateral vestibular damage <lb/>and normals. One task required mental rotation of 3D-objects <lb/>and two other tasks involved mental scanning and tested the <lb/>ability to construct and manipulate mental images with metric <lb/>properties. The authors reported variations in performance corre-<lb/>sponding to the level of vestibular loss. Bilateral vestibular patients <lb/>often had the worst results. The Menière&apos;s patients showed greater <lb/>deficits early after neurectomy and then gradually compensated. <lb/>This is of particular interest because it demonstrates a role for <lb/>vestibular signals in processing metric properties of mental rep-<lb/>resentations, supporting the hypothesis that high level processing <lb/>is in play. <lb/>It is fairly common for vestibular patients to have difficulty <lb/>detecting and estimating the magnitude of passive body displace-<lb/>ments in the dark. During goal-directed locomotion, these patients <lb/>usually make errors in executing the desired trajectory (e.g., Borel <lb/>et al., 2004; Brandt et al., 2005; Cohen and Sangi-Haghpeykar, <lb/>2011). Spatial disorientation is even stronger during complex tasks <lb/>such as reversing the trajectory along a triangular path or finding <lb/>a shortcut (Péruch et al., 1999, 2005; Glasauer et al., 2002; Guidetti <lb/>et al., 2007). Péruch et al. (1999) found that unilateral vestibular <lb/>loss impairs the orientation component (estimation of the angular <lb/>displacements) of navigation. The distance component (estima-<lb/>tion of the linear displacements) of the spatial representation is <lb/>also impaired, although to a lesser extent. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>Self-motion or optic field flow in the opposite direc-<lb/>tion can elicit comparable perceptual, motor, and neuro-<lb/>physiological responses. Convergence of visual field flow and <lb/>vestibular inputs have been observed in many structures includ-<lb/>ing the vestibular nuclei (Xerri et al., 1988), vestibular area 2v <lb/>(Büttner and Buettner, 1978) and the parieto-insular vestibular <lb/>cortex (Grüsser et al., 1990). <lb/>Hanes and McCollum (2006) identified cognitive deficits asso-<lb/>ciated with vestibular dysfunction including short-term memory, <lb/>concentration, arithmetic, and reading. For example, patients with <lb/>central vestibular lesions required to count backward by twos make <lb/>more errors and are slower than controls. This was interpreted <lb/>as resulting from &quot;spatialization&quot; of the task, perhaps in terms of <lb/>number line representation. Performance impairments can be cat-<lb/>egorized as direct, that is, tasks that implicitly or explicitly require <lb/>using information about the 3D structure of space and movements <lb/>(such as navigation and spatial memory). This also includes the use <lb/>of spatial strategies in non-spatial domains. Of particular interest <lb/>here is that a common strategy of skilled mnemonists is to employ <lb/>mental imagery of places and signs to situate information to be <lb/>memorized. It would then follow that spatial cognitive deficits <lb/>could limit the capacities of patients for this type of memorization <lb/>skill. <lb/>Indirect effects of vestibular deficits on cognition derive from <lb/>the greater demand on attentional and cognitive processing <lb/>resources at the expense of other ongoing activities (Smith et al., <lb/>2005b). For example, the lack of vestibular information requires <lb/>the sometimes effortful substitution of visual, proprioceptive, and <lb/>other signals in order to maintain balance, posture, and gaze. <lb/>Visuospatial processing is also more difficult. This reduces atten-<lb/>tion, limits concentration and could tie up mental processing <lb/>resources, impairing other activities such as multi-tasking, pro-<lb/>cessing sequences, and attention-shifting. Patients could thus have <lb/>difficulty organizing multiple sources of information, in particu-<lb/>lar integrating new information while retaining previous items <lb/>in memory -this could impair problem solving and conflict res-<lb/>olution. All of these are important for spatial orientation and <lb/>navigation. For example, routes are often schematized in terms of <lb/>sequences of intermediate goals and the associated trajectories to <lb/>be followed to the next intermediate goal. <lb/>Note also that vestibular deficits often report sensations such <lb/>as vertigo, disorientation, discomfort with repeated peripheral <lb/>patterns during movement, etc. These then are associated with <lb/>psychiatric problems such as agoraphobia (such environments <lb/>provide troubling cue conflicts), excessive fatigue, depression, and <lb/>anxiety. Overall, these all can lead to indirect negative impacts on <lb/>measures of spatial and non-spatial cognitive processing. <lb/>PROCESSING OF VESTIBULAR SIGNALS FOR SPATIAL <lb/>REPRESENTATIONS IN THE HIPPOCAMPAL SYSTEM <lb/>Head direction (HD) cells fire when the head of the rat (or mouse, <lb/>or chinchilla) is oriented in a particular direction in the yaw <lb/>plane, regardless of its position in the environment (Ranck, 1986; <lb/>Taube et al., 1990; Muir et al., 2009; Yoder and Taube, 2009). HD <lb/>responses are found in all of the brain areas designated as the Papez <lb/>circuit, running from the brainstem to the hippocampus. The sig-<lb/>nals are generated in the brainstem lateral mammillary nucleus and <lb/>dorsal tegmental nucleus (DTN) of Guddens which receives inputs <lb/>from the vestibular nuclei (Bassett and Taube, 2005). Although <lb/>the direction responses are anchored by background visual cues <lb/>(likely distinguished by motion parallax; Zugaro et al., 2001) and <lb/>are influenced by optic flow stimuli (Arleo et al., 2013), they remain <lb/>selective for direction in darkness (e.g., Yoder and Taube, 2009). <lb/>Stackman and Taube (1997) injected sodium arsanilate in the <lb/>vestibular end-organs of rats, and this abolished the directional <lb/>responses in the anterodorsal thalamus. Yoder and Taube (2009) <lb/>studied HD cells in a mouse strain with nearly complete absence <lb/>of otoconia and hence minimal otolith function. HD cells were <lb/>observed but signals were more weakly controlled by visual land-<lb/>mark cues, and responses degraded over successive trials and were <lb/>unstable in darkness. <lb/>Principal neurons of the hippocampus discharge selectively <lb/>as the rat, mouse, or human occupies a particular position in <lb/>its real or virtual environment (O&apos;Keefe and Dostrovsky, 1971; <lb/>Ekstrom et al., 2003; Chen et al., 2013). This activity is considered <lb/>to participate in an internal representation of the environment <lb/>(O&apos;Keefe and Nadel, 1978). Indeed, during immobile pauses <lb/>prior to locomotion, these cells fire in rapid sequences corre-<lb/>sponding to the imminent trajectory the rat is about to take <lb/>(Pfeiffer and Foster, 2013). Vestibular lesions suppress these place <lb/>responses (Stackman et al., 2002; Russell et al., 2003a) and cause <lb/>other changes in hippocampal physiology (Smith et al., 2005a; <lb/>Russell et al., 2006). Furthermore, rats with hippocampal lesions <lb/>are impaired in orienting to a goal after being passively rotated <lb/>(Mathews et al., 1989) and in spatial learning (Russell et al., 2003b). <lb/>Place learning in the Morris water task critically depends upon <lb/>intact circuitry upstream of the vestibular organs leading to hip-<lb/>pocampus (and involved in the generation of HD cell signals; <lb/>Vann et al., 2003; Clark and Taube, 2009; Clark et al., 2013) as <lb/>well as the hippocampus itself and related structures (Morris <lb/>et al., 1982; Sutherland et al., 1982). These patterns of damage <lb/>can leave other forms of navigation, such as cued navigation, <lb/>unimpaired. <lb/>Comparisons of place responses in hippocampal neurons of <lb/>rats before and after rotation of the experimental arena in <lb/>darkness revealed that a subset of neurons maintained their fir-<lb/>ing fields at the same position in absolute space, rather than <lb/>rotating with the apparatus (Wiener et al., 1995). This was inter-<lb/>preted to indicate that the brain had detected the angle of <lb/>rotation, perhaps via the horizontal semicircular canals, then <lb/>compensated for it by stabilizing the hippocampal position rep-<lb/>resentation. Since proprioceptive cues may have also played a <lb/>role in this, a new experiment was devised where the head <lb/>of the rat was immobilized, its body suspended in a ham-<lb/>mock (with the leg protruding through holes), and passively <lb/>displaced on a mobile robot (Gavrilov et al., 1998). Hippocam-<lb/>pal place responses were recorded under light conditions, and <lb/>they persisted in complete darkness. This provided further, and <lb/>more direct support for vestibular updating of hippocampal <lb/>spatial representations. In this same experimental protocol, pas-<lb/>sive rotations in the dark synchronized hippocampal local field <lb/>potentials to rhythmically oscillate at 8 Hz, the &quot;theta&quot; rhythm, <lb/>which is associated with locomotion and active exploration <lb/>(Gavrilov et al., 1996). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | </note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>During locomotion in an open field, hippocampal responses <lb/>in a given place are the same regardless of the orientation of the <lb/>head, and hence the view perceived by the rat, which is a form of <lb/>abstraction (Wiener, 1996). This suggests that there is a memory <lb/>process associating the successive multiple views to produce the <lb/>same cellular response, presumably reflecting a single coherent <lb/>representation. One way for the brain to detect that the head is in a <lb/>certain place would be to compute the distances and angular head-<lb/>ings of at least two environmental landmarks. This would require <lb/>simultaneous storage and comparison of this information, impli-<lb/>cating working memory and multi-tasking, processes associated <lb/>with the hippocampal-prefrontal cortex pathway. Since vestibular <lb/>lesions abolish place cell activity and induce hippocampal atrophy, <lb/>perhaps these losses could also impair these processes as well as <lb/>affecting memory in spatial and non-spatial domains as observed <lb/>after hippocampal lesions. <lb/>Grid cells of the entorhinal cortex (situated in the pathway from <lb/>the HD system to the hippocampus) discharge as a rat occupies <lb/>places that are distributed along the nodes of a hexagonal grid <lb/>within its environment (Moser et al., 2008). Thus these neurons <lb/>provide a coordinate reference frame for navigation. No study <lb/>has yet tested the effects of vestibular lesions on grid cells. How-<lb/>ever, computational models of grid cells require head orientation <lb/>input -and HD cells are also found in entorhinal cortex. This, and <lb/>the additional computational requirement for self-displacement <lb/>signals, indicates that vestibular signals would also be required for <lb/>grid cell activity. <lb/>If vestibular-deficient patients do not have place, HD or <lb/>grid responses in their hippocampal system, this would deprive <lb/>them of valuable spatial signal processing and representation <lb/>capacities. Furthermore, the absence of these signals during devel-<lb/>opment could impair the construction of circuits underlying <lb/>orientation and navigation behaviors, and perhaps other cog-<lb/>nitive functions that these areas contribute to as well. Indeed, <lb/>eventual hippocampus mis-wiring in the absence of vestibu-<lb/>lar inputs could also have an impact on non-spatial cognitive <lb/>processing (Wiener, 1996) by this structure as well and on sig-<lb/>naling to downstream structures like prefrontal cortex and ventral <lb/>striatum. <lb/>DEVELOPMENT OF BRAIN REPRESENTATIONS OF THE <lb/>ENVIRONMENT AND ORIENTATION CAPACITIES IN RATS <lb/>During the first few weeks of postnatal life the navigational capac-<lb/>ities of the rat and other rodents develops rapidly. Rat pups first <lb/>venture out of the nest around postnatal days (PD) 10-11 (Bolles <lb/>and Woods, 1964) and rapidly increase explorations there around <lb/>PD 16-19 (Alberts and Leimbach, 1980). (Rat pups first open their <lb/>eyes on PD 15, the same age that they start to walk while bearing <lb/>the body weight). These exploratory trips appear to be directed <lb/>not only by internal motivational cues and biologically significant <lb/>proximal cues (e.g., heat sources) but also to acquire informa-<lb/>tion about distal visual cues (Loewen et al., 2005). During this <lb/>period the circuitry of the hippocampus and related structures <lb/>also undergo significant structural and functional development <lb/>(Bachevalier and Beauregard, 1993; Dumas, 2005). It is generally <lb/>believed that maturation of the hippocampus is delayed compared <lb/>to other brain regions, rendering rats incapable of performing <lb/>hippocampal dependent tasks until at least PD 19-25 (Bachevalier <lb/>and Beauregard, 1993; Stanton, 2000; Dumas, 2005). A growing <lb/>body of data from studies investigating the ability of young rats <lb/>to navigate, however, suggests that the neural systems involved in <lb/>navigation may be functional even earlier than this. Of particu-<lb/>lar interest are studies examining the ontogeny of spatial firing <lb/>characteristics of neurons in the hippocampus and related brain <lb/>regions implicated in spatial navigation and memory. Langston <lb/>et al. (2010) reported that the activity of HD cells in the pre-or <lb/>parasubiculum of preweanling rats displayed adult-like properties <lb/>at PD 15-16 and the proportion of HD cells was similar to that <lb/>of the adult animal. Although hippocampal place cells displayed <lb/>spatially selective firing and medial entorhinal grid cells displayed <lb/>their characteristic spatially periodic firing shortly thereafter (PD <lb/>16-18), the spatial firing patterns of these cells either continued to <lb/>become more precise and mature and the proportion of responsive <lb/>cells continued to increase toward adult levels over the next 10-17 <lb/>days (Langston et al., 2010; but see Wills et al., 2010, 2012). Over-<lb/>all, these observations suggest a primacy of directional processing <lb/>by HD cells, which is followed by the maturation of place and <lb/>grid cell signals, respectively (Ainge and Langston, 2012). If hip-<lb/>pocampal place cells and the directional tuning observed in some <lb/>grid cells depend upon HD cells (Knierim and Hamilton, 2011), it <lb/>is perhaps not surprising that HD cells also mature earlier. These <lb/>considerations would lead to the expectation that behaviors guided <lb/>by orientation signals provided HD cells should emerge earlier in <lb/>development than more complicated cognitive functions such as <lb/>place navigation (Ainge and Langston, 2012). <lb/>Akers et al. (2011) adapted the Morris water task in order to <lb/>develop a more sensitive assessment of control of navigation by <lb/>distal visual cues. Prior work from this group examined the effects <lb/>of translating the pool to another overlapping position in the room <lb/>with salient visual cues on the walls (i.e., shifting it within the dis-<lb/>tal cue reference frame). The rats were first trained to navigate to <lb/>a hidden platform, the pool was displaced in the room, and the <lb/>rats could swim either to the same precise location in the room <lb/>where the platform was previously located or to navigate toward <lb/>the previous location relative to the pool border, respecting its <lb/>orientation relative to the room cues (Hamilton et al., 2007, 2008, <lb/>2009). The rats chose the latter, suggesting that the distal cues <lb/>can be engaged for orientation information while precise spatial <lb/>location is based on the local frame of reference (the pool border). <lb/>The possible outcomes of the translation test described above were <lb/>recently dissociated by Stackman et al. (2012) in the mouse. Fol-<lb/>lowing training these authors pharmacologically inactivated either <lb/>the anterodorsal thalamus or CA1 subfield of the hippocampus <lb/>prior to the translation test. Mice with CA1 inactivation navigated <lb/>to the relative location relative to the pool, whereas mice with <lb/>thalamic inactivation preferred the location in the room, support-<lb/>ing the contention that navigation based on orientation relative to <lb/>distal room cues depends on thalamic HD cells. <lb/>Hamilton et al. (2007) also trained rats to navigate to a cued <lb/>platform (i.e., marked by a conspicuous visual cues) in the same <lb/>distal room environment as used in the hidden platform task. After <lb/>the rats mastered performance the pool was translated while the <lb/>cued platform either remained in the same location relative to the <lb/>room cues or the same location relative to the pool border. The rats <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>succeeded at the latter, but surprisingly, when the cued platform <lb/>was placed in the same precise location relative to the room cues, <lb/>but in a different part of the pool, the rats first navigated in the <lb/>direction of the platform&apos;s previous position relative to the pool <lb/>walls (respecting the orientation of the room) before correcting <lb/>course to the cued platform. Thus they initially ignored the cues <lb/>co-localized with the platform, and instead relied on the pool bor-<lb/>der in relation to the room orientation, suggesting a priority for <lb/>this type of navigation strategy at the expense of beacon utilization. <lb/>These observations provide further evidence that distal cues can <lb/>control orientation independently of processes that would deter-<lb/>mine precise spatial localization, and are consistent with previous <lb/>work by the same group showing that the initial orientation of <lb/>swim trajectories to a cued platform in the water task are con-<lb/>trolled by distal room cues, whereas the proximal cue co-localized <lb/>with the platform guided subsequent navigation (Hamilton et al., <lb/>2004). Interestingly, this dissociation was hinted at by the fact that <lb/>rats tended to engage in head-scanning behavior after navigating a <lb/>short distance from the release point. Further manipulations such <lb/>as changing room cues or relocating the cued platform revealed <lb/>that these head-scanning behaviors marked the transition between <lb/>control by distal room cues and control by the proximal cue. <lb/>Recently, Clark et al. (2013) demonstrated that lesions of the <lb/>DTN (part of the brainstem circuit processing vestibular signals to <lb/>generate HD cell activity) dramatically impair the engagement of <lb/>distal cues in this Morris water task. Using the cued navigation task <lb/>described above these authors demonstrated that rats with DTN <lb/>lesions directly to the cued platform regardless of its position in <lb/>the room and pool during the translation test. Akers et al. (2011) <lb/>also utilized this variant of the task to examine the developmen-<lb/>tal trajectory of orientation control by distal cues. Interestingly, <lb/>rats at PD 16 showed no significant difference in latencies to the <lb/>cued platform whether it was in the same location in the pool or <lb/>room, whereas all rats PD 17 or older displayed the adult pattern <lb/>of outcomes, first erroneously swimming to the previous posi-<lb/>tion relative to the pool walls, as guided by its orientation relative <lb/>to the room. Most studies indicate that the emergence of place <lb/>navigation in rats begins between PD 20-22 (review: Akers and <lb/>Hamilton, 2007) which is generally taken to reflect the matura-<lb/>tion of the hippocampus, supported by upstream sensory and <lb/>cognitive systems involved in navigation. The observations of <lb/>Akers et al. (2011) are consistent with the hypothesis that distal <lb/>cues control orientation, but not precise position, very early in <lb/>development, at the same time that HD cells are maturing func-<lb/>tionally, prior to the appearance of mature place cell and grid cell <lb/>responses. <lb/>HIPPOCAMPAL DEVELOPMENT IN CHILDREN <lb/>Knickmeyer et al. (2008) reported a 13% increase of hippocampal <lb/>volume from the ages of 1 to 2 years (but relatively little growth <lb/>could be seen after it was normalized for total brain volume). <lb/>Giedd et al. (1996) found that right hippocampus growth (nor-<lb/>malized with respect to cerebral volume) correlated with age only <lb/>in females, and that the left hippocampus did not increase with <lb/>age between 4 to 18 years in males, or females. Uematsu et al. <lb/>(2012) employed a cubic regression to chart the developmental <lb/>trajectories of hippocampal regions. Their data show increases in <lb/>hippocampal volume during the first 6-7 years of life, with a peak <lb/>at about the age of 10-11. Gogtay et al. (2006) performed a volu-<lb/>metric study of MRI scans from humans aged from 4 to 25. They <lb/>observed that total hippocampal volume does not change over this <lb/>period although there are regional variations. Concerning connec-<lb/>tivity, Ábrahám et al. (2010) showed that myelination progresses <lb/>differently in hippocampal subregions, reaching adult levels in <lb/>fimbria-fornix, stratum lacunosum-moleculare and alveus at 3 <lb/>years of age, stratum radiatum of CA3 and all of stratum oriens at <lb/>8 years, but not the stratum radiatum of CA1, pyramidal cell layer <lb/>of all subregions and the hilus. Even at the age of 11, myelinization <lb/>was not complete in the hilus. An adult-like pattern of calbindin <lb/>immunoreactivity can be observed at 11 years of age. <lb/>All of these data show periods when growth is taking place and <lb/>is completed, but do not reveal when the networks are functional, <lb/>which may occur somewhere within these periods. Even if a par-<lb/>ticular network arrives at maturity in the absence of vestibular <lb/>inputs, the hippocampus is a highly plastic structure and would <lb/>be expected to integrate substitutive inputs easily. However, the <lb/>hippocampal atrophy in adult neurectomy patients would suggest <lb/>that the absence of vestibular input in childhood would also impair <lb/>hippocampal development. This could have different impacts at <lb/>the respective ages. The data presented above suggests that differ-<lb/>ent types of growth and maturation are occurring in the periods <lb/>up to age 2-3, then leading up to 6-8, and then up to the age of 11 <lb/>where adult-like characteristics appear. <lb/>ONTOGENESIS OF SPATIAL NAVIGATION AND ORIENTATION <lb/>IN CHILDREN <lb/>Several laboratories have examined the development of place nav-<lb/>igation and related processes in young children, controlling and <lb/>distinguishing from other simpler behaviors such as cued navi-<lb/>gation. Lehnung et al. (1998) tested children in a 3.6-m diameter <lb/>circular area closed off with curtains. Under dim lighting condi-<lb/>tions, points on the floor were marked with lit fiberglass wires. <lb/>The child had to first explore the group of points to find those <lb/>selected as rewarded sites for that day, and then return and find <lb/>them again. Both proximal cues on the floor (teddy bear, etc.) and <lb/>wall cues were present. Various controls and experimental condi-<lb/>tions were tested. While 5-year-olds employed the proximal cues, <lb/>the 10-year-olds were able to use distal or proximal cues for orien-<lb/>tation. Seven-year-olds were at a transition point, where half used <lb/>only proximal cues, while the other half could use both cue types. <lb/>Overman et al. (1996) tested children in large real world envi-<lb/>ronments, including a radial arm maze, a &quot;dry Morris water maze&quot; <lb/>0.9 m high and 3.6 m in diameter filled with plastic packing chips <lb/>and a large 61 m circle in an outdoor playing field. In the radial <lb/>arm maze, where each arm was rewarded only once per trial, chil-<lb/>dren under 5 years old were impaired in both cued and non-cued <lb/>versions when eight arms were used, showing spatial working <lb/>memory performance inferior to older children and adults. (With <lb/>only four arms open in the maze, these children succeeded at <lb/>performing at adult levels however). When confronted with four <lb/>forced choice trials, then, after a short delay, they were required to <lb/>go to the remaining arms, the children under 5 years old performed <lb/>at chance levels, 6-to 10-year-olds performed better, but only 20% <lb/>of the latter achieved adult performance in this place learning task. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>In the dry Morris water maze, performance in finding the hidden <lb/>&quot;treasure chest&quot; progressively improved among subjects until the <lb/>age of 7 years. And only those children above the age of 8 years <lb/>could localize the reward on a scale model of the maze. In the field <lb/>the subjects were shown a goal location, blindfolded and driven <lb/>along a circuitous route inside the circle, then asked to return to <lb/>it. Performance improved in children 7 years and above, with 9-<lb/>year-olds and older performing as well as adults. This is consistent <lb/>with observations that 10-year-old children can resolve large-scale <lb/>navigation tasks, but not 3-to 4-year-olds (Acredolo, 1976). <lb/>Virtual navigation tasks were developed as analogs of behav-<lb/>ioral protocols used with rodents, and it is notable that many <lb/>aspects of control of these tasks by spatial and non-spatial cues <lb/>are similar across species. In cue competition experiments rats <lb/>and humans display similar patterns of responses to removal of <lb/>distal visual cues (e.g., Hamilton and Sutherland, 1999; Red-<lb/>head and Hamilton, 2009). When the local apparatus is displaced <lb/>in the same room after training both animal and human vir-<lb/>tual navigation experiments suggest that distal cues control the <lb/>directionality of navigation within the local apparatus (i.e., the <lb/>pool). This too provides evidence for a fundamental simi-<lb/>larity in how distal cues control navigation in the respective <lb/>tasks. Thus it has been argued that parallel studies in humans <lb/>and non-human animals could provide important information <lb/>at multiple levels of analysis about the neurobehavioral rela-<lb/>tionships involved in place navigation and the development of <lb/>these relationships. Interestingly, there are notable parallels in <lb/>the development of spatial navigation abilities in rodents and <lb/>humans in the respective tasks. Using a VMWT, Hoesing et al. <lb/>(2000) found that children younger than age 7 did not reli-<lb/>ably use a place navigation strategy to solve the VMWT but <lb/>rather relied on various types of other strategies (e.g., circling <lb/>a particular distance from the pool wall until the platform was <lb/>encountered, randomly searching the pool). However, the pat-<lb/>tern of successful performance by prepubertal children above age <lb/>7 (Hoesing et al., 2000) and post-pubertal adolescents (Hamil-<lb/>ton et al., 2003) are comparable to that observed in adults <lb/>(e.g., Hamilton et al., 2009) in that they learn to execute direct <lb/>trajectories from multiple release points and persisted in search-<lb/>ing at the target location during a probe trial with no escape <lb/>platform. <lb/>Newcombe et al. (1998) found that from the age of 22 months, <lb/>infants benefit from the use of the relations between distal cues <lb/>to find a toy they had seen buried in a sand box. The children&apos;s <lb/>gaze at the site was interrupted and they started searching from <lb/>a different point on the periphery. Ribordy et al. (2013) studied <lb/>children aged from 2 to 5 years searching for rewards beneath an <lb/>array of cups distributed in an open field arena 4 m × 4 m sur-<lb/>rounded by opaque plastic walls on three sides. At 25-39 months <lb/>of age, the infants could locate one rewarded cup out of the four <lb/>presented (a simplified version of the task), albeit in the absence <lb/>of local cues. However, 18-to 23-month-old infants were inca-<lb/>pable of this. Thus both studies concur that near the age of 2 years <lb/>capacities emerge for localization relative to distal cue configura-<lb/>tions. Ribordy et al. (2013) point out that the age of 2 also marks <lb/>the beginning of autobiographical memory as well as when the <lb/>hippocampus reaches a certain state of maturity. <lb/>In summary, these studies suggest that there are at least two <lb/>periods in development when new spatial skills appear. At the <lb/>age of 2, infants are capable of rudimentary spatial localization <lb/>(Ribordy et al., 2013), while capacity for place navigation emerges <lb/>around 6-7 years of age in the Overman et al. (1996) and Hoesing <lb/>et al. (2000) studies, and at the age of 11, adult performance <lb/>appears. This is remarkably concordant with the three ages which <lb/>mark milestones in hippocampal volume increase and myelination <lb/>as noted in the previous section. Nevertheless, the interpretation <lb/>of the coincidences of crucial ages in these developmental studies <lb/>is clouded by the occurrence of other interrelated events at these <lb/>ages. For example, at the age of 2, infants have recently gained mas-<lb/>tery of independent walking and exploration, and this too might <lb/>help elaborate spatial representations and promote hippocampal <lb/>development. <lb/>Further advances could be made measuring performance in <lb/>specific types of navigational processing using virtual environ-<lb/>ments such as the VMWT. Manipulations such as the combined <lb/>cued navigation and pool translation in the VMWT permit to dis-<lb/>tinguish different ways of using distal visual cues for orientation <lb/>alone or precise localization -processes that may be differen-<lb/>tially affected by loss of vestibular function before or after key <lb/>ages. Thus such approaches may prove useful in characterizing the <lb/>effects of damage to the vestibular system on subsequent devel-<lb/>opment of spatial navigation abilities. Importantly, because tasks <lb/>of this type are administered via a computer program and inter-<lb/>face experimental conditions can be controlled precisely, and can <lb/>also be easily coupled with measures of functional brain activ-<lb/>ity (Cornwell et al., 2008), they will likely play an important role <lb/>in further advancing our understanding of the behavioral con-<lb/>sequences of early vestibular damage and their neurobiological <lb/>bases. <lb/>CRITICAL PERIODS <lb/>Rieser et al. (1986) compared sighted with blind adults who had <lb/>lost vision early or late in life and had similar performance in <lb/>evaluating perspective from an imaginary new observation point. <lb/>When subjects walked without vision to the new point, pointing <lb/>performance improved in the sighted and late-blinded subjects <lb/>but not those of the early-blinded subjects. This suggests that <lb/>early absence of vision leads to different types of representations <lb/>of space. While there is a great variety in the performance levels <lb/>of early blind vs late blind subjects, there seems to be a tendency <lb/>for the former to employ route strategies while the latter engage <lb/>mapping for navigation tasks (Thinus-Blanc and Gaunet, 1997). <lb/>The concept of critical period has been well developed for visual <lb/>system ontogenesis (Imbert and Buisseret, 1975). Since multiple <lb/>brain systems are respectively implicated in complementary ori-<lb/>entation and navigational processing and they mature at different <lb/>times, accurate vestibular signals at these times would be neces-<lb/>sary for timely development. Critical periods for vestibular inputs <lb/>would thus exist for each respective type of spatial processing. <lb/>POSSIBLE MECHANISMS FOR VESTIBULAR DEFICITS <lb/>LEADING TO COGNITIVE IMPAIRMENTS <lb/>Vestibular deficits could lead to diverse and distinct types of prob-<lb/>lems in cognitive processing problems with different respective <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>underlying mechanisms. We showed (Wiener-Vacher et al., 2012b) <lb/>that posturomotor control is delayed after a sudden complete <lb/>vestibular loss due to meningitis before the age of independent <lb/>walking. This led to long-lasting posturomotor instability in the <lb/>absence of any neurological impairment. We suggested that the <lb/>oscillopsia resulting from a complete lack of vestibular informa-<lb/>tion in these children leads to dynamic and head-trunk instability. <lb/>This could then contribute to secondary delays in learning pro-<lb/>cesses (reading, writing, fine motor control) as well as building <lb/>coherent representations of the body as well as its position rela-<lb/>tive to surrounding space. Much remains to be learned about the <lb/>impact of complete or partial vestibular loss at different ages in <lb/>children on the development posturomotor and fine motor con-<lb/>trol, oculomotor control in cognitive activities (reading, writing), <lb/>spatial orientation, and body representation. <lb/>The absence of vestibular inputs to the hippocampus would <lb/>lead to failure to establish normal brain representations of the <lb/>body in space. A consequence of this would be difficulties in <lb/>understanding spatial relations of environmental features. How-<lb/>ever, the resulting hippocampal atrophy could have a negative <lb/>impact on other processes as well, like memory, context-dependent <lb/>behaviors and relational reasoning. Another problem would derive <lb/>from vestibular impairments leading to incomplete and impre-<lb/>cise sensorimotor feedback loops of many varieties. This would <lb/>not be limited to activities involving head movements, since head <lb/>immobility would be detected with lower certainty too. During <lb/>development infants make myriad movements, and when the <lb/>brain detects their outcomes, it can make corrections to refine <lb/>sensorimotor coordination and build representations. Objects <lb/>in three-dimensional space are understood not simply by their <lb/>visual profile, but by how they feel, how they change appear-<lb/>ance when manually rotated or when one walks around them, <lb/>their weight, inertial and dynamic properties. Vestibular-impaired <lb/>children&apos;s problems with the gravity sense, the sense of orienta-<lb/>tion, awareness of the relations among one&apos;s body parts and the <lb/>distinction of self-movement from object movement could lead <lb/>to impairments in their acquisition of knowledge through such <lb/>sensorimotor feedback and interactive behavior. Another type of <lb/>problem is related to absent or incomplete gravitational infor-<lb/>mation which can lead not only to balance problems, but also to <lb/>inaccurate compensation for gravitational forces on the body parts <lb/>and environmental objects, particularly during movement. It has <lb/>been demonstrated that the brain elaborates models of visually <lb/>observed movement dynamics that distinguish those modulated <lb/>by gravitational force (i.e., linear acceleration at 9.8 m/s 2 ) from <lb/>others (Zago and Lacquaniti, 2005). Other cognitive representa-<lb/>tions may also be built up from cerebral simulation of concordant <lb/>sensorimotor loop activation experience, for example, mentally <lb/>replaying walking through an environment could help build brain <lb/>representations of that environment. Whether such experience <lb/>is limited by choice (by a child who moves about and explores <lb/>less frequently and less freely to avoid instable or disturbing <lb/>situations) or by the incomplete nature of the sensory return <lb/>information, this would nonetheless lead to poor spatial repre-<lb/>sentations. Other sensory inputs can also be compromised in <lb/>cases of vestibular deficits. For example, unstable gaze (in par-<lb/>ticular patients with spontaneous nystagmus) would impair visual <lb/>perception and hence visual feedback from movements. Again <lb/>the failure to distinguish visual field movements due to self or <lb/>environmental features could have dramatic consequences. Many <lb/>vestibular patients also suffer from partial or complete auditory <lb/>deficits, which would impair access to echoes and ambient sound <lb/>which also provide information about position and environmental <lb/>structure. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>Our hypothesis is that an absence of vestibular information early in <lb/>life can lead to reduced cognitive performance in several domains, <lb/>as well as altered spatial cognitive representations (compared to <lb/>children with no such vestibular deficit). This would persist a long <lb/>time after vestibular compensation in the absence of appropriate <lb/>therapy. The argument can be summarized as follows: the impor-<lb/>tance of the hippocampal system in spatial and other cognitive <lb/>processing is supported by a vast experimental and neurological <lb/>literature. Particularly striking evidence comes from neurophys-<lb/>iological recordings of place cell, HD cell and grid activity in <lb/>rodents, activation of the hippocampus during virtual naviga-<lb/>tion in humans, and others. Theoretical arguments were advanced <lb/>here for the roles of vestibular signals in building spatial reference <lb/>frames and updating spatial representations. This is motivated by <lb/>the observations that vestibular inactivation leads to the loss of HD <lb/>and place cell activities as well as hippocampal atrophy and navi-<lb/>gation deficits. Finally, the data on the ontogenesis of navigation <lb/>behavior and hippocampal development converged remarkably <lb/>on milestones at the ages of 2, 7, and 11. This leads to a refine-<lb/>ment of our hypothesis wherein the onset of vestibular dysfunction <lb/>prior to these milestones will delay the normal development of <lb/>corresponding cognitive functions, and possibly lead to specific <lb/>period-dependent changes in hippocampal structure and func-<lb/>tion. These may prove difficult to detect behaviorally because of <lb/>rapid compensation of partial vestibular deficits, the high degree of <lb/>plasticity that characterizes the hippocampal system, and variabil-<lb/>ity among patients in their experiences learning to substitute other <lb/>sensory modalities for the missing vestibular inputs. Nonetheless <lb/>we predict that specific cognitive deficits will be detectable in at <lb/>least a subpopulation of patients who lost vestibular function prior <lb/>to the respective ages of 2, 7, and 11. One interesting question <lb/>concerns the respective contributions of otolith and semicircu-<lb/>lar canal inputs for achieving these milestones. This knowledge <lb/>would then lead to adapted therapies to help recover from these <lb/>deficits. <lb/>In general, the issue of cognitive impact of deprivation of <lb/>vestibular signal in children should have important consequences <lb/>in patient care. Screening for vestibular loss should be done <lb/>routinely in deaf children or in children with psychomotor devel-<lb/>opmental delays, who are often misdiagnosed as neurologically <lb/>impaired or &quot;slow.&quot; Every effort should be made to avoid aggravat-<lb/>ing vestibular loss, for example, detect residual vestibular function <lb/>prior to cochlear implantation in young patients and planning <lb/>surgeries accordingly (Jacot et al., 2009). It is important to con-<lb/>trol for the possible effects of hearing impairment that are often <lb/>associated with vestibular deficits. For example, vestibular deficits <lb/>may impact on reading performance and further compromise <lb/>language skills beyond impairments due to hearing loss. These <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | </note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<body>screening tests must be comprehensive, including otolith testing <lb/>which can now be performed easily, reliably, and relatively inex-<lb/>pensively via vestibular evoked myogenic potentials (VEMP; Jacot <lb/>and Wiener-Vacher, 2008). While the caloric test remains a staple <lb/>of the vestibulometry clinical battery, it is insensitive to otolith <lb/>function, which we argue to be essential for establishing spatial <lb/>reference frames. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>During preparation of this manuscript, Derek A. Hamilton was <lb/>funded by NIH grant AA019462 and the Quad-L foundation, <lb/>Sidney I. Wiener was funded by French Agence National pour <lb/>la Recherche grant number: ANR-10-BLAN-02 (Neurobot) and <lb/>Sylvette R. Wiener-Vacher was funded by a PHRC Regional grant <lb/>of the Assistance Publique-Hôpitaux de Paris. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>Each author wrote substantial portions of the text and all edited <lb/>the entire manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Ábrahám, H., Vincze, A., Jewgenow, I., Veszprémi, B., Kravják, A., Gömöri, E., et al. <lb/>(2010). Myelination in the human hippocampal formation from midgestation to <lb/>adulthood. Int. J. Dev. Neurosci. 28, 401-410. doi: 10.1016/j.ijdevneu.2010.03.004 <lb/>Acredolo, L. P. (1976). &quot;Frames of reference used by children for orientation in <lb/>unfamiliar spaces,&quot; in Environmental Knowing, eds G. T. Moore and R. Golledge <lb/>(Stroudsburg, PA: Dowden, Hutchinson, and Ross), 165-172. <lb/>Ainge, J. A., and Langston, R. F. (2012). Ontogeny of neural circuits underlying spa-<lb/>tial memory in the rat. Front. Neural Circuits 6:8. doi: 10.3389/fncir.2012.00008 <lb/>Akers, K. G., Candelaria-Cook, F. T., Rice, J. P., Johnson, T. E., and Hamilton, <lb/>D. A. (2011). Cued platform training reveals early development of directional <lb/>responding among preweanling rats in the Morris water task. Dev. Psychobiol. 53, <lb/>1-12. doi: 10.1002/dev.20480 <lb/>Akers, K. G., and Hamilton, D. A. (2007). Comparison of developmental trajectories <lb/>for place and cued navigation in the Morris water task. Dev. Psychobiol. 49, <lb/>553-564. doi: 10.1002/dev.20227 <lb/>Alberts, J. R., and Leimbach, M. P. (1980). The 1st foray -maternal influ-<lb/>ences in nest egression in the weanling rat. Dev. Psychobiol. 13, 417-429. doi: <lb/>10.1002/dev.420130408 <lb/>Arleo, A., Déjean, C., Allegraud, P., Khamassi, M., Zugaro, M. B., and Wiener, S. I. <lb/>(2013). Optic flow stimuli update anterodorsal thalamus head direction neuronal <lb/>activity in rats. J. Neurosci. 33, 16790-16795. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2698-<lb/>13.2013 <lb/>Astur, R. S., Ortiz, M. L., and Sutherland, R. J. (1998). A characterization of perfor-<lb/>mance by men and women in a virtual Morris water task: a large and reliable sex <lb/>difference. Behav. Brain Res. 93, 185-190. doi: 10.1016/S0166-4328(98)00019-9 <lb/>Astur, R. S., Taylor, L. B., Mamelak, A. N., Philpott, L., and Sutherland, R. J. (2002). <lb/>Humans with hippocampus damage display severe spatial memory impairments <lb/>in a virtual Morris water task. Behav. Brain Res. 132, 77-84. doi: 10.1016/S0166-<lb/>4328(01)00399-0 <lb/>Bachevalier, J., and Beauregard, M. (1993). Maturation of medial temporal lobe <lb/>memory functions in rodents, monkeys and humans. Hippocampus 3, 191-201. <lb/>Bassett, J. P., and Taube, J. S. (2005). &quot;Head direction signal generation: ascend-<lb/>ing and descending information streams,&quot; in Head Direction Cells and Neuronal <lb/>Mechanisms of Spatial Orientation, eds S. I. Wiener and J. S. Taube (Cambridge: <lb/>MIT Press), 83-109. <lb/>Beritoff, J. S. (1965). Neural Mechanisms of Higher Vertebrate Behavior. London: J. <lb/>and A. Churchill, Ltd. <lb/>Bolles, R. C., and Woods, P. J. (1964). Ontogeny of behaviour in albino rat. Anim. <lb/>Behav. 12, 427-441. doi: 10.1016/0003-3472(64)90062-4 <lb/>Borel, L., Harlay, F., Lopez, C., Magnan, J., Chays, A., and Lacour, M. (2004). Walking <lb/>performance of vestibular-defective patients before and after unilateral vestibular <lb/>neurotomy. Behav. Brain Res. 150, 191-200. doi: 10.1016/S0166-4328(03)00257-2 <lb/>Borel, L., Lopez, C., Peruch, P., and Lacour, M. (2008). Vestibular syndrome: a <lb/>change in internal spatial representation. Neurophysiol. Clin. 38, 375-389. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.neucli.2008.09.002 <lb/>Brandt, T., Schautzer, F., Hamilton, D. A., Bruning, R., Markowitsch, H. J., Kalla, <lb/>R., et al. (2005). Vestibular loss causes hippocampal atrophy and impaired spatial <lb/>memory in humans. Brain 128, 2732-2741. doi: 10.1093/brain/awh617 <lb/>Braswell, J., and Rine, R. M. (2006). Evidence that vestibular hypofunction affects <lb/>reading acuity in children. Int. J. Pediatr. Otorhinolaryngol. 70, 1957-1965. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.ijporl.2006.07.013 <lb/>Büttner, U., and Buettner, U. W. (1978). Parietal cortex (2v) neuronal activity in the <lb/>alert monkey during natural vestibular and optokinetic stimulation. Brain Res. <lb/>153, 392-397. doi: 10.1016/0006-8993(78)90421-3 <lb/>Chen, G., King, J. A., Burgess, N., and O&apos;Keefe, J. (2013). How vision and movement <lb/>combine in the hippocampal place code. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. U.S.A. 110, 378-<lb/>383. doi: 10.1073/pnas.1215834110 <lb/>Clark, B. J., Rice, J. P., Akers, K. G., Candelaria-Cook, F. T., Taube, J. S., and Hamilton, <lb/>D. A. (2013). Lesions of the dorsal tegmental nuclei disrupt control of navigation <lb/>by distal landmarks in cued, directional, and place variants of the Morris water <lb/>task. Behav. Neurosci. 127, 566-581. doi: 10.1037/a0033087 <lb/>Clark, B. J., and Taube, J. S. (2009). Deficits in landmark navigation and path <lb/>integration after lesions of the interpeduncular nucleus. Behav. Neurosci. 123, <lb/>490-503. doi: 10.1037/a0015477 <lb/>Cohen, H. S., and Sangi-Haghpeykar, H. (2011). Walking speed and vestibu-<lb/>lar disorders in a path integration task. Gait Posture 33, 211-213. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.gaitpost.2010.11.007 <lb/>Cornwell, B. R., Johnson, L. L., Holroyd, T., Carver, F. W., and Grillon, C. (2008). <lb/>Human hippocampal and parahippocampal theta during goal-directed spatial <lb/>navigation predicts performance on a virtual Morris water maze. J. Neurosci. 28, <lb/>5983-5990. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5001-07.2008 <lb/>Doeller, C. F., and Burgess, N. (2008). Distinct error-correcting and incidental <lb/>learning of location relative to landmarks and boundaries. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>U.S.A. 105, 5909-5914. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0711433105 <lb/>Doeller, C. F., King, J. A., and Burgess, N. (2008). Parallel striatal and hippocampal <lb/>systems for landmarks and boundaries in spatial memory. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. <lb/>U.S.A. 105, 5915-5920. doi: 10.1073/pnas.0801489105 <lb/>Driscoll, I., Hamilton, D. A., Petropoulos, H., Yeo, R. A., Brooks, W. M., Baum-<lb/>gartner, R. N., et al. (2003). The aging hippocampus: cognitive, biochemical and <lb/>structural findings. Cereb. Cortex 13, 1344-1351. doi: 10.1093/cercor/bhg081 <lb/>Dumas, T. C. (2005). Late postnatal maturation of excitatory synaptic trans-<lb/>mission permits adult-like expression of hippocampal-dependent behaviors. <lb/>Hippocampus 15, 562-578. doi: 10.1002/hipo.20077 <lb/>Ekstrom, A. D., Kahana, M. J., Caplan, J. B., Fields, T. A., Isham, E. A., Newman, E. <lb/>L., et al. (2003). Cellular networks underlying human spatial navigation. Nature <lb/>425, 184-188. doi: 10.1038/nature01964 <lb/>Etienne, A. S., Maurer, R., and Saucy, F. (1988). Limitations in the assessment of path <lb/>dependent information. Behaviour 106, 81-111. doi: 10.1163/156853988X00106 <lb/>Franco, E. S., and Panhoca, I. (2008). Vestibular function in children underper-<lb/>forming at school. Braz. J. Otorhinolaryngol. 74, 815-825. doi: 10.1590/S0034-<lb/>72992008000600003 <lb/>Gavrilov, V. V., Wiener, S. I., and Berthoz, A. (1996). Whole body rotations enhance <lb/>hippocampal theta rhythmic slow activity in awake rats passively transported <lb/>on a mobile robot. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 781, 385-398. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-<lb/>6632.1996.tb15714.x <lb/>Gavrilov, V. V., Wiener, S. I., and Berthoz, A. (1998). Discharge correlates <lb/>of hippocampal complex spike neurons in behaving rats passively displaced <lb/>on a mobile robot. Hippocampus 8, 475-490. doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1098-<lb/>1063(1998)8:5&lt;475::AID-HIPO7&gt;3.0.CO;2-H <lb/>Giedd, J. N., Vaituzis, A. C., Hamburger, S. D., Lange, N., Rajapakse, J. C., Kaysen, D., <lb/>et al. (1996). Quantitative MRI of the temporal lobe, amygdala, and hippocampus <lb/>in normal human development: ages 4-18 years. J. Comp. Neurol. 366, 223-230. <lb/>doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1096-9861(19960304)366:2&lt;223::AID-CNE3&gt;3.0.CO;2-7 <lb/>Glasauer, S., Amorim, M. A., Viaud-Delmon, I., and Berthoz, A. (2002). Differential <lb/>effects of labyrinthine dysfunction on distance and direction during blindfolded <lb/>walking of a triangular path. Exp. Brain Res. 145, 489-497. doi: 10.1007/s00221-<lb/>002-1146-1 <lb/>Gogtay, N., Nugent, T. F. III, Herman, D. H., Ordonez, A., Greenstein, D., <lb/>Hayashi, K. M., et al. (2006). Dynamic mapping of normal human hippocampal <lb/>development. Hippocampus 16, 664-672. doi: 10.1002/hipo.20193 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Grüsser, O. J., Pause, M., and Schreiter, U. (1990). Vestibular neurones in the <lb/>parieto-insular cortex of monkeys (Macaca fascicularis): visual and neck receptor <lb/>responses. J. Physiol. 430, 559-583. <lb/>Guidetti, G., Monzani, D., Trebbi, M., and Rovatti, V. (2007). Peripheral vestibu-<lb/>lar damage causes impaired navigation tasks on memorized routes in humans. <lb/>Ann. Otolaryngol. Chir. Cervicofac. 124, 197-201. doi: 10.1016/j.aorl.2007. <lb/>04.004 <lb/>Halmagyi, G. M., Colebatch, J. G., and Curthoys, I. S. (1994). New tests of vestibular <lb/>function. Baillières Clin. Neurol. 3, 485-500. <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., Akers, K. G., Johnson, T. E., Rice, J. P., Candelaria, F. T., Sutherland, <lb/>R. J., et al. (2008). The relative influence of place and direction in the Morris <lb/>water task. J. Exp. Psychol. Anim. Behav. Process. 34, 31-53. doi: 10.1037/0097-<lb/>7403.34.1.31 <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., Akers, K. G., Weisend, M. P., and Sutherland, R. J. (2007). How do <lb/>room and apparatus cues control navigation in the Morris water task? Evidence <lb/>for distinct contributions to a movement vector. J. Exp. Psychol. Anim. Behav. <lb/>Process. 33, 100-114. doi: 10.1037/0097-7403.33.2.100 <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., Johnson, T. E., Redhead, E. S., and Verney, S. R. (2009). Control of <lb/>rodent and human spatial navigation by room and apparatus cues. Behav. Process. <lb/>81, 154-169. doi: 10.1016/j.beproc.2008.12.003 <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., Kodituwakku, P., Sutherland, R. J., and Savage, D. D. (2003). <lb/>Children with fetal alcohol syndrome are impaired at place learning but not <lb/>cued-navigation in a virtual Morris water task. Behav. Brain Res. 143, 453-461. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/S0166-4328(03)00028-7 <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., Rosenfelt, C. S., and Whishaw I. Q. (2004). Sequential control of <lb/>navigation by locale and taxon cues in the Morris water task. Behav. Brain Res. <lb/>154, 385-397. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2004.03.005 <lb/>Hamilton, D. A., and Sutherland, R. J. (1999). Blocking in human place <lb/>learning: evidence from virtual navigation. Psychobiology 27, 453-461. doi: <lb/>10.3758/BF03332140 <lb/>Hanes, D. A., and McCollum, G. (2006). Cognitive-vestibular interactions: a review <lb/>of patient difficulties and possible mechanisms. J. Vestib. Res. 16, 75-91. <lb/>Hanlon, F. M., Weisend, M. P., Hamilton, D. A., Jones, A. P., Thoma, R. J., Huang, <lb/>M. X., et al. (2006). Impairment on the hippocampal-dependent virtual Morris <lb/>water task in schizophrenia. Schizophr. Res. 87, 67-80. doi: 10.1016/j.schres.2006. <lb/>05.021 <lb/>Hartley, T., Maguire, E. A., Spiers, H. J., and Burgess, N. (2003). The well-worn route <lb/>and the path less traveled: distinct neural bases of route following and wayfinding <lb/>in humans. Neuron 37, 877-888. doi: 10.1016/S0896-6273(03)00095-3 <lb/>Herdman, S. J., Hall, C. D., Schubert, M. C., Das, V. E., and Tusa, R. J. <lb/>(2007). Recovery of dynamic visual acuity in bilateral vestibular hypofunction. <lb/>Arch. Otolaryngol. Head Neck Surg. 133, 383-389. doi: 10.1001/archotol.133. <lb/>4.383 <lb/>Hoesing, J. M., Hamilton, D. A., and Sutherland, R. J. (2000). Equivalent sex dif-<lb/>ference in virtual place learning before and after puberty. J. Cogn. Neurosci. SS, <lb/>23-24. <lb/>Hufner, K., Hamilton, D. A., Kalla, R., Stephan, T., Glasauer, S., Ma, J., et al. (2007). <lb/>Spatial memory and hippocampal volume in humans with unilateral vestibular <lb/>deafferentation. Hippocampus 17, 471-485. doi: 10.1002/hipo.20283 <lb/>Hufner, K., Stephan, T., Hamilton, D. A., Kalla, R., Glasauer, S., Strupp, M., <lb/>et al. (2009). Gray-matter atrophy after chronic complete unilateral vestibular <lb/>deafferentation. Ann. N. Y. Acad. Sci. 1164, 383-385. doi: 10.1111/j.1749-<lb/>6632.2008.03719.x <lb/>Imbert, M., and Buisseret, P. (1975). Receptive field characteristics and plastic prop-<lb/>erties of visual cortical cells in kittens reared with or without visual experience. <lb/>Exp. Brain Res. 22, 25-36. doi: 10.1007/BF00235409 <lb/>Isableu, B., Ohlmann, T., Cremieux, J., Vuillerme, N., Amblard, B., and Gresty, M. A. <lb/>(2010). Individual differences in the ability to identify, select and use appropriate <lb/>frames of reference for perceptuo-motor control. Neurosci. 169, 1199-1215. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.neuroscience.2010.05.072 <lb/>Israël, I., Capelli, A., Sablé, D., Laurent, C., Lecoq, C., and Bredin, J. (2004). <lb/>Multifactorial interactions involved in linear self-transport distance estimate: <lb/>a place for time. Int. J. Psychophysiol. 53, 21-28. doi: 10.1016/j.ijpsycho.2004. <lb/>01.002 <lb/>Israël, I., and Warren, W. H. (2005). &quot;Vestibular, proprioceptive, and visual influ-<lb/>ences on the perception of orientation and self-motion in humans,&quot; in Head <lb/>Direction Cells and Neuronal Mechanisms of Spatial Orientation, eds S. I. Wiener <lb/>and J. S. Taube (Cambridge: MIT Press), 347-381. <lb/>Jacobs, W. J., Thomas, K. G. F., Laurance, H. E., and Nadel, L. (1998). Place learning <lb/>in virtual space II. Topographical relations as one dimension of stimulus control. <lb/>Learn. Motiv. 29, 288-308. doi: 10.1006/lmot.1998.1008 <lb/>Jacot, E., Van Den Abbeele, T., and Wiener-Vacher, S. R. (2009). Vestibular impair-<lb/>ment pre-and post-cochlear implant in children. Int. J. Pediatr. Otorhinolaryngol. <lb/>73, 209-217. doi: 10.1016/j.ijporl.2008.10.024 <lb/>Jacot, E., and Wiener-Vacher, S. R. (2008). Potential value of vestibular evoked <lb/>myogenic potentials in paediatric neuropathies. J. Vestib. Res. 18, 231-237. <lb/>Knickmeyer, R. C., Gouttard, S., Kang, C., Evans, D., Wilber, K., Smith, J. K., et al. <lb/>(2008). A structural MRI study of human brain development from birth to 2 <lb/>years. J. Neurosci. 28, 12176-12182. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3479-08.2008 <lb/>Knierim, J. J., and Hamilton, D. A. (2011). Framing spatial cognition: neural repre-<lb/>sentations of proximal and distal frames of reference and their roles in navigation. <lb/>Physiol. Rev. 91, 1245-1279. doi: 10.1152/physrev.00021.2010 <lb/>Lacour, M., Barthelemy, J., Borel, L., Magnan, J., Xerri, C., Chays, A., et al. (1997). <lb/>Sensory strategies in human postural control before and after unilateral vestibular <lb/>neurotomy. Exp. Brain Res. 115, 300-310. doi: 10.1007/PL00005698 <lb/>Langston, R. F., Ainge, J. A., Couey, J. J., Canto, C. B., Bjerknes, T. L., Witter, M. P., <lb/>et al. (2010). Development of the spatial representation system in the rat. Science <lb/>328, 1576-1580. doi: 10.1126/science.1188210 <lb/>Lehnung, M., Leplow, B., Friege, L., Herzog, A., Ferstl, R., and Mehdorn, M. <lb/>(1998). Development of spatial memory and spatial orientation in preschool-<lb/>ers and primary school children. Br. J. Psychol. 89 (Pt 3), 463-480. doi: <lb/>10.1111/j.2044-8295.1998.tb02697.x <lb/>Loewen, I., Wallace, D. G., and Whishaw, I. Q. (2005). The development of spatial <lb/>capacity in piloting and dead reckoning by infant rats: use of the huddle as a <lb/>home base for spatial navigation. Dev. Psychobiol. 46, 350-361. doi: 10.1002/dev. <lb/>Mathews, B. L., Ryu, J. H., and Bockaneck, C. (1989). Vestibular contribution to <lb/>spatial orientation: evidence of vestibular navigation in an animal model. Acta <lb/>Otolaryngol. Suppl. 468, 149-154 doi: 10.3109/00016488909139036 <lb/>Morris, R. G. M. (1981). Spatial localisation does not require the presence of local <lb/>cues. Learn. Motiv. 12, 239-260. doi: 10.1016/0023-9690(81)90020-5 <lb/>Morris, R. G. M. (1984). Developments of a water-maze procedure for studying <lb/>spatial-learning in the rat. J. Neurosci. Methods 11, 47-60. doi: 10.1016/0165-<lb/>0270(84)90007-4 <lb/>Morris, R. G. M., Garrud, P., Rawlins, J. N. P., and O&apos;Keefe, J. (1982). Place nav-<lb/>igation impaired in rats with hippocampal damage. Nature 297, 681-683. doi: <lb/>10.1038/297681a0 <lb/>Moser, E. I., Kropff, E., and Moser, M. B. (2008). Place cells, grid cells, and <lb/>the brain&apos;s spatial representation system. Annu. Rev. Neurosci. 31, 69-89. doi: <lb/>10.1146/annurev.neuro.31.061307.090723 <lb/>Mueller, S. C., Jackon, C. P. T., and Skelton, R. W. (2008). Sex differences in a <lb/>virtual water maze: an eye tracking and pupillometry study. Behav. Brain Res. <lb/>193, 209-215. doi: 10.1016/j.bbr.2008.05.017 <lb/>Muir, G. M., Brown, J. E., Carey, J. P., Hirvonen, T. P., Della Santina, C. C., Minor, <lb/>L. B., et al. (2009). Disruption of the head direction cell signal after occlusion of <lb/>the semicircular canals in the freely moving chinchilla. J. Neurosci. 29, 14521-<lb/>14533. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.3450-09.2009 <lb/>Newcombe, N., Huttenlocher, J., Drummey, A. B., and Wiley, J. G. (1998). The <lb/>development of spatial location coding: place learning and dead reckoning <lb/>in the second and third years. Cogn. Dev. 13, 185-200. doi: 10.1016/S0885-<lb/>2014(98)90038-7 <lb/>O&apos;Keefe, J., and Dostrovsky, J. (1971). The hippocampus as a spatial map. Prelimi-<lb/>nary evidence from unit activity in the freely-moving rat. Brain Res. 34, 171-175. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/0006-8993(71)90358-1 <lb/>O&apos;Keefe, J., and Nadel, L. (1978). The Hippocampus as a Cognitive Map. New York: <lb/>Oxford University Press. <lb/>Overman, W. H., Pate, B. J., Moore, K., and Peuster, A. (1996). Ontogeny <lb/>of place learning in children as measured in the radial arm maze, Mor-<lb/>ris search task, and open field task. Behav. Neurosci. 110, 1205-1228. doi: <lb/>10.1037/0735-7044.110.6.1205 <lb/>Pearce, J. M., Roberts, A. D. L., and Good, M. A. (1998). Hippocampal lesions <lb/>disrupt navigation based on cognitive maps but not heading vectors. Nature 396, <lb/>75-77. doi: 10.1038/23941 <lb/>Péruch, P., Borel, L., Gaunet, F., Thinus-Blanc, C., Magnan, J., and Lacour, M. (1999). <lb/>Spatial performance of unilateral vestibular defective patients in nonvisual versus <lb/>visual navigation. J. Vestib. Res. 9, 37-47. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/>December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | </note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Péruch, P., Borel, L., Magnan, J., and Lacour, M. (2005). Direction and distance <lb/>deficits in path integration after unilateral vestibular loss depend on task com-<lb/>plexity. Brain Res. Cogn. Brain Res. 25, 862-872. doi: 10.1016/j.cogbrainres. <lb/>2005.09.012 <lb/>Péruch, P., Lopez, C., Redon-Zouiteni, C., Escoffier, G., Zeitoun, A., Sanjuan, M., <lb/>et al. (2011). Vestibular information is necessary for maintaining metric proper-<lb/>ties of representational space: evidence from mental imagery. Neuropsychologia <lb/>49, 3136-3144. doi: 10.1016/j.neuropsychologia.2011.07.026 <lb/>Pfeiffer, B. E., and Foster, D. J. (2013). Hippocampal place-cell sequences depict <lb/>future paths to remembered goals. Nature 497, 74-79. doi: 10.1038/nature <lb/>12112 <lb/>Potegal, M. (1982). &quot;Vestibular and neostriatal contributions to spatial orientation,&quot; <lb/>in Spatial Abilities: Development and Physiological Foundations, ed. M. Potegal <lb/>(New York: Academic Press), 361-387. <lb/>Ranck, J. B. Jr. (1986). &quot;Head direction cells in the deep cell layer of dorsal pre-<lb/>subiculum in freely moving rats,&quot; in Electrical Activity of the Archicortex, eds G. <lb/>Buszáki and C. H. Vanderwolf (Budapest: Akademai Kiado), 217-220. <lb/>Redhead, E. S., and Hamilton, D. A. (2009). Evidence of blocking with <lb/>geometric cues in a virtual watermaze. Learn. Motiv. 40, 15-34. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.lmot.2008.06.002 <lb/>Ribordy, F., Jabes, A., Banta, L. P., and Lavenex, P. (2013). Development of allocentric <lb/>spatial memory abilities in children from 18 months to 5 years of age. Cogn. <lb/>Psychol. 66, 1-29. doi: 10.1016/j.cogpsych.2012.08.001 <lb/>Rieser, J. J., Guth, D. A., and Hill, E. W. (1986). Sensitivity to perspective struc-<lb/>ture while walking without vision. Perception 15, 173-188. doi: 10.1068/p1 <lb/>50173 <lb/>Rine, R. M., and Braswell, J. (2003). A clinical test of dynamic visual acu-<lb/>ity for children. Int. J. Pediatr. Otorhinolaryngol. 67, 1195-1201. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.ijporl.2003.07.004 <lb/>Rine, R. M., Cornwall, G., Gan, K., LoCascio, C., O&apos;Hare, T., Robinson, E., et al. <lb/>(2000). Evidence of progressive delay of motor development in children with <lb/>sensorineural hearing loss and concurrent vestibular dysfunction. Percept. Mot. <lb/>Skills 90, 1101-1112. doi: 10.2466/pms.2000.90.3c.1101 <lb/>Russell, N. A., Horii, A., Smith, P. F., Darlington, C. L., and Bilkey, D. K. <lb/>(2003a). Bilateral peripheral vestibular lesions produce long-term changes in <lb/>spatial learning in the rat. J. Vestib. Res. 13, 9-16. <lb/>Russell, N. A., Horii, A., Smith, P. F., Darlington, C. L., and Bilkey, D. K. (2003b). <lb/>Long-term effects of permanent vestibular lesions on hippocampal spatial firing. <lb/>J. Neurosci. 23, 6490-6498. <lb/>Russell, N. A., Horii, A., Smith, P. F., Darlington, C. L., and Bilkey, D. K. (2006). <lb/>Lesions of the vestibular system disrupt hippocampal theta rhythm in the rat. J. <lb/>Neurophysiol. 96, 4-14. doi: 10.1152/jn.00953.2005 <lb/>Schautzer, F., Hamilton, D., Kalla, R., Strupp, M., and Brandt, T. (2003). Spatial <lb/>memory deficits in patients with chronic bilateral vestibular failure. Ann. N. Y. <lb/>Acad. Sci. 1004, 316-324. doi: 10.1196/annals.1303.029 <lb/>Schubert, M. C., Migliaccio, A. A., and Della Santina, C. C. (2006). Dynamic visual <lb/>acuity during passive head thrusts in canal planes. J. Assoc. Res. Otolaryngol. 7, <lb/>329-338. doi: 10.1007/s10162-006-0047-6 <lb/>Smith, P. F., Horii, A., Russell, N., Bilkey, D. K., Zheng, Y., Liu, P., et al. (2005a). The <lb/>effects of vestibular lesions on hippocampal function in rats. Prog. Neurobiol. 75, <lb/>391-405. doi: 10.1016/j.pneurobio.2005.04.004 <lb/>Smith, P. F., Zheng, Y., Horii, A., and Darlington, C. L. (2005b). Does <lb/>vestibular damage cause cognitive dysfunction in humans? J. Vestib. Res. 15, <lb/>1-9. <lb/>Stackman, R., Lora, J., and Williams, S. (2012). Directional responding of C57BL/6J <lb/>mice in the Morris water maze is influenced by visual and vestibular cues and is <lb/>dependent upon the anterior thalamic nuclei. J. Neurosci. 32, 10211-10225. doi: <lb/>10.1523/JNEUROSCI.4868-11.2012 <lb/>Stackman, R. W., Clark, A. S., and Taube, J. S. (2002). Hippocampal spa-<lb/>tial representations require vestibular input. Hippocampus 12, 291-303. doi: <lb/>10.1002/hipo.1112 <lb/>Stackman, R. W., and Taube, J. S. (1997). Firing properties of head direction cells <lb/>in the rat anterior thalamic nucleus: dependence on vestibular input. J. Neurosci. <lb/>17, 4349-4358. <lb/>Stanton, M. E. (2000). Multiple memory systems, development and conditioning. <lb/>Behav. Brain Res. 110, 25-37. doi: 10.1016/S0166-4328(99)00182-5 <lb/>Sutherland, R. J., and Dyck, R. H. (1984). Place navigation by rats in a swimming <lb/>pool. Can. J. Psychol. 38, 322-347. doi: 10.1037/h0080832 <lb/>Sutherland, R. J., Kolb, B., and Whishaw, I. Q. (1982). Spatial mapping: definitive <lb/>disruption by hippocampal or frontal cortical damage in the rat. Neurosci. Lett. <lb/>31, 271-276. doi: 10.1016/0304-3940(82)90032-5 <lb/>Taube, J. S., Muller, R. U., and Ranck, J. B. Jr. (1990). Head-direction cells recorded <lb/>from the postsubiculum in freely moving rats. II. Effects of environmental <lb/>manipulations. J. Neurosci. 10, 436-447. <lb/>Thinus-Blanc, C., and Gaunet, F. (1997). Representation of space in blind <lb/>persons: vision as a spatial sense? Psychol. Bull. 121, 20-42. doi: 10.1037/0033-<lb/>2909.121.1.20 <lb/>Trullier, O., Wiener, S. I., Berthoz, A., and Meyer, J. A. (1997). Biologically based <lb/>artificial navigation systems: review and prospects. Prog. Neurobiol. 51, 483-544. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/S0301-0082(96)00060-3 <lb/>Uematsu, A., Matsui, M., Tanaka, C., Takahashi, T., Noguchi, K., Suzuki, M., <lb/>et al. (2012). Developmental trajectories of amygdala and hippocampus from <lb/>infancy to early adulthood in healthy individuals. PLoS ONE 7:e46970. doi: <lb/>10.1371/journal.pone.0046970 <lb/>Vann, S. D., Honey, R. C., and Aggleton, J. P. (2003). Lesions of the mammil-<lb/>lothalamic tract impair the acquisition of spatial but not nonspatial contextual <lb/>conditional discriminations. Eur. J. Neurosci. 18, 2413-2416. doi: 10.1046/j.1460-<lb/>9568.2003.02959.x <lb/>Vitte, E., Derosier, C., Caritu, Y., Berthoz, A., Hasboun, D., and Soulié, D. (1996). <lb/>Activation of the hippocampal formation by vestibular stimulation: a func-<lb/>tional magnetic resonance imaging study. Exp. Brain Res. 112, 523-526. doi: <lb/>10.1007/BF00227958 <lb/>Wallace, D. G., Hines, D. J., Pellis, S. M., and Whishaw, I. Q. (2002). Vestibular <lb/>information is required for dead reckoning in the rat. J. Neurosci. 22, 10009-<lb/>10017. <lb/>Wallace, D. G., and Whishaw, I. Q. (2003). NMDA lesions of Ammon&apos;s horn and <lb/>the dentate gyrus disrupt the direct and temporally paced homing displayed by <lb/>rats exploring a novel environment: evidence for a role of the hippocampus in <lb/>dead reckoning. Eur. J. Neurosci. 18, 513-523. doi: 10.1046/j.1460-9568.2003. <lb/>02772.x <lb/>Whitney, S. L., Marchetti, G. F., Pritcher, M., and Furman, J. M. (2009). Gaze <lb/>stabilization and gait performance in vestibular dysfunction. Gait Posture 29, <lb/>194-198. doi: 10.1016/j.gaitpost.2008.08.002 <lb/>Wiener, S. I. (1996). Spatial, behavioral and sensory correlates of hippocampal CA1 <lb/>complex spike cell activity: implications for information processing functions. <lb/>Prog. Neurobiol. 49, 335-361. doi: 10.1016/0301-0082(96)00019-6 <lb/>Wiener, S. I., and Berthoz, A. (1993). &quot;Forebrain structures mediating the vestibular <lb/>contribution during navigation,&quot; in Multisensory Control of Movement, ed. A. <lb/>Berthoz (Oxford: Oxford University Press), 427-456. <lb/>Wiener, S. I., Korshunov, V. A., Garcia, R., and Berthoz, A. (1995). Inertial, substratal <lb/>and landmark cue control of hippocampal CA1 place cell activity. Eur. J. Neurosci. <lb/>7, 2206-2219. doi: 10.1111/j.1460-9568.1995.tb00642.x <lb/>Wiener-Vacher, S., Lecervoisier, S., Lasserre, E., Le Bolloch, F., Sansous, <lb/>S., Busquet, D., et al. (2012a). Troubles de l&apos;équilibre chez l&apos;enfant. Paris: <lb/>ACFOS. Available at: http://www.acfos.org/publication/autresp/troublesequilibre <lb/>_juin2012.pdf <lb/>Wiener-Vacher, S. R., Obeid, R., and Abou-Elew, M. (2012b). Vestibular impairment <lb/>after bacterial meningitis delays infant posturomotor development. J. Pediatr. 161, <lb/>246-251. doi: 10.1016/j.jpeds.2012.02.009 <lb/>Wills, T. J., Barry, C., and Cacucci, F. (2012). The abrupt development of adult-like <lb/>grid cell firing in the medial entorhinal cortex. Front. Neural Circuits 6:21. doi: <lb/>10.3389/fncir.2012.00021 <lb/>Wills, T. J., Cacucci, F., Burgess, N., and O&apos;Keefe, J. (2010). Development of the <lb/>hippocampal cognitive map in preweanling rats. Science 328, 1573-1576. doi: <lb/>10.1126/science.1188224 <lb/>Wolbers, T., Wiener, J. M., Mallot, H. A., and Buchel, C. (2007). Differential <lb/>recruitment of the hippocampus, medial prefrontal cortex, and the human <lb/>motion complex during path integration in humans. J. Neurosci. 27, 9408-<lb/>9416. doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.2146-07.2007 <lb/>Xerri, C., Barthelemy, J., Borel, L., and Lacour, M. (1988). Neuronal coding of <lb/>linear motion in the vestibular nuclei of the alert cat. III. Dynamic characteristics <lb/>of visual-otolith interactions. Exp. Brain Res. 70, 299-309. doi: 10.1007/BF00 <lb/>248355 <lb/>Yoder, R. M., and Taube, J. S. (2009). Head direction cell activity in mice: robust <lb/>directional signal depends on intact otolith organs. J. Neurosci. 29, 1061-1076. <lb/>doi: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.1679-08.2009 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | </note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Wiener-Vacher et al. <lb/>Vestibular activity and cognitive development <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Zago, M., and Lacquaniti, F. (2005). Internal model of gravity for hand interception: <lb/>parametric adaptation to zero-gravity visual targets on Earth. J. Neurophysiol. 94, <lb/>1346-1357. doi: 10.1152/jn.00215.2005 <lb/>zu Eulenburg, P., Stoeter, P., and Dieterich, M. (2010). Voxel-based morphometry <lb/>depicts central compensation after vestibular neuritis. Ann. Neurol. 68, 241-249. <lb/>doi: 10.1002/ana.22063.10.1002/ana.22063. <lb/>Zugaro, M. B., Berthoz, A., and Wiener, S. I. (2001). Background, but not fore-<lb/>ground, spatial cues are taken as references for head direction responses by rat <lb/>anterodorsal thalamus neurons. J. Neurosci. 21, RC154. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest Statement: The authors declare that the research was conducted <lb/>in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed <lb/>as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 31 July 2013; paper pending published: 09 November 2013; accepted: 21 <lb/>November 2013; published online: 11 December 2013. <lb/>Citation: Wiener-Vacher SR, Hamilton DA and Wiener SI (2013) Vestibular activity <lb/>and cognitive development in children: perspectives. Front. Integr. Neurosci. 7:92. doi: <lb/>10.3389/fnint.2013.00092 <lb/>This article was submitted to the journal Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience. <lb/>Copyright © 2013 Wiener-Vacher, Hamilton and Wiener. This is an open-access <lb/>article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is permitted, <lb/>provided the original author(s) or licensor are credited and that the original pub-<lb/>lication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No <lb/>use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Integrative Neuroscience <lb/>www.frontiersin.org <lb/> December 2013 | Volume 7 | Article 92 | </note>


	</text>
</tei>
