<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>COMMENTS AND <lb/>RESPONSES <lb/>Response to <lb/>Comment on: <lb/>Wheeler et al. <lb/>Macronutrients, Food <lb/>Groups, and Eating <lb/>Patterns in the <lb/>Management of <lb/>Diabetes: A <lb/>Systematic Review of <lb/>the Literature, 2010. <lb/>Diabetes Care <lb/>2012;35:434-445 <lb/></front>

            <body>W <lb/>e appreciate the comments from <lb/>Drs. Esposito and Giugliano (1) <lb/>concerning our systematic review <lb/>(2). Each issue will be addressed as out-<lb/>lined in their letter. <lb/>Wrong statement about results of <lb/>published articles (reference 104): We ac-<lb/>knowledge that the results were misquoted <lb/>in the systematic review and appreciate the <lb/>identification of the error. The correct data <lb/>have been substituted in the online version <lb/>of the article. <lb/>Reporting of one triplicate study (refer-<lb/>ences 105-107): The three publications <lb/>include different patients from the same <lb/>hospital, different meals consumed, and, to <lb/>some extent, different methodology used. <lb/>The authors (personal communication <lb/> with Smaragdi Antonopoulou, PhD on 22 <lb/>February 2012) have confirmed that the <lb/>publications are three separate studies. <lb/>Missing published studies: The two <lb/>other clinical trial references provided (3,4) <lb/>do meet the inclusion criteria for the sys-<lb/>tematic review and should have been in-<lb/>cluded in the review. However, because <lb/>both of these studies had a retention rate <lb/>of ,80%, according to our systematic re-<lb/>view procedure, they would not have been <lb/>included in the key summary for each topic <lb/>area. Further, the diet that significantly im-<lb/>proved A1C over the control diet in the <lb/>three-arm study by Elhayany et al. was a <lb/>combination of a Mediterranean diet <lb/>and a moderately low-carbohydrate diet <lb/>(35% carbohydrate, 45% fat); the traditional <lb/>Mediterranean diet (50-55% carbohydrate, <lb/>30% fat) did not demonstrate an advantage <lb/>for A1C over the control diet. <lb/>Two other studies provided-a cross-<lb/>sectional study (5) and a systematic re-<lb/>view (6)-also meet our inclusion criteria <lb/>and should have been included in the re-<lb/>view. However, neither would have affected <lb/>the summary statement. The cross-sectional <lb/>study would not have been included in the <lb/>summary as it did not compare the Medi-<lb/>terranean diet to any other type of eating <lb/>pattern, and the systematic review did not <lb/>add any additional studies that fit our in-<lb/>clusion criteria. <lb/>To clarify, our review does not sug-<lb/>gest that the Mediterranean diet should be <lb/>avoided in patients with diabetes; we <lb/>simply state that &quot;there appears to be no <lb/>advantage in using the Mediterranean-<lb/>style eating pattern compared with other <lb/>eating patterns for glycemic control.&quot; <lb/>From our review, we found that several <lb/>different eating patterns, including the <lb/>Mediterranean diet, show promise for <lb/>achieving glycemic control. There was, <lb/>however, not one particular eating pat-<lb/>tern with definitive evidence as being bet-<lb/>ter than the others. This leaves health care <lb/>providers the opportunity to work with <lb/>individuals to adopt eating patterns hon-<lb/>oring their own culture, food preferences, <lb/>and food availability while still achieving <lb/>glycemic control. <lb/></body>

            <front>MADELYN L. WHEELER, MS, RD, FADA, CD 1 <lb/>STEPHANIE A. DUNBAR, MPH, RD 2 <lb/>LINDSAY M. JAACKS, BS 3 <lb/>WAHIDA KARMALLY, DRPH, RD, CDE, CLS, <lb/>FNLA <lb/>4 <lb/>ELIZABETH J. MAYER-DAVIS, MSPH, PHD, RD 5 <lb/>JUDITH WYLIE-ROSETT, EDD, RD 6 <lb/>WILLIAM S. YANCY JR., MD, MHS 7 <lb/>From 1 Nutritional Computing Concepts, Zionsville, <lb/>Indiana; 2 Medical Affairs, American Diabetes As-<lb/>sociation, Alexandria, Virginia; the 3 School of <lb/>Public Health, Nutritional Epidemiology, The <lb/>University of North Carolina, Chapel Hill, Chapel <lb/>Hill, North Carolina; the 4 Irving Institute for <lb/>Clinical and Translational Research, Columbia <lb/>University, New York, New York; the 5 Depart-<lb/>ment of Nutrition, The University of North Carolina, <lb/>Chapel Hill, Chapel Hill, North Carolina; the <lb/>6 Department of Epidemiology and Population <lb/>Health, Albert Einstein College of Medicine, <lb/>Bronx, New York; and the 7 Division of General <lb/>Internal Medicine, Duke University School of <lb/>Medicine, Durham, North Carolina. <lb/>

            Corresponding author: Stephanie A. Dunbar, sdunbar@ <lb/>diabetes.org. <lb/>

            DOI: 10.2337/dc12-0585 <lb/>

            © 2012 by the American Diabetes Association. <lb/>

            Readers may use this article as long as the work is <lb/>properly cited, the use is educational and not for <lb/>profit, and the work is not altered. See http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/3.0/ for <lb/>details. <lb/></front>

            <back>

                <div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments-W.K. has reported <lb/>being a member of the Research Committee <lb/>for the American Pistachio Growers. No other <lb/>potential conflicts of interest relevant to this <lb/>article were reported. <lb/></div>

                c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c c <lb/>

                <listBibl>References <lb/>1. Esposito K, Giugliano D. Comment on: <lb/>Wheeler et al. Macronutrients, food <lb/>groups, and eating patterns in the manage-<lb/>ment of diabetes: a systematic review of the <lb/>literature, 2010. Diabetes Care 2012;35: <lb/>434-445 (Letter). Diabetes Care 2012;35: <lb/>e51. DOI: 10.2337/dc12-0247 <lb/>2. Wheeler ML, Dunbar SA, Jaacks LM, et al. <lb/>Macronutrients, food groups, and eating <lb/>patterns in the management of diabetes: <lb/>a systematic review of the literature, 2010. <lb/>Diabetes Care 2012;35:434-445 <lb/>3. Elhayany A, Lustman A, Abel R, Attal-<lb/>Singer J, Vinker S. A low carbohydrate <lb/>Mediterranean diet improves cardiovascu-<lb/>lar risk factors and diabetes control among <lb/>overweight patients with type 2 diabetes <lb/>mellitus: a 1-year prospective randomized <lb/>intervention study. Diabetes Obes Metab <lb/>2010;12:204-209 <lb/>4. Shai I, Schwarzfuchs D, Henkin Y, et al.; <lb/>Dietary Intervention Randomized Con-<lb/>trolled Trial (DIRECT) Group. Weight <lb/>loss with a low-carbohydrate, Mediterra-<lb/>nean, or low-fat diet. N Engl J Med 2008; <lb/>359:229-241 <lb/>5. Esposito K, Maiorino MI, Di Palo C, <lb/>Giugliano D; Campanian Postprandial Hy-<lb/>perglycemia Study Group. Adherence to a <lb/>Mediterranean diet and glycaemic control <lb/>in type 2 diabetes mellitus. Diabet Med <lb/>2009;26:900-907 <lb/>6. Esposito K, Maiorino MI, Ceriello A, <lb/>Giugliano D. Prevention and control of <lb/>type 2 diabetes by Mediterranean diet: a sys-<lb/>tematic review. Diabetes Res Clin Pract <lb/>2010;89:97-102 <lb/></listBibl>
            </back>

            <page>e52 <lb/></page>

            <note place="footnote"> DIABETES CARE, VOLUME 35, JUNE 2012 <lb/>care.diabetesjournals.org <lb/></note>

            <note place="headnote"> O N L I N E <lb/>L E T T E R S</note> 


	</text>
</tei>
