<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Introduction: Feature Issue on Cellular Imaging <lb/>of the Retina <lb/>Joseph Carroll, 1,* Michael Pircher, 2 and Robert J. Zawadzki 3 <lb/>1 Department of Ophthalmology, Medical College of Wisconsin, 925 North 87th Street, Milwaukee, WI 53226, USA <lb/>2 Center for Medical Physics and Biomedical Engineering, Medical University of Vienna, Waehringer Straße 13, 1090 <lb/>Vienna, Austria <lb/>3 Vision Science and Advanced Retinal Imaging Laboratory (VSRI), Department of Ophthalmology &amp; Vision Science, <lb/>University of California Davis, 4860 Y Street, Suite 2400, Sacramento, CA 95817, USA <lb/>*jcarroll@mcw.edu <lb/>Abstract: The editors introduce the Biomedical Optics Express feature <lb/>issue, &quot;Cellular Imaging of the Retina,&quot; which includes 14 contributions <lb/>from the vision and optics community. <lb/>©2011 Optical Society of America <lb/>OCIS codes: (000.1200) Announcements, awards, news, and organizational activities; <lb/>(110.1080) Active or adaptive optics; (110.2960) Image analysis; (170.0170) Medical optics and <lb/>biotechnology; (170.4500) Optical coherence tomography; (170.5755) Retina scanning; <lb/>(330.4460) Ophthalmic optics and devices; (330.5310) Vision-photoreceptors; (330.7327) <lb/>Visual optics, ophthalmic instrumentation <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References and links <lb/> 1. A. Dubra and Y. Sulai, &quot;Reflective afocal broadband adaptive optics scanning ophthalmoscope,&quot; Biomed. Opt. <lb/>Express 2 1757-1768 (2011). <lb/>2. R. J. Zawadzki, S. M. Jones, S. Pilli, S. Balderas-Mata, D. Y. Kim, S. S. Olivier, and J. S. Werner, &quot;Integrated <lb/>adaptive optics optical coherence tomography and adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope system for <lb/>simultaneous cellular resolution in vivo retinal imaging,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2, 1674-1686 (2011). <lb/>3. S. Manzanera, M. A. Helmbrecht, C. J. Kempf, and A. Roorda, &quot;MEMS segmented-based adaptive optics <lb/>scanning laser ophthalmoscope,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(5), 1204-1217 (2011). <lb/>4. B. Vohnsen and D. Rativa, &quot;Ultrasmall spot size scanning laser ophthalmoscopy,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(6), <lb/>1597-1609 (2011). <lb/>5. O. P. Kocaoglu, S. Lee, R. S. Jonnal, Q. Wang, A. E. Herde, J. C. Derby, W. Gao, and D. T. Miller, &quot;Imaging <lb/>cone photoreceptors in three dimensions and in time using ultrahigh resolution optical coherence tomography <lb/>with adaptive optics,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(4), 748-763 (2011). <lb/>6. D. Rativa and B. Vohnsen, &quot;Analysis of individual cone-photoreceptor directionality using scanning laser <lb/>ophthalmoscopy,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(6), 1423-1431 (2011). <lb/>7. E. W. Dees, A. Dubra, and R. C. Baraas, &quot;Variability in parafoveal cone mosaic in normal trichromatic <lb/>individuals,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(5), 1351-1358 (2011). <lb/>8. A. Dubra, Y. Sulai, J. L. Norris, R. F. Cooper, A. M. Dubis, D. R. Williams, and J. Carroll, &quot;Noninvasive in <lb/>vivo imaging of the human rod photoreceptor mosaic using a confocal adaptive optics scanning <lb/>ophthalmoscope,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(7), 1864-1876 (2011). <lb/>9. J. Tam, P. Tiruveedhula, and A. Roorda, &quot;Characterization of single-file flow through human retinal parafoveal <lb/>capillaries using an adaptive optics scanning laser ophthalmoscope,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(4), 781-793 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>10. D. C. Hood and A. S. Raza, &quot;Method for comparing visual field defects to local RNFL and RGC damage seen on <lb/>frequency domain OCT in patients with glaucoma,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(5), 1097-1105 (2011). <lb/>11. D. C. Hood, R. Ramachandran, K. Holopigian, M. Lazow, D. G. Birch, and V. C. Greenstein, &quot;Method for <lb/>deriving visual field boundaries from OCT scans of patients with retinitis pigmentosa,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express <lb/>2(5), 1106-1114 (2011). <lb/>12. A. A. Moayed, S. Hariri, E. S. Song, V. Choh, and K. Bizheva, &quot;In vivo volumetric imaging of chicken retina <lb/>with ultrahigh-resolution spectral domain optical coherence tomography,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(5), 1268-<lb/>1274 (2011). <lb/>13. J. M. Bueno, A. Giakoumaki, E. J. Gualda, F. Schaeffel, and P. Artal, &quot;Analysis of the chicken retina with an <lb/>adaptive optics multiphoton microscope,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(6), 1637-1648 (2011). <lb/>14. R.-W. Lu, Y.-C. Li, T. Ye, C. Strang, K. Keyser, C. A. Curcio, and X.-C. Yao, &quot;Two-photon excited <lb/>autofluorescence imaging of freshly isolated frog retinas,&quot; Biomed. Opt. Express 2(6), 1494-1503 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Retinal imaging is a powerful tool, enabling clinicians to directly observe pathology and <lb/>researchers to probe retinal structure and function. Cellular resolution imaging of the retina is <lb/>a broad and rapidly growing field, benefiting from continued advances in optical <lb/></body>

			<front>#148292 -$15.00 USD <lb/>Received 26 May 2011; published 31 May 2011 <lb/>(C) 2011 OSA <lb/>1 June 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 6 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS <lb/></front>

			<body>instrumentation as well as data and image processing capabilities. In many cases, this can be <lb/>accomplished in vivo. Advances in retinal imaging are made possible through interactions <lb/>between the vision and optics communities, something that the Optical Society of America <lb/>has staunchly supported throughout its history. Reflecting the continued commitment to this <lb/>field, we were invited by the editors at Biomedical Optics Express to organize a feature issue <lb/>highlighting recent advances in the field of Cellular Imaging of the Retina. We were quite <lb/>pleased with the response (outlined below), and believe the assembled feature issue <lb/>appropriately captures the current state of the field. <lb/>The 14 papers in this issue span many disciplines, including clinical imaging, new <lb/>instrumentation, image analysis, imaging in animal models, and functional retinal imaging. <lb/>Reflecting the multidisciplinary nature of this field, most papers fit in multiple categories, and <lb/>here we provide a brief précis of the entire issue. <lb/>Using a variety of imaging techniques, the majority of the papers examined the human <lb/>retina. Among the imaging tools used to acquire retinal images were stand-alone and <lb/>adaptive-optics enhanced: scanning laser ophthalmoscopy/scanning ophthalmoscopy <lb/>(AOSLO/AOSO), optical coherence tomography (OCT), and fundus imaging. Adaptive optics <lb/>(AO) has opened numerous avenues of research in cellular resolution retinal imaging, thus it <lb/>is no surprise that we find AO at the heart of many of the papers in this feature issue. <lb/>Dubra et al. [1], Zawadzki et al. [2], Manzanera et al. [3], and Vohnsen and Rativa [4] <lb/>introduced new instrumentation for imaging the photoreceptor mosaic using a broadband <lb/>AOSO, an integrated AO-OCT SLO, a new MEMS-based AOSLO, and an annular-<lb/>illumination SLO, respectively. What we take away from these papers is that there is a <lb/>continued drive to improve the technology even further, which must occur in parallel to robust <lb/>application of existing imaging tools to studying the retina in order to keep the field moving <lb/>forward at its current pace. <lb/>Four additional papers examined structural and functional properties of the photoreceptor <lb/>mosaic. Kacaoglu et al. [5] examined spatial and temporal evaluation of individual cone <lb/>photoreceptors using AO-OCT. Rativa and Vohnsen [6] probed the directionality of cone <lb/>photoreceptors at different retinal eccentricities using scanning laser ophthalmoscopy. Dees et <lb/>al. [7] examined variability in parafoveal cone density in normal trichromatic individuals <lb/>using a high-speed flood-illuminated AO fundus camera. Dubra et al. [8] move beyond cones <lb/>and demonstrate striking images of the rod photoreceptor mosaic at various retinal locations <lb/>using a newly developed confocal AOSO. <lb/>Moving to clinical imaging, Tam et al. [9] developed a method to characterize capillary <lb/>flow dynamics in the living human retina using an AOSLO, something which could be quite <lb/>valuable for studying certain retinal diseases. In glaucoma patients, Hood and Raza [10] <lb/>provide a method for comparing functional visual field defects to local nerve fiber and retinal <lb/>ganglion cell damage seen on OCT. Hood et al. [11] present a method to define visual field <lb/>boundaries from an analysis of the inner segment/outer segment border in OCT images of <lb/>patients with retinitis pigmentosa. While the image resolution in these latter cases is not <lb/>cellular, the approach provides a key step forward in linking retinal structure with function, <lb/>and could be extended to some of the cellular imaging techniques described in this feature <lb/>issue. <lb/>The final three papers applied high-resolution imaging techniques to animal models. <lb/>Moayed et al. [12] provide volumetric imaging of the chicken retina in vivo using spectral <lb/>domain OCT. Also in the chicken, but ex vivo, Bueno et al. [13] developed an AO <lb/>multiphoton microscope for examining multiple retinal layers. Lu et al. [14] examined the <lb/>cellular sources of autofluorescence in freshly isolated frog retinas using a two-photon <lb/>excitation fluorescence microscope. Ultimately, there are questions that just can&apos;t be <lb/>addressed by imaging the human retina, and animal models will continue to be needed. As <lb/>such, adaptation and development of cellular imaging systems for use in various animal <lb/>preparations remains an area of need in this field. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">All papers in this issue have undergone a rigorous peer review process, and we are <lb/>indebted to the referees for their efforts in ensuring that the Optical Society of America&apos;s <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">#148292 -$15.00 USD <lb/>Received 26 May 2011; published 31 May 2011 <lb/>(C) 2011 OSA <lb/>1 June 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 6 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">standards for quality and integrity were met. We are especially gratefully to Joseph A. Izatt <lb/>(Editor-in-Chief), Gregory W. Faris (Deputy Editor), and the publication staff at the Optical <lb/>Society of America for their hard work and dedication to this feature issue: Joe Richardson, <lb/>Miriam Day, Kelly Cohen and the many others who contributed behind the scenes. We hope <lb/>you find the papers in this feature issue as enlightening as we did, and expect that they will <lb/>stimulate research to further move the field forward. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">#148292 -$15.00 USD <lb/>Received 26 May 2011; published 31 May 2011 <lb/>(C) 2011 OSA <lb/>1 June 2011 / Vol. 2, No. 6 / BIOMEDICAL OPTICS EXPRESS </note>


	</text>
</tei>
