<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>SAGE-Hindawi Access to Research <lb/>Enzyme Research <lb/>Volume 2011, Article ID 513905, 9 pages <lb/>doi:10.4061/2011/513905 <lb/>Research Article <lb/>Fluorescence Polarization Binding Assay for Aspergillus <lb/>fumigatus Virulence Factor UDP-Galactopyranose Mutase <lb/>Jun Qi, 1, 2 Michelle Oppenheimer, 1, 2 and Pablo Sobrado 1, 2, 3 <lb/>1 Department of Biochemistry, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA 26061, USA <lb/>2 Enzyme Research and Drug Discovery Laboratory, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA 26061, USA <lb/>3 Fralin Life Science Institute, Virginia Tech, Blacksburg, VA 26061, USA <lb/>Correspondence should be addressed to Pablo Sobrado, psobrado@vt.edu <lb/>Received 2 April 2011; Accepted 20 May 2011 <lb/>Academic Editor: Qi-Zhuang Ye <lb/>Copyright © 2011 Jun Qi et al. This is an open access article distributed under the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Aspergillus fumigatus is an opportunistic human pathogenic fungus responsible for deadly lung infections in immunocompromised <lb/>individuals. Galactofuranose (Galf ) residues are essential components of the cell wall and play an important role in A. fumigatus <lb/>virulence. The flavoenzyme UDP-galactopyranose mutase (UGM) catalyzes the isomerization of UDP-galactopyranose to UDP-<lb/>galactofuranose, the biosynthetic precursor of Galf. Thus, inhibitors of UGM that block the biosynthesis of Galf can lead to novel <lb/>chemotherapeutics for treating A. fumigatus-related diseases. Here, we describe the synthesis of fluorescently labeled UDP analogs <lb/>and the development of a fluorescence polarization (FP) binding assay for A. fumigatus UGM (Af UGM). High-affinity binding to <lb/>Af UGM was only obtained with the chromophore TAMRA, linked to UDP by either 2 or 6 carbons with K d values of 2.6 ± 0.2 μM <lb/>and 3.0 ± 0.7μM, respectively. These values were ∼6 times lower than when UDP was linked to fluorescein. The FP assay was <lb/>validated against several known ligands and displayed an excellent Z factor (0.79 ± 0.02) and good tolerance to dimethyl sulfoxide. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Aspergillus fumigatus is an opportunistic human pathogen <lb/>responsible for diseases such as allergic reactions and <lb/>lung infections, including bronchopulmonary aspergillosis <lb/>(ABPA) and invasive pulmonary aspergillosis (IPA) [1, 2]. <lb/>This fungus is a significant health threat to immunocom-<lb/>promised patients, such as organ transplant recipients and <lb/>people with AIDS or leukemia [3, 4]. It has been reported <lb/>that IPA infections are typically accompanied by a mortality <lb/>rate of 50-70% [5]. Thus, identification of novel and effective <lb/>drug targets is essential in the fight against fungal infections. <lb/>Recently, the biosynthetic pathway of galactofuranose <lb/>(Galf ), the 5-membered ring form of galactose, has been <lb/>described in A. fumigatus. Galf is a component of the cell wall <lb/>of A. fumigatus and plays an important role in virulence [6-<lb/>8]. In A. fumigatus, Galf was first identified as a component <lb/>of galactomannan by immunodetection in IPA patients [9]. <lb/>Later, it was found that Galf is also a major component <lb/>of saccharide structures in membrane lipids and glycosyl <lb/>phosphoinositol (GPI-)anchored lipophospholipids [10, 11]. <lb/>UDP-galactopyranose mutase (UGM) is a flavoenzyme that <lb/>catalyzes the conversion of UDP-galactopyranose (UDP-<lb/>Galp) to UDP-galactofuranose (UDP-Galf, Figure 1), the <lb/>biosynthetic precursor of Galf [7, 12]. Deletion of the A. <lb/>fumigatus UGM (Af UGM) gene results in mutant fungi <lb/>with attenuated virulence, a decrease in cell wall thickness, <lb/>and an increase in the sensitivity to antifungal agents <lb/>[8, 13]. Moreover, Galf is absent in humans [12]. Thus, <lb/>inhibitors of Af UGM that block the biosynthesis of Galf <lb/>represent attractive drug targets for the identification of <lb/>novel therapeutics against A. fumigatus. <lb/>Here, we describe the development of a fluorescence <lb/>polarization (FP) binding assay to identify specific Af UGM <lb/>inhibitors. Four fluorescently labeled UDP derivatives <lb/>including two known UDP-fluorescein analogs (1 and 2, <lb/>Figure 2) and two novel UDP-TAMRA analogs (3 and 4, <lb/>Figure 2) were synthesized to be used as fluorescent probes <lb/>in the FP assay. Their concentrations were optimized to <lb/>obtain a stable FP signal with minimal standard deviation, <lb/>and their K d values were determined by measuring the <lb/>anisotropy changes as a function of Af UGM concentration. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<body>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>NH <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>HO <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>HO <lb/>HO <lb/>HO <lb/>UDP-Galp <lb/>UDP-Gal f <lb/>A f UGM <lb/>Figure 1: Reaction catalyzed by Af UGM. <lb/>C <lb/>COOH <lb/>COOH <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>COO <lb/>COO <lb/>HN <lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>NH <lb/>NH <lb/>NH <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>HO <lb/>HO <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>2 <lb/>= 1 5 <lb/>= 5 6 <lb/>= 1 <lb/>Chromophore 3 <lb/>= 5 <lb/>Chromophore 4 <lb/>5-TA <lb/>A <lb/>MR -succinimidyl ester <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>OH OH <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>P <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/> O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>1 <lb/>Chromophore <lb/>Chromophore <lb/>FITC <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>= 1 <lb/>= 5 <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>Figure 2: Synthetic scheme of the chromophores used as ligands to Af UGM for application in FP assays. <lb/>We found that the UDP-TAMRA analogs bind to Af UGM <lb/>6-fold tighter than the UDP-fluorescein analogs, suggesting <lb/>that UDP-TAMRA analogs are better fluorescent probes for <lb/>this enzyme. UDP-TAMRA probes could be competed out <lb/>by UDP, a known ligand of UGMs, and the K d value of UDP <lb/>was in good agreement with the value determined previously <lb/>in a fluorescence assay [7]. Furthermore, the FP assay was <lb/>validated using several known ligands and displayed an <lb/>excellent Z factor (0.79 ± 0.02) and good tolerance to <lb/>DMSO. Therefore, this fast convenient one-step FP assay is <lb/>suitable for a high-throughput screening to identify Af UGM <lb/>inhibitors. <lb/>2. Materials and Methods <lb/>2.1. Materials. All chemicals were obtained from commercial <lb/>sources and were used without further purification. Anhy-<lb/>drous reactions were performed under argon. All solvents <lb/>were either reagent grade or HPLC grade. NMR spectral <lb/>data were obtained using a JEOL Eclipse spectrometer at <lb/>500 MHz, or a Varian Inova spectrometer at 400 MHz. <lb/>Chemical shifts were reported as δ-values relative to known <lb/>solvent residue peaks. High-resolution mass spectra (HRMS) <lb/>were obtained in the Mass Spec Incubator, Department <lb/>of Biochemistry, Virginia Tech. High-performance liquid <lb/>chromatography (HPLC) was performed on a C18 reverse <lb/>phase column (Phenomenex Luna C18 column, 250 × <lb/>21.20 mm, 5 microns) using water and acetonitrile as the <lb/>elution solvents. All compounds were more than 95% pure <lb/>as judged by HPLC and 1 H NMR. <lb/>2.2. Protein Expression and Purification. Af UGM and <lb/>MtUGM were expressed and purified with the same pro-<lb/>tocol as described by Oppenheimer et al. [7]. A large <lb/>quantity of highly pure Af UGM was obtained, which was <lb/>confirmed by UV-visible spectrophotometry and SDS-PAGE <lb/>(see Figure S1 Supplementary Material available online at <lb/>doi:10.4061/2011/513905). <lb/>2.3. Synthesis of UDP-Fluorescein Chromophore 1 and 2. The <lb/>synthesis of chromophore 1 was accomplished by reacting <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Polarized light <lb/>Enzyme-ligand com lex <lb/>Slow tumbling <lb/>Polarized fluorescence <lb/>UDP <lb/>UDP <lb/>Af UGM <lb/>Af UGM <lb/>p <lb/>(a) <lb/>Polarized light <lb/>Small molecule <lb/>UDP <lb/>UDP <lb/>Af UGM <lb/>Af UGM <lb/>Rapid tumbling <lb/>Depolarized fluorescence <lb/>Inhibitor <lb/>= <lb/>=Fluorophore (fluorescein or TAMRA) <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 3: FP assay design. (a) Binding of the FP probe to Af UGM leads to polarized fluorescence. (b) Displacement of the FP probe from <lb/>Af UGM by inhibitor results in depolarized fluorescence. <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>Chromophore (nM) <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>Figure 4: Determination of optimal concentration of fluorescent <lb/>probe for FP binding assay. Conditions are described in Material <lb/>and Methods sections. Chromophore 1 ( ), 2 ( ) (excitation at <lb/>492 nm and emission at 524 nm), 3 ( ), and 4 ( ) (excitation at <lb/>544 nm and emission at 584 nm). <lb/>4 mg of compound 5, which was synthesized following a pre-<lb/>viously published procedure [15], with 6 mg of fluorescein-<lb/>5-isothiocyanate (FITC) in 0.1 M pH 9.0 NaHCO 3 buffer <lb/>(50 μL) and DMF (100 μL) (Figure 2). After stirring at <lb/>room temperature for 2 hours, the yellow solution was <lb/>concentrated and loaded onto a preparative silica gel TLC <lb/>plate. The isolated crude product was dissolved in water, <lb/>injected onto reverse-phase HPLC (Phenomenex Luna C18 <lb/>column, 250 × 21.20 mm, 5 microns), and purified at a flow <lb/>rate of 5.0 mL/min with linear gradient elution of 5% to 95% <lb/>acetonitrile in H 2 O over 20 min to afford chromophore 1 <lb/>(4 mg, 52%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, 6 : 1 D 2 O: d 7 -DMF): δ 7.96 <lb/>(d, J = 8.2, 1H), 7.78 (s, 1H), 7.70 (d, J = 8.1, 1H), 7.30 (dd, J <lb/>= 8.2, 1.5, 1H), 7.27-7.27 (m, 2H) (t, J = 8.7, 2H), 6.65-6.61 <lb/>(m, 2H), 6.61-6.58 (m, 2H), 5.91 (s, 1H), 5.91 (s, 1H), 4.36-<lb/>4.30 (m, 2H), 4.24-4.21 (m, 3H), 4.19-4.16 (m, 2H), 3.88 (s, <lb/>2H); HRMS (MALDI) calcd for C 32 H 29 N 4 O 17 P 2 S (M-H) -: <lb/>835.0729, found 835.0759 (Figure S2). <lb/>Chromophore 2 (7.1 mg, 55%) was synthesized from the <lb/>reaction of compound 6 and FITC by the same procedure <lb/>as above (Figure 2) and was purified by preparative TLC and <lb/>reverse-phase HPLC (Phenomenex Luna C18 column, 250 <lb/>× 21.20 mm, 5 micron). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, 6 : 1 D 2 O: d 7 -<lb/>DMF): δ 8.00 (d, J = 8.0, 1H), 7.73 (s, 1H), 7.61 (d, J = 8.3, <lb/>1H), 7.31 (d, J = 8.3, 1H), 7.27-7.27 (m, 2H), 6.66-6.60 (m, <lb/>4H), 5.96 (s, 1H), 4.38-4.34 (m, 2H), 4.27-4.23 (m, 2H), <lb/>4.23-4.18 (m, 2H), 3.97-3.92 (m, 2H), 3.58 (s, 1H), 1.66-<lb/>1.61 (m, 4H), 1.42-1.36 (m, 4H); HRMS (MALDI) calcd <lb/>for C 36 H 37 N 4 O 17 P 2 S (M-H) -: 891.1350, found 891.1348 <lb/>(Figure S3). <lb/>2.4. Synthesis of UDP-TAMRA Chromophore 3 and 4. The <lb/>synthesis of chromophore 3 was accomplished by a reaction <lb/>of 4 mg of compound 6, which was synthesized follow-<lb/>ing a previously published procedure [15], with 0.8 mg <lb/>of 5-carboxytetramethylrhodamine, succinimidyl ester (5-<lb/>TAMRA, SE) in 0.1 M pH 8.3 NaHCO 3 buffer (50 μL) and <lb/>DMF (50 μL) (Figure 2). After stirring at room temperature <lb/>for 2 hours, the pink solution was concentrated and loaded <lb/>onto a preparative TLC plate. The isolated crude product was <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>
				
			<body>Anisotropy <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>A f UGM (µM) <lb/>(a) <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.001 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>A f UGM (µM) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 5: FP binding assay to determine K d of the chromophores. (a) Chromophores 1 ( ) and 2 ( ) (excitation at 492 nm and emission <lb/>at 524 nm). (b) Chromophores 3 ( ) and 4 ( ) (excitation at 544 nm and emission at 584 nm). <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>3 <lb/>3.5 <lb/>Z  <lb/>factor <lb/>A f UGM (µM) <lb/>Figure 6: Determination of optimal Af UGM concentration to use <lb/>in the FP assay with chromophore 3 ( ) and chromophore 4 ( ). <lb/>dissolved in water, injected onto reverse-phase HPLC (Phe-<lb/>nomenex Luna C18 column, 250 × 21.20 mm, 5 microns), <lb/>and purified at a flow rate of 5.0 mL/min with linear gradient <lb/>elution of 5% to 95% acetonitrile in H 2 O over 20 min to <lb/>afford chromophore 3 (1.1 mg, 80%). 1 H NMR (500 MHz, <lb/>D 2 O) δ 8.22 (s, 1H), 8.08 (d, J = 7.7, 1H), 7.89 (d, J = 7.3, <lb/>1H), 7.60 (d, J = 8.8, 1H), 7.28-7.22 (m, 1H), 6.91-6.88 (m, <lb/>2H), 6.61 (s, 1H), 6.59 (s, 1H), 5.89-5.83 (m, 2H), 4.35-<lb/>4.31 (m, 1H), 4.30-4.26 (m, 1H), 4.18-4.15 (m, 3H), 4.00 <lb/>(dd, J = 13.3, 6.4, 2H), 3.49 (t, J = 6.8, 2H), 3.19 (s, 3H), <lb/>3.18 (s, 3H), 1.75 -1.67 (m, 4H), 1.51-1.45 (m, 4H), 1.34 (s, <lb/>3H), 1.32 (s, 3H); HRMS (MALDI) calcd for C 40 H 46 N 5 O 16 P 2 <lb/>(M-H) -: 914.2415, found 914.2431 (Figure S4). The above <lb/>synthetic approach was also used to synthesize and purify <lb/>chromophore 4 (1.5 mg, 77%). HRMS (MALDI) calcd for <lb/>C 36 H 38 N 5 O 16 P 2 (M-H) -: 858.1789, found 858.1851 (Figure <lb/>S5). <lb/>2.5. Optimization of Chromophore Concentration. Solutions <lb/>containing various concentrations of chromophore in 0.05 M <lb/>sodium phosphate buffer (pH 7.0) were added to 12 wells <lb/>in a 96-well half area black bottom plate (Corning) with <lb/>final volumes of 25 μL. FP was analyzed by a SpectraMax M5 <lb/>plate reader (Molecular Devices). The parallel fluorescence <lb/>emission (F = ) and perpendicular fluorescence emission (F ⊥ ) <lb/>at 524 nm (for compounds 1 and 2, excitation at 492 nm) <lb/>or at 584 nm (for compounds 3 and 4, excitation at 544 nm) <lb/>were measured by a SpectraMax M5 plate reader (Molecular <lb/>Devices), and the anisotropy (r) was calculated using (1), <lb/>the minimal concentration at which stable FP signals with <lb/>minimal standard deviations were chosen as the optimal <lb/>concentration for the chromophore. <lb/>r = <lb/>F = -G • F ⊥ <lb/>F = + 2G • F ⊥ <lb/>(1) <lb/>y = m 1 + (m 2 -m 1 ) <lb/>× <lb/>(x + C t + m 3 ) -(x + C t + m 3 ) 2 -4xC t <lb/>2C t <lb/>(2) <lb/>2.6. FP Binding Assay to Determine the Chromophore Binding <lb/>Affinities. Solutions containing serially diluted Af UGM and <lb/>15 nM of chromophore in 0.05 M sodium phosphate buffer <lb/>(pH 7.0) were incubated at room temperature for 5 minutes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.001 0.01 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>UDP (µM) <lb/>(a) <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>UDP-Galp (µM) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 7: FP competitive binding assay with UDP (a) and UDP-Galp (b). <lb/>HN <lb/>N <lb/>HO <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Br <lb/>2-(2-(4-bromophenyI)-1, 3-dioxoisoindolin -<lb/>5-carboxamido) benzoic acid <lb/>(7) <lb/>e <lb/>(a) <lb/>2 N <lb/>NH <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>S <lb/>(Z)-N-((E)-5-(5-nitro-2-oxoindolin-3-ylidene)-<lb/>4-oxothiazolidin-2-ylidene) benzenesulfonamide <lb/>(8) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 8: Structures of known inhibitors of bacterial UGM [14]. <lb/>Each experiment was done in triplicate in a 96-well black bot-<lb/>tom plate at final volumes of 25 μL. Fluorescence anisotropy <lb/>was measured as indicated above, and the K d values were <lb/>obtained by fitting the anisotropy data to (2), where m 1 <lb/>and m 2 are the minimum and maximum anisotropy values, <lb/>respectively; m 3 is the K d value, and the total concentration <lb/>of UDP-chromophore is represented by C t . <lb/>2.7. Determination of the Assay Z Factor. Solutions contain-<lb/>ing 2 μM of Af UGM and 15 nM of chromophore 3 in the <lb/>absence (negative control) and presence (positive control) of <lb/>300 μM of UDP were incubated at room temperature for 5 <lb/>minutes. Each solution was added to octuplicate wells in a <lb/>96-well half area black bottom plate with final volumes of <lb/>25 μL. The Z factors were calculated using (3), where μ -<lb/>represents the mean anisotropy value of the negative control, <lb/>and μ + is the mean anisotropy value of the positive control; <lb/>σ -represents the standard deviation of the negative control, <lb/>and σ + is the standard deviation of the positive control. A Z <lb/>factor of 0.79 ± 0.02 was obtained for chromophore 3. <lb/>Z = 1 -<lb/>3(σ -+ σ + ) <lb/>μ --μ + <lb/>(3) <lb/>2.8. Optimization of AfUGM Concentration. To determine <lb/>the optimal concentration of Af UGM in the FP assay, <lb/>solutions containing 15 nM of chromophore 3 and Af UGM <lb/>at various concentrations in the absence (negative control) <lb/>and presence (positive control) of 300 μM of UDP were <lb/>incubated at room temperature for 5 minutes. Each was <lb/>added to octuplicate wells at a final volume of 25 μL. FP <lb/>was analyzed as indicated previously, and Z factors were <lb/>calculated from (3). <lb/>2.9. Competitive Binding Experiments Using FP Inhibition <lb/>Assay. Solutions (25 μL) containing 2 μM of Af UGM and <lb/>15 nM of chromophore 3 in 0.05 M sodium phosphate buffer <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<body>Compound 7 <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>(µM) <lb/>(a) <lb/>Compound 8 <lb/>Anisotropy <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>(µM) <lb/>(b) <lb/>Figure 9: FP inhibition assay with compounds 7 (a) and 8 (b). <lb/>(pH 7.0) were mixed with various concentrations of UDP, <lb/>UDP-Galp, 7, or 8 (Figure 8), and the reactions incubated <lb/>at room temperature for 5 minutes. Each solution was done <lb/>in triplicate. Anisotropy values were measured and the IC 50 <lb/>values obtained by fitting the data to (4), where m 1 and m 2 <lb/>are the minimum and maximum anisotropy, respectively; m 3 <lb/>is the slope, and m 4 is the IC 50 . The K d values were obtained <lb/>using (5), where K i is the binding affinity of chromophore 3 <lb/>on Af UGM (2.6 ± 0.6 μM), and I is the concentration of the <lb/>chromophore (15 nM). <lb/>y = m 1 + <lb/>(m 2 -m 1 )x m3 <lb/>m m3 <lb/>4 + x m3 <lb/>(4) <lb/>K d = <lb/>IC 50 <lb/>1 + (I/K i ) <lb/>(5) <lb/>2.10. AfUGM Activity Assay. The Af UGM activity assay was <lb/>performed by monitoring the formation of UDP-Galp from <lb/>UDP-Galf by HPLC. A 20 μL reaction containing 20 mM <lb/>dithiothreitol, 0.5 mM UDP-Galf in 25 mM HEPES, 125 mM <lb/>NaCl buffer, pH 7.5 in the absence of 7 or 8 was initiated <lb/>by the addition of Af UGM at a final concentration of <lb/>50 nM. After incubation at 37 • C for 10 min, the reaction <lb/>was quenched by heat denaturation (95 • C for 5 min) in a <lb/>DNA engine thermocycler (BioRad, Hercules, Calif, USA). <lb/>The same reaction was also performed in the presence <lb/>of 7 (500 μM) or 8 (50 μM). The suspension was cen-<lb/>trifuged and the supernatant was injected onto a CarboPac <lb/>PA100 (Dionex) anion-exchange column. The sample was <lb/>eluted isocratically with 75 mM KH 2 PO 4 (pH 4.5), and the <lb/>absorbance at 262 nm was monitored to identify fractions of <lb/>substrate and product. The substrate UDP-Galf was eluted at <lb/>36.5 min, and the product UDP-Galp was eluted at 28.3 min. <lb/>The inhibition of Af UGM activity was indicated by the <lb/>extent of conversion of UDP-Galf to UDP-Galp. <lb/>2.11. Tolerance to DMSO. To determine the tolerance of <lb/>the assay to DMSO, solutions containing 2 μM of Af UGM, <lb/>15 nM of chromophore 3, and DMSO at various concen-<lb/>trations in the absence (negative control) and presence <lb/>(positive control) of 300 μM of UDP were incubated at room <lb/>temperature for 5 minutes. Fluorescence anisotropy values <lb/>and Z factors were calculated as indicated previously. <lb/>3. Results and Discussion <lb/>3.1. Assay Design and Optimization. In this study, we report <lb/>the development of an FP assay that can be used in a high-<lb/>throughput format for the identification of inhibitors of <lb/>Af UGM, which we believe will lead to the development <lb/>of new therapeutics against A. fumigatus-related diseases. <lb/>The FP assay was designed as shown in Figure 3. If the <lb/>UDP fluorescent probe binds to Af UGM and is excited with <lb/>plane-polarized light, the resulting enzyme-ligand complex <lb/>tumbles slowly in solution, and thus, the fluorescence <lb/>emission remains polarized (Figure 3(a)). Otherwise, the <lb/>emission will be depolarized as the free chromophore will <lb/>rotate rapidly. The change in the rotational motion between <lb/>the bound and free chromophore can be used as a signal <lb/>for detection of the binding of small molecules to the active <lb/>site of Af UGM because, as the small molecule replaces <lb/>the bound fluorescent probe, the free probe will rapidly <lb/>rotate increasing the amount of depolarized fluorescence <lb/>(Figure 3(b)). <lb/>An essential component of an FP assay is a fluorescent <lb/>probe that specifically binds to the enzyme or protein of <lb/>interest. To design the fluorescent probe, we reasoned that <lb/>the incorporation of the UDP moiety into the structure <lb/>would target binding to the Af UGM active site since it <lb/>is a major part of the UGM substrate. The fluorophore <lb/>we first selected was fluorescein because UDP-fluorescein <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>UDP-Galp <lb/>UDP-Gal f <lb/>Intensity UV (%) <lb/>Retention time (min) <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>Intensity UV (%) <lb/>Retention time (min) <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>Retention time (min) <lb/>Intensity UV (%) <lb/>(c) <lb/>Figure 10: Af UGM activity assay. The HPLC chromatograms at 262 nm are shown. (a) Af UGM activity in the absence of inhibitor. (b) In <lb/>the presence of 7 (500 μM). (c) In the presence of 8 (50 μM). <lb/>derivatives have been found to bind to prokaryotic UGMs <lb/>from Klebsiella pneumoniae and Mycobacterium tuberculosis <lb/>[15]. To minimize the steric hindrance of fluorescein with <lb/>Af UGM binding site residues, UDP and fluorescein were <lb/>connected with alkyl linkers of different lengths, which <lb/>resulted in two UDP-fluorescein analogs (1 and 2, Figure 2). <lb/>We also designed a UDP bound to the chromophore, com-<lb/>mercially known as TAMRA (Figure 2). This chromophore <lb/>offers several advantages over fluorescein. First, TAMRA is <lb/>more resistant to photobleaching compared to fluorescein <lb/>[16]. Second, the fluorescence emission of TAMRA does <lb/>not overlap with that of the flavin cofactor in Af UGM. <lb/>Fluorescein is typically excited at 494 nm and emits at <lb/>520 nm, which significantly overlaps with the absorbance <lb/>and fluorescence emission of the flavin. In contrast, TAMRA&apos;s <lb/>absorbance and fluorescence maxima is at 546 nm and 580 <lb/>nm, respectively [16]. This is significantly different from <lb/>the flavin absorbance/emission properties and improves <lb/>signal-to-noise ratio. Finally, in comparison with fluorescein, <lb/>TAMRA has one extra positive charge, which we believe <lb/>increases the interaction between TAMRA and flavin and <lb/>helps improve binding of the probe to Af UGM. Alkyl linkers <lb/>of different lengths were also included to minimize the steric <lb/>interaction of TAMRA with the binding site residues, giving <lb/>two novel UDP-TAMRA analogs (3 and 4, Figure 2). <lb/>In order to increase the signal-to-noise ratio, stable FP <lb/>values are necessary. Therefore, we varied the concentration <lb/>of UDP-chromophores to determine the optimal concentra-<lb/>tion (Figure 4). Stable FP values with minimal standard devi-<lb/>ation were obtained at concentrations higher than 15 nM. <lb/>Therefore, we chose the 15 nM UDP-chromophore as the <lb/>minimal concentration to use for further characterization. <lb/>3.2. AfUGM Specific UDP-Chromophore for HTS Assay Appli-<lb/>cation. Binding of the UDP-chromophore to Af UGM was <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<body>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>DMSO (%) <lb/>Z  <lb/>factor <lb/>Figure 11: Tolerance to DMSO. <lb/>Table 1: K d values of UDP-fluorescent probes. <lb/>Chromophore <lb/>K d for Af UGM (μM) <lb/>K d for MtUGM (μM) <lb/>1 <lb/>17 ± 3 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>2 <lb/>16 ± 3 <lb/>0 . 1 0 ± 0.01 <lb/>3 <lb/>2.6 ± 0.2 <lb/>0.73 ± 0.07 <lb/>4 <lb/>3.0 ± 0.7 <lb/>&gt;30 <lb/>determined by varying the concentration of the enzyme at a <lb/>constant concentration of the UDP-chromophores (15 nM) <lb/>(Figure 5). Binding assays with the UDP-fluorescein probes <lb/>(chromophores 1 and 2) show that these ligands bind <lb/>weakly to Af UGM, with K d values of ∼15 μM (Figure 5(a)). <lb/>This relatively low affinity impedes the utilization of these <lb/>chromophores for a high-throughput FP binding assay, as <lb/>it will require high quantities of enzyme. Interestingly, we <lb/>tested the binding of these chromophores to bacterial UGM <lb/>from M. tuberculosis, and the K d value of chromophore 2 was <lb/>0.10 ± 0.01 μM, consistent with previously published values <lb/>(Table 1) [15]. This tighter binding suggests differences in <lb/>the active-site architecture between the prokaryotic and <lb/>A. fumigatus UGM enzymes. This is also consistent with <lb/>our recent report on binding assays monitoring flavin <lb/>fluorescence that showed that Af UGM binds UDP-glucose <lb/>5 times tighter than K. pneumoniae UGM. Similarly, binding <lb/>of UDP-Galp to Af UGM was not detected although UDP-<lb/>Galp binds to the bacterial enzyme with a K d value of <lb/>220 μM [7, 17]. These differences in ligand binding might <lb/>originate from the low amino acid identity between the <lb/>bacterial and eukaryotic UGMs (&lt;18%). Furthermore, we <lb/>have shown that the quaternary structure between these <lb/>enzymes is not conserved as the bacterial enzymes have been <lb/>shown to function as homodimers, while Af UGM functions <lb/>as a homotetramer [7]. <lb/>With the UDP-TAMRA analogs (chromophores 3 and 4), <lb/>the binding to Af UGM was ∼6 times better than with the <lb/>UDP-fluorescein analogs, and significant anisotropy change <lb/>Table 2: K d values of UGM ligands. <lb/>Ligand <lb/>K d for Af UGM (μM) <lb/>K d for MtUGM (μM) <lb/>UDP <lb/>9.0 ± 1.7 <lb/>15 ± 2 <lb/>UDP-Galp <lb/>495 ± 66 <lb/>563 ± 75 <lb/>7 <lb/>140 ± 9 <lb/>2 1 ± 1 <lb/>8 <lb/>11 ± 0.4 <lb/>25 ± 2 <lb/>was measured (Figure 5(b)). Interestingly, the length of <lb/>the linker had little or no effect on the binding affinities <lb/>(Table 1), suggesting that with Af UGM the interaction <lb/>between the chromophore and some components of the <lb/>active site or perhaps directly with the flavin cofactor play a <lb/>major role in binding. Compound 3 and 4 bound to MtUGM <lb/>with similar affinities as chromophores 1 and 2, respectively. <lb/>In contrast to Af UGM, in the bacterial enzymes, the length <lb/>of the linker plays a major role in binding with longer <lb/>linkers increasing the affinity, further demonstrating that the <lb/>active-site architecture varied among the UGM enzymes. We <lb/>selected 3 as the FP probe for further characterization of the <lb/>binding assay. <lb/>3.3. Determination of Competitive Binding Using FP Assay. <lb/>FP competitive inhibition binding assay was conducted to <lb/>confirm that the FP probes bind to the active site on Af UGM. <lb/>First, the Z factor as a function of Af UGM was determined <lb/>to establish the proper enzyme concentration to be used in <lb/>the assay. The Z factor is a statistical parameter that reports <lb/>on the quality of the assay [18]. As shown in Figure 6, the FP <lb/>assay exhibits excellent quality at an Af UGM concentration <lb/>higher than 2 μM with a Z factor above 0.8. The minimum <lb/>value (2 μM) in this range was selected as the optimal assay <lb/>concentration. <lb/>The K d for UDP was determined using the FP assay by <lb/>titrating Af UGM with serial dilutions of UDP. A value of <lb/>9.0 ± 1.7 μM was obtained, which is in good agreement <lb/>with the K d (33 ± 9 μM) previously determined by directly <lb/>monitoring the flavin fluorescence (Figure 7(a)) [7]. <lb/>UDP-Galp was the second ligand tested in the FP <lb/>inhibition assay, and a K d value of 495 ± 66 μM was <lb/>calculated (Figure 7(b)), indicating that UDP-Galp is a poor <lb/>ligand for Af UGM, which agrees well with the observation <lb/>previously reported by Oppenheimer et al. [7]. <lb/>Recently, a series of prokaryotic UGM inhibitors were <lb/>identified from chemical libraries by high-throughput <lb/>screening (HTS) [14]. In our FP assay, we tested two of <lb/>the best prokaryotic UGM inhibitors, compound 7 and <lb/>compound 8 (Figure 8). Interestingly, they behaved differ-<lb/>ently on Af UGM. Compound 7 turned out to be a poor <lb/>ligand for Af UGM with a K d of 140 ± 9 μM (Figure 9(a)). <lb/>In contrast, compound 8 exhibits much better binding to <lb/>Af UGM (Figure 9(b)), and its K d was found to be 11 <lb/>± 0.4 μM (Table 2). We also tested these two compounds <lb/>in a secondary assay, directly monitoring the activity of <lb/>Af UGM to see if these molecules function as inhibitors. The <lb/>HPLC chromatograms (Figure 10) indicated that both of the <lb/>compounds inhibit the activity of Af UGM. These results <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Enzyme Research <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>confirm that the FP assay identifies ligands that bind to the <lb/>active site of Af UGM and that these molecules inhibit the <lb/>activity of the enzyme in a secondary assay that directly <lb/>measures product formation. <lb/>3.4. FP Assay Quality. The Z factor value using chro-<lb/>mophore 3 was calculated to be 0.79 ± 0.02. An assay with <lb/>a Z factor greater than 0.5 is considered a good assay; <lb/>therefore, our FP assay is suitable for HTS (Figure 6). We <lb/>also estimated the tolerance of the FP assay to DMSO by <lb/>calculating the Z factors at various DMSO concentrations, <lb/>because a majority of compounds in HTS libraries are <lb/>dissolved in DMSO. The Z factors were plotted against <lb/>DMSO concentrations to generate a DMSO calibration curve <lb/>(Figure 11), and our assay maintains excellent quality with <lb/>DMSO concentration up to 5% (v/v). <lb/>4. Conclusion <lb/>In conclusion, four fluorescently labeled UDP derivatives <lb/>(1-4) were synthesized and tested for binding to Af UGM. <lb/>Different from the bacterial UGM, the nature of the chro-<lb/>mophore enhanced binding to AfUGM while the length of <lb/>the linkers did not. UDP-TAMRA analogs (3 and 4) bind to <lb/>Af UGM with high affinities. Binding of chromophore 3 to <lb/>the active site of Af UGM was demonstrated by a competi-<lb/>tion experiment using UDP and UDP-Galp. Furthermore, <lb/>binding of known inhibitors of bacterial UGM was tested <lb/>against Af UGM, and it was found that these compounds <lb/>bound Af UGM, however, with lower affinities. Inhibition <lb/>of Af UGM, measuring product formation by HPLC, was <lb/>demonstrated with compounds 7 and 8. A Z factor of 0.79 <lb/>was calculated, and the assay was shown to exhibit good <lb/>tolerance to DMSO. We expect that the FP assay described <lb/>here will allow fast identification of Af UGM inhibitors from <lb/>chemical libraries. We believe that inhibitors of Af UGM <lb/>that block the biosynthesis of Galf could lead to novel <lb/>therapeutics against A. fumigatus-related diseases. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was supported in part by NIH Grants RO1 <lb/>GM094469 (P. Sobrado, PI) and RO1 AI082542 (R. Tarleton, <lb/>PI). M. Oppenheimer was supported by a fellowship from <lb/>the American Heart Association. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] R. J. Trof, A. Beishuizen, Y. J. Debets-Ossenkopp, A. R. <lb/>J. Girbes, and A. B. J. Groeneveld, &quot;Management of inva-<lb/>sive pulmonary aspergillosis in non-neutropenic critically ill <lb/>patients,&quot; Intensive Care Medicine, vol. 33, no. 10, pp. 1694-<lb/>1703, 2007. <lb/>[2] R. L. Kradin and E. J. Mark, &quot;The pathology of pulmonary <lb/>disorders due to Aspergillus spp,&quot; Archives of Pathology and <lb/>Laboratory Medicine, vol. 132, no. 4, pp. 606-614, 2008. <lb/>[3] S. Chong, T. S. Kim, W. J. Koh, E. Y. Cho, and K. Kim, <lb/>&quot;Invasive pulmonary aspergillosis complicated by pulmonary <lb/>artery occlusion in an immunocompetent patient,&quot; Clinical <lb/>Radiology, vol. 61, no. 3, pp. 287-290, 2006. <lb/>[4] C. Virnig and R. K. Bush, &quot;Allergic bronchopulmonary <lb/>aspergillosis: a US perspective,&quot; Current Opinion in Pulmonary <lb/>Medicine, vol. 13, no. 1, pp. 67-71, 2007. <lb/>[5] G. Chamilos, M. Luna, R. E. Lewis et al., &quot;Invasive fungal <lb/>infections in patients with hematologic malignancies in a <lb/>tertiary care cancer center: an autopsy study over a 15-year <lb/>period (1989-2003),&quot; Haematologica, vol. 91, no. 7, pp. 986-<lb/>989, 2006. <lb/>[6] J. P. Latge, &quot;Galactofuranose containing molecules in <lb/>Aspergillus fumigatus,&quot; Medical Mycology, vol. 47, 1, pp. <lb/>S104-S109, 2009. <lb/>[7] M. Oppenheimer, M. B. Poulin, T. L. Lowary, R. F. Helm, <lb/>and P. Sobrado, &quot;Characterization of recombinant UDP-<lb/>galactopyranose mutase from Aspergillus fumigatus,&quot; Archives <lb/>of Biochemistry and Biophysics, vol. 502, no. 1, pp. 31-38, 2010. <lb/>[8] P. S. Schmalhorst, S. Krappmann, W. Vervecken et al., &quot;Contri-<lb/>bution of galactofuranose to the virulence of the opportunistic <lb/>pathogen Aspergillus fumigatus,&quot; Eukaryotic Cell, vol. 7, no. 8, <lb/>pp. 1268-1277, 2008. <lb/>[9] D. Stynen, A. Goris, J. Sarfati, and J. P. Latge, &quot;A new <lb/>sensitive sandwich enzyme-linked immunosorbent assay to <lb/>detect galactofuran in patients with invasive Aspergillosis,&quot; <lb/>Journal of Clinical Microbiology, vol. 33, no. 2, pp. 497-500, <lb/>1995. <lb/>[10] C. Costachel, B. Coddeville, J. P. Latgé, and T. Fontaine, <lb/>&quot;Glycosylphosphatidylinositol-anchored fungal polysaccha-<lb/>ride in Aspergillus fumigatus,&quot; Journal of Biological Chemistry, <lb/>vol. 280, no. 48, pp. 39835-39842, 2005. <lb/>[11] C. Simenel, B. Coddeville, M. Delepierre, J. P. Latgé, and <lb/>T. Fontaine, &quot;Glycosylinositolphosphoceramides in Aspergillus <lb/>fumigatus,&quot; Glycobiology, vol. 18, no. 1, pp. 84-96, 2008. <lb/>[12] P. M. Nassau, S. L. Martin, R. E. Brown et al., &quot;Galactofu-<lb/>ranose biosynthesis in Escherichia coli K-12: identification <lb/>and cloning of UDP-galactopyranose mutase,&quot; Journal of <lb/>Bacteriology, vol. 178, no. 4, pp. 1047-1052, 1996. <lb/>[13] J. Engel, P. S. Schmalhorst, T. Dörk-Bousset, V. Ferrières, and <lb/>F. H. Routier, &quot;A single UDP-galactofuranose transporter is <lb/>required for galactofuranosylation in Aspergillus fumigatus,&quot; <lb/>Journal of Biological Chemistry, vol. 284, no. 49, pp. 33859-<lb/>33868, 2009. <lb/>[14] E. E. Carlson, J. F. May, and L. L. Kiessling, &quot;Chemical Probes <lb/>of UDP-Galactopyranose Mutase,&quot; Chemistry and Biology, vol. <lb/>13, no. 8, pp. 825-837, 2006. <lb/>[15] E. C. Dykhuizen and L. L. Kiessling, &quot;Potent ligands for <lb/>prokaryotic UDP-galactopyranose mutase that exploit an <lb/>enzyme subsite,&quot; Organic Letters, vol. 11, no. 1, pp. 193-196, <lb/>2009. <lb/>[16] R. P. Haugland, Handbook of Fluorescent Probes and Research <lb/>Chemicals, Molecular Probes, Eugene, Ore, USA, 1996. <lb/>[17] X. Yao, D. W. Bleile, Y. Yuan et al., &quot;Substrate directs enzyme <lb/>dynamics by bridging distal sites: UDP-galactopyranose <lb/>mutase,&quot; Proteins, vol. 74, no. 4, pp. 972-979, 2009. <lb/>[18] J. H. Zhang, T. D. Y. Chung, and K. R. Oldenburg, &quot;A simple <lb/>statistical parameter for use in evaluation and validation of <lb/>high throughput screening assays,&quot; Journal of Biomolecular <lb/>Screening, vol. 4, no. 2, pp. 67-73, 1999. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>