<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>FSH Modulates PKAI and GPR3 Activities in Mouse <lb/>Oocyte of COC in a Gap Junctional Communication (GJC)-<lb/>Dependent Manner to Initiate Meiotic Resumption <lb/>Junxia Li . , Guankun Mao . , Guoliang Xia* <lb/>State Key Laboratory for Agro-Biotechnology, College of Biological Science, China Agricultural University, Beijing, China <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Many studies have shown that cyclic adenosine-59-monophosphate (cAMP)-dependent protein kinase A (PKA) and G-<lb/>protein-coupled receptor 3 (GPR3) are crucial for controlling meiotic arrest in oocytes. However, it is unclear how <lb/>gonadotropins modulate these factors to regulate oocyte maturation, especially by gap junctional communication (GJC). <lb/>Using an in vitro meiosis-arrested mouse cumulus-oocyte complex (COC) culture model, we showed that there is a close <lb/>relationship between follicle-stimulating hormone (FSH) and the PKA type I (PKAI) and GPR3. The effect of FSH on oocyte <lb/>maturation was biphasic, initially inhibitory and then stimulatory. During FSH-induced maturation, rapid cAMP surges were <lb/>observed in both cumulus cells and oocyte. Most GJC between cumulus cells and oocyte ceased immediately after FSH <lb/>stimulation and recommenced after the cAMP surge. FSH-induced maturation was blocked by PKAI activator 8-AHA-cAMP. <lb/>Levels of PKAI regulatory subunits and GPR3 decreased and increased, respectively, after FSH stimulation. In the presence of <lb/>the GJC inhibitor carbenoxolone (CBX), FSH failed to induce the meiotic resumption and the changes in PKAI, GPR3 and <lb/>cAMP surge in oocyte were no longer detected. Furthermore, GPR3 was upregulated by high cAMP levels, but not by PKAI <lb/>activation. When applied after FSH stimulation, the specific phosphodiesterase 3A (PDE3A) inhibitor cilostamide <lb/>immediately blocked meiotic induction, regardless of when it was administered. PKAI activation inhibited mitogen-<lb/>activated protein kinase (MAPK) phosphorylation in the oocytes of COCs, which participated in the initiation of FSH-induced <lb/>meiotic maturation in vitro. Just before FSH-induced meiotic maturation, cAMP, PKAI, and GPR3 returned to basal levels, and <lb/>PDE3A activity and MAPK phosphorylation increased markedly. These experiments show that FSH induces a transient <lb/>increase in cAMP levels and regulates GJC to control PKAI and GPR3 activities, thereby creating an inhibitory phase. After <lb/>PDE3A and MAPK activities increase, meiosis resumes. <lb/>Citation: Li J, Mao G, Xia G (2012) FSH Modulates PKAI and GPR3 Activities in Mouse Oocyte of COC in a Gap Junctional Communication (GJC)-Dependent <lb/>Manner to Initiate Meiotic Resumption. PLoS ONE 7(9): e37835. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835 <lb/>Editor: Hongmei Wang, Institute of Zoology, Chinese Academy of Sciences, China <lb/>Received December 28, 2011; Accepted April 24, 2012; Published September 13, 2012 <lb/>Copyright: ß 2012 Li et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted <lb/>use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by National Basic Research Program of China (No. 2012CB944401 and No. 2012CB944701). The funders had no role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. <lb/>* E-mail: glxiachina@sohu.com <lb/>. These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Physiologically, even if fully grown oocytes in follicles acquire <lb/>complete maturation potential, they remain at the germinal vesicle <lb/>(GV) stage before the gonadotropin surge. Similar to in vivo <lb/>resumption of meiosis in response to gonadotropin signaling, <lb/>oocytes undergo meiotic maturation spontaneously when liberated <lb/>from the follicle into a suitable culture medium. Maintaining high <lb/>intracellular levels of cyclic adenosine-59-monophosphate (cAMP) <lb/>by modulation activity of adenylyl cyclase (AC), which catalyzes <lb/>the synthesis of cAMP, or phosphodiesterase (PDE), which <lb/>hydrolyzes cAMP, or by supplementing the culture medium with <lb/>cAMP analogs, will arrest oocytes in the prophase during the first <lb/>meiotic division [1,2], because it is believed that a consistently high <lb/>concentration of cAMP in mammalian oocytes is an important <lb/>factor for maintaining maturation arrest. <lb/>Elevated levels of cAMP in the oocyte maintain meiotic arrest <lb/>by activating protein kinase A (PKA). PKA regulates proteins <lb/>that control the activity of cyclin-dependent kinase 1 (CDK1) <lb/>[3]. These proteins include the phosphatase, CDC25 [4,5], and <lb/>the kinase, WEE IB [6]. When CDK1 is phosphorylated, it is <lb/>inactive, and oocytes become arrested in the prophase. However, <lb/>when it is dephosphorylated by CDC25, it becomes active, and <lb/>the prophase-to-metaphase transition occurs [5,7]. Thus, high <lb/>levels of cAMP in the oocyte keep PKA active and CDK1 <lb/>inactive, while low levels of cAMP reduce PKA activity and <lb/>allow CDK1 activation and meiotic progression. In vivo, cAMP in <lb/>oocyte is supplied not only by follicle cells, through gap <lb/>junctional communication (GJC), but also by oocyte itself. They <lb/>are all necessary for meiotic arrest. The mouse oocyte generates <lb/>cAMP through the G-protein-coupled receptor 3 (GPR3) <lb/>[8,9,10,11]; the Gs G-protein [12], and AC [13]. If any of these <lb/>components is inhibited or removed from the oocyte, germinal <lb/>vesicle breakdown (GVBD) proceeds spontaneously. Even if <lb/>additional cAMP generated in somatic cells enters the oocyte, <lb/>the amount is insufficient to maintain meiotic arrest in the <lb/>absence of GPR3 in the oocyte [9,10,11,14]. Recently, it was <lb/>reported that mouse mural granulosa cells express natriuretic <lb/>peptide precursor type C (NPPC) messenger RNA (mRNA), <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<front>September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></front>

			<body>whereas cumulus cells express mRNA encoding the NPPC <lb/>receptor NPR2, a guanylyl cyclase. NPPC increases cGMP levels <lb/>in cumulus cells and oocytes, and inhibits the resumption of <lb/>meiosis in vitro [15]. <lb/>Meiotic maturation in cumulus-oocyte complexes (COCs), but <lb/>not denuded oocytes (DOs), can be induced in vitro by follicle-<lb/>stimulating hormone (FSH). The FSH-induced COC model is <lb/>generally used to study mechanisms of gonadotropin-induced <lb/>oocyte maturation, because LH receptors are absent or expressed <lb/>at very low levels in cumulus cells, and LH has no effect on mouse <lb/>COC maturation [16,17]. <lb/>A cAMP surge in the follicle or COC may trigger GVBD <lb/>following stimulation with LH or FSH. It has been hypothesized <lb/>that a certain concentration of cAMP is maintained in GV <lb/>oocytes, while a transient increase in cAMP induced by hormonal <lb/>stimulation is likely to trigger GVBD [18]. The dramatic change <lb/>in cAMP levels may be an important stimulus for meiosis <lb/>reinitiation but not the absolute cAMP levels in the oocyte. When <lb/>gonadotropic hormones activate their receptors, cAMP is <lb/>produced in cumulus cells. In vitro studies have shown that FSH <lb/>induces an increase in cAMP levels in cumulus cells and in the <lb/>oocyte via diffusion from somatic cells through GJC [19]. <lb/>However, the meiotic resumption must involve a decrease in <lb/>oocyte cAMP levels. The uncoupling of cumulus cells from <lb/>oocytes by interruption of gap junctions accompanied by cumulus <lb/>expansion may block the elevation of intra-oocyte cAMP. <lb/>PDE3A, the major cAMP-hydrolyzing PDE present in the <lb/>oocyte, may degrade cAMP in oocytes. As the hydrolytic capacity <lb/>of PDE far exceeds the maximum rate of synthesis by AC, <lb/>cellular levels of cAMP are thought to be more sensitive to <lb/>inhibition of PDE than to changes in AC activity. Thus, an <lb/>increase in PDE enzyme activity may be involved in the <lb/>resumption of meiosis. <lb/>PDE3A has been shown to play a critical role in mouse oocyte <lb/>maturation; microinjection of active PDE into isolated mouse <lb/>oocytes arrested with the PDE inhibitor IBMX caused GVBD <lb/>[20]. The oocytes of female Pde3A 2/2 mice are unable to <lb/>undergo meiotic resumption despite normal follicular growth <lb/>and ovulation. Likewise, oocytes from Pde3A 2/2 mice do not <lb/>spontaneously mature when released from the follicles into <lb/>culture medium. The ability of these oocytes to resume meiosis <lb/>is restored by PKA inhibition or by microinjecting RNA <lb/>encoding the phosphatase CDC25 [21] and inactivation of Gs <lb/>or downregulation of the GPR3 can also restore meiotic <lb/>resumption in the Pde3A 2/2 oocytes [14]. Moreover, 59-AMP, <lb/>the product of PDE activity, may serve as a transducer of the <lb/>meiotic induction process by stimulating AMP-activated protein <lb/>kinase [22]. <lb/>Several studies have revealed that FSH has a biphasic effect <lb/>on oocyte maturation; after adding FSH, oocyte maturation <lb/>was initially inhibited and then stimulated [23,24,25]. Howev-<lb/>er, the mechanism involved remains unclear. Although PKAI, <lb/>GPR3, and PDE3A have been shown to participate in meiotic <lb/>arrest in oocytes, their relationships with FSH are not well <lb/>understood. <lb/>The aim of the present study was to determine the <lb/>molecular mechanisms underlying the biphasic effect of FSH <lb/>on oocyte maturation, especially the possible correlations <lb/>among GJC, PKAI, GPR3, PDE3A and mitogen-activated <lb/>protein kinase (MAPK), and to elucidate the signal transduc-<lb/>tion pathways involved in this process. Finally, to better <lb/>understand the mechanisms of gonadotropin-induced meiotic <lb/>resumption. <lb/>Results <lb/>FSH increases cAMP levels in both the oocyte and <lb/>cumulus cells of the cumulus-oocyte complex (COC) and <lb/>blocks oocyte-cumulus cell GJC <lb/>As observed previously, hypothaxing (HX) maintained meiosis <lb/>arrest in most COCs in the present study. FSH had a biphasic <lb/>effect on oocyte maturation, i.e., inhibitory during the first 8 h and <lb/>stimulatory after 8 h (Figure 1A). <lb/>To determine why FSH initially inhibited oocyte maturation, <lb/>mouse COCs were cultured in control HX medium or HX <lb/>medium supplemented with 50 IU/L FSH. At various time points, <lb/>oocytes and cumulus cells were collected and analyzed for cAMP <lb/>concentrations by radioimmunoassay (RIA). There was a notable <lb/>cAMP surge not only in cumulus cells, but also in oocytes, <lb/>approximately 30 min after FSH stimulation. However, the <lb/>change in cAMP level was much greater in cumulus cells than <lb/>in oocytes. In control COCs (not treated with FSH), cAMP levels <lb/>increased only slightly (Figure 1B and 1C). <lb/>During FSH-induced COC maturation, GJC between the <lb/>oocyte and the cumulus cells decreased sharply during the first <lb/>10 min of culture, thereafter remaining stable for 40 min, before <lb/>increasing to initial levels at 60 min. Compared to COCs cultured <lb/>in the presence of FSH, GJC in control COCs remained high at all <lb/>time points (Figure 1D). <lb/>The PKAI activator 8-AHA-cAMP inhibits FSH-induced <lb/>meiotic resumption in COCs but only when applied <lb/>within 4 h after FSH stimulation <lb/>The specific PKAI activator 8-AHA-cAMP inhibited FSH-<lb/>stimulated meiotic resumption and cumulus expansion in a dose-<lb/>dependent manner in COCs. The maturation rate of COCs <lb/>treated with 100 mM 8-AHA-cAMP was similar to that of COCs <lb/>treated with HX alone (Figure 2A). <lb/>To define the time period during which PKAI activity <lb/>modulated the effects of FSH stimulation, COCs were cultured <lb/>in the presence of 4 mM HX and 50 IU/L FSH. In one set of <lb/>cultures, 250 mM 8-AHA-cAMP was added 3, 4, 5 h after the start <lb/>of culture. The oocytes in all of these groups were examined after <lb/>22 h of culture for GVBD. When 8-AHA-cAMP was added to <lb/>cultures before 4 h from the start of culture, meiotic induction was <lb/>significantly reduced. In contrast, administration of 8-AHA-cAMP <lb/>after 4 h did not inhibit meiotic induction (Figure 2B). <lb/>FSH regulates levels of the regulatory subunit of PKAI (RI) <lb/>during its inhibitory phase, whereas activation of PKAI <lb/>results in down-regulation of its RI <lb/>Western blotting analysis showed that, under conditions of FSH <lb/>stimulation, RI levels in DOs, but not cumulus cells, were <lb/>significantly reduced at 2 h and subsequently increased. In control <lb/>cultures, RI levels decreased gradually during 0-8 h of culture <lb/>(Figure 3A and Figure S1A). PKA catalytic subunit (C) levels <lb/>showed no obvious changes. <lb/>We next attempted to define the relationship between PKAI <lb/>activation and RI downregulation. The 8-AHA-cAMP treatment <lb/>reduced RI levels in oocytes in a dose-dependent fashion, but had no <lb/>obvious effect on PKA C subunit levels (Figure 3B and Figure S1B). <lb/>GPR3 expression is increased by FSH at 2 h and is <lb/>induced by activation of AC but not PKAI <lb/>To evaluate the relationship between FSH and GPR3 before <lb/>the initiation of meiosis, we used the same FSH-induced <lb/>maturation model and Western blotting analysis. The effect of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>FSH on GPR3 expression was opposite to its effect on PKA RI <lb/>levels. Levels of GPR3 were markedly increased in DOs of COCs <lb/>treated with FSH for 2 h. No change was detected in cumulus cells <lb/>(Figure 4A and Figure S2A). To determine which factors may <lb/>control GPR3 expression, we treated COCs with the AC activator <lb/>forskolin. We found that AC activation contributed to the <lb/>upregulation of GPR3 in oocytes, but not in cumulus cells <lb/>(Figure 4B and Figure. S2B). However, there was no notable <lb/>change in GPR3 levels after PKAI was directly activated <lb/>(Figure 4C and Figure S2C). <lb/>The Effect of FSH on PKAI, GPR3 and cAMP surge in <lb/>oocyte needs GJC <lb/>In this experiment, BSA was replaced with polyvinylpyrrolidone <lb/>(PVP) because carbenoxolone (CBX) is less effective in BSA-<lb/>supplemented medium. COCs were pretreated for 30 min in HX <lb/>medium containing 100 mM CBX to block GJC. FSH was then <lb/>added to cultures, which were maintained for 22 h to examine <lb/>percentage maturation, or harvested at various time points to <lb/>detect cAMP concentrations or changes in PKAI or GPR3 levels <lb/>by Western blotting. In the CBX treatment groups, about 26.90% <lb/>of the COCs underwent maturation, compared to 88.03% of <lb/>COCs not treated with CBX (Figure 5A). CBX completely <lb/>suppressed FSH-induced GVBD and cumulus expansion <lb/>(Figure 5B). <lb/>As expected, the changes in PKAI and GPR3 levels were <lb/>abolished by the blockade of oocyte-cumulus cell GJC, and no <lb/>cAMP surge could be detected in the oocytes of FSH-stimulated <lb/>COCs. Changes in GPR3 and RI protein levels were similar to <lb/>those in the control groups in experiments 3 and 4 (Figure 5E and <lb/>Figure 1. FSH increases cAMP levels and blocks oocyte-cumulus cell gap junctional communication (GJC). (A) The biphasic effect of <lb/>FSH on oocyte maturation. Cumulus-oocyte complexes (COCs) were cultured with or without 50 IU/L FSH in HX medium for 22 h. The rate of GVBD <lb/>was scored in 2-h intervals during culture. FSH inhibited maturation during the first 8 h of the treatment period and stimulated maturation after 8 h. <lb/>*P,0.01 vs. the control group for that time point. (B) Changes in cAMP levels in cumulus cells of COCs after FSH treatment. (C) Changes in cAMP <lb/>levels in the oocytes of COCs stimulated with FSH. (D) Cumulus cell-oocyte GJC during FSH-induced in vitro oocyte maturation. COCs were cultured in <lb/>HX medium containing FSH (open circles) or not containing FSH (filled circles) for various periods of time. Then they were pulsed with calcein-AM, <lb/>denuded of surrounding cumulus cells, and assessed for intra-oocyte fluorescence. A mean of 10 oocytes were used at each time point in each of <lb/>three replicate experiments. **P,0.05, *P,0.01 vs. control. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Effect of PKAI on the FSH-induced resumption of <lb/>meiosis in COC. (A) The PKAI activator 8-AHA-cAMP (8-AHA) dose-<lb/>dependently inhibited the FSH-induced resumption of meiosis in COC. <lb/>(B) Cumulus expansion. Cumulus expansion was detected at the end of <lb/>22 h culture. HX, control; FSH, IU/L FSH; mM 8-AHA-cAMP; 100 mM <lb/>8-AHA-cAMP. Scale bar, approximately 50 mm. (C) The crucial period for <lb/>the effect of PKAI on FSH stimulation. When 8-AHA-cAMP was added to <lb/>cultures 3 or 4 h after the start of culture, meiotic induction was <lb/>significantly reduced. Administration of 8-AHA-cAMP 5 h after the start <lb/>of culture did not inhibit the induction of meiosis. Columns with <lb/>different superscripts are significantly different (P,0.05). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g002 <lb/>Figure 3. Effects of FSH on PKAI, and decrease in PKAI <lb/>regulatory subunit (RIa) levels after activation of PKAI. (A) <lb/>FSH reduced PKAI regulatory subunit RIa levels, but not levels of the <lb/>catalytic subunit (C) of PKAI, in oocytes of COCs (DOs), but not cumulus <lb/>cells (CCs), 2 h after the start of culture. DOs and CCs from 200 COCs <lb/>treated/not treated with FSH were collected at various time points and <lb/>analyzed by Western blotting. (B) PKAI activation resulted in a decrease <lb/>in RIa levels in oocytes. COCs were incubated in HX medium <lb/>supplemented with increasing concentrations of 8-AHA-cAMP (0-<lb/>mM) for 2 h. Oocytes of COCs were collected at 2 h for Western <lb/>blotting analysis of PKAI RIa and C levels. 8-AHA-cAMP reduced oocyte <lb/>RI levels in a dose-dependent fashion, but had no obvious effect on <lb/>PKAI C levels. Western blotting experiments were performed at least <lb/>three times with similar results. The blot shown is representative of <lb/>three experiments. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure S3). There was still a notable cAMP surge in cumulus cells <lb/>about 30 min after FSH stimulation. In oocytes, cAMP levels <lb/>increased gradually, which was similar to that in the control group <lb/>(not treated with FSH) (Figure 5C and 5D). <lb/>PDE3A inhibition blocks the effect of FSH on mouse <lb/>oocyte maturation, but not cumulus expansion <lb/>COCs were cultured in 4 mM HX and 50 IU/L FSH. In one <lb/>set of cultures, 2 mM cilostamide was added at different time points <lb/>after the start of culture. The oocytes in all of the groups were <lb/>examined at 22 h for GVBD. As shown in Figure 6A, when <lb/>cilostamide was added to the cultures, meiotic induction was <lb/>immediately blocked, regardless of the time point at which <lb/>cilostamide was administered, i.e., the percentage of GVBD at <lb/>22 h was identical to that at the time of cilostamide administration <lb/>(Figure 6A). However, cumulus expansion was normal (Figure 6B). <lb/>MAPK pathway in oocyte participates in the regulation of FSH-<lb/>induced COC meiotic resumption We pretreated COCs with FSH <lb/>for different periods of time and then stripped the cumulus cells <lb/>away. Then we cultured the denuded oocytes in fresh HX medium <lb/>without FSH for 22 h. The percentage of maturation of DOs from <lb/>COCs primed with FSH for h or more was significantly higher <lb/>(72.4% of COCs primed for 3 h) than in controls (26.67%) <lb/>(Figure 7A, open circles). <lb/>DOs from COCs primed with FSH for 3, 4, 5 or 6 h were <lb/>transferred to fresh HX medium containing the specific MAPK <lb/>inhibitor U0126, and were further cultured for a total 22 h. U0126 <lb/>significantly inhibited GVBD in the DOs. However, when U0126 <lb/>was added after 5 h, the difference between the U0126 and <lb/>control groups was non-significant (Figure 7A). <lb/>PKAI activation inhibits MAPK phosphorylation in the <lb/>oocyte of the COC <lb/>DOs from COCs were collected at 0, 2, 4, 6, 8 h for Western <lb/>blotting analysis with anti-p-ERK1/2 and anti-ERK2 antibodies <lb/>after culture in HX medium, HX medium containing FSH, or HX <lb/>medium containing FSH and 8-AHA-cAMP. Only very low levels <lb/>of MAPK phosphorylation were detected during culture in non-<lb/>supplemented HX medium. FSH activated MAPK in oocytes of <lb/>COCs, with phosphorylation reaching its maximum level at 8 h <lb/>(Figure 7B). 8-AHA-cAMP significantly inhibited MAPK phos-<lb/>phorylation (Figure 7C). <lb/>PDE3A activity increases significantly before the initiation <lb/>of meiosis <lb/>To determine how PDE3A activity changes during FSH-<lb/>induced oocyte maturation, we cultured COCs in HX medium or <lb/>HX medium containing 50 IU/L FSH. At different time points, <lb/>oocytes of COCs were collected and analyzed for PDE3A <lb/>enzymatic activity. There was a significant increase in PDE3A <lb/>activity in oocytes approximately 6 h after FSH stimulation. No <lb/>obvious change in PDE3 activity was detected in control oocytes at <lb/>any time point (Figure 6C). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>FSH had a biphasic effect on oocyte maturation, initially <lb/>inhibitory and then stimulatory. A large body of research has <lb/>addressed the mechanism of stimulation induced by FSH. The aim <lb/>of the present study was to investigate regulatory mechanisms <lb/>during the inhibitory phase. We found that FSH controls oocyte <lb/>maturation through the GJC-dependent modulation of the <lb/>activities of PKAI and GPR3 in mouse COCs, and that the <lb/>activities of MAPK and PDE3A are arrested until just before the <lb/>resumption of meiosis. <lb/>In vivo, FSH induces follicular development, but not oocyte <lb/>maturation. Studies from our lab have revealed that FSH increases <lb/>the levels of NPPC in mural granulose cells and that of its receptor <lb/>Npr2 in cumulus cells in vivo, as a result maintaining high levels of <lb/>cAMP in oocyte itself and meiotic arrest [15]. However, in vitro, <lb/>FSH also shows an inhibitory effect to meiotic resumption of COC <lb/>during its early culture, although at the end of culture, FSH <lb/>induces meiotic maturation. The one of the reasons may be that <lb/>there are not mural granulosa cells for FSH-induced COC model, <lb/>but NPPC on cumulus cells still exist. Although FSH can up <lb/>regulate the levels of Npr2 in cumulus cells [26], NPPC decreased <lb/>gradually after COCs are isolated from follicle. So, it may be one <lb/>Figure 4. GPR3 levels are increased by FSH, as well as the <lb/>activation of AC but not PKAI. (A) FSH increased GPR3 levels in DOs, <lb/>but not CCs, at 2 h, during the resumption of meiosis. DOs and CCs <lb/>from 200 COCs treated/not treated with FSH were collected at various <lb/>time points and analyzed by Western blotting. (B) Forskolin (For) <lb/>upregulated GPR3 levels in DOs, but not CCs. COCs were incubated in <lb/>HX medium supplemented with 5 mM forskolin for 3 h. Oocytes of COCs <lb/>were collected at 2 h for Western blot analysis of GPR3 levels. (C) Direct <lb/>activation of PKAI had no effect on the change in GPR3 levels. COCs <lb/>were incubated in HX medium supplemented with increasing <lb/>concentrations of 8-AHA-cAMP (0-250 mM) for 2 h; Oocytes of COCs <lb/>were collected at 2 h for Western blotting analysis of GPR3. Western <lb/>blotting experiments were performed at least three times with similar <lb/>results. The blot shown is representative of three experiments. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>of the reasons that FSH has a biphasic effect on oocyte maturation <lb/>in vitro. <lb/>The PKA holoenzyme is a tetramer consisting of two regulatory <lb/>(R) subunits and two inactive catalytic (C) subunits. There are two <lb/>major isoforms of PKA, types I and II, which are defined by the <lb/>presence of an RI or RII subunit. When cAMP binds to the R <lb/>subunits, active C monomers are released, which phosphorylate <lb/>substrates. In mice, four R subunits (RIa, RIb, RIIa, and RIIb) <lb/>and two C subunits (Ca and Cb) originating from distinct genes <lb/>are present. In mouse oocytes, only RI protein was detected by <lb/>photoaffinity labeling, but RI and RII were detected in cumulus <lb/>cells [27]. The predominant R subunit mRNA expressed in <lb/>oocytes was found to be RIa mRNA; no RIb or RIIb mRNA was <lb/>detected [28]. Downs and Hunziker-Dunn [27] demonstrated that <lb/>elevation of type I PKA in the oocyte is related to the maintenance <lb/>of meiotic arrest, while type II PKA mediates cAMP-stimulated <lb/>cumulus expansion and meiotic resumption. Persistent activation <lb/>of PKAI leads to suppression of spontaneous meiotic maturation. <lb/>Our results show that activation of PKAI leads to suppression of <lb/>FSH-induced meiotic maturation. This suppressive effect persisted <lb/>until 4 h after initial exposure to FSH. RI levels in oocytes from <lb/>COCs were significantly reduced at 2 h after stimulation with <lb/>FSH, but subsequently increased. There was no obvious change in <lb/>catalytic subunit levels. In cumulus cells, there was no change in <lb/>RI levels. <lb/>In our study, the decrease in PKAI R levels in oocytes suggests <lb/>the activation of PKAI, but the similar results have not been seen <lb/>in other reports and it is easy understood that reducing the <lb/>regulatory subunit levels would increase the population of free <lb/>catalytic subunits that can phosphorylate substrates. While RIa <lb/>levels in mouse oocytes were reduced to undetectable levels by <lb/>RNA-interference, the oocytes resumed maturation because they <lb/>also lacked Ca [28]. Therefore, modulation of PKA by <lb/>knockdown technology and physiological methods may be <lb/>different. Following FSH stimulation, although R levels did not <lb/>change before 2 h, a .8-fold increase in cAMP over basal levels <lb/>was observed at 30 min in oocytes. PKAI was activated as a result <lb/>of this increase in cAMP levels. PKAI activation may have peaked <lb/>at 2 h, because activation of PKAI after 4 h did not suppress <lb/>maturation. Similar to our results, in previous studies on rat PC12 <lb/>pheochromocytoma cells, forskolin induced 70% of total cellular <lb/>PKA activity within 30 min and this effect persisted throughout <lb/>2 h of stimulation [29,30]. Increased intracellular cAMP concen-<lb/>trations have been demonstrated to affect the stability of certain <lb/>mRNA species, including PKA regulatory subunit RIa mRNA <lb/>[31]. The decrease in RIa protein levels at 2 h may reflect the <lb/>instability of RIa mRNA. While PKAI is more sensitive to slight <lb/>increases in cAMP levels, PKAII responds preferentially to higher <lb/>cAMP levels because RI has a 2-to 8-fold higher affinity for cAMP <lb/>than RII [32]. We detected a .90-fold increase in cAMP over <lb/>basal levels in cumulus cells after FSH stimulation, but only an 8-<lb/>fold increase in cAMP levels in oocytes. Together with the <lb/>presence of PKAII in cumulus cells, this may contribute to the <lb/>different modulation of PKAI in oocytes and cumulus cells. <lb/>The effect of FSH on GPR3 expression in oocytes was opposite <lb/>to its effect on PKA RI levels. Like PKAI, no change was detected <lb/>in cumulus cells. GPR3 activates Gs, which stimulates AC in the <lb/>oocyte to elevate cAMP levels. Thus, the elevated cAMP levels in <lb/>oocytes of COCs after FSH stimulation may partly contribute to <lb/>the change in GPR3 expression. Because forskolin can also <lb/>upregulate GPR3, upregulation of GPR3 after FSH stimulation <lb/>results from high cAMP levels. According to the generally <lb/>accepted paradigm for cAMP-induced transcription of genes, <lb/>cAMP activates PKA, which in turn phosphorylates cAMP <lb/>responsive element (CRE)-binding protein (CREB), which medi-<lb/>ates transcription of cAMP-responsive genes. We found two <lb/>CREB-binding sites in the GPR3 gene promoter, one located 106 <lb/>base pairs (bp) upstream of the transcription initiation site and the <lb/>other 67 bp downstream of the transcription initiation site (http:// <lb/>www.sabiosciences.com/chipqpcrsearch.php?species_id=1&amp;factor= <lb/>CREB&amp;gene=GPR3&amp;nfactor=n&amp;ninfo=n&amp;ngene=n&amp;B2=Search). <lb/>Because most known functional CREs are located within 170 bp <lb/>upstream of the transcription start site [33], the putative CRE <lb/>located upstream of the GPR3 transcription initiation may be <lb/>functional and cAMP-inducible. While we still do not know the role <lb/>of the CRE located downstream of the transcription start site, we <lb/>proved that activation of PKAI did not affect the expression of <lb/>GPR3. In NG108-15 cells, forskolin-induced nuclear translocation of <lb/>the catalytic subunits is only blocked by a type II PKA inhibitor, <lb/>forskolin-triggered phosphorylation of CREB depends only on <lb/>PKAII, and PKAI regulates a downstream cytoplasmic pathway <lb/>leading to activation of other transcription cofactors that interact <lb/>with phosphorylated CREB to induce gene transcription [34]. This <lb/>means that both PKA isoforms are involved in the mediation of <lb/>CREB-driven transcription in response to cAMP. Although levels of <lb/>RIa mRNA are 10-to 40-fold higher than those of RIIa mRNA in <lb/>oocytes [28], RII protein was detected in oocytes by immunofluo-<lb/>rescence staining, and showed a punctuate distribution within the <lb/>cytoplasm [35]. Although the amount of PKAII is very low, it may <lb/>have a crucial role in oocytes (e.g., in the control of gene <lb/>transcription). Based on our results, we propose that GPR3 is <lb/>regulated by a positive feedback mechanism, i.e., when cAMP levels <lb/>are elevated, GPR3 expression is upregulated and more cAMP is <lb/>produced. <lb/>FSH receptors are only present in cumulus cells which are <lb/>coupled to oocyte via GJC. GJC is necessary for normal oocyte <lb/>growth [36] and, in particular, control of the meiotic cell cycle <lb/>[37,38,39,40]. Similar to a previous report on isolated rat follicles <lb/>exposed to LH [41], our results show that GJC between oocytes <lb/>and the cumulus cells was significantly reduced soon after FSH <lb/>stimulation, and was gradually restored after the cAMP surge. <lb/>Why is there also a cAMP surge in oocyte at 30 min after the <lb/>stimulation of FSH? Our results show that during the time from <lb/>10 min to 40 min, although it is the lowest levels of GJC opening, <lb/>there is still about 15% opening GJC compared with the initial <lb/>Figure 5. The effects of GJC on PKAI, GPR3 levels and cAMP surge in oocytes of COCs stimulated by FSH. (A) Carbenoxolone (CBX) <lb/>completely suppressed FSH-induced GVBD. COCs were preincubated for 0.5 h in HX medium containing 100 mM CBX. Then FSH was added to some <lb/>COC cultures, and the cultures were maintained for 22 h. Percent GVBD was then determined. The bar marked with the asterisk is significantly <lb/>different from the other bars. (B) CBX suppressed FSH-induced cumulus expansion of COC. HX, control; FSH, 50 IU/L FSH; HX+CBX, HX medium <lb/>supplemented with 100 mM CBX; FSH+CBX, HX medium supplemented with 50 IU/L FSH and 100 mM CBX. Scale bar, approximately 50 mm. (C) cAMP <lb/>levels in cumulus cells (CCs) of COCs preincubated with CBX and then treated with FSH. (D) cAMP levels in oocytes of COCs preincubated with CBX <lb/>and then treated with FSH. A mean of 100 COCs were used at each time point in each of three replicate experiments. The mean SEM of three <lb/>individual experiments are shown. (E) Inhibition of oocyte-cumulus cell GJC abolished FSH-induced changes in PKAI and GPR3 levels. COCs were <lb/>preincubated for 0.5 h in HX medium containing 100 mM CBX. Then FSH was added to the culture medium. DOs and CCs from 200 COCs treated/not <lb/>treated with FSH were collected at various time points and analyzed by Western blotting. The blot shown is representative of three experiments. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>levels, thus when the cAMP levels in cumulus cell change sharply, <lb/>the cAMP levels in oocyte will be affected by that in cumulus, but <lb/>due to a small amount of opening GJC, the change level of cAMP <lb/>of oocyte is much less than that in cumulus cells. <lb/>Oocyte can communicate with cumulus cells through not only <lb/>the cell-cell coupling pathway, but also paracrine pathways. Our <lb/>results show that changes in cAMP, PKAI, and GPR3 levels in the <lb/>oocyte followed the effects of FSH on cumulus cells. To distinguish <lb/>the cell-cell coupling and paracrine pathways, we blocked oocyte-<lb/>cumulus cell GJC and then treated oocytes with FSH. We found <lb/>that the FSH-induced cAMP surge in the oocyte mainly depended <lb/>on patent gap junctions with neighboring cumulus cells, and that <lb/>inhibition of oocyte-cumulus cell GJC abolished the changes in <lb/>PKA I and GPR3. This indicates that all of these responses require <lb/>GJC. Although GPR3 mainly exists in oocytes, there seemed to be <lb/>no cAMP-activated cumulus cell-derived GPR3 ligands with <lb/>paracrine effects on oocytes in our study. The results presented <lb/>above suggest that modulation of the closing and opening of GJC <lb/>is important for gonadotropin-induced maturation, and that <lb/>closing GJC continually results in FSH losing its power of <lb/>inducing meiotic maturation, which may result from continual <lb/>PKAI activation. <lb/>As mentioned above, PKA may inactivate Cdc25B during <lb/>meiotic arrest. Inactive Cdc25B fails to activate MPF. PKA can <lb/>also activate Wee1B, thereby leading to MPF inactivation. PKA/ <lb/>Cdc25B and PKA/Wee1B pathways most likely work in a <lb/>synergistic manner to maintain an inactive Cdc2/cyclin B <lb/>complex and regulate the resumption of meiosis in mouse oocytes <lb/>[42]. However, our results show that activation of mitogen-<lb/>activated protein kinase (MAPK) in oocytes is important for the <lb/>oocyte maturationinduced by FSH. and that PKA could inhibit <lb/>the activation of MAPK. <lb/>MAPK is more abundantly expressed in both oocytes and <lb/>cumulus cells in later stages of meiosis. It is well known that <lb/>gonadotropic stimulation of meiotic resumption depends on <lb/>MAPK activation in the somatic compartment of the follicle, but <lb/>not in the oocyte, while intra-oocyte MAPK cascade activation is <lb/>more closely related to post-GVBD events such as meiotic spindle <lb/>organization [43,44]. Strong evidence comes from knockout <lb/>studies. Oocytes of c-mos-knockout mice undergo spontaneous <lb/>GVBD with an abnormal polar body [45,46], but granulosa cell-<lb/>specific knockout oocytes do not mature [47]. Treating COCs <lb/>with MAPK inhibitors inhibits MAPK signaling not only in <lb/>cumulus cells, but also in oocytes. It is thus difficult to determine <lb/>which compartment is more important. Although the microinjec-<lb/>tion of oocytes can interfere with MAPK function, the technolog-<lb/>ical barrier is relatively high. Our gonadotropin-priming model <lb/>allowed us to confirm the importance of MAPK in the oocyte itself <lb/>for the resumption of meiosis. In our study, U0126 was used to <lb/>inhibit MAPK pathway, it inhibits the second kinase from the <lb/>Figure 6. Correlations between FSH and PDE3A. (A) Inhibiting <lb/>PDE3A blocked the effect of FSH on maturation. COCs were cultured in <lb/>HX medium containing 50 IU/L FSH. Cilostamide (cilo) was added to <lb/>one set of cultures 3, 4, 5, 6, 7, or 8 h after the start of culture. GVBD was <lb/>assessed at 22 h (gray bars). The other set of cultures was examined at <lb/>different intervals up to 8 h (black bars). Cilostamide blocked further <lb/>meiotic maturation at each time point at which it was administered. <lb/>GVBD percentage of the controls is indicated by the box. (B) Inhibiting <lb/>PDE3A didn&apos;t affect cumulus expansion induced by FSH. Cumulus <lb/>expansion was detected at the end of 22 h culture. HX, control; FSH, <lb/>50 IU/L FSH; FSH 3 h+Cilo, Cilostamide (cilo) was added to culture 3 h <lb/>after the start of FSH treatment. FSH 8 h+Cilo, Cilostamide (cilo) was <lb/>added to culture 8 h after the start of FSH treatment. Scale bar, <lb/>approximately 50 mm. (C) After stimulation with FSH for 6 h, oocyte <lb/>PDE3A activity significantly increased. Means marked with asterisks are <lb/>significantly different (*P,0.05, **P,0.01). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>bottom of MAPK pathway, namely, MEK, but not the last, MOS. <lb/>Now, there is not MEK 2/2 oocyte, and none knows the effect of <lb/>MEK on oocyte meiotic maturation. Thus, it is the possible reason <lb/>that our result is different from that of mos knockout. The other <lb/>possibility is that there is some compensatory mechanism in mos 2/2 <lb/>oocyte for meiosis resumption, which compensates the lost of MOS <lb/>partly. In addition, we make sure that we can pick up the oocyte <lb/>whose cumulus cells are excluded absolutely. Although we are not <lb/>sure whether some projections of cumulus cell were still stay in zona <lb/>after removing of cumulus cells, no evidence has shown that MAPK <lb/>can pass through the projections. Thus, it really needs a deep study. <lb/>Intra-oocyte MAPK was not activated by FSH after activation of <lb/>PKAI, which suggests that FSH activation of type I PKA in oocytes <lb/>is required for inhibition of not only MPF, but also MAPK. Previous <lb/>work on NG108-15 cells demonstrated that activation of PKA by <lb/>ethanol inhibits B-Raf kinase activity, resulting in decreased MAPK <lb/>phosphorylation, i.e., inhibition of MAPK signaling [48]. We think <lb/>that naturally, MAPK pathway in oocyte itself participates in the <lb/>regulation of FSH-induced COC maturation and makes the process <lb/>of GVBD more normal and successful than that of inhibition of <lb/>MAPK. <lb/>Before the initiation of meiotic resumption, the activities of MPF <lb/>and MAPK must be restored. This depends on inactivation of <lb/>PKA, which in turn depends on a decrease in the cAMP level. <lb/>PDE3A is the major cAMP-hydrolyzing PDE present in oocytes, <lb/>and it is important for the maintenance of meiotic arrest and <lb/>oocyte maturation. Therefore, it is not surprising that the PDE3A <lb/>inhibitor cilostamide prevented FSH-induced maturation, regard-<lb/>less of the time at which it was administered. PDE3A clearly has a <lb/>permissive role in the control of FSH-induced oocyte maturation, <lb/>although the COCs still appeared fully expanded, which indicates <lb/>that cumulus expansion can be independent of GVBD. During <lb/>FSH-induced maturation, PDE3A activity is tightly controlled, <lb/>increasing markedly immediately before the resumption of <lb/>meiosis. However, the precise mechanism of PDE3A activation <lb/>in oocytes is unknown. <lb/>In conclusion, the results of this study demonstrate that FSH, <lb/>acting on cumulus cells of COCs, regulates the activities of PKAI <lb/>and GPR3 in oocytes in a GJC-dependent manner. Active PKAI <lb/>inhibits the activation of MAPK in oocytes, which is important for <lb/>the FSH-induced meiosis resumption. Until immediately before <lb/>the resumption of meiosis, PDE3A activity is not elevated, <lb/>resulting in very low cAMP levels. Inactivation of PKAI results <lb/>in the activation of MAPK and MPF, resulting in the meiotic <lb/>resumption. These are the potential causes of the biphasic function <lb/>of FSH. Our work links the inhibitory and stimulatory phases of <lb/>FSH action and improves our understanding of the mechanisms of <lb/>gonadotropin-induced meiotic resumption. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Experimental animals <lb/>Immature to 23 days old Kunming White female mice <lb/>(outbreed strain) were used for all experiments. All animal <lb/>treatment procedures were approved by the Animal Care <lb/>Committee of China Agricultural University (CAU). Mice were <lb/>provided with water and chow ad libitum and housed in air-<lb/>conditioned rooms illuminated for 12 h per day. Follicle develop-<lb/>ment was primed by intraperitoneal injection of each mouse with <lb/>5 IU pregnant mare serum gonadotropin (PMSG) and mice were <lb/>killed by cervical dislocation 46-48 h later. <lb/>Chemicals <lb/>All reagents and chemicals used in this study were obtained <lb/>from Sigma-Aldrich Corp (St. Louis, MO), unless otherwise <lb/>indicated. FSH was prepared as stock solutions in filtered <lb/>phosphate buffered saline (PBS) containing 0.1% BSA. Carbenox-<lb/>olone (3b-hydroxy-11-oxoolean-12-en-30-oic acid 3-hemisucci-<lb/>nate, CBX) was prepared as stock solutions in PBS. U0126, <lb/>8-AHA-cAMP (catalog number: A2104 [27]), and Forskolin were <lb/>prepared in dimethylsulfoxide (DMSO) and the final concentration <lb/>Figure 7. Correlations between FSH and MAPK and PKAI in <lb/>oocytes. (A) Activation of MAPK in the oocytes of COCs was required <lb/>for FSH-induced meiotic maturation. DOs from the COCs primed with <lb/>FSH for 3, 4, 5, or 6 h were transferred to fresh HX medium containing <lb/>the specific MAPK inhibitor U0126 and were further cultured for a total <lb/>22 h. U0126 significantly inhibited GVBD in DOs. Means marked with <lb/>asterisks are significantly different (*P,0.05, **P,0.01). (B) FSH-<lb/>activated MAPK in oocytes of COCs. Oocytes of COCs were collected <lb/>after treatment with FSH for 0, 2, 4, 6, or 8 h for Western blot analysis of <lb/>MAPK phosphorylation. (C) PKAI activation inhibited FSH-induced MAPK <lb/>phosphorylation in oocytes of COCs. Oocytes from COCs were collected <lb/>8 h after treatment for Western blot analysis of MAPK phosphorylation. <lb/>DOs from 100 COCs were collected at various time points for Western <lb/>blotting. The blot shown is representative of three experiments. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0037835.g007 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<body>of DMSO was less than 0.1%, which had no significant effect on <lb/>oocyte maturation (data not shown). Polyclonal rabbit anti-PKA RI <lb/>antibody (catalog number: sc-28893 [49]), polyclonal rabbit anti-<lb/>PKA Ca antibody (catalog number: sc-903 [25]), Polyclonal rabbit <lb/>anti-GPR3 antibody (catalog number: sc-68876 [50]), monoclonal <lb/>mouse anti-p-ERK1/2, polyclonal rabbit anti-ERK2 antibody, <lb/>monoclonal mouse glyceraldehyde-3-phosphate dehydrogenase <lb/>(GAPDH) antibody, and horseradish peroxidase-conjugated second <lb/>antibodies were purchased from Santa Cruz Biotechnology, Inc. <lb/>(Santa Cruz, CA, USA). <lb/>Oocyte isolation and culture <lb/>Ovaries were removed, placed in culture medium, and large <lb/>antral follicles (300-400 mm) were punctured under a stereomi-<lb/>croscope with sterile 27-gauge needles. Cumulus-oocyte complexes <lb/>(COCs) of equal size with several layers of cumulus cells were <lb/>collected. In each experiment, one group COCs were cultured in a <lb/>100 ml drop covered with paraffin oil in a 35-mm culture dish. <lb/>Oocytes were cultured at 37uC, in an atmosphere of 5% CO 2 <lb/>and 100% humidity. After culture, oocytes were denuded <lb/>mechanically and assessed for maturation scoring for GV (meiotic <lb/>arrest), GVBD (meiotic resumption). The percent of GVBD <lb/>(including polar body 1) per total number of oocytes (% GVBD) <lb/>were calculated. Oocytes that had degenerated were excluded. <lb/>The culture medium used for this study was M199 (GIBCO-<lb/>Invitrogen, Carlsbad, CA, USA) medium containing 4 mM HX; <lb/>0.23 mM sodium pyruvate; 2 mM glutamine; 3 mg/ml lyophi-<lb/>lized crystallized BSA; 75 mg/ml potassium penicillin G; and <lb/>50 mg/ml streptomycin sulfate. This medium is designated as HX <lb/>medium. <lb/>Western blot analysis <lb/>Proteins from cumulus cells (CC) or denuded oocytes (DO) of <lb/>COCs per sample were extracted with double-strength electro-<lb/>phoresis sample buffer after culture, supplemented with 1 mM <lb/>phenylmethylsulfonylfluoride and 1 mM sodium orthovanadate <lb/>for 20 min on ice, and stored at 280uC. Before electrophoresis, <lb/>the lysates were heated to 100uC for 5 min, cooled down on ice <lb/>immediately, and then centrifuged at 12,000 g for 5 min. The <lb/>proteins were separated by SDS-PAGE with a 4% stacking gel and <lb/>a 10% separating gel for 50 min at 160 V, and electrically <lb/>transferred to a nitrocellulose membrane (Amersham Pharmacia <lb/>Biotech, Braunschweig, Germany). The membrane was saturated <lb/>with 5% nonfat dry milk and then incubated with corresponding <lb/>antibody. Proteins were detected using SuperSignal West Pico TM <lb/>(enhanced chemiluminescence) detection system (Pierce Chemical <lb/>Co., Rockford, IL). <lb/>Determination of cAMP by radioimmunoassay (RIA) <lb/>After different incubation time, COCs were denuded by manual <lb/>pipetting with a small fine-bore pipette in HX medium containing <lb/>0.2 mM 3-isobutyl-1-methylxanthine (IBMX). CC and homoge-<lb/>neous DO were collected separately. In a volume less than 5 m1, <lb/>DOs isolated from the cultured COCs were transferred to 100 m1 <lb/>of 0.1 M HCl. CCs were centrifuged at 8,000 g for 5 min, and the <lb/>supernatant (culture medium) were pipetted out and 100 m1 of <lb/>0.1 M HCl was added. All samples were kept on ice for at least <lb/>10 min, and then stored at 280uC. An equal volume of medium <lb/>was collected and used as a blank. Prior to RIA, samples were <lb/>thawed and centrifuged at 12,000 g for 5 min and the supernatant <lb/>was collected to a glass tube and dried in a 60uC oven. The entire <lb/>samples were assayed for cAMP as the RIA kit (A Beckman coulter <lb/>company, Immunotech, IM1117, USA) procedure described. <lb/>Measured cAMP was proportional to the number of DOs or <lb/>CCs, which is equal to the number of COCs. <lb/>Oocyte-cumulus cell gap junctional communication <lb/>(GJC) assay <lb/>The oocyte-cumulus cell GJC was assayed using fluorescent dye, <lb/>calcein-AM [51]. Calcein-AM is nonfluorescent, electrically <lb/>neutral, and highly lipophilic because of the acetoxymethyl groups <lb/>in the molecule and can rapidly permeate into the cytoplasm <lb/>through the cell membrane. Once inside the cell, nonspecific <lb/>endogenous esterases cleave the lipophilic acetoxymethyl groups, <lb/>producing calcein-a fluorescent, negatively charged molecule <lb/>that is unable to leak out of cells across the plasma membrane, but <lb/>is able to pass between cells connected via gap junctions. Cumulus-<lb/>oocyte GJC was measured by quantitative fluorescence microsco-<lb/>py as the amount of calcein in the oocyte, transferred from the <lb/>cumulus cells through gap junctions via passive diffusion. <lb/>COCs were cultured in HX medium or HX medium+FSH for <lb/>5, 10, 20, 30, 40, 50 or 60 min after which they were transferred to <lb/>a solution of 1 mM calcein-AM freshly made up in a modified <lb/>phenol red-free and protein-free HX Medium+polyvinylpyrroli-<lb/>done (PVP, 0.3 mg/ml;), which is designated as modified medium, <lb/>for 1 min, and were then transferred to calcein-AM free modified <lb/>media and cultured for a further 3 min to allow for dye exchange <lb/>between the cumulus cells and the oocyte. Unincorporated dye <lb/>was then removed by three washes in calcein-AM-free modified <lb/>medium. Prior to fluorescence analysis, COCs were completely <lb/>denuded of their surrounding cumulus cells using vigorous <lb/>pipetting. The intraoocyte fluorescence emission of calcein in <lb/>pulsed oocytes was measured using a fluorophotometric-inverted <lb/>microscope (Leica, Wetzlar, Germany). DOs in the experimental <lb/>field of view were analyzed singularly and independently from <lb/>neighboring oocytes. Fluorescence readings of DO in each <lb/>replicate experiment are represented as relative fluorescence <lb/>intensity compared to that of t = 0 h (%). <lb/>PDE3A enzymatic activity assay <lb/>COCs were cultured in HX medium or HX medium+FSH for <lb/>0, 2, 4, 6 or 8 h after which they were denuded. DOs were <lb/>collected and homogenized in an isotonic buffer containing <lb/>10 mM sodium phosphate buffer pH 7.2, 50 mM NaF, 150 mM <lb/>NaCl, 2 mM EDTA, 5 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 30 mM sodium <lb/>pyrophosphate, 3 mM benzamidine, 5 mg/ml leupeptin, 20 mg/ <lb/>ml pepstatin, 2 mM phenylmethylsulfonyl fluoride, 1 mM micro-<lb/>cystin and 0.5% triton X-100. The homogenate was centrifuged <lb/>for 30 min at 14,000 g to obtain a soluble fraction [52]. PDE3A <lb/>activity was assayed using 1 mM cAMP as substrate according to <lb/>the method of Thompson [53]. Samples were assayed at 34uC in a <lb/>final volume of 200 ml; the solution consisting of 40 mM Tris-HCl <lb/>pH 8.0, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 5 mM 2-mercaptoethanol, 1 mg/ml <lb/>BSA, 1 mM cAMP and 15 nM [ H]cAMP (Perkin-Elmer Life <lb/>Sciences, Boston, MA). <lb/>Statistics <lb/>Each oocyte maturation experiment was conducted at least <lb/>three times with at least 30 oocytes per group per experiment. <lb/>Data are reported as the mean percentage of GVBD SEM. <lb/>Maturation frequencies were subjected to arcsin transformation <lb/>and analysed statistically by ANOVA followed by Duncan&apos;s <lb/>multiple range test and the other data no-transformed were <lb/>analysed by the same test (SigmaStat; Systat Software, Inc., <lb/>Richmond, CA, USA). A p value,0.05 was considered significant. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Supporting Information <lb/>Figure S1 Quantification of immunoblots correspond-<lb/>ing to the Figure 3. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S2 Quantification of immunoblots correspond-<lb/>ing to the Figure 4. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S3 Quantification of immunoblots correspond-<lb/>ing to the Figure 5. The densitometric data of the target <lb/>proteins were normalized according to GAPDH to evaluate the <lb/>relative abundance of them. Columns with different superscripts <lb/>are significantly different (P,0.05). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceived and designed the experiments: JXL GKM. Performed the <lb/>experiments: JXL GKM. Analyzed the data: JXL GKM. Contributed <lb/>reagents/materials/analysis tools: JXL GKM GLX. Wrote the paper: JXL <lb/>GKM. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Downs SM, Daniel SA, Bornslaeger EA, Hoppe PC, Eppig JJ (1989) <lb/>Maintenance of meiotic arrest in mouse oocytes by purines: modulation of <lb/>cAMP levels and cAMP phosphodiesterase activity. Gamete Res 23: 323-334. <lb/>2. Downs SM, Eppig JJ (1984) Cyclic adenosine monophosphate and ovarian <lb/>follicular fluid act synergistically to inhibit mouse oocyte maturation. <lb/>Endocrinology 114: 418-427. <lb/>3. Han SJ, Conti M (2006) New pathways from PKA to the Cdc2/cyclin B <lb/>complex in oocytes: Wee1B as a potential PKA substrate. Cell Cycle 5: 227-231. <lb/>4. Duckworth BC, Weaver JS, Ruderman JV (2002) G2 arrest in Xenopus oocytes <lb/>depends on phosphorylation of cdc25 by protein kinase A. Proc Natl Acad Sci <lb/>U S A 99: 16794-16799. <lb/>5. Lincoln AJ, Wickramasinghe D, Stein P, Schultz RM, Palko ME, et al. (2002) <lb/>Cdc25b phosphatase is required for resumption of meiosis during oocyte <lb/>maturation. Nat Genet 30: 446-449. <lb/>6. Freudzon L, Norris RP, Hand AR, Tanaka S, Saeki Y, et al. (2005) Regulation <lb/>of meiotic prophase arrest in mouse oocytes by GPR3, a constitutive activator of <lb/>the Gs G protein. J Cell Biol 171: 255-265. <lb/>7. Pirino G, Wescott MP, Donovan PJ (2009) Protein kinase A regulates <lb/>resumption of meiosis by phosphorylation of Cdc25B in mammalian oocytes. <lb/>Cell Cycle 8: 665-670. <lb/>8. Mehlmann LM, Saeki Y, Tanaka S, Brennan TJ, Evsikov AV, et al. (2004) The <lb/>Gs-linked receptor GPR3 maintains meiotic arrest in mammalian oocytes. <lb/>Science 306: 1947-1950. <lb/>9. Mehlmann LM (2005) Oocyte-specific expression of Gpr3 is required for the <lb/>maintenance of meiotic arrest in mouse oocytes. Dev Biol 288: 397-404. <lb/>10. Ledent C, Demeestere I, Blum D, Petermans J, Hamalainen T, et al. (2005) <lb/>Premature ovarian aging in mice deficient for Gpr3. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A <lb/>102: 8922-8926. <lb/>11. Hinckley M, Vaccari S, Horner K, Chen R, Conti M (2005) The G-protein-<lb/>coupled receptors GPR3 and GPR12 are involved in cAMP signaling and <lb/>maintenance of meiotic arrest in rodent oocytes. Dev Biol 287: 249-261. <lb/>12. Mehlmann LM, Jones TL, Jaffe LA (2002) Meiotic arrest in the mouse follicle <lb/>maintained by a Gs protein in the oocyte. Science 297: 1343-1345. <lb/>13. Horner K, Livera G, Hinckley M, Trinh K, Storm D, et al. (2003) Rodent <lb/>oocytes express an active adenylyl cyclase required for meiotic arrest. Dev Biol <lb/>258: 385-396. <lb/>14. Vaccari S, Horner K, Mehlmann LM, Conti M (2008) Generation of mouse <lb/>oocytes defective in cAMP synthesis and degradation: endogenous cyclic AMP is <lb/>essential for meiotic arrest. Dev Biol 316: 124-134. <lb/>15. Zhang M, Su YQ, Sugiura K, Xia G, Eppig JJ (2010) Granulosa cell ligand <lb/>NPPC and its receptor NPR2 maintain meiotic arrest in mouse oocytes. Science <lb/>330: 366-369. <lb/>16. Eppig JJ, Wigglesworth K, Pendola F, Hirao Y (1997) Murine oocytes suppress <lb/>expression of luteinizing hormone receptor messenger ribonucleic acid by <lb/>granulosa cells. Biol Reprod 56: 976-984. <lb/>17. Diaz FJ, Wigglesworth K, Eppig JJ (2007) Oocytes determine cumulus cell <lb/>lineage in mouse ovarian follicles. J Cell Sci 120: 1330-1340. <lb/>18. Dekel N, Galiani D, Sherizly I (1988) Dissociation between the inhibitory and <lb/>the stimulatory action of cAMP on maturation of rat oocytes. Mol Cell <lb/>Endocrinol 56: 115-121. <lb/>19. Webb RJ, Marshall F, Swann K, Carroll J (2002) Follicle-stimulating hormone <lb/>induces a gap junction-dependent dynamic change in [cAMP] and protein <lb/>kinase a in mammalian oocytes. Dev Biol 246: 441-454. <lb/>20. Bornslaeger EA, Mattei P, Schultz RM (1986) Involvement of cAMP-dependent <lb/>protein kinase and protein phosphorylation in regulation of mouse oocyte <lb/>maturation. Dev Biol 114: 453-462. <lb/>21. Masciarelli S, Horner K, Liu C, Park SH, Hinckley M, et al. (2004) Cyclic <lb/>nucleotide phosphodiesterase 3A-deficient mice as a model of female infertility. <lb/>J Clin Invest 114: 196-205. <lb/>22. Downs SM, Hudson ER, Hardie DG (2002) A potential role for AMP-activated <lb/>protein kinase in meiotic induction in mouse oocytes. Dev Biol 245: 200-212. <lb/>23. Downs SM, Daniel SA, Eppig JJ (1988) Induction of maturation in cumulus cell-<lb/>enclosed mouse oocytes by follicle-stimulating hormone and epidermal growth <lb/>factor: evidence for a positive stimulus of somatic cell origin. J Exp Zool 245: 86-<lb/>96. <lb/>24. Downs SM, Chen J (2008) EGF-like peptides mediate FSH-induced maturation <lb/>of cumulus cell-enclosed mouse oocytes. Mol Reprod Dev 75: 105-114. <lb/>25. Ning G, Ouyang H, Wang S, Chen X, Xu B, et al. (2008) 39,59-cyclic adenosine <lb/>monophosphate response element binding protein up-regulated cytochrome <lb/>P450 lanosterol 14alpha-demethylase expression involved in follicle-stimulating <lb/>hormone-induced mouse oocyte maturation. Mol Endocrinol 22: 1682-1694. <lb/>26. Zhang M, Su YQ, Sugiura K, Wigglesworth K, Xia G, et al. (2011) Estradiol <lb/>promotes and maintains cumulus cell expression of natriuretic peptide receptor 2 <lb/>(NPR2) and meiotic arrest in mouse oocytes in vitro. Endocrinology 152: 4377-<lb/>4385. <lb/>27. Downs SM, Hunzicker-Dunn M (1995) Differential regulation of oocyte <lb/>maturation and cumulus expansion in the mouse oocyte-cumulus cell complex <lb/>by site-selective analogs of cyclic adenosine monophosphate. Dev Biol 172: 72-<lb/>85. <lb/>28. Duncan FE, Moss SB, Williams CJ (2006) Knockdown of the cAMP-dependent <lb/>protein kinase (PKA) Type Ialpha regulatory subunit in mouse oocytes disrupts <lb/>meiotic arrest and results in meiotic spindle defects. Dev Dyn 235: 2961-2968. <lb/>29. Hagiwara M, Brindle P, Harootunian A, Armstrong R, Rivier J, et al. (1993) <lb/>Coupling of hormonal stimulation and transcription via the cyclic AMP-<lb/>responsive factor CREB is rate limited by nuclear entry of protein kinase A. Mol <lb/>Cell Biol 13: 4852-4859. <lb/>30. Michael LF, Asahara H, Shulman AI, Kraus WL, Montminy M (2000) The <lb/>phosphorylation status of a cyclic AMP-responsive activator is modulated via a <lb/>chromatin-dependent mechanism. Mol Cell Biol 20: 1596-1603. <lb/>31. Knutsen HK, Tasken KA, Eskild W, Jahnsen T, Hansson V (1992) Half-lives of <lb/>different sized mRNAs for the PKA subunit RI alpha are regulated differently in <lb/>response to inhibition of transcription and translation. Biochem Biophys Res <lb/>Commun 184: 454-460. <lb/>32. Tasken K, Aandahl EM (2004) Localized effects of cAMP mediated by distinct <lb/>routes of protein kinase A. Physiol Rev 84: 137-167. <lb/>33. Conkright MD, Guzman E, Flechner L, Su AI, Hogenesch JB, et al. (2003) <lb/>Genome-wide analysis of CREB target genes reveals a core promoter <lb/>requirement for cAMP responsiveness. Mol Cell 11: 1101-1108. <lb/>34. Constantinescu A, Gordon AS, Diamond I (2002) cAMP-dependent protein <lb/>kinase types I and II differentially regulate cAMP response element-mediated <lb/>gene expression: implications for neuronal responses to ethanol. J Biol Chem <lb/>277: 18810-18816. <lb/>35. Brown RL, Ord T, Moss SB, Williams CJ (2002) A-kinase anchor proteins as <lb/>potential regulators of protein kinase A function in oocytes. Biology of <lb/>reproduction 67: 981. <lb/>36. Brower PT, Schultz RM (1982) Intercellular communication between granulosa <lb/>cells and mouse oocytes: Existence and possible nutritional role during oocyte <lb/>growth* 1. Developmental Biology 90: 144-153. <lb/>37. Downs SM (1995) The influence of glucose, cumulus cells, and metabolic <lb/>coupling on ATP levels and meiotic control in the isolated mouse oocyte. Dev <lb/>Biol 167: 502-512. <lb/>38. Carabatsos MJ, Sellitto C, Goodenough DA, Albertini DF (2000) Oocyte-<lb/>granulosa cell heterologous gap junctions are required for the coordination of <lb/>nuclear and cytoplasmic meiotic competence. Dev Biol 226: 167-179. <lb/>39. Albertini DF, Combelles CM, Benecchi E, Carabatsos MJ (2001) Cellular basis <lb/>for paracrine regulation of ovarian follicle development. Reproduction 121: <lb/>647-653. <lb/>40. Vozzi C, Formenton A, Chanson A, Senn A, Sahli R, et al. (2001) Involvement <lb/>of connexin 43 in meiotic maturation of bovine oocytes. Reproduction 122: 619-<lb/>628. <lb/>41. Sherizly I, Galiani D, Dekel N (1988) Regulation of oocyte maturation: <lb/>communication in the rat cumulus-oocyte complex. Hum Reprod 3: 761-766. <lb/>42. Zhang Y, Zhang Z, Xu XY, Li XS, Yu M, et al. (2008) Protein kinase A <lb/>modulates Cdc25B activity during meiotic resumption of mouse oocytes. Dev <lb/>Dyn 237: 3777-3786. <lb/>43. Araki K, Naito K, Haraguchi S, Suzuki R, Yokoyama M, et al. (1996) Meiotic <lb/>abnormalities of c-mos knockout mouse oocytes: activation after first meiosis or <lb/>entrance into third meiotic metaphase. Biol Reprod 55: 1315-1324. <lb/>44. Choi T, Rulong S, Resau J, Fukasawa K, Matten W, et al. (1996) Mos/mitogen-<lb/>activated protein kinase can induce early meiotic phenotypes in the absence of <lb/>maturation-promoting factor: a novel system for analyzing spindle formation <lb/>during meiosis I. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 93: 4730-4735. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>45. Araki K, Naito K, Haraguchi S, Suzuki R, Yokoyama M, et al. (1996) Meiotic <lb/>abnormalities of c-mos knockout mouse oocytes: activation after first meiosis or <lb/>entrance into third meiotic metaphase. Biology of reproduction 55: 1315. <lb/>46. Verlhac MH, Lefebvre C, Guillaud P, Rassinier P, Maro B (2000) Asymmetric <lb/>division in mouse oocytes: with or without Mos. Current Biology 10: 1303-1306. <lb/>47. Su YQ, Denegre JM, Wigglesworth K, Pendola FL, O&apos;Brien MJ, et al. (2003) <lb/>Oocyte-dependent activation of mitogen-activated protein kinase (ERK1/2) in <lb/>cumulus cells is required for the maturation of the mouse oocyte-cumulus cell <lb/>complex. Developmental Biology 263: 126-138. <lb/>48. Constantinescu A, Wu M, Asher O, Diamond I (2004) cAMP-dependent protein <lb/>kinase type I regulates ethanol-induced cAMP response element-mediated gene <lb/>expression via activation of CREB-binding protein and inhibition of MAPK. <lb/>Journal of Biological Chemistry 279: 43321. <lb/>49. Vuong BQ, Lee M, Kabir S, Irimia C, Macchiarulo S, et al. (2009) Specific <lb/>recruitment of protein kinase A to the immunoglobulin locus regulates class-<lb/>switch recombination. Nat Immunol 10: 420-426. <lb/>50. Zhang B, Ding J, Li Y, Wang J, Zhao Y, et al. (2011) The porcine Gpr3 gene: <lb/>molecular cloning, characterization and expression level in tissues and cumulus-<lb/>oocyte complexes during in vitro maturation. Mol Biol Rep. <lb/>51. Thomas RE, Armstrong DT, Gilchrist RB (2004) Bovine cumulus cell-oocyte <lb/>gap junctional communication during in vitro maturation in response to <lb/>manipulation of cell-specific cyclic adenosine 39,59-monophosophate levels. Biol <lb/>Reprod 70: 548-556. <lb/>52. Richard FJ, Tsafriri A, Conti M (2001) Role of phosphodiesterase type 3A in rat <lb/>oocyte maturation. Biol Reprod 65: 1444-1451. <lb/>53. Thompson W, Terasaki W, Epstein P, Strada S (1979) Assay of cyclic nucleotide <lb/>phosphodiesterase and resolution of multiple molecular forms of the enzyme. <lb/>Advances in cyclic nucleotide research 10: 69. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">PKAI and GPR3 Activities Modulated by FSH <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">September 2012 | Volume 7 | Issue 9 | e37835 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
