<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Pathological Impact of Hepatitis B Virus Surface Proteins <lb/>on the Liver Is Associated with the Host Genetic <lb/>Background <lb/>Yuri Churin 1. , Martin Roderfeld 1. , Johannes Stiefel 1 , Tilman Wü rger , Dirk Schrö der 1 , <lb/>Tomomitsu Matono 1 , Hans-Joachim Mollenkopf 2 , Roberta Montalbano , Malvika Pompaiah 4 , <lb/>Kurt Reifenberg 5 , Daniel Zahner , Matthias Ocker 3¤ , Wolfram Gerlich , Dieter Glebe 7 , Elke Roeb 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Gastroenterology, Justus Liebig University, Giessen, Germany, Core Facility Microarray, Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology, Berlin, Germany, <lb/>3 Institute for Surgical Research, Philipps University of Marburg, Marburg, Germany, Department of Molecular Biology, Max Planck Institute for Infection Biology, Berlin, <lb/>Germany, 5 Central Laboratory Animal Facility, Johannes Gutenberg University, Mainz, Germany, 6 Division of Animal Welfare and Ethology, Justus Liebig University, <lb/>Giessen, Germany, 7 Institute of Medical Virology, National Reference Centre for Hepatitis B and D Viruses, Justus Liebig University, Giessen, Germany <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: While the immune pathogenesis caused by hepatitis B virus (HBV) infection has been studied extensively, little <lb/>is known about direct pathogenic effects of HBV surface proteins. Here, we have investigated pathological cellular effects of <lb/>HBV surface protein expression in the liver of transgenic mice with different genetic background. <lb/>Methods: The impact of HBV surface protein expression on the liver was studied in two mouse strains, BALB/c and C57BL/6. <lb/>Histology and hydroxyproline assays were performed to investigate liver morphology and fibrosis. Gene expression and <lb/>signaling were analyzed by microarray, qPCR and Western blotting. <lb/>Results: Expression of HBV surface proteins in the liver of transgenic mice induced activation of protein kinase-like <lb/>endoplasmic reticulum kinase (PERK) and eukaryotic initiation factor 2a (eIF2a) phosphorylation. Phosphorylation of eIF2a <lb/>resulted in activation of the ER stress markers glucose regulated protein (GRP) 78 and pro-apoptotic C/EBP homologous <lb/>protein (CHOP) in transgenic mice on BALB/c genetic background leading to stronger liver injury and fibrosis in comparison <lb/>with transgenic mice on C57BL/6 background. Hepatic stellate cells represented the main collagen-producing liver cells in <lb/>HBV transgenic mice. The key regulators of hepatocyte proliferation, transcription factors c-Jun and STAT3 were activated in <lb/>HBV transgenic mice. Tumour incidence in transgenic mice was strain-and sex-dependent. <lb/>Conclusions: Extent of liver injury, fibrosis, and tumour development induced by hepatic HBV surface protein expression <lb/>considerably depends on host genetic background. <lb/>Citation: Churin Y, Roderfeld M, Stiefel J, Wü rger T, Schrö der D, et al. (2014) Pathological Impact of Hepatitis B Virus Surface Proteins on the Liver Is Associated <lb/>with the Host Genetic Background. PLoS ONE 9(3): e90608. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608 <lb/>Editor: Antonio Bertoletti, Singapore Institute for Clinical Sciences, Singapore <lb/>Received November 18, 2013; Accepted February 2, 2014; Published March 4, 2014 <lb/>Copyright: ß 2014 Churin et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. <lb/>Funding: This work was supported by grants from the Deutsche Forschungsgemeinschaft (RO 957/7-1 and RO 957/8-1), ZooMAP (Bundesministerium fü r Bildung <lb/>und Forschung, BMBF), the von-Behring-Roentgen Foundation and the University Medical Center Giessen and Marburg (10/2012 GI, UKGM). The funders had no <lb/>role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. <lb/>* E-mail: elke.roeb@innere.med.uni-giessen.de <lb/>. These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>¤ Current address: Bayer Pharma AG, Clinical Sciences -Experimental Medicine Oncology, Berlin, Germany <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Chronic infection with hepatitis B virus (HBV) affects 350 to <lb/>400 million individuals worldwide and is the leading cause of liver <lb/>cirrhosis and hepatocellular carcinoma worldwide [1]. Although <lb/>much is known about HBV structure and replicative cycle [2] the <lb/>pathogenic mechanisms responsible for liver injury, cirrhosis <lb/>development and malignant transformation during chronic HBV <lb/>infection are not well understood. It is believed that these events <lb/>originate from persistent immune pathogenesis [3], but observa-<lb/>tions in transgenic mouse models of HBV infection suggest that in <lb/>absence of an adaptive immune responses cellular mechanisms <lb/>induced by HBV proteins may also lead to the development of <lb/>these liver diseases [4,5]. <lb/>The HBV transgenic mice used in the current study contain a <lb/>sub-genomic HBV DNA fragment (genotype D, subtype ayw) <lb/>encoding the three co-carboxyterminal HBV surface (HBs) <lb/>proteins under the control of the liver-specific murine albumin <lb/>promoter [6]. Although these transgenic mice have been shown to <lb/>develop chronic liver injury, regenerative hyperplasia, as well as <lb/>adenomas and hepatocellular carcinomas (HCC) [7,8] the <lb/>mechanisms of HBs proteins pathogenicity are poorly understood. <lb/>The HBs protein expression pattern in this mouse model mimics <lb/>the situation in the liver of patients with enhanced intracellular <lb/></body>

			<front>PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/> 1 <lb/> March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></front>

			<body>expression and retention of Hepatitis B virus surface proteins, e. g. <lb/>patients with Hepatitis B virus-related chronic liver disease treated <lb/>by transplantation. The liver damage in these patients was <lb/>attributable to a direct hepatocytotoxic effect of HBV, since they <lb/>were on a similar immunosuppresion regime [9,10]. <lb/>Accumulation of misfolded proteins in the ER activates the <lb/>unfolded protein response (UPR) that is sensed by the binding <lb/>immunoglobulin protein (BiP)/glucose-regulated protein 78 <lb/>(GRP78) [11-13]. Distinct branches of UPR are mediated by <lb/>three different classes of ER-membrane transducers: inositol-<lb/>requiring protein-1 (IRE1), activating transcription factor-6 <lb/>(ATF6) or protein kinase-like endoplasmic reticulum kinase <lb/>(PERK). PERK activation causes the phosphorylation of the <lb/>alpha subunit of eukaryotic translation-initiation factor 2 (eIF2a) <lb/>[11]. Phosphorylation of eIF2a leads to a reduction in the <lb/>initiation of mRNA translation thus reducing the load of new <lb/>proteins that require folding in the ER. However, the expression of <lb/>some proteins is enhanced. One of them is the C/EBP <lb/>homologous protein (CHOP), also known as growth arrest and <lb/>DNA damage-inducible gene (GADD) 153 that mediates pro-<lb/>apoptotic pathways emanating from the stressed ER [11,14]. <lb/>Previously it was shown that GRP78 expression was increased in a <lb/>human hepatoma cell line that overproduced HBs proteins [15] <lb/>and in the liver of transgenic mice that expressed deletion mutant <lb/>of large HBs [16]. <lb/>Hepatic fibrosis constitutes the wound healing response to liver <lb/>injury. During fibrosis, hepatic stellate cell (HSC) activation <lb/>represents a critical event, because these cells become the primary <lb/>source of extracellular matrix in the liver upon damage [17]. <lb/>Development of hepatic fibrosis after chemical liver injury is <lb/>enhanced in BALB/c mice exhibiting a Th2 response compared to <lb/>C57BL/6 mice, which demonstrated a primary Th1 response <lb/>[18]. Transgenic mice on fibrosis-resistant C57BL/6 genetic <lb/>background, which over-produce HBs proteins, develop modest <lb/>spontaneous liver fibrosis [19,20]. <lb/>Transcription factor c-Jun and signal transducer and activator <lb/>of transcription (STAT) 3 are implicated in several cellular <lb/>processes including proliferation, survival, and cell transformation <lb/>[21,22]. They are activated in chemically induced murine liver <lb/>tumours and in HCCs of humans [23,24], suggesting an important <lb/>function for these proteins in the development of liver tumours. <lb/>Here we report that the production of HBV surface proteins <lb/>stimulates the expression of CHOP in hepatocytes and could cause <lb/>stronger liver damage in transgenic mice on BALB/c genetic <lb/>background compared to C57BL/6. Furthermore, HBV trans-<lb/>genic mice develop hepatic fibrosis and the level of fibrosis <lb/>depends on the genetic background. Although c-Jun transcription <lb/>factor up-regulation and activation of STAT3 and PERK in the <lb/>liver of transgenic mice might contribute to tumour development, <lb/>CHOP expression might reduce tumorigenesis in transgenic mice <lb/>on BALB/c genetic background. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Animal Model <lb/>Transgenic mice were maintained at the Central Animal <lb/>Laboratory of the Justus-Liebig-University Giessen under specified <lb/>pathogen-free conditions. This study was carried out in strict <lb/>accordance with the recommendations in the Guide for the Care <lb/>and Use of Laboratory Animals of the German law of animal <lb/>welfare. The mice received humane care, and all experiments <lb/>were approved by the Committee on the ethics of Animal <lb/>Experiments of the Regierungspraesidium Giessen, Giessen, <lb/>Germany (permit number: V54-19c 20 15 h 01 GI20/10 Nr. <lb/>52/2011 and Nr. A5/2012). <lb/>Generation and characteristics of transgenic lineages Tg(Alb-<lb/>1HBV), internal designation (HBVTg/6) have been described <lb/>previously [8]. The HBVTg/6 strain had an inbred C57BL/6 <lb/>genetic background and was propagated by crossing hemizygous <lb/>transgenic males to C57BL/6 females. These mice were <lb/>backcrossed to fibrosis susceptible BALB/c genetic background <lb/>[18] for at least 6 generations. The obtained transgenic mouse line <lb/>was internally designed HBVTg/c. At age of 12, 26, and 52 weeks <lb/>mice were killed by CO 2 -inhalation. Liver samples were collected <lb/>and preserved for analyses in accordance with application. Serum <lb/>samples were stored at 280uC until analysis of alanine amino-<lb/>transferase (ALT) by routine clinical chemistry on a Reflotron Plus <lb/>Analyzer (Roche, Mannheim, Germany). <lb/>Histology and Hydroxyproline Assay <lb/>Immediately after necropsy, liver samples for histology were <lb/>fixed in 4% neutral buffered paraformaldehyde at 4uC for 16 <lb/>hours and embedded in paraffin. Paraffin sections (5 mm) were <lb/>stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E) or 0.1% Sirius Red <lb/>F3B in saturated picric acid (Chroma, Münster, Germany) for the <lb/>detection of collagen fibers [25]. The entire content of collagen <lb/>was determined by hydroxyproline (HYP) quantification [26]. <lb/>Immunohistochemistry <lb/>Immunohistochemistry (IHC) was performed using ImmPRESS <lb/>Peroxidase Detection Reagents (Vector Laboratories) and anti-<lb/>bodies specific for HBsAg (20-HR20), GADD153 (F-168, Santa <lb/>Cruz), Desmin and GFAP (Lab Vision), c-Jun (60A8, Cell <lb/>Signaling), BiP (C50B12, Cell Signaling). Colour reaction was <lb/>developed with VECTOR VIP Peroxidase Substrate Kit or DAB <lb/>Peroxidase Substrate Kit, (Vector Laboratories). The percentage <lb/>of BiP, Desmin, and GFAP-positive area was determined using <lb/>ImageJ image analysis system (National Institutes of Health, <lb/>Bethesda, MD, USA). <lb/>Western Blot Analysis <lb/>Total liver lysates were analyzed by immunoblotting using <lb/>antibodies against HBsAg (20-HR20, Fitzgerald), GADD153 (F-<lb/>168, Santa Cruz), phospho-PERK (16F8, Cell Signaling), PERK <lb/>(H-300, Santa Cruz), phospho-eIF2a (119A11, Cell Signaling), <lb/>eIF2a (L57A5, Cell Signaling), b-actin (13E5, Cell Signaling), <lb/>JNK2 (N-18, Santa Cruz), c-Jun (60A8, Cell Signaling), phospho-<lb/>c-Jun (D47G9, Cell Signaling), phospho-SAPK/JNK (81E11, Cell <lb/>Signaling), STAT3 (79D7, Cell Signaling), phospho-STAT3 <lb/>(D3A7, Cell Signaling). <lb/>Assay for HBV-specific proteins <lb/>HBsAg was measured in serum and in liver lysates by an in-<lb/>house sandwich ELISA as described [27]. HBsAg amount per <lb/>hepatocyte was calculated based on the hepatocellularity number <lb/>for mouse 135 million cells per gram of liver [28]. <lb/>Quantitative real-time PCR (qPCR) <lb/>RNA isolation, cDNA synthesis, qPCR and quality control of all <lb/>steps were performed as described previously [29]. Primers were <lb/>purchased from QIAGEN (Hilden, Germany). qPCR data were <lb/>analysed using DDCt method [30]. <lb/>Microarray analysis <lb/>Microarray experiments were performed with total RNA from <lb/>the liver of 12-week-old mice as described previously [31]. The <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<body>data presented here have been deposited in NCBI&apos;s Gene <lb/>Expression Omnibus (GEO; http://www.ncbi.nlm.nih.gov/geo/) <lb/>and are accessible through GEO Series accession number <lb/>GSE40826. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed with SPSS V.17.0 software <lb/>(SPSS Inc.). For non-normally distributed parameters, Mann-<lb/>Whitney U test and Spearman rank test were applied. The results <lb/>are presented as mean6SEM. A two-sided p,0.05 was considered <lb/>significant (shown as * in the figures]. <lb/>Results <lb/>Liver damage induced by HBs proteins expression <lb/>depends on host genetic background <lb/>Transgenic mice were sacrificed at week 12, 26, and 52. To <lb/>estimate the level of liver cell damage we have measured alanine <lb/>transaminase (ALT) in serum. Activities of serum ALT were <lb/>markedly increased already in 12-week-old HBVTg/c mice <lb/>compared to the wild-type and remained at that level during the <lb/>observation period. In HBVTg/6 mice the ALT elevation was <lb/>moderate at week 12 but increased later to levels almost as high as <lb/>in HBVTg/c mice (Figure 1A). Histological analysis revealed no <lb/>significant lymphocyte infiltration of the liver from 12-week-old <lb/>transgenic mice (Figure S1A). Furthermore, amounts of HBsAg <lb/>per hepatocyte in 12-week-old mice were similar: 0.42 pg/cell <lb/>(range, 0.18-0.71 pg/cell; n = 5) for HBVTg/c and 0.31 pg/cell <lb/>(range, 0.15-0.64 pg/cell; n = 5) for HBVTg/6. Immunohisto-<lb/>chemical and Western blot analyses of livers from transgenic mice <lb/>also showed that distributions and expression levels of HBs <lb/>proteins were similar in mice on both C57BL/6 and BALB/c <lb/>genetic backgrounds (Figure S1B and S2). Moreover, amounts of <lb/>HBsAg in serum of transgenic mice did not differ significantly: <lb/>2.02 ng/ml (range, 0.68-3.19 ng/ml; n = 5) for HBVTg/c and <lb/>1.34 ng/ml (range, 0.68-2.55 ng/ml; n = 4) for HBVTg/6. Thus, <lb/>the elevated serum ALT levels in HBVTg/c mice could be a <lb/>consequence of a specific host response to the presence of HBs <lb/>proteins. <lb/>To identify the pathways which are activated in the HBs-<lb/>expressing liver tissue we carried out transcriptional profiling using <lb/>microarray analysis. As illustrated in Table 1 a set of genes that is <lb/>known to be induced by UPR is up-regulated in the liver of 12-<lb/>week-old transgenic mice. Interestingly, the expression of gene <lb/>ddit3 that encodes CHOP protein is stronger up-regulated in the <lb/>liver of HBVTg/c mice compared to HBVTg/6. To confirm this <lb/>finding we studied the expression of CHOP by qRT-PCR and <lb/>Western blot analysis. Transcription of the ddit3 gene was strongly <lb/>activated in 12-week-old HBVTg/c mice and declined thereafter <lb/>with age, whereas in HBVTg/6 mice ddit3 transcription was rather <lb/>weakly enhanced in 12-week-old mice and increased with age <lb/>(Figure S3). Western blot analysis of liver proteins revealed that <lb/>CHOP was up-regulated much stronger in HBVTg/c mice <lb/>compared to HBVTg/6 (Fig. 1B). Selective CHOP translation <lb/>depends on eIF2a phosphorylation by PERK after induction of <lb/>UPR [11]. However, we detected similar level of PERK activation <lb/>and eIF2a phosphorylation in the liver from both mouse strains <lb/>irrespective of gender and age (Fig. 1C and D). Interestingly, other <lb/>UPR sensors ATF6 and IRE1 as well as eIF2a kinases PKR <lb/>(protein kinase R) and GCN2 (general control non-derepressible-2) <lb/>[32] were not activated in the liver of transgenic mice (data not <lb/>shown). Taken together, expression of HBs proteins in the liver of <lb/>transgenic mice leads to the specific activation of the PERK <lb/>branch of UPR in hepatocytes from both mouse strains, but <lb/>expression of CHOP was much stronger in HBVTg/c mice. <lb/>Enhanced translation of CHOP results in liver damage and could <lb/>explain higher serum ALT levels in HBVTg/c mice. <lb/>To examine the location of CHOP expressing hepatocytes <lb/>immunohistochemistry (IHC) was performed. According to our <lb/>previous finding a significant part of hepatocytes from 12-week-old <lb/>HBVTg/c mice accumulated CHOP in the nucleus and the <lb/>amount of CHOP-positive hepatocytes declined with age, whereas <lb/>we could detect only a few hepatocytes in HBVTg/6 liver <lb/>positively stained for CHOP independent of age (Figure 2A). <lb/>Interesting, CHOP-positive hepatocytes were located in centri-<lb/>lobular areas which surround a hepatic central vein (Figure 2A). <lb/>Furthermore, induction of UPR leads to activation of the major <lb/>sensor of unfolded protein accumulation BiP/GRP78 [12]. IHC <lb/>demonstrated strong expression of BiP in selected hepatocytes in <lb/>centrilobular areas (Figure 2B and Figure S4), although Western <lb/>blot analysis did not reveal any differences between wild-type and <lb/>transgenic mice in expression of BiP/GRP78 (data not shown). <lb/>Thus, expression of HBs proteins activated the UPR downstream <lb/>pathway (CHOP and BiP) much stronger in the liver of transgenic <lb/>mice on BALB/c genetic background compared to C57BL/6. <lb/>This activation is located in centrilobular zones of the liver. <lb/>Liver fibrosis <lb/>Measurement of liver hydroxyproline content demonstrated the <lb/>development of hepatic fibrosis in transgenic mice (Figure 3A). <lb/>Enhanced hepatic fibrosis was confirmed by Sirius red staining as <lb/>well. We observed minimal fibrosis in the liver of 12-week-old <lb/>mice. But fibrosis constantly increased with age. However, <lb/>HBVTg/c mice accumulated more collagen (Figure S5). Hepatic <lb/>stellate cells (HSC) are the primary effector cells responsible for the <lb/>deposition of ECM in normal and fibrotic liver [33]. Therefore, <lb/>we tested the expression of HSC activation markers. We detected <lb/>increased amounts of GFAP-and desmin-positive cells in the liver <lb/>of transgenic mice, thus demonstrating HSC proliferation in the <lb/>liver of transgenic mice (Figure 3B and Figure S6). Moreover, <lb/>double staining of desmin with specific antibodies and collagen <lb/>with Sirius red has shown co-localization of HSCs with collagen <lb/>fibres (Figure S7). Taken together, expression of HBs proteins in <lb/>mouse liver induces development of hepatic fibrosis, which <lb/>correlated with liver injury. HSCs might be the main collagen-<lb/>producing cells in this mouse model. <lb/>HBs protein-induced tumour development depends on <lb/>host genetic background <lb/>Microarray analysis showed an up-regulation of c-jun gene <lb/>expression in transgenic mice independent of genetic background <lb/>(Table 1). These results were confirmed using qPCR. Maximal <lb/>expression was detected in the liver of 52-week-old mice (Figure <lb/>S8). Expression of c-Jun protein was increased in the liver of 12-, <lb/>26-, and 52-week-old transgenic mice (Figure 4A). Major parts of <lb/>hepatocytes of 52-week-old mice accumulated c-Jun in the nucleus <lb/>(Figure S9). Phosphorylation of c-Jun by c-Jun N-terminal kinase <lb/>(JNK) stimulates its ability to activate transcription [34,35]. <lb/>Western blot analyses demonstrated that JNKs were activated <lb/>(Figure 4B) and the level of c-Jun phosphorylation was indeed <lb/>increased in the liver of 52-week-old transgenic mice (Figure 4C). <lb/>Thus, expression of HBs proteins in the liver of transgenic mice <lb/>leads to activation of c-Jun expression. <lb/>STAT3 activation was observed in mouse models of liver injury <lb/>and in human liver diseases in the context of inflammation and <lb/>cancer [22]. Therefore, we examined the status of STAT3 <lb/>activation in the liver of HBV transgenic mice. Western blot <lb/>analysis of liver protein extracts revealed STAT3 activation in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<body>liver of male but not female mice (Figure 4D). Thus, expression of <lb/>HBV surface proteins in the liver of transgenic mice results in <lb/>STAT3 activation in a gender-dependent manner. <lb/>Up-regulation of c-Jun expression and STAT3 activation could <lb/>promote hepatic tumour growth [21,22]. We checked transgenic <lb/>mice for occurrence of liver tumour. In young mice (12-and 26-<lb/>week-old) mice we could detect no tumours. However, they were <lb/>detected in 100% (6/6) of 52-week-old male and 20% (1/5) of <lb/>female HBVTg/6 mice, whereas only 58% (7/12; X = 3.46; <lb/>p = 0.06) of 52-week-old male and 0% (0/6) of female HBVTg/c <lb/>mice develop tumours. Hence, development of tumours in HBV <lb/>transgenic mice was age-, gender-, and strain-dependent. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study we investigated the effects of HBVs proteins <lb/>expression in the liver of transgenic mice BALB/c and C57BL/6 <lb/>genetic background. Since we observed only weak strain-<lb/>independent immune cell infiltration of transgenic mice liver <lb/>(Figure S1) this model could be considered as one with impaired <lb/>immune reaction. One important negative impact of immune <lb/>deficiency on chronic HBV infection in human is related to the <lb/>direct cytotoxicity of high levels of HBs and other HBV proteins <lb/>[9,10,36]. Low serum HBsAG titers were associated with strong <lb/>intracellular accumulation of HBs in HBV transgenic mice on <lb/>both genetic backgrounds. This condition was also seen in some <lb/>patients with late phases of chronic HBV infection [37,38]. Thus, <lb/>transgenic mice expressing HBs proteins reflect the situation in the <lb/>liver of HBV-infected patients demonstrated strong retention of <lb/>HBsAg in hepatocytes. <lb/>Higher serum ALT activities in HBVTg/c mice suggest <lb/>stronger liver injury compared to HBVTg/6 (Figure 1A). Since <lb/>the level of cellular infiltration was low in the liver of transgenic <lb/>mice on both genetic backgrounds we searched for other reasons <lb/>of hepatocyte death. Increased CHOP expression as a result of <lb/>prolonged ER stress promotes cell death, whereas CHOP deletion <lb/>protects against the death of ER-stressed cells [14]. Strongly <lb/>increased transcription and protein accumulation of CHOP in <lb/>HBVTg/c mice (Figure 1B and 2A; Figure S3) inducing <lb/>hepatocyte death could explain increased serum ALT level in <lb/>these mice. Expression of CHOP is mediated by phosphorylation <lb/>of eIF2a [32] that in turn is phosphorylated by PERK [11]. <lb/>Interestingly, levels of PERK activation and eIF2a phosphoryla-<lb/>tion were similar in the liver of both HBV transgenic mouse strains <lb/>(Figure 1C and 1D). Two other branches of UPR IRE1a and <lb/>ATF6 were not activated in the liver of HBV transgenic mice (data <lb/>not shown). PERK branch activation is largely sustained with <lb/>unmitigated ER stress, whereas persistent ER stress attenuates <lb/>IRE1a and ATF6 signaling [39]. Therefore, permanent expres-<lb/>sion of HBs proteins leads to the activation of persistent ER stress <lb/>in hepatocytes that induces PERK and impairs another branches <lb/>Figure 1. HBs proteins-induced liver injury depends on host genetic background. (A) Assessment of liver damage in wild-type and HBV <lb/>transgenic mice. ALT was measured in serum of 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old mice (mean6SEM, n = 5-10). (B-D) Western blot analysis of total protein <lb/>lysates from the liver of 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old mice was performed using (B) anti-CHOP/GADD153, (C) anti-phospho-PERK, and (D) anti-phospho-<lb/>eIF2a (Ser51) antibodies. Equal protein loading was confirmed with anti-PERK (B), anti-eIF2a (C), and anti-b-actin (D) antibodies. 1 -female BALB/c; <lb/>2,3 -female HBVTg/c; 4 -male BALB/c; 5, 6 -male HBVTg/c; 7 -female C57BL/6; 8, 9 -female HBVTg/6; 10 -male C57BL/6; 11, 12 -male HBVTg/6 <lb/>mice. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Selected hepatic genes significantly differentially expressed in the liver of 12-week-old HBV transgenic mice. <lb/>Accession <lb/>Primary Sequence <lb/>Name <lb/>Sequence Description <lb/>Fold Change HBVTg/c <lb/>Fold Change <lb/>HBVTg/6 <lb/>NM_019738 <lb/>Nupr1 <lb/>Nuclear protein 1 <lb/>14.97 <lb/>5.44 <lb/>NM_007498 <lb/>Atf3 <lb/>Activating transcription factor 3 <lb/>9.53 <lb/>3.25 <lb/>NM_007837 <lb/>Ddit3 <lb/>DNA-damage inducible transcript 3 <lb/>6.39 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>NM_024440 <lb/>Derl3 <lb/>Der1-like domain family, member 3 <lb/>8.52 <lb/>1.44 <lb/>NM_016773 <lb/>Nucb2 <lb/>Nucleobindin 2 <lb/>4.16 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>NM_012055 <lb/>Asns <lb/>Asparagine synthetase <lb/>4.14 <lb/>2.28 <lb/>NM_007836 <lb/>Gadd45a <lb/>Growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible 45 alpha <lb/>2.61 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>NM_144554 <lb/>Trib3 <lb/>Tribbles homolog 3 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>21.13 <lb/>NM_013560 <lb/>Hspb1 <lb/>Heat shock protein 1 <lb/>2.14 <lb/>2.01 <lb/>NM_022310 <lb/>Hspa5 <lb/>Heat shock 70 kD protein 5 (GRP78) <lb/>2.08 <lb/>1.19 <lb/>NM_011631 <lb/>Hsp90b1 <lb/>Heat shock protein 90 kDa beta (Grp94) <lb/>1.91 <lb/>21.05 <lb/>NM_011817 <lb/>Gadd45g <lb/>Growth arrest and DNA-damage-inducible 45 gamma <lb/>21.67 <lb/>2.18 <lb/>NM_010591 <lb/>Jun <lb/>Jun oncogene <lb/>4.17 <lb/>2.30 <lb/>NM_008182 <lb/>Gsta2 <lb/>Glutathione S-transferase, alpha 2 (Yc2) <lb/>3.20 <lb/>2.04 <lb/>NM_031170 <lb/>Krt2-8 <lb/>Keratin complex 2, basic, gene 8 <lb/>2.21 <lb/>1.95 <lb/>NM_007742 <lb/>Col1a1 <lb/>Procollagen, type I, alpha 1 <lb/>2.00 <lb/>1.48 <lb/>NM_007743 <lb/>Col1a2 <lb/>Procollagen, type I, alpha 2 <lb/>1.94 <lb/>1.23 <lb/>NM_011594 <lb/>Timp2 <lb/>Tissue inhibitor of metalloproteinase 2 <lb/>1.75 <lb/>21.04 <lb/>NM_010664 <lb/>Krt1-18 <lb/>Keratin complex 1, acidic, gene 18 <lb/>1.81 <lb/>1.80 <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608.t001 <lb/>Figure 2. Expression of CHOP/GADD153 and BiP/GRP78 in the liver of HBV transgenic mice. Immunohistochemical analysis of paraffin-<lb/>embedded liver sections from 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old mice was performed using specific anti-CHOP/GADD153 (A) and anti-BiP (B) antibodies. 100x-<lb/>original magnification 1006, bar = 200 mm. 200-original magnification 2006, bar = 100 mm. *-central vein. #-periportal vein. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<body>of UPR. It is possible that this situation is common for chronic <lb/>liver disease comprising ER stress induction. <lb/>It was previously shown that despite PERK activation and <lb/>eIF2a phosphorylation in the liver of patients with nonalcoholic <lb/>fatty liver disease (NAFLD) and nonalcoholic steatohepatitis <lb/>(NASH), downstream effectors such as CHOP remain inactive <lb/>[40]. A similar situation was observed in the liver of HBV <lb/>transgenic mice on C57BL/6 genetic background. However, <lb/>stimulation of CHOP and BiP expression in HBVTg/c mice <lb/>demonstrated that the outcome of UPR induction depends on the <lb/>genetic background of subjects. Furthermore, several studies have <lb/>demonstrated that PERK function is critical for maintaining <lb/>cellular redox homeostasis, promotes cancer cell proliferation and <lb/>tumour growth [41]. Thus, sustained activation of PERK could <lb/>also promote cancer development in the liver of HBV transgenic <lb/>mice. <lb/>Global reduction of translation initiation due to PERK-<lb/>mediated eIF2a phosphorylation [32] should also affect the <lb/>expression of HBs proteins in the liver. This suggests the following <lb/>feed-back mechanism: PERK activation results in the reduction of <lb/>HBs translation and that leads to a balance between PERK <lb/>activation and HBs protein synthesis in hepatocytes. <lb/>Development of tumours in HBV transgenic mice as it was <lb/>shown by us and others [8] is age-, gender-, and strain-dependent. <lb/>In this study we observed a strong up-regulation of c-Jun hepatic <lb/>expression and an activation of STAT3, whose role in tumori-<lb/>genesis is well established [22,23,42]. Jun controls liver cancer <lb/>initiation and is required for development of chemically induced <lb/>HCC [23]. Interestingly, transgenic mice comprising the whole or <lb/>partial HBV genome are also more susceptible to chemically <lb/>induced hepatocarcinogenesis [43,44]. Likewise, hepatitis C virus <lb/>core protein potentiates chemically induced HCC through c-Jun <lb/>and STAT3 activation [45]. Thus, stimulation of c-Jun expression <lb/>and STAT3 activation by HBs proteins could promote the <lb/>development of liver cancer induced by different causes, such as <lb/>sustained inflammation, activation of oncogenes etc. Furthermore, <lb/>the finding that STAT3 was activated in male mice only correlated <lb/>with our observation that tumour development in HBV transgenic <lb/>mice is gender-dependent. There is accumulating evidence that <lb/>tumour-specific ER stress can be exploited for cancer therapy by <lb/>treatment with ER stress-aggravating compounds [46]. Moderate, <lb/>transient ER stress response represents an adaptive mechanism to <lb/>support cellular survival. However, severe and excessive stress <lb/>conditions could turn this response system to its pro-apoptotic <lb/>mode. Stimulation of CHOP expression in HBVTg/c mice <lb/>indicated an activation of pro-apoptotic cellular stress responses in <lb/>the liver and resulted in reduced tumour incidence in 52-week-old <lb/>HBVTg/c mice. <lb/>Taken together, the outcome of HBV surface proteins <lb/>expression in the liver of transgenic mice depends on the host <lb/>genetic background. Liver injury and fibrosis were increased in <lb/>transgenic mice on BALB/c background compared to C57BL/6 <lb/>correlating with strong expression of PERK downstream pro-<lb/>apoptotic effector CHOP. More interesting finding is genetic <lb/>background-independent stimulation of c-Jun expression together <lb/>with STAT3 and PERK activation promoting cancer cell <lb/>proliferation and tumour growth. However, activation of pro-<lb/>apoptotic cellular stress response could result in reduced tumour <lb/>incidence in the liver. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting Information <lb/>Figure S1 Representative liver histology and distribu-<lb/>tion of HBs proteins in hepatocytes of transgenic mice. <lb/>(A) H&amp;E staining of liver sections from 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old <lb/>mice HBVTg/c and HBVTg/6 mice. Original magnification <lb/>1006, bar = 200 mm. Insets -H&amp;E staining of liver from <lb/>corresponding wild-type mice. (B) Paraffin-embedded sections of <lb/>transgenic mice liver were stained with an antibody against <lb/>HBsAg. Original magnification 1006, bar = 200 mm. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S2 Expression of HBs proteins in the liver of <lb/>transgenic mice. Western blot analysis of total protein lysates <lb/>from livers of HBV transgenic mice using specific anti-HBsAg <lb/>antibody. 1-female BALB/c; 2,3-female HBVTg/c; 4 -male <lb/>BALB/c; 5, 6 -male HBVTg/c; 7 -female C57BL/6; 8, 9 -<lb/>female HBVTg/6; 10 -male C57BL/6; 11, 12 -male HBVTg/6 <lb/>mice. Equal protein loading was confirmed with anti-b-actin <lb/>antibody. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S3 Transcriptional up-regulation of ddit3 gene in <lb/>the liver of HBV transgenic mice. All data are normalized to <lb/>Figure 3. Fibrogenesis in the liver of HBV transgenic mice. (A) <lb/>Entire collagen was assessed by measurement of hydroxyproline (HYP) <lb/>in murine liver (mean6SEM, n = 5-10). (B) Activation of hepatic stellate <lb/>cells in HBV transgenic mice. Paraffin-embedded liver sections of 26-<lb/>week-old HBVTg/c mice were analysed using anti-GFAP (left panel) and <lb/>anti-Desmin (right panel) antibodies. Inserts -immunohistochemical <lb/>analysis of the liver from wild-type BALB/c mouse. 1006 -original <lb/>magnification 1006, bar = 200 mm. 2006-original magnification 2006, <lb/>bar = 200 mm. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608.g003 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">r18S. Fold increase to wild-type animals is depicted (mean 6 <lb/>SEM, n = 5-10). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S4 Quantification of BiP expression in the liver <lb/>of HBV transgenic mice. Percentage of BiP-positive area in the <lb/>whole image was estimated with ImageJ software (mean6SEM, <lb/>n = 5). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S5 Development of fibrosis in the liver of HBV <lb/>transgenic mice. Collagen fibres are detected in polarized light <lb/>after Sirius red staining of 5-mm paraffin-embedded liver sections <lb/>of 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old HBVTg/c and HBVTg/6 mice. <lb/>Original magnification 1006, bar = 200 mm. Insets -Sirius red <lb/>staining of the liver from wild-type mice. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S6 Quantification of Desmin and GFAP expres-<lb/>sion in the liver of HBV transgenic mice. Percentages of <lb/>Desmin (A) and GFAP (B)-positive areas in the whole images were <lb/>estimated with ImageJ software (mean6SEM, n = 5). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S7 Hepatic stellate cells are major contributor to <lb/>hepatic fibrosis in HBV transgenic mice. Paraffin-embed-<lb/>ded liver section from 26-week-old HBVTg/c mouse was first <lb/>stained with anti-Desmin antibody and subsequently with Sirius <lb/>red. Collagen fibres are detected in polarized light, Desmin-<lb/>positive staining appears in black. Original magnification 2006, <lb/>bar = 100 mm. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S8 Transcriptional up-regulation of c-jun gene in <lb/>the liver of HBV transgenic mice. All data are normalized to <lb/>r18S. Fold increase to wild-type animals is depicted (mean <lb/>SEM, n = 5-10). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>Figure S9 Expression of Jun protein in the liver of HBV <lb/>transgenic mice. Immunohistochemical analysis of paraffin-<lb/>embedded liver sections from 52-week-old mice was performed <lb/>using specific anti-Jun antibody. Original magnification 1006, bar <lb/>= 200 mm. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>We thank Katharina Kopsch, Annette Tschuschner, Sandra Kremer <lb/>(Justus Liebig University Giessen) and Ina Wagner (MPI for Infection <lb/>Biology, Berlin) for excellent technical assistance. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceived and designed the experiments: YC MR ER. Performed the <lb/>experiments: YC MR JS TW DS TM RM. Analyzed the data: HJM MP. <lb/>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: KR DZ MO DG. Wrote <lb/>the paper: YC MR ER. Critically read the manuscript: WG. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Dienstag JL (2008) Hepatitis B virus infection. N Engl J Med 359: 1486-1500. <lb/>2. Glebe D, Bremer CM (2013) The molecular virology of hepatitis B virus. Semin <lb/>Liver Dis 33: 103-112. <lb/>3. Chisari FV, Isogawa M, Wieland SF (2010) Pathogenesis of hepatitis B virus <lb/>infection. Pathol Biol (Paris) 58: 258-266. <lb/>4. Meuleman P, Libbrecht L, Wieland S, De VR, Habib N, et al. (2006) Immune <lb/>suppression uncovers endogenous cytopathic effects of the hepatitis B virus. <lb/>J Virol 80: 2797-2807. <lb/>5. Sugiyama M, Tanaka Y, Kurbanov F, Maruyama I, Shimada T, et al. (2009) <lb/>Direct cytopathic effects of particular hepatitis B virus genotypes in severe <lb/>combined immunodeficiency transgenic with urokinase-type plasminogen <lb/>activator mouse with human hepatocytes. Gastroenterology 136: 652-662. <lb/>6. Chisari FV, Filippi P, McLachlan A, Milich DR, Riggs M, et al. (1986) <lb/>Expression of hepatitis B virus large envelope polypeptide inhibits hepatitis B <lb/>surface antigen secretion in transgenic mice. J Virol 60: 880-887. <lb/>7. Chisari FV, Filippi P, Buras J, McLachlan A, Popper H, et al. (1987) Structural <lb/>and pathological effects of synthesis of hepatitis B virus large envelope <lb/>polypeptide in transgenic mice. Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A 84: 6909-6913. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Figure 4. Activation of tumorigenic pathways in hepatocytes of HBV transgenic mice. Western blot analysis of total protein lysates from <lb/>the liver of 12-, 26-, and 52-week-old mice was performed using (A) anti-Jun, (B) anti-phospho-SAPK/JNK, (C), anti-phospho-c-Jun and (D) anti-<lb/>phospho-STAT3 antibodies. Samples were loaded as described in the legend of Fig. 1. Equal protein loading was confirmed with anti-b-actin (A, B and <lb/>C) and anti-STAT3 (D) antibodies. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0090608.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>8. Chisari FV, Klopchin K, Moriyama T, Pasquinelli C, Dunsford HA, et al. (1989) <lb/>Molecular pathogenesis of hepatocellular carcinoma in hepatitis B virus <lb/>transgenic mice. Cell 59: 1145-1156. <lb/>9. Davies SE, Portmann BC, O&apos;Grady JG, Aldis PM, Chaggar K, et al. (1991) <lb/>Hepatic histological findings after transplantation for chronic hepatitis B virus <lb/>infection, including a unique pattern of fibrosing cholestatic hepatitis. <lb/>Hepatology 13: 150-157. <lb/>10. Lau JY, Bain VG, Davies SE, O&apos;Grady JG, Alberti A, et al. (1992) High-level <lb/>expression of hepatitis B viral antigens in fibrosing cholestatic hepatitis. <lb/>Gastroenterology 102: 956-962. <lb/>11. Ron D, Walter P (2007) Signal integration in the endoplasmic reticulum <lb/>unfolded protein response. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 8: 519-529. <lb/>12. Hetz C (2012) The unfolded protein response: controlling cell fate decisions <lb/>under ER stress and beyond. Nat Rev Mol Cell Biol 13: 89-102. <lb/>13. Malhi H, Kaufman RJ (2011) Endoplasmic reticulum stress in liver disease. <lb/>J Hepatol 54: 795-809. <lb/>14. Oyadomari S, Mori M (2004) Roles of CHOP/GADD153 in endoplasmic <lb/>reticulum stress. Cell Death Differ 11: 381-389. <lb/>15. Xu Z, Jensen G, Yen TS (1997) Activation of hepatitis B virus S promoter by the <lb/>viral large surface protein via induction of stress in the endoplasmic reticulum. <lb/>J Virol 71: 7387-7392. <lb/>16. Wang HC, Chang WT, Chang WW, Wu HC, Huang W, et al. (2005) Hepatitis <lb/>B virus pre-S2 mutant upregulates cyclin A expression and induces nodular <lb/>proliferation of hepatocytes. Hepatology 41: 761-770. <lb/>17. Hernandez-Gea V, Friedman SL (2011) Pathogenesis of liver fibrosis. Annu Rev <lb/>Pathol 6: 425-456. <lb/>18. Shi Z, Wakil AE, Rockey DC (1997) Strain-specific differences in mouse hepatic <lb/>wound healing are mediated by divergent T helper cytokine responses. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci U S A 94: 10663-10668. <lb/>19. Spano D, Cimmino F, Capasso M, D&apos;Angelo F, Zambrano N, et al. (2008) <lb/>Changes of the hepatic proteome in hepatitis B-infected mouse model at early <lb/>stages of fibrosis. J Proteome Res 7: 2642-2653. <lb/>20. Jin Z, Sun R, Wei H, Gao X, Chen Y, et al. (2011) Accelerated liver fibrosis in <lb/>hepatitis B virus transgenic mice: involvement of natural killer T cells. <lb/>Hepatology 53: 219-229. <lb/>21. Jochum W, Passegue E, Wagner EF (2001) AP-1 in mouse development and <lb/>tumorigenesis. Oncogene 20: 2401-2412. <lb/>22. He G, Karin M (2011) NF-kappaB and ST. Cell Res 21: 159-168. <lb/>23. Eferl R, Ricci R, Kenner L, Zenz R, David JP, et al. (2003) Liver tumor <lb/>development. c-Jun antagonizes the proapoptotic activity of p53. Cell 112: 181-<lb/>192. <lb/>24. He G, Yu GY, Temkin V, Ogata H, Kuntzen C, et al. (2010) Hepatocyte <lb/>IKKbeta/NF-kappaB inhibits tumor promotion and progression by preventing <lb/>oxidative stress-driven STAT3 activation. Cancer Cell 17: 286-297. <lb/>25. Salguero PR, Roderfeld M, Hemmann S, Rath T, Atanasova S, et al. (2008) <lb/>Activation of hepatic stellate cells is associated with cytokine expression in <lb/>thioacetamide-induced hepatic fibrosis in mice. Lab Invest 88: 1192-1203. <lb/>26. Boigk G, Stroedter L, Herbst H, Waldschmidt J, Riecken EO, et al. (1997) <lb/>Silymarin retards collagen accumulation in early and advanced biliary fibrosis <lb/>secondary to complete bile duct obliteration in rats. Hepatology 26: 643-649. <lb/>27. Glebe D, Aliakbari M, Krass P, Knoop EV, Valerius KP, et al. (2003) Pre-s1 <lb/>antigen-dependent infection of Tupaia hepatocyte cultures with human hepatitis <lb/>B virus. J Virol 77: 9511-9521. <lb/>28. Sohlenius-Sternbeck AK (2006) Determination of the hepatocellularity number <lb/>for human, dog, rabbit, rat and mouse livers from protein concentration <lb/>measurements. Toxicol In Vitro 20: 1582-1586. <lb/>29. Roderfeld M, Rath T, Voswinckel R, Dierkes C, Dietrich H, et al. (2010) Bone <lb/>marrow transplantation demonstrates medullar origin of CD34+ fibrocytes and <lb/>ameliorates hepatic fibrosis in Abcb4-/-mice. Hepatology 51: 267-276. <lb/>30. Pfaffl MW (2001) A new mathematical model for relative quantification in real-<lb/>time RT-PCR. Nucleic Acids Res 29: e45. <lb/>31. Reece ST, Loddenkemper C, Askew DJ, Zedler U, Schommer-Leitner S, et al. <lb/>(2010) Serine protease activity contributes to control of Mycobacterium <lb/>tuberculosis in hypoxic lung granulomas in mice. J Clin Invest 120: 3365-3376. <lb/>32. Wek RC, Jiang HY, Anthony TG (2006) Coping with stress: eIF2 kinases and <lb/>translational control. Biochem Soc Trans 34: 7-11. <lb/>33. Lee UE, Friedman SL (2011) Mechanisms of hepatic fibrogenesis. Best Pract Res <lb/>Clin Gastroenterol 25: 195-206. <lb/>34. Pulverer BJ, Kyriakis JM, Avruch J, Nikolakaki E, Woodgett JR (1991) <lb/>Phosphorylation of c-jun mediated by MAP kinases. Nature 353: 670-674. <lb/>35. Smeal T, Binetruy B, Mercola DA, Birrer M, Karin M (1991) Oncogenic and <lb/>transcriptional cooperation with Ha-Ras requires phosphorylation of c-Jun on <lb/>serines 63 and 73. Nature 354: 494-496. <lb/>36. Pol S (2013) Management of HBV in immunocompromised patients. Liver Int <lb/>Suppl 1: 182-187. <lb/>37. Lau JY, Bain VG, Davies SE, Alexander GJ, Williams R (1991) Export of <lb/>intracellular HBsAg in chronic hepatitis B virus infection is related to viral <lb/>replication. Hepatology 14: 416-421. <lb/>38. Naoumov NV, Portmann BC, Tedder RS, Ferns B, Eddleston AL, et al. (1990) <lb/>Detection of hepatitis B virus antigens in liver tissue. A relation to viral <lb/>replication and histology in chronic hepatitis B infection. Gastroenterology 99: <lb/>1248-1253. <lb/>39. Lin JH, Li H, Yasumura D, Cohen HR, Zhang C, et al. (2007) IRE1 signaling <lb/>affects cell fate during the unfolded protein response. Science 318: 944-949. <lb/>40. Puri P, Mirshahi F, Cheung O, Natarajan R, Maher JW, et al. (2008) Activation <lb/>and dysregulation of the unfolded protein response in nonalcoholic fatty liver <lb/>disease. Gastroenterology 134: 568-576. <lb/>41. Bobrovnikova-Marjon E, Grigoriadou C, Pytel D, Zhang F, Ye J, et al. (2010) <lb/>PERK promotes cancer cell proliferation and tumor growth by limiting <lb/>oxidative DNA damage. Oncogene 29: 3881-3895. <lb/>42. Min L, Ji Y, Bakiri L, Qiu Z, Cen J, et al. (2012) Liver cancer initiation is <lb/>controlled by AP-1 through SIRT6-dependent inhibition of survivin. Nat Cell <lb/>Biol 14: 1203-1211. <lb/>43. Dragani TA, Manenti G, Farza H, Della PG, Tiollais P, et al. (1990) Transgenic <lb/>mice containing hepatitis B virus sequences are more susceptible to carcinogen-<lb/>induced hepatocarcinogenesis. Carcinogenesis 11: 953-956. <lb/>44. Zheng Y, Chen WL, Louie SG, Yen TS, Ou JH (2007) Hepatitis B virus <lb/>promotes hepatocarcinogenesis in transgenic mice. Hepatology 45: 16-21. <lb/>45. Machida K, Tsukamoto H, Liu JC, Han YP, Govindarajan S, et al. (2010) c-Jun <lb/>mediates hepatitis C virus hepatocarcinogenesis through signal transducer and <lb/>activator of transcription 3 and nitric oxide-dependent impairment of oxidative <lb/>DNA repair. Hepatology 52: 480-492. <lb/>46. Schonthal AH (2012) Targeting endoplasmic reticulum stress for cancer therapy. <lb/>Front Biosci (Schol Ed) 4: 412-431. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Pathological Impact of HBV Surface Proteins <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">March 2014 | Volume 9 | Issue 3 | e90608 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
