<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Highlight: Bacteria Shed DNA as They Adapt to <lb/>Hot Temperatures <lb/>Danielle Venton* <lb/>*Corresponding author: E-mail: danielle.venton@gmail.com. <lb/>Accepted: April 10, 2013 <lb/></front>

			<body>Prokaryotic genomes are no-nonsense items: small, compact, <lb/>with very little DNA between their genes compared with <lb/>eukaryotes. Whether this is adaptive has, for decades, been <lb/>a mystery. <lb/>Genomic researchers have proposed that natural selection <lb/>may favor small genomes-weeding out superfluous mate-<lb/>rial-through a process called &quot;genomic streamlining.&quot; <lb/>Streamlining makes inherent sense because a small genome <lb/>should aid metabolic efficiency, because genome size is cor-<lb/>related with cell size. Many researchers believe cells divide and <lb/>replicate faster if they remain small. <lb/>As logical as genomic streamlining might be, few examples <lb/>have so far been found. Instead, a bevy of articles from the last <lb/>10 years show that three separate lines of evidence argue <lb/>against widespread streamlining in prokaryotes. Genetic <lb/>drift, a purely random process, has been suggested as the <lb/>driving force behind small prokaryotic genomes. <lb/>&quot;There exists a kind of cognitive dissonance between the <lb/>common wisdom among many biologists-that bacterial ge-<lb/>nomes are streamlined,&quot; says Andreas Wagner, an evolution-<lb/>ary biologist at the University of Zurich, &quot;and rather solid proof <lb/>from molecular data that most genomes are not.&quot; <lb/>That may be set to change, at least for one bacterial group. <lb/>In a recent article by Sabath et al. (2013) in Genome Biology <lb/>Evolution article, the authors report that the heat-loving bac-<lb/>teria have extremely trim genomes and that the same three <lb/>lines of evidence (mentioned earlier) argue in favor of stream-<lb/>lining among thermophiles. <lb/>Finding such evidence came as a great surprise. &quot;Given that <lb/>some of the best researchers out there had looked into this <lb/>problem,&quot; says Wagner, &quot;I was surprised that the same kinds <lb/>of evidence that argues against streamlining in general argues <lb/>for it for thermophiles.&quot; <lb/>The finding was actually a secondary question-a piece <lb/>of scientific serendipity. The team began the research as a <lb/>look at the association between bacterial genome size and <lb/>growth temperature (previously unreported). Only later on, <lb/>says Sabath, did the team decide to test the streamlining <lb/>hypothesis. <lb/>To start, they found that all species living at temperatures <lb/>above 60 C have genomes smaller than 4 million base pairs <lb/>(4 Mb), and species living at temperatures below 45 C have <lb/>genomes larger than 6 Mb. The hotter the habitat, the smaller <lb/>the genome. <lb/>To find out whether this reduction is caused by genetic drift <lb/>or streamlining, they asked three questions. First, evolution <lb/>should weed out noncoding regions of DNA faster than <lb/>coding regions. Second, generation time (or cell division <lb/>rate) should correlate with genome size. Last, the smaller <lb/>genomes should have a slower protein evolution rate (evi-<lb/>dence of stronger selective pressure). <lb/>Comparing the percentage of a genome&apos;s intergenic DNA <lb/>with genome size revealed that, across bacteria, genomes of <lb/>smaller thermophiles also contain a smaller percentage of their <lb/>DNA in noncoding regions. No such correlation was seen <lb/>in nonthermophiles. Similarly, thermophiles living at higher <lb/>temperatures divide significantly faster. Past work looking at <lb/>general bacteria, however, has found no correlation between <lb/>genome size and reproduction time. <lb/>For the last line of evidence, the team compared 40 gene <lb/>pairs evolved from a common ancestor gene in independent, <lb/>but closely related, taxa. The more quickly the genes evolve, <lb/>according to current biological thinking, the weaker the selec-<lb/>tive constraints on those proteins. They found no significant <lb/>correlation between evolution rate and temperature, in either <lb/>bacterial group. (Interestingly, proteins in thermophilic bacte-<lb/>ria were generally shorter than their orthologs in nonthermo-<lb/>philic bacteria, probably because loops which can destabilize <lb/>structure get lost in the proteins of thermophiles.) Neither did <lb/>they find a correlation comparing rate and genome size. With <lb/>a larger sample size, the authors suspect a negative associa-<lb/>tion might be detected with thermophiles. <lb/>&quot;Although our analysis did not show an equivalent <lb/>significant decrease in dN/dS ratios [a measure of evolution <lb/>rate] . . . it shows that selective constraints are not weaker <lb/>in thermophiles (as they are in obligate parasites and endo-<lb/>symbionts),&quot; write the authors. &quot;Thus, genome size reduction <lb/>is unlikely to be the result of drift.&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">GBE <lb/></note>

			<front>ß The Author(s) 2013. Published by Oxford University Press on behalf of the Society for Molecular Biology and Evolution. <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), which permits <lb/>non-commercial re-use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. For commercial re-use, please contact journals.permissions@oup.com <lb/>Genome Biol. Evol. 5(5):987-988. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt062 <lb/></front>

			<page>987 <lb/></page>

			<body>The team wanted to test whether heat was the actual <lb/>cause of the detected streamlining, not the habitat of ther-<lb/>mophiles. It is conceivable that the environment might be <lb/>driving genome shrinking. That&apos;s because bacteria living in <lb/>more variable environments are capable of more enzymatic <lb/>reactions to metabolize a variety of nutrients. &quot;Such organ-<lb/>isms would need to have larger genomes,&quot; the authors write, <lb/>&quot;to accommodate all the genes that encode these enzymes.&quot; <lb/>If organisms in high temperature habitats live with less envi-<lb/>ronmental variability, that might explain the pattern observed. <lb/>To determine whether this might be an influencing factor, <lb/>they examined about 500 microbes&apos; species for which <lb/>information on both growth temperature and habitat was <lb/>available. They saw no relationship between habitat variability <lb/>and genome size (with the exception of host-associated <lb/>organisms), but the link between temperature and genome <lb/>size remained clear. <lb/>So what is going on? Sabath et al. say it is unlikely that <lb/>fast replication is slimming down genomes. The cost of DNA <lb/>replication is relatively low. It&apos;s more likely, they think, <lb/>selection is acting upon cell size itself (small cells have small <lb/>genomes, for reasons that are foggy at the moment). A small <lb/>cell might be an advantage for absorbing scare nutrients or <lb/>to escape predation by other organisms or viruses. At high <lb/>temperatures, small size might be a special advantage-to <lb/>save nutrients. &quot;[Temperature] requires cells to increase <lb/>the lipid content and change the lipid composition of <lb/>cell membranes . . . [And] high temperature increases the <lb/>amount cells need to expend on non-growth associated <lb/>maintenance,&quot; write the authors. <lb/>However, nailing down the exact mechanistic cause of the <lb/>streamlining, Wagner says, is work for the future. <lb/></body>

			<back>

				<listBibl>Literature Cited <lb/>Sabath N, Ferrada E, Barve A, Wagner A. 2013. Growth temperature <lb/>and genome size in bacteria are negatively correlated, suggesting <lb/>genomic streamlining during thermal adaptation. Genome Biol Evol., <lb/>Advance Access published April 5, 2013, doi: 10.1093/gbe/evt050. <lb/></listBibl>

			</back>

			<front>Highlights editor: George Jianzhi Zhang <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Venton <lb/>GBE <lb/></note>

			<page>988 </page>

			<note place="footnote">Genome Biol. Evol. 5(5):987-988. doi:10.1093/gbe/evt062 </note>

	</text>
</tei>
