<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H <lb/>Open Access <lb/>The late phase of sepsis is characterized by an <lb/>increased microbiological burden and death rate <lb/>Gordon P Otto 1 , Maik Sossdorf 1 , Ralf A Claus 1 , Jürgen Rödel , Katja Menge , Konrad Reinhart , Michael Bauer and <lb/>Niels C Riedemann 1* <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction: Recent models capturing the pathophysiology of sepsis and ex-vivo data from patients are <lb/>speculating about immunosuppression in the so-called late phase of sepsis. Clinical data regarding survival and <lb/>microbiological burden are missing. The aim of this study was to determine the clinical significance of the &apos;late <lb/>phase&apos; of sepsis with respect to overall survival and occurrence of microbiological findings. <lb/>Methods: In a retrospective trial, 16,041 patient charts from a university intensive care unit were screened, and 999 <lb/>patients with severe sepsis or septic shock were identified. Three phases were established according to the <lb/>mortality peaks which were separated by two distinct nadirs: phase I (days 1 to 5), phase II (days 6 to 15) and <lb/>phase III (days 16 to 150). Patients were analyzed for outcome, SOFA scores, procalcitonin levels, antimicrobial <lb/>treatment, dialysis, mechanical ventilation and results of blood cultures during their hospital stay. <lb/>Results: Out of 999 enrolled patients, 308 died during the course of sepsis presenting a characteristic mortality rate <lb/>(30.8%) with three distinct mortality peaks (at days 2, 7 and 17). Overall 36.7% of all deaths occurred in the early <lb/>phase (phase I) and 63.3% during the later phases (phase II + III). In total 2,117 blood cultures were drawn. In <lb/>phase I, 882 blood cultures were drawn, representing a sampling rate of 88% with a positive rate of 14.9%. In <lb/>phase II, 461 samples were taken, indicating a sampling rate of 52% and a positive rate of 11.3%. Within phase III, <lb/>524 samples were obtained representing a sampling rate of 66% with a positive rate of 15.3%, which was <lb/>significantly higher compared to the positive rate of phase II and similar to phase I. In particular, the rate of <lb/>typically opportunistic bacteria increased significantly from 9% in phase I up to 18% in phase III. The same is true <lb/>for Candida spp. (phase I 13%, phase III 30%). <lb/>Conclusions: The later phase of sepsis is associated with a significant re-increase of positive blood culture results, <lb/>especially regarding opportunistic bacteria and fungi. These observations warrant further studies focusing on the <lb/>underlying mechanisms resulting in this outcome burden in the later phase of sepsis. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Despite aggressive supportive care to improve treatment <lb/>options and outcome, sepsis and its sequelae remain a <lb/>leading cause of death in intensive care units [1]. Exten-<lb/>sive studies investigating the host responses during sep-<lb/>sis have revealed that the late phase of sepsis is <lb/>dominated by a status of immune suppression with <lb/>respect to missing or widespread depressed innate, as <lb/>well as adaptive, immune defense mechanisms. Since <lb/>various authors introduced the intriguing model of a <lb/>phase-dependent variation of immune activity [2-4], the <lb/>concept of an anergic immune system is held responsi-<lb/>ble as a principal mechanism and cause of death in <lb/>patients with sepsis [5,6]. However, the concept itself, <lb/>but more the impact of sequential hyper-and hypo-<lb/>inflammatory phases, has been discussed controversially <lb/>[7-9]. The lack of tools assessing the individual immune <lb/>status of patients at the bedside and the complex patho-<lb/>physiological processes, which are often overlapping, <lb/>have so far limited the meaning of such concepts <lb/>describing hyper-and hypo-inflammatory immune <lb/>phases for the clinician. Confirmatory studies demon-<lb/>strating the clinical significance, especially of the so-<lb/>called late phase in sepsis, are largely missing. We, <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: Niels.Riedemann@med.uni-jena.de <lb/>1 <lb/>Clinic for Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, Jena University Hospital, <lb/>Erlanger Allee 101, 07747 Jena, Germany <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/> Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/> © 2011 Otto et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<body>therefore, thought to investigate whether a so-called late <lb/>phase during the course of sepsis would be accompanied <lb/>by higher death rates and higher rates of positive blood <lb/>culture results, especially by typically opportunistic bac-<lb/>teria. The latter might be interpreted as a hint for an <lb/>underlying immune suppressive status, which has been <lb/>suggested by many studies investigating separate <lb/>immune defense mechanisms in patients suffering from <lb/>sepsis [2,3,6,9]. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>To clarify this question we used a large database of <lb/>patient records from daily practice and performed a ret-<lb/>rospective trial enrolling patients admitted from 1 Janu-<lb/>ary 2006 to 31 December 2009 to the intensive care unit <lb/>of the Jena university hospital. The study was approved <lb/>by the institutional review board of Friedrich Schiller <lb/>University Hospital, Jena, Germany (3080-03/11). <lb/>Informed consent was waived due to the anonymous <lb/>nature of the analysis. A total of 16,041 patients were <lb/>screened according to the criteria of the American Col-<lb/>lege of Chest Physicians/Society of Critical Care Medi-<lb/>cine (ACCP/SCCM) for severe sepsis or septic shock <lb/>[10,11]. We identified 999 patients qualifying for severe <lb/>sepsis or septic shock and evaluated demographics, clini-<lb/>cal characteristics, disease severity measured by SOFA <lb/>score [12,13], procalcitonin levels (PCT), requirement of <lb/>renal replacement therapy and mechanical ventilation, <lb/>and outcome of patients, as well as the results of micro-<lb/>biological blood cultures and antimicrobial treatment. <lb/>By the observed trajectory of mortality, periods with <lb/>different mortality rates were identified and classified by <lb/>the nadirs, yielding in the definition of three distinct <lb/>phases: Phase I from Day 1 until Day 5, phase II from <lb/>Day 6 until Day 15 and phase III from Day 16 until the <lb/>end of the observation period at Day 150. To investigate <lb/>the relevance of the various phases, analyses of all <lb/>obtained blood cultures with respect to their date of <lb/>sampling during patients&apos; hospital stay were performed. <lb/>In addition, samples taken 10 days prior to clinical diag-<lb/>nosis of sepsis were included and this time period was <lb/>defined as phase 0 (Day -10 to Day -1). Coagulase nega-<lb/>tive staphylococci (CNS) were interpreted as skin con-<lb/>tamination of no importance and presented separately. <lb/>Furthermore, epidemiology of microorganisms in the <lb/>different phases was analyzed. Beside the total number <lb/>of positive findings, the relative numbers of drawn <lb/>blood cultures in relation to the number of patients <lb/>alive during that period and, in particular, the rate of <lb/>positive findings per obtained samples during the corre-<lb/>sponding phase were also analyzed. Additionally, the <lb/>practice of antimicrobial treatment and clinical charac-<lb/>teristics of patients were studied dependent of the <lb/>defined phases and dependent of the results from the <lb/>obtained blood cultures at the day of sampling. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>All data are reported as relative numbers, including ori-<lb/>ginal absolute numbers. A Chi-square test was used for <lb/>comparisons of categorical data. Continuous data across <lb/>multiple groups were compared by ANOVA testing with <lb/>Bonferroni adjustment. P-values &lt; 0.05 were considered <lb/>significant. Data were analyzed using SPSS software <lb/>(version 13) from SPSS Inc. (Chicago, IL, USA). <lb/>Results <lb/>Demographics, clinical characteristics and outcome <lb/>An overview of the demographics and clinical character-<lb/>istics from the identified patients with severe sepsis or <lb/>septic shock is given in Table 1. Out of these 999 <lb/>patients, 308 died during the course of severe sepsis or <lb/>septic shock. The outcome data plotted from first onset <lb/>of sepsis until Day 36 of these enrolled patients were <lb/>characterized by three peaks of increased mortality <lb/>rates. The first one occurred at Day 2 after reported <lb/>diagnosis, the second one at Day 7 and the last one at <lb/>around Day 17 (Figure 1). In agreement with the <lb/>addressed concept of a late phase of sepsis, the second <lb/>and third maximum values might pertain to this phase <lb/>of sepsis. The further analyses were strictly performed <lb/>according to the defined phases by the observed nadirs <lb/>of mortality rate (phase I: Day 1 until Day 5, phase II: <lb/>Day 6 until Day 15, phase III: Day 16 until the end of <lb/>the observation period at Day 150). <lb/>Table 1 Demographics and clinical characteristics of <lb/>enrolled patients with severe sepsis or septic shock <lb/>Demographics and clinical characteristics <lb/>Gender, male/female, # <lb/>660/339 <lb/>Age (years), median (IQR) <lb/>67 (56 to 75) <lb/>BMI (kg/m 2 ), median (IQR) <lb/>26.3 (23.9 to 29.6) <lb/>APACHE II Score at admission, median (IQR) <lb/>14 (11 to 19) <lb/>Type of ICU admission <lb/>Medical, # (%) <lb/>410 (41) <lb/>Surgical, # (%) <lb/>589 (59) <lb/>Co-morbid conditions, # (%) <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>533 (53) <lb/>Diabetes <lb/>305 (31) <lb/>Cancer <lb/>272 (27) <lb/>Intestinal ischemia <lb/>96 (10) <lb/>Liver failure <lb/>78 (8) <lb/>Characteristics of patients enrolled. BMI, body mass index; APACHE II, Acute <lb/>Physiology and Chronic Health Evaluation II score was calculated at ICU <lb/>admission; LOS, length of stay; IQR, interquartile range; #, numbers; %, relative <lb/>number. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Out of all deaths, 36.7% occurred before the end of <lb/>Day 5 during phase I and 63.3% (30.8% phase II and <lb/>32.5% phase III) during the following period (phase I vs. <lb/>phase II + III P ≤ 0.01; c 2 test) (Table 2). The mortality <lb/>rate of the later phase was 22% (10.7% phase II and <lb/>12.6% phase III) -significantly higher than in the early <lb/>phase I with 11.3% (phase I vs. phase II + III P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>c 2 test). With regard to these numbers, the later phases <lb/>of sepsis, phase II and, especially, phase III, demon-<lb/>strated a broad clinical significance. <lb/>Positive blood cultures without CNS <lb/>In total, 2,117 blood cultures were drawn. Prior to diag-<lb/>nosis in phase 0, 250 blood cultures were obtained, <lb/>equaling a sampling rate of 25%, of which 9.6% were <lb/>positive. During phase I, 882 blood cultures were drawn, <lb/>representing a sampling rate of 88.3% with a positive <lb/>rate of 14.9%. For the 886 patients alive in phase II, 461 <lb/>samples were taken indicating a sampling rate of 52% <lb/>and a positive rate of 11.3%. In the last phase III from <lb/>Day 16 until Day 150, 524 samples were obtained repre-<lb/>senting a sampling rate of 66.2% with a positive rate of <lb/>15.3% (Table 2). There was a significant reduction in <lb/>the numbers of drawn specimens per patient in phase II <lb/>(phase II vs. phase I P ≤ 0.01; c 2 test) and a significant <lb/>re-increase in phase III (phase III vs. phase II P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>c 2 test). A significant increase in the rate of positive <lb/>blood cultures was found in phase I compared to phase <lb/>0 (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test), the rate of positive findings <lb/>dropped in phase II (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test) and rose again in <lb/>phase III (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test) comparable to levels of <lb/>phase I (P &gt; 0.05; c 2 test). <lb/>Epidemiology of microorganisms <lb/>A detailed overview of the epidemiology of isolated <lb/>microorganisms depicted according to the different <lb/>Figure 1 Distribution of non survivors and positive blood cultures during sepsis. Relative numbers of deaths per day from 999 patients <lb/>with severe sepsis or septic shock according to ACCP/SCCM criteria are shown from the day of onset/diagnosis until observation Day 36. Three <lb/>phases were defined, characterized by the nadir at Day 5 and Day 15. Also, the average rates of positive blood cultures without CNS in a five-<lb/>day period with respect to sampling times are shown. bc, blood cultures; CNS, Coagulase negative staphylococci; #, numbers; %, relative number. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>phases is presented in the online data supplement and a <lb/>short overview in Table 3 (see also, Additional file 1). <lb/>The rate of bacteria classified as typically opportunistic <lb/>bacteria (TOB) increased over time from 7.7% in phase <lb/>0 up to 17.8% in phase III. In phase III, TOB were sig-<lb/>nificantly more often identified in comparison to phase <lb/>1 (phase I vs. phase III P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test). Furthermore, <lb/>the rate of isolated Candida spp. increased from 7.7% in <lb/>phase 0 up to 35.7% in phase II and 30% in phase III. <lb/>Both later phases were characterized by a significantly <lb/>higher rate of Candida spp. compared to both earlier <lb/>phases (phase II or III vs. phase 0 or I; P ≤ 0.05; c 2 <lb/>test). The rate of CNS ranged from 50.9% in phase 0 to <lb/>26.7% in phase I (phase I vs. phases 0, II, III; P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>c 2 test). <lb/>Severity and use of antimicrobials <lb/>In the severity of disease measured by SOFA score, as <lb/>well as in the course of PCT as a prototypic biomarker <lb/>of infection, significant differences were found between <lb/>the various phases. In phase I, both parameters peaked <lb/>with the highest levels (phase I vs. phases 0, II, III; P ≤ <lb/>0.01; ANOVA, Table 4) and fell over time to reach the <lb/>lowest levels at phase III (phase III vs. phases 0, I, II; P <lb/>≤ 0.01; ANOVA). The same was true for the require-<lb/>ment of mechanical ventilation with the highest rate of <lb/>90.9% in phase I (phase I vs. phases 0, II, III; P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>c 2 test). In the use of renal replacement therapy with <lb/>exception of phase 0, in which only 13% and, therefore, <lb/>significantly fewer patients needed dialyses, no signifi-<lb/>cant differences between the phases were found (phase <lb/>0 vs. phases I, II, III; P ≤ 0.01; ANOVA). <lb/>The rates of antimycotic therapy increased signifi-<lb/>cantly over time with the highest rate of 28.7% during <lb/>phase III (phase III vs. phases 0, I, II; P ≤ 0.01; c 2 test). <lb/>Azole antifungal drugs were prescribed most often. <lb/>Antibiotic treatment was performed most often in phase <lb/>I with a rate of 97.5% (phase I vs. phases 0, II, III; P ≤ <lb/>0.01; c 2 test). The primarily used antibiotics during this <lb/>time were carbapenems and glycopeptides. <lb/>Additional analyses, referring to the various phases <lb/>and results of blood cultures were performed, including <lb/>the SOFA score, PCT levels and the requirement of <lb/>mechanical ventilation and renal replacement therapy <lb/>on the day the corresponding blood culture was <lb/>sampled. No significant differences were found in the <lb/>Table 2 Characteristics of phase-dependent outcome and microbiological diagnosis <lb/>phases in relation to diagnosis <lb/>phase 0 <lb/>phase I <lb/>phase II <lb/>phase III <lb/>days prior to diagnosis or during sepsis <lb/>Day -10 to Day -1 <lb/>Day 1 to Day 5 <lb/>Day 6 to Day 15 <lb/>Day 16 to Day 150 <lb/># of patients alive at onset of phase, # <lb/>999 <lb/>999 <lb/>886 <lb/>791 <lb/># of non survivors during phase, # <lb/>113 <lb/>95 <lb/>100 <lb/>relative # of non survivors wrt all non survivors, # (%) <lb/>36.7 (113/308) <lb/>30.8 (95/308) <lb/>32.5 (100/308) <lb/>relative numbers of non survivors during phase, # (%) <lb/>11.3 (113/999) <lb/>10.7 (95/886) <lb/>12.6 (100/791) <lb/># of drawn bc during phase, # <lb/>250 <lb/>882 <lb/>461 <lb/>524 <lb/>relative # of bc per patient alive, # (%) <lb/>25.0 (250/999) § <lb/>88.3 (882/999) § <lb/>52 (461/886) § <lb/>66.2 (524/791) § <lb/># of all positive bc during phase, # <lb/>49 <lb/>173 <lb/>96 <lb/>146 <lb/>relative # of positive bc during phase, # (%) <lb/>19.6 (49/250) <lb/>19.6 (173/882)* <lb/>20.8 (96/461) <lb/>27.9 (146/524)* <lb/># of positive bc without CNS during phase, # <lb/>24 <lb/>131 <lb/>52 <lb/>80 <lb/>relative # of positive bc without CNS during phase, # (%) <lb/>9.6 (24/250) <lb/>14.9 (131/882)* <lb/>11.3 (52/461) <lb/>15.3 (80/524)* <lb/>Outcome of patients enrolled (n = 999) with severe sepsis or septic shock is shown corresponding to the distinct phases as defined in Figure 1, starting with <lb/>phase 0 including a period of 10 days prior to diagnosis of sepsis up to the end of phase III at Day 150. Also, the absolute numbers of drawn blood culture <lb/>samples, the rate of blood culture samples per number of patients, the rate of all positive blood cultures (including CNS) and the rate of positive blood cultures <lb/>without CNS are presented. CNS, Coagulase negative staphylococci; §, indicates statistically significant difference between all phases (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test); *, <lb/>indicates statistically significant difference compared to phase 0 and II (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test); #, absolute numbers; %, relative number; bc, blood cultures; wrt, with <lb/>respect to. <lb/>Table 3 Epidemiology of isolated microorganisms <lb/>microorganisms <lb/>phase 0 <lb/>phase I <lb/>phase II <lb/>phase III <lb/>number of positive bc without CNS, # <lb/>26 <lb/>143 <lb/>56 <lb/>90 <lb/>typically opportunistic bacteria (TOB), % (#) <lb/>7.7 (2) <lb/>9.1 (13) <lb/>14.3 (8) <lb/>17.8 (16)* <lb/>Candida spp. overall, % (#) <lb/>7.7 (2) <lb/>12.6 (18) <lb/>35.7 (19) § <lb/>30 (27) § <lb/>pathogenic bacteria, % (#) <lb/>88.5 (23) <lb/>78.3 (112) <lb/>51.8 (29) <lb/>52.2 (47) <lb/>CNS ssp. overall, # <lb/>52 <lb/>53 <lb/>78 <lb/>Isolated microorganisms from blood cultures of patients with severe sepsis or septic shock are demonstrated. The absolute as well as relative numbers are given <lb/>in dependency of defined phases. Others include all other isolated pathogen and presented separately in the online supplement (Additional file 1: Table S1). CNS <lb/>are also presented but excluded from relative analyses. CNS, Coagulase negative staphylococci; bc, blood cultures; *, indicates statistically significant difference <lb/>compared to phase I (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test); §, indicates statistically significant difference compared to phase 0 and phase I (P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>SOFA score. In contrast, higher PCT levels and rates of <lb/>mechanical ventilations were found in patients with <lb/>positive blood cultures during observation phase I, <lb/>phase II and phase III (bc -vs. bc + in phases I, II, III; P ≤ <lb/>0.05; c 2 test and ANOVA). For the use of renal replace-<lb/>ment therapy this was true for phase I and III (bc -vs. <lb/>bc + in phases I, III; P ≤ 0.05; c 2 test). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Our findings demonstrate in a large retrospective clini-<lb/>cal study, the presence of three distinct mortailty peaks <lb/>and two nadirs in the course of the monitored mortality <lb/>rates. We were, therefore, able to identify three clinical <lb/>phases, phase I -approximately until Day 5 after the <lb/>onset of sepsis, phase II -the following days until Day <lb/>15, and phase III -beginning at Day 16, strictly deter-<lb/>mined by such peaks and nadirs. A total of 63.3% of all <lb/>deaths occurred during the defined late phases II and <lb/>III, which implicates a broad clinical significance. <lb/>Furthermore, our data demonstrate a significantly <lb/>renewed rate of positive blood cultures occurring in <lb/>phase III of sepsis, as well as the highest rates of TOB <lb/>in this phase. High positive rates of blood cultures, and <lb/>especially the rise of TOB during this phase, may indi-<lb/>cate either an inability to overcome underlying infec-<lb/>tions or a possible increase in secondary infections. The <lb/>Table 4 Patients characteristics and the use of antimicrobials <lb/>phases in relation to diagnosis <lb/>phase 0 <lb/>phase I <lb/>phase II <lb/>phase III <lb/>Overall <lb/># of patients on ICU during phase, # <lb/>661 <lb/>999 <lb/>690 <lb/>327 <lb/>SOFA Score, mean ± SD <lb/>8.5 ± 3.6 <lb/>9.6 ± 3.8* <lb/>8.4 ± 4.0 <lb/>7.1 ± 3.9 <lb/>PCT, mean ± SD <lb/>5.0 ± 10.8 <lb/>10.3 ± 23.5* <lb/>3.2 ± 8.5 <lb/>2.0 ± 4.9 <lb/>Requirement of mechanical ventilation, % <lb/>(#) <lb/>78.8 (521) <lb/>90.9 (908)* <lb/>82.8 (571) <lb/>83.8 (274) <lb/>Requirement of renal replacement <lb/>therapy, % (#) <lb/>13.2 (87) § <lb/>27.7 (277) <lb/>28.7 (198) <lb/>30.9 (101) <lb/>Treatment with antimycotica, % (#) <lb/>5.1 (34) 2 <lb/>10.6 (106) 2 <lb/>17.5 (121) 2 <lb/>28.7 (94) 2 <lb/>Amphotericin <lb/>2.6 (17) <lb/>3 (30) <lb/>4.8 (33) <lb/>8 (26) <lb/>Fluconazole/Itroconazole/Ketoconazole <lb/>2 (13) <lb/>5.3 (53) <lb/>9.6 (66) <lb/>20.8 (68) <lb/>Voriconazole <lb/>1.1 (7) <lb/>1.8 (18) <lb/>4.1 (28) <lb/>5.2 (17) <lb/>Echinocadine (Anidulafungin/Caspofungin) <lb/>0.3 (2) <lb/>1.3 (13) <lb/>1.9 (13) <lb/>3.4 (11) <lb/>Treatment with antibiotica, % (#) <lb/>75.2 (497) 2 <lb/>97.5 (974) 2 <lb/>91.6 (632) 2 <lb/>81.3 (266) 2 <lb/>Glycopeptides (Teichoplanin/Vancomycine) <lb/>10.3 (68) <lb/>19.2 (192) <lb/>31.3 (216) <lb/>34.3 (112) <lb/>aminoglycosides <lb/>5.3 (35) <lb/>7.9 (79) <lb/>7.5 (52) <lb/>10.7 (35) <lb/>Glycylcyclines <lb/>1.2 (8) <lb/>1.8 (18) <lb/>4.6 (32) <lb/>11.3 (37) <lb/>quinolones <lb/>11.8 (78) <lb/>18.1 (181) <lb/>24.8 (171) <lb/>38.2 (125) <lb/>carbapenems <lb/>15.8 (104) <lb/>35.2 (352) <lb/>48.1 (332) <lb/>40.1 (131) <lb/>cephalosporins (3rd/4th generation) <lb/>11.8 (78) <lb/>14.4 (144) <lb/>14.3 (99) <lb/>20.2 (66) <lb/>tetracyclines <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>0.2 (2) <lb/>0.1 (1) <lb/>0.3 (1) <lb/>ansamycins <lb/>2 (13) <lb/>2.7 (27) <lb/>2.8 (19) <lb/>3.4 (11) <lb/>oxazolidinones <lb/>1.4 (9) <lb/>2.4 (24) <lb/>3.5 (24) <lb/>8 (26) <lb/>penicillin <lb/>39.2 (259) <lb/>57.1 (570) <lb/>39.9 (275) <lb/>27.5 (90) <lb/>others+ <lb/>31.3 (207) <lb/>29.5 (295) <lb/>28.4 (196) <lb/>27.2 (89) <lb/>In dependency of bloodculture results <lb/>bc -<lb/>bc + <lb/>bc -<lb/>bc + <lb/>bc -<lb/>bc + <lb/>bc -<lb/>bc + <lb/>SOFA Score, mean ± SD <lb/>9.19 ± 3.93 <lb/>9.29 ± <lb/>4.02 <lb/>10.02 ± 3.58 10.52 ± 3.67 9.58 ± 3.7 <lb/>10.18 ± <lb/>4.53 <lb/>8.7 ± 3.51 <lb/>8.42 ± <lb/>4.07 <lb/>PCT, mean ± SD <lb/>5.24 ± 7.38 <lb/>8.1 ± <lb/>11.34 <lb/>12.12 ± <lb/>25.25 <lb/>20.86 ± <lb/>43.82³ <lb/>3.09 ± <lb/>7.82 <lb/>6.68 ± <lb/>12.32³ <lb/>2.07 ± 4.12 <lb/>4.89 ± <lb/>12.5³ <lb/>Requirement of mechanical ventilation, % <lb/>(#) <lb/>76.4 (120/ <lb/>157) <lb/>100 (7/7) 79.3 (521/ <lb/>657) <lb/>95.4 (103/ <lb/>108)³ <lb/>66 (210/ <lb/>318) <lb/>92.5 (37/ <lb/>40)³ <lb/>44.8 (126/ <lb/>281) <lb/>79.2 (38/ <lb/>48)³ <lb/>Requirement of renal replacement <lb/>therapy, % (#) <lb/>85.7 (36/42) 100 (2/2) 84.9 (141/ <lb/>166) <lb/>100 (30/30)³ 81.8 (54/ <lb/>66) <lb/>90.9 (10/ <lb/>11) <lb/>48.2 (39/81) 85.7 (18/ <lb/>21)³ <lb/>Selected characteristics and antimicrobial treatment of patients corresponding to the distinct phases are demonstrated. The absolute, relative numbers and mean <lb/>± SDs are given. CNS, coagulase negative staphylococci; +, others include cephalosporins of the first and second generation, lincosamides, folic acid antagonists, <lb/>macrolide antibiotics and nitroimidazole; #, absolute numbers; %, relative number; bc, blood cultures; *, indicates statistically significant difference compared to <lb/>phase 0, phase II and phase III (P ≤ 0.05; ANOVA and c 2 test); §, indicates statistically significant difference compared to phase I, phase II and phase III (P ≤ 0.01; <lb/>ANOVA); 2 , indicates statistically significant differences between all phases (P ≤ 0.05; ANOVA); ³, indicates statistically significant difference compared to bc -(P ≤ <lb/>0.05; ANOVA and c 2 test). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>rate of drawn blood culture samples is comparable over-<lb/>all to data from available literature and representative of <lb/>practice patterns [14,15]. However, we observed an <lb/>expected and significant reduction in the numbers of <lb/>drawn specimens per patient in phase II and, surpris-<lb/>ingly, a significant increase in phase III. <lb/>The rates of positive cultures ranged from 9.6% prior <lb/>to diagnosis, significantly up to 14.9% during phase I, <lb/>dropping during phase II to levels of 11.3% and rising <lb/>again to 15.3% during the last observational period -<lb/>phase III. These significant patterns of positive findings <lb/>and the increase of TOB from 9.1% in phase I up to <lb/>17.8% in phase III might indicate an inability to clear <lb/>persistent infections or the appearance of new, second-<lb/>ary infections, and potentially suggest the clinical signifi-<lb/>cance of the late phase of sepsis. It might be speculated <lb/>that one of the underlying reasons could be the pro-<lb/>posed immune compromised status of patients with sep-<lb/>sis developing during the progression of disease. <lb/>Additionally, the rate of Candida spp. significantly <lb/>increased from 12.6% in phase I up to 35.7% in phase II, <lb/>and to 30.0% in phase III. An underlying mechanism <lb/>might be the frequent use of antibiotics in phase I. <lb/>In this retrospective review, we attempt to explore the <lb/>clinically impacted and microbiological pattern of the <lb/>late phase of sepsis as a cause of late morbidity and <lb/>mortality by dividing sepsis, according to the observed <lb/>mortality peaks, into three periods. We detected a sig-<lb/>nificant increase of positive blood cultures drawn in <lb/>patients with sepsis at a later time point with higher <lb/>rates of TOB, which may indicate an anergic immune <lb/>system. It needs to be understood that such implications <lb/>have a number of important drawbacks due to the <lb/>design of this study. First, the demonstrated higher fre-<lb/>quency rate of positive cultures will be very sensitive to <lb/>existing practice patterns. In our ICU the decision to <lb/>draw cultures will be taken according to the guidelines <lb/>recommending a sampling by signs and symptoms of <lb/>infections as a new onset of fever, chills, hypothermia, <lb/>leukocytosis, PCT (demonstrated by the high levels in <lb/>bc +/-patients at the sampling day) or a raise in CRP, <lb/>neutropenia or left shift in differential blood count. In <lb/>our opinion, sampling based on guidelines without a <lb/>prospective investigative protocol reflects the situation <lb/>on ICU more reliably. The sampling rate clearly shows a <lb/>drop from 88.3% in phase I to 52% in phase II and a <lb/>rise up to 66.2% in phase III. This might demonstrate <lb/>the still ongoing inflammatory response in these <lb/>patients, especially after phase I and II in which almost <lb/>all of our patients had already received guideline-appro-<lb/>priate antibiotic treatment. In contrast to the early <lb/>phase, in which well described guidelines for the sam-<lb/>pling indication and procedure exist, the indication for <lb/>blood culture sampling during the late time points are <lb/>often also determined by the clinical phenotype and <lb/>may not be as precisely captured when compared to the <lb/>onset phase. This fact represents a confounder which is <lb/>very difficult to control. Within this study, we used a <lb/>definition of TOB. However, a precise definition of TOB <lb/>does not exist, and it must be pointed out that our clas-<lb/>sification was based on data from the literature and the <lb/>expert opinion of microbiologists and intensive care <lb/>physicians, which may also represent a drawback with <lb/>respect to derived implications. A further limitation of <lb/>this study might be that there is important informative <lb/>censoring going on; patients who die early contribute to <lb/>the initial blood culture sampling quota but obviously <lb/>not to the later ones. In contrast, patients who did well <lb/>and left the ICU and were sampled later were still <lb/>included in our analyses. Patients who did well and left <lb/>the hospital were not observed further. However, all <lb/>three scenarios provoke no bias for the rate of positive <lb/>blood cultures. Also limiting might be the fact that the <lb/>number and the duration of uses of a central venous <lb/>catheter were not included in our analyses. Only the <lb/>requirement of mechanical ventilation and renal replace-<lb/>ment therapy as additional risk factors for infections <lb/>were analyzed in greater detail. This study shows that <lb/>patients with sepsis treated on our ICU at a later time <lb/>point (&gt;16 days) were still or even more likely to exhibit <lb/>a positive blood culture in comparison to earlier time <lb/>points and that such patients are more prone to develop <lb/>TOBs. Of course, these results are not necessarily a <lb/>legitimate or validated proxy for an anergic immune sys-<lb/>tem, but due to the absence of a clinically established <lb/>and relevant indicator for immune suppression in daily <lb/>practices, the data might serve as further hints for this <lb/>hypothesis, which has been much more clearly described <lb/>in models of experimental sepsis. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Most of the adjunctive clinical trials that were con-<lb/>ducted with the aim to treat sepsis focused on early and <lb/>anti-inflammatory mechanisms abrogating hyper-inflam-<lb/>mation, with most of them failing to deliver the antici-<lb/>pated results [16-22]. Only a few trials were designed <lb/>with a strategy aimed at the later phases or at improving <lb/>immune suppression [23-25]. However, both strategies <lb/>have so far not resulted in new therapeutics capable of <lb/>significantly improving outcomes of septic patients. Our <lb/>data demonstrate that the later phase of sepsis is asso-<lb/>ciated with a significant re-increase of positive blood <lb/>culture results, especially opportunistic bacteria and <lb/>fungi, and that a majority of all deaths occurred after <lb/>Day 5. These data have a large potential impact on <lb/>treatment, monitoring and outcome of septic patients. <lb/>However, the underlying mechanisms are so far not well <lb/>understood. It, therefore, appears to be warranted to pay <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>more attention to the late phase of sepsis and to develop <lb/>strategies detecting the patients&apos; host immune response <lb/>level. <lb/>Key messages <lb/>• The time course of disease in a large population of <lb/>patients suffering from severe sepsis or septic shock <lb/>was characterized by three different mortality peaks, <lb/>which suggests that these patients undergo phases <lb/>which may also be dominated by different underly-<lb/>ing pathophysiological mechanisms. <lb/>• The late phase of sepsis is characterized by a sig-<lb/>nificant resurgence of positive blood culture findings, <lb/>which underlines the importance of the innate <lb/>immune responses in this phase. <lb/>• Positive microbiological findings of opportunistic <lb/>bacteria and Candida spp. increase over the length <lb/>of ICU stay in patients with severe sepsis and septic <lb/>shock. <lb/>• In sepsis, diagnostic tools monitoring the immune <lb/>status as well as therapies aimed at restoring the <lb/>immune response are urgently needed. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Additional material <lb/>Additional file 1: Additional Table S1. Supplement Table <lb/>1Epidemiology of isolated microorganisms. Isolated microorganisms <lb/>from blood cultures of patients with severe sepsis or septic shock are <lb/>listed. The absolute as well as relative numbers are given dependent on <lb/>the pre-defined phases. CNS are also presented but excluded from <lb/>relative analyses. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>#: numbers; *: indicates statistically significant differences P ≤0.05; %: relative <lb/>number; χ 2 : Chi-square test; abs: absolute numbers; bc: blood cultures; bc +/-: <lb/>positive or negative blood cultures; CNS: coagulase negative staphylococci; <lb/>PCT: procalcitonin; SOFA score: Sequential Organ Failure Assessment score; <lb/>TOB: typically opportunistic bacteria; wrt: with respect to. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We would like to thank Dr. B. Kabisch (Department of Anaesthesiology and <lb/>Intensive Care, Jena University Hospital, Germany) for his valuable efforts in <lb/>data collection and Dr. M. Kohl (Department of Mechanical and Process <lb/>Engineering, Furtwangen University, Germany) for his helpful statistical <lb/>advice. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Clinic for Anesthesiology and Intensive Care, Jena University Hospital, <lb/>Erlanger Allee 101, 07747 Jena, Germany. 2 Institute of Medical Microbiology, <lb/>Jena University Hospital, Erlanger Allee 101, 07747 Jena, Germany. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>GPO designed the study and performed data analysis and interpretation, <lb/>and wrote the first draft of the manuscript. MS, RAC and KM were involved <lb/>in data analysis and interpretation, and the writing of the manuscript. JR was <lb/>involved in microorganism identification and interpretation. KR was involved <lb/>in study design and data collection. MB was involved in data management <lb/>and interpretation. NCR was involved in study design, data analysis, and the <lb/>writing of the manuscript. All authors read and approved the final draft of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 24 February 2011 Revised: July 2011 <lb/>Accepted: 28 July 2011 Published: 28 July 2011 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Angus DC: The lingering consequences of sepsis: a hidden public health <lb/>disaster? JAMA 2010, 304:1833-1834. <lb/>2. Hotchkiss RS, Karl IE: The pathophysiology and treatment of sepsis. N Engl <lb/>J Med 2003, 348:138-150. <lb/>3. Bone RC: Sir Isaac Newton, sepsis, SIRS, and CARS. Crit Care Med 1996, <lb/>24:1125-1128. <lb/>4. Kox WJ, Volk T, Kox SN, Volk HD: Immunomodulatory therapies in sepsis. <lb/>Intensive Care Med 2000, 26(Suppl 1):S124-128. <lb/>5. Hotchkiss RS, Strasser A, McDunn JE, Swanson PE: Cell death. N Engl J Med <lb/>2009, 361:1570-1583. <lb/>6. Hotchkiss RS, Opal S: Immunotherapy for sepsis a new approach against <lb/>an ancient foe. N Engl J Med 2010, 363:87-89. <lb/>7. Netea MG, van der Meer JW, van Deuren M, Kullberg BJ: Proinflammatory <lb/>cytokines and sepsis syndrome: not enough, or too much of a good <lb/>thing? Trends Immunol 2003, 24:254-258. <lb/>8. Venet F, Davin F, Guignant C, Larue A, Cazalis MA, Darbon R, Allombert C, <lb/>Mougin B, Malcus C, Poitevin-Later F, Lepape A, Monneret G: Early <lb/>assessment of leukocyte alterations at diagnosis of septic shock. Shock <lb/>2010, 34:358-363. <lb/>9. Riedemann NC, Guo RF, Ward PA: Novel strategies for the treatment of <lb/>sepsis. Nat Med 2003, 9:517-524. <lb/>10. Levy MM, Fink MP, Marshall JC, Abraham E, Angus D, Cook D, Cohen J, <lb/>Opal SM, Vincent JL, Ramsay G: 2001 SCCM/ESICM/ACCP/ATS/SIS <lb/>International Sepsis Definitions Conference. Crit Care Med 2003, <lb/>31:1250-1256. <lb/>11. Bone RC, Balk RA, Cerra FB, Dellinger RP, Fein AM, Knaus WA, Schein RM, <lb/>Sibbald WJ: Definitions for sepsis and organ failure and guidelines for <lb/>the use of innovative therapies in sepsis. The ACCP/SCCM Consensus <lb/>Conference Committee. American College of Chest Physicians/Society of <lb/>Critical Care Medicine. Chest 1992, 101:1644-1655. <lb/>12. Vincent JL, de Mendonca A, Cantraine F, Moreno R, Takala J, Suter PM, <lb/>Sprung CL, Colardyn F, Blecher S: Use of the SOFA score to assess the <lb/>incidence of organ dysfunction/failure in intensive care units: results of <lb/>a multicenter, prospective study. Working group on &quot;sepsis-related <lb/>problems&quot; of the European Society of Intensive Care Medicine. Critical <lb/>Care Medicine 1998, 26:1793-1800. <lb/>13. Vincent JL, Moreno R, Takala J, Willatts S, De Mendonca A, Bruining H, <lb/>Reinhart CK, Suter PM, Thijs LG: The SOFA (Sepsis-related Organ Failure <lb/>Assessment) score to describe organ dysfunction/failure. On behalf of <lb/>the Working Group on Sepsis-Related Problems of the European Society <lb/>of Intensive Care Medicine. Intensive Care Med 1996, 22:707-710. <lb/>14. Westh H, Lisby G, Breysse F, Boddinghaus B, Chomarat M, Gant V, Goglio A, <lb/>Raglio A, Schuster H, Stuber F, Wissing H, Hoeft A: Multiplex real-time PCR <lb/>and blood culture for identification of bloodstream pathogens in <lb/>patients with suspected sepsis. Clin Microbiol Infect 2009, 15:544-551. <lb/>15. Ehrenstein BP, Ehrenstein V, Henke C, Linde HJ, Salzberger B, Scholmerich J, <lb/>Gluck T: Risk factors for negative blood cultures in adult medical <lb/>inpatients a retrospective analysis. BMC Infect Dis 2008, 8:148. <lb/>16. Sprung CL, Annane D, Keh D, Moreno R, Singer M, Freivogel K, Weiss YG, <lb/>Benbenishty J, Kalenka A, Forst H, Laterre PF, Reinhart K, Cuthbertson BH, <lb/>Payen D, Briegel J: Hydrocortisone therapy for patients with septic shock. <lb/>N Engl J Med 2008, 358:111-124. <lb/>17. Bernard GR, Vincent JL, Laterre PF, LaRosa SP, Dhainaut JF, Lopez-<lb/>Rodriguez A, Steingrub JS, Garber GE, Helterbrand JD, Ely EW, Fisher CJ Jr: <lb/>Efficacy and safety of recombinant human activated protein C for severe <lb/>sepsis. N Engl J Med 2001, 344:699-709. <lb/>18. Eichacker PQ, Natanson C: Increasing evidence that the risks of rhAPC <lb/>may outweigh its benefits. Intensive Care Med 2007, 33:396-399. <lb/>19. Rivers E, Nguyen B, Havstad S, Ressler J, Muzzin A, Knoblich B, Peterson E, <lb/>Tomlanovich M: Early goal-directed therapy in the treatment of severe <lb/>sepsis and septic shock. N Engl J Med 2001, 345:1368-1377. <lb/>20. Abraham E, Anzueto A, Gutierrez G, Tessler S, San Pedro G, Wunderink R, <lb/>Dal Nogare A, Nasraway S, Berman S, Cooney R, Levy H, Baughman R, <lb/>Rumbak M, Light RB, Poole L, Allred R, Constant J, Pennington J, Porter S: <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Double-blind randomised controlled trial of monoclonal antibody to <lb/>human tumour necrosis factor in treatment of septic shock. NORASEPT <lb/>II Study Group. Lancet 1998, 351:929-933. <lb/>21. Abraham E, Wunderink R, Silverman H, Perl TM, Nasraway S, Levy H, Bone R, <lb/>Wenzel RP, Balk R, Allred R, Pennington JE, Wherry JC, TNF-a MAb Sepsis <lb/>Study Group, Abraham E, Bellamy P, Cryer H, Busuttil R, Winston D, Perry C, <lb/>Wunderink R, Leeper KV, Jones C, Silverman H, Martin M, Tuma P, Baird I, <lb/>Brooks J, Baird R, Wenzel RP, Perl TM, et al: Efficacy and safety of <lb/>monoclonal antibody to human tumor necrosis factor alpha in patients <lb/>with sepsis syndrome. A randomized, controlled, double-blind, <lb/>multicenter clinical trial. TNF-alpha MAb Sepsis Study Group. JAMA 1995, <lb/>273:934-941. <lb/>22. Angus DC, Crowther MA: Unraveling severe sepsis: why did OPTIMIST fail <lb/>and what&apos;s next? JAMA 2003, 290:256-258. <lb/>23. Meisel C, Schefold JC, Pschowski R, Baumann T, Hetzger K, Gregor J, Weber-<lb/>Carstens S, Hasper D, Keh D, Zuckermann H, Reinke P, Volk HD: <lb/>Granulocyte-macrophage colony-stimulating factor to reverse sepsis-<lb/>associated immunosuppression: a double-blind, randomized, placebo-<lb/>controlled multicenter trial. Am J Respir Crit Care Med 2009, 180:640-648. <lb/>24. Nelson S, Belknap SM, Carlson RW, Dale D, DeBoisblanc B, Farkas S, <lb/>Fotheringham N, Ho H, Marrie T, Movahhed H, Root R, Wilson J: A <lb/>randomized controlled trial of filgrastim as an adjunct to antibiotics for <lb/>treatment of hospitalized patients with community-acquired <lb/>pneumonia. CAP Study Group. J Infect Dis 1998, 178:1075-1080. <lb/>25. Kox WJ, Bone RC, Krausch D, Docke WD, Kox SN, Wauer H, Egerer K, <lb/>Querner S, Asadullah K, von Baehr R, Volk HD: Interferon gamma-1b in the <lb/>treatment of compensatory anti-inflammatory response syndrome. A <lb/>new approach: proof of principle. Arch Intern Med 1997, 157:389-393. <lb/>doi:10.1186/cc10332 <lb/>Cite this article as: Otto et al.: The late phase of sepsis is characterized <lb/>by an increased microbiological burden and death rate. Critical Care <lb/>2011 15:R183. <lb/></listBibl>

			Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and take full advantage of: <lb/>• Convenient online submission <lb/>• Thorough peer review <lb/>• No space constraints or color figure charges <lb/>• Immediate publication on acceptance <lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar <lb/>• Research which is freely available for redistribution <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">Otto et al. Critical Care 2011, 15:R183 <lb/>http://ccforum.com/content/15/4/R183 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 8 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
