<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Editorial <lb/>Case Report <lb/>Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports 2013 April-June;3(2):32-34 <lb/>The Incomplete Superficial Palmar Arch <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Anneh Mohammad Gharravi* <lb/>Mohammad Reza <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>Gholami ,Daryoush Bijan Nejad <lb/>, Saeed Azandeh , <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction: <lb/>Case Report: <lb/>Conclusion: <lb/>Keywords: S <lb/>Superficial palmar arch (SPA) is dominant vascular structure in palm of hand. In <lb/>present study we described a case of Ulnar / Radiopalmar pattern of incomplete SPA in an Iranian <lb/>cadaver. When the SPA is complete, the superficial palmer branches of the radial artery contribute <lb/>to the ulnar artery. In incomplete type of SPA, there was no anastomosis between the ulnar and <lb/>radial arteries (UA, RA). <lb/>In the present case, the brachial artery divided into RA and UA at the cubital fossa. <lb/>There was no anastomosis between radial and ulnar arteries (RA, UA) in the palm of the hand. UA <lb/>gave three palmar digital arteries; proper palmar digital artery and two common palmar digital <lb/>arteries. RA gave proper palmar digital artery and arteria princeps pollicis. <lb/>Knowledge of anatomical variation of SPA is important for the hand surgical <lb/>interventions and this is a very rare variation which can be easily tested clinically by Allen&apos;s test <lb/>uperficial palmar arch, Ulnar artery, Radial artery <lb/>Copyright © 2013 by Journal of Orthpaedic Case Reports <lb/>Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports | pISSN 2250-0685 | eISSN <lb/>| Available on www.jocr.co.in | doi: <lb/>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0) which permits <lb/>unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>2321-3817 <lb/>10.13107/jocr.2250-0685.099 <lb/>What to Learn from this Article? <lb/>A rare variation of Incomplete Palmar arch? <lb/>Anatomical and Clinical review of such presentation? <lb/></front>

			<page>32 <lb/></page>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Although several studies have reported on various aspects <lb/>Superficial palmar arch (SPA) as a dominant vascular of the SPA form several countries, to our knowledge, no <lb/>structure supplies a majority of the muscles of the palm of study has attempted to report anatomical variation of SPA <lb/>the hand. The arch is localized between the palmer from Iran. <lb/>aponeurosis and the long flexor tendons [1]. When the In addition, road traffic injuries rate in Iran is the highest <lb/>SPA is complete, the superficial palmer branches of the of any country in the world for which reliable estimates are <lb/>radial artery contribute to the ulnar artery. In incomplete available [4] that need to surgical intervention. <lb/>type of SPA, there is no anastomosis between the ulnar and Awareness and identification of the SPA variation in the <lb/>radial arteries (UA, RA) [2]. Various variations in the SPA hands is critical for orthopaedicians and microvascular <lb/>have been studied by several authors. According to surgeons performing advanced surgical procedures such <lb/>Coleman and Anson (1961), the incomplete type of SPA is as arterial repairs, vascular graft applications. Therefore <lb/>categorized into four subtypes based on the absence of a we report a case of incomplete type of SPA in an Iranian <lb/>communication or anastomosis between the radial, 

			cadaver that is the first report of this variation. <lb/>

			median and the ulnar arteries [3]. <lb/></body>

			<front>Dr. Anne Mohammad Gharravi <lb/>Author&apos;s Photo Gallery <lb/>1 <lb/>Sciences, Shahroud, Iran. <lb/>2 Department of anatomy, Faculty of Medicine, Ahvaz <lb/>Jundishapour University of Medical Sciences (AJUMS), <lb/>Ahvaz, Iran <lb/>3 Department of anatomy, Faculty of Medicine, Lorestan <lb/>University of Medical Sciences, Khorram Abad, Iran <lb/>Address of Correspondence <lb/>Dr. Anneh Mohammad Gharravi <lb/>School of Medicine, Shahroud University of Medical <lb/>Sciences, Shahroud, Iran. <lb/>E-mail: annehgh@yahoo.com <lb/>School of Medicine, Shahroud University of Medical <lb/>Dr. Saeed Azandeh <lb/>Dr. Mohammad R Gholami Dr. Darioush B Nejad <lb/>Case Report <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Discussion <lb/>References <lb/></front>

			<body>Ulnar / Radiopalmar pattern from Iranian population; <lb/>and we believe that this is first report from our geopolitical <lb/>area. <lb/>Clinically the anastomosis between radial and ulnar <lb/>arteries in hand is of great significance when performing <lb/>surgical procedures on hand, forearm or on individual <lb/>arteries. One of the complications of common procedure <lb/>of radial artery like arterial blood sampling is occlusion of <lb/>the artery, however in these situations the hand perfusion <lb/>can be maintained by the ulnar artery through the palmar <lb/>arch. This can be easily established by using Allen&apos;s test <lb/>[11] or Doppler ultrasound studies [12] which can <lb/>provide good idea about the continuity of the palmar <lb/>arches. In cases of incomplete palmar arch, as in this case, <lb/>the Allen&apos;s test will be negative confirmed with and both <lb/>radius and ulna arteries will behave as &apos;end arteries&apos;. Thus <lb/>any procedure on radial or ulnar artery needs to be <lb/>After proper skin incision and dissection of flexor carefully planned and potential of ischemic complications <lb/>retinaculum, palmar aponeurosis and deep fascia covering should be kept in mind. <lb/>the thenar and hypothenar muscles, we encountered an <lb/>incomplete type of SPA in the left upper extremity of a <lb/>In viewof high rate of road traffic injuries in Iran and need <lb/>formalin-fixed adult male cadaver during routine <lb/>for surgical intervention, the anatomic knowledge of the <lb/>dissection. The history of the individual and the cause of <lb/>SPA variability as a dominant vascular structure of palm <lb/>death was not known. In the present case, the brachial <lb/>becomes essential. <lb/>artery divided into RA and UA at the cubital fossa. There <lb/>was no anastomosis between RA and UA at palm of hand <lb/>and SPA was incomplete. UA gave three palmar digital <lb/>arteries; proper palmar digital artery and two common <lb/>palmar digital arteries which passed to the medial three <lb/>interdigital clefts. RA gave two branches: proper palmar <lb/>digital artery to the radial side of the index finger and an <lb/>arteria princeps pollicis (Fig. 1). <lb/>A classic morphology of complete SPA is formed by the <lb/>linkage between superficial palmar branches of the radial <lb/>and ulnar arteries. But other morphology of incomplete <lb/>SPA was reported. The incidence of the incomplete SPA <lb/>reported 10%, 16%, 16% and 21.47% of cases in studies of <lb/>Loukas, et al. (2005), Patnaik, et al. (2002), Al-turk and <lb/>Metcalf. (1984) and Coleman and Anson (1961), <lb/>respectively. Most of the SPA arches (54.76%), in the study <lb/>of Sarkar et al. (2012) were incomplete [3, 5-8]. <lb/>According to Ottone, et al. (2010) the present case is Ulnar <lb/>/ Radiopalmar pattern subtype of incomplete SPA (9). The <lb/>incidence of this variation reported in 8.3%, 3.2% and <lb/>3.6% of cases in studies of Ottone, et al. (2010), Coleman <lb/>and Anson (1961) and Ikeda et al. (1988) [9,3,10]. <lb/>There was no report of the incomplete SPA, especially <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>1. Gajisin S, Zbrodowski A. Local vascular contribution of the <lb/>superficial palmar arch. Acta. Anat (Basel) 1993;147: 248-251. <lb/>2. Gellman H, Botte MJ, Shankwiler J, Gelberman RH. Arterial <lb/>patterns of the deep and superficial palmar arches. Clin Orthop <lb/>Relat Res 2001;383:41-46. <lb/>3. Coleman SS, Anson BJ. Arterial patterns in the hand based upon <lb/>the study of 650 specimens. Surg Gynecol Obstet 1961;113:409-424. <lb/>4. Bhalla K, Naghavi M, Shahraz S, Bartels D, Murray CJ. Building <lb/>national estimates of the burden of road traffic injuries in developing <lb/>countries from all available data sources: Iran. Inj Prev <lb/>2009;15:150-156. <lb/>5. Loukas M, Holdman D, Holdman S. Anatomical variations of the <lb/>superficial and deep palmar arches. Folia Morphol (Warsz) 2005; <lb/>64:78-83. <lb/>6. Patnaik VVG, Kalsey G, Singla RK. Palmar Arterial Arches-A <lb/>Morphological Study. J Anat Soc India 2002;51(2):187-193. <lb/>7. Al-Turk M, Metcalf WK. A study of the superficial palmar arteries <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.jocr.co.in <lb/>Gharravi et al <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports | Volume 3 | Issue 2 | April -June 2013 | Page 32-34 <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1 -Ventral aspect of the left hand. A, Cadaveric hand exhibiting the incomplete <lb/>type of SPA. B, Patterns of SPA ;HE, hypothenar eminence; RA, radial artery; TE, <lb/>thenar eminence; UA, ulnar artery; SPA, Superficial palmar arch; CDA, common <lb/>digital arteries; PDA, proper digital artery; APP, arteria princeps pollicis, * indicate the <lb/>Median nerve and arrow shown flexor retinaculum. <lb/>

			Clinical Message <lb/>Superficial palmar arch (SPA) as a dominant vascular <lb/>structure supplies a majority of the muscles of the <lb/>palm of the hand. Therefore The SPA variation should <lb/>be considered by orthopaedicians and microvascular <lb/>surgeons performing advanced surgical procedures <lb/>such as arterial repairs, vascular graft applications. <lb/></body>

			<page>33 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">www.jocr.co.in <lb/>Gharravi et al <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Journal of Orthopaedic Case Reports | Volume 3 | Issue 2 | April -June 2013 | Page 32-34 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>using the Doppler Ultrasonic Flow meter. J Anat 1984;138:27-32. <lb/>the hand based on three-dimensional analysis of 220 cadaver hands. <lb/>J Hand Surg 1988;13A:501-509. <lb/>8. Sarkar A, Dutta S, Bal K, Biswas J. Handedness may be related to <lb/>variations in palmar arterial arches in humans. Singapore Med J <lb/>11. Allen EV. Thromboangiitis obliterans: methods of diagnosis of <lb/>2012;53: 409-412 <lb/>chronic occlusive arterial lesions distal to the wrist with illustrative <lb/>cases. Am J Med Sci 1929;2:1-8. <lb/>9. Provenzano R. W. Congenital Dislocation of the Knee. Report of a <lb/>Case. New England Journal Medicine 1947 236: 360-362. <lb/>12. Starnes SL, Wolk SW, Lampman RM, Shanley CJ, Prager RL, <lb/>Kong BK, Fowler JJ, Page JM, Babcock SL, Lange LA, Erlandson EE, <lb/>10. Ikeda A, Ugawa A, Kazihara Y, Hamada N. Arterial patterns in <lb/>Whitehouse WM Jr. Noninvasive <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest: Nil <lb/>Source of Support: None <lb/>How to Cite this Article: <lb/>Gharravi AM, Azandeh S, Gholami MR, Nejad DB. The Incomplete Superficial Palmar Arch. Journal of <lb/>Orthopaedic Case Reports 2013 April-June;3(2): 32-34 <lb/></div>

			<page>34 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">An International Peer Review Journal Publishing Complex, Complicated and Difficult <lb/>Musculoskeletal Cases <lb/>Complications are one of the most important events in Career of an Orthopaedic Surgeons. Complications and Complex and <lb/>complicated cases provide an opportunity to learn practical points about patient management and lead to continuous <lb/>improvement in our surgical skills and clinical decision making. <lb/>Journal of Orthopaedic Complications (JOC) is First of its kind journal where a complete journal is dedicated to Complications <lb/>and difficult complex musculoskeletal cases. The submission format is kept very simple and practical. <lb/>Scope of the Journal <lb/>JOC will publish complicated/complications of musculoskeletal cases from all faculties including but not limited to Orthopaedic, <lb/>Rheumatology, Physiotherapy, Occupational therapy, Neurology, Neurosurgery, Oncology and Congenital disorders. <lb/>Manuscripts must meet one of the following criteria: <lb/>1. Primarily Complex or Difficult Cases <lb/>2. Known and Unknown Complication of a disease, fracture, treatment, implant. <lb/>3. Complications due to associated diagnosed or undiagnosed co-morbidities <lb/>4. A known complication treated with a new or rarely reported method <lb/>5. Any unexpected event in the course of observing or treating a patient <lb/>6. Cases presenting with failed primary management with complicated clinical condition <lb/>7. Delayed presentation of a fracture or disease leading to complex presentation <lb/>8. Unusual findings that shed new light on the possible pathogenesis of a disease or an adverse effect <lb/>9. A small series of cases with unusual Complication. <lb/>10. A technical note demonstrated on a single complicated case. <lb/>11. A series of cases {prospective or retrospective] using particular management modality with common complications over a <lb/>period of time [a case series of complications]. Example a case series of complications of proximal femur nail in treatment of <lb/>intertrochanteric fractures. <lb/>12. Complication Bank: this special section will publish every complex and complicated case associated with orthopaedic <lb/>surgery. Authors can send any case with complications [known or unknown; common or uncommon] and it will be published. <lb/>This need not be with details of management or follow up of the case. The idea is to create a database of complications <lb/>associated with various orthopaedic surgeries and dieases. A single page write up of less than 1000 words will be accepted. <lb/>Manuscripts will be reviewed by the Editorial Board and two external referees, and authors will usually receive a decision on <lb/>their manuscript within 8-12 weeks. <lb/>All manuscripts are to be submitted via journal submission software &apos;Scripture&apos; on the website www.orthocomplications.com. <lb/>Submissions can also be mailed to orthocomplications@gmail.com <lb/>JOC will accept following formats of articles: Case Reports, Original article on complications, Complication Bank Cases (as <lb/>above), Case Image, Technical Note on treatment of a complex/complicated case, Video Technique, Surgical Tips on avoiding <lb/>/ treating complications, Case Study /Series, Case Approach, Letter to Editor, Letter to Experts and Expert Opinion <lb/>Visit <lb/>for more information about the format and submission process. <lb/>www.orthocomplications.com </div>


	</text>
</tei>
