<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>M E E T I N G A B S T R A C T <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Bronchial hyperreactivity induced by tropomyosins <lb/>from cockroach and shrimp: a mouse model to <lb/>study in vivo cross-reactivity <lb/>Thalita Martins * , Marina Dias, Rafael Prado, Thamires Milani, Adriana S Moreno, Luana Maia, Vânia Bonato, <lb/>Simone Ramos, Marcos Borges, L Karla Arruda <lb/>From 3rd WAO International Scientific Conference (WISC) <lb/>Rio de Janeiro, Brazil. 6-9 December 2014 <lb/>Background <lb/>In vivo cross-reactivity among tropomyosins, major pan-<lb/>allergens among invertebrates, is not established. Our aim <lb/>was to investigate the effects of purified tropomyosins <lb/>from cockroach (recombinant Per a 7) and shrimp (natural <lb/>Lit v 1) on airway inflammation and hyperresponsiveness <lb/>in a mouse model of asthma. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Balb/c mice, 4 to 6 weeks-old, were sensitized twice with <lb/>50μg of rPer a 7 or nLit v 1 intraperitoneally with 1 mg <lb/>alum, and challenged with 50μg of rPer a 7 or nLit v 1 intra-<lb/>nasally for three days. A group was sensitized with rPer a 7 <lb/>and challenged with nLit v 1 under same conditions. Con-<lb/>trols received saline on same days. Twenty-four hours after <lb/>the last challenge, mice were ventilated with FlexiVent ® , <lb/>and in vivo bronchial hyperresponsiveness was evaluated <lb/>with increased doses of inhaled methacholine (6.25, 12.5, <lb/>25 and 50mg/ml). After ventilation, bronchoalveolar lavage <lb/>fluid (BALF) was collected and cell counts were performed. <lb/>Results <lb/>Sensitization and challenge of mice with rPer a 7 or nLit <lb/>v 1 resulted in increase in bronchial hyperresponsive-<lb/>ness, given by increase in total and tissue resistance and <lb/>elastance. Total cells in BALF increased in rPer a 7 <lb/>(1×10 5 vs 3×10 5 , p&lt;0.01) and nLit v 1 (1×10 vs 1×10 6 , <lb/>p&lt;0.001) groups, as compared to controls. There was <lb/>increase in macrophages for rPer a 7 (5×10 4 vs 1×10 5 , <lb/>p&lt;0.001) and nLit v 1 (5×10 vs 3×10 5 , p&lt;0.001) and <lb/>eosinophils for rPer a 7 (2×10 vs 1.4×10 5 , p&lt;0.001) and <lb/>nLit v 1 (2x10 3 vs 9.1x10 5 , p&lt;0.001). Mice immunized <lb/>with rPer a 7 and challenged with nLit v 1 showed no <lb/>changes in bronchial hyperresponsiveness or eosinophils <lb/>on BALF as compared to controls (2x10 vs 6x10 3 ). <lb/>However, there was an increase in neutrophils in this <lb/>group as compared to controls (5x10 vs 1x10 5 , p&lt;0.01). <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Experimental asthma induced by purified tropomyosins <lb/>from cockroach and shrimp mimicked the main character-<lb/>istics of human asthma. Despite the high degree of <lb/>sequence identity and IgE immunologic cross-reactivity, <lb/>our data suggested that in vivo cross-reactivity of these <lb/>tropomyosins is unlikely. <lb/> Published: 8 April 2015 <lb/>doi:10.1186/1939-4551-8-S1-A264 <lb/>Cite this article as: Martins et al.: Bronchial hyperreactivity induced by <lb/>tropomyosins from cockroach and shrimp: a mouse model to study in <lb/>vivo cross-reactivity. World Allergy Organization Journal 2015 8(Suppl 1):A264. <lb/></front>
			
			<div type="annex">Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and take full advantage of: <lb/>• Convenient online submission <lb/>• Thorough peer review <lb/>• No space constraints or color figure charges <lb/>• Immediate publication on acceptance <lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar <lb/>• Research which is freely available for redistribution <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/>School of Medicine of Ribeirao Preto -University of Sao Paulo, Brazil <lb/>Martins et al. World Allergy Organization Journal 2015, 8(Suppl 1):A264 <lb/>http://www.waojournal.org/content/8/S1/A264 <lb/></div>

			<front>© Martins et al; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver (http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated. </front>


	</text>
</tei>
