<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<page>106 </page>

			<front>Copyright © 2014 Korean Neurotraumatology Society <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) is one of the most <lb/>common disorders in the field of neurosurgery. 2) The current <lb/>understanding of the mechanism of development of CSDH <lb/>is that damage to the bridging veins by minor head trauma <lb/>results in a collection of hematomas in the subdural space. 15) <lb/>Then, the hematomas form a vessel-rich outer membrane. 18,21) <lb/>Fragility of this neovasculature leads to repeated micro-<lb/>bleeding and increases the permeability of the membrane, <lb/>resulting in the development of CSDH. 2,3,13,14) The known <lb/>risk factors of CSDH are trauma, old age, brain atrophy, al-<lb/>cohol abuse, seizure, coagulopathy, the use of anti-platelets, <lb/>and the use of anticoagulants. 7,10) In this study, we focused <lb/>on the fact that some patients do not develop CSDH after <lb/>head trauma and proceed through therapy without any com-<lb/>plications, while others need additional surgeries to treat <lb/>CSDH. Assuming there are differences between the pa-<lb/>tients who develop CSDH and those who do not, we inves-<lb/>tigated the various known risk factors, along with the com-<lb/>puted tomographic findings at the time of the head injury. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>We conducted a survey of 277 patients who scored over <lb/>13 on the Glasgow coma scale who received treatment at <lb/>our institution after minor head trauma in the period from <lb/>January 2012 to December 2013. Patients were enrolled pro-<lb/>spectively and their medical records were reviewed retro-<lb/>spectively. All the patients did not require surgery at the time <lb/>of their arrival. During the follow-up period, the 20 patients <lb/>who required surgery to treat CSDH were designated as the <lb/></body>

			<front>Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor <lb/>Head Trauma Patients <lb/>Sang-Beom Han, MD, Seung-Won Choi, MD, Shi-Hun Song, MD, Jin-Young Youm, MD, <lb/>Hyeon-Song Koh, MD, Seon-Hwan Kim, MD, and Hyon-Jo Kwon, MD <lb/>Department of Neurosurgery, School of Medicine, Chungnam National University, Daejeon, Korea <lb/>Objective: Chronic subdural hematoma (CSDH) is relatively common in neurosurgical field. However not all patients de-<lb/>velop CSDH after minor head trauma. In this study, we evaluate the risk factors of post-traumatic CSDH. <lb/>Methods: Two-hundred and seventy-seven patients were enrolled and analyzed in this study from January 2012 to Decem-<lb/>ber 2013. Of those, 20 participants had minor head trauma developed CSDH afterward. We also included 257 patients with <lb/>minor head trauma who did not develop CSDH during the same follow-up period as the control group. We investigated the <lb/>risk factors related to the development of CSDH after minor head trauma. <lb/>Results: Old age (p=0.014), preexisting diabetes mellitus (p=0.010), hypertension (p=0.026), history of cerebral infarction <lb/>(p=0.035), antiplatelet agents (p=0.000), acute subdural hematoma in the convexity (p=0.000), encephalomalacia (p= <lb/>0.029), and long distance between skull and brain parenchyma (p=0.000) were significantly correlated with the develop-<lb/>ment of CSDH after trauma. Multivariate analysis revealed that only the maximum distance between the skull and the cere-<lb/>bral parenchyma was the independent risk factor for the occurrence of CSDH (hazard ratio 2.55, p=0.000). <lb/>Conclusion: We should consider the possibility of developing CSDH in the post-traumatic patients with the identified risk <lb/>factors. <lb/>(Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111) <lb/>KEY WORDS: Hematoma subdural chronic ㆍRisk factors ㆍCraniocerebral trauma. <lb/>Received: September 16, 2014 / Revised: October 13, 2014 <lb/>Accepted: October 15, 2014 <lb/>Address for correspondence: Seung-Won Choi, MD <lb/>Department of Neurosurgery, School of Medicine, Chungnam Na-<lb/>tional University, 282 Munhwa-ro, Jung-gu, Daejeon 301-721, Korea <lb/>Tel: +82-42-280-7361, Fax: +82-42-280-7363 <lb/>E-mail: swchoi@cnu.ac.kr <lb/>CLINICAL ARTICLE <lb/>Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111 <lb/>pISSN 2234-8999 / eISSN 2288-2243 <lb/>http://dx.doi.org/10.13004/kjnt.2014.10.2.106 <lb/>online © ML Comm <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Sang-Beom Han, et al. <lb/> </note>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.kjnt.org</note> 

			<page>107 <lb/></page>

			<body>patient group, while the remaining 257 patients who did not <lb/>develop CSDH after minor head trauma and completed treat-<lb/>ment were selected as the control group. Head trauma, out <lb/>of many other factors, was set as the controlled variable. Age, <lb/>gender, and the history of diabetes mellitus (DM), hyper-<lb/>tension, cerebral infarction, cardiac disease, hematologic dis-<lb/>ease, and epilepsy were investigated as the factors contrib-<lb/>uting to progression of CSDH after minor trauma. The me-<lb/>dication history of antiplatelet and anticoagulant agents was <lb/>also surveyed, as well as the smoking and drinking habits <lb/>of subjects. The presence of acute subdural hematoma (AS-<lb/>DH) in the convexity, accompanying hemorrhage and en-<lb/>cephalomalacia, and the maximum distance from skull to <lb/>cerebral parenchyma (Figure 1) were investigated by exam-<lb/>ining the patients&apos; initial computerized tomography (CT) <lb/>scans. In our study, cardiac disease included valve disease, <lb/>arrhythmia, and ischemic heart disease. The diseases that <lb/>could cause coagulopathy, such as hematological malignan-<lb/>cies, were defined as hematologic disease. In cases where <lb/>the patients&apos; initial brain CT scans showed cerebral contu-<lb/>sion, subarachnoid hemorrhage, epidural hemorrhage, or <lb/>intracerebral hemorrhage, we defined the finding as an ac-<lb/>companying hemorrhage. The statistical analysis was per-<lb/>formed using Window SPSS version 20.0 (SPSS Inc., Chi-<lb/>cago, IL, USA). Statistical analyses included chi-square test, <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test and multivariate logistic regression anal-<lb/>ysis to assess the relationship between CSDH and various <lb/>factors. Differences were considered statistically significant <lb/>if the p value was less than 0.05. <lb/>Results <lb/>Demographic data, medical history, social history, and <lb/>CT findings are summarized in Table 1. <lb/>The number of patients enrolled in the study was 277, with <lb/>an age range of 0 to 94 years, and a mean age of 53.9 years. <lb/>The average age of the patient group was 67.5 years, while <lb/>that of the control group was 52.9 years, showing that the <lb/>patient group was statistically significantly older than the <lb/>control group (p=0.014)(Figure 2). Thirteen male patients <lb/>(65%) and 7 female patients (35%) were in the patient group, <lb/>while 173 male patients (67.3%) and 84 female patients (37.7%) <lb/>made up the control group with males contributing a little <lb/>higher number in both groups, without a noticeable signifi-<lb/>cance in the gender difference (p=0.832). <lb/>TABLE 1. Analysis of factors related to the occurrence of chronic subdural hematoma <lb/>Factors <lb/>Patient group (n=20) <lb/>Control group (n=257) <lb/>p value <lb/>Male/female (% male) <lb/>13/7 (65.0%) <lb/>173/84 (67.3%) <lb/>0.832 <lb/>DM <lb/>7 (35.0%) <lb/>35 (13.6%) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>Hypertension <lb/>12 (60.0%) <lb/>90 (35.0%) <lb/>0.026 <lb/>Hx of CI <lb/>3 (15.0%) <lb/>11 (4.3%) <lb/>0.035 <lb/>Cardiac disease <lb/>4 (20.0%) <lb/>29 (11.3%) <lb/>0.246 <lb/>Hematologic disease <lb/>0 (0%) <lb/>3 (1.2%) <lb/>0.627 <lb/>Epilepsy <lb/>0 (0%) <lb/>4 (1.6%) <lb/>0.547 <lb/>Antiplatelet agent <lb/>10 (50.0%) <lb/>45 (17.5%) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Anticoagulant agent <lb/>1 (5.0%) <lb/>11 (4.3%) <lb/>0.879 <lb/>Smoking <lb/>3 (15.0%) <lb/>71 (27.6%) <lb/>0.219 <lb/>Alcohol <lb/>5 (25.0%) <lb/>114 (44.4%) <lb/>0.092 <lb/>Convexity ASDH <lb/>15 (75.0%) <lb/>73 (28.4%) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Combined hemorrhages <lb/>20 (100.0%) <lb/>236 (91.8%) <lb/>0.184 <lb/>Encephalomalacia <lb/>4 (20.0%) <lb/>17 (6.6%) <lb/>0.029 <lb/>ASDH: acute subdural hematoma, DM: diabetic mellitus, Hx of CI: history of cerebral infarction <lb/>FIGURE 1. Brain computed tomography scans showing how to <lb/>measure the maximal distance between the skull and brain pa-<lb/>renchyma (arrow). <lb/></body>

			<page>108</page> 

			<note place="footnote">Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor Head Trauma <lb/></note>

			<body>In the patient group, there were 7 (35%) patients with DM <lb/>and 12 (65%) patients with hypertension, while there were <lb/>35 (13.6%) patients with DM and 90 (35.0%) patients with <lb/>hypertension in the control group. The presence of DM or <lb/>hypertension showed a statistical significance between <lb/>groups (p=0.010, p=0.026). <lb/>The numbers of the patients with a history of cerebral in-<lb/>farction were 3 (15%) in the patient group and 11 (4.3%) in <lb/>the control group, which was also statistically significant <lb/>(p=0.035). <lb/>With regards to medication history, the administration of <lb/>antiplatelet agents presented a statistically significant dif-<lb/>ference between the two groups (p=0.000); 10 in the patient <lb/>group (50%), 45 in the control group (17.5%). <lb/>The brain CT scans taken on the time of admission were <lb/>examined. A higher percentage of subjects in the patient <lb/>group (15 patients, 75%) had ASDH in the convexity from <lb/>the trauma than that of patients in the control group (78 pa-<lb/>tients, 28.4%) at a level of statistical significance (p=0.000). <lb/>Four subjects in the patient group (20%) had encephalo-<lb/>malacia, while 17 patients (6.6%) in the control group had <lb/>the affliction with statistically significant (p=0.029). <lb/>The brain CT scans taken right after the trauma were used <lb/>to measure the maximum distance between the skull and <lb/>the cerebral parenchyma. The average maximum distance <lb/>of the patient group (7.15 mm) was much longer than that of <lb/>the control group (1.35 mm) and the difference was statisti-<lb/>cally significant (p=0.000)(Figure 3). The receiver operat-<lb/>ing characteristic curve was drawn by plotting the occur-<lb/>rence of CSDH according to the maximum distance between <lb/>the skull and the brain parenchyma. It was determined to <lb/>be reliable test model due to its large area under the curve. <lb/>We found that the distance between the skull and parenchy-<lb/>ma as 3.52 mm can be a cutoff value, yielding 90.0% sensi-<lb/>tivity and 90.7% specificity (Figure 4). <lb/>The multivariate logistic regression analysis was used to <lb/>verify the correlation between the statistically significant <lb/>factors and CSDH occurrence. As a result, only the maxi-<lb/>mum distance between the skull and the cerebral parenchy-<lb/>ma showed a reliable correlation with CSDH occurrence (p= <lb/>0.000), while the other factors failed to show any remarkable <lb/>statistical significance (Table 2). <lb/>Each group was classified according to the type of trau-<lb/>ma. Slipping down stood out as the most common cause of <lb/>trauma but with no statistical significance between the two <lb/>groups (p=0.236)(Table 3). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Unlike other studies, 7,10) this study demonstrates that the <lb/>presence of DM or hypertension significantly influences <lb/>the occurrence of CSDH after minor head trauma. On the <lb/>90 <lb/>80 <lb/>70 <lb/>60 <lb/>50 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>Age <lb/>p=0.014 <lb/>Patient group <lb/>Control group <lb/>FIGURE 2. Bar graph showing the average age between two <lb/>groups. Average age of the patient group is significantly older <lb/>than that of the control group (p=0.014). <lb/>Patient group <lb/>Control group <lb/>12 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>mm <lb/>p=0.000 <lb/>FIGURE 3. Bar graph shows the average maximal distance be-<lb/>tween skull and brain parenchyma of the two groups. The patient <lb/>group had a statistically significant longer distance than control <lb/>group (p=0.000). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Sang-Beom Han, et al. <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">http://www.kjnt.org </note>

			<page>109 <lb/></page>

			<body>contrary, a study conducted by Yamamoto et al. 22) reported <lb/>that the hyperglycemia in DM patients leads to the hyper-<lb/>viscosity of blood and increases the intravascular osmotic <lb/>pressure, resulting in a reduced probability of CSDH recur. <lb/>However, considering the fact that one of the major compli-<lb/>cations of DM is capillary vasculopathy such as retinal hem-<lb/>orrhage, and the fact that micro-bleedings and the exuda-<lb/>tion of immature capillaries surrounding the CSDH outer <lb/>membrane are the major mechanisms in developing CSDH, <lb/>the capillary vasculopathy in DM patients affects the im-<lb/>mature capillaries around the outer membrane of the sub-<lb/>dural hematoma after head trauma, and consequently re-<lb/>sults in the development CSDH. 20) <lb/>Also, in the case of patients with hypertension, higher <lb/>blood pressures put more pressure on the immature capil-<lb/>laries around the outer membrane have to endure, increas-<lb/>ing the probability of repeated capillary injuries and micro-<lb/>bleedings. Even though there are few preexisting studies on <lb/>the impact of hypertension on the CSDH, 8) additional stud-<lb/>ies need to be performed to confirm a correlation between <lb/>hypertension and CSDH. <lb/>It is known that the old age is associated with CSDH, as <lb/>there is a higher CSDH prevalence rate among the elder-<lb/>ly. 1,5,6) The fragility of the bridging veins and accompany-<lb/>ing cerebral atrophy from the aging process are considered <lb/>as the major factors causing the increased prevalence. 5,19) As <lb/>aging progresses, the volume of the cerebral parenchyma <lb/>shrinks, resulting in an increase of the subdural space be-<lb/>tween the skull and the cerebral parenchyma. The enlarged <lb/>subdural space enables the brain to move around the skull <lb/>while patient ambulates, and the vulnerable bridging veins <lb/>can be injured easily with a minor head trauma. 9,12,23) The <lb/>correlation between the occurrence of CSDH and old age <lb/>was also confirmed in this study, and there was a tendency <lb/>to develop post-traumatic CSDH among the patients with <lb/>larger subdural spaces due to cerebral atrophy. The reason <lb/>why the history of cerebral infarction and the presence of <lb/>encephalomalacia are correlated with CSDH occurrence in <lb/>this study can be explained by considering the same mech-<lb/>anism described above. The presence of encephalomalacia <lb/>after the brain injury, such as cerebral infarction, results in <lb/>the reduction of brain parenchyma volume, which enlarges <lb/>the subdural space between the skull and brain parenchy-<lb/>ma, and consequently results in higher tendency of post-trau-<lb/>matic CSDH. 16) <lb/>A study from Lindvall and Koskinen, 10) which analyzed <lb/>71 patients with CSDH concluded that the administration <lb/>of antiplatelet or anticoagulation agents contributed a sig-<lb/>nificant difference in CSDH occurrence in the patients with-<lb/>out trauma compared to the patients with trauma. Another <lb/>1.000 <lb/>0.800 <lb/>0.600 <lb/>0.400 <lb/>0.200 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Sensitivity <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.200 <lb/>0.400 <lb/>0.600 <lb/>0.800 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1-specificity <lb/>FIGURE 4. Receiver operating characteristic (ROC) curve of the <lb/>maximal distance between the skull and brain parenchyme. In a <lb/>ROC curve, the true positive rate (sensitivity) is plotted against the <lb/>false positive rate (1-specificity) for different cut-off points of a pa-<lb/>rameter. In this graph, 3.52 mm is the cutoff value of 90.0% sen-<lb/>sitivity and 90.7% specificity. The area under the ROC curve is a <lb/>measurement of how well a parameter can distinguish between <lb/>two groups. Here, the maximal depth between the skull and brain <lb/>parenchyma is a good parameter for distinguishing between the <lb/>two groups. <lb/>TABLE 2. Multivariate logistic regression analysis of factors af-<lb/>fecting the occurrence of chronic subdural hematoma <lb/>Factors <lb/>Odds ratio <lb/>p value <lb/>Age <lb/>0.815 <lb/>0.807 <lb/>DM <lb/>0.348 <lb/>0.244 <lb/>Hx of CI <lb/>0.265 <lb/>0.625 <lb/>Antiplatelet agent <lb/>1.719 <lb/>0.559 <lb/>Convexity ASDH <lb/>0.630 <lb/>0.544 <lb/>Encephalomalacia <lb/>1.608 <lb/>0.855 <lb/>Maximum distance <lb/>2.550 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>ASDH: acute subdural hematoma, DM: diabetic mellitus, Hx <lb/>of CI: history of cerebral infarction, Maximum distance: maxi-<lb/>mum distance between the skull and brain parenchyma <lb/>TABLE 3. Classification of trauma <lb/>Trauma <lb/>Patient <lb/>group (n=20) <lb/>Control <lb/>group (n=257) <lb/>Slip down <lb/>11 (55%) <lb/>106 (41.2%) <lb/>Fall down <lb/>3 (15%) <lb/>45 (17.5%) <lb/>Driver accident <lb/>4 (20%) <lb/>19 (7.4%) <lb/>Pedestrian accident <lb/>1 (5%) <lb/>43 (16.7%) <lb/>Hit by material <lb/>0 (0%) <lb/>18 (7%) <lb/>Violence <lb/>0 (0%) <lb/>3 (1.2%) <lb/>Unknown <lb/>1 (5%) <lb/>23 (8.9%) <lb/>No statistical significance between group (p value=0.236) <lb/></body>

			<page>110</page> 

			<note place="footnote">Korean J Neurotrauma 2014;10(2):106-111 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Prediction of Chronic Subdural Hematoma in Minor Head Trauma <lb/></note>

			<body>study conducted by Reymond et al. 17) analyzing 198 patients <lb/>with severe head trauma also reported that there was a sta-<lb/>tistical significance between the administration of anti-<lb/>platelet or anticoagulation agents in CSDH occurrence. <lb/>Considering the analogous result in the preceding two stud-<lb/>ies, the same outcome was expected when analyzing our <lb/>data. However, there was no statistically significant differ-<lb/>ence between using anticoagulation agents and the occur-<lb/>rence of CSDH, while there was a significant correlation be-<lb/>tween the use of antiplatelet agents and the occurrence of <lb/>CSDH. While the preceding studies analyzed patients who <lb/>already developed CSDH or had severe head trauma, we in-<lb/>cluded all the patients with minor head trauma, which may <lb/>explain the difference in the outcome. Also, the fact that the <lb/>patient group only had a limited number of the patients may <lb/>be related to the difference as well. <lb/>It was expected that there would be a correlation between <lb/>CSDH occurrence and the patients with cerebral infarction <lb/>or with cardiac disease, as they are commonly administered <lb/>antiplatelet or anticoagulant agents. 10) The actual study <lb/>showed a higher ratio of patients with cerebral infarction <lb/>or cardiac disease in the patient group than in the control <lb/>group. However, only the history of cerebral infarction dem-<lb/>onstrated a statistically significant difference, while the <lb/>presence of cardiac disease failed to show a statistical sig-<lb/>nificance. With regard to cerebral infarction, aside from us-<lb/>ing antiplatelet agents or anticoagulants, other co-factors, <lb/>such as a decrease in brain volume due to encephalomala-<lb/>cia after infarction, could influence the outcome. Also, the <lb/>insufficient number of the patients analyzed in the patient <lb/>group is likely the reason why we could not find a signifi-<lb/>cance relationship between CSDH occurrence and the pres-<lb/>ence of cardiac disease. <lb/>Generally, the hematologic diseases that cause coagulop-<lb/>athy are known to be risk factors for post-traumatic CSDH <lb/>occurrence. 1,4) The history of epilepsy is also expected to be <lb/>a risk factor of CSDH since it can cause repeated seizures. 1,11) <lb/>We began our analysis considering these known concepts, <lb/>but the history of hematologic diseases and epilepsy showed <lb/>no significant differences in our study. Yet, there was no pa-<lb/>tient with a history of hematologic diseases or epilepsy in <lb/>the patient group, and a very small number of the patients <lb/>with a history of hematologic diseases (1.1%) or epilepsy <lb/>(1.4%) were present among the entire test population. It is <lb/>assumed that the limited number of patients analyzed in the <lb/>study impacted the result as well. <lb/>Limitations of the current study include the small num-<lb/>ber of patient group and the retrospective nature of the study <lb/>design. However this study creatively demonstrated the pre-<lb/>dictive factors of CSDH in patients with minor head trauma. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Based on the results of this study, the predictive factors <lb/>of post-traumatic CSDH occurrence are old age, preexisting <lb/>DM, hypertension, and history of cerebral infarction, the <lb/>presence of ASDH in the convexity found in brain CT scans <lb/>taken right after the trauma, encephalomalacia, and an en-<lb/>larged subdural space between skull and brain parenchyma. <lb/>When treating patients with minor head trauma accompa-<lb/>nied by those risk factors, physicians must pay careful at-<lb/>tention to the possibility of post-traumatic CSDH and need <lb/>to continuously observe the patients. <lb/>■ The authors have no financial conflicts of interest. <lb/></body>


			<back>

				<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1) Adhiyaman V, Asghar M, Ganeshram KN, Bhowmick BK. Chron-<lb/>ic subdural haematoma in the elderly. Postgrad Med J 78:71-75, <lb/>2002 <lb/>2) Asghar M, Adhiyaman V, Greenway MW, Bhowmick BK, Bates <lb/>A. Chronic subdural haematoma in the elderly--a North Wales ex-<lb/>perience. J R Soc Med 95:290-292, 2002 <lb/>3) Berghauser Pont LM, Dammers R, Schouten JW, Lingsma HF, <lb/>Dirven CM. Clinical factors associated with outcome in chronic <lb/>subdural hematoma: a retrospective cohort study of patients on <lb/>preoperative corticosteroid therapy. Neurosurgery 70:873-880; <lb/>discussion 880, 2012 <lb/>4) Chon KH, Lee JM, Koh EJ, Choi HY. Independent predictors for <lb/>recurrence of chronic subdural hematoma. Acta Neurochir (Wien) <lb/>154:1541-1548, 2012 <lb/>5) Jolobe OM. Chronic subdural haematoma in the elderly. J R Soc <lb/>Med 95:427-428, 2002 <lb/>6) Jones S, Kafetz K. A prospective study of chronic subdural hae-<lb/>matomas in elderly patients. Age Ageing 28:519-521, 1999 <lb/>7) Ko BS, Lee JK, Seo BR, Moon SJ, Kim JH, Kim SH. Clinical anal-<lb/>ysis of risk factors related to recurrent chronic subdural hemato-<lb/>ma. J Korean Neurosurg Soc 43:11-15, 2008 <lb/>8) Laviv Y, Rappaport ZH. Risk factors for development of signifi-<lb/>cant chronic subdural hematoma following conservative treatment <lb/>of acute subdural hemorrhage. Br J Neurosurg:1-6, 2014 <lb/>9) Lee KS, Bae WK, Doh JW, Bae HG, Yun IG. Origin of chronic sub-<lb/>dural haematoma and relation to traumatic subdural lesions. Brain <lb/>Inj 12:901-910, 1998 <lb/>10) Lindvall P, Koskinen LO. Anticoagulants and antiplatelet agents <lb/>and the risk of development and recurrence of chronic subdural <lb/>haematomas. J Clin Neurosci 16:1287-1290, 2009 <lb/>11) Luxon LM, Harrison MJ. Chronic subdural haematoma. Q J Med <lb/>48:43-53, 1979 <lb/>12) Markwalder TM. Chronic subdural hematomas: a review. J Neu-<lb/>rosurg 54:637-645, 1981 <lb/>13) Mori K, Adachi K, Cho K, Ishimaru S, Maeda M. Quantitative ki-<lb/>netic analysis of blood vessels in the outer membranes of chronic <lb/>subdural hematomas. Neurol Med Chir (Tokyo) 38:697-702; dis-<lb/>cussion 702-703, 1998 <lb/>14) Mori K, Mitsuoka H, Cho K, Tajima A, Maeda M. Rate constant of <lb/>gadolinium (Gd)-DTPA transfer into chronic subdural hematomas. <lb/>Neurol Res 18:126-134, 1996 <lb/></listBibl>

				<note place="headnote">Sang-Beom Han, et al. <lb/></note>

				<note place="footnote">http://www.kjnt.org </note>

				<page>111 <lb/></page>

				<listBibl>15) Ohno K, Suzuki R, Masaoka H, Matsushima Y, Inaba Y, Monma <lb/>S. Chronic subdural haematoma preceded by persistent traumatic <lb/>subdural fluid collection. J Neurol Neurosurg Psychiatry 50:1694-<lb/>1697, 1987 <lb/>16) Okano A, Oya S, Fujisawa N, Tsuchiya T, Indo M, Nakamura T, et <lb/>al. Analysis of risk factors for chronic subdural haematoma recur-<lb/>rence after burr hole surgery: optimal management of patients on <lb/>antiplatelet therapy. Br J Neurosurg 28:204-208, 2014 <lb/>17) Reymond MA, Marbet G, Radü EW, Gratzl O. Aspirin as a risk <lb/>factor for hemorrhage in patients with head injuries. Neurosurg <lb/>Rev 15:21-25, 1992 <lb/>18) Sato S, Suzuki J. Ultrastructural observations of the capsule of <lb/>chronic subdural hematoma in various clinical stages. J Neuro-<lb/>surg 43:569-578, 1975 <lb/>19) Teale EA, Iliffe S, Young JB. Subdural haematoma in the elderly. <lb/>BMJ 348:g1682, 2014 <lb/>20) Torihashi K, Sadamasa N, Yoshida K, Narumi O, Chin M, Yamaga-<lb/>ta S. Independent predictors for recurrence of chronic subdural <lb/>hematoma: a review of 343 consecutive surgical cases. Neurosur-<lb/>gery 63:1125-1129; discussion 1129, 2008 <lb/>21) Yamada H, Nihei H, Watanabe T, Shibui S, Murata S. [Chronic <lb/>subdural hematoma occurring consequently to the posttraumatic <lb/>subdural hygroma--on the pathogenesis of the chronic subdural he-<lb/>matoma (author&apos;s transl)]. No To Shinkei 31:115-121, 1979 <lb/>22) Yamamoto H, Hirashima Y, Hamada H, Hayashi N, Origasa H, Endo <lb/>S. Independent predictors of recurrence of chronic subdural hema-<lb/>toma: results of multivariate analysis performed using a logistic <lb/>regression model. J Neurosurg 98:1217-1221, 2003 <lb/>23) Yoon JW, Park IS, Park H, Kang DH, Park KB, Lee CH, et al. A <lb/>study of the progression from acute subdural hematoma to chron-<lb/>ic stage requiring surgical treatment. Korean J Neurotrauma 9: <lb/>74-80, 2013 </listBibl>

			</back>

	</text>
</tei>
