<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Online Discussion on #KidneyStones: A <lb/>Longitudinal Assessment of Activity, Users <lb/>and Content <lb/>Johannes Salem 1☯ *, Hendrik Borgmann 2☯ , Matthew Bultitude 3 , Hans-Martin Fritsche 4 , <lb/>Axel Haferkamp 2 , Axel Heidenreich 1 , Arkadiusz Miernik 5 , Andreas Neisius 2 , <lb/>Thomas Knoll 6 , Christian Thomas 2 , Igor Tsaur 2 <lb/>1 Department of Urology, University Hospital, Cologne, Germany, 2 Department of Urology, University of <lb/>Medicine, Mainz, Germany, 3 Stone Unit, Guy&apos;s and St. Thomas&apos; NHS Foundation Trust, London, United <lb/>Kingdom, 4 Department of Urology, Caritas St Josef Hospital, University of Regensburg, Regensburg, <lb/>Germany, 5 Department of Urology, University Medical Center, Freiburg, Germany, 6 Department of <lb/>Urology, Klinikum Sindelfingen-Böblingen, Sindelfingen, Germany <lb/>☯ These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>* j.salem@gesru.de <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Twitter is a popular microblogging platform for the rapid dissemination of information and <lb/>reciprocal exchange in the urological field. We aimed to assess the activity, users and con-<lb/>tent of the online discussion, #KidneyStones, on Twitter. <lb/>Methods <lb/>We investigated the Symplur Signals analytics tool for Twitter data distributed via the #Kid-<lb/>neyStones hashtag over a one year period. Activity analysis reflected overall activity and <lb/>tweet enhancements. We assessed users&apos; geolocations and performed an influencer analy-<lb/>sis. Content analysis included the most frequently used words, tweet sentiment and shares <lb/>for top tweets. <lb/>Results <lb/>3,426 users generated over 10,333 tweets, which were frequently accompanied by links <lb/>(49%), mentions (30%) and photos (13%). Users came from 106 countries across the globe <lb/>and were most frequently from North America (63%) and Europe (16%). Individual and <lb/>organisational healthcare professionals made up 56% of the influencers of the Twitter dis-<lb/>cussion on #KidneyStones. Besides the words &apos;kidney&apos; (used 4,045 times) and &apos;stones&apos; <lb/>(3,335), &apos;pain&apos; (1,233), &apos;urine&apos; (1,158), and &apos;risk&apos; (1,023) were the most frequently used <lb/>words. 56% of tweets had a positive sentiment. The median (range) number of shares was <lb/>85 (62-587) for the top 10 links, 45.5 (17-94) for the top 10 photos, and 44 (22-95) for the <lb/>top 10 retweets. <lb/></front>

			<front>PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/> 1 / 11 <lb/>a11111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Salem J, Borgmann H, Bultitude M, Fritsche <lb/>H-M, Haferkamp A, Heidenreich A, et al. (2016) <lb/>Online Discussion on #KidneyStones: A Longitudinal <lb/>Assessment of Activity, Users and Content. PLoS <lb/>ONE 11(8): e0160863. doi:10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0160863 <lb/>Editor: Jeff M Sands, Emory University Department <lb/>of Medicine, UNITED STATES <lb/>Received: April 10, 2016 <lb/>Accepted: July 26, 2016 <lb/>Published: August 18, 2016 <lb/>Copyright: © 2016 Salem et al. This is an open <lb/>access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits <lb/>unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any <lb/>medium, provided the original author and source are <lb/>credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: The information <lb/>underlying this study is available from the Symplur <lb/>Signals database, and can be accessed under www. <lb/>symplur.com/signals with a fee-based account <lb/>subscribed for the hashtag #KidneyStones. The time <lb/>period was set from 1st October 2014 to 1st October <lb/>2015. We paid US$1,099 for a one month explorative <lb/>analysis. <lb/>Funding: The authors have no support or funding to <lb/>report. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The rapidly growing Twitter discussion on #KidneyStones engaged multiple stakeholders in <lb/>the healthcare sector on a global scale and reached both professionals and laypeople. <lb/>When used effectively and responsibly, the Twitter platform could improve prevention and <lb/>medical care of kidney stone patients. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The microblogging social media platform, Twitter, enjoys increasing popularity in the health-<lb/>care sector. Currently, over 70% of urologists in Australia and New Zealand have a social <lb/>media presence, with Twitter being the second most commonly used form after LinkedIn, <lb/>which serves a completely different purpose [1]. Urologists using Twitter during the European <lb/>Association of Urology (EAU) and the American Urological Association (AUA) congresses <lb/>regarded it as beneficial for professional networking, disseminating information, research, <lb/>advocacy, and career development [2]. Impressively, 1,860 users generated 15,419 tweets in <lb/>total at the EAU14 and AUA14 congresses [3]. Notably, the Twitter-based International Urol-<lb/>ogy Journal Club, #urojc, has established a high-level academic discussion of urologic manu-<lb/>scripts [4]. In attempt to standardise the online discussion about urological care, a particular <lb/>structuring of the key urology-related hashtags has recently been proposed [5]. Interestingly, <lb/>the high technology field of endourology was the first urologic subspeciality assessed for Twit-<lb/>ter activity during the 2013 World Congress of Endourology [6]. Most recently, a Twitter dis-<lb/>cussion during the Third Meeting of the European Association of Urology Section of <lb/>Urolithiasis 2015 comprised 94 users contributing 446 tweets [7]. <lb/>In slightly more than a decade, the prevalence of urolithiasis in the United States has <lb/>increased from 5.2% to 8.8% [8], having a substantial socioeconomic impact [9] and incre-<lb/>mentally affecting younger patients [10]. Since evidence has been provided for both highly <lb/>prevalent urologic conditions and also diseases with young patient age at onset evoking more <lb/>Twitter activity than their counterparts [11], a vibrant Twitter discussion on stone disease is <lb/>likely. Interestingly, in conditions with broad-based Twitter communities, such as breast can-<lb/>cer, patients have reported an increase in disease knowledge from participating in Twitter dis-<lb/>cussions [12]. <lb/>In the current investigation, we aimed to assess the potential of Twitter to constitute a <lb/>potential platform for the dissemination of contemporary evidence on prevention, diagnosis <lb/>and treatment of stone disease. Hypothesising that a Twitter discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/>might appreciably involve both healthcare givers and laypeople, as well as encourage consider-<lb/>able global public awareness, we investigated the characteristics of its activity, users and <lb/>content. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>The study was approved by the Ethics Commission of the Faculty of Medicine of the University <lb/>of Cologne. We performed an extensive analysis of activity, users and content of the online dis-<lb/>cussion on #KidneyStones on Twitter, using the Symplur Signals database. Symplur (www. <lb/>symplur.com) is a Twitter analysis website that maintains a database of healthcare-related <lb/>Twitter conversations. Symplur Signals (www.symplur.com/signals) is a fee-based research <lb/>analytics tool that promotes the understanding of healthcare as seen by patients, doctors and <lb/>other stakeholders with access to healthcare social media data points. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>/ 11 <lb/></page>
			
			<front>Competing Interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>In October 2015, we searched the Symplur Signals database for analytic insights into the <lb/>online discussion on #KidneyStones for the time period 1st October 2014 to 1st October 2015. <lb/>The activity analysis comprised the assessment of overall tweet activity, tweet metrics, engage-<lb/>ment metrics and tweet language metrics. Overall tweet activity was recorded as the number of <lb/>tweets and users, and these were related to time periods. We performed a detailed analysis of <lb/>the tweet transcript (exact list of all tweets) to assess the issues inducing peak activities. The <lb/>tweet metrics analysis was performed by retrieving statistics about ratio and frequency of <lb/>retweets, tweets with links, tweets with photos, tweet replies and tweets where one or more <lb/>Twitter users were mentioned. Engagement metrics were retrieved by obtaining the number of <lb/>users who tweeted over a set period of time, grouped by the number of tweets sent. A tweet lan-<lb/>guage analysis illustrated the language used by active participants over a set period of time. <lb/>Language type was identified by a natural language processing algorithm directly provided by <lb/>the Twitter application programming interface. <lb/>User analysis included the cumulative user report, users&apos; geolocations, and an influencer <lb/>analysis of the top influencers in the #KidneyStones discussion. Cumulative and new users <lb/>were recorded for monthly intervals. Cumulative users did not represent recurring users, but <lb/>were counted as a new user the first time they used the #KidneyStones hashtag and as a previ-<lb/>ous user in subsequent reporting periods, regardless of activity. The geolocation of users was <lb/>recorded when users sent tweets tagged with certain geolocation data. We analysed the top 100 <lb/>contributors to the #KidneyStones discussion, as measured by number of tweets in the influen-<lb/>cer analysis. For this purpose, we performed a Twitter profile analysis and assigned these top <lb/>influencers to these healthcare categories, in line with the Symplur Signals healthcare category <lb/>definitions: physician; patient; healthcare professional; caregiver/advocate; researcher/aca-<lb/>demic; individual other healthcare; individual other non-healthcare; organisation provider; <lb/>organisation research/academic; organisation government; organisation advocate/support; <lb/>organisation pharma; organisation other healthcare; organisation other non-healthcare, and <lb/>spam [13]. <lb/>We used the Symplur Signals tools for content analysis. The 100 most frequently used <lb/>words in tweets on #KidneyStones were analysed and counted. Since multiple hashtags are <lb/>often used within a single tweet, we used the hashtag network graph to analyse hashtags accom-<lb/>panying the #KidneyStones discussion and their relationships. The sentiment report analysed <lb/>tweets for positive and negative sentiment by a natural language processing algorithm. The <lb/>algorithm is based on two custom dictionaries, one for positive words and one for negative <lb/>words. Each word in the dictionaries has a weighting from one to five, with five being the high-<lb/>est. Finally, we investigated the most frequently shared links, photos and the most frequently <lb/>retweeted tweets. We performed statistical calculations using the Statistical Package for the <lb/>Social Sciences 22.0 software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA). Values are described as median <lb/>and range. <lb/>Results <lb/>Table 1 shows overall activity for the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter for the time <lb/>period of one year. 3,426 users produced 10,806 tweets. Fig 1 portrays the weekly number of <lb/>tweets on #KidneyStones, which slightly increased over the investigated time period. The peak <lb/>tweet activity occurred during a strategic massive tweet activity of key influencers, evoking a <lb/>large amount of retweets (influencers: @virtualclinicng, 9th March 2015 and 11th March 2015, <lb/>41 tweets on kidney stones prevention leading to a peak of over 500 tweets in a week; @mayo-<lb/>clinic, 11th July 2015, 41 tweets on kidney stones prevention during a radio show leading to a <lb/>peak of over 400 tweets in a week). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>/ 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Out of 10,333 total tweets, 5,013 (49%) were accompanied by links, 3,101 (30%) by men-<lb/>tions and 1,337 (13%) by photos. 2,441 (24%) were retweets and 229 (2%) were tweet replies. <lb/>2,798 users (82%) generated one tweet, 331 (10%) two, 244 (7%) three to nine, and 53 (2%) 10 <lb/>or more tweets. 9,942 (96%) of tweets were in the English language. <lb/>Fig 2 demonstrates that the monthly number of users contributing to the #KidneyStones <lb/>online discussion on Twitter from October 2014 grew steadily, with a median of 262 (range <lb/>189-454) new users per month. The median number of active users contributing to the #Kid-<lb/>neyStones online discussion was 304.5 per month (range 227-545). Users came from 106 coun-<lb/>tries and from all continents around the globe (Fig 3). The S1 Table lists the location of users <lb/>according to country and continent. North American users were most active (63%), ahead of <lb/>Table 1. Overview of tweet activity for the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter over a time period of one year. <lb/>Metric <lb/>Total <lb/>Per Month <lb/>Per Week <lb/>Per Day <lb/>Per Hour <lb/>Tweets <lb/>10,333 <lb/>849 <lb/>198 <lb/>28.3 <lb/>1.18 <lb/>Tweets per user <lb/>3.02 <lb/>0.248 <lb/>0.0578 <lb/>0.00826 <lb/>0.000344 <lb/>Users who tweeted <lb/>3,426 <lb/>282 <lb/>65.7 <lb/>9.39 <lb/>0.391 <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.t001 <lb/>Fig 1. Tweet activity for the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter during the one year period. The weekly numbers of <lb/>tweets are represented as columns. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>European users (16%) and Asian users (10%). The top 100 influencers in the #KidneyStones <lb/>online discussion on Twitter, according to the number of tweets posted in the study period, <lb/>and stratified by healthcare category, are shown in Fig 4. Individuals not involved in healthcare <lb/>(38%) and healthcare organisations (37%; organisations: provider, advocate/support, govern-<lb/>ment, other) were the main influencers in the discussion. There were no spam accounts among <lb/>the top 100 influencers. <lb/>A content analysis of the most frequently used words in the #KidneyStones online discus-<lb/>sion on Twitter is shown in Fig 5. Besides &apos;kidney&apos; (used 4,045 times) and &apos;stones&apos; (3,335), <lb/>Fig 2. Growth in number of users contributing to the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.g002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>&apos;pain&apos; (1,233), &apos;urine&apos; (1,158), and &apos;risk&apos; (1,023) were the top words. The S2 Table presents the <lb/>complete content analysis with the 100 most frequently used words in #KidneyStones tweets. <lb/>The largest thematic proportion of tweets focused on disease awareness and prevention (35 of <lb/>words). The sentiment analysis revealed that 56% of the tweets had a positive sentiment <lb/>and 44% had a negative sentiment. The median (range) number of shares for the top 10 links <lb/>was 85 (62-587) and 45.5 (17-94) for the top 10 photos. The top 10 retweets had a median of <lb/>44 (22-95) retweets. The #KidneyStones hashtag was often related to the #health, #renalcolic, <lb/>#renalcalculus and #kidney hashtags. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We performed a longitudinal assessment of activity, users and content of the online discussion <lb/>on #KidneyStones, using the Symplur Signals health analytics database. Over the one year <lb/>period, Twitter activity was reflected by 10,806 tweets, which were frequently enhanced with <lb/>links and mentions, and were posted predominantly in English. Together, 3,426 users from 106 <lb/>countries contributed to the online discussion, with non-professional individuals and health-<lb/>care organisations being the main influencers. Content was dominated by the words &apos;kidney&apos;, <lb/>&apos;stones&apos;, &apos;pain&apos;, &apos;urine&apos; and &apos;risk&apos;, and tweets had more positive than negative sentiments. The <lb/>top links, photos and retweets were shared up to 100 times. <lb/>The Twitter activity of 10,806 tweets found for #KidneyStones in the study period is much <lb/>higher than 880 tweets found in 2012 for urinary tract infection, another urological disease <lb/>[14]. The majority of Twitter activity data in the literature are published on urological oncology <lb/>diseases, such as #testicularcancer (10,376 tweets in 2014) or #prostatecancer (79,242 tweets in <lb/>2014) [15]. Comparisons of tweet activity between #KidneyStones as a benign disease and <lb/>malignant diseases are compromised since the potentially life-threatening character of onco-<lb/>logical topics has been shown to provoke an over-representation on Twitter [14]. <lb/>The tweet metric analysis showed that contributors interacted using retweets (24%) and <lb/>mentions (30%) in their tweets. Relevant tweets inducing retweets are of high interest to the <lb/>Fig 3. Geolocation of users contributing to the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter. The colour tone reflects the number of users <lb/>per country: the colour shifts from light tones (countries with few or no users) to dark tones (countries with many users). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>/ 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Twitter community, which is underlined by the recently introduced concept of the Twitter <lb/>impact factor [16]. Moreover, almost half of the tweets were enhanced by a link. This is encour-<lb/>aging since the combination &apos;statement + proof&apos; is a basic principle in science which can be <lb/>translated to Twitter as the combination &apos;statement + link&apos;. A tweet analysis on the topic of <lb/>dementia showed that the top users applied links more frequently than average users [17]. Sim-<lb/>ilarly, successful tweets from public state health departments contained links in the majority of <lb/>tweets [18]. Thus, a high number of links used in tweets for #KidneyStones appears to enhance <lb/>the reach of tweets and enables followers to check the trustworthiness of the short information <lb/>presented in one tweet. Additionally, links enable more information to be conveyed in the <lb/>tweet than the 140 characters would otherwise allow. <lb/>The Twitter discussion on #KidneyStones is global, involving users from all continents. <lb/>Usage rates of social media were 74% among American urologists in 2013 [19] and 70% among <lb/>Australian urologists in 2014 [1]. As social media adoption rates continue to grow, so did the <lb/>number of cumulative contributors to the #KidneyStones discussion. This is in line with our <lb/>previous study on urologic oncology, with steadily increasing tweet activity over time [15]. <lb/>Twitter allows for rapid, informal, and thus low-threshold, participation in an online discus-<lb/>sion. These characteristics make it appealing for laypeople to join in the conversation. Notably, <lb/>Fig 4. Top 100 influencers in the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter according to tweet volume stratified by healthcare category. <lb/>Healthcare organisation consists of 8% provider, 1% government, 15% advocate/support and 13% other healthcare organisations (from darker blue to lighter <lb/>blue). Healthcare individual consists of 13% doctors, 2% healthcare practitioners and 4% other healthcare individuals (from darker turquoise to lighter <lb/>turquoise). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.g004 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>individuals such as patients, relatives and interested people who are not primarily involved in <lb/>healthcare accounted for a large number of the top influencers in the #KidneyStones discus-<lb/>sion. Similarly, individual and organisational healthcare professionals contributed as top influ-<lb/>encers, which demonstrates the potential of Twitter for disseminating valuable knowledge <lb/>from professionals on preventive, diagnostic and therapeutic options to the populace. <lb/>Particularly noteworthy is the finding of the content analysis, revealing that words symbolis-<lb/>ing disease awareness and prevention are most frequently used in tweets on #KidneyStones. <lb/>Primary prevention of kidney stones has been shown to be cost-effective for a national health-<lb/>care system [20]. This is crucial, particularly considering the rapidly increasing costs of urolith-<lb/>iasis treatment, predicted to be more than US$1 billion annually in the United States by 2030 <lb/>Fig 5. Bubble chart visualising the 100 most frequently used words in tweets in the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter. The larger the <lb/>bubble, the more a word is used. Colours only aid differentiation and have no other significance. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>
			
			<page>/ 11 <lb/></page>

			<body>[9]. Importantly, urolithiasis is associated with a 30-50% risk of recurrence within seven years <lb/>of initial treatment [21, 22]. Secondary nonmedical prevention with fluid intake, specific die-<lb/>tary therapy, adoption of a &apos;healthy&apos; lifestyle [23-25] as well as preventive pharmacological <lb/>treatment [26-28] were reported to effectively reduce recurrence rates. Unfortunately, due to <lb/>patient and provider scepticism about the evidence of secondary prevention effectiveness, it is <lb/>infrequently utilised in daily routines [29, 30]. An additional hurdle to the implementation of <lb/>preventive measures is low patient compliance; roughly half of stone formers were reported to <lb/>adhere to a prescribed preventive therapy in a contemporary series [30]. Considering the <lb/>under-utilised potential of primary and secondary prevention of urolithiasis, the Twitter plat-<lb/>form might make a beneficial contribution in these areas. The #KidneyStones Twitter discus-<lb/>sion can deliver currently valid guidelines and recommendations on urolithiasis prevention to <lb/>laypeople and thus lead to both a decrease of recurrence rates and increased cost-savings. In <lb/>this context, using links and photos to enhance a tweet&apos;s content and its reach can therefore be <lb/>a successful strategy. The most shared link in our analysis was distributed 587 times and the <lb/>most shared photos and retweets were spread up to nearly 100 times. <lb/>Although the #KidneyStones hashtag is proposed as standardised communication descrip-<lb/>tor [5], we acknowledge that this single hashtag cannot capture all the information that is <lb/>exchanged on urolithiasis on the Twitter platform. Particularly during congresses with high <lb/>tweet activity using multiple hashtags, discussions on stone disease might take place beside the <lb/>#KidneyStones channel. <lb/>We also used the Symplur Signals analytics platform for a systematic assessment of health-<lb/>care social media data. The automated data extraction and analysis algorithms allow for the <lb/>analysis of a vast amount of data, but cannot detect linguistic nuances, such as ambiguity or <lb/>irony when analysing content. Lastly, Twitter is a rapidly growing and changing social media <lb/>platform, implying that the results of our contemporary analysis might be out-dated in the <lb/>near future. <lb/>Notwithstanding the aforementioned limitations, several practice-oriented conclusions can <lb/>be drawn from the findings of the current study. The Twitter discussion on #KidneyStones is <lb/>maintained by users from all over the world and evokes a remarkable number of tweets, under-<lb/>scoring the global reach of this microblogging platform. Healthcare organisations, as one of the <lb/>top influencers in the discussion, have a unique opportunity to raise the awareness of patients <lb/>and providers for nonmedical and pharmacological prevention, eventually reducing recurrence <lb/>rates and care-related expenditure. Patients and other laypeople substantially contributing to <lb/>the discussion have the option of being discreetly and noncommittally counselled by experts, <lb/>optimising shared decision-making. Finally, given responsible Twitter usage, the dissemination <lb/>of novel diagnostic and therapeutic developments in the area of urolithiasis between stakehold-<lb/>ers and patients might be considerably accelerated. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>The Twitter discussion on #KidneyStones engaged multiple stakeholders in the healthcare sec-<lb/>tor on a global scale and involves both professionals and laypeople. Considering the rapidly <lb/>increasing prevalence and treatment-related costs of urolithiasis, Twitter might promote <lb/>shared decision-making and contribute to the optimisation of patient care. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting Information <lb/>S1 Table. Geolocation of users of the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">S2 Table. Top 100 words used in the #KidneyStones online discussion on Twitter. <lb/>(XLSX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors wish to thank all the participants in the lively Twitter discussion on <lb/>#KidneyStones. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceived and designed the experiments: JS HB IT. <lb/>Performed the experiments: JS HB IT. <lb/>Analyzed the data: JS HB MB HMF A. Haferkamp A. Heidenreich AM AN TK CT IT. <lb/>Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: JS HB IT. <lb/>Wrote the paper: JS HB MB HMF A. Haferkamp A. Heidenreich AM AN TK CT IT. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Davies N, Murphy DG, van Rij S, Woo HH, Lawrentschuk N. Online and social media presence of Aus-<lb/>tralian and New Zealand urologists. BJU Int. 2015; 116(6): 984-989. doi: 10.1111/bju.13159 PMID: <lb/>25906813. <lb/>2. Borgmann HD, Tsuar IS, Haferkamp A, Loeb S. Novel survey disseminated through Twitter supports its <lb/>utility for networking, disseminating research, advocacy, clinical practice and other professional goals. <lb/>CUAJ. 2015; 9(9-10). Novel survey disseminated through Twitter supports its utility for networking, dis-<lb/>seminating research, advocacy, clinical practice and other professional goals. <lb/>3. Chung A, Woo H. Twitter in urology and other surgical specialties at global conferences. ANZ J Surg. <lb/>2015. doi: 10.1111/ans.13393 PMID: 26631323. <lb/>4. Thangasamy IA, Leveridge M, Davies BJ, Finelli A, Stork B, Woo HH. International Urology Journal <lb/>Club via Twitter: 12-month experience. Eur Urol. 2014; 66(1): 112-117. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2014.01. <lb/>034 PMID: 24548686. <lb/>5. Kutikov A, Woo HH, Catto JW. Urology tag ontology project: Standardizing social media communication <lb/>descriptors. Eur Urol. 2015. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2015.09.034 PMID: 26443429. <lb/>6. Canvasser NE, Ramo C, Morgan TM, Zheng K, Hollenbeck BK, Ghani KR. The use of social media in <lb/>endourology: An analysis of the 2013 World Congress of Endourology meeting. J Endourol. 2015; 29 <lb/>(5): 615-620. doi: 10.1089/end.2014.0329 PMID: 25026076. <lb/>7. Symplur. The Healthcare Hashtag Project. Available from: http://www.symplur.com. <lb/>8. Scales CD Jr, Smith AC, Hanley JM, Saigal CS. Urologic diseases in America. Prevalence of kidney <lb/>stones in the United States. Eur Urol. 2012; 62(1): 160-165. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2012.03.052 PMID: <lb/>22498635; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3362665. <lb/>9. Antonelli JA, Maalouf NM, Pearle MS, Lotan Y. Use of the National Health and Nutrition Examination <lb/>Survey to calculate the impact of obesity and diabetes on cost and prevalence of urolithiasis in 2030. <lb/>Eur Urol. 2014; 66(4): 724-729. doi: 10.1016/j.eururo.2014.06.036 PMID: 25015037; PubMed Central <lb/>PMCID: PMCPMC4227394. <lb/>10. Tasian GE, Ross ME, Song L, Sas DJ, Keren R, Denburg MR, et al. Annual incidence of nephrolithiasis <lb/>among children and adults in South Carolina from 1997 to 2012. Clin J Am Soc Nephrol. 2016. doi: 10. <lb/>2215/CJN.07610715 PMID: 26769765. <lb/>11. Leveridge MJ. The state and potential of social media in bladder cancer. World J Urol. 2015. doi: 10. <lb/>1007/s00345-015-1725-y PMID: 26590917. <lb/>12. Attai DJ, Cowher MS, Al-Hamadani M, Schoger JM, Staley AC, Landercasper J. Twitter social media is <lb/>an effective tool for breast cancer patient education and support: Patient-reported outcomes by survey. <lb/>J Med Internet Res. 2015; 17(7): e188. doi: 10.2196/jmir.4721 PMID: 26228234. <lb/>13. Signals S. Healthcare category definitions. Available from: https://docs.google.com/spreadsheets/d/ <lb/>1HexI7X1KR0dPdFvJkd34DEtHF_18BGHzdnPNrauHNwI/edit-gid=0&amp;vpid=A1. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Weeg C, Schwartz HA, Hill S, Merchant RM, Arango C, Ungar L. Using Twitter to measure public dis-<lb/>cussion of diseases: A case study. JMIR Public Health Surveill. 2015; 1(1): e6. doi: 10.2196/ <lb/>publichealth.3953 PMID: 26925459; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC4763717. <lb/>15. Borgmann H, Loeb S, Salem J, Thomas C, Haferkamp A, Murphy DG, et al. Activity, content, contribu-<lb/>tors, and influencers of the Twitter discussion on urologic oncology. Urol Oncol. 2016. doi: 10.1016/j. <lb/>urolonc.2016.02.021 PMID: 27036217. <lb/>16. Cardona-Grau D SI, Leinwand G, Welliver C. Introducing the Twitter impact factor: An objective mea-<lb/>sure of urology&apos;s academic impact on Twitter. Eur Urol Focus. 2016; 138: In press. <lb/>17. Robillard JM, Johnson TW, Hennessey C, Beattie BL, Illes J. Aging 2.0: Health information about <lb/>dementia on Twitter. PLoS One. 2013; 8(7): e69861. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0069861 PMID: <lb/>23922827; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3724927. <lb/>18. Thackeray R, Neiger BL, Burton SH, Thackeray CR. Analysis of the purpose of state health depart-<lb/>ments&apos; tweets: Information sharing, engagement, and action. J Med Internet Res. 2013; 15(11):e255. <lb/>doi: 10.2196/jmir.3002 PMID: 24217361; PubMed Central PMCID: PMCPMC3841368. <lb/>19. Loeb S, Bayne CE, Frey C, Davies BJ, Averch TD, Woo HH, et al. Use of social media in urology: data <lb/>from the American Urological Association (AUA). BJU Int. 2014; 113(6): 993-998. doi: 10.1111/bju. <lb/>12586 PMID: 24274744. <lb/>20. Lotan Y, Buendia Jimenez I, Lenoir-Wijnkoop I, Daudon M, Molinier L, Tack I, et al. Primary prevention <lb/>of nephrolithiasis is cost-effective for a national healthcare system. BJU Int. 2012; 110(11 Pt C): <lb/>E1060-7. doi: 10.1111/j.1464-410X.2012.11212.x PMID: 22686216. <lb/>21. Sun BY, Lee YH, Jiaan BP, Chen KK, Chang LS, Chen KT. Recurrence rate and risk factors for urinary <lb/>calculi after extracorporeal shock wave lithotripsy. J Urol. 1996; 156(3): 903-905; discussion 6. PMID: <lb/>8709359. <lb/>22. Trinchieri A, Ostini F, Nespoli R, Rovera F, Montanari E, Zanetti G. A prospective study of recurrence <lb/>rate and risk factors for recurrence after a first renal stone. J Urol. 1999; 162(1): 27-30. doi: 10.1097/ <lb/>00005392-199907000-00007 PMID: 10379732. <lb/>23. Borghi L, Meschi T, Amato F, Briganti A, Novarini A, Giannini A. Urinary volume, water and recurrences <lb/>in idiopathic calcium nephrolithiasis: a 5-year randomized prospective study. J Urol. 1996; 155(3): 839-<lb/>843. PMID: 8583588. <lb/>24. Kocvara R, Plasgura P, Petrik A, Louzensky G, Bartonickova K, Dvoracek J. A prospective study of <lb/>nonmedical prophylaxis after a first kidney stone. BJU Int. 1999; 84(4): 393-398. PMID: 10468751. <lb/>25. Siener R, Glatz S, Nicolay C, Hesse A. The role of overweight and obesity in calcium oxalate stone for-<lb/>mation. Obes Res. 2004; 12(1): 106-113. doi: 10.1038/oby.2004.14 PMID: 14742848. <lb/>26. Barcelo P, Wuhl O, Servitge E, Rousaud A, Pak CY. Randomized double-blind study of potassium cit-<lb/>rate in idiopathic hypocitraturic calcium nephrolithiasis. J Urol. 1993; 150(6): 1761-1764. PMID: <lb/>8230497. <lb/>27. Ettinger B, Tang A, Citron JT, Livermore B, Williams T. Randomized trial of allopurinol in the prevention <lb/>of calcium oxalate calculi. N Engl J Med. 1986; 315(22): 1386-1389. doi: 10.1056/ <lb/>NEJM198611273152204 PMID: 3534570. <lb/>28. Laerum E, Larsen S. Thiazide prophylaxis of urolithiasis. A double-blind study in general practice. Acta <lb/>Med Scand. 1984; 215(4): 383-389. PMID: 6375276. <lb/>29. Dauw CA, Alruwaily AF, Bierlein MJ, Asplin JR, Ghani KR, Wolf JS Jr., et al. Provider variation in the <lb/>quality of metabolic stone management. J Urol. 2015; 193(3): 885-890. doi: 10.1016/j.juro.2014.09. <lb/>111 PMID: 25286012. <lb/>30. Dauw CA, Yi Y, Bierlein MJ, Yan P, Alruwaily AF, Ghani KR, et al. Medication nonadherence and effec-<lb/>tiveness of preventive pharmacological therapy for kidney stones. J Urol. 2015. doi: 10.1016/j.juro. <lb/>2015.10.082 PMID: 26485048. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Online Discussion on #KidneyStones <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS ONE | DOI:10.1371/journal.pone.0160863 August 18, 2016 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 11 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
