<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

			<front>1033 <lb/> Signal enhancement in cantilever magnetometry <lb/>based on a co-resonantly coupled sensor <lb/>Julia Körner 1 , Christopher F. Reiche 1 , Thomas Gemming 1 , Bernd Büchner 1,2 , <lb/>Gerald Gerlach 3 and Thomas Mühl *1 <lb/>Full Research Paper <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Address: <lb/>1 Leibniz Institute for Solid State and Materials Research IFW <lb/>Dresden, Helmholtzstr. 20, 01069 Dresden, Germany, 2 Institut für <lb/>Festkörperphysik, Technische Universität Dresden, Dresden, <lb/>Germany and 3 Institut für Festkörperelektronik, Technische <lb/>Universität Dresden, 01062 Dresden, Germany <lb/>Email: <lb/>Thomas Mühl * -t.muehl@ifw-dresden.de <lb/>* Corresponding author <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>cantilever magnetometry; coupled oscillator; iron-filled carbon <lb/>nanotube; magnetometry; signal enhancement <lb/>Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/>doi:10.3762/bjnano.7.96 <lb/>Received: 02 March 2016 <lb/>Accepted: 06 July 2016 <lb/>Published: 18 July 2016 <lb/>This article is part of the Thematic Series &quot;Advanced atomic force <lb/>microscopy techniques IV&quot;. <lb/>Guest Editor: T. Glatzel <lb/>© 2016 Körner et al.; licensee Beilstein-Institut. <lb/>License and terms: see end of document. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Cantilever magnetometry is a measurement technique used to study magnetic nanoparticles. With decreasing sample size, the signal <lb/>strength is significantly reduced, requiring advances of the technique. Ultrathin and slender cantilevers can address this challenge <lb/>but lead to increased complexity of detection. We present an approach based on the co-resonant coupling of a micro-and a nanome-<lb/>ter-sized cantilever. Via matching of the resonance frequencies of the two subsystems we induce a strong interplay between the <lb/>oscillations of the two cantilevers, allowing for a detection of interactions between the sensitive nanocantilever and external influ-<lb/>ences in the amplitude response curve of the microcantilever. In our magnetometry experiment we used an iron-filled carbon nano-<lb/>tube acting simultaneously as nanocantilever and magnetic sample. Measurements revealed an enhancement of the commonly used <lb/>frequency shift signal by five orders of magnitude compared to conventional cantilever magnetometry experiments with similar <lb/>nanomagnets. With this experiment we do not only demonstrate the functionality of our sensor design but also its potential for very <lb/>sensitive magnetometry measurements while maintaining a facile oscillation detection with a conventional microcantilever setup. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Over the last decade, magnetic objects of micro-and nanome-<lb/>ter size have come into focus of researchers, since they offer a <lb/>wide range of possible applications. These include magnetic <lb/>storage techniques and spintronics [1], as well as the study of <lb/>magnetic microorganisms in biology, for example for applica-<lb/>tions in hypothermia treatment [2]. A technique to investigate <lb/>such magnetic particles and samples is cantilever magnetom-<lb/>etry. The measurement setup is based on a cantilever oscil-<lb/>lating at or close to its resonance frequency, with the sample <lb/>placed at the free end of the cantilever. When an external mag-<lb/>netic field is applied to the setup, the magnetic interaction of the <lb/>sample with the field alters the resonance frequency of the can-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<body>tilever by creating a torque [3]. The resulting frequency shift <lb/>can be used as measurement signal to derive information on the <lb/>properties of the sample. In most cases the motion of the canti-<lb/>lever is detected optically, for example via laser deflection or <lb/>laser interferometry [4]. With decreasing sample size, the canti-<lb/>lever has to be adapted to compensate the weaker magnetic <lb/>interaction and, therefore, the loss in signal strength of the fre-<lb/>quency shift. This is usually achieved through geometric <lb/>changes, making the cantilever itself very small and thin. <lb/>An oscillating cantilever beam can be represented by a <lb/>harmonic oscillator model for each flexural eigenmode of the <lb/>beam [5]. Considering an external force gradient as an addition-<lb/>al spring constant Δk, the eigenfrequency of the cantilever as a <lb/>harmonic oscillator is given by: <lb/>(1) <lb/>with the spring constant k and effective mass m eff of the cantile-<lb/>ver. Please note that the eigenfrequency f 0 and the resonance <lb/>frequency <lb/>of a harmonic oscillator should in principle <lb/>be distinguished. They are connected by the relation <lb/>However, it is obvious that in the limit <lb/>of small dissipation or correspondingly a high quality factor of <lb/>the cantilever these frequencies coincide well. The resonance <lb/>frequency of a beam can easily be determined from amplitude <lb/>response curves and, since all our discussions will be based on <lb/>such curves, we will be using the term resonance frequency <lb/>throughout the remainder of this publication. <lb/>For magnetometry experiments, the mass of the cantilever with <lb/>the magnetic sample remains unchanged throughout the experi-<lb/>ment, making it unnecessary to consider the influence of mass <lb/>changes on the resonance frequency of the cantilever. The mag-<lb/>netic interaction between sample and external magnetic field <lb/>acts as the additional spring constant Δk, altering the resonance <lb/>frequency of the cantilever. The frequency shift Δf induced by <lb/>these interactions can be derived from Equation 1 as: <lb/>(2) <lb/>In the case of cantilever magnetometry, Δk does not only <lb/>depend on the interaction of the magnetic moment m of the <lb/>sample with the external magnetic field H but also on the effec-<lb/>tive length of the cantilever L eff [6,7]. Furthermore, by <lb/>assuming a simple Stoner-Wohlfarth single domain particle, the <lb/>magnetic interaction is related to the anisotropy field of the <lb/>sample H a , so Equation 2 reads: <lb/>(3) <lb/>This equation can be used as a good approximation for the iron-<lb/>filled carbon nanotube samples which are presented in this <lb/>publication. However, please note that other samples might ex-<lb/>hibit more complex magnetic configurations, as for example <lb/>multiple particles or domains, which then need a more elabo-<lb/>rate description. <lb/>From Equation 3 it is evident that small magnetic samples <lb/>require a low stiffness as well as a short length of the cantilever <lb/>which can be achieved by decreasing all of the dimensions of <lb/>the cantilever as already mentioned above. As an instructive ex-<lb/>ample to understand this, a simple cantilever with constant <lb/>rectangular cross section with the width w, the thickness t and <lb/>the length L can be considered. According to Euler-Bernoulli <lb/>beam theory, the spring constant and resonance frequency for <lb/>this kind of beam are given by <lb/>and <lb/>[6]. By <lb/>combining this with Equation 3 for the frequency shift signal in <lb/>cantilever magnetometry, it can be derived that <lb/>Therefore, a decrease of all dimensions of the rectangular canti-<lb/>lever is favorable to increase the signal strength. Please note <lb/>that while this simple derivation is only valid for cantilevers <lb/>with rectangular cross section, similar considerations can be <lb/>applied to other cantilever geometries. <lb/>However, ultrathin and small cantilevers are difficult to produce <lb/>and handle and furthermore still need a feature to allow for the <lb/>use of optical detection methods. This is usually realized by a <lb/>paddle-shaped structure positioned somewhere along the length <lb/>of the cantilever [4,8]. Still, the detection capability limits the <lb/>decrease in size. Conclusively, there are two competing condi-<lb/>tions: on the one hand, the stiffness and length of the cantilever <lb/>should be very low in order to obtain a strong signal even with <lb/>very small magnetic samples. On the other hand, detection <lb/>becomes increasingly difficult when the size of the cantilever is <lb/>reduced to dimensions on the nanoscale. <lb/>Our recently introduced sensor concept addresses these difficul-<lb/>ties by co-resonant coupling of a micro-and a nanocantilever <lb/>where the latter allows for very high sensitivity and the microm-<lb/>eter size part for an easy detection [9]. We will only briefly <lb/>review the theoretical considerations regarding the sensor <lb/>concept since it is discussed in depth elsewhere [9]. The main <lb/>focus of this publication is to demonstrate the applicability of <lb/>the concept for cantilever magnetometry by deriving magnetic <lb/>information of an iron nanowire and comparing them to the <lb/>results of other measurements. In our experiment we use a com-<lb/>mercially available silicon cantilever of micrometer dimensions <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1035 <lb/></page>

			<body>and an iron-filled carbon nanotube (FeCNT), the latter with two <lb/>out of three dimensions on the nanometer scale and therefore <lb/>with low stiffness and low effective mass. Typical diameters of <lb/>the iron filling are (15-30) nm and the nanotube length ranges <lb/>from (15-45) μm [10,11]. The FeCNT not only features favor-<lb/>able geometric and material properties [12] but the iron filling <lb/>allows for a magnetometry measurement as well and, therefore, <lb/>for a demonstration of the functionality of our sensor. The <lb/>remainder of this publication is structured as follows: first we <lb/>will introduce the main ideas of the co-resonant sensor concept. <lb/>Next, we will discuss the fabrication of such a sensor and then <lb/>evaluate a magnetometry measurement and derive magnetic <lb/>properties of an iron nanowire in order to prove the applicabili-<lb/>ty of the concept and to indicate its potential for signal enhance-<lb/>ment in magnetometry. <lb/>Experimental <lb/>Co-resonant concept <lb/>By applying the harmonic oscillator model for both subsystems <lb/>of our sensor approach, the simple model of a coupled harmonic <lb/>oscillating system is derived as depicted in Figure 1. It consists <lb/>of a spring, a mass and a damping element for each subsystem. <lb/>Furthermore, there are an additional spring k 3 and a damping el-<lb/>ement d 3 , modeling interactions between the coupled system <lb/>and external influences. The oscillation of the coupled system is <lb/>driven by a periodic force applied to the bigger subsystem. <lb/>Figure 1: Simple model for two coupled harmonic oscillators, each <lb/>represented by a mass (m 1 , m 2 ), a sping (k 1 , k 2 ) and a damping ele-<lb/>ment (d 1 , d 2 ). The system is excited to oscillations by a periodic force <lb/>with the driving angular frequency ω D = 2πf D applied to the first <lb/>subsystem. Interactions between the system and external influences <lb/>are modeled by an additional spring k 3 and the damping element d 3 . <lb/>For the described sensor setup, subsystem 1 corresponds to the canti-<lb/>lever and subsystem 2 to a FeCNT. <lb/>In our case, subsystem 1 represents the silicon cantilever and <lb/>subsystem 2 the FeCNT and, since the cantilever is the part of <lb/>the sensor that will be used for detection, we will discuss the <lb/>behaviour of the coupled system accordingly. Please note that <lb/>all the following considerations are valid for the FeCNT as <lb/>well. Theoretically, if coupled beams are each represented by a <lb/>harmonic oscillator model which is only valid for one reso-<lb/>nance mode of the beam, the amplitude response of each <lb/>subsystem should exhibit a number of resonance frequencies ac-<lb/>cording to the number of subsystems. Applied to our system it <lb/>means that two resonance peaks should occur in the amplitude <lb/>response of the subsystem representing the cantilever. However, <lb/>if the resonance frequencies of cantilever and FeCNT are far <lb/>apart, the amplitude of the second peak in the amplitude <lb/>response of the cantilever will be well below the limit of almost <lb/>every detection method. Figure 2 depicts a calculated ampli-<lb/>tude response of the cantilever based on typical values for our <lb/>system as summarized in Table 1. With the resonance frequen-<lb/>cies of the subsystem far apart, i.e., very weak interplay, the <lb/>amplitude response curve of the harmonic oscillator repre-<lb/>senting the cantilever only shows one prominent resonance <lb/>peak, coinciding well with the resonance frequency of the <lb/>uncoupled cantilever. The amplitude for the second peak caused <lb/>by the FeCNT is by several orders of magnitude smaller and <lb/>therefore not shown in Figure 2. <lb/>Figure 2: Calculated amplitude response for the cantilever (subsystem <lb/>1) with and without frequency matching between the two subsystems. <lb/>The calculation is based on typical values for cantilever and FeCNT <lb/>(see Table 1) and d 3 and k 3 are set to zero, assuming a system with-<lb/>out interaction. <lb/>Table 1: Properties of cantilever and FeCNT constituting the coupled <lb/>sensor. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Cantilever (1) <lb/>FeCNT (2) <lb/>spring constant k i <lb/>133.8 N/m <lb/>0.0086 N/m <lb/>effective mass m eff,i <lb/>6.5 • 10 −12 kg <lb/>4.1 • 10 −16 kg <lb/>quality factor Q i <lb/>3390 <lb/>450 <lb/>resonance frequency f i <lb/>before matching <lb/>723080 Hz <lb/>2082080 Hz <lb/>resonance frequency f i <lb/>after matching <lb/>723080 Hz <lb/>725610 Hz <lb/>This picture changes drastically when the resonance frequency <lb/>of the FeCNT is adjusted close to the value of the cantilever. In <lb/>that case, we observe two clear resonance peaks in the ampli-<lb/>tude response of the cantilever (Figure 2). Furthermore, due to <lb/>strong interplay between the subsystems induced by the <lb/>co-resonant frequency matching, the two resonance frequencies <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3: SEM images (a) of the fabricated sensor, (b) and (c) of the free end of the FeCNT before and after carbon deposition and (d) of the co-reso-<lb/>nant oscillation of the FeCNT. <lb/>of the coupled system are shifted compared to the resonance <lb/>frequencies of the single subsystems. We will therefore use f a <lb/>and f b for the resonance frequencies of the coupled system and <lb/>f 1 and f 2 for the individual resonance frequencies of cantilever <lb/>and FeCNT, respectively, in the following. Futher details on the <lb/>behaviour of a co-resonantly coupled system can be found else-<lb/>where [9], so we will only summarize the main points here: <lb/>1. A strong interplay is induced between the two subsys-<lb/>tems due to the matching of the resonance frequencies, <lb/>even for two highly asymmetric subsystems. <lb/>2. Interactions between FeCNT and an external influence <lb/>alter the oscillation of the FeCNT. Through the co-reso-<lb/>nant coupling this changes the resonance frequencies of <lb/>the coupled system and can be detected at the cantilever. <lb/>3. Small interactions result in rather large frequency shifts <lb/>due to the low stiffness, i.e., high sensitivity of the nano-<lb/>scale oscillator, and can be measured with a rather insen-<lb/>sitive cantilever. <lb/>Sensor fabrication <lb/>Based on the theoretical considerations we fabricated a magne-<lb/>tometry sensor consisting of a commercially available tipless <lb/>silicon cantilever and an iron-filled carbon nanotube. All <lb/>productions steps were carried out in a Zeiss FIB CrossBeam <lb/>1540 XB under high vacuum (≈10 −5 mbar). First, the cantilever <lb/>was shortened via focused ion beam milling to increase its reso-<lb/>nance frequency. This step also increased the stiffness of the <lb/>cantilever to about 133.8 N/m (see Table 1) which is rather high <lb/>compared to typical values in cantilever magnetometry. In a <lb/>second step, an individual nanotube was picked from a forest of <lb/>FeCNTs grown by chemical vapor deposition [10] by a <lb/>Kleindiek micromanipulator and placed at the free end of the <lb/>cantilever. Electron beam-induced deposition of amorphous car-<lb/>bon on the contact point between FeCNT and cantilever ensures <lb/>a strong attachment of the nanotube. Next, amorphous carbon <lb/>was also deposited at the free end of the FeCNT to lower its <lb/>resonance frequency from above 2 MHz close to that of the can-<lb/>tilever. Throughout the process of carbon deposition, the oscil-<lb/>lation of the FeCNT was observed with SEM to ensure close <lb/>matching of the two resonance frequencies by employing a <lb/>custom-made vibration stage. When the resonance frequencies <lb/>of the subsystem are approaching each other, the resonance <lb/>frequencies of the coupled system do not coincide with them <lb/>anymore, as discussed above. In order to still measure the single <lb/>resonance frequency of each subsystem we used a tungsten tip <lb/>to hold the respective other subsystem, therefore detuning the <lb/>coupled system. Figure 3 shows the sensor and magnified <lb/>images of the free of the FeCNT end before and after frequency <lb/>matching. Furthermore, the co-resonant oscillation of the nano-<lb/>tube is depicted. <lb/>Another feature of the co-resonant coupling is the amplitude <lb/>amplification [13] of the free end of the oscillating nanotube as <lb/>it is evident in Figure 3d. The free end of the FeCNT exhibits an <lb/>amplitude of more than 2 μm, whereas the cantilever and the <lb/>other end of the FeCNT conntected to the cantilever only oscil-<lb/>late in the range of a few nanometers. <lb/>Magnetometry measurement <lb/>All magnetometry measurements were carried out in a <lb/>NanoScan AG hr-MFM at room temperature and under high <lb/>vacuum (≈10 −5 mbar). The machine employs a piezo actuator <lb/>for oscillating the cantilever and a laser deflection detection <lb/>system with a sectioned photo diode to determine its oscillation. <lb/>We measured the amplitude response of the cantilever by <lb/>sweeping the excitation frequency at a constant amplitude of the <lb/>AC piezo voltage. <lb/>In order to generate a magnetic field parallel to the long axis of <lb/>the FeCNT inside the measurement chamber, we used commer-<lb/>cially available NdFeB magnets [14], positioned on a sample <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1037 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 4: Sketch of measurement positions which are reached by keeping the sensor position fixed and rotating the sample plate. (1) and (2) corre-<lb/>spond to the two orientations of the magnetic field and (3) is a field-free position. The CCD camera picture on the right hand side shows the sensor <lb/>close to one of the magnets. <lb/>plate. The sensor position was fixed throughout the measure-<lb/>ment and the sample plate carrying the magnets has been <lb/>rotated in order to allow measurements with both magnetic field <lb/>directions as well as at a field-free position. Figure 4 depicts a <lb/>sketch of the setup with the measurement positions indicated <lb/>and an image generated by the CCD camera of the instrument. <lb/>Furthermore, Figure 5 shows a two-dimensional simulation of <lb/>the magnetic field obtained with the finite element software <lb/>FEMM [15]. Close to the surface of the magnet at the height, <lb/>where the measurements were carried out, the magnetic flux <lb/>density reaches values of about 460 mT in the direction of the <lb/>FeCNT&apos;s easy axis. <lb/>In order to measure at various magnetic field values without <lb/>moving the sensor to ensure stable measurement conditions, the <lb/>distance between sensor and magnet was changed by stepwise <lb/>movement of the sample plate holding the magnet. At each step <lb/>we measured the amplitude response of the cantilever in the fre-<lb/>quency range of interest and determined the two resonance <lb/>frequencies of the coupled system. Figure 6 shows two ampli-<lb/>tude response curves as an example: one being taken at the po-<lb/>sition closest to the magnet, i.e., at a distance of about 100 μm <lb/>in a field of approximately 406 mT, and the other one at a field-<lb/>free position (see Figure 4). As can easily be seen, there is a sig-<lb/>nificant change in the resonance frequencies of the coupled <lb/>system which we attribute to the magnetic interaction between <lb/>the iron filling of the FeCNT and the magnetic field of the <lb/>NdFeB magnet. <lb/>Figure 7 depicts the measured resonance frequency shift for <lb/>each of the two peaks of the coupled system compared to the <lb/>field free measurement for various magnetic field values. We <lb/>Figure 5: Simulated magnetic field of the permanent magnet. The field <lb/>dependence on the distance to the surface of the magnet is calculated <lb/>for the black line, corresponding to the measurement height. <lb/>observe a frequency shift of several 100 Hz in high magnetic <lb/>field compared to the field free measurement for the left peak <lb/>(a) in Figure 6. The shifts are even higher for the smaller, i.e., <lb/>the right hand side, peak but it also features a higher measure-<lb/>ment uncertainty regarding the determination of the maximum <lb/>amplitude and hence resonance frequency. Table 2 summarizes <lb/>the maximum frequency shift for both peaks and orientations of <lb/>the magnetic field. The differences in the frequency shift values <lb/>can be attributed to limited position accuracy of the magnets. <lb/>Results and Discussion <lb/>Compared to previous cantilever magnetometry experiments <lb/>with similar FeCNTs, the frequency shifts in our experiment of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1038 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 6: Amplitude response curves of the cantilever measured at the field-free position (3) according to Figure 4 and approximately 100 μm above <lb/>the surface of the magnet (position (2)). The peaks are marked with (a) and (b) for reference purposes. <lb/>Figure 7: Measured frequency shifts of both peaks (a) and (b) compared to the field free measurement for various magnetic field values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1039 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2: Measured resonance frequencies f a/b of the coupled system <lb/>for both orientations of the magnet and corresponding frequency shift <lb/>values Δf compared to a field-free measurement. The values are given <lb/>for the highest magnetic field. <lb/>Left peak (a) <lb/>Right peak (b) <lb/>f a/b field-free <lb/>(720679.5 ± 10) Hz (728051.3 ± 83) Hz <lb/>Position 1 <lb/>f a/b @ 406 mT <lb/>(720402 ± 10) Hz <lb/>(727290 ± 83) Hz <lb/>Δf <lb/>(−277.5 ± 20) Hz <lb/>(−761.3 ± 166) Hz <lb/>Position 2 <lb/>f a/b @ −406 mT <lb/>(720962 ± 10) Hz <lb/>(729124 ± 83) Hz <lb/>Δf <lb/>(282.5 ± 20) Hz <lb/>(1072.7 ± 166) Hz <lb/>280 Hz and 1000 Hz, respectively, for the two resonance peaks <lb/>are increased by several orders of magnitude. For example, <lb/>Banerjee et al. used similar FeCNTs on sensitive cantilevers <lb/>with spring constants of about 0.2 N/m at low temperatures and <lb/>measured frequency shifts in the order of mHz [7]. It has also <lb/>been shown previously that a FeCNT oscillating in a magnetic <lb/>field without being placed onto a cantilever can indeed exhibit a <lb/>large frequency shift compared to the field-free case. However, <lb/>the detection of the oscillatory state of the small nanotube <lb/>remained a challenge as stated by Philippi et al. [16]. With our <lb/>approach of co-resonant coupling we simultaneously allow for a <lb/>very strong measurement signal and an easy detection of the <lb/>oscillatory state of the FeCNT. <lb/>After the rather qualitative analysis of our obtained data, we <lb/>now want to show the possibility to extract reliable magnetic <lb/>information from the measured frequency shifts, making our <lb/>sensor suitable for quantitative magnetic measurements. <lb/>Effective spring constant of the coupled <lb/>system <lb/>In order to derive magnetic information from the measured fre-<lb/>quency shift data, we use a relation similar to Equation 2 by <lb/>introducing effective spring constants <lb/>(4) <lb/>and evaluate it with respect to k 3 which contains the magnetic <lb/>interaction. Here f a/b and Δf a/b denote the two resonance <lb/>frequencies of the coupled system and their respective <lb/>shifts. The effective spring constants <lb/>determine the <lb/>sensitivity for each resonance peak of the coupled system and <lb/>have to be known for a quantitative analysis of the measured <lb/>data. <lb/>In order to obtain them for the given sensor geometry we will <lb/>be using an approximate formula to calculate the expected reso-<lb/>nance angular frequencies of the coupled system ω a/b = 2πf a/b <lb/>for a small interaction spring constant k 3 [17]: <lb/>(5) <lb/>with <lb/>= (k 1 + k 2 )/m 1 and <lb/>= (k 2 + k 3 )/m 2 . Furthermore, <lb/>m 1,2 denote the effective masses of the subsystems which can <lb/>easily be determined from their resonance frequencies (see <lb/>Table 1) by m 1,2 = k 1,2 /(2πf 1,2 ) 2 . Equation 5 neglects any <lb/>damping effects but this is a justified approximation since all <lb/>our measurements are carried out under high vacuum, limiting <lb/>damping to intrinsic effects due to the bending of the oscil-<lb/>lating structures [9]. This was futhermore confirmed by com-<lb/>parison between the results obtained by Equation 5 and evalu-<lb/>ating of the analytical solution of the differential equations <lb/>describing the system. <lb/>With Equation 5 we can calculate the resonance frequencies of <lb/>the coupled system for the two cases: without interaction, i.e., <lb/>k 3 = 0, and with a small interaction, k 3 = 1 • 10 −6 N/m, and de-<lb/>termine the resulting frequency shifts. By inserting these values <lb/>in Equation 4 and rearranging it, we are able to obtain the <lb/>values for the effective spring constants for the two resonance <lb/>peaks as: <lb/>Comparing these values to the spring constants of the single <lb/>subsystems k cant = 133.8 N/m and k CNT = 0.0086 N/m it is <lb/>obvious that the effective spring constants of the coupled <lb/>system are a mixture of the stiffnesses of the individual subsys-<lb/>tems and that they are strongly influenced by the low stiffness <lb/>of the FeCNT. Furthermore, the effective spring constants <lb/>depend on the grade of frequency matching as can be seen from <lb/>Equation 5. Closely matched resonance frequencies induce a <lb/>strong interplay between the two subsystems. Hence, any mag-<lb/>netic interaction between FeCNT and external influences can be <lb/>sensed with an effective stiffness slightly above the low spring <lb/>constant of the FeCNT (in our case approximately by a factor of <lb/>three) but be measured with a rather insensitive cantilever. <lb/>However, we do not see the full sensitivity of the FeCNT in the <lb/>measured frequency shift. Instead we observe a reduction <lb/>leading to the conclusion that the behaviour of the coupled <lb/>system can be described well by the effective spring constant <lb/>k eff . <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 8: Dependence of the effective spring constant of each peak <lb/>on the interaction spring constant k 3 . The calculations are based on the <lb/>properties of the system given in Table 1. <lb/>However, it is important to note that k eff is only constant as long <lb/>as k 3 &lt;&lt;k 1 ; k 2 is satisfied. Otherwise it shows a strong depen-<lb/>dence on k 3 . Calculations for our set of parameters depicted in <lb/>Figure 8 indicate that k 3 has to be at least two orders of magni-<lb/>tude below the smaller spring constant of the system. This is <lb/>well fulfilled in our case since the interaction spring constant <lb/>for the strongest magnetic field of |B| = 406 mT is approxi-<lb/>mately 2 • 10 −5 N/m (calculated with Equation 4). Please note <lb/>that the results in Figure 8 are only shown for k 3 ¿ 0 but the be-<lb/>haviour is approximately similar for k 3 &lt; 0, only with the devia-<lb/>tions from the constant values being in the opposite direction. <lb/>Since for closely matched frequencies k eff is mainly dominated <lb/>by the smaller subsystem, a decrease of its stiffness will lead to <lb/>an increase in sensitivity. Hence, possible sensor implementa-<lb/>tions could include the use of single walled carbon nanotubes as <lb/>smaller oscillator or fabrication of the complete sensor in <lb/>silicon technology, allowing for production of double cantile-<lb/>ver structures with one nanocantilever [13,18]. <lb/>However, it has to be noted that the low effective spring con-<lb/>stant is not the sole reason for the increased signal strength of <lb/>the proposed sensor setup. Other groups employed low-stiff-<lb/>ness cantilevers for magnetometry measurements as well but <lb/>did not obtain such a strong frequency shift signal. In cantilever <lb/>magnetometry the signal is related to the length of the sensing <lb/>cantilever and the spring constant as stated by Equation 3. <lb/>Therefore, an increased cantilever length would in principle <lb/>favorably affect the spring constant but nevertheless limits the <lb/>sensitivity increase. In view of that our geometry is favorable as <lb/>well since the sensing part, i.e., the nanotube, has a low spring <lb/>constant while also being relatively short (in the order of <lb/>10 μm). Both features contribute to the observed strong increase <lb/>in signal strength. <lb/>Determination of effective magnetic <lb/>monopole moment from measured data <lb/>With the determination of k eff it is possible to extract magnetic <lb/>information from the measured frequency shift data, i.e., k 3 . It <lb/>has been shown that in case of a FeCNT a suitable magnetic <lb/>quantity is the effective magnetic monopole moment q of the <lb/>iron nanowire [19,20]. Due to its single-domain magnetic struc-<lb/>ture it is acting as an elongated magnetic dipole oscillating in a <lb/>magnetic field. Since the magnetization of the iron nanowire is <lb/>considered to be nearly parallel to the axis of the FeCNT, its <lb/>two magnetic poles are positioned at either end, i.e., at a dis-<lb/>tance of L cnt = 10 μm. Furthermore, a decrease of the field of <lb/>the NdFeB magnet along the length of the FeCNT of maximal <lb/>5 mT is assumed. The interaction of each of the two poles with <lb/>the external magnetic field leads to a contribution to the <lb/>measured frequency shifts Δf a/b . However, the magnetic pole at <lb/>the attachement point between nanotube and cantilever gives a <lb/>much lower contribution for several reasons: its oscillation <lb/>trajectory radius and sensor stiffness are mainly given by the <lb/>cantilever. In contrast to that the sensor stiffness at the free end <lb/>of the FeCNT can be described by the soft effective spring con-<lb/>stant of the coupled system. Hence, only the monopole at the <lb/>free end of the FeCNT contributes to the frequency shift and the <lb/>influence of the other pole can be neglected. Thus, the effective <lb/>magnetic monopole moment proves to be a suitable parameter <lb/>to characterize the magnetostatic behaviour of the iron of the <lb/>FeCNT filling in the low external field approximation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1041 <lb/></page>

			<body>Following Philippi et al. [16], the effective magnetic monopole <lb/>moment q can be related to the interaction spring constant k 3 : <lb/>(6) <lb/>Here B is the magnetic flux density generated by the NdFeB <lb/>magnet at the position of the free end of the FeCNT (see <lb/>Figure 5). The parameter κ is given as the curvature of the oscil-<lb/>lating termination point of the FeCNT and has been obtained <lb/>from SEM pictures. The mechanical behaviour of an oscillating <lb/>nanowire is discussed in depth elsewhere [16] and for our <lb/>sensor we determined κ = (0.16 ± 0.016) μm −1 . <lb/>By inserting Equation 6 in Equation 4 we obtain the relation: <lb/>(7) <lb/>which is used for a linear regression analysis of the measured <lb/>frequency shift data in Figure 7 using the low field range <lb/>|B| &lt; 0.25 T to avoid major deviations from the <lb/>monopole approach. This evaluation yields two q-values <lb/>(q 1 = 3.05 • 10 −10 A•m and q 2 = 4.37 • 10 −10 A•m) correspond-<lb/>ing to the two resonance peaks of the coupled system. Since the <lb/>effective magnetic monopole moment has to be the same for <lb/>both peaks we calculate the mean value and finally obtain <lb/>q = (3.7 ± 0.7) • 10 −10 A•m, which corresponds to a magnetic <lb/>moment of approximately 4 • 10 8 μ B (CNT length 10 μm). <lb/>Geometric effective magnetic monopole <lb/>moment <lb/>For comparison, the q-value of the FeCNT can be determined <lb/>from geometric information obtained from high-resolution SEM <lb/>pictures. With a diameter of the iron filling of the FeCNT of <lb/>d Fe = (22 ± 6) nm and saturation magnetization of iron <lb/>M s,Fe = (1.71 ± 0.01) • 10 6 A/m, the corresponding effective <lb/>monopole moment is: <lb/>(8) <lb/>Despite the relatively large margin of uncertainty due to the di-<lb/>ameter measurement of the iron filling, this result corresponds <lb/>well to the effective magnetic monopole moment determined <lb/>from the frequency shift values. Furthermore, we can also <lb/>compare our results to values obtained in other experiments <lb/>with iron-filled carbon nanotubes of similar size and find a good <lb/>agreement [7,16,21]. These results demonstrate that the co-reso-<lb/>nant sensor concept applied to cantilever magnetometry allows <lb/>for a quantitative determination of magnetic sample properties <lb/>with strongly increased frequency shifts compared to single-<lb/>cantilever magnetometry experiments [7]. <lb/>Measurement limits <lb/>When proposing a novel sensor concept, inevitably the ques-<lb/>tion regarding the measurement limit arises. The sensitivity <lb/>limits of cantilever-based magnetometry sensors have already <lb/>been discussed by various groups [3,22,23], leading to three <lb/>main considerations which have to be taken into account: the <lb/>sensitivity of the detection setup and thermal and magnetic <lb/>noise in the oscillating system. From these, thermal noise is <lb/>considered to be the most dominant one [24], followed by the <lb/>detector noise which is statistically independent of the former <lb/>[25]. For our discussion, we will only focus on thermal noise. <lb/>Even if only this single noise source is considered it is still an <lb/>open question how the noise is distributed in the co-resonantly <lb/>coupled sensor system [26]. We will therefore use the approach <lb/>of discussing the noise limits for each subsystem, indicating a <lb/>range of the sensitivity for the coupled system. <lb/>In standard cantilever magnetometry the noise limits the <lb/>detectable frequency shift and, hence, the minimal detectable <lb/>magnetic moment. The thermal limit for the frequency shift for <lb/>a cantilever is given by [25]: <lb/>(9) <lb/>Hereby k B denotes the Boltzmann constant, T the temperature, <lb/>B w the measurement bandwidth and Q the quality factor. f 0 and <lb/>k 0 are the resonance frequency and spring constant of the canti-<lb/>lever and A is the amplitude at the free end of the cantilever. By <lb/>following the reasoning of Gysin et al. [23], the frequency shift <lb/>Δf induced by a high-aspect ratio, single domain ferromagnetic <lb/>cylinder placed on a cantilever is given by Equation 3. Combin-<lb/>ing Equation 3 and Equation 9, the minimal detectable magnet-<lb/>ic moment is: <lb/>(10) <lb/>From this expression one can conclude that it is favorable to <lb/>have a small cantilever length, a high oscillation amplitude, a <lb/>strong magnetic field, small spring constant, high resonance fre-<lb/>quency and a large quality factor. Both cantilever length and <lb/>amplitude have a major influence on the minimal detectable <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1042 <lb/></page>

			<body>magnetic moment. Furthermore, m min is maximized if H ext and <lb/>H a are high. <lb/>The above expression has been derived for a single cantilever <lb/>and it is still under investigation if and how it can be adapted <lb/>for the coupled system. It is a reasonable assumption that, in <lb/>accordance with the considerations of the effective spring con-<lb/>stant, the quality factor will as well be an effective one for the <lb/>coupled system. Similarly, the effective magnetic moment <lb/>sensitivity of the coupled system is expected to lie in between <lb/>the sensitivities of the two single systems. Therefore, in Table 3 <lb/>we calculated the minimal detectable magnetic moment for both <lb/>of our subsystems at room temperature, an external magnetic <lb/>field of 1 T and a measurement bandwidth B w = 1 Hz, in accor-<lb/>dance with literature values for such calculations [3,23]. The <lb/>necessary parameters for both subsystems are taken from <lb/>Table 1 for the unmatched frequency state and the length of <lb/>cantilever and nanotube have been taken from SEM pictures: <lb/>L cant = 85 μm and L cnt = 10 μm. They have been recalculated <lb/>into effective lengths by L eff = L/1.377 for the first bending <lb/>mode [6]. We are aware of the fact that there are carbon nano-<lb/>tubes, especially single wall CNTs, that can exhibit a much <lb/>lower stiffness than the FeCNT presented here but we want to <lb/>stick to our existing experimental system and have taken the <lb/>mechanical properties of the CNT as measured. <lb/>Table 3: Minimal detectable magnetic moment for both subsystems of <lb/>the coupled system. The calculations have been made for room tem-<lb/>perature T = 293 K, a bandwidth of B w = 1 Hz and magnetic field of <lb/>B ext = 1 T. <lb/>Parameter <lb/>Cantilever <lb/>FeCNT <lb/>spring constant [N/m] <lb/>133.8 <lb/>0.0086 <lb/>amplitude [nm] <lb/>10 <lb/>1000 <lb/>δf [mHz] <lb/>5 <lb/>26 <lb/>length [μm] <lb/>85 <lb/>10 <lb/>m min [A•m 2 ] <lb/>6 • 10 −15 <lb/>1 • 10 −20 <lb/>m min / μ B <lb/>7 • 10 8 <lb/>1 • 10 3 <lb/>From Table 3 we see that the cantilever has a lower minimal <lb/>detectable frequency shift (due to its better Q-factor and smaller <lb/>resonance frequency) compared to the nanotube but still the <lb/>nanotube exhibits a much better magnetic moment resolution of <lb/>10 3 μ B at room temperature. It has to be kept in mind that the <lb/>magnetization of small particles might not be thermally stable. <lb/>Comparing these calculated values to the measured magnetic <lb/>moment of the section &apos;Determination of effective magnetic <lb/>monopole moment from measured data&apos;, which was <lb/>m FeCNT ≈ 4 • 10 8 μ B , we see that it is already at the limit of <lb/>what could be measured with only the silicon cantilever. In our <lb/>experiment, we observed a frequency shift of several 100 Hertz <lb/>for the resonance frequencies of the coupled system which <lb/>already indicates that the magnetic moment sensitivity is signif-<lb/>icantly increased compared to that of a single cantilever. <lb/>Extending the considerations of Table 3 to single-wall carbon <lb/>nanotubes and applying low temperatures, a potential moment <lb/>sensitivity in the order of single Bohr magnetons could be <lb/>achieved. However, as for the effective spring constant, it will <lb/>probably not be possible to obtain the full moment sensitivity of <lb/>the nanotube due to the strong interplay between the subsys-<lb/>tems, but by using softer cantilevers and softer (unfilled) CNTs <lb/>the coupled sensor concept has a great potential of achieving <lb/>very low magnetic moment resolution while maintaining an <lb/>easy detection at the same time. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>We applied the universal concept of a co-resonantly coupled <lb/>sensor to cantilever magnetometry by using a commercially <lb/>available silicon cantilever and an iron-filled carbon nanotube. <lb/>The FeCNT acted simultaneously as nanocantilever and mag-<lb/>netic sample and, since the magnetic properties of similar <lb/>FeCNTs had already been studied, allowed for demonstrating <lb/>the functionality of the sensor setup. The evaluation of the mea-<lb/>surements shows that, once calibrated by determining the effec-<lb/>tive spring constant, the sensor can be used to derive magnetic <lb/>properties of nanometer-sized samples and significantly in-<lb/>creases the signal strength by several orders of magnitude com-<lb/>pared to conventional single-cantilever magnetometry experi-<lb/>ments. A further increase is possible by tailoring the compo-<lb/>nents of the coupled system according to the measurement task. <lb/>The basic principles of the co-resonant sensor concept [9] are of <lb/>general nature and therefore not limited to cantilever magne-<lb/>tometry but can also be used to fabricate mass and force sensors <lb/>in general. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Siegfried Menzel for supporting the FIB preparation <lb/>work and Uhland Weissker for preparing the FeCNT sample. <lb/>This work was funded by the DFG (Grant No. MU 1794/3-2). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Chappert, C.; Fert, A.; Van Dau, F. N. Nat. Mater. 2007, 6, 813. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nmat2024 <lb/>2. Pankhurst, Q. A.; Connolly, J.; Jones, S. K.; Dobson, J. <lb/>J. Phys. D: Appl. Phys. 2003, 36, R167. <lb/>doi:10.1088/0022-3727/36/13/201 <lb/>3. Stipe, B. C.; Mamin, H. J.; Stowe, T. D.; Kenny, T. W.; Rugar, D. <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 2001, 86, 2874. doi:10.1103/PhysRevLett.86.2874 <lb/>4. Weber, D. P.; Rüffer, D.; Buchter, A.; Xue, F.; Russo-Averchi, E.; <lb/>Huber, R.; Berberich, P.; Arbiol, J.; Fontcuberta i Morral, A.; <lb/>Grundler, D.; Poggio, M. Nano Lett. 2012, 12, 6139. <lb/>doi:10.1021/nl302950u <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Beilstein J. Nanotechnol. 2016, 7, 1033-1043. <lb/></note>

			<page>1043 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>5. Rast, S.; Wattinger, C.; Gysin, U.; Meyer, E. Rev. Sci. Instrum. 2000, <lb/>71, 2772. doi:10.1063/1.1150690 <lb/>6. Sidles, J. A.; Garbini, J. L.; Bruland, K. J.; Rugar, D.; Züger, O.; <lb/>Hoen, S.; Yannoni, C. S. Rev. Mod. Phys. 1995, 67, 249. <lb/>doi:10.1103/RevModPhys.67.249 <lb/>7. Banerjee, P.; Wolny, F.; Pelekhov, D. V.; Herman, M. R.; Fong, K. C.; <lb/>Weissker, U.; Mühl, T.; Obukhov, Y.; Leonhardt, A.; Büchner, B.; <lb/>Hammel, P. C. Appl. Phys. Lett. 2010, 96, 252505. <lb/>doi:10.1063/1.3440951 <lb/>8. Longenecker, J. G.; Mamin, H. J.; Senko, A. W.; Chen, L.; <lb/>Rettner, C. T.; Rugar, D.; Marohn, J. A. ACS Nano 2012, 6, 9637. <lb/>doi:10.1021/nn3030628 <lb/>9. Reiche, C. F.; Körner, J.; Büchner, B.; Mühl, T. Nanotechnology 2015, <lb/>26, 335501. doi:10.1088/0957-4484/26/33/335501 <lb/>10. Leonhardt, A.; Hampel, S.; Müller, C.; Mönch, I.; Koseva, R.; <lb/>Ritschel, M.; Elefant, D.; Biedermann, K.; Büchner, B. <lb/>Chem. Vap. Deposition 2006, 12, 380. doi:10.1002/cvde.200506441 <lb/>11. Leonhardt, A.; Ritschel, M.; Kozhuharova, R.; Graff, A.; Mühl, T.; <lb/>Huhle, R.; Mönch, I.; Elefant, D.; Schneider, C. M. <lb/>Diamond Relat. Mater. 2003, 12, 790. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0925-9635(02)00325-4 <lb/>12. Wolny, F.; Obukhov, Y.; Mühl, T.; Weissker, U.; Philippi, S.; <lb/>Leonhardt, A.; Banerjee, P.; Reed, A.; Xiang, G.; Adur, R.; Lee, I.; <lb/>Hauser, A. J.; Yang, A. J.; Pelekhov, D. V.; Büchner, B.; Hammel, P. C. <lb/>Ultramicroscopy 2011, 111, 1360. doi:10.1016/j.ultramic.2011.05.002 <lb/>13. Li, X.; Ono, T.; Lin, R.; Esashi, M. Microelectron. Eng. 2003, 65, 1. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0167-9317(02)00595-6 <lb/>14. Datasheet for NdFeB Magnet, grade 48. http://www.mtsmagnete.de/ <lb/>(accessed Feb 15, 2015). <lb/>15. Information on the simulation software Finite Element Method <lb/>Magnetics. http://www.femm.info/wiki/HomePage (accessed June 12, <lb/>2015). <lb/>16. Philippi, S.; Weißker, U.; Mühl, T.; Leonhardt, A.; Büchner, B. <lb/>J. Appl. Phys. 2011, 110, 084319. doi:10.1063/1.3651392 <lb/>17. Novotny, L. Am. J. Phys. 2010, 78, 1199. doi:10.1119/1.3471177 <lb/>18. Vidal-Álvarez, G.; Agustí, J.; Torres, F.; Abadal, G.; Barniol, N.; <lb/>Llobert, J.; Sansa, M.; Fernández-Regúlez, M.; Pérez-Murano, F.; <lb/>San Paulo, A.; Gottlieb, O. Nanotechnology 2015, 26, 145502. <lb/>doi:10.1088/0957-4484/26/14/145502 <lb/>19. Wolny, F.; Mühl, T.; Weissker, U.; Lipert, K.; Schumann, J.; <lb/>Leonhardt, A.; Büchner, B. Nanotechnology 2010, 21, 435501. <lb/>doi:10.1088/0957-4484/21/43/435501 <lb/>20. Vock, S.; Wolny, F.; Mühl, T.; Kaltofen, R.; Schultz, L.; Büchner, B.; <lb/>Hassel, C.; Lindner, J.; Neu, V. Appl. Phys. Lett. 2010, 97, 252505. <lb/>doi:10.1063/1.3528340 <lb/>21. Reiche, C. F.; Vock, S.; Neu, V.; Schultz, L.; Büchner, B.; Mühl, T. <lb/>New J. Phys. 2015, 17, 013014. doi:10.1088/1367-2630/17/1/013014 <lb/>22. van Honschoten, J. W.; Koelmans, W. W.; Koning, S. M.; <lb/>Abelmann, L.; Elwenspoek, M. In Proceedings of Eurosensors XXII, the <lb/>European Conference on Solid-State Transducers, 2008; pp 597 ff. <lb/>23. Gysin, U.; Rast, S.; Aste, A.; Speliotis, T.; Werle, C.; Meyer, E. <lb/>Nanotechnology 2011, 22, 285715. <lb/>doi:10.1088/0957-4484/22/28/285715 <lb/>24. Meyer, E.; Hug, H. J.; Bennewitz, R. Scanning Probe Microscopy, 1st <lb/>ed.; Springer: Heidelberg, Germany, 2004; p 92. <lb/>doi:10.1007/978-3-662-09801-1 <lb/>25. Giessibl, F. J. Rev. Mod. Phys. 2003, 75, 949. <lb/>doi:10.1103/revmodphys.75.949 <lb/>26. Majorana, E.; Ogawa, Y. Phys. Lett. A 1997, 233, 162. <lb/>doi:10.1016/S0375-9601(97)00458-1 <lb/>License and Terms <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>This is an Open Access article under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in <lb/>any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>The license is subject to the Beilstein Journal of <lb/>Nanotechnology terms and conditions: <lb/>(http://www.beilstein-journals.org/bjnano) <lb/>The definitive version of this article is the electronic one <lb/>which can be found at: <lb/>doi:10.3762/bjnano.7.96 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
