<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>EDITOR&apos;S PERSPECTIVE <lb/>Editor&apos;s note <lb/></front>

			<body>T <lb/>his is the fourth of five issues planned for JCHIMP <lb/>in volume 4, 2014. We are transitioning from four <lb/>issues annually in volumes 1Á3, to six issues start-<lb/>ing volume 5, beginning January 2015. The increased <lb/>frequency accommodates more manuscript efficiency, <lb/>decreasing publication wait times for accepted papers. <lb/>Volume 4, issue #5 will be published in late November <lb/>2014 and will include our fourth anniversary perspective. <lb/>In this issue there are 10 papers. Home institutions <lb/>for the authors are Reading (PA), Carillon (VA), Jersey <lb/>City (NJ), Des Moines (IA), Medstar Union Memorial <lb/>(MD), St. Francis (NJ), and Georgia Regents Univer-<lb/>sity//St. Mary&apos;s Hospital (GA). There is a very useful <lb/>medical student education research study on the applica-<lb/>tion of mobile technology in a university-affiliated com-<lb/>munity hospital (1). This should be very useful to faculty <lb/>and staff in community teaching hospitals Á the bread <lb/>and butter of JCHIMP&apos;s readership. There is an inter-<lb/>esting systematic review on the evidence of NSAID <lb/>efficacy in preventing altitude sickness (2). <lb/>Two papers (3, 4) report spontaneous coronary dissec-<lb/>tion: one paper enumerates a solitary case whereas the <lb/>other describes three cases: three of the four involved the <lb/>left anterior descending (LAD) and all were performed in <lb/>women. An unusual &apos;ground glass&apos; pulmonary nodule is <lb/>reported, and includes management standards compared <lb/>to the more common solid nodules (5). There are case <lb/>reports of a rare gelatinous bone marrow transformation <lb/>with an even more unusual successful nutritional treatment <lb/>(6), and a well-described case of symptomatic insulinoma <lb/>in a young woman (7). The mechanism of drug-induced <lb/>angioedema is reviewed in a unique case of Angiotensin II <lb/>Receptor Blocker (ARB)-induced visceral angioedema (8). <lb/>There are two interesting images: a radiology image <lb/>of an aspirated lithium battery (9) and an image of <lb/>phytodermatitis caused by exposure to a citrus fruit (10). <lb/></body>

			<front>Robert P. Ferguson, MD <lb/>Editor <lb/>Email: rferguson@gbmc.org <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Nuss MA, Hill JR, Cervero RM, Gaines JK, Middendorf BF. <lb/>Real-time use of the iPad by third-year medical students for <lb/>clinical decision support and learning: a mixed methods study. <lb/>J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; 4: 25184. <lb/>2. Pandit A, Karmacharya P, Pathak R, Giri S, Aryal MR. <lb/>Efficacy of NSAIDs for the prevention of acute mountain <lb/>sickness: a systematic review and meta-analysis. J Community <lb/>Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; 4: 24927. <lb/>3. Chevli P, Kelash F, Gadhvi P, Grandhi S, Syed A. Spontaneous <lb/>coronary artery dissection causing acute coronary syndrome in <lb/>a young patient without risk factors. J Community Hosp Intern <lb/>Med Perspect 2014; 4: 25104. <lb/>4. Telles Garcia NA, Khan AN, Boppana RC, Smith HL. <lb/>Spontaneous coronary artery dissection: a case series and liter-<lb/>ature review. J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; <lb/>4: 25261. <lb/>5. Sloane PJ. Evaluation of pure ground glass pulmonary nodule: <lb/>a case report. J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; <lb/>4: 24562. <lb/>6. Osgood E, Muddassir S, Jaju M, Moser R, Farid F, Mewada N. <lb/>Starvation marrow Á gelatinous transformation of bone marrow. <lb/>J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; 4: 24811. <lb/>7. Kelash F, Mulinda J. A rare cause of hypoglycemia in a young <lb/>female: insulinoma. J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect <lb/>2014; 4: 25093. <lb/>8. Thalanayar PM, Ghobrial I, Lubin F, Karnik R, Bhasin R. <lb/>Drug-induced visceral angioedema. J Community Hosp Intern <lb/>Med Perspect 2014; 4: 25260. <lb/>9. Bennett K, Supplee S, Vyas P, Gulati S, Alweis R. Surprising <lb/>cause of dysphagia in an elderly male. J Community Hosp <lb/>Intern Med Perspect 2014; 4: 25156. <lb/>10. Hankinson A, Lloyd B, Alweis R. Lime-induced phytophoto-<lb/>dermatitis. J Community Hosp Intern Med Perspect 2014; 4: <lb/>25090. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>JOURNAL OF COMMUNITY HOSPITAL <lb/>INTERNAL MEDICINE PERSPECTIVES <lb/>ae <lb/>Journal of Community Hospital Internal Medicine Perspectives 2014. # 2014 Robert P. Ferguson. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms <lb/>of the Creative Commons Attribution-Noncommercial 3.0 Unported License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/3.0/), permitting all non-<lb/>commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>1 <lb/>Citation: Journal of Community Hospital Internal Medicine Perspectives 2014, 4: 25955 -http://dx.doi.org/10.3402/jchimp.v4.25955 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">(page number not for citation purpose) </note>


	</text>
</tei>
