<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>C A S E R E P O R T <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Acute mercury poisoning presenting as fever of <lb/>unknown origin in an adult woman: a case report <lb/>Gonul Cicek-Senturk 1* , Fatma Aybala Altay 1 , Aysegul Ulu-Kilic 2 , Yunus Gurbuz 1 , Ediz Tutuncu 1 and Irfan Sencan 1 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Introduction: Mercury intoxication may present in a wide range of clinical forms from a simple disease to fatal <lb/>poisoning. This article presents a case of acute mercury poisoning, a rare condition that presents challenges for <lb/>diagnosis with fever of unknown origin. <lb/>Case presentation: A 52-year-old Caucasian woman was admitted to the hospital with high fever, sore throat, a <lb/>rash over her entire body, itching, nausea, and extensive muscle pain. She had cervical, bilateral axillary and mediastinal <lb/>lymphadenopathies. We learned that her son and husband had similar symptoms. After excluding infectious pathologies, <lb/>autoimmune diseases and malignancy were investigated. Multiple organs of our patient were involved and her fever <lb/>persisted at the fourth week of admission. A repeat medical history elicited that her son had brought mercury home <lb/>from school and put it on the hot stove, and the family had been exposed to the fumes for a long period of time. <lb/>Our patient&apos;s serum and urine mercury levels were high. She was diagnosed with mercury poisoning and treated <lb/>accordingly. <lb/>Conclusions: Mercury vapor is a colourless and odorless substance. Therefore, patients with various unexplained <lb/>symptoms and clinical conditions should be questioned about possible exposure to mercury. <lb/>Keywords: Fever of unknown origin, Mercury, Metal fume fever, Rash, Lymphadenopathy <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Disorders that result in classical fever of unknown origin <lb/>(FUO) fall into one of five categories: infections, neo-<lb/>plasms, connective tissue diseases, miscellaneous disorders, <lb/>and undiagnosed illnesses. Metal fume fever is included in <lb/>miscellaneous disorders [1]. The fumes or gases are a form <lb/>of several metals, for example cadmium (Cd), manganese <lb/>(Mn), mercury (Hg), and zinc chloride (ZnCl2). Metal <lb/>fume fever, which may occur after inhaling the metal <lb/>fumes, is a poorly understood influenza-like reaction [2]. <lb/>The clinical effects of mercury poisoning depend on the <lb/>form and the route of entry to the organism. Acute inhal-<lb/>ation of high vapor concentrations, usually from heated <lb/>elemental mercury, can result in acute lung injury with <lb/>symptoms of cough, sore throat, shortness of breath, and <lb/>chest pain. Other symptoms include fever, erythematous <lb/>rash, itching, chills, gastrointestinal complaints, metallic <lb/>taste, headache, and weakness [3]. <lb/>Case presentation <lb/>A 52-year-old Caucasian woman presented to a health-<lb/>care center with high fever, sore throat, itchy rash, gen-<lb/>eralized muscle pain, and nausea, which had continued <lb/>for 15 days. The patient&apos;s husband and son had similar <lb/>complaints over the same period. She was administered <lb/>Penicillin G, antihistaminic and antipyretic drugs. Because <lb/>her condition did not improve, she was referred to a <lb/>dermatology clinic with the suspicion of urticarial vascu-<lb/>litis. She received antihistaminic and depot steroid treat-<lb/>ment there and a consultation with the infectious diseases <lb/>department was requested. Her body temperature was <lb/>39°C (centigrade), her pulse rate was 96 beats/minute, and <lb/>respiratory rate was 22 breaths/minute at first examin-<lb/>ation. She had a generalized maculopapular rash spread <lb/>over her entire body, even the palms of her hands and the <lb/>soles of her feet. Our patient had bilateral cervical and ax-<lb/>illary painful and mobile lymphadenopathies. <lb/>Her laboratory test results were as follows; serum urea: <lb/>151mg/dL (normal range: 10 to 50mg/dL), serum creatinine: <lb/>2.6mg/dL (normal range: 0.6 to 1.1mg/dL), lactate dehydro-<lb/>genase (LDH): 608U/L (normal range: 207 to 414U/L), total <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: drgonulcicek@hotmail.com <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology, Dişkapi Yildirim <lb/>Beyazit, Training and Research Hospital, Ankara, Turkey <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/>JOURNAL OF MEDICAL <lb/>CASE REPORTS <lb/> © 2014 Cicek-Senturk et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the <lb/>Creative Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, <lb/>distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. <lb/>Cicek-Senturk et al. Journal of Medical Case Reports 2014, 8:266 <lb/>http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/8/1/266 <lb/></front>

			<body>protein: 5.8g/dL (normal range: 6.4 to 8.3g/dL), albumin: <lb/>2.7g/dL (normal range: 3.8 to 5.1g/dL), white blood cell <lb/>(WBC) count: 22,300/μL (normal range: 4300 to 10,300/ <lb/>μL), red blood cell (RBC) count: 4.02×106/μL (normal <lb/>range: 4.38 to 5.75×106/μL), hemoglobin: 12.4g/dL (nor-<lb/>mal range: 13.6 to 17.2g/dL), erythrocyte sedimentation <lb/>rate (ESR): 45mm/h, C-reactive protein (CRP): 52mg/L <lb/>(normal range: 0 to 5.0mg/L). <lb/>Abdominal ultrasonography (USG) revealed that hep-<lb/>atomegaly was present. All other intra-abdominal struc-<lb/>tures were normal. Her cervical USG revealed a large <lb/>number of reactive lymphadenopathies at submandibular, <lb/>submental, posterior cervical, upper and lower jugular re-<lb/>gions bilaterally and at the right and left submandibular <lb/>regions. Some of them were conglomerated. There were <lb/>also several reactive lymphadenopathies at both her axil-<lb/>lary regions, which were observed on the axillary ultrason-<lb/>ography. A thoracic computed tomography (CT) scan was <lb/>performed because our patient&apos;s chest radiography re-<lb/>vealed several uncertain nodular lesions. The thoracic CT <lb/>scan presented widespread areas of air trapping. Bilateral <lb/>multiple lymphadenopathies were present in the aortic <lb/>pulmonary, prevascular, precarinal, paratracheal, subcar-<lb/>inal and left supraclavicular regions. <lb/>Levofloxacin treatment was initiated empirically at the <lb/>dermatology clinic. On the fifth day, this treatment was <lb/>discontinued and our patient was transferred to the infec-<lb/>tious diseases clinic because there was no improvement in <lb/>her signs and symptoms. <lb/>Measles, Rubella, Epstein-Barr virus (EBV), Cytomegalo-<lb/>virus (CMV), Toxoplasma immunglobulin (Ig) M tests <lb/>were reported to be negative. The tests for Ricketsiosis, <lb/>Coxiellosis, Brucellosis and Tularemia were reported to be <lb/>negative. The autoimmune markers were studied to ex-<lb/>clude a rheumatologic disease and found to be negative. <lb/>On the twelfth day of admission, our patient&apos;s WBC <lb/>count increased to 35,000μL and her hemoglobin decreased <lb/>to 10.6g/dL (normal range: 13.6 to 17.2g/dL). Therefore, <lb/>our patient was referred to the hematologists. A total <lb/>of 45% polymorphonuclear leukocytes (PMN) (50% band <lb/>form), 40% lymphomonositer cells (50% atypical lympho-<lb/>cytes), and 11% eosinophils were identified in her peripheral <lb/>blood smear. Dysplasia was also present in neutrophils. A <lb/>bone marrow biopsy and tests were performed, yielding no <lb/>positive results. <lb/>Desquamation spread over her entire body (Figure 1), <lb/>an evident erythematous rash on her palms and soles, <lb/>dyspnea, chest pain and hypertension developed in the <lb/>following days. Kawasaki syndrome was suspected. Our <lb/>patient consulted with a chest diseases specialist and a <lb/>cardiologist. An electrocardiogram and echocardiogram <lb/>were performed and no cardiologic cause was found for <lb/>her symptoms. Bronchodilator and antihypertensive agents <lb/>were added to the treatment. <lb/>After insistent efforts of repeated medical history tak-<lb/>ing, we learned that the patient&apos;s son had brought mer-<lb/>cury home from school in a bottle and had spilled it on <lb/>the hot stove. All of the family members (mother, father <lb/>and son) were exposed to this environment of dense <lb/>mercury fumes for a long period of time. Because mercury <lb/>fumes are colorless and odorless, they were unable to detect <lb/>it. Approximately 10 hours after this event, our patient&apos;s <lb/>husband developed dyspnea, hypertension, tachycardia, <lb/>high fever and sore throat. He was admitted to the health-<lb/>care institution with these complaints. A physical examin-<lb/>ation of the patient revealed no pathological findings other <lb/>than hypertension (tension arterielle (TA): 160/100mmHg) <lb/>and erythema in the legs. His laboratory test results showed <lb/>leucocytosis (WBC count: 13,200/μL (normal range: 4300 <lb/>to 10300/μL)). Other laboratory findings were consid-<lb/>ered normal. His complaints improved with the support-<lb/>ive treatment administrated at the respiratory diseases <lb/>clinic of the hospital. He was discharged after eight days <lb/>of hospitalization, but a personality disorder developed in <lb/>the following days. <lb/>The 14-year-old son suffered from high fever, sore throat, <lb/>skin rash, diarrhea, and dyspnea. He was admitted to <lb/>the pediatric hospital with these complaints. A phys-<lb/>ical examination revealed the following: fever: 39°C, <lb/>TA: 110/50mmHg, respiratory rate: 20 breaths/minute, <lb/>Figure 1 Desquamation of the hands and feet of our patient. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cicek-Senturk et al. Journal of Medical Case Reports 2014, 8:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/8/1/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>pulse: 104 beats/minute. A generalized maculopapular <lb/>rash was spread over the patient&apos;s entire body, and he <lb/>was identified with hyperemia in the conjunctivas and <lb/>cervical and bilateral axillary lymphadenopathy. Rhon-<lb/>cuses were determined in the lungs by oscultation. No ab-<lb/>normal laboratory findings, other than leucocytosis (WBC <lb/>count: 11,100/μL (normal range: 4300 to 10,300/μL)) were <lb/>identified. The patient was initially given empirical doxy-<lb/>cycline and bronchodilator therapy based on the family <lb/>history. A thoracic CT scan was performed. Consolidation <lb/>areas containing air bronchograms were detected in the <lb/>paracardiac region in the right lung middle zone. Ceftriax-<lb/>one and clarithromycin were included in his treatment. <lb/>The tests performed revealed no findings of infection. Ma-<lb/>terial was submitted to the reference laboratory for blood <lb/>and urine mercury level tests upon persistent fever on day <lb/>10 of hospitalization. <lb/>The son&apos;s serum and urine mercury levels were ana-<lb/>lyzed using the inductively coupled plasma -mass spec-<lb/>trometer (ICP-MS) method in the reference laboratory. <lb/>His serum mercury level was 130μg/L (normal range: 0.6 <lb/>to 59μg/L), and his urine mercury level was 31μg/L (nor-<lb/>mal range: 0.1 to 20μg/L). He received chelating therapy <lb/>after high levels of mercury were identified in his blood. <lb/>Therefore, our patient&apos;s serum and urine mercury levels <lb/>were analyzed using the ICP-MS method in the refer-<lb/>ence laboratory. Her serum mercury level was 207μg/L <lb/>(normal range: 0.6 to 59μg/L), and her urine mercury <lb/>level was 524μg/L (normal range: 0.1 to 20μg/L). <lb/>The diagnosis of mercury intoxication was also corrobo-<lb/>rated by the consulted toxicologist. The toxicologist rec-<lb/>ommended the administration of penicillamine instead of <lb/>dimercaprol as our patient recovered from the acute <lb/>period. A dosage of 300mg of penicillamine every six hours <lb/>was administered for seven days. Her clinical and labora-<lb/>tory test results were significantly improved by the treat-<lb/>ment. No side effects of penicillamine were seen and our <lb/>patient was discharged. <lb/>Her husband&apos;s serum mercury level was 197μg/L (nor-<lb/>mal range 0.6 to 59μg/L), and his urine mercury level was <lb/>412μg/L (normal range 0.1 to 20μg/L). Therefore, he re-<lb/>ceived the same treatment as his wife. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>As a vapor, elemental mercury is absorbed rapidly through <lb/>the lungs, reaching the blood and entering the brain. A <lb/>clinical picture, which can be divided into three phases, <lb/>evolves. The initial phase manifests itself as metal fume <lb/>fever, the intermediate phase can be defined as the period <lb/>during which severe, multiorgan symptoms of the central <lb/>nervous, respiratory tract, gastrointestinal and urological <lb/>systems are reported, and the late phase can be described <lb/>as the period when the central nervous symptoms persist <lb/>and other organ system complaints are resolved. The <lb/>description of the earliest symptoms by the patients is con-<lb/>sistent with metal fume fever, a syndrome commonly con-<lb/>fused with a viral etiology, as was also true for these <lb/>patients [4]. Our patient had also high fever, lymphadenop-<lb/>athy, and a diffuse maculopapular rash initially. Her liver <lb/>and kidney function tests were elevated; she had dyspnea, <lb/>tachycardia and chest pain during the following days. <lb/>The exact pathogenesis of metal fume fever is poorly <lb/>understood. In some instances, allergic mechanisms may <lb/>be involved [2]. Our case confirms mechanisms of <lb/>hypersensitivity because she was diagnosed with urticarial <lb/>vacuities initially and had eosinophilia in her blood smear. <lb/>Because either our patient or the other family members <lb/>had similar signs such as fever, diffuse skin rash and mul-<lb/>tiple lymphadenopathies predominantly, an infectious <lb/>process was considered initially. Viral, bacterial infections, <lb/>autoimmune diseases, malignancies and Kawasaki syn-<lb/>drome were evaluated in the differential diagnosis, but <lb/>there were no findings to confirm these conditions. <lb/>Kawasaki syndrome is rarely seen in the adult popula-<lb/>tion since it is primarily a disease of childhood. It can be <lb/>seen as sporadic cases and in mini-epidemics [5]. It was <lb/>reported previously that mercury intoxication had pre-<lb/>sented with elevated urine mercury levels compared to <lb/>those of the matched controls [6]. <lb/>Acrodinia (&apos;pink disease&apos;) is a unique syndrome that can <lb/>occur in children from chronic exposure to elemental mer-<lb/>cury. Only a certain subset of exposed patients is affected, <lb/>suggesting that it represents an idiosyncratic hypersensitiv-<lb/>ity response. Clinical manifestations include extremity pain, <lb/>red face, red hands and feet, skin rash, gingivitis, desquam-<lb/>ation, tachycardia, hypertension, photophobia and irritabil-<lb/>ity [3,7]. Our patient had rash, significantly erythematous <lb/>on her soles and palms; and developed desquamation, <lb/>muscle pain and hypertension during the following days. <lb/>We described this clinical presentation as idiosyncratic <lb/>hypersensitivity due to mercury intoxication. <lb/>Elemental mercury is used in manufacturing and indus-<lb/>trial processes (mining, smelting), household, medical and <lb/>electrical devices (for example, thermometers, thermostats, <lb/>electrical switches, dental amalgam), and in folk remedies. <lb/>Thus, environmental release of elemental mercury that re-<lb/>sults in human exposure can occur in many different loca-<lb/>tions [8]. Sarıkaya et al. reported a case of acute elemental <lb/>mercury poisoning that they followed presenting with ab-<lb/>dominal pain, diarrhea and high fever. The patient&apos;s daugh-<lb/>ter had brought mercury home from school and heated <lb/>it. One day after the event, the patient&apos;s 14-month-old <lb/>daughter died of mercury poisoning [9]. Seen from this as-<lb/>pect, mercury should be kept under safer conditions and <lb/>whether it should continue to be held in schools should <lb/>be discussed. <lb/>Rowens et al. reported that four people from the same <lb/>family died as a result of respiratory failure caused by <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Cicek-Senturk et al. Journal of Medical Case Reports 2014, 8:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/8/1/266 <lb/></note>

			<body>heated elemental mercury [10]. Glezos et al. reported a <lb/>patient that was hospitalized and followed up for seven <lb/>days because of high fever, pneumonia, generalized <lb/>maculopapular rash, and axillary lymphadenopathy, and <lb/>it was learned one week after discharge that he had been <lb/>present in an environment in which mercury had been <lb/>heated for three hours [11]. Bamonti et al. reported that <lb/>cracked mercury dental amalgam was a possible cause of <lb/>fever of unknown origin [12]. The patients do not realize <lb/>that they have been exposed to the mercury vapor be-<lb/>cause it is colorless and odorless. Therefore, patients <lb/>with such symptoms should be questioned about pos-<lb/>sible exposure to mercury. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>Environmental release of elemental mercury that results in <lb/>human exposure can occur in many different locations <lb/>such as schools, universities, homes, healthcare facilities, <lb/>public utilities and manufacturing facilities. Thus, although <lb/>it is rarely seen, patients should be questioned about being <lb/>exposed to mercury or other metals when a case of fever <lb/>of unknown origin is encountered. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Consent <lb/>Written informed consent was obtained from the patients <lb/>for publication of this manuscript and any accompanying <lb/>images. A copy of the written consent is available for re-<lb/>view by the Editor-in-Chief of this journal. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>CRP: C-reactive protein; Cd: cadmium;°C: Centigrade; CT: computed <lb/>tomography; CMV: Cytomegalovirus; EBV: Epstein-Barr virus; ESR: erythrocyte <lb/>sedimentation rate; FUO: fever of unknown origin; Hg: mercury; <lb/>Ig: immunoglobulin; ICP-MS: inductively coupled lasma -mass spectrometer; <lb/>LDH: lactate dehydrogenase; Mn: manganese; RBC: red blood cell; <lb/>TA: tension arterielle; USG: ultrasonography; WBC: white blood cell; <lb/>ZnCl2: zinc chloride. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>GCS was involved in the conception of the report, literature review, <lb/>manuscript preparation, editing and submission. FAA, AUK, YG, ET and IS <lb/>were responsible for the manuscript critique and review. All authors have <lb/>read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors have no disclosures to make and have had no source of <lb/>funding in the preparation of this manuscript. We would like to thank our <lb/>patient for being so willing to share her experience with the medical <lb/>community. <lb/></div>
			
			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology, Dişkapi Yildirim <lb/>Beyazit, Training and Research Hospital, Ankara, Turkey. 2 Department of <lb/>Infectious Diseases and Clinical Microbiology, Erciyes University School of <lb/>Medicine, Kayseri, Turkey. <lb/>Received: 3 July 2013 Accepted: 19 May 2014 <lb/>Published: 1 August 2014 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Mackowiak PA, Durack DT: Fever of unknown origin. In Principles and <lb/>Practice of Infectious Diseases: Volume 1. 7th edition. Edited by Mandell GL, <lb/>Bennett JE, Dolin R. Philadelphia: Churchill Livingstone; 2010:779-789. <lb/>2. Nemery B: Metal toxicity and the respiratory tract. Eur Respir J 1990, <lb/>3:202-219. <lb/>3. Caravati EM, Erdman AR, Christianson G, Nelson LS, Woolf AD, Booze LL, <lb/>Cobaugh DJ, Chyka PA, Scharman EJ, Manoguerra AS, Troutman WG: <lb/>Elemental mercury exposure: an evidence-based consensus guideline for <lb/>out-of-hospital management. Clin Toxicol (Phila) 2008, 46:1-21. <lb/>4. Bluhm RE, Bobbitt RG, Welch LW, Wood AJJ, Bonfiglio JF, Sarzen C, Heath <lb/>AJ, Branch A: Elemental mercury vapour toxicity, treatment, and <lb/>prognosis after acute, intensive exposure in chloralkali plant workers. <lb/>Part I: history, neuropsychological findings and chelator effects. Hum Exp <lb/>Toxicol 1992, 11:201-210. <lb/>5. Saulsbury FT: Kawasaki syndrome. In Principles and Practice of Infectious <lb/>Diseases. Volume 2. 6th edition. Edited by Mandell GL, Bennett JE, Dolin R, <lb/>Mandell GL, Bennett JE, Dolin R. Philadelphia: Churchill Livingstone; <lb/>2005:3316-3319. <lb/>6. Mutter J, Yeter D: Kawasaki&apos;s disease, acrodynia, and mercury. Curr Med <lb/>Chem 2008, 15:3000-3010. <lb/>7. Boyd AS, Seger D, Vannucci S, Langley M, Abraham JL, King LE Jr: Mercury <lb/>exposure and cutaneous disease. J Am Acad Dermatol 2000, 43:81-90. <lb/>8. Zeitz P, Orr M, Kaye W: Public health consequences of mercury spills: <lb/>hazardous substances emergency events surveillance system, 1993-1998. <lb/>Environ Health Perspect 2002, 110:129-132. <lb/>9. Sarikaya S, Karcioglu O, Ay D, Cetin A, Aktas C, Serinken M: Acute mercury <lb/>poisoning: a case report. BMC Emerg Med 2010, 10:7. <lb/>10. Rowens B, Guerrero-Betancourt D, Gottlieb CA, Eichenhorn MS: Respiratory <lb/>failure and death following acute inhalation of mercury vapor: a clinical <lb/>and histologic perspective. Chest 1991, 99:185-190. <lb/>11. Glezos JD, Albrech JE, Gair RD: Pneumonitis after inhalation of mercury <lb/>vapours. Can Respir J 2006, 13:150-152. <lb/>12. Bamonti F, Guzzi G, Ferrero ME: Cracked mercury dental amalgam as a <lb/>possible cause of fever of unknown origin: a case report. J Med Case Rep <lb/>2008, 2:72. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">doi:10.1186/1752-1947-8-266 <lb/>Cite this article as: Cicek-Senturk et al.: Acute mercury poisoning <lb/>presenting as fever of unknown origin in an adult woman: a case <lb/>report. Journal of Medical Case Reports 8:266. <lb/>Submit your next manuscript to BioMed Central <lb/>and take full advantage of: <lb/>• Convenient online submission <lb/>• Thorough peer review <lb/>• No space constraints or color figure charges <lb/>• Immediate publication on acceptance <lb/>• Inclusion in PubMed, CAS, Scopus and Google Scholar <lb/>• Research which is freely available for redistribution <lb/>Submit your manuscript at <lb/>www.biomedcentral.com/submit <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Cicek-Senturk et al. Journal of Medical Case Reports 2014, 8:266 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.jmedicalcasereports.com/content/8/1/266 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
