<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>R E S E A R C H <lb/>Open Access <lb/>MTA1 promotes metastasis of MPM via <lb/>suppression of E-cadherin <lb/>Caihua Xu, Fei Hua, Yihuan Chen, Haoyue Huang, Wenxue Ye, Yunsheng Yu and Zhenya Shen * <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Metastasis-associated gene 1(MTA1) has been identified as an oncogene in many tumors, and <lb/>aberrant MTA1 expression has been linked to carcinogenesis and metastasis. We aim to investigate the mechanism <lb/>of MTA1 and metastasis in malignant pleural mesothelioma (MPM). <lb/>Methods: Real-time polymerase chain reaction (PCR) and immunohistochemical staining were employed to detect <lb/>MTA1 and E-cadherin expression in MPM tissues and corresponding adjacent tissues. Stable clone with knock-down <lb/>of MTA1 was generated with shRNA via lentivirus technology in MPM cell lines. Wound-healing assay, transwell <lb/>assay and PCR array were carried out for detecting invasion and migration of MPM cells. Luciferase reporter assay <lb/>was performed to validate the effect of MTA1 on E-cadherin. <lb/>Results: MTA1 expression is up-regulated in MPM and shown a negative correlation with E-cadherin expression. <lb/>MTA1 could enhance the invasion and migration of MPM cells via suppressing the expression of E-cadherin. MTA1 <lb/>overexpression is associated with pathology, metastasis and survival rate of MPM patients. <lb/>Conclusions: MTA1 plays an important role in Epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT) to promote metastasis via <lb/>suppressing E-cadherin expression, resulting in a poor prognosis in MPM. MTA1 is a novel biomarker and indicative <lb/>of a poor prognosis in MPM patients. <lb/>Keywords: MTA1, E-cadherin, Malignant pleural mesothelioma, Metastasis <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>Malignant pleural mesothelioma (MPM) is considered as <lb/>one of the highest aggressive tumor arising from the cells <lb/>lining serosal cavities, mostly resulting from the occupa-<lb/>tional exposure to asbestos fibers [1]. Although great ef-<lb/>forts have been made toward improving diagnosis and <lb/>treatment [2], there are no efficacious therapies for MPM <lb/>patients presently, and therefore the overall survival is ex-<lb/>tremely poor. Thus, the investigation of developing the <lb/>novel therapeutics, especially molecular targeting therapy, <lb/>is very important for the patients with MPM. <lb/>MTA (metastasis-associated gene) is a newly discovered <lb/>family of cancer progression-related genes and their <lb/>encoded products. MTA are integral parts of nucleosome <lb/>remodeling and histone deacetylation (NuRD) complexes, <lb/>function as transcriptional co-repressors which regulate <lb/>varieties pathways, including hormonal action, epithelial-<lb/>to-mesenchymal transitions, differentiations, protein sta-<lb/>bility and development [3, 4]. MTA1, the first gene found <lb/>in this family, has been repeatedly reported to be overex-<lb/>pressed along with its protein product MTA1 in a wide <lb/>range of human cancers such as endometrial adenocarcin-<lb/>omas, gastrointestinal carcinoids, colorectal carcinomas, <lb/>hepatocellular carcinomas and non-small cell lung cancers <lb/>[5-10]. However, the potential prognostic relevance of <lb/>MTA1 expression in MPM has not yet been investigated. <lb/>In this study, we aim to investigate the role of MTA1 <lb/>in the pathogenesis of MPM and identify MTA1 could <lb/>promote the metastasis of MPM cells by repressing the <lb/>expression of E-cadherin. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Patients and tissue samples <lb/>MPM and corresponding adjacent tissues employed in this <lb/>study were obtained from 65 consecutive patients who <lb/>had de novo disease and undergone surgical resection. <lb/></body>

			<front>* Correspondence: uuzyshen@126.com <lb/>Department of Cardiovascular Surgery of the First Affiliated Hospital and <lb/>Institute for Cardiovascular Science, Soochow University, Suzhou 215000, <lb/>China <lb/> © 2015 Xu et al. Open Access This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to <lb/>the Creative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The Creative Commons Public Domain Dedication waiver <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, unless otherwise stated. <lb/> Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/>DOI 10.1186/s13046-015-0269-8 <lb/></front>

			<body>They were included between December 2008 and <lb/>November 2013 at the First Affiliated Hospital of <lb/>Soochow University (Suzhou, China) and the First <lb/>Affiliated Hospital of Nanjing Medical University (Nanjing, <lb/>China). The patients were followed up for a median period <lb/>of 12 months (range, 3-28 months) after operation and <lb/>their complete clinical data were collected. The correct <lb/>diagnosis was assessed by an experienced pathologist and <lb/>the staging of MPM by a clinical oncologist according to <lb/>AJCC/UICC Guidelines version 7.2010 MPM. Adjacent tis-<lb/>sue was located within 3 cm of the edge of the tumor tissue <lb/>(Additional file 1: Fig. 1S). The study was approved by the <lb/>Ethical Committee of the First Affiliated Hospital of <lb/>Soochow University (Suzhou, China) and the First Affiliated <lb/>Hospital of Nanjing Medical University (Nanjing, China), <lb/>and written informed consent was obtained from the each <lb/>patient. <lb/>DNA and RNA preparation <lb/>Total RNA was extracted from fresh frozen tissue speci-<lb/>mens using TRIzol method (Invitrogen, Shanghai, China) <lb/>and RNA quality was detected by NanoDrop 2000 and <lb/>A260/A280 was between 1.95 and 2.05. cDNA was syn-<lb/>thesized using reverse transcriptase kit (TAKARA, Tokyo, <lb/>Japan) according to the manufacturers&apos; protocol. <lb/>Real-time PCR analysis <lb/>MTA1 and E-cadherin mRNA levels were measured by <lb/>real-time PCR using SYBR Premix Ex Taq (TAKARA, <lb/>Tokyo, Japan). MTA1 and E-cadherin transcription <lb/>values were normalized against the expression of β-<lb/>actin. Amplification conditions, primers, and probes se-<lb/>quences for MTA1 and β-actin were from the work by <lb/>Zhu X et al. [9] and for E-cadherin were the same as <lb/>those in the work by Martínez-Estrada et al. [11]. All <lb/>procedures are in agreement with MIQE guidelines. <lb/>Cell culture <lb/>MSTO-211H, NCI-H2452 and 293 T cell lines (ATCC, <lb/>Manassas, VA) were employed for the present study. <lb/>MSTO-211H and H2452 were origin from the patients <lb/>with mesothelioma and cultured in RPMI 1640 medium <lb/>supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine serum (Invitrogen, <lb/>Carlsbad, CA), while 293 T were origin from human em-<lb/>bryonic kidney cells and cultured in DMEM high glu-<lb/>cose medium supplemented with 10 % fetal bovine <lb/>serum. All cells were maintained in a humidified 37°C <lb/>incubator with 5 % CO 2 . <lb/>Lentivirus production and transduction <lb/>To generate plasmid-expressing MTA1-shRNA, double-<lb/>stranded oligonucleotides were cloned into pLL3.7 vec-<lb/>tor (gifted by D. Yun Chen, Nanjing Medical University, <lb/>China) and named pLL3.7-shMTA1. The sequences of <lb/>MTA1-shRNA used are ccggtGACCACCGACAGATAC <lb/>GTG ttcaagaga CACGTATCTGTCGGTGGTCTTTTT <lb/>Tg. The uppercase letters represent MTA1-specific se-<lb/>quence, and lowercase letters represent hairpin sequences. <lb/>Recombinant lentivirus was generated from 293 T cells <lb/>using calcium phosphate precipitation. MSTO-211H and <lb/>H2452 were transfected with lentivirus using polybrene <lb/>(8 μg/ml). <lb/>Western-blotting assay <lb/>Proteins were extracted from cultured cells, quantitated <lb/>using a protein assay (bicinchoninic acid [BCA] method; <lb/>Beyotime, Shanghai, China). Proteins were fractionated <lb/>by sodium dodecyl sulfate polyacrylamide gel electrophor-<lb/>esis, transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride (PVDF) mem-<lb/>brane, blocked in 4 % dry milk at room temperature for <lb/>1 hour, and immunostained with primary antibodies at 4°C <lb/>over-night using anti-MTA1 (1:2000, Abcam, Cambridge, <lb/>MA), anti-E-cadherin (1:1000; Abcam, Cambridge, MA), <lb/>and anti-GAPDH (1:1000, Kangchen,China). The results <lb/>were visualized via a chemiluminescent detection system <lb/>(Pierce ECL Substrate Western blot detection system; <lb/>Thermo, Rockford, IL) and exposed in Molecular Imager <lb/>ChemiDoc XRS System (Bio-Rad, Hercules, CA). <lb/>Cell proliferation assay <lb/>Cells were seeded into 96-well plates (6.0 × 10 cells per <lb/>well). Cell viability was assessed by cell-counting kit-8 <lb/>assay (CCK-8, Beyotime, Shanghai, China). The absorb-<lb/>ance of each well was read on a spectrophotometer <lb/>(Thermo) at 450 nm (A450). Five independent experi-<lb/>ments were performed in quintuplicate. <lb/>Wound-healing assay <lb/>Cells were seeded in six-well plates and cultured to con-<lb/>fluence. Wounds of 2-mm width were created with a <lb/>plastic scriber and the floating cells were washed away <lb/>thrice with phosphate buffered saline (PBS). After incu-<lb/>bation in a serum-free medium for 48 hours, cultures <lb/>were observed and photos were taken under a micro-<lb/>scope. A minimum of five randomly chosen areas was <lb/>measured. <lb/>Transwell invasion assay <lb/>The invasive ability of the cells was investigated using <lb/>Transwells (8-μm pore size; Corning Costar Corp, Bedford, <lb/>MA) put into the 24-well plates. First, 50 μl Matrigel <lb/>(50 μg/ml; BD Biosciences, San Jose, CA) was added onto <lb/>each surface of the chamber, incubated for 2 hours for so-<lb/>lidification, then the supernatant was washed away with <lb/>warm PBS. MSTO-211H and H2452 were suspended in <lb/>RPMI 1640 containing 2 % fetal bovine serum. A total of <lb/>μl of the cell suspension (5 × 10 cells) was added to <lb/>the upper chamber coated with Matrigel, and 400 μl of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>RPMI 1640 containing 10 % fetal bovine serum was added <lb/>to the lower compartment. After incubation for 48 hours at <lb/>37°C in a 5 % CO 2 humidified incubator, the Matrigel and <lb/>cells on the upper surface of the filter were removed with <lb/>cotton swabs and the cells that invaded into the lower sur-<lb/>face were fixed with 2 % paraformaldehyde, stained with <lb/>crystal violet. Then the filters were removed from the <lb/>chambers, air-dried on the precleaned slides and applied <lb/>with cover-slides using resina. Images were taken under <lb/>an inverted microscope (Olympus Corp, Tokyo, Japan) <lb/>at × 100 magnifications over three random fields in each <lb/>well. ImageJ 1.45 s software (National Insititutes of Health, <lb/>Bethesda, MD) was used for integrated optical density <lb/>analysis. Each experiment was performed in triplicate. <lb/>RT-PCR array <lb/>Total RNA was extracted from MSTO-211H, MSTO-<lb/>211H-shMTA1, H2452 and H2452-shMTA and reverse <lb/>transcribed to cDNA. Subsequently, cDNA was amplified <lb/>by PCR using 23 Super Array PCR master mix (SuperArray <lb/>Bioscience, Frederick, MD) and then RT-PCR was carried <lb/>out using the Human Tumor Metastasis RT2 Profiler PCR <lb/>array (SuperArray Bioscience, Frederick, MD) in an ABI <lb/>PRISM7900 system (Applied Biosystems, Foster City, CA), <lb/>according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Luciferase report assay <lb/>The promoter of E-cadherin was synthesized artificially <lb/>and cloned into the luciferase reporter vector (Promega, <lb/>Madison, WI). MSTO-211H and H2452 cells were seeded <lb/>into 24-well plates and cotransfected with MTA1-siRNA <lb/>(pooled siGENOME SMART pool MTA1 siRNA [50 nM <lb/>per well]; Dhamacon, Chicago, IL), and luciferase reporter <lb/>vectors using Lipofectamine 2000 (Invitrogen, Carlsbad, <lb/>CA), following the instructions. Zero, 12 and 24 hours <lb/>after incubation, cells were collected and firefly and <lb/>Renilla luciferase activity was measured with the dual-<lb/>luciferase reporter assay system (Promega). All results <lb/>were gained through three independent experiments. <lb/>TGF-β1 Inducing EMT of MPM cells <lb/>The MPM cells were cultured in vitro and induced by <lb/>transforming growth fact beta1 (TGF-β1, 5 ng/ml) for <lb/>0 h, 24 h, 48 h. The morphological characteristics of <lb/>cells were observed by microscope (Olympus Corp, <lb/>Tokyo, Japan) and the expression of MTA1 was detected <lb/>by real-time PCR. <lb/>Immunohistochemical staining <lb/>Tissues were fixed in 4 % paraformaldehyde and cut <lb/>from paraffin block to 5 μm thickness. After dewaxing <lb/>with xylene and rehydration with a graded series of etha-<lb/>nol, the slides were heated in the autoclave for three <lb/>minutes using citrate buffer (PH 6.0) and incubated with <lb/>primary antibody MTA1 (1:1000, Abcam, Cambridge, <lb/>MA), E-cadherin (1:1000; Abcam, Cambridge, MA) at <lb/>4°C overnight. Blocking serum or antibody dilution buf-<lb/>fer was prepared as Negative controls. The primary anti-<lb/>bodies utilized were all the same as for Western blot <lb/>analysis. Photographs were taken by microscope (Nikon, <lb/>ECLIPSE 50i) and software NIS-Elements v4.0. Average <lb/>values of integrated optical density (IOD) were obtained <lb/>from five random fields per slide by using Image-Pro <lb/>Plus software (v5.0). Every data was detected three times <lb/>at least. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed using GraphPad Prism <lb/>(version 5.01; GraphPad Software, Inc, La Jolla, CA) stat-<lb/>istical software. The Student&apos;s t test and paired t test <lb/>were used to analyze significance between independent <lb/>groups and paired materials, respectively. The correl-<lb/>ation test was used to analyze the correlation between <lb/>MTA1 and E-cadherin. The χ 2 test was used to test the <lb/>significance of observed differences in proportions ex-<lb/>cept when the cells size was less than 5 (Fisher&apos;s exact <lb/>tests). The significance was accepted as p value was less <lb/>than 0.05. <lb/>Results <lb/>MTA1 expression is up-regulated in MPM and shown a <lb/>negative correlation with E-cadherin expression <lb/>We investigated 65 pairs of MPM and corresponding <lb/>adjacent specimens using real-time PCR and immuno-<lb/>histochemistry. MTA1 RNA level in MPM was signifi-<lb/>cantly higher compared to adjacent tissues (p &lt; 0.0001; <lb/>Fig.1a). However, E-cadherin RNA level was just con-<lb/>trary (p &lt; 0.0001; Fig.1b). Moreover, a negative correl-<lb/>ation was observed between MTA1 and E-cadherin <lb/>expression in MPM samples (r = − 0.6250; p &lt; 0.0001; <lb/>Fig. 1c). To further evaluate the correlation between <lb/>MTA1 and E-cadherin expression, two cases with differ-<lb/>ent MTA1 expression levels are shown in Fig. 1d: CASE <lb/>(strong positive) and CASE 2 (weak positive). The <lb/>level of E-cadherin was down-regulated in CASE 1 com-<lb/>pared to CASE 2. Additionally, statistical analysis of <lb/>IOD values stained with E-cadherin in MTA1-high <lb/>group and MTA1-low group are shown in the histogram <lb/>in Fig. 1e and f (p &lt; 0.0001). The results suggested that <lb/>MTA1 expression was up-regulated and negatively cor-<lb/>related to E-cadherin expression in MPM. <lb/>MTA1 could enhance the invasion and migration of MPM <lb/>cells in vitro <lb/>In vitro, both two MPM cell lines (MSTO-211H and <lb/>H2452) were transduced by pLL3.7-shMTA1 and de-<lb/>tected the expression of MTA1 by real-time PCR and <lb/>Western-blot (Fig. 2a, b, and c). These results indicated <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 1 Expression and correlation of MTA1 and E-cadherin transcripts in MPM patients. a Significantly higher RNA expression of MTA1 in tumor <lb/>specimens than in the adjacent tissue samples (p &lt; 0.001). b Significantly decreased RNA expression of E-cadherin in tumor specimens in comparison with <lb/>adjacent tissues (p &lt; 0.001). c A negative correlation between MTA1 and E-cadherin in tumor samples (r = −0.5482, p &lt; 0.0001). d Immunohistochemical <lb/>staining of E-cadherin in MTA1 overexpression tumor tissue (CASE 1) and MTA1 low expression tumor tissue (CASE 2) in vivo. Data are represented as <lb/>mean ± SD. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.001. e and f Average value of integrated optical density (IOD) of E-cadherin in MTA1-high group and MTA1-low group were <lb/>assessed by analyzing five fields per slide and recorded in the histogram. MTA1, metastasis-associated gene 1; MPM, malignant pleural mesothelioma <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2 (See legend on next page.) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>expression of MTA1 was significantly reduced by the <lb/>lentivirus. As illustrated, the invasion and migration abil-<lb/>ities of both MSTO-211H and H2452 were evidently <lb/>suppressed when MTA1 was down-regulated by pLL3.7-<lb/>shMTA1 (Fig. 2d, f, h and i). And the quantification of <lb/>the invasion abilities of MSTO-211H and H2452 are <lb/>presented in Fig. 2e and g corresponding with Fig. 2d <lb/>and f. Moreover, We found that MTA1 silencing could <lb/>not affect cell proliferation (Fig. 2j and k). <lb/>MTA1 knockdown induces increase of E-cadherin <lb/>expression in MPM cells <lb/>A variety of EMT genes were screened out after MTA1 <lb/>down-regulation via the PCR array and nine genes <lb/>whose variation larger than two folds were picked. Then <lb/>we verified the expression of these nine genes in 65 sam-<lb/>ples by real-time PCR. We found E-cadherin was up-<lb/>regulated most after MTA1 silenced in both MSTO-211H <lb/>and H2452 (Fig. 3a and b). In order to confirm the nega-<lb/>tive regulatory effect of MTA1 on E-cadherin, we also de-<lb/>tected the E-cadherin protein in both two cells by <lb/>Western-blot. As shown in Fig. 3c, E-cadherin protein ex-<lb/>pression was increased significantly in both two cells <lb/>transduced by pLL3.7-shMTA1. Subsequently, we per-<lb/>formed luciferase report assay in MSTO-211H and H2452 <lb/>transfected with MTA1-siRNA and the luciferase activity <lb/>of E-cadherin was enhanced significantly with transfection <lb/>time increases (Fig. 3d and e). Moreover, we found the <lb/>mRNA expression of MTA1 was up-regulated in TGF-β1-<lb/>stimulated MPM cells (Fig 3f) which was according with <lb/>the result of Suresh B et al. [12]. Taken together, these <lb/>findings suggest that the decreased expression of MTA1 <lb/>could enhance E-cadherin expression in MPM cells. <lb/>MTA1 overexpression is associated with a poor prognosis <lb/>of MPM <lb/>A total of 65 MPM tissues were divided into two <lb/>groups using a semiquantitative immunoreactivity scor-<lb/>ing system (IRS), as reported elsewhere [9, 10, 13, 14]. <lb/>Concomitant cytoplasmicstaining was not counted. Cat-<lb/>egory A documented the intensity of immunostaining as 0 <lb/>(no immunostaining), 1(weak immunostaining), 2 (moder-<lb/>ate immunostaining), and 3 (strong immunostaining). <lb/>Category B documented the percentage of immunoreac-<lb/>tive cells as (none), 1 (&lt;10 %), 2(10-50 %), 3 (51-80 %), <lb/>and 4 (80 %). Multiplication of categories A and B resulted <lb/>in an IRS ranging from 0 to 12 (negative [IRS, 0] versus <lb/>weak [IRS, 1-4] versus moderate [IRS, 5-8] versus strong <lb/>[IRS, 9-12]) for each tumor. Both percent positivity of <lb/>cells and staining intensity were decidedin a double-<lb/>blinded manner. Interobserver and intraobserver variabil-<lb/>ity was negligible. Tumors with moderate or strong ex-<lb/>pression (IRS 4) were considered to show MTA1 <lb/>overexpression, whereas tumors with negative or weak ex-<lb/>pression (IRS &lt; 4) were considered to show MTA1 down-<lb/>expression. The relationship of MTA1 expression levels <lb/>and clinicopathological features were shown in Table 1. <lb/>Significant higher TNM stage (p &lt; 0.01), metastasis (lymph <lb/>node metastasis and distant metastasis, p &lt; 0.01) were ob-<lb/>served in high-MTA1 expression group. We also found <lb/>MTA1 level in sarcomatoid and biphasic malignant me-<lb/>sotheliomas were higher than the level in epithelioid ma-<lb/>lignant mesothelioma (p &lt; 0.05). There was no correlation <lb/>between MTA1 expression level and sex, age, as shown in <lb/>Table 1. Additionally, our findings indicated that MPM <lb/>patients with a high expression level of MTA1 had a sig-<lb/>nificantly shorter overall survival compared with pa-<lb/>tients with a low expression level of MTA1 and <lb/>10 months median survival compared with 19 months <lb/>median survival after operation (p &lt; 0.01, Fig. 3g). <lb/>These results strongly indicate that MTA1 overexpres-<lb/>sion contribute to the poor prognosis of MPM patients. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Malignant pleural mesothelioma (MPM), one of the most <lb/>deadly human carcinomas, is an aggressive tumor which <lb/>originates from the mesothelial cells of serosal tissues [15]. <lb/>Metastasis is the major cause of treatment failure in pa-<lb/>tients with MPM and its molecular mechanisms are still <lb/>not clear and are under intensive investigation. To eluci-<lb/>date the mechanisms of metastasis is essential for improv-<lb/>ing surgery and treatment outcome, especially for <lb/>selecting and customizing chemotherapy. <lb/>In this study, for the first time, we reported that MTA1 <lb/>gene and protein in MPM specimens was markedly up-<lb/>regulated compared to adjacent tissues, and MTA1 could <lb/>(See figure on previous page.) <lb/>Fig. 2 MTA1 enhances the invasion and migration in MPM cells. a and b MTA1 level of MPM wild-type cells (MSTO-211H and H2452) and MPM <lb/>cells transfected by lentivirus containing pLL3.7-empty and pLL3.7-shMTA1 by real-time PCR. c MTA1 expression of MPM wild-type cells (MSTO-211H <lb/>and H2452) and MPM cells transfected by lentivirus containing pLL3.7-empty and pLL3.7-shMTA1 by western-blot. d and e The result of transwell assay <lb/>showed that the invasion ability of MSTO-211H was significantly suppressed after MTA1 silencing, which was confirmed by integrated optical density <lb/>(IOD) value evaluation. f and g Similar effect of MTA1 was observed in H2452 MPM cells. h and i The result of wound-healing assay showed that the <lb/>migration ability of MPM cells was restrained after MTA1 silencing at 48 h time point. Data are represented as mean ± SD. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.001. <lb/>j and k, The viability of MPM wild-type cells (MSTO-211H and H2452) and MPM cells transfected by lentivirus containing pLL3.7-shMTA1 were <lb/>assessed by CCK-8 assay at 0 h, 24 h, 36 h and 48 h time point. MTA1, metastasis-associated gene 1; MPM, malignant pleural mesothelioma; <lb/>PCR, polymerase chain reaction; CCK-8, cell-counting kit 8 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 3 (See legend on next page.) <lb/>Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></body>

			<page>Page 7 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<body>enhance the metastasis of MPM cells by direct regulation <lb/>of E-cadherin. Additionally, the relationship of MTA1 <lb/>level and clinicopathological features in Table 1 sug-<lb/>gests that MTA1 overexpression was associated with <lb/>the poor prognosis of MPM patients. With all findings <lb/>taken together, we hypothesized that MTA1 potentially <lb/>play an oncogenic role in promoting metastasis of <lb/>MPM. <lb/>MTA1 has been considered to be related with the <lb/>poor prognosis due to increase the migration and in-<lb/>vasion of various tumors [6, 8, 16-19]. As a dual func-<lb/>tion co-regulator, MTA1 operates as a transcriptional <lb/>repressor of ER-α,BRCA1 and p21 and as a transcrip-<lb/>tional activator of BCAS3 and Pax5 [20-24]. Some <lb/>studies have indicated that down-regulation of MTA1 <lb/>by RNAi leads to an increase expression of E-cadherin <lb/>which acts as a key role in epithelial-to-mesenchymal <lb/>transition in cancer cells [25-27]. Moreover, Wenhao <lb/>Weng et al. have elucidated that MTA1, together with <lb/>Snail or Slug, acted to directly repress the promoter ac-<lb/>tivity of E-cadherin in ESCC (esophageal squamous cell <lb/>carcinoma) cells very recently [28]. Coincidentally, we <lb/>verified that MTA1 could enhance the epithelial-to-<lb/>mesenchymal transition by repressing the promoter activ-<lb/>ity of E-cadherin in MPM cells. <lb/>Epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition (EMT) is a cel-<lb/>lular process which is considered to be involved in <lb/>embryo-morphogenesis, fibrosis and tumor metastasis <lb/>[29, 30]. EMT could enhance not only the ability of <lb/>migration and invasion, but also the resistance to <lb/>apoptosis, senescence and drug resistance in cancer <lb/>[31]. EMT process always accompany by a reduced <lb/>expression of E-cadherin, cyto-keratins (CK), and β-<lb/>catenin (in the membrane), and an increased expres-<lb/>sion of Snail, Slug, Twist, ZEB1, ZEB2, N-cadherin, <lb/>vimentin, a-smooth muscle actin (aSMA), S100A4, and <lb/>matrix metalloproteinases (MMP) [31-33]. In particu-<lb/>lar, repressing the gene expression of E-cadherin could <lb/>notably promote the EMT which is considered as a <lb/>primary reason of tumor metastasis. According to our <lb/>study, the poor prognosis of patients with high <lb/>MTA1expression was correlated with E-cadherin, the <lb/>very classical metastasis suppressor. <lb/>Conclusion <lb/>Our study identified the negative correlation of MTA1 <lb/>and E-cadherin in 65 MPM cases, both of which were <lb/>associated with TNM stage, metastasis and histological <lb/>types and proved the regulatory function of MTA1 on E-<lb/>cadherin through direct binding of its promoter. How-<lb/>ever, as a limit of the number of MPM cases and cell <lb/>types, more elaborate research will be requireda for fur-<lb/>ther exploration of MTA1 in tumorigenesis and metasta-<lb/>sis. Thus, MTA1 potentially served as a therapeutic <lb/>target for the treatment of MPM. <lb/>(See figure on previous page.) <lb/>Fig. 3 MTA1 suppressed the expression of E-cadherin and was up-regulated by TGF-β1 inducing. a and b Nine metastasis genes varied larger <lb/>than two folds were picked via PCR array and were verified by real-time PCR in MPM cells. c Western-blot assay validated the result of PCR array <lb/>of negative trend of MTA1 and E-cadherin in MPM cells. d and e Luciferase report assay demonstrated that E-cadherin transcription was gradually <lb/>enhanced in MPM cells transfected by lentivirus containing pLL3.7-shMTA1 in a time-dependent manner. f MTA1 mRNA expression was up-regulated <lb/>in TGF-β1-stimulated MPM cells. g MPM patients with a high expression level of MTA1 had a significantly shorter overall survival compared with <lb/>patients with a low expression level of MTA1. Data are represented as mean ± SD. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.001. MTA1, metastasis-associated gene 1; MPM, <lb/>malignant pleural mesothelioma; TGF-β1, transforming growth factor beta 1; PCR, polymerase chain reaction <lb/>Table 1 Correlation of MTA1 expression and clinicopathological <lb/>features of MPM <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>All patients MTA1 expression P <lb/>Low <lb/>High <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>N <lb/>6 5 <lb/>2 5 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>Sex <lb/>0.455 0.559 <lb/>Male <lb/>35 <lb/>12 <lb/>23 <lb/>Female <lb/>30 <lb/>13 <lb/>17 <lb/>Age (years) <lb/>0.842 0.040 <lb/>&lt;60 <lb/>27 <lb/>10 <lb/>17 <lb/>≥60 <lb/>38 <lb/>15 <lb/>23 <lb/>Histology <lb/>0.038 6.524 <lb/>Epithelioid <lb/>20 <lb/>13 <lb/>7 <lb/>Sarcomatoid <lb/>25 <lb/>7 <lb/>18 <lb/>Biphasic <lb/>20 <lb/>5 <lb/>15 <lb/>TNM stage a <lb/>0.003 8.990 <lb/>I/II <lb/>29 <lb/>17 <lb/>12 <lb/>III/IV <lb/>36 <lb/>8 <lb/>28 <lb/>Lymph node Metastasis <lb/>0.001 11.714 <lb/>Yes <lb/>38 <lb/>8 <lb/>30 <lb/>No <lb/>27 <lb/>17 <lb/>10 <lb/>Distant Metastasis <lb/>&lt;0.001 14.562 <lb/>Yes <lb/>35 <lb/>6 <lb/>29 <lb/>No <lb/>30 <lb/>19 <lb/>11 <lb/>a <lb/>TNM stage was based on AJCC/UICC Guidelines version 7.2010 MPM. MTA1, <lb/>metastasis-associated protein 1; MPM, Malignant pleural mesothelioma <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional file <lb/>Additional file 1: Figure 1S. MTA1 protein expression in tumor tissue <lb/>and adjacent tissue of one MPM patient. A and B, immunohistochemical <lb/>staining of MTA1 in tumor specimen in comparison with adjacent tissue. <lb/>(TIF 2636 kb) <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">Abbreviation <lb/>MTA: Metastasis-associated gene; MTA1: Metastasis-associated gene 1; <lb/>MPM: Malignant pleural mesothelioma; PCR: Polymerase chain reaction; <lb/>EMT: Epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition; NuRD: Nucleosome remodeling <lb/>and histone deacetylation; CK: Cyto-keratins; aSMA: A-smooth muscle actin; <lb/>MMP: Matrix metalloproteinases. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>CX conceived and designed the experiments. CX, FH wrote the article. <lb/>YC and HH prepared the patient samples. CX and YC performed the <lb/>experiments. WY, YY and ZS collected and analyzed the datas. All authors <lb/>read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgment <lb/>The authors thank D. Yun Chen from Nanjing Medical University for <lb/>providing pLL-3.7 plasmids. <lb/></div>
			
			<front>Received: 20 October 2015 Accepted: 9 December 2015 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>Reference <lb/>1. Tsao AS, Wistuba I, Roth JA, Kindler HL. Malignant pleural mesothelioma. <lb/>J Clin Oncol. 2009;27:2081-90. <lb/>2. Carbonelli C, Rapicetta C, Cesario A. Surgery and survival of patients with <lb/>diagnosis of malignant pleural mesothelioma. J Thorac Oncol. 2015;10:e92-3. <lb/>3. Toh Y, Nicolson GL. The role of the MTA family and their encoded proteins <lb/>in human cancers: molecular functions and clinical implications. Clin Exp <lb/>Metastasis. 2009;26:215-27. <lb/>4. Manavathi B, Kumar R. Metastasis tumor antigens, an emerging family of <lb/>multifaceted master coregulators. J Biol Chem. 2007;282:1529-33. <lb/>5. Balasenthil S, Broaddus RR, Kumar R. Expression of metastasis-associated <lb/>protein 1 (MTA1) in benign endometrium and endometrial <lb/>adenocarcinomas. Hum Pathol. 2006;37:656-61. <lb/>6. Kidd M, Modlin IM, Mane SM, Camp RL, Eick G, Latich I. The role of genetic <lb/>markers-NAP1L1, MAGE-D2, and MTA1-in defining small-intestinal carcinoid <lb/>neoplasia. Ann Surg Oncol. 2006;13:253-62. <lb/>7. Giannini R, Cavallini A. Expression analysis of a subset of coregulators and <lb/>three nuclear receptors in human colorectal carcinoma. Anticancer Res. <lb/>2005;25:4287-92. <lb/>8. Hamatsu T, Rikimaru T, Yamashita Y, Aishima S, Tanaka S, Shirabe K, et al. <lb/>The role of MTA1 gene expression in human hepatocellular carcinoma. <lb/>Oncol Rep. 2003;10:599-604. <lb/>9. Zhu X, Guo Y, Li X, Ding Y, Chen L. Metastasis-associated protein 1 nuclear <lb/>expression is associated with tumor progression and clinical outcome in <lb/>patients with non-small cell lung cancer. J Thorac Oncol. 2010;5:1159-66. <lb/>10. Li Y, Chao Y, Fang Y, Wang J, Wang M, Zhang H, et al. MTA1 promotes the <lb/>invasion and migration of non-small cell lung cancer cells by <lb/>downregulating miR-125b. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2013;32:33. <lb/>11. Martinez-Estrada OM, Lettice LA, Essafi A, Guadix JA, Slight J, Velecela V, et <lb/>al. Wt1 is required for cardiovascular progenitor cell formation through <lb/>transcriptional control of Snail and E-cadherin. Nat Genet. 2010;42:89-93. <lb/>12. Pakala SB, Singh K, Reddy SD, Ohshiro K, Li DQ, Mishra L, et al. TGF-beta1 <lb/>signaling targets metastasis-associated protein 1, a new effector in epithelial <lb/>cells. Oncogene. 2011;30:2230-41. <lb/>13. Deng L, Yang H, Tang J, Lin Z, Yin A, Gao Y, et al. Inhibition of MTA1 by <lb/>ERalpha contributes to protection hepatocellular carcinoma from tumor <lb/>proliferation and metastasis. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2015;34:128. <lb/>14. Song Q, Zhang H, Wang M, Song W, Ying M, Fang Y, et al. MTA1 promotes <lb/>nasopharyngeal carcinoma growth in vitro and in vivo. J Exp Clin Cancer <lb/>Res. 2013;32:54. <lb/>15. Kumar P, Kratzke RA. Molecular prognostic markers in malignant <lb/>mesothelioma. Lung Cancer. 2005;49 Suppl 1:S53-60. <lb/>16. Toh Y, Ohga T, Endo K, Adachi E, Kusumoto H, Haraguchi M, et al. <lb/>Expression of the metastasis-associated MTA1 protein and its relationship to <lb/>deacetylation of the histone H4 in esophageal squamous cell carcinomas. <lb/>Int J Cancer. 2004;110:362-7. <lb/>17. Hofer MD, Kuefer R, Varambally S, Li H, Ma J, Shapiro GI, et al. The role of <lb/>metastasis-associated protein 1 in prostate cancer progression. Cancer Res. <lb/>2004;64:825-9. <lb/>18. Mahoney MG, Simpson A, Jost M, Noe M, Kari C, Pepe D, et al. Metastasis-<lb/>associated protein (MTA)1 enhances migration, invasion, and anchorage-<lb/>independent survival of immortalized human keratinocytes. Oncogene. <lb/>2002;21:2161-70. <lb/>19. Hofer MD, Menke A, Genze F, Gierschik P, Giehl K. Expression of MTA1 <lb/>promotes motility and invasiveness of PANC-1 pancreatic carcinoma cells. <lb/>Br J Cancer. 2004;90:455-62. <lb/>20. Mazumdar A, Wang RA, Mishra SK, Adam L, Bagheri-Yarmand R, Mandal M, <lb/>et al. Transcriptional repression of oestrogen receptor by metastasis-<lb/>associated protein 1 corepressor. Nat Cell Biol. 2001;3:30-7. <lb/>21. Molli PR, Singh RR, Lee SW, Kumar R. MTA1-mediated transcriptional <lb/>repression of BRCA1 tumor suppressor gene. Oncogene. 2008;27:1971-80. <lb/>22. Li DQ, Pakala SB, Reddy SD, Ohshiro K, Peng SH, Lian Y, et al. Revelation of <lb/>p53-independent function of MTA1 in DNA damage response via <lb/>modulation of the p21 WAF1-proliferating cell nuclear antigen pathway. <lb/>J Biol Chem. 2010;285:10044-52. <lb/>23. Gururaj AE, Singh RR, Rayala SK, Holm C, den Hollander P, Zhang H, et al. <lb/>MTA1, a transcriptional activator of breast cancer amplified sequence 3. <lb/>Proc Natl Acad Sci U S A. 2006;103:6670-5. <lb/>24. Balasenthil S, Gururaj AE, Talukder AH, Bagheri-Yarmand R, Arrington T, <lb/>Haas BJ, et al. Identification of Pax5 as a target of MTA1 in B-cell <lb/>lymphomas. Cancer Res. 2007;67:7132-8. <lb/>25. Jiang Q, Zhang H, Zhang P. ShRNA-mediated gene silencing of MTA1 <lb/>influenced on protein expression of ER alpha, MMP-9, CyclinD1 and <lb/>invasiveness, proliferation in breast cancer cell lines MDA-MB-231 and <lb/>MCF-7 in vitro. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2011;30:60. <lb/>26. Rao Y, Wang H, Fan L, Chen G. Silencing MTA1 by RNAi reverses adhesion, <lb/>migration and invasiveness of cervical cancer cells (SiHa) via altered <lb/>expression of p53, and E-cadherin/beta-catenin complex. J Huazhong Univ <lb/>Sci Technolog Med Sci. 2011;31:1-9. <lb/>27. Zhang KJ, Wang DS, Zhang SY, Jiao XL, Li CW, Wang XS, et al. The <lb/>E-cadherin repressor slug and progression of human extrahepatic hilar <lb/>cholangiocarcinoma. J Exp Clin Cancer Res. 2010;29:88. <lb/>28. Weng W, Yin J, Zhang Y, Qiu J, Wang X. Metastasis-associated protein 1 <lb/>promotes tumor invasion by downregulation of E-cadherin. Int J Oncol. <lb/>2014;44:812-8. <lb/>29. Acloque H, Adams MS, Fishwick K, Bronner-Fraser M, Nieto MA. <lb/>Epithelial-mesenchymal transitions: the importance of changing cell <lb/>state in development and disease. J Clin Invest. 2009;119:1438-49. <lb/>30. Thiery JP, Acloque H, Huang RY, Nieto MA. Epithelial-mesenchymal <lb/>transitions in development and disease. Cell. 2009;139:871-90. <lb/>31. Voulgari A, Pintzas A. Epithelial-mesenchymal transition in cancer metastasis: <lb/>mechanisms, markers and strategies to overcome drug resistance in the <lb/>clinic. Biochim Biophys Acta. 2009;1796:75-90. <lb/>32. Mani SA, Guo W, Liao MJ, Eaton EN, Ayyanan A, Zhou AY, et al. The <lb/>epithelial-mesenchymal transition generates cells with properties of stem <lb/>cells. Cell. 2008;133:704-15. <lb/>33. Zeisberg M, Neilson EG. Biomarkers for epithelial-mesenchymal transitions. <lb/>J Clin Invest. 2009;119:1429-37. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Xu et al. Journal of Experimental &amp; Clinical Cancer Research (2015) 34:151 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 9 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
