<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ARTICLE <lb/>Received 28 Jan 2016 | Accepted 29 Jul 2016 | Published 27 Sep 2016 <lb/>Protein kinase D regulates positive selection <lb/>of CD4 þ thymocytes through phosphorylation <lb/>of SHP-1 <lb/>Eri Ishikawa 1 , Hidetaka Kosako 2 , Tomoharu Yasuda 3,w , Masaki Ohmuraya 4,w , Kimi Araki 4 , Tomohiro Kurosaki 3,5 , <lb/>Takashi Saito 6,7 &amp; Sho Yamasaki 1 <lb/>Thymic selection shapes an appropriate T cell antigen receptor (TCR) repertoire during T cell <lb/>development. Here, we show that a serine/threonine kinase, protein kinase D (PKD), <lb/>is crucial for thymocyte positive selection. In T cell-specific PKD-deficient (PKD2/PKD3 <lb/>double-deficient) mice, the generation of CD4 single positive thymocytes is abrogated. This <lb/>defect is likely caused by attenuated TCR signalling during positive selection and incomplete <lb/>CD4 lineage specification in PKD-deficient thymocytes; however, TCR-proximal tyrosine <lb/>phosphorylation is not affected. PKD is activated in CD4 þ CD8 þ double positive (DP) <lb/>thymocytes on stimulation with positively selecting peptides. By phosphoproteomic analysis, <lb/>we identify SH2-containing protein tyrosine phosphatase-1 (SHP-1) as a direct substrate of <lb/>PKD. Substitution of wild-type SHP-1 by phosphorylation-defective mutant (SHP-1 S557A ) <lb/>impairs generation of CD4 þ thymocytes. These results suggest that the PKD-SHP-1 axis <lb/>positively regulates TCR signalling to promote CD4 þ T cell development. <lb/>DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>OPEN <lb/>1 Division of Molecular Immunology, Medical Institute of Bioregulation, Kyushu University, 3-1-1 Maidashi Higashiku, Fukuoka 812-8582, Japan. 2 Division of <lb/>Cell Signaling, Fujii Memorial Institute of Medical Sciences, Tokushima University, 3-18-15 Kuramoto-cho, Tokushima 770-8503, Japan. 3 Laboratory for <lb/>Lymphocyte Differentiation, RIKEN Center for Integrative Medical Sciences, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045, Japan. 4 Institute of <lb/>Resource Development and Analysis, Kumamoto University, 2-2-1, Honjo, Chuo-ku, Kumamoto 860-0811, Japan. 5 Laboratory for Lymphocyte Differentiation, <lb/>WPI Immunology Frontier Research Center (iFReC), Osaka University, 3-1 Yamadaoka, Suita 565-0871, Japan. 6 Laboratory for Cell Signaling, RIKEN Center <lb/>for Integrative Medical Sciences, 1-7-22 Suehiro-cho, Tsurumi-ku, Yokohama 230-0045, Japan. 7 Laboratory for Cell Signaling, WPI Immunology Frontier <lb/>Research Center (iFReC), Osaka University, 3-1 Yamadaoka, Suita 565-0871, Japan. w Present addresses: Max-Delbru ¨ck-Center for Molecular Medicine, <lb/>Robert Ro ¨ssel Street 10, 13125 Berlin, Germany (T.Y.); Department of Genetics, Hyogo College of Medicine, 1-1, Mukogawa-cho, Nishinomiya-shi, <lb/>Hyogo 663-8501, Japan (M.O.). Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to S.Y. (email: yamasaki@bioreg.kyushu-u.ac.jp). <lb/> NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/> 1 <lb/></front>

			<body>A <lb/>n appropriate ab T cell receptor (TCR) repertoire is <lb/>shaped in the thymus through multiple selection steps. In <lb/>this process, transduction of signals through the TCR <lb/>in CD4 þ CD8 þ double positive (DP) thymocytes determines <lb/>CD4/CD8 lineage specification and generates CD4 þ CD8 À and <lb/>CD4 À CD8 þ single positive (SP) thymocytes. At the DP stage, <lb/>interaction of the TCR with self-peptides on major histocompat-<lb/>ibility complex (MHC) molecules generates positive-selecting <lb/>signals. DP thymocytes that undergo positive selection increase <lb/>their surface expression of CD5, CD69 and TCR and differentiate <lb/>into a CD4 þ CD8 int transitional stage. At this stage, persistent <lb/>TCR signalling promotes CD4 lineage specification through a <lb/>series of transcriptional programs 1 . However, the molecular <lb/>mechanisms by which the signal duration is translated into <lb/>specific responses have yet to be fully defined. <lb/>It is well established that sequential tyrosine phosphorylation <lb/>events triggered by protein tyrosine kinases (PTKs), such as Src-, <lb/>Syk-and Tec-family PTKs, orchestrate TCR signalling during <lb/>T cell development 2 . Serine/threonine kinases also regulate T cell <lb/>development by controlling transcriptional and metabolic <lb/>programs 3 . Until now, loss of several serine/threonine kinases <lb/>has been reported to result in defective T cell development 4-10 . <lb/>However, the crosstalk between serine/threonine kinase and <lb/>tyrosine phosphorylation cascade is not clearly understood. <lb/>PKD, initially called PKCm, is a serine/threonine kinase family <lb/>now classified within the CaMK group and separated from the <lb/>AGC group (named for PKA, PKG and PKC) 11 . The three <lb/>isoforms, PKD1, PKD2 and PKD3, are encoded by different <lb/>genes, prkd1, prkd2 and prkd3, respectively. All PKD isoforms <lb/>have a highly conserved amino acid sequence with a <lb/>diacylglycerol (DAG)-binding domain, pleckstrin homology <lb/>(PH) domain and kinase domain 11 . Among them, PKD2 is <lb/>abundantly expressed in T cells 12,13 and is phosphorylated on <lb/>TCR stimulation 14 . In addition, constitutively active PKD2 drives <lb/>T cell development 15 . However, thymic selection was not grossly <lb/>disturbed in PKD2-deficient mice 13 . Until now, no studies have <lb/>addressed the role of PKD in thymocyte development using mice <lb/>lacking all PKD isoforms, and the downstream substrates of PKD <lb/>in thymocytes have not fully been elucidated. <lb/>Inhibitory signalling molecules, such as protein tyrosine <lb/>phosphatases (PTPs), modulate TCR signalling and thus <lb/>contribute to setting the threshold for thymocyte selection 16,17 . <lb/>In particular, SH2-containing protein tyrosine phosphatase-1 <lb/>(SHP-1) is reported to regulate thymic selection through a <lb/>variety of proposed mechanisms 18-21 . The inhibitory activity of <lb/>SHP-1 is regulated by binding to the phosphorylated targets via <lb/>SH2 domains and by phosphorylation of its C-terminal tyrosines <lb/>(Try 536 and Tyr 564 ) 17,22 . However, the role of serine/threonine <lb/>phosphorylation in the function of SHP-1 remains unclear 23 . <lb/>In this study, we established mice lacking all PKD isoforms in <lb/>T cells. The generation of CD4 SP thymocytes is impaired in these <lb/>T cell-specific PKD-deficient mice. Using a phosphoproteomic <lb/>approach, we identify SHP-1 as a direct substrate for PKD. The <lb/>phosphorylation of SHP-1 by PKD positively regulates TCR <lb/>signalling. Collectively, we demonstrate that the PKD-SHP-1 axis <lb/>is required for CD4 þ T cell development. <lb/>Results <lb/>PKD is phosphorylated in preselection DP thymocytes. We first <lb/>investigated whether PKD is activated on TCR engagement in <lb/>thymocytes by evaluating phosphorylation of its activation loop. <lb/>To address this, &apos;unengaged&apos; DP thymocytes that have never <lb/>encountered self-peptides were prepared. To obtain preselection <lb/>thymocytes bearing antigen-specific TCR, bone marrow (BM) <lb/>cells from OT-I TCR Tg mice were transferred into transporter <lb/>associated with antigen processing (TAP)-deficient mice, which <lb/>lack functional MHC class I. The preselection thymocytes were <lb/>stimulated with OVA peptides that differ in affinity such as <lb/>OVA 257-264 (SIINFEKL) (strong agonist), T4 (intermediate <lb/>agonist) and G4 (weak agonist). To evaluate PKD activation, <lb/>we established anti-phospho-PKD1/2/3 Abs that recognize <lb/>phosphorylated activation loops containing a common sequence <lb/>shared by all PKDs (Fig. 1a). Substantial PKD activation, as <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>PKD1 <lb/>PKD2 <lb/>PKD3 <lb/>Thymus Spleen Ovary Lung <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Total RNA (pg) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/>100 <lb/>1,000 10,000 <lb/>Number of labels <lb/>PKD1 <lb/>PKD2 <lb/>PKD3 <lb/>e <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>PKD1 PKD2 PKD3 <lb/>ND <lb/>Relative mRNA levels <lb/>DN <lb/>DP <lb/>CD4 SP <lb/>CD8 SP <lb/>anti-pPKDs <lb/>anti-PKDs <lb/>W <lb/>T S 7 0 7 A <lb/>S 7 1 1 A <lb/>M <lb/>o c k <lb/>S 7 0 7 / 7 1 1 A <lb/>Blot: <lb/>anti-pPKDs <lb/>anti-pErk <lb/>anti-Erk <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>0 5 15 30 60 90 0 5 15 30 60 90 0 5 15 30 60 90 (min) <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Transfected PKD2 <lb/>anti-PKDs <lb/>anti-β-actin <lb/>β-actin <lb/>Figure 1 | Expression of PKD isoforms in the thymus. (a) Characterization <lb/>of anti-phospho-PKD1/2/3 Abs (anti-pPKDs). Reactivities of anti-pPKDs <lb/>were evaluated by western blot analysis of lysates from HEK293 cells <lb/>overexpressing WT PKD2 and mutants. Note that overexpressed PKD2 is <lb/>constitutively phosphorylated. Anti-PKD1/2/3 (anti-PKDs) blotting was <lb/>also performed as a control. (b) Preselection OT-I DP thymocytes, that are <lb/>obtained from TAP-deficient mice transferred with OT-I Tg BM cells, were <lb/>stimulated with a variety of OVA peptides (10 mM) for the indicated times <lb/>and phosphorylation of PKD and Erk was analysed. PKD, Erk and b-actin <lb/>were used as loading controls. (c) RT-PCR analysis of expression of PKD <lb/>isoforms in the thymus, spleen, ovary and lung from C57BL/6 mice. mRNA <lb/>expression of b-actin was analysed as a control. Threefold serial dilutions of <lb/>cDNAs were used as templates. (d) RT-PCR analysis of PKD isoforms <lb/>expressions in various cell subsets sorted by flow cytometry from WT <lb/>thymocytes. Results are presented as expression relative to b-actin. ND, not <lb/>detected. (e) mRNA copy number was evaluated by molecular indexing <lb/>assay. The amount of RNA used in the experiment is indicated on the x axis. <lb/>Data are representative of two independent experiments (a-c). Data are <lb/>presented as mean ± s.d. of triplicate assays and representative of two <lb/>independent experiments (d,e). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>assessed by anti-phospho-PKDs Abs, was induced by low-affinity <lb/>peptides (Fig. 1b), implying a role for PKD in positive selection. <lb/>We next examined the PKD isoforms expressed in thymocytes. <lb/>Reverse transcription-PCR (RT-PCR) analyses confirmed that <lb/>thymocytes express abundant PKD2, less PKD3 and undetectable <lb/>PKD1 mRNA (Fig. 1c,d), as previously reported 13 . The lack of <lb/>PKD1 expression in thymocytes was further verified by evaluating <lb/>mRNA copy number using a molecular indexing assay (Fig. 1e) 24 . <lb/>To generate T cells lacking all PKD isoforms, we established T <lb/>cell-specific PKD2/PKD3 double-deficient mice using Lck-Cre Tg <lb/>mice (PKD2/3 DT ) (Fig. 2a,b). We confirmed that none of the <lb/>three PKD isoforms was expressed in PKD2/3 DT thymocytes <lb/>using Abs reacting with PKD1, PKD2 and PKD3 (Fig. 2c,d). <lb/>Defective T cell development in PKD2/3 DT mice. In PKD2/3 DT <lb/>mice, the proportion and number of CD4 SP thymocytes were <lb/>markedly lower compared with wild-type (WT) mice, whereas <lb/>those from single-deficient (PKD2 DT or PKD3 DT ) mice were not <lb/>altered (Fig. 3a,b). These trends were more prominent in the <lb/>TCR hi -gated mature CD4 SP population (Fig. 3a, lower panels). <lb/>Consistent with the reduction of CD4 SP cells, PKD2/3 DT mice <lb/>had small and fragmented thymic medulla (Fig. 3c). The above <lb/>results might be due to a possible survival defect of CD4 SP cells <lb/>(Fig. 3d; Supplementary Fig. 1), as Bcl-2 expression was reduced <lb/>by half in PKD2/3 DT cells (Fig. 3e). However, this possibility <lb/>seems unlikely as promotion of survival by a Bcl-2 transgene in <lb/>PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 3f) failed to restore the proportion and <lb/>number of CD4 SP thymocytes (Fig. 3g,h). Thus, PKD is likely to <lb/>regulate CD4 SP cell generation beyond any effects on survival. <lb/>A small number of CD4 SP thymocytes in PKD2/3 DT mice <lb/>expressed lower levels of TCR and CD5 on the cell surface <lb/>(Fig. 3i). This phenomenon was also observed in CD8 SP cells, <lb/>suggesting that TCR signalling is impaired during positive <lb/>selection in PKD2/3 DT mice. <lb/>Role of PKD in positive and negative selection. To examine the <lb/>role of PKD in positive selection, we crossed PKD2/3 DT mice with <lb/>MHC class II-restricted OT-II TCR transgenic (Tg) mice. In <lb/>OT-II Â PKD2/3 DT mice, the percentage of CD4 SP thymocytes <lb/>was reduced to one-tenth that of PKD-sufficient OT-II mice <lb/>(Fig. 4a), demonstrating that PKD is critically involved in positive <lb/>selection for the CD4 lineage. In the MHC class I-restricted OT-I <lb/>TCR background, the proportion of mature CD8 SP thymocytes <lb/>in PKD2/3 DT mice was reduced compared with that in control <lb/>OT-I Tg mice (Fig. 4b), albeit less severe than in OT-II <lb/>background. Furthermore, the expression of Tg-TCR was lower <lb/>in PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 4a,b, lower panels). Analysis of <lb/>female H-Y TCR Tg mice supported this finding, as CD8 SP <lb/>development was impaired in H-Y Â PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 4c). <lb/>Thus, positive selection for both the CD4 and CD8 lineages is <lb/>impaired in PKD2/3 DT mice, particularly when the abTCR is <lb/>fixed by transgenes. <lb/>We next investigated the function of PKD in negative selection <lb/>using two different models. In male H-Y Tg Â PKD2/3 DT mice, the <lb/>percentage and number of DP thymocytes were significantly higher <lb/>than in control male H-Y Tg mice, suggesting inefficient negative <lb/>selection in PKD-deficient thymocytes (Fig. 4d). Strikingly, male <lb/>H-Y Tg Â PKD2/3 DT mice had CD8 SP thymocytes bearing high <lb/>levels of the H-Y TCR (Fig. 4e). Furthermore, the peripheral T cells <lb/>in male H-Y Tg Â PKD2/3 DT mice expressed normal levels of <lb/>CD8, unlike low-level expression in WT H-Y controls (Fig. 4f). <lb/>These results suggest that the loss of PKD results in a shift of the <lb/>normal positive selection window towards high self-reactivity due <lb/>to impaired TCR signalling in thymocytes. <lb/>For the second model, we used a clonal deletion model <lb/>triggered by endogenous superantigens. Thymocytes bearing <lb/>Vb5 þ and Vb11 þ TCR are deleted in the presence of mtv-8 <lb/>and mtv-9 on I-E (Fig. 4g, H-2 b/d ) 25 . This deletion persisted in <lb/>PKD single-deficient mice; however, it was significantly blocked <lb/>in PKD2/3 DT (H-2 b/d ) mice (Fig. 4g, left panels). Irrelevant <lb/>Vb6 þ cells were not affected by the absence of PKD (Fig. 4g, <lb/>right panel). Thus, these two models reveal that PKD is involved <lb/>in negative selection. <lb/>Collectively, our results indicate that PKD is critical for positive <lb/>selection to the CD4 lineage and is also required for optimal <lb/>positive selection to the CD8 lineage and negative selection. <lb/>Impaired CD4 þ CD8 int thymocyte generation by loss of PKD. <lb/>DP thymocytes stimulated with positive-selecting peptides <lb/>express CD69 and then differentiate into CD4 þ CD8 int inter-<lb/>mediate cells, which are the precursors to both CD4 and CD8 SP <lb/>thymocytes 1 . Although the number of CD69 þ DP cells was not <lb/>altered in PKD2/3 DT mice, the CD4 þ CD8 int subpopulation was <lb/>significantly decreased (Fig. 5a). The impaired generation of the <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int population was also evident in OT-I and OT-II <lb/>PKD3 <lb/>PKD2 <lb/>anti-PKDs <lb/>anti-β-actin <lb/>anti-β-actin <lb/>anti-pPKDs <lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 5 3 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 5 3 0 6 0 <lb/>60 <lb/>(min) <lb/>WT-allele <lb/>flox-allele <lb/>Exon 14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>17 <lb/>17 <lb/>Δ-allele <lb/>Δ-allele <lb/>17 <lb/>5 kb <lb/>1.5 kb <lb/>2.5 kb <lb/>Exon 14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>Exon 14 <lb/>floxneo-<lb/>allele <lb/>17 <lb/>Exon 14 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>neo <lb/>WT-<lb/>allele <lb/>flox-allele <lb/>Exon 11 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>16 <lb/>16 <lb/>5 kb <lb/>1.5 kb <lb/>2.5 kb <lb/>Exon 11 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>Exon 11 <lb/>16 <lb/>Exon 11 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>neo <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>12 <lb/>floxneo-<lb/>allele <lb/>14 <lb/>14 <lb/>14 <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Blot: <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>P K D <lb/>3 Δ T <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 Δ T <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Figure 2 | Generation of PKD-deficient mice. (a,b) Genomic structures <lb/>and targeting constructs of PKD2 (a) and PKD3 (b). Exons encoding the <lb/>DxxxN motif and the phosphorylation sites required for kinase activity are <lb/>flanked by loxP sites (indicated by open triangles). (c) Total thymocytes <lb/>from WT, PKD2 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg (PKD2 DT ), PKD3 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg <lb/>(PKD3 DT ) and PKD2 fl/fl Â PKD3 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg (PKD2/3 DT ) mice were <lb/>analysed for PKD expression by western blotting using anti-PKDs antibody. <lb/>b-actin was used as a loading control. (d) PKD phosphorylation in <lb/>thymocytes on TCR stimulation by CD3 cross-linking for 2 min was <lb/>detected using anti-pPKDs. Data are representative of two independent <lb/>experiments (c,d). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>TCR Tg backgrounds (Fig. 5b), indicating that PKD is required <lb/>for the transition from the DP to the CD4 þ CD8 int <lb/>stage. Consistent with this, the CD4 þ CD8 int population in <lb/>PKD2/3 DT mice showed lower expression levels of CD5 than in <lb/>WT mice, suggesting that loss of PKD led to the attenuation of <lb/>TCR signalling during differentiation of DP to CD4 þ CD8 int <lb/>stage (Fig. 5c). <lb/>To confirm this assumption, we conducted two-step differ-<lb/>entiation assay in vitro. During recovery culture after cross-<lb/>linking of TCR and co-receptor, DP thymocytes differentiate into <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int cells (Fig. 5d), as previously reported 26 . However, <lb/>PKD2/3 DT DP thymocytes generated a much lower percentage of <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int cells than WT thymocytes after this treatment <lb/>(Fig. 5d). Collectively, these results suggest that PKD regulates the <lb/>TCR signals required for transition of DP to CD4 þ CD8 int <lb/>thymocytes during positive selection. <lb/>PKD mediates signals triggered by weak-affinity peptides. To <lb/>evaluate the strength of TCR signals, we performed quantitative <lb/>assays using OVA peptide variants to stimulate thymocytes from <lb/>TCR Tg mice. Ag peptide-induced co-receptor downregulation is <lb/>a molecular indicator of the strength of TCR signalling in DP <lb/>thymocytes 27 . Indeed, stimulation of thymocytes from OT-II <lb/>TCR Tg mice resulted in co-receptor downregulation in <lb/>accordance with the peptide affinity as seen using OVA 323-339 <lb/>(strong agonist), R9 (weak agonist) and F9 (very weak agonist) <lb/>(Fig. 5e, open circles) 28 . However, the responses were suppressed <lb/>in PKD-deficient OT-II thymocytes, even on stimulation with the <lb/>R9 variant (Fig. 5e, closed circles). Likewise, upregulation of <lb/>CD69 and CD5 was also reduced in the absence of PKD (Fig. 5f). <lb/>To further investigate, we stimulated thymocytes bearing OT-I <lb/>TCR. Again, the co-receptor downregulation faithfully reflected <lb/>the peptide affinity: namely, OVA 257-264 is the most potent, <lb/>followed by T4 and G4 (Fig. 5g, open circles). We found that in <lb/>the absence of PKD, the response was significantly attenuated <lb/>when stimulated with a low-affinity variant, G4, which is known <lb/>as a positive-selecting ligand (Fig. 5g, closed circles) 29 . These <lb/>findings suggest that PKD is required for TCR signalling triggered <lb/>by weak-affinity ligands, which is consistent with the above <lb/>observation that positive selection is severely affected in <lb/>PKD2/3 DT mice. <lb/>PKD is involved in CD4 lineage specification. As the generation <lb/>of CD4 SP cells was more severely affected than CD8 SP cells in <lb/>PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 3a,b), we next investigated whether PKD <lb/>influences CD4 lineage commitment. If PKD2/3 DT thymocytes <lb/>have an intrinsic defect in commitment to the CD4 lineage, they <lb/>b <lb/>CD4 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>WT <lb/>7.1 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>3.7 <lb/>60.4 <lb/>65.5 <lb/>24.6 <lb/>66.5 <lb/>19.7 <lb/>48.1 <lb/>21.2 <lb/>24.1 <lb/>86.5 <lb/>2.7 <lb/>87.5 <lb/>3.6 <lb/>87.4 <lb/>4.0 <lb/>80.0 <lb/>14.5 <lb/>Total <lb/>CD8 <lb/>WT <lb/>C <lb/>M <lb/>C <lb/>M <lb/>i <lb/>WT <lb/>CD4 SP <lb/>CD8 SP <lb/>CD5 <lb/>DP <lb/>TCRβ <lb/>Live cells (% of day 0) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>** <lb/>WT <lb/>e WT <lb/>Relative mRNA levels <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>Bcl-2 <lb/>** <lb/>f <lb/>Live cells (% of day 0) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>WT <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>** <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>NS <lb/>(d) <lb/>(d) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>** <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>** <lb/>TCR hi <lb/>gate <lb/>PKD2 ΔT <lb/>PKD3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2 ΔT <lb/>PKD3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>× Bcl-2 Tg <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>W <lb/>T <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>Thymocytes (× 10 8 <lb/>) <lb/>CD4 SP cells (× 10 7 <lb/>) <lb/>CD8 SP cells (× 10 7 <lb/>) <lb/>28.9 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>WT <lb/>60.4 <lb/>17.2 <lb/>40.9 <lb/>29.1 <lb/>40.2 <lb/>g <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT × Bcl-2 Tg <lb/>TCR hi <lb/>gate <lb/>h <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>(× 10 6 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>** <lb/>CD4 SP / <lb/>CD8 SP (ratio) <lb/>** <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>(× 10 7 ) <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>× Bcl-2 Tg <lb/>CD4 + <lb/>CD8 int <lb/>cells <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>× Bcl-2 Tg <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>× Bcl-2 Tg <lb/>WT <lb/>TCR hi <lb/>CD4 SP <lb/>cells <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Figure 3 | Defective T cell development in the absence of PKD. (a) Total <lb/>thymocytes (upper panels) and TCRb hi thymocytes (lower panels) from <lb/>WT, PKD2 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg (PKD2 DT ), PKD3 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg (PKD3 DT ) and <lb/>PKD2 fl/fl Â PKD3 fl/fl Â Lck-Cre Tg (PKD2/3 DT ) mice were analysed for CD4 <lb/>and CD8 expression by flow cytometry. Numbers in quadrants indicate <lb/>percentages. (b) Absolute cell numbers of total thymocytes, CD4 SP and <lb/>CD8 SP subsets. Each symbol represents an individual mouse. **Po0.01, <lb/>NS, not significant. (c) Hematoxylin and eosin staining of thymus sections. <lb/>M, medulla; C, cortex. Scale bar, 1 mm. (d) In vitro survival of thymocytes. <lb/>Total thymocytes from WT, PKD2 DT , PKD3 DT and PKD2/3 DT mice were <lb/>cultured in vitro and the live cell number of CD4 SP cells was analysed by <lb/>staining with Annexin V and propidium iodide followed by flow cytometry <lb/>analysis after the indicated numbers of days. **Po0.01. (e) Real time PCR <lb/>analysis of Bcl-2 mRNA expression in CD4 þ CD8 int thymocytes. Result is <lb/>presented as expression relative to b-actin. **Po0.01. (f) Analysis of <lb/>PKD2/3 DT Â Bcl-2 Tg mice. In vitro survival of thymocytes from WT, <lb/>PKD2/3 DT and PKD2/3 DT Â Bcl-2 Tg mice were analysed as in (d). <lb/>**Po0.01. (g) Flow cytometry analysis of CD4 and CD8 expression on <lb/>TCRb þ thymocytes from WT, PKD2/3 DT and PKD2/3 DT Â Bcl-2 Tg mice. <lb/>(h) Average cell number of CD4 þ CD8 int and CD4 SP thymocytes and the <lb/>ratio of CD4 SP to CD8 SP thymocytes. *Po0.05, **Po0.01. (i) TCRb and <lb/>CD5 expression on DP and CD4 and CD8 SP thymocytes from WT (filled <lb/>histograms) and PKD2/3 DT mice (open histograms). Data are presented as <lb/>mean±s.d. of triplicate assays (d-f) and eight mice (h) and are <lb/>representative of five (a,i), three (c,f,g), four (d) and two (e) independent <lb/>experiments. Unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to calculate <lb/>P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>should give rise to CD8 SP cells even in the absence of MHC class <lb/>I (in an MHC class II-dependent manner), which is called <lb/>&apos;CD8-redirection&apos; (refs 30,31). To address this possibility, <lb/>we transferred BM cells from WT or PKD2/3 DT mice to <lb/>TAP-deficient mice. PKD-deficient BM cells, but not WT <lb/>BM cells, gave rise to mature CD8 SP thymocytes even <lb/>in TAP-deficient hosts lacking functional MHC class I (Fig. 6a), <lb/>suggesting that PKD2/3 DT cells are defective in lineage <lb/>commitment to CD4 SP thymocytes. <lb/>In fact, expression of ThPOK, a critical regulator of <lb/>CD4 lineage commitment 32 , was decreased in PKD2/3 DT <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int cells, whereas Runx3, a transcription factor <lb/>essential for CD8 lineage specification, was not decreased <lb/>(Fig. 6b). Forced expression of ThPOK restored the percentage <lb/>of CD4 SP thymocytes to nearly WT levels (Fig. 6c). However, the <lb/>expression of the CD5 maturation marker in CD4 þ CD8 int cells <lb/>remained low even in the presence of ThPOK transgene (Fig. 6d). <lb/>Thus, these results suggest that PKD regulates the development of <lb/>38.9 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>25.0 <lb/>54.4 <lb/>Vα2 <lb/>Vα2 <lb/>OT-I <lb/>10.6 <lb/>2.6 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>H-Y (f) <lb/>11.4 <lb/>3.4 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>T3.70 <lb/>42.7 <lb/>34.3 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>Frequency (% of CD4 SP) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Vβ11 + <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>H-2 b/b <lb/>H-2 b/d <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>4.2 <lb/>29.9 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>OT-II × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>OT-I × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>3.0 <lb/>OT-II <lb/>33.7 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>3.2 <lb/>10.4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>** <lb/>WT PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>CD8 <lb/>H-Y × PKD2/3 ΔT (f) <lb/>H-Y (m) <lb/>H-Y × PKD2/3 ΔT (m) <lb/>DP cells (× 10 7 <lb/>) <lb/>H-Y (m) <lb/>H-Y × PKD2/3 ΔT (m) <lb/>H-Y (m) <lb/>H-Y × PKD2/3 ΔT (m) <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2 ΔT <lb/>PKD3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2 ΔT <lb/>PKD3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2 ΔT <lb/>PKD3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>Vβ6 + <lb/>Vβ5 + <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>g <lb/>f <lb/>Figure 4 | Impaired positive and negative selection in the absence of PKD. (a,b) Thymocytes from WT and PKD2/3 DT mice crossed with OT-II TCR Tg <lb/>(a) or OT-I TCR Tg (b) were analysed for expression of CD4 and CD8 by flow cytometry. Numbers indicate the percentages of cells in each gate (upper <lb/>panels). The percentage of Va2 þ cells is shown (lower panels). (c) Analysis of CD4 and CD8 expression (upper panels) and T3.70 expression (lower <lb/>panels) of thymocytes from female (f) H-Y TCR Tg mice. (d) Analysis of male (m) H-Y TCR Tg mice (left panels). The average number of DP thymocytes is <lb/>shown (bar graph). **Po0.01. (e) T3.70 þ thymocytes from male H-Y TCR Tg mice were analysed for CD8 SP population. (f) T3.70 þ splenocytes from <lb/>male H-Y Tg and H-Y Tg Â PKD2/3 DT mice were analysed for CD8 expression. Mean fluorescent intensities (MFIs) of gated population are 208.41 and <lb/>337.32, respectively. (g) Negative selection induced by endogenous superantigens. Percentage of Vb5 þ , Vb11 þ and Vb6 þ cells among CD4 SP <lb/>thymocytes from B6 (H-2 b ) WT, PKD2 DT , PKD3 DT and PKD2/3 DT mice, backcrossed (H-2 b/d ) or not (H-2 b/b ) onto B10.D2 (H-2 d ) mice was analysed by <lb/>flow cytometry. Each circle represents an individual mouse. Small horizontal lines indicate the mean. *Po0.05, **Po0.01. Data are presented as <lb/>mean±s.d. of eight mice (d, bar graph) and are representative of four independent experiments (a-f). Unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to <lb/>calculate P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>CD4 SP cells through at least two mechanisms: (i) promotion of <lb/>TCR signals in the DP stage that trigger transition to the <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int stage; and (ii) specification of CD4 lineage <lb/>development via a ThPOK-dependent process. <lb/>SHP-1 is a PKD substrate in thymocytes. The above results <lb/>demonstrate that PKD promotes TCR signalling during thymic <lb/>selection. However, proximal signalling events including Ca 2 þ <lb/>influx and Erk activation following TCR ligation were comparable <lb/>between WT and PKD2/3 DT thymocytes (Fig. 7a,b). Furthermore, <lb/>in DP cells, TCR-induced tyrosine phosphorylation of proximal <lb/>signalling molecules, such as CD3z and ZAP-70, as well as <lb/>MAPKs, such as Erk, p38 and JNK, was unaffected by the loss of <lb/>PKD (Fig. 7c). <lb/>On the other hand, expression of a truncated PKD2 transgene <lb/>lacking the kinase domain inhibited the generation of CD4 SP <lb/>thymocytes (Fig. 7d), suggesting that the PKD kinase activity is <lb/>required for thymocyte development. <lb/>Hence, to clarify downstream signalling events, we performed <lb/>an unbiased proteomic search for novel PKD substrates in <lb/>thymocytes. To identify proteins that exhibit TCR-induced <lb/>phosphorylation in WT but not PKD-deficient thymocytes, <lb/>phosphoproteins from unstimulated WT, stimulated WT and <lb/>stimulated PKD2/3 DT thymocytes were labelled with Cy2 (blue), <lb/>Cy3 (red) and Cy5 (green) fluorescent markers, respectively, <lb/>and analysed by two-dimensional fluorescence difference gel <lb/>electrophoresis (2D-DIGE) 33 . We detected six &apos;red&apos; spots <lb/>representing proteins that were phosphorylated in a <lb/>stimulation-and PKD-dependent manner (Fig. 8a). These spots <lb/>were identified to be pro-IL-16, SHP-1, NCK1 and Gads by mass <lb/>spectrometry (MS) (Fig. 8a,b; Supplementary Data 1). SHP-1, <lb/>NCK1 and Gads are reported to be involved in T cell <lb/>development 17,34,35 . Phosphate-affinity SDS-PAGE (Phos-tag) <lb/>western blotting 33 showed that the migration of SHP-1, NCK1 <lb/>and Gads was retarded (indicating phosphorylation) in <lb/>stimulated-WT thymocytes (Fig. 8c; Supplementary Fig. 2). In <lb/>PKD2/3 DT cells, the levels of phosphorylation of these proteins <lb/>were reduced (Fig. 8c). In vitro kinase assays with recombinant <lb/>PKD2 and PKD3 revealed that SHP-1, Gads and NCK1 are direct <lb/>substrates for PKD2/3, and were phosphorylated at an efficiency <lb/>similar to substrates previously identified in other tissues <lb/>(Fig. 8d) 36 . We next used MS and site-directed mutagenesis, <lb/>and identified the sites phosphorylated by PKD as SHP-1 Ser 557 , <lb/>Gads Ser 186 and NCK1 Ser 85 (Fig. 8e, Supplementary Fig. 3 and <lb/>Supplementary Data 2). Notably, these sites are similar in <lb/>sequence to the PKD consensus phosphorylation motif, <lb/>L/V/IxRxxpS/T (Fig. 8f) 37 . <lb/>These substrates were also phosphorylated in OT-I thymocytes <lb/>on stimulation with various OVA peptides as assessed by <lb/>Phos-tag western blotting. Among these substrates, the phos-<lb/>phorylation of SHP-1 was largely dependent on PKD2/3 (Fig. 9a). <lb/>In order to further examine SHP-1 phosphorylation in vivo, <lb/>tryptic phosphopeptides were enriched using TiO 2 from each <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>* <lb/>W T <lb/>P K D 2 /3 Δ T <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>W T <lb/>P K D 2 /3 Δ T <lb/>b <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>5 <lb/>WT <lb/>** <lb/>(μg ml <lb/>-1 ) <lb/>(μg ml -1 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>** <lb/>CD5 <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>T4 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>Dulling (%) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>G4 <lb/>OT-I <lb/>Log [peptide(M)] <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>80 <lb/>OVA 323-339 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Dulling (%) <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-10 -8 -6 -4 <lb/>-12 -10 -8 -6 <lb/>-12 -10 -8 -6 <lb/>-12 -10 -8 -6 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>Log [peptide(M)] <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Log [peptide(M)] <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>R9 <lb/>F9 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>OVA 323-339 <lb/>R9 <lb/>F9 <lb/>OT-II <lb/>OT-II × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>OT-II × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>OT-I × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>OT-II <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>Log [peptide(M)] <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>* <lb/>CD5 + <lb/>cells (%) <lb/>CD69 + <lb/>cells (%) <lb/>CD4 + <lb/>CD8 int <lb/>cells (%) <lb/>anti-TCRβ <lb/>anti-CD2 <lb/>CD69 + <lb/>DP cells (× 10 6 <lb/>) <lb/>CD4 + <lb/>CD8 int <lb/>cells (× 10 6 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>** <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>** <lb/>CD4 + <lb/>CD8 int <lb/>cells (× 10 6 <lb/>) <lb/>O <lb/>T -I <lb/>O <lb/>T -I × <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>O <lb/>T -I I <lb/>O <lb/>T -I I × <lb/>P K D <lb/>2 / 3 Δ T <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>g <lb/>Figure 5 | Role of PKD in early differentiation of DP thymocytes. <lb/>(a) Average cell number of CD69 þ DP and CD4 þ CD8 int thymocytes from <lb/>WT and PKD2/3 DT mice was analysed by flow cytometry. *Po0.05. <lb/>(b) Average cell number of CD4 þ CD8 int thymocytes from OT-I or OT-II Tg <lb/>mice. **Po0.01. (c) CD5 expression on TCRb hi CD4 þ CD8 int thymocytes <lb/>from WT and PKD2/3 DT mice. (d) Average percentage of CD4 þ CD8 int <lb/>cells from recovery culture in two-step differentiation assay. **Po0.01. <lb/>(e) Co-receptor downregulation (dulling) on OT-II DP thymocytes on <lb/>stimulation with OVA peptide variants (OVA 323-339 , R9 and F9) was <lb/>analysed by flow cytometry. The data are presented as the per cent <lb/>downregulation, which is the percentage of DP thymocytes with reduced <lb/>levels of CD4 and CD8 relative to the percentage of DP thymocytes <lb/>observed in unstimulated condition. *Po0.01. (f) Percentage of CD69 þ <lb/>cells (upper panels, *Po0.0001) and CD5 þ cells (lower panels, <lb/>*Po0.00001) in DP thymocytes on OVA peptides stimulation. <lb/>(g) Co-receptor downregulation (dulling) on preselection OT-I DP <lb/>thymocytes on stimulation with OVA peptide variants (OVA 257-264 , T4 and <lb/>G4). The data are presented as in e. *Po0.01. Data are presented as <lb/>mean±s.d. of seven mice (a), five mice (b) and triplicate assays <lb/>(d) and are representative of five (c), three (d) or two (e-g) independent <lb/>experiments. Unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to calculate <lb/>P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>thymocyte. The liquid chromatography (LC)-MS data revealed <lb/>that a phosphorylated peptide corresponding to amino <lb/>acid residues 555-570 was increased by TCR stimulation in a <lb/>PKD2/3-dependent manner (Fig. 9b, Supplementary Fig. 4 and <lb/>Supplementary Data 3). Tandem mass spectrometry (MS/MS) <lb/>analysis confirmed phosphorylation at Ser 557 of endogenous <lb/>SHP-1 derived from stimulated-WT thymocytes (Fig. 9c). Finally, <lb/>we developed an antibody that recognizes the phosphorylated <lb/>Ser 557 in SHP-1. TCR stimulation increased the levels of <lb/>phospho-Ser 557 SHP-1 in thymocytes from WT but not <lb/>PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 9d). These results indicate that PKD <lb/>mediates TCR-induced phosphorylation of Ser 557 in SHP-1. <lb/>Importantly, the Ser 557 amino acid is highly conserved across <lb/>mammalian species (Fig. 9e). <lb/>Mutant SHP-1 (SHP-1 S557A ) suppresses thymocyte development. <lb/>To further examine the role of the SHP-1 phosphorylation in T <lb/>cell development, we turned to the DPK cell line, a pigeon <lb/>cytochrome c (PCC)-specific DP cell line that retains the potential <lb/>to undergo differentiation in vitro 38 . Stimulation of DPK cells <lb/>with cognate peptide on I-E k resulted in downregulation of <lb/>CD8 expression and differentiation into CD4 SP cells as <lb/>previously reported 38 (Fig. 10a, Mock). Forced expression of a <lb/>phosphorylation-defective mutant of SHP-1 (SHP-1 S557A ) <lb/>reduced the generation of CD4 SP cells (Fig. 10a). Likewise, <lb/>SHP-1 S557A also inhibited CD5 upregulation induced by peptide <lb/>stimulation (Fig. 10b). These results suggest that SHP-1 S557A can <lb/>suppress TCR signalling in a dominant negative manner and <lb/>that phosphorylation of Ser 557 in SHP-1 promotes TCR signalling. <lb/>We finally examined the in vivo relevance of the phospho-<lb/>rylation of Ser 557 in SHP-1 by establishing knock-in mice <lb/>expressing mutant SHP-1 (SHP-1 S557A/S557A mice) (Fig. 10c). <lb/>Thymocytes from SHP-1 S557A/S557A mice expressed comparable <lb/>amount of SHP-1 to that of WT, whereas TCR-induced <lb/>phosphorylation was impaired (Fig. 10d), indicating that Ser 557 <lb/>is a major phosphorylation site on TCR stimulation. To address <lb/>the role of this site, we evaluated the ability of SHP-1 S557A/S557A <lb/>thymocytes to develop into SP cells in the context of competition <lb/>with WT. CD3e-deficient (CD3e D5/D5 ) mice lacking T cells were <lb/>transferred with mixed BM cells from CD45.1 þ WT and <lb/>CD45.2 þ SHP-1 S557A/S557A mice and analysed after T cell <lb/>reconstitution. SHP-1 S557A/S557A thymocytes showed impaired <lb/>development into CD4 SP population compared with WT <lb/>thymocytes (Fig. 10e), indicating that Ser 557 is required for the <lb/>optimal generation of CD4 SP thymocytes. Collectively, these <lb/>results suggest that the phosphorylation of Ser 557 in SHP-1 can <lb/>positively regulate TCR signalling in DP thymocytes to promote <lb/>T cell development. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we established T cell-specific PKD-deficient mice to <lb/>characterize the role of PKD in T cell development. PKD appears <lb/>to control the generation of CD4 SP thymocytes through <lb/>promoting (i) TCR signalling during positive selection, and <lb/>(ii) CD4 lineage specification. Since the decreased number of <lb/>CD4 þ CD8 int cells in PKD2/3 DT mice was restored by a Bcl-2 <lb/>transgene (Fig. 3h), an important function of PKD during positive <lb/>selection may be promoting survival that allows DP cells to <lb/>differentiate into the CD4 þ CD8 int stage. On the other hand, <lb/>defective CD4 lineage specification on loss of PKD is likely due to <lb/>the incomplete induction of ThPOK during positive selection, <lb/>as CD4/CD8 ratio was restored by ThPOK transgene, but not by <lb/>Bcl-2. Optimal ThPOK induction requires &apos;duration&apos; of TCR <lb/>signalling during positive selection 39 . In contrast, the expression <lb/>of Runx3, a transcription factor essential for CD8 lineage <lb/>specification, is controlled by TCR-induced immediate <lb/>upregulation of IL-7R and subsequent IL-7 signalling 40 . As <lb/>Runx3 induction occurred normally in PKD-deficient mice <lb/>(Fig. 6b), PKD is apparently dispensable for the transient TCR <lb/>signalling required for Runx3 induction. In this respect, we <lb/>speculate that another critical role of PKD may be to maintain the <lb/>&apos;duration&apos; of TCR/co-receptor signalling after sensing a weak-<lb/>affinity ligand. Consistent with this idea, PKD was efficiently <lb/>activated by stimulation with weak-affinity peptide variants in <lb/>preselection DP thymocytes (Supplementary Fig. 5). <lb/>PKD2 is abundantly expressed in thymocytes, while the <lb/>amount of PKD3 is considerably lower. Nevertheless, the <lb/>strikingly different phenotype of PKD2/3 DT versus PKD2 DT mice <lb/>CD8 <lb/>TCR hi <lb/>gate <lb/>TCR hi <lb/>gate <lb/>1.2 <lb/>12.2 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>WT <lb/>73.9 <lb/>12.7 <lb/>32.0 <lb/>20.1 <lb/>4.4 <lb/>60.9 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>CD5 <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>Relative mRNA levels <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>ThPOK <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>Runx3d <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>Runx3 <lb/>NS <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT -&gt; TAP -/-<lb/>WT -&gt; TAP -/-<lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT × ThPOK Tg <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT × ThPOK Tg <lb/>(× 10 -3 ) <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>d <lb/>c <lb/>Figure 6 | PKD is required for CD4 lineage commitment. (a) Analysis of CD8-redirection. BM cells from WT and PKD2/3 DT mice were transferred into <lb/>irradiated TAP À/ À recipient mice. At 8 weeks after BMT, CD4 and CD8 expression levels on TCRb hi thymocytes were analysed by flow cytometry. The <lb/>percentage of gated population is indicated. (b) Real time PCR analysis of ThPOK, Runx3 and Runx3d mRNA expressions in CD4 þ CD8 int thymocytes. <lb/>Results are presented as relative expression of b-actin. **Po0.01, NS, not significant. (c) Flow cytometry analysis of CD4 and CD8 expression on TCRb hi <lb/>thymocytes from WT, PKD2/3 DT and PKD2/3 DT Â ThPOK Tg mice. (d) CD5 expression on CD4 SP thymocytes. Data are presented as mean ± s.d. of <lb/>triplicate assays (b) and representative of two (a,b) or three (c,d) independent experiments. Unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to calculate <lb/>P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>demonstrates that a limited amount of PKD3 is sufficient to <lb/>support SP thymocyte generation. The redundant functions of <lb/>PKD2 and PKD3 in T cell development suggest that their <lb/>substrate specificities are likely to overlap. Indeed, all substrates <lb/>tested in this study were phosphorylated by both PKD2 and <lb/>PKD3 with similar efficiencies (Fig. 8d). The PKD consensus <lb/>phosphorylation motif has been reported to be L/V/IxRxxS/T 37 . <lb/>The new phosphorylation sites that we have identified <lb/>herein are similar but not identical to this motif (Fig. 8f). <lb/>This finding underscores the important contribution of <lb/>unbiased phospho-proteomics 33,41 , in addition to motif-based <lb/>approaches 42 , in identifying novel kinase substrates. <lb/>It has been suggested that SHP-1 dephosphorylates several key <lb/>molecules involved in TCR signalling mainly through interactions <lb/>with ITIM-containing transmembrane proteins 17 . Recently, <lb/>Themis, a molecule critical for positive selection, was reported <lb/>to recruit SHP-1 to antagonize TCR signalling, thereby <lb/>preventing the apoptosis of DP cells that encountered weak <lb/>agonists during positive selection 43 , although some debate <lb/>exists 44 . Given that loss of Themis or PKD cause similar defects <lb/>in T cell development, one might speculate that PKD also <lb/>antagonizes TCR signalling to ensure positive selection. However, <lb/>this possibility seems less likely, as the expression levels of CD5, <lb/>CD69 (Fig. 5f) and Nur77 (Supplementary Fig. 6), which <lb/>represent the summation of TCR signalling intensity 45,46 , were <lb/>reduced in PKD-deficient cells. This finding is consistent with <lb/>the fact that active PKD induces upregulation of CD5 in <lb/>thymocytes 15 . In addition, a &apos;selection shift&apos; from negative <lb/>WT <lb/>PKD2/3 <lb/>ΔT <lb/>pErk <lb/>pCD3ξ <lb/>pp38 <lb/>pZAP70 <lb/>pJNK <lb/>Unstim. <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>** <lb/>W T <lb/>P K D 2 Δ K D T g <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fluo-4 <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fluo-4 <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fluo-4 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>Goat anti-<lb/>hamster IgG <lb/>(μg ml -1 ) <lb/>WT <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 100 200 300 400 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>anti-pPKDs <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>anti-PKDs <lb/>Blot: <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>(min) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>30 <lb/>15 <lb/>60 120 <lb/>OT-I <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>30 <lb/>15 <lb/>60 120 <lb/>anti-pErk <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>anti-Erk <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>Fluo-4 <lb/>PKD2/3 <lb/>ΔT <lb/>OT-I × PKD2/3 <lb/>ΔT <lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>TCR <lb/>hi <lb/>CD4 SP cells (X 10 <lb/>6 <lb/>) <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Figure 7 | TCR downstream signalling in PKD-deficient thymocytes. (a) Ca 2 þ influx in freshly isolated DP thymocytes from WT and PKD2/3 DT mice <lb/>after TCR stimulation by CD3 cross-linking using indicated concentration of goat anti-hamster IgG (open arrowhead) followed by the addition of ionomycin <lb/>(closed arrowhead) was assessed by flow cytometry. (b) OT-I preselection DP thymocytes were stimulated with OVA peptide variants for the indicated <lb/>times and phosphorylation of PKD and Erk was analysed by immunoblotting. PKD and Erk were used as a loading control. (c) Phosphorylation of CD3z, <lb/>ZAP-70, Erk, p38 and JNK in unstimulated (filled histograms) and anti-CD3-stimulated DP thymocytes (open histograms) was analysed by intracellular <lb/>staining. (d) Average cell number of TCRb hi CD4 SP thymocytes from WT and truncated PKD2 Tg mice lacking the kinase domain (PKD2 DKD Tg) was <lb/>analysed by flow cytometry. Each circle represents an individual mouse. **Po0.01. Data are representative of three independent experiments (a-c). <lb/>Data are presented as mean±s.d. of four mice (d, bar graph). Unpaired two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to calculate P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>selection to positive selection has been reported in mice with <lb/>defective TCR signalling, such as ZAP-70-mutated mice <lb/>or CD3z À / À mice 47,48 , similar to what we observe herein <lb/>for PKD2/3 DT mice (Fig. 4e,f). In contrast, in Themis À / À mice, <lb/>proximal TCR signalling is enhanced rather than attenuated 43 . <lb/>Therefore, although PKD and Themis can both act on SHP-1, <lb/>they appear to regulate TCR signalling in opposite directions. The <lb/>generation of Themis À / À Â PKD2/3 DT triple-deficient mice will <lb/>clarify this issue. <lb/>What is the molecular basis for the positive signalling resulting <lb/>from the phosphorylation of Ser 557 in SHP-1? There are at least <lb/>three possibilities: First, the phosphorylation by PKD may <lb/>constrain the inhibitory function, such as phosphatase activity, <lb/>of SHP-1. Alternatively, the phosphorylation might alter the <lb/>proper cellular localization of SHP-1 away from the area where <lb/>efficient inhibition of TCR signalling takes place. Indeed, a 6-mer <lb/>motif including Ser 557 in SHP-1 is reported to regulate its <lb/>subcellular localization 49 . Second, we cannot rule out the <lb/>possibility that serine-phosphorylated SHP-1 dephosphorylates <lb/>proteins containing tyrosines that on phosphorylation, negatively <lb/>regulate TCR signalling. For example, SHP-1 dephosphorylates <lb/>the C-terminal regulatory tyrosine of Src family PTKs in <lb/>osteoblasts to activate their kinase activities 50 . Third, SHP-1 <lb/>may function as an adaptor rather than a phosphatase through <lb/>its C-terminal phospho-Ser 557 , and may recruit positive <lb/>regulators into the vicinity of the TCR. In every case, it would <lb/>pH <lb/>4 <lb/>7 <lb/>MW (kDa) <lb/>1 2 3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Name Accession Calc.MW Calc.pl Score Seq.cov <lb/>1 Pro-IL-16 O54824 141,435 <lb/>7.98 <lb/>396 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>2 Pro-IL-16 O54824 141,435 <lb/>7.98 <lb/>573 <lb/>15 <lb/>15 <lb/>3 Pro-IL-16 O54824 141,435 <lb/>7.98 <lb/>506 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>4 <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>P29351 <lb/>67,559 <lb/>7.66 <lb/>86 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>NCK1 <lb/>Q99M51 <lb/>42,891 <lb/>6.06 <lb/>80 <lb/>7 <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>Gads <lb/>O89100 <lb/>36,810 <lb/>6.10 <lb/>199 <lb/>27 <lb/>6 <lb/>Spot# <lb/>PKD2 <lb/>PKD3 <lb/>PKD2 <lb/>PKD3 <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>[ 32 P]-Gads <lb/>Gads <lb/>NCK1 <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>A S <lb/>T S S 557 <lb/>V N <lb/>K L S 186 <lb/>V K <lb/>K P S 85 <lb/>x <lb/>L/V/I <lb/>S/T <lb/>x x <lb/>150 <lb/>5 <lb/>anti-<lb/>Gads <lb/>anti-<lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>2/3 ΔT <lb/>WT <lb/>2/3 ΔT <lb/>WT <lb/>+ <lb/>-+ <lb/>+ <lb/>-+ <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Gads <lb/>NCK1 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>75 <lb/>50 <lb/>37 <lb/>25 <lb/>150 <lb/>100 <lb/>75 <lb/>50 <lb/>37 <lb/>25 <lb/>(kDa) <lb/>Que.Match <lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>anti-<lb/>NCK1 <lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>GST <lb/>Gads <lb/>NCK1 <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>Hsp27 <lb/>CREB <lb/>HDAC7 <lb/>GST <lb/>Gads <lb/>NCK1 <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>Hsp27 <lb/>CREB <lb/>HDAC7 <lb/>S557/591A <lb/>S591A <lb/>S557A <lb/>WT <lb/>S557/591A <lb/>S591A <lb/>S557A <lb/>WT <lb/>WT <lb/>[ 32 P]-SHP-1 <lb/>[ 32 P]-NCK1 <lb/>S186A <lb/>WT <lb/>WT <lb/>S186A <lb/>S85A <lb/>WT <lb/>S85A <lb/>WT (-) / WT (+) / PKD2/3 ΔT (+) <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>Figure 8 | Identification of PKD2 and PKD3 substrates. (a) A gel image of 2D-DIGE of phosphoproteins from unstimulated WT thymocytes <lb/>(Cy2-labelled, blue), WT thymocytes stimulated by CD3 cross-linking (Cy3-labelled, red) and stimulated PKD2/3 DT thymocytes (Cy5-labelled, green). <lb/>Red spots are indicated by arrowheads as spot #1 to #6. (b) The summary of the protein identity, accession number, calculated molecular weight, <lb/>calculated pI, Mascot score, sequence coverage and query match for each of six spots in a. Spots #1, #2 and #3, which have the same molecular weight <lb/>with different pI&apos;s were identified as pro-IL-16. (c) Phos-tag immunoblot analysis of cell lysates from unstimulated-and TCR-stimulated-WT thymocytes for <lb/>2 min and stimulated PKD2/3 DT thymocytes using anti-SHP-1, anti-NCK1 and anti-Gads. (d) In vitro kinase assays were performed in the presence of <lb/>[g-32 P]ATP with active, recombinant PKD2 or PKD3 and GST-fused substrates as indicated (upper panel). CBB staining shows that equivalent amounts of <lb/>proteins were used for the assays (lower panel). Red arrowheads indicate GST-fused substrates. (e) Identification of phosphorylation sites. In vitro kinase <lb/>assays were performed with PKD2 or PKD3 and, as substrates, WT or mutant SHP-1, Gads and NCK1. Mutant substrates carry serine to alanine substitution <lb/>at the indicated amino acid positions. CBB staining is shown as a loading control. (f) Comparison of the PKD consensus phosphorylation motif and <lb/>phosphorylation sites identified in e. Data are representative of two independent experiments (a-e). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>be extremely intriguing to identify the protein(s) that selectively <lb/>bind to Ser 557 -phosphrylated SHP-1. Johnson et al. 51 recently <lb/>reported that T cell-specific SHP-1 deletion using Cd4-Cre Tg <lb/>mice had no obvious effect on T cell development. This may be <lb/>explained by the loss of both positive and negative regulation via <lb/>SHP-1 in thymocytes lacking SHP-1 protein. <lb/>The observation that the defects found in SHP-1 S557A/S557A <lb/>mice are milder than that of PKD2/3 DT mice could be explained <lb/>by a possible contribution of other PKD substrates, such as Gads <lb/>and NCK1. Indeed, co-transfection of phosphorylation-defective <lb/>forms of three other PKD substrates (Gads, NCK1 and pro-IL-16) <lb/>together with SHP-1 S557A resulted in more severe impairment in <lb/>CD5 upregulation (Supplementary Fig. 7). Thus, we cannot <lb/>exclude the possibility that PKD might control T cell develop-<lb/>ment by modulating multiple TCR signalling pathways through <lb/>various substrates in addition to SHP-1. <lb/>Histone deacetylase 7 (HDAC7) is also reported to be a <lb/>substrate for PKD 52 and we confirmed this in in vitro kinase <lb/>assay (Fig. 8d), whereas we could not detect PKD-dependent <lb/>phosphorylation of HDAC7 in thymocytes by 2D-DIGE <lb/>Relative abundance <lb/>WT (+) <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>PKD2/3 ΔT (+) <lb/>21.70 <lb/>7.52 <lb/>5 10 15 20 25 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>WT (-) <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>TSpSKHKEEVYENVHSK <lb/>1 <lb/>557 <lb/>0.31 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>OVA 257-264 <lb/>T4 <lb/>G4 <lb/>OT-I <lb/>0 5 15 30 60120 0 5 15 30 60120 (min) <lb/>Blot: <lb/>anti-<lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>Mouse <lb/>HAKASRTSSKHKEEVY <lb/>HAKASRTSSKHKEEVY <lb/>HAKASRTSSKHKEDVY <lb/>HAKASRTSSRHKDEVY <lb/>HAKASRTSSKHKEDVY <lb/>HAKASRTSSKHKDEVY <lb/>557 <lb/>SH2 SH2 <lb/>Phosphatase <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>e <lb/>-+ -+ <lb/>WT PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>anti-pSHP-1(Ser 557 ) <lb/>anti-SHP-1 <lb/>Blot: <lb/>Rat <lb/>Pig <lb/>Bovine <lb/>Chimpanzee <lb/>Human <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>(kDa) <lb/>y 1 4 <lb/>b 2 <lb/>b 3 <lb/>b 5 <lb/>b 6 <lb/>b 7 <lb/>b 8 <lb/>b 9 <lb/>b 1 0 <lb/>b 1 1 <lb/>b 1 2 <lb/>b 1 3 <lb/>y 1 2 <lb/>y 1 1 <lb/>y 1 0 <lb/>y 9 <lb/>y 8 <lb/>y 7 <lb/>y 6 <lb/>y 5 y 4 y 3 y 2 y 1 <lb/>557 <lb/>K <lb/>S <lb/>H <lb/>V <lb/>N <lb/>E <lb/>Y <lb/>V <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>K <lb/>H <lb/>K <lb/>S <lb/>S <lb/>T <lb/>PH <lb/>1.5e+5 <lb/>HCD FT MS/MS <lb/>Precursor MS (4+) = m/z 496.23 <lb/>1.0e+5 <lb/>Ion current <lb/>5.0e+4 <lb/>0.0e+0 <lb/>% of base peak <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>b2-H <lb/>2 O <lb/>y2-H <lb/>2 C <lb/>y5 ++ <lb/>y3 <lb/>b6-H <lb/>2 O-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>++ <lb/>y3-H <lb/>2 O <lb/>b7-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>++ <lb/>b8-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>++ <lb/>b5-NH <lb/>3 -H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>b5-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>b9 ++ <lb/>y5-H <lb/>2 O <lb/>y10 ++ <lb/>b10 ++ <lb/>b11-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>++ <lb/>y11 ++ <lb/>y6-NH <lb/>3 <lb/>y6 <lb/>y12 ++ <lb/>b13 ++ <lb/>y14-H <lb/>3 PO <lb/>4 <lb/>++ <lb/>y7 <lb/>y5 <lb/>y7 ++ <lb/>y4 <lb/>y8 ++ <lb/>y1-NH <lb/>3 <lb/>y1 <lb/>y2 <lb/>b2 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>800 <lb/>900 <lb/>m /z <lb/>OT-I × PKD2/3 ΔT <lb/>SHP-1 <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Figure 9 | SHP-1 is phosphorylated by PKD2 and PKD3 at Ser 557 in thymocytes. (a) Phosphorylation of SHP-1 on peptide stimulation. OT-I DP <lb/>thymocytes were stimulated with the designated OVA peptides for the indicated times. Cell lysates were subjected to Phos-tag immunoblot analysis using <lb/>anti-SHP-1. Arrowheads indicate phosphorylated SHP-1 that showed stimulation-dependent mobility shift. (b) The extracted ion chromatogram of m/z <lb/>496.23096 corresponds to the quadruply charged SHP-1 phosphopeptide (TSpS 557 KHKEEVYENVHSK), which was increased by TCR stimulation in tryptic <lb/>phosphopeptides from WT thymocytes and was almost undetectable in those from stimulated PKD2/3 DT thymocytes. The relative values of the peak area <lb/>are indicated. Note that the hextuply charged ion peak at a retention time of 21.70 min was unrelated to this SHP-1 phosphopeptide. (c) Phosphorylation of <lb/>Ser 557 was demonstrated by the MS/MS spectrum of the m/z 496.23 ion at a retention time of 7.52 min in tryptic phosphopeptides from stimulated-WT <lb/>thymocytes. (d) Phosphorylation of Ser 557 of SHP-1 was analysed by immunoblotting. Total thymocytes were stimulated by CD3 cross-linking for 2 min and <lb/>analysed by anti-phospho-SHP-1 (Ser 557 ) Abs. Total SHP-1 was blotted as a control. (e) Schematic structure of SHP-1 and sequence alignment of the <lb/>C-terminal region of SHP-1 that contains Ser residue corresponding to Ser 557 of murine SHP-1 (shown in red). Data are representative of two independent <lb/>experiments (a-d). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>(Fig. 8a,b). HDAC7-deficient mice show poor generation of SP <lb/>thymocytes 53 . However, the phenotype of PKD-deficient mice is <lb/>unlikely to be attributed to HDAC7, as loss of HDAC7 results <lb/>in unique phenotypes, such as limited usage of TCR Ja segments, <lb/>which are not observed in PKD2/3 DT mice. In addition, in <lb/>HDAC7-deficient mice, the introduction of TCR transgenes <lb/>(OT-I or OT-II) reduced rather than exacerbated the defect in <lb/>thymocyte development 53 , which contrasts with the phenotypes <lb/>seen in PKD-deficient mice. <lb/>Currently, the pathway upstream of PKD during thymic <lb/>selection is not clearly understood. PKD is activated by binding to <lb/>DAG and, more importantly, by phosphorylation of serine <lb/>residues in the activation loop (Ser 707/711 in PKD2 and Ser 731/735 <lb/>in PKD3) 3 . In T cells, classical as well as novel PKCs, including <lb/>PKCa, d, e, Z and y, are implicated in the phosphorylation of <lb/>these residues 14 . Among them, PKCy and PKCZ are abundantly <lb/>expressed in DP thymocytes, and recently, PKCy À / À PKCZ À / À <lb/>double-deficient mice were demonstrated to have a decreased <lb/>number of SP thymocytes compared with single-deficient mice 54 . <lb/>In this regard, one can speculate that PKDy and PKCZ <lb/>act as upstream regulators of PKD after TCR engagement in <lb/>thymocytes. This hypothesis warrants further investigation. <lb/>In conclusion, we propose that the PKD represents one of the <lb/>molecular switches that converts weak TCR engagement to <lb/>positive selection and CD4 lineage specification. The critical roles <lb/>of PTKs and PTPs in thymic selection have been clearly <lb/>established. The present study brings to light the additional <lb/>importance of serine/threonine kinases as key modulators of TCR <lb/>signalling cascade regulated by tyrosine phosphorylation during <lb/>thymic selection. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Mice. PKD2-floxed and PKD3-floxed mice were generated by homologous <lb/>recombination-mediated gene targeting in embryonic stem (ES) cells of C57BL/6 <lb/>and 129 genetic background, respectively. PKD3-floxed mice were backcrossed to <lb/>C57BL/6 mice and floxed Neo cassette of each allele was deleted by crossing with <lb/>CAG-Cre Tg mice. Bcl-2 Tg mice 55 were provided by J. Domen (The Children&apos;s <lb/>Mercy Hospital, Kansas City, MO) by the courtesy of K. Ikuta (Kyoto University, <lb/>Kyoto, Japan). CD3e D5/D5 mice 56 were provided by B. Malissen (Aix Marseille <lb/>CD5 + <lb/>in DP cells (%) <lb/>80 <lb/>70 <lb/>60 <lb/>50 <lb/>40 <lb/>30 <lb/>20 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0.03 0.3 <lb/>3 <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>CD4 SP cells (%) <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 0.03 0.3 <lb/>3 <lb/>* <lb/>** <lb/>** <lb/>Mock <lb/>SHP-1 S557A <lb/>Mock <lb/>SHP-1 S557A <lb/>CD45.1 + <lb/>WT <lb/>15.9 <lb/>4.5 <lb/>CD45.2 + <lb/>SHP-1 S557A/S557A <lb/>8.6 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>CD8 <lb/>CD4 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>anti-CD3 <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>WT <lb/>SHP-1 S557A/S557A <lb/>Blot: anti-SHP-1 <lb/>(Phos-tag) <lb/>SHP-1 S557A -allele <lb/>Exon <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>13 <lb/>15 <lb/>16 <lb/>neo <lb/>SHP-1 S557A -allele <lb/>(Δneo) <lb/>neo <lb/>DT-A <lb/>Targeting vector <lb/>* <lb/>S 557 A <lb/>* <lb/>S 557 A <lb/>* <lb/>S 557 A <lb/>4.1 kb <lb/>1 kb <lb/>PCC (μM) <lb/>PCC (μM) <lb/>SHP-1 WT -allele <lb/>Blot: anti-SHP-1 <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>Figure 10 | Phosphorylation of SHP-1 Ser 557 is critical for T cell development. (a,b) DPK cells expressing vector alone (Mock) or mutant SHP-1 <lb/>(SHP-1 S557A ) were stimulated with the indicated concentrations of PCC peptides presented on DCEK cells expressing I-E k . The percentages of CD4 <lb/>SP thymocytes (a) and CD5 þ cells in DP thymocytes (b) at day 3 were analysed by flow cytometry. *Po0.05, **Po0.01. (c) Targeting construct <lb/>for establishment of SHP-1 S557A knock-in mice. (d) Phosphorylation and expression level of SHP-1 in unstimulated-and TCR-stimulated-WT and <lb/>SHP-1 S557A/S557A thymocytes were examined by Phos-tag immunoblot analysis (upper panel) and Western blot (lower panel). (e) Analysis of <lb/>CD4 SP cell generation in thymocytes expressing phosphorylation-defective SHP-1 S557A . CD3e D5/D5 mice that were transferred with mixed BM cells from <lb/>CD45.1 þ WT and CD45.2 þ SHP-1 S557A/S557A mice were analysed for CD4 and CD8 expression on thymocytes by flow cytometry 4 weeks after BMT. <lb/>Data are presented as mean±s.d. of triplicate assays (a,b) and representative of three (a,b), two (d) or five (e) independent experiments. Unpaired <lb/>two-tailed Student&apos;s t test is used to calculate P values. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>Universite ´UM2, Marseille, France). Truncated PKD2 (a.a. 1-381) Tg mice were <lb/>established under Lck proximal promoter 57 . Tg mice expressing ThPOK <lb/>were established under Cd4 enhancer and promoter 58 . For the generation of <lb/>SHP-1 S557A/S557A mice, C57BL/6-derived ES cells were co-transfected with a <lb/>circular form of targeting vector and two Cas9D10A and sgRNA expression vectors <lb/>(pX335, Addgene) to produce nicks in homology arms and genomic DNA for <lb/>efficient homologous recombination (gRNAs for CRISPR were GTGGTGGA <lb/>GTGGGAGAAGCCC (pX335-SHP-short arm) and AGCTATGATATGGCTTC <lb/>ACA (pX335-SHP-long arm)). A floxed Neo cassette was deleted by crossing with <lb/>CAG-Cre Tg mice. Male and female mice of 7-12 weeks of age with C57BL/6 <lb/>background were used for all experiments unless otherwise specified. For in vivo <lb/>negative selection model, C57BL/6 (H-2 b ) mice and B10.D2 (H-2 d ) mice were <lb/>obtained from Kyudo Co. Ltd. and Sankyo Labo Service Co. Inc., respectively. All <lb/>mice were maintained in filter-air, laminar-flow enclosures and given standard <lb/>laboratory food and water ad libitum. Animal protocols were approved by the <lb/>committee of Ethics on Animal Experiment, Faculty of Medical Sciences, <lb/>Kyushu University. <lb/>Cells and reagents. DP thymocyte cell line, DPK cells 59 were obtained from <lb/>J. G. Kaye (The Scripps Research Institute, La Jolla, CA, USA) and maintained in <lb/>RPMI1640 medium (SIGMA) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS) <lb/>(SIGMA), 100 U ml À 1 penicillin, 10 mg ml À 1 streptomycin, 50 mM 2-mercaptoehthanol, <lb/>0.1 mM non-essential amino acids and 1 mM sodium pyruvate. Murine fibroblast <lb/>cell line DCEK transfected with I-E k was kindly provided by K. Yasutomo <lb/>(Tokushima University, Tokushima, Japan) and maintained in DMEM medium <lb/>(SIGMA) supplemented with 10% FBS, 100 U ml À 1 penicillin, 10 mg ml À 1 <lb/>streptomycin and 50 mM 2-mercaptoehthanol. To use DCEK cells as APC in <lb/>in vitro DPK differentiation assay, cells were treated with 50 mg ml À 1 mitomycin C <lb/>for 30 min, washed with DMEM medium three times and plated on 96-well plates <lb/>at 1 Â 10 5 cells per well. After 24 h, PCC 88-104 peptides were added, and 2 h later, <lb/>5 Â 10 4 DPK cells were plated. The mixed culture was incubated for 3 days <lb/>and analysed by flow cytometry for the expression of CD4, CD8 and CD5. <lb/>Anti-PKD1/2/3 (pan) and anti-phospho-PKD1/2/3 (pan) were raised by <lb/>immunization of rabbits with peptides, CIIGEKSFRRSVVGTP and <lb/>CIIGEKpSFRRpSVVGTP, respectively, which are common sequence of PKD1, <lb/>PKD2 and PKD3. Specificity of these Abs was validated by Western blotting of <lb/>lysates from HEK293 cells that were transfected with PKD1, PKD2 and PKD3 or <lb/>WT PKD2, PKD2 S707A , PKD2 S711A and PKD2 S707/711A (Fig. 1a). Anti-PKDs Ab <lb/>and anti-pPKDs Ab were used at 10 and 2 mg ml À 1 , respectively. Anti-pSHP-1 <lb/>(Ser 557 ) was raised with a peptide, CASRTSpSKHKEE and used at 2 mg ml À 1 . <lb/>Anti-CD3e (cat#553058, 145-2C11, 10 mg ml À 1 ), anti-CD4 (cat#553051, RM4-5, <lb/>1:100), anti-CD8 (cat#553033, 53-6.7, 1:100), anti-CD69 (cat#553236, H1.2F3, <lb/>1:100), anti-Va2 (cat#553288, B20.1, 1:80), anti-mouse TCR Vb screening panel <lb/>(cat#557004, 1:2) and anti-pCD247 (Y 142 ) (pCD3z) (cat#558486, 1:50) were <lb/>purchased from BD Biosciences. Anti-CD5 (cat#100606, 53-7.3, 1:50), anti-TCRb <lb/>(cat#109206, H57, 1:20) and anti-CD4 (cat#100540, RM4-5, 1:100) were <lb/>from BioLegend. Anti-H-Y TCR (cat#11-9930-82, T3.70, 1:100), anti-TCRb <lb/>(cat#16-5961, H57) and anti-CD2 (cat#16-0021, RM2-5) were purchased from <lb/>eBioscience. Annexin V-FITC kit (cat#4700, 1:20) was from MBL. For intracellular <lb/>staining, anti-pErk1/2 (anti-ACTIVE MAPK) (cat#V8031, 1:40) was obtained from <lb/>Promega and anti-pZAP70 (cat#2717, 1:50), anti-pp38 (cat#4511, 1:50) and <lb/>anti-pJNK (cat#9255, 1:25) were from Cell Signaling Technology. For Western <lb/>blotting, anti-pErk1/2 (cat#4379, 1:2,000), anti-Erk1/2 (cat#9102, 1:1,000), <lb/>anti-NCK1 (cat#2319, 1:000) and anti-b-actin (cat#4970, 1:1,000) were obtained <lb/>from Cell Signaling Technology. Anti-SHP-1 (cat#sc-287, 1:200) was from Santa <lb/>Cruz Biotechnology. Anti-Gads (cat#06-983, 2.5 mg ml À 1 ) was from Upstate <lb/>Biotechnology. Goat anti-hamster IgG (cat#55397) was from MP Biomedicals. <lb/>OT-I TCR-specific OVA 257-264 peptide (SIINFEKL) and OT-II TCR-specific <lb/>OVA 323-339 peptide (ISQAVHAAHAEINEAGR) were from ABGENT. OVA 323-339 <lb/>variants, F9 and R9, were from ABGENT and MBL, respectively. OVA 257-264 <lb/>peptide variants, T4 (SIITFEKL) and G4 (SIIGFEKL), were purchased from <lb/>AnaSpec. <lb/>Immunoblotting. Preselection DP thymocytes were obtained from TAP-deficient <lb/>mice transferred with OT-I Tg BM cells. For peptide stimulation, preselection DP <lb/>thymocytes were added with 10 mM OVA peptides followed by centrifugation at <lb/>4 °C for packing, and stimulated at 37 °C. For CD3 cross-linking, cells were stained <lb/>with 10 mg ml À 1 anti-CD3 Ab at 4 °C for 30 min, washed twice with cold medium, <lb/>and then cross-linked by 100 mg ml À 1 goat anti-hamster IgG at 37 °C. After <lb/>stimulation, cells were rapidly transferred on ice and added with cold HEPES <lb/>buffered saline for washing. Then, cells were lysed in lysis buffer containing 1% <lb/>Nonidet P-40, 1 mM PMSF, protease inhibitor cocktail, 10 mM NaF and 1 mM <lb/>Na 3 VO 4 and the lysates were mixed with sample buffer and applied to western blot <lb/>analysis 60 . For Phos-tag immunoblotting, 50 U ml À 1 benzonase (Novagen) was <lb/>also added in RIPA buffer. Images have been cropped for presentation. Full size <lb/>images are presented in Supplementary Figs 8-12. <lb/>Quantitative RT-PCR. For RT-PCR, following primers were used: PKD1 <lb/>(F: 5 0 -ATAACACTCTTCCAAAATGACACAGG-3 0 , R: 5 0 -TCTCCCACATAATA <lb/>CACTACATTCGC-3 0 ), PKD2 (F: 5 0 -GATGAGTTGGAGGATTCTGGTGTC-3 0 , <lb/>R: 5 0 -AGGGTGGTGCTGGATTTCCG-3 0 ), PKD3 (F: 5 0 -AAGAGACATTATTG <lb/>GAGACTTGACAG-3 0 , R: 5 0 -AGTGTGGGTTACTGCCTTGTG-3 0 ), Bcl-2 <lb/>(F: 5 0 -TCCTTCCAGCCTGAGAGCAAC-3 0 , R: 5 0 -CACGACGGTAGCGACG <lb/>AGA-3 0 ), ThPOK (F: 5 0 -GGAGCAGAGCCCCAAGCC-3 0 , R: 5 0 -GATTCCAATCA <lb/>GGTCATCCTCGG-3 0 ), Runx3 (F: 5 0 -AGCACCACGAGCCACTTCAG-3 0 , <lb/>R: 5 0 -TAGGGAAGGAGCGGTCAAACTG-3 0 ), Runx3d (F: 5 0 -AGCACGTCCACC <lb/>ATCGAG-3 0 , R: 5 0 -TGCGACATGGCTTCCAACAG-3 0 ), Nur77 (F: 5 0 -CCACCTC <lb/>TCCGAACCGTGACA-3 0 , R: 5 0 -GAGAAGATTGGTAGGGGAGGC-3 0 ). <lb/>Molecular indexing assay. RNA extracted from DP thymocytes of WT mice was <lb/>reverse-transcribed with oligo(dT) primers containing molecular indexing labels. <lb/>ds cDNA was amplified with gene-specific primers and fluorescent dye-labelled <lb/>universal primers. The number of labels in amplified ds cDNA was detected by <lb/>microarray hybridization with Pixel System (Cellular Research). <lb/>Cell survival assay. Thymocytes were cultured in medium at 37 °C with 5% CO 2 . <lb/>After incubation for different times, cells were stained with APC-conjugated <lb/>anti-CD4, PE-conjugated anti-CD8, FITC-conjugated Annexin V at the <lb/>concentration described in the &apos;Cells and reagents&apos; section and propidium iodide at <lb/>room temperature for 15 min, and immediately analysed by flow cytometry. <lb/>In vivo negative selection model. C57BL/6 (H-2 b ) mice were backcrossed onto <lb/>B10.D2 (H-2 d ) mice and analysed for the expression of Vb5, Vb6 and Vb11. <lb/>Thymocytes expressing Vb5 or Vb11 are deleted by binding of Mtv-8 and Mtv-9 <lb/>superantigens only when I-E is also expressed. Thus, deletion occurs on H-2 b/d but <lb/>not H-2 b/b backgrounds. Thymocytes expressing Vb6 are not deleted by these <lb/>superantigens. <lb/>Two-step differentiation assay. In vitro differentiation of CD4 þ CD8 int <lb/>thymocytes was performed using purified DP thymocyets 26 . Thymocytes in <lb/>RPMI1640 medium supplemented with 10% (v/v) charcoal-and dextran-treated <lb/>FBS were plated on 96-well plates at 5 Â 10 5 cells per well and stimulated for 20 h <lb/>in wells coated with 5 mg ml À 1 anti-TCRb and 10 mg ml À 1 anti-CD2. Cells were <lb/>washed and immediately analysed for CD4 and CD8 expressions by flow cytometry <lb/>(stimulatory culture) or transferred to a new plate, washed extensively, and <lb/>cultured for another 20 h in same medium, followed by the analysis for the <lb/>expression of CD4 and CD8 by flow cytometry (recovery culture). <lb/>Co-receptor downregulation assay (Dulling assay). Co-receptor downregulation <lb/>was examined using OT-II thymocytes or preselection OT-I thymocytes 27 . Overall, <lb/>1 Â 10 5 thioglycollate-induced peritoneal cells were used as APC and pulsed with <lb/>peptides before the addition of thymocytes (1.5 Â 10 5 -5.0 Â 10 5 ) for stimulation of <lb/>OT-II thymocytes. To stimulate preselection OT-I thymocytes, peptides were loaded <lb/>on MHC class I expressed on thymocytes themselves. The expression of CD4 and <lb/>CD8 was analysed by flow cytometry after 16-20 h. <lb/>BM chimera for quantification of redirection. For the analysis of <lb/>CD8-redirection, BM cells from WT or PKD2/3 DT mice were suspended <lb/>in phosphate-buffered saline (PBS) and 1 Â 10 7 cells were injected into <lb/>8 Gy-irradiated TAP À / À mice. Then, 6 weeks after BMT, mice were dissected <lb/>and thymocytes were analysed. For mixed BM transfer, CD3e D5/D5 mice were <lb/>transferred with 5 Â 10 6 each of CD45.1 þ WT and CD45.2 þ SHP-1 S557A/S557A <lb/>BM cells and analysed 4 weeks after BMT. <lb/>Ca 2 þ mobilization. Thymocytes were freshly isolated and loaded with 1.2 mM <lb/>Fluo-4 (Molecular Probes) in phenol red-free RPMI1640 containing 5% FBS for <lb/>30 min at 30 °C. After washing, cells were stained with anti-CD3, phycoerythrin-<lb/>conjugated anti-CD8 and PerCP-Cy5.5 -conjugated anti-CD4 at the concentration <lb/>described in the &apos;Cells and reagents&apos; section for 30 min on ice. Cells were washed, <lb/>suspended in PBS containing 5% FBS, prewarmed to 37 °C before analysis and <lb/>were kept at 37 °C during event collection on FACSCalibur (Becton-Dickinson). <lb/>For cell stimulation, various concentrations of goat anti-hamster IgG were added to <lb/>crosslink anti-CD3 Abs. Maximum Ca 2 þ influx was obtained by the addition of <lb/>10 mM ionomycin (Calbiochem). Mean fluorescence ratio was calculated by FlowJo <lb/>software (Tree Star). <lb/>Intracellular staining. For intracellular staining of phosphorylated proteins, <lb/>thymocytes were stained with anti-CD3, anti-CD4 and anti-CD8 at the <lb/>concentration described in the &apos;Cells and reagents&apos; section for 30 min on ice and <lb/>cross-linked by goat anti-hamster IgG as described above. Cells were washed, fixed <lb/>and permeabilized using cytofix/cytoperm solution (BD Biosciences) for pCD3z, <lb/>pErk, pp38 and pJNK staining or fixation/permeabilization buffer (eBioscience) <lb/>for pZAP70 staining. Data were analysed by FACSCalibur flow cytometer and <lb/>CellQuest software (BD Biosciences). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>2D-DIGE. Thymocytes were freshly isolated and cultured for 16 h to upregulate <lb/>TCR. Cells were then incubated with 10 mg ml À 1 anti-CD3 mAb for 30 min on ice <lb/>and stimulated by cross-linking by 100 mg ml À 1 goat anti-hamster IgG Ab for <lb/>2 min at 37 °C. The unstimulated WT, stimulated WT and stimulated PKD2/3 DT <lb/>cells were lysed and phosphoproteins were enriched using PhosphoProtein <lb/>Purification Kit (Qiagen). The interfering non-protein materials were subsequently <lb/>removed by 2-D Clean Up Kit (GE Healthcare). Overall, 30 mg of the resultant <lb/>phosphoproteins were minimally labelled with 400 pmol Cy2, Cy3 or Cy5 <lb/>fluorescent dye (CyDye DIGE Fluors, GE Healthcare) for 30 min on ice. After <lb/>quenching the labelling reaction with 10 nmol lysine, differentially labelled samples <lb/>were mixed and subjected to first-dimension isoelectric focusing on immobilized <lb/>pH gradient strips (24 cm; pH4-7) using an Ettan IPGphor II system. The <lb/>second-dimensional SDS-PAGE was carried out on 10% acrylamide gel. The Cy2, <lb/>Cy3 and Cy5 signals were individually acquired with a Typhoon 9400 scanner <lb/>(GE Healthcare). <lb/>Phos-tag western blotting. Lysates from thymocytes were subjected to PAGE <lb/>clean up kit (Nacalai tesque) before phosphate-affinity SDS-PAGE is performed <lb/>using 6-7.5% acrylamide gels containing 25 or 50 mM Phos-tag acrylamide (Wako <lb/>chemicals) and 50 or 100 mM MnCl 2 . After electrophoresis, gels were washed in <lb/>Trans-Blot Turbo transfer buffer (Bio-Rad) added with 1 mM EDTA for 15 min <lb/>and then incubated in the buffer without EDTA for 15 min. Proteins were <lb/>transferred to polyvinylidene difluoride (PVDF) membranes using Trans-Blot <lb/>Turbo Transfer System (Bio-Rad) with the program for HIGH molecular weight <lb/>proteins (1.3A, 25 V, 10 min) and analysed by immunoblotting. For l protein <lb/>phosphatase (l PP) treatment, lysates were treated with l PP for 30 min at 30 <lb/>°C <lb/>before purification using PAGE clean up kit. <lb/>Preparation of GST fusion proteins. SHP-1, Gads and NCK1 cDNAs were cloned <lb/>into pGEX-6P-1 vector (GE Healthcare). For the mutant GST fusion proteins, <lb/>Ser 557 and Ser 591 of SHP-1, Ser 186 of Gads and Ser 85 of NCK1 were changed <lb/>to alanine by site-directed mutagenesis. The vectors were transformed into <lb/>E. coli BL21 and GST fusion proteins were purified using glutathione sepharose <lb/>(GE Healthcare). <lb/>In vitro kinase assay. For in vitro kinase assay using [g-32 P]ATP, 2 <lb/>GST-SHP-1, GST-Gads and GST-NCK1 were incubated with 50 ng active PKD2 or <lb/>PKD3 (Carna Bioscience) and 100 mM [g-32 P]ATP (5 mCi) in 20 ml kinase buffer <lb/>(5 mM MgCl 2 and 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH7.5) for 30 min at 30 °C. The reaction was <lb/>stopped by addition of sample buffer followed by heating at 95 °C for 5 min. Half of <lb/>the sample was subjected to 5-20% gradient SDS-PAGE and CBB staining. <lb/>Phosphorylated proteins were visualized by autoradiography. <lb/>Identification of proteins and peptides by LC-MS/MS analysis. The 2D-DIGE <lb/>gel was silver-stained (Thermo Scientific) and protein spots were excised and <lb/>digested with trypsin (Promega). The obtained peptides were analysed by a <lb/>capillary liquid chromatography system (Waters/Micromass) connected to a <lb/>Q-TOF Ultima mass spectrometer (Waters/Micromass). Raw data were acquired <lb/>and processed using MassLynx version 4.0. (Waters/Micromass) to generate a peak <lb/>list file for MS/MS ion search. The peak list files were searched against the NCBI <lb/>non-redundant protein database restricted Mus musculus using the MS/MS ion <lb/>search on Mascot search engine (Matrix Science). To identify in vitro phosphor-<lb/>ylation sites, GST fusion proteins phosphorylated by active PKD2 or PKD3 were <lb/>subjected to SDS-PAGE. The gel was stained with Coomassie Brilliant Blue and <lb/>protein bands were excised and digested with trypsin. The resultant peptides were <lb/>analysed by an ADVANCE UHPLC (Michrom Bioresources) connected to an <lb/>Orbitrap Velos Pro mass spectrometer (for GST-Gads and GST-NCK1) or by an <lb/>EASY-nLC1000 UHPLC (Thermo Fisher Scientific) connected to an Orbitrap <lb/>Fusion Tribrid mass spectrometer (for GST-SHP-1). <lb/>Identification of phosphopeptides by LC-MS/MS analysis. The unstimulated <lb/>WT, stimulated WT and stimulated PKD2/3 DT thymocytes were lysed in buffer <lb/>containing 50 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, 8 M urea, 1 mM DTT and PhosSTOP <lb/>phosphatase inhibitor mixture (Roche). The lysates were sonicated and cleared by <lb/>centrifugation at 20,000g at 4 °C for 15 min. Proteins (each 50 mg) were reduced <lb/>with 5 mM DTT for 30 min and alkylated with 27.5 mM iodoacetamide for 30 min <lb/>in the dark. The urea concentration was then reduced to 1 M before addition of <lb/>0.5 mg trypsin. After 4 h at 37 °C, the digestion was quenched by acidification <lb/>with 0.5% TFA. The digests were desalted using InertSep RP-1 (GL Sciences), <lb/>concentrated and adjusted to binding conditions for TiO 2 -based phosphopeptide <lb/>enrichment (80% acetonitrile, 0.5% TFA and 300 mg ml À 1 lactic acid). <lb/>Phosphopeptides were enriched using 50 mg of Titansphere Phos-TiO column <lb/>(GL Sciences) in accordance with the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. Peptides were <lb/>eluted with 200 ml of 5% ammonia and then with 200 ml of 5% pyrrolidine. <lb/>The collected eluates were acidified with TFA and desalted using GL-Tip SDB <lb/>(GL Sciences). LC-MS/MS analysis of enriched phosphopeptides was performed <lb/>on an EASY-nLC 1200 UHPLC (Thermo Fisher Scientific) connected to a <lb/>Q Exactive Plus mass spectrometer (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The peptides were <lb/>separated on an EASY-Spray column (15 cm Â 75 mm, PepMap C18, 3 mm) with a <lb/>linear gradient from 4 to 28% ACN in 0-100 min followed by increase to 80% ACN <lb/>in 100-110 min. The mass spectrometer was operated in a data-dependent <lb/>acquisition mode with a top 10 MS/MS method. Raw data were converted to the <lb/>mgf files using Proteome Discoverer version 2.0 (Thermo Fisher Scientific), which <lb/>were then searched against the SwissProt database restricted to M. musculus using <lb/>the MS/MS ion search on Mascot search engine. The false discovery rate was set to <lb/>be o0.01. To generate extracted ion chromatograms, the raw data were processed <lb/>using Xcalibur software (Thermo Fisher Scientific). <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability. The mass spectrometry proteomics have been deposited in the <lb/>jPOST repository (https://repository.jpostdb.org) under the accession codes <lb/>JPST000031, JPST000032 and JPST000033. All other data supporting the findings <lb/>of this study are available within the article and Supplementary Information, and <lb/>can also be obtained from the corresponding author upon request. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Singer, A., Adoro, S. &amp; Park, J. H. Lineage fate and intense debate: myths, <lb/>models and mechanisms of CD4-versus CD8-lineage choice. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Immunol. 8, 788-801 (2008). <lb/>2. Chan, A. C., Desai, D. M. &amp; Weiss, A. The role of protein tyrosine kinases and <lb/>protein tyrosine phosphatases in T cell antigen receptor signal transduction. <lb/>Annu. Rev. Immunol. 12, 555-592 (1994). <lb/>3. Matthews, S. A. &amp; Cantrell, D. A. New insights into the regulation and function <lb/>of serine/threonine kinases in T lymphocytes. Immunol. Rev. 228, 241-252 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>4. Cao, Y. et al. LKB1 regulates TCR-mediated PLCgamma1 activation and <lb/>thymocyte positive selection. EMBO J. 30, 2083-2093 (2011). <lb/>5. Hinton, H. J., Alessi, D. R. &amp; Cantrell, D. A. The serine kinase <lb/>phosphoinositide-dependent kinase 1 (PDK1) regulates T cell development. <lb/>Nat. Immunol. 5, 539-545 (2004). <lb/>6. Fayard, E. et al. Deletion of PKBalpha/Akt1 affects thymic development. PLoS <lb/>ONE 2, e992 (2007). <lb/>7. Juntilla, M. M., Wofford, J. A., Birnbaum, M. J., Rathmell, J. C. &amp; Koretzky, G. <lb/>A. Akt1 and Akt2 are required for alphabeta thymocyte survival and <lb/>differentiation. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 104, 12105-12110 (2007). <lb/>8. Gruber, T., Pfeifhofer-Obermair, C. &amp; Baier, G. PKCtheta is necessary for <lb/>efficient activation of NFkappaB, NFAT, and AP-1 during positive selection of <lb/>thymocytes. Immunol. Lett. 132, 6-11 (2010). <lb/>9. Zarrouk, M., Rolf, J. &amp; Cantrell, D. A. LKB1 mediates the development of <lb/>conventional and innate T cells via AMP-dependent kinase autonomous <lb/>pathways. PLoS ONE 8, e60217 (2013). <lb/>10. Raman, V. et al. Requirement for Ca2 þ /calmodulin-dependent kinase type <lb/>IV/Gr in setting the thymocyte selection threshold. J. Immunol. 167, 6270-6278 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>11. Rozengurt, E., Rey, O. &amp; Waldron, R. T. Protein kinase D signaling. J. Biol. <lb/>Chem. 280, 13205-13208 (2005). <lb/>12. Irie, A. et al. Protein kinase D2 contributes to either IL-2 promoter regulation <lb/>or induction of cell death upon TCR stimulation depending on its activity in <lb/>Jurkat cells. Int. Immunol. 18, 1737-1747 (2006). <lb/>13. Matthews, S. A. et al. Unique functions for protein kinase D1 and protein <lb/>kinase D2 in mammalian cells. Biochem. J. 432, 153-163 (2010). <lb/>14. Matthews, S. A., Rozengurt, E. &amp; Cantrell, D. Protein kinase D. A selective <lb/>target for antigen receptors and a downstream target for protein kinase C in <lb/>lymphocytes. J. Exp. Med. 191, 2075-2082 (2000). <lb/>15. Marklund, U., Lightfoot, K. &amp; Cantrell, D. Intracellular location and cell <lb/>context-dependent function of protein kinase D. Immunity 19, 491-501 (2003). <lb/>16. Brownlie, R. J. &amp; Zamoyska, R. T cell receptor signalling networks: branched, <lb/>diversified and bounded. Nat. Rev. Immunol. 13, 257-269 (2013). <lb/>17. Lorenz, U. SHP-1 and SHP-2 in T cells: two phosphatases functioning at many <lb/>levels. Immunol. Rev. 228, 342-359 (2009). <lb/>18. Stefanova, I. et al. TCR ligand discrimination is enforced by competing ERK <lb/>positive and SHP-1 negative feedback pathways. Nat. Immunol. 4, 248-254 <lb/>(2003). <lb/>19. Fu, G. et al. Fine-tuning T cell receptor signaling to control T cell development. <lb/>Trends. Immunol. 35, 311-318 (2014). <lb/>20. Carter, J. D., Neel, B. G. &amp; Lorenz, U. The tyrosine phosphatase SHP-1 <lb/>influences thymocyte selection by setting TCR signaling thresholds. <lb/>Int. Immunol. 11, 1999-2014 (1999). <lb/>21. Germain, R. N. T-cell development and the CD4-CD8 lineage decision. Nat. <lb/>Rev. Immunol. 2, 309-322 (2002). <lb/>22. Pao, L. I., Badour, K., Siminovitch, K. A. &amp; Neel, B. G. Nonreceptor <lb/>protein-tyrosine phosphatases in immune cell signaling. Annu. Rev. Immunol. <lb/>25, 473-523 (2007). <lb/>23. Liu, Y., Kruhlak, M. J., Hao, J. J. &amp; Shaw, S. Rapid T cell receptor-mediated <lb/>SHP-1 S591 phosphorylation regulates SHP-1 cellular localization and <lb/>phosphatase activity. J. Leukoc. Biol. 82, 742-751 (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>24. Fu, G. K., Hu, J., Wang, P. H. &amp; Fodor, S. P. Counting individual DNA <lb/>molecules by the stochastic attachment of diverse labels. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. <lb/>USA 108, 9026-9031 (2011). <lb/>25. Irwin, M. J. &amp; Gascoigne, N. R. Interplay between superantigens and the <lb/>immune system. J. Leukoc. Biol. 54, 495-503 (1993). <lb/>26. Cibotti, R., Punt, J. A., Dash, K. S., Sharrow, S. O. &amp; Singer, A. Surface <lb/>molecules that drive T cell development in vitro in the absence of thymic <lb/>epithelium and in the absence of lineage-specific signals. Immunity 6, 245-255 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>27. Hogquist, K. A. et al. Identification of a naturally occurring ligand for thymic <lb/>positive selection. Immunity 6, 389-399 (1997). <lb/>28. Albrecht, B., Woisetschlager, M. &amp; Robertson, M. W. Export of the <lb/>high affinity IgE receptor from the endoplasmic reticulum depends on <lb/>a glycosylation-mediated quality control mechanism. J. Immunol. 165, <lb/>5686-5694 (2000). <lb/>29. Daniels, M. A. et al. Thymic selection threshold defined by <lb/>compartmentalization of Ras/MAPK signalling. Nature 444, 724-729 (2006). <lb/>30. Liu, X. &amp; Bosselut, R. Duration of TCR signaling controls CD4-CD8 lineage <lb/>differentiation in vivo. Nat. Immunol. 5, 280-288 (2004). <lb/>31. Wang, L. et al. Distinct functions for the transcription factors GATA-3 and <lb/>ThPOK during intrathymic differentiation of CD4( þ ) T cells. Nat. Immunol. <lb/>9, 1122-1130 (2008). <lb/>32. He, X. et al. The zinc finger transcription factor Th-POK regulates CD4 versus <lb/>CD8 T-cell lineage commitment. Nature 433, 826-833 (2005). <lb/>33. Kosako, H. et al. Phosphoproteomics reveals new ERK MAP kinase targets and <lb/>links ERK to nucleoporin-mediated nuclear transport. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. <lb/>16, 1026-1035 (2009). <lb/>34. Yoder, J. et al. Requirement for the SLP-76 adaptor GADS in T cell <lb/>development. Science 291, 1987-1991 (2001). <lb/>35. Roy, E. et al. Fine tuning of the threshold of T cell selection by the Nck <lb/>adapters. J. Immunol. 185, 7518-7526 (2010). <lb/>36. Fu, Y. &amp; Rubin, C. S. Protein kinase D: coupling extracellular stimuli to the <lb/>regulation of cell physiology. EMBO Rep. 12, 785-796 (2011). <lb/>37. Nishikawa, K., Toker, A., Johannes, F. J., Songyang, Z. &amp; Cantley, L. C. <lb/>Determination of the specific substrate sequence motifs of protein kinase C <lb/>isozymes. J. Biol. Chem. 272, 952-960 (1997). <lb/>38. Kaye, J. &amp; Ellenberger, D. L. Differentiation of an immature T cell line: a <lb/>of thymic positive selection. Cell 71, 423-435 (1992). <lb/>39. Muroi, S. et al. Cascading suppression of transcriptional silencers by ThPOK <lb/>seals helper T cell fate. Nat. Immunol. 9, 1113-1121 (2008). <lb/>40. Park, J. H. et al. Signaling by intrathymic cytokines, not T cell antigen receptors, <lb/>specifies CD8 lineage choice and promotes the differentiation of cytotoxic-<lb/>lineage T cells. Nat. Immunol. 11, 257-264 (2010). <lb/>41. Navarro, M. N., Goebel, J., Hukelmann, J. L. &amp; Cantrell, D. A. Quantitative <lb/>phosphoproteomics of cytotoxic T cells to reveal protein kinase D 2 regulated <lb/>networks. Mol. Cell. Proteomics 13, 3544-3557 (2014). <lb/>42. Doppler, H., Storz, P., Li, J., Comb, M. J. &amp; Toker, A. A phosphorylation <lb/>state-specific antibody recognizes Hsp27, a novel substrate of protein kinase D. <lb/>J. Biol. Chem. 280, 15013-15019 (2005). <lb/>43. Fu, G. et al. Themis sets the signal threshold for positive and negative selection <lb/>in T-cell development. Nature 504, 441-445 (2013). <lb/>44. Zvezdova, E. et al. Themis1 enhances T cell receptor signaling during <lb/>thymocyte development by promoting Vav1 activity and Grb2 stability. Sci. <lb/>Signal 9, ra51 (2016). <lb/>45. Azzam, H. S. et al. CD5 expression is developmentally regulated by <lb/>T cell receptor (TCR) signals and TCR avidity. J. Exp. Med. 188, 2301-2311 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>46. Moran, A. E. et al. T cell receptor signal strength in Treg and iNKT cell <lb/>development demonstrated by a novel fluorescent reporter mouse. J. Exp. Med. <lb/>208, 1279-1289 (2011). <lb/>47. Sakaguchi, N. et al. Altered thymic T-cell selection due to a mutation of the <lb/>ZAP-70 gene causes autoimmune arthritis in mice. Nature 426, 454-460 <lb/>(2003). <lb/>48. Yamazaki, T. et al. A shift from negative to positive selection of autoreactive <lb/>T cells by the reduced level of TCR signal in TCR-transgenic CD3 zeta-deficient <lb/>mice. J. Immunol. 158, 1634-1640 (1997). <lb/>49. Sankarshanan, M., Ma, Z., Iype, T. &amp; Lorenz, U. Identification of a novel lipid <lb/>raft-targeting motif in Src homology 2-containing phosphatase 1. J. Immunol. <lb/>179, 483-490 (2007). <lb/>50. Rangaswami, H. et al. Cyclic GMP and protein kinase G control a <lb/>Src-containing mechanosome in osteoblasts. Sci. Signal 3, ra91 (2010). <lb/>51. Johnson, D. J. et al. Shp1 regulates T cell homeostasis by limiting IL-4 signals. <lb/>J. Exp. Med. 210, 1419-1431 (2013). <lb/>52. Dequiedt, F. et al. Phosphorylation of histone deacetylase 7 by protein kinase D <lb/>mediates T cell receptor-induced Nur77 expression and apoptosis. J. Exp. Med. <lb/>201, 793-804 (2005). <lb/>53. Kasler, H. G. et al. Histone deacetylase 7 regulates cell survival and TCR <lb/>signaling in CD4/CD8 double-positive thymocytes. J. Immunol. 186, <lb/>4782-4793 (2011). <lb/>54. Fu, G. et al. Protein kinase C eta is required for T cell activation and <lb/>homeostatic proliferation. Sci. Signal 4, ra84 (2011). <lb/>55. Kondo, M., Akashi, K., Domen, J., Sugamura, K. &amp; Weissman, I. L. Bcl-2 <lb/>rescues T lymphopoiesis, but not B or NK cell development, in common <lb/>gamma chain-deficient mice. Immunity 7, 155-162 (1997). <lb/>56. Malissen, M. et al. Altered T cell development in mice with a targeted mutation <lb/>of the CD3-epsilon gene. EMBO J. 14, 4641-4653 (1995). <lb/>57. Chaffin, K. E. et al. Dissection of thymocyte signaling pathways by in vivo <lb/>expression of pertussis toxin ADP-ribosyltransferase. EMBO J. 9, 3821-3829 <lb/>(1990). <lb/>58. Taniuchi, I. et al. Differential requirements for Runx proteins in CD4 <lb/>repression and epigenetic silencing during T lymphocyte development. Cell <lb/>111, 621-633 (2002). <lb/>59. Poirier, G., Lo, D., Reilly, C. R. &amp; Kaye, J. Discrimination between thymic <lb/>epithelial cells and peripheral antigen-presenting cells in the induction of <lb/>immature T cell differentiation. Immunity 1, 385-391 (1994). <lb/>60. Ishikawa, E., Miyake, Y., Hara, H., Saito, T. &amp; Yamasaki, S. Germ-line <lb/>elimination of electric charge on pre-T-cell receptor (TCR) impairs <lb/>autonomous signaling for beta-selection and TCR repertoire formation. Proc. <lb/>Natl Acad. Sci. USA 107, 19979-19984 (2010). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank M. Sakuma, M. Kurata and M. Kawano for technical assistance; Y. Ohkawa <lb/>and T. Iwabuchi for analyzing data; I. Taniuchi for constructs; N. Tani, A.C. Yoshizawa, <lb/>A. Nakai, I. Sagawa, D. Higo, E. Koba and M. Matsumoto for MS analyses; M.Y. Kimura <lb/>and H. Takayanagi for discussion; and Laboratory for Technical Support, Medical <lb/>Institute of Bioregulation, Kyushu University for technical support. This research was <lb/>supported by Grant-in-Aid for Young Scientists (B) (25860365) and for Scientific <lb/>Research (C) (16K08841) (E.I.) from Japan Society for the Promotion of Science, Joint <lb/>Usage/Research Center for Multi-scale Research of Host Defense Systems from MEXT <lb/>and Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research on Innovative Areas (26110009)(S.Y.) from <lb/>MEXT. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>E.I. performed experiments, analysed data and wrote the manuscript; H.K. performed <lb/>experiments and analysed data; T.Y., M.O., K.A. and T.K. contributed to development of <lb/>the mice; T.S. provided experimental mice and S.Y. designed the research, performed <lb/>experiments and wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional information <lb/>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ <lb/>naturecommunications <lb/>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/>Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ <lb/>reprintsandpermissions/ <lb/></div>

			<front>How to cite this article: Ishikawa, E. et al. Protein kinase D regulates positive selection of <lb/>CD4 þ thymocytes through phosphorylation of SHP-1. Nat. Commun. 7:12756 <lb/>doi: 10.1038/ncomms12756 (2016). <lb/>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 <lb/>International License. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise <lb/>in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, <lb/>users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. <lb/>To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ <lb/>r The Author(s) 2016 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 7:12756 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms12756 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </note>


	</text>
</tei>
