<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>Emergence of event cascades in <lb/>inhomogeneous networks <lb/>Tomokatsu Onaga &amp; Shigeru Shinomoto <lb/>There is a commonality among contagious diseases, tweets, and neuronal firings that past events <lb/>facilitate the future occurrence of events. The spread of events has been extensively studied such <lb/>that the systems exhibit catastrophic chain reactions if the interaction represented by the ratio of <lb/>reproduction exceeds unity; however, their subthreshold states are not fully understood. Here, we <lb/>report that these systems are possessed by nonstationary cascades of event-occurrences already in the <lb/>subthreshold regime. Event cascades can be harmful in some contexts, when the peak-demand causes <lb/>vaccine shortages, heavy traffic on communication lines, but may be beneficial in other contexts, such <lb/>that spontaneous activity in neural networks may be used to generate motion or store memory. Thus <lb/>it is important to comprehend the mechanism by which such cascades appear, and consider controlling <lb/>a system to tame or facilitate fluctuations in the event-occurrences. The critical interaction for the <lb/>emergence of cascades depends greatly on the network structure in which individuals are connected. <lb/>We demonstrate that we can predict whether cascades may emerge, given information about the <lb/>interactions between individuals. Furthermore, we develop a method of reallocating connections <lb/>among individuals so that event cascades may be either impeded or impelled in a network. <lb/></front>

			<body>Our life is full of cause-and-effect relationships, such that past events influence the future occurrence of events. <lb/>The proliferation process has been studied using both macroscopic models, such as the epidemic model 1 , and <lb/>microscopic models, such as the self-exciting point process proposed by Hawkes 2,3 . These models have been <lb/>applied to analyze not only the communication of diseases 4-8 but also urban crime 9 , human activity 10-14 , econom-<lb/>ics 15 , genome sequences 16 , and neuronal firing 17,18 . A key quantity representing the interaction in these various <lb/>phenomena is the basic reproduction ratio, which is defined as the average number of additional events induced <lb/>by a single event 19 . In epidemics, a disease becomes a pandemic in a homogeneous network if the reproduction <lb/>ratio is greater than unity, as in a nuclear chain reaction 20-22 , and vanishes otherwise. <lb/>Nevertheless, the event-occurrence does not cease if individuals are stimulated in external communities or <lb/>exhibit spontaneous activity. In such situations, the system may still exhibit cascades of event-occurrences inter-<lb/>mittently, even if the reproduction ratio is smaller than the epidemic threshold, as in tweets 11,23,24 and neuronal <lb/>firings in vivo 25 . The nonstationary fluctuations may be terminated by reducing the reproduction ratio further 26 . <lb/>Event cascades can be a nuisance in some contexts, such as when the peak-demand causes vaccine shortages 27,28 <lb/>or heavy traffic on communication lines 29 , but may be beneficial in other contexts; for example, spontaneous <lb/>activity in neural networks may be used to generate motion or store memory 30-32 . Thus, it is important to com-<lb/>prehend the mechanism by which such cascades appear. We show that such a transition between stationary and <lb/>nonstationary states generally occurs in every proliferation system, obtain the condition on which cascades may <lb/>emerge in a given network, and suggest a systematic method for controlling systems to oppress or promote the <lb/>event-occurrence bursts. <lb/>Results <lb/>Mean rate of event-occurrence. Although the epidemic model and the Hawkes process appear to differ <lb/>from one another, they have something in common because both were constructed to describe the proliferation <lb/>processes. To identify their common features, we first revise them by considering realistic constraints. <lb/>For an epidemic model, we consider the susceptible-infected-susceptible (SIS) model describing the situation <lb/>in which infected individuals may recover without immunity: <lb/>β <lb/>γ <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>di dt <lb/>si <lb/>i <lb/>/ <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/></body>

			<front>Department of Physics, Kyoto University, Kyoto 606-8502, Japan. Correspondence and requests for materials should <lb/>be addressed to S.S. (email: shinomoto@scphys.kyoto-u.ac.jp) <lb/>received: 05 April 2016 <lb/>Accepted: 24 August 2016 <lb/>Published: 14 September 2016 <lb/>OPEN <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>where i and s are the fractions of infected and susceptible individuals, respectively (i + s = 1); β is the rate at which <lb/>susceptible individuals are infected by contacting infected individuals; and γ is the rate at which infected individ-<lb/>uals recover and regain susceptibility. The infected individuals asymptotically vanish if the reproduction ratio <lb/>R 0 = β/γ is smaller than or equal to unity; otherwise, the fraction is finite: ≡ <lb/>= − <lb/>∞ <lb/>→ ∞ <lb/>i <lb/>i t <lb/>R <lb/>lim <lb/>( ) 1 1/ <lb/>t <lb/>0 . To con-<lb/>sider extrinsic or spontaneous activation, we suggest revising the SIS model by adding an inflow to the infected <lb/>population from the susceptible one: <lb/>β <lb/>γ <lb/>ρ <lb/>= <lb/>− + . <lb/>di dt <lb/>si <lb/>i <lb/>s <lb/>/ <lb/>(2) <lb/>In the presence of spontaneous activity ρ(&gt;0), the asymptotic fraction of infected individuals remains positive <lb/>and smoothly increases with R 0 , and, accordingly, the epidemic transition at R 0 = is softened (Fig. 1a). <lb/>The Hawkes process considers spontaneous occurrences in terms of the positive base rate ρ and describes the <lb/>manner in which the event-occurrence rate λ(t) is modulated by past events: <lb/>∑ <lb/>λ <lb/>ρ <lb/>= + <lb/>− <lb/>t <lb/>R <lb/>h t t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>), <lb/>(3) <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>0 <lb/>where t k is the occurrence time of the kth event. The history kernel h(t) satisfies the causality, h(t) = 0 for t &lt; 0, and <lb/>the normalization, ∫ <lb/>= <lb/>∞ h t dt <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>. By taking the ensemble average, the average rate of event-occurrence is <lb/>obtained as 〈λ(t)〉 = ρ/(1 − R 0 ). The divergence at R 0 = 1 arises from instantaneous reactivation, which is an arti-<lb/>fact caused by the simplicity of the linear model, which ignores the refractory period during which each individ-<lb/>ual does not recover susceptibility. Here, we suggest revising the model by introducing the effect of a refractory <lb/>period 1/γ: <lb/>∑ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>γ <lb/>ρ <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>. <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>R <lb/>h t t <lb/>( ) <lb/>1 <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(4) <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>0 <lb/>By taking an ensemble average and approximating 〈λ 2 〉 with 〈λ〉 2 , we obtain the average rate of event-occurrences <lb/>as 〈λ〉 = γi ∞ , where i ∞ is the asymptotic fraction obtained for the revised SIS model (Fig. 1b). Thus, the epidemic <lb/>model and the Hawkes process may represent the identical mean occurrence rate by taking the spontaneous acti-<lb/>vation and the refractory periods into account. <lb/>Fluctuations in the event-occurrence. Although the systems no longer exhibit a clear transition at R 0 = 1 <lb/>causing the catastrophic chain reaction, they may still show nonstationary fluctuations with intermittent cascades <lb/>of event-occurrences at lower reproduction ratios; when the reproduction ratio is even smaller, they may remain <lb/>stationary, producing apparently random events over time. <lb/>The SIS model that addresses the mean population dynamics cannot represent fluctuations in the <lb/>event-occurrences. Here, we construct and simulate a Markov process of microscopic dynamics in which indi-<lb/>viduals become infected and recover to be susceptible (Fig. 2a). In every interval of a small time-step δt, each <lb/>susceptible individual in total population of size N may become infected with a probability (βi + ρ)δt, which <lb/>Figure 1. Mean occurrence rate obtained by the revised epidemic model and the revised Hawkes process. <lb/>(a) The equilibrium fraction of infected individuals i ∞ obtained by the susceptible-infected-susceptible (SIS) <lb/>model revised by considering spontaneous activity ρ &gt; 0. (b) The mean occurrence rate 〈λ〉 of the Hawkes <lb/>process revised by introducing the refractory period 1/γ &gt; 0. These models give identical equilibria, 〈λ〉 = γi ∞ , <lb/>for the same spontaneous activation ρ and the refractory period 1/γ (magenta lines in (a,b)). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>shifts as i → i + 1/N. Each infected individual may regain their susceptibility with the probability γδt, which shifts <lb/>as i → i − 1/N. Figure 2b depicts sample sequences of infected times: At a reproduction ratio of R 0 = β/γ = 0.2, <lb/>the occurrence of infection appears random across individuals but stationary in the whole system. By contrast, <lb/>at R 0 = 0.6 or 0.8, the event sequence appears nonstationary, exhibiting spontaneous cascades of occurrences. <lb/>Indeed, microscopic fluctuations are amplified to be macroscopically visible, whereas the average rate is restrained <lb/>to be finite. <lb/>We suggest deciding whether a given series of events is stationary or nonstationary based on whether proper <lb/>rate estimators conclude a constant rate or a fluctuating rate, respectively. Here, we adopt a method of selecting <lb/>the histogram bin size to minimize the expected mean square error between the histogram and the unknown <lb/>underlying rate . Note that the decision regarding stationary vs nonstationary state is common across proper rate <lb/>estimators, such as the Empirical Bayes and variational Bayes Hidden Markov estimators 34 . <lb/>Histograms were fitted to the data: The optimal bin size Δ * was diverging (becoming as large as the entire <lb/>observation period) when R 0 = 0.2, whereas it was finite (significantly smaller than the entire period) when <lb/>R 0 = 0.6 and 0.8. Figure 2c depicts the manner in which the inverse bin size 1/Δ * varies with the reproduction <lb/>ratio R 0 . 1/Δ * remains near zero if R 0 is smaller than approximately 0.3, and it departs from zero otherwise, thus <lb/>exhibiting the stationary-nonstationary (SN) transition. <lb/>We also simulated the revised Hawkes process (4) with parameters identical to those used for the epidemic <lb/>Markov process. Here, events are indicated by repeating the Bernoulli trials with a probability of λ(t)δt in every <lb/>small interval of δt. By plotting 1/Δ * versus R 0 , we can also observe the transition (Fig. 2c). Figure 2d depicts the <lb/>critical reproduction ratios obtained for the epidemic Markov process and the revised Hawkes process plotted <lb/>against the refractory period 1/γ, indicating that the SN critical points for both models are robustly close to <lb/>− <lb/>≈ . <lb/>1 1/ 2 <lb/>0 3, which was obtained for the original (linear) Hawkes process (1/γ = 0) in our previous study 26 . <lb/>Note that the critical point is independent of the shape of the kernel, as well as the base rate. <lb/>Event-occurrences in inhomogeneous networks. Finally, we consider the emergence of cascades in a <lb/>population of individuals interacting through inhomogeneous connections. <lb/>To obtain the condition for the SN transition analytically, we analyze the linear multivariate Hawkes processes <lb/>(Fig. 3a). The rate of event-occurrences in the ith individual or node (i = 1, 2, •••, N) is given as <lb/>∑ ∑ <lb/>λ <lb/>ρ <lb/>α <lb/>= + <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>t <lb/>h t t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>), <lb/>(5) <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>N <lb/>ij <lb/>k <lb/>j <lb/>k <lb/>1 <lb/>where ρ i represents the base rate, t j <lb/>k is the occurrence time of the kth event in the jth node, and α ij represents the <lb/>interaction from the jth node to the ith node. Because of the interactions between individuals, A ≡ {α ij }, the aver-<lb/>age rates 〈λ〉 = {〈λ i 〉} are shifted from the base rates ρ = {ρ i } as 〈λ〉 = Lρ, where L is the Leontief inverse 35 : <lb/>≡ ∑ <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>∞ <lb/>L <lb/>A <lb/>I I A <lb/>/( <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>0 <lb/>. <lb/>Figure 2. Stationary-nonstationary (SN) transition in the epidemic Markov process and the revised <lb/>Hawkes process. (a) Microscopic epidemic Markov process. (b) Sample sequences of infected times obtained <lb/>by the epidemic Markov processes (model parameters: β = 0.06, 0.18, and 0.24, with γ = 0.3, ρ = 0.5, and <lb/>N = 1000). Below the raster diagrams are the fitted optimal histograms. (c) Inverse optimal binsize 1/Δ * plotted <lb/>against the reproduction ratio R 0 (γ = 0.3, ρ = 0.5, and N = 1000). (d) Critical points of the SN transition R c for <lb/>the epidemic Markov and revised Hawkes processes, plotted against the refractory period 1/γ. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>Even when the fluctuations are not detectable at any single node, all events occurring in the entire set of nodes <lb/>may exhibit visible fluctuations because the signal-to-noise ratio may increase when multiple series of events are <lb/>superposed (Fig. 3b). By analyzing equation (5), we obtain the condition for a series of events occurring in an <lb/>entire population to be nonstationary, or cascading (see Methods): <lb/>λ <lb/>Λ <lb/>≡ <lb/>∑ <lb/>∑ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>L L <lb/>C <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2, <lb/>(6) <lb/>i j <lb/>T <lb/>ij <lb/>i <lb/>i <lb/>, <lb/>where Λ ≡ diag(〈λ〉). <lb/>Here, we consider 0-1 connectivity with strength α ij = 0 or R 0 /Nc, where c is the fraction of connections. For <lb/>a fully connected uniform network (c = 1), the summed rate λ <lb/>λ <lb/>= ∑ = <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>i <lb/>N <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>obeys the original Hawkes process <lb/>equation (3) with ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>= ∑ = <lb/>i <lb/>N <lb/>i <lb/>1 , thus the entire system may exhibit the SN transition at = − <lb/>≈ . <lb/>R 1 1/ 2 <lb/>0 3 <lb/>c <lb/>. For <lb/>sparsely connected networks in which every pair of nodes is randomly linked at a fraction of c, the SN critical <lb/>point R c remains near 0.3. <lb/>Nevertheless, it is possible to shift the cascading condition C by reallocating the connections between indi-<lb/>viduals by conserving the fraction of connections c; exchanging connections α ij and α i′j′ may alter the cascading <lb/>condition C by <lb/> <lb/>α <lb/>α <lb/>λ <lb/>∆ = − <lb/>− <lb/>∑ <lb/>+ <lb/>′ ′ <lb/>′ ′ <lb/>C <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>R N <lb/>( / ) , <lb/>(7) <lb/>ij ij <lb/>i j <lb/>i j <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>where H ij ≡ ((∑ k L ki ) 2 − C)ρ j + 2(∑ k L kj )〈λ j 〉. To raise or lower C, we repeat exchanging a pair of connections that <lb/>maximizes or minimizes ΔC (Fig. 4a). <lb/>A network may change the state from stationary to nonstationary if the cascading condition C steps across <lb/>the critical value of 2 from below or vice versa by reconnecting individuals. Figure 4b demonstrates the manner <lb/>in which C is altered by the steepest ascent or descent based on equation (7). When (R 0 , c) = (0.1, 0.1), C remains <lb/>below 2, even when all connections are reallocated; however, when (R 0 , c) = (0.35, 0.1), C exceeds 2, indicating <lb/>that the system may change between nonstationary (C &gt; 2) and stationary (C ≤ 2). <lb/>In the study of epidemics, whether the epidemic threshold is higher in the clustered networks 8,36,37 or not 38 <lb/>has been controversial. Here, we are not addressing the epidemic transition, but we are interested in how the <lb/>clustering of individuals influences the SN transition. Figure 4c depicts the manner in which the average cluster-<lb/>ing coefficient changes with our gradient ascent or descent of C, indicating that clustering tends to facilitate the <lb/>event-occurrence cascades. A similar tendency was reported in neural network simulations 32 . An advantage of <lb/>our method is that we can control the cascade bursting activity by systematically rearranging connections based <lb/>on a single measure: C. <lb/>Figure 4d depicts the range of (R , c) in which a network of a large size N may exhibit stationary and nonsta-<lb/>tionary states. In the &quot;Stationary&quot; regime, the systems never generate visible cascades, even when connections are <lb/>reallocated, whereas in the &quot;Nonstationary&quot; regime, the systems always exhibit cascades. In the &quot;S-N 0&quot; regime, <lb/>networks may be either stationary or nonstationary, depending on the manner in which individuals are con-<lb/>nected. In the &quot;S-N 1&quot; regime, networks may be either stationary or nonstationary if the reciprocal connections <lb/>b <lb/>i <lb/>j <lb/>j′ <lb/>α ij <lb/>α ij&apos; <lb/>a <lb/>{t k <lb/>j } <lb/>{t k <lb/>j&apos; } <lb/>λ i (t) <lb/>{t k <lb/>i } <lb/>λ i (t) <lb/>t <lb/>α ij <lb/>t <lb/>δt <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>... <lb/>= <lb/>Figure 3. Multivariate Hawkes process. (a) The rate of event-occurrences in each node is modulated by the <lb/>influence of events generated at other nodes, and events are derived from the underlying rate λ i (t). (b) The <lb/>manner in which the nonstationary fluctuations become visible by superposing event series in individual nodes. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>can be controlled independently, whereas undirected networks, whose connections are reciprocally symmetric <lb/>{α ij = α ji }, remain nonstationary, always generating cascades of events. For undirected networks, the critical point <lb/>R c appears to be bounded at approximately 0.3. <lb/>As extreme configurations with low critical points, we considered networks of (i): the nodes of one group are <lb/>fully connected within the group, and the others are isolated; and (ii): the nodes of one group are fully connected <lb/>within the group and also receive undirected (reciprocal) connections from all nodes of another group. The criti-<lb/>cal points R c exhibit crossover at c = 0.20, and above and below this point, those of (i) and (ii) are lower. The crit-<lb/>icality in low R 0 implies that these configurations tend to facilitate cascade bursting. As an opposite extreme, we <lb/>considered another configuration (iii): each node of one group receives only directed connections from another <lb/>group. We also considered a specific hierarchical networks of (iv): every node exerts the influence over the lower <lb/>hierarchy nodes in a manner that connections form a triangular matrix. All critical points for these specific <lb/>cases are obtained analytically (see Methods) and plotted in Fig. 4d: The configurations (i) and (ii) tend to incite <lb/>bursting, whereas the configurations (iii) and (iv) impede bursting. These observations imply that networks in <lb/>which small number of individuals occupy reciprocal connections favor event cascade bursting, whereas directed <lb/>unilateral connections tend to impede cascades. <lb/>Any network exhibits the SN transition within the range of S-N 0 or S-N 1 on a plane of (R 0 , c), independently <lb/>of the system size N (Fig. 4d). The precise transition point within the transition range is determined by the net-<lb/>work configuration A ≡ {α ij }. Here we examine the SN transition in representative network models, such as the <lb/>scale-free network (Barabási-Albert model) 39 , the random network (Erdös-Rényi model) 40 , and the small-world <lb/>network (Watts-Strogatz model) 41 assuming reciprocal connections. In particular, we compare the SN critical <lb/>points R c of those networks of identical number of nodes N and the fraction of connections inversely proportional <lb/>to the number of nodes c = 6/N (Fig. 5). The scale-free network is assembled with the Barabási-Albert model. The <lb/>small-world network is made by rewiring a regular ring lattice with the rewiring probability p = 0.1. The critical <lb/>point R c in the scale-free network is the lowest among those networks, implying that the wide disparity in degrees <lb/>(numbers of connections) of individual nodes may facilitate the fluctuations in event occurrences. By obtaining <lb/>the average critical point analytically, we may confirm that R c → 0 as N → ∞ (see Methods). It is interesting to see <lb/>that R c is higher in the small-world network than in the Erdös-Rényi model. This may also be closely related to the <lb/>difference in degrees; the small-world network of the small rewiring probability exhibits the smaller degree dis-<lb/>persion than the Erdös-Rényi model. Indeed, a regular ring lattice in which individual degrees are identical gives <lb/>the highest critical point R c = 0.2929, which is equal to the critical point of a fully connected uniform network, <lb/>Figure 4. Controlling the emergence of event-occurrence cascades. (a) Elementary process of exchanging <lb/>connections α ij and α i′j′ . (b) The manner in which the potential for the cascades C is altered by the steepest <lb/>ascent or descent based on equation (7), starting from the Erdös-Rényi models. The blue and green lines <lb/>represent the cases of (R 0 , c) = (0.1, 0.1), and (0.35, 0.1), respectively (N = 100). (c) Changes in the average <lb/>clustering coefficient according to the reallocation of connections when (R 0 , c) = (0.35, 0.1). (d) Parameter <lb/>ranges of (R 0 , c) in which the networks may be either stationary or nonstationary. Some solvable extreme <lb/>configurations that give low and high critical points in R 0 are depicted. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>− <lb/>1 1/ 2 . In this way, the SN transition points R c can be different, crucially depending on the network structure, <lb/>in particular on the degree dispersion. <lb/>Finally we demonstrate the manner in which the network is reconnected by our method for inciting or imped-<lb/>ing cascades (Fig. 6); we take up the network of &quot;Zachary&apos;s Karate Club&quot; 42 and reallocate the (undirected) friend-<lb/>ships between 34 people. By assuming that the original network is at the criticality C = 2, we reorganized the <lb/>network so that their entire communication becomes stationary or nonstationary. The operation to impede the <lb/>communication cascades (ΔC &lt; 0) tended to make all people be connected harmoniously. Contrariwise, the <lb/>operation to incite the cascade (ΔC &gt; 0) made the society polarized into two kinds of people; a few people have <lb/>exclusive rich connections, while others are connected only with those people. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Here, we showed that the proliferation process may exhibit the SN transition at which nonstationary cascades <lb/>of event-occurrences emerge from the stationary process. The critical reproduction ratio for the SN transition <lb/>R c is much smaller than the threshold for the conventional epidemic transition exhibiting chain reactions. The <lb/>SN transition may depend greatly on the manner in which individuals are connected. We developed a theory <lb/>for predicting the occurrence of cascades in a network. We also suggested a method of reconnecting individuals <lb/>for impeding or inciting cascade bursting in a network. It was revealed that networks of reciprocal connections <lb/>exhibiting wide disparity in degrees of individual nodes are apt to trigger the event cascades. <lb/>Note that the term &quot;cascade&quot; has also been used differently in other contexts, as expressing transient phe-<lb/>nomena of event spreads, as in failures in a power grid, chain bankruptcies, and information cascades in social <lb/>systems 43-45 . Though their basic process is similar to that of our SN transition, the situations are different; we <lb/>considered here the fluctuations in the process of event occurrences that involves constant spontaneous activity <lb/>or external activation such that individuals are continually generating events at a finite probability. <lb/>In this study, we revealed that nonstationary fluctuations may occur autonomously in a static network without <lb/>environmental fluctuations. In real-world circumstances, however, both connections and environmental inputs <lb/>may change in time, and the event cascades may have been induced by such extrinsic cause. Thus it may be an <lb/>important direction in future to consider discerning the factor that may have contributed to the observed fluctu-<lb/>ations, namely, whether the fluctuations were originated intrinsically or extrinsically. <lb/>To set about applying our theory to real-world problems, we should also consider adapting models to indi-<lb/>vidual situations, by collecting information regarding interactions among individuals. Interactions in epidemic <lb/>networks may be inferred by getting hold of information of contacts between individuals and estimating the <lb/>infectivity of the disease. Interactions in neural networks may be estimated by detecting the synaptic connections <lb/>and measuring the strength of connections such as excitatory or inhibitory postsynaptic potentials. If the infor-<lb/>mation of interactions is given, we can predict whether the network may exhibit nonstationary fluctuations, using <lb/>the theory developed here. However, it is practically difficult to obtain the entire information of the interactions <lb/>among all pairs of existing nodes. Thus it is useful to devise a method of complementing information of the entire <lb/>network from partial observation, and furthermore, to suggest controlling systems by manipulating partially <lb/>available links. <lb/>Figure 5. Stationary-nonstationary (SN) transitions in representative complex networks. (a) The manner <lb/>in which the critical reproduction ratio R c varies with the number of nodes N in the scale-free network <lb/>(Barabási-Albert model), the random network (Erdös-Rényi model), and the small-world network (Watts-<lb/>Strogatz model), possessing reciprocal connections. In all networks, the fraction of connections varied inversely <lb/>proportional to the system size as c = 6/N. (b) Dependence of R c on c plotted on a plane in Fig. 4d. The error <lb/>bars represent standard deviation for 100 sample networks. The dashed line represents the average critical point <lb/>analytically obtained for the scale-free network. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>Methods <lb/>Derivation of the condition for the SN transition. Here, we derive the condition for the SN transition <lb/>for a given series of events. It has been proven that the optimal bin size may be finite if fluctuation in the underly-<lb/>ing rate δλ(t) ≡ λ(t) − 〈λ〉 satisfies the condition 34,46 <lb/>∫ <lb/>λ <lb/>δλ <lb/>δλ <lb/>+ <lb/>&gt; <lb/>−∞ <lb/>∞ <lb/>t s <lb/>t ds <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) ( ) <lb/>1, <lb/>(8) <lb/>and diverges otherwise. This condition (8) is derived as follows. The mean square error between the underlying <lb/>rate λ(t) and the histogram λ t <lb/>( ) is given as <lb/>∫ λ <lb/>λ <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>→∞Ŝ <lb/>T <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>dt <lb/>lim <lb/>1 <lb/>( ( ) <lb/>( )) <lb/>, <lb/>(9) <lb/>T <lb/>T <lb/>0 <lb/>where T is the entire observation interval, and the bracket represents the ensemble average over the possible real-<lb/>ization of the stochastic process. In each bin of size Δ, the histogram λ t <lb/>( ) is a constant whose height is the number <lb/>of events K divided by the bin size Δ. Thus, the mean square error is transformed as <lb/>∫ λ <lb/>λ <lb/>= <lb/>∆ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>− <lb/>∆ <lb/>+ <lb/>∆ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>. <lb/>∆ <lb/>S <lb/>t <lb/>K t <lb/>K dt <lb/>1 <lb/>( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>( ) <lb/>(10) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>The expected number of events in each interval is given by integrating the underlying rate: <lb/>∫ λ <lb/>= <lb/>∆ <lb/>K <lb/>tdt <lb/>( ) <lb/>0 <lb/>. <lb/>Because events are independently drawn, the Poisson relation holds: 〈K 2 〉 = 〈K〉 2 + 〈K〉. Inserting these relations <lb/>into equation (10), we have <lb/>∫ ∫ <lb/>φ <lb/>λ <lb/>φ <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>∆ <lb/>− <lb/>∆ <lb/>∆ <lb/>− <lb/>S <lb/>d t <lb/>sds <lb/>(0) <lb/>1 <lb/>( ) , <lb/>(11) <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>0 <lb/>where φ(s) ≡ 〈λ(t + s)λ(t)〉 − 〈λ〉 2 is the correlation of the rate fluctuation or φ(s) = 〈δλ(t + s)δλ(t)〉, where <lb/>δλ(t) ≡ λ(t) − 〈λ〉 is the temporal fluctuation of the rate. The mean square error may have a minimum at some <lb/>finite Δ. Based on the second-order transition in which the minimum position Δ * goes to infinity or 1/Δ * goes to <lb/>zero continuously, the condition for the transition is given as <lb/>∆ <lb/>&lt; . <lb/>∆=∞ <lb/>dS <lb/>d(1/ ) <lb/>0 <lb/>(12) <lb/>This can be summed up as a condition of the rate fluctuation given in inequality (8) if ∫ φ <lb/>∞ s s ds <lb/>( ) <lb/>0 <lb/>is finite. This <lb/>condition was derived from the optimization of a histogram and was found to be identical to that derived from <lb/>the marginal likelihood maximization of the Bayesian rate estimator, implying that this condition may be a uni-<lb/>versal bound for detecting rate fluctuation 47 . <lb/>Figure 6. Reallocating connections between individuals. (a) The manner in which the (undirected) friendships <lb/>between 34 people in &quot;Zachary&apos;s Karate Club&quot; are reconnected by increasing or decreasing C, respectively for <lb/>inciting or impeding cascades of communications. (b) The change in the potential for the cascades C with the <lb/>steepest ascent (rightward) or descent (leftward) based on equation (7), (c) Average clustering coefficient. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>For the linear self-exciting point process, the power spectrum of the rate fluctuation or the Fourier transfor-<lb/>mation of the autocorrelation φ(s) ≡ 〈δλ(t + s)δλ(t)〉 was obtained by Hawkes 2 . The result can be summarized as 26 <lb/>φ <lb/>λ <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    − <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>ω <lb/>ω <lb/>ω <lb/>− <lb/>∼ <lb/>∼ <lb/>∼ <lb/>R h <lb/>R h <lb/>1 <lb/>(1 <lb/>)(1 <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>, <lb/>(13) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>where ω <lb/>∼ <lb/>h is the Fourier transform of the kernel function h(t). Because <lb/>∫ <lb/>∫ <lb/>φ <lb/>φ <lb/>δ λ <lb/>δ λ <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>−∞ <lb/>∞ <lb/>−∞ <lb/>∞ <lb/>∼ <lb/>s ds <lb/>t s <lb/>t ds <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) ( ) <lb/>, <lb/>the condition for the linear self-exciting process to be nonstationary is obtained as 1/(1 − R 0 ) 2 &gt; 2. Thus, the SN <lb/>transition occurs at = − <lb/>R <lb/>1 1/ 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>independent of the time course of supplementary probability h(t) and the <lb/>base rate ρ. <lb/>The multivariate Hawkes process (5) is also analytically tractable; in particular, the Fourier zero-mode of the <lb/>correlations φ(s) ≡ {φ ij (s)} ≡ {〈δλ i (t + s)δλ j (t)〉} is obtained as 3,26 , <lb/>φ <lb/>Λ <lb/>Λ <lb/>= <lb/>− . <lb/>∼ <lb/>L L <lb/>(14) <lb/>T <lb/>0 <lb/>Each node may exhibit the SN criticality if the correlation of each individual, φ ii (s), satisfies the SN condition. <lb/>Even when rate fluctuations are not detectable at any single node, the summed activity of multiple nodes may <lb/>exhibit fluctuations. The condition for the superposed series to exhibit the SN transition is obtained by applying <lb/>the nonstationary condition (8) to the summed rate λ <lb/>λ <lb/>= ∑ = <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>i <lb/>N <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>, thus leading to the cascading condition, <lb/>equation (6). <lb/>Criticality conditions for extreme configurations. In the following, we give the criticality conditions <lb/>C = 2 in equation (6) for the proposed extreme configurations (i), (ii), (iii), and (iv) (Fig. 4d). The connectivity of <lb/>configuration (i) is given as <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>A <lb/>R <lb/>Nc <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>(15) <lb/>M M <lb/>M N M <lb/>N M M <lb/>N M N M <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>where 1 n,m and 0 n,m are n × m matrices consisting of all elements of 1 and 0, respectively. In this case, the fraction <lb/>of connections is related to M as c = M 2 /N 2 , and the critical point is obtained by solving a cubic equation: <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>. <lb/>x c <lb/>c x <lb/>cx <lb/>c x <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(16) <lb/>1/2 3 <lb/>1/2 3 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 /2 <lb/>The connectivity of the configuration (ii) is given as <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>. <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>A <lb/>R <lb/>Nc <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>(17) <lb/>M M <lb/>M N M <lb/>N M M <lb/>N M N M <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>The critical point is obtained by solving a fifth-degree equation: <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ − <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>− − <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ − <lb/>+ <lb/>= <lb/>b x <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>b x <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>b x <lb/>b <lb/>b b <lb/>b x <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>b x <lb/>b <lb/>b <lb/>2 (3 2 )(1 <lb/>) <lb/>( 6 12 <lb/>5 )(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1 <lb/>)(2 10 <lb/>)(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1 <lb/>) (4 <lb/>)(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1 <lb/>) (1 <lb/>) <lb/>0, <lb/>(18) <lb/>3 5 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 3 <lb/>32 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>5 <lb/>where = <lb/>− = <lb/>− <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>N M N <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>)/ . <lb/>The connectivity of the configuration (iii) is given as <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>. <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>− . <lb/>− <lb/>A <lb/>R <lb/>Nc <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>(19) <lb/>N M N M <lb/>N M M <lb/>M N M <lb/>MM <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>, <lb/>In this case, c is related to M with c = M(N − M)/N 2 , and the critical point is obtained as <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>− + <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>− <lb/>. <lb/>− <lb/>R <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>1 <lb/>1 4 <lb/>4 <lb/>( 1 <lb/>1 2 (1 <lb/>1 4 ) ) <lb/>(20) <lb/>1 <lb/>The connectivity of the configuration (iv) is given by the triangular matrix, <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>        <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>         <lb/>. <lb/>A <lb/>R <lb/>Nc <lb/>0 0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>( 21) <lb/>In this case, = <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>→∞ <lb/>c <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>lim <lb/>( <lb/>1)/(2 ) 1/2 <lb/>N <lb/>, and the critical point is obtained as <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>− = <lb/>≈ . <lb/>→∞ <lb/>− <lb/>R <lb/>N <lb/>lim <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>(2 <lb/>1) <lb/>log 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>35 <lb/>(22) <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>0 <lb/>1/( <lb/>1) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<body>Critical reproduction ratio of the scale-free network. Here, we derive the critical value R c in the scale <lb/>free network using degree based mean field approximation 48 . The critical point is obtained by solving a cubic <lb/>equation of x = R c : <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>− <lb/>= <lb/>k k <lb/>k <lb/>k <lb/>k x <lb/>k k <lb/>k <lb/>k x <lb/>k k <lb/>k x <lb/>k <lb/>( <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>3 <lb/>) <lb/>(3 <lb/>) <lb/>0 , <lb/>(23) <lb/>3 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 3 <lb/>2 2 <lb/>2 3 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>where k is the degree of each node and 〈⋅〉 represents the average over the degree distribution P(k). If <lb/>P(k) ~ k −γ (γ ≤ 3), we may confirm that R c → 0 as N → ∞. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kermack, W. O. &amp; McKendrick, A. G. A contribution to the mathematical theory of epidemics. Proc. Roy. Soc. Lond. A 115, 700-721 <lb/>(1927). <lb/>2. Hawkes, A. G. Spectra of some self-exciting and mutually exciting point processes. Biometrika 58, 83-90 (1971). <lb/>3. Hawkes, A. G. Point spectra of some mutually exciting point processes. J. Roy. Statist. Soc. Ser. B 33, 438-443 (1971). <lb/>4. Hethcote, H. W. The mathematics of infectious diseases. SIAM Review 42, 599-653 (2000). <lb/>5. Keeling, M. J. &amp; Rohani, P. Modeling infectious diseases in humans and animals (Princeton University Press, 2008). <lb/>6. Vespignani, A. Modelling dynamical processes in complex socio-technical systems. Nat. Phys. 8, 32-39 (2012). <lb/>7. Brockmann, D. &amp; Helbing, D. The hidden geometry of complex, network-driven contagion phenomena. Science 342, 1337-42 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>8. Pastor-Satorras, R., Castellano, C., Van Mieghem, P. &amp; Vespignani, A. Epidemic processes in complex networks. Rev. Mod. Phys. 87, <lb/>925-979 (2015). <lb/>9. Mohler, G. O., Short, M. B., Brantingham, P. J., Schoenberg, F. P. &amp; Tita, G. E. Self-Exciting Point Process Modeling of Crime. J. Am. <lb/>Stat. Assoc. 106, 100-108 (2011). <lb/>10. Goffman, W. &amp; Newill, V. Generalization of epidemic theory. Nature 204, 225-228 (1964). <lb/>11. Crane, R. &amp; Sornette, D. Robust dynamic classes revealed by measuring the response function of a social system. Proc. Natl. Acad. <lb/>Sci. USA 105, 15649-15653 (2008). <lb/>12. Kitsak, M. et al. Identification of influential spreaders in complex networks. Nat. Phys. 6, 888-893 (2010). <lb/>13. Lerman, K. &amp; Ghosh, R. Information contagion: An empirical study of the spread of news on digg and twitter social networks. <lb/>ICWSM 10, 90-97 (2010). <lb/>14. Romero, D. M., Meeder, B. &amp; Kleinberg, J. Differences in the mechanics of information diffusion across topics: idioms, political <lb/>hashtags, and complex contagion on twitter. Proc. 20th Intl. WWW Conf. 695-704 (ACM, 2011). <lb/>15. At-Sahalia, Y., Cacho-Diaz, J. &amp; Laeven, R. J. Modeling financial contagion using mutually exciting jump processes. Tech. Rep., <lb/>National Bureau of Economic Research (2010). <lb/>16. Reynaud-Bouret, P., Schbath, S. et al. Adaptive estimation for hawkes processes; application to genome analysis. Ann. Stat. 38, <lb/>2781-2822 (2010). <lb/>17. Pernice, V., Staude, B., Cardanobile, S. &amp; Rotter, S. How structure determines correlations in neuronal networks. PLoS Comput. Biol. <lb/>7, e1002059 (2011). <lb/>18. Reynaud-Bouret, P., Rivoirard, V., Grammont, F. &amp; Tuleau-Malot, C. Goodness-of-fit tests and nonparametric adaptive estimation <lb/>for spike train analysis. J. Math. Neurosci. 4, 3 (2014). <lb/>19. Heffernan, J., Smith, R. &amp; Wahl, L. Perspectives on the basic reproductive ratio. J. R. Soc. Interface 2, 281-293 (2005). <lb/>20. Anderson, H. L., Fermi, E. &amp; Szilard, L. Neutron production and absorption in uranium. Phys. Rev. 56, 284 (1939). <lb/>21. Scharff-Goldhaber, G. &amp; Klaiber, G. Spontaneous emission of neutrons from uranium. Phys. Rev. 70, 229 (1946). <lb/>22. Duderstadt, J. J. &amp; Hamilton, L. J. Nuclear reactor analysis (1976). <lb/>23. Barabási, A.-L. The origin of bursts and heavy tails in human dynamics. Nature 435, 207-211 (2005). <lb/>24. Kwak, H., Lee, C., Park, H. &amp; Moon, S. What is twitter, a social network or a news media? Proc. 19th Intl. WWW Conf. 591-600 <lb/>(ACM, 2010). <lb/>25. Sakata, S. &amp; Harris, K. D. Laminar structure of spontaneous and sensory-evoked population activity in auditory cortex. Neuron 64, <lb/>404-418 (2009). <lb/>26. Onaga, T. &amp; Shinomoto, S. Bursting transition in a linear self-exciting point process. Phys. Rev. E 89, 042817 (2014). <lb/>27. Hinman, A. R., Orenstein, W. A., Santoli, J. M., Rodewald, L. E. &amp; Cochi, S. L. Vaccine shortages: History, impact, and prospects for <lb/>the future. Annu. Rev. Public Health 27, 235-259 (2006). <lb/>28. Stöhr, K. Vaccinate before the next pandemic? Nature 465, 161 (2010). <lb/>29. Huberman, B. A. &amp; Lukose, R. M. Social dilemmas and internet congestion. Science 277, 535-537 (1997). <lb/>30. Jaeger, H. &amp; Haas, H. Harnessing nonlinearity: predicting chaotic systems and saving energy in wireless communication. Science <lb/>304, 78-80 (2004). <lb/>31. Sussillo, D. &amp; Abbott, L. F. Generating coherent patterns of activity from chaotic neural networks. Neuron 63, 544-557 (2009). <lb/>32. Laje, R. &amp; Buonomano, D. V. Robust timing and motor patterns by taming chaos in recurrent neural networks. Nat. Neurosci. 16, <lb/>925-933 (2013). <lb/>33. Shimazaki, H. &amp; Shinomoto, S. A method for selecting the bin size of a time histogram. Neural Comput. 19, 1503-1527 (2007). <lb/>34. Shintani, T. &amp; Shinomoto, S. Detection limit for rate fluctuations in inhomogeneous poisson processes. Phys. Rev. E 85, 041139 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>35. Waugh, F. V. Inversion of the leontief matrix by power series. Econometrica 18, 142-154 (1950). <lb/>36. Keeling, M. J. The effects of local spatial structure on epidemiological invasions. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. B 266, 859-867 (1999). <lb/>37. Miller, J. C. Percolation and epidemics in random clustered networks. Phys. Rev. E 80, 020901 (2009). <lb/>38. Newman, M. E. Properties of highly clustered networks. Phys. Rev. E 68, 026121 (2003). <lb/>39. Barabási, A.-L. &amp; Albert, R. Emergence of scaling in random networks. Science 286, 509-512 (1999). <lb/>40. Erdös, P. &amp; Rényi, A. On random graphs, i. Publicationes Mathematicae (Debrecen) 6, 290-297 (1959). <lb/>41. Watts, D. J. &amp; Strogatz, S. H. Collective dynamics of &apos;small-world&apos; networks. Nature 393, 440-442 (1998). <lb/>42. Zachary, W. W. An information flow model for conflict and fission in small groups. J. Anthropol. Res. 33, 452-473 (1977). <lb/>43. Watts, D. J. A simple model of global cascades on random networks. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 99, 5766-5771 (2002). <lb/>44. Buldyrev, S. V., Parshani, R., Paul, G., Stanley, H. E. &amp; Havlin, S. Catastrophic cascade of failures in interdependent networks. Nature <lb/>464, 1025-1028 (2010). <lb/>45. Zhao, J., Li, D., Sanhedrai, H., Cohen, R. &amp; Havlin, S. Spatio-temporal propagation of cascading overload failures in spatially <lb/>embedded networks. Nat. Commun. 7 (2016). <lb/>46. Koyama, S. &amp; Shinomoto, S. Histogram bin width selection for time-dependent poisson processes. J. Phys. A Math. Gen. 37, 7255 <lb/>(2004). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRts | 6:33321 | DOI: 10.1038/srep33321 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>47. Koyama, S., Shimokawa, T. &amp; Shinomoto, S. Phase transitions in the estimation of event rate: a path integral analysis. J. Phys. A Math. <lb/>Theor. 40, F383 (2007). <lb/>48. Pastor-Satorras, R. &amp; Vespignani, A. Epidemic spreading in scale-free networks. Phys. Rev. Lett. 86, 3200-3203 (2001). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We thank Takaaki Aoki, Hiroya Nakao, and Naoki Masuda for their advice and comments. This study was <lb/>supported in part by a Grant-in-Aid for Scientific Research to S.S. from MEXT Japan (26280007) and by JST and <lb/>CREST. T.O. is supported by a JSPS Research Fellowship for Young Scientists. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>S.S. designed the study. T.O. conducted the theoretical and numerical analysis. S.S. wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Additional Information <lb/>Competing financial interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

			<front>How to cite this article: Onaga, T. and Shinomoto, S. Emergence of event cascades in inhomogeneous <lb/>networks. Sci. Rep. 6, 33321; doi: 10.1038/srep33321 (2016). <lb/>This work is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License. The images <lb/>or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, <lb/>unless indicated otherwise in the credit line; if the material is not included under the Creative Commons license, <lb/>users will need to obtain permission from the license holder to reproduce the material. To view a copy of this <lb/>license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/ <lb/>© The Author(s) 2016 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
