<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Health Expectations. 2017;20:1421-1427. <lb/>| 1421 <lb/>wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/hex <lb/>Accepted: 16 May 2017 <lb/>DOI: 10.1111/hex.12585 <lb/>O R I G I N A L R E S E A R C H P A P E R <lb/>Research priorities about stoma-related quality of life from the <lb/>perspective of people with a stoma: A pilot survey <lb/>Gill Hubbard PhD, Associate Professor 1 | Claire Taylor PhD, Macmillan Nurse Consultant <lb/>Colorectal Cancer 2 | Becca Beeken PhD, Senior Research Associate | Anna Campbell MBE, PhD, <lb/>Senior Lecturer | Jackie Gracey PhD, Lecturer | Chloe Grimmett PhD, Senior Research Fellow 6 | <lb/>Abi Fisher PhD, Lecturer | Gozde Ozakinci PhD, Senior Lecturer | Sarah Slater FRCGP, Consultant <lb/>oncologist 8 | Trish Gorely PhD, Senior Lecturer <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, <lb/>provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>© 2017 The Authors Health Expectations Published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd <lb/>University of Stirling, Stirling, UK <lb/>London North West Healthcare NHS Trust, <lb/>London, UK <lb/>3 <lb/>University College London, London, UK <lb/>Edinburgh Napier University, Edinburgh, UK <lb/>Ulster University, Coleraine, UK <lb/>University of Southampton, Southampton, <lb/>UK <lb/>7 <lb/>University of St Andrews, St Andrews, UK <lb/>NHS Glasgow and Clyde, Glasgow, UK <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Gill Hubbard, School of Health Sciences, <lb/>University of Stirling, Highland Campus, <lb/>Centre for Health Science, Old Perth Road, <lb/>INVERNESS, IV2 3JH, UK. <lb/>Email: gill.hubbard@stir.ac.uk <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: There is a recognized need to include patients in setting research priori-<lb/>ties. Research priorities identified by people with a stoma are rarely elicited. <lb/>Objectives: To improve the quality of life of people with a stoma through use of <lb/>evidence-based practice based on research priorities set by patients. <lb/>Design and Methods: Online pilot survey publicized in 2016 via United Kingdom stoma char-<lb/>ities. People ranked nine stoma-related quality of life topics in order of research priority. <lb/>Participants: People 16 years of age and over who currently have or have had a stoma <lb/>for treatment for any medical condition. <lb/>Analysis: Distributions of the priority scores for each of the nine research topics were <lb/>examined. Group differences were explored using either the Mann-Whitney U-test or <lb/>the Kruskal-Wallis test depending on the number of groups. <lb/>Results: In total, 225 people completed the survey. The most important research priority was <lb/>pouch leak problems and stoma bag/appliance problems followed by hernia risk. There were <lb/>statistically significant differences in ranking research priorities between males and females, <lb/>age, underlying disease that led to a stoma, stoma type and length of time with a stoma. <lb/>Conclusion: People with a stoma are willing to engage in and set research priorities. <lb/>The results should contribute towards future research about setting the research <lb/>agenda for the study of stoma-related concerns that impact quality of life. <lb/>K E Y W O R D S <lb/>colostomy, ostomy, public/patient involvement, research priorities, stoma, urostomy <lb/></front>

			<body>1 | INTRODUCTION <lb/>There are a number of conditions that as part of treatment may <lb/>necessitate the formation of a stoma including colorectal cancer, <lb/>diverticular disease, incontinence, ulcerative colitis and Crohn&apos;s dis-<lb/>ease. Each year, for instance, 77% (n≈3000) of people in the United <lb/>Kingdom undergoing anterior resection for rectal cancer will have a <lb/>defunctioning or end stoma formed and 27% will still have a stoma <lb/></body>

			<page>1422</page>

			| <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<body>at 18-month follow-up. 1 A stoma is an artificial opening in the bowel <lb/>that has been made to bring the bowel onto the surface of the abdo-<lb/>men in order to divert the flow of faeces or urine. The three types of <lb/>eliminating stomas are colostomy, ileostomy and urostomy, which can <lb/>be temporary or permanent. Recent systematic reviews of empirical <lb/>evidence suggest that a stoma has a negative impact on quality of <lb/>life of the person with the stoma and that of their spouses. 2-4 Hence, <lb/>identifying factors associated with poor quality of life and recognizing <lb/>effective solutions are important for people with a stoma. Moreover, <lb/>stoma-related problems causing the most concern for people with a <lb/>stoma should arguably take precedence and be research priorities. <lb/>In the United Kingdom, there is a recognized need to include pa-<lb/>tients, carers and clinicians in setting research priorities. Recently, the <lb/>membership of the Association of Coloproctology of Great Britain and <lb/>Ireland (ACPGBI) was involved in a Delphi study to reach a consensus <lb/>on prioritizing clinical research questions in colorectal disease. The <lb/>study produced a list of 25 research questions that can be considered <lb/>to reflect the clinical matters of greatest importance by this expert <lb/>panel. A similar research priority setting exercise was conducted by <lb/>the American Society of Colon and Rectal Surgeons. 7 The top-scoring <lb/>ACPGBI non-cancer questions related to prevention and treatment of <lb/>colorectal complications, including anastomotic leakage, parastomal <lb/>hernia and the need for a defunctioning stoma. Top-scoring cancer-<lb/>related research questions were; &quot;Is there a price to cancer survival <lb/>after treatment for colon, rectal and anal cancer? What is the impact <lb/>of treatment on quality of life? What level of poor function is justi-<lb/>fied to avoid a permanent stoma?&quot; 7 Hence, surgeons clearly perceive <lb/>stoma and quality of life for people with colorectal disease as national <lb/>research priorities. <lb/>The ACPGBI acknowledge that there is a need to involve patient <lb/>support groups in developing these research questions and establish-<lb/>ing whether the questions resonate with patients as well as clinicians. <lb/>To address this, we conducted a pilot survey of people with experience <lb/>of having a stoma to identify research priorities about stoma-related <lb/>quality of life. The findings of this pilot survey could then be used to <lb/>inform the conduct of large-scale studies about research priorities for <lb/>people with a stoma. In conjunction with the research priorities identi-<lb/>fied by the ACPGBI, this could contribute towards identification of the <lb/>focus of future grant applications and act as a guide for future inves-<lb/>tigators and funders. Ultimately, the purpose is to improve the quality <lb/>of life of people with a stoma through use of evidence-based practice <lb/>based on research priorities set by patients. <lb/>2 | METHODS <lb/>A pilot cross-sectional survey to determine research priorities about <lb/>stoma-related quality of life was conducted over 3 months in 2016. <lb/>A pilot survey is a preliminary survey used to gather information <lb/>prior to conducting a survey on a larger scale. The survey was closed <lb/>after this 3-month period. It was administered online using Bristol <lb/>Survey On-line (BOS), which is an online service that allows research-<lb/>ers to develop, deploy and analyse an online survey (https://www. <lb/>onlinesurveys.ac.uk). An online questionnaire is a well-established <lb/>method used in health research 8 and was chosen as a practical way of <lb/>quickly reaching people to conduct the survey. A University of Stirling <lb/>research and ethics committee approved the study (REF SREC 15/16 <lb/>Paper No 54 Version 2). <lb/>2.1 | Recruitment <lb/>The inclusion criterion was people 16 years of age and over who cur-<lb/>rently have or have had a stoma for treatment for any medical condi-<lb/>tion. Several relevant UK charities (Colostomy Association, Ileostomy <lb/>Association, Urostomy Association and Bowel and Cancer Research) <lb/>included a link on their website and on social media (eg. Facebook) <lb/>to the study&apos;s online questionnaire. The Colostomy Association, <lb/>Urostomy Association and Ileostomy Association represent people <lb/>with a stoma, providing support, advice and practical information <lb/>and Bowel and Cancer Research is a charity funding research. Only <lb/>people who indicated consent by ticking a consent box could access <lb/>the questionnaire, which is an approach to obtaining consent used in <lb/>previous online health research projects. 9 The questionnaire was in <lb/>English, and the sampling approach and recruitment procedure were <lb/>chosen for convenience and are commensurate with the purpose and <lb/>scale of the pilot study. <lb/>2.2 | Variables <lb/>Single items were used to gather data on respondents&apos; gender, age <lb/>when first stoma was formed, underlying disease that led to a stoma, <lb/>type of stoma, if still had a stoma, and length of time with a stoma. <lb/>This information was gathered to examine, for example, whether fe-<lb/>males and males had different research priorities and so on. <lb/>Nine stoma-related quality of life topics derived from the literature <lb/>were listed, and people who completed the survey were requested <lb/>to rank them in order of research priority (range 1-9). 1 represented <lb/>the most important research priority and 9 the least important. The <lb/>nine stoma-related quality of life topics were selected as follows: <lb/>Key Points <lb/>1. This pilot study addresses the lack of patient-led research <lb/>priority setting about stoma-related quality of life. <lb/>2. The most important research priority was pouch leak <lb/>problems and stoma bag/appliance problems. The second <lb/>research priority was hernia risk. <lb/>3. Ranking of research priorities varied by gender, age, <lb/>underlying disease that led to a stoma, length of time with <lb/>a stoma and type of stoma. <lb/>4. It is anticipated that these results will contribute towards <lb/>further research about setting the research agenda for <lb/>the study of stoma-related concerns that impact quality <lb/>of life. <lb/></body>

			| 

			<page>1423 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<body>first, potential topics were identified from the literature about stoma-<lb/>related quality of life; 2,3,4 second, topics were discussed at a meeting <lb/>by the research team (ie. listed authors) and representatives from the <lb/>Colostomy Association, Ileostomy Association, Urostomy Association <lb/>and Bowel and Cancer Research and a final list of topics was agreed; <lb/>third, an individual with a stoma who acted as a patient advisor for the <lb/>study and the research team and representatives from the Colostomy <lb/>Association, Ileostomy Association, Urostomy Association and Bowel <lb/>and Cancer Research completed the survey, which included the final <lb/>list of nine topics. The wording for the questionnaire was revised in <lb/>the light of feedback. An open-ended question was included so that <lb/>people completing the survey could indicate any other issues and con-<lb/>cerns that were not listed, relating to their stoma, that they believed <lb/>ought to be a research priority. A copy of the final questionnaire is <lb/>available in a supplementary file. <lb/>2.3 | Analysis <lb/>The following characteristics of the people who completed the sur-<lb/>vey were summarized using descriptive statistics: gender, age when <lb/>first stoma was formed, underlying disease that led to a stoma, type <lb/>of stoma, if still had a stoma, and length of time with a stoma. The <lb/>proportion of people ranking each of the nine listed stoma-related <lb/>quality of life topics as most important (1 = most important) to least <lb/>important (9 = least important) were calculated. Distributions of the <lb/>priority scores for each of the nine research topics were examined <lb/>and the median scores (range 1-9) obtained. Research topics were <lb/>then ranked according to the median scores, to indicate the order of <lb/>priorities. Differences in the ranking of the nine research topics and <lb/>the characteristics of people completing the survey (eg. gender, age <lb/>when first stoma was formed, underlying disease that led to a stoma, <lb/>type of stoma, if still had a stoma, and length of time with a stoma) <lb/>were examined. The Mann-Whitney test was used to explore differ-<lb/>ences by age (2 groups: &lt;=50 years old, &lt;50 years old) or gender (2 <lb/>groups: male, female). The Kruskal-Wallis test was used to explore <lb/>differences by underlying disease (categorized into five groups: blad-<lb/>der cancer, colon cancer, rectal cancer, inflammatory bowel disease, <lb/>other), type of stoma (3 groups: colostomy, ileostomy, urostomy) or <lb/>length of time with stoma (4 groups: &lt;=12 months, 13-24 months, 25-<lb/>48 months and &gt;48 months). The additional research priority topics <lb/>identified by patients were listed and the proportion of people identi-<lb/>fying each topic was calculated. <lb/>3 | RESULTS <lb/>3.1 | Characteristics of people completing the survey <lb/>There were 225 people completing the survey (Table 1). One hundred <lb/>and sixty-four were female (73%). Sixty-nine (30.6%) were 61 years of <lb/>age and over when they first had a stoma. Two hundred and fourteen <lb/>(95.5%) still had a stoma with 90 (40.7%) of people having a stoma for <lb/>≥4 years. Ninety-nine (44.4%) had a colostomy, 84 (37.7%) ileostomy <lb/>and 40 (17.9%) a urostomy. <lb/>3.2 | Research priorities <lb/>Table 2 presents the proportion of respondents ranking each research <lb/>topic. The table shows for instance, that &quot;pouch leak problems and <lb/>stoma bag/appliance problems&quot; was ranked the most important re-<lb/>search priority by 49.5% (n=104) respondents and hernia risk was <lb/>T A B L E 1 Characteristics of people completing the survey <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>n=225 (%) <lb/>Gender <lb/>n=223 <lb/>Male <lb/>59 (26.4) <lb/>Female <lb/>164 (73.6) <lb/>Age when first had stoma <lb/>n=225 <lb/>&lt;15 y <lb/>8 (3.6) <lb/>16-20 <lb/>4 (1.8) <lb/>21-30 <lb/>30 (13.3) <lb/>31-40 <lb/>29 (12.9) <lb/>41-50 <lb/>32 (14.2) <lb/>51-60 <lb/>53 (23.6) <lb/>61-70 <lb/>48 (21.3) <lb/>71-80 <lb/>18 (8) <lb/>Over 81 <lb/>3 (1.3) <lb/>Reason for first stoma <lb/>n=222 <lb/>Inflammatory Bowel Disease (eg. diverticular disease, <lb/>Crohn&apos;s disease, ulcerative colitis) <lb/>80 (36) <lb/>Colon cancer <lb/>22 (9.9) <lb/>Rectal cancer <lb/>26 (11.7) <lb/>Bladder cancer <lb/>27 (12.2) <lb/>Birth defect <lb/>6 (2.7) <lb/>Peritonitis <lb/>3 (1.4) <lb/>Childbirth complications <lb/>2 (0.9) <lb/>Do not know <lb/>2 (0.9) <lb/>Other <lb/>54 (24.3) <lb/>Stoma at time of survey? <lb/>n=224 <lb/>Yes <lb/>214 (95.5) <lb/>No <lb/>10 (4.5) <lb/>Type of stoma <lb/>n=223 <lb/>Colostomy <lb/>99 (44.4) <lb/>Ileostomy <lb/>84 (37.7) <lb/>Urostomy <lb/>40 (17.9) <lb/>Length of time with stoma <lb/>n=221 <lb/>0-6 mo <lb/>16 (7.2) <lb/>7-12 <lb/>27 (12.2) <lb/>13-18 <lb/>23 (10.4) <lb/>19-24 <lb/>19 (8.6) <lb/>25-36 <lb/>27 (12.2) <lb/>37-48 <lb/>19 (8.7) <lb/>More than 4 y <lb/>90 (40.7) <lb/></body>

			<page>1424</page>

			| <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<body>ranked as the most important research priority by 21.3% (n=44) of <lb/>people completing the survey. <lb/>Using the median as an indicator of research priority it is possible <lb/>to rank the nine topics in order of five research priorities. The most <lb/>important research priority was pouch leak problems and stoma bag/ <lb/>appliance problems (median = 2). The second research priority was <lb/>hernia risk (median = 3). Four topics were ranked as the third most <lb/>important research priority: physical activity, pain and feeling uncom-<lb/>fortable, smell and odour problems, body image and body confidence <lb/>(median = 5). The fourth research priority was fatigue and low energy <lb/>levels (median = 6). Two subjects were ranked as the fifth most im-<lb/>portant research priority: sex life and intimacy and health professional <lb/>communication about living with a stoma (median = 7). <lb/>3.3 | Differences between groups in ranking <lb/>research priorities <lb/>3.3.1 | Gender <lb/>There were significant differences in ranking research priorities be-<lb/>tween males and females for one research topic. Males ranked hernia <lb/>risk as a more important research priority than women (mean rank <lb/>86.10 vs 109.84; Mann-Whitney U-test = 3195, P&lt;.05). No other dif-<lb/>ferences were observed. <lb/>3.3.2 | Age <lb/>There were significant differences in ranking research priorities by <lb/>age for two research priority topics. Those who were older when they <lb/>first had a stoma (&gt;50 years) ranked hernia risk as a more important <lb/>research priority than those who were younger when they first had <lb/>a stoma (&lt;=50 years) (mean rank 91.16 vs 118.85; Mann-Whitney <lb/>U-test = 3902.5, P&lt; .05). Those who were younger (&lt;50 years) ranked <lb/>physical activity as a more important research priority than those who <lb/>were older when they first had a stoma (&gt;50 years) (mean rank 88.84 <lb/>vs 108.08; Mann-Whitney U-test = 3891.5, P&lt; .05). <lb/>3.3.3 | Underlying disease that led to a stoma <lb/>A Kruskal-Wallis test (χ 2 (4) = 13.2, P&lt;.05) showed significant differ-<lb/>ences between the groups. People with Inflammatory bowel disease <lb/>ranked fatigue and low energy levels as a more important research <lb/>priority than any other group, with a mean rank of 77.89, compared <lb/>with 95.08 for bladder cancer, 91.33 for colon cancer, 110.75 for rec-<lb/>tal cancer and 109.42 for other reasons. <lb/>3.3.4 | Stoma type <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis tests showed that there were significant differences <lb/>in ranking research priorities by stoma type for five research prior-<lb/>ity topics. People with a colostomy (mean rank 92.77) and uros-<lb/>tomy (mean rank 90.91) ranked hernia risk as a more important <lb/>research priority than those with an ileostomy (mean rank 123.01) <lb/>((χ2 (2) = 13.30, P&lt;.05). People with an ileostomy (mean rank 88.44) and <lb/>urostomy (mean rank 90.90) ranked physical activity as a more impor-<lb/>tant research priority than those with a colostomy (mean rank 110.88) <lb/>(χ2 (2) = 7.23, P&lt;.05). People with a colostomy (mean rank 82.60) ranked <lb/>smell and odour problems as a more important research priority than <lb/>those with an ileostomy (mean rank 113.42) and urostomy (mean rank <lb/>122.76) (χ2 (2) = 17.49, P&lt;.05) People with a urostomy (mean rank <lb/>82.31) ranked body image and body confidence as a more important <lb/>research priority than those with an ileostomy (mean rank 91.59) and <lb/>T A B L E 2 Proportion of respondents ranking each research priority <lb/>Ranking n (%) <lb/>Topic <lb/>1st <lb/>2nd <lb/>3rd <lb/>4th <lb/>5th <lb/>6th <lb/>7th <lb/>8th <lb/>9th <lb/>Pouch leak/appliance <lb/>problems <lb/>104 (49.5) <lb/>30 (14.3) <lb/>19 (9) <lb/>10 (4.8) <lb/>16 (7.6) <lb/>5 (2.4) <lb/>9 (4.3) <lb/>7 (3.3) <lb/>10 (4.8) <lb/>Hernia risk <lb/>44 (21.3) <lb/>53 (25.6) <lb/>22 (10.6) <lb/>13 (6.3) <lb/>16 (7.7) <lb/>8 (3.9) <lb/>18 (8.7) <lb/>20 (9.7) <lb/>13 (6.3) <lb/>Physical activity <lb/>2 (1) <lb/>10 (5.1) <lb/>24 (12.2) <lb/>34 (17.3) <lb/>30 (15.2) <lb/>34 (17.3) <lb/>23 (11.7) <lb/>21 (10.7) <lb/>19 (9.6) <lb/>Pain and feeling <lb/>uncomfortable <lb/>9 (4.5) <lb/>23 (11.6) <lb/>31 (15.6) <lb/>31 (15.6) <lb/>33 (16.6) <lb/>27 (13.6) <lb/>23 (11.6) <lb/>14 (7) <lb/>8 (4) <lb/>Smell and odour <lb/>problems <lb/>12 (6) <lb/>24 (11.9) <lb/>27 (13.4) <lb/>31 (15.4) <lb/>29 (14.4) <lb/>24 (11.9) <lb/>21 (10.4) <lb/>14 (7) <lb/>19 (9.5) <lb/>Body image and body <lb/>confidence <lb/>12 (6.2) <lb/>16 (8.2) <lb/>22 (11.3) <lb/>28 (14.4) <lb/>29 (14.9) <lb/>35 (17.9) <lb/>22 (11.3) <lb/>21 (10.8) <lb/>10 (5.1) <lb/>Fatigue and low <lb/>energy levels <lb/>12 (6.3) <lb/>14 (7.4) <lb/>23 (12.2) <lb/>25 (13.2) <lb/>17 (9) <lb/>23 (12.2) <lb/>31 (16.4) <lb/>24 (12.7) <lb/>20 (10.6) <lb/>Sex life and intimacy <lb/>3 (1.6) <lb/>18 (9.4) <lb/>18 (9.4) <lb/>14 (7.3) <lb/>7 (3.6) <lb/>23 (12) <lb/>23 (12) <lb/>41 (21.4) <lb/>45 (23.4) <lb/>Health professional <lb/>communication <lb/>about living with a <lb/>stoma <lb/>14 (7) <lb/>14 (7) <lb/>15 (7.5) <lb/>15 (7.5) <lb/>23 (11.6) <lb/>15 (7.5) <lb/>21 (10.6) <lb/>32 (16.1) <lb/>50 (25.1) <lb/></body>

			| 

			<page>1425 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<body>colostomy (mean rank 109.59) (χ2 (2) = 7.38, P&lt;.05). Those with an il-<lb/>eostomy (mean rank 80.27) ranked fatigue and low energy levels as a <lb/>more important research priority than those with a colostomy (mean <lb/>rank 104.98) and urostomy (mean rank 102.4) (χ2 (2) = 8.08, P&lt;.05). <lb/>3.3.5 | Length of time with a stoma <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis analysis showed that there was a significant difference <lb/>in ranking research priorities by length of time with a stoma for one <lb/>research topic. People who had a stoma for &lt;=12 months (mean rank <lb/>90.68) or for &gt;48 months (mean rank 88.08) ranked pain and feel-<lb/>ing uncomfortable as a more important research priority than others <lb/>(mean rank 120.71 for 13-24 months and 106.60 for 25-48 months). <lb/>3.4 | Additional topics <lb/>Fifty-four percentage (n=121) of people who completed the survey <lb/>identified additional topics as research priorities. A minority (n=4) <lb/>listed more than one additional topic. Topics that were identified by <lb/>≥5 people completing the survey are presented in Table 3. It is clear <lb/>that most people who identified further topics focus on the physical <lb/>problems caused by a stoma such as skin problems and flatulence. <lb/>Topics that were identified by ≤5 people completing the survey are <lb/>as follows: public awareness and perceptions of stoma, information <lb/>about reversal, impact on family, hernia, exercising, returning to work, <lb/>early diagnosis and cure, clothing and support garments, pregnancy <lb/>and weight loss. <lb/>4 | DISCUSSION <lb/>This survey produced a ranking of priorities for stoma-related qual-<lb/>ity of life research of greatest important to people with a stoma. <lb/>This is the first attempt to specifically engage people with a stoma <lb/>to decide on research priorities using an online survey. The ACPGBI <lb/>recommended the involvement of patients in developing research <lb/>priorities. 7 This study did this through a United Kingdom pilot sur-<lb/>vey of people with a stoma. The research priorities identified in this <lb/>pilot study represent the perspectives of people with a stoma; 95% of <lb/>those who replied still had a stoma. <lb/>The ACPGBI wished to find out if the research questions identified <lb/>by clinicians would be supported by patients. Our survey suggests <lb/>that they would be. The ACPGBI highlighted anastomotic leakage, <lb/>parastomal hernia and quality of life as key research priorities. Our <lb/>survey identified pouch leak problems and stoma bag/appliance prob-<lb/>lems as the top stoma-related research priority and hernia risk as the <lb/>second most important research priority. Prioritization should be given <lb/>to these topics. <lb/>The main stated research priority identified in this study was <lb/>pouch leak and stoma/bag appliances. Pouch leakage can cause dis-<lb/>comfort and distress and the fear of this happening can profoundly <lb/>affect daily life, activities, and social life. Modern stoma appliances <lb/>have improved flatus filters and there are a variety of stoma accesso-<lb/>ries now available on prescription to secure the appliance and reduce <lb/>risk of leaks. Nevertheless, the Ostomy Life Study (4000 participants <lb/>from 11 countries) indicates that the majority of people with a stoma <lb/>have issues related to leakage and ballooning. There is also strong <lb/>evidence that peristomal skin complications, which cause leakage, are <lb/>endemic. 12 <lb/>The second top research priority identified in this pilot survey was <lb/>hernia risk. The reported incidence of parastomal herniation is vari-<lb/>able, ranging from 10%-52%. 13 The reasons why a colostomy appears <lb/>twice as likely to herniate as an ileostomy are not fully known beyond <lb/>possibly the increased trephine diameter. What is known is that <lb/>parastomal herniation not only causes further change in body image <lb/>and cosmesis and increased pain but also a difficulty with stoma appli-<lb/>ance application resulting in increased risk of pouch leakage which can <lb/>result in impaired quality of life. Two large trials about surgical proce-<lb/>dures to reduce the risk of parastomal herniation are underway in the <lb/>United Kingdom. 16,17 There have only been a handful of education and <lb/>abdominal exercise programmes in the post-surgical period designed <lb/>to prevent and support those with parastomal hernia. 13,18 <lb/>Our pilot survey found differences in ranking of research priori-<lb/>ties by gender, age, underlying disease that led to a stoma, length of <lb/>time with a stoma and type of stoma. These differences may reflect <lb/>variation in problems and concerns experienced by different groups <lb/>of people with a stoma. One study for instance, found that female <lb/>colorectal survivors with stomas had more specific psychological and <lb/>social issues than men including diet management, physical activity, <lb/>sexuality and social support. 19 A comparison of quality of life in can-<lb/>cer and non-cancer patients with colostomies found that non-cancer <lb/>patients reported lower scores for fatigue, strength, aches and pains, <lb/>appearance and body image and skin irritation compared to cancer <lb/>patients with colostomies. 20 However, the study found that concerns <lb/>associated with negative quality of life are common to all colostomy <lb/>patients and include sexual problems, gas, constipation, travel diffi-<lb/>culties and dissatisfaction with appearance. All of the research priori-<lb/>ties presented in this article are therefore likely to resonate with many <lb/>people with a stoma even if their ordering of research priorities varies. <lb/>The research priorities that we found in this pilot study may be <lb/>an indicator of lack of support to address these concerns. Forty-one <lb/>T A B L E 3 Additional topics <lb/>Topic <lb/>N= (%) <lb/>Flatulence, constipation, pancaking, blockages, mucus, and <lb/>anal discharge <lb/>25 (11) <lb/>Skin-related problems (eg. soreness, itching and infection <lb/>and fistulas) <lb/>22 (10) <lb/>Stoma bags and self-management (eg. product design, <lb/>adhesives and maintaining privacy) <lb/>20 (9) <lb/>WC facilities <lb/>10 (4) <lb/>Support at home and long-term aftercare <lb/>7 (3) <lb/>Mental health and emotions <lb/>5 (2) <lb/>Diet and nutrition <lb/>5 (2) <lb/>Communication with health professionals <lb/>5 (2) <lb/></body>

			<page>1426</page>

			| <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<body>percentage of survey respondents had been living with a stoma for at <lb/>least 4 years and yet still identified pouch leak and stoma/bag appli-<lb/>ances as the most pressing research priority. Research has identified <lb/>complications after ostomy surgery as high as 21%-70% including late <lb/>complications such as peristomal dermatitis, hernia and stenosis. 21 <lb/>Hence, addressing the research priorities reported in this study is crucial. <lb/>Several people completing the survey identified additional topics <lb/>as research priorities. Arguably, some of these topics could be cate-<lb/>gorized under the pre-set list of topics; for example, skin problems <lb/>could fall within the category, &quot;pouch leak problems and bag/appli-<lb/>ance problems.&quot; However, the additional topics listed by people with a <lb/>stoma highlight the topics or choice of wording that are perhaps more <lb/>relevant and should therefore be considered for use in future research <lb/>about research priorities. <lb/>4.1 | Limitations <lb/>There is a risk that our list of nine stoma-related quality of life topics <lb/>missed key topics for people with a stoma and only reflect those is-<lb/>sues deemed important by the research team and the collaborators. <lb/>However, the inclusion of an open question whereby people complet-<lb/>ing the survey could identify additional topics partially addressed this <lb/>limitation and the most common additional topics could be included in <lb/>future surveys. It must be acknowledged that this is not a large sam-<lb/>ple and there will be a selection bias in our pilot study based on the <lb/>surveyed population drawn from charities, who may have accessed <lb/>charitable support to address any unmet emotional and practical sup-<lb/>port needs. In this anonymous web-based pilot survey, we did not <lb/>have access to medical record information, which limits our ability to <lb/>describe the clinical characteristics of those surveyed. Certain peo-<lb/>ple with a stoma, for example, males are under-represented in the <lb/>pilot survey. The organizations advertising the survey were United <lb/>Kingdom charities. Nevertheless, we did not ask people completing <lb/>the survey to indicate where they lived, which means we cannot be <lb/>certain that most were from the United Kingdom. Finally, because it <lb/>is a survey advertised using social media, we do not know the total <lb/>population size and are therefore not able to examine whether the <lb/>study is representative. To address these limitations, any future large-<lb/>scale survey could recruit from bowel cancer consultant patient lists <lb/>so that we can calculate, for example the completion rate and study <lb/>representativeness. Given these limitations, it is premature to claim <lb/>that certain groups of people with a stoma will have different research <lb/>prioritizations. Further research is therefore needed to replicate the <lb/>findings in a more diverse population of people with a stoma. <lb/>5 | CONCLUSIONS <lb/>This pilot survey suggests that people with a stoma are willing to <lb/>engage in and set research priorities about stoma-related quality of <lb/>life. It is anticipated that these results will contribute towards further <lb/>research about setting the research agenda for the study of stoma-<lb/>related concerns that impact quality of life. The question remains as <lb/>to how this information should be disseminated and used by research <lb/>funding bodies and researchers. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank the following charities for advertising the study: Ileostomy <lb/>Association, Colostomy Association, Bowel and Cancer Research, <lb/>Urostomy Association. We also thank Lynne Russell, a Masters student at <lb/>the University of Stirling who added the questionnaire to the online system <lb/>and Jo Haviland, statistician at the University of Southampton for advice. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Healthcare Quality Improvement Partnership. National Bowel Cancer <lb/>Audit Reports: 2014 and 2015. HSCIC. Leeds, United Kingdom. <lb/>2. Ang SGM, Chen H, Siah RJC, He H, Klainin-Yobas P. Stressors relating <lb/>to patient psychological health following stoma surgery: an integrated <lb/>literature review. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2013;40:587-594. <lb/>3. Vonk-Klassen SM, de Vocht HM, den Ouden MEM, Eddes EH, <lb/>Schuurmans MJ. Ostomy-related problems and their impact on qual-<lb/>ity of life of colorectal cancer ostomates: a systematic review. Qual <lb/>Life Res. 2016;25:125-133. <lb/>4. Danielsen AK, Burcharth J, Rosenburg J. Spouses of patients with <lb/>a stoma lack information and support and are restricted in their <lb/>social and sexual life: a systematic review. Int J Colorectal Dis. <lb/>2013;28:1603-1612. <lb/>5. James Lind Alliance. Available at: http://www.jla.nihr.ac.uk/about-<lb/>the-james-lind-alliance/. Accessed 14 November 2016. <lb/>6. Tiernan J, Cook A, Geh I, et al. Use of a modified Delphi approach to <lb/>develop research priorities for the association of coloproctology of <lb/>Great Britain and Ireland. Colorectal Dis. 2014;16:965-970. <lb/>7. Burt CG, Cima RR, Koltun WA, et al. Developing a research agenda for <lb/>the American Society of Colon and Rectal Surgeons: results of a delphi <lb/>approach. Dis Colon Rectum. 2009;52:898-905. <lb/>8. Buchanan EA, Hvizdak EE. Online survey tools: ethical and method-<lb/>ological concerns of human research ethics committees. J Empir Res <lb/>Hum Res Ethics. 2009;4:37-48. <lb/>9. Vayena E, Mastroianni A, Kahn J. Caught in the web: informed con-<lb/>sent for online health research. Sci Transl Med. 2013;5:173fs6. <lb/>10. Feddern M. Life with a stoma after curative resection for rectal <lb/>cancer: A population-based cross-sectional study. Colorectal Dis. <lb/>2015;17:1011. <lb/>11. Claessens I, Probert R, Tielemans C, et al. The Ostomy Life Study: the <lb/>everyday challenges face by people living with a stoma in a snapshot. <lb/>Gastrointest Nurs. 2015;13:18-25. <lb/>12. Meisner S, Lehur P, Morn B, Martins L, Jemec GBE. Peristomal skin <lb/>complications are common, expensive, and difficult to manage: a pop-<lb/>ulation based cost modeling study. PLoS ONE. 2012;7:e37813. <lb/>13. North J. Early intervention, parastomal hernia and quality of life: A <lb/>research study. Br J Nurs. 2014;23:s15-s20. <lb/>14. Hotouras A, Murphy J, Thaha M, Chan CL. The persistent challenge of <lb/>parastomal herniation: A review of the literature and future develop-<lb/>ments. Colorectal Dis. 2013;15:e202-e214. <lb/>15. Scarpa M, Ruffolo C, Boetto R, Pozza A, Sadocchi L, Angriman I. <lb/>Diverting loop ileostomy after restorative proctocolectomy: pre-<lb/>dictors of poor outcome and poor quality of life. Colorectal Dis. <lb/>2010;12:914-920. <lb/>16. Brandsma HT, Hansson BM, deV-Haaren-HH, Aufenacker TJ, <lb/>Rosman C, Bleichrodt RP. PREVENTion of a parastomal hernia with <lb/>a prosthetic mesh in patients undergoing permanent end-colostomy; <lb/>the PREVENT-trial: study protocol for a multicenter randomized con-<lb/>trolled trial. Trials. 2012;13:226 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">| 1427 <lb/>HUBBARD et Al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>17. CiPHER trial. Available at: https://www.journalslibrary.nihr.ac.uk/ <lb/>programmes/hta/1416601/#/summary-of-research. Accessed 3rd <lb/>February 2017. <lb/>18. Thompson M, Trainor B. Incidence of parastomal hernia before and <lb/>after prevention program. Gastrointest Nurs. 2005;3:23-27. <lb/>19. Grant M, McMullen CK, Altschuler A, et al. Gender differences in <lb/>quality of life among long-term colorectal cancer survivors with osto-<lb/>mies. Oncol Nurs Forum. 2011;38:587-596. <lb/>20. Krouse R, Grant M, Ferrell B, Dean G, Nelson R, Chu D. Quality of life <lb/>outcomes in 599 cancer and non-cancer patients with colostomies. <lb/>J Surg Res. 2007;138:79-87. <lb/>21. Shabbir J, Britton DC. Stoma complications: a literature overview. <lb/>Colorectal Dis. 2010;12:958-964. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>How to cite this article: Hubbard G, Taylor C, Beeken B, et al. <lb/>Research priorities about stoma-related quality of life from the <lb/>perspective of people with a stoma: A pilot survey. Health Expect. <lb/>2017;20:1421-1427. https://doi.org/10.1111/hex.12585 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
