<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Structure and biochemical properties of recombinant <lb/>human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase and comparison to <lb/>the disease-related H109R variant <lb/>Peter Augustin 1 , Altijana Hromic , Tea Pavkov-Keller , Karl Gruber and Peter Macheroux <lb/>1 Institute of Biochemistry, Graz University of Technology, Austria <lb/>2 Institute of Molecular Biosciences, University of Graz, Austria <lb/>3 Austrian Centre of Industrial Biotechnology, Austria <lb/>Keywords <lb/>electron transfer; flavin adenine <lb/>dinucleotide; genetic disease; recombinant <lb/>protein expression; X-ray crystallography <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>P. Macheroux, Institute of Biochemistry, <lb/>Graz University of Technology, Petersgasse <lb/>12/II, A-8010 Graz, Austria <lb/>Fax: +43 (0)316 873 6952 <lb/>Tel: +43 (0)316 873 6450 <lb/>E-mail: peter.macheroux@tugraz.at <lb/>(Received 15 June 2016, revised 25 July <lb/>2016, accepted 1 August 2016) <lb/>doi:10.1111/febs.13828 <lb/>The human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase (hDMGDH) is a flavin adenine <lb/>dinucleotide (FAD)-and tetrahydrofolate (THF)-dependent, mitochondrial <lb/>matrix enzyme taking part in choline degradation, one-carbon metabolism <lb/>and electron transfer to the respiratory chain. The rare natural variant <lb/>H109R causes dimethylglycine dehydrogenase deficiency leading to <lb/>increased blood and urinary dimethylglycine concentrations. A detailed <lb/>biochemical and structural characterization of hDMGDH was thus far <lb/>hampered by insufficient heterologous expression of the protein. In the pre-<lb/>sent study, we report the development of an intracellular, heterologous <lb/>expression system in Komagataella phaffii (formerly known as Pichia pas-<lb/>toris) providing the opportunity to determine kinetic parameters, spectro-<lb/>scopic properties, thermostability, and the redox potential of hDMGDH. <lb/>Moreover, we have successfully crystallized the wild-type enzyme and <lb/>determined the structure to 3.1-<lb/>A resolution. The structure-based analysis <lb/>of our biochemical data provided new insights into the kinetic properties <lb/>of the enzyme in particular with respect to oxygen reactivity. A compara-<lb/>tive study with the H109R variant demonstrated that the variant suffers <lb/>from decreased protein stability, cofactor saturation, and substrate affinity. <lb/>Database <lb/>Structural data are available in the PDB database under the accession number 5L46. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The human flavoproteome comprises 90 enzymes with <lb/>versatile functions, structures, and protein characteris-<lb/>tics. Sixty percent of the known flavoproteins are <lb/>involved in human diseases and disorders emphasizing <lb/>their importance in human metabolism [1]. The human <lb/>mitochondrial matrix flavoprotein dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenase (hDMGDH, EC: 1.5.8.4) catalyzes the <lb/>oxidative demethylation of dimethylglycine (DMG) to <lb/>sarcosine, and also to a lesser extent the conversion of <lb/>sarcosine to glycine as part of choline degradation <lb/>(Fig. 1) [2,3]. Choline is an essential nutrient and <lb/>building block in a variety of vital biomolecules such <lb/>as the membrane phospholipid phosphatidylcholine <lb/>and the neurotransmitter acetylcholine [4]. Degrada-<lb/>tion of choline proceeds by consecutive oxidations <lb/>via betaine aldehyde, betaine, dimethylglycine, and <lb/></body>

			<front>Abbreviations <lb/>AgDMGO, Arthrobacter globiformis dimethylglycine oxidase; DCPIP, 2,6-dichlorophenolindophenol; DMG, dimethylglycine; DMGDH, <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase; ETF-QO, ETF-ubiquinone oxidoreductase; hDMGDH, human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase; hETF, human <lb/>electron-transferring flavoprotein; hMCAD, human medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase; MRE, mean residue ellipticity; PMS, phenazine <lb/>methosulfate; THF, tetrahydrofolate; WT, wild-type. <lb/>The FEBS Journal 283 (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, <lb/>distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/></front>

			<body>sarcosine to the amino acid glycine (Fig. 1) [5]. <lb/>hDMGDH, a key enzyme of this pathway, requires <lb/>two cofactors: flavin adenine dinucleotide (FAD) and <lb/>tetrahydrofolate (THF). The FAD is covalently <lb/>attached via its 8a-position to the N3 of a histidyl resi-<lb/>due and serves as the electron acceptor in the oxida-<lb/>tion of DMG. On the other hand, THF is used as the <lb/>acceptor of the incipient methyl group and thus pre-<lb/>vents the release of cell-toxic formaldehyde during <lb/>catalysis [3,6]. In the course of this reaction, N-5,10-<lb/>methylene tetrahydrofolate is formed, which plays an <lb/>important role in one-carbon metabolism. Regenera-<lb/>tion of oxidized FAD is achieved by electron transfer <lb/>to the human electron-transferring flavoprotein <lb/>(hETF), which in turn transfers the electrons to the <lb/>membrane-anchored ETF-ubiquinone oxidoreductase <lb/>(ETF-QO) for further utilization in the mitochondrial <lb/>respiratory chain [7,8]. <lb/>A rare naturally occurring point mutation found in <lb/>out of 118 656 (0.049%) analyzed human gene <lb/>sequences (Exome Aggregation Consortium online <lb/>browser; http://exac.broadinstitute.org/variant/5-78351 <lb/>682-T-C) results in the exchange of histidine 109 to <lb/>arginine (H109R). This variant reportedly suffers from <lb/>lower stability and enzymatic activity [9,10]. The <lb/>observed phenotype was described as dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenase deficiency with significantly higher <lb/>levels of dimethylglycine in human body fluids causing <lb/>muscle fatigue and a fish-like odor (OMIM: 605850). <lb/>Interestingly, the mutation is predominantly found in <lb/>individuals of African descent. <lb/>In recent years, also the product of the reaction cat-<lb/>alyzed by hDMGDH, sarcosine, attracted attention as <lb/>a biomarker for aggressive prostate cancer [11,12]. <lb/>Therefore, investigations on the regulation of sarcosine <lb/>levels and the enzymes involved are in the focus of <lb/>research. Furthermore, a recent epidemiological study <lb/>revealed a possible connection of dimethylglycine dehy-<lb/>drogenase deficiency to the development of diabetes, <lb/>further emphasizing the importance of the enzyme [13]. <lb/>Dimethylglycine dehydrogenase (DMGDH) was first <lb/>identified and purified from rat liver in the 1950s and <lb/>early 1960s [14,15]. Since then several publications <lb/>have dealt with the characterization of mammalian <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenases from rat [2,3,16] and <lb/>pig liver [8] as well as the recombinant rat [17,18] and <lb/>human enzyme [19] using Escherichia coli as expression <lb/>host. Furthermore, dimethylglycine oxidase from <lb/>Arthrobacter globiformis (AgDMGO) was character-<lb/>ized in biochemical and structural detail [6,20-23]. <lb/>However, the available information on the hDMGDH <lb/>appears insufficient and partly contradictory. In order <lb/>to overcome these deficiencies, we present a profound <lb/>analysis of the recombinant hDMGDH and the <lb/>H109R variant concerning kinetics, redox behavior, <lb/>and spectral properties. Furthermore, we have eluci-<lb/>dated the crystal structure of the human wild-type <lb/>enzyme. <lb/>THF <lb/>N-5,10-methylene-THF <lb/>Sarcosine <lb/>FAD + <lb/>FADH 2 <lb/>ETF <lb/>DMGDH <lb/>Glycine <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>ETF-QO <lb/>One-carbon metabolism <lb/>Mitochondrial respiratory chain <lb/>Choline <lb/>CHD <lb/>Dimethylglycine <lb/>PIPOX <lb/>2 e -<lb/>BAD <lb/>BHMT <lb/>DMGDH <lb/>SARDH <lb/>GNMT <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>+ <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>OH <lb/>Fig. 1. Mammalian choline degradation pathway with DMGDH as metabolic branch point. Choline degradation to dimethylglycine is <lb/>catalyzed by three enzymes, choline dehydrogenase (CHD), betaine aldehyde dehydrogenase (BAD), and betaine homocysteine <lb/>S-methyltransferase (BHMT). Conversion of dimethylglycine (DMG) to sarcosine by DMGDH reduces the FAD cofactor and a methyl group <lb/>is donated to THF resulting in FADH 2 and N-5,10-methylene-THF. The enzyme is reoxidized by the interaction with hETF and the derived <lb/>electrons are further channeled by ETF-QO to the mitochondrial respiratory chain. N-5,10-methylene-THF is consumed in further reactions <lb/>catalyzed by methylene-THF reductase (MTHFR) and serine hydroxymethyltransferase (SHMT). DMGDH is the only enzyme converting <lb/>dimethylglycine to sarcosine and the only other known route to sarcosine is via glycine N-methyl transferase (GNMT). Sarcosine is further <lb/>converted to glycine, mostly by sarcosine dehydrogenase (SARDH), and is also a substrate for dimethylglycine dehydrogenase and <lb/>peroxisomal sarcosine oxidase (PIPOX). <lb/></body>

			<page>3588 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>In order to characterize hDMGDH, we have estab-<lb/>lished a recombinant expression system for the <lb/>wild-type and the H109R variant in Komagataella phaffii <lb/>(formerly known as Pichia pastoris or Komagataella pas-<lb/>toris [24]) and a subsequent purification protocol. This <lb/>approach enabled us to determine key kinetic parame-<lb/>ters as well as physical and spectroscopic properties of <lb/>wild-type DMGDH. Consequently, we have also <lb/>employed our expression system to generate the <lb/>H109R variant to address the putative loss of function <lb/>that leads to DMGDH-deficiency in humans. More-<lb/>over, successful crystallization of the WT and subse-<lb/>quent crystallographic analysis provided us with the <lb/>opportunity to analyze the structure with regard to <lb/>substrate binding and oxygen reactivity. The latter <lb/>issue is especially interesting as the control of oxygen <lb/>reactivity in flavoenzymes is still a controversial topic. <lb/>The direct comparison of a dehydrogenase <lb/>(hDMGDH) and an oxidase (AgDMGO) allowed new <lb/>insights into the structural elements involved in oxygen <lb/>reactivity and supports concepts that are based on <lb/>gatekeeper residues in the vicinity of the isoalloxazine <lb/>ring system. In this vein, we show that a previously <lb/>proposed model to rationalize oxygen reactivity in the <lb/>vanillyl oxidase family is applicable to the family of <lb/>sarcosine and dimethylglycine dehydrogenases and oxi-<lb/>dases, respectively [25,26]. <lb/>Results <lb/>Enzyme expression and purification <lb/>Initial attempts to express the gene encoding <lb/>hDMGDH in Escherichia coli (BL21 DE3) yielded lar-<lb/>gely insoluble protein. On the other hand, heterologous <lb/>expression in the methanotrophic yeast Koma-<lb/>gataella phaffi (formerly known as Pichia pastoris [24]) <lb/>was successful. As shown in Fig. 2A, western blot anal-<lb/>ysis of K. phaffii cell lysates at different time points <lb/>indicates a stable expression of the protein after induc-<lb/>tion with methanol (MeOH). Typically, fermentations <lb/>were stopped after 96 h after MeOH induction result-<lb/>ing in 1.6-1.9 kg of wet cell pellet. A comparison of <lb/>signal intensities showed that the WT was expressed in <lb/>higher amounts than the variant under identical fer-<lb/>mentation conditions thus leading to a higher yield of <lb/>WT (Fig. 2A). After cell disruption and Ni-NTA affin-<lb/>ity chromatography, the yield of proteins (Fig. 2B, <lb/>lanes 3) was approximately 70 and 25 mg of the WT <lb/>and H109R variant, respectively (40 or 15 lg enzyme <lb/>per g wet cell weight). In order to achieve higher purity <lb/>for crystallization trials, the proteins were further puri-<lb/>fied using anion exchange chromatography (Fig. 2B, <lb/>lanes 4) resulting in lower protein yields of 30 and <lb/>2 mg (17 or 1 lg enzyme per g wet cell weight) of WT <lb/>and H109R variant, respectively. The protein loss <lb/>mainly occurred during the necessary buffer change to <lb/>lower salt concentrations after Ni-NTA affinity chro-<lb/>matography required for the subsequent anion <lb/>exchange chromatography. Although we experienced <lb/>that hDMGDH tends to precipitate at low salt concen-<lb/>trations, other chromatographic methods, like size-<lb/>exclusion chromatography or hydrophobic interaction <lb/>chromatography, were explored but did not give a <lb/>similar purity. <lb/>The A 280 /A 450 ratios of the highly pure protein frac-<lb/>tions were usually between 14-16 and 20-25 for the <lb/>WT and variant protein, respectively. The UV-Vis <lb/>absorption spectra show a clear difference between <lb/>enzyme-bound FAD and free FAD (Fig. 2C), whereas <lb/>hDMGDH-WT and the variant featured similar spec-<lb/>tral properties with identical absorption maxima. In <lb/>comparison with free FAD in solution, the UV-Vis <lb/>absorption maxima of FAD bound to either WT or <lb/>the H109R variant exhibit a hypsochromic shift from <lb/>370 to 350 nm and a bathochromic shift from 445 to <lb/>460 nm (Fig. 2C). <lb/>Determination of kinetic parameters for <lb/>hDMGDH-WT and H109R variant <lb/>The evaluation of the steady-state kinetic parameters <lb/>for hDMGDH-WT and H109R variant was conducted <lb/>using either ferrocene or 2,6-dichlorophenolindophenol <lb/>(DCPIP) as electron acceptor to oxidize the reduced <lb/>FAD cofactor. The obtained parameters show signifi-<lb/>cant differences between the two assay systems both in <lb/>terms of the k cat as well as the K M for DMG (Fig. 3, <lb/>Table 1). When ferrocene was used as the artificial <lb/>electron acceptor the k cat was fivefold greater than <lb/>with DCPIP (213 AE 4 versus 44 AE 1 min À1 , Table 1) <lb/>and the K M was significantly higher (1.4 AE 0.1 versus <lb/>0.3 AE 0.002 mM, Table 1). Interestingly, the H109R <lb/>variant exhibited a twofold higher activity than the <lb/>WT in both assays. At the same time, the K M of <lb/>DMG was strongly increased by a factor of 23 and 16 <lb/>in the ferrocene and DCPIP assay, respectively, result-<lb/>ing in an approximately 10-fold lower catalytic effi-<lb/>ciency of the H109R variant (Table 1). Notably, when <lb/>DCPIP was used as electron acceptor, data lineariza-<lb/>tion using the method of Eadie and Hofstee revealed a <lb/>second, much higher K M value of % 30 mM for DMG <lb/>(inset Fig. 3A). As the rate at which FAD is oxidized <lb/>by ferrocene is closer to the rate of flavin reduction, it <lb/>appears that ferrocene is superior to DCPIP as elec-<lb/>tron acceptor. <lb/></body>

			<page>3589 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>Due to much lower enzyme amounts available of <lb/>the H109R variant, presteady-state kinetics were solely <lb/>measured with the wild-type enzyme. As shown in <lb/>Fig. 4A, the rate of reduction as a function of DMG <lb/>concentration fitted to a hyperbolic equation yielding a <lb/>limiting reductive rate of 17 AE 0.3 s À1 and a dissocia-<lb/>tion constant of 4.9 AE 0.3 mM for DMG. Thus, the <lb/>reductive rate is 5-20 times faster than k cat determined <lb/>in the ferrocene and DCPIP (Table 1) indicating that <lb/>the electron transfer from the reduced FAD to the <lb/>artificial electron acceptor is rate-limiting in the assays <lb/>used to evaluate steady-state kinetics. Reoxidation of <lb/>hDMGDH with air-saturated buffer proceeds very <lb/>slowly with an observed rate of reoxidation of <lb/>0.006 AE 0.001 s À1 at an oxygen concentration of <lb/>Fig. 2. Heterologous expression and purification of hDMGDH-WT <lb/>and hDMGDH-H109R variant. (A) Western blot of K. phaffii cell <lb/>lysates taken at different time points after methanol induction. <lb/>Antibodies are directed against a C-terminal nona-histidine tag <lb/>fused to the recombinant enzymes and, as loading control, against <lb/>K. phaffii GAPDH. (B) SDS/PAGE of the different purification steps <lb/>of WT and variant shows efficient enzyme purification with Ni-NTA <lb/>affinity and MonoQ anion exchange chromatography. Lane 1, <lb/>fermentation pellet fraction; 2, K. phaffii lysate; 3, enzyme fraction <lb/>after Ni-NTA affinity chromatography; 4, enzyme fraction after <lb/>Mono Q; 5, protein standard. (C) UV-Vis absorption spectra of <lb/>DMGDH wild-type (black line) and the H109R variant (red line) after <lb/>anion exchange chromatography. The spectra were normalized to <lb/>the long-wavelength absorption maxima (445 and 450 nm, <lb/>respectively). Free FAD in solution is shown as a dotted blue line. <lb/>Fig. 3. Steady-state kinetics of hDMGDH-WT and H109R variant. <lb/>Steady-state kinetic experiments were performed with DCPIP (A) <lb/>and ferrocene activity assays (B) by plotting initial reaction <lb/>velocities (v 0 ) against the substrate concentration. Data obtained <lb/>for WT and H109R variant are represented in black and red, <lb/>respectively. Kinetic parameters are summarized in Table 1. <lb/>Linearization of the data in Eadie-Hofstee diagrams reveals two K M <lb/>values for the DCPIP assay, one at low (0-10 mM DMG) and one <lb/>at very high substrate concentrations (&gt; 50 mM DMG, inset panel <lb/>A). In contrast, the ferrocene assay produced a single K M value <lb/>when measured in the same concentration range (inset panel B). <lb/>Error bars are shown as standard deviations; n = 3. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3590 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>135 lM (inset Fig. 4A). Rapid reaction measurements <lb/>with sarcosine yielded a limiting rate of reduction of <lb/>0.7 AE 0.1 s À1 and a dissociation constant of <lb/>280 AE 10 mM clearly indicating that sarcosine is a <lb/>much poorer substrate than DMG (Fig. 4A). <lb/>Finally, we also studied the effect of THF on the <lb/>activity of hDMGDH using the ferrocene assay <lb/>(Fig. 5). The activity measurements were done simi-<lb/>larly to the ferrocene activity assay as described above <lb/>at 25°C and pH 7.8 in 50 mM HEPES/NaOH with <lb/>150 mM NaCl, 100 nM hDMGDH, 1 mM DMG, <lb/>0.1 mM EDTA, and 0.2 mM freshly prepared ferrocene <lb/>in a concentration range of 0-75 lM THF. As shown <lb/>in Fig. 5, the activity of WT decreases as a function of <lb/>the THF concentration. <lb/>Photoreduction and determination of the redox <lb/>potential of hDMGDH <lb/>Reduction of hDMGDH by DMG shows a <lb/>monophasic conversion of the oxidized FAD to the <lb/>two-electron reduced dihydroquinone state (Fig. 4B) <lb/>without any transient appearance of a semiquinone <lb/>radical. In contrast to substrate reduction, photore-<lb/>duction of hDMGDH leads to the anionic (red) fla-<lb/>vin semiquinone with a typical absorption maximum <lb/>at 372 nm (Fig. 6A). Further photoreduction eventu-<lb/>ally leads to the fully reduced dihydroquinone <lb/>(Fig. 6B), which is directly converted to the oxidized <lb/>state without the occurrence of a semiquinone upon <lb/>reaction with molecular dioxygen (Fig. 6C). This was <lb/>also seen when reduced hDMGDH was reacted with <lb/>air-saturated buffer in the stopped flow device (data <lb/>not shown). <lb/>In order to determine the redox potential of <lb/>hDMGDH, we employed the xanthine oxidase/xan-<lb/>thine method described by Massey [27] using indigo-<lb/>trisulfonic acid potassium salt as reference dye. The <lb/>slope of the double logarithmic plot was close to unity <lb/>indicating that the dye and the flavin receive an equal <lb/>Table 1. Summary of kinetic parameters obtained with steady-state kinetics for hDMGDH-WT and hDMGDH-H109R variant with two <lb/>different activity assays (DCPIP and ferrocene). <lb/>K M (mM) <lb/>v max (lMÁmin À1 ) <lb/>k cat (min À1 ) <lb/>A spec (lmolÁmg À1 Ámin À1 ) <lb/>k cat /K M (mM À1 Ámin À1 ) <lb/>WT DCPIP <lb/>0.3 AE 0.002 <lb/>30 a <lb/>4.7 AE 0.1 <lb/>11 a <lb/>44 AE 1 <lb/>0.5 AE 0.01 <lb/>146 AE 12 <lb/>WT ferrocene <lb/>1.4 AE 0.1 <lb/>22.1 AE 0.3 <lb/>213 AE 4 <lb/>2.0 AE 0.04 <lb/>137 AE 16 <lb/>H109R DCPIP <lb/>4.7 AE 0.4 <lb/>90 a <lb/>7.4 AE 0.3 <lb/>22 a <lb/>91 AE 4 <lb/>1 AE 0.04 <lb/>20 AE 2 <lb/>H109R ferrocene <lb/>32.2 AE 5.6 <lb/>44.1 AE 3.2 <lb/>544 AE 40 <lb/>6 AE 0.4 <lb/>11 AE 1 <lb/>a Two K M and v max values were obtained with the DCPIP, the higher was roughly estimated from Eadie-Hofstee plots (Fig. 3). <lb/>Fig. 4. Presteady-state kinetics of hDMGDH-WT. Reductive and <lb/>oxidative rates were measured under anoxic conditions with the <lb/>stopped flow device. (A) Reductive rates were determined for <lb/>DMG (black, left axis) and sarcosine (red, right axis). The inset <lb/>shows the reoxidation of reduced FAD as a function of time at <lb/>an oxygen concentration of 10.5% (135 lM O 2 ) at 460 nm. At <lb/>least three independent measurements were performed; error <lb/>bars are shown as standard deviations. (B) Selected absorption <lb/>spectra of the anoxic reduction of 10 lM hDMGDH-WT with <lb/>125 mM DMG. The direction of the change in absorption is <lb/>depicted by arrows. The top inset shows the absorption change <lb/>at 460 nm observed by mixing WT with 125 mM DMG, and the <lb/>bottom inset shows the change at 460 nm mixing WT with <lb/>125 mM sarcosine. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3591 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>number of electrons (i.e. two), although the anionic <lb/>semiquinone radical is clearly observable during the <lb/>redox titration (Fig. 6D). The redox potential for the <lb/>reduction of FAD bound to hDMGDH was calculated <lb/>from six independent measurements to À93 AE 1 mV. <lb/>Thermal stability of hDMGDH-WT and hDMGDH-<lb/>H109R <lb/>The thermal stability of both enzymes was determined <lb/>using <lb/>Thermofluor Ò <lb/>and <lb/>circular <lb/>dichroism <lb/>Fig. 5. hDMGDH-WT activity as a function of the THF <lb/>concentration. The activity was measured using the ferrocene <lb/>activity assay. The error bars show the standard deviation of at <lb/>least three measurements for each THF concentration. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>450 <lb/>500 <lb/>550 <lb/>600 <lb/>Absorption <lb/>Wavelength [nm] <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>300 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>450 <lb/>500 <lb/>550 <lb/>600 <lb/>Absorption <lb/>Wavelength [nm] <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>350 <lb/>400 <lb/>450 <lb/>500 <lb/>550 <lb/>600 <lb/>Absorption <lb/>Wavelength [nm] <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>360 <lb/>430 <lb/>500 <lb/>710 <lb/>Absorption <lb/>Wavelength [nm] <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>log[ox(dye)/red(dye)] <lb/>log[ox(DMGDH)/red(DMGDH)] <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>Fig. 6. Photoreduction and redoxpotential of hDMGDH-WT. (A) and <lb/>(B) show selected absorption spectra of the anoxic photoreduction <lb/>of the wild-type enzyme. About 20 lM of hDMGDH was <lb/>photoreduced in the presence of 1 mM EDTA, 2 lM 5-deaza FMN, <lb/>and 2 lM methylviologen. First, the enzyme is reduced to the red <lb/>semiquinone radical state (A) before proceeding to the typical <lb/>spectrum of a fully reduced hydroquinone species (B). The <lb/>admission of oxygen to the enzyme shows that reoxidation does <lb/>not proceed through a semiquinone redox state and directly yields <lb/>the oxidized state (C). (D) The redox potential for the WT was <lb/>determined with the xanthine/xanthine oxidase system described <lb/>by Massey [27]. The plot shows the simultaneous reduction of the <lb/>enzyme and the dye with the double logarithmic evaluation of the <lb/>data according to Minnaert [39] in the inset. About 20 lM <lb/>hDMGDH were reduced at 25°C over 120 min with <lb/>indigotrisulfonic acid potassium salt. The evaluation for the enzyme <lb/>was done at 480 nm where the dye does not show a contribution <lb/>to the absorption. Values for the dye were measured at 600 nm. <lb/>Initial absorption spectra in all panels are depicted in bold lines, <lb/>whereas final absorption spectra are shown as dashed lines. Only <lb/>selected absorption spectra are shown. The direction of the <lb/>change in absorption is depicted by arrows. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3592 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal 283 (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>spectroscopy. Thermofluor Ò temperature scans from <lb/>25 to 95°C showed that the WT and the H109R vari-<lb/>ant have melting points (T m ) of 52°C and 47°C, <lb/>respectively (Fig. 7A). A similar result was obtained <lb/>by means of CD spectroscopy yielding a T m of 53°C <lb/>and 47°C, for WT and the variant, respectively <lb/>(Fig. 7B). Thus, both independent methods confirm <lb/>that the variant exhibits reduced thermal stability. <lb/>Protein structure analysis <lb/>The X-ray crystal structure of hDMGDH was deter-<lb/>mined at 3.1 <lb/>A resolution (Table 2). The crystal <lb/>belongs to the monoclinic space group (P2 1 ) and <lb/>contains two dehydrogenase molecules in the asym-<lb/>metric unit. The two molecules in the asymmetric <lb/>unit are very similar to each other with an rmsd of <lb/>0.22 <lb/>A calculated after the superposition of 810 out <lb/>of 828 Ca-atoms using the program PYMOL (DeLano <lb/>Scientific). As previously observed in rDMGDH and <lb/>also after superposition with the rat enzyme (rmsd of <lb/>0.37 <lb/>A calculated for 739 out of 809 Ca-atoms), the <lb/>human enzyme consists of two domains: the FAD-<lb/>binding domain (N-terminal domain with residues <lb/>46-466) and the folate-binding domain (C-terminal <lb/>domain with residues 467-855, Fig. 8A). The FAD <lb/>Fig. 7. Thermal stability of hDMGDH-WT and the H109R variant. <lb/>The melting temperatures of wild-type and the variant enzyme <lb/>differ significantly when measured with Thermofluor â (A) or CD <lb/>spectroscopy (B). Thermofluor â was done with 2 lM enzyme and <lb/>the addition of SYPRO Orange. The change in fluorescence during <lb/>heating is shown for WT and H109R variant in black and red lines, <lb/>respectively. The inset in panel A shows the Àd(fluorescence)/dT <lb/>derivative curves of the raw data. CD spectroscopy was done with <lb/>approximately 6 lM enzyme. Mean residue ellipticity (MRE) was <lb/>measured every 0.1°C at 208 nm which is shown by black-and <lb/>red-filled circles for WT and variant, respectively. The data were <lb/>fitted with a sigmoidal curve in ORIGIN. The inset in panel B shows <lb/>the Àd(MRE)/dT derivative curves of the sigmoidal fits. The variant <lb/>(red line) exhibits an inflection point at a lower temperature as the <lb/>wild-type (black line) in both measurements. <lb/>Table 2. Data collection and refinement statistics. <lb/>X-ray source <lb/>ID29, ESRF, Grenoble, France <lb/>Wavelength ( A) <lb/>0.972 <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>100 <lb/>Space group <lb/>P2 1 <lb/>Cell dimensions <lb/>a, b, c ( A) <lb/>83.38, 119.87, 86.47 <lb/>b (°) <lb/>92.59 <lb/>Resolution ( A) <lb/>High resolution shell <lb/>58.65-3.09 (3.2-3.09) <lb/>Total no. reflections <lb/>86 727 (7935) <lb/>Unique no. reflections <lb/>30 495 (2897) <lb/>Multiplicity <lb/>2.8 (2.7) <lb/>Completeness (%) <lb/>97.7 (93.81) <lb/>&lt;I/rI&gt; <lb/>4.81 (1.53) <lb/>Wilson B-factor <lb/>47.09 <lb/>R merge <lb/>0.2058 (0.6573) <lb/>R meas <lb/>0.2531 <lb/>CC 1/2 <lb/>0.958 (0.604) <lb/>CC* <lb/>0.989 (0.868) <lb/>R work /R free <lb/>17.90/26.93 <lb/>Number of nonhydrogen atoms <lb/>Macromolecules <lb/>12 782 <lb/>Ligands <lb/>106 <lb/>Water <lb/>6 <lb/>Protein residues <lb/>1617 <lb/>Average B-factor <lb/>38.1 <lb/>Macromolecules <lb/>38.2 <lb/>Ligands <lb/>30.1 <lb/>Solvent <lb/>15.2 <lb/>R.m.s. deviations <lb/>Bond lengths ( A) <lb/>0.010 <lb/>Bond angles (°) <lb/>1.37 <lb/>Ramachandran outliers (%) <lb/>0.31 <lb/>Ramachandran favored (%) <lb/>94 <lb/>Clashscore <lb/>9.40 <lb/>PDB <lb/>5L46 <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3593 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>cofactor is covalently attached to the protein through <lb/>a linkage between N3 of His91 and the 8a-methyl <lb/>group of the isoalloxazine moiety as confirmed by <lb/>the crystal structure. The folate-binding domain can <lb/>be divided into three subdomains positioned in a <lb/>&apos;cloverleaf&apos;-like arrangement as previously described <lb/>for the rat enzyme [18]. Subdomain 1 (residues 467-<lb/>537 and 626-728) contains a Greek-key motif sur-<lb/>rounded by a-helices. Subdomain 2 (residues 538-625 <lb/>and 729-770) is defined by a five-stranded antiparal-<lb/>lel b-sheet with flanking a-helices. Subdomain 3 (resi-<lb/>dues 771-850) adopts a jellyroll fold. The structure <lb/>of the rDMGDH was determined in complex with <lb/>THF [18]. We also observed some difference electron <lb/>density in the same area in the folate-binding <lb/>domain. Due to the lower resolution of the diffrac-<lb/>tion data and/or an incomplete occupancy of the <lb/>ligand, however, this density was not clear enough to <lb/>unequivocally position a folate molecule. Based on <lb/>the structural similarity of the two enzymes, it is still <lb/>very likely that folate binds in the same position <lb/>(Fig. 8B). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Heterologous enzyme expression and purification <lb/>In this study, we demonstrated that intracellular <lb/>expression of hDMGDH in K. phaffii is feasible and <lb/>provides enough hDMGDH to perform a detailed <lb/>biochemical and structural characterization. The <lb/>expression of the full-length protein and a D50 trun-<lb/>cated version as well as secretory expression were <lb/>unsuccessful. However, an N-terminal D28 truncation <lb/>of the enzyme was expressed successfully representing <lb/>the mature form of the enzyme lacking its mitochon-<lb/>drial targeting sequence [28]. The intracellular <lb/>coexpression of the Saccharomyces cerevisiae protein <lb/>disulfide isomerase enzyme resulted in improved pro-<lb/>tein yields. The expression of hDMGDH in E. coli as <lb/>reported before [19] was unsuccessful and failed to <lb/>yield detectable amounts of protein as judged by <lb/>western blotting. A C-terminal nona-histidine-tag was <lb/>added to the gene in order to facilitate purification <lb/>by means of affinity chromatography. According to <lb/>the previously published structure of the rat enzyme <lb/>[18], this C-terminal tag should not interfere with the <lb/>native fold of the protein or catalytic activity. Wes-<lb/>tern blot analysis showed that the H109R variant is <lb/>expressed in lower amounts compared to the WT <lb/>(Fig. 2A). <lb/>A theoretical A 280 /A 450 ratio for hDMGDH fully <lb/>saturated with FAD cofactor can be roughly calcu-<lb/>lated to 14. The observed A 280 /A 450 ratios of the <lb/>highly pure proteins, 14-16 and 20-24 for WT and <lb/>H109R variant, respectively, revealed that the WT is <lb/>almost fully loaded with the covalently attached <lb/>FAD. In the case of the variant, the ratio was much <lb/>higher indicating a much lower saturation compared <lb/>to the WT (ca. 40-50% apoprotein), similar to <lb/>previously reported observations [19]. The higher <lb/>fraction of apoprotein may be responsible for the <lb/>recurring protein precipitation during purification of <lb/>the variant. Overall, this led to substantially reduced <lb/>yields of the variant protein and limited the scope of <lb/>experiments that could be conducted. <lb/>Spectral characteristics and steady-state kinetics <lb/>of hDMGDH <lb/>Recombinant hDMGDH features characteristic UV-<lb/>Vis absorption properties that clearly distinguish the <lb/>bound FAD from FAD free in solution (Fig. 2C). <lb/>These spectral characteristics are very similar to those <lb/>Fig. 8. Crystal structure of hDMGDH. (A) The overall structure of hDMGDH with the FAD-binding domain is shown in deep blue and the <lb/>folate-binding domain in raspberry. The THF-binding site is depicted with an arrow and the FAD cofactor is shown in yellow sticks. (B) <lb/>Superposition of the folate-binding domains of DMGDH from human (raspberry) and rat (cyan). The THF cofactor is shown in blue sticks <lb/>representation. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3594 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>reported earlier for DMGDH isolated from rat and <lb/>pig liver as well as for recombinant AgDMGO <lb/>[8,16,20]. In contrast, the UV-Vis absorption spectra <lb/>for heterologously expressed rat DMGDH [17] and <lb/>human DMGDH [19] are either of very poor quality <lb/>or apparently lack the spectral features that are typi-<lb/>cally found in these enzymes. In fact, the only pub-<lb/>lished spectrum of hDMGDH expressed in E. coli is <lb/>very similar to free FAD in solution (compare spectra <lb/>shown in Fig. 9). <lb/>A summary of our data and the previously pub-<lb/>lished kinetic steady-state data is given in Table 3. <lb/>These values were obtained using two different enzy-<lb/>matic activity assays, on one hand with ferrocenium <lb/>hexafluorophosphate as electron acceptor and on the <lb/>other hand, the combination of phenazine methosul-<lb/>fate (PMS) as electron mediator and DCPIP as termi-<lb/>nal electron acceptor. Both assays are physiologically <lb/>irrelevant as all mammalian DMGDHs interact with <lb/>the electron-transferring flavoprotein (hETF) for reoxi-<lb/>dation of the reduced cofactor. With the ferrocene <lb/>assay, we have obtained comparable results as <lb/>reported for the rat enzyme [18] and also for the bacte-<lb/>rial DMGO [22]. However, analysis of the data <lb/>obtained with the PMS/DCPIP yielded two Michaelis-<lb/>Menten constants similar to previously published data <lb/>for the rat enzyme [16,17]. Interestingly, aside from the <lb/>results reported by McAndrew et al. [19], two K M val-<lb/>ues were only observed for the two component DCPIP <lb/>activity assay, with PMS as electron mediator, but not <lb/>in the one component ferrocene or H 2 O 2 assay sug-<lb/>gesting that it is an experimental artifact. In view of <lb/>this apparent inconsistency, speculations that the pres-<lb/>ence of two K M values reflect the presence of activat-<lb/>ing or regulatory sites in the enzyme are unwarranted <lb/>[16,17]. Moreover, we have shown that the rate of <lb/>enzyme reduction is faster than k cat indicating that <lb/>reoxidation is rate-limiting for turnover in both assays. <lb/>Thus, the affinity of DMG to hDMGDH is more reli-<lb/>ably expressed as the dissociation constant determined <lb/>in presteady-state experiments. <lb/>Effects of a naturally occurring H109R enzyme <lb/>variation <lb/>The rare naturally occurring enzyme variant H109R <lb/>causes a nonfatal disease called dimethylglycine dehy-<lb/>drogenase deficiency (OMIM: 605850). The defect <lb/>results in an accumulation of DMG in blood serum <lb/>and urine, and patients suffer from a mild phenotype <lb/>including muscle fatigue and fish-like odor [9,10]. <lb/>During heterologous expression in K. phaffii, we <lb/>noticed decreased expression levels resulting in much <lb/>lower yields of the variant protein. Further character-<lb/>ization of the variant protein demonstrated lower <lb/>cofactor saturation and thermal stability. Interest-<lb/>ingly, the variant showed elevated turnover rates in <lb/>both of our assay systems although K M values were <lb/>15-25 times higher and the catalytic efficiency 10-fold <lb/>lower than for the WT (Table 1). Hence, our results <lb/>are clearly in contradiction with previously published <lb/>data [19] that claimed significantly decreased catalytic <lb/>activity of the H109R variant. As the spectral prop-<lb/>erties of DMGDH preparations obtained from the <lb/>E. coli expression system lacks the characteristic fea-<lb/>tures typically observed for DMGDH isolated from <lb/>natural sources (e.g., rat and pig liver), it is conceiv-<lb/>able that recombinant DMGDH generated in bacte-<lb/>rial host cells suffers from an altered FAD-binding <lb/>mode, such as noncovalent binding. In fact, the <lb/>absorption spectrum reported for wild-type DMGDH <lb/>and its H109R variant is clearly more similar to that <lb/>of free FAD (Fig. 9). In our hands, the bacterial <lb/>expression system produced solely insoluble protein <lb/>and therefore analysis of FAD binding to the protein <lb/>could not be inspected further. <lb/>Previous reports on the structure of bacterial <lb/>DMGO and rat DMGDH identified a large internal <lb/>cavity in the protein [6,18]. This cavity serves as &apos;reac-<lb/>tion chamber&apos; responsible for substrate delivery to the <lb/>active site, substrate conversion, as well as intermedi-<lb/>ate channeling to THF and product formation. The <lb/>binding site of THF is the only entry-exit point of the <lb/>protein, which was revealed by MD simulations for <lb/>the structurally related DMGO [6] and also confirmed <lb/>by cavity analysis of our structure (Fig. 10A). In <lb/>accordance with this interpretation, increasing THF <lb/>concentrations exhibited a negative effect on the <lb/>Fig. 9. Protein spectrum of this study (black line) compared with <lb/>the published hDMGDH spectrum (gray line, [19]) and free FAD in <lb/>solution (dotted blue line). The published spectrum resembles free <lb/>FAD in solution and not our spectral findings. <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>turnover rate (Fig. 5) as the substrate DMG competes <lb/>with THF for entrance into the cavity at the THF-<lb/>binding site. <lb/>The consistently (16-to 23-fold) higher K M <lb/>observed in both steady-state assays with the variant <lb/>suggests that replacement of histidine by the bulkier <lb/>arginine impedes access of DMG to the binding site <lb/>(Fig. 10B). On the other hand, the H109R variant <lb/>possessed higher k cat values indicating that the vari-<lb/>ant is more permissible in transferring electrons from <lb/>the reduced FAD to the artificial electron acceptors. <lb/>In conclusion, our analysis of the disease-related <lb/>H109R variant has revealed a lower thermal stability <lb/>and an approximately 10-fold lower catalytic efficiency <lb/>(Table 1) as major effects of the single amino acid <lb/>exchange. The diminished protein expression and <lb/>cofactor saturation found in our expression system <lb/>may also be relevant for homologous expression of the <lb/>variant in human cells and thus contribute to the over-<lb/>all reduced DMGDH activity manifested in affected <lb/>human subjects. <lb/>Substrate specificity, redox behavior, and active <lb/>site composition <lb/>The overall protein structure and the active site of <lb/>hDMGDH with the covalently bound FAD as well as <lb/>the THF-binding site are very similar to the rat <lb/>enzyme (PDB ID: 4PAA; [18]), and the structure of <lb/>AgDMGO [21]. In 2003, AgDMGO could be crystal-<lb/>lized with a bound folic acid (PDB ID: 1PJ6) but addi-<lb/>tionally also with a bound acetate ion that mimics the <lb/>negatively charged carboxylate group of DMG (PDB <lb/>ID: 1PJ5). Most residues in the active site of <lb/>AgDMGO described to play a role in catalysis and <lb/>substrate binding are also present in hDMGDH <lb/>(Fig. 11). Docking of DMG and sarcosine to the <lb/>active site of the hDMGDH structure results in a simi-<lb/>lar positioning of both substrates (Fig. 11A,B) and <lb/>thus do not rationalize the differences observed in <lb/>affinity and catalytic activity. This binding mode is <lb/>similar to the acetate moiety in the crystal structure of <lb/>DMGO (Fig. 11C). Presteady-state measurements <lb/>Fig. 10. hDMGDH internal cavity analysis and effect of H109R variation. (A) Cavity analysis of hDMGDH done with CASoX in PYMOL without <lb/>a bound THF cofactor. The protein cavity is shown in green surface view and the THF-binding site indicated by an arrow. (B) Close-up view <lb/>of the site of amino acid replacement (i.e., H109R) near the active site of the protein. A cavity analysis at this site was done in the wild-type <lb/>enzyme (His-109, blue mesh) and the H109R variant (Arg-109, green surface). The bulky, charged arginine extends into the cavity calculated <lb/>for the wild-type protein and potentially reduces the size of the substrate tunnel, thus substrate delivery to the FAD-binding site. FAD <lb/>cofactor is shown in yellow, the residues at position 109 in green and blue sticks, respectively. <lb/>Table 3. Comparison of steady-state kinetic parameters of published results for the DMGDH from Homo sapiens (human), <lb/>Rattus norvegicus (rat), Sus scrofa (pig), as well as the dimethylglycine oxidase from A. globiformis (Ag). <lb/>Enzyme <lb/>e --Acceptor <lb/>Conditions <lb/>K M (mM) <lb/>k cat (min À1 ) <lb/>A spec (lmolÁmg À1 Ámin À1 ) <lb/>k cat /K M (mM À1 Ámin À1 ) <lb/>Human -this study <lb/>DCPIP <lb/>pH 7.8, 25°C <lb/>0.3 AE 0.002 b <lb/>44 AE 1 <lb/>0.5 AE 0.01 <lb/>146 AE 12 <lb/>Human -this study <lb/>Ferrocene <lb/>pH 7.8, 25°C <lb/>1.4 AE 0.1 <lb/>213 AE 4 <lb/>2.0 AE 0.04 <lb/>137 AE 16 <lb/>Human -[19] <lb/>Ferrocene <lb/>pH 7.5, 25°C <lb/>0.04 AE 0.01 b <lb/>18 AE 2 <lb/>0.165 a <lb/>450 AE 110 <lb/>Rat -[18] a <lb/>Ferrocene <lb/>pH 7.5, 25°C <lb/>0.6 <lb/>160 <lb/>nd <lb/>270 <lb/>Rat -[17] a <lb/>DCPIP <lb/>pH 7.0, 30°C <lb/>0.05 b <lb/>12.1 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>nd <lb/>Rat -[16] a <lb/>DCPIP <lb/>pH 7.0, 25°C <lb/>0.05 b <lb/>8.4 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>nd <lb/>Pig -[8] a <lb/>DCPIP <lb/>pH 7.0, 25°C <lb/>nd <lb/>nd <lb/>0.157 <lb/>nd <lb/>Ag -[22] <lb/>O 2 <lb/>pH 8.5, 25°C <lb/>2.4 AE 0.2 <lb/>640 AE 20 <lb/>nd <lb/>270 AE 32 <lb/>nd, Not determined or stated in the publication. a No standard deviations available. b Two K M values were observed but only the physiologi-<lb/>cally relevant is displayed. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3596 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal 283 (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>comparing DMG and sarcosine as substrate for <lb/>hDMGDH-WT show a 25-fold decrease of the reduc-<lb/>tive rate for sarcosine as the substrate and a more than <lb/>50-fold higher K D . These results are in very good <lb/>agreement with data obtained for the bacterial DMGO <lb/>(Table 4) [22]. Therefore, sarcosine is a poor but possi-<lb/>bly physiologically relevant substrate for the enzyme <lb/>as already shown previously for the pig enzyme [3] <lb/>and AgDMGO [22]. On the other hand, sarcosine is <lb/>apparently oxidized by a homologous sarcosine dehy-<lb/>drogenase (SARDH) [16] and also by peroxisomal sar-<lb/>cosine oxidase (PIPOX) [29]. Therefore, the relative <lb/>turnover of sarcosine by these three FAD-dependent <lb/>enzymes must await further studies. <lb/>In the bacterial enzyme, a catalytic dyad, consisting of <lb/>a histidine and a tyrosine, is responsible for deprotona-<lb/>tion of the substrate amine [21]. This catalytic dyad is <lb/>also present in the human enzyme (Fig. 11). Further-<lb/>more, residues interacting with DMG (and sarcosine) <lb/>were identified in the structure of hDMGDH (Fig. 11A). <lb/>After binding and conversion of the substrate at the <lb/>active site, an intermediate, most likely a cyclic lactone is <lb/>channeled through the protein cavity to the THF-bind-<lb/>ing site [6]. The THF-binding sites of mammalian and <lb/>bacterial enzymes are again very similar and were <lb/>already extensively discussed by Luka et al. [18]. <lb/>Basran et al. reported a multistep kinetic model for <lb/>the reduction of DMGO by DMG. In contrast, the <lb/>reduction of hDMGDH by DMG was adequately fit <lb/>by a single exponential equation. The actual measure-<lb/>ment of the intermediate cyclic lactone could not be <lb/>observed, most likely due to its short lifetime as <lb/>described elsewhere [6]. <lb/>The two dehydrogenases in choline degradation <lb/>belong to a family of enzymes that delivers electrons to <lb/>the electron transferring flavoprotein (ETF). Among <lb/>these clients, only the redox potential for the two-elec-<lb/>tron reduction of human medium-chain acyl-CoA <lb/>dehydrogenases (hMCAD) was previously determined <lb/>[30,31]. This prompted us to determine the redox <lb/>potential for the covalently bound FAD in hDMGDH. <lb/>The obtained value of À93 AE mV is 40 mV more <lb/>positive than that of hMCAD (À135 mV [30,31]) in <lb/>agreement with the fact that covalent linkages to the 8-<lb/>methyl group increase the redox potential [32]. In any <lb/>case, the much higher redox potential of hETF <lb/>(+37 mV for the oxidized/semiquinone couple, [33]) <lb/>ensures that electrons from hDMGDH are readily <lb/>transferred to the ETF-bound FAD. <lb/>The rates of reduction determined for hDMGDH <lb/>are in good agreement with those observed for bacte-<lb/>rial DMGO (Table 4). In contrast to that, the oxygen <lb/>reactivity of reduced hDMGDH is more than 300 <lb/>times lower and apparently physiologically irrelevant <lb/>as reoxidation by its cognate partner protein hETF <lb/>proceeds over 30 times faster (P. Augustin, E. Gerst-<lb/>mann and P. Macheroux, unpublished results). <lb/>Recently, a study concerning steric control of dioxy-<lb/>gen reduction in enzymes of the vanillyl-alcohol oxi-<lb/>dase (VAO) family discovered a new &apos;gatekeeper&apos; <lb/>residue in berberine bridge enzyme and the pollen <lb/>allergen Phl p 4 [25]. This gatekeeper appears to con-<lb/>trol access to an oxyanion hole essential to stabilize <lb/>reaction intermediates during oxidation of the reduced <lb/>isoalloxazine ring by dioxygen. In this family, valine <lb/>was found to grant access to the oxyanion hole, <lb/>whereas isoleucine denies access [25]. Similarly, Lefer-<lb/>ink et al. discovered that a large number of oxidases <lb/>in the VAO family contain either a glycine or a proline <lb/>at a structurally conserved position near the isoalloxa-<lb/>Fig. 11. Docking and active site <lb/>composition of hDMGDH in comparison <lb/>with bound acetate in DMGO structure. <lb/>DMG (A) and sarcosine (B) were docked <lb/>into the active site of hDMGDH with <lb/>AUTODOCK/VINA [47]. The active site of DMGO <lb/>with bound acetate (C) was retrieved from <lb/>PDB ID: 1PJ5. The docked substrates and <lb/>the bound acetate are shown in green, <lb/>magenta, and black. FAD is shown in <lb/>yellow and all residues are depicted in stick <lb/>representation colored according to the <lb/>atom type. Key hydrogen bonds are shown <lb/>with black dotted lines. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3597 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal 283 (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>zine ring [26]. Although hDMGDH does not belong to <lb/>the VAO protein superfamily, comparison of the <lb/>hDMGDH to the AgDMGO structure reveals that <lb/>hDMGDH features residues typical for dehydroge-<lb/>nases suppressing oxygen reactivity, i.e., an alanine <lb/>and isoleucine, whereas AgDMGO possesses residues <lb/>compatible with high oxygen reactivity, i.e., proline <lb/>and valine (Fig. 12). Nevertheless, in order to further <lb/>support, if the emerging concept of how oxygen reac-<lb/>tivity is controlled in flavoproteins is applicable to <lb/>DMGDH, a member of the D-amino acid oxidase <lb/>(DAO) family of FAD-dependent oxidoreductases <lb/>(pfam: 01266), a detailed mutagenesis study of the con-<lb/>cerned residues has to be conducted. <lb/>Experimental procedures <lb/>Enzymes and reagents <lb/>Restriction enzymes and Phusion DNA polymerase were <lb/>from Thermo Fisher Scientific (Waltham, MA, USA), <lb/>purification columns and materials from GE Healthcare <lb/>(Chalfont St Giles, UK) and salt-free purified oligos for <lb/>site-directed mutagenesis from VBC-Biotech (Vienna, Aus-<lb/>tria). Antibodies used for western blot were from Cell Sig-<lb/>naling Technology (Cambridge, UK). The redox dye for <lb/>the determination of the redox potential, indigotrisulfonic <lb/>acid potassium salt, was from TCI Europe N.V. (Zwijn-<lb/>drecht, Belgium). All other chemicals and media were from <lb/>Carl Roth GmbH (Karlsruhe, Germany) and Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA) and were of the highest <lb/>grade available. <lb/>hDMGDH expression strain generation <lb/>hDMGDH and hDMGDH-H109R expression plasmids <lb/>were designed for intracellular enzyme expression in Koma-<lb/>gataella phaffii KM71H strain (formerly known as <lb/>Pichia pastoris or Komagataella pastoris [24]). The <lb/>hDMGDH sequence was codon optimized for expression <lb/>in K. phaffii using GeneOptimizer Ò (Thermo Fisher Scien-<lb/>tific). In accordance to Binzak et al., the sequence of the <lb/>mature form of hDMGDH (lacking the first 28 amino <lb/>acids, [28]) was used, flanked with XhoI and NotI restric-<lb/>tion sites. For enzyme expression and purification, a Kozak <lb/>sequence in front of the start codon (AAAA) and a C-<lb/>Table 4. Summary and comparison of transient kinetic data of hDMGDH (this study) with published results from A. globiformis DMGO <lb/>[22,23]. Measurements were done in a stopped flow at pH 7.8 and 25°C for hDMGDH and 25°C and pH 8.5 for the bacterial enzyme. <lb/>K D,DMG (mM) <lb/>k red,DMG (s À1 ) <lb/>K D,SAR (mM) <lb/>k red,SAR (s À1 ) <lb/>k ox (mM À1 Ás À1 ) <lb/>k obs,ox (s À1 ) <lb/>hDMGDH <lb/>4.9 AE 0.3 <lb/>17 AE 0.3 <lb/>280 AE 10 <lb/>0.7 AE 0.1 <lb/>0.04 AE 0.01 <lb/>0.006 AE 0.001 b <lb/>AgDMGO~10 a <lb/>15 AE 0.2 <lb/>850 AE 100 <lb/>0.16 AE 0.1 <lb/>201 <lb/>26 c <lb/>a Retrieved from Table 2 in [23]. b Measured at an oxygen concentration of 135 lM with p O2 = 0.105 bar, K H,pc = 791 bar M À1 [49] for the <lb/>substrate reduced enzyme. c Estimation from fig. 8 in [22]. <lb/>Fig. 12. Active site composition of the <lb/>oxygen-binding site of hDMGDH and <lb/>AgDMGO. The human structure is shown in <lb/>panel A with the most significant alternated <lb/>residues on the si-face of the flavin <lb/>isoalloxazine ring shown in green sticks. <lb/>The bacterial structure is shown in panel B, <lb/>important residues are shown in magenta. <lb/>For a better orientation, the catalytic active <lb/>histidine on the re-face is also displayed. <lb/>Panel C shows the alignment of the <lb/>bacterial and the human enzyme with the <lb/>supposed gatekeeper residues shown <lb/>corresponding to the reactive C(4a) carbon <lb/>of the isoalloxazine ring. All residues are <lb/>depicted in stick representation, FAD in <lb/>yellow and colored according to the atom <lb/>type. <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3598 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal 283 (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>terminal nona-histidine tag were added. The designed gene <lb/>was cloned into a pPICZ B expression vector (Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientific) and verified by automated sequencing. <lb/>The recombinant plasmid was transformed to K. phaffii <lb/>KM71H strain (Thermo Fisher Scientific), harboring a <lb/>pPICK-PDI vector containing the gene for the protein <lb/>disulfide isomerase from Saccharomyces cerevisiae following <lb/>the guidelines of the Invitrogen EasySelect TM Pichia Expres-<lb/>sion Kit (Thermo Fisher Scientific). Positive clones were <lb/>selected by Zeocin resistance and verified by western blot. <lb/>The H109R variant was constructed by a two-step site-<lb/>directed mutagenesis method employing Phusion DNA <lb/>polymerase and 5 0 -AACTTGAAGAAGATCAGATACG <lb/>ACTCCATCAAG-3 0 as forward and 5 0 -CTTGATGGAG <lb/>TCGTATCTGATCTTCTTCAAGTT-3 0 as reverse primer <lb/>(alternated codon underlined). For the first reaction step, <lb/>two separate PCR reactions using either the forward or the <lb/>reverse primer were run with the PCR program: 98°C <lb/>(2 min) -[98°C (50 s) -60°C (20 s) -68°C <lb/>(16.5 min)] 9 5 -4°C ∞. Afterwards, the two PCR reac-<lb/>tions were combined and the same program was employed <lb/>for another 20 cycles. Then, after a 2-h DpnI digestion step, <lb/>the plasmid was transformed to Escherichia coli TOP10 <lb/>cells for amplification before transformation to K. phaffii <lb/>KM71H [pPICK-PDI]. Strain selection was done as <lb/>described above. <lb/>Enzyme expression <lb/>hDMGDH and hDMGDH-H109R expression was carried <lb/>out in a 7-L glass fermenter BBI CT5-2 system (Sartorius, <lb/>G€ ottingen, Germany). Preparation of inoculum, and prepa-<lb/>ration of the fermenter, batch, and fed-batch were carried <lb/>out as described by Schrittwieser et al. [34]. The fermenta-<lb/>tion medium was a minimal basal salt medium (MgSO • <lb/>7 H 2 O -1.2 gÁL À1 ; K 2 SO 4 -14.9 gÁL À1 ; KOH -<lb/>18.2 gÁL À1 ; NaCl -4.13 gÁL À1 ; glycerol -40 gÁL À1 ; 85% <lb/>H 3 PO 4 -27 mLÁL À1 ). After the fed-batch, the MeOH <lb/>induction was started by injection of 5 g MeOH directly <lb/>into the fermenter and afterwards by a stepwise increase in <lb/>MeOH feed from 0 to 6 gÁh À1 over 2 h. Glycerol feed was <lb/>reduced from 15 to 6 gÁh À1 over 2 h and a mixed MeOH/ <lb/>glycerol feed was maintained until the end of the fermenta-<lb/>tion. In total, 400-500 g MeOH was fed to the cultures <lb/>before harvest after 96 h of induced growth. Samples were <lb/>taken for western blot analysis at different time points. The <lb/>cell pellet was collected by centrifugation (2704 g, 30 min, <lb/>4°C) and stored at À20°C. <lb/>Enzyme purification <lb/>Cell lysates were prepared by Merckenschlager (Braun Bio-<lb/>tech International, Melsungen, Germany) glass beads cell <lb/>homogenization under CO 2 cooling (3-min disruption <lb/>steps). For every 1 g harvested wet cell pellet, 2-mL cell <lb/>lysis buffer (50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, 35 mM <lb/>imidazole, 1 mM PMSF, pH 7.8) and a spatula tip of FAD <lb/>were added before cell disruption. The lysates were cleared <lb/>by centrifugation (38 720 g, 30 min, 4°C) and filtered <lb/>through a paper filter. Nickel ion affinity chromatography <lb/>was done by applying the lysates onto self-packed nickel-<lb/>Sepharose 6 Fast Flow columns (GE Healthcare) at 4°C. <lb/>Afterwards, the material was washed with washing buffer <lb/>(50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, 75 mM imidazole, <lb/>pH 7.8) and the enzyme stripped with elution buffer <lb/>(50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, 300 mM imidazole, <lb/>pH 7.8). The purification was monitored by SDS/PAGE <lb/>and fractions containing hDMGDH were concentrated and <lb/>rebuffered to storage buffer (50 mM HEPES/NaOH, <lb/>150 mM NaCl, pH 7.8) using Amicon ultracentrifugal filter <lb/>units (50 kDa cut-off; Merck-Milipore, Darmstadt, Ger-<lb/>many). The obtained enzyme purity was sufficient for <lb/>kinetic and photometric studies of the enzymes. If a higher <lb/>enzyme purity was needed, especially for protein crystalliza-<lb/>tion, the eluted fractions of the affinity chromatography <lb/>were rebuffered to buffer A (25 mM HEPES/NaOH, 25 mM <lb/>NaCl, pH 7.8), and anion exchange chromatography with a <lb/>MonoQ 5/50 GL column (GE Healthcare) was done on an <lb/>€ <lb/>AKTA FPLC system (GE Healthcare) at 4°C. The protein <lb/>was eluted with a gradient from 0% to 50% buffer B <lb/>(25 mM HEPES/NaOH, 1 M NaCl, pH 7.8). The chro-<lb/>matography was controlled by SDS/PAGE and fractions <lb/>containing hDMGDH were concentrated and rebuffered to <lb/>storage buffer as described above. Purification was done <lb/>identically for the wild-type and the variant enzyme. <lb/>SDS/PAGE <lb/>Enzyme samples were separated by SDS/PAGE, with <lb/>12.5% separation gels (for western blot 10%), under reduc-<lb/>ing conditions as described by Laemmli [35]. Gels were <lb/>either used for western blot analysis or stained with Coo-<lb/>massie brilliant blue R-250 for purification control. As pro-<lb/>tein standard, a PageRuler Prestained protein ladder <lb/>(Thermo Fisher Scientific) was employed. <lb/>Western blot <lb/>K. phaffii cell lysates for western blot screening and control <lb/>of fermentation were prepared by glass bead disruption fol-<lb/>lowing the Invitrogen EasySelect TM Pichia Expression Kit <lb/>manual (p. 42, Thermo Fisher Scientific). Western blot <lb/>analysis was done on nitrocellulose membranes essentially <lb/>following the General Protocol for western blotting from <lb/>Bio-Rad (Hercules, CA, USA; Bulletin 6376). As anti-<lb/>bodies, a rabbit anti-histidine IgG antibody at 1 : 2000 <lb/>overnight at 4°C as primary and an HRP-linked goat <lb/>anti-rabbit IgG antibody at 1 : 5000 for 1 h at room <lb/>temperature as secondary antibody were used. As loading <lb/>control, a rabbit anti-GAPDH antibody was used in a <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<body>1 : 1000 dilution overnight. Immunoreactive signals were <lb/>obtained using SuperSignal West Pico Chemiluminescent <lb/>Substrate (Thermo Fisher Scientific) and detection in a <lb/>G:BOX (Syngene, Cambridge, UK). <lb/>UV-Vis absorption spectroscopy <lb/>UV-Vis absorption spectra to assess protein concentration, <lb/>activity, purity, quality, and cofactor saturation, as well as <lb/>for steady-state kinetic measurements and photoreduction <lb/>were recorded with a Specord 210 spectrophotometer <lb/>(Analytik Jena, Jena, Germany). <lb/>Enzyme quantification and calculation of the <lb/>extinction coefficient <lb/>Protein concentrations of purified hDMGDH enzymes were <lb/>determined according to the characteristic absorption of <lb/>bound FAD at 450 nm. The molar extinction coefficient <lb/>for hDMGDH was calculated using the method described <lb/>by Macheroux [36] to 11 600 M À1 Ácm À1 . <lb/>Steady-state kinetics <lb/>Steady-state kinetic parameters were determined using <lb/>DCPIP according to Okamura-Ikeda et al. [37] or ferroce-<lb/>nium hexafluorophosphate (Fc + PF À <lb/>6 ) as described by <lb/>Lehman et al. [38] as terminal electron acceptor and mea-<lb/>surable dimension in the spectrophotometer. In short, <lb/>DCPIP assays were performed at 25°C and pH 7.8 in <lb/>50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, 135 lM DCPIP, and <lb/>100 nM hDMGDH with freshly prepared 3 mM phenazine <lb/>methosulfate (PMS) as intermediate electron mediator and <lb/>0-100 mM dimethylglycine (DMG) following the change of <lb/>absorption spectrophotometrically at 600 nm over 3 min. <lb/>Ferrocenium assays were performed at 25°C at pH 7.8 in <lb/>50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, 0.1 mM EDTA, <lb/>100 nM hDMGDH, 0-100 mM DMG, and freshly prepared <lb/>0.2 mM Fc + PF À <lb/>6 following the change of absorption at <lb/>300 nm over 3 min. For each concentration, at least a trip-<lb/>licate measurement was performed, the initial velocities <lb/>were determined, and K M and k cat were assessed by nonlin-<lb/>ear hyperbolic fit in ORIGIN 8.6 (OriginLab Corp., <lb/>Northampton, MA, USA). <lb/>Presteady-state kinetics <lb/>Presteady-state reaction kinetics were measured anaerobi-<lb/>cally with a Hi-Tech stopped flow instrument (SF-61DX2; <lb/>TgK Scientific Limited, Bradford-on-Avon, UK) in a glove <lb/>box (Belle Technology, Weymouth, UK) at 25°C. For <lb/>determination of the reductive rates of enzyme-bound <lb/>FAD, 20 lM purified hDMGDH in 50 mM HEPES/NaOH, <lb/>pH 7.8 containing 150 mM NaCl was shot against different <lb/>concentrations of DMG (0.25-250 mM) or sarcosine <lb/>(0-500 mM) dissolved in 50 mM HEPES/NaOH, mM <lb/>NaCl pH 7.8 and monitored at 460 nm with a Kineta-<lb/>ScanT diode array detector (MG-6560; TgK Scientific Lim-<lb/>ited). Each concentration was measured in triplicates and <lb/>the observed rate constants (k obs ) for different substrate <lb/>concentrations were calculated using an exponential fitting <lb/>function in the KINETIC STUDIO software (TgK Scientific <lb/>Limited). The dissociation constant (K D ) was determined <lb/>by a hyperbolic fitting curve employing ORIGIN 8.6 <lb/>(OriginLab Corp.). The oxidative rate (k ox ) of the enzyme <lb/>was measured three times at an oxygen concentration of <lb/>10.5% O 2 (135 lM O 2 ), by mixing substrate-reduced <lb/>hDMGDH with air equilibrated buffer (50 mM HEPES/ <lb/>NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.8). <lb/>Determination of the redox potential <lb/>The redox potential (E 0 ) of the enzyme-bound FAD was <lb/>measured by the dye-equilibration method using the xan-<lb/>thine/xanthine oxidase system as described by Massey [27]. <lb/>The concentrations of enzyme and redox dye were chosen <lb/>in a way that their absorption maxima were in the same <lb/>range. The reactions were performed with a Hi-Tech <lb/>stopped flow device (SF-61DX2; TgK Scientific Limited). <lb/>The measurements took place under anaerobic conditions <lb/>in a glove box (Belle Technology) at 25°C in 50 mM <lb/>HEPES/NaOH, 150 mM NaCl, pH 7.0. The simultaneous <lb/>reduction of FAD and the redox dye was monitored with <lb/>a KinetaScanT diode array detector (MG-6560; TgK <lb/>Scientific Limited). The reaction was started by mixing a <lb/>solution containing 300 lM xanthine, 5 lM benzyl violo-<lb/>gen, and an appropriate amount of enzyme with a solu-<lb/>tion containing catalytic amounts of xanthine oxidase <lb/>(approximately 200 nM, from bovine milk, Grade III pur-<lb/>ity; Sigma-Aldrich) and the redox dye indigotrisulfonic <lb/>acid dipotassium salt (E 0 , pH 7.0, 25°C = À81 mV). The <lb/>redox potential was calculated using double logarithmic <lb/>plots, log(ox/red) of the enzyme versus log(ox/red) of the <lb/>dye, according to Minnaert [39]. A linear least-squares fit <lb/>was done with Excel 2010 (Microsoft, Redmond, WA, <lb/>USA). <lb/>Anaerobic photoreduction and reoxidation <lb/>Photoreduction of hDMGDH was done according to the <lb/>procedure reported by Massey and Hemmerich [40]. About <lb/>lM purified enzyme sample in 50 mM HEPES/NaOH, <lb/>pH 7.8 containing 150 mM NaCl, 1 mM EDTA, 1 lM <lb/>5-diaza-FMN, and 2 lM methyl viologen were rendered <lb/>anaerobic by 2-h incubation in sealable quartz cuvettes in a <lb/>glove box (Belle Technology). Photoirradiation was carried <lb/>out with a 10 W LED flood light (Luminea, Buggingen, <lb/>Germany) and cooling of the cuvette to 15°C. Spectra <lb/>were recorded until no further changes were observed. For <lb/>reoxidation of the enzyme, the cuvettes were exposed to air <lb/></body>
			
			<page>3600 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>oxygen and absorption spectra were recorded until no <lb/>further changes were observed. <lb/>Temperature stability <lb/>Thermofluor ® <lb/>The temperature stability of the enzymes was assessed by <lb/>monitoring the change in fluorescence using the solva-<lb/>tochromic dye SYPRO Orange (Sigma-Aldrich) in a Ther-<lb/>mofluor Ò assay. Thermofluor Ò measurements were carried <lb/>out as reviewed elsewhere [41] in an FX Connect real-time <lb/>PCR system (Bio-Rad) in 25 lL of 50 mM HEPES/NaOH, <lb/>pH 7.8, containing 150 mM NaCl, 10 lM of enzyme, and <lb/>2.5 lL of a 5009 dilution of a SYPRO Orange Enzyme <lb/>Gel stain. The samples were preheated to 25°C and then <lb/>the temperature was increased in 0.5°CÁmin À1 steps to <lb/>95°C. Fluorescence data were collected using the FRET <lb/>channel. Melting temperatures (T m ) were determined using <lb/>CFX MANAGER 3.0 software (Bio-Rad). <lb/>Circular dichroism spectroscopy <lb/>CD spectra were recorded on a PS-150J spectropolarimeter <lb/>(Jasco, Groß-Umstadt, Germany) using a 0.02 cm water-<lb/>jacketed cylindrical cell thermostatically controlled by an <lb/>external computer-controlled water bath (Julabo F25, Seel-<lb/>bach, Germany). Thermal denaturation data were recorded <lb/>in a temperature range from 25 to 95°C with a heating <lb/>rate of 1°CÁmin À1 , a response of 1 s, and a resolution of <lb/>0.1°C. The protein concentration used was approximately <lb/>6 lM in 50 mM HEPES/NaOH, 50 mM NaCl, pH 7.8. The <lb/>melting temperature was estimated as the point of inflection <lb/>of the temperature-dependent mean residue ellipticity at <lb/>208 nm. <lb/>Crystallization of hDMGDH <lb/>Crystallization experiments were performed with the micro-<lb/>batch method using different commercial crystallization <lb/>screens [Index and Morpheus Screen from Hampton <lb/>Research (Aliso Viejo, CA, USA) and Molecular Dimen-<lb/>sions (Newmarket, UK), respectively]. Drops were prepared <lb/>by mixing 0.5 lL of the protein solution (at a concentra-<lb/>tion of 4 mgÁmL À1 in 25 mM HEPES, 25 mM NaCl, and <lb/>2 mM DTT, pH 7.5) with an equal volume of mother liquor <lb/>using an ORYX 8 pipetting robot (Douglas Instruments, <lb/>Hungerford, UK). The drops were sealed with a 3 : 1 mix-<lb/>ture of paraffin and silicon oil and the trays incubated at <lb/>20°C. First crystal clusters were observed after approxi-<lb/>mately 1 month in various conditions. Further optimization <lb/>involved dilutions of the original condition using 25 mM <lb/>HEPES, 25 mM NaCl, 2 mM DTT, pH 7.5. Diffracting <lb/>hDMGDH crystals were obtained with a 1 : 3 dilution of <lb/>the original condition H5 of the Morpheus Screen consist-<lb/>ing of 10% w/v PEG 20000, 20% v/v PEG MME 550, <lb/>0.02 M of each amino acid, and 0.1 M MOPS/HEPES-Na <lb/>pH 7.5. <lb/>Data collection and processing <lb/>X-ray diffraction data were collected to a maximum resolu-<lb/>tion of 3.1 <lb/>A on beam line ID29 (k = 0.972 <lb/>A) at the <lb/>ESRF Grenoble, France. The crystals were monoclinic <lb/>(space group P2 1 ) with unit-cell parameters a = 83.38 <lb/>A, <lb/>b = 119.87 <lb/>A, c = 86.47 <lb/>A, and b = 92.6°. The data were <lb/>processed using the XDS package [42] and the structure was <lb/>solved by molecular replacement using the structure of the <lb/>rat dimethylglycine dehydrogenase (PDB ID: 4PAA, 90% <lb/>sequence identity) [18]. Structure rebuilding and refinement <lb/>were performed using the programs COOT [43] and PHENIX <lb/>[44]. The model contained one B-factor per amino acid resi-<lb/>due. Noncrystallographic-symmetry (NCS) restraints were <lb/>applied. A small number of water molecules were added <lb/>only manually into the most significant electron difference <lb/>electron density peaks before the last cycle of refinement. <lb/>Clear electron density was observed for the majority of the <lb/>amino acids except of the first 18 N-terminal residues and <lb/>the 13 C-terminal residues in both chains present in the <lb/>asymmetric unit. Residual density was interpreted as FAD <lb/>in both chains. The final structure was validated using MOL-<lb/>PROBITY [45]. Detailed statistics pertaining to data process-<lb/>ing and structure refinement are summarized in Table 2. <lb/>The atomic coordinates and structure factors have been <lb/>deposited in the Protein Data Bank under the accession <lb/>number 5L46. <lb/>In silico procedures <lb/>Figures for structural analyses were prepared using PYMOL <lb/>(DeLano Scientific, San Carlos, CA, USA [46]). In silico <lb/>mutagenesis of hDMGDH residue H109 to R109 in the <lb/>crystal structure was performed with the mutagenesis wiz-<lb/>ard of PYMOL (DeLano Scientific) and subsequent energy <lb/>minimization using YASARA (Yasara Biosciences, Vienna, <lb/>Austria). Docking experiments of DMG and sarcosine into <lb/>the hDMGDH structure was done using AUTODOCK/VINA <lb/>[47] as implemented in YASARA. Cavity analyses after and <lb/>before mutagenesis were performed with the LIGSITE <lb/>algorithm (CASoX plugin of PYMOL, [48]). <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>This work was supported by a grant from the Austrian <lb/>Science Foundation (FWF) to KG and PM (Doctoral <lb/>program &quot;Molecular Enzymology&quot; W901). The <lb/>authors would like to thank the Exome Aggregation <lb/>Consortium and the groups that provided exome <lb/>variant data for comparison. A full list of contributing <lb/>groups can be found at http://exac.broadinstitute.org/ <lb/>about. <lb/></div>

			<page>3601 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>PA has expressed, purified, and characterized the wild-<lb/>type enzyme and the variant; AH, TPK, and KG crys-<lb/>tallized proteins and determined the crystal structure <lb/>of WT hDMGDH; PA and PM designed biochemical <lb/>experiments and interpreted the data; PA, AH, TPK, <lb/>KG, and PM wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>
			
			<div type="annex">Conflict of interests <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 Lienhart WD, Gudipati V &amp; Macheroux P (2013) The <lb/>human flavoproteome. Arch Biochem Biophys 535, 150-<lb/>162. <lb/>2 Wittwer AJ &amp; Wagner C (1981) Identification of the <lb/>folate-binding proteins of rat liver mitochondria as <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase and sarcosine <lb/>dehydrogenase. Purification and folate-binding <lb/>characteristics. J Biol Chem 256, 4102-4108. <lb/>3 Wittwer AJ &amp; Wagner C (1981) Identification of the <lb/>folate-binding proteins of rat liver mitochondria as <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase and sarcosine <lb/>dehydrogenase. Flavoprotein nature and enzymatic <lb/>properties of the purified proteins. J Biol Chem 256, <lb/>4109-4115. <lb/>4 Ueland PM (2011) Choline and betaine in health and <lb/>disease. J Inherit Metab Dis 34, 3-15. <lb/>5 Wittwer AJ (1980) Identification of folate binding <lb/>protein of mitochondria as dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenase. Proc Natl Acad Sci 77, 4484-4488. <lb/>6 Tralau T, Lafite P, Levy C, Combe JP, Scrutton NS &amp; <lb/>Leys D (2009) An internal reaction chamber in <lb/>dimethylglycine oxidase provides efficient protection <lb/>from exposure to toxic formaldehyde. J Biol Chem 284, <lb/>17826-17834. <lb/>7 Ruzicka FJ &amp; Beinert H (1977) A new iron-sulfur <lb/>flavoprotein of the respiratory chain. J Biol Chem 252, <lb/>8440-8445. <lb/>8 Steenkamp DJ &amp; Husain M (1982) The effect of <lb/>tetrahydrofolate on the reduction of electron transfer <lb/>flavoprotein by sarcosine and dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenases. Biochem J 203, 707-715. <lb/>9 Moolenaar SH, Poggi-Bach J, Engelke UFH, <lb/>Corstiaensen JMB, Heerschap A, De Jong JGN, Binzak <lb/>BA, Vockley J &amp; Wevers RA (1999) Defect in <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase, a new inborn error of <lb/>metabolism: NMR spectroscopy study. Clin Chem 45, <lb/>459-464. <lb/>10 Binzak BA, Vockley JG, Jenkins RB &amp; Vockley J <lb/>(2000) Structure and analysis of the human <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase gene. Mol Genet Metab <lb/>69, 181-187. <lb/>11 Sreekumar A, Poisson LM, Rajendiran TM, Khan AP, <lb/>Cao Q, Yu J, Laxman B, Mehra R, Lonigro RJ, Li Y <lb/>et al. (2009) Metabolomic profiles delineate potential <lb/>role for sarcosine in prostate cancer progression. Nature <lb/>457, 910-914. <lb/>12 Ferro M, Buonerba C, Terracciano D, Lucarelli G, <lb/>Cosimato V, Bottero D, Deliu VM, Ditonno P, <lb/>Perdon a S, Autorino R et al. (2016) Biomarkers in <lb/>localized prostate cancer. Future Oncol 12, 399-411. <lb/>13 Magnusson M, Wang TJ, Clish C, Engstr€ om G, <lb/>Nilsson P, Gerszten RE &amp; Melander O (2015) <lb/>Dimethylglycine deficiency and the development of <lb/>diabetes. Diabetes 64, 3010-3016. <lb/>14 Hoskins DD &amp; Mackenzie CG (1961) Solubilization <lb/>and electron transfer flavoprtein requirement of <lb/>mitochondrial sarcosine dehydrogenase and <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase. J Biol Chem 236, 177-<lb/>183. <lb/>Frisell WR &amp; Mackenzie CG (1962) Separation and <lb/>purification of sarcosine dehydrogenase and <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase. J Biol Chem 237, 94-<lb/>98. <lb/>Porter DH, Cook RJ &amp; Wagner C (1985) Enzymatic <lb/>properties of dimethylglycine dehydrogenase and <lb/>sarcosine dehydrogenase from rat liver. Arch Biochem <lb/>Biophys 243, 396-407. <lb/>17 Brizio C, Brandsch R, Bufano D, Pochini L, Indiveri C <lb/>&amp; Barile M (2004) Over-expression in Escherichia coli, <lb/>functional characterization and refolding of rat <lb/>dimethylglycine dehydrogenase. Protein Expr Purif 37, <lb/>434-442. <lb/>18 Luka Z, Pakhomova S, Loukachevitch LV, Newcomer <lb/>ME &amp; Wagner C (2014) Folate in demethylation: the <lb/>crystal structure of the rat dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenase complexed with tetrahydrofolate. <lb/>Biochem Biophys Res Commun 449, 392-398. <lb/>McAndrew RP, Vockley J &amp; Kim J-JP (2008) <lb/>Molecular basis of dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>deficiency associated with pathogenic variant H109R. <lb/>J Inherit Metab Dis 31, 761-768. <lb/>20 Meskys R, Harris RJ, Casaite V, Basran J &amp; Scrutton <lb/>NS (2001) Organization of the genes involved in <lb/>dimethylglycine and sarcosine degradation in <lb/>Arthrobacter spp.: implications for glycine betaine <lb/>catabolism. Eur J Biochem 268, 3390-3398. <lb/>Leys D, Basran J &amp; Scrutton NS (2003) Channelling <lb/>and formation of &quot;active&quot; formaldehyde in <lb/>dimethylglycine oxidase. EMBO J 22, 4038-4048. <lb/>22 Basran J, Bhanji N, Basran A, Nietlispach D, Mistry S, <lb/>Meskys R &amp; Scrutton NS (2002) Mechanistic aspects of <lb/>the covalent flavoprotein dimethylglycine oxidase of <lb/>Arthrobacter globiformis studied by stopped-flow <lb/>spectrophotometry. Biochemistry 41, 4733-4743. <lb/></listBibl>
			
			<page>3602 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase <lb/>P. Augustin et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>23 Basran J, Fullerton S, Leys D &amp; Scrutton NS (2006) <lb/>Mechanism of FAD reduction and role of active site <lb/>residues His-225 and Tyr-259 in Arthrobacter <lb/>globiformis dimethylglycine oxidase: analysis of mutant <lb/>structure and catalytic function. Biochemistry 45, <lb/>11151-11161. <lb/>24 Kurtzman CP (2009) Biotechnological strains of <lb/>Komagataella (Pichia) pastoris are Komagataella phaffii <lb/>as determined from multigene sequence analysis. J Ind <lb/>Microbiol Biotechnol 36, 1435-1438. <lb/>Zafred D, Steiner B, Teufelberger AR, Hromic A, <lb/>Karplus PA, Schofield CJ, Wallner S &amp; Macheroux P <lb/>(2015) Rationally engineered flavin-dependent oxidase <lb/>reveals steric control of dioxygen reduction. FEBS J <lb/>282, 3060-3074. <lb/>26 Leferink NGH, Fraaije MW, Joosten HJ, Schaap PJ, <lb/>Mattevi A &amp; van Berkel WJH (2009) Identification of a <lb/>gatekeeper residue that prevents dehydrogenases from <lb/>acting as oxidases. J Biol Chem 284, 4392-4397. <lb/>27 Massey V (1991) A simple method for the <lb/>determination of redox potentials. In Flavins and <lb/>Flavoproteins (Curti B, Zanetti G &amp; Ronchi S, eds), pp. <lb/>59-66. Walter de Gruyter, Como, Italy. <lb/>28 Binzak BA, Wevers RA, Moolenaar SH, Lee YM, Hwu <lb/>WL, Poggi-Bach J, Engelke UF, Hoard HM, Vockley <lb/>JG &amp; Vockley J (2001) Cloning of dimethylglycine <lb/>dehydrogenase and a new human inborn error of <lb/>metabolism, dimethylglycine dehydrogenase deficiency. <lb/>Am J Hum Genet 68, 839-847. <lb/>Dodt G, Kim DG, Reimann SA, Reuber BE, McCabe <lb/>K, Gould SJ &amp; Mihalik SJ (2000) L-Pipecolic acid <lb/>oxidase, a human enzyme essential for the degradation <lb/>of L-pipecolic acid, is most similar to the monomeric <lb/>sarcosine oxidases. Biochem J 345 (Pt 3), 487-494. <lb/>30 Gustafson W, Feinberg B &amp; McFarland JT (1986) <lb/>Energetics of beta-oxidation. Reduction potentials of <lb/>general fatty acyl-CoA dehydrogenase, electron transfer <lb/>flavoprotein, and fatty acyl-CoA substrates. J Biol <lb/>Chem 261, 7733-7741. <lb/>Lenn ND, Stankovich MT &amp; Liu HW (1990) <lb/>Regulation of the redox potential of general acyl-CoA <lb/>dehydrogenase by substrate binding. Biochemistry 29, <lb/>3709-3715. <lb/>32 Fraaije MW, van den Heuvel RH, van Berkel WJ &amp; <lb/>Mattevi A (1999) Covalent flavinylation is essential for <lb/>efficient redox catalysis in vanillyl-alcohol oxidase. <lb/>J Biol Chem 274, 35514-35520. <lb/>33 Salazar D, Zhang L, deGala GD &amp; Frerman FE (1997) <lb/>Expression and characterization of two pathogenic <lb/>mutations in human electron transfer flavoprotein. <lb/>J Biol Chem 272, 26425-26433. <lb/>34 Schrittwieser JH, Resch V, Wallner S, Lienhart W-D, <lb/>Sattler JH, Resch J, Macheroux P &amp; Kroutil W (2011) <lb/>Biocatalytic organic synthesis of optically pure <lb/>(S)-scoulerine and berbine and benzylisoquinoline <lb/>alkaloids. J Org Chem 76, 6703-6714. <lb/>35 Laemmli UK (1970) Cleavage of structural proteins <lb/>during the assembly of the head of bacteriophage T4. <lb/>Nature 227, 680-685. <lb/>Macheroux P (1999) UV-visible spectroscopy as a tool <lb/>to study flavoproteins. Methods Mol Biol 131, 1-7. <lb/>Okamura-Ikeda K, Ikeda Y &amp; Tanaka K (1985) An <lb/>essential cysteine residue located in the vicinity of the <lb/>FAD-binding site in short-chain, medium-chain, and <lb/>long-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenases from rat liver <lb/>mitochondria. J Biol Chem 260, 1338-1345. <lb/>Lehman TC &amp; Thorpe C (1990) Alternate electron <lb/>acceptors for medium-chain acyl-CoA dehydrogenase: <lb/>use of ferricenium salts. Biochemistry 29, 10594-<lb/>10602. <lb/>39 Minnaert K (1965) Measurement of the equilibrium <lb/>constant of the reaction between cytochrome c and <lb/>cytochrome a. Biochim Biophys Acta 110, 42-56. <lb/>Massey V &amp; Hemmerich P (1978) Photoreduction of <lb/>flavoproteins and other biological compounds catalyzed <lb/>by deazaflavins. Biochemistry 17, 9-16. <lb/>41 Boivin S, Kozak S &amp; Meijers R (2013) Optimization of <lb/>protein purification and characterization using <lb/>Thermofluor screens. Protein Expr Purif 91, 192-206. <lb/>42 Kabsch W (2010) XDS. Acta Crystallogr D 66, 125-<lb/>132. <lb/>43 Emsley P, Lohkamp B, Scott WG &amp; Cowtan K (2010) <lb/>Features and development of Coot. Acta Crystallogr D <lb/>66, 486-501. <lb/>44 Adams PD, Afonine PV, Bunk oczi G, Chen VB, Davis <lb/>IW, Echols N, Headd JJ, Hung L-W, Kapral GJ, <lb/>Grosse-Kunstleve RW et al. (2010) PHENIX : a <lb/>comprehensive Python-based system for macromolecular <lb/>structure solution. Acta Crystallogr D 66, 213-221. <lb/>45 Chen VB, Arendall WB, Headd JJ, Keedy DA, <lb/>Immormino RM, Kapral GJ, Murray LW, Richardson <lb/>JS &amp; Richardson DC (2010) MolProbity : all-atom <lb/>structure validation for macromolecular <lb/>crystallography. Acta Crystallogr D 66, 12-21. <lb/>46 DeLano WL (2002) The PyMOL molecular graphics <lb/>system, Version 1.5.0.4. Schr€ odinger, LLC, New York <lb/>City, NY, USA. <lb/>Trott O &amp; Olson AJ (2010) AutoDock Vina: improving <lb/>the speed and accuracy of docking with a new scoring <lb/>function, efficient optimization, and multithreading. <lb/>J Comput Chem 31, 455-461. <lb/>48 Hendlich M, Rippmann F &amp; Barnickel G (1997) <lb/>LIGSITE: automatic and efficient detection of potential <lb/>small molecule-binding sites in proteins. J Mol Graph <lb/>Model 15, 359-363. <lb/>49 Sander R (2015) Compilation of Henry&apos;s law constants <lb/>(version 4.0) for water as solvent. Atmos Chem Phys 15, <lb/>4399-4981. <lb/>3603 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">The FEBS Journal (2016) 3587-3603 ª 2016 The Authors. The FEBS Journal published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd on behalf of <lb/>Federation of European Biochemical Societies. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">P. Augustin et al. <lb/>Human dimethylglycine dehydrogenase </note>


	</text>
</tei>
