<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Editorial <lb/>Gut and Liver, Vol. 11, No. 1, January 2017, pp. 3-4 <lb/></front>

			<body>Inflammatory bowel diseases (IBD), including Crohn&apos;s disease <lb/>and ulcerative colitis, are idiopathic chronic intestinal inflam-<lb/>matory diseases, characterized by recurrent episodes of relapse <lb/>and remission of disease. The introduction of anti-tumor necro-<lb/>sis factor (anti-TNF) agents has greatly improved the treatment <lb/>outcomes for IBDs, enabling higher rates of clinical and endo-<lb/>scopic remission in patients who are refractory to conventional <lb/>therapies such as corticosteroids and thiopurines. 1,2 Despite <lb/>the proven therapeutic efficacy of anti-TNF agents, treatment <lb/>failures to those sometimes occur in the form of primary nonre-<lb/>sponse or secondary loss of response (LOR). <lb/>About 10% to 20% of IBD patients have been reported to be <lb/>unresponsive to induction treatment with anti-TNF agents. 3 The <lb/>mechanism of this primary nonresponse is unclear. Meanwhile, <lb/>of the patients who initially respond to anti-TNF treatment, a <lb/>significant proportion loses response over time with annual risk <lb/>of 13% to 24%. 4 Several distinct mechanisms for secondary <lb/>LOR have been suggested, including the formation of antidrug <lb/>antibodies (ADA), nonimmune drug clearance, relentless TNF-<lb/>mediated flare consuming the anti-TNF agent, shift of disease <lb/>pathway away from TNF, as well as non-IBD related mecha-<lb/>nisms such as irritable bowel syndrome, infection, cancer, and <lb/>so forth. 5 To prevent LOR to anti-TNF treatment, scheduled <lb/>treatment rather than episodic therapy and combination therapy <lb/>with immunomodulators than anti-TNF monotherapy are rec-<lb/>ommended. 6 <lb/>In patients presenting with LOR to anti-TNF agents, after ex-<lb/>cluding non-IBD, noninflammatory causes, several therapeutic <lb/>options such as dose intensification, switching to another anti-<lb/>TNF agents, and switching to another biologics with different <lb/>mechanism of action would be considered. In these circum-<lb/>stances, pharmacokinetic measurements of anti-TNF trough <lb/>levels (TL) and ADA could be useful to elucidate mechanisms of <lb/>LOR and guide selection of most appropriate therapeutic strat-<lb/>egy. 3 <lb/>Several studies have demonstrated clinical importance of <lb/>therapeutic drug monitoring (TDM) of anti-TNF agents by de-<lb/>termining drug levels and ADA in terms of a tailored approach <lb/>to IBD patients. Higher anti-TNF TLs have been associated with <lb/>better clinical outcomes and endoscopic improvement, while <lb/>undetectable anti-TNF TLs were related to loss of clinical re-<lb/>sponse and higher risk for surgery. On the contrary, immuno-<lb/>genicity (formation of ADA) has been known to accelerate anti-<lb/>TNF clearance and increase the risk of infusion reaction to anti-<lb/>TNF agents, although the exact clinical impact of ADA on anti-<lb/>TNF efficacy is still controversial. 7 In Western countries, clinical <lb/>decision algorithms with TDM based on drug levels and ADA <lb/>for the management of IBD patients with LOR, to optimize the <lb/>efficacy of anti-TNF and then to reduce health-related cost, has <lb/>been proposed and widely performed in clinical practice. 8 In <lb/>addition, some researchers have suggested that proactive TDM <lb/>will be promising even for IBD patients in clinical remission, to <lb/>maintain optimal anti-TNF concentrations and then to reduce <lb/>costs and risk for adverse events. 7 <lb/>However, most of these studies have been performed in West-<lb/>ern countries. To date, there has been no data regarding TDM <lb/>and its impact on clinical outcomes and medical costs in Korean <lb/>IBD patients with secondary LOR. And, measurements of drug <lb/>levels and ADA are not yet available in Korea. <lb/>In this issue of Gut and Liver, Choi et al. 9 investigated the <lb/></body>

			<front>This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution Non-Commercial License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0) <lb/>which permits unrestricted non-commercial use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Correspondence to: Chang Soo Eun <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Hanyang University Guri Hospital, 153 Gyeongchun-ro, Guri 11923, Korea <lb/>Tel: +82-31-560-2228, Fax: +82-31-555-2998, E-mail: cseun@hanyang.ac.kr <lb/>pISSN 1976-2283 eISSN 2005-1212 https://doi.org/10.5009/gnl16574 <lb/></front>

			<front>Is the Therapeutic Drug Monitoring of Anti-TNF Agents Necessary in Korean <lb/>Inflammatory Bowel Disease Patients? <lb/>Chang Soo Eun <lb/>Department of Internal Medicine, Hanyang University Guri Hospital, Guri, Korea <lb/>See &quot;Clinical Use of Measuring Trough Levels and Antibodies against Infliximab in Patients with Pediatric Inflammatory <lb/>Bowel Disease&quot; by So Yoon Choi, et al. on page 55, Vol. 11. No. 1, 2017 <lb/></front>

			<page>4</page> 

			<note place="headnote">Gut and Liver, Vol. 11, No. 1, January 2017 <lb/></note>

			<body>clinical usefulness of infliximab (IFX) TLs and ADA in 39 pe-<lb/>diatric IBD patients in a retrospective manner and proposed a <lb/>tailored therapeutic strategy for IFX therapy based on IFX TLs <lb/>and ADA status in patients with LOR. They compared serum <lb/>IFX TLs and ADA between 16 patients with clinical remission <lb/>and 23 patients with a poor response to IFX treatment and re-<lb/>measured the IFX TLs and ADA after IFX dose intensification <lb/>in 21 patients with LOR. The authors showed that the IFX TLs <lb/>were significantly higher in patients with clinical remission than <lb/>those with a poor response (median, 3.99 μg/mL vs 0.88 μg/mL; <lb/>p=0.002) and the ADA was detectable in only patients with LOR <lb/>(7/23, 30.4%). In addition, after IFX dose intensification in pa-<lb/>tients with LOR, the IFX TLs were increased in 17 patients with <lb/>improved response, while four patients with no response have <lb/>no detectable IFX but detectable ADA. This study, firstly evalu-<lb/>ated the efficacy of anti-TNF TLs and ADA in Korean IBD pa-<lb/>tients, provide a valuable clinical insight into the TDM of anti-<lb/>TNF agents for IBD patients with secondary LOR in Korea. <lb/>However, as the authors described, this study performed <lb/>retrospectively with a small sample size and did not evaluate <lb/>clinical outcomes and response to dose intensification of IFX in <lb/>the long-term. To validate the results of this study, especially <lb/>in adult patients, a prospective multicenter long-term clini-<lb/>cal trial with a larger sample size in Korean IBD patients with <lb/>anti-TNF treatments should be conducted. One of these would <lb/>undoubtedly be the OACIS study from KASID (Korean associa-<lb/>tion for the study of intestinal diseases), a prospective, open-<lb/>label, multicenter trial for the occurrence of ADA and change <lb/>of drug level after anti-TNF therapy and their impact on clinical <lb/>outcomes in moderate to severe IBD. <lb/></body>

			<back>
				<div type="annex">CONFLICTS OF INTEREST <lb/>No potential conflict of interest relevant to this article was <lb/>reported. <lb/></div>

				<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Lee HA, Suk JY, Choi SY, et al. Characteristics of pediatric inflam-<lb/>matory bowel disease in Korea: comparison with EUROKIDS data. <lb/>Gut Liver 2015;9:756-760. <lb/>2. Kim MJ, Lee WY, Choe YH. Expression of TIM-3, human beta-<lb/>defensin-2, and FOXP3 and correlation with disease activity <lb/>in pediatric Crohn&apos;s disease with infliximab therapy. Gut Liver <lb/>2015;9:370-380. <lb/>3. Ben-Horin S, Chowers Y. Tailoring anti-TNF therapy in IBD: <lb/>drug levels and disease activity. Nat Rev Gastroenterol Hepatol <lb/>2014;11:243-255. <lb/>4. Billioud V, Sandborn WJ, Peyrin-Biroulet L. Loss of response and <lb/>need for adalimumab dose intensification in Crohn&apos;s disease: a <lb/>systematic review. Am J Gastroenterol 2011;106:674-684. <lb/>5. Ben-Horin S, Kopylov U, Chowers Y. Optimizing anti-TNF treat-<lb/>ments in inflammatory bowel disease. Autoimmun Rev 2014;13: <lb/>24-30. <lb/> 6. Lee KM, Kim YS, Seo GS, Kim TO, Yang SK; IBD Study Group of <lb/>the Korean Association for the Study of Intestinal Diseases. Use of <lb/>thiopurines in inflammatory bowel disease: a consensus statement <lb/>by the Korean Association for the Study of Intestinal Diseases <lb/>(KASID). Intest Res 2015;13:193-207. <lb/>7. Felice C, Marzo M, Pugliese D, et al. Therapeutic drug monitoring <lb/>of anti-TNF-alpha agents in inflammatory bowel diseases. Expert <lb/>Opin Biol Ther 2015;15:1107-1117. <lb/>8. Khanna R, Sattin BD, Afif W, et al. Review article: a clinician&apos;s <lb/>guide for therapeutic drug monitoring of infliximab in inflamma-<lb/>tory bowel disease. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2013;38:447-459. <lb/>9. Choi SY, Kang B, Lee JH, Choe YH. Clinical use of measuring <lb/>trough levels and antibodies against infliximab in patients with <lb/>pediatric inflammatory bowel disease. Gut Liver 2017;11:55-61. </listBibl>

			</back>	

	</text>
</tei>
