<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Recent advances in the management of pruritus in chronic <lb/>liver diseases <lb/>Kazuto Tajiri, Yukihiro Shimizu <lb/>Kazuto Tajiri, Department of Gastroenterology, Toyama <lb/>University Hospital, Toyama 939-1724, Japan <lb/>Yukihiro Shimizu, Gastroenterology Center, Nanto Municipal <lb/>Hospital, Toyama 939-1724, Japan <lb/>Author contributions: Tajiri K and Shimizu Y wrote this paper, <lb/>Tajiri K conducted this work. <lb/>Conflict-of-interest statement: Tajiri K and Shimizu Y declare <lb/>no conflict of interests for this publication. <lb/>Open-Access: This article is an open-access article which was <lb/>selected by an in-house editor and fully peer-reviewed by external <lb/>reviewers. It is distributed in accordance with the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution Non Commercial (CC BY-NC 4.0) license, <lb/>which permits others to distribute, remix, adapt, build upon this <lb/>work non-commercially, and license their derivative works on <lb/>different terms, provided the original work is properly cited and <lb/>the use is non-commercial. See: http://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by-nc/4.0/ <lb/>Manuscript source: Invited manuscript <lb/>Correspondence to: Kazuto Tajiri, MD, PhD, Department of <lb/>Gastroenterology, Toyama University Hospital, 2630 Sugitani, <lb/>Toyama 939-1724, Japan. tajikazu@med.u-toyama.ac.jp <lb/>Telephone: +81-76-4347301 <lb/>Fax: +81-76-4345027 <lb/>Received: January 23, 2017 <lb/>Peer-review started: January 28, 2017 <lb/>First decision: March 3, 2017 <lb/>Revised: March 13, 2017 <lb/>Accepted: May 4, 2017 <lb/>Article in press: May 4, 2017 <lb/>Published online: May 21, 2017 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Pruritus is a symptom found in patients with chronic <lb/>liver diseases, especially cholestatic liver diseases such <lb/>as primary biliary cholangitis. This symptom impairs <lb/>patient quality of life by disturbing sleep and may lead <lb/>to consideration of liver transplantation. Mechanisms <lb/>implicated in pruritus have been associated with the <lb/>peripheral and central nervous systems, leading to <lb/>the development of various therapeutic options. Little <lb/>evidence for the efficacy of most of these treatments <lb/>is currently available, indicating a need for further <lb/>investigations. <lb/>Key words: Pruritus; Cholestasis; Autotaxin; Opioid <lb/>receptor antagonist <lb/>© The Author(s) 2017. Published by Baishideng Publishing <lb/>Group Inc. All rights reserved. <lb/>Core tip: Pruritus is a symptom influencing the quality <lb/>of life in patients with chronic liver diseases especially <lb/>with cholestatic liver diseases. Complex underlying <lb/>mechanisms have been identified and various <lb/>therapeutic options developed. More evidence is <lb/>needed for these treatments, as well as improvements <lb/>in their tolerability. <lb/>Tajiri K, Shimizu Y. Recent advances in the management of <lb/>pruritus in chronic liver diseases. World J Gastroenterol 2017; <lb/>23(19): 3418-3426 Available from: URL: http://www.wjgnet. <lb/>com/1007-9327/full/v23/i19/3418.htm DOI: http://dx.doi. <lb/>org/10.3748/wjg.v23.i19.3418 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Pruritus is one of the symptoms encountered in pa­ <lb/>tients with chronic liver diseases, especially in those <lb/>with cholestatic liver diseases such as primary biliary <lb/>cholangitis (PBC) and primary sclerosing cholangitis <lb/>(PSC) <lb/>[1­3] . Pruritus in patients with cholestasis is <lb/>characterized by a circadian rhythm, with the highest <lb/>intensity during the evening and early at night <lb/>[4] <lb/>. Chronic <lb/></body>

			<front>REVIEW <lb/> 3418 <lb/> May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/>Submit a Manuscript: http://www.f6publishing.com <lb/>DOI: 10.3748/wjg.v23.i19.3418 <lb/>World J Gastroenterol 2017 May 21; 23(19): 3418-3426 <lb/>ISSN 1007-9327 (print) ISSN 2219-2840 (online) <lb/></front>

			<body>pruritus generally tends to increase with warmth and <lb/>at night <lb/>[4,5] <lb/>. Women with cholestasis frequently show <lb/>worsening of pruritus during the progesterone phase <lb/>of the menstrual cycle, in late pregnancy, and during <lb/>hormone replacement treatment <lb/>[4­6] <lb/>. Although pruritus <lb/>may not be directly associated with the prognosis or <lb/>outcome of liver diseases, a recent systematic review <lb/>showed that pruritus has an impact on health­related <lb/>quality of life in patients with cholestatic liver diseases <lb/>[7] <lb/>. <lb/>Pruritus may be an indication for liver transplantation <lb/>even in the absence of liver failure <lb/>[8,9] <lb/>. Recently, several <lb/>mechanisms underlying pruritus, as well as treatment <lb/>advances have been identified. This review describes <lb/>recent advances in the management of pruritus in <lb/>chronic liver diseases. <lb/>MECHANISMS OF PRURITUS IN LIVER <lb/>DISEASES <lb/>Several lines of evidence have suggested mechanisms <lb/>by which pruritus is induced in cholestatic conditions. <lb/>First, accumulated bile salts are thought to act as <lb/>pruritogens <lb/>[10] . Bile salts have been reported to <lb/>induce degranulation of mast cells in vitro, which <lb/>may contribute to pruritus in cholestatic patients. <lb/>However the relationship between bile salts and <lb/>pruritus has not been clarified <lb/>[11] , although some <lb/>metabolites of bile salts may contribute to pruritus <lb/>[12] <lb/>. <lb/>Second, endogenous opioid levels have been reported <lb/>increased in cholestatic patients <lb/>[12,13] <lb/>. Activation of <lb/>μ­opioid receptors may cause pruritus by reducing <lb/>pain signaling, with μ­opioid receptor antagonists <lb/>showing antipruritic effects in patients with chronic <lb/>cholestasis <lb/>[14,15] . However the correlation between <lb/>those increased opioid levels and pruritus remains <lb/>unclear <lb/>[12,13] <lb/>. Thus, these mechanisms could not fully <lb/>explain the pathogenesis of pruritus. Furthermore, <lb/>conditions that may cause skin itching are often found <lb/>in cirrhotic patients. These include hyperhemodynamic <lb/>conditions and skin dryness caused by administration <lb/>of diuretics for hepatic edema <lb/>[16] <lb/>, complicating the <lb/>mechanism by which pruritus is induced in cirrhotic <lb/>patients. <lb/>MECHANISM OF PRURITUS IN THE <lb/>PERIPHERY <lb/>Research in recent decades has clarified mechanisms <lb/>of pruritus induction in the periphery (Figure 1). The <lb/>first involves an itch­selective pathway, consisting of <lb/>slow­conducting C­fibers insensitive to mechanical <lb/>stimuli, which convey itch signals that are distinct from <lb/>pain transmission <lb/>[17,18] <lb/>. Mechanical stimuli such as pain <lb/>and touch are transmitted through myelinated fast­ <lb/>conducting fibers with larger diameter and competitively <lb/>inhibit itch­transmission <lb/>[19­21] <lb/>, thus explaining reason <lb/>why itching is diminished by scratching <lb/>[22] <lb/>. Scratching <lb/>damages the skin barrier, inducing the release of <lb/>substance P or calcitonin gene­related peptide, thereby <lb/>increasing pruritus <lb/>[23] <lb/>. <lb/>Several pruritogens and their receptors specific <lb/>to itch signaling have been identified. Histamine and <lb/>the histamine H1 and H4 receptors are considered <lb/>the main contributors to itch signaling <lb/>[24] . The H1 <lb/>receptor interacts with phospholipase Cβ3 (PLCβ3) <lb/>[25] <lb/>and transient receptor potential (TRP) vanilloid <lb/>receptor subfamily V1 (TRPV1), which constitute <lb/>a nociceptive ion channel <lb/>[26] . Protease­activated <lb/>receptors (PAR) 2 and 4 are thought to be involved <lb/>in itch signaling <lb/>[27] <lb/>, and PAR2 activation may sensitize <lb/>TRPV1, thereby contributing to itch <lb/>[28,29] <lb/>. Serotonin <lb/>is another pruritogen, which, together with PLCβ3, <lb/>acts on G­protein­coupled receptors (GPCR) <lb/>[26] , <lb/>such as NK­1, a GPCR shown to play a critical role <lb/>in serotonin­mediated itch <lb/>[30] <lb/>. The Mrg subtype A3 <lb/>(MrgA3), a type of GPCR, is also involved in itch <lb/>signaling <lb/>[31,32] by interacting with TRPV1 <lb/>[32] <lb/>. Thus, the <lb/>mechanisms underlying itch signaling is complicated. <lb/>Other pruritogens may indirectly trigger itch signaling. <lb/>For example, mast cells are associated with itch not <lb/>only by releasing histamine but other pruritogens <lb/>[33] <lb/>. <lb/>Cytokines produced by immune cells are also involved <lb/>in itch <lb/>[22] <lb/>. Keratinocytes (KCs) may also be associated <lb/>with itching. These cells express the potential itch­ <lb/>associated molecules TRPV3 and 4 <lb/>[34] <lb/>, with TRPV3 <lb/>expression associated with allergic dermatitis <lb/>[35] <lb/>. Skin <lb/>inflammation suggests the involvement of immune <lb/>cells <lb/>[22] <lb/>. <lb/>Gastrin­releasing peptide (GRP) may act as an <lb/>itch transmitter <lb/>[36] <lb/>. GRP is an itch­selective neuro­ <lb/>transmitter of dorsal root ganglia (DRG) neurons that <lb/>activates the GRP receptor (GRPR) on spinal neurons <lb/>specific to itch not but to pain <lb/>[37] <lb/>. The vesicular glu­ <lb/>tamate transporter (VGLUT) 2 was also shown to be <lb/>involved in itch­selective neurotransmission <lb/>[38,39] <lb/>. <lb/>Lysophosphatidic acid (LPA) has been regarded <lb/>as a specific target pruritogen/neurotransmitter in <lb/>patients with cholestasis <lb/>[11,12] <lb/>. LPA is generated from <lb/>lysophosphatidylcholine (LPC) by autotaxin (ATX) <lb/>[40,41] <lb/>. <lb/>LPA and ATX were shown to be increased in cholestatic <lb/>patients, suggesting they may be potential therapeutic <lb/>targets <lb/>[11,12,42] <lb/>. Serum ATX level was also shown to be <lb/>increased by the administration of oral contraceptives <lb/>to healthy females, and was a potential good indicator <lb/>of intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy (ICP) <lb/>[43] . <lb/>The metabolism of sex hormones is impaired in <lb/>cirrhotic livers, accompanied by overt feminization <lb/>[44] <lb/>, <lb/>thereby partly explaining the mechanism of ATX­ <lb/>induced pruritus in cirrhotic patients. In addition, the <lb/>G­protein­coupled bile acid receptor 1, TGR5, encoded <lb/>by GPBAR1 and expressed on sensory nerves, <lb/>was recently shown to be involved in pruritus by <lb/>stimulating the release of neuropeptides in the spinal <lb/>cord <lb/>[45] <lb/>. TGR5 was also found to activate the transient <lb/>receptor potential ankyrin 1 (TRPA1) and to induce <lb/>pruritus <lb/>[46] <lb/>. Thus many pruritogens, especially those <lb/>specific to cholestatic conditions, have been identified. <lb/></body>

			<page>3419 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<body>MECHANISM OF PRURITUS IN THE <lb/>CENTRAL NERVOUS SYSTEM <lb/>Pruritus also involves the central nervous system (CNS). <lb/>For example, the most common adverse event of the <lb/>μ­opioid receptor agonist morphine is pruritus <lb/>[47,48] <lb/>. <lb/>The μ­opioid receptor antagonist naloxone, however, <lb/>inhibits morphine­induced pruritus <lb/>[49] <lb/>, and suppresses <lb/>pruritus in patients with chronic cholestasis <lb/>[50] <lb/>. Plasma <lb/>concentrations of the μ­opioid receptor agonists <lb/>methionine enkephalin and β­endorphin were shown <lb/>to be increased in patients with cirrhosis, as ascites <lb/>increased due to decreased hepatic elimination <lb/>[51,52] <lb/>. <lb/>The liver plays a major role in the elimination of blood­ <lb/>derived opioid peptides <lb/>[53] <lb/>. These findings suggest <lb/>that the μ­opioid receptor system is involved in <lb/>pruritus sensations in patients with liver diseases <lb/>[54] <lb/>. <lb/>In contrast, the κ­opioid receptor was shown to <lb/>suppress pruritus. The κ­receptor agonist, nalfurafine <lb/>(TRK­820) [(E)­N­[17­(cyclopropylmethyl)­4,5α­ <lb/>epoxy­3,14­ dihydroxymorphinan­6β−yl]-3-(furan-3-<lb/>yl)­N­methylpop­2­enamide monohydrochloride], was <lb/>shown to suppress anti­histamine­resistant pruritus in a <lb/>mouse model <lb/>[54] <lb/>, whereas pruritus was not neutralized <lb/>by the peripheral administration of the κ­opioid receptor <lb/>antagonist nor­binaltorphimine <lb/>[54] <lb/>. Nalfurafine was also <lb/>found to suppress pruritus induced by the intracisternal <lb/>administration of morphine <lb/>[55] <lb/>. Similar results were <lb/>observed in a rat model of cholestasis induced by <lb/>treatment with ethynylestradiol (EE), in which the levels <lb/>of expression of the κ­receptor agonist dynorphin and <lb/>nitric oxide (NO) were decreased <lb/>[56] <lb/>. Nalfurafine showed <lb/>anti­pruritic activity in this model, an activity partly <lb/>mediated by NO systems <lb/>[56] <lb/>. These model indicates <lb/>that NO is involved in mediating the antipruritic effect of <lb/>κ­receptor action <lb/>[56] <lb/>. <lb/>NO expression is enhanced in patients with cirrhosis <lb/>and primary biliary cholangitis, with NO being a main <lb/>contributor to hyperdynamic circulation in patients with <lb/>cirrhosis <lb/>[16,57] <lb/>. NO was shown to enhance substance <lb/>P­induced scratching in the periphery, whereas a NO <lb/>synthase inhibitor suppressed this scratching in a dose <lb/>dependent manner <lb/>[58] <lb/>. NO induces vasodilatation <lb/>[59] <lb/>, <lb/>suggesting it increases peripheral blood flow. Thus the <lb/>contribution of NO to pruritus remains still controversial <lb/>and requires further investigation. Furthermore β and <lb/>κ receptors have been shown to be distributed also in <lb/>peripheral nerves and contribute to the development <lb/>of pruritus <lb/>[60,61] . Thus their mechanisms of action <lb/>are complicated between the periphery and CNS, <lb/></body>

			<page>3420 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<body>Periphery <lb/>Blood flow <lb/>increase <lb/>Substance P <lb/>Mast cell <lb/>Bile acid <lb/>Histamine <lb/>LPC <lb/>LPA <lb/>ATX <lb/>Cytokines <lb/>Immune cell <lb/>Mechanical stimuli <lb/>receptor <lb/>Scratching <lb/>C-fiber <lb/>GRP <lb/>Thalamus <lb/>A-fiber <lb/>Spinal <lb/>cord <lb/>Cerebral <lb/>cortex <lb/>Pain <lb/>Touch <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>GRPR <lb/>DRG <lb/>Itch receptor <lb/>TRPV1 <lb/>VGLUT2 <lb/>H1, H4 <lb/>TRPV1 <lb/>PAR2, 4 <lb/>MrgA3 <lb/>TGR5 <lb/>Central nervous system <lb/>NO <lb/>μ receptor <lb/>κ receptor <lb/>Enkephalin <lb/>β-endorphin <lb/>Dynorphin <lb/>Figure 1 Mechanism of itch transmission in cholestatic conditions. Pruritogens such as histamine, bile acids, bile acid metabolites, LPA and cytokines act on itch <lb/>receptors. Itch signals are transmitted through C-fibers to the cerebral cortex. The μ and κ opioid receptors are expressed in both the central nervous system and the <lb/>periphery nerve and act to promote and suppress pruritus, respectively. Signals generated by mechanical stimuli compete with itch signals. Scratching induces C-fibers <lb/>to secrete substance P, and acts as a pruritogen. NO: Nitric oxide; LPC: Lysophosphatidylcholine; ATX: Autotaxin; LPA: Lysophosphatidic acid; GRP: Gastrin-releasing <lb/>peptide; GRPR: Gastrin-releasing peptide receptor; TRPV1: Transient receptor potential vanilloid receptor subfamily V1; PAR: Protease-activated receptors; MrgA3: <lb/>Mrg subtype A3; TGR5: G-protein-coupled bile acid receptor 1; VGLUT2: Vesicular glutamate transporter 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3421 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<body>BRIC is characterized by intermittent jaundice and <lb/>pruritus, and the clinical symptoms may be severe, <lb/>last from several weeks to months and usually resolve <lb/>spontaneously <lb/>[75,76] <lb/>. <lb/>Benign obstructive jaundice has been associated with <lb/>a lower rate of pruritus than malignant obstruction. For <lb/>example, pruritus was observed in 16% of patients with <lb/>benign biliary obstruction such as choledocholithiasis, <lb/>but in up to 45% of patients with malignant obstruction <lb/>such as carcinoma of the pancreatic head <lb/>[77] <lb/>. <lb/>TREATMENT OF PRURITUS <lb/>The guidelines of the American Association for the <lb/>Study of Liver Diseases (AASLD) and the European <lb/>Association for the Study of the Liver (EASL) include <lb/>criteria for the management of cholestatic pruritus in <lb/>patients with PBC and PSC <lb/>[78,79] <lb/>. Recommendations to <lb/>all patients should include the use of moisturizing and <lb/>cooling ointments and shortening of the fingernails to <lb/>avoid secondary skin damage. The principal goals of <lb/>treatment include <lb/>[5] <lb/>: (1) removal of pruritogens such <lb/>as cholestyramine or biliary drainage in the absence <lb/>of cholestasis; (2) alteration of the metabolism <lb/>of presumed pruritogens such as rifampicin; (3) <lb/>modulation of itch signaling such as opioid receptor <lb/>acting agents; and (4) removal of potential pruritogens <lb/>by anion absorption, plasmapheresis or extracorporeal <lb/>albumin dialysis (Figure 2). <lb/>Ursodeoxycholic acid (UDCA) is an established <lb/>drug for the management of PBC and PSC <lb/>[80,81] . <lb/>Although associated with biological and histological <lb/>improvements and improving overall survival <lb/>[80,81] <lb/>, <lb/>UDCA was ineffective in relieving cholestatic pruritus in <lb/>both PBC and PSC <lb/>[66,82] <lb/>. In patients with ICP, however, <lb/>UDCA not only improved biological parameters such as <lb/>aspartate aminotransferase and alkaline phosphatase <lb/>concentrations, but ameliorated pruritus <lb/>[74,83] <lb/>. UDCA <lb/>is used for BRIC to stimulate hepatobiliary secretion <lb/>of bile salts. Antiapoptotic effects of UDCA are also <lb/>expected to protect hepatocytes in the treatment for <lb/>BRIC <lb/>[75] <lb/>. <lb/>Cholestyramine, a bile acid resin, has been re­ <lb/>commended as the treatment of choice for patients <lb/>with cholestatic pruritus, as it was shown effective in <lb/>randomized studies with small numbers of patients <lb/>(eight and 10, respectively) <lb/>[84,85] <lb/>. Although generally <lb/>well­tolerated, cholestyramine has several side <lb/>effects, including unpleasant taste, fat malabsorption, <lb/>constipation, anorexia and gastrointestinal discomfort <lb/>[86] <lb/>. <lb/>A meta­analysis of five prospective randomized <lb/>control trials showed that rifampicin, a pregnane <lb/>X receptor (PXR) agonist commonly used to treat <lb/>mycobacterial infection, was effective in treating <lb/>chronic pruritus <lb/>[87] . Rifampicin was shown to re­ <lb/>duce ATX expression in vitro by a PXR­dependent <lb/>mechanism <lb/>[42] <lb/>. Although safe as short­term treatment <lb/>of chronic pruritus, rifampicin was associated with <lb/>hepatotoxicity in up to 13% of patients after treatment <lb/>especially in patients with chronic liver diseases, <lb/>making understanding of the pathogenesis of pruritus <lb/>in these patients difficult and making them refractory <lb/>to treatment. <lb/>PREVALENCE AND BURDEN OF <lb/>PRURITUS IN LIVER DISEASES <lb/>Chronic cholestatic diseases <lb/>Primary biliary cholangitis (PBC), formerly called <lb/>primary biliary cirrhosis, is a representative chronic <lb/>cholestatic liver disease manifesting pruritus. Pruritus <lb/>is found in about 70% of patients with PBC <lb/>[2,62] and <lb/>precedes the diagnosis of PBC in about 75% <lb/>[62] . <lb/>Pruritus has been shown to impair quality of life, such <lb/>as sleep, in patients with PBC <lb/>[62,63] <lb/>. <lb/>Primary sclerosing cholangitis (PSC) is also asso­ <lb/>ciated with pruritus during the course of disease <lb/>progression. In contrast to PBC, most patients with PSC <lb/>are asymptomatic at the time of diagnosis; therefore <lb/>the exact prevalence of pruritus in patients with PSC <lb/>remains unclear <lb/>[64] <lb/>. <lb/>Pruritus in patients with PBC and PSC manifests <lb/>frequently in the limbs, particularly in the palms and <lb/>soles <lb/>[1,65] <lb/>. Multivariate analysis showed that serum <lb/>alkaline phosphatase activity and Mayo risk score were <lb/>independent predictors of pruritus in patients with <lb/>PBC <lb/>[66] <lb/>. Severe pruritus limits daily life activities and <lb/>causes fatigue, depression and even suicidal tendencies, <lb/>becoming an indication for liver transplantation in some <lb/>patients <lb/>[8,67,68] <lb/>. <lb/>Chronic hepatitis and cirrhosis <lb/>Pruritus was observed in four of 49 (8%) patients with <lb/>chronic hepatitis B and 42 of 210 (20%) with chronic <lb/>hepatitis C <lb/>[69] . Studies of large cohorts found that <lb/>the proportion of HCV­infected patients with pruritus <lb/>ranged from 2.5% of 1060 patients <lb/>[70] to 15% of 1614 <lb/>patients <lb/>[71] <lb/>. Pruritus in these patients was not caused <lb/>by cholestasis <lb/>[70] <lb/>, whereas liver fibrosis progression <lb/>was a risk factor contributing to pruritus <lb/>[71] <lb/>. <lb/>Other cholestatic conditions <lb/>Pruritus is a defining symptom of intrahepatic cho­ <lb/>lestasis of pregnancy (ICP), a condition characterized <lb/>by increases in serum bile acid concentrations and <lb/>increased rates of adverse fetal outcomes <lb/>[72] <lb/>. Pruritus <lb/>in ICP is usually localized to the palms and soles <lb/>[73] <lb/>. <lb/>The incidence of ICP was reported to be 1.5%, with <lb/>increased fetal complications occurring at serum bile <lb/>acid concentrations &gt; 40 <lb/>[74] <lb/>. <lb/>Familial intrahepatic cholestasis, such as benign <lb/>recurrent intrahepatic cholestasis (BRIC), is an <lb/>autosomal recessive disorder associated with cana­ <lb/>licular transport defects resulting from mutations <lb/>in ATP8B1, ABCB11 and ABCB4. The phenotype is <lb/>ranging from BRIC to progressive familial intrahepatic <lb/>cholestasis according to the severity of disease <lb/>[75] <lb/>. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3422 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<body>for several weeks or months <lb/>[88] . Adverse effects <lb/>that may lead to discontinuation of therapy include <lb/>nausea, loss of appetite, hemolytic anemia, renal <lb/>failure and thrombocytopenia <lb/>[87,89] <lb/>. Careful monitoring <lb/>of blood count and liver function tests is required <lb/>during administration of rifampicin for cholestatic <lb/>pruritus, and administration for more than 2 wk is not <lb/>recommended <lb/>[90] <lb/>. <lb/>Prospective placebo­controlled showed that the <lb/>μ­opioid receptor antagonist naltrexone was effective <lb/>in treating cholestatic pruritus <lb/>[91­94] . Common side <lb/>effects of opioid antagonists include opiate withdrawal <lb/>reactions, particularly during the first days of therapy. <lb/>Contraindications to naltrexone include acute liver <lb/>injury and severe liver insufficiency. Opioid antagonists <lb/>should be avoided in patients with drug addictions <lb/>and those taking opioid containing medications <lb/>[95] <lb/>. <lb/>In Japan, nalfurafine, a κ­opioid receptor agonist, is <lb/>available for the treatment of pruritus in chronic liver <lb/>diseases (2.5­5 μg/d). Nalfurafine is metabolized <lb/>predominantly by cytochrome P450 <lb/>[96] <lb/>, but its main <lb/>metabolite has no pharmacological activity, suggesting <lb/>its availability and effectiveness for treatment of <lb/>patients with advanced liver diseases <lb/>[97] <lb/>. Recently a <lb/>randomized controlled trial showed the effectiveness of <lb/>nalfurafine by small dose (2.5 or 5 μg/d) for refractory <lb/>pruritus with chronic liver diseases <lb/>[98] <lb/>. <lb/>Sertraline, a selective serotonin re­uptake inhibitor <lb/>(SSRI), is a fourth­line therapeutic option for patients <lb/>with cholestatic pruritus. Sertraline (75­100 mg/d) <lb/>was well­tolerated and showed moderate anti­pruritic <lb/>effects in a randomized trial with a small number of <lb/>patients <lb/>[99] <lb/>. Because sertraline is largely metabolized <lb/>in the liver, careful administration (e.g., lower or less <lb/>frequent dosing) should be considered in patients <lb/>with advanced liver diseases. Sertraline should not be <lb/>administered to patients who treated with monoamine <lb/>oxidase inhibitors for the previous 14 d or those <lb/>concurrently taking pimozide, and oral sertraline <lb/>concentrate should not be administered together with <lb/>disulfiram <lb/>[90] <lb/>. <lb/>The AASLD and EASL guidelines both recommend <lb/>that patients who show no improvement on these <lb/>standard therapies be treated by experimental <lb/>approaches. Case studies have described methods <lb/>such as plasmapheresis <lb/>[100,101] <lb/>, albumin dialysis using a <lb/>molecular absorbent recirculating system (MARS) <lb/>[102­104] <lb/>, <lb/>plasma separation and anion absorption <lb/>[105] <lb/>, ultraviolet <lb/>B phototherapy <lb/>[106] , nasobiliary drainage <lb/>[107] and <lb/>surgical intervention such as partial biliary diversion <lb/>[75] <lb/>. <lb/>Little evidence is available for the effectiveness of <lb/>these approaches, suggesting a need for validation <lb/>prior to standard use. Furthermore therapeutic options <lb/>recommended by guidelines lack strong evidence, <lb/>except for rifampicin as second line­treatment. How­ <lb/>ever, rifampicin cannot be administered for longer <lb/>than 2 wk. Because pruritus is found in patients with <lb/>chronic liver diseases, especially cirrhosis, therapeutic <lb/>modalities tolerable for longer times are needed. <lb/>A large­scale (n = 337), placebo­controlled study <lb/>showed that nalfurafine was effective and safe in <lb/>hemodialysis patients with uremic pruritus resistant <lb/>to conventional treatments <lb/>[108] and that this treatment <lb/>was tolerable for 52 wk <lb/>[109] <lb/>. Its effectiveness in treating <lb/>pruritus in patients with chronic liver diseases was also <lb/>shown by a randomized controlled study (n = 318) <lb/>[98] <lb/>. <lb/>Its tolerability is under investigation. The effectiveness <lb/>and tolerability in non­Japanese or non­Asian people <lb/>are desired. <lb/>Recent studies have assessed the association of <lb/>nuclear receptors with the homeostasis of bile acids, <lb/>with farnesoid X receptor (FXR) shown to regulate bile <lb/>acid synthesis <lb/>[110,111] <lb/>. Obeticolic acid, a FXR agonist, <lb/>showed significant improvements in biochemical <lb/>parameters, but increased pruritus rates <lb/>[112] . The <lb/>incidence and severity of pruritus were reported to <lb/>be independent of PBC disease stage <lb/>[113,114] <lb/>, and the <lb/>mechanism of FXR­induced pruritus remains unknown. <lb/>The effect of FXR agonist on ATX level should be <lb/>evaluated. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>The mechanism of cholestatic pruritus in chronic liver <lb/>diseases is complex. The various mechanisms at the <lb/>periphery and in the central nervous system result <lb/>complicate determinations of its pathogenesis and <lb/>treatment strategies. Pruritus occurs frequently in <lb/>patients with chronic liver diseases, especially those <lb/>with chronic cholestatic diseases, and impairs patient <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Bile duct obstruction <lb/>Present <lb/>Absent <lb/>Evidence level <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>st line <lb/>2 <lb/>nd line <lb/>3 <lb/>rd line <lb/>4 <lb/>th line <lb/>5 <lb/>th line <lb/>Biliary drainage <lb/>Cholestyramine (4-16 g/d) <lb/>Rifampicin (150-300 mg) <lb/>Naltrexone (50 mg) <lb/>Sertraline (75-100 mg) <lb/>Experimental approach <lb/>II-2/B <lb/>I/A <lb/>I/B <lb/>II-2/C <lb/>-<lb/>Figure 2 Therapeutic recommendations for the management of <lb/>cholestatic pruritus modified from American Association for the Study of <lb/>Liver Diseases guidelines. 1 Evidence level involves categories of evidence <lb/>and evidence grading. Categories of evidence include: I, randomized controlled <lb/>trials; II-1 controlled trials without randomization; II-2, cohort and case-control <lb/>analytic studies; II-3, multiple time series, dramatic uncontrolled experiments; <lb/>and III, opinions of respected authorities, descriptive epidemiology. Evidence <lb/>grading includes A: High quality, indicating that further research is unlikely to <lb/>change confidence in the estimate of effect; B: Moderate quality, indicating that <lb/>further research may have an important impact on confidence in the estimate <lb/>of effect and may change that estimate; and C: Low quality, indicating that <lb/>further research is very likely to have an important impact on confidence in <lb/>the estimation of effect and is likely to change that estimate. Any change of <lb/>estimate is uncertain. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3423 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<body>quality of life. Current treatments for cholestatic <lb/>pruritus are inadequate, and additional, more effective <lb/>therapeutic options are required. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 <lb/>Bergasa NV, Mehlman JK, Jones EA. Pruritus and fatigue <lb/>in primary biliary cirrhosis. Baillieres Best Pract Res Clin <lb/>Gastroenterol 2000; 14: 643-655 [PMID: 10976020 DOI: 10.1053/ <lb/>bega.2000.0109] <lb/>2 <lb/>Koulentaki M, Ioannidou D, Stefanidou M, Maraki S, <lb/>Drigiannakis I, Dimoulios P, Melono JM, Tosca A, Kouroumalis <lb/>EA. Dermatological manifestations in primary biliary cirrhosis <lb/>patients: a case control study. Am J Gastroenterol 2006; 101: <lb/>541-546 [PMID: 16464228 DOI: 10.1111/j.1572-0241.2006.00423.x] <lb/>3 <lb/>Younossi ZM, Kiwi ML, Boparai N, Price LL, Guyatt G. <lb/>Cholestatic liver diseases and health-related quality of life. Am J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2000; 95: 497-502 [PMID: 10685757 DOI: 10.1111/ <lb/>j.1572-0241.2000.01774.x] <lb/>4 <lb/>Kremer AE, Beuers U, Oude-Elferink RP, Pusl T. Pathogenesis <lb/>and treatment of pruritus in cholestasis. Drugs 2008; 68: 2163-2182 <lb/>[PMID: 18840005] <lb/>5 <lb/>Kremer AE, Namer B, Bolier R, Fischer MJ, Oude Elferink RP, <lb/>Beuers U. Pathogenesis and Management of Pruritus in PBC and <lb/>PSC. Dig Dis 2015; 33 Suppl 2: 164-175 [PMID: 26641452 DOI: <lb/>10.1159/000440829] <lb/>6 <lb/>Bergasa NV. The pruritus of cholestasis. J Hepatol 2005; 43: <lb/>1078-1088 [PMID: 16253381 DOI: 10.1016/j.jhep.2005.09.004] <lb/>7 <lb/>Jin XY, Khan TM. Quality of life among patients suffering from <lb/>cholestatic liver disease-induced pruritus: A systematic review. J <lb/>Formos Med Assoc 2016; 115: 689-702 [PMID: 27431691 DOI: <lb/>10.1016/j.jfma.2016.05.006] <lb/>8 <lb/>Elias E, Burra P. Primary biliary cirrhosis: symptomatic treatment. <lb/>J Gastroenterol Hepatol 1991; 6: 570-573 [PMID: 1782372] <lb/>9 <lb/>Elias E. Liver transplantation. J R Coll Physicians Lond 1993; 27: <lb/>224-232 [PMID: 8377153] <lb/>10 Quist RG, Ton-Nu HT, Lillienau J, Hofmann AF, Barrett KE. <lb/>Activation of mast cells by bile acids. Gastroenterology 1991; 101: <lb/>446-456 [PMID: 1712330] <lb/>11 Kremer AE, Martens JJ, Kulik W, Ruëff F, Kuiper EM, van <lb/>Buuren HR, van Erpecum KJ, Kondrackiene J, Prieto J, Rust <lb/>C, Geenes VL, Williamson C, Moolenaar WH, Beuers U, Oude <lb/>Elferink RP. Lysophosphatidic acid is a potential mediator of <lb/>cholestatic pruritus. Gastroenterology 2010; 139: 1008-1018, 1018. <lb/>e1 [PMID: 20546739 DOI: 10.1053/j.gastro.2010.05.009] <lb/>12 Oude Elferink RP, Kremer AE, Martens JJ, Beuers UH. The <lb/>molecular mechanism of cholestatic pruritus. Dig Dis 2011; 29: <lb/>66-71 [PMID: 21691108 DOI: 10.1159/000324131] <lb/>13 Spivey JR, Jorgensen RA, Gores GJ, Lindor KD. Methionine-<lb/>enkephalin concentrations correlate with stage of disease but <lb/>not pruritus in patients with primary biliary cirrhosis. Am J <lb/>Gastroenterol 1994; 89: 2028-2032 [PMID: 7942730] <lb/>14 Bergasa NV, Schmitt JM, Talbot TL, Alling DW, Swain MG, <lb/>Turner ML, Jenkins JB, Jones EA. Open-label trial of oral <lb/>nalmefene therapy for the pruritus of cholestasis. Hepatology 1998; <lb/>27: 679-684 [PMID: 9500694 DOI: 10.1002/hep.510270307] <lb/>15 Bergasa NV, Alling DW, Talbot TL, Wells MC, Jones EA. Oral <lb/>nalmefene therapy reduces scratching activity due to the pruritus <lb/>of cholestasis: a controlled study. J Am Acad Dermatol 1999; 41: <lb/>431-434 [PMID: 10459118] <lb/>16 Vallance P, Moncada S. Hyperdynamic circulation in cirrhosis: a <lb/>role for nitric oxide? Lancet 1991; 337: 776-778 [PMID: 1706450] <lb/>17 Andrew D, Craig AD. Spinothalamic lamina I neurons selectively <lb/>sensitive to histamine: a central neural pathway for itch. Nat <lb/>Neurosci 2001; 4: 72-77 [PMID: 11135647 DOI: 10.1038/82924] <lb/>18 Schmelz M. A neural pathway for itch. Nat Neurosci 2001; 4: 9-10 <lb/>[PMID: 11135635 DOI: 10.1038/82956] <lb/>19 Patel KN, Dong X. An itch to be scratched. Neuron 2010; 68: <lb/> 334-339 [PMID: 21040839 DOI: 10.1016/j.neuron.2010.10.018] <lb/>20 Braz J, Solorzano C, Wang X, Basbaum AI. Transmitting pain and <lb/>itch messages: a contemporary view of the spinal cord circuits that <lb/>generate gate control. Neuron 2014; 82: 522-536 [PMID: 24811377 <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/j.neuron.2014.01.018] <lb/>21 LaMotte RH, Dong X, Ringkamp M. Sensory neurons and <lb/>circuits mediating itch. Nat Rev Neurosci 2014; 15: 19-31 [PMID: <lb/>24356071 DOI: 10.1038/nrn3641] <lb/>22 Ikoma A, Steinhoff M, Ständer S, Yosipovitch G, Schmelz M. The <lb/>neurobiology of itch. Nat Rev Neurosci 2006; 7: 535-547 [PMID: <lb/>16791143 DOI: 10.1038/nrn1950] <lb/>23 Yamaoka J, Di ZH, Sun W, Kawana S. Changes in cutaneous <lb/>sensory nerve fibers induced by skin-scratching in mice. J <lb/>Dermatol Sci 2007; 46: 41-51 [PMID: 17239567 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jdermsci.2006.12.007] <lb/>24 Bell JK, McQueen DS, Rees JL. Involvement of histamine H4 and <lb/>H1 receptors in scratching induced by histamine receptor agonists <lb/>in Balb C mice. Br J Pharmacol 2004; 142: 374-380 [PMID: <lb/>15066908 DOI: 10.1038/sj.bjp.0705754] <lb/>25 Han SK, Mancino V, Simon MI. Phospholipase Cbeta 3 mediates <lb/>the scratching response activated by the histamine H1 receptor on <lb/>C-fiber nociceptive neurons. Neuron 2006; 52: 691-703 [PMID: <lb/>17114052 DOI: 10.1016/j.neuron.2006.09.036] <lb/>26 Imamachi N, Park GH, Lee H, Anderson DJ, Simon MI, Basbaum <lb/>AI, Han SK. TRPV1-expressing primary afferents generate <lb/>behavioral responses to pruritogens via multiple mechanisms. Proc <lb/>Natl Acad Sci USA 2009; 106: 11330-11335 [PMID: 19564617 <lb/>DOI: 10.1073/pnas.0905605106] <lb/>27 Reddy VB, Iuga AO, Shimada SG, LaMotte RH, Lerner EA. <lb/>Cowhage-evoked itch is mediated by a novel cysteine protease: a <lb/>ligand of protease-activated receptors. J Neurosci 2008; 28: 4331-4335 <lb/>[PMID: 18434511 DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0716-08.2008] <lb/>28 Dai Y, Moriyama T, Higashi T, Togashi K, Kobayashi K, <lb/>Yamanaka H, Tominaga M, Noguchi K. Proteinase-activated <lb/>receptor 2-mediated potentiation of transient receptor potential <lb/>vanilloid subfamily 1 activity reveals a mechanism for proteinase-<lb/>induced inflammatory pain. J Neurosci 2004; 24: 4293-4299 <lb/>[PMID: 15128843 DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.0454-04.2004] <lb/>29 Amadesi S, Nie J, Vergnolle N, Cottrell GS, Grady EF, Trevisani M, <lb/>Manni C, Geppetti P, McRoberts JA, Ennes H, Davis JB, Mayer <lb/>EA, Bunnett NW. Protease-activated receptor 2 sensitizes the <lb/>capsaicin receptor transient receptor potential vanilloid receptor 1 <lb/>to induce hyperalgesia. J Neurosci 2004; 24: 4300-4312 [PMID: <lb/>15128844 DOI: 10.1523/JNEUROSCI.5679-03.2004] <lb/>30 Carstens EE, Carstens MI, Simons CT, Jinks SL. Dorsal horn <lb/>neurons expressing NK-1 receptors mediate scratching in rats. <lb/>Neuroreport 2010; 21: 303-308 [PMID: 20125052 DOI: 10.1097/ <lb/>WNR.0b013e328337310a] <lb/>31 Liu Q, Tang Z, Surdenikova L, Kim S, Patel KN, Kim A, Ru F, <lb/>Guan Y, Weng HJ, Geng Y, Undem BJ, Kollarik M, Chen ZF, <lb/>Anderson DJ, Dong X. Sensory neuron-specific GPCR Mrgprs <lb/>are itch receptors mediating chloroquine-induced pruritus. <lb/>Cell 2009; 139: 1353-1365 [PMID: 20004959 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.cell.2009.11.034] <lb/>32 Han L, Ma C, Liu Q, Weng HJ, Cui Y, Tang Z, Kim Y, Nie H, Qu <lb/>L, Patel KN, Li Z, McNeil B, He S, Guan Y, Xiao B, Lamotte RH, <lb/>Dong X. A subpopulation of nociceptors specifically linked to itch. <lb/>Nat Neurosci 2013; 16: 174-182 [PMID: 23263443 DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>nn.3289] <lb/>33 Harvima IT, Nilsson G, Suttle MM, Naukkarinen A. Is there a <lb/>role for mast cells in psoriasis? Arch Dermatol Res 2008; 300: <lb/>461-478 [PMID: 18719932 DOI: 10.1007/s00403-008-0874-x] <lb/>34 Chung MK, Lee H, Mizuno A, Suzuki M, Caterina MJ. TRPV3 <lb/>and TRPV4 mediate warmth-evoked currents in primary mouse <lb/>keratinocytes. J Biol Chem 2004; 279: 21569-21575 [PMID: <lb/>15004014 DOI: 10.1074/jbc.M401872200] <lb/>35 Yoshioka T, Imura K, Asakawa M, Suzuki M, Oshima I, Hirasawa <lb/>T, Sakata T, Horikawa T, Arimura A. Impact of the Gly573Ser <lb/>substitution in TRPV3 on the development of allergic and pruritic <lb/>dermatitis in mice. J Invest Dermatol 2009; 129: 714-722 [PMID: <lb/>18754035 DOI: 10.1038/jid.2008.245] <lb/>36 Sun YG, Chen ZF. A gastrin-releasing peptide receptor mediates <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3424 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/>WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>the itch sensation in the spinal cord. Nature 2007; 448: 700-703 <lb/>[PMID: 17653196 DOI: 10.1038/nature06029] <lb/>37 Sun YG, Zhao ZQ, Meng XL, Yin J, Liu XY, Chen ZF. Cellular <lb/>basis of itch sensation. Science 2009; 325: 1531-1534 [PMID: <lb/>19661382 DOI: 10.1126/science.1174868] <lb/>38 Lagerström MC, Rogoz K, Abrahamsen B, Persson E, Reinius B, <lb/>Nordenankar K, Olund C, Smith C, Mendez JA, Chen ZF, Wood <lb/>JN, Wallén-Mackenzie A, Kullander K. VGLUT2-dependent <lb/>sensory neurons in the TRPV1 population regulate pain and itch. <lb/>Neuron 2010; 68: 529-542 [PMID: 21040852 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.neuron.2010.09.016] <lb/>39 Liu Y, Abdel Samad O, Zhang L, Duan B, Tong Q, Lopes C, Ji <lb/>RR, Lowell BB, Ma Q. VGLUT2-dependent glutamate release <lb/>from nociceptors is required to sense pain and suppress itch. <lb/>Neuron 2010; 68: 543-556 [PMID: 21040853 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.neuron.2010.09.008] <lb/>40 Tokumura A, Majima E, Kariya Y, Tominaga K, Kogure <lb/>K, Yasuda K, Fukuzawa K. Identification of human plasma <lb/>lysophospholipase D, a lysophosphatidic acid-producing enzyme, <lb/>as autotaxin, a multifunctional phosphodiesterase. J Biol Chem <lb/>2002; 277: 39436-39442 [PMID: 12176993 DOI: 10.1074/jbc. <lb/>M205623200] <lb/>41 Umezu-Goto M, Kishi Y, Taira A, Hama K, Dohmae N, Takio <lb/>K, Yamori T, Mills GB, Inoue K, Aoki J, Arai H. Autotaxin has <lb/>lysophospholipase D activity leading to tumor cell growth and <lb/>motility by lysophosphatidic acid production. J Cell Biol 2002; <lb/>158: 227-233 [PMID: 12119361 DOI: 10.1083/jcb.200204026] <lb/>42 Kremer AE, van Dijk R, Leckie P, Schaap FG, Kuiper EM, <lb/>Mettang T, Reiners KS, Raap U, van Buuren HR, van Erpecum KJ, <lb/>Davies NA, Rust C, Engert A, Jalan R, Oude Elferink RP, Beuers U. <lb/>Serum autotaxin is increased in pruritus of cholestasis, but not of <lb/>other origin, and responds to therapeutic interventions. Hepatology <lb/>2012; 56: 1391-1400 [PMID: 22473838 DOI: 10.1002/hep.25748] <lb/>43 Kremer AE, Bolier R, Dixon PH, Geenes V, Chambers J, <lb/>Tolenaars D, Ris-Stalpers C, Kaess BM, Rust C, van der Post JA, <lb/>Williamson C, Beuers U, Oude Elferink RP. Autotaxin activity has <lb/>a high accuracy to diagnose intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy. <lb/>J Hepatol 2015; 62: 897-904 [PMID: 25450205 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jhep.2014.10.041] <lb/>44 Green GR. Mechanism of hypogonadism in cirrhotic males. Gut <lb/>1977; 18: 843-853 [PMID: 590844] <lb/>45 Alemi F, Kwon E, Poole DP, Lieu T, Lyo V, Cattaruzza F, Cevikbas <lb/>F, Steinhoff M, Nassini R, Materazzi S, Guerrero-Alba R, Valdez-<lb/>Morales E, Cottrell GS, Schoonjans K, Geppetti P, Vanner SJ, <lb/>Bunnett NW, Corvera CU. The TGR5 receptor mediates bile acid-<lb/>induced itch and analgesia. J Clin Invest 2013; 123: 1513-1530 <lb/>[PMID: 23524965 DOI: 10.1172/JCI64551] <lb/>46 Lieu T, Jayaweera G, Zhao P, Poole DP, Jensen D, Grace M, <lb/>McIntyre P, Bron R, Wilson YM, Krappitz M, Haerteis S, <lb/>Korbmacher C, Steinhoff MS, Nassini R, Materazzi S, Geppetti P, <lb/>Corvera CU, Bunnett NW. The bile acid receptor TGR5 activates <lb/>the TRPA1 channel to induce itch in mice. Gastroenterology <lb/>2014; 147: 1417-1428 [PMID: 25194674 DOI: 10.1053/ <lb/>j.gastro.2014.08.042] <lb/>47 Cousins MJ, Mather LE. Intrathecal and epidural administration <lb/>of opioids. Anesthesiology 1984; 61: 276-310 [PMID: 6206753] <lb/>48 Ballantyne JC, Loach AB, Carr DB. Itching after epidural and <lb/>spinal opiates. Pain 1988; 33: 149-160 [PMID: 2837714] <lb/>49 Bernstein JE, Swift RM, Soltani K, Lorincz AL. Antipruritic <lb/>effect of an opiate antagonist, naloxone hydrochloride. J Invest <lb/>Dermatol 1982; 78: 82-83 [PMID: 7054311] <lb/>50 Bergasa NV, Talbot TL, Alling DW, Schmitt JM, Walker EC, <lb/>Baker BL, Korenman JC, Park Y, Hoofnagle JH, Jones EA. A <lb/>controlled trial of naloxone infusions for the pruritus of chronic <lb/>cholestasis. Gastroenterology 1992; 102: 544-549 [PMID: <lb/>1732125] <lb/>51 Thornton JR, Dean H, Losowsky MS. Is ascites caused by <lb/>impaired hepatic inactivation of blood borne endogenous opioid <lb/>peptides? Gut 1988; 29: 1167-1172 [PMID: 3197989] <lb/>52 Thornton JR, Losowsky MS. Plasma beta endorphin in cirrhosis <lb/>and renal failure. Gut 1991; 32: 306-308 [PMID: 2013426] <lb/>53 Thornton JR, Losowsky MS. Methionine enkephalin is increased <lb/>in plasma in acute liver disease and is present in bile and urine. J <lb/>Hepatol 1989; 8: 53-59 [PMID: 2921503] <lb/>54 Togashi Y, Umeuchi H, Okano K, Ando N, Yoshizawa Y, <lb/>Honda T, Kawamura K, Endoh T, Utsumi J, Kamei J, Tanaka <lb/>T, Nagase H. Antipruritic activity of the kappa-opioid receptor <lb/>agonist, TRK-820. Eur J Pharmacol 2002; 435: 259-264 [PMID: <lb/>11821035] <lb/>55 Umeuchi H, Togashi Y, Honda T, Nakao K, Okano K, Tanaka <lb/>T, Nagase H. Involvement of central mu-opioid system in the <lb/>scratching behavior in mice, and the suppression of it by the <lb/>activation of kappa-opioid system. Eur J Pharmacol 2003; 477: <lb/>29-35 [PMID: 14512095] <lb/>56 Inan S, Cowan A. Nalfurafine, a kappa opioid receptor agonist, <lb/>inhibits scratching behavior secondary to cholestasis induced by <lb/>chronic ethynylestradiol injections in rats. Pharmacol Biochem <lb/>Behav 2006; 85: 39-43 [PMID: 16919318 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.pbb.2006.07.004] <lb/>57 Dimoulios P, Kolios G, Notas G, Matrella E, Xidakis C, <lb/>Koulentaki M, Tsagarakis N, Kouroumalis A, Kouroumalis E. <lb/>Ursodeoxycholic acid reduces increased circulating endothelin 2 <lb/>in primary biliary cirrhosis. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2005; 21: <lb/>227-234 [PMID: 15691296 DOI: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2005.02307. <lb/>x] <lb/>58 Andoh T, Kuraishi Y. Nitric oxide enhances substance P-induced <lb/>itch-associated responses in mice. Br J Pharmacol 2003; 138: <lb/>202-208 [PMID: 12522091 DOI: 10.1038/sj.bjp.0705004] <lb/>59 Tajiri K, Miyakawa H, Izumi N, Marumo F, Sato C. Systemic <lb/>hypotension and diuresis by L-arginine in cirrhotic patients with <lb/>ascites: role of nitric oxide. Hepatology 1995; 22: 1430-1435 <lb/>[PMID: 7590659] <lb/>60 Bigliardi PL, Bigliardi-Qi M, Buechner S, Rufli T. Expression of <lb/>mu-opiate receptor in human epidermis and keratinocytes. J Invest <lb/>Dermatol 1998; 111: 297-301 [PMID: 9699733 DOI: 10.1046/ <lb/>j.1523-1747.1998.00259.x] <lb/>61 Tominaga M, Ogawa H, Takamori K. Possible roles of epidermal <lb/>opioid systems in pruritus of atopic dermatitis. J Invest Dermatol <lb/>2007; 127: 2228-2235 [PMID: 17611580 DOI: 10.1038/ <lb/>sj.jid.5700942] <lb/>62 Rishe E, Azarm A, Bergasa NV. Itch in primary biliary cirrhosis: a <lb/>patients&apos; perspective. Acta Derm Venereol 2008; 88: 34-37 [PMID: <lb/>18176748 DOI: 10.2340/00015555-0350] <lb/>63 Mells GF, Pells G, Newton JL, Bathgate AJ, Burroughs AK, <lb/>Heneghan MA, Neuberger JM, Day DB, Ducker SJ, Sandford RN, <lb/>Alexander GJ, Jones DE. Impact of primary biliary cirrhosis on <lb/>perceived quality of life: the UK-PBC national study. Hepatology <lb/>2013; 58: 273-283 [PMID: 23471852 DOI: 10.1002/hep.26365] <lb/>64 Zein CO, Lindor KD. Latest and emerging therapies for primary <lb/>biliary cirrhosis and primary sclerosing cholangitis. Curr <lb/>Gastroenterol Rep 2010; 12: 13-22 [PMID: 20425480 DOI: <lb/>10.1007/s11894-009-0079-2] <lb/>65 Pusl T, Beuers U. Ursodeoxycholic acid treatment of vanishing <lb/>bile duct syndromes. World J Gastroenterol 2006; 12: 3487-3495 <lb/>[PMID: 16773706 DOI: 10.3748/wjg.v12.i22.3487] <lb/>66 Talwalkar JA, Souto E, Jorgensen RA, Lindor KD. Natural history <lb/>of pruritus in primary biliary cirrhosis. Clin Gastroenterol Hepatol <lb/>2003; 1: 297-302 [PMID: 15017671] <lb/>67 Heathcote EJ. Management of primary biliary cirrhosis. The <lb/>American Association for the Study of Liver Diseases practice <lb/>guidelines. Hepatology 2000; 31: 1005-1013 [PMID: 10733559 <lb/>DOI: 10.1053/he.2000.5984] <lb/>68 Neuberger J, Jones EA. Liver transplantation for intractable <lb/>pruritus is contraindicated before an adequate trial of opiate <lb/>antagonist therapy. Eur J Gastroenterol Hepatol 2001; 13: <lb/>1393-1394 [PMID: 11692070] <lb/>69 Bonacini M. Pruritus in patients with chronic human <lb/>immunodeficiency virus, hepatitis B and C virus infections. Dig <lb/>Liver Dis 2000; 32: 621-625 [PMID: 11142563] <lb/>70 Dega H, Francès C, Dupin N, Lebre C, Simantov A, Callot C, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3425 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/> WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Laporte JL, Blot C, Opolon P, Poynard T, Chosidow O. [Pruritus <lb/>and the hepatitis C virus. The MULTIVIRC Unit]. Ann Dermatol <lb/>Venereol 1998; 125: 9-12 [PMID: 9747198] <lb/>71 Cacoub P, Poynard T, Ghillani P, Charlotte F, Olivi M, Piette <lb/>JC, Opolon P. Extrahepatic manifestations of chronic hepatitis C. <lb/>MULTIVIRC Group. Multidepartment Virus C. Arthritis Rheum <lb/>1999; 42: 2204-2212 [PMID: 10524695 DOI: 10.1002/1529-0131( <lb/>199910)42] <lb/>72 Geenes V, Williamson C. Intrahepatic cholestasis of pregnancy. <lb/>World J Gastroenterol 2009; 15: 2049-2066 [PMID: 19418576 <lb/>DOI: 10.3748/wjg.15.2049] <lb/>73 Pathak B, Sheibani L, Lee RH. Cholestasis of pregnancy. Obstet <lb/>Gynecol Clin North Am 2010; 37: 269-282 [PMID: 20685553 DOI: <lb/>10.1016/j.ogc.2010.02.011] <lb/>74 Glantz A, Marschall HU, Mattsson LA. Intrahepatic cholestasis <lb/>of pregnancy: Relationships between bile acid levels and fetal <lb/>complication rates. Hepatology 2004; 40: 467-474 [PMID: <lb/>15368452 DOI: 10.1002/hep.20336] <lb/>75 van der Woerd WL, Houwen RH, van de Graaf SF. Current and <lb/>future therapies for inherited cholestatic liver diseases. World J <lb/>Gastroenterol 2017; 23: 763-775 [PMID: 28223721 DOI: 10.3748/ <lb/>wjg.v23.i5.763] <lb/>76 Summerskill WH, Walshe JM. Benign recurrent intrahepatic <lb/>&quot;obstructive&quot; jaundice. Lancet 1959; 2: 686-690 [PMID: <lb/>13835689] <lb/>77 Mcphedran NT, Henderson RD. Pruritus and jaundice. Can Med <lb/>Assoc J 1965; 92: 1258-1260 [PMID: 14296007] <lb/>78 Lindor KD, Gershwin ME, Poupon R, Kaplan M, Bergasa NV, <lb/>Heathcote EJ. Primary biliary cirrhosis. Hepatology 2009; 50: <lb/>291-308 [PMID: 19554543 DOI: 10.1002/hep.22906] <lb/>79 European Association for the Study of the Liver. EASL Clinical <lb/>Practice Guidelines: management of cholestatic liver diseases. <lb/>J Hepatol 2009; 51: 237-267 [PMID: 19501929 DOI: 10.1016/ <lb/>j.jhep.2009.04.009] <lb/>80 Parés A, Caballería L, Rodés J. Excellent long-term survival in <lb/>patients with primary biliary cirrhosis and biochemical response <lb/>to ursodeoxycholic Acid. Gastroenterology 2006; 130: 715-720 <lb/>[PMID: 16530513 DOI: 10.1053/j.gastro.2005.12.029] <lb/>81 Kuiper EM, Hansen BE, de Vries RA, den Ouden-Muller JW, <lb/>van Ditzhuijsen TJ, Haagsma EB, Houben MH, Witteman BJ, <lb/>van Erpecum KJ, van Buuren HR. Improved prognosis of patients <lb/>with primary biliary cirrhosis that have a biochemical response <lb/>to ursodeoxycholic acid. Gastroenterology 2009; 136: 1281-1287 <lb/>[PMID: 19208346 DOI: 10.1053/j.gastro.2009.01.003] <lb/>82 Lindor KD. Ursodiol for primary sclerosing cholangitis. Mayo <lb/>Primary Sclerosing Cholangitis-Ursodeoxycholic Acid Study <lb/>Group. N Engl J Med 1997; 336: 691-695 [PMID: 9041099 DOI: <lb/>10.1056/NEJM199703063361003] <lb/>83 Chappell LC, Gurung V, Seed PT, Chambers J, Williamson C, <lb/>Thornton JG. Ursodeoxycholic acid versus placebo, and early term <lb/>delivery versus expectant management, in women with intrahepatic <lb/>cholestasis of pregnancy: semifactorial randomised clinical trial. <lb/>BMJ 2012; 344: e3799 [PMID: 22695903 DOI: 10.1136/bmj. <lb/>e3799] <lb/>84 Duncan JS, Kennedy HJ, Triger DR. Treatment of pruritus due to <lb/>chronic obstructive liver disease. Br Med J (Clin Res Ed) 1984; <lb/>289: 22 [PMID: 6145483] <lb/>85 Di Padova C, Tritapepe R, Rovagnati P, Rossetti S. Double-blind <lb/>placebo-controlled clinical trial of microporous cholestyramine in <lb/>the treatment of intra-and extra-hepatic cholestasis: relationship <lb/>between itching and serum bile acids. Methods Find Exp Clin <lb/>Pharmacol 1984; 6: 773-776 [PMID: 6397677] <lb/>86 Mela M, Mancuso A, Burroughs AK. Review article: pruritus in <lb/>cholestatic and other liver diseases. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2003; <lb/>17: 857-870 [PMID: 12656688] <lb/>87 Khurana S, Singh P. Rifampin is safe for treatment of pruritus due <lb/>to chronic cholestasis: a meta-analysis of prospective randomized-<lb/>controlled trials. Liver Int 2006; 26: 943-948 [PMID: 16953834 <lb/>DOI: 10.1111/j.1478-3231.2006.01326.x] <lb/>88 Bachs L, Parés A, Elena M, Piera C, Rodés J. Effects of long-<lb/>term rifampicin administration in primary biliary cirrhosis. <lb/>Gastroenterology 1992; 102: 2077-2080 [PMID: 1587427] <lb/>89 Martínez E, Collazos J, Mayo J. Hypersensitivity reactions to <lb/>rifampin. Pathogenetic mechanisms, clinical manifestations, <lb/>management strategies, and review of the anaphylactic-like <lb/>reactions. Medicine (Baltimore) 1999; 78: 361-369 [PMID: <lb/>10575418] <lb/>90 Imam MH, Gossard AA, Sinakos E, Lindor KD. Pathogenesis and <lb/>management of pruritus in cholestatic liver disease. J Gastroenterol <lb/>Hepatol 2012; 27: 1150-1158 [PMID: 22413872 DOI: 10.1111/ <lb/>j.1440-1746.2012.07109.x] <lb/>91 Bergasa NV, Alling DW, Talbot TL, Swain MG, Yurdaydin C, <lb/>Turner ML, Schmitt JM, Walker EC, Jones EA. Effects of naloxone <lb/>infusions in patients with the pruritus of cholestasis. A double-<lb/>blind, randomized, controlled trial. Ann Intern Med 1995; 123: <lb/>161-167 [PMID: 7598296] <lb/>92 Wolfhagen FH, Sternieri E, Hop WC, Vitale G, Bertolotti M, Van <lb/>Buuren HR. Oral naltrexone treatment for cholestatic pruritus: a <lb/>double-blind, placebo-controlled study. Gastroenterology 1997; <lb/>113: 1264-1269 [PMID: 9322521] <lb/>93 Terg R, Coronel E, Sordá J, Muñoz AE, Findor J. Efficacy and <lb/>safety of oral naltrexone treatment for pruritus of cholestasis, a <lb/>crossover, double blind, placebo-controlled study. J Hepatol 2002; <lb/>37: 717-722 [PMID: 12445410] <lb/>94 Mansour-Ghanaei F, Taheri A, Froutan H, Ghofrani H, Nasiri-<lb/>Toosi M, Bagherzadeh AH, Farahvash MJ, Mirmomen S, <lb/>Ebrahimi-Dariani N, Farhangi E, Pourrasouli Z. Effect of oral <lb/>naltrexone on pruritus in cholestatic patients. World J Gastroenterol <lb/>2006; 12: 1125-1128 [PMID: 16534857 DOI: 10.3748/wjg.v12. <lb/>i7.1125] <lb/>95 Phan NQ, Bernhard JD, Luger TA, Ständer S. Antipruritic <lb/>treatment with systemic μ-opioid receptor antagonists: a review. <lb/>J Am Acad Dermatol 2010; 63: 680-688 [PMID: 20462660 DOI: <lb/>10.1016/j.jaad.2009.08.052] <lb/>96 Ando A, Oshida K, Fukuyama S, Watanabe A, Hashimoto H, <lb/>Miyamoto Y. Identification of human cytochrome P450 enzymes <lb/>involved in the metabolism of a novel к-opioid receptor agonist, <lb/>nalfurafine hydrochloride. Biopharm Drug Dispos 2012; 33: <lb/>257-264 [PMID: 22581509 DOI: 10.1002/bdd.1793] <lb/>97 Nakao K, Togashi Y, Honda T, Momen S, Umeuchi H, Sakakibara <lb/>S, Tanaka T, Okano K, Mochizuki H. In vitro and in vivo <lb/>pharmacological characterization of the main metabolites of <lb/>nalfurafine hydrochloride. Eur J Pharmacol 2012; 695: 57-61 <lb/>[PMID: 22981641 DOI: 10.1016/j.ejphar.2012.08.017] <lb/>98 Kumada H, Miyakawa H, Muramatsu T, Ando N, Oh T, Takamori <lb/>K, Nakamoto H. Efficacy of nalfurafine hydrochloride in patients <lb/>with chronic liver disease with refractory pruritus: A randomized, <lb/>double-blind trial. Hepatol Res 2016; Epub ahead of print [PMID: <lb/>27753159 DOI: 10.1111/hepr.12830] <lb/>99 Mayo MJ, Handem I, Saldana S, Jacobe H, Getachew Y, Rush <lb/>AJ. Sertraline as a first-line treatment for cholestatic pruritus. <lb/>Hepatology 2007; 45: 666-674 [PMID: 17326161 DOI: 10.1002/ <lb/>hep.21553] <lb/>100 Alallam A, Barth D, Heathcote EJ. Role of plasmapheresis in <lb/>the treatment of severe pruritus in pregnant patients with primary <lb/>biliary cirrhosis: case reports. Can J Gastroenterol 2008; 22: <lb/>505-507 [PMID: 18478137] <lb/>101 Fuhrmann V, Drolz A, Trauner M. Extracorporeal artificial liver <lb/>support systems in the management of intractable cholestatic <lb/>pruritus. Liver Int 2011; 31 Suppl 3: 31-33 [PMID: 21824282 DOI: <lb/>10.1111/j.1478-3231.2011.02584.x] <lb/>102 Parés A, Cisneros L, Salmerón JM, Caballería L, Mas A, Torras <lb/>A, Rodés J. Extracorporeal albumin dialysis: a procedure for <lb/>prolonged relief of intractable pruritus in patients with primary <lb/>biliary cirrhosis. Am J Gastroenterol 2004; 99: 1105-1110 [PMID: <lb/>15180733 DOI: 10.1111/j.1572-0241.2004.30204.x] <lb/>103 Leckie P, Tritto G, Mookerjee R, Davies N, Jones D, Jalan <lb/>R. &apos;Out-patient&apos; albumin dialysis for cholestatic patients with <lb/>intractable pruritus. Aliment Pharmacol Ther 2012; 35: 696-704 <lb/>[PMID: 22260552 DOI: 10.1111/j.1365-2036.2012.04994.x] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/></note>

			<page>3426 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">May 21, 2017|Volume 23|Issue 19| <lb/> WJG|www.wjgnet.com <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>104 Parés A, Herrera M, Avilés J, Sanz M, Mas A. Treatment of <lb/>resistant pruritus from cholestasis with albumin dialysis: combined <lb/>analysis of patients from three centers. J Hepatol 2010; 53: <lb/>307-312 [PMID: 20580987 DOI: 10.1016/j.jhep.2010.02.031] <lb/>105 Pusl T, Denk GU, Parhofer KG, Beuers U. Plasma separation and <lb/>anion adsorption transiently relieve intractable pruritus in primary <lb/>biliary cirrhosis. J Hepatol 2006; 45: 887-891 [PMID: 17046095 <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/j.jhep.2006.08.008] <lb/>106 Decock S, Roelandts R, Steenbergen WV, Laleman W, Cassiman <lb/>D, Verslype C, Fevery J, Pelt JV, Nevens F. Cholestasis-induced <lb/>pruritus treated with ultraviolet B phototherapy: an observational <lb/>case series study. J Hepatol 2012; 57: 637-641 [PMID: 22613002 <lb/>DOI: 10.1016/j.jhep.2012.04.023] <lb/>107 Beuers U, Gerken G, Pusl T. Biliary drainage transiently relieves <lb/>intractable pruritus in primary biliary cirrhosis. Hepatology 2006; <lb/>44: 280-281 [PMID: 16799978 DOI: 10.1002/hep.21271] <lb/>108 Kumagai H, Ebata T, Takamori K, Muramatsu T, Nakamoto H, <lb/>Suzuki H. Effect of a novel kappa-receptor agonist, nalfurafine <lb/>hydrochloride, on severe itch in 337 haemodialysis patients: a <lb/>Phase III, randomized, double-blind, placebo-controlled study. <lb/>Nephrol Dial Transplant 2010; 25: 1251-1257 [PMID: 19926718 <lb/>DOI: 10.1093/ndt/gfp588] <lb/>109 Kumagai H, Ebata T, Takamori K, Miyasato K, Muramatsu T, <lb/>Nakamoto H, Kurihara M, Yanagita T, Suzuki H. Efficacy and <lb/>safety of a novel ĸ-agonist for managing intractable pruritus <lb/>in dialysis patients. Am J Nephrol 2012; 36: 175-183 [PMID: <lb/>22868684 DOI: 10.1159/000341268] <lb/>110 Pellicciari R, Fiorucci S, Camaioni E, Clerici C, Costantino G, <lb/>Maloney PR, Morelli A, Parks DJ, Willson TM. 6alpha-ethyl-<lb/>chenodeoxycholic acid (6-ECDCA), a potent and selective FXR <lb/>agonist endowed with anticholestatic activity. J Med Chem 2002; <lb/>45: 3569-3572 [PMID: 12166927] <lb/>111 Lindor KD. Farnesoid X receptor agonists for primary biliary <lb/>cirrhosis. Curr Opin Gastroenterol 2011; 27: 285-288 [PMID: <lb/>21297469 DOI: 10.1097/MOG.0b013e32834452c8] <lb/>112 Nevens F, Andreone P, Mazzella G, Strasser SI, Bowlus C, <lb/>Invernizzi P, Drenth JP, Pockros PJ, Regula J, Beuers U, Trauner <lb/>M, Jones DE, Floreani A, Hohenester S, Luketic V, Shiffman M, <lb/>van Erpecum KJ, Vargas V, Vincent C, Hirschfield GM, Shah H, <lb/>Hansen B, Lindor KD, Marschall HU, Kowdley KV, Hooshmand-<lb/>Rad R, Marmon T, Sheeron S, Pencek R, MacConell L, Pruzanski <lb/>M, Shapiro D. A Placebo-Controlled Trial of Obeticholic Acid in <lb/>Primary Biliary Cholangitis. N Engl J Med 2016; 375: 631-643 <lb/>[PMID: 27532829 DOI: 10.1056/NEJMoa1509840] <lb/>113 Bolier AR, Peri S, Oude Elferink RP, Beuers U. The challenge of <lb/>cholestatic pruritus. Acta Gastroenterol Belg 2012; 75: 399-404 <lb/>[PMID: 23402082] <lb/>114 Jones EA, Bergasa NV. The pruritus of cholestasis. Hepatology <lb/>1999; 29: 1003-1006 [PMID: 10094938 DOI: 10.1002/ <lb/>hep.510290450] <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">P-Reviewer: Chamuleau RAFM, Feuerstein JD S-Editor: Qi Y <lb/>L-Editor: A E-Editor: Zhang FF <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Tajiri K et al . Pruritus and liver diseases <lb/>© 2017 Baishideng Publishing Group Inc. All rights reserved. <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Published by Baishideng Publishing Group Inc <lb/>7901 Stoneridge Drive, Suite 501, Pleasanton, CA 94588, USA <lb/>Telephone: +1-925-223-8242 <lb/>Fax: +1-925-223-8243 <lb/>E-mail: bpgoffice@wjgnet.com <lb/>Help Desk: http://www.f6publishing.com/helpdesk <lb/>http://www.wjgnet.com <lb/>I S S N 1 0 0 7 -9 3 2 7 <lb/>9 7 7 1 0 07 9 3 2 0 45 <lb/> 1 9</div>

	</text>
</tei>
