<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>published: 04 June 2019 <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2019.01239 <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>1 <lb/>June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/>Edited by: <lb/>Attila Mócsai, <lb/>Semmelweis University, Hungary <lb/>Reviewed by: <lb/>Seung-Ki Kwok, <lb/>The Catholic University of Korea, <lb/>South Korea <lb/>David S. Gyori, <lb/>Semmelweis University, Hungary <lb/>*Correspondence: <lb/>Zhengliang Chen <lb/>zhlchen@smu.edu.cn <lb/>Daming Zuo <lb/>zdaming@smu.edu.cn <lb/> † These authors have contributed <lb/>equally to this work <lb/>Specialty section: <lb/>This article was submitted to <lb/>Autoimmune and Autoinflammatory <lb/>Disorders, <lb/>a section of the journal <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>Received: 08 March 2019 <lb/>Accepted: 16 May 2019 <lb/>Published: 04 June 2019 <lb/>Citation: <lb/>Dong L, Wu J, Chen K, Xie J, Wang Y, <lb/>Li D, Liu Y, Yin A, Zhao Y, Han Y, <lb/>Zhou J, Zhang L, Chen Z and Zuo D <lb/>(2019) Mannan-Binding Lectin <lb/>Attenuates Inflammatory Arthritis <lb/>Through the Suppression of <lb/>Osteoclastogenesis. <lb/>Front. Immunol. 10:1239. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2019.01239 <lb/> Mannan-Binding Lectin Attenuates <lb/>Inflammatory Arthritis Through the <lb/>Suppression of Osteoclastogenesis <lb/> Lijun Dong 1 † , Jun Wu 2 † , Kai Chen 1 , Jingwen Xie 1 , Youyi Wang 1,3 , Dantong Li , Yunzhi Liu , <lb/>Aiping Yin 1 , Yue Zhao 4 , Yunpeng Han , Jia Zhou 1 , Liyun Zhang 1 , Zhengliang Chen 1,6 * and <lb/>Daming Zuo 1,3,6,7 * <lb/>1 Department of Immunology, School of Basic Medical Sciences, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China, 2 Geriatrics <lb/>Center, General Hospital of Southern Theater Command, PLA, Guangzhou, China, School of Laboratory Medicine and <lb/>Biotechnology, Institute of Molecular Immunology, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China, 4 Department of <lb/>Rheumatology, The Second Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou University of Traditional Chinese Medicine, Guangzhou, China, <lb/>5 Department of Clinical Laboratory, Guangdong 999 Brain Hospital, Guangzhou, China, 6 Guangdong Provincial Key <lb/>Laboratory of Proteomics, Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China, Microbiome Medicine Center, Zhujiang Hospital, <lb/>Southern Medical University, Guangzhou, China <lb/>Mannan-binding lectin (MBL) is a vital element in the host innate immune system, which <lb/>is primarily produced by the liver and secreted into the circulation. Low serum level <lb/>of MBL is reported to be associated with an increased risk of arthritis. However, the <lb/>underlying mechanism by which MBL contributes to the pathogenesis of arthritis is <lb/>poorly understood. In this study, we investigated the precise role of MBL on the course <lb/>of experimental murine adjuvant-induced arthritis (AIA). MBL-deficient (MBL −/− ) AIA <lb/>mice showed significantly increased inflammatory responses compared with wild-type <lb/>C57BL/6 AIA mice, including exacerbated cartilage damage, enhanced histopathological <lb/>features and high level of tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase (TRAP)-positive cells. <lb/>MBL protein markedly inhibited the osteoclast formation from human blood monocytes <lb/>induced by receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB ligand (RANKL) and macrophage <lb/>colony-stimulating factor (M-CSF) in vitro. Mechanistic studies established that MBL <lb/>inhibited osteoclast differentiation via down-regulation of p38 signaling pathway and <lb/>subsequent nuclear translocation of c-fos as well as activation of nuclear factor of <lb/>activated T-cells c1 (NFATc1) pathway. Importantly, we have provided the evidence that <lb/>concentrations of MBL correlated negatively with the serum levels of amino-terminal <lb/>propeptide of type I procollagen (PINP) and C-terminal telopeptide of type I collagen <lb/>(β-CTX), serum markers of bone turnover, in patients with arthritis. Our study revealed <lb/>an unexpected function of MBL in osteoclastogenesis, thus providing new insight into <lb/>inflammatory arthritis and other bone-related diseases in patients with MBL deficiency. <lb/>Keywords: mannan-binding lectin, arthritis, osteoclastogenesis, receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB <lb/>ligand, p38 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Osteoclasts are specialized multinucleated cells derived from precursors in the myeloid/monocyte <lb/>lineage which resorb bone matrix. Destruction of the joint, in the progression of inflammatory <lb/>arthritis, is mainly attributed to the osteoclast differentiation and the upregulation of <lb/>osteoclast-related proteins (1). In osteoclastogenesis, two essential cytokines, receptor activator of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>nuclear factor-κB ligand (RANKL) and macrophage colony-<lb/>stimulating factor (M-CSF), are required for the osteoclast <lb/>formation (2). Sufficient osteoclast differentiation relied on the <lb/>establishment of specific patterns of gene expression achieved <lb/>through activation of transcription factors such as PU.1, <lb/>microphthalmia transcription factor (MITF), c-Fos, c-Myc, NF-<lb/>kappaB (NF-κB), activator protein-1 (AP-1), and nuclear factor-<lb/>activated T cells c1 (NFATc1) (3, 4). Among these, NFATc1 <lb/>is the most highly inducible transcription factor in osteoclast <lb/>precursor cells and act as a master regulator of osteoclast <lb/>differentiation through upregulating the osteoclast-specific genes <lb/>such as cathepsin K (CTSK), tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase <lb/>(TRAP), matrix metalloproteinase-9 (MMP-9), and osteoclast-<lb/>associated receptor (OSCAR), thereby promoting the cells fuse <lb/>to TRAP-positive multinucleated cells (3, 5, 6). Subsequently, <lb/>osteoclast differentiation results in bone resorption through <lb/>activation of the RANKL/RANK/osteoprotegerin axis. It is <lb/>of critical importance to broaden our understanding of the <lb/>molecular mechanisms that control the osteoclastogenesis during <lb/>the pathogenesis of inflammatory arthritis. <lb/>Mannan-binding lectin (MBL, also called mannose-binding <lb/>lectin) is a prototypic pattern recognition molecule of the innate <lb/>immune system, primarily synthesized in the liver and is mostly <lb/>found in the blood (7, 8). MBL can distinguish between the <lb/>carbohydrates found on self-glycoproteins and the carbohydrate <lb/>patterns found on infectious non-self surfaces and initiates the <lb/>complement cascade through the lectin pathway (7, 9). It is <lb/>now evident that MBL deficiency is associated with different <lb/>infectious and autoimmune diseases (10). Previous clinical <lb/>studies demonstrated that low serum level of MBL predisposes <lb/>to the development of arthritis and is a risk factor for severity <lb/>and treatment outcome (11-13). It is noteworthy to mention <lb/>that we previously observed MBL at high concentrations could <lb/>suppress the transition of monocytes to dendritic cells (DCs) <lb/>in the culture condition for DC differentiation (14). Besides, <lb/>MBL limited the maturation of monocyte-derived DCs induced <lb/>by lipopolysaccharide (LPS) via inhibiting NF-κB activation <lb/>(15). Indeed, MBL can bind to monocytes and modulates <lb/>inflammatory cytokine mRNA and protein levels in response <lb/>to LPS stimulation (16, 17). Therefore, it is possible that MBL <lb/>might influence the differentiation of monocytes into TRAP-<lb/>positive osteoclasts and subsequently involved in inflammatory <lb/>Abbreviations: IA, adjuvant-induced arthritis; AP-1, activator protein-1; BMP, <lb/>bone morphogenetic proteins; CFA, complete Freund&apos;s adjuvant; CTR, calcitonin <lb/>receptor; CTSK, cathepsin K; β-CTX, C-terminal telopeptide of type I collagen; <lb/>DC, dendritic cell; DC-STAMP, dendritic cell-specific transmembrane protein; <lb/>ECM, extracellular matrix; ERK, extracellular signal-regulated kinase; ESR, <lb/>erythrocyte sedimentation rate; FBS, fetal bovine serum; H&amp;E, hematoxylin and <lb/>eosin; IFA, incomplete Freund&apos;s adjuvant; IHC, immunohistochemical; JNK, c-<lb/>Jun N-terminal kinase; LPS, lipopolysaccharide; MAC, membrane attack complex; <lb/>MBL, Mannan-binding lectin; M-CSF, Macrophage colony-stimulating factor; <lb/>MITF, microphthalmia transcription factor; MMP, matrix metalloproteinase; <lb/>NFATc1, nuclear factor of activated T-cells c1; NF-κB, NF-kappaB; OPG, <lb/>Osteoprotegerin; OSCAR, osteoclast-associated receptor; PINP, amino-terminal <lb/>propeptide of type I procollagen; PVDF, polyvinylidene fluoride; RA, Rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis; RF, rheumatoid factor; RANKL, receptor activator of nuclear factor-κB <lb/>ligand; TRAP, tartrate-resistant acid phosphatase; WT, wild-type. <lb/>bone destruction, which, however, so far has no evidence to <lb/>support it. <lb/>Adjuvant-induced arthritis (AIA) is a widely used <lb/>experimental model for the study of inflammatory arthritis <lb/>(18, 19). A great number of osteoclast precursors, as well as <lb/>osteoclasts, were generated immediately after the onset of AIA, <lb/>and these cells were found in the subcompartments of the <lb/>joints (20). In this study, we used MBL-deficient (MBL −/− ) <lb/>mice to generate AIA for evaluating the function MBL on <lb/>the process of inflammatory arthritis, especially the formation <lb/>and function of osteoclasts. The results showed that MBL −/− <lb/>mice were susceptible to AIA and exhibited substantially <lb/>increased osteoclast formation. In vitro study revealed that MBL <lb/>dose-dependently inhibited the RANKL-induced osteoclast <lb/>differentiation by suppressing the p38/c-fos/NFATc1 signaling <lb/>axis. It is noteworthy that we demonstrated that arthritis patients <lb/>had low serum levels of MBL compared with healthy donors <lb/>and that concentrations of MBL correlated negatively with the <lb/>levels of amino-terminal propeptide of type I procollagen (PINP) <lb/>and C-terminal telopeptide of type I collagen (β-CTX), serum <lb/>markers for osteoclastic activity, in patients with arthritis. In <lb/>summary, our findings provide the first line of evidence that <lb/>MBL might have potential anti-osteoclastogenic effects, which <lb/>offers insight into the disease mechanisms of inflammatory <lb/>arthritis and other bone-related diseases, especially in patients <lb/>with MBL deficiency. <lb/>MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>Patient Samples and Mice <lb/>Thirty four serum samples of patients with arthritis were <lb/>recruited at the Second Affiliated Hospital of Guangzhou <lb/>University of Traditional Chinese Medicine (Guangzhou, China) <lb/>from January 2018 to June 2018. Thirty serum samples of healthy <lb/>donors were also collected as healthy controls (HCs). The patients <lb/>and controls were well-matched by age and gender. The study <lb/>was reviewed and approved by the Medical Ethics Committee <lb/>of Southern Medical University. Before the collection of the <lb/>blood sample, informed consent for taking part in the study was <lb/>obtained from each participant. <lb/>WT C57BL/6J mice were obtained from the Laboratory <lb/>Animal Center of Southern Medical University (Guangzhou, <lb/>China). MBL −/− mice were purchased from the Jackson <lb/>Laboratory (Bar Harbor, ME, USA). The mice were housed under <lb/>a specific pathogen-free condition, on a 12-h light-dark cycle, <lb/>and with food and water ad libitum. All animal experiments in <lb/>this study were approved by the Welfare and Ethical Committee <lb/>for Experimental Animal Care of Southern Medical University <lb/>(Approval number: L2016014). <lb/>Reagents <lb/>MBL protein was prepared as previously described (16). <lb/>Recombinant human RANKL (310-01C) and M-CSF (300-25) <lb/>were purchased from Peprotech (London, UK). Recombinant <lb/>murine RANKL (315-11) and M-CSF (315-02) were purchased <lb/>from Peprotech (London, UK). Anti-c-fos antibody (26192-<lb/>1-AP), anti-GAPDH antibody (10494-1-AP), and anti-CTSK <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>antibody (11239-1-AP) were purchased from proteintech <lb/>(Chicago, IL, USA). The anti-NFATc1 antibody was purchased <lb/>from Abclonal Technology (Wuhan, China). Polyclonal <lb/>antibodies against p38 (8690), phospho-p38 (4511), and Histone <lb/>H3 (4499) were obtained from Cell Signaling Technology <lb/>(Cambridge, MA, USA). The TRAP staining kit (387A) was from <lb/>Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO, USA). Safranin O-solid green <lb/>cartilage staining solution (G1317), Hematoxylin-Eosin solution <lb/>(G4520), Masson&apos;s trichrome staining kit (G1340), and Toluidine <lb/>blue staining solution (G2543) were purchased from Solarbio <lb/>(Beijing, China). <lb/>Induction of Adjuvant-Induced <lb/>Arthritis (AIA) <lb/>Adjuvant arthritis was induced on day 0 of the experiment by <lb/>subcutaneous injection of 0.1 ml of complete Freund&apos;s adjuvant <lb/>(CFA) (4 mg/ml heat-killed Mycobacterium tuberculosis, <lb/>Chondrex, Redmond, WA, USA). Mice were injected with 20 µl <lb/>of incomplete Freund&apos;s adjuvant (IFA) into the knee joint space <lb/>under general anesthesia on day 14. <lb/>Cell Culture and Osteoclast Differentiation <lb/>Human monocytes were purified from EDTA-blood of healthy <lb/>donors using CD14 Microbeads (Miltenyi Biotec, Bergisch <lb/>Gladbach, Germany) following the manufacturers&apos; instructions <lb/>and cultured in α-minimum Eagle&apos;s medium (α-MEM) <lb/>supplemented with 10% heat-inactivated fetal bovine serum <lb/>(FBS), 1% penicillin/ streptomycin, 50 ng/ml of recombinant <lb/>human M-CSF and 100 ng/ml of RANKL for indicated days. <lb/>TRAP Staining <lb/>To identify osteoclasts, the differentiated cells were fixed in 4% <lb/>paraformaldehyde for 20 min and then stained with the TRAP <lb/>staining kit (Sigma-Aldrich) according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Dark-red cells containing three or more nuclei were <lb/>considered TRAP + multinucleated cells. The total number of <lb/>TRAP-positive osteoclasts was calculated using Osteomeasure <lb/>software (OsteoMetrics, Inc., Decatur, GA, USA). <lb/>Bone Resorption Assay <lb/>The resorptive function of mature osteoclasts was analyzed <lb/>on bovine bone slices (Immunodiagnostic Systems, London, <lb/>England). Briefly, cells were cultured in the differentiated <lb/>medium in the presence or absence of MBL protein for 8 days on <lb/>bone slices. Then the slices were washed twice with PBS, and the <lb/>resorption pits were stained with toluidine blue (Sigma-Aldrich) <lb/>for 5 min. The resorption area was analyzed using the Olympus <lb/>image system. <lb/>Immunofluorescence Staining <lb/>Cells were grown in confocal dishes, fixed in 4% formaldehyde <lb/>for 15 min at room temperature and permeabilized with 0.25% <lb/>Triton X-100 for 10 min at room temperature. After blocking <lb/>with 5% FBS for 1 h, cells were incubated with primary antibodies <lb/>overnight at 4 • C, rinsed, and incubated with fluorescent-<lb/>conjugated secondary antibodies for 1 h in the dark. Finally, <lb/>TABLE 1 | List of primer sequences used for RT-PCR analysis in this study. <lb/>Forward primer (5 <lb/>′ -3 <lb/>′ ) <lb/>Reverse primer (5 <lb/>′ -3 <lb/>′ ) <lb/>CTSK <lb/>ACACCCACTGGGAGCTATG <lb/>GACAGGGGTACTTTGAGTCCA <lb/>c-fos <lb/>CTGTGATCCAAAATCCCTTCAGC GGTCTGTGGTCTGTACGGAC <lb/>DC-STAMP GGGGCCAGTAGCCAATCTG <lb/>CCGTCTCACTATTCACCTGGG <lb/>CTR <lb/>CCTATCCAACAATAGAGCCCAAG TGCATTCGGTCATAGCATTTGTA <lb/>NFATc1 <lb/>CACCGCATCACAGGGAAGAC <lb/>GCACAGTCAATGACGGCTC <lb/>MMP9 <lb/>TGTACCGCTATGGTTACACTCG GGCAGGGACAGTTGCTTCT <lb/>GAPDH <lb/>GGAGCGAGATCCCTCCAAAAT GGCTGTTGTCATACTTCTCATGG <lb/>cells were counterstained with 4 <lb/>′ ,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole <lb/>(DAPI, Beyotime). <lb/>RNA Isolation and Quantitative Real-Time <lb/>PCR <lb/>Total RNA was extracted using Trizol (TransGene Biotech, <lb/>Beijing, China) and then transcribed into cDNA using TranScript <lb/>All-in-One First-Strand cDNA Synthesis SuperMix (TransGene <lb/>Biotech), as instructed by the manufacturer. Real-time PCR <lb/>was performed with an Eppendorf Realplex PCR system using <lb/>TransStart Tip Green qPCR SuperMix (TransGene Biotech). The <lb/>expression was normalized to the expression of the housekeeping <lb/>gene GAPDH. The primer sequences used in the experiment are <lb/>shown in Table 1. <lb/>ELISA Assay <lb/>Mice blood samples were obtained from the carotid artery and <lb/>centrifuged at 3,500 × g for 15 min, and then the supernatant <lb/>was collected and set aside at −80 • C for serum cytokine analysis. <lb/>Cytokine levels in the sera were assessed using commercial ELISA <lb/>kits purchased from eBioscience (San Diego, CA, USA). <lb/>Western Blotting Analysis <lb/>Protein lysate was prepared in RIPA buffer (Beyotime, Hangzhou, <lb/>China) supplemented with protease and phosphatase inhibitor <lb/>cocktails (Beyotime). Nuclear and cytoplasmic proteins <lb/>were extracted according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol <lb/>(Beyotime). Protein samples were fractionated by SDS-PAGE <lb/>and electrophoretically transferred onto polyvinylidene fluoride <lb/>(PVDF) membranes (Millipore, Billerica, MA, USA). After <lb/>blocking with bovine serum albumin (BSA, 5%) for 1 h at <lb/>room temperature, the membranes were incubated overnight <lb/>at 4 • C with primary antibodies. Subsequently, the membranes <lb/>were incubated with the horseradish peroxidase-conjugated <lb/>corresponding secondary antibody for 1 h at room temperature. <lb/>Finally, detection of the target protein was conducted with <lb/>enhanced chemiluminescence (Thermo Fisher, Carlsbad, CA, <lb/>USA) according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. <lb/>Histological Evaluation <lb/>Hind limb samples were collected from arthritis mice and <lb/>then fixed in 4% paraformaldehyde, embedded in paraffin, and <lb/>stained with hematoxylin and eosin (H&amp;E), TRAP, Masson&apos;s <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>trichrome, safranin O-fast green, and toluidine blue according to <lb/>the manufacturer&apos;s instruction. <lb/>For immunohistochemical (IHC) staining, antigen retrieval <lb/>was performed in a citrate buffer (pH 6.0) at 120 • C for 10 min <lb/>and endogenous peroxidase activity was blocked by exposure <lb/>to 3% H 2 O 2 for 15 min. Sections were then incubated with <lb/>primary antibodies at 4 • C overnight. Immuno-reactivity was <lb/>detected using the corresponding HRP-conjugated secondary <lb/>antibody and visualized using diaminobenzidine kit (Beyotime <lb/>Biotechnology, Shanghai, China). <lb/>Micro-Computed Tomography (Micro-CT) <lb/>Analysis <lb/>Knee joints were scanned using a skyscan micro-CT scanner <lb/>(Bruker, Karlsruhe, Germany) with X-ray beam settings of 50 kV <lb/>and 50 µA. Trabecular bone regions of interest were selected by <lb/>highlighting trabecular bone regions for cross-sectional slices of <lb/>the hind limb and bone architecture determined by quantifying <lb/>trabecular bone parameters using CTAN software. <lb/>Statistical Analysis <lb/>All values were expressed as mean ± SD. One-way ANOVA was <lb/>used for comparisons among multiple groups. Differences <lb/>between two groups in the experiments were analyzed <lb/>by Student&apos;s t-test. Value of p &lt; 0.05 was considered <lb/>statistically significant. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>MBL Deficiency Promotes the Progression <lb/>of Mouse AIA and Associated With <lb/>Enhanced Inflammatory Mediator <lb/>To explore the pathogenic role of MBL in inflammatory arthritis <lb/>disease, we developed AIA in MBL −/− and paired WT mice. <lb/>Histological analysis of knee joints after adjuvant injection <lb/>demonstrated that MBL −/− mice showed severe joint damage <lb/>compared with WT counterparts (Figure 1A). Besides, MBL −/− <lb/>mice exhibited more osteoporosis and collagen deposition than <lb/>WT mice during the development of arthritis (Figures 1B,C). <lb/>Moreover, there was significantly more destruction of the <lb/>bone and cartilage in the adjuvant-treated MBL −/− mice than <lb/>those in WT controls (Figures 1D,E). We also examined and <lb/>compared the expression of inflammatory cytokines between <lb/>adjuvant-treated WT and MBL −/− mice. The result showed that <lb/>aggravated joint damage in MBL −/− mice was accompanied by <lb/>a significant elevation of pro-inflammatory cytokines (i.e., IL-1β, <lb/>TNF-α, and IL-6) and reduction of anti-inflammatory cytokine <lb/>IL-10 in hind paw (Figure 1F). <lb/>Using the established murine model of AIA, the impact <lb/>of MBL on bone architecture was evaluated by micro-<lb/>CT analysis. Qualitative analysis of the three-dimensional <lb/>reconstruction of the knee joints (Figure 2A) confirmed that <lb/>MBL had been able to prevent the external focal erosion on <lb/>the periarticular surfaces. Similarly, longitudinal mid-sections <lb/>(Figure 2B) and transaxial (Figure 2C) images of knee joint <lb/>showed a reduction in trabecular bone mass in MBL −/− mice <lb/>upon adjuvant injection. Compared with WT AIA mice, the <lb/>MBL −/− AIA mice exhibited decreased bone volume/tissue <lb/>volume (BV/TV) (Figure 2D), reduced trabecular number <lb/>(Tb.N) (Figure 2E) and declined trabecular thickness (Tb.Th) <lb/>(Figure 2F). Concomitantly, the trabecular spacing (Tb.Sp) <lb/>of MBL −/− AIA mice was significantly higher than that of <lb/>WT counterparts (Figure 2G). Together, these results indicate <lb/>a potential protective role of MBL in the pathogenesis of <lb/>experimental AIA. <lb/>MBL Deficiency Facilitates Osteoclast <lb/>Formation in Mice AIA <lb/>Accumulating evidence pointed out that the increased <lb/>osteoclastic activity is responsible for bone loss or joint <lb/>destruction during the development of inflammatory arthritis <lb/>(21). To determine the role of MBL in osteoclastogenesis, <lb/>TRAP staining was performed on the bone sections isolated <lb/>from adjuvant-treated WT and MBL −/− mice. The result <lb/>demonstrated that a massive increase in numbers of osteoclasts <lb/>in the knee joints from MBL −/− mice compared with those from <lb/>WT mice (Figure 3A). CTSK is a novel cysteine protease <lb/>previously reported to be predominantly expressed by <lb/>osteoclasts (22). Immunolocalization of CTSK revealed a <lb/>higher amount of CSTK-positive osteoclasts in the joint from <lb/>adjuvant-treated MBL −/− mice than that from WT controls <lb/>(Figure 3B). Osteoprotegerin (OPG), produced by osteoblasts, is <lb/>an essential regulator in osteoclast formation via inhibiting both <lb/>differentiation and function of osteoclasts (23). We observed <lb/>that OPG expression was significantly lower in MBL −/− <lb/>AIA mice than WT controls by the immunohistochemical <lb/>staining (Figure 3C). Besides, bone morphogenetic proteins <lb/>(BMPs, e.g., BMP2 and BMP4), potent mediators for osteoblast <lb/>differentiation (24), were strongly over-expressed in the tissues <lb/>from MBL −/− arthritis mice compared to those from WT <lb/>counterparts (Figures 3D,E). Moreover, the levels of serum <lb/>PINP, a biochemical marker of bone formation, was significantly <lb/>higher in MBL −/− mice with arthritis than WT counterparts <lb/>(Figure 3F). The adjuvant-treated MBL −/− mice also displayed <lb/>a markedly increase in the serum level of β-CTX, a marker <lb/>of bone resorption, compared to WT controls (Figure 3F). <lb/>Collectively, these data suggest that MBL may modulate <lb/>the osteoclast formation and activity in the pathogenesis of <lb/>inflammatory arthritis. <lb/>MBL Suppresses RANKL-Induced <lb/>Osteoclast Formation in vitro <lb/>We compared the osteoclast formation in bone marrow <lb/>cells from WT and MBL −/− mice. Upon cultivation with <lb/>M-CSF and RANKL, bone marrow cells from MBL −/− <lb/>mice more efficiently differentiated into mature TRAP-<lb/>positive multinucleated osteoclasts than those from WT <lb/>littermates (Supplementary Figure 1A). Consistently, osteoclast <lb/>cultures of MBL −/− mice displayed an elevated resorption <lb/>activity (Supplementary Figure 1B). The data indicate that <lb/>MBL generated by osteoclast precursors and/or mature <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 1 | MBL ablation renders mice more susceptible to AIA. WT and MBL −/− mice (n = 6) arthritis was induced by immunization with Freund&apos;s complete <lb/>adjuvant and Freund&apos;s incomplete adjuvant. (A) Histopathological evaluation of the arthritis-induced damage to the knee joints was performed with H&amp;E staining. <lb/>Bottom panels showed the higher-magnification views of the box area. Scale bars = 200 µm. (B-E) Bone destruction and cartilage damage in knee bone from WT <lb/>and MBL −/− mice were determined after 6 months with adjuvant induction. Osteoporosis was examined by H&amp;E staining in knee bone from WT and MBL −/− mice <lb/>after 6 months with adjuvant induction (B). Masson&apos;s trichrome staining was used to assess collagen deposition (C). Cartilage erosion was assessed by safranin <lb/>O-fast green staining (D). Toluidine Blue staining was used to qualitatively assess the proteoglycan content in the cartilage (E). Scale bar = 50 µm. (F) The serum level <lb/>of TNF-α, IL-1β, IL-6, and IL-10 from each group of mice 4 months after the primary immunization was measured by ELISA. **p &lt; 0.01. Data are representative of <lb/>three independent experiments with similar results. <lb/>osteoclasts initiates an autocrine negative feedback loop to <lb/>regulate osteoclastogenesis. <lb/>Next, we investigated whether exogenous MBL protein <lb/>affected human osteoclast differentiation in vitro. Human <lb/>purified monocytes were treated with 100 ng/ml of RANKL <lb/>and 50 ng/ml of M-CSF, which is known to induce osteoclast <lb/>formation (4, 25), in the presence or absence of varying <lb/>concentrations of MBL protein. As shown in Figure 4A, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 2 | MBL prevents the systemic bone loss of AIA mice. (A-C) The hind knee joint was analyzed by micro-CT in AIA mice at months 4. Three-dimensional <lb/>images of the knee joints of WT and MBL −/− mice (n = 6 for each group) were reconstructed (A). Longitudinal mid images. Scale bar = 1 mm. (B) and transaxial <lb/>images. Scale bar = 1 mm. (C) from micro-CT analysis of knee joint were presented. Scale bar = 200 µm. (D-G) Changes in the morphometric parameters such as <lb/>bone surface density (BS/TV) (D), trabecular number (Tb.N) (E), trabecular thickness (Tb.Th) (F), and trabecular spacing (Tb.Sp) (G) were presented. **p &lt; 0.01. Data <lb/>shown represent three independent experiments with similar results. <lb/>FIGURE | Osteoclast formation is increased in MBL-deficient AIA mice. (A-E) The expressions of specific osteoclast markers, TRAP (A), CTSK (B), OPG (C) BMP2 <lb/>(D), and BMP4 (E), in the knee bone tissues from WT and MBL −/− AIA mice were detected 4 months after the primary immunization by immunohistochemical <lb/>staining. Scale bar = 100 µm. (F) Serum activities of P1NP and β-CTX in each group of mice was assessed 4 months after the primary immunization. *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; <lb/>0.01. Data are representative of three independent experiments with similar results. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 4 | MBL suppresses osteogenesis and osteoclast-specific genes expression in vitro. Purified human monocytes were cultured with RANKL (100 ng/ml) and <lb/>M-CSF (50 ng/ml) in the absence or presence of the indicated concentrations of MBL protein. (A,B) Osteoclast differentiation was determined by <lb/>immunohistochemical staining with TRAP. Scale bar = 50 µm (A). Bone resorption activity was evaluated by measuring the pit area of each well. Scale bar = 100 µm <lb/>(B). **p &lt; 0.01, compared to the group without MBL protein. (C) The mRNA level of osteoclast-specific genes, DC-STAMP, CTSK, and CTR, was detected by <lb/>quantitative RT-PCR analysis and expressed as a ratio to GAPDH. (D) The mRNA expression of novel transcription factors (NFATc1 and c-fos) in osteoclast <lb/>differentiation proteins was analyzed by real-time RT-PCR. (E) The protein level of CTSK, NFATc1, and c-fos was evaluated by immunoblotting analysis. (F) The <lb/>expression and nuclear accumulation of NFATc1 (left panel) and c-fos (right panel) were detected through immunofluorescence analysis. Scale bar = 50 µm. (G) <lb/>Relative mRNA expression levels of MMP9 was measured by quantitative RT-PCR and expressed as a ratio to GAPDH. **p &lt; 0.01, ND, not detectable, NS, not <lb/>significant. One of the three independent experiments is shown. <lb/>MBL treatment significantly reduced the number of TRAP-<lb/>positive multinucleated osteoclasts. Besides, MBL protein <lb/>inhibited the bone resorption ability of osteoclasts in a <lb/>dose-dependent manner (Figure 4B). Consistent with the <lb/>limitation of osteoclastogenesis, the expression levels of several <lb/>established osteoclast marker genes, including dendritic cell-<lb/>specific transmembrane protein (DC-STAMP), CTSK and <lb/>calcitonin receptor (CTR), were sharply reduced upon MBL <lb/>administration (Figure 4C). Besides, MBL also showed an <lb/>inhibitory effect on the induction of c-fos and NFATc1, <lb/>two of the essential osteoclasts-specific transcription factors, <lb/>during RANKL-stimulated osteoclast formation (Figure 4D). <lb/>Western blot analysis further confirmed the reduced protein <lb/>level of osteoclast marker and transcription factors in MBL-<lb/>treatment group compared to the control group (Figure 4E). <lb/>Notably, the nuclear localizations of NFATc1 and c-fos are <lb/>essential for the osteoclast differentiation (3, 25). We performed <lb/>immunofluorescence staining assay to confirm whether MBL <lb/>inhibited the expressions and nuclear localizations of NFATc1 <lb/>and c-fos in the osteoclasts. The result showed that MBL <lb/>treatment significantly decreased the expressions and nuclear <lb/>accumulations of NFATc1 and c-fos in M-CSF and RANKL-<lb/>stimulated human monocytes (Figure 4F). MMPs are a large <lb/>group of enzymes responsible for matrix degradation (26). <lb/>Among the MMPs, MMP-9, uniquely expressed by osteoclasts <lb/>(27), play a crucial role in joint destruction of inflammatory <lb/>arthritis (26, 28). Additional study demonstrated that MBL <lb/>inhibited the expression of MMP-9 in differentiated human <lb/>osteoclasts (Figure 4G). Taken together, these data indicate that <lb/>MBL impairs osteoclast differentiation in vitro. <lb/>MBL Affects Osteoclastogenesis Through <lb/>Modulation of p38 Signaling Pathway <lb/>All the three MAPK family members (i.e., extracellular signal-<lb/>regulated kinase (ERK), c-Jun N-terminal kinase (JNK), and <lb/>p38) are rapidly phosphorylated and activated following RANKL <lb/>stimulation of osteoclast precursor cells (29). Among them, <lb/>the role of p38 in osteoclast differentiation and function <lb/>was extensively investigated (25, 30). Inactivation of the p38 <lb/>signaling pathway completely blocked the induction of c-<lb/>fos and NFATc1 with concomitant inhibition of RANKL-<lb/>induced osteoclastogenesis (25). We, therefore, investigate <lb/>the activation of the p38 signaling pathway in RANKL-<lb/>induced osteoclast formation. Enhanced p38 phosphorylation <lb/>was observed in MBL −/− mice-derived osteoclasts compared <lb/>with WT controls (Supplementary Figure 2). Also, MBL protein <lb/>efficiently inhibited RANKL-induced phosphorylation of p38 <lb/>in human osteoclast precursors (Figure 5A). Intriguingly, <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 5 | MBL inhibits the osteoclast differentiation via downregulation of p38 signaling pathway. The monocytes were treated with RANKL (100 ng/mL) and M-CSF <lb/>(50 ng/mL) in the presence or absence of 20 µg/ml MBL protein for indicated time points. (A) The phosphorylated of p38 were determined by western blot analysis. <lb/>(B) The expression of NFATc1 and c-fos in cytosolic and nuclear fractions of the cells was evaluated by immunoblotting analysis. (C-E) Human monocytes were <lb/>cultured with RANKL (100 ng/mL), M-CSF (50 ng/mL) and MBL protein (20 µg/ml) in the presence or absence of the p38 inhibitor SB203580 (50 nM) for 4 days. Then, <lb/>the protein levels of CTSK, NFATc1, and c-fos were evaluated by immunoblotting analysis (C). The mRNA levels of osteoclast-specific genes (DC-STAMP, CTSK, and <lb/>CTR) (D) and the novel transcription factors (NFATc1 and c-fos). (E) were analyzed by quantitative RT-PCR analysis and expressed as a ratio to GAPDH. *p &lt; 0.05, <lb/>**p &lt; 0.01, NS, not significant. The data represent three independent experiments with similar results. <lb/>the subsequent nuclear translocations of NFATc1 and c-<lb/>fos were substantially limited in the presence of MBL <lb/>(Figure 5B). To further evaluate the effect of p38 activation <lb/>on MBL-mediated regulation of osteoclast differentiation, <lb/>osteoclast precursors were pre-treated with p38 inhibitor, <lb/>SB203580, before RANKL stimulation. The levels of osteoclast <lb/>markers and osteoclasts-specific transcription factors were <lb/>strongly reduced and comparable between RANKL-induced <lb/>osteoclast differentiations with or without MBL incubation upon <lb/>p38 blockade (Figures 5C-E). These results suggest that the <lb/>regulation by MBL of osteoclast differentiation is dependent on <lb/>the p38 signaling pathway. <lb/>The Correlation of Plasma MBL Levels <lb/>With Disease Severity and Osteoclast <lb/>Differentiation in Patients With <lb/>Inflammatory Arthritis <lb/>Rheumatoid arthritis (RA) is characterized by joint inflammation <lb/>and progressive joint damage, and bone destruction in RA is <lb/>mainly attributable to the abnormal activation of osteoclasts (1). <lb/>We, therefore, explored the role of MBL in the progression of RA <lb/>as well as the process of osteoclastogenesis. In line with previous <lb/>reports (12, 31), we found that the sera from RA patients showed <lb/>the MBL serum levels in these patients were significantly lower <lb/>than those in HCs (Figure 6A). We also analyzed the association <lb/>of MBL serum level with the disease activity. The results <lb/>showed that the serum level of MBL was negatively correlated <lb/>with rheumatoid factor (RF) (Figure 6B) and erythrocyte <lb/>sedimentation rate (ESR) (Figure 6C). Furthermore, MBL levels <lb/>were found to be negatively correlated with serum levels of <lb/>PINP and β-CTX in patients with RA (Figures 6D,E). These data <lb/>indicate that circulating levels of MBL was significantly associated <lb/>with the disease activity and osteoclastogenesis in patients with <lb/>inflammatory arthritis. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>MBL is a liver-derived circulating plasma protein, which usually <lb/>acts as an immunomodulator in the inflammatory response <lb/>during microbial infection and tissue regeneration (8, 9). It <lb/>has been reported that MBL deficiency is a significant risk <lb/>factor for inflammatory arthritis (12, 31). In the present study, <lb/>we demonstrated that MBL deficiency exacerbated adjuvant-<lb/>induced inflammatory arthritis in mice, which was associated <lb/>with a remarkable increase in the formation of osteoclasts. We <lb/>also assessed the effects of MBL protein on RANKL-induced <lb/>osteoclastogenesis in human monocytes. Our results indicated <lb/>that MBL inhibited the RANKL-induced osteoclastogenesis by <lb/>attenuating the RANKL-mediated p38 pathway activation and <lb/>inhibiting the level of c-fos and NFATc1 transcription factors. <lb/>Furthermore, our data demonstrated a significant correlation <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>FIGURE 6 | Serum MBL levels are negatively correlated with the severity of arthritis and bone turnover. (A) Comparison of serum MBL in healthy controls (HC) (n = <lb/>30) and arthritis patients (n = 34). (B,C) Correlation between serum MBL levels with arthritis serological parameters, RF (B) and ESR (C), in patients with arthritis. <lb/>(D-E) The relationship of serum MBL concentration with bone turnover biochemical markers, P1NP (D) and β-CTX (E), in patients with arthritis. <lb/>between the serum level of MBL and bone turnover markers (i.e., <lb/>PINP and β-CTX) in patients with arthritis. <lb/>Cartilage damage is a crucial feature of chronic inflammatory <lb/>joint diseases (32). Joint damage might result in the release of <lb/>extracellular matrix (ECM) components (e.g., fibromodulin <lb/>and aggrecan) into the synovial fluid, which can activate the <lb/>complement system and form membrane attack complex <lb/>(MAC) targeting chondrocytes and killing them to cause <lb/>cartilage damage, thereby continuing self-perpetuating cycle <lb/>of complement activation and cartilage damage. Wang <lb/>et al. (33) validated that the expression and activation of <lb/>complement are abnormally high in human arthritis joints <lb/>by proteomic and transcriptomic analysis of synovial fluids <lb/>and synovial membranes from subjects with arthritis. It <lb/>was thought that complement inhibition would be sufficient <lb/>to break the cycle of complement activation and cartilage <lb/>damage and consequent prevent inflammatory arthritis after <lb/>knee trauma. Indeed, the mice deficient for C3 or factor B <lb/>were highly resistant to experimental arthritis, indicating <lb/>that complement activation by both the classical and the <lb/>alternative pathway acts as a deleterious role in inflammatory <lb/>(34). Moreover, complement modulation by using C3aR <lb/>and C5aR antagonists and an anti-C5 blocking antibody <lb/>was found to be effective in animal studies by ameliorating <lb/>arthritis or even preventing the disease (35-37). Here, we <lb/>observed the adjuvant-treated MBL −/− mice exhibited <lb/>severe joint damage accompanied by the destruction of <lb/>joint cartilage and bone compared with WT counterparts, <lb/>indicating that MBL limits the pathogenesis and progression <lb/>of inflammatory arthritis. It is widely known that MBL-<lb/>initiated lectin pathway is one of the routes leading to <lb/>activate the complement cascade. Meanwhile, MBL also <lb/>performs a regulatory role in the immune system (10). <lb/>Therefore, we postulated that MBL might be critical in <lb/>the regulation of inflammatory responses rather than the <lb/>activation of the complement system in the pathogenesis of <lb/>inflammatory arthritis. <lb/>The effect of MBL on the protection of bone disruption <lb/>could also be manifested through regulating osteoclast formation. <lb/>As suggested by our data, MBL has potent activity in globally <lb/>reducing the expression of specific osteoclast markers in RANKL <lb/>and M-CSF treated cells, including TRAP, CTSK, CTR, as well <lb/>as the transcription factor NFATc1 and c-fos. It is noteworthy <lb/>to mention that osteoclast differentiation contributes to the <lb/>progressive joint destruction in patients with inflammatory <lb/>arthritis (4, 38). The involvement of MBL in the processes <lb/>of coagulation cascade initiation is extensive studied (10). <lb/>Notably, thrombin inhibits the early stages of RANKL-induced <lb/>osteoclast differentiation through a direct effect on osteoclast <lb/>precursors (39). Low MBL level caused by a genetic variation <lb/>has been reported to be disturbed the particular process during <lb/>bone healing (40). Herein, we provided the evidence for the <lb/>first time that MBL could inhibit RANKL-mediated osteoclast <lb/>differentiation, which strongly expanded our understanding of <lb/>the pathogenesis of inflammatory arthritis in patients with MBL <lb/>deficiency. Indeed, our and others&apos; previous reports showed that <lb/>MBL could modulate the differentiation and function of innate <lb/>immune cells (i.e., DCs, monocytes, T cells, and mesenchymal <lb/>cells) in different contexts (14-16, 41, 42). It could be concluded <lb/>that MBL balancing the differentiation and function of innate <lb/>immune cells plays an essential role in the maintenance of <lb/>tissue homeostasis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<body>The earlier studies have shown that activation of the <lb/>p38-mediated pathway is indispensable during the osteoclast <lb/>formation and pharmacological inhibition of p38 activation <lb/>severely blunts osteoclastogenesis (43, 44). Importantly, p38 <lb/>has been reported to be crucial for the induction of c-fos and <lb/>NFATc1 during RANKL-induced osteoclast formation (25). In <lb/>the present study, we investigated the role of the p38 signaling <lb/>pathway in RANKL-treated precursors in the presence of MBL <lb/>protein, and have demonstrated that MBL has an inhibitory <lb/>effect on osteoclast differentiation via downregulation of the <lb/>p38/c-fos/NFATc1 signaling pathways. The result is consistent <lb/>with several other observations showing that the regulation <lb/>of monocytes activation and macrophage polarization by MBL <lb/>under the inflammatory condition was associated with repression <lb/>of p38 signaling pathway (45, 46). <lb/>Several previous studies reported that the MBL serum levels <lb/>are significantly reduced in RA patients compared to HC controls <lb/>(11, 12, 47, 48). A high fraction of RA patients lacked detectable <lb/>MBL in serum in a long term prospective study, indicating that <lb/>MBL insufficiency might be a contributing pathogenic factor in <lb/>RA (48). Low serum MBL was associated with raised RF levels, <lb/>which therefore could predict poor prognosis in patients with <lb/>early RA (11). A study about southern Chinese patients with <lb/>RA determined that a low serum MBL level predisposes to the <lb/>development of RA and is a risk factor for the development <lb/>of erosive arthritis (12). Another Brazilian study found that <lb/>circulating serum MBL levels are significantly lower in RA <lb/>patients compared to their relatives and controls (47). In contrast, <lb/>a study done by Saevarsdottir et al. (49) in Iceland showed that <lb/>patients with RA had strongly higher MBL levels than their close <lb/>relatives and unrelated controls. Conflicting reports on serum <lb/>MBL level and the risk of RA may, at least partially, be attributed <lb/>to the differences in patient cohorts. It is noteworthy that MBL <lb/>is an acute-phase protein which may transiently increase during <lb/>inflammatory responses. Indeed, a high serum level of MBL <lb/>was found to confer an increased risk of overall death and <lb/>cardiovascular death in RA patients indicating a dual function <lb/>of MBL in this rheumatic disease (50). <lb/>In summary, we demonstrate that MBL deficiency exacerbates <lb/>AIA through promoting osteoclast differentiation. Importantly, <lb/>our work elucidates an unknown feature of MBL function in <lb/>osteoclastogenesis, indicating the association of MBL with bone-<lb/>related diseases. Our study reveals a new mechanism underlying <lb/>the pathogenesis of inflammatory arthritis in patients with MBL <lb/>deficiency and implicates that supplement of MBL may represent <lb/>a new strategy for the treatment of arthritis, especially in patients <lb/>with MBL deficiency. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this manuscript will <lb/>be made available by the authors, without undue reservation, to <lb/>any qualified researcher. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">ETHICS STATEMENT <lb/>The study was reviewed and approved by the Medical Ethics <lb/>Committee of Southern Medical University. Before the collection <lb/>of the blood sample, informed consent for taking part in <lb/>the study was obtained from each participant. All animal <lb/>experiments in this study were approved by the Welfare and <lb/>Ethical Committee for Experimental Animal Care of Southern <lb/>Medical University. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>DZ, ZC, and LD designed research. LD, JW, KC, AY, JX, YW, <lb/>DL, YZ, and YH performed experiments. LD, YL, JZ, LZ and DZ <lb/>analyzed data. DZ, ZC, and LD wrote the manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>This work was supported in part by National Natural <lb/>Science Foundation of China (grant nos.: 81671568, 81873872, <lb/>81571608, and 81771771), Science and Technology Planning <lb/>Project of Guangdong Province (grant no.: 2016A020215106), <lb/>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province (grant <lb/>no.: 2016A030313537 and 2017A030313542), Open Project of <lb/>Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Proteomics (grant <lb/>no.: P201801). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found <lb/>online at: https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu. <lb/>2019.01239/full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Sato K, Takayanagi H. Osteoclasts, rheumatoid arthritis, and <lb/>osteoimmunology. <lb/>Curr <lb/>Opin <lb/>Rheumatol. <lb/>(2006) <lb/>18:419-<lb/>26. doi: 10.1097/01.bor.0000231912.24740.a5 <lb/>2. Feng X, Teitelbaum SL. Osteoclasts: new insights. Bone Res. (2013) 1:11-<lb/>26. doi: 10.4248/BR201301003 <lb/>3. Kim JH, Kim N. Regulation of NFATc1 in osteoclast differentiation. J Bone <lb/>Metab. (2014) 21:233-41. doi: 10.11005/jbm.2014.21.4.233 <lb/>4. Zhao Q, Shao J, Chen W, Li YP. Osteoclast differentiation and gene regulation. <lb/>Front Biosci. (2007) 12:2519-29. doi: 10.2741/2252 <lb/>5. Kim K, Kim JH, Lee J, Jin HM, Lee SH, Fisher DE, et al. Nuclear <lb/>factor of activated T cells c1 induces osteoclast-associated receptor <lb/>gene expression during tumor necrosis factor-related activation-induced <lb/>cytokine-mediated osteoclastogenesis. J Biol Chem. (2005) 280:35209-<lb/>16. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M505815200 <lb/>6. Takayanagi H, Kim S, Koga T, Nishina H, Isshiki M, Yoshida H, et al. <lb/>Induction and activation of the transcription factor NFATc1 (NFAT2) <lb/>integrate RANKL signaling in terminal differentiation of osteoclasts. Dev Cell. <lb/>(2002) 3:889-901. doi: 10.1016/S1534-5807(02)00369-6 <lb/>7. Gadjeva M, Takahashi K, Thiel S. Mannan-binding lectin-<lb/>a soluble pattern recognition molecule. Mol Immunol. (2004) <lb/>41:113-21. doi: 10.1016/j.molimm.2004.03.015 <lb/>8. Takahashi K, Ezekowitz RA. The role of the mannose-binding lectin in <lb/>innate immunity. Clin Infect Dis. (2005) 41 (Suppl. 7):S440-4. doi: 10. <lb/>1086/431987 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>9. Ip WK, Takahashi K, Ezekowitz RA, Stuart LM. Mannose-<lb/>binding lectin and innate immunity. Immunol Rev. (2009) <lb/>230:9-21. doi: 10.1111/j.1600-065X.2009.00789.x <lb/>10. Takahashi K. Mannose-binding lectin and the balance between immune <lb/>protection and complication. Expert Rev Anti-Infect Ther. (2011) 9:1179-<lb/>90. doi: 10.1586/eri.11.136 <lb/>11. Saevarsdottir S, Vikingsdottir T, Vikingsson A, Manfredsdottir V, <lb/>Geirsson AJ, Valdimarsson H. Low mannose binding lectin predicts <lb/>poor prognosis in patients with early rheumatoid arthritis. A <lb/>prospective study. J Rheumatol. (2001) 28:728-34. Available online at: <lb/>http://www.jrheum.org/content/28/4/728 <lb/>12. Ip WK, Lau YL, Chan SY, Mok CC, Chan D, Tong KK, et al. Mannose-binding <lb/>lectin and rheumatoid arthritis in southern Chinese. Arthritis Rheumat. <lb/>(2000) 43:1679-87. doi: 10.1002/1529-0131(200008)43:8&lt;1679::aid-anr3&gt;3.3. <lb/>co;2-4 <lb/>13. Dolman KM, Brouwer N, Frakking FN, Flato B, Tak PP, Kuijpers TW, <lb/>et al. Mannose-binding lectin deficiency is associated with early onset of <lb/>polyarticular juvenile rheumatoid arthritis: a cohort study. Arthritis Res Ther. <lb/>(2008) 10:R32. doi: 10.1186/ar2386 <lb/>14. Xu XY, Li HJ, Zhang LY, Lu X, Zuo DM, Shan GQ, et al. Mannan-<lb/>binding lectin at supraphysiological concentrations inhibits differentiation of <lb/>dendritic cells from human CD14 + monocytes. Microbiol Immunol. (2015) <lb/>59:724-34. doi: 10.1111/1348-0421.12337 <lb/>15. Wang M, Zhang Y, Chen Y, Zhang L, Lu X, Chen Z. Mannan-binding <lb/>lectin regulates dendritic cell maturation and cytokine production induced by <lb/>lipopolysaccharide. BMC Immunol. (2011) 12:1. doi: 10.1186/1471-2172-12-1 <lb/>16. Wang Y, Chen AD, Lei YM, Shan GQ, Zhang LY, Lu X, et al. Mannose-<lb/>binding lectin inhibits monocyte proliferation through transforming <lb/>growth factor-beta1 and p38 signaling pathways. PLoS ONE. (2013) <lb/>8:e72505. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0072505 <lb/>17. Fraser DA, Bohlson SS, Jasinskiene N, Rawal N, Palmarini G, Ruiz <lb/>S, et al. C1q and MBL, components of the innate immune system, <lb/>influence monocyte cytokine expression. J Leukocyte Biol. (2006) 80:107-<lb/>16. doi: 10.1189/jlb.1105683 <lb/>18. Knight B, Katz DR, Isenberg DA, Ibrahim MA, Le Page S, Hutchings P, <lb/>et al. Induction of adjuvant arthritis in mice. Clin Exp Immunol. (1992) <lb/>90:459-65. doi: 10.1111/j.1365-2249.1992.tb05868.x <lb/>19. Alves CH, Farrell E, Vis M, Colin EM, Lubberts E. Animal models of bone loss <lb/>in inflammatory arthritis: from cytokines in the bench to novel treatments for <lb/>bone loss in the bedside-a comprehensive review. Clin Rev Allergy Immunol. <lb/>(2016) 51:27-47. doi: 10.1007/s12016-015-8522-7 <lb/>20. Schett G, Stolina M, Bolon B, Middleton S, Adlam M, Brown H, et al. Analysis <lb/>of the kinetics of osteoclastogenesis in arthritic rats. Arthritis Rheumat. (2005) <lb/>52:3192-201. doi: 10.1002/art.21343 <lb/>21. Hirayama T, Danks L, Sabokbar A, Athanasou NA. Osteoclast formation <lb/>and activity in the pathogenesis of osteoporosis in rheumatoid arthritis. <lb/>Rheumatology. (2002) 41:1232-9. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/41.11.1232 <lb/>22. Saftig P, Hunziker E, Everts V, Jones S, Boyde A, Wehmeyer O, et al. Functions <lb/>of cathepsin K in bone resorption. Lessons from cathepsin K deficient mice. <lb/>Adv Exp Med Biol. (2000) 477:293-303. doi: 10.1007/0-306-46826-3_32 <lb/>23. Udagawa N, Takahashi N, Yasuda H, Mizuno A, Itoh K, Ueno Y, et al. <lb/>Osteoprotegerin produced by osteoblasts is an important regulator in <lb/>osteoclast development and function. Endocrinology. (2000) 141:3478-<lb/>84. doi: 10.1210/endo.141.9.7634 <lb/>24. Abe E, Yamamoto M, Taguchi Y, Lecka-Czernik B, O&apos;Brien CA, Economides <lb/>AN, et al. Essential requirement of BMPs-2/4 for both osteoblast <lb/>and osteoclast formation in murine bone marrow cultures from adult <lb/>mice: antagonism by noggin. J Bone Mineral Res. (2000) 15:663-<lb/>73. doi: 10.1359/jbmr.2000.15.4.663 <lb/>25. Huang H, Chang EJ, Ryu J, Lee ZH, Lee Y, Kim HH. Induction of c-Fos and <lb/>NFATc1 during RANKL-stimulated osteoclast differentiation is mediated by <lb/>the p38 signaling pathway. Biochem Biophys Res Commun. (2006) 351:99-<lb/>105. doi: 10.1016/j.bbrc.2006.10.011 <lb/>26. Itoh T, Matsuda H, Tanioka M, Kuwabara K, Itohara S, <lb/>Suzuki R. The role of matrix metalloproteinase-2 and matrix <lb/>metalloproteinase-9 in antibody-induced arthritis. J Immunol. (2002) <lb/>169:2643-7. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.169.5.2643 <lb/>27. Reponen P, Sahlberg C, Munaut C, Thesleff I, Tryggvason K. High <lb/>expression of 92-kD type IV collagenase (gelatinase B) in the <lb/>osteoclast lineage during mouse development. J Cell Biol. (1994) <lb/>124:1091-102. doi: 10.1083/jcb.124.6.1091 <lb/>28. Kotani T, Takeuchi T, Takai S, Yoshida S, Hata K, Nagai K, et al. Serum levels of <lb/>matrix metalloproteinase (MMP) 9, a risk factor for acute coronary syndrome, <lb/>are reduced independently of serum MMP-3 by anti-TNF-alpha antibody <lb/>(infliximab) therapy in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. J Pharmacol Sci. <lb/>(2012) 120:50-3. doi: 10.1254/jphs.12129SC <lb/>29. Lee K, Seo I, Choi MH, Jeong D. Roles of mitogen-activated protein kinases in <lb/>osteoclast biology. Int J Mol Sci. (2018) 19:E3004. doi: 10.3390/ijms19103004 <lb/>30. Li X, Udagawa N, Itoh K, Suda K, Murase Y, Nishihara T, et al. <lb/>p38 MAPK-mediated signals are required for inducing osteoclast <lb/>differentiation but not for osteoclast function. Endocrinology. (2002) <lb/>143:3105-13. doi: 10.1210/endo.143.8.8954 <lb/>31. Nisihara R, Skare T, Capeletto CM, Moreira L, Goeldner I, Messias-<lb/>Reason I, et al. Mannose binding lectin deficiency and susceptibility to <lb/>infections in patients with rheumatoid arthritis. Rheumatology. (2016) 55:951-<lb/>2. doi: 10.1093/rheumatology/kev413 <lb/>32. Pap T, Korb-Pap A. Cartilage damage in osteoarthritis and <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis-two unequal siblings. Nat Rev Rheumatol. (2015) <lb/>11:606-15. doi: 10.1038/nrrheum.2015.95 <lb/>33. Wang Q, Rozelle AL, Lepus CM, Scanzello CR, Song JJ, Larsen DM, et al. <lb/>Identification of a central role for complement in osteoarthritis. Nat Med. <lb/>(2011) 17:1674-9. doi: 10.1038/nm.2543 <lb/>34. Hietala MA, Jonsson IM, Tarkowski A, Kleinau S, Pekna M. Complement <lb/>deficiency ameliorates collagen-induced arthritis in mice. J Immunol. (2002) <lb/>169:454-9. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.169.1.454 <lb/>35. Ames RS, Lee D, Foley JJ, Jurewicz AJ, Tornetta MA, Bautsch W, et al. <lb/>Identification of a selective nonpeptide antagonist of the anaphylatoxin C3a <lb/>receptor that demonstrates antiinflammatory activity in animal models. J <lb/>Immunol. (2001) 166:6341-8. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.166.10.6341 <lb/>36. Woodruff TM, Strachan AJ, Dryburgh N, Shiels IA, Reid RC, Fairlie DP, <lb/>et al. Antiarthritic activity of an orally active C5a receptor antagonist against <lb/>antigen-induced monarticular arthritis in the rat. Arthritis Rheumat. (2002) <lb/>46:2476-85. doi: 10.1002/art.10449 <lb/>37. Wang Y, Rollins SA, Madri JA, Matis LA. Anti-C5 monoclonal <lb/>antibody therapy prevents collagen-induced arthritis and ameliorates <lb/>established disease. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA. (1995) 92:8955-<lb/>9. doi: 10.1073/pnas.92.19.8955 <lb/>38. Karmakar S, Kay J, Gravallese EM. Bone damage in rheumatoid <lb/>arthritis: mechanistic insights and approaches to prevention. Rheum <lb/>Dis Clin North Am. (2010) 36:385-404. doi: 10.1016/j.rdc.201 <lb/>0.03.003 <lb/>39. Sivagurunathan S, Pagel CN, Loh LH, Wijeyewickrema LC, Pike RN, Mackie <lb/>EJ. Thrombin inhibits osteoclast differentiation through a non-proteolytic <lb/>mechanism. J Mol Endocrinol. (2013) 50:347-59. doi: 10.1530/JME-12-0177 <lb/>40. Van der Ende J, Van Baardewijk LJ, Sier CF, Schipper IB. <lb/>Bone healing and mannose-binding lectin. Int J Surg. (2013) <lb/>11:296-300. doi: 10.1016/j.ijsu.2013.02.022 <lb/>41. Bajaj M, Hinge A, Limaye LS, Gupta RK, Surolia A, Kale VP. Mannose-<lb/>binding dietary lectins induce adipogenic differentiation of the marrow-<lb/>derived mesenchymal cells via an active insulin-like signaling mechanism. <lb/>Glycobiology. (2011) 21:521-9. doi: 10.1093/glycob/cwq194 <lb/>42. Zhao N, Wu J, Xiong S, Zhang L, Lu X, Chen S, et al. Mannan-binding lectin, <lb/>a serum collectin, suppresses T-cell proliferation via direct interaction with <lb/>cell surface calreticulin and inhibition of proximal T-cell receptor signaling. <lb/>FASEB J. (2017) 31:2405-17. doi: 10.1096/fj.201601200RR <lb/>43. Matsumoto M, Sudo T, Saito T, Osada H, Tsujimoto M. Involvement of <lb/>p38 mitogen-activated protein kinase signaling pathway in osteoclastogenesis <lb/>mediated by receptor activator of NF-kappa B ligand (RANKL). J Biol Chem. <lb/>(2000) 275:31155-61. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M001229200 <lb/>44. Li X, Udagawa N, Takami M, Sato N, Kobayashi Y, Takahashi N. <lb/>p38 Mitogen-activated protein kinase is crucially involved in osteoclast <lb/>differentiation but not in cytokine production, phagocytosis, or dendritic <lb/>cell differentiation of bone marrow macrophages. Endocrinology. (2003) <lb/>144:4999-5005. doi: 10.1210/en.2003-0166 <lb/>45. Wang F, Li Y, Yang C, Mu Y, Wang Y, Zhang W, et al. <lb/>Mannan-binding <lb/>lectin <lb/>suppresses <lb/>peptidoglycan-induced <lb/>TLR2 <lb/>activation and inflammatory responses. Mediators Inflamm. (2019) <lb/>2019:1349784. doi: 10.1155/2019/1349784 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Dong et al. <lb/>MBL Inhibits Osteoclastogenesis <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>46. Cai Y, Zhang W, Xiong S. Mannose-binding lectin blunts macrophage <lb/>polarization and ameliorates lupus nephritis. PLoS ONE. (2013) <lb/>8:e62465. doi: 10.1371/journal.pone.0062465 <lb/>47. Goeldner I, Skare TL, Utiyama SR, Nisihara RM, Tong <lb/>H, Messias-Reason IJ, et al. Mannose binding lectin and <lb/>susceptibility to rheumatoid arthritis in Brazilian patients and <lb/>their relatives. PLoS ONE. (2014) 9:e95519. doi: 10.1371/journal. <lb/>pone.0095519 <lb/>48. Graudal NA, Homann C, Madsen HO, Svejgaard A, Jurik AG, Graudal HK, <lb/>et al. Mannan binding lectin in rheumatoid arthritis. A longitudinal study. J <lb/>Rheumatol. (1998) 25:629-35. <lb/>49. Saevarsdottir S, Steinsson K, Grondal G, Valdimarsson H. Patients with <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis have higher levels of mannan-binding lectin <lb/>than their first-degree relatives and unrelated controls. J Rheumatol. <lb/>(2007) 34:1692-5. Available online at: http://www.jrheum.org/content/34 <lb/>/8/1692 <lb/>50. Troelsen LN, Garred P, Jacobsen S. Mortality and predictors of mortality in <lb/>rheumatoid arthritis-a role for mannose-binding lectin? J Rheumatol. (2010) <lb/>37:536-43. doi: 10.3899/jrheum.090812 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest Statement: The authors declare that the research was <lb/>conducted in the absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could <lb/>be construed as a potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<front>Copyright © 2019 Dong, Wu, Chen, Xie, Wang, Li, Liu, Yin, Zhao, Han, Zhou, <lb/>Zhang, Chen and Zuo. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms <lb/>of the Creative Commons Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution <lb/>or reproduction in other forums is permitted, provided the original author(s) <lb/>and the copyright owner(s) are credited and that the original publication in <lb/>this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted academic practice. No use, <lb/>distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not comply with these <lb/>terms. <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">June 2019 | Volume 10 | Article 1239 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
