<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Molecules 2013, 18, 9582-9593; doi:10.3390/molecules18089582 <lb/>molecules <lb/>ISSN 1420-3049 <lb/>www.mdpi.com/journal/molecules <lb/>Article <lb/>Evaluation of the Effect of Different Growth Media and <lb/>Temperature on the Suitability of Biofilm Formation by <lb/>Enterobacter cloacae Strains Isolated from Food Samples in <lb/>South Africa <lb/>Mirriam E. Nyenje 1 , Ezekiel Green 1 and Roland N. Ndip 1,2, * <lb/>1 Department of Biochemistry and Microbiology, Faculty of Science and Agriculture, <lb/>University of Fort Hare, PMB X1314, Alice 5700, South Africa; <lb/>E-Mails: nyenjem@yahoo.com (M.E.N.); egreen@ufh.ac.za (E.G.) <lb/>Department of Microbiology and Parasitology, Faculty of Science, University of Buea, Box 63, <lb/>Buea, Cameroon <lb/>* Author to whom correspondence should be addressed; E-Mail: rndip@ufh.ac.za or <lb/>ndip3@yahoo.com; Tel.: +27-782696191; Fax: +27-86624759. <lb/>Received: 20 May 2013; in revised form: 22 July 2013 / Accepted: 23 July 2013 / <lb/>Published: 9 August 2013 <lb/>Abstract: This study evaluated the effects of growth medium, temperature, and incubation <lb/>time on biofilm formation by Enterobacter cloacae strains. The ability to adhere to a <lb/>surface was demonstrated using a microtiter plate adherence assay whereas the role of cell <lb/>surface properties in biofilm formation was assessed using the coaggregation and <lb/>autoaggregation assays. The architecture of the biofilms was examined under scanning <lb/>electron microscope (SEM). All the strains adhered to the well of the microtiter plate when <lb/>incubated for 48 h, irrespective of the growth medium and incubation temperature. It was <lb/>also noted that 90% and 73% of strains prepared from nutrient broth and cultured in brain <lb/>heart infusion (BHI) broth and tryptic soy broth (TSB), respectively, were able to form <lb/>biofilms, in contrast to 73% and 60% strains from nutrient agar and cultured in BHI and <lb/>TSB respectively grown under similar conditions. However, no statistically significant <lb/>difference was observed when the two methods were compared. The coaggregation index <lb/>ranged from 12% to 74%, with the best coaggregate activity observed when partnered with <lb/>Streptococcus pyogenes (54%-74%). The study indicates the suitability of BHI and TSB <lb/>medium for the cultivation of E. cloacae biofilms, however, temperature and incubation <lb/>time significantly affect biofilm formation by these bacteria. <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/> Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/>9583 <lb/> Keywords: Enterobacter cloacae; biofilm; growth medium; coaggregation; <lb/>autoaggregation; temperature <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>E. cloacae, a Gram negative bacterium, belongs to the family Enterobacteriaceae. The bacterium <lb/>comprises part of the normal flora of the gastrointestinal tract of 40%-80% of the human population <lb/>and is widely distributed in the environment [1]. The organism has also been isolated from food <lb/>processing plants, fresh vegetables, rice, meat and meat products [2-4]. E. cloacae are capable of <lb/>causing opportunistic infections including pneumonia, urinary tract, wound, skin and soft tissue, <lb/>ophthalmic and bloodstream infections, particularly catheter-related where it has been reported to form <lb/>biofilms in dwelling catheters of hospital patients [5,6]. <lb/>Biofilms are defined as matrix-enclosed bacterial populations, which adhere to each other and to <lb/>surfaces; observations have conclusively shown that biofilm bacteria predominate numerically and <lb/>metabolically, in virtually all ecosystems and are difficult to eliminate [7]. Bacterial biofilms are <lb/>known to be linked to medical conditions such as cystic fibrosis, periodontitis, and nosocomial <lb/>infections from the use of catheters and prosthetic heart valves [8]. However, biofilm formation in food <lb/>processing plants has also been documented; both pathogenic and food spoilage microorganisms have <lb/>been isolated from such bacterial communities [9]. <lb/>It is well known that bacteria, including foodborne pathogens grow predominantly as biofilms in <lb/>most of their natural habitats, but also in food processing, catering and the domestic environment [10]. <lb/>Biofilms may generate a persistent source of contamination, leading to serious hygienic problems and <lb/>also economic losses due to food spoilage [11]. Poor sanitation of food-contact surfaces is believed to <lb/>be an essential contributing factor of foodborne disease and development of bacterial biofilms. The <lb/>formed biofilms are a source of cross contamination as cells will continuously detach and contaminate <lb/>food once it passes over contaminated surfaces or through aerosols originating from contaminated <lb/>equipment. This may seriously affect the quality and safety of the processed food and pose a potential <lb/>risk to the consumer [12]. <lb/>E. cloacae and other species of Enterobacter have been reported to cause foodborne illnesses <lb/>through consumption of a variety of foods, including infant foods [2]. In our recent study, E. cloacae <lb/>was reported to be the second most prevalent organism from ready-to-eat foods [4]; implying that the <lb/>organism might be one of the emerging foodborne pathogens that can be endemic in food processing <lb/>environments. Studies on the ability of E. cloacae to form biofilms have focused mostly on clinical <lb/>isolates [13,14] where authors have hypothesized that their ability to persist in these environments as <lb/>well as their virulence, is a result of their capacity to colonize medical devices [14]. However, in the <lb/>food industry, studies have demonstrated the ability of Cronobacter sakazakii to adhere to feeding <lb/>bottles, feeding tubes and other food processing surfaces with sparse information on E. cloacae. <lb/>Modern food processing supports and selects for biofilm forming bacteria on food-contact surfaces due <lb/>to mass production, lengthy production cycles and vast surface areas for biofilm development [15]. <lb/>Biofilm formation depends on an interaction between three main components: the bacterial cells, the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9584 <lb/></page>

			<body>attachment surface and the surrounding medium [16]. However, environmental factors such as pH, <lb/>temperature, osmolarity, O 2 levels, nutrient composition and the presence of other bacteria also play <lb/>important roles [17,18]. The integration of these influences ultimately determines the pattern and <lb/>behavior of a given bacterium with respect to biofilm development [19]. Hence, biofilms are very <lb/>diverse and unique, not just to the microorganism, but to the particular environment in which they are <lb/>being formed. This makes in vitro characterization of biofilms difficult and requires the establishment <lb/>of laboratory conditions that mimic the natural setting being studied. The ability of these organisms to <lb/>form biofilms at ambient temperature (25 °C), which is mostly room temperature in tropical countries, <lb/>implies that under favorable conditions, they may be able to adhere to kitchen utensils and other <lb/>environments leading to cross-contamination of food processed in these areas. Therefore the present <lb/>study aimed to determine the effects of temperature, nutrient content and incubation time on <lb/>attachment and biofilm formation by E. cloacae strains at ambient (25 °C) and body (37 °C) <lb/>temperature in BHI and TSB media; in an effort to ascertain the suitable biofilm growth conditions for <lb/>this bacterium as a guide to its containment in the food industry. BHI was chosen as one of the <lb/>nutrient-rich laboratory medium, and TSB a less-rich (compared to BHI) culture medium which are <lb/>frequently used in biofilm investigation. <lb/>2. Results and Discussion <lb/>2.1. Microtiter Adherence <lb/>Tests were performed in triplicates on three occasions, the results averaged and standard deviations <lb/>were calculated. The cut-off was defined as three standard deviations above the mean OD of the <lb/>negative control (ODc) which contained broth only. The following criteria were used to classify the <lb/>different adherent strength: OD ≤ OD C = non-adherent, OD C &lt; OD ≤ (2 × OD C ) = weakly adherent; <lb/>(2 × OD C ) &lt; OD ≤ (4 × OD C ) = moderately adherent and (4 × OD C ) &lt; OD = strongly adherent [20]. <lb/>E. cloacae isolates displayed four different biofilm phenotypes (non, weak, moderate and strong <lb/>adherent) after incubation for 24 h in both BHI and TSB (Table 1). The optical density (OD) of non <lb/>adherent (NA), weak adherent (WA), moderate adherent (MA) and strong adherent (SA) obtained <lb/>when the bacteria were grown in BHI ranged from 0.359-0.486, 0.552-1.159, 1.092-2.14 and <lb/>2.192-4.22 respectively. On the other hand, the OD obtained when the bacteria were grown in TSB <lb/>ranged from 0.352-0.618, 0.62-1.583, 1.25-2.414 and 2.542-3.938 for NA, WA, MA and SA <lb/>respectively (Table 2). It was observed that all the strains (100%) adhered to the well of the microtiter <lb/>plate when incubated for 48 h, irrespective of the growth medium (BHI or TSB) and incubation <lb/>temperature (Table 1). On the other hand, adherence ability was demonstrated by 73% (22) and 60% <lb/>(18) of the strains obtained from inoculums prepared in nutrient agar and grown in BHI and TSB <lb/>respectively, compared to 90% (27) and 73% (22) prepared in nutrient broth grown in BHI and TSB <lb/>respectively, when the plates were incubated at 25 °C for 24 h (Table 1). All the strains (100%) from <lb/>nutrient agar cultures grown in BHI were able to form biofilm when incubated at 37 °C for 24 h <lb/>compared to 28 (93%) from nutrient broth grown in BHI; no difference was noted from TSB cultures, <lb/>as 93% of the strains from both nutrient agar and broth formed biofilm (Table 1). However, no <lb/>statistical significance (p-value &gt; 0.05) was observed when the two methods (agar and broth) were <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9585 <lb/></page>

			<body>compared; thus it can be suggested that E. cloacae strains for biofilm formation assays may be <lb/>cultivated either in broth or on solid medium. <lb/>Worthy of note is the fact that infecting bacteria are often surface-associated, and their cell surface <lb/>can therefore be expected to be more similar to that of bacteria grown on solid medium than to that <lb/>found grown in liquid media [13]. Bacterial cells grown on solid medium differ in expression of <lb/>cell-associated molecules compared to those grown in liquid medium [20,21]. Probably the presence of <lb/>slime layers that are regarded as soft polyelectrolyte layers surrounding the bacteria decreases the <lb/>energy barrier due to electrostatic repulsion in the interaction of the organisms with negatively charged <lb/>substrata and, thus, plays an important role in their adhesion [21]. In their study, Kiers et al. [21] found <lb/>that cell surface softness of Staphylococcus epidermidis first grown on agar medium increased by a <lb/>factor of two, compared to the cell surface softness for the strains grown in liquid medium. Therefore, <lb/>preparation of the inoculum from broth or agar may directly influence the biofilm production, since <lb/>adhesion is the first step in biofilm formation. <lb/>It was also noted that a good number of strains grown in nutrient broth, 90% and 73% cultured in <lb/>BHI and TSB respectively were able to form biofilm, in contrast to 73% and 60% strains prepared <lb/>from agar grown under similar conditions. However, no statistical significance was observed <lb/>(p &gt; 0.005) when the two methods were compared. <lb/>Composition of the medium has been documented to influence the ability of bacteria to produce <lb/>biofilm under in vitro conditions; in particular the presence of glucose in the growth medium <lb/>(i.e., standard TSB medium commonly contains 0.25% glucose) has been reported to enhance biofilm <lb/>formation [22]. Some studies have shown preference for BHI to TSB, although some strains of <lb/>Staphylococcus, Vibrio and Pseudomonas species have been reported to produce greater biofilm <lb/>quantities in TSB while others do so in BHI [22,23]. The present study compared the two growth <lb/>media and observed no statistical significance (p &gt; 0.005). However, a slightly higher number of <lb/>E. cloacae strains grown on BHI demonstrated the ability to adhere to the wells of the microtitre plate, <lb/>implying that although both BHI and TSB media could support the development of E. cloacae biofilms <lb/>in vitro, some strains will produce strong biofilms on BHI than TSB. These findings are in agreement <lb/>with other studies [17,24], which found that supplementation (enriching) of TSB medium with glucose <lb/>increased the ability of Staphylococci to form biofilms, while Knobloch et al. [25] recommended the <lb/>use of the two media to confirm a biofilm positive isolate. <lb/>All (100%) of the E. cloacae strains demonstrated adherence characteristics at the low temperature <lb/>of 25 °C when incubated for 48 h in comparison to the range of 60%-90% of the strains that had <lb/>the same characteristics when incubated for 24 h only; the range increased with high temperatures <lb/>(37 °C) where 93%-100% of the strains demonstrated the adherence ability when incubated for 24 h <lb/>(Table 1). Statistical significant adherence was observed (p &lt; 0.005) when the two incubation periods <lb/>were compared, which may imply that long incubation times and high temperatures influence <lb/>biofilm formation. <lb/>Previous works have indicated that temperature, nutrients and other components in media affect <lb/>attachment of microorganisms to surfaces of various materials [26,27]. The present study observed <lb/>strong biofilms from plates incubated at 37 °C (Table 1). This could be attributed to the fast growth <lb/>rate of the bacteria at higher temperatures [23]. Similarly, Iversen et al. [27] reported strong adherence <lb/>of their test bacteria at high temperatures (&gt;40 °C). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9586 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. The effects of temperature, incubation time and growth medium on the biofilm formation of E. cloacae isolates. <lb/>B. <lb/>phenotype <lb/>Parameters number (%) <lb/>BHI a <lb/>TSB a <lb/>BHI b <lb/>TSB b <lb/>24 h <lb/>48 h <lb/>24 h <lb/>48 h <lb/>24 h <lb/>48 h <lb/>24 h <lb/>48 h <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>25 °C <lb/>37 °C <lb/>NA <lb/>8(27) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>12(40) <lb/>2(7) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>3(10) <lb/>2(7) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>8(27) <lb/>2(7) <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>WA <lb/>18(60) <lb/>10(33) <lb/>10(33) <lb/>5(17) <lb/>14 (47) <lb/>17(57) <lb/>18(60) <lb/>4(13) <lb/>20(67) <lb/>11(37) <lb/>12(40) <lb/>4(13) <lb/>19(63) <lb/>14(47) <lb/>6(20) <lb/>2(7) <lb/>MA <lb/>4(13) <lb/>18(60) <lb/>16(53) <lb/>0 <lb/>4 (13) <lb/>10(33) <lb/>11(37) <lb/>10(33) <lb/>7(23) <lb/>14(47) <lb/>15(50) <lb/>9 (30) <lb/>3 (10) <lb/>11(37) <lb/>16(53) <lb/>11(37) <lb/>SA <lb/>0 <lb/>2(7) <lb/>4(13) <lb/>25(83) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 (3) <lb/>1 (3) <lb/>16(53) <lb/>0 <lb/>3(10) <lb/>3(10) <lb/>17(57) <lb/>0 <lb/>3(10) <lb/>8(27) <lb/>17(57) <lb/>T. adh. <lb/>(%) <lb/>22 <lb/>(73) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>18 <lb/>(60) <lb/>28 <lb/>(93) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>27 <lb/>(90) <lb/>28 <lb/>(93) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>22 <lb/>(73) <lb/>28 <lb/>(93) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>30 <lb/>(100) <lb/>BHI, brain heart infusion broth; TSB, tryptic soya broth; NA, non adherent; WA, weak adherent; MA, moderate adherent; SA, strong adherent; T. dh., total adherent; B. phenotype, biofilm <lb/>phenotype; BHI a , colonies from Nutrient agar and grown in BHI broth; TSB a , colonies from Nutrient agar and grown in TS broth; BHI b , inoculums from Nutrient broth and grown in BHI; <lb/>TSB b , inoculums from Nutrient broth and grown in TSB. <lb/>Table 2. The mean optical densities and standard deviations of the different biofilm phenotypes. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Biofilm formation <lb/>Non-adherent <lb/>Weakly adherent <lb/>Moderately adherent <lb/>Strongly adherent <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>25 °C BHI (24 h) a <lb/>0.448-0.486 <lb/>0 0.470 ± 0.02 <lb/>0.572-0.990 <lb/>0.733 ± 0.13 <lb/>1.30-2.14 <lb/>1.406 ± 0.15 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>°C BHI (48 h) a <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.611-1.06 <lb/>0.875 ± 0.13 <lb/>1.12-2.01 <lb/>1.344 ± 0.25 <lb/>2.192-2.769 <lb/>2.543 ± 0.39 <lb/>25 °C TSB (24 h) a <lb/>0.352-0.618 <lb/>0.512 ± 0.08 <lb/>0.626-1.131 <lb/>0.785 ± 0.15 <lb/>1.365-1.458 <lb/>1.405 ± 0.07 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>25 °C TSB (48 h) a <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.625-1.237 <lb/>0.984 ± 0.18 <lb/>1.625-1.789 <lb/>1.507 ± 0.231 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>37 °C BHI (24 h) a <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.590-1.074 <lb/>0.885 ± 0.12 <lb/>1.164-2.022 <lb/>1.504 ± 0.34 <lb/>2.224-3.327 <lb/>2.775 ± 0.77 <lb/>37 °C BHI (48 h) a <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.580-0.784 <lb/>1.872 ± 0.32 <lb/>1.331-2.13 <lb/>1.872± 0.32 <lb/>2.35-4.22 <lb/>3.034 ± 0.62 <lb/>37 °C TSB (24 h) a <lb/>0.421-0.464 <lb/>0.442 ± 0.03 <lb/>0.662-1.081 <lb/>0.861 ± 0.169 <lb/>1.297-1.997 <lb/>1.591 ± 0.199 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>37 °C TSB (48 h) a <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.988-1.583 <lb/>1.483 ± 0.493 <lb/>1.93-2.485 <lb/>2.149 ± 0.190 <lb/>2.556-3.635 <lb/>2.955 ± 0.503 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9587 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 2. Cont. <lb/>Parameters <lb/>Biofilm formation <lb/>Non-adherent <lb/>Weakly adherent <lb/>Moderately adherent <lb/>Strongly adherent <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>OD range <lb/>Mean <lb/>OD ± SD <lb/>25 °C BHI (24 h) b <lb/>0.359-0.462 <lb/>0.420 ± 0.05 <lb/>0.565-1.083 <lb/>0.832 ± 0.14 <lb/>1.098-1.988 <lb/>1.509 ± 0.340 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>25 °C BHI (48 h) b <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.729-1.048 <lb/>0.855 ± 0.13 <lb/>1.436-2.144 <lb/>1.728 ± 0.584 <lb/>2.253-3.24 <lb/>2.660 ± 1.13 <lb/>37 °C BHI (24 h) b <lb/>0.44-0.481 <lb/>0.460 ± 0.02 <lb/>0.552-1.111 <lb/>0.803 ± 0.17 <lb/>1.123-2.039 <lb/>1.577 ± 0.36 <lb/>2.405-3.27 <lb/>2.837 ± 0.61 <lb/>37 °C BHI (48 h) b <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>1.01-1.159 <lb/>1.074 ± 0.06 <lb/>1.392-2.129 <lb/>1.697 ± 0.24 <lb/>2.247-3.805 <lb/>2.93 ± 0.546 <lb/>25 °C TSB (24 h) b <lb/>0.421-0.559 <lb/>0.508 ± 0.04 <lb/>0.62-1.117 <lb/>0.834 ± 0.16 <lb/>1.319-1.774 <lb/>1.548 ± 0.22 <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>25 °C TSB (48 h) b <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.711-1.066 <lb/>1.034 ± 0.18 <lb/>1.364-2.414 <lb/>1.706 ± 0.36 <lb/>2.568-3.382 <lb/>2.929 ± 0.36 <lb/>37 °C TSB (24 h) b <lb/>0.503-0.535 <lb/>0.519 ± 0.2 <lb/>0.623-1.153 <lb/>0.877 ± 0.2 <lb/>1.561-2.413 <lb/>1.802 ± 0.2 <lb/>2.542-2.66 <lb/>2.601 ± 0.08 <lb/>37 °C TSB (48 h) b <lb/>ND <lb/>ND <lb/>0.841-1.076 <lb/>0.958 ± 1.66 <lb/>1.25-2.19 <lb/>1.831 ± 0.54 <lb/>2.612-3.938 <lb/>3.261 ± 0.54 <lb/>OD, optical density; SD, standard deviation; ND, not determined; a , colonies from Nutrient agar; b , inoculums from Nutrient broth; BHI, brain heart infusion broth; <lb/>TSB, tryptic soy broth. <lb/>Table 3. Coaggregation indices of selected biofilm forming E. cloacae strains with seven different reference strains partners. <lb/>Isolate <lb/>(biofilm <lb/>phenotype) <lb/>%Autoagg. <lb/>Coaggregation indices (%) <lb/>Partner strains <lb/>Range % <lb/>S. aureus <lb/>NCTC 6571 <lb/>S. pyogenes A <lb/>ATCC 49399 <lb/>S. Typhimurium <lb/>ATCC 13311 <lb/>P. aeruginosa <lb/>ATCC 15442 <lb/>P. shigelloides <lb/>ATCC 51903 <lb/>A. hydrophila <lb/>ATCC 35654 <lb/>S. sonnei <lb/>ATCC 29930 <lb/>EC 52-2 (NA) <lb/>27 <lb/>55-66 <lb/>55 <lb/>66 <lb/>63 <lb/>55 <lb/>64 <lb/>61 <lb/>58 <lb/>EC 205 (NA) <lb/>38 <lb/>54-66 <lb/>54 <lb/>63 <lb/>66 <lb/>62 <lb/>62 <lb/>64 <lb/>61 <lb/>EC 12-2 (WA) <lb/>45 <lb/>56-69 <lb/>69 <lb/>69 <lb/>59 <lb/>56 <lb/>68 <lb/>69 <lb/>ND <lb/>EC 70-2 (MA) <lb/>89 <lb/>12-70 <lb/>57 <lb/>61 <lb/>29 <lb/>70 <lb/>12 <lb/>64 <lb/>56 <lb/>EC 89-2 (MA) <lb/>30 <lb/>31-62 <lb/>43 <lb/>54 <lb/>62 <lb/>40 <lb/>53 <lb/>31 <lb/>23 <lb/>EC 235 (WA) <lb/>34 <lb/>65-74 <lb/>68 <lb/>74 <lb/>74 <lb/>72 <lb/>72 <lb/>65 <lb/>69 <lb/>NA, non adherent; WA, weak adherent; MA, moderate adherent; Autoagg, autoaggregation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9588 <lb/></page>

			<body>Contrary to these findings were the observations by Di Bonaventura et al. [18] who reported a <lb/>higher biofilm production at a lower temperature (32 °C) than the higher temperatures of 37 °C; which <lb/>may further suggest that biofilm formation varies with temperature and organism. Hence from the <lb/>findings of the current study it can be deduced that E. cloacae strains will produce strong biofilms at <lb/>higher temperatures. <lb/>2.2. The Capability of E. cloacae Strains to Autoaggregate and Coaggregate with Partner Organisms <lb/>All E. cloacae strains were able to coaggregate with the seven partner strains; the coaggregation <lb/>index ranged from 12%-74% with best coaggregate activity observed when partnered with <lb/>Streptococcus pyogenes (54%-74%) (Table 3). It was also noted that most of the strains which weakly <lb/>adhered to the wells had a slightly higher coaggregation index range of 56%-74% followed by <lb/>moderate adherent 12%-70% and the least was non-adherent with 54%-66% (Table 3). Of particular <lb/>interest was a weakly adherent isolate, EC 235 which demonstrated the strongest coaggregation with <lb/>all the partners. On the other hand, all the strains were able to adhere to each other, with <lb/>autoaggregation range of 27%-89% (Table 3). <lb/>First recognized between bacterial isolates from human dental plague, coaggregation is the highly <lb/>specific recognition and adhesion of different bacterial species to one another by specific molecules. <lb/>Coaggregation in biofilms is important in development of mix-culture biofilms; it enables cells to <lb/>withstand the highly changing environment, which on the other hand can adversely affect <lb/>mono-dispersed cells. The results of this study revealed that E. cloacae isolates which weakly adhered <lb/>to the microtiter plate demonstrated the strongest coaggregation with all the seven partner strain; these <lb/>findings suggest the possibility of these strains to act as bridging organisms in multi-generic biofilms <lb/>due to their ability to coaggregate with diverse coaggregating partners. Such bridging organisms are <lb/>believed to carry complementary receptors recognized by functionally similar adhesins on cells from <lb/>distinct genera [28]. Figure 1 shows the scanning electron micrographs of E. cloacae autoaggregates <lb/>and its coaggregate partner Pseudomonas aeruginosa ATCC 15442. The SEM graphics of coaggregate <lb/>assay demonstrated strong coaggregation with P. aeruginosa. It was also observed that E. cloacae <lb/>strains coaggregated with organisms important in food spoilage and/or intoxications, i.e., S. aureus, <lb/>S. Typhimurium, Shigella sonnei and P. aeruginosa implying that E. cloacae in food processing plants <lb/>can enhance the bridging of organisms in multi-generic biofilms. <lb/>3. Experimental <lb/>3.1. Bacterial Strains <lb/>Bacterial strains used in the study consist of E. cloacae previously isolated from various food <lb/>sources [4] and reference strains: S. pyogenes A ATCC 49399, Plesiomonas shigelloides ATCC <lb/>51903, P. aeruginosa ATCC 15442, S. Typhimurium ATCC 13311, Aeromonas hydrophila ATCC <lb/>35654 and S. sonnei ATCC 29930. These strains have been reported to form biofilms [29-32]; and <lb/>were also available in our laboratory at the time of the experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9589 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 1. Scanning electron micrographs of an autoaggregate and coaggregate biofilm of <lb/>E. cloacae and its coaggregate partner P. aeruginosa ATCC 15442 (a) strong adherent <lb/>autoaggregate; (b) coaggregate of E. cloacae and partner P. aeruginosa ATCC 15442. <lb/>(a) <lb/>(b) <lb/>3.2. Microtiter Plate Assay <lb/>E. cloacae isolates were screened for their adherence to polystyrene microtiter plate wells following <lb/>24 and 48 h incubation at 25 °C or 37 °C, in BHI and TSB. The method previously described by <lb/>Nyenje et al. [33] was employed which made use of the agar and broth techniques; for the agar <lb/>method, E. cloacae isolates were cultured on Nutrient agar (Oxoid, Basingstoke, England) and plates <lb/>incubated at 37 °C for 24 h. Few single colonies were suspended in sterile saline to a turbidity standard <lb/>comparable to a 0.5 McFarland. The suspension was vortexed for 1 min from which 20 µL was <lb/>pipetted into a 96-well U-bottomed microtiter plate (Greiner Bio-one GmbH, Frickenhausen, <lb/>Germany) containing 180 µL of BHI or TSB (Oxoid). With the inoculum for broth technique, isolates <lb/>were grown in Nutrient broth (Oxoid), incubated for 24 h at 37 °C. Subsequently, the bacterial <lb/>suspension was diluted 1:100 in BHI or TSB; an aliquot of 200 μL of diluted bacterial suspension was <lb/>added to each well. The negative control wells contained 200 mL of broth only per well. The plates <lb/>were incubated aerobically at different temperatures (25 °C and 37 °C) for 24 and 48 h. At the end of <lb/>incubation period, the wells were carefully aspirated and washed three times with 200 µL of sterile <lb/>normal saline to remove the unbound bacteria. The plates were left to dry overnight, fixed with hot air <lb/>at 65 °C for 1 h, and the wells were stained with 150 µL of 1% crystal violet for 30 min. The plates <lb/>were carefully rinsed off under running tap water to remove excess stain, left to dry at room <lb/>temperature before resolubilizing the dye bound cells with 150 µL of 33% (v/v) glacial acetic acid. <lb/>The optical density (OD) of each well was measured at 595 nm using a microtiter plate reader <lb/>(SynergyMx, Biotek TM Winooski, VT, USA). Reference strains of P. aeruginosa ATCC 15442 and <lb/>S. aureus NCTC 6571 were used as positive controls because they have been widely reported to form <lb/>biofilms in various environments [29-32]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9590 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.3. Autoaggregation and Coaggregation Assays <lb/>A representative of the different biofilm phenotypes were examined for their ability to coaggregate <lb/>with the following reference strains: S. aureus NCTC 6571, S. pyogenes A ATCC 49399, S. <lb/>Typhimurium ATCC 13311, P. aeruginosa ATCC 15442, P. shigelloides ATCC 51903, A. hydrophila <lb/>ATCC 35654, S. sonnei ATCC 29930. The individual strain was grown in 20 mL of BHI broth at <lb/>37 °C, harvested after 48 h and washed twice in 3mM NaCl containing 0.5 mM CaCl 2 . Subsequently, <lb/>the cells were re-suspended in the same solution (3 mM NaCl containing 0.5 mM CaCl 2 ), centrifuged <lb/>at 650 × g for 2 min and the supernatant discarded; the OD of the cell suspension used for coaggregation <lb/>assay was adjusted to 0.3 at a wavelength of 660 nm, using an automated spectrophotometer (Optima <lb/>Scientific V-1200, Cambridge, UK). Equal volumes of the cell suspension (1 mL each) of E. cloacae <lb/>and the coaggregating partners were mixed and the OD (OD Tot ) immediately read at 660 nm before <lb/>incubation at room temperature for 2 h. Subsequently, the tubes were centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for <lb/>2 min and the OD of the supernatant (OD s ) measured at the same wavelength (660 nm) [20]. The <lb/>degree of coaggregation of the paired isolates was determined using the equation: <lb/>% coaggregation = (OD Tot − OD s ) × 100/OD Tot <lb/>For autoaggregation assay, the individual bacterial suspension adjusted to an OD of 0.3 was <lb/>incubated at room temperature for 1 h, centrifuged at 2,000 rpm for 2 min and the OD of the <lb/>supernatant was measured at 660 nm. The degree of autoaggregation was calculated as follows: <lb/>% autoaggregation = (OD − OD 60 ) × 100/OD 0 <lb/>OD 0 refers to the initial OD of the organism, and OD 60 is the OD of the supernatant after 60 min <lb/>of incubation. <lb/>3.4. Characterization of Biofilm Formation Using Scanning Electron Microscope <lb/>To evaluate the architecture of the formed biofilms, SEM was used in accordance with the method <lb/>previously described by Nyenje et al. [33]. Briefly, the isolates were grown on a microscope cover slip <lb/>(22 × 22 mm) in a Petri-dish half-filled with BHI broth and incubated at 37 °C for 72 h. For the <lb/>coaggregation assay, the partner isolate was added after 1 h of incubation. At the end of the incubation, <lb/>the cover slips were washed three times with normal saline before fixing with 2.5% (w/v) <lb/>glutaraldehyde solution for 1 h. Subsequently, the samples were dehydrated in a series of 20, 40, 60, <lb/>80 and 99.5% ethanol solution for 30 min in each concentration before post fixing in 1% osmium <lb/>tetroxide (OsO 4 ). The samples were critical point-dried using CO 2 and sputter-coated with gold <lb/>palladium using an Elko 1B.3 ion coater before viewing with the SEM (Japan Electron Optical <lb/>Laboratories JSM-6390LV, Tokyo, Japan). <lb/>4. Statistical Analysis <lb/>Statistical analysis was performed using SPSS version 19. One way ANOVA followed by Turkey&apos;s <lb/>post hoc test was used to compare the agar and broth methods, BHI and TSB liquid media. The <lb/>incubation temperatures and periods were also compared; the mean difference was considered <lb/>significant at p &lt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9591 <lb/></page>

			<body>5. Conclusions <lb/>This study demonstrated that E. cloacae readily form biofilms on plastic surfaces, which are <lb/>nowadays frequently used in food-processing environments, raising a great concern for the food <lb/>industry as organisms in biofilms are difficult to eliminate, hence creating a reservoir for cross <lb/>contamination. The study also indicated the suitability of BHI and TSB medium for the cultivation of <lb/>E. cloacae biofilm however, temperature and incubation time significantly affected biofilm formation <lb/>by these bacteria. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors are thankful to the Govan Mbeki Research and Development Centre, University of Fort <lb/>Hare, South Africa for funding. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest <lb/>The authors declare no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Paterson, D.L.; Rossi, F.; Baquero, F.; Hsueh, P.R.; Woods, G.L.; Satishchandran, V.; <lb/>Snyder, T.A.; Harvey, C.M.; Teppler, H.; Di Nubile, M.J. In vitro susceptibilities of aerobic and <lb/>facultative Gram-negative bacilli isolated from patients with intra-abdominal infections <lb/>worldwide: the 2003 study for monitoring antimicrobial resistance trends (SMART). <lb/>J. Antimicrob. Chemother. 2005, 55, 965-970. <lb/>2. Shaker, R.; Osaili, T.; Al-Omary, W.; Jaradat, Z.; Al-Zuby, M. Isolation of Enterobacter <lb/>sakazakii and other Enterobacter species from food and food production environments. <lb/>Food Cont. 2007, 18, 1241-1245. <lb/>3. Haryani, Y.; Tunung, R.; Chai, L.C.; Lee, H.Y.; Tang, S.Y.; Son, R. Characterization of <lb/>Enterobacter cloacae isolated from street foods. ASEAN Food J. 2008, 15, 57-64. <lb/>4. Nyenje, M.E.; Odjadjare, C.E.; Tanih, N.F.; Green, E.; Ndip, R.N. Foodborne pathogens <lb/>recovered from ready-to-eat foods from roadside cafeterias and retail outlets in Alice, Eastern <lb/>Cape Province, South Africa: public health implications. Int. J. Environ. Res. Public Health 2012, <lb/>9, 2608-2619. <lb/>5. Storti, A. Pizzolitto, A.C, Pizzolitto E.L. Detection of mixed microbial biofilms on central venous <lb/>catheters removed from intensive care unit patients. Braz. J. Microbiol. 2005, 36, 275-280. <lb/>6. Mokracka, J.; Koczura, R.; Pawlowski, K.; Kaznowski, A. Resistance patterns and integron <lb/>cassette arrays of Enterobacter cloacae complex strains of human origin. J. Med. Microbiol. <lb/>2011, 60, 737-743. <lb/>7. Donlan, R.M. Biofilms: microbial life on surfaces. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2002, 8, 881-890. <lb/>8. Delle-Bovi, R.J.; Smits, A.; Pylypiw, H.M. Rapid method for the determination of total <lb/>monosaccharide in Enterobacter cloacae strains using Fourier Transform Infrared Spectroscopy. <lb/>Am. J. Analytical Chem. 2011, 2, 212-216. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9592 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>9. Schlegelová, J.; Babák, V.; Holasová, M.; Konstantinová, L.; Necidová, L.; Šišák, F.; Vlková, H.; <lb/>Roubal, P.; Jaglic, Z. Microbial contamination after sanitation of food contact surfaces in dairy <lb/>and meat processing plants. Czech J. Food Sc. 2010, 28, 450-461. <lb/>10. Kusumaningrum, H.D.; Riboldi, G.; Hazeleger, W.C.; R.R. Beumer, R.R. Survival of foodborne <lb/>pathogens on stainless steel surfaces and cross-contamination to foods. Int. J. Food Microbiol. <lb/>2003, 85, 227-236. <lb/>11. Brooks, J.D.; Flint, S.H. Biofilms in the food industry: problems and potential solutions. Int. J. <lb/>Food Sci. Technol. 2008, 43, 2163-2176. <lb/>12. Chmielewski, R.A.N.; Frank, J.F. Biofilm formation and control in food processing facilities. <lb/>Compr. Rev. Food Sci. Food Safety 2003, 2, 22-32. <lb/>13. Donlan, R.M. Biofilms and device-associated infections. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 2001, 7, 277-281. <lb/>14. Revdiwala, S.; Rajdey, B.M.; Mulla, S. Characterization of bacterial etiologic agents of biofilm <lb/>formation in medical devices in critical care setup. Crit. Care Res. Pract. 2012, 2012, 945805. <lb/>15. Lindsay, D.; von Holy, A. What food safety professionals should know about bacterial biofilms. <lb/>Brit. Food J. 2006, 108, 27-37. <lb/>16. Van Houdt, R.; Michiels, C.W. Biofilm formation and the food industry, a focus on the bacterial <lb/>outer surface. J. Appl. Microbiol. 2010, 109, 1117-1131. <lb/>17. Stepanovic, S.; Djukic, N.; Opavski, N.; Djukic, S. Significance of inoculum size in biofilm <lb/>formation by Staphylococci. New Microbiol. 2003, 26, 129-132. <lb/>18. Di Bonaventura, G.; Stepanović, S.; Picciani, C.; Pompilio, A.; Piccolomini, R. Effects of <lb/>environmental factors on biofilm formation by clinical Stenotrophomonas maltophilia isolates. <lb/>Folia Microbiol. 2007, 52, 86-90. <lb/>19. Goller, C.C.; Romeo, T. Environmental influences on biofilm development. Curr. Topics <lb/>Microbiol. Immunol. 2008, 322, 37-66. <lb/>20. Basson, A.; Flemming, L.A.; Chenia, H.Y. Evaluation of adherence, hydrophobicity, aggregation <lb/>characteristics and biofilm development of Flavobacterium johnsoniae-like isolates from South <lb/>African aquaculture systems. Microbial Ecol. 2007, 55, 1-14. <lb/>21. Kiers, P.J.; Bos, R.; van der Mei, H.C.; Busscher, H.J. The electrophoretic softness of the surface <lb/>of Staphylococcus epidermidis cells grown in a liquid medium and on a solid agar. Microbiology <lb/>2001, 147, 757-762. <lb/>22. Stepanovic, S.; Vukovic, D.; Hola, V.; Bonaventura, G.; Djukic, S.; Cirkovic, I.; Ruzika, F. <lb/>Quantification of biofilm in microtiter plates: overview of testing conditions and practical <lb/>recommendations for assessment of biofilm production by Staphylococci. Apmis 2007, 115, 891-899. <lb/>23. Hoštacká, A.; Čižnár, I.; Štefkovičová, M. Temperature and pH affect the production of bacterial <lb/>biofilm. Folia Microbiol. 2010, 55, 75-78. <lb/>24. Mathur, T.; Singhal, S.; Khan, S.; Upadhyay, D.J.; Fatma, T.; Rattan, A. Detection of biofilm <lb/>formation among the clinical isolates of Staphylococci: an evaluation of three different screening <lb/>methods. Ind. J. Med. Microbiol. 2006, 24, 25-29. <lb/>25. Knobloch, J.K.; Horstkotte, M.A.; Rohde, H.; Mack, D. Evaluation of different detection methods <lb/>of biofilm formation in Staphylococcus aureus. J. Med. Microbiol. Immunol. 2002, 191, 101-106. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Molecules 2013, 18 <lb/></note>

			<page>9593 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>26. Hood, S.K.; Zottola, E.A. Growth media and surface conditioning influence the adherence of <lb/>Pseudomonas fragi, Salmonella Typhimurium, and Listeria monocytogenes cells to stainless steel. <lb/>J. Food Protect. 1997, 60, 1034-1037. <lb/>27. Iversen, C.; Lane, M.; Forsythe, S.J. The growth profile, thermo-tolerance and biofilm formation <lb/>of Enterobacter sakazakii grown in infant formula milk. Lett. Appl. Microbiol. 2004, 38, 378-382. <lb/>28. Malik, A.; Sakamoto, M.; Hanazaki, S.; Osawa, M.; Suzuki, T.; Tochigi, M.; Kakii, K. <lb/>Coaggregation among nonflocculating bacteria isolated from activated sludge. Appl. Environ. <lb/>Microbiol. 2003, 69, 6056-6063. <lb/>29. Hammer, K.A.; Carson, C.F., Rilley, T.V. Australia Government report for the Rural Industries <lb/>Research and Development Corporation; RIRDC 05/115; Novasel Australia Pty Ltd: Crawley, <lb/>Australia, 2005. <lb/>30. Qadri, F., Hossain, S.A., Ciznar, I., Haider, K., Ljungh, A., Wadstrom, T., Sack, D.A. Congo red <lb/>binding and salt aggregation as indicators of virulence in Shigella species. J. Clin. Microbiol. <lb/>2007, 26, 1343-1348. <lb/>31. Bridier, A.; Dubois-Brissonnet, F.; Greub, G.; Thomas, V.; Briandet, R. Dynamics of the action of <lb/>biocides in Pseudomonas aeruginosa biofilms. Antimicrob. Agents Chemother. 2011, 55, 2648-2654. <lb/>32. Díez-García, M., Capita, R., Alonso-Calleja C. Influence of serotype on the growth kinetics and <lb/>the ability to form biofilms of Salmonella isolates from poultry. Food Microbiol. 2012, 31, 173-180. <lb/>33. Nyenje, M.E.; Green, E.; Ndip, R.N. Biofilm formation and adherence characteristics of Listeria <lb/>ivanovii strains isolated from ready-to-eat foods in Alice, South Africa. Scientific World J. 2012, <lb/>2012, 873909. <lb/></listBibl>
			
			<div type="annex">Sample Availability: Samples of the compounds of the present study are available from the authors. <lb/></div>
			
			<front>© 2013 by the authors; licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and conditions of the Creative Commons Attribution license <lb/>(http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/3.0/). </front>


	</text>
</tei>
