<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>O R I G I N A L A R T I C L E <lb/>Advance directives of lung cancer patients and caregivers in <lb/>China: A cross sectional survey <lb/>Chenchen Feng 1 , Juan Wu 1 , Junying Li , Han Yu Deng 3 , Jiewei Liu 3 &amp; Shuzhen Zhao 1 <lb/>Department of Outpatient, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China <lb/>2 Cancer Center, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China <lb/>3 Lung Cancer Center, West China Hospital, Sichuan University, Chengdu, China <lb/>Keywords <lb/>advance directives; attitudes; caregivers; lung <lb/>cancer; patients. <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Shuzhen Zhao, Outpatient Department, West <lb/>China Hospital, Sichuan University, <lb/>No. 37, Guoxue Lane, Chengdu 610041, <lb/>Sichuan Province, China. <lb/>Tel: +86 18980606083 <lb/>Email: ssszszzsz@126.com <lb/>Received: 20 September 2019; <lb/>Accepted: 18 October 2019. <lb/>doi: 10.1111/1759-7714.13237 <lb/>Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: This study aimed to investigate lung cancer patients and attitudes <lb/>of their caregivers toward advance directives (ADs) in China. <lb/>Methods: A cross sectional study was conducted in the Department of Oncology <lb/>outpatient clinic in West China Hospital, Sichuan University. A questionnaire <lb/>was used to survey the attitudes of lung cancer patients and caregivers <lb/>toward ADs. <lb/>Results: A total of 148 lung cancer patients and 149 caregivers were enrolled <lb/>into the study. Of these, 94.6% and 89.9% of patients and caregivers had <lb/>not heard of AD and none of those in the study had ever signed an AD. A <lb/>total of 79.7% patients and 75.2% caregivers were willing to sign ADs after <lb/>they were provided with information. Patients who preferred the end of <lb/>life period to sign ADs were 5.4 times more likely to have ADs than patients <lb/>who chose to sign ADs when their disease was diagnosed (P &lt; 0.05, <lb/>95%CI [1.27-22.93]). Caregivers who were reluctant to undergo chemother-<lb/>apy when diagnosed with cancer were 2.16 times more likely to sign ADs <lb/>than those willing to receive chemotherapy (P &lt; 0.05, 95%CI [1.20-3.90]). <lb/>Conclusions: In China, lung cancer patients and their caregivers showed lack of <lb/>knowledge about ADs, and the completion rate of ADs was extremely low. How-<lb/>ever, participants were positive about ADs and public education on ADs may <lb/>help to increase the completion rate of ADs in China. <lb/>Key points <lb/>Significant findings of the study: Lung cancer patients and their caregivers <lb/>lacked knowledge about ADs, and the completion rate of ADs was <lb/>extremely low. <lb/>What this study adds: Participants were positive about ADs and public edu-<lb/>cation on ADs may help increase the completion rate of ADs in China. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Advance directives (ADs) are legal documents in which <lb/>people choose the medical treatments they are, or are not, <lb/>willing to receive if in the future they lose the capacity to <lb/>talk about their wishes. 1 It gives people the right to choose <lb/>medical treatments following their values and wishes and <lb/>helps to minimize suffering and maintain dignity at the last <lb/>time of their life. 2,3 It has been reported that ADs are asso-<lb/>ciated with a reduction in aggressive treatments, 4-6 fewer <lb/>in-hospital deaths, increased use of hospices, 5,7 and lower hos-<lb/>pital charges. 8 Absence of ADs may lead to unwanted aggres-<lb/>sive treatments, which correlates to poor quality of life. In <lb/>tradition, Chinese families value interdependency between <lb/>family members, 11 and close relatives make decisions when <lb/>family members lose their capacity to communicate. As a <lb/>result, ADs could also help prevent family members from the <lb/>difficult situation of having to guess what kind of care their <lb/>loved ones would choose. <lb/></body>

			<front>Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided the <lb/>original work is properly cited. <lb/>Thoracic Cancer ISSN 1759-7706 <lb/></front>

			<body>Countries such as the United States, 12 Germany, 13 and <lb/>Singapore 14 have already developed legislation for ADs. <lb/>In 2000, Taiwan was the first place in Asia to enact <lb/>legislation to provide people with the right to make do-<lb/>not-resuscitate (DNR) decisions. However, there is no <lb/>legislation for ADs in mainland China. 16 The overall <lb/>AD preparation rate is low. Previous studies have indi-<lb/>cated that completion of ADs was 14%-30% among the <lb/>general population, 17-19 and 15%-49% among cancer <lb/>patients. 18,20-23 Many factors are associated with having <lb/>ADs including sociodemographic characteristics such as <lb/>age, 20 level of education, gender, religious beliefs, <lb/>health or functional status, 25,26 public education on <lb/>ADs, 14,27,28 and traditional perspectives. 22 Little work <lb/>has been done on the perception of ADs in both the <lb/>general and ill populations. Some studies have reported <lb/>the impact of patients and family members&apos; knowledge, <lb/>attitudes, and behaviors on the completion of ADs. <lb/>However, most of these studies focused on various can-<lb/>cers 29 or chronic diseases. 30 Since different diseases <lb/>have different diagnosis and treatment procedures <lb/>and mortality differs among them, it seems necessary <lb/>to focus on a specific disease. Moreover, there has been <lb/>a lack of comparison between patients and caregiv-<lb/>ers since some studies have analyzed these data <lb/>together. 16,31 Patients and caregivers may hold different <lb/>attitudes toward ADs since healthy people may have no <lb/>idea about the situation when they are ill. <lb/>Lung cancer is the most common cancer in the word, <lb/>with over 1.8 million new cases and about 1.6 million <lb/>deaths in 2012. 32 It is also the leading cause of cancer-<lb/>related death. 33 More than one third of all newly diag-<lb/>nosed lung cancers occur in China, 33 with the mortality <lb/>rate being higher than the international average level. <lb/>To our knowledge, there has been no study about lung <lb/>cancer patients&apos; and caregivers&apos; attitudes toward ADs in <lb/>mainland China and also a lack of comparison between <lb/>them. Therefore, we conducted this cross sectional <lb/>study which aimed to investigate the attitudes of lung <lb/>cancer patients and caregivers toward ADs. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Study design <lb/>A cross-sectional study was conducted in the Department <lb/>of Oncology outpatient clinic in West China Hospital of <lb/>Sichuan University (Chengdu, China). <lb/>Participants in the study <lb/>Between June 2017 and October 2017, 148 patients and <lb/>149 caregivers from West China Hospital, Sichuan <lb/>University were enrolled in the study by convenience sam-<lb/>pling. Patients&apos; inclusion criteria were: (i) Aged between <lb/>18 and 75 years old, (ii) diagnosed with lung cancer, <lb/>(iii) having no communication disability with interviewers, <lb/>(iv) informed consent. Exclusion criteria: (i) Do not know <lb/>his or her cancer diagnosis. Caregivers inclusion criteria: <lb/>(i) Aged between 18 and 75 years old, (ii) having no com-<lb/>munication disability with interviewers, (iii) informed con-<lb/>sent. Exclusion criteria: (i) Diagnosed with disease that <lb/>may threaten their life such as cancer, heart diseases, etc. <lb/>Measurements <lb/>Sociodemographic characteristics included gender, age, <lb/>marital status, education level, relationship between care-<lb/>giver and patient, address, current work status, personal <lb/>income (annual), medical insurance, religion, experience in <lb/>caring for seriously ill people, experiences of a loved one <lb/>dying of serious illness, disease duration, Numerical Rating <lb/>Scale (NRS) reflecting pain score, metastasis, complication, <lb/>radiotherapy times, and cycle of chemotherapy. <lb/>Based on previous studies, 16,24,35 we developed a struc-<lb/>tured questionnaire to explore the attitudes of patients and <lb/>caregivers toward ADs. The content validity of the ques-<lb/>tionnaire was tested by a group of five experts in the field <lb/>of end-of-life care and lung cancer. Items rated under four <lb/>(ranged from 1 = least relevant to 5 = most relevant) were <lb/>modified or deleted. After three rounds of modification, <lb/>the content validity index of the questionnaire was 0.93. <lb/>Data collection process <lb/>Patients and caregivers were informed about the aims and <lb/>process of the study when they visited the Oncology outpa-<lb/>tient clinic. After obtaining their informed consents, they <lb/>were interviewed by two researchers and data were ana-<lb/>lyzed by a third researcher. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>SPSS software (SPSS Inc., Chicago, IL, USA; version 17.0) <lb/>was used. Mean and standard deviation (SD) was used to <lb/>describe continuous variables. Percentages and frequencies <lb/>were applied to describe categorical variables. Chi-square <lb/>test was used to examine the proportion differences in <lb/>patients and caregivers&apos; characteristics and their attitudes <lb/>toward ADs. Binary logistic regression analysis was then <lb/>conducted to identify predictor of completion of ADs. <lb/>P &lt; 0.05 was considered statistically significant. <lb/></body>

			<page>254 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/>C. Feng et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Results <lb/>Participants&apos; characteristics <lb/>148 lung cancer patients and 149 caregivers were enrolled <lb/>into this study. The characteristics of participants are <lb/>showed in Table 1. The mean (SD) age of patients and <lb/>caregivers were 58.4 (11.96) and 45.18 (12.59), respectively. <lb/>Most of the patients&apos; education level was primary and <lb/>junior high school, while for caregivers, most were high <lb/>school/vocational high school level. Both participants of <lb/>cancer patients and caregivers mainly lived in the urban <lb/>area. Characteristics including gender, age, education level, <lb/>relationship between caregivers and patients, current work <lb/>status, personal income, and experience in caring for seri-<lb/>ously ill people showed a significant difference between <lb/>patients and caregivers (P &lt; 0.05). <lb/>Perception and willingness of patients and <lb/>caregivers toward ADs <lb/>A total of 140 patients (94.6%) and 134 caregivers (89.9%) <lb/>had never heard of ADs. There were 118 (79.7%) patients <lb/>who were willing to sign ADs when the concept of ADs <lb/>was explained to them. There was a significant difference <lb/>between patients and caregivers regarding the time to pre-<lb/>pare ADs (P &lt; 0.001). A total of 34.5% of patients pre-<lb/>ferred to sign ADs when treatment commenced and 31.1% <lb/>chose to complete ADs when they were diagnosed with <lb/>disease. A total of 112 (75.2%) caregivers were willing to <lb/>sign ADs, and 42 (28.2%) caregivers chose to have ADs <lb/>when they were healthy. Of the caregivers, 27.5% preferred <lb/>to have ADs when they were diagnosed with incurable dis-<lb/>ease or when their incurable disease was getting worse, <lb/>respectively. There was a significant difference between <lb/>patients and caregivers about the question that whose <lb/>advice will they largely rely on when making medical deci-<lb/>sions (P &lt; 0.001). A total of 60.2% of the patients chose <lb/>medical services mainly relying on the advice of medical <lb/>staff, while for caregivers, 44.3% of them would rely on <lb/>Table 1 Characteristics of participants <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Patients <lb/>(n = 148)n % <lb/>Caregiver <lb/>(n = 149)n % P-value <lb/>Gender <lb/>0.004 <lb/>Female <lb/>61 (41.2) <lb/>86 (57.7) <lb/>Male <lb/>87 (58.8) <lb/>63 (42.3) <lb/>Age, mean <lb/>58.4 (11.96) 45.18 (12.59) 0.000 <lb/>≤44 <lb/>18 (12.2) <lb/>78 (52.3) <lb/>45-59 <lb/>51 (34.5) <lb/>43 (28.9) <lb/>60-74 <lb/>70 (47.3) <lb/>28 (18.8) <lb/>≥75 <lb/>9 (6.1) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Marital status <lb/>0.678 <lb/>Married <lb/>133 (89.9) <lb/>136 (91.3) <lb/>Single <lb/>15 (10.1) <lb/>13 (8.7) <lb/>Education level <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Illiterate <lb/>4 (2.7) <lb/>2 (1.3) <lb/>Primary and junior high school <lb/>82 (55.4) <lb/>33 (22.1) <lb/>High school/vocational <lb/>high school <lb/>43 (29.1) <lb/>74 (49.7) <lb/>University and college <lb/>17 (11.5) <lb/>29 (19.5) <lb/>Graduate school <lb/>2 (1.3) <lb/>11 (7.4) <lb/>Relationship between <lb/>caregiver and patient <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Spouse <lb/>89 (60.1) <lb/>52 (34.9) <lb/>Relatives <lb/>44 (29.8) <lb/>91 (61.1) <lb/>Others <lb/>15 (10.1) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>Residence <lb/>0.664 <lb/>Rural area <lb/>39 (26.4) <lb/>36 (24.2) <lb/>Urban area <lb/>109 (73.6) <lb/>113 (75.8) <lb/>Current work status <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Retired <lb/>59 (39.9) <lb/>24 (16.1) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>46 (31.1) <lb/>46 (30.9) <lb/>Employed <lb/>43 (29.0) <lb/>79 (53.0) <lb/>Personal income (annual) <lb/>0.000 <lb/>≤10 000 <lb/>47 (31.8) <lb/>34 (22.8) <lb/>10 000-50 000 <lb/>78 (52.7) <lb/>61 (40.9) <lb/>000-100 000 <lb/>20 (13.5) <lb/>40 (26.8) <lb/>≥100 000 <lb/>3 (2.0) <lb/>14 (9.5) <lb/>Medical insurance <lb/>0.304 <lb/>Yes <lb/>132 (89.2) <lb/>138 (92.6) <lb/>No <lb/>16 (10.8) <lb/>11 (7.4) <lb/>Religiousness <lb/>0.781 <lb/>Religious <lb/>8 (5.4) <lb/>7 (4.7) <lb/>Nonreligious <lb/>140 (94.6) <lb/>142 (95.3) <lb/>Experience in caring for <lb/>seriously ill people <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Yes <lb/>34 (23.0) <lb/>80 (53.7) <lb/>No <lb/>114 (77.0) <lb/>69 (46.3) <lb/>Disease duration <lb/>-<lb/>&lt;3 years <lb/>130 (87.8) <lb/>-<lb/>≥3 years <lb/>18 (12.2) <lb/>-<lb/>NRS score, median (range) <lb/>0 (0-10) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Metastases <lb/>-<lb/>Yes <lb/>36 (24.3) <lb/>-<lb/>No <lb/>112 (75.7) <lb/>-<lb/>Complication <lb/>-<lb/>Yes <lb/>28 (18.9) <lb/>-<lb/>No <lb/>120 (81.1) <lb/>-<lb/>Table 1 Continued <lb/>Characteristics <lb/>Patients <lb/>(n = 148)n % <lb/>Caregiver <lb/>(n = 149)n % P-value <lb/>Radiotherapy times, <lb/>median (range) <lb/>0 (0-39) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>Chemotherapy times, <lb/>median (range) <lb/>0 (0-20) <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>For caregivers, disease information including disease duration, NRS <lb/>score, metastases, complication, radiotherapy times, chemotherapy <lb/>times were not collected. NRS, Numerical Rating Scale (NRS) reflecting <lb/>pain score. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">C. Feng et al. <lb/>Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/></note>

			<body>themselves. As for the question when should patients know <lb/>the diagnosis and prognosis of their incurable disease, <lb/>patients and caregivers&apos; attitudes showed significant differ-<lb/>ences (P &lt; 0.001). A total of 64.9% of the patients chose to <lb/>know about their diagnosis and prognosis soon after <lb/>diagnosis, while 42.3% of the caregivers thought that <lb/>patients should know their own diagnosis and prognosis <lb/>and there were still 37.6% of the caregivers who preferred <lb/>to conceal the diagnosis and prognosis to patients <lb/>(Table 2). <lb/>Table 2 Perception and willingness of participants toward ADs <lb/>Variables <lb/>Patients (n = 148) n % <lb/>Caregiver (n = 149) n % <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>P-value <lb/>Heard of ADs <lb/>2.258 <lb/>0.133 <lb/>Yes <lb/>8 (5.4) <lb/>15 (10.1) <lb/>No <lb/>140 (94.6) <lb/>134 (89.9) <lb/>Attitudes toward ADs <lb/>0.885 <lb/>0.347 <lb/>Agree <lb/>118 (79.7) <lb/>112 (75.2) <lb/>Disagree <lb/>30 (20.3) <lb/>37 (24.8) <lb/>Time to prepare ADs <lb/>57.356 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>When healthy <lb/>0(0) <lb/>42 (28.2) <lb/>When diagnosed with incurable disease <lb/>46 (31.1) <lb/>41 (27.5) <lb/>When receive treatments <lb/>51 (34.5) <lb/>21 (14.0) <lb/>When the incurable disease is getting worse <lb/>41 (27.7) <lb/>41 (27.5) <lb/>End of life <lb/>10 (6.7) <lb/>4 (2.8) <lb/>Making medical decisions mostly rely on whose advice <lb/>33.610 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>My own <lb/>28 (18.9) <lb/>66 (44.3) <lb/>Family members <lb/>31 (20.9) <lb/>41 (27.5) <lb/>Medical staffs <lb/>89 (60.2) <lb/>42 (28.2) <lb/>When should patient know incurable disease diagnosis and <lb/>prognosis <lb/>71.281 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>Do not want to know (patient should not know) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>56 (37.6) <lb/>Right after diagnosis <lb/>96 (64.9) <lb/>63 (42.3) <lb/>When receiving treatment <lb/>39 (26.3) <lb/>20 (13.4) <lb/>When the disease is getting worse <lb/>12 (8.1) <lb/>7 (4.70) <lb/>End time of life <lb/>1 (0.7) <lb/>3 (2.0) <lb/>Are you willing to undergo surgery? (do you want patient to <lb/>undergo surgery?) <lb/>-<lb/>0.501 <lb/>Yes <lb/>145 (98.0) <lb/>143 (96.0) <lb/>No <lb/>3 (2.0) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to undergo surgery? <lb/>Yes <lb/>-<lb/>141 (94.6) <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>8 (5.4) <lb/>Are you willing to receive radiotherapy? (do you want patient <lb/>to receive radiotherapy?) <lb/>1.720 <lb/>0.190 <lb/>Yes <lb/>143 (96.6) <lb/>139(93.3) <lb/>No <lb/>5 (3.4) <lb/>10 (6.7) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to receive radiotherapy? <lb/>Yes <lb/>-<lb/>138 (92.6) <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>11 (7.4) <lb/>Are you willing to undergo chemotherapy? (do you want <lb/>patient to undergo chemotherapy?) <lb/>2.656 <lb/>0.103 <lb/>Yes <lb/>144 (97.3) <lb/>139 (93.3) <lb/>No <lb/>4 (2.7) <lb/>10 (6.7) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to undergo chemotherapy? <lb/>Yes <lb/>-<lb/>137 (91.9) <lb/>No <lb/>-<lb/>12 (8.1) <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact test was used for variable &quot;Are you willing to undergo surgery? (do you want patient to undergo surgery?)&quot;,so there was no χ 2 value <lb/>for this variable. ADs, advance directives. <lb/></body>

			<page>256 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/>C. Feng et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>The basic life-sustaining treatment, cardiopulmonary <lb/>resuscitation (CPR), and rescue medication use were the <lb/>three mostly selected medical cares for all the participants <lb/>at terminal and cardiac arrest status, followed by sedative <lb/>drug and painkiller use (Table 3). There was no difference <lb/>of medical choices at terminal status and cardiac arrest for <lb/>both lung cancer patients and caregivers. <lb/>For lung cancer patients, there were significant differ-<lb/>ences in attitude toward having ADs among patients <lb/>choosing different time to have ADs (P &lt; 0.01) and those <lb/>relying on different people&apos;s advice to make medical <lb/>choices. No differences in gender, age, marital status, edu-<lb/>cation level, current work status or other characteristics <lb/>were found between groups with different attitudes <lb/>towards ADs (Table 4). Compared with patients who pre-<lb/>ferred to have ADs at the time of disease diagnosis, those <lb/>preferring end time of life as the time to have ADs were <lb/>5.4 times more likely to have ADs in the future (Table 5). <lb/>For caregivers, there were differences in attitude toward <lb/>having ADs among groups with different attitudes toward <lb/>the management of patients, including whether patients <lb/>should know the diagnosis and prognosis of the disease, <lb/>willingness to advocate surgery and radiotherapy for <lb/>patients, and caregivers own willingness to receive radio-<lb/>therapy and chemotherapy if they were diagnosed with <lb/>cancer. No differences in gender, marital status, education <lb/>level, current work status or other characteristics were <lb/>found between the two groups with different attitudes <lb/>toward ADs (Table 6). For caregivers, those who were <lb/>reluctant to undergo chemotherapy when they were diag-<lb/>nosed with cancer were 2.16 times more likely to prepare <lb/>ADs than those willing to receive chemotherapy (Table 7). <lb/>Discussion <lb/>To the best of our knowledge, this is the first study to focus <lb/>on lung cancer patients&apos; and caregivers&apos; attitudes toward <lb/>ADs in China. In our study, 94.6% of the patients and <lb/>89.9% caregivers had never heard of ADs, and none had <lb/>signed ADs. Our results were similar to a previous study <lb/>conducted in China focusing on various cancers, 24 in which <lb/>all of the 526 cancer patients did not have ADs, and 90% <lb/>of them had never heard of the terminology of &quot;advance <lb/>directive&quot;. There were obvious disparities in the compari-<lb/>son of the rate of completion of ADs in China with that of <lb/>other countries that had AD legislation. In Germany, 18% <lb/>of cancer patients, 19% of healthy people, and 28%-31% <lb/>hematology and oncology outpatient patients had signed <lb/>ADs. 36,37 In Korea, 35.5% of patients in a Hospice Center <lb/>completed ADs, 23 and in the report by White et al. 14% of <lb/>the Australian population had ADs. After being informed <lb/>about the concept of ADs, 79.7% of the patients and 75.2% <lb/>of the caregivers were willing to have ADs, which was in <lb/>line with previous studies conducted in various cancer <lb/>patients. 16 Interestingly, at the very beginning, our <lb/>researchers were concerned about the cancer patients&apos; <lb/>cooperation with the investigation. However, during the <lb/>investigation, most of the patients were cooperative, indi-<lb/>cating their willingness to accept ADs. China has experi-<lb/>enced great development and fast modernization during <lb/>the past several decades, and the behavior of Chinese peo-<lb/>ple and their values have greatly changed with the rapid <lb/>development of the economy. 38 At the same time, patients&apos; <lb/>sense of autonomy and self-determination has increased, 16 <lb/>which may help explain the overall positive attitude toward <lb/>ADs. A previous report indicated that insufficient knowl-<lb/>edge was frequently given as the reason for declining <lb/>ADs. 36 Therefore, it reminds us that the legislation of ADs <lb/>should be placed on the agenda, and that wider public edu-<lb/>cation of the benefit of ADs is essential. <lb/>We also found some interesting differences of partici-<lb/>pants&apos; attitude toward several questions. Most patients <lb/>made their decisions mainly relying on the information <lb/>and advice of medical staff. However, for caregivers, the <lb/>Table 3 Medical choices of participants at terminal status and cardiac arrest <lb/>Terminal status <lb/>Cardiac arrest <lb/>Medical choices <lb/>Patients % <lb/>Caregiver % <lb/>Patients % <lb/>Caregiver % <lb/>The basic life-sustaining treatment † <lb/>134 (90.5) <lb/>137 (91.9) <lb/>136 (91.9) <lb/>123 (82.6) <lb/>CPR † <lb/>83 (56.1) <lb/>84 (56.4) <lb/>89 (60.1) <lb/>76 (51.0) <lb/>Rescue medication use (such as pressor, respiratory stimulant <lb/>drugs) † <lb/>81 (54.7) <lb/>79 (53.0) <lb/>90 (60.8) <lb/>95 (63.8) <lb/>Sedative † <lb/>65 (43.9) <lb/>61 (40.9) <lb/>61 (41.2) <lb/>51(34.2) <lb/>Painkiller † <lb/>64 (43.2) <lb/>58 (38.9) <lb/>54 (36.5) <lb/>64 (43.0) <lb/>Tracheal intubation † <lb/>21 (14.2) <lb/>19 (12.8) <lb/>15 (10.1) <lb/>13 (8.7) <lb/>Stomach tube † <lb/>7 (4.7) <lb/>7 (4.7) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>Urinary catheter † <lb/>7 (4.7) <lb/>8 (5.4) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>Abandon † <lb/>7 (4.7) <lb/>8 (5.4) <lb/>6 (4.0) <lb/>11 (7.4) <lb/> †There was no difference for both participants&apos; medical choices at terminal status and cardiac arrest. Participants could choose more than one medi-<lb/>cal choice, so the value represents how many people chose each medical care. CPR, cardiopulmonary resuscitation. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">C. Feng et al. <lb/>Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/></note>

			<body>decisions they made were self-reliant. This may be <lb/>explained by when people are ill, they may want a cure for <lb/>their diseases or relief of their symptoms so they must rely <lb/>Table 4 Characteristics associated with attitudes of patients <lb/>toward ADs <lb/>Variables <lb/>Attitudes <lb/>Agree with <lb/>ADs <lb/>(n = 118) <lb/>Disagree <lb/>with ADs <lb/>(n = 30) χ 2 <lb/>P-value <lb/>Gender, n (%) <lb/>1.198 0.274 <lb/>Male <lb/>72 (82.8) 15 (17.2) <lb/>Female <lb/>46 (75.4) (24.6) <lb/>Age <lb/>3.211 0.360 <lb/>≤44 <lb/>13 (72.2) 5 (27.8) <lb/>45-59 <lb/>39 (76.5) 12 (23.5) <lb/>60-74 <lb/>57 (81.4) (18.6) <lb/>≥75 <lb/>9 (100.0) 0 (0) <lb/>Marital status <lb/>1.089 0.297 <lb/>Married <lb/>104 (78.2) (21.8) <lb/>Single <lb/>14 (93.3) 1 (6.7) <lb/>Education level <lb/>0.903 0.924 <lb/>Illiterate <lb/>3 (75) <lb/>1 (25) <lb/>Primary and junior high <lb/>school <lb/>66 (80.5) 16 (19.5) <lb/>High school/vocational high <lb/>school <lb/>33 (76.7) 10 (23.3) <lb/>University and college <lb/>14 (82.4) 3 (17.6) <lb/>Graduate school <lb/>2 (100) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Residence <lb/>0.177 0.674 <lb/>Rural area <lb/>32 (82.1) 7 (17.9) <lb/>Urban area <lb/>86 (78.9) 23 (21.1) <lb/>Current work status <lb/>4.509 0.105 <lb/>Retired <lb/>52 (88.1) 7(11.9) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>35 (76.1) 11(23.9) <lb/>Employed <lb/>31 (72.1) 12 (27.9) <lb/>Personal income (annual) <lb/>6.485 0.090 <lb/>≤10 000 RMB <lb/>35 (74.5) 12 (25.5) <lb/>10 000-50 000 RMB <lb/>68 (87.2) 10 (12.8) <lb/>50 000-100 000 RMB <lb/>13 (65.0) 7(35) <lb/>≥100 000 RMB <lb/>2 (66.7) 1 (33.3) <lb/>Medical insurance <lb/>0.240 0.625 <lb/>Yes <lb/>104 (78.8) 28 (21.2) <lb/>No <lb/>14 (87.5) 2 (12.5) <lb/>Religiousness <lb/>0.000 1.000 <lb/>Religious <lb/>6 (75) <lb/>2 (25) <lb/>Nonreligious <lb/>112 (80) <lb/>28 (20) <lb/>Experience in caring for <lb/>seriously ill people <lb/>0.188 0.665 <lb/>Yes <lb/>28 (82.4) 6 (17.6) <lb/>No <lb/>90 (78.9) 24 (21.1) <lb/>Disease duration <lb/>&lt;3 years <lb/>104 (80.0) 26 (20.0) 0.000 1 <lb/>≥3 years <lb/>14 (77.8) 4 (22.2) <lb/>NRS score <lb/>0.742 0.863 <lb/>None <lb/>74 (81.3) 17 (18.7) <lb/>Mild <lb/>26 (76.5) 8 (23.5) <lb/>Moderate <lb/>12 (75.0) 4 (25.0) <lb/>Severe <lb/>6 (85.7) 1 (14.3) <lb/>Metastases <lb/>1.659 0.198 <lb/>Yes <lb/>26 (72.2) 10 (27.8) <lb/>No <lb/>92 (82.1) 20 (17.9) <lb/>Table 4 Continued <lb/>Variables <lb/>Attitudes <lb/>Agree with <lb/>ADs <lb/>(n = 118) <lb/>Disagree <lb/>with ADs <lb/>(n = 30) χ 2 <lb/>P-value <lb/>Complication <lb/>0.029 0.866 <lb/>Yes <lb/>22 (78.6) 6 (21.4) <lb/>No <lb/>96 (80.0) 24 (20.0) <lb/>Receive radiotherapy <lb/>0.029 0.866 <lb/>Yes <lb/>96 (80.0) 24 (20.0) <lb/>No <lb/>22 (78.6) 6 (21.4) <lb/>Receive chemotherapy <lb/>2.972 0.085 <lb/>Yes <lb/>86 (83.5) 17 (16.5) <lb/>No <lb/>32 (71.1) 13 (28.9) <lb/>Heard of ADs <lb/>1.029 0.310 <lb/>Yes <lb/>8 (100) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>No <lb/>110 (78.6) 30 (21.4) <lb/>Time to prepare ADs <lb/>13.357 0.004 <lb/>When healthy <lb/>0(0) <lb/>0(0) <lb/>When diagnosed with <lb/>incurable disease <lb/>36 (78.3) 10 (21.7) <lb/>When receive treatments <lb/>46 (90.2) 5 (9.8) <lb/>When the incurable disease <lb/>is getting worse <lb/>32 (78.0) 9 (22.0) <lb/>End time of life <lb/>4 (40.0) 6 (60.0) <lb/>Make medical decisions <lb/>mostly rely on whose <lb/>advice <lb/>6.001 0.050 <lb/>My own <lb/>18 (64.2) 10 (35.8) <lb/>Family members <lb/>24 (77.4) 7 (22.6) <lb/>Medical staff <lb/>76 (85.4) 13 (14.6) <lb/>When should patient know <lb/>incurable disease diagnosis <lb/>and prognosis <lb/>3.648 0.302 <lb/>Do not want to know <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Right after diagnosis <lb/>73 (76.0) 23 (24.0) <lb/>When receiving treatment <lb/>35 (89.7) 4 (10.3) <lb/>When the disease is getting <lb/>worse <lb/>9 (75.0) 3 (25.0) <lb/>End of life <lb/>1 (100) <lb/>0 (0) <lb/>Are you willing to undergo <lb/>surgery? <lb/>0.000 1.000 <lb/>Yes <lb/>116 (80.0) 29 (20.0) <lb/>No <lb/>2 (66.7) 1 (33.3) <lb/>Are you willing to receive <lb/>radiotherapy? <lb/>0.000 0.988 <lb/>Yes <lb/>114 (79.4) 29 (20.6) <lb/>No <lb/>4 (80.0) 1 (20.0) <lb/>Are you willing to undergo <lb/>chemotherapy? <lb/>0.054 0.816 <lb/>Yes <lb/>115(79.9) 29 (20.1) <lb/>No <lb/>3 (75.0) 1 (25.0) <lb/>ADs, advance directives. <lb/></body>

			<page>258 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/>C. Feng et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>on medical staff, while healthy people cannot put them-<lb/>selves into a situation where they are ill, and they don&apos;t <lb/>have to rely on the advice of medical staff. Therefore, they <lb/>may think that their own willingness is more important, <lb/>which demonstrates that different attitudes toward ADs <lb/>are dependent upon health status. Therefore, we need to <lb/>investigate the attitude of people towards ADs when they <lb/>are both healthy and ill. <lb/>In China, many caregivers would not tell patients about <lb/>their disease diagnosis and prognosis for the fear of the <lb/>pressure this may place on them. However, the results of <lb/>our study indicated that all patients wanted to know their <lb/>diagnosis and prognosis, but there were still 37.6% of care-<lb/>givers who said that they did not want patients to know <lb/>the truth. The differences between patients and caregivers <lb/>toward disease, life, and death should be given more atten-<lb/>tion. In Chinese culture, when people lose their ability to <lb/>communicate, caregivers play an important role in assisting <lb/>patients to choose the medical options available to them. <lb/>To be aware of a person&apos;s attitude and willingness when <lb/>they are healthy may assist caregivers in making decisions <lb/>for patients in the future. <lb/>Patients and caregivers were invited to choose their medi-<lb/>cal cares when they were at terminal stage and cardiac <lb/>arrest. Before that, the meaning of terminal status and car-<lb/>diac arrest was explained to them. Basic life-sustaining treat-<lb/>ment, CPR, and use of rescue medication were the main <lb/>options chosen by participants of both health statuses, <lb/>followed by use of sedatives and painkillers. Other invasive <lb/>procedures such as tracheal intubation, or use of a stomach <lb/>tube were less preferred. There were no significant differ-<lb/>ences of willingness to medical treatments between lung <lb/>cancer patients and caregivers and both patients and healthy <lb/>people showed their first choice was to receive life saving <lb/>treatments. Our results were different to those of the study <lb/>of Zheng et al.24 in which the majority of patients chose <lb/>comfort care only, followed by limited care. The reasons <lb/>may be that 82.1% of the participants in the report by Zheng <lb/>et al. were religious and the study reported that faith can <lb/>influence cancer patients&apos; medical decisions, and make them <lb/>more likely to refuse the recommendations of physicians. <lb/>Moreover, the study by Zheng et al. included patients with <lb/>various cancers, while our study only focused on lung cancer <lb/>patients. The survival or mortality rate can be different in a <lb/>wide range of diseases, and therefore patients may have dif-<lb/>ferent confidence in overcoming the disease. Furthermore, <lb/>contrary to our study, in the study by Kong et al. 23 most ter-<lb/>minal cancer patients did not want to receive any invasive <lb/>medical interventions to sustain life. Possible reasons for this <lb/>may be that our patients were not yet at the terminal stage <lb/>of illness and terminal cancer patients may already have suf-<lb/>fered many invasive treatments and have known about their <lb/>prognosis. This indicates that we should pay attention to the <lb/>possibility of patients wanting to change their end of life AD <lb/>and future studies should be conducted which take this pref-<lb/>erence for care into account. <lb/>Patients preferred end time of life as the time when an <lb/>AD should be in place and were 5.4 times more likely to <lb/>have ADs at that stage than those choosing to have ADs <lb/>when first diagnosed. A previous study has reported that <lb/>completion of ADs in the last months of life was associated <lb/>with higher rates of aggressive care preferences. 26 Allison <lb/>et al. also reported that those preparing too late may be in <lb/>a rush to make a decision and did not represent patients&apos; <lb/>values and willingness. 40 Those results confirm that atten-<lb/>tion should be paid to those who prepare ADs at the end <lb/>time of life because ADs may cannot help to maintain peo-<lb/>ple&apos;s dignity at that time. For those patients, early educa-<lb/>tion so that they understand the meaning of ADs should <lb/>be compulsory. <lb/>For caregivers, those who were reluctant to undergo che-<lb/>motherapy when they become ill were 2.16 times more <lb/>likely to prepare ADs than those willing to receive chemo-<lb/>therapy. Chemotherapy is a commonly used treatment in <lb/>the majority of lung cancer patients, which might prolong <lb/>survival but can still cause adverse effects. This result may <lb/>be because some people are afraid of the adverse effects of <lb/>treatment and the suffering which can be caused by che-<lb/>motherapy, and those choosing not to receive chemother-<lb/>apy showed that they want more comfortable treatments, <lb/>but not to prolong survival. Therefore, they would like to <lb/>have ADs to reflect their willingness. <lb/>Our study had some limitations. First, it was conducted <lb/>only in one single hospital and the sample size was small <lb/>both for patients and caregivers, which may be the reason <lb/>why the study has not highlighted other factors. Multi-<lb/>center studies with a larger sample size are required in the <lb/>future to improve the representativeness of the partici-<lb/>pants. Second, some important information such as pat-<lb/>ients&apos;cancer stage could not be accessed due to the cross <lb/>sectional study design. As a result, some meaningful results <lb/>may have been left out of the investigation. <lb/>In conclusion, Chinese lung cancer patients and their <lb/>caregivers lacked knowledge concerning ADs, and the <lb/>completion rate of ADs was extremely low. However, after <lb/>Table 5 Binary logistic regression analysis of factors which predict <lb/>patients willing to prepare ADs <lb/>Variables <lb/>OR (95%CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>Timing to prepare ADs <lb/>When diagnosed with incurable disease <lb/>1 <lb/>When receiving treatments <lb/>0.39 (0.12-1.25) <lb/>When the disease is getting worse <lb/>1.01 (0.37-2.80) <lb/>End of life <lb/>5.40 (1.27-22.93) &lt;0.05 <lb/>ADs, advance directives. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">C. Feng et al. <lb/>Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 6 Characteristics associated with attitudes of caregivers toward ADs <lb/>Variables <lb/>Agree with ADs (n = 112) <lb/>Disagree with ADs (n = 37) <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>P-value <lb/>Gender, n (%) <lb/>0.061 <lb/>0.805 <lb/>Male <lb/>48 (76.2) <lb/>15 (23.8) <lb/>Female <lb/>64 (74.4) <lb/>22 (25.6) <lb/>Age <lb/>3.492 <lb/>0.174 <lb/>≤44 <lb/>54 (69.2) <lb/>24 (30.8) <lb/>45-59 <lb/>34 (79.1) <lb/>9 (20.9) <lb/>60-74 <lb/>24 (85.7) <lb/>4 (14.3) <lb/>Marital status <lb/>0.033 <lb/>0.855 <lb/>Married <lb/>103 (75.7) <lb/>33 (24.3) <lb/>Single <lb/>9 (69.2) <lb/>4 (30.8) <lb/>Education <lb/>1.712 <lb/>0.789 <lb/>Illiterate <lb/>2 (100.0) <lb/>0 (0.00) <lb/>Primary and junior high school <lb/>26 (78.8) <lb/>7 (21.2) <lb/>High school/vocational high school <lb/>55 (74.3) <lb/>19 (25.7) <lb/>University and college <lb/>22 (75.9) <lb/>7 (24.1) <lb/>Graduate school <lb/>7 (63.6) <lb/>4 (36.4) <lb/>Residence <lb/>3.046 <lb/>0.081 <lb/>Rural area <lb/>31 (86.1) <lb/>5 (13.9) <lb/>Urban area <lb/>81 (71.7) <lb/>32 (28.3) <lb/>Current work status <lb/>2.525 <lb/>0.283 <lb/>Retired <lb/>20 (83.3) <lb/>4 (16.7) <lb/>Unemployed <lb/>31 (67.4) <lb/>15 (32.6) <lb/>Employed <lb/>61 (77.2) <lb/>18 (22.8) <lb/>Personal income (annual) <lb/>1.970 <lb/>0.579 <lb/>≤10000 RMB <lb/>27 (79.4) <lb/>7 (20.6) <lb/>000-50 000 RMB <lb/>43 (70.5) <lb/>18 (29.5) <lb/>50 000-100 000 RMB <lb/>30 (75.0) <lb/>10 (25.0) <lb/>≥100 000 RMB <lb/>12 (85.7) <lb/>2 (14.3) <lb/>Have medical insurance <lb/>0.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Yes <lb/>104 (75.4) <lb/>34 (24.6) <lb/>No <lb/>8 (72.7) <lb/>3 (27.3) <lb/>Religiousness <lb/>0.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Religious <lb/>5 (71.4) <lb/>2 (28.6) <lb/>Nonreligious <lb/>107 (75.4) <lb/>35 (24.6) <lb/>Experience in caring for seriously ill people <lb/>2.161 <lb/>0.142 <lb/>Yes <lb/>64 (80.0) <lb/>16 (20.0) <lb/>No <lb/>48 (69.6) <lb/>21 (30.4) <lb/>Heard of ADs <lb/>0.569 <lb/>0.440 <lb/>Yes <lb/>13 (86.7) <lb/>2 (13.3) <lb/>No <lb/>99 (73.9) <lb/>35 (26.1) <lb/>Timing to prepare ADs <lb/>2.946 <lb/>0.557 <lb/>When healthy <lb/>31 (73.8) <lb/>11(26.2) <lb/>When diagnosed with incurable disease <lb/>33 (80.5) <lb/>8 (19.5) <lb/>When receive treatments <lb/>17 (81.0) <lb/>4 (19.0) <lb/>When the incurable disease is getting worse <lb/>29 (70.7) <lb/>12 (29.3) <lb/>End time of life <lb/>2 (50) <lb/>2 (50) <lb/>Preferences for proxy <lb/>1.310 <lb/>0.519 <lb/>My own <lb/>47 (71.2) <lb/>19 (28.8) <lb/>Family members <lb/>31 (75.6) <lb/>10 (24.4) <lb/>Medical staff <lb/>34 (81.0) <lb/>8 (19.0) <lb/>Whether the patient should know the diagnosis and prognosis <lb/>of the incurable disease? <lb/>3.977 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>Yes <lb/>75 (80.6) <lb/>18 (19.4) <lb/>No <lb/>37 (66.1) <lb/>19 (33.9) <lb/>When should patient know incurable disease diagnosis and <lb/>prognosis <lb/>7.222 <lb/>0.100 <lb/></body>

			<page>260 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/>C. Feng et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>being informed about them, most indicated that they <lb/>would be willing to prepare ADs. Public education on ADs <lb/>is necessary for Chinese people, and may help increase the <lb/>completion rate of ADs in China. Patients preferred end of <lb/>life as the time to have ADs were more likely to prepare <lb/>ADs, but attention should be paid because their medical <lb/>decisions at that time may be made in haste and cannot <lb/>reflect their true willingness to participate. For those <lb/>patients, early education on ADs may help them express <lb/>their preferences. Caregivers who were reluctant to <lb/>undergo chemotherapy if they became ill one day were <lb/>more inclined to prepare ADs than those willing to receive <lb/>chemotherapy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was supported by The Key Project of Interna-<lb/>tional Cooperation of Science and Technology innovation <lb/>between Governments, the National Key Research and <lb/>Development Plan of China (No.2016YEE0103400), China <lb/>Medical Board (0082827601130) and the Science and Tech-<lb/>nology Department of Sichuan Province (2018SZ0398). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Disclosure <lb/>The authors have nothing to declare. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1 GS R. Making an advance directive. Br Med J 1995; <lb/>310: 236. <lb/>2 Ko E, Berkman CS. Advance directives among Korean <lb/>American older adults: Knowledge, attitudes, and behavior. <lb/>J Gerontol Soc Work 2012; 55: 484-502. <lb/>3 Levi BH, Green MJ. Too soon to give up? Re-examining the <lb/>value of advance directives. Am J Bioeth 2010; 10: 3-22. <lb/>Nicholas LH, Langa KM, Iwashyna TJ, Weir DR. Regional <lb/>variation in the association between advance directives and <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Table 6 Continued <lb/>Variables <lb/>Agree with ADs (n = 112) <lb/>Disagree with ADs (n = 37) <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>P-value <lb/>Patient should not know <lb/>37 (66.1) <lb/>19 (33.9) <lb/>Right after diagnosis <lb/>53 (84.1) <lb/>10 (15.9) <lb/>When receiving treatment <lb/>16 (80.0) <lb/>4 (20.0) <lb/>When the disease is getting worse <lb/>4 (57.1) <lb/>3(42.9) <lb/>End time of life <lb/>2 (66.7) <lb/>1(33.3) <lb/>Do you want patient to undergo surgery? <lb/>3.759 <lb/>0.050 <lb/>Yes <lb/>110 (76.9) <lb/>33 (23.1) <lb/>No <lb/>2 (33.3) <lb/>4 (66.7) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to undergo surgery? <lb/>1.621 <lb/>0.203 <lb/>Yes <lb/>108 (76.6) <lb/>33 (23.4) <lb/>No <lb/>4 (50.0) <lb/>4 (50.0) <lb/>Do you want patient to receive radiotherapy? <lb/>5.227 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>Yes <lb/>108 (77.7) <lb/>31 (22.3) <lb/>No <lb/>4 (40.0) <lb/>6 (60.0) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to receive radiotherapy? <lb/>4.837 <lb/>0.030 <lb/>Yes <lb/>107 (77.5) <lb/>31(22.5) <lb/>No <lb/>5 (45.5) <lb/>6 (54.5) <lb/>Do you want patient to undergo chemotherapy? <lb/>3.170 <lb/>0.080 <lb/>Yes <lb/>107 (77.0) <lb/>32 (23.0) <lb/>No <lb/>5 (50.0) <lb/>5 (50.0) <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, would you be <lb/>willing to undergo chemotherapy? <lb/>3.870 <lb/>0.040 <lb/>Yes <lb/>106 (77.3) <lb/>31 (22.7) <lb/>No <lb/>6 (50.0) <lb/>6 (50.0) <lb/>ADs, Advance directives. <lb/>Table 7 Binary logistic regression analysis of factors which predict care-<lb/>givers willing to prepare ADs <lb/>Variables <lb/>OR (95%CI) <lb/>P-value <lb/>If you were diagnosed with cancer one day, <lb/>would you be willing to undergo <lb/>chemotherapy? <lb/>Yes <lb/>1 <lb/>No <lb/>2.16(1.20-3.90) &lt;0.05 <lb/>CI, confidence interval; OR, Odds Ratio. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">C. Feng et al. <lb/>Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>end-of-life medicare expenditures. JAMA 2011; 306: <lb/>1447-53. <lb/>5 Brinkman-Stoppelenburg A, Rietjens JA, van der Heide A. <lb/>The effects of advance care planning on end-of-life care: A <lb/>systematic review. Palliat Med 2014; 28: 1000-25. <lb/>6 Nicholas LH, Bynum JP, Iwashyna TJ, Weir DR, Langa KM. <lb/>Advance directives and nursing home stays associated with <lb/>less aggressive end-of-life care for patients with severe <lb/>dementia. Health Aff 2014; 33: 667-74. <lb/>7 Bischoff KE, Sudore R, Miao Y, Boscardin WJ, Smith AK. <lb/>Advance care planning and the quality of end-of-life care <lb/>among older adults. J Am Geriatr Soc 2013; 61: 209-14. <lb/>8 Chambers CV, Diamond JJ, Perkel RL, Lasch LA. <lb/>Relationship of advance directives to hospital charges in a <lb/>Medicare population. Arch Intern Med 1994; 154: 541-7. <lb/>9 Harrington SE, Smith TJ. The role of chemotherapy at the <lb/>end of life: &quot;when is enough, enough?&quot;. JAMA 2008; 299: <lb/>2667-78. <lb/>10 Earle CC, Landrum MB, Souza JM, Neville BA, Weeks JC, <lb/>Ayanian JZ. Aggressiveness of cancer care near the end of <lb/>life: Is it a quality-of-care issue? J Clin Oncol 2008; 26: <lb/>3860-6. <lb/>11 Bowman KW, Singer PA. Chinese seniors&apos; perspectives on <lb/>end-of-life decisions. Soc Sci Med 2001; 53: 455-64. <lb/>12 Brown BA. The history of advance directives. A literature <lb/>review. J Gerontol Nurs 2003; 29: 4-14. <lb/>13 Wiesing U, Jox RJ, Hessler HJ, Borasio GD. A new law on <lb/>advance directives in Germany. J Med Ethics 2010; 36: <lb/>779-83. <lb/>14 Tay M, Chia SE, Sng J. Knowledge, attitudes and practices of <lb/>the Advance Medical Directive in a residential estate in <lb/>Singapore. Ann Acad Med Singapore 2010; 39: 424-8. <lb/>15 Lo YT, Wang JJ, Liu LF, Wang CN. Prevalence and related <lb/>factors of do-not-resuscitate directives among nursing home <lb/>residents in Taiwan. J Am Med Dir Assoc 2010; 11: 436-42. <lb/>16 Zhang Q, Xie C, Xie S, Liu Q. The attitudes of Chinese <lb/>cancer patients and family caregivers toward advance <lb/>directives. Int J Environ Res Public Health 2016; 13: 816. <lb/>17 White B, Tilse C, Wilson J et al. Prevalence and predictors <lb/>of advance directives in Australia. Int Med J 2014; 44: <lb/>975-80. <lb/>18 Sahm S, Will R, Hommel G. Attitudes towards and barriers <lb/>to writing advance directives amongst cancer patients, <lb/>healthy controls, and medical staff. J Med Ethics 2005; 31: <lb/>437-40. <lb/>19 Song J, Ratner ER, Wall MM et al. Effect of an End-of-Life <lb/>Planning Intervention on the completion of advance <lb/>directives in homeless persons: A randomized trial. Ann <lb/>Intern Med 2010; 153: 76-84. <lb/>20 Brown AJ, Shen MJ, Urbauer D et al. Room for <lb/>improvement: An examination of advance care planning <lb/>documentation among gynecologic oncology patients. <lb/>Gynecol Oncol 2016; 142: 525-30. <lb/>21 Dow LA, Matsuyama RK, Ramakrishnan V et al. Paradoxes <lb/>in advance care planning: The complex relationship of <lb/>oncology patients, their physicians, and advance medical <lb/>directives. J Clin Oncol 2010; 28: 299-304. <lb/>22 Tan TS, Jatoi A. An update on advance directives in the <lb/>medical record: Findings from 1186 consecutive patients <lb/>with unresectable exocrine pancreas cancer. J Gastrointest <lb/>Cancer 2008; 39: 100-3. <lb/>23 Kong BH, An HJ, Kim HS et al. Experience of advance <lb/>directives in a hospice center. J Korean Med Sci 2015; <lb/>30: 151-4. <lb/>24 Zheng RJ, Fu Y, Xiang QF et al. Knowledge, attitudes, and <lb/>influencing factors of cancer patients toward approving <lb/>advance directives in China. Support Care Cancer 2016; 24: <lb/>4097-103. <lb/>25 del Pozo Puente K, Hidalgo JL, Herraez MJ, Bravo BN, <lb/>Rodriguez JO, Guillen VG. Study of the factors influencing <lb/>the preparation of advance directives. Arch Gerontol Geriatr <lb/>2014; 58: 20-4. <lb/>Enguidanos S, Ailshire J. Timing of advance directive <lb/>completion and relationship to care preferences. J Pain <lb/>Symptom Manage 2017; 53: 49-56. <lb/>Kwak J, Salmon JR. Attitudes and preferences of Korean-<lb/>American older adults and caregivers on end-of-life care. <lb/>J Am Geriatr Soc 2007; 55: 1867-72. <lb/>28 West SK, Hollis M. Barriers to completion of advance care <lb/>directives among African Americans ages 25-84: A cross-<lb/>generational study. Omega 2012; 65: 125-37. <lb/>29 Kizawa Y, Tsuneto S, Hamano J, Nagaoka H, Maeno T, <lb/>Shima Y. Advance directives and do-not-resuscitate orders <lb/>among patients with terminal cancer in palliative care units <lb/>in Japan: A nationwide survey. Am J Hosp Palliat Care 2013; <lb/>30: 664-9. <lb/>30 Ting FH, Mok E. Advance directives and life-sustaining <lb/>treatment: Attitudes of Hong Kong Chinese elders with <lb/>chronic disease. Hong Kong Med J 2011; 17: 105-11. <lb/>31 Keam B, Yun YH, Heo DS et al. The attitudes of Korean <lb/>cancer patients, family caregivers, oncologists, and members <lb/>of the general public toward advance directives. Support <lb/>Care Cancer 2013; 21: 1437-44. <lb/>32 Stewart BW, Wild CP, eds. World Cancer Report 2014. <lb/>IARC, WHO Press, Lyon, France 2014. <lb/>33 Hong QY, Wu GM, Qian GS et al. Prevention and <lb/>management of lung cancer in China. Cancer 2015; 121: <lb/>3080-8. <lb/>Chen WQ, Li H, Sun KX, Zheng RS et al. Report of cancer <lb/>incidence and mortality in China, 2014. Chin J Oncol 2018; <lb/>40: 5-13. <lb/>Lee J, Kim KH. Perspectives of Korean patients, families, <lb/>physicians and nurses on advance directives. Asian Nurs Res <lb/>2010; 4: 185-93. <lb/>36 Hubert E, Schulte N, Belle S et al. Cancer patients and <lb/>advance directives: A survey of patients in a hematology <lb/>and oncology outpatient clinic. Onkologie 2013; 36: <lb/>398-402. <lb/>37 Pfirstinger J, Kattner D, Edinger M, Andreesen R, <lb/>Vogelhuber M. The impact of a tumor diagnosis on patients&apos; <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>262 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs <lb/>C. Feng et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>attitudes toward advance directives. Oncology 2014; 87: <lb/>246-56. <lb/>38 Zhang YB, Lin M-C, Nonaka A, Beom K. Harmony, <lb/>hierarchy and conservatism: A cross-cultural comparison of <lb/>Confucian values in China, Korea, Japan, and Taiwan. <lb/>Commun Res Rep 2005; 22: 107-15. <lb/>39 Sharf BF, Stelljes LA, Gordon HS. &apos;A little bitty spot and <lb/>I&apos;m a big man&apos;: patients&apos; perspectives on refusing <lb/>diagnosis or treatment for lung cancer. Psychooncology <lb/>2005; 14: 636-46. <lb/>40 Allison TA, Sudore RL. Disregard of patients&apos; preferences is <lb/>a medical error. JAMA Intern Med 2013; 173: 787. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Thoracic Cancer 11 (2020) 253-263 <lb/>© 2019 The Authors. Thoracic Cancer published by China Lung Oncology Group and John Wiley &amp; Sons Australia, Ltd <lb/></note>

			<page>263 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">C. Feng et al. <lb/>Lung cancer patients and caregivers ADs </note>


	</text>
</tei>
