<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41398-019-0590-7 <lb/>Translational Psychiatry <lb/>A R T I C L E <lb/>O p e n A c c e s s <lb/>Precocious myelination in a mouse model of <lb/>autism <lb/>Maryam Khanbabaei 1 , Elizabeth Hughes 1 , Jacob Ellegood 2 , Lily R. Qiu 2 , Raven Yip , Jenna Dobry 1 , Kartikeya Murari 3 , <lb/>Jason P. Lerch 2 , Jong M. Rho 4,5 and Ning Cheng 1 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) has been hypothesized to be a result of altered connectivity in the brain. Recent <lb/>imaging studies suggest accelerated maturation of the white matter in young children with ASD, with underlying <lb/>mechanisms unknown. Myelin is an integral part of the white matter and critical for connectivity; however, its role in <lb/>ASD remains largely unclear. Here, we investigated myelin development in a model of idiopathic ASD, the BTBR mice. <lb/>Magnetic resonance imaging revealed that fiber tracts in the frontal brain of the BTBR mice had increased volume at <lb/>postnatal day 6, but the difference reduced over time, reminiscent of the findings in young patients. We further <lb/>identified that myelination in the frontal brain of both male and female neonatal BTBR mice was increased, associated <lb/>with elevated levels of myelin basic protein. However, myelin pattern was unaltered in adult BTBR mice, revealing <lb/>accelerated developmental trajectory of myelination. Consistently, we found that signaling of platelet-derived growth <lb/>factor receptor alpha (PDGFRα) was reduced in the frontal brain of neonatal BTBR mice. However, levels of microRNA <lb/>species known to regulate PDGFRα signaling and myelination were unaltered. Together, these results suggest that <lb/>precocious myelination could potentially contribute to increased volume and connectivity of the white matter <lb/>observed in young children with ASD. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Autism spectrum disorder (ASD) affects multiple brain <lb/>regions and probably involves impaired connectivity <lb/>among them 1-4 . Consistent with altered connectivity, <lb/>abnormal white matter growth and reduced white matter <lb/>integrity have been reported in patients with ASD 1,3,5 , <lb/>including atypical development of white matter micro-<lb/>structure observed in young patients 6-15 . In addition, <lb/>white matter maturation is associated with development <lb/>of social cognition in early childhood 16 , and altered white <lb/>matter connectivity probably contributes to core symp-<lb/>toms of ASD including atypical social communication 17 . <lb/>Although changes during early development may be <lb/>critical to the pathogenesis of ASD, they may disappear, or <lb/>may even be reversed later in life 18 . A notable example is <lb/>that children with ASD have increased brain size at early <lb/>childhood, but in older children and adults, decreases in <lb/>structural volumes are observed instead 19-25 . In a related <lb/>vein, reduced size of the corpus callosum in children and <lb/>adults with ASD has been a consistent finding 26 ; however, <lb/>a recent study of infants &lt;2 years of age showed that the <lb/>corpus callosum was larger in those who later developed <lb/>ASD 27 . Together, these observations strongly suggest that <lb/>alterations are dynamic but not uniform across the life-<lb/>span of ASD patients, and developmental trajectory could <lb/>be a critical component of the etiology. <lb/>In terms of functional and structural connectivity, evi-<lb/>dence suggests that hyper-connectivity may be more <lb/>characteristic of young children with autism, while hypo-<lb/>connectivity may be more prevalent in adolescents and <lb/>adults 18 . In older children, adolescents, and adults with <lb/></body>

			<front>© The Author(s) 2019 <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction <lb/>in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative Commons license, and indicate if <lb/>changes were made. The images or other third party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If <lb/>material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain <lb/>permission directly from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>Correspondence: Ning Cheng (ncheng@ucalgary.ca) <lb/>1 <lb/>Developmental Neurosciences Research Program, Alberta Children&apos;s Hospital <lb/>Research Institute (ACHRI), Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, <lb/>Calgary, AB, Canada <lb/>2 <lb/>Mouse Imaging Centre (MICe), Hospital for Sick Children, Toronto, ON, Canada <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article. <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/></front>

			<body>ASD, restriction of water diffusion (often measured by <lb/>fractional anisotropy, FA, using neuroimaging methods) <lb/>in white matter tracts is usually reduced, suggesting <lb/>functional hypo-connectivity. On the other hand, recent <lb/>imaging studies in patients 1-4-years-old have reported <lb/>that they display greater volume and increased FA of fiber <lb/>tracts in mostly frontal regions of the brain, but a slower <lb/>rate of continued development 6-15 . <lb/>The mechanisms underlying altered trajectory of white <lb/>matter development remain unclear, especially regarding <lb/>the involvement of the myelin sheath, a fundamental <lb/>component of the white matter. Myelin formation con-<lb/>tinues even decades after birth in the human brain. It <lb/>enables saltatory conduction of action potentials along <lb/>myelinated axons and regulates the timing of information <lb/>integration in neural networks 28 . In addition, myelin also <lb/>provides trophic and metabolic support to the axons . <lb/>During development, the timing of myelination is critical <lb/>as myelin stabilizes axon structure and wiring pattern in <lb/>neural networks. However, due to the limitations of <lb/>neuroimaging methods and the dearth of studies using <lb/>animal models (a few such studies so far have shown <lb/>delayed myelination in general using animal models), <lb/>development of myelin during the course of ASD has <lb/>largely remained unknown 30 . <lb/>Here, we investigated myelin development in a mouse <lb/>model of idiopathic ASD, the BTBR T + Itpr3 tf /J (BTBR) <lb/>inbred strain. In addition to robust behavioral phenotype <lb/>that models core autism-like impairments 31-35 , a striking <lb/>anatomical feature of the BTBR mice is agenesis of the <lb/>corpus callosum 36-38 . Dysgenesis of the corpus callosum <lb/>has been considered a major risk factor for ASD 39 , and <lb/>atypical developmental trajectory of the size and micro-<lb/>structure of the corpus callosum has been one of the most <lb/>replicated neuroimaging findings in the patient popula-<lb/>tion 26,27 . Here, magnetic resonance imaging (MRI) <lb/>revealed that fiber tracts in the frontal brain of the BTBR <lb/>mice had increased volume at postnatal day 6, but the <lb/>difference reduced over time, reminiscent of the findings <lb/>in young patients. We further identified accelerated <lb/>myelination during the neonatal stage, compared with <lb/>other inbred lines. We observed this phenomenon in both <lb/>male and female BTBR mice, and found that it involves <lb/>increased levels of myelin basic protein (MBP) and <lb/>reduced platelet-derived growth factor receptor alpha <lb/>(PDGFRα) signaling. <lb/>Methods and materials <lb/>Animals <lb/>Breeder C57BL/6 J (B6) and BTBR animals were <lb/>obtained from the Jackson Laboratory (ME) and the lines <lb/>were maintained at the mouse facility of the Cumming <lb/>School of Medicine, University of Calgary. Mice were <lb/>housed in a humidity-and temperature-controlled room <lb/>with a 12-h light/dark cycle and were fed ad libitum. Both <lb/>neonatal (between postnatal day 2 to day 12, specified in <lb/>the results section for individual experiment), adolescent <lb/>(P35), and adult (8 to 10 week old) B6 and BTBR male <lb/>animals were used. Female neonatal B6 and BTBR mice <lb/>were also examined. The 129S6 (129) inbred strain was <lb/>originally purchased from Taconic (NY). Experiments on <lb/>BTBR mice and B6 or 129 mice were performed in par-<lb/>allel. All procedures in this study were performed in <lb/>accordance with the recommendations from the Canadian <lb/>Council for Animal Care. The protocol for this study was <lb/>approved by the Health Sciences Animal Care Committee <lb/>of the University of Calgary. <lb/>MRI analysis <lb/>Preparation of brains for scanning <lb/>Initially the mice are anesthetized with ketamine/xyla-<lb/>zine and intracardially perfused with 30 ml of 0.1 M PBS <lb/>containing 10 U/ml heparin (Sigma) and 2 mM ProHance <lb/>(a Gadolinium contrast agent) followed by 30 ml of 4% <lb/>paraformaldehyde (PFA) containing 2 mM ProHance. <lb/>Perfusions were performed with a minipump at a rate of <lb/>approximately 1 ml/min. After perfusion, mice were <lb/>decapitated and the skin, lower jaw, ears, and the carti-<lb/>laginous nose tip were removed. The brain and remaining <lb/>skull structures were incubated in 4% PFA + 2 mM Pro-<lb/>Hance overnight at 4°C then transferred to 0.1 M PBS <lb/>containing 2 mM ProHance and 0.02% sodium azide for at <lb/>least 7 days prior to MRI scanning. <lb/>Image acquisition <lb/>Images were acquired on a 7 Tesla MRI scanner (Varian <lb/>Inc., Palo Alto, CA) 40,41 . The contrast required for image <lb/>registration and assessment of volume is not sufficient <lb/>with our typical T2-weighted imaging sequence. There-<lb/>fore, diffusion-weighted imaging was performed to <lb/>enhance the contrast between white and gray matter to <lb/>aid in the registration and volume measurements. <lb/>Diffusion imaging sequence <lb/>The diffusion sequence uses an in-house custom built <lb/>16-coil solenoid array to acquire images from 12 brains in <lb/>parallel 42 . The diffusion sequence used was a 3D <lb/>diffusion-weighted FSE, with TR = 270 ms, echo train <lb/>length = 6, first TE = 30 ms, TE = 10 ms for the remain-<lb/>ing 5 echoes, one average, FOV = 25 mm × 14 mm × <lb/>14 mm, and a matrix size of 450 × 250 × 250, which yiel-<lb/>ded an image with 56 µm isotropic voxels. One <lb/>b = 0 s/mm 2 image was acquired and 6 high b-value (b = <lb/>2147 s/mm 2 ) images were acquired in the following <lb/>directions (1, 1, 0), (1, 0, 1), (0, 1, 1), (−1, 1, 0), (−1, 0, 1), <lb/>and (0, 1, −1) corresponding to (G x , G y , G z ). Total ima-<lb/>ging time was~14 h. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Registration and analysis <lb/>To visualize and compare the mouse brains for anato-<lb/>mical volume assessment, the 6 high b-value images were <lb/>averaged together to make a high contrast image neces-<lb/>sary for accurate registration. Then these images were <lb/>linearly (6 parameter followed by a 12 parameter) and <lb/>nonlinearly registered together. All scans were then <lb/>resampled with an appropriate transform and averaged to <lb/>create a population atlas representing the average anat-<lb/>omy of the study sample. All registrations were performed <lb/>using a combination of the mni_autoreg tools 43 and <lb/>ANTS 44 . The result of the registration was to have all <lb/>scans deformed into exact alignment with each other in <lb/>an unbiased fashion. For the volume measurements, this <lb/>allowed for the analysis of the deformations needed to <lb/>take each individual mouse&apos;s anatomy into this final atlas <lb/>space, the goal being to model how the deformation fields <lb/>relate to genotype 40,45 . The Jacobian determinants of the <lb/>deformation fields are then calculated as measures of <lb/>volume at each voxel. These measurements were exam-<lb/>ined on a voxel-wise basis in order to localize the differ-<lb/>ences found within regions or across the brain. Multiple <lb/>comparisons were controlled for by using the False Dis-<lb/>covery Rate (FDR) 46 . <lb/>Fluorescent immunohistochemical staining and image <lb/>acquisition <lb/>Brain tissue was processed and a free-floating staining <lb/>method was used according to previously described <lb/>methods 47 . Briefly, after cardiac perfusion, brains were <lb/>removed and post-fixed, embedded in gelatin, cryopro-<lb/>tected in 30% sucrose, sectioned in the coronal or sagittal <lb/>plane using a cryostat. Sections were then incubated with <lb/>primary (anti-MBP, Millipore, MAB386, 1:500; anti-<lb/>CNPase, Developmental Studies Hybridoma Bank, <lb/>531796, 1:500; anti-PDGFRα, BD biosciences, Clone <lb/>APA5, 558774, 1:500; anti-Olig2, R&amp;D Systems, AF2418, <lb/>1:50; anti-CC1, Millipore, OP80, 1: 2,000) and corre-<lb/>sponding secondary antibodies 47 , as well as DAPI, before <lb/>being mounted onto slides. Images were then acquired <lb/>with a Zeiss LSM 510 confocal microscope or a Leica SP8 <lb/>confocal microscope. For an overview of myelination, tile <lb/>scans using a ×20 lens were conducted and the images <lb/>were stitched together using Zen software (Zeiss). <lb/>Cell counting <lb/>Z-stack confocal images spanning 20 μm depth were <lb/>collapsed and PDGFRα-positive cells were counted using <lb/>Imaris from both P2 and P8 animals in the following three <lb/>brain areas: dorsal lateral striatum, somatosensory cortex, <lb/>and external capsule, as the BTBR mice do not have <lb/>crossing corpus callosum. Four to six collapsed image <lb/>stacks from each brain region of each animal were used. <lb/>CC1-positive cells were imaged and counted in external <lb/>capsule region from P8 mice. Four to six images from <lb/>each animal were used. <lb/>Western blot <lb/>Brain regions of interest from mice of indicated ages <lb/>were dissected on ice and homogenized in RIPA buffer <lb/>(Pierce Biotechnology, MA) with protease and phospha-<lb/>tase inhibitor cocktails (Roche, QC). Homogenate was <lb/>centrifuged at × g for 10 min at 4°C. In all, 10-20 μg <lb/>of the protein extract was separated by SDS-PAGE, and <lb/>transferred to polyvinylidene fluoride membranes. After <lb/>blocking, blots were incubated with primary and corre-<lb/>sponding secondary antibodies, and visualized with an <lb/>enhanced chemiluminescence detection system. Bands <lb/>were imaged and quantified using a ChemiDOC MP gel <lb/>imaging system (Bio-Rad, CA). The following primary <lb/>antibodies were used: PDGFA, Santa Cruz, 1:100; <lb/>PDGFRα, Santa Cruz, sc-338, 1:200; MBP, Millipore, <lb/>MAB386, 1:100 (neonatal tissue) or 1:500 (adult tissue); <lb/>PLP, Santa Cruz, sc-98781, 1:400; actin, Cell Signaling, <lb/>4967, 1:10,000. The relative expression levels of a protein <lb/>were quantified by normalization using actin levels. When <lb/>quantifying western blot results, full size images without <lb/>any saturation were used. In addition, images of longer <lb/>exposure time were taken to ensure that the location of <lb/>even the weakest band was clear when drawing the region <lb/>of interest for analysis. <lb/>Quantitative RT-PCR <lb/>RNA was isolated from striatum using RNeasy mini kit <lb/>(Qiagen). cDNA was synthesized from 1 μg of total RNA <lb/>using an iScript gDNA Clear cDNA Synthesis Kit (Bio-<lb/>Rad). qRT-PCR was performed using 10 ng of cDNA in a <lb/>20-μL reaction using SsoFast EvaGreen Supermix (Bio-<lb/>Rad). Primer pairs (IDT) were used at a concentration of <lb/>0.375 μM. qPCR was performed in duplicate using the <lb/>following protocol: 95°C 2 min, 40 cycles of 95°C 15 s and <lb/>60°C 30 s, and then 75°C 10 s, followed by a melt curve <lb/>procedure on a Bio-Rad CFX96 qPCR machine. Cycle <lb/>thresholds (Ct) were determined by the software CFX <lb/>manager (Bio-Rad). Primer sequences used for qRT-PCR <lb/>to quantify mRNA levels of major myelin-related genes: <lb/>CNP For_ TTTACCCGCAAAAGCCACACA; CNP Rev_ <lb/>CACCGTGTCCTCATCTTGAAG; MBP For_ GACCA <lb/>TCCAAGAAGACCCCAC; MBP Rev_GCCATAATGGG <lb/>TAGTTCTCGTGT; PLP 1 For_ CCAGAATGTAT <lb/>GGTGTTCTCCC; PLP 1 Rev_ GGCCCATGAGT <lb/>TTAAGGACG. Primer sequences of house keeping <lb/>genes: HRPT1 For_ GCTGACCTGCTGGATTACAT; <lb/>HRPT1 Rev_ TTGGGGCTGTACTGCTTAAC; Ppia For_ <lb/>AGCTCTGAGCACTGGAGAGA; Ppia Rev_ GCCA <lb/>GGACCTGTATGCTTTA; Rpl13a For_ ATGACA <lb/>AGAAAAAGCGGATG; Rpl13a Rev_ CTTTTCT <lb/>GCCTGTTTCCGTA. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>For microRNA quantification, total RNA was isolated <lb/>from brain samples using miRCURY RNA isolation kit <lb/>(Exiqon) according to the manufactures instructions <lb/>using the modified protocol for fatty tissue. cDNA was <lb/>synthesized from 10 ng total RNA using a universal cDNA <lb/>synthesis kit (Exiqon). qRT-PCR was performed using <lb/>0.05 ng of cDNA in a 10-μL reaction using Exilent syber <lb/>green (Exiqon). LNA primer mixes (Exiqon) were used. <lb/>qPCR was performed in duplicate using the following <lb/>protocol: 95°C 10 min, 40 cycles of 95°C 10 s and 60°C <lb/>60 s, and then 60°C 5 s, followed by a melt curve proce-<lb/>dure on a Bio-Rad CFX96 qPCR machine. <lb/>Geometric mean of the Ct values of the housekeeping <lb/>genes were calculated using the program BestKeeper 48 , to <lb/>obtain reference Ct values. The relative abundance of <lb/>transcript of genes of interest was then analyzed using the <lb/>REST software 49 . <lb/>Transmission electron microscopy, image collection, and <lb/>computation of the g-ratio <lb/>Brain areas of interest were rapidly dissected. A por-<lb/>tion of the optic nerve anterior to the optic chiasm was <lb/>used. Dissected tissue was then immersed in 2% paraf-<lb/>ormaldehyde and 2.5% glutaraldehyde in 0.1 M cacody-<lb/>late buffer at pH 7.4 for 2 h at 4°C. After washing three <lb/>times with the same buffer, the samples were post-fixed <lb/>in 1% osmium tetroxide buffered with cacodylate for 1 h <lb/>at room temperature, dehydrated through a graded ser-<lb/>ies of ethanol and embedded in Spurr&apos;s resin. Thick <lb/>sections were cut, stained with 1% toluidine blue and <lb/>examined using a light microscope in order to select <lb/>appropriate areas. Ultrathin sections were cut with a <lb/>Leica EM UC7 ultramicrotome using a diamond knife <lb/>and stained with 2% aqueous uranyl acetate and Rey-<lb/>nolds&apos;s lead citrate. Optic nerve, external capsule (BTBR <lb/>mice do not have crossing corpus callosum) and dorsal <lb/>striatum at indicated ages were analyzed. Samples were <lb/>observed using a Hitachi H7650 transmission electron <lb/>microscope at 80 kV. Images were taken through an <lb/>AMT600 digital camera mounted on the microscope. <lb/>Images were collected from multiple (more than 3 for <lb/>optic nerve at P9 and more than 7 for corpus callosum <lb/>and striatum at adulthood), randomly chosen locations <lb/>of each sample. <lb/>To quantify the relative thickness of the myelin sheath, <lb/>g-ratios were computed for individual axons 50 . Both the <lb/>inner perimeter around the axon and the outer perimeter <lb/>around the intact myelin sheath were outlined manually <lb/>using ImageJ and a custom code was used to quantify the <lb/>pixels in the inner and outer perimeters. Then the inner <lb/>axonal diameter and the total outer diameter including <lb/>the myelin sheath were computed and the ratio of the two <lb/>(g-ratio) was plotted against axonal diameter. This pro-<lb/>cedure allowed for inclusion of irregularly shaped axons <lb/>and helped to eliminate bias based on circularity . <lb/>Totally, 316 axons in corpus callosum and 280 axons in <lb/>striatum of four B6 mice, and 346 axons in corpus cal-<lb/>losum and 291 axons in striatum of four BTBR mice were <lb/>analyzed. Experimenters who counted myelinated axons <lb/>or outlined axonal and myelin sheath perimeter were <lb/>blind to the genotype of the samples. <lb/>Statistical analysis <lb/>All sample sizes (n) are numbers of animals used. <lb/>Sample sizes were determined based on similar published <lb/>studies and the observed results. Student&apos;s t-test was <lb/>performed to determine statistical significance between <lb/>the sets of BTBR and B6 data, assuming two-tailed dis-<lb/>tribution and two-sample unequal variance. Distribution <lb/>normality was calculated using Shapiro-Wilk test. If the <lb/>data were not normally distributed, Mann-Whitney U <lb/>test was used instead. Values represented the mean ± <lb/>SEM, except the qRT-PCR results, which were repre-<lb/>sented by box and whisker plots generated by the REST <lb/>program. Two-way repeated measure ANOVA followed <lb/>by post hoc Tukey&apos;s test was used to compare distribution <lb/>of axonal area in the optic nerve between the B6 and <lb/>BTBR mice. One-way ANOVA or one-way ANOVA on <lb/>ranks (when normality test failed) followed by post hoc <lb/>test was used to compare relative expression levels of <lb/>MBP and PLP among BTBR, B6, and 129 strains of mice. <lb/>*P &lt; 0.05; **P &lt; 0.01; ***P &lt; 0.001. <lb/>Results <lb/>Increased volume of white matter tracts in frontal brain <lb/>regions of the BTBR mice during neonatal development <lb/>We first explored whether atypical development of <lb/>white matter, similar to that in human patients, was also <lb/>observed in the BTBR model. To this end, we measured <lb/>volumes of white matter tracts in neonatal male BTBR <lb/>brains at postnatal day 6 (P6), P8 and P10 using mag-<lb/>netic resonance imaging (MRI). The results were com-<lb/>pared with that from age-matched male B6 mice, which <lb/>display normal levels of sociability and repetitive beha-<lb/>viors and are most often used as the control strain for <lb/>the BTBR mice in autism-related studies 31-35 . Brains of <lb/>ten mice of each strain at each age were imaged and <lb/>analyzed. Results revealed that at P6, four (lateral <lb/>olfactory tract, anterior commissure pars anterior, optic <lb/>tract, and posterior commissure) out of 13 white matter <lb/>tracts had significantly increased volumes in the BTBR <lb/>mice (false discovery rate all &lt;0.007), while the volumes <lb/>of the other fiber tracts were not statistically different <lb/>from those in the B6 mice, with most displaying a trend <lb/>of decreased volume (Fig. 1a). At P8 and P10, the <lb/>increase in the volume of lateral olfactory tract, anterior <lb/>commissure pars anterior, and posterior commissure <lb/>was reduced so that the BTBR and B6 brains had similar <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>volumes of these tracts. The increase in the volume <lb/>of the optic tract in the BTBR brain stayed relatively <lb/>constant for this period. On the other hand, other <lb/>fiber tracts displayed decreased or similar volumes in <lb/>the BTBR brain at these ages (Fig. 1a). Note that the <lb/>corpus callosum in the BTBR mice does not cross the <lb/>midline 36-38 , but instead forms the Probst bundle, and <lb/>started to display significantly decreased volume from <lb/>P8. Together, these data revealed that during this short <lb/>period of early development, white matter tracts in the <lb/>BTBR brain exhibited spatially and temporally dynamic <lb/>alterations compared with the B6 brain: those located <lb/>more anteriorly displayed an initial increase in volumes, <lb/>which reduced rapidly in two out of three cases; whereas <lb/>those located more posteriorly had similar or decreased <lb/>volumes, except that posterior commissure showed an <lb/>initial increase at P6 (Fig. 1a). This is reminiscent of the <lb/>observations from young children with ASD that show <lb/>increased volume of fiber tracts in mostly frontal regions <lb/>of the brain, but a slower rate of continued development, <lb/>resulting in similar volumes of these fiber tracts in older <lb/>children 6-15 . <lb/>Fig. 1 Increased volume of white matter tracts in the frontal brain of the BTBR mice during neonatal development. a Comparison of mean <lb/>volume of white matter tracts at P6, P8, and P10 between B6 and BTBR mice using MRI. Results revealed that fiber tracts in frontal brain regions of the <lb/>BTBR mice had greater volume at P6, but the difference reduced over time in two out of three cases. n = 10 mice for each strain at each age. <lb/>b Representative TEM images of the optic nerve from B6 or BTBR mice at P9, and quantification of axons with compact myelin in optic nerve at this <lb/>age. Totally, 208 images from five B6 mice and 153 images from four BTBR mice were analyzed. Yellow arrows indicate examples of axons wrapped <lb/>by compact myelin. c Distribution of axonal cross-section area across different size bins in B6 and BTBR optic nerve. Totally, 8951axons from four B6 <lb/>mice and 10,182 axons from four BTBR mice were analyzed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Increased myelination during neonatal development in the <lb/>frontal brain of both male and female BTBR mice <lb/>Next, we examined whether greater volume of anterior <lb/>fiber tracts in neonatal BTBR brain could be due to <lb/>increased myelination. Results from MRI indicated that <lb/>the optic tract in the BTBR mice had a greater volume <lb/>than that in the B6 mice from P6 to P10 (Fig. 1a). Thus, <lb/>we first examined the optic nerve at P9 using electron <lb/>microscopy and quantified axons with compact myelin in <lb/>cross sections. Results revealed that BTBR mice had sig-<lb/>nificantly greater number of myelinated axons than the B6 <lb/>mice (Fig. 1b), indicating increased myelination could <lb/>contribute to the increased volume of the optic tract in <lb/>the BTBR mice. As axonal size influences initiation of <lb/>myelination in the optic nerve 51 , we measured cross sec-<lb/>tional area of axons in the optic nerve and compared the <lb/>distribution of axonal area between the B6 and BTBR <lb/>mice. Results indicated that there was a trend of an <lb/>increased proportion of the smallest axons and decreased <lb/>proportions of mid-sized ones in the BTBR mice, but no <lb/>significant difference between the two strains at any size <lb/>range we compared (Fig. 1c), suggesting that increased <lb/>volume of the optic tract in the BTBR mice was not due to <lb/>greater volume of individual axons, and that size of the <lb/>axons probably did not contribute to the increased mye-<lb/>lination in this model. <lb/>Next, we probed myelin development using immuno-<lb/>fluorescence staining of myelin basic protein (MBP), an <lb/>integral component and specific marker of myelin 52-56 , <lb/>whose cellular expression pattern has been widely used <lb/>to characterize myelination process. We observed <lb/>increased MBP signal in male BTBR brains at P6, com-<lb/>pared with age-and sex-matched B6 mice. Close exam-<lb/>ination revealed that MBP signal was located in many <lb/>cells in the BTBR frontal brain, including corpus callo-<lb/>sum and dorsal striatum, and to a lesser extent, the <lb/>cortex. Most of the positive cells displayed MBP signal in <lb/>both cell bodies and numerous processes, with some <lb/>already aligned in parallel tube-like structures pre-<lb/>sumably wrapping around axons. On the contrary, only a <lb/>few MBP-positive cells could be identified in the same <lb/>brain regions in the B6 brain, with the signal mostly <lb/>restricted to the cell bodies (Fig. 2a). At P8, MBP signal in <lb/>the BTBR frontal brain showed clear organization of <lb/>myelin sheath in the corpus callosum and dorsal stria-<lb/>tum, with dispersed positive cells in the cortex, while the <lb/>same staining showed mostly scattered signal in the same <lb/>brain regions in the B6 brain (Fig. 2b). A similar differ-<lb/>ence was observed in immunofluorescence staining of <lb/>2′,3′-cyclic nucleotide 3′-phosphodiesterase (CNP) as <lb/>well (Fig. 2c). In older pups aged P10 (Fig. 2d) and P12 <lb/>(Fig. 2e), MBP signal continued to increase rapidly in <lb/>both mouse strains; however, it spread further into more <lb/>dorsal regions of the cortex and ventral striatum in the <lb/>BTBR than the B6 brain. Totally, we examined two to <lb/>four mice of each strain at each age. <lb/>We also observed similar increased MBP signal in <lb/>female BTBR brains during neonatal development. At P6, <lb/>there were more cells with MBP-positive processes in the <lb/>corpus callosum and dorsal striatum of the BTBR than the <lb/>B6 brain (Fig. 2f). At P8, more widespread MBP signal was <lb/>observed in the corpus callosum and dorsal striatum in <lb/>the BTBR mice (Fig. 2g). Thus, both male and female <lb/>BTBR mice had increased MBP-positive myelin structure <lb/>during neonatal development. <lb/>Increased myelination suggested more abundant mature <lb/>oligodendrocytes in the BTBR brain. Indeed, staining <lb/>against CC1, a specific marker for mature oligoden-<lb/>drocytes, revealed that there was a significant increase in <lb/>the number of positive cells in the BTBR mice compared <lb/>with the B6 mice (Fig. 2h, i), corroborating the notion that <lb/>myelination was elevated in the BTBR mice. <lb/>Upregulated MBP expression accompanied increased <lb/>myelination in neonatal BTBR mice <lb/>As mentioned earlier, MBP is an essential component of <lb/>mature compact myelin in the central nervous system, and <lb/>has been considered as the &apos;executive molecule of myelin&apos;, <lb/>serving multiple functions beyond structural support 52-56 . <lb/>In addition, expression of MBP is a rate-limiting step in <lb/>myelination in the central nervous system 52-56 . Here, we <lb/>further quantified the protein expression level of MBP in <lb/>the striatum, and found it was significantly increased in P8 <lb/>male BTBR mice compared with two other age-and sex-<lb/>matched inbred mouse strains: B6 and 129 (Fig. 3a, c). In <lb/>contrast, the protein levels of myelin proteolipid protein <lb/>(PLP), the most abundant protein of myelin in the central <lb/>nervous system 57,58 , were similar among all three strains of <lb/>mice (Fig. 3b, c), indicating that upregulated MBP protein <lb/>expression is associated with the increased myelination <lb/>observed in the BTBR mice. Further experiments indicated <lb/>that there was no significant difference in the mRNA levels <lb/>of myelin-related genes MBP, CNP, or PLP1, encoding <lb/>MBP, CNP, or PLP, respectively, between the BTBR and <lb/>B6 mice at P8 (Fig. 3d). These results suggest that the <lb/>increased protein level of MBP in the BTBR mice is likely <lb/>due to alterations in translation or post-translational <lb/>processing, instead of transcription of the gene. <lb/>Similar myelin pattern and thickness in adolescent and <lb/>adult B6 and BTBR frontal brain <lb/>We further followed myelin development using immu-<lb/>nofluorescence staining of MBP into older ages. At P35, <lb/>we did not observe any obvious difference in the frontal <lb/>brain between male BTBR and B6 mice (Fig. 4a) (n = 4 <lb/>mice for each strain). In addition, relative protein <lb/>expression levels of MBP and PLP in the striatum were <lb/>also similar between adult male BTBR and B6 animals <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2 Increased myelination during neonatal development in the frontal brain of both male and female BTBR mice. a At P6, MBP signal was <lb/>located in many cells in male BTBR frontal brain (right panels), including corpus callosum and dorsal striatum, and to a less extent, the cortex. Most of <lb/>the positive cells had MBP signal in both cell bodies and numerous processes, with some already aligned in parallel tube-like structures presumably <lb/>wrapping around axons. On the contrary, only a few MBP-positive cells could be identified in the same brain region in the B6 brain (left panels), with <lb/>the signal mostly restricted to the cell bodies. Dotted lines outline corpus callosum. Boxed region is shown in higher magnification in the right panel <lb/>next to it. (b) At P8, MBP signal in the BTBR frontal brain showed clear organization of myelin sheath in the corpus callosum and dorsal striatum, with <lb/>dispersed positive cells in the cortex, while the same staining showed mostly scattered signal in the same brain regions in the B6 mice. Similar <lb/>difference was observed in CNP immunofluorescence staining as well (c). d, e At P10 and P12, MBP signal continued to increase rapidly in both <lb/>strains; however, it spread further into more superficial regions of the cortex and ventral striatum in the BTBR than the B6 brain. Similarly increased <lb/>MBP signal in female BTBR brains during neonatal development was observed at P6 (f) and P8 (g). n = 2 to 4 for each strain at each age of each sex. <lb/>White arrows in a, f indicate examples of MBP signal located in presumably myelin sheath that was starting to form. (h) CC1 (a specific marker for <lb/>mature oligodendrocytes) and DAPI co-staining in external capsule region from P8 mice. White arrows indicate examples of CC1-positive cells. <lb/>i Quantification of CC1-positive cells in the B6 and BTBR mice <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Fig. 4b). Using electron microscopy, we observed typical <lb/>myelination pattern and myelin micro structure in corpus <lb/>callosum and dorsal lateral striatum from both adult <lb/>male BTBR and B6 brains (Fig. 4c, d). Furthermore, the <lb/>g-ratios 50 of axons in both brain regions were similar <lb/>between the two strains, indicating that the relative <lb/>thickness of myelin was not altered (Fig. 4e). Thus, <lb/>increased myelination in the frontal brain of the BTBR <lb/>mice only appeared during neonatal development; both <lb/>BTBR and B6 mice reached similar degree of myelination <lb/>at adult stage. <lb/>PDGFRα signaling was reduced in the frontal brain of <lb/>neonatal BTBR mice <lb/>Based on these data, we investigated PDGFRα signaling, <lb/>as it is specifically expressed by oligodendrocyte precursor <lb/>cells (OPCs) 59,60 and critical in regulating the timing of <lb/>their differentiation, such that it is down-regulated when <lb/>OPCs stop proliferation to start differentiation. Extensive <lb/>studies indicate that PDGFRα level is a negative regulator <lb/>of the biological clock controlling the maturation process <lb/>of OPCs 61-67 . Using immunofluorescence staining (Fig. <lb/>5a-d), we found that the number of PDGFRα-positive <lb/>cells were slightly, but not significantly, decreased in the <lb/>corpus callosum, somatosensory cortex, and dorsal stria-<lb/>tum of the BTBR mice compared with the B6 mice at both <lb/>P2 and P8 (Fig. 5e, f). Meanwhile, the protein expression <lb/>level of PDGFRα (Fig. 5g, h) was significantly reduced in <lb/>the frontal brain of the BTBR mice at both P2 and P8 (Fig. <lb/>5i, j), while the expression level of PDGFA, the ligand of <lb/>PDGFRα involved in the timing of OPC differentiation, <lb/>was similar between the two strains (Fig. 5g-j). Thus, <lb/>PDGFRα signaling was reduced in the OPCs in the frontal <lb/>brain of neonatal BTBR mice, consistent with accelerated <lb/>myelin development observed in the same region. <lb/>Recent studies have uncovered important roles of <lb/>microRNAs in regulating myelination during develop-<lb/>ment 68-71 . Several microRNA species, including miR-219, <lb/>338, 138, and 23a, have been shown to inhibit expression <lb/>of PDGFRα 72-74 . Thus, we tested whether changes in <lb/>PDGFRα protein expression observed in the BTBR mice <lb/>could be due to altered levels of these microRNAs. <lb/>Quantitative RT-PCR of these microRNA species in the <lb/>frontal brain showed that there was no difference in <lb/>abundance between BTBR and B6 mice at both P2 and P8 <lb/>(Fig. 5k, l), suggesting that these microRNAs are unlikely <lb/>to contribute to the accelerated myelination observed in <lb/>the BTBR mice. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Development of myelin in ASD patients <lb/>Although neuroimaging studies on older children, <lb/>adolescents, and adults with ASD have generally shown <lb/>hypo-connectivity of brain circuits, more recent studies <lb/>on young children (1-4 year old) have suggested the <lb/>opposite may be the case, that is, hyper-connectivity <lb/>during early neurodevelopment 6-15 . However, the cellular <lb/>and molecular substrates of the hyper-connectivity <lb/>remain poorly understood. In these studies, increased <lb/>FA and in some cases greater volume were observed <lb/>within several fiber tracts that innervate the frontal lobes, <lb/>commissural fibers, long-range association tracts, and <lb/>thalamocortical projection fibers in the ASD population, <lb/>followed by overall slower than typical apparent rate of <lb/>continued development. Notably, the relationship <lb/>between diffusion and volume measures and severity of <lb/>social and communication symptoms was dependent on <lb/>the age at which the neuroimaging measurement took <lb/>place: greater FA and volume of frontal tracts in early <lb/>years predicted greater symptom severity later at the age <lb/>of final diagnosis, whereas a trend toward the opposite <lb/>relationship (lower FA and volume correlated with greater <lb/>severity) was observed for frontal tracts measured at older <lb/>ages, suggesting that greater abnormality in early growth <lb/>may be associated with greater severity of symptoms <lb/>observed later 6 . One possible reason of increased FA is <lb/>greater extent of myelination. Thus, it could be reasoned <lb/>Fig. 3 Upregulated MBP expression accompanied increased <lb/>myelination. Western blot examining MBP (a) and PLP (b) protein <lb/>expression in striatal homogenates from P8 mice. c Quantification of <lb/>relative protein expression levels of MBP and PLP normalized by actin. <lb/>d Relative mRNA expression levels of MBP, CNP, and PLP1 in striatal <lb/>homogenates from P8 mice, presented as a ratio of BTBR to B6 levels <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>that accelerated myelination could potentially contribute <lb/>to the hyper-connectivity during early development of <lb/>ASD, among other factors such as increased numbers of <lb/>axons 23,75 . <lb/>Increased brain volume, especially in young children <lb/>with ASD, has been a consistent finding 19,20,76 , resulting <lb/>from both gray and white matter increases 6,15 . Although <lb/>involvement of myelination in increased brain volume is <lb/>not clear, it is possible that it also plays an important but <lb/>so far underappreciated role. <lb/>Neuroimaging studies on myelin per se in ASD patients <lb/>are very limited, due to technical limitations. Notably, a <lb/>recent study utilized magnetization transfer imaging, <lb/>which has been shown to indirectly represent myelina-<lb/>tion during development , to compare 101 young chil-<lb/>dren with autism (mean age = 4.5) and 35 typically <lb/>developing children (mean age = 4.0), including both <lb/>boys and girls. The magnetization transfer ratio (MTR) <lb/>was calculated for each voxel within the midsagittal area <lb/>of the corpus callosum. Mean MTR as well as MTR <lb/>Fig. 4 Similar myelin pattern and thickness in adolescent and adult B6 and BTBR frontal brain. a At P35, the pattern of MBP <lb/>immunofluorescent signal was similar in the frontal brain between male B6 and BTBR mice. n = 4 mice for each strain. b Relative expression levels of <lb/>striatal MBP and PLP proteins were also similar between B6 and BTBR adult male animals at 8-10 weeks old. c Schematic indicating the locations and <lb/>regions where tissue was dissected (boxes), and the planes of tissue sectioning (dotted lines) for EM analysis. d Electron microscopy showed typical <lb/>myelination pattern and myelin micro structure in corpus callosum (cc) and striatum (CP) from both adult male BTBR and B6 brains. Images of both <lb/>lower (upper panels) and higher (lower panels) magnifications are shown. e The g-ratios of axons in both brain regions were similar between the B6 <lb/>and BTBR mice. Totally, 316 axons in corpus callosum and 280 axons in striatum from four B6 mice, and 346 axons in corpus callosum and 291 axons <lb/>in striatum from four BTBR mice were analyzed <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 5 PDGFRα signaling was reduced in neonatal frontal brain of the BTBR mice. a Co-immunofluorescence staining of PDGFRα and <lb/>Olig2 showed that PDGFRα-positive cells also expressed Olig2, another marker for oligodrendroglial lineage. White arrows indicate examples of cells <lb/>that are positive for both PDGFRα and Olig2. b-d PDGFRα and DAPI co-staining for cell counting purpose in the corpus callosum (cc), somatosensory <lb/>cortex (CTX), and striatum (CP). White arrows indicate examples of cells that are positive for PDGFRα. e, f Quantification of PDGFRα-positive cells at <lb/>both P2 and P8 in the three brain regions. g, h Western blots showing the protein expression levels of PDGFRα and PDGFA at both P2 and P8. <lb/>i, j Quantification of western blot results indicated that relative expression levels of PDGFRα were significantly reduced in the BTBR compared with <lb/>the B6 mice at both P2 and P8, while relative expression levels of PDGFA were similar between the two strains of mice at both ages. k, l Relative levels <lb/>of miR-219, 138, 338, and 23a in striatal homogenates from P2 and P8 mice, presented as a ratio of BTBR to B6 levels <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>histogram peak height and location were significantly <lb/>higher in children with autism, suggesting accelerated <lb/>myelination of the corpus callosum in very young chil-<lb/>dren with autism 30 . <lb/>Histological studies of postmortem patient brain tissue <lb/>have been very rare, especially from samples of young <lb/>children. Ultrastructural investigation of postmortem <lb/>adult brain tissue revealed decreased myelin thickness in <lb/>fibers beneath the orbitofrontal cortex 75 . It would be <lb/>important to determine whether such abnormalities are <lb/>present in young ASD population and how they might <lb/>change over time during development. <lb/>The consequences of accelerated myelination during <lb/>brain development are less well understood. Notably, <lb/>accelerated myelination is frequently observed in infants <lb/>with hemimegalencephaly, a rare neurological condition <lb/>characterized by frequent seizures, usually followed by <lb/>mental retardation 78 , both of which are comorbidities <lb/>of ASD. <lb/>Development of myelin in animal models of ASD <lb/>Studies on myelination using animal models of ASD <lb/>have also been very limited. Thus far, these studies have <lb/>found delayed myelination in general. One study reported <lb/>a delay in myelination accompanied by reduced OPC <lb/>number in the cerebellum, and smaller cerebellar volume <lb/>in Fmr1 knockout mice during early postnatal develop-<lb/>ment. Interestingly, although the amounts of myelin <lb/>specific proteins are reduced in neonatal mutant mice, <lb/>they reach similar levels, or even surpass those observed <lb/>in the wildtype control animals in adulthood . Another <lb/>study showed that maternal immune activation in mice <lb/>delays myelination and axonal development in the hip-<lb/>pocampus, but not cortex, of the offspring, and the defi-<lb/>cits disappear when the animals reach the adult stage 80 . In <lb/>addition, disruption of the tuberous sclerosis complex <lb/>(TSC) leads to hypomyelination 81,82 . Interestingly, in a rat <lb/>model of diffuse white matter injury, which is a major <lb/>complication in preterm infants and associated with <lb/>psychological conditions including ASD, delayed cortical <lb/>myelination and ASD-like behaviors were observed 83 . <lb/>Together, these studies suggest that different etiologies <lb/>underlying ASD may affect development of myelin <lb/>differently. <lb/>Here, our study showed precocious myelination in the <lb/>frontal brain of the BTBR mouse model of ASD. <lb/>According to previous studies, oligodendrocyte matura-<lb/>tion and myelination in neonatal mice around P6 to P12 <lb/>corresponds to term infants (36-40 week) in humans 84,85 , <lb/>when the brain experiences peak growth spurt and glio-<lb/>genesis, and the predominance of oligodendrocyte <lb/>maturation state changes from pre-oligodendrocytes to <lb/>immature oligodendrocytes. Our findings suggest accel-<lb/>erated myelin development could potentially contribute to <lb/>hyper-connectivity and increased brain volume typically <lb/>observed in young children with ASD. However, myelin <lb/>pattern and thickness were unaltered in adult BTBR ani-<lb/>mals, suggesting a blunted developmental trajectory, <lb/>reminiscent of what has been observed in ASD patients. <lb/>Thus, precocious myelination in the BTBR mice could <lb/>potentially serve as a model to investigate the mechanisms <lb/>and consequences of atypical myelin development in ASD. <lb/>Mechanisms underlying precocious myelination in the <lb/>BTBR mice <lb/>MBP has long been recognized as a crucial component <lb/>of mature myelin in the central nervous system. It is <lb/>responsible for adhesion of the cytosolic surface between <lb/>multiple layers of compact myelin. Mice harboring shi-<lb/>verer spontaneous mutation in the MBP gene have poorly <lb/>formed myelin 53 . Further studies showed that the <lb/>expression of MBP is a rate-limiting step in myelination in <lb/>the central nervous system 54,55 . In contrast, ablation of <lb/>other major myelin proteins such as PLP 57,58 and CNP 86 <lb/>seems to induce secondary axonal consequences rather <lb/>than affecting myelination process per se. Besides struc-<lb/>tural functions in myelin, MBP also actively participate in <lb/>other processes during myelination, and thus has been <lb/>referred to as the &apos;executive molecule of myelin&apos; 52,56 . The <lb/>importance of MBP for myelination is supported by the <lb/>notion that the emergence of MBP in ancient jawed fish <lb/>conferred myelination ability, which sped up the velocity <lb/>of nerve conduction more than 20-fold. Without MBP <lb/>and myelin, jawed vertebrates as we know them, including <lb/>humans, could not have evolved 87,88 . Interestingly, we <lb/>observed an increase in MBP protein, but not the mRNA, <lb/>expression levels in the BTBR mice (Fig. 3). As MBP is <lb/>transported in oligodendrocytes as mRNA rather than <lb/>protein, it has been suggested that localized translation of <lb/>MBP is advantageous for rapid and axon-tailored synth-<lb/>esis of the molecule as the required amounts may vary at <lb/>distinct axonal segments, and that localized translation of <lb/>MBP is tightly regulated 89 . Thus, it is plausible that <lb/>altered translation contributes to increased MBP protein <lb/>levels in the BTBR mice. It was also observed that the <lb/>protein levels of MBP appeared quite variable in P8 ani-<lb/>mals even among the same strain of mice (Fig. 3). A <lb/>possible reason was that during neonatal development <lb/>when MBP was just beginning to be expressed and <lb/>increased rapidly, individual variations might be more <lb/>than those when myelination had reached a stable level, as <lb/>observed in adult animals (Fig. 4). <lb/>The role of PDGFRα in determining the timing of OPC <lb/>differentiation has been extensively studied. PDGFRα is <lb/>the only PDGF receptor isoform expressed on OPCs 59,60 . <lb/>During OPC differentiation, expression of PDGFRα in <lb/>OPCs progressively decreases and then is rapidly extin-<lb/>guished in mature oligodendrocytes 63,64 . PDGF is a major <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<body>mitogen for OPC proliferation 65 , although PDGF signal-<lb/>ing is unlikely the only mechanism determining the final <lb/>numbers of oligodendrocyte 38 , as alterations of its levels <lb/>do not affect the levels of myelin at maturity 90 . Mean-<lb/>while, PDGF signaling has also been shown to inhibit <lb/>differentiation of OPCs into oligodendrocytes. With-<lb/>drawal of PDGF from culture medium triggers differ-<lb/>entiation of OPCs 61,62,65 . Consistently, genetic ablation of <lb/>PDGFRα also leads to precocious differentiation of OPCs <lb/>both in vitro and in vivo, and accelerated myelination 66,67 . <lb/>These results indicate that PDGFRα level is a negative <lb/>regulator of the biological clock controlling the matura-<lb/>tion process of OPCs. Thus, reduced PDGFRα signaling in <lb/>neonatal BTBR brain could potentially result in the <lb/>accelerated myelination we have observed. <lb/>Notably, studies using the BTBR mice have uncovered <lb/>profound alterations in both structural and functional <lb/>connectivity 32,36,91-96 , the most striking one being the <lb/>non-crossing corpus callosum in these animals 31,36-38 . In <lb/>addition, our previous work revealed impaired synaptic <lb/>pruning and dendritic overgrowth during neonatal devel-<lb/>opment in the BTBR brain 97,98 . The relation between these <lb/>changes and the accelerated myelination observed here <lb/>needs to be examined in the future. In addition, the total <lb/>number of axons in white matter tracts in the BTBR mice <lb/>has not been determined. Future studies to examine <lb/>parameters such as whether, where, and to what degree <lb/>axon number may alter could reveal additional axonal <lb/>abnormalities in this mouse model. <lb/>In summary, this study revealed precocious myelination <lb/>in a mouse model of autism. The high prevalence of ASD <lb/>and the grave cost associated with psychological, physio-<lb/>logical, and socioeconomic burden call for improved <lb/>understanding of the early developmental pathophysiol-<lb/>ogy, which may best reveal fundamental biological <lb/>underpinnings of ASD, and would also assist early diag-<lb/>nosis and inform therapeutic options, as well as help to <lb/>identify high-risk individuals. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We would like to thank Dr. Khalil Rawji for providing insightful comments; Rose <lb/>Tobias and Evelyn Ko for general laboratory administration and maintenance; <lb/>Wei-Xiang Dong for sample preparation of TEM. This work was funded by <lb/>the Alberta Children&apos;s Hospital Research Institute at the University of Calgary <lb/>(J.M.R.), Brain Canada (J.P.L.), Canadian Institutes of Health Research (J.P.L.), and <lb/>the Ontario Brain Institute (J.P.L.). <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Developmental Neurosciences Research Program, Alberta Children&apos;s Hospital <lb/>Research Institute (ACHRI), Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, <lb/>Calgary, AB, Canada. 2 Mouse Imaging Centre (MICe), Hospital for Sick Children, <lb/>Toronto, ON, Canada. 3 Department of Electrical and Computer Engineering, <lb/>Schulich School of Engineering, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, Canada. <lb/>4 <lb/>Departments of Pediatrics, Clinical Neurosciences, Physiology &amp; <lb/>Pharmacology, Alberta Children&apos;s Hospital Research Institute and Hotchkiss <lb/>Brain Institute, Cumming School of Medicine, University of Calgary, Calgary, AB, <lb/>Canada. 5 Present address: University of California, San Diego; Division of <lb/>Pediatric Neurology, Rady Children&apos;s Hospital San Diego, California, USA <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>N.C. designed the study and participated in the experiments and data analysis, <lb/>and drafted the manuscript. M.K., E.H. J.E., L.R.Q., J.P.L., R.Y. and J.D. helped to <lb/>design the study, participated in the experiments and data analysis, and <lb/>helped to draft the manuscript. K.M. participated in the data analysis and <lb/>helped to draft the manuscript. J.M.R. helped to design the study. All authors <lb/>read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>The authors declare that they have no conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Publisher&apos;s note <lb/>Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in <lb/>published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/></div>

			<front>Received: 9 January 2019 Revised: 4 September 2019 Accepted: 19 <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. DiCicco-Bloom, E. et al. The developmental neurobiology of autism spectrum <lb/>disorder. J. Neurosci. 26, 6897-6906 (2006). <lb/>2. Lai, M. C., Lombardo, M. V. &amp; Baron-Cohen, S. Autism. Lancet 383, 896-910 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>3. Maximo, J. O., Cadena, E. J. &amp; Kana, R. K. The implications of brain <lb/>connectivity in the neuropsychology of autism. Neuropsychol. Rev. 24, <lb/>16-31 (2014). <lb/>4. Lord C., Elsabbagh M., Baird G., Veenstra-Vanderweele J. Autism spectrum <lb/>disorder. Lancet 392, 508-520 (2018). <lb/>5. Travers, B. G. et al. Diffusion tensor imaging in autism spectrum disorder: a <lb/>review. Autism Res. 5, 289-313 (2012). <lb/>6. Solso, S. et al. Diffusion tensor imaging provides evidence of possible axonal <lb/>overconnectivity in frontal lobes in autism spectrum disorder toddlers. Biol. <lb/>Psychiatry 79, 676-684 (2016). <lb/>7. Ben Bashat, D. et al. Accelerated maturation of white matter in young children <lb/>with autism: a high b value DWI study. NeuroImage 37, 40-47 (2007). <lb/>8. Wolff, J. J. et al. Differences in white matter fiber tract development present <lb/>from 6 to 24 months in infants with autism. Am. J. Psychiatry 169, 589-600 <lb/>(2012). <lb/>9. Weinstein, M. et al. Abnormal white matter integrity in young children with <lb/>autism. Hum. Brain Mapp. 32, 534-543 (2011). <lb/>10. Conti, E. et al. The first 1000 days of the autistic brain: a systematic review of <lb/>diffusion imaging studies. Front. Hum. Neurosci. 9, 159 (2015). <lb/>11. Bohland, J. W. Toward a multimodal, multiscale understanding of white matter <lb/>abnormalities in autism spectrum disorder. Biol. Psychiatry 79, e47-e48 (2016). <lb/>12. Wolff J. J., Jacob S., Elison J. T. The journey to autism: insights from neuroi-<lb/>maging studies of infants and toddlers. Dev. Psychopathol. 30, 479-495 (2017). <lb/>13. Fingher, N. et al. Toddlers later diagnosed with autism exhibit multiple <lb/>structural abnormalities in temporal corpus callosum fibers. Cortex 97, <lb/>291-305 (2017). <lb/>14. Travers, B. G. et al. Atypical development of white matter microstructure of the <lb/>corpus callosum in males with autism: a longitudinal investigation. Mol. Autism <lb/>6, 15 (2015). <lb/>15. Xiao, Z. et al. Autism spectrum disorder as early neurodevelopmental disorder: <lb/>evidence from the brain imaging abnormalities in 2-3 years old toddlers. J. <lb/>Autism Dev. Disord. 44, 1633-1640 (2014). <lb/>16. Grosse Wiesmann, C., Schreiber, J., Singer, T., Steinbeis, N. &amp; Friederici, A. D. <lb/>White matter maturation is associated with the emergence of Theory of Mind <lb/>in early childhood. Nat. Commun. 8, 14692 (2017). <lb/>17. Ameis, S. H. &amp; Catani, M. Altered white matter connectivity as a neural sub-<lb/>strate for social impairment in Autism Spectrum Disorder. Cortex 62, 158-181 <lb/>(2015). <lb/>18. Uddin, L. Q., Supekar, K. &amp; Menon, V. Reconceptualizing functional brain <lb/>connectivity in autism from a developmental perspective. Front. Hum. Neu-<lb/>rosci. 7, 458 (2013). <lb/>19. Sparks, B. F. et al. Brain structural abnormalities in young children with autism <lb/>spectrum disorder. Neurology 59, 184-192 (2002). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 12 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>20. Hazlett, H. C. et al. Magnetic resonance imaging and head circumference <lb/>study of brain size in autism: birth through age 2 years. Arch. Gen. Psychiatry <lb/>62, 1366-1376 (2005). <lb/>21. Redcay, E. &amp; Courchesne, E. When is the brain enlarged in autism? A meta-<lb/>analysis of all brain size reports. Biol. Psychiatry 58, 1-9 (2005). <lb/>22. Schumann, C. M. et al. Longitudinal magnetic resonance imaging study of <lb/>cortical development through early childhood in autism. J. Neurosci. 30, <lb/>4419-4427 (2010). <lb/>23. Courchesne, E. et al. Neuron number and size in prefrontal cortex of children <lb/>with autism. JAMA 306, 2001-2010 (2011). <lb/>24. Aylward, E. H., Minshew, N. J., Field, K., Sparks, B. F. &amp; Singh, N. Effects of age on <lb/>brain volume and head circumference in autism. Neurology 59, 175-183 (2002). <lb/>25. Courchesne, E. et al. Unusual brain growth patterns in early life in patients with <lb/>autistic disorder: an MRI study. Neurology 57, 245-254 (2001). <lb/>26. Frazier, T. W. &amp; Hardan, A. Y. A meta-analysis of the corpus callosum in autism. <lb/>Biol. Psychiatry 66, 935-941 (2009). <lb/>27. Wolff, J. J. et al. Altered corpus callosum morphology associated with autism <lb/>over the first 2 years of life. Brain 138, 2046-2058 (2015). <lb/>28. Fields, R. D. Neuroscience. Myelin-more than insulation. Science 344, 264-266 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>29. Nave, K. A. Myelination and the trophic support of long axons. Nat. Rev. <lb/>Neurosci. 11, 275-283 (2010). <lb/>30. Gozzi, M. et al. A magnetization transfer imaging study of corpus callosum <lb/>myelination in young children with autism. Biol. Psychiatry 72, 215-220 (2012). <lb/>31. Meyza, K. Z. &amp; Blanchard, D. C. The BTBR mouse model of idiopathic autism -<lb/>current view on mechanisms. Neurosci. Biobehav. Rev. 76, 99-110 (2017). <lb/>32. Ellegood, J. &amp; Crawley, J. N. Behavioral and neuroanatomical phenotypes in <lb/>mouse models of autism. Neurotherapeutics 12, 521-533 (2015). <lb/>33. McFarlane, H. G. et al. Autism-like behavioral phenotypes in BTBR T + tf/J mice. <lb/>Genes Brain Behav. 7, 152-163 (2008). <lb/>34. Meyza, K. Z. et al. The BTBR T + tf/J mouse model for autism spectrum <lb/>disorders-in search of biomarkers. Behav. Brain Res. 251, 25-34 (2013). <lb/>35. Moy, S. S. et al. Mouse behavioral tasks relevant to autism: phenotypes of 10 <lb/>inbred strains. Behav. Brain Res. 176, 4-20 (2007). <lb/>36. Miller, V. M. et al. Novel inter-hemispheric white matter connectivity in the <lb/>BTBR mouse model of autism. Brain Res. 1513, 26-33 (2013). <lb/>37. Jones-Davis, D. M. et al. Quantitative trait loci for interhemispheric commissure <lb/>development and social behaviors in the BTBR T(+) tf/J mouse model of <lb/>autism. PLoS One 8, e61829 (2013). <lb/>38. Stephenson, D. T. et al. Histopathologic characterization of the BTBR mouse <lb/>model of autistic-like behavior reveals selective changes in neurodevelop-<lb/>mental proteins and adult hippocampal neurogenesis. Mol. Autism 2, 7 (2011). <lb/>39. Paul, L. K., Corsello, C., Kennedy, D. P. &amp; Adolphs, R. Agenesis of the corpus <lb/>callosum and autism: a comprehensive comparison. Brain 137, 1813-1829 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>40. Nieman, B. J., Flenniken, A. M., Adamson, S. L., Henkelman, R. M. &amp; Sled, J. G. <lb/>Anatomical phenotyping in the brain and skull of a mutant mouse by <lb/>magnetic resonance imaging and computed tomography. Physiol. Genomics <lb/>24, 154-162 (2006). <lb/>41. Nieman, B. J. et al. Magnetic resonance imaging for detection and analysis of <lb/>mouse phenotypes. NMR Biomed. 18, 447-468 (2005). <lb/>42. Nieman, B. J. et al. MR technology for biological studies in mice. NMR Biomed. <lb/>20, 291-303 (2007). <lb/>43. Collins, D. L., Neelin, P., Peters, T. M. &amp; Evans, A. C. Automatic 3D intersubject <lb/>registration of MR volumetric data in standardized Talairach space. J. Comput. <lb/>Assist. Tomogr. 18, 192-205 (1994). <lb/>44. Avants, B. B. et al. The optimal template effect in hippocampus studies of <lb/>diseased populations. NeuroImage 49, 2457-2466 (2010). <lb/>45. Lau, J. C. et al. Longitudinal neuroanatomical changes determined by <lb/>deformation-based morphometry in a mouse model of Alzheimer&apos;s disease. <lb/>NeuroImage 42, 19-27 (2008). <lb/>46. Genovese, C. R., Lazar, N. A. &amp; Nichols, T. Thresholding of statistical maps in <lb/>functional neuroimaging using the false discovery rate. NeuroImage 15, <lb/>870-878 (2002). <lb/>47. Cheng, N., Bai, L., Steuer, E. &amp; Belluscio, L. Olfactory functions scale with circuit <lb/>restoration in a rapidly reversible Alzheimer&apos;s disease model. J. Neurosci. 33, <lb/>12208-12217 (2013). <lb/>48. Pfaffl, M. W., Tichopad, A., Prgomet, C. &amp; Neuvians, T. P. Determination of stable <lb/>housekeeping genes, differentially regulated target genes and sample integ-<lb/>rity: BestKeeper-Excel-based tool using pair-wise correlations. Biotechnol. Lett. <lb/>26, 509-515 (2004). <lb/>49. Pfaffl, M. W., Horgan, G. W. &amp; Dempfle, L. Relative expression software tool <lb/>(REST) for group-wise comparison and statistical analysis of relative expression <lb/>results in real-time PCR. Nucleic Acids Res. 30, e36 (2002). <lb/>50. Liang, C. et al. Erbin is required for myelination in regenerated axons after <lb/>injury. J. Neurosci. 32, 15169-15180 (2012). <lb/>51. Mayoral, S. R., Etxeberria, A., Shen, Y. A. &amp; Chan, J. R. Initiation of CNS myelination <lb/>in the optic nerve is dependent on axon caliber. Cell Rep. 25, 544-550 e3 (2018). <lb/>52. Boggs, J. M. Myelin basic protein: a multifunctional protein. Cell. Mol. Life Sci. <lb/>63, 1945-1961 (2006). <lb/>53. Chernoff, G. F. Shiverer: an autosomal recessive mutant mouse with myelin <lb/>deficiency. J. Heredity 72, 128 (1981). <lb/>54. Popko, B. et al. Myelin deficient mice: expression of myelin basic protein and <lb/>generation of mice with varying levels of myelin. Cell 48, 713-721 (1987). <lb/>55. Readhead, C. et al. Expression of a myelin basic protein gene in transgenic <lb/>shiverer mice: correction of the dysmyelinating phenotype. Cell 48, 703-712 <lb/>(1987). <lb/>56. Vassall, K. A., Bamm, V. V. &amp; Harauz, G. MyelStones: the executive roles of myelin <lb/>basic protein in myelin assembly and destabilization in multiple sclerosis. <lb/>Biochem. J. 472, 17-32 (2015). <lb/>57. Klugmann, M. et al. Assembly of CNS myelin in the absence of proteolipid <lb/>protein. Neuron 18, 59-70 (1997). <lb/>58. Griffiths, I. et al. Axonal swellings and degeneration in mice lacking the major <lb/>proteolipid of myelin. Science 280, 1610-1613 (1998). <lb/>59. Hart, I. K., Richardson, W. D., Bolsover, S. R. &amp; Raff, M. C. PDGF and intracellular <lb/>signaling in the timing of oligodendrocyte differentiation. J. Cell Biol. 109, <lb/>3411-3417 (1989). <lb/>60. McKinnon, R. D., Matsui, T., Dubois-Dalcq, M. &amp; Aaronson, S. A. FGF modulates <lb/>the PDGF-driven pathway of oligodendrocyte development. Neuron 5, <lb/>603-614 (1990). <lb/>61. Raff, M. C., Abney, E. R. &amp; Fok-Seang, J. Reconstitution of a developmental clock <lb/>in vitro: a critical role for astrocytes in the timing of oligodendrocyte differ-<lb/>entiation. Cell 42, 61-69 (1985). <lb/>62. Raff, M. C., Lillien, L. E., Richardson, W. D., Burne, J. F. &amp; Noble, M. D. Platelet-<lb/>derived growth factor from astrocytes drives the clock that times oligoden-<lb/>drocyte development in culture. Nature 333, 562-565 (1988). <lb/>63. Richardson, W. D., Pringle, N., Mosley, M. J., Westermark, B. &amp; Dubois-Dalcq, M. <lb/>A role for platelet-derived growth factor in normal gliogenesis in the central <lb/>nervous system. Cell 53, 309-319 (1988). <lb/>64. Pringle, N. et al. PDGF A chain homodimers drive proliferation of bipotential <lb/>(O-2A) glial progenitor cells in the developing rat optic nerve. EMBO J. 8, <lb/>1049-1056 (1989). <lb/>65. van Heyningen, P., Calver, A. R. &amp; Richardson, W. D. Control of progenitor cell <lb/>number by mitogen supply and demand. Curr. Biol. 11, 232-241 (2001). <lb/>66. McKinnon, R. D., Waldron, S. &amp; Kiel, M. E. PDGF alpha-receptor signal strength <lb/>controls an RTK rheostat that integrates phosphoinositol 3&apos;-kinase and <lb/>phospholipase Cgamma pathways during oligodendrocyte maturation. J. <lb/>Neurosci. 25, 3499-3508 (2005). <lb/>67. Zhu, Q. et al. Genetic evidence that Nkx2.2 and Pdgfra are major determinants <lb/>of the timing of oligodendrocyte differentiation in the developing CNS. <lb/>Development 141, 548-555 (2014). <lb/>68. Huang, H., Zhao, X. F., Zheng, K. &amp; Qiu, M. Regulation of the timing of <lb/>oligodendrocyte differentiation: mechanisms and perspectives. Neurosci. Bull. <lb/>29, 155-164 (2013). <lb/>69. Galloway, D. A. &amp; Moore, C. S. miRNAs as emerging regulators of oligoden-<lb/>drocyte development and differentiation. Front. Cell Dev. Biol. 4, 59 (2016). <lb/>70. Liu, J., Moyon, S., Hernandez, M. &amp; Casaccia, P. Epigenetic control of oligo-<lb/>dendrocyte development: adding new players to old keepers. Curr. Opin. <lb/>Neurobiol. 39, 133-138 (2016). <lb/>71. Barca-Mayo, O. &amp; Lu, Q. R. Fine-tuning oligodendrocyte development by <lb/>microRNAs. Front. Neurosci. 6, 13 (2012). <lb/>72. Dugas, J. C. et al. Dicer1 and miR-219 Are required for normal oligodendrocyte <lb/>differentiation and myelination. Neuron 65, 597-611 (2010). <lb/>73. Zhao, X. et al. MicroRNA-mediated control of oligodendrocyte differentiation. <lb/>Neuron 65, 612-626 (2010). <lb/>74. Lin, S. T. et al. MicroRNA-23a promotes myelination in the central nervous <lb/>system. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 110, 17468-17473 (2013). <lb/>75. Zikopoulos, B. &amp; Barbas, H. Changes in prefrontal axons may disrupt the <lb/>network in autism. J. Neurosci. 30, 14595-14609 (2010). <lb/>76. Courchesne, E., Campbell, K. &amp; Solso, S. Brain growth across the life span in <lb/>autism: age-specific changes in anatomical pathology. Brain Res. 1380, <lb/>138-145 (2011). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 13 of 14 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>77. Engelbrecht, V., Rassek, M., Preiss, S., Wald, C. &amp; Modder, U. Age-dependent <lb/>changes in magnetization transfer contrast of white matter in the pediatric <lb/>brain. AJNR Am. J. Neuroradiol. 19, 1923-1929 (1998). <lb/>78. Kamiya, K. et al. Accelerated myelination along fiber tracts in patients with <lb/>hemimegalencephaly. J. Neuroradiol. 41, 202-210 (2014). <lb/>79. Pacey, L. K. et al. Delayed myelination in a mouse model of fragile X syndrome. <lb/>Hum. Mol. Genet. 22, 3920-3930 (2013). <lb/>80. Makinodan, M. et al. Maternal immune activation in mice delays myelination <lb/>and axonal development in the hippocampus of the offspring. J. Neurosci. Res. <lb/>86, 2190-2200 (2008). <lb/>81. Meikle, L. et al. A mouse model of tuberous sclerosis: neuronal loss of Tsc1 <lb/>causes dysplastic and ectopic neurons, reduced myelination, seizure activity, <lb/>and limited survival. J. Neurosci. 27, 5546-5558 (2007). <lb/>82. Figlia, G., Gerber, D. &amp; Suter, U. Myelination and mTOR. Glia 66, 693-707 (2018). <lb/>83. van Tilborg, E. et al. Combined fetal inflammation and postnatal hypoxia <lb/>causes myelin deficits and autism-like behavior in a rat model of diffuse white <lb/>matter injury. Glia 66, 78-93 (2018). <lb/>84. Semple, B. D., Blomgren, K., Gimlin, K., Ferriero, D. M. &amp; Noble-Haeusslein, L. J. <lb/>Brain development in rodents and humans: Identifying benchmarks of <lb/>maturation and vulnerability to injury across species. Prog. Neurobiol. 106-107, <lb/>1-16 (2013). <lb/>85. Workman, A. D., Charvet, C. J., Clancy, B., Darlington, R. B. &amp; Finlay, B. L. <lb/>Modeling transformations of neurodevelopmental sequences across mam-<lb/>malian species. J. Neurosci. 33, 7368-7383 (2013). <lb/>86. Lappe-Siefke, C. et al. Disruption of Cnp1 uncouples oligodendroglial functions <lb/>in axonal support and myelination. Nat. Genet. 33, 366-374 (2003). <lb/>87. Nawaz, S., Schweitzer, J., Jahn, O. &amp; Werner, H. B. Molecular evolution of myelin <lb/>basic protein, an abundant structural myelin component. Glia 61, 1364-1377 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>88. Werner, H. B. Do we have to reconsider the evolutionary emergence of <lb/>myelin? Front. Cell. Neurosci. 7, 217 (2013). <lb/>89. Muller, C., Bauer, N. M., Schafer, I. &amp; White, R. Making myelin basic protein -from <lb/>mRNA transport to localized translation. Front. Cell. Neurosci. 7, 169 (2013). <lb/>90. Calver, A. R. et al. Oligodendrocyte population dynamics and the role of PDGF <lb/>in vivo. Neuron 20, 869-882 (1998). <lb/>91. Dodero, L. et al. Neuroimaging evidence of major morpho-anatomical and <lb/>functional abnormalities in the BTBR T+TF/J mouse model of autism. PLoS <lb/>One 8, e76655 (2013). <lb/>92. Ellegood, J. et al. Clustering autism: using neuroanatomical differences in 26 <lb/>mouse models to gain insight into the heterogeneity. Mol. Psychiatry 20, <lb/>118-125 (2015). <lb/>93. Ellegood, J., Babineau, B. A., Henkelman, R. M., Lerch, J. P. &amp; Crawley, J. N. <lb/>Neuroanatomical analysis of the BTBR mouse model of autism using magnetic <lb/>resonance imaging and diffusion tensor imaging. NeuroImage 70, 288-300 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>94. Fenlon, L. R. et al. Formation of functional areas in the cerebral cortex is <lb/>disrupted in a mouse model of autism spectrum disorder. Neural Dev. 10, 10 <lb/>(2015). <lb/>95. Sforazzini, F. et al. Altered functional connectivity networks in acallosal and <lb/>socially impaired BTBR mice. Brain Struct. Funct. 221, 941-954 (2016). <lb/>96. Squillace, M. et al. Dysfunctional dopaminergic neurotransmission in asocial <lb/>BTBR mice. Transl. Psychiatry 4, e427 (2014). <lb/>97. Cheng, N., Khanbabaei, M., Murari, K. &amp; Rho, J. M. Disruption of visual circuit <lb/>formation and refinement in a mouse model of autism. Autism Res. 10, <lb/>212-223 (2017). <lb/>98. Cheng, N., Alshammari, F., Hughes, E., Khanbabaei, M. &amp; Rho, J. M. Dendritic <lb/>overgrowth and elevated ERK signaling during neonatal development in a <lb/>mouse model of autism. PLoS One 12, e0179409 (2017). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Khanbabaei et al. Translational Psychiatry (2019) 9:251 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 14 of 14 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
