<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ARTICLE <lb/>OPEN <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand <lb/>discrimination <lb/>Dibyendu K. Sasmal 1 , Wei Feng 1 , Sobhan Roy 2 , Peter Leung , Yanran He 3 , Chufan Cai 1 , Guoshuai Cao 1 , Huada Lian 4 , Jian Qin 5 , <lb/>Enfu Hui 6 , Hans Schreiber 3 , Erin J. Adams 2 and Jun Huang 1 <lb/>A major unanswered question is how a TCR discriminates between foreign and self-peptides presented on the APC surface. Here, <lb/>we used in situ fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET) to measure the distances of single TCR-pMHC bonds and the <lb/>conformations of individual TCR-CD3ζ receptors at the membranes of live primary T cells. We found that a TCR discriminates <lb/>between closely related peptides by forming single TCR-pMHC bonds with different conformations, and the most potent pMHC <lb/>forms the shortest bond. The bond conformation is an intrinsic property that is independent of the binding affinity and kinetics, <lb/>TCR microcluster formation, and CD4 binding. The bond conformation dictates the degree of CD3ζ dissociation from the inner <lb/>leaflet of the plasma membrane via a positive calcium signaling feedback loop to precisely control the accessibility of CD3ζ ITAMs <lb/>for phosphorylation. Our data revealed the mechanism by which a TCR deciphers the structural differences among peptides via the <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond conformation. <lb/>Keywords: Bond conformation; T cell receptor; Single molecule FRET; ligand discrimination <lb/>Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203-217; https://doi.org/10.1038/s41423-019-0273-6 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>A TCR consists of a variable TCRαβ heterodimer and a nonvariable <lb/>transmembrane signal transduction CD3 complex containing <lb/>CD3γε and CD3δε heterodimers and a CD3ζζ homodimer. TCRs <lb/>specifically and sensitively detect a small number of agonist <lb/>pMHCs among a plethora of structurally similar self-pMHCs to <lb/>trigger antigen-specific immune responses. 1-3 Despite intense <lb/>efforts, the mechanism underlying TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>remains a major unanswered question in immunology. 4-6 TCR <lb/>ligand discrimination is uniquely challenging. First, it requires TCRs <lb/>to detect very rare foreign pMHCs in the presence of considerably <lb/>abundant self-pMHCs. Second, it requires proper signaling <lb/>propagation from surface TCR binding to induce intracellular <lb/>CD3 phosphorylation. Although it is generally thought that the <lb/>engagement of the extracellular TCRαβ domain with a pMHC <lb/>results in biochemical changes in the cytoplasmic portions of the <lb/>CD3 complex, there are no experimental data that can directly <lb/>depict this process with enough spatiotemporal resolution at the <lb/>membranes of live primary T cells. <lb/>Many models have been proposed to explain the molecular <lb/>mechanism underlying TCR discrimination. The TCR conforma-<lb/>tional change model postulates that a conformational change in <lb/>a TCR occurs upon pMHC binding, but no conformational <lb/>changes at the TCR-pMHC binding interface have been identified <lb/>that are conserved in TCR-pMHC crystal structures. 5,7 However, <lb/>crystal structures only provide a &quot;snapshot&quot; of the thermodyna-<lb/>mically stable conformations of purified TCR and pMHC proteins. <lb/>The TCR is an active molecular machine that is anchored at the <lb/>live cell membrane, associates with CD3 signaling units, links to <lb/>the cytoskeleton, and interacts with other signaling molecules. <lb/>&quot;Active&quot; TCR molecules at cell membrane are very different from <lb/>purified &quot;quiescent&quot; TCR proteins isolated from the cellular <lb/>environment. A typical example of this is that the in situ binding <lb/>kinetics and affinities of TCR-pMHC interactions measured at the <lb/>T-cell membrane are dramatically different from those measured <lb/>in vitro in solution. 3,8 It has long been speculated that the TCR at <lb/>the cell membrane undergoes conformational changes upon <lb/>pMHC binding. This hypothesis is attractive, but it has never <lb/>been experimentally proven at the membranes of live primary <lb/>T cells, mainly due to the lack of appropriate experimental <lb/>approaches. Furthermore, another key issue for TCR discrimina-<lb/>tion is how different TCR-pMHC interactions result in distinct <lb/>biochemical changes in the cytoplasmic domains of CD3. It has <lb/>been suggested that CD3 ITAMs are sequestered in the plasma <lb/>membrane and TCR-pMHC engagement pulls the CD3 cytoplas-<lb/>mic domains away from the membrane, thus making the ITAMs <lb/>accessible to phosphorylation by Lck. 9 However, other studies <lb/>argue that the release of ITAMs from the plasma membrane <lb/>is unlikely to be a prerequisite step in the initiation of TCR <lb/>signaling. 6 <lb/>To carefully examine possible TCR conformational changes and <lb/>investigate the molecular mechanism of TCR triggering in situ, we <lb/>used fluorescence resonance energy transfer (FRET), 10,11 which <lb/>functions as a spectroscopic ruler with subnanometer precision, to <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 3 August 2019 Accepted: 7 August 2019 <lb/>Published online: 17 September 2019 <lb/>The Pritzker School of Molecular Engineering, The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA; 2 Department of Biochemistry and Molecular Biology, The University of Chicago, <lb/>Chicago, IL, USA; 3 Department of Pathology, The University of Chicago, Chicago, IL, USA; 4 Department of Materials Science &amp; Engineering, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA; <lb/>5 <lb/>Department of Chemical Engineering, Stanford University, Stanford, CA, USA and 6 Section of Cell &amp; Developmental Biology, Division of Biological Sciences, University of <lb/>California, San Diego, CA, USA <lb/>Correspondence: Jun Huang (huangjun@uchicago.edu) <lb/>www.nature.com/cmi <lb/>Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology <lb/> © The Author(s) 2019 <lb/></front>

			<body>measure the intermolecular distance of a TCR-pMHC bond and <lb/>the intramolecular conformation of a TCR-CD3ζ complex at the <lb/>immunological synapse of a live primary CD4 + T cell in real time <lb/>with high spatiotemporal resolution. These experiments enabled <lb/>us to critically test the TCR conformational change model and <lb/>probe the molecular mechanism underlying TCR ligand <lb/>discrimination. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>FRET design <lb/>To determine the conformation of a single TCR-pMHC bond, a TCR <lb/>and a pMHC were site-specifically labeled with the FRET acceptor <lb/>Cy5 and the FRET donor Cy3, respectively. 8 The peptide within the <lb/>MHC molecule was labeled with Cy3, and the TCR was labeled <lb/>with the anti-TCR single-chain variable fragment (scFv) J1-Cy5 <lb/>(Fig. 1a and Fig. S1a). The intermolecular distance between Cy3 <lb/>and Cy5 provided a reasonable approximation of the conforma-<lb/>tion (or compactness) of the TCR-pMHC bond. The conformation <lb/>of a single TCR-pMHC bond on the cell surface was measured by <lb/>Cy3/Cy5 FRET (FRET1) (Fig. 1a) in real time by total internal <lb/>reflection fluorescence (TIRF) microscopy (Fig. S1b). The Cy3/Cy5 <lb/>inter-dye distance of a TCR-pMHC bond is denoted as the <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond distance to describe the TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>conformation in the following paragraphs. To measure the <lb/>intramolecular distance between the TCR and CD3ζ in a <lb/>transmembrane TCR-CD3ζ complex, we added a green fluores-<lb/>cent protein (GFP) to the C-terminus of the CD3ζ chain, and the <lb/>TCR was labeled with an Alexa Fluor 568 fluorophore using a <lb/>different anti-TCR scFv J3 with a unique labeling site close to the <lb/>cell membrane. 8 The real-time intramolecular distances of the <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ complexes were measured by GFP/Alexa Fluor 568 <lb/>FRET (FRET2) (Fig. 1a) using epifluorescence time-lapse micro-<lb/>scopy (Fig. S1b). <lb/>We first performed experiments to assess the feasibility and <lb/>specificity of cell surface FRET1 and transmembrane FRET2 on a <lb/>lipid bilayer (Fig. 1a) and on a glass surface (Fig. S1a) containing <lb/>the pMHC and accessory molecules ICAM-1 and B7-1, respectively <lb/>(Fig. S2 and Movie S1-3). For cell surface FRET1, we readily <lb/>detected FRET signals from three agonist pMHCs but not from a <lb/>null pMHC on the lipid bilayer and on the glass surface, and the <lb/>FRET efficiencies (E FRET ) were positively correlated with the pMHC <lb/>potencies in activating T cells in vitro 12 (Fig. 1b, d). The average <lb/>synaptic E FRET1 was 0.79, 0.54, and 0.29 for the super agonist K5, <lb/>the agonist MCC, and the weak agonist 102S, respectively. <lb/>However, no synaptic FRET was observed for the null pMHC. <lb/>These data validated the specificity of the cell surface TCR-pMHC <lb/>FRET and were consistent with the results of a previous report. 8 In <lb/>contrast, the transmembrane TCR-CD3ζ FRET2 efficiencies were <lb/>inversely correlated with the pMHC potencies, and the highest <lb/>FRET was observed for the null pMHC (Fig. 1c, e). In the presence <lb/>of the K5, MCC, and 102S pMHCs, the transmembrane FRET <lb/>change was only detected in the TCR-CD3ζ colocalized micro-<lb/>clusters and not outside of the colocalized microclusters (Fig. 1c <lb/>and Fig. S3a). Replacing the FRET acceptor Alexa Fluor 568 with a <lb/>Cy5 dye abolished the transmembrane FRET2 (Fig. S3b). These <lb/>experiments confirmed the specificity of the transmembrane <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ FRET. <lb/>Cy5 <lb/>Lipid bilayer/ PEG <lb/>T Cell <lb/>pMHC <lb/>CD3ζ-GFP <lb/>a <lb/>Cy3 <lb/>TCR <lb/>Cover Glass <lb/>Alexa-568 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>e <lb/>d <lb/>FRET1 Efficiency <lb/>FRET2 Efficiency <lb/>Lipid <lb/>Glass <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Null <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Null <lb/>2 <lb/>T <lb/>E <lb/>R <lb/>F <lb/>1 <lb/>T <lb/>E <lb/>R <lb/>F <lb/>Lipid <lb/>Glass <lb/>n = 15-20 <lb/>n = 13-20 <lb/>Cy3 <lb/>Cy5 <lb/>FRET1 <lb/>T cell <lb/>b <lb/>K5 <lb/>/Lipid <lb/>K5 <lb/>/Glass <lb/>Null <lb/>/Glass <lb/>Null <lb/>/Lipid <lb/>Low <lb/>High <lb/>c <lb/>K5 <lb/>/Lipid <lb/>Null <lb/>/Glass <lb/>K5 <lb/>/Glass <lb/>Null <lb/>/Lipid <lb/>GFP <lb/>AF568 <lb/>FRET2 <lb/>Low <lb/>High <lb/>T cell <lb/>Fig. 1 Measurement of TCR conformational dynamics by FRET. a A composite structural model of 5C.C7 TCR (PDB ID: 4P2R), MCC-IE k (PDB ID: <lb/>3QIU), scFv (PDB ID: 1NFD), and CD3ζ-GFP (PDB ID for GFP: 1GFL). To measure the TCR-pMHC bond conformational dynamics using FRET1, <lb/>the TCR was labeled by Cy5 via the scFv J1, and the peptide C-terminus was labeled by Cy3. For determining the TCR-CD3ζ conformational <lb/>changes by FRET2, the TCR was labeled by Alexa Fluor 568 (Alexa568) via scFv J3, and the CD3ζ C-terminus was tagged with GFP. Extracellular <lb/>Cy3/Cy5 FRET1 and transmembrane GFP/Alexa568 FRET2 are indicated by dashed lines. The pMHC molecules were anchored on either a lipid <lb/>bilayer or on a PEG-Ni 2+ glass surface (Fig. S1a). Note: J1 and J3 are different scFvs, and each has only one unique labeling site. b, c T cell, <lb/>donor, acceptor, and calculated FRET signals of TCRs interacting with K5 or a null pMHC on a lipid bilayer or on a glass surface. The calculated <lb/>FRET efficiency images for FRET1 (b) and FRET2 (c) are shown in pseudocolor; the cold-to-hot color spectrum represents weak-to-strong FRET <lb/>efficiency. Representative data from 3-5 independent experiments for each pMHC at 37°C are shown. The scale bar is 5 µm. d, e FRET <lb/>efficiencies measured for K5, MCC, 102S, and null pMHCs on a lipid bilayer (red) and a glass surface (yellow) for extracellular TCR-pMHC FRET1 <lb/>(d) and transmembrane TCR-CD3ζ FRET2 (e). At least 13 cells were used to determine the FRET efficiency for each pMHC. Also see Figs. S1-4 <lb/>and Movies S1-3 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>204 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/>1234567890();,: <lb/></note>

			<body>Measurement of the TCR-pMHC bond conformation by smFRET <lb/>We next performed Cy3/Cy5 single-molecule FRET (smFRET) on a <lb/>lipid bilayer to measure the conformations of single TCR-pMHC <lb/>bonds using TIRF microscopy (Fig. 2 and Fig. S1b). TCR-pMHC <lb/>bond formation at live T-cell membrane brought the donor Cy3 <lb/>and the acceptor Cy5 into close enough proximity to produce <lb/>smFRET (Figs. 1a and 2a). The fluorescent intensities of Cy3 and <lb/>Cy5 were simultaneously recorded in real time (Fig. 2b, top panel, <lb/>and Fig. S4a), and the E FRET values were calculated based on the <lb/>fluorescence intensities of the donor Cy3 and the acceptor Cy5 <lb/>(Fig. 2b, bottom panel). As E FRET is inversely proportional to the <lb/>distance between the donor and the acceptor to the sixth power, <lb/>Cy3/Cy5 smFRET serves as a sensitive microscopic ruler to <lb/>precisely measure the intermolecular TCR-pMHC bond distance <lb/>in real time during binding. The time trajectory of E FRET showed <lb/>that the TCR-pMHC bond is dynamic and exhibits continuous <lb/>conformational changes (Fig. 2b), which is in line with the results <lb/>in recent reports that demonstrated that a TCR or a pMHC <lb/>undergoes conformational changes upon binding. 13,14 The <lb/>recording of the fluctuating conformational trajectories provided <lb/>for the real-time observation of single TCR-pMHC bond dynamics. <lb/>By plotting the E FRET histogram and fitting it with a Gaussian <lb/>function, we determined the most probale E FRET value of 0.7, <lb/>corresponding to a 47 ± 3 Å distance between the 5C.C7 TCR and <lb/>the super agonist K5 pMHC in a representative smFRET trajectory <lb/>(Fig. 2c). We repeated our single-bond measurements for the K5 <lb/>pMHC and performed smFRET experiments for the agonist MCC <lb/>and weak agonist 102S pMHCs (Fig. S5). After collecting many <lb/>individual smFRET trajectories for each pMHC, we pooled all E FRET <lb/>data together and plotted the histograms for each pMHC <lb/>(1577-1933 trajectories per histogram, Fig. 2d). Remarkably, the <lb/>distributions of E FRET showed that the intermolecular TCR-pMHC <lb/>bond distances were peptide dependent, and single TCR-pMHC <lb/>bonds were highly dynamic within a continuous range of <lb/>conformational states. Fitting each histogram with a Gaussian <lb/>function (curves, Fig. 2d) yielded the most probable intermole-<lb/>cular TCR-pMHC bond distance for each pMHC: 44 ± 9 Å for K5 <lb/>(super agonist), 54 ± 11 Å for MCC (agonist), and 66 ± 18 Å for <lb/>102S (weak agonist) (Fig. 2d), directly revealing the angstrom-<lb/>level, binding-induced, peptide-dependent TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distances and conformational dynamics in situ. This key informa-<lb/>tion was missing from previously reported TCR-pMHC crystal <lb/>structures. 7,15 In addition, we experimentally verified that the <lb/>differences in the distances of the pMHCs were not due to <lb/>peptide labeling-derived noise (Fig. S6). We further measured the <lb/>average TCR-pMHC bond distances using ensemble FRET on both <lb/>a lipid bilayer and a glass surface (Figs. S4b and S7), and the <lb/>results confirmed the single-bond measurements obtained using <lb/>smFRET (Fig. 2d). <lb/>We then quantified the binding strength of each single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond by analyzing the potential-of-mean-force <lb/>(PMF), 16 which measures the free energy cost of the variation in <lb/>bond conformation. PMF is at minimum when the bond <lb/>conformation is at equilibrium, and the PMF curve indicates the <lb/>sizes of the fluctuations (Fig. 2e). Clearly, the super agonist K5 and <lb/>agonist MCC have deep and narrow energy wells, indicating their <lb/>strong and stable bonds. In contrast, the weak agonist 102S has a <lb/>shallow and wide energy well, suggesting its weak bond strength <lb/>and unstable binding state. Overall, the depth and width of the <lb/>PMF curve revealed that K5 and MCC form more stable (shorter) <lb/>bonds with TCRs compared with 102S (Fig. 2e), which is consistent <lb/>with previous reports that indicated that K5 and MCC have higher <lb/>3D in vitro binding affinities with TCRs than 102S 8,12 and that TCR <lb/>triggering is dependent on the receptor-ligand complex dimen-<lb/>sions. 17,18 Our smFRET measurements not only revealed that TCR <lb/>triggering is critically dependent on the conformation of a <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond but also linked the bond conformation to the <lb/>bond energy, thus providing a fundamental basis for under-<lb/>standing TCR ligand discrimination. <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond conformation is an intrinsic property <lb/>independent of binding kinetics and affinity <lb/>Cell surface smFRET is highly distance dependent 8 and only <lb/>produces a FRET signal when a TCR binds to a pMHC (Fig. 1b, d, <lb/>comparison of K5 with null). To confirm the bound state, we <lb/>tracked and compared the diffusion of single pMHCs in smFRET <lb/>and those of individual-free pMHCs on the lipid bilayer (Fig. 2f, g <lb/>and Fig. S8). We found that the pMHCs in smFRET were tightly <lb/>restricted within the synapse, whereas the free pMHCs were very <lb/>mobile, as shown by their distinct diffusion trajectories and <lb/>coefficients (Fig. 2f, top panel). The diffusion coefficient of a pMHC <lb/>in smFRET was close to 0, which was 140-fold smaller than that of a <lb/>free pMHC (Fig. 2f, bottom panel). We further plotted the <lb/>horizontal (x) and vertical (y) positions of single-tracked pMHCs <lb/>over time (Fig. 2g, top panel) and analyzed the position changes <lb/>according to the 3-point moving standard deviation (Fig. 2g, <lb/>bottom panel). The pMHCs in smFRET and the free pMHCs on the <lb/>lipid bilayer showed dramatic differences in diffusion at the single-<lb/>molecule level. These differences have been previously used to <lb/>differentiate TCR-bound pMHCs from unbound pMHCs for kinetic <lb/>measurements. 19,20 Our tracking analyses verified that we detected <lb/>a FRET signal only if a TCR was bound to a pMHC. In other words, <lb/>smFRET only measured the conformational dynamics of single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds during the bound state, which are independent <lb/>of those of unbound molecules and bond association/dissociation. <lb/>Thus, our conformational measurements by smFRET were inde-<lb/>pendent of TCR-pMHC binding affinity and kinetics. <lb/>The effects of TCR microclusters and CD4 binding <lb/>TCRs form microclusters upon antigen stimulation (Movie S4). To <lb/>measure the conformational dynamics of single TCR-pMHC <lb/>bonds without possible interference from TCR microclusters, we <lb/>used latrunculin A (LA) to prevent the formation of TCR <lb/>microclusters during smFRET measurements. Consistent with <lb/>the results of a previous study, no TCR microclusters were <lb/>observed at the T-cell synapse after treatment with LA. 21 We <lb/>then performed smFRET in the absence of TCR microclusters. We <lb/>found that the most probale TCR-pMHC bond distances (and <lb/>distributions) measured in the absence of TCR microclusters <lb/>were very close to those measured in the presence of TCR <lb/>microclusters (compare Fig. 2d with Fig. 3), suggesting that our <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond distance measurements were not affected by <lb/>TCR microclusters. These results further confirmed that we had <lb/>determined the true intermolecular TCR-pMHC bond distances <lb/>at the single-molecule level. <lb/>Because the CD4 coreceptor also binds to pMHC, to evaluate <lb/>the effect of CD4 binding on the TCR-pMHC bond distances, we <lb/>used an antibody to block CD4 binding to pMHCs and performed <lb/>smFRET measurements. Our data showed that CD4 binding had <lb/>little effect on the TCR-pMHC bond distances (compare Fig. 2d <lb/>and Fig. 3b), which is consistent with the results of previous kinetic <lb/>studies showing that CD4-pMHC binding is negligible compared <lb/>to TCR-pMHC interaction in vitro and in situ. 8,22-24 <lb/>We then determined the most probable TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distances for K5 (super agonist), MCC (agonist), and 102S (weak <lb/>agonist) under different conditions by smFRET and bulk FRET, as <lb/>shown in Fig. 3c. We found that neither the disruption of TCR <lb/>microclusters nor the blocking of CD4 binding changed the <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond conformation for the three pMHCs. These data <lb/>(Fig. 3) significantly confirmed the aforementioned smFRET <lb/>measurements that were made in the absence of any treatments <lb/>(Fig. 2) and further strengthened our conclusion that the single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds of the three pMHCs have different conforma-<lb/>tions at the single-molecule level. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>205 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>Donor <lb/>Acceptor <lb/>FRET1 <lb/>a <lb/>I Cy3 x10 3 <lb/>(a.u.) <lb/>I Cy5 x10 3 <lb/>(a.u.) <lb/>E <lb/>FRET1 <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>b <lb/>40 45 50 55 <lb/>0.86 0.75 0.61 0.47 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>c <lb/>E FRET1 <lb/>Distance (Å) <lb/>Number of bins <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>15 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.99 <lb/>0.61 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0 <lb/>4000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>1500 <lb/>3000 <lb/>d <lb/>K5 <lb/>N = 1,606 <lb/>MCC <lb/>N = 1,577 <lb/>102S <lb/>N = 1,933 <lb/>E FRET1 <lb/>Number of bins <lb/>44 Å <lb/>54 Å <lb/>66 Å <lb/>Distance (Å) <lb/>U(x) (k <lb/>B T) <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>f <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>MSD (μm 2 <lb/>) <lb/>Free, <lb/>D t = 0.60 μm 2 /s <lb/>Bound, <lb/>D t = 0.0042 μm 2 /s <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>-5 <lb/>5 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>Bound <lb/>Free <lb/>Position_X (μm) <lb/>Position_Y (μm) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>-5 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>g <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>Time (s) <lb/>Moving SD_X (μm) <lb/>Moving SD_Y (μm) <lb/>Position_Y (μm) <lb/>Position_X (μm) <lb/>Bound <lb/>Free <lb/>Bound <lb/>Free <lb/>Bound <lb/>Free <lb/>Bound <lb/>Free <lb/>e <lb/>Fig. 2 The conformational dynamics of single TCR-pMHC bonds. a A representative smFRET event mediated by the interaction between a 5C. <lb/>C7 TCR and a K5 pMHC. The donor, acceptor, and FRET signals are shown, and white arrows indicate single molecules. b Single-molecule time <lb/>trajectories of the donor (green, Cy3-pMHC) and the acceptor (red, Cy5-TCR) intensities (upper panel) and the corresponding time trajectory of <lb/>smFRET efficiency (yellow, lower panel). Single donor and acceptor molecules were tracked in real time to calculate the FRET efficiency. Also <lb/>see Fig. S5. c Histogram of the Cy3-Cy5 distances that was calculated from the smFRET efficiencies shown b (lower panel, see methods) and <lb/>fitted according to a Gaussian distribution (black curve). Also see Fig. S6. d Histograms of the TCR-pMHC bond distances for a single bond for <lb/>the K5, MCC, and 102S pMHCs. Each histogram used 1577-1933 trajectories to determine the most probale TCR-pMHC bond distance for each <lb/>pMHC. Also see Figs. S7 and S8. e PMF determination of single TCR-pMHC bonds for the K5, MCC, and 102S pMHCs. PMF indicates the free <lb/>energy changes as a function of the TCR-pMHC bond distance. f Representative diffusion trajectories of single pMHCs under free (red) and <lb/>bound (black) conditions (top panel). The mean squared displacement (MSD) vs. time (t) was plotted to show the mobility of single-tracked <lb/>pMHCs (x-axis: acquisition time in seconds; y-axis: MSD). The calculated diffusion coefficients (D t ) were determined for each type of diffusion <lb/>(bottom panel). g The horizontal positions x and vertical positions y of each single-tracked pMHC were plotted vs. time t for representative <lb/>single free (red) and bound (black) pMHCs (top panels). The corresponding sliding standard deviation σ for three consecutive points <lb/>according to the x and y positions were calculated to reveal the position changes of the single-tracked pMHCs (bottom panels) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>206 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>Measurement of intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ conformational <lb/>changes by FRET <lb/>It is not clear what induces the dissociation of CD3ζ from the <lb/>membrane to initiate T-cell intracellular signaling. To further <lb/>understand how surface TCR-pMHC bonds propagate extracellular <lb/>recognition signals to intracellular CD3ζ ITAMs across the cell <lb/>membrane, we developed a transmembrane FRET assay to <lb/>measure the conformational change between the extracellular <lb/>TCR αβ domain and the intracellular CD3ζ chain in the same TCR/ <lb/>CD3ζ complex (Fig. 1a). Upon the addition of 5C.C7 transgenic <lb/>T cells with Alexa Fluor 568-labeled TCRs and GFP-tagged CD3ζ to <lb/>a lipid bilayer containing pMHC ligands, we observed rapid <lb/>microcluster formation and the instant production of transmem-<lb/>brane GFP/Alexa Fluor 568 FRET. The TCRs and CD3ζ were <lb/>predominantly colocalized in the microclusters [Pearson correla-<lb/>tion coefficient, 25 0.93 ± 0.07] (Fig. 4a, Figs. S9 and S10, and <lb/>Movie S5), demonstrating the initiation of T-cell signaling via <lb/>segregated TCR-pMHC bond-mediated close contacts. 26 The high <lb/>level of TCR-CD3ζ colocalization suggested that the obligate <lb/>assembly of TCR-CD3ζ was necessary for effective T-cell signaling <lb/>and verified the specificity of transmembrane TCR-CD3ζ FRET. <lb/>TCRs and CD3ζ microclusters continuously moved from <lb/>the periphery to the center of the cell and merged into the <lb/>immunological synapse (Fig. 4a). We tracked and measured <lb/>the FRET efficiencies of each individual microcluster in real time. <lb/>After converting the FRET efficiencies to TCR-CD3ζ distances, we <lb/>plotted a three-dimensional figure (Fig. 4b) to illustrate the <lb/>simultaneous lateral movement of TCR-CD3ζ complexes (x-y axis) <lb/>(also see Fig. S10b) and the intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ distance <lb/>changes across the cell membrane (z-axis) upon K5 pMHC <lb/>engagement. The intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ distances within <lb/>different microclusters at equilibrium consistently showed añ <lb/>15 Å difference before and after K5 pMHC binding. <lb/>To test whether TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes were <lb/>dependent on TCR signaling, we used an Src kinase inhibitor <lb/>PP2 27 to block TCR signaling. Consistent with the results of a <lb/>previous study, 21 PP2 completely abrogated T-cell calcium <lb/>signaling (Fig. 4c, top), while TCRs could still form microclusters <lb/>(Fig. 4c, bottom). To reveal the role of TCR signaling in TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>conformational changes, we plotted the time trajectories of the <lb/>normalized intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ distances against the <lb/>stimulation time in the absence and presence of PP2 (Fig. 4d). <lb/>In the absence of PP2, the intracellular CD3ζ chain quickly <lb/>separated from the TCR extracellular domain upon TCR engage-<lb/>ment with the K5 pMHC and then reached a stable, fully extended <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ conformation. In sharp contrast, the blocking of TCR <lb/>signaling by PP2 completely abolished the TCR-CD3 conforma-<lb/>tional change (Fig. 4d). Consistently, this effect of TCR signaling <lb/>was also found for the MCC and 102S pMHCs (Fig. S11). Together <lb/>with the results of our negative control experiments (Fig. S12), <lb/>these PP2 experiments (Fig. 4d and Fig. S11) further verified that <lb/>transmembrane FRET was specifically caused by the TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>conformational change. <lb/>To compare the conformational dynamics induced by different <lb/>pMHCs, we plotted the TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes against <lb/>the stimulation time for the three pMHCs (Fig. 4e). We found that <lb/>the TCR-CD3ζ conformational change was dependent on the <lb/>potency of the peptide, as demonstrated by the amplitude and <lb/>speed of the TCR-CD3ζ conformational change for different <lb/>peptides (Fig. 4e). Compared with the nonstimulatory null peptide, <lb/>the super agonist K5 caused the largest change, while the weak <lb/>agonist 102S caused the smallest conformational change in the <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ complex. Quantitatively, the K5, MCC, and 102S pMHCs <lb/>resulted in~15 Å,~10 Å, and~5 Å separations between the TCR and <lb/>CD3ζ after TCR-pMHC binding, respectively (Fig. 4e). We also found <lb/>that TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes were restricted in the TCR/ <lb/>CD3ζ microclusters (Fig. 4a and Figs. S3a and S10a). Similar <lb/>TCR-pMHC distance (Å) <lb/>b <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>CD4 blockade <lb/>44 Å <lb/>52 Å <lb/>60 Å <lb/>N = <lb/>N = 339 <lb/>N = 790 <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Number of bins <lb/>LA treatment <lb/>a <lb/>0 <lb/>600 <lb/>1200 <lb/>1800 <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 <lb/>1200 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>44 Å <lb/>52 Å <lb/>63 Å <lb/>N = 1153 <lb/>N = 1295 <lb/>N = 529 <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>c TCR-pMHC bond distances <lb/>pMHC <lb/>K5 (Å) <lb/>MCC (Å) <lb/>102S (Å) <lb/>smFRET: no treatment <lb/>44 ± 9 <lb/>54 ± 11 <lb/>66 ± 18 <lb/>smFRET: LA treatment <lb/>44 ± 3 <lb/>52 ± 3 <lb/>63 ± 7 <lb/>smFRET: CD4 blockade <lb/>44 ± 9 <lb/>52 ± 7 <lb/>60 ± 12 <lb/>Bulk FRET: no treatment <lb/>43 ± 4 <lb/>53 ± 4 <lb/>63 ± 1 <lb/>Fig. 3 The Effects of TCR microclusters and CD4 binding on TCR-pMHC bond conformation. smFRET TCR-pMHC bond distance <lb/>measurements in the presence of the actin polymerization inhibitor latrunculin A (LA) (1 µM) (a) or µg/mL anti-CD4 blocking antibody (b) at <lb/>37°C. In each case, cells were pretreated with LA or antibody for 1 h before introduction to the planar bilayer. Histograms of TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distances for the K5, MCC, and 102S pMHCs are shown. Each histogram used 339-1295 single TCR-pMHC bond trajectories to identify the <lb/>most probable distance for each pMHC. c The TCR-pMHC bond distances for each pMHC in different conditions measured by FRET. Data are <lb/>presented as the most probable distance ± standard deviation (SD) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>207 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes were observed on the glass <lb/>surface functionalized with pMHCs (Figs. S1a and S13). All together, <lb/>these data highlighted that the TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes <lb/>that occurred in the TCR microclusters were driven by TCR-pMHC <lb/>engagement, which is consistent with previous reports that showed <lb/>that TCR microclusters are hotspots for TCR signaling. 2,21,28 <lb/>We next examined how TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes <lb/>regulate CD3ζ phosphorylation. Of the three pMHCs tested, we <lb/>found that the most potent, K5, caused the largest TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>separation (Fig. 4e) and the highest level of phosphorylation <lb/>(Fig. 4f, g and Fig. S14). In contrast, the least potent, 102S, caused <lb/>the smallest TCR-CD3ζ conformational change (Fig. 4e) and <lb/>resulted in the lowest level of phosphorylation of CD3ζ (Fig. 4f, g <lb/>and Fig. S14). The CD3ζ conformation and phosphorylation data <lb/>together suggested that the TCR-CD3ζ conformation controls the <lb/>degree of the dissociation of CD3ζ from the inner leaflet of the <lb/>plasma membrane, which influences the temporal (Fig. 4g) and <lb/>spatial (Fig. 4h) aspects of the phosphorylation of the ITAMs in <lb/>CD3ζ. Thus, transmembrane FRET could not only directly visualize <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes in situ but could also explain <lb/>the molecular mechanisms underlying signal propagation in TCR <lb/>ligand discrimination. <lb/>Linking TCR conformational changes to T-cell responsiveness <lb/>We then designed a series of experiments to test how the TCR <lb/>conformation controls TCR binding, signaling, and activation. To <lb/>test how the TCR-pMHC bond conformation regulates the <lb/>TCR-pMHC interaction, we performed micropipette adhesion <lb/>assays to measure the in situ two-dimensional (2D) TCR-pMHC <lb/>binding kinetics and affinities (Fig. 5a-d, Table 1, Fig. S15, Table S1 <lb/>54 <lb/>57 <lb/>60 <lb/>66 <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ distance (Å) <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>102S <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>g <lb/>h <lb/>CD3ζ Phosphorylation <lb/>1 min. <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>Phosphorylation <lb/>R 2 = 0.99 <lb/>0.0 0.5 1.0 1.5 2.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>400 <lb/>800 <lb/>1200 <lb/>f <lb/>% of Max <lb/>CD3ζ Phosphorylation <lb/>Endogenous <lb/>102S <lb/>MCC <lb/>K5 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1500 <lb/>a <lb/>CD3ζ-<lb/>GFP <lb/>FRET2 <lb/>9 ( m i n . ) <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.7 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Time = <lb/>TCR-<lb/>AF568 <lb/>Low <lb/>High <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>F/F <lb/>0 , Ca 2+ <lb/>Signal <lb/>(min.) <lb/>14 <lb/>0 <lb/>d <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>4 <lb/>7 <lb/>10 <lb/>PP2 <lb/>D/D <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>c <lb/>With PP2 <lb/>Without PP2 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>Distance (Å) <lb/>e <lb/>K5, MCC, 102S, Null <lb/>0 2 4 6 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>2 0 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>b <lb/>Fig. 4 TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes induced by TCR binding. a Representative real-time CD3ζ-GFP (green, donor), TCR-Alexa568 (red, <lb/>acceptor), and FRET (pseudocolor) signals from a typical transmembrane FRET experiment on a lipid bilayer at 37°C for the K5 pMHC. The <lb/>same experiments were performed for the MCC and 102S pMHCs. The calculated FRET2 efficiency is indicated in pseudocolor, with the cold-<lb/>to-hot color spectrum representing weak-to-strong FRET efficiency. Six to eight independent experiments were conducted for each pMHC. <lb/>Scale bar: 5 µm. b 3D illustration of the lateral movement (x-y) and intramolecular distance change (z) between TCR and CD3ζ in the individual <lb/>TCR/CD3ζ microclusters shown in a on the lipid bilayer. The x and y positions of each microcluster were tracked by the TrackMate plugin in <lb/>ImageJ, and the z positions were calculated according to the corresponding FRET efficiencies. Also see Movie S4 and 5 for microcluster <lb/>formation, Figs. S9 and S10 for data analysis, Fig. S18 for data calibration and Fig. S12 for the negative controls. c Time-lapsed microscopy <lb/>images of T-cell calcium signaling (top) and CD3ζ clustering (bottom) in the presence of 10 μM PP2. d Representative TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>intramolecular distance changes with (black) and without (red) PP2 treatment. e Time-dependent TCR-CD3ζ intramolecular distance changes <lb/>upon TCR binding to the K5, MCC, 102S, or null pMHC. Each curve shows the average intramolecular distances at consecutive time points <lb/>measured in three individual microclusters. f Phospho-flow cytometry showing the phosphorylation of CD3ζ in T cells upon contact with <lb/>antigen-presenting cells loaded with K5, MCC, or 102S peptide for 1 min. g The time course of CD3ζ phosphorylation upon stimulation with <lb/>the K5, MCC, or 102S peptide. h Correlation between CD3ζ phosphorylation (1 min of stimulation) and TCR-CD3ζ distance <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>208 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>and Movie S6). 3 Our data showed that the binding affinity (driven <lb/>by the on-rate) is well correlated with the pMHC potency (Table 1). <lb/>As revealed by the association of a shorter TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distance (Fig. 2d) with an increased TCR-pMHC binding affinity <lb/>(Fig. 5b-d and Table 1), our data suggested that a shorter <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond promotes the formation of a more stable TCR/ <lb/>pMHC complex, which is consistent with the classic bond length <lb/>theory in chemistry. 29 <lb/>To understand how the TCR-pMHC bond conformation triggers <lb/>T-cell signaling, we devised a fluorescence micropipette assay to <lb/>measure real-time T-cell calcium signaling at the single-cell level. <lb/>Fast single T-cell calcium flux was observed upon T cell/APC <lb/>contact (bond formation). Consistently, the calcium signaling <lb/>amplitude and speed were dependent on the peptide potency <lb/>(Fig. 5e, f, Fig. S15, and Movie S7). To link the TCR conformational <lb/>change to TCR signaling, we simultaneously plotted the associa-<lb/>tion of the TCR-CD3ζ conformational change with the Ca 2+ signal <lb/>against the stimulation time. We found that the CD3ζ conforma-<lb/>tional change was synchronized with the Ca 2+ signal for all three <lb/>different pMHCs (Fig. 5g). Together with the aforementioned <lb/>smFRET measurements (Fig. 2), our data revealed that the <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond conformation (Fig. 2d) governs the amplitude <lb/>of Ca 2+ release (Fig. 5e), possibly through bond distance-<lb/>associated mechanical forces. 30,31 Ca 2+ release in turn drives the <lb/>dissociation of positively charged CD3ζ from the negatively <lb/>charged phospholipids in the plasma membrane 32 to expose <lb/>the CD3ζ ITAM domains for phosphorylation via a Ca 2+ signaling <lb/>feedback loop (Fig. 5h). <lb/>According to the values for half-maximal T-cell proliferation <lb/>(EC 50 ) and the 3D half-life of pMHC tetramer binding reported by <lb/>Corse et al., 12 we then plotted the intermolecular TCR-pMHC <lb/>conformations and the intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ distances against <lb/>the values for the 2D on-rate, affinity, signaling, and proliferation <lb/>and the 3D tetramer half-life (Fig. S16). Strong negative (Fig. 6a, <lb/>solid dots and dashed lines) and positive (Fig. 6b, open dots and <lb/>solid lines) correlations were found for the TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distances and the TCR-CD3ζ distances vs. all of the metrics of TCR <lb/>binding, signaling, and activation, which govern the entire process <lb/>of signal reception, transduction, and regulation, respectively. <lb/>These measurements and correlations indicated the direct <lb/>physiological relevance of the conformational dynamics of single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds and individual TCR-CD3ζ complexes. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>There is considerable controversy about TCR recognition and the <lb/>initiation of signaling, which are key steps by which a TCR <lb/>specifically and sensitively recognizes its agonist ligand and then <lb/>transduces the recognition signal across the plasma membrane to <lb/>cause alternations in the cytoplasmic portions of the associated <lb/>CD3 signaling domains. To elucidate the molecular mechanisms <lb/>underlying this critical process, we need to understand: (1) how <lb/>the TCR discriminates between signals from a single agonist and <lb/>those derived from the surrounding abundant self-peptides, and <lb/>(2) how the TCR precisely propagates such a signal to CD3 to <lb/>properly trigger T-cell activation. Here, we developed an in situ <lb/>FRET method to measure the conformational changes of single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds on the cell surface and individual TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>complexes across the cell membrane (Fig. 1a). Cell surface FRET1 <lb/>revealed signal generation, and transmembrane FRET2 showed <lb/>further signal propagation and amplification. The integration of <lb/>both types of FRET could show the entire process of signal <lb/>initiation for TCR triggering. <lb/>The TCR conformational change model has long been used to <lb/>explain the mechanism underlying TCR triggering. However, <lb/>neither crystal structures nor other biochemical assays have been <lb/>able to provide solid evidence with enough spatiotemporal <lb/>resolution to either prove or disprove this model. Here, we <lb/>measured the intermolecular distances of single TCR-pMHC bonds <lb/>using highly sensitive smFRET (Fig. 1a). In biochemistry, bond <lb/>length, which is the average distance between the nuclei of two <lb/>bonded atoms in a molecule, is used to describe the compactness <lb/>of a bond. Because the TCR was labeled with a scFv and CD4 was <lb/>also bound to the pMHC, the distance measured here (Fig. 2d) did <lb/>not reflect the bond length. However, the same scFv (Fig. 1a) was <lb/>used for all three pMHCs, and CD4 binding contributed negligibly <lb/>to the TCR-pMHC bond distances (Fig. 3b). The TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>distances (Fig. 2d) measured in this study provided a reasonable <lb/>approximation to determine the compactness (or bond length) of <lb/>a TCR-pMHC bond, thus providing the most basic conformational <lb/>information at the single-molecule level to advance the under-<lb/>standing of the molecular mechanism underlying TCR recognition <lb/>in situ. <lb/>More importantly, the TCR-pMHC bond conformations mea-<lb/>sured by our smFRET assay were independent of the binding <lb/>affinity and kinetics, although they were well correlated (Fig. 6). <lb/>The smFRET assay is highly distance dependent and is only able to <lb/>detect FRET signals when a TCR binds to a pMHC on the cell <lb/>surface (Fig. 1b, d; comparison of K5 with null); 8,33 in other words, <lb/>smFRET only measured the conformational dynamics of single <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds. The bound state was confirmed by the <lb/>presence of a nearly immobilized pMHC (diffusion coefficient <lb/>D bound ≈ 0) for each smFRET trajectory, compared with the fast <lb/>diffusion of free pMHCs (Fig. 2f, g and Fig. S8). Such a dramatic <lb/>diffusion difference has been previously used to differentiate <lb/>bound and unbound pMHCs at the single-molecule level. 19,20 By <lb/>definition, the affinity is the ratio between bound and unbound <lb/>molecules at the equilibrium phase, and kinetics describes the <lb/>rates of bond association/dissociation. Because the TCR-pMHC <lb/>bond conformation is not influenced by unbound molecules and <lb/>bond association/dissociation, it is independent of the TCR-pMHC <lb/>binding affinity and kinetics. In other words, the TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>conformation measured by smFRET reveals an intrinsic property of <lb/>the TCR/pMHC complex in the bound state. <lb/>Based on the observation that TCRs form microclusters during <lb/>antigen recognition by conventional TIRF and superresolution <lb/>microscopy, 21,28,34 serial engagement has been proposed to <lb/>explain the high sensitivity of T-cell recognition. 2,3 To measure <lb/>the conformational dynamics of single TCR-pMHC bonds without <lb/>the possible influence of TCR clustering, we used the actin <lb/>polymerization inhibitor LA to prevent the formation of TCR <lb/>microclusters. Consistently, the smFRET measurements showed no <lb/>differences in the TCR-pMHC bond distances measured in the <lb/>presence or absence of TCR microclusters (Fig. 3c), which <lb/>reinforced the importance of the single TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>conformation in the triggering of T-cell signaling and revealed <lb/>the high sensitivity of TCR recognition. 1,2 <lb/>Spatially, our data revealed strong correlations between the <lb/>intermolecular TCR-pMHC conformation and the Ca 2+ flux <lb/>(Fig. 7a), the intramolecular TCR-CD3ζ distance (Fig. 7b), and <lb/>CD3ζ phosphorylation (Fig. 7c). Our data showed that the <lb/>strongest agonist, K5, formed the shortest TCR-pMHC bond, <lb/>which caused the greatest dissociation of CD3ζ from the inner <lb/>leaflet of the plasma membrane and lead to the maximum <lb/>exposure of its ITAMs to result in the highest level of <lb/>phosphorylation. In contrast, a structurally similar but weaker <lb/>ligand, 102S, formed the longest bond with the TCR, resulting in <lb/>the least dissociation of CD3ζ from the membrane and the lowest <lb/>level of phosphorylation. Our results collectively showed that a <lb/>TCR discriminates between closely related peptides by forming <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds with different conformations, which precisely <lb/>control the accessibility of CD3ζ ITAMs to phosphorylation (Fig. 7d). <lb/>This discovery highlighted the critical importance of bond <lb/>conformation in TCR triggering. Physiologically, our study <lb/>suggested that a short bond, but not a long bond, can efficiently <lb/>exclude the large, inhibitory tyrosine phosphatase CD45 to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>209 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>e <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>F/F 0 <lb/>Null <lb/>K5 <lb/>APC <lb/>T Cell <lb/>-1.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.7 <lb/>7 (min) <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>DIC+ <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>DIC+ <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>-1.1 <lb/>0 <lb/>2.8 <lb/>6 (min) <lb/>f <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>Signaling (F/F <lb/>0 ) <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Null <lb/>RBC T Cell <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>d <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>Adhesion Probability <lb/>Adhesion Probability <lb/>Adhesion Probability <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Contact Time (s) <lb/>m l = 56 <lb/>23 <lb/>9 <lb/>m l = 139 <lb/>30 <lb/>14 <lb/>m l = 1023 <lb/>225 <lb/>121 <lb/>) <lb/>s <lb/>( <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>T <lb/>t <lb/>c <lb/>a <lb/>t <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>) <lb/>s <lb/>( <lb/>e <lb/>m <lb/>i <lb/>T <lb/>t <lb/>c <lb/>a <lb/>t <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>Contact <lb/>Retract <lb/>Bond <lb/>Dissociation <lb/>t &lt; 30 s <lb/>t ~ 1-2 mins <lb/>TCR <lb/>Resting state <lb/>h <lb/>T cell <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>pMHC <lb/>Initial CD3ζ dissociation <lb/>and Ca 2+ release <lb/>T cell <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>Amplified CD3ζ <lb/>dissociation <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>pMHC <lb/>T cell <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>⊕ <lb/>⊕ <lb/>⊖ <lb/>⊖ <lb/>⊖ <lb/>⊖ ⊕ <lb/>⊕ <lb/>⊖ <lb/>g <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>Signal (F/F <lb/>0 ) <lb/>D/D <lb/>0 of CD3ζ <lb/>dynamics <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Time (min.) <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.3 <lb/>⊖ <lb/>ζ <lb/>2+ ion <lb/>+ <lb/>Fig. 5 2D kinetics and T-cell Ca 2+ signaling. a 2D micropipette adhesion frequency assay. A micropipette-aspirated T cell (right) was driven by <lb/>a piezoelectric translator to make controlled contact with an RBC coated with pMHC held by another pipette (left). The retraction of T cells to <lb/>the starting position resulted in elongation of the RBC, enabling the visual detection of the TCR-pMHC bond. Also see Fig. S15 and Movie S6. <lb/>Adhesion curves for 5C.C7 TCRs interacting with the K5 (b), MCC (c), and 102S (d) pMHCs measured by micropipette assay at 25°C at the <lb/>indicated pMHC site densities. Each cell pair was tested 50 times with a given contact duration to estimate the adhesion probability, and three <lb/>cell pairs were tested for each contact duration to calculate the mean adhesion probability. The data (points) were fitted by a probabilistic <lb/>kinetic model (curves) to determine the 2D binding kinetics. The data are summarized in Table 1 and Table S1. e Real-time single T-cell calcium <lb/>signaling measured by fluorescence micropipette. A CH27 cell loaded with the K5 (top row) or null peptide (bottom row, control) was precisely <lb/>controlled to make contact with a primary 5C.C7 T cell loaded with the Fluo-4 calcium indicator at 37°C. The fluorescence signal was recorded <lb/>in real time by time-lapsed microscopy, and the fold increase in Ca 2+ signaling (F/F 0 ) is shown in pseudocolor. Representative Ca 2+ imaging <lb/>experiments for the K5 and null peptides consisting of 6-8 independent experiments for each peptide are shown. Also see Fig. S15c, d for the <lb/>peptides MCC and 102S. See Movie S7 for more data. f Representative time trajectories for Ca 2+ signaling stimulated by the K5, MCC, 102S, and <lb/>null peptides. Fluorescence intensity values (F) at any given timepoint were divided by the initial fluorescence intensity value at time zero (F 0 ) <lb/>to obtain the fold increase in Ca 2+ signaling after cell contact. g The time course of Ca 2+ signaling (colored curves) and TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>conformational changes (black curves). h TCR-CD3ζ conformational changes were caused by a calcium signaling feedback loop. TCR-pMHC <lb/>bond formation causes CD3ζ dissociation and initiates Ca 2+ flux, which in turn promotes CD3ζ dissociation by neutralizing the negative <lb/>charges of the anionic phospholipids in the T-cell membrane to fully expose the ITAMs on CD3ζ to allow phosphorylation <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>210 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>increase the phosphorylation of CD3ζ ITAMs by Lck. 5,26 As bond <lb/>conformation is independent of binding affinity and kinetics, the <lb/>results of our study are also very well aligned with those of a <lb/>previous study showing that elongating the pMHC ectodomain <lb/>greatly reduces TCR triggering without affecting TCR-pMHC <lb/>binding. 17 <lb/>Temporally, our results revealed that near-instantaneous <lb/>TCR-pMHC binding (Fig. 2b) was concurrently followed by <lb/>delayed Ca 2+ flux and CD3ζ disassociation (Fig. 5g), which was <lb/>in line with the observation in a previous work that Ca 2+ and <lb/>CD3ε/ζ phosphorylation use a positive feedback loop to amplify <lb/>and sustain T-cell signaling. 32 Together with the results of previous <lb/>studies, our data suggested a &quot;TCR-pMHC bond conformational <lb/>change model&quot; (Fig. 7d) in which a TCR deciphers the structural <lb/>differences between foreign and self-peptides by forming <lb/>TCR-pMHC bonds with different distances, which most likely <lb/>trigger an increase in Ca 2+ signaling that is proportional to the <lb/>bond distance through bond distance-controlled mechanical <lb/>forces; 3,30,31,35 a previous study has shown that mechanical forces <lb/>are required to trigger Ca 2+ flux. 30 In turn, the released Ca 2+ <lb/>regulates the dissociation of positively charged CD3ζ cytoplasmic <lb/>domains from negatively charged phospholipids in the plasma <lb/>membrane (Fig. 5h). Such a Ca 2+ positive signaling feedback loop <lb/>propagates and amplifies the differences between foreign and <lb/>self-peptides until TCR-pMHC bond dissociation occurs. 36 This <lb/>bond conformational change model (Fig. 7d) is compatible with <lb/>existing TCR triggering models 5,6 and explains the high specificity <lb/>and sensitivity of T-cell recognition and the results of previous <lb/>studies of CD3 conformational changes. 9,37-40 Our model suggests <lb/>that T cells use accurate, reliable, and efficient machinery to <lb/>faithfully transduce extracellular TCR-pMHC binding into appro-<lb/>priate intracellular signals to ensure the optimal spatial and <lb/>temporal activation of T cells. <lb/>In summary, our study revealed the dynamic process underlying <lb/>the manner in which TCR recognition signals are initiated, <lb/>controlled, transmitted, and amplified via the direct linking of <lb/>the intermolecular TCR-pMHC conformation and the intramole-<lb/>cular TCR-CD3ζ distance to T-cell surface binding, intracellular <lb/>signaling, and functional responses. This sheds light on the <lb/>molecular mechanisms by which a TCR deciphers the structural <lb/>differences between foreign and self-peptides via the TCR-pMHC <lb/>bond conformation to initiate and amplify different TCR signaling <lb/>responses for ligand discrimination. <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL PROCEDURES <lb/>Mice <lb/>The Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the University <lb/>of Chicago approved the animal protocols used in this study. The <lb/>5C.C7 TCR transgenic RAG2 knockout mice with a B10.A back-<lb/>ground were a generous gift from the NIAID. <lb/>Cells <lb/>T-cell blasts were obtained by stimulating splenocytes isolated from <lb/>5C.C7 TCR transgenic mice with 10 μM MCC peptide (amino acids <lb/>88-103, ANERADLIAYLKQATK) according to a protocol approved by <lb/>the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee of the University of <lb/>Chicago. The T-cell blasts were maintained in complete medium <lb/>a <lb/>On-rate <lb/>Log (2D affinity) (μm 4 <lb/>) <lb/>Log 2D (on rate) (μm 4 <lb/>s -1 <lb/>) <lb/>Area (unit 2 <lb/>) <lb/>1/Log EC <lb/>50 (nM) <lb/>n <lb/>o <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>a <lb/>r <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>i <lb/>l <lb/>o <lb/>r <lb/>P <lb/>y <lb/>t <lb/>i <lb/>n <lb/>i <lb/>f <lb/>f <lb/>A <lb/>Signaling <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>R 2 <lb/>R <lb/>3 <lb/>9 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>6 <lb/>9 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>9 <lb/>9 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 = 0.99 <lb/>TCR-pMHC Distance (Å) <lb/>b <lb/>Log 2D (on rate) (μm 4 <lb/>s -1 <lb/>) <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>Log (2D affinity) (μm 4 <lb/>) <lb/>Area (unit 2 <lb/>) <lb/>1/Log EC <lb/>50 (nM) <lb/>R 2 <lb/>R <lb/>2 <lb/>6 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>8 <lb/>6 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 = 0.87 <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ distance (Å) <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>-5.4 <lb/>-4.8 <lb/>-4.2 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>-5 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-3 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>-5.5 <lb/>-5.0 <lb/>-4.5 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>-5 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-3 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>Fig. 6 Correlations between TCR conformations and T-cell binding kinetics, signaling, and proliferation. Correlations of the TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>conformation (a) and TCR-CD3ζ distance (b) with the 2D on-rate, 2D affinity, calcium signaling, and proliferation for the K5, MCC, and 102S <lb/>peptides. The EC 50 data for cell proliferation were adapted from Corse et al. 12 Data points were fitted with a linear function, and the goodness <lb/>of correlation is indicated by the R 2 value <lb/>Table 1. 2D kinetic parameters <lb/>Peptide <lb/>Sequence <lb/>T-cell activation <lb/>A c K a (µm 4 ) <lb/>k off (s −1 ) <lb/>A c K on (µm 4 s −1 ) <lb/>K5 <lb/>ANERADLIAYFKAATKF <lb/>Super agonist <lb/>3.7 ± 0.6 × 10 −4 <lb/>1.0 ± 0.3 <lb/>3.6 ± 0.5 × 10 −5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>ANERADLIAYLKQATK <lb/>Agonist <lb/>1.5 ± 0.7 × 10 −4 <lb/>1.3 ± 0.7 <lb/>2.0 ± 1.1 × 10 −5 <lb/>102S <lb/>ANERADLIAYLKQASK <lb/>Weak agonist <lb/>1.6 ± 0.7 × 10 −5 <lb/>1.5 ± 0.3 <lb/>2.4 ± 0.8 × 10 −6 <lb/></body>
			
			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>211 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>(RPMI 1640 medium with 10% fetal bovine serum (FBS), 2 mM L-<lb/>glutamine, 50 μM β-mercaptoethanol, and penicillin-streptomycin). <lb/>The T cells were used on days 6-9 for imaging and the micropipette <lb/>experiments. The live T cells were separated from the dead cells by <lb/>Ficoll-Paque density gradient media (GE). B-cell lymphoma CH27 <lb/>cells were used as APCs. The APCs were maintained in the same <lb/>medium that was used for the T cells. 2 Human RBCs were isolated <lb/>from the whole blood of healthy donors from the hospital at the <lb/>University of Chicago according to a protocol approved by the <lb/>Institutional Review Board of the University of Chicago. <lb/>Reagents <lb/>1-palmitoyl-2-oleoyl-sn-glycero-3-phosphocholine (POPC), 1,2-dio-<lb/>leoyl-sn-glycero-3-[(N-(5-amino-1-carboxypentyl) iminodiacetic acid) <lb/>succinyl] nickel salt (DGS-NTA-Ni 2+ ), and 1,2-dioleoyl-sn-glycero-3-<lb/>phosphoethanolamine-N [methoxy (polyethyleneglycol)-5000] <lb/>ammonium salt (PEG5000 PE) were purchased from Avanti Polar <lb/>Lipids. PBS, BSA, FBS, and Alexa Fluor 568 C5 maleimide were <lb/>purchased from Thermo Fisher Scientific. PEG-NTA-Ni 2+ -coated <lb/>coverslips were purchased from MicroSurfaces, Inc. Nunc Lab-Tek <lb/>eight-well chambered coverslips were purchased from Thermo <lb/>Fisher Scientific. His-tagged B7 was generated as previously <lb/>reported. His-tagged ICAM-1 was purchased from Sino Biological. <lb/>Cy3 and Cy5 maleimide mono-reactive dyes were purchased from <lb/>GE Life Sciences. Alexa Fluor 568, Fura-4, and di-methyl sulfoxide <lb/>were purchased from Thermo Scientific. LB media was obtained <lb/>from Fisher Scientific. <lb/>pMHCs <lb/>For the FRET measurements between TCRs and pMHCs on the cell <lb/>surface (FRET1), we generated a peptide-exchangeable CLIP-IE k <lb/>molecule. 41 The α and β chains of the CLIP-IE K molecule were <lb/>cloned into pAC vectors with a gp67 signal sequence (BD <lb/>Biosciences), acidic or basic leucine zipper sequences and a <lb/>6-histidine tag at the C-terminus. Primary baculoviruses were <lb/>prepared for each chain by cotransfecting the construct with <lb/>linearized baculovirus DNA (BestBac 2.0, Expression Systems) into <lb/>Sf9 cells using CellFectin reagent (Thermo Fisher Scientific). The <lb/>cells were washed and incubated at 27°C for 1 week. The primary <lb/>viruses were harvested by centrifugation and the collection of the <lb/>supernatant. Baculoviruses were amplified to generate higher <lb/>titers by infecting Sf9 cells for another week. Hi5 cells were <lb/>coinfected with baculoviruses encoding both chains, and <lb/>the supernatants were harvested after 65 h of infection. The pH <lb/>of the supernatant was adjusted to pH 6.9 with HEPES-buffered <lb/>saline (10 mM HEPES pH 7.2, 150 mM NaCl, and 0.02% NaN 3 ), 20 <lb/>mM imidazole, pH 7.2, 5 mM MgCl 2 , and 0.5 mM NiCl 2 . Ni-NTA <lb/>agarose (Qiagen) was added to the supernatant and stirred <lb/>overnight at 4°C. The supernatant was filtered, the Ni-NTA agarose <lb/>was collected, and CLIP-IE K was eluted using 200 mM imidazole, <lb/>pH 7.2, in HBS. The protein fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. <lb/>CLIP-IE K was purified using Superdex 200 size-exclusion column <lb/>chromatography and Mono-Q anion exchange chromatography <lb/>(GE healthcare). The purified fractions were used for peptide <lb/>loading. According to a method described in a previous <lb/>publication, 8 peptides with fluorescent maleimide dye (Cy3) at <lb/>the C-terminus, including K5(C)-ANERADLIAYFKAATKFGGdSdC, <lb/>MCC(C)-ANERADLIAYLKQATKGGdSdC, T102S(C)-ANERADLIAYLK-<lb/>QASKGGdSdC, and null(C)-ANERAELIAYLTQAAKGGdSdC, were <lb/>synthesized, labeled with Cy3, purified by HPLC, and verified by <lb/>mass spectrometry by the Elim Biopharm Company (CA). The <lb/>peptides of interest were added to the purified CLIP-IE k protein at <lb/>a 100-fold molar excess for the peptide exchange reaction. <lb/>Thrombin (1 U/100 μg of IE k ) was added and incubated at 37°C for <lb/>1 h. The pH of the solution was decreased by adding MES buffer, <lb/>pH 6.2, at a final concentration of 30 mM, and the IE K was again <lb/>incubated at 37°C overnight. The pH of the protein solution was <lb/>adjusted with 40 mM HEPES, pH 7.2. Extra peptides and denatured <lb/>proteins were removed by centrifugation (16,000 × g for 30 min at <lb/>pMHC <lb/>TCR <lb/>44 Å <lb/>54 Å <lb/>66 Å <lb/>K5 <lb/>MCC <lb/>102S <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>CD3ζ <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>e <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>e <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>l <lb/>l <lb/>e <lb/>C <lb/>T <lb/>pMHC <lb/>TCR <lb/>pMHC <lb/>TCR <lb/>d <lb/>64 Å <lb/>55 Å <lb/>53 Å <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ distance (Å) <lb/>TCR-pMHC distance (Å) <lb/>Ca 2+ <lb/>Signal <lb/>(Area under the curve) <lb/>CD3ζ Phosphorylation <lb/>R 2 <lb/>R <lb/>9 <lb/>9 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 <lb/>R <lb/>5 <lb/>8 <lb/>. <lb/>0 <lb/>= <lb/>2 = 0.89 <lb/>MCC <lb/>K5 <lb/>102S <lb/>MCC <lb/>K5 <lb/>102S <lb/>MCC <lb/>K5 <lb/>102S <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>a <lb/>45 <lb/>60 <lb/>75 <lb/>90 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>60 <lb/>75 <lb/>90 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>45 <lb/>60 <lb/>75 <lb/>90 <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>Force <lb/>Force <lb/>Force <lb/>Fig. 7 Mechanistic models of TCR triggering and discrimination. Correlations between TCR-pMHC bond conformation and calcium flux (a), <lb/>TCR-CD3ζ distance (b), and CD3ζ phosphorylation (c). d Our proposed model for TCR ligand discrimination. The TCR-pMHC bond <lb/>conformation controls the TCR-CD3ζ distance to regulate the exposure of ITAMs on CD3ζ for subsequent phosphorylation for the K5, MCC, <lb/>and 102S pMHCs, respectively <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>212 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>4°C) and desalting twice with Zeba Spin Desalting Columns <lb/>(Thermo Fisher). <lb/>For the FRET measurements between TCR and CD3ζ across the <lb/>cell membrane (FRET2) and the 2D micropipette adhesion assays, <lb/>IE k pMHC monomers generated by the NIH Tetramer Core Facility <lb/>were used. Biotinylated monomeric IE k was covalently complexed <lb/>with the ANERADLIAYFKAATKF (K5), ANERADLIAYLKQATK (MCC), <lb/>ANERADLIAYLKQASK (102S), and PVSKMRMATPLLMQA (human <lb/>CLIP 87-101) peptides. The IE k monomers were aliquoted and <lb/>stored at −80°C until use. <lb/>Production and labeling of the scFvs <lb/>Plasmid constructs encoding two mutants of the anti-TCR scFvs <lb/>J1 and J3 were obtained as a generous gift from Mark M. Davis <lb/>at Stanford University. 8 J1 was used for cell surface FRET1, and J3 <lb/>was used for the transmembrane FRET2 experiments. To <lb/>generate the J1 and J3 proteins, BL21 bacteria were transfected <lb/>with cDNA and cultured on a large scale (2 L each) in the <lb/>presence of isopropyl β-D-1-thiogalactopyranoside. The bacteria <lb/>were spun down, and the cell pellets were resuspended with <lb/>bacterial-protein extraction reagent (Thermo Fisher), lysozyme, <lb/>and DNase, followed by washing with inclusion wash buffer <lb/>(100 mM NaCl, 50 mM Tris base, and 0.05% (volume) Triton X-<lb/>100). 42 The refolding and purification of the recombinant scFvs <lb/>were performed using a modified method based on previous <lb/>publications. 43,44 In brief, the scFvs were unfolded in the <lb/>presence of 10 mM β-mercaptoethanol for 2 h at 25°C (in <lb/>100 mL of 100 mM Tris-HCl buffer with pH = 8.0, 6 M GuHCl and <lb/>200 mM NaCl), so that they could be refolded to obtain proteins <lb/>with the correct conformations by stepwise dialysis methods <lb/>without causing protein oxidation. To remove the reducing <lb/>agent, the denatured recombinant scFvs were dialyzed against <lb/>1 L of 100 mM Tris-HCl, pH 8.0, buffer with 6 M GuHCl and 200 <lb/>mM NaCl for 15 h at 4°C with gentle stirring. Then, stepwise <lb/>dialyses were performed in the same Tris-HCl buffer containing <lb/>decreasing concentrations of GuHCl (4, 2, 1, 0.5, and 0 M) for 15 <lb/>h for each step at 4°C with gentle stirring. During the 1 and 0.5 <lb/>M dialysis steps, 400 mM L-arginine (Sigma-Aldrich) and 375 μM <lb/>of oxidized glutathione (Sigma-Aldrich) were added. The final <lb/>dialysis was performed in buffer without GuHCl for 18 h at 4°C <lb/>with gentle stirring. The protein was concentrated and stored at <lb/>4°C prior to long-term storage at −20°C in the presence of 50% <lb/>glycerol. The purified scFVs were labeled with Cy5-malimide in <lb/>the presence of 50 µM Tris-(2-carboxyethyl) phosphine hydro-<lb/>chloride for 2 h at room temperature followed by 12 h of gentle <lb/>mixing at 4°C. Then, the labeled scFVs were purified by a resin <lb/>spin column. J1 and J3 were labeled and purified for the FRET <lb/>experiments. The binding specificity of each of the scFvs for the <lb/>5C.C7 TCRs was confirmed by flow cytometry before the imaging <lb/>experiments. <lb/>CD3ζ-GFP transduction <lb/>Primary 5C.C7 T cells were retrovirally transduced with CD3ζ-GFP <lb/>according to a previously published method. 45 Ecotropic <lb/>platinum-E retroviral packaging cells were transiently transfected <lb/>with the MIG-CD3ζ-GFP vector by calcium phosphate precipita-<lb/>tion. The viral supernatant was harvested twice at 48 and 72 h <lb/>post transfection, filtered by a 0.2 μm cellulose acetate membrane, <lb/>and used for the subsequent experiments. Splenocytes isolated <lb/>from 5C.C7 mice were cultured in RPMI supplemented with 10% <lb/>FBS, 2 mM glutamine, 50 µM 2-mercaptoethanol, 1 mM HEPES, 1 <lb/>mM sodium pyruvate, 1× glutamine and nonessential amino <lb/>acids (Thermo Fisher), 100 U/mL penicillin, 100 µg/mL streptomy-<lb/>cin, and 50 µg/mL gentamycin and stimulated with precoated 1.5 <lb/>μg/mL anti-CD3ε Ab (Clone 145-2C11, University of Chicago <lb/>Monoclonal Antibody Facility) and 0.5 μg/mL anti-CD28 Ab (Clone <lb/>37.51, Biolegend) in the presence of 40 U/mL recombinant human <lb/>IL-2 (Peprotech). After 24 h of cell activation, 2 mL viral <lb/>supernatant was added to a well of a Retronectin (Clontech)-<lb/>precoated (12.5 µg/mL in PBS, incubated at 4°C overnight) six-well <lb/>plate and centrifuged for 90 min at 3000 × g, and then the <lb/>stimulated cells were transferred to the plate and centrifuged in <lb/>the viral supernatant supplemented with 4 μg/mL protamine <lb/>sulfate at 800 × g for 90 min. The transduction rate of CD3ζ-GFP <lb/>was determined by GFP fluorescence at least 16 h after <lb/>transduction. <lb/>Lipid bilayer preparation <lb/>The glass-supported lipid bilayer preparation method was <lb/>developed based on previous publications. 25,46 The lipid layer <lb/>was generated by mixing POPC (90%), DGS-NTA-Ni 2+ (9.9%), and <lb/>PEG500PE (0.1%) in chloroform in clean glass vials. The chloroform <lb/>was dried with 0.22-µm-filtered N 2 , and then vials containing the <lb/>lipid layer were kept in a vacuum for 2 h to dry them completely. <lb/>The lipid layer was then resuspended in filtered PBS buffer (pH 7.4; <lb/>Clontech) at a concentration of 4 µM/mL. To decrease the sizes of <lb/>the multilamellar lipid vesicles to generate unilamellar vesicles, the <lb/>cloudy vesicle solution was repeatedly frozen in liquid nitrogen <lb/>and thawed in a 37°C water bath 30 times until the solution <lb/>became clear. The unilamellar vesicle solution was stored at <lb/>−80°C for future experiments. Before each experiment, a tube <lb/>was centrifuged at 33,000 × g for 45 min at 4°C. The supernatant <lb/>was incubated for 90 min on an eight-well Lab-Tek chamber <lb/>coverslip that was thoroughly prewashed twice with 5 N NaOH at <lb/>50°C, followed by washing with PBS twice at 37°C. The lipid <lb/>vesicles fused onto the glass surface and formed a glass-<lb/>supported lipid bilayer. The lipid bilayer was washed three <lb/>times thoroughly with PBS to remove excess lipids. Then, a <lb/>mixture of His-tagged, fluorescently labeled pMHCs and <lb/>His-tagged, nonfluorescent ICAM-1, and B7 was added to the <lb/>lipid bilayer and incubated for 1 h. After 30 min, the unbound <lb/>proteins were washed with PBS three times. The bound protein <lb/>was incubated for another 30 min at 37°C, and the weakly bound <lb/>proteins were washed away with PBS three additional times. The <lb/>protein-bound lipid was incubated with 1% BSA for 20 min to <lb/>minimize the background fluorescence during microscopy experi-<lb/>ments. The excess BSA was washed away three times with PBS. <lb/>The microscopy experiments were performed using imaging <lb/>buffer (PBS, pH 7.4, 137 mM NaCl, 5 mM KCl, 1 mM CaCl , 2 mM <lb/>MgCl 2 , 0.7 mM Na 2 HPO 4 , 6 mM D-glucose, and 1% BSA). <lb/>The fluidity and integrity of the lipid bilayer were tested by <lb/>fluorescence recovery after photobleaching experiments with 32 <lb/>nM Cy3-labeled pMHC reconstituted on a supportive lipid bilayer <lb/>(Fig. S2a and Movie S2). The photobleaching was performed by <lb/>using a high power (60 mW) 532-nm CW laser with 5 s of exposure <lb/>at the center of the imaging area, and the fluorescence recovery of <lb/>the lipid bilayer was imaged with a 470 ± 10 nm LED light at 10 s <lb/>intervals. The power and duration of the laser and LED light <lb/>excitation were controlled by analog modulation. The diffusion <lb/>coefficient (D) was determined by labeling the lipid bilayer with <lb/>1 nM of Cy3-labeled pMHCs, which were excited by a stable <lb/>532-nm laser (Fig. S2g). The diffusion of the single pMHCs in the <lb/>lipid bilayer was tracked in real time and characterized (Fig. S2b-f <lb/>and Movie S1). The experimentally determined diffusion coeffi-<lb/>cient D e was verified by a small-scale simulation D s, which showed <lb/>high similarity (Fig. S2h-k). The pMHC diffusion constant was <lb/>determined by the TrackArt program in MATLAB and was <lb/>consistent with previously reported values. <lb/>Microscopy <lb/>All imaging experiments were performed using our custom-built <lb/>TIRF and epifluorescence microscope setup, which utilized a Nikon-<lb/>Ti-E inverted microscope attached to an Optosplit III (CAIRN <lb/>Research) and an Andor iXon 888 EMCCD camera (1024 × 1024 <lb/>pixel) (Fig. S1b). The individual of 405, 488, 532, and 647-nm <lb/>(Cobolt) CW laser lines were aligned to an achromatic fiber port <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>213 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>(APC type, 400-700 nm, Thorlabs, Inc.) and then passed through an <lb/>achromatic polarization-maintaining single-mode fiber to a motor-<lb/>ized Nikon TIRF illuminator. The lasers were directed by a custom-<lb/>built quad-band dichroic mirror (Chroma, ZT405-488-532-640rcp) <lb/>to the sample through a 1.42 NA 100× TIRF objective. A seven-<lb/>color solid-state LED light source with bandpass filters was also <lb/>attached with a liquid light guide to the upper filter cube wheel in <lb/>the Nikon microscope. The fluorescence from the donor and <lb/>acceptor passed through a quad-band laser clean-up filter (ZET405-<lb/>488-532-647m) and then passed through the Optosplit III to <lb/>separate the emission fluorescence of the FRET donor and the <lb/>acceptor. In the Optosplit cube, we used different filter sets for the <lb/>FRET1 and FRET2 experiments. For FRET1 (Cy3-Cy5), we used <lb/>T640lpxr-UF2 (Chroma) as a dichroic filter, ET585/65 for the Cy3 <lb/>channel (Chroma), and ET655lp for the Cy5 channel (Chroma) for <lb/>the individual fluorescence signals. For FRET2 (GFP-Alexa568), we <lb/>used the dichroic filter T560lpxr-UF2 and two bandpass filters: <lb/>Chroma ET510/20m for GFP and Chroma ET595/50m for Alexa568. <lb/>For single-molecule imaging, we used hardware sequencing to <lb/>obtain the highest frame rate (5-10 ms exposure) using high EM <lb/>gain. Either hardware sequencing (via the camera) or software <lb/>sequencing (Micromanager) was utilized with analog modulation <lb/>to synchronize the image acquisition by the EMCCD camera, which <lb/>triggered each laser and individual LED source. The donor and <lb/>acceptor signal channels were physically separated by the beam <lb/>splitter in the Optosplit III, and both signals were imaged <lb/>simultaneously on the same image frame. The hardware stage <lb/>control information and images were acquired by Micromanager. 48 <lb/>FRET experiments <lb/>For the intermolecular TCR-pMHC FRET1 measurements, T cells <lb/>were incubated with a saturated concentration (0.027 µg/µL, <lb/>Fig. S17a) of Cy5-labeled scFv J1 for 30 min at 4°C. After three <lb/>washes, the cells were added to a lipid bilayer containing Cy3-<lb/>labeled pMHCs (0.3 molecules/μm 2 ) to perform smFRET using <lb/>TIRF microscopy in a stream model. To perform the bulk FRET1 <lb/>experiments, we used a pMHC density of 95 molecules/μm 2 in <lb/>the lipid bilayer. For the intramolecular TCR-CD3 FRET2 <lb/>measurements, T cells transduced with CD3ζ-GFP were labeled <lb/>with a saturated concentration (0.027 µg/µL, Fig. S17a) of <lb/>Alexa568-labeled scFv J3 for 30 min at 4°C. After three washes, <lb/>the cells were added to a lipid bilayer containing unlabeled <lb/>pMHCs to perform transmembrane FRET2 using epifluorescence <lb/>microscopy. <lb/>Density quantification of the TCRs and pMHCs <lb/>The average surface TCR density in the 5C.C7 T cells (labeled with <lb/>a saturated concentration of H57 scFv) in the contact area <lb/>between a T cell and the lipid bilayer were quantified based on <lb/>the fluorescence signal of a single Cy5-or Alexa568-labeled <lb/>H57 scFv. The molecular density of pMHCs in the lipid bilayer was <lb/>estimated by dividing the total number of pMHC molecules by the <lb/>total surface area as described previously. 25 <lb/>CD4 blockade and pharmacological treatments <lb/>To measure the TCR-pMHC bond distance by smFRET in the <lb/>absence of CD4 binding, T cells were incubated with 10 μg/mL <lb/>anti-CD4 antibody (GK 1.5, Biolegend) and 0.027 µg/µL of Cy5-J1 <lb/>scFV for 30 min at 4°C. After three washes, the cells were added to <lb/>a lipid bilayer containing Cy3-pMHCs, and smFRET assays were <lb/>performed in the continuous presence of 10 μg/mL anti-CD4 <lb/>antibody at 37°C using TIRF microscopy. To measure the <lb/>TCR-pMHC bond distance by smFRET without the formation of <lb/>TCR microclusters, T cells were incubated with 1 μM LA (Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich) and 0.027 µg/µL of Cy5-J1 scFv for 1 h at 25°C. The cells <lb/>were washed three times, and smFRET assays were performed <lb/>with a lipid bilayer containing Cy3-labeled pMHCs in the <lb/>continuous presence of 1 μM LA 3 at 37°C using TIRF microscopy. <lb/>To measure the TCR-CD3ζ conformational dynamics in the <lb/>absence of TCR signaling, T cells were incubated with 10 μM <lb/>PP2 (Sigma-Aldrich) and 0.027 µg/µL of Cy5-J1 scFv for 1 h at <lb/>25°C. The cells were washed three times, and smFRET assays were <lb/>performed with a lipid bilayer containing Cy3-labeled pMHCs in <lb/>the continuous presence of 10 μM PP2 49 at 37°C using <lb/>epifluorescence microscopy. In parallel, to demonstrate the role <lb/>of PP2 in blocking TCR signaling, CD3ζ-GFP T cells were loaded <lb/>with a calcium indicator dye (X-Rhod-5F, Thermo Fisher Scientific), <lb/>and the real-time calcium flux was measured at 37°C using <lb/>epifluorescence microscopy. <lb/>Anisotropy measurements <lb/>Anisotropy measurements (Fig. S17b) were performed as pre-<lb/>viously described. 50 Briefly, a polarized 532-nm laser was used to <lb/>excite the samples, and the emission was split by a Wollaston <lb/>prism (CAIRN Res.) into parallel and perpendicular polarized <lb/>components that were imaged simultaneously with an EMCCD. <lb/>The fluorescence anisotropy was determined by the following <lb/>equation: 51 <lb/>rðtÞ ¼ I k À GI ? =I k þ 2GI ? ; <lb/>(1) <lb/>where I k and I ? are the fluorescence intensities of the parallel (k) <lb/>and perpendicular ð?Þ polarized emission components with <lb/>respect to the vertically polarized excitation. The G-factors were <lb/>calculated according to previously reported methods. 51 <lb/>2D fluorescent micropipette assays <lb/>The micropipette apparatuses were constructed by using a Leica <lb/>inverted microscope placed on an anti-vibration table (Newport) <lb/>equipped with manometer systems to apply suction pressure <lb/>through glass pipettes (Fig. S15a). Two opposing pipettes were <lb/>attached to two identical piezoelectric micromanipulators (Sensa-<lb/>pex) to control the contacts between a T cell and a pMHC-coated <lb/>RBC or CH27 APC. In the micropipette apparatus, one of the <lb/>pipettes was also attached to a PI piezo actuator to allow <lb/>computer-controlled fine movements for the repeated adhesion <lb/>test cycles. A cell chamber of the desired size was prepared by <lb/>cutting a coverslip. The temperature of the cell chamber (37°C) <lb/>was controlled by an objective heater (Bioptechs). To avoid <lb/>medium evaporation during heating, the chamber was sealed <lb/>with mineral oil (Sigma). The real-time images were acquired by an <lb/>Andor iXon 888 EMCCD camera with a 100× objective and <lb/>Micromanager software. For real-time calcium imaging, the <lb/>sample was illuminated by sequentially triggered exposure to <lb/>470 ± 20 nm blue light (Spectra X, Lumencor) and white LED light. <lb/>The triggering of the light channels and the data acquisition were <lb/>performed with analog modulation using Micromanager. 48 For the <lb/>2D kinetic measurements, only continuous white LED light was <lb/>used to detect the adhesion between a T cell and a pMHC-<lb/>coated RBC. <lb/>2D micropipette kinetic assays <lb/>The 2D micropipette adhesion experiments 3 were performed <lb/>using T-cell blasts 2 and pMHC-coated RBCs. Monomeric pMHCs <lb/>were coated onto RBCs by biotin-streptavidin coupling. RBCs <lb/>isolated from whole blood were biotinylated using different <lb/>concentrations of biotin-X-NHS according to the manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Ten microliters of RBC solution (~10 × 10 ) with 2 mg/mL <lb/>streptavidin solution (10 µl) were mixed for 30 min at 4°C and <lb/>then incubated with 20 μg/mL biotinylated pMHC monomer for <lb/>30 min at 4°C. After each step, the RBCs were washed three times. <lb/>To determine the surface TCR and pMHC densities, T cells were <lb/>incubated with 10 μg/mL of the PE-conjugated anti-mouse TCR β <lb/>chain antibody clone H57-597 (BD) in 200 μL of FACS buffer (RPMI <lb/>1640, 5 mM EDTA, 1% BSA, and 0.02% sodium azide) at 4°C for <lb/>min, and the pMHC-coated RBCs were stained with the PE-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>214 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>conjugated anti-IE k clone 14.4.4s (BD). The T cells and RBCs were <lb/>analyzed by a BD LSRFortessa flow cytometer. The fluorescence <lb/>intensities were compared with those of standard calibration <lb/>beads (BD Quantibrite PE Beads, BD) to determine the total <lb/>number of molecules per cell, which were divided by the cell or <lb/>bead surface area to obtain the site densities. The apparent <lb/>surface area of a T cell (523 μm 2 ) and an RBC (140 μm 2 ) were <lb/>calculated according to the areas of smooth spheres based on the <lb/>microscopic measurement of their radii. <lb/>T cells were incubated at 37°C with a saturating concentration <lb/>(10 µg/mL) of purified anti-mouse CD4 (clone GK 1.5, BD) prior to <lb/>their addition to the chamber. The RBC was moved in and out of <lb/>contact with the T cell to maintain specific contact times (0.25, 0.5, <lb/>0.75, 1, 2, and 5 s) and area by a computer program. The adhesion <lb/>events were detected by observing RBC elongation upon cell <lb/>separation. The contact-retraction cycle was repeated 50 times for <lb/>each given contact time. The specific adhesion probability (P a ) for <lb/>each contact timepoint was calculated by subtracting the <lb/>nonspecific adhesion frequency (P nonspecific ). The following equa-<lb/>tions were used to analyze the data. <lb/>P a vs. contact time t were fitted using a probabilistic model <lb/>(Eq. 1): 52 <lb/>P a ¼ 1 À exp Àm r m l A c K a 1 À exp Àk r t <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ <lb/>½ <lb/>f <lb/>g ; <lb/>(2) <lb/>where K a and k r are the 2D binding affinity and off-rate, m r and m l <lb/>are the respective TCR and pMHC densities that were measured by <lb/>flow cytometry, and A c is the contact area. The curve fitting <lb/>generates two parameters, the effective 2D affinity A c K a and the <lb/>2D off-rate k r . Its product with the off-rate is the effective 2D on-<lb/>rate: <lb/>A c k on ¼ A c K a´kr <lb/>(3) <lb/>P a ¼ <lb/>ðP measured À P nonspecific Þ <lb/>1 À P nonspecific <lb/>; <lb/>(4) <lb/>where P nonspecifc and P measured are the nonspecific adhesion <lb/>fraction and the total measured adhesion, respectively. <lb/>FRET analysis <lb/>FRET is a nonradiative process that originates from the <lb/>dipole-dipole interaction between the electronic states of the <lb/>donor and acceptor (11, 33). The energy transfer occurs only when <lb/>the oscillations of the optically induced electronic coherence of <lb/>the donor are resonant with the electronic energy gap of the <lb/>acceptor. The efficiency of energy transfer (E FRET ) is sensitive to the <lb/>distance between the donor and the acceptor, which is typically in <lb/>the range of 10-100 Å. The energy transfer efficiency (E FRET ) is <lb/>generally given by: 11,33 <lb/>E FRET ¼ <lb/>1 <lb/>1 þ ðr=R 0 Þ 6 ; <lb/>(5) <lb/>where r is the distance between donor (D) and acceptor (A) and R 0 <lb/>is Förster&apos;s distance. FRET is very sensitive to the distance between <lb/>the acceptor and the donor, which may change <lb/>due to conformational dynamics or other factors. The E FRET <lb/>between D and A was calculated by a ratiometric method to reveal <lb/>the conformational dynamics using the following equation: 11,33 <lb/>E FRET ¼ <lb/>I A <lb/>I A þ I D γ <lb/>; <lb/>(6) <lb/>where I A and I D are the fluorescence emission intensities of the <lb/>acceptor and the donor, respectively, and γ is the correction factor, <lb/>which is determined as the ratio of the detection efficiencies of <lb/>the acceptor and donor channels according to a previously <lb/>reported method. 33 Before E FRET calculation, each image was <lb/>background-corrected, and the bleed-through was corrected <lb/>according to a previously reported method. 33 The Alexa Fluor <lb/>intensity was further corrected according to the scFV <lb/>dissociation kinetics for FRET2 (Fig. S18). <lb/>To obtain the distribution of the FRET efficiencies, E FRET , and the <lb/>corresponding distances between a FRET donor and a FRET <lb/>acceptor, we tracked and measured the fluorescence intensities of <lb/>single donor and acceptor molecules. For each experiment, image <lb/>registration was first performed using MATLAB for the images of <lb/>the corresponding frames from the donor channel and the <lb/>acceptor channel. The donor and acceptor molecules were <lb/>identified and tracked using TrackMate in ImageJ until the end <lb/>of each FRET trajectory. The fluorescence intensities of a donor <lb/>and an acceptor were measured and background-corrected <lb/>frame-by-frame. Eqns. 5 and 6 were used to calculate E FRET and the <lb/>corresponding distance for both the FRET1 (Cy3/Cy5) and FRET2 <lb/>(GFP/Alexa568) experiments. By tracking the trajectories of many <lb/>individual FRET pairs, we obtained the values and distribution of <lb/>E FRET and the corresponding distance using Eqs. 5 and 6. <lb/>For the ensemble FRET1 experiments, because the binding <lb/>affinities were different for the three pMHCs, their TCR occupan-<lb/>cies were different. To calculate the TCR-pMHC bond distance in <lb/>the bound state, the unbound pMHCs were removed from the <lb/>FRET calculation. 53 The bound TCRs were directly measured by <lb/>Cy3/Cy5 FRET because FRET is highly distance specific 8 (Fig. 1b, <lb/>comparison of K5 with null). Only the bound pMHCs and the <lb/>bound TCRs were used to calculate the FRET efficiency and <lb/>distance using Eqs. 5 and 6 after background and bleed-through <lb/>correction. <lb/>PMF analysis <lb/>One way to quantify the binding strength is to examine the PMF <lb/>of the fluctuation of the donor-receptor distance R. The PMF in <lb/>this context is given by: 16,54 <lb/>F R <lb/>ð Þ ¼ Àk B T´ln P R <lb/>ð Þ <lb/>ð <lb/>Þ; <lb/>(7) <lb/>where P(R) is the histogram representing the distance that is an <lb/>average of the steady-state signals collected from 1500 indepen-<lb/>dent TCR-pMHC bond trajectories. The PMF measures the free <lb/>energy cost of variation for distance R. It is minimized at <lb/>equilibrium. Its curvature governs the size of the fluctuations. A <lb/>shallower potential curve implies greater fluctuation and weak <lb/>binding. <lb/>Microcluster tracking analysis <lb/>For the FRET2 analysis, we developed a method to track individual <lb/>CD3ζ (donor) and TCR (acceptor) microclusters in three dimen-<lb/>sions (x, y, and z) using the TrackMate plugin in Fiji. 55 The track for <lb/>each individual donor and acceptor cluster gave the lateral <lb/>movement (x-y axis) as well as the FRET2 efficiency (TCR-CD3ζ <lb/>distance, z-axis) as the microclusters moved toward the center and <lb/>formed immunological synapses. <lb/>Measurement of CD3ζ phosphorylation <lb/>We used phospho-flow cytometry to measure the phosphoryla-<lb/>tion of CD3ζ at the single-cell level. 56,57 CH27 cells were <lb/>preincubated with 10 μM peptide in complete medium for 3 h at <lb/>37°C. CH27 cells with preincubation were used as a negative <lb/>control. Peptide-loaded CH27 cells were washed three times. 2 5C. <lb/>C7 T cells were rested in serum-free RPMI medium at 37°C for 3 h <lb/>to reduce the background phosphorylation level. A total of <lb/>50,000 peptide-loaded CH27 cells and 50,000 rested 5C.C7 T cells <lb/>were precooled and mixed in a tube on ice. The tube was <lb/>centrifuged at 300 × g for 1 min at 4°C to initiate cell-cell contact <lb/>and immediately transferred to a 37°C water bath to initiate T-cell <lb/>stimulation. The stimulation was terminated at the indicated time <lb/>points with 4% PFA fixation. After 10 min of fixation at room <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>215 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<body>temperature, the cells were washed twice with ice-cold PBS <lb/>containing 2% BSA and then resuspended in 80% methanol and <lb/>incubated for 30 min at −20°C. After washing twice with ice-cold <lb/>PBS, 0.3 μg/mL Alexa Flour-488-labeled anti-pY142-CD3ζ antibody <lb/>(BD) was added to a final volume of 100 μL of ice-cold PBS and <lb/>incubated at 4°C for 45 min. The cells were washed three times <lb/>with ice-cold PBS containing 2% BSA and analyzed by flow <lb/>cytometry. The flow cytometry data were further processed with <lb/>FlowJo software. <lb/>Ca 2+ imaging <lb/>For the Ca 2+ flux experiments, T cells (~10 6 ) were incubated with <lb/>5 μM of the fluorescent dye Fluo-4 AM (Thermo Fisher Scientific) <lb/>for 30 min in complete RPMI 1640 medium. All the Fluo-4 loading <lb/>and imaging experiments were performed in the presence of 2.5 <lb/>mM probenecid. The T cells were washed twice with minimal <lb/>imaging media (MIM; colorless RPMI with 5% FBS and 10 mM <lb/>HEPES) and then incubated in MIM for 10 min at 37°C before data <lb/>collection. 58 For imaging, a LEITZ DMIRB Leica Microscope <lb/>equipped with a 100× objective and an iXON Ultra 888 EMCCD <lb/>camera were used. The calcium flux imaging acquisition was <lb/>performed with Micromanager software. For the T cell/APC <lb/>conjugate experiments, CH27 cells (10 6 ) were incubated with 4 <lb/>μM of each peptide for 4 h at 37°C and then washed with MIM. <lb/>The T cells (2 μL) and CH27 cells (2 μL) were added to MIM (300 μL) <lb/>in the cell chamber. The chamber was sealed using mineral oil on <lb/>both sides to avoid MIM evaporation. The signals from Fluo-4 were <lb/>collected at intervals of 100 ms for up to 20 min and postpro-<lb/>cessed with Fiji software. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We thank Mark M. Davis at Stanford for providing the constructs for the anti-TCR <lb/>scFvs, Michael Birnbaum at MIT for providing the IE k plasmids, Xiaolei Su and <lb/>Marcus Taylor in the lab of Ronald Vale at UCSF for advice regarding the <lb/>preparation of the glass-supported lipid bilayer, Jillian Rosenberg for reading the <lb/>manuscript, and the NIH Tetramer Core Facility for providing the pMHC monomers. <lb/>This work was mainly supported by NIH grants R00AI106941 and R21AI120010, NSF <lb/>CAREER Award 1653782, a Chicago Biomedical Consortium Catalyst Award (to J.H.) <lb/>and postdoctoral grant PDR-092 (to D.K.S.), with additional support from the Searle <lb/>Funds at The Chicago Community Trust. This work is also supported by NIH <lb/>grant R01AI126756 (to E.J.A.) and R01CA022677 (to H.S.). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>J.H. conceived, directed, and supervised the project. J.H. and D.K.S. designed the <lb/>experiments. D.K.S. custom-built the fluorescence microscopy system, performed the <lb/>imaging experiments, and analyzed the data unless otherwise indicated. W.F. and <lb/>D.K.S. custom-built the micropipette system. W.F. performed all 2D binding kinetics <lb/>assays and analyzed the data. W.F. and D.K.S. performed the Ca 2+ imaging <lb/>experiments and D.K.S. analyzed the data. The reagents and experimental systems <lb/>were designed and tested by D.K.S. unless otherwise indicated. S.R. and E.J.A. <lb/>generated the IE k proteins and made Fig. 1a. H.L. and J.Q. performed the PMF <lb/>analysis. G.C. analyzed the smFRET1 data. Y.H. and H.S. prepared the CD3ζ-GFP <lb/>construct and transduced the primary T cells. C.C. performed the phospho-flow <lb/>cytometry. D.K.S. and P.L. cultured the T cells. D.K.S. and J.H. wrote the manuscript <lb/>with input from all authors. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">ADDITIONAL INFORMATION <lb/>The online version of this article (https://doi.org/10.1038/s41423-019-0273-6) <lb/>contains supplementary material. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Irvine, D. J., Purbhoo, M. A., Krogsgaard, M. &amp; Davis, M. M. Direct observation of <lb/>ligand recognition by T cells. Nature 419, 845-849 (2002). <lb/>2. Huang, J. et al. A single peptide-major histocompatibility complex ligand triggers <lb/>digital cytokine secretion in CD4(+) T cells. Immunity 39, 846-857 (2013). <lb/>3. Huang, J. et al. The kinetics of two-dimensional TCR and pMHC interactions <lb/>determine T-cell responsiveness. Nature 464, 932-936 (2010). <lb/>4. Germain, R. N. Computational analysis of T cell receptor signaling and <lb/>ligand discrimination-past, present, and future. FEBS Lett. 584, 4814-4822 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>5. van der Merwe, P. A. &amp; Dushek, O. Mechanisms for T cell receptor triggering. Nat. <lb/>Rev. Immunol. 11, 47-55 (2010). <lb/>6. Chakraborty, A. K. &amp; Weiss, A. Insights into the initiation of TCR signaling. Nat. <lb/>Immunol. 15, 798-807 (2014). <lb/>7. Rudolph, M. G., Stanfield, R. L. &amp; Wilson, I. A. How TCRs bind MHCs, peptides, and <lb/>coreceptors. Annu. Rev. Immunol. 24, 419-466 (2006). <lb/>8. Huppa, J. B. et al. TCR-peptide-MHC interactions in situ show accelerated kinetics <lb/>and increased affinity. Nature 463, 963-967 (2010). <lb/>9. Xu, C. et al. Regulation of T cell receptor activation by dynamic membrane <lb/>binding of the CD3epsilon cytoplasmic tyrosine-based motif. Cell 135, 702-713 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>10. Ha, T. et al. Probing the interaction between two single molecules: fluorescence <lb/>resonance energy transfer between a single donor and a single acceptor. Proc. <lb/>Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 93, 6264-6268 (1996). <lb/>11. Sasmal, D. K., Pulido, L. E., Kasal, S. &amp; Huang, J. Single-molecule fluorescence <lb/>resonance energy transfer in molecular biology. Nanoscale 8, 19928-19944 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>12. Corse, E., Gottschalk, R. A., Krogsgaard, M. &amp; Allison, J. P. Attenuated T cell <lb/>responses to a high-potency ligand in vivo. PLoS Biol. 8, e1000481 (2010). <lb/>13. Natarajan, K. et al. An allosteric site in the T-cell receptor Cbeta domain plays a <lb/>critical signalling role. Nat. Commun. 8, 15260 (2017). <lb/>14. Wu, P. et al. Mechano-regulation of peptide-MHC class I conformations deter-<lb/>mines TCRantigen recognition. Mol. Cell 73, 1015-27 e7 (2019). <lb/>15. Newell, E. W. et al. Structural basis of specificity and cross-reactivity in T cell <lb/>receptors specific for cytochrome c-I-E(k). J. Immunol. 186, 5823-5832 (2011). <lb/>16. Yang, H. et al. Protein conformational dynamics probed by single-molecule <lb/>electron transfer. Science 302, 262-266 (2003). <lb/>17. Choudhuri, K., Wiseman, D., Brown, M. H., Gould, K. &amp; van der Merwe, P. A. T-cell <lb/>receptor triggering is critically dependent on the dimensions of its peptide-MHC <lb/>ligand. Nature 436, 578-582 (2005). <lb/>18. Choudhuri, K. et al. Peptide-major histocompatibility complex dimensions control <lb/>proximal kinase-phosphatase balance during T cell activation. J. Biol. Chem. 284, <lb/>26096-26105 (2009). <lb/>19. O&apos;Donoghue, G. P., Pielak, R. M., Smoligovets, A. A., Lin, J. J. &amp; Groves, J. T. Direct <lb/>single molecule measurement of TCR triggering by agonist pMHC in living pri-<lb/>mary T cells. eLife 2, e00778 (2013). <lb/>20. Taylor, M. J., Husain, K., Gartner, Z. J., Mayor, S. &amp; Vale, R. D. A DNA-based T cell <lb/>receptor reveals a role for receptor clustering in ligand discrimination. Cell 169, <lb/>108-119 e20 (2017). <lb/>21. Campi, G., Varma, R. &amp; Dustin, M. L. Actin and agonist MHC-peptide complex-<lb/>dependent T cell receptor microclusters as scaffolds for signaling. J. Exp. Med. <lb/>202, 1031-1036 (2005). <lb/>22. Hong, J. et al. Force-regulated in situ TCR-peptide-bound MHC class II kinetics <lb/>determine functions of CD4+ T Cells. J. Immunol. 195, 3557-3564 (2015). <lb/>23. Jonsson, P. et al. Remarkably low affinity of CD4/peptide-major histocompatibility <lb/>complex class II protein interactions. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 113, 5682-5687 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>24. Xiong, Y., Kern, P., Chang, H. &amp; Reinherz, E. T. Cell receptor binding to a pMHCII <lb/>ligand is kinetically distinct from and independent of CD4. J. Biol. Chem. 276, <lb/>5659-5667 (2001). <lb/>25. Hui, E. et al. T cell costimulatory receptor CD28 is a primary target for PD-1-<lb/>mediated inhibition. Science 355, 1428-1433 (2017). <lb/>26. Davis, S. J. &amp; van der Merwe, P. A. The kinetic-segregation model: TCR triggering <lb/>and beyond. Nat. Immunol. 7, 803-809 (2006). <lb/>27. Hanke, J. H. et al. Discovery of a novel, potent, and Src family-selective tyrosine <lb/>kinase inhibitor. Study of Lck-and FynT-dependent T cell activation. J. Biol. Chem. <lb/>271, 695-701 (1996). <lb/>28. Yokosuka, T. et al. Newly generated T cell receptor microclusters initiate and <lb/>sustain T cell activation by recruitment of Zap70 and SLP-76. Nat. Immunol. 6, <lb/>1253-1262 (2005). <lb/>29. Berg J. M., Tymoczko J. L., &amp; Stryer L. Biochemistry 5th edn. (W H Freeman, New <lb/>York, 2002). <lb/>30. Liu, B., Chen, W., Evavold, B. D. &amp; Zhu, C. Accumulation of dynamic catch bonds <lb/>between TCR and agonist peptide-MHC triggers T cell signaling. Cell 157, <lb/>357-368 (2014). <lb/>31. Sibener, L. V. et al. Isolation of a structural mechanism for uncoupling T cell <lb/>receptor signaling from peptide-MHC binding. Cell 174, 672-87 e27 (2018). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>216 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>32. Shi, X. et al. Ca2+ regulates T-cell receptor activation by modulating the charge <lb/>property of lipids. Nature 493, 111-115 (2013). <lb/>33. Roy, R., Hohng, S. &amp; Ha, T. A practical guide to single-molecule FRET. Nat. Methods <lb/>5, 507-516 (2008). <lb/>34. Lillemeier, B. F. et al. TCR and Lat are expressed on separate protein islands on T cell <lb/>membranes and concatenate during activation. Nat. Immunol. 11, 90-96 (2010). <lb/>35. Basu, R. et al. Cytotoxic T cells use mechanical force to potentiate target cell <lb/>killing. Cell 165, 100-110 (2016). <lb/>36. Altan-Bonnet, G. &amp; Germain, R. N. Modeling T cell antigen discrimination <lb/>based on feedback control of digital ERK responses. PLoS Biol. 3, e356 <lb/>(2005). <lb/>37. Gil, D., Schamel, W. W., Montoya, M., Sanchez-Madrid, F. &amp; Alarcon, B. <lb/>Recruitment of Nck by CD3 epsilon reveals a ligand-induced conformational <lb/>change essential for T cell receptor signaling and synapse formation. Cell 109, <lb/>901-912 (2002). <lb/>38. Guo, X. et al. Lipid-dependent conformational dynamics underlie the functional <lb/>versatility of T-cell receptor. Cell Res. 27, 505-525 (2017). <lb/>39. Lee, M. S. et al. A mechanical switch couples T cell receptor triggering to the <lb/>cytoplasmic juxtamembrane regions of CD3zetazeta. Immunity 43, 227-239 <lb/>(2015). <lb/>40. Li, L. et al. Ionic CD3-Lck interaction regulates the initiation of T-cell receptor <lb/>signaling. Proc. Natl. Acad. Sci. USA 114, E5891-E5899 (2017). <lb/>41. Birnbaum, M. E. et al. Deconstructing the peptide-MHC specificity of T cell <lb/>recognition. Cell 157, 1073-1087 (2014). <lb/>42. Howarth, M. &amp; Ting, A. Y. Imaging proteins in live mammalian cells with biotin <lb/>ligase and monovalent streptavidin. Nat. Protoc. 3, 534-545 (2008). <lb/>43. Ozaki, C. Y. et al. Single chain variable fragments produced in Escherichia coli <lb/>against heat-labile and heat-stable toxins from enterotoxigenic E. coli. PLoS ONE <lb/>10, e0131484 (2015). <lb/>44. Tsumoto, K. et al. Highly efficient recovery of functional single-chain Fv fragments <lb/>from inclusion bodies overexpressed in Escherichia coli by controlled introduc-<lb/>tion of oxidizing reagent-application to a human single-chain Fv fragment. J. <lb/>Immunol. Methods 219, 119-129 (1998). <lb/>45. Leisegang, M. et al. Eradication of large solid tumors by gene therapy with a T-cell <lb/>receptor targeting a single cancer-specific point mutation. Clin. Cancer Res. 22, <lb/>2734-2743 (2016). <lb/>46. Su, X. et al. Phase separation of signaling molecules promotes T cell receptor <lb/>signal transduction. Science 352, 595-599 (2016). <lb/>47. Matysik, A. &amp; Kraut, R. S. TrackArt: the user friendly interface for single molecule <lb/>tracking data analysis and simulation applied to complex diffusion in mica <lb/>supported lipid bilayers. BMC Res. Notes 7, 274 (2014). <lb/>48. Edelstein, A. D. et al. Advanced methods of microscope control using muManager <lb/>software. J. Biol. Methods 1, e10 (2014). <lb/>49. Jiang, N. et al. Two-stage cooperative T cell receptor-peptide major histo-<lb/>compatibility complex-CD8 trimolecular interactions amplify antigen dis-<lb/>crimination. Immunity 34, 13-23 (2011). <lb/>50. Sasmal, D. K., Yadav, R. &amp; Lu, H. P. Single-molecule patch-clamp FRET anisotropy <lb/>microscopy studies of NMDA receptor ion channel activation and deactivation <lb/>under agonist ligand binding in living cells. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 138, 8789-8801 (2016). <lb/>51. Lakowicz J. R. Principles of Fluorescence Spectroscopy 3rd edn. (Springer, 2006). <lb/>52. Huang, J., Edwards, L. J., Evavold, B. D. &amp; Zhu, C. Kinetics of MHC-CD8 interaction <lb/>at the T cell membrane. J. Immunol. 179, 7653-7662 (2007). <lb/>53. Zhu, D. M., Dustin, M. L., Cairo, C. W. &amp; Golan, D. E. Analysis of two-dimensional <lb/>dissociation constant of laterally mobile cell adhesion molecules. Biophys. J. 92, <lb/>1022-1034 (2007). <lb/>54. Chandler D. Introduction to Modern Statistical Mechanics 1st edn. (Oxford Uni-<lb/>versity Press, 1987). <lb/>55. Tinevez, J. Y. et al. TrackMate: an open and extensible platform for single-particle <lb/>tracking. Methods 115, 80-90 (2017). <lb/>56. Dominguez, D. et al. Exogenous IL-33 restores dendritic cell activation and <lb/>maturation in established cancer. J. Immunol. 198, 1365-1375 (2017). <lb/>57. Krutzik, P. O., Trejo, A., Schulz, K. R. &amp; Nolan, G. P. Phospho flow cytometry <lb/>methods for the analysis of kinase signaling in cell lines and primary human <lb/>blood samples. Methods Mol. Biol. 699, 179-202 (2011). <lb/>58. Huse, M. et al. Spatial and temporal dynamics of Tcell receptor signaling with a <lb/>photoactivatable agonist. Immunity 27, 76-88 (2007). <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party <lb/>material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless <lb/>indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the <lb/>article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory <lb/>regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly <lb/>from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons. <lb/>org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2019 <lb/></front>
			
			<note place="headnote">TCR-pMHC bond conformation controls TCR ligand discrimination <lb/>DK Sasmal et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>217 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Cellular &amp; Molecular Immunology (2020) 17:203 -217 </note>


	</text>
</tei>
