<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>A methoxy-substituted nitrodibenzofuran-based protecting <lb/>group with an improved two-photon action cross-section for <lb/>thiol protection in solid phase peptide synthesis <lb/>Taysir K. Bader † , Feng Xu † , Michael H. Hodny, David A. Blank, Mark D. Distefano * <lb/>Department of Chemistry, University of Minnesota, Minneapolis, MN 55455, USA <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Photoremovable caging groups are useful for biological applications since the deprotection process <lb/>can be initiated by illumination with light without the necessity of adding additional reagents such <lb/>as acids or bases that can perturb biological activity. In solid phase peptide synthesis (SPPS), the <lb/>most common photoremovable group used for thiol protection is the o-nitrobenzyl group and <lb/>related analogues. In earlier work, we explored the use of the nitrodibenzofuran (NDBF) group for <lb/>thiol protection and found it to exhibit a faster rate towards UV photolysis relative to simple <lb/>nitroveratryl-based protecting groups and a useful two-photon cross-section. Here we describe the <lb/>synthesis of a new NDBF-based protecting group bearing a methoxy substituent and use it to <lb/>prepare a protected form of cysteine suitable for SPPS. This reagent was then used to assemble <lb/>two biologically relevant peptides and characterize their photolysis kinetics in both UV-and two-<lb/>photon-mediated reactions; a two-photon action cross-section of 0.71 -1.4 GM for the new <lb/>protecting group was particularly notable. Finally, uncaging of these protected peptides by either <lb/>UV or two-photon activation was used to initiate their subsequent enzymatic processing by the <lb/>enzyme farnesyltransferase. These experiments highlight the utility of this new protecting group <lb/>for SPPS and biological experiments. <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Thiol groups play key roles in a diverse range of biological processes ranging from acting as <lb/>active site nucleophiles in enzymatic reactions to participating in disulfide bonds to stabilize <lb/>protein structure as well as serving as sites for post-translational modifications. 1-3 The <lb/>ability to mask a thiol group with a protecting group allows the resulting &quot;caged&quot; <lb/>biomolecule to be maintained in an inactive state prior to &quot;uncaging&quot; it by deprotection. <lb/>Photoremovable caging groups 4 are useful for biological applications since the uncaging <lb/>process can be initiated by illumination with light without the necessity of adding additional <lb/>reagents such as acids or bases that can perturb biological activity. 5,6 Light activated <lb/></body>

			<front>* <lb/>Corresponding Author: diste001@umn.edu. <lb/> † Both authors contributed equally to this work <lb/>Supporting Information <lb/>Additional Figures; Tables of ions observed via LC-MS/MS for protected peptides; 1 H NMR, 13 C NMR and 19 F NMR, for all new <lb/>compounds; ESI-MS and analytical HPLC chromatograms for reported peptides. This material is available free of charge via the <lb/>Internet at http://pubs.acs.org. <lb/>The authors declare no competing financial interest. <lb/>HHS Public Access <lb/>Author manuscript <lb/>J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/>Published in final edited form as: <lb/>J Org Chem. 2020 February 07; 85(3): 1614-1625. doi:10.1021/acs.joc.9b02751. <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></front>

			<body>processes are particularly well suited for applications in live cells where it is generally not <lb/>possible to use reagent-based deprotection conditions due to cellular toxicity. 7 <lb/>Photoremovable protecting groups are also advantageous due to the unique features <lb/>associated with light activation since uncaging can be triggered with high spatiotemporal <lb/>control; the specific location and time of deprotection can be controlled by the position and <lb/>timing of illumination. The spatial precision of uncaging can be improved using two-photon <lb/>(TP) activation provided the protecting group chromophore manifests a usable TP action <lb/>cross section; the development of caged neurotransmitters has benefited substantially from <lb/>this feature. 8 TP activation also reduces potential phototoxicity since irradiation is <lb/>performed at double the wavelength employed for UV excitation, which is in the visible or <lb/>near IR region of the electromagnetic spectrum. <lb/>In solid phase peptide synthesis (SPPS), a vast number of protecting groups have been <lb/>developed for cysteine. 9 However, for light-mediated deprotection, the most common <lb/>protecting group used for thiol protection is the o-nitrobenzyl group (NB) 10 and related <lb/>analogues including o-nitroveratryl (NV) (Figure 1). 7,11-14 While robust and useful for <lb/>many applications, such protecting groups do not exhibit useful TP action cross-sections, <lb/>thus limiting their utility. To circumvent this limitation, several groups have investigated the <lb/>use of other protecting groups based on coumarin, quinoline and dibenzofuran scaffolds. <lb/>15-18 Thiol protecting groups based on a coumarin core have been studied and employed for <lb/>a range of applications. 18-21 Protecting groups employing a thioether bond such as Bhc are <lb/>more stable than those featuring a thiocarbonate linkage (BCMACMOC). However, <lb/>irradiation of the former is often accompanied by isomerization without photocleavage 18,20 <lb/>while the latter can undergo rearrangement when unprotected thiols or primary amine groups <lb/>are present within the same peptide. 20 In earlier work, we explored the use of the <lb/>nitrodibenzofuran (NDBF) group for thiol protection and found it to exhibit a faster rate <lb/>towards UV photolysis relative to simple NV-based protecting groups. 18 Moreover, it <lb/>manifested a useful TP cross-section that could be particularly applicable to biological <lb/>experiments performed in live cells. Previous work with the NV group suggests that its <lb/>photochemical properties can be modulated via substitution of the aryl ring. 22 Here we <lb/>describe the synthesis of a new NDBF-based protecting group bearing a methoxy substituent <lb/>and use it to prepare Fmoc-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH (1), a building block suitable for SPPS. In <lb/>the design of this moiety, we elected to preserve the ethyl group used in 2 as the point of <lb/>thiol linkage (resulting in an additional stereogenic center) since photolysis of such <lb/>compounds leads to the production of ketone products that have less putative cellular <lb/>toxicity compared with the aldehyde products that are formed from simpler groups such as <lb/>NV. 23 This reagent was then used to assemble two biologically relevant peptides and <lb/>characterize their photolysis kinetics in both UV-and TP-mediated reactions. Finally, <lb/>uncaging of these protected peptides by either UV or TP activation was used to initiate their <lb/>subsequent enzymatic processing by the enzyme farnesyltransferase. These experiments <lb/>highlight the utility of this new protecting group for SPPS and biological experiments. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Synthetic Chemistry. <lb/>In our earlier work, N-Fmoc-L-Cys(NDBF)-OH (2) was prepared starting from <lb/>dibenzofuran. For the preparation of N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-NDBF-OH) (1), a new, and more <lb/>general route (Scheme 1), was developed to facilitate the synthesis of substituted <lb/>dibenzofurans. The precursor, 2-bromo-5-methoxyphenol, containing the desired methoxy <lb/>group was treated with 4-fluoro-2-nitrobenzaldehyde to yield diarylether 3. Protection of the <lb/>aldehyde as an acetal followed by palladium-catalyzed aryl coupling and deprotection <lb/>afforded aldehyde 6 that was then converted to the racemic secondary alcohol, 7, using <lb/>trimethylaluminum. That alcohol was then activated to the corresponding bromide that was <lb/>then used to alkylate N-Fmoc-L-cysteine methyl ester under acidic conditions 24 to produce <lb/>the fully protected amino acid 9. Hydrolysis of that ester using trimethyltin hydroxide 25 gave <lb/>N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH (1), a protected form of cysteine suitable for solid phase <lb/>peptide synthesis; mild conditions are essential for the hydrolysis of 9 to avoid potential <lb/>racemization of the protected cysteine residue. <lb/>With the desired building block in hand, a series of peptides (10-18, Figure 2) based on two <lb/>different sequences incorporating the caged cysteine residue were prepared. First, a 15-<lb/>residue peptide based on the sequence of a-factor, a yeast pheromone, was prepared starting <lb/>with Fmoc-Ala on Wang resin. Fmoc-deprotection and two cycles of standard SPPS using an <lb/>automated synthesizer yielded a VIA tripeptide on resin. Next, N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-<lb/>NDBF)-OH (1) was coupled offline with ninhydrin monitoring to insure complete reaction; <lb/>to increase the coupling efficiency, the coupling time was extended to 4 hours for this <lb/>modified cysteine residue. At that point, automated peptide synthesis was resumed to <lb/>complete the synthesis. After final Fmoc-deprotection, the peptide was cleaved from the <lb/>resin under acidic conditions, precipitated with ether, and the resulting crude material <lb/>purified via reversed-phase HPLC to yield the desired peptide. The final peptide, 10, was <lb/>analyzed via LC-MS/MS to confirm the sequence (Table S1). a-Factor-based peptides 11 <lb/>and 12 containing NDBF-and NV-protected cysteine were also prepared and characterized <lb/>in a similar manner (see Tables S2 and S3). A second peptide sequence based on the C-<lb/>terminus of the human K-Ras protein was also synthesized. Forms of that peptide containing <lb/>either Cys(MeO-NDBF) (15) or Cys(NDBF) (16) were prepared. Following purification of <lb/>the complete peptides, their sequences were again confirmed via LC-MS/MS analysis <lb/>(Tables S4 and S5). <lb/>In the initial preparation and purification of 10, the HPLC chromatogram of the crude <lb/>peptide revealed the presence of two double peaks: a main double peak corresponding to <lb/>~70-80% of the total integrated area, and a minor double peak corresponding to ~20-30% of <lb/>the total integrated area. The double peak pattern was clearer for the NDBF-protected <lb/>peptides 11 and 16 (Figures S1 and S2). For each peptide, all four peaks exhibited identical <lb/>m/z values and MS/MS fragmentation patterns. We attribute the two species present in each <lb/>of the double peaks as resulting from a mixture of two epimers due to the stereogenic center <lb/>adjacent to the dibenzofuran since bromide 8 was used as a racemic mixture. We attribute <lb/>the major double peak to be from the desired L-cysteine-containing peptides and the minor <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>double peak to be from D-cysteine-containing peptides that arise due to racemization of the <lb/>protected cysteine either during the hydrolysis of ester 9 or in the subsequent activation of 1 <lb/>during SPPS. This structural assignment is supported by the fact that peak doubling was not <lb/>observed with peptide 12 (Figure S3) which does not have the additional stereogenic center <lb/>present in 10 and 11 (since the NV group lacks the methyl group present in the NDBF and <lb/>MeO-NDBF protecting groups); however, 12 did have one major and one minor peak of <lb/>identical mass, presumably due to racemization of the cysteine as noted above. This <lb/>hypothesis was further corroborated when photolysis of the combined double peaks (from <lb/>11) led to the generation of two product peaks (13) exhibiting the same m/z ratio, whereas <lb/>photolysis of the purified major double peak lead to the generation of a single product peak <lb/>(Figure S4). While it was possible to remove the minor components via HPLC separation <lb/>and use the resulting material for subsequent experiments, this may not always be possible <lb/>depending on the specific peptide sequence under study. Hence, the epimerization process <lb/>was studied in more detail to obtain a more optimized synthetic procedure. <lb/>To better understand the origin of the epimerization observed here, we first elected to study <lb/>the hydrolysis of a Mosher&apos;s amide of NDBF-protected cysteine methyl ester (23a) to the <lb/>corresponding acid (24a). Accordingly, that compound was prepared from 21a by removal <lb/>of the Fmoc group followed by acylation with (S)-Mosher&apos;s acid chloride [(S)-(+)-α-<lb/>methoxy-α-(trifluoromethyl)phenylacetyl chloride] to yield the desired cysteine methyl <lb/>ester derivative (23a). Inspection of the 19 F NMR revealed the presence of two signals at <lb/>-69.03 and -68.92 ppm, consistent with the presence of two diastereomers (with equal <lb/>integration) due to the epimeric mixture, resulting from the stereogenic center present in the <lb/>NDBF group. Hydrolysis of the ester to the corresponding acid (24a) under conditions <lb/>necessary to obtain complete conversion (Me 3 SnOH, DCE, 75°, 12 h) and subsequent 19 F <lb/>NMR analysis showed only two signals (at -69.02 and -68.92 ppm, Figure 3A) suggesting <lb/>that no epimerization had occurred in the hydrolysis reaction; even when ester 23a was <lb/>subjected to more forcing conditions (Me 3 SnOH, DCE, 85°, overnight), no additional peaks <lb/>in the 19 F NMR were observed. To confirm the absence of epimerization, the authentic <lb/>product (the diastereomeric ester containing D-cysteine) was independently prepared by <lb/>reacting bromide 19 with N-Fmoc-D-cysteine methyl ester followed by Fmoc removal and <lb/>acylation with (S)-Mosher&apos;s acid chloride to yield 23b. Analysis of that material via 19 F <lb/>NMR showed two signals at -68.86 and -68.82 ppm that are different than those present in <lb/>the material produced from L-cysteine demonstrating that the two cysteine derivatives <lb/>(prepared from the enantiomers of cysteine) can be clearly distinguished via 19 F NMR. <lb/>Hydrolysis of the D-cysteine analogue (23b) yielded the corresponding acid (24b) whose <lb/>19 F NMR manifested two signals at -68.80 and 68.78 ppm (Figure 3B); an 19 F NMR of a <lb/>mixture of 24a and 24b confirms these chemical shift differences are real (Figure 3C). This <lb/>result validates the use of 19 F NMR to monitor this epimerization process and suggests that <lb/>no significant level of epimerization occurs in the hydrolysis of 9 to 1. <lb/>Next, we examined the potential for epimerization during SPPS. Karas et al. previously <lb/>reported that variable amounts of racemization occur in the activation of N-Fmoc-L-<lb/>Cys(NV)-OH depending on the precise coupling conditions used. 14 We initially adjusted our <lb/>synthetic conditions and employed the optimal conditions described by them, consisting of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>activation and coupling of 1 with 4 equivalents of N,N&apos;-diisopropylcarbodiimide (DIC) and <lb/>6-chloro-1-hydroxybenzotriazole (Cl-HOBt) for 1 hour, for the synthesis of 10. However, <lb/>LC-MS/MS analysis of the resulting material after synthesis still showed significant <lb/>epimerization (Figure S5). To confirm that the epimerization was occurring in the activation/ <lb/>coupling step of the protected cysteine residue, a model tripeptide GC(NDBF)F (18) was <lb/>prepared and subjected to prolonged treatment (2 h) with 20% piperidine/DMF to duplicate <lb/>the exposure to base that the embedded cysteine residue would experience (12 deprotection <lb/>steps) necessary to complete the synthesis of a-Factor. Comparison of chromatograms <lb/>obtained of the tripeptide before and after extensive piperidine treatment showed that no <lb/>additional epimerization had occurred (Figure S6), suggesting that cysteine racemization <lb/>must be occurring in the activation step. To minimize potential racemization, several <lb/>different coupling conditions for the caged cysteine residue were investigated by <lb/>synthesizing peptide 18 and subsequent LC-MS/MS analysis. Of the conditions surveyed, <lb/>the use of benzotriazole-1-yl-oxy-tris-pyrrolidino-phosphonium hexafluorophosphate <lb/>(PyBOP), 1-hydroxy-7-azabenzotriazole (HOAt) and DIEA gave the best results with less <lb/>than 2% racemization being observed. To confirm the utility of these revised conditions, <lb/>peptide 15 was resynthesized using 4 equivalents PyBOP/HOAT/DIEA for 30 min at a <lb/>concentration of 150 mM. After global deprotection and resin cleavage with Reagent K, LC-<lb/>MS analysis (Figure 4) showed less than 2% of the epimerized product was present. Overall, <lb/>these results indicate that NDBF-based protection of cysteine can be used to efficiently <lb/>prepare caged peptides. However, careful reaction monitoring is important to minimize <lb/>potential racemization during SPPS. <lb/>Photochemistry. <lb/>Previous work with o-nitrobenzyl-based protecting groups showed that the addition of <lb/>methoxy substituents to the nitrobenzyl chromophore shifted the absorbance maximum to <lb/>lower energy; that was accompanied by a decrease in the quantum yield for photolysis. <lb/>Comparison of the UV spectra of the parent compound, N-Fmoc-L-Cys(NDBF)-OH (2), and <lb/>N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH (1), shown in Figure 5, indicates an increase in the <lb/>absorbance maximum from 320 to 355 nm, consistent with the aforementioned simple o-<lb/>nitrobenzyl-based system; in fact the absorbance maximum for 1 is quite similar to that of <lb/>the simpler nitroveratryl group present in N-Fmoc-L-Cys(NV)-OH. Inspection of the UV <lb/>spectra also shows that the extinction coefficients of the compounds at their λ max vary less <lb/>than 2-fold with the MeO-NDBF-protected residue exhibiting the highest value. At 350 nm, <lb/>the wavelength used for the UV irradiation experiments described below, the extinction <lb/>coefficient for the MeO-NDBF-protected residue is 1.9-fold higher than that for the NDBF-<lb/>protected parent compound (Table 1). <lb/>Photolysis of peptides 10 and 11 using a Rayonet reactor centered at 350 nm and subsequent <lb/>LC-MS analysis showed that the two protecting groups uncage at comparable rates (Figure <lb/>S7). Since the bulbs used in these experiments manifest a fairly broad spectral bandwidth (~ <lb/>50 nm at half height), it is not possible to determine the quantum yields of these two <lb/>protecting groups from these experiments. However, it is clear from an operational <lb/>perspective (using a Rayonet reactor common to many laboratories performing photolysis <lb/>experiments) that these two protecting groups have similar UV photolysis properties. Those <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>results are in stark contrast to those obtained with peptide 12 that incorporates an NV-<lb/>protected cysteine where the rate of photolysis is 25-fold slower compared with peptide 10 <lb/>(containing a MeO-NDBF-protected cysteine residue); using 14 bulbs in a Rayonet reactor, <lb/>peptides 10 and 11 are essentially completed deprotected in less than 30 seconds; for <lb/>comparison, at that point, ~90% of the NV-protected peptide remains unreacted (Figure S7). <lb/>Those results are similar to what we previously reported 18 in comparing the monomeric <lb/>precursors Fmoc-Cys(NDBF)-OMe and Fmoc-Cys(NV)-OMe and highlight a key feature of <lb/>NDBF-based thiol protection, namely that it is much more sensitive to UV photolysis <lb/>compared with the simpler NV group. <lb/>To quantify the photophysical properties of peptides 10 and 11 in more detail, photolysis <lb/>reactions were performed at low concentration to minimize any inner filter effect using an <lb/>apparatus (Figure S8) equipped with 350 nm LEDs with a narrower spectral bandwidth (~ <lb/>10 nm at half height, Figure S9). After determining the intensity of the light source via <lb/>ferrioxylate actinometry, the apparatus was used to determine the rate of photolysis for <lb/>peptides 10, 11 and 12 (Figure 6A, Figure S10 and Table S6) and calculate their respective <lb/>quantum yields. Values of 0.53, 0.70 and 0.023 were obtained for 10, 11 and 12, respectively <lb/>(Table 1). It should be noted that the value obtained for peptide 11 that incorporates an <lb/>NDBF-protected thiol is comparable to the value reported for NDBF-EGTA (0.7), a caged <lb/>alcohol. These results quantitatively illustrate the greater efficiency of NDBF-based <lb/>protecting groups as photoremovable moieties compared with NV-based compounds and <lb/>serve to highlight their utility for uncaging applications. <lb/>One of the most important features of the NDBF protecting group is that it manifests a <lb/>significant TP action cross-section for uncaging, making it useful for biological experiments. <lb/>Accordingly, we wanted to study the rates of photolysis of peptides 10 and 11 upon TP <lb/>activation. Thus, solutions of the peptides were irradiated at 800 nm using a Ti:Saphire laser <lb/>followed by LC-MS analysis. Interestingly, peptide 10 containing the MeO-NDBF-protected <lb/>cysteine residue uncaged at a rate 3.6-fold greater than peptide 11 containing the parent <lb/>NDBF-protected cysteine (Figure 6B). Furthermore, irradiation of the K-Ras-derived, MeO-<lb/>NDBF-containing peptide 15 manifested an additional 2-fold rate increase compared to the <lb/>MeO-NDBF-containing a-Factor-derived peptide 10. Using BhcOAc as a standard, we <lb/>estimate the TP action cross-section for MeO-NDBF deprotection to be 0.7 GM for 10 and <lb/>1.4 GM for 15. Presumably, the observed variation in the TP action cross-section of different <lb/>peptides incorporating the same chromophore reflects differences in the local structure/ <lb/>environment around the chromophore; such results have been observed in homologues of <lb/>GFP where the fluorophore is constant throughout. 26 Overall, these results constitute a <lb/>significant improvement in TP photolysis efficiency and suggests that the MeO-NDBF <lb/>protecting group could be particularly useful for TP activation of peptides containing caged <lb/>cysteines in cells or even tissue. <lb/>Enzymatic reactions initiated by thiol uncaging. <lb/>Caged peptide substrates have potentially significant utility in cell-based biological <lb/>experiments since they are unreactive prior to photolysis. Peptides can be incubated with <lb/>cells and allowed to accumulate before activation with light. As a prelude to such cell-based <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>experiments, we sought to investigate whether photolysis of peptides containing MeO-<lb/>NDBF protected cysteine residues could be used to liberate peptides that could serve as <lb/>substrates for enzymatic reactions. Protein farnesylation involves the transfer of the <lb/>isoprenyl group from farnesyl diphosphate (FPP) to proteins bearing C-terminal CaaX-box <lb/>sequences. 27 Protein farnesyltransferase (PFTase) which catalyzes this reaction has been <lb/>intensely studied as a possible therapeutic target for a number of diseases including cancer. <lb/>28,29 Initially, peptide 10 was incubated in the presence of PFTase and the substrate FPP and <lb/>irradiated for 30 sec in a Rayonet photoreactor using three 350 nm bulbs. Analysis of the <lb/>resulting photolysis reaction via LC-MS before and after photolysis indicated that essentially <lb/>all of the starting peptide 10 (Figure S11A, before photolysis) had been converted to the <lb/>corresponding farnesylated product 14 (Figure S11C, after photolysis); in the absence of <lb/>PFTase, the deprotected thiol, 13, was the major species (Figure S11B, no PFTase). <lb/>Next, we explored the TP-mediated process. Accordingly, peptide 10 was incubated in the <lb/>presence of PFTase and FPP and irradiated at 800 nm for 10 minutes using the laser system <lb/>described above. Analysis of the resulting photolysis reaction via LC-MS before and after <lb/>photolysis indicated substantial conversion of the starting peptide 10 (Figure 7A, before <lb/>photolysis) to the corresponding farnesylated product 14 (Figure 7C, after photolysis) with a <lb/>small amount of the free thiol (13) remaining. In contrast, in the absence of PFTase, the <lb/>major species present after irradiation was the free thiol (13) (Figure 7B, after photolysis <lb/>without PFTase). To explore the dose dependence of this photochemical reaction, samples <lb/>containing 10, PFTase and FPP were irradiated at 800 nm for different times and the <lb/>amounts of starting peptide (10) and farnesylated product (14) were quantified from LC-MS <lb/>analysis. A plot of that data (Figure 8) showed a clear relationship between light exposure <lb/>and product formation. Importantly, under these conditions, significant quantities of the <lb/>farnesylated product (~20%) were easily detected within the first five minutes of irradiation, <lb/>highlighting the efficiency of this process. <lb/>CONCLUSIONS <lb/>In this work, the efficiency of TP-mediated thiol deprotection in cysteine-containing <lb/>peptides was improved using a new methoxy-substituted analogue of NDBF. An efficient <lb/>synthesis was developed to prepare Fmoc-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH (1), a protected form of <lb/>cysteine suitable for SPPS; installation of the methoxy substituent increased the absorption <lb/>maximum from 320 nm (NDBF) to 355 nm (MeO-NDBF). The cysteine analogue was <lb/>incorporated into two known bioactive peptides including a-Factor precursor (10, a <lb/>pentadecapeptide) and a fragment from the C-terminus of K-Ras (15, an undecapeptide). UV <lb/>irradiation of these MeO-NDBF-protected peptides resulted in deprotection at rates <lb/>comparable to those of peptides masked with the parent NDBF group but 25-fold faster <lb/>compared to an NV-protected peptide due to the larger quantum yield measured for the <lb/>NDBF-based caging groups. However, TP activation at 800 nm showed significant <lb/>differences between the two caging groups with the TP action cross-sections for 10 and 15 <lb/>determined to be 0.71 and 1.4 GM, respectively using BhcOAc as a standard. These are 3.5-<lb/>and 7-fold higher for 10 and 15, respectively, compared to the previously reported value for <lb/>the parent NDBF group of 0.2 GM, also reproduced here using peptide 11. Finally, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>deprotection of peptide 10 using either UV or 800 nm light rapidly liberated the free thiol <lb/>form (13) which was efficiently enzymatically transformed to its farnesylated congener (14) <lb/>via the action of PFTase. These experiments set the stage for future cell-based experiments <lb/>using this more efficiently removable protecting group. Finally, the results described here, <lb/>demonstrating an increase in TP action cross-section upon introduction of a methoxy <lb/>substituent, suggest additional exploration of the NDBF scaffold is warranted. <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL <lb/>General Details. <lb/>HPLC and LC-MS Grade H 2 O and CH 3 CN as well as HOATwere purchased from Fisher <lb/>Scientific (Pittsburgh PA). Fmoc-Cys-OH was purchased from Chem-Impex International <lb/>(Wood Dale, IL). All other protected amino acids and resins were purchased from P3 <lb/>BioSystems (Louisville, KY). HCTU was purchased from Oakwood Chemical (Estill, SC). <lb/>PyAOP was purchased from EMD Millipore (Burlington, MA). Other solvents and reagents <lb/>used were purchased from Sigma-Aldrich (St. Louis, MO) and were used without further <lb/>purification. 1 H NMR data of synthetic compounds were recorded at 500 MHz on a Bruker <lb/>Avance III HD Instrument at 25 °C. Liquid chromatography -mass spectrometry (LC-MS) <lb/>analysis was performed using an Agilent 1200 series LCMSD SL single quadrupole system <lb/>equipped with a C3 column (Agilent ZORBAX 300SB-C3, 5 μM, 4.6 × 250 mm) and a <lb/>variable wavelength detector. An H 2 O/CH 3 CN solvent system containing 0.1% HCO 2 H was <lb/>used, consisting of solvent A (H 2 O with 0.1% HCO 2 H) and solvent B (CH 3 CN with 0.1% <lb/>HCO 2 H). High resolution mass spectrometry and MS/MS fragmentation of peptides was <lb/>performed using a Thermo Scientific Elite Orbitrap instrument. High resolution mass spectra <lb/>of organic compounds were acquired using either a Bruker BioTOF II ESI/TOF-MS, or an <lb/>Applied Biosystems-Sciex 5800 MALDI-TOF instrument. High performance liquid <lb/>chromatography (HPLC) purification was performed using an Agilent 1100 series <lb/>instrument equipped with a diode-array detector and C18 columns (Agilent ZORBAX <lb/>300SB-C18 5 μM 9.4 × 250 mm, or Agilent Pursuit C18 5 μM 250 × 21.2mm, respectively), <lb/>and using an H 2 O/CH 3 CN system containing trifluoroacetic acid (TFA) consisting of solvent <lb/>A (H 2 O with 0.1% TFA) and solvent B (CH 3 CN with 0.1% TFA). <lb/>4-(2-bromo-5-methoxyphenoxy)-2-nitrobenzaldehyde (3). <lb/>4-fluoro-2-nitrobenzaldehyde (2.29 g, 13.6 mmol) was dissolved in DMF (100 mL). 2-<lb/>bromo-5-methoxyphenol (2.62 g, 12.9 mmol) and K 2 CO 3 (5.4 g, 39 mmol) were then <lb/>sequentially added and the reaction was purged with Ar (g) and stirred at rt for 6 h and then <lb/>50 °C for 12 h in an oil bath. The reaction progress was followed by TLC. After the reaction <lb/>was deemed complete, the mixture was cooled to rt and poured into aqueous NH 4 Cl (200 <lb/>mL) and extracted with EtOAc (3 × 100 mL). The organic phase was washed with H 2 O (500 <lb/>mL), brine (500 mL), dried with anhydrous MgSO 4 and evaporated to dryness. The crude <lb/>product was purified by column chromatography (Hexanes/EtOAc, 4:1, v/v) to yield 4.4 g <lb/>(98%) of product 3 as a pale yellow solid. mp 62-64 °C. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ <lb/>10.32 (s, 1H), 7.99 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.57 (d, J = 8.9 Hz, 1H), 7.50 (d, J = 2.3 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.22 (dd, J = 2.1, 8.6 Hz, 1H), 6.80 (dd, J = 2.8, 8.9 Hz, 1H), 6.72 (d, J = 2.8, 1H), 3.81 (s, <lb/>3H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR (CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 186.8, 161.4, 160.6, 151.4, 151.1, 134.5, 131.7, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>125.0, 120.8, 113.7, 111.9, 108.9, 106.1, 55.8. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 14 H 10 BrNNaO 5 [M <lb/>+Na] + : 373.9635; found: 373.9610. <lb/>2-(4-(2-bromo-5-methoxyphenoxy)-2-nitrophenyl)-1,3-dioxolane (4). <lb/>Compound 3 (5 g, 14.2 mmol) was dissolved in benzene (300 mL). Ethylene glycol (5 mL) <lb/>and p-toluene sulfonic acid monohydrate (500 mg, 2.91 mmol) were added. The reaction <lb/>was purged with Ar (g) and stirred at 110 °C in an oil bath using a Dean-Stark trap. Reaction <lb/>progress was monitored by TLC. After completion of this reaction, the mixture was cooled <lb/>to rt and poured into aqueous NaHCO 3 (200 mL), and extracted with EtOAc (3 × 150 mL). <lb/>The organic phase was washed with H 2 O (100 mL), brine (100 mL), dried with anhydrous <lb/>MgSO 4 , evaporated to dryness, and purified by column chromatography (Hexanes/EtOAc, <lb/>3:1, v/v) to yield 5.1 g (95%) of product 4 as a sticky oil. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ <lb/>7.74 (d, J = 8.7 Hz, 1H), 7.53 (d, J = 8.9 Hz, 1H), 7.41 (d, J = 2.5 Hz, 1H), 7.15 (dd, J = 2.5, <lb/>8.7 Hz, 1H), 6.72 (dd, J = 2.9, 8.9 Hz, 1H), 6.63 (dd, J = 2.9, 1H), 6.40 (s, 1H), 4.04 (s, 4H), <lb/>3.78 (s, 3H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR (CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 160.5, 158.0, 152.3, 149.7, 134.4, 129.5, <lb/>127.4, 121.0, 113.0, 112.9, 108.4, 106.2, 99.5, 65.5, 55.9. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for <lb/>C 16 H 14 BrNNaO 6 [M+Na] + , 417.9897; found: 417.9886. <lb/>2-(1,3-dioxolan-2-yl)-7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan (5). <lb/>Compound 4 (3 g, 8.1 mmol) was dissolved in dimethylacetamide (60 mL). NaOAc (1.0 g, <lb/>12.2 mmol) and Pd/C (0.228 mmol, 239 mg) were added into this mixture. The reaction was <lb/>stirred at 115 °C in an oil bath and the progress followed by NMR at selected intervals. The <lb/>reaction was deemed complete after 2 days. After filtration through a pad of Celite®, the <lb/>filtrate was diluted with EtOAc (80 mL), and poured into NH 4 Cl aqueous solution (200 mL), <lb/>and extracted with EtOAc (3 × 150 mL). The organic phase was washed with H 2 O (100 <lb/>mL), brine (100 mL), and was then dried over anhydrous MgSO 4 , evaporated to dryness, and <lb/>purified by column chromatography (Hexanes/EtOAc, 3:1, v/v) to yield 2.2 g (85%) of <lb/>product 5, isolated as a yellow solid. mp 220-222 °C. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.26 <lb/>(s, 1H), 8.15 (s, 1H), 7.88 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.12 (d, J = 1.9 Hz, 1H), 7.02 (dd, J = 2.0, 8.6 <lb/>Hz, 1H), 6.63 (s, 1H), 4.12 (s, 4H), 3.93 (s, 3H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR (CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 161.8, <lb/>160.2, 155.0, 146.2, 128.91, 128.89, 122.3, 118.6, 115.8, 112.9, 108.9, 100.09, 96.7, 65.5, <lb/>56.0. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 16 H 13 NNaO 6 [M+Na] + , 338.0635; found: 338.0619. <lb/>7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-carbaldehyde (6). <lb/>Compound 5 (3 g, 9.5 mmol) was dissolved in a THF/H 2 O solvent mixture (100 mL, 3:1, <lb/>v/v), and then p-toluene sulfonic acid monohydrate (300 mg, 1.74 mmol) as added. The <lb/>reaction was stirred at 60 °C in an oil bath and reaction progress was monitored by TLC. <lb/>After 24 h THF in the resulting solutions was removed by vacumn and the desired product <lb/>was precipitated, product 6 was isolated through filtration to yield 2.1 g (83%), as a red <lb/>solid. mp 205-208 °C. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 10.51 (s, 1H), 8.42 (s, 1H), 8.29 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.93 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.16 (d, J = 1.9 Hz, 1H), 7.08 (dd, J = 2.0, 8.7 Hz, 1H), 3.95 <lb/>(s, 3H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR (CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 188.2, 162.5, 160.6, 157.2, 147.5, 129.9, <lb/>127.8, 122.7, 120.9, 115.3, 113.7, 108.7, 96.8, 56.1. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 14 H 9 NNaO 5 <lb/>[M+Na] + , 294.0373; found: 294.0401. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>1-(7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethan-1-ol (7). <lb/>Trimethylaluminum (0.55 mL, 1.1 mmol; 2 M solution in hexanes) was added dropwise over <lb/>10 min to a solution of 6 (150 mg, 0.55 mmol) in dry CH 2 Cl 2 (3 mL) under Ar at 0 °C. The <lb/>reaction was stirred at 0 °C for 1 h, after which it was quenched with ice-cold water (50 <lb/>mL), followed by addition of 1 M NaOH (5 mL). The mixture was stirred for 30 min, after <lb/>which time additional CH 2 Cl 2 (10 mL) was added and the resulting organic layer was <lb/>washed with 1 M NaOH (50 mL), brine (50 mL), dried over MgSO 4 and the volatiles were <lb/>evaporated, affording crude 7. The crude product was passed through a thin pad of SiO 2 <lb/>eluted with EtOAc/Hexanes (150 mL, 1:3, v/v) to yield 123 mg (85%) of pure product 7, as <lb/>a yellow solid. mp 140-142 °C. 1 H NMR (THF-D 8 , 500 MHz) δ 8.42 (s, 1H), 8.29 (s, 1H), <lb/>7.93 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.28 (d, J = 2.2 Hz, 1H), 7.08 (dd, J = 1.5, 8.6 Hz, 1H), 5.50-5.45 <lb/>(m, 1H), 4.71 (d, J = 3.74 Hz, 1H), 3.95 (s, 3H), 1.54 (d, J = 6.25 Hz, 3H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR <lb/>(THF-D 8 , 125 MHz) δ 161.9, 160.0, 153.7, 145.1, 138.8, 129.0, 122.1, 118.2, 115.6, 112.4, <lb/>107.1, 96.5, 64.8, 55.2, 25.2. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 15 H 13 NNaO 5 [M+Na] + , 310.0686; <lb/>found: 310.0671. <lb/>2-(1-bromoethyl)-7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan (8). <lb/>To compound 7 (126 mg, 0.44 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (5 mL) in an ice bath, PPh 3 -polymer <lb/>supported (1.1 mmol, ~ 3 mmol/g, 367 mg), and CBr 4 (273 mg, 0.825 mmol) were <lb/>introduced. The reaction mixture was stirred at rt overnight. After filtration through a pad of <lb/>Celite®, the filtrate was collected, and the solvent evaporated. The crude product was <lb/>purified by column chromatography on SiO 2 (Hex/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) to give 120 mg (78%) of <lb/>the desired product, 8, as a yellow solid. mp 168 °C (decomposed). 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 <lb/>MHz) δ 8.29 (s, 1H), 8.05 (s, 1H), 7.91 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.11 (d, J = 2.2 Hz, 1H), 7.03 <lb/>(dd, J = 2.2, 8.6 Hz, 1H), 6.04 (q, J = 6.8 Hz, 1H), 3.94 (s, 3H), 2.20 (d, J = 6.8 Hz, 3H). <lb/>13 C{ 1 H} NMR (CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ162.0, 160.3, 154.3, 144.9, 133.6, 129.6, 122.4, 120.5, <lb/>115.4, 112.9, 108.3, 96.7, 56.0, 43.1, 28.0. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 15 H 12 BrNO 4 Na [M <lb/>+Na] + , 371.9842; found: 371.9872. <lb/>Methyl N-(((9H-fluoren-9-yl)methoxy)carbonyl)-S-(1-(7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-<lb/>yl)ethyl)-L-cysteinate (9). <lb/>Product 8, Fmoc-L-Cysteine methyl ester (327 mg, 0.93 mmol) and Zn(OAc) 2 (438 mg, 2.0 <lb/>mmol) were dissolved in 30 mL of a mixture of DMF/ACN/0.1% TFA in H 2 O (4:1:1, v/v/v). <lb/>The reaction was monitored by TLC (Hexanes/Et 2 O, 1:1, v/v) and stopped after 24 h of <lb/>stirring at rt by pouring the reaction mixture into H 2 O (100 mL), and extraction with EtOAc <lb/>(3 × 30 mL) three times. The organic phase was washed with 100 mL of brine, and was then <lb/>dried over anhydrous MgSO 4 , evaporated to dryness, and purified by column <lb/>chromatography on SiO 2 (Hexanes/EtOAc, 3:1, v/v) to give 221 mg (38%) of the desired <lb/>product 9, isolated as a yellow sticky oil, as a diastereomeric mixture. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 <lb/>MHz) δ 8.26 (s, 1H), 8.24 (s, 1H), 8.01 (s, 2H), 7.87 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.80 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.77-7.73 (m, 4H), 7.62-7.56 (m, 4H), 7.41-7.38 (m, 4H), 7.32-7.28 (m, 4H), 7.09-<lb/>6.91 (m, 4H), 5.59-5.55 (m, 2H), 4.92-4.85 (m, 2H), 4.59-4.56 (m, 1H), 4.52-4.49 (m, 1H), <lb/>4.39-4.32 (m, 2H), 4.28-4.20 (m, 3H), 4.15-4.11 (m, 1H), 3.92 (s, 3H), 3.88 (s, 3H), 3.77 <lb/>(s, 3H), 3.71 (s, 3H), 2.98-2.85 (m, 4H), 1.71-1.69 (m, 6H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>MHz) δ171.1, 161.9, 161.8, 160.1, 155.8, 153.9, 146.6, 146.5, 144.0, 143.9, 141.41, 141.38, <lb/>141.37, 134.1, 134.0, 129.6, 129.5, 127.9, 127.3, 125.3, 122.4, 122.3, 120.09, 120.07, <lb/>119.98, 119.90, 115.5, 112.79, 112.71, 108.14, 108.09, 100.11, 96.66, 96.63, 67.49, 67.45, <lb/>55.99, 55.96, 53.77, 53.71, 52.96, 52.93, 47.19, 47.11, 40.0, 39.7, 34.22, 34.10, 23.86, <lb/>23.74. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 34 H 30 N 2 O 8 SNa [M+Na] + , 649.1615; found: 649.1629. <lb/>N-(((9H-fluoren-9-yl)methoxy)carbonyl)-S-(1-(7-methoxy-3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-<lb/>yl)ethyl)-L-cysteine (1). <lb/>Ester 9 (300 mg, 0.48 mmol) was dissolved in CH 2 Cl 2 (6 mL) and Me 3 SnOH (226 mg, 1.25 <lb/>mmol) was added. The reaction was refluxed for 12 h in an oil bath and monitored by TLC <lb/>(Hexanes/EtOAc, 1:1, v/v), at which point the solvent was removed in vacuo and the <lb/>resulting oil dissolved in EtOAc (30 mL). The organic layer was washed with 5% HCl (3 × <lb/>10 mL) and brine (3 × 10 mL), dried over MgSO 4 , and evaporated to give 267 mg of the <lb/>desired product (89%) as a yellow foam, present as a diastereomeric mixture. mp 64-66 °C. <lb/>1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.25 (s, 1H), 8.21 (s, 1H), 7.97 (d, J = 7.6 Hz, 2H), 7.85 (d, J <lb/>= 8.5 Hz, 1H), 7.79 (d, J = 8.6 Hz, 1H), 7.75-7.73 (m, 4H), 7.60-7.55 (m, 4H), 7.45-7.38 <lb/>(m, 4H), 7.32-7.26 (m, 4H), 7.06-6.91 (m, 4H), 5.63-5.60 (m, 2H), 4.93-4.89 (m, 2H), <lb/>4.60-4.59 (m, 1H), 4.52-4.50 (m, 1H), 4.36-4.34 (m, 2H), 4.30-4.21 (m, 3H), 4.15-4.11 <lb/>(m, 1H), 3.89 (s, 3H), 3.87 (s, 3H), 3.01-2.89 (m, 4H), 1.71-1.68 (m, 6H). 13 C{ 1 H} <lb/>NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 161.8, 160.1, 156.0, 153.9, 146.5, 146.4, 143.0, 141.41, 141.38, <lb/>141.36, 133.98, 134.0, 129.6, 129.5, 127.8, 127.2, 125.3, 122.4, 122.3, 120.09, 120.07, <lb/>119.93, 119.90, 115.47, 115.44, 112.75, 112.71, 108.19, 96.6, 67.59, 67.57, 55.98, 55.96, <lb/>53.42, 53.41, 47.16, 47.05, 39.77, 39.70,33.76, 33.73, 31.09, 23.77, 23.73. HRMS (ESI): <lb/>Calcd for C 33 H 28 N 2 O 8 NaS [M+Na] + , 635.1459; found: 635.1479. <lb/>Methyl N-(((9H-fluoren-9-yl)methoxy)carbonyl)-S-(1-(3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethyl)-D-<lb/>cysteinate (21b). <lb/>N-Fmoc-D-Cysteine methyl ester 20b (179 mg, 0.5 mmol) and 19 (160 mg, 0.5 mmol) were <lb/>dissolved in 5 mL of a mixture of DMSO/DMF/ACN/H 2 O (3:3:1:1, v/v/v/v), and then, <lb/>DIPEA (0.1 mL) was added into this solution. The reaction was monitored by TLC <lb/>(Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) and stopped after 30 min of stirring at rt by pouring the reaction <lb/>mixture into H 2 O (100 mL), and extraction with EtOAc (3 × 30 mL). The organic phase was <lb/>washed with 100 mL of brine, and was then dried over anhydrous MgSO 4 , evaporated to <lb/>dryness, and purified by column chromatography on SiO 2 (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1 to 3:1, v/v) <lb/>to give 160 mg (53%) of the desired product 21b, isolated as a yellow sticky oil, as a <lb/>diastereomeric mixture. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.42 (s, 1H), 8.39 (s, 1H), 8.07-8.00 <lb/>(m, 4H), 7.65-7.55 (m, 10H), 7.79-7.77 (m, 4H), 7.65-7.56 (m, 8H), 7.47-7.33 (m, 10H), <lb/>5.59 (d, J = 7.7 Hz, 2H), 4.90-4.84 (m, 2H), 4.62-4.58 (m, 1H), 4.56-4.52 (m, 1H), 4.43-<lb/>4.36 (m, 2H), 4.32-4.24 (m, 3H), 4.19-4.12 (m, 2H), 3.80 (s, 3H), 3.74 (s, 3H), 3.01-2.87 <lb/>(m, 4H), 1.76-1.73 (m, 6H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 170.9, 158.3, 155.65, <lb/>155.56, 153.7, 147.74, 147.69, 143.9, 143.8, 141.29, 141.27, 141.23, 136.6, 133.6, 133.5, <lb/>129.47, 129.45, 129.42, 129.25, 129.01, 128.90, 127.78, 127.70, 127.1, 125.2, 123.80, <lb/>123.78, 123.76, 122.6, 122.4, 121.83, 121.81, 121.76, 121.0, 120.9, 120.04, 120.02, 119.95, <lb/>119.21, 112.25, 112.22, 112.19, 108.4, 108.2, 67.34, 67.29, 65.9, 53.6, 53.5, 52.82, 52.80, <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 11 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>47.1, 47.0, 29.8, 29.5, 34.1, 34.0, 27.1, 24.8, 23.7, 23.6. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for <lb/>C 33 H 28 N 2 NaO 7 S [M+Na] + , 619.1515; found: 619.1507. <lb/>Methyl S-(1-(3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethyl)-N-((S)-3,3,3-trifluoro-2-methoxy-2-<lb/>phenylpropanoyl)-L-cysteinate (23a). <lb/>Methyl ester 21a (100 mg, 0.168 mmol) was dissolved in 1 mL of a mixture of DMF/ <lb/>piperidine (4:1, v/v). The reaction was monitored by TLC (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) and <lb/>stopped after 30 min of stirring at rt, the solvents were removed using a stream of air, and <lb/>the crude product was purified by column chromatography on SiO 2 (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, <lb/>v/v, to EtOAc) to remove the byproduct and remaining starting materials. The purified <lb/>product 22a and Mosher&apos;s acid chloride [(S)-(+)-α-methoxy-α-<lb/>(trifluoromethyl)phenylacetyl chloride] (51 mg, 0.2 mmol) were dissolved in 1 mL dry <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 , then DIEPA (0.1 mL) was added into this mixture. The reaction was monitored by <lb/>TLC (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) and stopped after 20 min of stirring at rt, the solvents were <lb/>removed under vacuum, and the crude product was purified by column chromatography on <lb/>SiO 2 (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) to give 85 mg (86%) of the desired product 23a, isolated as <lb/>a yellow sticky oil. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.43 (s, 1H), 8.36 (s, 1H), 8.09-8.06 (m, <lb/>4H), 7.66-7.52 (m, 11H), 7.48-7.41 (m, 9H), 4.88-4.76 (m, 4H), 3.77 (s, 3H), 3.69 (s, 3H), <lb/>3.44 (s, 3H), 3.42 (s, 3H), 3.09-2.99 (m, 2H), 2.94-2.88 (m, 2H), 1.77 (d, J = 6.9 Hz, 2H), <lb/>1.73 (d, J = 6.9Hz, 2H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 170.4, 170.3, 166.3, 166.2, <lb/>158.32, 158.28, 153.7, 147.8, 147.7, 133.4, 133.2, 129.6, 129.5, 129.1, 128.9, 128.6, 127.9, <lb/>123.7 (q, J = 289.9 Hz, CF 3 ), 123.81, 123.79, 122.39, 122.37, 121.9, 121.8, 121.0, 120.8, <lb/>112.25, 112.19, 108.24, 108.19, 84.13 (q, J = 28.0 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 83.92 (q, J = 28.0 Hz, C-<lb/>CF 3 ), 55.1, 52.84, 52.80, 51.89, 51.83, 43.5, 39.7, 39.3, 33.7, 33.3, 23.6, 23.4. 19 F NMR <lb/>(CDCl 3 , 470 MHz) δ -68.9, -69.0. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 28 H 25 F 3 N 2 NaO 7 S [M+Na] + , <lb/>613.1227; found: 613.1234. <lb/>S-(1-(3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethyl)-N-((S)-3,3,3-trifluoro-2-methoxy-2-<lb/>phenylpropanoyl)-L-cysteine (24a). <lb/>Ester 23a (80 mg, 0.136 mmol) was dissolved in 1 mL of ClCH 2 CH 2 Cl, and Me 3 SnOH (49 <lb/>mg, 0.271 mmol) was added. The reaction was heated at 75 °C in an oil bath for 2 h and then <lb/>cooled down to rt. The solvent was removed in vacuo and the resulting oil was purified by <lb/>column chromatography on SiO 2 (CH 2 Cl 2 /CH 3 OH, 100:5, v/v) to give 71 mg (91%) of the <lb/>desired product 24a, isolated as a yellow sticky oil. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.42 (s, <lb/>1H), 8.34 (s, 1H), 8.08-8.03 (m, 4H), 7.72 (d, J = 7.6 Hz, 1H), 7.65-7.55 (m, 10H), 7.47-<lb/>7.36 (m, 9H), 4.89-4.74 (m, 4H), 3.42 (s, 3H), 3.40 (s, 3H), 3.12-2.88 (m, 4H), 1.75 (d, J = <lb/>6.1 Hz, 2H), 1.71 (d, J = 6.4Hz, 2H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ166.6, 166.5, <lb/>158.29, 158.25, 153.6, 147.7, 147.5, 133.4, 133.2, 131.9, 131.8, 129.60, 129.53, <lb/>129.1,129.45, 129.43, 129.1, 128.9, 128.6, 127.9, 123.7 (q, J = 289.9 Hz, CF 3 ), 123.8, 122.4, <lb/>121.9, 121.8, 121.0, 120.9, 112.16, 108.25, 108.18, 84.02 (q, J = 26.9 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 83.92 (q, <lb/>J = 27.0 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 55.1, 52.0, 51.8, 39.5, 39.2, 33.4, 33.0, 29.7, 29.2, 23.5, 23.4. 19 F <lb/>NMR (CDCl 3 , 470 MHz) δ -68.9, -69.0. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 27 H 22 F 3 N 2 O 7 S [M-H] + , <lb/>575.1105; found: 613.1085. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Methyl S-(1-(3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethyl)-N-((S)-3,3,3-trifluoro-2-methoxy-2-<lb/>phenylpropanoyl)-D-cysteinate (23b). <lb/>Methyl ester 21b (100 mg, 0.168 mmol) was dissolved in 1 mL of a mixture of DMF/ <lb/>piperidine (4:1, v/v). The reaction was monitored by TLC (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) and <lb/>stopped after 30 min of stirring at rt, the solvents were removed using a stream of air, and <lb/>the crude product was purified by column chromatography on SiO 2 (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, <lb/>v/v, to EtOAc) to remove the byproduct and remaining starting materials. The purified <lb/>product 22b and Mosher&apos;s acid chloride (51 mg, 0.2 mmol) were dissolved in 1 mL dry <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 , then DIEPA (0.1 mL) was added into this mixture. The reaction was monitored by <lb/>TLC (Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) and stopped after 30 min of stirring at rt, the solvents were <lb/>under vacuum, and the crude product was purified by column chromatography on SiO 2 <lb/>(Hexanes/EtOAc, 5:1, v/v) to give 80 mg (81%) of the desired product 23b, isolated as a <lb/>yellow sticky oil. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.35 (s, 1H), 8.31 (s, 1H), 8.04-8.00 (m, <lb/>4H), 7.65-7.57 (m, 9H), 7.51 (d, J = 7.9 Hz, 1H), 7.46-7.38 (m, 10H), 4.88-4.70 (m, 4H), <lb/>3.79 (s, 3H), 3.72 (s, 3H), 3.51 (s, 6H), 3.01-2.96 (m, 2H), 2.88-2.82 (m, 2H), 1.68 (d, J = <lb/>6.9 Hz, 2H), 1.65 (d, J = 6.9Hz, 2H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 170.4, 170.3, <lb/>166.4, 166.3, 158.29, 158.26, 153.6, 147.67, 147.65, 133.24, 133.15, 132.42, 132.39, 129.6, <lb/>129.5, 129.0, 128.8, 128.49, 128.47, 127.8, 127.6, 123.62 (q, J = 290.0 Hz, CF 3 ), 123.60 (q, <lb/>J = 290.2 Hz, CF 3 ),123.81, 123.79, 122.35, 122.34, 121.9, 121.7, 120.9, 120.8, 112.26, <lb/>112.20, 108.24, 108.19, 84.0 (q, J = 26.4 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 83.9 (q, J = 26.4 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 55.19, <lb/>55.18, 52.88, 52.86, 51.92, 51.39, 39.6, 39.2, 33.7, 33.3, 23.5, 23.4. 19 F NMR (CDCl 3 , 470 <lb/>MHz) δ -68.8, -68.9. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 28 H 25 F 3 N 2 NaO 7 S [M+Na] + , 613.1227; <lb/>found: 613.1250. <lb/>S-(1-(3-nitrodibenzo[b,d]furan-2-yl)ethyl)-N-((S)-3,3,3-trifluoro-2-methoxy-2-<lb/>phenylpropanoyl)-D-cysteine (24b). <lb/>Ester 23b (80 mg, 0.136 mmol) was dissolved in 1 mL of ClCH 2 CH 2 Cl, and Me 3 SnOH (49 <lb/>mg, 0.271 mmol) was added. The reaction was heated at 75 °C in an oil bath for 2 h and then <lb/>cooled down to rt. The solvent was removed in vacuo and the resulting oil was purified by <lb/>column chromatography on SiO 2 (CH 2 Cl 2 /CH 3 OH, 100:5, v/v) to give 69 mg (90%) of the <lb/>desired product 24b, isolated as a yellow sticky oil. 1 H NMR (CDCl 3 , 500 MHz) δ 8.31 (s, <lb/>1H), 8.28 (s, 1H), 8.03-7.90 (m, 4H), 7.60-7.52 (m, 11H), 7.41-7.36 (m, 9H), 4.78-4.74 (m, <lb/>4H), 3.46 (s, 6H), 3.02-2.99 (m, 2H), 2.89-2.85 (m, 2H), 1.64 (d, J = 4.9 Hz, 2H), 1.60 (d, J <lb/>= 5.6Hz, 2H). 13 C{ 1 H} NMR(CDCl 3 , 125 MHz) δ 166.6, 158.23, 158.19, 153.6, 147.56, <lb/>147.49, 133.3, 133.2, 132.41, 130.9, 129.52, 129.46, 129.41, 129.39, 128.89, 128.81, <lb/>128.79, 128.45, 128.44, 127.81,127.69, 123.2 (q, J = 292.0 Hz, CF 3 ), 123.7, 122.4, 121.9, <lb/>121.8, 120.9, 120.8, 112.1, 108.2, 84.0 (q, J = 25.9 Hz, C-CF 3 ), 83.8 (q, J = 26.3 Hz, C-<lb/>CF 3 ), 55.18, 52.27, 51.66, 39.5, 39.2, 33.6, 33.1, 30.9, 23.4, 23.3. 19 F NMR (CDCl 3 , 470 <lb/>MHz) δ -68.79, -68.81. HRMS (ESI): Calcd for C 27 H 22 F 3 N 2 O 7 S [M-H] + , 575.1105; <lb/>found: 575.1118. <lb/>General Procedure for Solid-Phase Peptide Synthesis (SPPS). <lb/>Peptides were synthesized using an automated solid-phase peptide synthesizer (PS3, Protein <lb/>Technologies Inc., Memphis, TN) employing Fmoc/HCTU-based chemistry. Fmoc-Met-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 13 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Wang or Fmoc-Ala-Wang resin (0.03 mmol) was placed in the reaction vessel and <lb/>deprotected twice using 20% piperidine in dimethylformamide (DMF) for 5 min each time. <lb/>Four equivalents of amino acids and HCTU were activated in 0.4 M N-methylmorpholine <lb/>(NMM) for 1 min before adding to the resin. Standard incubation time for each coupling <lb/>was 20 min. Manual coupling of caged Fmoc-Cys derivatives was performed in a <lb/>polypropylene filter syringe equipped with a polypropylene stopcock. Four equivalents of <lb/>the protected cysteine were activated with 4 equivalents of HCTU in 1 mL 0.4 M NMM for <lb/>10 min before adding to the resin. The reaction completion was tested every hour using a <lb/>ninhydrin assay. 30 All caged Fmoc-Cys derivatives required 4 h for completion. Once the <lb/>ninhydrin assay confirmed the absence of any free amines, the resin was washed thoroughly <lb/>with DMF before placing back on the synthesizer and resuming the synthesis as previously <lb/>described. Once complete, approximately half of the resin was transferred to a syringe filter <lb/>and washed three times with CH 2 Cl 2 . Global deprotection and resin cleavage was <lb/>accomplished via treatment with 5 mL reagent K (82.5% TFA, 5% phenol, 5% water, 5% <lb/>thioanisole, and 2.5 % ethanedithiol) for 2 h. Cleaved peptides were precipitated with Et 2 O <lb/>and centrifuged before decanting the Et 2 O layer (repeated 3 times total). The resulting crude <lb/>peptide was dried via a stream of dry N 2 , then dissolved in 8 mL of a mixture of H 2 O/ <lb/>CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v) containing 0.1% TFA, aided by sonication. The solution was filtered using <lb/>a 0.2 μm PTFE filter and then purified using preparative reverse-phase (RP)-HPLC. Once <lb/>pure peptides were obtained, their concentrations were quantified in solution using the ε 350 <lb/>value measured for the caged Fmoc-Cys derivatives (1, 2 or Fmoc-Cys(NV)-OH). Stock <lb/>solutions were generated by dilution in H 2 O/CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v) containing 0.1% TFA to a <lb/>final concentration of 300 μM and stored at -20 °C. <lb/>NH 2 -YIIKGVFWDPAC(MeO-NDBF)VIA-OH (10). <lb/>ESI-MS calcd for C 98 H 136 N 18 O 23 S [M+2H] 2+ 982.9883, found 982.9879. 33.6 mg were <lb/>obtained after cleavage of approximately half of the resin. <lb/>NH 2 -YIIKGVFWDPAC(NDBF)VIA-OH (11). <lb/>ESI-MS. calcd for C 97 H 134 N 18 O 22 S [M+2H] 2+ 967.9854, found 967.9826. 19.0 mg were <lb/>obtained after cleavage of approximately half of the resin. <lb/>NH 2 -YIIKGVFWDPAC(NV)VIA-OH (12). <lb/>ESI-MS. calcd for C 92 H 134 N 18 O 23 S [M+2H] 2+ 945.9829, found 945.9790. 10.5 mg were <lb/>obtained after cleavage of approximately half of the resin. <lb/>NH 2 -KKKSKTKC(MeO-NDBF)VIM-OH (15). <lb/>ESI-MS. calcd for C 71 H 121 N 17 O 18 S 2 [M+2H] 2+ 781.9253, found 781.9243. 17.7 mg were <lb/>obtained after cleavage of approximately half of the resin. <lb/>NH 2 -KKKSKTKC(NDBF)VIM-OH (16). <lb/>ESI-MS. calcd for C 70 H 119 N 167 O 17 S 2 [M+2H 2+ 766.9200, found 766.9193. 9.0 mg <lb/>obtained after cleavage of approximately half of the resin. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Model Tripeptide NH 2 -GC(NDBF)F-OH (18). <lb/>Peptide 18 was synthesized manually on a 0.01 mmol scale using the conditions described in <lb/>the General Procedure for Solid-Phase Peptide Synthesis (SPPS) section. Compound 2 (6 <lb/>equiv) along with PyBOP, HOAT, and DIEA (6 equiv each) were dissolved in DMF at 50 <lb/>mM concentration and coupled to Phe-Wang resin for 1 h. After synthesis, a small amount <lb/>of the peptide was cleaved from resin using 95% TFA with 2.5% CH 2 Cl 2 and 2.5% H 2 O for <lb/>20 min. The solvent was then removed using a gentle stream of dry N 2 , which took <lb/>approximately 40 min. The resulting residue was brought to dryness using a rotary <lb/>evaporator. DMF (200 μL) was used to dissolve the peptide and the solution was filtered <lb/>using a GHP filter before acquiring a LC-MS chromatogram with single ion monitoring to <lb/>observe the epimerized product. The gradient consisted of an isocratic hold at 1% buffer A <lb/>for 10 min to fully remove the DMF, followed by a 1-100% gradient over 100 min (1% <lb/>increase per min). The remaining resin was incubated in 6 mL of 20% piperidine in DMF for <lb/>2 h to simulate 12 coupling steps in the synthesis of a full dodecapeptide and another LC-<lb/>MS chromatogram was obtained as before to probe for epimerization. ESI-MS. calcd for <lb/>C 12 H 29 N 4 O 7 S [M+H] + 565.2, found 565.2. <lb/>Coupling Optimization on Complete Peptides to Reduce Epimerization. <lb/>Peptide 10 was synthesized on a 0.01 mmol scale using procedure described in the General <lb/>Procedure for Solid-Phase Peptide Synthesis (SPPS) section. However, compound 1 (4 <lb/>equiv) was coupled using 4 equiv of N,N&apos;-Diisopropylcarbodiimide (DIC) and 6-Chloro-1-<lb/>hydroxybenzotriazole (Cl-HOBT) in DMF at 150 mM concentration for 1 h. Peptide 15 was <lb/>synthesized on the same scale, but using 4 equiv of Benzotriazole-1-yl-oxy-tris-pyrrolidino-<lb/>phosphonium hexafluorophosphate (PyBOP), 1-Hydroxy-7-azabenzotriazole (HOAT), and <lb/>N,N-diisopropylethylamine (DIEA) for 30 min. LC-MS chromatograms with single ion <lb/>monitoring were acquired using an isocratic hold at 1% buffer A for 5 min, followed by a 1-<lb/>100% gradient over 100 min (1% increase per min). <lb/>General Procedure for UV Photolysis of Caged Peptides in Rayonet Reactor. <lb/>Peptides were diluted in 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (PB), pH 7.4 containing 1 mM <lb/>DTT to a final concentration of 100 μM. The solutions were transferred into the quartz tubes <lb/>and irradiated in using 14 × 350 nm bulbs (14 W, RPR-3500 Å). Aliquots (50 μL) were <lb/>withdrawn at various intervals ranging from 0 to 30 sec (up to 240 sec for peptide 12), and <lb/>40 μL were subjected to LC-MS analysis. It is important to note that photolysis in H 2 O/ <lb/>CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v) containing 0.1% TFA or in PB buffer containing 1 mM DTT led to <lb/>production of compounds with an m/z corresponding to the desired free thiols + 32 mass <lb/>units, believed to be the corresponding sulfinic acid (Figure S4A-B). Photolysis in PB buffer <lb/>containing 15 mM DTT showed only the desired free thiols (Figure S4C-D). <lb/>General Procedure for UV Photolysis of Caged Peptides in LED Reactor. <lb/>Photolysis was conducted in a home-built LED reactor equipped with 8 × 350 nm LEDs <lb/>(FoxUV, 5.5mm) evenly spaced in a radial arrangement. A round quartz tube (10 × 50 mm) <lb/>with 1 mm wall thickness was positioned in the middle of the reactor. 200 μL of solution <lb/>was used for photolysis, resulting in an irradiated surface area of 1 cm 2 . Kinetic analyses <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 15 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>were performed using caged peptides diluted in 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (PB), pH <lb/>7.4 containing 15 mM DTT to a final concentration of 10 μM. At this concentration, &gt; 90% <lb/>transmittance occurs, thereby minimizing any inter-filter effect. The samples were irradiated <lb/>for varying amounts of time ranging from 0 to 90 sec (180 to 1080 for peptide 12), and then <lb/>100 μL aliquots were subjected to LC-MS analysis with UV monitoring at 350 nm and MS <lb/>scanning over a 500-2000 m/z window. The gradient was isocratic at 1% buffer A for 5 min, <lb/>followed by a 1-100% gradient over 10 min (10% increase per min). Peaks exhibiting the <lb/>m/z of the caged peptide were integrated in the UV chromatogram, and the amount of <lb/>remaining caged peptide was calculated using the formula: Remaining SM (%) = (Peak area <lb/>after irradiation)/(Peak area of unirradiated sample)*100. The quantum yield of uncaging <lb/>(Φ) in mols/ein was calculated using the relationship Φ = (Iσt 90 ) -1 , where I is the irradiation <lb/>intensity in ein•cm -2 .sec -1 , σ is the decadic extinction coefficient in cm 2 •mol (1000•ε), and <lb/>t 90 is the irradiation time in seconds required to achieve 90% uncaging. 31 The intensity (I) at <lb/>350 nm was measured to be 1.93E-09 ein•cm -2 .sec -1 via actinometry using 6 mM potassium <lb/>ferrioxalate as a standard. 32 <lb/>Laser apparatus for Two-Photon (TP) irradiation: <lb/>For the two-photon kinetic experiments, a home-built regeneratively amplified Ti:Sapphire <lb/>laser operating at 1 kHz with the pulse power maintained between 68 -76 mW centered <lb/>around 800 nm was used. Each pulse had a Gaussian profile with a full width at half <lb/>maximum of 80 fs. This system is described in detail elsewhere. 33 The beam was sent <lb/>through a 35 cm focusing lens and then through the sample. Samples (30 μL) were irradiated <lb/>in a quartz microcuvette (Starna 16.10-Q-10/Z15, 1 mm × 1 mm sample window, 10 mm <lb/>path length) 15 cm after the focal plane of the lens. <lb/>General Procedure for Two-Photon Photolysis of Caged Peptides at 800 nm. <lb/>Samples were irradiated in a 30 μL quartz cuvette (Starna Cells Corp.). The TP action cross-<lb/>sections for 10, 11, and 15 were measured by comparing the photolysis rates of the peptides <lb/>with that of BhcOAc as a reference (δ u = 0.45 at 800 nm). Aliquots (30 μL) containing <lb/>peptides (100 μM in H 2 O/CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v) containing 0.1% TFA) were irradiated with the <lb/>800 nm laser system for varying amounts of time, ranging from 2.5 to 30 min. Each sample <lb/>was analyzed by LC-MS using the previously described method. BhcOAc photolysis <lb/>experiments were conducted in the same manner using a 100 μM solution in 50 mM PB, pH <lb/>7.4. Reaction progress data were analyzed as described above, and the first-order decay <lb/>constants for the two compounds were calculated from by fitting to a first order exponential <lb/>decay process. 18 <lb/>UV and TP-Triggered Enzymatic Reactions. <lb/>A 7.5 μM solution of peptide 10 was prepared in prenylation buffer (50 mM PB, pH 7.4, 15 <lb/>mM DTT, 10 mM MgCl 2 , 50 μM ZnCl 2 , 20 mM KCl, and 22 μM FPP) and divided into <lb/>three 50 μL aliquots. Yeast PFTase was added to the first aliquot to give a final concentration <lb/>of 50 nM, but the resulting sample was not subjected to photolysis. The second aliquot was <lb/>irradiated in the absence of yeast PFTase, while the third sample was supplemented with <lb/>yeast PFTase (50 nM) and then photolyzed with UV light using the Rayonet reactor. UV <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>photolysis was conducted for 30 sec at 350 nm as described above using three light bulbs. <lb/>Each sample was incubated for 90 min at rt to allow the enzymatic reaction to proceed and <lb/>then the entire sample was analyzed by LC-MS using the gradient described above, and <lb/>detected with single ion monitoring (SIM) for the [M+H] +1 , [M+2H] +2 , and [M+3H] +3 <lb/>charged states for the caged peptide (1967.9, 982.9, 655.6), the free thiol peptide (1694.9, <lb/>847.4, 565.3), and the farnesylated peptide (1900.1, 950.5, 634.0), respectively. The TP <lb/>experiments were performed in an analogous manner using peptide 10 at identical <lb/>concentrations as the UV experiment, but using 30 μL aliquots (due to the 30 uL cuvette <lb/>size). Samples used initially to generate either the free thiol (13) or farnesylated product (14) <lb/>were irradiated for 10 min. Samples used to generate the farnesylated product as a function <lb/>of time were irradiated for varying amounts ranging between 0 and 25 min. The percent <lb/>remaining starting material was determined by integrating the SIM peaks for the starting <lb/>peptide (10) and farnesylated product (14) and inputting into the following formula: <lb/>Remaining SM (%) = (SIM of 10)/[(SIM of 10) + (SIM of 14)]*100. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supplementary Material <lb/>Refer to Web version on PubMed Central for supplementary material. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>The authors thank Drs. Matt Hammers and Andrew Healy for valuable consultations. We acknowledge the Mass <lb/>Spectrometry Core Facility of the Masonic Cancer Center, a comprehensive cancer center designated by the <lb/>National Cancer Institute, supported by P30 CA77598, where the LC-MS/MS analysis was performed. This work <lb/>was supported by the National Institute of General Medical Sciences, including R01 GM084152, R21 CA185783 <lb/>and NSF/CHE 1905204 to M.D.D. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>(1). Haugaard N Reflections on the Role of the Thiol Group in Biology. Annals of the New York <lb/>Academy of Sciences 2000, 899, 148-158. [PubMed: 10863536] <lb/>(2). Couvertier SM; Zhou Y; Weerapana E Chemical-proteomic strategies to investigate cysteine <lb/>posttranslational modifications. Biochim. Biophys. Acta-Prot. Proteom 2014, 1844, 2315-2330. <lb/>(3). Poole LB The basics of thiols and cysteines in redox biology and chemistry. Free Radic. Biol. Med <lb/>2015, 80, 148-157. [PubMed: 25433365] <lb/>(4). Klán P; Šolomek T; Bochet CG; Blanc A; Givens R; Rubina M; Popik V; Kostikov A; Wirz J <lb/>Photoremovable Protecting Groups in Chemistry and Biology: Reaction Mechanisms and <lb/>Efficacy. Chem. Rev 2013, 113, 119-191. [PubMed: 23256727] <lb/>(5). Shao Q; Xing B Photoactive molecules for applications in molecular imaging and cell biology. <lb/>Chem. Soc. Rev 2010, 39, 2835-2846. [PubMed: 20480074] <lb/>(6). Silva JM; Silva E; Reis RL Light-triggered release of photocaged therapeutics -Where are we <lb/>now? Journal of Controlled Release 2019, 298, 154-176. [PubMed: 30742854] <lb/>(7). Uprety R; Luo J; Liu J; Naro Y; Samanta S; Deiters A Genetic encoding of caged cysteine and <lb/>caged homocysteine in bacterial and mammalian cells. ChemBioChem 2014, 15, 1793-1799. <lb/>[PubMed: 24976145] <lb/>(8). Ellis-Davies GCR Two-Photon Uncaging of Glutamate. Frontiers in Synaptic Neuroscience 2019, <lb/>10, 48. [PubMed: 30687075] <lb/>(9). Isidro-Llobet A; Álvarez M; Albericio F Amino Acid-Protecting Groups. Chem. Rev 2009, 109, <lb/>2455-2504. [PubMed: 19364121] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 17 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>(10). Kaplan JH; Forbush B; Hoffman JF Rapid photolytic release of adenosine 5&apos;-triphosphate from a <lb/>protected analog: utilization by the sodium:potassium pump of human red blood cell ghosts. <lb/>Biochemistry 1978, 17, 1929-1935. [PubMed: 148906] <lb/>(11). Chang C-y.; Niblack, B.; Walker, B.; Bayley, H. A photogenerated pore-forming protein. Chem. <lb/>Biol 1995, 2, 391-400. [PubMed: 9383441] <lb/>(12). DeGraw AJ; Hast MA; Xu J; Mullen D; Beese LS; Barany G; Distefano MD Caged Protein <lb/>Prenyltransferase Substrates: Tools for Understanding Protein Prenylation. Chem. Biol. Drug Des <lb/>2008, 72, 171-181. [PubMed: 18844669] <lb/>(13). Nguyen DP; Mahesh M; Elsässer SJ; Hancock SM; Uttamapinant C; Chin JW Genetic Encoding <lb/>of Photocaged Cysteine Allows Photoactivation of TEV Protease in Live Mammalian Cells. J. <lb/>Am. Chem. Soc 2014, 136, 2240-2243. [PubMed: 24479649] <lb/>(14). Karas JA; Scanlon DB; Forbes BE; Vetter I; Lewis RJ; Gardiner J; Separovic F; Wade JD; <lb/>Hossain MA 2-nitroveratryl as a photocleavable thiol-protecting group for directed disulfide bond <lb/>formation in the chemical synthesis of insulin. Chemistry 2014, 20, 9549-9552. [PubMed: <lb/>24957739] <lb/>(15). Furuta T; Wang SSH; Dantzker JL; Dore TM; Bybee WJ; Callaway EM; Denk W; Tsien RY <lb/>Brominated 7-hydroxycoumarin-4-ylmethyls: photolabile protecting groups with biologically <lb/>useful cross-sections for two photon photolysis. Proc. Nat. Acad. Sci. USA 1999, 96, 1193-1200. <lb/>[PubMed: 9990000] <lb/>(16). Momotake A; Lindegger N; Niggli E; Barsotti RJ; Ellis-Davies GC The nitrodibenzofuran <lb/>chromophore: a new caging group for ultra-efficient photolysis in living cells. Nat. Methods <lb/>2006, 3, 35-40. [PubMed: 16369551] <lb/>(17). Zhu Y; Pavlos CM; Toscano JP; Dore TM 8-Bromo-7-hydroxyquinoline as a Photoremovable <lb/>Protecting Group for Physiological Use: Mechanism and Scope. J. Am. Chem. Soc 2006, 128, <lb/>4267-4276. [PubMed: 16569001] <lb/>(18). Mahmoodi MM; Abate-Pella D; Pundsack TJ; Palsuledesai CC; Goff PC; Blank DA; Distefano <lb/>MD Nitrodibenzofuran: a One-and Two-Photon Sensitive Protecting Group that is Superior to <lb/>Brominated Hydroxycoumarin for Thiol Caging in Peptides. J. Am. Chem. Soc 2016, 138, 5848-<lb/>5859. [PubMed: 27027927] <lb/>(19). Wosnick JH; Shoichet MS Three-dimensional Chemical Patterning of Transparent Hydrogels. <lb/>Chem. Mater 2007, 20, 55-60. <lb/>(20). Kotzur N; Briand B; Beyermann M; Hagen V Wavelength-Selective Photoactivatable Protecting <lb/>Groups for Thiols. J. Am. Chem. Soc 2009, 131, 16927-16931. [PubMed: 19863095] <lb/>(21). Abate-Pella D; Zeliadt NA; Ochocki JD; Warmka JK; Dore TM; Blank DA; Wattenberg EV; <lb/>Distefano MD Photochemical Modulation of Ras-Mediated Signal Transduction using Caged <lb/>Farnesyltransferase Inhibitors: Activation via One-and Two-Photon Excitation. ChemBioChem <lb/>2012, 13, 1009-1016. [PubMed: 22492666] <lb/>(22). Aujard I; Benbrahim C; Gouget M; Ruel O; Baudin J-B; Neveu P; Jullien L o-Nitrobenzyl <lb/>Photolabile Protecting Groups with Red-Shifted Absorption: Syntheses and Uncaging Cross-<lb/>Sections for One-and Two-Photon Excitation. Chemistry -A European Journal 2006, 12, 6865-<lb/>6879. <lb/>(23). LoPachin RM; Gavin T Molecular mechanisms of aldehyde toxicity: a chemical perspective. <lb/>Chem. Res. Tox 2014, 27, 1081-1091. <lb/>(24). Xue C-B; Becker JM; Naider F Efficient Regioselective Isoprenylation of Peptides in Acidic <lb/>Aqueous Solution using Zinc Acetate as Catalyst. Tetrahedron. Lett 1992, 33, 1435-1438. <lb/>(25). Nicolaou KC; Estrada AA; Zak M; Lee SH; Safina BS A Mild and Selective Method for the <lb/>Hydrolysis of Esters with Trimethyltin Hydroxide. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed 2005, 44, 1378-1382. <lb/>(26). Molina RS; Tran TM; Campbell RE; Lambert GG; Salih A; Shaner NC; Hughes TE; Drobizhev <lb/>M Blue-Shifted Green Fluorescent Protein Homologues Are Brighter than Enhanced Green <lb/>Fluorescent Protein under Two-Photon Excitation. J. Phys. Chem. Lett 2017, 8, 2548-2554. <lb/>[PubMed: 28530831] <lb/>(27). Palsuledesai CC; Distefano MD Protein prenylation: enzymes, therapeutics and biotechnology <lb/>applications. ACS Chem. Biol 2015, 10, 51-62. [PubMed: 25402849] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>(28). Kohl NE; Omer CA; Conner MW; Anthony NJ; Davide JP; deSolms SJ; Giuliani EA; Gomez <lb/>RP; Graham SL; Hamilton K Inhibition of farnesyltransferase induces regression of mammary <lb/>and salivary carcinomas in ras transgenic mice. Nat. Med 1995, 1, 792-797. [PubMed: 7585182] <lb/>(29). Berndt N; Hamilton AD; Sebti SØM Targeting protein prenylation for cancer therapy. Nat Rev <lb/>Cancer 2011, 11, 775-791. [PubMed: 22020205] <lb/>(30). Kaiser E; Colescott RL; Bossinger CD; Cook PI Color test for detection of free terminal amino <lb/>groups in the solid-phase synthesis of peptides. Anal. Biochem 1970, 34, 595-598. [PubMed: <lb/>5443684] <lb/>(31). Tsien RY; Zucker RS Control of cytoplasmic calcium with photolabile tetracarboxylate 2-<lb/>nitrobenzhydrol chelators. Biophys, J 1986, 50, 843-853. [PubMed: 3098316] <lb/>(32). Hatchard CG; Parker CA; Bowen EJ A new sensitive chemical actinometer -II. Potassium <lb/>ferrioxalate as a standard chemical actinometer. Proc. R. Soc. Lond. A 1956, 235, 518-536. <lb/>(33). Underwood DF; Blank DA Ultrafast Solvation Dynamics: A View from the Solvent&apos;s Perspective <lb/>Using a Novel Resonant-Pump, Nonresonant-Probe Technique. J. Phys. Chem. A 2003, 107, <lb/>956-961. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 19 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 1. <lb/>Representative photoremovable protecting groups used for the protection of the thiol group <lb/>of cysteine and building blocks suitable for SPPS used here. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 20 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. <lb/>Synthetic peptides containing MeO-NDBF-, NBDF-and NV-protected cysteine residues <lb/>prepared in this study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 21 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 3. <lb/>Study of the hydrolysis of a Mosher amide of NDBF-protected L-cysteine via 19 F NMR. A: <lb/>19 F NMR of compound 24a, obtained after hydrolysis of 23a. B: 19 F NMR of compound <lb/>24b, prepared from D-cysteine. This corresponds to the product that would form from <lb/>cysteine racemization during coupling leading to an epimeric peptide product. 19 F NMR of a <lb/>mixture of compounds 24a and 24b, showing the difference in chemical shifts between the <lb/>two epimers. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 4. <lb/>LC-MS of crude peptide 15 synthesized using PyBOP, HOAT and DIEA shows minimal <lb/>epimerized product. The desired peptide elutes as a double peak centered at 33.3 min. Note <lb/>the near complete absence of epimerized product at 36.4 min. The coupling conditions for 1 <lb/>to resin-bound VIM consisted of 4 equivalents of PyBOP, HOAT and DIEA at 150 mM in <lb/>DMF for 30 min. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 5. <lb/>UV spectra of protected forms of cysteine suitable for SPPS used in this study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 6. <lb/>Photolysis of caged peptides via one and TP excitations. Above: Kinetic analysis of <lb/>photolysis of MeO-NDBF-, NBDF-and NV-containing a-Factor-based peptides (10, 11 and <lb/>12, respectively) using a 350 nm LED reactor. Below: Kinetic analysis of photolysis of <lb/>NBDF-and MeO-NDBF-containing a-Factor-based peptides (10 and 11, respectively) and <lb/>MeO-NDBF-containing K-Ras-based peptide (15) using a 800 nm Ti:Saphire laser <lb/>employing BhcOAc as a reference standard. For both the UV and TP photolysis reactions, <lb/>each reaction was performed in triplicate and the resulting data averaged and used to create <lb/>the above plots. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 7. <lb/>Analysis of PFTase-catalyzed farnesylation after TP-activated photolysis of 10. In each case, <lb/>reactions were monitored by LC-MS with single ion monitoring (SIM) of the protected <lb/>peptide (10), the uncaged free thiol (13) and the farnesylated product (14). Panel A: LC-MS <lb/>analysis of a reaction containing 10 and PFTase before irradiation at 800 nm. Panel B: LC-<lb/>MS analysis of a reaction containing 10 without PFTase after irradiation at 800 nm. Panel C: <lb/>LC-MS analysis of a reaction containing 10 with PFTase after irradiation at 800 nm. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 8. <lb/>Quantification of starting peptide 10 and enzymatically farnesylated product 14 from TP-<lb/>activated photolysis of 10 at 800 nm conducted for different durations in the presence of <lb/>PFTase and FPP. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Scheme 1. <lb/>Synthesis of N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH (1). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<body>Scheme 2. <lb/>Synthesis of Mosher&apos;s amides of NDBF-protected cysteine for subsequent stereochemical <lb/>analysis. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/>Author Manuscript <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Bader et al. <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 30 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. <lb/>Photophysical properties of caged molecules employed in this study. <lb/>Protected Cysteine <lb/>(λ max ) <lb/>a (nm) <lb/>ε (λ max ) <lb/>a (M -1 cm <lb/>-1 ) <lb/>ε (350 nm) <lb/>a (M <lb/>-1 cm -1 ) <lb/>Φ (350) <lb/>c (mol/ <lb/>ein) <lb/>δ u (800 nm) <lb/>d (GM) <lb/>N-Fmoc-L-Cys(MeO-NDBF)-OH <lb/>(1) <lb/>355 <lb/>8,780 <lb/>8,750 <lb/>0.53 <lb/>e <lb/>0.71 <lb/>e 1.4 <lb/>f <lb/>N-Fmoc-L-Cys(NDBF)-OH (2) <lb/>320 <lb/>b <lb/>5,990 <lb/>4,600 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>g <lb/>0.20 <lb/>g <lb/>N-Fmoc-L-Cys(NV)-OH <lb/>350 <lb/>6,290 <lb/>6,290 <lb/>0.023 <lb/>h <lb/>-<lb/>a Measured in H 2 O/CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v). <lb/>b <lb/>Fmoc-Cys(NDBF)-OH (2) exhibits a broad maximum. <lb/>c Measured in 50 mM sodium phosphate buffer (PB), pH 7.4 containing 15 mM DTT. <lb/>d Measured in H 2 O/CH 3 CN (1:1, v/v) containing 0.1% TFA. <lb/>e Measured using peptide 10. <lb/>f <lb/>Measured using peptide 15. <lb/>g Measured using peptide 11. <lb/>h Measured using peptide 12. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">J Org Chem. Author manuscript; available in PMC 2021 February 07. </note>


	</text>
</tei>