<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Current Organic Synthesis <lb/>Current <lb/>Organic Synthesis <lb/>ISSN: 1570-1794 <lb/>eISSN: 1875-6271 <lb/>Current <lb/>Organic Synthesis <lb/>Impact <lb/>Factor: <lb/>1.69 <lb/>SCIENCE <lb/>BENTHAM <lb/>Volume 16, Number 3 <lb/>Send Orders for Reprints to reprints@benthamscience.net <lb/>Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, 16, 413-422 <lb/>413 <lb/>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>Synthesis of Novel Fluorine Compounds Substituted-4-thiazolidinones Derived from <lb/>Rhodanine Drug as Highly Bioactive Probes <lb/>Mohammad S.T. Makki, Reda M. Abdel-Rahman and Nawaa A.H. Alshammari * <lb/>Department of Chemistry, Faculty of Science, King Abdul Aziz University, P.O. Box. 42805, Jeddah 21551, Saudi Arabia <lb/>A R T I C L E H I S T O R Y <lb/>Received: November 27, 2018 <lb/>Revised: February 01, 2019 <lb/>Accepted: March 06, 2019 <lb/>DOI: <lb/>10.2174/1570179416666190312150046 <lb/>Abstract: Aim and Objective: It is known that rhodanine drug has various biocidal activities. The aim of this <lb/>work was to improve the structure of rhodanine drug via alkylation at N, S, and O-centers in addition to the <lb/>introduction of fluorine atoms. The new fluorinated modified rhodanines 2-16 were evaluated as enzymatic <lb/>probes for cellobiase activity produced by fungi and as CDK2 inhibitors of tumor cells. <lb/>Materials and Methods: Novel fluorine substituted N-alkyl, S-alkyl and amino-rhodanines were obtained via <lb/>Hydroxy methylation, Mannich reactions, chlorination and amination of 5-(4&apos;-fluorophenylene)-2-thioxo-<lb/>thiazolidin-4-one, and the enzymatic effects of cellobiase produced by fungi and /or CDK2 inhibition of tumor <lb/>cells were evaluated. <lb/>Results: Most of the targets were obtained in high yield and in the form of very pure crystals with <lb/>characteristic colors. Only compounds 5, 8, 10, 13, and 14 exhibited a higher activity as cellobiase while com-<lb/>pounds 2 and 5 showed a highly enzymatic effect on tumor cells. In addition, compounds 2 and 10 can be used <lb/>as Olomoucine (standard referees). <lb/>Conclusion: Various N, S and O-alkyl derivatives of fluorine-substituted rhodanines were prepared via a sim-<lb/>ple method and used as enzymatic probes for cellobiase activity produced by fungi and CDK2 inhibitors for <lb/>tumor cells. The more bioactive compounds had rich fluorine atoms as p-fluorophenyl and p-fluorobenzoyl <lb/>bearing N, S, O-alkyl rhodanine. The highly active compounds may be used as enzymatic materials for various <lb/>biological transformations in the future. <lb/>Keywords: Synthesis, fluorine substituted rhodanine, cellobiase activity of fungi, CDK2 inhibitors, bioactive probes, tumor cells. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Most of the substituted-4-thiazolidinones exhibit a wide range <lb/>of pharmacological, medicinal and biological properties as anti-<lb/>bacterial [1, 2], antifungal [3], antitubercular [4], anticancer [5], <lb/>antiinflammatory [6], antianalgesic [7], anticonvulsant [8], antide-<lb/>pressant [9], antiviral /anti HIV [10], antidiaberic [11], a muscarinic <lb/>receptor1-agonist [12], an FSH receptor agonist [13], trypanocidal <lb/>(anti-epimastigote) [14] and antiarrhythmic activity [15, 16]. <lb/>Introduction of fluorine atoms to heterocyclic nitrogen systems <lb/>often improves their physical with chemical advantages and <lb/>enhances their biological activity [17-20]. Based on these obser-<lb/>vations, the present work describes the development of new <lb/>fluorine compound substituted rhodanine derivatives which may <lb/>enhance the biological effects, as cellobiase produced by fungi as <lb/>well as CDK2 inhibitors for tumor cell (DNA damage). <lb/>The structure-activity relationship has been discussed and their <lb/>binding conformation is further clarified by molecular modification <lb/>studies. <lb/>2. MATERIALS AND METHODS <lb/>All the melting points were determined on Stuart scientific <lb/>SMP30 (Bibby, UK) melting point apparatus and reported as <lb/>uncorrected. The FT-IR spectra were recorded on a Perkin-Elmer <lb/>*Address correspondence to this author at the Department of Chemistry, Faculty of <lb/>Science, King Abdul Aziz University, P.O. Box. 42805, Jeddah 21551, Saudi Arabia; <lb/>Tel: +966531097330; E-mail: ro-0s@hotmail.com <lb/>spectrum 100 spectrometer in ATR. 1 H, 13 C and 19 F NMR spectra <lb/>were recorded on a Brucker advance DPX NMR spectrometer (400 <lb/>and 100 MHz, respectively), by using DMSO-d 6 as a solvent <lb/>(chemical shift in δ, ppm), and TMS as an internal standard. Ele-<lb/>mental analysis was conducted by a 2400 Perkin Elmer series 2 <lb/>analyzer. Mass spectra were determined by using quadruple MS <lb/>(Electronic ionization mod E1 mode with source temperature: <lb/>200ºC) at 70 eV. All the reactions were monitored by TLC, using <lb/>silica gel coated Al plates with a fluorescent indicator F254 <lb/>(Merck). <lb/>19 F NMR spectra of all the compounds 2-16 showed resonated <lb/>signals as d,d at -119.75 and -123.16 ppm. <lb/>3. RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>3.1. Chemistry <lb/>A literature survey reported a new fluorine compound substi-<lb/>tuted for rhodanine at positions SH, NH 3 , and active CH 2 positions <lb/>[21] and is used for detecting Tau pathology in Alzheimer&apos;s Brains <lb/>[22] as well as inhibitors of JSP-1 [23]. <lb/>In view of these results, the aim of this work was to search for <lb/>new fluorine compounds derived from rhodanine drug with a hope <lb/>to enhance their biological activity. <lb/>Thus, hydroxyl methylation and/ or Mannich bases of 5-(4-<lb/>fluorobenzylidene)-2-thioxothiazolidin-4-one (2) [24] via refluxing <lb/>with HCHO-MeOH and /or HCHO-MeOH with secondary amines <lb/>afforded N 3 -substituted rhodanine 3-5 (Scheme 1). <lb/></body>

			<front>1875-6271/19 $58.00+.00 <lb/>© 2019 Bentham Science Publishers <lb/>414 Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 <lb/>Makki et al. <lb/></front>

			<body>A simple nucleophilic attack of primary aliphatic/aromatic <lb/>amines to SH group at position-2 of rhodanine by refluxing with <lb/>ethanolamine, 4-fluoroaniline and sulfanilamide (1:1 by mol) in <lb/>EtOH, furnished 2-substituted amino-5-(4&apos;-fluorobenzylidene)-4-<lb/>thiazolidinones (6-8) (Scheme 2). <lb/>Also, the treatment of compound 2 with POCl 3 under fusion <lb/>condition yielded 4-chloro-5-(4-fluorobenzylidene)thiazol-2(5H)-<lb/>thione (9). Chlorine atom at 4-position of rhodanine 9 was removed <lb/>by treatment with primary amines. Thus, compound 9 upon attack <lb/>by primary amines such as 4-fluoroaniline, hydrazine hydrate and <lb/>/or 4-chlorophenyl-hydrazine under refluxing with DMF produced <lb/>5-(4-fluorobenzylidene)-4-[(4-fluorophenyl) amino]thiazol-2(5H)-<lb/>thione (10); 3-(4-fluorophenyl)-1,3-dihydro-pyrazolo[3,4-d]thiazol-<lb/>5-thione (11), and / or 2-(4-chlorophenyl)-3-(4-fluorophenyl)-1,2-<lb/>dihydropyrazolo[3,4-d]thiazol-5-thione (12) (Scheme 3). <lb/>Formation of 4 and 5 from 2 is shown in Fig. (1). <lb/>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>+ <lb/>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>EtOH/ pipdn. <lb/>! 6-8 h <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>3 <lb/>OH <lb/>HCHO/ MeOH <lb/>! 2 h <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>4 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>5 <lb/>HCHO/ MeOH <lb/>! 2 h <lb/>HCHO/ MeOH <lb/>! 2 h <lb/>HN <lb/>HN <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>Scheme 1. Formation of compounds 3-5 from 2. <lb/>S <lb/>N !-<lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F 2 <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>+ <lb/>H d+ <lb/>!+ <lb/>!-<lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>Addition <lb/>reaction <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>H ! -<lb/>!+ <lb/>!+ <lb/>! -<lb/>-H 2 O <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>4 or 5 <lb/>N <lb/>X <lb/>X <lb/>X: 4= CH 2 , 5= O <lb/>Fig. (1). Formation of 4 and 5 from 2. <lb/>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>6 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>8 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>7 <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>OH <lb/>NH <lb/>F <lb/>NH <lb/>SO 2 NH 2 <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>OH <lb/>EtOH/ ! 6 h <lb/>-H 2 S <lb/>EtOH/ ! 6 h <lb/>-H 2 S <lb/>EtOH/ ! 6 h <lb/>-H 2 S <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>SO 2 NH 2 <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>F <lb/>Scheme 2. Formation of compounds 6 and 7 from 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Synthesis of Novel Fluorine Compounds Substituted-4-thiazolidinones <lb/>Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3</note>

			<page>415 <lb/></page>

			<body>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>HO <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>Cl <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>9 <lb/>POCl 3 <lb/>! 1 h <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>12 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>10 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>11 <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>HN <lb/>Cl <lb/>N <lb/>HN <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>NHNH 2 <lb/>Cl <lb/>F <lb/>DMF, ! 1 h <lb/>(1:1) <lb/>-HCl <lb/>NH 2 NH 2 • H 2 O <lb/>DMF, ! 6 h <lb/>(1:1) <lb/>-HCl <lb/>DMF, ! 6 h <lb/>(1:1) <lb/>-HCl <lb/>Scheme 3. Formation of compounds 9-12 from 2. <lb/>The formation of compound 11 is shown in Fig. (2). <lb/>Alkylation of compound 2 by refluxing with monochloroacetic <lb/>acid in DMF yielded 2-[(5-(4-fluorobenzylidene)-4-oxo-4, <lb/>5-dihydrothiazol-2-yl)thio] acetic acid (13), which on decarboxyla-<lb/>tion via warming with aqueous K 2 CO 3 gave 5-(4-fluorobenzyli-<lb/>dene)-2-(methylthio) thiazol-4(5H)-one (14) (Scheme 4). <lb/>The structural formula of new systems was obtained from the <lb/>correct elemental analysis and spectral data. <lb/>FT-IR absorption spectra of compounds 3-5 showed the absor-<lb/>ption bands at ῡ 2980 &amp; 2888 cm -1 , attributed to endo CH= and exo <lb/>CH 2 with lack of NH group, and with the presence of ῡ at 1700, <lb/>1610, 1240 and 1180 cm -1 due to C=O, C=C, C-F, and C=S respec-<lb/>tively. Also, FT-IR spectra of compounds 6-8 recorded ῡ at 3180-<lb/>3150 cm -1 for bonded NH which lacks the SH groups. Moreover, <lb/>FT-IR spectrum of compound 9 indicates a lack of C=O with the <lb/>presence of ῡ at 700 cm -1 for C-Cl. Also, FT-IR spectra of both the <lb/>compounds 10 and 12 recorded ῡ at 3180, 1230 and 1188 cm -1 <lb/>which were attributed to the presence of NH, C-F, and C=S with <lb/>lack of C=O, while 11 showed ῡ at 3200, 3180, 1590 and 1240 cm -1 <lb/>for NH, NH 2 , C=N, C-F functional groups. <lb/>It is interesting to note that 1,4-disubstitutedthiazolo[5,4-<lb/>d]pyrazole-piperazine (16) isolated from the interaction of <lb/>compound 2 with piperazine (2:1 by mole) / in refluxing EtOH gave <lb/>N 1 , N 4 -disubstituted piperazine 15 followed by hydrazinolysis in <lb/>EtOH (Scheme 5). <lb/>FT-IR spectra of compounds 13 and 14 showed ῡ at 2980 and <lb/>2880 cm -1 of alkyl groups, with the presence of two ῡ at 1720, and <lb/></body>

			<page>416 </page>
				
			<note place="headnote"> Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 <lb/>Makki et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>SH <lb/>F <lb/>2 <lb/>N N <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>N N <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>11 <lb/>Cycloaddn. <lb/>outo oxidn. <lb/>! <lb/>-H 2 <lb/>! <lb/>-H 2 S <lb/>! <lb/>-H 2 O <lb/>Fig. (2). Formation of compound 11 from 2. <lb/>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>2 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>13 <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>14 <lb/>S <lb/>COOH <lb/>Cl <lb/>COOH <lb/>DMF, ! 1 h <lb/>-HCl <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>aq. K 2 CO 3 <lb/>! 1 h <lb/>-CO2 <lb/>Scheme 4. Formation of compounds 13 and 14 from 2. <lb/>S <lb/>NH <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>2 <lb/>HN <lb/>NH <lb/>EtOH, ! 6-8 h <lb/>-2H 2 S <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>15 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>NH 2 NH 2 • H 2 O ! 6-8 h <lb/>EtOH/ pipdn. <lb/>-H 2 O <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>16 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>(2:1) <lb/>Scheme 5. Formation of compounds 15 and 16 from 2. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Synthesis of Novel Fluorine Compounds Substituted-4-thiazolidinones <lb/>Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 </note>
				
			<page>417 <lb/></page>

			<body>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>F <lb/>7, M+, 315 (317, M+2, 1.5%) <lb/>NH <lb/>F <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>! <lb/>&quot; <lb/># <lb/>F <lb/>NH <lb/>F <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>95 (100) <lb/>110 (23.8) <lb/>84 (5.15) <lb/># <lb/>&quot; <lb/>! <lb/>-CO 2 <lb/>Fig. (3). Mass fragmentation pattern of compound 7. <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>10, (M+) 332, (M+1) 333, (M+2) 334, (M+3) 335 (1.18%) <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>71 (12) <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>164 (25.10) <lb/>S <lb/>58 (12) <lb/>NH <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>CH 2 <lb/>F <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>109 (80) <lb/>95 (100) <lb/>110 (85) <lb/>-CH 3 <lb/>-NH <lb/>Fig. (4). Mass fragmentation pattern of compound 10. <lb/>1690 cm -1 attributed to C=O of acid and C=O of thiazole nucleus. <lb/>Its interesting to note that FT-IR spectrum of compound 15 showed <lb/>lack of SH and / or NH groups, with the presence ῡ at 1700, 1610 <lb/>and 1230 cm -1 , for C=O, C=C, and C-F groups, respectively, while <lb/>the spectrum of 16 showed lack of C=O, C=C, NH, and SH groups. <lb/>Both the compounds 15 and 16 exhibited only ῡ at 2985, and 2880 <lb/>cm -1 for stretching and ῡ at 1488, and 1440 cm -1 for bending of <lb/>CH 2 , for piperazine, respectively. <lb/>1 H NMR spectra of the new compounds give more indications <lb/>about their structures. <lb/>Therefore, 1 H NMR spectra of compounds 3-5 showed <lb/>resonated signals δ at 7.6 and 2.4 for the exo (C=CH-Ar) and endo <lb/>N-CH 2 , while the spectra of compound 6-8 recorded δ at 8.2 ppm <lb/>for NH bonded with aromatic protons at 7-8 ppm. <lb/>Compound 6 showed δ at 7.8 and 5.1 ppm attributed to NH, <lb/>OH, and CH 2 protons. Also, 1 H NMR spectra of compounds 10-12 <lb/>indicate the existence of NH protons with aryl protons at δ 8.5-8.1 <lb/>and 7.6-7.4 (m &amp; m) ppm. Both the compounds 13 and 14 showed δ <lb/>at 2.5 ppm for aliphatic protons. Only 1 H NMR spectra of com-<lb/>pounds 15 and 16 exhibited resonated signals at δ 2.90⁓2.51 ppm <lb/>for N-CH 2 , and aryl-H with lack of both SH and NH protons. All <lb/>the compounds recorded δ at 7.5 and 7.4 (d,d) ppm being attributed <lb/>to CH-F protons. The interaction can occur only in &apos;&apos;Z&apos;&apos; geometry. <lb/>Thus, the exocyclic -CH=C-was deduced from recorded signals at <lb/>higher chemical shift at δ7.6 ppm [28]. <lb/>Also, 13 C NMR spectra of compounds 3-5 showed resonated <lb/>signals at δ 180, 170⁓165, 146 and 142 ppm for C=S, C=O, C-F, <lb/>C=C respectively, while that of 6-8, there was lack of C=S carbons. <lb/>13 C NMR spectra of both 10 and 12 exhibited signals at δ 180, 146, <lb/>144, and 142-140 ppm which were attributed to C=S, C-F, C-Cl, <lb/>C=N respectively, and aryl carbons at 133-128 ppm; while the <lb/>spectra of compound 11 showed a resonated signal at 180 ppm for <lb/>C=S. Mass fragmentation pattern of some compounds showed a <lb/>molecular ion peak, which, under the fragmentation process pro-<lb/></body>

			<page>418 </page>
				
			<note place="headnote">Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 <lb/>Makki et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>duced the base peak m/e 95 attributed to 4-fluorophenyl ions shown <lb/>in Figs. (3-5). The pathway fragment steps indicated the relation-<lb/>ship between the common base peak which had a significant role in <lb/>the biodynamic effects. <lb/>It is interesting that 13 C NMR spectrum of compound 13, <lb/>showed lack of C-OH proton, due to the H-bonding formed as <lb/>shown in Fig. (6). <lb/>Finally, 19 F NMR spectra of all the synthesized compounds 2-<lb/>16 showed resonated signals as d,d at -119.75 and -123.16 ppm for <lb/>the fluorine bonded to the aromatic nucleus. <lb/>3.2. Biological Evaluation <lb/>3.2.1. Antifungal Activity <lb/>All the obtained compounds were evaluated as fungicidal <lb/>probes against Candida albicans and Aspergillus Fumigatus fungi <lb/>by using DMSO as the solvent (1mg/ml) and Ketoconazole as the <lb/>standard drug. The inhibition was recorded by measuring the di-<lb/>ameter inhibition zones at the end of 48 h according to the reported <lb/>method (Table 1) [25]. <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>13 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>!-<lb/>!+ <lb/>Fig. (6). H-bonding in compound 13. <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>16, (M+) 520, (M+2) 522, (M+3) 524 (15.15%) <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>S <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>HN <lb/>N <lb/>85 (76) <lb/>F <lb/>+ <lb/>95 (100) <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>96 (12.1) <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>+ <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>+ <lb/>218 (5.16) <lb/>124 (27.0) <lb/>F <lb/>S <lb/>N <lb/>+ <lb/>190 (8.5) <lb/>-N 2 <lb/>+ <lb/>Fig. (5). Mass fragmentation pattern of compound 16. <lb/>Table 1. <lb/>The biological activity as antifungal of the new fluori-<lb/>nated-substituted rhodanine. <lb/>Compd. No. <lb/>C. Albicans <lb/>(µg/ml) <lb/>A. Fumigatus <lb/>(µg/ml) <lb/>3 <lb/>16 <lb/>14 <lb/>4 <lb/>15 <lb/>12 <lb/>5 <lb/>16 <lb/>13 <lb/>6 <lb/>14 <lb/>10 <lb/>7 <lb/>15 <lb/>11 <lb/>8 <lb/>20 <lb/>18 <lb/>9 <lb/>12 <lb/>10 <lb/>10 <lb/>19 <lb/>17 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>13 <lb/>18 <lb/>18 <lb/>14 <lb/>19 <lb/>19 <lb/>15 <lb/>10 <lb/>8 <lb/>16 <lb/>8 <lb/>7 <lb/>Ketoconazole <lb/>18 <lb/>16 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Synthesis of Novel Fluorine Compounds Substituted-4-thiazolidinones <lb/>Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 </note>
				
			<page>419 <lb/></page>

			<body>From the results, we can conclude that all the fluorinated sys-<lb/>tems exhibited an antifungal activity. Higher effects of compounds <lb/>were observed towards the two tested fungi as: 14 &gt; 13, 8 &gt; 7 &gt; 6 <lb/>and 10 &gt; 12 &gt; 11 &gt; 3 &gt; 5 &gt; 4. <lb/>Also, the result obtained indicated a particular activity more <lb/>than the standard drug used in the order 8 &gt; 10 &gt; 14 &gt; 5 &gt; 3, while <lb/>compounds 1,4-disubstituted piperazine 15 and 16 exhibited a lethal <lb/>activity. <lb/>3.2.2. The Enzymatic Effects on Cellobiase of Some Fungi <lb/>The efficiency of the synthesized fluorinated systems obtained <lb/>towards the activity of cellobiase produced enzyme as thermophilic <lb/>fungi namely, Thermomyces lanuginosus and Chaetomium Ther-<lb/>mophilum was evaluated according to the reported method [26]. In <lb/>DMF, which was used as a solvent, the enzyme solution and the <lb/>substrate (cellobiase) was added and the solution was then dis-<lb/>solved in citrate-phosphate buffer at pH 5 and incubated at 40ºC for <lb/>1 h. The freed reducing sugar was evaluated colorimetrically at 540 <lb/>nm as an induction for the enzymatic activity [27]. <lb/>Table 2. <lb/>The efficiency of new compounds on cellobiase activity <lb/>produced by thermophilic fungi * . <lb/>Compd. No. <lb/>Amount of Glucose (mg/ml) <lb/>C. Thermophilum <lb/>T. lanuginosus <lb/>5 <lb/>4.6 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>8 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>10 <lb/>7.8 <lb/>8.0 <lb/>13 <lb/>6.2 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>14 <lb/>7.0 <lb/>7.7 <lb/>* Blank: 0.97 and 0.80 mg/ml-without substance DMF. DMF: 0.7 and 0.72 mg/ml. <lb/>The data is recorded in Table 2. Only compounds 5, 8, 10, 13 <lb/>and 14 showed higher activity against the two tested fungi, which <lb/>showed the activity of reducing sugar in the order 8 &gt; 10 &gt;14 &gt;13 &gt; <lb/>5. The relationship between the structure and activity showed that <lb/>the presence of a sulfa drug, fluoroaniline, and alkylthia of 5-(4&apos;-<lb/>fluorobenzylidene) -2-thioxo-thiazol-5-one Skelton enhanced the <lb/>antifungal activity. <lb/>3.2.3. CDK2 Inhibition of Tumor Cells (DNA Damage) <lb/>Cyclin dependent-kinases are a family of serine/ threonine <lb/>kinases, that strongly control the mammalian cell-cycle by binding <lb/>to cyclins. Thus, CDK/ cyclin complexes are involved in the DNA <lb/>repair when they are presented in the inhibition state in response to <lb/>DNA damage [28-31]. <lb/>Also, the presence of fluorine atom in various hetero-cyclic ni-<lb/>trogen/ sulfur and oxygen systems, has a significant effect on the <lb/>modulation of electronic, lipophilic and steric parameters determing <lb/>the pharmacodynamic and pharmacokinetic properties [32]. <lb/>Thus, the new fluorine substituted rhodanines (2-16) have been <lb/>evaluated toward CDK2 in a biochemical assay. The inhibitory <lb/>concentration (IC 50 ) values were reported according to the methods <lb/>described above [33]. Olomoucine has been used as a standard, and <lb/>the results are reported in Table 3. From the data obtained, we can <lb/>indicate that: <lb/>All the tested compounds showed a very significant CDK2 in-<lb/>hibitory activity. Only, compound 2 showed an Olomoucine effect, <lb/>while the other tested compounds were observed to be more potent <lb/>than the standard control. It is interesting to note that compound 10 <lb/>had a higher enzymatic effect as the strong inhibitor for CDK2, <lb/>which may be used as a new inhibitor in the future. <lb/>Table 3. <lb/>CDK2 inhibiting activity of fluorinated rhodanine deriva-<lb/>tives 2-16. <lb/>Compd. No. <lb/>IC50 ± SD (µM)* <lb/>2 <lb/>5.0 ± 1.7 <lb/>4 <lb/>6.0 ± 1.8 <lb/>8 <lb/>3.7 ± 1.7 <lb/>10 <lb/>15.0 ± 2.7 <lb/>14 <lb/>12.0 ± 1.7 <lb/>15 <lb/>12.2 ± 1.5 <lb/>16 <lb/>4.1 ± 2.8 <lb/>Olomoucine <lb/>5.0 ± 1.0 <lb/>*IC50 in µM/dm -1 , SD: standard deviation. <lb/>4. EXPERIMENTAL <lb/>Compound 2 was obtained according to the reported method <lb/>[24]. <lb/>4.1. 5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-3-(hydroxymethyl)-2-thioxo thia-<lb/>zolidin-4-one (3) <lb/>A solution of 2 (1.554 g, 6.5 mmol) and HCHO (0.195 g, 6.5 <lb/>mmol) in MeOH (40 ml) was refluxed for 2 h. The mixture of was <lb/>cooled down at room temperature. The precipitated product was <lb/>filtered off and crystallized from dioxane to give compound 3. Or-<lb/>ange crystals, Yield 75% (25.43 g), M.p: 128-130ºC. FT-IR spec-<lb/>trum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3450-3420(broad, OH), 3060(ArH), 2944, <lb/>2880(aliph. CH), 1716(C=O), 1616(C=C), 1594(C=C), 1229(C-F), <lb/>1157(C=S), 889, 852, 793(subst. phenyl), 707(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 <lb/>MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.76(s, 1H, Ar CH=C), 7.66, 7.64(d,d, <lb/>2H, CH-F), 7.59-7.28(m, 2H, Ar), 4.59(s, OH), 2.51-2.50(s, CH 2 -<lb/>OH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 180(C=S), <lb/>173(C=O) 167(C-S), 162(Ar CH=C), 142(C-F), 133.6-127.42(Ar <lb/>carbons), 66.45(CH 2 carbon). Calculated, C 11 H 8 NFS 2 O 2 (269), %: <lb/>C, 49.07; H, 2.97; N, 5.20; F, 7.06, S,23.79. Found, %: C, 48.77; H, <lb/>2.66; N, 5.01; F, 6.85; S, 23.69. <lb/>4.2. Mannish Bases 4 &amp; 5 <lb/>A mixture of compound 2 (1.554 g, 6.5 mmol), piperidine (0.55 <lb/>g, 6.5 mmol) and/ or morpholine (0.57 g, 6.5 mmol), and HCHO <lb/>(0.195 g, 6.5 mmol) in MeOH (40 ml) was refluxed for 2h. The <lb/>mixture was cooled down at room temperature. The obtained pre-<lb/>cipitate was filtered off and crystallized from dioxane to give 4 and <lb/>/or 5. <lb/>4: Yellow crystals, Yield 75% (1.57 g), M.p: 165-167ºC. FT-IR <lb/>spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3050(Ar CH), 2939, 2862, 2798 (aliph. CH), <lb/>1725(C=O), 1599(C=C), 1235(C-F), 1190 (C=S), 880, 853(subst. <lb/>phenyl), 723(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.62(s, <lb/>Ar-CH =C),7.60, 7.54(d,d, 2H , CH-F), 7.29-7.27(m, 2H, Ar), <lb/>2.4(N-Me) 1.62 &amp; 1.56(CH 2 of piperidine). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 180(C=S), 173(C=O), 164(C-S), 162(Ar-<lb/>CH=C), 146(C-F), 132.32-128.82(aromatic carbons), 50.55, <lb/>49.75(N-Me &amp; CH 2 -CH 2 of piperidine). Calculated, C 16 H 17 N 2 FS 2 O <lb/>(336), %: C, 57.14; H, 5.05; N, 8.33; F, 5.65; S, 19.04. Found, %: <lb/>C, 56.88; H, 4.91; N, 8.11; F, 5.55; S, 18.85. <lb/>5: Yellow crystals, Yield 78% (1.65 g), M.p: 163-165ºC. FT-IR <lb/>spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 2937, 2854(str. CH), 1676(C=O), 1600(C=C), <lb/>1448, 1412(bending CH), 1389(NCSN), 1266(C-F), 831, 803(aryl <lb/>ring). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.6, 7.59(d,d 2H, <lb/>Ar), 7.52, 7.26(d,d, 2H , Ar), 3.795(s, 2H, CH 2 ), 3.53, 2.46, 1.60, <lb/>1.54(CH 2 protons). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): <lb/></body>

			<page>420 </page>
				
			<note place="headnote">Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 <lb/>Makki et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>180.19(C=S), 174.98(C=O), 163(C-S), 162.38(Ar-CH=C), 146(C-<lb/>F), 132-116(Ar carbons), 66.27-65.42(2H, CH 2 ), 26.16-23.71(2H, <lb/>CH 2 ). Calculated, C 15 H 15 N 2 FS 2 O 2 (338), %: C, 53.25; H, 4.43; N, <lb/>8.28; F,5.62; S, 18.93. Found, %: C, 53.01; H, 4.13; N, 8.11; F, <lb/>5.50; S, 18.78. <lb/>4.3. 5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-2-[(2-hydroxyethyl)amino] thia-<lb/>zole-4(5H)-one (6) <lb/>An equimolar amounts of compound 2 and ethanolamine were <lb/>mixed with in ethanol (40 ml) and refluxed for 6h. The mixture was <lb/>then cooled down at room temperature. The precipitate obtained <lb/>was filtered off and crystallized from dioxane to give compound 6. <lb/>Yellow crystals, Yield 65% (1.125g), M.p: 233-235ºC. FT-IR spec-<lb/>trum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3500 (OH), 3259(NH), 3050(ArH), 2900, <lb/>2869(aliph. CH), 1696(C=O), 1621(C=C), 1594(C=C), 1550(C=N), <lb/>1488, 444 (bending CH 2 ), 1228(C-F), 895, 859, 790(subst. phenyl), <lb/>751(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.8(s, 1H, NH), <lb/>7.47, 7.46(d,d, CH-F), 7.21-7.19(m, 2H, Ar), 5.1(s, 1H , OH), 3.45 , <lb/>2.39(CH 2 -CH 2 ). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): <lb/>163.54(C=O), 162.27(Ar-CH=C), 146(C-F), 142(C=N), 32.5-<lb/>128.02(Ar carbons), 62.78, 47.48(CH 2 -CH &amp; CH 2 -N). Calculated, <lb/>C 12 H 11 N 2 FSO 2 (266), %: C, 54.13; H, 4.13; N, 10.52; F, 7.14; S, <lb/>12.03. Found, %: C, 53.89; H, 4.11; N, 10.35; F, 7.00; S, 11.79. <lb/>4.4. 5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-2-[(4-fluorophenyl)amino] thia-<lb/>zole-4(5H)-one (7) <lb/>Compound 2 (1.554 g, 6.5 mmol) and 4-fluoroaniline (0.723 g, <lb/>6.5 mmol) were dissolved in EtOH (30 ml) and refluxed for 6h. The <lb/>mixture was then cooled down at room temperature. The precipi-<lb/>tated product was filtered off and crystallized from ethanol to give <lb/>compound 7. Orange crystals, Yield 80% (1.64 g), M.p: 225-227ºC. <lb/>FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3150(NH), 3050(ArH), 2854(aliph. CH), <lb/>1678(C=O), 1610(C=C), 1590(C=N), 1465, 1413(bending CH 2 ), <lb/>1228(C-F), 891, 856, 825(substituted phenyl), 735(C-F). 1 H NMR <lb/>(400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 8.2 (s. 1H, NH), 7.67, 7.61(d,d, 2H, <lb/>CH-F), 7.39-7.37(m, 4H, ArH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>(ppm): 170(C=O), 169(Ar-CH=C), 145(C-F), 142(C=N), 133.47-<lb/>125.79(Ar carbons). Mass spectrum, m/z (I rel , %): 315 (317, M+2, <lb/>1.50 %), 110(23.8), 95(100), 84(5.15). Calculated, C 16 H 10 N 2 F 2 SO <lb/>(316), %: C, 60.75; H, 3.16; N, 8.86; F, 12.02; S, 10.12. Found, %: <lb/>C, 60.55; H, 3.11; N, 8.59; F, 11.83; S, 10.01. <lb/>4.5. 4-[(5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-4-oxo-4,5-dihydrothiazol-2-yl) <lb/>amino]benzenesulfon-amide (8) <lb/>Compound 2 (1.554 g, 6.5 mmol), and sulfanilamide (1.12 g, <lb/>6.5 mmol) were dissolved in EtOH (150 ml) with a small amount of <lb/>piperidine. The mixture was refluxed for 6h, and then cooled down <lb/>at room temperature. The precipitated product was filtered off and <lb/>crystallized from MeOH to give compound 8. Orange crystals, <lb/>Yield 70% (1.71g), M.p: 168-170ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): <lb/>3180(NH), 3050(ArH), 2859(aliph. CH), 1690(C=O), 1592(C=C), <lb/>1576(C=N), 1465, 1416(bend. CH 2 ), 1314 (NHSO 2 ), 1230(C-F), <lb/>910, 826, 794(subst. phenyl), 706(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 8.2(s,1H, NH), 7.67, 7.66(Ar-CH=C), 7.65, <lb/>7.63(d, d, 2H, CH-F), 7.46, 7.45(d,d, 2H, 2CH-SO 2 ), 7.40-7.34, <lb/>6.89-6.58(each m, 4H , ArH), 2.50(NH 2 -SO 2 ). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 173(C=O), 169(Ar-CH=C), 162(C-F), <lb/>152(C=N), 133.46-125.77(Ar carbons). Calculated, C 16 H 12 <lb/>N 3 FS 2 O 3 (377), %: C, 50.92; H, 3.18; N, 11.14; F, 5.03; S, 16.97. <lb/>Found, %: C, 50.71; H, 3.01; N, 10.95; F, 4.89; S, 16.77. <lb/>4.6. 4-Chloro-5-(4-fluorobenzylidene)thiazole-2(5H)-thione (9) <lb/>A mixture of 2 (7 g, 29.28 mmol) and POCl 3 (15ml) was heated <lb/>to the fusion for 1h, and then cooled down at room temperature. <lb/>After that, it was poured onto ice and stirred. The precipitated prod-<lb/>uct was filtered off and crystallized from ethyl benzene to give <lb/>compound 9. Dark-green crystals, Yield 65% (4.91 g), M.p: 178-<lb/>180ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3060(ArH), 2854(aliph. CH), <lb/>1594(C=N), 1229(C-F), 1192(C=S), 853, 827(subst. phenyl), <lb/>707(C-Cl). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.84 (Ar <lb/>CH=C), 7.78, 7.77(d,d, 2H, CH-F), 7.75-7.05(m , 2H, ArH). 13 C <lb/>NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 195(C=S), 169.4(Ar-CH=C), <lb/>165(C-F), 162(C=N), 139.28(C-Cl), 133-122.33(Ar carbons). Cal-<lb/>culated, C 10 H 5 NFClS 2 (257), %: C, 46.69; H, 1.94; N, 5.44; F, 7.30; <lb/>S, 24.90; Cl, 13.61. Found, %: C, 46.48; H, 1.69; N, 5.33; F, 7.15; <lb/>Cl, 13.45; S, 24.79. <lb/>4.7. 5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-4-[(4-fluorophenyl)amino] thia-<lb/>zole-2(5H)-thione (10) <lb/>Equimolar amounts of compound 2 and p-fluoroaniline were <lb/>dissolved in DMF (15 ml) and refluxed for 1h. The mixture was <lb/>then cooled down at room temperature and poured onto ice. The <lb/>precipitated product was filtered off and crystallized from ethanol <lb/>to give compound 10. Dark-brown crystals, Yield 82% (1.73 g), <lb/>M.p: 179-180ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3151(NH), 3060(ArH), <lb/>2880 (aliph. CH), 1603(C=C), 1574(C=N), 1221(C-F), 830, <lb/>810(subst. phenyl), 710 (C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ <lb/>(ppm): 8.26 (s, 1H, NH), 7.7(Ar-CH= C), 7.698, 7.694(d, d, 2H, <lb/>CH-F), 7.68, 7.63(d,d, 2H, CH-F ), 7.61-7.45, 7.37-7.12(each m, <lb/>4H, ArH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 178.89(C=S), <lb/>163.07(Ar-CH=C), 159.46(C-F), 157.53(C-F), 155(C=N), 135.65-<lb/>126.25(Ar carbons). Mass spectrum, m/z (I rel , %): 332(335, M+3, <lb/>1.18%); 164(25.10), 110(85.0), 109(80.11), 95(100), 71(12.0), <lb/>58(15.1). Calculated, C 16 H 10 N 2 F 2 S 2 (332), %: C, 57.83; H, 3.02; N, <lb/>8.43; F, 11.44; S, 19.27. Found, %: C, 57.61; H, 2.85; N, 8.12; F, <lb/>11.08; S,19.11. <lb/>4.8. 3-(4-Fluorophenyl)-3,6-dihydro-5H-pyrazolo[3,4-d] thia-<lb/>zole-5-thione (11) <lb/>A solution of compound 2 (1.635 g, 6.34 mmol) and NH 2 NH 2 <lb/>(0.2 g, 6.34 mmol) was dissolved in DMF (50ml) and refluxed for 6 <lb/>h. The reaction mixture was cooled down at room temperature, and <lb/>then poured onto ice. The precipitated product was filtered off and <lb/>crystallized from EtOH to give compound 11. Light-brown crystals, <lb/>Yield 72% (1.24 g), M.p: 133-135ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): <lb/>3180(NH), 3060(ArH), 2880(aliph. CH), 1644(bend. NH), <lb/>1607(C=C), 1568(C=N), 1230(C-F), 1150(C=S), 862, 810(subst. <lb/>phenyl), 716(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 8.5(s, <lb/>1H, NH), 7.8(Ar CH=C), 7.3, 7.2(d,d, 2H, CH-F), 7.0-6.5(m, 2H, <lb/>ArH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 180(C=S), 147(C-<lb/>F), 142(C=N), 138(C=C), 133-123(Ar carbons). Calculated, <lb/>C 10 H 7 N 3 FS 2 (252), %: C, 47.61; H, 2.77; N, 16.66; F, 7.53; S, <lb/>25.39. Found, %: C, 47.42; H, 2.55; N, 16.41; F, 7.11; S, 25.09. <lb/>4.9. 2-(4-Chlorophenyl)-3-(4-fluorophenyl)-1,2-dihydro-5H-pyr-<lb/>azolo[3,4-d]thiazole-5-thione (12) <lb/>Compound 2 (1.635 g, 6.34 mmol) and 4-chlorophenyl hydra-<lb/>zine HCl (0.904 g, 6.34 mmol) were dissolved in DMF (50ml) and <lb/>refluxed for 6h. The mixture was then cooled down at room tem-<lb/>perature and onto ice. The precipitated product was filtered off and <lb/>crystallized from ethanol to give 12. Black crystals, Yield 78% <lb/>(1.93g), M.p: 188-190ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3239(NH), <lb/>3060(ArH), 2900(aliph. CH), 1596(C=C), 1567 (C=N), 1488(bend. <lb/>CH), 1225(C-F), 1157(C=S), 890, 823, 786(subst. phenyl), 736(C-<lb/>F), 664(C-Cl). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 10.47(s, <lb/>1H, NH), 7.87, 7.71(d,d, 2H, CH-F), 7.0, 7.69 (d,d, 2H, CH-Cl), <lb/>7.63-7.24 &amp; 7.23-6.72(each m, 4H , ArH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 179.38(C=S), 168(C-S), 160(C=N), 148(C-F), <lb/>144(C-N), 137(C-C), 132.95-121.37(Ar carbons). Calculated, C 16 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Synthesis of Novel Fluorine Compounds Substituted-4-thiazolidinones <lb/>Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 </note>
				
			<page>421 <lb/></page>

			<body>H 9 N 3 FCl S 2 (361), %: C, 53.18; H, 2.49; N, 11.63; F, 5.26; Cl, 9.27; <lb/>S, 17.72. Found, %: C, 52.98; H, 2.39; N, 11.51; F, 5.20; Cl, 8.89; <lb/>S, 17.55. <lb/>4.10. <lb/>2-[(5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-4-oxo-4,5-dihydrothiazol-2-<lb/>yl)thio]acetic acid (13) <lb/>Compound 2 (4 g, 16.73 mmol) and chloroacetic acid (1.58 g, <lb/>16.73 mmol) were dissolved in DMF (25 ml) and refluxed for 1h. <lb/>The reaction mixture was then cooled down at room temperature <lb/>poured onto ice. The precipitated product was filtered off and crys-<lb/>tallized from ethanol to give compound 13. Light-yellow crystals, <lb/>Yield 65% (3.23 g), M.p: 238-240ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): <lb/>3500-3100(broad, OH), 3060(ArH), 2937, 2880(aliph. CH), 1693, <lb/>1675(2C=O), 1595(C=C), 1562 (C=N), 1443, 1411(bend. CH 2 ), <lb/>1232(C-F), 1001(C-S-C), 827, 793(subst. phenyl), 749 (C-F). 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.0(Ar CH=C), 7.697, <lb/>7.690(d,d, 2H, CH-F), 7.630-7.360(m, 2H, ArH ), 2.50(2H, CH 2 ). <lb/>13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 178.91(C-S), 163.0(Ar-<lb/>CH=C), 161(C-F), 144(C=N), 131.84-128.59(Ar carbons), <lb/>49.56(CH 2 carbons). Calculated, C 16 H 8 NFS 2 O 3 (297), %: C, 48.48; <lb/>H, 2.69; N, 4.71; F, 6.39; S, 21.54. Found, %: C, 48.31; H, 2.43; N, <lb/>4.55; F, 6.12; S, 21.40. <lb/>4.11. 5-(4-Fluorobenzylidene)-2-(methylthio)thiazol-4(5H)-one <lb/>(14) <lb/>Compound 13 (1.5 g, mmol) and aq. K 2 CO 3 (5%, 15 ml) were <lb/>heated for 1h, and then cooled down followed by neutralization by <lb/>AcOH to give 14. Light-yellow crystals, Yield 55% (0.70g), M.p: <lb/>173-175ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3050(ArH), 2936(aliph. CH), <lb/>1674.9(C=O), 1620(C=C), 1599(C=N), 1467, 1411(bend. CH 3 ), <lb/>1224(C-F), 1050(C-S-C), 853, 832, 822(subst. phenyl), 723(C-F). <lb/>1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 7.70(Ar CH=C), 7.69, <lb/>7.68(d,d, 2H, CH-F), 7.63-7.53, 7.37-7.16(2H , ArH), 2.51 (Me-S). <lb/>13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 184, 179(C-S), 163.52 <lb/>(Ar-CH=C), 162.70(C-F), 161.55(C=N), 136-121.39(Ar CH), <lb/>26.21(CH 3 ). Calculated, C 11 H 8 NFS 2 O (253), %: C, 52.17; H, 3.16; <lb/>N, 5.53; F, 7.50; S, 25.29. Found, %: C, 52.01; H, 2.89; N, 5.28; F, <lb/>7.31; S, 25.11. <lb/>4.12. 2,2&apos;-(Piperazine-1,4-diyl)bis[5-(4-fluorobenzylidene) thia-<lb/>zol-4(5H)-one] (15) <lb/>Compound 2 (4 g, 16.73 mmol) and piperazine (0.721 g, 8.37 <lb/>mmol) were dissolved in EtOH (70 ml), refluxed for 6-8h, and then <lb/>cooled down. The precipitated product was filtered off and crystal-<lb/>lized from ethanol to give compound 15. Yellow crystals, Yield <lb/>85% (3.53g), M.p: 273-275ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): <lb/>3060(ArH), 2939, 2880(aliph. CH), 1690, 1666(2C=O), <lb/>1597(C=C), 1564 (C=N), 1505, 1414(bend. CH 2 ), 1231(C-F), 847, <lb/>826, 810(subst. phenyl), 725(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) <lb/>δ (ppm): 7.70(Ar-CH=C), 7.696, 7.693, 7.68, 7.65(each d,d , 4H , <lb/>CH-F), 7.54-7.36 , 7.35-7.17(each m, 4H , ArH), 2.90, 2.89 ,2.86 , <lb/>2.55, 2.51(4 CH 2 ). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): <lb/>173.74, 173.2(C=O), 163.11, 161.90(C-F), 131.86-115.95(Ar car-<lb/>bons), 49.91-49.18(CH 2 ). Calculated, C 24 H 18 N 4 F 2 S 2 O 2 (496), %: C, <lb/>58.06; H, 3.62; N, 10.88; F, 7.66; S, 12.90. Found, %: C, 57.85; H, <lb/>3.41; N, 10.44; F, 7.49; S, 12.78. <lb/>4.13. <lb/>1,4-Bis(3-(4-fluorophenyl)-3H-pyrazolo[3,4-d]thiazol-5-<lb/>yl)piperazine (16) <lb/>Compound 15 (2.5 g, 5.03 mmol) and hydrazine hydrate (0.503 <lb/>g, 10.06 mmol) were dissolved in EtOH (45 ml) with a small <lb/>amount of piperidine, and refluxed for 6-8h. The reaction mixture <lb/>was cooled down at room temperature, and then poured onto ice. <lb/>The obtained product was filtered off and crystallized from MeOH <lb/>to give compound 16. Orange crystals, Yield 70% (1.835g), M.p: <lb/>188-190ºC. FT-IR spectrum ῡ (cm -1 ): 3080(ArH), 2938, <lb/>2880(aliph. CH), 1600(C=C), 1560(C=N), 1221(C-F), 914, 821, <lb/>785 (substituted-phenyl), 742(C-F). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-<lb/>d 6 ) δ (ppm): 10.27(s, 1H, C 5 -H of thiazole), 7.8-7.76, 7.40-7.34 <lb/>(each d,d, 4H, CH-F), 7.31-6.86(m, 4H, ArH). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>DMSO-d 6 ) δ (ppm): 172.21(S-CN-N), 161(C-F), 132.8-114.93 (Ar <lb/>carbons), 47-46.9(CH 2 ), 24.6-23.76(CH). Mass spectrum, m/z (I rel , <lb/>%): 520(524, M+3, 15.15%), 218(5.16), 124(27.0), 190(8.5), <lb/>95(100), 96(12.1), 85(70.0). Calculated, C 24 H 18 N 8 F 2 S 2 (520), %: C, <lb/>55.38; H, 3.46; N, 21.53; F, 7.30; S, 12.30. Found, %: C, 55.18; H, <lb/>3.28; N, 21.11; F, 7.15; S, 12.20. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>Due to the high resistance of fungi towardantibiotics and drugs, <lb/>the present work designed, synthesized and evaluated them as dual <lb/>binding site modified fluorine compounds bearing rhodanine drug <lb/>inhibitors <lb/>Thus, in search for new rhodanine derivatives, the recent devel-<lb/>opment of rhodanine via the introduction of both fluorine atoms <lb/>followed by alkyl, amino and hydrazino substituents at C-2, N-3, <lb/>C=O and CH 2 corresponding to 2, 3, 4 and 5-position has been de-<lb/>duced with a hope to obtain highly biologically active probes for <lb/>their enzymatic effects on the cellobiase activity produced by some <lb/>fungi and as CDK2 inhibitors of tumor cells. <lb/>The importance of novel fluorine substituted rhodanine as <lb/>modified drugs has been highlighted in this study. The highly bio-<lb/>active substitutes at positions 2 and 5 have gainedmore attention of <lb/>the researchers. The study also concluded that both the compounds <lb/>2 and 10 can be used as Olomoucine (standard referees). <lb/></body>
				
			<div type="annex">CONSENT FOR PUBLICATION <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>
				
			<div type="availability">AVAILABILITY OF DATA AND MATERIALS <lb/>Not applicable. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>KACST has propvided fund for this project under grant No. 1-<lb/>18-01-009-0194. NCI (National Cancer Institute), USA, Technical <lb/>Maryland USA, has provided technical and financial support for the <lb/>CDK2 activity. <lb/></div>

			<div type="conflict">CONFLICT OF INTEREST <lb/>The authors confirm that this article content has no conflict of <lb/>interest. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>We would like to thank the Deanship of Scientific Research <lb/>KACST for funds and to the NCI (National Cancer Institute), USA, <lb/>Technical Maryland USA, for technical and financial support. Also, <lb/>Dr. I. Ismail from Department of Biochemistry, Ain Shams <lb/>University, Eygpt, for the fungicidal evaluation. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] <lb/>Abdel-Rahman, R.M. Chemoselective heterocyclization and pharmacological <lb/>activities of new heterocycles-a review. Part V-Synthesis of biocidal 4-<lb/>thiazolidinones derivatives. Boll. Chim. Farm., 2001, 140(6), 401-410. <lb/>[2] <lb/>Liu, X.-F.; Zheng, C.-J.; Sun, L.-P.; Liu, X.-K.; Piao, H.-R. Synthesis of new <lb/>chalcone derivatives bearing 2,4-thiazolidinedione and benzoic acid moieties <lb/>as potential anti-bacterial agents. Eur. J. Med. Chem., 2011, 46(8), 3469-<lb/>3473. <lb/>[3] <lb/>Liesen, A.P.; de Aquino, T.M.; Carvalho, C.S.; Lima, V.T.; de Araújo, J.M.; <lb/>de Lima, J.G.; de Faria, A.R.; de Melo, E.J.T.; Alves, A.J.; Alves, E.W.; <lb/>Alves, A.Q.; Góes, A.J.S. Synthesis and evaluation of anti-Toxoplasma <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>422 </page>
				
			<note place="headnote">Current Organic Synthesis, 2019, Vol. 16, No. 3 <lb/>Makki et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>gondii and antimicrobial activities of thiosemicarbazides, 4-thiazolidinones <lb/>and 1,3,4-thiadiazoles. Eur. J. Med. Chem., 2010, 45(9), 3685-3691. <lb/>[4] <lb/>Aridoss, G.; Amirthaganesan, S.; Kim, M.; Kim, J.; Jeong, Y.T. Synthesis, <lb/>spectral and biological evaluation of some new thiazolidinones and thiazoles <lb/>based on t-3-alkyl-r-2,c-6-diarylpiperidin-4-ones. Eur. J. Med. Chem., 2009, <lb/>44(10), 4199-4210. <lb/>[5] <lb/>Havrylyuk, D.; Kovach, N.; Zimenkovsky, B.; Vasylenko, O.; Lesyk, R. <lb/>Synthesis and anticancer activity of isatin-based pyrazolines and <lb/>thiazolidines conjugates. Arch. Pharm. Chem. Life Sci., 2011, 344(8), 514-<lb/>522. <lb/>[6] <lb/>Amin, K.; Kamel, M.; Anwar, M.; Khedr, M.; Syam, Y. Synthesis, biological <lb/>evaluation and molecular docking of novel series of spiro [(2H, 3H) quina-<lb/>zoline-2, 1′-cyclohexan]-4(1H)-one derivatives as anti-inflammatory and an-<lb/>algesic agents. Eur. J. Med. Chem., 2010, 45(6), 2117-2131. <lb/>[7] <lb/>Geronikaki, A.A.; Lagunin, A.A.; Hadjipavlou-Litina, D.I.; Eleftheriou, P.T.; <lb/>Filimonov, D.A.; Poroikov, V.V.; Alam, I.; Saxena, A.K. Computer-aided <lb/>discovery of anti-inflammatory thiazolidinones with dual cyclooxygenase/ <lb/>lipoxygenase inhibition. J. Med. Chem., 2008, 51(6), 1601-1609. <lb/>[8] <lb/>Kaur, H.; Kumar, S.; Vishwakarma, P.; Sharma, M.; Saxena, K.; Kumar, A. <lb/>Synthesis and antipsychotic and anticonvulsant activity of some new substi-<lb/>tuted oxa/ thiadiazolylazetidinonyl/ thiazolidinonylcarbazoles. Eur. J. Med. <lb/>Chem., 2010, 45(7), 2777-2783. <lb/>[9] <lb/>Akula, G.; Srinivas, B.; Vidyasagar, M.; Kandikonda, S. Synthesis of 3-(1H-<lb/>benzimidazol-2-yl amino) 2-phenyl-1, 3-thiazolidin-4-one as potential CNS <lb/>depressant. Int. J. Pharm. Tech. Res., 2011, 3, 360-364. <lb/>[10] <lb/>Ravichandran, V.; Jain, A.; Kumar, K.S.; Rajak, H.; Agrawal, R.K. Design, <lb/>synthesis, and evaluation of thiazolidinone derivatives as antimicrobial and <lb/>anti-viral agents. Chem. Biol. Drug Des., 2011, 78(3), 464-470. <lb/>[11] <lb/>Kini, D.; Ghate, M. Synthesis and oral hypoglycemic activity of 3-[5&apos;-<lb/>methyl-2&apos;-aryl-3&apos;-(thiazol-2ʺ-yl amino) thiazolidin-4&apos;-one] coumarin deriva-<lb/>tives. E. J. Chem., 2011, 8(1), 386-390. <lb/>[12] <lb/>Sadashiva, C.; Chandra, J.N.S.; Kavitha, C.; Thimmegowda, A.; Subhash, <lb/>M.; Rangappa, K.S. Synthesis and pharmacological evaluation of novel N-<lb/>alkyl/aryl substituted thiazolidinone arecoline analogs as muscarinic receptor <lb/>1 agonist in Alzheimer&apos;s dementia models. Eur. J. Med. Chem., 2009, 44(12), <lb/>4848-4854. <lb/>[13] <lb/>Arey, B.J.; Yanofsky, S.D.; Pérez, M.C.; Holmes, C.P.; Wrobel, J.; Gopal-<lb/>samy, A.; Stevis, P.E.; López, F.J.; Winneker, R.C. Differing pharmacologi-<lb/>cal activities of thiazolidinone analogs at the FSH receptor. Biochem. Biophy. <lb/>Res. Commun., 2008, 368(3), 723-728. <lb/>[14] <lb/>Kouznetsov, V.; Rodríguez, W.; Stashenko, E.; Ochoa, C.; Vega, C.; Rolon, <lb/>M.; Pereira, D.M.; Escario, J.A.; Barrio, A.G. Transformation of Schiff bases <lb/>derived from alpha-naphthaldehyde. Synthesis, spectral data and biological <lb/>activity of new-3-aryl-2-(α-naphthyl)-4-thiazolidinones and N-aryl-N-[1-(α-<lb/>naphthyl)but-3-enyl] amines. J. Hetero. Chem., 2004, 41(6), 995-999. <lb/>[15] <lb/>Bhandari, S.V.; Bothara, K.G.; Patil, A.A.; Chitre, T.S.; Sarkate, A.P.; Gore, <lb/>S.T.; Dangre, S.C.; Khachane, C.V. Design, synthesis and pharmacological <lb/>screening of novel antihypertensive agents using hybrid approach. Bioorg. <lb/>Med. Chem., 2009, 17(1), 390-400. <lb/>[16] <lb/>Jain, A.K.; Vaidya, A.; Ravichandran, V.; Kashaw, S.K.; Agrawal, R.K. <lb/>Recent developments and biological activities of thiazolidinone derivatives: <lb/>A review. Bioorg. Med. Chem., 2012, 20(11), 3378-3395. <lb/>[17] <lb/>Makki, M.S.; Abdel-Rahman, R.M.; Alharbi, A.S. Synthetic approach for <lb/>novel fluorine substituted α-aminophosphonic acids containing 1,2,4-triazin-<lb/>5-one moiety as antioxidant agents. Inter. J. Org. Chem., 2018, 8(01), 1-15 <lb/>[18] <lb/>Makki, M.; Bakhotmah, D.A.; Abdel-Rahman, R.M.; Aqlan, F.M. New route <lb/>to synthesize fluorine substituted lamotrigine drug analogues as an anti-<lb/>inflammatory agent. Curr. Org. Synth., 2018, 15(1), 116-125. <lb/>[19] <lb/>Ali, T.E.; Abdel-Rahman, R.M. Synthesis and antioxidant activities of some <lb/>novel fluorinated spiro[oxindole-thiazolidine] fused with sulfur and phospho-<lb/>rus heterocycles. J. Sulfur Chem., 2014, 35(4), 399-411. <lb/>[20] <lb/>Makki, M.; Alfooty, K.; Abdel-Rahman, R.; El-Shahawi, M. Synthesis, <lb/>voltammetric and analytical applications of some fluorine substituted <lb/>spirosteroidalthiazolidin-4-one derivatives of sulfa drugs. J. Chinese Chem. <lb/>Soc., 2016, 63(2), 189-198. <lb/>[21] <lb/>Alegaon, S.G.; Alagawadi, K.R.; Vinod, D.; Unger, B.; Khatib, N. Synthesis, <lb/>pharmacophore modeling, and cytotoxic activity of 2-thioxothiazolidin-4-one <lb/>derivatives. Med. Chem. Res., 2014, 23(12), 5160-5173. <lb/>[22] <lb/>Ono, M.; Hayashi, S.; Matsumura, K.; Kimura, H.; Okamoto, Y.; Ihara, M.; <lb/>Takahashi, R.; Mori, H.; Saji, H. Rhodanine and thiohydantoin derivatives <lb/>for detecting tau pathology in Alzheimer&apos;s brains. Am. Chem. Soc. 2011, <lb/>2(5), 269-275. <lb/>[23] <lb/>Cutshall, N. S.; O&apos;Day, C.; Prezhdo, M. Rhodanine derivatives as inhibitors <lb/>of JSP-1. Bioorg. Med. Chem. Lett., 2005, 15(14), 3374-3379. <lb/>[24] <lb/>Russell, A.J.; Westwood, I.M.; Crawford, M.H.J.; Robinson, J.; Kawamura, <lb/>A.; Redfield, C.; Laurieri, N.; Lowe, E.D.; Davies, S.G.; Sim, E. Selective <lb/>small molecule inhibitors of the potential breast cancer marker, human ary-<lb/>lamine N-acetyltransferase 1, and its murine homologue, mouse arylamine <lb/>N-acetyltransferase 2. Bioorg. Med. Chem., 2009, 17(2), 905-918. <lb/>[25] <lb/>Barry, A. The Antimicrobial Suseptabalitytest: Principale and Practices. Lea <lb/>and Febiger: Philadelphia, PA, USA 1976. <lb/>[26] <lb/>Mandels, M.; Reese, E. Inhibition of cellulases and ß-glucosidases. Adv. <lb/>Enzy. Hydrol. Cell Relat. Mater., 1963, 58-115. <lb/>[27] <lb/>Somogyi, M. A new reagent for the determination of sugars. J. Biol. Chem., <lb/>1945, 160(1), 61-68. <lb/>[28] <lb/>Chandrappa, S.; Kavitha, C.V.; Shahabuddin, M.S.; Vinaya, K.; Ananda <lb/>Kumar, C.S.; Ranganatha, S.R.; Raghavan, S.C.; Rangappa, K.S. Synthesis <lb/>of 2-(5-((5-(4-chlorophenyl)furan-2-yl)methylene)-4-oxo-2-thioxothiazoli-<lb/>din-3-yl)acetic acid derivatives and evaluation of their cytotoxicity and in-<lb/>duction of apoptosis in human leukemia cells. Bioorg. Med. Chem., 2009, <lb/>17(6), 2576-2584. <lb/>[29] <lb/>Satyanarayana, A.; Kaldis, P. A dual role of Cdk2 in DNA damage response. <lb/>Cell Div., 2009, 4(1), 9. <lb/>[30] <lb/>O&apos;Connor, P.M. Mammalian G1, and G2 phase checkpoints. Cancer Surv., <lb/>1997, 29, 151-182. <lb/>[31] <lb/>Vaziri, H.; Benchimol, S. From telomere loss to p53 induction and activation <lb/>of a DNA-damage pathway at senescence: The telomere loss/DNA damage <lb/>model of cell aging. Exp. Gerontrol., 1996, 31(1), 295-301. <lb/>[32] <lb/>Makki, M.S.; Abdel-Rahman, R.M.; Khan, K.A. Fluorine substituted 1,2,4-<lb/>triazinones as potential anti-HIV-1 and CDK2 inhibitors. J. Chem., 2014, <lb/>2014, Article ID 430573. <lb/>[33] <lb/>Gucký, T.; Řezníčková, E.; Džubák, P.; Hajdúch, M.; Kryštof, V. Synthesis <lb/>and anticancer activity of some 1, 5-diaryl-3-(3,4,5-trihydroxyphenyl)-1H-<lb/>pyrazolo[4,3-e][1,2,4]triazines. Monatsh. Chem., 2010, 141(6), 709-714. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>