<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Clickable Vitamins as a New <lb/>Tool to Track Vitamin A and <lb/>Retinoic Acid in Immune Cells <lb/>Amelie V. Bos 1 , Martje N. Erkelens 1 , Sebastiaan T.A. Koenders 2 , Mario van der Stelt 2 , <lb/>Marjolein van Egmond 1,3 and Reina E. Mebius 1 * <lb/>1 Department of Molecular Cell Biology and Immunology, Amsterdam University Medical Center, location VUmc, <lb/>Amsterdam, Netherlands, 2 Department of Molecular Physiology, Leiden Institute of Chemistry, Leiden University, Leiden, <lb/>Netherlands, 3 Department of Surgery, Amsterdam University Medical Center, location VUmc, Amsterdam, Netherlands <lb/>The vitamin A derivative, retinoid acid (RA) is key player in guiding adaptive mucosal <lb/>immune responses. However, data on the uptake and metabolism of vitamin A within <lb/>human immune cells has remained largely elusive because retinoids are small, lipophilic <lb/>molecules which are difficult to detect. To overcome this problem and to be able to study <lb/>the effect of vitamin A metabolism in human immune cell subsets, we have synthesized <lb/>novel bio-orthogonal retinoid-based probes (clickable probes), which are structurally and <lb/>functionally indistinguishable from vitamin A. The probes contain a functional group (an <lb/>alkyne) to conjugate to a fluorogenic dye to monitor retinoid molecules in real-time in <lb/>immune cells. We demonstrate, by using flow cytometry and microscopy, that multiple <lb/>immune cells have the capacity to internalize retinoids to varying degrees, including <lb/>human monocyte-derived dendritic cells (DCs) and naïve B lymphocytes. We observed <lb/>that naïve B cells lack the enzymatic machinery to produce RA, but use exogenous <lb/>retinoic acid to enhance CD38 expression. Furthermore, we showed that human DCs <lb/>metabolize retinal into retinoic acid, which in co-culture with naïve B cells led to of the <lb/>induction of CD38 expression. These data demonstrate that in humans, DCs can serve as <lb/>an exogenous source of RA for naïve B cells. Taken together, through the use of clickable <lb/>vitamins our data provide valuable insight in the mechanism of vitamin A metabolism and <lb/>its importance for human adaptive immunity. <lb/>Keywords: copper-facilitated click chemistry, retinoid probes, retinoic acid, vitamin A metabolism, CD38 <lb/></front>

			<body>INTRODUCTION <lb/>Numerous dietary studies have stressed the importance of vitamin A for proper functioning of the <lb/>immune system as vitamin A insufficiency is correlated to multiple infectious diseases (1-3). <lb/>Vitamin A, also known as retinol, needs to be metabolized into its active form retinoic acid (RA) to <lb/>influence the immune system. Retinol is an essential fat-soluble molecule, which needs to be <lb/>obtained via the diet. Dietary retinoids are absorbed by intestinal epithelial cells (IEC) and <lb/>transported in chylomicrons, in the form of retinyl esters, via the lymphatic system and can be <lb/>stored in the liver from where it can be transported to target cells (4). Vitamin A is converted into <lb/></body>

			<front>Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/>1 <lb/>Edited by: <lb/>Mats Bemark, <lb/>University of Gothenburg, Sweden <lb/>Reviewed by: <lb/>Stephanie N. Langel, <lb/>Duke University, United States <lb/>Makoto Iwata, <lb/>Waseda University, Japan <lb/>Andrew John Stagg, <lb/>Queen Mary University of London, <lb/>United Kingdom <lb/>*Correspondence: <lb/>Reina E. Mebius <lb/>r.mebius@amsterdamumc.nl <lb/>Specialty section: <lb/>This article was submitted to <lb/>Mucosal Immunity, <lb/>a section of the journal <lb/>Frontiers in Immunology <lb/>Received: 23 February 2021 <lb/>Accepted: 02 June 2021 <lb/>Published: 08 July 2021 <lb/>Citation: <lb/>Bos AV, Erkelens MN, Koenders STA, <lb/>van der Stelt M, van Egmond M and <lb/>Mebius RE (2021) Clickable Vitamins <lb/>as a New Tool to Track Vitamin A and <lb/>Retinoic Acid in Immune Cells. <lb/>Front. Immunol. 12:671283. <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.671283 <lb/>ORIGINAL RESEARCH <lb/>published: 08 July 2021 <lb/>doi: 10.3389/fimmu.2021.671283 <lb/></front>

			<body>the metabolic active product RA within the IEC (5). First, retinol <lb/>is converted into retinal under normal physiological conditions <lb/>by microsomal retinol dehydrogenases (RDHs) in a reversible <lb/>mechanism (6). Second, retinal is irreversibly converted by <lb/>aldehyde dehydrogenases (ALDHs) to form RA (7). RA binds <lb/>to nuclear receptors to regulate target gene expression. <lb/>Metabolized vitamin A has an extensive influence on the <lb/>immune system. For instance, metabolism of vitamin A by <lb/>epithelial cells is responsible for steering mucosal dendritic <lb/>cells (DCs) towards CD103-expressing tolerogenic cells, which <lb/>in turn gain ALDH enzyme activity to produce RA themselves <lb/>(8-11). Moreover, metabolized vitamin A induces expression of <lb/>gut homing molecules (11, 12), differentiation of T and B cells <lb/>and antibody class switching (13-17). More specifically, mouse <lb/>strains with lower ALDH enzyme activity secrete less <lb/>immunoglobulin A (IgA) into the intestinal lumen, leading to <lb/>higher levels of bacterial translocation into the intestinal lamina <lb/>propria and mesenteric lymph nodes (MLN), compared to mice <lb/>with high ALDH enzyme activity (18). While RA was shown to <lb/>directly promote IgA class switching (17, 19), the lack of RA <lb/>signalling in B cells abrogated antigen specific IgA responses <lb/>after oral immunization and affected the microbial composition <lb/>of the intestine (17). The source of RA for lymphocytes in <lb/>intestinal tissues is not completely known, as dendritic cells <lb/>(DCs), stromal cells, as well as epithelial cells have all been <lb/>indicated as cells that express vitamin A converting enzymes (10, <lb/>20, 21). It is becoming clear that in mice mucosal DCs play a <lb/>critical role in the vitamin A mediated effects for the immune <lb/>system, thereby regulating mucosal adaptive immune responses <lb/>(22). Murine experiments have demonstrated that DCs <lb/>metabolize RA and skew B cell differentiation into IgA+ B cells <lb/>(11, 18, 23). However, studies assessing the mechanistic <lb/>contribution of dendritic cells to vitamin A metabolism and B <lb/>cell functionality are exclusive to murine studies. Human studies <lb/>have mainly demonstrated that human DCs can induce IL10-<lb/>producing regulatory T cells (23-25) and induce the expression <lb/>of gut homing receptor a4b7 (23, 26) in an RA-<lb/>dependent mechanism. <lb/>To date, the uptake and metabolism of vitamin A within <lb/>human immune cells has remained largely elusive. Partly because <lb/>retinoids are small, lipophilic molecules which are difficult to <lb/>detect via microscopy methods. Previously, we developed an <lb/>activity-based probe with alkyne click handle to visualize and <lb/>quantify ALDH activity (27). In line, we now designed, <lb/>synthesized and applied novel bio-orthogonal retinoid-based <lb/>probes (clickable probes), which were structurally and <lb/>functionally, virtually indistinguishable from vitamin A. Yet <lb/>they contain a functional group (an alkyne) to conjugate them <lb/>to a fluorogenic dye to monitor retinoid molecules in real-time in <lb/>immune cells, enabling their visualization by flow cytometry and <lb/>microscopy. These clickable probes showed to be functionally <lb/>comparable to their natural counterpart. The contribution of RA <lb/>derived from dendritic cells to B cell functionality in humans has <lb/>not been yet addressed. Using these probes we show that human <lb/>B lymphocytes lack the machinery to metabolize retinol into RA, <lb/>although they can internalize retinoids. Interestingly, exogenous <lb/>RA directly CD38 expression on B cells. In contrast, human <lb/>monocyte-derived dendritic cells (moDCs) have the machinery <lb/>to metabolize retinol into RA. We observed that retinal, when <lb/>metabolized by moDCs, led to increased CD38 expression on B <lb/>cells, suggesting that human dendritic cells can influence B <lb/>lymphocytes directly by the production of RA. Overall, this <lb/>study shows that human dendritic cells can serve as a source of <lb/>RA for B cells and that this influences B cell properties. <lb/>METHODS <lb/>Synthesis of Clickable Retinoid Analogues <lb/>The clickable retinoid analogues were synthesized using the <lb/>convergent synthesis route. Wittig salt (1 in scheme 1) was <lb/>coupled with aldehyde (2 in scheme 1) to make the protected <lb/>retinal analogue RE-click in 8% yield. Aldehyde (2 in scheme 1) <lb/>was synthesized following a literature procedure, which can be <lb/>found in scheme 2 (28). The poor yield is a result of several <lb/>purification steps, which were required to separate the product <lb/>from the unreacted aldehyde 2 and the facile deprotection of the <lb/>acetal group under acidic conditions. <lb/>Retinal analogue RE-click was stored in ethanol at -80°C with <lb/>the aldehyde still protected as dimethyl acetal. Exposure to <lb/>slightly acidic conditions using a buffer or MilliQ instantly <lb/>liberates the aldehyde, after which the compound can be used. <lb/>The retinoic acid analogue was made using commercially <lb/>available aldehyde (3 in scheme 1), which resulted in <lb/>compound 4 (4 in scheme 1) with a yield of 39%. This was <lb/>then converted into the clickable retinoic acid analogue RA-click <lb/>using 2M NaOH with a 24% yield, which was stored under the <lb/>same conditions as the aldehyde analogue RE-click. <lb/>All reactions were performed using oven or flame-dried <lb/>glassware and dry solvents. Reagents were purchased from Sigma <lb/>Aldrich, Acros, Biosolve, VWR, Fluka, Fischer Scientific and Merck <lb/>and used as received unless stated otherwise. Tetrahydrofuran <lb/>(THF) and N,N-dimethylformamide (DMF) were stored over <lb/>molecular sieves before use. All moisture sensitive reactions were <lb/>performed under a nitrogen atmosphere. TLC analysis was <lb/>performed using Merck aluminum sheets (TLC silica gel 60/ <lb/>Kieselguhr F 254 . Compounds were visualized using a solution of <lb/>KMnO 4 (7.5 g), K 2 CO 3 (50 g), 10% NaOH (6 mL) in H 2 O (1L). <lb/>Column chromatography was performed using Screening Device <lb/>B.V. silica gel (particle size of 40 -63 µm, pore diameter of 60 Å) <lb/>with the indicated eluents. 1 H-and 13 C-NMR spectra were recorded <lb/>on Brüker AV-400 (400 MHz and 101 MHz, respectively) or Brüker <lb/>AV-500 MHz (500 MHz and 150 MHz, respectively) using CDCl 3 <lb/>as solvent. Chemical shifts are reported in ppm (d) relative to the <lb/>residual solvent peak or tetramethylsilane. Coupling constants are <lb/>given in Hz. High-resolution mass spectometry (HRMS) analysis <lb/>was performed with a LTQ Orbitrap mass spectrometer (Thermo <lb/>Finnigan), equipped with an electronspray ion source in positive <lb/>mode (source voltage 3.5 kV, sheath gas flow 10 mL/min, capillary <lb/>temperature 250°C) with resolution R = 60000 at m/z 400 (mass <lb/>range m/z = 150 -2000) and dioctyl phthalate (m/z = 391.28428) as <lb/>a &quot;lock mass&quot;, or with a Synapt G2-Si (Waters), equipped with an <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>electronspray ion source in positive mode (ESI-TOF), injection via <lb/>NanoEquity system (Waters), with LeuEnk (m/z = 556.2771) as <lb/>&quot;lock mass&quot;. Eluents used: MeCN:H 2 O (1:1 v/v) supplemented with <lb/>0.1% formic acid. The high-resolution mass spectrometers were <lb/>calibrated prior to measurements with a calibration mixture <lb/>(Thermo Finnigan). The retinoids were handled under dark <lb/>conditions using amber colored flasks or aluminum foil when <lb/>containing more than 3 conjugated double bonds. Retinoid <lb/>intermediates were stored in the dark under nitrogen at -30°C <lb/>and final compounds as powder or as EtOH stock at -80°C under <lb/>nitrogen atmosphere. For further information on retinoid handling <lb/>and storage we refer to the review from Barua and Furr (29). <lb/>(E)-4-Chloro-3-methylbut-2-en-1-yl <lb/>acetate (6): <lb/>To a stirred solution of isoprene 5 (5 in scheme 2) (20 mL, <lb/>0.20 mol) in acetic acid (60 mL) at 0°C under N 2 was added tert-<lb/>butyl hypochlorite (18 mL, 0.16 mol). The reaction mixture was <lb/>stirred for 1 hour and then quenched with H 2 O and extracted <lb/>with Et 2 O. The organic layer was washed with NaHCO 3 sat. aq. <lb/>and brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and concentrated under <lb/>reduced pressure. The residue was then dissolved in acetic acid <lb/>(60 mL) and to this was added CuSO 4 (320 mg, 2.0 mmol) and <lb/>H 2 SO 4 (0.2 mL, 4 mmol). The reaction mixture was stirred for 96 <lb/>hours at room temperature and was then quenched with H 2 O <lb/>and extracted with Et 2 O. The organic layer was washed with <lb/>NaHCO 3 sat. aq. and brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and <lb/>concentrated under reduced pressure. Purification of the residue <lb/>by column chromatography afforded the title compound 6 (6 in <lb/>scheme 2) (7.8 g, 48 mmol, 30%). 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>5.70 (t, J = 6.8 Hz, 1H), 4.62 (d, J = 6.9 Hz, 2H), 4.02 (s, 2H), 2.06 <lb/>(s, 3H), 1.82 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 170.4, 136.6, <lb/>123.5, 60.4, 50.5, 20.5, 14.2. Spectroscopic data for H-NMR are in <lb/>agreement with those reported (30). <lb/>(E)-4-Chloro-3-methylbut-2-en-1-ol (7): <lb/>Compound 6 (7.8 g, 48 mmol) was dissolved in MeOH (120 mL). <lb/>To this was added a solution of Na 2 CO 3 (7.6 g, 72 mmol) in H 2 O <lb/>(40 mL). The reaction mixture was stirred for 5 hours at 0°C, <lb/>filtered and concentrated under reduced pressure. The remaining <lb/>water layer was then extracted with CHCl 3 . The organic layer <lb/>was washed with brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and <lb/>concentrated under reduced pressure. Purification of the <lb/>residue by column chromatography (Pent/Et 2 O) afforded the <lb/>title compound 7 (1.9 g, 16 mmol, 33%). R f (50% Et 2 O in Pent) = <lb/>0.5. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 5.70 (s, 1H), 4.15 (s, 2H), 4.02 <lb/>(s, 2H), 3.43 (s, 1H), 1.76 (s, 3H). 13 C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>128.8, 58.5, 51.2, 42.7, 14.1. <lb/>(E/Z)-4-Chloro-3-methylbut-2-enal (8): <lb/>A solution of 7 (1.9 g, 16 mmol) in dry DCM (20 mL) was added <lb/>to a stirred suspension of PCC (5.1 g, 24 mmol) in dry DCM (40 <lb/>mL) at 0°C under N 2 containing molecular sieves. The reaction <lb/>mixture was stirred for 90 minutes at 0°C and was then filtered <lb/>over celite and concentrated under reduced pressure. <lb/>Purification of the residue by column chromatography (Et 2 O/ <lb/>Pent) afforded the title compound 8 (8 in scheme 2) (0.94 g, 8.0 <lb/>mmol, 51%; 1:0.3 E/Z mixture). R f (50% Et 2 O in Pent) = 0.8. 1 H <lb/>SCHEME 1 | Synthesis of clickable vitamins. Reagents and conditions: a) n-Buli, THF, -78°C to RT, 3 h, 8% for RE-click and 39% for 4; b) 2M NaOH, MeOH, 50°C, <lb/>4 hours, 24%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 10.04 (d, J = 7.7 Hz, 1H), 6.12 (d, J = <lb/>7.7 Hz, 1H), 4.12 (s, 2H), 2.28 (s, 3H); 13 C NMR (101 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 191.0, 155.2, 128.6, 49.3, 15.5. <lb/>(E)-4-Chloro-1,1-dimethoxy-3-methylbut-2-<lb/>ene (9): <lb/>To a solution of 8 (8 in scheme 2) (0.94 g, 7.9 mmol) in MeOH (7 <lb/>mL) was added trimethyl orthoformate (7.1 mL, 40 mmol) and <lb/>PTSA (0.80 mmol, 84 mg). The reaction mixture was stirred <lb/>overnight at room temperature and was then quenched with <lb/>NaHCO 3 aq. and extracted with Et 2 O. The organic layer was <lb/>washed with brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and concentrated <lb/>under reduced pressure. Purification of the residue by column <lb/>chromatography (Et 2 O/Pent) afforded the title compound 9 (9 in <lb/>scheme 2) (0.88 g, 5.3 mmol, 67%). R f (10% Et 2 O in Pent) = 0.5. <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR (400 MHz, Chloroform-d) d 5.51 (d, 6.0 Hz, 1H), 5.04 <lb/>(d, J = 6.2 Hz, 1H), 4.01 (s, 2H), 3.32 (s, 6H), 1.85 (s, 3H). 13 C <lb/>NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 137.4, 126.6, 99.6, 52.2, 50.6, 14.9. <lb/>(E)-4,4-Dimethoxy-2-methylbut-2-enal (2): <lb/>To a stirred solution of 9 (9 in scheme 2) (0.78 g. 4.7 mmol) in <lb/>DMSO (25 mL) was added K 2 HPO 4 (1.1 g, 6.2 mmol), KH 2 PO 4 <lb/>(0.23 g, 1.7 mmol) and NaBr (73 mg, 0.71 mmol). The mixture <lb/>was stirred for 18 hours at 80°C. Then H 2 O was added and the <lb/>mixture extracted with CHCl 3 . The organic layer was washed <lb/>with brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and concentrated under <lb/>reduced pressure. Purification by column chromatography <lb/>(Et 2 O/Pent) afforded the title compound 2 (0.39 g, 2.7 mmol, <lb/>57%). R f (10% Et2O in Pent) = 0.3. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>d 9.49 (s, 1H), 6.39 (d, J = 5.9 Hz, 1H), 5.27 (d, J = 5.9 Hz, 1H), <lb/>3.38 (s, 6H), 1.85 (s, 3H); 13 C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 194.4, <lb/>146.7, 141.5, 99.1, 52.5, 9.5. Spectroscopic data are in agreement <lb/>with those reported (28). <lb/>2-((1E,3E,5E,7E)-9,9-Dimethoxy-3,7-<lb/>dimethylnona-1,3,5,7-tetraen-1-yl)-1,3,3-<lb/>trimethyl-5-(prop-2-yn-1-yloxy)cyclohex-1-<lb/>ene (RE-click): <lb/>To a stirred solution of 1 (1 in scheme 1) (420 mg, 0.70 mmol) in <lb/>dry THF (5 mL) at -78°under N 2 was added n-BuLi (0.3 mL, <lb/>2.5M in hexane, 0.76 mmol). The mixture was stirred for 30 <lb/>minutes at -78°C and then a solution of 2 (2 in scheme 1) (100 <lb/>mg, 0.70 mmol) in dry THF (5 mL) was added. The reaction <lb/>mixture was stirred for 1 hour at -78°C and then for 3 hours at <lb/>room temperature. Then the reaction was quenched with NH 4 Cl <lb/>aq., extracted with Et 2 O. The combined organic layers were <lb/>washed with H 2 O and brine, dried with MgSO 4 , filtered and <lb/>concentrated under reduced pressure. Purification of the residue <lb/>by column chromatography (Et 2 O/Pent) with neutral silica <lb/>afforded the title compound RE-click (21 mg, 55 mmol, 7.9%). <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 6.70 -6.07 (m, 5H), 5.56 -5.13 <lb/>(m, 2H), 4.22 (d, J = 2.4 Hz, 2H), 3.86 (dtt, J = 12.0, 5.7, 3.3 Hz, <lb/>1H), 3.33 (d, J = 10.1 Hz, 6H), 2.46 -2.38 (m, 2H), 2.07 (dd, J = <lb/>16.8, 9.6 Hz, 1H), 1.96 (s, 3H), 1.91 (s, 3H), 1.86 -1.82 (m, 1H), <lb/>1.73 (s, 3H), 1.44 (t, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H), 1.07 (s, 6H). 13 C NMR (126 <lb/>MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 154.6, 138.9, 138.3, 137.7, 136.3, 136.1, 130.4, <lb/>SCHEME 2 <lb/>| Synthesis of mono-protected aldehyde intermediate. Reagents and conditions: a) tBuOCl, AcOH, 1h and then CuSO <lb/>4 , H <lb/>2 SO <lb/>4 , 96h, 30%; b) Na <lb/>2 CO <lb/>3 , MeOH/H <lb/>2 O, 5h, 0°C, 33%; c) PCC, DCM, <lb/>90 min, 0°C, 51%; d) trimethyl orthoformate, pTsOH, MeOH, 24h, 67%; e) K <lb/>2 HPO <lb/>4 /KH <lb/>2 PO <lb/>4 , NaBr, DMSO, 24h, 80°C, 55%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>127.8, 126.1, 125.9, 125.7, 100.2, 80.4, 73.8, 71.6, 55.1, 52.2, 44.5, <lb/>39.2, 36.8, 30.2, 28.6, 21.6, 13.2, 12.7. HRMS (ESI) m/z: [M + H] + <lb/>calculated for deprotected RE-click C 23 H 30 O 2 : 339.23186, <lb/>found: 339.23185. <lb/>Ethyl (2E,4E/Z,6E,8E)-3,7-Dimethyl-9-<lb/>(2,6,6-trimethyl-4-(prop-2-yn-1-yloxy) <lb/>cyclohex-1-en-1-yl)nona-2,4,6,8-<lb/>tetraenoate (4): <lb/>To a stirred solution of 1 (1 in scheme 1) (0.50 g, 0.83 mmol) in <lb/>dry THF (4 mL) at -78°under N 2 was added n-BuLi (0.50 mL, <lb/>1.6M in hexane, 0.83 mmol). The mixture was stirred for 30 <lb/>minutes at -78°C and then ethyl 3-methyl-4-oxocrotonate 3 (0.10 <lb/>mL, 0.76 mmol) was added. The reaction was stirred for 1 hour at <lb/>-78°C and then for 2 hours at room temperature. Then the <lb/>reaction was quenched with NH 4 Cl aq. And extracted with Et 2 O. <lb/>The combined organic layers were washed with H 2 O and brine, <lb/>dried with MgSO 4 and concentrated under reduced pressure. <lb/>Purification of the residue by column chromatography (EtOAC/ <lb/>Pent) afforded the title compound 4 (4 in scheme 1) (0.11 g, 0.30 <lb/>mmol, 39%) as a yellow oil as an E/Z mixture (1:0.3). R f (10% <lb/>EtOAc in Pent) = 0.95. NMR spectra are obtained from the <lb/>mixture of stereoisomers. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 6.98 <lb/>(dd, J = 15.1, 11.4 Hz, 1H), 6.55 -6.09 (m, 4H), 5.93 -5.76 <lb/>(m, 1H), 4.25 -4.21 (m, 2H), 4.21 -4.13 (m, 2H), 3.92 -3.81 (m, <lb/>1H), 2.48 -2.38 (m, 2H), 2.37 -2.32 (m, 3H), 2.12 -2.03 (m, <lb/>1H), 2.01 -1.94 (m, 3H), 1.88 -1.82 (m, 1H), 1.73 (s, 3H), 1.45 <lb/>(t, J = 12.0 Hz, 1H), 1.29 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 3H), 1.11 -1.05 (m, 6H). <lb/>13 <lb/>C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) 13 C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>167.13, 152.54, 139.10, 137.98, 137.59, 135.51, 130.70, 129.95, <lb/>127.48, 126.60, 118.79, 80.30, 73.88, 71.48, 59.64, 55.13, 44.39, <lb/>39.23, 36.80, 30.16, 28.58, 21.62, 14.32, 13.78, 12.87. HRMS (ESI) <lb/>m/z: [M + H] + calculated for C 25 H 34 O 3 : 383.25807, found <lb/>383. 25801. <lb/>(2E,4E/Z,6E,8E)-3,7-Dimethyl-9-(2,6,6-<lb/>trimethyl-4-(prop-2-yn-1-yloxy)cyclohex-1-<lb/>en-1-yl)nona-2,4,6,8-tetraenoic acid (RA-<lb/>click): <lb/>To a stirred solution of 4 (4 in scheme 1) (64 mg, 0.167 mmol) in <lb/>MeOH (2.5 mL) was added 2M NaOH (aq) (2.5 mL). The <lb/>reaction was heated at 50°C for 3 hours and then another 5 <lb/>mmol of NaOH (200 mg) was added. The reaction was then <lb/>stirred for 1 hour at 50°C and then made acidic with 1M HCl. <lb/>The product was then extracted with EtOAc, washed with brine, <lb/>dried over MgSO4, filtrated and concentrated. Purification by <lb/>column chromatography (Et 2 O/Pent) afforded the title <lb/>compound RA-click (14 mg, 39 mmol, 24%; 7:3 4E/Z). The E/Z <lb/>mixture was inseparable and prone to further isomerization <lb/>under the influence of light. As retinoids are rapidly converted <lb/>in vivo into their biological equilibrium of stereoisomers. RA-<lb/>click was used as the reported E/Z mixture. 21,22 NMR spectra are <lb/>obtained from the mixture of stereoisomers. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 7.04 (dd, J = 15.0, 11.4 Hz, 1H), 6.62 -6.50 (m, 1H), 6.35 -<lb/>6.11 (m, 3H), 5.94 -5.79 (m, 1H), 4.22 (s, 2H), 3.91 -3.83 (m, 1H), <lb/>2.47 -2.40 (m, 2H), 2.39 -2.33 (m, 3H), 2.13 -2.04 (m, 1H), 2.02 -<lb/>1.96 (m, 3H), 1.88 -1.83 (m, 1H), 1.74 (s, 3H), 1.48 -1.42 (m, 1H), <lb/>1.08 (s, 6H). 13 C NMR (126 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 172.1, 155.1, 139.8, <lb/>137.9, 137.6, 135.2, 131.7, 129.9, 127.9, 126.8, 117.8, 80.3, 73.9, <lb/>71.5, 55.2, 44.4, 39.2, 36.8, 30.2, 28.6, 21.6, 14.0, 12.9. LC-MS <lb/>(ESI) m/z: [M + H] + calculated for C 23 H 30 O 3 : 355.22677, <lb/>found: 355.16667. <lb/>Human Primary Cells <lb/>Blood samples were collected from donors after they had given <lb/>informed consent, in accordance with the guidelines of the <lb/>Medical Ethical Committee of the VU University Medical <lb/>Center (The Netherlands), and the declaration of Helsinki. <lb/>Blood was used to isolate peripheral blood mononuclear cell <lb/>(PBMCs) using Lymphoprep (Axis-Shield) density <lb/>gradient centrifugation. <lb/>B Cell Cultures <lb/>B lymphocytes were purified from the PBMC fraction using <lb/>negative isolation EasySep ™ Human Naïve B Cell Isolation Kit <lb/>or EasySep ™ Human Pan-B Cell Enrichment Kit (both Stemcell <lb/>Technologies). B cells were cultured in RPMI supplemented with <lb/>10% FCS, 1%PSG (both Thermo Scientific), 1 µg/ml anti-IgM <lb/>(Clone DA4-4, MyBiosource), 20 ng/ml IL-4 (Immunotools) and <lb/>1 µg/ml anti-CD40 antibody (Clone G28.5 BioXcell) for 7 days. <lb/>When indicated, 1 µM retinoic acid, retinal, RA-click or RE-click <lb/>was added once at day 0. <lb/>Dendritic Cell Culture <lb/>CD14 + monocytes were isolated from the PBMC fraction with <lb/>positive selection using CD14 magnetic microbeads (Miltenyi <lb/>Biotec) and cultured in RPMI supplemented with 10% FCS, 1% <lb/>PSG (all Thermo Scientific), 20 ng/ml GM-CSF and 20 ng/ml IL-<lb/>4 (both Immunotools) for 7 days in order to induce the <lb/>development of dendritic cells. When indicated 1 µM retinoic <lb/>acid, RE-click or RA-click was added once at day 0. <lb/>Co-Culture of B Cells and Dendritic Cells <lb/>Naïve B cells were labelled with Cell trace Violet (ThermoFisher) <lb/>and seeded in RPMI containing 1%PSG (Thermo Scientific), <lb/>N21-MAX Vitamin A Free Media Supplement (R&amp;D systems) <lb/>and B cell stimulating factors as described above (anti-IgM, IL-4 <lb/>and anti-CD40 antibody). At a ratio of 1:1 differentiated moDCs <lb/>were added. Co-cultures were carried out for 9 days in the <lb/>presence of 250 nM all-trans retinal, 250 nM all-trans retinoic <lb/>acid or ethanol as a vehicle control. <lb/>Aldefluor Assay <lb/>Aldefluor assay (Stemcell Technologies) was performed <lb/>according to manufacturer&apos;s protocol. <lb/>Incubation of Cells With Clicklable <lb/>Retionoids and Click Chemistry <lb/>In all experiments, cells were incubated with 1 µM clickable <lb/>retinoids for 1 hour at 37°C in RPMI medium, without serum, <lb/>unless otherwise indicated. Cells were fixed using 1% PFA for 30 <lb/>minutes on ice. 5 µl (100 mM) CuSO4 and 5 µl (1 M) NaAsc <lb/>(both Sigma Aldrich) we mixed and vortexed for a few minutes <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>until the colour turned from brown to yellow. 2,5 µl THPTA (100 <lb/>mM) (Sigma Aldrich) was added to this mixture, together with <lb/>487.5 µl PBS. After a few minutes, 0,5 µl commercially available <lb/>azide labelled with alexa fluor 647/488 (ClickChemistryTools) <lb/>was added and incubated for 3 additional minutes. This is called <lb/>the &apos;click mixture&apos; and is used for incubation with target cells, in <lb/>order to visualize clickable retinoids. The azide and alkyne form a <lb/>triazole, via a copper(I)-catalyzed [2 + 3] cyclo-addition. The <lb/>interaction between the azide group and alkyne is covalent, <lb/>resulting in a stable product. Once the interaction is formed <lb/>with the retinoid probe, the fluorophore cannot leave anymore. <lb/>Per click condition, around 100 000 cells were treated with 100 ul <lb/>click mixture for 1 hour at 37°C. Subsequently, cells were washed <lb/>with 2 mM EDTA, 3% BSA and finally PBS using the centrifuge <lb/>at 1500 rpm at 4°C. <lb/>Microscopy <lb/>Upon clicking the probes with a fluorophore, cells were treated <lb/>with DAPI (Thermo Scientific). Single cells were embedded in <lb/>Mowiol (Sigma Aldrich) on a microscope slide and covered with <lb/>a coverslip. Slides were imaged using a DM6000 fluorescent <lb/>microscope (Leica) or a SP8 confocal microscope (Leica). <lb/>Flow Cytometry <lb/>B lymphocytes were stained with anti-CD38 APC (Clone HIT2, <lb/>Biolegend) and anti-IgA biotin (Novex). After washing, <lb/>streptavidin alexa-488 and fixable viability dye eFluor780 <lb/>(eBioscience) were used. Differentiated monocyte-derived <lb/>dendritic cells were incubated with an CD103 APC (Clone <lb/>Ber-ACT8, BD Bioscience) and fixable viability dye eFluor780. <lb/>Samples were acquired on LSR-Fortessa X20 (BD Bioscience) <lb/>and data was analyzed with Flowjo software (Tree Star). Data <lb/>represented in histograms are normalized to mode, meaning data <lb/>is normalized to the highest value per condition. <lb/>RESULT <lb/>Characterization of Clickable Retinoids <lb/>Within Human Dendritic Cells <lb/>To study the cellular uptake of endogenous vitamin A metabolites, <lb/>clickable retinal (RE-click) and retinoic acid (RA-click) were <lb/>designed to resemble its natural counterparts, including an <lb/>additional alkyne ligation handle to conjugate them to a <lb/>fluorescent dye, via an azyde, to allow their detection in cells <lb/>using microscopy or flow cytometry (Figures 1A, B). First, we <lb/>used all white blood cells to get an insight into the uptake of the RE-<lb/>and RA-clickable probes within peripheral immune subsets. Briefly, <lb/>cells were placed in RPMI without any further addition at 37°C for 1 <lb/>hr and the probes were added to the medium to allow cellular <lb/>uptake. For detection of the probes within cells fluorescently tagged <lb/>azide was ligated to the alkyne group present on the probe via a <lb/>copper-catalysed reaction. Using flow cytometry, uptake of the <lb/>clickable probes in granulocytes, monocytes and lymphocytes was <lb/>assessed by gating on their differences in flow cytometric <lb/>characteristics for forward-and side-scatter (Supplemental <lb/>Figure 1A). To determine background signal click chemistry was <lb/>performed on cells receiving vehicle instead of the clickable probes. <lb/>It was observed that lymphocytes, monocytes and granulocytes all <lb/>had the capacity to take up the probes, although to varying degrees <lb/>(Supplemental Figures 1B-G). <lb/>Vitamin A metabolism plays a prominent role in intestinal DCs. <lb/>Therefore, human DCs were used to assess the applicability of the <lb/>clickable retinoids. We first verified whether human monocyte-<lb/>derived dendritic cells (moDCs) showed ALDH activity as <lb/>measured with the aldefluor assay. This assay utilizes a fluorescent <lb/>substrate, which is converted by ALDH enzymes, leading to the <lb/>accumulation of fluorescent signal within the cells that express the <lb/>enzymes. The amount of fluorescent product is proportional to the <lb/>ALDH activity in the cells. As a negative control, <lb/>diethylaminobenzaldehyde (DEAB) reagent is used to inhibit <lb/>ALDH activity, which sets the threshold for background signal. <lb/>Human moDCs showed enhanced aldefluor activity ranging from 2 <lb/>to 21% within donors compared to 0.6 ± 0.5% SD in DEAB control <lb/>samples (Figures 1C, D). This suggests that moDCs have ALDH <lb/>enzyme activity, which varied per donor. The average fold increase <lb/>in aldefluor positivity compared to the DEAB control was twenty-<lb/>seven (Figure 1E). Subsequently, MoDCs were incubated with the <lb/>clickable probes to assess whether they were capable of taking up <lb/>retinoids. We observed that all moDCs demonstrated enhanced <lb/>mean fluorescent intensity (MFI) for the RE-click compared to the <lb/>vehicle treated negative control, resulting in two separate peaks <lb/>within the moDCs (Figures 1F, G). The RA-click was taken up by <lb/>approximately half of the moDCs, as the other half of the cells were <lb/>negative for the probe (Figures 1H, I). Next, we titrated the uptake <lb/>of our probes in concentrations ranging from 1-1000 nM during a 1 <lb/>hr incubation at 37°C in RPMI to see at which dose they were still <lb/>detectable within cells using flow cytometry. We observed that RE-<lb/>click and RA-click could still be detected at concentrations ranging <lb/>from 100 to 1000 nM compared to vehicle control, while below 10 <lb/>nM uptake was not observed above the vehicle control (Figure 1J). <lb/>To subsequently visualize the spatial distribution of the probes <lb/>within the cells, moDCs were incubated with the clickable probes <lb/>for 1 hr at 37°C in RPMI and analysed using microscopy. In line <lb/>with flow cytometric data, enhanced MFI compared to vehicle was <lb/>seen after incubation with clickable retinoid probes (Supplemental <lb/>Figure 2). The RE-click mainly accumulated outside the nucleus of <lb/>moDCs in the cytosol, whereas the RA-click was also detected <lb/>within the nucleus in a small fraction of the cells (Figure 1J). Three <lb/>dimensional analysis was performed and demonstrated that both <lb/>retinoid probes crossed the cell membrane and were internalized <lb/>(Supplemental Videos 1 and 2). Taken together our data <lb/>demonstrates that the clickable probes are a helpful tool to study <lb/>retinoid uptake, demonstrating that human moDCs have the <lb/>capacity to internalize retinoids. <lb/>Uptake of Clickable Retinoids in Human <lb/>Dendritic Cells Is Independent of Protein <lb/>and Temperature <lb/>Since we demonstrated that the clickable retinoids can be used to <lb/>quantify cellular uptake within human moDCs, we utilized the <lb/>probes to study the mechanism of uptake into more detail. For <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>blood-borne transport retinol is bound to retinol binding <lb/>protein-4 (RBP4) (31). Target cells expressing receptors to <lb/>recognize this retinoid-protein complex can take up retinol, <lb/>thereby providing the cells with cytoplasmic retinol for <lb/>metabolism (31). Therefore, we questioned whether the uptake <lb/>of our probes requires carrier proteins. Hereto we incubated <lb/>moDCs with the RE-and RA-click in phosphate buffered saline <lb/>(PBS) without any further supplementation. Using flow <lb/>cytometry, we observed that moDCs showed enhanced MFI for <lb/>both the RE-and RA-click compared to the vehicle control <lb/>(Figures 2A, B), suggesting that uptake can be achieved in the <lb/>absence of proteins. Moreover, multiple studies have proposed <lb/>that the uptake of free retinoids happens via passive diffusion <lb/>(32-34). To assess whether uptake of clickable retinoids is <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>I <lb/>H <lb/>J <lb/>K <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 1 | Monocyte-derived dendritic cells have the capacity to take up and metabolize retinoids. (A) Chemical structure of retinal and its synthetic clickable <lb/>counterpart which contains an alkyne ligation group to allow visualization. (B) Chemical structure of retinoic acid and its synthetic clickable couterpart which contains <lb/>an alkyne ligation group to allow visualization. (C-K) Monocytes were isolated from blood and differentiated into monocyte-derived dendritic cells (moDCs) during 7 <lb/>days of culture in the presence of GM-CSF and IL-4. (C) Representative dot plots of aldeluor positivity in moDCs and DEAB-treated negative control. (D) <lb/>Quantification of the aldefluor positivity in moDCs from 6 different donors. (E) Quantification of the increase of aldefluor positivity in moDCs compared to the paired <lb/>DEAB control from 7 different donors. (F-K) Clickable retinoid probes were incubated for one hour in RPMI at 37°C with differentiated moDCs. (F) Representative <lb/>histogram of the uptake of RE-click (pink) compared to the vehicle control (dotted line) in moDCs. (G) Quantification of the uptake RE-click compared to the vehicle <lb/>control in moDCs from 3 different donors. (H) Representative histogram of the uptake of RA-click (blue) compared to the vehicle control (dotted line) in moDCs. <lb/>(I) Quantification of the uptake of RA-click compared to the vehicle control in moDCs from 4 different donors. (J) Differentiated moDCs were incubated with multiple <lb/>concentrations of RE and RA-click ranging from 1000 to 1 nM. Quantification of the uptake of the clickable probes was detemtined using flow cytometry using blood <lb/>form 3 different donors (K) moDCs were put on a coverslip to assess the spatial distribution of retinoid probes (green) and nuclei (DAPI, blue) using confocal <lb/>microscopy. White arrow indicates cytoplasmic accumulation, whereas the red arrow indicates nuclear localization. Data are presented as mean± SD. Student&apos;s t <lb/>test; *p &lt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>dependent on ATP-driven metabolism, we incubated moDCs <lb/>with our probes at 4°C. It was observed that both RE-and RA-<lb/>click were taken up by moDCs when incubated at 4°C <lb/>(Figures 2C, D). Although this suggests that the uptake of <lb/>clickable probes is ATP-independent, we did observe that a <lb/>fraction of the moDCs had not taken up any clickable probe, <lb/>indicative of uptake by a subset of DCs(Figure 2E). Taken <lb/>together, the clickable probes can be used in a straightforward <lb/>method to study the cellular uptake of retinoids in immune cells. <lb/>Clickable Retinoic Acid Is Functionally <lb/>Active Within Human Dendritic Cells <lb/>Subsequently, the functionality of RA-click on human DC <lb/>behaviour was examined. Others have demonstrates that RA <lb/>polarizes peripheral monocytes into CD103 + tolerogenic DCs <lb/>with high ALDH activity (23, 26). Similarly, we differentiated <lb/>monocytes for 7 days within the presence of RA-click. Retinal was <lb/>excluded in these assays, as it has no functional effect on moDC <lb/>differentiation. In the presence of natural RA, and likewise the RA-<lb/>click, ALDH activity increased in moDCs (Figure 3A). Moreover, <lb/>the expression of CD103 increased compared to conventional <lb/>cultured moDCs after incubation with natural RA and also upon <lb/>incubation with RA-click (Figure 3B). Together, our data <lb/>demonstrates that the RA-click can induce the differentiation of <lb/>moDC in a similar fashion as its natural counterpart, suggesting the <lb/>probe is also suitable for functional assays. <lb/>Naïve B Cells Take Up Exogenous Retinoids <lb/>but Cannot Produce Retinoid Acid <lb/>After validating the clickable probes within human DCs, we <lb/>assessed vitamin A uptake and functionality within the less well <lb/>studied B lymphocyte compartment. Although it is recognized that <lb/>RA-mediated processes in B cells are important for proper adaptive <lb/>immune responses, such as IgA class-switching (14, 17, 19, 35, 36) <lb/>and induction of CD38 (37, 38), the physiological mechanism <lb/>remains unclear. To address the effects of retinoids on human B <lb/>lymphocytes, we first used the aldefluor assay to test whether B <lb/>lymphocytes have the machinery to produce retinoic acid. Within <lb/>the total CD19 + B lymphocyte population present in peripheral <lb/>blood, a small proportion was positive for the aldefluor assay <lb/>compared to DEAB treated samples (Supplemental Figures 3A, <lb/>B). However, when only naïve B cells were analysed no differences <lb/>were observed in MFI between cell treated with vehicle or DEAB, <lb/>demonstrating that human naïve B cells from peripheral blood <lb/>cannot metabolize the aldefluor assay substrate. This result suggests <lb/>that naïve B cells lack ALDH activity (Figures 4A, B). <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 2 | Uptake of dickable retinoids in human dendritic cells is independent of protein and temperature. Monocytes were isolated from blood and differentiated <lb/>into monocyte-derived dendritic cells (moDCs) during 7 days of culture in the presence of GM-CSF and IL-4 from 3 different donors. Uptake of (A) RE-click and <lb/>(B) RA-dick compared to the vehicle control in differentiated moDCs after incubation in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) for one hour at 37°c was determined by <lb/>flowcytometric analysis and expressed as mean fluorescent intensity (MFI). Uptake of (C) RE-click and (D) RA-click compared to the vehicle control in differentiated <lb/>moDCs after incubated in phosphate buffered saline (PBS) for one hour at 4°C was determined by flowcytometric analysis and expressed as MFI. (E) Representative <lb/>histogram of uptake of RE-(pink) and RA-click (blue) compared to the vehicle control (solid line) in moDCs at 4°C, as shown in (C, D) Data are presented as mean± <lb/>SD. Student&apos;s t test; *p &lt; 0.05, **p &lt; 0.01. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Next, we addressed whether clickable retinoids could be made <lb/>visible in B cells present in total PBMC fractions. Hereto, we first <lb/>tested whether flow cytometry and click chemistry were <lb/>compatible. We observed that the cupper-mediated click <lb/>reaction influenced the forward and side scatter profile of <lb/>leukocytes (Supplemental Figure 3A) as well as the intensity <lb/>of multiple fluorescently labelled antibodies (Supplemental <lb/>Figures 3B-D). This disqualified the combination of flow <lb/>cytometry and click chemistry in one assay as a viable method <lb/>for proper analysis of immune subsets. Therefore, we decided to <lb/>first use magnetic bead isolation to obtain naïve B cells, followed <lb/>by probe incubation and the click reaction, in order to address <lb/>whether B lymphocytes can take up retinoid probes. The RE-<lb/>probe accumulated with high MFI within the cells compared to <lb/>the vehicle control, suggesting that naïve B cells efficiently took <lb/>up the probe (Figures 4C, D). The RA-click was taken up as well, <lb/>however the MFI was lower when compared to RE-click. <lb/>Similarly, total CD19 + B cells, including naïve as well as <lb/>memory B cells, showed a higher MFI with RE-click when <lb/>compared to RA-click (Supplemental Figures 4C, D). Next, <lb/>we examined the intracellular location of the accumulated <lb/>retinoid probes. Hereto, naïve B cells were placed on <lb/>microscope slides upon probe incubation and analyzed <lb/>microscopically. Human naïve B cells treated with vehicle <lb/>control demonstrated low fluorescence intensity, whereas <lb/>incubation of the RE-and RA-click showed increased <lb/>fluorescent signal (Supplemental Figure 5). The RE-click <lb/>probe preferably located outside the nucleus (Figure 4E). The <lb/>RA-click was distributed evenly in most naïve B cells, while some <lb/>cells showed also accumulation of RA-click inside the nucleus <lb/>(Figure 4E). The number of cells with intra-nuclear probe <lb/>accumulation varied per donor. To examine whether the <lb/>probes were taken up by the cells, rather than non-specific <lb/>binding to the outer cell membrane, three dimensional analysis <lb/>was performed. Here, we found that both the RE-as the RA-click <lb/>were inside the cells, and had crossed the cell membrane <lb/>(Supplemental Videos 3 and 4). <lb/>Next, biological functionality of the clickable probes was <lb/>tested within naïve B lymphocytes. Hereto we first addressed <lb/>whether culture of human naïve B cells with T cell dependent <lb/>stimuli including aIgM antibodies, aCD40 antibodies and <lb/>interleukin-4 with the natural form of retinal or RA for 7 days <lb/>could affect CD38 expression. We observed that natural RA <lb/>induced upregulation of CD38 on naïve B lymphocytes, while its <lb/>substrate retinal had no effect (Figure 4F). In line, we observed <lb/>that both RA-click as well as natural RA induced CD38 <lb/>expression on naïve B cell in a similar fashion (Figures 4G, H). <lb/>For the induction of IgA on the cultured B cells in these <lb/>conditions we observed that both RA-click, as well as its natural <lb/>equivalent, increased the percentage and fluorescent intensity of <lb/>IgA on naïve B lymphocytes, however this was not significant <lb/>(Supplemental Figure 6). Taken together our data suggest that, <lb/>despite lacking ALDH activity, retinal and retinoic acid are taken <lb/>up by naïve B cells, and that RA induces CD38 expression in vitro. <lb/>Monocyte-Derived Dendritic Cells Convert <lb/>Retinal Into Retinoic Acid, and Increase B <lb/>Cell CD38 Expression <lb/>Since we observed that moDCs have the capacity to take up and <lb/>convert retinal into retinoic acid, we further addressed whether <lb/>dendritic cells can serve as a source of retinoic acid for naïve B cells <lb/>in vitro using the upregulation of CD38 as a read-out. To this end, <lb/>we set up a co-culture of naive B lymphocytes with moDCs and T <lb/>cell dependent stimuli including aIgM antibodies, aCD40 <lb/>antibodies and interleukin-4 with for 9 days. These co-cultures <lb/>were carried out in Vitamin A deficient medium as regular FCS-<lb/>supplemented medium contains retinal, which allowed us to <lb/>analyse the effect of the addition of retinal in the absence or <lb/>presence of moDCs on B cells. As a positive control, RA was <lb/>supplemented to the moDC and B cell co-culture leading to <lb/>increased expression of CD38 (Figures 5A, B). Addition of <lb/>retinal resulted in enhanced CD38 expression only when moDCs <lb/>and naïve B cells were cultured together and not when naïve B cells <lb/>were cultured alone(Figures 5A, B). Overall, this data indicates that <lb/>human dendritic cells can convert retinal into retinoic acid, which <lb/>can be transferred to naïve B cells, leading to B cell differentiation. <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>In this study, we designed clickable probes which closely <lb/>resemble the natural homologues, allowing analysis of the <lb/>retinoid uptake within human immune cells. A protocol was <lb/>established to study retinoid probes in a wide variety biological <lb/>analysis systems, including flow cytometry and microscopy. As a <lb/>result, we observed that multiple immune cell populations <lb/>including monocytes, granulocytes, dendritic cells and B <lb/>lymphocytes take up retinoids, to varying degrees of intensity, <lb/>indicating that these probes address cell specific uptake of <lb/>vitamin A metabolites by immune cells. Human dendritic cells <lb/>and B lymphocytes were both able to internalize the retinoid <lb/>analogues. Although dendritic cells have the machinery to <lb/>convert retinal into retinoic acid, our data shows that B <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 3 | Clickable RA probe induces tolerogenic phenotype in monocyte-<lb/>derived dendritic cells. Monocytes were isolated from blood and differentiated <lb/>into monocyte-derived dendritic cells (moDCs) during 7 days of culture in the <lb/>presence of GM-CSF and IL-4 from 3 different donors. (A) Aldefluor positivity <lb/>and (B) CD103 expression in moDCs differentiated in the presence of natural <lb/>RA or RA click. Data are presented as mean± SD. Student&apos;s t test; ANOYA; <lb/>**p &lt; 0.01, ***p &lt; 0.001. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>lymphocytes do not express ALDH enzymes, which is in line <lb/>with earlier reports (39). Despite the incapability of B cells to <lb/>produce RA, IgA class switching by B lymphocytes is facilitated <lb/>by RA (11, 35). In addition to existing data, we now demonstrate <lb/>that human dendritic cells convert retinal and provide B <lb/>lymphocytes with retinoic acid resulting in the upregulation of <lb/>CD38 expression. This suggests that similar as has been shown <lb/>with mouse studies, also for human B lymphocytes RA steers <lb/>adaptive immune responses and that DCs can serve as an <lb/>exogenous source of RA to facilitate this process. <lb/>The visualization of lipid mediators at cellular levels has been <lb/>a challenge. Although mass spectrometry imaging protocols have <lb/>been optimized to detect small lipid mediators within cell <lb/>structures (40, 41), this requires specialized equipment, <lb/>specialized knowledge and is time consuming. To overcome <lb/>this problem, researchers have used the chemical process of <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>F <lb/>G <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>FIGURE 4 | Human naive B cells cannot produce retinoic acid, but are affected by exogenous retinoids to upregulate CD38 expression. Human naive B cells were <lb/>isolated from peripheral blood. (A) Representative dot plot of aldefluor positivity in naive B cells. DEAB reagent was used as a negative control. (B) Quantification of <lb/>aldefluor positivity in naive B cells from 3 different donors. (C) Representative histogram of the uptake of RE-click (pink) and RA-dick (blue) in naive B cells compared <lb/>to vehicle control (dotted line). (D) Quantification of the uptake of RE-click and RE-click in naive B cells compared to vehicle control from 3 different donors. <lb/>(E) Visualization of the RE-and RA-click using Azide-AF488 (green) with a nucleus staining (DAPI, blue) in naive B lymphocytes from 5 different donors. (F) Human <lb/>naive B cells were isolated from peripheral blood and cultured in the presence of T cell dependent (TD) stimuli for 7 days, including interleukin-4, anti-CD40 and anti-<lb/>IgM antibodies. Histogram of CD38 expression on B cells upon addition of unmodified retinal (green) or retinoic acid {grey) in comparison to vehicle control (dotted <lb/>line). (G) Histogram of CD38 expression upon culturing with RA-click (blue), its unmodified counterpart retinoic acid (grey) and vehicle control (dotted line) during 7 <lb/>day TC-dependent stimulation. (H) Quantification of CD38 expression upon culturing with the RA-click, its unmodified counterpart retinoic acid and vehicle control <lb/>from 4 different donors. Data are presented as mean ± SD. ANOVA; *p &lt; 0.05. ns indicates p &gt; 0.05. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>copper(I)-catalyzed azide-alkyne cycloaddition to a variety of <lb/>lipid structures including fatty acids and cholesterols (42-45). <lb/>Previously, we developed an activity-based probe with alkyne <lb/>click handle to visualize and quantify ALDH activity (27). In line, <lb/>we now succeeded in chemically adjusting retinal and retinoid <lb/>acid, enabling their visualization in flow cytometry and <lb/>microscopy approaches and showing similar functionality <lb/>compared to their natural counterpart. Nevertheless, the <lb/>retinoid probes have two practical limitations, which we did <lb/>not further elaborate on during this study. We observed that <lb/>concentrations between 100 -1000 nM of retinoid probes in <lb/>moDCs result in significant uptake, while this was not obvious at <lb/>the concentration 1 -10 nM, during an incubation time of 1 <lb/>hour. To quantify physiological relevant concentrations of our <lb/>probes, longer incubation times might be required. However, <lb/>upon longer incubation with the probes at 37°C, we observed <lb/>that the probes were metabolized as the fluorescence intensity <lb/>signal decreased when incubation time was extended. Yet, when <lb/>incubated at 4°C the uptake of the probes increased when cells <lb/>were incubated for 4 hours, compared to 1 hour. This is in line <lb/>with a report stating that therapeutically administered retinoic <lb/>acid is metabolized in patients in a period of 30-40 min (46). <lb/>Moreover, we experienced that the chemical clicking process of <lb/>the fluorescent label affected fluorescent intensity of some <lb/>commercially available antibodies, making it difficult to <lb/>combine retinoid visualization with additional markers. To <lb/>circumvent this, immune populations were isolated using <lb/>magnetic beads or flow cytometry sorting prior to the chemical <lb/>clicking method, to allow assessment of uptake within specific <lb/>subsets without using additional fluorescent antibodies. <lb/>However, copper-mediated click chemistry has been <lb/>successfully combined with immunofluorescence by others (47, <lb/>48). One study demonstrated that specific fluorophores are <lb/>copper-resistant, such as td Tomato, allowing to combine <lb/>conventional staining with copper-mediated chemistry (47). <lb/>Consequently, additional studies are required to determine <lb/>which fluorescently labelled antibodies can withstand copper-<lb/>mediated chemistry to combine click-chemistry with flow <lb/>cytometry in future studies. <lb/>It is uncertain whether retinoids passively diffuse into cells <lb/>because of their hydrophobic properties, or whether it is a process <lb/>that requires specific receptors or transporters. Transport of the <lb/>vitamin A derivative retinol in the periphery takes place when <lb/>coupled to serum transport proteins, such as retinol binding protein <lb/>4 (RBP4) (31), and uptake is facilitated by a receptor expressed on <lb/>target cells (31). We questioned whether the uptake of our clickable <lb/>probes in moDCs, required any carrier proteins. However, we <lb/>observed that the probes were still efficiently internalized when <lb/>the incubations were performed with PBS buffer lacking any further <lb/>supplementation, meaning that the clickable retinoids had no access <lb/>to any transport proteins. This suggests that clickable probes were <lb/>not internalized via transport proteins. Moreover, it is also unlikely <lb/>that clickable retinoids entered immune cells in our experiments via <lb/>the retinoic acid 6 (STRA6) receptor, which has been described to be <lb/>involved in retinol uptake, as unbound retinoids cannot be <lb/>transported via STRA6 (49, 50). Others have proposed that <lb/>uptake of free retinoids is reliant on passive diffusion facilitated by <lb/>their size and hydrophobic properties (32-34). However, passive <lb/>diffusion would be an inconvenient mechanism as free retinoids are <lb/>highly toxic to cells (51, 52). Furthermore, we demonstrated that <lb/>both the RE-and RA-click probes can efficiently be taken up when <lb/>incubated on ice, suggesting that no active metabolism is required <lb/>for the internalization. Although it may not be an ATP-dependent <lb/>mechanism, we did observe that only half of the moDCS <lb/>internalized RA-click, suggesting that the uptake of retinoids is <lb/>not based purely on passive diffusion but rather on other <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>FIGURE 5 | Monocyte-derived dendritic cells convert retinal into retinoic acid, and increase B cell CD38 expression. Naive B cells and monocyte-derived dendritic <lb/>cells were co-cultured in vitamin A deficient medium in the presence of TD-dependent stimuli for 9 days, including interleukin-4, anti-CD40 and anti-IgM antibodies. <lb/>As a negative control naive B cells and monocyte-derived dendritic cells were co-cultured with vehicle alone. (A) Representative histogram of CD38 expression on <lb/>naive B cells supplemented with natural retinal (green) or RA (black) during the 9 day coculture. Vehicle treatment is indicated with the dotted line. As a negative <lb/>control, cocultures were treated with vehicle alone (dotted line). (B) Quantification CD38 mean fluorescent intensity of naive B cells supplemented with unmodified retinal <lb/>(green), RA (black) or vehicle treated cells (white) from 4 separate experiments with individual blood donors (n=4). Data are presented as mean ± SD. ANOVA; **p &lt; 0.01. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>mechanism such as facilitated diffusion or by binding to specific <lb/>receptors. The clickable retinoid probes will allow to further study <lb/>this mechanism at more detail. <lb/>We demonstrated that human peripheral B lymphocytes do not <lb/>possess ALDH enzymatic activity, but rely on DCs for RA <lb/>production. In the human gut, CD103 + ALDH + DCs are residing <lb/>within the lamina propria near the epithelium (53, 54). It was <lb/>demonstrated that human epithelial cells induce tolerogenic <lb/>properties in monocyte-derived DCs in vitro (24). Moreover, <lb/>mouse studies demonstrated that insufficient development of LP <lb/>tolerogenic DCs due to insufficient vitamin A metabolism, leads to <lb/>an impaired capacity to facilitate mucosal IgA class switching (11, <lb/>12, 55, 56). The effect of RA for IgA expression within human B cells <lb/>has been demonstrated by others (57). Yet, within this study neither <lb/>our probes, nor natural RA, were able to significantly induce IgA <lb/>class switching within B lymphocytes in vitro. This might be due to <lb/>slightly different variations in the protocols, which we did not <lb/>further explore. Tolerogenic DCs are migratory cells and have <lb/>been observed to travel from the LP into the MLNs using CCR7 <lb/>(58). It was reported in mice that these LP-derived DCs influence <lb/>the expression of the gut homing receptor a4b7 on T cells within <lb/>the MLNs, using retinoic acid (9, 58-60). Similarly, tolerogenic DCs <lb/>reside within human MLNs and have the ability to induce a4b7 <lb/>expression on T cells (10, 24). Therefore, we postulate that human <lb/>tolerogenic DCs produce RA and are involved in the induction of <lb/>IgA class switching locally within the LP, but also in mucosal <lb/>lymphoid tissues such as the MLNs. <lb/>Thus, in this study, we provide user friendly clickable retinoid <lb/>probes, which can be used to visualize and examine functionality <lb/>of retinoids in a wide variety biological systems. We demonstrate <lb/>that multiple human immune populations have the capacity to <lb/>internalize retinoids to varying degrees. Naïve B lymphocytes <lb/>cannot metabolize retinoids themselves because they lack <lb/>ALDH1 activity, and thus rely on additional cells for RA <lb/>production. We showed that human DCs provide RA to B <lb/>cells, leading to upregulation of CD38. Together with existing <lb/>data based on mouse studies, these observations support that <lb/>human DCs facilitate adaptive B cell immunity in a retinoic acid <lb/>dependent manner. Taken together, our data provide valuable <lb/>insight into the mechanism behind vitamin A metabolism and <lb/>the importance of retinoids for human adaptive immunity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT <lb/>The raw data supporting the conclusions of this article will be <lb/>made available by the authors, without undue reservation. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">AUTHOR CONTRIBUTIONS <lb/>AB wrote the manuscript, performed experiments and analysed <lb/>the data. MNE performed experiments. SK designed, synthesized <lb/>and validated the retinoid probes. MS, ME, and RM supervised <lb/>the experiments and analyses. All authors contributed to the <lb/>article and approved the submitted version. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING <lb/>This project received funding from the Institute for Chemical <lb/>Immunology (ICI) and Oncode Institute. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIAL <lb/>The Supplementary Material for this article can be found online at: <lb/>https://www.frontiersin.org/articles/10.3389/fimmu.2021.671283/ <lb/>full#supplementary-material <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Huang Z, Liu Y, Brand D, Zheng SG. Role of Vitamin A in the Immune <lb/>System. J Clin Med (2018) 7(9). doi: 10.3390/jcm7090258 <lb/>2. Aibana O, Franke MF, Huang CC, Galea JT, Calderon R, Zhang Z, et al. <lb/>Impact of Vitamin A and Carotenoids on the Risk of Tuberculosis <lb/>Progression. Clin Infect Dis (2017) 65(6):900-9. doi: 10.1093/cid/cix476 <lb/>3. Thorne-Lyman A, Fawzi WW. Vitamin A Supplementation, Infectious <lb/>Disease and Child Mortality: A Summary of the Evidence. Nestle Nutr Inst <lb/>Workshop Ser (2012) 70:79-90. doi: 10.1159/000337445 <lb/>4. Goodman DW, Huang HS, Shiratori T. Tissue Distribution and Metabolism <lb/>of Newly Absorbed Vitamin a in the Rat. J Lipid Res (1965) 6:390-6. doi: <lb/>10.1016/S0022-2275(20)39309-3 <lb/>5. Thomas S, Prabhu R, Balasubramanian KA. Retinoid Metabolism in the Rat <lb/>Small Intestine. Br J Nutr (2005) 93(1):59-63. doi: 10.1079/BJN20041306 <lb/>6. Sandell LL, Sanderson BW, Moiseyev G, Johnson T, Mushegian A, Young K, <lb/>et al. RDH10 is Essential for Synthesis of Embryonic Retinoic Acid and Is <lb/>Required for Limb, Craniofacial, and Organ Development. Genes Dev (2007) <lb/>21(9):1113-24. doi: 10.1101/gad.1533407 <lb/>7. Duester G, Mic FA, Molotkov A. Cytosolic Retinoid Dehydrogenases Govern <lb/>Ubiquitous Metabolism of Retinol to Retinaldehyde Followed by Tissue-<lb/>Specific Metabolism to Retinoic Acid. Chem Biol Interact (2003) 143-<lb/>144:201-10. doi: 10.1016/S0009-2797(02)00204-1 <lb/>8. Molenaar R, Knippenberg M, Goverse G, Olivier BJ, de Vos AF, O&apos;Toole T, <lb/>et al. Expression of Retinaldehyde Dehydrogenase Enzymes in Mucosal <lb/>Dendritic Cells and Gut-Draining Lymph Node Stromal Cells is Controlled <lb/>by Dietary Vitamin A. J Immunol (2011) 186(4):1934-42. doi: 10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.1001672 <lb/>9. Coombes JL, Siddiqui KR, Arancibia-Carcamo CV, Hall J, Sun CM, Belkaid Y, <lb/>et al. A Functionally Specialized Population of Mucosal CD103+ Dcs Induces <lb/>Foxp3+ Regulatory T Cells Via a TGF-beta and Retinoic Acid-Dependent <lb/>Mechanism. J Exp Med (2007) 204(8):1757-64. doi: 10.1084/jem.20070590 <lb/>10. Jaensson E, Uronen-Hansson H, Pabst O, Eksteen B, Tian J, Coombes JL, et al. <lb/>Small Intestinal CD103+ Dendritic Cells Display Unique Functional <lb/>Properties That are Conserved Between Mice and Humans. J Exp Med <lb/>(2008) 205(9):2139-49. doi: 10.1084/jem.20080414 <lb/>11. Mora JR, Iwata M, Eksteen B, Song SY, Junt T, Senman B, et al. Generation of Gut-<lb/>Homing Iga-Secreting B Cells by Intestinal Dendritic Cells. Science (2006) 314 <lb/>(5802):1157-60. doi: 10.1126/science.1132742 <lb/>12. Villablanca EJ, Wang S, de Calisto J, Gomes DC, Kane MA, Napoli JL, et al. <lb/>MyD88 and Retinoic Acid Signaling Pathways Interact to Modulate <lb/>Gastrointestinal Activities of Dendritic Cells. Gastroenterology (2011) 141 <lb/>(1):176-85. doi: 10.1053/j.gastro.2011.04.010 <lb/>13. Bono MR, Tejon G, Flores-Santibanez F, Fernandez D, Rosemblatt M, <lb/>Sauma D. Retinoic Acid as a Modulator of T Cell Immunity. Nutrients <lb/>(2016) 8(6). doi: 10.3390/nu8060349 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>14. Ross AC, Chen Q, Ma Y. Vitamin A and Retinoic Acid in the Regulation of B-<lb/>cell Development and Antibody Production. Vitam Horm (2011) 86:103-26. <lb/>doi: 10.1016/B978-0-12-386960-9.00005-8 <lb/>15. Iwata M, Hirakiyama A, Eshima Y, Kagechika H, Kato C, Song SY. Retinoic <lb/>Acid Imprints Gut-Homing Specificity on T Cells. Immunity (2004) 21 <lb/>(4):527-38. doi: 10.1016/j.immuni.2004.08.011 <lb/>16. Svensson M, Johansson-Lindbom B, Zapata F, Jaensson E, Austenaa LM, <lb/>Blomhoff R, et al. Retinoic Acid Receptor Signaling Levels and Antigen Dose <lb/>Regulate Gut Homing Receptor Expression on CD8+ T Cells. Mucosal <lb/>Immunol (2008) 1(1):38-48. doi: 10.1038/mi.2007.4 <lb/>17. Pantazi E, Marks E, Stolarczyk E, Lycke N, Noelle RJ, Elgueta R. Cutting Edge: <lb/>Retinoic Acid Signaling in B Cells Is Essential for Oral Immunization and <lb/>Microflora Composition. J Immunol (2015) 195(4):1368-71. doi: 10.4049/ <lb/>jimmunol.1500989 <lb/>18. Goverse G, Olivier BJ, Molenaar R, Knippenberg M, Greuter M, Konijn T, <lb/>et al. Vitamin A Metabolism and Mucosal Immune Function Are Distinct <lb/>Between BALB/c and C57BL/6 Mice. Eur J Immunol (2015) 45(1):89-100. doi: <lb/>10.1002/eji.201343340 <lb/>19. Lee JM, Jang YS, Jin BR, Kim SJ, Kim HJ, Kwon BE, et al. Retinoic Acid <lb/>Enhances Lactoferrin-Induced IgA Responses by Increasing Betaglycan <lb/>Expression. Cell Mol Immunol (2016) 13(6):862-70. doi: 10.1038/cmi.2015.73 <lb/>20. Molenaar R, Greuter M, van der Marel AP, Roozendaal R, Martin SF, Edele F, et al. <lb/>Lymph Node Stromal Cells Support Dendritic Cell-Induced Gut-Homing of T <lb/>Cells. J Immunol (2009) 183(10):6395-402. doi: 10.4049/jimmunol.0900311 <lb/>21. Hammerschmidt SI, Ahrendt M, Bode U, Wahl B, Kremmer E, Forster R, et al. <lb/>Stromal Mesenteric Lymph Node Cells Are Essential for the Generation of <lb/>Gut-Homing T Cells In Vivo. J Exp Med (2008) 205(11):2483-90. doi: <lb/>10.1084/jem.20080039 <lb/>22. Agace WW, Persson EK. How Vitamin A Metabolizing Dendritic Cells are <lb/>Generated in the Gut Mucosa. Trends Immunol (2012) 33(1):42-8. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.it.2011.10.001 <lb/>23. Bakdash G, Vogelpoel LT, van Capel TM, Kapsenberg ML, de Jong EC. <lb/>Retinoic Acid Primes Human Dendritic Cells to Induce Gut-Homing, IL-10-<lb/>producing Regulatory T Cells. Mucosal Immunol (2015) 8(2):265-78. doi: <lb/>10.1038/mi.2014.64 <lb/>24. Iliev ID, Spadoni I, Mileti E, Matteoli G, Sonzogni A, Sampietro GM, et al. Human <lb/>Intestinal Epithelial Cells Promote the Differentiation of Tolerogenic Dendritic Cells. <lb/>Gut (2009) 58(11):1481-9. doi: 10.1136/gut.2008.175166 <lb/>25. Kim MJ, Jeong EK, Kwon EY, Joo JY, Lee JY, Choi J. Human CD103(+) Dendritic <lb/>Cells Promote the Differentiation of Porphyromonas Gingivalis Heat Shock Protein <lb/>Peptide-Specific Regulatory T Cells. J Periodontal Implant Sci (2014) 44(5):235-41. <lb/>doi: 10.5051/jpis.2014.44.5.235 <lb/>26. Roe MM, Swain S, Sebrell TA, Sewell MA, Collins MM, Perrino BA, et al. <lb/>Differential Regulation of CD103 (Alphae Integrin) Expression in Human <lb/>Dendritic Cells by Retinoic Acid and Toll-like Receptor Ligands. J Leukoc Biol <lb/>(2017) 101(5):1169-80. doi: 10.1189/jlb.1MA0316-131R <lb/>27. Koenders STA, Wijaya LS, Erkelens MN, Bakker AT, van der Noord VE, van <lb/>Rooden EJ, et al. Development of a Retinal-Based Probe for the Profiling of <lb/>Retinaldehyde Dehydrogenases in Cancer Cells. ACS Cent Sci (2019) 5 <lb/>(12):1965-74. doi: 10.1021/acscentsci.9b01022 <lb/>28. Lambertin F, Wende M, Quirin MJ, Taran M, Delmond B. New Retinoid <lb/>Analogs From Delta-Pyronene, a Natural Synthon. Eur J Org Chem (1999) <lb/>1999(6):1489-94. doi: 10.1002/(SICI)1099-0690(199906)1999:6&lt;1489::AID-<lb/>EJOC1489&gt;3.0.CO;2-1 <lb/>29. Barua AB, Furr HC. Properties of Retinoids -Structure, Handling, and <lb/>Preparation. Mol Biotechnol (1998) 10(2):167-82. doi: 10.1007/BF02760863 <lb/>30. Babler JH, Coghlan MJ, Feng M, Fries P. Facile Synthesis of 4-Acetoxy-2-<lb/>Methyl-2-Butenal, a Vitamin-a Precursor, From Isoprene Chlorohydrin. J Org <lb/>Chem (1979) 44(10):1716-7. doi: 10.1021/jo01324a030 <lb/>31. Kawaguchi R, Yu J, Honda J, Hu J, Whitelegge J, Ping P, et al. A Membrane <lb/>Receptor for Retinol Binding Protein Mediates Cellular Uptake of Vitamin a. <lb/>Science (2007) 315(5813):820-5. doi: 10.1126/science.1136244 <lb/>32. Harrison EH. Mechanisms Involved in the Intestinal Absorption of Dietary <lb/>Vitamin A and Provitamin A Carotenoids. Biochim Et Biophys Acta-Mol Cell <lb/>Biol Lipids (2012) 1821(1):70-7. doi: 10.1016/j.bbalip.2011.06.002 <lb/>33. Kawaguchi R, Zhong M, Kassai M, Ter-Stepanian M, Sun H. Vitamin A <lb/>Transport Mechanism of the Multitransmembrane Cell-Surface Receptor Stra6. <lb/>Membranes (Basel) (2015) 5(3):425-53. doi: 10.3390/membranes5030425 <lb/>34. Blomhoff R. Transport and Metabolism of Vitamin a. Nutr Rev (1994) 52(2 Pt <lb/>2):S13-23. doi: 10.1111/j.1753-4887.1994.tb01382.x <lb/>35. Seo GY, Jang YS, Kim HA, Lee MR, Park MH, Park SR, et al. Retinoic Acid, <lb/>Acting as a Highly Specific IgA Isotype Switch Factor, Cooperates With TGF-<lb/>beta1 to Enhance the Overall IgA Response. J Leukoc Biol (2013) 94(2):325-<lb/>35. doi: 10.1189/jlb.0313128 <lb/>36. Roy B, Brennecke AM, Agarwal S, Krey M, Duber S, Weiss S. An Intrinsic <lb/>Propensity of Murine Peritoneal B1b Cells to Switch to IgA in Presence of <lb/>TGF-beta and Retinoic Acid. PloS One (2013) 8(12):e82121. doi: 10.1371/ <lb/>journal.pone.0082121 <lb/>37. Morikawa K, Nonaka M. All-Trans-Retinoic Acid Accelerates the Differentiation <lb/>of Human B Lymphocytes Maturing Into Plasma Cells. Int Immunopharmacol <lb/>(2005) 5(13-14):1830-8. doi: 10.1016/j.intimp.2005.06.002 <lb/>38. Gerco den Hartog TvO, Vos M, Meijer B, Savelkoul H, van Neerven J, <lb/>Brugman G. BAFF Augments IgA2 and IL-10 Production by TLR7/8 <lb/>Stimulated Total Peripheral Blood B Cells. Eur J Immunol (2018) 48:483-92. <lb/>39. Vsianska P, Bezdekova R, Kryukov F, Almasi M, Pour L, Penka M, et al. <lb/>Activity of Aldehyde Dehydrogenase in B-cell and Plasma Cell Subsets of <lb/>Monoclonal Gammopathy Patients and Healthy Donors. Eur J Haematol <lb/>(2017) 98(1):19-25. doi: 10.1111/ejh.12779 <lb/>40. Fincher JA, Jones DR, Korte AR, Dyer JE, Parlanti P, Popratiloff A, et al. Mass <lb/>Spectrometry Imaging of Lipids in Human Skin Disease Model Hidradenitis <lb/>Suppurativa by Laser Desorption Ionization From Silicon Nanopost Arrays. Sci <lb/>Rep (2019) 9:ARTN 17508. doi: 10.1038/s41598-019-53938-0 <lb/>41. Tobias F, Olson MT, Cologna SM. Mass Spectrometry Imaging of <lb/>Lipids: Untargeted Consensus Spectra Reveal Spatial Distributions in <lb/>Niemann-Pick Disease Type C1. J Lipid Res (2018) 59(12):2446-55. doi: <lb/>10.1194/jlr.D086090 <lb/>42. Thiele C, Papan C, Hoelper D, Kusserow K, Gaebler A, Schoene M, et al. <lb/>Tracing Fatty Acid Metabolism by Click Chemistry. ACS Chem Biol (2012) 7 <lb/>(12):2004-11. doi: 10.1021/cb300414v <lb/>43. Robichaud PP, Poirier SJ, Boudreau LH, Doiron JA, Barnett DA, Boilard E, <lb/>et al. On the Cellular Metabolism of the Click Chemistry Probe 19-Alkyne <lb/>Arachidonic Acid. J Lipid Res (2016) 57(10):1821-30. doi: 10.1194/jlr.M067637 <lb/>44. Gaebler A, Milan R, Straub L, Hoelper D, Kuerschner L, Thiele C. Alkyne <lb/>Lipids as Substrates for Click Chemistry-Based In Vitro Enzymatic Assays. <lb/>J Lipid Res (2013) 54(8):2282-90. doi: 10.1194/jlr.D038653 <lb/>45. Hannoush RN, Arenas-Ramirez N. Imaging the Lipidome: Omega-Alkynyl <lb/>Fatty Acids for Detection and Cellular Visualization of Lipid-Modified <lb/>Proteins. ACS Chem Biol (2009) 4(7):581-7. doi: 10.1021/cb900085z <lb/>46. Jing J, Nelson C, Paik J, Shirasaka Y, Amory JK, Isoherranen N. Physiologically <lb/>Based Pharmacokinetic Model of All-trans-Retinoic Acid With Application to <lb/>Cancer Populations and Drug Interactions. J Pharmacol Exp Ther (2017) 361 <lb/>(2):246-58. doi: 10.1124/jpet.117.240523 <lb/>47. Gaebler A, Penno A, Kuerschner L, Thiele C. A Highly Sensitive Protocol for <lb/>Microscopy of Alkyne Lipids and Fluorescently Tagged or Immunostained <lb/>Proteins. J Lipid Res (2016) 57(10):1934-47. doi: 10.1194/jlr.D070565 <lb/>48. Soethoudt M, Stolze SC, Westphal MV, van Stralen L, Martella A, van Rooden <lb/>EJ, et al. Selective Photoaffinity Probe That Enables Assessment of <lb/>Cannabinoid Cb2 Receptor Expression and Ligand Engagement in Human <lb/>Cells. J Am Chem Soc (2018) 140(19):6067-75. doi: 10.1021/jacs.7b11281 <lb/>49. Golczak M, Maeda A, Bereta G, Maeda T, Kiser PD, Hunzelmann S, et al. <lb/>Metabolic Basis of Visual Cycle Inhibition by Retinoid and Nonretinoid <lb/>Compounds in the Vertebrate Retina. J Biol Chem (2008) 283(15):9543-54. <lb/>doi: 10.1074/jbc.M708982200 <lb/>50. Kawaguchi R, Yu J, Ter-Stepanian M, Zhong M, Cheng G, Yuan Q, et al. <lb/>Receptor-Mediated Cellular Uptake Mechanism That Couples to Intracellular <lb/>Storage. ACS Chem Biol (2011) 6(10):1041-51. doi: 10.1021/cb200178w <lb/>51. Maeda A, Maeda T, Golczak M, Chou S, Desai A, Hoppel CL, et al. Involvement <lb/>of All-Trans-Retinal in Acute Light-Induced Retinopathy of Mice. J Biol Chem <lb/>(2009) 284(22):15173-83. doi: 10.1074/jbc.M900322200 <lb/>52. Maeda A, Maeda T, Golczak M, Palczewski K. Retinopathy in Mice Induced by <lb/>Disrupted All-Trans-Retinal Clearance. J Biol Chem (2008) 283(39):26684-93. doi: <lb/>10.1074/jbc.M804505200 <lb/>53. Magnusson MK, Brynjolfsson SF, Dige A, Uronen-Hansson H, Borjesson LG, <lb/>Bengtsson JL, et al. Macrophage and Dendritic Cell Subsets in IBD: ALDH+ Cells <lb/>are Reduced in Colon Tissue of Patients With Ulcerative Colitis Regardless of <lb/>Inflammation. Mucosal Immunol (2016) 9(1):171-82. doi: 10.1038/mi.2015.48 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>54. Watchmaker PB, Lahl K, Lee M, Baumjohann D, Morton J, Kim SJ, et al. <lb/>Comparative Transcriptional and Functional Profiling Defines Conserved <lb/>Programs of Intestinal DC Differentiation in Humans and Mice. Nat Immunol <lb/>(2014) 15(1):98-108. doi: 10.1038/ni.2768 <lb/>55. McDonald KG, Leach MR, Brooke KW, Wang C, Wheeler LW, Hanly EK, <lb/>et al. Epithelial Expression of the Cytosolic Retinoid Chaperone Cellular <lb/>Retinol Binding Protein II Is Essential for In Vivo Imprinting of Local Gut <lb/>Dendritic Cells by Lumenal Retinoids. Am J Pathol (2012) 180(3):984-97. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.ajpath.2011.11.009 <lb/>56. Jijon HB, Suarez-Lopez L, Diaz OE, Das S, De Calisto J, Parada-kusz M, et al. <lb/>Intestinal Epithelial Cell-Specific RARalpha Depletion Results in Aberrant <lb/>Epithelial Cell Homeostasis and Underdeveloped Immune System. Mucosal <lb/>Immunol (2018) 11(3):703-15. doi: 10.1038/mi.2017.91 <lb/>57. Seo GY, Jang YS, Kim J, Choe J, Han HJ, Lee JM, et al. Retinoic Acid Acts as a <lb/>Selective Human IgA Switch Factor. Hum Immunol (2014) 75(8):923-9. doi: <lb/>10.1016/j.humimm.2014.06.021 <lb/>58. Jang MH, Sougawa N, Tanaka T, Hirata T, Hiroi T, Tohya K, et al. CCR7 Is <lb/>Critically Important for Migration of Dendritic Cells in Intestinal Lamina <lb/>Propria to Mesenteric Lymph Nodes. J Immunol (2006) 176(2):803-10. doi: <lb/>10.4049/jimmunol.176.2.803 <lb/>59. Johansson-Lindbom B, Svensson M, Pabst O, Palmqvist C, Marquez G, <lb/>Forster R, et al. Functional Specialization of Gut CD103+ Dendritic Cells in <lb/>the Regulation of Tissue-Selective T Cell Homing. J Exp Med (2005) 202 <lb/>(8):1063-73. doi: 10.1084/jem.20051100 <lb/>60. Sun CM, Hall JA, Blank RB, Bouladoux N, Oukka M, Mora JR, et al. Small <lb/>Intestine Lamina Propria Dendritic Cells Promote De Novo Generation of <lb/>Foxp3 T Reg Cells Via Retinoic Acid. J Exp Med (2007) 204(8):1775-85. doi: <lb/>10.1084/jem.20070602 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of Interest: The authors declare that the research was conducted in the <lb/>absence of any commercial or financial relationships that could be construed as a <lb/>potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

			<front>Copyright © 2021 Bos, Erkelens, Koenders, van der Stelt, van Egmond and Mebius. <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution License (CC BY). The use, distribution or reproduction in other forums is <lb/>permitted, provided the original author(s) and the copyright owner(s) are credited and <lb/>that the original publication in this journal is cited, in accordance with accepted <lb/>academic practice. No use, distribution or reproduction is permitted which does not <lb/>comply with these terms. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Bos et al. <lb/>Click-Chemistry Visualizes Retinoids in Immunity <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Frontiers in Immunology | www.frontiersin.org <lb/>July 2021 | Volume 12 | Article 671283 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 </page>


	</text>
</tei>