<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_pone.0003353"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		
			<front> Rapid Chromosome Evolution in Recently Formed <lb/>Polyploids in Tragopogon (Asteraceae) <lb/> K. Yoong Lim 1 , Douglas E. Soltis 2 , Pamela S. Soltis 3 , Jennifer Tate 4 , Roman Matyasek 5 , Hana Srubarova 5 , <lb/>Ales Kovarik 5 , J. Chris Pires 6 , Zhiyong Xiong 6 , Andrew R. Leitch 1  * <lb/> 1 School of Biological and Chemical Sciences, Queen Mary College, University of London, London, United Kingdom, 2 Department of Botany and the Genetics Institute, <lb/>University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, United States of America, 3 Florida Museum of Natural History and the Genetics Institute, University of Florida, Gainesville, Florida, <lb/>United States of America, 4 Massey University, Institute of Molecular Biosciences, Palmerston North, New Zealand, 5 Institute of Biophysics, Academy of Sciences of the <lb/>Czech Republic, Brno, Czech Republic, 6 Division of Biological Sciences, Life Sciences Center, University of Missouri, Columbia, Missouri, United States of America <lb/> Abstract <lb/> Background:  Polyploidy, frequently termed &apos;&apos;whole genome duplication&apos;&apos;, is a major force in the evolution of many <lb/>eukaryotes. Indeed, most angiosperm species have undergone at least one round of polyploidy in their evolutionary history. <lb/>Despite enormous progress in our understanding of many aspects of polyploidy, we essentially have no information about <lb/>the role of chromosome divergence in the establishment of young polyploid populations. Here we investigate synthetic <lb/>lines and natural populations of two recently and recurrently formed allotetraploids Tragopogon mirus and T. miscellus <lb/> (formed within the past 80 years) to assess the role of aberrant meiosis in generating chromosomal/genomic diversity. That <lb/>diversity is likely important in the formation, establishment and survival of polyploid populations and species. <lb/> Methodology/Principal Findings:  Applications of fluorescence in situ hybridisation (FISH) to natural populations of T. mirus <lb/> and T. miscellus suggest that chromosomal rearrangements and other chromosomal changes are common in both <lb/>allotetraploids. We detected extensive chromosomal polymorphism between individuals and populations, including (i) <lb/>plants monosomic and trisomic for particular chromosomes (perhaps indicating compensatory trisomy), (ii) intergenomic <lb/>translocations and (iii) variable sizes and expression patterns of individual ribosomal DNA (rDNA) loci. We even observed <lb/>karyotypic variation among sibling plants. Significantly, translocations, chromosome loss, and meiotic irregularities, <lb/>including quadrivalent formation, were observed in synthetic (S 0 and S 1 generations) polyploid lines. Our results not only <lb/>provide a mechanism for chromosomal variation in natural populations, but also indicate that chromosomal changes occur <lb/>rapidly following polyploidisation. <lb/> Conclusions/Significance:  These data shed new light on previous analyses of genome and transcriptome structures in de <lb/>novo and establishing polyploid species. Crucially our results highlight the necessity of studying karyotypes in young <lb/>(,150 years old) polyploid species and synthetic polyploids that resemble natural species. The data also provide insight <lb/>into the mechanisms that perturb inheritance patterns of genetic markers in synthetic polyploids and populations of young <lb/>natural polyploid species. <lb/> Citation: Lim KY, Soltis DE, Soltis PS, Tate J, Matyasek R et al. (2008) Rapid Chromosome Evolution in Recently Formed Polyploids in Tragopogon <lb/> (Asteraceae). PLoS ONE 3(10): e3353. doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353 <lb/> Editor: Samuel P. Hazen, University of Massachusetts Amherst, United States of America <lb/> Received July 3, 2008; Accepted September 8, 2008; Published October 9, 2008 <lb/> Copyright: ß 2008 Lim et al. This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits unrestricted <lb/>use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original author and source are credited. <lb/> Funding: The authors thank NERC, Grant Agency of the Czech Republic (521/07/0116), and the USA National Science Foundation (grants MCB-0346437, DEB-<lb/>0608268, DBI 0638536 and DBI 0501712) for support. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of <lb/>the manuscript. <lb/> Competing Interests: The authors have declared that no competing interests exist. <lb/>* E-mail: a.r.leitch@qmul.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<body> Introduction <lb/> Polyploidy has played a major role in generating angiosperm <lb/>biodiversity. Chromosome counts suggest that between 30 and <lb/>80% of angiosperm species are polyploid, while genomic studies of <lb/>selected model and crop species reveal evidence of extensive <lb/>ancient genome-wide multiplications. Indeed recent genomic <lb/>investigations indicate that most, if not all, angiosperm species <lb/>have undergone at least one genome duplication event in their <lb/>evolutionary history, and several have evidence of multiple <lb/>polyploidy-diploidisation-polyploidy cycles [1,2,3]. <lb/>Angiosperm genomes are astonishingly plastic in their ability to <lb/>tolerate considerable karyotypic (e.g. chromosome number <lb/>variation, translocations), genetic (mutations, retroelement trans-<lb/>positon, deletions) and epigenetic (DNA methylation, histone <lb/>methylation/acetylation) variability. This tolerance enables poly-<lb/>ploids to form and establish and has contributed significantly to <lb/>their widespread occurrence [4]. Large-scale genetic changes <lb/>induced by polyploidy are thought to influence the transcriptome, <lb/>metabolome and proteome, which can concomitantly alter the <lb/>phenotype and ecology of the individuals. Most of the new genetic <lb/>changes are probably maladaptive, but in a few rare instances <lb/>individuals arise that are able to outcompete the parental diploids <lb/>or colonize new niches. <lb/>There are several examples of recent speciation via polyploidy <lb/>that occurred within the last 150 years: Spartina anglica [5], Senecio <lb/></body>

			<front> PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></front>
			
			<page>1 <lb/></page>
			
			<front>October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></front>

			<body>cambrensis and S. eboracensis [6], Cardamine schulzii [7], Tragopogon <lb/>mirus and T. miscellus [8]. Studies on the genetic consequences of <lb/>allopolyploidy in these de novo polyploid species reveal some <lb/>significant differences. In S. anglica allopolyploidy induced few <lb/>changes in genome structure, but there is epigenetic reprogramming <lb/>[5,9], while in Senecio [10,11] and Tragopogon [12] allopolyploids there <lb/>are substantial genetic changes including loss of sequence (genomic <lb/>DNA profiles) and perturbations to the transcriptome (cDNA <lb/>profiles). However, little attention has been paid to the chromosomal <lb/>content of any of these allopolyploids, and it is unknown what <lb/>mechanisms drive the observed genetic changes. For example, <lb/>genetic change could be driven by local mutation, small-scale <lb/>deletion or insertion of a particular sequence, or via major <lb/>chromosomal changes, including whole-arm transposition and <lb/>chromosome losses or duplications. Because there is little or no <lb/>understanding of chromosomal variation in these recently formed, <lb/>natural polyploids, we have embarked on a characterization of <lb/>karyotypic variation between individuals and populations of the two <lb/> Tragopogon allopolyploids from North America. <lb/> Tragopogon mirus and T. miscellus have proved to be excellent <lb/>evolutionary model systems for understanding early allopolyploid <lb/>formation. These allopolyploids are derived from three diploid <lb/>progenitors (each 2n = 2x = 12), T. pratensis, T. porrifolius and T. <lb/>dubius, the latter being shared by both allopolyploids (T. mirus <lb/> derived from T. dubius6T. porrifolius, 2n = 4x = 24; T. miscellus <lb/> derived from T. dubius6T. pratensis, 2n = 4x = 24, Figure 1) [13]. <lb/>The diploid parents of both polyploids are in well separated clades <lb/>[14] and are not closely related based on ITS/ETS sequences, <lb/>allozymes and other genetic markers [15,16]. There are many <lb/>reports of natural F 1 hybrids involving these diploids and we have <lb/>also produced them in the glasshouse, but these hybrids are highly <lb/>sterile suggesting minimal homeologue pairing at meiosis [8]. In <lb/>contrast the allopolyploids T. mirus and T. miscellus are fertile and <lb/>expanded their ranges rapidly after their initial formations, in large <lb/>part via multiple origins [17]. The two allotetraploids now occupy <lb/>a large geographic area of eastern Washington and adjacent <lb/>Idaho, USA, and comprise many thousands of individuals in <lb/>several populations. Molecular analyses have revealed that T. mirus <lb/> has recurrently formed at least 13 times and T. miscellus possibly as <lb/>many as 21 times [13,16,18,19,20, Symonds et al. unpubl.,21], <lb/>reviewed in Soltis et al. [8]. Furthermore, there are genetic <lb/>differences between populations of each tetraploid, most of which <lb/>likely reflect variation found in the diploids and inherited in the <lb/>polyploid populations through recurrent formation, and others of <lb/>which may have arisen through subsequent divergence of the <lb/>polyploids. Examples of the latter include the divergence of rRNA <lb/>gene copy number, sequence homogeneity and expression patterns <lb/>[22,23]. Here we show that population differences are also <lb/>reflected in substantial variability in karyotypes among individuals, <lb/>differences that appear correlated with irregular meiosis. <lb/> Results <lb/> Genome structure of Tragopogon allotetraploids <lb/> The chromosome sizes, numbers and centromere indices are <lb/>similar between the parental diploid species, and three tandem <lb/>repeats characterized by us do not generate differences in <lb/>chromosomal distribution. For these reasons we are unable to <lb/>identify the parental origin of the chromosomes in the derived <lb/>allotetraploid species via morphology alone [24]. We therefore <lb/> Figure 1. Tragopogon triangle with the flowers of the diploid  Tragopogon  species at the apices of the triangle. The flowers of the <lb/>polyploids T. miscellus and T. mirus are shown between their respective diploid parents. The synthetic polyploid described here has the same parents <lb/>as T. mirus. <lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g001 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>2 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			used FISH with total genomic DNA probes (called Genomic In <lb/>Situ Hybridization or GISH) to determine the genomic compo-<lb/>sition of karyotypes of T. mirus and T. miscellus individuals (Figures 2 <lb/>and 3). We analysed 12 plants, nine of T. mirus from three <lb/>populations (Table 1) and three of T. miscellus, two from one <lb/>population and a third individual from a second population <lb/>(Table 2). Five of these plants, including representatives of each <lb/>tetraploid, were chosen because we had previously observed <lb/>[22,23] that they had particular 45S nuclear ribosomal DNA (45S <lb/>rDNA) compositions and expression characteristics (Table 3). <lb/>GISH labelling enabled the genomic origin of the chromosomes to <lb/>be determined by fluorescence colour: digoxingenin-labelled <lb/>genomic DNA of T. dubius labelled chromosomes of T. dubius <lb/> origin green or yellow (D-genome) and biotin-labelled genomic <lb/>DNA of either T. pratensis (to T. miscellus) or T. porrifolius (to T. mirus) <lb/> labelled the P-genome (either T. pratensis or T. porrifolius) orange or <lb/>red. However, the distinction between genomes was only possible <lb/>after electronic merger of the images because there was <lb/>considerable cross-hybridisation of probes. The homologous group <lb/>assigned to each chromosome (A–F) was determined using size, <lb/>arm ratio, position of 5S and 45S rDNA, as described in Pires et <lb/>al. [24], and by using DAPI bright bands that were revealed after <lb/>denaturation in some metaphases. <lb/>Previous cytogenetic analyses revealed that both T. mirus and T. <lb/>miscellus had 24 chromosomes; aneuploidy has not been previously <lb/>reported in these taxa [13,24,25]. This chromosome number was <lb/>also observed here in all but one individual of T. mirus, which had 23 <lb/>chromosomes. It was assumed that GISH would partition the <lb/>chromosome sets into 12 chromosomes of T. dubius origin and 12 <lb/>chromosomes of either T. pratensis or T. porrifolius origin depending <lb/>on the tetraploid being analysed. However, only four had an entirely <lb/>balanced additive karyotype of that expected from the chromosomes <lb/>of the diploid parents (Tables 1 and 2 and Figures 2 and 3). We were <lb/>surprised to observe that five of the eight T. mirus karyotypes and two <lb/>of the three T. miscellus karyoypes with 2n = 24 chromosomes had <lb/>unbalanced genomic contributions. This was manifest by some <lb/>chromosomes occurring in one or three copies (monosomic and <lb/>trisomic, respectively; see Tables 1 and 2). In addition, four plants, <lb/>including individuals of both T. mirus and T. miscellus, carried <lb/>intergenomic translocations (Figures 2A, 3A, arrows). <lb/>The T. mirus individuals 2603-33A and 33B are siblings from <lb/>different flower heads of the same plant. Significantly, their <lb/>karyotypes exhibit substantial differences; 2603-33B has an <lb/>expected karyotype assuming complete additivity of parental <lb/>chromosome sets, while 2603-33A is monosomic for chromosome <lb/>F du and trisomic for chromosome E po . <lb/> Meiotic and mitotic aberrations in synthetic <lb/>reconstruction of T. mirus <lb/> Meiosis in newly formed, synthetic allotetraploids (S 0 and S 1 ) <lb/>(see Figure 1) was examined to determine if meiotic aberrations <lb/>occurred in early allotetraploid generations and could be a source <lb/>of genomic imbalance observed in root tip metaphases. Meiotic <lb/>cells of developing anthers at diplotene were analysed (Figure 4). <lb/>In many instances regular bivalent formation occurred (Figure 4A), <lb/>although frequently bivalents overlapped (Figure 4C, D), making it <lb/>difficult to be certain if they were in fact multivalents. However, in <lb/>a number of cases resolution was sufficient to determine the <lb/>presence of quadrivalents (Figure 4B). Using GISH, the genomic <lb/>origin of the chromosomes could be resolved, although the <lb/>distinction was less clear than at metaphase. Figures 4E–F show <lb/>GISH labelling of a quadrivalent with two chromosomes of T. <lb/>dubius origin and two chromosomes of T. porrifolius origin physically <lb/>linked via chiasma in a large, twisted ring. <lb/>An analysis of root tip metaphases in 12 allotetraploids of the <lb/>subsequent S 1 generation revealed one plant that was 2n = 23, the <lb/>rest were 2n = 24, as expected. There were cytogenetic abnormalities <lb/>in two additional plants. One of these plants (73-14) had unusually <lb/>large 45S rDNA loci occurring on both copies of chromosome A du <lb/> (Figure 5 A, B). This plant also had an rDNA locus on chromosome <lb/>A po of T. porrifolius origin, but the expected site on chromosome D po <lb/> was absent. The second plant (134-16-3) had a translocation of T. <lb/>porrifolius origin to chromosome C du . Since there is no missing <lb/>chromosome segment of T. porrifolius origin, it must be assumed that <lb/>this was a non-reciprocal translocation induced during the preceding <lb/>meiosis (Figure 5 C, D, E). <lb/> 45S rDNA decondensation <lb/> Previous cytogenetic analyses of diploid Tragopogon species <lb/>revealed that T. dubius and T. pratensis carry a 45S rDNA locus <lb/>on chromosome A du and A pr , respectively, while T. porrifolius has <lb/>two loci on chromosomes A po and D po . To determine if these sites <lb/>were inherited in the respective allotetraploid species we used <lb/>FISH with digoxigenin-labelled probe pTa71 (yellow fluorescence, <lb/>Figures 2 and 3). In T. miscellus, 45S rDNA loci occur on <lb/>chromosomes A du and A pr (Figure 3). At metaphase both <lb/>chromosomes carried secondary constrictions (Table 3). In T. <lb/>mirus, 45S rDNA loci occur on chromosomes A du , A po , and D po <lb/> (Figure 2). These loci were also frequently identifiable after GISH <lb/>labeling, without the use of the rDNA probe pTa71, appearing <lb/>with a brighter green (to T. dubius origin loci) or yellow <lb/>fluorescence (Figure 2). In all cells, both mitotic and meiotic, the <lb/>number of 45S loci and their parental distribution were as <lb/>expected, i.e. pairing and segregation of rDNA-carrying chromo-<lb/>somes is probably regular. This was not the case, however, for 5S <lb/>rDNA-carrying chromosomes (5S probe, red fluorescence). We <lb/>would expect T. mirus to carry 5S rDNA loci on chromosomes A du , <lb/>A po and F po . But here we observed one T. mirus individual (2602-<lb/>03-10) trisomic for chromosome F po and each of these chromo-<lb/>somes carried a single 5S rDNA locus (Figure 2). It was a surprise <lb/>that the chromosomes carrying the 45S rDNA were balanced <lb/>because at diplotene they were frequently in close proximity <lb/>(Figure 4 E, F), probably reflecting transcriptional activity and <lb/>nucleolar function. The absence of aberrant numbers of 45S <lb/>rDNA-carrying chromosomes at metaphase suggests that they <lb/>paired regularly at meiosis. <lb/>An analysis of 45S rDNA-carrying chromosomes in 14 <lb/>diplotene nuclei of T. mirus revealed that chromosome A du was <lb/>always associated with the nucleolus (Figure 4E–H). Often this <lb/>chromosome was associated with a chromosome from the T. <lb/>porrifolius genome (when identifiable it was chromosome D po , <lb/>Figure 4G, H). Similar results were observed at metaphase <lb/>(Table 3, Figure 2), where chromosome A du and sometimes <lb/>chromosome D po carried secondary constrictions (the exception is <lb/>plant 2603-33A–below). In contrast, chromosome A po was always <lb/>condensed and unassociated with the nucleolus. Interestingly, in <lb/>two individuals of population 2602 only one of the two <lb/>homologues of chromosome A du carried secondary constrictions. <lb/>In plant 2603-33A, there was no secondary constriction on <lb/>chromosome A du and the 45S rDNA locus was unusually small. <lb/>Instead, chromosome D po had a secondary constriction. Similarly <lb/>in two synthetic T. mirus, plants 134-16-3 and 73-14, there were <lb/>secondary constrictions on A du and A po , with the locus on <lb/>chromosome D po missing in the latter individual (Figure 5 A, C). <lb/>In natural T. mirus and T. miscellus, the presence of secondary <lb/>constrictions correlated well with patterns of condensation/ <lb/>decondensation at interphase (Figure 2D, E); for example, <lb/>chromosomes A po and D po have no secondary constrictions in <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>3 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			Figure 2. (A-C) Karyotype analyses of  T. mirus  from individuals in three populations (A) 2601, (B) 2603 and (C) 2602. Homeologous <lb/> chromosome group nomenclature (A-F) follows Ownbey and McCollum [25] and Pires et al. [24]. Fluorochrome colours: yellow/green (FITC, <lb/>digoxigenin-labelled probes), orange/red (Cy3, biotin-labelled probes), blue (DAPI staining). Each karyotype is shown with DAPI staining, sometimes <lb/>also simultaneously labelled for 45S rDNA (yellow fluorescence) or 5S rDNA (red fluorescence), and after GISH with T. dubius (green fluorescence) and <lb/> T. porrifolius (red fluorescence) total genomic DNA probes. Monosomic or trisomic chromosomes are underlined. Note: (1) intergenomic <lb/>translocations to chromosome C po/du (arrows) in individuals 2601-7 and 2601-8 and D du/po in individual 2602-0-3-4 (A). (2) The 45S rDNA locus on the <lb/>two homologues of chromosome A du in individuals 2602-4 and 2602-0-3-4 show different levels of decondensation, one being condensed and the <lb/>other with a secondary constriction (C). (3) A large reduction in size of the 45S rDNA locus on chromosome A du of individual 2603-33A (#) compared <lb/>with other individuals (D). (4) No secondary constrictions of 45S rDNA loci on T. porrifolius origin chromosomes (A po , D po ) in individual 2603-33B. (D-E) <lb/>Root-tip interphase nuclei of T. mirus after FISH with digoxigenin-labelled pTa71 for 45S rDNA. (D) Individual 2601-4, showing four large condensed <lb/>45S rDNA loci (arrows) and (E) Individual 2602-0-3-10 with two large condensed 45S rDNA loci (arrows). Scale bar (top right) is 10 mm. <lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g002 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note>

			T. mirus 2601-4 (not shown) and exhibit four sites of condensed <lb/>rDNA chromatin (Figure 2D) while in T. mirus (2602-0-3-10) <lb/>chromosome A po is without a secondary constriction (Figure 2C) <lb/>and at interphase there are two highly condensed rDNA loci <lb/>(Figure 2E). <lb/> Southern blot analysis of 5S rDNA loci <lb/> Given the imbalance observed in the inheritance of individual <lb/>chromosomes, we would expect the copy number of 5S rDNA units <lb/>to vary among plants. For example, individual 2602-3-10, showing <lb/>trisomy of the F po chromosome, had seven 5S rDNA signals instead <lb/>of the expected six (Figure 2C). On the other hand, if there was F po <lb/> monosomy, we might expect a reduction in gene copy numbers. <lb/>Using Southern blot hybridisation, we determined the parental T. <lb/>porrifolius/T. dubius 5S rRNA gene copy number ratio in the progeny <lb/>of a single T. mirus plant, 2602-0-3. Several progeny were studied, <lb/>including those analysed by GISH (plants 2602-0-3-10 and 2602-0-<lb/>3-4). To ascertain the parental origin of the 5S rDNA units, we <lb/>digested genomic DNA with TaqI restriction enzyme. This enzyme <lb/>takes advantage of a restriction site present in T. porrifolius units that is <lb/>not found in T. dubius units. Consequently, after digestion the T. <lb/>porrifolius 5S rDNA was digested mostly to monomers while there was <lb/>little digestion of T. dubius units that remained at high molecular <lb/>weight (Figure 6). In T. mirus, the 5S rDNA probe used for Southern <lb/>hybridisation revealed signals from both parental gene families. <lb/>However, the distribution of signal intensities between genes of T. <lb/>porrifolius and genes of T. dubius origin differed between progeny. For <lb/>example, the trisomic individual 2602-0-3-10 had a T. porrifolius/T. <lb/>dubius 5S rDNA unit ratio close to 1.0, while the &apos;&apos;normal&apos;&apos; disomic <lb/>plant 2602-0-3-4 had a ratio that was 0.82. Thus, trisomy of <lb/>chromosome F po resulted in an approximately 10% increase in the <lb/>number of 5S genes in the genome. This value is in a good <lb/>theoretical agreement with the expected increase in number of 5S <lb/>arrays from six to seven (per diploid cell). Three other plants (2602-0-<lb/>3-5, -7 and -8) had a 5S rDNA gene ratio corresponding to a trisomic <lb/>genotype, suggesting meiotic aberrations were frequent in this <lb/>lineage. On the other hand, two plants (2602-0-3-2 and -3) had a <lb/>decreased number of T. porrifolius genes compared with the <lb/>expectation (plant 2602-0-3-4, with balanced chromosomal sets). <lb/>Perhaps these two individuals are monosomic for F po . <lb/> Discussion <lb/> Effectiveness of GISH <lb/> Phylogenetic analyses of internal (ITS) and external transcribed <lb/>spacer (ETS) sequences of nuclear 45S rDNA suggest that the <lb/>diploid progenitors of both T. mirus and T. miscellus are distantly <lb/>related, with T. dubius in one major clade of Tragopogon and both T. <lb/>pratensis and the populations of T. porrifolius that served as parents <lb/>in another major clade [26,27]. Earlier allozyme studies also <lb/>suggested that the three diploid progenitors were well differenti-<lb/>ated genetically [16,28]. Likewise, comparisons of cDNA-AFLP <lb/>genetic markers between the diploid species reveal that T. pratensis <lb/> and T. dubius share only between 30-40% of markers [12], again <lb/>suggesting considerable genomic divergence. <lb/>Recently, Markova et al. [29] used GISH with genomic DNA <lb/>probes from diploid species of Silene onto metaphases of related <lb/>diploids to show that labeling strength was inversely correlated to <lb/>genetic distance, i.e. there was strongest labeling to the most <lb/>closely related species. Given these data and an apparently large <lb/> Figure 3. (A–C) Karyotype analyses of  T. miscellus  from two <lb/>populations (A) 2604 and (B) 2605. Homeologous chromosome <lb/>group nomenclature (A–F) follows Ownbey and McCollum [25] and <lb/>Pires et al. [24]. Fluorochrome colours and probes are as in Figure 2 <lb/>except that biotinylated T. pratensis genomic DNA was used in GISH <lb/>experiments. Monosomic and trisomic chromosomes are underlined. <lb/>Note in (A) that there is a large intergenomic translocation, <lb/>chromosome A du/pr (arrow). Scale bar (top right) is 10 mm. <lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g003 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note>

			genetic distance between Tragopogon diploids, we might expect <lb/>GISH to work effectively on the derived allopolyploids. Instead, <lb/>we observed that it worked rather weakly, with much cross-<lb/>hybridisation of probes, and the genomic distinction was only <lb/>resolvable after electronic merging of images. Indeed previously <lb/>we had reported that GISH had not worked at all in Tragopogon <lb/> [24]. Our success here is due to improved quality of the electronics <lb/>on the microscope&apos;s camera and improved facilities to electron-<lb/>ically merge images using Openlab software, but it remains an <lb/>enigma why GISH does not work more effectively in T. mirus and <lb/> T. miscellus. <lb/> rDNA inheritance and expression patterns <lb/> We expect T. miscellus to inherit two 45S rDNA loci (carried on <lb/>chromosome A du from T. dubius and A pr from T. pratensis), while T. <lb/>mirus inherits three loci (carried on chromosomes A du from T. <lb/>dubius and A po and D po from T. porrifolius). The observations of <lb/>only two 45S rDNA in synthetic T. mirus 73-14 (Figure 5A, B) can <lb/>be explained in one of two ways. First, the enlargement of the <lb/>rDNA locus on chromosome A du and the locus loss on D po <lb/> occurred through an rDNA translocation/fusion involving the loci <lb/>on D po and A du . However, given that the karyotype is balanced <lb/>and the material is the S 1 generation, this scenario seems unlikely <lb/>because it would suggest the union of two gametes carrying the <lb/>same abnormality, or arising via restitution of segregating <lb/>chromosomes in meiosis II. The second and alternative explana-<lb/>tion is that the rDNA locus number may reflect the situation in the <lb/> T. porrifolius parent used for the cross, although our past analyses of <lb/> T. porrifolius never revealed such a polymophism [24]. Unfortu-<lb/>nately the precise T. porrifolius parent used in the cross is now <lb/>deceased (the plants are annuals or biennials), preventing us from <lb/>determining which of the competing hypotheses is correct. <lb/>Previously we showed that natural Tragopogon allopolyploids also <lb/>do not have fixed patterns of 45S rDNA inheritance, with some <lb/>individuals showing a balanced distribution of rDNA sequences <lb/>originating from each of the parental diploids and some showing <lb/>biased inheritance, typically with the number of rDNA units from <lb/> T. dubius being underrepresented [22]. However, from molecular <lb/>studies it was not clear whether non-Mendelian rDNA inheritance <lb/>was caused by a decrease in copy number (elimination) or unit <lb/>replacement (e.g. via homogenisation mechanisms). In one <lb/>individual of T. mirus, 2603-33 (referred to here as 2603-33A), <lb/> Table 1. Karyotype organisation of individuals of T. mirus from three populations (localities of each population are indicated in <lb/>column 1). <lb/> T. mirus  population <lb/>Plant number <lb/>Chromosome No. (2n) <lb/>Nature of karyotype imbalance <lb/>Translocations <lb/> T. dubius  origin <lb/> T. porrifolius  origin <lb/> 2601 Pullman, Washington <lb/>4 <lb/>24 <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>– <lb/>7 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>2 6C  po/du <lb/> 8 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>3 6B  du <lb/> 16C po <lb/> 16C po/du <lb/> 2602 Palouse, Washington <lb/>0-3-4 <lb/>23 <lb/>E <lb/>16C po <lb/> 16D du/po <lb/> 0-3-10 <lb/>24 <lb/>16C du <lb/> 36E po <lb/> – <lb/>16D du <lb/> 36F po <lb/> 4 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>1 6F  du <lb/> 36F po <lb/> – <lb/>2603 Rosalia, Washington <lb/>33A <lb/>24 <lb/>16F du <lb/> 36E po <lb/> – <lb/>33B <lb/>24 <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>– <lb/>2 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>– <lb/>The parental origins of the chromosomes were determined by GISH. Chromosome nomenclature of homeologous groups (A–F) followed Ownbey and McCollum [25] <lb/>and Pires et al. [24]. Superscript letters indicate the genome origins of the chromosomes, du = T. dubius, po = T. porrifolius. Chromosomes carrying translocations are <lb/>indicated by naming the chromosome according to the genomic origins of the centromeres, followed by the genome origins of the translocated segments. E-indicates <lb/>chromosome set as expected from the diploid parents. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.t001 <lb/> Table 2. Karyotype organisation of individuals of T. miscellus from two populations (localities of each population are indicated in <lb/>column 1). <lb/> T. miscellus  population <lb/>Plant number <lb/>Chromosome No . (2n) <lb/>Nature of karyotype imbalance <lb/>Translocations <lb/> T. dubius  origin <lb/> T. pratensis  origin <lb/> 2604 Moscow, Idaho <lb/>7 <lb/>24 <lb/>36F du <lb/> 16C pr <lb/> A pr/du <lb/> A du/pr <lb/> 2605 Pullman, Washington <lb/>3 <lb/>24 <lb/>E <lb/>E <lb/>– <lb/>14 <lb/>24 <lb/>16D du <lb/> 36E pr <lb/> – <lb/>The parental origins of the chromosomes were determined by GISH. Chromosome nomenclature of homeologous groups (A–F) followed Ownbey and McCollum [25] <lb/>and Pires et al. [24]. Superscript letters indicate the genome origins of the chromosomes, du = T. dubius, pr = T. pratensis. Chromosomes carrying translocations are <lb/>indicated as in Table 1. E-indicates parental chromosome set as expected from the diploid parent. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.t002 <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>6 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			there was a considerable reduction in the number of T. dubius units <lb/>(to ,100 copies/diploid) from an expectation of ,700 units (typical <lb/>number for any given tetraploid population). An analysis of this <lb/>individual&apos;s karyotype (Figure 2) revealed that the loss in copy <lb/>number can be accounted for by a reduction in the size of the rDNA <lb/>locus on chromosome A du . The sibling to this plant, 2603-33B, does <lb/>not show this rDNA copy number deletion. Therefore, the locus size <lb/>reduction in 2603-33A may have arisen from a deletion event <lb/>occurring as a consequence of meiotic instability in the parent. <lb/>Despite the relatively small size (perhaps only 100 copies/ <lb/>diploid of the 45S rDNA unit) of the T. dubius 45S rDNA locus, it <lb/>usually dominates rRNA expression in leaf material of T. mirus <lb/> [23]. Even in the 2603-33A individual, with extremely reduced <lb/>numbers of 45S rRNA genes of T. dubius origin, the locus accounts <lb/>for 97% of the rRNA transcripts (see also Table 3). Nevertheless, <lb/>in root-tip metaphases a secondary constriction is observed on <lb/>chromosome D po , suggesting some transcription of the T. porrifolius <lb/> locus occurs in that tissue, perhaps to compensate for the reduced <lb/>45S rDNA gene copy number when there is a high demand for <lb/>ribosomes in metabolically active meristematic cells. In plant <lb/>2603-33B, with substantially higher numbers of T dubius derived <lb/>45S rRNA genes, the units of T. dubius origin are transcribed, and <lb/>those rDNA units of T. porrifolius origin are silent [23]. This is <lb/>reflected in the lack of a secondary constriction at the rDNA locus <lb/>on chromosomes A po and D po in this individual (Figure 2, Table 3). <lb/>The presence of secondary constrictions correlates strongly with <lb/>levels of decondensation at interphase and almost certainly reflects <lb/>transcriptional activity at the preceding interphase. Two individ-<lb/>uals of T. mirus (2602-4 and 2602-0-3-4) show different <lb/>decondensation of the two A du homologues, probably reflecting <lb/>genetic or epigenetic differentiation between the two homologues. <lb/>In population 2605 of T. miscellus, all individuals investigated show <lb/>only partial dominance in the expression of rDNA units of T. <lb/>dubius origin over those of T. pratensis origin [23]. This is also seen <lb/> Table 3. Genomic origin of decondensed rDNA compared with previously published data from Kovarik et al. [22] and Matyasek et <lb/>al. [23] using genomic–cleaved amplified polymorphic sequence (g-CAP) and reverse transcription-cleaved amplified polymorphic <lb/>sequence (RT-CAP) to determine the genomic origin of rDNA sequences in the genome and the cDNA, respectively. <lb/> Population <lb/>Figure Number <lb/>Plant <lb/>number <lb/>decondensed <lb/>rDNA <lb/>condensed <lb/>rDNA <lb/>Parental origin of <lb/>genomic rDNA units <lb/>determined by g-CAPS <lb/>(% of  T. dubius  origin <lb/>units) <lb/>Parental origin of <lb/>expressed rDNA units <lb/>determined by RT-CAPS, <lb/>(% of  T. dubius  origin <lb/>rRNA transcripts) <lb/> T. mirus, 2601 Pullman, <lb/>Washington <lb/>Figure 2D (interphase <lb/>only shown) <lb/>0-4 <lb/>26A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 35 <lb/>99 <lb/>26D po <lb/> Figure 2A <lb/>0-7 <lb/>26A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 28 <lb/>94 <lb/>26D po <lb/> Figure 2A <lb/>0-8 <lb/>26A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 29 <lb/>96 <lb/>26D po <lb/> T. mirus, 2602 Palouse, <lb/>Washington <lb/>0-3-4 <lb/>16A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 40 <lb/>34 <lb/>26D po <lb/> 16A du <lb/> Figure 2C <lb/>0-3-10 <lb/>26A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 41 <lb/>4 <lb/>26D po <lb/> Figure 2C <lb/>0-4 <lb/>16A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 47 <lb/>50 <lb/>26D po <lb/> 16A du <lb/> T. mirus, 2603 Rosalia, <lb/>Washington <lb/>Figure 2B <lb/>33A <lb/>26D p <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 6 <lb/>9 7 <lb/>26A du (loci of <lb/>reduced size) <lb/>Figure 2C <lb/>33B <lb/>26A du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 27 <lb/>97 <lb/>26D po <lb/> 2 <lb/>2 6A  du <lb/> 26A po <lb/> 27 <lb/>99 <lb/>26D po <lb/> T. miscellus, 2604 <lb/>Moscow, Idaho <lb/>7 <lb/>2 6A  du <lb/> – <lb/>23 <lb/>100 <lb/>26A pr <lb/> T. miscellus, 2605 <lb/>Pullman, Washington <lb/>3 <lb/>2 6A  du <lb/> – <lb/>2 5 <lb/>5 4 <lb/>26A pr <lb/> 14 <lb/>26A du <lb/> – <lb/>n d <lb/>n d <lb/>26A pr <lb/> Ns–FISH image not shown <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.t003 <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>7 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			Figure 4. Pollen meiosis in synthetic  T. mirus.  (A,B) Feulgen staining showing in (A) 12 regular bivalents and (B) one quadrivalent (arrow) and <lb/>bivalents in close association with each other and a nucleolus. (C–H). Fluorochrome colours and GISH probes are as in Figure 2. (C–D) Note <lb/>chromosome A du in association with the nucleolus. Two bivalents, one from the T. dubius genome (yellow) and one from the T. porrifolius genome <lb/>(orange), overlapped (arrow), perhaps occurring as a multivalent. (E–F). Note the rDNA and the bivalents carrying these genes associated with the <lb/>nucleolus. A quadrivalent with two chromosomes of T. dubius origin and two of T. porrifolius origin occurring in a ring (arrow). (G–H) Note two <lb/>bivalents (A du and D po ) with rDNA associated with the nucleolus and the A po bivalent with condensed rDNA unassociated with the nucleolus. <lb/>N = nucleolus. Scale bar (C–H) is 10 mm. <lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g004 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>8 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			in the occurrence of secondary constrictions on both rDNA-<lb/>carrying chromosomes A du and A pr (Figure 3, Table 3). <lb/>An analysis of 45S rDNA evolution in Nicotiana polyploids <lb/>indicates that parental loci are initially maintained in young <lb/>polyploids, although the sequences within a locus may be subject <lb/>to concerted evolution, and over time frames of .1 million years <lb/>individual loci are lost [30]. In Tragopogon polyploids we do not <lb/>know which of the different karyotype variants will survive <lb/>selection and become fixed. Perhaps over longer evolutionary <lb/>timescales interlocus homogenisation and new rDNA variants will <lb/>occur and spread across all rDNA loci. <lb/>Our study shows that more than one pathway can lead to non-<lb/>Mendelian inheritance of rDNA units in allotetraploids: (i) <lb/>elimination or amplification of repeats within an array can occur <lb/>without changes in locus number (as in the case of 45S rDNA <lb/>locus in 2601-33A); (ii) a change in the number of rDNA-bearing <lb/>chromosomes (and loci) without any material change in the <lb/>number of genes at each locus (as with the 5S rDNA locus– <lb/>Figure 6); or (iii) a combination of both, although this situation was <lb/>not detected in this study. <lb/> Meiotic irregularities <lb/> The chromosome multiplication step of polyploidy is thought to <lb/>establish species isolation barriers between the newly formed <lb/>polyploid and its diploid parents, whilst providing a homologous <lb/>partner for each of the chromosomes. However, analyses of newly <lb/>synthesised allopolyploids reveal that early-generation individuals <lb/>are often infertile, or have highly reduced fertility, due to problems <lb/>with meiosis including irregular pairing of homologous chromo-<lb/>somes [31,32]. Selection for fecundity in synthetic polyploids is <lb/>associated with generation-by-generation increased fertility [32]. <lb/>Nevertheless even after many thousands of years of evolution, <lb/>meiotic irregularities can still occur, as observed in Triticum aestivum <lb/> (wheat), an allohexaploid where meiotic misdivision has been <lb/>exploited in the formation of wheat aneuploid lines [33,34]. <lb/>An analysis of meiosis in the newly synthesised Tragopogon <lb/> allotetraploids revealed the frequent occurrence of multivalents <lb/>(Figure 4). Such aberrant pairing patterns may result in imbalanced <lb/>chromosome contribution in subsequent generations as well as <lb/>intergenomic translocations. Both abnormalities were observed in <lb/>several of 12 synthetic (S 1 generation) T. mirus plants analysed at <lb/>metaphase. One plant was 2n = 23 and lacked a T. dubius <lb/> chromosome and one plant carried a non-reciprocal translocation <lb/>from a T. porrifolius chromosome to chromosome C du (Figure 5E) <lb/>Multivalents were also observed at a low frequency in natural <lb/>populations of T. mirus and T. miscellus [13] and in the few F 2 <lb/> plants resulting from diploid F 1 hybrids of Tragopogon [35]. Meiotic <lb/>abnormalities can cause unequal segregation of homeologous <lb/>chromosomes and are a likely driver of the chromosomal <lb/>imbalance between genomes observed in both Tragopogon allote-<lb/>traploids. The two sibling plants of T. mirus 2603-33 had different <lb/>karyoypes: one had a balanced karyotype of 12 chromosomes from <lb/>each parental genome (2603-33B), while the other (2603-33A) was <lb/>monosomic for chromosome F du and trisomic for chromosome <lb/>E po . Given these data, it is likely that the parent plant had a <lb/>balanced karyotype, and meiotic irregularities, probably arising <lb/>through multivalent formation, gave rise to the imbalanced <lb/>karyotype of plant 2603-33A. <lb/>Multivalent pairing can arise either through (1) synapsis and <lb/>recombination between homeologous chromosomes in meiosis I, <lb/> Figure 5. Analyses of root tip metaphases of synthetic  T. mirus  (A, B is plant 73-14; C-E is plant 134-16-3). (A, C) Metaphase (merged <lb/>images) after FISH for 45S rDNA (red) and 5S rDNA (green) and counterstained with DAPI (blue). (B) and (D) Metaphases (merged images) from (A) and <lb/>(C), respectively, after reprobing using GISH with labeled genomic DNA from T. porrifolius (pink) and T. dubius (green) and counterstained with DAPI. <lb/>In (B) note the particularly there are only four 45S rDNA sites, the sites on A du. Chromosomes are particularly large (arrows) and the site expected on <lb/>chromosome D po is missing. In (D) note the T. porrifolius translocation to a T. dubius chromosome (red arrow) and the satellites to both A du <lb/> homologues are distant from the rest of the chromosome (see connecting white lines). (E) Karyotype of (D) revealing that the T. porrifolius origin <lb/>translocation is to chromosome C du and that no T. porrifolius chromosomes lack chromatin. Scale bar is 10 mm. <lb/> doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g005 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note>

			or (2) synapsis between chromosomes carrying intergenomic <lb/>translocations. Four out of 12 mitotic karyotypes in plants from <lb/>natural populations had intergenomic translocations visible at <lb/>mitotic metaphase following GISH (Tables 2 and 3), and <lb/>additional smaller translocations, not resolvable by GISH, may <lb/>also be present. Nevertheless, the quadrivalent indicated in <lb/>Figure 4F (see arrow) does not show intergenomic translocations <lb/>at the resolution obtained using GISH. Our analyses of plants <lb/>from different populations, although sample sizes were small, <lb/>showed that aberrant chromosome numbers were more prevalent <lb/>for certain chromosome types. For example, chromosome A was <lb/>not involved in any of the aneuploidy evetns detected, whereas <lb/>chromosome F accounted for almost 40% of all subgenomic <lb/>chromosome imbalances. There might be several explanations for <lb/>these results. First the homology between F-type chromosomes <lb/>may be larger than between other chromosomes. It is likely that <lb/>the greater sequence and morphological similarities between <lb/>homeologous chromosomes, the more likely there will be home-<lb/>ologous and multivalent pairing. In support of this, Nicolas et al. <lb/> [36] observed in Brassica napus haploid hybrids that chromosomes <lb/>with the highest synteny had the highest frequency of home-<lb/>ologous pairing. Nevertheless, in T. mirus, the presence of a 5S <lb/>rDNA locus on F po but not on F du indicates some divergence <lb/>between the homeologues. Secondly, all chromosomes may be <lb/>equally likely to form multivalents, but aberration in copy number <lb/>of some chromosomes, e.g. homeologous group A, may not be <lb/>favored by selection. <lb/>The surprisingly high incidence of trisomy and monosomy in <lb/>highly fertile plants with 2n = 24 suggests that &apos;&apos;compensating <lb/>trisomy&apos;&apos; may be operating in natural populations of both <lb/> Tragopogon allotetraploids. Compensating trisomy was first de-<lb/>scribed by Blakeslee [37] to refer to a situation in which the loss of <lb/>a normal chromosome is compensated by the presence of the two <lb/>arms in new translocated associations (secondary chromosomes). <lb/>That concept was extended to include the replacement of the <lb/>primary chromosome by two tertiary chromosomes, or by a <lb/>secondary and a tertiary chromosome [38]. Compensatory trisomy <lb/>has been reported in Datura stramonium from progeny of a plant <lb/>exposed to radium [37,38], and from crops, including from Poales <lb/>[39,40] and tomato [41]; all were produced experimentally [42]. <lb/>The putative compensatory trisomy observed here may be an <lb/>example from natural plants. <lb/>The allotetraploids T. mirus and T. miscellus formed from their <lb/>diploid progenitors within the last 80 years (perhaps even within <lb/>the last 60 years) and given their biennial habit, the number of <lb/>generations to present is likely to be less than 40 [8]. The long-<lb/>term outcome of meiotic irregularities in these species is not easily <lb/>predicted. On the one hand, the genomic imbalance will reduce <lb/>fitness and perpetuate cycles of meiotic irregularities. This may <lb/>lead to a cascade of reduced fitness, generation upon generation. <lb/>Such a phenomenon was observed in synthetic Brassica allopoly-<lb/>ploids maintained by single seed descent [43]. In the wild, cryptic <lb/>karyotypic instability manifest by aberrant ratios of homeologous <lb/>chromosomes might ultimately lead to a slow reduction in fitness <lb/>and ultimately extinction. Perhaps this accounts for the loss of <lb/>some local populations of both T. mirus and T. miscellus [8] and of <lb/>some recently formed Senecio polyploid populations [6]. Nonethe-<lb/>less, it is noteworthy that despite meiotic irregularities in the initial <lb/>synthetic S 0 plants and subsequent S 1 generations, pollen fertility <lb/>and seed set were generally high in the synthetic Tragopogon <lb/> polyploid lines (Tate et al., in prep.). In addition, selection will <lb/>favour the most fertile individuals, likely to be those with the most <lb/>regular chromosome pairing. Thus, if the population can expand <lb/>through early bottlenecks of reduced fertility, the derived <lb/>populations are likely to be more fertile with regular bivalent <lb/>pairing. Certainly in well-established allotetraploids (10 4 –10 5 myrs <lb/>old), e.g. of Nicotiana and Triticum, no major imbalances in <lb/>chromosome numbers or the distribution of chromosomes to <lb/>subgenomes are normally observed [44,45]. <lb/> Genomic instability <lb/> The angiosperm genome is characterised by its plasticity to <lb/>genetic change, including large-scale chromosome number <lb/>changes, aneuploidy and polyploidy [4]. However, it may be <lb/>significant that in Tragopogon polyploids, all the imbalances in <lb/>parental chromosome dosages between individuals occurred <lb/>within a near-regular karyotype of 2n = 24 (one exception at <lb/>2n = 23). Given the frequency of plants showing genomic <lb/>imbalance we might expect to find more plants with unexpected <lb/> Figure 6. Genomic analysis of 5S rDNA repeats. (A) Southern blot <lb/>hybridisation of 5S rDNA probe to TaqI-digested genomic DNA of the <lb/>progeny of 2602-0-3 individual and diploid parental accessions. (B) <lb/>Quantitative representation of the parental 5S gene families deter-<lb/>mined by a phosphorimager scanning of radioactivity signals on blots <lb/>(three independent experiments). <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pone.0003353.g006 <lb/>
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note>

			chromosome numbers. Perhaps there is selection against plants <lb/>that deviate from 2n = 24 and against those that are nullisomic for <lb/>a particular chromosome, or perhaps our sample size was too <lb/>small to find a representative range of abnormalities. <lb/>GISH data revealed that in two out of three individuals of T. <lb/> miscellus and four of nine individuals of T. mirus, there is an imbalance <lb/>in the parental contribution of the chromosomes. However, the <lb/>imbalance observed resulted from monosomy or trisomy, and no <lb/>individual was nullisomic for a particular chromosome. An analysis <lb/>of 10 genes in T. miscellus using genomic and cDNA CAPS revealed <lb/>that 65% of individuals displayed losses of one of the two <lb/>homeologues and a further 5% of individuals showed silencing of <lb/>one of the two homeologues in leaves [12]. The missing alleles were <lb/>interpreted as sequences that had been stochastically eliminated <lb/>from the T. miscellus genome. The results here may suggest that <lb/>chromosome loss or non-reciprocal translocations may contribute to <lb/>the loss of alleles, although we did not find any example of a <lb/>homozygous deletion for a chromosome segment. The differential <lb/>expression of rDNA on the A du chromosomes of two T. mirus <lb/> individuals (Figure 2) points to epigenetic or genetic heterozygosity <lb/>between the homologous chromosomes. <lb/>Large-scale genetic changes caused by parental genome <lb/>imbalance will influence the inheritance of genetic markers, which <lb/>will in turn influence the transcriptome, proteome and metabo-<lb/>lome. Clearly genetic analyses of young or synthetic polyploids <lb/>require in-depth cytogenetic studies to assess the contribution that <lb/>chromosomal changes play in the inheritance of genetic markers. <lb/>Unfortunately in recent years that work has seldom been standard <lb/>practice. Such cytogenetic data are clearly needed even if <lb/>chromosome counts appear regular [see also 43], since a deeper <lb/>analysis of the genome and chromosome substructure can reveal <lb/>substantial chromosome dosage deviation from expectation. <lb/> Materials and Methods <lb/> Plant material <lb/> Seeds of Tragopogon were collected from natural populations in <lb/>Idaho (ID) and Washington (WA) (USA) (Table 1) and planted <lb/>either in a greenhouse at the Department of Botany, University of <lb/>Florida, or in field plots at the Institute of Biophysics, Academy of <lb/>Sciences of the Czech Republic, Brno. Root tips from young, <lb/>healthy, vigorously growing plants were harvested and placed in <lb/>ice cold and saturated aqueous 2mM 8-hydroxyquinoline (Sigma-<lb/>Aldrich Company Ltd, Poole, Dorset, UK). After 60 min <lb/>incubation on ice, the roots were fixed in ethanol-acetic acid <lb/>(3:1) at room temperature overnight (several washes) and stored in <lb/>the same solution at 220uC until use. Developing anthers of 1 mm <lb/>length or less, that contain diplotene nuclei, were excised from <lb/>young buds of length 1 cm or less. Root tip and meiotic material <lb/>were fixed in freshly prepared 3:1 ethanol: glacial acetic acid for <lb/>two days. Root tip material was then transferred to 90% ethanol at <lb/> 220uC for long-term storage. <lb/> Making synthetic Tragopogon allotetraploids <lb/> Descriptions of the methods used to generate synthetic polyploid <lb/>lines are given in detail in a separate paper reporting the formation <lb/>and availability of these lines for research (Tate et al. in prep). <lb/>Briefly, numerous repeated T. dubius6T. porrifolius crosses were <lb/>made, and seeds from successful crosses germinated on moist filter <lb/>paper. The chromosome number was doubled to resynthesise <lb/>polyploids that closely resemble T. mirus by placing seedlings with <lb/>fully emerged cotyledons in 0.1% or 0.25% colchicine solution <lb/>overnight. After washing with water for two-three days, the <lb/>seedlings were transferred to 2.5&apos;&apos; pots with soil (and grown in the <lb/>glasshouse at the University of Florida under standard conditions). <lb/>Plants coded N197-3.132-1 and N197-4.98-1 were used for <lb/>meiotic analyses (S 0 generation) and root tips of selfed progeny <lb/>(S 1 generation) analysed in root tip mitosis, metaphases of plants <lb/>coded 134-16-3 and 73-14 are shown. <lb/> Feulgen staining of meiotic cells <lb/> For meiotic squashes, small developing inflorescences (1 cm or <lb/>less in length) were collected from the greenhouse and fixed in 3:1 <lb/>(as above, for root tips). Individual anthers were then removed and <lb/>macerated in 60% glacial acetic acid, stained in aceto-orcein [46], <lb/>spread under a coverslip by warming over a naked flame, and <lb/>observed using a Zeiss Photomicroscope III. At least 15 meiotic <lb/>cells per plant were scored. <lb/> Preparing cell spreads for in situ hybridisation <lb/> Chromosome preparations for FISH, using either cloned probes or <lb/>total genomic DNA probes (called GISH) were made using <lb/>modifications of established methods [47,48]. Briefly, root tips or <lb/>developing anthers were digested in 0.3% (w/v) cellulase Onozuka R-<lb/>10 (Apollo Scientific Ltd, Stockport, Cheshire, UK), 0.3% (w/v) <lb/>pectolyase Y23 (MP Biomedicals, Solon, Ohio, USA) and 0.3% (w/v) <lb/>drieselase (Sigma-Aldrich Company Ltd., Poole, Dorset, UK) for <lb/>28 min and transferred to 1% citrate buffer for 2 h. The meristematic <lb/>cells behind the root cap were isolated in a drop of 60% acetic acid <lb/>and squashed onto a glass slide. For meiotic preparation, fixed <lb/>anthers were dissected and meiotic cells gently dispersed into a drop <lb/>of 60% acetic acid, a coverslip applied and gently warmed. Coverslips <lb/>were removed following freezing with dry ice. <lb/> In situ hybridisation <lb/>
			
			Fluorescence in situ hybridisation followed standard protocols, <lb/>Figures 2–4, Leitch et al. [48], Figure 5, Telgmann-Rauber et al. <lb/> [47]. Genomic DNA from T. dubius, T. pratensis, and T. porrifolius <lb/> for labelling by GISH was extracted using DNeasy Plant mini kit <lb/>(Qiagen Ltd, Crawley, West Sussex, UK) following manufacturer&apos;s <lb/>instructions. Genomic DNA was labelled with biotin-16 dUTP <lb/>(Sigma-Aldrich Company Ltd., Poole, Dorset, UK) or digox-<lb/>igenin-11-dUTP (GE Healthcare, Chalfont St Giles, Buckingham-<lb/>shire, UK) using nick translation following standard protocols. The <lb/>probe against 5S ribosomal DNA (rDNA) was prepared by <lb/>amplifying the gene using primers described in Fulnecek et al. [49] <lb/>and biotin-16-dUTP-labelling protocol as described in Leitch et al. <lb/>[48]. The probe against 45S rDNA was the clone pTa71, which <lb/>includes the 18-26S rDNA subunit isolated from Triticum aestivum, <lb/> which was labelled with digoxignenin-11-dUTP as described in <lb/>Leitch et al. [48]. Briefly, slides were denatured in 70% (v/v) <lb/>formamide in 26 SSC (0.3 M sodium chloride, 0.03 M sodium <lb/>citrate) at 70uC for 2 min and the hybridisation mix added <lb/>(4 mg.ml  21  labeled probes and 50% (v/v) formamide, 10% (w/v) <lb/>dextran sulphate, 0.1% (w/v) sodium dodecyl sulphate in 26 <lb/>SSC). In situ hybridisation was carried out overnight at 37uC, after <lb/>which the slides were given a stringent wash (20% (v/v) formamide <lb/>in 0.16 SSC at 42uC). Sites of probe hybridisation were detected <lb/>using 20 mg.ml  21  fluorescein-conjugated anti-digoxigenin IgG <lb/>(GE Healthcare, Chalfont St Giles, Buckinghamshire, UK) and <lb/>5 mg.ml  21  Cy3-conjugated avidin (Roche Pharmaceuticals, Lewes, <lb/>East Sussex, UK) in 46SSC containing 0.2% (v/v) Tween 20 and <lb/>5% (w/v) bovine serum albumin. Chromosomes were counter-<lb/>stained with 2 mg/ml DAPI (49,6-diamidino-2-phenylindole, <lb/>Sigma Aldrich Company Ltd., in 46 SSC) and stabilised in <lb/>Vectashield medium (Vector Laboratories Ltd, Peterborough, <lb/>UK) prior to data acquisition using either: 1) Leica DMRA2 <lb/>epifluorescent microscope fitted with an Orca ER camera and <lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>11 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/></note> 
			
			Open Lab softwareH (Improvision, Coventry, UK) (Figures 2–4) <lb/>or; 2) Olympus BX61 epiflurescent microscope using Olympus <lb/>Microsuite 5 softwareH (Olympus America Inc, Center Valley, PA, <lb/>USA) (Figure 5). The images were analysed with Adobe <lb/>PhotoshopH version 7 and treated for colour contrast and uniform <lb/>brightness only. At least 5 mitotic or meiotic cells per plant were <lb/>scored with each probe used. <lb/> Southern hybridisation <lb/> TaqI restriction enzyme digestion was carried out on genomic <lb/>DNA extracted from leaves using standard protocols [50] with <lb/>modifications as in [51]. After fractionation in 1% agarose by gel <lb/>electrophoresis, the DNA was transferred to a Hybond N+ <lb/>membrane (GE Healthcare, Chalfont St Giles, Buckinghamshire, <lb/>UK). The 32 P-labelled 5S rDNA probe was from a 120-bp XbaI/ <lb/>EcoRI fragment of 5S rDNA cloned from N. tabacum [49]. Probe <lb/>hybridisation was conducted under high-stringency conditions in <lb/>the Church-Gilbert hybridisation buffer at 65 uC overnight. The <lb/>radioactivity signals were quantified by phosphorimager scanning <lb/>(Storm, GE Healthcare, UK). <lb/>
		
		</body>
		
		<back>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgments <lb/> We thank Mr. R. Joseph for assistance. <lb/> Author Contributions <lb/> Conceived and designed the experiments: DS PS AK AL. Performed the <lb/>experiments: KYL DS JT RM HS ZX AL. Analyzed the data: KYL PS <lb/>RM HS AK CP ZX AL. Contributed reagents/materials/analysis tools: <lb/>DS PS AK CP AL. Wrote the paper: DS PS JT AK CP AL. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> 1. Blanc G, Wolfe KH (2004) 2004. Widespread paleopolyploidy in model plant <lb/>species inferred from age distributions of duplicate genes. Plant Cell 16: 1667–1678. <lb/>2. Bowers JE, Chapman BA, Rong R, Paterson AH (2003) Unravelling angiosperm <lb/>genome evolution by phylogenetic analysis of chromosomal duplication events. <lb/>Nature 422: 433–438. <lb/>3. Cui LY, Wall PK, Leebens-Mack JH, Lindsay BG, Soltis DE, et al. (2006) <lb/>Widespread genome duplications throughout the history of flowering plants. <lb/>Genome Research 16: 738–749. <lb/>4. Leitch AR, Leitch IJ (2008) Genomic plasticity and the diversity of polyploid <lb/>plants. Science 320: 481–483. <lb/>5. Ainouche ML, Baumel A, Salmon A (2004) Spartina anglica C. E. Hubbard: a <lb/>natural model system for analysing early evolutionary changes that affect <lb/>allopolyploid genomes. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 82: 475–484. <lb/>6. Abbott RJ, Lowe AJ (2004) Origins, establishment and evolution of two new <lb/>polyploid species: Senecio cambrensis and S. eboracensis in the British Isles. Biological <lb/>Journal of the Linnean Society 82: 467–474. <lb/>7. Urbanska KM, Hurka H, Landolt E, Neuffer B, Mummenhoff K (1997) <lb/>Hybridization and evolution in Cardamine (Brassicaceae) at Urnerboden, central <lb/>Switzerland: Biosystematic and molecular evidence. Plant Systematics and <lb/>Evolution 204: 233–256. <lb/>8. Soltis DE, Soltis PS, Pires JC, Kovarik A, Tate JA, et al. (2004) Recent and <lb/>recurrent polyploidy in Tragopogon (Asteraceae): cytogenetic, genomic, genomic <lb/>and genetic comparisons. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 82: 485–501. <lb/>9. Salmon A, Ainouche ML, Wendel JF (2005) Genetic and epigenetic <lb/>consequences of recent hybridization and polyploidy in Spartina (Poaceae). <lb/>Molecular Ecology 14: 1163–1175. <lb/>10. Abbott RJ, Ireland HE, Rogers HJ (2007) Population decline despite high <lb/>genetic diversity in the new allopolyploid species Senecio cambrensis (Asteraceae). <lb/>Molecular Ecology 16: 1023–1033. <lb/>11. Hegarty MJ, Barker GL, Wilson ID, Abbott RJ, Edwards KJ, et al. (2006) <lb/>Transcriptome shock after interspecific hybridization in Senecio is ameliorated by <lb/>genome duplication. Current Biology 16: 1652–1659. <lb/>12. Tate JA, Ni ZF, Scheen AC, Koh J, Gilbert CA, et al. (2006) Evolution and <lb/>expression of homeologous loci in Tragopogon miscellus (Asteraceae), a recent and <lb/>reciprocally formed allopolyploid. Genetics 173: 1599–1611. <lb/>13. Ownbey M (1950) Natural hybridisation and amphidiploidy in the genus <lb/> Tragopogon. American Journal of Botany 37: 487–499. <lb/>14. Buggs RJA, Soltis PS, Mavrodiev EV, Symonds VV, Soltis DE (2008) Does <lb/>phylogenetic distance between parental genomes govern the success of <lb/>polyploids? Castanea 73: 74–93. <lb/>15. Soltis DE, Mavrodiev EV, Doyle JJ, Rauscher J, Soltis PS (2008) ITS and ETS <lb/>sequence data and phylogenetic reconstruction in allopolyploids and hybrids. <lb/>Systematic Botany 33: 7–20. <lb/>16. Soltis PS, Plunkett GM, Novak SJ, Soltis DE (1995) Genetic variation in <lb/> Tragopogon species -additional origins of the allotetraploids T. mirus and T. <lb/>miscellus (Compositae). American Journal of Botany 82: 1329–1341. <lb/>17. Novak SJ, Soltis DE, Soltis PS (1991) Ownbey&apos;s Tragopogons: Forty years later. <lb/>American Journal of Botany 78: 1586–1600. <lb/>18. Cook LM, Soltis PS, Brunsfeld SJ, Soltis DE (1998) Multiple independent <lb/>formations of Tragopogon tetraploids (Asteraceae): evidence from RAPD <lb/>markers. Molecular Ecology 7: 1293–1302. <lb/>19. Soltis DE, Soltis PS (1989) Allopolyploid speciation in Tragopogon -Insights from <lb/>chloroplast DNA. American Journal of Botany 76: 1119–1124. <lb/>20. Soltis PS, Soltis DE (1991) Multiple origins of the allotetraploid Tragopogon mirus <lb/> (Compositae) -rDNA evidence. Systematic Botany 16: 407–413. <lb/>21. Soltis DE, Soltis PS (1995) The dynamic nature of polyploid genomes. <lb/>Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences of the United States of <lb/>America 92: 8089–8091. <lb/>22. Kovarik A, Pires JC, Leitch AR, Lim K, Sherwood A, et al. (2005) Rapid <lb/>concerted evolution of nuclear ribosomal DNA in two allopolyploids of recent <lb/>and recurrent origin. Genetics 169: 931–944. <lb/>23. Matyasek R, Tate JA, Lim KY, Srubarova H, Leitch AR, et al. (2007) Concerted <lb/>evolution in recently formed Tragopogon allotetraploids is typically associated with <lb/>an inverse correlation between gene copy number and expression. Molecular <lb/>Biology and Evolution 176: 2509–2519. <lb/>24. Pires CJ, Lim KY, Kovarik A, Matyasek R, Boyd A, et al. (2004) Genome size <lb/>and distribution of tandem repetitive DNA in allopolyploid Tragopogon <lb/> (Asteraceae). American Journal of Botany 91: 1022–1035. <lb/>25. Ownbey M, McCollum GD (1954) The chromosomes of Tragopogon. Rhodora <lb/>56: 7–21. <lb/>26. Mavrodiev EV (2007) Polyphyly of Tragopogon porrifolius L. (asteraceae), a <lb/>European native with intercontinental disjuncts. International Journal of Plant <lb/>Sciences 168: 889–904. <lb/>27. Mavrodiev EV, Tancig M, Sherwood AM, Gitzendanner MA, Rocca J, et al. <lb/>(2005) Phylogeny of Tragopogon L. (Asteraceae) based on internal and external <lb/>transcribed spacer sequence data. International Journal of Plant Sciences 166: <lb/>117–133. <lb/>28. Roose ML, Gottlieb LD (1976) Genetic and biochemical consequences of <lb/>polyploidy in Tragopogon. Evolution 30: 818–830. <lb/>29. Markova M, Michu E, Vyskot B, Janousek B, Zluvova J (2007) An interspecific <lb/>hybrid as a tool to study phylogenetic relationships in plants using the GISH <lb/>technique. Chromosome Research 15: 1051–1059. <lb/>30. Kovarik A, Dadejova M, Lim K, Chase M, JJ C, et al. (2008) Evolution of rDNA <lb/>in Nicotiana allopolyploids: A potential link between rDNA homogenization and <lb/>epigentics. Annals of Botany 101: 815–823. <lb/>31. Goodspeed TH (1954) The genus Nicotiana. Massachusetts, USA: Chronica <lb/>Botanica Company. 536 p. <lb/>32. Burk LG (1973) Partial self-fertility in a theoretical amphiploid progenitor of N. <lb/>tabacum. Journal of Heredity 64: 348–350. <lb/>33. Riley R (1960) The diploidisation of polyploid wheat. Heredity 15: 407–429. <lb/>34. Sears E (1954) The aneuploids of common wheat. Research Bulletin of Missouri <lb/>Agricultural Experimental Station 572: 1–58. <lb/>35. Ownbey M, McCollum GD (1953) Cytoplasmic inheritance and reciprocal <lb/>amphiploidy in Tragopogon. American Journal of Botany 40: 788–796. <lb/>36. Nicolas SD, Le Mignon G, Eber F, Coriton O, Monod H, et al. (2007) <lb/>Homeologous recombination plays a major role in chromosome rearrangements <lb/>that occur during meiosis of Brassica napus haploids. Genetics 175: 487–503. <lb/>37. Blakeslee AF (1927) Genetics in Datura. Berlin: Vererbungswiss. pp 117–130. <lb/>38. Avery AG, Satina S, Reitsema J (1959) The Genus Datura. New York: Ronald <lb/>Press. <lb/>39. Sears E (1953) Nullisomic analysis in common wheat. The American Naturalist <lb/>87: 245–252. <lb/>40. Saini RS, Minocha JL (1981) A compensating trisomic in pearl millet. Journal of <lb/>Heredity 72: 354–355. <lb/>41. Kush GS, Rick CM (1967) Novel compensating trisomics of the tomato: <lb/>Cytogenetics, monosomic analysis, and other applications. Genetics 56: <lb/>297–307. <lb/>42. Singh RJ (2002) Plant Cytogenetics. New York: CRC Press. <lb/>43. Gaeta RT, Pires JC, Iniguez-Luy F, Leon E, Osborn TC (2007) Genomic <lb/>changes in resynthesized Brassica napus and their effect on gene expression and <lb/>phenotype. Plant Cell 19: 3403–3417. <lb/>44. Lim KY, Matyasek R, Kovarik A, Leitch AR (2004) Genome evolution in <lb/>allotetraploid Nicotiana. Biological Journal of the Linnean Society 82: 599–606. <lb/>45. Liu Z, Li DY, Zhang XY (2007) Genetic relationships among five basic genomes <lb/>St, E, A, B and D in triticeae revealed by genomic southern and in situ <lb/>hybridization. Journal of Integrative Plant Biology 49: 1080–1086. <lb/>46. Jackson RC (1973) Chromosomal evolution in Haplopappus gracilis: A centric <lb/>transposition race. Evolution 27: 243–256. <lb/>47. Telgmann-Rauber A, Jamsari A, Kinney MS, Pires JC, Jung C (2007) Genetic <lb/>and physical maps around the sex-determining M-locus of the dioecious plant <lb/>asparagus. Molecular Genetics and Genomics 278: 221–234. <lb/></listBibl>  
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="footnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>12 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="footnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353 <lb/> </note>
			
			<listBibl> 48. Leitch AR, Lim KY, Webb DR, McFadden GI (2001) In situ hybridisation. In: <lb/>Hawes C, Satiat-Jeunemaitre B, eds. Plant Cell Biology, a practical approach. <lb/>Oxford: Oxford University Press. pp 267–293. <lb/>49. Fulnecek J, Lim KY, Leitch AR, Kovarik A, Matyasek R (2002) Evolution and <lb/>structure of 5S rDNA loci in allotetraploid Nicotiana tabacum and its putative <lb/>parental species. Heredity 88: 19–25. <lb/>50. Saghai-Maroof MA, Soliman KM, Jorgensen RA, Allard RW (1984) Ribosomal <lb/>DNA spacer-length polymorphisms in barley -Mendelian inheritance, <lb/>chromosomal location, and population-dynamics. Proceedings of the National <lb/>Academy of Sciences, USA 81: 8014–8018. <lb/>51. Kovarik A, Fajkus J, Koukalova B, Bezdek M (1996) Species-specific evolution of <lb/>telomeric and rDNA repeats in the tobacco composite genome. Theoretical and <lb/>Applied Genetics 92: 1108–1111. <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<note place="headnote">Tragopogon Evolution <lb/></note>
			
			<note place="headnote">PLoS ONE | www.plosone.org <lb/></note>
			
			<page>13 <lb/></page>
			
			<note place="headnote">October 2008 | Volume 3 | Issue 10 | e3353</note> 

		</back>
	</text>
</tei>
