<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9901084v2 [cond-mat.supr-con] 22 Feb 1999 <lb/>Coexistence of ferromagnetism and superconductivity in the hybrid ruthenate-cuprate <lb/>compound RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 studied by muon spin rotation (µSR) and <lb/>DC-magnetization <lb/>C. Bernhard 1) , J.L. Tallon 2) , Ch. Niedermayer 3) , Th. Blasius 3) , A. Golnik 1) * , E. Brücher 1) , R.K. Kremer 1) , D.R. <lb/>Noakes 4) , C.E. Stronach 4) and E.J. Ansaldo 5)# <lb/>1) Max-Planck-Institut für Festkörperforschung Heisenbergstrasse 1, <lb/>D-70569 Stuttgart, Germany <lb/>2) Industrial Research Ltd., P.O. Box 31310, Lower Hutt, <lb/>New Zealand <lb/>3) Universität Konstanz, Fakultät fūr Physik, D-78434 <lb/>Konstanz, Germany <lb/>4) Department of Physics, Virginia State University, Petersburg, Virginia <lb/>23806, USA <lb/>5)University of Saskatchewan, Saskatoon S7N OWO, Canada <lb/>(26.1.99) <lb/>We have investigated the magnetic and the superconducting properties of the hybrid ruthenate-<lb/>cuprate compound RuSr2GdCu2O8 by means of zero-field muon spin rotation-(ZF-µSR) and DC <lb/>magnetization measurements. The DC-magnetisation data establish that this material exhibits <lb/>ferromagnetic order of the Ru-moments (µ(Ru) ≈ 1 µB) below TCurie = 133 K and becomes su-<lb/>perconducting at a much lower temperature Tc = 16 K. The ZF-µSR experiments indicate that the <lb/>ferromagnetic phase is homogeneous on a microscopic scale and accounts for most of the sample <lb/>volume. They also suggest that the magnetic order is not significantly modified at the onset of <lb/>superconductivity. <lb/>PACS Numbers: 76.75.+i, 74.72.Jt, 74.25.Ha, 74.25.-q <lb/></front>

			<body>I. INTRODUCTION <lb/>Since the discovery of superconductivity in the cuprate <lb/>system La 2−x Ba x CuO 4 in 1986 1 an ever growing vari-<lb/>ety of high-T c superconducting cuprate compounds has <lb/>been synthesized all of which contain CuO 2 planes (some <lb/>also contain CuO chains) as their essential structural el-<lb/>ements which host the superconducting charge carriers 2 . <lb/>Between the CuO 2 planes are various kinds of layers, typ-<lb/>ically NaCl-type, which are insulating and act merely as <lb/>a charge reservoir. To date, the ruthenate compound <lb/>Sr 2 RuO 4 is the only known layered perovskite-like sys-<lb/>tem which becomes superconducting even though it does <lb/>not contain any CuO 2 planes or CuO chains 3 . Despite its <lb/>rather low transition temperature T c = 1.5 K the study <lb/>of its electronic and magnetic properties has become a <lb/>very rich and active field of research 4 . In parallel, the <lb/>electronic and magnetic properties of the related ruthen-<lb/>ate compounds, such as for example the SrRuO 3 system <lb/>which is an itinerant 4d-band ferromagnet with T Curie <lb/>≈ 165 K, have attracted a great deal of interest 5 . <lb/>Another potentially promising and exciting direction <lb/>of research has been prompted by the circumstance that <lb/>the RuO 2 layers share the same square-planar coor-<lb/>dination and a rather similar bond length with their <lb/>CuO 2 counterparts. A whole new family of hybrid <lb/>ruthenate-cuprate compounds may therefore be con-<lb/>structed whose members consist of different sequences of <lb/>alternating RuO 2 -and CuO 2 layers. Recently, one such <lb/>a hybrid ruthenate-cuprate compound, the 1212-type <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 system comprising CuO 2 bilayers and <lb/>RuO 2 monolayers, has been synthesized as single-phase <lb/>material 6 . A subsequent study of its electronic and mag-<lb/>netic properties has revealed that this material exhibits <lb/>electronic ferromagnetic order at a rather high Curie tem-<lb/>perature T Curie =133-136 K and becomes superconduct-<lb/>ing at a significantly lower critical temperature T c =15-40 <lb/>K (depending on the condition of preparation and anneal-<lb/>ing) [6-8]. The most surprising observation, however, is <lb/>that the ferromagnetic order does not vanish when super-<lb/>conductivity sets in at T c . Instead, it appears that the <lb/>ferromagnetic state remains largely unchanged and coex-<lb/>ists with superconductivity. This finding implies that the <lb/>interaction between the superconducting-and the ferro-<lb/>magnetic order parameters is very weak and it raises the <lb/>question of whether both order parameters coexist on a <lb/>truly microscopic scale. Since the early investigations of <lb/>Ginzburg in 1957 9 the prevailing view is that the coexis-<lb/>tence of a superconducting-(with singlet Cooper pairs) <lb/>and a ferromagnetic order parameter is not possible on a <lb/>microscopic scale since the electromagnetic interaction <lb/>and the exchange coupling cause strong pairbreaking. <lb/>Indeed, merely based on magnetisation and transport <lb/>measurements one cannot exclude the possibility that <lb/>the RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 samples may be spatially inhomoge-<lb/>neous with some domains exhibiting ferromagnetic order <lb/>and others superconducting order 6 . We note that unam-<lb/>biguous evidence for the occurence of bulk superconduc-<lb/>tivity in RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 has recently been obtained from <lb/>specific heat measurements which reveal a sizeable jump <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>at T c of ∆γ ≡ C p /T ≈ 0.35 mJ/g at.K 2 characteristic of <lb/>a strongly underdoped cuprate superconductor 10 . In the <lb/>following we report on muon-spin rotation (µSR) mea-<lb/>surements which establish that the ferromagnetic order <lb/>is uniform and homogeneous even on a microscopic scale. <lb/>The µSR technique is ideally suited for such a purpose <lb/>since it provides an extremely sensitive local magnetic <lb/>probe and, furthermore, allows one to reliably obtain <lb/>the volume fraction of the magnetically-ordered phase 11 . <lb/>Here we present the result of a zero-field muon-spin ro-<lb/>tation (ZF-µSR) study of a RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 sample with <lb/>T c =16 K and T Curie =133 K which provides evidence <lb/>that the magnetic order parameter is spatially homoge-<lb/>neous and accounts for most of the sample volume. Fur-<lb/>thermore, the ZF-µSR data establish that the ferromag-<lb/>netic order is hardly affected by the onset of superconduc-<lb/>tivity and persists to the lowest available temperature of <lb/>the experiment T=2.2 K. The ZF-µSR data can be com-<lb/>plemented by DC-magnetisation measurements which es-<lb/>tablish the presence of ferromagnetic order from the ob-<lb/>servation of a spontaneous magnetization at T Curie = <lb/>133 K and of hysteretic isothermal magnetic behavior <lb/>with a remanent magnetization. It is shown that the fer-<lb/>romagnetic ordering involves the Ru magnetic moments <lb/>with µ(Ru) ≈ 1.05(5) µ B , while the larger Gd-moments <lb/>with µ(Gd 3+ ) ≈ 7.4(1) µ B remain paramagnetic down to <lb/>very low temperatures. In addition, the magnetisation <lb/>measurements indicate an almost complete diamagnetic <lb/>shielding effect below T c . <lb/>II. EXPERIMENT <lb/>A. sample preparation and characterization <lb/>Polycrystalline samples of the 1212-type system <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 have been synthesized as previously <lb/>described 8 by solid state reaction of RuO 2 , SrCO 3 , <lb/>Gd 2 O 3 and CuO powders. The mixture was first de-<lb/>composed at 960 • C in air. It was then ground, milled <lb/>and die-pressed into pellets. The first sintering step <lb/>took place in flowing nitrogen atmosphere at 1010 • C. <lb/>This step results in the formation of a mixture of the <lb/>precursor material Sr 2 GdRuO 6 and Cu 2 O and is di-<lb/>rected towards minimizing the formation of SrRuO 3 <lb/>6 . <lb/>The material was then reground before it was reacted <lb/>in flowing oxygen for 10 hours at 1050 • C. This sinter-<lb/>ing step was repeated twice with intermediate grinding <lb/>and milling. Each reaction step was carried out on a <lb/>MgO single crystal substrate to prevent reaction with <lb/>the alumina crucible. Finally the samples were cooled <lb/>slowly to room temperature in flowing oxygen. Follow-<lb/>ing this procedure we have also made a Zn-substituted <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 1.94 Zn 0.06 O 8 sample and a Y ↔ Gd cosubsti-<lb/>tuted sample RuSr 2 Gd 0.9 Y 0.1 Cu 2 O 8 . X-ray diffraction <lb/>(XRD) measurements indicate that all samples are single <lb/>phase 1212-type material and give no indication for traces <lb/>of the ferromagnetic phase SrRuO 3 . Figure 1(b) displays <lb/>a representative XRD-spectrum of RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 , the <lb/>plus signs show the raw data and the solid line shows the <lb/>result of the Rietveld refinement. The related structure <lb/>of RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 is shown in Fig. 1(a). <lb/>FIG. 1. (a) The structure of RuSr2GdCu2O8 with the Cu <lb/>atoms sited at the centre of the base of the square pyramids <lb/>and the Ru atoms at the centre of the octahedra. (b) The <lb/>X-ray diffraction (XRD) spectrum for a RuSr2GdCu2O8 sam-<lb/>ple (Co K-α source). The plus signs (+) are the raw x-ray data <lb/>and the solid line is the calculated Rietveld refinement profile <lb/>for tetragonal (space group P4/mmm) RuSr2GdCu2O8. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>The electronic properties of RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 have <lb/>been characterized by measurements of the temperature-<lb/>dependent resistivity and thermo-electric power. Repre-<lb/>sentative results are shown in Fig. 2(a) and 2(b) respec-<lb/>tively (see also Ref. 8). <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.03 <lb/>0 50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>a) <lb/>T Curie <lb/>resistance [Ω] <lb/>0 50 100 150 200 250 300 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>b) <lb/>T [K] <lb/>S(T) [µV/K] <lb/>FIG. 2. (a) Temperature dependence of the resistivity, ρ, <lb/>of RuSr2GdCu2O 8−δ . (b) The temperature-dependent ther-<lb/>moelectric power S(T). <lb/>The temperature dependence of the thermo-electric <lb/>power S(T) and, in particular, its normal state value of <lb/>S(300 K) ≈ 75 µV/K is rather typical for a strongly <lb/>underdoped cuprate superconductor with T c &lt;&lt;T c,max , <lb/>consistent with a hole content of p≈0.07 holes per CuO 2 <lb/>planes and a value of T c,max of the order of 100 K <lb/>[8,12]. The resistivity measurements indicate that the <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 sample exhibits zero resistivity at a crit-<lb/>ical temperature of T c = 16 K. The precise value of T c <lb/>varies between 12 and 24 K, depending on synthesis con-<lb/>ditions, and may be raised to 40 K by long-term anneal-<lb/>ing. The temperature dependence of the normal-state re-<lb/>sistivity is again characteristic of a strongly underdoped <lb/>superconducting cuprate compound. The ferromagnetic <lb/>transition at T Curie =133 K causes only a small yet no-<lb/>ticeable drop in the resistivity indicating that the RuO 2 <lb/>layer is almost insulating above T Curie while being poorly <lb/>conducting in the ferromagnetic state 5 . <lb/>B. The technique of muon spin rotation <lb/>The muon spin rotation (µSR) experiments have been <lb/>performed at the M15 beamline of TRIUMF in Vancou-<lb/>ver, Canada, which provides 100% spin polarized muons. <lb/>The µSR technique is especially suited for the study of <lb/>magnetic materials and allows one to study the homo-<lb/>geneity of the magnetic state on a microscopic scale and <lb/>also to access its volume fraction 11 . The µSR technique <lb/>typically covers a time window of 10 −6 to 10 −9 seconds <lb/>and allows one to detect internal magnetic fields over a <lb/>wide range of 0.1G to several Tesla. The 100% spin-<lb/>polarised &apos;surface muons&apos; (E µ ≈ 4.2 MeV) are implanted <lb/>into the bulk of the sample where they thermalize very <lb/>rapidly (∼10 −12 s) without any noticeable loss in their ini-<lb/>tial spin polarization. Each muon stops at a well-defined <lb/>interstitial lattice site and, for the perovskite compounds, <lb/>forms a muoxyl bond with one of the oxygen atoms 13 . <lb/>The whole ensemble of muons is randomly distributed <lb/>throughout a layer of 100-200 µm thickness and there-<lb/>fore probes a representative part of the sample volume. <lb/>Each muon spin precesses in its local magnetic field B µ <lb/>with a precession frequency of, ν µ = (γ µ /2π) • B µ , where <lb/>γ µ /2π= 135.5 MHz/T is the gyromagnetic ratio of the <lb/>positive muon. The muon decays with a mean life time <lb/>of τ µ + ≈ 2.2 µs −1 into two neutrinos and a positron which <lb/>is preferentially emitted along the direction of the muon <lb/>spin at the instant of decay. The time evolution of the <lb/>spin polarization P(t) of the muon ensemble can there-<lb/>fore be obtained via the time-resolved detection of the <lb/>spatial asymmetry of the decay positron emission rate. <lb/>More details regarding the zero-field (ZF) µSR technique <lb/>are given below. <lb/>III. EXPERIMENTAL RESULTS <lb/>A. DC magnetization <lb/>Before we discuss the result of the µSR experiments, <lb/>we first present some DC-magnetization data which es-<lb/>tablish that the RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 sample exhibits a spon-<lb/>taneous magnetization at a ferromagnetic transition of <lb/>T Curie = 133 K and becomes superconducting at a much <lb/>lower temperature T c = 16 K. Figure 3(a) shows the tem-<lb/>perature dependence of the volume susceptibility, χ V , <lb/>which has been obtained after zero-field cooling the sam-<lb/>ple to T = 2 K, then applying an external field of H ext = <lb/>5.5 Oe, and subsequently warming up to T = 200 K. The <lb/>density of the sample has been assumed to be ρ = 6.7 <lb/>g/cm 3 corresponding to stoichiometric RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 <lb/>with lattice parameters of a = 3.84Å and c = 11.57 <lb/>A 8 . The superconducting transition is evident in Fig <lb/>3(a) from the onset of a pronounced diamagnetic shift <lb/>below T c = 16 K. The diamagnetic shift at the lowest <lb/>available temperature of T = 2 K corresponds to an al-<lb/>most complete diamagnetic shielding of the sample vol-<lb/>ume, implying that at least the surface region of the <lb/>sample is homogeneously superconducting. In fact, all <lb/>pieces that have been cut from the pellet exhibit a simi-<lb/>larly large diamagnetic shielding effect (small differences <lb/>can be attributed to different demagnetization factors). <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>Nevertheless, the DC-magnetisation measurements can-<lb/>not give unambiguous evidence for the presence of bulk <lb/>superconductivity since an almost complete diamagnetic <lb/>shielding may also be caused by a filamentary structure <lb/>of superconducting material in a small fraction of the <lb/>otherwise non-superconducting material. <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>a) <lb/>zfc 5.5 Oe <lb/>T [K] <lb/>T Curie <lb/>T c <lb/>χ <lb/>Vol <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>b) <lb/>fc 50 Oe <lb/>fc 5.5 Oe <lb/>fc 100 Oe <lb/>T [K] <lb/>M <lb/>mol [emu/mol] <lb/>FIG. 3. (a) The temperature-dependence of the zero-field <lb/>cooled DC volume magnetization, χV , of RuSr2GdCu2O8. <lb/>The arrows show the superconducting-and the ferromagnetic <lb/>transition at Tc=16 K and TCurie = 133 K, respectively. (b) <lb/>The field-cooled molar magnetization, M mol , for applied fields <lb/>of H=5.5, 10, 100 Oe. <lb/>We note however, that unequivocal evidence for the <lb/>occurrence of bulk superconductivity in RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 <lb/>has recently been obtained from specific heat measure-<lb/>ments which reveal a sizeable jump of ∆γ ≡ Cp/T ≈ 0.35 <lb/>mJ/g at.K 2 at T c , comparable to or greater than that <lb/>seen in other underdoped cuprates 10 . For comparison <lb/>in strongly underdoped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ it is found that <lb/>∆γ ≈ 0.2 − 0.3 mJ/g at.K 214 . We also note that the <lb/>specific heat measurements have been performed on the <lb/>same samples which have been studied by µSR-and DC-<lb/>magnetisation measurements. Figure 3(b) displays the <lb/>(low) field-cooled molar magnetization M m for applied <lb/>fields of H ext = 5.5, 50 and 100 Oe. The ferromagnetic <lb/>transition at T Curie = 133 K is evident from the sud-<lb/>den onset of a spontaneous magnetization. Evidently, <lb/>the magnetic order parameter has at least a sizeable fer-<lb/>romagnetic component and it persists almost unchanged <lb/>to the lowest measured temperature T = 2 K. In partic-<lb/>ular, it does not appear to weaken as superconductivity <lb/>sets in at T c = 16 K. Additional evidence for the pres-<lb/>ence of ferromagnetic order is presented in Fig. 4, which <lb/>shows that the isothermal magnetization loops at T = 5 <lb/>K and 50 K exhibit hysteretic magnetic behavior with a <lb/>remanent magnetization M rem ≈ 400 Oe at 5 K and 200 <lb/>Oe at 50 K. <lb/>-7.5 -5.0 -2.5 0.0 2.5 5.0 7.5 <lb/>-10000 <lb/>-5000 <lb/>0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>200 K <lb/>50 K <lb/>5 K <lb/>M <lb/>mol [emu/mol] <lb/>H <lb/>ext [kOe] <lb/>-0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>-750 <lb/>-500 <lb/>-250 <lb/>0 <lb/>250 <lb/>500 <lb/>750 <lb/>FIG. 4. <lb/>The isothermal magnetization loops of <lb/>RuSr2GdCu2O8 at T = 5, 50 and 200 K. The inset shows <lb/>a magnification of the low-field region. <lb/>Having established the existence of ferromagnetic or-<lb/>der, the question arises of whether it involves the Ru-<lb/>moments or the Gd-moments. In the following we present <lb/>high-temperature susceptibility data which indicate that <lb/>the ferromagnetic order involves only the Ru−moments, <lb/>whereas the Gd-moments remain in the paramagnetic <lb/>state below T Curie . Figure 5 shows the inverse molar sus-<lb/>ceptibility, 1/χ m ≈ (M m /H ext ) −1 obtained for different <lb/>external fields in the range 5.5 H ext <lb/>1000 Oe (solid <lb/>lines) in the temperature region 200 K&lt;T&lt;400 K. Shown <lb/>by the plus signs (+) is the best fit to the experimen-<lb/>tal data using a two-component &apos;Curie-Weiss + Curie-<lb/>function&apos;, χ = C 1 /(T-Θ) + C 2 /T , with Θ = T Curie = <lb/>133 K kept fixed. This function describes the experimen-<lb/>tal data rather well and it gives us very reasonable values <lb/>for the magnetic moments, with µ 1 = 1.05(5) µ B for the <lb/>moments that order at T Curie and µ 2 = 7.4(1) µ B for the <lb/>moments that remain paramagnetic below T Curie . The <lb/>magnetic moment of the paramagnetic component agrees <lb/>reasonably well with the expected magnetic moment of <lb/>Gd 3+ which for a free Gd 3+ -ion 15 is µ(Gd 3+ ) = 7.94 <lb/>µ B and µ(Gd 3+ ) = 7.4 µ B for the structurally-similar <lb/>GdBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ compound 16 . On the other hand, the <lb/>value of the Ru-moments with µ(Ru) = 1.05(5) µ B also <lb/>appears to be reasonable. For Ru 5+ the number of 4d <lb/>electrons is 3 and the free ion value of the magnetic mo-<lb/>ment is 3 µ B for the high spin state and 1 µ B for the low <lb/>spin state. The experimentally observed value of µ(Ru) <lb/>= 1.05(5) µ B therefore seems to imply that Ru 5+ is in <lb/>the low spin state. Shown in the inset of Fig. 5 is the <lb/>field-dependent magnetization for the temperatures T = <lb/>2, 30, 50, 100 and 300 K. The low-temperature magne-<lb/>tization can be seen to saturate at a value of µ sat ≈ 8 <lb/>µ B , as may be expected for a system that contains one <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>Gd-moment per formula unit with µ(Gd) = 7 µ B plus <lb/>one Ru-moment with µ(Ru) = 1 µ B . <lb/>100 150 200 250 300 350 400 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Curie-Weiss + Curie <lb/>1/χ <lb/>m [mol/emu] <lb/>T [K] <lb/>0 25 50 75 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>H [kOe] <lb/>µ <lb/>eff [µ <lb/>B <lb/>] <lb/>FIG. 5. The temperature-dependent inverse molar suscep-<lb/>tibility, 1/χm for the high temperature range of 400 K &gt;100 <lb/>K. The plus signs show the best fit using a two component <lb/>&apos;Curie-Weiss-+ Curie-function&apos;. Shown in the inset is the <lb/>saturation magnetization in units of effective Bohr magnetons <lb/>per unit volume as a function of applied field at temperatures <lb/>of T = 2, 30, 50, 100, 200 K. <lb/>-0.3 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>-0.1 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>zfc 5.5 Oe <lb/>a) <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 <lb/>RuSr 2 Gd 0.9 Y 0.1 Cu 2 O 8 <lb/>RuSr 2 GdCu 1.94 Zn 0.06 O 8 <lb/>volume suceptibility <lb/>χ <lb/>V <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>fc 5.5 Oe <lb/>b) <lb/>T [K] <lb/>M <lb/>m [emu/mol] <lb/>FIG. 6. (a) The temperature-dependent volume suscepti-<lb/>bility, χV , of RuSr2GdCu2O8 (solid line), for Zn-substituted <lb/>RuSr2GdCu1.94Zn0.06O8 (dotted line) and for Y ←→ Gd co-<lb/>substituted RuSr2Gd0.9Y0.1Cu2O8 (dashed line). (b) The <lb/>temperature-dependent molar magnetization Mm, shown by <lb/>the same symbols as in (a). <lb/>The idea that the Gd-moments do not partici-<lb/>pate in the ferromagnetic transition at T Curie = 133 <lb/>K is supported by the result of DC-magnetization <lb/>measurements on the 10% Y ↔ Gd cosubstituted <lb/>RuSr 2 Gd 0.9 Y 0.1 Cu 2 O 8 . Figures 6(a) and 6(b) display <lb/>the zero-field-cooled-and the field-cooled susceptibilities <lb/>(dashed lines) and compare them with the corresponding <lb/>data on the pure RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 sample (solid line). It <lb/>is evident that the ferromagnetic transition is not sig-<lb/>nificantly affected by the partial substitution of non-<lb/>magnetic Y 3+ for magnetic Gd 3+ . Also shown in Fig. <lb/>6(a) and 6(b) by the dotted lines are the results for the <lb/>Zn-substituted RuSr 2 Cu 1.94 Zn 0.06 O 8 sample. The cir-<lb/>cumstance that the ferromagnetic order is not affected by <lb/>the Zn-substitution supports our view that the majority <lb/>of the Zn-impurities has been introduced into the CuO 2 <lb/>layers while hardly any of them reside within the RuO 2 -<lb/>layers. Moreover, we infer from the rapid T c -suppression <lb/>upon Zn-substitution that only the CuO 2 layers host the <lb/>superconducting charge carrier in RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 . <lb/>B. Zero-field muon-spin-rotation (ZF-µSR) <lb/>Next we discuss the result of the zero-field (ZF) µSR <lb/>experiments. Figures 7(a) and 7(b) show representative <lb/>ZF-µSR spectra for the evolution of the normalized time-<lb/>resolved muon spin polarization P(t)/P(0) at tempera-<lb/>tures of T = 5 and 48 K. <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>a) <lb/>T= 5.3 K <lb/>P(t)/P(0) <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>t [µs] <lb/>b) <lb/>T = 48 K <lb/>P(t)/P(0) <lb/>FIG. 7. The time-resolved normalized muon-spin polariza-<lb/>tion, P(t)/P(t=0), at temperatures of (a) T = 5.3 K &lt;Tc <lb/>and (b) Tc &lt;T = 48 K &lt;TCurie = 133 K. The large oscil-<lb/>latory component gives clear evidence for the presence of a <lb/>homogeneous magnetically-ordered state. <lb/>The value of the initial muon spin polarization, P(0), <lb/>has been determined by a transverse field (TF) µSR ex-<lb/>periment performed on the same sample at a temper-<lb/>ature above T Curie . In the ferromagnetic state below <lb/>T Curie =133 K we find that the spectra are well described <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>by the relaxation function: <lb/>P (t )/P (t =0) = A 1 •exp(−λt )•cos(2π ν µ t )+ <lb/>A 2 • exp(−Λt ), <lb/>(1) <lb/>where ν µ is the average muon spin precession frequency <lb/>which corresponds to the average value of the sponta-<lb/>neous internal magnetic field at the muons sites, ν µ = <lb/>γ µ /2π • B µ , with γ µ = 835.4 MHz/T the gyromagnetic <lb/>ratio. The damping rate of the non-oscillating (longi-<lb/>tudinal) component, Λ, is proportional to the dynamic <lb/>spin-lattice relaxation rate, Λ ∼ 1/T 1 , whereas the re-<lb/>laxation rate of the oscillating (transverse) component, <lb/>λ, is dominated by the static distribution of the local <lb/>magnetic field, i.e., λ ≈ γ µ • ∆B µ . Figure 8 shows the <lb/>temperature dependence of (a) the precession frequency, <lb/>ν µ (T ), (b) the transverse relaxation rate, λ(T ), and (c) <lb/>the longitudinal relaxation rate, Λ(T ). <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>0 25 50 75 100 125 150 <lb/>a) <lb/>T [K] <lb/>ν <lb/>µ [MHz] <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>b) <lb/>λ [µs <lb/>-1 <lb/>] <lb/>0 25 50 75 100 125 150 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>c) <lb/>T [K] <lb/>Λ [µs <lb/>-1 <lb/>] <lb/>FIG. 8. The temperature dependence of the µSR sig-<lb/>nal of RuSr2GdCu2O8 (a) The muon spin precession fre-<lb/>quency, νµ(T) [MHz] = 135.5 [MHz/T] Bµ . Shown by <lb/>the dashed line is the best fit using the scaling function <lb/>νµ(T ) = νo(1 − T /TCurie) β . with β = 0.333(5) TCurie = <lb/>133(1) K, and νo = 9.70(5) MHz (Bµ = 720(10) G). (b) The <lb/>relaxation rate of the precessing component, λ(T). (c) The re-<lb/>laxation rate of the non-precessing component, Λ(T) ∼ 1/T1. <lb/>Before we discuss the ZF-µSR data in more detail, we <lb/>first emphasize the most important implications, which <lb/>are evident from Figs. 7 and 8. Firstly, the presence <lb/>of an oscillating component in the ZF-µSR spectra for <lb/>T &lt;T Curie = 133 K gives unambiguous evidence for an <lb/>ordered magnetic state which is homogeneous on a mi-<lb/>croscopic length scale (of typically 20Å). Secondly, from <lb/>the amplitude of the oscillating component (A 1 ≈2/3) we <lb/>can deduce that the magnetically-ordered state accounts <lb/>for more or less the entire volume of the sample. And <lb/>thirdly, from the temperature dependence of the µSR <lb/>signal it becomes clear that the magnetic order persists <lb/>almost unchanged in the superconducting state. <lb/>1. The volume fraction of the magnetic phase <lb/>In the following we outline how the volume fraction <lb/>of the magnetically-ordered phase is obtained from the <lb/>amplitude of the oscillating component of the ZF-µSR <lb/>spectra. For a polycrystalline sample with randomly-<lb/>orientated grains in zero external field the local magnetic <lb/>field, on average, is parallel (perpendicular) to the di-<lb/>rection of the muon spin direction with probability 1/3 <lb/>(2/3). For a homogeneous magnetically-ordered sam-<lb/>ple one therefore expects that 2/3 of the amplitude of <lb/>the ZF-µSR signal (the transverse component) exhibit <lb/>an oscillatory behavior, while 1/3 of the signal (the lon-<lb/>gitudinal component) is non-oscillating and only slowly <lb/>damped due to spin-flip excitations. On the other hand, <lb/>for a sample with inhomogeneous magnetic order, for ex-<lb/>ample containing non-magnetic regions, the amplitude <lb/>of the oscillating signal will be accordingly reduced and <lb/>a second non-oscillating transverse component will ap-<lb/>pear. If the non-magnetic regions are microscopically <lb/>small, this non-oscillating component is likely to have a <lb/>rather large damping rate of the order of λ ∼ γ µ • B µ <lb/>due to stray fields which are imposed by the neighbor-<lb/>ing magnetic domains. From Fig. 7(a) and 7(b) it can <lb/>be seen that the ZF-µSR data on RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 give <lb/>no indication for such an inhomogeneous magnetic state. <lb/>As was mentioned above, the amplitude of the initial <lb/>muon spin polarization P(t = 0) has been determined <lb/>from a transverse-field (TF)-µSR measurement. From <lb/>the size of the amplitude of the oscillatory component <lb/>we deduce that more than 80 % of the sample is mag-<lb/>netically ordered below T Curie = 133 K. Based on this <lb/>analysis we estimate that the volume fraction of any dis-<lb/>ordered magnetic-or non-magnetic phase must be well <lb/>below 20%. Note that some of the muons (typically 10-<lb/>20 %) do not stop inside the sample but somewhere in the <lb/>cryostat walls. In the ZF-µSR experiment these muons <lb/>give rise to a missing fraction since their spin-polarization <lb/>is much more slowly damped than for the rest of the <lb/>signal. In the TF-µSR experiment, however, this very <lb/>slowly damped component can be detected via its pre-<lb/>cession in the external field and it contributes to the to-<lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>tal muon spin polarization P(0). The 80% fraction of the <lb/>magnetically ordered phase therefore has to be regarded <lb/>as a lower bound. In fact, it is rather likely that the entire <lb/>sample volume is magnetically ordered. Finally, we note <lb/>that the muons apparently occupy only one muon site, <lb/>since only one precession frequency is seen in the ZF-µSR <lb/>spectra. Also it is clear from the ZF-µSR data that muon <lb/>diffusion effects are negligibly small below T Curie = 133 <lb/>K, similar to the other cuprate superconductors where <lb/>muon diffusion is observed only at significantly higher <lb/>temperatures of T ≥ 250 K 13 . <lb/>2. Local magnetic field at the muon site <lb/>It is evident from Fig. 8(a) that the muon spin pre-<lb/>cession frequency (the local field at the muon site) does <lb/>not exhibit any strong anomaly at the superconducting <lb/>transition temperature T c . Instead, as shown by the <lb/>dashed line, the temperature of the muon spin preces-<lb/>sion frequency ν µ (T ) (and thus of the magnetic order <lb/>parameter) is well described by the function ν µ (T ) = <lb/>ν o (1 − T /T c ) <lb/>β , with ν o = 9.7(1) MHz (corresponding <lb/>to B µ (T → 0) ≈ 720(10) G), T c = 133(1) K, and β <lb/>= 0.333(5). This functional form is strictly valid only <lb/>in the critical regime close to T Curie but it can be seen <lb/>to provide a reasonable description of the magnetic order <lb/>parameter over a fairly wide temperature range of T Curie <lb/>T 5 K. The anomaly at very low temperature arises <lb/>most likely from the magnetic ordering transition of the <lb/>Gd-moments at T N ≈2.6 K. Note that for the struc-<lb/>turally related compound GdBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (Gd-123) the <lb/>antiferromagnetic ordering transition of the Gd-moment <lb/>occurs at a very similar temperature of T N =2.3K [16,17]. <lb/>The value of the critical exponent β = 0.333 is close to the <lb/>theoretical value 0.345 in the 3D XY model 18 . We can-<lb/>not determine with certainty the number of components <lb/>in the spin system with these data and, in particular, dis-<lb/>tinguish between the 2-component XY (β= 0.345) and <lb/>the 3-component Heisenberg (β = 0.365) models. The <lb/>contribution of ferromagnetic fluctuations above T Curie <lb/>to the susceptibility provides better discrimination as will <lb/>be discussed later. <lb/>The oscillating transverse component exhibits a damp-<lb/>ing rate of the order of λ ≈ 10-15 µs −1 corresponding to a <lb/>spread in the local magnetic field of ∆B µ / B µ ≈ 0.2. <lb/>This 20 % spread of the local magnetic field does not <lb/>seem to agree with a scenario where the ferromagnetic <lb/>order is assumed to exhibit a spiral modulation (with a <lb/>wavelength shorter than the superconducting coherence <lb/>length of typically 20Å in the cuprates) and/or to be <lb/>spatially inhomogeneous as in ErRh 4 B 4 <lb/>19 , HoMo 6 S 8 <lb/>20 <lb/>and Y 9 Co 7 <lb/>21 . Instead, we emphasize that the observed <lb/>spread in the local magnetic field can be accounted for by <lb/>the grain boundary effects and by the differences in the <lb/>demagnetization factors of the individual grains which <lb/>naturally arise for a polycrystalline sample that has a <lb/>very small average grain size of about 1 µm 8 . Also, we <lb/>point out that recent transmission-electron-microscopy <lb/>(TEM) studies have revealed that our present Ru-1212 <lb/>sample contains [100] rotation twins and also exhibits <lb/>some cationic disorder due to the intermixing of Sr ↔ <lb/>Gd and to a lesser extent of Ru ↔ Cu 8 . These kinds <lb/>of structural imperfections certainly tend to further in-<lb/>crease the transverse relaxation rate λ of the ZF-µSR <lb/>spectra. Meanwhile, we have prepared Ru-1212 sam-<lb/>ples which are structurally more perfect (by sintering at <lb/>slightly higher temperature and for longer periods) 8 . Re-<lb/>cent DC-magnetization measurements have shown that <lb/>these crystallographic defects do not affect the funda-<lb/>mental magnetic and superconducting behavior. In fact, <lb/>both the superconducting-and the ferromagnetic tran-<lb/>sitions become somewhat sharper and T c and T Curie <lb/>are slightly increased for these structurally more perfect <lb/>samples 8 . Additional µSR measurements on these sam-<lb/>ples are presently under way. <lb/>3. Longitudinal relaxation rate, Λ ∼ 1/T1 <lb/>The temperature dependence of the relaxation rate <lb/>of the non-oscillating component of the ZF-µSR signal, <lb/>Λ(T) ∼ 1/T , is shown in Fig. 8(c). As a function of <lb/>decreasing temperature Λ(T ) can be seen to exhibit a <lb/>cusp-like feature at the ferromagnetic transition of the <lb/>Ru-moments at T Curie =133 K and a step-like increase at <lb/>very low temperature which most likely is related to the <lb/>ordering of the Gd moments. The cusp feature at T Curie <lb/>= 133 K characterizes the slowing down of the spin dy-<lb/>namics of the Ru-moments as the ferromagnetic tran-<lb/>sition is approached. The cusp maximum occurs when <lb/>the spin fluctuation rate, τ c , equals the typical µSR time <lb/>scale for τ c ∼ 10 −611 . Note, that in the ferromagnetically-<lb/>ordered state the longitudinal relaxation rate remains <lb/>unusually large with values of Λ(T &lt;&lt;T Curie ) ≈ 0.3-<lb/>0.4 µs −1 that are at least an order of magnitude larger <lb/>than expected for a classical ferromagnet 22 (where two-<lb/>magnon excitations provide the major contribution to <lb/>spin dynamics). We have confirmed by a µSR measure-<lb/>ments in a longitudinal field of H LF =6 kOe that this <lb/>large relaxation rate is indeed characteristic for the lon-<lb/>gitudinal component of the µSR signal. At present we <lb/>cannot provide a definite explanation of the origin of <lb/>the unusually large value of Λ. However, we emphasize <lb/>that the RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 system can be expected to ex-<lb/>hibit a rather complex magnetic behavior since, besides <lb/>the ferromagnetically-ordered Ru moments, it also con-<lb/>tains the larger Gd moments with µ(Gd 3+ ) ≈ 7.4 µ B <lb/>which remain paramagnetic below T Curie . The magnetic <lb/>ordering transition of the Gd moments at T≈2.6 K is <lb/>evident in the ZF-µSR data in Fig. 8(a)-(c) from the <lb/>sudden increase in the local magnetic field (or the µSR <lb/>precession frequency, ν µ ) and a corresponding increase <lb/>in both relaxation rates, λ and Λ. In addition, we note <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>that recently it has been shown by µSR measurements <lb/>that in strongly underdoped high-T c cuprate supercon-<lb/>ductors (like the present RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 compound) also <lb/>the Cu moments exhibit a spin-glass type freezing tran-<lb/>sition at low temperature 23 . Finally, it appears that the <lb/>longitudinal relaxation rate Λ exhibits an additional weak <lb/>anomaly at a temperature of T≈20 K, i.e. in the vicinity <lb/>of the superconducting transition at T c =16 K. At present <lb/>we are not sure whether this effect is related to the onset <lb/>of superconductivity. From Fig. 8(b) it appears that the <lb/>transverse relaxation rate also exhibits a steplike increase <lb/>in the same temperature range. The local magnetic field <lb/>at the muon site, however, (see Fig. 8a) does not seem <lb/>to exhibit any anomaly in the vicinity of T c . We ex-<lb/>pect that further µSR measurements on rare earth (RE) <lb/>substituted RuSr 2 Gd 1−x RE x Cu 2 O 8 samples, as well as <lb/>on less strongly underdoped samples with higher critical <lb/>temperatures of T c up to 40 K, should shed more light <lb/>on the complex magnetic behavior and its interplay with <lb/>superconductivity in the Ru-1212 system. <lb/>C. Dipolar Field Calculation <lb/>While the ZF-µSR data give clear evidence for the <lb/>presence of a homogeneous magnetically ordered state, <lb/>they do not provide any direct information about the <lb/>origin of the magnetic moments, the type of the mag-<lb/>netic order and its direction. Based on dipolar-field cal-<lb/>culations of the local magnetic field at the muon site, <lb/>however, one can test the consistency with an assumed <lb/>magnetic structure. The result of these calculations de-<lb/>pends on the location of the interstitial muon site and <lb/>also on the orientation of the Ru-moments. Unfortu-<lb/>nately, for the Ru-1212 system neither of these is accu-<lb/>rately known at present. Nevertheless, it seems plausible <lb/>that the muon site is similar to that in YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ <lb/>(and other related cuprate compounds) where the posi-<lb/>tive muon forms a hydroxyl bond with the apex oxygen <lb/>and is located at the so-called &apos;apical-site&apos; near the point <lb/>(0.12a,0.225b,0.14c) 13 . Indeed, as is summarized in table <lb/>1, we obtain rather good agreement with the experimen-<lb/>tal value of B µ (T→0) = 720 G if we take a similar <lb/>apical-site near the point (0.13a, 0.22b, 0.16-0.17c) and <lb/>assume that the ferromagnetically-ordered Ru-moments <lb/>(µ(Ru)=1 µ B ) are oriented along the RuO 2 plane ei-<lb/>ther along the Ru-O bond, [100], or along the diago-<lb/>nal [110] (see table 1). For the [110] orientation, how-<lb/>ever, there exist two magnetically inequivalent muon sites <lb/>which should give rise to two distinctive precession fre-<lb/>quencies in the µSR spectra (which are not observed ex-<lb/>perimentally). For the Ru-moments oriented perpendic-<lb/>ular to the RuO 2 layer along [001] the resulting local <lb/>magnetic field at the apex-site is significantly larger than <lb/>the experimental value. In order to obtain reasonable <lb/>agreement with experiment for the [001]-orientation one <lb/>has to assume that the muon site is located much closer <lb/>to the CuO 2 planes. Such a muon site, however, is not <lb/>very realistic (simply speaking the positive muon is re-<lb/>pelled by the positively charged CuO 2 planes) and has <lb/>not been observed in any of the related cuprate com-<lb/>pounds. We thus tentatively conclude that the moments <lb/>align in-plane consistent with the 2-component XY sce-<lb/>nario. While this result is rather convenient in terms <lb/>of the coexistence of the ferromagnetic order of the Ru <lb/>moments and the superconductivity which resides within <lb/>the CuO 2 layers as discussed below, one has to keep in <lb/>mind that the underlying assumptions are rather crude. <lb/>For more detailed and decisive information on the struc-<lb/>ture and the orientation of the Ru spin order we must <lb/>await the result of neutron scattering experiments. <lb/>IV. A POSSIBLE SCENARIO FOR <lb/>COEXISTENCE OF FERROMAGNETIC-AND <lb/>SUPERCONDUCTING ORDER <lb/>Having established that the ferromagnetic and the su-<lb/>perconducting order parameter coexist on a microscopic <lb/>scale, we arrive at the important question as to how this <lb/>system manages to avoid strong pair-breaking effects. <lb/>We suspect that the answer is closely related to the lay-<lb/>ered structure of the hybrid ruthenate-cuprate compound <lb/>and, in particular, to the purely two-dimensional coher-<lb/>ent charge transport in the strongly underdoped CuO 2 <lb/>planes. We envisage a scenario where the ferromagneti-<lb/>cally ordered Ru spins are aligned in the RuO 2 plane hav-<lb/>ing a very large out-of-plane anisotropy while the charge <lb/>dynamics of the superconducting CuO 2 planes is purely <lb/>two-dimensional, i.e., coherent charge transport occurs <lb/>only along the direction of the CuO 2 planes. For such <lb/>a configuration the principal pair-breaking effect due to <lb/>the electromagnetic interaction can be minimized, since <lb/>the dot product of the magnetic vector potential (which <lb/>then is normal to the planes) and the momentum of the <lb/>Cooper pair (which is parallel to the planes) vanishes. <lb/>An additional requirement is that the direct hyperfine <lb/>interaction between the superconducting electrons of the <lb/>CuO 2 planes and the ordered Ru spins has to be ex-<lb/>tremely small. Both requirements may be fulfilled in <lb/>the present Ru-1212 system due to the confinement of <lb/>the superconducting electrons of the strongly underdoped <lb/>CuO 2 planes. The absence of magnetic pairbreaking is <lb/>suggested by the fact that the T c value is fully consistent <lb/>with the underdoped state indicated by the thermoelec-<lb/>tric power 12 . So far we have been unable to significantly <lb/>increase the doping state (by e.g. Ca substitution) so <lb/>as to explore these implications. Furthermore, we have <lb/>not yet succeeded in crystallographically aligning pow-<lb/>ders or growing single crystals which would allow one to <lb/>investigate the magnetic anisotropy. However, further <lb/>information can be obtained by examining the ferromag-<lb/>netic fluctuations above T Curie as seen in the divergence <lb/>of the susceptibility. Figure 9 shows dχ/dT plotted ver-<lb/>sus (T/T Curie -1) for the zero-field-cooled susceptibility <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

		<body>for T &gt;T Curie . The slope of -2.30(3) indicates a critical <lb/>exponent of γ = 1.30(3) consistent with 3D XY fluctu-<lb/>ations for which γ = 1.32 18 and again consistent with <lb/>orientation of the Ru-moments within the a-b plane. <lb/>-1.5 -1.0 -0.5 0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>-5 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-3 <lb/>-2 <lb/>-1 <lb/>γ = 1.30 <lb/>χ = C [ T/T Curie -1] <lb/>-γ <lb/>log[dχ/dT] <lb/>log[(T/T Curie ) -1] <lb/>FIG. 9. dχ/dT plotted versus (T/TCurie-1) for the <lb/>zero-field cooled susceptibility in the temperature range of T <lb/>&gt;TCurie. The slope of -2.30(3) indicates a critical exponent <lb/>of γ = 1.30(3) consistent with 3D XY fluctuations for which γ <lb/>= 1.32 18 and consistent with orientation of the Ru-moments <lb/>within the a-b plane. <lb/>Finally, we note that an alternative (and highly spec-<lb/>ulative) explanation for the coexistence of high-T c su-<lb/>perconductivity and ferromagnetic order in the present <lb/>Ru-1212 superconductor could be that the supercon-<lb/>ducting order parameter has a non-zero angular momen-<lb/>tum which itself breaks time-reversal symmetry. Such <lb/>a highly unconventional order parameter symmetry has <lb/>been discussed also in the context of the Sr 2 RuO 4 super-<lb/>conductor. We point out, however, that at present we <lb/>have no evidence in favor of such a scenario. <lb/>V. CONCLUSIONS <lb/>In summary, we have performed DC-magnetization <lb/>and zero-field muon spin rotation (ZF-µSR) measure-<lb/>ments which characterize the superconducting-and the <lb/>magnetic properties of the hybrid cuprate-ruthenate <lb/>compound RuSr 2 GdCu 2 O 8 . The DC-magnetization data <lb/>establish that this material exhibits ferromagnetic order <lb/>(or at least magnetic order with a sizeable ferromagnetic <lb/>component) below T Curie = 133 K and becomes super-<lb/>conducting at a much lower temperature of T c = 16 K. <lb/>We obtain evidence that superconducting charge carriers <lb/>originate from the CuO 2 planes, while the ferromagnetic <lb/>order is associated with the Ru moments with µ(Ru) ≈ <lb/>1 µ B . The larger Gd moments with µ(Gd) ≈ 7.4 µ B do <lb/>not appear to participate in the ferromagnetic transition <lb/>but remain paramagnetic to very low temperature and <lb/>undergo most likely an antiferromagnetic transition at <lb/>T N =2.6 K. The ZF-µSR experiments provide evidence <lb/>that the ferromagnetic phase is homogeneous on a mi-<lb/>croscopic scale and accounts for most of the sample vol-<lb/>ume. Furthermore, they indicate that the magnetically <lb/>ordered state is not significantly modified by the onset <lb/>of superconductivity. This rather surprising result raises <lb/>the question as to how ferromagnetic and superconduct-<lb/>ing order can coexist on a microscopic scale while avoid-<lb/>ing strong pairbreaking effects that tend to destroy su-<lb/>perconductivity. We have outlined a possible scenario <lb/>which relies on the two-dimensional charge dynamics of <lb/>the CuO 2 planes and the assumption that the ferromag-<lb/>netic order parameter of the Ru-moments is confined to <lb/>the RuO 2 layers. <lb/></body>

		<div type="acknowledgement">VI. ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We would like to acknowledge S. Kreitzman and B. <lb/>Hitti for the technical support during the µSR exper-<lb/>iments at TRIUMF. JLT thanks the Royal Society of <lb/>New Zealand for financial support under a James Cook <lb/>Fellowship. ChN and ThB thank the German BMBF for <lb/>financial support. CES and DRN were supported by US <lb/>Air Force Office of Scientific Research grant F49620-97-<lb/>1-0297. <lb/></div>

		<front>* Permanent address: Institute of Experimental Physics, Warsaw University, Hoża 69, 00-681 Warsaw, Poland; <lb/># Present address: 1318 Tenth St., Saskatoon, Canada S7H OJ3 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>1 J.G. Bednorz and K.A. Müller, Z. Phys. B64, 189 (1986) <lb/>2 R.J. Cava, Science 247, 656 (1990) <lb/>3 Y. Maeno, H. Hashimoto, K. Yoshida, S. Nishizaki, T. Fujita, J.G. Bednorz, and F. Lichtenberg, Nature 372, 532 (1994) <lb/>4 see for example, Y. Maeno, S. Nishizaki, K. Yoshida, S. Ikeda, and T. Fujita, J. Low. Temp. Phys. 105, 1577 (1996) <lb/>5 see for example, L. Klein, J.S. Dodge, C.H. Ahn, J.W. Reiner, L. Mieville, T.H. Geballe, M.R. Beasley, and A Kapitulnik, <lb/>J. Phys. Condens. Matter 8, 10111 (1996); G. Cao, S. McCall, M. Shepard, J.E. Crow, and R.P. Guertin, Phys. Rev. B 56, <lb/>321 (1997); I.I. Mazin, and D.J. Singh, Phys. Rev. B 56, 2556 (1997) <lb/>6 L. Bauernfeind, W. Widder, H.F. Braun, Physica C 254, 151 (1995); L. Bauernfeind, W. Widder, and H.F. Braun, J. Low <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

		<listBibl>Temp. Phys. 105, 1605 (1996); L. Bauernfeind, W. Widder, and H.F, Braun, Proceed. Fourth Euro Ceramics, Vol. 6, ed. by <lb/>A. Barone, D. Fiorani, A. Tampieri, Gruppo Editorale Faenza Editrice, Italy, 329 (1995) <lb/>7 I. Felner, U. Asaf, Y. Levi, and O. Millo, Phys. Rev. B 55, R3374 (1997) <lb/>8 J.L. Tallon, C. Bernhard, M.E. Bowden, T.M. Stoto, B. Walker, P.W. Gilbert, G.V.M. Williams, D.M. Pooke, and M.R. <lb/>Presland, to be published <lb/>9 V.L. Ginsburg, Sov. Phys. JETP 4, 153 (1957) <lb/>10 J.W. Loram, J.L. Tallon and K.A. Mirza, to be published <lb/>11 see for example, A. Schenck, Muon Spin Rotation: Principles and Applications in Solid State Physics (Adam Hilger, Bristol, <lb/>1986) <lb/>12 S.D. Obertelli, J.R. Cooper, and J.L. Tallon, Phys. Rev. B 46, 14928 (1992) <lb/>13 M. Weber, P. Birrer, F.N. Gygax, B. Hitti, E. Lippelt, H. Maletta, and A. Schenck, Hyperfine Interact. 63, 207 (1990); N. <lb/>Nishida and H. Miyatake, ibid. 63, 183 (1990) <lb/>14 J.W. Loram, K.A. Mirza, J.R. Cooper, and W.Y. Liang, Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 1740 (1993) <lb/>15 N.W. Ashcroft and N.D. Mermin, Solid State Physics (Holt, Rinehart and Winston, Philadelphia, 1976) <lb/>16 J.O. Willis, Z. Fisk, J.D. Thompson, S.-W.Cheong, R.A. Aiken, J.L. Smith, and E. Zirngiebl, J. Magn. Mater. 67, L139 <lb/>(1987); D.McK. Paul, H.A. Mook, A.W. Hewat, B.C. Sales, L.A. Boatner, R.J. Thompson, and M. Mostoller, Phys. Rev. B <lb/>37, 2341 (1988). <lb/>17 see for example A. Golnik, Ch. Niedermayer, E. Recknagel, M. Rossmanith, A. Weidinger, J.I. Budnick, B. Chamberland, M. <lb/>Filipkowsky, Y. Zhang, D.P. Yang, L.L. Lynds, F.A. Otter, and C. Baines, Phys. Lett. A125, 71 (1987); Ch. Niedermayer, <lb/>H. Glückler, A. Golnik, U. Binninger, M. Rauer, E. Recknagel, J.I. Budnick, and A. Weidinger, Phys. Rev. B 47, 3427 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>18 J.C. Le Guillou and J. Zinn-Justin, Phys. Rev. B 21, 3976 (1980) <lb/>19 W.A. Fertig, D.C. Johnston, L.E. DeLong, R.W. McCallum, M.B. Maple, and B.T. Mattias, Phys. Rev. Lett. 38, 987 (1977); <lb/>D.E. Moncton, D.B. McWhan, P.H. Schmidt, G. Shirane, W. Thomlinson, M.B. Maple, H.B. MacKay, L.D. Woolf, Z. Fisk, <lb/>and D.C. Johnston, Phys. Rev. Lett. 45, 2060, (1980) <lb/>20 M. Ishikawa and O. Fischer, Solid State Commun. 23, 37 (1977); P. Burlet, J. Flouquet, J.L Genicon, R. Horyn, O. Pena, <lb/>and M. Sergent, Physcia C 215, 127 (1995); J.W. Lynn, G. Shirane, W. Thomlinson, R.N. Shelton, and D.E. Moncton, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 24, 3817 (1981) <lb/>21 B.V. Sarkissian, J. Appl. Phys. 53, 8070 (1982); E.J. Ansaldo, D.R. Noakes, J.H. Brewer, R. Keitel, D.R. Harshman, M. <lb/>Semba, C.Y. Huang, and B.V.B. Sarkissian, Solid State Commun. 55, 193 (1985) <lb/>22 see for example A. Yaouanc and P. Dalmas de Reotier, J.Phys. Condens. Matter 3, 6195 (1991); P.C.M. Gubbens et al., <lb/>Hyperfine Interact. 85, 239 (1994) <lb/>23 see for example: Ch. Niedermayer, C. Bernhard, T. Blasius, A. Golnik, A. Moodenbaugh, and J.I Budnick, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>80, 3843 (1998). <lb/></listBibl>

		<body>Table 1: The local magnetic field at the muon site, B µ , obtained from the dipolar-field calculation. The results <lb/>are shown for two different muon sites and for three different orientations with the Ru moments (µ(Ru 5+ )=1 µ B ) <lb/>ferromagnetically ordered along the Ru-O bond [100], along the diagonal [110], or perpendicular to the RuO 2 planes <lb/>[001]. Note that for the [110] orientation there exist two magnetically inequivalent muon sites. <lb/>. <lb/>muon-site <lb/>[100] [110] <lb/>[001] <lb/>(0.13, 0.225, 0.16) <lb/>960 G 1068/805 G 1471 G <lb/>(0.128, 0.222, 0.175) 740 G 824/665 G 1231 G <lb/></body>

			<page>10 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
