<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9712189v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 16 Dec 1997 <lb/>Systematic behaviour of the in-plane penetration depth in d-wave cuprates <lb/>C. Panagopoulos, J.R. Cooper * and T. Xiang <lb/>Research Center in Superconductivity, University of Cambridge, Madingley Road, Cambridge CB3 0HE, United Kingdom <lb/>We report the temperature T and oxygen concentration dependences of the penetration depth of <lb/>grain-aligned YBa2Cu3O 7−δ with δ= 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43. The values of the in-plane λ ab (0) and out-<lb/>of-plane λc(0) penetration depths, the low temperature linear term in λ ab (T), and the ratio λc(0) <lb/>/λ ab (T) were found to increase with increasing δ. The systematic changes of the linear term in <lb/>λ ab (T) with Tc found here and in recent work on HgBa2Can−1CunO 2n+2+δ (n = 1 and 3) 1 are <lb/>discussed. <lb/></front>

			<body>In a recent study 1 of the c-axis coupling of d-wave <lb/>high-T c cuprates we reported the values and tempera-<lb/>ture (T) dependences of the in-plane (λ ab ) and out-of-<lb/>plane (λ c ) penetration depths for slightly overdoped 2,3 <lb/>HgBa 2 CuO 4+δ (Hg-1201) with critical temperature T c <lb/>= 93 K and slightly underdoped 4,5 HgBa 2 Ca 2 Cu 3 O 8+δ <lb/>(Hg-1223) with T c = 135 K. For both compounds the <lb/>low temperature dependence of λ ab was found to be lin-<lb/>ear as expected for d-wave superconductivity. In fact <lb/>normalised plots of [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T)] 2 versus T/T c were <lb/>the same, and like YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 (YBCO 7 ) 6 agreed very <lb/>well with mean field (MF) theory for a weak coupling <lb/>d-wave superconductor. However, recent angle-resolved <lb/>photoemission spectroscopy (ARPES) 7 and tunneling 8 <lb/>data strongly suggest that for underdoped samples the <lb/>superconducting gap, (∆ 0 ), remains constant, or even in-<lb/>creases slightly, while T c falls and so large deviations from <lb/>MF theory might be expected. We have therefore ex-<lb/>tended our investigation to deoxygenated (underdoped) <lb/>pure YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ using the same ac susceptibility tech-<lb/>nique to measure the penetration depth. 1,6,9,10 <lb/>We report experimental results for the values and tem-<lb/>perature dependences of λ ab and λ c of high quality c -axis <lb/>grain-aligned orthorhombic 11 YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (which has <lb/>two CuO 2 planes per unit cell as well as Cu-O chains) <lb/>with δ = 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43, and compare them with <lb/>tetragonal 12 Hg-1201 with one CuO 2 plane per unit cell <lb/>and tetragonal 13 Hg-1223 with three CuO 2 planes per <lb/>unit cell. We find that the presence of the linear term <lb/>in λ ab (T) is independent of the number of CuO 2 planes <lb/>per unit cell, carrier concentration, crystal structure, <lb/>anisotropy and the presence of chains. Surprisingly our <lb/>data show good agreement with weak coupling d-wave <lb/>theory, and the linear term in [λ ab (T) / λ ab (0)] appears <lb/>to scale with T /T c . This result highlights the need for <lb/>detailed consideration of the relationship between super-<lb/>conducting and normal state energy gaps in underdoped <lb/>cuprates. <lb/>Sample preparation was carried out by the standard <lb/>solid state reaction process using high purity (99.999%) <lb/>Y 2 O 3 , BaCO 3 and CuO oxides. Electron probe micro-<lb/>analysis and x-ray diffraction showed that all samples <lb/>were single phase within an accuracy of ≈ 1%. The fully <lb/>oxygenated, δ = 0.0 (YBCO 7 , T c = 92 K), samples were <lb/>prepared by annealing bulk pieces in pure oxygen atmo-<lb/>sphere at 380 o C for 24 hours and then slowly cooling to <lb/>room temperature. (Hereafter T c represents the temper-<lb/>ature where the onset of superconductivity occurs in the <lb/>ac susceptibility data for a measuring field H ac = 3 G <lb/>rms and frequency f = 333 Hz.) The δ = 0.3 (YBCO 6.7 , <lb/>T c = 66 K) sample was prepared by annealing in pure <lb/>oxygen atmosphere at 650 o C for 12 h and then quench-<lb/>ing in liquid nitrogen, while the δ = 0.43 (YBCO 6.57 , T c <lb/>= 56 K) sample was annealed in 0.2% O 2 / N 2 atmo-<lb/>sphere at 550 o C for 12 hours and also quenched into liq-<lb/>uid nitrogen. The final oxygen contents were determined <lb/>from the weight change of a fully oxygenated reference <lb/>sample. The δ = 0.0 bulk piece was lightly ground and <lb/>sedimented in acetone to obtain a well-defined grain size <lb/>distribution. The sedimented powders were then heat <lb/>treated to repair any structural damages to the surface <lb/>of the grains. 14 For δ = 0.3 and 0.43 on the other hand <lb/>a bulk piece for each δ was lightly ground and sieved <lb/>through a 20 µm sieve in an argon glove box to obtain a <lb/>well-defined grain size distribution 10 and to avoid surface <lb/>degradation of the crystallites. 14 The collected powders <lb/>were then kept in argon atmosphere for 30 min before be-<lb/>ing aligned. All powders, δ = 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43, were mag-<lb/>netically aligned in epoxy as described earlier. 1,6,10 The <lb/>average grain diameters corresponding to the 50% cumu-<lb/>lative volume point were 5 and 10 µm for the fully oxy-<lb/>genated and the oxygen deficient samples, respectively. <lb/>The fraction of the unoriented powder in all grain aligned <lb/>samples was estimated to be &lt; 5 %. Rocking curve anal-<lb/>ysis of the δ = 0.0 and δ &gt; 0.0 samples gave a full width <lb/>at half maximum of ± 1.4 and 1 o , respectively. 15 Low <lb/>field susceptibility, χ, measurements were performed us-<lb/>ing commercial equipment (down to 4.2 K) for samples <lb/>with δ = 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43. The sample with δ = 0.43 was <lb/>also measured down to 1.2 K using a home built suscep-<lb/>tometer. Details of the experimental technique and the <lb/>application of London&apos;s model for deriving λ from the <lb/>measured χ in cuprate superconductors can be found in <lb/>earlier publications. 1,6,9,10,16 <lb/>The values of λ ab (0) derived from our data are 0.14, <lb/>0.21 and 0.28 µm and the corresponding values for λ c (0) <lb/>are 1.26, 4.53 and 7.17 µm for δ = 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43, <lb/>respectively. The errors in λ ab (0) arising from a pos-<lb/>sible uncertainty of ± 5% in the alignment can be as <lb/>high as ± 25%, whereas those in λ c (0) are ± 8%. How-<lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>ever, the corresponding uncertainty in the linear term in <lb/>[λ ab (T)/λ ab (0)] is much less, at most ± 10%. The present <lb/>results differ from previous work 17 in which the surfaces <lb/>of the particles were probably not as clean and the degree <lb/>of grain alignment was probably lower. As T c is reduced <lb/>by lowering the carrier concentration (for δ = 0.3 and <lb/>0.43), [1 / λ ab <lb/>2 (0)] falls, a behaviour which has been ex-<lb/>tensively discussed in terms of the Uemura relation. 18,19 <lb/>The ratio γ = [λ c (0) / λ ab (0)] i.e. the anisotropy, in-<lb/>creases with oxygen deficiency. <lb/>Figures 1(a) and 1(b), show characteristic low temper-<lb/>ature plots of [λ(T) / λ(0)] for the ab-plane (measured <lb/>with the applied field H c) and c-axis (measured with <lb/>H ab), respectively, for the three oxygen concentrations <lb/>studied. The low temperature (T / T c &lt; 0.25) linear term <lb/>in λ ab (T), is 4.8Å/K for YBCO 7 in good agreement with <lb/>that found from microwave measurements on YBCO 6.95 <lb/>single crystals. 20 As oxygen is removed from the lattice <lb/>(the chains) the linear term increases to 12 and 20Å /K <lb/>for δ = 0.3 and 0.43, respectively. For YBCO 7 we also <lb/>observe a linear T dependence in λ c at low temperatures <lb/>but the relative change is about a factor of two smaller <lb/>than in [λ ab (T) / λ ab (0)], while λ c (T) of YBCO 6.7 and <lb/>YBCO 6.57 obeys a T 2 behaviour at low T. Details of the <lb/>systematics of λ c (T) of cuprate superconductors can be <lb/>found in Refs [1,6,21,22]. <lb/>In Fig. 2 we present normalised plots of [λ ab (0) <lb/>/λ ab (T)] 2 and [λ c (0) /λ c (T)] 2 versus T /T c . There is ex-<lb/>cellent agreement between the [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 curves <lb/>for the three oxygen concentrations. The data in Fig. <lb/>2(a) are compared with the weak coupling theory for a <lb/>d-wave superconductor (solid line). 23 It can be seen that <lb/>the d-wave curve fits the data very well. On the other <lb/>hand the [λ c (0) / λ c (T )] 2 curves do not fit the d-wave <lb/>curve and also differ from each other slightly, because of <lb/>the effect of the interplane coupling on λ c (T). 1,6,10,21,22 <lb/>We also find that [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 of YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ <lb/>agrees with that of Hg-1201 and Hg-1223. 1,10 The be-<lb/>haviour of [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 is generally similar to that <lb/>of YBa 2 (Cu 1−x Zn x ) 3 O 7 (x =0.02 and 0.03), 6 except at <lb/>very low temperatures where a T 2 term developed in the <lb/>Zn doped samples due to impurity scattering. <lb/>The full temperature dependences of [λ ab (0) / <lb/>λ ab (T )] 2 for YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (δ = 0.0, 0.3 and 0.43), <lb/>YBa 2 (Cu 1−x Zn x ) 3 O 7 (x =0.02 and 0.03), Hg-1201 and <lb/>Hg-1223 are also in agreement with recent data of <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ (Bi-2212) 24 and Tl 2 Ba 2 CuO 6+δ (Tl-<lb/>2201) 25 single crystals measured by a microwave tech-<lb/>nique with H c, but they only agree with another set of <lb/>microwave data (H c) for Bi-2212 single crystals 26 at T <lb/>/T c &lt; 0.3. At higher temperatures the data in Ref. [26] <lb/>deviate from the weak-coupling d-wave calculation. In-<lb/>dependent evidence for the scaling behaviour of [λ ab (0) / <lb/>λ ab (T )] 2 with T /T c can also be found in a recent publica-<lb/>tion by Bonn et al, 27 who measured the relative changes <lb/>in λ with temperature for underdoped, optimally doped <lb/>and slightly overdoped untwinned YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ crystals <lb/>using a microwave technique and H ⊥ c. However, in Ref. <lb/>[27] the changes of [λ a,b (0) / λ a,b (T )] 2 for YBCO 6.95 , at <lb/>high temperatures, and YBCO 6.6 , over the whole tem-<lb/>perature range, were smaller than ours and closer, at <lb/>high temperatures, to the Bi-2212 data in Ref. [26]. We <lb/>do not know the precise origin of this difference but we <lb/>believe that for weakly coupled layers, data taken with <lb/>H c give the best measure of the superfluid density. <lb/>Figure 3 shows plots of 1-[λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 vs T which <lb/>is equivalent to [n s (0) -n s (T)] / n s (0), i.e. the nor-<lb/>malised density of quasiparticle excitations, where n s (T) <lb/>is the density of condensed electrons at a temperature <lb/>T, for all the samples studied. It is clear that the linear <lb/>term in 1-[λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 increases as T c decreases. <lb/>If we use the standard BCS result for λ(T ) of a d-wave <lb/>superconductor, 28 <lb/>λ(0) <lb/>λ(T ) <lb/>2 <lb/>≈ 1 − <lb/>(2 ln 2)T <lb/>∆ 0 <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>to fit the experimental data shown in Fig. 3 (at T / <lb/>T c &lt; 0.25) we find that ∆ 0 scales approximately with T c <lb/>[Fig. 3 (inset)], giving ∆ 0 ≈ 2T c , a value close to that ex-<lb/>pected for weak-coupling superconductivity. 28 For com-<lb/>parison we also include data for the s-wave perovskite <lb/>Ba 0.6 K 0.4 BiO 3 (BKBO). 10 The compounds Bi-2212 24,26 <lb/>and Tl-2201 25 would also give ∆ 0 ≈ 2T c on this plot. <lb/>The maximum error in the linear terms i.e. the values of <lb/>∆ 0 in Fig. 3 (inset), is ± 20 %. <lb/>The scaling of ∆ 0 with T c , Fig. 3 (inset), is in <lb/>agreement with early tunneling spectroscopy data 29 for <lb/>several cuprates as a function of carrier concentration, <lb/>ranging from the underdoped to the optimally doped <lb/>regimes. It is not consistent however, with more recent <lb/>tunneling 8 and ARPES 7 results for underdoped cuprates <lb/>where ∆ 0 was actually found to increase slightly while <lb/>T c falls. There seems to be two possible ways of ac-<lb/>counting this discrepancy. One is that the recent spectro-<lb/>scopic experiments 7,8 actually measure the normal state <lb/>gap. In this scenario the effect of the normal state gap <lb/>would be to leave small pockets of holes whose supercon-<lb/>ducting properties are still described reasonably well by <lb/>MF theory. The other is similar to a recent phenomeno-<lb/>logical approach. 30 As shown in Fig. 4, it is probable, <lb/>that within experimental error, the unnormalised plots of <lb/>[1/λ ab (T ) 2 ], i.e. n s (T), versus T at low temperatures are <lb/>parallel for samples with different T c values. This would <lb/>correspond to the same number of excited quasiparticles, <lb/>[n s (0) -n s (T)], at a given temperature for all T c values-<lb/>as implied by specific heat work on underdoped YBCO. 31 <lb/>Such parallel shifts give [n s (0) -n s (T)] = aT, where a is <lb/>independent of doping level (T c ). In combination with <lb/>the well-known Uemura relation n s (0) ∝ T c , 18 this gives <lb/>[1-n s (T) /n s (0)] = b T /T c , where b is independent of <lb/>T c . So at low T, [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 versus T/T c would <lb/>still scale on to a single curve even when the MF relation <lb/>∆ 0 / T c ≈ 2, is strongly violated. <lb/>In conclusion, we have studied λ ab (T) and λ c (T) of <lb/>high quality grain-aligned YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ with δ = 0.0, <lb/>0.3 and 0.43. The values of λ ab (0), λ c (0) and γ were <lb/>found to increase with oxygen deficiency. We find that <lb/>the existence of the linear term in λ ab (T) is independent <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

		<body>of the number of CuO 2 planes per unit cell, carrier con-<lb/>centration, crystal structure, anisotropy and the presence <lb/>of chains. If viewed in isolation, all the penetration depth <lb/>data presented here and most of the microwave measure-<lb/>ments for H c appear to be in excellent agreement with <lb/>mean field theory for a weak coupling d-wave supercon-<lb/>ductor for which ∆ 0 / T c ≈ 2. However, recent spectro-<lb/>scopic data are more consistent with a different approach <lb/>30 in which there is a strong interplay between the super-<lb/>conducting and normal state gaps. Clearly the relation-<lb/>ship between these two gaps is of crucial importance for <lb/>understanding superconductivity in the cuprates. <lb/></body>

		<div type="acknowledgement">We thank J.W. Loram and P.A. Lee for enlightening <lb/>discussions and B. Mace for his assistance with the pow-<lb/>der preparation. One of us (C.P) would like to thank <lb/>Trinity College, Cambridge for financial support. This <lb/>work is supported by E.P.S.R.C of the United Kingdom. <lb/>* On leave from the Institute of Physics, The Univer-<lb/>sity of Zagreb, P.O. Box 304, Zagreb, Croatia. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. C. Panagopoulos et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 2320 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>2 G. B. Peacock, I. Gameson, and P. P. Edwards (in <lb/>preparation). <lb/>3 Q. Xiong et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 10 346 (1994). <lb/>4 G. B. Peacock, I. Gameson, and P. P. Edwards, Adv. <lb/>Mater. 9, 240 (1997). <lb/>5 A. Carrington et al., Physica C 234, 1 (1994); C.K. <lb/>Subramaniam, M. Paranthaman and A.B. Kaiser, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 51, 1330 (1995). <lb/>6 C. Panagopoulos, J.R. Cooper, N. Athanassopoulou <lb/>and J.Chrosch, Phys. Rev. B 54, R12 721 (1996). <lb/>7 See for example: J.M. Harris et al., Phys. Rev. B <lb/>54, R15 665 (1996). <lb/>8 M. Oda et al., Physica C (in press). <lb/>9 A. Porch et al., Physica C 214, 350 (1993). <lb/>10 C. Panagopoulos et al., Phys. Rev. B 53, R2999 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>11R. Beyers and T.M. Shaw in &quot;Solid State Physics <lb/>-Volume 42&quot; edited by H. Ehrenreich and D. Turnbull <lb/>(Academic press, inc. London 1989). <lb/>12 J.L. Wagner et al., Physica C 210, 447 (1993). <lb/>13 J.L. Wagner, B.A. Hunter, D.G. Hinks and J.D. <lb/>Jorgensen, Phys. Rev. B 51, 15 407 (1995). <lb/>14 C. Panagopoulos, W. Zhou, N. Athanassopoulou <lb/>and J.R. Cooper, Physica C 269, 157 (1996). <lb/>15 J. Chrosch et al., Physica C 265, 233 (1996). <lb/>16 D. Shoenberg, Superconductivity (Cambridge Uni-<lb/>versity Press, Cambridge, 1954), p.164. <lb/>17 N. Athanassopoulou, J.R. Cooper and J. Chrosch, <lb/>Physica C 235-240, 1835 (1994). <lb/>18 Y.J. Uemura et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 66, 2665 <lb/>(1991). <lb/>19 J. L. Tallon et al, Phys. Rev. Lett. 74, 1008 (1995). <lb/>20 W. N. Hardy et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, 3999 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>21 T. Xiang and J.M. Wheatley, Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, <lb/>4632 (1996). <lb/>22 T. Xiang and J.M. Wheatley, Phys. Rev. Lett. 76, <lb/>134 (1996). <lb/>23 A.J. Schofield (private communication). <lb/>24 S.F. Lee et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 735 (1996). <lb/>25 D. Broun et al., Phys. Rev. B (submitted). <lb/>26 T. Jakobs et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, 4516 (1995). <lb/>27 D.A. Bonn et al., Czech. J. Phys. 46 S6, 3195 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>28 K. Maki and H. Won, J. Phys. I France 6, 1 (1996). <lb/>29 For reviews see: J.R. Kirtley, Int. J. of Mod. Phys. <lb/>B 4, 201 (1990); T. Hasegawa, H. Ikuta and K. Kitazawa, <lb/>Physical Properties of High Temperature Superconduc-<lb/>tors, edited by D.M. Ginsberg (World Scientific, Singa-<lb/>pore, 1992), Volume III, chap. 7, p.525. <lb/>30 P.A. Lee and X-G Wen, Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, 4111 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>31 J.W. Loram et al, Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 1740 (1993). <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIGURE CAPTIONS <lb/>1 <lb/>1.01 <lb/>1.02 <lb/>1.03 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>[λ (Τ) / λ (0)] <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>(b) <lb/>1 <lb/>1.06 <lb/>1.12 <lb/>[λ (Τ) / λ (0)] <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>(a) <lb/>FIG. 1. Low temperature plots of (a) [λ ab (T) / λ ab (0)] <lb/>and (b) [λc(T) / λc(0)] for YBCO7 (closed circles), YBCO6.7 <lb/>(open circles) and YBCO6.57 (open squares). The Tc, λ ab (0) <lb/>and λc(0) values are given in the text. <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 1 <lb/>[λ (0) / λ (Τ)] 2 <lb/>T / T c <lb/>c <lb/>c <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>[λ (0) / λ (Τ)] 2 <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>(a) <lb/>FIG. 2. Plots of (a) [λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 and (b) [λc(0) / <lb/>λc(T )] 2 as functions of T /Tc for YBCO7 (closed circles), <lb/>YBCO6.7 (open circles) and YBCO6.57 (open squares). The <lb/>solid line in (a) is the theoretical prediction for the normalised <lb/>superfluid density from the weak coupling BCS theory for a <lb/>d-wave superconductor. 23 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>1 − [λ (0) / λ (Τ)] 2 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>T <lb/>c (K) <lb/>2∆ 0 <lb/>(Κ) <lb/>BKBO <lb/>YBCO 6.57 <lb/>YBCO 6.7 <lb/>YBCO 7 <lb/>Hg-1201 <lb/>Hg-1223 <lb/>FIG. 3. Low temperature plot of 1-[λ ab (0) / λ ab (T )] 2 for <lb/>Hg-1223 [λ ab (0) = 1770 ± 300Å] (closed triangles), 1 Hg-1201 <lb/>[λ ab (0) 1710 ± 250Å] (open triangles), 1 YBCO7 (closed cir-<lb/>cles), YBCO6.7 (open circles) and YBCO6.57 (open squares). <lb/>Inset: Tc versus 2∆0 as derived from the plot in the main <lb/>panel (see text for details). BKBO is included for compari-<lb/>son. The solid line is drawn as a guide to the eye. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>1 / λ 2 <lb/>(µ −2 <lb/>) <lb/>m <lb/>ab <lb/>FIG. 4. Low temperature plot of [1/λ 2 <lb/>ab (T)] (i.e. ns) for <lb/>YBCO6.57 (open squares) and Hg-1201 (open triangles) show-<lb/>ing the approximate parallel shift of ns with Tc as discussed <lb/>in the text. The dashed lines, immediately above and be-<lb/>low each data set, indicate the maximum possible error in <lb/>1/λ 2 <lb/>ab (T) arising from ± 5% uncertainty in the alignment (see <lb/>text). <lb/></body>

			<page>4 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
