<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9610032v3 [cond-mat.supr-con] 24 Apr 1997 <lb/>New features in the microwave response of Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 crystals : Evidence for a <lb/>multi-component order parameter <lb/>H.Srikanth, B. A. Willemsen, T.Jacobs and S.Sridhar <lb/>Physics Department, Northeastern University, 360 Huntington Avenue, Boston, <lb/>MA 02115 <lb/>A.Erb, E.Walker and R.Flükiger <lb/>DPMC, Université de Genéve, CH-1211 Genéve 4, Switzerland <lb/>(September 4, 1996) <lb/>New features are reported in precision measurements of the complex microwave conductivity of <lb/>high quality Y Ba2Cu3O6.95 crystals grown in BaZrO3 crucibles. A third peak in the normal conduc-<lb/>tivity, σ1(T ), at around 80K, and enhanced pair conductivity σ2(T ) below ∼ 65K are observed. The <lb/>data are inconsistent with a single order parameter, and instead are indicative of multi-component <lb/>superconductivity. Overall, these results point to the presence of multiple pairing interactions in <lb/>Y Ba2Cu3O6.95 and also provide a natural explanation to account for the low temperature 35K <lb/>conductivity peak observed in all Y Ba2Cu3O6.95 crystals. <lb/> PACS: 74.25.Nf, 74.72.-h, 74.72.Bk <lb/></front>

			<body>The mechanism for superconductivity and the nature <lb/>of the superconducting state in the cuprates continue to <lb/>be prime issues that are being debated [1]. Microwave <lb/>measurements have yielded important information on the <lb/>nature of the pairing, the quasiparticle density of states <lb/>and scattering in the cuprate superconductors [2-4]. Sur-<lb/>face impedance of Y BCO single crystals in the past have <lb/>consistently shown two features: A linear penetration <lb/>depth (λ(T ) ∝ T ) over a limited low T range, and the <lb/>presence of a bump in the surface resistance R s (T ) which <lb/>results in a peak in the normal conductivity σ 1 (T ) at <lb/>∼ 35K well below the superconducting T c ∼ 93K [2,5]. <lb/>The former behavior has been attributed to d − wave <lb/>order parameter symmetry or in general, the presence <lb/>of nodes in the gap. A rapidly decreasing quasiparticle <lb/>scattering rate below T c has been proposed to account for <lb/>the latter feature [5,6]. There is a general consensus that <lb/>the experimental results can be explained in the frame-<lb/>work of a single d − wave order parameter with inclusion <lb/>of effects due to strong coupling, scattering with strong <lb/>temperature dependence, and fluctuations [5,7]. <lb/>In this paper, we present new results on the microwave <lb/>response of high quality Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 single crystals <lb/>grown by a new method which avoids crucible corro-<lb/>sion. We measure the temperature dependent surface <lb/>impedance Z s = R s + iX s and penetration depth λ <lb/>(= X s /µ 0 ω) from which we extract the complex con-<lb/>ductivity σ s = σ 1 − iσ 2 . The two features mentioned <lb/>above, λ(T ) ∝ T at low T and the 35K peak in σ 1 are <lb/>still present in these crystals. However in addition, a <lb/>new peak in σ 1 (T ) at ∼ 80K and a distinct increase in <lb/>σ 2 (T ) below ∼ 65K are observed. A single d − wave <lb/>order parameter is insufficient to describe the new data, <lb/>and instead we show that an analysis in terms of two-<lb/>component superconductivity is necessary. <lb/>The single crystals (typically 1.3 × 1.3 × 0.1mm 3 in <lb/>size) used in this work were of very high quality grown <lb/>from BaZrO 3 crucibles (BZO) [8]. This growth method <lb/>leads to crystals with extremely clean surfaces and excep-<lb/>tional purity exceeding 99.995% [9] in contrast to crystals <lb/>grown in other crucibles which have final reported puri-<lb/>ties of 99.5 − 99.95% [10,11]. As shown in this paper, <lb/>this difference in purity appears to play a significant role <lb/>in the microwave properties. Standard oxygen annealing <lb/>procedures were followed to obtain optimally doped crys-<lb/>tals with oxygen stoichiometry around O 6.95 [12]. The <lb/>crystals have T c = 93.4K, and very sharp transitions <lb/>in R s (T ) and SQUID magnetic susceptibility measure-<lb/>ments. Crystals grown by this method also have unique <lb/>physical properties due to their exceptional purity, as re-<lb/>vealed in other experiments [13,14]. Unlike the case in <lb/>earlier crystals, the vortex lattice was imaged for the first <lb/>time in Y BCO with a low temperature STM [13]. Spe-<lb/>cific heat measurements indicated extremely sharp jumps <lb/>at T c [14]. <lb/>Three crystals of optimally doped Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 <lb/>grown in BZO crucibles (hereafter called Y BCO/BZO) <lb/>were measured. <lb/>In addition, measurements on <lb/>a Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 crystal (of comparable dimen-<lb/>sions) grown in the commonly used yttria-stabilized <lb/>zirconia(Y SZ) crucible (hereafter called Y BCO/Y SZ <lb/>) are also presented for comparison. <lb/>The high precision microwave measurements were car-<lb/>ried out in a 10GHz N b cavity using a &quot;hot finger&quot; tech-<lb/>nique [15]. This method has been extensively validated <lb/>for precision measurements of the surface impedance in <lb/>cuprate [3] and other superconductors. All measurements <lb/>reported in this paper were carried out with the mi-<lb/>crowave field H rf ĉ so that currents flow predominantly <lb/>in the ab planes. Any influence due to c − axis properties <lb/>[4] or finite size effects are minimal as the results obtained <lb/>on three samples with slightly different dimensions and <lb/>varying edge geometries were identical. <lb/>The T dependence of λ(T ) of Y BCO/BZO and <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>Y BCO/Y SZ crystals are shown in Fig.1. The data for <lb/>the new high purity Y BCO/BZO crystals clearly re-<lb/>veal a new feature -a bump or plateau in the vicinity <lb/>of 60 − 80K, which has not been reported in any previ-<lb/>ous λ(T ) data for Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ crystals. A plateau in <lb/>λ(T ) similar to that observed here has been reported in <lb/>films and was attributed there to a 2-gap behavior [16]. <lb/>The surface resistance R s (T ) is also displayed in Fig.1 <lb/>as a function of T /T c . At low temperatures all samples <lb/>showed the non-monotonic behavior in R s that is well-<lb/>known and the low temperature values are comparable <lb/>to that seen previously [5,6]. However at intermediate <lb/>temperatures, a new feature is seen -a shoulder in R s in <lb/>the Y BCO/BZO sample which is completely absent in <lb/>the Y BCO/Y SZ sample. We emphasize that the data <lb/>for Y BCO/Y SZ is representative of that reported in lit-<lb/>erature [5,2,17]. <lb/>These new features are best studied in terms of the <lb/>complex conductivity σ s = σ 1 − iσ 2 = iµ 0 ω/(R s + iX s ) 2 . <lb/>The pair conductivity σ 2 vs. T is shown in Fig.2, <lb/>and is a measure of the superfluid density n s (T ), since <lb/>σ 2 = n s (T )e 2 /mω = 1/[µ 0 ωλ 2 (T )] . Although only <lb/>changes ∆λ(T ) ≡ λ(T ) − λ(4.2K) and correspondingly <lb/>∆X s = µ 0 ω∆λ are measured in the experiment, the ab-<lb/>solute value of X s and hence λ are obtained by assum-<lb/>ing the normal state R n = X n at and slightly above <lb/>T c . This procedure yields a consistent value of λ(0) ≈ <lb/>1000Å for all the Y BCO/BZO crystals and a value of <lb/>λ(0) ≈ 1400Å for the Y BCO/Y SZ crystal. The σ 2 (T ) <lb/>data indicates an additional onset of pair conductivity <lb/>below around 60 − 70K, never observed in previous crys-<lb/>tals reported to date as is evident from the comparison <lb/>with the plot for the Y BCO/Y SZ crystal. Also the pair <lb/>conductivity σ 2 (T ) rises to a higher value in the BZO <lb/>grown crystals compared with the Y SZ grown crystals. <lb/>All the Y BCO/BZO crystals showed this feature in the <lb/>data. While the accuracy of ∆λ ∼ 1Å, the uncertainty in <lb/>λ(0) is much larger, perhaps of order 100 − 300Å. Never-<lb/>theless, the results are consistent with a lower λ(0) and <lb/>hence enhanced pair conductivity in the Y BCO/BZO <lb/>crystals compared with the Y BCO/Y SZ crystals. <lb/>The resultant plot of the normal conductivity σ 1 (T ) <lb/>is shown in Fig.3. The low temperature peak at around <lb/>35K (labeled A) is observed in several previous measure-<lb/>ments on crystals [5,6]. Note that very near T c a sharp <lb/>peak (labeled C) is also present (see insets to Fig.3) in <lb/>all Y BCO/BZO and Y BCO/Y SZ samples and which <lb/>is often attributed to fluctuations [17]. The sharpness of <lb/>these peaks in the Y BCO/BZO crystals attests to the <lb/>high quality of these crystals. The most striking feature <lb/>is a new (third) conductivity peak (labeled B) clearly vis-<lb/>ible in the Y BCO/BZO data centered at approximately <lb/>80K (∼ 0.9T c ), which has not been reported previously <lb/>in microwave measurements. <lb/>It is clear that the Y BCO/BZO crystals reveal two <lb/>new and important features in the data -(i) the addi-<lb/>tional enhancement of pair conductivity σ 2 with an onset <lb/>around 60 − 70K, indicative of enhanced pairing below <lb/>this temperature, and (ii) the new third normal conduc-<lb/>tivity peak at around 80K (∼ 0.9T c ) in σ 1 (T ). The for-<lb/>mer was observed in all the Y BCO/BZO crystals, while <lb/>the 80K peak in σ 1 is more sensitive to sample details, <lb/>particularly the normal state scattering, and was lower in <lb/>one of the samples which had the highest R n .(Details of <lb/>results on the other Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 and also on specially <lb/>oxygenated Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7.0 crystals will be published else-<lb/>where). <lb/>The data of Fig.1 for the new Y BCO/BZO samples is <lb/>difficult to describe using a single order parameter below <lb/>T c . This is evident from the curve for λ −2 (T ) obtained <lb/>from a weak-coupling d-wave calculation shown in Fig.3. <lb/>In the &quot;hydrodynamic&quot; limit, <lb/>σ 1s,d (T ) <lb/>= <lb/>n qp (T )e 2 τ (T )/m. A single peak in σ 1 (T ) can arise from <lb/>a combination of increasing τ and decreasing n qp as T <lb/>is lowered. Except for detailed dependences on T , this <lb/>peak should occur for an s-or d-wave superconductor <lb/>and even in a two-fluid model. (The BCS coherence <lb/>peak for an s-wave superconductor is masked by this <lb/>effect). In order to describe the conductivity data in <lb/>earlier Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ crystals [5,18] in the framework <lb/>of a d-wave model, one needs a dramatic drop in the <lb/>scattering rate below T c . However any model using a <lb/>single gap or order parameter (s-or d-wave) will only <lb/>lead to a single conductivity peak, in disagreement with <lb/>the present data. <lb/>Instead it is necessary to consider a two-component <lb/>system to understand the new data. The new feature in <lb/>the σ 2 (T ) data suggests that there is additional pairing of <lb/>carriers below approximately 60−70K. The essential fea-<lb/>tures of the data can be well described by a simple model <lb/>of two superconducting components with T cA = 65K and <lb/>T cB = 93K. We have calculated the total conductivity <lb/>σ s ≡ σ 1 − iσ 2 = (σ 1A + σ 1B ) − i(σ 2A + σ 2B ). For ease of <lb/>calculation we used s-wave order parameters for both the <lb/>A and B components to calculate the conductivities using <lb/>Mattis-Bardeen expressions. In the case of σ 2 , calcula-<lb/>tions assuming s and d which is closer to the realistic case <lb/>are also presented. Gap values of ∆ A (0)/kT cA = 1.5 and <lb/>∆ B (0)/kT cB = 2.8 were used. For σ 1 , temperature de-<lb/>pendent scattering times τ A,B = τ oA,B /(1 + (T /T * <lb/>A,B ) 4 ), <lb/>with τ 0A /τ 0B = 2, T * <lb/>A = 37K, T * <lb/>B = 83K were assumed. <lb/>The calculations reproduce the essential features of the <lb/>data , viz. the onset of pairing around 60K observed in <lb/>σ 2 (T ),and the 2 peaks in σ 1 (T ), as shown in Fig.4. Al-<lb/>though we have used two decoupled components in the <lb/>above model for illustrative purposes, a small attractive <lb/>coupling between the two components is probably essen-<lb/>tial. It is easy to show in the framework of Ginzburg-<lb/>Landau theory [19] that such coupling does not change <lb/>the results much, and the essential features of the data <lb/>are retained in more elaborate models. <lb/>The microwave measurements do not directly yield the <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>symmetry of the order parameter in the A and B com-<lb/>ponents, except as can be inferred from the temperature <lb/>dependence of the data. The fact that λ(T ) is linear at <lb/>low temperatures would indicate that pairing in compo-<lb/>nent A could be d-wave like, exhibiting nodes in the gap. <lb/>Several theories have suggested the strong possibility of <lb/>a mixed s + d state in the presence of orthorhombic dis-<lb/>tortion as is the case in Y BCO [20,21], and detailed BCS <lb/>calculations, such as those in ref. [20] of coupled s-d mix-<lb/>tures do yield penetration depth (λ −2 (T ) vs. T ) curves <lb/>similar to the present σ 2 (T ) data. <lb/>It is tempting to assign the two superconducting com-<lb/>ponents A and B with the associated condensates re-<lb/>siding on Cu − O planes and chains respectively in the <lb/>Y BCO system. However such an interpretation might <lb/>be inappropriate given the facts that the crystals are <lb/>twinned and microwaves probe a length scale spanning <lb/>several hundred unit cells. Instead the two sets of con-<lb/>densates may originate from different types of pairing as-<lb/>sociated with different regions of the Fermi surface. Such <lb/>a scenario based on band structure taking into account <lb/>the chain-plane coupling in Y BCO and eventually lead-<lb/>ing to two types of pairing interactions has been proposed <lb/>[21]. <lb/>Our results resolve an important issue regarding the <lb/>origin of the conductivity peak at 35K. While in pre-<lb/>vious cases, it was necessary to invoke a precipitous <lb/>drop in the scattering rate to account for its location, <lb/>it is natural from Figs.2 and 3 to associate the low T <lb/>(35K) peak with the A-(T cA ≈ 60K) component and <lb/>not the B (T cB ≈ 93K) component. The location at <lb/>35K (∼ 0.5T cA ) is now not unreasonable for a con-<lb/>ductivity peak associated with onset of pairing at T cA . <lb/>This implies that the type-A condensate is present in <lb/>the Y BCO/Y SZ samples also but has a weaker, al-<lb/>most gapless, temperature dependence. We therefore be-<lb/>lieve that the same mechanisms were operating in ear-<lb/>lier samples also but are clearly distinguished in the new <lb/>Y BCO/BZO crystals. <lb/>A natural suspicion that arises is whether the data <lb/>in the new Y BCO/BZO crystals arise from inadequate <lb/>oxygen annealing leading to macroscopic chemical phase <lb/>separation. It is important to note that the anneal-<lb/>ing procedures for the Y BCO/BZO crystals were ex-<lb/>actly the same as for the Y BCO/Y SZ crystals [12]. <lb/>An estimate suggests that the data cannot be explained <lb/>by macroscopic segregation of an O 6.5 60K phase and <lb/>an ideal O 7 90K phase. For O 6.95 one would require <lb/>∼ 6 − 10% of the 60K phase which cannot however ac-<lb/>count for the relative weights of the two components in <lb/>our σ 2 (T ) data. Instead, our data points to a physical <lb/>mechanism like interlayer coupling rather than to chem-<lb/>ical segregation for our results. <lb/>In conclusion, measurements of the microwave prop-<lb/>erties of ultra-pure Y Ba 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ crystals reveal new <lb/>features suggesting the presence of two superconduct-<lb/>ing components in this compound. Our work provides a <lb/>possible explanation for the 35K microwave conductivity <lb/>peak, and yields new insights into the pairing mechanism <lb/>in the high temperature superconductors. <lb/>Work at Northeastern was supported by NSF-DMR-<lb/>9623720, and at Geneva by the Fonds National Su-<lb/>isse de la Recherche Scientifique. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank R.S. <lb/>Markiewicz, A. Junod and J. Halbritter for useful dis-<lb/>cussions, D.P.Choudhury and Z.Zhai for assistance. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] J. R. Kirtley, C. C. Tsuei, and L. S. Yu-Jahnes, Nature <lb/>373, 225 (1995). <lb/>[2] W. N. Hardy et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, 3999 (1993). <lb/>[3] T. Jacobs et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, 4516 (1995). <lb/>[4] S. F. Lee et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 735 (1996). <lb/>[5] T. Jacobs et al., J. Phys. Chem. Solids 6, 1945 (1995). <lb/>[6] D. A. Bonn, P. Donsajh, R. Liang, and W. N. Hardy, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 68, 2390 (1992). <lb/>[7] P. J. Hirschfeld, W. O. Putikka, and D. J. Scalapino, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 50, 10250 (1994). <lb/>[8] A. Erb, E. Walker, and R. Flükiger, Physica C 245, 245 <lb/>(1995). <lb/>[9] A. Erb, E. Walker, and R. Flükiger, Physica C 258, 9 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[10] H. Ikuta and D. M. Ginsberg, J. Supercond. 9, 259 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[11] H. Casalta et al., Physica C 258, 321 (1996). <lb/>[12] A. Erb, E. Walker, and R. Flukiger, Physica C 259, 83 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[13] I. Maggio-Aprile et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, 2754 (1995). <lb/>[14] M. Roulin, A. Junod, A. Erb, and E. Walker, J. Low <lb/>Temp. Phys. 105, 1099 (1996). <lb/>[15] S. Sridhar and W. L. Kennedy, Rev. Sci. Instrum. 59, <lb/>531 (1988). <lb/>[16] N. Klein et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 3355 (1993). <lb/>[17] S. M. Anlage, J. Mao, and J. L. Peng, Phys. Rev. B 53, <lb/>2792 (1996). <lb/>[18] P. J. Hirschfeld, W. O. Putikka, and D. J. Scalapino, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 3705 (1993). <lb/>[19] J. Betouras and R. Joynt, Europhys. Lett. 31, 119 (1995). <lb/>[20] C. O&apos;Donovan and J. P. Carbotte, Phys. Rev. B 52, <lb/>16208 (1995). <lb/>[21] R. Combescot and X. Leynoras, Phys. Rev. Lett. 75, <lb/>3732 (1995). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>5000 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>T [K] <lb/>∆λ ∆λ(Å) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>1.0E-05 <lb/>1.0E+00 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>T/Tc <lb/>Rs (Ω <lb/>Ω) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>FIG. 1. λ(T ) vs. <lb/>T for YBCO/BZO(curve 1) and <lb/>YBCO/YSZ(curve 2) crystals. Data from ref.2 is also shown <lb/>for comparison(curve 3). Lower inset shows the low T <lb/>part. Top inset shows Rs(T ) vs. T /Tc of YBCO/BZO and <lb/>YBCO/YSZ. <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>1.E+09 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>T(K) <lb/>σ σ <lb/>2 <lb/>2 (Ω <lb/>Ω-m) <lb/>-1 <lb/>YBCO/YSZ <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>1.E+09 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>σ σ <lb/>2 <lb/>2 (Ω <lb/>Ω-m) <lb/>-1 <lb/>YBCO/BZO <lb/>FIG. 2. Pair conductivity σ2(T ) of YBCO/BZO (top) and <lb/>YBCO/YSZ (bottom). <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>5.E+07 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>T(K) <lb/>σ σ <lb/>1 (Ω <lb/>Ω-m) <lb/>-1 <lb/>A <lb/>C <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>1.E+08 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>σ σ <lb/>1 (Ω <lb/>Ω-m) <lb/>-1 <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>5.E+06 <lb/>85 <lb/>100 <lb/>C <lb/>0.E+00 <lb/>5.E+06 <lb/>85 <lb/>100 <lb/>C <lb/>FIG. 3. σ1(T ) of YBCO/BZO (top) and YBCO/YSZ (bot-<lb/>tom). The sharp peaks C present in both cases are shown in <lb/>insets. Note the appearance of a new peak B in YBCO/BZO. <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>T/T c <lb/>σ σ2 (arb. units) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>σ σ1 (arb. units) <lb/>FIG. 4. Calculations of σ1(T ) and σ2(T ) using the two <lb/>component model assuming two s − wave order parameters <lb/>(long dashed lines). For σ2(T ), the case for a more realis-<lb/>tic situation of an s + d symmetry is also shown (solid line). <lb/>The short dashed line represents the calculations for a single <lb/>weak-coupling d − wave order parameter. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
