<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Journal of Physics: Conference Series <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Synthesis and superconductivity of F-free <lb/> NdFeAsO 1-y <lb/>To cite this article: A Iyo et al 2009 J. Phys.: Conf. Ser. 150 052083 <lb/>View the article online for updates and enhancements. <lb/>Related content <lb/>Superconductivity at 100 <lb/>-<lb/>High-pressure growth of fluorine-<lb/>freeSmFeAsO 1x superconducting single <lb/>crystals <lb/>-<lb/>Pressure dependence of T c in LnFeAsO 1-y <lb/>(Ln = La, Ce, Nd, Tb) <lb/>-<lb/>Recent citations <lb/>Tight relation between the oxygen <lb/>deficiency and T in LaFeAsO1 <lb/>Y.F. Guo et al <lb/>-<lb/>This content was downloaded from IP address 144.213.253.16 on 23/10/2020 at 09:00 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>Synthesis and superconductivity of F-free NdFeAsO 1-y <lb/>A Iyo 1,2 , H Eisaki 1 , H Kito 1 , K Miyazawa 1,2 , P M Shirage 1 <lb/>1 National Institute of Advanced Industrial Science and Technology (AIST), Tsukuba, <lb/>Japan <lb/>2 Department of Applied Electronics, Tokyo University of Science, 2641 Yamazaki, <lb/>Noda, Chiba 278-3510, Japan <lb/>iyo-akira@aist.go.jp <lb/>Abstract. We have synthesized a series of oxygen-deficient, fluorine-free polycrystalline <lb/>samples with nominal chemical formula NdFeAsO 1-y using high-pressure technique and its <lb/>phase diagram is figured, which shows the distinguishable boundary between superconducting <lb/>and non-superconducting state. The a-and c-parameters were contracted with increase in the <lb/>oxygen deficiency. When the a-parameter is reduced to 3.964 Å from that of non-<lb/>superconducting sample, the superconductivity is induced with an abrupt raise of T c and the T c <lb/>saturates about 53 K at a=3.94 ~ 3.95 Å. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>The recent discovery of Iron (Fe)-based oxypnictide superconductor LaFeAs(O 1-x F x ) with its <lb/>superconducting transition temperature (T c ) of 26 K has motivated tremendous interest in scientific <lb/>community [1]. The discovery has proposed an alternative perspective for exploring novel high-T c <lb/>superconductors, besides the copper-oxide superconductors, which have been thoroughly investigated <lb/>for more than twenty years. Immediately after the discovery, it was reported that the replacement of La <lb/>by other lanthanide elements (Ln), such as Ce, Sm, Pr, Nd, Gd, Tb significantly improves T c exceeding <lb/>50 K [2-7]. Parent compounds LnFeAsO become superconductors through doping of electrons into <lb/>FeAs layers by the partial substitution of F -for O 2-. On the other hand, we have succeeded to <lb/>synthesize oxygen-deficient NdFeAsO 1-y with T c = 54 K using high-pressure synthesis technique [8]. <lb/>In this case, two electrons are doped by one oxygen defect. Ren et al. independently reported the <lb/>oxygen-deficient system at the same time [9]. <lb/>Crystal structure of the oxygen-deficient NdFeAsO 1-y was analyzed by electron diffraction and <lb/>electron microscopy [10]. Space group is determined to be P4/nmm (No.129) and the oxygen <lb/>vacancies are concluded as the state of disorder. By using above crystal structure, Rietveld analysis of <lb/>powder neutron diffraction for the series of NdFeAsO 1-y and LaFeAsO 1-y samples were performed [11]. <lb/>The oxygen contents of the samples were estimated and the superconducting phase diagram of <lb/>NdFeAsO1−y is established as a function of the oxygen content for the first time. Moreover, it is found <lb/>that the FeAs4-tetrahedrons transform toward a regular shape with increasing oxygen deficiency. The <lb/>superconducting transition temperatures seem to attain maximum values for regular FeAs4-<lb/>tetrahedrons. <lb/>The high-pressure synthesis method has advantageous compared to the other techniques as follows. <lb/>We can obtain high-purity samples safely due to a suppression of toxic As evaporation and high-<lb/></body>

			<front>25th International Conference on Low Temperature Physics (LT25) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 150 (2009) 052083 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/150/5/052083 <lb/>c 2009 IOP Publishing Ltd <lb/>1 <lb/></front>

			<body>density samples due to high-pressure sintering under several GPa. The NdFeAsO 1-y samples were used <lb/>for resistivity measurements under high-pressure [12]. As increasing pressure, the transition shows the <lb/>beautiful parallel shift to lower temperatures owing to the high quality and high density of samples. <lb/>Short reaction time typically 2 hours is also helpful to optimize synthesis conditions promptly. This <lb/>technique also versatile for the search of new compounds and we discovered a new superconductor of <lb/>(Ca,Na)Fe 2 As 2 by using this technique [13]. In this paper, we report the synthesis of NdFeAsO 1-y , its <lb/>physical properties and electrical phase diagram. <lb/>2. Experimentals <lb/>Polycrystalline samples were prepared by using a cubic-anvil-type high-pressure apparatus (Riken <lb/>CAP-07). Powders of Fe, Fe 2 O 3 and a precursor of NdAs were used as starting materials. Note that <lb/>there are no fluorine-containing starting materials, which significantly simplifies the sample synthesis <lb/>process. The precursor of NdAs was obtained by reacting Nd and As chips at 500 °C for 15 hours and <lb/>then 850 °C for 10 hours in an evacuate quarts tube. Assuming that the NdAs and Fe are free from <lb/>oxygen, the starting materials were weighed to the composition ratios of NdFeAsO 1-y . The <lb/>compositions written in this paper are the intended values. We note that the actual oxygen content of <lb/>the obtained NdFeAsO 1-y compounds estimated by neutron diffraction analysis was larger than the <lb/>intended values probably due to oxidation of the NdAs and Fe powders. Oxidation of the sample <lb/>during synthesis process such as the weighing, mixing also may cause as the source of oxygen gain. <lb/>The starting materials were ground with an agate mortar in a glove box filled with dry nitrogen gas. <lb/>The samples were synthesized by heating the mixtures in BN crucibles under a pressure of about 2 <lb/>GPa at 1200 °C for 2 hours. <lb/>Powder X-ray diffraction (XRD) patterns were measured using CuK a radiation (Rigaku RINT <lb/>1100). The dc magnetic susceptibility was measured using a SQUID magnetometer (Quantum Design <lb/>MPMS) under a magnetic field of 5 Oe. The resistivity was measured by a standard four-probe method. <lb/>3. Results and discussion <lb/>Figure 1 shows the powder XRD patterns of the samples with the intended oxygen content 1-y=0.90, <lb/>0.85, 0.80, 0.75 and 0.70. The ZrCuSiAs type crystal structure, as expected for NdFeAsO (and its <lb/>oxygen-deficient form), is formed as the main phase. <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>35 <lb/>40 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>55 <lb/>60 <lb/>Intensity (arb. units) <lb/>2θ (deg.) <lb/>101 <lb/>003 <lb/>110 <lb/>111 <lb/>112 <lb/>103 <lb/>004 <lb/>200 <lb/>104 <lb/>114 <lb/>212 <lb/>211 <lb/>105 <lb/>102 <lb/>1-y=0.90 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>NdFeAsO 1-y <lb/>CuKα <lb/>0.85 <lb/>Nd 2 O 3 <lb/>FeAs <lb/>NdAs <lb/>Figure 1. Powder X-ray diffraction patterns of the samples with the intended oxygen content <lb/>1-y=0.90, 0.85, 0.80, 0.75 and 0.70. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">25th International Conference on Low Temperature Physics (LT25) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 150 (2009) 052083 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/150/5/052083 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the XRD pattern of 1-y=0.90 sample, Nd 2 O 3 and FeAs peaks were observed. The real oxygen <lb/>content of 1-y=0.85 sample is estimated 0.96 by the neutron diffraction analysis as mentioned below. <lb/>The actual oxygen content of the starting composition of 1-y=0.90 sample would exceeded 1.0. Lattice <lb/>parameters for 1-y=0.90 and 0.85 samples were almost same, which support above possibility. The <lb/>XRD pattern of 1-y=0.85 and 0.80 samples are almost free from impurity phase, and most of the peaks <lb/>can be indexed on the basis of the tetragonal structure (P4/nmm). The lattice parameters for 1-y=0.85, <lb/>0.80, 0.75 and 0.70 samples are a=3.9667 and c=8.5757 Å, a=3.9643 and c=8.5636 Å, a=3.9525 and <lb/>c=8.5464 Å, a=3.9488 and c=8.5427 Å, respectively. The a-and c-parameters were contracted with <lb/>decrease in the oxygen content. With decreasing 1-y from 0.75, peaks assigned to NdAs were observed <lb/>to increase. <lb/>The temperature dependence of the magnetic susceptibility for the 1-y=0.85, 0.80, 0.75 and 0.70 <lb/>samples are shown in Fig. 2. The 1-y=0.85 sample did not show superconductivity above 5 K. The <lb/>sharp drop of the magnetic susceptibility, corresponding to the onset of superconductivity is observed <lb/>at around 50 K for 1-y=0.75 and 0.70, both in the zero-field cooling (ZFC) and the field cooling (FC) <lb/>curves. The volume fractions estimated from the magnitude of diamagnetic signal at 5 K are 93 % <lb/>(ZFC) and 26 % (FC) for 1-y=0.70, large enough as bulk superconductivity. We note that the 1-y=0.70 <lb/>sample has large magnetic moment above T c , most likely due to some ferromagnetic impurities such as <lb/>Fe 2 O 3 and/or Fe. The 1-y=0.80 sample that is located near the boundary between superconducting state <lb/>and non-superconducting one showed the lower T c of 35 K with a larger transition width and smaller <lb/>volume fraction. <lb/>-0.015 <lb/>-0.010 <lb/>-0.005 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.70 <lb/>Susceptibility (emu/g) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>Nominal composition: <lb/>NdFeAsO 1-y <lb/>1-y <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>3.94 <lb/>3.95 <lb/>3.96 <lb/>3.97 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>0.80 <lb/>0.85 <lb/>0.90 <lb/>0.95 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>T <lb/>c (K) <lb/>a (Å) <lb/>1-y* <lb/>NdFeAsO 1-y* <lb/>1-y*=6.637a-25.373 <lb/>Superconducting state <lb/>Figure 2. Temperature dependence of the <lb/>magnetic susceptibility for 1-y=0.85, 0.80, 0.75 <lb/>and 0.70 sample. <lb/>Figure 3. Electronic phase diagram drawn from <lb/>the a-parameters and T c for the samples <lb/>synthesized so far. The upper scale shows the <lb/>oxygen content 1-y* estimated by the neutron <lb/>diffraction analysis. <lb/>Figure 3 shows the electronic phase diagram obtained by plotting the a-parameters and T c for the <lb/>samples synthesized so far. The T c is determined from the onset of transition in magnetic susceptibility. <lb/>The upper scale shows the oxygen content 1-y* estimated using the linear fitting (1-y*=6.637a-25.373) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">25th International Conference on Low Temperature Physics (LT25) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 150 (2009) 052083 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/150/5/052083 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the data obtained by the powder neutron diffraction analysis [11]. Boundary between <lb/>superconducting state and non-superconducting one is very clear. When the a-parameter is reduced <lb/>from that of non-superconducting sample, superconductivity is induced with an abrupt raise of T c at <lb/>about a=3.964Å (1-y*=0.94) and the T c saturates about 53 K at a=3.94~3.95Å. Ren et al. also shows <lb/>the phase diagram of NdFeAsO 1-δ , where the T c decreases for further shrinkage of the a-parameter <lb/>(~3.92 Å). We have not obtained such samples having lower T c and short a-parameters. They <lb/>synthesized the samples under a pressure of 6 GPa. The higher pressure might have introduced more <lb/>oxygen deficiency, which results in the further shrinkage of the lattice parameters. <lb/>4. Summary <lb/>We have successfully synthesized oxygen-deficient, fluorine-free NdFeAsO 1-y superconductors using <lb/>high-pressure technique. Boundary between superconducting state and non-superconducting one is <lb/>distinguished. The a-and c-parameters were contracted with decrease in the oxygen content. The <lb/>superconductivity is induced with an abrupt raise of T c when a-parameter was shrank below 3.964Å <lb/>and the T c saturates about 53 K at a=3.94 ~ 3.95Å. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments <lb/>This work was partially supported by Grant-in-Aid for Specially promoted Research (20001004) from <lb/>The Ministry of Education, Culture, Sports, Science and Technology (MEXT). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] Kamihara Y, Watanabe T, Hirano M and Hosono H 2008 J. Am. Chem. Soc. 130 3296 <lb/>[2] Chen X H, Wu T, Wu G, Liu R H, Chen H, Fang D F 2008 Nature 453 761 <lb/>[3] Chen G F, Li Z, Wu D, Li G, Hu W Z, Dong J, Zheng P, Luo J L, Wang N L 2008 Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 100 247002 <lb/>[4] Ren Z A, Yang J, Lu W, Yi W, Shen X L, Li Z C, Che G C, Dong X L, Sun L L, Zhou F, Zhao <lb/>Z X 2008 Europhys. Lett. 82 57002 <lb/>[5] Ren Z A, Lu W, Yang J, Yi W, Shen X L, Li Z C, Che G C, Dong X L, Sun L L, Zhou F, Zhao <lb/>Z X 2008 Chinese Phys. Lett. 25 2215 <lb/>[6] Yang J, Li Z C, Lu W, Yi W, Shen X L, Ren Z A, Che G C, Dong X L, Sun L L, Zhou F, Zhao <lb/>Z X 2008 Supercond. Sci. Technol. 21 082001 <lb/>[7] Bos J W G, Penny G B S, Rodgers J A, Sokolov D A, Huxley A D, Attfield J P 2008 Chem. <lb/>Commun. DOI: 10.1039/b808474b <lb/>[8] Kito H, Eisaki H, Iyo A 2008 J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 77 063707 <lb/>[9] Ren Z A, Che G C, Dong X L, Yang J, Lu W, Yi W, Shen X L, Li Z C, Sun L L, Zhou F, Zhao <lb/>Z X, 2008 Europhys. Lett. 83 17002 <lb/>[10] Matsuhata H, Lee C H, Kihou K, Eisaki H, Kito H, Shirage P M, Miyazawa K, Ito T, Iyo A. in <lb/>preparation. <lb/>[11] Lee C H, Ito T, Iyo A, Eisaki H, Kito H, Fernandez-diaz M T, Kihou K, Matsuhata H, Braden <lb/>M, Yamada K 2008 J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 77 in press <lb/>[12] Takeshita N, Iyo A, Eisaki H, Kito H, Ito T 2008 J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 77 in press <lb/>[13] Shirage P M, Miyazawa K, Kito H, Eisaki H, Iyo A 2008 Appl. Phys. Exp. in press <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">25th International Conference on Low Temperature Physics (LT25) <lb/>IOP Publishing <lb/>Journal of Physics: Conference Series 150 (2009) 052083 <lb/>doi:10.1088/1742-6596/150/5/052083 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
