<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9703028v1 3 Mar 1997 <lb/>In-plane optical response of Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 <lb/>A. A. Tsvetkov a,b , J. Schützmann a , J. I. Gorina b , G. A. Kaljushnaia b and D. van der Marel a <lb/>a Material Science Center, Laboratory of Solid State Physics, University of Groningen, <lb/>Nijenborgh 4, 9747 AG Groningen, The Netherlands, <lb/>b P. N. Lebedev Physical Institute, Russian Academy of Sciences, Leninsky prospect 53, <lb/>117924 Moscow, Russia <lb/>(August 14, 2018) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>We report on infrared reflectivity measurements of the ab-plane response of <lb/>superconducting Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 single crystals. The frequency dependent con-<lb/>ductivity has a maximum near 500 cm −1 at room temperature, which shifts <lb/>to lower frequency and merges with a Drude peak below 100 K. We attribute <lb/>the unusual behavior of the mid-infrared conductivity to low frequency tran-<lb/>sitions between electronic bands of mainly BiO character near the M point. <lb/>The linear temperature dependence of the low-frequency resistivity can be <lb/>followed down to approximately 40 K where it saturates. <lb/>74.25.Gz,74.25.Jb,74.72.Hs,78.20.-e <lb/>Typeset using REVT E X <lb/> 1 <lb/></front>

			<body>The relatively simple crystal structure of single layer compounds offers the possibility <lb/>to study intrinsic properties of the CuO 2 -plane. It is however not clear to what extent the <lb/>BiO-layers contribute to the optical conductivity, and how the hole-doping into the CuO 2 -<lb/>planes proceeds. Previously, it was suggested from an optical study of Tl 2 Ba 2 CaCu 2 O 8 <lb/>that the TlO-layers exhibit non-conducting behavior. 1 The situation for the Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 -<lb/>system might be more complex. Band structure calculations using the generalized potential <lb/>augmented plane-wave (LAPW) method by Singh and Pickett 2 show that weak structural <lb/>distortions shift the Bi-O(3) derived bands below the Fermi level. <lb/>Since the normal state dynamics is of special interest for understanding strongly cor-<lb/>related electron systems, the low T c (&lt; 10 K) of the single layer Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 compound <lb/>offers the opportunity to examine these features well below the transition temperature of <lb/>the related double and triple layer systems. It is widely accepted that the in-plane response <lb/>of the cuprates is in the clean-limit and the strong mid-infrared response is due to strong <lb/>correlation effects in the cuprates. In particular the marginal Fermi-liquid (MFL) 3 , and Lut-<lb/>tinger liquid 4 approaches along with the conventional strong electron-phonon interaction 5 <lb/>have been put forward to account for these unusual properties. In these models the strong <lb/>mid-infrared conductivity is related to the linear frequency dependence of the scattering rate <lb/>of the quasi-particles in a single band picture. Therefore, the normal state properties of the <lb/>in-plane conductivity of Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 down to approximately 10 K should play a pivotal role <lb/>in a clear separation of the different excitations. <lb/>In this paper we report on the far-infrared ab-plane conductivity of a Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 single <lb/>crystal that was calculated via a Kramers-Kronig analysis of the measured reflectivity data. <lb/>Above 70 K the conductivity increases with frequency until it reaches a maximum, the <lb/>frequency of which increases with increasing temperature. The temperature dependence <lb/>of the low-frequency conductivity is consistent with the dc resistivity measured on crystals <lb/>of the same batch. Based on the f-sum rule we argue that phonon-contributions are too <lb/>weak to account for this maximum. We discuss a scenario, where the unusual temperature <lb/>dependence is due to intra-and interband transitions within and between electronic bands <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>near E F of CuO 2 and BiO character. <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 Cu0 6 single crystals were grown from a precursor dissolved in liquid KCl. 6 Due to <lb/>the formation of an enclosed cavity of a few cm 3 within the melt samples were obtained as <lb/>free standing crystalline platelets of sizes up to 1-2×1-2 mm 2 and of thickness 5-20 µm. 7 A <lb/>constant cavity temperature of 840-850 • C and a constant temperature gradient (2-3 K/cm) <lb/>were kept within the melt in order to provide permanent transport of the precursor to <lb/>the growth zone, which is important for a free growth of homogeneous crystals with a <lb/>flat mirror surface. Such samples require no mechanical or chemical polishing prior to the <lb/>infrared reflectivity measurements. X-ray measurements revealed a perfect crystal structure <lb/>with lattice parameters a = 5.36Å b =5.37Å and c = 24.64Å, which correspond to the <lb/>orthorhombic <lb/>√ <lb/>2 × <lb/>√ <lb/>2 distortion of the body centered tetragonal structure. No traces of <lb/>other phases could be detected. The rocking curves have a full width at half maximum of <lb/>0.1 • , 7 which is the minimum value so far reported. Both from the resistivity and the ac-<lb/>susceptibility we obtained the same values for the superconducting transition temperature <lb/>(T c =7-8 K) and for the transition width (∆T c =2 K). Unlike earlier reports where a linear <lb/>resistivity was observed down to the superconducting phase transition 8,9 , in the present <lb/>crystals ρ(T ) is only linear at high temperatures but saturates below 40 K 10 at a residual <lb/>resistivity with a sample to sample variation from 150 to 300 µΩcm. <lb/>The reflectance measurements were made on the a-b plane of Bi 2 Sr 2 Cu0 6 single crystals <lb/>at normal incidence for temperatures from 300 K down to 10 K. We used two Fourier-<lb/>transform spectrometers to cover the frequency range from 50 cm −1 to 12000 cm −1 and a flow <lb/>cryostat for the temperature variation. Absolute reflectivities were obtained by referencing <lb/>the reflected intensity of the sample to a Au-mirror with the same shape and size at each <lb/>temperature. The systematic errors introduced due to the sample/reference interchange fell <lb/>within 0.5%. A further confirmation of the absolute accuracy reached with this procedure <lb/>comes from the small (≈ 1 %) mismatch in the absolute reflectivity in the overlap region <lb/>between the FIR and MIR regions. <lb/>The temperature dependence of the reflectivity is shown in Fig. 1. Decreasing the tem-<lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>perature from 300 K down to 100 K the reflectivity shows an increase up to mid-infrared <lb/>frequencies. From 100K downto 40 K the only increase in reflectivity occurs in the far-<lb/>infrared range. The reflectivity is temperature independent below 40 K. The near-infrared <lb/>reflectivity has a broad plasma minimum around 8700 cm −1 . Weak reproducible structure <lb/>is observed at 181, 327, 427, and 508 cm −1 . The minima at 327 and 427 cm −1 coincide <lb/>with the frequencies of the c-axis LO phonon modes of Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 <lb/>11 . Under ideal condi-<lb/>tions (large perfect crystals with flat surfaces, perfectly s-polarized plane waves) leakage of <lb/>c-axis longitudinal optical phonons into the ab-plane response can be excluded 12 , but some <lb/>weak and surface dependent leakage may occur if the experimental conditions are less than <lb/>perfect. As the minima at 181 and 508 cm −1 are not seen for E c, we attribute these to <lb/>in-plane optical phonons. <lb/>To calculate the infrared conductivity through a Kramers-Kronig transformation we used <lb/>a Hagen-Rubens extrapolation for the low-frequency region. Extrapolation towards high <lb/>frequencies (up to 320,000 cm −1 ) was done using the data of Terasaki et al.. 13 <lb/>The real part of the conductivity σ 1 is shown up to 8000 cm −1 in Fig. 2 and in more <lb/>detail up to 2000 cm −1 in Fig. 3. The conductivity at low temperatures is almost featureless <lb/>and decreases monotonically with frequency. When the temperature is increased to 100 K, <lb/>a maximum in the conductivity appears, which shifts to 500 cm −1 at room temperature. <lb/>We also notice from the way the conductivity curves cross, that at least part of the spectral <lb/>weight removed from the low frequency side of the spectrum is recovered in the mid infrared <lb/>range. To demonstrate this, we present in Fig. 4 the carrier density obtained from integrat-<lb/>ing σ(ω) up to a cut-off frequency (n ef f (ω c ) = 2mπ −1 e −2 ωc <lb/>0 σ(ω ′ )dω ′ ). The dc resistivity <lb/>obtained by extrapolation of the optical conductivity to zero frequency is presented in the <lb/>insert of Fig. 2. This shows a linear temperature dependence, which saturates below 40 K. <lb/>The fact that the single layer compounds have almost the same volume per unit cell <lb/>as the double and triple layer compounds, results in a low free carrier concentration and a <lb/>relatively low conductivity. Thus, one might expect that the contribution of low-frequency <lb/>excitations, in particular optical phonons, can no longer be neglected. However, by applying <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>the f -sum-rule ( ∞ <lb/>0 8σ ion (ω)dω = j 4πn j Z 2 <lb/>j /m j ) to all ions with mass m j and ionic charges <lb/>Z j , we calculate an average value of the conductivity due to phonons of only 18 Ω −1 cm −1 in <lb/>the range of 0 to 700 cm −1 , i.e. one order of magnitude smaller than the rise in conductivity <lb/>between 0 and 500 cm −1 in Fig. 2. Hence the phonon contributions are far too weak to be <lb/>the main source of this rise in conductivity. <lb/>The maximum near 500 cm −1 (indicated with arrows in Fig. 3) shifts to a lower frequency <lb/>upon reducing the temperature, and is superimposed on a steeply falling free-electron con-<lb/>ductivity which increases as the temperature is decreased. At 10 K the free-electron response <lb/>is prevalent in the low frequency conductivity. In the remainder of this paper we will in-<lb/>dicate the depression of the conductivity below the maximum as a pseudo-gap. In the <lb/>present case there is no unambiguous -and physically meaningful-way to decompose the <lb/>conductivity in free-carrier and bound-charge components. One of the reasons is, that in <lb/>the high T c cuprates also the intraband conductivity deviates considerably from standard <lb/>Drude behavior. In particular the high T c cuprates, if optimally doped, are known to have a <lb/>linear frequency dependency of the scattering rate, as follows from inversion of the real and <lb/>imaginary part of σ(ω) using the expression 14 σ(ω) = ne 2 m −1 / {γ(ω) − iωm ⋆ (ω)/m}, where <lb/>n is the carrier density, m is the band mass, m ⋆ (ω)/m is the effective mass enhancement, <lb/>and 1/γ(ω) is the effective relaxation time. A further complication arises, if two or more <lb/>electronic bands cross the Fermi level. In this case, which we believe to be relevant for <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 , the spectrum of σ(ω) contains interband transitions in addition to the intra-<lb/>band components. The interband part has a complex line-shape which depends on the details <lb/>of the band-dispersion and the k-dependent optical transition matrix elements. Obviously if <lb/>the material has two or more bands of electrons, at least one of which (the CuO 2 bands) has <lb/>a frequency dependent scattering rate, it is no longer possible to make a meaningful sepa-<lb/>ration in several components. At low temperatures, where the CuO 2 channel has a reduced <lb/>scattering rate, σ(ω) is dominated by the CuO 2 channel at least at the low frequencies. In <lb/>this region one might hope to extract the frequency dependent scattering rate of the CuO 2 <lb/>carriers, at least up to a frequency where other contributions to σ(ω) become significant. For <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>this reason we display in the inset of Fig. 4 the frequency dependent scattering rate only for <lb/>the lowest temperature. We notice that the linear behavior of γ(ω), which is rather typical <lb/>for all high T c cuprates, exists only up to 0.1 eV in this case. In view of the possibility <lb/>of low energy interband transitions in this compound, even at 10 K γ(ω) extracted from <lb/>optical data is probably no longer meaningful forhω &gt; 0.1 eV. Our observations support <lb/>the conclusion by Romero et al, based on an analysis of infrared transmission data, that <lb/>the linear frequency dependency of γ(ω) is limited to the energy range below 0.1 eV. 15 The <lb/>non-linear temperature dependence of the resistivity in the crystals used for this study is <lb/>also inconsistent with MFL behavior at the lowest temperatures. <lb/>Transmission experiments on free standing non-superconducting single crystals of <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 performed by Romero et al 15 also reveal a singularity in the FIR conductiv-<lb/>ity, although the effect is less pronounced. The room temperature conductivity shows a <lb/>clear change of slope around 500 cm −1 , and the frequency dependent effective mass m ⋆ (ω) <lb/>has a minimum at this frequency. While only a trace of the pseudo-gap is observed in <lb/>non-superconducting single crystals 15 , the effective number of carriers remains the same. A <lb/>maximum in the optical conductivity was also observed in the related single layer compound <lb/>Tl 2 Ba 2 CuO 6 , 16 although a substantially larger spectral weight was involved. <lb/>A possible candidate for the observed pseudo-gap is the additional electronic degree <lb/>of freedom introduced by having both hole-doped CuO 2 and electron-doped BiO bands. <lb/>Although an interpretation in terms of direct transitions between these bands is probably <lb/>too simple due to the strong electron-electron correlations in the Cu-O bands, a pseudo-<lb/>gap may nevertheless exist, not unlike the situation encountered in Kondo-insulators. 17 The <lb/>LAPW band calculations of Singh and Pickett 2 give two types of bands: For a vanishing <lb/>orthorhombic distortion there is a large Cu-O derived barrel section centered at X and <lb/>its <lb/>√ <lb/>2 × <lb/>√ <lb/>2 folded counterpart centered around Γ. In addition there are two Bi-O derived <lb/>electron pockets with their BZ-folded counter parts, all of them centered at M . As suggested <lb/>by Singh and Pickett, 2 a weak structural change from tetragonal to orthorhombic strongly <lb/>affects the structure of the electronic bands. The bands are shifted up to 400 meV for <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Bi displacements of 0.14Å and 0.41Å for O. As a result 5 bands were calculated for k <lb/>close to the saddle point (M), all within a range of 200 meV around E F . Only two of <lb/>the Bi-O pockets (one of them barely) cross E F when the orthorhombic distortions are <lb/>taken into account. Because the band structure is strongly affected by modulations of the <lb/>lattice, it can also have an appreciable temperature dependence. Photoemission studies <lb/>have revealed a single occupied band near E F close to the M -point, which was originally <lb/>indicated as a possible BiO derived band 18 but was identified as a CuO 2 band in a later <lb/>publication 19 . The absence of a clear BiO-derived band in photoemission may however <lb/>result from a disorder induced smearing of the k-dispersion in the BiO-layers, or from the <lb/>small photoelectron cross section for Bi and O states compared to the Cu 3d cross-section. <lb/>The main &apos;generalized Drude&apos; component in our data then originates from the CuO barrels, <lb/>with a linearly frequency dependent decay-rate typical for optimally doped cuprates. The <lb/>pseudo-gap at high temperatures would be due to transitions between the closely spaced <lb/>bands which cross E F near M . In this scenario the disappearance of the pseudo-gap at <lb/>low temperatures can reflect a gradual change of atomic coordinates upon cooling, with a <lb/>corresponding change of the interband separation. This structural modulation can easily <lb/>result in a re-distribution of carriers between BiO and CuO 2 bands and the disappearance <lb/>of the pseudo-gap. Interestingly, large lattice distortions are generally present in films, which <lb/>show a higher T c and a more pronounced pseudo-gap. 20 <lb/>We have presented experimental data on the in-plane infrared response of superconduct-<lb/>ing Bi2201 single crystals for temperatures from 10 K to 300 K. The optical conductivity <lb/>shows a pseudo-gap feature, that shifts with temperature. The optical conductivity is at <lb/>least one order of magnitude too large to be compatible with a purely phononic interpre-<lb/>tation of this feature. This observation indicates the presence of two coupled conducting <lb/>channels and may provide important clues regarding the fact that T c in the single layer Bi-<lb/>cuprate material is much lower than in other nearly stoichiometric compounds. We discuss <lb/>the possibility that the pseudo-gap is related to electronic transitions between bands near <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

		<body>the M-point, which are strongly coupled to the orthorhombic lattice distortion. <lb/>We gratefully acknowledge many useful comments from W. N. Hardy.</body>

		<div type="acknowledgement">This investigation <lb/>was supported by the program for Russian-Dutch Cooperation under project # 047003033 <lb/>of the Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek, the Russian Scientific <lb/>Technical Program &quot;High Temperature Superconductivity&quot; (A.A.T., J.I.G., G.A.K.), and <lb/>the program Human Capital and Mobility under contract ERBCHBICT941820 (J.S.). <lb/></div>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1 G. Jehl et al., Europhys. Lett., 17, 255 (1992). <lb/>2 D. J. Singh and W. E. Pickett, Phys. Rev. B 51, 3128 (1995). <lb/>3 C.M. Varma et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 26, 1996 (1989). <lb/>4 P.W. Anderson, Phys. Rev. Lett. 67, 2092 (1991). <lb/>5 S. V. Shulga et al., Physica C 178, 226 (1991). <lb/>6 J. I. Gorina et al., Solid State Commun. 91, 615 (1994). <lb/>7 V. P. Martovitsky et al., Solid State Commun. 96, 893 (1995). <lb/>8 S. Martin et al., Phys. Rev. B 41, 846 (1990). <lb/>9 X.H. Hou et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 496 (1994). <lb/>10 S. I. Vedeneev et al., Phys. Rev. B 51, 16380 (1995). <lb/>11 A. A. Tsvetkov, J. Schützmann, and D. van der Marel (unpublished). <lb/>12 D. van der Marel et al., Phys Rev. Lett. 71, 2676 (1993). <lb/>13 I. Terasaki et al., Phys. Rev. B 41, 865 (1990). <lb/>14 J. W. Allen and J. C. Mikkelsen, Phys. Rev. B 15, 2952 (1977). <lb/>15 D. B. Romero et al., Solid State Commun. 82, 183 (1992). <lb/>16 A. V. Puchkov et al., Phys. Rev. B 51, 3312 (1995). <lb/>17 G. Aeppli and Z. Fisk, Comments Cond. Mat. Phys. 16, 155 (1992). <lb/>18 E.R. Ratner et al., Phys. Rev. B 48, 10482(1993). <lb/>19 D.M. King et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 73, 3298 (1994). <lb/>20 P. Calvani et al., Phys. Rev. B 53, 2756 (1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>FIGURES <lb/>FIG. 1. Reflectivity of a Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 single crystal at normal incidence and with the elec-<lb/>tric-field vector parallel to the ab-plane for T = 10, 100, 200, and 300 K. Inset: Reflectivity on an <lb/>expanded scale for T = 10, 40, 70, 100, 200, 300 K. <lb/>FIG. 2. Optical conductivity σ(ω) as a function of frequency for the same temperatures as in <lb/>Fig. 1. Inset: dc-resistivity obtained by extrapolating the optical conductivity to zero frequency. <lb/>FIG. 3. Optical conductivity σ(ω) on an expanded scale for 10, 100, 200, and 300 K. The <lb/>arrows indicate the evolution of the maximum. <lb/>FIG. 4. Effective number of carriers per unit of CuO 2 calculated from σ(ω) using the partial <lb/>f-sum rule. Inset: Frequency dependent scattering rate (γ(ω)) and effective mass enhancement <lb/>(m ⋆ (ω)/m) at 10 K. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Wave number (cm -1 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>4000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>12000 <lb/>Reflectivity <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>10 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>200 K <lb/>300 K <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6 <lb/>Wave number (cm <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>200 <lb/>400 <lb/>600 <lb/>R <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0.9 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>10 K <lb/>40 K <lb/>70 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>200 K <lb/>300 K <lb/>T C = 8 K <lb/>Wave number (cm -1 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>6000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>Conductivity ( <lb/>Ω -1 <lb/>cm -1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>ρ <lb/>dc (µΩ cm) <lb/>0 <lb/>300 <lb/>600 <lb/>900 <lb/>10 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>200 K <lb/>300 K <lb/>Wave number (cm -1 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>Coductivity (Ω -1 <lb/>cm -1 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>10 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>200 K <lb/>300 K <lb/>Wave number (cm <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>N <lb/>eff <lb/>ω (cm <lb/>-1 ) <lb/>γ (cm <lb/>-1 <lb/>) <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>m * <lb/>/m <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>10 K <lb/>300 K <lb/>100 K <lb/>200 K </body>


	</text>
</tei>
