<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Impurity scattering effects on the low-temperature specific heat of <lb/>d-wave superconductors <lb/>C. F. Chang 1 , J.-Y. Lin 2,* , and H. D. Yang 1 <lb/>1 Department of Physics, National Sun Yat-Sen University, Kaohsiung 804, Taiwan ROC <lb/>2 Institute of Physics, National Chiao Tung University, Hsinchu 300, Taiwan ROC <lb/>Very recently impurity scattering effects on quasiparticles in d-wave superconductors have <lb/>attracted much attention. Especially, the thermodynamic properties in magnetic fields H are of <lb/>interest. We have measured the low-temperature specific heat C(T,H) of La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 . For <lb/>the first time, the impurity scattering effects on C(T,H) of cuprate superconductors were clearly <lb/>observed, and are compared with theory of d-wave superconductivity. It is found that impurity <lb/>scattering leads to g(H)=g(0)(1+D´(H/H c2 )´ln(H c2 /H)) in small magnetic fields. Most amazingly, <lb/>the scaling of C(T,H) breaks down due to impurity scattering. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25.Bt; 74.62.Dh; 74.25.Jb <lb/></front>

		<body>Tunneling and ARPES experiments which <lb/>are sensitive to either the interface of the <lb/>junction or surface of the sample have suggested <lb/>a dominant d-wave pairing symmetry in <lb/>hole-doped cuprate superconductors [1,2]. Still, <lb/>low-temperature specific heat (C) is thought to <lb/>be one of the unique experiments which provide <lb/>evidence of d-wave pairing in bulk properties. <lb/>The T 2 temperature dependence of the electronic <lb/>term in C at zero magnetic field H=0 and the <lb/>H 1/2 dependence of the linear term coefficient g <lb/>have been interpreted as strong evidence of the <lb/>line nodes of order parameter [3-12]. Very <lb/>recently, the scaling behavior of the electronic <lb/>specific heat contribution C e (T,H) has been <lb/>predicted by theory [13,14], and confirmed by <lb/>experiments [5,9-11]. However, several papers <lb/>reported that the non-linear H dependence of g <lb/>was <lb/>also <lb/>observed <lb/>in <lb/>conventional <lb/>superconductors [15,16], and raised the question <lb/>whether the H 1/2 dependence of g is indeed due <lb/>to d-wave pairing. In addition, although most <lb/>studies of C(T,H) in cuprates agree on the H 1/2 <lb/>dependence of g, there remains controversies on <lb/>the existence of the T 2 term at H=0. Chen et al. <lb/>have presented data showing clear evidence of <lb/>the T 2 t e rm i n L a 1.78 Sr 0.22 CuO 4 and <lb/>disappearance of this T 2 term in H, both <lb/>consistent with the predictions for d-wave <lb/>superconductivity [5]. Nevertheless, in some <lb/>other works, evidence of the T 2 term was either <lb/>ambiguous or had to be identified through <lb/>sophisticated fit [6-10]. These difficulties make <lb/>the C(T,H) studies of the impurity-doped <lb/>cuprate superconductors particularly of interest. <lb/>If the recently developed theory [17-19] of the <lb/>impurity scattering effects on the quasiparticle <lb/>excitation in cuprates can be verified by C(T,H) <lb/>measurements, it would strongly indicate that <lb/>the observed properties of C(T,H) are <lb/>characteristic of d-wave pairing. These studies <lb/>may also help to improve the theories of the <lb/></body>

		<page>2 <lb/></page>

		<body>quasiparticles in cuprates. Furthermore, since a <lb/>small impurity scattering rate can cause <lb/>disappearance of the T 2 term, it is desirable to <lb/>know the magnetic field dependence of C(T,H) <lb/>in the impurity-doped cuprates. Comparisons <lb/>between C(T,H) of the nominally clean samples <lb/>and that of the impurity-doped ones may <lb/>generate fruitful implication on the existing <lb/>puzzles. <lb/>T o <lb/>s e rv e <lb/>t h e s e <lb/>pu rpos e s , <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 samples were chosen for <lb/>two main reasons. C of the Ni-doped samples <lb/>has a much smaller magnetic contribution than <lb/>that of the Zn-doped samples, and the data <lb/>analysis can be simplified. Moreover, <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 CuO 4 has been compellingly shown to <lb/>be a clean d-wave superconductor [5], and is <lb/>ideal to compare with the Ni-doped samples. <lb/>Polycrystalline samples of La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 <lb/>with nominal x=0, 0.01, and 0.02 were carefully <lb/>prepared from La 2 O 3 , SrCO 3 , and CuO powder <lb/>of 99.999% purity. Details of the preparation <lb/>were described elsewhere [5]. The powder <lb/>x-ray-diffraction patterns of all samples used in <lb/>the experiments show a single T phase with no <lb/>detection of impurity phases. The transition <lb/>temperature T c by the midpoint of the resistivity <lb/>drop is 28.7, 21.2 and 17.4 K for x=0, 0.01, and <lb/>0.02, respectively. The transition width (90% to <lb/>10% by the resistivity drop) of T c is 3 K or less <lb/>for all samples, suggesting a decent homogeneity. <lb/>C(T) was measured from 0.6 to 9 K with a 3 He <lb/>thermal relaxation calorimeter using the <lb/>heat-pulse technique. The precision of the <lb/>measurements in the temperature range is about <lb/>1%. To test the calibrations of the thermometer <lb/>and the measurements in H, a copper sample was <lb/>measured, and the scatter of data in different <lb/>magnetic fields is about 3% or better. Details of <lb/>the calorimeter calibrations by the copper <lb/>sample can be found in Ref. [5]. <lb/>The analysis of C(T,H) was carried out for <lb/>data from 0.6 to 7 K. Varying the temperature <lb/>range to 8 K or to 6 K does not lead to any <lb/>significant change of the results. Both the <lb/>individual-field and global fit have been <lb/>executed, and give similar results and conclusion. <lb/>In this Letter, the results from the <lb/>individual-field fit are reported. Data of all <lb/>samples are described by <lb/>C(T,H)=g(H)T+bT 3 + <lb/>n C S=2 (T,H) <lb/>(1) <lb/>where bT 3 is the phonon contribution and nC S=2 <lb/>is the magnetic contribution of spin-2 <lb/>paramagnetic centers (PC&apos;s) associated with <lb/>CuO 2 <lb/>p l a n e s <lb/>[ 2 0 -22]. <lb/>Since <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 has only CuO 2 planes and <lb/>lacks CuO chains, nC S=2 was used rather than the <lb/>conventional Schottky anomaly, which was <lb/>thought to be related to CuO Chains [7,22]. <lb/>Phenomenologically, inclusion of nC S=2 also <lb/>yields a better fit than that of the Schottky <lb/>anomaly. <lb/>C(T,0) of samples with x=0, 0.01 and 0.02 <lb/>is shown in Fig. 1. For x=0, at zero field C/T vs. <lb/>T 2 shows an obvious downward curve at low <lb/>temperatures due to the T 2 term in C. For x=0.01, <lb/>this downward curve becomes a straight line <lb/>except below 1 K where the contribution from <lb/>the magnetic contribution becomes important. <lb/>An increase in g with increasing x can also be <lb/>recognized directly from data shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>Both disappearance of the T 2 term and the <lb/>increase in g are considered as manifestations of <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>the impurity scattering. The low-temperature <lb/>upturn in C/T of both x=0.01 and 0.02 can be <lb/>attributed to nC S=2 by the solid lines resulted <lb/>from the fit by Eq. (1). To further show the <lb/>quality of the fit in H, C(T,H) of x=0.01 at low <lb/>temperatures is shown in Fig. 2(a) as an example, <lb/>together with the solid lines representing the fit <lb/>of data to Eq. (1). The results illustrate that <lb/>C(T,H) of L a 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 can be <lb/>satisfactorily described by Eq. (1). The <lb/>contribution of nC S=2 compared with other terms <lb/>is shown in Fig. 3. As expected, n resulting from <lb/>the fit does not change significantly with H, <lb/>however with variation in H³4 T as shown in <lb/>Fig. 2(b). Similar results of n vs. H can be found <lb/>in all three samples. It is likely that the effective <lb/>Hamiltonian for C S=2 in Ref. [20] results from <lb/>the experimental data with H&lt;4 T [21], and is <lb/>most suited for low magnetic fields. From the <lb/>low-field fitting results, n of x=0, 0.01, and 0.02 <lb/>is about 0.3, 0.9, and 1.8´10 -4 respectively. The <lb/>value of n for x=0 is taken from the fit of the <lb/>data in H and implemented into the fit at H=0. <lb/>The solid line for x=0 in Fig. 1(a) shows that the <lb/>data can accommodate a small nC S=2 . <lb/>For a clean d-wave superconductor in a <lb/>finite field H, an increase in g is predicted to be <lb/>proportional to H 1/2 at low temperatures due to <lb/>the Doppler shift on the quasiparticle energy <lb/>[3,4]. In the unitary limit, impurity scattering <lb/>leads to a modification to the density of states, <lb/>and the H dependence of g becomes [17-19] <lb/>g(H)=g(0)(1+D´(H/H c2 )´ln(H c2 /H)) <lb/>(2) <lb/>where D»D 0 /32G. D 0 is the superconducting gap, <lb/>G is the impurity scattering rate, and H c2 is the <lb/>upper critical field. The unitary limit is widely <lb/>considered as a good approximation to the nature <lb/>of the impurity scattering in cuprates, and is <lb/>supported by experimental evidences. To <lb/>compare g(H) of the clean sample with that of <lb/>the Ni-doped ones, g vs. H 1/2 of all samples was <lb/>plotted in Fig. 4. If g has a H 1/2 dependence as <lb/>expected in a clean sample, the data will follow <lb/>a straight line as represented by the dash line in <lb/>Fig. 4. Indeed, data of the sample with x=0 <lb/>indicate a clear H 1/2 dependence of g (Fig. 4(a)). <lb/>In Ni-doped samples, the H dependence of g is <lb/>smaller than in the clean one, and the data show <lb/>a pronounced curvature for small H (Fig. 4(b) <lb/>and (c)). This behavior makes g(H) of Ni-doped <lb/>samples distinct from that of the clean one. Thus <lb/>the effect of the impurity scattering is <lb/>distinguished. Actually, g(H) of both Ni-doped <lb/>samples can be well described by Eq. (2) with <lb/>reasonable parameters as shown by the solid line <lb/>in Fig. 4(b) and (c). The fit gives G/D 0 =0.020 <lb/>and 0.025 for x=0.01 and 0.02, respectively, with <lb/>H c2 »38 T. A twice increase in G/D 0 is expected <lb/>for x=0.02 by the nominal doping concentration; <lb/>nevertheless, this small increase in G/D 0 is in <lb/>accord with a less rapid T c suppression in the <lb/>x=0.02 sample. Furthermore, as a result of the <lb/>impurity scattering, the values of g/g n <lb/>corresponding to those of G/D 0 are in good <lb/>agreement with the calculated values in Refs. <lb/>[17,18] for both Ni-doped samples. On the other <lb/>hand, a try to fit g(H) of the clean sample by Eq. <lb/>(2) has proven to be fruitless and resulted in a <lb/>unrealistic H c2 &gt;1000 T. <lb/>The most crucial test of the recent theory <lb/>for a d-wave superconductor with impurities <lb/>probably lie on the breakdown of the scaling <lb/>behavior of C e (T,H)ºC(T,H)-g(H=0)T-bT 3 -nC S=2 . <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>For a clean d-wave superconductor, if C e /(TH 1/2 ) <lb/>vs. H 1/2 /T is plotted, all data at various T and H <lb/>should collapse into one scaling line according <lb/>to the recent scaling theory [13,14]. This scaling <lb/>of C e (T,H) has been observed in YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7-d <lb/>and La 1-x Sr x CuO 4 samples [5,9-11]. As shown in <lb/>Fig.5 (a), C e (T,H) of La 1.78 Sr 0.22 CuO 4 follows <lb/>this scaling. However, a recent theory predicts <lb/>that strong impurity scattering can cause <lb/>breakdown of the scaling [17,23]. This dramatic <lb/>effect is best illustrated in Fig. 5(b) and (c). In <lb/>contrast to the scaling of C e (T,H) of the clean <lb/>sample, C e (T,H) data of Ni-doped samples split <lb/>into individual isothermal lines as predicted by <lb/>the numerical calculations [17]. <lb/>The very theory also suggests that Eq. (2) <lb/>is exact only in fields H&lt;H * where H * /H c2 »G/D 0 <lb/>[17,18]. Though, g(H) should not deviate Eq. (2) <lb/>too much if H is slightly larger than H * [24]. In <lb/>case of H&gt;&gt;H * , g(H) would mimic the H 1/2 <lb/>behavior [18]. With H * »1 T in the present <lb/>experiments, g(H) in Fig. 4(b) and (c) behaves <lb/>exactly like what is expected. In small H, the <lb/>weak magnetic field dependence is well <lb/>described by Eq. (2). In large H, the data do not <lb/>obey Eq. (1) as well as in small H, and a <lb/>distinction between Eq. (2) and the H 1/2 <lb/>dependence is less easily made. Therefore, the <lb/>less satisfactory fit in high fields merely reflects <lb/>the limit of Eq. (2) as expected from the theory. <lb/>It is noted that n of the spin-2 PC&apos;s <lb/>increases with the doping concentration x. <lb/>However, it is unlikely that the magnetic <lb/>contribution in C(T,H) comes directly from the <lb/>Ni ions since n is two order of magnitude <lb/>smaller than x. Recently, it has been reported <lb/>that the nominal magnetic Ni ions do not disturb <lb/>the spin correlation in CuO 2 planes even on Ni <lb/>sites at small x in overdoped cuprates [25]. In <lb/>both C and susceptibility c measurements, no <lb/>paramagnetic contribution from Ni was observed. <lb/>C reported in this Letter and the related <lb/>preliminary studies on c are consistent with <lb/>these results [26]. The larger nC S=2 in the <lb/>Ni-doped samples probably comes from the <lb/>defects in CuO 2 planes, which are induced by Ni <lb/>substitution. On the other hand, Zn substitution <lb/>has strong effects on C (and c). The large <lb/>magnetic contribution usually makes the studies <lb/>of the impurity scattering effects on C(T,H) <lb/>inconclusive [27,28]. More detailed studies on <lb/>these novel properties of C and c in Ni-or <lb/>Zn-doped cuprates are desirable. <lb/>In conclusion, the impurity scattering <lb/>effects on C(T,H) of d-wave superconductors <lb/>have been clearly identified. The weak H <lb/>dependence of g(H) in small magnetic fields and <lb/>the breakdown of the scaling behavior of C e (T,H) <lb/>both are consistent with predictions of the <lb/>present theory. It is thus suggested that the <lb/>unconventional features observed in C(T,H) of <lb/>either clean or impurity-doped cuprate <lb/>superconductors are intrinsic bulk properties of <lb/>d-wave superconductivity. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We would like to thank H. F. Meng for <lb/>indispensable discussions, and Y. H. Tang for <lb/>technical assistance. This work was supported by <lb/>National Science Council of Republic of China <lb/>under Contract Nos. NSC89-2112-M-110-008 <lb/>and NSC89-2112-M-009-007. <lb/>References <lb/>* Author to whom correspondence should be sent <lb/></div>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[1] J. F. Annett, N. D. Goldenfeld, and A. J. <lb/>Leggett, in Physical Properties of High <lb/>Temperature Superconductors V, edited by <lb/>D. M. Ginsberg, World Scientific, Singapore <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[2] H. Ding, M. R. Norman, T. Yokoya, T. <lb/>Takeuchi, M. Randeria, J. C. Campuzano, T. <lb/>Takahashi, T. Mochiku, and Kadowaki, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, 2628 (1997) and <lb/>references therein. <lb/>[3] G. E. Volovik, JETP Lett. 58, 469 (1993). <lb/>[4] H. Won and K. Maki, Europhys. Lett. 73, <lb/>2744 (1995). <lb/>[5] S. J. Chen, C. F. Chang, H. L. Tsay, H. D. <lb/>Yang, and J.-Y. Lin, Phys. Rev. B 58, R14 <lb/>753 (1998). <lb/>[6] K. A. Moler, D. J. Baar, J. S. Urbach, <lb/>Ruixing Liang, W. N. Hardy, and A. <lb/>Kapitulnik, Phys. Rev. Lett. 73, 2744 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>[7] K. A. Moler, D. L. Sisson, J. S. Urbach, M. <lb/>R. Beasley, and A. Kapitulnik, Phys. Rev. B <lb/>55, 3954 (1997). <lb/>[8] R. A. Fisher, J. E. Gordon, S. F. Reklis, D. <lb/>A. Wright, J. P. Emerson, B. F. Woodfield, E. <lb/>M. McCarron III, and N. E. Phillips, <lb/>Physica C 252, 237 (1995). <lb/>[9] D. A. Wright, J. P. Emerson, B. F. <lb/>Woodfield, J. E. Golden, R.A. Fisher, and N. <lb/>E. Phillips, Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 1550 <lb/>(1999). <lb/>[10] R. A. Fisher, B. Buffeteau, R. Calemezuk, K. <lb/>W. Dennis, T. E. Hargreaves, C. Marcenat, <lb/>R. W. McCallum, A. S. O&apos;Connor, N. E. <lb/>Phillips, and A. Schilling, unpublished. <lb/>[11] B. Revaz, J.-Y. Genoud, A. Junod, A. Erb, <lb/>and E. Walker, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 3364 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[12] N. Momono and M. Ido, Physica C 264, 311 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[13] S. A. Simon and P. A. Lee, Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>78, 1548 (1997). <lb/>[14] G. E. Volovik, JETP Lett. 65, 491 (1997). <lb/>[15] A. P. Ramirez, Phys. Lett. A 211, 59 (1996). <lb/>[16] J. E. Sonier, M. F. Hundley, and J. W. Brill, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 4914 (1999). <lb/>[17] C. Kubert and P. J. Hirschfeld, Solid State <lb/>Com. 105, 459 (1998); C. Kubert and P. J. <lb/>Hirschfeld, Phys. Rev. Lett. 80, 4963 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[18] Y. S. Barash, A. A. Svidzinskii, and V. P. <lb/>Mineev, JETP Lett. 65, 638 (1997). <lb/>[19] E. Janod, R. Calemczuk, J.-Y. Henry, J. <lb/>Flouquet, Physica C 281, 176 (1997); the <lb/>theory including the effects of impurity <lb/>scattering was written by G. E. Volovik in <lb/>Appendix A of this paper. <lb/>[20] O. N. Bakharev, M. V. Eremin, and M. A. <lb/>Teplov, JETP Lett. 61, 515 (1995). <lb/>[21] P. G. Baranov and A. G. Badalyan, Solid <lb/>State Communications 85, 987 (1993). <lb/>[22] J. P. Emerson, D. A. Wright, B. F. <lb/>Woodfield, J. E. Golden, R.A. Fisher, and N. <lb/>E. Phillips, Phys. Rev. Lett. 82, 1546 <lb/>(1999). <lb/>[23] G. E. Volovik (private communication). <lb/>[24] P. J. Hirschfeld (private communication). <lb/>[25] T. Nakano, N. Momono, T. Nagata, M. Oda, <lb/>and M. Ido, Phys. Rev. 58, 5831 (1998). <lb/>[26] J.-Y. Lin, H. D. Yang, T. I. Hsu, and H. C. <lb/>Ku, unpublished. <lb/>[27] J.-Y. Lin, C. F. Chang, and H. D. Yang, <lb/>Physica B, in press. <lb/>[28] D. L. Sisson, S. G. Doettinger, A. <lb/>Kapitulnik, R. Liang, D. A. Bonn, and W. N. <lb/>Hardy, cond-mat/9904131. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure captions <lb/>Fig. 1. C/T vs. T 2 of La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 <lb/>with x=0,0.01 and 0.02 at H=0. The solid lines <lb/>are the results of the fit by Eq. (1). Inset: C/T vs. <lb/>T for T&lt;2 K, where the contribution from the T 2 <lb/>term is apparent. <lb/>F i g . <lb/>2 . <lb/>( a ) <lb/>C/T <lb/>v s . <lb/>T 2 <lb/>o f <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 in magnetic fields. The <lb/>solid lines are the results of the fit by Eq. (1). <lb/>For clarity, only data in H=0, 0.2, 1, 4, and 8 T <lb/>are shown. (b) The concentration n of the spin-2 <lb/>PC&apos;s from the fit. <lb/>Fig. 3. The components of C(T,H) of <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 . <lb/>Fig. 4. Normalized g(H) vs. H 1/2 for three <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 samples. The solid lines <lb/>are the results of the fit by Eq. (2), which <lb/>includes the impurity effects on C(T,H). Dash <lb/>lines represent g(H)µH 1/2 expected in clean <lb/>d-wave superconductors. In (a) no solid line is <lb/>presented since the fit by Eq. (2) gives a <lb/>unrealistic value of H c2 &gt;1000 T. g n =12 mJ/mol <lb/>K 2 is the normal state g of the samples [5]. <lb/>Fig. 5. Plots of C e /(TH 1/2 ) vs. H 1/2 /T for (a) <lb/>x=0, (b) x=0.01, and (c) x=0.02. Note that the <lb/>scaling which holds in (a) breaks down in (b) <lb/>and (c) due to impurity scattering. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 15 20 25 30 35 40 45 50 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/>x=0.02 <lb/>x=0.01 <lb/>x=0 <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 1-x Ni x O 4 <lb/>C/T (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>T <lb/>2 (K <lb/>2 ) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Fig. 1. <lb/>x=0 <lb/>T (K) <lb/>C/T (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 12 14 16 18 20 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>11 <lb/>12 <lb/>(a) <lb/>8T <lb/>4T <lb/>1T <lb/>0.2T <lb/>0T <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 <lb/>C/T (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>T <lb/>2 (K <lb/>2 ) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>Fig. 2 <lb/>(b) <lb/>n (10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>mol/mol LSCO) <lb/>H (T) <lb/>7 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 <lb/>10 <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 <lb/>C/T (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>nC S=2 (8 T)/T <lb/>nC S=2 (1 T)/T <lb/>nC S=2 (0 T)/T <lb/>C lattice /T <lb/>g (8 T) <lb/>g (1 T) <lb/>g (0 T) <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>(a) <lb/>g/g <lb/>n <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 CuO 4 <lb/>g(H) propotional to H <lb/>1/2 <lb/>g/g <lb/>n <lb/>H <lb/>1/2 (T <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.40 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>(b) <lb/>g/g <lb/>n <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.98 Ni 0.02 O 4 <lb/>Impurity scattering effect with G/D 0 =0.020, H c2 =38 T <lb/>g(H) propotional to H <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.55 <lb/>Fig. 4. <lb/>(c) <lb/>Impurity scattering effect with G/D 0 =0.025, H c2 =38 T <lb/>g(H) propotional to H <lb/>1/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>(a) <lb/>C <lb/>e <lb/>/(TH <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>T <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) <lb/>C <lb/>e <lb/>/(TH <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>T <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 CuO 4 <lb/>6 K <lb/>5 K <lb/>4 K <lb/>3 K <lb/>2 K <lb/>1 K <lb/>C <lb/>e <lb/>/(TH <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) (mJ/mol K <lb/>2 <lb/>T <lb/>1/2 <lb/>) <lb/>H <lb/>1/2 /T (T <lb/>1/2 <lb/>/K) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>(b) <lb/>6 K <lb/>5 K <lb/>4 K <lb/>3 K <lb/>2 K <lb/>1 K <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.99 Ni 0.01 O 4 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>Fig. 5 <lb/>(c) <lb/>6 K <lb/>5 K <lb/>4 K <lb/>3 K <lb/>2 K <lb/>1 K <lb/>La 1.78 Sr 0.22 Cu 0.98 Ni 0.02 O 4 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
