<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0502576v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 24 Feb 2005 <lb/>PREPRINT (November 23, 2018) <lb/>Pressure effects on the superconducting properties of YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 <lb/>R. Khasanov, 1, 2, 3 T. Schneider, 3 and H. Keller 3 <lb/>1 Laboratory for Neutron Scattering, ETH Zürich and Paul Scherrer Institut, CH-5232 Villigen PSI, Switzerland <lb/>2 DPMC, Université de Genève, 24 Quai Ernest-Ansermet, 1211 Genève 4, Switzerland <lb/>3 Physik-Institut der Universität Zürich, Winterthurerstrasse 190, CH-8057, Zürich, Switzerland <lb/>Measurements of the magnetization under high hydrostatic pressure (up to 10.2 kbar) in <lb/>YBa2Cu4O8 were carried out. From the scaling analysis of the magnetization data the pressure <lb/>induced shifts of the transition temperature Tc, the volume V and the anisotropy γ have been ob-<lb/>tained. It was shown that the pressure induced relative shift of Tc mirrors essentially that of the <lb/>anisotropy. This observation uncovers a novel generic property of anisotropic type II superconduc-<lb/>tors, that inexistent in the isotropic case. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.72.Bk, 74.62.Fj, 74.25.Ha, 83.80.Fg <lb/></front>

			<body>In the cuprate high-temperature superconductors <lb/>(HTS), the canonical change in T c with pressure is that it <lb/>first increases, passes through a maximum value at some <lb/>critical pressure, and then decreases. 1,2 It has been ar-<lb/>gued that there are at least two effects determining the <lb/>total pressure dependence of T c , an intrinsic effect and <lb/>the one that arises from the pressure-induced changes in <lb/>the charge carrier concentration. 1,2 However, there are ef-<lb/>fects which make the discrimination between these contri-<lb/>butions difficult. In most HTS the application of pressure <lb/>doesn&apos;t simply compress the lattice, but also prompts <lb/>mobile oxygen defects to assume a greater degree of lo-<lb/>cal order. 3 This leads to relaxation effects which are both <lb/>temperature and pressure dependent. An exception is the <lb/>double-chain compound YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 with a fixed oxygen <lb/>stoichiometry. Bucher et al. [4] found that in this com-<lb/>pound T c increases under hydrostatic pressure with the <lb/>rate dT c /dp ≃ 5.5 K/GPa. Subsequent studies revealed <lb/>that with increasing pressure T c passes through a maxi-<lb/>mum around 9 GPa and then decreases. 1,2,3 Furthermore, <lb/>measurements of the in-plane penetration depth λ ab of <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 revealed pressure induced changes which <lb/>cannot be simply attributed to the pressure changes of <lb/>T c . 5,6 Since in cuprate high-temperature superconduc-<lb/>tors, including YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 , the critical regime where <lb/>thermal critical fluctuations dominate is experimentally <lb/>accessible, various critical properties are not independent <lb/>but related by universal realtions. 7,8,9,10,11,12,13,14 Ac-<lb/>cordingly, the isotope or pressure effects on these quanti-<lb/>ties are related as well. 11,14 Here we explore the universal <lb/>relationship between the pressure effects on transition <lb/>temperature T c , volume V and anisotropy γ emerging <lb/>from the pressure induced changes of the magnetization <lb/>near T c . It is shown that in the underdoped YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 <lb/>the pressure effect on T c mirrors essentially that on the <lb/>anisotropy. This uncovers a novel generic property of <lb/>anisotropic type II superconductors, inexistent in the <lb/>isotropic case. <lb/>The polycrystalline YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 samples were synthe-<lb/>sized by solid-state reactions using high-purity Y 2 O 3 , <lb/>BaCO 3 and CuO. 5 The hydrostatic pressure was gen-<lb/>erated in a copper-beryllium piston cylinder clamp that <lb/>was especially designed for magnetization measurements <lb/>under pressure. 15 The sample was thoroughly mixed with <lb/>Fluorient FC77 (pressure transmitting medium) with a <lb/>sample to liquid volume ratio of approximately 1/6. The <lb/>pressure was measured in situ by monitoring the T c shift <lb/>of the small piece of In [T c (p = 0) ≃ 3.4K] included in the <lb/>pressure cell. The field-cooled magnetization measure-<lb/>ments were performed with a Quantum Design SQUID <lb/>magnetometer at temperatures ranging from 2 to 100K. <lb/>In Fig. 1(a) we displayed the field-cooled (0.5 mT) mag-<lb/>netization M of a YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 powder sample vs. T near <lb/>T c for various applied hydrostatic pressures (0.0 kbar, <lb/>2.67 kbar, 4.29 kbar, 7.52 kbar, and 10.2 kbar). To iden-<lb/>tify the temperature regime where critical fluctuations <lb/>play an essential role it is instructive to consider the be-<lb/>havior of dM/dT vs. T displayed in Fig. 1(b). With <lb/>decreasing temperature dM/dT is seen to raise below <lb/>the transition temperature and after passing a maximum <lb/>value it decreases. This behavior contradicts the mean-<lb/>field behavior where dM/dT below T c adopts a constant <lb/>value. 16 It implies that the fluctuation dominated regime <lb/>is accessible and attained. This calls for an analysis be-<lb/>yond the mean-field approximation as outlined below. <lb/>The detailed description of the scaling analysis adopted <lb/>for magnetization changes caused by isotope substitution <lb/>or applying pressure can be found in Refs. 17 and 18. <lb/>Briefly, the basic principles of the analysis can be summa-<lb/>rized as follows. When three-dimensional (3D) Gaussian <lb/>or 3D-XY thermal fluctuations dominate, the combina-<lb/>tion m (T, δ, H) / γǫ 3/2 (δ) T <lb/>√ <lb/>H adopts at T c a fixed <lb/>value 8,9,10,12 <lb/>m (T c ) <lb/>T c γǫ 3/2 (γ, δ) Tc <lb/>√ <lb/>H <lb/>= − <lb/>k B C <lb/>Φ <lb/>3/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>where m = M/V is the magnetization per unit volume, <lb/>C a constant adopting for Gaussian and 3D-XY fluctu-<lb/>ations distinct universal values. Furthermore, ǫ (δ) = <lb/>cos 2 (δ) + sin 2 (δ) /γ 2 1/2 , where δ is the angle between <lb/>the applied magnetic field H and the c-axis, Φ 0 the flux <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>-3.0x10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-2.0x10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-1.0x10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>M (emu) <lb/>(a) <lb/>75 <lb/>80 <lb/>85 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>2.0x10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>4.0x10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>6.0x10 <lb/>-5 <lb/>dM/dT (emu/K) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>(b) <lb/>FIG. 1: <lb/>(a) Field-cooled (0.5mT) magnetization of a <lb/>YBa2Cu4O8 powder sample vs. T near Tc for various applied <lb/>hydrostatic pressures (from the left to the right) 0.0 kbar, <lb/>2.67 kbar, 4.29 kbar, 7.52 kbar, and 10.2 kbar. (b) dM/dT <lb/>vs. T for the data shown in Fig. 1(a) <lb/>quantum, and k B Boltzmann&apos;s constant. In powder sam-<lb/>ples this relation reduces to <lb/>m (T c ) <lb/>T c <lb/>√ <lb/>Hf (γ (T c )) <lb/>= − <lb/>k B C <lb/>Φ <lb/>3/2 <lb/>0 <lb/>, f (γ (T c )) = γ ǫ 3/2 (γ, δ) <lb/>Tc <lb/>. <lb/>(2) <lb/>As the pressure effect on the magnetization at fixed mag-<lb/>netic field is concerned it implies that the relative shifts <lb/>of the magnetization M , volume V , magnetization per <lb/>unit volume m, anisotropy γ and T c are not independent <lb/>but close to T c related by <lb/>∆M <lb/>M <lb/>= <lb/>∆V <lb/>V <lb/>+ <lb/>∆T c <lb/>T c <lb/>+ <lb/>∆f <lb/>f <lb/>. <lb/>(3) <lb/>For YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 , where γ &gt;&gt; 1 (see e.g. Ref. 19) it <lb/>reduces to <lb/>∆M <lb/>M <lb/>= <lb/>∆V <lb/>V <lb/>+ <lb/>∆T c <lb/>T c <lb/>+ <lb/>∆γ <lb/>γ <lb/>(4) <lb/>On that condition it is impossible to extract these <lb/>changes from the temperature dependence of the mag-<lb/>netization. However, supposing that close to criticality <lb/>the magnetization data scale within experimental error <lb/>as <lb/>p=0 M (T ) = p M (aT ) , <lb/>(5) <lb/>the universal relation (4) reduces to <lb/>∆T c <lb/>T c <lb/>= − <lb/>∆V <lb/>V <lb/>− <lb/>∆γ <lb/>γ <lb/>= <lb/>T c (p) <lb/>T c (0) <lb/>− 1 = <lb/>1 <lb/>a <lb/>− 1. <lb/>(6) <lb/>In Fig. 2 we displayed the magnetization data rescaled <lb/>according to Eq.(5). Near T c the pressure induced <lb/>changes in M (aT ) is negligibly small so that Eqs. (5) <lb/>and (6) can be applied within experimental error. <lb/>76 <lb/>78 <lb/>80 <lb/>82 <lb/>-2.0x10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>-1.0x10 <lb/>-4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>M (emu) <lb/>aT (K) <lb/>p (kbar) <lb/>a <lb/>0kbar <lb/>1 <lb/>2.67 kbar <lb/>0.98 <lb/>4.29 kbar <lb/>0.97 <lb/>7.52 kbar <lb/>0.952 <lb/>10.20 kbar 0.936 <lb/>FIG. 2: <lb/>Magnetization data rescaled according to <lb/>p=0 M (T ) = p M (aT ) [Eq.(5)]. <lb/>Since a is less than one and decreases with increasing <lb/>pressure the transition temperature increases in the pres-<lb/>sure range considered here. Given then the bulk modulus <lb/>B = 1174 kbar (Ref. 4) for the pressure dependence of <lb/>the relative volume change we obtain the expression <lb/>∆V <lb/>V <lb/>= − <lb/>p (kbar) <lb/>1174 <lb/>, <lb/>(7) <lb/>and with Eq.(6) the estimates for the pressure induced <lb/>changes of the anisotropy listed in Table I. It is readily <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I: Estimates for the pressure induced relative change of volume V , transition temperature Tc and anisotropy γ derived <lb/>from the data shown in Fig. 2 with the aid of Eqs.(5), (6) and (7). Tc and λ −2 <lb/>ab0 at p = 0, 4.29, 7.52, and 10.2 kbar taken from <lb/>Khasanov et al. Ref. 5. Tc and λ −2 <lb/>ab0 at p =1.2 and 2.67 kbar were obtained from the linear interpolation of Tc(p) and λ −2 <lb/>ab0 (p) <lb/>data from Ref. 5. ∆ξc0/ξc0 follows from Eq.(9) and ∆ξ ab0 /ξ ab0 from relation (10). Hereafter the relative pressure shift of the <lb/>physical quantity X is determined as ∆X(p)/X(0) = [X(p) − X(0)]/X(0). <lb/>p (kbar) ∆V /V <lb/>a ∆Tc/Tc ∆γ/γ Tc(K) λ −2 <lb/>ab0 (µm −2 ) ∆ξco/ξc0 ∆ξ abo /ξ ab0 2∆λ abo /λ ab0 <lb/>0 <lb/>-<lb/>1 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>79.07 <lb/>34.3 <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>1.2 <lb/>-0.0010 0.991 0.008 -0.007 79.67 <lb/>35.9 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>-0.05 <lb/>2.67 -0.0023 0.98 0.017 -0.015 80.41 <lb/>37.5 <lb/>-0.07 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>-0.09 <lb/>4.29 -0.0037 0.97 0.031 -0.027 81.4 <lb/>39.2 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>-0.13 <lb/>-0.14 <lb/>7.52 -0.0064 0.952 0.050 -0.044 82.73 <lb/>44.1 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-0.23 <lb/>-0.28 <lb/>10.2 -0.0087 0.936 0.068 -0.059 84.22 <lb/>45.0 <lb/>-0.19 <lb/>-0.25 <lb/>-0.32 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.06 <lb/>0.08 <lb/>-0.08 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>-0.04 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>T <lb/>c <lb/>/T <lb/>c <lb/>p ( kbar) <lb/>/ <lb/>FIG. 3: ∆Tc/Tc (•) and ∆γ/γ ( ) vs. p for the estimates <lb/>listed in Table I. The solid line is ∆Tc/Tc = 0.0068p and the <lb/>dashed one is ∆γ/γ = −0.006p with p in kbar. <lb/>seen that the rise of T c mirrors essentially the decrease of <lb/>the anisotropy. Indeed the relative volume change is an <lb/>order of magnitude smaller. Furthermore, from Fig. 3, <lb/>showing ∆T c /T c and ∆γ/γ versus p for the estimates <lb/>listed in Table I, it is seen that in the pressure range <lb/>considered here, both ∆T c /T c and ∆γ/γ depend nearly <lb/>linearly on pressure. Thus, under pressure not only T c <lb/>and the volume changes but the anisotropy is modified as <lb/>well. A quick glance to Table I reveal that the pressure <lb/>effect on T c mirrors essentially that on the anisotropy. <lb/>In addition, recent in-plane penetration depth λ ab mea-<lb/>surements revealed that there is a pressure effect on this <lb/>important property also. 5 It was shown that the in-plane <lb/>penetration depth data of YBa 2 Cu 2 O 8 is consistent with <lb/>3D-XY critical behavior, 5 where the penetration depth <lb/>and correlation length in direction i diverge near T c as <lb/>λ 2 <lb/>i (T ) = λ 2 <lb/>i0 t −ν and ξ i (T ) = ξ i0 t −ν with t = 1 − T /T c <lb/>and ν ≃ 2/3. Moreover, as listed in Table I, the critical <lb/>amplitude λ −2 <lb/>ab0 was found to be pressure dependent. The <lb/>consistency with 3D-XY critical behavior implies that <lb/>the transition temperature T c and the critical amplitudes <lb/>of the in-plane penetration depths λ ab0 and the c-axis <lb/>correlation lengths ξ c0 are not independent but related <lb/>by 7,8,9,10,14,20 <lb/>k B T c = <lb/>Φ 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>16π 3 <lb/>f ξ c0 <lb/>λ 2 <lb/>ab0 <lb/>, f ≃ 0.453. <lb/>(8) <lb/>Universality implies that this relation holds irrespective <lb/>of the applied pressure. Thus, in addition to Eq.(6) the <lb/>pressure induced relative changes are then related by <lb/>∆T c <lb/>T c <lb/>= −2 <lb/>∆λ ab0 <lb/>λ ab0 <lb/>+ <lb/>∆ξ c0 <lb/>ξ c0 <lb/>(9) <lb/>and, because of γ = ξ ab0 /ξ c0 , <lb/>∆γ <lb/>γ <lb/>= <lb/>∆ξ ab0 <lb/>ξ ab0 <lb/>− <lb/>∆ξ c0 <lb/>ξ c0 <lb/>. <lb/>(10) <lb/>Using then the estimates for ∆T c /T c and −2∆λ ab0 /λ ab0 <lb/>the relative change ∆ξ c0 /ξ c0 is readily calculated with <lb/>aid of Eq. (9), while the values for ∆ξ ab0 /ξ ab0 follow from <lb/>relation (10). The values of ∆ξ c0 /ξ c0 and ∆ξ ab0 /ξ ab0 are <lb/>listed in Table I. <lb/>From the scaling analysis of the pressure effect on mag-<lb/>netization and in-plane penetration depth it then emerges <lb/>that the rise of the transition temperature of underdoped <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 with increasing pressure is associated with a <lb/>decreasing anisotropy and volume V . The relative change <lb/>of the transition temperature ∆T c /T c is seen to mirror <lb/>essentially that of the anisotropy ∆γ/γ. This is consis-<lb/>tent with the generic behavior for high-temperature su-<lb/>perconductors, where for a given HTS family T c increases <lb/>with reduced aniostropy. 10,13,14 Although these changes <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

		<body>are small compared to those in the critical amplitudes <lb/>of the in-plane penetration depth ∆λ abo /λ abo and the <lb/>correlation lengths ∆ξ ab0 /ξ ab0 , ∆ξ c0 /ξ c0 (see Table I) <lb/>it becomes clear that the pressure induced change of the <lb/>anisotropy is the essential ingredient which remains to be <lb/>understood microscopically. Empirically the anisotropy <lb/>decreases rather steeply by approaching optimum doping <lb/>and levels off in the overdoped regime. 10,13,14 Together <lb/>with Eq.(6) this explains why the pressure effect on T c <lb/>becomes very small in optimally and overdoped cuprate <lb/>superconductors. 1,2,3 <lb/></body>

		<div type="acknowledgement">This work was partially supported by the Swiss Na-<lb/>tional Science Foundation, the NCCR program Materials <lb/>with Novel Electronic Properties (MaNEP) sponsored by <lb/>the Swiss National Science Foundation. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>1 H. Takahashi and N. Mori, in Studies of High Temperature <lb/>Superconductors, ed. by A.V. Narlikar (Nova Science, New <lb/>York, 1995) Vol.16, p. 1. <lb/>2 R.J. Wijngaarden, D.T. Jover, and R. Griessen, Physica B <lb/>265, 128 (1999). <lb/>3 A.-K. Klehe, C. Looney, J.S. Schilling, H. Takahashi, <lb/>N. Mori, Y. Shimakawa, Y. Kubo, T. Manako, S. Doyle, <lb/>and A.M. Hermann, Physica C 257, 105 (1996). <lb/>4 B. Bucher et al. Physica C 157, 478 (1989). <lb/>5 R. Khasanov, T. Schneider, R. Brütsch, D. Gavillet, <lb/>J. Karpinski, and H. Keller, Phys. Rev. B 70, 144515 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>6 R. Khasanov, <lb/>J. Karpinski, <lb/>and H. Keller, <lb/>cond-mat/0405643. <lb/>7 T. Schneider and H. Keller, Int. J. Mod. Phys. B 8, 487 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>8 T. Schneider, J. Hofer, M. Willemin, J.M. Singer, and <lb/>H. Keller, Eur. Phys. J. B 3, 413 (1998). <lb/>9 T. Schneider and J. M. Singer, Phase Transition Approach <lb/>To High Temperature Superconductivity, (Imperial College <lb/>Press, London, 2000). <lb/>10 T. Schneider, in: The Physics of Superconductors, edited <lb/>by K. Bennemann and J.B. Ketterson (Springer, Berlin, <lb/>(2004), p. 111. <lb/>11 T. Schneider, Phys. Rev. B 67, 134514 (2003). <lb/>12 T. Schneider, Journal of Superconductivity, 17, 41 (2004). <lb/>13 T. Schneider and H. Keller, New Journal of Physics 6, 144 <lb/>(2004). <lb/>14 T. Schneider, Phys. Stat. Sol. B 242, 58 (2005). <lb/>15 T. Strässle, Ph.D. thesis, ETH Zürich, 2002. <lb/>16 A. Abrikosov, Zh. Eksp. Teor. Fiz. 32, 1442 (1957); Sov. <lb/>Phys. JETP 5, 1174 (1957). <lb/>17 T. Schneider, cond-mat/0410547. <lb/>18 T. Schneider and D.Di Castro, cond-mat/0502202. <lb/>19 N. Kagawa, T. Ishida, K. Okuda, S. Adachi, and <lb/>S. Tajiama, Physica C 357-360, 302 (2001). <lb/>20 A. Peliasetto and E. Vicari, Physics Reports 368, 549 <lb/>(2002). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
