<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9904131v2 [cond-mat.supr-con] 4 Nov 1999 <lb/>Specific Heat of Zn-Doped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 : Possible Evidence for Kondo Screening in <lb/>the Superconducting State <lb/>D. L. Sisson, S. G. Doettinger, and A. Kapitulnik <lb/>Departments of Applied Physics and of Physics, Stanford University, Stanford, CA 94305, USA <lb/>R. Liang, D. A. Bonn, and W. N. Hardy <lb/>Department of Physics, UBC, Vancouver, British Columbia V6T1Z1 <lb/>(August 12, 2018) <lb/>The magnetic field dependence of the specific heat of Zn-doped single crystals of YBa2Cu3O6.95 <lb/>was measured between 2 and 10 K and up to 8 Tesla. Doping levels of 0, 0.15%, 0.31%, and 1% <lb/>were studied and compared. In particular we searched for the Schottky anomaly associated with <lb/>the Zn-induced magnetic moments. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25, 74.62.D, 75.20.H <lb/></front>

			<body>Among systems for controlled studies of the effect of <lb/>disorder on the properties of cuprate superconductors, <lb/>Zn-doped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7−δ (YBCO) is a particularly in-<lb/>teresting choice. Unlike most dopants, Zn substitutes <lb/>for Cu on the planes [1] and causes significant changes <lb/>to the local electronic structure without much change <lb/>of hole concentration [2]. In the superconducting state <lb/>Zn substitution dramatically changes both the transition <lb/>temperature [3] and the temperature dependence of the <lb/>low-temperature penetration depth [4]. NMR and mag-<lb/>netization measurements in the normal state suggested <lb/>that Zn induces a weak magnetic moment µ ef f =0.32 to <lb/>0.36 µ B /Zn for fully oxygenated crystals, and that this <lb/>moment increases as the oxygen content decreases [3,5]. <lb/>An oxygen reduced sample (O 6.66 ) which exhibited a spin <lb/>gap showed a moment of 0.86µ B /Zn [6]. A model in <lb/>which each Zn atom effects the local magnetic order of <lb/>nearby copper atoms on the scale of the magnetic cop-<lb/>per correlation length (which varies with δ) explains the <lb/>normal-state magnetic measurements on this system [7]. <lb/>In the superconducting state, NMR measurements sug-<lb/>gested that in Zn substituted YBCO there exists a finite <lb/>electronic density of states (DOS) at the Fermi level [8]. <lb/>Early specific heat measurements [9] seemed to agreed <lb/>with this conclusion indicating increased DOS in the su-<lb/>perconducting state in Zn substituted samples. <lb/>Simple valence counting suggests that if the Zn impu-<lb/>rity maintains a nominal Cu 2+ charge, the Zn 2+ would <lb/>have a (3d) 10 , S=0 configuration and act as a nonmag-<lb/>netic impurity. Thus, it is important to understand <lb/>whether a nonmagnetic impurity can induce a local mo-<lb/>ment on the surrounding Cu 2+ sites. Early theoreti-<lb/>cal treatment of the problem expected that a nonmag-<lb/>netic impurity can only induce a local moment when the <lb/>&quot;mother&quot; phase has a spin gap [10]. Further studies of <lb/>this problem concluded that in a doped antiferromag-<lb/>net with no spin gap an induced localized magnetization <lb/>will exist around the impurity but it does not correspond <lb/>to a free moment. At low enough temperatures where <lb/>the staggered correlation length is larger than the local-<lb/>ization length associated with the impurity distortion, <lb/>this localized moment is always aligned with the local <lb/>staggered order [11]. While the question of whether the <lb/>magnetic moments exist in a global sense and in par-<lb/>ticular whether the moments are observable below the <lb/>superconducting transition temperature is still an open <lb/>question, new theoretical ideas argue that the moments <lb/>may be partially screened below the spin gap and fully <lb/>screened deep in the superconducting state [12] in the <lb/>cuprates. Recently, there has been some theoretical work <lb/>done considering the fact of a possible Kondo-screening. <lb/>In a conventional s-wave superconductor, the Kondo ef-<lb/>fect is suppressed by the formation of the superconduct-<lb/>ing gap, as shown by Abrikosov and Gorkov [13]. In d-<lb/>wave superconductors, however, there are quasiparticles <lb/>in the node lines which could cause a Kondo screening. <lb/>Indeed, Fradkin and Cassanello recently calculated the <lb/>thermodynamic properties of a d-wave superconductors <lb/>with magnetic impurities [14]. They predicted a screen-<lb/>ing mechanism analogous to the exchange coupling be-<lb/>tween magnetic impurities and the electrons in a Fermi <lb/>liquid that causes the Kondo effect. In the clean limit, <lb/>the Dirac like quasiparticles and the magnetic impurity <lb/>form a singlet state. The screening is only effective above <lb/>a critical exchange coupling , because in contrast to the <lb/>Kondo effect in metals, the density of states of normal <lb/>quasiparticles in a d-wave superconductor vanishes at the <lb/>Fermi surface. In this limit, the magnetic susceptibilty <lb/>disappears superlinearly, hence the effect can be consid-<lb/>ered as overscreening. <lb/>Observing the effect of a low concentration of Zn dop-<lb/>ing on the magnetic behavior of the cuprates in the su-<lb/>perconducting state is practically impossible due to the <lb/>strong signal associated with the vortex state. However, <lb/>applying a magnetic field will split the free Zn-induced <lb/>moments into a two-level system and a Schottky anomaly <lb/>should be apparent in the low temperature specific heat. <lb/>In the present paper we provide a comprehensive study <lb/>of the effect of Zn impurities on the behavior of low-lying <lb/>electronic excitations in YBCO. To this end we study <lb/>the specific heat of pure, 0.15%, 0.31% and 1% Zn-doped <lb/>single crystals YBCO samples. We extend earlier mea-<lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>surements on Zn-doped polycrystalline YBCO samples. <lb/>Compared to pure YBCO we find that: i) The linear-T <lb/>term, which has been regularly observed in specific heat <lb/>measurements of YBCO [15] is greatly increased. This <lb/>result is only qualitatively consistent with the &quot;dirty d-<lb/>wave&quot; scenario [16,17] used to explain the penetration <lb/>depth measurements and the suppression of T c . ii) The <lb/>T 3 term decreases, suggesting either a surprisingly large <lb/>increase in the Debye temperature or a new electronic <lb/>contribution with a similar temperature dependence. iii) <lb/>A low temperature upturn T −2 below ∼3.5 K is observed. <lb/>This upturn is seen in many specific heat measurements <lb/>[18] , though , its origin is still unclear. iv) The most <lb/>intriguing result of our measurements is that there is no <lb/>apparent increase in the number of free magnetic mo-<lb/>ments as indicated by a Schottky anomaly in any of the <lb/>Zn-doped samples as compared with the pure sample. <lb/>Normal state measurements of the magnetization of the <lb/>1% sample is in agreement with previous measurements <lb/>indicating a magnetic moment of the size ∼0.36 µ B /Zn. <lb/>From these results, we conclude that the magnetic mo-<lb/>ments that exist in the normal state must be screened at <lb/>low temperatures in the superconducting state. <lb/>Pure and Zn-doped YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 (optimally doped) <lb/>single crystals were grown by a flux-growth technique. <lb/>The detailed process and the characterization of the sam-<lb/>ples is described in [4]. The Zn concentration was deter-<lb/>mined by comparing T c of the crystals to powder sam-<lb/>ples with known Zn concentration and annealed at the <lb/>same conditions. This method gives an accuracy of 0.01 <lb/>-0.02% Zn per Cu. With increasing Zn-doping, the T c <lb/>is suppressed by ∆T c ∼12K/% Zn. Magnetic measure-<lb/>ments showed that in our 1% sample the T c is suppressed <lb/>by 12 K. Specific heat data were taken using the relax-<lb/>ation method, which especially allows the measurement <lb/>of relatively small samples. The addenda heat capacity <lb/>of the calorimeter was measured independently and sub-<lb/>tracted from the sample measurements. A more detailed <lb/>description is found elsewhere [15,19]. <lb/>Specific heat data on the Zn-doped YBCO crystal were <lb/>taken between 2 and 12 K at zero field and between 2 and <lb/>8 K at 0.5, 2, 4, 6, and 8 Tesla. The specific heat was <lb/>measured as a function of temperature at constant mag-<lb/>netic field which was applied above T c before cooling the <lb/>sample. The zero-field results are shown in figure 1, plot-<lb/>ted as c(T )/T vs. T 2 and compared with pure (0% Zn) <lb/>samples. In this representation, for a normal metal, the <lb/>slope β is the coefficient of the lattice T 3 term and the <lb/>intercept γ is the coefficient of the linear electronic heat <lb/>capacity and proportional to its density of states. Devi-<lb/>ations from this γT + βT 3 behavior are not very notice-<lb/>able for the nominally pure sample, but with increasing <lb/>Zn concentration the samples show a low-temperature <lb/>upturn below ∼3 K. Also, from a visual observation, <lb/>the curves for the Zn-doped samples have larger γ, and <lb/>smaller β suggesting higher electronic density of states <lb/>and higher Debye temperatures with increasing Zn con-<lb/>centration. While the cause of the low-temperature up-<lb/>turn is still unknown, there are some indications that it <lb/>is related to interaction between paramagnetic impurities <lb/>and a local field [18,20] or a result of collective behavior <lb/>of these impurities [18]. This is supported by our finding <lb/>that this upturn is somewhat influenced by the quality of <lb/>the sample. Previous reports of early samples of YBCO, <lb/>showed a much larger low-temperature upturn in the spe-<lb/>cific heat, thus, a straightforward fitting of the data at <lb/>higher temperatures (e.g. ≥ 5 K) to avoid the upturn will <lb/>result in misleading values of both the γT term and the <lb/>βT 3 term [20]. Although the &quot;upturn effect&quot; is not too <lb/>large below 3.5 K, and does not effect our overall data, <lb/>we still include it in our analysis as discussed below. <lb/>The magnetic field dependence is shown in figure 2 for <lb/>the 1% Zn sample. The lower Zn concentration samples <lb/>show similar behavior. The most notable result here is <lb/>the further increase in the extrapolated intercept with <lb/>the c(T )/T axis, an indication of further increase in the <lb/>quasi-particles density of states upon the application of <lb/>magnetic field. Based on our previous results on pure <lb/>YBCO crystals [15] we first attempt the general fit: <lb/>c(T, H = 0) = A(0)/T N + γ(0)T + βT 3 , <lb/>c(T, H ≥ 0.5T ) = A(H)/T N + γ(H)T + βT 3 <lb/>+c Sch (T, H) <lb/>(1) <lb/>where we omitted the T 2 term for the Zn doped samples <lb/>as we no longer expect to have clean lines of nodes, and <lb/>we attempt to account for the uncertainty in the upturn <lb/>by allowing the power law used to describe it to vary <lb/>as T −N where N=1,2. In these equations, β is field in-<lb/>dependent and the βT 3 term is assumed to result from <lb/>phonons. c Sch (T, H) is a Schottky anomaly associated <lb/>with a field-independent molar concentration ν Sch of free <lb/>spin-1/2 moments. Finally, we have a free function γ(H). <lb/>For pure samples, the coefficient of this linear-T term is <lb/>found to obey γ(H) = γ(0) +γ(H) where γ(0) decreases <lb/>as twin boundaries and oxygen vacancies are removed <lb/>from the crystal (for O 6.99 , γ(0) ∼ 1 mJ/mol-K 2 ), and <lb/>γ(H) ∝ H 1/2 with a coefficient which agrees semiquan-<lb/>titatively with the prediction for lines of nodes [21]. For <lb/>the low temperature upturn, in fitting only the zero-field <lb/>data, the best fit was obtained with N=2. However, a <lb/>global fit using data of all fields for a given Zn concen-<lb/>tration results in a best fit with N=1. As our results and <lb/>in particular the conclusions based on the results were <lb/>not sensitive to the choice of N, we used N=1 in all of <lb/>the following data analyses. In general we found that <lb/>the field dependence of the 1/T low temperature upturn <lb/>is not consistent with increasing spin-1/2 impurities: it <lb/>does not change dramatically with applied field and does <lb/>not become a Schottky-like term either. The coefficients <lb/>that we obtained in this fit are given in Table I. <lb/>Starting our analysis with the effect of Zn-doping on <lb/>β , we find that β = 0.308, 0.284, and 0.274 mJ/mol-K 4 <lb/>for the 0.15%, 0.31% and 1% Zn doped samples respec-<lb/>tively, as compared with 0.392± 0.001 mJ/mol-K 4 for <lb/>the nominally pure sample. If this T 3 term is only asso-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>ciated with phonons, it corresponds to an increase in the <lb/>Debye temperature from 403 K in the nominally pure <lb/>sample to 454 K in the 1% Zn-doped sample. Such a <lb/>large increase is very surprising and may indicate that <lb/>a portion of the T 3 term is electronic in nature. The <lb/>linear term, γ(0)T , also increases with Zn doping. The <lb/>zero-field linear-T term increases from 3.0 mJ/mol-K 2 in <lb/>the nominally pure sample to 4.3, 5.8 and 11.7 mJ/mol-<lb/>K 2 in the 0.15%, 0.31% and 1% Zn doped samples re-<lb/>spectively. Assuming a normal state linear T coefficient <lb/>γ n ∼20 mJ/mol-K 2 , this implies a residual density of <lb/>states ratios n res = N (E F )/N n of 0.066, 0.14, and 0.43 <lb/>for the three crystals (here N (E F ) is the density of states <lb/>at the Fermi level and N n is the density of states in the <lb/>normal state that results in that γ n ). From penetration <lb/>depth measurements of crystals from the same batches <lb/>[4], an analysis based on a &quot;dirty d-wave&quot; [17] found a <lb/>scattering parameter Γ/T c ≃ 0.018-0.030 for 0.31% Zn <lb/>doping and Γ/T c ≃ 0.006-0.009 for the 0.15% Zn dop-<lb/>ing. In the limit of strong resonant scattering the dirty <lb/>d-wave model predicts Γ ∝ n 2 <lb/>res with a logarithmic cor-<lb/>rection of order ln(T c n res /Γ) . Ref. [17] shows reasonable <lb/>agreement with that prediction using penetration depth <lb/>data of 0.15% and 0.31%. To analyze the specific heat <lb/>we first need to estimate the &quot;Zn-like&quot; impurities in the <lb/>nominally pure sample. Again, the penetration depth <lb/>of similar samples give a scattering parameter Γ/T c of <lb/>about 0.0008 which corresponds to an impurity concen-<lb/>tration of 0.013% and a residual density of states ratio of <lb/>0.03, which implies a contribution of ∼0.6 mJ/mol-K 2 to <lb/>the zero-field linear term. The residual ∼2.4 mJ/mol-K 2 <lb/>most probably come from the unfilled chains as was found <lb/>by measuring the high oxygen content crystals [15]. Us-<lb/>ing the above data figure 3 shows the change of the zero <lb/>field linear term from the Zn-free sample ( ∆γ(0) ) as <lb/>a function of the Zn concentration. For comparison we <lb/>also show in figure 3 the expected ∆γ(0) expected from <lb/>&quot;dirty d-wave&quot; theory [17]. While as for the penetration <lb/>depth data, the low Zn concentration fits the &quot;dirty d-<lb/>wave&quot; theory reasonably well, stronger deviation appears <lb/>for the 1% sample indicating a more linear dependence <lb/>on the Zn concentration. Table I summarizes the results <lb/>presented above. <lb/>For pure samples, the field dependent coefficient of the <lb/>linear-T term obeys γ(H) = γ(0) +γ(H). Whileγ ∝ <lb/>H 1/2 for pure samples, Zn doping alters this behavior and <lb/>the 1% Zn sample showedγ ∝ H as is shown in figure 4. <lb/>This suppression of the H 1/2 term was expected because <lb/>of increased scattering. In Volovik&apos;s work [21], the H 1/2 <lb/>magnetic field dependence of the density of states results <lb/>from the use of the intervortex spacing as a cutoff to the <lb/>spatial integral over the density of states in the vortex. <lb/>For the large Zn concentration such as our 1% sample we <lb/>expect a much shorter cutoff length. In the unitary limit <lb/>the scattering rate at low frequencies (and temperatures) <lb/>saturates at a value ℓ ∼ v F n res /2Γ [17]. Using our results <lb/>for Γ we find that this length is of order 100Å, thus <lb/>explaining the linear field dependence. <lb/>Finally we turn to the search of the Zn induced mag-<lb/>netic moments. As noted in the introduction the Zn-<lb/>induced impurities are expected to be observed in finite <lb/>magnetic field specific heat measurements. For a two-<lb/>level system this is a Schottky-like anomaly given by: <lb/>c Sch (T, H) = ν Sch R <lb/>∆ <lb/>k B T <lb/>2 <lb/>e <lb/>∆ <lb/>k B T <lb/>1 + e <lb/>∆ <lb/>k B T <lb/>2 <lb/>(2) <lb/>where ∆ is the size of the two-level system gap. Clearly a <lb/>true two level system exists for spin 1/2 impurities only. <lb/>In the case of Zn impurities we expect an effective mo-<lb/>ment of order one Bohr-magneton [5], hence, a simplified <lb/>two-level system with a moment µ and a gap ∆ = 2µH <lb/>should be a good approximation for the expected efect <lb/>on the specific heat. Also in equation 2, ν Sch is the mo-<lb/>lar concentration of moments and R is the gas constant. <lb/>Impurity moments are always found in specific heat mea-<lb/>surements of high-T c materials even for &quot;pure&quot; crystals. <lb/>For optimally doped YBCO a concentration of about <lb/>0.05% -0.1% per copper atom is found [15]. For higher <lb/>oxygen concentration this number is smaller providing us <lb/>with evidence that most of these moments come from un-<lb/>compensated copper atoms in the chains. As mentioned <lb/>above, it has been argued that Zn impurities induce mo-<lb/>ments that for the concentration range and oxygen level <lb/>of our samples is expected to be µ = 0.32µ B to 0.36µ B <lb/>[6]. Thus, it is easy to calculate the expected Schottky <lb/>anomaly associated with the Zn moments; in particular <lb/>we expect that since the Zn moments originate from the <lb/>Cu-O planes and the &quot;unaccounted&quot; spin-1/2 moments <lb/>come from the chains the Zn contribution will simply <lb/>be an addition to the pure crystal heat capacity. With <lb/>the above introduction, the most surprising result is that <lb/>we did not find any change in the Schottky anomaly for <lb/>any of the Zn doping all the way to 8 Tesla, the maxi-<lb/>mum field we measured. This result can most dramat-<lb/>ically be seen in figure 5 where the specific heat data <lb/>at 8 Tesla is plotted together with the calculated Schot-<lb/>tky anomaly expected for 1% Zn with magnetic moment <lb/>per Zn of µ = 0.32µ B (the smaller expected contribu-<lb/>tion). Also plotted in figure 5 is a Schottky anomaly with <lb/>µ = 1.28µ B , displaying the possibility of a &quot;composite&quot; <lb/>moment that results from local ferromagnetic interaction <lb/>of moments on four neighboring oxygen atoms [5]. If a <lb/>significant amount of either 0.32µ B or 1.28µ B moments <lb/>were present, it would be readily apparent in the size of <lb/>the Schottky anomaly, which is unchanged from undoped <lb/>samples. Fitting with a Schottky term with 1.28µ B mo-<lb/>ments in addition to the 1µ B -spin-1/2 anomaly finds no <lb/>more than 0.02% additional spins per Cu and is con-<lb/>sistent with no 1.28µ B moments at all. At 0.32µ B per <lb/>moment, the presence of 1% spins per Cu would create a <lb/>Schottky tail which wouldn&apos;t roll over at even the high-<lb/>est fields and lowest temperatures measured. However, <lb/>this upturn would increase proportionally to the square <lb/>of the applied field, being 16 times larger at 8 Tesla than <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

		<body>at 2 Tesla. Assuming that all of the low temperature up-<lb/>turn in the 8 Tesla data is from a small-moment Schottky <lb/>anomaly, we obtain an upper limit of 0.03% spins per Cu, <lb/>for 0.32µ B moment spins. Figure 5 highlights this dis-<lb/>crepancy, showing that even with different fitting meth-<lb/>ods, there are few, if any, of the Zn impurities creating <lb/>free magnetic moments in the crystal. <lb/>The absence of Zn-induced magnetic moments in the <lb/>superconducting state may be explained in two ways. <lb/>The first is that the moments exist only in a local sense <lb/>and thus will be found in local measurements such as <lb/>Knight shift but will be missed in bulk measurements <lb/>such as the present specific heat due to the &quot;spread&quot; <lb/>of the moment throughout the whole sample [11]. To <lb/>check for this hypothesis we measured the susceptibility <lb/>of the 1%-Zn doped sample. A weak Curie behavior was <lb/>found which is of similar magnitude to that measured by <lb/>Zagoulaev et al. [5] implying a similar size of magnetic <lb/>moment per Zn impurity. The fact that the Zn-moments <lb/>exist in the normal state may be explained by the fact <lb/>that we have been measuring a doped Heisenberg antifer-<lb/>romagnet which is close to optimal doping, and for which <lb/>the spin gap has not collapsed yet. <lb/>The second possibility for the &quot;disappearance&quot; of the <lb/>moments is that they are screened in a Kondo fashion. <lb/>Such a possibility was recently considered by Nagaosa <lb/>and Lee [12] and by Cassanello and Fradkin [14]. Rele-<lb/>vant to our measurements is the Cassanello and Fradkin <lb/>work in which they postulated that magnetic impurities <lb/>in a clean d-wave superconductor will be screened, and <lb/>show that the screening can be described as a multichan-<lb/>nel non-marginal Kondo problem. For simplicity they as-<lb/>sume spin-1/2 impurities that are located on the Cu sites <lb/>in the planes. Using expected values of the exchange cou-<lb/>pling, they find a critical temperature T K ∼ 10 K, below <lb/>which the impurities will be overscreened. Their calcu-<lb/>lation of the low-temperature specific heat yielded the <lb/>expressions: <lb/>c(T, H) = 9ζ(3)ν i RN c δ 2 T <lb/>T K <lb/>2 <lb/>ln <lb/>∆ 0 <lb/>k B T <lb/>f ork B T &gt; µH <lb/>c(T, H) = <lb/>π 2 <lb/>3 <lb/>ν i RN c δ 2 T <lb/>T K <lb/>µ B H <lb/>k B T K <lb/>ln <lb/>∆ 0 <lb/>µ B H <lb/>(3) <lb/>f ork B T &lt; µH <lb/>Here ν i is the impurity concentration per mole, R is the <lb/>universal gas constant, ζ(3) is the Rieman zeta function <lb/>of argument 3, N c is the rank of the symmetry group of <lb/>the impurity spin, taken to be 2 in the relevant case (see <lb/>[14] for details), δ is a dimensionless parameter related <lb/>to the strength of the screening ( the singlet amplitude), <lb/>∆ 0 is the maximum gap of the d x 2 <lb/>−y 2 superconductor, <lb/>and T K is the Kondo temperature associated with the <lb/>impurities. Before presenting our fit to the Cassanello <lb/>and Fradkin&apos;s calculation we note that the calculation <lb/>are based on a very simple model that assumes that the <lb/>quasiparticles that screen the moments come from the <lb/>nodes only. However, Zn impurities cause the depression <lb/>of the order parameter close to the impurity site due to <lb/>potential scattering (i.e. pair breaking). This effect is the <lb/>main cause of the depression of T c , and was not included <lb/>in the calculations. However, all the effects related to <lb/>Zn scattering are local in nature and thus should reduce <lb/>to a generalized Andreev boundary condition (general-<lb/>ized because of the different symmetries that may be in-<lb/>volved, including inter-node scattering and so on). It is <lb/>very unlikely that these effects will help in the Kondo <lb/>screening since these potentials are invariant under spin <lb/>rotations [22]. With the above discussion in mind we <lb/>fitted our Zn-doped specific heat data with the screen-<lb/>ing model, i.e. equations 3. Since the model provides us <lb/>with the limiting cases only for temperature and fields we <lb/>first fit the high field, assuming that all the field depen-<lb/>dence comes from the screening. We then introduce an <lb/>interpolation function that is exponential in nature which <lb/>connects the low and high magnetic fields. We show the <lb/>results of the fit in figure 6 while the fitting parameters <lb/>are shown in TABLE II. Again, compared with Zn-free <lb/>sample the Schottky anomaly does not change, the T 3 <lb/>contribution is smaller and a small low temperature up-<lb/>turn is observed. For the 1%Zn we find (δ/T K )= 0.0082, <lb/>a value within the range discussed in [14]. For that sam-<lb/>ple we also find that the quality of the fit degrades at <lb/>high fields, possibly due to the model becoming invalid <lb/>with the relatively large DOS at the nodes and its si-<lb/>multaneous smearing by the Zn doping and the magnetic <lb/>field. For the 0.31%Zn the value (δ/T K )= 0.003 seems <lb/>somewhat low as we expected to first approximation that <lb/>the two values will be the same. <lb/>In conclusion, we presented in this paper a comprehen-<lb/>sive study of the low temperature heat capacity of Zn-<lb/>doped YBCO single crystals. Several trends have been <lb/>found as a function of Zn doping. The T 3 term decreases <lb/>with increasing Zn while the liner term increasing, in-<lb/>dicating an increasing DOS at the nodes. This residual <lb/>density of states is only qualitatively consistent with a <lb/>d-wave resonant scattering theory. The 1%Zn clearly de-<lb/>viates from the theoretical expectation, showing excess <lb/>DOS. A low temperature upturn is consistently observed <lb/>for the Zn-doped samples, similar to early measurements <lb/>on more disordered YBCO samples. The cause and exact <lb/>form of this upturn is still not clear. The most surprising <lb/>result of our study tough is that no Schottky anomaly <lb/>is observed for the presumed magnetic moments created <lb/>by Zn doping. Based on a recent theory by Cassanello <lb/>and Fradkin we fitted the data with Kondo screened mo-<lb/>ments. The relatively good quality of the fit and the rea-<lb/>sonable parameters extracted from it give us confidence <lb/>that indeed Zn-moments in YBCO crystals are screened <lb/>by quasiparticles in the nodes of the d x 2 <lb/>−y 2 superconduc-<lb/>tor. <lb/></body>

		<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgments: Work at Stanford University was <lb/>supported by Air Force Office of scientific Research. <lb/>S.G.D. was supported by a Feodor-Lynen-Fellowship of <lb/></div>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<div type="acknowledgment">the Alexander von Humboldt-Stiftung. The authors wish <lb/>to thank Kathryn Moler for her valuable contributions <lb/>at the initial stages of this work. we also wish to thank <lb/>Doug Scalapino and Eduardo Fradkin for many useful <lb/>discussions. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] G. Xiao et al., Nature (London) 332, 238 (1988); H. <lb/>Maeda et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 157C, 483 (1989). <lb/>[2] P. Mendels, H. Alloul, J. H. Brewer, G. D. Morris, <lb/>T. L. Duty, S. Johnston, E. J. Ansaldo, G. Collin, J. <lb/>F. Marucco, C. Niedermayer, d. R. Noakes, and C. E. <lb/>Stronach, Phys. Rev. B 49, 10035 (1994). <lb/>[3] P. Mendels, H. Alloul, G. Collin, N. Blanchard, J. F. <lb/>Maracco, J. Bobroff, Physica C 235-40, 1595 (1994). <lb/>[4] D. A. Bonn, S. Kamal, K. Zhang, R. Liang, D. J. Baar, <lb/>E. Klein, and W. A. Hardy, Phys. Rev. B 50, 4051 (1994). <lb/>[5] S. Zagoulaev, P Monod, and J. Jegoudez, Phys. Rev. B <lb/>52, 10474 (1995). <lb/>[6] V.A. Mahajan, H. Alloul, G. Collin, and J.F. Marucco, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 72, 3100 (1994). <lb/>[7] M. Gabay, Physics C 235-240, 1337 (1994). <lb/>[8] K. Ishida, Y. Kitaoka, N. Ogata, T. Kamino, K. <lb/>Asayama, J.R. Cooper, and N. Athanassopoulou, J. <lb/>Phys. Soc. Jpn. 62, 2803 (1993). <lb/>[9] J.W. Loram, K.A. Mirza, and P.F. Freeman, Physica <lb/>C171, 243 (1990). <lb/>[10] N. Nagaosa and T.-K. Ng, Phys. Rev. B43, 5950 (1991). <lb/>[11] A.W. Sandvik, E. Dagotto, and D.J. Scalapino, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B56, 11701 (1997). <lb/>[12] N. Nagaosa, P. A. Lee, Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 3755 (1997). <lb/>[13] A. Abrikosov and L. P. Gorkov, Sov. Phys. JETP 12, <lb/>1243 (1961). <lb/>[14] C. R. Cassanello and E. Fradkin, Phys. Rev. B 56, 11246 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>[15] K. A. Moler, D. J. Baar, J. S. Urbach, R.Liang, W. N. <lb/>Hardy, A. Kapitulnik, Phys. Rev. Lett. 73, 2744 (1994); <lb/>K. A. Moler, D. L. Sisson, J. S. Urbach, M.R. Beasley, A. <lb/>Kapitulnik, D.J. Baar, R.Liang, and W. N. Hardy, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 55, 3954 (1997). <lb/>[16] P. J. Hirschfeld, N. Goldenfeld, Phys. Rev. B 48, 4219 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[17] P. J. Hirschfeld, W. O. Putikka, D. J. Scalapino, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 50, 10250 (1994). <lb/>[18] J.S. Urbach, D.B. Mitzi, A. Kapitulnik, J.Y.T. Wei, D.E. <lb/>Morris, Phys. Rev. B 39, 12391 (1989). <lb/>[19] S. G. Doettinger, M. Uhl, D. L. Sisson, A. Kapitulnik, <lb/>submitted to Review of Scientific Instruments. <lb/>[20] J.P. Emerson, R.A. Fisher, N.E. Phillips, D.A. Wright, <lb/>E.M. McCarron, Phys. Rev. B 49, 9256 (1994). <lb/>[21] G. E. Volovik, JETP Lett. 58, 469 (1993). <lb/>[22] E. Fradkin, Private communication. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>FIG. 1. The effect of Zn doping on the zero-field spe-<lb/>cific heat of YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6.95 . <lb/>FIG. 2. The temperature dependence of the specific <lb/>heat (plotted as c(T)/T of 1% Zn doped YBCO, cooled <lb/>in applied fields from 0 to 8 Tesla. <lb/>FIG. 3. The zero-field γ term as a function of Zn dop-<lb/>ing. Line that connects the points is guide to the eye, <lb/>emphasizing the sub-linear trend of the data. <lb/>FIG. 4. The field dependence of the coefficient of the <lb/>linear-T term, γ(H), as determined from the global fits <lb/>described in the text. Note, a T 2 term was allowed for <lb/>the nominally pure sample. Connecting lines are only <lb/>guide to the eye. <lb/>FIG. 5. The Schottky effect observed in the 1%Zn-<lb/>doped sample together with an expected Schottky effect <lb/>associated with 1% moments of size: 0.32 µ B (dashed <lb/>line) or 1.28 µ B (dash-dotted line), see text. solid line <lb/>through the 8 T data is the fit as presented in figure 6. <lb/>Solid circles are the zero-field data. <lb/>FIG. 6. Fit of the screening approximation [14] to the <lb/>1% Zn doped sample. The fit assumes that all the field <lb/>dependence in that limit comes from the screening. <lb/>TABLE I. Parameters for fit with equation 1 (no screening <lb/>term). <lb/>Zn Tc <lb/>β <lb/>ν Sch R <lb/>A(0) <lb/>γ(0) <lb/>% [K] [mJ/mol-K 4 ] [mJ/mol-K] [mJ/mol] [mJ/mol-K 2 ] <lb/>0.0 93 0.392±0.001 <lb/>24±1 <lb/>no term <lb/>3.0±0.1 <lb/>0.15 90 0.308±0.003 <lb/>20±2 <lb/>7±1 <lb/>4.3±0.1 <lb/>0.31 88 0.284±0.003 <lb/>25±2 <lb/>16±2 <lb/>5.8±0.2 <lb/>1.0 81 0.274±0.003 <lb/>24±2 <lb/>3±1 <lb/>11.7±0.2 <lb/>TABLE II. Parameters for fit with equation 3 (including <lb/>screening term). <lb/>Zn <lb/>β <lb/>ν Sch R <lb/>γ(0) <lb/>δ/TK <lb/>% [mJ/mol-K 4 ] [mJ/mol-K] [mJ/mol-K 2 ] <lb/>[K −1 ] <lb/>0.31 0.284±0.003 <lb/>25±2 <lb/>5.8±0.2 <lb/>0.003±0.002 <lb/>1.0 0.274±0.003 <lb/>24±2 <lb/>11.7±0.1 0.0082±0.0004 <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>0% Zn <lb/>0.15% Zn <lb/>0.31% Zn <lb/>1% Zn <lb/>T 2 (K 2 ) <lb/>c/T (mJ/mol-K 2 <lb/>) <lb/>Figure 1 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>8 T <lb/>6 T <lb/>4 T <lb/>2 T <lb/>0.5 T <lb/>0 T <lb/>c/T (mJ/molK 2 <lb/>) <lb/>T 2 (K 2 ) <lb/>Figure 2 <lb/>-2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>∆γ(0) (mJ/molK 2 <lb/>) <lb/>% of Zn <lb/>Figure 3 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>nominally pure <lb/>0.15% Zn <lb/>0.31% Zn <lb/>1% Zn <lb/>γ(H) (mJ/molK 2 <lb/>) <lb/>H (Tesla) <lb/>Figure 4 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>60 <lb/>70 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>(c-βT 3 <lb/>)/T (mJ/molK 2 <lb/>) <lb/>T 2 (K 2 ) <lb/>Specific heat with expected <lb/>Schottky at 8 T ( <lb/>) <lb/>µ=1.28µ Β <lb/>Actual Data at 8 T <lb/>Figure 5 <lb/>Specific heat with expected <lb/>Schottky at 8 T ( <lb/>) <lb/>µ=0.32µ Β <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>14 <lb/>16 <lb/>18 <lb/>20 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>8 T <lb/>6 T <lb/>4 T <lb/>2 T <lb/>0.5 T <lb/>0 T <lb/>(c-βT 3 <lb/>)/T (mJ/molK 2 <lb/>) <lb/>T 2 (K 2 ) <lb/>Figure 6 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
