<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/9903117v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 6 Mar 1999 <lb/>Effects of carrier concentration on the superfluid density of high-T c cuprates <lb/>C. Panagopoulos 1 , B.D. Rainford 2 , J.R. Cooper 1 , W. Lo 1 , J.L. Tallon 3 , J.W. Loram 1 , J. Betouras 4 , Y.S. Wang 5 and <lb/>C.W. Chu 5 <lb/>1 IRC in Superconductivity, University of Cambridge, Cambridge CB3 0HE, United Kingdom <lb/>2 Department of Physics and Astronomy, University of Southampton, Southampton SO17 1BJ, United Kingdom <lb/>3 New Zealand Institute for Industrial Research, P.O. Box 31310, Lower Hutt, New Zealand <lb/>4 Department of Physics, Theoretical Physics, University of Oxford, Oxford, OX1 3NP, United Kingdom <lb/>5 Department of Physics and Texas Centre for Superconductivity at the University of Houston, Houston, Texas 77204-5932 <lb/>(today) <lb/>The absolute values and temperature, T, dependence of the in-plane magnetic penetration depth, <lb/>λ ab , of La2−xSrxCuO4 and HgBa2CuO 4+δ have been measured as a function of carrier concentration. <lb/>We find that the superfluid density, ρs, changes substantially and systematically with doping. The <lb/>values of ρs(0) are closely linked to the available low energy spectral weight as determined by the <lb/>electronic entropy just above Tc and the initial slope of ρs(T )/ρs(0) increases rapidly with carrier <lb/>concentration. The results are discussed in the context of a possible relationship between ρs and <lb/>the normal-state (or pseudo) energy gap. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25.Nf, 74.62. Dh, 74.72.Dn, 74.72.Gr <lb/></front>

			<body>Superconductivity arises from the binding of electrons <lb/>into Cooper pairs thereby forming a superfluid with a <lb/>superconducting energy gap, ∆, in the single-particle ex-<lb/>citation spectrum. In high-temperature superconductors <lb/>(HTS) ∆ has essentially d x 2 <lb/>−y 2 symmetry in k-space with <lb/>∆ k = ∆ 0 cos(2φ) [1], where φ = arctan(k y /k x ) and ∆ 0 <lb/>is the superconducting gap amplitude which will in gen-<lb/>eral be φ dependent. Changes in carrier concentration <lb/>affect the superconducting [2-8] and normal state (NS) <lb/>[4-7] properties of HTS and there is evidence [3-7] that <lb/>in addition to ∆ k there is a normal state (or pseudo) gap, <lb/>∆ N , in the NS energy excitation spectrum in under-and <lb/>optimally doped samples which increases with decreasing <lb/>doping. The maximum gap amplitude shows little vari-<lb/>ation with underdoping even though T c is reduced [3-8], <lb/>in disagreement with the standard mean-field Bardeen-<lb/>Cooper-Schrieffer (BCS) theory. This unusual behaviour <lb/>is probably linked to the presence of ∆ N [7]. However, <lb/>fundamental problems such as the origin of ∆ N and its <lb/>possible effect on the superfluid density, ρ s , have not been <lb/>clearly resolved experimentally or theoretically. <lb/>The physical quantity most directly associated with <lb/>ρ s is the magnetic penetration depth λ. Appropriate <lb/>systems to investigate ρ s as a function of doping are <lb/>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 and HgBa 2 CuO 4+δ . Both have a sim-<lb/>ple crystal structure with one CuO 2 plane per unit cell, <lb/>can have their carrier concentration controlled, and there <lb/>is experimental evidence suggesting the presence of ∆ N <lb/>which closes with doping [3-5,9]. Here we report in-plane <lb/>penetration depth, λ ab , measurements for high-quality <lb/>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 (LSCO) with x = 0.10, 0.15, 0.20, 0.22, <lb/>0.24 measured by the ac-susceptibility (acs) and muon <lb/>spin relaxation (µSR) techniques and for HgBa 2 CuO 4+δ <lb/>(Hg-1201) with δ = 0.10, 0.37 measured only by µSR. We <lb/>find systematic changes in ρ s with carrier concentration <lb/>and a correlation with ∆ N . <lb/>Single-phase polycrystalline samples of LSCO were <lb/>prepared in Cambridge using solid-state reaction proce-<lb/>dures. No other phases were detected by powder x-ray <lb/>diffraction and the phase purity is thought to be bet-<lb/>ter than 1%. Lattice parameters were in good agreement <lb/>with published work [10]. High field magnetic susceptibil-<lb/>ity measurements showed no signatures of excess param-<lb/>agnetic centres. The measured T c &apos;s are 30, 37.7, 36, 27.5 <lb/>and 20.3 K for x = 0.10, 0.15, 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24, re-<lb/>spectively. These values are also in very good agreement <lb/>with previous measurements [10]. µSR experiments as a <lb/>function of T were performed on the same powders for <lb/>x = 0.10 and 0.15. Although unoriented powders can be <lb/>used to determine λ ab by µSR [2], the acs technique re-<lb/>quires the powders to be magnetically aligned [11]. To <lb/>eliminate grain agglomerates, powders were ball-milled <lb/>in ethanol and dried after adding a defloculant. Scan-<lb/>ning electron microscopy confirmed the absence of grain <lb/>boundaries and showed that the average grain diameter <lb/>was ∼ 5µm. The powders were mixed with a 5 min curing <lb/>epoxy and aligned in a static field of 12T at room tem-<lb/>perature. Debye-Scherrer x-ray scans showed that ∼ 90% <lb/>of the grains were aligned within ∼ 2.0 o . Low-field sus-<lb/>ceptibility measurements were performed at an ac-field <lb/>H ac = 1 G rms (parallel to the c-axis) and a frequency <lb/>f = 333 Hz down to 1.2K. Details of the application of <lb/>London&apos;s model for deriving λ from the measured sus-<lb/>ceptibility can be found in an earlier publication [11]. <lb/>Transverse-field-cooled µSR experiments were performed <lb/>at 400 Gauss in the ISIS, Rutherford-Appleton Labora-<lb/>tory. The field produced a flux-line lattice whose field <lb/>distribution was probed by muons. The depolarisation <lb/>rate, σ(T ), of the initial muon spin is proportional to <lb/>λ ab <lb/>−2 (T ) [2,12]. Checks were made to ensure that the <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>values of λ ab obtained were independent of the applied <lb/>field. The Hg-1201 [δ = 0.10 (T c = 60K) and 0.37 (T c <lb/>= 35K)] samples were prepared in Houston by the con-<lb/>trolled solid-vapour reaction technique [13]. <lb/>The values of λ ab (0) derived from the acs data for <lb/>LSCO are 0.28, 0.26, 0.197, 0.193, 0.194 µm for x = <lb/>p = 0.10, 0.15, 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24, respectively. Here <lb/>p is the hole content per planar copper atom. The esti-<lb/>mated error for λ ab (0) obtained by the acs technique is <lb/>±15% and within this uncertainty the λ ab (0) values agree <lb/>with the µSR measurements. We thus find that λ −2 <lb/>ab (0) <lb/>is strongly suppressed on the underdoped side, including <lb/>optimal doping, but there is no suppression with increas-<lb/>ing overdoping (up to p = 0.24) in contrast to reports <lb/>for Tl 2 Ba 2 CuO 6+δ [14]. Values of λ ab (0) as obtained by <lb/>µSR for Hg-1201 are 0.194 and 0.148 µm for δ = 0.10 <lb/>and 0.37, respectively. We note that δ = 0.10 and 0.37 in <lb/>Hg-1201 correspond to p = 0.075 and 0.22, respectively <lb/>[15]. <lb/>The T-dependence of λ ab for LSCO is shown in Fig. <lb/>1(a) as a plot of [1/λ ab (T )] 2 ∝ ρ s (T ). Data for x = 0.10 <lb/>and 0.15 obtained by µSR are also included for compari-<lb/>son. Overall there is good agreement between the results <lb/>from the two techniques. From the acs data we find that <lb/>the initial linear term in λ ab (T ), characteristic of a clean <lb/>d-wave superconductor, persists up to the highest doping <lb/>measured (x = 0.24) in agreement with electronic specific <lb/>heat studies on polycrystalline LSCO samples from the <lb/>same batch as those studied here [16]. Figure 1(b) de-<lb/>picts data for Hg-1201 powders measured only by µSR, <lb/>including data from Ref. [17] for a Hg-1201 sample (also <lb/>from Houston) with δ = 0.154 (p = 0.17). As in LSCO, <lb/>we observe a change in the shape of σ(T ) ∝ [1/λ ab (T )] 2 of <lb/>Hg-1201 with doping. Namely, in the underdoped region <lb/>[1/λ ab (T )] 2 shows a more pronounced curvature. Taking <lb/>the slope of the low-T linear term to be proportional to <lb/>ρ s (0)/∆ 0 the observed trend of [1/λ ab (T )] 2 with p would <lb/>imply that ∆ 0 remains approximately constant in the un-<lb/>derdoped region and decreases rapidly with overdoping. <lb/>Figure 2 shows a comparison of the present results for <lb/>LSCO with specific heat data taken on the same samples <lb/>[16] where ∆ N was observed for x = p &lt; 0.19. In the <lb/>inset we observe a good correlation between [1/λ ab (0)] 2 <lb/>and [S/T(T c ) -S/T(2K)] both plotted versus Sr con-<lb/>tent x, where S(T) is the electronic entropy obtained by <lb/>integrating the electronic specific heat coefficient γ(T) <lb/>from 0 to T. The quantity [S/T(T c ) -S/T(2K)] is a <lb/>measure of the energy-dependent NS electronic density of <lb/>states (DOS), g n (E), averaged over ±2k B T c around the <lb/>Fermi energy E F . The effect of an energy -dependent <lb/>DOS on the London penetration depth λ L or ρ s (0) is <lb/>not usually considered in standard theory which implic-<lb/>itly assumes a constant DOS and a parabolic E( k) dis-<lb/>persion relation. It has been argued elsewhere [5] that <lb/>ρ s (0) = 4π 2 v x <lb/>2 g n (E) /e 2 where the average is over an <lb/>(anisotropic) energy shell E F ± ∆ 0 . Note that this result <lb/>agrees with the standard expression for the NS conduc-<lb/>tivity and the usual relation between λ L (0) and the real <lb/>part of the frequency-dependent electronic conductivity <lb/>in the normal and superconducting states σ 1 <lb/>n (ω) and <lb/>σ s <lb/>1 (ω), respectively. Namely, λ L (0) is determined by the <lb/>area under the [σ 1 <lb/>n (ω) − σ 1 <lb/>s (ω)] curve in the frequency <lb/>range 0 &lt; hω/2π &lt; 2∆ 0 . Thus the inset to Fig. 2 sug-<lb/>gests that the strong decrease of ρ s (0) with x from x <lb/>= 0.20 to 0.10 is related to the suppression of spectral <lb/>weight with energy range E F ± ∆ 0 due to the presence <lb/>of ∆ N . <lb/>The main panel in Fig. 2 shows a correlation be-<lb/>tween the doping dependence of the initial linear terms <lb/>of λ ab (T ) and the low-T specific heat coefficient γ, both <lb/>quantities being related to the number of excited quasi-<lb/>particles n e (T). For low values of x, n e (T=10) is much <lb/>smaller than expected from the T c value and this proba-<lb/>bly implies that the average value of ∆ 0 (φ) is significantly <lb/>larger than T c . The rapid rise above x = 0.20 may arise <lb/>from the combined effects of the closure of ∆ N at x = <lb/>0.19 [4,16], the decreasing T c plus the fact that for LSCO <lb/>there is significant pile up of states near E F in the over-<lb/>doped region 0.20 &lt; x &lt; 0.35 [16]. <lb/>In Fig. 3(a) we present the LSCO acs data as <lb/>[λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 versus T/T c and compare the data with <lb/>the mean-field calculation for a d-wave weak-coupled <lb/>BCS superconductor with a cylindrical Fermi surface <lb/>(FS) which gives ∆ 0 /T c ∼ 2.14 [18]. There appears to <lb/>be a systematic deviation of the data from the weak-<lb/>coupling T-dependence with a greater (weaker) curvature <lb/>on the underdoped (overdoped) side. We note however, <lb/>that particularly in the overdoped samples there is pos-<lb/>itive curvature near T c which may arise from a small <lb/>amount of doping inhomogeneity giving a distribution of <lb/>T c values in this region where dT c /dp is maximal [10]. <lb/>The effect of this is to rescale the curves with a slightly <lb/>lower value of T c . We have modelled ρ s (T ) using the <lb/>d-wave T-dependence and a normal distribution of T c <lb/>values with standard deviation of 3%, 5% and 9% for x <lb/>= 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24, respectively. These corrections, <lb/>plotted in Fig. 3(b), bring the curves for x = 0.20 and <lb/>0.22 into good agreement with weak-coupling BCS with <lb/>∆ 0 /T c ∼ 2.14. Similar deductions, as to the magnitude <lb/>and p-dependence of ∆ 0 /T c , were made in the specific <lb/>heat studies on these overdoped samples [16]. However, <lb/>the x = 0.24 sample still shows significant deviations that <lb/>possibly reflect changes in the electronic structure. This <lb/>would not be surprising given the changes in the FS with <lb/>the rapid crossover from hole-like to electron-like states <lb/>near x = 0.27 [19]. We note that the data for x = 0.24 <lb/>is in excellent agreement with a weak-coupling d-wave <lb/>calculation for a rectangular FS [20]. <lb/>In contrast to the overdoped samples the optimal and <lb/>underdoped samples [Fig. 3(a)], both possessing very <lb/>small rounding near T c , diverge significantly from the <lb/>weak-coupling curve and in the opposite direction. We <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>note that accounting for inhomogeneities in these sam-<lb/>ples will, if anything, move the curves even further from <lb/>the weak-coupling BCS fit. <lb/>A central conclusion of the present work is that there <lb/>is a crossover in both ρ s (0) and ρ s (T ) near p = 0.20. <lb/>Such behaviour is characteristic of many other NS and <lb/>superconducting properties which have been interpreted <lb/>in terms of the presence of ∆ N in the underdoped region. <lb/>The rate of depression of T c due to impurity scattering <lb/>(∝ 1/γ at T c ) remains constant across the overdoped <lb/>region then rises sharply with the opening of ∆ N , be-<lb/>ginning in the lightly overdoped region at p ∼ 0.19 [21]. <lb/>Boebinger and coworkers [22] using intense pulsed mag-<lb/>netic fields observe a crossover from insulating to metallic <lb/>behaviour at T = 0 occurring near p = 0.18 and angle-<lb/>resolved photoemission studies show the development, in <lb/>the overdoped region, of a full NS Fermi surface [23]. In <lb/>this region the resistivity coefficient, [ρ(T ) − ρ(0)]/T , ex-<lb/>hibits a low-T suppression due to the opening of ∆ N [24]. <lb/>These considerations provide a compelling motivation for <lb/>interpreting our penetration depth data within a similar <lb/>scenario. <lb/>The proper means of incorporating the pseudogap ef-<lb/>fects within a realistic model, and indeed the very nature <lb/>of the pseudogap is a matter of current debate. How-<lb/>ever, a key characteristic of ∆ N is the loss of NS spectral <lb/>weight near E F . The loss of spectral weight can cause, as <lb/>discussed above, both a strong reduction in ρ s (0) and, in <lb/>a simple model, enhanced curvature in ρ s (T )/ρ s (0) above <lb/>the BCS weak-coupling d-wave T-dependence [25], the <lb/>very features we observe for the optimal and underdoped <lb/>samples. <lb/>We note that our data are in reasonable agreement <lb/>with earlier reports for slightly underdoped grain-aligned <lb/>HgBa 2 Ca 2 Cu 3 O 8+δ [11,26] and single crystal LSCO with <lb/>x = 0.15 [27]. In contrast to the strong p dependence we <lb/>have found in [λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 for LSCO and Hg-1201, <lb/>studies in YBCO [28,29] reported that [λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 <lb/>scaled approximately with 1/T c for various dopings, <lb/>at all temperatures. However, systematic changes in <lb/>[λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 with p were noted at the time [29] al-<lb/>though these were too small to allow further analysis. <lb/>This may simply be due to the fact that the YBCO sam-<lb/>ples were not as heavily underdoped as the x = 0.10 <lb/>LSCO sample. We also note that YBCO is complicated <lb/>by a mixed s+d order parameter [1,30] and the effect of <lb/>the Cu-O chains on the total ρ s [31,32]. <lb/>In summary, using the acs and µSR techniques we have <lb/>obtained consistent and systematic results on the effects <lb/>of carrier concentration on ρ s of monolayer cuprates. In <lb/>the overdoped region we find a more or less constant value <lb/>of ρ s (0) (up to p = 0.24), and ρ s (T )/ρ s (0) is in rea-<lb/>sonably good agreement with the weak-coupling d-wave <lb/>T-dependence. In the optimal and underdoped regions <lb/>ρ s (0) is rapidly suppressed and above 0.1T c there is a <lb/>marked departure of ρ s (T )/ρ s (0) from the weak-coupling <lb/>curve. In a comparative study with available specific <lb/>heat data we found evidence supporting a link in the be-<lb/>haviour of ρ s and the normal state gap ∆ N . <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We thank P.A. Lee, P.B. Littlewood, T. Xiang and <lb/>J.F. Annett for stimulating discussions; J. Chrosch for <lb/>assistance with part of the x-ray analysis of the grain-<lb/>aligned samples, and P. King and C. Scott (ISIS) for <lb/>technical support during the µSR measurements. C.P. <lb/>thanks Trinity College, Cambridge for financial support <lb/>and J.B. the European Union for a Marie Curie grant. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] C.C. Tsuei and J.R. Kirtley, Physica (Amsterdam) <lb/>282C-287C, 4 (1997). <lb/>[2] Y.J. Uemura et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 62, 2317 (1989); C. <lb/>Bernhard et al., Phys. Rev. B 52, 10 488 (1995). <lb/>[3] T. Nakano et al., J. Phys. Soc. Jpn. 67, 2622 (1998). <lb/>[4] J.R. Cooper and J.W. Loram, J. Phys. I 6, 2237 (1996). <lb/>[5] J.W. Loram, K.A. Mirza and J.R. Cooper, in &quot;High Tem-<lb/>perature Superconductivity&quot;, Research Review (Editor: <lb/>W.Y. Liang, University of Cambridge 1998). <lb/>[6] B. Batlogg et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 235-240C, 130 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>[7] J.W. Loram et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 235-240C, 134 <lb/>(1994) <lb/>[8] C. Panagopoulos and T. Xiang, Phys. Rev. Lett. 81, 2336 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[9] J. Bobroff et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, 3757 (1997). <lb/>[10] P.G. Radaelli et al., Phys. Rev. B 49, 4163 (1994). <lb/>[11] C. Panagopoulos et al., Phys. Rev. B 53, R2 999 (1996) <lb/>and references therein. <lb/>[12] W. Barford and J.M.F. Gunn, Physica (Amsterdam) <lb/>156C, 515 (1988). <lb/>[13] R.L. Meng et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 216C, 21 (1993). <lb/>[14] Ch. Niedermayer et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 71, 1764 (1993). <lb/>[15] Q. Xiong et al., Phys. Rev. B 50, 10 346 (1994). <lb/>[16] J.W. Loram et al., 10th Ann HTS Workshop (World Sci-<lb/>entific, Singapore 1996) p. 341. <lb/>[17] B. Nachumi et al., Hyperfine Interactions 105, 119 <lb/>(1997). <lb/>[18] P.J. Hirschfeld and N. Goldenfeld, Phys. Rev. B 48, 4219 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[19] A. Ino et. al., cond-mat/9809311. <lb/>[20] T. Xiang and J.M. Wheatley Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 4632 <lb/>(1996). <lb/>[21] J.L. Tallon et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 5294 (1997). <lb/>[22] G.S. Boebinger et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 77, 5417 (1998). <lb/>[23] H. Ding et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 78, 2628 (1997); M.R. <lb/>Norman et al., Nature 392, 157 (1998). <lb/>[24] T. Ito, K. Takenako and S. Uchida, Phys. Rev. Lett. 70, <lb/>3995 (1993). <lb/>[25] G.V.M. Williams, E.M. Haines and J.L. Tallon, Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 57, 146 (1998); J.W. Loram, unpublished. <lb/>[26] C. Panagopoulos et al, Phys. Rev. Lett. 79, 2320 (1997). <lb/>[27] T. Shibauchi et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 72, 2263 (1994). <lb/>[28] D.A. Bonn et al., Czech. J. Phys. 46, S6, 3195 (1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

		<listBibl>[29] C. Panagopoulos, J.R. Cooper, and T. Xiang, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 57, 13 422 (1998). <lb/>[30] J.J. Betouras and R. Joynt, Phys. Rev. B 57, 11 752 <lb/>(1998). <lb/>[31] J.L. Tallon et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 74, 1008 (1995); <lb/>W.A. Atkinson and J.P. Carbotte, Phys. Rev. B 52, 10 <lb/>601(1995). <lb/>[32] C. Panagopoulos, J.L. Tallon, and T. Xiang, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B (Rapid Comm.) (in press) (also at cond-mat/9812333). <lb/></listBibl>

		<body>FIG. 1. (a) λ ab <lb/>−2 (T ) obtained by the ac-susceptibility technique for grain-aligned La2−xSrxCuO4 (LSCO) with x = p = <lb/>0.10, 0.15, 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24. Data obtained by µSR for unoriented LSCO (p = 0.10, 0.15) powders are also included (closed <lb/>symbols). (b) σ(T ) ∝ λ −2 <lb/>ab (T ), for HgBa2CuO 4+δ unoriented powders with δ = 0.10, 0.154 and 0.37 (p = 0.075, 0.17 and 0.22, <lb/>respectively). The data for δ = 0.154 is taken from Ref. [17]. <lb/>FIG. 2. Low-T λ ab <lb/>−2 (T ) for La2−xSrxCuO4 (LSCO) versus x compared with the low-T specific heat coefficient γ [16]. <lb/>Inset: λ ab <lb/>−2 (0) for LSCO compared with [S/T(Tc) -S/T(2K)] [16]. <lb/>FIG. 3. (a) [λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 obtained by the ac-susceptibility technique for grain-aligned La2−xSrxCuO4 with x = p = 0.10, <lb/>0.15, 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24 compared with the weak-coupling BCS theory (solid line) for a d-wave superconductor [18]. (b) The <lb/>[λ ab (0)/λ ab (T )] 2 data for x = 0.20, 0.22 and 0.24 shown in panel (a) but corrected for a distribution of Tc values with standard <lb/>deviation 3%, 5% and 9% respectively (see text for details). The solid lines are the BCS d-wave T-dependence corrected for <lb/>the respective distribution in Tc&apos;s. The curves for x = 0.22 and 0.24 are shifted vertically for clarity. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>x=0.10 <lb/>x=0.15 <lb/>x=0.20 <lb/>x=0.22 <lb/>x=0.24 <lb/>x=0.10 µSR <lb/>x=0.15 µSR <lb/>1/λ 2 <lb/>(µ −2 <lb/>) <lb/>ab <lb/>m <lb/>(a) <lb/>La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 <lb/>T(K) <lb/>Fig. 1(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>40 <lb/>80 <lb/>δ=0.154 <lb/>δ=0.10 <lb/>δ=0.37 <lb/>Relaxation rate ( s -1 <lb/>) <lb/>T (K) <lb/>σ µ <lb/>(b) <lb/>HgBa 2 CuO 4+ δ <lb/>Fig. 1(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>4 <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>γ <lb/>1/λ 2 <lb/>γ(10) − γ(2) <lb/>[1/λ (2)] 2 − [1/λ (10)] 2 (µ −2 ) <lb/>Sr content x (%) <lb/>mJ/g-at.K 2 <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>m <lb/>0 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>8 <lb/>16 <lb/>24 <lb/>(S/T) <lb/>1/λ 2 <lb/>[S/T (T <lb/>c )] -[S/T (2K)] <lb/>[1/λ (0)] 2 (µ −2 ) <lb/>ab <lb/>m <lb/>Sr content x (%) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>d-wave <lb/>x=0.10 <lb/>x=0.15 <lb/>x=0.20 <lb/>x=0.22 <lb/>x=0.24 <lb/>T/T c <lb/>[λ (0) / λ (Τ)] 2 <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 <lb/>Fig. 3(a) <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>x=0.20 <lb/>x=0.22 <lb/>x=0.24 <lb/>[λ (0) / λ (Τ)] 2 <lb/>T/T c <lb/>La 2-x Sr x CuO 4 <lb/>ab <lb/>ab <lb/>(b) <lb/>Fig. 3(b) </body>


	</text>
</tei>
