<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>arXiv:cond-mat/0004133v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 10 Apr 2000 <lb/>Carrier concentrations in Bi 2 Sr 2−z La z CuO 6+δ single crystals and <lb/>their relation to Hall coefficient and thermopower <lb/>Yoichi Ando, 1,2 Y. Hanaki, 1,2 S. Ono, 1 T. Murayama, 1,2, † Kouji Segawa, 1 N. Miyamoto, 1,2 and Seiki Komiya 1 <lb/>1 Central Research Institute of Electric Power Industry, Komae, Tokyo 201-8511, Japan <lb/>2 Department of Physics, Science University of Tokyo, Shinjuku-ku, Tokyo 162-8601, Japan <lb/>(2201conc-3.tex) <lb/>We measured the thermopower S and the Hall coefficients RH of Bi2Sr2−zLazCuO 6+δ (BSLCO) <lb/>single crystals in a wide doping range, in an effort to identify the actual hole concentrations per <lb/>Cu, p, in this system. It is found that the &quot;universal&quot; relation between the room-temperature <lb/>thermopower and Tc does not hold in the BSLCO system. Instead, comparison of the temperature-<lb/>dependent RH data with other cuprate systems is used as a tool to identify the actual p value. <lb/>To justify this approach, we compare normalized RH(T ) data of BSLCO, La2−xSrxCuO4 (LSCO), <lb/>YBa2Cu3Oy, and Tl2Ba2CuO 6+δ , and demonstrate that the RH(T ) data of the LSCO system can <lb/>be used as a template for the estimation of p. The resulting phase diagram of p vs Tc suggests that <lb/>Tc is anomalously suppressed in the underdoped samples, becoming zero at around p ≃ 0.10, while <lb/>the optimum Tc is achieved at p ≃ 0.16 as expected. <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.25.Dw, 74.25.Fy, 74.62.-c, 74.72.Hs <lb/></front>

			<body>Determination of the actual carrier concentration in <lb/>the high-T c cuprates is in general a difficult task. The La-<lb/>214 system [La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 (LSCO) or La 2−x Ba x CuO 4 <lb/>(LBCO)] is almost the only system where the carrier con-<lb/>centration is nearly unambiguously known; in this sys-<lb/>tem, the hole concentrations per Cu, p, is identical to <lb/>the x value, as long as the oxygen is stoichiometric. In <lb/>the YBa 2 Cu 3 O y (YBCO) system, the hole concentration <lb/>in the CuO 2 planes is ambiguous because of the exis-<lb/>tence of the imperfect CuO chains which absorb part of <lb/>the doped holes. In other systems like Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8+δ <lb/>(Bi-2212), Bi 2 Sr 2 CuO 6+δ (Bi-2201), or Tl 2 Ba 2 CuO 6+δ <lb/>(Tl-2201), the determination of the hole concentration is <lb/>also ambiguous because Bi and Tl ions have mixed va-<lb/>lencies [1]. <lb/>In ordinary metals or semiconductors, the Hall coeffi-<lb/>cient R H is often used for the determination of the carrier <lb/>concentration. However, R H of the cuprates has not been <lb/>considered to be a useful tool to determine p, because R H <lb/>shows a rather strong temperature dependence. More-<lb/>over, it has been reported for LSCO that the magnitude <lb/>of R H is several times smaller than that expected from <lb/>the chemically-determined carrier concentration [2]. On <lb/>the other hand, it has been proposed [3] that the magni-<lb/>tude of the thermopower at room temperature (290 K), <lb/>denoted as S(290K), can be used for the determination <lb/>of p, based on the observation that the plot of T c /T max <lb/>c <lb/>vs S(290K) is almost &quot;universal&quot; among many cuprates <lb/>(T max <lb/>c <lb/>is the optimum T c of each system), although the <lb/>data of the LSCO system do not follow the &quot;universal&quot; <lb/>relation [4]. If one assumes another &quot;universal&quot; relation <lb/>[5] between p and T c /T max <lb/>c <lb/>, so-called the &quot;bell shape&quot;, <lb/>the measurement of S(290K) yields an estimation of p as <lb/>long as the two &quot;universal&quot; relations hold. <lb/>The above mentioned relation between p and S(290K) <lb/>has not been tested in Bi 2 Sr 2−z La z CuO 6+δ (BSLCO, or <lb/>La-doped Bi2201), in which the carrier concentration can <lb/>be changed over a wide range [6]. An increase in the La <lb/>concentration z in this system leads to a smaller den-<lb/>sity of holes in the CuO 2 planes, and the optimum T c <lb/>is achieved with z ≃ 0.4. In this paper, we report our <lb/>systematic measurements of S(290K) and R H (T ) for a <lb/>series of BSLCO single crystals, for which z is varied <lb/>from 0.2 to 1.0. It is found that the optimally-doped <lb/>BSLCO crystal show notably smaller S(290K) value than <lb/>that expected from the &quot;universal&quot; relation. This is a <lb/>strong indication that the &quot;universal&quot; relation does not <lb/>hold in the BSLCO system and thus one should not use <lb/>this relation to determine p. We therefore tried to use <lb/>the temperature-dependent R H for the determination of <lb/>p. We show that, using R H (T ) of the LSCO system as a <lb/>template, the R H (T ) data can give reasonable estimate <lb/>of p. With the p values thus obtained, we construct the <lb/>relation between p and S(290K), which is actually quite <lb/>different from the &quot;universal&quot; relation. The final phase <lb/>diagram of T c vs p for the BSLCO system suggests that <lb/>T c is anomalously suppressed in the underdoped samples, <lb/>becoming zero at around p ≃ 0.10, while the optimum T c <lb/>is achieved at p ≃ 0.16. <lb/>The single crystals of Bi 2 Sr 2−z La z CuO 6+δ are grown <lb/>using a floating-zone (FZ) technique [6]. Here we report <lb/>crystals with z from 0.23 to 1.02. The crystal with z=0.39 <lb/>is optimally-doped; the optimum T c is 36 K, which is <lb/>very high for BSLCO [6] and indicates that the crystals <lb/>reported here are among the best crystals available to <lb/>date. The actual La concentration in the crystals are <lb/>determined by employing both the inductively-coupled <lb/>plasma analysis and the electron-probe microanalysis. <lb/>For the transport measurements, the crystals are cut into <lb/>dimensions of typically 2 × 1 × 0.05 mm 3 . Since the <lb/>absolute magnitude of the Hall coefficient is important <lb/>for this work, the thickness of the samples is accurately <lb/></body>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<body>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>ρ <lb/>ab <lb/>[mΩcm] <lb/>T [K] <lb/>z=1.02 <lb/>ρ <lb/>ab <lb/>/ 30 <lb/>z= <lb/>0.84 <lb/>0.73 <lb/>0.66 <lb/>0.51 <lb/>0.49 <lb/>0.39 <lb/>0.23 <lb/>(a) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>ρ <lb/>0 [mΩcm] <lb/>La concentration z <lb/>Residual <lb/>Resistivity <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>1 <lb/>-20 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 120 <lb/>z=0.2 <lb/>z=0.3 <lb/>z=0.4 <lb/>z=0.5 <lb/>z=0.6 <lb/>z=0.7 <lb/>z=0.8 <lb/>z=1.0 <lb/>&quot;universal&quot; <lb/>T <lb/>c / T <lb/>c <lb/>max <lb/>S(290K) [µV/K] <lb/>(c) <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2-z La z CuO 6 <lb/>Single Crystals <lb/>FIG. 1. (a) ρ ab (T ) data of the BSLCO crystals for selected <lb/>z values. (b) z dependence of ρ0 obtained from Fig. 1(a). (c) <lb/>Tc/T max <lb/>c <lb/>vs S(290K) of the BSLCO crystals, plotted together <lb/>with the &quot;universal&quot; relation [3] reproduced as a dashed line. <lb/>The z values shown in this panel are nominal values. The <lb/>solid line is a guide to the eyes. <lb/>determined by measuring their weight with 0.1-µg reso-<lb/>lution, and the uncertainty in the absolute magnitude of <lb/>R H is estimated to be less than ±8%. All the crystals <lb/>are annealed in flowing oxygen at 650 • C for 48 hours to <lb/>guarantee uniform oxygen distribution in the samples. <lb/>We define T c in this paper by the onset of the Meissner <lb/>effect measured by dc magnetic susceptibility. We have <lb/>confirmed that the Meissner-onset T c agrees very well <lb/>with the zero-resistance T c for our crystals [6]. The Hall <lb/>coefficient R H is measured together with the in-plane re-<lb/>sistivity ρ ab by using a standard six probe technique. The <lb/>current contacts are carefully painted to cover two oppos-<lb/>ing side faces of the platelet-shaped crystals to ensure a <lb/>uniform current flow. The voltage contacts are painted <lb/>on the two remaining side faces of the crystals (not on <lb/>the top or bottom faces), which is important for the ac-<lb/>curate Hall effect measurement. The Hall coefficients are <lb/>measured by sweeping the magnetic field to both plus <lb/>and minus polarities, while the temperature is stabilized <lb/>by a combination of the calibrated Cernox sensor and <lb/>a capacitance sensor [6]. The thermopower is measured <lb/>with a standard steady-state technique with a reversible <lb/>temperature gradient of ∼1 K, and the thermopower of <lb/>the gold wires are corrected for. <lb/>Figure 1(a) shows the ρ ab (T ) data of the BSLCO crys-<lb/>tals for selected z values from 0.23 -1.02, which show <lb/>systematic evolution with changing carrier concentration. <lb/>One may notice that the residual resistivity ρ 0 of these <lb/>samples [7] becomes systematically larger with increasing <lb/>La doping, although ρ 0 is very small (∼20 µΩcm) at op-<lb/>timum doping; the z dependence of ρ 0 is plotted in Fig. <lb/>1(b). Figure 1(c) shows the plot of T c /T max <lb/>c <lb/>vs S(290K) <lb/>of our BSLCO crystals (T max <lb/>c <lb/>= 36 K), together with <lb/>the &quot;universal&quot; relation [3] reproduced as a dashed line. <lb/>It is clear that the two curves do not agree at all. This <lb/>is either because the universal relation between p and <lb/>S(290K) does not hold in the BSLCO system or because <lb/>the T c values are somehow reduced from the ideal value <lb/>(and thus does not correctly reflect the hole concentra-<lb/>tions). To determine which is actually the case, we pay <lb/>attention to the peaks in Fig. 1(c), which corresponds <lb/>to the optimum doping; if we can find an evidence from <lb/>another experiment that the optimum T c of BSLCO is in-<lb/>deed realized at p ≃ 0.16, it is a clear indication that the <lb/>universal relation of T c /T max <lb/>c <lb/>vs S(290K) is disobeyed in <lb/>BSLCO. Note that the S(290K) value of the optimally-<lb/>doped BSLCO sample (∼ −6 µV/K) corresponds to p ≃ <lb/>0.22 in the &quot;universal&quot; relation [3]. <lb/>We now demonstrate that the magnitude of the Hall <lb/>coefficient can be used as a guide to estimate p. It has <lb/>been pointed out [4] that the fictitious carrier density <lb/>calculated from the room-temperature value of R H does <lb/>not vary much among different cuprates at the same hole <lb/>concentration. Therefore, if R H is normalized by the unit <lb/>volume V and the number of Cu atoms in the unit, N , <lb/>the resulting R H /N V is expected to show similar val-<lb/>ues for different cuprates at optimum doping (p ≃ 0.16). <lb/>Note that R H e/N V (e is the electronic charge) gives the <lb/>inverse of the fictitious hole density per Cu. Figure 2(a) <lb/>shows the plot of R H e/N V vs T for various cuprates, <lb/>LSCO, YBCO, Tl-2201, and BSLCO, at optimum dop-<lb/>ing. The data for Tl-2201 is taken from Ref. [8], and <lb/>all other data are measured by ourselves paying particu-<lb/>lar attention to the accuracy in the absolute magnitude. <lb/>The LSCO sample is a high-purity polycrystal [9], and <lb/>the YBCO sample is a high-quality single crystal grown <lb/>by a flux method using Y 2 O 3 crucible [10]. In the R H <lb/>data of LSCO and YBCO, the uncertainty in the ab-<lb/>solute magnitude is less than ±8%. It is clear in Fig. <lb/>2(a) that the normalized R H of all the optimally-doped <lb/>cuprates shown here agree reasonably well in the temper-<lb/>ature range 150 -300 K, where the data fall in a rather <lb/>narrow band of ∼20%. This observation is remarkable <lb/>and has not been emphasized before in the literature. <lb/>For the purpose of this paper, Fig. 2(a) strongly suggests <lb/>that it is reasonable to assert p to be actually around 0.16 <lb/>in our optimally-doped BSLCO crystal. <lb/>Figure 2(b) shows the comparison of R H e/N V vs T <lb/>for LSCO and YBCO at three representative dopings: <lb/>optimum doping, 1/8 doping, and the superconductor-<lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>LSCO <lb/>YBCO <lb/>R <lb/>H <lb/>e / NV <lb/>T [K] <lb/>x=0.04 <lb/>x=0.05 <lb/>x=0.13 <lb/>x=0.16 <lb/>y=6.75 <lb/>y=6.93 <lb/>y∼6.40 <lb/>(b) <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>LSCO x=0.16 <lb/>YBCO <lb/>BSLCO z=0.39 <lb/>Tl2201 <lb/>R <lb/>H e/ NV <lb/>T [K] <lb/>(a) <lb/>FIG. 2. <lb/>(a) Plots of RH e/N V vs T for various op-<lb/>timally-doped cuprates, LSCO (x=0.16), YBCO (y=6.93), <lb/>Tl-2201, and BSLCO (z=0.39). The data for Tl-2201 is taken <lb/>from Ref. [8]. Note that all the data lie in a rather narrow <lb/>band of ∼20% in the temperature range 150 -300 K, implying <lb/>that RH e/N V can be a good measure of the hole concentra-<lb/>tion. (b) Comparison of RH e/N V of LSCO and YBCO at <lb/>three representative dopings: optimum doping, 1/8 doping, <lb/>and the superconductor-insulator boundary (p ≃ 0.05). <lb/>insulator (S-I) boundary (p ≃ 0.05). For YBCO, it has <lb/>been reported [11] that the 60-K phase (y ≃ 6.7) corre-<lb/>sponds roughly to p ≃ 1/8 and the S-I boundary (y ≃ <lb/>6.4) lies at p ≃ 0.05. Therefore, because of the special <lb/>physical meanings attached to these hole concentrations, <lb/>the three dopings shown in Fig. 2(b) give good reference <lb/>points where the p values are well-defined. One can see <lb/>in Fig. 2(b) that the R H e/N V data of the two systems <lb/>agree reasonably well at the three dopings at tempera-<lb/>tures above ∼200 K. This observation gives further sup-<lb/>port to the idea that R H e/N V can be used as a guide <lb/>to estimate p; the comparison shown in Fig. 2(b) sug-<lb/>gests that the data of LSCO system, for which p is nearly <lb/>unambiguous, can be used as a template to compare the <lb/>data of other systems. <lb/>Based on the above observation, we try to estimate p <lb/>of our BSLCO crystals by comparing the R H e/N V data <lb/>with that of LSCO. Figure 3 shows the data of the two <lb/>systems for selected concentrations. From Fig. 3, one can <lb/>infer that the La concentration, z, of 0.73 corresponds to <lb/>p ≃ 0.12, z=0.84 to p ≃ 0.10, and z=1.0 to p ≃ 0.03. <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>BSLCO <lb/>LSCO <lb/>R <lb/>H <lb/>e/ NV <lb/>T [K] <lb/>z=0.23 <lb/>x=0.20 <lb/>x=0.16 <lb/>z=0.39 <lb/>z=0.73 <lb/>x=0.12 <lb/>z=0.84 <lb/>x=0.10 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>x=0.03 <lb/>z=1.02 <lb/>FIG. 3. Comparison of RH(T )e/N V of LSCO and BSLCO <lb/>at various hole concentrations. <lb/>Based on this observation, we determine the p values for <lb/>various z as follows: p = 0.18, 0.16, 0.15, 0.14, 0.13, 0.12, <lb/>0.10, and 0.03, for z = 0.23, 0.39, 0.49, 0.51, 0.66, 0.73, <lb/>0.84, and 1.02, respectively [12]. Note that these determi-<lb/>nation are not precise and the expected accuracy would <lb/>be ±10% at best [13]. This result implies that the su-<lb/>perconductivity of our BSLCO is about to disappear at <lb/>z=0.84 not because the hole concentration is reduced to <lb/>p ∼ 0.05. Remember that there is a tendency that ρ 0 be-<lb/>comes systematically larger with increasing La doping, <lb/>as shown in Fig. 1(b). This suggests that one possi-<lb/>ble reason for the disappearance of superconductivity at <lb/>z ≃ 0.9 (which corresponds to p = 0.09 -0.10) is the <lb/>increased disorder in the heavily-La-doped crystals. In <lb/>other words, in our BSLCO samples the superconductiv-<lb/>ity is more significantly suppressed in more underdoped <lb/>samples because of the larger amount of disorder probed <lb/>by ρ 0 . The microscopic origin of this disorder triggered <lb/>by heavy La doping is yet to be elucidated; it is difficult <lb/>to imagine that the random potential produced by the <lb/>replacement of Sr with La itself is responsible to produce <lb/>ρ 0 of as large as 400 µΩcm. <lb/>Figure 4 shows the plot of S(290K) vs p for our BSLCO <lb/>crystals (where p is determined as above), together with <lb/>the &quot;universal&quot; relation that is reported to be valid for <lb/>most of the cuprates except for LSCO [4]. Clearly, the <lb/>BSLCO system does not follow the &quot;universal&quot; trend. <lb/>The reason for this deviation is not clear, but it is in-<lb/>triguing to note that both BSLCO and LSCO are pecu-<lb/>liar systems in which the optimum T c is much lower than <lb/>the &quot;intrinsic&quot; T c (about 80 K) expected for single-layer <lb/>cuprates. It has been discussed [14] that these two sys-<lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>0.1 <lb/>0.12 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>0.18 <lb/>0.2 0.4 0.6 0.8 <lb/>p <lb/>z <lb/>-20 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>BSLCO <lb/>&quot;universal&quot; <lb/>S (290K) [µV/K] <lb/>p (hole concentration per Cu) <lb/>FIG. 4. S(290K) vs p plot for the BSLCO crystals to-<lb/>gether with the &quot;universal&quot; relation [3]. The solid line is a <lb/>guide to the eyes. Inset shows a plot of estimated p vs z, <lb/>together with a straight line fit. <lb/>tems might share the common trend to stabilize charged <lb/>stripes, which is known to suppress superconductivity <lb/>[15]. <lb/>Using the p values inferred for our BSLCO samples, <lb/>we can estimate the fictitious T 0 <lb/>c values for each La con-<lb/>centration by assuming the ordinary &quot;bell shape&quot; [5] for <lb/>T 0 <lb/>c /T max <lb/>c <lb/>vs p; this T 0 <lb/>c is the ideal value that would be <lb/>expected for a given p if there were no cause for the re-<lb/>duction of T c . Since ρ 0 of the z=0.39 sample is small <lb/>[Fig. 1(b)], we assume that our optimum T c is not sig-<lb/>nificantly affected by disorder and thus we take T max <lb/>c <lb/>= <lb/>36 K for the calculation of T 0 <lb/>c . Figure 5 shows the plot <lb/>of actual T c vs p of the BSLCO system, together with <lb/>the fictitious T 0 <lb/>c vs p. It is clear in Fig. 5 that T c (p) <lb/>of the BSLCO system shows a faster drop in both the <lb/>underdoped and overdoped sides of the phase diagram, <lb/>which is probably caused by disorder as inferred from <lb/>the increase in ρ 0 when z moves away from the optimum <lb/>doping [Fig. 1(b)]. <lb/>In summary, we estimate the hole concentration per <lb/>Cu, p, of a series of BSLCO crystals by using the normal-<lb/>ized Hall coefficient R H e/N V and its comparison with <lb/>other cuprates. It is demonstrated that at optimum dop-<lb/>ing R H (T )e/N V of various cuprates (LSCO, YBCO, Tl-<lb/>2201, and BSLCO) agree reasonably well in the temper-<lb/>ature range 150 -300 K, where the data fall in a rather <lb/>narrow band of ∼20%. This implies that R H e/N V can <lb/>be used as a guide to estimate p. It is found that in <lb/>the BSLCO system the room-temperature thermopower <lb/>S(290K) as a function of p does not follow the &quot;univer-<lb/>sal&quot; trend. The phase diagram of T c vs p for our BSLCO <lb/>crystals suggests that T c is anomalously suppressed in <lb/>the underdoped samples, where the residual resistivity is <lb/>found to increase systematically with increasing La dop-<lb/>ing. <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>0 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>T <lb/>c [K] <lb/>p (hole concentration per Cu) <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2-z La z CuO 6+δ <lb/>Single Crystals <lb/>FIG. 5. <lb/>Actual Tc (solid circles) and the fictitious T 0 <lb/>c <lb/>(dashed line) plotted vs p for the BSLCO crystals. The p <lb/>value is calculated from z by using p = 0.21 − 0.13z [13]. The <lb/>solid line is a guide to the eyes. <lb/></body>

		<front> † <lb/>Present Address: Nichia Corporation, Kaminaka-cho, <lb/>Anan-shi, Tokushima 774-8601, Japan. <lb/></front>

		<listBibl>[1] Y. Idemoto, H. Tokunaga, and K. Fueki, Physica C 231, <lb/>37 (1994), and references therein. <lb/>[2] H. Takagi, T. Ido, S. Ishibashi, M. Uota, S. Uchida, and <lb/>Y. Tokura, Phys. Rev. B 40, 2254 (1989). <lb/>[3] S.D. Obertelli, J.R. Cooper, and J.L. Tallon, Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 46, 14928 (1992). <lb/>[4] J.R. Cooper and J.W. Loram, J. Phys. I 6, 2237 (1996). <lb/>[5] M.R. Presland, J.L. Tallon, R. Buckley, R.S. Liu, and N. <lb/>Flower, Physica C 176, 95 (1991). <lb/>[6] Y. Ando and T. Murayama, Phys. Rev. B 60, R6991 <lb/>(1999). <lb/>[7] ρ0 is obtained by extrapolating the T -linear part of <lb/>ρ ab (T ) to 0 K, except for the z=0.23 sample for which <lb/>ρ ab (T ) is well fitted by ρ0 + aT 1.3 . <lb/>[8] Y. Kubo, Y. Shimakawa, T. Manako, and H. Igarashi, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 43, 7875 (1991). <lb/>[9] Y. Ando, N. Miyamoto, Y. Abe, and S. Komiya, (in <lb/>preparation). <lb/>[10] K. Segawa and Y. Ando, Phys. Rev. B 59, R3948 (1999). <lb/>[11] J.L. Tallon, C. Bernhard, H. Shaked, R.L. Hitterman, <lb/>and J.D. Jorgensen, Phys. Rev. B 51, 12911 (1995). <lb/>[12] It is intriguing that p changes drastically between z=0.84 <lb/>and 1.02, where the superconductivity is lost. It is pos-<lb/>sible that a strong localization of the carriers (which is <lb/>known from the ρ ab (T ) data for z=1.02) is responsible <lb/>for the loss of mobile carriers. <lb/>[13] For a limited range of 0.23 ≤ z ≤ 0.84, the obtained <lb/>relation between p and z can be approximated by a linear <lb/>relation p = 0.21 − 0.13z, see inset to Fig. 4. <lb/>[14] G. Baskaran, preprint (cond-mat/9910161). <lb/>[15] J. M. Tranquada, J.D. Axe, N. Ichikawa, Y. Nakamura, S. <lb/>Uchida, and B. Nachumi, Phys. Rev. B 54, 7489 (1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
