<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>VOLUME 80, NUMBER 19 <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/>11 MAY 1998 <lb/>General Features of Quantum Creep in High-T c Superconductors <lb/>A. F. Th. Hoekstra, 1 R. Griessen, 1 A. M. Testa, 1,2 and J. el Fattahi 1 <lb/>1 Institute COMPAS and Faculty of Physics and Astronomy, Vrije Universiteit, Amsterdam, The Netherlands <lb/>ICMAT-CNR, Area della Ricerca di Roma, Rome, Italy <lb/>M. Brinkmann and K. Westerholt <lb/>Institut für Experimentalphysik/Festkörperphysik, Ruhr-Universität Bochum, Bochum, Germany <lb/>W. K. Kwok and G. W. Crabtree <lb/>Materials Science Division, Argonne National Laboratory, Argonne, Illinois 60439 <lb/>(Received 25 September 1997) <lb/>Measurements of the relaxation rate Q͑T͒ of superconducting currents have been performed on a <lb/>carefully selected set of dirty and clean high-T c superconductors for temperatures T down to 100 mK <lb/>and magnetic fields up to 7 T. The extrapolated relaxation rates Q͑0͒ for the dirty compounds indicate <lb/>that the viscosity experienced by a tunneling vortex segment is grossly underestimated by the standard <lb/>Bardeen-Stephen theory. For the clean compounds a universal value Q͑0͒ Х 0.022 is found at 1 T, <lb/>implying that the number of superconducting charge carriers involved in the tunneling of a vortex <lb/>segment is Х14. [S0031-9007(98)06075-X] <lb/>PACS numbers: 74.60.Ge, 47.32.Cc, 75.45. + j <lb/></front>

			<body>Soon after the report of large relaxation of the supercon-<lb/>ducting current at low temperatures in high-T c supercon-<lb/>ductors (HTS&apos;s) it was proposed that quantum tunneling <lb/>of almost macroscopic vortex segments could be respon-<lb/>sible for this dissipation. In dirty superconductors tunnel-<lb/>ing of vortices is a dissipative process [1]. From the work <lb/>of Blatter, Geshkenbein, and Vinokur [2] one obtains that <lb/>in this case the normalized relaxation rate Q dirty ͑0͒ of su-<lb/>percurrents in the quantum regime at T 0 is given by <lb/>Q dirty ͑0͒ Х <lb/>e 2 <lb/>h <lb/>r n ͑0͒ <lb/>L c ͑0͒ <lb/>(1) <lb/>in case of single vortex tunneling. Here r n ͑0͒ is the normal <lb/>state resistivity and L c ͑0͒ the length of the tunneling vortex <lb/>segment, at T 0 K and with the magnetic field applied <lb/>along the c axis. For the case of weak collective pinning <lb/>L c ͑0͒ Х ͑j ab ͞g͒ ͑j 0 ͞j c ͒ 1͞2 , where j ab is the Ginzburg-<lb/>Landau coherence length in the ab plane, g ϵ <lb/>p <lb/>͑m z ͞m͒ <lb/>the anisotropy, j 0 the depairing current density, and j c <lb/>the critical current density, all at T 0 K. For strongly <lb/>layered HTS&apos;s Blatter et al. [3] argue that Eq. (1) is still <lb/>valid provided that L c ͑0͒ is replaced by the distance d <lb/>between the CuO 2 layers, since here the moving objects <lb/>are pancake vortices with thickness d. <lb/>To show that Eq. (1) predicts the right order of mag-<lb/>nitude theorists have usually taken values for the arche-<lb/>typal HTS YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 and with j ab ͑0͒ ഠ 1.5 nm, g Х <lb/>10, j 0 ͞j c Х 100, and r n ͑0͒ Х 10 mV cm they obtain <lb/>Q dirty ͑0͒ Х 0.02 close to the experimentally observed val-<lb/>ues. However, this agreement might be fortuitous since <lb/>it is arbitrarily assumed that YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 is in the dirty <lb/>limit and since the value of r n ͑0͒ cannot be determined <lb/>unambiguously for HTS&apos;s such as YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 where the <lb/>extrapolation of r n ͑T ͒ from data above T c ͑Х 90 K͒ all <lb/>the way down to 0 K is not at all reliable. To the best of <lb/>our knowledge the dependence of Q dirty ͑0͒ on dissipation <lb/>(i.e., resistivity) has never been tested quantitatively and <lb/>systematically so far. <lb/>In this Letter we present and analyze quantum creep <lb/>measurements on two sets of samples which are repre-<lb/>sentative for dirty and clean HTS&apos;s. We show that in <lb/>the dirty limit quantum creep is indeed proportional to <lb/>r n ͑0͒͞L c ͑0͒ but that L c ͑0͒ has to be replaced by an ef-<lb/>fective length L eff which, in contrast to theoretical ex-<lb/>pectations, turns out to be much larger than d for certain <lb/>highly anisotropic HTS&apos;s. Since Eq. (1) is derived using <lb/>the standard Bardeen-Stephen theory [4] for the viscos-<lb/>ity experienced by a moving vortex segment, our results <lb/>imply that this theory is not applicable for the case of a <lb/>tunneling pancake or similarly that dissipation is not re-<lb/>stricted to the CuO 2 plane in which a pancake is moving <lb/>but extends to neighboring layers. <lb/>A completely different behavior is found for clean su-<lb/>perconductors where the quantum relaxation rate Q clean ͑0͒ <lb/>at, e.g., B 1 T turns out to be essentially independent of <lb/>the HTS under investigation. This leads to the intriguing <lb/>conclusion that in all clean HTS&apos;s the number of super-<lb/>conducting charge carriers involved in the tunneling of a <lb/>vortex segment is typically 14. <lb/>We now consider quantum creep in the dirty and clean <lb/>regimes separately. <lb/>(i) Quantum creep in dirty HTS&apos;s.-For a quantita-<lb/>tive check of Eq. (1) it is necessary to make a selec-<lb/>tion of HTS&apos;s according to the following criteria. First, <lb/>the HTS should be in the dirty limit, i.e., vt͑0͒ ø 1. <lb/>Herehv͑0͒ ХheB c2 ͑0͒͞m e is the energy separation be-<lb/>tween the lowest levels of the electrons localized in the <lb/>vortex core and t͑0͒ the elastic scattering time. With <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">0031-9007͞98͞80(19)͞4293(4)$15.00 <lb/>© 1998 The American Physical Society <lb/></note>

			<page>4293 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">VOLUME 80, NUMBER 19 <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/></note>

			<page>11 MAY 1998 <lb/></page>

			<body>t͑0͒ m e ͞n e e 2 r n ͑0͒ this condition reduces to <lb/>vt͑0͒ Хh <lb/>2e 2 <lb/>1 <lb/>n e r n ͑0͒j 2 <lb/>ab ͑0͒ <lb/>ø 1 , <lb/>(2) <lb/>where n e is the density of electrons in the vortex core. This <lb/>implies that superconductors are in the dirty limit when <lb/>they have a high j ab ͑0͒ [or similarly a low upper criti-<lb/>cal field B c2 ͑0͒] and a high r n ͑0͒. Second, for r n ͑0͒ to <lb/>be determined unambiguously from extrapolation of r n ͑T͒ <lb/>to T 0 K, the selected materials should have a rela-<lb/>tively low T c and a relatively high resistivity. As a set of <lb/>HTS&apos;s satisfying these criteria we chose oxygen depleted <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O x films, ͑YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ n ͑͞PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 8 multi-<lb/>layers (consisting of n unit cells of YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 separated <lb/>by eight unit cells of PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ), and electron doped <lb/>Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d single crystals with various oxygen <lb/>contents. The r n ͑T͒ curves for the dirty HTS&apos;s consid-<lb/>ered here are shown in Fig. 1. <lb/>The latter samples are most interesting since they <lb/>have very high resistivities and low critical fields. For <lb/>two Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d single crystals [with typical <lb/>size 1 3 1 3 0.1 mm 3 and oxygen doping resulting <lb/>in T c 23.2 K, B c2 ͑0͒ ഠ 10 T for sample A and <lb/>T c 12.1 K, B c2 ͑0͒ ഠ 6 T for sample B; see Ref. [5] <lb/>for details of the fabrication] the relaxation rate Q has <lb/>been determined down to 100 mK in fields up to 7 T by <lb/>means of a sensitive capacitance torque magnetometer [6] <lb/>mounted on the tail of a dilution refrigerator. The sample <lb/>is attached to the moving spring of the torquemeter with <lb/>a thin layer of N-Apiezon grease. This spring is covered <lb/>with a 20 mm thick gold layer to obtain good thermal <lb/>contact of the sample with the refrigerator tail. The <lb/>superconducting current density j s ͑T , B͒ is measured by <lb/>performing hysteresis loops around selected values of the <lb/>magnetic field. This is done with 8 different sweep rates <lb/>dB͞dt ranging from 40 to 0.3 mT͞s in order to extract the <lb/>FIG. 1. Temperature dependence of the normal state re-<lb/>sistivity r n of the dirty HTS&apos;s Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d A ͑͒, <lb/>Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d B ͑᭹͒, ͑YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ n ͑͞PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 8 with <lb/>n 1 ͑᭡͒, n 2 ͑᭢͒, and n 3 ͑᭜͒, YBa 2 Cu 3 O x with <lb/>x 6.55 ͑ᮀ͒, x 6.6 ͑᭺͒, and x 6.7 ͑᭝͒. The correspond-<lb/>ing quantum relaxation rates Q͑0͒ at B 1 T are given in <lb/>Table I. <lb/>dynamic relaxation rate Q͑T , B͒ d ln j s ͞d ln͑dB͞dt͒ <lb/>[7]. The results for B 1 T are reported in Table I, <lb/>where we also indicate the relevant parameters for the <lb/>other examined dirty compounds [8]. <lb/>The parameter vt in Table I has been calculated at <lb/>T 0 K using Eq. (2) where r n ͑0͒ is reliably found <lb/>from linear extrapolation of r n ͑T ͒ to 0 K. We con-<lb/>clude that all the compounds mentioned in Table I <lb/>are indeed in the dirty limit. The quantum relaxation <lb/>rate Q͑0͒ is found from extrapolating the measured <lb/>Q͑T ͒ down to 0 K. This is done for B 1 T, above <lb/>which the relaxation rate is roughly field independent <lb/>for all examined samples. According to Eq. (1) for <lb/>͑YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 1 ͑͞PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 8 , Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d A <lb/>and B, these values would lead to L c ͑0͒ Х 13, 28, and <lb/>38 nm, respectively, which does not make sense for the <lb/>single unit cell ͑YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 1 ͑͞PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 8 and for <lb/>the highly anisotropic Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d (g ഠ 55 [9]). <lb/>In order to explore the origin of this discrepancy we <lb/>consider dissipative quantum creep in more detail. <lb/>As calculated exactly by Larkin and Ovchinnikov [10] <lb/>for the case of a cubic potential well of the form U͑x͒ <lb/>3U 0 ͑x͞x 0 ͒ 2 ͑1 2 2x͞3x 0 ͒ the tunneling probability in the <lb/>presence of dissipation is <lb/>P~exp <lb/>√ <lb/>2 <lb/>p <lb/>2 <lb/>h͑0͒x 2 <lb/>0 ͑1 2 j s ͞j c ͒ <lb/>h <lb/>! <lb/>. <lb/>(3) <lb/>Here h͑0͒ is the viscosity experienced by a tunneling <lb/>vortex segment and x 0 the range of the effective pinning <lb/>potential U͑x͒ in the absence of current. The factor <lb/>͑1 2 j s ͞j c ͒ is due to the reduction of this range by <lb/>a factor ͑1 2 j s ͞j c ͒ 1͞2 in the presence of an external <lb/>superconducting current density j s , where j c is the current <lb/>density at which the tunneling barrier vanishes. The <lb/>electric field arising from the vortices moving with <lb/>velocity y y is given by <lb/>E <lb/>y y 3 <lb/>B and therefore <lb/>E~P. For the case of dynamic relaxation in which <lb/>j s is measured as a function of the magnetic field <lb/>sweep rate dB͞dt [7] E ഠ ͑r͞2͒ ͑dB͞dt͒ for a sample <lb/>of radius r. Thus, dB͞dt~P and from the definition <lb/>Q ϵ d ln j s ͞d ln͑dB͞dt͒ of the dynamic relaxation rate <lb/>follows that <lb/>Q dirty ͑0͒ ഠ <lb/>2 <lb/>ph h͑0͒x 2 <lb/>0 <lb/>j c ͑0͒ <lb/>j s ͑0͒ <lb/>ഠ <lb/>2 <lb/>ph h͑0͒j 2 <lb/>ab ͑0͒ <lb/>, (4) <lb/>since x 0 ഠ j ab ͑0͒ [11] and j s ͑0͒ ഠ j c ͑0͒. Equation (4) <lb/>shows explicitly that quantum creep in dirty HTS&apos;s can be <lb/>used to measure the viscosity h͑0͒ (Table I). <lb/>All papers published so far on the dissipative tunneling <lb/>of vortices use the Bardeen-Stephen expression [4] <lb/>h͑0͒ <lb/>f 0 B c2 ͑0͒L c ͑0͒ <lb/>r n ͑0͒ <lb/>(5) <lb/>for the viscosity experienced by a cylindrical vortex <lb/>segment with length L c ͑0͒ and radius j ab ͑0͒. For strongly <lb/>layered compounds Blatter et al. [3] argue that L c ͑0͒ <lb/></body>

			<page>4294 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">VOLUME 80, NUMBER 19 <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/></note>

			<page>11 MAY 1998 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE I. Parameters for the dirty high-T c superconductors considered in this work. n s is the density of superconducting electrons <lb/>evaluated using n s ഠ 3.5m e ͞m 0 e 2 l 2 <lb/>ab ͑0͒ found for the values of various high T c superconductors in Refs. [16], [17], and [22]. The <lb/>quantum creep rate Q͑0͒ is found from a linear extrapolation of Q͑T ͒ measured down to 100 mK for Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d A and B <lb/>and down to 1.7 K for the other compounds. vt͑0͒ is calculated by means of Eq. (2) and the viscosity h͑0͒ by means of Eq. (4). <lb/>T c <lb/>r n ͑0͒ <lb/>l ab ͑0͒ <lb/>n s <lb/>j ab ͑0͒ <lb/>Q͑0͒ <lb/>h͑0͒ <lb/>(K) <lb/>͑mV cm͒ <lb/>(nm) <lb/>͑10 27 m 23 ͒ <lb/>(nm) <lb/>at 1 T <lb/>vt͑0͒ <lb/>0.1͞n s j 3 vt <lb/>͑10 217 kg͞s͒ <lb/>PCeCO B <lb/>12.1 <lb/>895 <lb/>90 a <lb/>12 <lb/>7.3 <lb/>0.055 <lb/>0.0004 <lb/>0.054 <lb/>2.3 <lb/>PCeCO A <lb/>23.2 <lb/>300 <lb/>85 a <lb/>13.8 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>0.002 <lb/>0.021 <lb/>8.6 <lb/>͑YBCO͒ 1 ͑͞PBCO͒ 8 <lb/>42 <lb/>560 <lb/>375 b <lb/>0.7 <lb/>2.4 e <lb/>0.1 f <lb/>0.090 <lb/>0.11 <lb/>11.7 <lb/>͑YBCO͒ 2 ͑͞PBCO͒ 8 <lb/>67 <lb/>150 <lb/>235 b <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 e <lb/>0.035 f <lb/>0.189 <lb/>0.037 <lb/>48.0 <lb/>͑YBCO͒ 3 ͑͞PBCO͒ 8 <lb/>77 <lb/>90 <lb/>195 b <lb/>2.6 <lb/>1.8 e <lb/>0.025 f <lb/>0.268 <lb/>0.025 <lb/>82.9 <lb/>YBCO 6.55 thin film <lb/>66 <lb/>325 <lb/>175 c <lb/>2.5 d <lb/>2.4 c <lb/>0.055 g <lb/>0.044 <lb/>0.066 <lb/>21.2 <lb/>YBCO 6.6 thin film <lb/>52 <lb/>155 <lb/>165 c <lb/>3.4 d <lb/>2.2 c <lb/>0.035 g <lb/>0.082 <lb/>0.034 <lb/>39.6 <lb/>YBCO 6.7 thin film <lb/>57 <lb/>95 <lb/>155 c <lb/>4.6 d <lb/>1.9 c <lb/>0.03 g <lb/>0.130 <lb/>0.024 <lb/>62.0 <lb/>a <lb/>Reference [14]. b Reference [15]. c Reference [16]. d Reference [17]. e Reference [18]. f Reference [19]. g Reference [20]. <lb/>should be replaced by d, the separation between super-<lb/>conducting CuO 2 planes which is ഠ1.2 nm for the highly <lb/>anisotropic dirty HTS&apos;s examined here. In order to check <lb/>the validity of the Bardeen-Stephen expression we looked <lb/>for a correlation between the effective length <lb/>L eff ϵ <lb/>h͑0͒r n ͑0͒ <lb/>f 0 B c2 ͑0͒ <lb/>ഠ <lb/>4 <lb/>p 2 <lb/>e 2 <lb/>h <lb/>r n ͑0͒ <lb/>Q͑0͒ <lb/>(6) <lb/>[from Eqs. (4) and (5)] and typical lengths such as <lb/>L c ͑0͒, d, j ab ͑0͒, j c ͑0͒, l ab ͑0͒, . . . , characterizing the su-<lb/>perconducting state of the host material. The only sig-<lb/>nificant correlation that could be found is shown in <lb/>Fig. 2: It implies L eff ഠ 2.1j ab ͑0͒. This is a striking <lb/>result as can be seen best from the data for the HTS&apos;s <lb/>Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d which have a large j ab ͑0͒ and at the <lb/>same time a large anisotropy. For samples A and B <lb/>we find L eff ഠ 2.1j ab ͑0͒ 9.9d and 12.8d, respectively, <lb/>while L eff ഠ L c ͑0͒ d is expected theoretically since <lb/>FIG. 2. The effective length L eff defined in Eq. (6) <lb/>versus j ab ͑0͒ at T 0 K for the dirty high-T c su-<lb/>perconductors Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d A ͑͒ and B ͑᭹͒, <lb/>͑YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ n ͑͞PrBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 ͒ 8 <lb/>multilayers with n 1 <lb/>͑᭡͒, n 2 ͑᭢͒, and n 3 ͑᭜͒, YBa 2 Cu 3 O x with x 6.55 <lb/>͑ᮀ͒, x 6.6 ͑᭺͒, and x 6.7 ͑᭝͒. The line is a linear fit <lb/>implying L eff ഠ 2.1j ab ͑0͒. <lb/>g ഠ 55. The correlation found in Fig. 2 implies, when <lb/>a vortex segment moves under the action of the Lorentz <lb/>force generated by superconducting currents, that dissipa-<lb/>tion is taking place in a volume ϳj 3 <lb/>ab , even for highly <lb/>anisotropic HTS&apos;s where a much smaller volume ϳj 2 <lb/>ab d <lb/>is moving in case of a vortex pancake. This might be due <lb/>to the fact that vortex motion generates a homogeneous <lb/>electric field <lb/>E <lb/>y y 3 <lb/>B c2 inside the normal core but <lb/>also a dipolar electric field outside the core. This induces <lb/>a normal current to run not only in the CuO planes to <lb/>which the pancake belongs but also in the normal cores of <lb/>pancakes in adjacent CuO 2 layers. The vertical extension <lb/>of the region in which normal currents are flowing can be <lb/>estimated by considering the current flow pattern in a re-<lb/>sistive conductor, which is indeed of the order of j ab . <lb/>Therefore we suggest that L c ͑0͒ in Eq. (5) should be <lb/>replaced by L eff , the length of the volume in which <lb/>dissipation takes place. The latter quantity is determined <lb/>in experiments since the relaxation rate Q͑0͒ depends <lb/>on the dissipative volume ϳL eff j 2 <lb/>ab and not on the <lb/>volume ϳL c j 2 <lb/>ab of the tunneling vortex segment. We <lb/>expect the assumption L c L eff of the Bardeen-Stephen <lb/>theory to be valid only in case of low anisotropy where <lb/>the moving vortex segments have L c . d, since for <lb/>highly anisotropic dirty HTS&apos;s it clearly leads to an <lb/>underestimation of h͑0͒. Equations (2), (4), and (5) <lb/>then lead to Q dirty ͑T 0, vt͒ ഠ 2͞p 2 n s 2.1j 3 <lb/>ab vt ഠ <lb/>0.1͞n s j 3 <lb/>ab vt, giving rise to values which are close to <lb/>the observed Q͑0͒ (Table I) and which are smaller <lb/>than Q dirty ͑T 0, vt͒ ഠ 2͞p 2 n s j 2 dvt expected on <lb/>the basis of the Bardeen-Stephen theory. <lb/>Having determined L eff we can calculate the viscos-<lb/>ity h l ͑0͒ per unit length using Eq. (4) and the definition <lb/>h l ͑0͒ ϵ h͑0͒͞L eff ഠ 0.95h͞pQ͑0͒j 3 <lb/>ab ͑0͒. Interestingly <lb/>the values for h l ͑0͒ determined in this way from our <lb/>quantum creep rates are comparable to the values of h l ͑0͒ <lb/>found by high frequency surface impedance measure-<lb/>ments. The latter techniques probe the intra-well-vortex <lb/>motion and are very distinct from relaxation measure-<lb/>ments which probe the motion between adjacent pinning <lb/></body>

			<page>4295 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">VOLUME 80, NUMBER 19 <lb/>P H Y S I C A L R E V I E W L E T T E R S <lb/></note>

			<page>11 MAY 1998 <lb/></page>

			<body>TABLE II. Parameters for the clean high-T c superconductors considered in this work. Q͑0͒ is found from a linear extrapolation <lb/>of Q͑T ͒ measured down to 100 mK for all compounds except Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8 which was measured down to 1.7 K. <lb/>T c <lb/>r n ͑0͒ <lb/>l ab ͑0͒ <lb/>n s <lb/>j ab ͑0͒ <lb/>Q͑0͒ <lb/>(K) <lb/>͑mV cm͒ <lb/>(nm) <lb/>͑10 27 m 23 ͒ <lb/>(nm) <lb/>at 1 T <lb/>vt͑0͒ <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O 72d thin film <lb/>92 <lb/>,10 <lb/>142 a <lb/>5.8 b <lb/>1.6 c <lb/>0.017 <lb/>.1.32 <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 3 O 72d single crystal <lb/>92 <lb/>,10 <lb/>142 a <lb/>5.8 b <lb/>1.6 c <lb/>0.017 <lb/>.1.32 <lb/>YBa 2 Cu 4 O 8 thin film <lb/>80 <lb/>,10 <lb/>198 a <lb/>2.8 a <lb/>2.0 d <lb/>0.022 <lb/>.1.83 <lb/>Tl 2 Ba 2 CaCu 2 O 8 thin film <lb/>114 <lb/>,15 <lb/>221 a <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.0 e <lb/>0.027 <lb/>.1.71 <lb/>Bi 2 Sr 2 CaCu 2 O 8 single crystal <lb/>88 <lb/>,15 <lb/>250 a <lb/>1.5 <lb/>2.1 f <lb/>0.029 g <lb/>.2.07 <lb/>a <lb/>Reference [21]. b Reference [17]. c Reference [22]. d Reference [23]. e Reference [24]. f Reference [25]. g Reference [26]. <lb/>sites. Nevertheless, for YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 Golosovsky et al. <lb/>[12] report h l ͑0͒ ഠ 3.8 3 10 27 kg͞s m from high fre-<lb/>quency measurements, while we find 1.6 3 10 27 kg͞s m <lb/>for YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6.7 . Our lower value is understandable <lb/>since YBa 2 Cu 3 O 6.7 is dirtier than YBa 2 Cu 3 O 7 which is <lb/>in the clean limit (see below). <lb/>(ii) Quantum creep in clean HTS&apos;s.-Table II summa-<lb/>rizes the measured quantum creep rates for HTS&apos;s with <lb/>a relatively low extrapolated r n ͑0͒. For all these com-<lb/>pounds we find vt͑0͒ $ 1, implying that they are in the <lb/>clean limit. <lb/>The tunneling probability in the clean limit is given by <lb/>Feigel&apos;mann et al. [13] as <lb/>P~exp͑2pn s V ͒ , <lb/>(7) <lb/>where n s is the density of superconducting electrons and V <lb/>the volume enclosed by the tunneling trajectory of the vor-<lb/>tex segment. In this case the expression for the quantum <lb/>relaxation rate becomes Q clean ͑0͒ 1͞pn s V ͑0͒. From <lb/>Table II we conclude that at B 1 T a quantum relaxa-<lb/>tion rate Q͑0͒ of the order of 0.022 is a general feature <lb/>of the various investigated compounds. This implies that <lb/>the amount of superconducting charge carriers within the <lb/>volume enclosed by the trajectory of the vortex segment, <lb/>n s V ͑0͒ 1͞pQ͑0͒, is a material independent parameter <lb/>of the order of 14 for clean superconductors. <lb/>In conclusion, we have shown that the quantum creep <lb/>behavior of dirty and clean HTS&apos;s can be consistently <lb/>rationalized. Our results call for a new treatment of <lb/>dissipation of moving vortices. In a forthcoming paper <lb/>we shall propose an interpolation formula to describe <lb/>quantum creep for any value of vt, i.e., from the dirty <lb/>to the clean limit. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">This work is part of the research programme of <lb/>the Dutch Stichting voor Fundamenteel Onderzoek der <lb/>Materie (FOM) which is financially supported by NWO. <lb/>Stimulating discussions with G. Doornbos and N. Kopnin <lb/>are gratefully acknowledged. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>[1] A. O. Caldeira and A. J. Leggett, Ann. Phys. (N.Y.) 149, <lb/>374 (1983). <lb/>[2] G. Blatter, V. B. Geshkenbein, and V. M. Vinokur, Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 66, 3297 (1991). <lb/>[3] G. Blatter and V. B. Geshkenbein, Phys. Rev. B 47, 2725 <lb/>(1993). <lb/>[4] J. Bardeen and M. J. Stephen, Phys. Rev. 140, 1197A <lb/>(1965). <lb/>[5] M. Brinkmann et al., J. Cryst. Growth 163, 369 (1996). <lb/>[6] M. Qvarford et al., Rev. Sci. Instrum. 63, 5726 (1992). <lb/>[7] H. H. Wen et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 241C, 353 (1995); <lb/>A. F. Th. Hoekstra et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 235 -<lb/>240C, 2955 (1994); A. J. J. van Dalen et al., Physica <lb/>(Amsterdam) 259C, 157 (1996). <lb/>[8] j ab ͑0͒ is evaluated using the Werthamer formula <lb/>B c2 ͑0͒ ഠ 20.7 dB c2 ͞dT j Tc T c with the Ginzburg-Landau <lb/>relation B c2 ͑0͒ f 0 ͞2pj 2 <lb/>ab ͑0͒ for the samples with <lb/>B c2 ͑0͒ far outside the experimental range. It is deter-<lb/>mined resistively and via torque measurements for the <lb/>Pr 1.85 Ce 0.15 CuO 41d samples. <lb/>[9] Value obtained from torque rotation measurements around <lb/>T c . To be reported elsewhere. <lb/>[10] A. I. Larkin and Yu. N. Ovchinnikov, JETP Lett. 37, 382 <lb/>(1983). <lb/>[11] G. Blatter et al., Rev. Mod. Phys. 66, 1199 (1994). <lb/>[12] M. Golosovsky, M. Tsindlekht, and D. Davidov, Super-<lb/>cond. Sci. Technol. 9, 1 (1996), and references therein. <lb/>NB: h and h͞phn in their Fig. 12 correspond to h l ͓1 1 <lb/>͑vt͒ 2 ͔ and vt, respectively, in our case. <lb/>[13] M. V. Feigel&apos;mann et al., JETP Lett. 57, 711 (1993). <lb/>[14] Value obtained from susceptibility measurements <lb/>and the Ginzburg-Landau relation B c1 ͑0͒ f 0 ͞ <lb/>4pl 2 <lb/>ab ͑0͒ ln͓l ab ͑0͒͞j ab ͑0͔͒. <lb/>[15] D. Ariosa et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 235-240C, 1801 <lb/>(1994); L. Krusin-Elbaum et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 62, 217 <lb/>(1989). <lb/>[16] K. E. Gray et al., Phys. Rev. B 45, 10 071 (1992); A. T. <lb/>Fiory et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 65, 3441 (1990); J. G. <lb/>Ossandon et al., Phys. Rev. B 45, 12 534 (1992). <lb/>[17] A. Zibold et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 212C, 365 (1993). <lb/>[18] Ø. Fischer et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 177C, 87 (1992); <lb/>O. Brunner et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 165 -166B, 469 <lb/>(1990); Q. Li et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 235 -240B, 91 <lb/>(1994). <lb/>[19] A. J. J. van Dalen et al., J. Alloys Compd. 195, 447 (1993). <lb/>[20] A. J. J. van Dalen et al., Phys. Rev. B 54, 1366 (1996). <lb/>[21] D. R. Harshman and A. P. Mills, Phys. Rev. B 45, 10 684 <lb/>(1992). <lb/>[22] U. Welp et al., Phys. Rev. Lett. 62, 1908 (1989). <lb/>[23] M. S. Kim et al., J. Appl. Phys. 81, 4231 (1997); P. <lb/>Berghuis et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 167C, 348 (1990). <lb/>[24] J. H. Kang et al., Appl. Phys. Lett. 53, 2560 (1988). <lb/>[25] J. N. Li et al., Appl. Phys. A 47, 209 (1988). <lb/>[26] A. J. J. van Dalen et al., Physica (Amsterdam) 257C, 271 <lb/>(1996). <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>4296 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
