<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Creative Commons Non Commercial CC BY-NC: This article is distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution-<lb/>NonCommercial 4.0 License (https://creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc/4.0/) which permits non-commercial use, reproduction and <lb/>distribution of the work without further permission provided the original work is attributed as specified on the SAGE and Open Access pages <lb/>(https://us.sagepub.com/en-us/nam/open-access-at-sage). <lb/>Journal canadien de la santé et de la maladie rénale <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/20543581231183856 <lb/>Canadian Journal of Kidney Health <lb/>and Disease <lb/>Volume 10: 1 -10 <lb/>© The Author(s) 2023 <lb/>Article reuse guidelines: <lb/>sagepub.com/journals-permissions <lb/>DOI: 10.1177/20543581231183856 <lb/>journals.sagepub.com/home/cjk <lb/>Basic Research Protocol <lb/>1183856C JKXXX10.1177/20543581231183856Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and DiseaseSharma et al <lb/>research-article20232023 <lb/>Basic Research Protocol: Exome <lb/>Sequencing in Adults With Loin Pain <lb/>Hematuria Syndrome: A Pilot Study <lb/>Aditi Sharma 1 , Matthew B. Lanktree 2,3 , Sarah Liskowich 4 , <lb/>Pouneh Dokouhaki 5 , and Bhanu Prasad 6,7 <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Loin pain hematuria syndrome (LPHS) is a poorly understood clinical syndrome characterized by hematuria and <lb/>either unilateral or bilateral severe kidney pain in the absence of identifiable urological disease. Loin pain hematuria syndrome <lb/>imposes a significant health and economic impact with a loss of productivity and quality of life in a young population. Owing <lb/>to an incomplete understanding of its pathophysiology, treatment has been limited to nonspecific pain management. Nearly <lb/>60 years after its initial description, we are no further ahead in understanding the molecular pathways involved in LPHS. <lb/>Objective: To outline the study design for exome sequencing in adults with LPHS and their families. <lb/>Methods: In this single-center case series, 24 patients with LPHS and 2 additional first-degree family members per participant <lb/>will be recruited. DNA extracted from venous blood samples will undergo exome sequencing on the Illumina NovaSeq <lb/>6000 System at 100× depth and will be assessed for pathogenic variants in genes associated with hematuria (number of <lb/>genes in: glomerular endothelium [n = 10] and basement membrane [n = 8]), and pain pathways (number of genes in: pain <lb/>transduction [n = 17], conduction [n = 8], synaptic transmission [n = 37], and modulation [n = 27]). We will further <lb/>examine identified potentially pathogenic variants that co-segregate with LPHS features among affected families. <lb/>Conclusions: This pilot study may identify new directions for an investigation into the molecular mechanisms underlying <lb/>LPHS. <lb/>Abrégé <lb/>Contexte: Le syndrome de lombalgie-hématurie est un syndrome clinique encore mal compris qui se caractérise par une <lb/>hématurie et une forte douleur rénale unilatérale ou bilatérale en l&apos;absence d&apos;une maladie urologique identifiable. Le syndrome <lb/>de lombalgie-hématurie a une incidence importante sur la santé et l&apos;économie en entraînant une perte de productivité et <lb/>de qualité de vie dans une population jeune. La compréhension de la physiopathologie de ce syndrome étant incomplète, le <lb/>traitement a été limité à la gestion non spécifique de la douleur. Près de soixante ans après sa description initiale, nous en <lb/>sommes au même point dans la compréhension des voies moléculaires impliquées dans le syndrome de lombalgie-hématurie. <lb/>Objectif: Décrire le plan de l&apos;étude pour le séquençage de l&apos;exome chez les adultes atteints du syndrome de lombalgie-<lb/>hématurie et des membres de leur famille. <lb/>Méthodologie: Pour cette série de cas menée dans un seul center, nous recruterons 24 patients atteints du syndrome de <lb/>lombalgie-hématurie et deux membres au premier degré de leur famille. L&apos;ADN extrait d&apos;échantillons de sang veineux sera <lb/>soumis à un séquençage de l&apos;exome sur le système Ilumina NovaSeq 6000 réglé à 100X de profondeur. Il sera également <lb/>analysé pour la présence de variants pathogènes dans les gènes associés à l&apos;hématurie (nombre de gènes dans l&apos;endothélium <lb/>glomérulaire [n = 10] et la membrane basale [n = 8]), et aux voies de transmission de la douleur (nombre de gènes dans la <lb/>transduction [n = 17], la conduction [n = 8], la transmission synaptique [n = 37] et la modulation [n = 27] de la douleur). <lb/>Nous poursuivrons l&apos;examen des variants potentiellement pathogènes identifiés qui co-ségrègent avec les caractéristiques du <lb/>syndrome de lombalgie-hématurie parmi les familles touchées. <lb/>Conclusion: Cette étude pilote pourrait révéler de nouveaux axes de recherche sur les mécanismes moléculaires qui sous-<lb/>tendent le syndrome de lombalgie-hématurie. <lb/>Keywords <lb/>loin pain hematuria syndrome, exome sequencing, rare disease, eGFR, hematuria, chronic pain <lb/>Received November 9, 2022. Accepted for publication May 18, 2023. <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and Disease <lb/></note>

			<body>What was known before <lb/>Hematuria in patients with loin pain hematuria syndrome is <lb/>glomerular in origin, but the source of pain is a mystery. <lb/>What this adds <lb/>We outline our study protocol to investigate genetic variants <lb/>in the glomerular endothelium and basement membrane as <lb/>potential contributors to glomerular hematuria in LPHS. We <lb/>will also evaluate variants in candidate genes in pain path-<lb/>ways. We anticipate that the results from this study will iden-<lb/>tify new directions for an investigation into the molecular <lb/>mechanisms underlying LPHS pathophysiology. <lb/>Introduction <lb/>Loin pain hematuria syndrome (LPHS) remains a poorly <lb/>understood chronic pain disorder since its first description in <lb/>1967. 1 With a reported prevalence of .012%, 2 it typically <lb/>affects young women in their late 20s or early 30s. Patients <lb/>with LPHS experience debilitating flank (loin) pain, which <lb/>can be unilateral or bilateral, along with gross or microscopic <lb/>hematuria. 2,3 In 1996, Hebert et al proposed glomerular <lb/>hematuria as the instigating event, sequentially leading to <lb/>tubular obstruction, back leak of glomerular filtrate, and <lb/>local parenchymal edema promoting compression of adja-<lb/>cent tubules and subsequent capsular stretch leading to pain. 4 <lb/>However, the absence of pain in other clinical conditions that <lb/>include red blood cell and cellular cast formation including <lb/>acute tubular necrosis (ATN), pyelonephritis, IgA nephropa-<lb/>thy (Henoch Schoenlein Syndrome), vasculitis, and antiglo-<lb/>merular basement membrane disease argues against the <lb/>validity of this mechanism. We believe LPHS likely repre-<lb/>sents a heterogeneous collection of cases that present with <lb/>shared phenotypic features of glomerular hematuria and pain <lb/>originating from the kidneys but with different pathogenesis <lb/>and natural history. <lb/>Glomerular hematuria in the absence of proteinuria is <lb/>typically associated with defects in the glomerular filtration <lb/>barrier, as most forms of podocyte injury lead to some degree <lb/>of proteinuria. The remaining structural components of the <lb/>filtration barrier include the glomerular basement membrane <lb/>(GBM) and the specialized fenestrated glomerular endothe-<lb/>lial cells (GEC). Glomerular basement membrane plays a <lb/>key role in keeping the cellular elements of blood from tres-<lb/>passing into the urinary space. The best technique to evaluate <lb/>GBM structure is electron microscopy of a kidney biopsy. <lb/>However, electron microscopy has not revealed structural <lb/>deficits in the GBM structure of most patient&apos;s with LPHS. 4 <lb/>There is a real need for an enhanced understanding of <lb/>LPHS pathogenesis using advanced cellular and molecular <lb/>technologies to explicate, detect, and diagnose both its pres-<lb/>ence and probable outcome to treatment. Rapid advances in <lb/>next-generation sequencing (NGS) technologies over the last <lb/>2 decades have enabled the extensive unbiased interrogation <lb/>of the exome, with patient/parent trio being a successful <lb/>approach for identifying candidates and de novo variants. <lb/>Specifically, the trio exome analysis has added crucial <lb/>insights for diseases with complex pathogenesis and a heter-<lb/>ogenous rate of progressions, such as IgA nephropathy, 5 ste-<lb/>roid-resistant nephrotic syndrome, 6 nephrolithiasis, and <lb/>nephrocalcinosis. 7 In addition, for diseases like chronic kid-<lb/>ney disease (CKD) of unknown cause, where renal ultra-<lb/>sounds and kidney biopsies are uninformative and are unable <lb/>to distinguish between multiple diseases, exome sequencing <lb/>has led to the identification of 500 monogenic causes of <lb/>CKD, 8,9 which in turn led to an increased diagnosis rate. 10 <lb/>Similarly, a phenotypic spectrum of GBM abnormalities has <lb/>been reported in patients with rare pathogenic variants in <lb/>type IV collagen genes (COL4A3/4/5), classically associated <lb/>with Alport syndrome, ranging from severe abnormalities in <lb/>GBM thickness to no visible abnormalities at all. The identi-<lb/>fication of more than 1000 mutations in the COL43/4/5 <lb/>genes 11,12 that encode for the type IV collagen A3A4A5 het-<lb/>erotrimer (a major component of the GBM), has led to the <lb/>reclassification of Alport syndrome and benign familial <lb/>hematuria/thin basement membrane nephropathy (TBMN) <lb/>as type IV collagen nephropathies, 13 promoting genetic test-<lb/>ing as the gold standard in understanding the prognosis of the <lb/>phenotype. Therefore, we believe that the next logical step <lb/>will be to interrogate the genes that encode the filtration bar-<lb/>rier in patients with LPHS. There are 8 genes that encode <lb/>GBM and receptors and 10 genes that code for endothelial <lb/>cells that we know of to date. 14 <lb/>While hematuria is believed to be glomerular in origin, the <lb/>genesis of the pain remains an unsolved issue. The transmis-<lb/>sion of pain from the viscera to the brain involves a pathway <lb/>that is controlled by a series of genes that code for transduc-<lb/>tion, conduction, synaptic transduction, and modulation. <lb/>Specialized receptors, expressed in the peripheral termini of <lb/>these neurons, allow noxious stimuli to be transduced into <lb/>electrical impulses. The local membrane depolarization gen-<lb/>erated by stimulus transduction is transmitted along the axon <lb/>by specific channels, some of which are expressed <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Dr. T. Bhanu Prasad Med Prof Corp, Regina, SK, Canada <lb/>2 Departments of Medicine and Health Research Methodology, Evidence, <lb/>and Impact, McMaster University, Hamilton, ON, Canada <lb/>3 Division of Nephrology, St Joseph&apos;s Healthcare Hamilton, ON, Canada <lb/>4 Department of Academic Family Medicine, College of Medicine, <lb/>University of Saskatchewan, Regina, Canada <lb/>5 Department of Pathology and Lab Medicine, University of Saskatchewan, <lb/>Saskatoon, Canada <lb/>6 Section of Nephrology, Department of Medicine, Regina General <lb/>Hospital, SK, Canada <lb/>7 College of Medicine, University of Saskatchewan, Regina, Canada <lb/>Corresponding Author: <lb/>Bhanu Prasad, Section of Nephrology, Department of Medicine, Regina <lb/>General Hospital, 1440, 14th Avenue, Regina, SK S4P 0W5, Canada. <lb/>Email: bprasad@sasktel.net <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Sharma et al <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>specifically in nociceptors. Transmission is modulated by <lb/>specific channels, which generally act to reduce excitability. <lb/>Nociceptors terminate in the spinal cord dorsal horn, forming <lb/>synapses with nociceptive-specific spinal projection neurons. <lb/>From the spinal cord, information is transmitted to the brain <lb/>stem and then processed by a pain matrix in multiple brain <lb/>regions. Descending input from the brain to the spinal cord <lb/>back to the periphery can both inhibit and facilitate the trans-<lb/>mission of information in nociceptive circuits. We believe <lb/>that LPHS patients have either gain-of-function mutation of <lb/>the pain pathways and/or a loss-of-function mutation in the <lb/>pain dampening pathways. We hypothesize that rare variants <lb/>identified in this study will help delineate disease pathways <lb/>from a syndrome driven by clinically ascertained phenotype <lb/>as a diagnosis of exclusion into one based on the molecular <lb/>basis of disease that leads to hematuria and physically inca-<lb/>pacitating pain (Figure 1). To improve the sensitivity and <lb/>specificity to identify a responsible variant over singleton <lb/>analysis, we decided to perform a family-based analysis. <lb/>Exome sequencing will be performed in LPHS-affected pro-<lb/>bands and participating first-degree family members, to <lb/>effectively detect de novo and compound heterozygous vari-<lb/>ants. In the absence of parents, analysis will be performed on <lb/>the other family members such as siblings or cousins. <lb/>Systematic Review of Observational <lb/>Studies <lb/>We searched PubMed, Embase, Scopus and Web of Science <lb/>databases to identify published studies on LPHS (search term: <lb/>&quot;loin pain hematuria&quot; OR &quot;Loin pain-hematuria&quot; OR &quot;loin <lb/>pain/haematuria&quot; OR &quot;loin pain haematuria&quot;). The search <lb/>was generated in September 2021, with no date limits set. A <lb/>total of 110 articles were identified. Studies with no abstracts <lb/>or articles were excluded (n = 6). Upon review of 104 LPHS <lb/>articles included, encompassing 610 LPHS patients, with <lb/>68% of the articles and 87% of patients reported from the <lb/>United States and United Kingdom alone. With all articles <lb/>published so far focusing on symptomatic pain management <lb/>using oral narcotic therapy and/or interventional management <lb/>strategies such as intra-ureteric infusions, 15-17 surgical renal <lb/>denervation, 18-20 radiofrequency ablation, 21-23 neuromodula-<lb/>tion, 24-26 and auto-transplantation, 27-31 we did not identify any <lb/>studies looking at (A) evidence of familial clustering of LPHS <lb/>or its components, variability in prevalence across different <lb/>ancestries, or antecedent exposures or condition, or (B) vari-<lb/>ants in genes coding for proteins that are involved in GEC, <lb/>GBM, or the pain pathways. <lb/>Research Objectives <lb/>The specific objectives of the study are as follows: <lb/>Objective 1: Identify potentially pathogenic variants in <lb/>18 genes associated with hematuria 14 (Table 1). <lb/>Objective 2: Identify potentially pathogenic variants in <lb/>89 genes associated with pain syndromes 32 (Table 2). <lb/>Methods <lb/>We plan to conduct a single-center, pilot study with the aim <lb/>of decoding the molecular basis of LPHS. The study has <lb/>Figure 1. Study design. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and Disease <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1. Candidate Genes to be Investigated for Contributing to Hematuria in LPHS. <lb/>Gene name <lb/>Chromosome number <lb/>Inheritance a <lb/>Gene annotation <lb/>Glomerular basement membrane and receptors <lb/>LAMB2 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>AR <lb/>Laminin subunit beta 2 <lb/>LAMA5 <lb/>chr20 <lb/>AR <lb/>Laminin subunit alpha 5 <lb/>ITGA3 <lb/>chr17 <lb/>AR <lb/>Integrin subunit alpha 3 <lb/>COL4A3/4/5 <lb/>chr2/chr2/chrX <lb/>AR, AD/AR, AD/XLD <lb/>Collagen type IV alpha 3/4/5 chain <lb/>GPC5 <lb/>chr13 <lb/>Glypican 5 <lb/>CD151 <lb/>chr11 <lb/>CD151 molecule -transmembrane 4 superfamily <lb/>Endothelial cells <lb/>CFH <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Complement factor H <lb/>CFB <lb/>chr6 <lb/>AR, AD, DD <lb/>Complement factor B <lb/>CFI <lb/>chr4 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Complement factor I <lb/>C3 <lb/>chr19 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Complement C3 <lb/>MCP <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Membrane cofactor protein <lb/>THBD <lb/>chr20 <lb/>AD <lb/>Thrombomodulin <lb/>PLG <lb/>chr6 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Plasminogen <lb/>DGKE <lb/>chr17 <lb/>AR <lb/>Diacylglycerol kinase epsilon <lb/>INF2 <lb/>chr14 <lb/>AD <lb/>Inverted formin 2 <lb/>MMACHC <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AR <lb/>Metabolism of cobalamin associated C <lb/>a <lb/>Inheritance based on OMIM database: AD, autosomal dominant; AR, autosomal recessive; Mu, multifactorial; SMu, somatic mutation; XL, X linked; XLR, <lb/>X linked recessive; XLD, X linked dominant <lb/>Table 2. Candidate Genes to be Investigated for Understanding Pain in LPHS Patients. <lb/>Gene name <lb/>Chromosome number <lb/>Inheritance a <lb/>Gene annotation <lb/>Pain transduction <lb/>TRPV1/2/3/4 <lb/>chr17/chr17/chr17/chr12 TRPV3/4: AD <lb/>Transient receptor potential cation channel subfamily <lb/>V member 1/2/3/4 <lb/>P2RX3 <lb/>chr11 <lb/>P2X purinergic receptor <lb/>TRPM8 <lb/>chr2 <lb/>Transient receptor potential cation channel subfamily <lb/>M member 8 <lb/>TRPA1 <lb/>chr8 <lb/>AD <lb/>Transient receptor potential cation channel subfamily <lb/>A member 1 <lb/>P2RY12 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>AR <lb/>Purinergic receptor P2y12 <lb/>BDKRB1/2 <lb/>chr14/chr14 <lb/>Bradykinin receptor B1/2 <lb/>HTR3a <lb/>chr11 <lb/>5-Hydroxytryptamine receptor 3a <lb/>ACCN1/2 <lb/>chr17/chr12 <lb/>Acid sensing ion channel subunit 1/2 <lb/>TRPC/P <lb/>chr13 <lb/>Transient receptor potential canonical <lb/>Pain conduction <lb/>SCN10A <lb/>chr3 <lb/>AD <lb/>Sodium voltage-gated channel alpha subunit 10 <lb/>SCN11A <lb/>chr3 <lb/>AD <lb/>Sodium voltage-gated channel alpha subunit 11 <lb/>SCN1,3,8A <lb/>chr2/chr2/chr12 <lb/>AD/AD/AD <lb/>Sodium channel protein type 1/3/8A <lb/>SCN9A <lb/>chr2 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Sodium voltage-gated channel alpha subunit 9 <lb/>KCNQ <lb/>chr11 <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Potassium voltage-gated channel subfamily Q <lb/>Pain synaptic transmission <lb/>NR1, 2 <lb/>chr9/ <lb/>AR, AD <lb/>Nuclear receptor subfamily 1/2 <lb/>GRIA1-4 <lb/>chr5/chr4/chrX/chr11 <lb/>AR, AD/ AD/ XLR/ AD <lb/>AMPA receptor 1-4 <lb/>NK1R <lb/>chr2 <lb/>Tachykinin receptor 1 <lb/>CACNA1A-I, S <lb/>chr19/chr9/chr12/chr3/ <lb/>chr1/chrX/chr17/chr16/ <lb/>chr22/chr1 <lb/>AD/ AR/ AD/ AR, AD/ AD/ <lb/>XL, XLR/ AD/ AD/ AD/ A <lb/>R, AD <lb/>Calcium voltage-gated channel subunit alpha1 A-S <lb/>CACNA2D1 <lb/>chr7 <lb/>AR <lb/>Calcium voltage-gated channel auxiliary subunit alpha2 <lb/>delta 1 <lb/>(continued) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Sharma et al <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>Gene name <lb/>Chromosome number <lb/>Inheritance a <lb/>Gene annotation <lb/>Pain modulation <lb/>BDNF <lb/>chr11 <lb/>Brain-derived neurotrophic factor <lb/>OPRD1/M1/K1 <lb/>chr1/ chr6/ chr8 <lb/>Opioid receptor delta 1/Mu1/kappa 1 <lb/>CNR1 <lb/>chr6 <lb/>Cannabinoid receptor 1 <lb/>GABRs (GABRD/E/ <lb/>P/Q/A1-A6/BR1-<lb/>BR3/G1-G3/R1-R3 <lb/>chr1/chrX/chr5/chrX/chr5/ <lb/>chr4/chrX/chr4/chr15/ <lb/>chr5/chr4/chr5/chr15/ <lb/>chr4/chr5/chr15/chr6/ <lb/>chr6/chr3 <lb/>AD/ M/ M/ M/ AD/ AD, Mu/ <lb/>XL/ M/ AD/ M/ AD/AD/ <lb/>AD/ M/ AD/ M/ M/ M/ M <lb/>Gamma-aminobutyric acid type A receptors <lb/>TNF <lb/>chr6 <lb/>AD <lb/>Tumor necrosis factor <lb/>PLA2G2A <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AD, SMu <lb/>Phospholipase A2 <lb/>IL1/6/12/18 <lb/>chr2/chr7/chr3/chr11 <lb/>M/ Mu, SMu, AR, AD/ M/ M Interleukin 1/6/12/18 <lb/>COX2 <lb/>chrMT <lb/>Cytochrome C oxidase subunit 2 <lb/>NTRK1 <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AR <lb/>High affinity nerve growth factor receptor <lb/>NGF <lb/>chr1 <lb/>AR <lb/>Beta-nerve growth factor <lb/>GDNF <lb/>chr5 <lb/>AD <lb/>Glial cell line-derived neurotrophic factor <lb/>LIF <lb/>chr22 <lb/>AD <lb/>Leukemia inhibitory factor <lb/>CCL2 <lb/>chr17 <lb/>C-C motif chemokine 2 <lb/>CNR2 <lb/>chr1 <lb/>Cannabinoid receptor 2 <lb/>TLR2/4 <lb/>chr4/chr9 <lb/>AD, SMu/ M <lb/>Toll-like receptor 2/4 <lb/>P2RX4/7 <lb/>chr12/chr12 <lb/>P2X purinoceptor 4/7 <lb/>CX3CR1 <lb/>chr3 <lb/>CX3C chemokine receptor 1 <lb/>a <lb/>Inheritance based on OMIM database: AD, autosomal dominant; AR, autosomal recessive; Mu, multifactorial; SMu, somatic mutation; XL, X linked; XLR, <lb/>X linked recessive; M, missing or no information in OMIM database. <lb/>Table 2. (continued) <lb/>been approved by the Saskatchewan Health Authority <lb/>Research Ethics Board (REB-22-66). <lb/>Design <lb/>Number of Subjects <lb/>Twenty-four LPHS patients referred to the nephrology clinic <lb/>(run by the corresponding author) were approached by the <lb/>study coordinator, and all 24 agreed to participate in the <lb/>study. Recruitment of 2 family members of the LPHS patient <lb/>(parents/siblings/cousins/children) is ongoing. We are the <lb/>first study to identify and report 2 patients with LPHS (12, <lb/>17) with a positive family history of LPHS (Figure 2). In <lb/>addition, 6 LPHS patients (LPHS: 01, 02, 04, 05, 11, and 21) <lb/>had a positive family history of intermittent hematuria <lb/>(Figure 2). <lb/>Duration of Study Period <lb/>The study period extended for about 3 years (2022-2025). <lb/>Participant Selection and Informed Consent <lb/>The LPHS patients have been identified by BP (Nephrologist) <lb/>and FG (Urologist), based on the inclusion and exclusion cri-<lb/>teria defined by Spetie et al 4 All patients and family mem-<lb/>bers that meet the eligibility criteria will need to complete <lb/>the written consent forms followed by baseline data collec-<lb/>tion (detailed below). <lb/>Inclusion criteria for LPHS patient <lb/>• <lb/>• ≥18 years of age <lb/>• <lb/>• Patients diagnosed with LPHS (by nephrologist and/ <lb/>or urologist). <lb/>Exclusion criteria for LPHS patient <lb/>• <lb/>• Urological causes of flank pain and hematuria <lb/>(obstructive uropathy, nephrolithiasis, pyelonephritis, <lb/>polycystic kidney disease, renal artery embolism, <lb/>renal artery dissection, renal papillary necrosis, renal <lb/>vein thrombosis, left renal vein entrapment [nut-<lb/>cracker syndrome], renal trauma, or renal tumor). <lb/>• <lb/>• Additional functional/structural reason for hematuria <lb/>by kidney biopsy or other interventions. <lb/>Inclusion/exclusion criteria for family members <lb/>• <lb/>• Only family members (parents/siblings/children/first <lb/>cousin) of the patient who provide informed consent. <lb/>Data Collection, Sample Collection, <lb/>and Exome Analysis <lb/>Demographic Data <lb/>Data related to age, sex, gender, self-reported race/ethnic-<lb/>ity, occupation, socioeconomic status, weight, height, <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and Disease <lb/></note>

			<body>Figure 2. Pedigree of LPHS patients with a family history of LPHS or isolated hematuria (IH). Roman numbers represent the <lb/>generations of the family. <lb/>Note. Proband is indicated by arrow. Abbreviations: k, kidney stones; m, migraine. <lb/>comorbidities, family history of diseases (eg, kidney stones, <lb/>isolated hematuria, LPHS, diabetes, hypertension, chronic <lb/>fatigue syndrome, mood disorders, asthma, and allergies), <lb/>the location of pain (bilateral or unilateral), the number and <lb/>frequency of pain medications, and pain score using the brief <lb/>pain inventory form and PainDetect questionnaire will be <lb/>collected for the LPHS patients. <lb/>Laboratory Data <lb/>Complete blood count, serum electrolytes, serum urea and <lb/>creatinine, albumin creatinine ratio, and urine analysis. <lb/>Genetic Data <lb/>Rare variants in genes associated with hematuria (n = 18) <lb/>and in pain transduction (n = 17), conduction (n = 8), syn-<lb/>aptic transmission (n = 37), and pain modulation (n = 27). <lb/>Hierarchical Clustering of Patient Phenotype Data <lb/>Patients will be grouped based on their demographic, labora-<lb/>tory, and genetic data using unsupervised hierarchical clus-<lb/>tering (Ward&apos;s method with Euclidean distances). 33 The data <lb/>will be presented as clustered dendrograms. <lb/>Sample Collection, Storage, and Preparation <lb/>Venous blood samples will be collected for study probands <lb/>and participating family members in PAXgene Blood RNA <lb/>Tubes (Qiagen, Hilden, Germany). DNA will be extracted <lb/>from PAXgene Blood RNA Tube using the New England <lb/>Biolabs Monarch Genomic DNA Purification Kit as per the <lb/>protocol by Kruhøffer et al. 34 DNA libraries will be con-<lb/>structed using the Illumina DNA Prep with Enrichment, <lb/>Tagmentation kit and IDT xGen Exome Research Panel v2 <lb/>with xGen Universal Blockers-NXT Mix and dual unique <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Sharma et al <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>barcodes. Paired-end sequencing (2 × 150 bps) on the <lb/>Illumina NovaSeq 6000 System at 100× depth for exome <lb/>sequencing. Library preparation and sequencing will be per-<lb/>formed for all family members at the same time to minimize <lb/>potential artifactual differences due to sample preparation. <lb/>DNA samples will be stored at -80° centigrade to allow for <lb/>future verification studies. <lb/>Exome Analysis <lb/>As depicted in Figure 3, raw fastq files will be processed to <lb/>remove adapter sequences using cutadapt (v1.11). 35 Reads <lb/>with quality score of ≥30 will be retained for analysis. <lb/>Contaminating reads will be removed after aligning of the <lb/>processed reads to the human genome using BWA 36 and <lb/>Samtools. 37 The reads will be preprocessed using the <lb/>Genomic Analysis Tool Kit (GATK), as per the recommen-<lb/>dations in the Best Practices Workflow by the GATK 38 for all <lb/>positions with ≥20× coverage, genotype quality ≥20, and <lb/>minor read ratio ≥0.2 for indel alignment, base quality score <lb/>recalibration, base alignment quality scoring, and variant <lb/>calling (single-nucleotide variants [SNVs], indels, short tan-<lb/>dem repeats [STRs], structural variant [SV]). Variant allele <lb/>frequency (VAF) will be calculated as the percentage of <lb/>sequence reads observed for the alternative allele compared <lb/>to all coverage of that nucleotide. Exome data will first be <lb/>evaluated for genes associated with isolated hematuria and <lb/>pain (as listed in Tables 1 and 2). The variants will be further <lb/>filtered and prioritized using VarSeq software (Golden Helix, <lb/>Bozeman, MT, USA) and variant effect predictor. Benign <lb/>variants with MAF (minor allele frequency) &gt;1% in any <lb/>ancestry will be eliminated using the 1000 Genomes <lb/>Project, 39 dbSNP, 40 gnomAD 41 and National Institutes of <lb/>Health (NIH)&apos;s All of Us. 42 In silico bioinformatic prediction <lb/>of pathogenicity of variants will be performed using the fol-<lb/>lowing prediction algorithms: scale-invariant feature trans-<lb/>form (SIFT), 43 PolyPhen2, 44 Mutation Taster, 45 CADD, 46 <lb/>VEST, 47 and FATHMM. 48 Finally, the candidate variants will <lb/>be checked against the human gene mutation database <lb/>(HGMD) 41 , LOVD, 12 Clinvar, 49 and Alport database. 50 A <lb/>multidisciplinary team will then review each variant for evi-<lb/>dence of pathogenicity and contribution to the phenotype <lb/>and classify them according to the American College of <lb/>Medical Genetics guidelines. 51 Possible pathogenic loci will <lb/>be screened according to 3 heredity models, namely autoso-<lb/>mal recessive (AR) inheritance, autosomal dominant (AD), <lb/>and X-linked inheritance. Sanger sequencing will be carried <lb/>out to validate potentially pathogenic variants identified <lb/>through high-throughput exome sequencing. Special atten-<lb/>tion will be paid to de novo variants, not present in parents, <lb/>as well as variants with variant allele frequencies suggestive <lb/>of potential somatic variation. Finally, we will also assess for <lb/>the presence of copy number variation using CoNIFER, 52 <lb/>cn.MOPS, 53 and CNVkit. 54 To evaluate the pathogenicity of <lb/>a rare variant, we will look at the segregation of variants <lb/>among all sequenced family members using (A) probability-<lb/>based models by Helbig et al 55 and Jarvik et al, 56 and (B) <lb/>gene-based segregation methods. 57 <lb/>Potential Risks to the Participants <lb/>In Canada, people are protected from being required to <lb/>provide the results of a genetic test by the Genetic Non-<lb/>Discrimination Act. 58 The genetic results will not be <lb/>Figure 3. Pipeline for exome data analysis. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and Disease <lb/></note>

			<body>disclosed to any third party such as employers, insurance <lb/>companies, or educational institutions. The confidentiality of <lb/>the participant will be respected. All collected samples will <lb/>be assigned a unique study number, with no reference to indi-<lb/>vidual identifiers. As this research involves looking at genetic <lb/>information, it carries the risk of identifying an underlying <lb/>genetic change(s) which are unrelated to this study and have <lb/>the potential of affecting the participant. However, this <lb/>research is being conducted for the scientific purpose of <lb/>understanding only the cause of pain and hematuria in LPHS <lb/>patients. In addition, the results of this research project will <lb/>not be placed in the participant&apos;s medical record. All efforts <lb/>will be made to safeguard participants&apos; privacy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>BP conceived and designed the study. AS wrote the initial draft. <lb/>ML and SL assisted with the drafts. ML provided advice regarding <lb/>genetic study design. BP edited the final manuscript. All authors <lb/>read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/>Declaration of Conflicting Interests <lb/>The author(s) declared the following potential conflicts of interest <lb/>with respect to the research, authorship, and/or publication of this <lb/>article: BP has received speaker and advisory fees from Bayer, <lb/>Otsuka and Astra Zeneca. MBL has received speaker and advisory <lb/>fees from Otsuka, Reata, Bayer, and Sanofi Genzyme. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>The author(s) disclosed receipt of the following financial support <lb/>for the research, authorship, and/or publication of this article: The <lb/>author(s) received financial support for the research, authorship, <lb/>and/or publication of this article from the Hospitals of Regina <lb/>Foundation. MBL has funding support from CIHR project grant <lb/>(grant no. 201909-PJT). The funding sources had no role in the <lb/>design, conduct, and analysis of the study or in the decision to sub-<lb/>mit the manuscript for publication. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Ethics Approval and Consent to Participate <lb/>The study will be conducted in accordance with the second edition <lb/>of the Tri-Council Policy Statement-Ethical Conduct for Research <lb/>Involving Humans-TCPS 2. We have received REB certificate of <lb/>approval for the study (REB-22-66). Written informed consent will <lb/>be obtained from all the participants in the study. <lb/>Consent for Publication <lb/>Not applicable as there is no patient identifying information in this <lb/>article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Availability of Data and Materials <lb/>The data sets used and/or analyzed during the current study are <lb/>available from the corresponding author on reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID iDs <lb/>Matthew B. Lanktree <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-5750-6286 <lb/>Bhanu Prasad <lb/>https://orcid.org/0000-0002-1139-4821 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Little PJ, Sloper JS, de Wardener HE. A syndrome of loin pain <lb/>and haematuria associated with disease of peripheral renal <lb/>arteries. Q J Med. 1967;36(142):253-259 <lb/>2. Vakili STT, Alam T, Sollinger H. Loin pain hematuria syn-<lb/>drome. Am J Kidney Dis. 2014;64(3):460-472. doi:10.1053/j. <lb/>ajkd.2014.01.439 <lb/>3. Aber GM, Higgins PM. The natural history and management of <lb/>the loin pain/haematuria syndrome. Br J Urol. 1982;54(6):613-<lb/>615. doi:10.1111/j.1464-410x.1982.tb13607.x <lb/>4. Spetie DN, Nadasdy T, Nadasdy G, et al. Proposed pathogen-<lb/>esis of idiopathic loin pain-hematuria syndrome. Am J Kidney <lb/>Dis. 2006;47(3):419-427. doi:10.1053/j.ajkd.2005.11.029 <lb/>5. Cox SN, Pesce F, El-Sayed Moustafa JS, et al. Multiple rare <lb/>genetic variants co-segregating with familial IgA nephropathy <lb/>all act within a single immune-related network. J Intern Med. <lb/>2017;281(2):189-205. doi:10.1111/joim.12565 <lb/>6. Warejko JK, Tan W, Daga A, et al. Whole exome sequencing <lb/>of patients with steroid-resistant nephrotic syndrome. Clin J <lb/>Am Soc Nephro. 2018;13(1):53-62. doi:10.2215/cjn.04120417 <lb/>7. Daga A, Majmundar AJ, Braun DA, et al. Whole exome <lb/>sequencing frequently detects a monogenic cause in early <lb/>onset nephrolithiasis and nephrocalcinosis. Kidney Int. <lb/>2018;93(1):204-213. doi:10.1016/j.kint.2017.06.025 <lb/>8. Connaughton DM, Hildebrandt F. Personalized medicine in <lb/>chronic kidney disease by detection of monogenic mutations. <lb/>Nephrol Dial Transpl. 2019;35(3):gfz028. doi:10.1093/ndt/ <lb/>gfz028 <lb/>9. Schrezenmeier E, Kremerskothen E, Halleck F, et al. The <lb/>underestimated burden of monogenic kidney disease in <lb/>adults waitlisted for kidney transplantation. Genet Med. <lb/>2021;23(7):1219-1224. doi:10.1038/s41436-021-01127-8 <lb/>10. Connaughton DM, Kennedy C, Shril S, et al. Monogenic causes <lb/>of chronic kidney disease in adults. Kidney Int. 2019;95(4):914-<lb/>928. doi:10.1016/j.kint.2018.10.031 <lb/>11. Consortium TIAM, Savige J, Ars E, et al. DNA variant data-<lb/>bases improve test accuracy and phenotype prediction in Alport <lb/>syndrome. Pediatr Nephrol. 2014;29(6):971-977. doi:10.1007/ <lb/>s00467-013-2486-8 <lb/>12. Fokkema IFAC, Kroon M, López Hernández JA, et al. <lb/>The LOVD3 platform: efficient genome-wide sharing of <lb/>genetic variants. Eur J Hum Genet. 2021;29(12):1796-1803. <lb/>doi:10.1038/s41431-021-00959-x <lb/>13. Kashtan CE, Ding J, Garosi G, et al. Alport syndrome: a uni-<lb/>fied classification of genetic disorders of collagen IV α345: a <lb/>position paper of the Alport Syndrome Classification Working <lb/>Group. Kidney Int. 2018;93(5):1045-1051. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>kint.2017.12.018 <lb/>14. Li AS, Ingham JF, Lennon R. Genetic disorders of the <lb/>glomerular filtration barrier. Clin J Am Soc Nephro. <lb/>2020;15(12):CJN11440919. doi:10.2215/cjn.11440919 <lb/>15. Armstrong T, McLean AD, Hayes M, Morgans BT, Tulloch <lb/>DN. Early experience of intra-ureteric capsaicin infusion in <lb/>loin pain haematuria syndrome. BJU Int. 2000;85(3):233-237. <lb/>doi:10.1046/j.1464-410x.2000.00469.x <lb/>16. Playford D, Kulkarni H, Thomas M, et al. Intra-ureteric <lb/>capsaicin in loin pain haematuria syndrome: efficacy and <lb/>complications. BJU Int. 2002;90(6):518-521. doi:10.1046/ <lb/>j.1464-410x.2002.02966.x <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Sharma et al <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>17. Ahmed M, Acher P, Deane AM. Ureteric bupivicaine <lb/>infusion for loin pain haematuria syndrome. Ann R Coll <lb/>Surg Engl. 2010;92(2):139-141. doi:10.1308/0035884 <lb/>10x12628812458338 <lb/>18. Blacklock AR. Renal denervation with releasing renal cap-<lb/>sule incision in the loin pain/haematuria syndrome. Br J Urol. <lb/>1989;64(2):203-204. doi:10.1111/j.1464-410x.1989.tb05995.x <lb/>19. Greenwell TJ, Peters JL, Neild GH, Shah PJ. The outcome of renal <lb/>denervation for managing loin pain haematuria syndrome. BJU <lb/>Int. 2004;93(6):818-821. doi:10.1111/j.1464-410x.2003.04724.x <lb/>20. de Beus E, Blankestijn PJ, Fox JG, Zoccali C. Catheter-based <lb/>renal denervation as a novel treatment for loin pain haematuria <lb/>syndrome. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2013;28(9):2197-2199. <lb/>doi:10.1093/ndt/gft225 <lb/>21. Gambaro G, Fulignati P, Spinelli A, Rovella V, Di Daniele N. <lb/>Percutaneous renal sympathetic nerve ablation for loin pain hae-<lb/>maturia syndrome. Nephrol Dial Transplant. 2013;28(9):2393-<lb/>2395. doi:10.1093/ndt/gft059 <lb/>22. Prasad B, Giebel S, Garcia F, Goyal K, St Onge JR. Renal <lb/>denervation in patients with loin pain hematuria syndrome. <lb/>Am J Kidney Dis. 2017;69(1):156-159. doi:10.1053/j. <lb/>ajkd.2016.06.016 <lb/>23. Prasad B, Giebel S, Garcia F, Goyal K, Shrivastava P, Berry <lb/>W. Successful use of renal denervation in patients with loin <lb/>pain hematuria syndrome-the Regina loin pain hematu-<lb/>ria syndrome study. Kidney Int Rep. 2018;3(3):638-644. <lb/>doi:10.1016/j.ekir.2018.01.006 <lb/>24. Goroszeniuk T, Khan R, Kothari S. Lumbar sympathetic chain <lb/>neuromodulation with implanted electrodes for long-term pain <lb/>relief in loin pain haematuria syndrome. Neuromodulation. <lb/>2009;12(4):284-291. doi:10.1111/j.1525-1403.2009.00237.x <lb/>25. Richter B, Bergman J, Pierre J, Tomycz ND. Spinal cord stimu-<lb/>lation for loin pain hematuria syndrome: clinical report. Pain <lb/>Pract. 2019;19(4):440-442. doi:10.1111/papr.12755 <lb/>26. Zuidema X, Schapendonk JWLC. Dorsal root ganglion stimu-<lb/>lation: a treatment option for chronic pain due to refractory loin <lb/>pain haematuria syndrome. Neuromodulation. 2017;20(8):841-<lb/>843. doi:10.1111/ner.12703 <lb/>27. Chin JL. Loin pain-hematuria syndrome: role for renal auto-<lb/>transplantation. J Urol. 1992;147(4):987-989. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>s0022-5347(17)37442-6 <lb/>28. Talic RF, Parr N, Hargreave TB. Anephric state after graft <lb/>nephrectomy in a patient treated with renal autotransplan-<lb/>tation for bilateral metachronous loin pain/hematuria syn-<lb/>drome. J Urol. 1994;152(4):1194-1195. doi:10.1016/ <lb/>s0022-5347(17)32538-7 <lb/>29. Parnham AP, Low A, Finch P, Perlman D, Thomas MA. <lb/>Recurrent graft pain following renal autotransplantation for <lb/>loin pain haematuria syndrome. Br J Urol. 1996;78(1):25-28. <lb/>doi:10.1046/j.1464-410x.1996.00455.x <lb/>30. Campsen J, Pan G, Quencer K, Zhang C, Presson A, Hamilton <lb/>B. Renal auto-transplantation for loin pain hematuria syn-<lb/>drome using a multidisciplinary team model: intermediate-<lb/>term results. Cureus. 2020;12(12):e12379. doi:10.7759/ <lb/>cureus.12379 <lb/>31. Cowan NG, Banerji JS, Johnston RB, et al. Renal auto-<lb/>transplantation: 27-year experience at 2 institutions. J Urol. <lb/>2015;194(5):1357-1361. doi:10.1016/j.juro.2015.05.088 <lb/>32. Foulkes T, Wood JN. Pain genes. PLoS Genet. <lb/>2008;4(7):e1000086. doi:10.1371/journal.pgen.1000086 <lb/>33. Kimes PK, Liu Y, Hayes DN, Marron JS. Statistical signifi-<lb/>cance for hierarchical clustering. Biometrics. 2017;73(3):811-<lb/>821. doi:10.1111/biom.12647 <lb/>34. Kruhøffer M, Dyrskjøt L, Voss T, et al. Isolation of micro-<lb/>array-grade total RNA, MicroRNA, and DNA from a Single <lb/>PAXgene Blood RNA Tube. J Mol Diagn. 2007;9(4):452-458. <lb/>doi:10.2353/jmoldx.2007.060175 <lb/>35. Martin M. Cutadapt removes adapter sequences from high-<lb/>throughput sequencing reads. Embnet J. 2011;17(1):10-12. <lb/>doi:10.14806/ej.17.1.200 <lb/>36. Li H, Durbin R. Fast and accurate short read align-<lb/>ment with Burrows-Wheeler transform. Bioinformatics. <lb/>2009;25(14):1754-1760. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp324 <lb/>37. Li H, Handsaker B, Wysoker A, et al. The sequence alignment/ <lb/>map format and SAMtools. Bioinformatics. 2009;25(16):2078-<lb/>2079. doi:10.1093/bioinformatics/btp352 <lb/>38. Poplin R, Poplin R, Ruano -Rubio V, DePristo MA, et al. <lb/>Scaling accurate genetic variant discovery to tens of thousands <lb/>of samples. BioRxiv. 2018:201178. doi:10.1101/201178 <lb/>39. Auton A, Abecasis GR, Altshuler DM, et al. A global reference <lb/>for human genetic variation. Nature. 2015;526(7571):68-74. <lb/>doi:10.1038/nature15393 <lb/>40. Sherry ST, Ward MH, Kholodov M, et al. DbSNP: the <lb/>NCBI database of genetic variation. Nucleic Acids Res. <lb/>2001;29(1):308-311. doi:10.1093/nar/29.1.308 <lb/>41. Konrad JK, Laurent CF, Grace T, et al. The mutational con-<lb/>straint spectrum quantified from variation in 141,456 humans. <lb/>Nature. 2020;581(7809):434-443. doi:10.1038/s41586-020-<lb/>2308-7 <lb/>42. Investigators A of URP, Denny JC, Rutter JL, et al. The &quot;all of <lb/>us&quot; research program. New Engl J Med. 2019;381(7):668-676. <lb/>doi:10.1056/nejmsr1809937 <lb/>43. Kumar P, Henikoff S, Ng PC. Predicting the effects of coding <lb/>non-synonymous variants on protein function using the SIFT <lb/>algorithm. Nat Protoc. 2009;4(7):1073-1081. doi:10.1038/ <lb/>nprot.2009.86 <lb/>44. Adzhubei IA, Schmidt S, Peshkin L, et al. A method and server <lb/>for predicting damaging missense mutations. Nat Methods. <lb/>2010;7(4):248-249. doi:10.1038/nmeth0410-248 <lb/>45. Schwarz JM, Cooper DN, Schuelke M, Seelow D. <lb/>MutationTaster2: mutation prediction for the deep-sequencing <lb/>age. Nat Methods. 2014;11(4):361-362. doi:10.1038/nmeth.2890 <lb/>46. Rentzsch P, Witten D, Cooper GM, Shendure J, Kircher M. <lb/>CADD: predicting the deleteriousness of variants throughout the <lb/>human genome. Nucleic Acids Res. 2018;47(D1):D886-D894. <lb/>doi:10.1093/nar/gky1016 <lb/>47. Douville C, Masica DL, Stenson PD, et al. Assessing the patho-<lb/>genicity of insertion and deletion Variants with the Variant <lb/>Effect Scoring Tool (VEST-Indel). Hum Mutat. 2016;37(1):28-<lb/>35. doi:10.1002/humu.22911 <lb/>48. Shihab HA, Gough J, Mort M, Cooper DN, Day IN, Gaunt TR. <lb/>Ranking non-synonymous single nucleotide polymorphisms <lb/>based on disease concepts. Hum Genomics. 2014;8(1):11. <lb/>doi:10.1186/1479-7364-8-11 <lb/>49. Landrum MJ, Lee JM, Benson M, et al. ClinVar: improv-<lb/>ing access to variant interpretations and supporting evi-<lb/>dence. Nucleic Acids Res. 2017;46(Database Issue):gkx1153. <lb/>doi:10.1093/nar/gkx1153 <lb/>50. Crockett DK, Pont-Kingdon G, Gedge F, Sumner K, <lb/>Seamons R, Lyon E. The Alport syndrome COL4A5 variant <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Canadian Journal of Kidney Health and Disease <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>database. Hum Mutat. 2010;31(8):E1652-1657. doi:10.1002/ <lb/>humu.21312 <lb/>51. Richards S, Aziz N, Bale S, et al. Standards and guidelines <lb/>for the interpretation of sequence variants: a joint consensus <lb/>recommendation of the American College of Medical Genetics <lb/>and Genomics and the Association for Molecular Pathology. <lb/>Genet Med. 2015;17(5):405-424. doi:10.1038/gim.2015.30 <lb/>52. Krumm N, Sudmant PH, Ko A, et al. Copy number variation <lb/>detection and genotyping from exome sequence data. Genome <lb/>Res. 2012;22(8):1525-1532. doi:10.1101/gr.138115.112 <lb/>53. Klambauer G, Schwarzbauer K, Mayr A, et al. cn.MOPS: mix-<lb/>ture of Poissons for discovering copy number variations in <lb/>next-generation sequencing data with a low false discovery rate. <lb/>Nucleic Acids Res. 2012;40(9):e69-e69. doi:10.1093/nar/gks003 <lb/>54. Talevich E, Shain AH, Botton T, Bastian BC. CNVkit: genome-<lb/>wide copy number detection and visualization from targeted <lb/>DNA sequencing. PLoS Comput Biol. 2016;12(4):e1004873. <lb/>doi:10.1371/journal.pcbi.1004873 <lb/>55. Helbig I, Hodge SE, Ottman R. Familial cosegregation of rare <lb/>genetic variants with disease in complex disorders. Eur J Hum <lb/>Genet. 2013;21(4):444-450. doi:10.1038/ejhg.2012.194 <lb/>56. Jarvik GP, Browning BL. Consideration of cosegrega-<lb/>tion in the pathogenicity classification of genomic variants. <lb/>Am J Hum Genetics. 2016;98(6):1077-1081. doi:10.1016/j. <lb/>ajhg.2016.04.003 <lb/>57. Qiao D, Lange C, Laird NM, et al. Gene-based segregation <lb/>method for identifying rare variants in family-based sequencing <lb/>studies. Genet Epidemiol. 2017;41(4):309-319. doi:10.1002/ <lb/>gepi.22037 <lb/>58. Minister of Justice. Genetic Non-Discrimination Act (S.C. 2017, <lb/>c. 3). https://laws-lois.justice.gc.ca/eng/acts/G-2.5/FullText. <lb/>html. Published October 18, 2022. Accessed October 31, 2022. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
