<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Title <lb/>Patient-specific alterations in blood plasma cfRNA profiles enable accurate classification of <lb/>cancer patients and controls <lb/>Authors <lb/>Annelien Morlion (1,2), Philippe Decruyenaere (1,2,3), Kathleen Schoofs (1,2,4), Jasper <lb/>Anckaert (1,2), Justine Nuytens (1,2), Eveline Vanden Eynde (1,2), Kimberly Verniers (1,2), <lb/>Celine Everaert (4), Fritz Offner (3), Jo Van Dorpe (5), Jo Vandesompele° (1,2), Pieter <lb/>Mestdagh°* (1,2) <lb/>(1) Department of Biomolecular Medicine, Ghent University, Ghent, Belgium <lb/>(2) OncoRNALab, Cancer Research Institute Ghent (CRIG), Ghent, Belgium <lb/>(3) Department of Hematology, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium <lb/>(4) TOBI Lab, Center for Medical Biotechnology, VIB-UGent, Zwijnaarde, Belgium <lb/>(5) Department of Pathology, Ghent University Hospital, Ghent, Belgium <lb/>°Both authors contributed equally to this work <lb/>*Corresponding author <lb/>Author contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: AM, CE, JV, PM <lb/>Data Curation: AM <lb/>Funding acquisition: AM, JV, JVD, PM <lb/>Software: AM, JA <lb/>Validation: AM <lb/>Formal analysis: AM <lb/>Investigation: EV, JN, KV <lb/>Methodology: AM, JV, PM <lb/>Project administration: AM, JV, PM <lb/>Resources: FO, JV, JVD, KS, PD, PM <lb/>Supervision: JV, PM <lb/>Visualization: AM <lb/>Writing -original draft: AM, JV, PM <lb/>Writing -review &amp; editing: all authors <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Circulating nucleic acids in blood plasma form an attractive resource to study human health <lb/>and disease. Here, we applied mRNA capture sequencing of blood plasma cell-free RNA from <lb/>266 cancer patients and cancer-free controls (discovery n=208, 25 cancer types; validation <lb/>n=58, 3 types). We observed cancer-type specific as well as pan-cancer alterations in cell-free <lb/>transcriptomes compared to controls. Differentially abundant RNAs were heterogenous <lb/>among patients and among cohorts, hampering identification of robust cancer biomarkers. <lb/>Therefore, we developed a novel method that compares each individual cancer patient to a <lb/>reference control population to identify so-called biomarker tail genes. These biomarker tail <lb/>genes discriminate ovarian, prostate, and uterine cancer patients from controls with very high <lb/>accuracy (AUC = 0.980). Our results were confirmed in additional cohorts of 65 plasma donors <lb/>(2 lymphoma types) and 24 urine donors (bladder cancer). Together, our findings <lb/>demonstrate heterogeneity in cell-free RNA alterations among cancer patients and propose <lb/>that case-specific alterations can be exploited for classification purposes. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>Cancer is a complex disease with considerable heterogeneity, both between as well as within <lb/>cancer types. Finding robust and easily accessible biomarkers is crucial to improve patient <lb/>well-being and outcome. Such biomarkers can either assist in early detection of cancer, <lb/>enabling treatment to start at an earlier stage, or they can support diagnosis, treatment <lb/>selection or response monitoring. As an alternative for biomarkers that require invasive tissue <lb/>biopsies, liquid biopsy-based biomarkers such as circulating nucleic acids have emerged as a <lb/>promising tool for cancer diagnosis and monitoring. <lb/>To date, most studies on circulating nucleic acids in cancer patients have focused on <lb/>circulating tumor DNA (ctDNA). The amount of tumor DNA in circulation is highly dependent <lb/>on the tumor type and burden 1 , suggesting that ctDNA can be less informative for certain <lb/>cancer types or early-stage cancers. Cell-free RNA (cfRNA) may complement ctDNA by <lb/>reflecting dynamic changes in gene expression during cancer development and progression, <lb/>or upon treatment, in both healthy and diseased cells. A recent study showed that different <lb/>cell types contribute RNA to the healthy cell-free plasma transcriptome, and that cfRNA <lb/>allows monitoring of cell-type-specific changes in diseases, such as non-alcoholic fatty liver <lb/>and Alzheimer&apos;s disease 2 . The potential of cfRNA as prognostic biomarker has also been <lb/>demonstrated for pre-eclampsia and organ damage in pregnancy 3 . Some studies have also <lb/>shown potential of using cfRNA biomarkers in certain cancer types 4-6 . Larson et al. 4 <lb/>specifically looked at genes that are &quot;dark&quot; (no or few detected transcripts) in plasma from <lb/>healthy controls but abundant in plasma from lung and/or breast cancer patients and found <lb/>indications of tissue-of-origin signal. Chen et al. 5 reported potential of combining human and <lb/>microbe-derived plasma cfRNA for distinguishing healthy donor and cancer plasma samples <lb/>(colorectum, stomach, liver, lung, and esophageal cancer) based on profiles of RNAs showing <lb/>group-level differences. Roskams-Hieter et al. 6 showed plasma cfRNA classification potential <lb/>for liver cancer and multiple myeloma patient samples compared to non-cancer controls, with <lb/>a higher accuracy using learning vector quantization feature selection compared to group-<lb/>level differential abundance. The authors, however, indicated that liver and bone marrow are <lb/>major contributors to the plasma transcriptome which may result in more cancer signal. <lb/>Here, we further examined the impact of different cancer types on plasma cfRNA profiles in <lb/>different cohorts (Table 1). We first quantified cell-free mRNAs in different cohorts of blood <lb/>plasma from cancer patients with locally advanced or metastatic tumors and cancer-free <lb/>donors to uncover tumor or tissue-of-origin mRNA signatures with diagnostic potential. <lb/>Results revealed substantial heterogeneity in cell-free mRNA abundance among cohorts, <lb/>questioning the biomarker potential of cell-free mRNA signatures. However, patient-specific <lb/>alterations, reflected by the number of cell-free mRNAs with differential abundance in a <lb/>patient sample compared to a cancer-free control population, enabled to accurately <lb/>distinguish cancer patients from healthy individuals. <lb/>Table 1: Cohort overview. Name, number of donors (one sample per donor), biofluid type, library preparation <lb/>method and application of the cohort in this study. (*) eight control donors also included in pan-cancer cohort, <lb/>data of these donors not used for validation analyses (see Methods). <lb/>cohort name <lb/>cancer patients <lb/>(cancer types) <lb/>controls biofluid <lb/>library preparation <lb/>application <lb/>pan-cancer <lb/>cohort <lb/>200 (25) <lb/>8 <lb/>plasma <lb/>mRNA capture (Illumina DNA <lb/>Prep with Enrichment) <lb/>discovery <lb/>three-cancer <lb/>cohort <lb/>36 (3) <lb/>30* <lb/>plasma <lb/>mRNA capture (Illumina DNA <lb/>Prep with Enrichment) <lb/>validation pan-cancer <lb/>analyses &amp; discovery tail <lb/>gene concept <lb/>lymphoma <lb/>cohort <lb/>43 (2) <lb/>22 <lb/>plasma <lb/>total RNA (SMARTer Stranded <lb/>Total RNA-Seq Kit v3 -Pico <lb/>Input Mammalian) <lb/>validation tail gene <lb/>concept <lb/>bladder <lb/>cancer cohort <lb/>12 (1) <lb/>12 <lb/>urine <lb/>mRNA capture (TruSeq RNA <lb/>Exome) <lb/>validation tail gene <lb/>concept <lb/>Results <lb/>A diverse repertoire of cell-free mRNAs in plasma <lb/>To characterize the blood plasma cell-free mRNA transcriptome, we collected blood plasma <lb/>from a pan-cancer discovery cohort consisting of 208 individuals covering 25 different cancer <lb/>types and aged-matched healthy controls (Figure 1a, Supplemental Table 1). MRNA capture <lb/>sequencing of the pan-cancer plasma cohort resulted in 3 to 56M paired-end reads per <lb/>sample (median 16M) after quality filtering with no significant differences among groups <lb/>(Kruskal-Wallis test p&gt;0.05) (Supplemental Figure 1). On average 84% (95% CI [82.59, 84.66]) <lb/>of uniquely mapped reads were assigned to protein coding genes and most other reads <lb/>originated from mitochondrially encoded ribosomal RNAs (Supplemental Figure 2). Per <lb/>sample, between 7439 and 13,039 unique mRNAs (median 10,932) were detected with at <lb/>least 10 counts -we use the term mRNA to refer to all mRNA reads mapping to the same <lb/>gene (Figure 1b). All plasma samples had 5263 mRNAs in common and 9908 mRNAs were <lb/>found in at least 75% of the samples. Of note, we detected more mRNAs in plasma from acute <lb/>myeloid leukemia (AML) patients compared to plasma from controls and from patients with <lb/>solid cancers (Kruskal-Wallis p=6.6E-4, effect size= 0.163, post hoc two-sided Wilcoxon rank-<lb/>sum q &lt; 0.05 for AML vs controls and 16 out of 24 solid cancer types). Although some AML <lb/>samples were sequenced deeper, sequencing depth alone did not explain the higher number <lb/>of detected mRNAs (Supplemental Figure 3). We next determined the mRNA concentration <lb/>using synthetic RNA spikes that were added to each lysed plasma sample (Figure 1c). MRNA <lb/>concentrations ranged from 0.003 to 8.302 ng/ml with an average concentration of 0.486 <lb/>ng/ml. Despite the higher number of detected mRNAs, the mRNA-concentration in AML <lb/>plasma was not significantly higher than controls or other cancer types. Moreover, though <lb/>the largest median mRNA concentration (READ, 0.648 ng/ml) was more than 10 times higher <lb/>than the smallest median (ANA, 0.063 ng/ml), no significant concentration differences were <lb/>found between the groups (Kruskal-Wallis test p=0.0275, effect size=0.087, with all post hoc <lb/>two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum q &gt; 0.05). Besides the small sample sizes, this may be related <lb/>to the considerable cfRNA concentration variability between patients, which is also reported <lb/>at cfDNA level 7 . <lb/>We then searched for evidence of tumor-derived cfRNA by investigating known cancer fusion <lb/>transcripts in individual plasma samples. In every cancer plasma sample, we only considered <lb/>fusion transcripts that had been documented in tumor tissue of that same cancer type. Such <lb/>fusion transcripts were only identified in plasma samples of AML patients. The PML::RARA <lb/>fusion transcript 8 was found in two AML plasma samples with several reads supporting the <lb/>fusion (7 to 19 spanning pairs and 6 to 9 unique spanning reads). The reciprocal RARA::PML <lb/>fusion was found in one of both AML plasma samples (19 pairs and 17 unique reads). In <lb/>plasma samples of solid cancer types, we only detected fusion transcripts that had not been <lb/>reported in the tumor tissue of these cancer types (Supplemental Table 2). Of note, these <lb/>fusion transcripts had fewer supporting reads (1 to 2 pairs and 2 to 5 unique reads) than the <lb/>PML::RARA/RARA::PML fusions in AML and may thus represent false positives. Moreover, <lb/>other fusions with few supporting reads were also identified in healthy control plasma <lb/>samples. While the two AML samples with the PML::RARA fusion transcripts were sequenced <lb/>deeper than other samples, the fusions were still detected when downsampling to the <lb/>median number of reads of the pan-cancer cohort. These analyses confirm the presence of <lb/>tumor cell-derived cfRNA in plasma samples from AML patients. <lb/>Figure 1: Pan-cancer plasma cohort overview, mRNA content and sample clustering. a, Primary sites of the 25 <lb/>cancer types in the pan-cancer cohort. Primary sites are indicated with colored dots and corresponding cancer <lb/>types are listed (top to bottom) with the (sub)type abbreviations between brackets. Full names and more details <lb/>can be found in Supplemental Table 1. b, Number of plasma mRNAs, detected with at least 10 counts, across <lb/>cancer types and healthy controls. Groups ordered according to median. c, Variability in plasma mRNA <lb/>concentration across cancer types and healthy controls. Groups ordered according to median. b and c, Boxplots <lb/>show lower quartile (Q1), median, and upper quartile (Q3). Whiskers extend from the lower and upper quartile <lb/>to the smallest and largest value, respectively, within at most 1.5*interquartile range (Q3-Q1) from that quartile. <lb/>More extreme points are plotted as individual dots. d, Principal component analysis using the 500 most variable <lb/>mRNAs in the pan-cancer cohort (with variance stabilizing transformation DESeq2). Yellow squares: control <lb/>samples; red triangles: acute myeloid leukemia samples; blue dots: non-leukemia cancer samples. e and f, <lb/>Principal component analysis using the 500 most variable mRNAs in controls and anaplastic astrocytoma (ANA) <lb/>or prostate cancer (PRAD) patients, respectively. Replicate numbers are indicated in the plot. PC: principal <lb/>component. <lb/>Differential mRNA abundance in cancer patients&apos; plasma compared to controls <lb/>Principal component analysis revealed a clear separation between AML and other plasma <lb/>samples for six out of eight AML patients (Figure 1d). Control samples mostly clustered in <lb/>between samples of solid tumors. Analysis of individual solid tumor types revealed that most <lb/>patient samples could be separated from controls in the first two principal components <lb/>(Figure 1e and f, Supplemental Figure 4), suggesting that plasma cfRNA profiles of cancer <lb/>patients differ from that of controls. <lb/>Differentially abundant mRNAs were identified in every cancer-control comparison, with <lb/>numbers varying from 10 to 2583 (median 128) for higher abundant mRNAs and from 89 to <lb/>2727 (median 221) for lower abundant mRNAs in cancer compared to control (Figure 2a). <lb/>Most differentially abundant mRNAs were found in AML (5310 mRNAs), followed by uterine <lb/>cancer (UCEC) and sarcoma (SARC) with 1154 and 763 mRNAs, respectively. Head and neck <lb/>(HNSC), rectal (READ) and breast cancer (BRCA) had the lowest number of differentially <lb/>abundant mRNAs (127, 136, and 145 respectively). <lb/>In total, 6758 unique mRNAs were differentially abundant in one or more cancer-control <lb/>comparisons (b) and the median absolute fold change was 3.1. One quarter of differentially <lb/>abundant mRNAs had an absolute fold change of at least 4.6. Hierarchical clustering based on <lb/>differential mRNA abundance mostly separated cancer and control samples but also revealed <lb/>variability in gene abundance within groups (Figure 2b and c, Supplemental Figure 5). <lb/>4442 mRNAs (66%) were differentially abundant in one cancer type only (Figure 2d), and most <lb/>(3680 mRNAs) were identified in AML. While many mRNAs were differentially abundant in <lb/>plasma of only one or a few cancer types, 26 differentially abundant mRNAs were recurrent <lb/>in 23 out of 25 cancer-control comparisons (Figure 2d). These mRNAs were all lower abundant <lb/>in cancer compared to controls and showed enrichment for inflammatory and immune <lb/>response pathways (Supplemental Table 3). <lb/>Figure 2: Differentially abundant mRNAs in cancer versus control. a, Differentially abundant mRNAs in plasma <lb/>from cancer patients versus controls. Cancer types ordered based on total number of differentially abundant <lb/>mRNAs (q &lt; 0.05 and |log2 fold change|&gt;1). b and c, Volcano plot and heatmap of differentially abundant mRNAs <lb/>in anaplastic astrocytoma vs controls (b) and in prostate cancer vs controls (c). Volcano plots have a horizontal <lb/>line at q = 0.05 and vertical lines at log2 fold change of -1 and 1, resp. Higher (red): higher abundant in cancer <lb/>compared to control samples (q &lt; 0.05 and log2 fold change &gt; 1); lower (blue): lower abundant in cancer <lb/>compared to control samples (q &lt; 0.05 and log2 fold change &lt; -1). Heatmaps show relative abundance of <lb/>differentially abundant mRNAs (columns) in individual plasma samples (rows) based on log2(normalized <lb/>counts+1) followed by z-score transformation per gene. Clustering of genes and samples based on Pearson <lb/>correlation. d, Recurrence of differentially abundant mRNAs (shown in a) across cancer types. <lb/>Enrichment of pathways and cell types in cancer patients&apos; plasma <lb/>To explore the pathways, cell types and tissues underlying the differentially abundant mRNAs <lb/>in cancer plasma, we first applied gene set enrichment analyses using hallmark 9 , Kyoto <lb/>Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes (KEGG) 10 , and custom tissue-and cell type gene sets <lb/>(Figure 3a, Supplemental Figure 6a and b). We observed a negative enrichment of various <lb/>immune-related signals (interleukin signaling, interferon gamma and inflammatory response, <lb/>and neutrophils) across all cancer types except UCEC, with q&lt;0.05 in at least 21 out of 25 <lb/>cancer types. &apos;Ribosome&apos; was also negatively enriched in all solid cancer types (q&lt;0.05 in 19 <lb/>out of 24 types). These results are in line with a previous study by Chen et al. 5 on plasma <lb/>cfRNA profiles of five early-stage solid cancer types. Other negatively enriched gene sets with <lb/>q&lt;0.05 in at least half of the cancer types in our cohort were &apos;epithelium&apos; and &apos;blood&apos; related. <lb/>Conversely, &apos;extracellular matrix receptor&apos; and &apos;focal adhesion&apos; gene sets were significantly <lb/>positively enriched in at least half of the cancer types, confirming results by Chen et al. Other <lb/>positively enriched gene sets included &apos;epithelial-mesenchymal transition&apos;, &apos;vasculature&apos;, <lb/>&apos;adipose tissue&apos;, &apos;brain&apos;, and &apos;hematopoietic stem cells&apos;. <lb/>Cancer type-specific enrichment of cfRNA reflecting the primary tumor site was only observed <lb/>for liver cancer patients. &apos;Liver tissue&apos;, &apos;liver cancer tissue&apos;, and &apos;hepatocyte&apos; gene sets were <lb/>all positively enriched in liver cancer patients&apos; plasma (q&lt;0.05, Figure 3b) and not in plasma <lb/>from any other cancer type. A &apos;bronchial epithelial cells&apos; gene set was significantly enriched <lb/>in lung adenocarcinoma and lung squamous cell carcinoma (LUAD q=0.027; LUSC q=0.026), <lb/>but this enrichment was also found in four other cancer types (ANA, CESC, CHOL, and UCEC). <lb/>We then applied computational deconvolution to enumerate the cell type fractions <lb/>contributing to plasma cfRNA profiles (Supplemental Table 4). Platelets, <lb/>erythrocytes/erythrocyte progenitors, monocytes, macrophages, and B-cells formed the top-<lb/>5 of most abundant cell types that contributed to plasma cfRNA of both controls and patients <lb/>with solid tumors (Figure 3c). Except for macrophages, these cell types were also reported as <lb/>the most abundant cell types in a previous study on healthy donor plasma 2 . Plasma from AML <lb/>patients showed a very different composition. Several cell types -including hematopoietic <lb/>stem cells, myeloid progenitor cells, and monocytes -were increased or even exclusively <lb/>present in AML plasma samples, in line with the blood cell counts typically observed in these <lb/>patients 11 . Myeloid progenitor cells, normally not present in peripheral blood, were the <lb/>second most abundant cell type in the AML plasma samples (mean 10.7%), with almost no <lb/>signal in other plasma samples (mean 0.1%) (Supplemental Figure 7). Moreover, the platelet <lb/>fraction in AML plasma was significantly lower compared to other groups (two-sided <lb/>Wilcoxon rank sum p=3.8E-5, effect size=0.289) with on average 18.3% in AML compared to <lb/>62.3% in other samples, reflecting the reduced thrombocyte counts commonly found in <lb/>leukemia patients 11 . <lb/>In plasma from patients with solid tumors, the platelet fraction was significantly higher <lb/>compared to controls (Supplemental Figure 7, two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum p=2.3E-2, effect <lb/>size=0.163), which is in line with the prognostic value of platelet counts and the frequent <lb/>occurrence of thrombocytosis in solid tumor patients 12,13 . For neutrophils, <lb/>erythrocyte/erythroid progenitor cells, thymocytes, and T-cells, the fraction was significantly <lb/>lower in cancer patients&apos; plasma compared to controls (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum p=1.8E-<lb/>2 (effect size=0.169), p=1.4E-2 (effect size=0.176), p=1.8E-2 (effect size=0.164), p=4.3E-4 <lb/>(effect size=0.252), respectively). <lb/>Figure 3: Gene set enrichment and cell type deconvolution reveal pan-cancer and cancer-type specific signals. <lb/>a, Gene set enrichment analysis results for custom tissue and cell type sets. Only sets that are significantly <lb/>enriched in at least half of the cancer types are shown. Gene sets with q &lt; 0.05 colored according to normalized <lb/>enrichment scores (NES). b, Liver-related gene set enrichment in plasma from liver cancer patients, gene sets <lb/>with q &lt; 0.25 colored according to NES. Detailed information about gene sets can be found in Methods. c, Average <lb/>fraction of the five most abundant cell types based on deconvolution. Other: cumulative sum of other cell types. <lb/>The five most abundant cell types were selected based on mean ranking in all groups. <lb/>Independent validation cohort confirms systemic signal and cfRNA heterogeneity <lb/>To validate our findings, we processed an independent (three-cancer) cohort of plasma <lb/>samples which, after removing samples with low read depth, included samples from 20 <lb/>cancer-free control donors and 35 cancer patients with one of three different solid cancer <lb/>types: prostate (PRAD, n=12), ovarian (OV, n=11), and uterine (UCEC, n=12) cancer. 7 to 61M <lb/>paired-end reads were obtained per sample (median 28M) with no significant difference in <lb/>sequencing depth among groups (Kruskal-Wallis p=0.7858) (Supplemental Figure 8a). In line <lb/>with the pan-cancer cohort, we detected between 8642 and 11,944 mRNAs per sample <lb/>(Supplemental Figure 8b), with 6194 mRNAs shared across all plasma samples of this three-<lb/>cancer cohort. MRNA concentrations ranged from 0.007 to 0.414 ng/ml (Supplemental Figure <lb/>8c). <lb/>Most cancer samples could be separated from controls in the first principal component, <lb/>especially for prostate and ovarian cancer (Figure 4a). Based on differential abundance <lb/>analyses between cancer and control samples, we found the highest number of differentially <lb/>abundant mRNAs in OV (995 higher abundant, 1644 lower abundant), followed by PRAD (848 <lb/>higher abundant, 1043 lower abundant) (Figure 4b). The lowest number of differentially <lb/>abundant mRNAs was found for UCEC (243 higher abundant, 349 lower abundant) even <lb/>though this cancer type had the most differentially abundant mRNAs in the pan-cancer <lb/>cohort. Hierarchical clustering based on differential mRNA abundance in this three-cancer <lb/>cohort mostly separated cancer and control samples but again revealed variability in mRNA <lb/>abundance within groups (Supplemental Figure 9). <lb/>189 and 299 mRNAs were significantly higher and lower abundant, respectively, in plasma <lb/>from all three cancer types compared to controls (Figure 4b). The lower abundant mRNAs <lb/>included all 26 mRNAs that were identified as lower abundant in most cancers in the pan-<lb/>cancer cohort. There was a significant, although limited, overlap in differentially abundant <lb/>mRNAs between the three-cancer and the pan-cancer cohort for each of the three cancer <lb/>types (Fisher&apos;s exact test on lower abundant mRNAs: OV p=8.4E-118 (odds ratio=30.0), PRAD <lb/>p=1.1E-155 (odds ratio=59.3), UCEC p=7.6E-13 (odds ratio=4.2); on higher abundant mRNAs: <lb/>OV p=4.0E-4 (odds ratio=4.6), PRAD p=2.9E-52 (odds ratio=12.2), UCEC p=2.2E-5 (odds <lb/>ratio=3.3); Jaccard index [0.9-14.3%]) (Figure 4c and Supplemental Figure 10a). Respectively <lb/>38%, 49%, and 95% of the differentially abundant mRNAs in OV, PRAD, and UCEC in the pan-<lb/>cancer cohort could not be confirmed in the three-cancer cohort. Notably, mRNAs with lower <lb/>abundance showed a higher overlap between both cohorts than mRNAs with higher <lb/>abundance. <lb/>In line with the pan-cancer cohort, there was no enrichment of cancer type specific gene sets <lb/>reflecting tumor tissue of origin in the OV, PRAD and UCEC samples in the three-cancer <lb/>cohort. However, enriched gene sets shared among at least half of the cancer types in the <lb/>pan-cancer cohort were confirmed in the three-cancer cohort, except for adipose tissue <lb/>(Figure 4d, Supplemental Figure 10b and c). <lb/>Cell type deconvolution confirmed platelets, erythrocyte/erythroid progenitor cells, <lb/>monocytes and B-cells among the top-5 cell types contributing cfRNA to plasma (Figure 4e, <lb/>Supplemental Table 4), with neutrophils being ranked as the fourth most abundant cell type. <lb/>The higher platelet fraction in cancer patient plasma was even more pronounced in the three-<lb/>cancer cohort (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum cancer versus control p=5.8E-9, effect size= <lb/>0.679), especially for ovarian and prostate cancer (Supplemental Figure 11). Neutrophils, <lb/>erythrocyte/erythroid progenitor cells, thymocytes and T-cells again had a lower plasma <lb/>fraction in cancer patients compared to controls (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum p=4.4E-6 <lb/>(effect size=0.556), p=3.2E-7 (effect size=0.610), p=6.4E-5 (effect size=0.419), p=4.1E-2 (effect <lb/>size=0.261), respectively). <lb/>Taken together, the limited overlap of differentially abundant mRNAs between the pan-<lb/>cancer and three-cancer cohort highlights plasma transcriptome variability, yet enrichment <lb/>and cell type contribution analyses confirm the systemic cfRNA changes in plasma from <lb/>cancer patients. <lb/>Figure 4: Three-cancer cohort confirms findings from pan-cancer cohort and reveals significant, yet limited, <lb/>overlap in differentially abundant mRNAs. a, Principal component analysis on top 500 most variable mRNAs <lb/>shows distinct clustering of most cancer and control samples (variance stabilizing transformation DESeq2). b, <lb/>0verlap between differentially abundant mRNAs detected in individual cancer-control comparisons. Circles are <lb/>proportional to the number of genes. c, Overlap between differentially abundant genes in prostate cancer versus <lb/>control for the pan-cancer and three-cancer cohort. Fisher&apos;s exact test: p=2.9E-52, odds ratio=12.2, Jaccard <lb/>index=8.3% for higher abundant mRNAs in cancer versus control (higher); p=1.1E-155, odds ratio=59.3, Jaccard <lb/>index=14.3% for lower abundant mRNAs (lower). Circles are proportional to the number of genes. d, Gene set <lb/>enrichment analysis results for custom tissue and cell type sets. Only pathways of Figure 3a shown. Gene sets <lb/>with q &lt; 0.05 colored according to normalized enrichment scores (NES). e, Average fraction of the five most <lb/>abundant cell types and macrophages based on cell type deconvolution. Other: cumulative sum of other cell <lb/>types. Differential abundance: q&lt;0.05 &amp; |log2 fold change|&gt;1. OV: ovarian cancer; PRAD: prostate cancer; UCEC: <lb/>uterine cancer. <lb/>cfRNA tail genes distinguish cancer samples from controls <lb/>Apart from liver cancer and AML, our analyses did not reveal evidence for a tumor or tissue <lb/>of origin signal among mRNAs that were more abundant in cancer patient versus control <lb/>plasma. Moreover, higher abundant mRNAs were less recurrent across cancer types and <lb/>showed lower validation rates between cohorts compared to mRNAs with lower abundance <lb/>in cancer versus control plasma. Our analyses suggest that the latter represent a systemic <lb/>immune response rather than a tumor derived signal. Based on these observations, we <lb/>hypothesized that (tumor derived) cfRNA signals may be heterogeneous among patients, and <lb/>that classic differential mRNA and pathway abundance analysis between groups may not <lb/>reveal such non-uniform signals. We therefore decided to investigate cfRNA profiles in <lb/>individual cancer patients using samples from the three-cancer cohort. <lb/>To capture aberrations in the cfRNA profile of an individual cancer patient, we compared the <lb/>mRNA abundance of a cancer plasma sample to the mRNA abundance distribution in the <lb/>entire control group, that served as a reference. More specifically, a z-score was calculated <lb/>for each mRNA based on the mean and standard deviation of the log2 normalized count <lb/>distribution in the control group. Abundant mRNAs with an absolute z-score of at least 3 were <lb/>defined as &quot;tail genes&quot; for that patient, referring to their position in one of the tails of the <lb/>control z-score distribution (Figure 5a). <lb/>We searched for tail genes in each cancer patient from the three-cancer cohort (where we <lb/>could take advantage of a large control group) and in each control sample, always using all <lb/>other control samples as reference (Supplemental Figure 12). We identified a total of 3312 <lb/>unique tail genes in this cohort and observed a significantly higher number of tail genes in <lb/>plasma samples from cancer patients compared to controls (Kruskal-Wallis p=0.0012, effect <lb/>size=0.222, Figure 5b). 74% of the tail genes were not identified as differentially abundant in <lb/>cancer samples versus controls (Figure 5c). Moreover, for 40.0% of cancer sample tail genes <lb/>that were differentially abundant between cancer and controls, the direction (i.e. positive or <lb/>negative z-score) in at least one cancer sample was opposite to the direction reported by the <lb/>differential abundance analysis, further highlighting the heterogeneity among patients. <lb/>Notably, the recurrence of tail genes was much higher in cancer samples than controls; 98% <lb/>of the control tail genes were identified in only one control sample while 47% of cancer tail <lb/>genes were identified in more than one cancer sample (Figure 5d). <lb/>To determine the significance of the observed results, we randomly swapped sample labels <lb/>prior to tail gene identification and repeated this procedure 20 times. Doing so, we did not <lb/>observe a significant difference in number of tail genes between the newly labeled cancer <lb/>samples and controls in any of the repeats (all Kruskal-Wallis p≥0.05), confirming that an <lb/>increased number of tail genes is specifically associated with cancer samples. <lb/>Tail genes detected in one cancer type showed significant overlap with tail genes detected in <lb/>another cancer type (Fisher&apos;s exact tests p≤5.4E-168, odds ratio: [11.1-15.2]), yet limited <lb/>similarity (Jaccard index: [19.7-34.8%]) (Figure 5e). The 1182 unique control tail genes also <lb/>showed significant overlap with any of the cancer tail gene subsets (pairwise Fisher exact tests <lb/>p: [5.9E-15 -8.5E-32], odds ratio: [2.1-2.5]) with less similarity (Jaccard index: [7.4-11.9%]). <lb/>63% of control tail genes were not identified as tail gene in any of the cancer samples. <lb/>Seven Cancer Gene Census oncogenes were identified as tail genes (z&gt;3) in at least one <lb/>sample, which is significantly more than expected by chance (Fisher&apos;s exact p=0.019, odds <lb/>ratio=3.13). While most oncogenes were only identified as tail gene in a single sample, KAT6A <lb/>was found in seven cancer samples (4 OV, 2 PRAD, and 1 UCEC) but also in one control sample. <lb/>Overrepresentation analyses (Supplemental Figure 13, Supplemental Table 5) demonstrated <lb/>that tail genes that are higher abundant in at least one cancer sample (z&gt;3) were involved in <lb/>different processes including platelet activation and signaling, actin binding and dynamics, <lb/>and extracellular matrix. Tail genes that are lower abundant in at least one cancer sample (z&lt;-<lb/>3) were mainly related to mRNA splicing and translation. Significantly enriched processes in <lb/>the cancer tail gene sets were not enriched in the control tail gene set, and processes enriched <lb/>in the lower abundant (cancer) tail genes showed higher recurrence across the three cancer <lb/>types compared to those enriched in the higher abundant tail genes. <lb/>Given the higher number of tail genes in cancer versus controls, we further assessed the <lb/>binary (cancer/control) classification potential of the number of tail genes per sample. We <lb/>first selected a subset of tail genes, further coined biomarker tail genes, that were significantly <lb/>associated to either the cancer or control state using leave-one-out Fisher exact tests (see <lb/>Methods for details). This resulted in 108 biomarker tail genes, with a significant difference <lb/>in number of biomarker tail genes in cancer and control samples (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-<lb/>sum p=3.1E-11, effect size=0.845). None of the biomarker tail genes were recurrent tail genes <lb/>in control samples and 54% were not identified as differentially abundant in any cancer type <lb/>compared to controls (Supplemental Figure 14). Applying the biomarker tail gene selection <lb/>strategy to the 20 datasets with randomly swapped sample labels resulted in considerably <lb/>fewer or no biomarker tail genes at all: between 0 and 7 biomarker tail genes (median: 2) <lb/>instead of 108. <lb/>When selecting biomarker tail genes in a specific cancer group versus controls, we obtained <lb/>143 biomarker tail genes for OV, 46 for PRAD, and 13 for UCEC. The difference in number of <lb/>biomarker tail genes between cancer and control samples per biomarker tail gene subset was <lb/>more significant than based on all tail genes (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum: for OV p=1.1E-7 <lb/>and effect size=0.864; for PRAD p=5.7E-8 and effect size=0.872; for UCEC p=1.4E-8 and effect <lb/>size=0.912) (Figure 5f). Note that the cancer type-specific biomarker tail gene sets showed <lb/>significant overlap (Fisher&apos;s exact p≤1.8E-3, odds ratio: [10.1-22.6]) with limited similarity <lb/>(Jaccard index: [2.6-9.9%]) (Figure 5h). <lb/>We then built a classifier for discriminating cancer and control samples based on the number <lb/>of biomarker tail genes in a particular sample. Using leave-one-out cross-validation, we <lb/>obtained perfect binary classification for ovarian or prostate cancer samples and controls <lb/>(AUC=1.000, based on 143 and 46 biomarker tail genes, resp.), and a high classification <lb/>performance for uterine cancer samples and controls (AUC=0.917, based on 13 biomarker tail <lb/>genes) (Figure 5g). The classification performance was still high when combining all cancer <lb/>samples (AUC=0.980, based on 108 biomarker tail genes). <lb/>Together, these analyses suggest that individual cancer samples can be distinguished from <lb/>controls based on the number of biomarker tail genes in their plasma cfRNA profiles. <lb/>Figure 5: Higher number of tail (biomarker) genes in cancer patient plasma samples compared to controls. a, <lb/>Tail gene identification workflow. A gene in a particular sample for which the abundance deviates more than 3 <lb/>standard deviations from the reference group abundance distribution is a tail gene for that sample. The number <lb/>of tail genes is used as a metric to determine cancer/control status. b, Boxplot of the number of tail genes per <lb/>group, with grey dots representing individual sample counts. Kruskal-Wallis p = 0.001, effect size = 0.222. Two-<lb/>sided Wilcoxon rank-sum q-values for specific cancer versus control comparisons indicated in the plot. c, Z-score <lb/>distribution of tail genes in the different samples, all 3312 genes that fulfilled tail gene criteria in at least one of <lb/>the samples are shown. For visualization purposes, z-scores above 5 or below -5 were reduced to 5 and -5, <lb/>respectively. Genes (rows) clustered based on Euclidean distance. d, Number of tail genes shared by a certain <lb/>fraction of samples of the same type. Number of samples indicated between brackets. e, Overlap between tail <lb/>genes detected in the different cancer types. f, Boxplot of number of biomarker tail genes per subset in control <lb/>(CONTROL) versus the respective cancer samples. Total number of biomarker tail genes considered for each <lb/>comparison: 108 for all cancer (n=35) versus control, 143 for OV versus control, 46 for PRAD versus control, 13 <lb/>for UCEC versus control. Grey dots represent individual sample counts. Two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum p-values <lb/>indicated in plot. g, ROC curve of leave-one-out cross-validated classifier for binary cancer/control classification <lb/>based on the number of biomarker tail genes for control and ovarian cancer samples (OV), prostate cancer <lb/>samples (PRAD), uterine cancer samples (UCEC), or all cancer samples (all) using the respective biomarker tail <lb/>gene sets. h, Overlap of cancer type-specific biomarker tail genes. Boxplots show lower quartile (Q1), median, <lb/>and upper quartile (Q3). Whiskers extend from the lower and upper quartile to the smallest and largest value, <lb/>respectively, within at most 1.5*interquartile range (Q3-Q1) from that quartile. More extreme points are plotted <lb/>as individual black dots. 62 plasma samples considered in total from 27 cancer-free controls (CONTROL), 11 <lb/>ovarian cancer (OV), 12 prostate cancer (PRAD), and 12 uterine cancer patients (UCEC). <lb/>To independently validate the classification potential of the number of biomarker tail genes, <lb/>we generated additional plasma cfRNA profiles (lymphoma cohort), including plasma samples <lb/>from 22 cancer-free control donors and 43 lymphoma patients, more specifically 30 diffuse <lb/>large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL) and 13 primary mediastinal large B-cell lymphoma (PMBCL) <lb/>patients. We identified 5374 unique tail genes, again with more tail genes in cancer samples <lb/>compared to controls (Kruskal-Wallis p=2.9E-5, effect size= 0.305, Supplemental Figure 15a). <lb/>All control tail genes were identified in only one control sample while 45.9% of DLBCL and <lb/>44.2% of PMBCL tail genes were identified in more than one DLBCL and PMBCL sample, <lb/>respectively (Supplemental Figure 15b). When swapping sample labels (20 repeats) prior to <lb/>tail gene identification, no significant differences in the number of tail genes between cancer <lb/>and control samples were observed in any of the repeats (Kruskal-Wallis p≥0.05). <lb/>Among the tail genes, 297 and 931 were identified as biomarker tail genes using leave-one-<lb/>out Fisher&apos;s exact tests for respectively DLBCL or PMBCL. The number of biomarker tail genes <lb/>was significantly higher in DLBCL and PMBCL compared to control samples (two-sided <lb/>Wilcoxon rank-sum: for DLBCL p=3.3E-9, effect size=0.822; for PMBCL p=1.7E-6, effect <lb/>size=0.811, Figure 6a). A binary classifier (cancer/control) based on biomarker tail genes with <lb/>leave-one-out cross-validation resulted in an AUC of 0.937 and 0.944 for DLBCL and PMBCL, <lb/>respectively (Figure 6b). 78% of the biomarker tail genes were not differentially abundant in <lb/>any lymphoma subtype versus controls. Notably, early-stage lymphoma patients also <lb/>displayed an increased number of biomarker tail genes (Figure 6c). Cancer diagnosis (i.e. <lb/>DLBCL or PMBCL) was the only factor significantly associated to the number of biomarker tail <lb/>genes (p=1.8E-4 and 3.1E-5 for DLBCL and PMBCL, respectively) in a generalized linear model <lb/>including diagnosis and tumor stage. <lb/>To test if our cancer-control classification strategy based on biomarker tail genes is also <lb/>applicable to other biofluids, we applied it to a cohort of urine cfRNA profiles (bladder cancer <lb/>cohort) 14 . This cohort included urine samples of 12 bladder cancer patients (BLCA) and 12 <lb/>cancer-free control donors. We identified 1152 tail genes of which 39 qualified as biomarker <lb/>tail gene. The number of biomarker tail genes was significantly higher in bladder cancer versus <lb/>controls (two-sided Wilcoxon rank-sum p=6.0E-5 and effect size=0.826, Figure 6d) and 62% <lb/>of biomarker tail genes were not differentially abundant between the cancer and control <lb/>group. In line with the other datasets, sample label swapping prior to tail gene identification <lb/>did not result in significant differences in the number of tail genes between the newly labeled <lb/>cancer samples and controls. A binary classifier based on biomarker tail genes with leave-one-<lb/>out cross-validation resulted in an AUC of 0.903 (Figure 6e). <lb/>Taken together, our results confirm that the number of biomarker tail genes in blood plasma <lb/>cfRNA enables accurate classification of cancer patients from controls and suggest that the <lb/>concept may also be applicable to cfRNA profiles from other biofluids. <lb/>Figure 6: Number of biomarker tail genes is significantly higher in cancer versus control samples in an <lb/>independent blood plasma and urine cohort. a-c, lymphoma cohort: plasma samples from 22 control, 30 diffuse <lb/>large B-cell lymphoma (DLBCL), and 13 primary mediastinal large B-cell lymphoma (PMBCL) patients. a, Boxplot <lb/>of number of biomarker tail genes in control versus the respective cancer samples. Total number of biomarker <lb/>tail genes considered for each comparison: 297 for DLBCL versus control, 931 for PMBCL versus control. Grey dots <lb/>represent individual sample counts. Wilcoxon rank-sum p-values indicated in plot. b, ROC curve of leave-one-out <lb/>cross-validated classifier for binary cancer/control classification based on the number of biomarker tail genes for <lb/>control and DLBCL, or control and PMBCL using the respective biomarker tail gene sets. c, Number of biomarker <lb/>tail genes of panel a visualized per cancer stage. d-e, bladder cancer cohort: urine samples from 12 control <lb/>(CONTROL) and 12 bladder cancer (BLCA) patients. d, Boxplot of number of biomarker tail genes in control versus <lb/>cancer samples. 39 biomarker tail genes considered in total. Wilcoxon rank-sum p-value indicated in the plot. e, <lb/>ROC curve of leave-one-out cross-validated classifier for binary cancer/control classification based on the number <lb/>of biomarker tail genes. Boxplots: lower quartile, median, upper quartile, whiskers of 1.5*interquartile range; <lb/>more extreme points are indicated by black dots. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In this study, we explored cancer-induced changes in blood plasma cfRNA profiles and <lb/>investigated if these changes could be exploited for classification purposes. Results from our <lb/>pan-cancer discovery cohort revealed that AML was the only cancer type for which we found <lb/>direct evidence for tumor-derived cfRNA in plasma in the form of PML::RARA fusion <lb/>transcripts. Also, deconvolution of AML plasma cfRNA revealed a high fraction of myeloid <lb/>progenitor cells, providing additional -albeit indirect -evidence for tumor-derived cfRNA. <lb/>For solid tumor types, we identified differentially abundant mRNAs in plasma for every cancer <lb/>versus control comparison, but a cancer type-specific signal was only observed in plasma from <lb/>liver cancer patients through the enrichment of liver-specific gene sets. Liver is a major <lb/>contributor to the plasma transcriptome 4 and its high vascularization and blood flow may <lb/>facilitate mRNA release in blood upon liver cancer progression. Increased cfDNA contributions <lb/>from the liver have also been observed in liver cancer patients 15 . Note that, despite the <lb/>enrichment of liver-related mRNAs, the total cfRNA concentration was not increased in <lb/>plasma from liver cancer patients, indicating that this signal was still strongly diluted. <lb/>Considering the organ contribution and dilution argument, other types of liquid biopsies may <lb/>be better suited to monitor tumor-derived cfRNA for other cancer types. For instance, we <lb/>could not detect enrichment of prostate tissue-related nor prostate cancer-specific <lb/>transcripts in blood plasma from prostate cancer patients, in contrast to earlier findings in <lb/>seminal plasma samples 16 . <lb/>We did observe several general trends in patients&apos; blood plasma transcriptomes in the pan-<lb/>cancer cohort, which were confirmed in an independent cohort. The lower abundance of <lb/>immune-related mRNAs may be linked to the suppressed immune system status in cancer <lb/>patients. It was recently shown that local tumors can have a systemic impact on the immune <lb/>system, and that different tumor sites of origin resulted in distinct relative abundances and <lb/>activity profiles of immune cell types 17 . This may be linked to the observed variations in <lb/>immune-related mRNA abundance, both between and within cancer types. The (immune) <lb/>cell-related mRNA contributions agreed with reported cell abundance trends found in blood <lb/>from several cancer patients 18 , with the exception of neutrophil-related mRNAs that are <lb/>lower abundant in plasma. However, neutrophils can have a dual role in cancer 19 and reduced <lb/>neutrophil cell-free mRNA abundance may result from neutrophils specifically recruited to <lb/>tumor sites. Finally, the negative enrichment of blood/erythrocyte gene sets may be linked to <lb/>anemia, a common condition in cancer patients. Among the processes that we found <lb/>positively enriched in cancer patient plasma, some are linked to hallmarks for cancer <lb/>progression and metastasis, including epithelial-to-mesenchymal transition and increased <lb/>blood vessel signal that stem from leaky vasculature and angiogenesis 20 . <lb/>A limitation of the pan-cancer cohort is that control samples were not always perfectly age <lb/>and sex-matched. The anaplastic astrocytoma, cervical cancer, and testicular germ cell tumor <lb/>patients were younger as these types predominantly appear at younger age. A dedicated <lb/>cohort with matched control samples may be better for exposing cancer-related changes in <lb/>these cancer types. Similarly, while male and female donors were balanced in the control <lb/>group, this was not always possible for the different cancer types due to sex-specificity (e.g. <lb/>prostate, testicular, breast, cervical, and ovarian cancer) or sample availability. Nevertheless, <lb/>at most 4 out of 8 donors were not sex-matched in cancer vs control group comparisons in <lb/>the pan-cancer cohort, and our main conclusions were not impacted when only using controls <lb/>of the same sex in the three-cancer cohort. Another limitation is the relatively small sample <lb/>size per cancer type, which might contribute to false positives and insufficient power to detect <lb/>true differences. <lb/>The variable mRNA abundance in plasma, combined with the limited overlap of differentially <lb/>abundant mRNAs across cohorts of the same cancer type prompted an alternative approach <lb/>that can effectively deal with patient heterogeneity. The tail gene concept satisfies this <lb/>requirement by identifying mRNAs whose abundance in individual samples significantly <lb/>deviates from the abundance distribution in a reference group. While the dark channel <lb/>biomarker gene concept 4 is in part based on a more patient-centric approach, it also requires <lb/>differential abundance at group level to be considered potential biomarkers. Moreover, the <lb/>dark channel concept specifically looks at genes that are absent (dark) in control samples and <lb/>therefore cannot capture changes in transcript abundance of genes that are also present in <lb/>healthy plasma transcriptomes. Of note, 19 dark channel biomarker genes were identified for <lb/>lung and breast cancer by Larson et al. 4 but five of those genes could be readily detected in <lb/>control samples from our cohorts, indicating that the &quot;darkness&quot; (i.e. absence of gene <lb/>transcripts in control samples) should be re-evaluated in different cohorts. <lb/>Tail gene counting is a simple metric for classifying samples as cancer or controls. Considering <lb/>that it is not based on gene signatures with weighted contributions of individual features, we <lb/>believe it could be more robust and compatible with observed patient heterogeneity. <lb/>Nevertheless, it requires a large and representative group of cancer-free control samples. A <lb/>control group only needs to be established once, if the entire workflow -from sample <lb/>collection to RNA-sequencing -is standardized across cancer and control samples. This <lb/>approach should minimize the introduction of batch effects that may skew cfRNA <lb/>distributions between a pre-established cohort of cancer-free controls and newly profiled <lb/>cancer or control samples. In this regard, our group has demonstrated that preanalytical <lb/>variables (blood collection tube, time between blood collection and plasma preparation, RNA <lb/>extraction kit) can indeed dramatically impact cfRNA profiles 21 . <lb/>Deviations in the number of tail genes is not necessarily restricted to cancer patients, nor to <lb/>blood plasma. Indeed, cfRNA from urine provides a good source of biomarker tail genes to <lb/>identify bladder cancer patients. Other diseases may be characterized by an increase in tail <lb/>genes, although the specific tail (biomarker) genes may differ. Further studies are needed to <lb/>examine the applicability and overlap of tail genes in non-malignant disease cohorts. Similarly, <lb/>while we have preliminary evidence that biomarker tail genes are also significantly more <lb/>numerous in low stage patients, additional follow-up studies comprising different stages <lb/>across various cancer types could reveal whether the concept is suited for early-stage cancer <lb/>screening or monitoring. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Sample cohorts <lb/>The study was approved by the ethics committee of Ghent University Hospital, Belgium (no. <lb/>B670201734362) and performed in accordance with the Declaration of Helsinki. <lb/>Pan-cancer plasma and three-cancer cohort <lb/>Blood plasma samples of 266 human donors were obtained from Proteogenex (CA, USA) with <lb/>informed consent from all donors. The pan-cancer discovery cohort covers 25 different cancer <lb/>types and a cancer-free control group. For each type, plasma was collected from 8 different <lb/>donors. The three-cancer cohort consisted of prostate cancer (PRAD), ovarian cancer (OV), <lb/>and endometrial cancer (UCEC) plasma samples, with 12 donors per type. This cohort also <lb/>included plasma samples from the 8 control donors of the pan-cancer cohort as well as from <lb/>22 additional control donors. For independent validation of pan-cancer results, only the <lb/>control samples from the additional control donors were used. For tail gene discovery, all <lb/>control samples in the three-cancer cohort were used. <lb/>All cancer patients in both cohorts had locally advanced (stage 3) to metastatic cancer (stage <lb/>4), except for 6 seminoma patients (stage 1). Blood was drawn before treatment with 6 <lb/>exceptions: 4 glioblastoma patients (grade 4-5) already received chemo and radiation <lb/>therapy, one prostate cancer patient with metastasis received hormone therapy, and one <lb/>melanoma patient with metastasis received immunotherapy. Demographic and clinical <lb/>information can be found in Supplemental Table 1. <lb/>Lymphoma cohort <lb/>The lymphoma cohort consisted of plasma samples from 65 human donors: 30 DLBCL <lb/>patients, 13 PMBCL patients, and 22 cancer-free control donors. Plasma samples were <lb/>collected following approval by the ethics committee of Ghent University Hospital, Belgium <lb/>(B670201733701), and written, informed consent was obtained from all patients. <lb/>Bladder cancer cohort <lb/>The bladder cancer cohort is described in more detail elsewhere 14 . This cohort consists of <lb/>urine samples from 12 muscle-invasive bladder cancer patients and 12 control donors. <lb/>Blood collection and plasma preparation <lb/>Blood from the pan-cancer and three-cancer cohort donors was collected in EDTA vacutainer <lb/>tubes (Becton Dickinson, 367525). Blood was stored at 4 °C until plasma preparation which <lb/>started by gently inverting the EDTA tube 10 times and centrifugating for 10 min at 1500 g <lb/>(without brake at 4 °C). Supernatans was then transferred to 15 mL centrifuge tubes and <lb/>centrifuged again for 10 min at 1500 g (without brake at 4 °C). The resulting platelet depleted <lb/>plasma was transferred to 2 mL cryovials, frozen and stored at -80 °C within 4 hours of blood <lb/>collection. Plasma samples were shipped on dry ice and only thawed on ice immediately <lb/>before RNA isolation. <lb/>For the lymphoma cohort, 2.5 mL of blood was collected from each donor in PAXgene Blood <lb/>DNA Tubes (BD Biosciences, 761165). Plasma was prepared by a one-step 15 min <lb/>centrifugation at 1900 g without brake (room temperature) and stored at -80 °C within 4 <lb/>hours of blood collection. <lb/>RNA isolation and gDNA removal <lb/>RNA was isolated from 200 µL of plasma with the miRNeasy Serum/Plasma kit (Qiagen, <lb/>217184), according to the manufacturer&apos;s instructions. For the pan-cancer and three-cancer <lb/>cohort, 2 µL Sequin spike-in controls (1/1,300,000 of stock solutions mix A, Garvan Institute <lb/>of Medical Research, Australia) was added to the lysate during RNA isolation as previously <lb/>described 22 . For the lymphoma cohort, 2 µL of Sequin spike-in controls were added to the <lb/>sample lysates (1/5000 of stock solution mix A (Garvan Institute of Medical Research) and 2 <lb/>µL of External RNA Control Consortium (ERCC) spike-in controls (ThermoFisher Scientific, <lb/>4456740) were added to 12 µl RNA eluate. <lb/>Genomic DNA was removed by adding 1 μL HL-dsDNase (ArcticZymes, 70800-202) and 1.6 µL <lb/>reaction buffer (ArcticZymes, 66001) to 12 µL RNA eluate, 10 min incubation at 37 °C, followed <lb/>by 5 min incubation at 55 °C. RNA was stored at -80 °C and thawed on ice immediately before <lb/>library preparation. <lb/>Messenger RNA capture library preparation, sequencing, and quantification <lb/>MRNA capture library preparation in pan-cancer and three-cancer cohorts started from 8.5 <lb/>µL DNase treated RNA eluate. cDNA synthesis was performed using TruSeq RNA Library Prep <lb/>for Enrichment (Illumina, 20020189) as previously described 22 . Briefly, RNA was fragmented, <lb/>and first strand cDNA was generated using random priming. RNA templates were <lb/>subsequently removed and replaced by a newly synthesized second strand of cDNA. AMPure <lb/>XP beads (Beckman Coulter Life Sciences, A63881) were used for purifying the blunt-ended <lb/>double stranded cDNA. 30 μL cDNA of each sample was then used as input for Illumina DNA <lb/>Prep with Enrichment (previously Nextera Flex for Enrichment; Illumina, 20025524). <lb/>Tagmentation and amplification steps were done according to manufacturer&apos;s instructions. <lb/>Quality of resulting pre-enriched libraries was assessed using a high sensitivity Small DNA <lb/>Fragment Analysis Kit (Agilent Technologies, DNF-477-0500). The libraries were randomly <lb/>pooled per 8 or 6 samples, for the pan-cancer and three-cancer cohort, respectively, based <lb/>on their relative concentrations determined using qPCR for reference genes YWHAZ, ACTB, <lb/>B2M, and UBC. Each multiplex pool was concentrated to a volume of 15 µL with AMPure XP <lb/>beads (Beckman Coulter Life Sciences, A63881). Finally, enrichment was performed using <lb/>probes from the Illumina Exome Panel (Illumina, 20020183), probes complementary to the <lb/>spike-in controls, and blocking probes against globin (anti-CEX) as previously described 22 . At <lb/>the end of the enrichment workflow, equimolar library pools were prepared based on qPCR <lb/>quantification with KAPA Library Quantification Kit (Roche Diagnostics, KK4854). <lb/>Paired-end sequencing of both cohorts was performed (2x100 nucleotides) on a NovaSeq <lb/>6000. For the pan-cancer cohort, a NovaSeq S2 kit (Illumina, 20028315) was used with <lb/>standard workflow loading of 1.55 nM (1% PhiX). For the three-cancer cohort, a NovaSeq S1 <lb/>kit (Illumina, 20028318) was used with Xp workflow loading of 1.25 nM (2% PhiX). <lb/>Adapter trimming and removal of reads shorter than 20 nucleotides was done with cutadapt <lb/>(v1.18). Read quality was assessed with FastQC (v0.11.9) and low-quality reads were filtered: <lb/>only reads where at least 80% of bases in both mates have a quality score ≥20 (99% accuracy) <lb/>were kept (between 87 and 99% of reads/sample). Samples with very few reads (&lt; 2M) were <lb/>removed from all analyses. More specifically, 4 samples were removed in the pan cancer <lb/>plasma cohort (1 lymphoma, 1 bladder, 1 head and neck, and 1 lung cancer sample) and 4 <lb/>samples in the three-cancer cohort (3 control samples, of which 1 repeated from first cohort, <lb/>and 1 ovarian cancer) as indicated in Supplemental Table 1. Quality filtered reads were then <lb/>mapped with STAR 23 (v2.6.0) using the default parameters (except for --twopassMode Basic, <lb/>--outFilterMatchNmin 20 and --outSAMprimaryFlag AllBestScore). The reference files for all <lb/>analyses were based on genome build GRCh38 and transcriptome build Ensembl v91, <lb/>complemented with spike annotations. Finally, gene counts were determined with HTSeq 24 <lb/>(v0.11.0) in non-stranded mode, only considering uniquely mapping reads. <lb/>Total RNA library preparation, sequencing, and quantification <lb/>Total RNA sequencing libraries of the lymphoma cohort were prepared starting from 8 µL of <lb/>RNA eluate using the SMARTer Stranded Total RNA-Seq Kit v3 -Pico Input Mammalian <lb/>(Takara, 634487) according to the manufacturer&apos;s protocol. Equimolar library pools were <lb/>prepared based on qPCR quantification with KAPA Library Quantification Kit (Roche <lb/>Diagnostics, KK4854). The libraries were paired-end sequenced (2x100 nucleotides) on a <lb/>NovaSeq 6000 instrument using a NovaSeq S2 kit (Illumina, 20028315) with standard <lb/>workflow loading of 0.65 nM (2% PhiX). <lb/>After adapter trimming with cutadapt (v1.18) and quality control with FASTQC (v0.11.9), <lb/>reads were mapped with STAR 23 (v2.7.3) using default options and the GRCh38 reference <lb/>described above. Resulting BAM files were deduplicated using UMI-tools (v1.0.0) based on <lb/>the unique molecular identifier (UMI) sequences in the Pico v3 SMART UMI adapters. Gene <lb/>counts were determined with HTSeq 24 (v0.11.0) in reverse stranded mode, only considering <lb/>uniquely mapping reads. <lb/>Data analyses <lb/>Most data processing and visualization was done in R (v4.2.1) using tidyverse (v1.3.2) and <lb/>pheatmap (v1.0.12). Other tools and R packages used for specific analyses are mentioned <lb/>below. Color schemes are based on Paul Tol&apos;s technical note 25 . <lb/>Detection threshold <lb/>To remove noisy datapoints, we applied a threshold of at least 10 counts. This threshold was <lb/>based on the median threshold that removes at least 95% of single positive genes 26 -genes <lb/>that have counts in one replicate but not in the other -between control samples. <lb/>MRNA concentration <lb/>MRNA concentration was determined as previously described 22 . Briefly, the mass of a specific <lb/>Sequin spike-in control was calculated based on the input concentration and volume of spike-<lb/>in mix added to the sample. The corresponding mRNA concentration was then estimated by <lb/>multiplying the spike mass by the ratio of reads mapped to the human genome versus the <lb/>number of reads mapped to the specific spike, and finally dividing the obtained mass by the <lb/>plasma volume of the sample. In this study, all spikes above detection threshold were <lb/>considered and the geometric mean per sample was taken as the sample&apos;s mRNA <lb/>concentration. <lb/>Fusion gene detection <lb/>FusionCatcher 27 (v1.30) was used with default settings for fusion transcript identification. <lb/>Stringent filtering was applied to exclude potential false positives: transcripts with a <lb/>FusionCatcher label indicative for false positives, transcripts with reads simultaneously <lb/>mapping to both fusion partners, and transcripts with fusion partners less than 100 kbp apart <lb/>were filtered out. Only exon-exon fusions were included and detected fusions in plasma were <lb/>compared to fusions in the Fusion Gene annotation DataBase (FusionGDB) 28 , focusing on <lb/>fusion genes identified in tissue samples of The Cancer Genome Atlas 29 . <lb/>Differential abundance and principal component analysis <lb/>DESeq2 (v1.36.0) was used for normalization and differential abundance analysis. MRNAs <lb/>were pre-filtered by requiring gene counts equal to or greater than the detection threshold <lb/>in at least half of the tumor or half of the control samples. In the DESeq2 result table, genes <lb/>with a Benjamini-Hochberg corrected p-value (q) below 0.05 and an absolute log2 fold change <lb/>above 1 were considered differentially abundant. Principal component analysis was <lb/>performed with DESeq2 plotPCA on the 500 most variable genes after applying variance <lb/>stabilizing transformation. Volcano plots were visualized using EnhancedVolcano (v1.14.0) <lb/>and area-proportional Euler diagrams were made using eulerr (v6.1.1). Differential <lb/>abundance analysis results are freely available at Zenodo (doi:10.5281/zenodo.7953707). <lb/>Gene set enrichment and overrepresentation <lb/>Fgsea 30 (v1.22.0) was used for preranked gene set enrichment analysis based on log2 <lb/>transformed fold changes between cancer and controls obtained from DESeq2 differential <lb/>abundance analysis. Significant enrichment was defined by a false discovery rate ≤ 0.05. <lb/>Hallmark 9 and Canonical Pathways gene sets derived from Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and <lb/>Genomes (KEGG) 10 , http://www.pathway.jp, were obtained via the Molecular Signatures <lb/>Database, MSigDB (v2022.1) 31 . Besides these MSigDB gene sets, custom tissue and cell type <lb/>specific gene sets were made using inhouse and external references as described below. Gene <lb/>set enrichment analysis results and custom gene sets are available at Zenodo <lb/>(doi:10.5281/zenodo.7953707). Functional analysis of mRNA sets was done using the <lb/>functional annotation tool of DAVID (v2021) 32,33 and -for custom gene sets -the fora function <lb/>of fgsea. For each functional analysis, a background was provided which included all mRNAs <lb/>satisfying the count threshold in at least one sample. <lb/>RNA Atlas cell type gene sets <lb/>These cell type gene sets were defined based on total RNA sequencing data of cells and cell <lb/>lines in the RNA Atlas 34 . Protein coding gene inclusion criteria were an expression of at least <lb/>16 counts after variance stabilizing transformation and an expression fold change of at least <lb/>10 compared to the cell type with second highest expression. 15 out of 32 defined cell type <lb/>sets included more than 5 genes. <lb/>Tabula Sapiens cell type gene sets <lb/>These cell type gene sets were based on the Tabula Sapiens v1 basis matrix defined by <lb/>Vorperian et al 2 . Protein coding genes with at least 5 CPM and an expression fold change of <lb/>at least 10 compared to the cell type with the second highest expression were retained. 13 <lb/>out of 39 defined cell type gene sets included more than 5 genes. <lb/>GTEX tissue gene sets <lb/>These tissue gene sets were defined using SPECS specificity scores 35 of GTEx 36 tissue samples, <lb/>summarized in https://specs.cmgg.be. Criteria for protein coding gene inclusion in a certain <lb/>tissue gene set were a SPECS score ≥ 0.98 and a median TPM ≥ 5. Large gene sets were <lb/>reduced to the top 200 genes based on the highest SPECS score. 23 out of 27 defined tissues <lb/>gene sets included more than 5 genes. <lb/>HPA-RNA Atlas tissue gene sets <lb/>These tissue gene sets were defined based on expression data from the Human Protein Atlas 37 <lb/>(HPA, v18, https://v18.proteinatlas.org/) in combination with total RNA-sequencing data <lb/>from the RNA Atlas 34 . Human Protein Atlas protein coding genes needed to have a TPM value <lb/>of at least 5 and expression that is at least 10 times higher in the tissue with highest expression <lb/>compared to the tissue with second highest expression. These genes sets were further <lb/>finetuned by only keeping those genes with the highest expression in the same tissue in the <lb/>RNA Atlas dataset. Finally, large gene sets were reduced to the top 200 genes based on the <lb/>highest fold changes. 15 out of 18 defined tissue gene sets included more than 5 genes. <lb/>TCGA cancer tissue gene sets <lb/>These gene sets were defined similarly to the GTEX gene sets but using expression in The <lb/>Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) cancer tissue samples, generated by the TCGA Research <lb/>Network: https://www.cancer.gov/tcga. Protein coding genes with a SPECS score of at least <lb/>0.98 in a certain tissue were included in the gene set with a limit of 200 genes, based on <lb/>highest SPECS score. 19 out of 23 defined cancer tissue gene sets included more than 5 genes. <lb/>Cell type deconvolution <lb/>NuSVR deconvolution using the Tabula Sapiens v1 basis matrix was performed as described <lb/>by <lb/>Vorperian <lb/>et <lb/>al. 2 <lb/>and <lb/>the <lb/>accompanying <lb/>GitHub <lb/>repository, <lb/>https://github.com/sevahn/deconvolution. As recommended by the authors, data was CPM <lb/>normalized and no log transformation was performed. Note that the erythrocyte fraction is <lb/>underestimated due to the absence of hemoglobin probes in mRNA capture sequencing. <lb/>Tail genes <lb/>To identify tail genes, transcript counts of every sample were first converted to a customized <lb/>z score based on the mean and standard deviation in the reference group, including all control <lb/>samples except the sample of interest. More specifically, a pseudocount was added to all <lb/>normalized transcript counts followed by log2 transformation. Then, for each gene, the mean <lb/>and standard deviation of these transformed counts in the reference group was used to scale <lb/>the transformed counts in the sample of interest. <lb/>Tail genes were then defined as genes with at least 40 counts after DESeq2 normalization and <lb/>deviating more than 3 standard deviations from the mean of the control reference (|z|&gt;3). <lb/>For each gene in a sample of interest: <lb/>𝑧𝑠𝑐𝑜𝑟𝑒 !&quot;#&quot; = <lb/>𝑙𝑜𝑔 $ *𝑛𝑜𝑟𝑚𝑎𝑙𝑖𝑧𝑒𝑑 𝑐𝑜𝑢𝑛𝑡𝑠 !&quot;#&quot; + 15 -𝑟𝑒𝑓 88888 !&quot;#&quot; <lb/>𝑆𝐷 %&quot;&amp; !&quot;#&quot; <lb/>where 𝑟𝑒𝑓 <lb/>88888 !&quot;#&quot; and 𝑆𝐷 %&quot;&amp; !&quot;#&quot; are respectively the mean and standard deviation of log2 <lb/>transformed counts for this gene over all (other) control samples. <lb/>Fisher&apos;s exact tests (based on |z|&gt;3 and donor cancer/control status) were used to select a <lb/>subset of tail genes, named biomarker tail genes, that are specifically associated to the <lb/>disease state. To avoid selection being biased by individual samples, Fisher&apos;s exact testing for <lb/>each tail gene was done iteratively, each time leaving out a different sample, and a tail gene <lb/>needed to be significant (p&lt;0.05) in every iteration to be called a biomarker tail gene. As a <lb/>result, the tail gene needs to be recurrent in at least two samples. <lb/>Binary logistic regression, R glm function with binomial family, was used to classify a sample <lb/>as cancer or control based on the number of biomarker tail genes. Leave-one-out cross-<lb/>validation was used by iteratively leaving out a different sample from the training set and <lb/>testing the model on this sample. Based on these predictions, the Receiver Operating <lb/>Characteristic (ROC) curve and Area Under Curve (AUC) were calculated and visualized using <lb/>pROC (v1.18.0) 38 . <lb/>For internal validation, all sample labels were randomly reshuffled using the sample function <lb/>in R without replacement. Next, tail gene identification and evaluation was repeated based <lb/>on the new class labels (using the new control samples as reference). This process was <lb/>repeated 20 times. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>Kruskal-Wallis tests were used to compare multiple groups, and Wilcoxon rank-sum tests <lb/>were used to compare two groups. Corresponding statistical significance and effect sizes were <lb/>calculated with rstatix (v0.7.2). For individual testing, p-values smaller than 0.05 were <lb/>considered significant. In case of multiple testing, the Benjamini-Hochberg procedure was <lb/>used to calculate false discovery rate adjusted p-values (q-values) and significance was <lb/>defined as q smaller than 0.05. <lb/>Significance of overlap between gene sets was determined by Fisher&apos;s exact test in <lb/>GeneOverlap (v1.32.0). The universe consisted of all genes considered for the corresponding <lb/>differential abundance or tail gene analyses (see filtering above). A Jaccard index was <lb/>calculated to assess similarity between the gene sets, with 0% indicating no similarity and <lb/>100% indicating identical sets. <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>Raw RNA-sequencing data is available under restricted access (access can be requested) in <lb/>the European Genome-phenome Archive (EGA) to preserve individuals&apos; privacy and comply <lb/>with patient consent for data sharing under the European General Data Protection <lb/>Regulation. The pan-cancer and three-cancer cohort FASTQs can be found under study <lb/>EGAS00001006755 (dataset EGAD00001009713). The lymphoma cohort FASTQs can be found <lb/>under study EGAS00001007127 (dataset EGAD00001010259). The bladder cancer cohort <lb/>FASTQs can be found under study EGAS00001003917 (dataset EGAD00001005439). <lb/>Differential abundance and gene set enrichment analysis results are available (open access) <lb/>in a Zenodo repository (doi:10.5281/zenodo.7953707). <lb/>Code availability <lb/>Code for differential abundance and tail gene analyses is available on GitHub at <lb/>https://github.com/OncoRNALab/tailgenes. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Figures 1a and 5b were created with BioRender.com. We would like to thank Tim Mercer for <lb/>providing the Sequin spikes, Eva Hulstaert and Francisco Avila Cobos for their support during <lb/>the first phase of the project, and Anneleen Decock for her feedback on the initial draft. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>This work was supported by Ghent University (BOF; BOF19/DOC/228), Ghent University <lb/>Hospital, Fund for Scientific Research Flanders (FWO; 11C1623N to A.M., 11H7523N to P.D., <lb/>G0B2820N), and Kom Op Tegen Kanker (Stand up to Cancer, the Flemish cancer society). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflict of interest <lb/>A.M., J.V. and P.M. are inventors on a patent application regarding the tail gene concept. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Pessoa, L. S., Heringer, M. &amp; Ferrer, V. P. ctDNA as a cancer biomarker: A broad overview. <lb/>Critical Reviews in Oncology/Hematology 155, 103109 (2020). <lb/>2. Vorperian, S. K., Moufarrej, M. N. &amp; Quake, S. R. Cell types of origin of the cell-free <lb/>transcriptome. Nat Biotechnol 40, 855-861 (2022). <lb/>3. Moufarrej, M. N. et al. Early prediction of preeclampsia in pregnancy with cell-free RNA. <lb/>Nature 602, 689-694 (2022). <lb/>4. Larson, M. H. et al. A comprehensive characterization of the cell-free transcriptome <lb/>reveals tissue-and subtype-specific biomarkers for cancer detection. Nat Commun 12, <lb/>2357 (2021). <lb/>5. Chen, S. et al. Cancer type classification using plasma cell-free RNAs derived from human <lb/>and microbes. eLife 11, e75181 (2022). <lb/>6. Roskams-Hieter, B. et al. Plasma cell-free RNA profiling distinguishes cancers from pre-<lb/>malignant conditions in solid and hematologic malignancies. npj Precis. Onc. 6, 1-11 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>7. Bryzgunova, O. E., Konoshenko, M. Y. &amp; Laktionov, P. P. Concentration of cell-free DNA in <lb/>different tumor types. Expert Review of Molecular Diagnostics 21, 63-75 (2021). <lb/>8. Liquori, A. et al. Acute Promyelocytic Leukemia: A Constellation of Molecular Events <lb/>around a Single PML-RARA Fusion Gene. Cancers (Basel) 12, 624 (2020). <lb/>9. Liberzon, A. et al. The Molecular Signatures Database (MSigDB) hallmark gene set <lb/>collection. Cell Syst 1, 417-425 (2015). <lb/>10. Kanehisa, M. &amp; Goto, S. KEGG: Kyoto Encyclopedia of Genes and Genomes. Nucleic Acids <lb/>Research 28, 27-30 (2000). <lb/>11. Khwaja, A. et al. Acute myeloid leukaemia. Nat Rev Dis Primers 2, 1-22 (2016). <lb/>12. Giannakeas, V. et al. Analysis of Platelet Count and New Cancer Diagnosis Over a 10-Year <lb/>Period. JAMA Network Open 5, e2141633 (2022). <lb/>13. Haemmerle, M., Stone, R. L., Menter, D. G., Afshar-Kharghan, V. &amp; Sood, A. K. The Platelet <lb/>Lifeline to Cancer: Challenges and Opportunities. Cancer Cell 33, 965-983 (2018). <lb/>14. Hulstaert, E. et al. Charting Extracellular Transcriptomes in The Human Biofluid RNA Atlas. <lb/>Cell Reports 33, 108552 (2020). <lb/>15. Sun, K. et al. Plasma DNA tissue mapping by genome-wide methylation sequencing for <lb/>noninvasive prenatal, cancer, and transplantation assessments. Proceedings of the <lb/>National Academy of Sciences 112, E5503-E5512 (2015). <lb/>16. Hulstaert, E. et al. Exploring the extracellular transcriptome in seminal plasma for non-<lb/>invasive <lb/>prostate <lb/>cancer <lb/>diagnosis. <lb/>2021.05.11.21256306 <lb/>Preprint <lb/>at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.21256306 (2021). <lb/>17. Allen, B. M. et al. Systemic dysfunction and plasticity of the immune macroenvironment <lb/>in cancer models. Nat Med 26, 1125-1134 (2020). <lb/>18. Hiam-Galvez, K. J., Allen, B. M. &amp; Spitzer, M. H. Systemic immunity in cancer. Nat Rev <lb/>Cancer 21, 345-359 (2021). <lb/>19. Xiong, S., Dong, L. &amp; Cheng, L. Neutrophils in cancer carcinogenesis and metastasis. <lb/>Journal of Hematology &amp; Oncology 14, 173 (2021). <lb/>20. Lugano, R., Ramachandran, M. &amp; Dimberg, A. Tumor angiogenesis: causes, consequences, <lb/>challenges and opportunities. Cell. Mol. Life Sci. 77, 1745-1770 (2020). <lb/>21. Consortium, exRNAQC et al. Performance of RNA purification kits and blood collection <lb/>tubes in the Extracellular RNA Quality Control (exRNAQC) study. 2021.05.11.442610 <lb/>Preprint at https://doi.org/10.1101/2021.05.11.442610 (2021). <lb/>22. Hulstaert, E. et al. Messenger RNA capture sequencing of extracellular RNA from human <lb/>biofluids using a comprehensive set of spike-in controls. STAR Protocols 2, 100475 (2021). <lb/>23. Dobin, A. et al. STAR: ultrafast universal RNA-seq aligner. Bioinformatics 29, 15-21 (2013). <lb/>24. Anders, S., Pyl, P. T. &amp; Huber, W. HTSeq-a Python framework to work with high-<lb/>throughput sequencing data. Bioinformatics 31, 166-169 (2015). <lb/>25. Tol, P. Colour Schemes, Technical Note SRON/EPS/TN/09-002. (2012). <lb/>26. Mestdagh, P. et al. Evaluation of quantitative miRNA expression platforms in the <lb/>microRNA quality control (miRQC) study. Nature Methods 11, 809-815 (2014). <lb/>27. Nicorici, D. et al. FusionCatcher -a tool for finding somatic fusion genes in paired-end <lb/>RNA-sequencing data. 011650 Preprint at https://doi.org/10.1101/011650 (2014). <lb/>28. Kim, P. &amp; Zhou, X. FusionGDB: fusion gene annotation DataBase. Nucleic Acids Research <lb/>47, D994-D1004 (2019). <lb/>29. Gao, Q. et al. Driver Fusions and Their Implications in the Development and Treatment of <lb/>Human Cancers. Cell Reports 23, 227-238.e3 (2018). <lb/>30. Korotkevich, G. et al. Fast gene set enrichment analysis. 060012 Preprint at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/060012 (2021). <lb/>31. Subramanian, A. et al. Gene set enrichment analysis: A knowledge-based approach for <lb/>interpreting genome-wide expression profiles. Proceedings of the National Academy of <lb/>Sciences 102, 15545-15550 (2005). <lb/>32. Huang, D. W., Sherman, B. T. &amp; Lempicki, R. A. Systematic and integrative analysis of large <lb/>gene lists using DAVID bioinformatics resources. Nat Protoc 4, 44-57 (2009). <lb/>33. Sherman, B. T. et al. DAVID: a web server for functional enrichment analysis and <lb/>functional annotation of gene lists (2021 update). Nucleic Acids Res 50, W216-W221 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>34. Lorenzi, L. et al. The RNA Atlas expands the catalog of human non-coding RNAs. Nat <lb/>Biotechnol 39, 1453-1465 (2021). <lb/>35. Everaert, C., Volders, P.-J., Morlion, A., Thas, O. &amp; Mestdagh, P. SPECS: a non-parametric <lb/>method to identify tissue-specific molecular features for unbalanced sample groups. BMC <lb/>Bioinformatics 21, 58 (2020). <lb/>36. Lonsdale, J. et al. The Genotype-Tissue Expression (GTEx) project. Nat Genet 45, 580-585 <lb/>(2013). <lb/>37. Uhlén, M. et al. Tissue-based map of the human proteome. Science 347, 1260419 (2015). <lb/>38. Robin, X. et al. pROC: an open-source package for R and S+ to analyze and compare ROC <lb/>curves. BMC Bioinformatics 12, 77 (2011). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
