<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Iodocyclization in Aqueous Media and Supramolecular Reaction <lb/>Control Using Water-Soluble Hosts <lb/>Treyvon Bokoskie, † Christopher Cunningham, ‡ Cory Kornman, ‡ Tanay Kesharwani,* , ‡ <lb/>and Mahesh Pattabiraman* , † <lb/> † <lb/>Department of Chemistry, University of Nebraska Kearney, Kearney, Nebraska 68849, United States <lb/> ‡ <lb/>Department of Chemistry, University of West Florida, Pensacola, Florida 32514, United States <lb/>* S Supporting Information <lb/>ABSTRACT: Iodocyclization of 2-alkynylanisoles is an efficient route for <lb/>synthesizing substituted benzofurans. Reaction efficiency with copper(II) sulfate <lb/>and sodium iodide in an aqueous slurry under mild conditions is a manifold higher <lb/>than in organic solvents. Water-soluble hosts of the cyclodextrin family solubilize <lb/>the compounds in aqueous media and affect the reaction efficiency through <lb/>conformation control and steric interactions. Computational chemistry and <lb/>spectral titration provide information on the host-guest complex structure and <lb/>insight into the mechanistic basis of the observed effects. <lb/></front>

			<body>■ INTRODUCTION <lb/>Benzo[b]furans are frequently encountered structural cores in <lb/>natural compounds 1-4 and bioactive molecules. 5-11 The <lb/>significance of the benzofuran framework is evidenced from <lb/>its ubiquity in plant products and prevalence as the central <lb/>structures of several biomolecules, especially antimicro-<lb/>bials, 12-14 analgesics, 15,16 and anti-inflammatory agents. 7,17 <lb/>This biologically useful heterocyclic core structure is also part <lb/>of several drug molecules (Figure 1). 6,18,19 Given its practical <lb/>significance, there is strong justification for the development of <lb/>new and efficient synthetic routes to access benzofurans, <lb/>especially in an environmentally benign and sustainable <lb/>manner. Currently, there are several synthetic routes reported <lb/>in the synthetic organic chemistry literature for these <lb/>compounds that report excellent reaction yields and <lb/>selectivity. 13,14,20,21 However, there are very few reports on <lb/>improving efficiency of these reactions in a sustainable manner <lb/>consistent with the principles of green chemistry. We report a <lb/>convenient and efficient method for the synthesis of <lb/>substituted benzofurans through the iodocyclization reaction <lb/>(Scheme 1) in an aqueous environment using economic, safe, <lb/>and environmentally benign reagents (CuSO 4 and NaI) under <lb/>mild/moderate conditions. In the aforementioned reaction <lb/>condition, iodocyclization conversions are at least thrice higher <lb/>than the reaction in a polar protic solvent such as ethanol. <lb/>There have been no reports on the in situ generation of I 2 for <lb/>iodocyclization of 2-alkynylanisoles and its efficiency in organic <lb/>and aqueous media. This work features the unusual <lb/></body>

		<front>Received: August 2, 2019 <lb/>Accepted: October 3, 2019 <lb/>Published: October 17, 2019 <lb/></front>

		<body>Figure 1. Drug molecules containing a benzo[b]furan core structure. <lb/>Scheme 1. The Iodocyclization Reaction Yielding <lb/>Benzo[b]furan <lb/></body>

		<front>Article <lb/>http://pubs.acs.org/journal/acsodf <lb/>Cite This: ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/>© 2019 American Chemical Society <lb/>17830 <lb/>DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/>This is an open access article published under an ACS AuthorChoice License, which permits <lb/>copying and redistribution of the article or any adaptations for non-commercial purposes. <lb/>Downloaded via 37.168.2.205 on October 18, 2024 at 10:25:06 (UTC). <lb/>See https://pubs.acs.org/sharingguidelines for options on how to legitimately share published articles. <lb/></front>

			<body>phenomenon of an organic reaction in an aqueous slurry and <lb/>the amenability of this reaction toward sustainable synthesis. <lb/>Water-soluble hosts, such as cyclodextrins (CDs), calixar-<lb/>enes, and micelles, have been often employed in influencing <lb/>reaction rates of reactions in aqueous media; both increase <lb/>(catalysis) and decrease (retardant) in reaction rates have been <lb/>used to understand the characteristics of the reaction in the <lb/>aqueous environment. Herein, we report our findings on the <lb/>influence of cyclodextrin family on the iodocyclization reaction <lb/>rates in an aqueous environment through encapsulation. <lb/>Empirical findings of reaction rates coupled with spectral <lb/>titration and computational investigations provide information <lb/>about the structural aspects of the host-guest inclusion <lb/>complex. In addition, the influence of hosts on the reaction <lb/>rates has been studied in this work, which offers a unique <lb/>insight into a previously unexplored mechanistic feature of the <lb/>iodocyclization reaction. <lb/>■ EXPERIMENTAL SECTION <lb/>The starting substrate, 1-methoxy-2-(phenylethynyl)benzene <lb/>(1a), was prepared based on the previously reported <lb/>procedure. 22 Stock solutions of the alkyne 1a in dichloro-<lb/>methane and aqueous solutions of copper sulfate and sodium <lb/>iodide (separately) were prepared in standard flasks. The <lb/>volume corresponding to the required mass of the substrate <lb/>was pipetted into a glass vial and the solvent was evaporated <lb/>off. To the resulting neat substrate in the vial, the required <lb/>volume of aqueous solution of reagents was dispensed, <lb/>followed by water to bring the solution to a specific dilution. <lb/>Typical concentrations of the experiment are 0.3 mmol of the <lb/>substrate in 25 mL of the aqueous medium. The durations and <lb/>temperature of the reaction are specified in Table 1. Following <lb/>the reaction, the slurry was diluted with water and subject to <lb/>biphasic extraction by stirring the solution with ethyl acetate <lb/>for 5 h. The organic layer was isolated, the solvent removed in <lb/>vacuo, and the residue from the reaction analyzed <lb/>spectroscopically. The proportions of the product and reactant <lb/>as well as conversions were calculated based on the integration <lb/>of peak areas in the 1 H NMR spectra (Supporting <lb/>Information) recorded on a 400 MHz Bruker AVANCE <lb/>spectrometer. <lb/>For the reaction in organic solvent, 0.3 mmol of alkyne was <lb/>dissolved in 10 mL of an appropriate solvent followed by the <lb/>addition of specific amounts of CuSO 4 •5H 2 O and NaI. <lb/>Additional solvent was added such that the final volume was <lb/>25 mL. The reaction solutions were stirred at the temperatures <lb/>and for the durations in Table 2. Following the reactions, ethyl <lb/>alcohol was removed in vacuo. Residue water and ethyl acetate <lb/>were added to separate the organic and the inorganic <lb/>components. The organic layer was separated and evaporated <lb/>in vacuo after which the products were dried under high <lb/>vacuum and characterized by 1 H NMR spectroscopy. <lb/>NMR titration was performed by obtaining a saturated <lb/>solution of 1a in water by sonicating ∼7 mg of the compound <lb/>in 2 mL D 2 O followed by removing the ppt through a syringe <lb/>filter. Then, 0.6 mL of the filtered solution was subject to <lb/>NMR titration with an addition of the powder form of <lb/>cyclodextrin(s). Concentration of the saturated solution of 1a <lb/>in water was sufficient enough to be observed in the <lb/>spectrometer at with 64 scans. <lb/>Computational chemistry of the reactant and its host-guest <lb/>complexes with cyclodextrin was performed using Gaussian &apos;09 <lb/>software package. Structures of host-guest complexes were <lb/>calculated using the ONIOM multilevel theory function in the <lb/>software. The host molecules (CDs) were treated at the <lb/>molecular mechanics level (UFF) and the guests were treated <lb/>at the HF 6-31G basis set. Geometric optimizations and <lb/>frequency calculations were performed in the gas phase. All <lb/>normal mode frequencies of optimized structures were <lb/>positive. <lb/>■ RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>Iodocyclization Reaction. Mixtures of copper sulfate and <lb/>sodium iodide generate molecular iodine (I 2 ) in situ, and the <lb/>cyclization of 2-phenethynylanisole (1a) is initiated by the <lb/>electrophilic interaction of I 2 with the alkyne. The mechanism <lb/>of iodocyclization reaction is understood to proceed via the <lb/>formation of a cyclic iodinium intermediate 3a (Scheme <lb/>2). 23-25 This electrophilic attack triggers the electrocyclization <lb/>process involving nucleophilic assistance from the conforma-<lb/>tionally predisposed ether functionality in the molecule. The <lb/>Table 1. Extent of Iodocyclization of 1a in Aqueous Slurry <lb/>time <lb/>ratio (sub/reagent) a <lb/>conv (%) b <lb/>temp <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:1:1 <lb/>33 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>58 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:5:5 <lb/>92 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>36 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>73 <lb/>60 <lb/>°C <lb/>48 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>81 <lb/>60 <lb/>°C <lb/>a <lb/>Quantities of reactants in 25 mL water: 0.3 mmol substrate, relative <lb/>ratios of CuSO 4 , and NaI listed in table. b Conversions are the average <lb/>of three independent, but simultaneous, trials that yield standard <lb/>deviations less than 5%. <lb/>Table 2. Extent of Iodocyclization of 1a in Homogeneous <lb/>Media <lb/>system <lb/>time ratio (sub/reagent) a conv (%) b <lb/>temp <lb/>methanol <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>14 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>50% MeOH/H 2 O <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>45 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>ethanol <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:3:3 <lb/>11 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>ethanol <lb/>60 h <lb/>1:5:5 <lb/>52 <lb/>25 <lb/>°C <lb/>ethanol <lb/>24 h <lb/>1:5:5 <lb/>62 <lb/>60 <lb/>°C <lb/>a Quantities of reactants in 25 mL of medium: 0.3 mmol substrate, <lb/>relative ratios of CuSO 4 and NaI listed in table. b Conversions are the <lb/>average of three independent, but simultaneous, trials that yield <lb/>standard deviations less than 5%. <lb/>Scheme 2. Mechanism of Iodocyclization Reaction <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

			<page>17831 <lb/></page>

			<body>concomitant oxonium ion intermediate 4a reinstates its <lb/>neutrality through the loss of the methyl group in the presence <lb/>of the prospective counter-anion in the medium. Due to the <lb/>involvement of an electrophilic attack in the first step and <lb/>cationic intermediate that is in conjugation with aromatic rings, <lb/>substituents with electronic effects greatly influence the <lb/>reaction rates; electron donating groups increase the reaction <lb/>rate, whereas electron withdrawing groups reduce the rate. <lb/>Reaction in Homogeneous Aqueous Slurry and <lb/>Organic Solvents. Results from the experiments performed <lb/>at different reagent concentrations, temperatures, and <lb/>durations are outlined in Table 1. It is evident that even <lb/>though the reaction mixture was heterogeneous (the reagents <lb/>and substrates were not in the same macrophase) significant <lb/>conversion was realized. This was an intriguing finding, as the <lb/>common knowledge in organic synthesis is that maximization <lb/>of the reaction speed requires complete solubility of the <lb/>reactants. While this finding was surprising, trends in the <lb/>influence of physical factors on the extent of conversion were <lb/>as expected; conversions increased progressively with time, <lb/>with an increase in concentration of reagents, and at higher <lb/>temperatures. <lb/>The conditions employed in the slurry reactions presented <lb/>in Table 1 are moderate. Near-quantitative conversion (greater <lb/>than 90%) was achieved at room temperature and in the <lb/>presence of 5 equiv of copper sulfate and sodium iodide for 24 <lb/>h. Presence of slightly lesser amounts of reagents (3 equiv) still <lb/>resulted in moderate conversions of around 50%. The extent of <lb/>the reaction was significantly higher than that observed for the <lb/>same reaction in organic media (vide infra). This observation <lb/>provides an applied significance for our work due to its <lb/>enhancement of the reaction rate as well as its green chemistry <lb/>aspect; our work is now expected to be an example, among few <lb/>others, where the reaction rate is higher in aqueous media <lb/>compared to that in organic solvents. However, the most <lb/>notable aspect of the experimental findings is that the reaction <lb/>proceeds to a significant extent in an environmentally benign <lb/>solvent, and that without the need of solubilizing agents such <lb/>as surfactants or crown ethers. <lb/>To gain perspective regarding the efficiency of the slurry <lb/>reaction, we compared the iodocyclization conversions to <lb/>those in traditional reaction conditions, such as a solution in <lb/>the organic solvent. Hence the experimental conditions <lb/>outlined above were employed, except in this case where <lb/>alcoholic organic solvents were used. Table 2 lists the <lb/>conversions achieved in various solvents and binary solvent <lb/>mixtures. The reaction conversions were overall significantly <lb/>lower than those observed using aqueous slurry conditions. <lb/>The conversions in pure organic solvents at room temperatures <lb/>were quite low, wherein for the same duration, the conversion <lb/>in the slurry was at least five folds higher. Similarly, the <lb/>conversions were many folds higher at elevated temperatures, <lb/>as well as in the presence of increased equivalents of the <lb/>reagents. A comparison of the data in Tables 1 and 2 clearly <lb/>establishes the fact that the reaction proceeds with a higher <lb/>rate and improved efficiency in the aqueous environment than <lb/>in the organic solvent. Time-dependent reaction conversion <lb/>experiment followed by NMR provides a clear perspective on <lb/>the progress of the reaction (Figure S4, Supporting <lb/>Information) where the ratio between proton signals of <lb/>phenylene (2a) and the methoxy (1a) is proportional to <lb/>reaction conversion. The importance of water in enhancing the <lb/>reaction rate is evident from the second entry in Table 2, <lb/>wherein a 50% v/v mixture of methanol in water was used as <lb/>the reaction medium. The reaction conversion increased <lb/>noticeably (about three times higher) and was comparable to <lb/>that of the reaction in water. <lb/>Supramolecular Influence on Reaction Rate. While <lb/>solubility of the inorganic reagents in water increases, solubility <lb/>of the substrate is starkly reduced. We hypothesized that <lb/>increasing the solubility of the substrate, acting like a phase-<lb/>transfer catalyst (PTC), might increase the reaction rate using <lb/>solubilizing agents. Cavitands, especially cyclodextrins, have <lb/>been used for this purpose. One specific example is the <lb/>enhancement of the rate of cyclization of o-aminobenzamides <lb/>due to its encapsulation reported by Wu et al. 26 It is especially <lb/>relevant due to its structural similarity involving ring closure to <lb/>form a five-membered benzofuran ring, in which the authors <lb/>demonstrated the role of CDs acting as a PTC as well as a <lb/>possible catalyst in stabilizing the reactant transition state. <lb/>Expecting a similar effect in our reaction involving cyclization <lb/>of an o-substituted substrate, we employed cyclodextrins to act <lb/>as a PTC thereby increasing reaction rates (Figure 2). Three <lb/>cavitands from the cyclodextrin family were used to solubilize <lb/>the reactant in the aqueous environment (Figure 3). <lb/>Cyclodextrins (CD) are bucket-shaped oligomeric structures <lb/>composed of glucopyranose units (Figure 3, left). The <lb/>hydroxyl groups of the gluropyranose on the circumference <lb/>Figure 2. Encapsulation of aminobenzamides with ketones enhances cyclization through stabilization of the transition state. 26 Presence of a similar <lb/>effect was explored in this iodocyclization cyclization of alkynyl anisoles. <lb/>Figure 3. Chemical structure of cyclodextrins, its simplified topology, and 3-D rendering in a ball-and-stick model. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

			<page>17832 <lb/></page>

			<body>of the upper and lower rims of the CD render the molecule <lb/>water-soluble, while the inner hydrophobic cavity encapsulates <lb/>smaller organic compounds, such as the substrate (1), in water. <lb/>The hexameric, heptameric, and octameric oligomer macro-<lb/>cycles are termed α-, β-, γ-CD respectively. <lb/>The electrocyclization was performed in aqueous under <lb/>identical conditions at room temperature as discussed earlier in <lb/>the presence of 3 equivalents of each CD oligomer (Table 3). <lb/>Whereas, near quantitative conversion was achieved in an <lb/>aqueous slurry reaction in 24 h, inclusion of substrate 1a within <lb/>the smallest oligomer, α-CD, resulted in a 2.4 fold decrease in <lb/>conversion. This was contradictory to the expected rate <lb/>enhancement based on the originally hypothesized PTC <lb/>advantage. Similar outcome was observed for the next larger <lb/>oligomer β-CD, though the decrease in reaction rate was not as <lb/>dramatic. The effect of the largest oligomer, γ-CD, continued <lb/>in the same trend, except in this case an enhancement in <lb/>reaction rate was observed compared to the slurry reaction. <lb/>Near quantitative conversion was observed for γ-CD in less <lb/>than 20 h, a significantly higher conversion than the <lb/>corresponding reaction for water in 24 h. This suggested that <lb/>the effect of CDs on the reaction rates were highly dependent <lb/>on their cavity sizes suggesting a strong supramolecular control <lb/>on the reaction mechanism as opposed to a simple PTC <lb/>phenomenon. <lb/>Computational Chemistry. We aimed to understand the <lb/>effect of CDs on the reaction rates based on the computed <lb/>geometry of inclusion complexes. Geometry-optimized struc-<lb/>tures of reactants, products, and their complexes with β-<lb/>cyclodextrin (all in gas phase) were studied. Initial analysis of <lb/>the computational structures of the reactant 1a optimized in <lb/>gas phase (HF 6-31G, Figure 4) and in an aqueous medium <lb/>(SE PM6, Supporting Information) suggested that the <lb/>molecule could adopt two possible conformations correspond-<lb/>ing to a local minima: one in which the methyl group is <lb/>pointed away from the alkyne group (conformation 1, C1), <lb/>and the second in which the methyl group is pointed towards it <lb/>(conformation 2, C2). Conformation 2 was less stable than <lb/>conformation 1 in both levels of theory, perhaps due to the <lb/>possible increased steric interaction between the methyl and <lb/>alkynyl groups. Based on this information, we realized that our <lb/>in silico studies should involve complexes of reactants with the <lb/>CDs in C1 and C2 conformations as well. <lb/>ΔΔ <lb/>=Δ <lb/>-Δ <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/>G <lb/>stabilization <lb/>nonreactive conf <lb/>reactive conf <lb/>(1) <lb/>In the nonreacting conformation (C1), the methyl group is <lb/>pointed perpendicular to the alkynyl moiety while in the <lb/>reactive conformation (C2) it is pointed away, resulting in <lb/>oxygen&apos;s lone pair predisposed for cyclization. The energies of <lb/>geometry optimized structures of both conformations in the <lb/>three CD hosts were performed in two-level ONIOM <lb/>calculation with the lower level theory (MM, UFF) applied <lb/>to host and the higher-level theory (HF-6-31G) applied to the <lb/>guests. Geometry-optimized structures in the gas phase <lb/>suggested that both phenyl and the anisole rings are <lb/>conveniently encapsulated within the host cavities. For our <lb/>analysis, we studied only structures in which the anisole ring is <lb/>encapsulated as an influence on its conformation will have the <lb/>most influence on its mechanism. <lb/>Comparing the geometry-optimized structure of the reactant <lb/>conformations C1 and C2 included within the cavitand <lb/>provided a possible explanation for the observed change. For <lb/>the unbound reactant, computational chemistry suggests that <lb/>the preferred conformation is the reactive geometry, <lb/>presumably due to coplanarity of lone pairs for conjugation. <lb/>Frequency calculations on the geometry-optimized structures <lb/>allowed us to evaluate the thermochemistry of the isomeric <lb/>complex structures: C1@CD vs C2@CD (Figure 5). <lb/>Comparison of the free energies of the complex formation <lb/>showed that as the cavitand size increases the stability of <lb/>reactive conformation decreases and that of the nonreactive <lb/>conformation increases (Figure 6). If stabilization of the <lb/>reactive geometry (due to oxygen predisposition) is the only <lb/>factor, then α-CD would be the most reactive and γ-CD the <lb/>least; however, experimentally this is not the case. Therefore, <lb/>the second factor that would influence the reaction rate is the <lb/>accessibility of the molecular iodine to the alkyne moiety to <lb/>form the cyclic iodonium intermediate. Based on the analysis <lb/>of complex structures it is evident that as the size of cavitand <lb/>increases, the ability of iodine to react with the substrate would <lb/>increase. While all CDs enhance the solubility of the substrate, <lb/>the limited cavitand volume of α-CD also imposes a steric <lb/>barrier on the I 2 -substrate interaction, which reduces reactivity. <lb/>On the other hand, the larger cavity volume of γ-CD is able to <lb/>simultaneously encapsulate the substrate and the reagent while <lb/>also conferring the solubility advantage for the host without <lb/>imposing a steric hindrance, which increases the reaction rate; <lb/>the ability of γ-CD to form ternary complexes is well-<lb/>documented in literature. <lb/>Empirical Observation of Host-Guest Complex. <lb/>Complex formation was experimentally ascertained through <lb/>NMR host-guest titrations (Figure 7). Compound 1a is soluble <lb/>enough in D 2 O (saturated solution) for 1 H NMR analysis. <lb/>Addition of aliquots of β-and γ-CDs showed peak broadening <lb/>indicating complexation. Surprisingly, there was no observable <lb/>shift in signals, which is unusual. The extent of peak <lb/>Table 3. Extent of Iodocyclization of 1a Complexed by <lb/>Water-Soluble Hosts in the Presence of Three Equivalents <lb/>of Host at 25 °C in the Presence of Five Equivalents of <lb/>Reagents a <lb/>system <lb/>duration <lb/>% conv <lb/>α-CD <lb/>24 h <lb/>39 <lb/>β-CD <lb/>12 h <lb/>66 <lb/>β-CD <lb/>24 h <lb/>82 <lb/>γ-CD <lb/>12 h <lb/>73 <lb/>γ-CD <lb/>19 h <lb/>&gt; 95 <lb/>a <lb/>Quantities of reactants in 25 mL water: 0.3 mmol substrate, 1.5 <lb/>mmol of CuSO 4 and NaI; conversions are the average of three <lb/>independent, but simultaneous, trials that yield standard deviations <lb/>less than 5%. <lb/>Figure 4. Geometry-optimized structures (Gaussian09, HF 6-31G) of <lb/>the free guests starting at two different conformations: nonreacting <lb/>(C1, left) and reacting (C2, right). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

			<page>17833 <lb/></page>

			<body>broadening was significant for γ-CD even at 1 equivalent, while <lb/>it was minimal (though noticeable) for β-CD. The extent of <lb/>peak broadening was similar for all nine aromatic protons, <lb/>suggesting complexation of the host to both the phenyl and <lb/>phenoxy sides. The presence of a single set of peaks indicated <lb/>complexation kinetics faster than the NMR time scale, <lb/>consistent with a weak complexation dynamic typically <lb/>observed for CDs in general. <lb/>Complexation of the guest to CDs was further ascertained <lb/>through UV-vis and fluorometric titrations (section D, <lb/>Supporting Information). UV-vis titration of 1a with β-CD <lb/>showed increase in extinction coefficient of the chromophore <lb/>(absorbance increase) with each addition. Similarly, there was <lb/>a significant decrease in fluorescence of the chromophore in <lb/>the presence of the host compared to that of the free guest. <lb/>Spectral analysis of guest 1a in the presence and absence of <lb/>water-soluble hosts indicated inclusion complex formation, <lb/>which considered along with the NMR titration experiments, <lb/>confirmed inclusion of the guest within the cavitand. <lb/>Therefore, the changes in reaction conversion that we observed <lb/>in our experiments were evidently the result of supramolecular <lb/>(weak) interactions between the host and guest. <lb/>Figure 5. Geometry-optimized of host-guest complex of 1a bound to CDs and relative stabilities based on free energies of formation as deduced <lb/>from eq 1. <lb/>Figure 6. Chart showing the trend in stabilization energy of the <lb/>nonreacting conformer (ΔΔG stabilization eq 1, maroon, left axis) and its <lb/>correlation with experimental reaction conversion (green, right axis). <lb/>Figure 7. Partial 1 H NMR spectra of the saturated solution of 1a in D 2 O (top) and its complexes with two equivalents of β-CD (middle) and γ-CD <lb/>(bottom). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

			<page>17834 <lb/></page>

			<body>Effect of Substituents. The effect of substituents on the <lb/>reaction outcome, performed under the reported conditions, <lb/>was explored. Two additional substrates were used, namely 4-<lb/>methoxy-and a 4-cyano-substituted derivatives. As iodocycli-<lb/>zation involves a cationic iodonium intermediate, it is expected <lb/>that electronically activated substrates would enhance the <lb/>reaction rate and vice versa. The 4-methoxy derivative of 1a <lb/>underwent near quantitative conversion in 20 h under <lb/>unmediated conditions, while the 4-cyano derivative resulted <lb/>in no significant conversion under similar conditions (Table <lb/>4). These results were consistent with expectations. Similar to <lb/>the experiments with 1a, the reaction was performed in the <lb/>presence of CDs. Consistent with the earlier findings, the <lb/>reaction conversions were enhanced for all substrates, <lb/>substantiating our hypothesis that the complexation of <lb/>substrates to CDs increases interaction between I 2 and the <lb/>alkynyl bond along with PTC effect. <lb/>■ CONCLUSIONS <lb/>This work reports enhancement of the iodocyclization reaction <lb/>of 1-alkoxyphenyl-2-phenyl acetylene in the presence of copper <lb/>sulfate and sodium iodide to yield the corresponding <lb/>benzofuran. The reaction has been observed to proceed faster <lb/>in an aqueous environment as a homogeneous slurry than in <lb/>the solution in organic solvents. We speculate that this is due <lb/>to the increased solubility of the inorganic reagents in water <lb/>leading to an increase in the local concentration of the <lb/>reactants and reagents. High reaction conversions were <lb/>achieved under moderate conditions in an environmentally <lb/>friendly solvent. We attempted to improve the reaction <lb/>conversions by utilizing solubilizers to enhance the aqueous <lb/>solubility of the substrate, which yielded mixed results: the <lb/>large host γ-CD enhanced reaction rate compared to the aq <lb/>slurry while the smaller hosts showing reduced rates exhibiting <lb/>a clear size-dependent trend. Energy-minimized structures of <lb/>the reactant and the complex suggested that the gradation in <lb/>reaction rates is due to the differential stabilization of two <lb/>different conformations (reactive and nonreactive) of the <lb/>substrate. While all three hosts increase solubility of the <lb/>substrate in water, the smaller hosts also prevent their <lb/>reactivity through steric hinderance; the larger cavity volume <lb/>of γ-CD does not impose such physical limitation, which <lb/>results in an overall rate enhancement. <lb/>■ ASSOCIATED CONTENT <lb/>* S Supporting Information <lb/>The Supporting Information is available free of charge on the <lb/>ACS Publications website at DOI: 10.1021/acsome-<lb/>ga.9b02466. <lb/>Synthesis of substrates, time-dependent conversion, <lb/>computational chemistry details, and UV/Fluorescence <lb/>spectra (PDF) <lb/>■ AUTHOR INFORMATION <lb/>Corresponding Authors <lb/>*E-mail: tkesharwani@uwf.edu (T.K.). <lb/>*E-mail: pattabiramm2@unk.edu (M.P.). <lb/>ORCID <lb/>Tanay Kesharwani: 0000-0001-8193-0004 <lb/>Mahesh Pattabiraman: 0000-0002-6763-6711 <lb/>Notes <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">The authors declare no competing financial interest. <lb/>■ ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>This research was supported by the ACS-Petroleum Research <lb/>Fund (#54862-UR4) and the Research Corporation for <lb/>Science Advancement for the Cottrell College Science Award <lb/>(ID 23248). M.P. is thankful for the support from the UNK&apos;s <lb/>Office of Sponsored Programs. T.K. and C.C. are grateful for <lb/>generous support provided by the University of West Florida <lb/>(UWF), the UWF&apos;s Office of Research and Sponsored <lb/>Programs and Office of Undergraduate Research. C.C. is <lb/>thankful to the National Institute of General Medical Sciences <lb/>of the National Institutes of Health under grant no. <lb/>1T34GM110517-01. This content is solely the responsibility <lb/>of the authors and does not necessarily represent the official <lb/>views of the National Institutes of Health. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>■ REFERENCES <lb/>(1) Chand, K.; Rajeshwari; Hiremathad, A.; Singh, M.; Santos, M. <lb/>A.; Keri, R. S. A review on antioxidant potential of bioactive <lb/>heterocycle benzofuran: Natural and synthetic derivatives. Pharmacol. <lb/>Rep. 2017, 69, 281-295. <lb/>(2) Kuramochi, K.; Tsubaki, K. Synthesis and structural character-<lb/>ization of natural benzofuranoids. J. Nat. Prod. 2015, 78, 1056-1066. <lb/>(3) Reddy, V. K.; Rao, J. V.; Reddy, L. B.; Ram, B.; Balram, B. <lb/>Synthesis and antibacterial activity of 4,6-dimethoxy-2-(4-<lb/>methoxyphenyl)benzofuran-3-yl-methanone derivatives and its inter-<lb/>mediates. Asian J. Chem. 2015, 27, 2245-2248. <lb/>(4) Heravi, M. M.; Zadsirjan, V.; Hamidi, H.; Tabar Amiri, P. H. <lb/>Total synthesis of natural products containing benzofuran rings. RSC <lb/>Adv. 2017, 7, 24470-24521. <lb/>(5) Dixit, M.; Tripathi, B. K.; Tamrakar, A. K.; Srivastava, A. K.; <lb/>Kumar, B.; Goel, A. Synthesis of benzofuran scaffold-based potential <lb/>PTP-1B inhibitors. Bioorg. Med. Chem. 2007, 15, 727-734. <lb/>(6) Khanam, H.; Shamsuzzaman. Bioactive Benzofuran derivatives: <lb/>A review. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2015, 97, 483-504. <lb/>(7) Naik, R.; Harmalkar, D. S.; Xu, X.; Jang, K.; Lee, K. Bioactive <lb/>benzofuran derivatives: moracins A-Z in medicinal chemistry. Eur. J. <lb/>Med. Chem. 2015, 90, 379-393. <lb/>(8) Radadiya, A.; Shah, A. Bioactive benzofuran derivatives: An <lb/>insight on lead developments, radioligands and advances of the last <lb/>decade. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2015, 97, 356-376. <lb/>(9) Rizzo, S.; Rivieŕe, C.; Piazzi, L.; Bisi, A.; Gobbi, S.; Bartolini, M.; <lb/>Andrisano, V.; Morroni, F.; Tarozzi, A.; Monti, J.-P.; Rampa, A. <lb/>Benzofuran-based hybrid compounds for the inhibition of cholines-<lb/>terase activity, β amyloid aggregation, and aβ neurotoxicity. J. Med. <lb/>Chem. 2008, 51, 2883-2886. <lb/>(10) Kirilmis, C.; Ahmedzade, M.; Servi, S.; Koca, M.; Kizirgil, A.; <lb/>Kazaz, C. Synthesis and antimicrobial activity of some novel <lb/>derivatives of benzofuran: part 2. The synthesis and antimicrobial <lb/>activity of some novel 1-(1-benzofuran-2-yl)-2-mesitylethanone <lb/>derivatives. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2008, 43, 300-308. <lb/></listBibl>

			<body>Table 4. Substituent Effect on Extent of Reaction in <lb/>Presence and Absence of Macrocyclic Cavitand a <lb/>R <lb/>time <lb/>conv (%) <lb/>water <lb/>γ-CD <lb/>4-H (1a) <lb/>20 h <lb/>81 <lb/>&gt;95 <lb/>4-OCH 3 (1b) <lb/>20 h <lb/>95 <lb/>&gt;95 <lb/>4-CN(1c) <lb/>3 6 h <lb/>1 1 <lb/>a <lb/>Quantities of reactants in 25 mL water: 0.3 mmol substrate, in the <lb/>presence of five equivalents of reagents and three equivalents of host; <lb/>conversions are the average of three independent, but simultaneous, <lb/>trials that yield standard deviations less than 5%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

			<page>17835 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>(11) Koca, M.; Servi, S.; Kirilmis, C.; Ahmedzade, M.; Kazaz, C.; <lb/>O ̈zbek, B.; O ̈tuk, G. Synthesis and antimicrobial activity of some <lb/>novel derivatives of benzofuran: part 1. Synthesis and antimicrobial <lb/>activity of (benzofuran-2-yl)(3-phenyl-3-methylcyclobutyl) ketoxime <lb/>derivatives. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2005, 40, 1351-1358. <lb/>(12) Hiremathad, A.; Patil, M. R.; Chethana, K. R.; Chand, K.; <lb/>Santos, M. A.; Keri, R. S. Benzofuran: an emerging scaffold for <lb/>antimicrobial agents. RSC Adv. 2015, 5, 96809-96828. <lb/>(13) Jiang, X.; Liu, W.; Zhang, W.; Jiang, F.; Gao, Z.; Zhuang, H.; <lb/>Fu, L. Synthesis and antimicrobial evaluation of new benzofuran <lb/>derivatives. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2011, 46, 3526-3530. <lb/>(14) Zhang, W.; Liu, W.; Jiang, X.; Jiang, F.; Zhuang, H.; Fu, L. <lb/>Design, synthesis and antimicrobial activity of chiral 2-(substituted-<lb/>hydroxyl)-3-(benzo[d]oxazol-5-yl)propanoic acid derivatives. Eur. J. <lb/>Med. Chem. 2011, 46, 3639-3650. <lb/>(15) El-Sawy, E. R.; Ebaid, M. S.; Abo-Salem, H. M.; El-Hallouty, S.; <lb/>Kassem, E. M.; Mandour, A. H. Synthesis and biological activity of <lb/>novel series of 4-methoxy, and 4,9-dimethoxy-5-substituted furo[2,3-<lb/>g]-1,2,3-benzoxathiazine-7,7-dioxide derivatives. J. Adv. Res. 2014, 5, <lb/>337-346. <lb/>(16) Boyle, E. A.; Mangan, F. R.; Markwell, R. E.; Smith, S. A.; <lb/>Thomson, M. J.; Ward, R. W.; Wyman, P. A. 7-Aroyl-2,3-<lb/>dihydrobenzo[b]furan-3-carboxylic acids and 7-benzoyl-2,3-<lb/>dihydrobenzo[b]thiophene-3-carboxylic acids as analgesic agents. J. <lb/>Med. Chem. 1986, 29, 894-898. <lb/>(17) Dawood, K. M. Benzofuran derivatives: a patent review. Expert <lb/>Opin. Ther. Pat. 2013, 23, 1133-1156. <lb/>(18) Goyal, D.; Kaur, A.; Goyal, B. Benzofuran and Indole: <lb/>Promising Scaffolds for Drug Development in Alzheimer&apos;s Disease. <lb/>ChemMedChem 2018, 13, 1275-1299. <lb/>(19) Nevagi, R. J.; Dighe, S. N.; Dighe, S. N. Biological and <lb/>medicinal significance of benzofuran. Eur. J. Med. Chem. 2015, 97, <lb/>561-581. <lb/>(20) Heravi, M. M.; Zadsirjan, V. Recent advances in the synthesis of <lb/>benzo[b]furans. Adv. Heterocycl. Chem. 2015, 117, 261-376. <lb/>(21) Kwiecien, H.; Smist, M.; Kowalewska, M. Recent development <lb/>on the synthesis of benzo[b]-and naphtho[b]furans: a review. Curr. <lb/>Org. Synth. 2012, 9, 529-560. <lb/>(22) Yue, D.; Yao, T.; Larock, R. C. Synthesis of 2,3-disubstituted <lb/>benzo[b]furans by the palladium-catalyzed coupling of o-iodoanisoles <lb/>and terminal alkynes, followed by electrophilic cyclization. J. Org. <lb/>Chem. 2005, 70, 10292-10296. <lb/>(23) Kim, S.; Dahal, N.; Kesharwani, T. Environmentally benign <lb/>process for the synthesis of 2,3-disubstituted benzo[b]thiophenes <lb/>using electrophilic cyclization. Tetrahedron Lett. 2013, 54, 4373-<lb/>4376. <lb/>(24) Kesharwani, T.; Worlikar, S. A.; Larock, R. C. Synthesis of 2,3-<lb/>Disubstituted Benzo[b]selenophenes via Electrophilic Cyclization. J. <lb/>Org. Chem. 2006, 71, 2307-2312. <lb/>(25) Kesharwani, T.; Kornman, C.; Tonnaer, A.; Hayes, A.; Kim, S.; <lb/>Dahal, N.; Romero, R.; Royappa, A. Sodium halides as the source of <lb/>electrophilic halogens in green synthesis of 3-halo-and 3,n-<lb/>dihalobenzo[b]thiophenes. Tetrahedron 2018, 74, 2973-2984. <lb/>(26) Wu, J.; Du, X.; Ma, J.; Zhang, Y.; Shi, Q.; Luo, L.; Song, B.; <lb/>Yang, S.; Hu, D. Preparation of 2,3-dihydroquinazolin-4(1H)-one <lb/>derivatives in aqueous media with β-cyclodextrin-SO3H as a <lb/>recyclable catalyst. Green Chem. 2014, 16, 3210-3217. <lb/></listBibl>

		<note place="headnote">ACS Omega <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">DOI: 10.1021/acsomega.9b02466 <lb/>ACS Omega 2019, 4, 17830-17836 <lb/></note>

		<page>17836 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
