<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/>Small LEA proteins mitigate air-water <lb/>interface damage to fragile cryo-EM samples <lb/>during plunge freezing <lb/>Kaitlyn M. Abe 1 , Gan Li 1,2 , Qixiang He 1 , Timothy Grant 1,2 &amp; Ci Ji Lim 1 <lb/>Air-water interface (AWI) interactions during cryo-electron microscopy (cryo-<lb/>EM) sample preparation cause significant sample loss, hindering structural <lb/>biology research. Organisms like nematodes and tardigrades produce Late <lb/>Embryogenesis Abundant (LEA) proteins to withstand desiccation stress. Here <lb/>we show that these LEA proteins, when used as additives during plunge <lb/>freezing, effectively mitigate AWI damage to fragile multi-subunit molecular <lb/>samples. The resulting high-resolution cryo-EM maps are comparable to or <lb/>better than those obtained using existing AWI damage mitigation methods. <lb/>Cryogenic electron tomography reveals that particles are localized at specific <lb/>interfaces, suggesting LEA proteins form a barrier at the AWI. This interaction <lb/>may explain the observed sample-dependent preferred orientation of parti-<lb/>cles. LEA proteins offer a simple, cost-effective, and adaptable approach for <lb/>cryo-EM structural biologists to overcome AWI-related sample damage, <lb/>potentially revitalizing challenging projects and advancing the field of struc-<lb/>tural biology. <lb/></front>

			<body>The &quot;resolution revolution&quot; of cryogenic-electron microscopy (cryo-<lb/>EM) marked a significant shift in the field of structural biology 1 . How-<lb/>ever, the continued growth of cryo-EM single-particle analysis faces a <lb/>critical problem, namely sample damage that occurs during grid <lb/>preparation 2-9 . The standard method for cryo-EM single-particle ana-<lb/>lysis sample preparation is plunge freezing, where small volumes of <lb/>sample are applied onto a pretreated cryo-EM grid, blotted, and <lb/>rapidly plunged into a cryogen such as liquid ethane (Fig. 1a). This <lb/>process forms a thin layer (~10-100 nm) 5,10 of sample-embedded vitr-<lb/>eous ice for transmission electron microscopy imaging 11,12 (Fig. 1b). <lb/>Between the blotting and rapid freezing steps, the sample exists as a <lb/>thin aqueous film with a high surface-to-volume ratio. During this <lb/>transitional phase (typically lasting for seconds), the proteins in the <lb/>aqueous solution collide with the air-water interface (AWI) thousands <lb/>of times before finally being vitrified 5,9 . <lb/>Adsorption to the AWI can destroy the protein&apos;s structural <lb/>integrity, causing it to denature, or disintegrate 2,5,7,13 (Fig. 1c). In a <lb/>scenario where the protein maintains its structure after AWI adsorp-<lb/>tion, the sample interaction with the AWI may be biased towards <lb/>certain regions, leading to preferred sample orientations and an ani-<lb/>sotropic 3D reconstruction of the sample 2,3,14,15 . To mitigate the AWI <lb/>problem, researchers have developed a variety of solutions. These <lb/>include the addition of mild detergents to the sample 16,17 , using che-<lb/>mical crosslinking 18-21 , and adsorbing or tethering samples to surfaces <lb/>to prevent sample contact with the AWI 4,22-30 . More sophisticated <lb/>techniques involve rapidly freezing the sample before the proteins can <lb/>diffuse to the AWIs 30-35 . However, these methods are often technically <lb/>challenging, cost-prohibitive and demonstrate sample-specific results. <lb/>Here we show an AWI mitigation strategy that is accessible, cost-<lb/>effective, and readily deployable in all cryo-EM facilities and research <lb/>laboratories. <lb/>Results <lb/>AavLEA1 mitigates AWI damage to fragile cryo-EM samples <lb/>during grid plunge freezing <lb/>In search of a new solution to mitigate AWI damage, we explored the <lb/>biological world, hypothesizing that cellular response mechanisms to <lb/>desiccation stress could offer an evolved solution for mitigating <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 17 February 2024 <lb/>Accepted: 27 August 2024 <lb/>Check for updates <lb/>1 <lb/>Department of Biochemistry, University of Wisconsin-Madison, Madison, WI 53706, USA. 2 John and Jeanne Rowe Center for Research in Virology, Morgridge <lb/>Institute for Research, Madison, WI 53715, USA. <lb/>e-mail: ciji.lim@wisc.edu <lb/>Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/>1 <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/>1234567890():,; <lb/></front>

			<body>protein damage caused by AWI interaction. We identified late embry-<lb/>ogenesis abundant (LEA) proteins 36-38 , specifically a group 3 LEA pro-<lb/>tein, AavLEA1, from the roundworm (nematode) Aphelenchus avenae 39 <lb/>as a potential candidate. Studies have indicated that AavLEA1, which <lb/>has a molecular weight of ~16 kDa, prevents protein aggregation due to <lb/>desiccation 39 . This is likely due to the formation of an AavLEA1 barrier <lb/>which mitigates damage caused by direct interaction of the sample <lb/>with the AWI 38 . We thus propose that AavLEA1 can be used as a sample <lb/>additive to mitigate damage to protein samples caused by AWI inter-<lb/>action during cryo-EM grid plunge freezing (Fig. 1d). The relatively <lb/>small molecular mass of AavLEA1 (approximately 16 kDa) compared to <lb/>a typical sample of interest (several hundred kDa) should allow Aav-<lb/>LEA1 to reach the AWI faster than the larger samples. <lb/>To evaluate the AWI damage mitigation effects of LEA proteins, <lb/>we used two protein complexes that are AWI-sensitive as model sys-<lb/>tems: human DNA polymerase-α-primase (PP) 40-42 and Polycomb <lb/>repressive complex 2 (PRC2) 20,43,44 . It is important to note that in this <lb/>study, both complexes were tested in their apo-state, and all data <lb/>collection was performed using a 200 keV electron microscope with a <lb/>direct electron detector (for details, please see the Methods section). <lb/>Reported cryo-EM structures of apo-state PP complexes were solved <lb/>using chemically crosslinked samples 42 , suggesting that the PP parti-<lb/>cles fell apart due to AWI damage during plunge freezing. Another <lb/>arguably more challenging structure to solve for cryo-EM single-par-<lb/>ticle analysis is that of PRC2. Reported PRC2 cryo-EM structures were <lb/>solved by highly specialized strategies using either chemically <lb/>crosslinked samples on thin carbon-support grids 20,45 or biotinylated <lb/>samples tethered onto Streptavidin-crystal grids 43,44 . <lb/>We found that the addition of AavLEA1 to PP and PRC2 before <lb/>freezing eliminates the need for the abovementioned methods, <lb/>allowing us to solve their structures at comparable or higher resolu-<lb/>tions (Fig. 2). The optimal addition amount was found to be between <lb/>1:8-1:40 molar ratio of the sample to the LEA proteins (Supplementary <lb/>Figs. 1-3). The addition of AavLEA1 at a 1:40 PP:AavLEA1 molar ratio <lb/>before plunge freezing led to considerably better grids than freezing <lb/>the PP sample alone; with clear and homogeneously sized particles <lb/>(Fig. 2a). Multiple high-resolution two-dimensional (2D) class averages <lb/>of PP were obtained from these particles (Fig. 2b), and subsequent <lb/>image processing led to a 3.0 Å global resolution map of the apo-state <lb/>PP (Fig. 2c and Supplementary Fig. 3). This is the highest resolution <lb/>cryo-EM map reported for the human apo-state PP; the previous X-ray <lb/>structure was solved at 3.6 Å 46 and a chemically crosslinked cryo-EM <lb/>structure determined at a 3.8 Å global resolution 42 . Most importantly, <lb/>we demonstrated that AavLEA1 can be used to mitigate sample damage <lb/>from AWI interactions during plunge freezing, resulting in high-<lb/>resolution cryo-EM maps. <lb/>Initially, we had some potential concerns with the AavLEA1 <lb/>approach. Firstly, the addition of AavLEA1 could have led to an ele-<lb/>vated background signal in the micrograph. Secondly, interaction with <lb/>AavLEA1 could have distorted the sample conformation. Given that we <lb/>obtained a 3.0 Å resolution cryo-EM map for human PP apo-state <lb/>complex in the presence of excess AavLEA1 (sample:AavLEA1 of 1:40), <lb/>we deduce that background AavLEA1 did not significantly affect image <lb/>alignment or hinder high-resolution reconstruction. Additionally, we <lb/>did not find any extra map density that would indicate AavLEA1 bind-<lb/>ing to PP in a consistent manner, nor a significant change in the PP <lb/>conformation; we calculated a RMSD of 1.2 Å when a refined model <lb/>derived from the 3.0 Å cryo-EM map was aligned to a published crystal <lb/>structure of an apo-state human PP (PDB: 5EXR) 46 (Supplementary <lb/>Figs. 4, 5 and Table 1). In short, AavLEA1 addition did not alter the PP <lb/>apo-state conformation. <lb/>We saw similar results for PRC2 with the addition of AavLEA1 (1:40 <lb/>PRC2:AavLEA1 molar ratio)-Adding AavLEA1 resulted in clear and <lb/>homogeneously sized particles (Fig. 2d). Without additives, we saw <lb/>smaller sized particles in the micrographs, indicating broken PRC2 <lb/>complexes, consistent with previous studies 47 . Subsequent cryo-EM <lb/>image processing led to a 3.8 Å global resolution map of PRC2 (Fig. 2e, f <lb/>and Supplementary Fig. 6). This result further exemplifies the efficacy <lb/>of AavLEA1 in facilitating the determination of high-resolution cryo-EM <lb/>structures of protein samples sensitive to the air-water interface. <lb/>A truncated form of LEA protein from tardigrade also mitigates <lb/>AWI sample damage <lb/>Encouraged by the success of using nematode AavLEA1 to mitigate <lb/>AWI sample damage, we pondered whether LEA proteins from other <lb/>organisms could provide comparable results. Tardigrades, also known <lb/>as water bears, are tolerant of desiccation stress 48 , and the species <lb/>Ramazzottius varieornatus has a group 3 LEA protein, RvLEAM 49 . <lb/>Because RvLEAM has nine LEA-like motifs and is about 30 kDa in mass, <lb/>we truncated it to ~15 kDa to increase its diffusion coefficient and <lb/>match the size of AavLEA1 for ease of comparison (refer to the Meth-<lb/>ods section for details). The truncated RvLEAM is hereafter termed <lb/>RvLEAM short . <lb/>Similar to AavLEA1, adding RvLEAM short to PP or PRC2 sample at a <lb/>molar ratio of 1:6 sample:RvLEAM short before plunge freezing led to the <lb/>appearance of monodisperse and discernable particles (Fig. 3). From <lb/>datasets collected over a single night, we successfully reconstructed <lb/>cryo-EM maps of human apo-state PP and PRC2 at a reported global <lb/>resolution of 4.5 and 3.7 Å, respectively (Fig. 3c, f and Supplementary <lb/>Figs. 7, 8). The final resolution of PP and RvLEAM short in this dataset is <lb/>lower than our other PP dataset because significantly fewer movies <lb/>Cryo-EM SPA grid <lb/>preparation robot <lb/>Cryo-EM <lb/>SPA grid <lb/>Example of regularly-spaced <lb/>holey grid with vitrified ice <lb/>Ideal <lb/>sample distribution <lb/>in thin film of vitrified ice <lb/>Holey <lb/>carbon film <lb/>Holes for <lb/>vitrified sample <lb/>Carbon film <lb/>Typical <lb/>sample distribution <lb/>in thin film of vitrified ice <lb/>Air <lb/>Water <lb/>Preferred <lb/>orientation <lb/>Complex <lb/>dissociation <lb/>Protein <lb/>denaturation <lb/>Vitrified sample <lb/>Rescued <lb/>sample distribution <lb/>in thin film of vitrified ice <lb/>with LEA proteins <lb/>LEA-water interface (LWI) forming a barrier at AWI <lb/>LEA protein <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>d <lb/>Severity of AWI damage to sample <lb/>Fig. 1 | Cryo-EM sample grid preparation and potential role of LEA proteins on <lb/>AWI damage mitigation. Cartoon illustration of the process and outcomes of <lb/>preparing cryo-EM SPA grids and the hypothesized effects of LEA proteins on <lb/>sample structural integrity. a Shows a Cryo-EM SPA grid preparation robot along-<lb/>side a detailed view of a typical holey grid with vitrified ice, which is used for <lb/>embedding protein samples. b-d Depict different states of protein sample dis-<lb/>tribution within the vitrified ice. In panel (b), an ideal sample distribution is shown <lb/>where proteins are evenly dispersed without any structural damage. c Illustrates the <lb/>typical impact of air-water interface (AWI) damage on protein samples, leading to <lb/>preferred orientation, complex dissociation, and protein denaturation. <lb/>d Demonstrates how LEA proteins can mitigate sample damage by forming a barrier <lb/>at the AWI, which significantly mitigates these damages and preserves protein <lb/>integrity in vitrified ice. <lb/></body>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>were collected (see methods). Given that this is the second LEA protein <lb/>we have tested that successfully rescued the cryo-EM structure <lb/>determination of two challenging AWI-sensitive protein complexes, we <lb/>believe group 3 LEA proteins, as a cryo-EM single-particle analysis <lb/>sample additive, offers a promising and powerful method for struc-<lb/>tural biologists to mitigate sample damage caused by AWI during <lb/>plunge freezing. <lb/>Samples with LEA protein addition distribute at vitrified ice <lb/>surfaces <lb/>While our prediction that LEA proteins mitigate AWI damage was <lb/>correct, our initial hypothesis about the mechanism of LEA-mediated <lb/>AWI damage mitigation proved inaccurate. We speculated that once <lb/>the LEA proteins formed a barrier at the AWI, which we termed the LEA-<lb/>water interface (LWI), the sample particles would remain in the aqu-<lb/>eous layer. When imaged in vitreous ice after plunge freezing, we <lb/>expected the projected views of the frozen particles to be randomly <lb/>distributed (Fig. 1). However, a major underlying assumption was that <lb/>there was no interaction between the sample and the LWI. If such <lb/>interactions exist, they would manifest as a bias in the particle orien-<lb/>tation (view projection) 6,17 . Our particle orientation distribution ana-<lb/>lysis for the cryo-EM maps derived from the LEA protein datasets <lb/>suggests this was the case (Fig. 4a and Supplementary Table 2). Cal-<lb/>culations from the 3DFSC server 14 indicated that the PP maps show a <lb/>good isotropic distribution, approaching perfect isotropy with a <lb/>sphericity of 0.98 for those with AavLEA1 and 0.83 with RvLEAM short . <lb/>Conversely, the PRC2 maps exhibited poorer particle orientation dis-<lb/>tribution, regardless of the LEA protein used; sphericity values were <lb/>0.77 and 0.79 for maps with AavLEA1 and RvLEAM short , respectively. <lb/>Overall, these results suggest that the samples interact with the LWI to <lb/>varying degrees, dependent on the specific sample. <lb/>If the samples are indeed interacting with the interface, the par-<lb/>ticles should be distributed as plane(s). To test this, we used fiducial-<lb/>less cryo-electron tomography (cryo-ET) analysis to visualize the par-<lb/>ticle distribution of PP with AavLEA1 (1:40 molar ratio) and PRC2 with <lb/>RvLEAM short (1:6 molar ratio) in our grids (Fig. 4b, c and Supplementary <lb/>Movies 1, 2). In both cases, we saw most of the particles were dis-<lb/>tributed within one or two planes in the vitrified ice, confirming that <lb/>the samples were adsorbed to a surface in the presence of LEA <lb/>proteins. <lb/>Due to the small sizes of LEA proteins, we were unable to visualize <lb/>them in our cryo-EM images directly, preventing us from determining <lb/>their empirical coverage at the AWI. Consequently, we cannot rule out <lb/>the possibility of incomplete LEA protein coverage, and that the par-<lb/>ticle orientation bias could have resulted, in part or entirely, from <lb/>interactions with exposed pockets of the AWI. If this is indeed the case, <lb/>it is reassuring to note that these interactions with the AWI, in the <lb/>presence of LEA proteins, did not significantly compromise the sam-<lb/>ples&apos; structural integrity, as demonstrated by the reconstructed high-<lb/>resolution cryo-EM maps of the tested samples (Figs. 2, 3). <lb/>Biochemical strategies to improve particle orientation dis-<lb/>tribution of LEA datasets <lb/>Given that interactions between the sample and LEA proteins at the <lb/>LWI can contribute to the observed particle orientation bias, we aimed <lb/>to explore strategies that influenced these interactions to achieve a <lb/>desirable particle orientation outcome. Both AavLEA1 and RvLEAM short <lb/>are predicted to form amphiphilic alpha-helical structures, with the <lb/>hydrophobic face oriented towards the air at the AWI and the hydro-<lb/>philic side (negatively charged) facing the aqueous solution 49,50 . Thus, <lb/>the negatively charged, solution-facing side of the LWI could create a <lb/>&quot;sticky&quot; surface that leads to the particle orientation bias observed in <lb/>the LEA datasets. <lb/>Past studies have demonstrated that electrostatic charge on a <lb/>surface, whether AWI or carbon film, can influence sample particle <lb/>orientation 51,52 . Using PRC2 and RvLEAM short as the model condition, <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>90°1 <lb/>00 Å <lb/>2D class averages <lb/>Representative micrographs and their CTFs <lb/>PP alone <lb/>PP + AavLEA1 (1:40) <lb/>Global resolution: 3.0 Å <lb/>100 Å <lb/>d <lb/>PRC2 alone <lb/>PRC2 + AavLEA1 (1:40) <lb/>90°G <lb/>lobal resolution: 3.8 Å <lb/>100 Å <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>Representative micrographs and their CTFs <lb/>100 Å <lb/>2D class averages <lb/>90 nm <lb/>90 nm <lb/>90 nm <lb/>90 nm <lb/>Fig. 2 | High-resolution cryo-EM structure determination of fragile human <lb/>Polymerase alpha-Primase and Polycomb repressive complex 2 using nema-<lb/>tode AavLEA1. Cryo-EM single-particle analysis of human polymerase α-primase <lb/>complex (PP), (a-c), and polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2), panels (d-f), both <lb/>with the addition of Nematode AavLEA1. a, d Display representative micrographs <lb/>and CTFs-cropped up to the ice ring for the complexes both alone and with <lb/>AavLEA1 added at a 1:40 ratio, highlighting improved sample preservation due to <lb/>LEA protein addition. Representative micrographs were chosen out of 42 (a) top, <lb/>4403 (a) bottom, 5 (d) top, and 2843 (d) bottom. b, e Depict 2D class averages, <lb/>illustrating defined and consistent particle shapes with visible protein features <lb/>when AavLEA1 was used. Finally, c, f show reconstructed cryo-EM maps of the <lb/>complexes from the AavLEA1 datasets, presented in two orientations. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>we added a divalent cation, MgCl 2 , to the sample buffer to neutralize <lb/>the negatively charged LWI surface, with the hope that this strategy <lb/>would change the PRC2 particle orientation distribution. However, this <lb/>approach did not improve the particle orientation distribution and <lb/>instead made it worse with more limited views (Supplementary Fig. 9). <lb/>Next, we investigated the effect of mild glutaraldehyde cross-<lb/>linking on PRC2 prior to freezing with RvLEAM short to determine if this <lb/>could improve particle orientation distribution. Our rationale was that <lb/>the glutaraldehyde reaction would neutralize the positively charged <lb/>groups on the surface of PRC2 and lead to particle orientation dis-<lb/>tribution changes, as has been demonstrated by past studies 18,19,52 . <lb/>Chemical crosslinking also has the benefit of stabilizing the complex <lb/>for improved structural homogeneity 18,19 . We collected cryo-EM data-<lb/>sets of crosslinked PRC2 with RvLEAM short at a 1:6 sample:LEA molar <lb/>ratio; the PRC2 samples were crosslinked with glutaraldehyde for 2 and <lb/>10 min (Supplementary Fig. 10). <lb/>Our analysis indicated that chemical crosslinking improved the <lb/>orientation distribution of PRC2 particles (Fig. 5a and Supplementary <lb/>Figs. 11, 12). The map sphericity increased from 0.79 in non-crosslinked <lb/>samples to 0.83 after 2 min of crosslinking. Extending the crosslinking <lb/>to 10 min further enhanced this value to 0.97 (Supplementary Table 2). <lb/>This incremental improvement suggests that longer crosslinking <lb/>durations may be slightly more effective. The 10 min crosslinked <lb/>sample dataset enabled us to achieve a 3.1 Å global resolution cryo-EM <lb/>map of the PRC2 complex (Fig. 5b). This map represents the highest <lb/>resolution yet reported for the human PRC2 apo-state complex. Given <lb/>that the map was reconstructed from a dataset collected on a 200 kV <lb/>microscope, using a 300 kV microscope could potentially yield an even <lb/>higher resolution. Our PRC2 model, built using this cryo-EM map, has a <lb/>structure similar to that obtained through the streptavidin-biotin <lb/>affinity EM grid approach 25,44 , with the RMSD between the two aligned <lb/>structures being 0.89 Å (Supplementary Figs. 13, 14 and Supplemen-<lb/>tary Table 3). <lb/>A control 10 min crosslinked PRC2 cryo-EM dataset without <lb/>RvLEAM short was also collected to determine the effect of adding LEA <lb/>proteins crosslinked samples. While discernable and somewhat <lb/>homogeneous particles were observed, the subsequent single-particle <lb/>analysis revealed that most particles were broken subcomplexes of <lb/>PRC2 (Supplementary Fig. 15), a result consistent with a previous <lb/>study 47 . Nonetheless, we obtained a 4.3 Å cryo-EM map of an intact <lb/>PRC2 complex (Supplementary Fig. 15), although the efficiency was <lb/>modest; from 3274 movies, ~1.7 million particles were picked, but only <lb/>about ~3% contributed to the final cryo-EM map reconstruction (Sup-<lb/>plementary Fig. 15). In contrast, with the addition of RvLEAM short , ~14% <lb/>of initially picked particles (~2.5 million particles) were utilized in the <lb/>final reconstruction (Supplementary Fig. 12). Furthermore, particles <lb/>from the crosslinked control dataset suffered from biased particle <lb/>orientation, with a 3DFSC calculated sphericity value of 0.66. The <lb/>inclusion of RvLEAM short improved the sphericity value to 0.97 (Sup-<lb/>plementary Table 2). Overall, the above comparison suggests the <lb/>addition of RvLEAM short enhanced the stability and particle orientation <lb/>distribution of crosslinked PRC2 complexes. <lb/>Comparative analysis of LEA proteins and CHAPSO as AWI <lb/>damage mitigation strategies <lb/>CHAPSO, a zwitterionic detergent, can mitigate AWI damage to protein <lb/>samples during plunge freezing 17,53 . In our hands, it is an effective <lb/>strategy for determining the high-resolution cryo-EM structures of PP-<lb/>related complexes 40,54 . Hence, we wanted to compare LEA protein&apos;s <lb/>efficiency in obtaining a high-resolution cryo-EM structure against that <lb/>of CHAPSO. To this end, we determined a 3.4 Å cryo-EM map of apo-<lb/>state PP using CHAPSO (Fig. 6a and Supplementary Fig. 16). By visual <lb/>inspection, we found no discernable differences between the two cryo-<lb/>EM maps or modeled structures (compared to the 40:1 AavLEA1:PP <lb/>cryo-EM map, Supplementary Figs. 17, 18 and Table 1). However, three <lb/>separate empirical analyses, Reslog 55 (Fig. 6b), per-particle spectral <lb/>signal-to-noise (ppSSNR) 56 (Fig. 6c), and Rosenthal-Henderson 57 <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 19) plots, all pointed to the AavLEA1 dataset <lb/>having the better particle image quality. It is possible that thicker ice in <lb/>the CHAPSO dataset impacted particle image quality, explaining the <lb/>observed differences. Nonetheless, our results demonstrate that Aav-<lb/>LEA1, when used as a sample additive, can achieve cryo-EM map quality <lb/>comparable to, or even better than, that obtained with detergents. <lb/>A major advantage of using AavLEA1 over CHAPSO, or other <lb/>detergents, is its effectiveness when cryo-EM samples are limited or <lb/>unstable at high concentrations. CHAPSO and similar detergents <lb/>typically require high sample concentrations 51,58 -over 4 mg/mL or <lb/>~13 μM for a 300 kDa protein sample-which can be challenging for <lb/>precious samples. In contrast, with AavLEA1, we used only 1-1.5 μM of <lb/>sample protein, which is more than ten times less than that required <lb/>for CHAPSO or detergents in general. While the application of LEA <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>c <lb/>100 Å <lb/>2D class averages <lb/>Representative micrograph and CTF <lb/>PP + RvLEAMshort (1:6) <lb/>100 Å <lb/>d <lb/>e <lb/>f <lb/>100 Å <lb/>Representative micrograph and CTF <lb/>PRC2 + RvLEAMshort (1:6) <lb/>2D class averages <lb/>100 Å <lb/>Global resolution: 4.5 Å <lb/>Global resolution: 3.7 Å <lb/>90°9 <lb/>0°9 <lb/>0 nm <lb/>90 nm <lb/>Fig. 3 | A truncated form of LEA protein from tardigrade also mitigates AWI <lb/>sample damage. Cryo-EM single-particle analysis of protein complexes with <lb/>RvLEAM short . a, d Display representative micrographs and CTFs-cropped up to the <lb/>ice ring-out of the 1308 and 3896 collected respectively of the polymerase-primase <lb/>complex (PP) and Polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2), each treated with <lb/>RvLEAM short at a molar ratio of 1:6. b, e Show 2D class averages, which demonstrate <lb/>the structural homogeneity and quality of the sample with RvLEAM short added. <lb/>c, f Present the reconstructed cryo-EM maps of PP and PRC2, depicted in two <lb/>orientations, achieving resolutions of 4.5 and 3.7 Å, respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>proteins can lead to an anisotropic distribution of particle orientations <lb/>(see Result section: Samples with LEA proteins addition distribute at <lb/>vitrified ice surfaces and Fig. 4b, c), this issue does not arise with the <lb/>use of CHAPSO. The particles in the CHAPSO dataset have an even <lb/>distribution of particle orientations (Supplementary Fig. 16 and <lb/>Table 2). Consequently, the calculated sphericity value of the PP cryo-<lb/>EM map from the CHAPSO dataset is 0.99. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>In summary, we have shown that two group three LEA proteins, Aav-<lb/>LEA1 from nematodes and RvLEAM (truncated) from tardigrades, can <lb/>mitigate sample damage caused by sample interaction with the AWI <lb/>during cryo-EM plunge freezing. We demonstrated the effects on two <lb/>model multi-subunit protein complexes, human PP and PRC2, in the <lb/>apo-state, both challenging targets for cryo-EM analysis. By simply <lb/>adding AavLEA1 or RvLEAM short to the samples before plunge freezing, <lb/>we determined the cryo-EM structures of both PP and PRC2 at com-<lb/>parable, or better resolution than those previously reported using <lb/>more <lb/>challenging <lb/>and <lb/>complicated <lb/>anti-AWI <lb/>damage <lb/>strategies 20,42-44,47 . It is important to note that these fragile samples did <lb/>not yield any discernable monodisperse particles using standard <lb/>plunge freezing methods. Therefore, our results underscore the <lb/>effectiveness of LEA proteins in revitalizing cryo-EM projects that <lb/>would otherwise be deemed unfeasible. While our study demonstrates <lb/>the effectiveness of LEA proteins in mitigating AWI damage for PP and <lb/>PRC2 complexes, further investigation is needed to determine their <lb/>applicability to other macromolecular assemblies, membrane pro-<lb/>teins, or smaller protein complexes. <lb/>The LEA proteins require lower sample concentration com-<lb/>pared to other AWI mitigation solutions, such as Spotiton 31-33 or <lb/>detergents 51,58,59 , offering a significant advantage when working with <lb/>limited samples or those prone to aggregation at high concentra-<lb/>tions. Another common solution for accommodating low sample <lb/>concentrations is the use of cryo-EM grids with support films. <lb/>However, the quality of these specialized EM grids can vary due to <lb/>production batch reproducibility, and they can be technically <lb/>a <lb/>Density of particles (normalized) <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>2 min crosslinked PRC2 <lb/>Sphericity = 0.83 <lb/>10 min crosslinked PRC2 <lb/>Sphericity = 0.97 <lb/>b <lb/>90°G <lb/>lobal resolution: 3.1 Å <lb/>100 Å <lb/>Fig. 5 | Chemical crosslinking enhances the orientation distribution of PRC2 <lb/>particles in the presence of RvLEAM short . a Displays Mollweide projections of the <lb/>particle orientation distribution for the Polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2) <lb/>treated with chemical crosslinking for 2 and 10 min, demonstrating improved <lb/>isotropy as evidenced by the increased sphericity values of 0.83 and 0.97, <lb/>respectively. b Shows the high-resolution cryo-EM maps of PRC2 crosslinked for <lb/>10 min, presented in two orientations to highlight the detailed structural features <lb/>achieved, with a global resolution of 3.1 Å. <lb/>b <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>250 <lb/>200 <lb/>150 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>PRC2 + RvLEAMshort (1:6) <lb/>c <lb/>Ice contamination <lb/>PR C2 par ticl es <lb/>Vit rifi ed ice <lb/>100 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>700 <lb/>180 <lb/>140 <lb/>20 <lb/>60 <lb/>PP + AavLEA1 (1:40) <lb/>Ice contamination <lb/>Hole edge <lb/>Vitrifie d ice <lb/>PP partic les <lb/>a PP + AavLEA1 (1:40) <lb/>PP + RvLEAMshort (1:6) <lb/>PRC2 + AavLEA1 (1:40) <lb/>PRC2 + RvLEAMshort (1:6) <lb/>Sphericity = 0.98 <lb/>Sphericity = 0.83 <lb/>Sphericity = 0.77 <lb/>Sphericity = 0.79 <lb/>Density of particles (normalized) <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>nm <lb/>nm <lb/>nm <lb/>nm <lb/>Fig. 4 | Samples with LEA protein addition distribute at vitrified ice surfaces. <lb/>Particle orientation distribution and cryo-electron tomography (cryo-ET) analysis <lb/>for samples with LEA proteins addition. a Displays Mollweide projections that <lb/>compare the particle distribution for the polymerase α-primase complex (PP) and <lb/>Polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2) with AavLEA1 (1:40) and RvLEAM short (1:6) <lb/>added respectively. Corresponding sphericity values demonstrate the degree of <lb/>isotropy achieved in the cryo-EM map under each condition. b, c Show cryo-ET <lb/>cross-sectional analysis of the spatial distribution of PP and PRC2 particles within <lb/>the grid holes, respectively. These plots highlight the location of particles relative <lb/>to the edge of the holes and identify regions affected by ice contamination. The <lb/>axes are expressed in pixels, with a scale of 4.4 Å per pixel. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>challenging to produce in research laboratories. Unlike these <lb/>methods, the application of LEA proteins does not require specia-<lb/>lized grids and is compatible with standard cryo-EM holey grids. <lb/>While the utilization of LEA proteins can lead to preferred particle <lb/>orientation problems and varying degrees of anisotropy depending <lb/>on the sample, this issue is not insurmountable. It can be mitigated <lb/>by employing chemical crosslinking 18 or tilted-stage data collection <lb/>strategies 14 . Additionally, given that the proteins adhere to LEA-<lb/>water interfaces, the molar ratio between the sample and LEA pro-<lb/>teins may not be a key optimization parameter for sample grid <lb/>plunge freezing. Rather, the concentration of LEA proteins used is <lb/>important. In our hands, a minimum of 6 µM LEA proteins was suf-<lb/>ficient to mitigate AWI damage to fragile samples. <lb/>We believe that LEA proteins represent a promising avenue for <lb/>structural biologists to revisit cryo-EM projects previously hindered by <lb/>AWI issues, particularly those that have exhausted conventional AWI <lb/>mitigation strategies. These proteins can be produced in large quan-<lb/>tities using standard bacterial expression systems and purification <lb/>schemes, providing a sustainable and cost-effective alternative to <lb/>methods that rely on more expensive and perishable materials and <lb/>reagents. Most importantly, the accessibility and economic benefits of <lb/>LEA proteins enable any structural biology laboratory or cryo-EM <lb/>facility to readily adopt this method, potentially revolutionizing their <lb/>approach to cryo-EM structure determination. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Expression and purification of AavLEA1 and RvLEAM short <lb/>The expression plasmid for HIS-tagged AavLEA1 was sourced from the <lb/>Addgene plasmid repository [pET15b-AavLEA1, a gift from Claude <lb/>Férec (Addgene plasmid # 53093)] 60 . The expression plasmid for HIS-<lb/>tagged RvLEAM short was constructed by inserting a truncated cDNA <lb/>from pEThT-RvLEAM [pEThT-RvLEAM was a gift from Takekazu <lb/>Kunieda (Addgene plasmid # 90033)] 49 into a pET15b vector. <lb/>RvLEAM short encodes residues 58-181 of RvLEAM (A0A0E4AVP3.1). <lb/>Both recombinant AavLEA1 and RvLEAM short were expressed in <lb/>Escherichia coli BL21 (DE3) cells. A single bacterial colony containing <lb/>the transformed plasmid was cultured overnight in 2 mL of Luria Ber-<lb/>tani broth (LB) with 100 µg mL -1 carbenicillin at 37 °C. This starter <lb/>culture was then used to inoculate 1 L of LB supplemented with the <lb/>same antibiotic. At an optical density (A600) of 0.6, gene expression <lb/>was induced using 0.1 mM isopropyl-β-D-thiogalactopyranoside (IPTG) <lb/>for 16 h at 12 °C and shaken at 230 rpm. <lb/>Cells were harvested by centrifugation, resuspended in lysis buf-<lb/>fer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, 10 mM imidazole, 1 mM DTT <lb/>or TCEP, 1 mM PMSF), and lysed via sonication. The cell debris was then <lb/>removed by centrifugation. The clarified lysate was incubated with pre-<lb/>equilibrated nickel-NTA resin (Qiagen, Germany) and stirred for 1 h at <lb/>4 °C. The protein-bound resin was washed three times with 50 mL of <lb/>lysis buffer. Proteins were eluted with 10 mL of elution buffer (wash <lb/>buffer supplemented with 250 mM imidazole) using a gravity flow <lb/>column. The proteins were then concentrated to ~500 μL using a 3 kDa <lb/>MWCO spin column and further purified on a Superdex 75 10/300 size-<lb/>exclusion chromatography (SEC) column (Cytiva, USA) pre-<lb/>equilibrated with SEC buffer (50 mM HEPES pH 7.5, 300 mM NaCl, <lb/>1 mM TCEP, 10% glycerol). Eluted fractions were analyzed by SDS-<lb/>PAGE. Chosen fractions were pooled, concentrated, snap-frozen in <lb/>5-10 µL aliquots, and stored at -80 °C until use. The protein con-<lb/>centration of the aliquots was determined using the Beer-Lambert <lb/>equation, with absorbance measurements obtained from a NanoDrop <lb/>spectrophotometer (Thermo Fisher, USA) and extinction coefficients <lb/>calculated based on their protein sequences. <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>90°G <lb/>lobal resolution: 3.4 Å <lb/>100 Å <lb/>c <lb/>ResLog Analysis <lb/>Per-particle spectra SNR Analysis <lb/>Batch size (log scale) <lb/>Spatial frequency (1/Å) <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.22 <lb/>0.24 <lb/>0.26 <lb/>0.28 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.32 <lb/>10 3 <lb/>10 4 <lb/>10 5 <lb/>AavLEA1 <lb/>(1:40) <lb/>CHAPSO <lb/>(4 mM) <lb/>CHAPSO <lb/>AavLEA1 <lb/>Ln(ppSSNR) <lb/>Spatial frequency (1/Å) <lb/>0.35 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.15 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>-18 <lb/>-16 <lb/>-14 <lb/>-12 <lb/>-10 <lb/>-8 <lb/>-6 <lb/>-4 <lb/>Fig. 6 | Comparative evaluation of LEA Proteins and CHAPSO as AWI damage <lb/>mitigation strategies. a Showcases the reconstructed cryo-EM map of the <lb/>polymerase α-primase complex, visualized in two orientations, achieving a global <lb/>resolution of 3.4 Å. b, c Detail the ResLog and per-particle spectra SNR (ppSSNR) <lb/>analyses respectively, comparing the effects of AavLEA1 and CHAPSO addition on <lb/>particle image data and map reconstruction quality. The ResLog analysis in panel <lb/>(b) illustrates the spatial frequency improvements associated with each additive, <lb/>plotted against batch size on a logarithmic scale, indicating that AavLEA1 out-<lb/>performs CHAPSO at higher spatial frequencies. c Displays the logarithm of <lb/>ppSSNR, demonstrating that AavLEA1 maintains higher SNR values across the <lb/>majority of the spatial frequencies tested. Source data are provided as a Source <lb/>Data file. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>Production of recombinant human DNA polymerase alpha-<lb/>primase <lb/>Recombinant human Polα-primase was expressed and purified as <lb/>previously described 54 . Briefly, Trichoplusia ni (T.ni) cells (Expression <lb/>System) were infected with four baculoviruses (POLA1, POLA2, PRIM1, <lb/>and PRIM2) for the co-expression of human Polα-primase. The infec-<lb/>ted T.ni cells were collected for protein purification after 66-68 h post-<lb/>infection. The human Polα-primase was obtained using a tandem <lb/>affinity approach. First, His-tagged POLA2, PRIM1, and PRIM2 were <lb/>captured using Ni-NTA agarose resin (Qiagen). The elute was then <lb/>subjected to a second pull-down using Strep-Tactin XT 4Flow-resin <lb/>(IBA LifeScience) for strep-tagged POLA1. The purified Polα-primase <lb/>complex was verified using SDS-PAGE analysis. <lb/>Production of recombinant human polycomb repressive <lb/>complex 2 <lb/>Purified recombinant human polycomb repressive complex 2 (PRC2) <lb/>protein complexes were generously provided by Dr. Tom Cech at the <lb/>University of Colorado Boulder 44 . <lb/>PRC2 cryo-EM sample glutaraldehyde crosslinking <lb/>Approximately 2 µM of PRC2 was incubated with a 0.1% (v/v) final <lb/>concentration of glutaraldehyde for 2-and 10-min intervals. After <lb/>each interval, an aliquot was removed and quenched with 80 mM <lb/>Tris-HCl to stop the reaction. SDS-PAGE was then used to assess <lb/>the crosslinking efficiency of the PRC2 samples at each incubation <lb/>time point. <lb/>All samples were thawed just prior to cryo-EM grid preparation. <lb/>Holey carbon cryo-EM grids, either Quantifoil R 1.2/1.3 300 mesh Au <lb/>or C-flat R 1.2/1.3 300 mesh Au, were glow discharged using a PELCO <lb/>EasiGlow glow-discharge unit (15 mA for 30 s with a 10-s hold). <lb/>These treated grids were used within 30 minutes. Protein samples <lb/>were diluted to the working concentration immediately before <lb/>application to the grid. Where indicated, the sample (~3.5 μL) was <lb/>supplemented with LEA proteins, CHAPSO, or MgCl 2 just before <lb/>being applied to the glow-discharged grid. Typically, the high-<lb/>concentration LEA protein stock was first diluted to an intermediate <lb/>working solution using the sample buffer and then mixed with the <lb/>sample (e.g., 2 μL of LEA with 2 μL of the sample). The grid was then <lb/>blotted for 4 to 6 s at 4 °C and 95% humidity before being plunged <lb/>frozen into liquid ethane using a Vitrobot Mark IV (Thermo <lb/>Fisher, USA). <lb/>For all conditions except those specified, 1-1.5 μM of PP or PRC2 <lb/>were used with the indicated molar ratio of AavLEA1 or RvLEAMshort. <lb/>For conditions with PP and 4 mM CHAPSO, 13.8 μM of PP was utilized. <lb/>Cryo-EM data collection <lb/>All data collections and screenings were conducted on a Talos Arctica <lb/>200 kV TEM (Thermo Fisher Scientific, USA) equipped with a Gatan <lb/>BioQuantum K3 direct electron detector (Gatan, USA). Data screening <lb/>and acquisition were managed using either EPU (Thermo Fisher, USA) <lb/>or SerialEM 61 . All cryo-EM datasets were collected at a pixel size of <lb/>1.064 Å/pixel, with a total dose of 50 e -Å -2 distributed across 40 <lb/>frames. The CDS counting mode was utilized along with a 20 eV energy <lb/>filter slit. The defocus range was set between -1 and -2.5 μm in 0.25-μm <lb/>intervals. <lb/>Cryo-EM data processing <lb/>For all datasets, image processing was carried out using cryoSPARC 62 . <lb/>In brief, movies were subjected to patch motion correction, and the <lb/>aligned micrographs had their contrast transfer function (CTF) esti-<lb/>mated. The CTF values were utilized to select a subset of micrographs <lb/>deemed suitable for high-resolution single-particle analysis. Detailed <lb/>procedures for subsequent image processing steps specific to each <lb/>dataset are outlined below: <lb/>1.5 μM PP, 12 μM AavLEA1 (1:8) dataset. A total of 2764 movies were <lb/>collected. After micrograph curation 2112 movies remained and <lb/>1,724,984 particles were extracted and binned 4x binning (4.3 Å/pixel). <lb/>After 2D classification, 785,653 particles proceeded to ab initio <lb/>reconstruction and were sorted into four separated reference-free 3D <lb/>classes. Particles underwent another round of ab initio modeling and <lb/>separated into two classes. The intact complex was re-extracted at <lb/>1.1 Å/pixel and was sorted into one of the two classes (239,029 parti-<lb/>cles, 75%). Non-uniform refinement of this class with per-particle CTF <lb/>refinement resulted in a global resolution (reported at Fourier shell <lb/>correlation of 0.143) of 3.6 Å. <lb/>1.5 μM PP, 60 μM AavLEA1 (1:40) dataset. A total of 4403 movies <lb/>were collected. After micrograph curation, 500 movies were initi-<lb/>ally used, with a total of 340,430 particles extracted at 4x binning. <lb/>From 2D classification, 201,337 particles were selected and re-<lb/>extracted at the original pixel size. Particles then proceeded to ab <lb/>initio reconstruction and were sorted into four separated reference-<lb/>free 3D classes. Two of the four classes resulted in intact particles, <lb/>which were verified through non-uniform refinement of the com-<lb/>bined classes using 165,472 particles, resulting in a 3.8 Å structure. <lb/>Particles were extracted from the remaining 3771 movies and bin-<lb/>ned 4x, resulting in 2,668,602 particles. These particles were then <lb/>sorted into 2D classes, and the selected 1,438,074 particles under-<lb/>went ab initio modeling. Selected particles underwent another <lb/>round of ab initio modeling with two classes. One of the two classes <lb/>showed intact particles, and those 1,009,026 particles were sent to <lb/>non-uniform refinement yielding a 3.4 Å global resolution. CryoS-<lb/>parc global and local CTF refinement jobs were run, followed by <lb/>further filtering, resulting in 988,417 particles. These particles were <lb/>then extracted at the original pixel size, 1.1 Å/pixel. All resulting <lb/>particles underwent non-uniform refinement, reference motion <lb/>correction, and heterogeneous refinement. 856,205 particles were <lb/>used for a final non-uniform refinement, with a final global resolu-<lb/>tion of 3.0 Å. <lb/>1 µM PP, 6 µM RvLEAM short (1:6) dataset. A total of 1308 movies were <lb/>collected. Following micrograph curation, 335,907 particles were <lb/>extracted from 1076 micrographs and binned 4x. About 125,231 par-<lb/>ticles were extracted with 2D classification. These particles then pro-<lb/>ceeded to ab initio reconstruction and split into 3D classes. The <lb/>selected 74,198 particles were re-extracted at the original pixel size <lb/>(1.1 Å/pixel) from 1071 micrographs. Particles underwent another <lb/>round of 2D classification and ab initio 3D reconstruction. Selected <lb/>particles underwent non-uniform refinement and had a final global <lb/>resolution of 4.5 Å. The final resolution of this dataset is lower than our <lb/>other PP datasets which is likely because this data collection contains <lb/>only 1308 movies while other PP datasets have 2700 or more movies. <lb/>13.8 μM PP, 4 mM CHAPSO dataset. A total of 4567 movies were <lb/>collected. Following micrograph curation, 1,832,455 particles were <lb/>extracted from 4510 micrographs and binned 4x. Particles underwent <lb/>2D classification where and ab initio reconstruction. Selected particles <lb/>were re-extracted at the original pixel size of 1.1 Å/pixel (744,824 par-<lb/>ticles). Extracted particles were then sorted into 2D classes and <lb/>underwent non-uniform refinement with per-particle CTF refinement <lb/>and reference motion correction, with a final global resolution of 3.4 Å <lb/>with 674,793 particles. <lb/>1.5 μM PRC2, 60 μM AavLEA1 (1:40) dataset. A total of 2843 movies <lb/>were collected. Following micrograph curation, 687,121 particles were <lb/>extracted from 1642 micrographs and binned 4x. Particles underwent <lb/>2D classification and ab initio reconstruction. Selected classes were re-<lb/>extracted at the original pixel size, 1.1 Å/pixel, yielding 150,359 parti-<lb/>cles. The re-extracted particles underwent non-uniform refinement <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>with per-particle CTF refinement and resulted in a global resolu-<lb/>tion of 3.8 Å. <lb/>1 μM PRC2, 6.7 μM RvLEAM short (~1:6) dataset. A total of 3896 movies <lb/>were collected. Following micrograph curation, 1,766,944 particles <lb/>were extracted from 3637 micrographs and binned 4x. Particles were <lb/>sorted into 2D classes followed by 3D classes via ab initio recon-<lb/>struction. The selected 547,610 particles were re-extracted at 1.1 Å/ <lb/>pixel and subjected to ab initio 3D reconstruction. The final 206,807 <lb/>particles underwent non-uniform refinement with per-particle CTF <lb/>refinement, resulting in a global resolution of 3.7 Å. <lb/>1 μM PRC2, 6.7 μM RvLEAM short (~1:6) 10 mM MgCl 2 dataset. A total <lb/>of 4333 movies were collected. Following micrograph curation, <lb/>1,755,138 particles were extracted from 3759 micrographs and bin-<lb/>ned 4x. Particles underwent two rounds of 2D classification. From <lb/>here, 408,373 particles were selected and proceeded to ab initio 3D <lb/>reconstruction. The resulting 406,148 particles were re-extracted <lb/>from 3746 movies at the original pixel size (1.1 Å/pixel) and under-<lb/>went another round of ab initio reconstruction. The final 102,181 <lb/>particles proceeded to non-uniform refinement with a final global <lb/>resolution was 4.2 Å. <lb/>1 μM PRC2 crosslinked 2 min, 6.7 μM RvLEAM short (~1:6) dataset. A <lb/>total of 2981 movies were collected. Following micrograph curation, <lb/>982,264 particles were extracted from 2189 movies and binned 4x. <lb/>Particles were sorted into 2D classes followed by 3D classes via ab initio <lb/>reconstruction. Selected particles were re-extracted at the original <lb/>pixel size (1.1 Å/pixel) and underwent ab initio reconstruction again. <lb/>The resulting 534,068 particles were subjected to non-uniform <lb/>refinement with per-particle CTF refinement, resulting in a global <lb/>resolution of 3.5 Å. <lb/>1 μM PRC2 crosslinked 10 min, 6.7 μM RvLEAM short (~1:6) dataset. A <lb/>total of 3432 movies were collected. Following micrograph curation, <lb/>2,084,816 particles were extracted from 3295 movies and binned 4x. <lb/>Particles underwent 2D classification followed by ab initio 3D recon-<lb/>struction. Selected particles were re-extracted at the original pixel size <lb/>(1.1 Å/pixel). Particles underwent non-uniform refinement, resulting in <lb/>a global resolution of 3.3 Å. Global CTF refinement, reference-based <lb/>motion correction, and heterogeneous refinement jobs were run. <lb/>366,459 particles were used in this final round of non-uniform refine-<lb/>ment, resulting in a global resolution of 3.1 Å. <lb/>1 μM PRC2 crosslinked 10 min dataset. A total of 3274 movies were <lb/>collected. Following micrograph curation, 1,231,903 particles were <lb/>extracted from 3274 movies and binned 4x. Particles underwent 2D <lb/>classification followed by ab initio 3D reconstruction. Selected <lb/>particles were re-extracted at the original pixel size (1.1 Å/pixel) and <lb/>underwent a second batch of ab initio 3D reconstruction, reference-<lb/>based motion correction non-uniform refinement. The final 51,494 <lb/>particles resulted in a global resolution of 4.3 Å. <lb/>Cryo-EM structure modeling and refinement <lb/>The published apo-state models of Polymerase alpha-primase (PP, <lb/>PDB: 5EXR) 46 and Polycomb Repressive Complex 2 (PRC2, PDB: <lb/>8FYH) 44 were used as initial models for real-space refinement against <lb/>their respective cryo-EM maps using Phenix 63 . Structural alignments <lb/>between the published models and the refined models were per-<lb/>formed using the MatchMaker module in ChimeraX 64 . Refinement <lb/>statistics and validation reports are provided in Supplementary <lb/>Tables 1, 3 for PP and PRC2, respectively. Q-score 65 analysis was con-<lb/>ducted for each refined model and reported in the abovementioned <lb/>tables. <lb/>Particle image quality and orientation distribution analysis <lb/>ResLog plots were generated using the ResLog job in cryoSPARC 62 . <lb/>Rosenthal-Henderson plots were derived from the data utilized in the <lb/>ResLog plot, following the method described by Rosenthal and <lb/>Henderson 57 . The per-particle spectral signal-to-noise ratio (ppSSNR) <lb/>plots were produced using the FSC_noisesub data from the ResLog <lb/>Analysis job in cryoSPARC. Particles were segmented into stacks of <lb/>30,000, 60,000, 90,000, 120,000, and 150,000 for analysis. The <lb/>ppSSNR calculations are performed as described by ref. 66. Cryo-EM <lb/>map sphericity values are calculated using the 3DFSC server 14 . The <lb/>conical FSC area ratio (cFAR) and sampling compensation factor <lb/>(SCF) 56,67 were computed using CryoSPARC 62 . <lb/>Tilt-series collection <lb/>Tilt series were collected on a Titan Krios (Thermo Fisher Scientific, <lb/>USA) operating at 300 kV, equipped with a K3 summit direct electron <lb/>detector and a Quantum energy filter (Gatan, USA), controlled by <lb/>SerialEM 61 . Images were collected with an exposure of 8 e-/pixel/s on <lb/>the detector, with the camera operating in CDS mode, with a calibrated <lb/>pixel size of 1.1 Å per pixel. Tilt series were collected using a dose-<lb/>symmetric tilt scheme from -45°to 45°with a tilt increment of 3°and <lb/>nominal defocus between 2 and 4 μm 68 . Each tilt angle was collected as <lb/>a five-frame movie, with an exposure of 5 e -/Å 2 per tilt, and, therefore, a <lb/>total exposure of 150 e -/Å 2 per tilt series. <lb/>Tilt-series data processing <lb/>Each movie was whole frame aligned using the Unblur package in <lb/>cisTEM 69 . Tilt series were aligned and reconstructed at a binning factor <lb/>4 using AreTomo 70 . To further enhance the contrast of protein parti-<lb/>cles for better localization, the reconstructed tomograms were <lb/>denoised using IsoNet 71 . The reconstructions are shown in Supple-<lb/>mentary Movies 1, 2. These movies were created using 3dmod from the <lb/>IMOD package 72 and ImageJ 73 . <lb/>Particle localization and ice surface estimation <lb/>Particles in the tomograms were picked manually with Dynamo 74 . The <lb/>surfaces of vitrified ice were determined via three markers: crystalline <lb/>ice contaminations above the ice, carbon edges, and the protein layers, <lb/>which are assumed to be close to the surface. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Reporting summary <lb/>Further information on research design is available in the Nature <lb/>Portfolio Reporting Summary linked to this article. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>The described cryo-EM maps and coordinate files have been deposited <lb/>in the Electron Microscopy Data Bank and the Protein Data Bank (PDB) <lb/>under the following accession codes: Polymerase alpha-primase <lb/>(PP)-AavLEA1, 1:8 molar ratio under code EMD-43619, PP-AavLEA1, <lb/>1:40 molar ratio under codes PDB-ID 8VY3 and EMD-43628, <lb/>PP-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio under code EMD-43626, PP-CHAPSO <lb/>4 mM under codes PDB-ID 9C8V and EMD-43627, Polycomb repressive <lb/>complex 2 (PRC2)-AavLEA1, 1:40 molar ratio under code EMD-43620, <lb/>PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio under code EMD-43621, <lb/>PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio, 10 mM MgCl 2 under code EMD-<lb/>43622, PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio, 2 min crosslink under code <lb/>EMD-43623, PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio, 10 min crosslink under <lb/>codes PDB-ID 9C8U and EMD-43625, and PRC2, 10 min crosslink under <lb/>code EMD-45273 [https://www.ebi.ac.uk/emdb/EMD-45723]. Raw <lb/>datasets (movies) and their respective gain references were deposited <lb/>in the Electron Microscopy Public Image Archive (EMPIAR): <lb/>PP-AavLEA1, 1:8 molar ratio under accession code EMPIAR-11963, <lb/>PP-AavLEA1, 1:40 molar ratio under accession code EMPIAR-11964, <lb/>PP-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio under accession code EMPIAR-11965, <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<div type="availability">PP-CHAPSO 4 mM under accession code EMPIAR-11966, <lb/>PRC2-AavLEA1, 1:40 molar ratio under accession code EMPIAR-11975, <lb/>PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio under accession code EMPIAR-<lb/>11976, PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio, 2 min crosslink under <lb/>accession code EMPIAR-11978, PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio, <lb/>10 min crosslink under accession code EMPIAR-11979, and PRC2, <lb/>10 min crosslink under accession code EMPIAR-12125. The <lb/>PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio with 10 mM MgCl 2 dataset is <lb/>uploaded as aligned micrographs, under accession code EMPIAR-<lb/>12140. Reconstructed tomograms for PP-AavLEA1, 1:8 molar ratio are <lb/>included in EMD-43619 and PRC2-RvLEAM short , 1:6 molar ratio in EMD-<lb/>43621. The following previously published PDB depositions were used <lb/>in this study: PDB-ID 8FYH and PDB-ID 5EXR. Source data are provided <lb/>with this paper. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kühlbrandt, W. The resolution revolution. Science 343, <lb/>1443-1444 (2014). <lb/>2. Han, B.-G., Avila-Sakar, A., Remis, J. &amp; Glaeser, R. M. Challenges in <lb/>making ideal cryo-EM samples. Curr. Opin. Struct. Biol. 81, <lb/>102646 (2023). <lb/>3. Xu, Y. &amp; Dang, S. Recent technical advances in sample preparation <lb/>for single-particle cryo-EM. Front. Mol. Biosci. 9, 892459 (2022). <lb/>4. D&apos;Imprima, E. et al. Protein denaturation at the air-water interface <lb/>and how to prevent it. Elife 8, e42747 (2019). <lb/>5. Noble, A. J. et al. Reducing effects of particle adsorption to the <lb/>air-water interface in cryo-EM. Nat. Methods 15, 793-795 (2018). <lb/>6. Noble, A. J. et al. Routine single particle CryoEM sample and grid <lb/>characterization by tomography. Elife 7, e34257 (2018). <lb/>7. Glaeser, R. M. Proteins, interfaces, and cryo-EM grids. Curr. Opin. <lb/>Colloid Interface Sci. 34, 1-8 (2018). <lb/>8. Glaeser, R. M. &amp; Han, B.-G. Opinion: hazards faced by macro-<lb/>molecules when confined to thin aqueous films. Biophys. Rep. 3, <lb/>1-7 (2017). <lb/>9. Taylor, K. A. &amp; Glaeser, R. M. Retrospective on the early develop-<lb/>ment of cryoelectron microscopy of macromolecules and a pro-<lb/>spective on opportunities for the future. J. Struct. Biol. 163, <lb/>214-223 (2008). <lb/>10. Kim, L. Y. et al. Benchmarking cryo-EM single particle analysis <lb/>workflow. Front. Mol. Biosci. 5, 50 (2018). <lb/>11. Adrian, M., Dubochet, J., Lepault, J. &amp; McDowall, A. W. Cryo-<lb/>electron microscopy of viruses. Nature 308, 32-36 (1984). <lb/>12. Dubochet, J., Chang, J.-J., Freeman, R., Lepault, J. &amp; McDowall, A. W. <lb/>Frozen aqueous suspensions. Ultramicroscopy 10, 55-61 (1982). <lb/>13. Glaeser, R. M. Preparing better samples for cryo-electron micro-<lb/>scopy: biochemical challenges do not end with isolation and pur-<lb/>ification. Ann. Rev. Biochem. 90, 451-474 (2021). <lb/>14. Tan, Y. Z. et al. Addressing preferred specimen orientation in single-<lb/>particle cryo-EM through tilting. Nat. Methods 14, 793-796 (2017). <lb/>15. Naydenova, K. &amp; Russo, C. J. Measuring the effects of particle <lb/>orientation to improve the efficiency of electron cryomicroscopy. <lb/>Nat. Commun. 8, 629 (2017). <lb/>16. Liu, N. &amp; Wang, H.-W. Better cryo-EM specimen preparation: how to <lb/>deal with the air-water interface? J. Mol. Biol. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1016/j.jmb.2022.167926 (2022). <lb/>17. Chen, J., Noble, A. J., Kang, J. Y. &amp; Darst, S. A. Eliminating effects of <lb/>particle adsorption to the air/water interface in single-particle cryo-<lb/>electron microscopy: bacterial RNA polymerase and CHAPSO. J. <lb/>Struct. Biol. X 1, 100005 (2019). <lb/>18. Stark, H. GraFix: stabilization of fragile macromolecular <lb/>complexes for single particle cryo-EM. Methods Enzymol. 481, <lb/>109-126 (2010). <lb/>19. Kastner, B. et al. GraFix: sample preparation for single-particle <lb/>electron cryomicroscopy. Nat. Methods 5, 53-55 (2008). <lb/>20. Kasinath, V. et al. Structures of human PRC2 with its cofactors <lb/>AEBP2 and JARID2. Science 359, 940-944 (2018). <lb/>21. Adamus, K., Le, S. N., Elmlund, H., Boudes, M. &amp; Elmlund, D. AgarFix: <lb/>simple and accessible stabilization of challenging single-particle <lb/>cryo-EM specimens through crosslinking in a matrix of agar. J. <lb/>Struct. Biol. 207, 327-331 (2019). <lb/>22. Wang, F. et al. General and robust covalently linked graphene oxide <lb/>affinity grids for high-resolution cryo-EM. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA <lb/>117, 24269-24273 (2020). <lb/>23. Wang, F. et al. Amino and PEG-amino graphene oxide grids enrich <lb/>and protect samples for high-resolution single particle cryo-<lb/>electron microscopy. J. Struct. Biol. 209, 107437 (2020). <lb/>24. Liu, N. et al. Bioactive functionalized monolayer graphene for high-<lb/>resolution cryo-electron microscopy. J. Am. Chem. Soc. 141, <lb/>4016-4025 (2019). <lb/>25. Glaeser, R. M. &amp; Han, B.-G. Streptavidin affinity grids for single-<lb/>particle cryo-EM. Microsc. Microanal. 25, 990-991 (2019). <lb/>26. Palovcak, E. et al. A simple and robust procedure for preparing <lb/>graphene-oxide cryo-EM grids. J. Struct. Biol. 204, 80-84 (2018). <lb/>27. Lu, Y. et al. Functionalized graphene grids with various charges for <lb/>single-particle cryo-EM. Nat. Commun. 13, 6718 (2022). <lb/>28. Zheng, L. et al. Uniform thin ice on ultraflat graphene for high-<lb/>resolution cryo-EM. Nat. Methods 20, 123-130 (2023). <lb/>29. Han, Y. et al. High-yield monolayer graphene grids for near-atomic <lb/>resolution cryoelectron microscopy. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 117, <lb/>1009-1014 (2020). <lb/>30. Esfahani, B. G. et al. SPOT-RASTR-a cryo-EM specimen preparation <lb/>technique that overcomes problems with preferred orientation and <lb/>the air/water interface. Biophys. J. 123 (2024). <lb/>31. Jain, T., Sheehan, P., Crum, J., Carragher, B. &amp; Potter, C. S. Spotiton: <lb/>a prototype for an integrated inkjet dispense and vitrification sys-<lb/>tem for cryo-TEM. J. Struct. Biol. 179, 68-75 (2012). <lb/>32. Darrow, M. C., Moore, J. P., Walker, R. J., Doering, K. &amp; King, R. S. <lb/>Chameleon: next generation sample preparation for cryoEM based <lb/>on Spotiton. Microsc. Microanal. 25, 994-995 (2019). <lb/>33. Dandey, V. P. et al. Time-resolved cryo-EM using Spotiton. Nat. <lb/>Methods 17, 897-900 (2020). <lb/>34. Rubinstein, J. L. et al. Shake-it-off: a simple ultrasonic cryo-EM <lb/>specimen-preparation device. Acta Crystallogr. D. Struct. Biol. 75, <lb/>1063-1070 (2019). <lb/>35. Tan, Y. Z. &amp; Rubinstein, J. L. Through-grid wicking enables high-<lb/>speed cryoEM specimen preparation. Acta Crystallogr. D. Struct. <lb/>Biol. 76, 1092-1103 (2020). <lb/>36. Hernández-Sánchez, I. E. et al. LEAfing through literature: late <lb/>embryogenesis abundant proteins coming of age -achievements <lb/>and perspectives. J. Exp. Bot. 73, 6525-6546 (2022). <lb/>37. Hibshman, J. D. &amp; Goldstein, B. LEA motifs promote desiccation <lb/>tolerance in vivo. BMC Biol. 19, 263 (2021). <lb/>38. Hibshman, J. D., Clegg, J. S. &amp; Goldstein, B. Mechanisms of desic-<lb/>cation tolerance: themes and variations in brine shrimp, round-<lb/>worms, and tardigrades. Front. Physiol. 11, 592016 (2020). <lb/>39. Goyal, K., Walton, L. J. &amp; Tunnacliffe, A. LEA proteins prevent protein <lb/>aggregation due to water stress. Biochem. J. 388, 151-157 (2005). <lb/>40. He, Q. et al. Structures of human primosome elongation com-<lb/>plexes. Nat. Struct. Mol. Biol. 30, 579-583 (2023). <lb/>41. Yin, Z., Kilkenny, M. L., Ker, D. S. &amp; Pellegrini, L. CryoEM insights into <lb/>RNA primer synthesis by the human primosome. FEBS J. 291, <lb/>1813-1829 (2024). <lb/>42. Kilkenny, M. L. et al. Structural basis for the interaction of SARS-<lb/>CoV-2 virulence factor nsp1 with DNA polymerase α-primase. Pro-<lb/>tein Sci. 31, 333-344 (2022). <lb/>43. Kasinath, V. et al. JARID2 and AEBP2 regulate PRC2 in the presence <lb/>of H2AK119ub1 and other histone modifications. Science 371, <lb/>eabc3393 (2021). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>44. Song, J. et al. Structural basis for inactivation of PRC2 by <lb/>G-quadruplex RNA. Science 381, 1331-1337 (2023). <lb/>45. Grau, D. et al. Structures of monomeric and dimeric PRC2:EZH1 <lb/>reveal flexible modules involved in chromatin compaction. Nat. <lb/>Commun. 12, 714 (2021). <lb/>46. Baranovskiy, A. G. et al. Mechanism of concerted RNA-DNA primer <lb/>synthesis by the human primosome. J. Biol. Chem. 291, <lb/>10006-10020 (2016). <lb/>47. Lipscomb, D. M. Electron Microscopy Methods to Overcome the <lb/>Challenges of Structural Heterogeneity and Preferred Orientations in <lb/>Small (sub-500 kDa) Macromolecular Complexes. Ph.D thesis, <lb/>California Univ. (2017). <lb/>48. Møbjerg, N. et al. Survival in extreme environments -on the current <lb/>knowledge of adaptations in tardigrades. Acta Physiol. 202, <lb/>409-420 (2011). <lb/>49. Tanaka, S. et al. Novel mitochondria-targeted heat-soluble proteins <lb/>identified in the anhydrobiotic tardigrade improve osmotic toler-<lb/>ance of human cells. PLoS ONE 10, e0118272 (2015). <lb/>50. Li, D. &amp; He, X. Desiccation dependent structure and stability of an <lb/>anhydrobiotic nematode late embryogenesis abundant (LEA) pro-<lb/>tein. In ASME 2009 Summer Bioengineering Conference, Parts A <lb/>and B 213-214 (American Society of Mechanical Engineers, 2009). <lb/>51. Li, B., Zhu, D., Shi, H. &amp; Zhang, X. Effect of charge on protein pre-<lb/>ferred orientation at the air-water interface in cryo-electron <lb/>microscopy. J. Struct. Biol. 213, 107783 (2021). <lb/>52. Patel, A. B. et al. Structure of human TFIID and mechanism of TBP <lb/>loading onto promoter DNA. Science 362, eaau8872 (2018). <lb/>53. Chen, S., Li, J., Vinothkumar, K. R. &amp; Henderson, R. Interaction of <lb/>human erythrocyte catalase with air -water interface in cryoEM. <lb/>Microscopy 71, i51-i59 (2022). <lb/>54. He, Q. et al. Structures of the human CST-Polα-primase complex <lb/>bound to telomere templates. Nature 608, 826-832 (2022). <lb/>55. Stagg, S. M., Noble, A. J., Spilman, M. &amp; Chapman, M. S. ResLog <lb/>plots as an empirical metric of the quality of cryo-EM reconstruc-<lb/>tions. J. Struct. Biol. 185, 418-426 (2014). <lb/>56. Baldwin, P. R. &amp; Lyumkis, D. Non-uniformity of projection distribu-<lb/>tions attenuates resolution in Cryo-EM. Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol. 150, <lb/>160-183 (2020). <lb/>57. Rosenthal, P. B. &amp; Henderson, R. Optimal determination of particle <lb/>orientation, absolute hand, and contrast loss in single-particle <lb/>electron cryomicroscopy. J. Mol. Biol. 333, 721-745 (2003). <lb/>58. Snijder, J. et al. Vitrification after multiple rounds of sample appli-<lb/>cation and blotting improves particle density on cryo-electron <lb/>microscopy grids. J. Struct. Biol. 198, 38-42 (2017). <lb/>59. Kampjut, D., Steiner, J. &amp; Sazanov, L. A. Cryo-EM grid optimization <lb/>for membrane proteins. iScience 24, 102139 (2021). <lb/>60. Tripathi, R., Benz, N., Culleton, B., Trouvé, P. &amp; Férec, C. Biophysical <lb/>characterisation of calumenin as a charged F508del-CFTR folding <lb/>modulator. PLoS ONE 9, e104970 (2014). <lb/>61. Mastronarde, D. N. Automated electron microscope tomography <lb/>using robust prediction of specimen movements. J. Struct. Biol. 152, <lb/>36-51 (2005). <lb/>62. Punjani, A., Rubinstein, J. L., Fleet, D. J. &amp; Brubaker, M. A. cryoS-<lb/>PARC: algorithms for rapid unsupervised cryo-EM structure deter-<lb/>mination. Nat. Methods 14, 290-296 (2017). <lb/>63. Adams, P. D. et al. PHENIX: a comprehensive Python-based system <lb/>for macromolecular structure solution. Acta Crystallogr. D. Biol. <lb/>Crystallogr. 66, 213-221 (2010). <lb/>64. Meng, E. C. et al. UCSF ChimeraX: tools for structure building and <lb/>analysis. Protein Sci. 32, e4792 (2023). <lb/>65. Pintilie, G. et al. Measurement of atom resolvability in cryo-EM maps <lb/>with Q-scores. Nat. Methods 17, 328-334 (2020). <lb/>66. Chan, L. M. et al. High-resolution single-particle imaging at 100-<lb/>200 keV with the Gatan Alpine direct electron detector. J. Struct. <lb/>Biol. 216, 108108 (2024). <lb/>67. Baldwin, P. R. &amp; Lyumkis, D. Tools for visualizing and analyzing <lb/>Fourier space sampling in Cryo-EM. Prog. Biophys. Mol. Biol. 160, <lb/>53-65 (2021). <lb/>68. Hagen, W. J. H., Wan, W. &amp; Briggs, J. A. G. Implementation of a cryo-<lb/>electron tomography tilt-scheme optimized for high resolution <lb/>subtomogram averaging. J. Struct. Biol. 197, 191-198 (2017). <lb/>69. Grant, T., Rohou, A. &amp; Grigorieff, N. CisTEM, user-friendly software <lb/>for single-particle image processing. Elife 7, e35383 (2018). <lb/>70. Zheng, S. et al. AreTomo: an integrated software package for <lb/>automated marker-free, motion-corrected cryo-electron tomo-<lb/>graphic alignment and reconstruction. J. Struct. Biol. X 6, <lb/>100068 (2022). <lb/>71. Liu, Y. T. et al. Isotropic reconstruction for electron tomography <lb/>with deep learning. Nat. Commun. 13, 6482 (2022). <lb/>72. Kremer, J. R., Mastronarde, D. N. &amp; McIntosh, J. R. Computer <lb/>visualization of three-dimensional image data using IMOD. J. Struct. <lb/>Biol. 116, 71-76 (1996). <lb/>73. Schneider, C. A., Rasband, W. S. &amp; Eliceiri, K. W. NIH Image to <lb/>ImageJ: 25 years of image analysis. Nat. Methods 9, 671-675 (2012). <lb/>74. Castaño-Díez, D., Kudryashev, M., Arheit, M. &amp; Stahlberg, H. <lb/>Dynamo: a flexible, user-friendly development tool for sub-<lb/>tomogram averaging of cryo-EM data in high-performance com-<lb/>puting environments. J. Struct. Biol. 178, 139-151 (2012). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We are grateful to Tom Cech, Anne Gooding, and Jiarui Song at the <lb/>University of Colorado Boulder for their generous gift of purified <lb/>recombinant human PRC2. We also extend our thanks to members of <lb/>the Lim and Grant laboratories for their valuable suggestions. Our <lb/>appreciation goes to Kliment Verba and his lab members at the Uni-<lb/>versity of California San Francisco for their assistance with our <lb/>ppSSNR calculations. We thank Lori Passmore and her lab members <lb/>at MRC LMB for providing insightful feedback on our preprint. We also <lb/>like to thank Tom Terwilliger at the Los Alamos National Lab for his <lb/>help in model refinement using the Phenix software. Lastly, we are <lb/>thankful to our colleagues Elizabeth Wright and Robert Kirchdoerfer <lb/>for their helpful feedback and suggestions. Some of this work was <lb/>performed in the Cryo-EM Research Center (CEMRC) in the Depart-<lb/>ment of Biochemistry at the University of Wisconsin-Madison. We <lb/>thank the staff at CEMRC for their support and assistance in cryo-EM <lb/>data collection. The Lim lab is a member of the SBGrid consortium <lb/>(www.sbgrid.org) and some of the analyses were performed using <lb/>software compiled by SBGrid. Support for this research was provided <lb/>to C.L. by the National Institutes of Health (NIH), the National Institute <lb/>of General Medical Sciences (R00GM131023 and DP2GM150023), <lb/>and the University of Wisconsin-Madison, Office of the Vice-<lb/>Chancellor for Research and Graduate Education with funding from <lb/>the Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation and the Department of <lb/>Biochemistry. In addition, K.M.A. is supported by an NIH T32 pre-<lb/>doctoral fellowship (T32GM130550). T.G. is an Investigator of The <lb/>Morgridge Institute for Research. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>C.L. conceived the study. K.M.A. and Q.H. made the recombinant pro-<lb/>teins. K.M.A made the cryo-EM grids, and performed data collection and <lb/>image processing with C.L. in support. C.L. and K.M.A. collected the <lb/>cryo-EM tilt-series datasets with T.G. in support. G.L. and T.G. recon-<lb/>structed the cryo-EM tomograms and performed related analyses. <lb/>K.M.A. performed the crosslinking experiments and analysis. K.M.A., <lb/>G.L., T.G., and C.L. wrote the manuscript and prepared the figures. <lb/>Competing interests <lb/>A provisional patent has been filed by C.L. for this technology with the <lb/>Wisconsin Alumni Research Foundation (WARF). The remaining authors <lb/>declare no competing interests. <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/>Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></div>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Additional information <lb/>Supplementary information The online version contains <lb/>supplementary material available at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to <lb/>Ci Ji Lim. <lb/>Peer review information Nature Communications thanks Alex Noble and <lb/>the other, anonymous, reviewer(s) for their contribution to the peer <lb/>review of this work. A peer review file is available. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at <lb/>http://www.nature.com/reprints <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jur-<lb/>isdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution-NonCommercial-NoDerivatives 4.0 International License, <lb/>which permits any non-commercial use, sharing, distribution and <lb/>reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give appropriate <lb/>credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the <lb/>Creative Commons licence, and indicate if you modified the licensed <lb/>material. You do not have permission under this licence to share adapted <lb/>material derived from this article or parts of it. The images or other third <lb/>party material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative <lb/>Commons licence, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons <lb/>licence and your intended use is not permitted by statutory regulation or <lb/>exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly <lb/>from the copyright holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by-nc-nd/4.0/. <lb/></div>

			<front>© The Author(s) 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41467-024-52091-1 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Communications | (2024) 15:7705 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
