<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>1 <lb/>Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/> from LaH 10 to room-temperature <lb/>superconductors <lb/>M. Kostrzewa 1 , K. M. Szczęśniak 2 , A. p. Durajski 3* &amp; R. Szczęśniak 1,3 <lb/>thermodynamic parameters of the LaH 10 superconductor were an object of our interest. LaH 10 is <lb/>characterised by the highest experimentally observed value of the critical temperature: = <lb/>T <lb/>215 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K <lb/>(p a = 150 GPa) and <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>260 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K (p b = 190 GPa). It belongs to the group of superconductors with a strong <lb/>electron-phonon coupling (λ a ~ 2.2 and λ b ~ 2.8). We calculated the thermodynamic parameters of this <lb/>superconductor and found that the values of the order parameter, the thermodynamic critical field, and <lb/>the specific heat differ significantly from the values predicted by the conventional BCS theory. Due to <lb/>the specific structure of the Eliashberg function for the hydrogenated compounds, the qualitative <lb/>analysis suggests that the superconductors of the La δ X 1−δ H 10 -type (LaXH-type) structure, where <lb/>X ∈ {Sc, Y}, would exhibit significantly higher critical temperature than T C obtained for LaH 10 . in the case <lb/>of LaScH we came to the following assessments: ∈ <lb/>T <lb/>220 267 <lb/>, <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K and ∈ <lb/>T <lb/>263 294 <lb/>, <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K, while the <lb/>results for LaYH were: ∈ <lb/>T <lb/>218 247 <lb/>, <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K and ∈ <lb/>T <lb/>261 274 <lb/>, <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K. <lb/></front>

			<body>The experimental discovery of the high-temperature superconducting state in the compressed hydrogen and sul-<lb/>fur systems H 2 S (T C = 150 K for p = 150 GPa) and H 3 S (T C = 203 K for p = 150 GPa) 1,2 accounts for carrying out <lb/>investigations, which can potentially lead to the discovery of a material showing the superconducting properties <lb/>at room temperature. For the first time, the possibility of the existence of the superconducting state in hydrogen-<lb/>ated compounds was pointed out by Ashcroft in 2004 3 . It was stated in his second fundamental work concerning <lb/>the high-temperature superconductivity, following his first work written in 1968, in which he propounded the <lb/>existence of the high-temperature superconducting state in metallic hydrogen 4 . The superconducting state in <lb/>hydrogenated compounds is induced by the conventional electron-phonon interaction. This fact made possible <lb/>the theoretical description of the superconducting phase in H 2 S and H 3 S even prior to carrying out the suitable <lb/>experiments 5,6 . The detailed discussion with respect to the thermodynamic properties of the superconducting <lb/>state occurring in H 2 S and H 3 S one can find in references 7-17 . <lb/>In 2018, there were held the groundbreaking experiments, which confirmed the existence of the supercon-<lb/>ducting state of extremely high values of the critical temperature in the LaH 10 compound: <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>215 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K for <lb/>p a = 150 GPa and <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>260 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K for p b ∈ (180-200) GPa (and then T <lb/>250 <lb/>C <lb/>c <lb/>K for p c ~ 170 GPa 18 ). It was proved <lb/>on the theoretical basis 19 that the results achieved by Drozdov et al. 20 can be related to the induction of the <lb/>superconducting phase in the R m <lb/>3 structure (T C = 206-223 K). The experimental results reported by <lb/>Somayazulu et al. 21 should be related to the superconducting state induced in the Fm m <lb/>3 structure, where the <lb/>critical temperature can potentially reach even the value of 280 K. From the materials science perspective, the <lb/>achieved results imply that all possible actions should be taken in order to examine the hydrogen-containing <lb/>materials with respect to the existence of the high-temperature superconducting state at room temperature. <lb/>Attention should be paid to the importance of the discovery of the high-temperature superconducting state in <lb/>LaH 10 because La can form stable hydrogenated compounds with other metals. Such materials can exhibit so <lb/>large hydrogen concentration, that they are presently taken into account as basic components of the hydrogen <lb/>cells intended for vehicle drives 22 . <lb/>The purpose of this work is, firstly, to present the performed analysis of the thermodynamic properties of <lb/>the superconducting state in the LaH 10 compound. We took advantage of the phenomenological version of the <lb/>Eliashberg equations, for which we fitted the value of the electron-phonon coupling constant on the basis of <lb/>the experimentally found T C value. Our next step consisted in examining the hydrogenated compounds of the <lb/>La δ X 1−δ H 10 -type (LaXH-type) on the basis of the achieved results in order to find a system with an even higher <lb/>value of the critical temperature. Taking into account the structure of the Eliashberg function for hydrogenated <lb/></body>

			<front>1 Institute of Physics, Jan Długosz University in Częstochowa, Ave. Armii Krajowej 13/15, 42-200, Częstochowa, <lb/>Poland. 2 Faculty of Chemistry, University of Warsaw, Pasteura 1, 02-093, Warsaw, Poland. 3 Institute of Physics, <lb/>Częstochowa University of Technology, Ave. Armii Krajowej 19, 42-200, Częstochowa, Poland. *email: adurajski@ <lb/>wip.pcz.pl <lb/>open <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>compounds, with its distinctly separated parts coming from the heavy elements and from hydrogen, we assumed <lb/>X to be Sc or Y, what would, in our opinion, fill the gap in the Eliashberg function occurring within the range <lb/>from about 40 meV to 100 meV. A significant increase in the value of critical temperature should take place as a <lb/>consequence. <lb/>computational Details, Results and Discussion <lb/>The thermodynamic parameters of the LaH 10 superconductor were calculated by means of Eliashberg equations <lb/>on the imaginary axis 23 : <lb/>∑ <lb/>π <lb/>μ <lb/>Δ <lb/>= <lb/>Ω − Ω − <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω + Δ <lb/>Δ <lb/>=− <lb/>Z <lb/>k T <lb/>K <lb/>[ ( <lb/>) <lb/>( )] <lb/>, <lb/>(1) <lb/>n n <lb/>B <lb/>m <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>n <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/> <lb/>and <lb/>∑ <lb/>π <lb/>= + <lb/>Ω − Ω <lb/>Ω + Δ <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/>. <lb/>=− <lb/>Z <lb/>kT <lb/>K <lb/>Z <lb/>1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(2) <lb/>n <lb/>B <lb/>m <lb/>M <lb/>M <lb/>n <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>m <lb/>n <lb/>m <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>The symbols Δ = Δ Ω <lb/>i <lb/>( ) <lb/>n <lb/>n and = <lb/>Ω <lb/>Z <lb/>Z i <lb/>( ) <lb/>n <lb/>n denote the order parameter and the wave function renormalization <lb/>factor, respectively. The quantity Ω n represents the Matsubara frequency: <lb/>π <lb/>Ω = <lb/>− <lb/>k T n <lb/>(2 <lb/>1) <lb/>n <lb/>B <lb/>, where k B is the <lb/>Boltzmann constant. The pairing kernel is defined by: <lb/>λ <lb/>Ω − Ω = <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω − Ω <lb/>+Ω <lb/>K( <lb/>) <lb/>n <lb/>m <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>C <lb/>n <lb/>m <lb/>C <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 , where λ denotes the elec-<lb/>tron-phonon coupling constant. We determined the value of λ on the basis of experimental data 20,21 and the <lb/>condition: Δ <lb/>= <lb/>= = <lb/>[ <lb/>] <lb/>0 <lb/>n <lb/>T T <lb/>1 <lb/>C <lb/>. The fitting between the theory and the experimental results is presented in Fig. 1. We <lb/>obtained λ a = 2.187 for p a = 150 GPa and λ b = 2.818 for p b = 190 GPa. The symbol Ω C represents the character-<lb/>istic phonon frequency, its value being assumed as Ω C = 100 meV. <lb/>The repulsion between electrons is modeled by the function: μ <lb/>μ θ <lb/>Ω = <lb/>Ω − Ω <lb/>( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>m <lb/>C <lb/>m <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>, where  <lb/>μ is the <lb/>Coulomb pseudopotential (  <lb/>μ = 0.1). The quantity Ω C denotes the cut-off frequency (Ω C = 1 eV). The Eliashberg <lb/>equations were solved for the Matsubara frequency equal to 1000. We used numerical methods presented in the <lb/>previous paper 24 . In the considered case, we obtained stable equation solutions for T ≥ T 0 = 15 K. <lb/>Figure 2 illustrates the full dependence of the order parameter on temperature. Physical values of the order <lb/>parameter were calculated from the equation: Δ <lb/>= <lb/>Δ Ω = Δ <lb/>T <lb/>T <lb/>( ) Re[ ( <lb/>( ))], while the function of the order <lb/>parameter on the real axis (Δ Ω <lb/>( )) was determined using the solutions of the Eliashberg equations on the imagi-<lb/>nary axis and the analytical continuation method described in the reference 25 . It can be easily seen that the order <lb/>parameter curves determined within the Eliashberg formalism differ significantly from the curves resulting from <lb/>the BCS theory 26,27 . These differences arise from the very high value of the electron-phonon coupling constant of <lb/>the superconductor, what is mirrored by the high value of the dimensionless <lb/>= Δ <lb/>Δ <lb/>R <lb/>T k T <lb/>2 ( )/ B C <lb/>0 <lb/>ratio, namely <lb/>= . <lb/>Δ <lb/>R <lb/>4 91 <lb/>a <lb/>and <lb/>= . <lb/>Δ <lb/>R <lb/>5 25 <lb/>b <lb/>. Let us recall that within the BCS theory we come to the result: <lb/>= . <lb/>Δ <lb/>R <lb/>[ ] <lb/>353 <lb/>BCS <lb/>, how-<lb/>ever the BCS theory approximates well the experimental results for λ &lt; 0.5. <lb/>We plotted the temperature dependence of the effective electron mass (m e <lb/> ) to the band electron mass (m e ) <lb/>ratio in the insets in Fig. 2. The value of the  <lb/>m m <lb/>/ <lb/>e <lb/>e ratio is given with good approximation by the value of 1 + λ 28 . <lb/>Figure 3 presents the results achieved for the difference in free energy between the superconducting and the <lb/>normal state (ΔF), the thermodynamic critical field (H C ), and the specific heat in both the superconducting (C S ) <lb/>and the normal (C N ) states. The values of the considered quantities were calculated on the basis of formulae given <lb/>in reference 28 . In particular, the difference in free energy between the superconducting and the normal state is <lb/>given by: <lb/>Figure 1. The dependence of the maximum value of the order parameter on the electron-phonon coupling <lb/>constant. We consider two cases: = <lb/>T <lb/>215 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K (p a = 150 GPa) and = <lb/>T <lb/>260 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K (p b = 190 GPa). <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>∑ <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/>Δ = − <lb/>Ω + Δ − Ω <lb/>× <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>     <lb/>− <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω + Δ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>      <lb/>= <lb/>F <lb/>k T <lb/>Z <lb/>Z <lb/>(0) <lb/>2 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>, <lb/>(3) <lb/>B <lb/>n <lb/>M <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>S <lb/>n <lb/>N <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>n <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>where ρ(0) denotes the value of electronic density of states at Fermi surface; Z n <lb/>S and Z n <lb/>N are the wave function <lb/>normalization factors for the superconducting and the normal state, respectively. Note that ΔF is equal to zero <lb/>exactly for T = T C . This fact results from the overt dependence of free energy on solutions of Eliashberg equations <lb/>(Δ n and Z n ) that have been adjusted to the experimental value of critical temperature by appropriate selection of <lb/>electron-phonon coupling constant (see Fig. 1). Thermodynamic critical field should be calculated from the <lb/>formula: <lb/>ρ <lb/>π <lb/>ρ <lb/>= − Δ <lb/>. <lb/>H <lb/>F <lb/>(0) <lb/>8 [ / (0)] <lb/>(4) <lb/>C <lb/>The difference in the specific heat between the superconducting and the normal state (ΔC = C S − C N ) is given by: <lb/>ρ <lb/>ρ <lb/>Δ <lb/>= − <lb/>Δ <lb/>. <lb/>C T <lb/>k <lb/>k T <lb/>d <lb/>F <lb/>d k T <lb/>( ) <lb/>(0) <lb/>[ / (0)] <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>(5) <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>The most convenient way of estimation the specific heat for the normal state is using the expression: <lb/>ρ <lb/>γ <lb/>= <lb/>. <lb/>C T <lb/>k <lb/>k T <lb/>( ) <lb/>(0) <lb/>(6) <lb/>N <lb/>B <lb/>B <lb/>Figure 2. The dependence of the order parameter on temperature. The insets present the influence of <lb/>temperature on the value of effective electron mass to the band electron mass ratio. Blue or red disks represent <lb/>numerical results. Black curves were obtained from the analytical formulae: Δ <lb/>= Δ <lb/>− <lb/>Γ <lb/>T <lb/>T <lb/>T T <lb/>( ) <lb/>( ) 1 ( / ) <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>and <lb/> <lb/>= <lb/>− <lb/>+ <lb/>Γ <lb/>m m <lb/>Z T <lb/>Z T T T <lb/>ZT <lb/>/ <lb/>[ ( ) <lb/>( )]( / ) <lb/>( ) <lb/>e <lb/>e <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>0 <lb/>0 , where <lb/>λ <lb/>= + <lb/>Z T <lb/>( ) 1 <lb/>C <lb/>, Γ a = 3.5 and Γ b = 3.4. The predictions of <lb/>the BCS theory we marked with grey circles. <lb/>Figure 3. (Navy and orange line:) The difference in free energy between the superconducting and the normal <lb/>state versus temperature. (Blue and red line:) Thermodynamic critical field. (Insets:) The specific heat in the <lb/>superconducting and the normal states. <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>The Sommerfeld constant take the form: γ <lb/>π <lb/>λ <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>(1 <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>. <lb/>Deviations from the results of the BCS theory can be traced in the easiest way by determining the values of <lb/>dimensionless ratios: <lb/>= <lb/>R <lb/>T C T H <lb/>( )/ (0) <lb/>H <lb/>C <lb/>N <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>2 <lb/>and <lb/>= Δ <lb/>R <lb/>C T C T <lb/>( )/ ( ) <lb/>C <lb/>C <lb/>N <lb/>C . For the LaH 10 superconductor, we <lb/>achieved the following results: <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>0 117 <lb/>H <lb/>a <lb/>, <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>0 113 <lb/>H <lb/>b <lb/>and <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>3 51 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>, <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>3 75 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>. It is worth noticing that the <lb/>BCS theory predicts <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>[ ] <lb/>0168 <lb/>H BCS <lb/>and <lb/>= . <lb/>R <lb/>[ ] <lb/>143 <lb/>C BCS <lb/>26-29 <lb/>. <lb/>The subsequent last part of the paper discusses the question of induction of the superconducting state in a <lb/>group of compounds of the La δ X 1−δ H 10 -type (or LaXH-type for short). Firstly, we are going to give some criteria, <lb/>which can potentially make easier the search for a material showing the required high-temperature supercon-<lb/>ducting properties. To do this, let us take into account the formula for the critical temperature valid for the BCS <lb/>theory: <lb/>ρ <lb/>= . Ω <lb/>− <lb/>k T <lb/>V <lb/>1 13 <lb/>exp[ 1/ (0) ] <lb/>B C <lb/>max <lb/>, where Ω max denotes the Debye frequency and V stands for the pairing <lb/>potential value. It can be easily noticed that the critical temperature is the higher, the greater are the values of the <lb/>electron density of states at the Fermi surface, the pairing potential, and the maximum phonon frequency. <lb/>Therefore it should be supposed, even at such an early stage of analysis, that special attention is to be paid to these <lb/>hydrogenated compounds, for which the respective non-hydrogenated compounds (La δ X 1−δ ) or hydrides XH <lb/>exhibit the high density of electron states at the Fermi surface. Considerations given to the pairing potential at the <lb/>phenomenological level do not get us very far because this quantity is calculated in a rather complicated way, <lb/>usually employing the DFT (Density Functional Theory) method. <lb/>Nevertheless, a sensible qualitative analysis can be made with respect to the influence of the atomic mass of the <lb/>X element on a value of the critical temperature (since the mass of the X element determines Ω max ). In this regard, <lb/>let us refer to the theoretical results obtained within the Eliashberg formalism for H 2 S and H 3 S superconduc-<lb/>tors 5,6 . They prove that contributions to the Eliashberg function (α Ω <lb/>F( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>) coming from sulphur and from hydro-<lb/>gen are separated due to a huge difference between atomic masses of these two elements. To be precise, the <lb/>electron-phonon interaction derived from sulphur is crucial in the frequency range from 0 meV to Ω max <lb/>S <lb/>equal to <lb/>about 70 meV, while the contribution derived from hydrogen (Ω <lb/>= 220 <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>meV) is significant above ~100 meV. <lb/>It is noteworthy that we come upon a similar situation in the case of the LaH 10 compound 30 . Therefore the follow-<lb/>ing factorization of the Eliashberg function for the LaXH compound can be assumed: <lb/>α <lb/>λ <lb/>θ <lb/>λ <lb/>θ <lb/>λ <lb/>θ <lb/>Ω = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>Ω <lb/>− Ω + <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>     <lb/>Ω <lb/>− Ω <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>    <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>     <lb/>Ω <lb/>− Ω <lb/>F( ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) , <lb/>(7) <lb/>2 <lb/>L a <lb/>max <lb/>La 2 <lb/>max <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>2 <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>2 <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>where λ La , λ X , and λ H are the contributions to the electron-phonon coupling constant derived from both metals <lb/>(La, X) and hydrogen, respectively. Similarly, the symbols Ω max <lb/>La , Ω max <lb/>X , and Ω max <lb/>H represent the respective maxi-<lb/>mum phonon frequencies. The value of the critical temperature can be assessed from the generalised formula of <lb/>the BCS theory 7 : <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λμ <lb/>= <lb/>Ω <lb/>. <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>− . <lb/>+ <lb/>− + . <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>k T <lb/>f f <lb/>1 27 <lb/>exp <lb/>1 14(1 <lb/>) <lb/>(1 0 163 ) <lb/>, <lb/>(8) <lb/>B C <lb/>1 2 <lb/>ln <lb/> <lb/>while the symbols appearing in Eq. (8) are defined in Table 1. <lb/>Let us calculate explicitly the relevant quantities: <lb/>λ λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>= <lb/>+ <lb/>+ , <lb/>(9) <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>Quantity <lb/>∫ <lb/>λ = <lb/>Ω <lb/>α <lb/>+∞ <lb/>Ω Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/>d <lb/>2 <lb/>F <lb/>0 <lb/>2 ( ) ( ) , <lb/>∫ <lb/>Ω = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>λ <lb/>α <lb/>+∞ <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/>d <lb/>exp <lb/>l n( ) <lb/>F <lb/>ln <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 ( ) <lb/>, <lb/>∫ <lb/>α <lb/>Ω = <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω Ω <lb/>λ <lb/>+∞ <lb/>d <lb/>F( ) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>= <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>λ <lb/>Λ <lb/>( ) <lb/>f <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>3 <lb/>, = + <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>     <lb/>Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>     <lb/>+ Λ <lb/>f <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>ln <lb/>1 2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>2 , <lb/>Λ 1 = 2.4 − 0.14μ &apos; , <lb/>μ <lb/>Λ = . + <lb/>Ω Ω <lb/>(0 1 9 )( <lb/>/ ) <lb/>2 <lb/>2 <lb/>ln <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>Table 1. The quantities: λ (electron-phonon coupling constant), Ω ln (logarithmic phonon frequency), Ω 2 <lb/>(second moment of the normalized weight function), f 1 (strong-coupling correction function), and f 2 (shape <lb/>correction function) μ. <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>Ω = <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  Ω <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>× <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  Ω <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>× <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>  Ω <lb/>− <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>   <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/>exp <lb/>l n( <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>exp <lb/>l n( <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>exp <lb/>l n( <lb/>) <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>, <lb/>(10) <lb/>ln <lb/>La <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>and <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>λ <lb/>Ω = <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Ω <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Ω <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>+ <lb/>Ω <lb/>. <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>2 <lb/>( 11) <lb/>2 <lb/>La <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>La 2 <lb/>X <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>2 <lb/>H <lb/>La <lb/>X <lb/>H <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>2 <lb/>We are going to consider the case Ω <lb/>&lt; Ω <lb/>&lt; <lb/>~40 meV <lb/>100 meV <lb/>max <lb/>La <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>. It means that we are interested in <lb/>such an X element, the contribution of which to the Eliashberg function fills the gap between contributions com-<lb/>ing from lanthanum and hydrogen. It can be assumed that 0 &lt; λ X &lt; 1, while keeping in mind that λ La = 0.68 31 . <lb/>Additionally, the previous calculations discussed in the work allow to write that λ La + λ H is equal to λ a = 2.187 <lb/>for p a = 150 GPa or to λ b = 2.818 for p b = 190 GPa. The quantity  <lb/>μ occurring in the Eq. (8) serves now as the <lb/>fitting parameter. One should remember that the formula for the critical temperature given by the Eq. (8) was <lb/>derived with the use of significant simplifying assumptions (the value of the cut-off frequency is neglected, as well <lb/>as the retardation effects modeled by the Matsubara frequency). Therefore the value of the Coulomb pseudopo-<lb/>tential determined from the full Eliashberg equations usually differs from the value of  <lb/>μ calculated analytically. <lb/>The experimental data for the LaH 10 superconductor can be reproduced using Eq. (8) and assuming that <lb/> <lb/>μ = . <lb/>0 170 <lb/>a <lb/>and μ = . <lb/>0 276 <lb/>b <lb/> <lb/>. <lb/>The achieved results are presented in Fig. 4. It is evident that taking into consideration the additional X ele-<lb/>ment, which enriches the LaH 10 composition, leads to a large increase in the critical temperature value. The esti-<lb/>mated upper limit of the T C <lb/>a value is equal to 288 K for p a = 150 GPa, while for p b = 190 GPa we obtain = <lb/>T <lb/>315 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K. <lb/>Therefore the superconducting state can potentially exist at room temperature for both cases. <lb/>Now, let us take into account elements with the identical electron configuration at the valence shell as lantha-<lb/>num, but lighter than lanthanum: scandium and yttrium, both being selected as X. Attention should be paid to the <lb/>fact that the electron configuration of X, identical as in lanthanum, should minimize such changes in properties <lb/>of the obtained compound which could result from changes in both the electron dispersion relation and the <lb/>matrix elements of the electron-phonon interaction. Applying the formula: Ω <lb/>Ω <lb/>~M M <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>max <lb/>X <lb/>max <lb/>La <lb/>La <lb/>X we get <lb/>Ω <lb/>~70 <lb/>max <lb/>Sc <lb/>meV and Ω <lb/>~50 <lb/>max <lb/>Y <lb/>meV (M La and M X denote atomic mass of lanthanum and the element X, i.e. Sc or <lb/>Y, respectively). <lb/>Figure 5 presents the expected range of the critical temperature values for the LaScH and the LaYH com-<lb/>pounds. We took into account two pressure values: p a = 150 GPa and p b = 190 GPa. For LaScH we got: <lb/>∈ <lb/>T <lb/>220, 267 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K and <lb/>∈ <lb/>T <lb/>263, 294 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K, while the results for LaYH are as follows: <lb/>∈ <lb/>T <lb/>218, 247 <lb/>C <lb/>a <lb/>K and <lb/>∈ <lb/>T <lb/>261, 274 <lb/>C <lb/>b <lb/>K. Apparently, the significant increase in the critical temperature value should be observed in <lb/>both cases. The effect of growth in the value of the critical temperature results from filling the gap in the Eliashberg <lb/>function between the contributions coming from La and H, as was already stated above. <lb/>To summarize, the experimental results obtained for the LaH 10 compound get us much closer to the pur-<lb/>pose of obtaining the superconducting state at room temperature. The huge difference between atomic masses <lb/>of lanthanum and hydrogen results in the characteristic structure of the Eliashberg function modeling the <lb/>electron-phonon interaction in the considered compound, with distinctly separated parts proceeded either from <lb/>lanthanum or from hydrogen. The proper selection of the additional element (X) in the LaXH compound is <lb/>expected to fill the &apos; empty&apos; range of the Eliashberg function between the parts coming from La and H. In our opin-<lb/>ion, good candidates are scandium and yttrium. These elements have the electron configuration at the valence <lb/>shell exactly the same as lanthanum, and yet they are considerably lighter. Our numerical calculations suggest the <lb/>Figure 4. The dependence of the critical temperature on λ X and Ω max <lb/>X . (a) presents the results for λ La + <lb/>λ H =2.187 and  <lb/>μ = . <lb/>0 170 <lb/>a <lb/>. (b) is plotted for λ La + λ H = 2.818 and  <lb/>μ = . <lb/>0 276 <lb/>b <lb/>. It was assumed that <lb/>Ω <lb/>= 40 <lb/>max <lb/>La <lb/>meV and Ω <lb/>= 290 <lb/>max <lb/>H <lb/>meV for both cases. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<body>possible growth in the critical temperature of the LaScH compound equal to about 52 K (150 GPa) or to about <lb/>79 K (190 GPa) as compared to the T C value for the LaH 10 compound. As far as the LaYH compound is con-<lb/>cerned, the pertinent increase in T C value can reach about 32 K for 150 GPa or about 59 K for 190 GPa. <lb/>Our results can be the starting point for the advanced DFT calculations or perhaps provide inspiration for <lb/>carrying out the appropriate experimental measurements. Of course, we realize that the presented analysis is <lb/>based on the semi-quantitative approximations and may raise some critical remarks. For this reason, we refer to <lb/>the most significant reservations: <lb/>• In the paper, we assume the relatively simple form of Eliashberg function, which is the linear combination of each <lb/>of the contributions from La, H and X. Does this mean that any contribution related to Sc or Y will be positive? <lb/>Of course, this doesn&apos;t have to be the case. For example, the properly selected concentration of Sc or Y atoms <lb/>can lead to a decrease in the electron-phonon coupling constant. On the other hand, one should remember <lb/>the results obtained for YH 10 compound 32,33 . Based on the DFT it was found that the critical temper-<lb/>ature for ∈ <lb/>p (250, 300) GPa can exceed the room temperature ( <lb/>T <lb/>[ ] <lb/>320 <lb/>C max <lb/>K). This result suggests that a <lb/>high concentration of Y atoms in the LaYH compound should not lead to a decrease in T C . It should also be <lb/>noted that future DFT calculations (or possible experiments) should take into account different concentra-<lb/>tions of Sc and Y atoms. <lb/>• In the paper, we assume that the phonon frequency regime is completely decoupled (La contributes to low pho-<lb/>non modes and hydrogen vibration should be high). What significance will La-H, Sc-H or Y-H modes which are <lb/>related to the moderate frequency regime? In our opinion, they will contribute to the increase in the critical <lb/>temperature. This will result from activating the Eliashberg function in the frequency range from ~ 40 meV <lb/>to ~100 meV. This effect was clearly visible in the case of YSH 6 and LaSH 6 (p ~ 200 GPa), where the role of <lb/>dopant fulfilled sulphur 34 . <lb/>• Do the values of the Coulomb pseudopotential assumed in Eq. (8) (  <lb/>μ = . <lb/>0 170 <lb/>a <lb/>and μ = . <lb/>0 276 <lb/>b <lb/> <lb/>) roughly corre-<lb/>spond to the physical values of this parameters? In particular, are these values too low, which would lead to the <lb/>significant overestimation of the critical temperature in our paper. In this case, it is worth referring to the <lb/>recently obtained DFT results for LaH 10 . In the publication 19 , the authors showed that qualitative compliance <lb/>with experimental data can be obtained assuming  <lb/>μ = 0.2 ( <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>[ ] <lb/>197 <lb/>C p 150GPa <lb/>K for the crystal structure R3 <lb/>m, and <lb/>= <lb/>= <lb/>T <lb/>[ ] <lb/>271 <lb/>C p 200GPa <lb/>K for the crystal structure Fm3m). In the first case, the experimental critical tem-<lb/>perature was underestimated by 18 K (too high value of  <lb/>μ ), in the second case, T <lb/>[ ] <lb/>C exp was revalued by 11 K <lb/>(too low value of  <lb/>μ ). Comparing the results obtained in the paper 19 with ours, it is clearly seen that μ a <lb/> and μ b <lb/> <lb/>are fairly well-obtained. In the most interesting case for LaH 10 corresponds to the pressure of 190 GPa, taking <lb/>into account the possible reduction of μ b <lb/> suggested in 19 , the increase in the critical temperature value for the <lb/>LaScH and LaYH compounds can be expected. It is worth noting that our results also correlate well with the <lb/>data obtained in the paper 30 , where  <lb/>μ = 0.22 was assumed, which allowed to reproduce the experimental <lb/>critical temperature for LaH 10 (p = 190 GPa). <lb/>One needs to recognise that the exact quantitative analysis of the problem discussed in our work would <lb/>require to be carried out using the Eliashberg equations including the anharmonicity of the phonon system and <lb/>the non-linear terms of the electron-phonon-phonon interaction, especially for such high values of the critical <lb/>temperature as are observed for LaH 10 . Presently we work upon the derivation of suitable equations. <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 5 August 2019; Accepted: 8 January 2020; <lb/>Published: xx xx xxxx <lb/></front>

			<body>Figure 5. The expected range of critical temperature values for the LaScH and the LaYH compounds. <lb/></body>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/>References <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>1. Drozdov, A. P., Eremets, M. I. &amp; Troyan, I. A. Conventional superconductivity at 190 K at high pressures, https://arxiv.org/ <lb/>abs/1706.05180 (2014). <lb/>2. Drozdov, A. P., Eremets, M. I., Troyan, I. A., Ksenofontov, V. &amp; Shylin, S. I. Conventional superconductivity at 203 kelvin at high <lb/>pressures in the sulfur hydride system. Nature 525, 73 (2015). <lb/>3. Ashcroft, N. W. Hydrogen dominant metallic alloys: high temperature superconductors? Physical Review Letters 92, 187002 (2004). <lb/>4. Ashcroft, N. W. Metallic hydrogen: a high-temperature superconductor? Physical Review Letters 21, 1748 (1968). <lb/>5. Li, Y., Hao, J., Liu, H., Li, Y. &amp; Ma, Y. The metallization and superconductivity of dense hydrogen sulfide. The Journal of Chemical <lb/>Physics 140, 174712 (2014). <lb/>6. Duan, D. et al. Pressure-induced metallization of dense (H 2 S) 2 H 2 with high-T C superconductivity. Scientific Reports 4, 6968 (2014). <lb/>7. Durajski, A. P., Szczęśniak, R. &amp; Li, Y. Non-bcs thermodynamic properties of H 2 S superconductor. Physica C 515, 1 (2015). <lb/>8. Duan, D. et al. Pressure-induced decomposition of solid hydrogen sulfide. Physical Review B 91, 180502(R) (2015). <lb/>9. Errea, I. et al. High-pressure hydrogen sulfide from first principles: A strongly anharmonic phonon-mediated superconductor. <lb/>Physical Review Letters 114, 157004 (2015). <lb/>10. Durajski, A. P. Quantitative analysis of nonadiabatic effects in dense H 3 S and PH 3 superconductors. Scientific Reports 6, 38570 <lb/>(2016). <lb/>11. Durajski, A. P., Szczęśniak, R. &amp; Pietronero, L. High-temperature study of superconducting hydrogen and deuterium sulfide. <lb/>Annalen der Physik 528, 358 (2016). <lb/>12. Ishikawa, T. et al. Superconducting H 5 S 2 phase in sulfur-hydrogen system under highpressure. Scientific Reports 6, 23160 (2016). <lb/>13. Errea, I. et al. Quantum hydrogen-bond symmetrization in the superconducting hydrogen sulfide system. Nature 532, 81 (2016). <lb/>14. Sano, W., Koretsune, T., Tadano, T., Akashi, R. &amp; Arita, R. Effect of van hove singularities on high-T C superconductivity in H 3 S. <lb/>Physical Review B 93, 094525 (2016). <lb/>15. Durajski, A. P. &amp; Szczęśniak, R. First-principles study of superconducting hydrogen sulfide at pressure up to 500 GPa. Scientific <lb/>Reports 7, 4473 (2017). <lb/>16. Szczęśniak, R. &amp; Durajski, A. P. Unusual sulfur isotope effect and extremely high critical temperature in H 3 S superconductor. <lb/>Scientific Reports 8, 6037 (2018). <lb/>17. Kostrzewa, M., Szczęśniak, R., Kalaga, J. K. &amp; Wrona, I. A. Anomalously high value of coulomb pseudopotential for the H 5 S 2 <lb/>superconductor. Scientific Reports 8, 11957 (2018). <lb/>18. Drozdov, A. P. et al. Superconductivity at 250 K in lanthanum hydride under high pressures. Nature 569, 528-531 (2019). <lb/>19. Kruglov, I. A. et al. Superconductivity of LaH 10 and LaH 16 polyhydrides. Phys. Rev. B 101, 024508 (2020). <lb/>20. Drozdov, A. P. et al. Superconductivity at 215 K in lanthanum hydride at high pressures. https://arxiv.org/abs/1808.07039 (2018). <lb/>21. Somayazulu, M. et al. Evidence for superconductivity above 260 K in lanthanum superhydride at megabar pressures. Physical Review <lb/>Letters 122, 027001 (2019). <lb/>22. Schlapbach, L. &amp; Züttel, A. Hydrogen-storage materials for mobile applications. Nature 414, 353 (2001). <lb/>23. Eliashberg, G. M. Interactions between electrons and lattice vibrations in a superconductor. Soviet Physics JETP 11, 696 (1960). <lb/>24. Szczęśniak, R. The numerical solution of the imaginary-axis eliashberg equations. Acta Physica Polonica A 109, 179 (2006). <lb/>25. Beach, K. S. D., Gooding, R. J. &amp; Marsiglio, F. Reliable padé analytical continuation method based on a high-accuracy symbolic <lb/>computation algorithm. Physical Review B 61, 5147 (2000). <lb/>26. Bardeen, J., Cooper, L. N. &amp; Schrieffer, J. R. Microscopic theory of superconductivity. Physical Review 106, 162 (1957). <lb/>27. Bardeen, J., Cooper, L. N. &amp; Schrieffer, J. R. Theory of superconductivity. Physical Review 108, 1175 (1957). <lb/>28. Carbotte, J. P. Properties of boson-exchange superconductors. Reviews of Modern Physics 62, 1027 (1990). <lb/>29. Aguilera-Navarro, V. &amp; de Llano, M. Generalizing the bcs universal constants to high-temperature superconductivity. Symmetries in <lb/>Physics. Springer 28, 28-34 (1992). <lb/>30. Liu, L. et al. Microscopic mechanism of room-temperature superconductivity in compressed LaH 10 . Phys. Rev. B 99, 140501(R) <lb/>(2019). <lb/>31. Chen, W. et al. Superconductivity and equation of state of distorted fcc-lanthanum above megabar pressures. https://arxiv.org/ <lb/>abs/1903.02194 (2019). <lb/>32. Christoph Heil, Simone di Cataldo, Giovanni B. Bachelet, Lilia Boeri. Superconductivity in sodalite-like yttrium hydride clathrates. <lb/>Physical Review B 99 (2019). <lb/>33. Hanyu Liu, Ivan I. Naumov, Roald Hoffmann, N. W. Ashcroft, Russell J. Hemley. Potential high-superconducting lanthanum and <lb/>yttrium hydrides at high pressure. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences 114, 6990-6995 (2017). <lb/>34. Xiaowei Liang, Shutao Zhao, Cancan Shao, Aitor Bergara, Hanyu Liu, Linyan Wang, Rongxin Sun, Yang Zhang, Yufei Gao, Zhisheng <lb/>Zhao, Xiang-Feng Zhou, Julong He, Dongli Yu, Guoying Gao, Yongjun Tian. First-principles study of crystal structures and <lb/>superconductivity of ternary and at high pressures. Physical Review B 100 (2019). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>A.P. Durajski acknowledges the financial support from the Polish National Science Centre (NCN) under Grant <lb/>No. 2016/23/D/ST3/02109. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>R. Szczęśniak wrote the part of the code for numerical calculations and participated in writing the manuscript. M. <lb/>Kostrzewa, K. Szczęśniak, and A. Durajski designed and carried out the calculations, collected data and drafted <lb/>the final version of the manuscript. All authors reviewed the manuscript. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/></div>

            <front>Additional information <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to A.P.D. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in published maps and <lb/>institutional affiliations. <lb/></front>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Scientific RepoRtS | <lb/>(2020) 10:1592 | https://doi.org/10.1038/s41598-020-58065-9 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">www.nature.com/scientificreports <lb/>www.nature.com/scientificreports/ <lb/></note>

			<front>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International <lb/>License, which permits use, sharing, adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or <lb/>format, as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Cre-<lb/>ative Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless indicated otherwise in a credit line to the <lb/>material. If material is not included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not per-<lb/>mitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the <lb/>copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2020 </front>


	</text>
</tei>
