<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/>1868 <lb/>nature genetics <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/>Analysis of 10,478 cancer genomes identifies <lb/>candidate driver genes and opportunities for <lb/>precision oncology <lb/>Ben Kinnersley 1,2,11 , Amit Sud 1,3,4,5,6,11 , Andrew Everall 1,11 , Alex J. Cornish 1 , <lb/>Daniel Chubb 1 , Richard Culliford 1 , Andreas J. Gruber 7 , Adrian Lärkeryd 8 , <lb/>Costas Mitsopoulos 9 , David Wedge 10 &amp; Richard Houlston 1 <lb/>Tumor genomic profiling is increasingly seen as a prerequisite to guide the <lb/>treatment of patients with cancer. To explore the value of whole-genome <lb/>sequencing (WGS) in broadening the scope of cancers potentially amenable <lb/>to a precision therapy, we analysed whole-genome sequencing data on <lb/>10,478 patients spanning 35 cancer types recruited to the UK 100,000 <lb/>Genomes Project. We identified 330 candidate driver genes, including 74 <lb/>that are new to any cancer. We estimate that approximately 55% of patients <lb/>studied harbor at least one clinically relevant mutation, predicting either <lb/>sensitivity or resistance to certain treatments or clinical trial eligibility. By <lb/>performing computational chemogenomic analysis of cancer mutations <lb/>we identify additional targets for compounds that represent attractive <lb/>candidates for future clinical trials. This study represents one of the most <lb/>comprehensive efforts thus far to identify cancer driver genes in the real <lb/>world setting and assess their impact on informing precision oncology. <lb/></front>

		<body>Precision oncology aims to tailor therapy to the unique biology of the <lb/>patient&apos;s cancer, thereby optimizing treatment efficacy and minimizing <lb/>toxicity 1,2 . Underpinning precision oncology is the concept of somatic <lb/>driver mutations as the foundation of cancer biology 3,4 . <lb/>The expansion in the number of therapeutically actionable <lb/>genes has exposed the limitations of single-analyte genomic assays <lb/>in cancer 5 . The modest incremental cost of adding additional can-<lb/>cer genes to high-throughput sequencing-based panels has made <lb/>the development of drugs targeting increasingly smaller subsets of <lb/>molecularly defined patients with cancer financially and logistically <lb/>feasible 6 . The development of inhibitors effective in cancers driven by <lb/>rare genomic mutations has required the concurrent development <lb/>of clinical trial designs, such as basket trials, in which eligibility is <lb/>based on mutational status instead of organ site, cancer stage and <lb/>histology 7 . With the advent of basket studies, many oncologists <lb/>now consider that tumor genomic profiling should be offered to all <lb/>patients with cancer who are not candidates for curative-intent local <lb/>or systemic therapy 8 . <lb/>At present, several standalone tests or a panel are typically used to <lb/>capture a set of genomic, transcriptomic or epigenomic features in a <lb/>tumor to inform patient treatment 9 . However, falling costs are making <lb/>whole-genome sequencing (WGS) a potentially attractive proposition <lb/>as a single all-encompassing test to identify cancer drivers and other <lb/>genomic features, which may not be captured by standard testing but <lb/>are clinically actionable 10 . This approach is being explored in the UK by <lb/>the 100,000 Genomes Project (100kGP), which is seeking to deliver the <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 25 September 2023 <lb/>Accepted: 1 May 2024 <lb/>Published online: 18 June 2024 <lb/>Check for updates <lb/>1 <lb/>Division of Genetics and Epidemiology, The Institute of Cancer Research, London, UK. 2 University College London Cancer Institute, University College <lb/>London, London, UK. 3 Department of Medical Oncology, Dana-Farber Cancer Institute, Boston, MA, USA. 4 Broad Institute of MIT and Harvard, Cambridge, <lb/>MA, USA. 5 Harvard Medical School, Boston, MA, USA. 6 Centre for Immuno-Oncology, Nuffield Department of Medicine, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK. <lb/>7 <lb/>Systems Biology &amp; Biomedical Data Science Laboratory, University of Konstanz, Konstanz, Germany. 8 Division of Molecular Pathology, The Institute of Cancer <lb/>Research, London, UK. 9 Division of Cancer Therapeutics, The Institute of Cancer Research, London, UK. 10 Manchester Cancer Research Centre, University of <lb/>Manchester, Manchester, UK. 11 These authors contributed equally: Ben Kinnersley, Amit Sud, Andrew Everall. e-mail: richard.houlston@icr.ac.uk <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1869 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>Mutation rates varied across the different cancer types with cuta-<lb/>neous melanoma having the highest single nucleotide variant mutation <lb/>count and meningioma the lowest (Extended Data Fig. 2). A total of 945 <lb/>samples, notably colorectal and uterine cancers, were hypermutated, <lb/>either as result of defective mismatch repair (dMMR) or POLE mutation. <lb/>Invasive ductal carcinoma of the breast had the highest power for driver <lb/>gene detection (&gt;90% power for a mutation rate of at least 2% higher <lb/>than background) and large cell lung cancer had the lowest power (Fig. 2 <lb/>and Supplementary Table 4). Compared with the recent Pan-Cancer <lb/>Analysis of Whole Genomes analysis 12 , the 100kGP cohort was better <lb/>powered to identify a driver mutation for 19 cancers, notably for breast, <lb/>colorectal, esophageal and uterine cancer, lung adenocarcinoma and <lb/>bladder transitional cell carcinoma where the sample sizes were more <lb/>than tenfold higher. <lb/>Spectrum of cancer driver genes <lb/>Across all cancer types we identified 770 unique tumor-driver gene <lb/>pairs corresponding to 330 unique candidate cancer driver genes <lb/>(Fig. 3, Extended Data Fig. 3 and Supplementary Table 5). When <lb/>vision of precision oncology through WGS to National Health Service <lb/>(NHS) patients as part of their routine care 11 . <lb/>Here, we report an analysis of WGS data on 10,478 patients span-<lb/>ning 35 cancer types recruited to the 100kGP (Fig. 1a). Across all cancer <lb/>types we identify 330 candidate driver genes, including 74 which are <lb/>new to any cancer. We relate these to their actionability both in terms <lb/>of currently approved therapeutic agents and through computational <lb/>chemogenomic analysis to predict candidacy for future clinical trials. <lb/>Results <lb/>We analysed 10,478 cancer genomes spanning 35 different cancer types <lb/>(Fig. 1b and Supplementary Tables 1 and 2). While broadly reflecting <lb/>the spectrum and frequencies of cancers diagnosed in the UK popula-<lb/>tion, there were differences, with an over-representation of colorectal <lb/>and kidney cancers and a paucity of prostate and pancreatic cancers <lb/>(Extended Data Fig. 1). Additionally, for the main cancer types, the <lb/>patients recruited to 100kGP tended to be younger and had earlier <lb/>stage tumors compared to patients in the general UK population (Sup-<lb/>plementary Table 3). <lb/></body>

			<body>a <lb/>b <lb/>Sequencing of 14,129 tumor-normal whole genomes <lb/>Essential and selective <lb/>driver genes <lb/>New druggable cancer <lb/>targets <lb/>Patients with cancer <lb/>Sample and sequencing quality control <lb/>35 cancer types <lb/>10,478 tumor-normal whole genomes <lb/>Actionable driver genes <lb/>FDA approved therapies <lb/>and clinical trials <lb/>Multilayered cancer <lb/>gene druggability <lb/>Driver gene identification <lb/>330 cancer driver genes <lb/>(74 new drivers) <lb/>dMMR, HRD <lb/>Clinically informative mutational signatures <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Tumor type <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>Lung-SmaliCell <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>1,500 <lb/>2,000 <lb/>Number <lb/>Fig. 1 | Study design and number of samples per tumor type included in <lb/>the analysis. a, Study design. b, Number of samples per tumor type. BileDuct-<lb/>AdenoCA, bile duct adenocarcinoma; Bladder-TCC, bladder transitional cell <lb/>carcinoma; Breast-DuctalCA, breast ductal carcinoma; Breast-LobularCA, breast <lb/>lobular carcinoma; CNS-Astro, astrocytoma; CNS-GBM-IDHmut, IDH mutated <lb/>glioblastoma; CNS-GBM-IDHwt, IDH wild-type glioblastoma; CNS-Menin, <lb/>meningioma; CNS-Oligo, oligodendroglioma; ColoRect-AdenoCA, colorectal <lb/>adenocarcinoma; Connective-Chondro, chondrosarcoma; Connective-Leiomyo, <lb/>leiomyosarcoma; Connective-Liposarc, liposarcoma; Connective-Myxofibro, <lb/>myxofibrosarcoma; Connective-Osteosarc, osteosarcoma; Connective-<lb/>SCS, spindle cell sarcoma; Connective-SS, synovial sarcoma; Eso-AdenoCA, <lb/>esophageal adenocarcinoma; HeadNeck-SCC, squamous cell carcinoma of the <lb/>head and neck; Kidney-CCRCC, clear cell renal cell carcinoma; Kidney-ChRCC, <lb/>chromophobe renal cell carcinoma; Kidney-PRCC, papillary renal cell carcinoma; <lb/>Liver-HCC, hepatocellular carcinoma; Lung-AdenoCA, lung adenocarcinoma; <lb/>Lung-LargeCell, large cell lung cancer; Lung-SCC, squamous cell carcinoma of <lb/>the lung; Lung-SmallCell, small cell carcinoma of the lung; Mes-Mesothelioma, <lb/>mesothelioma; Ovary-AdenoCA, ovarian adenocarcinoma; Panc-AdenoCA, <lb/>pancreatic adenocarcinoma; Prost-AdenoCA, prostate adenocarcinom; Skin-<lb/>Melanoma, melanoma of the skin; Stomach-AdenoCA, gastric adenocarcinoma; <lb/>Testis-GCT, testicular germ cell tumor; Uterus-AdenoCA, uterine <lb/>adenocarcinoma. Fig. 1a created with BioRender.com. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1870 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>compared to the largest pan-cancer driver analysis, in 21 of 31 cancer <lb/>types where tumor histologies could be matched, we recovered 61% of <lb/>all cancer drivers reported by the Catalogue of Somatic Mutations in <lb/>Cancer (COSMIC), the Integrative OncoGenomics (IntOGen) 4 and The <lb/>Cancer Genome Atlas (TCGA) Program pan-cancer analysis reported by <lb/>ref. 13 (Supplementary Table 5). We were able to detect 80% of drivers <lb/>reported for colorectal, breast, lung and ovarian cancers but only &lt;20% <lb/>of drivers reported for hepatocellular and stomach cancers, which may <lb/>be a result of differing sample size or intertumour heterogeneity 14 . <lb/>The number of identified cancer driver genes varied between cancer <lb/>types, with colorectal and uterine cancers having the most (60 genes) <lb/>and spindle cell carcinoma having the fewest (4 genes). Across the <lb/>35 cancers, we found no correlation between average mutation bur-<lb/>den and the number of driver genes in each cancer (Pearson&apos;s r = 0.19, <lb/>P = 0.27). The consensus list also includes 326 tumor-driver pairs that <lb/>have not previously been reported by the Cancer Gene Census, IntOGen <lb/>or the pan-cancer analysis of TCGA 4,13 (Supplementary Table 5) and <lb/>74 that have not previously been associated with any specific tissue. <lb/>Almost all of the candidate drivers identified were uncommon, with <lb/>88% (65 of 74) having a mutation frequency &lt;10% in the respective <lb/>cancer type. The highest numbers of new cancer driver genes were <lb/>found for uterine (n = 42), bladder (n = 40) and colorectal (n = 37) can-<lb/>cers. Furthermore, we identified drivers in tumor types which have not <lb/>been cataloged by IntOGen 4 and ref. 13. These include breast lobular <lb/>carcinoma, meningioma and myxofibrosarcoma. Predictions of known <lb/>cancer driver genes in new cancer types include SPTA1, CHD4 and ASXL1 <lb/>in colorectal cancer, FOXO3, MUC16 and ZFPM1 in breast cancers and <lb/>CNTNAP2, CTNND2 and TRRAP in lung adenocarcinoma. Entirely new <lb/>predictions include MAP3K21 (encoding a mixed-lineage kinase) in <lb/>colorectal cancer, USP17L22 (encoding a deubiquitinating enzyme) in <lb/>breast ductal carcinoma and TPTE (encoding a tyrosine phosphatase) <lb/>in lung adenocarcinoma (Supplementary Table 5). <lb/>Eighty-five genes were identified as a driver in more than two <lb/>tumor types, with 26 genes functioning as drivers in more than five <lb/>tumor types (Fig. 4a). As expected, TP53 was identified as a driver gene <lb/>in the most tumor types, followed by PIK3CA, ARID1A and PTEN, acting <lb/>as cancer driver genes in 29, 18, 16 and 14 different tumor types, respec-<lb/>tively. While many genes function as drivers in several cancer types, <lb/>some drivers are mutated at high frequencies only in specific tumors, <lb/>such as VHL in clear cell renal cell carcinoma and FGFR3 in bladder <lb/>cancer (Fig. 4a). Across drivers operating in several cancer types, the <lb/>clearest examples of domain-specific driver mutations were in EGFR, <lb/>where protein tyrosine and serine/threonine kinase domain mutations <lb/>predominated in lung adenocarcinoma, in contrast to extracellular <lb/>furin-like cysteine-rich region domain mutations in IDH wild-type <lb/>glioblastoma (Supplementary Table 6 and Extended Data Fig. 4a). <lb/>PIK3CA also showed a preference for p85-binding domain mutations <lb/>in uterine adenocarcinoma compared to other cancer types, such as <lb/>breast ductal carcinoma, which are enriched for mutations in the PIK <lb/>family domain (Supplementary Table 6 and Extended Data Fig. 4b). <lb/>Hierarchical clustering of cancers based on the presence of identified <lb/>driver mutations and their respective q value demonstrated clustering <lb/>of cancer types by cell of origin (for example, head and neck and lung <lb/>squamous cell carcinoma) and by organ (for example, breast ductal <lb/>and lobular carcinomas; Extended Data Fig. 5). The ratio of predicted <lb/>activating versus tumor suppressor driver genes varied across tumor <lb/>types with meningioma and myxofibrosarcoma possessing the highest <lb/>and lowest ratios, respectively (Fig. 4b and Supplementary Table 5). <lb/>Across the 35 different tumor types in 9,070 unique samples we <lb/>identified 12,606 distinct oncogenic mutations in tumor-relevant <lb/>cancer driver genes. The median number of oncogenic mutations in <lb/>cancer driver genes per sample was two, across all tumors. The highest <lb/>median number of oncogenic mutations in driver genes per sample <lb/>was seen in uterine cancer (n = 6; Extended Data Fig. 6). We observed <lb/>significant differences (P binomial &lt; 3.5 × 10 -3 ) in oncogenic mutation <lb/>frequency in cancer driver genes across different tumor histologies <lb/>arising from the same organ. Examples include CDH1, TBX3 and TP53 <lb/>in breast cancers, ATRX, CIC, IDH1, PTEN and TP53 in central nervous <lb/>system tumors, IDH1 and TP53 in connective tissue tumors, PBRM1 and <lb/>VHL in renal cancers and EGFR, KMT2D, KRAS, NFE2L2, PTEN, STK11 and <lb/>TP53 in lung cancers (Fig. 5). <lb/>Considering all 330 cancer driver genes, 217 featured at least one <lb/>clonal oncogenic mutation (214 clonal, 167 clonal early and 114 clonal <lb/>late events (Supplementary Table 7). APC, TP53 and PIK3CA possessed <lb/>the most clonal oncogenic mutations (Fig. 6a and Extended Data Fig. 7). <lb/>Of the 162 driver genes that harbored at least one subclonal oncogenic <lb/>mutation, ARID1A, TP53 and PIK3CA possessed the most (Fig. 6b and <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 7). Consistent with published work, a high propor-<lb/>tion (55%) of all early clonal driver mutations occur in just four genes <lb/>(TP53, APC, KRAS and PIK3CA) whereas the equivalent percentage of <lb/>late and subclonal oncogenic mutations was observed in 19 different <lb/>genes (Supplementary Table 7) 15-18 . This finding supports a model in <lb/>which early events in cancer evolution tend to occur in a restricted <lb/>set of driver genes and a wider range of drivers feature late in tumor <lb/>evolution. In tumors with more than ten oncogenic mutations, menin-<lb/>gioma exhibited the greatest proportion of clonal oncogenic mutations <lb/>(Extended Data Fig. 8a). Large cell lung, testicular germ cell tumor and <lb/>oligodendroglioma carried the highest proportion of early clonal, late <lb/>clonal and subclonal oncogenic mutations, respectively (Extended <lb/>Data Fig. 8b-d). <lb/>Sensitivity of WGS mutation detection compared to panels <lb/>We initially investigated the performance of WGS to detect clinically <lb/>relevant mutations compared to conventional panel-based testing <lb/>through comparison of mutation calls with Memorial Sloan Kettering <lb/>(MSK) Cancer Center cohorts at 43 established drivers (Supplemen-<lb/>tary Note 1). For primary tumors represented in the MSK and 100kGP <lb/>cohorts, the rate of mutations called for each driver gene was com-<lb/>parable (Supplementary Figs. 1 and 2). Thereafter, we estimated the <lb/>sensitivity of mutation detection in the 100kGP cohort by extracting <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>CNS-GBM-Menin <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>100 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>10,000 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>1 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>Mutation rate (per Mb) <lb/>Sample size <lb/>Effect size above background <lb/>0.01 <lb/>0.02 <lb/>0.05 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>Fig. 2 | Power estimates for driver gene identification per tumor type. The <lb/>number of samples needed to achieve 90% power for 90% of genes (y axis). Gray <lb/>vertical lines indicate exome-wide background mutation rates (x axis). Black dots <lb/>indicate sample sizes and mutation rates in the current study. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1871 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>per-tumor coverage across the panel of 43 driver genes (Supplemen-<lb/>tary Note 1). Specifically, for 88% of cancer driver genes, the expected <lb/>sensitivity for mutation detection was &gt;99% in the 100kGP cohort. Fur-<lb/>thermore, for 90% of cancer driver genes, &gt;98% of the coding sequence <lb/>had sufficient coverage such that more than six reads could be used for <lb/>mutation detection after accounting for tumor purity (Supplementary <lb/>Figs. 3-7). These findings are in agreement with published data on the <lb/>diagnostic accuracy of 100kGP WGS compared to panel sequencing <lb/>conducted by Genomics England (sensitivity of 99% for variant allele <lb/>frequency &gt;5% and coverage &gt;70×). <lb/>Actionability of driver gene mutations <lb/>We next sought to evaluate the landscape of clinically actionable driver <lb/>alterations through reference to the COSMIC and Precision Oncol-<lb/>ogy Knowledge Base (OncoKB). We observed that both the fraction of <lb/>samples and proportion of alteration types varied across tissue types. <lb/>Data from COSMIC indicated that 85% of all samples (8,880 of 10,478) <lb/>possessed at least one putatively actionable alteration being targeted <lb/>in a clinical setting (Fig. 7a and Supplementary Table 8), while 55% of <lb/>samples (5,805 of 10,478) had at least one putatively actionable or <lb/>biologically relevant alteration from OncoKB (Fig. 7b and Supplemen-<lb/>tary Tables 9 and 10). Across all cancer types, 15% (1,560 of 10,470) <lb/>of the patients would be eligible for a currently approved therapy as <lb/>defined by OncoKB. Of the actionable mutations defined by OncoKB <lb/>(n = 9,639), 5,823 were clonal, 2,632 were early clonal, 229 were late <lb/>clonal and 852 were subclonal. <lb/>The most common putatively actionable alterations across all of <lb/>the 35 cancer types were mutations in PIK3CA, KRAS and PTEN (Supple-<lb/>mentary Fig. 8). PIK3CA encodes the p110α protein, which is a catalytic <lb/>subunit of phosphatidylinositol 3-kinase (PI3K). Specific oncogenic <lb/>missense mutations in PIK3CA were present in 50% of lobular breast can-<lb/>cers and 38% of ductal breast cancers and their presence is an indication <lb/>for the use of PI3Kα inhibitor alpelisib 19 . These mutations are present <lb/>in a number of cancers including colorectal (20%) and uterine cancers <lb/>(47%) and in these tumor types are subject to early clinical studies with <lb/>an allosteric inhibitor of PI3Kα 20 . We found high fractions of patients <lb/>with pancreatic cancer, colorectal cancer and lung adenocarcinoma <lb/>with actionable KRAS mutations (39-64% of all cases). The KRAS G12C <lb/>mutation was present in 17% of lung adenocarcinoma cases and is tar-<lb/>geted by mutation-specific selective covalent inhibition with adagrasib <lb/>C&gt;A <lb/>C&gt;G <lb/>C&gt;T <lb/>T&gt;A <lb/>T&gt;C <lb/>T&gt;G <lb/>a <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>ANK1 <lb/>APC <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>ATM <lb/>ATRX <lb/>BAP1 <lb/>BRAF <lb/>CDKN2A <lb/>CIC <lb/>CSMD3 <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>ERBB2 <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>FGFR3 <lb/>FUBP1 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>KIT <lb/>KMT2C <lb/>KMT2D <lb/>KRAS <lb/>LRP1B <lb/>MGAM <lb/>MTOR <lb/>NF1 <lb/>NF2 <lb/>NOTCH1 <lb/>NRAS <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PKHD1L1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>RB1 <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>SYNE1 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>TRAF7 <lb/>TSC1 <lb/>VHL <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>Number of tumor types <lb/>Maximum mutation prevalence in a tumor type (%) <lb/>b <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>75 <lb/>50 <lb/>25 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>Percentage of tumor-specific driver genes <lb/>Tumor group <lb/>Activating <lb/>Ambiguous <lb/>Loss of function <lb/>Predicted <lb/>driver role <lb/>Fig. 4 | Distribution and predicted function of candidate cancer driver genes <lb/>across tumor types. a, Distribution of driver genes across different types of <lb/>cancer: y axis, maximal mutational prevalence in a tumor type; x axis, number of <lb/>tumor types in which the driver gene is identified. Genes labeled are candidate <lb/>drivers in at least six tumor types or have a maximum mutation prevalence in a <lb/>tumor type of &gt;17%. b, Distribution of cancer driver gene function associated <lb/>with each cancer type: y axis, tumor group; x axis, percentage of tumor-specific <lb/>driver genes. <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>TP53 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PTEN <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>KRAS <lb/>BRAF <lb/>NRAS <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>APC <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>ATM <lb/>ERBB3 <lb/>MTOR <lb/>DUSP16 <lb/>ACVR2A <lb/>RNF43 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>ATRX <lb/>CDKN2A <lb/>NF1 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>KMT2C <lb/>FOXA1 <lb/>MAP3K1 <lb/>MAP2K4 <lb/>RUNX1 <lb/>NCOR1 <lb/>ZFPM1 <lb/>SPEN <lb/>GATA3 <lb/>SF3B1 <lb/>ERBB2 <lb/>CDH1 <lb/>TBX3 <lb/>CBFB <lb/>RB1 <lb/>KMT2D <lb/>TSC1 <lb/>KDM6A <lb/>CREBBP <lb/>STAG2 <lb/>ELF3 <lb/>EP300 <lb/>KMT2A <lb/>RHOA <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>PPP2R1A <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>FGFR2 <lb/>CHD4 <lb/>BCOR <lb/>SPOP <lb/>CIC <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>NOTCH1 <lb/>NFE2L2 <lb/>SETD2 <lb/>BAP1 <lb/>VHL <lb/>PBRM1 <lb/>MGA <lb/>RBM10 <lb/>STK11 <lb/>KEAP1 <lb/>ARID2 <lb/>RAC1 <lb/>IDH2 <lb/>CASP8 <lb/>MAX <lb/>ARHGAP35 <lb/>CTCF <lb/>ESR1 <lb/>NF2 <lb/>KLF4 <lb/>TRAF7 <lb/>ARID1B <lb/>SIN3A <lb/>GNAS <lb/>HLA-A <lb/>MAP2K1 <lb/>PSPC1 <lb/>ZFHX3 <lb/>MED12 <lb/>ZMYM3 <lb/>CDK12 <lb/>HRAS <lb/>CDKN1A <lb/>ASXL1 <lb/>MUC4 <lb/>ZNF98 <lb/>ZSCAN5A <lb/>MUC20 <lb/>CDKN1B <lb/>FOXO3 <lb/>USP17L22 <lb/>SEC22B <lb/>SMARCA4 <lb/>PRPF8 <lb/>TET2 <lb/>CUL3 <lb/>SMARCB1 <lb/>ROCK1 <lb/>PRAMEF15 <lb/>AGAP6 <lb/>BRCA2 <lb/>CSMD3 <lb/>HLA-B <lb/>MYH9 <lb/>SETD1B <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>LRP1B <lb/>FAT3 <lb/>NCOR2 <lb/>CDH10 <lb/>NBEA <lb/>PDGFRB <lb/>EPHA3 <lb/>NSD1 <lb/>ATR <lb/>BIRC6 <lb/>ROBO2 <lb/>PTPRB <lb/>MUC16 <lb/>PDE4DIP <lb/>FAT4 <lb/>TRRAP <lb/>SLC35G5 <lb/>DCTN1 <lb/>AKAP9 <lb/>CNTNAP2 <lb/>N4BP2 <lb/>DDX3X <lb/>MET <lb/>PTPN11 <lb/>KIT <lb/>-log10q <lb/>&gt;6 <lb/>4 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fig. 3 | Heatmap of candidate cancer driver genes identified in at least two different cancer types. Heatmap intensity proportional to q value. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1872 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>or sotorasib 21,22 . PI3Kβ inhibition is of significant biological interest <lb/>in patients with oncogenic inactivating PTEN mutations, as PI3Kβ is <lb/>thought to drive cellular proliferation in these tumors. Inactivating <lb/>PTEN mutations were prevalent in melanoma (10%), hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma (13%), squamous cell carcinoma of the lung (15%), glioblas-<lb/>toma multiforme (29%) and uterine carcinoma (66%) and their presence <lb/>would result in eligibility for early studies of PI3Kβ inhibition 23 . <lb/>Landscape of clinical actionability <lb/>In addition to actionable mutations in single genes, other classes of <lb/>molecular alterations are recognized as tumor-agnostic biomark-<lb/>ers of drug response. These include mutational profiles caused by <lb/>dMMR/POLE mutations and homologous recombination deficiency <lb/>(HRD), which represent phenotypic markers for response to immu-<lb/>notherapy and PARP inhibition respectively. A total of 319 tumors (3%) <lb/>exhibited a mutational signature for HRD, which provides an indica-<lb/>tion for PARP inhibition therapy and potential sensitivity to platinum <lb/>chemotherapy 24-28 . As demonstrated in our companion paper, the etio-<lb/>logical basis of HRD was, however, only identifiable in 16% of these cases <lb/>based on biallelic inactivation of BRCA1, BRCA2, PALB2, BRIP1 or RAD51B <lb/>through germline and somatic mutations 29 . While other cases may be <lb/>caused by promoter methylation, which could not be assessed because <lb/>these data are not available for 100kGP samples, the findings provide <lb/>a strong rationale for extending the number of patients potentially <lb/>eligible for PARP inhibitors rather than solely relying on BRCA-testing. <lb/>A total of 1,309 tumors possessed a high coding tumor mutational <lb/>burden (more than ten mutations per megabase, Mb) and 144 cancers <lb/>had evidence of dMMR. Considering these collectively would suggest <lb/>that 1,312 patients may be eligible for checkpoint inhibition 30,31 . To <lb/>explore the prospect of several targeted therapies being used in the <lb/>same patient, we combined the OncoKB clinical actionability annota-<lb/>tions with that of TMB, dMMR and HRD clinical actionability annota-<lb/>tions. In total, 11,503 independent unique gene targets were present <lb/>in 6,151 samples with 34% (3,577 of 10,478) of tumors possessing one, <lb/>13% (1,361 of 10,478) two and 12% (1,213 of 10,478) possessing at least <lb/>three clinically actionable driver mutations. <lb/>Expanding the druggable cancer genome <lb/>An opportunity emerging from the systematic analysis of cancer <lb/>genomes is the identification of new therapeutic intervention strate-<lb/>gies. Of the 330 candidate cancer driver genes identified in this study, <lb/>261 (79%) are not currently identified as therapeutic targets in either <lb/>COSMIC or OncoKB databases. As a means of triaging these genes as <lb/>candidates for therapeutic intervention, we assessed the essential-<lb/>ity and selectivity of driver genes and their druggability using RNAi/ <lb/>CRISPR DepMap data and the integrative cancer-focused knowledge-<lb/>base, canSAR, respectively 32,33 . We found 96 of 261 (37%) of these genes <lb/>are predicted to be commonly essential and of these 12 of 96 (13%) <lb/>have a chemical probe available and 35 of 96 (36%) have a ligandable <lb/>three-dimensional (3D) structure (Supplementary Table 11). <lb/>Motivated by the observation that targeting proteins which inter-<lb/>act with cancer driver genes can result in successful precision oncology <lb/>strategies, we sought to expand the network of druggable targets in <lb/>cancer 34,35 . To this end, we used canSAR to map and pharmacologically <lb/>annotate networks of the cancer genes identified for each tumor type. <lb/>Specifically, we seeded networks with driver genes identified in each <lb/>tumor group and used transcriptional and curated protein-protein <lb/>interactions to recover a refined cancer-specific network of proteins, <lb/>Breast_DuctalCA <lb/>Breast_LobularCA <lb/>P value <lb/>P value <lb/>Expected mutation <lb/>rate <lb/>Expected mutation <lb/>rate <lb/>10 -4 <lb/>10 -10 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>10 -4 <lb/>10 -10 <lb/>10 0 <lb/>10 -1 <lb/>10 -2 <lb/>10 -3 <lb/>CNS_Astro <lb/>CNS_GBM_IDHmut <lb/>CNS_GBM_IDHwt <lb/>CNS_Menin <lb/>CNS_Oligo <lb/>Kidney_CCRCC <lb/>Kidney_ChRCC <lb/>Breast <lb/>Kidney <lb/>CNS Connective <lb/>Lung <lb/>Connective_Chondro <lb/>Connective_Leiomyo <lb/>Connective_Liposarc <lb/>Connective_Myxofibro <lb/>Connective_Osteosarc <lb/>Connective_SCS <lb/>Connective_SS <lb/>Lung_AdenoCA <lb/>Lung_LargeCell <lb/>Lung_SCC <lb/>Lung_SmallCell <lb/>Kidney_PRCC <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>BRCA2 <lb/>CBFB <lb/>CDH1 <lb/>CDKN1B <lb/>CTCF <lb/>ERBB2 <lb/>GATA3 <lb/>FOXA1 <lb/>KMT2C <lb/>KMT2D <lb/>SPEN <lb/>SF3B1 <lb/>RUNX1 <lb/>RB1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>NF1 <lb/>NCOR1 <lb/>MAP3K1 <lb/>MAP2K4 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>NF1 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>CIC <lb/>ATRX <lb/>ZFPM1 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>TBX3 <lb/>RB1 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>ATRX <lb/>RB1 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>TERT <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>BAP1 <lb/>KDM5C <lb/>MTOR <lb/>PBRM1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>SETD2 <lb/>TET2 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>VHL <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>ARID2 <lb/>ATM <lb/>BRAF <lb/>CDH10 <lb/>CDKN2A <lb/>CMTR2 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>KEAP1 <lb/>KMT2D <lb/>TP53 <lb/>RB1 <lb/>KRAS <lb/>LRP1B <lb/>MGA <lb/>NF1 <lb/>NFE2L2 <lb/>NOTCH1 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PTEN <lb/>PKHD1L1 <lb/>RASA1 <lb/>RBM10 <lb/>SETD2 <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>SMARCA4 <lb/>STK11 <lb/>Fig. 5 | Comparison of driver gene somatic mutation rates between tumor <lb/>histologies. Expected mutation rate and 95% confidence intervals of each driver <lb/>in the cohort (2,306 breast, 440 central nervous system (CNS), 1,045 kidney, <lb/>1,110 lung and 607 connective tissue tumors in the 100kGP cohort) based on <lb/>the number of samples in which the driver gene is mutated for the given tumor <lb/>histology. Binomial P values are shown. The dashed red line corresponds to a <lb/>false discovery rate of 0.01. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1873 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>each protein being annotated on the basis of several assessments of <lb/>&apos;druggability&apos;, that is the likelihood of the protein being amenable to <lb/>small molecule drug intervention. After seeding each cancer-specific <lb/>network with their respective drivers, we yielded a total of 631 distinct <lb/>proteins across all cancers (Supplementary Table 12). The median num-<lb/>ber of unique proteins in each network across all cohorts was 57, with <lb/>colorectal cancer possessing the largest network (n = 231; Extended <lb/>Data Fig. 9) and spindle cell carcinoma possessing the smallest net-<lb/>work (n = 10). As expected there was a correlation between network <lb/>size and number of identified drivers for each cancer type (Pearson&apos;s <lb/>r = 0.9, P = 1.23 × 10 -9 ). <lb/>Of these 631 proteins, 58% (n = 369) were retrieved solely through <lb/>network analysis, of which most (n = 323) were not formally identified <lb/>as candidate driver genes in any cancer type (hereafter referred to as <lb/>cancer-network proteins). Notable examples include HDAC1, CDK2 <lb/>and CDK1, which were present in 31, 29 and 28 cohorts, respectively. <lb/>We observed 70% (n = 225) of these cancer-network proteins as being <lb/>targetable by existing approved or investigational therapies, with <lb/>notable examples including BCL2 and BTK. Of the remaining 97 genes, <lb/>34 are commonly essential, 11 possess concordant lineage specificity, <lb/>48 are ligandable by 3D structure and 11 have an existing high-quality <lb/>probe available (Supplementary Table 13). Collectively these data <lb/>provide potential future opportunities for therapy for several cancers. <lb/>For example, CDC5L, a core component of the Prp19 (hPrp19)/Cdc5L <lb/>pre-RNA splicing complex, is part of the melanoma cancer protein <lb/>network 36 . This protein is predicted to be commonly essential with <lb/>lineage specificity and has a 3D ligandable structure. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Clinical and laboratory observations have led to the recognition <lb/>that genomic profiling of tumors is increasingly important for the <lb/>management of patients with cancers 37 . To explore the value of WGS <lb/>to precision oncology we have analysed WGS data on 10,470 patients <lb/>recruited to the 100kGP study. <lb/>Across all cancers, we identified 330 cancer driver genes, 74 of <lb/>which are new to any cancer type. The candidate driver gene list is <lb/>limited by focusing on point mutations and small indels without <lb/>consideration of copy-number alterations, genomic fusions or meth-<lb/>ylation events. Nevertheless, we believe it represents one of the most <lb/>comprehensive efforts thus far to identify cancer driver genes and <lb/>serves as an important research asset. The similarities and differences <lb/>in driver mutation frequencies in cancers arising from the same organ <lb/>imply both shared and divergent pathways in oncogenesis. Notably, <lb/>however, many driver mutations are common across several differ-<lb/>ent tumor types. If clinically translated, these observations suggest <lb/>that currently 55% of patients&apos; tumors harbor a potentially actionable <lb/>mutation, either in terms of predicting sensitivity to certain treat-<lb/>ments or clinical trial eligibility. This contrasts with 22% achievable <lb/>if based on the current small variant testing panels in widespread <lb/>use 38 . Although our assumption is predicated on approved drugs as <lb/>a proxy for effective cancer therapies, a recent study of cancer drug <lb/>approvals by the Food and Drug Administration (FDA) concluded <lb/>that new cancer drug approvals reduce the risk of death and tumor <lb/>progression 39 . To inform potential future therapeutic opportunities, <lb/>we applied established chemogenomic technologies to map and <lb/>pharmacologically annotate the cellular network of cancer genes <lb/>identified by WGS. Through annotation of cellular networks with <lb/>measures of essentiality and selectivity, we were able to highlight <lb/>additional potential therapeutic targets in cancer. It is likely that such <lb/>endeavors will be improved by exploiting emergent high-throughput <lb/>reporter assays to assess the functional consequences of somatic <lb/>driver mutations in greater detail 40 . <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>ATM <lb/>BCL9L <lb/>CREBBP <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>INPPL1 <lb/>KMT2C <lb/>MGA <lb/>NF1 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>PSPC1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>RB1 <lb/>RNF43 <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>ZFHX3 <lb/>ZFP36L2 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>Total number of subclonal oncogenic mutations in a <lb/>cancer driver gene <lb/>Proportion of oncogenic mutations in a cancer driver <lb/>gene that are subclonal (%) <lb/>APC <lb/>KRAS <lb/>APC <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>ATM <lb/>BRAF <lb/>KRAS <lb/>NF1 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>TP53 <lb/>VHL <lb/>0 <lb/>25 <lb/>50 <lb/>75 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>2,000 <lb/>3,000 <lb/>Total number of clonal oncogenic mutations in a <lb/>cancer driver gene <lb/>Proportion of oncogenic mutations in a cancer driver <lb/>gene that are clonal (%) <lb/>Fig. 6 | Distribution of clonal and subclonal oncogenic mutations in candidate <lb/>cancer driver genes. a, Distribution of clonal oncogenic mutations in candidate <lb/>cancer driver genes across all cancer types: y axis, percentage of all clonal <lb/>oncogenic mutations of all oncogenic mutations; x axis, total number of clonal <lb/>oncogenic mutations. Clonal oncogenic mutations include clonal mutations <lb/>that occurred before duplications involving the relevant chromosome (early), <lb/>clonal mutations that occurred after such duplications (late), and mutations that <lb/>occurred when no duplication was observed. Genes labeled are those with &gt;250 <lb/>clonal oncogenic mutations or clonal oncogenic mutations represent &gt;95% of <lb/>all oncogenic mutations. b, Distribution of all subclonal oncogenic mutations <lb/>in candidate cancer driver genes across all cancer types: y axis, percentage of all <lb/>subclonal oncogenic mutations of all oncogenic mutations; x axis, total number <lb/>of subclonal oncogenic mutations. Genes labeled are those with &gt;50 subclonal <lb/>oncogenic mutations and &gt;5% of all oncogenic mutations as subclonal. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1874 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>The strengths of this study not only include the cohort size but <lb/>the combination of systematic processing of samples and data aris-<lb/>ing from several treatment centers across England. These strengths <lb/>minimize the impact of between-center sequencing effects while <lb/>ensuring a representative cohort of cancers are captured 41 . We do, <lb/>however, acknowledge that while the spectrum of cancers included in <lb/>our analysis is largely representative of those diagnosed in the United <lb/>Kingdom, patients recruited to 100kGP are younger and predominantly <lb/>have early-stage disease. Furthermore, characteristics such as patient <lb/>ancestry and geography can affect the mutagenic profile of tumors, <lb/>a <lb/>Supported by compelling biological evidence <lb/>None <lb/>Clinical evidence in the cancer type or standard <lb/>of care in a di erent cancer type <lb/>FDA approved drug in the cancer type <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>0 <lb/>b <lb/>OncoKB actionability <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>Standard of care in the cancer type <lb/>COSMIC actionability <lb/>3 <lb/>Approved marketed drug with <lb/>demonstrated e icacy at the mutation <lb/>Phase 2/3 clinical results meet <lb/>primary outcome measures <lb/>Drug in ongoing clinical trials <lb/>None <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Tumor type <lb/>2,000 <lb/>1,500 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>500 <lb/>0 <lb/>Number <lb/>2,000 <lb/>1,500 <lb/>1,000 <lb/>500 <lb/>0 <lb/>Number <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Tumor type <lb/>Fig. 7 | Clinical actionability ascribable to each candidate cancer driver <lb/>gene. a, Clinical actionability ascribable to each candidate cancer driver gene <lb/>according to COSMIC by cancer type. Tumors were annotated by the highest <lb/>scoring gene mutation-indication pairing, with &apos;None&apos; indicating no actionable <lb/>mutations were detected in the tumor. b, Clinical actionability ascribable to each <lb/>candidate cancer driver gene according to OncoKB by cancer type. Tumors were <lb/>annotated by the highest scoring gene mutation-indication pairing, with &apos;None&apos; <lb/>indicating no actionable mutations were detected in the tumor. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1875 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>which potentially impacts on the generalizability of our findings to <lb/>worldwide populations 42,43 . <lb/>Accepting these limitations, our observations indicate that, <lb/>depending on cancer type, approximately 15% of patients are poten-<lb/>tially eligible for a currently approved therapy targeting an oncogenic <lb/>driver. Our discovery analysis, however, implies that far more patients <lb/>may potentially be candidates for a therapy targeting a driver mutation <lb/>or pathway. A long-standing criticism of precision oncology is that <lb/>often its proponents overstate the clinical actionability of individual <lb/>genes or genomic variants 44 . Mutations that are clinically validated and <lb/>FDA-recognized as predictive biomarkers of drug response are often <lb/>grouped together as clinically actionable, with such mutations poten-<lb/>tially erroneously identified as the putative basis for outlier exceptional <lb/>responses. To better communicate the strength of evidence support-<lb/>ing the clinical actionability of individual mutant alleles, many variant <lb/>knowledge bases stratify genomic alterations on the basis of the level <lb/>of clinical and/or biological data supporting their use as a predictive <lb/>biomarker of drug response or resistance. Here, we have sought to <lb/>address such concerns by making use of well-curated resources to <lb/>assign actionability to driver mutations. Specifically, we have queried <lb/>knowledge databases which are regularly curated by an expert panel <lb/>and are therefore recognized to reflect the current state of knowledge 31 . <lb/>While the 100kGP was predicated on delivering diagnostic tests <lb/>for well-established actionable mutations in NHS cancer patients with <lb/>high sensitivity, concern has been raised over missing well-recognized <lb/>clinically actionable mutations 45 . In our analysis the frequency of estab-<lb/>lished cancer-specific oncogenic drivers recovered was, however, <lb/>comparable to MSK-IMPACT and MSK-MET 6,9 . Moreover, the sensitivity <lb/>of 100× WGS to identify mutations was high even for samples with low <lb/>tumor purity (Supplementary Note 1 and Supplementary Figs. 3-7). <lb/>A barrier to the broader success of precision oncology paradigms <lb/>may be the many &apos;undruggable&apos; oncogenic mutations coupled with the <lb/>fact that targeting downstream effectors typically fails to demonstrate <lb/>the levels of clinical efficacy of drugs that directly inhibit the mutated <lb/>oncoprotein. Recent developments in protein structure prediction, <lb/>new degraders, covalent inhibition and allosteric protein domain <lb/>maps seek to unlock these &apos;undruggable&apos; proteins 46-49 . Furthermore, <lb/>WGS allows for the extension of analyses beyond the consideration of <lb/>individual genetic alterations, thereby affording a clinically significant <lb/>benefit over targeted panel sequencing assays. Mutational signatures <lb/>associated with dMMR and HRD are increasingly being shown to be <lb/>clinically relevant to defining responsiveness to immunotherapy and <lb/>PARP inhibition, respectively 24,30 . Additionally, there is increasing <lb/>evidence that other signatures reflecting the DNA repair capacity of <lb/>cancer cells are predictive of drug responsiveness to other agents 5,50 . A <lb/>more detailed discussion and comprehensive description of all classes <lb/>of mutational signatures observed across the 100kGP are reported in <lb/>our companion paper 29 . The ability to robustly characterize mutational <lb/>signatures may therefore prove to be a major clinically significant <lb/>incremental benefit of WGS over targeted panel sequencing assays. <lb/>Moreover, the provision of WGS is likely to play a greater role in patient <lb/>management given that T cell-based therapies are of increasing impor-<lb/>tance and in silico approaches are now used to predict the presence of <lb/>immunogenic tumor-specific neoantigens from WGS 51-54 . <lb/>Despite the merits of WGS as a one-stop clinical assay, its wider <lb/>adoption outside selected academic and commercial centers has been <lb/>limited 37 . A great hurdle is that the tumor material available for many <lb/>patients is of insufficient quantity, quality or purity for these broader <lb/>sequencing platforms. Indeed, in the 100kGP the lack of access to fresh <lb/>frozen samples (and/or those of sufficient quantity) precluded the <lb/>analysis of tumors from many patients 11 . In designing clinical assays, <lb/>the limitations imposed by cost and sequencing capacity require the <lb/>balancing of sequencing breadth and depth 41 . At present, the higher <lb/>coverage of targeted assays represents an advantage over WGS for <lb/>detection of alterations in genes clinically validated as biomarkers of <lb/>drug response, especially in samples with poor DNA quality or high stro-<lb/>mal contamination. A wider adoption of WGS will require further reduc-<lb/>tions in sequencing costs and technological improvements to enable <lb/>the use of lower-quality, archival formalin-fixed, paraffin-embedded <lb/>tumor tissue 55 . Any such developments will have to address the issue <lb/>that formalin fixation adversely affects DNA quality and the ability to <lb/>reliably call variants from WGS data, even when using bioinformatic <lb/>correction 41,56,57 . Aside from such technical issues there are also inher-<lb/>ent limitations to short-read WGS. Notably, structural variants cannot <lb/>be robustly called, with low concordance being a feature of present <lb/>implemented algorithms 58,59 . It is likely that this limitation will only be <lb/>addressed by adoption of long-read sequencing, albeit presently this <lb/>incurs a high requirement for DNA and further cost, thus restricting its <lb/>use in the diagnostic setting 60 . The continued decline in sequencing <lb/>costs and the identification of new genomic biomarkers predictive of <lb/>drug response have driven the rapid adoption of multigene profiling <lb/>of patients as a component of routine cancer care. As our analysis indi-<lb/>cates, the future adoption of WGS or broader panels has the potential to <lb/>enable more accurate assessments of the driver mutational landscape <lb/>predictive of drug response. <lb/>Online content <lb/>Any methods, additional references, Nature Portfolio reporting sum-<lb/>maries, source data, extended data, supplementary information, <lb/>acknowledgements, peer review information; details of author contri-<lb/>butions and competing interests; and statements of data and code avail-<lb/>ability are available at https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Topol, E. J. Individualized medicine from pre-womb to tomb. Cell <lb/>157, 241-253 (2014). <lb/>2. Schwartzberg, L., Kim, E. S., Liu, D. &amp; Schrag, D. Precision <lb/>oncology: who, how, what, when and when not? Am. Soc. Clin. <lb/>Oncol. Educ. Book 37, 160-169 (2017). <lb/>3. Stratton, M. R., Campbell, P. J. &amp; Futreal, P. A. The cancer genome. <lb/>Nature 458, 719-724 (2009). <lb/>4. Martínez-Jiménez, F. et al. A compendium of mutational cancer <lb/>driver genes. Nat. Rev. Cancer 20, 555-572 (2020). <lb/>5. Chakravarty, D. &amp; Solit, D. B. Clinical cancer genomic profiling. <lb/>Nat. Rev. Genet. 22, 483-501 (2021). <lb/>6. Cheng, D. T. et al. Memorial Sloan Kettering-integrated <lb/>mutation profiling of actionable cancer targets (MSK-IMPACT): a <lb/>hybridization capture-based next-generation sequencing clinical <lb/>assay for solid tumor molecular oncology. J. Mol. Diagn. 17, <lb/>251-264 (2015). <lb/>7. Redig, A. J. &amp; Jänne, P. A. Basket trials and the evolution of clinical <lb/>trial design in an era of genomic medicine. J. Clin. Oncol. 33, <lb/>975-977 (2015). <lb/>8. Hyman, D. M., Taylor, B. S. &amp; Baselga, J. Implementing <lb/>genome-driven oncology. Cell 168, 584-599 (2017). <lb/>9. Zehir, A. et al. Mutational landscape of metastatic cancer revealed <lb/>from prospective clinical sequencing of 10,000 patients. Nat. <lb/>Med. 23, 703-713 (2017). <lb/>10. Cuppen, E. et al. Implementation of whole-genome and <lb/>transcriptome sequencing into clinical cancer care. JCO Precis <lb/>Oncol. 6, e2200245 (2022). <lb/>11. Turnbull, C. et al. The 100 000 Genomes Project: bringing whole <lb/>genome sequencing to the NHS. Br. Med. J. 361, k1687 (2018). <lb/>12. ICGC/TCGA Pan-Cancer Analysis of Whole Genomes Consortium. <lb/>Pan-cancer analysis of whole genomes. Nature 578, 82-93 (2020). <lb/>13. Bailey, M. H. et al. Comprehensive characterization of cancer <lb/>driver genes and mutations. Cell 173, 371-385 (2018). <lb/>14. Wang, K. et al. Whole-genome sequencing and comprehensive <lb/>molecular profiling identify new driver mutations in gastric <lb/>cancer. Nat. Genet. 46, 573-582 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1876 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>15. Gerstung, M. et al. The evolutionary history of 2,658 cancers. <lb/>Nature 578, 122-128 (2020). <lb/>16. Gerlinger, M. et al. Genomic architecture and evolution of clear <lb/>cell renal cell carcinomas defined by multiregion sequencing. <lb/>Nat. Genet. 46, 225-233 (2014). <lb/>17. Gibson, W. J. et al. The genomic landscape and evolution of <lb/>endometrial carcinoma progression and abdominopelvic <lb/>metastasis. Nat. Genet. 48, 848-855 (2016). <lb/>18. Yates, L. R. et al. Genomic evolution of breast cancer metastasis <lb/>and relapse. Cancer Cell 32, 169-184 (2017). <lb/>19. André, F. et al. Alpelisib for PIK3CA-mutated, hormone <lb/>receptor-positive advanced breast cancer. N. Engl. J. Med. 380, <lb/>1929-1940 (2019). <lb/>20. Varkaris, A. et al. Allosteric PI3K-alpha inhibition overcomes <lb/>on-target resistance to orthosteric inhibitors mediated by <lb/>secondary PIK3CA mutations. Cancer Discov. 14, 227-239 (2024). <lb/>21. Fell, J. B. et al. Identification of the clinical development <lb/>candidate, a covalent KRAS inhibitor for the treatment of cancer. <lb/>J. Med. Chem. 63, 6679-6693 (2020). <lb/>22. Canon, J. et al. The clinical KRAS(G12C) inhibitor AMG 510 drives <lb/>anti-tumour immunity. Nature 575, 217-223 (2019). <lb/>23. Mateo, J. et al. A first-time-in-human study of GSK2636771, a <lb/>phosphoinositide 3 kinase beta-selective inhibitor, in patients with <lb/>advanced solid tumors. Clin. Cancer Res. 23, 5981-5992 (2017). <lb/>24. Chopra, N. et al. Homologous recombination DNA repair <lb/>deficiency and PARP inhibition activity in primary triple negative <lb/>breast cancer. Nat. Commun. 11, 2662 (2020). <lb/>25. Farmer, H. et al. Targeting the DNA repair defect in BRCA mutant <lb/>cells as a therapeutic strategy. Nature 434, 917-921 (2005). <lb/>26. Fong, P. C. et al. Inhibition of poly(ADP-ribose) polymerase in <lb/>tumors from BRCA mutation carriers. N. Engl. J. Med. 361, 123-134 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>27. Konstantinopoulos, P. A. et al. Gene expression profile of <lb/>BRCAness that correlates with responsiveness to chemotherapy <lb/>and with outcome in patients with epithelial ovarian cancer. J. <lb/>Clin. Oncol. 28, 3555-3561 (2010). <lb/>28. Purwar, R. et al. Role of PARP inhibitors beyond BRCA mutation <lb/>and platinum sensitivity in epithelial ovarian cancer: a <lb/>meta-analysis of hazard ratios from randomized clinical trials. <lb/>World J. Surg. Oncol. 21, 157 (2023). <lb/>29. Everall, A. et al. Comprehensive repertoire of the chromosomal <lb/>alteration and mutational signatures across 16 cancer types <lb/>from 10,983 cancer patients. Preprint at medRxiv https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1101/2023.06.07.23290970 (2023). <lb/>30. Marabelle, A. et al. Association of tumour mutational burden <lb/>with outcomes in patients with advanced solid tumours treated <lb/>with pembrolizumab: prospective biomarker analysis of the <lb/>multicohort, open-label, phase 2 KEYNOTE-158 study. Lancet <lb/>Oncol. 21, 1353-1365 (2020). <lb/>31. Chakravarty, D. et al. OncoKB: a precision oncology knowledge <lb/>base. JCO Precis. Oncol. https://doi.org/10.1200/po.17.00011 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>32. Shimada, K., Bachman, J. A., Muhlich, J. L. &amp; Mitchison, T. J. <lb/>shinyDepMap, a tool to identify targetable cancer genes and their <lb/>functional connections from Cancer Dependency Map data. eLife <lb/>10, e57116 (2021). <lb/>33. Mitsopoulos, C. et al. canSAR: update to the cancer translational <lb/>research and drug discovery knowledgebase. Nucleic Acids Res. <lb/>49, D1074-D1082 (2020). <lb/>34. Filippakopoulos, P. et al. Selective inhibition of BET <lb/>bromodomains. Nature 468, 1067-1073 (2010). <lb/>35. Zhao, Y., Aguilar, A., Bernard, D. &amp; Wang, S. Small-molecule <lb/>inhibitors of the MDM2-p53 protein-protein interaction (MDM2 <lb/>inhibitors) in clinical trials for cancer treatment. J. Med. Chem. 58, <lb/>1038-1052 (2015). <lb/>36. Burns, C. G., Ohi, R., Krainer, A. R. &amp; Gould, K. L. Evidence that <lb/>Myb-related CDC5 proteins are required for pre-mRNA splicing. <lb/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 96, 13789-13794 (1999). <lb/>37. Freedman, A. N. et al. Use of next-generation sequencing tests to <lb/>guide cancer treatment: results from a nationally representative <lb/>survey of oncologists in the United States. JCO Precis. Oncol. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1200/PO.18.00169 (2018). <lb/>38. National Genomic Test Directory (NHS England, accessed 7 <lb/>February 2023); https://www.england.nhs.uk/publication/ <lb/>national-genomic-test-directories/ <lb/>39. Michaeli, D. T. &amp; Michaeli, T. Overall survival, progression-free <lb/>survival and tumor response benefit supporting initial US Food <lb/>and Drug Administration approval and indication extension of <lb/>new cancer drugs, 2003-2021. J. Clin. Oncol. 40, 4095-4106 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>40. Kim, Y. et al. High-throughput functional evaluation of human <lb/>cancer-associated mutations using base editors. Nat. Biotechnol. <lb/>40, 874-884 (2022). <lb/>41. Xiao, W. et al. Toward best practice in cancer mutation detection <lb/>with whole-genome and whole-exome sequencing. Nat. <lb/>Biotechnol. 39, 1141-1150 (2021). <lb/>42. Ansari-Pour, N. et al. Whole-genome analysis of Nigerian patients <lb/>with breast cancer reveals ethnic-driven somatic evolution and <lb/>distinct genomic subtypes. Nat. Commun. 12, 6946 (2021). <lb/>43. Hoang, M. L. et al. Mutational signature of aristolochic acid <lb/>exposure as revealed by whole-exome sequencing. Sci. Transl. <lb/>Med. 5, 197ra102 (2013). <lb/>44. Prasad, V. Perspective: the precision-oncology illusion. Nature <lb/>537, S63 (2016). <lb/>45. Cibulskis, K. et al. Sensitive detection of somatic point mutations <lb/>in impure and heterogeneous cancer samples. Nat. Biotechnol. <lb/>31, 213-219 (2013). <lb/>46. Jumper, J. et al. Highly accurate protein structure prediction with <lb/>AlphaFold. Nature 596, 583-589 (2021). <lb/>47. Faure, A. J. et al. Mapping the energetic and allosteric <lb/>landscapes of protein binding domains. Nature 604, 175-183 <lb/>(2022). <lb/>48. Singh, J., Petter, R. C., Baillie, T. A. &amp; Whitty, A. The resurgence <lb/>of covalent drugs. Nat. Rev. Drug Discov. 10, 307-317 <lb/>(2011). <lb/>49. Sakamoto, K. M. et al. Protacs: chimeric molecules that target <lb/>proteins to the Skp1-Cullin-F box complex for ubiquitination <lb/>and degradation. Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 98, 8554-8559 <lb/>(2001). <lb/>50. Brady, S. W., Gout, A. M. &amp; Zhang, J. Therapeutic and prognostic <lb/>insights from the analysis of cancer mutational signatures. Trends <lb/>Genet. 38, 194-208 (2022). <lb/>51. Gross, G., Waks, T. &amp; Eshhar, Z. Expression of <lb/>immunoglobulin-T-cell receptor chimeric molecules as <lb/>functional receptors with antibody-type specificity. Proc. Natl <lb/>Acad. Sci. USA 86, 10024-10028 (1989). <lb/>52. June, C. H., O&apos;Connor, R. S., Kawalekar, O. U., Ghassemi, S. &amp; <lb/>Milone, M. C. CAR T cell immunotherapy for human cancer. <lb/>Science 359, 1361-1365 (2018). <lb/>53. Hundal, J. et al. pVAC-Seq: a genome-guided in silico approach to <lb/>identifying tumor neoantigens. Genome Med. 8, 11 (2016). <lb/>54. Sarkizova, S. et al. A large peptidome dataset improves HLA class <lb/>I epitope prediction across most of the human population. Nat. <lb/>Biotechnol. 38, 199-209 (2020). <lb/>55. Schwarze, K. et al. The complete costs of genome sequencing: <lb/>a microcosting study in cancer and rare diseases from a single <lb/>center in the United Kingdom. Genet. Med. 22, 85-94 (2019). <lb/>56. Do, H. &amp; Dobrovic, A. Sequence artifacts in DNA from <lb/>formalin-fixed tissues: causes and strategies for minimization. <lb/>Clin. Chem. 61, 64-71 (2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics | Volume 56 | September 2024 | 1868-1877 <lb/></note>

			<page>1877 <lb/></page>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>57. Wong, S. Q. et al. Sequence artefacts in a prospective series of <lb/>formalin-fixed tumours tested for mutations in hotspot regions by <lb/>massively parallel sequencing. BMC Med. Genomics 7, 23 <lb/>(2014). <lb/>58. Li, Y. et al. Patterns of somatic structural variation in human <lb/>cancer genomes. Nature 578, 112-121 (2020). <lb/>59. Kosugi, S. et al. Comprehensive evaluation of structural variation <lb/>detection algorithms for whole genome sequencing. Genome <lb/>Biol. 20, 117 (2019). <lb/>60. Amarasinghe, S. L. et al. Opportunities and challenges in <lb/>long-read sequencing data analysis. Genome Biol. 21, 30 <lb/>(2020). <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>Publisher&apos;s note Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to <lb/>jurisdictional claims in published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, <lb/>as long as you give appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the <lb/>source, provide a link to the Creative Commons licence, and indicate <lb/>if changes were made. The images or other third party material in this <lb/>article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence, unless <lb/>indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not <lb/>included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons licence and your intended <lb/>use is not permitted by statutory regulation or exceeds the permitted <lb/>use, you will need to obtain permission directly from the copyright <lb/>holder. To view a copy of this licence, visit http://creativecommons. <lb/>org/licenses/by/4.0/. <lb/>© The Author(s) 2024 <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/>Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

		<div type="annex">Methods <lb/>The 100kGP cohort <lb/>The analysed cohort comprised tumor-normal sample pairs from <lb/>patients with primary cancers recruited to 100kGP (v.11 release) <lb/>through 13 Genomic Medicine Centers across England (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 9). Genomics England has obtained written informed consent from <lb/>all participants. We restricted our analysis to high-quality sequencing <lb/>data derived from PCR-free, flash-frozen primary solid tumor samples <lb/>from 10,470 adults (34 bile duct, 305 bladder, 2,306 breast, 2,324 colo-<lb/>rectal, 440 central nervous system, 91 esophageal, 201 head and neck, <lb/>1,045 renal cell, 24 liver, 1,110 lung, 35 mesothelioma, 607 soft tissue, <lb/>454 ovarian, 94 pancreas, 366 prostate, 270 melanoma, 72 gastric, 51 <lb/>testicular and 649 uterus) (Supplementary Tables 1-3). Comprehensive <lb/>clinicopathology information on the patients is provided in Supple-<lb/>mentary Table 3 and complete details on sample curation, tumor purity <lb/>per cancer type (Extended Data Fig. 10), WGS, somatic variant calling, <lb/>mutation annotation and power calculations are provided in Supple-<lb/>mentary Note 1. We identified mutational signatures associated with <lb/>dMMR and HRD in tumors using SigProfilerExtractor complemented <lb/>by mSINGS and HRDetect (Supplementary Note 1) 29,61,62 . <lb/>Identification and timing of driver genes <lb/>Cancer driver genes for each of the tumor types were identified <lb/>using the IntOGen pipeline (Supplementary Note 1) 4 . We examined <lb/>the sensitivity of WGS in the 100kGP cohort to detect mutations in <lb/>well-established driver genes based on sample purity and gene cover-<lb/>age and by comparing the call rates of panel sequencing reported in <lb/>the Integrated Mutation Profiling of Actionable Cancer Targets and <lb/>Metastatic Events and Tropisms studies of cancer conducted by the <lb/>MSK Cancer Center (Supplementary Note 1) 6,63 . The relative evolu-<lb/>tionary timings of candidate driver mutations were obtained using <lb/>MutationTimeR (Supplementary Note 1) 15 . <lb/>Actionability of driver gene mutations and networks <lb/>We first queried the OncoKB and COSMIC Mutation Actionability in <lb/>Precision Oncology Product databases to evaluate the therapeutic <lb/>implications of genetic events 31,64 . Both databases catalog approved <lb/>marketed drugs having demonstrated efficacy in tumors with specified <lb/>driver gene mutations, based on clinical trials and published clinical <lb/>evidence. OncoKB also provides compelling biological evidence sup-<lb/>porting the cancer driver gene as being predictive of a response to a <lb/>given drug. <lb/>To undertake a chemogenic analysis of cancer networks for each <lb/>cancer type, we used protein products of the cancer driver genes to <lb/>seed a search for all interacting proteins in the canSAR interactome 33 , <lb/>which is based on information from eight databases, including the <lb/>IMeX consortium 65 , Phosphosite 66 and key publications. We annotated <lb/>proteins with pharmacological and druggability data using canSAR&apos;s <lb/>Cancer Protein Annotation Tool. Essential and selective genes including <lb/>lineage specificity were ascertained from the ShinyDepMap analysis <lb/>server (Supplementary Note 1) 32 . <lb/>Reporting summary <lb/>Further information on research design is available in the Nature <lb/>Portfolio Reporting Summary linked to this article. <lb/></div>

		<div type="availability">Data availability <lb/>Summary statistics for each tumor group are provided in the Supplemen-<lb/>tary Tables where such data do not enable identification of participants. <lb/>All sample-specific WGS data and processed files from the 100,000 <lb/>Genomes Project can be accessed by joining the Pan Cancer Genomics <lb/>England Clinical Interpretation Partnership (GeCIP) Domain once an <lb/>individual&apos;s data access has been approved (https://www.genomicseng-<lb/>land.co.uk/research/pan-cancer-and-molecular-oncology-communit <lb/>y). The link to becoming a member of the Genomics England research <lb/>network and obtaining access can be found at https://www.genomic-<lb/>sengland.co.uk/research/academic/join-gecip. The process involves <lb/>an online application, verification by the applicant&apos;s institution, com-<lb/>pletion of a short information governance training course and veri-<lb/>fication of approval by Genomics England. Please see https://www. <lb/>genomicsengland.co.uk/research/academic for more information. <lb/>The Genomics England data access agreement can be obtained from <lb/>figshare at https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4530893.v7 (ref. 67). All <lb/>analysis of Genomics England data must take place within the Genom-<lb/>ics England Research Environment (https://www.genomicsengland. <lb/>co.uk/understanding-genomics/data). The 100,000 Genomes Pro-<lb/>ject publication policies can be obtained from https://www.genom-<lb/>icsengland.co.uk/about-gecip/publications. Samples and results <lb/>used in this study are provided in Genomics England under /re_gecip/ <lb/>shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/results/. A MAF-like file detailing <lb/>coding mutations across all 100kGP tumors analysed is available at / <lb/>re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/results/. The COSMIC <lb/>and OncoKB clinical actionability data are available from https://cancer. <lb/>sanger.ac.uk/actionability and https://www.oncokb.org/actionable <lb/>Genes#sections=Tx, respectively. The canSAR chemogenomics data <lb/>are available from https://cansar.ai/. The NHS Genomic Test Directory <lb/>for Cancer is available from https://www.england.nhs.uk/publication/ <lb/>national-genomic-test-directories/. Lists of drivers from previous stud-<lb/>ies were obtained from COSMIC (https://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cmc/ <lb/>home), IntOGen (https://www.intogen.org/search) and the The Cancer <lb/>Genome Atlas (TCGA) Program pan-cancer analysis reported by ref. 13. <lb/>Somatic mutations were annotated to the cached version of GRCh38 <lb/>in VEP v.101. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">Code availability <lb/>Details and code for using the IntOGen framework are available at <lb/>https://intogen.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html. The specific <lb/>code to perform this analysis is available in the Genomics England <lb/>research environment (https://re-docs.genomicsengland.co.uk/ <lb/>access/) under /re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/code/. <lb/>The link to becoming a member of the Genomics England research <lb/>network and obtaining access can be found at https://www.genomic-<lb/>sengland.co.uk/research/academic/join-gecip. The code to perform <lb/>the canSAR chemogenomics analysis is available through Zenodo <lb/>(https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8329054) (ref. 68). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>61. Davies, H. et al. HRDetect is a predictor of BRCA1 and BRCA2 <lb/>deficiency based on mutational signatures. Nat. Med. 23, 517-525 <lb/>(2017). <lb/>62. Salipante, S. J., Scroggins, S. M., Hampel, H. L., Turner, E. H. <lb/>&amp; Pritchard, C. C. Microsatellite instability detection by next <lb/>generation sequencing. Clin. Chem. 60, 1192-1199 (2014). <lb/>63. Nguyen, B. et al. Genomic characterization of metastatic patterns <lb/>from prospective clinical sequencing of 25,000 patients. Cell 185, <lb/>563-575 (2022). <lb/>64. Tate, J. G. et al. COSMIC: the catalogue of somatic mutations in <lb/>cancer. Nucleic Acids Res. 47, D941-D947 (2019). <lb/>65. Orchard, S. et al. The MIntAct project-IntAct as a common <lb/>curation platform for 11 molecular interaction databases. Nucleic <lb/>Acids Res. 42, D358-D363 (2014). <lb/>66. Hornbeck, P. V. et al. PhosphoSitePlus, 2014: mutations, PTMs and <lb/>recalibrations. Nucleic Acids Res. 43, D512-D520 (2015). <lb/>67. Caulfield, M. et al. National Genomic Research Library [Dataset]. <lb/>figshare https://doi.org/10.6084/m9.figshare.4530893.v7 (2017). <lb/>68. Lärkeryd, A. instituteofcancerresearch/cansar-ddn: v0.1.0 (v0.1.0). <lb/>Zenodo https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.8329054 (2023). <lb/>69. Shannon, P. et al. Cytoscape: a software environment for <lb/>integrated models of biomolecular interaction networks. Genome <lb/>Res. 13, 2498-2504 (2003). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Funding was provided by the Wellcome Trust (214388), Cancer <lb/>Research UK (C1298/A8362) and the Medical Research Council. <lb/>A.S. is in receipt of a National Institute for Health Research (NIHR) <lb/>Academic Clinical Lectureship, funding from the Royal Marsden <lb/>Biomedical Research Centre, a starter grant for clinical lecturers from <lb/>the Academy of Medical Sciences and a Wellcome Trust Early Career <lb/>Award (227000/Z/23/Z). This is a summary of independent research <lb/>supported by the NIHR Biomedical Research Centre at the Royal <lb/>Marsden NHS Foundation Trust and the Institute of Cancer Research. <lb/>This research was made possible through access to the data and <lb/>findings generated by the 100,000 Genomes Project. The 100,000 <lb/>Genomes Project is managed by Genomics England Limited (a wholly <lb/>owned company of the Department of Health and Social Care). The <lb/>100,000 Genomes Project is funded by the National Institute for Health <lb/>Research and NHS England. The Wellcome Trust, Cancer Research UK <lb/>and the Medical Research Council also funded research infrastructure. <lb/>The 100,000 Genomes Project uses data provided by patients and <lb/>collected by the NHS as part of their care and support. We thank <lb/>Genomics England for the communication regarding the sensitivity of <lb/>WGS for detection of well-established cancer driver mutations. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author contributions <lb/>B.K., A.S. and R.H. designed the study. B.K., A.S., A.J.C. and <lb/>D.C. performed sample curation. B.K., A.S., A.E., A.J.C., D.C., <lb/>R.C., A.J.G., A.L., C.M. and D.W. performed bioinformatic <lb/>and statistical analysis. B.K., A.S., A.E. and R.H. drafted the <lb/>manuscript; all authors reviewed, read and approved the final <lb/>manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare no competing interests. <lb/>Additional information <lb/>Extended data is available for this paper at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9. <lb/>Supplementary information The online version <lb/>contains supplementary material available at <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9. <lb/>Correspondence and requests for materials should be addressed to <lb/>Richard Houlston. <lb/>Peer review information Nature Genetics thanks Stephen J. Chanock <lb/>and Jo Lynne Rokita for their contribution to the peer review of this <lb/>work. Peer reviewer reports are available. <lb/>Reprints and permissions information is available at <lb/>www.nature.com/reprints. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1500 <lb/>2000 <lb/>Bladder <lb/>Breast <lb/>Colorectum <lb/>Kidney <lb/>Lung <lb/>Melanoma <lb/>Oesophagus <lb/>Ovary <lb/>Pancreas <lb/>Prostate <lb/>Testis <lb/>Uterus <lb/>Site <lb/>Number <lb/>0 <lb/>10000 <lb/>20000 <lb/>30000 <lb/>40000 <lb/>50000 <lb/>Bladder <lb/>Breast <lb/>Colorectum <lb/>Kidney <lb/>Lung <lb/>Melanoma <lb/>Oesophagus <lb/>Ovary <lb/>Pancreas <lb/>Prostate <lb/>Testis <lb/>Uterus <lb/>Site <lb/>Number <lb/>Genomics England <lb/>NHS England <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 1 | Comparison of number of samples per tumour type in the pan-cancer cohort compared to all cancer diagnosed in England in 2019. Upper <lb/>panel: the 100kGP cohort; lower panel: incidence of the different cancer types reported in the general population. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">55 <lb/>61 <lb/>27 <lb/>241 <lb/>56 <lb/>51 <lb/>34 <lb/>305 <lb/>2001 <lb/>305 <lb/>2324 <lb/>117 <lb/>95 <lb/>111 <lb/>126 <lb/>60 <lb/>64 <lb/>34 <lb/>91 <lb/>52 <lb/>133 <lb/>157 <lb/>49 <lb/>61 <lb/>53 <lb/>201 <lb/>872 <lb/>68 <lb/>105 <lb/>24 <lb/>677 <lb/>25 <lb/>382 <lb/>26 <lb/>35 <lb/>10 <lb/>100 <lb/>1000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>100000 <lb/>1000000 <lb/>10000000 <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>SNV Mutation Count <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 2 | Mutation burden of tumours by each tumour type. The number of samples contributing to each tumour type are shown above the plot. <lb/>SNV, single nucleotide variant. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/>Article <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>Extended Data Fig. 3 | Circos heatmap of candidate cancer driver genes identified. Heatmap intensity proportional to the q value. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Recep_L_domain <lb/>Furin-like <lb/>GF_recep_IV <lb/>PK_Tyr_Ser-Thr <lb/>0 <lb/>150 <lb/>300 <lb/>450 <lb/>600 <lb/>750 <lb/>900 <lb/>1050 <lb/>1200 <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 0 9 A la <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 0 9 _ T h r7 <lb/>1 0 d e li n s A s p <lb/>p .G <lb/>ly <lb/>7 1 9 A la <lb/>p .G <lb/>ly <lb/>7 1 9 S e r <lb/>p .G <lb/>ly <lb/>7 1 9 C <lb/>y s <lb/>p .G <lb/>ly <lb/>7 1 9 A s p <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 4 6 _ T h r7 <lb/>5 1 d e li n s Il e <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 4 6 _ A la <lb/>7 5 0 d e l <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 4 6 _ A la <lb/>7 5 0 d e l <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>7 4 6 _ S e r7 <lb/>5 2 d e li n s V a l <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ S e r7 <lb/>5 2 d e l <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ P ro <lb/>7 5 3 d e li n s S e r <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ T h r7 <lb/>5 1 d e l <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ A la <lb/>7 5 0 d e l <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ T h r7 <lb/>5 1 d e li n s P ro <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 7 4 7 _ A la <lb/>7 5 0 d e li n s P ro <lb/>p .A <lb/>la <lb/>7 6 7 _ S e r7 <lb/>6 8 in <lb/>s C <lb/>y s V a l <lb/>p .A <lb/>la <lb/>7 6 7 _ V a l7 <lb/>6 9 d u p <lb/>p .S <lb/>e r7 <lb/>6 8 C <lb/>y s <lb/>p .S <lb/>e r7 <lb/>6 8 Il e <lb/>p .S <lb/>e r7 <lb/>6 8 _ A s p 7 7 0 d u p <lb/>p .P <lb/>ro <lb/>7 7 2 _ H <lb/>is <lb/>7 7 3 in <lb/>s T h rG <lb/>ln <lb/>P ro <lb/>A s n P ro <lb/>p .P <lb/>ro <lb/>7 7 2 _ H <lb/>is <lb/>7 7 3 in <lb/>s G <lb/>ly <lb/>H <lb/>is <lb/>P ro <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>7 7 3 d e li n s A s n P ro <lb/>A s n P ro <lb/>T y r <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>7 7 3 L e u <lb/>p .T <lb/>h r7 <lb/>9 0 M <lb/>e t <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 8 3 3 V a l <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 8 3 3 P h e <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>8 3 5 L e u <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 8 5 8 A rg <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 8 5 8 A rg <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 8 6 1 G <lb/>ln <lb/>Inframe deletion <lb/>Inframe insertion <lb/>Missense <lb/>Nonsynonymous <lb/>VUS <lb/>Mutation count <lb/>AA position <lb/>EGFR (ENST00000275493) <lb/>Recep_L_domain <lb/>Furin-like <lb/>GF_recep_IV <lb/>PK_Tyr_Ser-Thr <lb/>0 <lb/>150 <lb/>300 <lb/>450 <lb/>600 <lb/>750 <lb/>900 <lb/>1050 <lb/>1200 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/>p .L <lb/>e u 6 2 A rg <lb/>p .A <lb/>rg <lb/>1 0 8 T h r <lb/>p .A <lb/>rg <lb/>1 0 8 L y s <lb/>p .A <lb/>rg <lb/>2 2 2 C <lb/>y s <lb/>p .T <lb/>h r2 <lb/>6 3 P ro <lb/>p .A <lb/>la <lb/>2 8 9 V a l <lb/>p .A <lb/>la <lb/>2 8 9 T h r <lb/>p .A <lb/>la <lb/>2 8 9 A s p <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>3 0 4 T y r <lb/>p .T <lb/>h r3 <lb/>6 3 S e r <lb/>p .T <lb/>h r3 <lb/>6 3 Il e <lb/>p .P <lb/>ro <lb/>5 9 6 L e u <lb/>p .G <lb/>ly <lb/>5 9 8 V a l <lb/>p .S <lb/>e r6 <lb/>4 5 C <lb/>y s <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>7 7 3 d u p <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>9 3 1 G <lb/>ly <lb/>Missense <lb/>VUS <lb/>Inframe insertion <lb/>Mutation count <lb/>AA position <lb/>EGFR (ENST00000275493) <lb/>Lung adenocarcinoma <lb/>GBM, IDH wildtype <lb/>PI3K_rbd <lb/>PI3_PI4_kinase <lb/>PI3K_C2 <lb/>PI3K_p85B <lb/>PI3Ka <lb/>0 <lb/>125 <lb/>250 <lb/>375 <lb/>500 <lb/>625 <lb/>750 <lb/>875 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1068 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>p .A <lb/>rg <lb/>8 8 G <lb/>ln <lb/>p .A <lb/>rg <lb/>9 3 T r p <lb/>p .L <lb/>y s 1 1 1 G <lb/>lu <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>5 4 2 L y s <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>5 4 5 L y s <lb/>p .G <lb/>ln <lb/>5 4 6 A rg <lb/>p .T <lb/>h r1 <lb/>0 2 5 A la p .H <lb/>is <lb/>1 0 4 7 A rg <lb/>Missense <lb/>VUS <lb/>Inframe deletion <lb/>Frameshift <lb/>Inframe insertion <lb/>Mutation count <lb/>AA position <lb/>PIK3CA (ENST00000263967) <lb/>Uterine adenocarcinoma <lb/>PI3K_rbd <lb/>PI3_PI4_kinase <lb/>PI3K_C2 <lb/>PI3K_p85B <lb/>PI3Ka <lb/>0 <lb/>125 <lb/>250 <lb/>375 <lb/>500 <lb/>625 <lb/>750 <lb/>875 <lb/>1000 <lb/>1068 <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>p .A <lb/>s n 3 4 5 L y s <lb/>p .C <lb/>y s 4 2 0 A rg <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>5 4 2 L y s <lb/>p .G <lb/>lu <lb/>5 4 5 L y s <lb/>p .G <lb/>ln <lb/>5 4 6 A rg <lb/>p .H <lb/>is <lb/>1 0 4 7 A rg <lb/>Missense <lb/>VUS <lb/>Inframe deletion <lb/>Frameshift <lb/>Nonsynonymous <lb/>Mutation count <lb/>AA position <lb/>PIK3CA (ENST00000263967) <lb/>Breast ductal carcinoma <lb/>a <lb/>b <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 4 | Mutation plots and pfam domain overlap for: (a) <lb/>EGFR mutations in lung adenocarcinoma and GBM IDH wildtype; (b) PIK3CA <lb/>mutations in uterine adenocarcinoma and breast ductal carcinoma. Domain <lb/>specific mutations were assessed by considering the cancer drivers where <lb/>smRegions is a significant bidder (Q-value &lt; 0.1) and the driver is annotated in <lb/>multiple cancer types. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="footnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 5 | Hierarchical clustering of tumour types based on P-value of candidate driver genes across the 35 different tumour types. Clustering <lb/>performed using the hclust function in R. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>20 <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-SS <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Tumour type <lb/>Number <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 6 | Per-tumour distribution of oncogenic mutations in <lb/>tumour specific candidate cancer driver genes, across the 35 cancer types. <lb/>Analysis restricted to driver genes as predicted by IntOGen in the given cancer <lb/>type. Oncogenicity predicted using OncoKB. The line within the box shows the <lb/>median number of oncogenic mutations per sample in the cancer type. The box <lb/>represents the interquartile range and whiskers represent the range. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">TP53 <lb/>APC <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>KRAS <lb/>PTEN <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>KMT2C <lb/>VHL <lb/>ACVR2A <lb/>RNF43 <lb/>BRAF <lb/>PBRM1 <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>NF1 <lb/>ATM <lb/>MAP3K1 <lb/>TCF7L2 <lb/>TGFBR2 <lb/>RB1 <lb/>SETD2 <lb/>CDH1 <lb/>SOX9 <lb/>GATA3 <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>CDKN2A <lb/>FAT1 <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>SPEN <lb/>NRAS <lb/>CASP8 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>EP300 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>NOTCH1 <lb/>TET2 <lb/>STK11 <lb/>BCOR <lb/>SMARCA4 <lb/>ARID1B <lb/>FGFR3 <lb/>BAP1 <lb/>HLA-A <lb/>HLA-B <lb/>ERBB3 <lb/>SF3B1 <lb/>NFE2L2 <lb/>ELF3 <lb/>MTOR <lb/>BRCA1 <lb/>SMAD2 <lb/>CBFB <lb/>FGFR2 <lb/>KDM6A <lb/>PPP2R1A <lb/>AMER1 <lb/>KEAP1 <lb/>STAG2 <lb/>PDE4DIP <lb/>SMAD3 <lb/>ESR1 <lb/>MUC20 <lb/>XPO1 <lb/>KIT <lb/>FCGR3A <lb/>ACVR1 <lb/>XCL2 <lb/>ANKRD36 <lb/>CNTNAP3 <lb/>IGSF3 <lb/>PCBP1 <lb/>PNRC2 <lb/>SEC22B <lb/>SLC35G5 <lb/>CHD4 <lb/>PANCANCER (Oncogenic) <lb/>0 <lb/>1000 <lb/>2000 <lb/>3000 <lb/>Clonal (NA) <lb/>Clonal (early) <lb/>Clonal (late) <lb/>Subclonal <lb/>NA <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 7 | Oncogenic clonal and subclonal mutations across candidate driver genes across all tumor types. Oncogenic clonal and subclonal <lb/>mutations across candidate driver genes pan-cancer. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<body>a) <lb/>c) <lb/>b) <lb/>d) <lb/>TP53 <lb/>RB1 <lb/>KRAS <lb/>LRRC4C <lb/>AKAP9 <lb/>PKHD1L1 <lb/>ANK1 <lb/>BCL7A <lb/>CDH10 <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>PREX2 <lb/>Lung-LargeCell (Oncogenic) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>Clonal (NA) <lb/>Clonal (early) <lb/>Clonal (late) <lb/>Subclonal <lb/>NA <lb/>NF2 <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>KLF4 <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>SMARCB1 <lb/>SMO <lb/>USP17L22 <lb/>ATM <lb/>TRAF7 <lb/>ZSCAN5A <lb/>CNS-Menin (Oncogenic) <lb/>0 <lb/>5 <lb/>10 <lb/>15 <lb/>Clonal (NA) <lb/>Clonal (early) <lb/>Clonal (late) <lb/>Subclonal <lb/>NA <lb/>KIT <lb/>KRAS <lb/>MUC20 <lb/>NRAS <lb/>RAC1 <lb/>BIRC6 <lb/>KLF4 <lb/>EP300 <lb/>SPEN <lb/>Testis-GCT (Oncogenic) <lb/>0 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>Clonal (NA) <lb/>Clonal (early) <lb/>Clonal (late) <lb/>Subclonal <lb/>NA <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>CIC <lb/>FUBP1 <lb/>NIPBL <lb/>NOTCH1 <lb/>IDH2 <lb/>TCF12 <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>SMARCA4 <lb/>ZBTB20 <lb/>ATRX <lb/>BCOR <lb/>PBRM1 <lb/>CNS-Oligo (Oncogenic) <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>Clonal (NA) <lb/>Clonal (early) <lb/>Clonal (late) <lb/>Subclonal <lb/>NA <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 8 | Oncogenic clonal and subclonal mutations across candidate driver genes. Oncogenic clonal and subclonal mutations across candidate <lb/>driver genes in: a) Meningioma; b) Large cell lung cancer; c) Testicular germ cell tumour; d) Oligodendroglioma. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">RUNX1 <lb/>IFNG <lb/>PRKCD <lb/>ASXL1 <lb/>APC <lb/>HNF4A <lb/>PRKCI <lb/>HDAC6 <lb/>CDK1 <lb/>HLA-B <lb/>BTK <lb/>BCL2 <lb/>MT-ND4 <lb/>ERBB4 <lb/>PLG <lb/>ALK <lb/>BCL9 <lb/>SPTA1 <lb/>EP300 <lb/>KIT <lb/>AMER1 <lb/>PIK3CB <lb/>MC4R <lb/>TNRC6B <lb/>CDK2 <lb/>ESR1 <lb/>MAPK11 <lb/>THRB <lb/>PSMA3 <lb/>RPS27 <lb/>TOP2B <lb/>ARID1A <lb/>ERBB2 <lb/>MAPK14 <lb/>BCR <lb/>RPL13 <lb/>FRK <lb/>MAP3K21 <lb/>AKT1 <lb/>MTOR <lb/>SMG1 <lb/>TOP1 <lb/>NTRK1 <lb/>PTGIR <lb/>PPARD <lb/>CHEK1 <lb/>MAP3K1 <lb/>HDAC9 <lb/>TOP2A <lb/>INSR <lb/>GLP1R <lb/>ACVR2A <lb/>ATM <lb/>MMP1 <lb/>CYP17A1 <lb/>VDR <lb/>RET <lb/>SYK <lb/>PPARA <lb/>SRC <lb/>CTNNB1 <lb/>CYP11A1 <lb/>CDK4 <lb/>PDGFRA <lb/>MAP3K11 <lb/>ITK <lb/>CTNND1 <lb/>TCF7L2 <lb/>IL6 <lb/>RARG <lb/>KDR <lb/>GCGR <lb/>SMAD1 <lb/>PRKCA <lb/>RAF1 <lb/>RPLP0 <lb/>EEF2 <lb/>FLT3 <lb/>ZFP36L2 <lb/>OLIG2 <lb/>CSNK1A1 <lb/>NR3C1 <lb/>RARB <lb/>ADRB3 <lb/>TGFBR1 <lb/>ROCK1 <lb/>HDAC1 <lb/>CSNK1E <lb/>HLA-A <lb/>HDAC4 <lb/>MGAM <lb/>EPHA2 <lb/>MTNR1B <lb/>CHD4 <lb/>PRKCE <lb/>JAK2 <lb/>PRKD1 <lb/>NCF1 <lb/>WEE1 <lb/>HTR6 <lb/>PABPC1 <lb/>ABL1 <lb/>TYMS <lb/>ESR2 <lb/>IL1R1 <lb/>AVPR2 <lb/>IDH1 <lb/>PCBP1 <lb/>EGFR <lb/>FYN <lb/>LCK <lb/>PAK1 <lb/>AXL <lb/>PEX5 <lb/>EZH2 <lb/>TP53 <lb/>YES1 <lb/>PGR <lb/>VEGFA <lb/>ADORA1 <lb/>BLK <lb/>DDB1 <lb/>JUN <lb/>CYP19A1 <lb/>CSF1R <lb/>EPCAM <lb/>OXTR <lb/>SMARCA4 <lb/>DUSP16 <lb/>CREBBP <lb/>IKBKB <lb/>GNAS <lb/>TSHR <lb/>SSTR2 <lb/>TUBB <lb/>SMN1 <lb/>NRAS <lb/>XPO1 <lb/>ADRB2 <lb/>FLT1 <lb/>GNRHR <lb/>LYN <lb/>SMN2 <lb/>AR <lb/>HDAC3 <lb/>HSP90AA1 <lb/>ALOX12 <lb/>PDPK1 <lb/>RPL14 <lb/>FAM83B <lb/>MAP2K2 <lb/>ZBTB7A <lb/>IGF1R <lb/>MAP2K4 <lb/>PIK3CG <lb/>IL2 <lb/>RNF43 <lb/>MAP2K1 <lb/>PAK4 <lb/>ABCB1 <lb/>RXRA <lb/>ACVR1 <lb/>RPS20 <lb/>RRM2B <lb/>FNTA <lb/>PARP1 <lb/>MME <lb/>TGIF1 <lb/>PTK6 <lb/>UBE2N <lb/>BCL9L <lb/>FNTB <lb/>DNMT1 <lb/>MET <lb/>DRD1 <lb/>FGFR2 <lb/>RPS6 <lb/>MGA <lb/>PRKCQ <lb/>PPARG <lb/>SMAD2 <lb/>TBXA2R <lb/>FGFR3 <lb/>RPS26 <lb/>ARID1B <lb/>TGFB1 <lb/>GSK3B <lb/>HCK <lb/>FGFR1 <lb/>JAK3 <lb/>RPS27A <lb/>PSPC1 <lb/>BRAF <lb/>CDK9 <lb/>MMP7 <lb/>RPS3 <lb/>CDK6 <lb/>ADORA2A <lb/>HDAC2 <lb/>KRAS <lb/>SMAD3 <lb/>PLK1 <lb/>PDGFRB <lb/>PIK3CA <lb/>PRKCZ <lb/>PTGER4 <lb/>FBXW7 <lb/>PIK3CD <lb/>SMAD4 <lb/>CSNK2A1 <lb/>PTEN <lb/>RPS6KB1 <lb/>PARP2 <lb/>PTGER2 <lb/>SIN3A <lb/>ERBB3 <lb/>TNF <lb/>PRKDC <lb/>SOX9 <lb/>JAK1 <lb/>PTGS2 <lb/>TNNC1 <lb/>EPAS1 <lb/>PIK3R1 <lb/>RBM10 <lb/>CDK5 <lb/>RARA <lb/>CCND1 <lb/>ELF3 <lb/>TUBA1B <lb/>PNRC2 <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 9 | Example druggability network for colorectal cancer. <lb/>Nodes acting as cancer-specific drivers are shaded purple. Edge visual properties <lb/>are as follows: OncoKB interactions, red contiguous arrow; Signor interactions, <lb/>green contiguous arrow; Signor inhibitors, black vertical slash; complex, black <lb/>zigzag; direct interaction, red solid line; direct X-ray interaction, green solid <lb/>line; direct non-protein data bank interaction, blue solid line; reaction, blue <lb/>contiguous arrow; transcriptional interaction, black sinewave. Figure generated <lb/>using Cytoscape 69 . <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Nature Genetics <lb/></note>

		<note place="headnote">Article <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/s41588-024-01785-9 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Connective-SS <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHmut <lb/>Connective-Leiomyo <lb/>CNS-Oligo <lb/>CNS-Astro <lb/>Lung-SmallCell <lb/>Kidney-ChRCC <lb/>CNS-GBM-IDHwt <lb/>Bladder-TCC <lb/>CNS-Menin <lb/>Lung-LargeCell <lb/>Kidney-PRCC <lb/>Liver-HCC <lb/>Connective-Osteosarc <lb/>Uterus-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-Liposarc <lb/>Ovary-AdenoCA <lb/>Connective-SCS <lb/>Connective-Chondro <lb/>Connective-Myxofibro <lb/>Skin-Melanoma <lb/>Prost-AdenoCA <lb/>Kidney-CCRCC <lb/>Breast-DuctalCA <lb/>ColoRect-AdenoCA <lb/>Testis-GCT <lb/>Breast-LobularCA <lb/>Eso-AdenoCA <lb/>Mes-Mesothelioma <lb/>Stomach-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-SCC <lb/>HeadNeck-SCC <lb/>BileDuct-AdenoCA <lb/>Lung-AdenoCA <lb/>Panc-AdenoCA <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>0.50 <lb/>0.75 <lb/>1.00 <lb/>Tumour Purity <lb/>Tumour Group <lb/>Extended Data Fig. 10 | Violin plot of estimated tumour purity per cancer type. Black square within each violin corresponds to the median value. Violin trimmed to <lb/>the lowest and highest tumour purity estimate per cancer group. Purity estimates from Battenberg or Ccube. <lb/></div>

			<page>1 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">nature portfolio | reporting summary <lb/>April 2023 <lb/>Corresponding author(s): Richard Houlston <lb/>Last updated by author(s): Mar 30, 2024 <lb/>Reporting Summary <lb/>Nature Portfolio wishes to improve the reproducibility of the work that we publish. This form provides structure for consistency and transparency <lb/>in reporting. For further information on Nature Portfolio policies, see our Editorial Policies and the Editorial Policy Checklist. <lb/>Statistics <lb/>For all statistical analyses, confirm that the following items are present in the figure legend, table legend, main text, or Methods section. <lb/>n/a Confirmed <lb/>The exact sample size (n) for each experimental group/condition, given as a discrete number and unit of measurement <lb/>A statement on whether measurements were taken from distinct samples or whether the same sample was measured repeatedly <lb/>The statistical test(s) used AND whether they are one-or two-sided <lb/>Only common tests should be described solely by name; describe more complex techniques in the Methods section. <lb/>A description of all covariates tested <lb/>A description of any assumptions or corrections, such as tests of normality and adjustment for multiple comparisons <lb/>A full description of the statistical parameters including central tendency (e.g. means) or other basic estimates (e.g. regression coefficient) <lb/>AND variation (e.g. standard deviation) or associated estimates of uncertainty (e.g. confidence intervals) <lb/>For null hypothesis testing, the test statistic (e.g. F, t, r) with confidence intervals, effect sizes, degrees of freedom and P value noted <lb/>Give P values as exact values whenever suitable. <lb/>For Bayesian analysis, information on the choice of priors and Markov chain Monte Carlo settings <lb/>For hierarchical and complex designs, identification of the appropriate level for tests and full reporting of outcomes <lb/>Estimates of effect sizes (e.g. Cohen&apos;s d, Pearson&apos;s r), indicating how they were calculated <lb/>Our web collection on statistics for biologists contains articles on many of the points above. <lb/>Software and code <lb/>Policy information about availability of computer code <lb/>Data collection Samples were collected and processed by Genomics England. The code used for curation of samples is available inside the Genomics England <lb/>Research Environment under /re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_signatures/code/processClinicalData. <lb/>Data analysis <lb/>Details and code for using the Intogen framework are available here (https://intogen.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html). The specific code <lb/>to perform this analysis is available in the Genomics England research environment under /re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/ <lb/>code/. The link to becoming a member of the Genomics England research network and obtaining access can be found here https:// <lb/>www.genomicsengland.co.uk/research/academic/join-gecip. The code to perform the canSAR chemogenomics analysis is available through <lb/>Zenodo (https://zenodo.org/record/8329054). <lb/>Additional packages/softwware used: <lb/>VerifyBamID v1.1.3 = https://github.com/statgen/verifyBamID <lb/>Ccube v1 = https://github.com/keyuan/ccube <lb/>Isaac aligner v03.16.02.19 = https://github.com/Illumina/Isaac3 <lb/>Strelka v2.4.7 = https://github.com/Illumina/strelka <lb/>bcftools v1.9 = https://samtools.github.io/bcftools/bcftools.html <lb/>alleleCount-FixVAF v4.1.0 = https://github.com/danchubb/alleleCount-FixVAF <lb/>VEP v101 = https://github.com/Ensembl/ensembl-vep <lb/>CADD v1.6 = https://github.com/kircherlab/CADD-scripts/ <lb/>OncoKb v3.11 = https://www.oncokb.org/api-access <lb/>trackViewer v1.38.2 = https://github.com/jianhong/trackViewer <lb/>mSINGS = https://bitbucket.org/uwlabmed/msings/src/master/ <lb/>HRDetect = https://github.com/eyzhao/hrdetect-pipeline <lb/></div>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">nature portfolio | reporting summary <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">April 2023 <lb/>Battenberg v2.2.8 =https://github.com/Wedge-lab/battenberg <lb/>Delly v0.7.9= https://github.com/dellytools/delly <lb/>Lumpy v0.2.13 = https://github.com/arq5x/lumpy-sv/releases <lb/>Manta v1.5.0 = https://github.com/Illumina/manta <lb/>GATK v.4.4.0 = https://github.com/broadinstitute/gatk <lb/>BEDOPS v2.4.2 = https://github.com/bedops/bedops <lb/>bedtools v2.3.0 = https://bedtools.readthedocs.io/en/latest/index.html <lb/>MutationTimeR v0.99.2 = https://github.com/gerstung-lab/MutationTimeR <lb/>For manuscripts utilizing custom algorithms or software that are central to the research but not yet described in published literature, software must be made available to editors and <lb/>reviewers. We strongly encourage code deposition in a community repository (e.g. GitHub). See the Nature Portfolio guidelines for submitting code &amp; software for further information. <lb/>Data <lb/>Policy information about availability of data <lb/>All manuscripts must include a data availability statement. This statement should provide the following information, where applicable: <lb/>-Accession codes, unique identifiers, or web links for publicly available datasets <lb/>-A description of any restrictions on data availability <lb/>-For clinical datasets or third party data, please ensure that the statement adheres to our policy <lb/>Summary statistics for each tumour group are provided in the supplementary tables where such data does not enable identification of participants. All sample-<lb/>specific WGS data and processed files from the 100,000 Genomes Project can be accessed by joining the Pan Cancer Genomics England Clinical Interpretation <lb/>Partnership (GeCIP) Domain once an individual&apos;s data access has been approved (https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/research/pan-cancer). The link to becoming <lb/>a member of the genomics england research network and having access can be found here https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/research/academic/join-gecip. The <lb/>process involves an online application, verification by the applicant&apos;s institution, completion of a short information governance training course, and verification of <lb/>approval by Genomics England. Please see https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/research/academic for more information. The Genomics England data access <lb/>agreement can be obtained from https://figshare.com/articles/dataset/GenomicEnglandProtocol_pdf/4530893/7. All analysis of Genomics England data must take <lb/>place within the Genomics England Research Environment (https://www.genomicsengland.co.uk/understanding-genomics/data). The 100,000 Genomes Project <lb/>publication policies can be obtained from https://www. genomicsengland.co.uk/about-gecip/publications. Samples and used in this study are provided in <lb/>Genomics England under /re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/results/. A MAF-like file detailing coding mutations across all 100kGP tumours analysed is <lb/>available at /re_gecip/shared_allGeCIPs/pancancer_drivers/results/. The COSMIC and OncoKB clinical actionability data are available from https:// <lb/>cancer.sanger.ac.uk/actionability and https://www.oncokb.org/actionableGenes#sections=Tx, respectively. The canSAR chemogenomics data are available from <lb/>https://cansar.ai/. The NHS Genomic Test Directory for Cancer is available from https://www.england.nhs.uk/publication/national-genomic-test-directories/. List of <lb/>drivers from prior studies obtained from COSMIC (https://cancer.sanger.ac.uk/cmc/home), Intogen (https://www.intogen.org/search) and and the The Cancer <lb/>Genome Atlas (TCGA) Program pan-cancer analysis reported by Bailey et al. Somatic mutations were annotated to the cached version of GRCh38 in VEP v101. <lb/>Research involving human participants, their data, or biological material <lb/>Policy information about studies with human participants or human data. See also policy information about sex, gender (identity/presentation), <lb/>and sexual orientation and race, ethnicity and racism. <lb/>Reporting on sex and gender <lb/>Sex was used as reported by NHSD, PHE/NCRAS and the GMCs where this matched the inferred sex from genomic <lb/>sequencing. Where they do not match the sample was excluded. <lb/>Reporting on race, ethnicity, or <lb/>other socially relevant <lb/>groupings <lb/>Reported race, ethnicity, or other socially relevant groupings were not used in this study. <lb/>Population characteristics <lb/>Information relating to the cohort in this analysis are provided in supplementary table 3. The collection and processing of <lb/>treatment information is described in detail in the methods. <lb/>Recruitment <lb/>Clinical and demographic data were obtained from NHS Digital (NHSD), Public Health England&apos;s National Cancer Registration <lb/>and Analysis Service (PHE-NCRAS) and the Genomic Medicine Centres (GMCs) through the Genomics England Research <lb/>Environment. <lb/>Ethics oversight <lb/>The 100,000 Genomes Project protocol was approved by the East of England and South Cambridge Research Ethics <lb/>Committee on 20 February 2015, REC reference 14/EE/1112 <lb/>Note that full information on the approval of the study protocol must also be provided in the manuscript. <lb/>Field-specific reporting <lb/>Please select the one below that is the best fit for your research. If you are not sure, read the appropriate sections before making your selection. <lb/>Life sciences <lb/>Behavioural &amp; social sciences <lb/>Ecological, evolutionary &amp; environmental sciences <lb/>For a reference copy of the document with all sections, see nature.com/documents/nr-reporting-summary-flat.pdf <lb/></div>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">nature portfolio | reporting summary <lb/>April 2023 <lb/>Life sciences study design <lb/>All studies must disclose on these points even when the disclosure is negative. <lb/>Sample size <lb/>10,478 samples were included in the full cohort. Exact sample sizes for tumour groups are provided in supplementary table 2. Sample size was <lb/>chosen based on the availability of whole genome sequencing of tumour/normal pairs in the Genomics England research environment. <lb/>Data exclusions A detailed description of the sample quality control is provided in the methods. Supplementary table 1 provides information on how many <lb/>samples were excluded. Sequenced tumour samples were excluded if clinical data were missing or if unresolvable conflicts existed between <lb/>the clinical data sources (GMCs, NHSD, PHE-NCRAS, histology reports). In total 2,251/14,129 (15.9%) of tumour samples were excluded based <lb/>on availability and consistency of reported sex, tumour histology, tumour type, sampling date or if the participant was recorded as less than <lb/>18 years old at the time of sampling. 267/11878 (2.2%) of tumour samples with required clinical data available were excluded based on <lb/>tumour sample purity and sequencing data quality. Duplicate tumour samples were also removed, to ensure that no individual was <lb/>represented more than once in a tumour group. If multiple sequenced tumour samples from the same tumour group were available for an <lb/>individual, we preferentially kept primary tumour samples with highest purity. Non-solid tumours were removed from this analysis. Based on <lb/>these criteria, 10,478 tumour samples were suitable for analysis. <lb/>Replication <lb/>This study has an observational rather than an experimental study design, and only one sample was sequenced from each participant, in the <lb/>great majority of cases. We replicate many of the findings from previously published studies of somatic cancer driver genes. <lb/>Randomization This study has an observational rather than an experimental study design hence randomisation of study participants is not relevant. <lb/>Blinding <lb/>This study used real-world observation data collected from NHS trusts. The investigators did not have control over sample selection, collection <lb/>and processing and as such blinding is not relevant to this study. <lb/>Reporting for specific materials, systems and methods <lb/>We require information from authors about some types of materials, experimental systems and methods used in many studies. Here, indicate whether each material, <lb/>system or method listed is relevant to your study. If you are not sure if a list item applies to your research, read the appropriate section before selecting a response. <lb/>Materials &amp; experimental systems <lb/>n/a Involved in the study <lb/>Antibodies <lb/>Eukaryotic cell lines <lb/>Palaeontology and archaeology <lb/>Animals and other organisms <lb/>Clinical data <lb/>Dual use research of concern <lb/>Plants <lb/>Methods <lb/>n/a Involved in the study <lb/>ChIP-seq <lb/>Flow cytometry <lb/>MRI-based neuroimaging <lb/>Novel plant genotypes <lb/>Describe the methods by which all novel plant genotypes were produced. This includes those generated by transgenic approaches, <lb/>gene editing, chemical/radiation-based mutagenesis and hybridization. For transgenic lines, describe the transformation method, the <lb/>number of independent lines analyzed and the generation upon which experiments were performed. For gene-edited lines, describe <lb/>the editor used, the endogenous sequence targeted for editing, the targeting guide RNA sequence (if applicable) and how the editor <lb/>was applied. <lb/>Seed stocks <lb/>Report on the source of all seed stocks or other plant material used. If applicable, state the seed stock centre and catalogue number. If <lb/>plant specimens were collected from the field, describe the collection location, date and sampling procedures. <lb/>Authentication <lb/>Describe any authentication procedures for each seed stock used or novel genotype generated. Describe any experiments used to <lb/>assess the effect of a mutation and, where applicable, how potential secondary effects (e.g. second site T-DNA insertions, mosiacism, <lb/>off-target gene editing) were examined. <lb/>Plants </div>


	</text>
</tei>
