<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_SAM-P6"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Geometrical Specification Model for Gear -<lb/>Expression, Metrology and Analysis <lb/> J.Y. Dantan <lb/> 1 , J. Bruyere <lb/> 1 , C. Baudouin <lb/> 1 , L. Mathieu <lb/> 2 (1), <lb/> 1 Laboratoire de Génie Industriel et Production Mécanique -<lb/>Ecole Nationale Supérieure d&apos;Arts et Métiers, Metz, France <lb/> 2 Laboratoire Universitaire de Recherche en Production Automatisée <lb/>Ecole Normale Supérieure, Cachan, France <lb/> Abstract <lb/> To ensure the gear precision, industries need a coherent model to express, to analyse and to check <lb/>geometrical specifications. Most gear tolerance representations are directly driven by the convenience of <lb/>dimensional metrology and not by the convenience of the set of activities of the tolerancing process. <lb/>Therefore, to ensure the coherence of all tolerancing process activities, there is a necessity to develop a <lb/>complete gear tolerance model which should: represent standard tolerance practices; be integrated in the <lb/>Computer-Aided systems of design, manufacturing and metrology; be controlled by CMM; and support <lb/>automated tolerance analysis. The proposed model extends capabilities of a vectorial dimensioning &amp; <lb/>tolerancing model in order to satisfy the four requirements. This model is based on GeoSpelling [1]. Its <lb/>coherence is illustrated by two applications: gear tolerance analysis and gear tolerance verification by CMM. <lb/> Keywords: <lb/> Tolerancing Model, Functional Metrology, Gear <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 INTRODUCTION <lb/> As technology increases and performance requirements <lb/>continually tighten, the cost and required precision of <lb/>assemblies increase as well. There is a strong need for <lb/>increased attention to tolerance design to enable high-<lb/>precision assemblies to be manufactured at lower costs. <lb/>Indeed, tolerance analysis is a key element in industry for <lb/>improving product quality. <lb/>Designers want tight tolerances to assure product <lb/>performance; manufacturers prefer loose tolerances to <lb/>reduce cost. There is a critical need for a quantitative <lb/>design tool for specifying tolerances. Tolerance analysis <lb/>brings the engineering design requirements and <lb/>manufacturing capabilities together in a common model, <lb/>where the effects of tolerance specifications on both <lb/>design and manufacturing requirements can be <lb/>evaluated quantitatively. <lb/>The inherent imperfections of manufacturing processes <lb/>(forging, cutting or grinding) involve geometrical <lb/>variations and a degradation of product quality. The <lb/>geometrical variations of each part must be limited by <lb/>geometrical specifications (tolerances) to ensure a <lb/>certain level of product quality, which is defined by the <lb/>functional requirements. <lb/>In the case of gears, their geometrical variations impact <lb/>the transmission error, the tooth contact position, <lb/>meshing interference, and gap. To ensure a quality level, <lb/>designers limit these parameters by requirements. <lb/>Tolerancing decisions can profoundly impact the quality <lb/>and cost of gears. To assess the impact of tolerance on <lb/>gear quality, designers need to simulate the influences of <lb/>tolerance with respect to the functional requirements. To <lb/>do so, they use AGMA [2] or ISO tables. These tables are <lb/>a set of discrete associations between tolerances and <lb/>meshing quality. They do not take into account all <lb/>tolerances, and they focus on the pitch error and the <lb/>misalignment. In the case of a forged gear or not <lb/>classical gear like WILDHABER-NOVIKOV, designers <lb/>can not use them to allocate the gear tolerances to <lb/>achieve the optimal manufacturing cost. This first <lb/>approach, however, is not very flexible. A second <lb/>approach is based on experimentations. In order to <lb/>determine the effects of a tolerance and to understand <lb/>the contributions of tolerances on a functional <lb/>requirement, it is necessary to identify the relationships <lb/>between gear tolerances and functional requirements by <lb/>a set of experimentations. Effective reuse of experimental <lb/>knowledge about the effect between gear tolerances and <lb/>functional requirements is a key strategic component of <lb/>the gear tolerancing process. This second approach is <lb/>expensive. There is an important question that requires <lb/>need to be looked upon: How to determine gear <lb/>tolerances? <lb/>A significant amount of literature is related to tolerance <lb/>design. It distinguishes four aspects: tolerance <lb/>representation, tolerance specification, tolerance <lb/>analysis, and tolerance synthesis [3] (Figure 1). But, <lb/>few of this research apply to gear. <lb/> Tolerance <lb/>representation <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>specification <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>analysis <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>synthesis <lb/>need a <lb/>need a <lb/>need a <lb/> Figure 1: Four aspects and their dependences. <lb/>These four aspects are not at the same level, the first <lb/>one refers to how tolerances are represented internally <lb/>by the computer, this aspect is indicated directly on the <lb/>models used for the description of the mechanism <lb/>without and with geometric variations. Tolerance <lb/>specification is an important activity for tolerancing. It <lb/>tries to answer the question: Which tolerance types and <lb/> </body>
			
			<front>Annals of the CIRP Vol. 56/1/2007 <lb/></front> 
			
			<body>values are needed on features to control functional <lb/>requirements? Tolerance analysis is a method to verify <lb/>the value of functional requirements after tolerances have <lb/>been specified on each isolated part. This method is <lb/>totally dependent on the models chosen before. <lb/>Tolerance synthesis is regarded as a tolerance allocation <lb/>and a tolerance optimization method taking into account <lb/>manufacturing and inspection aspects. <lb/>The tolerancing process is defined through all the <lb/>activities involved by geometric product variations <lb/>management. We can propose four classical activities: <lb/>tolerance specification, tolerance analysis, tolerance <lb/>synthesis, and tolerance verification. Tolerance <lb/>specification, tolerance analysis and tolerance synthesis <lb/>are sub activities of tolerance design. Tolerance <lb/>verification defines inspection planning and metrological <lb/>procedures for functional requirements, functional <lb/>specifications and manufacturing specifications. It is very <lb/>important to consider tolerance verification early in the <lb/>design activities to be able to assess uncertainties. <lb/>Tolerance verification permits to close the process loop, <lb/>to check the product conformity and to verify <lb/>assumptions made by the designer. The tolerancing <lb/>process depends totally on the models used. The <lb/>representation of deviations and tolerances, on parts or <lb/>assembly, is the key problem of tolerancing [1] (Figure 2). <lb/> Tolerance representation / coherent model <lb/> Tolerance <lb/>specification <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>analysis <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>synthesis <lb/>Tolerance <lb/>verification <lb/> Figure 2: Tolerancing process. <lb/>To be coherent, the tolerancing process has to use the <lb/>same language based on a unified mathematical model <lb/>to express tolerancing for each person involved during <lb/>the process. To ensure this coherence between gear <lb/>tolerance design and gear tolerance verification, there is <lb/>a necessity of developing a complete gear tolerance <lb/>model which should: (i) represent standard tolerance <lb/>practices; (ii) be integrated in the Computer-Aided <lb/>systems of design, manufacturing and metrology, (iii) be <lb/>controlled by CMM and (iiii) support automated tolerance <lb/>analysis. <lb/>Indeed, most gear tolerance representation schemes are <lb/>not directly driven by functional requirements, but by the <lb/>dimensional metrology pratice. In fact, an amount of <lb/>research has been devoted to the development of Gear <lb/>Metrology [4]. <lb/>The paper focuses on the gear tolerance model and its <lb/>utilization during the tolerancing process. The proposed <lb/>model extends capabilities of a vectorial dimensioning &amp; <lb/>tolerancing model in order to satisfy the four <lb/>requirements. It is based on GeoSpelling [1] -the model <lb/>proposed for rebuilding standards [5] in the fields of <lb/>tolerancing and metrology -GeoSpelling allows to <lb/>express the specification from the function to the <lb/>verification with a common language. This model is <lb/>based on geometrical operations which are applied not <lb/>only to ideal features, but also to the non-ideal features <lb/>which represent a real part. These operations are <lb/>themselves defined by constraints on the form and <lb/>relative characteristics of the features. <lb/>The use of the gear tolerance model for gear tolerance <lb/>analysis and for gear tolerance verification by CMM <lb/>illustrates its coherence. <lb/> 2 EXPRESSION OF GEOMETRICAL GEAR <lb/>SPECIFICATION WITH GEOSPELLING <lb/> Obviously, the vast spectrum of gear tolerancing cannot <lb/>be covered within this paper. Therefore, the following <lb/>sections will be mainly restricted to the bevel gear and <lb/>focuses on three types of gear variations which are <lb/>limited by some tolerances: the flank deviations, the <lb/>deviations between flanks and the deviations between <lb/>teeth and hole. <lb/>To express these tolerances, we use the classical <lb/>standardized language and GeoSpelling which is based <lb/>on the following basic concept: <lb/> • <lb/> a specification is a condition on a characteristic <lb/>defined from geometric features [1], [5], <lb/> • <lb/> these geometric features are features created from <lb/>the model of the real surface of the part (SKIN <lb/>model) by different operations. <lb/>A condition defines an interval of IR inside of which the <lb/>value of a characteristic of geometric features must lie <lb/>[1], [5]. <lb/> 2.1 &quot; Profile or form tolerances &quot; <lb/> In the case of the GD&amp;T standards, the profile deviations <lb/>are the deviations normal to the transverse involute <lb/>profiles, measured within the profile evaluation range L : <lb/>F, ff, fH, [4] … These profile characteristics can easily <lb/>be measured but they are not adapted for tolerance <lb/>analysis [6]. Therefore, we propose a set of flank form <lb/>specifications like flank topography [4], [1] (Figure 3). <lb/>Like F, ff, fH, …, we can distinguish different datum <lb/>systems that define the position and the orientation of the <lb/>tolerance zone. <lb/> A <lb/>C <lb/> A <lb/>A <lb/>AA <lb/> B <lb/> t1 <lb/>t2 <lb/>t3 <lb/> A <lb/>A <lb/> t4 C <lb/>B <lb/> Figure 3: Flank form tolerances. <lb/>These specifications of the flank form are defined by a <lb/>tolerance zone in which this flank must be included. The <lb/>tolerance zone can be generated according to various <lb/>methods [7]. The translation of the specification 1 and 2 <lb/>(Figure 3) in GeoSpelling language is given in Table 1 <lb/>and Table 2. Let us suppose, Sa and Sf (Figure 4) <lb/>defined by partition operations [5]. Sa is the non ideal <lb/>feature [8] which is nominally the cylinder A and Sf the <lb/>non ideal feature which is nominally a spherical involute, <lb/>the range of this non ideal feature can be L. <lb/>With these four specifications, we can explicitly define <lb/>the datum system which allows to fit the ideal flank and <lb/>which locates the tolerance zone. These expressions <lb/>make easier the tolerance analysis and the tolerance <lb/>verification. In the case of the conventional profile <lb/>evaluation, the result requires some rules to interpret <lb/>deviations correctly. <lb/> 
			
			Sf <lb/> F 1 <lb/> F 2 <lb/> C 1 <lb/> C 2 <lb/> Sa <lb/>CY a <lb/> Figure 4: Features and characteristics. <lb/> Definition of the associated spherical involute F 1 <lb/> Association F 1 , ideal feature, type spherical involute <lb/>Objective to minimize : maximum distance (Sf, F 1 ) <lb/> Evaluation C 1 : maximum distance (Sf, F 1 ) <lb/>Definition of the toleranced characteristic C 1 <lb/> Definition of the condition <lb/>C 1   t 1 / 2 <lb/> Table 1: GeoSpelling expression of specification 1. <lb/> Definition of the associated spherical involute F 2 <lb/> Association F 2 , ideal feature, type spherical involute <lb/>Constraints: coaxiality between CYa and axis of F 2 <lb/> Objective to minimize : maximum distance (Sf, F 2 ) <lb/> Evaluation C 2 : maximum distance (Sf, F 2 ) <lb/>Definition of the toleranced characteristic C 2 <lb/> Definition of the condition <lb/>C 2   t 2 / 2 <lb/>Definition of the datum A <lb/> Association CYa, ideal feature, type Cylinder <lb/>Constraints: minimum signed distance (Sa, CYa)  0 <lb/>Objective to maximize : diameter of CYa <lb/> Table 2: GeoSpelling expression of specification 2. <lb/> 2.2 &quot; Pitch tolerances &quot; and &quot; Runout tolerances &quot; <lb/> In the same way, we can express some specifications <lb/>which limit the cumulative angular pitch deviation <lb/>(orientation deviations between flanks) and the runout <lb/>(situation deviations between teeth and hole). <lb/>In the case of the standard [2], the cumulative pitch <lb/>deviation Fpk over a sector of k pitches is the algebraic <lb/>difference between the actual length and the theoretical <lb/>length of the relevant arc. Bevel gears are being tested <lb/>close to the mean pitch cone diameter dM [4], but the <lb/>datum in which dM is defined is not clarified. <lb/>Therefore, we propose to limit the cumulative angular <lb/>pitch deviation which is the difference between the <lb/>nominal angle between two flanks and the angle [8] <lb/>around a datum axis between two associated flanks. The <lb/>two associated flanks are defined by association <lb/>operations [1] with constraints: coaxiality between the <lb/>datum axis and the axis of the involute cone. The datum <lb/>axis can be the axis of the associated hole or the <lb/>associated teeth cone (Figure 5). <lb/>In the case of the standard, the runout of teeth [4], Fr, is <lb/>the total variation of the distance between a datum <lb/>surface(s) (hole) and an indicated surface(s) (teeth). <lb/>Typical runout types are axial and radial. Runout of a <lb/>bevel gear is caused by the superposition of different <lb/>deviations. Therefore, the runout tolerance analysis is <lb/>complex. <lb/> Associated <lb/>teeth cone <lb/>Associated <lb/>hole <lb/>Associated <lb/>flank <lb/>Associated <lb/>flank <lb/>Angle around <lb/>associated hole axis <lb/>Angle around <lb/>associated <lb/>teeth cone axis <lb/> Figure 5: Pitch deviations. <lb/>We propose to dissociate the cause of the runout and to <lb/>limit the situation deviations [5] between the associated <lb/>hole and the associated teeth cone (Figure 6). <lb/> Situation <lb/>deviation <lb/>Associated <lb/>teeth cone <lb/>Associated <lb/>hole <lb/>SKIN <lb/>model <lb/> Figure 6: Runout deviation. <lb/>For the functional tolerancing, we advocate to consider <lb/>the form tolerance (specification 1 – Figure 3), the form <lb/>position tolerances with the hole datum system <lb/>(specifications 2 and 3 – Figure 3) and the pitch <lb/>tolerance around the hole datum axis; because the gear <lb/>revolves around of the hole axis. <lb/>For the manufacturing tolerancing, we advocate to <lb/>consideration the form tolerance (specification 1 – Figure <lb/>3), the form position tolerance with the teeth datum <lb/>system (specification 4 – Figure 3), the pitch tolerance <lb/>around the teeth datum axis and the runout deviation; <lb/>because we can dissociate the cumulative pitch angular <lb/>error around the teeth cone axis and the deviations <lb/>between the teeth cone axis and the hole axis. This <lb/>dissociation is interesting for the simulation of the impact <lb/>of forging and machining variations, because the <lb/>cumulative pitch angular errors around the teeth cone <lb/>axis are due to the forging operation and the deviation <lb/>between the teeth cone axis and the hole axis are due to <lb/>the machining operation. <lb/> 3 A COHERENT TOLERANCING PROCESS <lb/> To illustrate the coherence of this proposed geometrical <lb/>specification model, two examples are shown: Tolerance <lb/>analysis and tolerance verification by CMM. <lb/> 3.1 Gear Tolerance analysis <lb/> This example is based on: <lb/> • <lb/> an analytical definition (parametric model) of tooth <lb/>surface in a global coordinate system which includes <lb/>form deviations, location and orientation deviations <lb/>between features and gaps, <lb/>  
			
			• <lb/> a mathematical representation of the geometrical <lb/>specifications which are detailed in section 2, <lb/> • <lb/> a digital simulation tool based on Tooth Contact <lb/>Analysis [9] which enables one to evaluate functional <lb/>characteristics as kinematic error, position of contact <lb/>point, , … (the result is similar to the tangential <lb/>composite test [6], but the cost of a digital simulation <lb/>is lower than the cost of an experimental simulation), <lb/> • <lb/> a tolerance analysis tool by Monte Carlo simulation, <lb/>which computes the probability that the product can <lb/>be assembled and will function (respect of <lb/>requirements on the kinematic error, …) for given <lb/>individual tolerances. <lb/>The result of a statistical tolerance analysis [6] is a set of <lb/>meshing simulations (Figure 7), the probability <lb/>distribution of each functional characteristics like <lb/>kinematic error (Figure 8). <lb/> Kinematic error (radian) <lb/> Rotational angle –   1  (radian) <lb/> 5 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0,02 <lb/>-0,02 <lb/>-0,04 <lb/>-0,06 <lb/>-0,08 <lb/> Kinematic error (radian) <lb/> Rotational angle –   1  (radian) <lb/> 5 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 5 <lb/>0 <lb/>0,02 <lb/>-0,02 <lb/>-0,04 <lb/>-0,06 <lb/>-0,08 <lb/> Figure 7: Numerical meshing simulations <lb/> 2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 <lb/>12 <lb/> Number <lb/> Kinematic error (10 -3 radian) <lb/> 0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>120 <lb/>140 <lb/>160 <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>10 12 <lb/>0 <lb/> Figure 8: Tolerance analysis <lb/> 3.2 Gear Tolerance verification. <lb/> Tolerance verification permits one to check the product <lb/>conformity and to verify assumptions made by the <lb/>designer. To do so, we develop some metrological <lb/>procedures for adequacy with the GeoSpelling [5] <lb/>expression of each geometrical specification which is <lb/>detailed in section 2. <lb/>Section 2.2 explains the importance of the definition of a <lb/>datum axis to specify the cumulative angular pitch <lb/>deviation. To illustrate this, we evaluate the circular <lb/>thickness around two datum systems: the datum system <lb/>based on the teeth (Figure 5) and the datum system <lb/>based on the hole (Figure 5), we can determine the <lb/>difference of the values according to the datum systems <lb/>(Figure 9). In fact, we can dissociate the impact of the <lb/>cumulative pitch angular error around the teeth cone axis <lb/>and the situation deviations between the teeth cone axis <lb/>and the hole axis. <lb/> 9,48 <lb/>9,50 <lb/>9,52 <lb/>9,54 <lb/>9,56 <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>9 10 11 12 13 14 <lb/> Tooth number <lb/>Circular thickness (mm) <lb/> evaluation in the datum system based on teeth <lb/>evaluation in the datum system based <lb/>on plane and cylinder <lb/> Figure 9: Influence of the datum system on pitch <lb/>deviations. <lb/> 4 CONCLUSION <lb/> The important point of the proposed geometrical <lb/>specification model for a gear based on GeoSpelling is to <lb/>provide an unique solution to express tolerances based <lb/>on geometry. This way is based on the characteristic <lb/>concept. Taken into account directly, in the expression of <lb/>the specification, the result based on a mathematical <lb/>expression is unique and clearly described for everybody. <lb/>There is no more interpretation for the designer, the <lb/>manufacturer and the metrologist. <lb/>Indeed, tolerance analysis or tolerance verification are <lb/>based on tolerance representation. Given a particular <lb/>tolerance representation, efficient and accurate <lb/>algorithms are needed to actually perform the tolerance <lb/>analysis. Unfortunately, as the geometric tolerances are <lb/>complex, so too are the algorithms using these <lb/>tolerances. <lb/>For managing efficiently geometrical variations along the <lb/>product life cycle, we propose a geometrical specification <lb/>model for gears based on GeoSpelling which is the basis <lb/>of a complete and coherent tolerancing process. <lb/></body> 
			
			<listBibl>5 REFERENCES <lb/> [1] Mathieu L. and Ballu A, 2003, GeoSpelling: a <lb/>common language for Specification and Verification <lb/>to express Method Uncertainty, Proc. of 8th CIRP <lb/>Seminar on Computer Aided Tolerancing, North <lb/>Carolina, USA. <lb/>[2] ANSI/AGMA <lb/>2009-B01, <lb/>2005, <lb/>Bevel <lb/>Gear <lb/>Classification, Tolerances, and Measuring Methods. <lb/> [3] Salomons O., Van Houten F., Kals H., 1998, Current <lb/>Status of CAT Systems, Geometric Design <lb/>Tolerancing: Theories, Standards and Applications, <lb/>pp. 438-452, ISBN O-412-83000-0. <lb/>[4] Goch G., 2003, Gear Metrology, Annals of CIRP, <lb/>52/2:659-695. <lb/>[5] ISO/TS 17450-1, 2005, Geometric Product <lb/>Specification (GPS) – General concepts – Part 1: <lb/>Model for geometrical specification and verification. <lb/>[6] Bruyere J., Dantan J.Y., Bigot R., Martin P., 2006, <lb/>Statistical tolerance analysis of bevel gear by Tooth <lb/>Contact Analysis and Monte Carlo simulation, in <lb/>press, Mechanism and Machine Theory. <lb/>[7] Pasupathy T., Zhao X., Wilhelm R., 2006, Flexible <lb/>tools for specifying design variation, Int. J. Adv. <lb/>Manufacturing Technology, 28:659-664. <lb/>[8] Ballu A., Mathieu L., Dantan J.Y., 2001, Global view <lb/>of geometrical specifications, Proc. of 7th CIRP <lb/>Seminar on Computer Aided Tolerancing, Cachan, <lb/>France. <lb/>[9] Litvin F.L., 2004, Gear Geometry and Applied <lb/>Theory, PTR Prentice Hall, Englewood Cliffs, NJ. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
