<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<cover>RESEARCH ARTICLE SUMMARY <lb/>◥ <lb/>CORONAVIRUS <lb/>Inferring the effectiveness of government <lb/>interventions against COVID-19 <lb/>Jan M. Brauner* †, Sören Mindermann* †, Mrinank Sharma* †, David Johnston, John Salvatier, <lb/>Tomáš Gavenčiak, Anna B. Stephenson, Gavin Leech, George Altman, Vladimir Mikulik, <lb/>Alexander John Norman, Joshua Teperowski Monrad, Tamay Besiroglu, Hong Ge, <lb/>Meghan A. Hartwick, Yee Whye Teh, Leonid Chindelevitch ‡, Yarin Gal ‡, Jan Kulveit ‡ <lb/>INTRODUCTION: Governments across the world <lb/>have implemented a wide range of non-<lb/>pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) to miti-<lb/>gate the spread of severe acute respiratory <lb/>syndrome coronavirus 2 (SARS-CoV-2). Given <lb/>the increasing death toll of the pandemic and <lb/>the social cost of some interventions, it is <lb/>critical to understand their relative effective-<lb/>ness. By considering the effects that inter-<lb/>ventions had on transmission during the first <lb/>wave of the outbreak, governments can make <lb/>more-informed decisions about how to con-<lb/>trol the pandemic. <lb/>RATIONALE: Rigorously studying the effective-<lb/>ness of individual interventions poses consid-<lb/>erable methodological challenges. Simulation <lb/>studies can explore scenarios, but they make <lb/>strong assumptions that may be difficult to <lb/>validate. Data-driven, cross-country modeling <lb/>comparing the timing of national interven-<lb/>tions to the subsequent numbers of cases or <lb/>deaths is a promising alternative approach. <lb/>We have collected chronological data on the <lb/>implementation of several interventions in <lb/>41 countries between January and the end <lb/>of May 2020, using independent double entry <lb/>by researchers to ensure high data quality. <lb/>Because countries deployed different com-<lb/>binations of interventions in different orders <lb/>and with different outcomes, it is possible to <lb/>disentangle the effect of individual interven-<lb/>tions. We estimate the effectiveness of specific <lb/>interventions with a Bayesian hierarchical <lb/>model by linking intervention implementa-<lb/>tion dates to national case and death counts. <lb/>We partially pool NPI effectiveness to allow <lb/>for country-specific NPI effects. Our model also <lb/>accounts for uncertainty in key epidemiological <lb/>parameters, such as the average delay from <lb/>infection to death. However, intervention ef-<lb/>fectiveness estimates should only be used for <lb/>policy-making if they are robust across a range <lb/>of modeling choices. We therefore support the <lb/>results with extensive empirical validation, in-<lb/>cluding 11 sensitivity analyses under 206 ex-<lb/>perimental conditions. In these analyses, we <lb/>show how results change when we vary the <lb/>data, the epidemiological parameters, or the <lb/>model structure or when we account for <lb/>confounders. <lb/>RESULTS: While exact intervention effectiveness <lb/>estimates varied with modeling assumptions, <lb/>broader trends in the results were highly con-<lb/>sistent across experimental conditions. To de-<lb/>scribe these trends, we categorized intervention <lb/>effect sizes as small, moderate, or large, corre-<lb/>sponding to posterior median reductions in <lb/>the reproduction number R of &lt;17.5%, between <lb/>17.5 and 35%, and &gt;35%, respectively. Across <lb/>all experimental conditions, all interventions <lb/>could robustly be placed in one or two of these <lb/>categories. Closing both schools and universities <lb/>was consistently highly effective at reducing <lb/>transmission at the advent of the pandemic. <lb/>Banning gatherings was effective, with a large <lb/>effect size for limiting gatherings to 10 people <lb/>or less, a moderate-to-large effect for 100 people <lb/>or less, and a small-to-moderate effect for 1000 <lb/>people or less. Targeted closures of face-to-face <lb/>businesses with a high risk of infection, such as <lb/>restaurants, bars, and nightclubs, had a small-<lb/>to-moderate effect. Closing most nonessential <lb/>businesses delivering personal services was only <lb/>somewhat more effective (moderate effect). <lb/>When these interventions were already in <lb/>place, issuing a stay-at-home order had only <lb/>a small additional effect. These results indicate <lb/>that, by using effective interventions, some <lb/>countries could control the epidemic while <lb/>avoiding stay-at-home orders. <lb/>CONCLUSION: We estimated the effects of non-<lb/>pharmaceutical interventions on COVID-19 <lb/>transmission in 41 countries during the first <lb/>wave of the pandemic. Some interventions <lb/>were robustly more effective than others. This <lb/>work may provide insights into which areas of <lb/>public life require additional interventions to <lb/>be able to maintain activity despite the pan-<lb/>demic. However, because of the limitations <lb/>inherent in observational study designs, our <lb/>estimates should not be seen as final but <lb/>rather as a contribution to a diverse body of <lb/>evidence, alongside other retrospective studies, <lb/>simulation studies, and experimental trials. ▪ <lb/>RESEARCH <lb/>Brauner et al., Science 371, 802 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/>1 of 1 <lb/>The list of author affiliations is available in the full article online. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Email: jan.brauner@cs.ox.ac.uk <lb/>(J.M.B.); soren.mindermann@cs.ox.ac.uk (S.M.); mrinank@ <lb/>robots.ox.ac.uk (M.S.) <lb/> †These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> ‡These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/>This is an open-access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution license (https://creative-<lb/>commons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which permits unrestricted <lb/>use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided <lb/>the original work is properly cited. <lb/>Cite this article as J. M. Brauner et al., Science 371, <lb/>eabd9338 (2021). DOI: 10.1126/science.abd9338 <lb/>READ THE FULL ARTICLE AT <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1126/science.abd9338 <lb/>0.0% <lb/>17.5% <lb/>52.5% <lb/>Gatherings limited to 1000 people or less <lb/>Gatherings limited to 100 people or less <lb/>Gatherings limited to 10 people or less <lb/>Some businesses closed <lb/>Most nonessential businesses closed <lb/>Additional benefit of stay-at-home order <lb/>on top of above NPIs <lb/>Schools and universities closed <lb/>Posterior median reduction in R t <lb/>35.0% <lb/>Median intervention effectiveness estimates across a suite of 206 analyses with different epidemio-<lb/>logical parameters, data, and modeling assumptions. Bayesian inference using a semimechanistic <lb/>hierarchical model with observed national case and death data across 41 countries between January and May <lb/>2020 is used to infer the effectiveness of several nonpharmaceutical interventions. Although precise <lb/>effectiveness estimates depend on the assumed data and parameters, there are clear trends across the <lb/>experimental conditions. Violins show kernel density estimates of the posterior median effectiveness across <lb/>the sensitivity analysis. R t , instantaneous reproduction number. <lb/></cover>

			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>◥ <lb/>CORONAVIRUS <lb/>Inferring the effectiveness of government <lb/>interventions against COVID-19 <lb/>Jan M. Brauner 1,2 * †, Sören Mindermann 1 * †, Mrinank Sharma 2,3,4 * †, David Johnston 5,6 , John Salvatier 6 , <lb/>Tomáš Gavenčiak 7 , Anna B. Stephenson 8 , Gavin Leech 9 , George Altman 10 , Vladimir Mikulik 11 , <lb/>Alexander John Norman 12 , Joshua Teperowski Monrad 2,13,14 , Tamay Besiroglu 15 , Hong Ge 16 , <lb/>Meghan A. Hartwick 17 , Yee Whye Teh 3 , Leonid Chindelevitch 18,19 ‡, Yarin Gal 1 ‡, Jan Kulveit 2 ‡ <lb/>Governments are attempting to control the COVID-19 pandemic with nonpharmaceutical interventions <lb/>(NPIs). However, the effectiveness of different NPIs at reducing transmission is poorly understood. We <lb/>gathered chronological data on the implementation of NPIs for several European and non-European <lb/>countries between January and the end of May 2020. We estimated the effectiveness of these NPIs, <lb/>which range from limiting gathering sizes and closing businesses or educational institutions to <lb/>stay-at-home orders. To do so, we used a Bayesian hierarchical model that links NPI implementation <lb/>dates to national case and death counts and supported the results with extensive empirical validation. <lb/>Closing all educational institutions, limiting gatherings to 10 people or less, and closing face-to-face <lb/>businesses each reduced transmission considerably. The additional effect of stay-at-home orders was <lb/>comparatively small. <lb/></front>

            <body>W <lb/>orldwide, governments have mobi-<lb/>lized resources to fight the COVID-19 <lb/>pandemic. A wide range of non-<lb/>pharmaceutical interventions (NPIs) <lb/>has been deployed, including stay-at-<lb/>home orders and the closure of all nonessential <lb/>businesses. Recent analyses show that these <lb/>large-scale NPIs were jointly effective at reduc-<lb/>ing the virus&apos;s effective reproduction number <lb/>R t (1), but it is still largely unknown how <lb/>effective individual NPIs were. As more data <lb/>become available, we can move beyond esti-<lb/>mating the combined effect of a bundle of <lb/>NPIs and begin to understand the effects of <lb/>individual interventions. This can help govern-<lb/>ments efficiently control the epidemic, by <lb/>focusing on the most effective NPIs to ease <lb/>the burden put on the population. <lb/>A promising way to estimate NPI effective-<lb/>ness is data-driven, cross-country modeling: <lb/>inferring effectiveness by relating the NPIs <lb/>implemented in different countries to the <lb/>course of the epidemic in these countries. To <lb/>disentangle the effects of individual NPIs, we <lb/>need to leverage data from multiple coun-<lb/>tries with diverse sets of interventions in place. <lb/>Previous data-driven studies (table S8) esti-<lb/>mate effectiveness for individual countries <lb/>(2-4) or NPIs, although some exceptions do <lb/>exist [(1, 5-8); summarized in table S7]. In <lb/>contrast, we evaluated the impact of several <lb/>NPIs on the epidemic&apos;s growth in 34 European <lb/>and 7 non-European countries. If all countries <lb/>implemented the same set of NPIs on the same <lb/>day, the individual effect of each NPI would <lb/>be unidentifiable. However, the COVID-19 re-<lb/>sponse was far less coordinated: Countries <lb/>implemented different sets of NPIs at differ-<lb/>ent times and in different orders (Fig. 1). <lb/>Even with diverse data from many countries, <lb/>estimating NPI effects remains a challenging <lb/>task. To begin with, models are based on un-<lb/>certain epidemiological parameters; our NPI <lb/>effectiveness study incorporates some of this <lb/>uncertainty directly into the model. Further-<lb/>more, the data are retrospective and observa-<lb/>tional, meaning that unobserved factors could <lb/>confound the results. Also, NPI effectiveness <lb/>estimates can be highly sensitive to arbitrary <lb/>modeling decisions, as shown by two recent <lb/>replication studies (9, 10). And finally, large-<lb/>scale public NPI datasets suffer from frequent <lb/>inconsistencies (11) and missing data (12). <lb/>Hence, the data and the model must be care-<lb/>fully validated if they are to be used to guide <lb/>policy decisions. We have collected a large <lb/>public dataset on NPI implementation dates <lb/>that has been validated by independent double <lb/>entry, and we have extensively validated our <lb/>effectiveness estimates. This validation of data <lb/>and model is a crucial but often absent or in-<lb/>complete element of COVID-19 NPI effective-<lb/>ness studies (10). <lb/>Our results provide insight on the amount <lb/>of COVID-19 transmission associated with var-<lb/>ious areas and activities of public life, such as <lb/>gatherings of different sizes. Therefore, they <lb/>may inform the packages of interventions that <lb/>countries implement to control transmission <lb/>in current and future waves of infections. How-<lb/>ever, we need to be careful when interpreting <lb/>this study&apos;s results. We only analyzed the effect <lb/>NPIs had between January and the end of May <lb/>2020, and NPI effectiveness may change over <lb/>time as circumstances change. Lifting an NPI <lb/>does not imply that transmission will return to <lb/>its original level, and our window of analysis <lb/>does not include relaxation of NPIs. These and <lb/>other limitations are detailed in the Discussion <lb/>section. <lb/>Cross-country NPI effectiveness modeling <lb/>We analyzed the effects of seven commonly used <lb/>NPIs between 22 January and 30 May 2020. All <lb/>NPIs aimed to reduce the number of contacts <lb/>within the population (Table 1). If a country <lb/>lifted an NPI before 30 May, the window of <lb/>analysis for that country terminates on the <lb/>day of the lifting (see Materials and methods). <lb/>To ensure high data quality, all NPI data were <lb/>independently entered by two of the authors <lb/>(independent double entry) using primary <lb/>sources and then manually compared with <lb/>several public datasets. Data on confirmed <lb/>COVID-19 cases and deaths were taken from <lb/>the Johns Hopkins Center for Systems Science <lb/>and Engineering (CSSE) COVID-19 Dataset <lb/>(13). The data used in this study, including <lb/>sources, are available online (14). <lb/>We estimated the effectiveness of NPIs with <lb/>a Bayesian hierarchical model. We used case <lb/>and death data from each country to infer the <lb/>number of new infections at each point in <lb/>time, which is itself used to infer the (instan-<lb/>taneous) reproduction number R t over time. <lb/>NPI effects were then estimated by relating <lb/>the daily reproduction numbers to the active <lb/>NPIs, across all days and countries. This rela-<lb/>tively simple, data-driven approach allowed us <lb/>to sidestep assumptions about contact patterns <lb/>and intensity, infectiousness of different age <lb/>groups, and so forth that are typically required <lb/>in modeling studies. This approach also <lb/></body>

			<front place="headnote">RESEARCH <lb/>Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/>1 of 8 <lb/>1 Oxford Applied and Theoretical Machine Learning (OATML) <lb/>Group, Department of Computer Science, University of <lb/>Oxford, Oxford, UK. 2 Future of Humanity Institute, University <lb/>of Oxford, Oxford, UK. 3 Department of Statistics, University <lb/>of Oxford, Oxford, UK. 4 Department of Engineering Science, <lb/>University of Oxford, Oxford, UK. 5 College of Engineering and <lb/>Computer Science, Australian National University, Canberra, <lb/>Australia. 6 Quantified Uncertainty Research Institute, San <lb/>Francisco, CA, USA. 7 Independent scholar, Prague, Czech <lb/>Republic. 8 Harvard John A. Paulson School of Engineering <lb/>and Applied Sciences, Harvard University, Cambridge, MA, <lb/>USA. 9 School of Computer Science, University of Bristol, <lb/>Bristol, UK. 10 School of Medical Sciences, University of <lb/>Manchester, Manchester, UK. 11 Independent scholar, London, <lb/>UK. 12 Mathematical, Physical and Life Sciences (MPLS) <lb/>Doctoral Training Centre, University of Oxford, Oxford, UK. <lb/>13 Faculty of Public Health and Policy, London School of <lb/>Hygiene and Tropical Medicine, London, UK. 14 Department of <lb/>Health Policy, London School of Economics and Political <lb/>Science, London, UK. 15 Faculty of Economics, University of <lb/>Cambridge, Cambridge, UK. 16 Engineering Department, <lb/>University of Cambridge, Cambridge, UK. 17 Tufts Initiative for <lb/>the Forecasting and Modeling of Infectious Diseases, Tufts <lb/>University, Boston, MA, USA. 18 Medical Research Council <lb/>(MRC) Centre for Global Infectious Disease Analysis, School <lb/>of Public Health, Imperial College London, London, UK. <lb/>19 Abdul Latif Jameel Institute for Disease and Emergency <lb/>Analytics (J-IDEA), School of Public Health, Imperial College <lb/>London, London, UK. <lb/>*Corresponding author. Email: jan.brauner@cs.ox.ac.uk (J.M.B.); <lb/>soren.mindermann@cs.ox.ac.uk (S.M.); mrinank@robots.ox.ac. <lb/>uk (M.S.) †These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/> ‡These authors contributed equally to this work. <lb/></front>

			<body>allowed us to directly model many sources <lb/>of uncertainty, such as uncertain epidemio-<lb/>logical parameters, differences in NPI effec-<lb/>tiveness between countries, unknown changes <lb/>in testing and infection fatality rates, and the <lb/>effect of unobserved influences on R t . The <lb/>code is available online (14). <lb/>Effectiveness of individual NPIs <lb/>Our model enabled us to estimate the indi-<lb/>vidual effectiveness of each NPI, expressed as <lb/>a percentage reduction in R t . We quantified <lb/>uncertainty with Bayesian prediction inter-<lb/>vals, which are wider than standard credible <lb/>intervals. Bayesian prediction intervals reflect <lb/>differences in NPI effectiveness across coun-<lb/>tries among several other sources of uncer-<lb/>tainty. They are analogous to the standard <lb/>deviation of the effectiveness across coun-<lb/>tries rather than the standard error of the <lb/>mean effectiveness. Under the default model <lb/>settings, the percentage reduction in R t (with <lb/>95% prediction interval; Fig. 2) associated with <lb/>each NPI was as follows: limiting gatherings to <lb/>1000 people or less: 23% (0 to 40%); limit-<lb/>ing gatherings to 100 people or less: 34% <lb/>(12 to 52%); limiting gatherings to 10 people <lb/>or less: 42% (17 to 60%); closing some high-<lb/>risk face-to-face businesses: 18% (-8 to 40%); <lb/>closing most nonessential face-to-face busi-<lb/>nesses: 27% (-3 to 49%); closing both schools <lb/>and universities in conjunction: 38% (16 to <lb/>54%); and issuing stay-at-home orders (addi-<lb/>tional effect on top of all other NPIs): 13% <lb/>(-5 to 31%). Note that we were not able to <lb/>robustly disentangle the individual effects <lb/>of closing only schools or only universities, <lb/>because these NPIs were implemented on <lb/>the same day or in close succession in most <lb/>countries [except Iceland and Sweden, where <lb/>only universities were closed (see also fig. <lb/>S21)]. We thus reported &quot;schools and uni-<lb/>versities closed&quot; as one NPI. <lb/>Some NPIs frequently co-occurred, i.e., were <lb/>partly collinear. However, we were able to <lb/>isolate the effects of individual NPIs, because <lb/>the collinearity was imperfect and our data-<lb/>set large. For every pair of NPIs, we observed <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 8 <lb/></page>

            <body>Fig. 1. Timing of NPI implementations in early 2020. Crossed-out icons signify when an NPI was lifted. Detailed definitions of the NPIs are given in Table 1.<lb/></body>

            <note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<body>one without the other for 504 days across all <lb/>countries (country-days) on average (table S5). <lb/>The minimum number of country-days for any <lb/>NPI pair is 148 (for limiting gatherings to 1000 <lb/>or 100 attendees). Additionally, under exces-<lb/>sive collinearity, and insufficient data to over-<lb/>come it, individual effectiveness estimates would <lb/>be highly sensitive to variations in the data and <lb/>model parameters (15). Indeed, high sensitivity <lb/>prevented Flaxman et al. (1), who had a smaller <lb/>dataset, from disentangling NPI effects (9). In <lb/>contrast, our effectiveness estimates are sub-<lb/>stantially less sensitive (see below). Finally, the <lb/>posterior correlations between the effectiveness <lb/>estimates are weak, further suggesting manage-<lb/>able collinearity (fig. S22). <lb/>Effectiveness of NPI combinations <lb/>Although the correlations between the indi-<lb/>vidual estimates were weak, we took them <lb/>into account when evaluating combined NPI <lb/>effectiveness. For example, if two NPIs fre-<lb/>quently co-occur, there may be more certainty <lb/>about the combined effectiveness than about <lb/>the effectiveness of each NPI individually. <lb/>Figure 3 shows the combined effectiveness of <lb/>the sets of NPIs that are most common in our <lb/>data. In combination, the NPIs in this study <lb/>reduced R t by 77% (67 to 85%). Across coun-<lb/>tries, the mean R t without any NPIs (i.e., the <lb/>R 0 ) was 3.3 (table S4). Starting from this num-<lb/>ber, the estimated R t likely could have been <lb/>brought below 1 by closing schools and univer-<lb/>sities, closing high-risk businesses, and limiting <lb/>gathering sizes to at most 10 people. Readers can <lb/>interactively explore the effects of sets of NPIs <lb/>with our online mitigation calculator (16). A <lb/>comma-separated value file containing the <lb/>joint effectiveness of all NPI combinations is <lb/>available online (14). <lb/>Sensitivity and validation <lb/>We performed a range of validation and sen-<lb/>sitivity experiments (figs. S2 to S19). First, we <lb/>analyzed how the model extrapolated to coun-<lb/>tries that did not contribute data for fitting the <lb/>model, and we found that it could generate <lb/>calibrated forecasts for up to 2 months, with <lb/>uncertainty increasing over time. Multiple <lb/>sensitivity analyses showed how the results <lb/>changed when we modified the priors over <lb/>epidemiological parameters, excluded countries <lb/>from the dataset, used only deaths or confirmed <lb/>cases as observations, varied the data prepro-<lb/>cessing, and more. Finally, we tested our key <lb/>assumptions by showing results for several <lb/>alternative models [structural sensitivity (10)] <lb/>and examined possible confounding of our es-<lb/>timates by unobserved factors influencing R t . <lb/>In total, we considered NPI effectiveness un-<lb/>der 206 alternative experimental conditions <lb/>(Fig. 4A). Compared with the results obtained <lb/>under our default settings (Figs. 2 and 3), <lb/>median NPI effectiveness varied under alter-<lb/>native plausible experimental conditions. How-<lb/>ever, the trends in the results are robust, and <lb/>some NPIs outperformed others under all tested <lb/>conditions. Although we tested large ranges <lb/>of plausible values, our experiments did not <lb/>include every possible source of uncertainty. <lb/>We categorized NPI effects into small, mod-<lb/>erate, and large, which we define as a posterior <lb/>median reduction in R t of &lt;17.5%, between 17.5 <lb/>and 35%, and &gt;35%, respectively (vertical lines <lb/>in Fig. 4). Four of the NPIs fell into the same <lb/>category across a large fraction of experimen-<lb/>tal conditions: closing both schools and uni-<lb/>versities was associated with a large effect in <lb/>96% of experimental conditions, and limiting <lb/>gatherings to 10 people or less had a large ef-<lb/>fect in 99% of conditions. Closing most non-<lb/>essential businesses had a moderate effect in <lb/>98% of conditions. Issuing stay-at-home orders <lb/>(that is, in addition to the other NPIs) fell into <lb/>the &quot;small effect&quot; category in 96% of experi-<lb/>mental conditions. Three NPIs fell less clearly <lb/>into one category: Limiting gatherings to 1000 <lb/>people or less had a small-to-moderate effect <lb/>(moderate in 81% of conditions) while limit-<lb/>ing gatherings to 100 people or less had a <lb/>moderate-to-large effect (moderate in 66% of <lb/>conditions). Finally, closing some high-risk <lb/>businesses, including bars, restaurants, and <lb/>nightclubs, had a small-to-moderate effect <lb/>(moderate in 58% of conditions). Limiting gather-<lb/>ings to 1000 people or less was the NPI with the <lb/>highest variation in median effectiveness across <lb/>the experimental conditions (Fig. 4A), which may <lb/>reflect this NPI&apos;s partial collinearity with limiting <lb/>gatherings to 100 people or less. <lb/>Aggregating all sensitivity analyses can hide <lb/>sensitivity to specific assumptions. We display <lb/>the median NPI effects in four categories of <lb/>sensitivity analyses (Fig. 4, B to E), and each <lb/>individual sensitivity analysis is shown in the <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. NPIs included in the study. <lb/>NPI <lb/>Description <lb/>Gatherings limited to <lb/>1000 people or less <lb/>A country has set a size limit on gatherings. The limit is at most 1000 people <lb/>(often less), and gatherings above the maximum size are disallowed. <lb/>For example, a ban on gatherings of 500 people or more would be classified as <lb/>&quot;gatherings limited to 1000 or less,&quot; but a ban on gatherings of 2000 people or more would not. <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Gatherings limited to <lb/>100 people or less <lb/>A country has set a size limit on gatherings. The limit is at most 100 people (often less). <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Gatherings limited to <lb/>10 people or less <lb/>A country has set a size limit on gatherings. The limit is at most 10 people (often less). <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Some businesses closed <lb/>A country has specified a few kinds of face-to-face businesses that are <lb/>considered high risk and need to suspend operations (blacklist). <lb/>Common examples are restaurants, bars, nightclubs, cinemas, and gyms. <lb/>By default, businesses are not suspended. <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Most nonessential <lb/>businesses closed <lb/>A country has suspended the operations of many face-to-face businesses. <lb/>By default, face-to-face businesses are suspended unless they are designated as essential (whitelist). <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Schools closed <lb/>A country has closed most or all schools. <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Universities closed <lb/>A country has closed most or all universities and higher-education facilities. <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/>Stay-at-home order <lb/>An order for the general public to stay at home has been issued. This is mandatory, not just a <lb/>recommendation. Exemptions are usually granted for certain purposes (such as shopping, <lb/>exercise, or going to work) or, more rarely, for certain times of the day. Whenever countries <lb/>in our dataset introduced stay-at-home orders, they essentially always also implemented, or already <lb/>had in place, all other NPIs listed in this table. All these are encoded as distinct NPIs in the data. In our results, <lb/>we thus estimate the additional effect of a stay-at-home order on top of all other NPIs. <lb/>............................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................................ <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<body>supplementary materials. The trends in the <lb/>results are also stable within these categories. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>We used a data-driven approach to estimate <lb/>the effects that seven nonpharmaceutical in-<lb/>terventions had on COVID-19 transmission in <lb/>41 countries between January and the end of <lb/>May 2020. We found that several NPIs were <lb/>associated with a clear reduction in R t , in line <lb/>with mounting evidence that NPIs are effec-<lb/>tive at mitigating and suppressing outbreaks <lb/>of COVID-19. Furthermore, our results indicate <lb/>that some NPIs outperformed others. While <lb/>the exact effectiveness estimates vary with <lb/>modeling assumptions, the broad conclusions <lb/>discussed below are largely robust across <lb/>206 experimental conditions in 11 sensitivity <lb/>analyses. <lb/>Business closures and gathering bans both <lb/>seem to have been effective at reducing <lb/>COVID-19 transmission. Closing most non-<lb/>essential face-to-face businesses was only some-<lb/>what more effective than targeted closures, <lb/>which only affected businesses with high in-<lb/>fection risk, such as bars, restaurants, and <lb/>nightclubs (see also Table 1). Therefore, tar-<lb/>geted business closures can be a promising <lb/>policy option in some circumstances. Limit-<lb/>ing gatherings to 10 people or less was more <lb/>effective than limits of up to 100 or 1000 <lb/>people and had a more robust effect estimate. <lb/>Note that our estimates are derived from data <lb/>between January and May 2020, a period <lb/>when most gatherings were likely indoors <lb/>owing to the weather. <lb/>Whenever countries in our dataset intro-<lb/>duced stay-at-home orders, they essentially <lb/>always also implemented, or already had in <lb/>place, all other NPIs in this study. We ac-<lb/>counted for these other NPIs separately and <lb/>isolated the effect of ordering the population <lb/>to stay at home, in addition to the effect of all <lb/>other NPIs. In accordance with other studies <lb/>that took this approach (2, 6), we found that <lb/>issuing a stay-at-home order had a small effect <lb/>when a country had already closed educational <lb/>institutions and nonessential businesses and <lb/>had banned gatherings. In contrast, Flaxman et al. <lb/>(1) and Hsiang et al. (3) included the effect of <lb/>several NPIs in the effectiveness of their stay-at-<lb/>home order (or &quot;lockdown&quot;) NPIs and accord-<lb/>ingly found a large effect for this NPI. Our <lb/>finding suggests that some countries may have <lb/>been able to reduce R t to &lt;1 without a stay-at-<lb/>home order (Fig. 3) by issuing other NPIs. <lb/>We found a large effect for closing both <lb/>schools and universities in conjunction, which <lb/>was remarkably robust across different model <lb/>structures, variations in the data, and epide-<lb/>miological assumptions (Fig. 4). This effect <lb/>remained robust when controlling for NPIs <lb/>excluded from our study (fig. S9). Our approach <lb/>cannot distinguish direct effects on transmission <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 2. NPI effectiveness under default model settings. Posterior percentage reductions in R t with <lb/>median, 50%, and 95% prediction intervals shown. Prediction intervals reflect many sources of uncertainty, <lb/>including NPI effectiveness varying by country and uncertainty in epidemiological parameters. A negative <lb/>1% reduction refers to a 1% increase in R t . &quot;Schools and universities closed&quot; shows the joint effect of closing <lb/>both schools and universities; the individual effect of closing just one will be smaller (see text). Cumulative <lb/>effects are shown for hierarchical NPIs (gathering bans and business closures), that is, the result for &quot;Most <lb/>nonessential businesses closed&quot; shows the cumulative effect of two NPIs with separate parameters and <lb/>icons-closing some (high-risk) businesses, and additionally closing most remaining (non-high-risk but <lb/>nonessential) businesses given that some businesses are already closed. <lb/>A <lb/>B <lb/>Fig. 3. Combined NPI effectiveness for the 15 most commonly implemented sets of NPIs in our data. <lb/>Black and gray bars denote 50% and 95% Bayesian prediction intervals, respectively. (A) Predicted R t after <lb/>implementation of each set of NPIs, assuming R 0 = 3.3. (B) Maximum R 0 that can be reduced to R t below 1 by <lb/>common sets of NPIs. Readers can interactively explore the effects of all sets of NPIs, while setting R 0 and <lb/>adjusting NPI effectiveness to local circumstances, with our online mitigation calculator (16). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<body>in schools and universities from indirect effects, <lb/>such as the general population behaving more <lb/>cautiously after school closures signaled the <lb/>gravity of the pandemic. Additionally, because <lb/>school and university closures were imple-<lb/>mented on the same day or in close succession <lb/>in most of the countries we studied, our ap-<lb/>proach cannot distinguish their individual ef-<lb/>fects (fig. S21). This limitation likely also holds <lb/>for other observational studies that do not in-<lb/>clude data on university closures and estimate <lb/>only the effect of school closures (1-3, 5-8). <lb/>Furthermore, our study does not provide evi-<lb/>dence on the effect of closing preschools and <lb/>nurseries. <lb/>Previous evidence on the role of pupils and <lb/>students in transmission is mixed. Although <lb/>infected young people (~12 to 25 years of age) <lb/>are often asymptomatic, they appear to shed <lb/>similar amounts of virus as older people <lb/>(17, 18) and might therefore infect higher-<lb/>risk individuals. Early data suggested that <lb/>children and young adults had a notably lower <lb/>observed incidence rate than older adults-<lb/>whether this was due to school and univer-<lb/>sity closures remains unknown (19-22). In <lb/>contrast, the recent resurgence of cases in <lb/>European countries has been concentrated <lb/>in the age group corresponding to secondary <lb/>school and higher education (especially the <lb/>latter) and is now spreading to older age <lb/>groups as well as primary school-aged children <lb/>(23, 24). Primary schools may be generally less <lb/>affected than secondary schools (20, 25-28), <lb/>perhaps partly because children under the age <lb/>of 12 are less susceptible to SARS-CoV-2 (29). <lb/>Our study has several limitations. (i) NPI <lb/>effectiveness may depend on the context of <lb/>implementation, such as the presence of other <lb/>NPIs, country demographics, and specific im-<lb/>plementation details. Our results thus need to <lb/>be interpreted as indicating the effectiveness <lb/>in the contexts in which the NPI was imple-<lb/>mented in our data (10). For example, in a <lb/>country with a comparatively old population, <lb/>the effectiveness of closing schools and uni-<lb/>versities would likely have been on the lower <lb/>end of our prediction interval. Expert judg-<lb/>ment should thus be used to adjust our esti-<lb/>mates to local circumstances. (ii) R t may have <lb/>been reduced by unobserved NPIs or volun-<lb/>tary behavior changes such as mask-wearing. <lb/>To investigate whether the effect of these po-<lb/>tential confounders could be falsely attributed <lb/>to the observed NPIs, we performed several <lb/>additional analyses and found that our results <lb/>are stable to a range of unobserved factors <lb/>(fig. S9). However, this sensitivity check can-<lb/>not provide certainty, and investigating the <lb/>role of unobserved factors is an important <lb/>topic to explore further. (iii) Our results can-<lb/>not be used without qualification to predict <lb/>the effect of lifting NPIs. For example, closing <lb/>schools and universities in conjunction seems <lb/>to have greatly reduced transmission, but this <lb/>does not mean that reopening them will nec-<lb/>essarily cause infections to soar. Educational <lb/>institutions can implement safety measures, <lb/>such as reduced class sizes, as they reopen. <lb/>However, the nearly 40,000 confirmed cases <lb/>associated with universities in the United <lb/>Kingdom since they reopened in September <lb/>2020 show that educational institutions may <lb/>still play a large role in transmission, despite <lb/>safety measures (30). (iv) We do not have data <lb/>on some promising interventions, such as test-<lb/>ing, tracing, and case isolation. These inter-<lb/>ventions could become an important part of a <lb/>cost-effective epidemic response (31), but we <lb/>did not include them because it is difficult to <lb/>obtain comprehensive data on their imple-<lb/>mentation. In addition, although the data are <lb/>more readily available, it is difficult to estimate <lb/>the effect of mask-wearing in public spaces <lb/>because there was limited public life as a result <lb/>of other NPIs. We discuss further limitations <lb/>in supplementary text section E. <lb/>Although our work focused on estimating the <lb/>impact of NPIs on the reproduction number R t , <lb/>the ultimate goal of governments may be to <lb/>reduce the incidence, prevalence, and excess <lb/>mortality of COVID-19. For this, controlling <lb/>R t is essential, but the contribution of NPIs <lb/>toward these goals may also be mediated by <lb/></body>

            <note type="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

            <page>5 of 8 <lb/></page>

            <body>A <lb/>B <lb/>C <lb/>D <lb/>E <lb/>Fig. 4. Median NPI effectiveness across the sensitivity analyses. (A) Median NPI effectiveness <lb/>(reduction in R t ) when varying different components of the model or the data in 206 experimental conditions. <lb/>Results are displayed as violin plots, using kernel density estimation to create the distributions. Inside <lb/>the violins, the box plots show median and interquartile range. The vertical lines mark 0, 17.5, and 35% <lb/>(see text). (B to E) Categorized sensitivity analyses. (B) Sensitivity to model structure. Using only cases or <lb/>only deaths as observations (two experimental conditions; fig. S7); varying the model structure (three <lb/>conditions; fig. S8, left). (C) Sensitivity to data and preprocessing. Leaving out countries from the dataset <lb/>(42 conditions; figs. S5 and S21); varying the threshold below which cases and deaths are masked (eight <lb/>conditions; fig. S13); sensitivity to correcting for undocumented cases and to country-level differences in case <lb/>ascertainment (two conditions; fig. S6). (D) Sensitivity to epidemiological parameters. Jointly varying the <lb/>means of the priors over the means of the generation interval, the infection-to-case-confirmation delay, and <lb/>the infection-to-death delay (125 conditions; fig. S10); varying the prior over R 0 (four conditions; fig. S11); <lb/>varying the prior over NPI effect parameters (three conditions; fig. S11); varying the prior over the degree to <lb/>which NPI effects vary across countries (three conditions; fig. S12). (E) Sensitivity to unobserved factors <lb/>influencing R t . Excluding observed NPIs one at a time (eight conditions; fig. S9); controlling for additional <lb/>NPIs from a different dataset (six conditions; fig. S9). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<body>other factors, such as their duration and timing <lb/>(32), periodicity and adherence (33, 34), and <lb/>successful containment (35). While each of <lb/>these factors addresses transmission within <lb/>individual countries, it can be crucial to also <lb/>synchronize NPIs between countries, given <lb/>that cases can be imported (36). <lb/>Many governments around the world seek <lb/>to keep R t below 1 while minimizing the <lb/>social and economic costs of their interven-<lb/>tions. Our work offers insights into which <lb/>areas of public life are most in need of virus <lb/>containment measures so that activities can <lb/>continue as the pandemic develops; however, <lb/>our estimates should not be taken as the final <lb/>word on NPI effectiveness. <lb/>Materials and methods <lb/>Dataset <lb/>We analyzed the effects of NPIs (Table 1) in <lb/>41 countries (37) (Fig. 1). We recorded NPI <lb/>implementations when the measures were <lb/>implemented nationally or in most regions <lb/>of a country (affecting at least three-fourths <lb/>of the population). We recorded only manda-<lb/>tory restrictions, not recommendations. Sup-<lb/>plementary text section G details how edge <lb/>cases in the data collection were handled. For <lb/>each country, the window of analysis starts <lb/>on 22 January and ends either after the first <lb/>lifting of an NPI or on 30 May 2020, whichever <lb/>came first. The reason to end the analysis after <lb/>the first major reopening (38) was to avoid a <lb/>distribution shift. For example, when schools <lb/>reopened, it was often with safety measures, <lb/>such as smaller class sizes and distancing rules. <lb/>It is therefore expected that contact patterns in <lb/>schools will have been different before school <lb/>closure compared with after reopening. Model-<lb/>ing this difference explicitly is left for future <lb/>work. Data on confirmed COVID-19 cases and <lb/>deaths were taken from the Johns Hopkins <lb/>CSSE COVID-19 Dataset (13). The data used <lb/>in this study, including sources, are available <lb/>online (14). <lb/>Data collection <lb/>We collected data on the start and end dates <lb/>of NPI implementations, from the start of the <lb/>pandemic until 30 May 2020. Before collect-<lb/>ing the data, we experimented with several <lb/>public NPI datasets, finding that they were <lb/>not complete enough for our modeling and <lb/>contained incorrect dates (39). By focusing <lb/>on a smaller set of countries and NPIs than <lb/>these datasets, we were able to enforce strong <lb/>quality controls: We used independent double <lb/>entry and manually compared our data with <lb/>public datasets for cross-checking. <lb/>First, two authors independently researched <lb/>each country and entered the NPI data into <lb/>separate spreadsheets. The researchers manu-<lb/>ally researched the dates using internet <lb/>searches: There was no automatic component <lb/>in the data-gathering process. The average <lb/>time spent researching each country was <lb/>1.5 hours per researcher. Next, the researchers <lb/>independently compared their entries against <lb/>two public datasets, the Epidemic Forecasting <lb/>Global NPI (EFGNPI) Database (40) and the <lb/>Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker <lb/>(41), and, if there were conflicts, visited all pri-<lb/>mary sources to resolve the conflicts. After that, <lb/>each country and NPI was again independently <lb/>entered by one to three paid contractors, who <lb/>were provided with a detailed description of <lb/>the NPIs and asked to include primary sources <lb/>with their data. A researcher then resolved any <lb/>conflicts between this data and one (but not <lb/>both) of the spreadsheets. Finally, the two inde-<lb/>pendent spreadsheets were combined and all <lb/>conflicts resolved by a researcher. The final <lb/>dataset contains primary sources (govern-<lb/>ment websites and/or media articles) for <lb/>each entry. <lb/>Data preprocessing <lb/>When the case count is small, a large fraction <lb/>of cases may be imported from other countries <lb/>and the testing regime may change rapidly. <lb/>To prevent this from biasing our model, we <lb/>neglected case numbers before a country had <lb/>reached 100 confirmed cases and fatality num-<lb/>bers before a country had reached 10 deaths. <lb/>We included these thresholds in our sensitivity <lb/>analysis (fig. S13). <lb/>Brief model description <lb/>In this section, we give a short summary of the <lb/>model (Fig. 5). The detailed model description <lb/>is given in supplementary text section A. <lb/>Briefly, our model uses case and death data <lb/>from each country to &quot;backward&quot; infer the <lb/>number of new infections at each point in <lb/>time, which is itself used to infer the reproduc-<lb/>tion numbers. NPI effects are then estimated <lb/>by relating the daily reproduction numbers to <lb/>the active NPIs, across all days and countries. <lb/>This relatively simple, data-driven approach <lb/>allowed us to sidestep assumptions about con-<lb/>tact patterns and intensity, infectiousness of <lb/>different age groups, and so forth that are <lb/>typically required in modeling studies. Code <lb/>is available online (14). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<body>Fig. 5. Model overview. Unshaded, white nodes are observed. From bottom to top: The mean effect <lb/>parameter of NPI i is a i , and the country-specific effect parameter is a i,c . On each day t, a country&apos;s daily <lb/>reproduction number R t,c depends on the country&apos;s basic reproduction number R 0,c and the active NPIs. <lb/>The active NPIs are encoded by x i,t,c , which is 1 if NPI i is active in country c at time t, and 0 otherwise. R t,c is <lb/>transformed into the daily growth rate g t,c using the generation interval parameters and subsequently is used <lb/>to compute the new infections N <lb/>ðCÞ <lb/>t;c and N <lb/>ðDÞ <lb/>t;c that will subsequently become confirmed cases and deaths, <lb/>respectively. Finally, the expected numbers of daily confirmed cases y <lb/>ðCÞ <lb/>t;c and deaths y <lb/>ðDÞ <lb/>t;c are computed using <lb/>discrete convolutions of N <lb/>ð:Þ <lb/>t;c with the relevant delay distributions. Our model uses both case and death <lb/>data; it splits all nodes above the daily growth rate g t,c into separate branches for deaths and confirmed <lb/>cases. We account for uncertainty in the generation interval, infection-to-case confirmation delay, and the <lb/>infection-to-death delay by placing priors over the parameters of these distributions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<body>Our model builds on the semimechanistic <lb/>Bayesian hierarchical model of Flaxman et al. <lb/>(1), with several additions. First, we allow our <lb/>model to observe both case and death data. <lb/>This increases the amount of data from which <lb/>we can extract NPI effects, reduces distinct <lb/>biases in case and death reporting, and re-<lb/>duces the bias from including only countries <lb/>with many deaths. Second, since epidemiolog-<lb/>ical parameters are only known with uncer-<lb/>tainty, we place priors over them, following <lb/>recent recommended practice (42). Third, as <lb/>we do not aim to infer the total number of <lb/>COVID-19 infections, we can avoid assuming <lb/>a specific infection fatality rate (IFR) or ascer-<lb/>tainment rate (rate of testing). Fourth, we <lb/>allow the effects of all NPIs to vary across <lb/>countries, reflecting differences in NPI im-<lb/>plementation and adherence. <lb/>We now describe the model by going <lb/>through Fig. 5 from bottom to top. The growth <lb/>of the epidemic is determined by the time-and <lb/>country-specific reproduction number R t,c , <lb/>which depends on (i) the (unobserved) basic <lb/>reproduction number in country c, R 0,c , and <lb/>(ii) the active NPIs at time t. R 0,c accounts for <lb/>all time-invariant factors that affect transmis-<lb/>sion in country c, such as differences in demo-<lb/>graphics, population density, culture, and health <lb/>systems (43). <lb/>Following Flaxman et al. and others (1, 6, 8), <lb/>each NPI is assumed to independently affect <lb/>R t,c as a multiplicative factor <lb/>R t;c ¼ R 0;c <lb/>Y I <lb/>i¼1 <lb/>expðÀa i;c x i;t;c Þ <lb/>where x i,t,c = 1 indicates that NPI i is active in <lb/>country c on day t (x i,t,c = 0 otherwise), I is the <lb/>number of NPIs, and a i,c is the effect param-<lb/>eter for NPI i in country c. The multiplicative <lb/>effect encodes the plausible assumption that <lb/>NPIs have a smaller absolute effect when R t,c is <lb/>already low. <lb/>We assume that the effect of each NPI on <lb/>R t,c is stable across time but can vary across <lb/>countries to some degree. Concretely, the ef-<lb/>fect parameter of intervention i in country c is <lb/>defined as a i,c = a i + z i,c , where a i represents <lb/>the mean effect parameter, and z i;c e N ð0; s 2 <lb/>i Þ. <lb/>The variance s i <lb/>2 corresponds to the degree of <lb/>cross-country variation in the effectiveness <lb/>of NPI i and is inferred from the data. This <lb/>partial pooling of NPI effect parameters min-<lb/>imizes bias from country-specific sources <lb/>while also reflecting that NPI effectiveness <lb/>is likely different across countries. We define <lb/>the effectiveness of NPI i as the percentage <lb/>reduction in R t associated with NPI i across <lb/>countries. This effectiveness, displayed in Figs. <lb/>2 to 4, is computed as 1 -exp(-(a i + z i )), where <lb/>again z i e N ð0; s 2 <lb/>i Þ and s i <lb/>2 is drawn from its <lb/>posterior. We place an asymmetric Laplace <lb/>prior on a i that allows for both positive and <lb/>negative effects but places 80% of its proba-<lb/>bility mass on positive effects, reflecting that <lb/>NPIs are more likely to reduce R t,c than to <lb/>increase it. <lb/>In the early phase of an epidemic, the num-<lb/>ber of new daily infections grows exponen-<lb/>tially. During exponential growth, there is a <lb/>one-to-one correspondence between the daily <lb/>growth rate and R t,c (44). The correspondence <lb/>depends on the generation interval (the time <lb/>between successive infections in a chain of <lb/>transmission), which we assume to have a <lb/>gamma distribution. The prior on the mean <lb/>generation interval has a mean of 5.06 days, <lb/>derived from a meta-analysis (45). <lb/>We model the daily new infection count <lb/>separately for confirmed cases and deaths, <lb/>representing those infections that are sub-<lb/>sequently reported and those that are sub-<lb/>sequently fatal. However, both infection <lb/>numbers are assumed to grow at the same <lb/>daily rate in expectation, allowing the use of <lb/>both data sources to estimate each a i . The <lb/>infection numbers translate into reported <lb/>confirmed cases and deaths after a delay. The <lb/>delay is the sum of two independent distri-<lb/>butions, assumed to be equal across countries: <lb/>the incubation period and the delay from <lb/>onset of symptoms to confirmation. We put <lb/>priors over the means of both distributions, <lb/>resulting in a prior over the mean infection-<lb/>to-confirmation delay with a mean of 10.92 days <lb/>(45) (see supplementary text section A.3). Sim-<lb/>ilarly, the infection-to-death delay is the sum of <lb/>the incubation period and the delay from onset <lb/>of symptoms to death, and the prior over its <lb/>mean has a mean of 21.8 days (45). Finally, as in <lb/>related models (1, 6), both the reported cases <lb/>and deaths follow a negative binomial output <lb/>distribution with separate inferred dispersion <lb/>parameters for cases and deaths. <lb/>Using a Markov chain Monte Carlo (MCMC) <lb/>sampling algorithm (46), this model infers <lb/>posterior distributions of each NPI&apos;s effec-<lb/>tiveness while accounting for cross-country <lb/>variations in effectiveness, reporting, and fatal-<lb/>ity rates as well as uncertainty in the generation <lb/>interval and delay distributions. To analyze the <lb/>extent to which modeling assumptions affect <lb/>the results, our sensitivity analysis included <lb/>all epidemiological parameters, prior distri-<lb/>butions, and many of the structural assump-<lb/>tions introduced above. MCMC convergence <lb/>statistics are shown in fig. S19. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES AND NOTES <lb/>1. S. Flaxman et al., Estimating the effects of non-pharmaceutical <lb/>interventions on COVID-19 in Europe. Nature 584, 257-261 <lb/>(2020). doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2405-7; pmid: 32512579 <lb/>2. J. Dehning et al., Inferring change points in the spread of <lb/>COVID-19 reveals the effectiveness of interventions. <lb/>Science 369, eabb9789 (2020). doi: 10.1126/science.abb9789; <lb/>pmid: 32414780 <lb/>3. S. Hsiang et al., The effect of large-scale anti-contagion policies <lb/>on the COVID-19 pandemic. Nature 584, 262-267 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2404-8; pmid: 32512578 <lb/>4. S. Lai et al., Effect of non-pharmaceutical interventions to <lb/>contain COVID-19 in China. Nature 585, 410-413 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2293-x; pmid: 32365354 <lb/>5. Y. Liu, C. Morgenstern, J. Kelly, R. Lowe, CMMID <lb/>COVID-19 Working Group, M. Jit, The impact of non-<lb/>pharmaceutical interventions on SARS-CoV-2 <lb/>transmission across 130 countries and territories. medRxiv <lb/>2020.08.11.20172643v1 [Preprint]. 12 August 2020. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.08.11.20172643. <lb/>6. N. Banholzer et al., Impact of non-pharmaceutical interventions <lb/>on documented cases of COVID-19. medRxiv <lb/>2020.04.16.20062141v3 [Preprint]. 28 April 2020. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.04.16.20062141. <lb/>7. N. Islam et al., Physical distancing interventions and incidence <lb/>of coronavirus disease 2019: Natural experiment in 149 <lb/>countries. BMJ 370, m2743 (2020). doi: 10.1136/bmj.m2743; <lb/>pmid: 32669358 <lb/>8. X. Chen, Z. Qiu, Scenario analysis of non-pharmaceutical <lb/>interventions on global COVID-19 transmissions. Covid <lb/>Economics 7, 46-67 (2020). <lb/>9. K. Soltesz et al., On the sensitivity of non-pharmaceutical <lb/>intervention models for SARS-CoV-2 spread estimation. <lb/>medRxiv 2020.06.10.20127324 [Preprint]. 12 June 2020. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.10.20127324. <lb/>10. M. Sharma et al., How robust are the estimated effects of <lb/>nonpharmaceutical interventions against COVID-19? <lb/>arXiv:2007.13454 [stat.AP] (27 July 2020). <lb/>11. C. Cheng, J. Barceló, A. S. Hartnett, R. Kubinec, <lb/>L. Messerschmidt, COVID-19 government response <lb/>event dataset (CoronaNet v. 1.0). Nat. Hum. Behav. 4, <lb/>756-768 (2020). doi: 10.1038/s41562-020-0909-7; <lb/>pmid: 32576982 <lb/>12. Oxford COVID-19 Government Response Tracker (OxCGRT) <lb/>(2020); https://github.com/OxCGRT/covid-policy-tracker. <lb/>13. E. Dong, H. Du, L. Gardner, An interactive web-based <lb/>dashboard to track COVID-19 in real time. Lancet Infect. Dis. <lb/>20, 533-534 (2020). doi: 10.1016/S1473-3099(20)30120-1; <lb/>pmid: 32087114 <lb/>14. J. M. Brauner et al., epidemics/COVIDNPIs: Inferring the <lb/>effectiveness of government interventions against COVID-19, <lb/>Zenodo (2020); https://doi.org/10.5281/zenodo.4268449. <lb/>15. C. Winship, B. Western, Multicollinearity and model <lb/>misspecification. Sociol. Sci. 3, 627-649 (2016). doi: 10.15195/ <lb/>v3.a27 <lb/>16. EpidemicForecasting.org, Mitigation calculator (2020); <lb/>http://epidemicforecasting.org/calc. <lb/>17. T. C. Jones et al., An analysis of SARS-CoV-2 viral load by <lb/>patient age. medRxiv 2020.06.08.20125484v1 [Preprint]. <lb/>9 June 2020. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.08.20125484. <lb/>18. A. G. L&apos;Huillier, G. Torriani, F. Pigny, L. Kaiser, I. Eckerle, <lb/>Culture-competent SARS-CoV-2 in nasopharynx of <lb/>symptomatic neonates, children, and adolescents. Emerg. <lb/>Infect. Dis. 26, 2494-2497 (2020). doi: 10.3201/ <lb/>eid2610.202403; pmid: 32603290 <lb/>19. The Independent Scientific Advisory Group for Emergencies <lb/>(SAGE), The Independent SAGE Report 3, &quot;When should a <lb/>school reopen? Final report&quot; (2020); www.independentsage. <lb/>org/wp-content/uploads/2020/06/Independent-Sage-Brief-<lb/>Report-on-Schools.pdf. <lb/>20. Y. J. Park et al., Contact tracing during coronavirus disease <lb/>outbreak, South Korea, 2020. Emerg. Infect. Dis. 26, 2465-2468 <lb/>(2020). doi: 10.3201/eid2610.201315; pmid: 32673193 <lb/>21. N. S. Mehta et al., SARS-CoV-2 (COVID-19): What do we know <lb/>about children? A systematic review. Clin. Infect. Dis. 71, <lb/>2469-2479 (2020). doi: 10.1093/cid/ciaa556; <lb/>pmid: 32392337 <lb/>22. P. Zimmermann, N. Curtis, Coronavirus infections in children <lb/>including COVID-19: An overview of the epidemiology, clinical <lb/>features, diagnosis, treatment and prevention options in <lb/>children. Pediatr. Infect. Dis. J. 39, 355-368 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1097/INF.0000000000002660; pmid: 32310621 <lb/>23. Office for National Statistics, Coronavirus (COVID-19) Infection <lb/>Survey, UK: 6 November 2020 (2020); www.ons.gov.uk/ <lb/>peoplepopulationandcommunity/healthandsocialcare/ <lb/>conditionsanddiseases/bulletins/ <lb/>coronaviruscovid19infectionsurveypilot/6november2020. <lb/>24. A. Aleta, Y. Moreno, Age differential analysis of COVID-19 <lb/>second wave in Europe reveals highest incidence amongst <lb/>young adults. medRxiv 2020.11.11.20230177 [Preprint]. <lb/>13 November 2020. https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.11.11.20230177. <lb/>25. M. Levinson, M. Cevik, M. Lipsitch, Reopening primary schools <lb/>during the pandemic. N. Engl. J. Med. 383, 981-985 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1056/NEJMms2024920; pmid: 32726550 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>26. J.Couzin-Frankel, G.Vogel, M.Weiland, School openings across <lb/>globe suggest ways to keep coronavirus at bay, despite <lb/>outbreaks. Science 10.1126/science.abd7107 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1126/science.abd7107 <lb/>27. A. Fontanet et al., Cluster of COVID-19 in northern France: <lb/>A retrospective closed cohort study. medRxiv <lb/>2020.04.18.20071134 [Preprint]. 23 April 2020. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1101/2020.04.18.20071134. <lb/>28. C. Stein-Zamir et al., A large COVID-19 outbreak in a high <lb/>school 10 days after schools&apos; reopening, Israel, May 2020. Euro <lb/>Surveill. 25, 2001352 (2020). doi: 10.2807/1560-7917. <lb/>ES.2020.25.29.2001352; pmid: 32720636 <lb/>29. K. Sun et al., Transmission heterogeneities, kinetics, and <lb/>controllability of SARS-CoV-2. Science 10.1126/science. <lb/>abe2424 (2020). doi: 10.1126/science.abe2424; <lb/>pmid: 33234698 <lb/>30. University and College Union, COVID-19 case dashboard <lb/>(2020); www.ucu.org.uk/covid-dashboard. <lb/>31. T. Colbourn et al., Modelling the health and economic impacts <lb/>of population-wide testing, contact tracing and isolation (PTTI) <lb/>strategies for COVID-19 in the UK. SSRN 10.2139/ssrn.3627273 <lb/>(2020). doi: 10.2139/ssrn.3627273 <lb/>32. K. Prem et al., The effect of control strategies to reduce social <lb/>mixing on outcomes of the COVID-19 epidemic in Wuhan, <lb/>China: A modelling study. Lancet Public Health 5, e261-e270 <lb/>(2020). doi: 10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30073-6; <lb/>pmid: 32220655 <lb/>33. P. G. T. Walker et al., The impact of COVID-19 and strategies <lb/>for mitigation and suppression in low-and middle-income <lb/>countries. Science 369, 413-422 (2020). doi: 10.1126/science. <lb/>abc0035; pmid: 32532802 <lb/>34. N. G. Davies et al., Effects of non-pharmaceutical interventions <lb/>on COVID-19 cases, deaths, and demand for hospital services <lb/>in the UK: A modelling study. Lancet Public Health 5, <lb/>e375-e385 (2020). doi: 10.1016/S2468-2667(20)30133-X; <lb/>pmid: 32502389 <lb/>35. X. Hao et al., Reconstruction of the full transmission dynamics <lb/>of COVID-19 in Wuhan. Nature 584, 420-424 (2020). <lb/>doi: 10.1038/s41586-020-2554-8; pmid: 32674112 <lb/>36. N. W. Ruktanonchai et al., Assessing the impact of coordinated <lb/>COVID-19 exit strategies across Europe. Science 369, <lb/>1465-1470 (2020). doi: 10.1126/science.abc5096; <lb/>pmid: 32680881 <lb/>37. The countries were selected for the availability of reliable NPI data <lb/>at the time when we started data collection and modeling <lb/>(April 2020) and for their presence in at least one of the public <lb/>datasets that we used to cross-validate our collected data. We <lb/>excluded countries with fewer than 100 cases (or 10 deaths) by <lb/>31 March, as our model neglects new cases and deaths below <lb/>these thresholds. We also excluded a small number of countries if <lb/>there were credible media reports casting doubt on the <lb/>trustworthiness of their reporting of cases and deaths. Finally, we <lb/>excluded very large countries such as China, the United States, <lb/>and Canada for ease of data collection, as these would require <lb/>more locally fine-grained data. Of the 41 included countries, <lb/>33 are in Europe. As a result, the NPI effectiveness estimates may <lb/>be biased toward effects in Europe, and NPI effectiveness may <lb/>have been different in other parts of the world. <lb/>38. The window of analysis extended until 2 days after the first <lb/>reopening for confirmed cases and 10 days after the first reopening <lb/>for deaths. These durations correspond to the 5% quantiles of the <lb/>infection-to-case confirmation and infection-to-death distribu-<lb/>tions, ensuring that &lt;5% of the new infections on the reopening <lb/>day or later were observed in the window of analysis. <lb/>39. We evaluated the following datasets: the Oxford COVID-19 <lb/>Government Response Tracker (OxCGRT), the Epidemic <lb/>Forecasting Global NPI Database, and the ACAPS COVID-19 <lb/>Government Measures Dataset. Note that these datasets are under <lb/>continuous development. Many of the mistakes found will already <lb/>have been corrected. We know from our own experience that data <lb/>collection can be very challenging. We have the fullest respect <lb/>for the individuals behind these datasets. In this paper, we focus on <lb/>a more limited set of countries and NPIs than these datasets <lb/>contain, allowing us to ensure higher data quality in this subset. <lb/>Given our experience with public datasets and our data collection, <lb/>we encourage fellow COVID-19 researchers to independently verify <lb/>the quality of public data they use, if feasible. <lb/>40. EpidemicForecasting.org, Epidemic forecasting global NPI <lb/>database (2020); http://epidemicforecasting.org/datasets. <lb/>41. T. Hale, S. Webster, A. Petherick, T. Phillips, B. Kira, Oxford <lb/>COVID-19 Government Response Tracker, Blavatnik School of <lb/>Government (2020); www.bsg.ox.ac.uk/research/research-<lb/>projects/coronavirus-government-response-tracker. <lb/>42. S. Abbott et al., Estimating the time-varying reproduction <lb/>number of SARS-CoV-2 using national and subnational case <lb/>counts. Wellcome Open Res. 5, 112 (2020). doi: 10.12688/ <lb/>wellcomeopenres.16006.2 <lb/>43. S. Yadav, P. K. Yadav, Basic reproduction rate and case fatality <lb/>rate of COVID-19: Application of meta-analysis. medRxiv <lb/>2020.05.13.20100750v1 [Preprint]. 16 May 2020. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1101/2020.05.13.20100750. <lb/>44. J. Wallinga, M. Lipsitch, How generation intervals shape the <lb/>relationship between growth rates and reproductive numbers. <lb/>Proc. Biol. Sci. 274, 599-604 (2007). doi: 10.1098/ <lb/>rspb.2006.3754; pmid: 17476782 <lb/>45. E. S. Fonfria et al., Essential epidemiological parameters of <lb/>COVID-19 for clinical and mathematical modeling purposes: A <lb/>rapid review and meta-analysis. medRxiv <lb/>2020.06.17.20133587v1 [Preprint]. 19 June 2020. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1101/2020.06.17.20133587. <lb/>46. M. D. Hoffman, A. Gelman, The No-U-Turn Sampler: Adaptively <lb/>setting path lengths in Hamiltonian Monte Carlo. J. Mach. <lb/>Learn. Res. 15, 1593-1623 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We thank J. Lagerros for operational support and for introducing <lb/>some of the authors to each other. We thank M. Balatsko, <lb/>M. Pukaj, and T. Witzany for developing the interactive website. We <lb/>thank T. Groemer, G. Krönke, and M. Herrmann for advice and <lb/>mentorship.</div>

            <div type="funding">Funding: J.M.B. was supported by the EPSRC Centre <lb/>for Doctoral Training in Autonomous Intelligent Machines and <lb/>Systems (EP/S024050/1) and by Cancer Research UK. S.M.&apos;s <lb/>funding for graduate studies was from Oxford University and <lb/>DeepMind. M.S. was supported by the EPSRC Centre for Doctoral <lb/>Training in Autonomous Intelligent Machines and Systems <lb/>(EP/S024050/1). G.L. was supported by the UKRI Centre for <lb/>Doctoral Training in Interactive Artificial Intelligence (EP/S022937/ <lb/>1). V.M. contributed in his personal time while employed at <lb/>DeepMind. L.C. acknowledges funding from the MRC Centre for <lb/>Global Infectious Disease Analysis (MR/R015600/1), jointly <lb/>funded by the U.K. Medical Research Council (MRC) and the <lb/>U.K. Foreign, Commonwealth and Development Office (FCDO), <lb/>under the MRC/FCDO Concordat agreement; is part of the <lb/>EDCTP2 program supported by the European Union; and <lb/>acknowledges funding by Community Jameel. Y.W.T. is also <lb/>a principal research scientist at DeepMind. The paid contractor <lb/>work helping with the data collection, the development of the <lb/>interactive website, and the costs for cloud computing were <lb/>funded by the Berkeley Existential Risk Initiative.</div>

            <div type="annex">Author <lb/>contributions: D.J., J.M.B., J.K., G.A., A.J.N., J.T.M., G.L., and <lb/>V.M. designed and conducted the NPI data collection. S.M., <lb/>M.S., J.M.B., A.B.S., H.G., Y.W.T., Y.G., J.K., T.G., J.S., V.M., <lb/>M.A.H., and L.C. designed the model and modeling experiments. <lb/>M.S., A.B.S., T.G., and J.S. performed and analyzed the modeling <lb/>experiments. J.M.B., S.M., M.S., J.K., and T.G. conceived of <lb/>the research. S.M., M.S., J.M.B., L.C., J.K., and T.B. did the <lb/>literature search. J.M.B., S.M., M.S., G.L., L.C., T.B., and V.M. <lb/>wrote the manuscript. All authors read and gave feedback on <lb/>the manuscript and approved the final manuscript. J.M.B., <lb/>S.M., and M.S. contributed equally. L.C., Y.G., and J.K. <lb/>contributed equally to senior authorship.</div>

            <div type="annex">Competing interests: <lb/>No conflicts of interests. L.C. has acted as a paid consultant to <lb/>Pfizer and the Foundation for Innovative New Diagnostics, <lb/>outside of the submitted work. Y.G. has received a research <lb/>grant (studentship) from GlaxoSmithKline, outside of the <lb/>submitted work. J.K. has advised several governmental and <lb/>nongovernmental entities about interventions against COVID-19. <lb/></div>

            <div type="availability">Data and materials availability: All data and code are available <lb/>in the paper or publicly online at (14).</div>

            <front>This work is licensed <lb/>under a Creative Commons Attribution 4.0 International (CC BY <lb/>4.0) license, which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is <lb/>properly cited. To view a copy of this license, visit https:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/. This license does not <lb/>apply to figures/photos/artwork or other content included in <lb/>the article that is credited to a third party; obtain authorization <lb/>from the rights holder before using such material. <lb/></front>

			<div type="annex">SUPPLEMENTARY MATERIALS <lb/>science.sciencemag.org/content/371/6531/eabd9338/suppl/DC1 <lb/>Supplementary Text <lb/>Figs. S1 to S24 <lb/>Tables S1 to S8 <lb/>References (47-79) <lb/>MDAR Reproducibility Checklist <lb/>21 July 2020; resubmitted 25 September 2020 <lb/>Accepted 8 December 2020 <lb/>Published online 15 December 2020 <lb/>10.1126/science.abd9338 <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Brauner et al., Science 371, eabd9338 (2021) <lb/>19 February 2021 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RESEARCH | RESEARCH ARTICLE </note>


	</text>
</tei>
