<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety and depression in myocardial<lb/> infarction patients<lb/> Ingvor Johansson a , Björn W. Karlson b , Gunne Grankvist c , Eva Brink d,e, ⁎<lb/> a Department of Internal Medicine, NU Hospital group, Sweden<lb/> b Astra Zeneca R&amp;D, Mölndal, Sweden<lb/> c Department of Social and Behavioural Studies, University West, Sweden<lb/> d Department of Nursing, Health and Culture, University West, Sweden<lb/> e Institute of Health and Care Sciences, The Sahlgrenska Academy at University of Gothenburg, Sweden<lb/> Received 17 April 2009; received in revised form 4 November 2009; accepted 15 December 2009<lb/> Available online 13 January 2010<lb/> Abstract<lb/> Background: Disturbed sleep has been linked to increased morbidity, mortality and depression and worsened health-related quality of life in<lb/> patients with chronic illness. Few studies of readjustment after coronary artery disease have explicitly focused on sleep disturbance.<lb/> Aim: To explore associations between disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety and depression, and to assess to what extent fatigue four months post-<lb/>MI could be explained.<lb/> Method: The sample included 204 consecutive patients, ≤ 80 years of age who answered questionnaires about disturbed sleep, fatigue,<lb/> anxiety and depression four months after MI.<lb/> Results: The variables anxiety, depression and disturbed sleep were all associated with fatigue. The regression model accounted for 46% of<lb/> the variance in fatigue with depression and disturbed sleep as predictors. Infarct size measured by conventional biochemical markers, left<lb/> ventricle ejection fraction and history of previous MI were not correlated with disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety or depression.<lb/> Conclusions: From knowledge about associations between disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety and depression after MI, cardiac nurses could be<lb/> trained to observe such symptoms. Optimal care for sleep disturbance may include actions to reduce anxiety and depression as well as self-<lb/>care advices about sleep hygiene in order to improve sleep quality and reduce fatigue.<lb/> © 2009 European Society of Cardiology. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/> Keywords: Anxiety; Depression; Disturbed sleep; Fatigue; Myocardial infarction<lb/> </front>
			
			<body>1. Introduction<lb/> Fatigue has been found to be a significant health<lb/> complaint in myocardial infarction (MI) patients [1–4],	as<lb/> well as something that is difficult to cope with [5]. A wide<lb/> range of definitions are found in the literature. Fatigue is a<lb/> multidimensional construct with components of general,<lb/> physical, and mental fatigue, as well as reduced activity and<lb/> motivation [6]. Fatigue can be distinguished from tiredness<lb/> by defining a continuum along which fatigue is a state<lb/> existing anywhere between the two poles tiredness and<lb/> exhaustion [7]. High rates of depression [8–10] and anxiety<lb/> [10,11] have been found among patients who have suffered<lb/> an MI. Fatigue and depression may be different expressions<lb/> of the same phenomenon [12,13], or they may tend to<lb/> overlap, as fatigue is a key symptom of depression [14,15].<lb/> Nevertheless, fatigue is sometimes experienced by myocar-<lb/>dial infarction patients without coexisting depression [3],<lb/> and therefore measures of physical components of fatigue<lb/> </body>
			
			<front>European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175 – 180<lb/> www.elsevier.com/locate/ejcnurse<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>⁎ Corresponding author. Institute of Health and Care Sciences, The<lb/> Sahlgrenska Academy at University of Gothenburg, Box 457, SE 405 30<lb/> Göteborg, Sweden. Tel.: +46 31 7866104.<lb/> E-mail address: eva.brink@gu.se (E. Brink).<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>1474-5151/$ -see front matter © 2009 European Society of Cardiology. Published by Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.ejcnurse.2009.12.003<lb/></front>
 			
			<body>could be valuable in combination with measures of<lb/> depression.<lb/> Adaptation after MI entails adjustment to illness con-<lb/>sequences [16,17], management of behavioural and lifestyle<lb/> changes [18,19] and a desire to return to normal [20].<lb/> Few studies of adaptation after MI have explicitly focused<lb/> on fatigue and sleep disturbance. Sleep disturbance refers to<lb/> an imbalance of sleep and wakefulness during a night of<lb/> sleep [21–23]. The mean sleep time for an adult, up to<lb/> 64 years of age, is about 7.5 h [24,25]. One study conducted<lb/> one year after percutaneous transluminal coronary angio-<lb/>plasty (PTCA) showed that physical tiredness/fatigue was<lb/> the greatest consequence of disturbed sleep [26]. A recent<lb/> interview study of patients with coronary artery disease<lb/> (CAD) revealed that personal lifestyle was reflected in sleep<lb/> behaviour, showing that maintaining a balance between<lb/> sleep, rest and activities resulted in better sleep quality [27].<lb/> Women report a higher prevalence of sleep disturbances<lb/> [23–25,28,29]. This is in line with results from studies on<lb/> women with CAD, who report sleep disturbances more<lb/> frequently than men do [30,31]. Sleeplessness behaviour,<lb/> depressed mood and female gender were associated with poor<lb/> sleep quality in CAD patients [32].<lb/> Disturbed sleep has been linked to increased morbidity<lb/> and mortality [33–35], depression [36,37], and worsened<lb/> health-related quality of life in patients with chronic illness<lb/> [38]. Poor prognosis has been described in MI or CAD<lb/> patients who have poor sleep quality [14], and there is an<lb/> increased risk for CAD in persons with disturbed sleep [39].<lb/> The negative effects of sleep disturbance on health,<lb/> together with frequent experiences of mental distress and<lb/> fatigue after MI, make it important to further explore this<lb/> field. Therefore, the present study had two primary aims: 1.<lb/> to explore associations between disturbed sleep, fatigue,<lb/> anxiety and depression four months after MI, and 2. to assess<lb/> to what extent fatigue four months post-MI could be<lb/> explained by disturbed sleep, anxiety and depression.<lb/> 2. Methods<lb/> 2.1. Subjects and procedures<lb/> The present study included MI patients, ≤80 years of age,<lb/> who had been admitted to the coronary care unit in two<lb/> Swedish hospital from October 2005 to September 2006, and<lb/> who participated in a longitudinal follow-up study of<lb/> readjustment one week and four months after MI. Excluded<lb/> were patients with other severe diseases and/or a greatly<lb/> limited life expectancy (e.g., due to cancer), patients who<lb/> were not able to participate (e.g., due to stroke and dementia<lb/> disorders) and patients who could not speak Swedish<lb/> fluently. Of the 236 invited patients, 204 (144 men, 60<lb/> women) agreed to participate (response rate 87%). Demo-<lb/>graphic and medical data were obtained from hospital charts<lb/> and from a questionnaire finalized during the first week in<lb/> hospital. The demographic data covered age, gender and<lb/> living alone or together. The medical data covered previous<lb/> diagnosis (hypertension, hyperlipedemia, angina pectoris,<lb/> previous MI, congestive heart failure, diabetes mellitus, and<lb/> left ventricular ejection fraction) and acute treatment (beta-<lb/>blocker medication, percutaneous coronary intervention<lb/> (PCI), coronary artery bypass graft surgery (CABG) and<lb/> thrombolysis. Infarct size was measured using the biochem-<lb/>ical marker Troponin I (TNI). Left ventricular ejection<lb/> fraction was measured using transthoracic echocardiography<lb/> and is presented in percent.<lb/> Four months after the MI, the patients answered<lb/> questionnaires about sleep disturbance, fatigue, anxiety and<lb/> depression.<lb/> The project was approved by the Research Ethics<lb/> Committee at the University of Gothenburg. The informants<lb/> gave their informed written consent to participate, and the<lb/> investigation conforms to the principles outlined in the<lb/> Declaration of Helsinki [40].<lb/> 2.2. Questionnaires<lb/> 2.2.1. Disturbed sleep<lb/> Initially, nine questions regarding sleep disturbance,<lb/> previously used as separate items in studies at Sahlgrenska<lb/> University Hospital, Sweden e.g., [41], and also found to be<lb/> included in the Karolinska Sleep Questionnaire (KSQ) [42],<lb/> were analysed. The nine items were tested for reliability to<lb/> form a scale. The inter-item correlations for all items were<lb/> not fully satisfactory. Therefore, in the first step, two of them<lb/> were excluded due to doubtful content (nightmares and<lb/> involuntary sleep episodes during day-time). The Cronbach<lb/> alpha coefficient for the scale with seven items was 0.80. In<lb/> the second step, we excluded two more items with low inter-<lb/>item correlations (difficulty waking and taking sleeping<lb/> pills). Cronbach&apos;s alpha coefficient increased to 0.83 and the<lb/> inter-item correlations were good and indicated that the<lb/> remaining five items could be summed to form a scale about<lb/> sleep disturbance after MI. The final 5 items included in the<lb/> questionnaire were related to disturbed or troubled sleep,<lb/> difficulties initiating sleep, repeated nocturnal awakenings<lb/> associated with difficulties returning to sleep, a feeling of<lb/> non-refreshing sleep upon awakening, and premature<lb/> awakening from sleep. Each question was answered using<lb/> a 6-point scale with scores from never (1) to always (6)<lb/> (range 5–30).<lb/> 2.2.2. Fatigue<lb/> Fatigue was measured using the Somatic Health Com-<lb/>plaints Questionnaire (SHCQ). This questionnaire addresses<lb/> 13 health issues concerning common health problems in<lb/> cardiac patients [43]. In the present study, the subscale<lb/> fatigue, consisting of the four items general fatigue,<lb/> weakness, lack of energy and dizziness, was used. Each<lb/> question was answered using a 6-point scale with scores<lb/> from never (1) to always (6) (range 4–24). The Cronbach&apos;s<lb/> alpha coefficient in the present sample was 0.87.<lb/> 						
			
			<page>176</page> 
			
			<note place="headnote">I. Johansson et al. / European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175–180<lb/></note> 
			
			2.2.3. Anxiety and depression<lb/> The Hospital-Anxiety Depression Scale (HAD) is a 14-item<lb/> questionnaire comprising two scales, one for anxiety (seven<lb/> questions) and one for depression (seven questions). All items<lb/> were scored on a 4-point scale from low anxiety/depression (0)<lb/> to high anxiety/depression (3) [44]. The HAD Scale was<lb/> developed for measuring mental distress in patients with<lb/> physical illness and has been found to be a reliable instrument<lb/> for detecting severity of emotional distress, with Cronbach&apos;s<lb/> alpha between 0.80 and 0.93 [45]. On either the anxiety or<lb/> depression subscale, a score of 7 or less is considered normal, a<lb/> score of 8–10 is considered to indicate possible and 11 or<lb/> higher to indicate probable psychological distress.<lb/> 2.3. Statistical analyses<lb/> The Statistical Package for the Social Sciences (SPSS) 15.0<lb/> was used. Descriptive statistics were calculated: mean (m) and<lb/> standard deviations (SD). Pearson&apos;s correlation coefficients (r)<lb/> were used to explore associations between variables. Gender<lb/> differences were tested using independent sample t-tests. To<lb/> identify variables that best predicted fatigue in myocardial<lb/> infarction patients, a multiple regression model was used with<lb/> sleep disturbance, anxiety, depression, gender and age as<lb/> independent variables. A p-value b 0.05 was considered sta-<lb/>tistically significant.<lb/> 3. Results<lb/> 3.1. Demographic data<lb/> Table 1 shows the characteristics of the participating<lb/> patients, including medical information. The mean age was<lb/> 64 years (SD = 10, range 31–80) and 30% were women. One<lb/> fourth of the sample had a diagnosis of at least one previous<lb/> MI. Only 7% suffered from congestive heart failure, and<lb/> nearly one fourth were hyperlipidemic. The acute treatment<lb/> included CABG in 7% and PCI in 70% of the sample.<lb/> 3.2. Disturbed sleep<lb/> Means, SDs and ranges for disturbed sleep measured as<lb/> described above are displayed in Table 2. The theoretical ranges<lb/> of scale scores were well covered by the observed scores for all<lb/> four scales. A gender difference was identified; women<lb/> reported more disturbed sleep (p b 0.05). Difficulties falling<lb/> asleep during the past week were reported by 21% of the<lb/> individuals four months after the MI. A feeling of non-<lb/>refreshing sleep upon awakening was the most common sleep<lb/> complaint (Table 3). Of all patients, 55% reported sleep<lb/> disturbance sometimes to always, 45% reported almost no sleep<lb/> disturbance at all, and 79% did not use any sleep medication.<lb/> 3.3. Fatigue<lb/> One third of the MI patients reported fatigue often to<lb/> always (summed SHCQ scale scores between 13 and 24),<lb/> one third reported fatigue sometimes, and 35% experienced<lb/> hardly any fatigue at all. No difference between women and<lb/> men was identified (Table 2).<lb/> 3.4. Anxiety and depression<lb/> According to the HAD scale, one fourth of the MI patients<lb/> scored possible or probable anxiety, and 20% scored<lb/> possible or probable depression. Regarding anxiety a<lb/> difference between women and men was identified (Table 2).<lb/> 3.5. Associations between variables<lb/> Infarct size measured using conventional biochemical<lb/> markers, left ventricular ejection fraction and history of<lb/> Table 1<lb/> Demographic and medical information (n = 204).<lb/> Gender (% woman)<lb/> 30 Age m (SD)<lb/> 64 (10)<lb/> Married/living together (%)<lb/> 68.1<lb/> Medical history:<lb/> Hypertension (%)<lb/> 36.1<lb/> Hyperlipidemia (%)<lb/> 23.5<lb/> Angina pectoris (%)<lb/> 13.2<lb/> Previous MI (%)<lb/> 23.4<lb/> Congestive heart failure (%)<lb/> 7.3<lb/> Ejection fraction % m (SD))<lb/> 48 (11)<lb/> Diabetes mellitus (%)<lb/> 21.5<lb/> Acute treatment:<lb/> Beta-blocker (%)<lb/> 79.5<lb/> PCI (%)<lb/> 70.2<lb/> CABG (%)<lb/> 7.3<lb/> Trombolysis (%)<lb/> 2<lb/> PCI, Percutaneous Coronary Intervention; CABG coronary artery bypass<lb/> graft surgery.<lb/> Table 2<lb/> Means (SD) for measured variables and gender comparisons by t-tests.<lb/> Variable Total<lb/> n = 204<lb/> Women n = 60<lb/> Men n = 144<lb/> Theoretical range<lb/> Observed range<lb/> Disturbed sleep<lb/> 11.99 (5.04)<lb/> 13.28 (5.42) a<lb/> 11.44 (4.80)<lb/> 5–30<lb/> 5–28<lb/> Anxiety 4.86 (3.81)<lb/> 5.92 (3.96) a<lb/> 4.42 (3.67)<lb/> 0–21<lb/> 0–15<lb/> Depression 4.45 (3.62)<lb/> 4.64 (3.55)<lb/> 4.38 (3.67)<lb/> 0–21<lb/> 0–19<lb/> Fatigue 10.56 (4.49)<lb/> 11.20 (4.93)<lb/> 10.30 (4.28)<lb/> 4–24<lb/> 4–24<lb/> a Difference is significant at the .05 level (2-tailed).<lb/> 
			
			<page>177</page>  
			
			<note place="headnote">I. Johansson et al. / European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175–180<lb/> </note>
			
			previous MI were not significantly correlated with disturbed<lb/> sleep, fatigue, anxiety or depression. The variables disturbed<lb/> sleep, anxiety and depression were all associated with fatigue<lb/> (Table 4).<lb/> To further explore these associations, a regression model<lb/> was analysed with fatigue as the dependent variable and<lb/> disturbed sleep, anxiety and depression as independent<lb/> variables, controlling for age and gender. The regression<lb/> model accounted for 46% of the variance in fatigue, with<lb/> depression and disturbed sleep as strong predictors.<lb/> Additionally, age, but not gender, was related to fatigue<lb/> (Table 5).<lb/> 4. Discussion<lb/> Four months after the acute heart attack, one third of the<lb/> patients reported fatigue sometimes too often. Also, around<lb/> 20% reported sleep disturbance. Medical variables such as<lb/> enzymatically estimated infarct size or left ventricular ejection<lb/> fraction were not related to the individuals&apos; experience of<lb/> fatigue. However, our findings showing relationships between<lb/> disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety and depression point out that<lb/> these aspects are important in rehabilitation care, especially<lb/> with aging people. In a multiple regression model analysis, it<lb/> was found that both depression and disturbed sleep explained a<lb/> great deal of the variance in fatigue.<lb/> Many individuals who have suffered an MI report fatigue<lb/> prior to the acute heart event [46], and many patients report<lb/> fatigue after MI [5,47,48]. The prevalence of fatigue in CAD<lb/> patients tends to be higher among women [3,32] and is linked<lb/> to increased prevalence of depression and anxiety [3,15].<lb/> Fatigue has been found to be associated with subjective sleep<lb/> quality in the general population [15] and fragmented sleep in<lb/> CAD patients [26]. Also, poor prognosis in female coronary<lb/> patients was associated with poor sleep and sleep without a<lb/> restorative function [49]. In the present study, we identified<lb/> some gender differences; women reported more anxiety and<lb/> disturbed sleep, but did not report higher rates of fatigue.<lb/> In the literature, there are several terms for an individual&apos;s<lb/> report of difficulty with sleep. Commonly used concepts are<lb/> insomnia and disturbed sleep, both including for example<lb/> difficulty falling asleep, problems with staying asleep and/or<lb/> non-restorative sleep [50,51]. Nevertheless, measures of<lb/> insomnia and disturbed sleep vary across studies, and<lb/> therefore it may be difficult to compare the results. About<lb/> 18% of the general population report sleep dissatisfaction<lb/> [29,52], and this proportion is in line with that found among<lb/> the individuals who have suffered an MI in the present study<lb/> and in a former study of MI patients [2]. In the present study,<lb/> one problem associated with identifying disturbed sleep due<lb/> to the heart attack itself is that we do not know the prevalence<lb/> of impaired sleep before the MI. However, one possible<lb/> reflection is that sleep disturbance after MI may be<lb/> associated with the illness. Due to anxiety and worries<lb/> about illness consequences, insomnia problems may occur.<lb/> Physical functioning may be reduced, implying decreased<lb/> physical activity and exercise, which in turn may negatively<lb/> influence sleep quality. Also, experiences of fatigue may<lb/> lead to day-time rests or naps, which in turn may influence<lb/> the quality of night-time sleep.<lb/> To our knowledge, no previous studies have evaluated the<lb/> effects of any treatment on disturbed sleep among post-MI<lb/> patients. Individuals with insomnia are more likely to have a<lb/> major depressive illness [29]. When depression is the main<lb/> cause of sleep disturbance, anti-depressive therapy might be<lb/> required. Individuals who were distressed in the hospital<lb/> experienced lowered health-related quality of life four<lb/> months [53] and one year after MI [11], and therefore, in-<lb/>hospital identification and treatment of anxiety and depres-<lb/>sion could be of benefit to patients&apos; prognosis. Nurses should<lb/> increase their awareness regarding anxiety, depression and<lb/> fatigue as well as regarding the impact of sleep disturbance<lb/> on health and well-being. Johansson et al. [27] concluded<lb/> that it is important to identify patients&apos; needs, symptoms and<lb/> self-care strategies regarding impaired sleep.<lb/> 4.1. Limitations<lb/> One limitation of the present study was that sleep<lb/> disturbance was not examined before MI, and thus we<lb/> cannot determine whether these problems were new and due<lb/> to illness consequences. The results only reflect the situation<lb/> Table 3<lb/> Prevalence of disturbed sleep (from several times to always).<lb/> Items of sleep disturbance (n = 204)<lb/> %<lb/> 1. Difficulties initiating sleep<lb/> 21 2. Repeated nocturnal awakenings that were associated<lb/> with difficulties returning to sleep<lb/> 21<lb/> 3. A feeling of non-refreshing sleep upon awakening<lb/> 23 4. Premature awakening from sleep<lb/> 19 5. Disturbed or troubled sleep<lb/> 18<lb/> Table 4<lb/> Correlations between variables (n = 204).<lb/> Variables Fatigue<lb/> Disturbed sleep<lb/> Anxiety Depression<lb/> Fatigue –<lb/> Disturbed sleep<lb/> .466 a<lb/> –<lb/> Anxiety .403 a<lb/> .535 a<lb/> –<lb/> Depression .643 a<lb/> .455 a<lb/> .628 a<lb/> –<lb/> a Correlation is significant at the .01 level (2-tailed).<lb/> Table 5<lb/> Regression model with fatigue as dependent variable, adj. R 2 = 0.46 (n = 204).<lb/> Variables B<lb/> p<lb/> Disturbed sleep<lb/> .269<lb/> b.001<lb/> Anxiety − .028<lb/> .199<lb/> Depression .182<lb/> b.001<lb/> Gender − .121<lb/> .332<lb/> Age .014<lb/> .021<lb/> 
			
			<page>178</page> 
			
			<note place="headnote">I. Johansson et al. / European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175–180<lb/></note>

			four months after an MI. It might be worthwhile to perform a<lb/> prolonged follow-up for several years. Such a study could<lb/> provide the opportunity to estimate the medical risks and<lb/> morbidity resulting from sleep disturbance post-MI, and the<lb/> possible beneficial effects of a well-performed nursing inter-<lb/>vention intended to increase sleep quality. Regarding the few<lb/> identified gender differences in the present study, the small<lb/> sample size of women could have camouflaged such differ-<lb/>ences. However, to guarantee satisfactory representatively,<lb/> we performed the data collection during a period of one<lb/> year and included every consecutive patient admitted to a<lb/> rural coronary care unit with a diagnosis of an acute MI.<lb/> This procedure resulted in more male participants due to<lb/> the difference in incidence of MI between men and wom-<lb/>en ≤80 years of age.<lb/> The items used for assessing disturbed sleep in the present<lb/> study reflect a basis for insomnia symptoms that did not<lb/> include an obstructive sleep apnea (OSA) evaluation.<lb/> Coronary heart disease has been associated with OSA. A<lb/> high prevalence of OSA in patients with acute myocardial<lb/> infarction has been identified [54]. Some of the participants<lb/> in our sample may have suffered from problems with sleep<lb/> apnea causing depression, fatigue and non-restorative sleep,<lb/> while others may have experienced disturbed sleep for other<lb/> reasons. The item &quot;a feeling of non-refreshing sleep upon<lb/> awakening&quot; was the most common sleep complaint (reported<lb/> by 23% of the respondents), which could be a sign of OSA.<lb/> In future research, this distinction should be accounted for.<lb/> 5. Conclusion<lb/> Associations between sleep disturbance, fatigue, anxiety<lb/> and depression were identified. Infarct size measured using<lb/> conventional biochemical markers, left ventricle ejection<lb/> fraction and history of previous MI were not correlated with<lb/> disturbed sleep, fatigue, anxiety or depression. Thus, psycho-<lb/>social symptoms and needs are important to recognize owing to<lb/> their influence on health and well-being. Based on knowledge<lb/> about associations between disturbed sleep, fatigue and<lb/> psychological distress such as anxiety and depression, cardiac<lb/> nurses could be trained to observe such symptoms. Optimal<lb/> care of sleep disturbance may include measures to reduce<lb/> anxiety and depression as well as self-care advice on sleep<lb/> hygiene intended to improve sleep quality and reduce fatigue.<lb/> 
			
			</body>
			
			<back>
			
			<listBibl>
				References<lb/> 
				
				[1] Appels A. Exhaustion and coronary heart disease: the history of a<lb/> scientific quest. Patient Educ Couns 2004;55:223–9.<lb/> [2] Brink E, Karlson BW, Hallberg LRM. Health experiences of first-time<lb/> myocardial infarction: factors influencing women&apos;s and men&apos;s health-<lb/>related quality of life after five months. Psychol Health Med 2002;7:5–16.<lb/> [3] Mc Gowan L, Dickens C, Percival C, Douglas J, Tomenson B, Creed<lb/> F. The relationship between vital exhaustion, depression and comorbid<lb/> illnesses in patients following first myocardial infarction. J Psychosom<lb/> Res 2004;57:183–8.<lb/> [4] Varvaro F, Zullo TG, Robertson RJ. Fatigue in women with myocardial<lb/> infarction. Health Care Women Int 1996;17:593–602.<lb/> [5] Alsén P, Brink E, Persson L-O. Living with incomprehensive fatigue<lb/> after myocardial infarction. J Adv Nurs 2008;64(5):459–68.<lb/> [6] Smets EM, Garssen B, Bonke B, De Haes JC. The Multidimensional<lb/> Fatigue Inventory (MFI) psychometric qualities of an instrument to<lb/> assess fatigue. J Psychosom Res 1995;39(3):315–25.<lb/> [7] Olson K. A new way of thinking about fatigue: a reconceptualization.<lb/> Oncol Nurs Forum 2007;34(1):93–9.<lb/> [8] Frasure-Smith N, Lespérance F, Gravel G, Masson A, Juneau M,<lb/> Talajic M, et al. Social support, depression, and mortality during the<lb/> first year after myocardial infarction. Circulation 2000;101:1919–24.<lb/> [9] Grace S, Abbey SE, Irvine J, Shnek ZM, Stewart DE. Prospective<lb/> examination of anxiety percistence and its relationship to cardiac symp-<lb/>toms and recurrent cardiac events. Psychother Psychosom 2004;73:<lb/> 344–52.<lb/> [10] Strik J, Denollet J, Lousberg R, Honing A. Comparing symptoms of<lb/> depression and anxiety as predictors of cardiac events and increased<lb/> health care consumption after myocardial infarction. J Am Coll Cardiol<lb/> 2003;42:1801–7.<lb/> [11] Mayou RA, Gill D, Thompson DR, Nicholas AD, Volmink J, Neil A.<lb/> Depression and anxiety as predictors of outcome after myocardial<lb/> infarction. Psychosom Med 2000;62:212–9.<lb/> [12] Dickens CM, McGowan L, Percival C, Tomensson B, Cottter L,<lb/> Heagerty A, et al. Contribution of depression and anxiety to impaired<lb/> health-related quality of life following first myocardial infarction. Br J<lb/> Psychiatry 2006;189:367–72.<lb/> [13] Wojciechowski FL, Strik JJ, Falger P, Lousberg R, Honig A. The<lb/> relationship between depressive and vital exhaustion symptomatology<lb/> post-myocardial infarction. Acta Phychiatr Scand 2000;102:359–65.<lb/> [14] Irvine J, Basinski A, Baker B, Jandciu S, Paquette M, Cairns J, et al.<lb/> Depression and risk of sudden death after acute myocardial infarction:<lb/> testing for the confounding effects of fatigue. Psycosom Med 1999;61:<lb/> 729–37.<lb/> [15] Lavidor M, Weller A, Babkoff H. How sleep is related to fatigue. B J<lb/> Health Psychol 2003;8:95–105.<lb/> [16] Brink E. Adaptation positions and behaviour among post-myocardial<lb/> infarction patients. Clin Nurs Res 2009;18(2):119–35.<lb/> [17] Jensen B, Petersson K. The illness experiences of patients after a first<lb/> time myocardial infarction. Patient Educ Couns 2003;51(2):123–31.<lb/> [18] Kristofferzon M-L, Löfmark R, Carlsson M. Managing conse-<lb/>quences and finding hope — experiences of Swedish women and<lb/> men 4–6 months after myocardial infarction. Scand J Caring Sci<lb/> 2008;22(3):367–75.<lb/> [19] Sutherland B, Jensen J. Living with change: elderly women&apos;s per-<lb/>ceptions of having a myocardial infarction. Qual Health Res 2000;10:<lb/> 661–76.<lb/> [20] Tobin B. Getting back to normal: women&apos;s recovery after a myocardial<lb/> infarction. Canadian J Cardiovasc Nurs 2000;11:11–9.<lb/> [21] American Psychiatric Association. Diagnostic and Statistical Manual<lb/> of Mental Disorders. DSM-IV-TR. Fourth Edition. Washington, DC:<lb/> American Psychiatric Association; 2000.<lb/> [22] Parmeggiani PJ. Brain cooling across wake-sleep behavioral states in<lb/> homeothermic species: an analysis of the underlying physiological<lb/> mechanisms. Rev Neurosci 1995;6:353–63.<lb/> [23] Åkerstedt T, Nilsson PM. Sleep as restitution: an introduction. J Intern<lb/> Med 2003;254:6–12.<lb/> [24] Groeger JA, Zijlstra FRH, Dijk D-J. Sleep quality, sleep difficulties<lb/> and their perceived consequences in a representative sample of some<lb/> 2000 British adults. J Sleep Res 2004;13:359–71.<lb/> [25] National Sleep Foundation. Sleep in America Poll. http://www.<lb/>sleepfoundation .org. 2007.<lb/> [26] Edéll-Gustafsson UM, Hetta JE. Fragmented sleep and tiredness in<lb/> males and females one year after percutaneous transluminal coronary<lb/> angioplasty (PTCA). J Adv Nurs 2001;34:203–11.<lb/> [27] Johansson A, Windahl M, Svanborg E, Fredrichsen M, Swahn E, Yngman<lb/> Uhlin P, et al. Perceptions of how sleep is influenced by rest, activity and<lb/> health in patients with coronary heart disease: a phenomenographical<lb/> study. Scand J Caring Sci 2007;21:467–75.<lb/> 

			<page>179</page>

			<note place="headnote">I. Johansson et al. / European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175–180<lb/> </note> 
			
			[28] Asplund R. Sleep and hypnotic use in relation to perceived somatic and<lb/> mental health among the elderly. Arch Geronto Geriatr 2000;31:<lb/> 199–205.<lb/> [29] Ohayon MM. Epidemiology of insomnia: what we know and what we<lb/> still need to learn. Sleep Med Rev 2002;6:97–111.<lb/> [30] Bengtson A, Karlsson T, Herlitz J. Differences between men and<lb/> women on the waiting list for coronary revascularization. J Adv Nurs<lb/> 2000;31(6):1361–7.<lb/> [31] Billing E, Eriksson SV, Hjemdahl P, Rehnqvist N. Psychosocial<lb/> variables in relation to various risk factors in patients with stable<lb/> angina pectoris. J Intern Med 2000;247(2):240–8.<lb/> [32] Edéll-Gustafsson U, Svanborg E, Swahn E. A gender perspective on<lb/> sleeplessness behavior, effects of sleep loss, and coping resources in<lb/> patients with stable coronary artery disease. Heart Lung 2006;35:75–89.<lb/> [33] Brabbins CJ, Dewey ME, Copeland JRM, Davidson IA, McWilliam C,<lb/> Saunders P, et al. Insomnia in the elderly: prevalence, gender<lb/> differences and relationship with morbidity and mortality. Int J Geriatr<lb/> Psychiatry 1993;8:473–80.<lb/> [34] Mallon L, Broman J-E, Hetta J. Relationship between insomnia,<lb/> depression, and mortality: A 12-years follow-up of older adults in the<lb/> community. Int Psychogeriatr 2000;12(3):295–306.<lb/> [35] Phillips B, Mannino DM. Does insomnia kill? Sleep 2005;28:965–71.<lb/> [36] Lustberg L, Reynolds CF. Depression and insomnia: questions of<lb/> cause and effect. Sleep Med 2000;4:253–62.<lb/> [37] Carney RM, Freedland KE, Miller GE, Jaffe AS. Depression as a risk<lb/> factor for cardiac mortality and morbidity: a review of potential mech-<lb/>anisms. J Psychosom Res 2002;53:897–902.<lb/> [38] Katz DA, McHorney CA. The relationship between insomnia and<lb/> health-related quality of life in patients with chronic illness. J Fam<lb/> Pract 2002;51(3):229–35.<lb/> [39] Schwartz S, McDowell Anderson W, Cole SR, Cornoni-Huntley J, Hays<lb/> JC, Blazer D. Insomnia and heart disease: a review of epidemiological<lb/> studies. J Psychosom Res 1999;47:313–30.<lb/> [40] The World Medical Association. Declaration of Helsinki. World Med J<lb/> 2008;54:122–5.<lb/> [41] Karlson BW, Wiklund I, Bengtson A, Herlitz J. Prognosis, severity of<lb/> symptoms, and aspects of well-being for patients in whom myocardial<lb/> infarction was ruled out. Clin Cardiol 1994;17:427–31.<lb/> [42] Åkerstedt T, Knutsson A, Westerholm P, Theorell T, Alfredsson L,<lb/> Kecklund G. Sleep disturbances, work stress and work hours. A cross-<lb/>sectional study. J Psychosom Res 2002;53:741–8.<lb/> [43] Brink E, Cliffordson C, Herlitz J, Karlson BW. Dimensions of the<lb/> Somatic Health Complaints Questionnaire (SHCQ) in a sample of<lb/> myocardial infarction patients. Eur J Cardiovasc Nurs 2007;6(1):27–31.<lb/> [44] Zigmond AS, Snaith RP. The Hospital Anxiety and Depression Scale.<lb/> Acta Psychiatr Scand 1983;67:361–70.<lb/> [45] Herrmann C. International experiences with the hospital anxiety and<lb/> depression scale — a review of validation data and clinical results.<lb/> J Psychosom Res 1997;42:17–41.<lb/> [46] Appels A, Kop WJ, Schouten E. The nature of the depressive symp-<lb/>tomatology preceding myocardial infarction. Behav Med 2000;26:86–9.<lb/> [47] Crane PB. Fatigue and physical activity in older women after myo-<lb/>cardial infarction. Heart Lung 2005;34:30–8.<lb/> [48] Brink E, Grankvist G. Associations between depression, fatigue and<lb/> life orientation in myocardial infarction patients. J Cardiovasc Nurs<lb/> 2006;21(5):407–11.<lb/> [49] Leineweber C, Kecklund G, Janszky, Åkerstedt T, Orth-Gomér K.<lb/> Poor sleep increases the prospective risk for recurrent events in middle<lb/> aged women with coronary disease. The Stockholm female coronary<lb/> risk study. J Psychosom Res 2003;54:121–7.<lb/> [50] Keklund G, Åkerstedt T. Objective components of individual differ-<lb/>ences in subjective sleep quality. J Sleep Res 1997;6:217–20.<lb/> [51] Roth T. Insomnia: definition, prevalence, etiology, and consequences.<lb/> J Clin Sleep Med 2007;3(5):7–10.<lb/> [52] Asplund R, Åberg H. Sleep and cardiac symptoms amongst women<lb/> aged 40–64 years. J Intern Med 1998;243:209–13.<lb/> [53] Lane D, Carroll D, Ring C, Beevers G, Lip G. Effects of depression<lb/> and anxiety on mortality and quality-of-life 4 months after myocardial<lb/> infarction. J Psychosom Res 2000;49:229–38.<lb/> [54] Lee CH, Khoo SM, Chong EY, Lau C, Than Y, Shi DX, et al. Obstructive<lb/> sleep apnea in patients admitted for acute myocardial infarction. Prev-<lb/>alence, predictors, and effect on microvascular perfusion. Chest 2009;135:<lb/> 1488–95.<lb/> </listBibl>
			
			<page>180</page>
			
			<note place="headnote">I. Johansson et al. / European Journal of Cardiovascular Nursing 9 (2010) 175–180</note>
			
			</back>

	</text>
</tei>
