<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="-1"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>A hierarchical model for the relationships between general and specific<lb/> vulnerability factors and symptom levels of generalized anxiety disorder<lb/> Colin van der Heiden a,b, *, Kim Melchior a,b , Peter Muris b , S. Bouwmeester b , Arjan E.R. Bos c ,<lb/> Henk T. van der Molen b<lb/> a Outpatient Treatment Center PsyQ, Rotterdam, The Netherlands<lb/> b Institute of Psychology, Erasmus University Rotterdam, The Netherlands<lb/> c Faculty of Psychology and Neuroscience, Maastricht University, The Netherlands<lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction<lb/> Generalized anxiety disorder (GAD) is among the most common<lb/> mental health problems, with an estimated 12-month prevalence<lb/> of 3.1% and a life-time prevalence of 5.1% (American Psychiatric<lb/> Association [APA], 2000). GAD is characterized by excessive<lb/> anxiety and uncontrollable worry about several problematic issues<lb/> for at least 6 months (APA, 2000), that leads to severe distress and<lb/> functional impairments (Yonkers, Warshaw, Massion, &amp; Keller,<lb/> 1996). Some authors have referred to GAD as the &apos;&apos;basic anxiety<lb/> disorder&apos;&apos;, suggesting that a better understanding of the etiological<lb/> factors for GAD may also increase our knowledge about the origins<lb/> of other anxiety disorders, and perhaps unipolar mood disorders as<lb/> well (Mineka, Yovel, &amp; Pineles, 2002; Roemer, Orsillo, &amp; Barlow,<lb/> 2002).<lb/> As to the etiology of GAD, it has been proposed that the general<lb/> vulnerability factor of neuroticism plays a prominent role (Mineka,<lb/> Watson, &amp; Clark, 1998). This notion is mainly based on research<lb/> that examined the relationship between neuroticism and emo-<lb/>tional disorders, which has demonstrated that there are clear-cut<lb/> positive associations between this personality trait and all anxiety<lb/> disorders (Brown, Chorpita, &amp; Barlow, 1998; Clark &amp; Watson, 1991;<lb/> Watson, 2005), with the link to GAD emerging as the strongest<lb/> (Kotov, Watson, Robles, &amp; Schmidt, 2007). However, critics have<lb/> argued that neuroticism can better be viewed as a universal<lb/> concomitant of abnormal functioning that by itself has little<lb/> explanatory value (Claridge &amp; Davis, 2001; Ormel, Rosmalen, &amp;<lb/> Farmer, 2004). Further, it has been pointed out that (high)<lb/> neuroticism and GAD seem to refer to a similar construct (Hettema,<lb/> Prescott, &amp; Kendler, 2004), which is supported by studies<lb/> indicating that neuroticism is hardly distinguishable from chronic<lb/> worry, the key feature of GAD (Kotov et al., 2007; Mineka et al.,<lb/> 1998; Watson, 1999; Watson, Gamez, &amp; Simms, 2005). Thus,<lb/> although it is generally assumed that neuroticism is involved in<lb/> various emotional problems, little is known about the precise<lb/> mechanisms by which neuroticism exerts its influence on specific<lb/> syndromes. The examination of such mechanisms can be justified<lb/> because their identification might lead to the development of more<lb/> effective treatment methods.<lb/> In an attempt to conceptualize the role of neuroticism in GAD<lb/> and other emotional disorders in a more satisfactory way, several<lb/> authors have proposed hierarchical models for the vulnerability of<lb/> these problems. Such models imply that neuroticism should be<lb/> regarded as a higher order vulnerability factor, while there are<lb/> more specific second-order factors that intermediate between this<lb/> basic personality trait and various manifestations of emotional<lb/> problems (Taylor, 1998). Empirical tests of such models have<lb/> </body>

			<front>Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </front>
			
			<front>A R T I C L E I N F O<lb/> Article history:<lb/> Received 10 July 2009<lb/> Received in revised form 11 December 2009<lb/> Accepted 11 December 2009<lb/> Keywords:<lb/> Generalized anxiety disorder<lb/> Hierarchical model<lb/> Neuroticism Metacognitions<lb/> Intolerance of uncertainty<lb/> Worry<lb/> A B S T R A C T<lb/> The present study examined a hierarchical model for the relationships between general and specific<lb/> vulnerability factors and symptom manifestations of generalized anxiety disorder (GAD). A clinical<lb/> sample of patients with GAD (N = 137) completed a set of self-report questionnaires for measuring<lb/> neuroticism, extraversion, intolerance of uncertainty, metacognitive beliefs, and symptoms of<lb/> generalized anxiety (i.e., worry) and depression. A bootstrapping analysis yielded support for a model<lb/> in which the relation between the general vulnerability factor of neuroticism and symptoms of GAD<lb/> were mediated by the specific vulnerability factors of intolerance of uncertainty and negative<lb/> metacognitions. Implications for the classification and treatment of GAD are discussed.<lb/> ß 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/></front>

			<front>* Corresponding author at: PsyQ, Van Vollenhovenstraat 3 (2nd floor), 3016 BE<lb/> Rotterdam, The Netherlands. Tel.: +31 88 0013991; fax: +31 88 0013999.<lb/> E-mail address: c.vanderheiden@psyq.nl (C. van der Heiden).<lb/> Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/> Journal of Anxiety Disorders<lb/> 0887-6185/$ – see front matter ß 2009 Elsevier Ltd. All rights reserved.<lb/> doi:10.1016/j.janxdis.2009.12.005<lb/></front>

			<body>yielded interesting results. For example, Norton and Mehta (2007),<lb/> Norton, Sexton, Walker, and Norton (2005), and Sexton, Norton,<lb/> Walker, and Norton (2003) tested a hierarchical model in which<lb/> anxiety sensitivity (AS), the tendency to be afraid of physical<lb/> anxiety symptoms based on the belief that they have negative<lb/> consequences (McNally, 1999), and intolerance of uncertainty (IU),<lb/> a dispositional characteristic which results from a set of negative<lb/> beliefs about uncertainty and its implications (Dugas &amp; Robichaud,<lb/> 2007), were included as second-order factors. They found AS and<lb/> IU to differentially mediate between the higher order factor of<lb/> neuroticism, and symptoms of various anxiety and mood<lb/> disorders. With regard to GAD, IU but not AS was found to<lb/> partially mediate between neuroticism and worry, the core<lb/> symptom of this anxiety disorder. Interestingly, IU also emerged<lb/> as a partial mediator in a model explaining depressive symptoms<lb/> (Norton &amp; Mehta, 2007; Norton et al., 2005). Further, results<lb/> indicated that another higher order factor, i.e., extraversion, made<lb/> a significant direct contribution to the model of depressive<lb/> symptoms, but not to the model explaining worry, which suggests<lb/> that this basic personality factor might play a differential role in<lb/> the etiology of GAD and depression (Clark, Watson, &amp; Mineka,<lb/> 1994; Goldberg, 2008; Mineka et al., 1998).<lb/> Although previous studies have provided insight in the<lb/> hierarchical model of vulnerability for anxiety disorders and<lb/> depression (Norton &amp; Mehta, 2007; Norton et al., 2005; Sexton<lb/> et al., 2003), no definitive conclusions can be drawn with regard to<lb/> GAD because the research conducted so far suffers from a number<lb/> of limitations. First of all, few clinical patients with GAD have been<lb/> included in these studies. That is, Norton and Mehta (2007) and<lb/> Sexton et al. (2003) relied on non-clinical samples of psychology<lb/> students, while Norton et al. (2005) used 125 outpatients<lb/> diagnosed with various emotional disorders, with only 8% of the<lb/> participants meeting the DSM-IV-criteria of GAD (APA, 2000).<lb/> Therefore, the extent to which the results of these studies hold for<lb/> specific clinical samples is unclear, and should be further<lb/> addressed.<lb/> Second, the studies of Norton et al. (2005) and Sexton et al.<lb/> (2003) assessed the unique contributions of various vulnerability<lb/> factors by means of a series of multiple regression analyses, which<lb/> may lead to biased estimates due to the omitted parameter<lb/> problem (Judd &amp; Kenny, 1981). In response to this latter critique,<lb/> Norton and Mehta (2007) carried out a formal mediation analysis<lb/> using structural equation modeling (SEM) in order to investigate to<lb/> what extent disorder-specific vulnerability factors account for the<lb/> relationship between general vulnerability factors (i.e., high<lb/> neuroticism and low extraversion) and symptom levels. Because<lb/> the sample size in Norton and Mehta&apos;s study was quite large<lb/> (N = 650), SEM allowed for assessing whether a predictor variable<lb/> affects a dependent variable indirectly through one or more<lb/> mediator variables (Sobel, 1982, 1986). However, a disadvantage of<lb/> this analytic strategy was that it was not possible to determine (1)<lb/> to what extent specific mediators accounted for the effect of the<lb/> predictor on the outcome variable, and (2) the relative magnitudes<lb/> of the specific indirect effects associated with each of the<lb/> mediators. To address these problems, the current study employed<lb/> a bootstrapping method for testing multiple mediation effects<lb/> (Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008). This method will be discussed in more<lb/> detail in the further course of this article.<lb/> A third and final shortcoming of previous studies examining the<lb/> hierarchical vulnerability model with regard to GAD is that they<lb/> have only focused on IU as a specific vulnerability factor. In recent<lb/> years, metacognitive beliefs about worry have been described as<lb/> another specific variable that may be involved in the vulnerability<lb/> to GAD (Borkovec &amp; Roemer, 1995; Davis &amp; Valentiner, 2000;<lb/> Wells, 1995; Wells &amp; Carter, 1999; Wells &amp; Carter, 2001). Briefly,<lb/> such metacognitions can be defined as trait-like ideas and<lb/> appraisals about worrying (Wells, 1999) and in patients with<lb/> GAD two broad classes of metacognitive beliefs can be identified:<lb/> positive metacognitions, which refer to the conviction that<lb/> worrying can be used as a means of coping with threat (e.g.,<lb/> &apos;&apos;Worrying helps me cope with problems&apos;&apos;), and negative meta-<lb/>cognitions, which pertain to the problematic aspects of worrying<lb/> (e.g., &apos;&apos;Worrying will make me go crazy&apos;&apos;).<lb/> The present study was conducted to replicate and extend<lb/> previous work (Norton &amp; Mehta, 2007; Norton et al., 2005; Sexton<lb/> et al., 2003) by examining a hierarchical model of the vulnerability<lb/> for GAD in a sample of patients suffering from this particular<lb/> anxiety disorder. Apart from IU, metacognitive beliefs were<lb/> included in the model as a second potential mediating variable.<lb/> The main purpose of the study was to investigate the relationships<lb/> between the general higher order vulnerability factors of neuroti-<lb/>cism and extraversion, the specific second-order vulnerability<lb/> factors of IU and metacognitive beliefs, and symptoms of<lb/> generalized anxiety (i.e., worry) in clinically referred GAD patients.<lb/> To investigate the specificity of various general and specific<lb/> vulnerability factors for GAD, their links to symptoms of<lb/> depression (which is a common comorbid problem in patients<lb/> with GAD) were also explored. First and foremost, it was<lb/> investigated to what extent the expected relation between the<lb/> higher order factor of neuroticism and worry would be mediated<lb/> by the second-order factors of IU and metacognitive beliefs.<lb/> Further, in the case of depression, both the higher order factors of<lb/> neuroticism and (low) extraversion were expected to be associated<lb/> with symptom levels, and here it was explored whether these links<lb/> were also mediated by the second-order factors of IU and<lb/> metacognitive beliefs (see Fig. 1).<lb/> 2. Method<lb/> 2.1. Participants<lb/> Participants were 137 patients with a primary diagnosis of GAD<lb/> (101 women and 36 men; mean age = 35 years, range 19–66 years)<lb/> who were referred for treatment to a community mental health<lb/> center in Rotterdam, The Netherlands. The diagnosis of GAD was<lb/> established by means of a semi-structured DSM-IV-based clinical<lb/> interview (SCID-I; First, Spitzer, Gibbon, &amp; Williams, 1994), which<lb/> was administered by a trained psychologist. Most participants<lb/> were married (32.1%) or living together (35.8%), 22.6% were single,<lb/> and 8.0% were divorced or living separately from their partner.<lb/> Three-quarter of the participants were full-time employed, 12.4%<lb/> Fig. 1. Hypothesized hierarchical model of the vulnerability for GAD (bold lines) and<lb/> comorbid depressive symptoms (regular lines).<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">C. van der Heiden et al. / Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>285<lb/> </page>
			
			had a part-time job, and 8.8% were unemployed. The sample<lb/> breakdown in terms of educational level was as follows: 19.7% had<lb/> a low level of education, 41.6% an average level of education, and<lb/> 38.7% a high level of education. More than half of the participants<lb/> (57.8%) met the DSM-IV criteria for at least one comorbid axis-I<lb/> diagnosis. The most common comorbid diagnoses were depressive<lb/> disorder (21.8%), panic disorder (13.6%), social phobia (10.2%),<lb/> somatoform disorder (8.8%), obsessive-compulsive disorder (4.1%),<lb/> dysthymic disorder (3.4%), specific phobia (2.7%), and insomnia<lb/> (2%). Patients were not screened for DSM-IV axis-II disorders.<lb/> 2.2. Questionnaires and procedure<lb/> After patients had provided informed consent, they completed a<lb/> number of questions pertaining to demographic characteristics<lb/> along with a set of self-report scales, which were presented in<lb/> random order to minimize possible order effects. For all<lb/> questionnaires, the Dutch translations were used.<lb/> The neuroticism and extraversion scales of the NEO-Five Factor<lb/> Inventory (NEO-FFI; Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992), a 60-item self-report<lb/> scale for measuring the &apos;Big Five&apos; personality factors: neuroticism,<lb/> extraversion, openness, agreeableness, and conscientiousness.<lb/> Both the original English and the Dutch version of the NEO-FFI<lb/> have been demonstrated to possess sound reliability and validity in<lb/> both clinical and community samples (Costa &amp; McCrae, 1992;<lb/> Hoekstra, Ormel, &amp; De Fruyt, 1996). In the present study,<lb/> Cronbach&apos;s alpha values were .87 for neuroticism and .82 for<lb/> extraversion.<lb/> The Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale (IUS; Freeston, Rheaume,<lb/> Letarte, Dugas, &amp; Ladouceur, 1994) is a 27-item self-report<lb/> measure which intends to assess &apos;&apos;emotional, cognitive and<lb/> behavioral reactions to ambiguous situations, implications of<lb/> being uncertain, and attempts to control the future&apos;&apos; (Dugas,<lb/> Freeston, &amp; Ladouceur, 1994, p. 56). The original French version<lb/> (Freeston et al., 1994), the English version (Buhr &amp; Dugas, 2002),<lb/> and the Dutch version of the IUS (De Bruin, Rassin, Van der Heiden,<lb/> &amp; Muris, 2006) all have demonstrated comparable, adequate<lb/> psychometric properties. In the current study, Cronbach&apos;s alpha of<lb/> the IUS was .80.<lb/> The MetaCognitions Questionnaire (MCQ; Cartwright-Hatton &amp;<lb/> Wells, 1997) is a 65-item self-report scale for assessing individual<lb/> differences in positive beliefs about worry, negative beliefs about<lb/> worry, beliefs about the need to control thoughts, metacognitive<lb/> monitoring of thoughts, and the judgment of cognitive effective-<lb/>ness. In the present study, we only employed the two subscales<lb/> that are considered as most relevant to GAD (Wells, 1999), namely<lb/> positive beliefs about worry (e.g., &apos;&apos;Worrying helps me to cope&apos;&apos;)<lb/> and negative beliefs about worry (e.g., &apos;&apos;Worrying is dangerous for<lb/> me&apos;&apos;). The MCQ has been shown to possess good psychometric<lb/> properties (Cartwright-Hatton &amp; Wells, 1997), and this seems also<lb/> true for the Dutch translation of the scale (Hermans, Crombez, van<lb/> Rijsoort, &amp; Laeremans, 2002). In the present sample, Cronbach&apos;s<lb/> alphas were .89 for the positive metacognitions and .93 for the<lb/> negative metacognitions subscales.<lb/> The Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ; Meyer, Miller,<lb/> Metzger, &amp; Borkovec, 1990) is a widely used 16-item self-report<lb/> scale for measuring the intensity and uncontrollability of worry,<lb/> which is regarded as the key symptom of GAD. The PSWQ assesses<lb/> a construct that is separate from both anxiety and depression, and<lb/> is capable of discriminating GAD from other anxiety disorders<lb/> (Brown, Antony, &amp; Barlow, 1992; Meyer et al., 1990). Various<lb/> studies have reported adequate psychometric qualities for the<lb/> English (Startup &amp; Erickson, 2006) and the Dutch version of the<lb/> PSWQ (Van der Heiden, Muris, Bos, Van der Molen, &amp; Oostra, 2009;<lb/> Van Rijsoort, Emmelkamp, &amp; Vervaeke, 1999). In the current study,<lb/> a Cronbach&apos;s alpha value of .83 was found.<lb/> The second edition of the Beck Depression Inventory (BDI-II;<lb/> Beck, Steer, &amp; Brown, 1996) is a 21-item self-report index to assess<lb/> the affective, cognitive, behavioral, somatic, and motivational<lb/> components of depression, as well as suicidal ideas. This scale has<lb/> been shown to possess sound psychometric properties (Beck et al.,<lb/> 1996), and this is also true for the Dutch BDI-II (Van der Does,<lb/> 2002). The Cronbach&apos;s alpha value in the current study was .92.<lb/> 3. Results<lb/> 3.1. Data screening and outlier analysis<lb/> Prior to carrying out the main statistical analyses, the data were<lb/> screened to determine whether statistical assumptions were met<lb/> (see Tabachnick &amp; Fidell, 1996). Assumptions for linearity,<lb/> normality, and homogeneity of variance were met for all measures.<lb/> Second, data were screened for univariate and multivariate<lb/> outliers. Again, no violations were identified. Means and standard<lb/> deviations for the questionnaires, and the correlations among<lb/> them are provided in Table 1.<lb/> 3.2. Bootstrapping<lb/> To test the hypothesis of mediation by multiple variables,<lb/> multiple mediation is the appropriate analytic strategy (Preacher &amp;<lb/> Hayes, 2008). In multiple mediation models not only the total<lb/> direct effect of the independent variable X on the dependent<lb/> variable Y is assessed, but also the specific indirect effect of each<lb/> potential mediator M (West &amp; Aiken, 1997). As the present sample<lb/> was not that large, the assumption of normality of the sampling<lb/> distribution for the indirect effect could not be met (Preacher &amp;<lb/> Hayes, 2008). In such cases, bootstrapping provides the most<lb/> powerful and reasonable method for obtaining confidence inter-<lb/>vals of specific indirect effects. An advantage of using this<lb/> nonparametric re-sampling procedure is that it is possible to<lb/> draw conclusions about (a) the extent to which mediators mediate<lb/> the effect of the independent variable on the outcome variable<lb/> (conditional on the presence of other mediators in the model), and<lb/> Table 1<lb/> Means, standard deviations, and intercorrelations among the main variables in this study.<lb/> M ( S D )<lb/> 1 2<lb/> 3 4<lb/> 5 6<lb/> 1. NEO-FFI neuroticism<lb/> 44.07 (7.25)<lb/> 2. NEO-FFI extraversion<lb/> 35.97 (7.23)<lb/> À.46 **<lb/> 3. IUS intolerance of uncertainty<lb/> 81.14 (21.15)<lb/> .63 **<lb/> À.47 **<lb/> 4. MCQ negative metacognitions<lb/> 50.76 (7.93)<lb/> .49 **<lb/> À.22 *<lb/> .47 **<lb/> 5. MCQ positive metacognitions<lb/> 33.06 (10.92)<lb/> .34 **<lb/> À.09<lb/> .35 **<lb/> .17 *<lb/> 6. PSWQ worry<lb/> 67.62 (8.27)<lb/> .57 **<lb/> À.30 **<lb/> .53 **<lb/> .62 **<lb/> .23 **<lb/> 7. BDI-II depression<lb/> 23.18 (12.15)<lb/> .62 **<lb/> À.41 **<lb/> .63 **<lb/> .57 **<lb/> .31 **<lb/> .45 **<lb/> Note. NEO-FFI = NEO-Five Factor Inventory; IUS = Intolerance of Uncertainty Scale; MCQ = MetaCognitions Questionnaire; PSWQ = Penn State Worry Questionnaire; BDI-<lb/>II = Beck Depression Inventory, 2nd edition.<lb/> * p &lt; .05<lb/> ** p &lt; .01.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">C. van der Heiden et al. / Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>286<lb/> </page>
			
			(b) the relative magnitudes of the specific indirect effects<lb/> associated with each of the mediators (Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008).<lb/> Bootstrapping involves at least a thousand times of repeatedly<lb/> sampling from the original data and estimating the indirect effect<lb/> in each re-sampled data set. As such, an empirical approximation<lb/> of the sampling distribution of the indirect effect of X on Y through<lb/> multiple M&apos;s can be obtained. This approximation is then used to<lb/> construct percentile bootstrap confidence intervals (CIs) for the<lb/> total and specific indirect effects. As this procedure results in<lb/> estimation inaccuracy and problems with Type I error and power<lb/> when used in hypothesis testing, percentile bootstrap CIs are<lb/> improved by an adjustment to the percentage values of the sorted<lb/> distribution of bootstrap estimates used for determining the<lb/> boundaries of the interval (bias-corrected CI; Efron &amp; Tibshirani,<lb/> 1993; Preacher &amp; Hayes, 2008). To test the mediation hypotheses<lb/> in the current study, data were analyzed using a SPSS-macro for<lb/> estimating a bias-corrected 95% CI, as developed by Preacher and<lb/> Hayes (2008).<lb/> We first tested the relations between the higher order factors of<lb/> neuroticism and extraversion, the second-order factors of positive<lb/> metacognitions, negative metacognitions, and intolerance of<lb/> uncertainty, and the symptom variable worry. The higher order<lb/> and second-order factors together explained 39.8% of the variation<lb/> in worry, F(5,115) = 15.18, p &lt; .0001. After controlling for neuroti-<lb/>cism no significant relationship between extraversion and worry<lb/> was found (b = À.10, SE = .09, t = À1.06, p &gt; .05): both the direct<lb/> effect (b = À.04, SE = .09, t = À.45, p &gt; .05) and total indirect effect<lb/> (b = À.06, SE = .05, bootstrapped 95% CI = À.17 to .05) were not<lb/> significant. After controlling for extraversion, the link between<lb/> neuroticism and worry appeared to be significant (b = .46, SE = .10,<lb/> t = 4.59, p &lt; .01). The direct effect of neuroticism on worry was not<lb/> significant (b = .17, SE = .11, t = 1.53, p &gt; .05). However, the total<lb/> indirect effect was significant (b = .29, SE = .08, bootstrapped 95%<lb/> CI = .13 to .45). Within the indirect effect, both negative<lb/> metacognitions (b = .20, SE = .05, bootstrapped 95% CI = .11 to<lb/> .31) and intolerance of uncertainty (b = .10, SE = .05, bootstrapped<lb/> 95% CI = .01 to .21) made significant contributions.<lb/> A similar procedure was performed to study the link between<lb/> the higher order and second-order vulnerability factors and<lb/> depressive symptoms. Results indicated that 48.8% of the variation<lb/> in depressive symptoms was explained by all variables together,<lb/> F(5,115) = 21.92, p &lt; .0001. After controlling for extraversion, the<lb/> link between neuroticism and depressive symptoms appeared to<lb/> be significant (b = .85, SE = .15, t = 5.82, p &lt; .001). Both the direct<lb/> effect (b = .39, SE = .16, t = 2.43, p &lt; .05) and the total indirect effect<lb/> (b = .46, SE = .11, bootstrapped 95% CI = .25 to .67) of neuroticism on<lb/> depressive symptoms were significant. Within the indirect effect,<lb/> negative metacognitions (b = .25, SE = .08, bootstrapped 95%<lb/> CI = .14 to .47) and intolerance of uncertainty (b = .16, SE = .09,<lb/> bootstrapped 95% CI = .00 to .35) both made a significant<lb/> contribution. After controlling for neuroticism, the link between<lb/> extraversion and depressive symptoms appeared to be significant<lb/> (b = À.34, SE = .13, t = À2.52, p &lt; .02). The direct effect was<lb/> significant (b = À.26, SE = .13, t = À2.01, p &lt; .05), but the indirect<lb/> effect was not (b = À.08, SE = .08, bootstrapped 95% CI = À.26 to .06).<lb/> From these results, it can be concluded that the variation in<lb/> worry was, as expected, mainly explained by neuroticism. This<lb/> relationship between neuroticism and worry was fully mediated<lb/> by both negative metacognitions and intolerance of uncertainty.<lb/> Furthermore, contrary to expectations positive metacognitions<lb/> were not found to have a mediating effect in the link between<lb/> neuroticism and worry. The variation in depressive symptoms was<lb/> explained by both neuroticism and (low) extraversion, which was<lb/> as predicted. Low extraversion was only found to exert a direct<lb/> effect on depressive symptoms. The effect of neuroticism on<lb/> depressive symptoms was found to be both direct and indirect.<lb/> Particularly the vulnerability factors of negative metacognitions<lb/> and intolerance of uncertainty were found to have a mediating<lb/> effect, whereas positive metacognitions did not influence the<lb/> relationship between neuroticism and depressive symptoms in<lb/> patients with GAD. Fig. 2 presents the hierarchical model in which<lb/> the observed significant direct and indirect effects are shown.<lb/> 4. Discussion<lb/> Despite empirical support for the causal role of personality<lb/> traits in the development of anxiety disorders (see Kotov et al.,<lb/> 2007), little is known about the precise mechanisms by which such<lb/> traits influence specific disorders. The investigation of factors<lb/> mediating the relations between personality traits and symptom-<lb/>atic manifestations of specific anxiety disorders advances our<lb/> understanding of etiology, and may lead to the development of<lb/> more effective treatments. In the present study, we tested a<lb/> hierarchical model for GAD, which was based on a recently<lb/> developed and tested model for various emotional disorders<lb/> (Norton &amp; Mehta, 2007; Norton et al., 2005; Sexton et al., 2003). In<lb/> this model the two basic personality dimensions of neuroticism<lb/> and extraversion served as higher order vulnerability factors,<lb/> whereas IU and metacognitive beliefs, two trait-like constructs<lb/> that are hypothesized to contribute to GAD, acted as specific<lb/> second-order vulnerability factors. At the symptom level worry<lb/> featured as the specific manifestation of GAD. Moreover, we also<lb/> examined the contribution of both the higher order and second-<lb/>order vulnerabilities to depressive symptoms in GAD patients,<lb/> given the high comorbidity rate and the shared genetic and<lb/> environmental risk factors between GAD and depression (Gold-<lb/>berg, 2008).<lb/> Overall, results of the multiple mediation analysis are generally<lb/> consistent with the hypothesized theoretical model. As expected,<lb/> the general vulnerability factor of neuroticism was significantly<lb/> associated with symptoms of worry and depressive symptoms in<lb/> these clinically referred GAD patients. Further, both negative<lb/> metacognitions and, to a lesser extent, IU were found to mediate<lb/> Fig. 2. Hierarchical model of the vulnerability for GAD (bold lines) and comorbid<lb/> depressive symptoms (regular lines). Note: only significant (p &lt; .05) pathways are<lb/> shown. Values in parentheses represent bootstrapped 95% confidence intervals.<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">C. van der Heiden et al. / Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>287<lb/> </page>
			
			the relationship between the higher order factor of neuroticism<lb/> and the symptom variables, and this was particularly true for<lb/> worry. In contrast with the predictions, positive metacognitions<lb/> did not have a mediating effect on the relationship between the<lb/> higher order factor of neuroticism and both symptom variables,<lb/> although it should be noted that there are also earlier findings that<lb/> have demonstrated that positive beliefs about worrying are not<lb/> convincingly associated with symptom levels (Wells &amp; Carter,<lb/> 1999). Finally, as hypothesized, low extraversion was only found to<lb/> be associated with depressive symptoms in the present sample of<lb/> patients with GAD. This relationship was direct in nature and not<lb/> mediated by IU or metacognitive beliefs. All in all, these findings<lb/> suggest that worrying and depressive symptoms are related but<lb/> nevertheless distinct manifestations in patients with GAD, and that<lb/> low extraversion may define the difference between them.<lb/> Results of the current study support a hierarchical model of<lb/> GAD that serves as a descriptive framework for understanding this<lb/> anxiety disorder, and may provide a basis for developing more<lb/> specific treatments for GAD that not only target the main<lb/> symptoms of this disorder, but also the specific processes that<lb/> underlie them. As such, the model supports the appropriateness of<lb/> two recently developed cognitive-behavioral treatments for GAD,<lb/> based on the metacognitive (Wells, 1995) and the intolerance of<lb/> uncertainty (Dugas &amp; Ladouceur, 2000) accounts of this specific<lb/> disorder. Preliminary results from research into the efficacy of<lb/> these GAD-specific interventions have shown that the recovery<lb/> rates are higher than recovery rates obtained by other less targeted<lb/> treatment approaches (Fisher, 2006). Interestingly, our data seem<lb/> to suggest that it may be important to target both intolerance of<lb/> uncertainty and negative metacognitions in the treatment of GAD.<lb/> Further, as most variables in the hierarchical model reflect<lb/> transdiagnostic phenomena (Harvey, Watkins, Mansell, &amp; Shafran,<lb/> 2004), it might be worthwhile to examine specific second-order<lb/> vulnerability factors also in the context of other emotional<lb/> disorders. Increasing knowledge about common, underlying core<lb/> psychopathological processes may be particularly helpful to better<lb/> explain the high comorbidity rates between several emotional<lb/> disorders (see Krueger, 1999; Watson, 2005). For instance, the fact<lb/> that GAD is strongly linked to depression, both phenotypically and<lb/> genotypically (e.g., Goldberg, 2008; Kendler, Prescott, Myers, &amp;<lb/> Neale, 2003; Mineka et al., 1998), might be well explained by the<lb/> overlap in generalized and specific vulnerability factors that are<lb/> linked to both types of disorder (Krueger, 1999; Watson, 2005).<lb/> Results of this study should be interpreted in the context of<lb/> various limitations. To begin with, although hierarchical models of<lb/> anxiety and depression implicate neuroticism as an underlying<lb/> vulnerability factor (Clark &amp; Watson, 1991; Mineka et al., 1998;<lb/> Norton et al., 2005), the current study does not permit definitive<lb/> conclusions regarding etiology of GAD because of the cross-<lb/>sectional, correlational design of this investigation. A further<lb/> shortcoming pertains to the fact that the variables in our model<lb/> were only assessed by one measure that was completed by one<lb/> informant (i.e., GAD patients). To effectively deal with this critique,<lb/> a multitrait-multimethod approach would be preferable (Kotov<lb/> et al., 2007; Sexton et al., 2003; Starcevic &amp; Berle, 2006).<lb/> Furthermore, apart from the higher order factors and two<lb/> second-order factors of IU and metacognitions, there may still<lb/> be other vulnerability factors involved in the etiology of GAD, a<lb/> notion that is supported by the finding that the included variables<lb/> only accounted for a limited proportion of the variance in worry<lb/> scores. Finally, although the comorbidity rate among the sample of<lb/> GAD patients used in this study (57.8%) is in keeping with that<lb/> observed in other clinical studies (i.e., 45–98%; Holaway,<lb/> Rodebaugh, &amp; Heimberg, 2006), the comorbidity rates with some<lb/> of the disorders (e.g., depression, insomnia) seemed to be<lb/> considerably lower than those found in large epidemiological<lb/> studies (e.g., Carter, Wittchen, Pfister, &amp; Kessler, 2001). Thus, it is<lb/> not fully clear whether the participants in this study were &apos;&apos;typical&apos;&apos;<lb/> GAD patients, and to what extent the present findings can be<lb/> generalized to other samples of patients with this anxiety disorder.<lb/> In sum, results of this study extend findings of Norton and Mehta<lb/> (2007), Norton et al. (2005), and Sexton et al. (2003), by providing<lb/> support for a hierarchical model of the vulnerability for GAD, in<lb/> which neuroticism serves as a common higher order vulnerability<lb/> factor, IU and metacognitions act as more specific vulnerability<lb/> variables, while extraversion only seems to be involved as a higher<lb/> order vulnerability factor in the comorbid depressive symptoms of<lb/> patients suffering from this anxiety disorder.<lb/> 
			
			</body>
			
			<back>
			
			<listBibl>
			References<lb/> 
				
				American Psychiatric Association (APA). (2000). Diagnostic and statistical manual of<lb/> mental disorders, 4th Edition, text revision (DSM-IV-TR). Washington: APA.<lb/> Beck, A. T., Steer, R. A., &amp; Brown, G. K. (1996). Manual for the Beck depression inventory-II.<lb/> San Antonio, TX: Psychological Corporation.<lb/> Borkovec, T. D., &amp; Roemer, L. (1995). Perceived functions of worry among generalized<lb/> anxiety disorder subjects: distraction from more emotionally distressing topics?<lb/> Journal of Behaviour Therapy and Experimental Psychiatry, 26, 25–30.<lb/> Brown, T. A., Antony, M. M., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (1992). Psychometric properties of the Penn<lb/> State Worry Questionnaire in a clinical anxiety disorders sample. Behaviour<lb/> Research and Therapy, 30, 33–37.<lb/> Brown, T. A., Chorpita, B. F., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (1998). Structural relationships among<lb/> dimensions of the DSM-IV anxiety and mood disorders and dimensions of negative<lb/> affect, positive affect and autonomic arousal. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 107,<lb/> 179–192.<lb/> Buhr, K., &amp; Dugas, M. J. (2002). The intolerance of uncertainty scale: psychometric<lb/> properties of the English version. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 40, 931–945.<lb/> Carter, R. M., Wittchen, H.-U., Pfister, H., &amp; Kessler, R. C. (2001). One-year prevalence of<lb/> subthreshold and threshold DSM-IV generalized anxiety disorder in a nationally<lb/> representative sample. Depression and Anxiety, 13, 78–88.<lb/> Cartwright-Hatton, S., &amp; Wells, A. (1997). Beliefs about worry and intrusions: the Meta-<lb/>Cognitions Questionnaire and its correlates. Journal of Anxiety Disorders, 11, 279–296.<lb/> Claridge, G., &amp; Davis, C. (2001). What&apos;s the use of neuroticism. Personality and Individual<lb/> Differences, 31, 383–400.<lb/> Clark, L. A., &amp; Watson, D. (1991). Tripartite model of anxiety and depression: psycho-<lb/>metric evidence and taxonomic implications. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 100,<lb/> 316–336.<lb/> Clark, L. A., Watson, D., &amp; Mineka, S. (1994). Temperament, personality, and the mood<lb/> and anxiety disorders. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 103, 103–116.<lb/> Costa, P. T., &amp; McCrae, R. R. (1992). Revised NEO Personality Inventory (NEO-PI-R) and the<lb/> Five Factor Inventory (NEO-FFI): professional manual. Odessa, FL: Psychological<lb/> Assessment Resources.<lb/> Davis, R. N., &amp; Valentiner, D. P. (2000). Does meta-cognitive theory enhance our<lb/> understanding of pathological worry and anxiety? Personality and Individual<lb/> Differences, 29, 513–526.<lb/> De Bruin, G. O., Rassin, E., Van der Heiden, C., &amp; Muris, P. (2006). Psychometric<lb/> properties of a Dutch version of the intolerance of uncertainty scale. Netherlands<lb/> Journal of Psychology, 62, 91–97.<lb/> Dugas, M. J., Freeston, M. H., &amp; Ladouceur, R. (1994). Intolerance of uncertainty and<lb/> problem orientation in worry. Cognitive Therapy and Research, 21, 593–606.<lb/> Dugas, M. J., &amp; Ladouceur, R. (2000). Treatment of generalized anxiety disorder: targeting<lb/> intolerance of uncertainty in two types of worry. Behaviour Modification, 24, 635–657.<lb/> Dugas, M. J., &amp; Robichaud, M. (2007). Cognitive-behavioral treatment for generalized<lb/> anxiety disorder: from science to practice. New York, NY: Routledge.<lb/> Efron, B., &amp; Tibshirani, R. J. (1993). An introduction to the bootstrap. Boca Raton, FL:<lb/> Chapman &amp; Hall.<lb/> First, M. B., Spitzer, R. L., Gibbon, M., &amp; Williams, J. B. (1994). Structured clinical interview<lb/> for DSM-IV axis-I disorders, research Version. Patient edition (SCID-I/P), New York:<lb/> Biometrics Research Department, New York State Psychiatric Institute.<lb/> Fisher, P. L. (2006). The efficacy of psychological treatments for generalized anxiety<lb/> disorder? In: A. Wells &amp; D. Graham (Eds.), Worry and its psychological disorders:<lb/> theory assessment and treatment (pp. 359–377). Hoboken, NJ: Wiley Publishing.<lb/> Freeston, M. H., Rheaume, J., Letarte, H., Dugas, M. J., &amp; Ladouceur, R. (1994). Why do<lb/> people worry? Personality and Individual Differences, 17, 791–802.<lb/> Goldberg, D. (2008). Towards DSM-V: the relationship between generalized anxiety<lb/> disorder and major depressive episode. Psychological Medicine, 38, 1671–1675.<lb/> Harvey, A. G., Watkins, E., Mansell, W., &amp; Shafran, R. (2004). Cognitive behavioural<lb/> processes across psychological disorders: a transdiagnostic approach to research and<lb/> treatment. Oxford, UK: Oxford University Press.<lb/> Hermans, D., Crombez, G., van Rijsoort, S., &amp; Laeremans, I. (2002). De MetaCognities<lb/> Vragenlijst. Gedragstherapie, 35, 341–352.<lb/> Hettema, J. M., Prescott, C. A., &amp; Kendler, K. S. (2004). Genetic and environmental<lb/> sources of covariation between generalized anxiety disorder and neuroticism.<lb/> American Journal of Psychiatry, 161, 1581–1587.<lb/> Hoekstra, H. A., Ormel, J., &amp; De Fruyt, F. (1996). De NEO-PI-R/NEO-FFI: Big Five Persoon-<lb/>lijkheidsvragenlijsten. Handleiding. Lisse, NL: Swets and Zeitlinger.<lb/> Holaway, R. M., Rodebaugh, T. L., &amp; Heimberg, R. G. M. (2006). The epidemilogy of worry<lb/> and generalized anxiety disorder. In: G. C. L. Davey &amp; A. Wells (Eds.), Worry and its<lb/> 
			
			<note place="headnote">C. van der Heiden et al. / Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </note>
			
			<page>288<lb/> </page>
			
			psychological disorders: Theory, assessment and treatment (pp. 3–20). Chichester:<lb/> John Wiley &amp; Sons.<lb/> Judd, C. M., &amp; Kenny, D. A. (1981). Process analysis: estimating mediation in treatment<lb/> evaluations. Evaluation Review, 5, 602–619.<lb/> Kendler, K. S., Prescott, C. A., Myers, J., &amp; Neale, M. C. (2003). The structure of genetic and<lb/> environmental risk factors for common psychiatric and substance use disorders in<lb/> men and women. Archives of General Psychiatry, 60, 929–937.<lb/> Kotov, R., Watson, D., Robles, J. P., &amp; Schmidt, N. B. (2007). Personality traits and anxiety<lb/> symptoms: the multilevel trait predictor model. Behaviour Research and Therapy,<lb/> 45, 1485–1503.<lb/> Krueger, R. F. (1999). The structure of common mental disorders. Archives of General<lb/> Psychiatry, 56, 921–926.<lb/> McNally, R. (1999). Theoretical approaches to the fear of anxiety. In: S. Taylor (Ed.),<lb/> Anxiety sensitivity: theory, research and treatment of the fear of anxiety (pp. 3–16).<lb/> Mahwah, NJ: Erlbaum.<lb/> Meyer, T. J., Miller, M. L., Metzger, R. L., &amp; Borkovec, T. D. (1990). Development and<lb/> validation of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire. Behaviour Research and Therapy,<lb/> 28, 487–495.<lb/> Mineka, S., Watson, D., &amp; Clark, L. A. (1998). Comorbidity of anxiety and unipolar mood<lb/> disorders. Annual Review of Psychology, 49, 377–412.<lb/> Mineka, S., Yovel, I., &amp; Pineles, S. L. (2002). Toward a psychological model of the etiology<lb/> of generalized anxiety disorder. In: D. Nutt, K. Rickels, &amp; D. J. Stein (Eds.),<lb/> Generalized anxiety disorder: symptomatology, pathogenesis and management (pp.<lb/> 41–55). London: Martin Dunitz.<lb/> Norton, P. J., &amp; Mehta, P. D. (2007). Hierarchical model of vulnerabilities for emotional<lb/> disorders. Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, 36, 240–254.<lb/> Norton, P. J., Sexton, K. A., Walker, J. R., &amp; Norton, R. (2005). Hierarchical model of<lb/> vulnerability for anxiety: replication and extension with a clinical sample. Cogni-<lb/>tive Behaviour Therapy, 34, 50–63.<lb/> Ormel, J., Rosmalen, J., &amp; Farmer, A. (2004). Neuroticism: a non-informative marker of<lb/> vulnerability to psychopathology. Social Psychiatry and Psychiatric Epidemiology, 39,<lb/> 906–912.<lb/> Preacher, K. J., &amp; Hayes, A. F. (2008). Asymptotic and resampling strategies for assessing<lb/> and comparing indirect effects in multiple mediator models. Behaviour Research<lb/> Methods, 40, 879–891.<lb/> Roemer, L., Orsillo, S. M., &amp; Barlow, D. H. (2002). Generalized anxiety disorder. In: D. H.<lb/> Barlow (Ed.), Anxiety and its disorders (2nd ed., pp. 477–515). New York, NY:<lb/> Guilford Press.<lb/> Sexton, K. A., Norton, P. J., Walker, J. R., &amp; Norton, G. R. (2003). Hierarchical model of<lb/> generalized and specific vulnerabilities in anxiety. Cognitive Behaviour Therapy, 32,<lb/> 82–94.<lb/> Sobel, M. E. (1982). Asymptotic confidence intervals for indirect effects in structural<lb/> equations models. In: S. Leinhart (Ed.), Sociological methodology 1982 (pp. 290–<lb/> 312). San Francisco, CA: Jossey-Bass.<lb/> Sobel, M. E. (1986). Some new results on indirect effects and their standardized errors<lb/> in covariance structure models. In: N. Truma (Ed.), Sociological methodology 1986<lb/> (pp. 159–186). Washington, DC: American Sociological Association.<lb/> Starcevic, V., &amp; Berle, D. (2006). Cognitive specificity of anxiety disorders: a review of<lb/> selected key constructs. Depression and Anxiety, 23, 51–61.<lb/> Startup, H. M., &amp; Erickson, T. M. (2006). The Penn State Worry Questionnaire (PSWQ).<lb/> In: G. C. L. Davey &amp; A. Wells (Eds.), Worry and its psychological disorders: theory,<lb/> assessment and treatment (pp. 265–283). Chichester, England: Wiley.<lb/> Tabachnick, B. G., &amp; Fidell, L. S. (1996). Using multivariate statistics (3rd ed.). New York,<lb/> NY: Harper Collins Publishers.<lb/> Taylor, S. (1998). The hierarchical structure of fears. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 36,<lb/> 205–214.<lb/> Van der Does, A. J. W. (2002). Handleiding bij de Nederlandse versie van Beck Depression<lb/> Inventory–second edition (BDI–II–NL). Lisse, NL: Swets Test Publishers.<lb/> Van der Heiden, C., Muris, P., Bos, A. E. R., Van der Molen, H. T., &amp; Oostra, M. (2009).<lb/> Normative data for the Dutch version of the Penn State Worry Questionnaire.<lb/> Netherlands Journal of Psychology, 65, 69–75.<lb/> Van Rijsoort, S., Emmelkamp, P., &amp; Vervaeke, G. (1999). The Penn State Worry<lb/> Questionnaire and the Worry Domains Questionnaire: structure, reliability and<lb/> validity. Clinical Psychology and Psychotherapy, 6, 297–307.<lb/> Watson, D. (1999). Dimensions underlying the anxiety disorders: a hierarchical<lb/> perspective. Current Opinion in Psychiatry, 12, 181–186.<lb/> Watson, D. (2005). Rethinking the mood and anxiety disorders: a quantitative hierar-<lb/>chical model for the DSM-V. Journal of Abnormal Psychology, 114, 522–536.<lb/> Watson, D., Gamez, W., &amp; Simms, L. J. (2005). Basic dimensions of temperament and<lb/> their relation to anxiety and depression: a symptom-based perspective. Journal of<lb/> Research in Personality, 39, 46–66.<lb/> Wells, A. (1995). Metacognition and worry: a cognitive model of generalized anxiety<lb/> disorder. Behavioural and Cognitive Psychotherapy, 23, 301–320.<lb/> Wells, A. (1999). A cognitive model of generalized anxiety disorder. Behaviour Modifi-<lb/>cation, 23, 526–555.<lb/> Wells, A., &amp; Carter, K. (1999). Preliminary test of a cognitive model of generalized<lb/> anxiety disorder. Behaviour Research and Therapy, 37, 585–594.<lb/> Wells, A., &amp; Carter, K. (2001). Further tests of a cognitive model of generalized anxiety<lb/> disorder: metacognitions and worry in GAD, panic disorder, social phobia, depres-<lb/>sion and nonpatients. Behavior Therapy, 31, 85–102.<lb/> West, S. G., &amp; Aiken, L. S. (1997). Toward understanding individual effects in multi-<lb/>component prevention programs: design and analysis strategies. In: K. J. Bryant, M.<lb/> Windle, &amp; S. G. West (Eds.), The science of prevention: methodological advances from<lb/> alcohol and substance abuse research (pp. 167–209). Washington, DC: American<lb/> Psychological Association.<lb/> Yonkers, K. A., Warshaw, M. G., Massion, A. O., &amp; Keller, M. B. (1996). Phenomenology<lb/> and course of generalized anxiety disorder. British Journal of Psychiatry, 168, 308–<lb/> 313.<lb/> C. van der Heiden et al. / Journal of Anxiety Disorders 24 (2010) 284–289<lb/> </listBibl>
			
			<page>289</page>

			</back>

	</text>
</tei>
