<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

        <titlePage>UC Irvine <lb/>UC Irvine Previously Published Works <lb/>Title <lb/>NOVEL PHASE-TRANSITION IN NON-ANTIFERROMAGNETICALLY ORDERED <lb/>CRYSTALS OF LA2CUO4 <lb/>Permalink <lb/>https://escholarship.org/uc/item/38f1d08j <lb/>Journal <lb/>SOLID STATE COMMUNICATIONS, 65(2) <lb/>ISSN <lb/>0038-1098 <lb/>Authors <lb/>CHEONG, SW <lb/>FISK, Z <lb/>WILLIS, JO <lb/>et al. <lb/>Publication Date <lb/>1988 <lb/>DOI <lb/>10.1016/0038-1098(88)90669-2 <lb/>License <lb/>CC BY 4.0 <lb/>Peer reviewed <lb/>eScholarship.org <lb/>Powered by the California Digital Library <lb/>University of California <lb/></titlePage>

        =

        <front>Solid State Communications, Vol.65,No.2, pp.111-114, 1988. <lb/>_ <lb/>Printed in Great Britain. <lb/>0038-I098/88 $3.00 + .00 <lb/>Pergamon Journals Ltd. <lb/>NOVEL PHASE TRANSITION IN NON-ANTIFERRObIAGNETICALLY ORDERED CRYSTALS OF La2Cu04 <lb/>S-W. Cheong, Z. Flsk, J. O. Willis, S. E. Brown, J. D. Thompson, <lb/>J. P. RemeikaN, A. S. Coopers, R. M. Aikin, D. Schiferl, and C. Cruner~-~ <lb/>Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NM 87545 <lb/>~AT&amp;T Bell Laboratories, Murray Hill, NJ 07974 <lb/>~O~Also at UCtA, Department of Physics and Solid State Science Center, <lb/>Los Angeles, CA 90024 <lb/>(Received 6 October 1987 by G. Burns) <lb/>We report the discovery of a new phase diagram in the magnetic field-<lb/>temperature plane for single crystals o£ La2Cu04 that show no sign of <lb/>antiferromagnetic order. <lb/>The phase boundary is defined by magneto-<lb/>resistance and sucseptibility <lb/>measurements. We discuss several possibi-<lb/>lities <lb/>that may lead to the phase diagram observed. <lb/></front>

        <body>An antiferromagnetic phase transition, <lb/>indicated by a maximum in the magnetic <lb/>susceptibility <lb/>(K) and anomalies in the <lb/>electrical <lb/>resistivity <lb/>(p), has been widely <lb/>observed in sintered powders and single crystals <lb/>of LR2CuO 4. Work by Johnston et al. and <lb/>Freltoft et al. i on the variation of the Neel <lb/>temperature (TN) of La2Od04_ 6 as a function of 5 <lb/>in sintered powders and crystals indicates that <lb/>T N approaches zero as 6 goes to zero. <lb/>More <lb/>recent experiments 2 on single crystals of <lb/>La2Cu04_ ~ show the presence of strong 2D spin-<lb/>1/2 antiferromagnetic <lb/>fluctuations (quantum spin <lb/>fluid state) in the Cu-O planes above T N, with <lb/>three dimensional ordering setting in at <lb/>approximately 200 K in the crystal measured. <lb/>Although the nature of the proposed 2]) quantum <lb/>state is not understood theoretically, <lb/>its <lb/>existence is not surprising given the huge <lb/>anisotropy observed 3 in transport measurements <lb/>on single crystals of La2Cu04 that implies a <lb/>strongly 2D character in this material. <lb/>To <lb/>provide further understanding of the highly <lb/>unusual physical properties of La2Cu04, we have <lb/>investigated the magnetic, transport and thermal <lb/>properties of single crystals in magnetic fields <lb/>applied in different directions with respect to <lb/>the Cu-O plane. <lb/>Our samples were La2Cu04 crystals (~1 x 1 x <lb/>0.1 cm 3) grown from a PbO-based flux. <lb/>Lattice <lb/>constants were determined by the eight-position <lb/>Hamilton technique 4 using ten reflections with <lb/>29 ° &lt; e &lt; 37 ° . These x-ray measurements <lb/>indicated the orthorhombically distorted K2NiF4 <lb/>structure at room temperatuge with lattice <lb/>constants a = 5.358 ± O.O02A, b = 13.181 ± 0.007 <lb/>o <lb/>o <lb/>o <lb/>A and c = 5.403 ± 0.002 A (volume = 379.26 A3). <lb/>Wet chemical analyses gave a composition of <lb/>Lat.vsCu04.3, plus ~2 at % Pb, for the crystals <lb/>studied. <lb/>The presence of Pb and excess oxygen <lb/>may be associated in part with PbO flux at the <lb/>sample surface; however, this cannot account for <lb/>all the oxygen excess. <lb/>Resistance and magnetoresistance were <lb/>measured with a standard four probe technique <lb/>using In pressed contracts on the a-c basal <lb/>plane. <lb/>As plotted in Fig. 1, the resistance in <lb/>10 4 <lb/>, <lb/>~_ ~o~{ <lb/>Q: ~d <lb/>&lt; <lb/>n.-<lb/>&quot;% 10 ~ <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>,_1 <lb/>10 <lb/>La2CuO, <lb/>[ <lb/>T <lb/>1 <lb/>1 .oo <lb/>1 <lb/>~o.75 <lb/>L <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>IO00/TEMPERATURE <lb/>(K -~) <lb/>300 <lb/>Fig. 1. <lb/>Log e R vs. 1/T of a single crystal <lb/>La2CuO ~ sample in zero applied <lb/>magnetic field which does not show any <lb/>antiferromagnetic ordering-like <lb/>resistance anomaly. The inset shows a <lb/>resistance anomaly characteristic <lb/>of a <lb/>single crystal sample which undergoes <lb/>an antiferromagnetic transition at <lb/>2dO K. <lb/></body>

        <page>111 <lb/></page>

        <body>zero applied field increases strongly with <lb/>decreasing temperature, with a non-exponential <lb/>variation characteristic <lb/>of dirty semiconduc-<lb/>tors, s and does not show any resistance anomaly <lb/>typical of 3I) antiferromagnetic ordering. <lb/>In <lb/>contrast, the inset of Fig. 1 shows the typical <lb/>resistance anomaly of single crystal La2Cu04_5 <lb/></body>

        <page>112 <lb/></page>

        <body>which orders antiferromagnetically <lb/>near 240 K. <lb/>All data shown here, except the inset of Fig. 1, <lb/>are taken from single crystal samples which do <lb/>not indicate any ant•ferromagnetic <lb/>ordering-like <lb/>resistance anomaly in zero applied magnetic <lb/>field. <lb/>In Fig. 2 resistances <lb/>at various fixed <lb/>temperatures are plotted as a function of <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">NON-ANTIFERROMAGNETICALLY ORDERED CRYSTALS OF La2Cu0 h <lb/>Vol. 65, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <body>The magnetization M, with magnetic field H <lb/>applied perpendicular to the basal plane, was <lb/>measured at various temperatures with a Quantum <lb/>Design SQUID susceptometer and is plotted in <lb/>Fig. 3. We see no evidence for a &quot;conventional&quot; <lb/>antiferromagnetic <lb/>transition, <lb/>i.e., a sharp cusp <lb/>in K(T), in these data. <lb/>Instead, we find a <lb/>rounded feature in the vicinity <lb/>of 120 K in a <lb/>measuring field of 0.3 T; this bump moves <lb/>10 <lb/>v <lb/>S <lb/>o <lb/>0 ~ <lb/>0 <lb/>m-<lb/>I -2.5 <lb/>&quot;1-O~ <lb/>n-<lb/>-2.5 <lb/>T <lb/>] <lb/>1 <lb/>La2CuO 4 <lb/>E*~-<lb/>~ <lb/>r <lb/>7 <lb/>4K <lb/>o_2 <lb/>;I <lb/>\ <lb/>r <lb/>70K <lb/>£% <lb/>• <lb/>o <lb/>5o <lb/>too <lb/>~5o <lb/>20o <lb/>• • • • • • • • <lb/>%• * <lb/>TEMPERATURE (K) <lb/>~-<lb/>107K <lb/>&quot; <lb/>&quot;&quot;&quot;&quot; <lb/>~ <lb/>2 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>8 <lb/>MAGNETIC FIELD (T) <lb/>Fig. 2. <lb/>Representative magnetoresistance <lb/>curves of La2Cu04 at various fixed <lb/>temperatures. <lb/>The magnetic field is <lb/>applied perpendicular <lb/>to the Cu-O <lb/>plane. <lb/>The inset displays the phase <lb/>diagram determined from the mid-point <lb/>of the magnetoresistance jump. <lb/>magnetic field applied perpendicular <lb/>to the <lb/>basal plane. <lb/>The resistance drops rather <lb/>sharply at some magnetic field, suggesting the <lb/>presence of a field-induced phase transition. <lb/>(The notation &quot;phase transition&quot; <lb/>is used in the <lb/>sense of characterizing <lb/>the anomalies observed <lb/>as the temperature or magnetic field is varied.) <lb/>The resistance <lb/>drop is of the order of 10% at <lb/>4 K and the effect diminishes as the temperature <lb/>is raised, becoming undetectable in our <lb/>measurements above 120 K. This leads to some <lb/>uncertainty <lb/>in determining the high temperature <lb/>portion of the magnetic field-temperature <lb/>phase <lb/>diagram shown in the inset of Fig. 2. <lb/>Hysteresis, <lb/>seen clearly in the 4 K-curve in <lb/>Fig. 2, reduces rapidly as the temperature <lb/>increases and is unnoticeable above 20 K. We <lb/>note that conduction is highly anisotropic <lb/>in <lb/>these crystals. <lb/>The anisotropy factor was <lb/>determined by the Montgomery method s in several <lb/>specimens. <lb/>Although slight variations <lb/>from <lb/>sample to sample were found, typical values for <lb/>the anisotropy are &gt;150 (&gt;250) at room tempera-<lb/>ture (liquid nitrogen temperature), with the <lb/>lower resistivity <lb/>in the Cu-O plane. <lb/>Such a <lb/>huge anisotropy in the electrical <lb/>resistivity <lb/>clearly demonstrates that La2Cu04 is electroni-<lb/>cally two-dimensional. <lb/>Futhermore, the CU-O <lb/>plane has a metallic-like <lb/>temperature dependent <lb/>resistivity <lb/>above ~130 K but is semiconductor-<lb/>like at lower temperatures; however, <lb/>conductivity perpendicular <lb/>to the Cu-O plane is <lb/>semiconductor-like <lb/>for all T &lt; 300 K. <lb/>I&apos;. <lb/>• .... <lb/>.AO,ETO <lb/>O&apos;T&apos; <lb/>/ <lb/>N <lb/>o% <lb/>Oeeoo.ooo.ooOe ¶ <lb/>N <lb/>QOO000000001~ <lb/>Z <lb/>Oo .......... <lb/>. .... <lb/>| <lb/>&quot;: <lb/>I <lb/>L <lb/>..Jo.6 <lb/>1 <lb/>0.3 T <lb/>= <lb/>l <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>TEMPERATURE (K) <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>Magnetization vs. temperature measured <lb/>with applied field 0.3 T (refer to <lb/>right vertical <lb/>scale), 2.5 T, and 4 T <lb/>(refer to left vertical <lb/>scale). <lb/>The <lb/>temperature at which the rounded peak <lb/>occurs is approximately 120 K (80 K) <lb/>at 0.3 T (2.5 T). <lb/>A magnetization <lb/>curve at 20 K is plotted in the inset. <lb/>The total mass of measured crystals <lb/>was 343.37 mg and the applied field is <lb/>perpendicular <lb/>to the basal plane. <lb/>rapidly to lower temperatures as the field is <lb/>increased and disappears in the field of 4 T. <lb/>[Below ~170 K, the susceptibility <lb/>measured in a <lb/>4 T field can be fit to Kmole = ~o + C/(T + e), <lb/>where Ko = 8.2 x 10 -~ emu/mole Cu, C = 5.3 x <lb/>10 -° emu-K/mole Cu, and e = 37.5 K, implying an <lb/>effective moment of 0.21 y.D/Cu i£ the Curie term <lb/>is due solely to Cu.] The utemperatures at which <lb/>the peak appears in various fields agree with <lb/>the phase boundary shown in the inset of Fig. 2, <lb/>additionally <lb/>supporting the presence of a phase <lb/>transition. <lb/>The magnetization as a function of <lb/>applied magnetic field perpendicular to the <lb/>basal plane at 20 K is displayed in the inset of <lb/>Fig. 3, where a slope change can be seen clearly <lb/>near 3 T. <lb/>The jump in magnetization at 3 T and <lb/>20 K, defined by the construction shown in the <lb/>inset, is ~5,9 x 10 -4 emu, which implies an <lb/>increase of 1.25 x 10 -4 pB/formula unit. <lb/>We <lb/>note that the magnetization curve as a function <lb/>of magnetic field taken at 2 K shows a large <lb/>hysteresis <lb/>which by 20 K becomes smaller than <lb/>the experimental resolution. <lb/>It is interesting <lb/>that magnetization vs. magnetic field applied in <lb/>the basal plane at various fixed temperatures <lb/>does not show a similar jump within the <lb/>sensitivity <lb/>in our measurement. <lb/>We also note <lb/>that for 4 K &lt; T &lt; 350 K the magnetic <lb/>susceptibility <lb/>measured with H in the basal <lb/>plane is nearly three times smaller than that <lb/>with the magnetic field perpendicular <lb/>to the <lb/>basal plane. <lb/></body>

	<note place="headnote">Vol. 65, No. 2 <lb/>NON-ANTIFERROMAGNETICALLY ORDERED CRYSTALS OF La2Cu04 <lb/></note>

	<body>Specific heat (C) measurements also were <lb/>performed on two of these crystals <lb/>{total mass <lb/>39.38 mg) and the results are plotted as C/T vs. <lb/>T 2 in Fig. 4. <lb/>As shown in the inset, an <lb/>200 <lb/>I <lb/>)_2 <lb/>• <lb/>G° <lb/>2~ • <lb/>--<lb/>o <lb/>G <lb/>lO <lb/>1G <lb/>TEMPERATURE2(K 21 <lb/>OeO °° <lb/>La 2 CuO 4 <lb/>° <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>I <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>TEMPERATURE 2 (K 2) <lb/>400 <lb/>~&quot; 150 <lb/>x-<lb/>I <lb/>(D <lb/>0 <lb/>El00 <lb/>&quot;-3 <lb/>E <lb/>I--<lb/>%-50 <lb/>o <lb/>the linear term in the specific heat also <lb/>appears to be intrinsic, <lb/>being observed in <lb/>different <lb/>single crystals as well as in <lb/>polycrystalline <lb/>samples of La2CuO 4. <lb/>We believe there is substantial <lb/>indirect <lb/>evidence that the phase transition <lb/>we observe is <lb/>not o£ conventional origin and is a bulk <lb/>property of La2CuO 4 crystals which do not order <lb/>three-dimensionally. <lb/>(1) <lb/>The extreme sensiti-<lb/>vity of the transition <lb/>temperature to applied <lb/>magnetic fields is to be contrasted with <lb/>observations ~° on the Neel temperature of oxygen <lb/>deficient <lb/>polycrystalline <lb/>samples in which 4.5 T <lb/>suppresses T N by only ~10%. <lb/>We find a similar <lb/>field dependence of T N in oxygen deficient <lb/>Fig. 4. <lb/>Specific heat divided by temperature <lb/>vs. temperature squared (C/T vs. T 2) <lb/>from 1.8 K to 20 K. As shown in the <lb/>inset, an extrapolated value for the <lb/>linear term in the specific heat is 1 <lb/>mJ/mole K 2 and the Debye 8 D is 320 K. <lb/>extrapolation <lb/>of the data to T = 0 gives a <lb/>finite <lb/>intercept of 1.0 ± 0.1 mJ/mole Cu K2, 7,e <lb/>which is unchanged in a 10 T magnetic field, <lb/>suggesting that the finite value of C/T at T = 0 <lb/>may not be related to the phase transition. <lb/>Normalized per unit volume, the result ~ = 8.8 <lb/>J/m3K 2 is smaller than metallic copper by one <lb/>order o£ magnitude but several times larger than <lb/>typical structural <lb/>glasses, e.g. vitreous <lb/>silica. <lb/>The low temperature upturn in C/T may <lb/>si~l <lb/>the onset o£ a nuclear Schottky anomaly; <lb/>although, an alternative <lb/>explanation has been <lb/>proposed 9 that attributes <lb/>this behavior to the <lb/>presence of a hyperfine magnetic field at the Cu <lb/>nucleus produced by itinerant <lb/>antiferromagnetic <lb/>order in the Cu-O planes. <lb/>We emphasize that our experimental findings <lb/>are not limited to one crystal but are highly <lb/>reproducible: <lb/>the response of the magnetic <lb/>susceptibility <lb/>and resistance <lb/>to temperature and <lb/>magnetic field reported here has been observed <lb/>in several crystals <lb/>from the same preparation <lb/>batch. <lb/>I~gnetoresistance <lb/>measurements on <lb/>La2Cu04 crystals prepared in a different <lb/>batch, <lb/>but using the same growth procedure, also show a <lb/>phase transition <lb/>at similar fields and tempera-<lb/>tures. <lb/>Furthermore, the transition <lb/>was affected <lb/>only weakly by doping crystals with Zn impuri-<lb/>ties and by removing small amounts of oxygen via <lb/>vacuum annealing with a Zr getter. <lb/>In the <lb/>latter case, still <lb/>no evidence for 3D antiferro-<lb/>magnetic order was found but the magneto-<lb/>resistance anomaly at 4 K was less pronounced. <lb/>Analysis of resistivity <lb/>data on these other <lb/>crystals <lb/>results <lb/>in H-T phase diagrams similar <lb/>to the one in the inset of Fig. 2. <lb/>Likewise. <lb/></body>

	<page>113 <lb/></page>

	<body>single crystals; <lb/>(2) The temperature dependence <lb/>of the phase transition <lb/>field is opposite that <lb/>expected for a conventional spin-flop <lb/>transition; <lb/>(3) The &quot;universality&quot; <lb/>of results <lb/>obtained on several different <lb/>single crystals <lb/>argues against impurities or defects causing the <lb/>phase transition; <lb/>and (4) Rather large changes <lb/>in the resistivity <lb/>and magnetization at the <lb/>transition <lb/>surest <lb/>that it is a bulk effect. <lb/>In the absence o£ detailed microscopic <lb/>measurements, it is difficult <lb/>to specify the <lb/>nature of the phase diagram we have observed. <lb/>As discussed earlier by others, 2 the small <lb/>susceptibility <lb/>for a system such as La2CuO 4 with <lb/>a large concentration of S = 1/2 spins suggests <lb/>the presence of strong antiferromagnetic <lb/>fluctuations <lb/>at room temperature or below. <lb/>The <lb/>absence o£ a well-defined <lb/>(i.e., <lb/>sharp in field <lb/>and temperature) phase transition <lb/>may be due to <lb/>either low dimensionality effects, <lb/>deviation <lb/>from perfect stoichiometry, <lb/>quantum fluctua-<lb/>tions, or frustrations <lb/>arising from nearest and <lb/>next-nearest <lb/>neighbor interactions. <lb/>Low <lb/>dimensionality has been invoked tl to account for <lb/>the relatively <lb/>low 3D antiferromagnetic <lb/>ordering <lb/>temperature in oxygen deficient <lb/>specimens. <lb/>Our <lb/>observations, <lb/>if related to 3D ordering, are of <lb/>a distinctly <lb/>different <lb/>nature because: <lb/>(1) a <lb/>magnetic field suppresses the transition <lb/>temperature much more rapidly than it does T N in <lb/>oxygen deficient <lb/>samples and (2) the transition <lb/>is insensitive <lb/>to partial <lb/>removal of oxygen. <lb/>An <lb/>attractive <lb/>alternative <lb/>is the possibility <lb/>of an <lb/>unusual transition <lb/>not involving 3D order, as <lb/>could be envisioned for a system with aniso-<lb/>tropic magnetic interactions <lb/>sufficiently <lb/>weak <lb/>that it could not be described within the <lb/>framework of either 2D Ising or Heisenberg <lb/>models. <lb/>Frustration <lb/>effects, <lb/>common to the <lb/>resonating valence bond model of Anderson, t2 <lb/>also are distinctly <lb/>possible explanations for <lb/>the observed phase transition. <lb/>Some of these <lb/>questions may be resolved by additional <lb/>experiments on single crystals <lb/>in which both <lb/>metal atoms and oxygen content are varied <lb/>systematically. <lb/></body>

	<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement -Work at Los Alamos was <lb/>performed under the auspices of the U.S. <lb/>Department of Energy, Office of Basic Energy <lb/>Sciences, Division of Materials Science. <lb/>Work <lb/>at UCLA was supported in part by National <lb/>Science Foundation Grant No. DbIR 87-8620340. <lb/></div>

	<page>114 <lb/></page>

	<note place="headnote">NON-ANTIFERROMAGNETICALLY ORDERED CRYSTALS OF La2Cu04 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>I. D. C. Johnston, J. P. Stokes, D. P. <lb/>Goshorn, and J. T. Lewandowski <lb/>(unpublished); T. Frelto£t, J. P. Remeika, <lb/>D. E. Moncton, A. S. Cooper, J. E. Fischer, <lb/>D. Harsh, <lb/>G. Shirane, S. K. Sinha, and <lb/>D. Vaknin, Phys. Rev. B 36, 826 (1987). <lb/>2. G. Shirane, Y. Endoh, R. J. Birgeneau, M. <lb/>A. Kastner, Y. Hidaka, M. Oda, M. Suzuki, <lb/>and T. Murakami (unpublished). <lb/>3. S-W. Cheong, Z. Fisk, J. D. Thompson, J. P. <lb/>Remeika, and G. Gruner (in preparation}. <lb/>4. W. C. Hamilton, International Tables for <lb/>X-ray CrystalloKraphy, Vol. IV, Kynoch <lb/>Press, Birmingham, UK, p. 282 (1974). <lb/>5. N. F. Mort and E. A. Davis, Electronic <lb/>Processes in Non-Crystalline Materials, <lb/>Oxford University Press (1971). <lb/>6. H. C. Montgomery, J. Appl. Phys. 42, 2971 <lb/>(1971). <lb/>7. Similar results have been reported by: <lb/>H. Maletta, M. W. Sharer, T. Penney, B. L. <lb/>Olson, A. M. Torressen, and R. L. Greene, <lb/>Physica B (in press); and N. E. Phillips, <lb/>R. A. Fisher, S. E. Lacy, C. Marcenat, J. <lb/>A. Olsen, W. K. Ham, and A. M. Stacy, Jpn. <lb/>J. Appl. Phys. 26, (Suppl. 26-3), 1115, <lb/>(1987). <lb/>S. The lattice contribution to the specific <lb/>heat can be estimated from the low <lb/>9. <lb/>10. <lb/>11. <lb/>12. <lb/></listBibl>

        <note place="headnote">Vol. 65, No. 2 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>temperature slope (~) of C/T vs. T 2. From <lb/>this slope we obtain a Debye temperature 8 D <lb/>= 320 ± 10 K. This value of 8 D may be <lb/>affected slightly by the presence of a <lb/>small bump near 25 K observed in a plot of <lb/>C/T 3 vs. T. The origin of this bump <lb/>possibly arises from an excess phonon <lb/>density of states relative to the Debye <lb/>model [A. Junod et al., Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. <lb/>26 (Suppl. 26-3), 1119 (1987)]. <lb/>P. Gutsmiedl, K. Andres, E. Amberger, and <lb/>H. Rietschel, Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. 26 <lb/>(Suppl. 26-3) 1117 (1987). <lb/>R. L. Greene, H. bialetta, T. S. P1askett, <lb/>J. G. Bednore, and K. A. Muller, Solid <lb/>State Commun. 63, 379 (1987). <lb/>Y. J. Uemura, W. J. Kossler, X. H. Yu, J. <lb/>R. Kempton, H. E. Schone, D. Opie, C. E. <lb/>Stronach, D. C. Johnston, M. S. A1varez, <lb/>and D. P. Goshorn, Phys. Rev. Lett. 59, <lb/>1045 (1987). <lb/>P. W. Anderson, Mat. Res. Bull. 8, 153 <lb/>(1973); Science 235, 1196 (1987); P. W. <lb/>Anderson, G. Baskaran, Z. Zou, and T. Hsu, <lb/>Phys. Rev. Lett. 58, 2790 (1987). </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
