<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">

        <titlePage>UC Irvine <lb/>UC Irvine Previously Published Works <lb/>Title <lb/>MAGNETIC AND THERMAL MEASUREMENTS ON HIGH-TC (LA0.9BA0.1)2CUO4-Y <lb/>Permalink <lb/>https://escholarship.org/uc/item/3rk861bn <lb/>Journal <lb/>SOLID STATE COMMUNICATIONS, 63(8) <lb/>ISSN <lb/>0038-1098 <lb/>Authors <lb/>ZIRNGIEBL, E <lb/>WILLIS, JO <lb/>THOMPSON, JD <lb/>et al. <lb/>Publication Date <lb/>1987-08-01 <lb/>DOI <lb/>10.1016/0038-1098(87)90118-9 <lb/>License <lb/>CC BY 4.0 <lb/>Peer reviewed <lb/>eScholarship.org <lb/>Powered by the California Digital Library <lb/>University of California <lb/></titlePage>

        ~
        <front>Solid State Communications, Vol.63,No.8, pp.721-724, ]987. <lb/>0038-1098/87 $3.00 + .00 <lb/>Printed in Great Britaln. <lb/>Pergamon Journals Ltd. <lb/>MAGNETIC AND THERMAL MFASURF.MENI&apos;S ON HIGH-T c (Lao.9Bao. I )2CuO~i-y <lb/>E. Zirngiebl, J. O. Willis, J. D. Thompson, C. Y. Huang, <lb/>J. L. Smith, and Z. Flsk <lb/>Los Alamos National Laboratory, Los Alamos, NI4 87545 <lb/>P. H. Hor, R. L. Meng, C. W. Chu <lb/>Department of Physics and Space Vacuum, Epitaxy Center <lb/>University of Houston, Houston, TX 77004 <lb/>and <lb/>M. K. Wu <lb/>Department of Physics, University of Alabema <lb/>Huntsville, AL 35899 <lb/>(Received April 7, 1987 by H. Suhl) <lb/>We have measured the magnetic moment of (l-~to.gBao.t)=C-&quot;u.O,-as a <lb/>function of temperature and magnetic field and have found the onset of <lb/>superconductivity at a temperature T ~ 3,5 K. From the magnetic field <lb/>dependencies, we have shown that the sample is a type-II superconductor <lb/>with ~ ~ 11. Specific heat measurements ~ield a finite electronic <lb/>specific heat coefficient of ~6 mJ/mole-K at 4 K and a Debye <lb/>temperature of only 330 K, suggesting that a strong electron-phonon <lb/>interaction may be responsible for the high T in our sample. <lb/></front>

        <body>Recently, high T c La-(Ba,Sr)-Cu-O supercon-<lb/>ductors have been intensively investigated, i-a <lb/>Bednorz and Muller i have measured the tempera-<lb/>ture dependence of the resistivity of <lb/>Bao.v6La4.zsCu6Os(3_y) and have found a <lb/>superconducting onset temperature Tco = 35 K <lb/>followed by the disappearance of resistivity <lb/>below To ~ 12 K. C~u et al. 4 have obtained Tco <lb/>35 K and To = 14 K for their Lai_xBaxCuOo_y <lb/>with x = 0.15 and 0.20, and at a pressure of <lb/>12 khar, Tco increases to 52.3 K and To to 25 K. <lb/>Very recently, they have improved the quality of <lb/>their sample and have obtained an excellent <lb/>sample (Lao.4~lao.1)~CuO4_v, whlchhas the K2NiF~ <lb/>crystal structure with Tc~ = 44 K and To = 28 K, <lb/>but, at 10 kber, Tco = q5 and To = 40K. <lb/>This <lb/>value of To is the highest among the <lb/>La-{Ba.Sr)-~--O system. Therefore, it is of <lb/>great interest to investigate the magnetic <lb/>properties of this material for the purpose of <lb/>providing more information on this new type of <lb/>high Tcmaterial. <lb/>A Quantum Design SQUID susceptometer has <lb/>been employed to measure the sample magnetiza-<lb/>tion M as a function of applied field and <lb/>temperatures. We obtain the susceptibility by K <lb/>= d}I/dHH= o. Figure 1 shows our results as a <lb/>function of temperature. The susceptibility <lb/>becomes negative below To = 31K. <lb/>However, it <lb/>starts to decrease at Tco = 35 K (not shown). <lb/>At 2 K, K = 3.3 x I0 &quot;~ emu/cm 3. which is 42X of <lb/>perfect diamagnetism, indicating bulk supercon-<lb/>ductivity in the sample. <lb/>In order to observe <lb/>the Melssner effect, we have measured the <lb/>mAgnetlzation as the sample was cooled in a <lb/></body>

        <page>721 <lb/></page>

        <body>E <lb/>0 <lb/>E <lb/>I <lb/>o <lb/>&gt;-<lb/>_---J <lb/>ca <lb/>I-<lb/>n <lb/>ILl <lb/>0 <lb/>CO <lb/>~-3 <lb/>(~ <lb/>-4 <lb/>0 <lb/>Fig. I. <lb/>,b <lb/>~o <lb/>~o <lb/>TEMPERATURE <lb/>(K) <lb/>Temperature dependence of the magnetic <lb/>susceptibility K of ~t.aBe~.~CuO4.y <lb/>defined from dN/dH (H = 0), where M is <lb/>the magnetization. <lb/></body>

        <page>722 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">MAGNETIC AND THERMAL MEASUREMENTS ON HIGH-T c (Lao.gBaO. l)2CuO4_y <lb/></note>

        <body>field. HCOOL. Figure 2 shows the temperature <lb/>dependence of N at HCOOL = 30. 45. 60. 75 and <lb/>90 G. As shown. M is negative below To. and it <lb/>increases with increasing HCOOL. The inset <lb/>exhibits the field dependencies of M at 2 and <lb/>15 K. both of which clearly indicate that M is <lb/>not linear in HCOOL. <lb/>-1 <lb/>E <lb/>o <lb/>E <lb/>-2 <lb/>T <lb/>o <lb/>Z <lb/>0 <lb/>F---3 <lb/>&lt;C <lb/>b-<lb/>uJ <lb/>Z <lb/>(D <lb/>-4 <lb/>HCOOL=30 G * <lb/>ooetooo •°° <lb/>45 G ,&quot; <lb/>,~ <lb/>• ••• <lb/>m~o <lb/>• <lb/>-o <lb/>60 G <lb/>&quot; <lb/>&quot; <lb/>• <lb/>o <lb/>• mum• <lb/>v <lb/>v <lb/>o <lb/>Q <lb/>75 G,&quot; <lb/>vvvv <lb/>o <lb/>o <lb/>-90 Go ° <lb/>OOOo <lb/>o <lb/>• | almmm=&quot; m&apos;=&quot; <lb/>• II <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>D <lb/>l <lb/>• <lb/>o <lb/>o kal. 8 Bao. 2 Cu 04_y <lb/>(U -24) <lb/>~) ~. -8[ *2K <lb/>~-E•-6F ~ 15 K <lb/>--&apos;F <lb/>/. <lb/>zT <lb/>/ <lb/>//o, <lb/>~o <lb/>21 <lb/>//* <lb/>-<lb/>&apos;= 0I// <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>HCOOL(G) <lb/>1 &apos;O <lb/>2AO <lb/>3LO <lb/>TEMPERATURE <lb/>(K) <lb/>-5 <lb/>~etization <lb/>of La s .eBao.2CuO4_y as a <lb/>function of temperature on field co•l-<lb/>ing for different applied magnetic <lb/>fields. The inset shows the field <lb/>cooled magnetization values for T = <lb/>2 K, 15 K as a function of the applied <lb/>field. <lb/>Fig. 2. <lb/>The magnetization as a function of applied <lb/>magnetic field is shown in Figs. 3 and 4 for two <lb/>different ranges of applied field. Each of <lb/>these M vs. H curves displays a peak, whose <lb/>shape is reminiscent of behavior typical for a <lb/>type-II superconductor. <lb/>From these peaks (Fig. <lb/>3), we obtain the lower critical field, H ~. <lb/>Its temperature dependence is shown in Fig. 5, <lb/>and is quite different from that of a conven-<lb/>tional type-If superconductor. <lb/>By linearly <lb/>extrapolating N at high fields to M = 0 in Fig. <lb/>4, we obtain the upper critical field Hc2. Its <lb/>temperature dependence is depicted in Fig. 5 and <lb/>is again unexpected for a type-If superconduc-<lb/>tor. From Hct and Hc=, we can deduce the <lb/>coherence length ~ = 6.7 run, the thermodynamic <lb/>critical field Hc = 4900 G. and the Ginzburg-<lb/>Landau parameter K = 11 at 2 K. <lb/>v <lb/>z <lb/>0 <lb/>C---3 <lb/>&lt; <lb/>-21 <lb/>z <lb/>0 <lb/>t <lb/>0 <lb/>o <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>Lat8 Ba o 2Cu 04-y <lb/>(J -24) <lb/>Rcl J <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Vol. 63, No. 8 <lb/></note>

        <body>-1.6 <lb/>% <lb/>0 <lb/>~-1.2 <lb/>Z <lb/>_o <lb/>D--<lb/>&lt;~ -0.8 <lb/>N <lb/>I--<lb/>LU <lb/>Z <lb/>&lt;-0.4 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>Fig. 4. <lb/>.o4 <lb/>E <lb/>.03 • <lb/>-r <lb/>E3 <lb/>.J <lb/>U. <lb/>.021 <lb/>&lt;c <lb/>o <lb/>P_ <lb/>o-<lb/>o <lb/>or&quot; .01 <lb/>tJJ <lb/>0 <lb/>...=/ <lb/>o o <lb/>Fig. 5. <lb/>• 2K <lb/>A5 <lb/>v8 <lb/>&quot;1 <lb/>&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp;&amp; <lb/>• <lb/>VVVVVVVV <lb/>t =~=s== <lb/>L <lb/>t <lb/>I <lb/>t <lb/>t <lb/>I <lb/>t <lb/>.02 <lb/>.04 <lb/>.06 <lb/>.08 <lb/>MAGNETICFIE~(T) <lb/>Magnetic ~mont N vs. ~etic <lb/>field H <lb/>(H &lt; 7~G) <lb/>at ~rious temperatures <lb/>for ~2.e~o.2~04-y. <lb/>The ~sition of <lb/>the maximum defines the lower crlti~l <lb/>field Hcl. <lb/>• 2K <lb/>• 5K <lb/>• 8K <lb/>=11K <lb/>o 17K <lb/>Lat8 Bao. 2 Cu 04 -y <lb/>(J -24) <lb/>@<lb/>t <lb/>@ <lb/>6 <lb/>t <lb/>• <lb/>n <lb/>• <lb/>T <lb/>~ <lb/>n <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>6 <lb/>MAGNETIC FIELD (T) <lb/>o <lb/>i <lb/>1 <lb/>Nagnetic moment M vs. magnetic field H <lb/>(H &gt; 1 kG) at various temperatures for <lb/>Lat.eBao.20~O4.y. <lb/>• HCl <lb/>Lal. 8 Bao~Cu O4-y <lb/>• Hc2 <lb/>(J -24) <lb/>i <lb/>30 <lb/>TEMPERATURE (K) <lb/>t0 <lb/>Upper and lower critical fields of <lb/>Lai.iBao.2CuO4_y as a functon of <lb/>temperature. <lb/>@<lb/>E <lb/>83 <lb/>Q <lb/>.M <lb/>_,,, <lb/>tL <lb/>4.J <lb/>0 <lb/>F-<lb/>0 <lb/>2fr <lb/>tU <lb/></body>

        <note place="headnote">Vol. 63, No. 8 <lb/>MAGNETIC AND THERMAL MEASUREMENTS ON HIGH-T c (Lao.9Bao.l)2CuO4_y <lb/></note>

        <body>As shown in Fig. 6, the susceptibility <lb/>[ <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>above Tco is 1.2 x I0 &quot;~ emu/mole and nearly <lb/>I LatsBao. 2 Cu 04_y <lb/>independent of temperature. We thus identify <lb/>e~ <lb/>(J -6 -3) <lb/>this as the Pauli susceptibility K~. Using the <lb/>free-electron model, ~p = 3~tB2~/(~B) z, we <lb/>obtain the electronic specific heat coefficient <lb/>= 8.5 mJlmole-K =. Another (Lao.gBao.t)2CuO4_y <lb/>~ 4~ <lb/>sample (J-6-3) with I0~ diamagnetic signal gives <lb/>~p = 3.05 x 10 &quot;~ emu/mole (see Fig. 6), yielding <lb/>= 2.23 mJlmele-K =. For another sample, <lb/>~ <lb/>1 <lb/>** <lb/>(Lao.vSro.s)zCuO~_y (SL-6), wlth 83~ of perfect <lb/>o~ 2001 <lb/>&apos;&apos;0 <lb/>dlamagnetlsmand K~ = 5.11 x I0&quot; enm/mole, we <lb/>0&quot; <lb/>have ~ = 3.7 mJlmo[e-K z. <lb/>In comparison, we flnd <lb/>..*&quot; <lb/>our present sample has the highest ~ value. <lb/>Because of our use of the free-electron model, <lb/>o ~P... <lb/>we only expect the ~ values to be moderately <lb/>o <lb/>accurate. <lb/>E <lb/>Et5 <lb/>= <lb/>o <lb/>~10 <lb/>&gt;-<lb/>m <lb/>~ 5 <lb/>if) <lb/>~ o <lb/>Fig. 6. <lb/>I•ee <lb/>•• <lb/>~-Lat 8 Ba0,2Cu <lb/>O4 -y <lb/>I I <lb/>I I I I I I I = I I I I = I I I I = (J -24) <lb/>L818 Slo. 2 Cu 04 -y <lb/>• <lb/>t <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>. <lb/>(SL -6) <lb/>• La~sBao2Cu <lb/>04-<lb/>y <lb/>• . ...... <lb/>&quot;•&apos;•.. <lb/>..... <lb/>*&apos;.,. <lb/>&apos;&apos;&apos; <lb/>&quot;&apos;(J-6-3) <lb/>5o <lb/>,~o <lb/>,~o <lb/>2~o <lb/>2~o <lb/>3~o <lb/>3&apos;~o <lb/>TEMPERATURE <lb/>(K) <lb/>Paramagnetlc susceptibility of <lb/>Lat.sBao.~CuO4_yand Lal.sSro.2CuO4.y <lb/>samples in the normal state as a <lb/>function of temperature. <lb/>For comperlson, we have made specific heat <lb/>measurements. For this purpose, approximately <lb/>55 mg of the (Lao.gBao.1)zCuO4_y powder with I0~ <lb/>perfect diamagnetism (sample J-6-3) was pressed <lb/>into a pellet to improve the sample thermal <lb/>conductivity. The specimen was mounted on the <lb/>platform of a small sample calorimeter with a <lb/>small amount of Wakefield thermal compound. The <lb/>specific heat was measured by the time constant <lb/>relaxation method 6 between 4 and 36 K. The <lb/>experimental precision was about ±3Z, and the <lb/>addenda contribution was between 15 and 20~ of <lb/>the total measured specific heat. The results <lb/>are shown in Flg. 7, plotted as C/T vs. T 2. <lb/>Because of the relatively large scatter in the <lb/>data, it was not possible to directly observe <lb/>the specific heat Jump at the superconducting <lb/>transition. Below about 10 K, the specific heat <lb/>can be represented as cJ&apos;r = ~ + /yr 2. where ~ is <lb/>related to the Deby_e temperature ODand Is <lb/>proportional to 0 D . From these data, one can <lb/>I <lb/>el <lb/>7 IIK)~ <lb/>4;0&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>&apos; <lb/>8;0 <lb/>&apos; <lb/>1200 <lb/>&apos; <lb/>,eO0 <lb/>(Temperature) 2 (K)2 <lb/>Fig. 7. <lb/>Specific heat C of Lat.s]~.2CuO4-y <lb/>T 2 , <lb/>plotted as CJT vs. <lb/>The inset <lb/>shows details of the low temperature <lb/>region. <lb/></body>

        <page>723 <lb/></page>

        <body>extract a ~ value of 6 ± 0.6 mJ/mole-K 2 and a 8 D <lb/>of 330 ± I0 K. The finite value of ~ suggests <lb/>that not all of the sample is superconducting <lb/>even though an x-ray study showed the sample to <lb/>have only the K2NiF= crystal structure. <lb/>Evidence of a gap from infrared transmission <lb/>experiments s would seem to preclude the <lb/>possibility of (Lao.9~to.s)2CuO4_y being a <lb/>gapless superconductor. <lb/>Based on specific heat <lb/>measurements on a sample of (Lao.~iSro.og)zCu04 <lb/>that showed a 55X Meissner effect, a 81) of <lb/>360 K. and a ~ value of 2.SmJlmele-K 2, it <lb/>seems likely that the observed ~ results from <lb/>volumes of the majority phase that are <lb/>nonsuperconductlng due to stoichiometry <lb/>variations. <lb/>If the superconducting fraction of <lb/>the sample can be assumed proportional to the <lb/>size of the Melssner effect (IOX), then the <lb/>nonsuperconducting fraction of approximately 90&quot;Z <lb/>must be responsible for the finite ~ value <lb/>observed, and the true value of ~ must be at <lb/>least lOXhlgher, approximately 6.6 to 7 <lb/>mJlmole-K ~ . This ~ value is in reasonable <lb/>accord wlth that estimated from the Paull <lb/>susceptibility (~ = 2.2 mJ/mole-K2). The Debye <lb/>temperature is lower than expected, indicating <lb/>that the high T c value in our sample may arise <lb/>from strong electron-phonon interactions. <lb/>In conclusion, mag~etlc measurements have <lb/>shown that our sample is a bulk type-II super-<lb/>conductor with Tco= 35 K and K = 11. The <lb/>value obtained from specific heat is not very <lb/>high relatlve to a typical A-15 superconductor <lb/>(such as Nb3Sn with ~ = 52 mJ/mole-K2), v We <lb/>conclude that a strong electron-phonon inter-<lb/>action may be responsible for the high T c. <lb/></body>

        <listBibl>References <lb/>I. <lb/>J.G. Bednorz and K. A. Muller. Z. Phys. B <lb/>64, 189 (1986). <lb/>2. <lb/>C.W. Chu. P. H. Hor, R. L. Meng, L. Gao. <lb/>Z. J. Huang, and Y. Q. Wang, Phys. Rev. <lb/>Lett. 58. 405 (1987). <lb/>3. <lb/>R.j. Cava, R. B. VanDover, B. Batlogg, and <lb/>E. A. Rietman, Phys. Rev. Lett. 58, 408 <lb/>( 1987 ). <lb/>d. <lb/>C.W. Chu, P. H. Hor, R. L. Neng, L. Gao, <lb/>and Z. J. Huang, Science 235. 567 (1987). <lb/></listBibl>

        <page>724 <lb/></page>

        <note place="headnote">MAGNETIC AND THERMAL HEASUREMENTS ON HICH-Tc (Lao. 9BAG. l)2CuO4_y <lb/>Vol. 63, No. 8 <lb/></note>

        <listBibl>5. <lb/>S. Vehida, N. Takagl, S. Uchida, K. <lb/>Instrum. 43, 20~ {1972}. <lb/>Kit~Awa and S. Tamalm, preprint. <lb/>7. <lb/>L.J. Vieland and A. W. Wicklund, <lb/>6. <lb/>R. Bechman, F. J. DiSalvo, T. H. Geballe, <lb/>Phys. Rev. 166, 424 (1968). <lb/>R. L. Greene, R. E. Hoard, C. N. King, H. <lb/>8. <lb/>Z. Schlesinger, R. L. Greene, J. G. <lb/>C. Kirsch, K. N. Lee, R. E. Schwall, H.U. <lb/>Bednorz, and K. A. Muller, unpublished. <lb/>Thomas, and R. B. Zubeck, Rev. Sci. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
