<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/>Studies on La 2-x Pr x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z (x = 0.1 -0.5, y = 2x) type mixed <lb/>oxide superconductors <lb/>S. Rayaprol a, * , K. R. Mavani a , D. S. Rana a , C. M. Thaker a , Manglesh Dixit b , <lb/>Shovit Bhattacharya b and D. G. Kuberkar a <lb/>a Department of Physics, Saurashtra University, Rajkot -005 (INDIA) <lb/>b Department of Physics, Barkatullah University, Bhopal (INDIA) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The La 2-x Pr x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z (LaPrCaBCO) mixed oxides have been studied for their structural and <lb/>superconducting properties using X-ray diffraction (XRD), d. c. resistivity, d. c. susceptibility and <lb/>iodometric double titration. All the LaPrCaBCO samples for x = 0.1 -0.5, exhibit tetragonal crystalline <lb/>structure with P 4/mmm space group as determined by Rietveld analysis of the X-ray diffraction data. <lb/>With increasing x, enhancement in T c is observed, which is quite interesting for Pr substituted high T c <lb/>oxides. Maximum T c ~ 58 K has been observed for x = 0.5 <lb/>(La-2125 stoichiometry). The results of <lb/>structural studies and superconducting property measurements are presented in light of increase in T c in <lb/>LaPrCaBCO system with increasing Pr concentration. <lb/>Keywords: <lb/>La-2125, Pr-substitution, Rietveld analysis, hole concentration, oxygen content <lb/>PACS: <lb/>74.62.Dh, 74.72.Dn <lb/> * Corresponding Author, Present Address: DCMP &amp; MS, TIFR, Mumbai, India (sudhindra@rayaprol.com) <lb/></front>

            <note place="headnote">Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/></note>

            <body>1. <lb/> INTRODUCTION <lb/>The substitution of Pr in R-123 (R = <lb/>rare earth) and related systems has been widely <lb/>studied, for its role in suppressing <lb/>superconductivity either due to hybridization <lb/>between Pr (4f) and conducting CuO 2 (2p) <lb/>plane leading to localization of mobile charge <lb/>carriers and/or hole filling by fluctuating <lb/>valence of Pr (3+ or 4+) at rare earth or even at <lb/>Ba (Barium) site [1-5]. Even though many <lb/>studies have been carried out on these <lb/>compounds, yet the correct explanation for <lb/>such a phenomenon is still a matter of debate. <lb/>Majority of Pr substituted R-123 and derived <lb/>systems have shown decrease in T c with <lb/>increasing Pr concentration. The Pr-substituted <lb/>R-123 compounds also show rare earth ion <lb/>effect and for every x cr (critical Pr <lb/>concentration) with respect to the R ion, <lb/>superconductivity is totally suppressed [6, 7]. <lb/>Our <lb/>studies <lb/>on <lb/>the <lb/>La 2-<lb/>x R x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z (La-2125) type of R-123 <lb/>derived compounds have shown enhancement <lb/>in T c with increasing x, with maximum T c ~ 78 <lb/>K achieved with different R, for x = 0.5 <lb/>compound [8,9]. It has been established that T c <lb/>is related to the hole concentration in Cu-O <lb/>sheets (p sh ) [10]. By adding equal amounts of <lb/>CaO and CuO in non-superconducting, <lb/>tetragonal <lb/>La Ba 2 Cu 4 O z <lb/>(x <lb/>= <lb/>0.0), <lb/>superconductivity is &apos;turned on&apos; with <lb/>maximum T c achieved for x = 0.5 (La-2125) <lb/>compound. <lb/>In R-123 systems, magnetic moment <lb/>of R does not contribute to superconducting <lb/>properties, except for Ce, Tb and Pr [11]. Pr-<lb/>substituted <lb/>systems <lb/>become <lb/>non-<lb/>superconductor above x cr , where as, in the <lb/>present study we observe increase in T c in with <lb/>increase in Pr concentration. <lb/>2. <lb/>EXPERIMENTAL <lb/>All the samples of LaPrCaBCO series <lb/>(x = 0.1 -0.5) were synthesized by solid state <lb/>reaction method. The high purity (99.9+ %) <lb/>starting compounds of La O 3 , BaCO 3 , CaCO 3 , <lb/>CuO and Pr 6 O 11 were taken in stoichiometric <lb/>quantities and grinded thoroughly using agate <lb/>and mortar under acetone. The calcination and <lb/>sintering of these compounds were carried out <lb/>in pellet form in the temperature range of 930 <lb/>-940 0 C for about 72 hrs with intermediate <lb/>grindings. Thus prepared samples were <lb/>annealed in oxygen at 500 C for about 24 hrs <lb/>and then slow cooled to room temperature. <lb/>The samples were characterized for <lb/>their structural properties by X-ray diffraction <lb/>(Cu-K α , λ = 1.5405 Å) at room temperature. <lb/>All the XRD patterns show single phase <lb/>formation. The patterns were then fitted by <lb/>Rietveld analysis using FULLPROF program <lb/>[12]. The results show that there is no <lb/>structural transition in the entire doping range, <lb/>as all the samples are tetragonal, with <lb/>decreasing unit cell parameters and volume. <lb/>The transition temperature were recorded by <lb/>four probe d. c. resistivity method and verified <lb/>by d. c. susceptibility method, using a <lb/>commercial SQUID magnetometer. Both the <lb/>values are in good agreement, showing the <lb/>good quality of samples. The oxygen content <lb/>for all the samples were determined by <lb/>iodometric double titration method. The hole <lb/>concentration in the unit cell, and also in Cu-O <lb/>sheets were calculated from oxygen content <lb/>values using Tokura&apos;s method [13]. <lb/>3. <lb/>RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>The XRD Rietveld fitted patterns are <lb/>shown in Figure 1. The refinement was done <lb/>assuming an R-123 tetragonal unit cell and all <lb/>the patterns fits well into this model. The <lb/>occupancies were kept fixed, as per the site <lb/>occupancy, and the fitting parameters like, <lb/>scale factor, zero angle correction, atomic <lb/>positions, half width parameters, unit cell <lb/>parameters etc were varied to fit the observed <lb/>and calculated profiles. The results of the <lb/>analysis are listed in Table 1. Figure 2 shows <lb/>the variation of unit cell parameters and <lb/>volume with respect to increasing x. The <lb/>decrease in unit cell parameters and cell <lb/>volume can be attributed to the fact that, <lb/>smaller ionic radii ions Pr and Ca are replacing <lb/>La. <lb/>Since the starting model was assumed <lb/>to be an R-123 tetragonal structure, the <lb/>LaPrCaBCO (x = 0.1 -0.5) were normalized <lb/>to La-123. In this normalized form, La shares <lb/>its site with both Pr and Ca; similarly Ba site is <lb/>occupied by Ba, Ca and La. Increasing x, <lb/>increases the percentage of Ca onto La and La <lb/>onto Ba site. During initial refinements, Pr was <lb/>kept full and fixed at La site. The refinement <lb/>converged with good agreement between <lb/>observed and calculated patterns. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 1. XRD Rietveld fitted pattern for all the <lb/>samples. The open circles represent data <lb/>points, and the line passing through them <lb/>shows calculated pattern. The difference <lb/>between observed and calculated pattern is <lb/>shown for x = 0.5 sample <lb/>Fig.2. Variation in unit cell parameters and <lb/>volume with increasing Pr (x) content. <lb/>Subsequent refinements with Pr <lb/>distributed at both La and Ba site did not <lb/>improve the fitting. Hence, Pr was kept full <lb/>and fixed at La site during final analysis. There <lb/>is also concomitant displacement of La onto <lb/>Ba site. The Ca occupying La site and La onto <lb/>Ba site can be viewed as hole doping and hole <lb/>filling respectively. Also there is some portion <lb/>of Ca at Ba site, which we assume may be <lb/>counter balancing the hole filling by La. <lb/>Looking at Table 1, out of total Ca in the <lb/>sample, the Ca concentration increases from 35 <lb/>% (for x = 0.1) to 68% (x = 0.5) at La site. The <lb/>occupancy of Ca at La site increases from 39% <lb/>-41 %. <lb/>Fig. 3. <lb/>Transition temperatures for <lb/>La 2-x Pr x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z compounds determined <lb/>by resistivity and susceptibility as a function of <lb/>temperature. <lb/>Figure 3 shows the transition <lb/>temperatures observed by electrical (resistance <lb/>vs. temperature) and magnetic (susceptibility <lb/>vs. temperature) methods. It is interesting to <lb/>observe here that, with increasing Ca <lb/>concentration at La site (as x increases), <lb/>transition temperature increases, as can be seen <lb/>in Figure 4. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/></note>

			<body>Fig. 4. Variation in T c with increasing x, for <lb/>R = Nd, Dy and Pr in La 2-x R x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z <lb/>The Figure 4 also shows, for the sake <lb/>of comparison, the increase in T c for Nd and <lb/>Dy substituted La-2125 compounds. The <lb/>difference in maximum T c achieved by Pr and <lb/>Nd &amp; Dy systems is quite large (~ 20 K). <lb/>Fig. 5. Change in oxygen content and hole <lb/>concentration in sheets (p sh ). <lb/>The Pr is known to hybridize with <lb/>conducting CuO 2 plane and localize the mobile <lb/>charge carriers. On the other hand, Ca is a <lb/>known hole dopant in R-123 systems. In <lb/>LaPrCaBCO system also, increasing x, <lb/>increases <lb/>oxygen <lb/>content <lb/>and <lb/>hole <lb/>concentration, as shown in Figure 5. Thus, we <lb/>can feel that the rise in T c (but not up to <lb/>maximum of La-2125 system i.e., ~ 78K) in <lb/>LaPrCaBCO <lb/>is due to the competition <lb/>between hole filling and/or hybridization and <lb/>hole doping which results from the <lb/>simultaneous increase of both Pr and Ca with <lb/>x. <lb/>4. <lb/>CONCLUSION <lb/>The studies on LaPrCaBCO system, <lb/>presents a unique case of increase in T c with <lb/>the simultaneous increase of both Pr and Ca. <lb/>The present study also highlights the role of Ca <lb/>in contributing conducting holes to, otherwise <lb/>non-superconductor, and &apos;turning on&apos; the <lb/>superconductivity. The present result of <lb/>increase in T c with x is in consistence with our <lb/>earlier observations, for different R, except for <lb/>the maximum T c achieved. We feel that <lb/>LaPrCaBCO <lb/>compounds <lb/>are <lb/>possible <lb/>candidates for further investigations in better <lb/>understanding for the actual role Pr in high T c <lb/>oxides. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGEMENTS <lb/>The authors are thankful to Dr. D. C. <lb/>Kundaliya and Prof. S. K. Malik for magnetic <lb/>measurements. The work at Saurashtra <lb/>University, Rajkot was carried out under the <lb/>IUC-DAEF (India) project number CRS-M-88 <lb/>of Dr. D. G. Kuberkar. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>[1] <lb/>V. P. S. Awana, Claudio A. Cardoso, <lb/>O. F. de Lima, Rajvir Singh, A. V. <lb/>Narlikar, W. B. Yelon and S. K. <lb/>Malik. Physica C 316 (1999) 113 and <lb/>references there in <lb/>[2] <lb/>H. M. Luo, S. Y. Ding, G. X. Lu, Z. <lb/>Y. Chen. Physica C 364-365 (2001) <lb/>254 <lb/>[3] <lb/>Katsukuni Yoshida. Phys. Rev. B 60 <lb/>(1999) 9325 <lb/>[4] <lb/>Zhigang Zou, Jihua Ye, Kunihiko <lb/>Oka and Yoshikazu Nishihara. Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 80 (1998) 1074 <lb/>[5] <lb/>H. A. Blackstead and John D. Dow. <lb/>Phys. Rev B 57 (1998) 5048 <lb/>[6] <lb/>Yunhui Xu and Weiyan Guan. Phys. <lb/>Rev. B 45 (1992) 3176 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[7] <lb/>S. K. Malik, C. V. Tomy and <lb/>P. Bhargava. Phys. Rev. B (1991) <lb/>7042 <lb/>[8] <lb/>S. Rayaprol, Krushna Mavani, D. S. <lb/>Rana, C. M. Thaker, R. S. Thampi, D. <lb/>G. Kuberkar, R. G. Kulkarni and S. <lb/>K. Malik, <lb/>J. of Supercond. 15 (2002) 211 <lb/>[9] <lb/>S. Rayaprol, Krushna Mavani, C. M. <lb/>Thaker, <lb/>D. <lb/>S. <lb/>Rana, <lb/>Keka <lb/>Chakravorty, S. K. Paranjape, M. <lb/>Ramanadham, Nilesh Kulkarni and D. <lb/>G. Kuberkar Pramana -Ind. J of <lb/>Physics, 58 (2002) 877 <lb/>[10] <lb/>D. G. Kuberkar, N. A. Shah, R. S. <lb/>Thampi, M. R. Gonal, Ram Prasad <lb/>and R. G. Kulkarni. Physica B <lb/>281&amp;282 (2000) 924 <lb/>[11] <lb/>Z. Fisk, J. D. Thompson, E. Zirngiebl, <lb/>J. L. Smith and S-W. Cheong. Solid <lb/>State Commun. 62 (1987) 743 <lb/>[12] <lb/>J. Rodriquez-Carvajal. Physica B 192 <lb/>(1993) 55 <lb/>[13] <lb/>Y. Tokura, Y. B. Torrance, T. C. <lb/>Huang and A. I. Nazzal. <lb/>Phys Rev B 38 (1988) 7156 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Submitted for publication in Solid State Communications, 2003 <lb/></note>

			<body>Table 1 <lb/>Values obtained from the Rietveld analysis of La 2-x Pr x Ca y Ba 2 Cu 4+y O z compounds for <lb/>x = 0.1 -0.5 (y = 2x) <lb/>Sample (x, y) <lb/>Parameters <lb/>(0.1, 0.2) <lb/>(0.2, 0.4) <lb/>(0.3, 0.6) <lb/>(0.4, 0.8) <lb/>(0.5, 1.0) <lb/>Space group <lb/>a = b (Å) <lb/>c (Å) <lb/>P4/MMM <lb/>3.8988 (3) <lb/>11.7235 (8) <lb/>P4/MMM <lb/>3.8824 (3) <lb/>11.6698 (8) <lb/>P4/MMM <lb/>3.8724 (3) <lb/>11.6417 (8) <lb/>P4/MMM <lb/>3.8650 (3) <lb/>11.6336 (8) <lb/>P4/MMM <lb/>3.8712 (3) <lb/>11.6388 (8) <lb/>La/Pr/Ca <lb/>(½, ½, ½) <lb/>N La <lb/>N Pr <lb/>N Ca <lb/>0.821 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.035 <lb/>0.630 <lb/>0.143 <lb/>0.094 <lb/>0.451 <lb/>0.184 <lb/>0.279 <lb/>0.476 <lb/>0.226 <lb/>0.226 <lb/>0.274 <lb/>0.275 <lb/>0.395 <lb/>Ba (½,½, z) <lb/>z <lb/>N <lb/>0.1804 <lb/>1.433 <lb/>0.1830 <lb/>1.328 <lb/>0.1819 <lb/>1.242 <lb/>0.1864 <lb/>1.255 <lb/>0.1868 <lb/>1.120 <lb/>La @ Ba (N) <lb/>0.505 <lb/>0.509 <lb/>0.594 <lb/>0.505 <lb/>0.560 <lb/>Ca @ Ba (N) <lb/>0.076 <lb/>0.090 <lb/>0.142 <lb/>0.255 <lb/>0.180 <lb/>Cu (1) (0,0,0) <lb/>N <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>1.000 <lb/>Cu (2) (0,0,z) <lb/>z <lb/>N <lb/>0.3504 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.3521 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.3535 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.3536 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.3596 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>O (1) (0,½,0) <lb/>N <lb/>1.0562 <lb/>1.3192 <lb/>1.0100 <lb/>0.9415 <lb/>1.5050 <lb/>O (2) (0,0,z) <lb/>z <lb/>N <lb/>0.1527 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.1687 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.1594 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.1626 <lb/>2.0000 <lb/>0.1575 <lb/>1.3903 <lb/>O (4) (0,½,z) <lb/>z <lb/>N <lb/>0.3653 <lb/>4.0000 <lb/>0.3799 <lb/>4.0000 <lb/>0.3687 <lb/>4.0000 <lb/>0.3622 <lb/>4.0000 <lb/>0.3735 <lb/>3.1823 <lb/>Total Oxygen <lb/>(z&apos; -in 123) <lb/>(z -in 2125) <lb/>7.0562 <lb/>9.8786 <lb/>7.3192 <lb/>10.7348 <lb/>7.0997 <lb/>10.8862 <lb/>6.9415 <lb/>11.1064 <lb/>7.0692 <lb/>11.7820 <lb/>Factors <lb/>χ 2 <lb/>R p <lb/>2.18 <lb/>22.8 <lb/>2.01 <lb/>28.9 <lb/>2.20 <lb/>30.6 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>35.2 <lb/>1.57 <lb/>32.7 </body>


	</text>
</tei>
