<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Solid State Communications <lb/>Submitted: April 22, 2003 <lb/>Superconductivity in CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ <lb/>Y. Morita, H. Yamauchi, M. Karppinen* <lb/>Materials and Structures Laboratory, Tokyo Institute of Technology, Yokohama 226-8503, Japan <lb/>____________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The roles of aliovalent Ca II -for-Y III substitution and high-pressure-oxygen annealing in the <lb/>process of &quot;superconducterizing&quot; the Co-based layered copper oxide, CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ <lb/>(Co-1212), were investigated. The as-air-synthesized samples up to x = 0.4 were found essentially <lb/>oxygen stoichiometric (-0.03 ≤ δ ≤ 0.00). These samples, however, were not superconductive, <lb/>suggesting that the holes created by the divalent-for-trivalent cation substitution are trapped on <lb/>Co in the charge reservoir. Ultra-high-pressure heat treatment carried out at 5 GPa and 500 o C for <lb/>30 min in the presence of Ag 2 O 2 as an excess oxygen source induced bulk superconductivity in <lb/>these samples. The highest T c was obtained for the high-oxygen-pressure treated x = 0.3 sample at <lb/>∼40 K. <lb/>PACS : 74.10.+v; 74.25.Dw; 74.62.Bf; 74.72.Jt <lb/>Keywords: A. High-T c superconductors; B. Chemical synthesis; E. High-pressure <lb/>____________________________________________________________________________ <lb/>*Corresponding author: karppinen@msl.titech.ac.jp <lb/></front>

			<body>The still expanding variety of high-T c superconductive and related M m A 2 Q n-1 Cu n O m+2+2n±δ <lb/>(M-m2(n-1)n; category-A) and M m A 2k B s Cu 1+k O m+4k+2s±δ (M-m(2k)s(1+k); category-B) phases are <lb/>all based on rather robust CuO 2 planes stacked with other layer blocks that are more flexible in <lb/>the cation and/or oxygen composition [1]. The A site is typically occupied by Ba, Sr or La, <lb/>whereas the Q site prefers somewhat smaller cations of Ca, and/or Y and other (smaller) rare <lb/>earths, RE (only for n = 2). In terms of the M constituent, the &quot;chameleon&quot; is nothing but the <lb/>M-1212 structure: it tolerates a wide range of single-element constituents such as Cu, Co, Fe, Nb, <lb/>Ta, Ru, Hg, Tl, Al, Ga, C, and various cation mixtures as M. Some of the M-1212 phases are <lb/>well-established superconductors, whereas others remain to be &quot;superconducterized&quot; yet. <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>The amount and location of oxygen in the MO 1±δ charge reservoir of the M-1212-type <lb/>phases varies considerably. In the prototype M-1212 phase, i.e. CuBa 2 YCu 2 O 7-δ (Cu-1212), the <lb/>excess oxygen atoms fill half of the perovskite-type positions such that the charge-reservoir Cu <lb/>atom with surrounding oxygen atoms forms a square-planar CuO 4 polyhedron. Octahedral <lb/>coordination is possible as well, with excess oxygen atoms being located at either rock-salt <lb/>position for, e.g. M = Tl [2], or perovskite position for, e.g. M = Ru [3], though the real structures <lb/>deviate from the ideal ones: in Tl-1212 the oxygen site in the TlO layer is subject to large <lb/>concentration of oxygen vacancies, while in Ru-1212 the RuO 6 octahedra are rotated such that <lb/>the oxygen atom is slightly shifted from the ideal a-axis site. Another well-known example of the <lb/>M-1212 phase with a rock-salt type MO 1±δ layer, i.e. Hg-1212 [4], exhibits even much larger <lb/>oxygen deficiency than Tl-1212, such that the coordination polyhedron is considered as an <lb/>O-Hg-O dumbbell. The tetrahedral coordination polyhedron has been seen for three phases with <lb/>M = Ga [5], Al [6,7] and Co [8,9]. Among these, Ga-1212 shows superconductivity up to ∼70 K <lb/>when properly doped with holes [10,11]. Superconductivity in Al-1212 has been somewhat <lb/>debated [12,13]; even in the positive case the onset temperature is low, i.e. 18 ∼ 30 K [13]. The <lb/>third phase, Co-1212, was synthesized in 1989 with the composition of CoSr 2 YCu 2 O 7+δ [14]. The <lb/>crystal structure of CoSr 2 YCu 2 O 7+δ was later reported by Huang et al. [8]. The charge reservoir of <lb/>Co-1212 consists of zigzag chains of corner-linked CoO 4 tetrahedra that run diagonally relative to <lb/>the perovskite base. Later this picture was further elaborated by careful ED and TEM studies that <lb/>revealed the presence of an orthorhombic superstructure originating from a regular alternation of <lb/>two zigzag chains that are mirror images of each other [15,16]. Even though the Co-1212 phase <lb/>has been well known for long, the first indication of superconductivity at ∼30 K was revealed for <lb/>it only very recently by Mochiku et al. [17]. In the present communication we summarize our <lb/>systematic work carried out independently of that of Mochiku et al. on the effects of aliovalent <lb/>Ca II -for-Y III substitution and high-oxygen-pressure annealing in CoSr 2 YCu 2 O 7+δ . The work <lb/>resulted in finding of bulk superconductivity with T c up to 40 K. <lb/>We first synthesized a series of samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ (x = 0 ∼ 0.7) via <lb/>solid-state reaction in air. The starting materials, Co 3 O 4 , SrCO 3 , Y 2 O 3 , CaCO 3 and CuO, were <lb/>mixed to nominal ratios and calcined at 975 o C and 1000 o C with an intermediate grinding. The <lb/>phase purity was checked for each sample with powder x-ray diffraction (XRD; MAC Science: <lb/>MXP18VAHF 22 ; Cu K α radiation). Figure 1 displays XRD patterns for the as-synthesized samples <lb/>(henceforth referred to as AS samples) with various Ca contents, x. From Fig. 1, the AS samples <lb/>are free of any visible impurity peaks at least up to x = 0.5. For the samples with x ≥ 0.5, a small <lb/>unidentified diffraction peak develops around 2θ ≈ 44° and also the peak at 2θ ≈ 32° increases <lb/>abruptly. The lattice parameters as determined from the XRD data (using space group Imcm [8]) <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>are plotted against x in Fig. 2. (Note that we use the crystal-axis naming scheme typically <lb/>employed for the structures of high-T c superconductors, i.e. assign the longest lattice parameter <lb/>along the layer-piling direction as c axis.) From Fig. 2, systematic decrease in the a-and the <lb/>b-axis parameter and increase in the c-axis parameter are evident with increasing Ca-substitution <lb/>level up to x = 0.5. Beyond x = 0.5, the c parameter still continues to increase but the behavior of <lb/>parameters, a and b, is different from that seen for x ≤ 0.5. Therefore it is likely that the solubility <lb/>limit of Ca in CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ is in the vicinity of x = 0.5. The fact that the c-axis <lb/>parameter increases with increasing Ca-substitution level is a clear indication of Ca entering the <lb/>Y site, since substitution of Sr by the smaller alkaline earth, Ca, would result in shrinkage of the c <lb/>axis. Related experimental data to support this reasoning are reported for the AlSr 2 HoCu 2 O 7 <lb/>phase [18]. In AlSr 2 HoCu 2 O 7 , Ca was found to enter either the Sr site or the Ho site depending on <lb/>the synthesis condition: substitution of Sr ended up with a shortened c axis, whereas that of Ho <lb/>resulted in a lengthened c axis. <lb/>When aliovalent cation substitution such as the present Ca II -for-Y III one is applied, it is <lb/>highly probable that the lattice responses to the &quot;substitutional oxidation&quot; by concomitantly <lb/>reducing the oxygen content [19]. Therefore, we precisely analyzed the oxygen content of each <lb/>AS sample. Iodometric titration has been shown to be a well-suited method for perovskite Co <lb/>oxides [20,21], and was therefore employed for the present oxygen-content analyses. The titration <lb/>was carried out in an air-tight cell under flowing N 2 gas. The sample (of ca. 30 mg) was dissolved <lb/>in oxygen-freed 1 M HCl solution containing an excess of KI. Reaction with iodide results in <lb/>reduction of all high-valent Cu and Co species of the sample, i.e. Cu II/III and Co III/IV , to <lb/>monovalent copper (solid CuI) and divalent cobalt (Co 2+ ions), respectively. Concomitantly <lb/>stoichiometric amount of iodine is formed, that is then titrated with Na 2 S 2 O 3 solution (ca. 0.015 <lb/>M), using starch as an indicator for visual end-point detection. The values of oxygen content <lb/>determined for the AS samples with various Ca contents are given in Table 1. From Table 1, it is <lb/>seen that the oxygen content remains essentially stoichiometric (-0.03 ≤ δ ≤ 0.00) up to x = 0.4. <lb/>We have thus confirmed that up to x = 0.4, i.e. as long as the oxygen content remains constant, <lb/>the Ca II -for-Y III substitution increases the oxidation state of Cu and/or Co, thus working in the <lb/>way expected for ideal aliovalent cation substitution. <lb/>For a non-superconductive Ca-free CoSr 2 YCu 2 O 6.97 sample our preliminary Cu L-edge <lb/>XANES (x-ray absorption near-edge structure) spectroscopy study showed that the valence of Cu <lb/>in this sample is II [22]. Accordingly, based on a simple charge-balance calculation, the valence <lb/>of Co is III. Now, taking respectively the values of II and III as the &quot;bottom valence values&quot; for <lb/>Cu and Co in an undoped situation, we may calculate the amount of excess positive charge <lb/>(holes) per formula unit in the present CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ samples from the nominal cation <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>content and the amount of oxygen precisely analyzed by iodometric titration. The hole numbers <lb/>thus derived are given in Table 1. The amount of induced holes increases with increasing x up to x <lb/>= 0.4, where it reaches a value of 0.36 holes per formula unit. <lb/>Next we checked possible superconductivity for the AS samples. Magnetization <lb/>measurements were performed with a SQUID magnetometer (Quantum Design: MPMS-XL) in <lb/>both field-cooled (FC) and zero-field-cooled (ZFC) modes down to 5 K. None of the AS samples <lb/>showed any sign of superconductivity, being in agreement with the observation made earlier for <lb/>an x = 0.4 sample by Huang et al. [8]. In Fig. 3(a) displayed is the χ vs. T curve for the x = 0.4 <lb/>sample as an example. As given in Table 1, the amount of excess holes varies from 0.14 to 0.36 <lb/>per formula unit in the x = 0.2 -0.4 samples. Assignment of all the holes to the CuO 2 plane (that <lb/>appears in duplicate in the formula unit) would end up with the CuO 2 -plane hole concentration <lb/>ranging from 0.07 to 0.18. These values should be adequate for inducing high-T c <lb/>superconductivity. Here, to explain the absence of superconductivity we recognize the following <lb/>two plausible reasons: (i) Co and Cu are partly intermixed such that the content of Co in the <lb/>CuO 2 plane is high enough to kill superconductivity [8], and (ii) holes induced by Ca substitution <lb/>are not directed into the CuO 2 plane but are (mostly) located in the CoO 1+δ charge reservoir. <lb/>Meanwhile we assume that the former is not the present case but the latter applies, that is, the <lb/>induced holes are trapped on Co III/IV in the CoO 1+δ charge reservoir. <lb/>In order to push the holes into the CuO 2 plane and/or introduce more holes in the lattice we <lb/>performed a high-pressure-oxygen (HPO) annealing for the AS samples. The HPO annealing was <lb/>carried out in a cubic-anvil-type ultra-high-pressure apparatus at 5 GPa and 500 o C for 30 min. As <lb/>an oxygen source, Ag 2 O 2 (that readily releases O 2 upon heating while decomposing via Ag 2 O to <lb/>Ag) was utilized: Ag 2 O 2 was mixed with Co-1212 powder to a molar ratio of 1 : 2. XRD patterns <lb/>for the HPO samples are shown in Fig. 4. Comparison with those for the AS samples (Fig. 1) <lb/>reveals that the HPO annealing had no effect on the phase purity of the samples. On the other <lb/>hand, in Fig. 2 where the lattice parameters are plotted for both the AS and the HPO samples, it is <lb/>observed that upon HPO annealing the lattice drastically shrank along the b and c axes, whereas <lb/>the a-axis parameter remained unchanged. As a consequence of the b-axis shrinkage, the degree <lb/>of orthorhombic distortion decreases. We recognize the same from the fact that every pair of <lb/>double peaks seen in the XRD pattern for the AS samples, e.g. 026 and 206, 136 and 316, 138 <lb/>and 318, merges into a single peak after HPO annealings. This suggests that the CoO 4 tetrahedra <lb/>have got broken as a consequence of the change in the oxygen amount/arrangement about the Co <lb/>atom. For the HPO-annealed samples superconductivity appears with the transition temperature <lb/>(T c ) up to 40 K (as determined at the onset of the diamagnetic signal) for the x = 0.3 sample. The <lb/>largest volume fraction of superconductivity (16 % from the ZFC data and 11 % from the FC <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>data) is due to the x = 0.35 sample. In Fig. 5, we show the T c values for all the HPO samples as <lb/>plotted against x. A bell-shape relation is seen. In Fig. 3(b) we have shown the χ vs. T curve for <lb/>the x = 0.4 sample as an example. <lb/>Now a question arises on the primary reason for the appearance of superconductivity in the <lb/>HPO samples. To be able to reach the correct answer, we first investigated whether the pure <lb/>high-pressure (HP) effect alone would induce superconductivity in the Ca-substituted <lb/>CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ samples. As-synthesized powder with x = 0.4 was annealed without <lb/>Ag 2 O 2 at 5 GPa and 500 o C for 30 min, i.e. under the condition otherwise the same as that <lb/>employed for the HPO samples except that no excess oxygen source was added. <lb/>Superconductivity did not show for this HP sample. Furthermore, upon the HP annealing the <lb/>lattice parameters of the AS sample as well as the χ vs. T behavior (see Fig. 3(c) for the x = 0.4 <lb/>case) remained unchanged. It is thus concluded that both the drastic decrease in the lattice <lb/>parameters, b and c, and the appearance of superconductivity upon high-pressure annealing have <lb/>resulted from the application of high oxygen partial pressure during annealing. <lb/>Next we annealed the HPO-superconducterized x = 0.4 sample in flowing N 2 gas. This <lb/>annealing was carried out in a thermobalance (Perkin Elmer: Pyris 1) in order to be able to <lb/>thermogravimetrically (TG) follow changes in the sample weight occurring during the annealing. <lb/>The initial mass of the sample was 22 mg and the heating rate was 1 o C/min. After reaching the <lb/>final temperature of 500 o C the sample was quenched to room temperature. From the TG curve <lb/>recorded, two weight-loss steps are seen about 150 and 300 o C (Fig. 6). The overall amounts of <lb/>oxygen depleted in these two steps from the HPO sample (that is a mixture of <lb/>CoSr 2 (Y 0.6 Ca 0.4 )Cu 2 O 7+δ + (1-y) Ag + 0.5y Ag 2 O) were calculated at ∼0.4 and ∼0.2, respectively. <lb/>From the XRD pattern for the HPO-N 2 sample it was concluded that the N 2 annealing made the <lb/>lattice parameters of the Co-1212 phase to recover back to the same values as those of the AS <lb/>sample before the HPO annealing. On the other hand, the amount of Ag seen in the XRD pattern <lb/>did not visibly increase as compared to that seen for the HPO sample. Therefore, it is likely that <lb/>the weight/oxygen loss detected by TG upon N 2 annealing is primarily due to the Co-1212 phase <lb/>itself. This conclusion is supported by the magnetization data: upon annealing the HPO sample in <lb/>N 2 not only superconductivity but also the magnetic transition characteristically seen for all the <lb/>HPO samples around 150 K disappeared (Fig. 3(d)). Note that the origin of the magnetic <lb/>transition (manifested by the branching of the ZFC and FC magnetization curves) was left <lb/>unaddressed yet, as the structure of the CoO 1+δ charge reservoir is not determined for the HPO <lb/>samples. The second, smaller weight step in the TG curve about 300 o C well coincides with that <lb/>seen for the decomposition of pure Ag 2 O [23]. We thus assign the second step for the <lb/>decomposition of leftover Ag 2 O, i.e. y ≈ 0.4, and the first step only to the oxygen evolution from <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body>the Co-1212 phase, i.e. δ ≈ 0.4. <lb/>As the final step of the present work we checked the optimum amount of Ag 2 O 2 used as a <lb/>source of excess oxygen in the HPO annealing. The first HPO treatments were all carried out <lb/>with 50 mol-% Ag 2 O 2 . Here we made ad hoc HPO annealings for the x = 0.4 sample using 25 and <lb/>100 mol-% Ag 2 O 2 . It was found that with 25 mol-% Ag 2 O 2 , the c axis decreased less as compared <lb/>with the case of 50 mol-%. More importantly, the sample did not show superconductivity. On the <lb/>other hand, with 100 mol-% Ag 2 O 2 peaks due to Ag 2 O appeared in the XRD pattern for the HPO <lb/>annealed sample. The annealed sample exhibited superconductivity with a lower T c value of 20 K <lb/>than that of the HPO annealed product with 50 mol-% of Ag 2 O 2 (T c ≈ 35 K). It was thus revealed <lb/>that the optimum amount of Ag 2 O 2 as an oxygen source for the HPO annealing is in the vicinity <lb/>of 50 mol-%. Here it should also be noted that we annealed the two new HPO samples in a <lb/>thermobalance in N 2 . From the TG curves shown in Fig. 6 together with that for the sample with <lb/>50 % Ag 2 O 2 we could see the following features: the second weight-loss step about 300 o C that <lb/>we had previously assigned to the decomposition of leftover Ag 2 O was not seen at all for the <lb/>HPO sample with 25 % Ag 2 O 2 (y ≈ 0), whereas it was more pronounced for that with 100 % <lb/>Ag 2 O 2 (y ≈ 1.0) in comparison with the original HPO sample with 50 % Ag 2 O 2 (y ≈ 0.4). The <lb/>amount of oxygen depleted from the Co-1212 phase in the first weight-loss step increased with <lb/>increasing amount of Ag 2 O 2 used for the HPO annealing, i.e. δ ≈ 0.3 (25 % Ag 2 O 2 ), 0.4 (50 %) <lb/>and 0.5 (100 %). <lb/>In conclusion, we have systematically clarified the influence of aliovalent Ca II -for-Y III <lb/>substitution and high-pressure-oxygen annealing on the superconductivity of <lb/>CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ (Co-1212) samples. It was found that at least up to x ≈ 0.4 Ca dissolves in <lb/>the Co-1212 phase at the Y site. Within this range of Ca substitution the oxygen content of <lb/>as-synthesized samples remained stoichiometric. Therefore we could assure that holes were <lb/>gradually doped in the Co-1212 structure upon Ca substitution. The as-synthesized samples, <lb/>however, were not superconductive, suggesting that the holes created by the divalent-for-trivalent <lb/>substitution are trapped about the Co atom in the charge reservoir. The combination of Ca <lb/>substitution and high-pressure-oxygen annealing was necessary to induce superconductivity in <lb/>the Co-1212 phase. The highest T c obtained in the present study for the HPO-annealed x = 0.3 <lb/>sample was ∼40 K. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">We gratefully acknowledge Dr. V.P.S. Awana for his contribution in initiating the research <lb/>on the phases of Co-12s2 homologous series in our group. Dr. T. Motohashi is acknowledged for <lb/>fruitful discussions. This work was supported by Grants-in-aid for Scientific Research (Nos. <lb/>15206002 and 15206071) from Japan Society for the Promotion of Science. <lb/></div>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>[1] M. Karppinen, H. Yamauchi, Mater. Sci. Eng. R26 (1999) 844. <lb/>[2] B. Morosin, E.L. Venturini, R.G. Dunn, P.P. Newcomer, Physica C 288 (1997) 255. <lb/>[3] O. Chmaissem, J.D. Jorgensen, H. Shaked, P. Dollar, J.L. Tallon, Phys. Rev. B 61 (2000) <lb/>6401. <lb/>[4] P.G. Radaelli, J.L. Wagner, B.A. Hunter, M.A. Beno, G.S. Knapp, J.D. Jorgensen, D.G. Hinks, <lb/>Physica C 216 (1993) 29. <lb/>[5] G. Roth, P. Adelmann, G. Heger, R. Knitter, Th. Wolf, J. Phys. I 5 (1991) 721. <lb/>[6] J. Ramirez-Castellanos, Y. Matsui, M. Isobe, E. Takayama-Muromachi, J. Solid State Chem. <lb/>133 (1997) 434. <lb/>[7] P. Bordet, F. Licci, C. Bougerol-Chaillout, M. Marezio, J. Solid State Chem. 149 (2000) 256. <lb/>[8] Q. Huang, R.J. Cava, A.Santoro, J.J. Krajewski, W.F. Peck, Physica C 193 (1992) 196. <lb/>[9] V.P.S. Awana, S.K. Malik, W.B. Yelon, M. Karppinen, H. Yamauchi, Physica C 378-381 <lb/>(2002) 155. <lb/>[10] B. Dabrowski, P. Radaelli, D.G.. Hinks, A.W. Mitchell, J.T. Vaughey, D.A. Groenke, K.R. <lb/>Poeppelmeir, Physica C 193 (1992) 63. <lb/>[11] M. Isobe, K. Kosuda, E. Takayama-Muromachi, Physica C 227 (1994) 351. <lb/>[12] A.T. Matveev, E. Takayama-Muromachi, Physica C 254 (1995) 26. <lb/>[13] A. Ono, Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. 36 (1997) L849. <lb/>[14] S.A. Sunshine, L.F. Schneemeyer, T. Siegrist, D.C. Douglass, J.V. Waszczak, R.J. Cava, E.M. <lb/>Gyorgy, D.W. Murphy, Chem. Mater. 1 (1989) 331. <lb/>[15] T. Krekels, O. Milat, G. van Tendeloo, S. Amelinckx, T.G. N. Babu, A.J. Wright, C. Greaves, <lb/>J. Solid State Chem. 105 (1993) 313. <lb/>[16] T. Nagai, V.P.S. Awana, E. Takayama-Muromachi, A. Yamazaki, M. Karppinen, H. <lb/>Yamauchi, S.K. Malik, W.B. Yelon, Y. Matsui, J. Solid State Chem., submitted. <lb/>[17] T. Mochiku, H. Kito, Y. Nakano, Y. Hata, J. Suzuki, I. Kakeya, K. Kadowaki, K. Hirata, H. <lb/>Ihara, 63 rd Autumn Meeting of the Japan Society of Applied Physics, 2002, Extended <lb/>Abstracts, 6pPSA-19 (in Japanese). <lb/>[18] A. Ono, J. Mao, S. Horiuchi, Jpn. J. Appl. Phys. 37 (1998) 4342. <lb/>[19] M. Karppinen, M. Kotiranta, T. Nakane, H. Yamauchi, S.C. Chang, R.S. Liu, J.M. Chen, <lb/>Phys. Rev. B, in press (2003). <lb/>[20] M. Karppinen, V.P.S. Awana, Y. Morita, H. Yamauchi, Physica C, in press (2003). <lb/>[21] M. Karppinen, M. Matvejeff, K. Salomäki, H. Yamauchi, J. Mater. Chem. 12 (2002) 1761. <lb/>[22] M. Karppinen, Y. Morita, V.P.S. Awana, H. Yamauchi, R.S. Liu, J.M. Chen, unpublished. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>[23] M. Karppinen, H. Yamauchi, Oxygen Engineering for Functional Oxide Materials, In: <lb/>International Book Series: Studies of High Temperature Superconductors, Vol. 37, A.V. <lb/>Narlikar (Ed.), Nova Science Publishers, New York 2001, pp. 109-143. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. The degree of oxygen nonstoichiometry, δ, as determined by iodometric titration and <lb/>the amount of &quot;excess holes&quot; per formula unit for the as-synthesized (AS) <lb/>CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ samples. The amount of &quot;excess holes&quot; is calculated from the <lb/>values of x and δ against the &quot;bottom valence values&quot; of II and III for Cu and Co, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>x <lb/>δ <lb/>&quot;excess holes&quot; <lb/>0.0 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>-0.06 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.04 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>-0.03 <lb/>0.14 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>0.00 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>-0.02 <lb/>0.36 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>-0.10 <lb/>0.30 <lb/>0.6 * <lb/>-0.20 <lb/>0.20 <lb/>0.7 * <lb/>-0.27 <lb/>0.16 <lb/>* May not be totally phase-pure. <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure captions <lb/>Fig. 1. XRD patterns for the as-synthesized (AS) samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ . Note that <lb/>the intensity scale is logarithmic. <lb/>Fig. 2. Lattice parameters, a, b and c, for the as-synthesized (AS; open circles) and the high-<lb/>pressure-oxygen annealed (HPO; filled triangles) samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ . <lb/>Fig. 3. Magnetic susceptibility (χ) versus temperature (T) curves measured in FC and ZFC <lb/>modes for the following x = 0.4 samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ : as-synthesized (AS), <lb/>high-pressure-oxygen (HPO) annealed, high-pressure (HP) annealed, and N 2 annealed <lb/>after HPO annealing (HPO-N 2 ). <lb/>Fig. 4. XRD patterns for the high-pressure-oxygen (HPO) annealed samples of <lb/>CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ . Besides those for the Co-1212 phase, seen are peaks due to Ag <lb/>as a decomposition product of Ag 2 O 2 . Note that the intensity scale is logarithmic. <lb/>Fig. 5. Superconductivity transition temperature, T c , for the high-pressure-oxygen (HPO) <lb/>annealed samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ . <lb/>Fig. 6. TG curves for the N 2 annealing of the high-pressure-oxygen (HPO) annealed x = 0.4 <lb/>samples of CoSr 2 (Y 1-x Ca x )Cu 2 O 7+δ : for the HPO annealing 25 %, 50 % or 100 % Ag 2 O 2 <lb/>was used. The heating rate is 1 o C/min. The first/second weight-loss step is due to <lb/>oxygen evolution from the Co-1212 phase/decomposition of leftover Ag 2 O. <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 1. <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>Intensity (cps) <lb/>x = 0.0 <lb/>002 <lb/>110 <lb/>112 <lb/>114 <lb/>020 <lb/>116 <lb/>118 <lb/>206 <lb/>220 <lb/>0012 <lb/>0014 <lb/>136 <lb/>2014 <lb/>336 <lb/>208 <lb/>316 <lb/>040 <lb/>2114 <lb/>2214 <lb/>026 <lb/>138 <lb/>318 <lb/>017 <lb/>004 <lb/>024 <lb/>204 <lb/>030 <lb/>0210 <lb/>130 <lb/>1114 <lb/>1116 <lb/>240 <lb/>338 <lb/>015 <lb/>013 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>2θ ( <lb/>°) <lb/>0.7 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 2. <lb/>5.38 <lb/>5.40 <lb/>5.42 <lb/>5.44 <lb/>5.46 <lb/>Lattice parameter (Å) <lb/>a axis <lb/>○ AS <lb/>▲ HPO <lb/>5.38 <lb/>5.40 <lb/>5.42 <lb/>5.44 <lb/>5.46 <lb/>b axis <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>22.5 <lb/>22.6 <lb/>22.7 <lb/>22.8 <lb/>22.9 <lb/>c axis <lb/>Ca content, x <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 3. <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>Magnetic Susceptibility (10 -5 <lb/>emu/g Oe) <lb/>AS <lb/>ZFC <lb/>FC <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>HP <lb/>ZFC <lb/>FC <lb/>-150 <lb/>-120 <lb/>-90 <lb/>-60 <lb/>-30 <lb/>0 <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>HPO <lb/>ZFC <lb/>FC <lb/>0 <lb/>50 <lb/>100 <lb/>150 <lb/>200 <lb/>250 <lb/>300 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>1.2 <lb/>1.4 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>1.8 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>2.4 <lb/>HPO-N 2 <lb/>Temperature (K) <lb/>ZFC <lb/>FC <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 4. <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>Intensity (cps) <lb/>0.2 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>2θ( <lb/>°) <lb/>0.7 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.3 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.1 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>x = 0.0 <lb/>• Ag <lb/>002 <lb/>110 <lb/>114 <lb/>020 <lb/>116 <lb/>118 <lb/>206 <lb/>220 <lb/>0012 <lb/>316 <lb/>318 <lb/>040 <lb/>240 <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>• <lb/>017 <lb/>204 <lb/>0014 <lb/>1014 <lb/>2014 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.25 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.35 <lb/>500 <lb/>1000 <lb/>5000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>0.45 <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 5. <lb/>0 <lb/>0.2 <lb/>0.4 <lb/>0.6 <lb/>0.8 <lb/>0 <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>50 <lb/>Ca content, x <lb/>T <lb/>c (K) <lb/>Morita et al: Fig. 6. <lb/>0 <lb/>100 <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>97.0 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>98.0 <lb/>98.5 <lb/>99.0 <lb/>99.5 <lb/>100.0 <lb/>100.5 <lb/>Temperature (℃) <lb/>Weight (%) <lb/>25 mol % <lb/>50 mol % <lb/>100 mol % </body>


	</text>
</tei>
