<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		
            <front>arXiv:cond-mat/0212282v1 [cond-mat.supr-con] 12 Dec 2002 <lb/> 1 <lb/> Under-doped La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 with x = 0.063 -0.125: <lb/>TSFZ growth of high-quality crystals and anomalous doping <lb/>dependences of superconducting properties <lb/>F Zhou , W X Ti 1 , J W Xiong 1 and Z X Zhao 1 <lb/>X L Dong 1,2 , P H Hor 2 , Z H Zhang and W K Chu <lb/>1 National Laboratory for Superconductivity, Institute of Physics &amp; Center for Condensed Matter <lb/>Physics, Chinese Academy of Sciences, P.O. Box 603, Beijing 100080, P. R. China <lb/>Texas Center for Superconductivity and Department of Physics <lb/>University of Houston, Houston, Texas 77204-5002 <lb/>to be published on Superconductor Science and Technology <lb/>A series of high-quality La2−xSrxCuO4 (LSCO) superconductor crystals in the under-doping region with x = <lb/>0.063, 0.07, 0.09, 0.10, 0.111 and 0.125 has been successfully prepared by traveling-solvent floating-zone (TSFZ) <lb/>technique. The crystals are large and free of sub-grains and foreign phases. The high crystal quality has been <lb/>revealed by double-crystal x-ray rocking curves and Rutherford backscattering spectrometry combined with ion-<lb/>beam channeling effect. We find that the evolutions of the superconducting transition width and volume fraction <lb/>as a function of carrier concentration exhibit interesting anomalies in the vicinity of some &quot;magic number&quot; doping <lb/>levels such as x = 1/4 2 (=0.0625) and 1/3 2 (=0.111). We argue that these behaviours are of intrinsic electronic <lb/>origin. PACS Number: 74.72.Dn; 74.25.Ha. <lb/></front>

			<body>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 (LSCO) system is known to be <lb/>one of the cuprate superconductor systems with <lb/>fewer components and a simple layered structure <lb/>of K 2 NiF 4 type which can be basically described <lb/>as a stacking of single-plane CuO 2 superconduct-<lb/>ing layers separated by two (La, Sr)O layers. The <lb/>intrinsic Josephson junctions of LSCO have re-<lb/>cently been characterized as stacked serial SIS <lb/>junctions [1], and its high Josephson plasma fre-<lb/>quency in THz region is quite interesting for de-<lb/>veloping new electronic devices such as THz gen-<lb/>erators and detectors [2]. On the other hand, its <lb/>electronic states strongly depend on hole-doping <lb/>which can be achieved with the substitution of <lb/>Sr 2+ cations for La 3+ ones. At very low doping <lb/>(x &lt; 0.02), La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 is an antiferromag-<lb/>netic Mott insulator. After crossing a spin glass <lb/>state (0.02 &lt; x &lt; 0.05) [3,4], it becomes a super-<lb/>conductor (0.05 &lt; x &lt; 0.26) and then changes <lb/>to a normal metal (0.26 &lt; x &lt; 0.6) [5] and fi-<lb/>nally it behaves as a semiconductor (x &gt; 0.6) <lb/>[6]. In the superconductor regime, the critical <lb/>temperature of LSCO reaches its maximum of 38 <lb/>K at x = 0.15. The investigation on the doping <lb/>dependences of low temperature physical proper-<lb/>ties in both normal and superconducting states <lb/>is important for acquiring a better understanding <lb/>of high T C superconductivity and strongly cor-<lb/>related electron systems. LSCO system is there-<lb/>fore not only attractive in its possible applications <lb/>but also in such fundamental research. For both <lb/>purposes, high-quality and sizable single crystals <lb/>are highly demanded, and persistent effort has <lb/>been made in the crystal growth using differ-<lb/>ent techniques [7,8,9,10,11,12]. Traveling-solvent <lb/>floating-zone (TSFZ) method is widely accepted <lb/>as a unique approach to growing such incongru-<lb/>ent melting oxide superconductor crystals. This <lb/>crucible-free technique avoids the crystal contam-<lb/>ination from crucible material that will otherwise <lb/>interfere with the observation of intrinsic phys-<lb/>ical properties. The large temperature gradient <lb/>produced by focused lamp images makes possible <lb/>good solid-liquid interfaces and a stable molten <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body>zone. <lb/>By using TSFZ method, we have success-<lb/>fully prepared a series of large and high-quality <lb/>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 single crystals covering some in-<lb/>teresting under-doping levels (x = 0.063 -0.125) <lb/>with the aim of systematic investigation on the <lb/>physical properties. We first report here the re-<lb/>sults of TSFZ growth and characterizations of <lb/>some properties of these LSCO crystals. Inter-<lb/>esting anomalous doping dependences of super-<lb/>conducting properties are observed in this series <lb/>of crystals and are briefly discussed. <lb/>High purity (≥ 99.99%) oxides La 2 O 3 , CuO <lb/>and carbonate SrCO 3 were used as the raw ma-<lb/>terials. For the feed rods, the initial composition <lb/>was (1-x/2)La O 3 /xSrCO 3 /CuO in molar ratio <lb/>with x = 0.063, 0.07, 0.09, 0.10, 0.111 and 0.125. <lb/>Excess CuO of 1 -2 mol% was added for com-<lb/>pensating its evaporation loss in the growth pro-<lb/>cess. The solvents were much richer in CuO as <lb/>self-flux, typically of 78 mol% CuO. In determin-<lb/>ing the Sr contents of the solvents, we took into <lb/>account the previously reported results of distri-<lb/>bution coefficients k Sr of Sr doping into La 2 CuO 4 <lb/>[10]. The Preparation of dense and homogeneous <lb/>feed rods is one of the key factors in achieving a <lb/>stable and continuous TSFZ growth. Each step <lb/>in the preparation was carefully checked and op-<lb/>timized, such as thorough mixing and grinding of <lb/>the starting and prefired powders by a planetary <lb/>ball mill, forming compact cylindrical rods under <lb/>a high hydrostatic pressure before the feed rods <lb/>being finally well sintered. An infrared heating <lb/>floating-zone furnace with a quartet ellipsoidal <lb/>mirror (Crystal Systems Inc., Model FZ-T-10000-<lb/>H) was used for TSFZ experiments. The crystals <lb/>were grown under an oxygen pressure of 0.2 MPa <lb/>at a zone traveling rate of 0.8 mm/hr using seed <lb/>crystals orientated along orthorhombic or tetrag-<lb/>onal [100] or [110] directions. <lb/>By careful operations and the use of high qual-<lb/>ity feed rods, a stable molten zone was success-<lb/>fully maintained in most experiments until pro-<lb/>ceeding growths were artificially stopped just be-<lb/>fore the whole feed rods, typically 125 mm long, <lb/>ran out. Shown in Fig.1 is the photo for one of <lb/>as-grown ingots, with a typical size of 5-6 mm <lb/>in diameter and 110 mm in length. Polished <lb/>crystal pieces cut from the ingots were checked <lb/>by optical microscopy using polarized or normal <lb/>light. No grain boundaries were observed in the <lb/>crystallized ingots after several centimeters away <lb/>from the starting point of crystallization on seed <lb/>crystals, indicating that large single-grain crys-<lb/>tals were obtained. The compositions of grown <lb/>crystals estimated by ICP-AES were very close <lb/>to those of feed rods, and no foreign phases in <lb/>crystal samples were detected by powder XRD <lb/>analysis. <lb/>cm <lb/>Figure 1. As-grown ingot of La 1.875 Sr 0.125 CuO 4 <lb/>crystal. <lb/>Experiments of x-ray rocking curves were per-<lb/>formed on representative La 1.91 Sr 0.09 CuO 4 (x = <lb/>0.09) crystal using a double-crystal diffractometer <lb/>(Rigaku, Model SLX-1) equipped with a 12 KW <lb/>rotating Cu target and a Ge (004) monochroma-<lb/>tor (α ∼ 5 o ). Fig. 2 shows the rocking curve <lb/>of (008) Bragg reflection for this sample having <lb/>a surface dimension of 4mm × 15mm (the beam <lb/>slit size was set to 0.5mm × 10mm). The full-<lb/>width-at-half-maximum (FWHM), which is cor-<lb/>related with the crystal mosaicity, is as small as <lb/>0.10 o . This is one of the best data reported so <lb/>far for LSCO crystals [12]. The quality of the <lb/>same crystal was also examined by Rutherford <lb/>backscattering spectrometry combined with ion-<lb/>beam channeling effect (RBS-channeling) which <lb/>was carried out using 2 MeV well collimated He <lb/>ion beam and a Si detector set at 160 o to the in-<lb/>cident direction. The channeling spectrum was <lb/>taken along the c-axis of the crystal. The RBS-<lb/>channeling minimum yield [13] is only χ min = <lb/>3.8% (Fig. 3), being another evidence for the high <lb/>quality of the crystal. Moreover, it can be seen <lb/>from Fig. 3 that, for the aligned spectrum, the <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>backscattering counts increase very slowly with <lb/>depth. This is a strong indication that the defect <lb/>density in the crystal is very low. <lb/>26.5 27.0 27.5 28.0 28.5 29.0 29.5 <lb/>0 <lb/>2000 <lb/>4000 <lb/>8000 <lb/>10000 <lb/>12000 <lb/>FW HM: 0.10 <lb/>o <lb/>Bragg Peak: (008) <lb/>I (cps) <lb/>Omega (deg.) <lb/>Figure 2. Rocking curve of (008) reflection for <lb/>La 1.91 Sr 0.09 CuO 4 (x = 0.09) crystal taken by <lb/>double-crystal x-ray diffraction using Cu Kα ra-<lb/>diation. The surface dimension of the sample is <lb/>4mm × 15mm and the beam slit size is 0.5mm × <lb/>10mm. <lb/>The Meissner (field-cooled) and shielding (zero-<lb/>field-cooled) signals of all the six crystal sam-<lb/>ples were measured on a SQUID magnetometer <lb/>(Quantum Design, MPMS XL) in a low field of <lb/>5 Oe with c//H, as shown in Fig. 4. The super-<lb/>conducting critical temperatures observed from <lb/>the Meissner effects range from about 11K for <lb/>x = 0.063 to about 31K for x = 0.125. It is <lb/>of much interest to note that, around some spe-<lb/>cial doping levels with &quot;magic numbers&quot; such as <lb/>x = 1/4 2 (=0.0625) and 1/3 (=0.111), the su-<lb/>perconducting transitions are much sharper (∆T <lb/>≈ 2K) than those at the doping contents away <lb/>from them and the Meissner fraction drops re-<lb/>markably upon doping in the close vicinity of x <lb/>= 1/3 2 (Fig. 4). Moreover, the shielding sig-<lb/>nals exhibit the same broadening trend for the <lb/>doping levels away from the magic numbers and <lb/>they all have 100% volume fraction. This indi-<lb/>cates that there is no macroscopic inhomogene-<lb/>ity and/or weak links. Generally speaking, crys-<lb/>talline imperfection may broaden superconduct-<lb/>ing transition and a narrow transition width is <lb/>200 <lb/>300 <lb/>400 <lb/>500 <lb/>600 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>0 <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>3 <lb/>4 <lb/>5 <lb/>Aligned <lb/>Random <lb/>F min = 3.8% <lb/>Counts (x1000) <lb/>Channel <lb/>Figure 3. 2-MeV 4 He + ions RBS-channeling ef-<lb/>fect on La 1.91 Sr 0.09 CuO 4 (x = 0.09) crystal. The <lb/>aligned spectrum is taken along c-axis of the crys-<lb/>tal and the random spectrum with the sample ro-<lb/>tating and tilted 10 degrees away from the aligned <lb/>direction. The RBS-channeling minimum yield is <lb/>only χ min = 3.8%. <lb/>expected for superconductor crystals of high qual-<lb/>ity. We have evidenced that the x = 0.09 LSCO <lb/>crystal is of excellent crystalline perfection, but, <lb/>contrary to the expectation, it exhibits a broad <lb/>superconducting transition. As a further check, <lb/>the La 1.91 Sr 0.09 CuO 4 sample was annealed under <lb/>various conditions for several to twelve days at <lb/>600-1000 o C under oxygen flow or 0.3 MPa oxy-<lb/>gen pressure before quenched in liquid nitrogen. <lb/>However, magnetic measurements showed that its <lb/>transition width remained unchanged after these <lb/>annealing processes. These results and observa-<lb/>tions thus lead us to conclude that such anoma-<lb/>lies of superconducting properties in the vicin-<lb/>ity of these magic doping levels as well as the <lb/>broad transitions at the dopant contents away <lb/>from these magic numbers are of intrinsic elec-<lb/>tronic origin. At these special carrier concentra-<lb/>tions, some specific electronic state may occur but <lb/>it may not be completely pinned down elsewhere <lb/>in this doping region. Indeed, both supercon-<lb/>ducting electronic phase separations [14] and the <lb/>formation of 2D electronic lattices [15,16,17] at <lb/>magic doping numbers are reported in Sr doped <lb/>and Sr/O co-doped lanthanum cuprates. Further <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body>related investigations are currently in progress. <lb/>10 <lb/>20 <lb/>30 <lb/>40 <lb/>-1.0 <lb/>-0.8 <lb/>-0.6 <lb/>-0.4 <lb/>-0.2 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0.063 <lb/>0.07 <lb/>0.09 <lb/>0.10 <lb/>0.111 <lb/>0.125 <lb/>H//c, 5 Oe <lb/>4SF <lb/>T (K) <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>60 <lb/>40 <lb/>20 <lb/>Meissner / shielding fraction (%) <lb/>Figure 4. Meissner curves (symboled lines) and <lb/>shielding curves (bare lines) of La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 <lb/>single crystals with various doping levels (x = <lb/>0.063 -0.125). <lb/>In conclusion, we have successfully prepared <lb/>by TSFZ method a series of high-quality <lb/>La 2−x Sr x CuO 4 superconductor crystals in the <lb/>under-doping regime with x = 0.063 -0.125. The <lb/>crystals are pure, subgrain-free and large in size. <lb/>We have observed from the magnetic measure-<lb/>ments that the superconducting transition width <lb/>narrows in the close vicinity of some magic dop-<lb/>ing levels while remains broad at other dopant <lb/>contents, and the Meissner fraction shows an un-<lb/>usual decrease around x = 1/3 2 . We suppose <lb/>that such interesting anomalous behaviours in su-<lb/>perconducting state may probably originate from <lb/>some intrinsic electronic state occurring at these <lb/>special carrier-dopings. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgement <lb/>The <lb/>authors <lb/>at <lb/>IP&amp;CCMP-CAS are very grateful to Prof. Z. <lb/>L. Wang and Mrs. N. L. Li for their various and <lb/>valuable helps in crystal orientation and process-<lb/>ing. They would also like to thank many other <lb/>colleagues for their technical assistances and mea-<lb/>surements (SQUID, XRD, SEM etc.). The work <lb/>in Beijing is supported by Ministry of Science <lb/>and Technology of China and National Natural <lb/>Science Foundation of China through Project <lb/>G1999064601 and Project 10174090. The work <lb/>in Houston is supported by the State of Texas <lb/>through The Texas Center for Superconductivity. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Uematsu Y, Mizugaki Y, Nakajima K, Ya-<lb/>mashita T, Watauchi S and Tanaka I 2002 <lb/>Physica C 367 382). <lb/>2. Yamashita T 2001 Physica C 362 58. <lb/>3. Wakimoto S, Shirane G, Endoh Y, Hirota K, <lb/>Ueki S, Yamada K, Birgeneau R J, Kastner <lb/>M A, Lee Y S, Gehring P M and Lee S H 1999 <lb/>Phys. Rev. B 60 R769. <lb/>4. Chou F C, Belk N R, Kastner M A, Birge-<lb/>neau R J, Aharony A 1995 Phys. Rev. Lett. <lb/>75 2204. <lb/>5. Torrance J B, Yokura Y, Nazzal A I, Bezinge <lb/>A, Huang T C and Parkin S S P 1988 Phys. <lb/>Rev. Lett. 61 1127. <lb/>6. Sreedhar K and Ganguly P 1990 Phys. Rev. <lb/>B 41 371. <lb/>7. Tanaka I and Kojima H 1989 Nature 337 21. <lb/>8. Chen C, Watts B E, Wanklyn B M, Thomas P <lb/>A and Haycock P W 1988 J. Crystal Growth <lb/>659. <lb/>9. Cassanho A, Keimer B and Greven M 1993 J. <lb/>Crystal Growth 128 813. <lb/>10. Kojima H, Yamamoto J, Mori Y, Khan M K <lb/>R, Tanabe H and Tanaka I 1997 Physica C <lb/>14. <lb/>11. Marin C, Charvolin T, Braithwaite D and <lb/>Calemczuk R 1999 Physica C 320 197. <lb/>12. Komiya S, Ando Y, Sun X F and Lavrov A <lb/>N 2002 Phys. Rev. B 65 214535. <lb/>13. Lindhard J 1965 Mat. Fys. Medd. K. Dan. <lb/>Vidensk. Selsk. 34. <lb/>14. Lorenz B, Li Z G, Honma T and Hor P H <lb/>2002 Phys. Rev. B 65 144522. <lb/>15. Kim Y H and Hor P H 2001 Modern Physics <lb/>Letter B 15 497. <lb/>16. Hor P H and Kim Y H 2002 J. Phys.: Con-<lb/>dens. Matter 14 10377. <lb/>17. Kim Y H, Hor P H, Dong X L, Zhou F, Zhao <lb/>Z X, Song Y S, to be submitted. </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
