<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_stokes_ddfv_omnes_hal"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> A discrete duality finite volume discretization of the <lb/>vorticity-velocity-pressure Stokes problem on almost arbitrary <lb/>two-dimensional grids <lb/> Sarah Delcourte  1  and Pascal Omnes  23 <lb/> Abstract <lb/> We present an application of the discrete duality finite volume method to the numerical <lb/>approximation of the vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation of the 2D Stokes equations, <lb/>associated to various non-standard boundary conditions. The finite volume method is <lb/>based on the use of discrete differential operators obeying some discrete duality principles. <lb/>The scheme may be seen as an extension of the classical MAC scheme to almost arbitrary <lb/>meshes, thanks to an appropriate choice of degrees of freedom. The efficiency of the scheme <lb/>is illustrated by numerical examples over unstructured triangular and locally refined non-<lb/>conforming meshes, which confirm the theoretical convergence analysis led in the article. <lb/> Keywords: Stokes equations; vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation; boundary conditions; <lb/>discrete duality; finite volumes; arbitrary meshes; a priori estimates <lb/></front>

			<body> 1 Introduction <lb/> Let Ω be a bounded, open, connected but not necessarily simply connected polygon of R  2  , whose <lb/>boundary is denoted by Γ; we consider the numerical approximation by means of finite volumes <lb/>of the solution of the Stokes equations: with given functions f , g, σ, p  d  and ω  d  and a given real <lb/>number m  ω  , find (u, p) satisfying <lb/> −∆u + 񮽙p = f in Ω, <lb/> (1.1) <lb/> 񮽙 · u = g in Ω, <lb/> (1.2) <lb/>supplemented with one of the following non-standard sets of conditions <lb/> u · n = σ over Γ , 񮽙 × u = ω  d  over Γ and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> p(x)dx = 0 , <lb/> (1.3) <lb/> u · n = σ over Γ , p = p  d  over Γ and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> 񮽙 × u(x)dx = m  ω  , <lb/> (1.4) <lb/> u · τ = σ over Γ , 񮽙 × u = ω  d  over Γ and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> p(x)dx = 0 , <lb/> (1.5) <lb/> u · τ = σ over Γ , p = p  d  over Γ and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> 񮽙 × u(x)dx = m  ω  . <lb/> (1.6) <lb/></body>

			<front> 1  Universit´é de Lyon, CNRS UMR 5208, Université Lyon 1, Institut Camille Jordan, 43 boulevard du 11 <lb/>novembre 1918, F-69622 Villeurbanne cedex, France. Partially supported by the European Research Council <lb/>ERC Starting Grant 2009, project 239983-NuSiKiMo. delcourte@math.univ-lyon1.fr <lb/> 2  CEA-Saclay, DEN, DM2S, STMF, LMSF, F-91191 Gif-sur-Yvette, France. E-Mail: pascal.omnes@cea.fr <lb/> 3  Université Paris 13, Sorbonne Paris Cité, LAGA, CNRS UMR 7539, Institut Galilée, 99, Avenue J.-B. <lb/>Clément F-93430 Villetaneuse Cedex, France. <lb/></front>

			<page> 1 <lb/></page>

			<body> These conditions are written here in the case of simply connected domains, but they will be <lb/>extended in the core of the article to non-simply connected domains. There are compatibility <lb/>conditions between the data (g, σ) in (1.3) and (1.4), the data (ω  d  , σ) in (1.5) and the data <lb/>(m  ω  , σ) in (1.6). They will be discussed in subsection 4.1. <lb/>As recognized for example by Dubois et. al. [1], these non-standard conditions can be treated <lb/>in a very general and natural way thanks to the vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation of the <lb/>Stokes problem (for earlier works based on different approaches, we refer to [2] and [3]). Since <lb/> −∆u = 񮽙 × × × u − 񮽙񮽙 · u, using (1.2), and introducing the vorticity ω, Eq. (1.1) may be <lb/>split as <lb/> 񮽙 × ω + 񮽙p = f + 񮽙g in Ω , <lb/> (1.7) <lb/> 񮽙 × u = ω in Ω . <lb/> (1.8) <lb/>The mathematical analysis of system (1.7)-(1.8)-(1.2) with various boundary conditions was led <lb/>in several references, among which [4, 5, 6, 7, 1]. Finite element methods for the vorticity-<lb/>velocity-pressure formulation were analyzed in [4, 5, 8, 9]. Spectral methods were considered in <lb/>[6, 10] and [11], where a least-square formulation is used. <lb/>In the present work, we shall be interested in a finite volume generalization of the Marker <lb/>and Cell (MAC) scheme on very general meshes. The MAC scheme was developed initially <lb/>in [12] on staggered rectangular grids and extended to the so-called covolume scheme using <lb/>Delaunay-Voronoi mesh pairs, as reviewed in [13]. We note that the orthogonality property of <lb/>these mesh pairs might be in certain cases a drawback, in particular in the context of adaptive <lb/>mesh refinement. The standard MAC scheme discretizes (1.1)-(1.2), while the covolume scheme <lb/>discretizes (1.7)-(1.8)-(1.2). Given a (primal) mesh, the MAC and covolume schemes use as <lb/>velocity unknowns the normal components of the velocity field with respect to the edges of the <lb/>control volumes, while the pressure unknowns are located at their circumcenters. In addition, <lb/>the covolume scheme considers vorticity unknowns at the vertices of the primal mesh. <lb/>The generalization of the MAC scheme we propose is a new application of the &quot; discrete dual-<lb/>ity finite volume &quot; (DDFV) method [14]. Originally developed for linear diffusion equations [15, <lb/>16, 17], the DDFV method was extended to nonlinear diffusion [18, 19, 20], convection-diffusion <lb/>[21], electro-cardiology [22, 23], drift-diffusion and energy-transport models [24], electro-and <lb/>magnetostatics [25], electromagnetism [26], and Stokes flows [27, 28, 29, 30]. The advantage of <lb/>this covolume-like method is that it allows the use of almost arbitrary meshes, including very <lb/>distorted, degenerating, or highly non-conforming meshes (see the numerical tests in [15]). The <lb/>name of the method comes from the definition of discrete gradient and divergence operators <lb/>verifying a discrete Green formula. <lb/>In order to get rid of the orthogonality constraints that restrict the use of MAC and covolume <lb/>schemes to certain families of meshes, the price to pay in the DDFV framework is to discretize <lb/> both velocity components on the edges of the control volumes, while pressure and vorticity <lb/>unknowns are associated with the centroids of the primal cells and to their vertices. Then, we <lb/>integrate both components of (1.7) on cells associated with the edges (the so-called &quot; diamond <lb/>mesh &quot; ) and (1.8) and (1.2) on both primal and dual cells associated to the vertices. This process <lb/>uses discrete versions of the divergence, gradient and curl operators which appear in (1.7), (1.8) <lb/>and (1.2). These discrete operators are known to satisfy properties analogous to those verified <lb/>by the continuous operators [25]. With these properties, we show that the solution of the DDFV <lb/></body>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<body> discretization of the Stokes equations with any of the conditions (1.3) to (1.6) can be reduced <lb/>to the solution of four discrete Laplace equations involving the pressure, the vorticity and the <lb/>potentials stemming from the discrete Hodge decomposition of the velocity. <lb/>Other approaches with finite volumes were developed in [31, 32, 33, 34]. In [31, 32], velocity <lb/>unknowns are located at the cell centers, and pressure unknowns at the vertices. But an orthog-<lb/>onality condition is also needed: the segments connecting the cell centers must be orthogonal to <lb/>the edges of the mesh, which restricts this scheme to particular families of meshes. The same <lb/>kind of orthogonality condition is needed in [33, 34], where velocity and pressure unknowns <lb/>are all located at the cell centers. This choice requires some stabilization obtained by penaliz-<lb/>ing the discrete incompressibility equation. Such a penalization is also needed in the previous <lb/>approaches that used the DDFV ideas [28, 29, 30] because in these works, velocity unknowns <lb/>are located at the cell centers and vertices, while pressure is defined on the edges (or faces in <lb/>3D) of the cells, and thus the pressure gradient is proved to be injective only on simplices, and <lb/>there might be spurious pressure modes on more general meshes if no penalization is added. In <lb/>the approach developed in the present article, such a penalization is not needed: The pressure <lb/>gradient is computed from two pressure differences, one related to pressure unknowns located <lb/>at the vertices of an edge, and another related to pressure unknowns located at two neighboring <lb/>cell centers. This leads to the fact that on any mesh, a vanishing gradient implies that pressure <lb/>is a constant on the primal and on the dual meshes. Moreover, in our work, the important role <lb/>played in the Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition of vector fields by internal boundaries in the case <lb/>of non-simply connected domains is very simply taken into account through the Euler formula <lb/>that links the number of edges, cells, vertices and internal boundaries (see [25] for more details <lb/>on this). This wouldn&apos;t have been the case if we had chosen the same unknown locations as in <lb/>[28, 29, 30]. <lb/>Another important result we obtain here is that there exists a way to discretize the data <lb/> f such that if g = 0 and if f is the gradient of the pressure (resp. the curl of the vorticity), <lb/>then our scheme computes exactly (up to the precision of 1D quadrature formulas) the pressure <lb/>and a vanishing vorticity (resp. the vorticity and a vanishing pressure) at the cell centers and <lb/>vertices. <lb/>As compared to previous work with DDFV schemes, the novelty here is to realize that <lb/>the vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation of the Stokes equations associated to an appropriate <lb/>choice of the degrees of freedom reduces the numerical solution of this problem to four discrete <lb/>DDFV Laplace equations. Another novelty is that in the course of the numerical analysis of the <lb/>scheme, we are led to evaluate the difference between some functions and their pointwise values <lb/>on the one hand, and their mean-value projections on the other hand, both on the primal and <lb/>dual meshes. These kinds of estimations had never been used previously in the DDFV context. <lb/>Moreover, we had to combine this with some Poincaré inequalities which have recently been <lb/>proved [35]. <lb/>When g = 0 in Eq. (1.2), another feature of this scheme is that it satisfies the notion of <lb/> &quot; reinforced incompressibility &quot; introduced in a finite volume element context in [36] and in a finite <lb/>element context in [37] to overcome non-perfectly divergence free velocity modes that may appear <lb/>in unsteady Navier-Stokes simulations performed with Crouzeix-Raviart [38] finite elements of <lb/>lowest order. Indeed, since these elements involve pressure unknowns located at the triangle <lb/>barycenters only, the incompressibility constraint is satisfied only around these barycenters, but <lb/>the discrete velocity divergence, when computed around the vertices of the mesh, may not vanish <lb/></body>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body> or even be small. A cure to this problem, proposed in [37] and [36], is to add pressure unknowns <lb/>at the vertices of the mesh, which introduces incompressibility constraints around these nodes. <lb/>Thus, on triangular meshes, the scheme presented here has exactly the same unknowns as (but <lb/>is however not equivalent to) those involved in [37] and [36], and incompressibility conditions <lb/>are written on each triangle (primal cell) and around each vertex (dual cell) of the mesh. The <lb/>advantage of the scheme we present here is that it handles meshes that are much more general <lb/>than triangular. <lb/>The convergence analysis shows that pressure, vorticity, their gradients and the velocity field <lb/>are all first order accurate on general meshes. Moreover, for families of meshes where diamond <lb/>cells are almost all parallelograms, pressure and vorticity gradients superconverge with the order <lb/>1.5. The numerical tests included in this work validate these theoretical results, and even go <lb/>beyond: We observe that pressure and vorticity converge on general meshes with the order 2, <lb/>while velocity converges with the order 2 for families of triangular meshes or for which the <lb/>diamond cells are almost all parallelograms. <lb/>The paper is organized as follows: in Section 2, we introduce the notations associated with <lb/>the primal, dual and diamond meshes. In Section 3, we define the discrete gradient and vector <lb/>curl on the diamond cells, and the corresponding adjoint discrete divergence and scalar curl <lb/>on the primal and dual cells and state their properties. In Section 4, we present the DDFV <lb/>schemes for the steady Stokes problems with the various conditions (1.3)–(1.6) extended to <lb/>non-simply connected domains. Section 5 is devoted to the convergence analysis of the DDFV <lb/>scheme with conditions (1.3). Finally, section 6 presents numerical results over unstructured <lb/>and non-conforming meshes. <lb/> 2 Definitions and notations <lb/> Let Ω be a bounded connected polygon of R  2  , with boundary denoted by Γ. We suppose that <lb/>the domain has Q holes. Throughout the paper, we shall assume that Q &gt; 0, but the results also <lb/>hold for the case Q = 0. Let Γ  0  denote the exterior boundary of Ω and let Γ  q  , with q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> be the interior polygonal boundaries of Ω, so that Γ = Γ  0 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> q∈[1,Q] <lb/> Γ  q  . <lb/> 2.1 Construction of the primal mesh <lb/> We consider a first partition of Ω (named primal mesh) composed of elements T  i  , with i ∈ [1, I], <lb/> supposed to be convex polygons. With each element T  i  of the mesh, we associate a node G  i <lb/> located at the barycentre of T  i  . The area of T  i  is denoted by |T  i  |. We shall denote by J the <lb/>total number of edges of this mesh and by J  Γ  the number of these edges which are located on <lb/>the boundary Γ and we associate with each of these boundary edges its midpoint, also denoted <lb/>by G  i  with i ∈ [I + 1, I + J  Γ  ]. By a slight abuse of notations, we shall write i ∈ Γ  q  if and only <lb/>if G  i  ∈ Γ  q  . <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<body> 2.2 Construction of the dual mesh <lb/> We denote by S  k  , with k ∈ [1, K], the nodes of the polygons of the primal mesh. Around each <lb/> S  k  , we construct a polygon P  k  by joining the points G  i  associated to the elements of the primal <lb/>mesh (and possibly to the boundary edges) of which S  k  is a node, through the midpoints of the <lb/>edges. The area of P  k  is denoted by |P  k  |. The family of cells (P  k  )  k∈[1,K]  constitutes a second <lb/>partition of Ω, which we name dual mesh. We shall also write k ∈ Γ  q  (respectively k ∈ Γ) if and <lb/>only if S  k  ∈ Γ  q  (resp. S  k  ∈ Γ). Figure 1 displays an example of a non-conforming primal mesh <lb/>and its associated dual mesh. <lb/> Pk <lb/> Ti <lb/>Sk <lb/>Gi <lb/> Figure 1: An example of a primal mesh and its associated dual mesh. <lb/> 2.3 Construction of the diamond mesh <lb/> With each edge of the primal mesh, denoted by A  j  (whose length is |A  j  |), with j ∈ [1, J], <lb/> we associate a quadrilateral named &quot; diamond cell &quot; , denoted by D  j  . When A  j  is not on the <lb/>boundary, this cell is obtained by joining the points S  k1(j)  and S  k2(j)  , which are the two nodes <lb/>of A  j  , with the points G  i1(j)  and G  i2(j)  associated with the elements of the primal mesh which <lb/>share this edge. When A  j  is on the boundary Γ, the cell D  j  is obtained by joining the two <lb/>nodes of A  j  with the point G  i1(j)  associated with the only element of the primal mesh of which <lb/> A  j  is an edge and to the point G  i2(j)  associated with A  j  (i.e. by convention i  2  (j) is element of <lb/>[I + 1, I + J  Γ  ] when A  j  is located on Γ). The cells D  j  constitute the &quot; diamond-mesh &quot; , which is <lb/>a third partition of Ω. The area of the cell D  j  is denoted by |D  j  |. Such cells are displayed on <lb/>Fig. 2. We shall also write j ∈ Γ  q  (respectively j ∈ Γ) if and only if A  j  ⊂ Γ  q  (resp. j ⊂ Γ). <lb/> 2.4 Definitions of geometrical elements <lb/> The following geometrical elements are displayed on Fig. 3. The unit vector normal to A  j <lb/> is denoted by n  j  and is oriented so that its dot product with G  i1(j)  G  i2(j)  is positive. We <lb/>further denote by A  񮽙 <lb/> j  the segment [G  i1(j)  G  i2(j)  ] (whose length is |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  |) and by n  񮽙 <lb/> j  the unit <lb/>vector normal to A  񮽙 <lb/> j  oriented so that S  k1(j)  S  k2(j)  · n  񮽙 <lb/> j  ≥ 0. We also define the unit vectors <lb/> τ  j  and τ  񮽙 <lb/> j  such that (n  j  , τ  j  ) and (n  񮽙 <lb/> j  , τ  񮽙 <lb/> j  ) are orthogonal positively oriented bases of R  2  . We <lb/>denote by M  j  the midpoint of A  j  and by A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  (respectively A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  ) the segment [G  i1(j)  M  j  ] (resp. <lb/>[M  j  G  i2(j)  ]) and by n  񮽙 <lb/> j1  (resp. n  񮽙 <lb/> j2  ) the unit normal vector to A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  (resp. A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  ) oriented so that <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  |n  񮽙 <lb/> j  = |A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  |n  񮽙 <lb/> j1  + |A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  |n  񮽙 <lb/> j2  . We define for each i ∈ [1, I] the set V (i) of integers j ∈ [1, J] such <lb/></body>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>G  i 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> S <lb/>G i <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/>k <lb/> S k <lb/> j <lb/> D <lb/> G <lb/>G <lb/>1 <lb/>i <lb/>S 2 <lb/>k <lb/>S k 1 <lb/>i 2 <lb/>D <lb/>j <lb/> Figure 2: Examples of diamond cells. <lb/> i 2 <lb/>G 1 <lb/>S <lb/>S k 1 <lb/>G <lb/>i <lb/>2 <lb/>k <lb/>A <lb/>n <lb/>n&apos; <lb/> j <lb/> D <lb/> j <lb/>j <lb/>j <lb/> A&apos; j <lb/> S k 1 <lb/> A&apos; j <lb/> G <lb/> 2 <lb/> i <lb/> G i 1 <lb/> j <lb/> n&apos; <lb/>M j <lb/> n&apos; j1 <lb/> A&apos; j1 <lb/> n&apos; j2 <lb/> A&apos; j2 <lb/> S k 2 <lb/> Figure 3: Notations for the diamond cell. <lb/>that A  j  is an edge of T  i  and for each k ∈ [1, K] the set E(k) of integers j ∈ [1, J] such that S  k <lb/> is a node of A  j  . <lb/>We define for each j ∈ [1, J] and each k such that j ∈ E(k) (resp. each i such that j ∈ V (i)) <lb/>the real-valued number s  񮽙 <lb/> jk  (resp. s  ji  ) whose value is +1 or −1 whether n  񮽙 <lb/> j  (resp. n  j  ) points <lb/>outward or inward P  k  (resp. T  i  ). We define n  񮽙 <lb/> jk  := s  񮽙 <lb/> jk  n  񮽙 <lb/> j  (resp. n  ji  := s  ji  n  j  ) and remark that <lb/> n  񮽙 <lb/> jk  (resp. n  ji  ) always points outward P  k  (resp. T  i  ). In the same way, we set n  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  := s  񮽙 <lb/> jk  n  񮽙 <lb/> j1 <lb/> and n  񮽙 <lb/> jk2  := s  񮽙 <lb/> jk  n  񮽙 <lb/> j2  . <lb/> 2.5 A hypothesis on the mesh regularity <lb/> In the sequel of this article, we shall obtain error estimates under the following hypothesis (see <lb/>Figure 4 for the notations). <lb/> Hypothesis 2.1. The angles of the subtriangulation G  i  M  j  S  k  of the diamond-cells D  j  are <lb/>greater than an angle θ  *  which is strictly positive and independent of the mesh: <lb/> ∃θ  *  , 0 &lt; θ  *  &lt; <lb/> π <lb/> 2 <lb/> such that <lb/> min{α  m  , β  m  , γ  m  } ≥ θ  *  , m = 1, 2, 3, 4. <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<body> i <lb/> G 1 <lb/> G 2 <lb/> S <lb/>M j <lb/> S k 1 <lb/> i <lb/> 2 <lb/> k <lb/>4 <lb/> β <lb/> 1 <lb/> γ <lb/>α  1 <lb/> β  1 <lb/> γ  2 <lb/> β  2 <lb/>3 <lb/> γ <lb/> 3 <lb/> β <lb/> 4 <lb/> γ <lb/>α  4 <lb/>2 <lb/> α <lb/> 3 <lb/> α <lb/> Figure 4: Notations for Hypothesis 2.1. <lb/>We can easily verify that Hypothesis 2.1 implies various weaker hypotheses: [15, Hypotheses <lb/>5.5 and 5.6], [25, Hypothesis 5.5] and [35, Definition 2.1] under which results obtained in these <lb/>articles, and used in the present work, are valid. <lb/> 3 The discrete operators and their properties <lb/> We may approach the gradient 񮽙 = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/> ∂x  ,  ∂ <lb/>∂y <lb/> 񮽙  T <lb/> and the vector curl 񮽙× = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂ <lb/>∂y  , −  ∂ <lb/>∂x <lb/> 񮽙  T <lb/> by <lb/>discrete counterparts on the diamond cells D  j  (see [15, 25]). <lb/> Definition 3.1. For any φ = (φ  T <lb/>i  , φ  P <lb/>k  ) ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  , the discrete gradient 񮽙  D <lb/>h  and vector <lb/>curl 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × are defined by their values over the diamond cells D  j  (see Fig. 3): <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  j  := <lb/>1 <lb/>2 |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> φ  P <lb/>k2  − φ  P <lb/>k1 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  |n  񮽙 <lb/> j  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> φ  T <lb/>i2  − φ  T <lb/>i1 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  j  |n  j <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> , <lb/> (3.1) <lb/>(񮽙  D <lb/>h  × φ)  j  := − <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> φ  P <lb/>k2  − φ  P <lb/>k1 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  |τ  񮽙 <lb/> j  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> φ  T <lb/>i2  − φ  T <lb/>i1 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  j  |τ  j <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.2) <lb/>Note that formulas (3.1)-(3.2) are exact for any affine function φ if we set φ  P <lb/>k  := φ(S  k  ) and <lb/> φ  T <lb/>i  := φ(G  i  ), for any (i, k). <lb/> Next, for a discrete vector field u, given by its values u  j  on the cells D  j  , we define its discrete <lb/>divergence and curl on the primal and dual cells. <lb/> Definition 3.2. For u = (u  j  ) ∈ (R  2  )  J  , the discrete divergence 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h  · := (񮽙  T <lb/>h  ·, 񮽙  P <lb/>h  ·) and discrete <lb/>curl 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h  × := (񮽙  T <lb/>h  ×, 񮽙  P <lb/>h  ×) are defined by their values over the primal cells T  i  and the dual <lb/></body>

			<page> 7 <lb/></page>

			<body> T  i <lb/> A j <lb/> τ  ji <lb/>ji <lb/> n <lb/> jk1 <lb/> n&apos; <lb/> jk1 <lb/> τ  &apos; <lb/> jk2 <lb/> τ <lb/> jk2 <lb/> n&apos; <lb/> k <lb/> A&apos; <lb/>A&apos; j2 <lb/>j1 <lb/> P <lb/> &apos; <lb/> Figure 5: Edges and unit vectors for the discrete divergence and curl <lb/> cells P  k  (see Fig. 5) <lb/> (񮽙  T <lb/>h  · u)  i  := <lb/>1 <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈V (i) <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · n  ji  , <lb/> (3.3) <lb/>(񮽙  P <lb/>h  · u)  k  := <lb/>1 <lb/> |P  k  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  |n  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  + |A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  |n  񮽙 <lb/> jk2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> · u  j  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k)∩Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · n  j <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (񮽙  T <lb/>h  × u)  i  : = <lb/>1 <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈V (i) <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · τ  ji  , <lb/> (3.4) <lb/>(񮽙  P <lb/>h  × u)  k  : = <lb/>1 <lb/> |P  k  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  |τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  + |A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  |τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> · u  j  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k)∩Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · τ  j <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> Remark that if the node S  k  is not on the boundary Γ (i.e. if k / <lb/> ∈ Γ), then the set E(k) ∩ Γ is <lb/>empty. On the contrary, if P  k  is a boundary dual cell, then the set E(k) ∩ Γ is composed of the <lb/>two boundary edges which have S  k  as a vertex. In this case, the quantity <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k)∩Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · n  j <lb/> (resp. <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈E(k)∩Γ <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · τ  j  ) is an approximation of <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂P  k  ∩Γ <lb/> u · n(ξ) dξ (resp. <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ∂P  k  ∩Γ <lb/> u · τ (ξ) dξ.) <lb/> For a given vector field u, it is straightforward to check that formulae (3.3) (resp. (3.4)) are the <lb/>exact mean-values of 񮽙·u (resp. 񮽙·τ ) over T  i  and an inner P  k  if |A  j  |u  j  ·n  ji  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> u·n  ji  ds (resp. <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · τ  ji  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> u · τ  ji  ds) and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  |n  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  + |A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  |n  񮽙 <lb/> jk2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> · u  j  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j1 <lb/> u · n  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  ds + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j2 <lb/> u · n  񮽙 <lb/> jk2  ds <lb/> (resp. <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j1  |τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  + |A  񮽙 <lb/> j2  |τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> · u  j  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j1 <lb/> u · τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk1  ds + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j2 <lb/> u · τ  񮽙 <lb/> jk2  ds). <lb/> Now, we define discrete scalar products and a trace operator. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<body> Definition 3.3. For (φ, ψ) ∈ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> R  I  × R  K  񮽙  2  and (u, v) ∈ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (R  2  )  J  񮽙  2  , we set: <lb/> (u, v)  D  := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈[1,J] <lb/> |D  j  | u  j  · v  j  , <lb/> (3.5) <lb/>(φ, ψ)  T,P  := <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  | φ  T <lb/>i  ψ  T <lb/>i  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  | φ  P <lb/>k  ψ  P <lb/>k <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.6) <lb/> The associated norms will be denoted by || · ||  D  and || · ||  T,P  . We also define discrete scalar <lb/>products on the boundaries Γ  q  and Γ: for sets of values (u  j  , v  j  )  j∈Γ  we set: <lb/> (u, v)  Γq,h  := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γq <lb/> |A  j  | u  j  v  j <lb/> , <lb/> (u, v)  Γ,h  := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> q∈[0,Q] <lb/> (u, v)  Γq,h  . <lb/> (3.7) <lb/>In particular, we shall often consider these boundary scalar products for the trace <lb/> φ of a <lb/>given φ ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  , defined by <lb/> Definition 3.4. (Trace operator) For any φ ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  , and for any j ∈ Γ, we set <lb/> φ  j  := <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> φ  P <lb/>k1(j)  + 2φ  T <lb/>i2(j)  + φ  P <lb/>k2(j) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (3.8) <lb/>With these scalar products, the discrete operators verify properties which are analogues to <lb/>properties of the continuous operators [25, 15]: <lb/> Proposition 3.5. The following discrete analogues of the Green formulae hold: <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · u, φ)  T,P  = −(u, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  D  + (u · n, ˜ <lb/> φ)  Γ,h  , <lb/> (3.9) <lb/>(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × u, φ)  T,P  = (u, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × φ)  D  + (u · τ , ˜ <lb/> φ)  Γ,h  , <lb/> (3.10) <lb/> for all u ∈ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> R  J  񮽙  2  and all φ = (φ  T  , φ  P  ) ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  . <lb/> The following two propositions state discrete equivalents of the continuous properties 񮽙 · <lb/> (񮽙×) = 0, 񮽙 × 񮽙 = 0 and 񮽙 × (񮽙×) = −− · 񮽙 (in two dimensions). Note however the <lb/>hypothesis needed on the boundary dual cells: <lb/> Proposition 3.6. For all φ = (φ  T  , φ  P  ) ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  , the following equalities hold: <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × φ) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i,k <lb/> = 0, <lb/> ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> (3.11) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × (񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i,k <lb/> = 0, <lb/> ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ. <lb/> (3.12) <lb/> Moreover, these formulae still hold on boundary dual cells P  k  , k ∈ Γ, if for any q ∈ [0, Q], there <lb/>exist two real numbers (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  ) such that φ  T <lb/>i  = c  T <lb/>q  and φ  P <lb/>k  = c  P <lb/>q  uniformly over Γ  q  . <lb/> Proposition 3.7. For all φ = (φ  T  , φ  P  ) ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  , the following equality holds: <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × φ)  i,k  = −(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k ∈ [1, K]. <lb/> (3.13) <lb/></body>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body> Finally, a discrete Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition of vector fields in non simply connected <lb/>domains holds [25]: <lb/> Proposition 3.8. Let (u  j  )  j∈[1,J]  be a discrete vector field defined by its values on the diamond <lb/>cells D  j  . Then, there exist unique φ = (φ  T <lb/>i  , φ  P <lb/>k  ) and ψ = (ψ  T <lb/>i  , ψ  P <lb/>k  ) both in R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  and <lb/> (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  ) in R  Q  × R  Q  such that: <lb/> u  j  = (񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  j  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  j  , ∀j ∈ [1, J], <lb/> (3.14) <lb/> with <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |φ  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |φ  P <lb/>k  = 0 , <lb/> (3.15) <lb/> ψ  T <lb/>i <lb/> = 0 , ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , ψ  P <lb/>k  = 0 , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , <lb/> (3.16) <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q] , <lb/> ψ  T <lb/>i <lb/> = c  T <lb/>q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ψ  P <lb/>k  = c  P <lb/>q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  . <lb/> (3.17) <lb/> Moreover, the decomposition (3.14) is orthogonal, in the sense that <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  D  = 0, <lb/>(3.18) <lb/> a property that is true for all φ and all ψ verifying (3.16) and (3.17). <lb/> Formulae (3.15) are discrete analogues (respectively stated on the primal mesh and on the <lb/>dual mesh) of the condition <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> φ = 0 that appears in the continuous Helmholtz-Hodge decom-<lb/>position, while formulae (3.16) and (3.17) are discrete analogues of the boundary conditions <lb/> ψ = 0 on Γ  0  and ψ = c  q  on Γ  q  . <lb/> Remark 3.9. We may also write a similar decomposition by changing the conditions (3.15)– <lb/>(3.17) in the following way <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |ψ  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |ψ  P <lb/>k  = 0 , <lb/> (3.19) <lb/> φ  T <lb/>i <lb/> = 0 , ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , φ  P <lb/>k  = 0 , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , <lb/> (3.20) <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q] , <lb/> φ  T <lb/>i <lb/> = c  T <lb/>q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , φ  P <lb/>k  = c  P <lb/>q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  . <lb/> (3.21) <lb/>Finally, we mention discrete analogues of the so-called Poincaré inequalities, which were <lb/>proved in [35] (respectively Theorem 3.2 and Theorem 3.6): <lb/> Proposition 3.10. Let φ = (φ  T <lb/>i  , φ  P <lb/>k  ) and ψ = (ψ  T <lb/>i  , ψ  P <lb/>k  ) both in R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  and (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  ) <lb/> in R  Q  × R  Q  be such that (3.15), (3.16) and (3.17) hold; then, there exists a constant C(θ  *  ), <lb/> depending only on θ  *  and on Ω such that <lb/> ||φ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  )||񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ||  D  , ||ψ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  )||񮽙  D <lb/>h  ψ||  D  . <lb/> (3.22) <lb/> 4 Application to the Stokes equations <lb/> In this section, we are interested in the discretization of Eqs. (1.7), (1.8) and (1.2) supplemented <lb/>with one of the following non-standard sets of conditions, which generalize conditions (1.3) to <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<body> (1.6) to non-simply connected domains, with σ, p  d  and ω  d  given functions, m  ω  a given real <lb/>number and (k  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  a set of given real numbers: <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> u · n = σ over Γ , ω  |Γ0  = ω  d  ; ω  |Γq  = ω  d  + c  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> u · τ = k  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> p(x)dx = 0 , <lb/> (4.1) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> u · n = σ over Γ , p  |Γ0  = p  d  ; p  |Γq  = p  d  + c  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> u · τ = k  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ω(x)dx = m  ω  , <lb/> (4.2) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> u · τ = σ over Γ , ω  |Γ0  = ω  d  ; ω  |Γq  = ω  d  + c  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> u · n = k  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> p(x)dx = 0 , <lb/> (4.3) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> u · τ = σ over Γ , p  |Γ0  = p  d  ; p  |Γq  = p  d  + c  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> u · n = k  q  , ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ω(x)dx = m  ω  , <lb/> (4.4) <lb/>where the constants (c  q  ) ∈ R  Q  have to be determined. <lb/>Before going into details of the discretization of these equations, we discuss the compatibility <lb/>conditions of the right-hand sides of these sets of equations. <lb/> 4.1 Compatibility conditions <lb/> Consider Eqs. (1.2), (1.7) and (1.8). First, when associated with one of the sets of conditions <lb/>(4.1) or (4.2), the data has to verify <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> g(x)dx = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γ <lb/> σ(ξ)dξ. <lb/> (4.5) <lb/>Then, when associated with the set (4.4), integration of (1.8) over Ω and application of the <lb/>Green formula and of the boundary conditions yield <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γ <lb/> σ(ξ)dξ = m  ω  . <lb/> (4.6) <lb/>Finally, in the case of Eqs. (1.2), (1.7) and (1.8) associated with the set (4.3), the situation is <lb/>more involved. Indeed, we infer from (1.8) that <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γ <lb/> σ(ξ)dξ = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ω(x)dx. However, the quantity <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ω(x)dx is not a data given by (4.3), but is a result of the computation of ω through the <lb/>Hodge decomposition of f + 񮽙g expressed by Eq. (1.7) associated with the conditions over p <lb/> and ω expressed in the set (4.3). This may be interpreted as an implicit compatibility condition <lb/>between the boundary conditions ω  d  and σ in (4.3). Further details on how to handle this will <lb/>be given in subsection 4.2. <lb/> 4.2 Discretization of the Stokes equations in vorticity-velocity-pressure <lb/>formulation <lb/> In this subsection, we are interested in the approximation of the continuous problem given <lb/>by (1.2)-(1.7)-(1.8) associated with one of the sets of conditions (4.1) to (4.4). We choose to <lb/></body>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body> approach the solution of this problem by a vector (u  j  ), with j ∈ [1, J], which discretizes the <lb/>velocity field by values defined over the diamond cells of the mesh, and by scalars (ω  T <lb/>i  , ω  P <lb/>k  ) and <lb/>(p  T <lb/>i  , p  P <lb/>k  ), with i ∈ [1, I + J  Γ  ], k ∈ [1, K], which discretize the vorticity and the pressure fields <lb/>by values defined over the primal and dual cells, as well as boundary edges of the mesh. The <lb/>problem will be solved in two steps. In the first, we use the Hodge decomposition of f + 񮽙g (see <lb/>prop. 3.8) to solve for p and ω. In the second, we solve a div-curl problem for u. <lb/>Step 1: The discrete Hodge decomposition of the data f + 񮽙g reads: <lb/>find p = (p  T <lb/>i  , p  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ], k∈[1,K]  , ω = (ω  T <lb/>i  , ω  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ], k∈[1,K]  and (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  )  q∈[1,Q]  such that <lb/>(񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  j  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω)  j  = f  D <lb/>j  + (񮽙g)  D <lb/>j  , ∀j ∈ [1, J], <lb/> (4.7) <lb/>together with one of the following sets of conditions <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ω  T <lb/>i  = ω  d  (G  i  ) , ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , ω  T <lb/>i  = ω  d  (G  i  ) + c  T <lb/>q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q , <lb/> ω  P <lb/>k  = ω  d  (S  k  ) , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , ω  P <lb/>k  = ω  d  (S  k  ) + c  P <lb/>q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q , <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  | p  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  | p  P <lb/>k  = 0, <lb/>(4.8) <lb/>for a given (up to constants to be determined on each internal boundary) vorticity field ω  d  on <lb/>the boundary (see the corresponding equations in (4.1) and (4.3)), or <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> p  T <lb/>i  = p  d  (G  i  ) , ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , p  T <lb/>i  = p  d  (G  i  ) + c  T <lb/>q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q , <lb/>p  P <lb/>k  = p  d  (S  k  ) , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , p  P <lb/>k  = p  d  (S  k  ) + c  P <lb/>q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q , <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  | ω  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  | ω  P <lb/>k  = m  ω  , <lb/> (4.9) <lb/>for a given (up to constants to be determined on each internal boundary) pressure field p  d  on <lb/>the boundary (see the corresponding equations in (4.2) and (4.4)). <lb/>In (4.7), the following definitions have been used <lb/> f  D <lb/>j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> f (x) dx , (񮽙g)  D <lb/>j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> 񮽙g (x) dx ∀j ∈ [1, J]. <lb/> (4.10) <lb/>The two problems involving (4.7) and (4.8) on the one hand, and (4.7) and (4.9) on the other <lb/>hand are solved in a very similar way, thus we only detail the solution of (4.7)-(4.8). <lb/> Proposition 4.1. Problem (4.7)-(4.8) may be split into two independent subproblems: setting <lb/> s := (s  D <lb/>j  )  j∈[1,J]  with s  D <lb/>j  := f  D <lb/>j  + (񮽙g)  D <lb/>j  , find (ω  T <lb/>i  , ω  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ],k∈[1,K]  and (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  )  q∈[1,Q]  such <lb/>that <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −(񮽙  T <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω)  i  = (񮽙  T <lb/>h  × s)  i  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], <lb/> −(񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω)  k  = (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × s)  k  , ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω · n, 1)  Γq ,h  = −(s · τ , 1)  Γq,h  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × s)  k  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> ω  T <lb/>i  = ω  d  (G  i  ), ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , ω  P <lb/>k  = ω  d  (S  k  ), ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , <lb/> ω  T <lb/>i  = ω  d  (G  i  ) + c  T <lb/>q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ω  P <lb/>k  = ω  d  (S  k  ) + c  P <lb/>q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q] , <lb/> (4.11) <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<body> and, once ω has been computed, find (p  T <lb/> i  , p  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ],k∈[1,K]  such that <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  i  = (񮽙  T <lb/>h  · s)  i  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], <lb/> (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  k  = (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · (s − 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω))  k  , ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  j  · n  j  = (s  j  − (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω)  j  )) · n  j  , ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  | p  T <lb/>i <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  | p  P <lb/>k  = 0. <lb/>(4.12) <lb/> Proof. Applying the discrete vector curl operator to (4.7) on any primal cell and on any inner <lb/>dual cell yields the first two lines of (4.11), thanks to (3.12) and (3.13). <lb/>Next, for a given q ∈ [1, Q], we consider the element ψ ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  which has the <lb/>following values: ψ  T <lb/>i  = 1, ∀i ∈ Γ  q  and ψ  T <lb/>i  = 0 everywhere else, and ψ  P <lb/>k  = 0 everywhere. Then, <lb/>we compute the scalar product (3.5) of Eq. (4.7) with 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ: <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  D  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  p, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  D  = (s, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  D  . <lb/> (4.13) <lb/>Using the orthogonality of 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ (see last line of Prop. 3.8), using the discrete <lb/>Green formula (3.10) and Eq. (3.13), we infer <lb/> −(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω, ψ)  T,P  − (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω · τ , ˜ <lb/> ψ)  Γ,h  = (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × s, ψ)  T,P  − (s · τ , ˜ <lb/> ψ)  Γ,h  . <lb/> (4.14) <lb/>Further, using the fact that ψ vanishes everywhere but on the boundary points G  i  , the first <lb/>term in the left-hand side and the first term in the right-hand side of (4.14) vanish. Next, since <lb/> 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω · τ = −񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω · n, and using the definition (3.7) and the fact that the values of ψ on <lb/>the boundaries imply that <lb/> ψ  j  = 1/2 for all j ∈ Γ  q  and <lb/> ψ  j  = 0 for all j ∈ Γ  񮽙 <lb/> q  for any q  񮽙  񮽙 = q, <lb/> Equ. (4.14) implies −(񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω · n,  1 <lb/>2  )  Γq,h  = (s · τ ,  1 <lb/>2  )  Γq,h  and thus the third line of (4.11). <lb/>Last, we consider the element ψ ∈ R  I+J  Γ  × R  K  which has the following values: ψ  T <lb/>i  = 1, <lb/> ∀i ∈ Γ  q  and ψ  P <lb/>k  = 1, ∀k ∈ Γ  q  and vanishing everywhere else. Then, the dot product of Eq. <lb/>(4.7) with 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ yields (4.13) and (4.14) again. Now, we use the fact that the first term <lb/>in the left-hand side of (4.14) equals −  1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω)  k  while the first term in the <lb/>right-hand side of (4.14) equals  1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × s)  k  . Using the previously proved third line <lb/>of (4.11), we obtain the fourth line of (4.11). <lb/>Once ω has been computed, the derivation of (4.12) from (4.7)-(4.8) is obvious. We stress <lb/>that in the second equation of (4.12), there holds (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω)  k  = 0 for all inner dual cells <lb/>(k / <lb/> ∈ Γ) but that this property might not necessarily be true for boundary dual cells (k ∈ Γ), <lb/> see Prop. 3.6. <lb/>Step 1 ends with the fact that (4.11) and (4.12) are well-posed: <lb/> Lemma 4.2. It was shown in [25, Proposition 5.2] that systems of types (4.11) and (4.12) both <lb/>have a unique solution. <lb/> Now, let us describe Step 2 of the calculations, which consists in solving for the velocity. <lb/></body>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body> Step 2: Once (ω  T <lb/> i  , ω  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I],k∈[1,K]  has been computed through Step 1, we solve a div-curl <lb/>problem for u: given (k  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  , find (u  j  )  j∈[1,J]  such that <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · u)  i,k  = g  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × u)  i,k  = ω  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> u  j  · n  j  = σ  j  , <lb/> ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> (u · τ , 1)  Γq,h  = k  q  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × u)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | ω  P <lb/>k  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> (4.15) <lb/>in the case of a given normal velocity field on the boundary (Eqs. (4.1) or (4.2)) or <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · u)  i,k  = g  T,P <lb/>i,k  , <lb/> ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × u)  i,k  = ω  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> u  j  · τ  j  = σ  j  , <lb/> ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> (u · n, 1)  Γq,h  = k  q  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · u)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq  |P  k  | g  P <lb/>k  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> (4.16) <lb/>in the case of a given tangential velocity field on the boundary (Eqs. (4.3) or (4.4)). <lb/>In (4.15) and (4.16), we have set <lb/> g  T <lb/>i  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/> g(x) dx ∀i ∈ [1, I] , g  P <lb/>k  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |P  k  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> P  k <lb/> g(x) dx ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (4.17) <lb/> σ  j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |A  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> σ(ξ) dξ ∀j ∈ Γ. <lb/> (4.18) <lb/>Moreover, the right-hand sides in (4.15) and (4.16) have to verify compatibility conditions. <lb/>Indeed, it is readily seen from the definition of the discrete divergence and curl operators (3.3) <lb/>and (3.4) that the following two equalities hold <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |(񮽙  T <lb/>h  · u)  i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  P <lb/>h  · u)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γ <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · n  j  , <lb/> (4.19) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |(񮽙  T <lb/>h  × u)  i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  P <lb/>h  × u)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γ <lb/> |A  j  |u  j  · τ  j  . <lb/> (4.20) <lb/>Then, because of (4.19), the right-hand sides in (4.15) must satisfy <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |g  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |g  P <lb/>k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γ <lb/> |A  j  |σ  j  . <lb/> (4.21) <lb/>This relation is true thanks to the definitions (4.17) and (4.18) since <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |g  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |g  P <lb/>k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> g(x) dx <lb/> and <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γ <lb/> |A  j  |σ  j  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γ <lb/> σ(ξ) dξ . <lb/></body>

			<page> 14 <lb/></page>

			<body> That the right-hand sides of the above two equalities are identical follows from (4.5). <lb/>Further, because of (4.20), the right-hand sides in (4.16) must satisfy <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |ω  T <lb/>i  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  |ω  P <lb/>k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈Γ <lb/> |A  j  |σ  j  . <lb/> (4.22) <lb/>For the set of conditions (4.9), the first two terms in (4.22) are equal to m  ω  and the last term <lb/>in (4.22) is equal to <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γ <lb/> σ(ξ) dξ. These two quantities are identical thanks to (4.6). <lb/>On the other hand, for the set of conditions (4.8), the values of the first two terms in (4.22) <lb/>are never imposed, but, rather, are results of the computations involved in the first step of our <lb/>procedure, see Eq. (4.11), so that the compatibility condition (4.22) may not be verified in <lb/>general. A possible way to overcome this problem is to change ω  T <lb/>i  into ω  T <lb/>i  + c  T  and ω  P <lb/>k  into <lb/> ω  P <lb/>k  +c  P  for all i ∈ [1, I +J  Γ  ] and all k ∈ [1, K] in (4.16), with two constants c  T  and c  P  computed <lb/>so that (4.22) holds. Doing so does not change the value of 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω, so that the modified ω still <lb/>verifies system (4.11), but with modified boundary conditions. This may be interpreted as an <lb/>implicit compatibility condition between the boundary conditions ω  d  and σ in (4.3). <lb/>Now, using the discrete Hodge decomposition of (u  j  )  j∈[1,J]  , each of the problems (4.15) and <lb/>(4.16) may be split into two independent subproblems involving the potentials. We only detail <lb/>the resulting systems for problem (4.15) using the Hodge decomposition with boundary condi-<lb/>tions (3.15) to (3.17). A similar result holds for problem (4.16) using the Hodge decomposition <lb/>with boundary conditions (3.19) to (3.21). <lb/> Proposition 4.3. Problem (4.15) may be split into two independent problems: <lb/>find (φ  T <lb/>i  , φ  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ],k∈[1,K]  such that <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  i  = g  T <lb/>i  , <lb/> ∀i ∈ [1, I], <lb/> (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  k  = g  P <lb/>k  , <lb/> ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  j  · n  j  = σ  j  , <lb/> ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  | φ  T <lb/>i <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K] <lb/> |P  k  | φ  P <lb/>k  = 0, <lb/>(4.23) <lb/> and find (ψ  T <lb/>i  , ψ  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ],k∈[1,K]  and (c  T <lb/>q  , c  P <lb/>q  )  q∈[1,Q]  such that <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −(񮽙  T <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ψ)  i  = ω  T <lb/>i  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], <lb/> −(񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ψ)  k  = ω  P <lb/>k  , ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> −(񮽙  D <lb/>h  ψ · n, 1)  Γq ,h  = k  q  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> − <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  · 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ψ)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | ω  P <lb/>k  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> ψ  T <lb/>i  = ψ  P <lb/>k <lb/> = 0, <lb/> ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], ψ  T <lb/>i  = c  T <lb/>q <lb/> , ψ  P <lb/>k  = c  P <lb/>q  , <lb/> ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  . <lb/> (4.24) <lb/> Proof. The proof is given in [25, Proposition 5.1]. <lb/>Step 2 ends with the fact that (4.23) and (4.24) are well-posed: <lb/> Lemma 4.4. It was shown in [25, Proposition 5.2] that systems of the type (4.23) and (4.24) <lb/>both have a unique solution. <lb/></body>

			<page> 15 <lb/></page>

			<body> Once these two subproblems have been solved, the vector u is then reconstructed by u  j  = <lb/>(񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ)  j  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ)  j  . <lb/> 5 Error estimates <lb/> Obtaining error estimates usually relies on regularity assumptions on the solution of the problem. <lb/>In order to apply results given in [25, 15], we shall assume more regularity on the vorticity and <lb/>pressure fields (ˆ ω, ˆ <lb/> p) given by Proposition 5.1 below, and on the velocity potentials given by <lb/>Proposition 5.3 below. <lb/> Proposition 5.1. Let (f , g, σ, ω  d  ) belong to L  2  (Ω) <lb/> 2  × H  1  (Ω) × H  1/2  (Γ) × H  1/2  (Γ), and let <lb/> (k  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  be a set of given real numbers. Then, system (1.7)-(1.8)-(1.2)-(4.1) associated with <lb/>(4.5) may be split into two subproblems, where (ˆ p, ˆ <lb/> w) ∈ H  1  (Ω) <lb/> 2  and a set of real numbers <lb/> (C  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  are the exact solution of the Hodge decomposition of f + 񮽙g: <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> 񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω + 񮽙ˆ     ?g in Ω, <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ω  |Γ0  = ω  d  ; <lb/>ˆ <lb/> ω  |Γq  = ω  d  + C  q  ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ˆ <lb/> p(x)dx = 0, <lb/>(5.1) <lb/> and, onceê <lb/> ω has been determined, ˆ <lb/> u ∈ Hdiv(Ω) ∩ Hcurl(Ω) solves the div-curl problem: <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> 񮽙 · ˆ <lb/> u = g in Ω, <lb/> 񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> u = ˆ <lb/> ω in Ω, <lb/> ˆ <lb/> u · n = σ on Γ, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> u · τ = k  q  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q]. <lb/> (5.2) <lb/> Hypothesis 5.2. We assume that  <lb/> ω and  <lb/> p given by Proposition 5.1 belong to H  2  (Ω). <lb/>The velocity field <lb/> u solving (5.2) may be found by the following Hodge decomposition. <lb/> Proposition 5.3. Let (g, ˆ <lb/> ω, σ) belong to H  1  (Ω) × H  2  (Ω) × H  1/2  (Γ), and let (k  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  be a set <lb/>of given real numbers; let  <lb/> u be the exact solution of problem (5.2). Then, there exist  <lb/> φ and  <lb/> ψ <lb/> both in H  1  (Ω) and a set of real numbers (C  q  )  q∈[1,Q]  such that <lb/> u = 񮽙  <lb/> φ + 񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ψ, <lb/> whereê <lb/> φ and  <lb/> ψ are the solutions of <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> ∆ ˆ <lb/> φ = 񮽙 · ˆ <lb/> u = g in Ω, <lb/> 񮽙  <lb/> φ · n = ˆ <lb/> u · n = σ on Γ, <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ˆ <lb/> φ = 0, <lb/>and <lb/>(5.3) <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> −∆  <lb/> ψ = 񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> u = ˆ <lb/> ω in Ω, <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ψ  |Γ0  = 0; ˆ <lb/> ψ  |Γq  = C  q  ∀ q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Γq <lb/> 񮽙  <lb/> ψ · n = −k  q  . <lb/> (5.4) <lb/></body>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. The Hodge decomposition of <lb/> u and the determination of <lb/> φ and <lb/> ψ through (5.3) and (5.4) <lb/>are direct consequences of [39, Theorem 3.2 and Corollary 3.1]. <lb/> Hypothesis 5.4. We suppose that  <lb/> φ and  <lb/> ψ given by Proposition 5.3 belong to H  2  (Ω). <lb/>Due to re-entrant corners related to the internal polygonal boundaries Γ  q  , the H  2  regularity <lb/>of the potentials is not a consequence of the regularity of the data (g, ˆ <lb/> ω, σ). <lb/> 5.1 Error estimates in the H  1  semi-norm for the pressure and the <lb/>vorticity <lb/> Definition 5.5. For any continuous function v, we define Πv by <lb/> ∀i ∈ [1, I + J  Γ  ], <lb/>(Πv)  T <lb/>i  = v(G  i  ), <lb/> ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (Πv)  P <lb/>k  = v(S  k  ). <lb/>We note that, under Hypothesis 5.2, ˆ <lb/> ω and <lb/> p belong to H  2  (Ω), which implies they are <lb/>continuous on ¯ <lb/> Ω, so that considering Πˆ ând Πˆ  akes sense. <lb/> Theorem 5.6. Let p and ω be the solutions of the numerical scheme (4.7)–(4.8), and let (ˆ p, ˆ <lb/> ω) <lb/> be the exact solutions of (5.1). Then, if all diamond-cells are convex and under assumptions 2.1 <lb/>and 5.2, there exists a constant C(θ  *  ), independent of h, such that <lb/> ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (p − Πˆ |  D  + ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (ω − Πˆ |  D  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h (񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  ). <lb/>(5.5) <lb/> Proof. Firstly, taking the mean-value of each term of the first line of Equ. (5.1) on a diamond <lb/>cell D  j  and using (4.10), we get: <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ   ? × ˆ <lb/> ω)(x)dx = f  D <lb/>j  + (񮽙g)  D <lb/>j  , ∀j ∈ [1, J]. <lb/> (5.6) <lb/>Then, since (5.6) and (4.7) have the same right-hand side, we infer that: <lb/>(񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  j  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ω)  j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ   ? × ˆ <lb/> ω)(x)dx, ∀j ∈ [1, J]. <lb/> (5.7) <lb/>Setting <lb/> ε  p  := p − Πˆ ând ε  ω  := ω − Πˆ  <lb/>Equ. (5.7) implies the following equality: <lb/>(񮽙  D <lb/>h  ε  p  )  j  + (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ε  ω  )  j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ   ?  D <lb/>h  Πˆ    x <lb/>+ <lb/>1 <lb/> |D  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω(x) − (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ    x, ∀j ∈ [1, J]. <lb/> (5.9) <lb/>According to (4.8) and the second line of (5.1), the error ε  ω  satisfies on the boundary <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (ε  ω  )  T <lb/>i  = 0 , ∀i ∈ Γ  0  , (ε  ω  )  T <lb/>i  = c  T <lb/>q  − C  q  , ∀i ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q , <lb/> (ε  ω  )  P <lb/>k  = 0 , ∀k ∈ Γ  0  , (ε  ω  )  P <lb/>k  = c  P <lb/>q  − C  q  , ∀k ∈ Γ  q  , ∀q . <lb/> (5.10) <lb/></body>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<body> Therefore, (񮽙  D <lb/> h  ε  p  ) and (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ε  ω  ) are orthogonal for the scalar product (·, ·)  D  , as recalled at <lb/>the end of Proposition 3.8. Consequently, multiplying (5.9) by |D  j  |(񮽙  D <lb/>h  ε  p  )  j  and summing for <lb/>all j ∈ [1, J], we obtain: <lb/> ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  ε  p  ||  2 <lb/> D <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈[1,J] <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ   ?  D <lb/>h  Πˆ      ?  D <lb/>h  ε  p  )  j  dx <lb/> (5.11) <lb/>+ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈[1,J] <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω(x) − (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ      ?  D <lb/>h  ε  p  )  j  dx. <lb/> In the very same way, multiplying (5.9) by |D  j  |(񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ε  ω  )  j  and summing for all j ∈ [1, J], we <lb/>obtain: <lb/> ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  ε  ω  ||  2 <lb/> D <lb/> = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈[1,J] <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ   ?  D <lb/>h  Πˆ      ?  D <lb/>h  × ε  ω  )  j  dx <lb/> (5.12) <lb/>+ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j∈[1,J] <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Dj <lb/> (񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω(x) − (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ      ?  D <lb/>h  × ε  ω  )  j  dx. <lb/> The right-hand sides of (5.11) and (5.12) may be bounded using the traditional P  1  Lagrange <lb/>interpolations of <lb/> p and <lb/> ω on a submesh of the diamond mesh, obtained by splitting each diamond <lb/>cell, along any of its diagonals, into two triangles. The details of the calculations may be found <lb/>in [15], starting with inequality (62) of that reference, and then using Lemma 5.11, where the <lb/>norm in the right-hand side of inequality (66) has to be replaced by the H  2  (Ω) norm of <lb/> p and <lb/> ω. <lb/> 5.2 Error estimates in the L  2  -norm for the pressure and the vorticity <lb/> We shall use the discrete Poincaré inequalities recalled in Proposition 3.10 to infer error estimates <lb/>for the discrete L  2  norm of the errors in the pressure and the vorticity. <lb/>On the one hand, Proposition 3.10 can be applied directly to the error ε  ω  because it verifies <lb/>(5.10), which are exactly conditions (3.16) and (3.17) that Proposition 3.10 requires. Thus, we <lb/>infer from (5.5) the following theorem <lb/> Theorem 5.7. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) that does not depend on h such that <lb/> ||ω − Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h (񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  ). <lb/>(5.13) <lb/>On the other hand, since (p − Πˆ  oes not in general verify the vanishing mean-value <lb/>condition (3.15) (because Πˆ  oesn&apos;t), we may not apply the discrete Poincaré inequality in a <lb/>straightforward way. However, defining <lb/> c  T  := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I]  |T  i  |(Πˆ   <lb/>i <lb/> |Ω| <lb/> , ( ˜ <lb/> Πˆ   î  := (Πˆ   î  − c  T  , ∀i ∈ [1, I + J  Γ  ], <lb/>(5.14) <lb/> c  P  := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈[1,K]  |P  k  |(Πˆ   <lb/>k <lb/> |Ω| <lb/> , ( ˜ <lb/> Πˆ   <lb/>  ˆ   <lb/>       k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (5.15) <lb/></body>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<body> we have that <lb/> Πp verifies the vanishing mean-value condition (3.15) and <lb/> 񮽙  D <lb/> h  ( ˜ <lb/> Πˆ   ?  D <lb/>h  (Πˆ  <lb/>because ( ˜ <lb/> Πˆ ând (Πˆ ônly differ by a constant on the primal and dual meshes, and defini-<lb/>tion (3.1) of the discrete gradient implies that this does not affect its values. Further, <lb/> ||p − Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ ||p − ˜ <lb/> Πˆ ||  T,P  + ||Πˆ    <lb/> Πˆ ||  T,P  . <lb/> (5.17) <lb/>Estimating the first term in the right-hand-side of (5.17) may be performed through the discrete <lb/>Poincaré inequality applied to (p − ˜ <lb/> Πˆ  <lb/> emma 5.8. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) that does not depend on h such that <lb/> ||p − ˜ <lb/> Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h (񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  ). <lb/>(5.18) <lb/> Proof. From Prop. 3.10, it holds that <lb/> ||p − ˜ <lb/> Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  )||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (p − ˜ <lb/> Πˆ |  D  = C(θ  *  )||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (p − Πˆ |  D <lb/> (5.19) <lb/>because of (5.16). Applying (5.5), we get (5.18). <lb/>To estimate the second term in the right-hand-side of (5.17), we first recall (5.14) and (5.15). <lb/>This leads to <lb/> ||Πˆ    <lb/> Πˆ ||  2 <lb/> T,P  = <lb/> |Ω| <lb/> 2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (c  T  )  2  + (c  P  )  2  񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.20) <lb/> Lemma 5.9. Let c  T  be defined by (5.14); then <lb/> |c  T  | ≤ |Ω|  −1/2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ti) <lb/> 񮽙  1/2 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.21) <lb/> Proof. From (5.14), we have that <lb/> |Ω|c  T  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> |T  i  |(Πˆ   î  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (Πˆ   î  − ˆ <lb/> p <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (x)dx <lb/>because <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/>î <lb/> p(x)dx = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> ˆ <lb/> p(x)dx = 0. Then, a continuous and a discrete Cauchy-Schwarz <lb/>inequality lead to (5.21) through <lb/> |Ω||c  T  | ≤ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> |T  i  |  1/2  ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  L  2  (Ti)  ≤ |Ω|  1/2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ti) <lb/> 񮽙  1/2 <lb/> . <lb/> So, what remains to evaluate is the L  2  norm of (Πˆ   î  − ˆ <lb/> p on T  i  . <lb/> Lemma 5.10. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) that does not depend on h such that <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  L  2  (Ti)  ≤ C(θ  *  )h||ˆ ||  2,Ti  . <lb/> (5.22) <lb/></body>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. First, we split the integral on the subtriangles t  i,j,k  with vertices G  i  M  j  S  k  (see Fig. 4), <lb/>where M  j  is the midpoint of the edge A  j  ⊂ ∂T  i  and S  k  one of its vertices: <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (Πˆ   î  − ˆ <lb/> p <lb/> 񮽙  2  (x)dx = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> t  i,j,k  ⊂Ti <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> t  i,j,k <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> (Πˆ   î  − ˆ <lb/> p <lb/> 񮽙  2  (x)dx. <lb/>(5.23) <lb/>Let π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p be the standard P  1  Lagrange interpolation of <lb/> p on t  i,j,k  . We have <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  2 <lb/> L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  ≤ 2||(Πˆ   î  − π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p||  2 <lb/> L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  + 2||π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p − ˆ <lb/> p||  2 <lb/> L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  . <lb/> (5.24) <lb/>It is a standard result (see Theorem 3.1.5 of [40]) that there exists a constant C, not depending <lb/>on t  i,j,k  such that <lb/> ||π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p − ˆ <lb/> p||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  ≤ Cdiam(t  i,j,k  )  2  ||ˆ ||  H  2  (t  i,j,k  )  , <lb/> (5.25) <lb/>which evaluates the second term in the right-hand side of (5.24). As far as the first term in the <lb/>right-hand side of (5.24) is concerned, since (Πˆ   î  − π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p(G  i  ) = 0, and since π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p is a P  1 <lb/> function, we have that, for all x ∈ t  i,j,k <lb/> (Πˆ   î  − π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p(x) = 񮽙π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p · (G  i  − x), <lb/> which ensures that |(Πˆ   î  − π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p(x)| ≤ diam(t  i,j,k  )||񮽙π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p|| for all x ∈ t  i,j,k  . Thus <lb/> ||π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p − (Πˆ   î  ||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  ≤ diam(t  i,j,k  )||񮽙π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  . <lb/> (5.26) <lb/>Using the triangular inequality <lb/> ||񮽙π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  ≤ ||񮽙(π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p − ˆ <lb/> p)||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  + ||񮽙ˆ ||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  ) <lb/> and using again Theorem 3.1.5 of [40], we have that there exists a constant C depending only <lb/>the regularity parameter of the subtriangulation (and thus on θ  *  ) such that <lb/> ||񮽙π  i,j,k  ˆ <lb/> p||  L  2  (t  i,j,k  )  ≤ (1 + Cdiam(t  i,j,k  ))||ˆ ||  H  2  (t  i,j,k  )  . <lb/> (5.27) <lb/>Gathering (5.23), (5.24), (5.25), (5.26) and (5.27) implies (5.22). <lb/>We are now able to estimate the second term in the right-hand side of (5.17) <lb/> Proposition 5.11. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) that does not depend on h such that <lb/> ||Πˆ    <lb/> Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h ||ˆ ||  2,Ω  . <lb/> (5.28) <lb/> Proof. Bounds (5.21) and (5.22) imply that <lb/> |c  T  | ≤ C(θ  *  )h||ˆ ||  2,Ω  . <lb/> (5.29) <lb/>Using (5.20), (5.29) and a similar bound that can be obtained in the same way for c  P  , we obtain <lb/>(5.28). <lb/>Finally, using (5.17), (5.18) and (5.28), we obtain the following theorem: <lb/> Theorem 5.12. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) that does not depend on h such that <lb/> ||p − Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h (񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  ). <lb/>(5.30) <lb/></body>

			<page>20 <lb/></page>

			<body> 5.3 Error estimate in the L  2  -norm for the velocity <lb/> Once the numerical approximation ω = (ω  T <lb/> i  , ω  P <lb/>k  )  i∈[1,I+J  Γ  ], k∈[1,K]  of the vorticity <lb/> ω is known, <lb/>we have to solve (4.15) in order to find the discrete velocity u = (u  j  )  j∈[1,J]  , with which we <lb/>define a piecewise constant function u  h  by <lb/> u  h  (x) = u  j  , ∀x ∈ D  j  , ∀j ∈ [1, J]. <lb/> In order to estimate the error between u  h  and the exact velocity <lb/> u, we first introduce an <lb/>intermediate discrete velocity <lb/> u = (˜ u  j  )  j∈[1,J]  , solution of the discrete div-curl system <lb/>  <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · ˜ <lb/> u)  i,k  = g  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × ˜ <lb/> u)  i,k  = 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> ˜ <lb/> u  j  · n  j  = σ  j  , <lb/> ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> (˜ u · τ , 1)  Γq,h  = k  q  , <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × ˜ <lb/> u)  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  P <lb/>k  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> (5.31) <lb/>where we have set <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  := <lb/>1 <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/>î <lb/> ω(x) dx ∀i ∈ [1, I] and 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  P <lb/>k  := <lb/>1 <lb/> |P  k  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> P  k <lb/> ˆ <lb/> ω(x) dx ∀k ∈ [1, K]. <lb/> Note that <lb/> u is of course never actually computed (because the exact vorticity <lb/> ω is not known), <lb/>but only serves for theoretical reasons. The following triangle inequality holds <lb/> ||u  h  − ˆ <lb/> u||  0,Ω  ≤ ||u − ˜ <lb/> u||  D  + ||˜      <lb/> u||  0,Ω  . <lb/> (5.32) <lb/>A bound of the second term in the right-hand side of (5.32) is given by [25, Th. 5.22]: <lb/> Proposition 5.13. If all diamond-cells are convex and under Hypotheses 2.1 and 5.4, there <lb/>exists a constant C(θ  *  ) independent of h such that <lb/> ||˜      <lb/> u||  0,Ω  ≤ C(θ  *  )h <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ||g||  0,Ω  + ||ˆ ||  0,Ω  + ||  <lb/> φ||  2,Ω  + ||  <lb/> ψ||  2,Ω <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.33) <lb/>The next step is the evaluation of the difference d  u  := u − ˜ <lb/> u, which, using (4.15) and (5.31), <lb/>and setting d  ω  := ω − −ˆ 񮽙, is the solution of <lb/>  <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · d  u  )  i,k  = 0, ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k ∈ [1, K], <lb/> (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  )  i,k  = (d  ω  )  T,P <lb/>i,k  , ∀i ∈ [1, I], ∀k / <lb/> ∈ Γ, <lb/> (d  u  )  j  · n  j  = 0, <lb/> ∀j ∈ Γ, <lb/> (d  u  · τ , 1)  Γq,h  = 0, <lb/> ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | (񮽙  P <lb/>h  × d  u  )  k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  | (d  ω  )  P <lb/>k  , ∀q ∈ [1, Q], <lb/> (5.34) <lb/> Proposition 5.14. There exists a constant C(θ  *  ) independent of h such that <lb/> ||u − ˜ <lb/> u||  D  ≤ C(θ  *  )||ω − −ˆ 񮽙||  T,P  . <lb/> (5.35) <lb/></body>

			<page>21 <lb/></page>

			<body> Proof. We use the discrete Hodge decomposition (see Proposition 3.8) of d  u  into 񮽙  D <lb/>h  φ  d  + <lb/> 񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ  d  . Using Proposition 4.3, we get that φ  d  vanishes. Next, performing like in the proof <lb/>of Theorem 4.1 in [35], we obtain ||d  u  ||  2 <lb/> D  = (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  , ψ  d  )  T,P  . By definition of the scalar <lb/>product (3.6), and using the second line in (5.34), it holds that <lb/>(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  , ψ  d  )  T,P  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> i∈[1,I] <lb/> |T  i  |(d  ω  )  T <lb/>i  (ψ  d  )  T <lb/>i  + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k / <lb/> ∈Γ <lb/> |P  k  |(d  ω  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k <lb/> + <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γ0 <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> q∈[1,Q] <lb/> 1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  . <lb/> (5.36) <lb/>Using boundary condition (3.16) for ψ  d  , we obtain <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γ0 <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  = 0 = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γ0 <lb/> |P  k  |(d  ω  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  . <lb/> (5.37) <lb/>Moreover, using boundary condition (3.17) and the last line in (5.34), we obtain <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  |(񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k∈Γq <lb/> |P  k  |(d  ω  )  P <lb/>k  (ψ  d  )  P <lb/>k  . <lb/> (5.38) <lb/>Thus, gathering (5.36), (5.37), (5.38), and recalling that ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ  d  ||  2 <lb/> D  = ||d  u  ||  2 <lb/> D  = (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × <lb/> d  u  , ψ  d  )  T,P  , we get <lb/> ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  × ψ  d  ||  2  = (񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × d  u  , ψ  d  )  T,P  = (d  ω  , ψ  d  )  T,P  . <lb/> (5.39) <lb/>Using (5.39), the Cauchy-Schwarz inequality (d  ω  , ψ  d  )  T,P  ≤ ||d  ω  ||  T,P  ||ψ  d  ||  T,P  and the discrete <lb/>Poincaré inequality (3.22) for ψ  d  , allow us to conclude. <lb/>Next, it remains to estimate d  ω  . We first link ||ω − −ˆ 񮽙||  T,P  to a previous result by the <lb/>triangle inequality <lb/> ||ω − −ˆ 񮽙||  T,P  ≤ ||ω − Πˆ ||  T,P  + ||񮽙ˆ 񮽙 − Πˆ ||  T,P  . <lb/> (5.40) <lb/>The first term in the right-hand side of (5.40) is bounded by (5.13). Bounding the second term <lb/>requires some more analysis. <lb/> Proposition 5.15. Under hypotheses 2.1 and 5.2, there exists a constant C(θ  *  ) independent <lb/>of h such that <lb/> ||񮽙ˆ 񮽙 − Πˆ ||  T,P  ≤ C(θ  *  ) h 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  . <lb/> (5.41) <lb/> Proof. First, we have <lb/> ||񮽙ˆ 񮽙 − Πˆ ||  2 <lb/> T,P  = <lb/>1 <lb/>2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> i <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  − (Πˆ   <lb/>i <lb/> 񮽙  2  + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> k <lb/> |P  k  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  P <lb/>k  − (Πˆ   <lb/>k <lb/> 񮽙  2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.42) <lb/>Let us consider the first sum in the right-hand side of (5.42); the second sum will be treated <lb/>in the same way, with however an important modification that will be underlined within the <lb/>developments that follow. <lb/></body>

			<page>22 <lb/></page>

			<body> Since 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/> i  − (Πˆ   î  is a constant on T  i  , we have <lb/> |T  i  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  − (Πˆ   <lb/>i <lb/> 񮽙  2  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ti <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  − (Πˆ   <lb/>i <lb/> 񮽙  2  dx <lb/> ≤ 2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  ||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ti)  + ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ti) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.43) <lb/>Using arguments similar to those that led to (5.22), we have that <lb/> ||ˆ   ˆ   î  ||  L  2  (Ti)  ≤ Ch||ˆ ||  2,Ti  . <lb/> (5.44) <lb/>Since T  i  is an open bounded set which is star-shaped with respect to G  i  , there exists a constant <lb/> C(T  i  ) only depending on the shape of T  i  , but not on its diameter such that <lb/> 񮽙ˆ   ˆ 񮽙  T <lb/>i  񮽙  L  2  (Ti)  ≤ C(T  i  )diam(T  i  )񮽙񮽙ˆ 񮽙  L  2  (Ti)  . <lb/> (5.45) <lb/>Since T  i  is convex, a universal constant C(T  i  ) is given by  1 <lb/> π  , see [41]. Since any dual cell P  k  is <lb/>star-shaped with respect to S  k  , a similar inequality holds: <lb/> 񮽙ˆ   ˆ 񮽙  P <lb/>k  񮽙  L  2  (P  k  )  ≤ C(P  k  )diam(P  k  )񮽙񮽙ˆ 񮽙  L  2  (P  k  )  . <lb/> (5.46) <lb/>However, since P  k  is not necessarily convex, the estimation of C(P  k  ) is less obvious, but we <lb/>may use explicitly computable formulas given, for example, by [42, 43]. These formulas show <lb/>that C(P  k  ) only depend on the angles of the subtriangulation mentioned in Hyp. 2.1. Gathering <lb/>(5.43), (5.44) and (5.45), and similar inequalities on the dual cells P  k  , the upper bound (5.41) <lb/>is obtained from (5.42). <lb/>Now, we are able to estimate the first term in the right-hand side of (5.32). With (5.40), <lb/>(5.13) and (5.41), we obtain from (5.35) the following proposition: <lb/> Proposition 5.16. Under hypotheses 2.1 and 5.2, there exists a constant C(θ  *  ) independent <lb/>of h such that <lb/> ||u − ˜ <lb/> u||  D  ≤ C(θ  *  )h (񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  ) . <lb/> (5.47) <lb/>Finally, plugging (5.47) and (5.33) into (5.32) leads to the following theorem <lb/> Theorem 5.17. If all diamond cells are convex and under hypotheses 2.1, 5.2 and 5.4, there <lb/>exists a constant C(θ  *  ) independent of h such that <lb/> ||u  h  − ˆ <lb/> u||  0,Ω  ≤ C(θ  *  )h <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + 񮽙ˆ 񮽙  2,Ω  + ||g||  0,Ω  + ||  <lb/> φ||  2,Ω  + ||  <lb/> ψ||  2,Ω <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (5.48) <lb/> Remark 5.18. The convergence results obtained in this section are valid on any mesh; however, <lb/>on some type of meshes, it is possible to prove some superconverge results. They will not be proved <lb/>here, but it may be shown that if  <lb/> ω and  <lb/> p given by Proposition 5.1 belong to H  3  (Ω), then, on <lb/>families of meshes such that there exists a finite number L of sub-domains (Ω  񮽙  )  񮽙∈[1,L]  included in <lb/> Ω and independent of the mesh step h, such that the diamond-cells which are not parallelograms <lb/>are included in strips δ  񮽙  , having width Ch and located along the boundaries of the various Ω  񮽙  , <lb/>where C is a constant independent of h, then ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (p−Πˆ |  D  and ||񮽙  D <lb/>h  (ω−Πˆ |  D  both converge <lb/></body>

			<page> 23 <lb/></page>

			<body> to 0 with the order h  3/2  , and, using the discrete Poincaré inequality, so do ||p − Πˆ |  T,P  and <lb/> ||ω − Πˆ |  T,P  . <lb/>Families of uniformly refined meshes of rectangles, or any (possibly non-conforming) union <lb/>of such meshes verify such an hypothesis; see for example on Fig. 7 the second family of meshes <lb/>used in section 6. In that case, each mesh of rectangles is an Ω  񮽙  . Another example of such <lb/>families of meshes is what is called &quot; homothetically refined triangular meshes &quot; , obtained from a <lb/>coarse triangular mesh by iteratively refining each triangle into four homothetic sub-triangles by <lb/>joining the midpoints of its edges. In that case, each triangle of the coarse mesh is an Ω  񮽙  . <lb/> 6 Numerical results <lb/> In this section, we first test the finite volume method applied to the vorticity-velocity-pressure <lb/>formulation against known analytical solutions and plot convergence curves (in log-log scale) for <lb/>several quantities; then we consider the Bercovier-Engelman [44] as well as the Ruas [45] test <lb/>case. <lb/> 6.1 Convergence curves <lb/> First, the data are chosen so that the exact solution is <lb/>ˆ <lb/> u = (exp(x) cos(πy), x sin(πy) + cos(πx)) <lb/> T <lb/> and <lb/> p = xy exp(x) cos(πy). <lb/>(6.1) <lb/>The boundary conditions are those given by (4.1). <lb/>Three families of increasingly fine meshes are used. The first is a family of standard triangular <lb/>meshes, used on the non-simply connected domain Ω =] − 1/2; 1/2[  2  \] − 1/6; 1/6[  2  , see Fig. 6. <lb/>The second and third families are nonconforming meshes used on the domain Ω =] − 1/2; 1/2[  2  . <lb/>The second family has very localized non-conformities, see Fig. 7, and is obtained in the following <lb/>way: the first mesh is obtained by dividing the domain into 8 × 8 identical squares, and the 4 <lb/>squares at the center of the mesh are further refined into 4×4 sub-squares. Then, the subsequent <lb/>meshes are obtained by dividing each cell of the previous mesh into 2 × 2 square cells. The third <lb/>family has non-conformities spread over the entire domain, see Fig. 8, since every other cell is <lb/>refined into 4 × 4 sub-cells. Of course, the third family of meshes is not of practical use but <lb/>illustrates well the ability of the scheme to deal with heavily non-conforming meshes. <lb/>We have proved (see Sections 5.1 and 5.2) that p, ω, as well as their gradients converge to the <lb/>exact solution of the Stokes problem. We are thus interested here in the numerical convergence <lb/>of p, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p, ω and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω, which we measure by the following errors <lb/>(e0p)(h) := <lb/> ||p − Πˆ ||  T,P <lb/> ||Πˆ ||  T,P <lb/> and (e1p)  2  (h) := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j  |D  j  | |(񮽙  D <lb/>h  p)  j  − (Π񮽙ˆ      <lb/> ? <lb/> j  |D  j  | |(Π񮽙ˆ      <lb/> here ∀j ∈ [1, J], (Π񮽙ˆ     ?ˆ     here B  j  is the center of gravity of the diamond cell <lb/> D  j  . The same definitions hold for ω by replacing p by ω in the previous formulae. From the <lb/>numerical results given in [15], we may expect second-order accuracy for p and ω (although <lb/>we were able to prove only first-order accuracy in section 5), and first-order accuracy for 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p <lb/> and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω on general meshes. However, on meshes with diamond-cells which are almost all <lb/></body>

			<page>24 <lb/></page>

			<body> parallelograms, which is the case for the second family of meshes, we expect a convergence order <lb/>of 1.5 for 񮽙  D <lb/> h  p and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω. <lb/> We also proved the convergence of the velocity field u to the exact solution. The discrete <lb/>relative L  2  error on the diamond cells for the velocity is measured by: <lb/> e  2  (h) := <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j  |D  j  | |u  j  − (Πˆû)  j  |  2 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> j  |D  j  | |(Πˆû)  j  |  2  , <lb/> where (Πˆû)  j  is the value of the exact solution <lb/> u at the midpoint M  j  of the edge A  j  : <lb/> ∀j ∈ [1, J], (Πˆû)  j  = ˆ <lb/> u(M  j  ). <lb/>We expect first-order convergence of the velocity field on general meshes like those of the first and <lb/>third families. On the second family of meshes, since almost all diamond cells are parallelograms, <lb/>we may expect from the numerical results of [25] an order of convergence of at least 1.5. In <lb/>Finite Element methods, one is also usually concerned with the convergence of 񮽙u, since u <lb/> belongs to H  1  (Ω) and since the term <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Ω <lb/> 񮽙u : 񮽙vdx appears in the bilinear form associated <lb/>with the variational formulation of the Stokes problem. In our formulation, the natural norm <lb/>induced by the variational formulation is <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> || · u||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ω)  + || × u||  2 <lb/> L  2  (Ω) <lb/> 񮽙  1/2 <lb/> . Since 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> · u is <lb/>always exactly imposed through the first equation of (4.15) or (4.16), we measure the errors on <lb/>the derivatives of u through the error on ω = 񮽙  T,P <lb/>h <lb/> × u. <lb/>6.1.1 Triangular meshes <lb/> We first consider standard triangular meshes, as shown in Fig. 6. On this type of meshes, 񮽙  D <lb/>h  p <lb/> and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω are all first-order accurate, while p, ω and u are second-order accurate, as displayed in <lb/>Fig. 6. Apart from u which displays superconverge, these are the expected orders of convergence. <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> h <lb/>e1p(h) <lb/>e0p(h) <lb/>e(h) <lb/>e1ω(h) <lb/>e0ω(h) <lb/>slope=2 <lb/>slope=1 <lb/> Figure 6: Left: Triangular mesh. Right: Errors. <lb/></body>

			<page>25 <lb/></page>

			<body> 6.1.2 Locally refined meshes <lb/> On the second family of meshes (see Fig. 7), we observe a super-convergence of order 1.5 of 񮽙  D <lb/> h  p <lb/> and 񮽙  D <lb/>h  ω, as expected. Moreover, as far as u is concerned, we observe in practice an order of <lb/>convergence which is better than expected since it is slightly lower than 2. On the third family <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> h <lb/>e1p(h) <lb/>e0p(h) <lb/>e(h) <lb/>e1ω(h) <lb/>e0ω(h) <lb/>slope=2 <lb/>slope=1.5 <lb/> Figure 7: Left: Non-conforming mesh. Right: Errors. <lb/>of meshes, see Fig. 8, we recover the same orders of convergence as those obtained on triangular <lb/>meshes, except for u which has only first-order convergence. <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −6 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −5 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −4 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −3 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −2 <lb/> 10 <lb/> −1 <lb/> 10 <lb/> 0 <lb/> h <lb/>e1p(h) <lb/>e0p(h) <lb/>e(h) <lb/>e1ω(h) <lb/>e0ω(h) <lb/>slope=2 <lb/>slope=1 <lb/> Figure 8: Left: Non-conforming mesh. Right: Errors. <lb/> 6.2 The Bercovier-Engelman test case <lb/> The domain of computation is the unit square and the boundary conditions are u · n = 0 on the <lb/>whole boundary and ω = 256y  2  (y − 1)  2  for x = 0 or x = 1 and ω = 256x  2  (x − 1)  2  for y = 0 or <lb/></body>

			<page>26 <lb/></page>

			<body> y = 1, while f = (f  1  , f  2  )  T  with <lb/> f  1  (x, y) = 256 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> x  2  (x − 1)  2  (12y − 6) + y(y − 1)(2y − 1)(12x  2  − 12x + 2) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> + (y − 1/2) <lb/> f  2  (x, y) = −f  1  (y, x) <lb/> The exact solution is ω = 256 <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> y  2  (y − 1)  2  (6x  2  − 6x + 1) + x  2  (x − 1)  2  (6y  2  − 6y + 1) <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> , p = (x − <lb/> 1/2)(y − 1/2) and u = (u  1  , u  2  )  T  with <lb/> u  1  (x, y) = −256y(y − 1)(2y − 1)x  2  (x − 1)  2 <lb/> u  2  (x, y) = −u  1  (y, x). <lb/> This test case is interesting because in the source term f , the component related to 񮽙 × ω is <lb/>much larger in magnitude as that related to 񮽙p, and thus one may wish to know if a numerical <lb/>scheme is able to calculate the pressure field correctly. This is indeed the case as may be seen <lb/>from the results displayed on Figure 9 which were computed on a triangular mesh with around <lb/>63000 triangles. <lb/>Figure 9: Bercovier-Engelman test. Left: pressure contours (expected extrema : −1/4 and 1/4, <lb/>computed extrema: −0.24989 and 0.25003). Center: velocity field. Right: vorticity contours <lb/>(expected extrema : −16 and 16, computed extrema: −16.001 and 16). <lb/> 6.3 The Ruas test-case <lb/> The domain of computation is the unit circle, we use u · n = 0 on the boundary, where we <lb/>also prescribe the value of the exact vorticity <lb/> ω = 32 − 16(x  2  + y  2  ). Setting f = 񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω and <lb/> g = 0 yields that <lb/> p = 0. This test is interesting because a numerical method will compute a <lb/>discrete pressure which will be, in general, different from 0, and thus one wishes to know the <lb/>magnitude of this spurious pressure. However, in the DDFV framework, we wish to emphasize <lb/>that there is a way of prescribing the right-hand side f  j  on each diamond-cell D  j  in the discrete <lb/>Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition (Step 1 of our procedure) such that the discrete values p and <lb/> ω computed by our scheme are exactly equal to 0 and Πˆ  espectively. Indeed, instead of using <lb/></body>

			<page>27 <lb/></page>

			<body> (4.10), we define f  D <lb/> j  by its scalar products with n  j  and n  񮽙 <lb/> j  in the following way <lb/> f  D <lb/>j  · n  j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |A  j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> f · n  j  dσ and f  D <lb/>j  · n  񮽙 <lb/> j  = <lb/>1 <lb/> |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  | <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/>񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j1 <lb/> f · n  񮽙 <lb/> j1  dσ + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j2 <lb/> f · n  񮽙 <lb/> j2  dσ <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> . <lb/> (6.2) <lb/>Then since <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> f · n  j  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> (񮽙 × ˆ <lb/> ω) · n  j  = <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> Aj <lb/> (񮽙ˆ       <lb/> ω(S  k1  ) − ˆ <lb/> ω(S  k2  ) = |A  j  |(񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ       <lb/>ând, in the same way <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j1 <lb/> f · n  񮽙 <lb/> j1  dσ + <lb/> 񮽙 <lb/> A  񮽙 <lb/> j2 <lb/> f · n  񮽙 <lb/> j2  dσ = (ˆ ω(M  j  ) − ˆ <lb/> ω(G  i1  )) + (ˆ ω(G  i2  ) − ˆ <lb/> ω(M  j  )) <lb/>= ˆ <lb/> ω(G  i2  ) − ˆ <lb/> ω(G  i1  ) = |A  񮽙 <lb/> j  |(񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ       ? <lb/> j  , <lb/> we have that f  j  = (񮽙  D <lb/>h  × Πˆ    or all j; then it follows from the uniqueness of the discrete <lb/>Helmholtz-Hodge decomposition of the discrete f that ω  i,k  = (Πˆ  î,k  and p  T,P <lb/>i,k  = 0. Of course, <lb/>defining f  D <lb/>j  by (6.2) requires the calculations of the 1D integrals along the edges; this may be <lb/>performed by numerical quadrature, up to a user-defined precision. In the Ruas test case, since <lb/> f is a P  1  function, the midpoint rule is enough to calculate the integrals exactly. We checked <lb/>that the computed vorticity is exactly equal to Πˆ ând that the computed pressure vanishes, up <lb/>to the linear solver precision. The vorticity and the velocity fields are displayed on Figure 10. <lb/>Figure 10: Ruas test. Left: velocity field. Right: vorticity contours. <lb/> 7 Conclusion <lb/> We have proposed a discrete duality finite volume method for the two-dimensional Stokes equa-<lb/>tions with the non-standard boundary conditions (4.1) to (4.4). These non-standard boundary <lb/></body>

			<page>28 <lb/></page>

			<body> conditions are treated through the vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation of the Stokes equa-<lb/>tions, for which the finite volume method was successfully applied over unstructured and non-<lb/>conforming meshes. Numerical results show a first-order convergence for the velocity, the pres-<lb/>sure gradient and the vorticity gradient and a second order convergence for the pressure and <lb/>the vorticity, while a superconvergence order of 1.5 for the pressure gradient and the vortic-<lb/>ity gradient and an order two for the velocity are obtained on regular (but possibly locally <lb/>non-conforming) meshes. Some of these convergence orders were proved through the theoreti-<lb/>cal analysis we led in this paper, while only suboptimal orders were obtained for pressure and <lb/>vorticity on general meshes and for velocity on regular meshes. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl> References <lb/> [1] F. Dubois, M. Salaün, and S. Salmon, Vorticity-velocity-pressure and stream function-<lb/>vorticity formulations for the Stokes problem, J Math Pures Appl 82 (2003), 1395–1451. <lb/>[2] C. B` egue, C. Conca, F. Murat, and O. Pironneau, &quot; Les equations de Stokes et de Navier-<lb/>Stokes avec des conditions aux limites sur la pression, &quot; In Nonlinear Partial Differential <lb/>Equations and their Applications, Coì ege de France Seminar Vol. IX, 1988, p. 179–264. <lb/>[3] V. Girault, Incompressible Finite Element Methods for Navier-Stokes Equations with Non-<lb/>standard Boundary Conditions in R  3  , Math Comput 183 (1988), 55–74. <lb/>[4] M. Amara, D. Capatina-Papaghiuc, E. Chacón-Vera, and D. Trujillo, Vorticity-velocity-<lb/>pressure formulation for Navier-Stokes equations, Comput Vis Sci 6 (2004), 47–52. <lb/>[5] M. Amara, E. Chacón-Vera, and D. Trujillo, Vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation for the <lb/>Stokes equations, Math Comput 73 (2004), 1673–1697. <lb/>[6] M. Aza¨ ez, C. Bernardi, and N. Chorfi, Spectral discretization of the vorticity, velocity and <lb/>pressure formulation of the Navier-Stokes equations, Numer Math 104 (2006), 1–26. <lb/>[7] F. Dubois, Vorticity-velocity-pressure formulation for the Stokes problem, Math Meth Appl <lb/>Sci 25 (2002), 1091–1191. <lb/>[8] F. Dubois, M. Salaün, and S. Salmon, First vorticity-velocity-pressure numerical scheme <lb/>for the Stokes problem, Comput Meth Appl Mech Eng 192 (2003), 4877–4907. <lb/>[9] H. Abboud, F. El Chami, and T. Sayah, A priori and a posteriori estimates for three-<lb/>dimensional Stokes equations with nonstandard boundary conditions, Numer Methods Par-<lb/>tial Differ Equations 28 (2012), 1178–1193. <lb/>[10] C. Bernardi and N. Chorfi, Spectral discretization of the vorticity, velocity and pressure <lb/>formulation of the Stokes equations, SIAM J Numer Anal 44 (2006), 826–850. <lb/>[11] M.M.J. Proot and M.I. Gerrtisma, Least-Squares spectral elements applied to the Stokes <lb/>problem, J Comput Phys 181 (2002), 454–477. <lb/>[12] F.H. Harlow and F.E. Welch, Numerical calculations of time dependent viscous incompress-<lb/>ible flow of fluids with a free surface, Phys Fluids 8 (1965), 2182–2189. <lb/>

			<page>29 <lb/></page>

			[13] R.A. Nicolaides, T.A. Porshing, and C.A. Hall, &quot; Covolume methods, &quot; In computational <lb/>fluid dynamics review, M. Hafez and K. Oshma (Editors), John Wiley and sons, 1995, p. <lb/>279–299. <lb/>[14] S. Delcourte, K. Domelevo, and P. Omnes, &quot; Discrete duality finite volume method for sec-<lb/>ond order elliptic problems, &quot; In Finite Volumes for Complex Applications IV, F. Benkhal-<lb/>doun, D. Ouazar and S. Raghay (Editors), Hermes Science publishing, 2005, p. 447–458. <lb/>[15] K. Domelevo and P. Omnes, A finite volume method for the Laplace equation on almost <lb/>arbitrary two-dimensional grids, Math Model Numer Anal 39 (2005), 1203–1249. <lb/>[16] F. Hermeline, A finite volume method for the approximation of diffusion operators on <lb/>distorted meshes, J Comput Phys 160 (2000), 481–499. <lb/>[17] F. Hermeline, Approximation of diffusion operators with discontinuous tensor coefficients <lb/>on distorted meshes, Comput Methods Appl Mech Eng 192 (2003), 1939–1959. <lb/>[18] B. Andreianov, F. Boyer, and F. Hubert, Discrete duality finite volume schemes for Leray-<lb/>Lions-type elliptic problems on general 2D meshes, Numer Methods Partial Differ Equations <lb/>23 (2007), 145–195. <lb/>[19] F. Boyer and F. Hubert, Finite volume method for 2D linear and nonlinear elliptic problems <lb/>with discontinuities, SIAM J Numer Anal 46 (2008), 3032–3070. <lb/>[20] Y. Couì ere and F. Hubert, A 3D discrete duality finite volume method for nonlinear elliptic <lb/>equations, SIAM J Sci Comput 33 (2011), 1739–1764. <lb/>[21] Y. Couì ere and G. Manzini, The discrete duality finite volume method for convection-<lb/>diffusion problems, SIAM J Numer Anal 47 (2010), 4163–4192. <lb/>[22] B. Andreianov, M. Bendahmane, K. H. Karlsen, and C. Pierre, Convergence of discrete <lb/>duality finite volume schemes for the cardiac bidomain model, Networks and Heterogeneous <lb/>Media 6 (2011), 195–240. <lb/>[23] Y. Couì ere, C. Pierre, O. Rousseau, and R. Turpault, A 2D/3D Discrete Duality Finite <lb/>Volume Scheme. Application to ECG simulation, Int J Finite Volumes 6 (2009), electronic <lb/>only. <lb/>[24] C. Chainais-Hillairet, Discrete duality finite volume schemes for two-dimensional drift-<lb/>diffusion and energy-transport models, Internat J Numer Methods Fluids 59 (2009), 239– <lb/>257. <lb/>[25] S. Delcourte, K. Domelevo, and P. Omnes, A discrete duality finite volume approach to <lb/>Hodge decomposition and div-curl problems on almost arbitrary two-dimensional meshes, <lb/>SIAM J Numer Anal 45 (2007), 1142–1174. <lb/>[26] F. Hermeline, S. Layouni, and P. Omnes, A finite volume method for the approximation <lb/>of Maxwell&apos;s equations in two space dimensions on arbitrary meshes, J Comput Phys 227 <lb/>(2008), 9365–9388. <lb/>

			<page>30 <lb/></page>

			[27] S. Delcourte, Développement de méthodes de volumes finis pour la mécanique des flu-<lb/>ides, Ph.D. Thesis (in French), University of Toulouse III, France, 2007. Available at <lb/>http://tel.archives-ouvertes.fr/tel-00200833/fr/ <lb/>[28] S. Krell, Stabilized DDFV Schemes for Stokes Problem with Variable Viscosity on General <lb/>2D Meshes, Numer Methods Partial Differential Eq (2011), 1666–1706. <lb/>[29] S. Krell, Finite volume method for general multifluid flows governed by the interface Stokes <lb/>problem, Math Models Methods Appl Sci 22 (2012), 1150025, 35 p. <lb/>[30] S. Krell and G. Manzini, The discrete duality finite volume method for Stokes equations <lb/>on three-dimensional polyhedral meshes, SIAM J Numer Anal 50 (2012), 808–837. <lb/>[31] P. Blanc, R. Eymard, and R. Herbin, A staggered finite volume scheme on general meshes <lb/>for the generalized Stokes problem in two space dimensions, Int J Finite Volumes 2 (2005), <lb/>electronic only. <lb/>[32] R. Eymard and R. Herbin, A staggered finite volume scheme on general meshes for the <lb/>Navier-Stokes equations in two space dimensions, Int J Finite Volumes 2 (2005), electronic <lb/>only. <lb/>[33] R. Eymard, J.C. Latché, and R. Herbin, On a stabilized collocated finite volume scheme <lb/>for the Stokes problem. Math Model Numer Anal 40 (2006), 501–527. <lb/>[34] R. Eymard, J.C. Latché, and R. Herbin, Convergence analysis of a colocated finite volume <lb/>scheme for the incompressible Navier-Stokes equations on general 2 or 3D meshes, SIAM J <lb/>Numer Anal 45 (2007), 1–36. <lb/>[35] A.H. Le and P. Omnes, Discrete Poincaré inequalities for arbitrary meshes in the discrete <lb/>duality finite volume context, ETNA, Electronic Transactions on Numerical Analysis 40 <lb/>(2013), 94–119. <lb/>[36] S. Heib, Nouvelles discrétisations non structurées pour des ecoulements de fluides a incom-<lb/>pressibilité renforcée (in French), Ph.D. Thesis, Université Pierre et Marie Curie, Paris, <lb/>France, 2002. <lb/>[37] C. Bernardi and F. Hecht, More pressure in the finite element discretization of the Stokes <lb/>Problem, Math Model Numer Anal 34 (2000), 953–980. <lb/>[38] M. Crouzeix and P.-A. Raviart, Conforming and nonconforming finite element methods for <lb/>solving the stationary Stokes equations, RAIRO Anal Numer 7 (1973), 33–76. <lb/>[39] V. Girault and P.-A. Raviart, Finite Element Methods for Navier-Stokes Equations, <lb/>Springer-Verlag, Berlin, 1986. <lb/>[40] P.G. Ciarlet, The finite element method for elliptic problems, North Holland publishing <lb/>company, 1978. <lb/>[41] L.E. Payne, and H.F. Weinberger, An optimal Poincaré inequality for convex domain. Arch <lb/>Rational Mech Anal 5 (1960), 286–292. <lb/>

			<page>31 <lb/></page>

			[42] C. Carstensen and S. Funken, Constants in Clément-interpolation error and residual based a <lb/> posteriori estimates in finite element methods, East-West J Numer Math 8 (2000), 153–175. <lb/>[43] R. Verfürth, Error estimates for some quasi-interpolation operators, Math Model Numer <lb/>Anal 33 (1999), 695–713. <lb/>[44] M. Bercovier and M. Engelman, A finite element for the numerical solution of viscous <lb/>incompressible flows, J Comput Phys 30 (1979), 181–201. <lb/>[45] V. Ruas, Méthodes vitesse-tourbillon pour les equations de Navier-Stokes, in: Actes du <lb/>29 eme congr es d&apos;Analyse Numérique, Canum&apos;97 (1997), 329–330. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>32 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
