<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="_sxd0004-0213"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front> Fax +41 61 306 12 34 <lb/>E-Mail karger@karger.ch <lb/>www.karger.com <lb/> 
			
			Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/>DOI: 10.1159/000314917 <lb/> 
			
			New Technologies for the Identification <lb/>of Novel Genetic Markers of Disorders of <lb/>Sex Development (DSD) <lb/> A. Bashamboo  a S. Ledig  b P. Wieacker  b J. Achermann  c K. McElreavey  a <lb/> a <lb/> Human Developmental Genetics Unit, Institut Pasteur, Paris , France; b <lb/> Institute of Human Genetics, <lb/>Westfalian-Wilhelms University Münster, Münster , Germany; c <lb/> The Developmental Endocrinology Research Group, <lb/>Clinical and Molecular Genetics Unit, UCL Institute of Child Health, London , UK <lb/></front> 
			
			<body>The term &apos;disorders of sex development&apos; (DSD) has <lb/>been defined as &apos;congenital conditions in which the de-<lb/>velopment of chromosomal, gonadal, or anatomical sex is <lb/>atypical&apos; [Hughes et al., 2006]. DSD covers a wide spec-<lb/>trum of phenotypes. 46,XY DSD includes 46,XY com-<lb/>plete or partial gonadal dysgenesis, or undervirilisation <lb/>or undermasculinisation of an XY male due to defects in <lb/>androgen synthesis or action. 46,XX DSD includes go-<lb/>nadal dysgenesis, or more commonly overvirilisation or <lb/>masculinisation of an XX female due to androgen excess. <lb/>Ovotesticular DSD refers to an individual with both <lb/>ovarian and testicular material present in the same or dif-<lb/>ferent gonads, and 46,XX testicular DSD refers to an XX <lb/>male with testes. Other forms of DSD include cloacal ex-<lb/>trophy, severe hypospadias, vaginal atresia, and as part <lb/>of other conditions such as Mayer-Rokitansky-Kuster-<lb/>Hauser syndrome, Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome or geni-<lb/>to-palato-cardiac syndrome [Porter, 2008; Sultan et al., <lb/>2009]. Although there have been considerable advances <lb/>in our understanding of the genetic factors involved in <lb/>gonadal differentiation in the last 20 years ( fig. 1 ), it has <lb/>been estimated that a molecular diagnosis is made in only <lb/>around 20% of DSD, except in cases where the biochemi-<lb/>cal profile indicates a specific steroidogenic block [Hughes <lb/>et al., 2006]. <lb/> </body>
			
			<front>Key Words <lb/> Comparative genomic hybridization 񮽙 Disorders of sex <lb/>development 񮽙 High-throughput sequencing 񮽙 <lb/> Next generation sequencing <lb/> 
			
			Abstract <lb/> Although the genetic basis of human sexual determination <lb/>and differentiation has advanced considerably in recent <lb/>years, the fact remains that in most subjects with disorders <lb/>of sex development (DSD) the underlying genetic cause is <lb/>unknown. Where pathogenic mutations have been identi-<lb/>fied, the phenotype can be highly variable, even within fam-<lb/>ilies, suggesting that other genetic variants are influencing <lb/>the expression of the phenotype. This situation is likely to <lb/>change, as more powerful and affordable tools become <lb/>widely available for detailed genetic analyses. Here, we de-<lb/>scribe recent advances in comparative genomic hybridisa-<lb/>tion, sequencing by hybridisation and next generation se-<lb/>quencing, and we describe how these technologies will have <lb/>an impact on our understanding of the genetic causes of <lb/>DSD. <lb/> 
			
			Copyright © 2010 S. Karger AG, Basel <lb/>Published online: July 3, 2010 <lb/> Dr. Ken McElreavey <lb/>Human Developmental Genetics, Institut Pasteur <lb/>25, rue du Dr Roux <lb/>FR–75724 Paris Cedex 15 (France) <lb/>Tel. +33 145 688 920, Fax +33 145 688 639, E-Mail kenneth.mcelreavey  @  pasteur.fr <lb/>© 2010 S. Karger AG, Basel <lb/>Accessible online at: <lb/>www.karger.com/sxd <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/>Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>214 <lb/></page> 
			
			<body>Identification of Novel Genetic Factors by <lb/>Comparative Genomic Hybridisation <lb/> Comparative genomic hybridisation (CGH) was first <lb/>described in 1992 as an approach to interrogate cancer <lb/>genomic DNA using metaphase chromosomes as probes <lb/>[Kallioniemi et al., 1992]. The strategy of the technique <lb/>was to differentially label the DNA isolated from a test <lb/>and reference cell population with different fluoro-<lb/>chromes and to cohybridise the labelled samples to a <lb/>metaphase spread from a reference cell. The relative hy-<lb/>bridisation intensity of the test and reference signals at a <lb/>given location is then proportional to the relative copy <lb/>number of those sequences in the test and reference ge-<lb/>nomes. If the reference genome is normal, then increases <lb/>and decreases in the intensity ratio directly indicate DNA <lb/>copy number variation in the genome of the test cells. The <lb/>ratio of the intensities of the 2 fluorochromes reflects the <lb/>copy number differences between the cells of interest and <lb/>the control cells. <lb/>The major technical challenge of array CGH is the <lb/>generation of hybridisation signals that are sufficiently <lb/>intense, specific and quantitative so that copy number <lb/>changes can be accurately and reliably detected. In the <lb/>late 1990s, array CGH was first developed by spotting <lb/>DNA from large-insert clones such as BACs (bacterial <lb/>artificial chromosomes) and cDNAs onto microarray <lb/>slides [Solinas-Toldo et al., 1997; Pinkel et al., 1998]. Ar-<lb/>ray elements made from genomic BAC clones (complex-<lb/>ity 100–200 kb) typically provide more intense signals <lb/>than do elements with shorter sequences such as oligo-<lb/>nucleotides, so could be analysed by early detection sys-<lb/>tems. However, the advantage of smaller array elements, <lb/>such as oligonucleotides is the much higher genomic res-<lb/> Genital ridge <lb/> WT1, NR5A1 <lb/> GATA4, FOG2, WT1 <lb/> PBX1, EMX2, <lb/>CBX2, LHX9 <lb/> SRY <lb/> WNT4 <lb/>RSPO1 <lb/> 񮽙-catenin <lb/> SOX9 <lb/> FOXL2 <lb/>FOXL2 <lb/> SOX9 <lb/>SOX9 <lb/>AMH <lb/> NR5A1 <lb/>NR5A1,GATA4 <lb/>WT1, SOX8 <lb/>FGF9, <lb/>PTGDS <lb/> FOXL2 <lb/> SOX9 <lb/> DHH <lb/> Leydig cell <lb/> NR5A1 <lb/> Steroidogenesis <lb/> DMRT1? <lb/> NR5A1 <lb/>NR5A1 <lb/> Steroidogenesis <lb/> Time <lb/>Foetal <lb/>Adult <lb/>s <lb/>i <lb/>t <lb/>s <lb/>e <lb/>T <lb/>y <lb/>r <lb/>a <lb/>v <lb/>O <lb/> Fig. 1.  The molecular and genetic events in mammalian sex deter-<lb/>mination and differentiation. The bipotential genital ridge is es-<lb/>tablished by several genes including NR5A1 [Wilhelm et al., 2007; <lb/>Sekido and Lovell-Badge, 2009]. In the XY gonad the activation of <lb/> SRY expression, possibly initiated by GATA4/FOG2/NR5A1/ <lb/>WT1, leads to the upregulation of SOX9 expression via a synergy <lb/>with NR5A1 [Sekido and Lovell-Badge 2008, 2009]. In the XX go-<lb/>nad, the supporting cell precursors accumulate 񮽙 -catenin in re-<lb/>sponse to RSPO1/WNT4 signalling and repress SOX9 activity <lb/>[Schlessinger et al., 2010]. Once SOX9 levels reach a critical thresh-<lb/>old, several positive regulatory loops are initiated, including au-<lb/>toregulation of its own expression and formation of feed-forward <lb/>loops via FGF9 or PGD2 signalling [Sekido and Lovell-Badge, <lb/>2009]. At later stages, FOXL2 may repress Sox9 expression [Uhlen-<lb/>haut et al., 2009]. In the testis, SOX9 promotes the testis pathway, <lb/>including Amh activation, and it also probably represses the ovar-<lb/>ian genes Wnt4 and Foxl2 [Sekido and Lovell-Badge, 2009; Uhlen-<lb/>haut et al., 2009; Schlessinger et al., 2010]. DMRT1 controls sex <lb/>determination in some species of fish and may be the master sex-<lb/>determining switch in birds, but its role in mammalian sexual <lb/>development is unclear [Wilhelm et al., 2007; Smith et al., 2009]. <lb/>Much of this data has been generated from studies in mice. <lb/>
			
			<note place="footnote">New Technologies for DSD <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>215 <lb/></page> 
			
			olution (often ! 100) if measurement precision can be <lb/>maintained. The most recent advancement in CGH mi-<lb/>croarrays has been the use of oligonucleotide sequences <lb/>as probes [Lucito et al., 2003] ( fig. 2 ) and the development <lb/>of genotyping arrays from low-resolution SNP (single <lb/>nucleotide polymorphism) arrays to high-resolution hy-<lb/>brid arrays that integrate both SNP and CNV (copy <lb/>number variation) probes [Bignell et al., 2004]. Now <lb/>many different oligoarray platforms are available for <lb/>CGH analyses from various companies including Nim-<lb/>blegen (www.nimblegen.com) and Agilent (www.agi-<lb/>lent.com) with ever increasing levels of resolution. In ad-<lb/>dition, several recent Next Generation Sequencing (NGS) <lb/>approaches also provide information on structural vari-<lb/>ation (see below). <lb/>The recent impact of these technologies on medical <lb/>genetics has been substantial [Zhang et al., 2009]. These <lb/>advances include the detection of subtle changes in chro-<lb/>mosome architecture associated with cancers [Berou-<lb/>khim et al., 2010], severe developmental delay [Girirajan <lb/>et al., 2010], epilepsy [de Kovel et al., 2010], and schizo-<lb/>phrenia [Glessner and Hakonarson, 2009]. Like many de-<lb/>velopmental processes, human sex development is sensi-<lb/>tive to gene dosage effects, and duplication and deletion <lb/>events in the human genome are associated with DSD. <lb/>For example, deletions of terminal 9p24 are associated <lb/>with varying degrees of 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis in <lb/>around 70% of XY individuals with this chromosomal <lb/>change [Barbaro et al., 2009]. A number of reports have <lb/>described deletions of terminal 10q associated with 46,XY <lb/>gonadal dysgenesis together with somatic anomalies. The <lb/>gene responsible for the gonadal phenotype remains un-<lb/>identified although EMX2 has been suggested as a likely <lb/>candidate [Ogata et al., 2000]. Deletions and duplications <lb/>of chromosome 22q11.2 have been described in 3 cases of <lb/>46,XX SRY -negative testicular DSD [Aleck et al., 1999; <lb/>Erickson et al., 2003; Seeherunvong et al., 2004]. A micro-<lb/>duplication of chromosome 17q, including the SOX9 gene <lb/>has been reported in a 46,XX man with ambiguous exter-<lb/>nal genitalia and otherwise unremarkable phenotype <lb/>[Huang et al., 1999]. Deletion of the dosage sensitive gene <lb/> NR0B1 , encoding DAX1 on chromosome Xp21.2 results <lb/>in congenital adrenal hypoplasia (AHC), whereas an <lb/> NR0B1 duplication in 46,XY individuals leads to gonadal <lb/>dysgenesis and a female phenotype [Bardoni et al., 1994]. <lb/>Duplications of NR0B1 gene have been described in a <lb/>small number of other cases of 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis. <lb/>Duplication of 1p has also been associated with 46,XY <lb/>gonadal dysgenesis although the gene(s) responsible is <lb/>not known [Wieacker and Volleth, 2007]. <lb/>CGH analysis is beginning to reveal novel rearrange-<lb/>ments associated with 46,XY and 46,XX DSD. This ap-<lb/>proach has been used to physically map translocation <lb/>breakpoints in a case of 46,XX ovotesticular DSD asso-<lb/>ciated with a 12;17 translocation upstream of the SOX9 <lb/> gene [Refai et al., 2010]. An inherited 960 kb deletion, <lb/>positioned 517 kb to 1.477 Mb upstream of the SOX9 <lb/> gene, was detected by oligoarray CGH in a XY DSD <lb/>child with acampomelic dysplasia and in her affected <lb/>mother [Lecointre et al., 2009]. In both these examples, <lb/>the rearrangements may have lead to the deregulation of <lb/> SOX9 expression. A large 3 Mb deletion of 9q34 that in-<lb/>cludes the LMX1B and NR5A1 genes was identified us-<lb/>ing an array CGH approach in a 46,XY girl with clinical <lb/>features of genitopatellar syndrome and ovotesticular <lb/>DSD [Schlaubitz et al., 2007]. More recently a smaller <lb/>970 kb deletion that included the NR5A1 gene (encoding <lb/>steroidogenic factor-1) was also detected in a 46,XY <lb/>DSD girl without skeletal features [van Silfhout et al., <lb/>2009]. CGH analysis has also been used to define dele-<lb/>tions on 11p13 and 9p24 associated with syndromic <lb/>forms of 46,XY DSD [Le Caignec et al., 2007; Vinci et <lb/>al., 2007]. <lb/>CGH has successfully identified duplications of NR0B1 <lb/> associated with 46,XY complete gonadal dysgenesis in <lb/>the absence of somatic anomalies [Barbaro et al., 2007] <lb/>and a unique 257 kb deletion located 250 kb upstream of <lb/> NR0B1 in a 21-year-old girl with 46,XY complete gonad-<lb/>al dysgenesis [Smyk et al., 2007]. This deletion presum-<lb/>ably results in deregulation of NR0B1 expression. <lb/>Aside from the detection of subtle rearrangements of <lb/>genetic factors known to be involved in gonadal determi-<lb/>nation and differentiation, CGH analyses offer the pos-<lb/>sibility to detect new genes involved in these processes. <lb/>CGH analyses revealed a novel recurrent 15q24 microde-<lb/>letion syndrome (1.7–3.9 Mb in size) that is characterised <lb/>by growth retardation, microcephaly, digital abnormali-<lb/>ties, characteristic facial dysmorphia (high anterior hair <lb/>line, broad medial eyebrows, hypertelorism, downslant-<lb/>ed palpebral fissures, broad nasal base, long smooth <lb/>philtrum and full lower lip), and genital anomalies in <lb/>the male (micropenis/hypospadias) [Sharp et al., 2007; <lb/>Andrieux et al., 2009]. <lb/>As increasing numbers of subjects with DSD are un-<lb/>dergoing analysis using CGH platforms, more pathogen-<lb/>ic rearrangements will be reported that may reveal unique <lb/>insights into the mechanism of gonadal somatic cell fate <lb/>determination and development. <lb/> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/>Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>216 <lb/></page> 
			
			SRY <lb/> RPS4Y <lb/>ZFY <lb/> Pseudoautosomal <lb/>region <lb/>Centromere <lb/>XY female <lb/>NV <lb/>0 10 20 30 40 50 60 70 80 90 100 110 120 130 140 150 160 170 180 <lb/>kb <lb/>Probes: <lb/>pY53.3 <lb/>pY53.3 <lb/>pDP 1225 <lb/>p09 <lb/>pYR04 PCR <lb/>amplification <lb/>pDP 1226 <lb/>pDP 1007 <lb/> HindIII <lb/> HindIII <lb/>Stu I <lb/> Stu I <lb/> Stu I <lb/> Taq I <lb/>–2.1 <lb/>–9 <lb/>–5.5 <lb/>–1.5 <lb/>–0.12 <lb/>–10 <lb/>–8 <lb/>–12 <lb/>–7.5 <lb/>–2.3 <lb/>–1.9 <lb/>–6 <lb/>–3 <lb/>Father <lb/> Father <lb/> Father <lb/> NV <lb/> NV <lb/> NV <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control female <lb/> Father <lb/> Father <lb/> Father <lb/> Father <lb/> NV <lb/> NV <lb/> NV <lb/> NV <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control female <lb/> Control female <lb/> Control female <lb/> Control female <lb/> H20 <lb/> Control male <lb/> Control female <lb/> 1.131 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>–0.800 <lb/>–1.600 <lb/>–2.266 <lb/>3.807 <lb/>1.800 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>–1.800 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>–6.300 <lb/>–12.000 <lb/>–4.817 <lb/>9.000 <lb/>chrY <lb/> 4529402_0300bp <lb/>4529402_normalized <lb/>primary_transcript <lb/> 2 ,5 <lb/> 2 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,5 <lb/> 4 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,5 <lb/> 6 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,5 <lb/> 8 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,6 <lb/> 0 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,6 <lb/> 2 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,6 <lb/> 4 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,6 <lb/> 6 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,6 <lb/> 8 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,7 <lb/> 0 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,7 <lb/> 2 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,7 <lb/> 4 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> 2 ,7 <lb/> 6 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 2 ,7 <lb/> 8 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 2 ,8 <lb/> 0 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 2 ,8 <lb/> 2 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 2 ,8 <lb/> 4 0 ,0 <lb/> 0 0 <lb/> A <lb/> B <lb/> Fig. 2.  CGH analysis of a de novo Y chromosome deletion associ-<lb/>ated with 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis.  A  This case was first pub-<lb/>lished almost 20 years ago and the deletion was detected and the <lb/>extent of the deletion mapped by Southern blotting [McElreavy et <lb/>al., 1992b].  B  The same deletion identified by CGH analysis using <lb/>a Y chromosome-specific platform (www.nimblegen.com). The <lb/>genome profile of the patient versus normal male reference ge-<lb/>nomic DNA is shown for the short arm of the Y chromosome. The <lb/>x-axis coordinates indicate the relative position of the oligo probes <lb/>ordered by genomic map position on the Y chromosome. The y-<lb/>axis shows the log2 ratio shift. The top panel shows window aver-<lb/>aging of signals in 300 bp segments. The middle panel shows the <lb/>normalized signal profile using qspline normalisation. The lower <lb/>panel indicates the genomic position of transcripts on this region <lb/>of chromosome Yp. <lb/>
			
			<note place="footnote">New Technologies for DSD <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>217 <lb/></page> 
			
			Identification of Novel Genetic Factors Associated <lb/>with DSD by Custom Array Sequencing <lb/> Diagnostic sequencing of genes known to be respon-<lb/>sible for DSD using conventional Sanger sequencing is <lb/>useful to identify novel mutations associated with gonad <lb/>development and it is the mainstay of most diagnostic <lb/>laboratories. However, this approach is both time-con-<lb/>suming and laborious. High-throughput, high-density <lb/>sequencing using microarray technology offers the pos-<lb/>sibility of rapidly and accurately sequencing portions of <lb/>the genome at reduced costs. Several next-generation se-<lb/>quencing technologies are emerging (see below) for whole <lb/>genome analyses but at present the costs and considerable <lb/>data handling that are involved means that these ap-<lb/>proaches will be limited to the research environment for <lb/>the foreseeable future. In contrast, sequencing by hybri-<lb/>disation is suitable for situations in which a moderate <lb/>amount of sequence is being analysed (10–300 kb, repre-<lb/>senting several to tens of genes) in a repetitive manner. <lb/>The principle of oligo-hybridisation sequencing is <lb/>based on the differential hybridisation of target DNA to <lb/>an array of oligonucleotide probes, thereby decoding its <lb/>primary DNA sequence. This is most applicable to disor-<lb/>der-specific studies such as DSD where sequences can be <lb/>compared with an established reference. CustomSeq ar-<lb/>rays developed by Affymetrix rely on allele-specific hy-<lb/>bridisation for determining the DNA sequence of interest <lb/>and a single array can be used to sequence up to 300 kb <lb/>of double-stranded unique DNA sequence. Every base to <lb/>be sequenced is represented by probes that are 25 bp long <lb/>and differ only at a single central position [Lipshutz et al., <lb/>1999]. The array uses 4 oligomers per base for each of the <lb/>2 DNA strands. The 4 oligomers differ at a single central <lb/>position that could be A, C, G, or T, and they query com-<lb/>plementary bases on the DNA strand. The remaining 24 <lb/>positions are the same for all 4 oligomers and are comple-<lb/>mentary to the reference DNA sequence being queried. <lb/>Sufficient DNA must be generated for hybridisation to <lb/>the microarray. Current protocols for target-enriched pa-<lb/>tient material use locus-specific long-range PCR amplifi-<lb/>cation of regions of interest. Long-range PCR minimises <lb/>the number of reactions required, but genes at multiple <lb/>loci, with highly dispersed exons, will require many PCR <lb/>reactions. Long-range PCR products also usually require <lb/>quantification and normalisation prior to hybridisation <lb/>( fig. 3 ). The PCR products are then pooled and fragment-<lb/>ed. The DNA fragments are labelled with biotin and sub-<lb/>sequently hybridised with the microarray. Finally, the <lb/>microarray is washed, stained and scanned to measure <lb/>the fluorescence intensities ( fig. 3 ). Software, such as the <lb/>GeneChip Sequence Analysis Software (GSEQ; www. <lb/>affymetrix.com) allows the user to perform sequence <lb/>analysis of the data to produce the final sequence calls. <lb/>Although relatively cheap, sequencing by hybridisa-<lb/>tion does have the major drawback of false positive calls. <lb/>These can arise through various mechanisms such as <lb/>PCR failure or SNP interference. The latter occurs when <lb/>2 variants are very close together on the same patient <lb/>DNA fragment. If there is a homozygous variant, the per-<lb/>formance of neighbouring probes, which assume a wild-<lb/>type base at the variant position, can be poor. Therefore, <lb/>clusters of SNP calls (i.e. SNPs within 9 bases of each oth-<lb/>er) should be interpreted with caution. Cross-hybridisa-<lb/>tion is a cause of false positives, so a single array cannot <lb/>analyse homologous loci. Repetitive sequences can also <lb/>generate false positive data, although algorithms have <lb/>been developed to improve base call reading. <lb/>The elimination of false positive calls is essential to <lb/>reduce the need to perform confirmatory capillary rese-<lb/>quencing. Computational algorithms can be developed <lb/>for specific arrays so that for the detection of rare muta-<lb/>tions in clinical disease settings such as DSD, the use of <lb/>an algorithm that compares a single patient data set to <lb/> Genomic DNA <lb/>Long-range PCR <lb/>DNA fragmentation <lb/>End label fragments <lb/>Hybridisation to custom array <lb/>Scan microarray <lb/> Fig. 3.  Schematic overview of procedure involved in sequencing <lb/>by hybridisation. <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/>Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note>

			<page> 218 <lb/></page>

			data from a group of controls is likely to improve call rates <lb/>and false positive rates through a statistical comparison <lb/>of signal strength for each probe. Algorithms may also <lb/>help to solve another problem confronted by array se-<lb/>quencing technologies, the detection of novel insertion or <lb/>deletion mutations. However, monoallelic deletions that <lb/>are larger than a PCR amplicon could be missed due to <lb/>the normalisation of PCR products prior to hybridisa-<lb/>tion. <lb/>Despite these disadvantages, custom sequencing ar-<lb/>rays offer a high-throughput sequencing method that is <lb/>efficient, fast, automatable, and cost-effective for repeti-<lb/>tive resequencing of targeted regions of DNA. Relatively <lb/>few examples of this approach have been reported in the <lb/>literature to date. A microarray-based sequencing plat-<lb/>form technology to detect sequence alterations in multi-<lb/>ple autosomal recessive retinal disease genes was report-<lb/>ed with a 99% accuracy and reproducibility [Mandal et <lb/>al., 2005]. A 16 gene sequencing array has recently been <lb/>described for studying genetic variation in genes involved <lb/>in angiogenesis that had a 99.4% sequencing accuracy <lb/>compared with Sanger capillary sequencing [Szoke et al., <lb/>2009]. Similarly, a comparison of 93 worldwide mito-<lb/>chondrial genomes sequenced using either the Affyme-<lb/>trix GeneChip Human Mitochondrial Resequencing Ar-<lb/>ray 2.0 (MitoChip v.2.0) or Sanger sequencing an average <lb/>call rate of 99.48% and an accuracy of 99.98% for the Mi-<lb/>toChip [Hartmann et al., 2009]. The failure to detect <lb/>some variants was largely due to the inherent difficulty of <lb/>the array to detect insertions and deletions. <lb/> Identification of Novel Genetic Factors by Next <lb/>Generation Sequencing <lb/> The advent of next generation sequencing (NGS) tech-<lb/>nologies has tremendously reduced the sequencing cost <lb/>and experimental complexity. NGS technologies also of-<lb/>fer improved template coverage, rendering sequencing-<lb/>based genome analysis more readily available and useful <lb/>to individual laboratories. These sequencing methods <lb/>employ massively parallel approaches to sequence several <lb/>hundred thousand to millions of reads simultaneously <lb/>[Ansorge, 2009; Metzker, 2010]. <lb/>The current approaches to NGS falls broadly into 2 <lb/>types – polymerase based and ligase based [Ansorge, <lb/>2009; Metzker, 2010]. The recent use of ligases for mas-<lb/>sively parallel short-read DNA sequencing of human ge-<lb/>nomes offers several unique attributes compared to poly-<lb/>merases [Valouev et al., 2008]. In the context of mutation <lb/>detection, the most important difference is the use of an <lb/>error-correcting probe-labelling scheme (two-base en-<lb/>coding, or 2BE), which provides error correction concur-<lb/>rent with the color-called alignment of the data (i.e. with-<lb/>out having to resequence the reads). There are currently <lb/>4 commercially available new-generation sequencing <lb/>technologies. These are the polymerase based systems of <lb/>Roche/454, Illumina/Solexa, Helicos HeliScope and the <lb/>ligase-based Applied Biosystems SOLiD [Margulies et al., <lb/>2005; Bentley et al., 2008; Harris et al., 2008; Valouev et <lb/>al., 2008]. All of these systems produce an abundance of <lb/>short reads at a much higher throughput than is achiev-<lb/> Table 1.  Next generation sequencing approaches <lb/> Platform <lb/>Sequencing <lb/>chemistry <lb/>Read length <lb/>(bases) <lb/>Gb per <lb/>run <lb/>Run time (frag-<lb/>ment library) <lb/>System raw <lb/>accuracy <lb/>Consensus base <lb/>accuracy <lb/>Disadvantages <lb/> Roche/454 GS <lb/>FLX titanium <lb/>Polymerase 400 <lb/>0.4–0.6 10 h <lb/>99% to <lb/>400 bases <lb/>99.99% at <lb/>15! coverage <lb/>Prone to sequence error in <lb/>homopolymer DNA sequences <lb/>Cost per run expensive. <lb/>Illumina/ <lb/>Solexa GAII <lb/>Polymerase 75–100 20 a <lb/> 4 days <lb/>98–99% <lb/>&gt;99.999% at <lb/>20! coverage <lb/>Low multiplexing capabilities <lb/>Life Technologies, <lb/>ABI SOLiD 3+ <lb/>Ligase <lb/>50 <lb/>60 b <lb/> 12 days <lb/>99.94% <lb/>&gt;99.999% at <lb/>15! coverage <lb/>Duration of run <lb/>Helicos <lb/>Biosciences, <lb/>Heliscope <lb/>Polymerase 32 <lb/>21 <lb/>8 days <lb/>93–97% <lb/>99.995% at <lb/>20! coverage <lb/>Higher error rates <lb/> a Paired end sequences. The new Illumina/Solexa HiSeq 2000 generates up to 200 Gb per run. b The recent SOLiD TM 4 System gen-<lb/>erates over 100 gigabases. <lb/>
			
			<note place="footnote">New Technologies for DSD <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>219 <lb/></page> 
			
			able with the state-of-the-art Sanger sequencer and <lb/>each have their own unique properties ( table 1 ; see also <lb/>http://www.wellcome.ac.uk/Education-resources/Teach-<lb/>ing-and-education/Animations/DNA/index.htm). Other <lb/>NGS approaches are on the horizon. These include nano-<lb/>pore sequencing, where individual nucleic acid strands in <lb/>solution are electrophoretically driven through nano-<lb/>pore-based devices. The narrow pore can ensure that the <lb/>sequence of nucleic acids can be analysed in their native <lb/>order without the need for prior amplification or label-<lb/>ling, therefore resulting in increased accuracy and re-<lb/>duced sequencing costs [Branton et al., 2008]. <lb/>In NGS, the sequencing is only a part of the entire pro-<lb/>cess that includes template preparation, the sequencing <lb/>reaction itself and the data handling and analyses [Med-<lb/>vedev et al., 2009; McPherson, 2009; Metzker, 2010]. The <lb/>latter may in fact be more expensive than the costs in-<lb/>volved in generating the billions of base pairs of sequence. <lb/>Considerable challenges remain in terms of data transfer, <lb/>storage and quality control. Specialised computational <lb/>analysis and skill are required to align or assemble read <lb/>data, along with laboratory information management <lb/>systems for sample tracking and process management <lb/>[McPherson, 2009]. <lb/>DNA template for NGS is achieved either by solution-<lb/>based hybridisation strategies or by solid phase amplifi-<lb/>cation [Vogelstein, 2003; Fedurco et al., 2006]. In emul-<lb/>sion PCR (emPCR), a library of targets is created, and <lb/>adaptors containing universal priming sites are ligated to <lb/>the target ends, allowing complex genomes to be ampli-<lb/>fied with common PCR primers. After ligation, the DNA <lb/>is separated into single strands and captured onto beads <lb/>under conditions that favour one DNA molecule per <lb/>bead. After the successful amplification and enrichment <lb/>of emPCR beads, millions can be immobilised in a poly-<lb/>acrylamide gel on a standard microscope slide, chemi-<lb/>cally crosslinked to an aminocoated glass surface, or <lb/>deposited into individual PicoTiterPlate (PTP) wells <lb/>(Roche/454) in which the NGS chemistry can be per-<lb/>formed [Leamon, 2003; Metzker, 2010]. <lb/>Solid-phase amplification can also be used to pro-<lb/>duce randomly distributed, clonally amplified clusters <lb/>from fragment or mate-pair templates on a glass slide. <lb/>High-density forward and reverse primers are covalent-<lb/>ly attached to the slide, and the ratio of the primers to <lb/>the template on the support defines the surface density <lb/>of the amplified clusters. Solid-phase amplification can <lb/>produce 100–200 million spatially separated template <lb/>clusters (Illumina/Solexa), providing free ends to which <lb/>a universal sequencing primer can be hybridised to ini-<lb/>tiate the NGS reaction. The Helicos BioSciences, Heli-<lb/>Scope system is also based on polymerase sequencing-<lb/>by-synthesis of single molecules in which labelled DNA <lb/>bases are sequentially added to the nucleic acid tem-<lb/>plates captured on a flow cell (http://www.helicosbio. <lb/>com). No prior amplification process is involved in this <lb/>system resulting in a non-bias representation of tem-<lb/>plates for genome sequencing, although the error rate <lb/>may be higher than other polymerase-based systems <lb/>[Harris et al., 2008]. <lb/>The Roche 454 system uses pyrosequencing technol-<lb/>ogies to enable the simultaneous sequencing of several <lb/>hundred thousand DNA fragments, with a read of 400 <lb/>bp (www.454.com). Pyrosequencing is a biolumines-<lb/>cence method that measures the release of inorganic py-<lb/>rophosphate into a synthesised DNA strand by convert-<lb/>ing it into visible light by a series of enzymatic reactions <lb/>[Ronaghi et al., 1996]. The order and intensity of the <lb/>generated light is detected and recorded in the form of <lb/>a peak signal, which reveals the underlying DNA se-<lb/>quence. The Illumina (Solexa) Genome Analyzer (GA) <lb/>uses sequencing-by-synthesis to generate 񮽙 200 million <lb/>75–100-bp reads (http://www.illumina.com/systems/ <lb/>genome_analyzer.ilmn). This is a cyclic method that <lb/>comprises nucleotide incorporation, fluorescence imag-<lb/>ing and cleavage. In the first step, a DNA polymerase, <lb/>bound to the primed template, adds or incorporates just <lb/>one fluorescently modified nucleotide, which represents <lb/>the complement of the template base. The termination <lb/>of DNA synthesis after the addition of a single nucleo-<lb/>tide is an important feature of this approach. Following <lb/>incorporation, the remaining unincorporated nucleo-<lb/>tides are washed away. Imaging is then performed to <lb/>determine the identity of the incorporated nucleotide. <lb/>This is followed by a cleavage step, which removes the <lb/>terminating/inhibiting group and the fluorescent dye. <lb/>Additional washing is performed before starting the <lb/>next incorporation. <lb/>A novel massively parallel sequencing technology <lb/>based on ligation of oligonucleotides as opposed to se-<lb/>quencing by synthesis has been developed by Applied <lb/>Biosystems (http://solid.appliedbiosystems.com). In this <lb/>approach, sequencing is carried out via sequential rounds <lb/>of probe annealing and ligation with high fidelity and <lb/>high read quality ( fig. 4 ). Sequence errors are consider-<lb/>ably reduced compared to polymerase-based systems be-<lb/>cause the ligation method is based on probe recognition <lb/>rather than sequential nucleotide addition. In this sys-<lb/>tem, there are 16 dinucleotide combinations with 4 fluo-<lb/>rescent dyes, each dye corresponding to a probe pool of 4 <lb/>

			<note place="footnote"> Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/>Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note>

			<page> 220 <lb/></page>

			dinucleotides per pool ( fig. 4 ). Using this dinucleotide, <lb/>4-dye encoding scheme in conjunction with a sequencing <lb/>assay that samples every base, each base is effectively <lb/>probed by 2 different and independent reactions. The <lb/>double interrogation of each base causes a true SNP poly-<lb/>morphism to result in a 2 consecutive colour change <lb/>while a measurement error results in a single colour <lb/>change. The SOLiD TM (Sequencing by Oligo Ligation and <lb/>Detection) platform is capable now of producing 400 mil-<lb/>lion 50-bp reads (combined total in 2 independent flow <lb/>cells). This approach essentially eliminates the possibility <lb/>of spurious insertions or deletions. <lb/>Recently, the SOLiD system has been used to assay nu-<lb/>cleotide variation in HapMap samples, in the framework <lb/>of the 1000 Genomes Project [McKernan et al., 2009]. The <lb/>1000 Genomes Project is a collaboration among research <lb/>groups in the US, UK, China, and Germany to produce <lb/>an extensive catalogue of human genetic variation that <lb/>will support future medical research studies (www. <lb/>1000genomes.org). It will extend the data from the Inter-<lb/>national HapMap Project and will allow genome-wide as-<lb/>sociation studies to focus on almost all variants that exist <lb/>in regions found to be associated with disease. The ge-<lb/>nomes of over 1,000 unidentified individuals from around <lb/>the world will be sequenced using next generation se-<lb/>quencing technologies. Three HapMap samples were se-<lb/>quenced via the ligation-based approach utilised in the <lb/>SOLiD sequencing system [McKernan et al., 2009]. In one <lb/>sample with a sequence coverage estimated at 29 ! , 97% <lb/>of heterozygotes SNPs and 99.96% of homozygotes SNPs <lb/>were detected and false discovery rate was negligible <lb/>[McKernan et al., 2009]. <lb/>This approach is particularly useful for variation dis-<lb/>covery in genetic association studies, where low se-<lb/>quence coverage (5 ! ) and therefore lower cost, may de-<lb/>tect a significant portion of the total sequence variation. <lb/>To detect pathogenic mutations associated with disease <lb/>a higher coverage is needed. What is the required accu-<lb/>racy for mutation discovery? A single base pair change <lb/>may result in a DSD phenotype and any error in se-<lb/>quencing can give rise to false positives or false nega-<lb/>tives, leading to time-consuming and challenging <lb/>downstream studies. The raw sequencing accuracy is <lb/>the accuracy of a single-pass sequencing read. This is an <lb/>excellent measurement of each method&apos;s chemistry, flu-<lb/>orescence readout, process, and base-calling software <lb/> Ligase <lb/> Primer <lb/> Adapter sequence <lb/> Template <lb/> 5&apos; <lb/>3&apos; <lb/> Bead <lb/> Primer <lb/> Adapter sequence <lb/> Template <lb/> 5&apos; <lb/>3&apos; <lb/> Bead <lb/> Primer <lb/> Adapter sequence <lb/> Template <lb/> 5&apos; <lb/>3&apos; <lb/> Bead <lb/> 3&apos; <lb/> * <lb/> 3&apos; <lb/> * <lb/> 3&apos; <lb/> * <lb/> 3&apos; <lb/> * <lb/> Cleavage <lb/> G A <lb/> * <lb/> C-T-n-n-n <lb/>G A <lb/> * <lb/> P 5&apos; <lb/> P 5&apos; <lb/> Cleavage <lb/> Ligate <lb/> G-A-n-n-n <lb/>A-G-n-n-n <lb/>C-C-n-n-n <lb/>C-T-n-n-n <lb/>C-T-n-n-n <lb/> Fig. 4.  Schematic representation of <lb/>SOLiD TM sequencing by ligation. Primers <lb/>hybridise to the P1 adapter within the li-<lb/>brary template. A set of 4 fluorescence-la-<lb/>belled di-base probes competes for ligation <lb/>to the sequencing primer. These probes <lb/>have partly degenerated DNA sequence <lb/>(indicated by n) and for simplicity only one <lb/>probe is shown (labelling is denoted by as-<lb/>terisk). The specificity of the di-base probe <lb/>is achieved by interrogating every 1st and <lb/>2nd base in each ligation reaction. Multi-<lb/>ple cycles of ligation, detection and cleav-<lb/>age are performed with the number of cy-<lb/>cles determining the eventual read length <lb/>(modified from http://www3.appliedbio-<lb/>systems.com). <lb/>

			<note place="footnote">New Technologies for DSD <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note>

			<page> 221 <lb/></page>

			( table 1 ). Ultimately, the more robust the raw reads, the <lb/>fewer redundant reads are required, keeping the overall <lb/>costs down. At the time of writing, the SOLiD system <lb/>shows a high degree of sequence accuracy, even at low <lb/>coverage, and this may be the system of choice for muta-<lb/>tion detection. <lb/>Overall substantial cost reductions are associated <lb/>with NGS technologies when compared with the Sanger <lb/>method, but sequencing the whole human genome re-<lb/>mains expensive for most laboratories. In the search for <lb/>novel genetic markers of DSD, the medium term may see <lb/>a more targeted approach. Specific regions of the ge-<lb/>nome may be enriched for sequencing: for example, se-<lb/>quencing all of the exons in the genome; sequencing <lb/>specific gene families of interest; or focusing just on <lb/>large chromosome regions or entire chromosomes that <lb/>are implicated in disease. Exome capture approaches are <lb/>available for targeting approximately 33 Mb or 񮽙 180,000 <lb/>coding exons across the human genome. Many plat-<lb/>forms also offer capture of miRNAs and non-coding <lb/>RNA sequences. Selective genomic enrichment of the <lb/>human exome offers an attractive option for devising <lb/>new experimental designs aimed at quick identification <lb/>of potential disease-associated genetic variants. Human <lb/>exome capture methods are currently based on either <lb/>custom-designed oligonucleotide microarrays or solu-<lb/>tion-based hybridisation strategies. Roche/Nimblegen <lb/>offers microarray capture platforms for solid phase hy-<lb/>bridisation for the enrichment of exons [Albert et al., <lb/>2007]. The reported capture efficiency for these plat-<lb/>forms ranges from 50–90% [Hodges et al., 2007]. Solu-<lb/>tion-based hybridisation methods for exon capture, <lb/>such as molecular inversion probes (mIPs) [Porreca et <lb/>al., 2007; Turner et al., 2009] and biotinylated RNA cap-<lb/>ture sequences [Gnirke et al., 2009; SureSelect Human <lb/>All Exon Kit; Agilent Technologies] have also been de-<lb/>veloped that have capture efficiencies of 70–90%. Rain-<lb/>dance technologies (www.raindancetechnologies.com) <lb/>offers targeted sequence enrichment using a microflu-<lb/>idic device to create aqueous picolitre-volume droplets <lb/>of forward-and reverse-targeting primers in an oil solu-<lb/>tion [Tewhey et al., 2009]. In a microfluidic chip, the <lb/>primer pair droplets and template droplets, which con-<lb/>tain fragmented genomic DNA and PCR reagents, are <lb/>paired together in a 1: 1 ratio. An electric field induces <lb/>the 2 droplets to merge into a single PCR droplet. Around <lb/>1.5 million PCR droplets can be collected in a single <lb/>PCR tube. This approach has been reported to have an <lb/>84% capture efficiency with 90% of the targeted bases <lb/>showing uniform coverage when sequenced with either <lb/>the Roche/454 or Illumina/Solexa platform [Tewhey et <lb/>al., 2009]. From a medical perspective, this approach is <lb/>interesting since it is particularly suitable for working <lb/>with cells of limited availability, such as stem cells or <lb/>primary cells from patients [Brouzes et al., 2009]. <lb/>NGS with exome capture has recently been applied to <lb/>identify mutations associated with mendelian disorders <lb/>[Ng et al., 2009, 2010]. Using Freeman-Sheldon syndrome <lb/>(FSS) as a proof-of-concept, Ng and colleagues performed <lb/>exome enrichment and sequencing using the Illumina <lb/>system to identify the causal mutation for FSS. The same <lb/>group has recently identified mutations in the DHODH <lb/> gene in 4 individuals from 3 pedigrees with Miller syn-<lb/>drome (postaxial acrofacial dysostosis) using exome se-<lb/>quence capture and sequencing to a coverage of 40 ! with <lb/>sufficient depth to call variants at approximately 97% of <lb/>each targeted exome. <lb/>In addition, the recent NGS applications not only <lb/>have the ability to generate huge amounts of sequence <lb/>data but they also reveal structural variation, thereby <lb/>bypassing the need for CGH analyses [McKernan et al., <lb/>2009]. <lb/>These recent studies show the power of NGS approach-<lb/>es to detect pathogenic mutations causing disease. This <lb/>approach also offers the opportunity to identify genetic <lb/>modifiers. Familial cases of both 46,XY and 46,XX DSD <lb/>often show considerable variation in the expression of the <lb/>phenotype, including families where the underlying ge-<lb/>netic mutation has been identified [Lourenco et al., 2009; <lb/>Temel et al., 2007]. This phenotypic variability may be <lb/>explained by variations in other genes that may interact <lb/>with or influence the activity of the target gene. This has <lb/>been shown in a pedigree with hypogonadotropic hypo-<lb/>gonadism, where a compound heterozygous GNRHR and <lb/>a heterozygous FGFR1 mutation were identified [Pittel-<lb/>oud et al., 2007]. <lb/>When considering these NGS approaches that are <lb/>currently costly and require considerable bioinformatics <lb/>analyses, an important question to pose is what would be <lb/>the cost benefits to the DSD field? The usefulness of this <lb/>non-a priori approach to identify genetic modifiers has <lb/>been mentioned above, but are there new genetic factors <lb/>that when mutated could cause DSD? The reply to this <lb/>question is yes. For example, almost all cases of non-syn-<lb/>dromic ovotesticular DSD remain unexplained although <lb/>there have been considerable genetic analyses of candi-<lb/>date genes [McElreavey et al., 1992a; Temel et al., 2007]. <lb/>Despite advances in understanding the mechanisms of <lb/>mammalian gonad formation, the underlying genetic <lb/>cause of most cases of 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis remains <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote"> Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/>Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note>

			<page> 222 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>References <lb/> Albert TJ, Molla MN, Muzny DM, Nazareth L, <lb/>Wheeler D, et al: Direct selection of human <lb/>genomic loci by microarray hybridization. <lb/>Nat Methods 4: 903–905 (2007). <lb/>Aleck KA, Argueso L, Stone J, Hackel JG, Erick-<lb/>son RP: True hermaphroditism with partial <lb/>duplication of chromosome 22 and without <lb/> SRY . Am J Med Genet 85: 2–4 (1999). <lb/>Andrieux J, Dubourg C, Rio M, Attie-Bitach T, <lb/>Delaby E, et al: Genotype-phenotype corre-<lb/>lation in four 15q24 deleted patients identi-<lb/>fied by array-CGH. Am J Med Genet A <lb/>149A:2813–2819 (2009). <lb/>Ansorge WJ: Next-generation DNA sequencing <lb/>techniques. N Biotechnol 25: 195–203 (2009). <lb/>Audi L, Fernández-Cancio M, Carrascosa A, <lb/>Andaluz P, Torán N, et al: Novel (60%) and <lb/>recurrent (40%) androgen receptor gene mu-<lb/>tations in a series of 59 patients with a 46,XY <lb/>disorder of sex development. J Clin Endocri-<lb/>nol Metab 95: 1876–1888 (2010). <lb/>Barbaro M, Oscarson M, Schoumans J, Staaf J, <lb/>Ivarsson SA, Wedell A: Isolated 46,XY go-<lb/>nadal dysgenesis in two sisters caused by a <lb/>Xp21.2 interstitial duplication containing <lb/>the DAX1 gene. J Clin Endocrinol Metab 92: <lb/>3305–3313 (2007). <lb/>Barbaro M, Balsamo A, Anderlid BM, Myhre <lb/>AG, Gennari M, et al: Characterization of <lb/>deletions at 9p affecting the candidate re-<lb/>gions for sex reversal and deletion 9p syn-<lb/>drome by MLPA. Eur J Hum Genet 17: 1439– <lb/>1447 (2009). <lb/>Bardoni B, Zanaria E, Guioli S, Floridia G, Wor-<lb/>ley KC, et al: A dosage sensitive locus at chro-<lb/>mosome Xp21 is involved in male to female <lb/>sex reversal. Nat Genet 7: 497–501 (1994). <lb/>Bentley DR, Balasubramanian S, Swerdlow HP, <lb/>Smith GP, Milton J, et al: Accurate whole hu-<lb/>man genome sequencing using reversible <lb/>terminator chemistry. Nature 456: 53–59 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>Beroukhim R, Mermel CH, Porter D, Wei G, <lb/>Raychaudhuri S, et el: The landscape of so-<lb/>matic copy-number alteration across human <lb/>cancers. Nature 463: 899–905 (2010). <lb/>Bignell GR, Huang J, Greshock J, Watt S, Butler <lb/>A, et al: High-resolution analysis of DNA <lb/>copy number using oligonucleotide microar-<lb/>rays. Genome Res 14: 287–295 (2004). <lb/>Bogani D, Siggers P, Brixey R, Warr N, Beddow <lb/>S, et al: Loss of mitogen-activated protein ki-<lb/>nase kinase kinase 4 (MAP3K4) reveals a re-<lb/>quirement for MAPK signalling in mouse <lb/>sex determination. PLoS Biol 7:e1000196 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>Branton D, Deamer DW, Marziali A, Bayley H, <lb/>Benner SA, et al: The potential and challeng-<lb/>es of nanopore sequencing. Nat Biotechnol <lb/>26: 1146–1153 (2008). <lb/>Brouzes E, Medkova M, Savenelli N, Marran D, <lb/>Twardowski M, et al: Droplet microfluidic <lb/>technology for single-cell high-throughput <lb/>screening. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 106: <lb/>14195–14200 (2009). <lb/>de Kovel CG, Trucks H, Helbig I, Mefford HC, <lb/>Baker C, et al: Recurrent microdeletions at <lb/>15q11.2 and 16p13.11 predispose to idiopath-<lb/>ic generalized epilepsies. Brain 133: 23–32 <lb/>(2010). <lb/>Erickson RP, Skinner S, Jacquet H, Campion D, <lb/>Buckley PG, et al: Does chromosome 22 have <lb/>anything to do with sex determination: fur-<lb/>ther studies on a 46,XX,22q11.2 del male. <lb/>Am J Med Genet A 123A:64–67 (2003) <lb/>Fedurco M, Romieu A, Williams S, Lawrence I, <lb/>Turcatti G: BTA, a novel reagent for DNA at-<lb/>tachment on glass and efficient generation <lb/>of solid-phase amplified glass and efficient <lb/>generation of solid-phase amplified DNA <lb/>colonies. Nucleic Acids Res 34:e22 (2006). <lb/>Fukami M, Wada Y, Miyabayashi K, Nishino I, <lb/>Hasegawa T, et al: CXorf6 is a causative gene <lb/>for hypospadias. Nat Genet 38: 1369–1371 <lb/>(2006). <lb/>Girirajan S, Rosenfeld JA, Cooper GM, Antonac-<lb/>ci F, Siswara P, et al: A recurrent 16p12.1 mi-<lb/>crodeletion supports a two-hit model for se-<lb/>vere developmental delay. Nat Genet 42: <lb/>203–209 (2010). <lb/>Glessner JT, Hakonarson H: Common variants <lb/>in polygenic schizophrenia. Genome Biol 10: <lb/>236 (2009). <lb/>Gnirke A, Melnikov A, Maguire J, Rogov P, LeP-<lb/>roust EM, et al: Solution hybrid selection <lb/>with ultralong oligonucleotides for massive-<lb/>ly parallel targeted sequencing. Nature Bio-<lb/>tech 27: 182–189 (2009). <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<body>unknown [McElreavey and Fellous, 1999]. Mutations in <lb/>the androgen receptor (AR) gene are the most common <lb/>genetic cause of 46,XY DSD. However, even in 46,XY <lb/>underandrogenised subjects with testes who are suspect-<lb/>ed to have an AR defect, a pathogenic mutation is found <lb/>only in less than half of the cases [Audi et al., 2010]. In <lb/>cases of simple hypospadias or cryptorchidism a genetic <lb/>cause is rarely detected despite epidemiological evidence <lb/>suggesting a major genetic contribution to these pheno-<lb/>types [Fukami et al., 2006; Schnack et al., 2008; Köhler <lb/>et al., 2009]. Recently, a mutation in Map3k4 was associ-<lb/>ated with XY gonadal sex reversal in the mouse, suggest-<lb/>ing that mutations in mitogen-activated protein kinase <lb/>(MAPK) signalling pathway may be associated with <lb/>DSD [McElreavey et al., unpublished data; Bogani et al., <lb/>2009]. <lb/>It is clear that NGS will have a tremendous impact on <lb/>medicine [Voelkerding et al., 2009]. Exciting develop-<lb/>ments are rapidly taking place in the field and these are <lb/>leading to a deeper understanding of variation across in-<lb/>dividual genomes, genetic variation in tissues within an <lb/>individual and the identification of disease causing muta-<lb/>tions. Sequencing technology is continuing to evolve at <lb/>an unprecedented pace. The generation of massive data <lb/>sets of qualitative and quantitative information of both <lb/>RNA and DNA sequences in a patient sample at a rela-<lb/>tively limited cost will transform the field of reproductive <lb/>disorders by offering novel insights into the genetics and <lb/>physiology of DSD. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement"> Acknowledgements <lb/> Supported by grants from the Agence Nationale de la Recher-<lb/>che-GIS Institut des Maladies Rares (to Dr. McElreavey); by a re-<lb/>search grant (1-FY07-490) from the March of Dimes Foundation <lb/>(to Dr. McElreavey); by a research grant from the EuroDSD in <lb/>the European Community&apos;s Seventh Framework Programme <lb/>FP7/2007-2013 under grant agreement No. 201444 (Drs Acher-<lb/>mann, Wieacker, Ledig, McElreavey and Bashamboo); a Well-<lb/>come Trust Senior Research Fellowship in Clinical Science <lb/>(079666, to Dr Achermann). <lb/></div>
			
			<note place="footnote">New Technologies for DSD <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>223 <lb/></page> 
			
			<listBibl>Harris TD, Buzby PR, Babcock H, Beer E, Bowers <lb/>J, et al: Single-molecule DNA sequencing of <lb/>a viral genome. Science 320: 106–109 (2008). <lb/>Hartmann A, Thieme M, Nanduri LK, Stempfl <lb/>T, Moehle C, et al: Validation of microarray-<lb/>based resequencing of 93 worldwide mito-<lb/>chondrial genomes. Hum Mutat 30: 115–122 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>Hodges E, Xuan Z, Balija V, Kramer M, Molla <lb/>MN, et al: Genome-wide in situ exon capture <lb/>for selective resequencing. Nature Genet 39: <lb/>1522–1527 (2007). <lb/>Huang B, Wang S, Ning Y, Lamb AN, Bartley J: <lb/>Autosomal XX sex reversal caused by dupli-<lb/>cation of SOX9 . Am J Med Genet 87: 349–353 <lb/>(1999). <lb/>Hughes IA, Houk C, Ahmed SF, Lee PA; LWPES <lb/>Consensus Group; ESPE Consensus Group: <lb/>Consensus statement on management of in-<lb/>tersex disorders. Arch Dis Child 91: 554–563 <lb/>(2006). <lb/>Kallioniemi A, Kallioniemi OP, Sudar D, Ruto-<lb/>vitz D, Gray JW, et al: Comparative genomic <lb/>hybridization for molecular cytogenetic <lb/>analysis of solid tumors. Science 258: 818– <lb/>821 (1992). <lb/>Köhler B, Lin L, Mazen I, Cetindag C, Bieber-<lb/>mann H, et al: The spectrum of phenotypes <lb/>associated with mutations in steroidogenic <lb/>factor 1 (SF-1, NR5A1, Ad4BP) includes <lb/>severe penoscrotal hypospadias in 46,XY <lb/>males without adrenal insufficiency. Eur J <lb/>Endocrinol 161: 237–242 (2009). <lb/>Leamon JH: A massively parallel PicoTiterPlate <lb/>based platform for discrete picoliter-scale <lb/>polymerase chain reactions. Electrophoresis <lb/>24: 3769–3777 (2003). <lb/>Le Caignec C, Delnatte C, Vermeesch JR, Boceno <lb/>M, Joubert M, et al: Complete sex reversal in <lb/>a WAGR syndrome patient. Am J Med Genet <lb/>A 143A:2692–2695 (2007). <lb/>Lecointre C, Pichon O, Hamel A, Heloury Y, Mi-<lb/>chel-Calemard L, et al: Familial acampo-<lb/>melic form of campomelic dysplasia caused <lb/>by a 960 kb deletion upstream of SOX9 . Am <lb/>J Med Genet A 149A:1183–1189 (2009). <lb/>Lipshutz RJ, Fodor SP, Gingeras TR, Lockhart <lb/>DJ: High density synthetic oligonucleotide <lb/>arrays. Nat Genet 21 Suppl 1: 20–24 (1999). <lb/>Lourenço D, Brauner R, Lin L, De Perdigo A, <lb/>Weryha G, et al: Mutations in NR5A1 associ-<lb/>ated with ovarian insufficiency. N Engl J <lb/>Med 360: 1200–1210 (2009). <lb/>Lucito R, Healy J, Alexander J, Reiner A, Esposi-<lb/>to D, et al: Representational oligonucleotide <lb/>microarray analysis: a high-resolution meth-<lb/>od to detect genome copy number variation. <lb/>Genome Res 13: 2291–2305 (2003). <lb/>Mandal MN, Heckenlively JR, Burch T, Chen L, <lb/>Vasireddy V, et al: Sequencing arrays for <lb/>screening multiple genes associated with <lb/>early-onset human retinal degenerations on <lb/>a high-throughput platform. Invest Oph-<lb/>thalmol Vis Sci 46: 3355–3362 (2005). <lb/>Margulies M, Egholm M, Altman WE, Attiya S, <lb/>Bader JS, et al: Genome sequencing in micro-<lb/>fabricated high-density picolitre reactors. <lb/>Nature 437: 376–380 (2005). <lb/>McElreavey K, Rappaport R, Vilain E, Abbas N, <lb/>Richaud F, et al: A minority of 46,XX true <lb/>hermaphrodites are positive for the Y-DNA <lb/>sequence including SRY . Hum Genet 90: 121– <lb/>125 (1992a). <lb/>McElreavey K, Vilain E, Abbas N, Costa JM, <lb/>Souleyreau N, et al: XY sex reversal associ-<lb/>ated with a deletion 5 񮽙 to the SRY &apos;HMG box&apos; <lb/>in the testis-determining region. Proc Natl <lb/>Acad Sci USA 89: 11016–11020 (1992b). <lb/>McElreavey K, Fellous M. Sex determination and <lb/>the Y chromosome. Am J Med Genet 89: 176– <lb/>185 (1999). <lb/>McKernan KJ, Peckham HE, Costa GL, <lb/>McLaughlin SF, Fu Y, et al: Sequence and <lb/>structural variation in a human genome un-<lb/>covered by short-read, massively parallel li-<lb/>gation sequencing using two-base encoding. <lb/>Genome Res 19: 1527–1541 (2009). <lb/>McPherson JD: Next-generation gap. Nat Meth-<lb/>ods 6(suppl 11):S2–S5 (2009). <lb/>Medvedev P, Stanciu M, Brudno M: Computa-<lb/>tional methods for discovering structural <lb/>variation with next-generation sequencing. <lb/>Nat Methods 6(suppl 11):S13–S20 (2009). <lb/>Metzker ML: Sequencing technologies – the next <lb/>generation. Nat Rev Genet 11: 31–46 (2010). <lb/>Ng SB, Turner EH, Robertson PD, Flygare SD, <lb/>Bigham AW, et al: Targeted capture and mas-<lb/>sively parallel sequencing of 12 human <lb/>exomes. Nature 461: 272–276 (2009). <lb/>Ng SB, Buckingham KJ, Lee C, Bigham AW, Ta-<lb/>bor HK, et al: Exome sequencing identifies <lb/>the cause of a mendelian disorder. Nat Genet <lb/>42: 30–35 (2010). <lb/>Ogata T, Muroya K, Sasagawa I, Kosho T, Wakui <lb/>K, et al: Genetic evidence for a novel gene(s) <lb/>involved in urogenital development on <lb/>10q26. Kidney Int 58: 2281–2290 (2000). <lb/>Pinkel D, Segraves R, Sudar D, Clark S, Poole I, <lb/>et al: High resolution analysis of DNA copy <lb/>number variation using comparative ge-<lb/>nomic hybridization to microarrays. Nat <lb/>Genet 20: 207–211 (1998). <lb/>Pitteloud N, Quinton R, Pearce S, Raivio T, Aci-<lb/>erno J, et al: Digenic mutations account for <lb/>variable phenotypes in idiopathic hypogo-<lb/>nadotropic hypogonadism. J Clin Invest 117: <lb/>457–463 (2007). <lb/>Porreca GJ, Zhang K, Li JB, Xie B, Austin D, et <lb/>al: Multiplex amplification of large sets of <lb/>human exons. Nature Methods 4: 931–936 <lb/>(2007). <lb/>Porter FD: Smith-Lemli-Opitz syndrome: <lb/>pathogenesis, diagnosis and management. <lb/>Eur J Hum Genet 16: 535–541 (2008). <lb/>Refai O, Friedman A, Terry L, Jewett T, Pearlman <lb/>A, et al: De novo 12; 17 translocation up-<lb/>stream of SOX9 resulting in 46,XX testicular <lb/>disorder of sex development. Am J Med Gen-<lb/>et A 152A:422–426 (2010). <lb/>Ronaghi M, Karamohamed S, Pettersson B, <lb/>Uhlé n M, Nyré n P: Real-time DNA sequenc-<lb/>ing using detection of pyrophosphate re-<lb/>lease. Anal Biochem 242: 84–89 (1996). <lb/>Schlaubitz S, Yatsenko SA, Smith LD, Keller KL, <lb/>Vissers LE, et al: Ovotestes and XY sex rever-<lb/>sal in a female with an interstitial 9q33.3– <lb/>q34.1 deletion encompassing NR5A1 and <lb/> LMX1B causing features of Genitopatellar <lb/>syndrome. Am J Med Genet A 143A:1071– <lb/>1081 (2007). <lb/>Schlessinger D, Garcia-Ortiz JE, Forabosco A, <lb/>Uda M, Crisponi L, Pelosi E: Determination <lb/>and stability of gonadal sex. J Androl 31: 16– <lb/>25 (2010). <lb/>Schnack TH, Zdravkovic S, Myrup C, Wester-<lb/>gaard T, Christensen K, et al: Familial aggre-<lb/>gation of hypospadias: a cohort study. Am J <lb/>Epidemiol 167: 251–256 (2008). <lb/>Seeherunvong T, Perera EM, Bao Y, Benke PJ, Be-<lb/>nigno A, et al: 46,XX sex reversal with partial <lb/>duplication of chromosome arm 22q. Am J <lb/>Med Genet A 127A:149–151 (2004). <lb/>Sekido R, Lovell-Badge R: Sex determination in-<lb/>volves synergistic action of SRY and SF1 on a <lb/>specific Sox9 enhancer. Nature 453: 930–934 <lb/>(2008). <lb/>Sekido R, Lovell-Badge R: Sex determination <lb/>and SRY : down to a wink and a nudge? <lb/>Trends Genet 25: 19–29 (2009). <lb/>Sharp AJ, Selzer RR, Veltman JA, Gimelli S, Gi-<lb/>melli G, et al: Characterization of a recurrent <lb/>15q24 microdeletion syndrome. Hum Mol <lb/>Genet 16: 567–752 (2007). <lb/>Smith CA, Roeszler KN, Ohnesorg T, Cummins <lb/>DM, Farlie PG, et al: The avian Z-linked gene <lb/> DMRT1 is required for male sex determina-<lb/>tion in the chicken. Nature 461: 267–271 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>Smyk M, Berg JS, Pursley A, Curtis FK, Fernan-<lb/>dez BA, et al: Male-to-female sex reversal <lb/>associated with an approximately 250 kb <lb/>deletion upstream of NR0B1 (DAX1). Hum <lb/>Genet 122: 63–70 (2007). <lb/>Solinas-Toldo S, Lampel S, Stilgenbauer S, Nick-<lb/>olenko J, Benner A, et al: Matrix-based com-<lb/>parative genomic hybridization: biochips to <lb/>screen for genomic imbalances. Genes Chro-<lb/>mosomes Cancer 20: 399–407 (1997). <lb/>Sultan C, Biason-Lauber A, Philibert P: Mayer-<lb/>Rokitansky-Kuster-Hauser syndrome: re-<lb/>cent clinical and genetic findings. Gynecol <lb/>Endocrinol 25: 8–11 (2009). <lb/>Szoke D, Molnar B, Solymosi N, Racz K, Gergics <lb/>P, et al: Polymorphisms of the ApoE , HS-<lb/>D3B1 , IL-1beta and p53 genes are associated <lb/>with the development of early uremic com-<lb/>plications in diabetic patients: results of a <lb/>DNA resequencing array study. Int J Mol <lb/>Med 23: 217–227 (2009). <lb/>Temel SG, Gulten T, Yakut T, Saglam H, Kilic N, <lb/>et al: Extended pedigree with multiple cases <lb/>of XX sex reversal in the absence of SRY and <lb/>of a mutation at the SOX9 locus. Sex Dev 1: <lb/>24–34 (2007). <lb/> Bashamboo  /Ledig  /Wieacker  / <lb/></listBibl>
			
			<note place="footnote">Achermann  /McElreavey <lb/></note> 
			
			<note place="footnote">Sex Dev 2010;4:213–224 <lb/></note> 
			
			<page>224 <lb/></page> 
			
			<listBibl>Tewhey R, Warner JB, Nakano M, Libby B, Med-<lb/>kova M, et al: Microdroplet-based PCR en-<lb/>richment for large-scale targeted sequenc-<lb/>ing. Nat Biotechnol 27: 1025–1031 (2009). <lb/>Turner EH, Lee C, Ng SB, Nickerson DA, Shen-<lb/>dure J: Massively parallel exon capture and <lb/>library-free resequencing across 16 genomes. <lb/>Nature Methods 6: 315–316 (2009). <lb/>Uhlenhaut NH, Jakob S, Anlag K, Eisenberger T, <lb/>Sekido R, et al: Somatic sex reprogramming <lb/>of adult ovaries to testes by FOXL2 ablation. <lb/>Cell 139: 1130–1142 (2009). <lb/>Valouev A, Ichikawa J, Tonthat T, Stuart J, <lb/>Ranade S, et al: A high-resolution, nucleo-<lb/>some position map of C. elegans reveals a <lb/>lack of universal sequence-dictated position-<lb/>ing. Genome Res 18: 1051–1063 (2008). <lb/>van Silfhout A, Boot AM, Dijkhuizen T, Hoek A, <lb/>Nijman R, et al: A unique 970 kb microdele-<lb/>tion in 9q33.3, including the NR5A1 gene in <lb/>a 46,XY female. Eur J Med Genet 52: 157–160 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>Vinci G, Chantot-Bastaraud S, El Houate B, Lor-<lb/>tat-Jacob S, Brauner R, et al: Association of <lb/>deletion of 9p, 46,XY gonadal dysgenesis and <lb/>autistic spectrum disorder. Mol Hum Re-<lb/>prod 13: 685–689 (2007). <lb/>Voelkerding KV, Dames SA, Durtschi JD: Next-<lb/>generation sequencing: from basic research <lb/>to diagnostics. Clin Chem 55: 641–658 <lb/>(2009). <lb/>Vogelstein B: Transforming single DNA mole-<lb/>cules into fluorescent magnetic particles for <lb/>detection and enumeration of genetic varia-<lb/>tions. Proc Natl Acad Sci USA 100: 8817– <lb/>8822 (2003). <lb/>Wieacker P, Volleth M: WNT4 and RSPO1 are <lb/>not involved in a case of male-to-female sex <lb/>reversal with partial duplication of 1p. Sex <lb/>Dev 1: 111–113 (2007). <lb/>Wilhelm D, Palmer S, Koopman P: Sex determi-<lb/>nation and gonadal development in mam-<lb/>mals. Physiol Rev 87: 1–28 (2007). <lb/>Zhang F, Gu W, Hurles ME, Lupski JR: Copy <lb/>number variation in human health, disease, <lb/>and evolution. Annu Rev Genomics Hum <lb/>Genet 10: 451–481 (2009). <lb/></listBibl> 
			
			<div type="annex">Erratum <lb/> In the article by Bashamboo et al. &apos;New Technologies for the Identification of Novel Ge-<lb/>netic Markers of Disorders of Sex Development (DSD)&apos; (Sex Dev DOI: 10.1159/000314917) <lb/>an error occurred with one of the author names. <lb/>Now it reads &apos;J. Achermann&apos; but the correct name is &apos;J.C. Achermann&apos;. </div>

	</text>
</tei>
