<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Tobacco marketing in California and implications for <lb/>the future <lb/>April Roeseler, 1 Ellen C Feighery, 2 Tess Boley Cruz 3 <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>Background Tobacco marketing influences tobacco use <lb/>initiation, maintenance of use, and it undermines <lb/>comprehensive tobacco control programmes. Policies to <lb/>ban the impact of tobacco marketing are most likely to <lb/>be more effective if they are comprehensive, as partial <lb/>bans shift marketing to non-banned forms of media. A <lb/>comprehensive approach to reducing tobacco marketing <lb/>includes documentation through monitoring, media and <lb/>policy interventions and aggressive enforcement of <lb/>existing laws. <lb/>Methods This paper summarises California tobacco <lb/>industry monitoring of events and retail outlets, and <lb/>findings about exposure to and beliefs about tobacco <lb/>industry marketing among youths and adults conducted <lb/>during the period 2000 through 2008. <lb/>Results There was no overall change in the average <lb/>number of cigarette materials per store, and an increase <lb/>in the percentage of stores with advertisements <lb/>promoting price discounts for cigarettes. Stores with <lb/>cigarette advertisements near candy displays declined <lb/>from 12.5% (95% CI 9.8% to 15.2%) to 1% (95% CI 0.2% <lb/>to 1.9%) of stores, and advertisements at or below the <lb/>eye-level of children declined from 78.6% (95% CI 75.2% <lb/>to 82.0%) to 31% (95% CI 27.1% to 34.9%) of stores. <lb/>Overall, the number of public events with tobacco <lb/>sponsorship declined from 77.3% to 48.1%. This trend <lb/>was consistent with a significant decline noted among <lb/>high school students and adults who reported seeing <lb/>tobacco advertisements at events or attending a tobacco <lb/>company-sponsored event. <lb/>Conclusions Tobacco industry monitoring, media, policy <lb/>and enforcement interventions may have contributed to <lb/>observed changes in tobacco marketing and to declines <lb/>in reported exposure to tobacco marketing. <lb/></front>

			<body>BACKGROUND <lb/>Tobacco industry marketing encompasses planned <lb/>efforts to convince people to desire, buy or support <lb/>tobacco company interests using methods that <lb/>include paid advertising, price promotions, public <lb/>relations and distribution of tobacco products and <lb/>promotional items. 1 These marketing strategies are <lb/>an important factor affecting individual uptake, 2 <lb/>maintenance of tobacco use, and they impact the <lb/>success of comprehensive tobacco control <lb/>programmes in ways that extend beyond its effect <lb/>on individual tobacco users. 3 Exposure to point-of-<lb/>sale tobacco promotions influences susceptibility to <lb/>smoking, smoking initiation, impulse tobacco <lb/>purchases and undermines quitting. 4 5 Price <lb/>promotions undermine the effect of tobacco taxes <lb/>to reduce tobacco consumption and smoking <lb/>prevalence by increasing the affordability of <lb/>tobacco products, 6e9 while political campaign <lb/>contributions, sponsorship, philanthropy and <lb/>corporate responsibility efforts subtly influence <lb/>tobacco-related policy decisions made by elected <lb/>officials, community leaders, constituency groups <lb/>and even juries. 10e16 <lb/>The California Department of Public Health <lb/>(CDPH), California Tobacco Control Program <lb/>(CTCP) has continuously monitored exposure to <lb/>and beliefs about tobacco industry marketing <lb/>among adults and youths through telephone and <lb/>in-school surveys. These population-based surveys <lb/>are supplemented with observational surveys of <lb/>tobacco marketing focused on sponsored events and <lb/>the retail environment. This paper describes Cali-<lb/>fornia&apos;s media and programme interventions to <lb/>stimulate tobacco marketing restrictions; enforce-<lb/>ment of the Master Settlement Agreement i (MSA), <lb/>Smokeless Tobacco Settlement Agreement and <lb/>existing laws; and reports on changes in marketing, <lb/>and adult and youth attitudes about and exposure <lb/>to tobacco industry marketing in California. <lb/>Sponsorship <lb/>Sponsorship occurs when a company pays money <lb/>to an event organiser, site owner or competitor in <lb/>exchange for access to the audience, promotional <lb/>rights and use of the event or property trade-<lb/>marks. 11 It is an important form of marketing <lb/>because it allows tobacco companies to associate <lb/>their name and brands with a desirable lifestyle <lb/>image, people&apos;s pastimes and passions, 17e19 and <lb/>provides tobacco companies the ability to circum-<lb/>vent the 1971 ban on marketing cigarettes in the <lb/>broadcast media. 20 Viewers of tobacco-sponsored <lb/>sporting events have more brand awareness, more <lb/>favourable attitudes towards tobacco use and pref-<lb/>erences for specific tobacco brands. 21 22 Sponsorship <lb/>also occurs at adult-only facilities such as bars, clubs <lb/>and fraternities. These staged marketing opportuni-<lb/>ties usually involve distributing free product samples, <lb/>coupons and promotional items to build brand <lb/>awareness, introduce a new product, encourage <lb/>experimentation, retain and build customer loyalty, <lb/>and generate names for direct mail. 23e25 Attendance <lb/>at these events has been associated with higher <lb/>smoking prevalence among college students. 26 <lb/></body>

			<front>1 California Department of Public <lb/>Health, California Tobacco <lb/>Control Program, Sacramento, <lb/>California, USA <lb/>2 International Research, <lb/>Campaign for Tobacco Free <lb/>Kids, Washington, DC, USA <lb/>3 Preventive Medicine, University <lb/>of Southern California, Keck <lb/>School of Medicine, Los <lb/>Angeles, California, USA <lb/>Correspondence to <lb/>April Roeseler, Programs and <lb/>Media Operations Section, <lb/>California Department of Public <lb/>Health, CDIC/California Tobacco <lb/>Control Program, MS 7206, PO <lb/>Box 997377, Sacramento, CA <lb/>95899-7377, USA; <lb/>April.Roeseler@cdph.ca.gov <lb/>Received 3 June 2009 <lb/>Accepted 8 January 2010 <lb/>This paper is freely available <lb/>online under the BMJ Journals <lb/>unlocked scheme, see http:// <lb/>tobaccocontrol.bmj.com/site/ <lb/>about/unlocked.xhtml <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">i The 1998 Master Settlement Agreement (MSA) and the Smokeless <lb/>Tobacco Master Settlement Agreement (STMSA) are legal <lb/>contracts established between 46 states, including California, and <lb/>five US territories, with participating tobacco manufacturers. The <lb/>MSA and STMSA provide numerous restrictions and prohibitions, <lb/>including bans on the use of cartoons in tobacco advertisements, <lb/>youth exposure to sampling, certain sponsorships, and the use of <lb/>most outdoor advertisements. Tobacco Litigation and Enforcement. <lb/>California Office of the Attorney General. Available from: http://ag. <lb/>ca.gov/tobacco/index.php (accessed 29 September 2008). <lb/></note>

			<front>Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/>i21 <lb/>Research paper <lb/></front>

			<body>In 2006, US cigarette companies spent $168 million on <lb/>sponsoring public entertainment, and smokeless tobacco <lb/>companies spent $144 000 on this marketing category. Cigarette <lb/>companies reported spending $29 million on free sample distri-<lb/>bution in 2006 while smokeless tobacco companies spent $42 <lb/>million on free samples. 27 28 <lb/>Retail environment <lb/>Retail outlets are an important environment for tobacco <lb/>companies to promote their products, segment the market and <lb/>target groups they might lose such as those thinking about <lb/>quitting or who have recently quit. In-store marketing strategies <lb/>to achieve these goals include point-of-sale advertising, <lb/>payments for prime product placement and a variety of price <lb/>discounting tools. 4 Numerous studies document the influence of <lb/>point-of-purchase tobacco marketing and price promotions on <lb/>smoking initiation, movement along the smoking continuum to <lb/>a regular smoker and undermining of quit efforts. 3 4 <lb/>In 2006, point-of-sale advertising led traditional tobacco <lb/>advertising expenditures among cigarette and smokeless tobacco <lb/>companies at approximately $243 million for cigarette compa-<lb/>nies and $21 million for smokeless tobacco companies. 27 28 <lb/>However, price-related marketing strategies dominated <lb/>marketing expenditures of both cigarette and tobacco companies <lb/>in 2006. 27 28 Price promotions are frequently linked to contrac-<lb/>tual agreements between the tobacco companies and retailers to <lb/>offer volume discounts and financial incentives to secure product <lb/>placement and marketing materials where they will be noticed <lb/>by consumers. 29 <lb/>The trend towards price-related marketing relative to expen-<lb/>ditures for image-oriented cigarette advertising began in the late <lb/>1980s. 25 Following the 1998 MSA which banned tobacco bill-<lb/>board advertising and placed restrictions on other forms of <lb/>traditional advertising and promotions, this trend was acceler-<lb/>ated. 4 25 30 31 In 2006, cigarette companies allocated 93% ($11.5 <lb/>billion) of all their advertising and promotions expenditures <lb/>toward price-related strategies (promotional allowances, <lb/>coupons, retail value added and price discounts) and smokeless <lb/>tobacco companies spent 69% ($246 million) of all their adver-<lb/>tising and promotion expenditures on these categories. 27 28 <lb/>Media and programme interventions to address tobacco <lb/>marketing <lb/>Since 1990, California&apos;s media campaign has raised awareness <lb/>about the tobacco industry&apos;s marketing practices and sought to <lb/>shape attitudes that support placing restrictions on tobacco <lb/>marketing. As illustrated in figure 1, a 1994 outdoor advertise-<lb/>ment called attention to tobacco company sponsorship of <lb/>motorsport events and their appeal to youth. Between 2001 and <lb/>2004 a television advertising campaign featuring Ken Lane, <lb/>a fictional tobacco industry marketing executive, was aired. <lb/>These advertisements, which are available from the Centers for <lb/>Disease Control Media Resource Center, discussed tobacco <lb/>industry marketing, (eg, sponsorship of motorsports, in-store <lb/>advertising and target marketing). 32 Figure 2 displays a print <lb/>advertisement from the Ken Lane campaign, which raised <lb/>awareness about the strategic placement of tobacco advertise-<lb/>ments in stores. More recently, the 2009 Grim Reapers television <lb/>advertisement called attention to the deadly nature of distrib-<lb/>uting free tobacco products. 33 See figure 3. <lb/>In addition to the media campaign, three statewide advocacy <lb/>campaigns mobilised community efforts to address tobacco <lb/>marketing. Each campaign provided training and electronic or <lb/>print toolkits for tobacco control projects, including instruments <lb/>to monitor tobacco marketing, sample policies, talking points <lb/>and educational and public relations materials. 34e43 <lb/>The first campaign, Operation Storefront: Youth Against Tobacco <lb/>Advertising and Promotions began in 1994 (A Roeseler, C Russell, <lb/>E Feighery, et al, unpublished report, 1995). This campaign <lb/>sought to restrict the placement of in-store tobacco advertising <lb/>in locations where it was likely to be seen by youths and to <lb/>stimulate enforcement of existing laws that restrict placement <lb/>of exterior retail advertising. Compliance with these exterior <lb/>signage laws, which were originally enacted for beautification <lb/>(eg, prohibit outdoor sandwich board signs) or public safety <lb/>purposes (eg, limits on the percentage of a store window that <lb/>may be covered by advertising to ensure the store interior is <lb/>visible to police from the outside), reduces tobacco advertising. 44 <lb/>By 2001, approximately 40 California cities and counties had <lb/>enacted ordinances restricting in-store tobacco advertising or <lb/>outdoors in locations frequented by minors. 45 These ordinances <lb/>were nullified as the result of the US Supreme Court Lorillard <lb/>Tobacco Co v Reilly (533 US 525 (2001) decision which struck <lb/>down a Massachusetts regulation prohibiting tobacco product <lb/>advertising within 1000 feet of any school or playground. 4 <lb/>A second CTCP campaign, initiated in 1997 was Project <lb/>SMART (Sponsorship Mission: Avoid Reliance on Tobacco) Money. It <lb/>focused on reducing tobacco industry event sponsorship and free <lb/>tobacco product sampling through policy adoption and <lb/>enforcement of existing sampling laws (TB Cruz, N Preacely, <lb/>unpublished report, 2005). California policies to eliminate <lb/>tobacco-related event sponsorship include 22 state, county and <lb/>local fair board policies, seven rodeo-level policies and 20 <lb/>university, college and community level policies prohibiting <lb/>tobacco sponsorship or advertising. 46e48 <lb/>California state law prohibits tobacco sampling in many <lb/>locales, but permits it in adult-only facilities. 49 As of 2009, there <lb/>were 47 ordinances restricting the free distribution of tobacco <lb/>products in California. 50 One of the strongest of these is the city <lb/>of Chico&apos;s 2007 ban on the non-sale distribution of smokeless <lb/>tobacco and cigarettes, coupons and rebates in locations <lb/>including bars, fraternities, sororities, convenience stores and gas <lb/>stations. 51 This college community has a population of 69 000 <lb/>and a student population of 17 000 at California State Univer-<lb/>sity Chico. Before its ordinance, the US Smokeless Tobacco <lb/>Company (USST) sponsored bar nights in the city, and parties at <lb/>the university&apos;s fraternities and sororities. Students were often <lb/>hired to give away free samples of tobacco products along with <lb/>promotional items, including T-shirts, shot glasses and lighted <lb/>necklaces in exchange for personal information. 52 53 <lb/>The third statewide advocacy effort launched was the STORE <lb/>(Strategic Tobacco Retail Effort) Campaign in 2002. It took <lb/>a comprehensive approach to the retail environment in terms of <lb/>tobacco marketing and sales. 43 This campaign helped build <lb/>momentum for local tobacco retail licensing and self-service <lb/>display bans. From 1998 to September 2009, 102 tobacco retail <lb/>licensing ordinances were enacted which cover about 57% of the <lb/>state&apos;s population. 54 The number of self-service tobacco sales <lb/>bans enacted increased from 27 in 1994 to 157 in July 2009. 54 55 <lb/>The large number of local self-service display ordinances facili-<lb/>tated passage of a statewide self-service display ban on cigarettes <lb/>in 2002, which was expanded to include other tobacco products <lb/>in 2004. 56 57 <lb/>California Attorney General Office collaboration <lb/>The campaigns described above were complemented by aggressive <lb/>enforcement activity by the California Attorney General&apos;s Office. <lb/>The California Attorney General&apos;s Office used documentation <lb/></body>

			<page>i22 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<body>provided by state and local tobacco control programmes to <lb/>pursue enforcement and lawsuits against tobacco companies and <lb/>to compel large corporate retailers to enter into voluntary <lb/>agreements to abide by business practices aimed at reducing <lb/>illegal tobacco sales to minors. Since 2000, the California <lb/>Attorney General&apos;s Office efforts resulted in 14 successful <lb/>enforcement actions against tobacco companies totalling more <lb/>than $24 million in payments, penalties and fees. Of these <lb/>payments, nearly $1.9 million was earmarked for tobacco <lb/>control. Eight (57%) of the enforcement actions involved viola-<lb/>tions of the MSA and six (43%) were for violations of California <lb/>state law regulating the non-sale distribution of tobacco prod-<lb/>ucts. RJ Reynolds and USST were responsible for 13 (93%) of <lb/>these enforcement actions. Appendix 1 provides additional <lb/>details. 58e72 <lb/>In 2002 the California Attorney General&apos;s Office negotiated <lb/>with the Coalition for Responsible Tobacco Retailing and Philip <lb/>Morris to revise information and materials they distributed to <lb/>retailers to educate them about mandated age-of-sale warning <lb/>sign requirements and to communicate that the use of the We <lb/>Card sign did not comply with State law. 73 In partnership with <lb/>other state attorneys general, it also negotiated voluntary <lb/>agreements with 12 major chain retail convenience, drug store, <lb/>gas station and grocery stores to implement meaningful business <lb/>practices to reduce tobacco sales to minors. An additional <lb/>agreement with a California grocery store chain resulted from <lb/>litigation. 74 <lb/>METHODS <lb/>California&apos;s tobacco industry monitoring system collects data on <lb/>tobacco marketing at public events, in the retail environment <lb/>and from adults and youths through telephone and in-school <lb/>surveys. An abbreviated description of each survey&apos;s method-<lb/>ology is described here with references given to obtain a full <lb/>description. <lb/>Event sponsorship monitoring methods <lb/>From 2001 to 2003, tobacco industry event sponsorship moni-<lb/>toring and analyses were conducted by the University of <lb/>Southern California (USC). Beginning in 2006, Population <lb/>Research System (PRS) took over the data collection with CTCP <lb/>conducting the analyses. No statewide tobacco industry event <lb/>sponsorship data were collected during 2004 and 2005. <lb/>During the 2004 to 2005 transition, the USC data collection <lb/>instrument was revised. Open-ended questions were converted <lb/>to close-ended multiple choice questions to standardise data <lb/>Figure 1 California Tobacco Control <lb/>Program outdoor advertisement to raise <lb/>awareness about tobacco company <lb/>sponsorship of car racing events and <lb/>their appeal to youth. <lb/>Figure 2 California Tobacco Control Program print advertisement to <lb/>raise awareness about retail tobacco advertising placed at the eye-level <lb/>of children. <lb/>Figure 3 Scene from California Tobacco Control Program television <lb/>advertisement to raise awareness about the deadly nature of free <lb/>tobacco product distribution. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<page>i23 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<body>collection and analysis. Survey instruments from both USC <lb/>and PRS collected data on event information, tobacco <lb/>industry sponsorship, youth activities at the event, the presence <lb/>of adult-only areas and event attendance. The methodology to <lb/>estimate audience size varied slightly between the two surveys. <lb/>Owing to funding limitations, a purposive sampling plan was <lb/>used to select events for observation. Selection criteria were <lb/>based on past history of the event including having a large <lb/>audience, a tobacco-sponsored adult-only area, the free distri-<lb/>bution of tobacco products, presence of a mobile electronic <lb/>scoreboard or previous history of tobacco marketing violations <lb/>at similar event types. Both USC and PRS placed a pre-event <lb/>telephone call to confirm the date, location, ticket information <lb/>and information about tobacco industry sponsorship. <lb/>USC staff and volunteers from CTCP-funded projects <lb/>conducted observations from 2001 to 2003. Beginning in 2006, <lb/>only paid observers were used. For the period 2001e2003, <lb/>observers were provided with written instructions and a video <lb/>training programme on how to complete the forms. Completed <lb/>observation forms, tobacco promotional materials and photo-<lb/>graphs from the event were mailed to USC where the data were <lb/>entered into a database. <lb/>Beginning in 2006, observers were trained by CTCP staff. <lb/>Completed observation forms were scanned and emailed to PRS <lb/>following the event observation. Observations forms, the event <lb/>programme, promotional materials and photographs were also <lb/>electronically scanned and uploaded to a file transfer protocol <lb/>(ftp) site by the data collectors. The California Attorney <lb/>General&apos;s Office was provided access to the ftp site to monitor <lb/>the data for potential MSA violations. <lb/>Retail environment monitoring methods <lb/>The California Tobacco Assessment Study is a longitudinal <lb/>prospective cohort study of California stores that sell tobacco. <lb/>Since 2000, six survey waves were conducted to assess tobacco <lb/>marketing materials in the retail environment. The survey was <lb/>conducted in 2000, annually from 2002 to 2005 and in 2008. The <lb/>baseline study sample was based on a 1997 randomly selected <lb/>sample of California stores that sold cigarettes. Each year, stores <lb/>that were found to be &apos;no longer in business&apos; were replaced with <lb/>new randomly selected stores from the original sampling frame. <lb/>Trained paid observers collected data on the amount, placement <lb/>and type of branded cigarette marketing materials, and func-<lb/>tional items (eg, trash cans and coin trays); placement of <lb/>advertisements; posting of tobacco age-of-sale warning signs and <lb/>the required tobacco retail licence; and compliance with the ban <lb/>on self-service displays of tobacco. Further information on the <lb/>methods and analyses can be found in a paper by Feighery et al. 75 <lb/>Telephone surveys and in-school survey methods <lb/>Perceptions of and exposure to tobacco marketing are collected <lb/>through telephone and in-school surveys. The California Adult <lb/>Tobacco Survey (1993e2007) is an ongoing monthly random-<lb/>digit-dial telephone survey of approximately 6200 adults <lb/>conducted using computer assisted telephone interviewing by <lb/>the survey research group, Public Health Institute. Data were <lb/>weighted to the 2000 California population using gender, four <lb/>race groups and two age groups. Additional information on the <lb/>methodology is available in a paper by Wayland et al. 76 The <lb/>California Tobacco Survey is a cross-sectional random-digit-dial <lb/>telephone survey conducted approximately every 3 years since <lb/>1990 by the University of California, San Diego, Cancer <lb/>Prevention and Control Center and Westat, Inc to measure <lb/>changes in attitudes and behaviours in the California popula-<lb/>tion. It has a sample size of approximately 30 575 screener <lb/>households. Oversampling of racial/ethnic groups and in-<lb/>language survey methods are used to ensure adequate sample <lb/>sizes within subpopulation groups. Data were weighted to the <lb/>2005 Current Population Survey, California population. Addi-<lb/>tional information on the methodology is available in a paper by <lb/>Al-Delaimy et al. 77 <lb/>The California Student Tobacco Survey (2002e2006) is a <lb/>school-based survey conducted among approximately 17 000 <lb/>students in over 300 middle (grades 6e8) and high schools <lb/>(grades 9e12). The data were weighted to the 2005 population <lb/>of California in-school youth, by gender, grade level and race/ <lb/>ethnicity. Further information about the methods is available in <lb/>a paper by McCarthy et al. 78 <lb/>Limitations <lb/>It is not possible to determine that the changes documented <lb/>among adults, students and tobacco company marketing prac-<lb/>tices are the result of exposure to the media, policy and <lb/>enforcement interventions. This is due to the cross-sectional <lb/>nature of the population survey data and the lack of measures <lb/>that determine the extent of exposure of adults and youths to <lb/>specific tobacco marketing-related media, programme and <lb/>enforcement interventions. However, the triangulation of data <lb/>from multiple sources increases confidence in the individual <lb/>survey results and the conclusions drawn about progress. <lb/>RESULTS <lb/>Event sponsorship results <lb/>Tobacco event sponsorship was monitored at large public events <lb/>at risk of tobacco sponsorship such as rodeos, motorsports or <lb/>other events with a history of tobacco sponsorship. Tobacco <lb/>company, brand names, youth participation and free tobacco <lb/>product distribution were key variables that were observed. <lb/>Simple description statistics were used to analyse the data. As <lb/>depicted in table 1, from 2001 to 2008, the percentage of <lb/>observed events with tobacco industry sponsorship declined <lb/>from 77.3% to 48.1%. As displayed in table 2, in 2001, the <lb/>percentage of events with smokeless tobacco and cigarette <lb/>company sponsorship collectively were comparable with each <lb/>having a presence at 60% of the events observed. In subsequent <lb/>years, smokeless tobacco dominated event sponsorship. In 2008, <lb/>USST or its brands sponsored 79% of events in comparison to <lb/>Philip Morris/Altria at 21%. <lb/>As displayed in table 3, rodeo-related events represented <lb/>approximately one-half or more of the total number of tobacco <lb/>industry-sponsored events each year. During 2007 and 2008, the <lb/>percentage of tobacco industry-sponsored music or performing <lb/>art events increased from previous years and is now on par with <lb/>racing, a more traditional tobacco venue. <lb/>The non-sale distribution of tobacco products (eg, free tobacco <lb/>samples and coupons for tobacco products) and youth involve-<lb/>ment activities are sometimes found at tobacco industry-spon-<lb/>sored events. As depicted in table 4, during the six observation <lb/>periods the proportion of events with youth participation <lb/>generally declined; however, more than one-third (36.8%) of <lb/>Table 1 Percentage of observed events with tobacco industry <lb/>sponsorship, 2001e2003 and 2006e2008 <lb/>2001 <lb/>2002 <lb/>2003 <lb/>2006 <lb/>2007 <lb/>2008 <lb/>n[88 <lb/>n[80 <lb/>n[91 <lb/>n[68 <lb/>n[80 <lb/>n[79 <lb/>77.3 <lb/>77.2 <lb/>67.0 <lb/>58.8 <lb/>56.3 <lb/>48.1 <lb/></body>

			<page>i24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<body>tobacco industry-sponsored events still included youth partici-<lb/>pation either as competitors in races, riding or mutton-busting <lb/>events, or they carried flags or banners at event ceremonies, <lb/>demonstrating the long-term strategic nature of tobacco spon-<lb/>sorship in 2008. Overall, there was no real decline in the <lb/>proportion of tobacco industry-sponsored events that offered <lb/>free tobacco product sampling with the proportion ranging from <lb/>a low of 11.5% of events in 2003 rising to 24.4% in 2006 and <lb/>then declining to 18.4% in 2008. <lb/>Tobacco retail advertising results <lb/>Tobacco advertising in the retail environment has been moni-<lb/>tored since 2000. From these surveys, key variables related to the <lb/>saturation of retail tobacco advertising, its placement and <lb/>compliance with state laws are presented. Table 5 presents the <lb/>change in the average number of cigarette marketing materials <lb/>per store for 2000, 2004 and 2008. It rose in 2004, but remained <lb/>constant throughout the observation period. <lb/>Table 6 depicts the change in the percentage of stores with at <lb/>least one cigarette advertisement promoting a price discount and <lb/>the percentage of stores placing cigarette advertisements within <lb/>six inches of candy and placed at or below three feet. The <lb/>placement of advertisements near candy and placement of <lb/>advertisements under three feet declined from 2002 to 2008; <lb/>however, the percentage of stores with at least one advertise-<lb/>ment promoting a price discount increased. <lb/>Between 2000 and 2004, there was a large increase in the <lb/>proportion of stores that had a least one required warning sign <lb/>posted, rising from 53.6% (95% CI 49.0% to 57.3%) in 2000 to <lb/>66.2% (95% CI 62.2% to 70.2%) in 2008. However, as depicted <lb/>by table 7, in 2008 a greater proportion of stores posted the <lb/>tobacco industry-produced We Card sign rather than the age-of-<lb/>sale warning sign required by California law. In contrast, more <lb/>than 99% of stores complied with the state law banning self-<lb/>service displays of tobacco products in 2008. <lb/>Adult and youth attitudes and exposure results <lb/>Attitudes, beliefs and exposure to tobacco marketing are tracked <lb/>through adult telephone surveys and in-school surveys. Key data <lb/>are presented that relate to support for regulating tobacco <lb/>marketing and exposure to tobacco sponsorship. <lb/>In 2007, California adults expressed strong support for regu-<lb/>lating tobacco marketing: 76.4% (95% CI 74.4% to 78.4%) <lb/>agreed that tobacco products should be regulated as a drug by <lb/>a government agency such as the Food and Drug Administration <lb/>(FDA); 75.0% (95% CI 73.9% to 76.0%) agreed that a ban on <lb/>cigarette advertising should be extended to all print and elec-<lb/>tronic media; and 78.2% (95% CI 77.2% to 79.3%) agreed that <lb/>advertising tobacco products at sports and athletic events should <lb/>be banned. 79 Seeing tobacco advertisements at sporting and <lb/>community events and reported attendance at a tobacco <lb/>company-sponsored event in the past year declined among <lb/>youths and adults compared to earlier years. The proportion of <lb/>high school students reporting they had seen tobacco adver-<lb/>tisements at sport or community events declined significantly <lb/>from 58.1% to 52% (p value &lt;0.001) between 2002 and 2006. 80 <lb/>The proportion of adults who reported attending a tobacco <lb/>company-sponsored event in the past year also declined signifi-<lb/>cantly from 19% in 2002 to 14.0% in 2005 (p value &lt;0.001). 81 <lb/>DISCUSSION <lb/>Since the mid-1990s, the CTCP has raised awareness about the <lb/>influence that tobacco marketing has on tobacco use. Its media <lb/>campaign, statewide advocacy campaigns and the partnership <lb/>with the California Attorney General&apos;s Office sought to curb <lb/>tobacco marketing through a variety of voluntary, legislated and <lb/>enforcement approaches. <lb/>Since 2000, there was little change in the overall average <lb/>number of cigarette marketing materials per store but there was <lb/>a substantial increase in the percentage of stores with adver-<lb/>tising promoting price discounts for cigarettes. Progress was <lb/>made in decreasing the percentage of stores placing tobacco <lb/>advertisements near candy displays (reduced to 1% of stores) <lb/>and at the eye-level of young children (reduced from 78.6% to <lb/>31.0%). Compliance with posting required age-of-sale warning <lb/>signs increased significantly, but remained substantially lower <lb/>than posting of the tobacco industry&apos;s We Card sign (66.2% vs <lb/>94.0%). <lb/>Table 2 Percentage of tobacco industry sponsored events by tobacco <lb/>company*, 2001e2003 and 2006e2008 <lb/>Tobacco company <lb/>2001 <lb/>2002 <lb/>2003 <lb/>2006 <lb/>2007 <lb/>2008 <lb/>n[68 <lb/>n[58 <lb/>n[61 <lb/>n[40 <lb/>n[45 <lb/>n[38 <lb/>USST <lb/>60.3 <lb/>77.6 <lb/>77.0 <lb/>95.0 <lb/>84.4 <lb/>78.9 <lb/>Philip Morris/Altria <lb/>19.1 <lb/>20.7 <lb/>11.5 <lb/>5.0 <lb/>15.6 <lb/>21.1 <lb/>RJ Reynolds <lb/>25.0 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>13.1 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.2 <lb/>0 <lb/>Lorillard <lb/>16.2 <lb/>5.2 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Swedish Match <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>1.1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>*A single event may have been sponsored by multiple tobacco companies or brands. If <lb/>a tobacco company and one or more of its brands were event sponsors, the sponsorship <lb/>was counted only once for the tobacco company (eg, a dual Skoal and Copenhagen <lb/>sponsorship was only counted as one USST sponsored event). If an event was sponsored <lb/>by brands of two different tobacco companies, the sponsorship was counted twice, once <lb/>for each tobacco company, (eg, if an event were sponsored by both Winston and Skoal it <lb/>was counted as one RJR sponsored event and as one USST sponsored event). <lb/>Table 3 Percentage of tobacco industry sponsored events by event <lb/>type, 2001e2003 and 2006e2008 <lb/>Event type <lb/>2001 <lb/>2002 <lb/>2003 <lb/>2006 <lb/>2007 <lb/>2008 <lb/>n[68 n[58 n[61 n[40 n[45 n[38 <lb/>Rodeo* <lb/>50.0 <lb/>62.1 <lb/>49.1 <lb/>70.0 <lb/>71.1 <lb/>57.9 <lb/>Motorsporty <lb/>32.4 <lb/>20.7 <lb/>36.1 <lb/>27.5 <lb/>11.1 <lb/>21.1 <lb/>Music or performing arts 14.7 <lb/>10.3 <lb/>1.6 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>17.8 <lb/>21.1 <lb/>Other events <lb/>2.9 <lb/>6.9 <lb/>13.1 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>*Rodeo events include rodeo, bull riding and team roping. <lb/>yMotorsport events include auto and motorcycle racing. <lb/>Table 4 Percentage of tobacco industry sponsored events with non-<lb/>sale distribution of tobacco products or youth participation activities, <lb/>2001e2003 and 2006e2008 <lb/>2001 <lb/>2002 <lb/>2003 <lb/>2006 <lb/>2007 <lb/>2008 <lb/>n[68 <lb/>n[58 <lb/>n[61 <lb/>n[40 <lb/>n[45 <lb/>n[38 <lb/>Non-sale distribution <lb/>of tobacco products* <lb/>16.2 <lb/>22.4 <lb/>11.5 <lb/>22.5 <lb/>17.8 <lb/>18.4 <lb/>Youth participation <lb/>eventsy <lb/>44.1 <lb/>43.1 <lb/>54.1 <lb/>52.5 <lb/>44.4 <lb/>36.8 <lb/>*Defined as free tobacco product or coupon giveaways. <lb/>yDefined as events in which participants or competitors were under 18 years of agedfor <lb/>example, racing or riding contestants, mutton-busting participants, carried flags or banners. <lb/>Table 5 2000e2008: average number of cigarette marketing materials <lb/>per store <lb/>Saturation or placement <lb/>2000 <lb/>2004 <lb/>2008 <lb/>(n[562) <lb/>(n[565) <lb/>(n[545) <lb/>Average number of cigarette <lb/>marketing materials <lb/>19.1 (SD¼18.6) 1 26.1 (SD¼25.2) 17.6 (SD¼11.2) <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<page>i25 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<body>The continued saturation of stores with cigarette advertising <lb/>and increase in price promotion advertisements mirrors the <lb/>emphasis seen in tobacco company expenditures for point-of-<lb/>sale retail advertising and price-related marketing. The high rate <lb/>of retailers posting We Card signs is probably a function of <lb/>contract requirements between tobacco companies and stores. <lb/>These contracts require specific marketing provisions in return <lb/>for price promotions aimed to stimulate sales. 29 This situation <lb/>may improve as local tobacco retail licensing ordinances <lb/>earmarking a portion of the licence fees for enforcement are <lb/>enacted, but a straightforward solution would be for tobacco <lb/>companies to incorporate mandated age-of-sale signage require-<lb/>ments into their price promotion contracts. <lb/>Overall there was a decline in the number and percentage of <lb/>tobacco-sponsored events between 2001 and 2008. This is <lb/>consistent with the significant decline noted among high school <lb/>students and adults who reported seeing tobacco advertisements <lb/>at events or attending a tobacco company-sponsored event. <lb/>There was a marked shift towards smokeless tobacco-related <lb/>sponsorships and rodeo-related event sponsorship, which may <lb/>reflect an industry-wide move to add smokeless tobacco prod-<lb/>ucts to their promoted brands. <lb/>The pervasiveness of free tobacco product sampling at events <lb/>remained relatively unchanged over the six observation periods. <lb/>A modest decline in youth participation-oriented activities at <lb/>tobacco-sponsored events was observed, but more than one-<lb/>third (36.8%) of them continued to include these activities. <lb/>Repeated enforcement action was taken against RJ Reynolds and <lb/>USST to address compliance with the MSA/STMSA and the <lb/>state restriction on no-cost tobacco distribution. This suggests <lb/>that partial bans on tobacco marketing provide greater opport-<lb/>unity to test limits or may be difficult to understand. <lb/>Tobacco industry monitoring data were used to develop media <lb/>and policy interventions such as the Ken Lane and Grim Reapers <lb/>advertisements and statewide advocacy campaigns. The data <lb/>also helped to forge a partnership with the California Attorneys <lb/>General&apos;s Office. Consequently, substantial enforcement opera-<lb/>tions and voluntary agreements were achieved. These resulted in <lb/>new resources for tobacco control work including regular <lb/>correspondence from the tobacco companies about the date and <lb/>location of free tobacco sampling activities and earmarking <lb/>a portion of payments resulting from enforcement action <lb/>towards tobacco control efforts. <lb/>Local tobacco control ordinances restricting tobacco <lb/>marketing before the 2001 US-Supreme Court decision Lorillard <lb/>v Reilly along with the current level of public support for <lb/>tobacco marketing restrictions suggests that California <lb/>communities are well-positioned to seize opportunities afforded <lb/>by the Family Smoking Prevention and Tobacco Control Act. <lb/>This federal legislation implements a number of new marketing <lb/>restrictions and gives the US Food and Drug Administration <lb/>(FDA) comprehensive authority to regulate the manufacturing, <lb/>marketing and sale of tobacco product. It also eliminates the pre-<lb/>existing federal pre-emption of the state and local restrictions on <lb/>the time, place or manner of cigarette advertising for public <lb/>health purposes. 82 <lb/>Despite these new opportunities, numerous challenges <lb/>remain. Monitoring tobacco industry marketing is difficult <lb/>owing to its sheer volume, diversity and pervasiveness. 1 4 The <lb/>task has become increasingly formidable given the industry&apos;s <lb/>agile response to US restrictions on the use of television, radio, <lb/>billboard, sponsorship and magazine advertisement placement <lb/>and use of technology. Data collection at tobacco industry-<lb/>sponsored bar nights, fraternity parties and adult-only facilities <lb/>relies on labour-intensive methods vastly different from <lb/>surveillance systems traditionally used to monitor communi-<lb/>cable diseases or to track cancer. Monitoring the nature and <lb/>extent of direct mail marketing is difficult, as tobacco industry <lb/>practices incorporate the use of sophisticated technology to <lb/>create one-on-one relationships with consumers through the use <lb/>of contests, the internet, coupons, direct mail, email and mobile <lb/>marketing. 83 84 The First Amendment and tobacco industry <lb/>opposition will continue to create hurdles to the enactment of <lb/>comprehensive bans on tobacco marketing. Yet, there is <lb/>considerable evidence that restrictions to curb the impact of <lb/>tobacco marketing are most effective at reducing tobacco <lb/>consumption when they are comprehensive. 85e88 <lb/>Given these challenges, a network among state and federal <lb/>agencies including attorneys general is needed to coordinate <lb/>efforts and resources to uniformly monitor tobacco industry <lb/>marketing, improve state-specific marketing reporting by <lb/>tobacco companies, leverage legal technical assistance resources, <lb/>coordinate enforcement actions to achieve a greater deterrent <lb/>effect and disseminate educational and media materials to raise <lb/>awareness and facilitate policy adoption. 1 The FDA legislation <lb/>provides a tool to start this work, but success depends on how <lb/>well local, state and national partners can execute meaningful <lb/>policies and their agility at identifying and effectively <lb/>responding to the tobacco industry&apos;s response to use of non-<lb/>restricted media and new marketing techniques. The convening <lb/>and investment of public health, surveillance, legal and <lb/>marketing experts to facilitate this complex, but important <lb/>work should be a high priority among state and federal agencies. <lb/>Table 6 2002e2008: percentage of stores with at least one cigarette advertisement promoting a price <lb/>discount and placement of advertising in a location that may appeal to youths <lb/>Saturation or placement <lb/>2002* <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>2004 <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>2008 <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>(n[569) <lb/>(n[565) <lb/>(n[545) <lb/>At least one cigarette advertisement <lb/>with a price discount <lb/>68.4 <lb/>(64.5 to 72.2) 74.3 <lb/>(70.7 to 78.0) 78.5 <lb/>(75.0 to 82.0) <lb/>Advertisements near candy <lb/>12.5 <lb/>(9.8 to 15.2) <lb/>12.9 <lb/>(10.1 to 15.7) <lb/>1.1 <lb/>(0.2 to 1.9) <lb/>Advertisements at or below 3 feet <lb/>78.6 <lb/>(75.2 to 82.0) 77.9 <lb/>(74.5 to 81.3) 31.0 <lb/>(27.1 to 34.9) <lb/>*2002 data are use for comparison because the 2000 data for advertisements near candy and at or below 3 feet were not comparable <lb/>with subsequent years. <lb/>Table 7 2008 Percentage of tobacco stores posting tobacco sale <lb/>signage <lb/>Year legal <lb/>requirement enacted <lb/>Percentage <lb/>(95% CI) <lb/>(n[) <lb/>State tobacco retail licence 2003 <lb/>45.3 (536) <lb/>(41.0 to 50.0) <lb/>Age-of-sale warning sign <lb/>1994 <lb/>66.2 (545) <lb/>(62.2 to 70.2) <lb/>Tobacco industry <lb/>We Card sign <lb/>Not required by law <lb/>93.8 (545) <lb/>(91.8 to 95.8) <lb/></body>

			<page>i26 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements We thank Nina Schleicher for assistance with the analysis of <lb/>the retail tobacco data. We thank David Cowling, Mary Modayil and Tonia Hagaman <lb/>for assistance with comments on earlier versions and assistance with the <lb/>sponsorship data. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Competing interests None. <lb/>Contributors All authors contributed to the conception and design of the study and <lb/>the acquisition of the data. ECF analyzed and interpreted the retail tobacco advertising <lb/>data. TCB and AR analyzed and interpreted the tobacco sponsorship data. AR drafted <lb/>the article and all authors revised it critically for important intellectual content. All <lb/>authors had final approval of the version published. <lb/>Provenance and peer review Not commissioned; externally peer reviewed. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Cruz TB. Monitoring the tobacco use epidemic IV. Tobacco industry data sources <lb/>and recommendations for research and evaluation. Prev Med 2009;48(Suppl 1): <lb/>s24e34. <lb/>2. Lovato C, Linn G, Stead LF, et al. Impact of tobacco advertising and promotion on <lb/>increasing adolescent smoking behaviors. Cochrane Database Syst Rev 2003;(4): <lb/>CD003439. http://mrw.interscience.wiley.com/cochrane/clsysrev/articles/CD003439/ <lb/>pdf_fs.html (accessed 4 Apr 2009). <lb/>3. US Department of Health and Human Services. Reducing tobacco use: <lb/>a report of the Surgeon General. Atlanta, GA: US Department of Health and <lb/>Human Services, Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, National Center for <lb/>Chronic Disease Prevention and Health Promotion, Office on Smoking and Health, <lb/>2000. <lb/>4. National Cancer Institute. The role of media in promoting and reducing tobacco <lb/>use. Tobacco Control Monograph No. 19. Bethesda, MD: US Department of Health <lb/>and Human Services, national Institutes of Health, national Cancer Institute. NIH Pub. <lb/>No. 07-6242, 2008. <lb/>5. Paynter J, Edwards R. The impact of tobacco promotion at the point of sale: <lb/>a systematic review. Nicotine Tob Res 2009;1:25e35. <lb/>6. Loomis BR, Farrelly MC, Mann NH. The association of retail promotions for <lb/>cigarettes with the master settlement agreement, tobacco control programmes and <lb/>cigarette excise taxes. Tob Control 2006;15:458e63. <lb/>7. Slater S, Chaloupka FJ, Wakefield M. State variability in retail promotions and <lb/>advertising for Marlboro cigarettes. Tob Control 2001;10:337e9. <lb/>8. Chaloupka F, Cummings K, Morley C, et al. Tax, price and cigarette smoking: <lb/>evidence from the tobacco documents and implications for tobacco company <lb/>marketing strategies. Tob Control 2002;11(Supp 1):i62e72. <lb/>9. Pierce JP, Glimer TP, Lee L, et al. Tobacco industry price-subsidizing promotions <lb/>may overcome the downward pressure of higher prices on initiation of regular <lb/>smoking. Health Econ 2005;14:1061e71. <lb/>10. Givel MS, Glantz SA. Tobacco lobby political influence on US state legislatures in the <lb/>1990s. Tob Control 2001;10:124e34. <lb/>11. Rosenberg NJ, Siegel M. Use of corporate sponsorship as a tobacco marketing <lb/>tool: a review of tobacco industry sponsorship in the USA, 1995e99. Tob Control <lb/>2001;10:239e46. <lb/>12. Hastings G, Liberman J. Tobacco corporate social responsibility and fairy <lb/>godmothers: the Framework Convention on Tobacco Control slays a modern myth. <lb/>Tob Control 2009;18:73e4. <lb/>13. Tesler LE, Malone RE. Corporate philanthropy, lobbying and public health policy. Am <lb/>J Public Health 2008;98:2123e33. <lb/>14. Traynor MP, Begay ME, Glantz SA. New tobacco industry strategy to prevent local <lb/>tobacco control. JAMA 1993;270:479e86. <lb/>15. Yerger VB, Malone RE. African American leadership groups: smoking with the <lb/>enemy. Tob Control 2002;11:336e45. <lb/>16. Chapman S. Advocacy in action: extreme corporate makeover interruptus: <lb/>denormalising tobacco industry corporate schmoosing. Tob Control 2004; <lb/>13:445e7. <lb/>17. Dewhirst T, Hunter A. Tobacco sponsorship of Formula One and CART auto racing: <lb/>tobacco brand exposure and enhanced symbolic imagery through co-sponsors&apos; third <lb/>party advertising. Tob Control 2002;11:146e50. <lb/>18. Dewhirst T, Sparks R. Intertextuality, tobacco sponsorship of sports, and adolescent <lb/>male smoking culture: a selective review of tobacco industry documents. Journal of <lb/>Sport and Social Issues 2003;27:372e98. <lb/>19. Atiken PP, Leathar DS, Squair SI. Children&apos;s awareness of cigarette brand <lb/>sponsorship of sports and games in the UK. Health Educ Res 1986;1:203e11. <lb/>20. Ledwith F. Does tobacco sports sponsorship on television act as advertising to <lb/>children? Health Educ J 1984;43:85e8. <lb/>21. Sparks R. Youth awareness of tobacco sponsorship as a dimension of brand equity. <lb/>International Journal of Sports Marketing and Sponsorship 1999;1:236e60. <lb/>22. Hoek J, Gendall P, Stockdale M. Some effects of tobacco sponsorship <lb/>advertisements on young males. International Journal of Advertising 1993; <lb/>12:25e36. <lb/>23. Cornwell TB. State of the art and science in sponsorship-linked marketing. <lb/>Journal of Advertising 2008;37:41e55. <lb/>24. Biener L, Albers AB. Young adults: vulnerable new targets of tobacco marketing. <lb/>Am J Public Health 2004;94:326e30. <lb/>25. Chaloupka FJ. Written direct examination United States of American v. Philip <lb/>Morris. 99-CV-02496 (GK). United States District Court for the District of Columbia, <lb/>2004. http://www.usdoj.gov/civil/cases/tobacco2/Chaloupka%20Direct%20-%20final. <lb/>pdf (accessed Sep 2009). <lb/>26. Rigotti NA, Moran SE, Wechsler H. US college students&apos; exposure to tobacco <lb/>promotions: prevalence and association with tobacco use. Am J Public Health <lb/>2005;95:138e44. <lb/>27. Federal Trade Commission. Federal trade commission cigarette report for the year <lb/>2006. Washington DC: US Federal Trade Commission, 2009. http://www2.ftc.gov/ <lb/>os/2009/08/090812cigarettereport.pdf (accessed 11 Sep 2009). <lb/>28. Federal Trade Commission. Federal trade commission smokeless tobacco report <lb/>for the years 2006. Washington DC: US Federal Trade Commission, 2009. http:// <lb/>www2.ftc.gov/os/2009/08/090812smokelesstobaccoreport.pdf (accessed 11 Sep <lb/>2009). <lb/>29. Feighery EC, Ribisl KM, Clark PI, et al. How tobacco companies ensure placement of <lb/>their advertising and products in stores: interviews with retailers and tobacco <lb/>company incentive programmes. Tob Control 2003;12:184e8. <lb/>30. Loomis B, Farrelly M, Nonnemaker J, et al. Point of purchase cigarette promotions <lb/>before and after the master settlement agreement: exploring retail scanner data. <lb/>Tob Control 2006;15:140e2. <lb/>31. Wakefield M, Terry-McElrath YM, Chaloupka FJ, et al. Tobacco industry marketing <lb/>at point of purchase after the 1998 MSA billboard advertising ban. Am J Public <lb/>Health 2002;92:937e40. <lb/>32. Centers for Disease Control and Prevention, Media Campaign Resource Center, <lb/>2009. http://apps.nccd.cdc.gov/MCRC/Apps/QuickSearch.aspx (accessed Sep 2009). <lb/>33. California Department of Public Health. Grim reapers, 2009. http://www. <lb/>tobaccofreeca.com/ads_tv.html (accessed Apr 2009). <lb/>34. Anon. Operation Storefront Phase I Training: youth against tobacco advertising and <lb/>promotion. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health Services, Tobacco <lb/>Control Section and Stanford University, Stanford Center for Research in Disease <lb/>Prevention, 1994. <lb/>35. Anon. Operation Storefront phase II training: assessing community readiness. <lb/>Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health Services, Tobacco Control Section <lb/>and Stanford University, Stanford Center for Research in Disease Prevention, 1994. <lb/>36. Anon. Operation Storefront Phase III Training: youth against tobacco advertising and <lb/>promotion. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health Services, Tobacco <lb/>Control Section and Stanford University, Stanford Center for Research in Disease <lb/>Prevention, 1996. <lb/>37. Tencati E, Howard-Pitney B, Roeseler AG, et al. Operation Storefront: Five case <lb/>studies of phase III projects. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health <lb/>Services, Tobacco Control Section, 1996. <lb/>38. California Department of Health Services, Tobacco Control Section and <lb/>Stanford University, Stanford Center for Research in Disease Prevention. <lb/>Operation Storefront Phase IV: Taking the next step. California Department of Health <lb/>Services, Tobacco Control Section, 1996. <lb/>39. California Department of Health Services, California Tobacco Control <lb/>Section. Operation Storefront 1997: maximizing media coverage of your results. <lb/>California Department of Health Services, California Tobacco Control Section, 1997. <lb/>40. Belanger L, Kent S, Flynn P. Racing toolkit: helping motorsports get free of tobacco <lb/>sponsorship. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health Services, 2004. <lb/>41. Belanger L, Flynn P. Rodeo toolkit: for tobacco prevention advocates helping rodeos <lb/>become tobacco free. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health Services, <lb/>2001. <lb/>42. Belanger L, Flynn P. Tack and tools for rodeo organizers. Sacramento, CA: California <lb/>Department of Health Services, 2001. <lb/>43. California Department of Public Health. California Tobacco Control Program. <lb/>STORE Campaign website, 2002. http://www.tcsstore.org/ (accessed Sep 2009). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">What this paper adds <lb/>This paper illustrates the integration of tobacco industry moni-<lb/>toring with the implementation of mass media campaigns, policy <lb/>enactment and enforcement efforts. It provides a framework for <lb/>comprehensive tobacco control programmes in the United States <lb/>as they move to act upon the opportunities afforded by the 2009 <lb/>Family Smoking Prevention and Control Act. This federal legis-<lb/>lation implements a number of new tobacco marketing restric-<lb/>tions and provides new legal authority for state, local and tribal <lb/>governments to restrict the time, place and manner of cigarette <lb/>advertising for public health purposes. Additionally, this paper <lb/>highlights areas of continued concern regarding marketing prac-<lb/>tices at events and in the retail environment. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<page>i27 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>44. Rogers T, Feighery EC, Tenacti EM, et al. Community mobilization to reduce point of <lb/>purchase advertising of tobacco products. Health Educ Q 1995;22:427e42. <lb/>45. American Nonsmokers&apos; Rights Foundation. Ordinances Restricting Tobacco <lb/>Advertising, 2001 Dec 10. http://www.nsmoke.org. <lb/>46. University of Southern California Tobacco Industry Monitoring Evaluation. <lb/>Project SMART Money: The local policies index: policies to keep California <lb/>organizations, businesses and events tobacco free. Los Angeles, California, USA: <lb/>University of Southern California, TIME Project, 2004. <lb/>47. Buck Tobacco Sponsorship. Policies restricting tobacco sponsorship at rodeos in <lb/>California, 2009. http://www.bucktobacco.org/policy/index.html (accessed Nov 2009). <lb/>48. California Youth Advocacy Network. College advertising and marketing policies. <lb/>Sep 2009. http://www.cyanonline.org (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>49. State of California. California Health and Safety Code Section118950, 2008. http:// <lb/>www.leginfo.ca.gov/cgi-bin/waisgate?WAISdocID¼73730216050+0+0 <lb/>+0&amp;WAISaction¼retrieve (accessed Sep 2009). <lb/>50. Americans for Nonsmokers&apos; Rights Foundation. California municipalities with <lb/>sampling laws. 2009 Jul 6. http://bucktobacco.org/policy/SamplingLaws-CA-2009-<lb/>10-02.pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>51. Chico Municipal Code Chapter 9.18. Nonsale distribution of smokeless tobacco <lb/>or cigarettes, 2008. http://www.chico.ca.us/document_library/municode/Title_9.pdf <lb/>(accessed Apr 2009). <lb/>52. American Lung Association of California Center for Tobacco Policy and <lb/>Organizing. Prohibiting sample of tobacco products through a local ordinance, <lb/>Jul 2009. http://www.center4tobaccopolicy.org/_files/_files/Prohibiting%20Sampling <lb/>%20of%20Tobacco%20Products%20through%20a%20Local%20Ordinance.pdf <lb/>(accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>53. Brantley S. Final evaluation report-American Lung Association of California: City of <lb/>Chico Tobacco Distribution Policy. Chico, CA: American Lung Association of California, <lb/>2009. <lb/>54. Americans for Nonsmokers Rights&apos; Foundation. California municipalities with <lb/>laws restricting youth access to tobacco products, 2009 Jul 1. http://www.phlpnet. <lb/>org/tobacco-control/products/anrf-list-communities-licensing-and-self-service-<lb/>display-ordinances (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>55. California Department of Public Health. California tobacco control program. <lb/>California tobacco control update 2009: 20 years of tobacco control in California: <lb/>Sacramento, CA: California Department of Public Health, 2009. http://www.cdph.ca. <lb/>gov/programs/tobacco/Documents/CTCPUpdate2009.pdf (accessed 15 Sep 2009). <lb/>56. State of California. Senate Bill 1766, Chapter 686, 2001. http://www.leginfo.ca. <lb/>gov/pub/01-02/bill/sen/sb_1751-1800/sb_1766_bill_20020918_chaptered.pdf <lb/>(accessed 16 Sept 2009). <lb/>57. State of California. Senate Bill 1173, Chapter 812, 2004. http://www.leginfo.ca. <lb/>gov/pub/03-04/bill/sen/sb_1151-1200/sb_1173_bill_20040927_chaptered.pdf <lb/>(accessed 16 Sep 2009). <lb/>58. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney General&apos;s Office enters into <lb/>settlement agreement with RJ Reynolds concerning activities at brand name <lb/>sponsorship events, announcement, May 2000. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/1bns. <lb/>pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>59. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Settlement agreement between the <lb/>Attorney General&apos;s Office and RJ Reynolds Tobacco Company, May 2000. http://ag. <lb/>ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/bns_ag3.pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>60. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney general reaches settlement <lb/>agreement with United States Tobacco Company over alleged advertisement <lb/>violations. press release, 2000 Dec 6. http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/release.php? <lb/>id¼760 (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>61. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Settlement agreement between California <lb/>Attorney General&apos;s Office and US Tobacco Company smokeless tobacco <lb/>advertisements, 2001 Nov. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/chewsett.pdf (accessed 12 <lb/>Sep 2009). <lb/>62. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney General Lockyer announces <lb/>settlement of free tobacco samples lawsuit, press release, 2001 Jul 13. http://ag.ca. <lb/>gov/newsalerts/release.php?id¼1322 (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>63. People of the State of California ex rel. Bill Lockyer, Attorney General of the <lb/>State of California v. Swedish Match North America Inc. free smokeless tobacco <lb/>sampling on public property in California stipulation for order and order for entry of <lb/>final judgment and permanent injunction signed by Judge Robert B. Yonts Jr. on <lb/>2001 Jun 21. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/Swedish_Match.pdf (accessed 12 Sep <lb/>2009). <lb/>64. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. US Smokeless Tobacco Company <lb/>agreement relating to brand name sponsorship: memorandum of understanding <lb/>concerning adult-only facilities. 2002 Jul 31. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/ <lb/>UST_MOU.pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>65. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney General Lockyer settles lawsuit <lb/>over illegal distribution of smokeless tobacco products, press release, 2002 Oct 17. <lb/>http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/release.php?id¼1005 (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>66. Stipulation for order and proposed order for entry of a final judgment and permanent <lb/>injunction. Superior Court, 2002 Oct 17. http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/cms02/02-120. <lb/>pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>67. People of the State of California v. RJ Reynolds Tobacco Company. 107 Cal. <lb/>App 4th 516, 132 Cal. Rptr 2d. 151, 2003. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/decision.pdf <lb/>(accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>68. People of the State of California ex rel. Attorney General Bill Lockyer v. RJ <lb/>Reynolds Tobacco Company stipulation for order and order for entry of final judgment <lb/>signed by Judge Ronald S. Prager, 2004 Mar 23. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/ <lb/>StipOrder.pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>69. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney General Lockyer announces $5 <lb/>million settlement with RJ Reynolds to resolve lawsuit over firm&apos;s distribution of free <lb/>cigarettes, press release, 2006 May 8. http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/release.php? <lb/>id¼1301. (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>70. People for the State of California, ex rel Bill Lockyer, v. RJ Reynolds <lb/>Tobacco Company signed by Dennis Eckhart, Esq, State of California, Department <lb/>of Justice and H. Joseph Escher II, Attorney for RJ Reynolds Tobacco Company. <lb/>2006 Mar 22. http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/cms06/06-048_0a.pdf (accessed <lb/>12 Sep 2009). <lb/>71. People for the State of California, ex rel Bill Lockyer, Attorney General v. US <lb/>Smokeless Tobacco Company stipulation for entry of judgment and final judgment <lb/>singed by Judge Ronald S. Prager. 2007 Aug 20. http://ag.ca.gov/tobacco/pdf/usstc. <lb/>pdf (accessed 12 Sep 2009). <lb/>72. California Attorney General&apos;s Office. Attorney General Lockyer announces <lb/>agreement with 7-Eleven to curb tobacco sales to minors, press release, 2005 <lb/>Aug 11. http://ag.ca.gov/newsalerts/release.php?id¼1188 (accessed 12 Sep <lb/>2009). <lb/>73. Unger JB, Cruz TB, Feighery EC. Tobacco advertising in retail outlets in <lb/>California, 2000e2004. Sacramento, CA: California Department of Health <lb/>Services, Tobacco Control Section, 2007. http://www.tcsrover.org/catalog/files/ <lb/>CTCPAdvertisingRetailOutletsCA.pdf (accessed 23 Sep 2009). <lb/>74. California Department of Justice. Biennial report, major activities 2007e2008. <lb/>Sacramento, CA: California Department of Justice, 2008. http://ag.ca.gov/ <lb/>publications/biennial_report_07-08.pdf#xml¼http://search.doj.ca.gov:8004/ <lb/>AGSearch/isysquery/0782d7a1-77b4-4b3e-bac0-9906296bcbfc/5/hilite/ (accessed <lb/>24 Oct 2009). <lb/>75. Feighery EC, Schleicher NC, Cruz BT, et al. An examination of trends in amount and <lb/>type of cigarette advertising and sales promotions in California stores, 2002e2005. <lb/>Tob Control 2008;17:93e8. <lb/>76. Wayland S, Induni M, Davis B. California adult tobacco survey SAS dataset <lb/>documentation and technical report: 1993e2007. Survey Research Group, Cancer <lb/>Surveillance and Research Branch, California Department of Public Health, 2008. Report: <lb/>http://www.surveyresearchgroup.org/sub.php?page¼projects_adult_tobacco <lb/>(accessed 2 Oct 2008). <lb/>77. Al-Delaimy WK, Messer K, Pierce JP, et al. Technical report on analytic methods and <lb/>approaches use in the 2005 California Tobacco Survey Analysis. Vol 1: data collection <lb/>methodology. La Jolla, CA: University of California, San Diego, 2007. http://libraries. <lb/>ucsd.edu/ssds/pub/CTS/cpc00008/2005%20Final%20TECH%20Report-Vol.%201.pdf <lb/>(accessed 2 Oct 2008). <lb/>78. McCarthy WJ, Dietsch BJ, Dent C, et al. Evaluation of the In-School Tobacco Use <lb/>Prevention Education Program, 2005-2006: technical findings and documentation. <lb/>Sacramento, CA, USA: California Department of Public Health, California Tobacco <lb/>Control Program, 2007. <lb/>79. California Adult Tobacco Survey (CATS), California Department of Public <lb/>Health. Sacramento, CA, 2007. <lb/>80. C-STATS. Percent of youth who see advertisements for cigarettes or chewing <lb/>tobacco sometimes or a lot when they go to sports events, fairs, or community <lb/>events. California Student Tobacco Survey, 2002e2006. 2006. http://www.cstats. <lb/>info/index.cfm?fuseaction¼reports.html_GenericSW&amp;deID¼80&amp;ttID¼11&amp; <lb/>deTableName¼tblMEY_1_SW&amp;areaID¼1&amp;yearID¼44,46,48&amp;format¼1&amp;CrossTab¼ <lb/>&amp;location¼1&amp;SWType¼GenericSW&amp;yaID¼1&amp;CFID¼67572&amp;CFTOKEN¼ <lb/>d410ea646a406260-41B2BE73-1143-D8D6-116A94E2F5172DF6 (accessed Apr <lb/>2009). <lb/>81. Al-Delaimy WF, White MM, Trinidad DR, et al. The California tobacco control <lb/>program: can we maintain the progress? Results from the California Tobacco Survey, <lb/>1990-2005. vol 2. La Jolla, CA: University of California San Diego, 2008. <lb/>82. H.R. 1256 Family Smoking Prevention and Control Act, 2009. http://thomas.loc.gov/ <lb/>cgi-bin/query/D?c111:6:./temp/wc111ar39Kr (accessed Sep 2009). <lb/>83. Katz SK, Lavack AM. Tobacco related bar promotions: insights from tobacco <lb/>industry documents. Tob Control 2002;11(Suppl 1):i92e101. <lb/>84. Lewis MJ, Delnevo CD, Slade J. Tobacco industry direct mail marketing and <lb/>participation by New Jersey Adults. Am J Public Health 2004:94:257e9. <lb/>85. Saffer H, Chaloupka F. The effect of tobacco advertising bans on tobacco <lb/>consumption. J Health Econ 2000;19:1117e37. Review. <lb/>86. Jha P, Chaloupka FJ, Corrao M, et al. Reducing the burden of smoking world-wide: <lb/>effectiveness of interventions and their coverage. Drug Alcohol Rev <lb/>2006;25:597e609. <lb/>87. Quentin W, Neubauer S, Leidl R, et al. Advertising bans as a means of tobacco <lb/>policy: a systemic literature review of time-series analyses. Int J Public Health <lb/>2007;52:295e307. <lb/>88. Blecher E. The impact of tobacco advertising bans on consumption in developing <lb/>countries. J Health Econ 2008;27:930e42. <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>i28 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">APPENDIX 1 <lb/>Highlights of California Attorney General Enforcement Actions <lb/>Tobacco company <lb/>or association <lb/>Enforcement action <lb/>Outcome <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2000 <lb/>Violated MSA outdoor signage advertising provisions at sponsored events <lb/>and restrictions on free tobacco product distribution at the Winston Cup <lb/>National Association Stock Car Racing and National Hot Road Association <lb/>Drag Racing series <lb/>&lt; Settlement agreement <lb/>&lt; $30000 payment for investigative costs <lb/>&lt; Established restrictions and standards for placement of advertising <lb/>at events <lb/>&lt; Established requirements to enclose booths where free tobacco product <lb/>sampling was occurring to prevent youth exposure <lb/>USST 2000 <lb/>Violated California Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits <lb/>non-sale distribution of coupons for smokeless tobacco on public grounds) <lb/>with its placement of an Ultimate Playboy Weekend sweepstake contest <lb/>advertisement in the San Diego State University student newspaper <lb/>The Daily Aztec, which included a $1.00-off coupon for Rooster <lb/>smokeless tobacco <lb/>&lt; Settlement Agreement <lb/>&lt; $150000 payment to Rogers &amp; Associates to create and place an <lb/>alternative advertisement and to pay for investigative fees and <lb/>other damages <lb/>Swedish Match 2001 Violated California Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits <lb/>non-sale distribution of smokeless tobacco on public grounds) at the <lb/>Watsonville Speedway and the California Mid-State Fair in Paso Robles <lb/>&lt; Stipulated court judgment <lb/>&lt; $375000 payment to the Public Health Institute to monitor tobacco <lb/>advertising and promotions and raise awareness about tobacco use <lb/>&lt; $10200 payment for investigative costs <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2001 <lb/>Violated MSA provisions related to restrictions of free tobacco product <lb/>sampling with its nationwide programme that involved distributing massive <lb/>quantities of free cigarettes through the mail to individuals&apos; homes <lb/>&lt; Court approved settlement <lb/>&lt; $175000 payment to California and Arizona for investigative costs and <lb/>attorney fees <lb/>&lt; Established: requirements for written consent to receive samples for <lb/>evaluation purposes; placed limits on the number of packs sent and the <lb/>size of mail containers; and reporting requirements describing the <lb/>number of packs distributed in the state <lb/>USST 2002 <lb/>Violated STMSA provisions related to adult-only facilities where free <lb/>tobacco product sampling occurred and brand name advertising at <lb/>these facilities <lb/>&lt; Multi-state memorandum of understanding <lb/>&lt; Requirements for enclosing booths where free tobacco product <lb/>sampling was occurring to prevent youth exposure <lb/>&lt; Established requirements on the use of brand name advertisements at <lb/>facilities where free tobacco product sampling was occurring <lb/>USST 2002 <lb/>Violated Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits non-sale <lb/>distribution of smokeless tobacco on public grounds) at Wild West <lb/>Stampede in Auburn and Livermore Rodeo in Livermore <lb/>&lt; Stipulated court judgment <lb/>&lt; $150000 payment to the Public Health Institute for tobacco use <lb/>prevention and cessation education related to tobacco products and <lb/>tobacco brand name sponsorships <lb/>&lt; $21000 for investigation costs <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2003 <lb/>Violated MSA outdoor signage restrictions at the National Association for <lb/>Stock Car Auto Racing Winston Cup Series at Sears Point Raceway and <lb/>other auto race tracks <lb/>&lt; Court of Appeal decision <lb/>&lt; Established restrictions to prohibit the placement of event signage more <lb/>than 90 days before and 10 days after an event <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2004 <lb/>Violated California Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits non-<lb/>sale distribution of cigarettes on public grounds) by distributing free tobacco <lb/>products outside of bars on the sidewalks of San Francisco <lb/>&lt; Superior Court decision <lb/>&lt; $60000 payment to the Public Health Foundation Enterprises for youth <lb/>and young adult tobacco control advocacy efforts <lb/>&lt; $35000 for investigative costs <lb/>&lt; Required RJ Reynolds to notify the California Attorney General&apos;s Office <lb/>of the site and date of planned bar promotions in the month prior to the <lb/>sampling activity (through December 2005) <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2005 <lb/>Violated provisions of the MSA related to placement of advertisements in <lb/>national magazines with a large youth readership <lb/>&lt; Stipulated court judgment (following successful appeal of permanent <lb/>injunction and reversal of $20 million penalty) <lb/>&lt; $11.4 million in penalties <lb/>&lt; $5.8 million in attorneys fees and costs <lb/>&lt; Placed restrictions on the total gross number of impressions viewable <lb/>by youth in youth-measured publications <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2006 <lb/>Violated California Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits non-<lb/>sale distribution of cigarettes on public grounds) that occurred at six public <lb/>events including the Pomona Raceway <lb/>&lt; Superior Court decision <lb/>&lt; $5 million payment <lb/>-$3.1 million civil penalties <lb/>-$900000 attorney fees and costs <lb/>-$1 million to Public Health Institute for training and education related to <lb/>tobacco product promotion <lb/>USST 2007 <lb/>MSA violations related to a Skoal promotion at Hot Rod Association Drag <lb/>Racing events where minors were allowed to compete <lb/>&lt; Superior Court decision <lb/>&lt; Required the Hot Rod Association to adopt a rule that prohibited youths <lb/>under the age of 18 from participating in its drag racing events <lb/>&lt; $1.5 million payment in attorney fees and other costs <lb/>USST 2009 <lb/>Violated STMSA provisions that restrict brand name sponsorship which <lb/>occurred at Professional Bull Riders events <lb/>&lt; Stipulated court judgment <lb/>&lt; Limited brand name sponsorship to events in a single national series <lb/>of events <lb/>&lt; Permitted no more than three riders on a sponsored team <lb/>USST 2009 <lb/>Violated California Health and Safety Code Section 118950 (prohibits non-<lb/>sale distribution of coupons for smokeless tobacco on public grounds) that <lb/>occurred at Pomona Raceway <lb/>&lt; $150000 payment to the Public Health Institute for tobacco use <lb/>prevention and cessation education related to products and tobacco <lb/>brand name sponsorships <lb/>RJ Reynolds 2009 <lb/>Violated MSA provision related to the use of cartoons to advertise or <lb/>promote cigarettes <lb/>&lt; Court judgment <lb/>&lt; Declaration that some images in Camel the Farm promotion were <lb/>prohibited cartoons <lb/>&lt; State entitled to attorneys fees (amount to be determined; case <lb/>still pending) <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Tobacco Control 2010;19(Suppl 1):i21ei29. doi:10.1136/tc.2009.031963 <lb/></note>

			<page>i29 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Research paper </note>


	</text>
</tei>
