<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Cogent Business &amp; Management <lb/>ISSN: (Print) (Online) Journal homepage: www.tandfonline.com/journals/oabm20 <lb/>The role of value co-creation in building trust and <lb/>reputation in the digital banking era <lb/>Marcelo Royo-Vela, Moreno Frau &amp; Alberto Ferrer <lb/>To cite this article: Marcelo Royo-Vela, Moreno Frau &amp; Alberto Ferrer (2024) The role of value <lb/>co-creation in building trust and reputation in the digital banking era, Cogent Business &amp; <lb/>Management, 11:1, 2375405, DOI: 10.1080/23311975.2024.2375405 <lb/>To link to this article: https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2024.2375405 <lb/>© 2024 The Author(s). Published by Informa <lb/>UK Limited, trading as Taylor &amp; Francis <lb/>Group <lb/>Published online: 12 Jul 2024. <lb/>Submit your article to this journal <lb/>Article views: 1959 <lb/>View related articles <lb/>View Crossmark data <lb/>Citing articles: 3 View citing articles <lb/>Full Terms &amp; Conditions of access and use can be found at <lb/>https://www.tandfonline.com/action/journalInformation?journalCode=oabm20 <lb/>Marketing | research article <lb/>Cogent Business &amp; ManageMent <lb/>2024, VoL. 11, no. 1, 2375405 <lb/>The role of value co-creation in building trust and reputation in the <lb/>digital banking era <lb/>Marcelo royo-Vela a , Moreno Frau b <lb/>and alberto Ferrer a <lb/>a <lb/>Department of Commercialization and Market Research, university of Valencia, Valencia, spain; b institute of Marketing and <lb/>Communication sciences, Department of Marketing Management, Corvinus university of Budapest, Budapest, Hungary <lb/>ABSTRACT <lb/>this study investigates how customers co-create value in online banking. the aims of <lb/>this study were twofold. First, it tests the Dart model (dialogue, access, risk assessment, <lb/>and transparency) as a driver of customer value co-creation. second, this study <lb/>investigates trust and reputation as the outcomes of value co-creation in online <lb/>banking. exploratory factor analysis was used by applying a Principal components <lb/>analysis with sPss and sMart Pls to check the model and the relationship between <lb/>the factors of the Dart model, value co-creation, company reputation, and customer <lb/>trust. Data were collected through a questionnaire sent to 217 online bank customers. <lb/>the findings show that strategic value co-creation is influenced by dialogue, access to <lb/>information, risk assessment, and transparency. the results also show that customer <lb/>value co-creation can result in greater reputation and trust. this study contributes to <lb/>the literature in two ways. First, this study extends the marketing literature by showing <lb/>that value co-creation can generate reputation and trust as an outcome, changing the <lb/>perspective in which the phenomenon is traditionally observed. second, the study tests <lb/>the Dart model in the online banking industry, showing that the original model also <lb/>works for bank customers. this study provides managerial guidelines for each variable <lb/>of the Drat model. <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Online banking allows customers to conduct more financial operations without going to physical <lb/>branches. customers play a more significant role in developing innovations (thomke &amp; hippel, 2002). <lb/>they have skills equal to those of the company&apos;s internal teams (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). <lb/>Moreover, customers can provide resources beyond purchases and financial contributions, such as knowl-<lb/>edge (harmeling et al., 2017). this makes the customer a pivotal actor in the online banking sector that <lb/>must be involved in the strategic process of value co-creation (agrawal &amp; rahman, 2015). Value co-creation <lb/>centres on active customer interaction with the company (Vargo &amp; lusch, 2008, 2011, 2016). this collab-<lb/>orative interaction creates value by integrating resources, such as customer knowledge and company <lb/>experience, leading to better products and services that are adjusted to customers&apos; needs (Prahalad &amp; <lb/>ramaswamy, 2004a). <lb/>however, the dematerialized world of the internet could still be a scary place for customers, especially <lb/>regarding people&apos;s savings and financial resources. therefore, studying value co-creation and its relation-<lb/>ships with customer trust and the company&apos;s reputation in an online bank environment is essential for <lb/>several reasons. this may empower banks to build stronger customer relationships, differentiate them-<lb/>selves in a competitive market, and ensure long-term success. Focusing on customer trust is the founda-<lb/>tion of any successful banking relationship, particularly in an online setting where customers may be <lb/></body>

			<front>© 2024 the author(s). Published by informa uK Limited, trading as taylor &amp; Francis group <lb/>CONTACT Moreno Frau <lb/>moreno.frau@uni-corvinus.hu <lb/>institute of Marketing and Communication sciences, Department of Marketing <lb/>Management, Corvinus university of Budapest, Fővám tér 8, Budapest, 1093, Hungary <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2024.2375405 <lb/>this is an open access article distributed under the terms of the Creative Commons attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/4.0/), which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly cited. the terms on which this article has been <lb/>published allow the posting of the accepted Manuscript in a repository by the author(s) or with their consent. <lb/>ARTICLE HISTORY <lb/>received 10 april 2024 <lb/>revised 24 June 2024 <lb/>accepted 27 June 2024 <lb/>KEYWORDS <lb/>strategic value <lb/>co-creation; online <lb/>banking; Dart model; <lb/>trust; reputation <lb/>REVIEWING EDITOR <lb/>kaouther kooli, <lb/>Bournemouth University, <lb/>United kingdom of great <lb/>Britain and northern <lb/>ireland <lb/>SUBJECTS <lb/>services Marketing; <lb/>Banking; Marketing <lb/></front>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>concerned about security and privacy. Value co-creation fosters customer participation, collaboration, and <lb/>resource sharing, all contributing to trust-building between customers and banks. Further, a bank&apos;s rep-<lb/>utation is a crucial asset in the financial industry. Banks can enhance their reputation through value <lb/>co-creation by showcasing their commitment to customer satisfaction, innovation, and responsiveness to <lb/>customer needs (Oklevik et al., 2024). <lb/>although previous studies have the merit of increasing our knowledge of how customer value <lb/>co-creation occurs (kucharska, 2017; syah &amp; Olivia, 2022), also in online banking (aldás et al., 2009), <lb/>showing how customers&apos; trust in online settings and banks&apos; reputation may be pivotal in customer-bank <lb/>relations as a prerequisite for strategic value co-creation (Dhaigude et al., 2023; Mccormack &amp; Deacon, <lb/>2017), only a few studies focus on customers&apos; trust and company reputation as consequences of the <lb/>value co-creation process. <lb/>trust and company reputation have traditionally been viewed as antecedents that positively influence <lb/>customer value co-creation (Mostafa, 2020). additionally, some studies have explored the mediating role <lb/>of trust in the context of privacy risk and value co-creation (Wang et al., 2020). however, our research <lb/>shifts this perspective by demonstrating that effective value co-creation can enhance reputation and <lb/>trust. this, in turn, enables banks to adopt a customer-centric approach, offering tailored solutions and <lb/>fostering long-term relationships grounded in shared values and customer satisfaction (Oklevik et al., 2024). <lb/>We propose that customers&apos; trust and company reputation should be recognized as direct outcomes <lb/>of successful value co-creation strategies in the online banking environment. By embracing this innova-<lb/>tive perspective, our study addresses a critical gap in the literature. By conceptualizing Dart elements <lb/>as drivers, we investigate how these components directly influence trust and company reputation, both <lb/>essential for strategic success in the online banking sector. this novel approach aligns with the Dart <lb/>model&apos;s core principles and provides fresh insights into the intricate relationship between value co-creation <lb/>and its outcomes. <lb/>the aims of this study were twofold. First, it tests the Dart model (dialogue, access, risk assessment, <lb/>and transparency) as a driver of customer value co-creation (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). second, <lb/>this study investigates trust and reputation as the outcomes of value co-creation in online banking. <lb/>consequently, this study addresses the following research questions: (1) is the effect of dialogue, access, <lb/>risk assessment, and transparency on customer value co-creation significant in the banking industry? (2) <lb/>how is value co-creation related to customer trust and bank reputation? <lb/>this study uses exploratory factor analysis applying a Principal components analysis and sPss version <lb/>28 and sMart Pls version 4 software to check the model and evaluate the relationship between the <lb/>factors of the Dart model, value co-creation, company reputation, and customer trust. to do so, data <lb/>were collected through a survey, resulting in 217 valid questionnaires from online bank customers. thus, <lb/>this study makes two contributions. First, it tests the Dart model in the online banking industry and <lb/>shows that the original model also works in the banking industry. second, this study extends the mar-<lb/>keting literature by showing that value co-creation can generate reputation and trust as an outcome. <lb/>the remainder of this paper is organized as follows. First, a theoretical framework is presented in the <lb/>following sections, and the research hypotheses are developed. subsequently, this paper introduces the <lb/>model&apos;s empirical research methodology, measures, and tests. Finally, the results are presented and dis-<lb/>cussed, along with the theoretical and managerial implications, research limitations, and suggestions for <lb/>future research. <lb/>2. Theoretical background <lb/>2.1. Strategic value co-creation in the bank industry <lb/>the value creation process considers the joint efforts of actors in the dyad, actors benefiting themselves <lb/>while interacting and collaborating in the strategic process of value co-creation (Vargo &amp; lusch, 2008, <lb/>2011, 2016). the numerous interactions and outcomes of these activities can have a widespread impact <lb/>on the evolution of business strategies (gadde &amp; håkansson, 2011) because of the participatory role of <lb/>customers collaborating as innovators (amegbe et al., 2023; ramaswamy &amp; Ozcan, 2018). this practice <lb/>continues to develop, particularly with new interactive and information technologies. the nature of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>digital interactions, dynamic, synchronous, and changing, calls for special attention to co-creational activ-<lb/>ities and their measurement (royo-Vela &amp; Mariell Velasquez serrano, 2021). Value creation is based on <lb/>interaction, and value co-creation is defined as joint activities by actors involved in direct dyadic inter-<lb/>actions (grönroos &amp; ravald, 2011). this interaction among actors generates strategic experiences for <lb/>value creation (ramaswamy, 2008; suryadi et al., 2023). thus, customers can actively participate in both <lb/>service or product shaping and the perception and creation of value and experience based on the inter-<lb/>action (Vargo &amp; lusch, 2011). <lb/>thus, value creation has changed from a linear process across supply chains to value co-creation, in <lb/>which network actors interact and share resources assisted by digital and interactive technologies <lb/>(royo-Vela &amp; Mariell Velasquez serrano, 2021). Digital technologies like it platforms and mobile apps <lb/>allow banks to integrate complementary resources and capabilities and collaborate with customers to <lb/>co-create value (Mefoute Badiang &amp; nkwei, 2024). however, many banks aim for innovation as a strategic <lb/>outcome of value co-creation, as they lack innovative capabilities or tools (Ferguson &amp; hlavinka, 2007). <lb/>thus, banks must tap into customer creativity and objectivity (Yoo et al., 2010). accordingly, direct <lb/>bank-customer interaction is needed to strategically co-create value (andreu et al., 2010). additionally, <lb/>banks must implement a customer relationship approach to support strategic value co-creation (Payne <lb/>et al., 2008). <lb/>the banking industry uses advanced technology to provide consumers access to products and ser-<lb/>vices (Malar et al., 2019). the rise of digital technologies, such as virtual environments, has enabled banks <lb/>to have a closer and quicker relationship with their customers, making physical interactions obsolete <lb/>(Martovoy &amp; santos, 2012; royo-Vela et al., 2022). Besides technologies, market orientation helps banks <lb/>become closer to their customers (ind &amp; coates, 2013). hence, customers are invited to contribute toward <lb/>satisfying their needs. consequently, the relationship between banks and their customers is active, with <lb/>consumers perceiving usefulness when using the provider&apos;s services (grönroos, 2011). such dynamics <lb/>animate new customer needs and demands (hosseini et al., 2022). <lb/>Furthermore, customers&apos; expectations grow as much as effortlessly accessing the product and service <lb/>information offered by the internet. therefore, another market segment might easily detect an innova-<lb/>tion available in a small market segment (Mainardes et al., 2017). another aspect of online banking is <lb/>accessibility to consumers, as depicted by the constant sharing of ideas and value co-creation of new <lb/>tailor-made services strategically created from customers&apos; needs (akter et al., 2020; Oliveira &amp; Von <lb/>hippel, 2011). <lb/>When it comes to the advantages that strategic value co-creation brings to both consumers and <lb/>banks, direct interaction with the bank has a stronger relationship with customers, which, in turn, posi-<lb/>tively affects the bank&apos;s economic performance (e.g. operating cost reduction and higher return of invest-<lb/>ment) (Mainardes et al., 2017). in addition to financial performance, direct customer interaction has <lb/>fostered responsiveness to market changes in the banking industry. From the customer perspective, their <lb/>strategic involvement in the value co-creation process brings numerous benefits, such as lower bank <lb/>account charges, more accessible access to credit, and quicker customer care service (Jain &amp; Jain, 2015). <lb/>2.2. The DART model and the role of reputation and customer trust <lb/>When theorizing the Dart model, Prahalad and ramaswamy (2004a) focused on the features of strategic <lb/>value co-creation and identified four variables: dialogue, which implies interactivity between the parties; <lb/>access, which promotes dialogue; risk assessment based on firm-customer pairing when deciding to <lb/>co-create; and transparency so that the information between the involved actors is symmetrical. Prahalad <lb/>and ramaswamy (2004a) highlight the necessity and importance of employing the Dart model for cus-<lb/>tomer strategic value co-creation, including elements characterizing firm-customer collaborative work. <lb/>the Dart model has been used in several sectors and settings. For example, using the Dart model, <lb/>russo spena et al. (2012) detected an intense exchange of information between customers and compa-<lb/>nies in the pop-up retail industry in italy. ramaswamy (2008) showed how nike sustained its competitive <lb/>advantages through a value co-creation strategy based on customers&apos; ideas to improve products and <lb/>their feelings when using them. several studies have tested the effectiveness of the Dart model. For <lb/>instance, albinsson et al. (2016) formulated 23 items to measure Dart variables of strategic value <lb/></body>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>co-creation. these scholars surveyed 327 participants in two Us business schools and found a statistical <lb/>correlation. Finally, Mazur and Zaborek (2014) tested the Dart model on 30 indicators with 440 mid-level <lb/>managers from various companies (e.g. food and beverage, cosmetics manufacturing, hotels and accom-<lb/>modation, catering, and other tourism services). nevertheless, to our knowledge, studies have not yet <lb/>tested the Dart model in online banking (Banik &amp; rabbanee, 2023). <lb/>Moreover, this study included reputation and trust to understand how they relate to the Dart model. <lb/>this study also aims to verify whether reputation and trust are the outcomes of customer value <lb/>co-creation in online banking. this study included reputation because it generates online endorsers <lb/>(Madden &amp; smith, 2010). however, few studies have directly related to co-creation and reputation. <lb/>Moreover, previous studies have neglected that reputation may occur due to value co-creation, leaving <lb/>a gap in the literature. For example, in Oreg and nov (2008) study, reputation motivates customers to <lb/>participate in strategic value co-creation because it increases people&apos;s desire to create notoriety and, <lb/>thereby, obtain the approval of others. in addition, a good reputation favours stakeholder engagement, <lb/>which is critical for customer value co-creation (abror et al., 2023; Dandis et al., 2021; nguyen et al., <lb/>2022). in particular, Oklevik et al. (2024) explored the intricate relationships between co-creation ele-<lb/>ments and customer engagement within various service industries, including banking. their study <lb/>emphasized the significance of the Dart model as a fundamental component driving brand experience <lb/>strength and satisfaction. <lb/>customer trust is another factor traditionally studied as an antecedent of value co-creation (Dhaigude <lb/>et al., 2023; Mccormack &amp; Deacon, 2017). For instance, Pavlou (2003) considered trust a fundamental <lb/>pillar of consumer behaviour in physical and online purchases. trust in the internet channel includes <lb/>specific attributes between firms and customers, such as perceived benevolence, capacity, competence, <lb/>honesty, integrity, credibility, predictability, and reliability, and other characteristics specific to the online <lb/>environment, such as security and privacy (grabner-kräuter &amp; Faullant, 2008). consequently, trust is <lb/>essential in online banking because risk perception is higher online than offline (cheung &amp; lee, 2001). <lb/>Furthermore, with internet banking, customers&apos; trust does not physically see the product or the person <lb/>carrying out the transactions. thus, generating trust in online users is vital as there is no personal con-<lb/>tact (Flavián &amp; guinalíu, 2005; lee, 2002). in addition, trust pushes internet users to recommend online <lb/>services, which turns trust into a viral marketing tool (li &amp; chen, 2009). therefore, trust leads to long-term <lb/>relationships because of emotional bonds (Frau et al., 2023a, 2023b). in conclusion, there is broad con-<lb/>sensus in the literature regarding the importance of trust in the value co-creation process. What is still <lb/>under discussion is whether trust is a consequence of value co-creation. <lb/>3. Research framework and hypotheses <lb/>a key variable explaining customer value co-creation is dialogue, which Prahalad and ramaswamy <lb/>(2004b, p.6) define as &quot;interactivity, engagement, and propensity to act -on both sides […] it implies <lb/>shared learning and communication between two equal problem solvers.&quot; Dialogue facilitates a two-way <lb/>interaction where firms and customers engage in mutual problem-solving and value creation. hoyer <lb/>et al. (2010) emphasize that dialogue is crucial for creating value and driving innovation. When custom-<lb/>ers are given a voice in the value co-creation strategy, they are more likely to contribute ideas and <lb/>feedback that enhance the value proposition (Vargo &amp; lusch, 2008). this participatory approach ensures <lb/>that the solutions developed are closely aligned with customer needs and preferences, leading to higher <lb/>perceived value. Moreover, dialogue fosters a sense of customer ownership and involvement, which is <lb/>essential for value co-creation. Beckers et al. (2018) suggest that when customers feel heard and valued, <lb/>they are more likely to engage in positive actions on social networks, enhancing brand equity and share-<lb/>holder value. this engagement is critical in social media, where customer interactions can significantly <lb/>influence public perception and brand reputation. While Frau et al. (2018) acknowledge that interacting <lb/>with customers and other stakeholders might sometimes decrease perceived value due to potential con-<lb/>flicts or misunderstandings, the overall impact of effective dialogue is positive. the Dart model identi-<lb/>fies dialogue as a fundamental element linking consumers to firms, emphasizing that meaningful <lb/>interactions can lead to better mutual understanding and collaboration (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). <lb/>Furthermore, effective dialogue helps build trust and long-term relationships, which are critical <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>components of value co-creation. When companies actively listen to and act on customer feedback, they <lb/>demonstrate commitment and responsiveness, enhancing trust and fostering loyalty (Prahalad &amp; <lb/>ramaswamy, 2004a). this continuous feedback loop not only improves the immediate value co-creation <lb/>outcomes but also strengthens the foundation for ongoing collaboration and value enhancement. <lb/>therefore, we propose the following hypothesis: <lb/>H1: Dialogue positively influences the value co-created by customers. <lb/>the second variable considered in this research model is access, which has been conceptualized as <lb/>the ability of the value co-creation parties to obtain and use &quot;information and tools&quot; (Prahalad &amp; <lb/>ramaswamy, 2004b, p. 7). Prahalad and ramaswamy (2004a) illustrate access to information with custom-<lb/>ers tracking production progress online without going to the factory. also, consumers need access to <lb/>relevant information to participate in production (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). this information is <lb/>valuable for a better relationship between customers and a company (garbarino &amp; strahilevitz, 2004). <lb/>according to sawhney et al. (2005), optimizing these tools through investments and technologies con-<lb/>tributes to efficient collaboration because it permits interactivity between the customer and the company. <lb/>the co-creation process sees the company as an experienced provider for the consumer, which moti-<lb/>vates said consumers to provide relevant information (grönroos &amp; ravald, 2011). thus, consumer partic-<lb/>ipation in strategic value co-creation occurs through exchanging information and constructing experiences <lb/>(Bolton &amp; saxena-iyer, 2009). the association between co-creation and active participation by consumers <lb/>implies more information about the company (cova &amp; Dalli, 2009). the disclosure of information by cus-<lb/>tomers leads to a better understanding of their relationships with the company (Moon et al., 2019). By <lb/>contrast, practices denying access to knowledge and information or disabling their exploitation may hin-<lb/>der strategic value co-creation (cabiddu et al., 2019). Based on these previous studies, the following <lb/>hypothesis was proposed: <lb/>H2: access to information positively influences the value co-created by customers. <lb/>the model considered risk assessment as the third variable, which refers to evaluating &quot;the proba-<lb/>bility of harm to the customer&quot; (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004b, p. 7). risk plays a significant role in <lb/>consumer behaviour, influencing information search and purchase decision-making (Masoud, 2013). <lb/>Despite recognizing the benefits of using the internet, consumers often feel uncertain about online <lb/>transactions, perceiving them as risky (lee &amp; tan, 2003). Perceived risk in online buying is defined as <lb/>the potential loss in pursuing a desired result, combining uncertainty and the possibility of severe <lb/>consequences (ko et al., 2004). this concept has been extensively studied, with various scales devel-<lb/>oped to measure perceived danger (Featherman &amp; hajli, 2016). high levels of perceived risk can sig-<lb/>nificantly reduce consumers&apos; willingness to purchase products online (Barnes et al., 2007). in online <lb/>commerce, perceived risk negatively impacts purchasing behaviour, attitudes towards usage, and the <lb/>intention to adopt online platforms (Zhou et al., 2008). Without a physical environment, customers <lb/>cannot directly assess product quality, engage in personal interactions, and feel secure about payment <lb/>processes. additionally, they face the costs of learning how to navigate online systems (Jain &amp; Jain, <lb/>2015). these factors contribute to the perception of online commerce as risky for some customers. <lb/>conversely, other consumers appreciate online commerce&apos;s advantages, such as real-time information <lb/>availability for product and price comparisons (san Martín &amp; camarero, 2009). Featherman and hajli <lb/>(2016) highlight that consumers are more concerned about perceived risks than usability when con-<lb/>tracting services online. this heightened concern about risk over usability indicates that risk assess-<lb/>ment is critical in shaping consumer behaviour in online environments. When consumers perceive high <lb/>levels of risk, they are less likely to engage in value co-creation activities, as their focus shifts towards <lb/>mitigating potential adverse outcomes rather than collaborating and innovating with firms. therefore, <lb/>practical risk assessment and mitigation are crucial for fostering value co-creation online. companies <lb/>must implement robust risk management strategies to alleviate customers&apos; concerns, enhancing their <lb/>willingness to participate in value co-creation processes. these strategies include ensuring secure pay-<lb/>ment systems, providing transparent information about products and services, and offering reliable <lb/>customer support. the literature indicates that perceived risk negatively influences consumer behaviour <lb/></body>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>and attitudes in online commerce. given the importance of risk assessment in shaping these percep-<lb/>tions, we propose the following hypothesis: <lb/>H3: risk assessment negatively influences the co-creation of value by customers. <lb/>transparency has been conceptualized as the result of symmetric information-sharing processes <lb/>between customers and firms involved in strategic value co-creation (Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). <lb/>this concept emphasizes the importance of open and honest communication, where both parties <lb/>exchange information with equal clarity and accessibility. Ballantyne and Varey (2006) argue that custom-<lb/>ers require a degree of fair reciprocity in their dialogue with companies, meaning that the information <lb/>shared with consumers must be as clear and understandable as what they share with the organization. <lb/>this reciprocity builds trust and fosters a collaborative environment, which is essential for effective value <lb/>co-creation. consequently, companies can no longer operate with opaque pricing and profit margins <lb/>(Prahalad &amp; ramaswamy, 2004a). instead, they must ensure that information is accessible and transpar-<lb/>ent, providing customers with the knowledge they need to make informed decisions. garbarino and <lb/>strahilevitz (2004) highlight that information transparency offers a competitive advantage to companies, <lb/>as it enhances customer trust and engagement. customers who perceive that a company is transparent <lb/>are more likely to feel confident in their interactions and transactions. this confidence encourages greater <lb/>participation in co-creation activities, as customers are assured that their contributions are valued and <lb/>that they clearly understand the processes involved. transparency not only facilitates participation but <lb/>also enables continuous feedback. Open information channels allow customers to provide feedback on <lb/>products and services, which companies can use to make improvements and innovations. this ongoing <lb/>feedback loop enhances value co-creation by ensuring that the products and services align with cus-<lb/>tomer needs and preferences. Furthermore, transparency in information-sharing helps mitigate uncertain-<lb/>ties and reduces perceived risks associated with online transactions. When customers have clear and <lb/>accurate information about products, services, and company practices, they are less likely to perceive <lb/>high levels of risk, promoting a positive co-creation experience (Masoud, 2013). this reduced perceived <lb/>risk is crucial for fostering an environment where customers feel comfortable engaging in value <lb/>co-creation activities. transparency is vital in strategic value co-creation by promoting open communica-<lb/>tion, building trust, enabling continuous feedback, and reducing perceived risks. these elements are <lb/>essential for creating a collaborative environment where customers feel empowered to contribute to the <lb/>value co-creation process. therefore, we propose the following hypothesis: <lb/>H4: transparency positively influences the value co-created by customers. <lb/>considering the significance of reputation in the banking industry, it is crucial to explore the factors <lb/>influencing a company&apos;s reputation, including value co-creation. Value co-creation, as proposed by Vargo <lb/>and lusch (2008, 2011, 2016), is centred on active customer interaction with the company. this collabo-<lb/>rative interaction creates value, such as a reputation and personalized customer experiences (Prahalad &amp; <lb/>ramaswamy, 2004a). From this perspective, it is worth investigating whether the value co-creation pro-<lb/>cess between retail banks and their customers contributes to a more robust company reputation. <lb/>traditionally, company reputation has been studied as a determinant of value co-creation. scholars have <lb/>focused on examining the effective management of customer relationships, which results in a long-term <lb/>competitive advantage in the long term (nguyen et al., 2022). <lb/>conversely, pursuing a high company reputation may require increased investments in new it solu-<lb/>tions to maintain a competitive edge, potentially affecting short-term profits and hindering the economic <lb/>value generation from assets (eccles et al., 2007; nguyen et al., 2022). <lb/>consequently, a recent line of literature has shifted its perspective to analyzing value co-creation as <lb/>an antecedent of company reputation (Martillo Jeremías &amp; Polo Peña, 2021). For instance, recent studies <lb/>have demonstrated that customer value co-creation positively impacts a company&apos;s reputation by foster-<lb/>ing a customer-centric organizational culture and delivering enhanced customer experience (Foroudi <lb/>et al., 2019). a company&apos;s reputation is further solidified by fulfilling promises to stakeholders and meet-<lb/>ing their expectations (Ponzi et al., 2011). through customer value co-creation, companies can exhibit <lb/>their dedication to delivering value to customers and stakeholders, strengthening their reputation as <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>customer-centric and responsible organizations (Martillo Jeremías &amp; Polo Peña, 2021). Ultimately, <lb/>co-creation initiatives empower customers to actively participate in the value-creation process, enabling <lb/>companies to tailor their offerings to meet specific customer needs and preferences, thus improving their <lb/>reputation (Pera et al., 2016). however, despite the importance of identifying antecedent variables of <lb/>reputation, such as value co-creation, a gap exists in the literature regarding how value co-creation pos-<lb/>itively influences banks&apos; company reputation. Based on these studies, the following hypothesis was <lb/>proposed: <lb/>H5: customer value co-created is positively related to company reputation. <lb/>customer trust, a fundamental belief in the dependability, honesty, or competence of a person or <lb/>entity, emerges as a crucial emotion resulting from the interaction between banks and their customers <lb/>during the value-formation process (Frau et al., 2023a, 2023b). customers trust service providers when <lb/>they are assured that their sensitive information remains secure (Parasuraman et al., 1985). to establish <lb/>trust, companies must commit to matters relevant to the customers&apos; value co-creation process and then <lb/>fulfil those commitments (Yap et al., 2010). <lb/>research indicates that higher customer co-creation increases trust between companies and their cus-<lb/>tomers (lundkvist &amp; Yakhlef, 2004). scholars support this view by suggesting that value co-creation sig-<lb/>nificantly influences trust because it helps mitigate risks arising from open information exchanges <lb/>between partners (ayuni &amp; engriani, 2019). companies create connections between their employees and <lb/>customers through value co-creation and work together in harmony. this involves not only listening to <lb/>customers but also taking action based on their suggestions (lundkvist &amp; Yakhlef, 2004). <lb/>a crucial aspect of value co-creation is communication between the parties involved, serving as a <lb/>platform for developing a shared understanding and exchanging knowledge related to each other&apos;s <lb/>activities, generating mutual trust (lundkvist &amp; Yakhlef, 2004). Based on these findings, the last hypoth-<lb/>esis of this study is as follows: <lb/>H6: customer value co-creation is positively related to trust. <lb/>From the analyzed literature and the six suggested hypotheses, we propose the following model of <lb/>online banking customers&apos; value co-creation towards reputation and trust development (see Figure 1). <lb/>4. Methodology <lb/>4.1. Population, sampling procedure and sample adequacy <lb/>the population must be consistent with the proposed study&apos;s objectives to ensure the research&apos;s effec-<lb/>tiveness. in the research context, the population is not finite, it is challenging to quantify, and it has over <lb/>100,000 units. it consists of customers who regularly use online banking services and have a stable <lb/>relationship with an important spanish bank, caixa Bank. 1 . the primary reasons for selecting this bank <lb/>include the proprietary nature of the information, the specific strategic initiatives of this bank in the <lb/>realm of value co-creation, and the depth of data we could access. this bank&apos;s unique practices provided <lb/>a rich context for addressing our research questions in detail. the respondents&apos; knowledge level limits <lb/>this sampling frame regarding the organization and the tools available for value co-creation. the survey <lb/>Figure 1. Conceptual model: towards the reputation and trust development. <lb/></body>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>was sent to all private customers of an important bank outlet in Valencia, spain&apos;s third most populated <lb/>city, who appeared in its database whenever they used online banking services. ethical approval was <lb/>obtained from the University of Valencia ethics committee for the study. 243 clients answered the ques-<lb/>tionnaire, of which 26 were discarded because of incorrect responses. Written informed consent for par-<lb/>ticipation in the study has been obtained. therefore, the final sample of 217 clients is not probabilistic, <lb/>although big enough to be proportional, as well as representative of the outlet&apos;s customers, as it meets <lb/>the criteria and weight of gender, age, educational level, income, and employment situation of the bank&apos;s <lb/>clients (see table 1). therefore, the sample was understood as non-probability judgmental sampling <lb/>(etikan &amp; Bala, 2017). <lb/>to determine whether this sample size was sufficient for the study&apos;s objectives, both chin&apos;s (1989) <lb/>minimum sample size criteria and the results of the applied power test using gPower 3.1, described later <lb/>in the section, confirmed a sufficient sample size. Data were collected through online questionnaires sent <lb/>to mobile phones during February and May 2022 and June-July 2023. <lb/>the key respondents were 62.08% males and 37.92% females. respondents were under the age of <lb/>sixty-five, and most of them were between 26 and 55 years old. in addition, most respondents had a <lb/>university degree or higher (77.43%). three-quarters of the sample is actively working. regarding average <lb/>income, 40.20% of those surveyed were within the range of 24,001-48,000 euros (see table 1). <lb/>4.2. Measurement scales <lb/>the survey included measures of the key constructs of the Dart model: dialogue, access, risk assess-<lb/>ment, and transparency. these form the second-order construct of value co-creation. a repeated indica-<lb/>tor procedure was applied (lohmöller, 1989). in addition, the survey comprised measurements of the <lb/>dependent constructs of trust and company reputation. each construct was measured with multiple <lb/>items using a five-point likert scale with anchors for all items (see tables 2-4). the questionnaire was <lb/>tested using a two-step process. First, two academics with more than 20 years of experience in academic <lb/>research conducted a semantic review of the questionnaire. they identified sentences that might confuse <lb/>or tax respondents&apos; patience. second, a convenience sample of 20 bank customers completed the ques-<lb/>tionnaire. they pinpointed all unclear, illogical, or problematic sentences to respond to. <lb/>Table 1. Key characteristics of the customers in the sample (n = 217). <lb/>Customers characteristics <lb/>Percentage <lb/>Gender: <lb/>Female <lb/>37.92 <lb/>Male <lb/>62.08 <lb/>Age: <lb/>16-25 <lb/>1.07 <lb/>26-35 <lb/>21.40 <lb/>36-45 <lb/>31.66 <lb/>46-55 <lb/>23.70 <lb/>56-65 <lb/>14.15 <lb/>over 65 <lb/>8.02 <lb/>Educational level: <lb/>no formal education/studies <lb/>0.89 <lb/>secondary education (ESO) <lb/>4.75 <lb/>spanish baccalaureate/vocational education <lb/>16.93 <lb/>Higher education <lb/>77.43 <lb/>Occupation: <lb/>actively working <lb/>74.62 <lb/>student <lb/>2.26 <lb/>unemployed <lb/>8.62 <lb/>Retired <lb/>11.33 <lb/>Homemaker <lb/>3.17 <lb/>Average income: <lb/>Less than 12,000 euros <lb/>16,12 <lb/>12,001-24,000 euros <lb/>20,92 <lb/>24,001-48,000 euros <lb/>40,20 <lb/>over 48,000 euros <lb/>22,76 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>4.3. Exploratory factor analysis <lb/>to identify the underlying structure of the dimensions, we performed an exploratory factor analysis by <lb/>applying a principal component analysis using sPss version 28. We subsequently checked the model <lb/>using the sMart Pls version 4 software (hair et al., 2019; ringle et al., 2022). We used partial least <lb/>squares (Pls) for two reasons. First, this study mainly aims to analyze the predictive capacity of a model <lb/>composed of two dependent constructs (company reputation and company trust) and maximize their <lb/>explained variance by one predictive variable: value co-creation, a second-order construct formed by the <lb/>variables dialogue, access to information, risk assessment, and transparency). second, a small sample size <lb/>was available, although it was sufficient. <lb/>Factor analysis showed an adequate and clear underlying factor structure that identified five factors <lb/>with eigenvalues greater than 1.0, which accounted for 77.16% of the variance. Oblimin rotation was <lb/>selected because the factors are not independent, and some correlation exists between them. Bartlett&apos;s <lb/>test of sphericity was statistically significant (χ2 = 5381,26; p &lt; 0.001), and the kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure <lb/>Table 2. source of the scales. <lb/>independent factors <lb/>scales and sources <lb/>Dialogue <lb/>DaRt model (albinsson et al., 2016) <lb/>access to information <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>transparency <lb/>the reputation of the company <lb/>ReP1 -the banking service has quality <lb/>ReP2 -the bank&apos;s after-sales service has quality. <lb/>ReP3 -the banking production process has quality. <lb/>ReP4 -the entity offers its users services resulting from research <lb/>and development. <lb/>ReP5 -the entity offers its users innovative products. <lb/>agency theory (Jensen, 1986) <lb/>trust <lb/>tRu1 -i am worried that the service in the bank is not good. <lb/>tRu2 -sometimes you can&apos;t trust this bank. <lb/>tRu3 -i&apos;m worried that the banking service isn&apos;t worth it. <lb/>tRu4 -i&apos;m worried that my stake in this bank isn&apos;t worth it. <lb/>service-dominant logic (Vargo &amp; Lusch, 2004) <lb/>Table 3. albinsson&apos;s items. <lb/>items <lb/>Dia4 -the provider communicates with the customer to receive <lb/>input on improving the service/product experience. <lb/>aCC1 -it is easy for the customer to receive the service/ product <lb/>offering when, where and how he/she wants it. <lb/>Dia5 -the provider is interested in communicating the best ways to <lb/>design and deliver a quality service/product experience to the <lb/>customer. <lb/>Ris2 -the provider provides the customer with comprehensive <lb/>information about risks and benefits assessed for the service <lb/>experience or product. <lb/>Dia6 -the provider uses multiple communication channels to <lb/>encourage a greater exchange of ideas with the customer about <lb/>the service/product experience. <lb/>Ris1 -the customer receives comprehensive information about the <lb/>risks and benefits of the service/product experience. <lb/>Dia3 -the provider and the customer actively discuss adding value <lb/>to the service /product experience. <lb/>Ris4 -the provider fully informs the customer about all risks <lb/>stemming from product or service use. <lb/>Dia9 -the customer is encouraged to communicate with the <lb/>provider about all service/product experience aspects. <lb/>Ris5 -the provider is clear and factual about the negative and <lb/>positive factors associated with the service/ product offering. <lb/>Dia7 -the provider uses multiple lines of communication to gather <lb/>input and ideas from the customer. <lb/>Ris6 -the provider allows the customer to make informed decisions <lb/>regarding the risks and benefits of the product/service experience. <lb/>Dia8 -the provider actively promotes dialogue with the customer <lb/>to learn more about the customer&apos;s reaction to the service/ <lb/>product experience. <lb/>Ris3 -the provider encourages the customer to familiarize himself/ <lb/>herself with the risks associated with the service/product experience. <lb/>Dia2 -the customer has many opportunities to share his/her ideas <lb/>with the provider about adding value to the service/provider <lb/>experience. <lb/>tRa2 -the provider fully discloses to the customer information, <lb/>which might be helpful to improve the outcomes of the service/ <lb/>product experience. <lb/>Dia1 -the provider makes it easy for the customer to communicate <lb/>his/her ideas about the design and delivery of the service/product <lb/>experience. <lb/>tRa3 -the customer is given access to information that might <lb/>enhance the overall design and delivery of the service/product <lb/>experience. <lb/>aCC3 -the provider lets the customer decide how he/she receives <lb/>the service/product offering. <lb/>tRa4 -the customer and provider are treated as equal partners in <lb/>sharing information needed to achieve a successful service/product <lb/>experience. <lb/>aCC2 -the customer has many options to choose how he/she <lb/>experiences the service/ product offering. <lb/>tRa1 -the provider fully discloses to the customer detailed <lb/>information regarding the costs and pricing associated with the <lb/>design and delivery of the service/ product experience. <lb/>source: DaRt scale development: diagnosing a firm&apos;s readiness for strategic value co-creation of albinsson et al. (2016). <lb/></body>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>of sampling adequacy was 0.89, exceeding the minimum threshold of 0.50, as proposed by kaiser (1974). <lb/>Before applying Pca, some items from the scales were dropped because the reliability and quantity of <lb/>items matter. in the Dialogue scale, items 3, 5, 6, and 7 were dropped; in the risk scale, item 3 and the <lb/>transparency scale, item 4 were also dropped. the composition of the components is shown in table 4. <lb/>as seen in table 4, the three items in the trust scale do not compose an individual factor because they <lb/>weigh in three other factors: accessibility, transparency and reputation. therefore, the access to informa-<lb/>tion factor is composed of four items, including trU1, which is composed of five items; the reputation <lb/>factor is composed of six items, including trU3; the risk factor is formed of five items, and four items, <lb/>including trU2, form the transparency. <lb/>this structure changes the previous conceptual model structure shown in Figures 1 and 2. now, the <lb/>latent variables&apos; access to information, Dialogue, risk and transparency measure the second-order con-<lb/>struct Value co-creation (VacOcre), and the latter affects reputation (see Figure 2). <lb/>4.4. Reliability and validity of the measurement instrument <lb/>Depending on the number of relations that need to be evaluated, an initial concern relates to the sam-<lb/>ple size. according to chin (1998), the overall sample size must be ten times the largest of the two <lb/>possibilities: (1) the factor that has the largest number of indicators or (2) the dependent factor that is <lb/>affected by the largest number of independent factors. in our model, the first possibility was equal to <lb/>six (reputation and trust), while the second was equal to four (the number of factors directly forming <lb/>value co-creation). accordingly, the minimum sample size was 60, and the sample included 217 cases. <lb/>additionally, we calculated the test power for the dependent variable (r2) for one predictor (α= .01, and <lb/>a low effect size (0.10). the minimum level for the social sciences is 0.8. the result showed a test power <lb/>(1-β) of over 0.97 for a sample size of 217 (df = 215; 1-β = 0.979). <lb/>reliability, validity, and the hypothesized structural equation model were assessed using smartPls 4.0 <lb/>(ringle et al., 2022). Measurement scale reliability was assessed using cronbach&apos;s alpha (ca) as the <lb/>Table 4. Principal components analysis results. <lb/>Components and corresponding variance explained <lb/>Components and items <lb/>1 (8.67%) <lb/>2 (4.72%) <lb/>3 (5.98%) <lb/>4 (5.43%) <lb/>5 (8.16%) <lb/>access to information <lb/>aCC1 <lb/>,568 <lb/>aCC2 <lb/>,771 <lb/>aCC3 <lb/>,919 <lb/>tRu1 <lb/>,925 <lb/>Dialogue <lb/>Dia1 <lb/>,833 <lb/>Dia2 <lb/>,865 <lb/>Dia4 <lb/>,776 <lb/>Dia8 <lb/>,764 <lb/>Dia9 <lb/>,744 <lb/>Reputation &amp; trust <lb/>ReP1 <lb/>,915 <lb/>ReP2 <lb/>,870 <lb/>ReP3 <lb/>,898 <lb/>ReP4 <lb/>,788 <lb/>ReP5 <lb/>,738 <lb/>tRu3 <lb/>,931 <lb/>Risk <lb/>Ris1 <lb/>-,889 <lb/>Ris2 <lb/>-,864 <lb/>Ris4 <lb/>-,896 <lb/>Rie5 <lb/>-,809 <lb/>Ris6 <lb/>-,810 <lb/>transparency <lb/>tRa1 <lb/>,940 <lb/>tRa2 <lb/>,789 <lb/>tRa3 <lb/>,633 <lb/>tRu2 <lb/>,923 <lb/>oblimin rotation with Kaiser normalization. <lb/>KMo= .89; Bartlett&apos;s test: χ 2 =5381,26 ; gl = 276; p &lt; 0.001. <lb/>explained variance = 77.16%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<body>standard criterion (nunnally &amp; Bernstein, 1994). however, since ca tends to underestimate the internal <lb/>consistency in Pls (Werts et al., 1974), we also checked composite reliability (see table 5). For ca and <lb/>cr, all scores were over 0.84, higher than the minimum threshold of 0.7 (Bagozzi &amp; Yi, 1988; nunnally &amp; <lb/>Bernstein, 1994). <lb/>to evaluate convergent validity, a bootstrap test was conducted over 5,000 resamples, with no sign <lb/>of change in resampling. We then compared the results with sign changes at the construct level and <lb/>individual changes. We used the one-tailed test with a significance level of 0.05. as can be seen in table <lb/>5, all items loaded above 0.7 in terms of their respective reflective constructs (hair et al., 2014). convergent <lb/>validity within the reflective constructs was assessed using average variance extracted (aVe). the results <lb/>showed scores higher than the minimum threshold of 0.5 suggested by Bagozzi and Yi (1988) and hair <lb/>et al. (2012) (see table 5). <lb/>regarding discriminant validity and following the criteria proposed by Fornell and larcker (1981), we <lb/>calculated the square root of each latent variable&apos;s aVe. these should be higher than the correlations <lb/>Figure 2. Resulting model based on the exploratory analysis. <lb/>Table 5. Reliability and convergent validity of the model. <lb/>Factor <lb/>item <lb/>Loadings <lb/>Cronbach&apos;s alpha <lb/>Ca <lb/>Composite reliability <lb/>CR <lb/>average variance <lb/>extracted <lb/>aVe <lb/>VaLCoCRe <lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>-<lb/>0.922 <lb/>0.725 <lb/>Dialogue <lb/>Dia 1 <lb/>0.795 <lb/>0.871 <lb/>0.906 <lb/>0.659 <lb/>Dia 2 <lb/>0.806 <lb/>Dia 4 <lb/>0.820 <lb/>Dia 8 <lb/>0.823 <lb/>Dia 9 <lb/>0.817 <lb/>access <lb/>aCC 1 <lb/>0.735 <lb/>0.847 <lb/>0.898 <lb/>0.689 <lb/>aCC 2 <lb/>0.758 <lb/>aCC 3 <lb/>0.896 <lb/>tRu1 <lb/>0.916 <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>Ris 1 <lb/>0.891 <lb/>0.921 <lb/>0.940 <lb/>0.760 <lb/>Ris 2 <lb/>0.833 <lb/>Ris 4 <lb/>0.903 <lb/>Ris 5 <lb/>0.866 <lb/>Ris 6 <lb/>0.864 <lb/>transparency <lb/>tRa 1 <lb/>0.924 <lb/>0.911 <lb/>0.938 <lb/>0.791 <lb/>tRa 2 <lb/>0.901 <lb/>tRa 3 <lb/>0.803 <lb/>tRu2 <lb/>0.924 <lb/>Reputation and trust <lb/>ReP 1 <lb/>0.899 <lb/>0.939 <lb/>0.952 <lb/>0.769 <lb/>ReP 2 <lb/>0.887 <lb/>ReP 3 <lb/>0.904 <lb/>ReP 4 <lb/>0.843 <lb/>ReP 5 <lb/>0.812 <lb/>tRu 3 <lb/>0.868 <lb/></body>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>between the latent variables. as shown in table 6, this criterion was met by the data. in addition, we <lb/>ran the heterotrait-monotrait ratio (htMt) to test discriminant validity (henseler et al., 2015). all the <lb/>htMt ratios in absolute value were below the threshold of 0.90, even below 0.85, which indicated that <lb/>discriminant validity exists between the reflective factors (see table 6). <lb/>these results indicate satisfactory reliability and convergent and discriminant validity of the measure-<lb/>ment model&apos;s variables and constructs. <lb/>5. Results <lb/>to assess the structural model, we observed the dependent latent variable variance, explained by the <lb/>predictive factor. the criterion to apply is r 2 , which must be higher than 0.1 (Falk &amp; Miller, 1992). in <lb/>addition to r 2 , we checked the significance of the path coefficients using their respective t-values (hair <lb/>et al., 2012). Finally, we assessed the cross-validated redundancy index (Q 2 ) by blindfolding (geisser, <lb/>1975), which, together with r 2 , informed on the predictive capacity of endogenous factors, with values <lb/>above zero, indicated a clear predictive relevance of the model (chin, 1998; see table 6). the ViF indica-<lb/>tor for the inner model is less than five and higher than 0.20, which is the recommended range accord-<lb/>ing to hair et al. (2011). specifically, the ViF for the independent constructs is 1.496 (accinF), 1.768 <lb/>(DialOgUe), 2.645 (risk), and 1.970 (transParencY); all values are less than 3, which is ideal, according <lb/>to hair et al. (2019). therefore, collinearity between the independent constructs was not observed. <lb/>the empirical results support four hypotheses about customer value co-creation and one about the <lb/>effects of value co-creation on company reputation and trust (see Figure 3 and table 7). the first four <lb/>hypotheses are as follows: h1 (β = 0.291; p &lt; 0.001) shows that dialogue significantly and positively influ-<lb/>ences customer value co-creation. the same is true for h2, where access to information significantly and <lb/>positively explains customer value co-creation (β = 0.230; p &lt; 0.001). in the case of h3, risk assessment, <lb/>insofar as it implies information to be able to assess the risk of the financial service product adequately, <lb/>positively influences value co-creation (β = -0.394; p &lt; 0.001), with the variable having the highest effect <lb/>on value co-creation. h4 shows transparency positively affects customer value co-creation (β = 0.301; <lb/>p &lt; 0.001). Finally, regarding h5, the results show that value co-creation affects reputation and trust in a <lb/>company (β = 0.769; p &lt; 0.001). <lb/>regarding the proposed model and its predictive capacity, both r2, with a value of 0.591 and a Q2 <lb/>of 0.580, show an explicit model predictive capacity. these results support that customer value co-creation <lb/>in the banking sector has a relevant impact on a company&apos;s reputation and trust development. <lb/>6. Discussion <lb/>studying dialogue, access to information, risk assessment, transparency, customer trust, and bank repu-<lb/>tation is critical to understanding customer value co-creation in the bank setting. such factors are espe-<lb/>cially paramount nowadays because customers can see bank operations in real time and have access to <lb/>a personal manager through their mobile devices. <lb/>6.1. Theoretical implications <lb/>regarding the research questions, this study makes two key contributions to the test and extant theory <lb/>on customer strategic value co-creation in the banking context. <lb/>First, when conceptualizing the Dart model, Prahalad and ramaswamy (2004a) considered dialogue, <lb/>access, risk assessment, and transparency as the fundamental pillars that allow the customer to co-create <lb/>Table 6. Discriminant validity. the HtMt ratio and the Fornell-Larker criteria are in brackets. <lb/>Construct <lb/>Dialogue <lb/>access <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>transparency <lb/>Dialogue <lb/>(0.812) <lb/>access <lb/>0.562 (0.498) <lb/>(0.830) <lb/>Risk assessment <lb/>0.697 (0.628) <lb/>0.601 (0.536) <lb/>(0.872) <lb/>transparency <lb/>0.544 (0.489) <lb/>0.845 (0.411) <lb/>0.758 (0.698) <lb/>(0.889) <lb/>Reputation &amp; trust <lb/>0.607 (0.557) <lb/>0.656 (0.589) <lb/>0.729 (0.679) <lb/>0.717 (0.665) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>13 <lb/></page>

			<body>strategic value with the company, keeping open the opportunity to further studies enriching their model <lb/>with additional and industry-specific variables. this study attempts to extend the Dart model by involv-<lb/>ing two significant strategic variables for customer value co-creation in the online banking industry: trust <lb/>and reputation. the findings reveal that value co-creation significantly affects a company&apos;s reputation <lb/>and trust. therefore, this study supports the notion that the customer value co-creation process can <lb/>develop a company&apos;s reputation and trust. Previous research has contributed in various ways to our <lb/>understanding of customer value co-creation (kucharska, 2017; syah &amp; Olivia, 2022) and online banking <lb/>(aldás et al., 2009). For instance, it highlights the significance of customers&apos; trust in online settings and <lb/>banks&apos; reputations as essential prerequisites for strategic value co-creation (Dhaigude et al., 2023; <lb/>Mccormack &amp; Deacon, 2017). Oklevik et al. (2024) also underscored the importance of the Dart model <lb/>elements in enhancing customer-brand interactions, providing a foundational understanding that further <lb/>supports the role of trust and reputation as outcomes of value co-creation. <lb/>Figure 3. the structural model. <lb/>Table 7. Hypotheses testing. <lb/>Hypothesis <lb/>standardized path coefficient <lb/>t-value (Bootstrap) <lb/>Result <lb/>H1: DiaLogue→ value co-creation <lb/>0.291 <lb/>14.110** <lb/>supported <lb/>H2: inFoRMation aCCess→ value <lb/>co-creation <lb/>0.230 <lb/>9.141** <lb/>supported <lb/>H3: RisK →value co-creation <lb/>0.394 <lb/>21.903** <lb/>supported <lb/>H4: tRansPaRenCY→value co-creation <lb/>0.301 <lb/>16.315** <lb/>supported <lb/>H5: VaLue CoCReation → Reputation &amp; <lb/>trust* <lb/>0.769 <lb/>25.159** <lb/>supported <lb/>* R2 = 0.591; Q 2 = 0.580; **p &lt; 0.001. <lb/></body>

			<page>14 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<body>Furthermore, studies have shown that trust and company reputation are antecedents that positively <lb/>influence customer value co-creation (e.g. Mostafa, 2020). additionally, researchers have explored how <lb/>trust mediates relationships with factors such as privacy risk, concern, and value co-creation (Wang et al., <lb/>2020). in contrast, our study extends the existing literature by demonstrating that constructive and col-<lb/>laborative relationships, along with resource integration, arise from the positive management of dia-<lb/>logue, access to information, risk assessment, and transparency between the bank and customers during <lb/>the value co-creation process. these factors foster long-term relationships and build customer trust and <lb/>reputation. consequently, customers&apos; trust and company reputation can be seen as direct outcomes of a <lb/>successful value co-creation strategy in online banking. <lb/>in conclusion, building upon the original Dart model and existing research on the relationships <lb/>between customer trust, company reputation, and customer value co-creation, this article contributes to <lb/>the strategic marketing literature by highlighting that the value co-creation process can yield reputation <lb/>and trust as outcomes. traditionally, trust and company reputation have been seen as antecedents that <lb/>positively impact customer value co-creation (Mostafa, 2020). Our research, however, shifts this perspec-<lb/>tive by showing that effective value co-creation can enhance reputation and trust. consequently, we <lb/>propose that customers&apos; trust and company reputation should be recognized as direct outcomes of suc-<lb/>cessful value co-creation strategies in online banking. By adopting this innovative approach, our findings <lb/>offer fresh insights into the complex relationship between value co-creation and its outcomes. <lb/>second, the Dart model has been studied in several settings. For example, the Dart model has been <lb/>employed in the pop-up retail sector in italy (russo spena et al., 2012) and the fashion industry, showing <lb/>how nike co-created strategic value with customers (ramaswamy, 2008). however, there is a lack of <lb/>studies that employ the Dart model in banks (Banik &amp; rabbanee, 2023), especially in the online banking <lb/>setting. therefore, this study suggests four hypotheses for testing the Dart model in an online bank <lb/>setting. hypotheses involving dialogue, access to information, risk assessment, and transparency are <lb/>accepted. thus, the present study&apos;s findings show that the Dart model works successfully in the online <lb/>banking industry. this result extends the current literature that tested the Dart model in an offline <lb/>context (e.g. Banik &amp; rabbanee, 2023). therefore, this study provides a broader vision of the Dart model, <lb/>including banks&apos; online customers. <lb/>6.2. Management implications <lb/>Vale co-creation is pivotal to online banking. therefore, this study provides managerial and strategic <lb/>suggestions for each variable involved in the Drat model: customer trust and bank reputation. <lb/>Dialogues require active attitudes from both customers and banks. From the banks&apos; point of view, as <lb/>a minimum requirement, they must inform customers about products and services at the time of their <lb/>launch. however, a more advanced practice requires banks to encourage customers to participate in the <lb/>product innovation process, clearly informing them of their role in innovation and their benefits. this will <lb/>efficiently impact customers&apos; co-creation engagement and increase value. <lb/>access refers to tools and information that facilitate collaboration in strategic value co-creation. For <lb/>this reason, banks must provide sufficient means for customers to facilitate collaboration. For example, <lb/>banks may invest in digital platforms to allow customers to collaborate remotely in the innovation pro-<lb/>cess without going to the bank&apos;s office. in addition, banks may develop procedures to allow customers <lb/>to collaborate whenever they want. <lb/>risk assessment is based on identifying, analyzing, and controlling unforeseen events that may arise <lb/>when co-creating. therefore, banks must identify what customers recognize as risky in collaboration. <lb/>Banks need to take action to resolve each customer-perceived unsafe aspect of the collaboration and <lb/>quantify the possibility that unforeseen events occur and their impact on co-creation. Banks may also be <lb/>proactive in quantifying the possibility of unforeseen risky events to guarantee a smooth value co-creation <lb/>strategic process with customers. <lb/>transparency, which refers to information equality between the customer and company, occurs when <lb/>banks strategically communicate the value they aim to gain in the collaborative process. this also means <lb/>being open to consumer criticism, which requires negotiation. thus, banks must be ready to be asked <lb/>and share collaboration and project development data. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>15 <lb/></page>

			<body>Finally, dialogue, access, risk assessment, and transparency are crucial in promoting online value <lb/>co-creation. additionally, marketing planners must consider that successfully managing the value <lb/>co-creation process results in greater customer trust and bank reputation. thus, developing reliability <lb/>policies based on best collaboration practices and banks&apos; ability to place customers in the centre of value <lb/>co-creation processes increases bank reputation and customer trust. <lb/>6.3. Limitations and future lines of research <lb/>this study shows findings from an underexplored perspective of online-back customers. While it demon-<lb/>strates the key role that Dart variables play in customer value co-creation and how it results in cus-<lb/>tomer trust and bank reputation, it also has a few limitations. <lb/>this study was based on homogeneous survey respondents. For example, data collection is based <lb/>on customers from only one bank, caixa Bank, and only one country, spain. We acknowledge that <lb/>collecting data from a single bank limits the generalizability of our findings. We discuss the potential <lb/>biases introduced by this approach. this enhanced discussion aims to give readers a clearer under-<lb/>standing of the study&apos;s boundaries and encourage future research to build upon our findings with a <lb/>broader dataset. <lb/>Note <lb/>1. according to the magazine global Finance, caixabank has been the First bank in spain for the last eight years <lb/>and the best West european bank for the fourth time in 2022 (Press notice, caixa bank, 13/04/2022; http:// <lb/>www.ciaxabank.com/comunicacion/noticia/caixabank-elegido-mejor-banco-en-espana-2022-y-mejor-ban <lb/>co-en-europa-occidental-2022-por-la-revista-global-finance_es). <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>Marcelo royo-Vela: conception and design, analysis and interpretation of the data, methodology, visualization, writ-<lb/>ing -original draft, writing -review &amp; editing, supervision. Moreno Frau: conceptualization, methodology, investiga-<lb/>tion, writing -original draft, writing -review &amp; editing, project administration. alberto Ferrer: conception and <lb/>design, data curation, visualization, writing -original draft. all authors approved the final version of the article to <lb/>be published and agreed to be accountable for all aspects of the work. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Disclosure of interest <lb/>the authors reported no potential conflict of interest. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">About the authors <lb/>Marcelo Royo-Vela is a full time professor in Marketing, University of Valencia, spain, and is currently Director of the <lb/>Marketing Department and coordinator of the Doctorate Program in Marketing. his major research lines are in mar-<lb/>keting communication, tourism marketing, tourist destination model and emotions, tourist time-space behaviour, <lb/>research methodology, consumer behavior, branding, co-creation of value and business networks. he has published <lb/>in other tourism journals such as Journal of tourism Development, tourism Management, cuadernos de turismo, <lb/>Papers de turisme, estudios turísticos, international Journal of culture, tourism and hospitality research and the <lb/>Journal of air transport Management. <lb/>Moreno Frau is a research Fellow at the Marketing Management Department, corvinus University of Budapest (hungary). <lb/>he holds a PhD in Business and economics took at the University of cagliari (italy) with honours and the additional <lb/>label of Doctor europaeus, thanks to a period of research spent at the Bi norwegian Business school. his research <lb/>interests focus on marketing, digital transformation, sustainability, and interactive value formation. he held a Marie curie <lb/>research project called FooDization about the impact of digital transformation on sustainable food production. his <lb/>research has appeared in peer-reviewed journals such as Journal of service research, Journal of cleaner Production, <lb/>international Journal of Marketing studies, British Food Journal as well as other academic and applied journals. <lb/>Alberto Ferrer graduated in Business Management and holds a Master&apos;s degree in Marketing and Market research <lb/>from the University of Valencia. he currently works as a director at caixa Bank. <lb/></div>

			<page>16 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<div type="funding">Funding <lb/>no funding was received. <lb/></div>

			<front>ORCID <lb/>Marcelo royo-Vela <lb/>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-9310-5201 <lb/>Moreno Frau <lb/>http://orcid.org/0000-0002-3740-1743 <lb/></front>

			<div type="availability">Data availability statement <lb/>the data supporting this study&apos;s findings are available upon request to the email address marcelo.royo@uv.es. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>abror, a., Patrisia, D., engriani, Y., noor, n. M. B. M., Omar, M. W., hafizh, M. a., gaffar, V., &amp; linda, M. r. (2023). <lb/>antecedents of customer value co-creation in islamic banking: the role of religiosity, perceived value and behav-<lb/>ioral factors. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 10(3), 1. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2023.2259577 <lb/>agrawal, a. k., &amp; rahman, Z. (2015). roles and resource contributions of customers in value co-creation. International <lb/>Strategic Management Review, 3(1-2), 144-19. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ism.2015.03.001 <lb/>akter, s., Motamarri, s., hani, U., shams, r., Fernando, M., Babu, M. M., &amp; shen, k. n. (2020). Building dynamic service <lb/>analytics capabilities for the digital marketplace. Journal of Business Research, 118, 177-188. https://doi.org/10.1016/ <lb/>j.jbusres.2020.06.016 <lb/>albinsson, P. a., Perera, B. Y., &amp; sautter, P. t. (2016). Dart scale development: Diagnosing a firm&apos;s readiness for stra-<lb/>tegic value co-creation. Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice, 24(1), 42-58. https://doi.org/10.1080/10696679. <lb/>2016.1089763 <lb/>aldás, J., lassala, c., ruiz, c., &amp; sanz, s. (2009). key drivers of internet banking services use. Online Information Review, <lb/>33(4), 672-695. https://doi.org/10.1108/14684520910985675 <lb/>amegbe, h., hanu, c., &amp; Zungu, n. P. (2023). the dynamics of customer value and brand love among shoppers in <lb/>emerging market. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 10(3), 2272382. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2023.2272382 <lb/>andreu, l., sánchez, i., &amp; Mele, c. (2010). Value co-creation among retailers and consumers: new insights into the <lb/>furniture market. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services, 17(4), 241-250. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jretconser. <lb/>2010.02.001 <lb/>ayuni, s., &amp; engriani, Y. (2019). the influence of electronic word of mouth, value co-creation and brand image on <lb/>trust. Third Padang International Conference on Economics Education, Economics, Business and Management, <lb/>Accounting and Entrepreneurship (PICEEBA 2019) (pp. 276-287.). atlantis Press. <lb/>Bagozzi, r. P., &amp; Yi, Y. (1988). On the evaluation of structural equation models. Journal of the Academy of Marketing <lb/>Science, 16(1), 74-94. https://doi.org/10.1007/BF02723327 <lb/>Ballantyne, D., &amp; Varey, r. J. (2006). creating value-in-use through marketing interaction: the exchange logic of relat-<lb/>ing, communicating and knowing. Marketing Theory, 6(3), 335-348. https://doi.org/10.1177/1470593106066795 <lb/>Banik, s., &amp; rabbanee, F. k. (2023). Value co-creation and customer retention in services: identifying a relevant mod-<lb/>erator and mediator. Journal of Consumer Behaviour, 22(3), 646-663. https://doi.org/10.1002/cb.2150 <lb/>Barnes, s., Bauer, h., neumann, M., &amp; huber, F. (2007). segmenting cyberspace: a customer typology for the internet. <lb/>European Journal of Marketing, 41(1/2), 71-93. https://doi.org/10.1108/03090560710718120 <lb/>Beckers, s. F. M., Van Doorn, J., &amp; Verhoef, P. c. (2018). good, better, engaged? the effect of company-initiated cus-<lb/>tomer engagement behavior on shareholder value. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 46(3), 366-383. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s11747-017-0539-4 <lb/>Bolton, r. n., &amp; saxena-iyer, s. (2009). interactive services: a framework, synthesis and research directions. Journal of <lb/>Interactive Marketing, 23(1), 91-104. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.intmar.2008.11.002 <lb/>cabiddu, F., Moreno, F., &amp; sebastiano, l. (2019). toxic collaborations: co-destroying value in the B2B context. Journal <lb/>of Service Research, 22(3), 241-255. https://doi.org/10.1177/1094670519835311 <lb/>cheung, c., &amp; lee, M. (2001). trust in internet shopping: instrument development and validation through classical <lb/>and modern approaches. Journal of Global Information Management, 9(3), 23-35. https://doi.org/10.4018/jgim. <lb/>2001070103 <lb/>chin, W. W. (1998). the partial least squares approach to structural equation modelling. Modern Methods for Business <lb/>Research, 295(2), 295-336. <lb/>cova, B., &amp; Dalli, D. (2009). Working consumers: the next step in marketing theory? Marketing Theory, 9(3), 315-339. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1177/1470593109338144 <lb/>Dandis, a. O., Wright, l. t., Wallace-Williams, D. M., Mukattash, i., al haj eid, M., &amp; cai, h. (2021). enhancing consum-<lb/>ers&apos; self-reported loyalty intentions in islamic Banks: the relationship between service quality and the mediating <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>17 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>role of customer satisfaction. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 8(1), 1892256. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2021. <lb/>1892256 <lb/>Dhaigude, a. s., Vinod tapar, a., shameem Jawed, M., &amp; kamath, g. B. (2023). is perceived value enough to create <lb/>loyalty for m-wallets? exploring the role of trust and satisfaction. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 10(3), 2281050. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2023.2281050 <lb/>eccles, r. g., newquist, s. c., &amp; schatz, r. (2007). reputation and its risks. Harvard Business Review, 85(2), 104-114, <lb/>156. <lb/>etikan, i., &amp; Bala, k. (2017). sampling and sampling methods. Biometrics &amp; Biostatistics International Journal, 5(6), 149. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.15406/bbij.2017.05.00149 <lb/>Falk, r. F., &amp; Miller, n. B. (1992). A primer for soft modelling. aPa Psycinfo University of akron Press. <lb/>Featherman, M., &amp; hajli, n. (2016). self-service technologies and e-services risks in social commerce era. Journal of <lb/>Business Ethics, 139(2), 251-269. https://doi.org/10.1007/s10551-015-2614-4 <lb/>Ferguson, r., &amp; hlavinka, k. (2007). choosing the right tools for your relationship banking strategy. Journal of <lb/>Consumer Marketing, 24(2), 110-117. https://doi.org/10.1108/07363760710737111 <lb/>Flavián, c., &amp; guinalíu, M. (2005). the influence of virtual communities on distribution strategies in the internet. <lb/>International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management, 33(6), 405-425. https://doi.org/10.1108/09590550510600843 <lb/>Fornell, c., &amp; larcker, D. (1981). evaluating structural equation models with unobservable variables and measurement <lb/>error. Journal of Marketing Research, 18(1), 39-50. https://www.jstor.org/stable/3151312 https://doi.org/10.2307/ <lb/>3151312 <lb/>Foroudi, P., Yu, Q., gupta, s., &amp; Foroudi, M. M. (2019). enhancing university brand image and reputation through <lb/>customer value co-creation behaviour. Technological Forecasting and Social Change, 138, 218-227. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.techfore.2018.09.006 <lb/>Frau, M., cabiddu, F., Frigau, l., tomczyk, P., &amp; Mola, F. (2023a). how emotions impact the interactive value formation <lb/>process during problematic social media interactions. Journal of Research in Interactive Marketing, 17(5), 773-793. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1108/JriM-06-2022-0186 <lb/>Frau, M., cabiddu, F., &amp; Muscas, F. (2018). When multiple actors&apos; online interactions lead to value co-destruction: an explor-<lb/>ative case study. in Diverse methods in customer relationship marketing and management (pp. 163-180). igi global. <lb/>Frau, M., Frigau, l., cabiddu, F., &amp; Mola, F. (2023b). Value co-creation or value co-destruction? the role of negative <lb/>emotions in consumer-firm interaction in the social media platform. in The Palgrave handbook of interactive mar-<lb/>keting (pp. 987-1011). springer international Publishing. <lb/>gadde, l.-e., &amp; håkansson, h. (2011). interaction in networks. in The Sage handbook of marketing theory (pp. 355-364). <lb/>sage Publications. <lb/>garbarino, e., &amp; strahilevitz, M. (2004). gender differences in the perceived risk of buying online and the effects of <lb/>receiving a site recommendation. Journal of Business Research, 57(7), 768-775. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0148-<lb/>2963(02)00363-6 <lb/>geisser, s. (1975). the predictive sample reuse method with applications. Journal of the American Statistical Association, <lb/>70(350), 320-328. https://doi.org/10.2307/2285815 <lb/>grabner-kräuter, s., &amp; Faullant, r. (2008). consumer acceptance of internet banking: the influence of internet trust. <lb/>International Journal of Bank Marketing, 26(7), 483-504. https://doi.org/10.1108/02652320810913855 <lb/>grönroos, c. (2011). Value co-creation in service logic: a critical analysis. Marketing Theory, 11(3), 279-301. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1177/1470593111408177 <lb/>grönroos, c., &amp; ravald, a. (2011). service as business logic: implications for value creation and marketing. Journal of <lb/>Service Management, 22(1), 5-22. https://doi.org/10.1108/09564231111106893 <lb/>hair, J. F., ringle, c. M., &amp; sarstedt, M. (2011). Pls-seM: indeed a silver bullet. Journal of Marketing Theory and Practice, <lb/>19(2), 139-152. https://doi.org/10.2753/MtP1069-6679190202 <lb/>hair, J. F., risher, J. J., sarstedt, M., &amp; ringle, c. M. (2019). When to use and how to report the results of Pls-seM. <lb/>European Business Review, 31(1), 2-24. https://doi.org/10.1108/eBr-11-2018-0203 <lb/>hair, J. F., Jr, sarstedt, M., hopkins, l., &amp; g. kuppelwieser, V. (2014). Partial least squares structural equation modelling <lb/>(Pls-seM), an emerging tool in business research. European Business Review, 26(2), 106-121. https://doi.org/10.1108/ <lb/>eBr-10-2013-0128 <lb/>hair, J. F., sarstedt, M., ringle, c. M., &amp; Mena, J. a. (2012). an assessment of the use of partial least squares structur-<lb/>al equation modeling in marketing research. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 40(3), 414-433. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1007/s11747-011-0261-6 <lb/>harmeling, c. M., Moffett, J. W., arnold, M. J., &amp; carlson, B. D. (2017). toward a theory of customer engagement <lb/>marketing. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 45(3), 312-335. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11747-016-0509-2 <lb/>henseler, J., ringle, c. M., &amp; sarstedt, M. (2015). a new criterion for assessing discriminant validity in variance-based <lb/>structural equation modelling. Journal of the Academy of Marketing Science, 43(1), 115-135. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s11747-014-0403-8 <lb/>hosseini, M., shajari, s., &amp; akbarabadi, M. (2022). identifying multi-channel value co-creator groups in the banking <lb/>industry. Journal of Retailing and Consumer Services, 65, 102312. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jretconser.2020.102312 <lb/>hoyer, W. D., chandy, r., Dorotic, M., krafft, M., &amp; singh, s. s. (2010). consumer co-creation in new product develop-<lb/>ment. Journal of Service Research, 13(3), 283-296. https://doi.org/10.1177/1094670510375604 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>18 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">M. rOYO-Vela et al. <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>ind, n., &amp; coates, n. (2013). the meanings of co-creation. European Business Review, 25(1), 86-95. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1108/09555341311287754 <lb/>Jain, s., &amp; Jain, s. k. (2015). Does outcome quality matter? an investigation in the context of banking services in an <lb/>emerging market. Journal of Consumer Marketing, 32(5), 341-355. https://doi.org/10.1108/JcM-10-2014-1169 <lb/>Jensen, M. c. (1986). agency costs of free cash flow, corporate finance, and takeovers. The American Economic Review, <lb/>76(2), 323-329. <lb/>kaiser, M. O. (1974). kaiser-Meyer-Olkin measure for identity correlation matrix. Journal of the Royal Statistical Society, <lb/>52(1), 296-298. <lb/>ko, h., Jung, J., kim, J., &amp; shim, s. W. (2004). cross-cultural differences in perceived risk of online shopping. Journal <lb/>of Interactive Advertising, 4(2), 20-29. https://doi.org/10.1080/15252019.2004.10722084 <lb/>kucharska, W. (2017). consumer social network brand identification and personal branding. how do social network <lb/>users choose among brand sites? Cogent Business &amp; Management, 4(1), 1315879. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975 <lb/>.2017.1315879 <lb/>lee, J. (2002). a key to marketing financial services: the right mix of products, services, channels and customers. <lb/>Journal of Services Marketing, 16(3), 238-258. https://doi.org/10.1108/08876040210427227 <lb/>lee, k., &amp; tan, s. (2003). e-retailing versus physical retailing: a theoretical model and empirical test of consumer <lb/>choice. Journal of Business Research, 56(11), 877-885. https://doi.org/10.1016/s0148-2963(01)00274-0 <lb/>li, Y. M., &amp; chen, c. W. (2009). a synthetical approach for blog recommendation: combining trust, social relatoin, and <lb/>semantic analysis. Expert Systems with Applications, 36(3), 6536-6547. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.eswa.2008.07.077 <lb/>lohmöller, J. B. (1989). Latent variable path modelling with partial least squares. Physica. <lb/>lundkvist, a., &amp; Yakhlef, a. (2004). customer involvement in new service development: a conversational approach. <lb/>Managing Service Quality: An International Journal, 14(2/3), 249-257. https://doi.org/10.1108/09604520410528662 <lb/>Madden, M., &amp; smith, a. (2010). Reputation management and social media. Pew internet &amp; american life Project. <lb/>Mainardes, e. W., teixeira, a., &amp; Da silveira romano, P. c. (2017). Determinants of co-creation in banking services. <lb/>International Journal of Bank Marketing, 35(2), 187-204. https://doi.org/10.1108/iJBM-10-2015-0165 <lb/>Malar, D. a., arvidsson, V., &amp; holmstrom, J. (2019). Digital transformation in banking: exploring value co-creation in <lb/>online banking services in india. Journal of Global Information Technology Management, 22(1), 7-24. https://doi.org <lb/>/10.1080/1097198X.2019.1567216 <lb/>Martillo Jeremías, l. D., &amp; Polo Peña, a. i. (2021). exploring the antecedents of retail banks&apos; reputation in <lb/>low-bankarization markets: Brand equity, value co-creation and brand experience. International Journal of Bank <lb/>Marketing, 39(7), 1049-1067. https://doi.org/10.1108/iJBM-10-2020-0519 <lb/>Martovoy, a., &amp; santos, J. (2012). co-creation and co-profiting in financial services. International Journal of <lb/>Entrepreneurship and Innovation Management, 16(1/2), 114-135. https://doi.org/10.1504/iJeiM.2012.050446 <lb/>Masoud, e. (2013). the effect of perceived risk on online shopping in Jordan. European Journal of Business and <lb/>Management, 5(6), 76-87. <lb/>Mazur, J., &amp; Zaborek, P. (2014). Validating Dart model. International Journal of Management and Economics, 44(1), <lb/>106-125. https://doi.org/10.1515/ijme-2015-0012 <lb/>Mccormack, P., &amp; Deacon, J. (2017). can trust be restored to high-street banking: a 20-year challenge? Cogent <lb/>Business &amp; Management, 4(1), 1366284. https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2017.1366284 <lb/>Mefoute Badiang, a., &amp; nkwei, e. s. (2024). Mobile banking adoption its antecedents and post-adoption effects: the <lb/>role of consumers status orientation in an african context. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 11(1), 2321787. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2024.2321787 <lb/>Moon, h., Miao, l., hanks, l., &amp; line, n. D. (2019). Peer-to-peer interactions: Perspectives of airbnb guests and hosts. <lb/>International Journal of Hospitality Management, 77, 405-414. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ijhm.2018.08.004 <lb/>Mostafa, r. B. (2020). Mobile banking service quality: a new avenue for customer value co-creation. International <lb/>Journal of Bank Marketing, 38(5), 1107-1132. https://doi.org/10.1108/iJBM-11-2019-0421 <lb/>nguyen, Y. t. h., tapanainen, t., &amp; nguyen, h. t. t. (2022). reputation and its consequences in Fintech services: the <lb/>case of mobile banking. International Journal of Bank Marketing, 40(7), 1364-1397. https://doi.org/10.1108/iJBM-<lb/>08-2021-0371 <lb/>nunnally, J. c., &amp; Bernstein, i. h. (1994). Psychometric theory. Mcgraw hill. <lb/>Oklevik, O., nysveen, h., &amp; Pedersen, P. e. (2024). exploring the relationship between co-creation (Dart), brand ex-<lb/>perience strength, and brand satisfaction: a brand engagement perspective. Journal of Marketing Theory and <lb/>Practice, 32(1), 1-24. https://doi.org/10.1080/10696679.2022.2120013 <lb/>Oliveira, P., &amp; Von hippel, e. (2011). Users as service innovators: the case of banking services. Research Policy, 40(6), <lb/>806-818. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.respol.2011.03.009 <lb/>Oreg, s., &amp; nov, O. (2008). exploring motivations for contributing to open source initiatives: the roles of contribution context <lb/>and personal values. Computers in Human Behavior, 24(5), 2055-2073. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chb.2007.09.007 <lb/>Parasuraman, a., Zeithaml, V. a., &amp; Berry, l. l. (1985). a conceptual model of service quality and its implications for <lb/>future research. Journal of Marketing, 49(4), 41-50. <lb/>Pavlou, P. a. (2003). consumer acceptance of electronic commerce: integrating trust and risk with the technology ac-<lb/>ceptance model. International Journal of Electronic Commerce, 7(3), 101-134. https://doi.org/10.1080/10864415.2003.1 <lb/>1044275 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">cOgent BUsiness &amp; ManageMent <lb/></note>

			<page>19 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Payne, a. F., storbacka, k., &amp; Frow, P. (2008). Managing the co-creation of value. Journal of the Academy of Marketing <lb/>Science, 36(1), 83-96. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11747-007-0070-0 <lb/>Pera, r., Occhiocupo, n., &amp; clarke, J. (2016). Motives and resources for value co-creation in a multi-stakeholder eco-<lb/>system: a managerial perspective. Journal of Business Research, 69(10), 4033-4041. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbus-<lb/>res.2016.03.047 <lb/>Ponzi, l. J., Fombrun, c. J., &amp; gardberg, n. a. (2011). reptrak pulse: conceptualizing and validating a short term <lb/>measure of corporate reputation. Corporate Reputation Review, 14(1), 15-35. https://doi.org/10.1057/crr.2011.5 <lb/>Prahalad, c. k., &amp; ramaswamy, V. (2004a). co-creating unique value with customers. Strategy &amp; Leadership, 32(3), 4-9. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1108/10878570410699249 <lb/>Prahalad, c. k., &amp; ramaswamy, V. (2004b). co-creation experiences: the next practice in value creation. Journal of <lb/>Interactive Marketing, 18(3), 5-14. https://doi.org/10.1002/dir.20015 <lb/>ramaswamy, V. (2008). co-creating value through customers&apos; experiences: the nike case. Strategy &amp; Leadership, 36(5), <lb/>9-14. https://doi.org/10.1108/10878570810902068 <lb/>ramaswamy, V., &amp; Ozcan, k. (2018). What is co-creation? an interactional creation framework and its implications for <lb/>value creation. Journal of Business Research, 84, 196-205. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jbusres.2017.11.027 <lb/>ringle, c. M., Wende, s., &amp; Becker, J. M. (2022). &quot;SmartPLS 4.&quot; Oststeinbek: smartPls gmbh. http://www.smartpls. <lb/>com. <lb/>royo-Vela, M., leszczyński, g., &amp; Velasquez-serrano, M. (2022). sustainable value co-production and co-creation in <lb/>virtual reality: an exploratory research on business-to-business interactions. Sustainability, 14(13), 7754. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3390/su14137754 <lb/>royo-Vela, M., &amp; Mariell Velasquez serrano, M. (2021). Value co-creation process and measurement in 4.0 sMes: an <lb/>exploratory research in a b2b marketing innovation context. Administrative Sciences, 11(1), 20. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.3390/admsci11010020 <lb/>russo spena, t., caridà, a., colurcio, M., &amp; Melia, M. (2012). store experience and co-creation: the case of temporary <lb/>shop. International Journal of Retail &amp; Distribution Management, 40(1), 21-40. https://doi.org/10.1108/09590551211193586 <lb/>san Martín, s., &amp; camarero, c. (2009). how perceived risk affects online buying. Online Information Review, 33(4), <lb/>629-654. https://doi.org/10.1108/14684520910985657 <lb/>sawhney, M., Verona, g., &amp; Prandelli, e. (2005). collaborating to create: the internet as a platform for customer en-<lb/>gagement in product innovation. Journal of Interactive Marketing, 19(4), 4-17. https://doi.org/10.1002/dir.20046 <lb/>suryadi, D. F., Muis, M., taba, M. i., &amp; hakim, W. (2023). the role of religion and social capital on employees&apos; perfor-<lb/>mance: an empirical study post indonesia&apos;s islamic bank merger. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 10(2), 2207676. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/23311975.2023.2207676 <lb/>syah, t. Y. r., &amp; Olivia, D. (2022). enhancing patronage intention on online fashion industry in indonesia: the role of <lb/>value co-creation, brand image, and e-service quality. Cogent Business &amp; Management, 9(1), 2065790. https://doi.or <lb/>g/10.1080/23311975.2022.2065790 <lb/>thomke, s., &amp; hippel, e. V. (2002). customers as innovators: a new way to create value. Harvard Business Review, 80, <lb/>74-81. <lb/>Vargo, s. l., &amp; lusch, r. F. (2004). evolving to a new dominant logic for marketing. Journal of Marketing, 68(1), 1-17. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1509/jmkg.68.1.1.24036 <lb/>Vargo, s. l., &amp; lusch, r. F. (2008). service-dominant logic: continuing the evolution. Journal of the Academy of <lb/>Marketing Science, 36(1), 1-10. https://doi.org/10.1007/s11747-007-0069-6 <lb/>Vargo, s. l., &amp; lusch, r. F. (2011). it&apos;s all B2B…and beyond: toward a systems perspective of the market. Industrial <lb/>Marketing Management, 40(2), 181-187. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.indmarman.2010.06.026 <lb/>Vargo, s. l., &amp; lusch, r. F. (2016). institutions and axioms: an extension and update of service-dominant logic. Journal <lb/>of the Academy of marketing Science, 44, 5-23. <lb/>Wang, X., tajvidi, M., lin, X., &amp; hajli, n. (2020). towards an ethical and trustworthy social commerce community for <lb/>brand value co-creation: a trust-commitment perspective. Journal of Business Ethics, 167(1), 137-152. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/s10551-019-04182-z <lb/>Werts, c. e., linn, r. l., &amp; Jöreskog, k. g. (1974). intraclass reliability estimates: testing structural assumptions. <lb/>Educational and Psychological Measurement, 34(1), 25-33. https://doi.org/10.1177/001316447403400104 <lb/>Yap, k. B., Wong, D. h., loh, c., &amp; Bak, r. (2010). Offline and online banking -Where to draw the line when building <lb/>trust in e-banking?. International Journal of Bank Marketing, 28(1), 27-46. https://doi.org/10.1108/02652321011013571 <lb/>Yoo, Y., henfridsson, O., &amp; lyytinen, k. (2010). the new organizing logic of digital innovation: an agenda for informa-<lb/>tion systems research. Information Systems Research, 21(4), 724-735. https://doi.org/10.1287/isre.1100.0322 <lb/>Zhou, M., Dresner, M., &amp; Windle, r. J. (2008). Online reputation systems: Design and strategic practices. Decision <lb/>Support Systems, 44(4), 785-797. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.dss.2007.10.001 </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
