<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>NIAID-Sponsored 2010 Guidelines for Managing Food <lb/>Allergy: Applications in the Pediatric Population <lb/>abstract <lb/>Data from many studies have suggested a rise in the prevalence of food <lb/>allergies during the past 10 to 20 years. Currently, no curative treat-<lb/>ments for food allergy exist, and there are no effective means of pre-<lb/>venting the disease. Management of food allergy involves strict avoid-<lb/>ance of the allergen in the patient&apos;s diet and treatment of symptoms as <lb/>they arise. Because diagnosis and management of the disease can vary <lb/>between clinical practice settings, the National Institute of Allergy and <lb/>Infectious Diseases (NIAID) sponsored development of clinical guide-<lb/>lines for the diagnosis and management of food allergy. The guidelines <lb/>establish consensus and consistency in definitions, diagnostic criteria, <lb/>and management practices. They also provide concise recommenda-<lb/>tions on how to diagnose and manage food allergy and treat acute food <lb/>allergy reactions. The original guidelines encompass practices rele-<lb/>vant to patients of all ages, but food allergy presents unique and spe-<lb/>cific concerns for infants, children, and teenagers. To focus on those <lb/>concerns, we describe here the guidelines most pertinent to the pedi-<lb/>atric population. Pediatrics 2011;128:955-965 <lb/>AUTHORS: A. Wesley Burks, MD, a Stacie M. Jones, MD, b <lb/>Joshua A. Boyce, MD, c Scott H. Sicherer, MD, d Robert A. <lb/>Wood, MD, e Amal Assa&apos;ad, MD, f and Hugh A. Sampson, <lb/>MD d <lb/>a Division of Allergy and Immunology, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Duke University Medical Center, Durham, North Carolina; <lb/>b Division of Allergy and Immunology, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>University of Arkansas for Medical Sciences and Arkansas <lb/>Children&apos;s Hospital, Little Rock, Arkansas; c Division of <lb/>Rheumatology, Immunology and Allergy, Brigham and Women&apos;s <lb/>Hospital and Department of Medicine, Harvard Medical School, <lb/>Boston, Massachusetts; d Elliot and Roslyn Jaffe Food Allergy <lb/>Institute, Division of Allergy and Immunology, Department of <lb/>Pediatrics, Mount Sinai School of Medicine, New York, New York; <lb/>e Division of Allergy and Immunology, Department of Pediatrics, <lb/>Johns Hopkins University Medical Center, Baltimore, Maryland; <lb/>and f Division of Allergy and Immunology, Cincinnati Children&apos;s <lb/>Hospital Medical Center, University of Cincinnati, Cincinnati, Ohio <lb/>KEY WORDS <lb/>food allergy, food hypersensitivity, infants, children, guidelines, <lb/>anaphylaxis <lb/>ABBREVIATIONS <lb/>NIAID-National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Diseases <lb/>IgE-immunoglobulin E <lb/>DBPCFC-double-blind, placebo-controlled food challenge <lb/>All the authors provided substantial contributions to the <lb/>conception of the manuscript and its drafting or revision, and all <lb/>the authors viewed and approved the manuscript before <lb/>submission. <lb/>www.pediatrics.org/cgi/doi/10.1542/peds.2011-0539 <lb/>doi:10.1542/peds.2011-0539 <lb/>Accepted for publication Jun 1, 2011 <lb/>Address correspondence to A.Wesley Burks, MD, Duke University <lb/>Medical Center, PO Box 2644 DUMC, Durham, NC 27710. E-mail: <lb/>wesley.burks@duke.edu <lb/>PEDIATRICS (ISSN Numbers: Print, 0031-4005; Online, 1098-4275). <lb/>Copyright © 2011 by the American Academy of Pediatrics <lb/> FINANCIAL DISCLOSURE: Dr Jones has served as a speaker and <lb/>grant reviewer and has served on the medical advisory <lb/>committee for the Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network, has <lb/>received funding/grant support from Dyax Corp, the Food <lb/>Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network, the Food Allergy Initiative, <lb/>Mead Johnson, the National Peanut Board, and the National <lb/>Institutes of Health, and has served as a speaker and/or <lb/>consultant for Sanofi-Aventis and Abbott Laboratories; Dr Boyce <lb/>has served on the advisory board of GlaxoSmithKline, has <lb/>served as a consultant and/or speaker for Altana, <lb/>GlaxoSmithKline, and Merck, and has received funding/grant <lb/>support from the National Institutes of Health; Dr Sicherer has <lb/>served on an expert panel for Sunovion, has received funding/ <lb/>grant support from the Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network, <lb/>the Food Allergy Initiative, and the National Institutes of Health, <lb/>and is a consultant to the Food Allergy Initiative; Dr Wood has <lb/>served as a speaker/advisory board member for <lb/>(Continued on last page) <lb/> STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/>PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/>955 <lb/></front>

			<body>Food allergy is a serious public <lb/>health problem that affects people of <lb/>all ages, but the natural history of <lb/>the disease creates considerations <lb/>exclusive to the pediatric population. <lb/>Examples of such considerations are <lb/>introduction of solid foods in infants <lb/>and development of tolerance during <lb/>childhood. Data from many studies <lb/>have indicated a rise in the preva-<lb/>lence of food allergies during the <lb/>past 10 to 20 years. 1,2 Currently, no <lb/>treatment for food allergy exists. <lb/>Managing the disease involves strict <lb/>dietary avoidance of the allergen and <lb/>treatment of symptoms. Diagnosis <lb/>and management of the disease can <lb/>vary between clinical practice <lb/>settings. <lb/>To harmonize best clinical practices <lb/>across medical specialties, the Na-<lb/>tional Institute of Allergy and Infec-<lb/>tious Diseases (NIAID) sponsored de-<lb/>velopment of clinical guidelines for the <lb/>diagnosis and management of food al-<lb/>lergy in the United States. 3 An expert <lb/>panel and coordinating committee <lb/>representing 34 professional organi-<lb/>zations (including the American Acad-<lb/>emy of Pediatrics), federal agencies, <lb/>and patient advocacy groups devel-<lb/>oped the guidelines during a 2-year pe-<lb/>riod. The guidelines were drafted by <lb/>using a comprehensive, independent <lb/>literature review and evidence report <lb/>on the state of the science in food al-<lb/>lergy in combination with expert clini-<lb/>cal opinion. <lb/>Here we summarize the content of the <lb/>guidelines most pertinent to the pedi-<lb/>atric population. Readers of this sum-<lb/>mary are encouraged to review the <lb/>original guidelines document, 3 which <lb/>has a comprehensive reference list <lb/>and explicitly defines the evidence lev-<lb/>els of individual recommendations. <lb/>The guidelines did not address public <lb/>health issues such as managing food <lb/>allergy in schools or restaurants. 4 <lb/>FOOD ALLERGY: DEFINITION, <lb/>PREVALENCE, AND COEXISTING <lb/>CONDITIONS <lb/>A food allergy is an adverse health <lb/>effect arising from a specific im-<lb/>mune response that occurs repro-<lb/>ducibly after exposure to a given <lb/>food. Food allergy includes condi-<lb/>tions associated with immunologic <lb/>reactivity that may be either immu-<lb/>noglobulin E (IgE)-mediated or non-<lb/>IgE-mediated. In contrast, reproduc-<lb/>ible but nonimmunologic adverse <lb/>reactions, such as the inability to di-<lb/>gest lactose, are food intolerances. A <lb/>diagnosis of IgE-mediated food allergy <lb/>requires both sensitization, meaning <lb/>the presence of allergen-specific IgE, <lb/>and clinical symptoms after exposure <lb/>to the allergen. <lb/>The incidence and prevalence of food <lb/>allergy is difficult to measure, in part <lb/>because methods for reporting food <lb/>allergy vary. In a meta-analysis by Rona <lb/>et al, 5 the overall prevalence of food <lb/>allergy to cow&apos;s milk, egg, peanut, fish, <lb/>or crustacean shellfish was 12% in <lb/>children and 13% in adults when as-<lb/>sessed by self-reported symptoms. <lb/>This figure compares to a much lower <lb/>value of 3% for adults and children <lb/>combined when assessed by self-<lb/>reported symptoms plus sensitization <lb/>or by double-blind, placebo-controlled <lb/>food challenge (DBPCFC). <lb/>Children with food allergy are ϳ2 to 4 <lb/>times more likely to have related con-<lb/>ditions such as asthma (4.0-fold), <lb/>atopic dermatitis (2.4-fold), and respi-<lb/>ratory allergies (3.6-fold) compared <lb/>with children without food allergy. 1 <lb/>However, estimates of comorbidities <lb/>can be subject to selection bias. Food <lb/>allergy may coexist with eosinophilic <lb/>esophagitis or exercise-induced <lb/>anaphylaxis. <lb/>In patients with asthma, coexistence of <lb/>food allergy may be a risk factor for <lb/>severe asthma exacerbations. 6-9 More-<lb/>over, a high prevalence of asthma has <lb/>been reported among people who <lb/>died as a result of food-induced <lb/>anaphylaxis. 10,11 <lb/>RISK FACTORS FOR DEVELOPING <lb/>FOOD ALLERGY AND SEVERITY OF <lb/>REACTIONS <lb/>Patients defined as at risk for food al-<lb/>lergy have a biological parent or sib-<lb/>ling with a history of allergic rhinitis, <lb/>asthma, atopic dermatitis, or food al-<lb/>lergy. 12-14 Children at high risk for de-<lb/>veloping food allergy have preexisting <lb/>severe allergic disease (significant <lb/>atopic dermatitis or asthma) or family <lb/>history of food allergy. 3 <lb/>Up to 37% of children younger than 5 <lb/>years with moderate-to-severe atopic <lb/>dermatitis have IgE-mediated food al-<lb/>lergy. 15 Whether or how food allergy <lb/>can exacerbate atopic dermatitis is <lb/>unclear. <lb/>The severity of allergic reactions to <lb/>foods is multifactorial and vari-<lb/>able. 9,11,16,17 The severity of a reaction <lb/>cannot be accurately predicted by the <lb/>severity of past reactions, by food-<lb/>specific IgE level, or by wheal size in a <lb/>skin-prick test. 3 The factor most com-<lb/>monly identified with severe reactions <lb/>is coexistence of asthma, especially <lb/>with peanut or tree nut allergy. <lb/>Diet in At-Risk Children <lb/>Patients at risk for developing food al-<lb/>lergy do not need to limit exposure to <lb/>potential nonfood allergens (eg, dust <lb/>mites or pollen), and they do not need <lb/>to limit exposure to foods that may be <lb/>cross-reactive with the 8 major food <lb/>allergens in the United States (cow&apos;s <lb/>milk, egg, peanut, tree nuts, soy, <lb/>wheat, fish, and crustacean shellfish). <lb/>There is insufficient evidence to rec-<lb/>ommend routine food allergy testing <lb/>before introducing highly allergenic <lb/>foods (such as cow&apos;s milk, egg, and <lb/>peanut) in children at high risk of de-<lb/>veloping food allergy. 3 Nevertheless, <lb/>there may be value in food allergy eval-<lb/></body>

			<page>956 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">BURKS et al <lb/></note>

			<body>uations that include some diagnostic <lb/>testing and an oral food challenge for <lb/>patients with certain risk factors, such <lb/>as having a sibling with peanut al-<lb/>lergy 18,19 or evidence of another food <lb/>allergy. <lb/>Although conclusive data on the sub-<lb/>ject are lacking, if a child is younger <lb/>than 5 years and has persistent atopic <lb/>dermatitis, there can be benefit to de-<lb/>termining whether the child is allergic <lb/>to a food. Early diagnosis can lead to <lb/>better management of food allergy and <lb/>reduce the risk of exposure to food <lb/>antigens. However, testing can be <lb/>time-consuming and costly. Children <lb/>younger than 5 years with moderate-<lb/>to-severe atopic dermatitis should be <lb/>considered for food allergy evaluation <lb/>for cow&apos;s milk, egg, peanut, wheat, and <lb/>soy if the child has persistent atopic <lb/>dermatitis despite optimized manage-<lb/>ment and topical therapy or the child <lb/>has a reliable history of an immediate <lb/>reaction after ingestion of a specific <lb/>food. However, because false-positive <lb/>tests for food allergy are common, <lb/>care should be taken to ensure that <lb/>children are clinically allergic and not <lb/>just sensitized (as judged by the pres-<lb/>ence of a positive skin-prick test result <lb/>or specific IgE level) to a food before <lb/>dietary removal. <lb/>Diet During Pregnancy and Infancy <lb/>Restricting maternal diet during preg-<lb/>nancy or lactation is not recom-<lb/>mended as a strategy for preventing <lb/>the development or clinical course of <lb/>food allergy. Because of the benefits of <lb/>breastfeeding, it is recommended that <lb/>all infants, including those with a fam-<lb/>ily history of atopic disease, be exclu-<lb/>sively breastfed until 4 to 6 months of <lb/>age unless breastfeeding is contrain-<lb/>dicated for medical reasons. Using soy <lb/>infant formula instead of cow&apos;s milk in-<lb/>fant formula is not recommended as a <lb/>strategy for preventing food allergy in <lb/>at-risk infants. <lb/>Use of hydrolyzed infant formulas, as <lb/>opposed to cow&apos;s milk formula, may be <lb/>considered as a strategy for prevent-<lb/>ing the development of food allergy in <lb/>at-risk infants who are not exclusively <lb/>breastfed. Cost and availability of ex-<lb/>tensively hydrolyzed infant formulas <lb/>may be weighed as prohibitive factors. <lb/>The preventive effects of hydrolyzed in-<lb/>fant formulas on allergy in infants and <lb/>children have varied considerably be-<lb/>tween studies. Evidence from a small <lb/>number of large-population studies in-<lb/>dicates that feeding hydrolyzed versus <lb/>cow&apos;s milk infant formulas to at-risk <lb/>infants may reduce, albeit to a small <lb/>extent, allergy in infants and children <lb/>and cow&apos;s milk allergy in infants. None <lb/>of the studies showed reduction in <lb/>allergy to foods other than cow&apos;s <lb/>milk. 20-23 There is no evidence to sug-<lb/>gest that exclusive feeding with a hy-<lb/>drolyzed infant formula is more likely <lb/>to prevent atopic disease than exclu-<lb/>sive breastfeeding. <lb/>In infants, solid-food introduction <lb/>should occur by 4 to 6 months of age. <lb/>Potentially allergenic foods may be in-<lb/>troduced any time afterward. These <lb/>guidelines are in agreement with <lb/>those in the American Academy of Pe-<lb/>diatrics 2008 clinical report. 24 <lb/>Development of Tolerance <lb/>The time course of food allergy resolu-<lb/>tion in children varies according to <lb/>food and may occur during the teen-<lb/>age years. Most children with food al-<lb/>lergy eventually tolerate cow&apos;s milk, <lb/>egg, soy, and wheat; far fewer will <lb/>eventually tolerate peanuts, tree nuts, <lb/>fish, and shellfish. Generally, risk fac-<lb/>tors for persistence of food allergy are <lb/>the presence of high initial levels of <lb/>specific IgE antibodies, additional <lb/>atopic disease, or allergy to more than <lb/>1 food. For many food-allergic patients, <lb/>specific IgE antibodies to foods appear <lb/>within 2 years after birth. Levels may <lb/>increase or decrease. In children, a de-<lb/>crease in food-specific IgE levels is of-<lb/>ten a marker for the onset of toler-<lb/>ance, although with some foods, <lb/>allergy persists despite a decrease in <lb/>specific IgE. Similarly, a reduction in <lb/>wheal size after a skin-prick test may <lb/>be a marker for the onset of tolerance, <lb/>although skin-prick test response can <lb/>remain positive long after the food is <lb/>safely consumed. 3 <lb/>DIAGNOSIS OF IgE-MEDIATED FOOD <lb/>ALLERGY <lb/>IgE-mediated food allergy should be <lb/>suspected in children who have expe-<lb/>rienced anaphylaxis or the symptoms <lb/>listed in Table 1 within minutes to <lb/>hours of ingesting food, especially if <lb/>the symptoms occur repeatedly or in <lb/>young children. 3 Food allergy should <lb/>also be suspected in infants, young <lb/>children, and selected older children <lb/>who have been diagnosed with <lb/>moderate-to-severe atopic dermatitis, <lb/>eosinophilic esophagitis, gastritis, en-<lb/>teritis or enterocolitis, enteropathy, <lb/>or allergic proctocolitis. With IgE-<lb/>mediated food allergy, allergic reac-<lb/>tions can occur within minutes to a <lb/>few hours. 3 Mixed IgE-and non-IgE-<lb/>mediated food allergy, such as eosino-<lb/>philic esophagitis, should be sus-<lb/>pected when symptoms affect the <lb/>gastrointestinal tract, are of a more <lb/>chronic nature, do not resolve rapidly, <lb/>and are not closely associated with in-<lb/>gestion of an offending food. <lb/>Although medical history and physical <lb/>examination are mainstays in diagnos-<lb/>ing food allergy, they are not sufficient <lb/>for diagnosis and should be consid-<lb/>ered in combination with diagnostic <lb/>testing. Skin-prick tests or measure-<lb/>ment of specific IgE level are recom-<lb/>mended for identifying foods that may <lb/>provoke allergic reactions, but the <lb/>tests (either alone or in combination) <lb/>are not diagnostic of food allergy. Nei-<lb/>ther intradermal testing nor measure-<lb/>ment of total serum IgE level is recom-<lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/></note>

			<page>957 <lb/></page>

			<body>mended for use in diagnosing food <lb/>allergy. The atopy patch test should not <lb/>be used in the routine evaluation of <lb/>food allergy. <lb/>Verification of clinical reactivity re-<lb/>quires well-designed oral food-<lb/>challenge testing. 25-31 The DBPCFC is <lb/>the gold standard for diagnosis, par-<lb/>ticularly in research studies. DBPCFC <lb/>can be useful for ruling out foods that <lb/>do not cause allergy; in several studies <lb/>that used DBPCFC, only approximately <lb/>one-third of the suspected foods were <lb/>confirmed to be allergenic. Open food <lb/>challenges can help identify which <lb/>food(s) are causing an allergic reac-<lb/>tion if the patient&apos;s history and results <lb/>from diagnostic tests are not clear. <lb/>Open food challenges can also be used <lb/>if the child is likely outgrowing the food <lb/>allergy. In older children, single-blind <lb/>food challenges or DBPCFCs might be <lb/>necessary to minimize patient and phy-<lb/>sician bias. In the case of postprandial <lb/>exercise-induced reactions, food chal-<lb/>lenge should be followed by exercise. 32 <lb/>Because of the inherent risk, an oral <lb/>food challenge must be conducted at a <lb/>medical facility that has onsite medical <lb/>supervision and appropriate medi-<lb/>cines and devices (Table 2). <lb/>DIAGNOSIS OF NON-IgE-MEDIATED <lb/>FOOD ALLERGY <lb/>Before a diagnostic workup, it may be <lb/>difficult to distinguish an IgE-mediated <lb/>allergy from a non-IgE-mediated al-<lb/>lergy on the basis of medical history <lb/>and physical examination alone. A <lb/>number of diagnostic tools have been <lb/>suggested for use in diagnosing non-<lb/>IgE-mediated reactions, including food <lb/>challenges, contact dermatitis patch <lb/>testing, and atopy patch tests. Food <lb/>challenges are recommended for diag-<lb/>nosis if the clinical history and labora-<lb/>tory studies are not definitive and for <lb/>determining when the disease has <lb/>been outgrown. 3 The other diagnostic <lb/>tests have not been validated and are <lb/>not recommended. <lb/>Eosinophilic Gastrointestinal <lb/>Diseases <lb/>Skin-prick tests, specific IgE tests, and <lb/>atopy patch tests may be helpful in <lb/>identifying foods that are associated <lb/>with eosinophilic esophagitis, but <lb/>these tests alone are not sufficient for <lb/>diagnosing food allergy. The role of <lb/>these tests in diagnosing other eosin-<lb/>ophilic gastrointestinal diseases has <lb/>not been established. <lb/>Food Protein-Induced <lb/>Enterocolitis Syndrome <lb/>Medical history and oral food chal-<lb/>lenge should be used to diagnose food <lb/>protein-induced enterocolitis syn-<lb/>drome. However, when infants or chil-<lb/>dren have experienced hypotensive ep-<lb/>isodes or multiple reactions to the <lb/>same food, a diagnosis may be made <lb/>on the basis of a convincing history <lb/>TABLE 1 Symptoms of Food-Induced Allergic Reactions <lb/>Target Organ <lb/>Immediate Symptoms <lb/>Delayed Symptoms <lb/>Cutaneous <lb/>Erythema <lb/>Erythema <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Flushing <lb/>Urticaria <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Morbilliform eruption <lb/>Morbilliform eruption <lb/>Angioedema <lb/>Angioedema <lb/>Eczematous rash <lb/>Ocular <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Conjunctival erythema <lb/>Conjunctival erythema <lb/>Tearing <lb/>Tearing <lb/>Periorbital edema <lb/>Periorbital edema <lb/>Upper respiratory <lb/>Nasal congestion <lb/>Pruritus <lb/>Rhinorrhea <lb/>Sneezing <lb/>Laryngeal edema <lb/>Hoarseness <lb/>Dry staccato cough <lb/>Lower respiratory <lb/>Cough <lb/>Cough, dyspnea, and wheezing <lb/>Chest tightness <lb/>Dyspnea <lb/>Wheezing <lb/>Intercostal retractions <lb/>Accessory muscle use <lb/>Gastrointestinal (oral) <lb/>Angioedema of the lips, tongue, <lb/>or palate <lb/>Oral pruritus <lb/>Tongue swelling <lb/>Gastrointestinal (lower) <lb/>Nausea <lb/>Nausea <lb/>Colicky abdominal pain <lb/>Abdominal pain <lb/>Reflux <lb/>Reflux <lb/>Vomiting <lb/>Vomiting <lb/>Diarrhea <lb/>Diarrhea <lb/>Hematochezia <lb/>Irritability and food refusal with <lb/>weight loss (young children) <lb/>Cardiovascular <lb/>Tachycardia (occasionally <lb/>bradycardia in anaphylaxis) <lb/>Hypotension <lb/>Dizziness <lb/>Fainting <lb/>Loss of consciousness <lb/>Miscellaneous <lb/>Uterine contractions <lb/>Sense of &quot;impending doom&quot; <lb/>Reproduced with permission from Elsevier Limited: NIAID-Sponsored Expert Panel; Boyce JA, Assa&apos;ad A, Burks AW, et al. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 2010;126(suppl 6):S19. <lb/></body>

			<page>958 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BURKS et al <lb/></note>

			<body>and absence of symptoms after elimi-<lb/>nating the trigger food. <lb/>Food Protein-Induced Allergic <lb/>Proctocolitis <lb/>The diagnosis of allergic proctocolitis <lb/>should be made on the basis of medi-<lb/>cal history, resolution of symptoms af-<lb/>ter eliminating the causative food, <lb/>and/or recurrence of symptoms after <lb/>oral food challenge. <lb/>MANAGEMENT OF FOOD ALLERGY <lb/>Dietary Avoidance <lb/>Children with documented IgE-<lb/>mediated or non-IgE-mediated food al-<lb/>lergy should avoid ingesting their spe-<lb/>cific allergens. Carefully planned <lb/>allergen-free diets can provide suffi-<lb/>cient nutrients to maintain a healthy <lb/>and active life. For children without <lb/>documented or proven food allergy, <lb/>avoiding potentially allergenic foods is <lb/>not recommended as a means of man-<lb/>aging atopic dermatitis, asthma, or eo-<lb/>sinophilic esophagitis. <lb/>Nutritional counseling and regular <lb/>growth monitoring are recommended <lb/>for all children with food allergy. Chil-<lb/>dren with food allergy and their care-<lb/>givers should receive education and <lb/>training on interpreting food labels <lb/>and recognizing food-allergen ingredi-<lb/>ents. Products with precautionary la-<lb/>beling, such as &quot;this product may con-<lb/>tain trace amounts of allergen,&quot; <lb/>should be avoided because of the <lb/>small but significant risk of actual food <lb/>contamination. The Food Allergy and <lb/>Anaphylaxis Network (www.foodallergy. <lb/>org) provides practical information <lb/>on recognizing and avoiding food <lb/>allergens. <lb/>Retesting <lb/>Tolerance to cow&apos;s milk and egg gener-<lb/>ally occurs at an earlier age than to <lb/>peanut and tree nuts. 33-41 Insufficient <lb/>data exist to recommend specific opti-<lb/>mal intervals for food-allergy follow-up <lb/>testing. The interval depends on the <lb/>food, the child&apos;s age, and the interven-<lb/>ing medical history. Annual testing in <lb/>younger children is often done for <lb/>cow&apos;s milk, egg, soy, or wheat allergy. <lb/>The testing interval is more commonly <lb/>every 2 to 3 years for older children or <lb/>those with allergy to peanut, tree nuts, <lb/>fish, or crustacean shellfish. <lb/>Medications <lb/>There are currently no recommended <lb/>medications for preventing IgE-or <lb/>non-IgE-mediated food-induced aller-<lb/>gic reactions. Epinephrine is the main-<lb/>stay for the treatment of acute, sys-<lb/>temic allergic reactions. Use of <lb/>antihistamines remains the mainstay <lb/>of managing symptoms of nonsevere <lb/>allergic reactions. 3 Allergen-specific <lb/>oral and sublingual immunotherapy <lb/>have been used for inducing clinical <lb/>desensitization to foods (for review <lb/>see ref 42 ), but this approach carries <lb/>the risk of severe reactions and is not <lb/>recommended for clinical practice at <lb/>this time. Immunotherapy with cross-<lb/>reactive allergens is not recom-<lb/>mended for treating IgE-mediated food <lb/>allergy. <lb/>Quality-of-Life Issues <lb/>Food allergy can increase anxiety and <lb/>diminish quality of life for patients and <lb/>their families. 43,44 Patients and caregiv-<lb/>ers should be provided culturally and <lb/>age-appropriate information on food-<lb/>allergen avoidance and emergency <lb/>management. As children transition <lb/>into adolescence and adulthood, they <lb/>have increased responsibility regard-<lb/>ing food selection and should be coun-<lb/>seled on strategies for avoiding poten-<lb/>tially allergenic foods in various <lb/>settings. Patients can be referred to <lb/>the Consortium of Food Allergy Re-<lb/>search&apos;s online educational program <lb/>(https://web.emmes.com/study/cofar/ <lb/>EducationProgram.htm). <lb/>Egg-Containing Vaccines <lb/>Several vaccines are grown in chick <lb/>embryos or embryonic tissues and <lb/>contain egg protein (Table 3). However, <lb/>some of these vaccines, such as mea-<lb/>sles, mumps, and rubella (MMR), are <lb/>safe for patients with egg allergy. Oth-<lb/>ers are either contraindicated or may <lb/>be used after testing with the vaccine. <lb/>There have been limited studies with <lb/>results that indicate that influenza vac-<lb/>cines may be administered to persons <lb/>with severe egg allergy under appro-<lb/>priate supervision depending on the <lb/>ovalbumin content. 45 Approaches in-<lb/>TABLE 2 Conducting an Oral Food Challenge 3 <lb/>Before the challenge <lb/>Suspected foods should be eliminated from the diet for 2 to 8 wk <lb/>Length of time will depend on the type of food-induced allergic reaction being examined (eg, <lb/>urticaria vs eosinophilic esophagitis) <lb/>In infants, diet can be limited to a hypoallergenic formula <lb/>For exclusively breastfed infants, the suspected food can be eliminated from the mother&apos;s diet <lb/>Document any significant improvements as a result of dietary elimination <lb/>If dietary elimination has led to significant improvement, the challenge test may be carried out while <lb/>the patient is on minimal or no medication for treating allergy symptoms <lb/>The test should be designed with supervision from medical personnel with experience in carrying out <lb/>challenges <lb/>During the challenge <lb/>The challenge should be carried out by medical personnel with experience in performing food <lb/>challenges <lb/>Oral food challenge begins with a low dose (intended to be lower than a dose that can induce a <lb/>reaction) <lb/>While monitoring for any allergic symptoms, the dose is gradually increased until a cumulative dose at <lb/>least equivalent to a standard portion for age is consumed <lb/>Treatment for reactions, including anaphylaxis, must be available for immediate administration <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/></note>

			<page>959 <lb/></page>

			<body>clude full or split dosing, possibly with <lb/>vaccine testing. 46-49 There have been a <lb/>number of study reports that have <lb/>been published or are coming that will <lb/>likely change these recommendations <lb/>in the next few years. <lb/>DIAGNOSIS AND MANAGEMENT OF <lb/>FOOD-INDUCED ANAPHYLAXIS <lb/>Anaphylaxis is a serious allergic reac-<lb/>tion that is rapid in onset and may <lb/>cause death. 50,51 IgE-mediated food-<lb/>induced anaphylaxis is believed to in-<lb/>volve systemic mediator release from <lb/>sensitized mast cells and basophils. 52 <lb/>Although prompt recognition and man-<lb/>agement of anaphylaxis are essential <lb/>for a good treatment outcome, 53 ana-<lb/>phylaxis is significantly underrecog-<lb/>nized and undertreated. 50,54-56 <lb/>Diagnosis of Anaphylaxis <lb/>Diagnostic criteria for anaphylaxis are <lb/>detailed in Table 4. The signs and <lb/>symptoms of food-induced anaphy-<lb/>laxis are the same as those of anaphy-<lb/>laxis in general 53,57-61 : <lb/>• Cutaneous symptoms such as flush-<lb/>ing, pruritus, urticaria, and angio-<lb/>edema: cutaneous symptoms occur <lb/>in most patients, but 10% to 20% of <lb/>cases (including many fatal and <lb/>near-fatal reactions) involve no cu-<lb/>taneous manifestations. <lb/>• Respiratory symptoms such as na-<lb/>sal congestion and rhinorrhea, <lb/>throat pruritus and laryngeal <lb/>edema, stridor, choking, wheeze, <lb/>cough, and dyspnea: up to 70% <lb/>of cases involve respiratory <lb/>symptoms. <lb/>• Gastrointestinal symptoms such as <lb/>cramping, abdominal pain, nausea, <lb/>emesis, and diarrhea: up to 40% <lb/>of cases involve gastrointestinal <lb/>symptoms. <lb/>• Cardiovascular symptoms such as <lb/>dizziness, tachycardia, hypotension, <lb/>and hypotonia: up to 35% of cases <lb/>involve cardiovascular symptoms. <lb/>• Anxiety, mental confusion, lethargy, <lb/>and seizures. <lb/>Time Course of Food-Induced <lb/>Anaphylaxis <lb/>In food-induced anaphylaxis, exposure <lb/>to a food allergen is followed by a rapid <lb/>onset of symptoms over minutes to <lb/>several hours. Death caused by food-<lb/>induced anaphylaxis can occur within <lb/>30 minutes to 2 hours of exposure 10,11,62 <lb/>TABLE 4 Diagnostic Criteria for Anaphylaxis 3 <lb/>The presence of any 1 of these 3 criteria indicates that anaphylaxis is highly likely: <lb/>1. Acute onset of an illness (over minutes to several hours) involving skin, mucosal tissue, or both (eg, <lb/>generalized hives, pruritus or flushing, swollen lips-tongue-uvula) and at least 1 of the following: <lb/>Respiratory compromise (eg, dyspnea, wheeze-bronchospasm, stridor, reduced peak expiratory flow <lb/>rate, hypoxemia) <lb/>Reduced blood pressure or associated symptoms of end-organ dysfunction (eg, hypotonia [circulatory <lb/>collapse], syncope, incontinence) or <lb/>2. Ն2 of the following that occur rapidly after exposure to a likely allergen for that patient (minutes to <lb/>several hours): <lb/>Involvement of the skin-mucosal tissue (eg, generalized hives, itch-flush, swollen lips-tongue-uvula) <lb/>Respiratory compromise (eg, dyspnea, wheeze, bronchospasm, stridor, reduced peak expiratory flow <lb/>rate, hypoxemia) <lb/>Reduced blood pressure or associated symptoms of end-organ dysfunction (eg, hypotonia, syncope, <lb/>incontinence) <lb/>Persistent gastrointestinal symptoms (eg, crampy abdominal pain, vomiting) or <lb/>3. Reduced blood pressure after exposure to a known allergen for that patient (minutes to several <lb/>hours); in infants and children, reduced blood pressure is defined by the following: <lb/>Low systolic blood pressure (age-specific) or Ͼ30% decrease in systolic blood pressure <lb/>Low systolic blood pressure is defined as follows: <lb/>Ͻ70 mm Hg for ages 1 mo to 1 y <lb/>Ͻ(70 mm Hg plus twice the age) for ages 1-10 y <lb/>Ͻ90 mm Hg for ages 11-17 y <lb/>Note that in infants and young children, hypotension may be a late manifestation of hypovolemic shock. Tachycardia, in the <lb/>absence of hypotension, also may indicate shock. 73 <lb/>TABLE 3 Recommendations for Administering Egg-Containing Vaccines to Egg-Allergic Patients 3 <lb/>Vaccine <lb/>Recommendation <lb/>Notes <lb/>MMR or MMRV <lb/>Safe for children with egg allergy, even those with a history of severe <lb/>reactions <lb/>-<lb/>Influenza <lb/>(inactivated or live-attenuated) <lb/>Not recommended for patients who have a history of severe reactions <lb/>to egg or egg protein; severe reactions include a history of hives, <lb/>angioedema, allergic asthma, or systemic anaphylaxis to egg or <lb/>chicken proteins; less-severe or local manifestations of allergy to <lb/>egg or feather are not contraindications <lb/>Live-attenuated vaccine is not licensed for use in <lb/>patients with asthma 72 <lb/>Yellow fever <lb/>Do not administer to patients with a history of hives, angioedema, <lb/>allergic asthma, or systemic anaphylaxis to egg proteins unless an <lb/>allergy evaluation and testing with the vaccine are performed first <lb/>-<lb/>Rabies <lb/>Do not administer to patients with a history of hives, angioedema, <lb/>allergic asthma, or systemic anaphylaxis to egg proteins unless an <lb/>allergy evaluation and testing with the vaccine are performed first <lb/>1 rabies vaccine (Imovax [Sanofi Pasteur, <lb/>Swiftwater, PA]) is not made in chick embryos <lb/>and does not contain egg protein; this vaccine <lb/>is not contraindicated in egg-allergic people <lb/>MMR indicates measles, mumps, and rubella; MMRV, MMR with varicella. <lb/></body>

			<page>960 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BURKS et al <lb/></note>

			<body>and usually results from cardiorespi-<lb/>ratory compromise. 58 Food-induced <lb/>anaphylaxis also can have a milder <lb/>course and resolve spontaneously. <lb/>The time course of an anaphylactic re-<lb/>action may be uniphasic, biphasic, or <lb/>protracted. A uniphasic reaction oc-<lb/>curs immediately after exposure, re-<lb/>solves with or without treatment <lb/>within the first minutes to hours, and <lb/>does not recur. In a biphasic reaction, <lb/>a recurrence of symptoms develops af-<lb/>ter apparent resolution of the initial <lb/>reaction. Biphasic reactions have been <lb/>reported to occur in 1% to 20% of ana-<lb/>phylaxis episodes, and they typically <lb/>occur ϳ8 hours after the first reac-<lb/>tion, although they have been reported <lb/>to occur up to 72 hours later. 11,63,64 A <lb/>protracted reaction is any anaphylaxis <lb/>episode that lasts for hours or days <lb/>after the initial reaction. 11 <lb/>Risk Factors for Anaphylaxis and <lb/>Resulting Fatality <lb/>Those at the highest risk for life-<lb/>threatening food-induced anaphylaxis <lb/>are adolescents and young adults; peo-<lb/>ple with known food allergy and a pre-<lb/>vious history of anaphylaxis; and peo-<lb/>ple with asthma, especially with poorly <lb/>controlled symptoms. Peanuts and <lb/>tree nuts cause the majority of fatali-<lb/>ties from food-induced anaphy-<lb/>laxis. 10,11,62 Fatalities are also associ-<lb/>ated with delayed use or improper <lb/>dosing of epinephrine. <lb/>MANAGEMENT OF PATIENTS AT <lb/>RISK FOR ANAPHYLAXIS <lb/>Patients with the following should be <lb/>prescribed an epinephrine autoinjec-<lb/>tor: a previous systemic allergic reac-<lb/>tion; food allergy and asthma; or a <lb/>known food allergy to peanut, tree <lb/>nuts, fish, or crustacean shellfish. In <lb/>addition, some consideration should <lb/>be given to prescribing an epinephrine <lb/>autoinjector for all patients with food <lb/>allergy who have IgE-mediated reac-<lb/>tions, because it is impossible to pre-<lb/>dict the severity of subsequent <lb/>reactions. <lb/>Patients should be verbally instructed <lb/>on the proper use of epinephrine auto-<lb/>injectors. They should also receive an <lb/>instructional video, if available, and a <lb/>written anaphylaxis emergency action <lb/>plan. Patients should be instructed on <lb/>the value of medical identification jew-<lb/>elry for easy recognition of their poten-<lb/>tial for anaphylaxis and food-allergen <lb/>triggers. Patients should be told the <lb/>importance of carrying epinephrine at <lb/>all times and of making sure that fam-<lb/>ily and friends are aware of the risks of <lb/>anaphylaxis, the patient&apos;s triggers, and <lb/>how to administer epinephrine. If al-<lb/>lowed by state law, students should be <lb/>advised to carry their epinephrine au-<lb/>toinjector at school and at all school-<lb/>related events. <lb/>Patients and family members should <lb/>be advised to regularly check the epi-<lb/>nephrine autoinjector expiration dates <lb/>(which expire after 1 year) and to <lb/>verify that the liquid remains clear. <lb/>Ideally, the prescribing physician&apos;s of-<lb/>fice should see patients annually or no-<lb/>tify patients (or their parents or guard-<lb/>ians) by telephone or mail that their <lb/>autoinjector will soon reach its expira-<lb/>tion date. Patients can be encouraged <lb/>to register for automated pharmacy <lb/>reminders for epinephrine renewal. <lb/>Epinephrine autoinjectors are temper-<lb/>ature sensitive and should be stored at <lb/>room temperature to prevent degra-<lb/>dation of the medication. <lb/>Treatment of Acute, Life-<lb/>Threatening, Food-Induced Allergic <lb/>Reactions <lb/>For food-induced anaphylaxis, prompt <lb/>and rapid treatment with epinephrine <lb/>is paramount. Delayed administration <lb/>of epinephrine has been implicated in <lb/>contributing to fatalities. 10,11,16,62 Initial <lb/>management of anaphylaxis should in-<lb/>clude elimination of the allergen and <lb/>intramuscular injection of epinephrine <lb/>(Table 5). Autoinjector dosing for epi-<lb/>nephrine is 0.15 mg for children who <lb/>weigh 10 to 25 kg and 0.3 mg for those <lb/>who weigh Ͼ25 kg. These steps should <lb/>be followed by a call for an emergency <lb/>medical team, placement of the patient <lb/>in a recumbent position with lower ex-<lb/>tremities elevated (if tolerated), and <lb/>adjunctive therapy (Table 5). If a pa-<lb/>tient responds poorly to the initial <lb/>dose of epinephrine or has ongoing or <lb/>progressive symptoms, repeated dos-<lb/>ing may be required after 5 to 15 <lb/>minutes. <lb/>Given their anti-inflammatory proper-<lb/>ties, systemic corticosteroids are of-<lb/>ten recommended for preventing bi-<lb/>phasic or protracted food-induced <lb/>allergic reactions, but evidence to sup-<lb/>port their use is lacking. 65 <lb/>Observation Period After Food-<lb/>Induced Anaphylaxis <lb/>There is no consensus in the literature <lb/>regarding the optimal time duration <lb/>for observing a patient who has been <lb/>successfully treated for anaphylaxis <lb/>before discharge. All patients who re-<lb/>ceive epinephrine for food-induced <lb/>anaphylaxis should proceed to an <lb/>emergency facility for observation <lb/>and possibly additional treatment. A <lb/>reasonable length of time for obser-<lb/>vation of most patients who have ex-<lb/>perienced anaphylaxis is 4 to 6 <lb/>hours; a prolonged observation time <lb/>or hospital admission is reasonable <lb/>for patients with severe or refractory <lb/>symptoms. 51,61 <lb/>Discharge Plan After Treatment for <lb/>Food-Induced Anaphylaxis <lb/>All patients who have experienced ana-<lb/>phylaxis should be sent home with (1) <lb/>an anaphylaxis emergency action plan, <lb/>(2) an epinephrine autoinjector (2 <lb/>doses), (3) a plan for monitoring auto-<lb/>injector expiration dates, (4) a plan for <lb/>arranging further evaluation, and (5) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/></note>

			<page>961 <lb/></page>

			<body>printed information about anaphylaxis <lb/>and its treatment 66 (Table 5). Advice <lb/>should be provided to the patient re-<lb/>garding follow-up with his or her pri-<lb/>mary health care professional within 1 <lb/>to 2 weeks after a food-induced ana-<lb/>phylaxis event. The patient may be re-<lb/>ferred to a specialist such as an aller-<lb/>gist or immunologist for further <lb/>evaluation. <lb/>Management of Milder Acute Food-<lb/>Induced Allergic Reactions in <lb/>Health Care Settings <lb/>Milder forms of allergic reactions, <lb/>such as flushing, urticaria, isolated <lb/>mild angioedema, and symptoms of <lb/>oral allergy syndrome, can be treated <lb/>with H 1 and H 2 antihistamine medica-<lb/>tions. 67,68 When antihistamines alone <lb/>are given, ongoing observation and <lb/>monitoring are warranted to ensure a <lb/>lack of progression to more significant <lb/>symptoms of anaphylaxis. If progres-<lb/>sion or increased severity is noted, epi-<lb/>nephrine should be administered im-<lb/>mediately. If there is history of a <lb/>previous severe allergic reaction, epi-<lb/>nephrine should be administered <lb/>promptly and earlier in the course of <lb/>treatment (eg, at the onset of even <lb/>mild symptoms). <lb/>KNOWLEDGE GAPS AND RESEARCH <lb/>PRIORITIES <lb/>In developing these guidelines, the ex-<lb/>pert panel noted several knowledge <lb/>gaps and priority areas of research re-<lb/>lated to pediatric care. Published data <lb/>on remission rates for specific food al-<lb/>lergies are lacking and even contradic-<lb/>tory. For example, Sampson 35 has esti-<lb/>mated that milk tolerance develops in <lb/>80% of patients by the age of 5 years, <lb/>whereas Skripak et al 41 concluded that <lb/>only 5% of patients were tolerant by <lb/>the age of 4 and that 21% were tolerant <lb/>by the age of 8. A better understanding <lb/>of remission rates and time frames <lb/>would help determine optimal inter-<lb/>vals for follow-up testing. The expert <lb/>TABLE 5 Pharmacologic Management of Anaphylaxis <lb/>With the exception of epinephrine as first-line treatment, these treatments often occur concomitantly and <lb/>are not meant to be sequential. <lb/>In an outpatient setting <lb/>• First-line treatment <lb/>-Epinephrine, IM; auto-injector or 1:1000 solution <lb/>X Weight 10 to 25 kg: 0.15 mg epinephrine autoinjector, IM (anterior-lateral thigh) <lb/>X Weight Ͼ25 kg: 0.3 mg epinephrine autoinjector, IM (anterior-lateral thigh) <lb/>X Epinephrine (1:1000 solution) (IM), 0.01 mg/kg per dose; maximum dose, 0.5 mg per dose <lb/>(anterior-lateral thigh) <lb/>-Epinephrine doses may need to be repeated every 5-15 minutes <lb/>• Adjunctive treatment <lb/>-Bronchodilator (␤2-agonist): albuterol <lb/>X MDI (child: 4-8 puffs; adult: 8 puffs) or <lb/>X Nebulized solution (child: 1.5 mL; adult: 3 mL) every 20 minutes or continuously as needed <lb/>-H 1 antihistamine: diphenhydramine <lb/>X 1 to 2 mg/kg per dose <lb/>X Maximum dose, 50 mg IV or oral (oral liquid is more readily absorbed than tablets) <lb/>X Alternative dosing may be with a less-sedating second generation antihistamine <lb/>-Supplemental oxygen therapy <lb/>-IV fluids in large volumes if patient presents with orthostasis, hypotension, or incomplete response <lb/>to IM epinephrine <lb/>-Place the patient in recumbent position if tolerated, with the lower extremities elevated <lb/>In a hospital-based setting <lb/>• First-line treatment <lb/>-Epinephrine IM as above, consider continuous epinephrine infusion for persistent hypotension <lb/>(ideally with continuous non-invasive monitoring of blood pressure and heart rate); alternatives <lb/>are endotracheal or intra-osseous epinephrine <lb/>• Adjunctive treatment <lb/>-Bronchodilator (␤2-agonist): albuterol <lb/>X MDI (child: 4-8 puffs; adult: 8 puffs) or <lb/>X Nebulized solution (child: 1.5 mL; adult: 3 mL) every 20 minutes or continuously as needed <lb/>-H 1 antihistamine: diphenhydramine <lb/>X 1 to 2 mg/kg per dose <lb/>X Maximum dose, 50 mg IV or oral (oral liquid is more readily absorbed than tablets) <lb/>X Alternative dosing may be with a less-sedating second generation antihistamine <lb/>-H 2 antihistamine: ranitidine <lb/>X 1 to 2 mg/kg per dose <lb/>X Maximum dose, 75 to 150 mg oral and IV <lb/>-Corticosteroids <lb/>X Prednisone at 1 mg/kg with a maximum dose of 60 to 80 mg oral or <lb/>X Methylprednisolone at 1 mg/kg with a maximum dose of 60 to 80 mg IV <lb/>-Vasopressors (other than epinephrine) for refractory hypotension, titrate to effect <lb/>-Glucagon for refractory hypotension, titrate to effect <lb/>X Child: 20-30 mcg/kg <lb/>X Adult: 1-5 mg <lb/>X Dose may be repeated or followed by infusion of 5-15 mcg/min <lb/>-Atropine for bradycardia, titrate to effect <lb/>-Supplemental oxygen therapy <lb/>-IV fluids in large volumes if patients present with orthostasis, hypotension, or incomplete response <lb/>to IM epinephrine <lb/>-Place the patient in recumbent position if tolerated, with the lower extremities elevated <lb/>To instruct to patients at discharge <lb/>• First-line treatment <lb/>-Epinephrine auto-injector prescription (2 doses) and instructions <lb/>-Education on avoidance of allergen <lb/>-Follow-up with primary care physician <lb/>-Consider referral to an allergist <lb/>• Adjunctive treatment <lb/>-H 1 antihistamine: diphenhydramine every 6 hours for 2-3 days; alternative dosing with a non-<lb/>sedating second generation antihistamine <lb/>-H 2 antihistamine: ranitidine twice daily for 2-3 days <lb/>-Corticosteroid: prednisone daily for 2-3 days <lb/>IM indicates intramuscular; IV, intravenous; MDI, metered-dose inhaler. <lb/>Reproduced with permission from Elsevier Limited: NIAID-Sponsored Expert Panel; Boyce JA, Assa&apos;ad A, Burks AW, et al. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 2010;126(suppl 6):S39. <lb/></body>

			<page>962 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BURKS et al <lb/></note>

			<body>panel noted that the quality of evi-<lb/>dence was low in regards to whether <lb/>exclusive breastfeeding can help pre-<lb/>vent atopic disease, the optimal timing <lb/>of introduction of potentially aller-<lb/>genic foods to infants, and whether <lb/>food allergy testing should precede in-<lb/>troducing allergenic foods to children <lb/>at high risk. <lb/>Both peanut allergy 69 and atopic der-<lb/>matitis 70,71 have been associated with <lb/>loss-of-function mutations in the epi-<lb/>dermal barrier protein filaggrin, <lb/>which indicates that impaired skin <lb/>barrier function has a role in atopic <lb/>diseases. However, whether filaggrin <lb/>mutations are common among pa-<lb/>tients with both atopic dermatitis and <lb/>food allergy is unknown. <lb/>Although not noted in the guidelines, <lb/>transitions in care, such as an adoles-<lb/>cent leaving a pediatric clinic or a child <lb/>leaving an academic center, are points <lb/>of concern for the pediatric popula-<lb/>tion, because continuous care is cru-<lb/>cial for the safety of patients with food <lb/>allergy. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>We thank the following people for their <lb/>extensive contributions in developing <lb/>the NIAID-sponsored guidelines: Mar-<lb/>shall Plaut, MD, Susan Cooper, MSc, <lb/>Matthew Fenton, PhD, S. Hasan Arshad, <lb/>MBBS, MRCP, DM, FRCP, Sami Bahna, <lb/>MD, DrPH, Lisa Beck, MD, Carol Byrd-<lb/>Bredbenner, PhD, RD, FADA, Carlos Ca-<lb/>margo Jr, MD, DrPH, Lawrence Eichen-<lb/>field, MD, Glenn Furuta, MD, Jon <lb/>Hanifin, MD, Carol Jones, RN, AE-C, Mon-<lb/>ica Kraft, MD, Bruce Levy, MD, Phil <lb/>Lieberman, MD, Stefano Luccioli, MD, <lb/>Kathleen McCall, BSN, RN, Lynda Sch-<lb/>neider, MD, Ronald Simon, MD, F. Es-<lb/>telle Simons, MD, Stephen Teach, MD, <lb/>MPH, Barbara Yawn, MD, MPH, MSc, <lb/>and Julie Schwaninger, MSc. We also <lb/>thank Anne Muñoz-Furlong for her con-<lb/>tributions to the concept and initiation <lb/>of the process for the NIAID-sponsored <lb/>food allergy guidelines. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>1. Branum AM, Lukacs SL. Food allergy among <lb/>children in the United States. Pediatrics. <lb/>2009;124(6):1549 -1555 <lb/>2. Sicherer SH, Muñoz-Furlong A, Godbold JH, <lb/>Sampson HA. US prevalence of self-<lb/>reported peanut, tree nut, and sesame <lb/>allergy: 11-year follow-up. J Allergy Clin Im-<lb/>munol. 2010;125(6):1322-1326 <lb/>3. NIAID-Sponsored Expert Panel; Boyce JA, <lb/>Assa&apos;ad A, Burks AW, et al. Guidelines for the <lb/>diagnosis and management of food allergy <lb/>in the United States: report of the NIAID-<lb/>sponsored expert panel. J Allergy Clin Im-<lb/>munol. 2010;126(suppl 6):S1-S58 <lb/>4. Sicherer SH, Mahr T; American Academy of <lb/>Pediatrics, Section on Allergy and Immunol-<lb/>ogy. Management of food allergy in the <lb/>school setting. Pediatrics. 2010;126(6): <lb/>1232-1239 <lb/>5. Rona RJ, Keil T, Summers C, et al. The <lb/>prevalence of food allergy: a meta-<lb/>analysis. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2007; <lb/>120(3):638 -646 <lb/>6. Emery NL, Vollmer WM, Buist AS, Osborne <lb/>ML. Self-reported food reactions and their <lb/>associations with asthma. West J Nurs Res. <lb/>1996;18(6):643-654 <lb/>7. Wang J, Visness CM, Sampson HA. Food al-<lb/>lergen sensitization in inner-city children <lb/>with asthma. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2005; <lb/>115(5):1076 -1080 <lb/>8. Berns SH, Halm EA, Sampson HA, Sicherer <lb/>SH, Busse PJ, Wisnivesky JP. Food allergy as <lb/>a risk factor for asthma morbidity in adults. <lb/>J Asthma. 2007;44(5):377-381 <lb/>9. Vogel NM, Katz HT, Lopez R, Lang DM. Food <lb/>allergy is associated with potentially fatal <lb/>childhood asthma. J Asthma. 2008;45(10): <lb/>862-866 <lb/>10. Bock SA, Muñoz-Furlong A, Sampson HA. Fa-<lb/>talities due to anaphylactic reactions to <lb/>foods. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2001;107(1): <lb/>191-193 <lb/>11. Sampson HA, Mendelson L, Rosen JP. Fatal <lb/>and near-fatal anaphylactic reactions to <lb/>food in children and adolescents. N Engl J <lb/>Med. 1992;327(6):380 -384 <lb/>12. Kjellman NI. Atopic disease in seven-year-<lb/>old children: incidence in relation to family <lb/>history. Acta Paediatr Scand. 1977;66(4): <lb/>465-471 <lb/>13. Bousquet J, Kjellman NI. Predictive value of <lb/>tests in childhood allergy. J Allergy Clin Im-<lb/>munol. 1986;78(5 pt 2):1019 -1022 <lb/>14. Halken S, Host A. The lessons of noninter-<lb/>ventional and interventional prospective <lb/>studies on the development of atopic dis-<lb/>ease during childhood. Allergy. 2000;55(9): <lb/>793-802 <lb/>15. Eigenmann PA, Sicherer SH, Borkowski TA, <lb/>Cohen BA, Sampson HA. Prevalence of IgE-<lb/>mediated food allergy among children with <lb/>atopic dermatitis. Pediatrics. 1998;101(3). <lb/>Available at: www.pediatrics.org/cgi/ <lb/>content/full/101/3/e8 <lb/>16. Yunginger JW, Squillace DL, Jones RT, Helm <lb/>RM. Fatal anaphylactic reactions induced by <lb/>peanuts. Allergy Proc. 1989;10(4):249 -253 <lb/>17. Yunginger JW, Sweeney KG, Sturner WQ, et <lb/>al. Fatal food-induced anaphylaxis. JAMA. <lb/>1988;260(10):1450 -1452 <lb/>18. Hourihane JO, Dean TP, Warner JO. Peanut <lb/>allergy in relation to heredity, maternal <lb/>diet, and other atopic diseases: results of a <lb/>questionnaire survey, skin prick testing, <lb/>and food challenges. BMJ. 1996;313(7056): <lb/>518 -521 <lb/>19. Sicherer SH, Furlong TJ, Maes HH, Desnick <lb/>RJ, Sampson HA, Gelb BD. Genetics of peanut <lb/>allergy: a twin study. J Allergy Clin Immunol. <lb/>2000;106(1 pt 1):53-56 <lb/>20. Osborn DA, Sinn J. Formulas containing hy-<lb/>drolysed protein for prevention of allergy <lb/>and food intolerance in infants. Cochrane <lb/>Database Syst Rev. 2006;(4):CD003664 <lb/>21. Hays T, Wood RA. A systematic review of the <lb/>role of hydrolyzed infant formulas in allergy <lb/>prevention. Arch Pediatr Adolesc Med. 2005; <lb/>159(9):810 -816 <lb/>22. American Academy of Pediatrics, Commit-<lb/>tee on Nutrition. Hypoallergenic infant for-<lb/>mulas. Pediatrics. 2000;106(2 pt 1):346 -349 <lb/>23. von Berg A, Koletzko S, Filipiak-Pittroff B, et <lb/>al; German Infant Nutritional Intervention <lb/>Study Group. Certain hydrolyzed formulas <lb/>reduce the incidence of atopic dermatitis <lb/>but not that of asthma: three-year results of <lb/>the German Infant Nutritional Intervention <lb/>Study. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2007;119(3): <lb/>718 -725 <lb/>24. Greer FR, Sicherer SH, Burks AW; American <lb/>Academy of Pediatrics, Committee on <lb/>Nutrition; American Academy of Pediatrics <lb/>Section on Allergy and Immunology. Effects <lb/>of early nutritional interventions on the de-<lb/>velopment of atopic disease in infants and <lb/>children: the role of maternal dietary re-<lb/>striction, breastfeeding, timing of introduc-<lb/>tion of complementary foods, and hydro-<lb/>lyzed formulas. Pediatrics. 2008;121(1): <lb/>183-191 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/></note>

			<page>963 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>25. Bock SA, Buckley J, Holst A, May CD. Proper <lb/>use of skin tests with food extracts in diag-<lb/>nosis of hypersensitivity to food in children. <lb/>Clin Allergy. 1978;8(6):559 -564 <lb/>26. Sampson HA, Albergo R. Comparison of re-<lb/>sults of skin tests, RAST, and double-blind, <lb/>placebo-controlled food challenges in chil-<lb/>dren with atopic dermatitis. J Allergy Clin <lb/>Immunol. 1984;74(1):26 -33 <lb/>27. Sampson HA, Jolie PL. Increased plasma <lb/>histamine concentrations after food chal-<lb/>lenges in children with atopic dermatitis. N <lb/>Engl J Med. 1984;311(6):372-376 <lb/>28. Sicherer SH, Morrow EH, Sampson HA. Dose-<lb/>response in double-blind, placebo-<lb/>controlled oral food challenges in children <lb/>with atopic dermatitis. J Allergy Clin Immu-<lb/>nol. 2000;105(3):582-586 <lb/>29. Hansen TK, Bindslev-Jensen C. Codfish al-<lb/>lergy in adults. Identification and diagnosis. <lb/>Allergy. 1992;47(6):610 -617 <lb/>30. Nørgaard A, Bindslev-Jensen C. Egg and <lb/>milk allergy in adults. Allergy. 1992;47(5): <lb/>503-509 <lb/>31. Nowak-Wegrzyn A, Assa&apos;ad AH, Bahna SL, <lb/>Bock SA, Sicherer SH, Teuber SS. Work <lb/>group report: oral food challenge testing. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 2009;123(6 suppl): <lb/>S365-S383 <lb/>32. Romano A, Di Fonso M, Giuffreda F, et al. <lb/>F o o d -d e p e n d e n t e x e r c i s e -i n d u c e d <lb/>anaphylaxis: clinical and laboratory find-<lb/>ings in 54 subjects. Int Arch Allergy Immu-<lb/>nol. 2001;125(3):264 -272 <lb/>33. Hattevig G, Kjellman B, Björkstén B. Clinical <lb/>symptoms and IgE responses to common <lb/>food proteins and inhalants in the first 7 <lb/>years of life. Clin Allergy. 1987;17(6): <lb/>571-578 <lb/>34. Bock SA, Atkins FM. The natural history of <lb/>peanut allergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 1989; <lb/>83(5):900 -904 <lb/>35. Sampson HA. Food allergy. Part 1: immuno-<lb/>pathogenesis and clinical disorders. J Al-<lb/>lergy Clin Immunol. 1999;103(5 pt 1): <lb/>717-728 <lb/>36. Spergel JM, Beausoleil JL, Pawlowski NA. <lb/>Resolution of childhood peanut allergy. Ann <lb/>Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2000;85(6 pt 1): <lb/>473-476 <lb/>37. Skolnick HS, Conover-Walker MK, Koerner <lb/>CB, Sampson HA, Burks W, Wood RA. The nat-<lb/>ural history of peanut allergy. J Allergy Clin <lb/>Immunol. 2001;107(2):367-374 <lb/>38. Boyano-Martínez T, García-Ara C, Díaz-Pena <lb/>JM, Martín-Esteban M. Prediction of toler-<lb/>ance on the basis of quantification of egg <lb/>white-specific IgE antibodies in children <lb/>with egg allergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. <lb/>2002;110(2):304 -309 <lb/>39. Fleischer DM, Conover-Walker MK, Matsui <lb/>EC, Wood RA. The natural history of tree nut <lb/>allergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2005;116(5): <lb/>1087-1093 <lb/>40. Savage JH, Matsui EC, Skripak JM, Wood RA. <lb/>The natural history of egg allergy. J Allergy <lb/>Clin Immunol. 2007;120(6):1413-1417 <lb/>41. Skripak JM, Matsui EC, Mudd K, Wood RA. <lb/>The natural history of IgE-mediated cow&apos;s <lb/>milk allergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2007; <lb/>120(5):1172-1177 <lb/>42. Burks AW, Laubach S, Jones SM. Oral toler-<lb/>ance, food allergy, and immunotherapy: im-<lb/>plications for future treatment. J Allergy <lb/>Clin Immunol. 2008;121(6):1344 -1350 <lb/>43. King RM, Knibb RC, Hourihane JO. Impact of <lb/>peanut allergy on quality of life, stress and <lb/>anxiety in the family. Allergy. 2009;64(3): <lb/>461-468 <lb/>44. Ostblom E, Egmar AC, Gardulf A, Lilja G, Wick-<lb/>man M. The impact of food hypersensitivity <lb/>reported in 9-year-old children by their par-<lb/>ents on health-related quality of life. Allergy. <lb/>2008;63(2):211-218 <lb/>45. James JM, Zeiger RS, Lester MR, et al. Safe <lb/>administration of influenza vaccine to pa-<lb/>tients with egg allergy. J Pediatr. 1998; <lb/>133(5):624 -628 <lb/>46. Zeiger RS. Current issues with influenza <lb/>vaccination in egg allergy. J Allergy Clin Im-<lb/>munol. 2002;110(6):834 -840 <lb/>47. Chung EY, Huang L, Schneider L. Safety of <lb/>influenza vaccine administration in egg-<lb/>allergic patients. Pediatrics. 2010;125(5). <lb/>Available at: www.pediatrics.org/cgi/ <lb/>content/full/125/5/e1024 <lb/>48. Kletz MR, Holland CL, Mendelson JS, Bielory <lb/>L. Administration of egg-derived vaccines in <lb/>patients with history of egg sensitivity. Ann <lb/>Allergy. 1990;64(6):527-529 <lb/>49. Rank MA, Li JT. Clinical pearls for prevent-<lb/>ing, diagnosing, and treating seasonal and <lb/>2009 H1N1 influenza infection in patients <lb/>with asthma. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2009; <lb/>124(5):1123-1126 <lb/>50. Lieberman P, Camargo CA Jr, Bohlke K, et al. <lb/>Epidemiology of anaphylaxis: findings of the <lb/>American College of Allergy, Asthma and Im-<lb/>munology Epidemiology of Anaphylaxis <lb/>Working Group. Ann Allergy Asthma Immu-<lb/>nol. 2006;97(5):596 -602 <lb/>51. Sampson HA, Muñoz-Furlong A, Campbell RL, <lb/>et al. Second symposium on the definition <lb/>and management of anaphylaxis: summary <lb/>report-second National Institute of Al-<lb/>lergy and Infectious Disease/Food Allergy <lb/>and Anaphylaxis Network symposium. J Al-<lb/>lergy Clin Immunol. 2006;117(2):391-397 <lb/>52. Metcalfe DD, Sampson HA, Simon RA. Food <lb/>Allergy: Adverse Reactions to Foods and <lb/>Food Additives. 4th ed. Walden, MA: Wiley-<lb/>Blackwell; 2008 <lb/>53. Sampson HA, Muñoz-Furlong A, Bock SA, et <lb/>al. Symposium on the definition and man-<lb/>agement of anaphylaxis: summary report. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 2005;115(3):584 -591 <lb/>54. Klein JS, Yocum MW. Underreporting of ana-<lb/>phylaxis in a community emergency room. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 1995;95(2):637-638 <lb/>55. Neugut AI, Ghatak AT, Miller RL. Anaphylaxis <lb/>in the United States: an investigation into its <lb/>epidemiology. Arch Intern Med. 2001;161(1): <lb/>15-21 <lb/>56. Moneret-Vautrin DA, Morisset M, Flabbee J, <lb/>Beaudouin E, Kanny G. Epidemiology of life-<lb/>threatening and lethal anaphylaxis: a re-<lb/>view. Allergy. 2005;60(4):443-451 <lb/>57. Helbling A, Hurni T, Mueller UR, Pichler WJ. <lb/>Incidence of anaphylaxis with circulatory <lb/>symptoms: a study over a 3-year period <lb/>comprising 940,000 inhabitants of the <lb/>Swiss Canton Bern. Clin Exp Allergy. 2004; <lb/>34(2):285-290 <lb/>58. Keet CA, Wood RA. Food allergy and anaphy-<lb/>laxis. Immunol Allergy Clin North Am. 2007; <lb/>27(2):193-212 <lb/>59. Oswalt ML, Kemp SF. Anaphylaxis: office <lb/>management and prevention. Immunol Al-<lb/>lergy Clin North Am. 2007;27(2):177-191 <lb/>60. Simons FE. Anaphylaxis, killer allergy: long-<lb/>term management in the community. J Al-<lb/>lergy Clin Immunol. 2006;117(2):367-377 <lb/>61. Joint Task Force on Practice Parameters; <lb/>American Academy of Allergy, Asthma and <lb/>Immunology; Joint Council of Allergy, <lb/>Asthma and Immunology. The diagnosis and <lb/>management of anaphylaxis: an updated <lb/>practice parameter. J Allergy Clin Immunol. <lb/>2005;115(3 suppl 2):S483-S523 <lb/>62. Bock SA, Muñoz-Furlong A, Sampson HA. Fur-<lb/>ther fatalities caused by anaphylactic reac-<lb/>tions to food, 2001-2006. J Allergy Clin Im-<lb/>munol. 2007;119(4):1016 -1018 <lb/>63. Lee JM, Greenes DS. Biphasic anaphylactic <lb/>reactions in pediatrics. Pediatrics. 2000; <lb/>106(4):762-766 <lb/>64. Lieberman P. Biphasic anaphylactic reac-<lb/>tions. Ann Allergy Asthma Immunol. 2005; <lb/>95(3):217-226 <lb/>65. Choo KJ, Simons E, Sheikh A. Glucocorticoids <lb/>for the treatment of anaphylaxis: Cochrane <lb/>systematic review. Allergy. 2010;65(10): <lb/>1205-1211 <lb/>66. Simons FE, Clark S, Camargo CA Jr. Anaphy-<lb/>laxis in the community: learning from the <lb/>survivors. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2009; <lb/>124(2):301-306 <lb/>67. Sampson HA. Update on food allergy. J Al-<lb/>lergy Clin Immunol. 2004;113(5):805-819 <lb/></listBibl>

			<page>964 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">BURKS et al <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>68. Runge JW, Martinez JC, Caravati EM, Wil-<lb/>liamson SG, Hartsell SC. Histamine antago-<lb/>nists in the treatment of acute allergic re-<lb/>actions. Ann Emerg Med. 1992;21(3): <lb/>237-242 <lb/>69. Brown SJ, Asai Y, Cordell HJ, et al. Loss-of-<lb/>function variants in the filaggrin gene are <lb/>a significant risk factor for peanut al-<lb/>lergy. J Allergy Clin Immunol. 2011;127(3): <lb/>661-667 <lb/>70. Palmer CN, Irvine AD, Terron-Kwiatkowski <lb/>A, et al. Common loss-of-function variants <lb/>of the epidermal barrier protein filaggrin <lb/>are a major predisposing factor for <lb/>atopic dermatitis. Nat Genet. 2006;38(4): <lb/>441-446 <lb/>71. Baurecht H, Irvine AD, Novak N, et al. Toward <lb/>a major risk factor for atopic eczema: meta-<lb/>analysis of filaggrin polymorphism data. J <lb/>Allergy Clin Immunol. 2007;120(6): <lb/>1406 -1412 <lb/>72. Harper SA, Fukuda K, Uyeki TM, Cox NJ, <lb/>Bridges CB; Centers for Disease Control and <lb/>Prevention Advisory Committee on Immuni-<lb/>zation Practices. Prevention and control of <lb/>influenza: recommendations of the Advisory <lb/>Committee on Immunization Practices <lb/>(ACIP) [published correction appears in <lb/>MMWR Recomm Rep. 2004;53(32):743]. <lb/>MMWR Recomm Rep. 2004;53(RR-06):1-40. <lb/>Available at: www.cdc.gov/mmwr/preview/ <lb/>mmwrhtml/rr5306a1.htm. Accessed August <lb/>22, 2011. <lb/>73. Dieckmann RA. Pediatric assessment. In: <lb/>Gausche-Hill MS, Fuchs S, Yamamoto L, <lb/>editors. APLS: The Pediatric Emergency <lb/>Medicine Resource. 4th ed. Sudbury, MA: <lb/>Jones and Bartlett Publishers, Inc; <lb/>2004:41 <lb/></listBibl>

            <div type="funding">(Continued from first page) <lb/>GlaxoSmithKline, Merck, and Dey and has received funding/grant support from Genentech and the National Institutes of Health (NIAID); Dr Assa&apos;ad holds, or is <lb/>listed as an inventor on, US patent application 10/566903, entitled &quot;Genetic Markers of Food Allergy,&quot; has served as a consultant for GlaxoSmithKline and Novartis <lb/>and as a speaker for the American College of Allergy, Asthma, and Immunology, the North East Allergy Society, the Virginia Allergy Society, the New England <lb/>Allergy Society, and the American Academy of Pediatrics, and has received funding/grant support from GlaxoSmithKline; Dr Sampson holds, or is listed as an <lb/>inventor on, multiple US patents related to food allergy, owns stock in Allertein Therapeutics, is a past president of the American Academy of Allergy, Asthma, <lb/>and Immunology, has served as a consultant for Allertein Therapeutics, the American Academy of Allergy, Asthma, and Immunology, and the Food Allergy <lb/>Initiative, has received funding/grant support for research projects from the Food Allergy Initiative, the National Institutes of Health (NIAID, National Center for <lb/>Complementary and Alternative Medicine), and is a co-owner of Herbal Spring, LLC; and Dr Burks holds, or is listed as an inventor on, multiple US patents related <lb/>to food allergy, owns stock in Allertein and MastCell, Inc, is a minority stockholder in Dannon Co Probiotics, has served as a consultant for McNeil Nutritionals, <lb/>Mead Johnson, Schering-Plough, and Novartis, has served on the speaker&apos;s bureau for EpiPen/Dey, LP, has served on the data-monitoring committee for <lb/>Genentech, has served on an expert panel for Nutricia, and has received funding/grant support from the Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network, Gerber, Mead <lb/>Johnson, and the National Institutes of Health. <lb/>Funded by the National Institutes of Health (NIH). <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">STATE-OF-THE-ART REVIEW ARTICLES <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PEDIATRICS Volume 128, Number 5, November 2011 <lb/></note>

			<page>965 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
