<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8" standalone="no"?>
<fundings>
    <funding>This work was in part funded by the <fundingAgency>Novo Nordisk Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NNF14CC0001</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>U54 CA189205-01</grantNumber>).</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Perros Trust</fundingAgency> and the Integrative Epidemiology Unit. The Integrative Epidemiology Unit is supported by the <fundingAgency>Medical Research Council</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>University of Bristol</fundingAgency> [grant number <grantNumber>MC_UU_12013/9</grantNumber>]. Stephen Burgess is supported by a post-doctoral fellowship from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> [<grantNumber>100114</grantNumber>].</funding>
    <funding>1 Supported in part by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CCR-9315354</grantNumber>. 2 Supported in part by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> <programName>CAREER Award</programName> <grantNumber>CCR-9701911</grantNumber>. 3 Supported in part by grants <grantNumber>NSF-INT-9513368/DAAD-315-PRO-fo-ab</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>NSF-CCR-9322513</grantNumber> and by a <fundingAgency>NATO</fundingAgency> <programName>Postdoctoral Science Fellowship</programName> from the <fundingAgency>Deutscher Akademischer Austausch-dienst</fundingAgency> (\<programName>Gemeinsames Hochschulsonderprogramm III von Bund und L andern</programName>").</funding>
    <funding>The funding was provided by Department of Medical Research, <fundingAgency>Mackay Memorial Hospital</fundingAgency> and <grantNumber>MOST-109-2314-B-195-007</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Science and Technology</fundingAgency>, for encouraging members to carry out clinical studies. After reviewing the proposals and approving the promising studies, the funding body will not intervene in the design of the study and collection, analysis, and interpretation of data and in writing the manuscript in any way.</funding>
    <funding>This work performed under the auspices of the <fundingAgency>U.S. Department of Energy</fundingAgency> by <fundingAgency>Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory</fundingAgency> under Contract <grantNumber>DE-AC52-07NA27344</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>The post-doctoral research fellowship was funded by the <fundingAgency>Department of Agriculture-Bureau of Agricultural Research (DA-BAR)</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>University of the Philippines Diliman, Natural Sciences Research Institute (UP NSRI)</fundingAgency> and the <projectName>Next Generation Sequencing</projectName> by the <projectName>project of Dr. Doo-Sang Park</projectName> through the <fundingAgency>National Research Foundation of Korea</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>NRF-2016M3A9A5919255</grantNumber>).</funding>
    <funding>JMA <grantNumber>UL1 TR003107</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> JMA <grantNumber>KL2 TR003108</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> KWB <grantNumber>TL1 TR003109</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>National Center for Advancing Translational Sciences</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> JCF,KWB, JLK <grantNumber>P20 GM103625</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>National Institute of General Medical Sciences</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>AWD00054193</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>University of Arkansas</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>This study is funded by The <programName>Deanship of Scientific Research</programName> at <fundingAgency>Princess Nourah Bint Abdulrahman University</fundingAgency> (Grant number <grantNumber>225-X-38</grantNumber>).</funding>
    <funding>This work was funded by the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Science and Technology (MOST</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>104-2313-B-002 -014 -MY3</grantNumber>) of Taiwan (https://www.most.gov.tw/) to YL. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>Funding: This project was funded by the <fundingAgency>Australian Research Council</fundingAgency> (https://www.arc.gov.au/) grant number <grantNumber>DP120103994</grantNumber> awarded to RAH. JJH and NDN are supported by <projectName>Australian Postgraduate Awards</projectName>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding><fundingAgency>Samenwerkingsverband Noord-Nederland (SNN)</fundingAgency> Program (Project <projectName>RICIBION-Robotic Interventions using CT-Images for Biopsies of Lung Nodules</projectName>) to MO, <fundingAgency>European Research Council (ERC)</fundingAgency>, The European Unions <programName>Horizon 2020 Research and Innovation program</programName> (Project <projectName>ROBOTAR: Robot-Assisted Flexible Needle Steering for Targeted Delivery of Magnetic Agents</projectName>) <grantNumber>638428</grantNumber> to SM, and <fundingAgency>University Medical Center Groningen (UMCG)</fundingAgency>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by grant # <grantNumber>07/ 59319-5</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>Sao Paulo Research Foundation</fundingAgency> -Fapesp -http://www.fapesp.br/en/ -NBM; grant # <grantNumber>015/ 2014</grantNumber>-<fundingAgency>Fundo de Apoio à Dermatologia do Estado de São Paulo "Sebastião Sampaio"</fundingAgency> -Funadersp -http://www.sbd-sp.org.br/funadersp.php -PENFV; grant # <grantNumber>043/2016</grantNumber> -<fundingAgency>Fundo de Apoio à Dermatologia do Estado de São Paulo "Sebastião Sampaio"</fundingAgency> -Conclusion EFA treatment induces topical (observed by local IGF-1, leptin, IL-6 and IFN-γ production) and systemic effects, lowering IL-6 levels in the serum. As the oil is widely used to shorten ulcer healing time, studies are needed to evaluate the treatment safety and possible unde-sired effects. Funadersp -http://www.sbd-sp.org.br/funadersp. php -PENFV; grant # <grantNumber>01P-04520-2013</grantNumber> -<fundingAgency>Coordenac ¸ão de Aperfeic ¸oamento de Pessoal de Nı ´vel Superior -Capes</fundingAgency> -http://www.capes.gov.br/ -BGL; <fundingAgency>Fundo de Apoio ao Ensino, à Pesquisa e Extensão, Universidade Estadual de Campinas</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>0044/17</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The author(s) received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MH083911</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>AG045656</grantNumber>) and an <programName>Endowment Fund</programName> from <fundingAgency>Pennsylvania State University</fundingAgency> to G.C.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received funding from <fundingAgency>Bio-Rad/DiaMed</fundingAgency> for blood sample testing (JS, MP, NA) and from <fundingAgency>Ortho Clinical Diagnostics</fundingAgency> for speaking engagements (NA). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by a <fundingAgency>National Health &amp; Medical Research Council (NHMRC)</fundingAgency> (https://www.nhmrc.gov.au/) <grantName>Project Grant</grantName> (<grantNumber>ID 1010536</grantNumber>), a <grantName>Strategic Research Partnership Grant</grantName> (<grantNumber>CSR 11-02</grantNumber>) from <fundingAgency>Cancer Council NSW</fundingAgency> to the Newcastle Cancer Control Collaborative (New-3C) (https://www. cancercouncil.com.au/) (https://www.cancer.nsw. gov.au/), and infrastructure funding from the <fundingAgency>Hunter Medical Research Institute (HMRI)</fundingAgency> (https:// hmri.org.au/). MC is supported by a <fundingAgency>NHMRC</fundingAgency> <grantName>Translating Research Into Practice fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>APP1073031</grantNumber>), AB is supported by a <fundingAgency>NHMRC</fundingAgency> <grantName>Early Career Fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>APP1073317</grantNumber>) and a <fundingAgency>Cancer Institute New South Wales</fundingAgency> <grantName>Early Career Fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>13/ECF/1-37</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>Funding for the study was provided to the Human Environments Analysis Laboratory at Western University (PI: Gilliland) by the <fundingAgency>West Elgin Community Health Centre</fundingAgency> on behalf of the <fundingAgency>South West Local Health Integration Network</fundingAgency>.</funding>
    <funding>The author(s) received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>This project was funded by the <fundingAgency>United States Fish and Wildlife Service</fundingAgency>, grant #<grantNumber>F11AC01390</grantNumber> to JC and KLH. Support was also provided by the <fundingAgency>U.S. Department of Commerce's National Oceanic and Atmospheric Administration</fundingAgency> under <grantName>NOAA award</grantName> <grantNumber>NA14OAR4170098</grantNumber> and the <fundingAgency>Mississippi-Alabama Sea Grant Consortium</fundingAgency>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>We thank the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>US Environmental Protection Agency</fundingAgency> through a <grantName>supplemental award</grantName> (GRH), for their support of this research through the <grantName>Triangle, NC, Urban Long Term Research Area-Exploratory award</grantName> (<grantNumber>BCS-0948229</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection, and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported through <fundingAgency>USAID funding Advancing Partners &amp; Communities (APC)</fundingAgency> cooperative agreement number <grantNumber>AID-OAA-A-12-00047</grantNumber> (implemented by JSI Research &amp; Training Institute, Inc., in partnership with FHI 360) and Contract No. <grantNumber>AID-OAA-C-15-00001</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>USAID Global Health Supply Chain Quality Assurance Program</fundingAgency> (implemented by FHI 360). USAID staff (indicated co-authors) contributed to study design, project management, and manuscript preparation. </funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Korea Health Technology R&amp;D Project</fundingAgency> through the <fundingAgency>Korea Health Industry Development</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>Center for Veterinary Health Sciences, Oklahoma State University</fundingAgency>, to CCL; and <fundingAgency>Oklahoma Agricultural Experiment Station</fundingAgency>, to UD. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>This author received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>Renan Codonhato was a master's student awarded with a scholarship from <fundingAgency>CAPES-Brazil</fundingAgency> (<programName>Coordenac ¸ão de Aperfeic ¸oamento de Pessoal de Nı ´vel Superior</programName>). Victor Rubio and Lenamar Fiorese received funding from <fundingAgency>Santander Bank-Spain</fundingAgency> for a project to study sport injuries (code <grantNumber>00391462</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This research has been carried out through funding by the <fundingAgency>North Bristol NHS Trust Springboard Fund</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>Round 9, Ref: 13</grantNumber>). The funder had no role in the study design, data collection, analysis, interpretation of the data, writing of the</funding>
    <funding>report or decision to submit the paper for publication. This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>NIHR Biomedical Research Centre at University Hospitals Bristol NHS Foundation Trust</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>University of Bristol</fundingAgency>. The views expressed in this publication are those of the authors and not necessarily those of the NHS, the National Institute for Health Research or the Department of Health and Social Care.</funding>
    <funding>RR is funded by the <projectName>DCOMM</projectName> project (Deictic Communication -www.dcomm.eu). This project has received funding from the <fundingAgency>European Union</fundingAgency>'s <programName>Horizon 2020 research and innovation programme</programName> under the <grantName>Marie Sklodowska-Curie Actions</grantName> grant agreement No <grantNumber>676063</grantNumber>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The study was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Faculty of Tropical Medicine, Mahidol University</fundingAgency>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>The work described in the manuscript was funded by <fundingAgency>USDA-NIFA</fundingAgency> (<programName>Food Safety Priority Area</programName>, Award number <grantNumber>2014-67005-21702</grantNumber>), which included partial funding of the stipends / salaries of each of the authors (Lena Diaz, Yong Li, and myself Daniel M. Jenkins). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (https://www.snf.ch/ en) grant number <grantNumber>200021_178768</grantNumber> awarded to SA. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The paper is supported by the <grantNumber>RFFI-Grant 09-01-00172-a</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>Work done while the rst author was a graduate student at the University of Chicago Computer Science Depart-ment, supported in part by a <fundingAgency>University of Chicago</fundingAgency> <grantName>Fellowship</grantName>. y Supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>CCR-9009936</grantNumber> 1</funding>
    <funding>This research is supported by <fundingAgency>ARPA-AFOSR</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>F30602-91-C-0076</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>1 This work was partly supported by the <fundingAgency>Office of Naval Research</fundingAgency> under a <grantName>University Research Initiative</grantName> grant, number <grantNumber>N00014-86-K-0764</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>CDA 8922572</grantNumber>, and <fundingAgency>ONR</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>N00014-89-J-1877</grantNumber>. This work is sponsored by the <fundingAgency>Department of the Navy, Office of the Chief of Naval Research</fundingAgency>, and the content of the information does not necessarily reflect the position or the policy of the Government and no official endorsement should be inferred.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> Grants <grantNumber>IRI9306580</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>DDM-9201779</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>EEC 94-02384</grantNumber> and a forgivable loan from <fundingAgency>General Electric Corporation</fundingAgency> awarded to the rst author. Any opinions, ndings, and conclusions or recommendations expressed in this material are those of the author(s) and do not necessarily re ect the views of the National Science Foundation.</funding>
    <funding>This work is supported in part by <fundingAgency>Rome Labs</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>DARPA</fundingAgency> under contract <grantNumber>F30602-90-C-0010</grantNumber> to UMIACS at the University of Maryland. The views, opinions, and/or ndings contained in this report are those of the author(s) and should not be interpreted as representing the o cial policies, either expressed or implied, of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency, RL, or the U.S. Government. Computer facilities were provided in part by NSF grant CCR-8811954.</funding>
    <funding>With oversight by O ce of Naval Research, this research is supported by <fundingAgency>ARPA/SISTO</fundingAgency> in conjunction with the <projectName>Domain Speci c Software Architectures</projectName> project.</funding>
    <funding>This work is supported in part by <fundingAgency>ARPA</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Philips Labs</fundingAgency> under contract <grantNumber>DASG60-92-0055</grantNumber> to Department of Computer Science, University of Maryland, and by <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>NCR 89-04590</grantNumber>. The views, opinions, and/or ndings contained in this report are those of the author(s) and should not be interpreted as representing the o cial policies, either expressed or implied, of the Advanced Research Projects Agency, PL, NSF, or the U.S. Government. Computer facilities were provided in part by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CCR-8811954</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This work was partially supported by <fundingAgency>NSA</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>MDA904-96-1-0111</grantNumber>. 1</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by <fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>NAG 5-2648</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This research was partially supported by the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant # <grantNumber>CCR 9318933</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>* This work supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (grant numbers <grantNumber>CCR-9110938</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>ICI-9015443</grantNumber>), and by the <fundingAgency>IBM</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Intel</fundingAgency> Corporations. </funding>
    <funding>1 This research w as sponsored by the <fundingAgency>Advanced Research Projects Agency (DOD)</fundingAgency>, monitored by the Department of the Navy, O ce of the Chief of Naval Research, under Grant n umber <grantNumber>N00014-91-J-4046</grantNumber>. The views and conclusions contained in this document are those of the authors and should not be interpreted as representing o cial policies, either expressed or implied, of the Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency or the US Government.</funding>
    <funding>This material is based in part upon work supported by <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> Award <grantNumber>CCR-9111912</grantNumber></funding>
    <funding>This work was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> under Grants No. <grantNumber>CCR-8619663</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>CCR-8907666</grantNumber>, by the <fundingAgency>Washington Technology Center</fundingAgency>, and by the <fundingAgency>Digital Equipment Corporation Systems Research Center and External Research Program</fundingAgency>.</funding>
    <funding>The support of the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> under Grant No. <grantNumber>IRI-9002582</grantNumber> is gratefully acknowledged.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Army Research Office</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>Air Force Office of Scientific Research</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>Supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China (NSFC)</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>11235011</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>11475187</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>11521505</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>U1632106</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Ministry of Science and Technology of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2015CB856701</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Key Research Program of Frontier Sciences, CAS</fundingAgency>, (<grantNumber>QYZDJ-SSW-SLH011</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>CAS Center for Excellence in Particle Physics (CCEPP)</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>This research was sponsored in part by the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> under grants <grantNumber>IRI-9015423</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>IRI-9010645</grantNumber>, and <grantName>IRI-9158473</grantName>, and by <fundingAgency>DARPA</fundingAgency> under contract <grantNumber>DAAE-07-92-C-R012</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>0 This research was sponsored, in part, by the <fundingAgency>University of Michigan</fundingAgency> under a <grantName>Rackham Faculty Research Grant</grantName>, and by a <grantName>Bell Northern Research Postgraduate Award</grantName>.</funding>
    <funding>This research was sponsored in part by the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> under grants <grantNumber>IRI-9015423</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>IRI-9010645</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>IRI-9158473</grantNumber>, and by <fundingAgency>DARPA</fundingAgency> under contract <grantNumber>DAAE-07-92-C-R012</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>University of Michigan</fundingAgency> <grantName>ITS Center of Excellence grant</grantName> (<grantNumber>DTFH61-93-X-00017-Sub</grantNumber>) sponsored by the <fundingAgency>U.S. Department of Transportation</fundingAgency> and by the <fundingAgency>Michigan Department of Transportation</fundingAgency>. Ning Jing, on leave from the Changsha Institute of Technology, is currently visiting the University of Michigan and likes to thank the State Education Commission of P.R. China. </funding>
    <funding>This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>Horace Stansel Jr Research Fund</fundingAgency>. IRB protocol ID: <grantNumber>2000020356</grantNumber>, approval date: 3/2/2017 </funding>
    <funding>The first author acknowledges partial support from the <fundingAgency>Center for Research in Economics and Statistics (CREST)</fundingAgency> at the French National Institute of Statistics and Economic Studies (INSEE), </funding>
    <funding>Supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>CCR89-10707</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>Research partially supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency>/<fundingAgency>DARPA</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>CCR-9005448</grantNumber> y Research partially supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> operating grant <grantNumber>CCR-9016468</grantNumber> and by grant No. <grantNumber>89-00312</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>United States-Israel Binational Science Foundation (BSF)</fundingAgency>, Jerusalem, Israel. z Part of work was done during a visit at the International Computer Science Institute at Berkeley; supported in part by <fundingAgency>DFG</fundingAgency>-<programName>Forschergruppe \E ziente Nutzung massiv paralleler Systeme, Teilprojekt 4</programName>", and by the <programName>Esprit Basic Research Action</programName> Nr. <grantNumber>7141</grantNumber> (<projectName>ALCOM II</projectName>).</funding>
    <funding>y This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> under grant <grantNumber>NCR-9206908</grantNumber> and by <fundingAgency>ARPA</fundingAgency> under <grantName>ESD/AVS</grantName> contract <grantNumber>F-19628-92-C-0089</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>for CBCL is provided in part by a grant from the <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ASC{9217041</grantNumber>). Support for the laboratory's arti cial intelligence research is provided in part by the <fundingAgency>Advanced Research Projects Agency of the Dept. of Defense</fundingAgency>. MIJ gratefully acknowledges discussions with Ste en Lauritzen on the application of the IPF algorithm to UPINs.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by: <fundingAgency>Center for Research on Parallel Computation</fundingAgency>, a National Science Foundation Sci-ence and Technology Center, through Cooperative Agree-ment No. <grantNumber>CCR-9120008</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency>/<fundingAgency>NASA</fundingAgency> Agreement No. <grantNumber>ASC-9213821</grantNumber>, and <fundingAgency>ONR</fundingAgency> Agreement No. <grantNumber>N00014-93-1-0158</grantNumber>. Use of the Intel i860 was provided under a <fundingAgency>Texas CER</fundingAgency> Grant No. <grantNumber>CISE 8619893</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This work has been supported by the <fundingAgency>Defense Advanced Research Projects Agency (Avionics Lab, Wright Research and Development Center, Aeronautical Systems Division (AFSC), U.S. Air Force</fundingAgency>, Wright-Patterson AFB, Ohio, 45433-6543 under Contract <grantNumber>F33615-90-C-1465</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>ARPA</fundingAgency>  Order No. <grantNumber>7597</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantName>PYI</grantName> Award), and the <fundingAgency>IBM Corporation</fundingAgency> (<grantName>Research Initiation Grant</grantName>). The views and conclusion expressed in this paper are those of the author, and should not be interpreted as those of the funding agencies or Carnegie Mellon University.</funding>
    <funding>Research partially supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CCR-9258355</grantNumber> and by matching funds from <fundingAgency>Xerox Corporation</fundingAgency>.</funding>
    <funding>Research supported by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DMS-9627683</grantNumber> and by <fundingAgency>U. S. Army Research Office</fundingAgency> <grantName>MURI grant</grantName> <grantNumber>DAAH04-96-1-0013</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>Research partially supported by an <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> <grantName>PYI</grantName> award, <grantNumber>CCR-9157620</grantNumber>, together with PYI matching funds from <fundingAgency>Thinking Machines Corporation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Xerox Corporation</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Honeywell Corporation</fundingAgency>. Additional support provided by <fundingAgency>DARPA</fundingAgency> Contract No. <grantNumber>N00014-91-J-4052</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>ARPA</fundingAgency> Order No. <grantNumber>8225</grantNumber>, and by the <fundingAgency>NEC Research Institute</fundingAgency>, Princeton, NJ. </funding>
    <funding>Research at Princeton University partially supported by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency>, Grant No. <grantNumber>CCR-8920505</grantNumber>; the <fundingAgency>Office of Naval Research</fundingAgency>, Contract No. <grantNumber>N0014-91-J-1463</grantNumber>; and <fundingAgency>DIMACS (Center for Discrete Mathematics and Theoretical Computer Science)</fundingAgency>, a National Science and Technology Center, Grant No. <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency>-<grantNumber>STC88-09648</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Army Research Office</fundingAgency> under Contracts <grantNumber>DAAH 049510494</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>DAAH 0494G0417</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Advanced Research Projects Agency of the Department of Defense</fundingAgency>, monitored by the Office of Naval Research under contract <grantNumber>N00014-91-J-4136</grantNumber>, in part by the <fundingAgency>National Sci-ence Foundation</fundingAgency> under Grant <grantNumber>CCR-8822158</grantNumber>, and in part by the <fundingAgency>Department of the Army</fundingAgency> under Contract <grantNumber>DABT63-92-C-0012</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>John Grych was supported in this research by a <grantName>National Research Service Award</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Mental Health</fundingAgency>. Frank Fincham was supported by grants from the <fundingAgency>Harry Frank Guggenheim Foundation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>National Institute of Mental Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MH 44078</grantNumber>) and by a <grantName>Faculty Scholar Award</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>W.T. Grant Foundation</fundingAgency>. We thank Susan Englund and Reliford Sanders for their help in creating the vignettes used in this project and Michael Seid for his assistance in collecting the data. </funding>
    <funding>This research was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>U. S. National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> under Grant <grantNumber>CCR-90-07195</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>Support for the work described in this paper was provided in part by <fundingAgency>Misubishi Electric Research Laboratories, Inc.</fundingAgency> Support for the laboratory's artificial intelligence research is provided in part by the <fundingAgency>Advanced Research Projects Agency of the Department of Defense</fundingAgency> under Office of Naval Research contract <grantNumber>N00014-85-K-0124</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>IRI-8819624</grantNumber> and in part by the <fundingAgency>Advanced Research Projects Agency of the Department of Defense</fundingAgency> under Office of Naval Research contract <grantNumber>N00014-85-K-0124</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>N00014-89-J-3202</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>. Incumbent of the Morris and Rose Goldman Career Develop-ment Chair, supported by an <grantName>Alon fellowship</grantName> and by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Israel Science Foundation</fundingAgency> administered by the Israeli Academy of Sciences and Humanities.</funding>
    <funding>* This research was supported by an <fundingAgency>NSERC</fundingAgency> <grantName>Canada International Fellowship</grantName>. ** This research was supported by an <fundingAgency>NSERC</fundingAgency> <grantName>Research Grant</grantName>.</funding>
    <funding>Partial support for this work was provided by the <fundingAgency>Ad-vanced Research Projects Agency</fundingAgency> under contract <grantNumber>N00014-91-J-4052</grantNumber> <fundingAgency>ARPA</fundingAgency> order <grantName>8225</grantName>, and contract <grantNumber>DAAB-07-91-C-Q518</grantNumber> under subcontract <grantNumber>F41100</grantNumber>.</funding>
    <funding>y Supported in part by <fundingAgency>NSF</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>CCR-9204284</grantNumber></funding>
    <funding>2 This work was supported in part by a <grantName>Merit Review Award</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Veterans' Administration Research Service (MBA)</fundingAgency> and by fund-ing from the <fundingAgency>Gonda Family Endowment</fundingAgency>. MBA received partial sup-port from the <fundingAgency>Gonda Family Endowment</fundingAgency>. </funding>
    <funding>Contact grant sponsor: the <programName>"K. Karatheodori" program</programName> of the <fundingAgency>University of Patras</fundingAgency> Contract grant sponsor: the <programName>"PENED" program</programName> of the <fundingAgency>Greek Secretariat for Research and Technology</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>£ This work was supported by a grant from <fundingAgency>Sylantro Corp.</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>Preparation of this article was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Institute of Mental Health</fundingAgency> Grant #<grantNumber>MH35042-02</grantNumber> to Sherryl Goodman. We gratefully acknowledge the assistance of the Project PACT staff in the data collection and of the families for their participation in the research. Nangel Lindberg and Mary Goedde assisted in the final preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This research was supported by <fundingAgency>National Institute on Alcohol Abuse and Alcoholism</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>AA07549</grantNumber>. The authors acknowledge Ms. Susan Bradford for assistance in data management and Ms. Shirley Mazenko for secretarial assistance. </funding>
    <funding>Kessler gratefully acknowledges funding from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes on Aging</fundingAgency> through the <fundingAgency>NBER</fundingAgency>. All errors or misstatements are our own.</funding>
    <funding>funding/contracted research: <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>; Gerald Falchook: None; Marshall Hicks: None; Sijin Wen: None; Apostolia M. Tsimberidou: None; Razelle Kurzrock: None.</funding>
    <funding>supported by <fundingAgency>CNRS</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>INPG</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>INRIA</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>UJF</fundingAgency></funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Scottish Government Rural and Environment Research and Analysis Directorate (RERAD)</fundingAgency> [<grantNumber>SCR/908/03</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>SCR/842/04</grantNumber>]. JS and PF were also supported by the <fundingAgency>European Union</fundingAgency> [<programName>COST</programName> <grantNumber>C05.0103</grantNumber> to JS] and the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> [<grantNumber>3100A0-116075/1</grantNumber> to PF, <grantNumber>3100A0-112370/1</grantNumber> to JS]. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Stowers Institute for Medical Research</fundingAgency>. The funder had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
    <funding>* This work was supported in part by a <grantName>scholarship</grantName> from <fundingAgency>Novo Nordisk A/S</fundingAgency> (to C. R. U.), <fundingAgency>European Membrane Protein Consortium</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Federal State of Saxony-Anhalt</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>3324 A/0021 L</grantNumber>, and the <fundingAgency>Deutsche Forschungsgemeinshaft</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>SFRB 610/TP A11</grantNumber>. Author's Choice-Final version full access. □ S The on-line version of this article (available at http://www.jbc.org) contains supplemental Fig. S1. The atomic coordinates and structure factors (code 3IOL) have been deposited in the Protein Data Bank, Research Collaboratory for Structural Bioinformatics, Rutgers University, New Brunswick, NJ (http://www.rcsb.org/). 1 Supported by the <fundingAgency>Danish National Research Foundation</fundingAgency> via a grant to the MEMPHYS Center of Biomembrane Physics. </funding>
    <funding>*This study was financially supported by a <fundingAgency>Chung-Ang University</fundingAgency> <grantName>Research Grant</grantName>, 2004.</funding>
    <funding>* This study was supported by <fundingAgency>Research Funds of Korea Food and Drug Administration</fundingAgency>.</funding>
    <funding>This work was supported by <fundingAgency>National Basic Research Program of China</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>2012CB944401</grantNumber> and No. <grantNumber>2012CB944701</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The authors have no support or funding to report.</funding>
    <funding>S.S. (L-14568) received <grantName>Research Professorship</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Japan Society for Promotion of Science (JSPS)</fundingAgency>. </funding>
    <funding>The authors received no specific funding for this work.</funding>
    <funding>No direct funding was received for this study. The authors were personally salaried by their institutions during the period of writing (although no specific salary was set aside or given for the writing of this paper). No funding bodies had any role in the study design, data collection, analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>The authors thank <fundingAgency>NERC</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Grant Agency of the Czech Republic</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>521/07/0116</grantNumber>), and the <fundingAgency>USA National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (grants <grantNumber>MCB-0346437</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>DEB-0608268</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>DBI 0638536</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>DBI 0501712</grantNumber>) for support. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.</funding>
    <funding>Partially supported by the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> <grantName>ERC Starting Grant</grantName> 2009, project <grantNumber>239983</grantNumber>-<projectName>NuSiKiMo</projectName>.</funding>
    <funding>Dr Jones has served as a speaker and grant reviewer and has served on the medical advisory committee for the Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network, has received funding/grant support from <fundingAgency>Dyax Corp</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Food Allergy Initiative</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Mead Johnson</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>National Peanut Board</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>, and has served as a speaker and/or consultant for Sanofi-Aventis and Abbott Laboratories; Dr Boyce has served on the advisory board of GlaxoSmithKline, has served as a consultant and/or speaker for Altana, GlaxoSmithKline, and Merck, and has received funding/grant support from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>; Dr Sicherer has served on an expert panel for Sunovion, has received funding/ grant support from the <fundingAgency>Food Allergy and Anaphylaxis Network</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Food Allergy Initiative</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>, and is a consultant to the Food Allergy Initiative; Dr Wood has served as a speaker/advisory board member for </funding>
   <funding>Funding Statement The research reported herein was funded by <fundingAgency>Norwegian Research Council</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>235073/F20</grantNumber> to L.H. Liow. </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING INFORMATION This research was supported by an operating grant from the <fundingAgency>Canadian Institutes of Health Research</fundingAgency> to EF (<grantNumber>MOP 77746</grantNumber>). AG was supported by a <grantName>Frederick Banting and Charles Best Canada Graduate Scholarship</grantName> (<fundingAgency>CIHR</fundingAgency> CGS-M), and a <grantName>Walter H. Johns Graduate Fellowship</grantName> (UofA). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and interpretation, or the decision to submit the work for publication. </funding>
   <funding>Funding Funding: This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organisation for Scientific Research (NWOALW)</fundingAgency> [<grantNumber>863.12.002</grantNumber> to S.J.v.H.]. G.G. was supported by the <fundingAgency>US National Institutes of Health (NICHD)</fundingAgency> [<grantNumber>R01HD069344</grantNumber>]. </funding>
   <funding>VII. FINANCIAL SUPPORT This work was performed as part of an internship by ASR sponsored by <fundingAgency>Genentech, Inc.</fundingAgency>, DNA Way, South San Francisco, CA , United States. JDC acknowledges sup-port from the <fundingAgency>Sloan Kettering Institute</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grant P CA . DLM appreciates financial support from <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (CHE ). </funding>
   <funding>Funding Open access funding provided by <fundingAgency>University of Bergen</fundingAgency>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>European Union</fundingAgency>'s <programName>Seventh Framework Program</programName> (FP7/2007-2013; grant #<grantNumber>602102</grantNumber>, A.F.), the <fundingAgency>Israel Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (A.F.), the <fundingAgency>Israel-USA bi-national Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (A.F. and D.K.), the <fundingAgency>Nova Scotia Health Research Foundation</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Canada Institute for Health Research (CIHR)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Crown Family Foundation</fundingAgency> (L.E.G. and A.F.), <fundingAgency>NIH-NIA Boston University Alzheimer's Disease Center</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>P30 AG013846</grantNumber>, L.E.G.), <fundingAgency>Thermo Scientific</fundingAgency> (in kind support; L.E.G.), <fundingAgency>Office of the Dean, Boston University School of Medicine</fundingAgency> (L.E.G.). </funding>
   <funding>Funding Project No.<grantNumber>2020CDJGRH-YJ03</grantNumber> supported by the <fundingAgency>Fundamental Research Funds for the Central Universities</fundingAgency>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research was supported by the <fundingAgency>Harvard University Department of Psychology</fundingAgency> (M.M.K. and S.A.M.); the <fundingAgency>Harvard College Research Program</fundingAgency> (H.L-R.); the <fundingAgency>Harvard Data Science Initiative</fundingAgency> (S.A.M.); the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health Director's Early Independence</fundingAgency> Award <grantNumber>DP5OD024566</grantNumber> (S.A.M.); the <fundingAgency>Academy of Finland</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>298513</grantNumber> (J.A.); the <fundingAgency>Royal Society of New Zealand</fundingAgency> Te <grantName>Apārangi Rutherford Discovery Fellowship</grantName> <grantNumber>RDF-UOA1101</grantNumber> (Q.D.A., T.A.V.); the <fundingAgency>Social Sciences and Humanities Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency> (L.K.C.); the <fundingAgency>Polish Ministry of Science and Higher Education</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>N43/DBS/000068</grantNumber> (G.J.); the <fundingAgency>Fogarty International Center and National Heart, Lung, and Blood Institute</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Neurological Disorders and Stroke</fundingAgency> Award <grantNumber>D43 TW010540</grantNumber> (P.M., C.D.P.); the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Allergy and Infectious Dis-eases</fundingAgency> Award <grantNumber>R15-AI128714-01</grantNumber> (P.M.); the <fundingAgency>Max Planck Institute for Evolutionary Anthropology</fundingAgency> (C.T.R.); a <fundingAgency>British Academy Research</fundingAgency> Fellowship and Grant <grantNumber>SRG-171409</grantNumber> (G.D.S.); the <fundingAgency>Institute for Advanced Study in Toulouse</fundingAgency>, under an <fundingAgency>Agence nationale de la recherche</fundingAgency> grant, <programName>Investissements d'Avenir</programName> <grantNumber>ANR-17-EURE-0010</grantNumber> (J. Stieglitz); and the <fundingAgency>Natural Sciences and Engineering Research Council of Canada</fundingAgency> (S.E.T.). </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research received no external funding </funding>
   <funding>Funding This work was supported by <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> grants: <grantNumber>DC007176</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>DC015400</grantNumber>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research was partly supported by the <fundingAgency>National Institute of Health</fundingAgency> (grant #<grantNumber>R21HL125191</grantNumber> to MK). </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING This work was funded in part by the <fundingAgency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research (BMBF)</fundingAgency> within the <programName>Medical Informatics Initiative</programName> (<projectName>MIRACUM</projectName> Consortium, FKZ: <grantNumber>01ZZ1801A</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801B</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801L</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801D</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801G</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801M</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1801H</grantNumber>; <projectName>DIFUTURE</projectName> Consortium, FKZ: <grantNumber>01ZZ1804H</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1804I</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1804D</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1804G</grantNumber>; <projectName>HiGHmed</projectName> Consortium, FKZ: <grantNumber>01ZZ1802V</grantNumber>, <projectName>01ZZ1802C</projectName>; <projectName>SMITH</projectName> Consortium, FZK: <grantNumber>01ZZ1803D</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1803C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1803N</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>01ZZ1803B</grantNumber>). </funding>
   <funding>Funding: This research was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO</fundingAgency>, <projectName>ACCESS</projectName> project, grant No. <grantNumber>CISC.CC.016</grantNumber>). </funding>
   <funding>Funding This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>NIAID</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>NIGMS</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> under grant numbers <grantNumber>R01AI127893</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R01GM102198</grantNumber>. JDB is supported in part by a <grantName>Faculty Scholars grant</grantName> from the <fundingAgency>Howard Hughes Medical Institute</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Simons Foundation</fundingAgency>. MBD and SKH are supported in part by training grant <grantNumber>T32AI083203</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>NIAID</fundingAgency> of the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency>. The funders had no role in the design of the project or the decision to publish. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This study was funded by the <fundingAgency>German Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>STR 478/3-1</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>German Federal Ministry of Education and Research</fundingAgency> under the grant number <grantNumber>01 EO 0901</grantNumber>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This trial is co-funded by the <fundingAgency>Carlos III Health Institute (ISCIII)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>European Fund of Regional Development (FEDER)</fundingAgency> (Grant <grantNumber>PI 17/01887</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Spanish Ministry of Economy and Competitiveness</fundingAgency>. The funding agency did not have any role in the design of the study, collection, analysis, interpretation of data, and in writing the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding Wenbin Chen was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>11671098</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>91630309</grantNumber>) and 111 project(<grantNumber>B08018</grantNumber>), Jin Cheng was supported in part by the <fundingAgency>National Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>11971121</grantNumber>). </funding>
   <funding>Funding: This project was funded by the <fundingAgency>IONIS engineering schools Sup'Biotech and Epita</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>French Embassy in USA</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>French departments Val de Marne and Sèvres</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Les Mousquetaires group</fundingAgency> and the private company <fundingAgency>Chamorin</fundingAgency>.The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding: Research was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>National Environment Research Council</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>RG53472</grantNumber>) and the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>294494</grantNumber>) to T.H.C-B. I.B.G. was funded by the <fundingAgency>Swiss National Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (grant no. <grantNumber>31003A_13676</grantNumber> to M. Manser). NCB was supported by a <fundingAgency>DST-NRF</fundingAgency> <grantName>SARCHl chair of Mammal Behavioural</grantName> </funding>
   <funding>FUNDINGS This study was supported by the <fundingAgency>European Research Council</fundingAgency> (<grantName>ERC Consolidator Grant</grantName> <grantNumber>617629</grantNumber>), by the <fundingAgency>French Agence Nationale de la Recherche</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ANR-12-CORD-0030</grantNumber>), by <fundingAgency>Sorbonne-Universités</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>SU-15-R-PERSU-14</grantNumber>), by the <fundingAgency>Centre National de la Recherche Scientifique</fundingAgency> (<programName>Osez l'Interdisciplinarité Program</programName>, <projectName>ROBAUTISTE</projectName> Project), and two department-wide grants from the <fundingAgency>French National Research Agency</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>ANR-10-LABX-0087 IEC</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>ANR-10-IDEX-0001-02 PSL</grantNumber>). The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This work has been supported by the Swedish strategic research programme <programName>eSSENCE</programName>, the <fundingAgency>Swedish e-Science Research Centre (SeRC)</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>National Bioinformatics Infrastructure Sweden (NBIS)</fundingAgency>, and the <fundingAgency>European Union</fundingAgency>'s <programName>Horizon research and innovation programme</programName> under grant agreement No for the <projectName>PhenoMeNal</projectName> project. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This publication was made possible through the support of a grant from the <fundingAgency>Templeton World Charity Foundation</fundingAgency>: "<projectName>The Epistemic Responsibilities of the University</projectName>" (2016-2019). The opinions expressed in this publication are those of the author and do not necessarily reflect the views of the Templeton World Charity Foundation. </funding>
   <funding>FUNDINGS This work was funded by the <fundingAgency>National Key Research and Development Program of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>2017YFA0102602</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2016YFA0100400</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>31322031</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>31371288</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>31571365</grantNumber>), <programName>Program of Shanghai Academic Research Leader</programName> (<grantNumber>17XD1403600</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>National Program for Support of Top-notch Young Professionals</fundingAgency>. </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING This work was supported by scholarships of the <fundingAgency>Marshall Plan Foundation</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Austrian Federal Ministry for Education</fundingAgency> (to K.K., A.G., and T.B.), <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health (NIH)</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>R01-ES015339</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R35-ES028374</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>U54-CA112967</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>Charles and Marjorie Holloway Foundation</fundingAgency>, the and a <fundingAgency>Starr Cancer Consortium</fundingAgency> Award <grantNumber>I9-A9-077</grantNumber> (to M.B.Y. and I.G.C.). </funding>
   <funding>Source of funding This work was supported by <fundingAgency>Ministerio de Economía y Competitividad del Gobierno de España (MINECO</fundingAgency>, Plan Nacional I+D+i <grantNumber>AGL2016-76736-C3</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Gobierno regional de la Comunidad de Madrid</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>P2013/ABI-2728</grantNumber>, <projectName>ALIBIRD-CM</projectName>) and <fundingAgency>EU</fundingAgency> <programName>Structural Funds</programName>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding: This work was supported by the <fundingAgency>Neuroscience in Psychiatry Network</fundingAgency>, a strategic award from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> to the University of Cambridge and University College London (<grantNumber>095844/Z/11/Z</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>093270</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Bernard Wolfe Health Neuroscience Fund</fundingAgency> (P.C.F. and H.Z)., and the <fundingAgency>Niels Stensen Foundation</fundingAgency> (K.M.J.D). </funding>
   <funding>Funding statement This work was funded by a <fundingAgency>British Heart Foundation</fundingAgency> <grantName>Intermediate Basic Science Research Fellowship</grantName> (<grantNumber>FS/08/016/24741</grantNumber>; to SDB), a <fundingAgency>British Heart Foundation</fundingAgency> project grant (<grantNumber>PG/16/39/32115</grantNumber>; to SDB), a <fundingAgency>British Heart Foundation</fundingAgency> <grantName>PhD Non-Clinical PhD Studentship</grantName> (<grantNumber>FS/16/8/31984</grantNumber> to; SDB) and a grant from the <fundingAgency>Newcastle upon Tyne Hospitals NHS Charities</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>BH120404</grantNumber>; to SDB). JABL received a PhD Scholarship from the <fundingAgency>National Science and Technology Council of Mexico</fundingAgency> (<projectName>CONACyT</projectName>). RRK received a PhD Scholarship from <fundingAgency>Yarmouk University, Jordan</fundingAgency>. </funding>
   <funding>Funding. This work was funded by the <fundingAgency>Antimicrobial Resistance Cross-council Initiative</fundingAgency> supported by the seven research councils [<grantNumber>NE/N019989/1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>NE/N019660/1</grantNumber>]. DWC, TEAP, and ASW are affiliated to the <fundingAgency>National Institute for Health Research Health Protection Research Unit (NIHR HPRU)</fundingAgency> in Healthcare Associated Infections and Antimicrobial Resistance at University of Oxford in partnership with <fundingAgency>Public Health England (PHE)</fundingAgency> [grant <grantNumber>HPRU-2012-10041</grantNumber>]. The views expressed are those of the author(s) and not necessarily those of the NHS, the NIHR, the Department of Health or Public Health England. This work is supported by the NIHR Oxford Biomedical Research Centre. The funders had no role in the design of the study, analyses, interpretation of the data or writing of the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding: This work was supported by a <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> <grantName>Investigator Award</grantName> to S.R.M. (<grantNumber>098387/Z/12/Z</grantNumber> &amp; <grantNumber>212284/Z/18/Z</grantNumber>) and <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> <grantName>PhD Studentship</grantName> to D.W. (<grantNumber>109109/Z/15/Z</grantNumber>). Graphical abstract was created with BioRender.com. </funding>
   <funding>Funding Statement The author(s) received no specific funding for this work. </funding>
   <funding>Funding: TA: <fundingAgency>Academy of Finland</fundingAgency> (grants <grantNumber>310507</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>313267</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Cancer Society of Finland</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Sigrid Jusélius Foundation</fundingAgency>. CW, TW, DD: <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>1U24DK116204-01</grantNumber>). The SGC is a registered charity that receives funds from <fundingAgency>AbbVie</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Bayer Pharma AG</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Boehringer Ingelheim</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Canada Foundation for Innovation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Eshelman Institute for Innovation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Genome Canada</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Innovative Medicines Initiative</fundingAgency> (<projectName>ULTRA-DD</projectName> <grantNumber>115766</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Janssen</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Merck Kga</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Merck Sharp &amp; Dohme</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Novartis Pharma AG</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Ontario Ministry of Economic Development and Innovation</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Pfizer</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>São Paulo Research Foundation-FAPESP</fundingAgency>, and <fundingAgency>Takeda</fundingAgency> . </funding>
   <funding>Funding HJ and CM were supported by the <fundingAgency>U.S. Department of Energy</fundingAgency>, Office of Science, Office of Biological and Environmental Research, <programName>Genomic Sciences Program</programName> under Award Number <grantNumber>DE-SC0016469</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>DE-SC0020374</grantNumber>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research was supported by a <grantName>VICI grant</grantName> to D.W., from the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NWO</fundingAgency>; <grantNumber>865.14.001</grantNumber>). </funding>
   <funding>The study of neurodegenerative processes in model systems was supported by a grant of the <fundingAgency>Russian Science Foundation</fundingAgency> (No. <grantNumber>18-15-00357</grantNumber>); maintenance of the animals was funded by the program for the support of bioresource collections of the <fundingAgency>Institute of Physiologically Active Compounds (IPAC) (Federal Agency for Scientific Organizations</fundingAgency> No. <grantNumber>0090-2017-0016</grantNumber>) and conducted on the equipment of the <fundingAgency>Center for Scientific and Technical Studies of IPAC RAS and IGB RAS</fundingAgency>, in the framework of the State Assignment of IPAC RAS (topic of the State registration number <grantNumber>0090-2017-0019</grantNumber>) and the basic research program of the <fundingAgency>Presidium of the Russian Academy of Sciences</fundingAgency> "<programName>Fundamental research for biomedical technologies</programName>." </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING  The study was funded by <fundingAgency>Cancer Research UK</fundingAgency>. Funding to pay the Open Access publication charges for this article was pro-vided by <fundingAgency>Cancer Research UK</fundingAgency>. </funding>
   <funding>Grant information This work is supported by the <fundingAgency>Human Heredity and Health in Africa (H3Africa)</fundingAgency> in Partnership with the <fundingAgency>African Academy of Sciences</fundingAgency>. The Framework drafting meeting was supported by a grant from the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>WT201245/Z/16/Z</grantNumber>). Dur-ing the development of this Framework, Jantina de Vries was supported by the <grantName>RHDGen grant</grantName>, a <grantName>H3Africa grant</grantName> funded by the <fundingAgency>Wellcome Trust</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>WT099313MA</grantNumber>) and the <grantName>Stigma in African Genomics grant</grantName> funded by the <fundingAgency>National Human Genome Research Institute of the National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> under Award Number <grantNumber>U01HG008226</grantNumber>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This work was supported by federal grants to <fundingAgency>Nanoprobes and The Cleveland Clinic</fundingAgency> (<fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R43CA84875-01</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NIH/NCI</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R41CA83618-01</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NIH/NCI</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R41CA83618-02</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R43GM64257-01</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>NIH/NIGMS</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R43GM0628250-01</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> <grantNumber>1R43 CA111182-01</grantNumber>) and an <grantName>Industry sponsored grant</grantName> from <fundingAgency>Ventana Medical Systems</fundingAgency> to RRT. </funding>
   <funding>Funding: Reagents and technical support were kindly provided by DiaSorin for the Liaison-XL and Roche for the Elecsys. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This work was supported by a <fundingAgency>City University London</fundingAgency> <grantName>Pump Priming Grant</grantName> and the <fundingAgency>Dunhill Medical Trust</fundingAgency> [grant reference: <grantNumber>R171/0710</grantNumber>]. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research was made possible by the <programName>Program of Human Resources Formation for Science and Technology</programName> grant number <grantNumber>20326/FPI/2017</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>Seneca Foundation-Agency for Science and Technology in the Region of Murcia (Spain)</fundingAgency>. This study is part of the project entitled ''<projectName>Estudio del riesgo de lesión en jóvenes deportistas a través de redes de inteligencia artificial</projectName>'', funded by the <fundingAgency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>DEP2017-88775-P</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>State Research Agency (AEI)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>European Regional Development Fund (ERDF)</fundingAgency>. The funders had no role in study design, data collection and analysis, decision to publish, or preparation of the manuscript.  Grant Disclosures The following grant information was disclosed by the authors: <programName>Program of Human Resources Formation for Science and Technology</programName>: <grantNumber>20326/FPI/2017</grantNumber>. <fundingAgency>Seneca Foundation-Agency for Science and Technology in the Region of Murcia (Spain)</fundingAgency>. <fundingAgency>Spanish Ministry of Science and Innovation</fundingAgency>: <grantNumber>DEP2017-88775-P</grantNumber>. </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING <fundingAgency>National Library of Medicine</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>LM04971</grantNumber>); <fundingAgency>New England Biolabs, Inc.</fundingAgency> Funding for open access charge: <fundingAgency>New England Biolabs</fundingAgency>; <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> grant. </funding>
   <funding>Funding The author(s) received no financial support for the research, author-ship, and/or publication of this article. </funding>
   <funding>Funding This research did not receive any specific grant from funding agencies in the public, commercial, or not-for-profit sectors. </funding>
   <funding>FUNDING This work was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Natural Science Foundation of China</fundingAgency> (grant nos.: <grantNumber>81671568</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81873872</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>81571608</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>81771771</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Science and Technology Planning Project of Guangdong Province</fundingAgency> (grant no.: <grantNumber>2016A020215106</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Natural Science Foundation of Guangdong Province</fundingAgency> (grant no.: <grantNumber>2016A030313537</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>2017A030313542</grantNumber>), <fundingAgency>Open Project of Guangdong Provincial Key Laboratory of Proteomics</fundingAgency> (grant no.: <grantNumber>P201801</grantNumber>). </funding>
   <funding>Funding: This research was funded by the Project <grantNumber>RTI2018-096903-B-I00</grantNumber> of the <fundingAgency>AEI/FEDER UE</fundingAgency> and the Project <grantNumber>JIUZ-2019-TEC-03</grantNumber> of <fundingAgency>Unizar and Fundacion Ibercaja</fundingAgency>. </funding>

   <funding>Funding Sources: The <projectName>Amish Study</projectName> was supported by grants <grantNumber>R01 088119</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01 AR046838</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>U01 HL72515</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>R01 AG18728</grantNumber>, the <fundingAgency>University of Maryland General Clinical Research Center</fundingAgency>, Grant <grantNumber>M01 RR 16500</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>Mid-Atlantic Nutrition Obesity Research Center</fundingAgency> Grant <grantNumber>P30 DK072488</grantNumber>, <fundingAgency>General Clinical Research Centers Program, National Center for Research Resources (NCRR)</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>Baltimore Veterans Administration Geriatric Research and Education Clinical Center (GRECC)</fundingAgency>. Dr. Montasser was supported by <grantNumber>AG000219</grantNumber>. ARIC is carried out as a collaborative study supported by <fundingAgency>NHLBI</fundingAgency> contracts(<grantNumber>HHSN268201100005C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100006C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100007C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100008C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100009C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100010C</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HHSN268201100011C</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>HHSN268201100012C</grantNumber>), <grantNumber>R01HL087641</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>R01HL59367</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R01HL086694</grantNumber>; <fundingAgency>National Human Genome Research Institute</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>U01HG004402</grantNumber>; and <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency> contract <grantNumber>HHSN268200625226C</grantNumber> and infrastructure support <grantNumber>UL1RR025005</grantNumber>. CHS research was supported by <fundingAgency>NHLBI</fundingAgency> contracts <grantNumber>N01-HC-85239</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01-HC-85079</grantNumber> through <grantNumber>N01-HC-85086</grantNumber>; <grantNumber>N01-HC-35129</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01 HC-15103</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01 HC-55222</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01-HC-75150</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01-HC-45133</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>NHLBI</fundingAgency> grants <grantNumber>HL080295</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HL075366</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HL087652</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>HL105756</grantNumber> with additional contribution from <fundingAgency>NINDS</fundingAgency>. Additional support was provided through <grantNumber>AG-023629</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AG-15928</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>AG-20098</grantNumber> , and <grantNumber>AG-027058</grantNumber> from the <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency>. DNA handling and genotyping was supported in part by <fundingAgency>National Center for Research Resources</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>M01-RR00425</grantNumber> and <fundingAgency>National Institute of Diabetes and Digestive and Kidney Diseases</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>DK063491</grantNumber>. The <projectName>Family Heart Study GWAS</projectName> was funded by grant <grantNumber>HL08770002</grantNumber> and the work was supported by <fundingAgency>NHLBI</fundingAgency> contract numbers <grantNumber>R01HL08770003I</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>R01DK06833603</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>R01DK07568101</grantNumber> from <fundingAgency>NIDDK</fundingAgency>. This work was partially supported by the <fundingAgency>National Heart, Lung and Blood Institute's Framingham Heart Study</fundingAgency> (Contract No. <grantNumber>N01-HC-25195</grantNumber>) and its contract with <fundingAgency>Affymetrix, Inc</fundingAgency> for genotyping services (Contract No. <grantNumber>N02-HL-6-4278</grantNumber>). A portion of this research utilized the Linux Cluster for Genetic Analysis (LinGA-II) funded by the <programName>Robert Dawson Evans Endowment</programName> of the <fundingAgency>Department of Medicine at Boston University School of Medicine and Boston Medical Center</fundingAgency>. "<projectName>Genetic Epidemiology Network of Arteriopathy (GENOA) study</projectName> is supported by the <fundingAgency>NIH</fundingAgency>, grant number <grantNumber>5R01HL087660</grantNumber>." The <projectName>Gutenberg Heart Study</projectName> is funded through <fundingAgency>Rheinland-Pfalz</fundingAgency> ("<programName>Stiftung Rheinland Pfalz für Innovation</programName>", contract number <grantNumber>AZ 961-386261/733</grantNumber>), the research programs "<programName>Wissen schafft Zukunft</programName>" and "<programName>Schwerpunkt Vaskuläre Prävention</programName>" of the <fundingAgency>Johannes Gutenberg-University of Mainz</fundingAgency> and its contract with <fundingAgency>Boehringer Ingelheim</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>PHILIPS Medical Systems</fundingAgency> including an unrestricted grant for the <projectName>Gutenberg Heart Study</projectName>. This research was also supported by the <fundingAgency>National Genome Network "NGFNplus"</fundingAgency> (contract number project <grantNumber>A3 01GS0833</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>01GS0831</grantNumber>) by the <fundingAgency>Federal Ministry of Education and Research, Germany</fundingAgency>. <projectName>Health ABC</projectName> was supported by <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> contracts <grantNumber>N01AG62101</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>N01AG62103</grantNumber>, and <grantNumber>N01AG62106</grantNumber>. The <projectName>GWAS</projectName> was funded by <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> grant <grantNumber>1R01AG032098-01A1</grantNumber> to Wake Forest University Health Sciences and genotyping services were provided by the Center for Inherited Disease Research (CIDR). CIDR is fully funded through a federal contract from the <fundingAgency>National Institutes of Health</fundingAgency> to The Johns Hopkins University, contract number <grantNumber>HHSN268200782096C</grantNumber>. The <projectName>InCHIANTI study baseline</projectName> (1998-2000) was supported as a "<programName>targeted project</programName>"(<grantNumber>ICS110.1/RF97.71</grantNumber>) by the <fundingAgency>Italian Ministry of Health</fundingAgency> and in part by the <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> (Contracts: <grantNumber>263 MD 9164</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>263 MD 821336</grantNumber>); the <projectName>InCHIANTI Follow-up 1</projectName> (2001-2003) was funded by <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> (Contracts: <grantNumber>N.1-AG-1-1</grantNumber> and <grantNumber>N.1-AG-1-2111</grantNumber>); the <projectName>InCHIANTI Follow-ups 2 and 3 studies</projectName> (2004-2010) were funded by <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> ( Contract: <grantNumber>N01-AG-5-0002</grantNumber>); supported in part by the <fundingAgency>NIA</fundingAgency> <programName>Intramural research program</programName>. A portion of the support was through a R&amp;D contract with <fundingAgency>MedStar Health Research Institute</fundingAgency>. <projectName>KORA F3</projectName> and <projectName>KORA F4</projectName> was partially funded by the "<programName>Genomics of Lipid-associated Disorders -GOLD</programName>" of the "<programName>Austrian Genome Research Programme GEN-AU</programName>" and by the <fundingAgency>Austrian Heart Fund</fundingAgency> to F. Kronenberg and by the <fundingAgency>Austrian National Bank</fundingAgency> (Project-Nr. <grantNumber>13662</grantNumber>) to Barbara Kollerits. The <projectName>MONICA/KORA Augsburg cohort study</projectName> was financed by the <fundingAgency>Helmholtz Zentrum München</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>German National Genome Research Net NGFN2 and NGFNplus</fundingAgency> (H.-E. Wichmann <grantNumber>01GS0823</grantNumber>). NESDA was supported by the <programName>Geestkracht program</programName> of <fundingAgency>ZonMW</fundingAgency> [grant <grantNumber>10-000-1002</grantNumber>]; matching funds from universities and mental health care institutes involved in NESDA (<fundingAgency>GGZ Buitenamstel-Geestgronden</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Rivierduinen</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>University Medical Center Groningen</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>GGZ 25 Lentis</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>GGZ Friesland</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>GGZ Drenthe</fundingAgency>). Genotyping was funded by the <fundingAgency>Genetic Association Information Network (GAIN)</fundingAgency> of the Foundation for the <fundingAgency>US NIH</fundingAgency>, and analysis was supported by grants from <fundingAgency>GAIN</fundingAgency> and the <fundingAgency>NIMH</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>MH081802</grantNumber>). NBS support was obtained from <fundingAgency>RUNMC</fundingAgency>. The measurement of ABI was supported by Grant <grantNumber>2003B057</grantNumber> of the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Heart Foundation</fundingAgency>. This work was sponsored by the <fundingAgency>Stichting Nationale Computerfaciliteiten (National Computing Facilities Foundation, NCF)</fundingAgency> for the use of supercomputer facilities, with financial support from the <fundingAgency>Nederlandse Organisatie voor Wetenschappelijk Onderzoek (Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research, NWO)</fundingAgency>. The <projectName>Rotterdam GWA study</projectName> was funded by the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organisation of Scientific Research NWO Investments</fundingAgency> (nr. <grantNumber>175.010.2005.011</grantNumber>, <grantNumber>911-03-012</grantNumber>), the <fundingAgency>Research Institute for Diseases in the Elderly</fundingAgency> (<grantNumber>014-93-015</grantNumber>; <projectName>RIDE2</projectName>), the <fundingAgency>Netherlands Genomics Initiative (NGI)</fundingAgency>/<fundingAgency>Netherlands Consortium for Healthy Aging (NCHA)</fundingAgency> project nr. <grantNumber>050-060-810</grantNumber>. Dr Jacqueline Witteman is supported by <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for Scientific Research (NOW)</fundingAgency> grant (<grantName>vici</grantName>, <grantNumber>918-76-619</grantNumber>). Abbas Dehghan is supported by <fundingAgency>Erasmus University Rotterdam</fundingAgency> (EUR) <grantName>fellowship</grantName>. The <projectName>Rotterdam Study</projectName> is funded by <fundingAgency>Erasmus Medical Center</fundingAgency> and <fundingAgency>Erasmus University, Rotterdam</fundingAgency>, <fundingAgency>Netherlands Organization for the Health Research and Development (ZonMw)</fundingAgency>, the <fundingAgency>Research Institute for Diseases in the Elderly</fundingAgency> </funding>
</fundings>