<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>server date 20190912; downloaded by EPO on 20190913 <lb/>CCAMP Working Group <lb/>I. Busi <lb/>Internet Draft <lb/>Huawei <lb/>Intended status: Informational <lb/>D. King <lb/>Old Dog Consulting <lb/>H. Zheng <lb/>Huawei <lb/>Y. Xu <lb/>CAICT <lb/>Expires: March 2020 <lb/>September 12, 2019 <lb/>Transport Northbound Interface Applicability Statement <lb/>draft-ietf-ccamp-transport-nbi-app-statement-06 <lb/>Status of this Memo <lb/>This Internet-Draft is submitted in full conformance with the <lb/>provisions of BCP 78 and BCP 79. <lb/>Internet-Drafts are working documents of the Internet Engineering <lb/>Task Force (IETF), its areas, and its working groups. Note that <lb/>other groups may also distribute working documents as Internet-<lb/>Drafts. <lb/>Internet-Drafts are draft documents valid for a maximum of six <lb/>months and may be updated, replaced, or obsoleted by other documents <lb/>at any time. It is inappropriate to use Internet-Drafts as <lb/>reference material or to cite them other than as &quot;work in progress.&quot; <lb/>The list of current Internet-Drafts can be accessed at <lb/>http://www.ietf.org/ietf/1id-abstracts.txt <lb/>The list of Internet-Draft Shadow Directories can be accessed at <lb/>http://www.ietf.org/shadow.html <lb/>This Internet-Draft will expire on March 12, 2020. <lb/>Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/>[Page 1] <lb/>Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/>Copyright Notice <lb/>Copyright (c) 2019 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the <lb/>document authors. All rights reserved. <lb/>This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust&apos;s Legal <lb/>Provisions Relating to IETF Documents <lb/>(http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of <lb/>publication of this document. Please review these documents <lb/>carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with <lb/>respect to this document. Code Components extracted from this <lb/>document must include Simplified BSD License text as described in <lb/>Section 4.e of the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without <lb/>warranty as described in the Simplified BSD License. <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Transport network domains, including Optical Transport Network (OTN) <lb/>and Wavelength Division Multiplexing (WDM) networks, are typically <lb/>deployed based on a single vendor or technology platforms. They are <lb/>often managed using proprietary interfaces to dedicated Element <lb/>Management Systems (EMS), Network Management Systems (NMS) and <lb/>increasingly Software Defined Network (SDN) controllers. <lb/>A well-defined open interface to each domain management system or <lb/>controller is required for network operators to facilitate control <lb/>automation and orchestrate end-to-end services across multi-domain <lb/>networks. These functions may be enabled using standardized data <lb/>models (e.g. YANG), and appropriate protocol (e.g., RESTCONF). <lb/>This document analyses the applicability of the YANG models being <lb/>defined by the IETF (Traffic Engineering Architecture and Signaling <lb/>(TEAS) and Common Control and Measurement Plane (CCAMP) WGs in <lb/>particular) to support OTN single and multi-domain scenarios. <lb/></front>

			<div type="toc">Table of Contents <lb/>1. Introduction...................................................4 <lb/>1.1. The scope of this document................................4 <lb/>1.2. Assumptions...............................................5 <lb/>2. Terminology....................................................6 <lb/>3. Conventions used in this document..............................7 <lb/>3.1. Topology and traffic flow processing......................7 <lb/>3.2. JSON code.................................................8 <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 2] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="toc">4. Scenarios Description..........................................9 <lb/>4.1. Reference Network.........................................9 <lb/>4.2. Topology Abstractions....................................13 <lb/>4.3. Service Configuration....................................15 <lb/>4.3.1. ODU Transit.........................................16 <lb/>4.3.2. EPL over ODU........................................17 <lb/>4.3.3. Other OTN Clients Services..........................18 <lb/>4.3.4. EVPL over ODU.......................................19 <lb/>4.4. Multi-function Access Links..............................20 <lb/>4.5. Protection and Restoration Configuration.................21 <lb/>4.5.1. Linear Protection (end-to-end)......................21 <lb/>4.5.2. Segmented Protection................................23 <lb/>4.6. Notification.............................................23 <lb/>4.7. Path Computation with Constraint.........................24 <lb/>5. YANG Model Analysis...........................................24 <lb/>5.1. YANG Models for Topology Abstraction.....................25 <lb/>5.1.1. Domain 1 Black Topology Abstraction.................26 <lb/>5.1.2. Domain 2 Black Topology Abstraction.................30 <lb/>5.1.3. Domain 3 White Topology Abstraction.................31 <lb/>5.1.4. Multi-domain Topology Merging.......................31 <lb/>5.2. YANG Models for Service Configuration....................33 <lb/>5.2.1. ODU Transit Service.................................36 <lb/>5.2.1.1. Single Domain Example..........................38 <lb/>5.2.2. EPL over ODU Service................................38 <lb/>5.2.2.1. Single Domain Example..........................40 <lb/>5.2.3. Other OTN Client Services...........................41 <lb/>5.2.3.1. Single Domain Example..........................42 <lb/>5.2.4. EVPL over ODU Service...............................42 <lb/>5.3. YANG Models for Protection Configuration.................44 <lb/>5.3.1. Linear Protection (end-to-end)......................44 <lb/>5.4. Notifications............................................44 <lb/>5.5. Path Computation with Constraints........................44 <lb/>6. Security Considerations.......................................44 <lb/>7. IANA Considerations...........................................45 <lb/>8. References....................................................45 <lb/>8.1. Normative References.....................................45 <lb/>8.2. Informative References...................................46 <lb/>9. Acknowledgments...............................................47 <lb/>Appendix A. <lb/>Validating a JSON fragment against a YANG Model...49 <lb/>A.1. Manipulation of JSON fragments..........................49 <lb/>A.2. Comments in JSON fragments..............................50 <lb/>A.3. Validation of JSON fragments: DSDL-based approach.......50 <lb/>A.4. Validation of JSON fragments: why not using a XSD-based <lb/>approach......................................................51 <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 3] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="toc">Appendix B. <lb/> Detailed JSON Examples............................52 <lb/>B.1. JSON Examples for Topology Abstractions.................52 <lb/>B.1.1. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-otn-topology.json.................52 <lb/>B.2. JSON Examples for Service Configuration.................68 <lb/>B.2.1. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-odu2-service-config.json..........68 <lb/>B.2.2. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-odu2-tunnel-config.json...........72 <lb/>B.2.3. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-epl-service-config.json...........72 <lb/></div>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Transport of packet services are critical for a wide-range of <lb/>applications and services, including data center and LAN <lb/>interconnects, Internet service backhauling mobile backhaul and <lb/>enterprise Carrier Ethernet services. These services are typically <lb/>setup using stovepipe NMS and EMS platforms, often requiring <lb/>propriety management platforms and legacy management interfaces. A <lb/>clear goal of operators is to automate the setup of transport <lb/>services across multiple transport technology domains. <lb/>A common open interface (API) to each domain controller and or <lb/>management system is pre-requisite for network operators to control <lb/>multi-vendor and multi-domain networks and also enable service <lb/>provisioning coordination/automation. This can be achieved by using <lb/>standardized YANG models, used together with an appropriate protocol <lb/>(e.g., RESTCONF [RFC8040]). <lb/>This document analyses the applicability of the YANG models being <lb/>defined by IETF (Traffic Engineering Architecture and Signaling <lb/>(TEAS) and Common Control and Measurement Plane (CCAMP) WGs in <lb/>particular) to support Optical Transport Networks (OTN) single and <lb/>multi-domain scenarios. <lb/>1.1. The scope of this document <lb/>This document assumes a reference architecture, including <lb/>interfaces, based on the Abstraction and Control of Traffic-<lb/>Engineered Networks (ACTN), defined in [RFC8453]. <lb/>The focus of this document is on the MPI (interface between the <lb/>Multi Domain Service Coordinator (MDSC) and a Physical Network <lb/>Controller (PNC), controlling a transport network domain). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 4] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>It is worth noting that the same MPI analyzed in this document could <lb/> be used between hierarchical MDSC controllers, as shown in Figure 4 <lb/>of [RFC8453]. <lb/>Detailed analysis of the CMI (interface between the Customer Network <lb/>Controller (CNC) and the MDSC) as well as of the interface between <lb/>service and network orchestrators are outside the scope of this <lb/>document. However, some considerations and assumptions about the <lb/>information are described when needed. <lb/>The relationship between the current IETF YANG models and the type <lb/>of ACTN interfaces can be found in [ACTN-YANG]. Therefore, it <lb/>considers the TE Topology YANG model defined in [TE-TOPO], with the <lb/>OTN Topology augmentation defined in [OTN-TOPO] and the TE Tunnel <lb/>YANG model defined in [TE-TUNNEL], with the OTN Tunnel augmentation <lb/>defined in [OTN-TUNNEL]. It also considers the Ethernet Client <lb/>Topology augmentation defined in [CLIENT-TOPO] as well as the Client <lb/>Signal YANG models defined in [CLIENT-SIGNAL] for both Transparent <lb/>and Ethernet clients. <lb/>The ONF Technical Recommendations for Functional Requirements for <lb/>the transport API in [ONF TR-527] and the ONF transport API multi-<lb/>domain examples in [ONF GitHub] have been considered as input for <lb/>defining the reference scenarios analyzed in this document. <lb/>1.2. Assumptions <lb/>This document is making the following assumptions: <lb/>1. The MDSC can request, at the MPI, a PNC to setup a Transit Tunnel <lb/>Segment using the TE Tunnel YANG model: in this case, since the <lb/>endpoints of the E2E Tunnel are outside the domain controlled by <lb/>that PNC, the MDSC would not specify any source or destination TE <lb/>Tunnel Termination Point (TTP), i.e., it would leave empty the <lb/>source, destination, src-tp-id and dst-tp-id attributes of the TE <lb/>tunnel instance, and it would use the explicit-route-object (ERO) <lb/>or route-object-include-exclude list to specify the ingress and <lb/>egress links for each path of the Transit Tunnel Segment. <lb/>2. Each PNC provides to the MDSC, at the MPI, the list of available <lb/>timeslots on the inter-domain links using the TE Topology YANG <lb/>model and OTN Topology augmentation. The TE Topology YANG model <lb/>in [TE-TOPO] is being updated to report the label set <lb/>information. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 5] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>See section 1.7 of [TE-TUTORIAL] for more details. <lb/> This document has made the following assumptions: <lb/>1. The topology information for the Ethernet Client access links is <lb/>modelled using the YANG model defined in [CLIENT-TOPO]; <lb/>2. The topology information for the OTN and Transparent Client <lb/>access links is modelled using the YANG model defined in [OTN-<lb/>TOPO]; <lb/>3. The mapping information for Ethernet and Transparent Client <lb/>signals are modelled using the YANG model defined in [CLIENT-<lb/>SIGNAL]. <lb/>Finally, the Network Elements (NEs) described in the scenarios used <lb/>in the document are using ODU switching. It is assumed that the ODU <lb/>links are pre-configured and using mechanisms such as WDM <lb/>wavelength, which are outside the scope of this document. <lb/>2. Terminology <lb/>Domain: A domain as defined by [RFC4655] is &quot;any collection of <lb/>network elements within a common sphere of address management or <lb/>path computation responsibility&quot;. Specifically, within this <lb/>document we mean a part of an operator&apos;s network that is under <lb/>common management (i.e., under shared operational management using <lb/>the same instances of a tool and the same policies). Network <lb/>elements will often be grouped into domains based on technology <lb/>types, vendor profiles, and geographic proximity. <lb/>E-LINE: Ethernet Line <lb/>EPL: Ethernet Private Line <lb/>EVPL: Ethernet Virtual Private Line <lb/>OTN: Optical Transport Network <lb/>Service: A service in the context of this document can be considered <lb/>as some form of connectivity between customer sites across the <lb/>network operator&apos;s network [RFC8309]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 6] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Service Model: As described in [RFC8309] it describes a service and <lb/> the parameters of the service in a portable way that can be used <lb/>uniformly and independent of the equipment and operating <lb/>environment. <lb/>UNI: User Network Interface <lb/>MDSC: Multi-Domain Service Coordinator <lb/>CNC: Customer Network Controller <lb/>PNC: Provisioning Network Controller <lb/>3. Conventions used in this document <lb/>3.1. Topology and traffic flow processing <lb/>The traffic flow between different nodes is specified as an ordered <lb/>list of nodes, separated with commas, indicating within the brackets <lb/>the processing within each node: <lb/>&lt;node&gt; [&lt;processing&gt;]{, &lt;node&gt; [&lt;processing&gt;]} <lb/>The order represents the order of traffic flow being forwarded <lb/>through the network. <lb/>The processing can be just switching at a given layer <lb/>&quot;[(switching)]&quot; or also having an adaptation of a client layer into <lb/>a server layer &quot;[(client) -&gt; server]&quot; or [client -&gt; (server)], <lb/>depending on whether the node is switching in the client or in the <lb/>server layer. <lb/>For example, the following traffic flow: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ODU2], S3 [(ODU2)], S5 [(ODU2)], S6 [(ODU2)], <lb/>R3 [ODU2 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>Node R1 is switching at the packet (PKT) layer and mapping packets <lb/>into an ODU2 before transmission to node S3. Nodes S3, S5 and S6 are <lb/>switching at the ODU2 layer: S3 sends the ODU2 traffic to S5 which <lb/>then sends it to S6 which finally sends to R3. Node R3 terminates <lb/>the ODU2 from S6 before switching at the packet (PKT) layer. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 7] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>The paths of working and protection transport entities are specified <lb/>as an ordered list of nodes, separated with commas: <lb/>&lt;node&gt; {, &lt;node&gt;} <lb/>The order represents the order of traffic flow being forwarded <lb/>through the network in the forward direction. In the case of <lb/>bidirectional paths, the forward and backward directions are <lb/>selected arbitrarily, but the convention is consistent between <lb/>working/protection path pairs, as well as across multiple domains. <lb/>3.2. JSON code <lb/>This document provides some detailed JSON code examples to describe <lb/>how the YANG models being developed by the IETF (TEAS and CCAMP WG <lb/>in particular) may be used. The scenario examples are provided using <lb/>JSON to facilitate readability. <lb/>Different objects need to have an identifier. The convention used to <lb/>create mnemonic identifiers is to use the object name (e.g., S3 for <lb/>node S3), followed by its type (e.g., NODE), separated by an &quot;-&quot;, <lb/>followed by &quot;-ID&quot;. For example, the mnemonic identifier for node S3 <lb/>would be S3-NODE-ID. <lb/>The JSON language does not support the insertion of comments that <lb/>have been instead found to be useful when writing the examples. This <lb/>document will insert comments into the JSON code as JSON name/value <lb/>pair with the JSON name string starting with the &quot;//&quot; characters. <lb/>For example, when describing the example of a TE Topology instance <lb/>representing the ODU Abstract Topology exposed by the Transport PNC, <lb/>the following comment has been added to the JSON code: <lb/>&quot;// comment&quot;: &quot;ODU Abstract Topology @ MPI&quot;, <lb/>The JSON code examples provided in this document have been validated <lb/>against the YANG models following the validation process described <lb/>in Appendix A, which would not consider the comments. <lb/>In order to have successful validation of the examples, some <lb/>numbering scheme has been defined to assign identifiers to the <lb/>different entities which would pass the syntax checks. In that case, <lb/>to simplify the reading, another JSON name/value pair formatted as a <lb/>comment and using the mnemonic identifiers is also provided. For <lb/>example, the identifier of node S3 (S3-NODE-ID) has been assumed to <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 8] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>be &quot;10.0.0.3&quot; and would be shown in the JSON code example using the <lb/>two JSON name/value pair: <lb/>&quot;// te-node-id&quot;: &quot;S3-NODE-ID&quot;, <lb/>&quot;te-node-id&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.3&quot;, <lb/>The first JSON name/value pair will be automatically removed in the <lb/>first step of the validation process while the second JSON <lb/>name/value pair will be validated against the YANG model <lb/>definitions. <lb/>4. Scenarios Description <lb/>4.1. Reference Network <lb/>The physical topology of the reference network is shown in Figure 1. <lb/>It represents an OTN network composed of three transport network <lb/>domains which provide transport connectivity services to an IP <lb/>customer network through eight access links: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 9] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019</note>

			<body> <lb/>........................ <lb/>......... <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>Network domain 1 <lb/>: <lb/>............. <lb/>Customer: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>domain : <lb/>: <lb/>S1 -------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: Network : <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: domain 3 : <lb/>.......... <lb/>R1 -------S3 -----S4 <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>\ <lb/>S2 --------+ <lb/>: <lb/>:Customer <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>\ <lb/>| : <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: domain <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S5 <lb/>\ <lb/>| : <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>R2 ------+ <lb/>/ \ <lb/>\ | : <lb/>: <lb/>S31 ---------R5 <lb/>: <lb/>: \ / <lb/>\ <lb/>\ | : <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>R3 -------S6 ----S7 ----S8 ------S32 <lb/>S33 ------R6 <lb/>: <lb/>: / <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: / \ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>:....... <lb/>R4 ------+ <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>:/ <lb/>S34 <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>:..........|.......|...: <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>........: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>/:.../.......: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>...........|.......|..../..../... <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>.............. <lb/>: Network | <lb/>| / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: domain 2 | <lb/>| / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>:Customer <lb/>: <lb/>S11 ----S12 <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: domain <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>| \ / <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S13 <lb/>S14 <lb/>| S15 -------------R7 <lb/>: <lb/>| \ <lb/>/ <lb/>\ | <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>S16 <lb/>\ | <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| / <lb/>S17 --S18 ---------R8 <lb/>: <lb/>| / <lb/>\ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S19 ----S20 ----S21 ------------R9 <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>:...............................: <lb/>:............. <lb/>Figure 1 -Reference network <lb/>This document assumes that all the transport network switching nodes <lb/>Si are capable of switching in the electrical domain (ODU switching) <lb/>and that all the Si-Sj OTN links within the transport network <lb/>(intra-domain or inter-domain) are 100G links while the access Ri-Sj <lb/>links are 10G links. <lb/>It is also assumed that, within the transport network, the <lb/>physical/optical interconnections supporting the Si-Sj OTN links (up <lb/>to the OTU4 trail), are pre-configured using mechanisms which are <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 10] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>outside the scope of this document and are not exposed at the MPIs <lb/> to the MDSC. <lb/>Different technologies can be used on the access links (e.g., <lb/>Ethernet, STM-N and OTU). Section 4.3 provides more details about <lb/>the different assumptions on the access links for different services <lb/>types and section 4.4 describes the control of access links which <lb/>can support different technology configuration (e.g., STM-64, 10GE <lb/>or OTU2) depending on the type of service being configured (multi-<lb/>function access links). <lb/>The transport domain control architecture, shown in Figure 2, <lb/>follows the ACTN architecture and framework document [RFC8453], and <lb/>functional components: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 11] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>--------------<lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>CNC <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>--------------<lb/>| <lb/>....................|....................... CMI <lb/>| <lb/>----------------<lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>MDSC <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>----------------<lb/>/ <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>/ <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>............../.....|......\................ MPIs <lb/>/ <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>/ <lb/>----------<lb/>\ <lb/>/ <lb/>| <lb/>PNC2 <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>/ <lb/>----------<lb/>\ <lb/>----------<lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>PNC1 <lb/>| <lb/>-----<lb/>\ <lb/>----------<lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>----------<lb/>| <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>| <lb/>PNC3 <lb/>| <lb/>-----<lb/>( Network ) <lb/>----------<lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( Domain 2 ) <lb/>| <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>-----<lb/>( Network ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( Domain 1 ) <lb/>-----<lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( Network ) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( Domain 3 ) <lb/>-----<lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>-----<lb/>Figure 2 -Controlling Hierarchies <lb/>The ACTN framework facilitates the detachment of the network and <lb/>service control from the underlying technology. It helps the <lb/>customer define the network as desired by business needs. Therefore, <lb/>care must be taken to keep a minimal level of dependency on the CMI <lb/>(or no dependency at all) with respect to the network domain <lb/>technologies. The MPI instead requires some specialization according <lb/>to the domain technology. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 12] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>The control interfaces within the scope of this document are the <lb/>three MPIs shown in Figure 2. <lb/>It is worth noting that the split of functionality at the MPI in the <lb/>ACTN architecture between the MDSC and the PNCs is <lb/>equivalent/analogous to the split of functionality which is assumed <lb/>for the ONF T-API interface when used between a multi-domain <lb/>controller and domain controllers, as described in the ONF T-API <lb/>multi-domain use cases [ONF TR-527], as well as at the MEF PRESTO <lb/>interface between the Service Orchestration Functionality (SOF) and <lb/>the Infrastructure Control and Management (ICM) in the MEF LSO <lb/>Architecture [MEF 55]. <lb/>This document does not make any assumption about the control <lb/>architecture of the customer IP network: in line with [RFC8453], the <lb/>CNC is just a functional component within the customer control <lb/>architecture which is capable of requesting, at the CMI, transport <lb/>connectivity between IP routers, when needed. <lb/>The CNC can request transport connectivity services between IP <lb/>routers which can be attached to different transport domains (e.g., <lb/>between R1 and R8 in Figure 1) or to the same transport domain <lb/>(e.g., between R1 and R3 in Figure 1). Since the CNC is not aware of <lb/>the transport network controlling hierarchy, the mechanisms used by <lb/>the CNC to request, at the CMI, transport connectivity services are <lb/>independent on whether the service request is single-domain or <lb/>multi-domain. <lb/>It is assumed that the CMI allows the CNC to provide all the <lb/>information that is required by the MDSC to understand the <lb/>connectivity service request and to decide the network <lb/>configurations to be requested, at the MPIs, to its underlying PNCs <lb/>to support the requested connectivity service. <lb/>When a single-domain service is requested by the CNC at the CMI <lb/>(e.g., between R1 and R3 in Figure 1), the MDSC can follow the same <lb/>procedures, described above for the multi-domain service, and decide <lb/>the network configuration to request only at the MPI of the PNC <lb/>controlling that domain (e.g., MPI1 of PNC1 in Figure 2). <lb/>4.2. Topology Abstractions <lb/>Abstraction provides a selective method for representing <lb/>connectivity information within a domain. There are multiple methods <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 13] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>to abstract a network topology. This document assumes the <lb/> abstraction method defined in [RFC7926]: <lb/>&quot;Abstraction is the process of applying the policy to the <lb/>available TE information within a domain, to produce selective <lb/>information that represents the potential ability to connect <lb/>across the domain. Thus, abstraction does not necessarily offer <lb/>all possible connectivity options, but presents a general view of <lb/>potential connectivity according to the policies that determine <lb/>how the domain&apos;s administrator wants to allow the domain resources <lb/>to be used.&quot; <lb/>[RFC8453] Provides the context of topology abstraction in the ACTN <lb/>architecture and discusses a few alternatives for the abstraction <lb/>methods for both packet and optical networks. This is an important <lb/>consideration since the choice of the abstraction method impacts <lb/>protocol design and the information it carries. According to <lb/>[RFC8453], there are three types of topology: <lb/>o White topology: This is a case where the PNC provides the actual <lb/>network topology to the MDSC without any hiding or filtering. In <lb/>this case, the MDSC has the full knowledge of the underlying <lb/>network topology; <lb/>o Black topology: The entire domain network is abstracted as a <lb/>single virtual node with the access/egress links without <lb/>disclosing any node internal connectivity information; <lb/>o Grey topology: This abstraction level is between black topology <lb/>and white topology from a granularity point of view. This is an <lb/>abstraction of TE tunnels for all pairs of border nodes. We may <lb/>further differentiate from a perspective of how to abstract <lb/>internal TE resources between the pairs of border nodes: <lb/>-Grey topology type A: border nodes with TE links between them <lb/>in a full mesh fashion; <lb/>-Grey topology type B: border nodes with some internal <lb/>abstracted nodes and abstracted links. <lb/>Each PNC should provide the MDSC with a network topology <lb/>abstractions hiding the internal details of the physical domain <lb/>network topology controlled by the PNC and this abstraction is <lb/>independent of the abstractions provided by other PNCs. Therefore it <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 14] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>is possible that different PNCs provide different types of topology <lb/> abstractions and each MPI operates on the abstract topology <lb/>regardless of, and independently from, the type of abstraction <lb/>provided by the PNC. <lb/>To analyze how the MDSC can operate on abstract topologies <lb/>independently from the topology abstraction provided by each PNC <lb/>and, therefore, that different PNCs can provide different topology <lb/>abstractions, that the following examples are assumed: <lb/>o PNC1 and PNC2 provide black topology abstractions which expose at <lb/>MPI1, and MPI2 respectively, a single virtual node (representing <lb/>the whole network domain 1, and domain 2 respectively). <lb/>o PNC3 provides a white topology abstraction which exposes at MPI3 <lb/>all the physical nodes and links within network domain 3. <lb/>The MDSC should be capable of stitching together the abstracted <lb/>topologies provided by each PNC to build its own view of the <lb/>multi-domain network topology. The process may require suitable <lb/>oversight, including administrative configuration and trust models, <lb/>a method of how to achieve this is out of scope for this document. <lb/>The MDSC can also provide topology abstraction of its own view of <lb/>the multi-domain network topology at its CMIs depending on the <lb/>customers&apos; needs: it can provide different types of topology <lb/>abstractions at different CMIs. Analyzing the topology abstractions <lb/>provided by the MDSC to its CMIs is outside the scope of this <lb/>document. <lb/>4.3. Service Configuration <lb/>In the following scenarios, it is assumed that the CNC is capable of <lb/>requesting service connectivity from the MDSC to support IP routers <lb/>connectivity. <lb/>The type of services could depend on the type of physical links <lb/>(e.g. OTN link, ETH link or SDH link) between the routers and <lb/>transport network. <lb/>The control of different adaptations inside IP routers, Ri (PKT -&gt; <lb/>foo) and Rj (foo -&gt; PKT), are assumed to be performed by means that <lb/>are not under the control of, and not visible to, the MDSC nor to <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 15] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>the PNCs. Therefore, these mechanisms are outside the scope of this <lb/>document. <lb/>4.3.1. ODU Transit <lb/>The physical links interconnecting the IP routers and the transport <lb/>network can be 10G OTN links. <lb/>In this case, it is assumed that the physical/optical <lb/>interconnections below the ODU layer (up to the OTU2 trail) are <lb/>pre-configured using mechanisms which are outside the scope of this <lb/>document and not exposed at the MPIs between the PNCs and the MDSC. <lb/>For simplicity of the description, it is also assumed that these <lb/>interfaces are not channelized (i.e., they can only support one <lb/>ODU2). <lb/>To setup a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R8, an ODU2 end-to-end <lb/>connection needs to be created, passing through transport nodes S3, <lb/>S1, S2, S31, S33, S34, S15 and S18 which belong to different PNC <lb/>domains (multi-domain service request): <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ODU2], S3 [(ODU2]), S1 [(ODU2]), S2 [(ODU2]), <lb/>S31 [(ODU2)], S33 [(ODU2)], S34 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU2)], S18 [(ODU2)], R8 [ODU2 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>The MDSC understands that it needs to establish an ODU2 transit <lb/>service between the access links on S3 and S18, which belong to <lb/>different PNC domains (multi-domain service request). It also <lb/>decides the network configurations to request, at the MPIs, to its <lb/>underlying PNCs, to coordinate the setup of a multi-domain ODU2 <lb/>segment connection between the access links on S3 and S18. <lb/>To setup of a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R3, an ODU2 end-to-end <lb/>connection needs to be created, passing through transport nodes S3, <lb/>S5 and S6 which belong to the same PNC domain (single-domain service <lb/>request): <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ODU2], S3 [(ODU2)], S5 [(ODU2)], S6 [(ODU2)], <lb/>R3 [ODU2 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>As described in section 4.1, the mechanisms used by the CNC at the <lb/>CMI are independent on whether the service request is single-domain <lb/>service or multi-domain. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 16] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>The MDSC can understand that it needs to setup an ODU2 transit <lb/> service between the access links on S3 and S6, which belong to the <lb/>same PNC domain (single-domain service request) and it decides the <lb/>proper network configuration to request PNC1. <lb/>4.3.2. EPL over ODU <lb/>The physical links interconnecting the IP routers and the transport <lb/>network can be 10G Ethernet physical links (10GE). <lb/>In this case, it is assumed that the Ethernet physical interfaces <lb/>(up to the MAC layer) are pre-configured using mechanisms which are <lb/>outside the scope of this document and not exposed at the MPIs <lb/>between the PNCs and the MDSC. <lb/>To setup a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R8, an EPL service needs to <lb/>be created, supported by an ODU2 end-to-end connection, between <lb/>transport nodes S3 and S18, passing through transport nodes S1, S2, <lb/>S31, S33, S34 and S15, which belong to different PNC domains (multi-<lb/>domain service request): <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ETH], S3 [ETH -&gt; (ODU2)], S1 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S2 [(ODU2)], S31 [(ODU2)), S33 [(ODU2)], S34 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU2)], S18 [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH], R8 [ETH -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>The MDSC understands that it needs to setup an EPL service between <lb/>the access links on S3 and S18, which belong to different PNC <lb/>domains (multi-domain service request). It also decides the network <lb/>configurations to request, at the MPIs, to its underlying PNCs, to <lb/>coordinate the setup of an end-to-end ODU2 connection between the <lb/>nodes S3 and S8, including the configuration of the adaptation <lb/>functions inside these edge nodes, such as S3 [ETH -&gt; (ODU2)] and <lb/>S18 [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH]. <lb/>To setup a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R2, an EPL service needs to <lb/>be created, supported by an ODU2 end-to-end connection between <lb/>transport nodes S3 and S6, passing through the transport node S5, <lb/>which belong to the same PNC domain (single-domain service request): <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ETH], S3 [ETH -&gt; (PKT)] S5 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S6 [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH], R2 [ETH -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 17] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>As described in section 4.1, the mechanisms used by the CNC at the <lb/>CMI are independent on whether the service request is single-domain <lb/>service or multi-domain. <lb/>Based on the assumption above, in this case, the MDSC can understand <lb/>that it needs to setup an EPL service between the access links on S3 <lb/>and S6, which belong to the same PNC domain (single-domain service <lb/>request) and it decides the proper network configuration to request <lb/>PNC1. <lb/>4.3.3. Other OTN Clients Services <lb/>[ITU-T G.709] defines mappings of different Transparent Client <lb/>layers into ODU. Most of them are used to provide Private Line <lb/>services over an OTN transport network supporting a variety of types <lb/>of physical access links (e.g., Ethernet, SDH STM-N, Fibre Channel, <lb/>InfiniBand, etc.) interconnecting the IP routers and the transport <lb/>network. <lb/>In order to setup a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R8 using, with for <lb/>example SDH physical links between the IP routers and the transport <lb/>network, an STM-64 Private Line service needs to be created, <lb/>supported by an ODU2 end-to-end connection, between transport nodes <lb/>S3 and S18, passing through transport nodes S1, S2, S31, S33, S34 <lb/>and S15, which belong to different PNC domains (multi-domain service <lb/>request): <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; STM-64], S3 [STM-64 -&gt; (ODU2)], S1 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S2 [(ODU2)], S31 [(ODU2)], S33 [(ODU2)], S34[(ODU2)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU2)], S18 [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64], R8 [STM-64 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>As already described (section 4.1) CNC provides the essential <lb/>information to permit the MDSC to understand which type of service <lb/>is needed, in this case, an STM-64 Private Line service between the <lb/>access links on S3 and S8, and it also decides the network <lb/>configurations, including the configuration of the adaptation <lb/>functions inside these edge nodes, such as S3 [STM-64 -&gt; (ODU2)] and <lb/>S18 [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64]. <lb/>To setup a 10Gb IP link between R1 and R3), an STM-64 Private Line <lb/>service needs to be created between R1 and R3 (single-domain service <lb/>request): <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 18] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; STM-64], S3[STM-64 -&gt; (ODU2)], S5 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S6 [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64], R3[STM-64 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>As described in section 4.1, the mechanisms used by the CNC at the <lb/>CMI are independent on whether the service request is single-domain <lb/>service or multi-domain. <lb/>Based on the assumption above, in this case, the MDSC can understand <lb/>that it needs to setup an STM-64 Private Line service between the <lb/>access links on S3 and S6, which belong to the same PNC domain <lb/>(single-domain service request) and it decides the proper network <lb/>configuration to request PNC1. <lb/>4.3.4. EVPL over ODU <lb/>When the physical links interconnecting the IP routers and the <lb/>transport network are Ethernet physical links, it is also possible <lb/>that different Ethernet services (e.g., EVPL) can share the same <lb/>physical access link using different VLANs. <lb/>As described in section 4.3.2, it is assumed that the Ethernet <lb/>physical interfaces (up to the MAC layer) are pre-configured. <lb/>To setup two 1Gb IP links between R1 to R2 and between R1 and R8, <lb/>two EVPL services need to be created, supported by two ODU0 end-to-<lb/>end connections: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; VLAN], S3 [VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)], S5 [(ODU0)], <lb/>S6 [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN], R2 [VLAN -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; VLAN], S3[VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)], S1 [(ODU0)], <lb/>S2 [(ODU0)], S31 [(ODU0)], S33 [(ODU0)], S34 [(ODU0)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU0)], S18 [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN], R8[VLAN -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>It is worth noting that the fist EVPL service is required between <lb/>access links which belong to the same PNC domain (single-domain <lb/>service request) while the second EVPL service is required between <lb/>access links which belong to different PNC domains (multi-domain <lb/>service request). <lb/>Since the two EVPL services are sharing the same Ethernet physical <lb/>link between R1 and S3, different VLAN IDs are associated with <lb/>different EVPL services: for example, VLAN IDs 10 and 20 <lb/>respectively. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 19] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Based on the assumptions described in section 4.3.2, the CNC <lb/>requests at the CMI the MDSC to setup these EVPL services and the <lb/>MDSC understands the network configurations to request to the <lb/>underlying PNCs, as described in section 4.3.2. <lb/>4.4. Multi-function Access Links <lb/>Some physical links interconnecting the IP routers and the transport <lb/>network can be configured in different modes, e.g., as OTU2 trail or <lb/>STM-64 or 10GE physical links. <lb/>This configuration can be done a-priori by means which are outside <lb/>the scope of this document. In this case, these links will appear at <lb/>the MPI as links supporting only one mode (depending on the a-priori <lb/>configuration) and will be controlled at the MPI as discussed in <lb/>section 4.3: for example, a 10G multi-function access link can be <lb/>pre-configured as an OTU2 trail (section 4.3.1), a 10GE physical <lb/>link (section 4.3.2) or an STM-64 physical link (section 4.3.3). <lb/>It is also possible not to configure these links a-priori and let <lb/>the MDSC (or, in case of a single-domain service request, the PNC) <lb/>decide how to configure these links, based on the service <lb/>configuration. <lb/>For example, if the physical link between R1 and S3 is a <lb/>multi-functional access link while the physical links between R4 and <lb/>S6 and between R8 and S18 are STM-64 and 10GE physical links <lb/>respectively, it is possible to configure either an STM-64 Private <lb/>Line service between R1 and R4 or an EPL service between R1 and R8. <lb/>The traffic flow between R1 and R4 can be summarized as: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; STM-64], S3 [STM-64 -&gt; (ODU2)], S5 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S6 [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64], R4 [STM-64 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>The traffic flow between R1 and R8 can be summarized as: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ETH], S3 [ETH -&gt; (ODU2)], S1 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S2 [(ODU2)], S31 [(ODU2)), S33 [(ODU2)], S34 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU2)], S18 [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH], R8 [ETH -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>The CNC is capable to request at the CMI the setup either an STM-64 <lb/>Private Line service, between R1 and R4, or an EPL service, between <lb/>R1 and R8. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 20] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>The MDSC, based on the service being request, decides the network <lb/>configurations to request, at the MPIs, to its underlying PNCs, to <lb/>coordinate the setup of an end-to-end ODU2 connection, either <lb/>between nodes S3 and S6, or between nodes S3 and S18, including the <lb/>configuration of the adaptation functions on these edge nodes, and <lb/>in particular whether the multi-function access link between R1 and <lb/>S3 should operate as an STM-64 or as a 10GE physical link. <lb/>4.5. Protection and Restoration Configuration <lb/>Protection switching provides a pre-allocated survivability <lb/>mechanism, typically provided via linear protection methods and <lb/>would be configured to operate as 1+1 unidirectional (the most <lb/>common OTN protection method), 1+1 bidirectional or 1:n <lb/>bidirectional. This ensures fast and simple service survivability. <lb/>Restoration methods would provide the capability to reroute and <lb/>restore connectivity traffic around network faults, without the <lb/>network penalty imposed with dedicated 1+1 protection schemes. <lb/>This section describes only services which are protected with linear <lb/>protection. The description of services using dynamic restoration is <lb/>outside the scope of this document. <lb/>The MDSC needs to be capable of deciding the network configuration <lb/>to request different PNCs to coordinate the protection switching <lb/>configuration to support protected connectivity services described <lb/>in section 4.3. <lb/>Since in these service examples, switching within the transport <lb/>network domain is performed only in the OTN ODU layer. It may also <lb/>be assumed that protection switching within the transport network <lb/>domain is provided at the OTN ODU layer. <lb/>4.5.1. Linear Protection (end-to-end) <lb/>In order to protect the connectivity services described in section <lb/>4.3 from failures within the OTN multi-domain transport network, the <lb/>MDSC can decide to request its underlying PNCs to configure ODU2 <lb/>linear protection between the access nodes (e.g., nodes S3 and S18 <lb/>for the services setup between R1 and R8). <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 21] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>It is assumed that the OTN linear protection is configured to with <lb/>1+1 unidirectional protection switching type, as defined in [ITU-T <lb/>G.808.1] and [ITU-T G.873.1], as well as in [RFC4427]. <lb/>In these scenarios, a working transport entity and a protection <lb/>transport entity, as defined in [ITU-T G.808.1], (or a working LSP <lb/>and a protection LSP, as defined in [RFC4427]) should be configured <lb/>in the data plane. <lb/>Two cases can be considered: <lb/>o In one case, the working and protection transport entities pass <lb/>through the same PNC domains: <lb/>Working transport entity: <lb/>S3, S1, S2, <lb/>S31, S33, S34, <lb/>S15, S18 <lb/>Protection transport entity: S3, S4, S8, <lb/>S32, <lb/>S12, S17, S18 <lb/>o In another case, the working and protection transport entities <lb/>can pass through different PNC domains: <lb/>Working transport entity: <lb/>S3, S5, S7, <lb/>S11, S12, S17, S18 <lb/>Protection transport entity: S3, S1, S2, <lb/>S31, S33, S34, <lb/>S15, S18 <lb/>The PNCs should be capable to report to the MDSC which is the active <lb/>transport entity, as defined in [ITU-T G.808.1], in the data plane. <lb/>Given the fast dynamic of protection switching operations in the <lb/>data plane (50ms recovery time), this reporting is not expected to <lb/>be in real-time. <lb/>It is also worth noting that with unidirectional protection <lb/>switching, e.g., 1+1 unidirectional protection switching, the active <lb/>transport entity may be different in the two directions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 22] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>4.5.2. Segmented Protection <lb/>To protect the connectivity services defined in section 4.3 from <lb/>failures within the OTN multi-domain transport network, the MDSC can <lb/>decide to request its underlying PNCs to configure ODU2 linear <lb/>protection between the edge nodes of each domain. <lb/>For example, MDSC can request PNC1 to configure linear protection <lb/>between its edge nodes S3 and S2: <lb/>Working transport entity: <lb/>S3, S1, S2 <lb/>Protection transport entity: S3, S4, S8, S2 <lb/>MDSC can also request PNC2 to configure linear protection between <lb/>its edge nodes S15 and S18: <lb/>Working transport entity: <lb/>S15, S18 <lb/>Protection transport entity: S15, S12, S17, S18 <lb/>MDSC can also request PNC3 to configure linear protection between <lb/>its edge nodes S31 and S34: <lb/>Working transport entity: <lb/>S31, S33, S34 <lb/>Protection transport entity: S31, S32, S34 <lb/>4.6. Notification <lb/>To realize the topology update, service update and restoration <lb/>function, following notification type should be supported: <lb/>1. Object create <lb/>2. Object delete <lb/>3. Object state change <lb/>4. Alarm <lb/>There are three types of topology abstraction type defined in <lb/>section 4.2, the notification should also be abstracted. The PNC and <lb/>MDSC should coordinate together to determine the notification <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 23] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>policy, such as when an intra-domain alarm occurred, the PNC may not <lb/>report the alarm but the service state change notification to the <lb/>MDSC. <lb/>4.7. Path Computation with Constraint <lb/>It is possible to define constraints to be taken into account during <lb/>path computation procedures (e.g., IRO/XRO). <lb/>For example, the CNC can request, at the CMI, an ODU transit <lb/>service, as described in section 4.3.1, between R1 and R8 with the <lb/>constraint to pass through the link from S2 to S31 (IRO), such that <lb/>a qualified path could be: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ODU2], S3 [(ODU2]), S1 [(ODU2]), S2 [(ODU2]), <lb/>S31 [(ODU2)], S33 [(ODU2)], S34 [(ODU2)], <lb/>S15 [(ODU2)], S18 [(ODU2)], R8 [ODU2 -&gt; (PKT)] <lb/>If the CNC instead requested to pass through the link from S8 to <lb/>S12, then the above path would not be qualified, while the following <lb/>would be: <lb/>R1 [(PKT) -&gt; ODU2], S3[(ODU2]), S1 [(ODU2]), S2[(ODU2]), <lb/>S8 [(ODU2]), S12[(ODU2]), S15 [(ODU2]), S18[(ODU2]), R8 [ODU2 -&gt; <lb/>(PKT)] <lb/>The mechanisms used by the CNC to provide path constraints at the <lb/>CMI are outside the scope of this document. It is assumed that the <lb/>MDSC can understand these constraints and take them into account in <lb/>its path computation procedures (which would decide at least which <lb/>domains and inter-domain links) and in the path constraints to <lb/>provide to its underlying PNCs, to be taken into account in the path <lb/>computation procedures implemented by the PNCs (with a more detailed <lb/>view of topology). <lb/>5. YANG Model Analysis <lb/>This section analyses how the IETF YANG models can be used at the <lb/>MPIs, between the MDSC and the PNCs, to support the scenarios <lb/>described in section 4. <lb/>The YANG models described in [ACTN-YANG] are assumed to be used at <lb/>the MPI. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 24] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Section 5.1 describes the different topology abstractions provided <lb/>to the MDSC by each PNC via its own MPI. <lb/>Section 5.2 describes how the MDSC can request different PNCs, via <lb/>their own MPIs, the network configuration needed to setup the <lb/>different services described in section 4.3. <lb/>Section 5.3 describes how the protection scenarios can be deployed, <lb/>including end-to-end protection and segment protection, for both <lb/>intra-domain and inter-domain scenario. <lb/>5.1. YANG Models for Topology Abstraction <lb/>Each PNC reports its respective OTN abstract topology to the MDSC, <lb/>as described in section 4.2, using the Topology YANG models, defined <lb/>in [RFC8345], with the TE Topology YANG augmentations, provided in <lb/>[TE-TOPO], and the OTN technology-specific YANG augmentations, <lb/>defined in [OTN-TOPO]. <lb/>The [OTN-TOPO] model allows reporting within the OTN abstract <lb/>topology also the access links which are capable of supporting the <lb/>transparent client layers, defined in section 4.3.3 and in <lb/>[CLIENT-SIGNAL]. These links can also be multi-function access links <lb/>that can be configured as a transparent client physical links (e.g., <lb/>STM-64 physical link) as an OTUk trail. <lb/>In order to support the EPL and EVPL services, described in sections <lb/>4.3.2 and 4.3.4, the access links, which are capable to be <lb/>configured as Ethernet physical links, are reported by each PNC <lb/>within its respective Ethernet abstract topology, using the Topology <lb/>YANG models, defined in [RFC8345], with the TE Topology YANG <lb/>augmentations, defined in [TE-TOPO], and the Ethernet client <lb/>technology-specific YANG augmentations, defined in [CLIENT-TOPO]. <lb/>These links can also be multi-function access links that can be <lb/>configured as an Ethernet physical link or as an OTUk trail and/or <lb/>as transparent client physical links (e.g., STM-64 physical link). <lb/>In this case, these physical access links are represented in both <lb/>the OTN and Ethernet abstract topologies. <lb/>It is worth noting that in the network scenarios analyzed in this <lb/>document (where switching is performed only in the ODU layer), the <lb/>Ethernet abstract topologies reported by the PNCs describes only the <lb/>Ethernet client access links: no Ethernet TE switching capabilities <lb/>are reported in these Ethernet abstract topologies. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 25] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>5.1.1. Domain 1 Black Topology Abstraction <lb/>PNC1 provides the required black topology abstraction, as described <lb/>in section 4.2. It exposes at MPI1 to the MDSC, two TE Topology <lb/>instances with only one TE node each. <lb/>The first TE Topology instance reports the domain 1 OTN abstract <lb/>topology view (MPI1 OTN Topology), using the OTN technology-specific <lb/>augmentations [OTN-TOPO], with only one abstract TE node (i.e., AN1) <lb/>and only inter-domain and access abstract TE links (which represent <lb/>the inter-domain physical links and the access physical links which <lb/>can support ODU and/or transparent client layers), as shown in <lb/>Figure 3 below. <lb/>................................... <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+-----------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R1)----------| <lb/>|----------(S31) <lb/>: AN1-1 | <lb/>| AN1-7 : <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R3)----------| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: AN1-2 | <lb/>AN1 <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R4)----------| <lb/>|----------(S32) <lb/>: AN1-3 | <lb/>| AN1-6 : <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+-----------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>AN1-4 | <lb/>| AN1-5 <lb/>: <lb/>:..........|..........|...........: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>(S11) <lb/>(S12) <lb/>Figure 3 -OTN Abstract Topology exposed at MPI1 (MPI1 OTN Topology) <lb/>The second TE Topology instance reports the domain 1 Ethernet <lb/>abstract topology view (MPI1 ETH Topology), using the Ethernet <lb/>technology-specific augmentations [CLIENT-TOPO], with only one <lb/>abstract TE node (i.e., AN1) and only access abstract TE links <lb/>(which represent the access physical links which can support <lb/>Ethernet client layers), as shown in Figure 4 below. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 26] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>................................... <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+-----------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R1)----------| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: AN1-1 | <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R2)----------| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: AN1-8 | <lb/>AN1 <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+-----------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>:.................................: <lb/>Figure 4 -ETH Abstract Topology exposed at MPI1 (MPI1 ETH Topology) <lb/>As described in section 4.1, it is assumed that the OTU4 trails on <lb/>the inter-domain physical links (e.g., the link between S2 and S31) <lb/>are pre-configured and exposed as external TE Links, within the MPI1 <lb/>OTN topology (e.g., the external TE Link terminating on AN1-7 TE <lb/>Link Termination Point (LTP) abstracting the OTU4 trail between S2 <lb/>and S31). <lb/>In order to analyze the service scenarios of sections 4.3 and 4.4: <lb/>o the access link between S3 and R1 is assumed to be a <lb/>multi-function access link, which can be configured as an OTU2 <lb/>trail or as an STM-64 or a 10GE physical link; <lb/>o the access link between S6 and R2 is assumed to be pre-configured <lb/>as a 10GE physical link, up to the MAC layer; <lb/>o the access link between S6 and R3 is assumed to be a <lb/>multi-function access link which can be configured as an OTU2 <lb/>trail or as an STM-64 physical link; <lb/>o the access link connected to router R4 is assumed to be <lb/>pre-configured as an STM-64 physical link. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 27] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Therefore PNC1 exports at MPI1 the following external TE Links, <lb/>within the MPI1 OTN topology: <lb/>o two abstract TE Links, terminating on LTP AN1-1 and AN1-2 <lb/>respectively, abstracting the physical access link between S3 and <lb/>R1 and the access link between S6 and R3 respectively, reporting <lb/>that they can support STM-64 client signals as well as ODU2 <lb/>connections; <lb/>o one abstract TE Link, terminating on LTP AN1-3, abstracting the <lb/>physical access link between S6 and R4, reporting that it can <lb/>support STM-64 client signals but no ODU2 connections. <lb/>The information about the 10GE access link between S6 and R2 as well <lb/>as the fact that the access link between S3 and R1 can also be <lb/>configured as a 10GE link cannot be exposed by PNC1 within the MPI1 <lb/>OTN topology. <lb/>Therefore, PNC1 exports at MPI1, within the MPI1 ETH topology, two <lb/>abstract TE Links, terminating on LTP AN1-1 and AN1-8 respectively, <lb/>abstracting the physical access link between S3 and R1 and the <lb/>access link between S6 and R2 respectively, reporting that they can <lb/>support Ethernet client signal with port-based and VLAN-based <lb/>classifications. The PNC1 native topology would represent the <lb/>physical network topology of the domain controlled by the PNC, as <lb/>shown in Figure 5. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 28] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>.................................. <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>Physical Topology @ PNC1 <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>+----+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>|S1-1 <lb/>| <lb/>|S2-3: <lb/>: <lb/>| S1 |--------| S2 |-------(S31) <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>S2-1+----+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S1-2/ <lb/>|S2-2 : <lb/>: <lb/>S3-4/ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>+----+ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>|3 1| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R1)-------| S3 |---| S4 | <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>:S3-1+----+ <lb/>+----+ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S3-2 \ <lb/>\S4-2 <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\S5-1 <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>\S8-2| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| S5 | <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>\ |S8-1 : <lb/>(R2)--------2/ <lb/>\3 <lb/>\ | <lb/>: <lb/>:S6-1 \ /5 <lb/>\1 <lb/>\| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+----+ <lb/>+----+ <lb/>+----+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>|S8-5: <lb/>(R3)-------| S6 |---| S7 |---| S8 |-------(S32) <lb/>:S6-2+----+4 2+----+4 3+----+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>(R3)--------<lb/>S7-3 | <lb/>| S8-4 : <lb/>:S6-3 <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>:...............|........|.......: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>(S11) <lb/>(S12) <lb/>Figure 5 -Physical Topology controlled by PNC1 <lb/>The PNC1 native topology is not exposed and therefore it under PNC <lb/>responsibility to abstract the whole domain physical topology as a <lb/>single TE node and to maintain a mapping between the LTPs exposed at <lb/>MPI abstract topologies and the associated physical interfaces <lb/>controlled by the PNC: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 29] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Physical Interface <lb/>OTN Topology LTP <lb/>ETH Topology LTP <lb/>(Figure 5) <lb/>(Figure 3) <lb/>(Figure 4) <lb/>S2-3 <lb/>AN1-7 <lb/>S3-1 <lb/>AN1-1 <lb/>AN1-1 <lb/>S6-1 <lb/>AN1-8 <lb/>S6-2 <lb/>AN1-2 <lb/>S6-3 <lb/>AN1-3 <lb/>S7-3 <lb/>AN1-4 <lb/>S8-4 <lb/>AN1-5 <lb/>S8-5 <lb/>AN1-6 <lb/> Appendix B.1.1 provides the detailed JSON code example (&quot;mpi1-otn-<lb/>topology.json&quot;) describing how the MPI1 ODU Topology is reported by <lb/>the PNC1, using the [RFC8345], [TE-TOPO] and [OTN-TOPO] YANG models, <lb/>at MPI1. <lb/>It is worth noting that this JSON code example does not provide all <lb/>the attributes defined in the relevant YANG models, including: <lb/>o YANG attributes which are outside the scope of this document are <lb/>not shown; <lb/>o The attributes describing the set of label values that are <lb/>available at the inter-domain links (label-restriction container) <lb/>are also not shown to simplify the JSON code example; <lb/>o The comments describing the rationale for not including some <lb/>attributes in this JSON code example even if in the scope of this <lb/>document are identified with the prefix &quot;// __COMMENT&quot; and <lb/>included only in the first object instance (e.g., in the Access <lb/>Link from the AN1-1 description or in the AN1-1 LTP description). <lb/>5.1.2. Domain 2 Black Topology Abstraction <lb/>PNC2 provides the required black topology abstraction, as described <lb/>in section 4.2, to expose to the MDSC, at MPI2, two TE Topology <lb/>instances with only one TE node each: <lb/>o the first instance reports the domain 2 OTN abstract topology <lb/>view (MPI2 OTN Topology), with only one abstract node (i.e., AN2) <lb/>and only inter-domain and access abstract TE links (which <lb/>represent the inter-domain physical links and the access physical <lb/>links which can support ODU and/or transparent client layers); <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 30] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>o the instance reports the domain 2 Ethernet abstract topology view <lb/> (MPI2 ETH Topology), with only one abstract TE node (i.e., AN2) <lb/>and only access abstract TE links (which represent the access <lb/>physical links which can support Ethernet client layers). <lb/>5.1.3. Domain 3 White Topology Abstraction <lb/>PNC3 provides the required white topology abstraction, as described <lb/>in section 4.2, to expose to the MDSC, at MPI3, two TE Topology <lb/>instances with multiple TE nodes, one for each physical node: <lb/>o the first instance reports the domain 3 OTN topology view (MPI3 <lb/>OTN Topology), with four TE nodes, which represent the four <lb/>physical nodes (i.e. S31, S32, S33 and S34), and abstract TE <lb/>links, which represent the inter-domain and internal physical <lb/>links; <lb/>o the second instance reports the domain 3 Ethernet abstract <lb/>topology view (MPI3 ETH Topology), with only two TE nodes, which <lb/>represent the two edge physical nodes (i.e., S31 and S33) and <lb/>only the two access TE links which represent the access physical <lb/>links. <lb/>5.1.4. Multi-domain Topology Merging <lb/>As assumed at the beginning of this section, MDSC does not have any <lb/>knowledge of the topologies of each domain until each PNC reports <lb/>its own abstract topologies, so the MDSC needs to merge together <lb/>these abstract topologies, provided by different PNCs, to build its <lb/>own topology view of the multi-domain network (MDSC multi-domain <lb/>native topology), as described in section 4.3 of [TE-TOPO]. <lb/>Given the topologies reported from multiple PNCs, the MDSC need to <lb/>merge them into its multi-domain native topology. The topology of <lb/>each domain may be in an abstracted shape (refer to section 5.2 of <lb/>[RFC8453] for a different level of abstraction), while the inter-<lb/>domain link information must be complete and fully configured by the <lb/>MDSC. <lb/>The inter-domain link information is reported to the MDSC by the two <lb/>PNCs, controlling the two ends of the inter-domain link. <lb/>The MDSC needs to understand how to merge together these inter-<lb/>domain links. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 31] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>One possibility is to use the plug-id information, defined in [TE-<lb/> TOPO]: two inter-domain TE links, within two different MPI abstract <lb/>topologies, terminating on two LTPs reporting the same plug-id value <lb/>can be merged as a single intra-domain link, within any MDSC native <lb/>topology. <lb/>The value of the reported plug-id information can be either assigned <lb/>by a central network authority, and configured within the two PNC <lb/>domains. Alternatively, it may be discovered using an automatic <lb/>discovery mechanisms (e.g., LMP-based, as defined in [RFC6898]). <lb/>In case the plug-id values are assigned by a central authority, it <lb/>is under the central authority responsibility to assign unique <lb/>values. <lb/>In case the plug-id values are automatically discovered, the <lb/>information discovered by the automatic discovery mechanisms needs <lb/>to be encoded as a bit string within the plug-id value. This <lb/>encoding is implementation specific, but the encoding rules need to <lb/>be consistent across all the PNCs. <lb/>In case of co-existence within the same network of multiple sources <lb/>for the plug-id (e.g., central authority and automatic discovery or <lb/>even different automatic discovery mechanisms), it is needed that <lb/>the plug-id namespace is partitioned to avoid that different sources <lb/>assign the same plug-id value to different inter-domain links. Also, <lb/>the encoding of the plug-id namespace within the plug-id value is <lb/>implementation specific and will need to be consistent across all <lb/>the PNCs. <lb/>This document assumes that the plug-id is assigned by a central <lb/>authority, with the first octet set to 0x00 to represent the central <lb/>authority namespace. The configuration method used, within each PNC <lb/>domain, are outside the scope of this document. <lb/>Based on the plug-id values, the MDSC can merge together the <lb/>abstract topologies exposed by the underlying PNCs, as described in <lb/>sections 5.1.1, 5.1.2 and 5.1.3 above, into its multi-domain native <lb/>TE topology as shown in Figure 6. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 32] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>........................ <lb/> : <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>Network domain 1 <lb/>: <lb/>............. <lb/>: <lb/>Black Topology <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>Abstraction <lb/>: <lb/>: Network : <lb/>: AN1-1 <lb/>: <lb/>: domain 3 : <lb/>(R1)------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>: (White) : <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>+--------------+ <lb/>: <lb/>(R2)-----------+ + / <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\| / <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>(R3)-----------AN1 --+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>S31 -----(R5) <lb/>: <lb/>/|\ <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>\ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>(R4)-----------+ | \ <lb/>+---------S32 <lb/>S33 --(R6) <lb/>: <lb/>| \ <lb/>: <lb/>:/ \ <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>+---+ <lb/>: <lb/>/ <lb/>S34 <lb/>: <lb/>:..........|.......|...: /: <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>/ :../........: <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>/ <lb/>/ <lb/>...........|.......|.../..../.... <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>| / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: Network | <lb/>+ / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: domain 2 | <lb/>/ / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>/ / <lb/>/ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>+ / +--+ <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>|/ / <lb/>: <lb/>: Black <lb/>+---AN2 ---------------(R7) <lb/>: Topology <lb/>| | <lb/>AN2-1 <lb/>: <lb/>: Abstraction <lb/>| +----------------(R8) <lb/>: <lb/>| <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>+------------------(R9) <lb/>: <lb/>: <lb/>:...............................: <lb/>Figure 6 -Multi-domain Abstract Topology controlled by an MDSC <lb/>5.2. YANG Models for Service Configuration <lb/>The service configuration procedure is assumed to be initiated (step <lb/>1 in Figure 7) at the CMI from CNC to MDSC. Analysis of the CMI <lb/>models is (e.g., L1CSM, L2SM, VN) is outside the scope of this <lb/>document. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 33] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>As described in section 4.3, it is assumed that the CMI YANG models <lb/> provide all the information that allows the MDSC to understand that <lb/>it needs to coordinate the setup of a multi-domain ODU data plane <lb/>connection (which can be either an end-to-end connection or a <lb/>segment connection) and, when needed, also the configuration of the <lb/>adaptation functions in the edge nodes belonging to different <lb/>domains. <lb/>| <lb/>| {1} <lb/>V <lb/>----------------<lb/>| <lb/>{2} | <lb/>| {3} MDSC <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>----------------<lb/>^ <lb/>^ <lb/>^ <lb/>{3.1} | <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>+---------+ <lb/>|{3.2} | <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>+----------+ <lb/>| <lb/>V <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>----------<lb/>|{3.3} <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>PNC2 <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>----------<lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>^ <lb/>| <lb/>V <lb/>| {4.2} <lb/>| <lb/>----------<lb/>V <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>PNC1 <lb/>| <lb/>-----<lb/>V <lb/>----------<lb/>(Network) <lb/>----------<lb/>^ <lb/>( Domain 2) <lb/>| <lb/>PNC3 <lb/>| <lb/>| {4.1} <lb/>( <lb/>_) <lb/>----------<lb/>V <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>^ <lb/>-----<lb/>C==========D <lb/>| {4.3} <lb/>(Network) <lb/>/ ( <lb/>) \ <lb/>V <lb/>( Domain 1) / <lb/>-----<lb/>\ <lb/>-----<lb/>( <lb/>)/ <lb/>\ <lb/>(Network) <lb/>A===========B <lb/>\ ( Domain 3) <lb/>/ ( <lb/>) <lb/>\( <lb/>) <lb/>AP-1 <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>X===========Z <lb/>-----<lb/>( <lb/>) \ <lb/>( <lb/>) <lb/>AP-2 <lb/>-----<lb/>Figure 7 -Multi-domain Service Setup <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 34] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>As an example, the objective in this section is to configure a <lb/> transport service between R1 and R8, such as one of the services <lb/>described in section 4.3. The inter-domain path is assumed to be R1 <lb/>&lt;-&gt; S3 &lt;-&gt; S1 &lt;-&gt; S2 &lt;-&gt; S31 &lt;-&gt; S33 &lt;-&gt; S34 &lt;-&gt;S15 &lt;-&gt; S18 &lt;-&gt; R8 <lb/>(see the physical topology in Figure 1). <lb/>According to the different client signal types, different <lb/>adaptations can be required to be configured at the edge nodes <lb/>(i.e., S3 and S18). <lb/>After receiving such request, MDSC determines the domain sequence, <lb/>i.e., domain 1 &lt;-&gt; domain 3 &lt;-&gt; domain 2, with corresponding PNCs <lb/>and the inter-domain links (step 2 in Figure 7). <lb/>As described in [PATH-COMPUTE], the domain sequence can be <lb/>determined by running the MDSC own path computation on the MDSC <lb/>native topology, defined in section 5.1.4, if and only if the MDSC <lb/>has enough topology information. Otherwise, the MDSC can send path <lb/>computation requests to the different PNCs (steps 2.1, 2.2 and 2.3 <lb/>in Figure 7) and use this information to determine the optimal path <lb/>on its internal topology and therefore the domain sequence. <lb/>The MDSC will then decompose the tunnel request into a few tunnel <lb/>segments via tunnel models (both technology agnostic TE tunnel model <lb/>and OTN tunnel model), and request different PNCs to setup each <lb/>intra-domain tunnel segment (steps 3, 3.1, 3.2 and 3.3 in Figure 7). <lb/>The MDSC will take care of the configuration of both the intra-<lb/>domain tunnel segment and inter-domain tunnel via corresponding MPI <lb/>(via TE tunnel model and OTN tunnel model) through all the PNCs <lb/>controlling the domains selected during path computation. More <lb/>specifically, for the inter-domain tunnel hand-off, taking into <lb/>account that the inter-domain links are all OTN links, the list of <lb/>timeslots and the TPN value assigned to that ODUk connection at the <lb/>inter-domain link needs to be configured by the MDSC. <lb/>In any case, the access link configuration is done only on the PNCs <lb/>that control the access links (e.g., PNC-1 and PNC-3) and not on the <lb/>PNCs of transit domain(s) (e.g., PNC-2). An access link will be <lb/>configured by MDSC after the OTN tunnel is set up. <lb/>Access configuration will vary and will be dependent on each type of <lb/>service. Further discussion and examples are provided in the <lb/>following sub-sections. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 35] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>5.2.1. ODU Transit Service <lb/> In this scenario, described in section 4.3.1, the physical access <lb/>links are configured as 10G OTN links and, as described in section <lb/>5.1, reported by each PNC as TE Links within the OTN abstract <lb/>topologies they expose to the MDSC. <lb/>To setup this IP link, between R1 and R8, the CNC requests, at the <lb/>CMI, the MDSC to setup an ODU transit service. <lb/>From its native topology, shown in Figure 6, the MDSC understands, <lb/>by means which are outside the scope of this document, that R1 is <lb/>attached to the access link terminating on AN1-1 LTP in the MPI1 OTN <lb/>Abstract Topology (Figure 3), exposed by PNC1, and that R8 is <lb/>attached to the access link terminating on AN2-1 LTP in the MPI2 <lb/>Abstract Topology, exposed by PNC2. <lb/>MDSC then performs multi-domain path computation (step 2 in Figure <lb/>7) and requests PNC1, PNC2 and PNC3, at MPI1, MPI2 and MPI3 <lb/>respectively, to setup ODU2 (Transit Segment) Tunnels within the OTN <lb/>Abstract Topologies they expose (MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology, MPI2 <lb/>OTN Abstract Topology and MPI3 OTN Abstract Topology, respectively). <lb/>MDSC requests, at MPI1, PNC1 to setup an ODU2 (Transit Segment) <lb/>Tunnel with one primary path between AN-1 and AN1-7 LTPs, within the <lb/>MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology (Figure 4), using the TE Tunnel YANG <lb/>model, defined in [TE-TUNNEL], with the OTN technology-specific <lb/>augmentations, defined in [OTN-TUNNEL]: <lb/>o Source and Destination TTPs are not specified (since it is a <lb/>Transit Tunnel) <lb/>o Ingress and egress points are indicated in the route-object-<lb/>include-exclude list of the explicit-route-objects of the primary <lb/>path: <lb/>o The first element references the access link terminating on <lb/>AN1-1 LTP <lb/>o The last two element reference respectively the inter-domain <lb/>link terminating on AN1-7 LTP and the data plane resources <lb/>(i.e., the list of timeslots and the TPN) used by the ODU2 <lb/>connection over that link. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 36] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>The configuration of the timeslots used by the ODU2 connection on <lb/> the internal links within a PNC domain (i.e., on the internal links <lb/>within domain1) is outside the scope of this document since it is a <lb/>matter of the PNC domain internal implementation. <lb/>However, the configuration of the timeslots used by the ODU2 <lb/>connection at the transport network domain boundaries (e.g., on the <lb/>inter-domain links) needs to take into account the timeslots <lb/>available on physical nodes belonging to different PNC domains <lb/>(e.g., on node S2 within PNC1 domain and on node S31 within PNC3 <lb/>domain). <lb/>The MDSC, when coordinating the setup of a multi-domain ODU <lb/>connection, also configures the data plane resources (i.e., the list <lb/>of timeslots and the TPN) to be used on the inter-domain links. The <lb/>MDSC can know the timeslots which are available on the physical OTN <lb/>nodes terminating the inter-domain links (e.g., S2 and S31) from the <lb/>OTN Topology information exposed, at the MPIs, by the PNCs <lb/>controlling the OTN physical nodes (e.g., PNC1 and PNC3 controlling <lb/>the physical nodes S2 and S31 respectively). <lb/>Appendix B.2.1 provides the detailed JSON code (&quot;mpi1-odu2-service-<lb/>config.json&quot;) describing how the setup of this ODU2 (Transit <lb/>Segment) Tunnel can be requested by the MDSC, using the [TE-TUNNEL] <lb/>and [OTN-TUNNEL] YANG models at MPI1. <lb/>PNC1 knows, as described in the mapping table in Section 5.1.1, that <lb/>AN-1 and AN1-7 LTPs within the MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology it exposes <lb/>at MPI1 correspond to the S3-1 and S2-3 LTPs, respectively, within <lb/>its native topology. Therefore it performs path computation, for an <lb/>ODU2 connection between these LTPs within its native topology, and <lb/>sets up the ODU2 cross-connections within the physical nodes S3, S1 <lb/>and S2, as shown in section 4.3.1. <lb/>Since the R1-S3 access link is a multi-function access link, PNC1 <lb/>also configures the OTU2 trail before setting up the ODU2 <lb/>cross-connection in node S3. <lb/>As part of the OUD2 cross-connection configuration in node S2, PNC1 <lb/>configures the data plane resources (i.e., the list of timeslots and <lb/>the TPN), to be used by this ODU2 connection on the S2-S31 <lb/>inter-domain link, as requested by the MDSC. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 37] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Following similar requests from MDSC to setup ODU2 (Transit Segment) <lb/> Tunnels within the OTN Abstract Topologies they expose, PNC2 then <lb/>sets up ODU2 cross-connections on nodes S31 and S33 while PNC3 sets <lb/>up ODU2 cross-connections on nodes S15 and S18, as shown in section <lb/>4.3.1. PNC2 also configures the OTU2 trail on the S18-R8 <lb/>multi-function access link. <lb/>5.2.1.1. Single Domain Example <lb/>To setup an ODU2 end-to-end connection, supporting an IP link, <lb/>between R1 and R3, the CNC requests, at the CMI, the MDSC to setup <lb/>an ODU transit service. <lb/>Following the procedures described in section 5.2.1, MDSC requests <lb/>only PCN1 to setup the ODU2 (Transit Segment) Tunnel between the <lb/>access links terminating on AN-1 and AN1-2 LTPs within the MPI1 <lb/>Abstract Topology and PNC1 sets up ODU2 cross-connections on nodes <lb/>S3, S5 and S6, as shown in section 4.3.1. PNC1 also configures the <lb/>OTU2 trails on the R1-S3 and R3-S6 multi-function access links. <lb/>5.2.2. EPL over ODU Service <lb/>In this scenario, described in section 4.3.2, the access links are <lb/>configured as 10GE Links and, as described in section 5.1, reported <lb/>by each PNC as TE Links within the ETH abstract topologies they <lb/>expose to the MDSC. <lb/>To setup this IP link, between R1 and R8, the CNC requests, at the <lb/>CMI, the MDSC to setup an EPL service. <lb/>From its native topology, shown in Figure 6, the MDSC understands, <lb/>by means which are outside the scope of this document, that R1 is <lb/>attached to the access link terminating on AN1-1 LTP in the MPI1 ETH <lb/>Abstract Topology, exposed by PNC1, and that R8 is attached to the <lb/>access link terminating on AN2-1 LTP in the MPI2 ETH Abstract <lb/>Topology, exposed by PNC2. <lb/>The MDSC also understands that it needs to coordinate the setup of a <lb/>multi-domain ODU2 Tunnel between the TTPs, abstracting nodes S3 and <lb/>S18 within the OTN Abstract Topologies exposed by PNC1 and PNC2, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>MDSC then performs multi-domain path computation (step 2 in Figure <lb/>7) and then requests: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 38] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>o PNC1, at MPI1, to setup an ODU2 (Head Segment) Tunnel within the <lb/> MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/>o PNC1, at MPI1, to steer the Ethernet client traffic from/to AN1-1 <lb/>LTP, within the MPI1 ETH Abstract Topology, thought that ODU2 <lb/>(Head Segment) Tunnel; <lb/>o PNC3, at MPI3, to setup an ODU2 (Transit Segment) Tunnel within <lb/>the MPI3 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/>o PNC2, at MPI2, to setup ODU2 (Tail Segment) Tunnel within the <lb/>MPI2 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/>o PNC2, at MPI2, to steer the Ethernet client traffic to/from AN2-1 <lb/>LTP, within the MPI2 ETH Abstract Topology, through that ODU2 <lb/>(Tail Segment) Tunnel. <lb/>MDSC requests, at MPI1, PNC1 to setup an ODU2 (Head Segment) Tunnel <lb/>with one primary path between the source TTP and AN1-7 LTP, within <lb/>the MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology (Figure 4), using the TE Tunnel YANG <lb/>model, defined in [TE-TUNNEL], with the OTN technology-specific <lb/>augmentations, defined in [OTN-TUNNEL]: <lb/>o Only the Source TTP is specified (since it is a Head Segment <lb/>Tunnel): therefore the Destination TTP is not specified <lb/>o The egress point in indicated in the route-object-include-exclude <lb/>list of the explicit-route-objects of the primary path: <lb/>o The last two element reference respectively the inter-domain <lb/>link terminating on AN1-7 LTP and the data plane resources <lb/>(i.e., the list of timeslots and the TPN) used by the ODU2 <lb/>connection over that link. <lb/>Appendix B.2.2 provides the detailed JSON code (&quot;mpi1-odu2-tunnel-<lb/>config.json&quot;) describing how the setup of this ODU2 (Head Segment) <lb/>Tunnel can be requested by the MDSC, using the [TE-TUNNEL] and [OTN-<lb/>TUNNEL] YANG models at MPI1. <lb/>MDSC requests, at MPI1, PNC1 to steer the Ethernet client traffic <lb/>from/to AN1-2 LTP, within the MPI1 ETH Abstract Topology (Figure 4), <lb/>thought the MPI1 ODU2 (Head Segment) Tunnel, using the Ethernet <lb/>Client YANG model, defined in [CLIENT-SIGNAL]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 39] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>Appendix B.2.3 provides the detailed JSON code (&quot;mpi1-epl-service-<lb/>config.json&quot;) describing how the setup of this EPL service using the <lb/>ODU2 Tunnel can be requested by the MDSC, using the [CLIENT-SIGNAL] <lb/>YANG model at MPI1. <lb/>PNC1 knows, as described in the table in section 5.1.1, that the <lb/>tunnel source TTP and AN1-7 LTP, within the MPI1 OTN Abstract <lb/>Topology it exposes at MPI1, correspond to node S3 and S2-3 LTP, <lb/>respectively, within its native topology. Therefore it performs path <lb/>computation, for an ODU2 connection between node S3 and S2-3 LTP <lb/>within its native topology, and sets up the ODU2 cross-connections <lb/>within the physical nodes S3, S1 and S2, as shown in section 4.3.2. <lb/>As part of the OUD2 cross-connection configuration in node S2, PNC1 <lb/>configures the data plane resources (i.e., the list of timeslots and <lb/>the TPN), to be used by this ODU2 connection on the S2-S31 <lb/>inter-domain link, as requested by the MDSC. <lb/>After the configuration of the ODU2 cross-connection in node S3, <lb/>PNC1 also configures the [ETH -&gt; (ODU)] and [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH] <lb/>adaptation functions, within node S3, as shown in section 4.3.2. <lb/>Since the R1-S3 access link is a multi-function access link, PNC1 <lb/>also configures the 10GE link before this step. <lb/>Following similar requests from MDSC to setup ODU2 (Segment) Tunnels <lb/>within the OTN Abstract Topologies they expose as well as the <lb/>steering of the Ethernet client traffic, PNC3 then sets up ODU2 <lb/>cross-connections on nodes S31 and S33 while PNC2 sets up ODU2 <lb/>cross-connections on nodes S15 and S18 as well as the [ETH -&gt; <lb/>(ODU2)] and [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH] adaptation functions in node S18, as <lb/>shown in section 4.3.2. PNC2 also configures the 10GE link on the <lb/>S18-R8 multi-function access link. <lb/>5.2.2.1. Single Domain Example <lb/>To setup this IP link, between R1 and R2, the CNC requests, at the <lb/>CMI, the MDSC to setup an EPL service. <lb/>Following the procedures described in section 5.2.2, the MDSC <lb/>requests PCN1 to: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 40] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>o setup an ODU2 (end-to-end) Tunnel between the TTPs, abstracting <lb/> nodes S3 and S6 within MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology exposed by PNC1 <lb/>at MPI1; <lb/>o steer the Ethernet client traffic between the AN1-1 and AN1-8 <lb/>LTPs, exposed by PNC1 within MPI1 ETH Abstract Topology, through <lb/>that ODU2 (end-to-end) Tunnel. <lb/>Then PNC1 sets up ODU2 cross-connections on nodes S3, S5 and S6 as <lb/>well as the [ETH -&gt; (ODU)] and [(ODU2) -&gt; ETH] adaptation functions <lb/>in nodes S3 and S6, as shown in section 4.3.2. PNC1 also configures <lb/>the 10GE link on the R1-S3 multi-function access link (the R2-S6 <lb/>access link has been pre-configured as a 10GE link). <lb/>5.2.3. Other OTN Client Services <lb/>In this scenario, described in section 4.3.3, the access links are <lb/>configured as STM-64 links and, as described in section 5.1, <lb/>reported by each PNC as TE Links within the OTN Abstract Topologies <lb/>they expose to the MDSC. <lb/>The CNC requests, at the CMI, MDSC to setup an STM-64 Private Line <lb/>service between R1 and R8. <lb/>Following similar procedures as described in section 5.2.2, MDSC <lb/>understands that: <lb/>o R1 is attached to the access link terminating on AN1-1 LTP in the <lb/>MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology, exposed by PNC1, and that R8 is <lb/>attached to the access link terminating on AN2-1 LTP in the MPI2 <lb/>OTN Abstract Topology, exposed by PNC2; <lb/>o it needs to coordinate the setup of a multi-domain ODU2 Tunnel <lb/>between the TTPs, abstracting nodes S3 and S18 within the OTN <lb/>Abstract Topologies exposed by PNC1 and PNC2, respectively. <lb/>The MDSC then performs multi-domain path computation (step 2 in <lb/>Figure 7) and then requests: <lb/>o PNC1, at MPI1, to setup an ODU2 (Head Segment) Tunnel within the <lb/>MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 41] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>o PNC1, at MPI1, to steer the STM-64 transparent client traffic <lb/> from/to AN1-1 LTP, within the MPI1 OTN Abstract Topology, thought <lb/>that ODU2 (Head Segment) Tunnel; <lb/>o PNC3, at MPI3, to setup an ODU2 (Transit Segment) Tunnel within <lb/>the MPI3 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/>o PNC2, at MPI2, to setup ODU2 (Tail Segment) Tunnel within the <lb/>MPI2 OTN Abstract Topology; <lb/>o PNC2, at MPI2, to steer the STM-64 transparent client traffic <lb/>to/from AN2-1 LTP, within the MPI2 ETH Abstract Topology, through <lb/>that ODU2 (Tail Segment) Tunnel. <lb/>PNC1, PNC2 and PNC3 then sets up the ODU2 cross-connections within <lb/>the physical nodes S3, S1, S2, S31, S33, S15 and S18 as well as the <lb/>[STM-64 -&gt; (ODU)] and [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64] adaptation functions in <lb/>nodes S3 and S18, as shown in section 4.3.3. PNC1 and PNC2 also <lb/>configure the STM-64 links on the R1-S3 and R8-S18 multi-function <lb/>access links, respectively. <lb/>5.2.3.1. Single Domain Example <lb/>To setup this IP link, between R1 and R3, the CNC requests, at the <lb/>CMI, the MDSC to setup an STM-64 Private Line service. <lb/>The MDSC and PNC1 follows similar procedures as described in section <lb/>5.2.2.1 to set up ODU2 cross-connections on nodes S3, S5 and S6 as <lb/>well as the [STM-64 -&gt; (ODU)] and [(ODU2) -&gt; STM-64] adaptation <lb/>functions in nodes S3 and S6, as shown in section 4.3.3. PNC1 also <lb/>configures the STM-64 links on the R1-S3 and R3-S6 multi-function <lb/>access links. <lb/>5.2.4. EVPL over ODU Service <lb/>In this scenario, described in section 4.3.4, the access links are <lb/>configured as 10GE links, as described in section 5.2.2 above. <lb/>The CNC requests, at the CMI, the MDSC to setup two EVPL services: <lb/>one between R1 and R2, and another between R1 and R8. <lb/>Following similar procedures as described in section 5.2.2 and <lb/>5.2.2.1, MDSC understands that: <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 42] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>o R1 and R2 are attached to the access links terminating <lb/> respectively on AN1-1 and AN1-8 LTPs in the MPI1 ETH Abstract <lb/>Topology, exposed by PNC1, and that R8 is attached to the access <lb/>link terminating on AN2-1 LTP in the MPI2 ETH Abstract Topology, <lb/>exposed by PNC2; <lb/>o to setup the first (single-domain) EVPL service, between R1 and <lb/>R2, it needs to coordinate the setup of a single-domain ODU0 <lb/>Tunnel between the TTPs, abstracting nodes S3 and S6 within the <lb/>OTN Abstract Topology exposed by PNC1; <lb/>o to setup the second (multi-domain) EPVL service, between R1 and <lb/>R8, it needs to coordinate the setup of a multi-domain ODU0 <lb/>Tunnel between the TTPs, abstracting nodes S3 and S18 within the <lb/>OTN Abstract Topologies exposed by PNC1 and PNC2, respectively. <lb/>To setup the first (single-domain) EVPL service between R1 and R2, <lb/>the MDSC and PNC1 follows similar procedures as described in section <lb/>5.2.2.1 to set up ODU0 cross-connections on nodes S3, S5 and S6 as <lb/>well as the [VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)] and [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN] adaptation <lb/>functions, in nodes S3 and S6, as shown in section 4.3.4. PNC1 also <lb/>configures the 10GE link on the R1-S3 multi-function access link. <lb/>As part of the [VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)] and [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN] adaptation <lb/>functions configurations in nodes S2 and S6, PNC1 configures also <lb/>the classification rules required to associated only the Ethernet <lb/>client traffic received with VLAN ID 10 on the R1-S3 and R2-S6 <lb/>access links with this EVPL service. The MDSC provides this <lb/>information to PNC1 using the [CLIENT-SIGNAL] model. <lb/>To setup the second (multi-domain) EVPL service between R1 and R8, <lb/>the MDSC, PNC1, PNC2 and PNC3 follows similar procedures as <lb/>described in section 5.2.2 to setup the ODU0 cross-connections <lb/>within the physical nodes S3, S1, S2, S31, S33, S15 and S18 as well <lb/>as the [VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)] and [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN] adaptation functions in <lb/>nodes S3 and S18, as shown in section 4.3.4. PNC2 also configures <lb/>the 10GE link on the R8-S18 multi-function access link (the R1-S3 <lb/>10GE link has been already configured when the first EVPL service <lb/>has been setup). <lb/>As part of the [VLAN -&gt; (ODU0)] and [(ODU0) -&gt; VLAN] adaptation <lb/>functions configurations in nodes S3 and S18, PNC1 and, <lb/>respectively, PNC2 configure also the classification rules required <lb/>to associated only the Ethernet client traffic received with VLAN ID <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 43] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>20 on the R1-S3 and R8-S18 access links with this EVPL service. The <lb/>MDSC provides this information to PNC1 and PNC2 using the <lb/>[CLIENT-SIGNAL] model. <lb/>5.3. YANG Models for Protection Configuration <lb/>5.3.1. Linear Protection (end-to-end) <lb/>To be discussed in future versions of this document. <lb/>5.4. Notifications <lb/>Further detailed analysis is outside the scope of this document <lb/>5.5. Path Computation with Constraints <lb/>The path computation constraints that can be supported at the MPI <lb/>using the IETF YANG models defined in [TE-TUNNEL] and [PATH-<lb/>COMPUTE]. <lb/>When there is a technology specific network (e.g., OTN), the <lb/>corresponding technology (e.g., OTN) model should also be used to <lb/>specify the tunnel information on MPI, with the constraint included <lb/>in TE Tunnel model. <lb/>Further detailed analysis is outside the scope of this document <lb/>6. Security Considerations <lb/>This document analyses the applicability of the YANG models being <lb/>defined by the IETF to support OTN single and multi-domain <lb/>scenarios. <lb/>Inherently OTN networks ensure privacy and security via hard <lb/>partitioning of traffic onto dedicated circuits. The separation of <lb/>network traffic makes it difficult to intercept data transferred <lb/>between nodes over OTN-channelized links. <lb/>In OTN the (General Communication Channel) GCC is used for OAM <lb/>functions such as performance monitoring, fault detection, and <lb/>signaling. The GCC control channel should be secured using a <lb/>suitable mechanism. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 44] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>There are no additional or new security considerations introduced by <lb/> this document. <lb/>7. IANA Considerations <lb/>This document requires no IANA actions. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8. References <lb/>8.1. Normative References <lb/>[RFC4427] Mannie, E., Papadimitriou, D., &quot;Recovery (Protection and <lb/>Restoration) Terminology for Generalized Multi-Protocol <lb/>Label Switching (GMPLS)&quot;, RFC 4427, March 2006. <lb/>[RFC4655] Farrel, A. et al., &quot;A Path Computation Element (PCE)-Based <lb/>Architecture&quot;, RFC4655, August 2006. <lb/>[RFC7926] Farrel, A. et al., &quot;Problem Statement and Architecture for <lb/>Information Exchange between Interconnected Traffic-<lb/>Engineered Networks&quot;, BCP 206, RFC 7926, July 2016. <lb/>[RFC8345] Clemm, A.,Medved, J. et al., &quot;A Yang Data Model for <lb/>Network Topologies&quot;, RFC8345, March 2018. <lb/>[RFC8453] Ceccarelli, D., Lee, Y. et al., &quot;Framework for Abstraction <lb/>and Control of TE Networks (ACTN)&quot;, RFC8453, August 2018. <lb/>[ITU-T G.709] ITU-T Recommendation G.709 (06/16), &quot;Interfaces for <lb/>the optical transport network&quot;, June 2016. <lb/>[ITU-T G.808.1] ITU-T Recommendation G.808.1 (05/14), &quot;Generic <lb/>protection switching -Linear trail and subnetwork <lb/>protection&quot;, May 2014. <lb/>[ITU-T G.873.1] ITU-T Recommendation G.873.1 (05/14), &quot;Optical <lb/>transport network (OTN): Linear protection&quot;, May 2014. <lb/>[TE-TOPO] Liu, X. et al., &quot;YANG Data Model for TE Topologies&quot;, <lb/>draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-topo, work in progress. <lb/>[OTN-TOPO] Zheng, H. et al., &quot;A YANG Data Model for Optical <lb/>Transport Network Topology&quot;, draft-ietf-ccamp-otn-topo-<lb/>yang, work in progress. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 45] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[CLIENT-TOPO] Zheng, H. et al., &quot;A YANG Data Model for Client-layer <lb/> Topology&quot;, draft-zheng-ccamp-client-topo-yang, work in <lb/>progress. <lb/>[TE-TUNNEL] Saad, T. et al., &quot;A YANG Data Model for Traffic <lb/>Engineering Tunnels and Interfaces&quot;, draft-ietf-teas-yang-<lb/>te, work in progress. <lb/>[PATH-COMPUTE] Busi, I., Belotti, S. et al, &quot;Yang model for <lb/>requesting Path Computation&quot;, draft-ietf-teas-yang-path-<lb/>computation, work in progress. <lb/>[OTN-TUNNEL] <lb/>Zheng, H. et al., &quot;OTN Tunnel YANG Model&quot;, draft-<lb/>ietf-ccamp-otn-tunnel-model, work in progress. <lb/>[CLIENT-SIGNAL] <lb/>Zheng, H. et al., &quot;A YANG Data Model for Optical <lb/>Transport Network Client Signals&quot;, draft-zheng-ccamp-otn-<lb/>client-signal-yang, work in progress. <lb/>8.2. Informative References <lb/>[RFC5151] Farrel, A. et al., &quot;Inter-Domain MPLS and GMPLS Traffic <lb/>Engineering --Resource Reservation Protocol-Traffic <lb/>Engineering (RSVP-TE) Extensions&quot;, RFC 5151, February <lb/>2008. <lb/>[RFC6898] Li, D. et al., &quot;Link Management Protocol Behavior <lb/>Negotiation and Configuration Modifications&quot;, RFC 6898, <lb/>March 2013. <lb/>[RFC8040] Bierman, A. et al., &quot;RESTCONF Protocol&quot;, RFC 8040, January <lb/>2017. <lb/>[RFC8309] Wu, Q. et al., &quot;Service Models Explained&quot;, RFC 8309, <lb/>January 2018. <lb/>[ACTN-YANG] Zhang, X. et al., &quot;Applicability of YANG models for <lb/>Abstraction and Control of Traffic Engineered Networks&quot;, <lb/>draft-zhang-teas-actn-yang, work in progress. <lb/>[RFC-FOLD] Watsen, K. et al., &quot;Handling Long Lines in Artwork in <lb/>Internet-Drafts and RFCs&quot;, draft-ietf-netmod-artwork-<lb/>folding, work in progress <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 46] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>[TE-TUTORIAL] Bryskin, I. et al., &quot;TE Topology and Tunnel Modeling <lb/> for Transport Networks&quot;, draft-ietf-teas-te-topo-and-<lb/>tunnel-modeling, work in progress <lb/>[ONF TR-527] ONF Technical Recommendation TR-527, &quot;Functional <lb/>Requirements for Transport API&quot;, June 2016. <lb/>[ONF GitHub] ONF Open Transport (SNOWMASS), <lb/>&lt;https://github.com/OpenNetworkingFoundation/Snowmass-<lb/>ONFOpenTransport&gt; <lb/>[MEF 55] Metro Ethernet Forum, &quot;Lifecycle Service Orchestration <lb/>(LSO): Reference Architecture and Framework&quot;, Technical <lb/>Specification MEF 55, March 2016, <lb/>&lt;https://www.mef.net/Assets/Technical_Specifications/PDF/M <lb/>EF_55.pdf&gt; <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">9. Acknowledgments <lb/>The authors would like to thank all members of the Transport NBI <lb/>Design Team involved in the definition of use cases, gap analysis <lb/>and guidelines for using the IETF YANG models at the Northbound <lb/>Interface (NBI) of a Transport SDN Controller. <lb/>The authors would like to thank Xian Zhang, Anurag Sharma, Sergio <lb/>Belotti, Tara Cummings, Michael Scharf, Karthik Sethuraman, Oscar <lb/>Gonzalez de Dios, Hans Bjursrom and Italo Busi for having initiated <lb/>the work on gap analysis for transport NBI and having provided <lb/>foundations work for the development of this document. <lb/>The authors would like to thank the authors of the TE Topology and <lb/>Tunnel YANG models [TE-TOPO] and [TE-TUNNEL], in particular, Igor <lb/>Bryskin, Vishnu Pavan Beeram, Tarek Saad and Xufeng Liu, for their <lb/>support in addressing any gap identified during the analysis work. <lb/>The authors would like to thank Henry Yu and Aihua Guo for their <lb/>input and review of the URIs structures used within the JSON code <lb/>examples. <lb/>This work was supported in part by the European Commission funded <lb/>H2020-ICT-2016-2 METRO-HAUL project (G.A. 761727). <lb/>This document was prepared using 2-Word-v2.0.template.dot. <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 47] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 48] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A. Validating a JSON fragment against a YANG Model <lb/> The objective is to have a tool that allows validating whether a <lb/>piece of JSON code embedded in an Internet-Draft is compliant with a <lb/>YANG model without using a client/server. <lb/>A.1. Manipulation of JSON fragments <lb/>This section describes the various ways JSON fragments are used in <lb/>the I-D processing and how to manage them. <lb/>Let&apos;s call &quot;folded-JSON&quot; the JSON embedded in the I-D: it fits the <lb/>72 chars width and it is acceptable for it to be invalid JSON. <lb/>We then define &quot;unfolded-JSON&quot; a valid JSON fragment having the same <lb/>contents of the &quot;folded-JSON &quot; without folding, i.e. limits on the <lb/>text width. The folding/unfolding operation may be done according to <lb/>[RFC-FOLD]. The &quot;unfolded-JSON&quot; can be edited by the authors using <lb/>JSON editors with the advantages of syntax validation and pretty-<lb/>printing. <lb/>Both the &quot;folded&quot; and the &quot;unfolded&quot; JSON fragments can include <lb/>comments having descriptive fields and directives we&apos;ll describe <lb/>later to facilitate the reader and enable some automatic processing. <lb/>The presence of comments in the &quot;unfolded-JSON&quot; fragment makes it an <lb/>invalid JSON encoding of YANG data. Therefore we call &quot;naked JSON&quot; <lb/>the JSON where the comments have been stripped out: not only it is <lb/>valid JSON but it is a valid JSON encoding of YANG data. <lb/>The following schema resumes these definitions: <lb/>unfold_it --&gt; <lb/>stripper --&gt; <lb/>Folded-JSON <lb/>Unfolded-JSON <lb/>Naked JSON <lb/>&lt;--fold_it <lb/>&lt;--author edits <lb/>&lt;=72-chars? <lb/>MUST <lb/>MAY <lb/>MAY <lb/>valid JSON? <lb/>MAY <lb/>MUST <lb/>MUST <lb/>JSON-encoding <lb/>MAY <lb/>MAY <lb/>MUST <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 49] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">of YANG data <lb/>Our validation toolchain has been designed to take a JSON in any of <lb/>the three formats and validate it automatically against a set of <lb/>relevant YANG modules using available open-source tools. It can be <lb/>found at: https://github.com/GianmarcoBruno/json-yang/ <lb/>A.2. Comments in JSON fragments <lb/>We found useful to introduce two kinds of comments, both defined as <lb/>key-value pairs where the key starts with &quot;//&quot;: <lb/>-free-form descriptive comments, e.g.&quot;// COMMENT&quot; : &quot;refine this&quot; <lb/>to describe properties of JSON fragments. <lb/>-machine-usable directives e.g. &quot;// __REFERENCES__DRAFTS__&quot; : { <lb/>&quot;ietf-routing-types@2017-12-04&quot;: &quot;rfc8294&quot;,} which can be used to <lb/>automatically download from the network the relevant I-Ds or RFCs <lb/>and extract from them the YANG models of interest. This is <lb/>particularly useful to keep consistency when the drafting work is <lb/>rapidly evolving. <lb/>A.3. Validation of JSON fragments: DSDL-based approach <lb/>The idea is to generate a JSON driver file (JTOX) from YANG, then <lb/>use it to translate JSON to XML and validate it against the DSDL <lb/>schemas, as shown in Figure 8. <lb/>Useful link: https://github.com/mbj4668/pyang/wiki/XmlJson <lb/>(2) <lb/>YANG-module ---&gt; DSDL-schemas (RNG,SCH,DSRL) <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| (1) <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>Config/state JTOX-file <lb/>| (4) <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>| <lb/>| <lb/>\ <lb/>V <lb/>V <lb/>JSON-file------------&gt; XML-file ----------------&gt; Output <lb/>(3) <lb/>Figure 8 -DSDL-based approach for JSON code validation <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 50] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">In order to allow the use of comments following the convention <lb/> defined in section 3, without impacting the validation process, <lb/>these comments will be automatically removed from the JSON-file that <lb/>will be validate. <lb/>A.4. Validation of JSON fragments: why not using a XSD-based approach <lb/>This approach has been analyzed and discarded because no longer <lb/>supported by pyang. <lb/>The idea is to convert YANG to XSD, JSON to XML and validate it <lb/>against the XSD, as shown in Figure 9: <lb/>(1) <lb/>YANG-module ---&gt; XSD-schema -\ <lb/>(3) <lb/>+--&gt; Validation <lb/>JSON-file------&gt; XML-file ----/ <lb/>(2) <lb/>Figure 9 -XSD-based approach for JSON code validation <lb/>The pyang support for the XSD output format was deprecated in 1.5 <lb/>and removed in 1.7.1. However pyang 1.7.1 is necessary to work with <lb/>YANG 1.1 so the process shown in Figure 9 will stop just at step <lb/>(1). <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 51] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">Appendix B. Detailed JSON Examples <lb/> The JSON code examples provided in this appendix have been validated <lb/>using the tools in Appendix A and folded using the tool in [RFC-<lb/>FOLD]. <lb/>B.1. JSON Examples for Topology Abstractions <lb/>B.1.1. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-otn-topology.json <lb/>This is the JSON code reporting the OTN Topology @ MPI: <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 52] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">========== NOTE: &apos;\\&apos; line wrapping per BCP XX (RFC XXXX) =========== <lb/> { <lb/>&quot;// __TITLE__&quot;: &quot;ODU Black Topology @ MPI1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __LAST_UPDATE__&quot;: &quot;October 18, 2018&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __MISSING_ATTRIBUTES__&quot;: true, <lb/>&quot;// __REFERENCE_DRAFTS__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-routing-types@2017-12-04&quot;: &quot;rfc8294&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-types@2017-10-30&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-ccamp-otn-tunnel-model-\ <lb/>\01&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network@2018-02-26&quot;: &quot;rfc8345&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network-topology@2018-02-26&quot;: &quot;rfc8345&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-types@2018-06-12&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-15&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology@2018-06-15&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-topo-18&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-topology@2017-10-30&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-ccamp-otn-topo-yang-\ <lb/>\02&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __RESTCONF_OPERATION__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;operation&quot;: &quot;GET&quot;, <lb/>&quot;url&quot;: &quot;http://{{PNC1-ADDR}}/restconf/data/ietf-network:networks&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network:networks&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;network&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;network-id&quot;: &quot;providerId/201/clientId/300/topologyId/otn-bl\ <lb/>\ack-topology&quot;, <lb/>&quot;network-types&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-topology&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-topology:otn-topology&quot;: {} <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:provider-id&quot;: 201, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:client-id&quot;: 300, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-topology-id&quot;: &quot;otn-black-topology&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: &quot;presence container requires: prov\ <lb/>\ider, client and te-topology-id&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;OTN Black Topology @ MPI1&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// ietf-network:node&quot;: &quot;Access LTPs to be reviewed in a fut\ <lb/>\ure update&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network:node&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __NODE__:__DESCRIPTION__&quot;: { <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 53] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;identifier&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;Abstract Node&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node(s)&quot;: &quot;whole network domain 1&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;node-id&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-node-id&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-node-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN11&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay-topology&quot;: &quot;To be discussed\ <lb/>\ with TE Topology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ tunnel-termination-point&quot;: [] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network-topology:termination-point&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-1 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S3&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;tributary port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;R1&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-1 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/1)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Access Lin\ <lb/>\k&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __COMMENT__ inter-layer-lock-id&quot;: &quot;Empty: OTN \ <lb/>\Links are pre-configured&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;List of ODU clients?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 54] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">\true <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-2 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;S31&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 2, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-2 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/2)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Inter-doma\ <lb/>\in Link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;Empty? (inter-domain OTN link)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DEFAULT__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\false <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-3 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;tributary port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;R2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;3&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 3, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-3 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/3)&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 55] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Access Lin\ <lb/>\k&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;List of ODU clients?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\true <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-4 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S8&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;S32&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 4, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-4 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/4)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Inter-doma\ <lb/>\in Link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;Empty? (inter-domain OTN link)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DEFAULT__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\false <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-5 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S8&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 5, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;S12&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;5&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 56] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 5, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-5 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/5)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Inter-doma\ <lb/>\in Link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;Empty? (inter-domain OTN link)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DEFAULT__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\false <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-6 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S7&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 4, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;S11&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 6, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-6 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/6)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Inter-doma\ <lb/>\in Link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;Empty? (inter-domain OTN link)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DEFAULT__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\false <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LTP__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-7 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link type(s)&quot;: &quot;OTU-2&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 57] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;physical node&quot;: &quot;S6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;unnumberd/ifIndex&quot;: 2, <lb/>&quot;port type&quot;: &quot;tributary port&quot;, <lb/>&quot;connected to&quot;: &quot;R3&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;tp-id&quot;: &quot;7&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te-tp-id&quot;: 7, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;AN1-7 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ interface-switching-capability&quot;: &quot;\ <lb/>\See Link attributes (teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/7)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ inter-domain-plug-id&quot;: &quot;Access Lin\ <lb/>\k&quot;, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:supported-payloa\ <lb/>\d-types&quot;: &quot;List of ODU clients?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ ietf-otn-topology:client-facing&quot;: \ <lb/>\true <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// ietf-network-topology:link&quot;: &quot;Access links to be reviewe\ <lb/>\d in a future update&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-network-topology:link&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;access link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S3-1 to R1&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __COMMENT__ external-domain&quot;: &quot;Empty: the plug-i\ <lb/>\d is used instead of this container&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 58] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __COMMENT__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;Not described \ <lb/>\in this JSON example&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 1 <lb/>}, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 59] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;access link&quot; <lb/> }, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S2-1 to S31&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-2&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU4&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 60] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/> { <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 2 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-3&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;access link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S6-1 to R2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/3&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-3&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 61] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/> &quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 3 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;access link&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S8-1 to S32&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 62] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/> &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-4&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU4&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 63] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/> \opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 4 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-5&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S8-5 to S12&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/5&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-5&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU4&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 64] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/> &quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 5 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S7-4 to S11&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1/teLinkId/6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Inter-domain Link from AN1-6&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 65] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/> { <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU4&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU4, ...&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 6 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;inter-domain link&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 66] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __DESCRIPTION__:__LINK__&quot;: { <lb/> &quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-7&quot;, <lb/>&quot;type&quot;: &quot;access link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;physical link&quot;: &quot;Link from S6-2 to R3&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;link-id&quot;: &quot;teNodeId/10.0.0.1teLinkId/7&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-topology:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-link-attributes&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;Access Link from AN1-7&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ access-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assume point-t\ <lb/>\o-point as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;access-type&quot;: &quot;point-to-point&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ is-abstract&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with \ <lb/>\TE Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay&quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE \ <lb/>\Topology authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;admin-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;interface-switching-capability&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;switching-capability&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching\ <lb/>\-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-lsp-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;ODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ label-restrictions&quot;: &quot;To be adde\ <lb/>\d?&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>], <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;Can we assum\ <lb/>\e unprotected as the default value?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-protection-type&quot;: &quot;unprotected&quot;, <lb/>&quot;max-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;max-resv-link-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;unreserved-bandwidth&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;priority&quot;: 0, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 67] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// __DISCUSS__ te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;1xODU2&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;oper-status&quot;: &quot;up&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ is-transitional&quot;: &quot;It is not a transitio\ <lb/>\nal link&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __DISCUSS__ underlay &quot;: &quot;To be discussed with TE T\ <lb/>\opology authors&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;source&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;source-node&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;source-tp&quot;: 7 <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __EMPTY__ destination&quot;: &quot;access link&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>B.2. JSON Examples for Service Configuration <lb/>B.2.1. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-odu2-service-config.json <lb/>This is the JSON code reporting the ODU2 transit service <lb/>configuration @ MPI: <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 68] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">========== NOTE: &apos;\\&apos; line wrapping per BCP XX (RFC XXXX) =========== <lb/> { <lb/>&quot;// __TITLE__&quot;: &quot;ODU2 Service Configuration @ MPI1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __LAST_UPDATE__&quot;: &quot;October 22, 2018&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __MISSING_ATTRIBUTES__&quot;: true, <lb/>&quot;// __REFERENCE_DRAFTS__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-routing-types@2017-12-04&quot;: &quot;rfc8294&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-types@2018-06-07&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-ccamp-otn-tunnel-model-\ <lb/>\02&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te-types@2018-07-01&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-16&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te@2018-07-01&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-teas-yang-te-16&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-tunnel@2018-06-07&quot;: &quot;draft-ietf-ccamp-otn-tunnel-model\ <lb/>\-02&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// __RESTCONF_OPERATION__&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;operation&quot;: &quot;PUT&quot;, <lb/>&quot;url&quot;: &quot;http://{{PNC1-ADDR}}/restconf/data/ietf-te:te&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;ietf-te:te&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;tunnels&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;tunnel&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;mpi1-odu2-service&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// identifier&quot;: &quot;ODU2-SERVICE-TUNNEL-ID @ MPI1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;identifier&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;description&quot;: &quot;ODU2 Service implemented by ODU2 OTN Tunne\ <lb/>\l Segment @ MPI1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// encoding and switching-type&quot;: &quot;ODU&quot;, <lb/>&quot;encoding&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:lsp-encoding-oduk &quot;, <lb/>&quot;switching-type&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:switching-otn&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// source&quot;: &quot;None: transit tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// destination&quot;: &quot;None: transit tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// src-tp-id&quot;: &quot;None: transit tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// dst-tp-id&quot;: &quot;None: transit tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// ietf-otn-tunnel:src-client-signal&quot;: &quot;None: ODU transit\ <lb/>\ tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// ietf-otn-tunnel:dst-client-signal&quot;: &quot;None: ODU transit\ <lb/>\ tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;bidirectional&quot;: true, <lb/>&quot;// protection&quot;: &quot;No protection&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __ DEFAULT __ protection&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __ DEFAULT __ enable&quot;: false <lb/>}, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 69] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;// restoration&quot;: &quot;No restoration&quot;, <lb/> &quot;// __ DEFAULT __ restoration&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __ DEFAULT __ enable&quot;: false <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// te-topology-identifier&quot;: &quot;ODU Black Topology @ MPI1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;te-topology-identifier&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;provider-id&quot;: 201, <lb/>&quot;client-id&quot;: 300, <lb/>&quot;topology-id&quot;: &quot;otn-black-topology&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;te-bandwidth&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-tunnel:odu-type&quot;: &quot;ietf-otn-types:prot-ODU2&quot; <lb/>}, <lb/>&quot;// hierarchical-link&quot;: &quot;None: transit tunnel segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;p2p-primary-paths&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;p2p-primary-path&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;name&quot;: &quot;mpi1-odu2-service-primary-path&quot;, <lb/>&quot;path-scope&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:path-scope-segment&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// te-bandwidth&quot;: &quot;None: only the tunnel bandwidth \ <lb/>\needs to be specified in transport applications&quot;, <lb/>&quot;explicit-route-objects&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;route-object-include-exclude&quot;: [ <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// comment&quot;: &quot;Tunnel hand-off OTU2 ingress in\ <lb/>\terface (S3-1)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;index&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;explicit-route-usage&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:route-i\ <lb/>\nclude-ero&quot;, <lb/>&quot;num-unnum-hop&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// node-id&quot;: &quot;AN1 Node&quot;, <lb/>&quot;node-id&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// link-tp-id&quot;: &quot;AN1-1 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-tp-id&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;hop-type&quot;: &quot;STRICT&quot;, <lb/>&quot;direction&quot;: &quot;INCOMING&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// comment&quot;: &quot;Tunnel hand-off ODU2 ingress la\ <lb/>\bel (ODU2 over OTU2) at S3-1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;index&quot;: 2, <lb/>&quot;explicit-route-usage&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:route-i\ <lb/>\nclude-ero&quot;, <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 70] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 20199 <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">&quot;label-hop&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-label&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// __ DISCUSS __ odu-label&quot;: &quot;How are HO-\ <lb/>\ODU (ODUk over OTUk) label represented?&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __ DISCUSS __ direction&quot;: &quot;Check with \ <lb/>\TE Tunnel authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;direction&quot;: &quot;FORWARD &quot; <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// comment&quot;: &quot;Tunnel hand-off OTU4 egress int\ <lb/>\erface (S2-1)&quot;, <lb/>&quot;index&quot;: 3, <lb/>&quot;explicit-route-usage&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:route-i\ <lb/>\nclude-ero&quot;, <lb/>&quot;num-unnum-hop&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;// node-id&quot;: &quot;AN1 Node&quot;, <lb/>&quot;node-id&quot;: &quot;10.0.0.1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// link-tp-id&quot;: &quot;AN1-2 LTP&quot;, <lb/>&quot;link-tp-id&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;hop-type&quot;: &quot;STRICT&quot;, <lb/>&quot;direction&quot;: &quot;OUTGOING&quot; <lb/>} <lb/>}, <lb/>{ <lb/>&quot;// comment&quot;: &quot;Tunnel hand-off ODU2 egress lab\ <lb/>\el (ODU2 over OTU4) at S2-1&quot;, <lb/>&quot;index&quot;: 4, <lb/>&quot;explicit-route-usage&quot;: &quot;ietf-te-types:route-i\ <lb/>\nclude-ero&quot;, <lb/>&quot;label-hop&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;te-label&quot;: { <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-tunnel:tpn&quot;: 1, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-tunnel:tsg&quot;: &quot;ietf-otn-types:tsg\ <lb/>\-1.25G&quot;, <lb/>&quot;ietf-otn-tunnel:ts-list&quot;: &quot;1-8&quot;, <lb/>&quot;// __ DISCUSS __ direction&quot;: &quot;Check with \ <lb/>\TE Tunnel authors&quot;, <lb/>&quot;direction&quot;: &quot;FORWARD &quot; <lb/>} <lb/> } <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 71] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/>} <lb/></note>

			<div type="annex">} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>] <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>} <lb/>B.2.2. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-odu2-tunnel-config.json <lb/>The JSON code for this use case will be added in a future version of <lb/>this document <lb/>An incomplete version is located on GitHub at: <lb/>https://github.com/danielkinguk/transport-nbi <lb/>B.2.3. <lb/>JSON Code: mpi1-epl-service-config.json <lb/>The JSON code for this use case will be added in a future version of <lb/>this document <lb/>An incomplete version is located on GitHub at: <lb/>https://github.com/danielkinguk/transport-nbi <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 72] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			Author&apos;s Address <lb/>			

			<front>Italo Busi (Editor) <lb/>Huawei <lb/>Email: italo.busi@huawei.com <lb/>Daniel King (Editor) <lb/>Old Dog Consulting <lb/>Email: daniel@olddog.co.uk <lb/>Haomian Zheng (Editor) <lb/>Huawei <lb/>Email: zhenghaomian@huawei.com <lb/>Yunbin Xu (Editor) <lb/>CAICT <lb/>Email: xuyunbin@ritt.cn <lb/>Yang Zhao <lb/>China Mobile <lb/>Email: zhaoyangyjy@chinamobile.com <lb/>Sergio Belotti <lb/>Nokia <lb/>Email: sergio.belotti@nokia.com <lb/>Gianmarco Bruno <lb/>Ericsson <lb/>Email: gianmarco.bruno@ericsson.com <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 73] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Internet-Draft Transport NBI Applicability-Statement <lb/>September 2019 <lb/></note>

			<front>Young Lee <lb/> Sung Kyun Kwan University <lb/>Email: younglee.tx@gmail.com <lb/>Victor Lopez <lb/>Telefonica <lb/>Email: victor.lopezalvarez@telefonica.com <lb/>Carlo Perocchio <lb/>Ericsson <lb/>Email: carlo.perocchio@ericsson.com <lb/>Ricard Vilalta <lb/>CTTC <lb/>Email: ricard.vilalta@cttc.es <lb/>Michael Scharf <lb/>Hochschule Esslingen -University of Applied Sciences <lb/>Email: michael.scharf@hs-esslingen.de <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Busi, King, et al. <lb/>Expires March, 2020 <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 74] </page>


	</text>
</tei>
