<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>server date 20190720; downloaded by EPO on 20190722 <lb/>Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF) <lb/>E. Wilde <lb/>Request for Comments: 8631 <lb/>July 2019 <lb/>Category: Informational <lb/>ISSN: 2070-1721 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Many resources provided on the Web are part of sets of resources that <lb/>are provided in a context that is managed by one particular service <lb/>provider. Often, these sets of resources are referred to as &quot;Web <lb/>services&quot; or &quot;Web APIs&quot;. This specification defines link relations <lb/>that represent relationships from Web services or APIs to resources <lb/>that provide documentation, descriptions, metadata, or status <lb/>information for these resources. Documentation is primarily intended <lb/>for human consumers, whereas descriptions are primarily intended for <lb/>automated consumers. Metadata provides information about a service&apos;s <lb/>context. This specification also defines a link relation to identify <lb/>status resources that are used to represent information about service <lb/>status. <lb/>Status of This Memo <lb/>This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is <lb/>published for informational purposes. <lb/>This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force <lb/>(IETF). It represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has <lb/>received public review and has been approved for publication by the <lb/>Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG). Not all documents <lb/>approved by the IESG are candidates for any level of Internet <lb/>Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 7841. <lb/>Information about the current status of this document, any errata, <lb/>and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at <lb/>https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8631. <lb/>Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/>[Page 1] <lb/>RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/> Copyright Notice <lb/>Copyright (c) 2019 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the <lb/>document authors. All rights reserved. <lb/>This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust&apos;s Legal <lb/>Provisions Relating to IETF Documents <lb/>(https://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of <lb/>publication of this document. Please review these documents <lb/>carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect <lb/>to this document. Code Components extracted from this document must <lb/>include Simplified BSD License text as described in Section 4.e of <lb/>the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without warranty as <lb/>described in the Simplified BSD License. <lb/></front>

			<div type="toc">Table of Contents <lb/>1. Introduction . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>2 <lb/>2. Terminology . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4 <lb/>3. Web Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>4 <lb/>3.1. Documenting Web Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>5 <lb/>3.2. Describing Web Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>5 <lb/>3.3. Unified Documentation/Description . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>5 <lb/>4. Link Relations for Web Services . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>5 <lb/>4.1. The service-doc Link Relation Type . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>6 <lb/>4.2. The service-desc Link Relation Type . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>6 <lb/>4.3. The service-meta Link Relation Type . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>6 <lb/>5. Web Service Status Resources . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>7 <lb/>6. IANA Considerations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>7 <lb/>6.1. Link Relation Type: service-doc . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>7 <lb/>6.2. Link Relation Type: service-desc . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>7 <lb/>6.3. Link Relation Type: service-meta . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>8 <lb/>6.4. Link Relation Type: status . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>8 <lb/>7. Security Considerations . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>8 <lb/>8. References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>9 <lb/>8.1. Normative References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>9 <lb/>8.2. Informative References . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>9 <lb/>Acknowledgements . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>9 <lb/>Author&apos;s Address . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . . <lb/>9 <lb/></div>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 2] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>One of the defining aspects of the Web is that it is possible to <lb/>interact with Web resources without any prior knowledge of the <lb/>specifics of the resource. Following the practices described in Web <lb/>architecture [W3C.REC-webarch-20041215] by using URIs, HTTP, and <lb/>media types, the Web&apos;s uniform interface allows interactions with <lb/>resources without the more complex binding procedures often necessary <lb/>with other approaches. <lb/>Many resources on the Web are provided as part of a set of resources <lb/>that are referred to as a &quot;Web service&quot; or a &quot;Web API&quot;. In many <lb/>cases, these services or APIs are defined and managed as a whole, and <lb/>it may be desirable for clients to be able to discover this service <lb/>information. <lb/>Service information that provides information on how to use service <lb/>resources can be broadly separated into two categories: One category <lb/>primarily targets human users and often uses generic representations <lb/>for human readable documents, such as HTML or PDF. The other <lb/>category is structured information that follows a more formalized <lb/>description model and is primarily intended for consumption by <lb/>machines --for example, tools and code libraries. <lb/>In the context of this memo, the human-oriented variant is referred <lb/>to as &quot;documentation&quot;, and the machine-oriented variant is referred <lb/>to as &quot;description&quot;. <lb/>These two categories are not necessarily mutually exclusive, as <lb/>representations have been proposed that are intended for both human <lb/>consumption and interpretation by machine clients. In addition, a <lb/>typical pattern for service documentation/descriptions is that there <lb/>is human-oriented, high-level documentation that is intended to put a <lb/>service in context and explain the general model, which is <lb/>complemented by machine-level descriptions that are intended as <lb/>detailed technical descriptions of the service. These two resources <lb/>could be interlinked, but since they are intended for different <lb/>audiences, it can make sense to provide entry points for both of <lb/>them. <lb/>In addition, while both documentation and descriptions may be <lb/>provided as part of a Web service, there may be other information as <lb/>well. Generally speaking, a Web service may have any metadata/ <lb/>resources associated with it (with documentation and descriptions <lb/>being two specific kinds of resources). If there is a way in which <lb/>all of these metadata/resources can be represented, then it should be <lb/>possible to find such a resource that provides access to general Web <lb/>service metadata. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 3] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>In addition to these resources about mostly static aspects of a Web <lb/>service, this memo also defines a link relation that allows providers <lb/>of a Web service to link to a resource that represents status <lb/>information about the service. This information often represents <lb/>operational information that allows service consumers to retrieve <lb/>information about &quot;service health&quot; and related issues. <lb/>This memo places no constraints on the specific representations used <lb/>for all of these resources. It simply allows providers of a Web <lb/>service to make the documentation, descriptions, metadata, and status <lb/>of their services discoverable and defines link relations that serve <lb/>that purpose. <lb/>2. Terminology <lb/>The key words &quot;MUST&quot;, &quot;MUST NOT&quot;, &quot;REQUIRED&quot;, &quot;SHALL&quot;, &quot;SHALL NOT&quot;, <lb/>&quot;SHOULD&quot;, &quot;SHOULD NOT&quot;, &quot;RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;NOT RECOMMENDED&quot;, &quot;MAY&quot;, and <lb/>&quot;OPTIONAL&quot; in this document are to be interpreted as described in <lb/>BCP 14 [RFC2119] [RFC8174] when, and only when, they appear in all <lb/>capitals, as shown here. <lb/>3. Web Services <lb/>&quot;Web Services&quot; or &quot;Web APIs&quot; (sometimes also referred to as &quot;HTTP <lb/>API&quot; or &quot;REST API&quot;) expose information and services on the Web. <lb/>Following the principles of Web architecture <lb/>[W3C.REC-webarch-20041215], they expose URI-identified resources, <lb/>which are then accessed and transferred using a specific <lb/>representation. Many services use representations that contain <lb/>links, and these links are often typed links. <lb/>Using typed links, resources can identify relationship types to other <lb/>resources. RFC 8288 [RFC8288] establishes a framework of registered <lb/>link relation types, which are identified by simple strings and <lb/>registered in an IANA registry. Any resource that supports typed <lb/>links according to RFC 8288 can then use these identifiers to <lb/>represent resource relationships on the Web without having to <lb/>reinvent registered relation types. <lb/>In recent years, Web services, as well as their documentation and <lb/>description languages, have gained popularity due to the general <lb/>popularity of the Web as a platform for providing information and <lb/>services. However, the design of documentation and description <lb/>languages varies according to a number of factors, such as the <lb/>general application domain, the preferred application data model, and <lb/>the preferred approach for exposing services. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 4] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>This specification allows service providers to use a unified method <lb/>to link to service documentation and/or descriptions. This link <lb/>should not make any assumptions about the provided type of <lb/>documentation and/or descriptions, so service providers can choose <lb/>those that best fit their services and needs. <lb/>This specification also allows service providers to link to general <lb/>service metadata. One part of the metadata may have links to <lb/>documentation and/or description as well as other information about a <lb/>service, such as deployment or operational information. <lb/>3.1. Documenting Web Services <lb/>In the context of this specification, &quot;documentation&quot; refers to <lb/>information that is primarily intended for human consumption. <lb/>Typical representations of this kind of documentation are HTML and <lb/>PDF. <lb/>Documentation is often structured, but its structure depends on the <lb/>structure of the service in question as well as the specific way in <lb/>which the authors choose to present it. <lb/>3.2. Describing Web Services <lb/>In the context of this specification, &quot;description&quot; refers to <lb/>information that is primarily intended for machine consumption. <lb/>Typical representations are dictated by the technology underlying the <lb/>service itself, which means that description formats in today&apos;s <lb/>technology landscape are based on XML, JSON, Resource Description <lb/>Framework (RDF), and a variety of other structured data models. In <lb/>each of those technologies, there may be a variety of languages <lb/>defined to serve the same general purpose of describing a Web <lb/>service. <lb/>Descriptions are always structured, but the structuring principles <lb/>depend on the nature of the described service. For example, one of <lb/>the earlier service description approaches, the Web Services <lb/>Description Language (WSDL), uses &quot;operations&quot; as its core concept, <lb/>which are essentially identical to function calls because the <lb/>underlying model is based on the Remote Procedure Call (RPC) model. <lb/>Other description languages for non-RPC approaches to services will <lb/>use different structuring approaches, such as structuring service <lb/>descriptions by URIs and/or URI patterns. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 5] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>3.3. Unified Documentation/Description <lb/>If service providers use an approach where there is no distinction <lb/>between service documentation (Section 3.1) and service description <lb/>(Section 3.2), then they may not feel the need to use two separate <lb/>links. In such a case, an alternative approach is to use the <lb/>previously defined &quot;service&quot; link relation type [RFC5023], which does <lb/>not indicate whether it links to documentation or description and <lb/>thus may be a better fit if no such differentiation is required. <lb/>4. Link Relations for Web Services <lb/>In order to allow Web services to represent the relation of <lb/>individual resources to service documentation/description and <lb/>metadata, this specification introduces and registers three new link <lb/>relation types. <lb/>4.1. The service-doc Link Relation Type <lb/>The &quot;service-doc&quot; link relation type is used to represent the fact <lb/>that a resource or a set of resources is documented at a specific <lb/>URI. The target resource is expected to provide documentation that <lb/>is primarily intended for human consumption. <lb/>4.2. The service-desc Link Relation Type <lb/>The &quot;service-desc&quot; link relation type is used to represent the fact <lb/>that a resource or a set of resources is described at a specific URI. <lb/>The target resource is expected to provide a service description that <lb/>is primarily intended for machine consumption. In many cases, it is <lb/>provided in a representation that is consumed by tools, code <lb/>libraries, or similar components. <lb/>4.3. The service-meta Link Relation Type <lb/>The &quot;service-meta&quot; link relation type is used to link to available <lb/>metadata for the service context of a resource. Service metadata is <lb/>any kind of data that may be of interest to existing or potential <lb/>service users, with documentation/description being only two possible <lb/>facets of service metadata. The target resource is expected to <lb/>provide a representation that is primarily intended for machine <lb/>consumption. In many cases, it is provided in a representation that <lb/>is consumed by tools, code libraries, or similar components. <lb/>Since service metadata can have many different purposes and use many <lb/>different representations, it may make sense for representations <lb/>using the &quot;service-meta&quot; link relation to offer additional hints <lb/>about the specific kind or format of metadata that is being linked. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 6] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>This definition of the &quot;service-meta&quot; link relation makes no specific <lb/>assumptions about how these link hints will be represented, and the <lb/>specific mechanism will depend on the context where the &quot;service-<lb/>meta&quot; link relation is being used. <lb/>One example is that a &quot;service-desc&quot; link may identify an OpenAPI <lb/>description, which is supposed to be the machine-readable description <lb/>of a Web API. A &quot;service-meta&quot; link may identify a resource that <lb/>contains additional metadata about the Web API, such as labels that <lb/>classify the API according to a labeling scheme and a privacy policy <lb/>that makes statements about how the Web API manages personally <lb/>identifiable information. <lb/>5. Web Service Status Resources <lb/>Web services providing access to one or more resources often are <lb/>hosted and operated in an environment for which status information <lb/>may be available. This information may be as simple as confirming <lb/>that a service is operational, or it may provide additional <lb/>information about different aspects of a service and/or a history of <lb/>status information, possibly listing incidents and their resolution. <lb/>The &quot;status&quot; link relation type can be used to link to such a status <lb/>resource, allowing service consumers to retrieve information about a <lb/>Web service&apos;s status. Such a link may not be available for and from <lb/>all resources provided by a Web service --only from key resources <lb/>such as a Web service&apos;s metadata resource and/or a service&apos;s home <lb/>resource (i.e., a resource analogous to the home page of a Web site). <lb/>This memo does not restrict the representation of a status resource <lb/>in any way. It may be primarily focused on human or machine <lb/>consumption or a combination of both. It may be a simple &quot;traffic <lb/>light&quot; indicator for service health or a more sophisticated <lb/>representation conveying more detailed information, such as service <lb/>subsystems and/or a status history. <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 7] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>6. IANA Considerations <lb/>The link relation types below have been registered by IANA per <lb/>Section 4.2 of RFC 8288 [RFC8288]. <lb/>6.1. Link Relation Type: service-doc <lb/>Relation Name: service-doc <lb/>Description: Identifies service documentation for the context that <lb/>is primarily intended for human consumption. <lb/>Reference: RFC 8631 <lb/>6.2. Link Relation Type: service-desc <lb/>Relation Name: service-desc <lb/>Description: Identifies service description for the context that is <lb/>primarily intended for consumption by machines. <lb/>Reference: RFC 8631 <lb/>6.3. Link Relation Type: service-meta <lb/>Relation Name: service-meta <lb/>Description: Identifies general metadata for the context that is <lb/>primarily intended for consumption by machines. <lb/>Reference: RFC 8631 <lb/>6.4. Link Relation Type: status <lb/>Relation Name: status <lb/>Description: Identifies a resource that represents the context&apos;s <lb/>status. <lb/>Reference: RFC 8631 <lb/></body>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 8] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<body>7. Security Considerations <lb/>Web service providers should be aware that service descriptions and <lb/>documentation may be used by attackers to gain additional information <lb/>about a service (particularly its implementation) and to test for <lb/>known security issues. It may thus be advisable to restrict service <lb/>descriptions and documentation to aspects of a service that are <lb/>necessary and to exclude any details that are not necessary for using <lb/>the service. <lb/>Another potential security issue for Web service providers is that <lb/>publishing service descriptions and documentation may generally allow <lb/>clients (both malicious and otherwise) more automated and systematic <lb/>access to a service. It may therefore be possible that more of a <lb/>service&apos;s potential vulnerabilities are made easier to find and <lb/>exploit or simply that a service might receive more load because it <lb/>is accessed by automated clients. <lb/>Web service consumers should be aware that service descriptions and <lb/>documentation can be out of sync or simply incorrect. Blindly <lb/>trusting service descriptions and documentation (particularly when <lb/>descriptions are retrieved and interpreted programmatically) is not a <lb/>safe practice. Web service consumers SHOULD always assume that <lb/>service descriptions and documentation may be incorrect and SHOULD <lb/>therefore be prepared to handle errors at runtime. <lb/></body>

			<listBibl>8. References <lb/>8.1. Normative References <lb/>[RFC2119] Bradner, S., &quot;Key words for use in RFCs to Indicate <lb/>Requirement Levels&quot;, BCP 14, RFC 2119, <lb/>DOI 10.17487/RFC2119, March 1997, <lb/>&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc2119&gt;. <lb/>[RFC8174] Leiba, B., &quot;Ambiguity of Uppercase vs Lowercase in RFC <lb/>2119 Key Words&quot;, BCP 14, RFC 8174, DOI 10.17487/RFC8174, <lb/>May 2017, &lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8174&gt;. <lb/>[RFC8288] Nottingham, M., &quot;Web Linking&quot;, RFC 8288, <lb/>DOI 10.17487/RFC8288, October 2017, <lb/>&lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc8288&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 9] <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">RFC 8631 <lb/>Link Relation Types for Web Services <lb/>July 2019 <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>8.2. Informative References <lb/>[RFC5023] Gregorio, J., Ed. and B. de hOra, Ed., &quot;The Atom <lb/>Publishing Protocol&quot;, RFC 5023, DOI 10.17487/RFC5023, <lb/>October 2007, &lt;https://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc5023&gt;. <lb/>[W3C.REC-webarch-20041215] <lb/>Jacobs, I. and N. Walsh, &quot;Architecture of the World Wide <lb/>Web, Volume One&quot;, World Wide Web Consortium <lb/>Recommendation REC-webarch-20041215, December 2004, <lb/>&lt;http://www.w3.org/TR/2004/REC-webarch-20041215&gt;. <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>Thanks to Mike Amundsen, Ben Campbell, Alissa Cooper, Oliver Gierke, <lb/>Benjamin Kaduk, Sebastien Lambla, Darrell Miller, and Adam Roach for <lb/>their comments and suggestions. <lb/></div>

			Author&apos;s Address <lb/>

			<front>Erik Wilde <lb/>Email: erik.wilde@dret.net <lb/>URI: <lb/>http://dret.net/netdret/ <lb/></front>

			<note place="footnote">Wilde <lb/>Informational <lb/></note>

			<page>[Page 10] </page>


	</text>
</tei>
