<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<citations>
    <bibl><author>Chen Y, Han M, Matsumoto A, Wang Y, Thompson DC, Vasiliou V</author>. <title level="a">Glutathione and Transsulfuration in Alcohol-Associated Tissue Injury and Carcinogenesis</title>. <title level="j">Adv Exp Med Biol</title>. <date>2018</date>;<biblScope type="vol">1032</biblScope>:<biblScope type="pp">37-53</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-98788-0_3</idno>. PubMed <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30362089</idno>.</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Marshall S, Chen Y, Singh S, Berrios-Carcamo P, Heit C, Apostolopoulos N, Golla JP, Thompson DC, Vasiliou V</author>. <title level="a">Engineered Animal Models Designed for Investigating Ethanol Metabolism, Toxicity and Cancer</title>. <title level="j">Adv Exp Med Biol</title>. <date>2018</date>;<biblScope type="vol">1032</biblScope>:<biblScope type="pp">203-221</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1007/978-3-319-98788-0_14</idno>. PubMed <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30362100</idno>.</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Charkoftaki G, Jester J, Thompson D, Vasiliou V</author>. <title level="a">Nitrogen mustard-induced corneal injury involves the sphingomyelin-ceramide pathway</title>. <title level="j">Ocul Surf</title>. <biblScope type="vol">16</biblScope>:<biblScope type="pp">154-162</biblScope>, <date>2018</date>, <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29129753</idno>.</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Belfort-DeAguiar RD, Gallezot JD, Hwang JJ, Elshafie A, Yeckel CW, Chan O, Carson R, Yu-Shin Ding Y-S, Sherwin RS</author>.  <title level="a">Noradrenergic Activity in the Human Brain: A Mechanism Supporting the Defense Against Hypoglycemia</title>", has been accepted for publication in The <title level="j">Journal of Clinical Endocrinology &amp; Metabolism. JCEM</title>, <date>2018 Jun 1</date>;<biblScope type="vol">103</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>):<biblScope type="pp">2244-2252</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1210/jc.2017-02717</idno>.<idno type="PMID">PMID: 29590401</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><title level="a">Yale School of Public Health Symposium on tissue imaging mass spectrometry: illuminating phenotypic heterogeneity and drug disposition at the molecular level</title>. <author>Charkoftaki G, Rattray NJW, Andrén PE, Caprioli RM, Castellino S, Duncan MW, Goodwin RJA, Schey KL, Shahidi-Latham SK, Veselkov KA, Johnson CH, Vasiliou V</author>. <title level="j">Hum Genomics</title>. <date>2018 Feb 27</date>;<biblScope type="vol">12</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">1</biblScope>):<biblScope type="pp">10</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1186/s40246-018-0142-x</idno>. <note>No abstract available</note>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29482659</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Pettigrew MM, Gent JF, Kong Y, Laufer Halpin A, Pineles L, Harris AD, Johnson JK</author>. <title level="a">Gastrointestinal microbiota disruption and risk of colonization with carbapenem-resistant Pseudomonas aeruginosa in ICU patients</title>. <title level="j">Clinical Infectious Diseases</title>. <date>2018</date>; <idno type="DOI">doi.10.1093/cid/ciy936</idno>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30383203</idno>.</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Warth B, Palermo A, Rattray NJW, Lee NV, Zhu Z, Hoang LT, Cai Y, Mazurek A, Dann S, VanArsdale T, Fantin VR, Shields D, Siuzdak G, Johnson CH</author>: <title level="a">Palbociclib and Fulvestrant Act in Synergy to Modulate Central Carbon Metabolism in Breast Cancer Cells</title>. <title level="j">Metabolites</title>. <date>2019 Jan 2</date>; <date>2019 Jan 2</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30609717</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Jacobs D, Zhu R, Luo J, Grisotti G, Heller DR, Kurbatov V, Johnson CH, Zhang Y, Khan SA</author>: <title level="a">Defining Early-Onset Colon and Rectal Cancers</title>. <title level="j">Front Oncol</title>. <date>2018</date>; <date>2018 Nov 6</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30460196</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Robinson AR, Yousefzadeh MJ, Rozgaja TA, Wang J, Li X, Tilstra JS, Feldman CH, Gregg SQ, Johnson CH, Skoda EM, Frantz MC, Bell-Temin H, Pope-Varsalona H, Gurkar AU, Nasto LA, Robinson RAS, Fuhrmann-Stroissnigg H, Czerwinska J, McGowan SJ, Cantu-Medellin N, Harris JB, Maniar S, Ross MA, Trussoni CE, LaRusso NF, Cifuentes-Pagano E, Pagano PJ, Tudek B, Vo NV, Rigatti LH, Opresko PL, Stolz DB, Watkins SC, Burd CE, Croix CMS, Siuzdak G, Yates NA, Robbins PD, Wang Y, Wipf P, Kelley EE, Niedernhofer LJ</author>: <title level="a">Spontaneous DNA damage to the nuclear genome promotes senescence, redox imbalance and aging</title>. <title level="j">Redox Biol</title>. <date>2018 Jul</date>; <date>2018 Apr 13</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29747066</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Zhu R, Liu F, Grisotti G, Pérez-Irizarry J, Cha CH, Johnson CH, Boffa DJ, Han D, Johung KL, Zhang Y, Khan SA</author>: <title level="a">Distinctive features of gastrointestinal stromal tumors arising from the colon and rectum</title>. <title level="j">J Gastrointest Oncol</title>. <date>2018 Apr</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29755761</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Warth B, Raffeiner P, Granados A, Huan T, Fang M, Forsberg EM, Benton HP, Goetz L, Johnson CH, Siuzdak G</author>: <title level="a">Metabolomics Reveals that Dietary Xenoestrogens Alter Cellular Metabolism Induced by Palbociclib/Letrozole Combination Cancer Therapy</title>. <title level="j">Cell Chem Biol</title>. <date>2018 Mar 15</date>; <date>2018 Jan 11</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29337187</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Wang Y, Chen Y, Guan L, Zhang H, Huang Y, Johnson CH, Wu Z, Gonzalez FJ, Yu A, Huang P, Wang Y, Yang S, Chen P, Fan X, Huang M, Bi H</author>: <title level="a">Carnitine palmitoyltransferase 1C regulates cancer cell senescence through mitochondria-associated metabolic reprograming</title>. <title level="j">Cell Death Differ</title>. <date>2018 Mar</date>; <date>2018 Jan 9</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29317762</idno></bibl>

    <bibl><author>Warren JL, Son JY, Pereira G, Leaderer BP, Bell ML</author>. <title level="a">Investigating the Impact of Maternal Residential Mobility on Identifying Critical Windows of Susceptibility to Ambient Air Pollution During Pregnancy</title>. <title level="j">Am J Epidemiol</title>. <date>2018 May 1</date>;<biblScope type="vol">187</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">5</biblScope>):<biblScope type="pp">992-1000</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1093/aje/kwx335</idno>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 29053768</idno> PMCID: <idno type="PMC">PMC5928458</idno> [<note>Available on 2019-05-01</note>].</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Hsieh S, Leaderer BP, Feldstein AE, Santoro N, McKay LA, Caprio S, McConnell R</author>. <title level="a">Traffic-related air pollution associations with cytokeratin-18, a marker of hepatocellular apoptosis, in an overweight and obese paediatric population</title>. <title level="j">Pediatr Obes</title>. <date>2018 Jun</date>;<biblScope type="vol">13</biblScope>(<biblScope unit="issue">6</biblScope>):<biblScope type="pp">342-347</biblScope>. <idno type="DOI">doi: 10.1111/ijpo.12228</idno>. Epub <date>2017 Jul 20</date>. <idno type="PMID">PMID: 28730729</idno>. PMCID:  <idno type="PMC">PMC5775922</idno>. [<note>Available on 2019-06-01</note>].</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Pantouris G, Dioletis E, Chen Y, Thompson DC, Vasiliou V, Lolis EJ</author>. <title level="a">Expression, purification and crystallization of the novel Xenopus tropicalis ALDH16B1, a homologue of human ALDH16A1</title>. <title level="j">Chemico-Biol Interactions</title>, <biblScope type="vol">304</biblScope>:<biblScope type="pp">168-172</biblScope>, <date>2019</date>, <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30894314</idno>.</bibl>

    <bibl><author>Kant S, Davuluri G, Alchirazi K, Heit C, Kumar A, Gangadhariah M, McMullen M, Nagy N, Vasiliou V, Marini AM, Weiner D, Dasarathy S</author>. <title level="a">Ethanol sensitizes skeletal muscle to ammonia-induced molecular perturbations</title>, <title level="j">J Biol Chem</title>, <biblScope type="vol">294</biblScope>:<biblScope type="pp">7231-7244</biblScope>; <date>2019</date>, <idno type="PMID">PMID: 30872403</idno>.</bibl>

</citations>





