<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>Chem Biol Drug Des. 2023;102:1367-1386. <lb/>| 1367 <lb/>wileyonlinelibrary.com/journal/cbdd <lb/></front>

			<body>1 | INTRODUCTION <lb/>Phthalimide is an aromatic imide with two carbonyl groups <lb/>bounded to amine moiety and used in organic synthesis for <lb/>the preparation of a wide variety of compounds with differ-<lb/>ent substituents in both the aromatic ring and the nitrogen <lb/>atom. These compounds are attractive for their biological ac-<lb/>tivities (Sharma et al., 2010) among them, as antibacterial, <lb/>antifungal, antimicrobial, anticancer (Ahmed et al., 2016; <lb/>Akgün et al., 2012; Santos et al., 2009; Tandon et al., 2009; <lb/>Wang et al., 2013), as platelet aggregation, tryptase inhib-<lb/>itors (Krysko et al., 2013; Tetsuhashi et al., 2010), anti-<lb/>inflammatory and immunomodulatory prototypes (Leite <lb/>et al., 2014), hypolipidemic activity (El-Zahabi et al., 2012), <lb/>antiangiogenic activity (Nagarajan et al., 2013), and HDAC&apos;s <lb/>inhibitors (Lee et al., 2007; Shinji et al., 2005, 2006). <lb/></body>

			<front>Received: 17 June 2023 | Revised: 2 August 2023 | Accepted: 3 August 2023 <lb/>DOI: 10.1111/cbdd.14323 <lb/>R E S E A R C H A R T I C L E <lb/>Synthesis of N-aminophalimides derived from α-amino <lb/>acids: Theoretical study to find them as HDAC8 inhibitors <lb/>by docking simulations and in vitro assays <lb/>José Eduardo Guzmán Ramírez | Teresa Mancilla Percino <lb/>Departamento de Química, Centro de <lb/>Investigación y de Estudios Avanzados <lb/>del Instituto Politécnico Nacional, <lb/>Ciudad de México, Mexico <lb/>Correspondence <lb/>Teresa Mancilla Percino, Departamento <lb/>de Química, Centro de Investigación <lb/>y de Estudios Avanzados del Instituto <lb/>Politécnico Nacional, Apartado Postal <lb/>14-740, 07000 Ciudad de México, <lb/>México. <lb/>Email: tmancill@cinvestav.mx <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Phthalimides are valuable for synthesis and biological properties. New acetamides <lb/>3(a-c) and 4(a-c) were synthesized and characterized as precursors for novel N-<lb/>aminophalimides 5(a-c) and 6(a-c). Structures of 4a, 5(a-b), and 6(a-b) were <lb/>confirmed by single crystal X-ray. Docking studies identified compounds with <lb/>favorable Gibbs free energy values for binding to histone deacetylase 8 (HDAC8), <lb/>an enzyme targeted for anticancer drug development. These compounds bound <lb/>to both the orthosteric and allosteric pockets of HDAC8, similar to Trichostatin A <lb/>(TSA), an HDAC8 inhibitor. 6(a-c) contain hydroxyacetamide moiety as a zinc-<lb/>binding group, a phthalimide moiety as a capping group, and aminoacetamide <lb/>moiety as a linker group, which are important for ligand-receptor binding. ΔG <lb/>values indicated that compounds 5b, 6b, and 6c had higher affinity for HDAC8 in <lb/>the allosteric pocket compared to TSA. In vitro evaluation of inhibitory activities <lb/>on HDAC8 revealed that compounds 3(a-c) and 5(a-c) showed similar inhibitory <lb/>effects (IC 50 ) ranging from 0.445 to 0.751 μM. Compounds 6(a-c) showed better <lb/>affinity, with 6a (IC 50 = 28 nM) and 6b (IC 50 = 0.18 μM) showing potent inhibitory <lb/>effects slightly lower than TSA (IC 50 = 26 nM). These findings suggest that the <lb/>studied compounds hold promise as potential candidates for further biological <lb/>investigations. <lb/>K E Y W O R D S <lb/>acetamides, docking, HDAC8, synthesis of N-aminophalimides, α-amino acids <lb/>This is an open access article under the terms of the Creative Commons Attribution License, which permits use, distribution and reproduction in any medium, provided <lb/>the original work is properly cited. <lb/>© 2023 The Authors. Chemical Biology &amp; Drug Design published by John Wiley &amp; Sons Ltd. <lb/></front>

			<page>1368</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>The N-aminophthalimides having an amino group <lb/>bonded to phthalimide moiety have been used to the syn-<lb/>thesis of aziridines, sulfonamides, and hydrazine substituted <lb/>(Bibian et al., 2009; Brosse et al., 2002, 2003; Felten et al., 2008; <lb/>Wang et al., 2018). Also, they have shown biological activities <lb/>like antimicrobial, anticonvulsants, anti-inflammatory, car-<lb/>bonic anhydrase II/IX inhibitor, and chemosensors (Abdel-<lb/>Aziza et al., 2019; Al-Salahi et al., 2010; El-Helby et al., 2017; <lb/>Fakhr et al., 2008; Joo et al., 2017). <lb/>On the other hand, cancer remains one of the lead-<lb/>ing causes of death worldwide (Chakrabarti et al., 2016; <lb/>Falkenberg &amp; Johnstone, 2014; Harrison &amp; Dexter, 2013; <lb/>Kazantsev &amp; Thompson, 2008; Minucci &amp; Pelicci, 2006; <lb/>Nayab et al., 2015; Yang et al., 2019), and cancer treat-<lb/>ments include inhibiting the HDACs that are linked to its <lb/>development. The function of the HDACs is to eliminate <lb/>the acetyl groups of the ε-amino groups of the lysine resi-<lb/>dues of the histones that form the chromatin resulting in <lb/>packing of the structure and preventing gene transcrip-<lb/>tion and causing gene silencing, reversibly regulated by <lb/>histone acetyltransferases (HATs) (Gallinari et al., 2007; <lb/>Struhl, 1998). Aberrant HDAC expression result in er-<lb/>roneous cellular functions, its overexpression has been <lb/>observed in different types of cancer, leading to repres-<lb/>sion of genes, as well as tumor suppressor genes (Marks <lb/>et al., 2001; Roche &amp; Bertrand, 2016). The large family <lb/>of HDAC consists of four classes, according to their se-<lb/>quence homologies to yeast and domain organization, <lb/>those that are zinc-dependent or that require zinc ion to <lb/>carry out their catalytic function: Class I (HDAC1-3, 8), <lb/>class II (HDAC4-7, 9 and 10), and class IV (HDAC11), <lb/>those that are NAD + dependent and structurally different <lb/>from other HDACs called sirtuins: class III (Sir 1-7) (Gre-<lb/>goretti et al., 2004). HDAC8 is the most-studied HDAC <lb/>isoform due to its human oncological relevance and it is <lb/>known that the overexpression of HDAC8 has been linked <lb/>with various types of cancer such as pancreas, colon, <lb/>lung, childhood neuroblastoma, and breast (Falkenberg <lb/>&amp; Johnstone, 2014). Knockdown of HDAC8 has shown <lb/>cell antiproliferative activity, apoptosis in T-cell lympho-<lb/>mas, and gastric adenocarcinoma (Balasubramanian <lb/>et al., 2008; Kang et al., 2014; Nakagawa et al., 2007; <lb/>Oehme et al., 2009; Song et al., 2015; West et al., 2014; Wu <lb/>et al., 2013), as well as cell cycle arrest and induction of <lb/>cell differentiation without affecting global histone acetyl-<lb/>ation or cellular HDAC activity (Witt et al., 2009). In ad-<lb/>dition, in order to understand the catalytic mechanism <lb/>of HDAC8, X-ray crystal structures of various inhibitors <lb/>complexed with this enzyme have been studied, thus re-<lb/>vealing in detail insight into their binding modes (Dowling <lb/>et al., 2008; Somoza et al., 2004; Vannini et al., 2004, 2007). <lb/>Besides, molecular docking study has also been a useful <lb/>tool to design and investigate new HDAC8 inhibitors <lb/>(HDAC8i) (Banerjee et al., 2019; Marek et al., 2018; Uba <lb/>et al., 2019; Yang et al., 2019). In addition, HDAC8 inhib-<lb/>itors have been developed based on the pharmacophoric <lb/>model, these molecules containing a bulky substituent <lb/>such as tetrahydroisoquinoline, pyrazole, methoxyphe-<lb/>nyl, p(prop-2-yn-1-yloxy)phenyl, p(azacyclododec-8-ene-<lb/>5,12-dione)phenyl-derived, aromatic sulphide group, <lb/>3,5-CF 3 -phenyl, bulky heteroaromatic group, as a cap-<lb/>ping group (CG), an aromatic group, phenyl group linked <lb/>to hydrazide or triazole, indolyl group, sulfamoyl motif, <lb/>phenylamides, piperazine as a linker (LG), and ortho-<lb/>aryl N-hydroxycinnamides, hydroxamic acid, triazole, <lb/>anilide, disulphide or azetidine-2-one as a zinc-binding <lb/>group (ZBG) among others (Fontana et al., 2022; Huang <lb/>et al., 2012; Ingham et al., 2016; Neelarapu et al., 2011; Su-<lb/>zuki et al., 2012; Taha et al., 2017; Tang et al., 2011; Wang <lb/>&amp; Dymock, 2009; Zhang et al., 2011, 2018). <lb/>On this background, our research has been interesting <lb/>in the synthesis of compounds derived from α-amino acids <lb/>and in researching their biological properties, for instance, <lb/>we have synthesized and carried out docking studies and in <lb/>vitro assays of some 2,3-dihydro-1H-isoindole derived from <lb/>α-amino acids as channel blockers, Cox-1 and -2 inhibitors, <lb/>effect over HDAC8 activity and expression, and HDACs in-<lb/>hibitors, as well as effect on the K14E6 transgenic mouse <lb/>model (Mancilla et al., 2001; Mancilla-Percino et al., 2010, <lb/>2016; Rodríguez-Uribe et al., 2018, 2020; Santamaria-<lb/>Herrera et al., 2016; Trejo Muñoz et al., 2014). <lb/>Thus, continuing with our studies, in this work, we <lb/>present the synthesis of novel N-aminophalimides 5(a-<lb/>c) and 6(a-c) derived from α-amino acids, which have <lb/>the phthalimide moiety as analogous compounds stud-<lb/>ied as anticancer agents and HDAC inhibitors, as well <lb/>as new 3(a-c), 4(a-c) acetamides as precursors of N-<lb/>aminophalimides. The compounds under study were se-<lb/>lected to their synthesis from molecular docking results of <lb/>acetamides y N-aminophalimides derived of 20 α-amino <lb/>acids against HDAC8. All compounds synthetized in this <lb/>work were characterized by nuclear magnetic and high-<lb/>resolution mass spectrometry, and confirmation of the <lb/>structures of 4a, 5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b by X-ray diffraction. <lb/>Furthermore, evaluation of the inhibitory activity of 3(a-<lb/>c), 5(a-c), and 6(a-c) on HDAC8 enzyme is reported. <lb/>2 | EXPERIMENTAL SECTION <lb/>2.1 | General procedures and materials <lb/>All solvents and chemicals were used as bought without <lb/>further purification. HDAC8 Inhibitor Screening kit was <lb/>bought from Sigma Aldrich Co® Catalog Number EPI007. <lb/> 1 <lb/>H and 13 C NMR spectra were recorded on a Jeol 500 ECA <lb/></body>
				
			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1369 <lb/></page>
				
			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>
				
			<body>(500 MHz for 1 H; 125 MHz for 13 C), or BRUKER_DMX <lb/>(400 MHz for 1 H and 100 MHz for 13 C) using Chloroform-<lb/>d, DMSO-d6, or Acetone-d6. Chemical shifts of 1 H and 13 C <lb/>are reported relative to tetramethylsilane (TMS) and are <lb/>given in parts per million (ppm). The following abbrevia-<lb/>tions were used for signal patterns: s (singlet), d (doublet), <lb/>dd (doublet of doublets), dt (doublet of triplets), q (quarter), <lb/>t (triplet), and m (multiplet). HRMS were recorded on an <lb/>HPLC 1100 coupled to an MSD-TOF Agilent Technologies <lb/>HR-MSTOF 1069A or Bruker micrOTOF-Q II spectrom-<lb/>eter, both equipment with electrospray ionization (ESI). <lb/>X-ray spectroscopy was performed using a Bruker D8 VEN-<lb/>TURE or Bruker-APEX-II Diffractometer. IR spectra were <lb/>recorded on a Varian FT-IR-IR 640 series. Melting points <lb/>were determined on a Gallenkamp equipment MFB-595 <lb/>with open capillary tubes and were uncorrected. Measure-<lb/>ment of the enzymatic assay was Read Ex/Em = 390/485 nm <lb/>using a Fluoroskan Ascent FL Thermo Scientific. <lb/>2.2 | Chemistry <lb/>2.2.1 | Synthesis of tert-Butoxy acetic acid (2) <lb/>In a 100 mL balloon flask equipped with a magnetic bar on an <lb/>ice bath, NaH 60% dispersion in mineral oil (4 equiv., 2.40 g, <lb/>60 mmol) and anhydrous THF (50 mL) were added, anhy-<lb/>drous tert-butanol (4 equiv., 5.70 mL, 60 mmol) was added <lb/>dropwise, the reaction mixture was allowed to stir for 20 min <lb/>and Bromoacetic acid 1 (1 equiv., 2.09 g, 15 mmol) dissolved <lb/>in anhydrous THF (10 mL) was added dropwise, The reac-<lb/>tion mixture was allowed to warm to room temperature and <lb/>subsequently heated to reflux for 6 h. After being cooled to <lb/>room temperature, the solvent was removed under reduced <lb/>pressure, the residue was dissolved in water (15 mL) and <lb/>washed with hexane (10 mL × 3), the aqueous layer was neu-<lb/>tralized with dilute HCl and extracted with dichloromethane <lb/>(10 mL × 3), the organic layer was dried with magnesium <lb/>sulfate anhydrous and filtered, and the solvent was removed <lb/>under reduced pressure. The target compound was obtained <lb/>as colorless oil 94% (1.86 g, 14.10 mmol). <lb/>2.2.2 | General procedure for the synthesis of <lb/>compounds 3(a-c) <lb/>In a 50 mL balloon flask provided with a magnetic bar on <lb/>an ice bath, compound 2 (1 equiv., 4.5 mmol), the respec-<lb/>tive amino methyl ester hydrochloride (1 equiv., 4.5 mmol), <lb/>dichloromethane (15 mL, for 3a) or acetonitrile (15 mL, <lb/>for 3b and 3c) and DIPEA (3 equiv., 2.4 mL, 13.5 mmol) <lb/>were added, the reaction mixture was allowed to stir for <lb/>20 min, T3P® ≥50 wt. % in ethyl acetate (1.2 equiv., 3.22 mL, <lb/>5.4 mmol) was added dropwise, the solution was stirred <lb/>overnight at room temperature. The solvent was removed <lb/>under reduced pressure, the residue was dissolved in di-<lb/>chloromethane (30 mL) and washed with distilled water <lb/>and (10 mL), diluted HCl (10 mL), aq. NaHCO 3 (10 mL), <lb/>and distilled water and (10 mL), the organic layer was dried <lb/>with magnesium sulfate anhydrous and filtered, and the <lb/>solvent was removed under reduced pressure. <lb/>2.2.3 | Synthesis of methyl 2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)acetate (3a) <lb/>Yellowish liquid; yield 85% (0.81 g, 3.96 mmol). 1 H NMR <lb/>(500 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 7.18 (s, 1H), 4.09 (d, J = 5.7 Hz, 2H), <lb/>3.94 (s, 2H), 3.77 (s, 3H), 1.25 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ): δ = 171.2, 170.2, 74.7, 62.0, 52.3, 40.5, 27.4, 74.7, <lb/>62.0, 52.3, 40.5, and 27.4. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 2972, 1747, <lb/>1667, 1526, 1182, and 1096 cm -1 . HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + <lb/>calcd. for C 9 H 17 NO 4 , 204.12303 and found 204.12326. <lb/>2.2.4 | Synthesis of (S)-methyl <lb/>2-(2-(tert-butoxy)acetamido)-3-<lb/>phenylpropanoate (3b) <lb/>Yellow viscous liquid; yield 92% (1.21 g, 4.14 mmol). 1 H <lb/>NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 7.31-7.23 (m, 3H), 7.13 (d, <lb/>J = 7.8 Hz, 2H), 7.08 (d, J = 7.3 Hz, 1H), 4.89 (q, J = 7.1, <lb/>1H), 3.86 (s, 2H), 3.72 (s, 3H), 3.14 (d, J = 5.8 Hz, 2H), and <lb/>1.16 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 171.7, 170.6, <lb/>135.8, 129.3, 128.6, 127.2, 74.6, 62.0, 52.32, 52.27, 38.0, and <lb/>27.3. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3027, 2974, 1742, 1675. 1519, <lb/>1189, and 1096 cm -1 . HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for <lb/>C 16 H 23 NO 4 , 294.16998 and found 294.17001. <lb/>2.2.5 | Synthesis of (S)-methyl 2-(2-<lb/>(tert-butoxy)acetamido)-3-(1H-indol-3-yl) <lb/>propanoate (3c) <lb/>Yellowish viscous liquid; yield 95% (1.42 g, 4.28 mmol). <lb/>1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 10.96 (s, 1H), 7.47 (d, <lb/>J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.45 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.35 (d, J = 8.1 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.14 (d, J = 2.5 Hz, 1H), 7.07 (dt, J = 7.6 and 1.1 Hz, <lb/>1H), 6.98 (dt, J = 8.1 and 1.1 Hz, 1H), 4.61 (q, J = 6.0 Hz, <lb/>1H), 3.75 (s, 2H), 3.62 (s, 3H), 3.22 (d, J = 6.0 Hz, 2H), and <lb/>1.06 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 172.0, <lb/>170.1, 136.2, 127.2, 123.9, 121.1, 118.7, 118.1, 111.5, 108.8, <lb/>74.1, 61.7, 52.3, 52.1, 27.0, and 26.7. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): <lb/>3051, 2975, 1738, 1663, 1519, 1182, and 1095 cm -1 . HRMS <lb/>(ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 18 H 24 N 2 O 4 , 333.18088 and <lb/>found 333.18090. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1370</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>2.2.6 | General procedure for the synthesis of <lb/>compounds 4(a-c) <lb/>The respective tert-butoxy acetamide 3(a-c) (1 equiv., <lb/>3 mmol), was dissolved in MeOH:H 2 O 4:1 (5 mL) and a <lb/>solution of KOH 2.2 N (2 equiv., 2.73 mL, 6 mmol) was <lb/>added, the solution was stirred overnight at room tem-<lb/>perature. The mixture reaction was neutralized with <lb/>HCl 2.5 N (2 equiv., 2.4 mL, 6 mmol), the solvent was <lb/>removed under reduced pressure, the residue was dis-<lb/>solved in acetonitrile (10 mL) was dried with magne-<lb/>sium sulfate anhydrous and filtered, the solvent was <lb/>removed under reduced pressure. <lb/>2.2.7 | Synthesis of 2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)acetic acid (4a) <lb/>White solid; yield 90.6% (0.51 g, 2.72 mmol); mp 107-<lb/>109°C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 8.91 (s, 1H), 7.36 <lb/>(t, J = 5.2 Hz, 1H), 4.09 (d, J = 5.6 Hz, 2H), 3.97 (s, 2H), <lb/>and 1.24 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 172.4, <lb/>172.3, 74.9, 61.7, 40.8, and 27.3. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): <lb/>2975, 1734, 1615, 1539, 1212, and 1097 cm -1 . HRMS <lb/>(ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 8 H 15 NO 4 , 212.08933 and <lb/>found 212.08954. <lb/>2.2.8 | Synthesis of (S)-2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)-3-phenylpropanoic acid (4b) <lb/>White solid; yield 97.2% (0.81 g, 2.92 mmol); mp 87-<lb/>89°C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 9.02 (s, 1H), <lb/>7.31-7.17 (m, 6H), 4.86 (q, J = 6.1 Hz, 1H), 3.89 (d, <lb/>J AB = 15.6 Hz, 1H), 3.87 (d, J BA = 15.6 Hz, 1H), 3.22 (dd, <lb/>J AB = 13.9 Hz, J AX = 5.6 Hz, 1H), 3.16 (dd, J BA = 13.9 Hz, <lb/>J BX = 6.1 Hz, 1H), and 1.13 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ): δ = 174.3, 171.8, 135.6, 129.4, 128.6, 127.2, 74.8, <lb/>61.7, 52.5, 37.3, and 27.2. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3028, <lb/>2969, 1731, 1615, 1538, 1192, and 1098 cm -1 . HRMS <lb/>(ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 15 H 21 NO 4 , 280.15433 and <lb/>found 280.15465. <lb/>2.2.9 | Synthesis of (S)-2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)-3-(1H-indol-3-yl)propanoic acid <lb/>(4c) <lb/>White solid; yield 87% (0.83 g, 2.61 mmol); mp 191-<lb/>193°C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 12.84 (s, 1H), <lb/>10.95 (s, 1H), 7.50 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.33 (d, J = 8.0 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.31 (d, J = 7.3 Hz, 1H), 7.12 (d, J = 2.2 Hz, 1H), 7.06 <lb/>(t, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 6.96 (t, J = 8.0 Hz, 1H), 4.52 (q, J = 6.9 <lb/>and 6.1 Hz, 1H), 3.73 (s, 2H), 3.20 (d, J = 5.8 Hz, 2H), and <lb/>1.05 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 173.0, <lb/>169.8, 136.1, 127.4, 123.8, 121.0, 118.6, 118.3, 111.4, <lb/>109.1, 74.0, 61.8, 52.1, 27.0, and 26.7. ATR-FTIR (ν, <lb/>cm -1 ): 3373, 2966, 1702, 1616, 1541, 1216, and 1105 cm -1 . <lb/>HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 17 H 22 N 2 O 4 , 319.16523 <lb/>and found 319.16537. <lb/>2.2.10 | General procedure for the <lb/>synthesis of compounds 5(a-c) <lb/>Under a nitrogen atmosphere to a solution of the respec-<lb/>tive compound 4(a-c) (1 equiv., 2 mmol) in DMF anhy-<lb/>drous (4 mL) and DIPEA (3 equiv., 1.05 mL, 6 mmol) <lb/>was added HATU (1.2 equiv., 0.913 g, 2.4 mmol) and <lb/>subsequently N-Aminophthalimide, the reaction mix-<lb/>ture was stirred overnight at room temperature. Di-<lb/>chloromethane (20 mL) was added to the solution and <lb/>washed with distilled water (10 mL) and diluted HCl <lb/>(10 mL), aq. NaHCO 3 (10 mL), and distilled water and <lb/>(10 mL), the organic layer was dried over magnesium <lb/>sulfate anhydrous and filtered, the solvent was removed <lb/>under reduced pressure. The residue was purified by <lb/>column chromatography on silica gel using chloroform/ <lb/>acetonitrile (9:1). <lb/>2.2.11 | Synthesis of 2-(tert-butoxy)-N-(2-<lb/>((1,3-dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)amino)-2-oxoethyl) <lb/>acetamide (5a) <lb/>Yellowish solid; yield 72% (0.48 g, 1.44 mmol); mp 215-<lb/>217°C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 10.75 (s, <lb/>1H), 7.97-7.91 (m, 4H), 7.86 (t, J = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 4.02 (d, <lb/>J = 5.8 Hz, 2H), 3.82 (s, 2H), and 1.17 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR <lb/>(100 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 170.6, 168.5, 165.0, 135.3, 129.4, <lb/>123.7, 73.9, 61.9, 39.8, and 27.0. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3015, <lb/>2971, 1731, 1652, 1542, 1121, and 1095 cm -1 . HRMS (ESI): <lb/>[M + H] + calcd. for C 16 H 19 N 3 O 5 , 334.13974 and found <lb/>334.1350. <lb/>2.2.12 | Synthesis of (S)-2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)-N-(1,3-dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)-3-<lb/>phenyl-propanamide (5b) <lb/>White solid; yield 88% (0.75 g, 1.76 mmol); mp 152-<lb/>154°C. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 9.10 (s, 1H), <lb/>7.91-7.86 (m, 2H), 7.79-7.75 (m, 2H), 7.34-7.23 (m, 5H), <lb/>7.20 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 4.93 (q, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 3.90 (d, <lb/>J AB = 15.6 Hz, 1H), 3.82 (d, J BA = 15.6 Hz, 1H), 3.21 (dd, <lb/>J AB = 14.1 Hz, J AX = 6.3 Hz, 1H), 3.20 (dd, J BA = 14.4 Hz, <lb/></body>
				
			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1371 <lb/></page>
				
			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>J BX = 7.8 Hz, 1H), and 1.14 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ): δ = 172.4, 170.1, 164.7, 135.8, 134.6, 130.1, 129.6, <lb/>128.8, 127.2, 123.9, 74.8, 61.8, 52.0, 36.6, and 27.2. ATR-<lb/>FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3161, 2973, 1740, 1716, 1651, 1534, <lb/>1173, and 1097 cm -1 . HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for <lb/>C 23 H 25 N 3 O 5 , 424.18669 and found 424.1838. <lb/>2.2.13 | Synthesis of (S)-2-(2-(tert-butoxy) <lb/>acetamido)-N-(1,3-dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)-3-<lb/>(1H-indol-3-yl) propanamide (5c) <lb/>Yellow solid; yield 78% (0.72 g, 1.56 mmol); mp <lb/>110.8-113.2°C. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, CDCl 3 ): δ = 9.07 (s, <lb/>1H), 8.55 (s, 1H), 7.84-7.81 (m, 2H), 774.-7.71 (m, 2H), <lb/>7.67 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.39 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.29 (d, <lb/>J = 8.1 Hz, 1H), 7.25 (d, J = 2.5 Hz, 1H), 7.11 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, <lb/>1H), 7.05 (t, J = 7.1 Hz, 1H), 5.07 (q, J = 6.9 Hz, 1H), 3.80 <lb/>(d, J AB = 15.5 Hz, 1H), 3.75 (d, J BA = 15.5 Hz, 1H), 3.35 <lb/>(d, J = 6.7 Hz, 2H), and 1.05 (s, 9H). 13 C NMR (125 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ): δ = 171.8, 170.7, 165.0, 136.1, 134.6, 129.9, 127.5, <lb/>124.0, 123.9, 122.0, 119.7, 118.6, 111.2, 109.6, 74.6, 61.8, <lb/>51.8, 27.8, and 27.1. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3338, 2977, 1736, <lb/>1653, 1519, 1211, and 1100 cm -1 . HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + <lb/>calcd. for C 25 H 26 N 4 O 5 , 463.19759 and found 463.1923. <lb/>2.2.14 | General procedure for the <lb/>synthesis of compounds 6a-6c <lb/>By applying the technique described in the literature <lb/>(Mallesha et al., 2012), the right compound 5(a-c) <lb/>(1 mmol) was dissolved in methanol (10 mL) and Amber-<lb/>lite® IR120 hydrogen form (2 g) was added, the reaction <lb/>mixture was refluxed for 36 h, filtered, and washed with <lb/>methanol. The solvent was evaporated, and the residue <lb/>was purified by column chromatography on silica gel <lb/>using chloroform/acetonitrile (7:3). <lb/>2.2.15 | Synthesis of N-(1,3-<lb/>dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)-2-(2-hydroxyacetamido) <lb/>acetamide (6a) <lb/>Yellowish solid; yield 77% (0.21 g, 0.77 mmol); mp &gt;250°C. <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 10.74 (s, 1H), 8.09 (t, <lb/>J = 5.7 Hz, 1H), 7.97-7.91 (m, 4H), 5.57 (t, J = 5.7 Hz, 1H), <lb/>4.00 (d, J = 6.0 Hz, 2H), and 3.86 (d, J = 5.7 Hz, 2H). 13 C <lb/>NMR (125 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 172.3, 168.6, 165.0, 135.3, <lb/>129.4, 123.8, 61.3, and 39.5. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): 3277, <lb/>2975, 1742, 1657, 1514, 1217, 1117, and 1096 cm -1 . HRMS <lb/>(ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 12 H 11 N 3 O 5 , 278.07714 and <lb/>found 278.0730. <lb/>2.2.16 | Synthesis of (S)-N-<lb/>(1,3-dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)-2-(2-<lb/>hydroxyacetamido)-3-phenylpropa-namide (6b) <lb/>White solid; yield 94% (0.35 g, 0.94 mmol); mp 209-2011°C. <lb/>1 H NMR (400 MHz, Acetone-d6): δ = 10.02 (s, 1H), 7.95 (s, <lb/>4H), 7.55 (d, J = 8.3 Hz, 1H), 7.38 (d, J = 6.8 Hz, 2H), 7.29 <lb/>(dt, J 1 = 7.3, J 2 = 1.9 Hz, 2H), 7.22 (dt, J 1 = 7.3, J 2 = 1.8 Hz, <lb/>1H), 5.09-5.03 (m, 1H), 4.64 (s, 1H), 3.95 (s, 2H), 3.33 (dd, <lb/>J AB = 14.1 Hz, J AX = 5.4 Hz, 1H), and 3.18 (dd, J BA = 14.1 Hz, <lb/>J BX = 7.8 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR (100 MHz, Acetone-d6): <lb/>δ = 171.6, 170.3, 164.8, 136.7, 135.0, 130.1, 129.6, 128.2, <lb/>126.6, 123.5, 61.6, 51.9, and 37.9. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): <lb/>3138, 2971, 1745, 1665, 1520, 1180, and 1093 cm -1 . HRMS <lb/>(ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 19 H 17 N 3 O 5 , 368.12410 and <lb/>found 368.1203. <lb/>2.2.17 | Synthesis of (S)-N-<lb/>(1,3-dioxoisoindolin-2-yl)-2-(2-<lb/>hydroxyacetamido)-3-(1H-indol-3-yl) <lb/>propanamide (6c) <lb/>Brown solid; yield 72% (0.29 g, 0.72 mmol); mp 184-<lb/>187°C. 1 H NMR (500 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 11.08 (s, 1H), <lb/>10.90 (s, 1H), 7.97-7.91 (m, 4H), 7.70 (d, J = 8.5 Hz, 1H), <lb/>7.61 (d, J = 7.8 Hz, 1H), 7.30 (d, J = 8.1 Hz, 1H), 7.23 (d, <lb/>J = 1.8 Hz, 1H). 7.04 (t, J = 7.2 Hz, 1H), 6.96 (t, J = 7.2 Hz, <lb/>1H), 5.48 (t, J = 5.7 Hz, 1H), 4.91-4.87 (m, 1H), 3.78-<lb/>3.70 (m, 2H), 3.29 (dd, J AB = 14.7 Hz, J AX = 4.8 Hz, 1H), <lb/>and 3.16 (dd, J BA = 14.7 Hz, J BX = 8.3 Hz, 1H). 13 C NMR <lb/>(125 MHz, DMSO-d6): δ = 172.1, 171.5, 165.6, 136.6, <lb/>135.9, 130.0, 127.9, 124.6, 124.3, 121.5, 118.91, 118.89, <lb/>111.9, 109.4, 61.7, 51.6, and 28.7. ATR-FTIR (ν, cm -1 ): <lb/>3124, 2976, 1736, 1623, 1518, 1234, 1186, and 1092 cm -1 . <lb/>HRMS (ESI): [M + H] + calcd. for C 21 H 18 N 4 O 5 , 429.11694 <lb/>and found 429.1138. <lb/>2.3 | Crystal structure determination of <lb/>4a, 5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b <lb/>X-ray diffraction data were collected at 273 K on a Bruker <lb/>D8 VENTURE for 4a, and 297 K on a Bruker APEX-II for <lb/>5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b, using MoKα radiation (λ = 0.71073 Å). <lb/>Data collection: Bruker APEX2 software; cell refinement: <lb/>SAINT V8.38A integration software; data reduction: SOR-<lb/>TAV (Blessing, 1995) program(s) used to refine structure: <lb/>SHELXL2018/3 (Sheldrick, 2015), molecular graphics: <lb/>ORTEP for Windows; software used to prepare mate-<lb/>rial for publication: WinGX publication routines (Farru-<lb/>gia, 2012). Crystallographic data have been deposited at <lb/>the Cambridge Crystallographic Data Center, www.ccdc. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1372</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>cam.ac.uk/conts/ retri eving.html. CCDC-1969858 (4a), <lb/>-1969859 (5a), -1969860 (5b), -1969861 (6a), and -1969862 <lb/>(6b), they are shown in supplementary crystallographic <lb/>(Appendix S1). <lb/>2.4 | Computational methodology <lb/>Molecular docking of the acetamides and TSA (reference <lb/>compound) was performed on the X-ray crystal struc-<lb/>ture of human HDAC8 enzyme, which was retrieved <lb/>from RCSB Protein Data Bank (PDB ID: 1T64) (Somoza <lb/>et al., 2004; Vannini et al., 2004). The crystal structure was <lb/>optimized by removing the water and the co-crystallized <lb/>ligands using Discovery Studio Visualizer v19.1.0.18287 <lb/>(Dassault Systèmes BIOVIA, 2019), whereas hydrogen <lb/>atoms were added using AutoDockTools-1.5.6. All the <lb/>compounds were drawn using GaussView 5.0.8 and were <lb/>geometrically optimized by density functional theory <lb/>calculations at the B3LYP/6-31G** level using Gaussian <lb/>09W software (Frisch et al., 2013). Docking calculations <lb/>were conducted using AutoDock 4.2.6® software (Mor-<lb/>ris et al., 2009). The grid box covered the entire volume <lb/>of the HDAC8 (126 Å × 126 Å × 126 Å dimensions) with a <lb/>grid spacing of 0.375 Å. The main Lamarckian Genetic Al-<lb/>gorithm (Morris et al., 2009) parameters were set to 100 <lb/>runs, a population size of 100, and a maximum number <lb/>of 1 × 10 7 energy evaluation. The co-crystallized TSA was <lb/>re-docked on HDAC8 to valid the docking protocol. The <lb/>re-docked was evaluated by calculation of root stand-<lb/>ard deviation (RMSD) using Discovery Studio Visualizer <lb/>v19.1.0.18287 (Dassault Systèmes BIOVIA, 2019). Dock-<lb/>ing poses of the target compounds and TSA were analyzed <lb/>based on the best energy and were visualized using Dis-<lb/>covery studio 3.5 software v19.1.0.18287 (Dassault Sys-<lb/>tèmes BIOVIA, 2019). <lb/>2.5 | HDAC8 inhibition assay <lb/>The inhibitory activity of 3(a-c), 5(a-c), and 6(a-c) on <lb/>HDAC8 was evaluated by detection of lysyl deacety-<lb/>lase activity of the recombinant human HDAC8, using <lb/>HDAC8 Fluorometric Drug Discovery Kit according to <lb/>manufacturer&apos;s instructions (Sigma Aldrich Co® Catalog <lb/>No EPI007). The stock solutions of the compounds and <lb/>TSA (inhibitor control) were prepared in DMSO and di-<lb/>luted in assay buffer to reach the final concentration in <lb/>the range of 0.25 nM-100 μM. The final concentration of <lb/>DMSO was &lt;10% and did not affect the activity of the as-<lb/>says. The assays were performed by preincubating the en-<lb/>zyme with the test compounds, including TSA, at 37°C for <lb/>10 min. Then, the substrate was added, and the mixture <lb/>was incubated at 37°C for 60 min. After, 10 μL of the devel-<lb/>oper were added and the mixture was incubated at 37°C <lb/>for 5 min. The fluorescence signal was measured using a <lb/>fluorescence plate reader (Thermo Scientific Fluoroskan <lb/>Ascent FL) at excitation and emission wavelengths of 390 <lb/>and 485 nm, respectively. All experiments were performed <lb/>in triplicate. The IC 50 values were calculated using non-<lb/>linear regression dose-response fit in (Prism GraphPad <lb/>Software). <lb/>3 | RESULTS AND DISCUSSION <lb/>3.1 | Chemistry <lb/>The synthetic route leading to the formation of the target <lb/>compounds 3(a-c), 4(a-c), 5(a-c), and 6(a-c) is outlined <lb/>in Scheme 1. Compound 2, which was raw material, was <lb/>obtained by the reaction of Bromo acetic acid 1 with tert-<lb/>butanol in the presence of NaH. Compound 2 was con-<lb/>verted by a coupling reaction to tert-butoxyacetamides <lb/>methyl ester 3(a-c) with corresponding α-amino methyl <lb/>ester hydrochloride (a, b, and c: Gly, Phe, and Trp derived, <lb/>respectively), using T3P® in DCM or ACN depending on <lb/>their solubility. Compounds 3(a-c) were then converted <lb/>into the corresponding tert-butoxyacetamides 4(a-c) after <lb/>alkaline hydrolysis using potassium hydroxide in aqueous <lb/>methanol. Compounds 5(a-c) were obtained through the <lb/>coupling between N-aminophthalimide and correspond-<lb/>ing 4(a-c), using HATU as coupling reagent with stir-<lb/>ring at room temperature overnight. Finally, 6(a-c) were <lb/>obtained by the deprotection of the hydroxyl group with <lb/>Amberlite® IR120 hydrogen form under methanol reflux <lb/>(Mallesha et al., 2012). <lb/>3.2 | Spectroscopy <lb/>All compounds were characterized by spectroscopic meth-<lb/>ods of 1 H, 13 C NMR (Spectra are given in Appendix S1), <lb/>Infrared and spectrometry of HRMS (Spectra are given <lb/>in Appendix S1). Besides, suitable crystals of compounds <lb/>4a, 5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b were obtained for X-ray diffraction, <lb/>which confirmed their structures (X-ray data are given in <lb/>SI). All data for each compound are given in the materials <lb/>and methods section. <lb/>1 <lb/>H NMR spectra of compounds 3a, 3b, 4a, and 4b were <lb/>recorded in CDCl 3 , while 3c and 4c in DMSO-d6. The <lb/>spectra of 3(a-c) showed a singlet signal for methoxy and <lb/>tert-butoxy protons in the range of 3.62-3.77 and 1.06-<lb/>1.25 ppm, respectively. H-2 of 3a displayed a doublet at <lb/>4.09 ppm, and that of 3b and 3c showed a quartet at 4.89 <lb/>and 4.61 ppm, respectively. The NH-3 of 3a exhibited a <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1373 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>singlet signal at 7.18 ppm and that of 3b and 3c a doublet <lb/>at 7.08 and 7.45 ppm, respectively. The H-5 showed a sin-<lb/>glet signal between 3.75 and 3.94 ppm. Benzyl protons of <lb/>3b and indolyl group of 3c shown the coupling patterns <lb/>expected in the range of 3.14-3.22 ppm for H-12 and be-<lb/>tween 6.98 and 7.47 ppm for aromatics protons and NH <lb/>of indolyl group showed a singlet at 10.96 ppm. 1 H NMR <lb/>spectra of 4(a-c) showed for tert-butoxy, H-2, NH-3, ben-<lb/>zyl of 4b, and indolyl of 4c protons almost the same chem-<lb/>ical shifts and coupling patterns observed for 3(a-c). The <lb/>carboxylic protons displayed a broad signal in the range of <lb/>8.91 and 12.84 ppm. H-5 of 4a and 4c exhibited a singlet <lb/>signal at 3.97 and 3.73, respectively, while those of 4b ex-<lb/>hibited an AB system at 3.87 and 3.89 ppm. <lb/>1 H NMR spectra 5(a-c) and 6(a-c) were recorded in <lb/>CDCl 3 for 5a, in DMSO-d6 for 5b, 5c, 6a, and 6c, and in <lb/>acetone-d6 for 6b. Spectra of 5(a-c) showed that chemical <lb/>shifts and coupling patterns of tert-butoxy (1.05-1.17 ppm), <lb/>H-2 (4.02-5.07 ppm), NH-3 (7.20-7.86 ppm), benzyl, and <lb/>indolyl protons were almost identically to that of 4(a-c). <lb/>H-5 of 5a exhibited a simple signal at 3.82 ppm, and those <lb/>of 5b and 5c exhibited an AB system between 3.75 and <lb/>3.90 ppm. H-10 and H-11 of phthalimide moiety displayed <lb/>a complex pattern in the range of 7.71-7.97 ppm, NH-6 <lb/>showed a singlet in the range of 9.07-10.75 ppm. Spec-<lb/>tra of 6(a-c) showed for H-2 of 6a a doublet at 4.00 ppm, <lb/>while that of 6b and 6c exhibited a complex pattern at <lb/>5.06 and 4.89 ppm, respectively. H-5 of 6a exhibited a <lb/>doublet signal at 3.86 ppm by coupling with OH, which <lb/>showed a triplet at 5.57 ppm, whereas H-5 and OH of 6b <lb/>displayed a simple signal at 3.95 and 4.64, respectively, <lb/>H-5 of 6c showed a complex pattern at 3.74 ppm by cou-<lb/>pling with OH, which showed a triplet at 5.48 ppm. NH-3 <lb/>of 6a showed a triplet at 8.09 ppm, while that of 6b and <lb/>6c exhibited a doublet at 7.55 and 7.70 ppm, respectively. <lb/>NH-6 for these compounds displayed a simple signal in <lb/>the range of 10.02-11.08 ppm. H-10 and H-11 of 6a and <lb/>6c exhibited a complex pattern at 7.94 ppm, while those <lb/>of 6b showed a simple signal at 7.95 ppm. H-12 of 6b and <lb/>6c displayed an AB coupling system in the range of 3.18-<lb/>3.33 ppm, chemical shifts of the aromatic protons of ben-<lb/>zyl and indolyl groups are in the range of 6.96-7.61 ppm, <lb/>and NH of indolyl showed a simple signal at 10.90 ppm. <lb/>13 C NMR spectra of 3(a-c) and 4(a-c) showed a signal <lb/>for methyl of the tert-butoxy groups in the range of 27.0-<lb/>27.4 ppm, for carbon the CH 3 O group of 3(a-c) the sig-<lb/>nal at 52.3 ppm, C-2 showed the signal between 40.5 and <lb/>52.5 ppm, and C-5 between 61.7 and 62.0 ppm. The signal <lb/>of quaternary carbon of the tert-butoxy group was in the <lb/>range of 74.0-74.9 ppm, the C-1 of the compounds 3(a-c) <lb/>showed the signal between 170.2 and 172.0 ppm, whereas <lb/>C-1 of the compounds 4(a-c) exhibited the signal within <lb/>172.4-174.3 ppm, C-4 exhibited the signal within 169.8-<lb/>172.3 ppm. Carbons of the benzyl and indolyl groups <lb/>S C H E M E 1 Synthetic rout 3(a-c), 4(a-c), 5(a-c), and 6(a-c). Reagents and conditions: (a) NaH, t-BuOH, THF 0°C to rt, reflux; (b) <lb/>respective α-amino methyl ester hydrochloride (a, b, and c: Gly, Phe, and Trp derived, respectively), DIPEA, T3P®, DCM, or ACN 0°C to rt; <lb/>(c) KOH, MeOH:H 2 O; (d) N-aminophthalimide, HATU, DIPEA, DMF; (e) Amberlite® IR120 hydrogen form, MeOH, reflux. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1374</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>displayed signals between 26.7 and 38.0 ppm for C-12, in <lb/>the range of 127.2-135.8 ppm for C-13 to C-16, and within <lb/>108.8-136.2 ppm for C-13 to C-20. 13 C NMR spectra of <lb/>5(a-c) and 6(a-c) showed that chemical shifts of methyl <lb/>carbons of the tert-butoxy moiety of 5a (27.0-27.2 ppm), <lb/>C-2 (39.5-52.0 ppm), C-5 (61.3-61.9 ppm), quaternary car-<lb/>bons of the tert-butoxy groups of 5a (73.9-74.8 ppm), C-1 <lb/>(168.5-171.5 ppm), C-4 (170.6-172.6 ppm), C-12 (27.8-<lb/>37.9), C-13 to C-16 (126.6-136.7 ppm), and C-13 to C-20 <lb/>(109.4-136.6) were almost identical to that of 3(a-c) and <lb/>4(a-c). Aromatic carbons C-9 to C-11 and carbonyl car-<lb/>bons C-8 of the phthalimide moiety displayed the signals <lb/>in the range of 123.5-135.9 ppm and 164.7-165.6 ppm, re-<lb/>spectively. The high-resolution mass spectra of the target <lb/>compounds showed the ion of the protonated molecules <lb/>[M + H] + , which agreed with their molecular formula, the <lb/>data are given in the experimental section. <lb/>3.3 | X-ray structures <lb/>Suitable crystals of 4a, 5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b were obtained <lb/>for X-ray analysis, an ORTEP view, and crystallographic <lb/>numbering are given in the Figures 1-3. Compound 4a, <lb/>5a, 6a, and 6b crystallized with four molecules in the <lb/>unit cell, while 5b crystallized with two molecules to-<lb/>gether with two chloroform molecules, which was used <lb/>to crystallize. In general, all bond distances are within <lb/>the values expected (Bondi, 1964; Zamudio Rivera <lb/>et al., 1999); bond lengths selected are summarized in <lb/>Tables 1-3. <lb/>The molecules in the crystal structure exhibit intra-<lb/>molecular hydrogen bonding between oxygen of alkoxy <lb/>group and hydrogen of NH of the amide moiety as fol-<lb/>lows: O 2 …H 1 2.33, O 5 …H 03 2.19, O 5 …H 03 2.16 for 4a, <lb/>5a, and 5b, respectively. Molecules 6a and 6b show the <lb/>following intermolecular interaction H 03 …O 5 2.22, and <lb/>O 5 …H 03 2.20 Å, respectively. Besides, 4a exhibit the in-<lb/>termolecular interaction H 3 …O 4 2.22 Å of the carboxylic <lb/>group. Therefore, these molecules in the crystal structure <lb/>show intermolecular hydrogen bonding as follows: O 1 … <lb/>H 3 1.81 Å for 4a, H 02 …O 4 1.88, H 03 …O 2 2.50 and H 10B …O 2 <lb/>2.630 Å for 5a, O 4 …H 02 2.08 Å for 5b, H02…O4 1.89, 03… <lb/>H05 2.01, H03…01 2.24 Å for 6a, and H 02 …O 4 1.87, H 03 …O 1 <lb/>2.65, H 05 …O 3 1.874 for 6b, which are significantly shorter <lb/>than the sum of the van der Waals radii of oxygen and <lb/>hydrogen (2.70 Å) (Bondi, 1964). <lb/>In addition, the torsion angles values indicate the pla-<lb/>narity in acetamide moiety in these crystal structures as <lb/>179 (4) o (O 1 -C 3 -N 1 -H 1 ) and 1 (4) o (C 4 -C 3 -N 1 -H 1 ) for 4a, <lb/>180 (2) o (O 4 -C 11 -N 3 -H 03 ) and 0 (2) o (C 12 -C 11 -N 3 -H 03 ) for <lb/>5a, -173 (3) o (O 4 -C 11 -N 3 -H 03 ) for 5b, 176 (1) o (O 4 -C 11 -<lb/>N 3 -H 03 ), -4 (1) o (C 12 -C 11 -N 3 -H 03 ) and -175(2) o (O 3 -<lb/>C 9 -N 2 -H0 2 ) for 6a, and 176 (2) o (O 4 -C 11 -N 3 -H 03 ) and <lb/>-171(2) o (O 3 -C 9 -N 2 -H 02 ) for 6b. <lb/>4 | MOLECULAR DOCKING <lb/>STUDY <lb/>X-ray structures of various HDAC8-inhibitor complexes <lb/>have been described, including TSA among other (Brun-<lb/>steiner &amp; Petukhov, 2012), and considerable structural <lb/>differences were found in the protein surface in the vicin-<lb/>ity of the aperture of the active site, depending on which <lb/>inhibitor is bonded (Estiu et al., 2010), these changes de-<lb/>rived from the presence of two deep pockets one denoted <lb/>as the orthosteric pocket and the second close to the first <lb/>denoted as the allosteric pocket, where Trp141, Phe152, <lb/>and Tyr306 form the wall between both cavities (Estiu <lb/>et al., 2010). In particular, the crystal structure of HDAC8-<lb/>TSA complex (PDB ID: 1T64) (Somoza et al., 2004), shows <lb/>that TSA binds at two pockets, in this sense, it has been <lb/>considered as competitive inhibitor because it is binding <lb/>at catalytic pocket and noncompetitive inhibitor since <lb/>is noncatalytic binding pocket (Su et al., 2008). The or-<lb/>thosteric that is the active site is described as a long and <lb/>narrow tunnel constituted for the amino acids residues <lb/>His142, His143, Gly151, Phe152, His180, Phe208, Met274, <lb/>and Tyr306 (Somoza et al., 2004; Vannini et al., 2004), at <lb/>the bottom of this tunnel, the catalytic site is found, which <lb/>is formed by Zn 2+ ion and the catalytic triad of His142, <lb/>His143, and Tyr306n (Gantt et al., 2016). One of the char-<lb/>acteristics in HDAC8 is loop L1, which is formed by seven <lb/>amino acid residues (Ser30, Leu31, Ala32, Lys33, Ile34, <lb/>Pro35, and Lys36) (Maolanon et al., 2016), is highly flex-<lb/>ible and found toward the proximity of the active site <lb/>and can undergo conformational changes for substrates <lb/>binding. <lb/>F I G U R E 1 Molecular structure of C 8 H 15 NO 4 , and <lb/>crystallographic numbering scheme of 4a. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1375 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>Thus, in this work, we described the binding mode <lb/>of 3(a-c), 4(a-c), 5(a-c), and 6(a-c), as well as for TSA <lb/>on two pockets of X-ray structure of HDAC8 (PDB ID: <lb/>1T64). Hence, a molecular docking study was performed <lb/>to investigate binding modes of compounds 3(a-t), 4(a-<lb/>t), 5(a-t), and 6(a-t) derived of 20 α-amino acids (Gly, <lb/>Phe, Trp, Ala, Val, Leu, Ile, Met, Tyr, Ser, Pro, Thr, Cis, <lb/>Asn, Gln, Lys, His, Arg, Asp, and Glu) on HDAC8; results <lb/>F I G U R E 2 Molecular structure of C 16 H 19 N 3 O 5 and C 24 H 26 Cl 3 N 3 O 5 , crystallographic numbering scheme of 5a and 5b, respectively. <lb/>F I G U R E 3 Molecular structure of C 12 H 11 N 3 O 5 and C 19 H 17 N 3 O 5 , crystallographic numbering scheme of molecules 6a and 6b, <lb/>respectively. <lb/>O (3)-H (3) <lb/>0.824 (18) <lb/>C (1)-O (4) <lb/>1.206 (4) <lb/>N (1)-H (1) <lb/>0.82 (2) <lb/>C (3)-N (1) <lb/>1.310 (4) <lb/>C (3)-O (1) <lb/>1.236 (4) <lb/>C (4)-O (2) <lb/>1.401(4) <lb/>C (5)-O (2) <lb/>1.458 (3) <lb/>T A B L E 1 Bond lengths selected (Å) <lb/>for (4a). <lb/>Compound 5a <lb/>N (3)-H (03) <lb/>0.92 (2) <lb/>C (11)-N <lb/>(3) <lb/>1.322 (3) <lb/>C (11)-O <lb/>(4) <lb/>1.241 (2) <lb/>C (12)-O (5) <lb/>1.412 (3) <lb/>C (13)-O <lb/>(5) <lb/>1.436 (3) <lb/>C (4)-O (1) <lb/>1.198 (3) <lb/>C (5)-O (2) <lb/>1.204 (2) <lb/>N (1)-N (2) <lb/>1.378 (2) <lb/>N (2)-H <lb/>(02) <lb/>0.92 (3) <lb/>Compound 5b <lb/>N (3)-H (03) <lb/>0.94 (4) <lb/>C (11)-N <lb/>(3) <lb/>1.329 (5) <lb/>C (11)-O <lb/>(4) <lb/>1.232 (4) <lb/>C (12)-O (5) <lb/>1.399 (5) <lb/>C (13)-O <lb/>(5) <lb/>1.441 (5) <lb/>C (4)-O (1) <lb/>1.196 (4) <lb/>C (5)-O (2) <lb/>1.193 (4) <lb/>N (1)-N (2) <lb/>1.376 (4) <lb/>N (2)-H <lb/>(02) <lb/>0.82 (5) <lb/>T A B L E 2 Bond lengths selected (Å) <lb/>for 5a and 5b. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1376</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>showed that most of the compounds binding in both or-<lb/>thosteric and allosteric site of the enzyme, as it has been <lb/>observed for TSA (Docking data are given in SI). Based <lb/>on the results, compounds 3(a-c), 4(a-t), 5(a-t), and <lb/>6(a-t) were selected for analysis of the binding modes <lb/>on the X-ray structure of HDAC8 (PDB ID: 1T64). The <lb/>docking protocol was confirmed through the re-docking <lb/>of the co-crystallized TSA within the HDAC8 structure. <lb/>It showed that the inhibitor bound into both pockets <lb/>of the enzyme providing an RMSD value of 0.9304 and <lb/>1.3509 Å. Therefore, the docking protocol was reliable <lb/>for the analysis of the binding modes of the target com-<lb/>pounds with HDAC8. <lb/>The Gibbs free energies (ΔG, kcal/mol), along with <lb/>the corresponding dissociation constants (K d , μM) val-<lb/>ues were obtained for the four series HDAC8-ligands <lb/>complexes in each pocket, showing all these compounds <lb/>more affinity at the allosteric pocket than in orthosteric <lb/>pocket, except 5c, and 4a that did not show affinity to <lb/>orthosteric site. Furthermore, compounds 5b, 6b, and 6c <lb/>inhibited more affinity than TSA. The data are summa-<lb/>rized in Table 4. <lb/>The study of binding modes of 3(a-c), 4(a-c), 5(a-<lb/>c), and 6(a-c) and TSA with amino acid residues of both <lb/>pockets of HDAC8 was based on the analysis of the type <lb/>of interactions, such as hydrogen bonds, π-π interactions <lb/>coordination bonds, π-sulfur, π-lone pairs, and π-cation <lb/>interactions, where the analysis of the distances were <lb/>considered as &lt;4 Å for hydrogen bonds and &lt;6 Å for hy-<lb/>drophobic interactions, (Brylinski, 2018; Copeland, 2000) <lb/>between heteroatoms, carbons, or protons coupled to het-<lb/>eroatoms of all target acetamides to atoms of amino acids <lb/>residues of HDAC8. The docking results showed that all <lb/>the binding interactions depended on the conformations <lb/>and functional groups of the acetamides. <lb/>4.1 | Binding modes of compounds 3(a-c) <lb/>with HDAC8 <lb/>Acetamides 3(a-c) showed interactions in the orthosteric <lb/>site of HDAC8, in which binding modes depended on <lb/>the orientation of the molecules based on the substitute <lb/>in position three. Thus, the oxygen atom of carbonyl-1 of <lb/>Compound 6a <lb/>N (3)-H (03) <lb/>0.811 (19) <lb/>C (11)-N <lb/>(3) <lb/>1.322 (3) <lb/>C (11)-O <lb/>(4) <lb/>1.238 (2) <lb/>C (12)-O (5) <lb/>1.391 (3) <lb/>C (4)-O (1) <lb/>1.204 (2) <lb/>C (5)-O (2) <lb/>1.202 (2) <lb/>N (1)-N (2) <lb/>1.377 (2) <lb/>N (2)-H <lb/>(02) <lb/>0.86 (2) <lb/>Compound 6b <lb/>N (3)-H (03) <lb/>0.87 (2) <lb/>C (11)-N <lb/>(3) <lb/>1.325 (2) <lb/>C (11)-O <lb/>(4) <lb/>1.227 (2) <lb/>C (12)-O (5) <lb/>1.396 (3) <lb/>C (4)-O (1) <lb/>1.203 (3) <lb/>C (5)-O (2) <lb/>1.196 (3) <lb/>N (1)-N (2) <lb/>1.377 (2) <lb/>N (2)-H <lb/>(02) <lb/>0.88 (2) <lb/>T A B L E 3 Bond lengths selected (Å) <lb/>for 6a and 6b. <lb/>T A B L E 4 Gibbs free energy ΔG (kcal mol -1 ) and dissociation constant K d (μM) values of HDAC8-ligand complexes. <lb/>Compd. <lb/>Orthosteric site <lb/>Allosteric site <lb/>Compd. <lb/>Orthosteric site <lb/>Allosteric site <lb/>ΔG <lb/>K d <lb/>ΔG <lb/>K d <lb/>ΔG <lb/>K d <lb/>ΔG <lb/>K d <lb/>3a <lb/>-5.17 <lb/>162.37 <lb/>-6.12 <lb/>32.42 <lb/>3c <lb/>-5.92 <lb/>45.69 <lb/>-6.85 <lb/>9.52 <lb/>3b <lb/>-5.05 <lb/>200.41 <lb/>-6.96 <lb/>7.96 <lb/>4a <lb/>-4.92 <lb/>249.19 <lb/>4c <lb/>-5.66 <lb/>70.72 <lb/>-6.59 <lb/>14.85 <lb/>4b <lb/>-4.04 <lb/>1090 <lb/>-5.53 <lb/>88.96 <lb/>5a <lb/>-6.01 <lb/>39.0 <lb/>-7.28 <lb/>4.62 <lb/>5c <lb/>-7.59 <lb/>2.74 <lb/>-7.34 <lb/>4.16 <lb/>5b <lb/>-6.83 <lb/>9.9 <lb/>-8.45 <lb/>638.43 a <lb/>6a <lb/>-6.34 <lb/>22.65 <lb/>-8.02 <lb/>1.32 <lb/>6c <lb/>-7.79 <lb/>1.96 <lb/>-9.44 <lb/>119.74 a <lb/>6b <lb/>-7.15 <lb/>5.74 <lb/>-8.79 <lb/>358.78 a <lb/>TSA <lb/>-8.34 <lb/>771.6 a <lb/>-8.34 <lb/>764.93 a <lb/>a <lb/>Value is given in nM. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1377 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>ester moiety of 3a showed a coordination bond to Zn 2+ at <lb/>2.22 Å, by hydrogen bonds with the proton of OH (side <lb/>chain) of Tyr306 (2.23 Å) and with the NH (backbone) <lb/>of Gly304 (2.51 Å). A carbon atom from the tert-butoxy <lb/>moiety showed hydrophobic binds alkyl-π (side chain) of <lb/>Phe208 (3.71 Å) and Phe152 (4.23 Å). Acetamides 3b and <lb/>3c, which have the phenyl and indole groups at position <lb/>three, respectively, showed that both groups interacted <lb/>with the amino acid residues of the surface of the enzyme <lb/>in the vicinity of the opening of the active site, exhibiting <lb/>different orientation, and bind modes to that observed for <lb/>3a, which does not have a substituent at position three. <lb/>This can be attributed to the different conformations <lb/>adopted by the three acetamides in the pocket. <lb/>Thus, the oxygen atom of tert-butoxy group of 3b exhib-<lb/>ited a hydrogen bond with the proton of NH (backbone) <lb/>of Phe208 at 2.12 Å, phenyl group exhibited π-π T-shaped <lb/>interaction with Phe152 at 4.89 Å, and π-lone pair interac-<lb/>tion (side chain) with His180 at 4.09 Å. Hydrogens, NH-3 <lb/>and NH of indole group of 3c showed hydrogen bonds <lb/>with the oxygen of carbonyl (backbone) of Gly206 (1.99 Å) <lb/>and carbonyl (side chain) of Asp101 (2.09 Å), respectively; <lb/>indole exhibited π-π stacking interactions with Phe208 at <lb/>3.82 and 3.94 Å, and π-sulfur interaction with Met274 at <lb/>5.18 Å. The results show that compounds 3(a-c) bonded <lb/>to the residues of the active site of HDAC8, and 3a ad-<lb/>ditionally bonded to zinc ion, suggesting it bonded in a <lb/>competitive manner. Compounds 3b and 3c also showed <lb/>interactions with the amino acid residues that do not be-<lb/>long to the active site, which are in the L8 loop as Tyr306, <lb/>the L5 loop as Phe 208, and Asp101 residue is strictly con-<lb/>served in the L2 loop of all class I and class II HDAC&apos;s and <lb/>has been established that is important for the substrate <lb/>recognition (Dowling et al., 2008; Estiu et al., 2010; Van-<lb/>nini et al., 2007). The results showed that the ester group <lb/>of 3a oriented toward the catalytic site as the hydroxamic <lb/>group of TSA. Also, acetamides and inhibitor showed in-<lb/>teractions with the same amino residues of the active site <lb/>Phe152, Phe208, Gly304, Met274, and Tyr306. Therefore, <lb/>acetamides 3(a-c) may be considered as possible HDAC8 <lb/>inhibitors. <lb/>Acetamides 3(a-c) exhibited different conformations <lb/>between them at the allosteric site of HDAC8, therefore <lb/>displayed the following binds, 3a showed four hydrogen <lb/>bonds, NH-3 with C=O (backbone) of Cys28 at 2.79 Å, <lb/>with C=O (side chain) of Asp29 at 2.21 Å and the oxygen <lb/>atom of the C=O-4 with NH 2 of guanidine group (side <lb/>chain) of Arg37 at 1.88 Å. A carbon atom from tert-butoxy <lb/>moiety showed alkyl-π interaction with Tyr306 at 5.05 Å. <lb/>Compound 3b showed two hydrogen bonds, the oxygen <lb/>atom of C=O-1 with NH (backbone) of Arg37 at 2.15 Å <lb/>and NH-3 with OH (side chain) of Tyr111 at 2.50 Å, and <lb/>the phenyl group exhibited π-π T-shaped interaction with <lb/>Tyr 306 at 5.03 Å. Indole moiety of 3c showed π-alkyl in-<lb/>teraction with C (side chain) of Arg37 at 4.97 Å and π-<lb/>guanidine group protonated interaction (side chain) at <lb/>4.45 Å. NH of indole moiety exhibited a hydrogen bond <lb/>with OH (side chain) of Tyr111 at 1.88 Å, also indole group <lb/>showed π-π stacked interaction with Trp141 at 4.38 Å. <lb/>Among the common binding of these compounds are to <lb/>Arg37 through C=O-4 and C=O-1 of 3a and 3b, respec-<lb/>tively, and indole group of 3c, acetamides 3a and 3d bind <lb/>to Tyr306 through tert-butoxy moiety and phenyl moiety, <lb/>respectively; 3b and 3c bind to Tyr111 by NH-3 and NH <lb/>of indole moiety, (Figure 4). These results revealed that <lb/>both acetamides and TSA bind to the amino acid residues <lb/>Arg37, Tyr111, and Ser138 in the allosteric site of HDAC8, <lb/>but different binding types depending on their conforma-<lb/>tion adopted at the site. <lb/>4.2 | Binding modes of compounds 4(a-c) <lb/>with HDAC8 <lb/>Compounds 4(a-c), which have a carboxylic group instead <lb/>of the ester group of their precursors 3(a-c), showed dif-<lb/>ferent orientations and binding types in the orthosteric <lb/>site in comparison with those of 3(a-c), except 4a that did <lb/>not show interactions in this pocket. Thus, the tert-butoxy <lb/>group of 4b and 4c orient toward the inside of the tunnel, <lb/>while the groups of 3b and 3c oriented inside were phe-<lb/>nyl and indole, respectively. Two carbon atoms of the tert-<lb/>butoxy moiety of 4b exhibited alkyl-π interactions with <lb/>side chains of His143, Phe152, and His180 at 3.89, 4.44, <lb/>and 4.12 Å, respectively, and two carbon atoms of the tert-<lb/>butoxy group of 4c displayed alkyl-π interactions with the <lb/>side chain of Phe152 (4.20, 4.60 Å), His180 (4.44 Å), Tyr306 <lb/>(4.18 Å), and Met274 at (4.59 Å). C=O-1 of 4b and 4c bind <lb/>by a hydrogen bond to NH (backbone) of Phe208 at 1.88 <lb/>and 1.79 Å, respectively. The hydrogen atom of the carbox-<lb/>ylic acid of 4b exhibited hydrogen bond with N (side chain) <lb/>of His180 at 2.24 Å, NH-3 of 4b and 4c displayed hydrogen <lb/>bonds with N (side chain) of His180 at 2.72 and 2.14 Å, re-<lb/>spectively. C-5 of 4c exhibited alkyl-π interaction with the <lb/>side chain of Phe208 at 3.70 Å. NH of indole moiety of 4c <lb/>bind by a hydrogen bond to C=O (backbone) of Pro273 at <lb/>2.01 Å, although it does not belong to active site residues, <lb/>it is joined to Met274, and indole moiety exhibited bind <lb/>π-alkyl interaction with C (side chain) of Met274 at 4.17 Å. <lb/>These data showed that 4b and 4c interacted to the amino <lb/>acid residues of the active site of HDAC8 and that carbox-<lb/>ylic acid moiety contributed to the orientation of the mole-<lb/>cules where tert-butoxy moiety, although voluminous, was <lb/>oriented in the tunnel. These two acetamides and inhibitor <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1378</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>showed binding with the same amino residues of the ac-<lb/>tive site Phe152, Phe208, Met274, and Tyr306, where 4c <lb/>displayed more bindings. Therefore, 4(b-c) may be con-<lb/>sidered HDAC8 inhibitors. <lb/>Compounds 4(a-c) in the allosteric site showed the fol-<lb/>lowing binding, for 4a, hydrogen bonds HO of the carbox-<lb/>ylic acid with OH (side chain) of Ser138 at 2.18 Å, C=O-1 <lb/>with guanidine group (side chain) of Arg37 at 1.63 Å, and <lb/>with NH-3 (backbone) of Cys28 at 2.15 Å, and hydrophobic <lb/>interactions alkyl-π interactions between carbon atoms of <lb/>tert-butoxy moiety and (side chain) of Trp141 and Tyr306 <lb/>at 4.89 and 4.94 Å, respectively. 4b exhibited the following <lb/>hydrogen bonds, the proton of carboxylic acid moiety with <lb/>C=O (backbone) of Cys28 and C=O (side chain) of Asp29 <lb/>at 2.89 and 1.80 Å, respectively, NH-3 with (backbone) of <lb/>Pro35 at 2.5 Å, and phenyl moiety showed π-π T-shaped in-<lb/>teraction with (side chain) of Trp141 at 4.77 Å. 4c displayed <lb/>hydrogen bonds between NH-3 with C=O (backbone) of <lb/>Pro35 at 2.15 Å, NH of indole group with OH (side chain) <lb/>of Trp141 at 1.80 Å, and hydrophobic π-sigma interaction <lb/>was observed between indole moiety and (side chain) of <lb/>Ile34 at 3.58 Å. Carbons of tert-butoxy moiety exhibited <lb/>alkyl interaction with C (side chain) of Arg37 at 3.99 Å, and <lb/>Trp141 at 3.99 and 4.46 Å, respectively. These acetamides <lb/>showed binding with Try141, which is one of the residues <lb/>that form the wall between the two pockets, they also show <lb/>inhibitor shown interactions with the same amino acid res-<lb/>idues Pro35, Arg37, Ser138, and Tyr111 (Figure 5). <lb/>4.3 | Binding modes of compounds 5(a-c) <lb/>with HDAC8 <lb/>Compounds 5(a-c), which have N-aminophthalimide <lb/>group showed differences in the orientation of the com-<lb/>pounds toward the orthosteric site, phthalimide group of <lb/>5a and 5c was orient to the pocket favoring hydrophobic <lb/>interactions and with the residues that they form the walls <lb/>of the channel, while 5b maintains the orientation of the <lb/>tert-butyl group toward the pocket, leaving the indole part <lb/>on the surface, which allows greater interaction with sur-<lb/>face residues and aromatic groups of the amino acids resi-<lb/>dues. The types of binding are described below. <lb/>The oxygen atom of C=O-1 and NH-3 of 5a bind by <lb/>hydrogen bonds with NH (backbone) of Phe208 and the <lb/>oxygen of Gly206 at 1.86 and 2.15 Å, respectively, π-π <lb/>T-shaped interactions were between phthalimide moi-<lb/>ety and the side chain of His180 and Phe208 at 4.69 and <lb/>4.12 Å, also π-sulfur interaction between phthalimide <lb/>and Met274 at 5.06 Å was observed. Compound 5b only <lb/>showed π-alkyl interactions between phthalimide moiety <lb/>and the side chain of Pro35 at 5.46 Å, and π-π T-shaped <lb/>interactions with the side chain of Phe152 and Tyr306 at <lb/>4.45 and 5.38 Å. Carbon atoms of the tert-butoxy group <lb/>π-alkyl interactions with His143, His180, and Phe208 <lb/>were displayed at 4.71, 3.59, and 4.23 Å, respectively, <lb/>also phenyl moiety presented π-sulfur interaction with <lb/>Met274 at 4.47 Å. NH of indole moiety of 5c showed a <lb/>F I G U R E 4 Binding modes of <lb/>HDAC8-3(a-c): 3a-, 3b-, and 3c-O <lb/>represent binding of the compounds with <lb/>the amino acid residues in the orthosteric <lb/>site; 3a-, 3b-, and 3c-A represent the <lb/>binding in the allosteric site. Bindings <lb/>were hydrogen bonds (green dotted <lb/>line), hydrophobics π-π (purple dotted <lb/>line), π-alkyl (pink dotted line), π-sulfur <lb/>and π-guanidine group protonated <lb/>(orange dotted line), and Zn ion (orange <lb/>ball). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1379 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>hydrogen bond with the backbone of Gly206 at 1.97 Å, <lb/>and carbon atoms of tert-butoxy moiety exhibited π-alkyl <lb/>interactions with the side chain of Phe207 and Met274 <lb/>at 4.62 and 4.16 Å, respectively. These results showed <lb/>that although no compound showed the suitable con-<lb/>formation to bind the zinc ion, they and TSA displayed <lb/>interactions with the same amino acid residues of the <lb/>active site Phe152, Phe208, Met274, and Tyr306. Besides, <lb/>phenyl moiety of TSA showed binding only with Met274, <lb/>and the phthalimide group of 5a and 5b displayed bind-<lb/>ing with His180, Phe208, Met274, and Phe208, Tyr306, <lb/>respectively, while that of 5c did not show bind. There-<lb/>fore, 5(a-c) could be considered as possible HDAC8 <lb/>inhibitors. <lb/>Compounds 5(a-c) in the allosteric site showed the <lb/>following binds, phthalimide moiety of 5a exhibited π-π <lb/>T-shaped interactions with the side chain of Phe208 (4.51 <lb/>and 4.75 Å), 5b with the side chain of Tyr306 at 5.09 Å, <lb/>and π-alkyl interactions of these compounds with the side <lb/>chain of Pro35 (3.72, 4.0, and 3.63 Å). While phthalimide <lb/>moiety of 5c displayed π-alkyl interactions with the side <lb/>chain of Ile34 and Pro35 at 4.96 and 4.50 Å, respectively. <lb/>NH-3 and oxygen atom of the tert-butoxy moiety of 5a <lb/>showed hydrogen bonds with OH of the side chain of <lb/>Tyr111 at 2.11 and 2.27 Å. The carbon atoms of the tert-<lb/>butoxy moiety of 5a exhibited π-alkyl interactions whit <lb/>the side chain of Trp141 at 4.86 and 5.03 Å, 5b with the <lb/>side chain of Tyr111 at 3.95 and 5.05 Å and the side chain <lb/>of Trp141 at 3.80 and 4.56 Å, and 5c with the side chain <lb/>of Tyr100 at 4.46 and 5.18 Å. Phenyl moiety of 5b showed <lb/>π-guanidine group protonated interaction (side chain) of <lb/>Arg37 at 3.97 Å, and indole moiety of 5c exhibited π-π T-<lb/>shaped interaction with the side chain of Tyr100 at 5.08 Å <lb/>(Figure 6). The data showed that phthalimide moiety of <lb/>5(a-c) showed binding with Pro35, Arg37, Ile34, Phe208, <lb/>and Tyr306, while phenyl moiety of TSA showed binding <lb/>with Pro35 and Phe152. 5a and 5b conformations allowed <lb/>to these binding with the inner amino acid residues of the <lb/>pocket (Tyr111, Trp141, Phe208, and Tyr306), where these <lb/>compounds and TSA showed binding with Tyr111, while <lb/>F I G U R E 5 Binding modes of <lb/>HDAC8-4(a-c): 4b-O and 4c-O represent <lb/>binds of the compounds with the amino <lb/>acid residues in the orthosteric site; 4a-, <lb/>4b-, and 4c-A represent the binding in the <lb/>allosteric site. Bindings were hydrogen <lb/>bonds (green dotted line), hydrophobics <lb/>π-π (purple dotted line) and π-alkyl (pink <lb/>dotted line), and π-sulfur (orange dotted <lb/>line). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1380</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>5c conformation let more binding with amino acid resi-<lb/>dues of the surface pocket. <lb/>4.4 | Binding modes of compounds 6(a-c) <lb/>with HDAC8 <lb/>It is known that several classes of small molecule have <lb/>been recognized as HDAC inhibitors, most of these are <lb/>hydroxamic acid derivatives, exemplified by suberoylani-<lb/>lide hydroxamic acid (SAHA), where hydroxamate moiety <lb/>chelate the zinc ion in the active site. While hydroxamic <lb/>acid group is responsible for various potent inhibitors, <lb/>they usually have many problems associated with their <lb/>use such as low oral availability, poor in vivo stability, and <lb/>undesirable side effects. Based on the above, research on <lb/>this topic was focused on the replacement of hydroxam-<lb/>ate by non-hydroxamate groups to find potent molecules <lb/>as inhibitors of HDACs, thus, several suberoylanilide <lb/>hydroxamic acid (SAHA)-based compounds have been <lb/>synthesized containing sulfonamide, sulfone, aminoca-<lb/>tetamide, hydroxyacetamine, and mercaptoacetamide as <lb/>ZBG. The kinetic enzyme assays and molecular modeling <lb/>suggested that compounds with mercaptoacetamide moi-<lb/>ety interacts with the zinc in the active site of HDACs (Su-<lb/>zuki et al., 2005; Wang &amp; Dymock, 2009). <lb/>In this context, compounds 6(a-c) are attractive <lb/>because having a hydroxyacetamide moiety as a zinc-<lb/>binding group (ZBG), a phthalimide moiety as a capping <lb/>group, and aminoacetamide moiety as a linker group, <lb/>which are important in the ligand-receptor binding <lb/>(Marks et al., 2003; Figure 7). The binding modes of these <lb/>compounds with HDAC8 depend on their conformations <lb/>led to different orientations on each site. Hydroxyl group <lb/>F I G U R E 6 Binding modes of <lb/>HDAC8-5(a-c): 5a-, 5b-, and 5c-O <lb/>represent binds of the compounds with <lb/>the amino acid residues in the orthosteric <lb/>site; 5a-, 5b-, and 5c-A represent the <lb/>binds in the allosteric site. Bindings were <lb/>hydrogen bonds (green dotted line), <lb/>hydrophobics π-π (purple dotted line), π-<lb/>alkyl (pink dotted line), and π-sulfur and <lb/>π-guanidine group protonated (orange <lb/>dotted line). <lb/>F I G U R E 7 Structure general for 6(a-c), red color ZBG, green <lb/>color LG, and blue color CG. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1381 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>of 6a was orient toward the inner of the orthosteric site, <lb/>where the oxygen of C=O-4 showed binding at zinc ion <lb/>at 2.05 Å. Also, 6a exhibited hydrogen bonds with the <lb/>enzyme as follows, hydrogen of NH-3 with oxygen atom <lb/>(backbone) of Gly151 at 2.5 Å, oxygen of C=O-4 with OH <lb/>(side chain) of Tyr306 at 2.22 Å, hydrogen of NH with oxy-<lb/>gen atom (backbone) of Gly304 at 2.61 Å, and hydrogen of <lb/>OH group bind to an oxygen atom (side chain) of Asp178 <lb/>at 2.10 Å. Phthalimide moiety showed π-π stacking inter-<lb/>actions with Phe208 at 3.83 and 4.44 Å. Due to 6a binding <lb/>to zinc ion and Asp178, Phe208, and Tyr306 just like TSA, <lb/>it may be promising as an HDAC8 inhibitor, and a candi-<lb/>date for additional studies. <lb/>Compounds 6b and 6c were oriented at the active <lb/>site in a different way than 6a because they had different <lb/>conformations. Although these compounds did not show <lb/>interaction with the zinc ion, they showed binding inter-<lb/>actions with the amino acid residues of the active site. <lb/>Compound 6b displayed interactions by hydrogen bonds <lb/>as follows, hydrogen of NH-3 and that of hydroxyl group <lb/>interacted with oxygen (side chain) of Asp101 at 2.08 and <lb/>1.97 Å, respectively, the oxygen atom of C=O-8 with NH <lb/>(backbone) of Phe208 at 1.97 Å. The aromatic moiety of <lb/>phthalimide of 6b exhibited π-π T-shaped interaction <lb/>whit (side chain) of His180 at 5.67 Å and π-alkyl with <lb/>(side chain) of Met274 at 4.38 and 4.60 Å. Compound 6c <lb/>exhibited interactions by hydrogen bonds as follows: Oxy-<lb/>gen atom of C=O-4 with the hydrogen of NH (backbone) <lb/>of Phe208 at 1.69 Å, hydrogen of OH group with oxygen <lb/>(side chain) of Gly206 at 1.77 Å, NH-6 with S (side chain) <lb/>of Met274 at 2.98 Å, and the oxygen atom of C=O-8 with <lb/>NH (side chain) Lys202 at 2.20 Å. The phthalimide moiety <lb/>showed π-alkyl interaction with (side chain) of Met274 at <lb/>5.02 Å, indole moiety showed the π-π T-shaped interac-<lb/>tions with Phe152 (4.78 Å) and His180 (4.31 Å), and the <lb/>π-π stacked with Phe208 at 4.13 and 4.86 Å. As it is men-<lb/>tioned above, although 6b and 6c did not interact with <lb/>zinc ion, they showed binding interactions with the amino <lb/>acid residues of the active site Phe208 and Met274 as well <lb/>as TSA; therefore, these compounds could be considered <lb/>for further studies, (Figure 5). Compounds 6(a-c) in the <lb/>allosteric site showed hydrogen bonds interactions of the <lb/>oxygen atoms of C=O-1 and C=O-4 of 6a with guanidine <lb/>moiety (side chain) of Arg37 at 2.66 and 2.49 Å, respec-<lb/>tively, whereas only oxygen atom of C=O-4 of 6b bind to <lb/>Arg37 at 1.83 Å, NH-6 of 6a and 6b with oxygen (back-<lb/>bone) of Pro35 at 1.78 and 2.18 Å, respectively, oxygen of <lb/>OH group of 6a with OH (side chain) of Tyr111 and hy-<lb/>drogen of HO with of 6a (side chain) of Ser138 at 1.80 and <lb/>2.10 Å, hydrogen of OH group of 6b with oxygen (back-<lb/>bone) of Ser138 at 1.66 Å, and hydrogen of OH group of 6c <lb/>whit OH (side chain) of Tyr111 and oxygen (backbone) of <lb/>Phe152 at 1.95 and 2.07 Å. <lb/>The phthalimide moiety displayed the following in-<lb/>teractions: For that of 6a π-alkyl with CH 2 (side chain) <lb/>of Pro35 (4.13 Å), CH 2 (side chain) of Arg37 (5.15 Å), and <lb/>π-π T-shaped (side chain) of Phe152 at 4.82 Å, for 6b and <lb/>6c a π-π T-shaped with the side chain of Tyr306 at 4.54 <lb/>and 4.53 Å, respectively. Phenyl moiety of 6b displayed <lb/>π-π stacking interaction with the side chain of Tyr111 at <lb/>4.61 Å. The hydrogen of NH of indole moiety of 6c showed <lb/>a hydrogen bond with oxygen (backbone) of Pro35 at <lb/>1.75 Å, and the indole moiety exhibited π-π T-shaped in-<lb/>teraction with (side chain) of Tyr111 at 5.91 (Figure 8). <lb/>The results showed that phthalimide moiety of 6a bound <lb/>with Ile34, Pro35, and Phe152, and that of 6b and 6c with <lb/>Tyr306, while phenyl moiety of TSA bind with Pro35 and <lb/>Phe152. The hydroxy group of these compounds bind with <lb/>Tyr111 (6a, 6c), Ser138 (6a, 6b), and Phe152 (6c), while <lb/>the hydroxamic moiety of TSA did not display interaction <lb/>in this pocket, but the inhibitor showed interactions with <lb/>the same amino acid residues by binding mode different to <lb/>those of the target compounds. Thus, compounds 6(a-c) <lb/>are promising for further studies. <lb/>5 | HDAC8 INHIBITORY ASSAY <lb/>It is known that several drugs have been identified to in-<lb/>hibit class I and/or class II histone deacetylases (HDACs), <lb/>of which Trichostatin A (TSA) is one of the well-known <lb/>HDAC inhibitors. However, little is known about the <lb/>effect of TSA on HDAC8, of which is the inhibition of <lb/>proliferation of Molt-4 cells which express HDAC8 (Jing <lb/>et al., 2006). Another study has been conducted to explore <lb/>whether the function of HDACs was modulated by TSA at <lb/>concentrations that block cancer cell viability by enzyme <lb/>activity assays in purified systems and in cell extracts. <lb/>TSA&apos;s effective killing dose of 400 nM fully inhibited <lb/>HDAC1 and HDAC2, and HDAC8 only partly activity, <lb/>however, 5 mM TSA fully eliminated its activity (Chang <lb/>et al., 2012). <lb/>The inhibitory activity of compounds 3(a-c), 5(a-c), <lb/>and 6(a-c) on HDAC8 was evaluated based on the results <lb/>obtained from the docking study because they presented <lb/>better values of ΔG and K d than 4(a-c), and even 4a did <lb/>not present interactions in the orthosteric site of HDAC8. <lb/>The in vitro inhibitory activity of target acetamides was <lb/>evaluated with the HDAC8 Fluorometric Drug Discovery <lb/>Kit, TSA as a control inhibitor included in the Kit. Table 5 <lb/>shows the IC 50 values, although 5(a-c) showed better <lb/>values of ΔG and K d from the docking study than 3(a-c), <lb/>both series exhibited almost the same inhibitory effect <lb/>in the range of 0.751-0.445 μM. Regarding compounds <lb/>6(a-c), that displayed better affinity in docking, 6a (IC 50 <lb/>of 28 nM) and 6b (IC 50 = 0.18 μM) revealed the best effect <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1382</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<body>inhibitory effect on HDAC8, except for 6c. Compound 6a <lb/>showed the best IC 50 slightly above the TSA. <lb/>6 | CONCLUSION <lb/>Twelve new acetamides and novel N-aminophalimides <lb/>derived from α-amino acids were selected for their syn-<lb/>thesis from docking study and were obtained in good <lb/>yields; they were characterized by 1 H and 13 C NMR, infra-<lb/>red, HRMS, and structures of 4a, 5a, 5b, 6a, and 6b were <lb/>confirmed by X-ray crystallography. The molecular dock-<lb/>ing results showed that all compounds, except 4a binds <lb/>in both pockets, and their orientation within HDAC8 <lb/>depended on the conformation in each site. In general, <lb/>acetamides without and with phthalimide moiety showed <lb/>interactions with the amino acid residues of the active site <lb/>and allosteric site, where binding modes were similar or <lb/>different to those displayed for TSA. Although only 3a and <lb/>6a displayed interaction with the Zn, all target acetamides <lb/>studied may be considered for further studies. According <lb/>to the inhibition assays, all the evaluated acetamides ex-<lb/>hibited inhibitory activity on HDAC8. Among them, 6a <lb/>(IC 50 = 28 nM) and 6b showed better enzymatic inhibitory, <lb/>where 6a showed the greatest effect, slightly less than <lb/>TSA (IC 50 = 26 nM). These results suggested that the tar-<lb/>get acetamides and N-aminophalimides may be promising <lb/>anticancer agents for further biological studies. <lb/></body>

			<div type="acknowledgement">ACKNOWLEDGMENTS <lb/>The authors thank Consejo Nacional de Ciencia y Tec-<lb/>nología (Conacyt-México) for the doctoral scholarship to <lb/>JEGM No. 283361. Authors also thank for the computing <lb/> time granted by LANCAD and Conacyt in the supercom-<lb/>puter Hybrid Cluster &quot;Xiuhcoatl&quot; at General Coordina-<lb/>tion of Information and Communications Technologies <lb/>(CGSTIC) of Cinvestav. The authors also thank Dr. Pa-<lb/>tricia Talamás-Rohana for allowing us to use the Thermo <lb/>Scientific Fluoroskan Ascent FL from the Department of <lb/>Infectomics and Molecular Pathogenesis at Cinvestav and <lb/></div>
				
			<body>Compd. <lb/>IC 50 <lb/>Compd. <lb/>IC 50 <lb/>Compd. <lb/>IC 50 <lb/>3a <lb/>0.751 ± 0.1406 5a <lb/>0.709 ± 0.034 <lb/>6a b <lb/>28 ± 1.9 <lb/>3b <lb/>0.491 ± 0.0902 5b <lb/>0.489 ± 0.071 <lb/>6b <lb/>0.180 ± 0.0311 <lb/>3c <lb/>0.543 ± 0.0613 5c <lb/>0.445 ± 0.015 <lb/>6c <lb/>8.812 ± 1.9130 <lb/>TSA b <lb/>26.160 ± 1.99 <lb/>a <lb/>Results expressed as the mean ± standard deviation of three separated determinations, p &lt; 0.05. <lb/>b Values given in nM. <lb/>T A B L E 5 IC 50 (μM) a values of 3(a-c), <lb/>5(a-c), 6(a-c) and TSA on HDAC8. <lb/>F I G U R E 8 Binding modes of <lb/>HDAC8-6(a-c): 6a-, 6b-, and 6c-O <lb/>represent binds of the compounds with <lb/>the amino acid residues in the orthosteric <lb/>site; 6a-, 6b-, and 6c-A represent the <lb/>binds in the allosteric site. Bindings were <lb/>hydrogen bonding (green dotted line), <lb/>hydrophobics π-π (purple dotted line), <lb/>π-alkyl (pink dotted line), and interactions <lb/>π-sulfur (orange dotted line). The zinc ion <lb/>is represented by an orange ball. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1383 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<div type="acknowledgement">also thank MSc. Juan Carlos Osorio-Trujillo Biol. José <lb/>Daniel Morales-Mora for their support in the development <lb/>of the enzymatic assays. We thank Ma. Teresa Cortez Pi-<lb/>casso for obtaining NMR spectra. Thank Marco Antonio <lb/>Leyva for his technical help in X-ray crystallography and <lb/>thanks for the experimental support from CNMN-IPN in <lb/>obtaining the HRMS spectra. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">FUNDING INFORMATION <lb/>None. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">CONFLICT OF INTEREST STATEMENT <lb/>None. <lb/></div>

			<div type="availability">DATA AVAILABILITY STATEMENT <lb/>I would like the availability of the data to be published <lb/>until the manuscript is accepted for publication. <lb/>ORCID <lb/>Teresa Mancilla Percino https://orcid. <lb/>org/0000-0002-4919-2985 <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>REFERENCES <lb/>Abdel-Aziza, A. A. M., El-Azaba, A. S., Ghiatyc, A. H., Gratterid, <lb/>P., Supurane, C. T., &amp; Nocentini, A. (2019). 4-Substituted ben-<lb/>zenesulfonamides featuring cyclic imides moieties exhibit po-<lb/>tent and isoform-selective carbonic anhydrase II/IX inhibition. <lb/>Bioorganic Chemistry, 83, 198-204. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>bioorg.2018.10.037 <lb/>Ahmed, H. E. A., Abdel-Salam, H. A., &amp; Shaker, M. A. (2016). <lb/>Synthesis, characterization, molecular modeling, and poten-<lb/>tial antimicrobial and anticancer activities of novel 2-amino <lb/>isoindoline-1,3-dione derivatives. Bioorganic Chemistry, 66, <lb/>1-11. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bioorg.2016.03.003 <lb/>Akgün, H., Karamelekoglu, I., Berk, B., Kurnaz, I., Saribiyik, G., <lb/>Öktem, S., &amp; Kocagöz, T. (2012). Synthesis and antimycobac-<lb/>terial activity of some phthalimide derivatives. Bioorganic <lb/>&amp; Medicinal Chemistry, 20(13), 4149-4154. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.bmc.2012.04.060 <lb/>Al-Salahi, R. A., Al-Omar, M. A., &amp; Amr, A. E. G. E. (2010). Synthesis <lb/>of chiral macrocyclic or linear pyridine carboxamides from <lb/>pyridine-2,6-dicarbonyl dichloride as antimicrobial agents. <lb/>Molecules, 15(9), 6588-6597. https://doi.org/10.3390/molec <lb/>ules1 5096588 <lb/>Balasubramanian, S., Ramos, J., Luo, W., Sirisawad, M., Verner, E., &amp; <lb/>Buggy, J. J. (2008). A novel histone deacetylase 8 (HDAC8)-specific <lb/>inhibitor PCI-34051 induces apoptosis in T-cell lymphomas. <lb/>Leukemia, 22(5), 1026-1034. https://doi.org/10.1038/leu.2008.9 <lb/>Banerjee, S., Adhikari, N., Amin, S. A., &amp; Jha, T. (2019). Histone <lb/>deacetylase 8 (HDAC8) and its inhibitors with selectivity to other <lb/>isoforms: An overview. European Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, <lb/>164, 214-240. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2018.12.039 <lb/>Bibian, M., El-Habnouni, S., Martinez, J., &amp; Fehrentz, J. A. <lb/>(2009). Enantioselective synthesis of N-protected α-amino <lb/>acid hydrazides. Synthesis, 7, 1180-1184. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1055/s-0028-1088013 <lb/>Blessing, R. H. (1995). An empirical correction for absorption an-<lb/>isotropy. Acta Crystallographica Section A: Foundations of <lb/>Crystallography, 51(1), 33-38. https://doi.org/10.1107/S0108 <lb/>76739 4005726 <lb/>Bondi, A. (1964). van der Waals volumes and radii. The Journal of <lb/>Physical Chemistry, 68(3), 441-445. https://doi.org/10.1021/ <lb/>j1007 85a001 <lb/>Brosse, N., Grandeury, A., &amp; Jamart-Grégoire, B. (2002). Original and <lb/>efficient method for the preparation of N-aminoamide pseu-<lb/>dodipeptides in high optical purity. Tetrahedron Letters, 43(11), <lb/>2009-2011. https://doi.org/10.1016/S0040 -4039(02)00119 -3 <lb/>Brosse, N., Pinto, M. F., &amp; Jamart-Grégoire, B. (2003). Preparation <lb/>of multiply protected alkylhydrazine derivatives by mitsunobu <lb/>and PTC approaches. European Journal of Organic Chemistry, <lb/>24, 4757-4764. https://doi.org/10.1002/ejoc.20030 0445 <lb/>Brunsteiner, M., &amp; Petukhov, P. A. (2012). Insights from compre-<lb/>hensive multiple receptor docking to HDAC8. Journal of <lb/>Molecular Modeling, 24, 3927-3939. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s0089 4-011-1297-8 <lb/>Brylinski, M. (2018). Aromatic interactions at the ligand-protein <lb/>interface: Implications for the development of docking scor-<lb/>ing functions. Chemical Biology &amp; Drug Design, 91(2), 380-390. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1111/cbdd.13084 <lb/>Chakrabarti, A., Melesina, J., Kolbinger, F. R., Oehme, I., Senger, <lb/>J., Witt, O., Sippl, W., &amp; Jung, M. (2016). Targeting histone <lb/>deacetylase 8 as a therapeutic approach to cancer and neurode-<lb/>generative diseases. Future Medicinal Chemistry, 8(13), 1609-<lb/>1634. https://doi.org/10.4155/fmc-2016-0117 <lb/>Chang, J., Varghese, D., Gillam, M., Peyton, M., Modi, B., Schiltz, R. <lb/>L., Girard, L., &amp; Martinez, E. D. (2012). Differential response <lb/>of cancer cells to HDAC inhibitors trichostatin a and depsi-<lb/>peptide. British Journal of Cancer, 106, 116-125. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/bjc.2011.532 <lb/>Copeland, R. A. (2000). Enzymes: A practical introduction to struc-<lb/>ture, mechanism, and data analysis (2nd ed.). WILEY-VCH, Ed. <lb/>Dassault Systèmes BIOVIA. (2019). Discovery studio visualizer, <lb/>V19.1.0.18287. Dassault Systèmes. <lb/>Dowling, D. P., Gantt, S. L., Gattis, S. G., Fierke, C. A., &amp; Christianson, <lb/>D. W. (2008). Structural studies of human histone deacetyl-<lb/>ase 8 and its site-specific variants complexed with substrate <lb/>and inhibitors. Biochemistry, 47, 13554-13563. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1021/bi801 610c <lb/>El-Helby, A. G. A., Ayyad, R. R., Sakr, H. M., Abdelrahim, A. <lb/>S., El-Adl, K., Sherbiny, F. S., Eissa, I. H., &amp; Khalifa, M. M. <lb/>(2017). Design, synthesis, molecular modeling and biological <lb/>evaluation of novel 2,3-dihydrophthalazine-1,4-dione deriva-<lb/>tives as potential anticonvulsant agents. Journal of Molecular <lb/>Structure, 1130, 333-351. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.molst <lb/>ruc.2016.10.052 <lb/>El-Zahabi, M. A., Gad, L. M., Bamanie, F. H., &amp; Al-Marzooki, Z. <lb/>(2012). Synthesis of new cyclic imides derivatives with po-<lb/>tential hypolipidemic activity. Medicinal Chemistry Research, <lb/>21(1), 75-84. https://doi.org/10.1007/s0004 4-010-9492-1 <lb/>Estiu, G., West, N., Mazitschek, R., Greenberg, E., Bradner, J. E., &amp; <lb/>Wiest, O. (2010). On the inhibition of histone deacetylase 8. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, 18(11), 4103-4110. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2010.03.080 <lb/>Fakhr, I. M., Amr, A. G. E., Sabry, N. M., &amp; Abdalah, M. M. (2008). <lb/>Anti-inflammatory and analgesic activities of newly synthe-<lb/>sized chiral peptide derivatives using (3-benzoyl-4,5-dioxo-2-p <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1384</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>henyl-pyrrolidin-1-yl)acetic acid ethylester as starting material. <lb/>Archiv der Pharmazie, 341(3), 174-180. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>ardp.20070 0158 <lb/>Falkenberg, K. J., &amp; Johnstone, R. W. (2014). Histone deacetylases <lb/>and their inhibitors in cancer, neurological diseases and im-<lb/>mune disorders. Nature Reviews Drug Discovery, 13, 673-691. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd4360 <lb/>Farrugia, L. J. (2012). WinGX and ORTEP for windows: An update. <lb/>Journal of Applied Crystallography, 45(4), 849-854. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1107/S0021 88981 2029111 <lb/>Felten, A. S., Dautrey, S., Bodiguel, J., Vanderesse, R., Didierjean, C., <lb/>Arrault, A., &amp; Jamart-Grégoire, B. (2008). Oligomerization of N-<lb/>aminodipeptides: To the synthesis of heterogeneous backbone <lb/>with 1:1 α:α-N-amino aminoacid residue patterns. Tetrahedron, <lb/>64(47), 10741-10753. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tet.2008.08.087 <lb/>Fontana, A., Cursaro, I., Carullo, G., Gemma, S., Butini, S., &amp; <lb/>Campiani, G. (2022). A therapeutic perspective of HDAC8 <lb/>in different diseases: An overview of selective inhibitors. <lb/>International Journal of Molecular Sciences, 23, 10014. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3390/ijms2 31710014 <lb/>Frisch, M. J., Trucks, G. W., Schlegel, H. B., Scuseria, G. E., Robb, M. <lb/>A., Cheeseman, J. R., Scalmani, G., Barone, V., Mennucci, B., <lb/>Petersson, G. A., Nakatsuji, H., Caricato, M., Li, X., Hratchian, <lb/>H. P., Izmaylov, A. F., Bloino, J., Zheng, G., Sonnenberg, J. L., <lb/>Hada, M., … Fox, D. J. (2013). Gaussian 09, Revision D.01. <lb/>Gallinari, P., Di Marco, S., Jones, P., Pallaoro, M., &amp; Steinkühler, C. <lb/>(2007). HDACs, histone deacetylation and gene transcription: <lb/>From molecular biology to cancer therapeutics. Cell Research, <lb/>17(3), 195-211. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.cr.7310149 <lb/>Gantt, S. M. L., Decroos, C., Lee, M. S., Gullett, L. E., Bowman, <lb/>C. M., Christianson, D. W., &amp; Fierke, C. A. (2016). General <lb/>base-general acid catalysis in human histone deacetylase 8. <lb/>Biochemistry, 55(5), 820-832. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.bioch <lb/>em.5b01327 <lb/>Gregoretti, I. V., Lee, Y. M., &amp; Goodson, H. V. (2004). Molecular <lb/>evolution of the histone deacetylase family: Functional impli-<lb/>cations of phylogenetic analysis. Journal of Molecular Biology, <lb/>338(1), 17-31. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.jmb.2004.02.006 <lb/>Harrison, I. F., &amp; Dexter, D. T. (2013). Epigenetic targeting of his-<lb/>tone deacetylase: Therapeutic potential in parkinson&apos;s dis-<lb/>ease? Pharmacology &amp; Therapeutics, 140(1), 34-52. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.pharm thera.2013.05.010 <lb/>Huang, W. J., Wang, Y. C., Chao, S. W., Yang, C. Y., Chen, L. C., Lin, <lb/>M. H., Hou, W. C., Chen, M. Y., Lee, T. L., Yang, P., &amp; Chang, <lb/>C. I. (2012). Synthesis and biological evaluation of ortho-aryl <lb/>N-hydroxycinnamides as potent histone deacetylase (HDAC) 8 <lb/>isoform-selective inhibitors. ChemMedChem, 7(10), 1815-1824. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1002/cmdc.20120 0300 <lb/>Ingham, O. J., Paranal, R. M., Smith, W. B., Escobar, R. A., Yueh, H., <lb/>Snyder, T., Porco, J. A., Bradner, J. E., &amp; Beeler, A. B. (2016). <lb/>Development of a potent and selective HDAC8 inhibitor. <lb/>ACS Medicinal Chemistry Letters, 7(10), 929-932. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1021/acsme dchem lett.6b00239 <lb/>Jing, H., Hongli, L., &amp; Yan, C. (2006). Effects of trichostatin a on <lb/>HDAC8 expression, proliferation and cell cycle of Molt-4 cells. <lb/>Journal of Huazhong University of Science and Technology, 26, <lb/>531-533. https://doi.org/10.1007/s1159 6-006-0511-x <lb/>Joo, D. H., Mok, J. S., Bae, G. H., Oh, S. E., Kang, J. H., &amp; Kim, C. <lb/>(2017). Colorimetric detection of Cu 2+ and fluorescent de-<lb/>tection of PO43-and S2-by a multifunctional chemosensor. <lb/>Industrial and Engineering Chemistry Research, 56(30), 8399-<lb/>8407. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.iecr.7b01115 <lb/>Kang, Y., Nian, H., Rajendran, P., Dashwood, W. M., Pinto, J. T., <lb/>Boardman, L. A., Thibodeau, S. N., Limburg, P. J., Löhr, C. <lb/>V., Bisson, W. H., Williams, D. E., Ho, E., &amp; Dashwood, R. H. <lb/>(2014). HDAC8 and STAT3 repress BMF gene activity in colon <lb/>cancer cells. Cell Death &amp; Disease, 5(10), 1-8. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/cddis.2014.422 <lb/>Kazantsev, A. G., &amp; Thompson, L. M. (2008). Therapeutic applica-<lb/>tion of histone deacetylase inhibitors for central nervous sys-<lb/>tem disorders. Nature Reviews Drug Discovery, 7(10), 854-868. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1038/nrd2681 <lb/>Krysko, A. A., Samoylenko, G. V., Polishchuk, P. G., Fonari, M. S., <lb/>Kravtsov, V. C., Andronati, S. A., Kabanova, T. A., Lipkowski, J., <lb/>Khristova, T. M., Kuz&apos;min, V. E., Kabanov, V. M., Krysko, O. L., &amp; <lb/>Varnek, A. A. (2013). Synthesis, biological evaluation, X-ray mo-<lb/>lecular structure and molecular docking studies of RGD mimet-<lb/>ics containing 6-amino-2,3-dihydroisoindolin-1-one fragment <lb/>as ligands of integrin ΑiIbβ3. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, <lb/>21(15), 4646-4661. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2013.05.019 <lb/>Lee, S., Shinji, C., Ogura, K., Shimizu, M., Maeda, S., Sato, M., <lb/>Yoshida, M., Hashimoto, Y., &amp; Miyachi, H. (2007). Design, syn-<lb/>thesis, and evaluation of isoindolinone-hydroxamic acid de-<lb/>rivatives as histone deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors. Bioorganic <lb/>&amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters, 17(17), 4895-4900. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2007.06.038 <lb/>Leite, A. C. L., Barbosa, F. F., Cardoso, M. V. D. O., Moreira, D. R. M., <lb/>Coêlho, L. C. D., Da Silva, E. B., Filho, G. B. D. O., De Souza, V. <lb/>M. O., Pereira, V. R. A., Reis, L. D. C., Ferreira, P. M. P., Pessoa, <lb/>C., Wanderley, A. G., Mota, F. V. B.&amp; da Silva, T. G. (2014). <lb/>Phthaloyl amino acids as anti-inflammatory and immunomod-<lb/>ulatory prototypes. Medicinal Chemistry Research, 23(4), 1701-<lb/>1708. https://doi.org/10.1007/s0004 4-013-0730-1 <lb/>Mallesha, N., Prahlada Rao, S., Suhas, R., &amp; Channe Gowda, D. (2012). <lb/>An efficient synthesis of tert-butyl ethers/esters of alcohols/ <lb/>amino acids using methyl tert-butyl ether. Tetrahedron Letters, <lb/>53(6), 641-645. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.tetlet.2011.11.108 <lb/>Mancilla, T., Luis, C., Zamudio Rivera, L., Beltran, H., &amp; Farfán, N. <lb/>(2001). Synthesis and characterization of new 2-substituted <lb/>isoindoline derivatives of α-amino acids. Organic Preparations <lb/>and Procedures International, 33, 341-349. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1080/00304 94910 9458247 <lb/>Mancilla-Percino, T., Correa-Basurto, J., Trujillo-Ferrara, J., Ramos-<lb/>Morales, F. R., Acosta Hernández, M. E., Cruz-Sánchez, J. S., <lb/>&amp; Saavedra-Vélez, M. (2010). Molecular modeling study of <lb/>Isoindolines as L-type Ca 2+ channel blockers by docking cal-<lb/>culations. Journal of Molecular Modeling, 16(8), 1377-1382. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s0089 4-010-0643-6 <lb/>Mancilla-Percino, T., Trejo-Muñoz, C. R., Díaz-Gandarilla, J. A., <lb/>Talamás-Rohana, P., Guzmán Ramírez, J. E., Cervantes, J., <lb/>&amp; Figueroa Ortíz, A. (2016). Isoindoline derivatives of α-<lb/>amino acids as cyclooxygenase 1 and 2 inhibitors. Archiv <lb/>der Pharmazie, 349(3), 175-185. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>ardp.20150 0372 <lb/>Maolanon, A. R., Madsen, A. S., &amp; Olsen, C. A. (2016). Innovative <lb/>strategies for selective inhibition of histone deacetylases. Cell <lb/>Chemical Biology, 23, 759-768. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.chemb <lb/>iol.2016.06.011 <lb/>Marek, M., Shaik, T. B., Heimburg, T., Chakrabarti, A., Lancelot, J., <lb/>Ramos Morales, E., Da Veiga, C., Kalinin, D., Melesina, J., Robaa, <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			| <page>1385 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>D., Schmidtkunz, K., Suzuki, T., Holl, R., Ennifar, E., Pierce, R. <lb/>J., Jung, M., Sippl, W., &amp; Romier, C. (2018). Characterization <lb/>of histone deacetylase 8 (HDAC8) selective inhibition reveals <lb/>specific active site structural and functional determinants. <lb/>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 61, 10000-10016. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1021/acs.jmedc hem.8b01087 <lb/>Marks, P. A., Miller, T., &amp; Richon, V. M. (2003). Histone deacetylases. <lb/>Current Opinion in Pharmacology, 3(4), 344-351. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/S1471 -4892(03)00084 -5 <lb/>Marks, P. A., Rifkind, R. A., Richon, V. M., Breslow, R., Miller, T., <lb/>&amp; Kelly, W. K. (2001). Histone deacetylases and cancer: Causes <lb/>and therapies. Nature Reviews Cancer, 1(3), 194-202. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1038/35106079 <lb/>Minucci, S., &amp; Pelicci, P. G. (2006). Histone deacetylase inhibitors <lb/>and the promise of epigenetic (and more) treatments for cancer. <lb/>Nature Reviews Cancer, 6(1), 38-51. https://doi.org/10.1038/ <lb/>nrc1779 <lb/>Morris, G. M., Huey, R., Lindstrom, W., Sanner, M. F., Belew, R. K., <lb/>Goodsell, D. S., &amp; Olson, A. J. (2009). Software news and up-<lb/>dates AutoDock4 and AutoDockTools4: Automated docking <lb/>with selective receptor flexibility. Journal of Computational <lb/>Chemistry, 30, 2785-2791. https://doi.org/10.1002/jcc.21256 <lb/>Nagarajan, S., Majumder, S., Sharma, U., Rajendran, S., Kumar, N., <lb/>Chatterjee, S., &amp; Singh, B. (2013). Synthesis and anti-angiogenic <lb/>activity of benzothiazole, benzimidazole containing phthalim-<lb/>ide derivatives. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters, 23(1), <lb/>287-290. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2012.10.106 <lb/>Nakagawa, M., Oda, Y., Eguchi, T., Aishima, S. I., Yao, T., Hosoi, F., <lb/>Basaki, Y., Ono, M., Kuwano, M., Tanaka, M., &amp; Tsuneyoshi, <lb/>M. (2007). Expression profile of class I histone deacetylases <lb/>in human cancer tissues. Oncology Reports, 18(4), 769-774. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.3892/or.18.4.769 <lb/>Nayab, P. S., Pulaganti, M., Chitta, S. K., &amp; Rahisuddin. (2015). A new <lb/>isoindoline based schiff base derivative as Cu(II) chemosensor: <lb/>Synthesis, photophysical, DNA binding and molecular docking <lb/>studies. Journal of Fluorescence, 25(6), 1763-1773. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1007/s1089 5-015-1664-4 <lb/>Neelarapu, R., Holzle, D. L., Velaparthi, S., Bai, H., Brunsteiner, <lb/>M., Blond, S. Y., &amp; Petukhov, P. A. (2011). Design, synthesis, <lb/>docking, and biological evaluation of novel diazide-containing <lb/>isoxazole-and pyrazole-based histone deacetylase probes. <lb/>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 54(13), 4350-4364. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1021/jm200 1025 <lb/>Oehme, I., Deubzer, H. E., Wegener, D., Pickert, D., Linke, J. P., Hero, <lb/>B., Kopp-Schneider, A., Westermann, F., Ulrich, S. M., Von <lb/>Deimling, A., &amp; Fischer, M. (2009). Histone deacetylase 8 in <lb/>neuroblastoma tumorigenesis. Clinical Cancer Research, 15(1), <lb/>91-99. https://doi.org/10.1158/1078-0432.CCR-08-0684 <lb/>Roche, J., &amp; Bertrand, P. (2016). Inside HDAC with HDAC inhibi-<lb/>tors. European Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 121, 451-483. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2016.05.047 <lb/>Rodríguez Uribe, G., Serafín Higuera, N., Bonilla, D. J., Trejo Muñoz, <lb/>C. R., Gariglio, V., &amp; Mancilla Percino, T. (2020). Métodos <lb/>para la prevención de opacidad capsular posterior mediante la <lb/>inhibición de las vías TGF-ß y WNT/ß-catenina por medio de <lb/>un inhibidor de HDAC. Instituto Mexicano de la Propiedad <lb/>Industrial. Título de patente No. 373069. MX/a/2014/002124. <lb/>Rodríguez-Uribe, G., Serafín-Higuera, N., Damian-Morales, G., <lb/>Cortés-Malagón, E. M., García-Hernández, V., Verdejo-Torres, <lb/>O., Campos-Blázquez, J. P., Trejo-Muñoz, C. R., Contreras, <lb/>R. G., Ocadiz-Delgado, R., Palacios-Reyes, C., Lambert, P. <lb/>F., Griep, A. E., Mancilla-Percino, T., Escobar-Herrera, J., <lb/>Álvarez-Ríos, E., Ugarte-Briones, C., Moreno, J., Gariglio, P., <lb/>&amp; Bonilla-Delgado, J. (2018). HPV16-E6 Oncoprotein acti-<lb/>vates TGF-β and Wnt/β-catenin pathways in the epithelium-<lb/>mesenchymal transition of cataracts in a transgenic mouse <lb/>model. BioMed Research International, 2018, 2847873. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1155/2018/2847873 <lb/>Santamaria-Herrera, M. A., Ríos-Pérez, E. B., De La Rosa, J. A. <lb/>M., García-Castañeda, M., Osornio-Garduño, D. S., Ramos-<lb/>Mondragón, R., Mancilla-Percino, T., &amp; Avila, G. (2016). <lb/>MDIMP, a novel cardiac Ca 2+ channel blocker with atrial se-<lb/>lectivity. European Journal of Pharmacology, 781, 218-228. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.ejphar.2016.04.027 <lb/>Santos, J. L., Yamasaki, P. R., Chin, C. M., Takashi, C. H., Pavan, F. <lb/>R., &amp; Leite, C. Q. F. (2009). Synthesis and in vitro anti myco-<lb/>bacterium tuberculosis activity of a series of phthalimide de-<lb/>rivatives. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, 17(11), 3795-3799. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2009.04.042 <lb/>Sharma, U., Kumar, P., Kumar, N., &amp; Singh, B. (2010). Recent ad-<lb/>vances in the chemistry of phthalimide analogues and their <lb/>therapeutic potential. Mini-Reviews in Medicinal Chemistry, <lb/>10(8), 678-704. https://doi.org/10.2174/13895 57107 91572442 <lb/>Sheldrick, G. M. (2015). Crystal structure refinement with SHELXL. <lb/>Acta Crystallographica Section C: Structural Chemistry, 71, 3-8. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1107/S2053 22961 4024218 <lb/>Shinji, C., Maeda, S., Imai, K., Yoshida, M., Hashimoto, Y., &amp; Miyachi, <lb/>H. (2006). Design, synthesis, and evaluation of cyclic amide/imide-<lb/>bearing hydroxamic acid derivatives as class-selective histone <lb/>deacetylase (HDAC) inhibitors. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, <lb/>14(22), 7625-7651. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2006.07.008 <lb/>Shinji, C., Nakamura, T., Maeda, S., Yoshida, M., Hashimoto, Y., <lb/>&amp; Miyachi, H. (2005). Design and synthesis of phthalimide-<lb/>type histone deacetylase inhibitors. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal <lb/>Chemistry Letters, 15(20), 4427-4431. https://doi.org/10.1016/j. <lb/>bmcl.2005.07.048 <lb/>Somoza, J. R., Skene, R. J., Katz, B. A., Mol, C., Ho, J. D., Jennings, <lb/>A. J., Luong, C., Arvai, A., Buggy, J. J., Chi, E., Tang, J., Sang, B. <lb/>C., Verner, E., Wynands, R., Leahy, E. M., Dougan, D. R., Snell, <lb/>G., Navre, M., Knuth, M. W., … Tari, L. W. (2004). Structural <lb/>snapshots of human HDAC8 provide insights into the class I <lb/>histone deacetylases. Structure, 12, 1325-1334. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.str.2004.04.012 <lb/>Song, S., Wang, Y., Xu, P., Yang, R., Ma, Z., Liang, S., &amp; Zhang, G. <lb/>(2015). The inhibition of histone deacetylase 8 suppresses pro-<lb/>liferation and inhibits apoptosis in gastric adenocarcinoma. <lb/>International Journal of Oncology, 47(5), 1819-1828. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.3892/ijo.2015.3182 <lb/>Struhl, K. (1998). Histone acetylation and transcriptional regulatory <lb/>mechanisms. Genes &amp; Development, 12(5), 599-606. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1101/gad.12.5.599 <lb/>Su, H., Altucci, L., &amp; You, Q. (2008). Competitive or noncompetitive, <lb/>that&apos;s the question: Research toward histone deacetylase inhib-<lb/>itors. Molecular Cancer Therapeutics, 7(5), 1007-1012. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1158/1535-7163.MCT-07-2289 <lb/>Suzuki, T., Matsuura, A., Kouketsu, A., Nakagawa, H., &amp; Miyata, <lb/>N. (2005). Identification of a potent non-hydroxamate his-<lb/>tone deacetylase inhibitor by mechanism-based drug design. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters, 15, 331-335. https:// <lb/>doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2004.10.074 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License <lb/></note>

			<page>1386</page> | <lb/>

			<note place="headnote">GUZMÁN RAMÍREZ and MANCILLA PERCINO <lb/></note>

			<listBibl>Suzuki, T., Ota, Y., Ri, M., Bando, M., Gotoh, A., Itoh, Y., Tsumoto, <lb/>H., Tatum, P. R., Mizukami, T., Nakagawa, H., Iida, S., Ueda, R., <lb/>Shirahige, K., &amp; Miyata, N. (2012). Rapid discovery of highly po-<lb/>tent and selective inhibitors of histone deacetylase 8 using click <lb/>chemistry to generate candidate libraries. Journal of Medicinal <lb/>Chemistry, 55(22), 9562-9575. https://doi.org/10.1021/jm300 <lb/>837y <lb/>Taha, T. Y., Aboukhatwa, S. M., Knopp, R. C., Ikegaki, N., <lb/>Abdelkarim, H., Neerasa, J., Lu, Y., Neelarapu, R., Hanigan, T. <lb/>W., Thatcher, G. R. J., &amp; Petukhov, P. A. (2017). Design, syn-<lb/>thesis, and biological evaluation of tetrahydroisoquinoline-<lb/>based histone deacetylase 8 selective inhibitors. ACS Medicinal <lb/>Chemistry Letters, 8(8), 824-829. https://doi.org/10.1021/acsme <lb/>dchem lett.7b00126 <lb/>Tandon, V. K., Maurya, H. K., Mishra, N. N., &amp; Shukla, P. K. <lb/>(2009). Design, synthesis and biological evaluation of novel <lb/>nitrogen and sulfur containing hetero-1,4-naphthoquinones <lb/>as potent antifungal and antibacterial agents. European <lb/>Journal of Medicinal Chemistry, 44(8), 3130-3137. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1016/j.ejmech.2009.03.006 <lb/>Tang, W., Luo, T., Greenberg, E. F., Bradner, J. E., &amp; Schreiber, S. L. <lb/>(2011). Discovery of histone deacetylase 8 selective inhibitors. <lb/>Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry Letters, 21(9), 2601-2605. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmcl.2011.01.134 <lb/>Tetsuhashi, M., Ishikawa, M., Hashimoto, M., Hashimoto, Y., &amp; <lb/>Aoyama, H. (2010). Development of tryptase inhibitors derived <lb/>from thalidomide. Bioorganic &amp; Medicinal Chemistry, 18(14), <lb/>5323-5338. https://doi.org/10.1016/j.bmc.2010.05.037 <lb/>Trejo Muñoz, C. R., Jiménez, E. M., Pinto-Almazán, R., Gandarilla, J. <lb/>A. D., Correa-Basurto, J., Trujillo-Ferrara, J. G., Guerra-Araiza, <lb/>C., Rohana, P. T., &amp; Percino, T. M. (2014). Effect of two series <lb/>of Isoindolines over HDAC8 activity and expression. Medicinal <lb/>Chemistry Research, 23(6), 3227-3234. https://doi.org/10.1007/ <lb/>s0004 4-013-0903-y <lb/>Uba, A. I., Weako, J., Keskin, Ö., Gürsoy, A., &amp; Yelekçi, K. (2019). <lb/>Examining the stability of binding modes of the co-crystallized <lb/>inhibitors of human HDAC8 by molecular dynamics simula-<lb/>tion. Journal of Biomolecular Structure &amp; Dynamics, 38, 1751-<lb/>1760. https://doi.org/10.1080/07391 102.2019.1615989 <lb/>Vannini, A., Volpari, C., Filocamo, G., Casavola, E. C., Brunetti, <lb/>M., Renzoni, D., Chakravarty, P., Paolini, C., De Francesco, R., <lb/>Gallinari, P., Steinkühler, C., &amp; Di Marco, S. (2004). Crystal <lb/>structure of a eukaryotic zinc-dependent histone deacetylase, <lb/>human HDAC8, complexed with a hydroxamic acid inhibi-<lb/>tor. Proceedings of the National Academy of Sciences, 101(42), <lb/>15064-15069. https://doi.org/10.1073/pnas.04046 03101 <lb/>Vannini, A., Volpari, C., Gallinari, P., Jhones, P., Mattu, M., Carfí, <lb/>A., De Francesco, R., Steinkühler, C., &amp; Di Marco, S. (2007). <lb/>Substrate binding to histone deacetylases as shown by the crys-<lb/>tal structure of the HDAC8-substrate complex. EMBO Reports, <lb/>8, 879-884. https://doi.org/10.1038/sj.embor.7401047 <lb/>Wang, G., Wang, X., Yu, H., Wei, S., Williams, N., Holmes, D. L., <lb/>Halfmann, R., Naidoo, J., Wang, L., Li, L., Chen, S., Harran, P., <lb/>Lei, X., &amp; Wang, X. (2013). Small-molecule activation of the trail <lb/>receptor DR5 in human cancer cells. Nature Chemical Biology, <lb/>9(2), 84-89. https://doi.org/10.1038/nchem bio.1153 <lb/>Wang, H., &amp; Dymock, B. W. (2009). New patented histone deacety-<lb/>lase inhibitors. Expert Opinion on Therapeutic Patents, 19(12), <lb/>1727-1757. <lb/>Wang, J., Sun, Y., Jiang, M. H., Hu, T. Y., Zhao, Y. J., Li, X., Wang, G., <lb/>Hao, K., &amp; Zhen, L. (2018). Iminium ion and N-hydroxyimide <lb/>as the surrogate components in dead-promoted oxidative Ugi <lb/>variant. The Journal of Organic Chemistry, 83(21), 13121-<lb/>13131. https://doi.org/10.1021/acs.joc.8b01868 <lb/>West, A. C., Johnstone, R. W., West, A. C., &amp; Johnstone, R. W. (2014). <lb/>New and emerging HDAC inhibitors for cancer treatment. The <lb/>Journal of Clinical Investigation, 124(1), 30-39. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1172/JCI69 738.30 <lb/>Witt, O., Deubzer, H. E., Milde, T., &amp; Oehme, I. (2009). HDAC family: <lb/>What are the cancer relevant targets? Cancer Letters, 277, 8-21. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1016/j.canlet.2008.08.016 <lb/>Wu, J., Du, C., Lv, Z., Ding, C., Cheng, J., Xie, H., Zhou, L., &amp; Zheng, <lb/>S. (2013). The up-regulation of histone deacetylase 8 pro-<lb/>motes proliferation and inhibits apoptosis in hepatocellular <lb/>carcinoma. Digestive Diseases and Sciences, 58(12), 3545-3553. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1007/s1062 0-013-2867-7 <lb/>Yang, F., Zhao, N., Ge, D., &amp; Chen, Y. (2019). Next-generation of <lb/>selective histone deacetylase inhibitors. RSC Advances, 9(34), <lb/>19571-19583. https://doi.org/10.1039/c9ra0 2985k <lb/>Zamudio Rivera, L. S., Carrillo, L., &amp; Mancilla, T. (1999). Syntheses and <lb/>characterization of 2-hydroxy-N-(2&apos;-hydroxyalkyl)acetamides. <lb/>Heteroatom Chemistry, 10(2), 153-158. https://doi.org/10.1002/ <lb/>(SICI)1098-1071(1999)10:2&lt;153::AID-HC9&gt;3.0.CO;2-0 <lb/>Zhang, L., Zhanga, J., Jiang, Q., Zhang, L., &amp; Song, W. (2018). Zinc <lb/>binding groups for histone deacetylase inhibitors. Journal of <lb/>Enzyme Inhibition and Medicinal Chemistry, 33(1), 714-721. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1080/14756 366.2017.1417274 <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="annex">SUPPORTING INFORMATION <lb/>Additional supporting information can be found online <lb/>in the Supporting Information section at the end of this <lb/>article. <lb/>How to cite this article: Guzmán Ramírez, J. E., <lb/>&amp; Mancilla Percino, T. (2023). Synthesis of N-<lb/>aminophalimides derived from α-amino acids: <lb/>Theoretical study to find them as HDAC8 <lb/>inhibitors by docking simulations and in vitro <lb/>assays. Chemical Biology &amp; Drug Design, 102, <lb/>1367-1386. https://doi.org/10.1111/cbdd.14323 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">17470285, 2023, 6, Downloaded from https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/doi/10.1111/cbdd.14323, Wiley Online Library on [18/06/2025]. See the Terms and Conditions (https://onlinelibrary.wiley.com/terms-and-conditions) on Wiley Online Library for rules of use; OA articles are governed by the applicable Creative Commons License </note>


	</text>
</tei>
