<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>RESEARCH ARTICLE <lb/>HupA, the main undecaprenyl pyrophosphate <lb/>and phosphatidylglycerol phosphate <lb/>phosphatase in Helicobacter pylori is essential <lb/>for colonization of the stomach <lb/>Elise Gasiorowski 1,2,3 , Rodolphe Auger 4 , Xudong Tian 4 , Samia Hicham 1,2 , <lb/>Chantal Ecobichon 1,2 , Sophie Roure 4 , Martin V. Douglass 5,6,7 , M. Stephen Trent 5,6,7 , <lb/>Dominique Mengin-Lecreulx ID <lb/>4 <lb/>, Thierry Touze ´4*, Ivo Gomperts Boneca ID <lb/>1,2 <lb/>* <lb/>1 Institut Pasteur, Unite ´biologie et ge ´ne ´tique de la paroi bacte ´rienne, 28, rue du Docteur Roux, Paris, <lb/>France, 2 INSERM, Groupe Avenir, Paris, France, 3 Universite ´Paris Descartes, Sorbonne Paris Cite ´, Paris, <lb/>France, 4 Institute for Integrative Biology of the Cell (I2BC), CEA, CNRS, Univ Paris-Sud, Universite ´Paris-<lb/>Saclay, Gif-sur-Yvette, France, 5 Department of Infectious Diseases, College of Veterinary Medicine, <lb/>University of Georgia, Georgia, United States of America, 6 Department of Microbiology, Franklin College of <lb/>Arts and Sciences, University of Georgia, Georgia, United States of America, 7 Center for Vaccines and <lb/>Immunology, University of Georgia, Georgia, United States of America <lb/>* thierry.touze@u-psud.fr (TT); bonecai@pasteur.fr (IGB) <lb/>Abstract <lb/>The biogenesis of bacterial cell-envelope polysaccharides requires the translocation, across <lb/>the plasma membrane, of sugar sub-units that are produced inside the cytoplasm. To this <lb/>end, the hydrophilic sugars are anchored to a lipid phosphate carrier (undecaprenyl phos-<lb/>phate (C 55 -P)), yielding membrane intermediates which are translocated to the outer face of <lb/>the membrane. Finally, the glycan moiety is transferred to a nascent acceptor polymer, <lb/>releasing the carrier in the &quot;inactive&quot; undecaprenyl pyrophosphate (C 55 -PP) form. Thus, <lb/>C 55 -P is generated through the dephosphorylation of C 55 -PP, itself arising from either de <lb/>novo synthesis or recycling. Two types of integral membrane C 55 -PP phosphatases were <lb/>described: BacA enzymes and a sub-group of PAP2 enzymes (type 2 phosphatidic acid <lb/>phosphatases). The human pathogen Helicobacter pylori does not contain BacA homologue <lb/>but has four membrane PAP2 proteins: LpxE, LpxF, HP0350 and HP0851. Here, we report <lb/>the physiological role of HP0851, renamed HupA, via multiple and complementary <lb/>approaches ranging from a detailed biochemical characterization to the assessment of its <lb/>effect on cell envelope metabolism and microbe-host interactions. HupA displays a dual <lb/>function as being the main C 55 -PP pyrophosphatase (UppP) and phosphatidylglycerol phos-<lb/>phate phosphatase (PGPase). Although not essential in vitro, HupA was essential in vivo for <lb/>stomach colonization. In vitro, the remaining UppP activity was carried out by LpxE in addi-<lb/>tion to its lipid A 1-phosphate phosphatase activity. Both HupA and LpxE have crucial roles <lb/>in the biosynthesis of several cell wall polysaccharides and thus constitute potential targets <lb/>for new therapeutic strategies. <lb/>PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/>1 / 24 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>a1111111111 <lb/>OPEN ACCESS <lb/>Citation: Gasiorowski E, Auger R, Tian X, Hicham <lb/>S, Ecobichon C, Roure S, et al. (2019) HupA, the <lb/>main undecaprenyl pyrophosphate and <lb/>phosphatidylglycerol phosphate phosphatase in <lb/>Helicobacter pylori is essential for colonization of <lb/>the stomach. PLoS Pathog 15(9): e1007972. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 <lb/>Editor: Mario F. Feldman, University of Alberta, <lb/>CANADA <lb/>Received: March 14, 2019 <lb/>Accepted: July 9, 2019 <lb/>Published: September 5, 2019 <lb/>Copyright: © 2019 Gasiorowski et al. This is an <lb/>open access article distributed under the terms of <lb/>the Creative Commons Attribution License, which <lb/>permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original <lb/>author and source are credited. <lb/>Data Availability Statement: All relevant data are <lb/>within the manuscript and its Supporting <lb/>Information files. <lb/>Funding: Funding from the National Institutes of <lb/>Health (NIH; grants AI129940 and AI38576; https:// <lb/>www.nih.gov/) to M. Stephen Trent is gratefully <lb/>acknowledged. This study has received funding <lb/>from the French Government&apos;s Investissement <lb/>d&apos;Avenir program, Laboratoire d&apos;Excellence <lb/>&quot;Integrative Biology of Emerging Infectious <lb/>Author summary <lb/>Helicobacter pylori colonizes the human&apos;s gastric mucosa and infects around 50% of the <lb/>world&apos;s population. This pathogen is responsible for chronic gastritis, peptic ulcers and in <lb/>worst cases leads to gastric cancer. It has been classified as a class I carcinogen by the <lb/>World Health Organization in 1994. Here, we show that HP0851, renamed HupA, is the <lb/>major undecaprenyl pyrophosphate (C 55 -PP) phosphatase (UppP) and the major phos-<lb/>phatidylglycerol phosphate phosphatase (PGPase). This enzyme is also involved in cat-<lb/>ionic antimicrobial peptide (CAMP) resistance to which H. pylori hupA mutant shows an <lb/>increased sensitivity (4 fold). This mutant was unable to colonize the stomach in mouse <lb/>model of infection showing that even if hupA was not essential in vitro, this gene was <lb/>essential in vivo. Both HupA and LpxE have crucial roles in the biosynthesis of several cell <lb/>wall polysaccharides and thus constitute potential targets for new therapeutic strategies. <lb/></front>

			<body>Introduction <lb/>The biogenesis of many bacterial cell-envelope polysaccharides (i.e., peptidoglycan (PGN), <lb/>lipopolysaccharides (LPS), teichoic acids, enterobacterial common antigen) requires the trans-<lb/>location, across the cytoplasmic membrane, of glycan units that are produced inside the cyto-<lb/>plasm [1]. Therefore, the hydrophilic sugars must be anchored to a lipid carrier (undecaprenyl <lb/>phosphate (C 55 -P)), yielding membrane intermediates which are translocated to the outer face <lb/>of the membrane [2]. In PGN biosynthesis, these intermediates are finally cross-linked by <lb/>transglycosylase and transpeptidase activities to a nascent acceptor polymer. These polymeri-<lb/>zation reactions release the lipid carrier in an &quot;inactive&quot; undecaprenyl pyrophosphate form <lb/>(C 55 -PP) which must be recycled to participate in new rounds of cell-envelope polysaccharides <lb/>biosynthesis. <lb/>C 55 -P originates from the dephosphorylation of C 55 -PP, itself arising from either (i) cyto-<lb/>plasmic de novo synthesis by condensation of eight isopentenyl pyrophosphate (C 5 -PP) mole-<lb/>cules with one farnesyl pyrophosphate (C 15 -PP) catalyzed by the essential C 55 -PP synthase <lb/>(UppS) [3] or (ii) recycling [4] when it is released at the periplasmic side of the membrane. <lb/>Two unrelated families of integral membrane proteins exhibiting C 55 -PP phosphatase (UppP) <lb/>activity were identified: BacA and members of the PAP2 (type 2 phosphatidic acid phospha-<lb/>tase) super-family. Escherichia coli cells possess four UppPs: BacA enzyme which accounts for <lb/>75% of UppP activity and three PAP2 enzymes (PgpB, YbjG and LpxT) which ensure the <lb/>remaining activity [5]. The plurality of UppPs as observed in E. coli and Bacillus subtilis [6] <lb/>seems to be shared by most of the bacteria as suggested by a search for homologues, raising the <lb/>question of the role of such a multiplicity. The simultaneous inactivation of bacA, ybjG and <lb/>pgpB is lethal in E. coli whereas any single or double deletions had no effect on bacterial <lb/>growth. Overexpression of BacA, PgpB or YbjG resulted in bacitracin resistance, and an <lb/>increase of the UppP activity contained in membrane extracts [7]. Bacitracin is an antibiotic <lb/>produced by Bacillus licheniformis [8] which strongly binds C 55 -PP, thereby inhibiting its <lb/>dephosphorylation and leading to an arrest of PGN biosynthesis. When overexpressed, the <lb/>UppP enzymes likely compete with the bacitracin for C 55 -PP binding, thus favoring its <lb/>dephosphorylation. LpxT was not able to sustain growth of the triple bacA-ybjG-pgpB mutant <lb/>and its overexpression did not lead to any bacitracin resistance suggesting that LpxT displays <lb/>another function. Nevertheless, LpxT was shown to catalyze the transfer of C 55 -PP distal phos-<lb/>phate group onto lipid A, the lipid moiety of LPS, yielding C 55 -P and a pyrophosphorylated <lb/>form of lipid A [9]. In addition to its UppP activity, PgpB is involved in phospholipids <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<front>Diseases&quot; (grant n˚ANR-10-LABX-62-IBEID; http:// <lb/>www.agence-nationale-recherche.fr/ <lb/>investissements-d-avenir/). This work was <lb/>supported by the Agence National de la Recherche <lb/>(ANR; grant n˚ANR-11-BSV3-0002; http://www. <lb/>agence-nationale-recherche.fr/) and DIM Malinf <lb/>(grant n˚dim140053; http://www.dim-malinf.org/) <lb/>to Dominique Mengin-Lecreulx and Ivo G. Boneca. <lb/>Elise Gasiorowski was supported by a fellowship <lb/>from the Fondation pour la Recherche Me ´dicale <lb/>(FRM; fellowship FDT20170436808; https://www. <lb/>frm.org/en). The funders had no role in study <lb/>design, data collection and analysis, decision to <lb/>publish, or preparation of the manuscript. <lb/>Competing interests: The authors have declared <lb/>that no competing interests exist. <lb/></front>

			<body>biosynthesis via the hydrolysis of phosphatidylglycerol phosphate (PGP) to form phosphatidyl-<lb/>glycerol (PG) [10]. In E. coli, PgpA and PgpC are two additional integral membrane enzymes <lb/>sharing the latter function. It has been shown that the co-inactivation of the three PGP phos-<lb/>phatases leads to a lethal phenotype [11]. Topology and structural analyses of PAP2 enzymes <lb/>from E. coli and B. subtilis showed that these enzymes exhibit their active site at the interface <lb/>between the plasma membrane and the periplasmic space, suggesting they are rather involved <lb/>in C 55 -PP recycling [6,12,13]. <lb/>More recently, the structure of BacA from E. coli was also resolved [14,15] showing here <lb/>again an enzyme with its active site residues accessible from the periplasmic side. Nevertheless, <lb/>the unique structure of BacA was reminiscent of that of transporters or channels raising the <lb/>possibility that BacA may have alternate active sites on either side of the membrane and/or <lb/>may function as a flippase allowing complete recycling of C 55 -P. <lb/>Helicobacter pylori is a microaerophilic, spiral-shaped, flagellated, Gram-negative bacte-<lb/>rium that colonizes the human&apos;s gastric mucosa [16]. This pathogen is responsible of chronic <lb/>gastritis and peptic ulcers [17] and is a risk factor for gastric cancer. It has been classified as a <lb/>class I carcinogen by the World Health Organization in 1994. In contrast to E. coli, H. pylori <lb/>does not contain a BacA protein but has four PAP2 enzymes: HP0021 (LpxE), HP0350, <lb/>HP0851 and HP1580 (LpxF). LpxE and LpxF have been shown to be involved in LPS modifica-<lb/>tions. The lipid A structure of H. pylori is unique and constitutively modified. LpxE is respon-<lb/>sible for the removal of the lipid A 1-phosphate group that is required for the further addition <lb/>of a phosphoethanolamine (PE) group at the same position [18]. LpxF is a lipid A 4&apos;-phosphate <lb/>phosphatase. Both modifications increase the net positive charge of the lipid A, which then <lb/>confers cationic antimicrobial peptide (CAMP) resistance and escape to the host innate <lb/>immune system, thereby allowing H. pylori to survive in the gastric mucosa [19]. The aim of <lb/>this study was to decipher the physiological role of the multiple PAP2 enzymes from H. pylori. <lb/>We describe that HP0851, renamed HupA, is the main UppP but is also involved in phospho-<lb/>lipid biosynthesis by catalyzing the dephosphorylation of PGP in PG. In addition, we show <lb/>that HupA has a role in CAMP resistance and is essential for colonization of the mouse stom-<lb/>ach. In a global context of increasing resistance to antibiotics, finding new potential therapeu-<lb/>tic targets is crucial especially against H. pylori, which colonizes half of the world&apos;s population <lb/>and is classified by the World Health Organization as a priority 2 pathogen regarding antibi-<lb/>otic resistance. A better understanding of essential metabolic pathways, and of the enzymes <lb/>involved in such processes, could lead to the development of new antibacterials. <lb/>Results <lb/>Purification of PAP2 proteins and determination of their UppP activities <lb/>To characterize the PAP2 enzymes from H. pylori (LpxE, HP0350, HP0851 and LpxF), the cor-<lb/>responding genes were cloned on the pTrcHis30 expression vector under the control of a <lb/>strong IPTG-inducible promoter (Table 1). The recombinant N-terminally His-tagged pro-<lb/>teins were overproduced in E. coli C43(DE3) cells. The integral membrane proteins were <lb/>extracted from membranes via their solubilization with n-dodecyl-β-D-maltoside (DDM) <lb/>detergent and the PAP2 proteins were purified by affinity chromatography using Ni 2+ -NTA <lb/>agarose beads (Materials and Methods). Due to the difficulty in getting high expression levels <lb/>of these membrane proteins in E. coli, they could not be purified to homogeneity. Nevertheless, <lb/>LpxE, HP0350 and HP0851 were enriched to a high level as judged from SDS-PAGE analysis <lb/>(Fig 1A), while LpxF could not be visualized by Coomassie blue staining. However, LpxF was <lb/>in the purified samples as confirmed by western blot analysis (Fig 1B). We then measured the <lb/>UppP activities present in these purified solutions. Considering the niche of H. pylori, which <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>Table 1. Bacterial strains and plasmids. <lb/>Strains <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Resistance a Reference <lb/>E. coli <lb/>DH5α <lb/>F -endA1 glnV44 thi-1 recA1 relA1 gyrA96 deoR nupG purB20 φ80dlacZΔM15 Δ(lacZYA-argF)U169, <lb/>hsdR17(r K <lb/>-<lb/>m K <lb/>+ ), λ -<lb/>Life Science <lb/>Technologies <lb/>C43(DE3) <lb/>F -ompT gal dcm hsdS B (r B <lb/>-m B <lb/>-)(DE3) <lb/>Avidis <lb/>BWPGPTs <lb/>BW25113 ΔpgpA ΔpgpC ΔpgpB::Cm + pMAKkanpgpB <lb/>Cm, Kan <lb/>[6] <lb/>BWTsbacA <lb/>BW25113 ΔbacA ΔybjG ΔpgpB::Kan + pMAKbacA <lb/>Cm, Kan <lb/>[7] <lb/>H. pylori <lb/>HP-1 <lb/>N6 <lb/>[20] <lb/>HP-2 <lb/>N6 lpxE::Gm <lb/>Genta <lb/>This work <lb/> HP-3 <lb/>N6 hp0350::Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-4 <lb/>N6 lpxF::Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-13 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-5 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-7 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 bacA <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-8 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 lpxT <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-9 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 pgpB <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-10 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 ybjG <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-14 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 lpxE <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-15 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 hp0350 <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-16 <lb/>N6 pILL2150 lpxF <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>N6 +pILL2157 bacA N6 pILL2157 bacA <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>N6 +pILL2157 lpxT N6 pILL2157 lpxT <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>N6 +pILL2157 pgpB N6 pILL2157 pgpB <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>N6 +pILL2157 ybjG N6 pILL2157 ybjG <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-22 <lb/>X47-2AL <lb/>[21] <lb/>HP-50 <lb/>X47 hupA::Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-37 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km pILL2150 lpxE <lb/>Kan, Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-38 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km pILL2150 hp0350 <lb/>Kan, Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-39 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km pILL2150 hupA <lb/>Kan, Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-40 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km pILL2150 lpxF <lb/>Kan, Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-33 <lb/>N6 hupA::Km pILL2150 <lb/>Kan, Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>HP-49 <lb/>N6 pgpA::Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>Plasmids <lb/>Topo TAΔlpxE:Gm <lb/>Genta <lb/>This work <lb/>Topo TAΔlpxE:Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>Topo TAΔhp0350: <lb/>Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>Topo TAΔhupA:Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>Topo TAΔlpxF:Km <lb/>Kan <lb/>This work <lb/>pTrcHis30 lpxE <lb/>Amp <lb/>This work <lb/>pTrcHis30 hp0350 <lb/>Amp <lb/>This work <lb/>pTrcHis30 hupA <lb/>Amp <lb/>This work <lb/>pTrcHis30 lpxF <lb/>Amp <lb/>This work <lb/>pTrcHis30 pgpA <lb/>Amp <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 lpxE <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 hp0350 <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 hupA <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 lpxF <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>(Continued ) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>ranges from the human stomach with an acidic pH to the epithelial interphase with a neutral <lb/>pH, we measured enzymatic activities on a large range of pHs (Fig 1C). <lb/>The uncharacterized HP0350 protein did not catalyze C 55 -PP dephosphorylation even <lb/>under prolonged incubation time and high protein concentration. LpxE displayed an UppP <lb/>activity of 900 nmol/min/mg at an optimal pH of 7.4, while HP0851 exhibited a 6.7-fold higher <lb/>UppP activity of 6039 nmol/min/mg at an optimal pH of 5. LpxE displayed UppP activity in <lb/>vitro in addition to its role as lipid A 1-phosphate phosphatase [19]. Considering the highest <lb/>activity of HP0851, this protein may account for a large part of C 55 -P (re)generation in vivo. <lb/>LpxF was shown to act as a lipid A 4&apos;-phosphate phosphatase [19]. In this study, we also <lb/>detected a low UppP activity for LpxF (Table 2 and Fig 1C). This activity is unlikely to arise <lb/>from contaminants since HP0350, which was purified using the same methodology, exhibited <lb/>no activity as compared to LpxF. <lb/>HP0851 accounts for more than 90% of the UppP activity <lb/>To further address the contribution of each PAP2 protein in the global UppP activity in H. <lb/>pylori, we generated the four corresponding single mutants in H. pylori N6. All four mutants <lb/>were readily obtained showing that none of these proteins is essential for survival of H. pylori <lb/>in vitro. We prepared DDM-solubilized membrane extracts from exponentially growing wild-<lb/>type and mutant cells and we measured the residual UppP activity present in these extracts <lb/>(Fig 2). The UppP activities present in membranes of hp0350, lpxE and lpxF single mutants <lb/>and wild-type strain were very similar. In contrast, the UppP activity decreased in hp0851 <lb/>membranes to about 10% of residual activity as compared to the wild-type. Thus, these data <lb/>confirmed the major contribution of HP0851 in C 55 -PP recycling in C 55 -P. <lb/>Only LpxE and HP0851 complement the E. coli conditionally UppP <lb/>deficient strain <lb/>The simultaneous inactivation of bacA, pgpB and ybjG is lethal in E. coli. The BWTsbacA strain <lb/>is a thermosensitive conditional triple mutant (ΔbacA, ΔybjG, ΔpgpB) containing an ectopic <lb/>copy of bacA on a plasmid whose replication is impaired at 42˚C [7]. This mutant accumulates <lb/>soluble PGN precursors and lyses after a shift from 30˚C to 42˚C, due to the depletion of the <lb/>pool of C 55 -P that arrests cell-wall synthesis. The ability of the PAP2 proteins from H. pylori to <lb/>restore the growth of BWTsbacA at the restrictive temperature was tested using the <lb/>pTrcHis30-based plasmids previously used for protein purification (Table 3). The hp0350 <lb/>gene was unable to complement BWTsbacA strain even in the presence of 1 mM IPTG. The <lb/>Table 1. (Continued) <lb/>Strains <lb/>Genotype <lb/>Resistance a Reference <lb/>pILL2150 bacA <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 lpxT <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 pgpB <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2150 ybjG <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2157 bacA <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2157 lpxT <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2157 pgpB <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>pILL2157 ybjG <lb/>Cm <lb/>This work <lb/>(a) Genta or Gm, Kan or Km, Cm and Amp: gentamycin, kanamycin, chloramphenicol and ampicillin resistance cassettes, respectively. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>lpxF gene was also unable to complement in the absence of inducer and was found to be toxic <lb/>in the presence of IPTG as no growth was observed either at 30˚C or at 42˚C. In contrast, lpxE <lb/>and hp0851 genes complemented BWTsbacA without the need of inducer, indicating that a <lb/>basal level of the corresponding proteins allows a supply of C 55 -P that is appropriate for opti-<lb/>mal growth of E. coli. The overproduction of LpxE and LpxF in E. coli, due to the addition of <lb/>IPTG, was lethal possibly due: 1) to interference with LPS biosynthesis, since the modifications <lb/>Fig 1. PAP2 proteins purification and effect of the pH on their UppP activity. The N-terminal His-tagged PAP2 proteins were purified on Ni 2+ -NTA-agarose beads <lb/>as detailed in Materials and Methods, and 10 μL aliquots of the elution fractions were analyzed by SDS-PAGE. The proteins were revealed either (A) by Coomassie blue <lb/>staining or (B) by Western blotting using anti�His tag antibody conjugated to the horseradish peroxidase (C) UppP phosphatase activity present in the purified solutions <lb/>was determined at different pH (from pH 3 to pH 11). LpxE (black), HP0350 (blue), HP0851 (HupA; brown) and LpxF (red) The values are also reported in Table 2. The <lb/>observed molecular weight of recombinant proteins are consistent with their calculated molecular weight: LpxE (21,2 kDa), HP0350 (24,5 kDa), HupA (25,8 kDa) and <lb/>LpxF (24,6 kDa). <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g001 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>they catalyze do not normally exist in E. coli and likely generate cytotoxicity, and/or 2) to accu-<lb/>mulation of large amounts of membrane proteins. These complementation assays perfectly <lb/>corroborate the previous biochemical data, further demonstrating that LpxE and HP0851 act <lb/>as the major and perhaps the sole C 55 -PP phosphatases in H. pylori. Hence, we renamed <lb/>HP0851 to HupA (Helicobacter UppP and PGPase A). <lb/>The simultaneous inactivation of lpxE and hupA is lethal <lb/>To address whether LpxE and HupA are the only C 55 -PP phosphatases in H. pylori, we <lb/>attempted to construct a lpxE/hupA double mutant. However, we failed to generate this strain <lb/>suggesting that co-inactivation of both genes is lethal. We then performed transformation effi-<lb/>ciency assays to test the capacity of each PAP2 from H. pylori to complement this apparent <lb/>lethality. We generated four strains deleted for hupA and carrying a copy of one PAP2 encod-<lb/>ing gene under the control of an IPTG-inducible promoter on the pILL2150 vector. We then <lb/>transformed these cells with the Topo TAΔlpxE plasmid in order to replace lpxE by a gentamy-<lb/>cin resistance cassette. The transformed H. pylori population was diluted and spread on nor-<lb/>mal (total number of bacteria) or selective (ΔlpxE recombinants) plates to measure the <lb/>transformation efficiency expressed in cfu/μg of Topo TAΔlpxE plasmid (Table 4). LpxF and <lb/>HP0350 were unable to complement the lpxE/hupA double mutant as no recombinant was <lb/>obtained even in the presence of IPTG. In contrast, LpxE and HupA complemented the double <lb/>mutant in the presence of IPTG. These data excluded LpxF and HP0350 as bona fide UppP <lb/>and confirm that only LpxE and HupA are major UppPs in H. pylori. <lb/>HupA is involved in resistance to CAMPs <lb/>H. pylori infects the stomach and persists in the mucosa during years due to the expression of <lb/>multiple virulence factors. Persistence also requires a resistance towards CAMPs, which are <lb/>secreted by the host [22]. To evaluate the involvement of PAP2 proteins in CAMPs resistance, <lb/>Table 2. UppP activity of H. pylori PAP2 enzymes. <lb/>UppP specific activity (nmol/min/mg) <lb/>pH <lb/>LpxE <lb/>HP0350 <lb/>HP0851 (HupA) <lb/>LpxF <lb/>3 <lb/>10 <lb/>ND <lb/>131 <lb/>30.8 <lb/>4 <lb/>13.8 <lb/>ND <lb/>1227 <lb/>97.2 <lb/>5 <lb/>21.3 <lb/>ND <lb/>6039 <lb/>130.3 <lb/>6 <lb/>291.3 <lb/>ND <lb/>4616 <lb/>97.5 <lb/>7 <lb/>671.3 <lb/>ND <lb/>3755 <lb/>91.8 <lb/>7 <lb/>735 <lb/>ND <lb/>4157 <lb/>84.8 <lb/>7.4 <lb/>900 <lb/>ND <lb/>3493 <lb/>71.5 <lb/>8 <lb/>492.5 <lb/>ND <lb/>2528 <lb/>48.8 <lb/>9 <lb/>285 <lb/>ND <lb/>1180 <lb/>28.7 <lb/>9 <lb/>76.3 <lb/>ND <lb/>974 <lb/>20.5 <lb/>10 <lb/>0 <lb/>ND <lb/>159 <lb/>9 <lb/>11 <lb/>8.8 <lb/>ND <lb/>19 <lb/>4.2 <lb/>The enzymatic activity was measured in the presence of 50 μM of [ 14 C]C 55 -PP substrate and an appropriate amount <lb/>of enzyme to obtain less than 30% of hydrolysis. Buffering of the reaction mixture was obtained with sodium acetate <lb/>(pH 3-7), Tris-HCl (pH 7-9) or sodium carbonate (pH 9-11). The C 55 -P product and the substrate were separated <lb/>by TLC and further quantified by radioactivity counting. Values represent the mean of at least three individual <lb/>experiments (the S.D. being within 15% of the presented values). ND, no detectable activity. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t002 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>we used polymyxin B as a surrogate for CAMPs [23]. The modifications generated by LpxE <lb/>and LpxF through their lipid A 1-and 4&apos;-phosphate phosphatase activities promote resistance <lb/>to different CAMPs and they further confer host innate immune system evasion [19]. We con-<lb/>firmed the increased sensitivity already described in [19] for the lpxE and lpxF mutants (32-<lb/>and 128-fold, respectively, Table 5). The hp0350 mutant did not show any increase of poly-<lb/>myxin B sensitivity, while the sensitivity of hupA mutant increased by four-fold as compared <lb/>Fig 2. UppP activity in membranes of H. pylori. The UppP activity of the wild-type and the four single mutants of H. <lb/>pylori N6 strain was measured and normalized by the quantity of proteins in each membrane extracts. The relative <lb/>activities as compared to the wild-type strain membrane extracts are indicated. Each value is the mean of three <lb/>independent measurements. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g002 <lb/>Table 3. Functional complementation of E. coli BWTsbacA conditional strain by PAP2 encoding genes from H. <lb/>pylori. <lb/>E. coli BWTsbacA <lb/>CFU/mL <lb/>30˚C <lb/>42˚C <lb/>30˚C <lb/>+IPTG 1mM <lb/>42˚C <lb/>+IPTG 1mM <lb/>-<lb/>782 <lb/>0 <lb/>876 <lb/>1 <lb/>+pTrc His30 lpxE <lb/>229 <lb/>222 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pTrc His30 hp0350 <lb/>396 <lb/>2 <lb/>354 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pTrc His30 hupA <lb/>265 <lb/>219 <lb/>186 <lb/>172 <lb/>+pTrc His30 lpxF <lb/>180 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>The E. coli thermosensitive strain was transformed with the pTrcHis30-based plasmids and aliquots were plated onto <lb/>two ampicillin-containing 2YT agar plates incubated at either 30˚C or 42˚C. The CFU were counted after 24 h <lb/>incubation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>to the wild-type strain. The polymyxin B sensitivity of hupA mutant was fully restored upon <lb/>complementation with an ectopic copy of hupA gene. <lb/>HupA has no effect on lipid A structure <lb/>As already mentioned, LpxE and LpxF modify lipid A structure in H. pylori. We then investi-<lb/>gated whether the four-fold decrease in polymyxin B resistance of hupA mutant was a conse-<lb/>quence of an altered lipid A structure. LpxE exhibits UppP activity while also acting as a lipid <lb/>A 1-phosphate phosphatase. We hypothesized that, in the absence of HupA, LpxE has to cope <lb/>with this very low UppP activity. This hypothesis predicted the presence of a mixture of lipid A <lb/>species in hupA mutant with lipid A 1-phosphate together with the usual lipid A 1-PE. The <lb/>resulting rise in net negative charges at the outermost surface of the bacterium could then <lb/>account for the increased sensitivity towards polymyxin B. <lb/>To test this hypothesis, the lipid A from wild-type, hupA mutant and hupA mutant trans-<lb/>formed with pILL2150 hupA plasmid were extracted and analyzed by mass spectrometry. As <lb/>shown in Fig 3A-3C, the main form of lipid A present in wild-type strain was the tetra-acyl-<lb/>ated lipid A with a PE group at position 1 and no phosphate group at position 4&apos;, as described <lb/>[19]. Two additional minor species were observed, a penta-acylated lipid A with PE at position <lb/>1 and no phosphate at position 4&apos; and a hexa-acylated lipid A with PE at position 1 and with <lb/>phosphate at position 4&apos;. In hupA mutant and its complemented derivative, the lipid A profiles <lb/>were very similar to that of the wild-type strain. We then concluded that the moderate decrease <lb/>in polymyxin B resistance in hupA strain was independent of the lipid A structure. In parallel, <lb/>we confirmed the roles of LpxE and LpxF (Fig 3E and 3F) while we show that HP0350 is not <lb/>involved in lipid A modifications (Fig 3D). <lb/>Table 4. Complementation of lpxE/hupA double mutant with an ectopic copy of H. pylori PAP2 encoding genes. <lb/>Helicobacter pylori N6 <lb/>hupA::Km <lb/>Transformation rate <lb/>(transformants/cfu/μg TopoTAΔlpxE) <lb/>-ITPG <lb/>+IPTG (1mM) <lb/>+pILL2150 empty <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2150 lpxE <lb/>0 <lb/>1.44E-05 <lb/>+pILL2150 hp0350 <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2150 hupA <lb/>0 <lb/>1.16E-05 <lb/>+pILL2150 lpxF <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>Quantification of lpxE gene inactivation in ΔhupA single mutant transformed with plasmids expressing one PAP2 <lb/>from H. pylori. The transformation rates were measured in the presence and in the absence of IPTG. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t004 <lb/>Table 5. Minimal Inhibitory Concentrations (MIC) of polymyxin B of H. pylori strains. <lb/>Helicobacter pylori N6 <lb/>Polymyxin B <lb/>Fold change vs <lb/>WT strain <lb/>WT <lb/>2048 <lb/>-<lb/>lpxE::Gm <lb/>64 <lb/>32 <lb/>lpxF::Km <lb/>16 <lb/>128 <lb/>hp0350::Km <lb/>2048 <lb/>1 <lb/>hupA::Km <lb/>512 <lb/>4 <lb/>hupA::Km + pILL2157 hupA <lb/>2048 <lb/>1 <lb/>MICs are reported as μg/ml and are the average of three experiments. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>HupA is essential for stomach colonization <lb/>The maximal UppP activity of LpxE was reached at pH 7.4 (Fig 1) and all complementation <lb/>assays were performed at neutral pH. H. pylori resumes growth in acidic media only after <lb/>Fig 3. Mass spectrometry analysis of lipid A. Lipid A was isolated from wild-type (A), hupA (B), hp0350 (D), lpxE (E) and lpxF (F) mutant and complemented cells (C) <lb/>in strain N6 and analyzed by MALDI-TOF mass spectrometry in the negative-ion mode. The corresponding lipid A structure of the most abundant species is depicted <lb/>for each analyzed strain. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g003 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>buffering the environment to a pH above 6 thanks to the urease enzyme [24], which precludes <lb/>any assays at acidic pH. However, in mouse colonization, the natural environment of H. pylori <lb/>is mainly acidic, ranging from 2 in the lumen to 5-6 in the mucus layer. But at low pH, we <lb/>noticed that the in vitro activity of LpxE drastically decreased by 43-fold (from 900 to 21 nmol/ <lb/>min/mg), while that of HupA increased by 1.7-fold (from 3493 to 6039 nmol/min/mg) <lb/>(Table 2). Therefore, LpxE may be unable to fully complement the reduced UppP activity in <lb/>the hupA mutant in an acidic environment. This issue was then addressed by mouse coloniza-<lb/>tion assays. The ΔhupA mutation was first introduced into the mouse-adapted strain H pylori <lb/>X47 and the kinetics of colonization of wild-type and hupA strains was followed by sacrificing <lb/>mice after 1, 4, 7, 15 and 32 days after bacterial inoculation. Seven mice per group were sacri-<lb/>ficed in two independent experiments and Fig 4 illustrates the CFU/g of stomach in a time <lb/>course. The hupA mutant was unable to colonize the stomach neither at early or later stages <lb/>after inoculation, showing therefore that HupA is absolutely essential for viability of H. pylori <lb/>in vivo, in sharp contrast to in vitro where neither of the four PAP2 mutants was affected in <lb/>growth (Fig 5). <lb/>HupA has major involvement in phospholipid biosynthesis <lb/>HupA is an orthologue of PgpB from E. coli, which is a bifunctional enzyme acting as a minor <lb/>UppP and being largely involved in phospholipid biosynthesis through the dephosphorylation <lb/>of PGP in PG. In E. coli, the latter activity is also provided by two other integral membrane <lb/>proteins named PgpA and PgpC, which are unrelated to the PAP2 superfamily [10,11,25]. One <lb/>putative gene encoding a PgpA homolog was identified in the genome of H. pylori, hp0737, <lb/>while no PgpC encoding gene was found. The hp0737 was cloned on a pTrcHis30 vector and <lb/>the N-terminal-His tagged protein was expressed in E. coli C43(DE3) cells and purified from <lb/>membranes to high homogeneity in DDM micelles (S1A Fig). In contrast to the PAP2 <lb/>enzymes, PgpA enzymes are Mg 2+ -dependent, which was confirmed for HP0737 that pre-<lb/>sented an optimal Mg 2+ concentration of 6 mM (S1B Fig). Its PGP phosphatase activity was <lb/>then fully confirmed in vitro with a specific activity of 1138 ± 174 nmol/min/mg. Noticeably, <lb/>HP0737 did not display any significant UppP activity and the plasmid carrying hp0737 gene <lb/>did not restore the growth of E. coli BWTsbacA strain at 42˚C. Considering the activity of <lb/>HP0737 both in vivo and in vitro, this protein was renamed PgpA. The pgpA null mutant was <lb/>readily generated by replacement with a resistance cassette (Table 1). These disagree with a <lb/>previous study in which pgpA was described as an essential gene [26]. Our data further sug-<lb/>gested the existence of one or several other PGP phosphatases. <lb/>We then assessed whether the PAP2 proteins from H. pylori are also involved in the synthe-<lb/>sis of PG. DDM-solubilized membrane extracts obtained from wild-type and mutant cells <lb/>(lpxE, hp0350, hupA, lpxF and pgpA) were assayed for their PGP phosphatase activity. This <lb/>activity was measured in the absence and presence of 6 mM Mg 2+ (Fig 6A). A drastic decrease <lb/>of the PGP phosphatase activity in the hupA mutant as compared to the wild-type strain was <lb/>observed, while the other mutants displayed similar activities as the control. Under these con-<lb/>ditions, HupA accounted for 98% of the PGP phosphatase activity in the membrane of H. <lb/>pylori. <lb/>To further confirm the involvement of HupA in the biosynthesis of PG, we also performed <lb/>complementation assays using the conditional BWPGPTs E. coli strain and the different <lb/>pTrcHis30-based plasmids. Like the BWTsbacA strain, the BWPGPTs is a thermosensitive tri-<lb/>ple mutant (ΔpgpA, ΔpgpB, ΔpgpC) containing an ectopic copy of pgpB on a plasmid whose <lb/>replication is impaired at 42˚C. LpxE, HupA and PgpA fully restored the growth at 42˚C of <lb/>this thermosensitive strain without IPTG, while LpxF and HP0350 were unable to complement <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>(Table 6). Thus, LpxE, HupA and PgpA carry enough of PGP phosphatase activity to support <lb/>growth of the BWPGPTs strain. <lb/>The apparent PGP phosphatase activity of HupA and LpxE in vivo could explain why pgpA <lb/>inactivation did not lead to a lethal phenotype. To further decipher the role of PAP2 enzymes <lb/>in the biosynthesis of PG in H. pylori, we tried to generate mutant strains inactivated for hupA <lb/>and pgpA but we failed, while a double mutant lpxE/pgpA was readily obtained. These results <lb/>suggest that HupA and PgpA are the only PGP phosphatases able to sustain growth of H. pylori <lb/>in vitro. <lb/>Broad substrate specificity of H. pylori PAP2 enzymes <lb/>Since the HupA and LpxE accept very dissimilar lipidic substrates in vivo, we further analyzed <lb/>the substrate specificity of PAP2 enzymes in vitro (Fig 6B). Again, HP0350 had no visible <lb/>phosphatase activity on any of the tested substrates. HupA was the most active phosphatase <lb/>using all substrates tested except phosphatidic acid and the highest activity was by far obtained <lb/>with the C 15 -PP substrate. Structural and topology analyses of integral membrane PAP2 <lb/>enzymes revealed that their active site residues are oriented towards the periplasm, which is <lb/>likely the same for HupA. Small molecules such as C 15 -PP are never exposed at the periplasmic <lb/>site, therefore the C 15 -PP should not be a natural substrate in vivo. Nevertheless, this analysis <lb/>demonstrates that HupA accepts a large range of pyro-and monophosphate substrates, in par-<lb/>ticular C 55 -PP and PGP. Noticeably, HupA and PgpA displayed very similar activities towards <lb/>Fig 4. In vivo colonization of the hp0851 mutant in strain X47 at days 1, 4, 7, 15 and 32 using OF1 mice. OF1 mice were infected orogastrically <lb/>with the indicated strains at 2 × 10 8 bacteria per mouse. Colonization rates were determined after 1 (A), 4 (B), 7 (C) 15 (D) and 32 (E) days by <lb/>enumeration of colony forming units per gram (CFU/g) of stomach. Circles and square represent individual mice while mean colonization levels <lb/>are illustrated by horizontal bars. Circles and square located on the x-axis represent mice with no colonization. The single hp0851 mutant showed <lb/>a statistically significant colonization defect at day 4, 7, 15 and 32 when compared to wild-type as indicated by a red asterisk ( � p&lt;0.05; <lb/>��� p&lt;0,001). Data from two independent cohorts of mice were combined to increase significance and robustness of our analysis. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g004 <lb/>Fig 5. Growth curves of Helicobacter pylori N6. WT (black) and the four single mutants lpxE::Km (purple), hp0350::Km (blue), <lb/>hupA::Km (brown) and lpxF::Km (red) were grown with classic conditions previously described in Bacterial strains, plasmids and bacterial <lb/>growth conditions section. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g005 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>PGP. LpxE had similar substrate specificity as HupA, except for C 5 -PP, and much lower activi-<lb/>ties were found. In contrast, LpxF only showed very low activity towards C 15 -PP and PGP. <lb/>Since HupA showed broad substrate specificity, we wondered whether the polymyxin B <lb/>sensitivity could be related to a general membrane permeability defect of the hupA mutant. <lb/>We measured the MIC of the wild-type strain and its four PAP2 mutants to four different <lb/>Fig 6. PGP phosphatase activities in membranes of H. pylori. The PGP phosphatase activity in presence or absence of MgCl 2 of <lb/>the wild-type and five single mutants of H. pylori N6 strain was measured and normalized by the quantity of proteins in membrane <lb/>extracts (A). Ratios were then normalized by the wild-type strain. (B) The phosphatase specific activity of the recombinant proteins <lb/>towards various substrates. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.g006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>antimicrobial, one clinically relevant CAMP, colistin, and three large antibiotics, vancomycin, <lb/>teicoplanin and daptomycin that do not cross the outer membrane. Table 7 illustrates the <lb/>MICs to the four antimicrobials. <lb/>Absence of HupA, LpxE and LpxF affected specifically resistance to CAMPs without affect-<lb/>ing the resistance to large antimicrobials suggesting that these three PAP2 only affect overall <lb/>membrane charge and not permeability. Given the specific effect on CAMPs resistance and <lb/>the broad substrate specificity of HupA, we next analyzed the phospholipid composition of the <lb/>hupA mutant. As illustrated in S2 Fig, the wild-type N6 and its four PAP2 mutants showed a <lb/>similar phospholipid profile. <lb/>PgpB, YbjG and BacA from E. coli are functional in H. pylori <lb/>Since, HupA and LpxE are functional in E. coli, we tested if the PAP2/BacA enzymes from E. <lb/>coli are also functional in H. pylori. We performed complementation assays as previously <lb/>described by measuring the transformation rate of lpxE inactivation in hupA mutant contain-<lb/>ing different plasmids encoding PAP2/BacA from E. coli. We then generated eight strains <lb/>deleted for hupA and carrying a plasmid (pILL2150 or pILL2157 vector) bearing one of the <lb/>four E. coli genes (bacA, pbpB, ybjG and lpxT) placed under the control of an IPTG-inducible <lb/>promoter. The transgene is under control of a promoter from H. pylori in pILL2157, while it is <lb/>under control of an E. coli promoter in pILL2150. Consequently, the transgenes in pILL2157 <lb/>are likely more expressed in H. pylori as compared to those in pILL2150. Moreover, the <lb/>pILL2157 promoter was previously found to be leaky in contrast to that of pILL2150 vector <lb/>[27]. The transformation rates are summarized in Table 8. As expected, LpxT was unable to <lb/>complement the lack of UppP activity in H. pylori whatever the expression level. At a moderate <lb/>expression level (i.e. in pILL2150), only PgpB was able to complement the double lpxE/hupA <lb/>mutant (1.08 × 10 -5 transformants/cfu/μg DNA topoTAΔlpxE) in the presence of IPTG. In <lb/>contrast, at a higher level of expression (i.e. in pILL2157), BacA, PgpB and YbjG were able to <lb/>complement the double mutant both in the presence and in the absence of inducer. Therefore, <lb/>even though BacA does not belong to the PAP2 super-family, and H. pylori does not possess <lb/>UppP of the BacA type, this enzyme was functional in H. pylori. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>The recycling of C 55 -PP is an essential step for the biosynthesis of many polysaccharides such <lb/>as PGN, LPS O-antigen or teichoic acid [4]. This pathway was only studied in the Gram-<lb/>Table 6. Complementation of E. coli BWPGPTs conditional strain by PAP2 and PgpA encoding genes from H. <lb/>pylori. <lb/>E. coli BWPGPTs <lb/>CFU/mL <lb/>30˚C <lb/>42˚C <lb/>-<lb/>211 <lb/>1 <lb/>+pTrc His30 lpxE <lb/>97 <lb/>140 <lb/>+pTrc His30 hp0350 <lb/>152 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pTrc His30 hupA <lb/>289 <lb/>279 <lb/>+pTrc His30 lpxF <lb/>75 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pTrc His30 pgpA <lb/>652 <lb/>844 <lb/>The E. coli thermosensitive strain was transformed with the pTrcHis30-based plasmids and aliquots were plated onto <lb/>two ampicillin-containing 2YT agar plates incubated at either 30˚C or 42˚C. The CFU were counted after 24 h <lb/>incubation. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t006 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>positive bacterium B. subtilis [6] and more intensively in the Gram-negative E. coli. Two <lb/>enzymes from H. pylori belonging to the PAP2 super-family, LpxE and LpxF, were previously <lb/>demonstrated to have critical functions through the dephosphorylation of the lipid A moiety <lb/>from LPS. The other two members of the PAP2 super-family, HupA and HP0350, were not <lb/>characterized. HupA and HP0350 are orthologues of PgpB from E. coli, which was described <lb/>as a dual functional enzyme exhibiting both C 55 -PP and PGP phosphatase activities, thus <lb/>involved in both cell-envelope polysaccharides and phospholipids biosynthesis [11]. <lb/>Here, we demonstrated, by in vitro and in vivo analyses, that HupA constitutes the major <lb/>C 55 -PP phosphatase in H. pylori, being responsible for 90% of the total UppP activity present <lb/>in the membranes. Interestingly, HupA presented an optimal pH of 5 for its enzymatic activity, <lb/>which is close to the pH that H. pylori cells face in the human stomach. To further confirm this <lb/>function, we showed that HupA was also fully functional in E. coli by complementing a PAP2/ <lb/>BacA conditionally deficient strain. The deletion of hupA gene was not lethal suggesting that <lb/>one or several other C 55 -PP phosphatases exist in H. pylori. Among the three other PAP2, we <lb/>showed that LpxE and LpxF exhibited UppP activity with an optimal pH of 7.4 and 5, respec-<lb/>tively. However, only LpxE was also capable of complementing the conditional E. coli strain. <lb/>The inactivation of both lpxE and hupA genes was found to be lethal, which was further <lb/>Table 7. Minimal Inhibitory Concentrations (MIC) of H. pylori strains. <lb/>Helicobacter pylori N6 <lb/>Colistin <lb/>Vancomycin <lb/>Teicoplanin <lb/>Daptomycin <lb/>WT <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>lpxE::Gm <lb/>12 <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>lpxF::Km <lb/>1 <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>hp0350::Km <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>hupA::Km <lb/>64 <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>R <lb/>MICs are reported as μg/ml or R: Resistant. R indicates above the highest concentration on the E-test, i.e. MIC &gt;256 μg/mL. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t007 <lb/>Table 8. Complementation of lpxE/hupA double mutant with an ectopic copy of E. coli PAP2/BacA encoding <lb/>genes. <lb/>Helicobacter pylori N6 <lb/>hupA::Km <lb/>Transformation rate <lb/>(transformants/cfu/μg TopoTAΔlpxE) <lb/>-ITPG <lb/>+IPTG (1mM) <lb/>+pILL2150 empty <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2150 bacA <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2150 lpxT <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2150 pgpB <lb/>0 <lb/>1.08E-05 <lb/>+pILL2150 ybjG <lb/>0 <lb/>0 <lb/>+pILL2157 bacA <lb/>3.85E-05 <lb/>5.25E-05 <lb/>+pILL2157 lpxT <lb/>+pILL2157 pgpB <lb/>1.51E-05 <lb/>2.07E-05 <lb/>+pILL21570 ybjG <lb/>5.86E-06 <lb/>1.06E-06 <lb/>Quantification of lpxE gene inactivation in ΔhupA single mutant transformed with plasmids expressing one PAP2/ <lb/>BacA from E. coli. Two types of expression vectors were used: pILL2150 and pILL2157. The pILL2150 vector <lb/>possesses an E. coli promoter and leads to low levels of expression in H. pylori, while pILL2157 displays a H. pylori <lb/>promoter yielding high levels of expression in H. pylori. The transformation rates were measured in the presence and <lb/>in the absence of IPTG. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972.t008 <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>confirmed by complementation assays of the double mutant by ectopic copies of lpxE or hupA. <lb/>All these data confirmed that HupA and LpxE are the only physiologically relevant UppP in H. <lb/>pylori. <lb/>In addition, we demonstrated that HupA plays critical roles in vivo. Indeed, HupA appeared <lb/>important for the resistance towards CAMPs by a yet uncharacterized process. In this study, <lb/>we excluded potential alteration of the structure of lipid A. More importantly, HupA was <lb/>shown to be essential for stomach colonization. Indeed, the PAP2 super-family members all <lb/>have their active site exposed to the periplasmic space where the pH is determined by the envi-<lb/>ronmental pH. We then hypothesized, based on in vitro data, that LpxE enzyme might not be <lb/>sufficiently active at acidic to sustain growth in the absence of HupA. Indeed, during colo-<lb/>nization, LpxE is unlikely to function properly since it was poorly active at pH 5 in vitro. In <lb/>fact, apart from the niche that is in contact with the epithelial cells where there exists a neutral <lb/>pH, H. pylori cells are always exposed to an acidic environment. In these conditions, LpxE will <lb/>likely be unable to provide the UppP activity required in absence of HupA enzyme. <lb/>The first step for stomach colonization by H. pylori is dependent on its motility and its ure-<lb/>ase enzyme to buffer its cytoplasm [24]. H. pylori escapes the lumen towards the mucus layer <lb/>to reach a more favorable environment with a higher pH. Therefore, we cannot exclude a rele-<lb/>vant physiological role of LpxE in C 55 -PP dephosphorylation after the first step of colonization, <lb/>once H. pylori has reached the mucus layer and the epithelial surface. Our previous work on <lb/>LpxE showed that LpxE is needed for long-term colonization. However, this is likely due to its <lb/>role as lipid A 1-phosphate phosphatase and escape to TLR4 signaling rather than to its UppP <lb/>activity since the mutant was able to colonize TLR4 KO mice [19]. <lb/>This study also highlighted the dual function of HupA, which has also a major involvement <lb/>in the biosynthesis of phospholipids through the synthesis of PG from PGP. By sequence <lb/>homology, only one additional putative PGP phosphatase was found in H. pylori, i.e. HP0737, <lb/>which is homologous to E. coli PgpA. A global transposon analysis performed on H. pylori <lb/>reported hp0737 as an essential gene [26]. However, we were able to delete hp0737 gene by <lb/>resistance cassette replacement. HP0737 could then account for the residual PGP phosphatase <lb/>activity in H. pylori hupA null mutant. In E. coli, three PGP phosphatases were described, <lb/>PgpA, PgpB and PgpC and only a triple mutant is lethal [11]. Even if the composition of phos-<lb/>pholipids differs between E. coli and H. pylori, i.e. PG represents 25% and 12.5% of the total <lb/>phospholipids, respectively [28,29], we can expect that the presence of PG is also essential in <lb/>H. pylori, especially because PG is the precursor of another important phospholipid, the cardi-<lb/>olipin. A pgpA/hupA double mutant is lethal and confirms the importance of PG in H. pylori. <lb/>Members of the PgpA-family have a predicted cytoplasmic active site while PAP2-like enzymes <lb/>have a periplasmic oriented active site. These results suggest that PGP is accessible to dephos-<lb/>phorylation on both sides of the cytoplasmic membrane similarly to E. coli. Thus, HupA and <lb/>PgpA are the only two physiologically relevant PGP phosphatases in H. pylori despite the weak <lb/>PGP phosphatase activity of LpxE. <lb/>The involvement of HupA in phospholipid biosynthesis may explain the decrease of resis-<lb/>tance to polymyxin B and colistin of the corresponding mutant. Indeed, these cationic peptides <lb/>form pores in the cytoplasmic membrane leading to cytoplasmic leakage. Therefore, if the <lb/>composition of the plasma membrane differs in the hupA mutant as compared to the wild-<lb/>type strain, particularly with a possible accumulation of PGP, the membrane net negative <lb/>charge might increase, favoring the binding of CAMPs, which could potentiate their capacity <lb/>to insert within the membrane. However, our analysis of phospholipid composition of the <lb/>wild-type N6 and its four PAP2 mutants showed similar phospholipid composition. Although <lb/>TLC analysis is mainly qualitative, these results suggest that changes in membrane charge are <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>unlikely to be due to an accumulation of PGP and suggest that accumulation of C55-PP might <lb/>contribute to the mild increased sensitivity of the hupA mutant to CAMPs. <lb/>LpxE and HupA have similar broad substrate specificities although LpxE exhibits a much <lb/>weaker activity. In contrast, LpxF has a very narrow substrate specificity and, so far, only cata-<lb/>lyzes the dephosphorylation of the lipid A. It would be interesting to study the molecular basis <lb/>of such distinct substrate specificity. The low sequence conservation among the membrane <lb/>PAP2 proteins precludes in silico modelling studies using PgpB and BsPgpB. Insights into sub-<lb/>strate specificity will require 3D structures of HupA, LpxE and LpxF with their substrates. <lb/>In this report, we described HupA as the main C 55 -PP and PGP phosphatase in H. pylori. <lb/>This protein was also essential for colonization, likely due to its dual functionality and its cen-<lb/>tral role in several lipid biosynthetic pathways, suggesting that HupA is the sole enzyme capa-<lb/>ble to support C 55 -PP recycling and PG synthesis in its natural niche. Hence, HupA, as well as <lb/>LpxE and LpxF, constitute bona fide new targets for innovative therapeutic strategies against <lb/>H. pylori, which is becoming increasingly resistant to the existing antibiotic arsenal. <lb/>Materials and Methods <lb/>Ethics Statement <lb/>Animal experiments were done according to European (Directive 2010/63 EU) and French <lb/>regulation (De ´cret 2013-118) under the authorized protocol CETEA 2014-072 reviewed by <lb/>the Institut Pasteur Ethical Committee (registered as number 89 with the French Ministry of <lb/>Research). The experimental protocol was also approved by the French Ministry of Research <lb/>under the number APAFIS#11694-2017100510327765 v2. <lb/>Bacterial strains, plasmids and bacterial growth conditions <lb/>The bacterial strains and plasmids used in the study are summarized in Table 1. Precultures of <lb/>H. pylori were started from glycerol stocks routinely stored at -80˚C, plated onto 10% horse <lb/>blood agar medium supplemented with an antibiotic-antifungal mix [19] and incubated at <lb/>37˚C for 24 h in a microaerobic atmosphere (6% O 2 , 10% CO 2 , 84% N 2 ). The glycerol storage <lb/>media is composed of 25% glycerol, 38% Brain Heart Infusion liquid (BHI) (Oxoid) and 37% <lb/>sterilized water. Amplification of the preculture was performed in the same conditions as pre-<lb/>cultures in new plates at 37˚C for 24 h in a microaerobic atmosphere. Liquid precultures were <lb/>started from amplification plates and inoculated into BHI (Oxoid) supplemented with 10% <lb/>fetal bovine serum (FBS) incubated at 37˚C overnight in a microaerobic atmosphere. Liquid <lb/>cultures of H. pylori were started from overnight liquid culture and inoculated into BHI <lb/>(Oxoid) supplemented with 10% fetal bovine serum. In general, liquid cultures of H. pylori <lb/>were grown to an OD 600nm of ~1.0 at 37˚C under microaerobic conditions with shaking. Oth-<lb/>erwise indicated, E. coli was routinely grown at 37˚C in 2YT broth using standard conditions. <lb/>A non-polar kanamycin cassette was digested out of plasmid pUC18-Km2 [30] using <lb/>BamHI and KpnI and ligated into the PCR products of the 5&apos;and 3&apos; flanking regions of genes <lb/>lpxE, hp0350, hupA, lpxF and pgpA using standard cloning techniques. The oligonucleotides <lb/>used for the PCR amplification are described in S1 Table. The generated plasmids, TopoTA <lb/>ΔlpxE:kan, TopoTA Δhp0350:kan, TopoTA ΔhupA:kan, TopoTA ΔlpxF:kan and TopoTA <lb/>ΔpgpA:kan were used to create the corresponding null mutants in H. pylori N6 and/or X47 by <lb/>natural transformation. Similarly, a non-polar gentamycin cassette was digested out of plasmid <lb/>pUC18-Gm [31] using BamHI and KpnI to generate TopoTA ΔlpxE:Gm. <lb/>For the expression of PAP2, BacA and PgpA encoding genes from E. coli or H. pylori, the <lb/>genes were amplified by PCR using appropriate primers (S1 Table) and cloned into the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>pILL2150 or pILL2157 vectors (for expression in H. pylori) or in pTrcHis30 vector (for expres-<lb/>sion in E. coli). <lb/>Expression and purification of the PAP2 and PgpA proteins from H. pylori <lb/>E. coli C43(DE3) cells carrying pTrcHis30-based plasmids were used for the overproduction of <lb/>N-terminal His 6 -tagged proteins. Cells were grown in 1 liter 2YT-ampicillin at 37˚C until the <lb/>A 600nm reached 0.9, when the expression was induced by the addition of 1 mM IPTG and the <lb/>growth was continued for 3 h at 37˚C. Cells were harvested by centrifugation at 4˚C for 20 min <lb/>at 4000 × g, were washed and finally resuspended in buffer A (20 mM Tris-HCl pH 7.4, 400 <lb/>mM NaCl, 10% glycerol) before disruption by sonication with a Vibracell 72412 sonicator <lb/>(Bioblock). The suspension was centrifuged at 4˚C for 1 h at 100,000 × g to harvest the mem-<lb/>branes, which were washed three times in buffer A. The membranes were finally resuspended <lb/>in buffer A supplemented with 2% DDM for solubilization at 4˚C for 2 h with gentle agitation. <lb/>Solubilized membranes were loaded on nickel-nitrilotriacetate agarose (Ni 2+ -NTA-agarose, <lb/>Qiagen) equilibrated in buffer A supplemented with 0.2% DDM and 10 mM imidazole. The <lb/>column was washed with increasing imidazole concentration using the same buffer and the <lb/>elution was performed with 2 ml of buffer A supplemented with 0.2% DDM and 200 mM <lb/>imidazole. Desalting of samples was carried out using PD-10 desalting columns (GE Health-<lb/>care) and buffer A supplemented with 0.1% DDM. Protein concentrations were determined <lb/>with the QuantiProBCA assay kit (Sigma) or by densitometry analysis of the gel when <lb/>appropriate. <lb/>H. pylori membrane extracts preparation <lb/>H. pylori wild-type and single mutant strains were grown at 37˚C in BHI medium (200 ml cul-<lb/>ture) up to exponential phase. Cell free extracts, membrane free cytosol, and washed mem-<lb/>branes were prepared as previously described [22]. Cells were harvested by centrifugation, <lb/>washed and finally resuspended in 20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 200 mM NaCl (buffer B). After <lb/>disruption by sonication, membranes were pelleted by centrifugation at 177 420 × g and resus-<lb/>pended in buffer B supplemented with 2% DDM for solubilization during 1.5 h in the cold. <lb/>The solubilized proteins were recovered by centrifugation at 177 420 × g and conserved at <lb/>-20˚C before activity measurement. <lb/>H. pylori membrane phospholipids extraction and staining <lb/>H. pylori wild-type and four single mutant strains were grown at 37˚C in BHI medium (50 ml <lb/>culture) up to exponential phase. Lipid extraction was performed using a new protocol (Nozeret <lb/>K et al. manuscript submitted). For thin-layer chromatography (TLC) analysis of phospholipids, <lb/>the dried lipid extracts and controls were dissolved respectively in 500μl and 350μl of chloro-<lb/>form. 10μl of the solution was spotted onto a TLC silica gel 60 plate. The TLC plate was devel-<lb/>oped in tanks equilibrated with dichloromethane-methanol-water (65:28:4 [vol/vol]). After <lb/>drying the plate, phospholipids were visualized with molybdenum blue reagent (Sigma). <lb/>C 55 -PP and PGP phosphatase assays <lb/>The C 55 -PP and PGP phosphatase assays were carried out in a 10 μl reaction mixture containing <lb/>20 mM Tris-HCl, pH 7.4, 10 mM β-mercaptoethanol, 150 mM NaCl, 0.2% DDM, 50 μM [ 14 C] <lb/>C 55 -PP or 50 μM [ 14 C]PGP (900 Bq) and enzyme. MgCl 2 was added at 6 mM in the reaction <lb/>mixture when PgpA activity was measured. Appropriate dilutions of purified phosphatases, or <lb/>of membrane extracts, were used to achieve less than 30% substrate hydrolysis. The reaction <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>mixture was incubated at 37˚C for 10 to 30 min and the reaction was stopped by freezing in liq-<lb/>uid nitrogen. The substrates and products were then separated and quantified by thin layer <lb/>chromatography (TLC) analysis, as previously described for C 55 -PP [5] and PGP [11] hydroly-<lb/>sis. When the phosphatase activity was investigated at various pH values, buffering was achieved <lb/>in sodium acetate (pH 3-7), Tris-HCl (pH 7-9) or sodium carbonate buffer (pH 9-11). <lb/>The phosphatase activity towards other non-radiolabeled substrates: C 5 -PP, C 15 -PP, diacyl <lb/>(C8) glycerol-PP (DGPP) and phosphatidic acid (PA), was determined by measuring the <lb/>amount of released inorganic phosphate during catalysis. The reaction mixture was as <lb/>described above with 50 μM substrate in a final volume of 50 μl. After 10 min of incubation at <lb/>37˚C, the reaction was stopped by the addition of 100 μl of Malachite green solution (Biomol <lb/>green, Enzo Life Sciences), and the released phosphate was quantified by measurement of the <lb/>absorbance at 620 nm. <lb/>E. coli functional complementation <lb/>The E. coli thermosensitive strains BWTsbacA and BWPGPTs, carrying multiple chromo-<lb/>somal gene deletions and harboring a bacA-or pgpB-expressing plasmid, respectively, whose <lb/>replication is impaired at 42˚C, have been previously described [7]. These strains were trans-<lb/>formed by the pTrcHis30-based plasmids encoding the different H. pylori PAP2 and PgpA <lb/>encoding genes. Isolated transformants were subcultured at 30˚C in liquid 2YT medium sup-<lb/>plemented with 100 μg/ml ampicillin and, when the absorbance of the culture reached 0.5, the <lb/>cell suspension was diluted to 10 -5 in 2YT medium and 100 μl aliquots were plated onto two <lb/>ampicillin-containing 2YT agar plates which were incubated at either 30˚C or 42˚C for 24 h. <lb/>The colony forming units (CFU) were numerated on each plate and the functional comple-<lb/>mentation of the thermosensitive mutants was evaluated by the capacity of the transformants <lb/>to equally grow at both temperatures. <lb/>Transformation rate <lb/>Precultures of H. pylori were started from glycerol stocks routinely stored at -80˚C, plated onto <lb/>10% horse blood agar medium and incubated at 37˚C for 24 h in a microaerobic atmosphere <lb/>(6% O 2 , 10% CO 2 , 84% N 2 ). Amplification of the pre-culture was performed in the same con-<lb/>ditions such as pre-cultures in new plates at 37˚C for 24 h in a microaerobic atmosphere. 50 μl <lb/>of suspension in BHI at OD 600nm = 20 were made until the amplification plate and mixed with <lb/>10 ng of Topo TAΔlpxE plasmid. The whole mixture was put on a non-selective plate onto <lb/>10% horse blood agar medium and incubated at 37˚C for 24 h in a microaerobic atmosphere. <lb/>The transformation spot was then diluted (10 -1 to 10 -8 ). 50 μl of the non-diluted suspension <lb/>and 10 μl of the 10 -1 to 10 -4 dilutions were spread on 10% horse blood agar medium supple-<lb/>mented with chloramphenicol (4 μg/ml), kanamycin (20 μg/ml) and gentamycin (5 μg/ml) ± <lb/>IPTG 1mM to estimate the number of transformants. The 10 -5 to 10 -8 dilutions were spread <lb/>on non-selective plates containing 10% horse blood agar medium supplemented with chlor-<lb/>amphenicol (4 μg/ml), kanamycin (20 μg/ml) ± IPTG 1mM to estimate the total number of <lb/>bacteria. The CFU of all plates incubated at 37˚C for 5 days in a microaerobic atmosphere <lb/>were enumerated. The transformation rate was expressed by the number of transformants/ <lb/>total cfu/μg of DNA TopoTAΔlpxE. <lb/>Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) of polymyxin B <lb/>Strains were grown routinely on amplification plates. Two ml of suspension in 0.9% NaCl at <lb/>OD 600nm = 0.75 were made from the amplification plates and spread by inundation onto Muel-<lb/>ler Hinton medium (Difco) supplemented with 10% of FBS and 2,3,5-triphenyltetrazolium <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<body>chloride (TTC, Sigma) (40 μg/ml). Polymyxin B was diluted by serial dilutions of two <lb/>(16384 μg/ml down to 0.5 μg/ml). Once the square plates with bacterial lawns were dried, 10 μl <lb/>of each dilution of polymyxin B was dropped on and allowed to dry. All plates were then incu-<lb/>bated at 37˚C for 3 days in a microaerobic atmosphere. TTC is a non-toxic dye which colors in <lb/>red the alive bacteria. MICs were determined as the lowest concentration of polymyxin B lead-<lb/>ing to a clear halo of inhibition. <lb/>Determination of Minimum Inhibitory Concentration (MIC) by Etest <lb/>Strains were grown routinely on amplification plates. Two ml of suspension in 0.9% NaCl at <lb/>OD 600nm = 0.75 were made from the amplification plates and spread by inundation onto 10% <lb/>horse blood agar medium. Once the square plates with bacterial lawns were dried, Etes, Bio-<lb/>me ´rieux, with different antibiotics targeting the cell wall (Vancomycin, Teicoplanin, Dapto-<lb/>mycin and Colistin) were put on plate and incubated at 37˚C for 48 h in a microaerobic <lb/>atmosphere. MICs were determined as the lowest concentration of antibiotics leading to a <lb/>clear halo of inhibition. <lb/>Colonization <lb/>OF1 female mice purchased from Charles River Laboratories aged 5 weeks were infected by <lb/>gavage with feeding needles with X47 strain (2 × 10 8 bacteria per mouse). Colonization rates <lb/>were determined after 1, 4, 7, 15 and 32 days by enumeration of CFU per gram of stomach. <lb/>Mice were euthanized with CO 2 and the stomachs were ground and homogenized in peptone <lb/>broth. The samples were then diluted and spread on blood agar plates supplemented with <lb/>10 μg/ml of nalidixic acid, to inhibit the growth of resident bacteria from the mouse foresto-<lb/>mach and 20 μg/ml of kanamycin for hupA mutant strain. The CFU were enumerated after 5 <lb/>days of incubation under microaerobic conditions. The results of two independent coloniza-<lb/>tion experiments (seven mice by cage) were pooled and a one tailed Mann-Whitney test was <lb/>used to determine statistical significance of observed differences (GraphPad Prism v5.0 Graph-<lb/>Pad Software, CA). <lb/>Isolation of lipid A for mass spectrometry analysis <lb/>For isolation of lipid A, H. pylori cultures were grown to an OD 600 of ~0.6. Lipid A chemical <lb/>extraction was carried out after mild acidic hydrolysis of LPS as previously described [32,33]. <lb/>For visualization of lipid A by mass spectrometry, lipids were analyzed using MALDI-TOF <lb/>(ABI 4700 Proteomic Analyzer) in the negative-ion linear mode similar to previously <lb/>described [34,35]. Briefly, lipid A samples were dissolved in a mixture of chloroform-methanol <lb/>(4:1, vol/vol), with 1 μL of sample mixed with 1 μL of matrix solution consisting of 5-chloro-<lb/>2meracaptobenzothiazole (CBMT) (20 mg/mL) resuspended in chloroform-methanol-water <lb/>(4:4:1, vol/vol/vol) mixed with saturated ammonium citrate (20:1, vol/vol), and 1 μL of sam-<lb/>ple-matrix mixture was loaded on to MALDI target plate. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Supporting information <lb/>S1 Fig. Purification and characterization of PgpA from H. pylori. (A) SDS-PAGE analysis <lb/>of His 6 -PgpA purification. Coloration was performed with Coomassie Blue R-250. Purified <lb/>PgpA protein is indicated with an asterisk in the elution fraction. (B) Mg 2+ -dependence of <lb/>PgpA PGPase activity. The results are expressed as the percentage of the optimal activity found <lb/>at a final concentration of 6 mM of MgCl 2 . The observed molecular weight of recombinant <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">PgpA was lower than the calculated one (16,9 kDa). <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S2 Fig. Membrane phospholipids of Helicobacter pylori. TLC analysis of total lipid extracts <lb/>from N6 (1) WT strain and the four single mutants (2) lpxE::Gm; (3) hp0350::Km; (4) <lb/>lpxF::Km; (5) hupA::Km grown to exponential phase in BHI medium. Left panel contains con-<lb/>trol phospholipids: CL: Cardiolipin; PC: Phosphotidylcholine; PE: Phosphotidylethanolamine; <lb/>PG: Phosphotidylglycerol; PS: Phosphotidylserine; Lip. EC: Lipid extracts from E. coli. <lb/>(TIF) <lb/>S1 Table. Oligonucleotides used in this study. Oligonucleotides which have an underlined <lb/>nucleotide sequence, the sequence corresponds to the restriction enzyme cutting site. <lb/>(DOCX) <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions <lb/>Conceptualization: Dominique Mengin-Lecreulx, Thierry Touze ´, Ivo Gomperts Boneca. <lb/>
			Funding acquisition: M. Stephen Trent, Dominique Mengin-Lecreulx, Ivo Gomperts Boneca. <lb/>
			Investigation: Elise Gasiorowski, Rodolphe Auger, Xudong Tian, Samia Hicham, Chantal <lb/>Ecobichon, Sophie Roure, Martin V. Douglass. <lb/>
			Project administration: Thierry Touze <lb/>´. <lb/>
			Resources: Chantal Ecobichon, Sophie Roure. <lb/>
			Supervision: M. Stephen Trent, Thierry Touze ´, Ivo Gomperts Boneca. <lb/>
			Validation: Rodolphe Auger, Samia Hicham, Ivo Gomperts Boneca. <lb/>
			Visualization: Elise Gasiorowski, Rodolphe Auger, Martin V. Douglass. <lb/>
			Writing -original draft: Elise Gasiorowski. <lb/>
			Writing -review &amp; editing: Dominique Mengin-Lecreulx, Thierry Touze ´, Ivo Gomperts <lb/>Boneca. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Barreteau H, Kovač A, Boniface A, Sova M, Gobec S, Blanot D. Cytoplasmic steps of peptidoglycan bio-<lb/>synthesis. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2008; 32: 168-207. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2008.00104.x <lb/>PMID: 18266853 <lb/>2. Bouhss A, Trunkfield AE, Bugg TDH, Mengin-Lecreulx D. The biosynthesis of peptidoglycan lipid-linked <lb/>intermediates. FEMS Microbiol Rev. 2008; 32: 208-233. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1574-6976.2007. <lb/>00089.x PMID: 18081839 <lb/>3. Apfel CM, Taka ´cs B, Fountoulakis M, Stieger M, Keck W. Use of Genomics To Identify Bacterial Unde-<lb/>caprenyl Pyrophosphate Synthetase: Cloning, Expression, and Characterization of the Essential uppS <lb/>Gene. J Bacteriol. 1999; 181: 483-492. PMID: 9882662 <lb/>4. Manat G, Roure S, Auger R, Bouhss A, Barreteau H, Mengin-Lecreulx D, et al. Deciphering the Metabo-<lb/>lism of Undecaprenyl-Phosphate: The Bacterial Cell-Wall Unit Carrier at the Membrane Frontier. Microb <lb/>Drug Resist. 2014; 20: 199-214. https://doi.org/10.1089/mdr.2014.0035 PMID: 24799078 <lb/>5. Ghachi ME, Bouhss A, Blanot D, Mengin-Lecreulx D. The bacA Gene of Escherichia coli Encodes an <lb/>Undecaprenyl Pyrophosphate Phosphatase Activity. J Biol Chem. 2004; 279: 30106-30113. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1074/jbc.M401701200 PMID: 15138271 <lb/>6. Ghachi ME, Howe N, Auger R, Lambion A, Guiseppi A, Delbrassine F, et al. Crystal structure and bio-<lb/>chemical characterization of the transmembrane PAP2 type phosphatidylglycerol phosphate phospha-<lb/>tase from Bacillus subtilis. Cell Mol Life Sci. 2017; 74: 2319-2332. https://doi.org/10.1007/s00018-017-<lb/>2464-6 PMID: 28168443 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>7. Ghachi ME, Derbise A, Bouhss A, Mengin-Lecreulx D. Identification of Multiple Genes Encoding Mem-<lb/>brane Proteins with Undecaprenyl Pyrophosphate Phosphatase (UppP) Activity in Escherichia coli. J <lb/>Biol Chem. 2005; 280: 18689-18695. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M412277200 PMID: 15778224 <lb/>8. Azevedo EC, Rios EM, Fukushima K, Campos-Takaki GM. Bacitracin production by a new strain of <lb/>Bacillus subtilis. Extraction, purification, and characterization. Appl Biochem Biotechnol. 1993; 42: 1-7. <lb/>PMID: 8215347 <lb/>9. Touze ´T, Tran AX, Hankins JV, Mengin-Lecreulx D, Trent MS. Periplasmic phosphorylation of lipid A is <lb/>linked to the synthesis of undecaprenyl phosphate. Mol Microbiol. 2008; 67: 264-277. https://doi.org/ <lb/>10.1111/j.1365-2958.2007.06044.x PMID: 18047581 <lb/>10. Icho T, Raetz CR. Multiple genes for membrane-bound phosphatases in Escherichia coli and their <lb/>action on phospholipid precursors. J Bacteriol. 1983; 153: 722-730. PMID: 6296050 <lb/>11. Lu Y-H, Guan Z, Zhao J, Raetz CRH. Three Phosphatidylglycerol-phosphate Phosphatases in the Inner <lb/>Membrane of Escherichia coli. J Biol Chem. 2011; 286: 5506-5518. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M110. <lb/>199265 PMID: 21148555 <lb/>12. Tatar LD, Marolda CL, Polischuk AN, van Leeuwen D, Valvano MA. An Escherichia coli undecaprenyl-<lb/>pyrophosphate phosphatase implicated in undecaprenyl phosphate recycling. Microbiology. 2007; 153: <lb/>2518-2529. https://doi.org/10.1099/mic.0.2007/006312-0 PMID: 17660416 <lb/>13. Touze ´T, Blanot D, Mengin-Lecreulx D. Substrate Specificity and Membrane Topology of Escherichia <lb/>coli PgpB, an Undecaprenyl Pyrophosphate Phosphatase. J Biol Chem. 2008; 283: 16573-16583. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M800394200 PMID: 18411271 <lb/>14. El Ghachi M, Howe N, Huang C-Y, Olieric V, Warshamanage R, Touze ´T, et al. Crystal structure of <lb/>undecaprenyl-pyrophosphate phosphatase and its role in peptidoglycan biosynthesis. Nat Commun. <lb/>2018; 9. <lb/>15. Workman SD, Worrall LJ, Strynadka NCJ. Crystal structure of an intramembranal phosphatase central <lb/>to bacterial cell-wall peptidoglycan biosynthesis and lipid recycling. Nat Commun. 2018;9. https://doi. <lb/>org/10.1038/s41467-017-01881-x <lb/>16. Marshall B, Warren JR. Unidentified curved bacilli in the stomach of patients with gastritis and peptic <lb/>ulceration. The Lancet. 1984; 323: 1311-1315. <lb/>17. Blaser MJ. Hypotheses on the pathogenesis and natural history of Helicobacter pylori-induced inflam-<lb/>mation. Gastroenterology. 1992; 102: 720-727. https://doi.org/10.1016/0016-5085(92)90126-j PMID: <lb/>1732141 <lb/>18. Tran AX, Karbarz MJ, Wang X, Raetz CRH, McGrath SC, Cotter RJ, et al. Periplasmic Cleavage and <lb/>Modification of the 1-Phosphate Group of Helicobacter pylori Lipid A. J Biol Chem. 2004; 279: 55780-<lb/>55791. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc.M406480200 PMID: 15489235 <lb/>19. Cullen TW, Giles DK, Wolf LN, Ecobichon C, Boneca IG, Trent MS. Helicobacter pylori versus the Host: <lb/>Remodeling of the Bacterial Outer Membrane Is Required for Survival in the Gastric Mucosa. PLoS <lb/>Pathog. 2011;7. <lb/>20. Behrens W, Bo ¨nig T, Suerbaum S, Josenhans C. Genome sequence of Helicobacter pylori hpEurope <lb/>strain N6. J Bacteriol. 2012; 194: 3725-3726. https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.00386-12 PMID: 22740658 <lb/>21. Veyrier FJ, Ecobichon C, Boneca IG. Draft Genome Sequence of Strain X47-2AL, a Feline Helicobacter <lb/>pylori Isolate. Genome Announc. 2013; 1. <lb/>22. Stead CM, Zhao J, Raetz CRH, Trent MS. Removal of the outer Kdo from Helicobacter pylori lipopoly-<lb/>saccharide and its impact on the bacterial surface. Mol Microbiol. 2010; 78: 837-852. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1111/j.1365-2958.2010.07304.x PMID: 20659292 <lb/>23. Gutsmann T, Hagge SO, David A, Roes S, Bo ¨hling A, Hammer MU, et al. Lipid-mediated resistance of <lb/>Gram-negative bacteria against various pore-forming antimicrobial peptides. J Endotoxin Res. 2005; <lb/>11: 167-173. https://doi.org/10.1179/096805105X37330 PMID: 15949145 <lb/>24. Smoot DT, Mobley HL, Chippendale GR, Lewison JF, Resau JH. Helicobacter pylori urease activity is <lb/>toxic to human gastric epithelial cells. Infect Immun. 1990; 58: 1992-1994. PMID: 2341188 <lb/>25. Icho T. Membrane-bound phosphatases in Escherichia coli: sequence of the pgpB gene and dual sub-<lb/>cellular localization of the pgpB product. J Bacteriol. 1988; 170: 5117-5124. https://doi.org/10.1128/jb. <lb/>170.11.5117-5124.1988 PMID: 2846511 <lb/>26. Salama NR, Shepherd B, Falkow S. Global Transposon Mutagenesis and Essential Gene Analysis of <lb/>Helicobacter pylori. J Bacteriol. 2004; 186: 7926-7935. https://doi.org/10.1128/JB.186.23.7926-7935. <lb/>2004 PMID: 15547264 <lb/>27. Boneca IG, Ecobichon C, Chaput C, Mathieu A, Guadagnini S, Pre ´vost M-C, et al. Development of <lb/>Inducible Systems To Engineer Conditional Mutants of Essential Genes of Helicobacter pylori. Appl <lb/>Environ Microbiol. 2008; 74: 2095-2102. https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.01348-07 PMID: 18245237 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 / 24 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>28. Raetz CR. Enzymology, genetics, and regulation of membrane phospholipid synthesis in Escherichia <lb/>coli. Microbiol Rev. 1978; 42: 614-659. PMID: 362151 <lb/>29. Hirai Y, Haque M, Yoshida T, Yokota K, Yasuda T, Oguma K. Unique cholesteryl glucosides in Helico-<lb/>bacter pylori: composition and structural analysis. J Bacteriol. 1995; 177: 5327-5333. https://doi.org/10. <lb/>1128/jb.177.18.5327-5333.1995 PMID: 7665522 <lb/>30. Skouloubris S, Labigne A, Reuse HD. Identification and characterization of an aliphatic amidase in Heli-<lb/>cobacter pylori. Mol Microbiol. 1997; 25: 989-998. https://doi.org/10.1111/j.1365-2958.1997.mmi536.x <lb/>PMID: 9364923 <lb/>31. Bury-Mone ´S, Mendz GL, Ball GE, Thibonnier M, Stingl K, Ecobichon C, et al. Roles of alpha and beta <lb/>carbonic anhydrases of Helicobacter pylori in the urease-dependent response to acidity and in coloniza-<lb/>tion of the murine gastric mucosa. Infect Immun. 2008; 76: 497-509. https://doi.org/10.1128/IAI.00993-<lb/>07 PMID: 18025096 <lb/>32. Zhou Z, Lin S, Cotter RJ, Raetz CRH. Lipid A Modifications Characteristic of Salmonella typhimurium <lb/>Are Induced by NH4VO3 in Escherichia coli K12 detection of 4-amino-4-deoxy-l-arabinose, phos-<lb/>phoethanolamine and palmitate. J Biol Chem. 1999; 274: 18503-18514. https://doi.org/10.1074/jbc. <lb/>274.26.18503 PMID: 10373459 <lb/>33. Herrera CM, Crofts AA, Henderson JC, Pingali SC, Davies BW, Trent MS. The Vibrio cholerae VprA-<lb/>VprB two-component system controls virulence through endotoxin modification. mBio. 2014; 5. <lb/>34. Henderson JC, O&apos;Brien JP, Brodbelt JS, Trent MS. Isolation and chemical characterization of lipid A <lb/>from gram-negative bacteria. J Vis Exp JoVE. 2013; e50623. https://doi.org/10.3791/50623 PMID: <lb/>24084191 <lb/>35. Zhou P, Altman E, Perry MB, Li J. Study of matrix additives for sensitive analysis of lipid A by matrix-<lb/>assisted laser desorption ionization mass spectrometry. Appl Environ Microbiol. 2010; 76: 3437-3443. <lb/>https://doi.org/10.1128/AEM.03082-09 PMID: 20382818 <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">HupA, the main UppP and PGPase in H.pylori <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">PLOS Pathogens | https://doi.org/10.1371/journal.ppat.1007972 September 5, 2019 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 / 24 </page>


	</text>
</tei>
