<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<titlePage>Recombinant S. cerevisiae expressing Old Yellow <lb/>Enzymes from non-conventional yeasts: an easy <lb/>system for selective reduction of activated alkenes <lb/>Romano et al. <lb/>Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/>http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></titlePage>

			<front>R E S E A R C H <lb/>Open Access <lb/>Recombinant S. cerevisiae expressing Old Yellow <lb/>Enzymes from non-conventional yeasts: an easy <lb/>system for selective reduction of activated alkenes <lb/>Diego Romano 2 , Martina Letizia Contente 2 , Francesco Molinari 2 , Ivano Eberini 3 , Erica Ruvutuso 3 , Cristina Sensi 3 , <lb/>Alberto Amaretti 1 , Maddalena Rossi 1 and Stefano Raimondi 1* <lb/>Abstract <lb/>Background: Old Yellow Enzymes (OYEs) are flavin-dependent enoate reductases (EC 1.6.99.1) that catalyze the <lb/>stereoselective hydrogenation of electron-poor alkenes. Their ability to generate up to two stereocenters by the <lb/>trans-hydrogenation of the C = C double bond is highly demanded in asymmetric synthesis. Isolated redox enzymes <lb/>utilization require the addition of cofactors and systems for their regeneration. Microbial whole-cells may represent <lb/>a valid alternative combining desired enzymatic activity and efficient cofactor regeneration. Considerable efforts <lb/>were addressed at developing novel whole-cell OYE biocatalysts, based on recombinant Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>expressing OYE genes. <lb/>Results: Recombinant S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2 strains, lacking endogenous OYE and expressing nine <lb/>separate OYE genes from non-conventional yeasts, were used as whole-cell biocatalysts to reduce substrates <lb/>with an electron-poor double bond activated by different electron-withdrawing groups. Ketoisophorone, <lb/>α-methyl-trans-cinnamaldehyde, and trans-β-methyl-β-nitrostyrene were successfully reduced with high rates <lb/>and selectivity. A series of four alkyl-substituted cyclohex-2-enones was tested to check the versatility and <lb/>efficiency of the biocatalysts. Reduction of double bond occurred with high rates and enantioselectivity, except <lb/>for 3,5,5-trimethyl-2-cyclohexenone. DFT (density functional theory) computational studies were performed to <lb/>investigate whether the steric hindrance and/or the electronic properties of the substrates were crucial for <lb/>reactivity. The three-dimensional structure of enoate reductases from Kluyveromyces lodderae and Candida <lb/>castellii, predicted through comparative modeling, resulted similar to that of S. cerevisiae OYE2 and revealed <lb/>the key role of Trp116 both in substrate specificity and stereocontrol. All the modeling studies indicate that steric <lb/>hindrance was a major determinant in the enzyme reactivity. <lb/>Conclusions: The OYE biocatalysts, based on recombinant S. cerevisiae expressing OYE genes from non-conventional <lb/>yeasts, were able to differently reduce the activated double bond of enones, enals and nitro-olefins, exhibiting <lb/>a wide range of substrate specificity. Moreover whole-cells biocatalysts bypassed the necessity of the cofactor <lb/>recycling and, tuning reaction parameters, allowed the synthetic exploitation of endogenous carbonyl reductases. <lb/>Molecular modeling studies highlighted key structural features for further improvement of catalytic properties of <lb/>OYE enzymes. <lb/>* Correspondence: stefano.raimondi@unimore.it <lb/>1 <lb/>Dipartimento di Scienze della Vita, Università degli Studi di Modena e <lb/>Reggio Emilia, Via G. Campi 183, 41125 Modena, Italy <lb/>Full list of author information is available at the end of the article <lb/>© 2014 Romano et al.; licensee BioMed Central Ltd. This is an Open Access article distributed under the terms of the Creative <lb/>Commons Attribution License (http://creativecommons.org/licenses/by/2.0), which permits unrestricted use, distribution, and <lb/>reproduction in any medium, provided the original work is properly credited. The Creative Commons Public Domain <lb/>Dedication waiver (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/) applies to the data made available in this article, <lb/>unless otherwise stated. <lb/>Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/>http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></front>

			<body>Background <lb/>Fine chemical industry is increasingly taking advantage <lb/>of biocatalysts to produce high-value products because <lb/>enzymes and whole-cell biocatalysts can be sometimes <lb/>more convenient than synthetic chemistry [1]. Biotrans-<lb/>formations occur under mild conditions of temperature, <lb/>pressure and pH, and may display their activity with high <lb/>chemo-, regio-and stereoselectivity [1,2]. Thus, biocataly-<lb/>sis has developed from a niche technology to a widely <lb/>used manufacturing method, and the availability of new <lb/>biocatalytic processes for the preparation of optically pure <lb/>molecules is very attractive for organic chemists. <lb/>Due to the increasing demand of optically pure building <lb/>blocks, considerable efforts are addressed at identifying, <lb/>characterizing, improving, and developing Old Yellow <lb/>Enzymes (OYE) biocatalysts, i.e. flavin-dependent eno-<lb/>ate reductases (EC 1.6.99.1), that catalyze the chemo-<lb/>and stereoselective hydrogenation of electron-poor al-<lb/>kenes [3,4]. Their biotechnological potential lies on the <lb/>ability to generate up to two stereocenters by the stereo-<lb/>selective anti-hydrogenation of the activated C = C double <lb/>bond, which is highly demanded in asymmetric synthesis, <lb/>since conventional chemical methods mostly give syn-<lb/>hydrogenation [5,6]. OYEs have been found in plants, <lb/>bacteria, and fungi [7-10], OYE1 from Saccharomyces <lb/>pastorianus being the first to be widely studied for <lb/>structure, substrate selectivity and stereoselectivity <lb/>[11-14]. In order to improve the tools for asymmetric <lb/>reductions of activated olefins, the biodiversity of non-<lb/>conventional yeasts was explored as well, and yielded <lb/>several novel OYE genes [15,16]. OYE genes from un-<lb/>conventional yeasts were cloned and expressed in Sac-<lb/>charomyces cerevisiae which was used as a whole-cell <lb/>biocatalyst, demonstrating the important role of uncon-<lb/>ventional yeasts as sources of novel biocatalysts and <lb/>their potential for the expansion of known genetic bio-<lb/>diversity [16]. <lb/>In the present study, recombinant strains of S. cerevisiae <lb/>lacking endogenous OYE and expressing eight OYE genes <lb/>from as many unconventional yeasts were used as whole-<lb/>cell biocatalysts to reduce different substrates with an acti-<lb/>vated electron-poor double bond, in order to compare <lb/>their catalytic and selectivity properties. It was investigated <lb/>whether the electronic properties and the steric hindrance <lb/>affected reactivity and/or enzyme stereoselectivity in the <lb/>asymmetric reduction. The structure of three selected en-<lb/>zymes was predicted through comparative modeling and <lb/>the active sites compared. The reactivity of the tested <lb/>substrates, has been also studied by means of electronic <lb/>computations, such as the lowest unoccupied molecular <lb/>orbitals (LUMO) distribution and OYE-substrate inter-<lb/>actions were analyzed to reveal the key features of the <lb/>structure and the sequence patterns of these new eno-<lb/>ate reductases. <lb/>Results and discussion <lb/>Asymmetric reductions with recombinant strains of <lb/>S. cerevisiae expressing OYE genes. <lb/>The strain S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2, that lacks en-<lb/>dogenous Oye2 gene and presents negligible overall OYE <lb/>activity [16], was used as the host to express the OYE <lb/>genes from S. cerevisiae BY4741 (OYE2), S. cerevisiae <lb/>L12, and from the unconventional yeasts Candida cas-<lb/>tellii DBVPG3704, Candida sake DBVPG6162, Kazach-<lb/>stania exigua L10, Kazachstania lodderae DBVPG6308, <lb/>Kazachstania spencerorum DBVPG6748, Nakaseomyces <lb/>bacillisporus DBVPG6945, and Naumovia castellii DBV <lb/>PG6298 [16]. Recombinant strains bearing heterologous <lb/>OYE genes were used as whole-cells biocatalysts to reduce <lb/>three molecules with electron-poor double bond activated <lb/>by different electron-withdrawing groups (Figure 1), i.e. <lb/>ketoisophorone (2,6,6-trimethylcyclohex-2-ene-1,4-dione, <lb/>1a), α-methyl-trans-cinnamaldehyde ((E)-2-methyl-3-phenyl-<lb/>2-propenal, 2a), and trans-β-methyl-β-nitrostyrene ((E)-<lb/>1-phenyl-2-nitropropene, 3a). <lb/>The activity towards 1a of the diverse recombinant <lb/>S. cerevisiae was evaluated using resting cells. The con-<lb/>version was at least 86% after 5 h and, for most of the <lb/>strains, was nearly complete after 24 h (Table 1). How-<lb/>ever, even though high efficiency of 1a transformation <lb/>was observed, and the reaction proceeded with prefer-<lb/>ence for the R-levodione (1b), the enantioselectivity <lb/>generally decreased compared to that obtained with <lb/>the corresponding wild type yeasts [16]. <lb/>The biotransformation of 2a by whole-cells of wild-<lb/>type Baker&apos;s yeast has been reported to result in a mix-<lb/>ture of saturated 2-methyl-3-phenylpropanol (2c) and <lb/>unsaturated primary alcohol 2-methyl-3-phenyl-2-prope-<lb/>nol (2d, Figure 1), with different ratios depending on the <lb/>strain and the experimental conditions [17,18]. Consist-<lb/>ently, the transformation of 2a using the wild type S. <lb/>cerevisiae BY4741 gave a mixture of 2c (78%) and 2d <lb/>(22%). On the contrary, S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2, that <lb/>lacks endogenous Oye2 gene, yielded 2d as the sole de-<lb/>tectable product, indicating the pivotal role of OYE2 <lb/>protein in the enoate reductase activity of the parental <lb/>strain [19]. Reduction of 2a with most of the recombin-<lb/>ant strains gave 2c as the only observed product by <lb/>means of the subsequent C = C and carbonyl reductions <lb/>(Table 1). The enhanced OYE activity of the recombin-<lb/>ant strains prevented the formation of 2d observed using <lb/>S. cerevisiae BY4741, with the exception of the strain ex-<lb/>pressing the C. castellii OYE gene that yielded a mixture <lb/>of 2c and 2d. Interestingly, enantioselectivity ranged be-<lb/>tween 59 and &gt; 98%, with four strains yielding (S)-2c as <lb/>the sole detectable enantiomer. <lb/>The majority of recombinant strains exhibited a high <lb/>rate in reducing 3a to 1-phenyl-2-nitropropane (3b), but <lb/>low e.e. (29-58%) was generally observed (Table 1). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 2 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>Similar behavior was observed with different microbial <lb/>whole-cells, where the scarce enantioselectivity was <lb/>mostly due to the easy racemization of the saturated <lb/>nitro-derivative [20]. <lb/>The data herein reported proved that the OYE biocata-<lb/>lysts, based on recombinant S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2 <lb/>expressing OYE genes from non-conventional yeasts, <lb/>were able to efficiently convert not only the enone 1a, a <lb/>well-established OYE substrate, but present a broader <lb/>substrate specificities being able to reduce also the acti-<lb/>vated C = C double bond of enals (2a) and nitro-olefins <lb/>(3a), showing that these systems seem to have a great <lb/>potential for synthetic chemists. <lb/>Bioconversion of a series of alkyl-substituted <lb/>cyclohex-2-enones <lb/>Recombinant strains were tested to reduce four alkyl-<lb/>substituted cyclohex-2-enones (4a, 5a, 6a, and 7a; Figure 1). <lb/>The substrates were selected in order to investigate the <lb/>versatility and efficiency of these biocatalysts, defining <lb/>how the electronic properties and steric hindrance <lb/>affect substrate reactivity and enzyme stereoselectivity <lb/>in the asymmetric reduction of double bond. <lb/>All the recombinant yeasts totally reduced 2-cyclohexenone <lb/>(4a) into cyclohexanone (4b) within 2 h (Table 2), <lb/>yielding no traces of cyclohex-2-enol or cyclohexanol <lb/>(4c), that could result from carbonyl reductases (CR) <lb/>activity on the keto group of 4a or 4b, respectively. <lb/>The strains also reduced 4,4-dimethyl-2-cyclohexe-<lb/>none (5a) into 4,4-dimethyl-cyclohexanone (5b) at a <lb/>good extent, with yields ranging between 76 and 97%. <lb/>The strains carrying the genes from Candida castellii <lb/>DBVPG3704 and Kazachstania lodderae DBVPG6308 <lb/>showed the lowest conversions and produced also 4,4-<lb/>dimethyl-2-cyclohexenol (5d; 20% and 15%, respectively) <lb/>through carbonyl reduction of 5a, indicating that CR be-<lb/>came competitive when C = C double bond reduction <lb/>was less effective. <lb/>The yeast bearing the OYE gene from C. castellii <lb/>DBVPG3704 was the only ineffective in the reduction of <lb/>3-methyl-2-cyclohexenone (6a). All the other strains re-<lb/>duced this substrate with high stereoselectivity (&gt;98%), <lb/>with homogeneous stereobias and formation of (S)-6b as <lb/>the sole detectable enantiomer. Small amounts of 3-<lb/>methylcyclohexanol (6c, 3-6%) were observed after 48 h. <lb/>Conversion yield of 6a towards 6b ranged from 23 to <lb/>75% after 72 h and was lower compared to the conver-<lb/>sion of substrates 4a and 5a. Consistently, previous stud-<lb/>ies proved that 6a is a &apos;difficult&apos; substrate for enoate <lb/>reductases, due to the presence of a substituent on the <lb/>C3 position [21,22]. All the recombinant strains failed to <lb/>transform α-isophorone (3,5,5-trimethyl-2-cyclohexenone, <lb/>7a), neither the C = C or C = O double bonds being re-<lb/>duced after 72 h. <lb/>OYE <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>8a <lb/>8b <lb/>8c <lb/>OYE <lb/>CR <lb/>7a <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>O <lb/>1a <lb/>1b <lb/>1c <lb/>CR <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>NO 2 <lb/>3a <lb/>3b <lb/>OYE <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>6a <lb/>6b <lb/>6c <lb/>OYE <lb/>CR <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>4a <lb/>4b <lb/>4c <lb/>OYE <lb/>CR <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>OH <lb/>5a <lb/>5b <lb/>5c <lb/>5d <lb/>OYE <lb/>CR <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>CH 2 OH <lb/>CH 2 OH <lb/>2a <lb/>2d <lb/>2b <lb/>2c <lb/>CR <lb/>OYE <lb/>CR <lb/>CR <lb/>Figure 1 Tested substrates and main products observed during <lb/>bioreductions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 3 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>As a whole, most of the nine recombinant strains exhib-<lb/>ited similar activity toward the tested cyclohexenone deriv-<lb/>atives and a common stereobias was observed toward 6a. <lb/>Moreover, substrates 4a, 5a, 6a and 7a which are increas-<lb/>ingly sterically hindered, were progressively less reactive in <lb/>C = C reduction. The electronic features of the tested sub-<lb/>strates and the structural properties of the investigated <lb/>OYEs will be thoroughly described in a following section. <lb/>Computational analysis: evaluation of substrate electronic <lb/>features, and OYE three-dimensional structure prediction <lb/>through comparative modeling <lb/>The enoate reductases preferentially reduce substrates <lb/>containing electron-poor double bonds [3]. In order to <lb/>evaluate the electronic features of the tested substrates, a <lb/>geometry optimization in the gas phase with an approach <lb/>based on density functional theory (DFT/B3LYP/6-31G*) <lb/>was performed, resulting in prediction of the double bond <lb/>lengths and of the electrostatic potential (ESP) derived <lb/>charges for the C atom involved in the hydride attack of <lb/>the substrates (Table 3). A further characterization has <lb/>been carried out by the analysis of the lowest unoccupied <lb/>molecular orbitals (LUMO) for the investigated substrates. <lb/>The surfaces were rendered in order to encapsulate ap-<lb/>proximately 80% of the integral of the evaluated grid points <lb/>(Figure 2). Based on the length of the double bonds, 4a, <lb/>5a, 6a, and 7a resulted very similar. The values 1.34 Å for <lb/>substrates 4a and 5a and 1.35 Å for substrates 6a and 7a, <lb/>typical of the sp 2 hybridization state, were not sufficiently <lb/>different to explain a diverse reactivity based on elec-<lb/>tronic configurations. The comparison among the LUMO <lb/>frontier orbitals revealed very similar configuration and <lb/>Table 1 Bioreductions of ketoisophorone (1a), α-methyl-trans-cinnamaldehyde (2a), and trans-β-methyl-β-nitrostyrene <lb/>(3a), with recombinant S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2 bearing heterologous OYE genes <lb/>OYE gene source <lb/>1a → 1b* <lb/>2a → 2c <lb/>3a → 3b <lb/>Time <lb/>1b <lb/>(R)-1b <lb/>Time <lb/>2c <lb/>(S)-2c <lb/>Time <lb/>3b <lb/>(R)-3b <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>e.e.% <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>e.e.% <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>e.e.% <lb/>C. castellii DBVPG3704 <lb/>5 <lb/>≥ 99 <lb/>70 <lb/>24 <lb/>70 † <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>2 <lb/>45 <lb/>50 <lb/>C. sake DBVPG6162 <lb/>5 <lb/>97 <lb/>71 <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>59 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>93 <lb/>48 <lb/>K. exigua L10 <lb/>5 <lb/>94 <lb/>82 <lb/>24 <lb/>100 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>97 <lb/>30 <lb/>K. lodderae DBVPG6308 <lb/>5 <lb/>≥ 99 <lb/>78 <lb/>16 <lb/>100 <lb/>80 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>97 <lb/>58 <lb/>K. spencerorum DBVPG6748 <lb/>5 <lb/>96 <lb/>65 <lb/>3 <lb/>100 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>94 <lb/>50 <lb/>Nak. bacillisporus DBVPG6945 <lb/>5 <lb/>98 <lb/>68 <lb/>2 <lb/>100 <lb/>95 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>92 <lb/>40 <lb/>Nau. castellii DBVPG6298 <lb/>5 <lb/>93 <lb/>78 <lb/>2 <lb/>100 <lb/>85 <lb/>5 <lb/>92 <lb/>29 <lb/>S. cerevisiae BY4741 (Oye2) <lb/>5 <lb/>89 <lb/>80 <lb/>2 <lb/>100 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>1 <lb/>96 <lb/>50 <lb/>S. cerevisiae L12 <lb/>5 <lb/>86 <lb/>79 <lb/>2 <lb/>100 <lb/>72 <lb/>2 <lb/>95 <lb/>44 <lb/>Data are reported as molar conversion (%). *Results from Raimondi et al. 2010. † 30% of compound 2d was also observed. The experiment were performed in <lb/>triplicate, the yield standard deviations (SD) were always less than 4%, and the ee% SD were always less than 3%. <lb/>Table 2 Bioreductions of alkyl-substituted cyclohex-2-enones (substrates 4a, 5a, 6a, and 7a # ) with recombinant <lb/>S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2 bearing heterologous OYE genes <lb/>OYE gene source <lb/>4a → 4b <lb/>5a → 5b <lb/>6a → 6b ‡ <lb/>Time <lb/>Yield <lb/>Time <lb/>Yield <lb/>Time <lb/>Yield <lb/>(S)-6b <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>h <lb/>% <lb/>e.e.% <lb/>C. castellii DBVPG3704 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 99 <lb/>2 <lb/>76 † <lb/>72 <lb/>&lt; 5 <lb/>n.d. <lb/>C. sake DBVPG6162 <lb/>1 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>1 <lb/>9 5 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>7 5 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>K. exigua L10 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>2 <lb/>9 2 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>2 3 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>K. lodderae DBVPG6308 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 99 <lb/>2 <lb/>84 † <lb/>72 <lb/>25 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>K. spencerorum DBVPG6748 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>1 <lb/>9 5 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>6 0 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>Nak. bacillisporus DBVPG6945 <lb/>1 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>2 <lb/>9 4 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>Nau. castellii DBVPG6298 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>2 <lb/>9 5 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>5 3 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>S. cerevisiae BY4741 (Oye2) <lb/>1 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>2 <lb/>9 6 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>4 5 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>S. cerevisiae L12 <lb/>2 <lb/>≥ 9 9 <lb/>1 <lb/>9 7 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>4 0 <lb/>≥ 98 <lb/>Data are reported as molar conversion (%). # No conversion of compound 7a was observed in the first 72 h. † 15-20% of compound 5d was also observed; ‡ product <lb/>6c was always less than 15%. The experiment were performed in triplicate, the yield standard deviations (SD) were always less than 4%, and the ee% SD were <lb/>always less than 3%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 4 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>reactivity around the sp 2 carbons of all the substrates. <lb/>Conversely, computed ESP charges suggested that sub-<lb/>strates 5a, 6a, and 7a were the most favored for the <lb/>reduction of the double bond, outcome partially in <lb/>contrast with bioconversion data indicating 6a and 7a <lb/>as &quot;difficult&quot; substrates. <lb/>The data herein presented demonstrated that the dif-<lb/>ferent reactivity of these substrates cannot be ascribed to <lb/>their electronic configurations. As a whole, the sub-<lb/>strates which are increasingly sterically hindered, were <lb/>progressively less reactive in double bond reduction and <lb/>their electronic properties do not affect this behavior. <lb/>In order to evaluate the role of steric hindrance with re-<lb/>spect to the substrate selectivity, the three-dimensional <lb/>structures of the S. cerevisiae OYE2 and of the K. lodderae <lb/>DBVPG6308 and C. castellii DBVPG3704 enoate reduc-<lb/>tases were predicted through comparative modeling, <lb/>using the structure of the S. pastorianus OYE1 (RCSB <lb/>PDB: 1OYA) as template [11]. These three enzymes were <lb/>chosen because, when overexpressed in S. cerevisiae <lb/>BY4741ΔOye2, the corresponding recombinant strains ex-<lb/>hibited different activity and/or enantioselectivity towards <lb/>many of the tested substrates. The proteins and the tem-<lb/>plate OYE1 share a very high level of identity, ranging from <lb/>73 to 91% (Table 4, Figure 3). The active sites are highly <lb/>conserved and few differences in amino acid composition <lb/>are present (Table 5). Furthermore, similar distances be-<lb/>tween the three core amino acids (His191, Asn194, and <lb/>Tyr196) belonging to the catalytic site have been calculated <lb/>(Table 6). The high identity between both the primary <lb/>structures of the investigated OYEs and the low root mean <lb/>square deviation (RMSD) values for the modeled structures <lb/>suggested that the different transformation rates of the <lb/>tested substrates can hardly be ascribed only to the struc-<lb/>tural diversity elucidated by our computational work. <lb/>The substrate α-isophorone (7a) was not reduced by <lb/>OYEs, although electronic features suggested a good re-<lb/>activity, likely because of a dramatic steric effect. A <lb/>docking study of this molecule have been performed on <lb/>the predicted structure of OYE2 protein. The repulsive <lb/>van der Waals interactions between the alkylic groups of <lb/>substrate 7a and Trp116 of OYE2 confirmed that steric <lb/>hindrance was present (Figure 4). Consistently, in a pre-<lb/>vious study, the interactions between substrates and <lb/>Trp116 in the active site of S. pastorianus OYE1 influ-<lb/>enced the catalytic activity of the enzyme and the stereo-<lb/>chemistry of the products [23]. <lb/>The analysis of the unfavorable contacts between the side <lb/>chain of Trp116 and the substrates confirmed that the <lb/>transformation efficiency on a series of alkyl-substituted <lb/>cyclohex-2-enones was associated to the length of the <lb/>alkyl-substituent. The larger was the substrate hindrance, <lb/>the lower was the reactivity. Furthermore, the pivotal role <lb/>of Trp116 on catalytic properties of OYE enzymes has <lb/>been highlighted, suggesting this key structural features as <lb/>an hot spot for modification and further improvement of <lb/>the biocatalysts. <lb/>Whole-cell OYE biocatalysts: synthetic exploitation tuning <lb/>reaction time <lb/>Biotransformation of αβ-unsaturated carbonyls occurred <lb/>with carbonyl reduction by endogenous CR as side-<lb/>reaction. Thus, the biotransformations of substrates 4a, <lb/>Table 3 Electronic features of the alkyl-substituted <lb/>cyclohex-2-enones predicted by DFT calculations <lb/>Substrate <lb/>Double bond length <lb/>ESP charge <lb/>4a <lb/>1.34 Å <lb/>-0.003 <lb/>5a <lb/>1.34 Å <lb/>-0.174 <lb/>6a <lb/>1.35 Å <lb/>0.350 <lb/>7a <lb/>1.35 Å <lb/>0.404 <lb/>4a <lb/>5a <lb/>6a <lb/>7a <lb/>Figure 2 Lower Unoccupied Molecular Orbitals (LUMO) of the <lb/>alkyl-substituted cyclohex-2-enones. <lb/>Table 4 OYE sequences alignment <lb/>1OYA <lb/>OYE2 <lb/>OYE from <lb/>K. lodderae <lb/>OYE from <lb/>C. castellii <lb/>1OYA <lb/>-<lb/>91.0 <lb/>77.2 <lb/>74.8 <lb/>OYE2 <lb/>91.0 <lb/>-<lb/>77.7 <lb/>73.2 <lb/>OYE from K. lodderae <lb/>77.2 <lb/>77.7 <lb/>-<lb/>77.4 <lb/>OYE from C. castellii <lb/>74.8 <lb/>73.2 <lb/>77.4 <lb/>-<lb/>Sequence identity (%) among the template 1OYA and the three OYE proteins <lb/>selected for the structure prediction through comparative modelling. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 5 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>5a, 6a, and 8a were analyzed until prolonged reaction <lb/>times, in order to obtain also the reduction of the car-<lb/>bonyl group. In all cases we observed a prevailing OYE <lb/>activity in the first hours of reaction, while at longer <lb/>times the carbonyl reductase activity led to the forma-<lb/>tion of the saturated alcohols (Figure 5). More in detail, <lb/>using 4a as substrate, it was possible to quantitatively re-<lb/>cover 4b after 2 hours of reaction. Later (144 h), the en-<lb/>dogenous carbonyl reductase(s) led to the formation of <lb/>4c, with high yield (97%). The same behavior was ob-<lb/>served with substrate 8a: at short reaction times (2 h) <lb/>the OYE product (R)-8b was almost (99%) the only <lb/>chemical species present, whereas a 1/10 ratio between <lb/>8b and 8c was observed after 168 h; the stereochemical <lb/>analysis of 8c showed that the ratio (1S,2R)-8c/ <lb/>(1R,2R)-8c was 70/30. The bioreduction of 6a, that is a <lb/>less reactive substrate, proceeded with the concomitant <lb/>formation of 6b and 6c; 6b was obtained with high <lb/>enantioselectivity (e.e. &gt; 98%). The saturated alcohol (6c) <lb/>was the minor product during the first hours of reaction <lb/>and became the sole product after 120 h; 6c was produced <lb/>with a syn/anti composition of 75/25. In the case of 5a, <lb/>bioreductions proceeded faster: the saturated ketone 5b <lb/>was produced at 95% molar conversion after 1 h while 5c <lb/>reached 95% after 48 h of biotransformation. <lb/>Overall, our whole-cells system, compared to the use <lb/>of purified enzymes, showed a peculiar synthetic advan-<lb/>tage: with a unique biocatalyst, tuning the reaction time, <lb/>it is possible to have access to different molecules, with <lb/>high yields, starting from a single substrate. <lb/>Conclusions <lb/>S. cerevisiae is well suited for biotechnological applica-<lb/>tions owing to the wealth of the genetic techniques <lb/>available, the ease of manipulation and the rapid <lb/>growth rates. The expression in the host S. cerevisiae <lb/>BY4741ΔOye2 of the OYE genes make possible the ex-<lb/>ploitation of these technological feature leading to the <lb/>development of efficient biocatalysts base on yeast cells. <lb/>The recombinant S. cerevisiae, showed a wide range of <lb/>substrate specificity, being able to reduce the activated <lb/>C = C double bond of enones, enals and nitro-olefins. <lb/>Moreover, whole-cells biocatalysts bypassed the neces-<lb/>sity of the cofactor recycling and, tuning reaction pa-<lb/>rameters, allowed the synthetic exploitation of the <lb/>endogenous carbonyl reductases. Versatility and effi-<lb/>ciency of these biocatalysts was analyzed revealing that <lb/>the different reactivity was not ascribed to substrate <lb/>electronic properties, but steric hindrance resulted the <lb/>most relevant factor affecting the asymmetric reduction <lb/>of double bond. Molecular modeling studies on OYE <lb/>proteins highlighted the pivotal role of Trp116 both in <lb/>activity and stereochemistry and it was established as a <lb/>key structural features for further improvement of cata-<lb/>lytic properties of OYE enzymes. <lb/>Methods <lb/>Strains and culture conditions <lb/>Recombinant S. cerevisiae BY4741ΔOye2 strains (bearing <lb/>OYE genes from Candida castellii DBVPG3704, Can-<lb/>dida sake DBVPG6162, Naumovia castellii DBVPG6298, <lb/>Figure 3 Sequence alignment of OYE proteins. Sequence alignment among the template 1OYA from S. pastorianus and the three OYE <lb/>proteins selected for the structure prediction through comparative modelling. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 6 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>Kazachstania exigua L10, Kazachstania lodderae DBVP <lb/>G6308, Kazachstania spencerorum DBVPG6748, Naka-<lb/>seomyces bacillisporus DBVPG6945, Saccharomyces cere-<lb/>visiae BY4741 (Oye2), and Saccharomyces cerevisiae <lb/>L12) were prepared as described earlier [16]. Strains were <lb/>routinely maintained on YNB agar medium (DifcoTM <lb/>Yeast Nitrogen Base without aminoacids 6.7 g/L, glucose <lb/>20 g/L, histidine 0.15 g/L, leucine 0.73 g/L, methionine <lb/>0.15 g/L) and grown in YNB liquid medium, in baf-<lb/>fled Erlenmeyer flasks on orbital shaker at 30°C and <lb/>150 rpm. <lb/>Biotransformations <lb/>Recombinant cells grown for 24 h were centrifuged <lb/>(5000 rpm for 10 min at 4°C), washed and resuspended <lb/>at a concentration of 15 AU of OD 600 in 100 mM phos-<lb/>phate buffer at pH 7, containing 50 g/L glucose. Sub-<lb/>strate stock solutions (200 g/L) prepared in ethanol were <lb/>added to the reaction obtaining 1 g/L of substrate <lb/>concentration. Biotransformations were carried out in <lb/>baffled Erlenmeyer flasks on orbital shaker, incubated at <lb/>30°C and 150 rpm. Samples for analysis were extracted 1:1 <lb/>with EtOAc containing 0.05% (v/v) of 1-phenylethanol as <lb/>internal GC standard and dried over Na 2 SO 4 . At the end <lb/>of the biotransformation, the whole reaction mixture was <lb/>centrifuged and the aqueous supernatant extracted three <lb/>times with EtOAc. The combined organic phases were <lb/>dried over Na 2 SO 4 and the residue purified by flash <lb/>chromatography. <lb/>Analytical methods <lb/>Gas chromatographic analysis were performed on a Dani <lb/>86.10 HT instrument (Dani Instruments, Italy; carrier <lb/>H 2 , 0.6 bar, FID detector), using a MEGA-DEX DET-Beta <lb/>(column A; Mega Snc, Legnano, Italy) chiral column or a <lb/>SE30 polydimethylsiloxane non-chiral column (column B), <lb/>under the following conditions. Bioreduction of 1a: column <lb/>A; 45°C for 2 min, 5°min -1 rate to 130°C, 30°min -1 to <lb/>200°C; retention times: 1a 18.0 min, (R)-1b 19.2 min, <lb/>(S)-1b 19.5 min. Bioreduction of 2a: column A; 95°C, <lb/>1°min -1 rate to 120°C, 30°min -1 to 200°C; retention <lb/>times: 2a 31.0 min, (R)-2b 16.4 min, (S)-2b 16.7 min, <lb/>(R)-2c 28.7 min, (S)-2c 29.2 min, 2d 19.4 min. Bioreduc-<lb/>tion of 3a: column B; 105°C for 5 min, 1°min -1 rate to <lb/>115°C, 30°min -1 to 200°C; retention times 3a 20.4 min, <lb/>(R)-3b 18.8 min, (S)-3b 19.0 min. Bioreduction of 4a: col-<lb/>umn B; 55°C isotherm analysis; retention times 4a 5.1 min, <lb/>4b 4.1 min. Bioreduction of 5a: column B; 60°C for 3 min, <lb/>1°C min -1 rate to 140°C, 30°min -1 to 200°C; retention <lb/>times 5a 14.6 min, 5b 14.0 min, 5c 16.9 min, 5d 16.2 min. <lb/>Bioreduction of 6a: column A; 50°C, 1°C min -1 rate to <lb/>150°, 30°min -1 to 200°C; retention times 6a 20.9 min, <lb/>(R)-6b 13.0 min, (S)-6b 13.7 min. Column B; 40°C iso-<lb/>therm analysis; retention times 6a 25.3 min, 6b 11.4 min, <lb/>6c 12.3 min. Bioreduction of 7a: column A; 60°C for <lb/>5 min, 3°C min -1 to 100°C, 30°min -1 to 200°C; retention <lb/>times 7a 19.5 min. Bioreduction of 8a: column A; 50°C for <lb/>5 min, 5°C min -1 rate to 150°, 30°min -1 to 200°C; reten-<lb/>tion times 8a 19.8 min, (R)-8b 12.3, (S)-8b 13.0. Column B; <lb/>50°C for 5 min, 5°C min -1 rate to 120°, 30°min -1 to <lb/>200°C; retention times 8a 8.70 min, 8b 7.02 min, 8c <lb/>7.35 min. Biotransformation products were identified by <lb/>comparison with authentic reference materials. The abso-<lb/>lute configuration and e.e. of 6b and 8b were determined <lb/>by co-injection in chiral GC with reference materials of <lb/>known absolute configuration [21 and references therein]. <lb/>Table 6 OYEs catalytic triad <lb/>Protein <lb/>His-Asn <lb/>His-Tyr <lb/>Tyr-Asn <lb/>OYE2 <lb/>6.5 <lb/>6.8 <lb/>5.1 <lb/>K. lodderae <lb/>7.5 <lb/>6.0 <lb/>5.3 <lb/>C. castellii <lb/>7.3 <lb/>5.6 <lb/>5.5 <lb/>Distances between the core amino acids belonging to the catalytic site <lb/>(His191, Asn194, and Tyr196) in the three modelled OYEs (Å). <lb/>Table 5 Amino acid composition of OYE active sites <lb/>Position <lb/>OYE2 <lb/>OYE from K. lodderae <lb/>OYE from C. castellii <lb/>82 <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>116 <lb/>TRP <lb/>TRP <lb/>TRP <lb/>117 <lb/>VAL <lb/>VAL <lb/>VAL <lb/>118 <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>119 <lb/>GLY <lb/>GLY <lb/>GLY <lb/>120 <lb/>TRP <lb/>ARG <lb/>ARG <lb/>121 <lb/>ALA <lb/>GLN <lb/>GLN <lb/>122 <lb/>ALA <lb/>GLY <lb/>GLY <lb/>191 <lb/>HIS <lb/>HIS <lb/>HIS <lb/>192 <lb/>SER <lb/>SER <lb/>SER <lb/>193 <lb/>ALA <lb/>ALA <lb/>ALA <lb/>194 <lb/>ASN <lb/>ASN <lb/>ASN <lb/>195 <lb/>GLY <lb/>SER <lb/>SER <lb/>196 <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>197 <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>198 <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>LEU <lb/>199 <lb/>ASN <lb/>ASN <lb/>ASN <lb/>200 <lb/>GLN <lb/>GLN <lb/>GLN <lb/>201 <lb/>PHE <lb/>PHE <lb/>PHE <lb/>250 <lb/>PHE <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>251 <lb/>ASN <lb/>GLY <lb/>GLY <lb/>253 <lb/>MET <lb/>MET <lb/>MET <lb/>295 <lb/>PRO <lb/>SER <lb/>PRO <lb/>296 <lb/>PHE <lb/>PHE <lb/>PHE <lb/>375 <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>TYR <lb/>Differences are highlighted in bold. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 7 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>Stereoisomeric composition of 6c and 8c were determined <lb/>by 1 H NMR [24] after purification of the products. <lb/>Computational details <lb/>All the comparative modeling procedures were carried out <lb/>with the Homology module of the Molecular Operating <lb/>Environment 2011.10 (MOE; Chemical Computing Group <lb/>Inc., Montreal, QC, Canada). The alignment produced by <lb/>the Align program of MOE with default parameters was <lb/>manually adjusted. Comparative model building was car-<lb/>ried out with the MOE Homology Model program. 1OYA <lb/>(S. pastorianus OYE1) was set as template for all the mod-<lb/>eled sequences. For each sequence, ten independent <lb/>models were built and refined, and then the highest <lb/>Figure 4 Repulsive van der waals interactions between the alkyl groups of α-isophorone (7a) and OYE2 Trp116. <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>9 6 <lb/>1 2 0 <lb/>time (h) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>9 6 <lb/>1 2 0 <lb/>1 4 4 <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>2 4 <lb/>4 8 <lb/>7 2 <lb/>9 6 <lb/>1 2 0 <lb/>1 4 4 <lb/>time (h) <lb/>0 <lb/>20 <lb/>40 <lb/>60 <lb/>80 <lb/>100 <lb/>0 <lb/>8 <lb/>16 <lb/>24 <lb/>32 <lb/>40 <lb/>48 <lb/>substrate, products (%) <lb/>substrate, products <lb/>(%) <lb/>4a <lb/>5a <lb/>6a <lb/>8a <lb/>Figure 5 Bioreductions of alkyl-substituted cyclohex-2-enones (substrates 4a, 5a, 6a, and 8a) until prolonged reaction times. Data are <lb/>reported as molar conversion (%). Blue line and circles: substrates. Red line and squares: OYE products; Green line and diamonds: OYE and CR <lb/>products. The curves were representative of three independent experiments and the standard deviations were always less than 4%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 8 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 <lb/></note>

			<body>scoring intermediate model was submitted to a further <lb/>round of energy minimization (EM). For both the inter-<lb/>mediate and the final structures the refinement proce-<lb/>dures consisted in EM runs based on the AMBER99 force <lb/>field, with the reaction field solvation model. <lb/>Geometry optimization and electronic computations of <lb/>the substrates were carried out in the gas phase through <lb/>the MOE SCF Calculation interface to the GAMESS soft-<lb/>ware [25,26]. The DFT calculations were based on the <lb/>B3LYP hybrid functional with the 6-31G* basis set. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Abbreviations <lb/>OYE: Old Yellow Enzyme (enoate reductase); CR: Carbonyl reductase; <lb/>1a: 2,6,6-trimethylcyclohex-2-ene-1,4-dione [ketoisophorone]; 1b: 2,2,6-<lb/>trimethylcyclohexane-1,4-dione [(6R)-levodione]; 1c: 4-hydroxy-2,2,6-<lb/>trimethylcyclohexaone [(4R, 6R)-actinol]; 2a: (E)-2-methyl-3-phenyl-2-propenal <lb/>[α-methyl-trans-cinnamaldehyde]; 2b: 2-methyl-3-phenylpropanal; 2c: 2-methyl-<lb/>3-phenylpropanol; 2d: 2-methyl-3-phenyl-2-propenol; 3a: (E)-1-phenyl-2-<lb/>nitropropene [trans-β-methyl-β-nitrostyrene]; 3b: 1-phenyl-2-nitropropane; <lb/>4a: 2-cyclohexenone; 4b: Cyclohexanone; 4c: Cyclohexanol; 5a: 4,4-dimethyl-2-<lb/>cyclohexenone; 5b: 4,4-dimethylcyclohexanone; 5c: 4,4-dimethylcyclohexanol; <lb/>5d: 4,4-dimethyl-2-cyclohexenol; 6a: 3-methyl-2-cyclohexenone; 6b: 3-<lb/>methylcyclohexanone; 6c: 3-methylcyclohexanol; 7a: 3,5,5-trimethyl-2-<lb/>cyclohexenone [α-isophorone]; 8a: 2-methyl-2-cyclohexenone; 8b: 2-<lb/>methylcyclohexanone; 8c: 2-methylcyclohexanol; DFT: Density functional theory; <lb/>ESP: Electrostatic potential; LUMO: Lowest Unoccupied Molecular Orbitals. <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Competing interests <lb/>The authors declare that they have no competing interests. <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">Authors&apos; contributions <lb/>DR and SR conceived the study, performed the experimental work and drafted <lb/>the manuscript. MC performed bioreductions and chemical analysis. ER and CS <lb/>contributed to the computational analysis. AA, FM, IE and MR accomplished <lb/>data interpretation, participated in the design of the study, and writing of the <lb/>manuscript. All authors read and approved the final manuscript. <lb/></div>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>The authors are most grateful to Dr. Luca Bertini from the Università degli <lb/>Studi di Milano Bicocca for fruitful discussion on DFT application. <lb/></div>

			<front>Author details <lb/>1 <lb/>Dipartimento di Scienze della Vita, Università degli Studi di Modena e <lb/>Reggio Emilia, Via G. Campi 183, 41125 Modena, Italy. 2 Department of Food, <lb/>Environmental and Nutritional Sciences (DeFENS), University of Milan, Via G. <lb/>Celoria 2, 20133 Milan, Italy. 3 Dipartimento di Scienze Farmacologiche e <lb/>Biomolecolari, Università degli Studi di Milano, Via Trentacoste 2, 20134 <lb/>Milan, Italy. <lb/>Received: 8 January 2014 Accepted: 15 April 2014 <lb/>Published: 25 April 2014 <lb/></front>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Panke S, Held M, Wubbolts M: Trends and innovations in industrial <lb/>biocatalysis for the production of fine chemicals. Curr Opin Biotechnol <lb/>2004, 15:272-279. <lb/>2. Faber K: Biotransformations in Organic Chemistry: A Textbook. 6th edition. <lb/>Berlin, Heidelberg: Springer; 2011. <lb/>3. Stuermer R, Hauer B, Hall M, Faber K: Asymmetric bioreduction of <lb/>activated C = C bonds using enoate reductases from the old yellow <lb/>enzyme family. Curr Opin Chem Biol 2007, 11:203-213. <lb/>4. Williams RE, Bruce NC: &quot;New uses for an Old Enzyme&quot; -the Old Yellow <lb/>Enzyme family of flavoenzymes. Microbiology 2002, 148:1607-1614. <lb/>5. Blaser HU, Malan C, Pugin B, Spindler F, Steiner H, Studer M: Selective <lb/>hydrogenation for fine chemicals: recent trends and new developments. <lb/>Adv Synth Catal 2003, 345:103-151. <lb/>6. De Wildeman SMA, Sonke T, Schoemaker HE, May O: Biocatalytic reductions: <lb/>from lab curiosity to &quot;first choice&quot;. Acc Chem Res 2007, 40:1260-1266. <lb/>7. Strassner J, Fürholz A, Macheroux P, Amrhein N, Schaller A: A homolog of old <lb/>yellow enzyme in tomato. Spectral properties and substrate specificity of <lb/>the recombinant protein. J Biol Chem 1999, 274:35067-35073. <lb/>8. Brigé A, Van Den Hemel D, Carpentier W, De Smet L, Van Beeumen JJ: <lb/>Comparative characterization and expression analysis of the four Old <lb/>Yellow Enzyme homologues from Shewanella oneidensis indicate <lb/>differences in physiological function. Biochem J 2006, 394:335-344. <lb/>9. Kataoka M, Kotaka A, Thiwthong R, Wada M, Nakamori S, Shimizu S: Cloning <lb/>and overexpression of the old yellow enzyme gene of Candida <lb/>macedoniensis, and its application to the production of a chiral <lb/>compound. J Biotechnol 2004, 114:1-9. <lb/>10. Arnone A, Cardillo R, Nasini G, Depava OV: Enantioselective reduction of <lb/>racemic abscisic acid by Aspergillus niger cultures. J Chem Soc Perkin Trans <lb/>1 1990, 11:3061-3063. <lb/>11. Fox KM, Karplus PA: Old yellow enzyme at 2 Å resolution: overall <lb/>structure, ligand binding, and comparison with related flavoproteins. <lb/>Structure 1994, 2:1089-1105. <lb/>12. Meah Y, Massey V: Old yellow enzyme: stepwise reduction of nitro-olefins <lb/>and catalysis of aci-nitro tautomerization. Proc Natl Acad Sci 2000, <lb/>97:10733-10738. <lb/>13. Swiderska MA, Stewart JD: Stereoselective enone reductions by <lb/>Saccharomyces carlsbergensis old yellow enzyme. J Mol Catal B: Enzym <lb/>2006, 42:52-54. <lb/>14. Vaz AD, Chakraborty S, Massey V: Old Yellow enzyme: aromatization of <lb/>cyclic enones and the mechanism of a novel dismutation reaction. <lb/>Biochemistry 1995, 34:4246-4256. <lb/>15. Raimondi S, Roncaglia L, Amaretti A, Leonardi A, Buzzini P, Forti L, Rossi M: <lb/>Rapid method for screening enoate reductase activity in yeasts. J <lb/>Microbiol Methods 2010, 83:106-110. <lb/>16. Raimondi S, Romano D, Amaretti A, Molinari F, Rossi M: Enoate reductases <lb/>from non conventional yeasts: bioconversion, cloning, and functional <lb/>expression in Saccharomyces cerevisiae. J Biotechnol 2010, 156:279-285. <lb/>17. Fardelone LC, Augusto J, Rodrigues R, Moran PJ: Baker&apos;s yeast mediated <lb/>asymmetric reduction of cinnamaldehyde derivatives. J Mol Catal B: <lb/>Enzym 2004, 29:41-45. <lb/>18. Fuganti C, Chiringhelli D, Grasselli P: Stereochemical course of the <lb/>reduction of cinnamaldehyde and cinnamyl alcohol to 3-phenylpropanol <lb/>by fermenting Baker&apos;s yeast. J Chem Soc Chem Commun 1975, 20:846-847. <lb/>19. Contente M, Granato T, Remelli W, Zambelli P, Raimondi S, Rossi M, Romano <lb/>D: Complementary microbial approaches for the preparation of optically <lb/>pure aromatic molecules. Ann Microbiol 2013, 63(3):1021-1027. <lb/>20. Mori A, Ishiyama I, Akita H, Suzuki K, Mitsuoka T, Oishi T: Reduction of <lb/>nitroolefin using microorganisms. Chem Pharm Bull 1990, 38:3449-3451. <lb/>21. Hall M, Stueckler C, Ehammer H, Pointner E, Oberdorfer G: Asymmetric <lb/>bioreduction of C = C bonds using enoate reductases OPR1, OPR3 and <lb/>YqjM: enzyme-based stereocontrol. Adv Synth Catal 2008, 350:411-418. <lb/>22. Hall M, Stueckler C, Hauer B, Stuermer R, Friedrich T, Breuer M, Kroutil W, <lb/>Faber K: Asymmetric bioreduction of activated c = c bonds Using <lb/>Zymomonas mobilis NCR Enoate reductase and Old Yellow Enzymes OYE <lb/>1-3 from yeasts. Eur J Org Chem 2008, 9:1511-1516. <lb/>23. Padhi SK, Bougioukou DJ, Stewart JD: Site-saturation mutagenesis of <lb/>tryptophan 116 of Saccharomyces pastorianus old yellow enzyme uncovers <lb/>stereocomplementary variants. J Am Chem Soc 2009, 131:3271-3280. <lb/>24. Solladié-Cavallo A, Barama A, Choucaira E, Norouzi-Arasib H, Schmit M, Garin <lb/>F: Heterogeneous hydrogenation of substituted phenols over Al2O3 <lb/>supported ruthenium. J Mol Cat A Chem 2007, 273:92-98. <lb/>25. Schmidt MW, Baldridge KK, Boatz JA, Elbert ST, Gordon MS, Jensen JH, <lb/>Koseki S, Matsunaga N, Nguyen KA, Su S, Windus TL, Dupuis M, <lb/>Montgomery JA: General atomic and molecular electronic structure <lb/>system. J Comput Chem 1993, 14:1347-1363. <lb/>26. Gordon MS, Schmidt MW: Chapter 41 -Advances in electronic structure <lb/>theory: GAMESS a decade later. In Theory and Applications of <lb/>Computational Chemistry. Edited by Dykstra CE, Frenking G, Kim KS, Scuseria <lb/>GE. Amsterdam: Elsevier; 2005:1167-1189. <lb/></listBibl>

			<front>doi:10.1186/1475-2859-13-60 <lb/>Cite this article as: Romano et al.: Recombinant S. cerevisiae expressing <lb/>Old Yellow Enzymes from non-conventional yeasts: an easy system for <lb/>selective reduction of activated alkenes. Microbial Cell Factories 2014 13:60. <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Romano et al. Microbial Cell Factories 2014, 13:60 <lb/></note>

			<page>Page 9 of 9 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">http://www.microbialcellfactories.com/content/13/1/60 </note>


	</text>
</tei>