<?xml version="1.0"?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>ARTICLE <lb/>Received 21 Dec 2016 | Accepted 27 Apr 2017 | Published 8 Jun 2017 <lb/>Synthesis and preliminary PET imaging of 11 C <lb/>and 18 F isotopologues of the ROS1/ALK inhibitor <lb/>lorlatinib <lb/>Thomas Lee Collier 1,2 , Marc D. Normandin 1 , Nickeisha A. Stephenson 1,w , Eli Livni 1 , Steven H. Liang 1 , <lb/>Dustin W. Wooten 1 , Shadi A. Esfahani 1 , Michael G. Stabin 3 , Umar Mahmood 1 , Jianqing Chen 4 , Wei Wang 5 , <lb/>Kevin Maresca 4 , Rikki N. Waterhouse 4,w , Georges El Fakhri 1 , Paul Richardson 5 &amp; Neil Vasdev 1 <lb/>Lorlatinib (PF-06463922) is a next-generation small-molecule inhibitor of the orphan <lb/>receptor tyrosine kinase c-ros oncogene 1 (ROS1), which has a kinase domain that is <lb/>physiologically related to anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK), and is undergoing Phase I/II <lb/>clinical trial investigations for non-small cell lung cancers. An early goal is to measure the <lb/>concentrations of this drug in brain tumour lesions of lung cancer patients, as penetration <lb/>of the blood-brain barrier is important for optimal therapeutic outcomes. Here we <lb/>prepare both 11 C-and 18 F-isotopologues of lorlatinib to determine the biodistribution and <lb/>whole-body dosimetry assessments by positron emission tomography (PET). Non-traditional <lb/>radiolabelling strategies are employed to enable an automated multistep 11 C-labelling process <lb/>and an iodonium ylide-based radiofluorination. Carbon-11-labelled lorlatinib is routinely <lb/>prepared with good radiochemical yields and shows reasonable tumour uptake in rodents. <lb/>PET imaging in non-human primates confirms that this radiotracer has high brain <lb/>permeability. <lb/>DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>OPEN <lb/>1 Massachusetts General Hospital and Harvard Medical School, 55 Fruit Street, Boston, Massachusetts 02114, USA. 2 Advion Inc., 30 Brown Road, Ithaca, <lb/>New York 14850, USA. 3 Vanderbilt University, 1161 21st Avenue South, Nashville, Tennessee 37232, USA. 4 Pfizer Inc., Quantitative Medicine, Worldwide <lb/>Research and Development, 1 Portland Street, Cambridge, Massachusetts 02139, USA. 5 Pfizer Worldwide Research and Development, 10770 Science Center <lb/>Drive, San Diego, California 92121, USA. w Present addresses: Department of Chemistry, University of the West Indies, Mona, Kingston 7, Jamaica (N.A.S.); <lb/>Waterhouse Imaging and Biomarker Consultants, 208 Candia Road, Chester, New Hampshire 03036, USA (R.N.W.). Correspondence and requests for <lb/>materials should be addressed to N.V. (email: vasdev.neil@mgh.harvard.edu). <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/>1 <lb/></front>

			<body>A <lb/>naplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) is a member of the <lb/>insulin receptor family of receptor tyrosine kinases, and is <lb/>primarily expressed in the central nervous system 1,2 . Over <lb/>a dozen ALK fusion partners have been identified in several <lb/>cancer types 1-4 , and this has ultimately led to clinical translation <lb/>and United States Food and Drug Administration approval of <lb/>ALK inhibitors 5 as a first-line treatment for ALK-positive lung <lb/>cancer patients. Lorlatinib (PF-06463922) is a next-generation, <lb/>small-molecule inhibitor of the orphan receptor tyrosine kinase <lb/>c-ros oncogene 1 (ROS1), which has a kinase domain that is <lb/>physiologically related to and also inhibits ALK 6 . This orally <lb/>available, ATP-competitive inhibitor has shown excellent <lb/>therapeutic potential against ROS1-driven fusion cancers, <lb/>and significantly improved inhibitory activity compared with <lb/>the first-generation-approved tyrosine kinase inhibitors (TKIs) <lb/>including the ALK/mesenchymal-epithelial transition factor/ROS <lb/>inhibitor, crizotinib (Xalkori) 7 , as well as next-generation ALK <lb/>and ALK/ROS1 inhibitors, ceritinib and alectinib 8,9 . Most ALK <lb/>inhibitors (and all known TKIs) are limited by acquired resistance <lb/>to therapy, generally driven by mutations that alter the kinase <lb/>domain of ALK, activation of other oncogenic signals or <lb/>pharmacokinetic (PK) issues with the drug and are generally <lb/>not optimized for brain penetration 10 . A common site of <lb/>metastases in non-small cell lung cancer (NSCLC) patients is in <lb/>the brain where previous generation ALK inhibitors have limited <lb/>effectiveness, and may be attributed to poor blood-brain barrier <lb/>(BBB) penetration or active transport out of the brain by efflux <lb/>pumps 11-13 . Lorlatinib was specifically designed to address this <lb/>unmet clinical need for robust brain penetration and activity <lb/>against TKI-resistant ALK mutants, including the crizotinib-, <lb/>alectinib-and ceritinib-resistant fusion of echinoderm <lb/>microtubule-associated protein-like 4 (EML-4)-ALK Gly1202Arg <lb/>mutant 14 . This drug is presently undergoing Phase I/II clinical <lb/>trial investigations (http://clinicaltrials.gov/ct2/show/NCT01970865) <lb/>in ROS1 and ALK fusion-positive NSCLC patients 13,15-21 . <lb/>Unfortunately, imaging receptor tyrosine kinases and their <lb/>associated signal transduction pathways with isotopologues of <lb/>potent and selective drugs are rarely explored for oncology and <lb/>neuroimaging 22-27 with positron emission tomography (PET). <lb/>This lack of effort is partially attributed to the additional <lb/>challenges of imaging intracellular targets, compared to high-<lb/>density receptor and enzyme targets at the extracellular domain, <lb/>and competition at binding sites with high intracellular levels of <lb/>ATP. These difficulties are further exacerbated by the challenging <lb/>radiochemistry required to prepare isotopologues of the <lb/>structurally complex potent and selective TKIs. A PET <lb/>radiotracer for ALK could aid many ongoing clinical trials with <lb/>ALK-targeted therapeutics by indicating the success and extent of <lb/>engagement by ALK in the periphery and central nervous system, <lb/>as well as for occupancy studies to assess dose-response and to <lb/>understand the PK properties of a labelled drug. Although this <lb/>effort has been hindered by the low BBB permeability of <lb/>crizotinib 28 and related compounds, there is a critical need to <lb/>develop a PET neuroimaging agent for ALK; hence, our goal is to <lb/>evaluate the PK of lorlatinib by PET for clinical oncology. Such a <lb/>radiotracer would enable us to further our understanding <lb/>of ALK-drug concentrations in normal brain and in brain <lb/>metastases. In the present work, we synthesize carbon-11 <lb/>( 11 C; b þ , t ½ ¼ 20.4 min) and fluorine-18 ( 18 F; b þ , t ½ ¼ 109.7 min)-<lb/>labelled isotopologues of lorlatinib and carry out preliminary <lb/>biodistribution and PET imaging using [ 11 C]lorlatinib in <lb/>tumour-bearing rodents and non-human primates (NHPs). <lb/>Results <lb/>Precursor synthesis. With the goal of exploring both 11 C and 18 F <lb/>radiolabelling of lorlatinib, ((10R) À 7-amino-12-fluoro-2,10, <lb/>16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H À 8,4-(metheno) <lb/>pyrazolo[4,3 À h][2,5,11]-benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbo-<lb/>nitrile (PF-06463922; (R)-1), five compounds ((R)-2 À (R)-6; <lb/>Fig. 1) were synthesized to serve as potential precursors. <lb/>Compounds (R)-2 and (R)-3 were intended to be evaluated <lb/>for 11 C labelling through methylation of the amide nitrogen, <lb/>whereas compound (R)-6 was a desirable intermediate to assess <lb/>an iodonium ylide labelling strategy 29-31 . Compounds (R)-4 and <lb/>(R)-5 were attractive from the perspective of utilizing nucleophilic <lb/>aromatic substitution approach to access the 18 F-labelled material. <lb/>Synthesis of labelling precursors for lorlatinib ((R)-1). <lb/>Compound (R)-2 was originally synthesized as a standard for <lb/>metabolite studies and also serves as a precursor for 11 C labelling <lb/>with [ 11 C]CH 3 I (Fig. 2; Supplementary Fig. 2). With compound <lb/>(R)-2 in hand, it may be possible to selectively methylate the <lb/>amide nitrogen with [ 11 C]CH 3 I; however, a more likely labelling <lb/>strategy would involve protection of the aminopyridine motif, <lb/>and carry out a two-step alkylation/deprotection sequence. <lb/>Attempting to simply selectively bis-Boc-protect the aminopyr-<lb/>idine compound (R)-2, led under standard conditions, to mainly <lb/>the tri-Boc-protected compound, and all attempts to selectively <lb/>remove the Boc group from the amide nitrogen failed. With these <lb/>results, and a limited amount of materials in hand, an alternative <lb/>approach to (R)-3 was devised. As we have previously reported 6 , <lb/>a direct arylation can be utilized to form the macrocyclic ring, <lb/>although the success of this approach is to some degree enabled <lb/>by protection of the amino pyridine 6 . This is reinforced by a poor <lb/>yield (o5%) being obtained when direct cyclization was <lb/>attempted to form compound (R)-2. However, this approach is <lb/>successful for (R)-3 (Fig. 3; Supplementary Fig. 3). <lb/>Synthesis of [ 11 C]Lorlatinib ([ 11 C](R)-1). Owing to the <lb/>short half-life of carbon-11, our initial attempts to synthesize <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-1 employed a one-step direct methylation of unpro-<lb/>tected precursor (R)-2 with [ 11 C]CH 3 I using the &apos;Loop Method&apos; 32 <lb/>(Fig. 2). In this established method, the entire reaction is carried <lb/>out on an high-performance liquid chromatography (HPLC) loop <lb/>prior to purification, and no losses to transfer of reagents occur. <lb/>The &apos;Loop Method&apos; is commonly used instead of vial-based <lb/>11 C-methylation reactions, because of its simplicity (no heating or <lb/>cooling required) as well as ease of automation, including <lb/>adaptation to the commercial radiosynthesis modules. Labelling <lb/>of precursor (R)-2 was initiated by flowing [ 11 C]CH 3 I through <lb/>an HPLC loop coated with a thin film of (R)-2 (1 mg) in <lb/>N,N-dimethylformamide (DMF) with 0.7 equivalents of <lb/>tetrabutylammonium hydroxide (TBAOH, 1 M in methanol) at <lb/>room temperature. After 5 min, the contents of the HPLC loop <lb/>were eluted with 10% water in acetonitrile to give 25% <lb/>uncorrected radiochemical yield (RCY) of a labelled compound. <lb/>Analysis of the crude reaction mixture by HPLC indicated that <lb/>the major radiolabelled product had a similar retention time as <lb/>the desired product, but was not easily separated from the <lb/>precursor (R)-2, using semipreparative HPLC. It cannot be ruled <lb/>out that the major radiolabelled product in this reaction was not <lb/>the desired product, [ 11 C](R)-1, but was the methyl pyridinium <lb/>salt [ 11 C](R)-7. Methylation of 2-aminopyridines occurs <lb/>favourably at the pyridine nitrogen because of resonance <lb/>electron-releasing properties of the amino group, which leads <lb/>to enhanced nucleophilicity of the pyridine 33 . In light of the <lb/>challenge to isolate [ 11 C](R)-1 from the reaction mixture <lb/>with confidence and suitable radiochemical purity for clinical <lb/>translation, we abandoned the 1-step strategy and focused <lb/>on a more robust 2-step 11 C-labelling process that employs a <lb/>diBoc-protected amine for routine radiotracer production. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>H <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>-<lb/>+ <lb/>N <lb/>H 3 <lb/>11 C <lb/>H 3 <lb/>11 <lb/>C <lb/>11 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>a, b <lb/>or <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>(R)-2 <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-1 <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-7 <lb/>(R)-3 <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-8 <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-1 <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H 3 <lb/>11 C <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>F <lb/>N N <lb/>N <lb/>a, b, c <lb/>d, e, f <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>N <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>Figure 2 | Development of [ 11 C]lorlatinib. The one-step reaction (top) presented challenging separation of the precursor (R)-2 from [ 11 C]lorlatinib and <lb/>confirmation of identity, which is likely attributed to [ 11 C](R)-7. A two-step methodology (bottom) allowed for facile removal of the precursor and <lb/>simplified the automation for routine production. Reagents and conditions: (a) 1 mg of precursor ((R)-2 or (R)-3), 0.7 eq TBAOH (1 M in methanol), in 80 ml <lb/>anhydrous DMF; (b) [ 11 C]CH 3 I, via &apos;Loop Method&apos;; (c) HPLC purification (see ESI); (d) 0.7 ml of 6 M HCl, 80 °C, 5 min; (e) 4.5 ml of 1 N NaOH, 6 ml of 3 M <lb/>NaOAc, 6 ml H 2 O; (f) SPE reformulation. <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>Lorlatinib (PF-06463922; (R)-1)) <lb/>(R)-2 <lb/>(R )-3 <lb/>(R)-4 <lb/>(R )-5 <lb/>(R)-6 <lb/>11 <lb/>C Precursors <lb/>18 F Precursors <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>F <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O 2 N <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O 2 N <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H <lb/>H <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Figure 1 | Structures of lorlatinib and labelling precursors. The target compound lorlatinib is shown at the top. Sites of derivatization are shown in <lb/>blue for reactions with [ 11 C]CH 3 I (middle) or green for [ 18 F]fluoride (bottom). The iodonium ylide precursor was prepared from (R)-6. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>3 <lb/></page>

			<body>In order to attenuate the reactivity of the pyridine and to <lb/>favour selective labelling of the amide functionality, a doubly <lb/>Boc-protected molecule, precursor (R)-3, was used in a two-step <lb/>labelling employing [ 11 C]CH 3 I via the aforementioned &apos;Loop <lb/>Method&apos;, followed by purification and hydrolysis on a modified <lb/>commercial radiofluorination unit (GE TracerLab FX FN ; <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 13). By using the two-step methylation <lb/>procedure (Fig. 2), the labelled intermediate [ 11 C](R)-8 could be <lb/>easily separated from the precursor (R)-3, by semipreparative <lb/>HPLC, and could then be rapidly deprotected and purified <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 14). A slow stream of [ 11 C]CH 3 I in helium <lb/>was pushed into an HPLC loop containing (R)-3, TBAOH and <lb/>DMF over 4 min. The mixture was allowed to react in the loop, <lb/>and after 5 min the solution was injected directly into the HPLC <lb/>system for semipreparative purification. The large difference in <lb/>the chromatographic properties of protected labelled product <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-8 allowed for the complete separation of (R)-8 from the <lb/>starting precursor (R)-3. The desired radiolabelled product, <lb/>[ 11 C](R)-8, was collected by HPLC separation and the Boc <lb/>groups were deprotected with HCl (6 N) in ethanol at 80 °C for <lb/>5 min. The resulting solution was cooled, and then neutralized <lb/>with NaOH (1 N) and buffered with sodium acetate (3 M). The <lb/>final product was purified by solid phase extraction (SPE) and <lb/>reformulated in 10% ethanol in saline to provide [ 11 C]lorlatinib <lb/>([ 11 C](R)-1), in 3% uncorrected RCY (17% decay-corrected) at <lb/>end of synthesis (50 min) and a high specific activity of <lb/>3 Ci mmol À 1 , with 495% radiochemical purity. <lb/>This work demonstrates the proof of concept labelling of a <lb/>two-step 11 C reaction that can be obtained on a commercial <lb/>radiofluorination unit with a rapid and simple reversible <lb/>modification that does not alter the standard plumbing of the <lb/>GE TracerLab FX FN . We anticipate that this methodology may <lb/>find applications in other 11 C-labelling sequences involving <lb/>two-step reactions 34,35 . <lb/>In vivo PET imaging of [ 11 C](R)-1. PET imaging studies were <lb/>initially performed with [ 11 C](R)-1 in NHPs. In each of two <lb/>rhesus macaques, high initial uptake was seen in the brain after <lb/>intravenous injection of [ 11 C](R)-1, and is consistent with the <lb/>previously reported brain penetration properties of the <lb/>non-radioactive molecule 6 . Whole-body dynamic PET imaging <lb/>revealed radioactivity primarily in the liver and kidneys (Fig. 3a), <lb/>the latter exhibiting signal primarily at early time points that <lb/>progressively shifted to the urinary bladder (Supplementary <lb/>Figs 22 and 23). The peak-measured brain concentrations were <lb/>locally high with the cerebellum exceeding a standardized uptake <lb/>value (SUV) of 2 at B10 min post injection (Fig. 3b); the <lb/>maximum measured per cent injected dose in the brain was 1.4% <lb/>at B10 min post injection. SUV time activity curves exhibit rapid <lb/>uptake, followed by fast washout of the radiotracer in normal <lb/>NHPs (Fig. 3c). Regional uptake exhibits modest heterogeneity <lb/>but is generally concordant with expected ALK distribution, with <lb/>highest [ 11 C]lorlatinib concentrations in the cerebellum, frontal <lb/>cortex and thalamus; intermediate levels in other cortical grey <lb/>matter; and lowest values in the white matter 36 . <lb/>It is noteworthy that a preliminary assessment of tumour <lb/>uptake of this radiotracer was also carried out in mice bearing <lb/>subcutaneous human H3122 (EML4-ALK-positive) NSCLC <lb/>xenografts and evaluated by PET-CT imaging in conjunction <lb/>with blocking studies (Supplementary Figs 24 and 25). Briefly, our <lb/>initial results show that the tumour uptake reached its plateau in <lb/>B30-60 min after injection of [ 11 C](R)-1 (with 2.2-2.37% ID/g) <lb/>and co-injection with (R)-1 resulted in a significant decrease in <lb/>the tumour uptake (o0.4% ID/g) during the entire imaging <lb/>course of 90 min. <lb/>The dosimetry of the 11 C-tracer was determined in NHPs after <lb/>the injection of [ 11 C](R)-1. Doses from any carbon-11 compound <lb/>are generally low, because of the short physical half-life 37 . <lb/>Radioactivity levels were measured in various organs of the <lb/>animals at 13 time points at up to B120 min post injection. <lb/>With these data, the liver dose appears to be 0.021 mSv MBq À 1 , <lb/>and the effective dose appears to be 0.0035 mSv MBq À 1 <lb/>(Supplementary Table 1). The dosimetry estimates from NHPs <lb/>are consistent with those of other 11 C-labelled compounds. <lb/>Clinical translation of this radiotracer is warranted and regulatory <lb/>10 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>0.020 <lb/>Frontal cortex <lb/>Thalamus <lb/>Cerebellum <lb/>White matter <lb/>0.015 <lb/>0.010 <lb/>0.005 <lb/>0.000 <lb/>2.5 <lb/>2.0 <lb/>1.5 <lb/>1.0 <lb/>0.5 <lb/>0.0 <lb/>0 <lb/>c <lb/>b <lb/>a <lb/>30 <lb/>60 <lb/>Time (min) <lb/>90 <lb/>120 <lb/>0 <lb/>Whole body PET (SUV) <lb/>%I.D./g <lb/>Brain PET (SUV) <lb/>Regional uptake (SUV) <lb/>0 <lb/>Figure 3 | Non-human primate PET imaging of [ 11 C]lorlatinib. Representative dynamic multibed PET imaging data with [ 11 C](R)-1 in rhesus macaque. <lb/>(a) Maximum intensity projection PET images from the first two whole-body passes corresponding to data acquired over the initial 17 min after <lb/>radiotracer administration. (b) Axial and coronal slices of PET images at peak-measured brain levels corresponding to data acquired at B10 min post <lb/>injection. (c) Regional time activity curves exhibit rapid uptake, followed by fast washout of the radiotracer. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>submissions should be facilitated, given that further toxicity <lb/>studies are not required. <lb/>Synthesis of labelling precursors for [ 18 F]lorlatinib. The longer <lb/>half-life of fluorine-18 offers many advantages for radiosynthesis <lb/>and imaging protocols compared to carbon-11. Specifically, <lb/>the ability to conduct several scans from a single production <lb/>of an 18 F-labelled radiotracer, facilitation of widespread use <lb/>and multicentre trials, as well as longer scanning protocols <lb/>can be achieved. Therefore, 18 F-labelling is a preferred option, <lb/>particularly since a direct isotopologue of lorlatinib could be <lb/>prepared. For the corresponding nitro-aromatic precursors <lb/>needed for 18 F-labelling (4 and 5; Supplementary Fig. 7), both the <lb/>standard amidation and the direct arylation approaches were also <lb/>investigated to access this novel core. Rather than start with <lb/>enantiopure starting material, we pursued a less labour-intensive <lb/>late-stage chiral separation, and then correlated the product to the <lb/>desired enantiomer. <lb/>Our current synthetic methodology was useful in securing <lb/>enough substrate for initial labelling investigations; however, <lb/>in order to provide a sustainable supply of key intermediates, <lb/>a higher-yielding methodology was needed. Synthesis of cores <lb/>such as (R)-4, (R)-5 and potentially (R)-6 became key to the <lb/>success of the project. A logistical challenge was to determine at <lb/>what point to carry out the chiral separation. Having correlated <lb/>the stereochemistry of the chiral alcohol (S)-19 to the final <lb/>macrocycles, we decided that it would be more facile in terms of <lb/>scale to carry out the separation on either 4 or 5 with the final <lb/>decision being based on which displayed better solubility and <lb/>more efficient chiral separation. In addition, investigating a direct <lb/>arylation route to these compounds could potentially lead to an <lb/>improvement in yield, avoidance of issues with nitrile hydrolysis <lb/>as well as a shortening in the synthetic route (Fig. 4). <lb/>Using the syntheses outlined in Fig. 4, multigram quantities of <lb/>racemic 5 could be obtained, which could then be separated by <lb/>chiral supercritical fluid chromatography (SFC). Correlation of <lb/>the materials obtained with the compound obtained from (S)-19 <lb/>enabled the isolation of (R)-5 on a gram scale. <lb/>The harsh conditions required for fluorodenitration of <lb/>both (R)-4 and (R)-5 lead to significant decomposition of the <lb/>macrocycle, in particular with respect to the sensitivity of the <lb/>nitrile moiety (vide infra). As such, alternative approaches to <lb/>18 F-labelling were also investigated. We recently reported on a <lb/>spirocyclic hypervalent iodine(III)-mediated radiofluorination <lb/>strategy, based on iodonium ylides to afford 18 F-aryl <lb/>fluorides in high RCYs 29 . The technique involves stable, easily <lb/>purified precursors and is readily implemented with standard <lb/>workup procedures. The conceptual advantages of excellent <lb/>regioselectivity and viability of incorporation of 18 F into a wide <lb/>array of non-activated (hetero) arenes make this methodology <lb/>suitable for use on non-activated aromatic rings. With this <lb/>methodology in mind, access to (R)-6 became attractive, and we <lb/>were confident that this compound could be accessed from the <lb/>enantiopure (R)-5. As shown in Fig. 5, Boc-protection again <lb/>provides (R)-4, which could be reduced to (R)-12 using sodium <lb/>dithionite. Diazotization/iodination was then utilized to install <lb/>the requisite iodide to form (R)-6. <lb/>The corresponding ylide (R)-13 was prepared following the <lb/>general literature procedure 29 (Supplementary Fig. 10); in short, <lb/>the aryl iodide (R)-6 was reacted with Selectfluor and <lb/>trimethylsilyl acetate to form the intermediate iododiacetoxy <lb/>compound. A basic solution of 6,10-dioxaspiro[4.5]decane-7, <lb/>9-dione was added to the iododiacetoxy intermediate and <lb/>the reaction allowed to proceed until full conversion of the <lb/>iododiacetoxy starting materials. After purification, the iodonium <lb/>ylide (R)-13 was isolated in 36% yield. <lb/>Radiosynthesis of [ 18 F]lorlatinib. Attempted manual fluor-<lb/>odenitration with [ 18 F]Et 4 NF ([ 18 F]TEAF) was performed using <lb/>the nitro precursors (3-4 mg) in dimethylsulphoxide with heating <lb/>ranging from 160 to 215 °C for 15 min; however, [ 18 F](R)-1 could <lb/>not be identified in the reaction mixture. The radiosynthesis was <lb/>then attempted using the commerical microfluidic system 38 ; <lb/>however, complete HPLC separation of the nitro precursor from <lb/>the final product proved to be problematic (Supplementary <lb/>Figs 16 and 17). Given that precursor (R)-4 or (R)-5 possesses an <lb/>electron-rich aromatic ring and are only mildly activated towards <lb/>nucleophilic aromatic substitution reactions due to the presence <lb/>of the para-amide, it represents a challenging substrate for <lb/>labelling with fluorine-18 using conventional labelling methods. <lb/>It is therefore not surprising that fluordenitration was not fruitful <lb/>in our hands by manual or microfluidic approaches. Fortunately, <lb/>O 2 N <lb/>O <lb/>OH <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Br <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>NH N N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>+ <lb/>a <lb/>b, c <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>O 2 N <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>d, e <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>H 2 N <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>f <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>9 <lb/>1 0 <lb/>1 1 <lb/>O 2 N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>O <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>Br <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>(R )-5 <lb/>(R )-12 <lb/>(R )-6 <lb/>Figure 4 | Direct arylation approach to (R)-5 and (R)-6. Reagents and conditions: (a) 1.5 eq pyrazole 10, 2 eq T3P (50% in EtOAc), 4 eq TEA, 2-MeTHF, <lb/>room temperature (rt), 5 h, 79%; (b) 8 mol% CataCXium A, 8 mol% Pd(OAc) 2 , 3 eq KOAc, 1 eq H 2 O, t-AmOH, reflux, 16 h; (c) 4 M HCl/EtOAc, EtOAc, <lb/>rt, 56 h, 71% over two steps, chiral purification by SFC; (d) 10 eq (Boc) 2 O, 0.5 eq DMAP, CH 2 Cl 2 , 25 °C, 16 h, 76%; (e) 8 eq Na 2 S 2 O 4 , 8 eq NaHCO 3 , <lb/>H 2 O/THF (1:1), 20 °C, 16 h, 58%; (f) 2 eq isoamyl nitrite, 2 eq CH 2 I 2 , CH 3 CN, 80 °C, 4 h, 21%. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>5 <lb/></page>

			<body>our iodonium ylide-based radiochemistry 29-31 proved to be the <lb/>most effective method for preparation of the 18 F isotopologue of <lb/>(R)-1 (Fig. 5), resulting in a 14% uncorrected RCY, relative to <lb/>starting [ 18 F]fluoride (compared to the 1% RCY by microfluidic <lb/>fluorodenitration 39 ), and in a radiochemical purity of 497%. <lb/>We anticipate that this methodology will be applicable for <lb/>18 F-labelling of other mildly activated aromatic clinical <lb/>candidates 40 . This development of [ 18 F](R)-1 is also worthy of <lb/>further investigations in vivo. <lb/>Discussion <lb/>Clinically useful amounts of the 11 C-and 18 F-isotopologues of <lb/>the ROS1/ALK inhibitor lorlatinib were synthesized, enabling the <lb/>possibility for in vivo quantification of ALK-drug concentrations <lb/>and brain metastases. To accommodate the non-traditional <lb/>radiolabelling strategies that were required, five precursor <lb/>molecules were synthesized via multistep syntheses and <lb/>strategically placed chiral separations. Carbon-11-and fluorine-<lb/>18-labelled lorlatinib were prepared in good RCYs and purities <lb/>via a unique and fully automated 2-step 11 C-labelling strategy, as <lb/>well as our iodonium ylide-based radiofluorination methodology. <lb/>The initial PET imaging study was designed to confirm that <lb/>[ 11 C]lorlatinib readily crosses the BBB. Our future work <lb/>with [ 11 C]lorlatinib includes further PET imaging in rodent <lb/>tumour models, normal NHPs, with concurrent automation and <lb/>preclinical translation of [ 18 F]lorlatinib. <lb/>Methods <lb/>General chemistry experimental procedures. Starting materials and other <lb/>reagents were purchased from commercial suppliers and were used without further <lb/>purification unless otherwise stated. Lorlatinib, also known as PF-06463922, is now <lb/>commercially available from Sigma-Aldrich. All reactions were under a <lb/>positive pressure of nitrogen, argon or with a drying tube, at ambient temperature <lb/>(unless otherwise stated), in anhydrous solvents, unless otherwise indicated. <lb/>Analytical thin-layer chromatography (TLC) was performed on glass-backed Silica <lb/>Gel 60_F 254 plates (Analtech (0.25 mm) and eluted with the appropriate solvent <lb/>ratios (v/v). Flash column chromatography was performed using a Biotage Isolera <lb/>One system and preloaded Biotage columns. Silica gel for flash chromatography <lb/>was high-purity grade 40-63 mm pore size and was purchased from Sigma-Aldrich. <lb/>Reactions were monitored by HPLC or TLC and terminated as judged by the <lb/>consumption of starting material. The TLC plates were visualized by ultraviolet, <lb/>phosphomolybdic acid stain or iodine stain. Microwave-assisted reactions were <lb/>carried out in a Biotage Initiator. All test compounds showed 495% purity as <lb/>determined by combustion analysis or by HPLC. HPLC conditions were as follows: <lb/>X-Bridge C18 column at 80 °C, 4.6 mm Â 150 mm, 5 mm, 5-95% MeOH/H 2 O <lb/>buffered with 0.2% formic acid/0.4% ammonium formate, 3 min run, flow rate <lb/>1.2 ml min À 1 , ultraviolet detection (l ¼ 254, 224 nm). <lb/>Spectroscopy. Multi-NMR spectra were recorded on either a Bruker 300 MHz, a <lb/>Bruker 400 MHz, or a Varian Unity Inova 500 MHz spectrometer, and resonances <lb/>are given in parts per million (p.p.m.) relative residual solvent. 1 H NMR spectra <lb/>were obtained as DMSO-d 6 or CDCl 3 solutions as indicated (reported in p.p.m.), <lb/>using chloroform as the reference standard (7.25 p.p.m.) or DMSO-d 6 <lb/>(2.50 p.p.m.), unless otherwise stated. Peak multiplicities are reported using the <lb/>following abbreviations: s ¼ singlet, d ¼ doublet, t ¼ triplet, m ¼ multiplet, <lb/>br ¼ broadened, dd ¼ doublet of doublets, dt ¼ doublet of triplets. J coupling <lb/>constants, when given, are reported in hertz (Hz). HRMS spectra were recorded on <lb/>an Agilent 6,220 ESI TOF mass spectrometer using flow injection analysis. Mass <lb/>spectrum data were also obtained by liquid chromatography mass spectrometry <lb/>(LCMS) on an Agilent instrument using atmospheric pressure chemical ionization <lb/>(APCI) or electrospray ionization (ESI). Selected infrared spectra were recorded <lb/>from neat compounds on a Bruker ALPHA FT-IR. <lb/>Synthesis of labelling precursors for [ 11 C]lorlatinib. Compound (R)-2 was <lb/>originally synthesized as a standard for metabolite studies and also serves as a <lb/>precursor for 11 C-labelling with [ 11 C]CH 3 I (Supplementary Fig. 1). Initial one-pot <lb/>Suzuki coupling between (R)-15 and the pyrazole 16, using B 2 pin 2 and CataCXium <lb/>A as a ligand followed by N-Boc deprotection then ester hydrolysis led to (R)-19, <lb/>the precursor for the macrolactamization. Ring-closure is known to be the <lb/>challenging step in the formation of macrocycles, and often strategies such as <lb/>high dilution and slow addition techniques are utilized to address this. The <lb/>conformational preferences of the precursor also have a strong influence on the <lb/>success of the ring formation 41 , and herein a modest yield was obtained after <lb/>EDCI-mediated ring formation (it is interesting to contrast this with the yields <lb/>obtained in the case of the clinical candidate (R)-2, which differs by an additional <lb/>methyl group on the amide nitrogen, which leads to a 10-20% increase in yield for <lb/>the cyclization step probably due to the greater nucleophilicity of the secondary <lb/>amine). Other amide-bond-forming reagents were not tested in this step, and the <lb/>presence of cis/trans diastereomers (1/3) around the amide bond can clearly be <lb/>observed in the NMR spectroscopic and LCMS analysis of (R)-2. <lb/>Methyl 2-[(1R)-1-{[2-amino-5-(3-{[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]methyl}-<lb/>5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoate <lb/>(R)-17. To a solution of methyl 2-{(1R)-1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)ox-<lb/>y]ethyl}-4-fluorobenzoate (R)-15 (0.3 g, 0.81 mol), di-tert-butyl [(4-bromo-5-<lb/>cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl)methyl]imidodicarbonate 16 (505 mg, <lb/>1.22 mmol) and B 2 Pin 2 (620 g, 2.44 mmol) in methanol (60 ml) was added <lb/>cataCXium A (40 mg, 0.1057 mmol) and Pd(OAc) 2 (25 mg, 0.1057 mmol). The <lb/>reaction mixture was degassed three times with N 2 gas and an aqueous solution of <lb/>NaOH (12 ml, 0.14 M) was added to the mixture under a blanket of N 2 gas. The <lb/>resulting mixture was again degassed with N 2 gas three times prior to being heated <lb/>to reflux for 16 h and the reaction was monitored by TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc <lb/>3:1). Upon completion of the reaction, the resulting mixture was extracted with <lb/>EtOAc (3 Â 50 ml), and the combined organic layers washed with brine <lb/>(2 Â 30 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo to afford a residue, <lb/>which was purified via column chromatography on silica gel eluting with <lb/>petroleum ether/EtOAc (from 10:1 to 5:1) to give methyl 2-[(1R)-1-{[2-amino-5-<lb/>(3-{[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]methyl}-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl) <lb/>pyridine-3-yl]oxy}ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoate (R)-17 (340 mg, 52%) as a brown solid. <lb/>LCMS (APCI) m/z 647.1 [M þ Na] þ . <lb/>Methyl 2-[(1R)-1-({2-amino-5-[3-(aminomethyl)-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyr-<lb/>azol-4-yl]pyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoate (R)-18. To a stirred <lb/>solution of (R)-17 (340 mg, 0.42 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (2 ml) was added in a dropwise <lb/>manner at room temperature hydrogen chloride (4 M in dioxane, 10 ml). After <lb/>the addition was complete, the reaction was stirred at room temperature for <lb/>2 h after which time LCMS showed that the reaction was complete. The reaction <lb/>was concentrated in vacuo to afford crude methyl 2-[(1R)-1-({2-amino-5-<lb/>[3-(aminomethyl)-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl]pyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-<lb/>fluorobenzoate (R)-18, which was used in the next step without any further <lb/>purification. LCMS (APCI) m/z 425.2 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>2-[(1R)-1-({2-amino-5-[3-(aminomethyl)-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-<lb/>yl]pyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoic acid (R)-19. A mixture (R)-18 <lb/>(B300 mg) and KOH (0.395 g, 7.0 mmol) in methanol (15 ml) was stirred at 50 <lb/>°C <lb/>for 36 h after which time LCMS showed that the reaction was complete. The <lb/>solvent was removed in vacuo to afford a residue, which was treated with 1 N aq. <lb/>HCl to adjust the pH to B5. The solution was saturated with solid NaCl, <lb/>and then extracted with EtOAc (5 Â 30 ml). The combined EtOAc layers were <lb/>dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo to give 2-[(1R)-1-({2-amino-5-<lb/>[3-(aminomethyl)-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl]pyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-<lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>I <lb/>O N <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>N <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>O N <lb/>18 F <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>Boc <lb/>a, b <lb/>c, d <lb/>O <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>NH 2 <lb/>O N <lb/>18 F <lb/>H 3 C <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>N <lb/>CH 3 <lb/>(R )-13 <lb/>[ 18 F](R)-8 <lb/>[ 18 F](R)-1 <lb/>Figure 5 | Synthesis of [ 18 F](R)-1 via an iodonium ylide precursor. Reagents and conditions: (a) 2 mg iodonium ylide (R)-13 in 400 ml of DMF <lb/>(anhydrous), azeotropically dried [ 18 F]Et 4 NF, 80 °C, 10 min.; (b) HPLC purification followed by C18 SPE isolation; (c) 4 M HCl, 90 °C, 10 min; <lb/>(d) neutralization to pH 5 using NaOH and NaOAc, reformulation on HLB SPE. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>fluorobenzoic acid (180 mg) as a brown solid, which was further purified by <lb/>preparative HPLC to give 2-[(1R)-1-({2-amino-5-[3-(aminomethyl)-5-cyano-1-<lb/>methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl]pyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoic acid (R)-19 <lb/>(70 mg, 41%) as a white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 411.1 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>(10R)-7-amino-12-fluoro-2,10-dimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-<lb/>8,4-(metheno) pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-car-<lb/>bonitrile (R)-2. To a solution of (R)-19 (70 mg, 0.17 mmol) and N,N-Diisopro-<lb/>pylethylamine (DIPEA) (33 mg, 0.256 mmol) in DMF (25 ml) was added at <lb/>À 35 °C a solution of 1-Hydroxybenzotriazole (HOBT) (35 mg, 0.256 mmol) and <lb/>1-Ethyl-3-(3-dimethylaminopropyl)carbodiimide (EDCI) (33 mg, 0.256 mmol) in <lb/>DMF (10 ml). After the addition was completed, the resulting mixture was stirred <lb/>at 80 °C for 72 h, after which time LCMS showed the reaction to be complete. The <lb/>mixture was poured into ice water (50 ml) and extracted with EtOAc (5 Â 40 ml). <lb/>The combined EtOAc layers were washed with brine (5 Â 20 ml), dried over <lb/>Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo to give a residue, which was purified initially via <lb/>preparative TLC, and then subsequently by preparative HPLC to give (10R)-7-<lb/>amino-12-fluoro-2,10-dimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)-<lb/>pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile (R)-2 (11.5 mg, <lb/>17%) as a white solid, which was shown by both NMR and HPLC to be a mixture <lb/>of cis and trans diastereomers (1:3). LCMS (APCI) m/z 392.2 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR <lb/>Major (600 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 7.64 (dd, J ¼ 10.8, 2.6 Hz, 1H), 7.62 (s, 1 H), 7.29 (dd, <lb/>J ¼ 8.5, 5.5 Hz, 7.25 (s, 1 H), 7.03 (td, J ¼ 8.3, 2.6 Hz, 1 H), 6.28 (q, J ¼ 7.5 Hz, 1 H), <lb/>5.59 (d, J ¼ 16.8 Hz, 1H), 4.36 (d, J ¼ 16.8 Hz, 1 H), 4.02 (s, 3 H), 1.81 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, <lb/>3 H); 13 C NMR (151 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 172.23, 165.12 (d, J ¼ 248.3 Hz), 153.30, <lb/>145.84, 143.83 (d, J ¼ 7.2 Hz), 139.99, 139.58, 134.88 (d, J ¼ 3.2 Hz), 129.06 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 8.5 Hz), 125.34, 125.25, 116.48 (d, J ¼ 22.1 Hz), 115.71 (d, J ¼ 22.6 Hz), <lb/>115.22, 114.83, 111.98, 73.43, 39.32, 38.79, 20.89; 19 F NMR (377 MHz, CD 3 OD) <lb/>d À 113.68, À 111.48 (note that it is negative relative to the reference CFCl 3 at <lb/>0 p.p.m. for 19 F). Minor (600 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 7.62 (s, 1H), 7.52 (dd, J ¼ 9.9, <lb/>2.6 Hz, 1 H), 7.43 (dd, J ¼ 8.5, 5.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.14 (td, J ¼ 8.3, 2.6 Hz, 1 H), 5.78 <lb/>(q, J ¼ 6.6 Hz, 1 H), 4.47 (d, J ¼ 14.5 Hz, 1 H), 4.03 (s, 3 H), 3.97 (d, J ¼ 14.5 Hz, <lb/>1 H), 1.79 (s, 3 H); 13 C NMR (151 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 172.76, 165.45 (d, J ¼ 249.7 <lb/>Hz), 151.94, 146.69, 144.53 (d, J ¼ 7.3 Hz), 140.47, 137.10, 132.70 (d, J ¼ 2.8 Hz), <lb/>130.00 (d, J ¼ 8.9 Hz), 127.57, 119.79, 116.57 (d, J ¼ 22.3 Hz), 115.51 (d, J ¼ 22.7 <lb/>Hz), 115.34, 113.45, 111.65, 72.55, 42.15, 38.89, 22.57; 19 F NMR (377 MHz, <lb/>CD 3 OD) d À 113.68, À 110.59 (note that it is negative relative to the reference <lb/>CFCl 3 at 0 p.p.m. for 19 F). <lb/>Methyl 2-[(1R)-1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-<lb/>yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoate (R)-20. To a stirred yellow solution of methyl 2-<lb/>{(1R)-1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-fluorobenzoate (R)-15 (3.0 g, <lb/>8.126 mmol) in anhydrous CH 2 Cl 2 (40 ml) was added DIPEA (3.15 g, 24.4 mmol) <lb/>and DMAP (496 mg, 4.06 mmol). To this mixture was added in a dropwise <lb/>manner, a solution of Boc 2 O (14.2 g, 65.0 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (10 ml). The yellow <lb/>reaction mixture was stirred at 10 °C for 20 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc 6/1, <lb/>ultraviolet, 254 nm) showed that the starting material had been consumed, <lb/>and a new main product was detected. The reaction mixture was diluted with <lb/>CH 2 Cl 2 (100 ml), washed with brine (20 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and <lb/>concentrated to give a residual yellow oil, which was purified by silica gel <lb/>chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc 6/1) to give methyl 2-[(1R)-1-({2-[bis <lb/>(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoate <lb/>(R)-20 (3.5 g, 76%) as a white solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.09-8.07 <lb/>(m, 2 H), 7.32 (d, J ¼ 2 Hz, 1 H), 7.15 (s, 1 H), 7.09-7.04 (m, 1 H), 6.42 <lb/>(q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 3.97 (s, 3 H), 1.58 (d, J ¼ 6.0 Hz, 3 H), 1.45 (s, 18 H). <lb/>2-[(1R)-1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}ox-<lb/>y)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoic acid (R)-21. To a suspension of methyl 2-[(1R)-1-({2-<lb/>[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluor-<lb/>obenzoate (R)-20 (3.5 g, 6.147 mmol) in water (17.5 ml) was added tetrahydrofuran <lb/>(THF) (15.4 g, 214 mmol) followed by an aqueous solution of NaOH (9.22 ml, <lb/>9.22 mmol, 1 M). The cloudy mixture was stirred at 30 °C for 48 h. TLC (petroleum <lb/>ether/EtOAc 6/1) indicated that the starting material had been consumed. The <lb/>mixture was acidified with 1 N HCl to pHB2, and the resulting colourless solution <lb/>was concentrated to remove the THF. The suspension was extracted with EtOAc <lb/>(3 Â 250 ml), and the combined organic layers washed with brine (100 ml), dried <lb/>over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated. The residue was diluted with petroleum <lb/>ether/EtOAc (10: 1, 600 ml), and the suspension filtered and dried to give 2-[(1R)-<lb/>1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluor-<lb/>obenzoic acid (R)-21 (3.2 g, 94%) as a white solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>8.24-8.20 (m, 1 H), 8.13 (s, 1 H), 7.37 (d, J ¼ 2.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.15 (s, 1 H), 7.15-7.09 <lb/>(m, 1 H), 6.47-6.45 (m, 1 H), 1.65 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H), 1.47 (s, 18 H). <lb/>3-(Aminomethyl)-1-methyl-1H-pyrazole-5-carbonitrile hydrochloride 22. To a <lb/>stirred colourless solution of di-tert-butyl [(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-<lb/>yl)methyl]imidodicarbonate 10 (2.0 g, 5.95 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (10 ml) was added <lb/>HCl(g) in dioxane (30 ml, 4 M) at 0 °C. After the addition was completed, the <lb/>solution was allowed to warm slowly to 15 °C, and stirred at this temperature for <lb/>2 h. During the stirring, a white solid precipitated, and TLC (petroleum ether/ <lb/>EtOAc 10/1) showed that the di-tert-butyl [(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-<lb/>yl)methyl]imidodicarbonate had been consumed. The white suspension was <lb/>concentrated to give 3-(aminomethyl)-1-methyl-1H-pyrazole-5-carbonitrile <lb/>hydrochloride 22 (1 g, 97%) as a white solid, which was used without further <lb/>purification. <lb/>Tert-Butyl N-{5-bromo-3-[(1R)-1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl) <lb/>methyl]carbamoyl}-5-fluorophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}-N-(tert-<lb/>butoxycarbonyl) glycinate (R)-23. To a white suspension of 2-[(1R)-1-({2-<lb/>[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-fluorobenzoic <lb/>acid (R)-21 (3.4 g, 6.12 mmol) and 3-(aminomethyl)-1-methyl-1H-pyrazole-5-<lb/>carbonitrile hydrochloride 22 (1.37 g, 7.96 mmol) in 2-MeTHF (40 ml) was added <lb/>at o35 °C under a N 2 atmosphere with Et 3 N (2.48 g, 24.5 mmol). After the <lb/>addition was completed, the mixture was stirred at 10B15 °C for 30 min. T3P <lb/>(7.79 g, 12.2 mmol, 50% in EtOAc) was added in a dropwise manner at 10-20 °C, <lb/>and then the white cloudy reaction was stirred at the same temperature for 17 h. <lb/>TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc 1/1, R f B0.6) showed that (R)-21 had been <lb/>consumed. The light-yellow and cloudy reaction mixture was diluted with EtOAc <lb/>(100 ml) and nH 2 O (40 ml), and the layers were separated. The organic layer was <lb/>washed with saturated NaHCO 3 (25 ml), brine (25 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered <lb/>and concentrated to give the crude product as a solid, which was purified by <lb/>silica gel chromatography with petroleum ether/EtOAc 2:1 to give tert-butyl <lb/>N-{5-bromo-3-[(1R)-1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl)methyl] <lb/>carbamoyl}-5-fluorophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}-N-(tert-butoxycarbonyl)glycinate <lb/>(R)-23 (3.4 g, 83%) as a white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 696.8 [M þ Na] þ ; 1 H NMR <lb/>(400 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 8.07-8.02 (m, 1 H), 7.50-7.46 (m, 2 H), 7.25-7.20 (m, 2 H), <lb/>7.03-6.99 (m, 1 H), 6.78-6.77 (m, 1 H), 6.60-6.59 (m, 1 H), 6.09-6.07 (m, 1 H), <lb/>4.65 (t, J ¼ 5.6 Hz, 2 H), 4.01 (s, 3 H), 1.60 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H), 1.42 (s, 18 H). <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-12-fluoro-2,10-dimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-3. Argon was bubbled through a colourless <lb/>solution of tert-butyl N-{5-bromo-3-[(1R)-1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-<lb/>3-yl)methyl]carbamoyl}-5-fluorophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}-N-(tert-butox-<lb/>ycarbonyl)glycinate (R)-23 (250 mg, 0.37 mmol), KOAc (120 mg, 1.22 mmol), <lb/>Pd(OAc) 2 (6.33 mg, 0.028 mmol) and H 2 O (6.69 mg, 0.37 mmol) in 2-methyl-2-<lb/>butanol (10 ml) for 3 min. CataCXiumA (10.1 mg, 0.028 mmol) was added, and the <lb/>mixture was bubbled with Ar for a further 3 min. The yellow reaction mixture was <lb/>stirred at 140 °C under microwave heating for 1 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc <lb/>1:1) showed that tert-butyl N-{5-bromo-3-[(1R)-1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-<lb/>pyrazol-3-yl)methyl]carbamoyl}-5-fluorophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}-N-<lb/>(tert-butoxycarbonyl)glycinate had been consumed, and two new spots were <lb/>detected. The yellow mixture was poured into ice-H 2 O (10 ml), and extracted with <lb/>EtOAc (3 Â 25 ml). The combined organic layers were washed with brine (20 ml), <lb/>dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated to give the crude product as a brown <lb/>solid. Initial purification was achieved by preparative TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc <lb/>1/3, R f B0.5) to afford the desired compound as a white solid, which was further <lb/>purified by preparative HPLC to afford di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-12-fluoro-<lb/>2,10-dimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h] <lb/>[2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-3 (99 mg, 45%) as <lb/>an off-white solid as a mixture of cis and trans diastereomers. LCMS (APCI) m/z <lb/>593.1 [M þ H] þ ; mixture of cis and trans diastereomers 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>CD 3 OD) d 8.18 (s, 1 H), 7.71 (s, 0.35 H), 7.55-7.21 (m, 2 H), 7.18-7.03 (m, 1 H), <lb/>6.51-6.49 (m, 0.65 H), 5.83-5.82 (m, 0.3 H), 5.72-5.68 (m, 0.7 H), 4.62-4.58 <lb/>(m, 1 H), 4.43-4.41 (m, 3 H), 1.82-1.80 (m, 3 H), 1.48-1.41 (m, 18 H); 13 C NMR <lb/>(101 MHz, CD 3 OD) d 171.02, 170.74, 165.04, 162.57, 150.94, 148.00, 145.46, <lb/>142.58, 138.93. 136.81, 133.03, 127.87, 126.58, 126.44, 122.06, 114.53, 115.31, <lb/>114.74, 114.61, 114.52, 110.13, 83.29, 83.15, 72.06, 40.76, 37.91, 37.63, 26.68, 21.33, <lb/>19.58; 19 F NMR (377 MHz, CD 3 OD) d À 109.99, À 109.83 (note that it is negative <lb/>relative to the reference CFCl 3 at 0 p.p.m. for 19 F). <lb/>The synthesis of methyl 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoate 31 (Supplementary Fig. 4) is described below. <lb/>1-(2-Amino-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone 25. A mixture of 1-(2-fluoro-5-nitrophenyl) <lb/>ethanone 24 (50 g, 273 mmol) in 28% NH 4 OH (500 ml) and THF (500 ml) was <lb/>stirred at 70 °C for 16 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc ¼ 5:1) showed the majority <lb/>of 1-(2-fluoro-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone had been consumed with one new spot <lb/>detected. The mixture was concentrated under vacuum, and the aqueous solution <lb/>was extracted with EtOAc (3 Â 400 ml). The organic layers were washed with brine <lb/>(400 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuum to afford a residue, which <lb/>was purified by silica gel chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc from 10:1 to <lb/>3:1) to give 1-(2-amino-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone 25 (42 g, 85%) as a yellow solid. <lb/>1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.72 (d, J ¼ 2 Hz, 1 H), 8.15-8.12 (m, 1 H), 6.66 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 8.8 Hz, 1 H), 2.67 (s, 3 H). <lb/>1-(2-Iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone 26. To a stirred solution of 1-(2-amino-5-<lb/>nitrophenyl)ethanone 25 (42 g, 233 mmol) and isoamyl nitrite (54.6 g, 466 mmol) <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>7 <lb/></page>

			<body>in CH 3 CN (420 ml) was added CH 2 I 2 (125 g, 466 mmol) at 15 °C in a single <lb/>portion. The mixture was stirred at 80 °C for 4 h. TLC (petroleum ether/ <lb/>EtOAc ¼ 5/1) indicated that 1-(2-amino-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone had been <lb/>consumed with several new spots being detected. The mixture was concentrated <lb/>under vacuum, and the residue purified by silica gel chromatography (petroleum <lb/>ether/EtOAc ¼ 10:1) to give 1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone 26 (36 g, 53%) as a <lb/>yellow solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.27 (d, J ¼ 2.4 Hz, 1 H), 8.16 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 7.97-7.94 (m, 1 H), 2.69 (s, 3 H). <lb/>1-(2-Iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol 27. To a stirred solution of 1-(2-iodo-5-nitro-<lb/>phenyl)ethanone 26 (36 g, 123.69 mmol) in EtOH (360 ml) was added NaBH 4 <lb/>(5.62 g, 148 mmol) in portions at 0 °C. After the addition, the reaction mixture was <lb/>stirred at room temperature for 2 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc ¼ 5:1) indicated <lb/>that the 1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanone had been consumed with one new spot <lb/>being detected. The reaction mixture was quenched with water (20 ml), and then <lb/>concentrated. The residue was diluted with EtOAc (400 ml) and water (200 ml). <lb/>The organic layer was washed with brine (200 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and <lb/>concentrated in vacuo to afford a residue, which was purified by silica gel <lb/>chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc from 10:1 to 5:1) to give 1-(2-iodo-5-<lb/>nitrophenyl)ethanol 27 (30 g, 83%) as a yellow solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>d 8.43-8.42 (m, 1 H), 8.01-7.98 (m, 1 H), 7.81 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 5.14-5.10 <lb/>(m, 1 H), 2.15-2.14 (m, 1 H), 1.52-1.49 (m, 3 H). <lb/>1-(2-Iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethyl methanesulfonate 28. To a stirred solution of <lb/>1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol 27 (30 g, 102.4 mmol), DMAP (6.25 g, 51.2 mmol) <lb/>and TEA (31.1 g, 307 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (300 ml) was added in a dropwise manner <lb/>MsCl (23.5 g, 205 mmol) at 0 °C under a N 2 atmosphere. Then, the mixture was <lb/>allowed to warm to room temperature and stirred for 16 h. TLC (petroleum ether/ <lb/>EtOAc ¼ 5:1) showed that 1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol had been consumed, <lb/>one new spot being detected. The mixture was diluted with CH 2 Cl 2 (100 ml), <lb/>washed with water (100 ml) and brine (3 Â 100 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and con-<lb/>centrated to dryness to afford 1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethyl methanesulfonate 28 <lb/>(37.99 g), which was used directly in the next step without further purification. <lb/>3-[1-(2-Iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-amine 29. A mixture of 1-(2-<lb/>iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethyl methanesulfonate 28 (37.99 g, 102.37 mmol), 3-hydroxy-<lb/>2-aminopyridine (12.4 g, 113 mmol) and Cs 2 CO 3 (100 g, 307 mmol) in acetone <lb/>(400 ml) was stirred at 45 °C for 16 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc) showed that <lb/>1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethyl methanesulfonate had been consumed with several <lb/>new spots detected. The mixture was filtered, and the filtrate was concentrated <lb/>under vacuum. The residue was dissolved in EtOAc (500 ml), washed with water <lb/>(200 ml) and brine (200 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo. The <lb/>residue was purified by silica gel chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc from <lb/>5:1 to 1:1) to give 3-[1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-amine 29 (15.1 g, <lb/>38%) as a yellow solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.20 (d, J ¼ 2.8 Hz, 1 H), <lb/>8.05 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.85-7.83 (m, 1 H), 7.64 (d, J ¼ 5.2 Hz, 1 H), 6.52-6.45 <lb/>(m, 2 H), 5.48 (q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 4.80 (br s, 1 H), 1.67 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>Methyl 2-{1-[(2-aminopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate 30. <lb/>A mixture of 3-[1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-amine 29 (15.1 g, <lb/>39.21 mmol), TEA (7.93 g, 78.4 mmol) and (PPh 3 ) 2 PdCl 2 (1.93 g, 2.74 mmol) in <lb/>MeOH (180 ml) and CH 3 CN (300 ml) was stirred at 50 °C under 4 bar of CO <lb/>pressure for 16 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc ¼ 1:1) showed that 3-[1-(2-iodo-5-<lb/>nitrophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-amine had been consumed, with several new spots <lb/>being detected. The mixture was concentrated in vacuo, and the residue dissolved <lb/>in EtOAc (500 ml) and washed with water (200 ml) and brine (200 ml). The organic <lb/>phase was dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated under vacuum, and the <lb/>residue purified by silica gel chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc from 3:1 to <lb/>1:1) to give methyl 2-{1-[(2-aminopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate 30 <lb/>(7.51 g, 60%) as a yellow solid. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.41 (d, J ¼ 2.0 Hz, <lb/>1 H), 8.19-8.17 (m, 2 H), 7.76 (d, J ¼ 5.2 Hz, 1 H), 6.70 (d, J ¼ 6.8 Hz, 1 H), <lb/>6.47-6.45 (m, 1 H), 6.33-6.31 (m, 1 H), 5.50 (br s, 2 H), 4.01 (s, 3 H), 1.71 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 6.0 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>Ethyl 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate 31. <lb/>To a stirred solution of methyl 2-{1-[(2-aminopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoate 30 (7.51 g, 23.67 mmol) in CH 3 CN (100 ml) was added N-Bromo-<lb/>succinimide (NBS) (4.21 g, 23.7 mmol) in portions at 0 °C. After the addition was <lb/>complete, the resulting mixture was stirred at 0 °C for 2 h. TLC (petroleum ether/ <lb/>EtOAc ¼ 1:1) showed that methyl 2-{1-[(2-aminopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitro-<lb/>benzoate had been consumed, with several new spots being detected. The reaction <lb/>mixture was quenched with saturated NaHCO 3 (50 ml) and extracted with EtOAc <lb/>(2 Â 300 ml). The organic layer was washed with brine (2 Â 100 ml), dried over <lb/>Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo. The residue was purified by silica gel chro-<lb/>matography (petroleum ether/EtOAc from 10:1 to 2:1) to give methyl 2-{1-[(2-<lb/>amino-5-<lb/>bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate 31 (3.76 g, 40%) as a red solid. <lb/>LCMS (APCI) m/z 397.8 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.43 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 1.6 Hz, 1 H), 8.22-8.13 (m, 2 H), 7.69 (s, 1 H), 6.80 (d, J ¼ 1.6 Hz, 1 H), <lb/>6.30-6.28 (m, 1 H), 4.82 (br s, 2 H), 4.03 (s, 3 H), 1.70 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>The synthesis of the nitro-bearing head group is shown in Supplementary Fig. 4, <lb/>and for a large part mirrors the chemistry utilized for the formation of the head <lb/>group of lorlatinib. Starting with compound 31 (Supplementary Fig. 5), the <lb/>macrocycle 4 can be accessed through a series of well-established transformations, <lb/>as shown in Supplementary Fig. 4. Suzuki coupling with pyrazole 32 leads to 33, <lb/>which undergoes controlled ester hydrolysis, thus minimizing the potential for side <lb/>reactions such as nitrile hydrolysis, followed by Boc deprotection to provide the <lb/>macrolactamization precursor. Addition of this precursor to a solution of HATU in <lb/>DMF leads to 5, which could be smoothly protected to provide 4. <lb/>The synthesis of 7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-<lb/>3-carbonitrile 5 and Di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-<lb/>oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno) pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate 4 (Supplementary Fig. 5) is <lb/>described below. <lb/>Methyl 2-(1-{[2-amino-5-(3-{[(tert-butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino]methyl}-<lb/>5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl)-4-nitrobenzoate 33. <lb/>A mixture of methyl 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoate 31 (2.5 g, 6.31 mmol), tert-butyl [(4-bromo-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-<lb/>pyrazol-3-yl)methyl]methylcarbamate 32 (3.12 g, 9.47 mmol), B 2 Pin 2 (2.08 g, <lb/>8.20 mmol) and CsF (4.79 g, 31.6 mmol) in MeOH (50 ml) was warmed to 50 <lb/>°C <lb/>under a N 2 atmosphere. Pd(OAc) 2 (0.142 g, 0.631 mmol) and cataCXium A <lb/>(0.452 g, 1.26 mmol) in toluene (50 ml) were added to the mixture, which was then <lb/>stirred at reflux under N 2 for 2 h. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc ¼ 2:1) showed that <lb/>methyl 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate had been <lb/>consumed with several new spots being detected. The reaction mixture was cooled, <lb/>diluted with EtOAc (200 ml) and then filtered. The filtrate was concentrated in <lb/>vacuo to give crude product, which was purified by silica gel chromatography <lb/>(petroleum ether/EtOAc from 5:1 to 1:1) to give methyl 2-(1-{[2-amino-5-(3-<lb/>{[(tert-butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino]methyl}-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-<lb/>yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl)-4-nitrobenzoate 33 (1.83 g, 51%) as a yellow solid. <lb/>LCMS (APCI) m/z 566.1 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>2-(1-{[2-Amino-5-(3-{[(tert-butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino]methyl}-5-cyano-<lb/>1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl)-4-nitrobenzoic acid 34. <lb/>A mixture of methyl 2-(1-{[2-amino-5-(3-{[(tert-butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino] <lb/>methyl}-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl)-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoate 33 (1.0 g, 1.77 mmol) and KOH (992 mg, 17.7 mmol) in MeOH <lb/>(50 ml) and water (1 ml) was stirred at 15 °C for 16 h. TLC (petroleum ether/ <lb/>EtOAc ¼ 1:1) showed that 33 had been consumed with one new spot being <lb/>detected. The reaction mixture was neutralized to pH ¼ 7 with 5% aqueous HCl <lb/>solution. The mixture was concentrated under vacuum, and the residue acidified <lb/>with 5% HCl aqueous solution to pH ¼ 3. The mixture was extracted with EtOAc <lb/>(3 Â 30 ml, and the combined organic layers washed with brine (30 ml), dried <lb/>over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated in vacuo to give 2-(1-{[2-amino-5-(3-{[(tert-<lb/>butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino]methyl}-5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl) <lb/>pyridin-3-yl]oxy}ethyl)-4-nitrobenzoic acid 34 (975 mg) as a yellow solid, which <lb/>was used directly in the next step. LCMS (APCI) m/z 552.1 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>2-{1-[(2-Amino-5-{5-cyano-1-methyl-3-[(methylamino)methyl]-1H-pyrazol-<lb/>4-yl}pyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoic acid 35. To a stirred solution of <lb/>2-(1-{[2-amino-5-(3-{[(tert-butoxycarbonyl)(methyl)amino]methyl}-5-cyano-1-<lb/>methyl-1H-pyrazol-4-yl)pyridin-3-yl]oxy} ethyl)-4-nitrobenzoic acid 34 (1.95 g, <lb/>3.54 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (20 ml) was added in a dropwise manner B4 N HCl <lb/>(g)/EtOAc (20 ml) at 0 °C. After addition was completed, the resulting mixture was <lb/>stirred at 20 °C for 4 h. LCMS indicated that the reaction was completed and the <lb/>main peak was the desired product. The reaction mixture was concentrated in <lb/>vacuo to afford the hydrochloride salt of 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-{5-cyano-1-methyl-3-<lb/>[(methylamino)methyl]-1H-pyrazol-4-yl}pyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoic <lb/>acid 35 (B3.54 mmol) as a yellow solid, which was used directly in the next step <lb/>without further purification. LCMS (APCI) m/z 451.9 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>7-Amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-<lb/>(metheno)pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-<lb/>carbonitrile 5. A mixture of the hydrochloride salt of 2-{1-[(2-amino-5-{5-cyano-<lb/>1-methyl-3-[(methylamino)methyl]-1H-pyrazol-4-yl}pyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoic acid 35 (200 mg, 0.41 mmol) and DIPEA (530 mg, 4.1 mmol) in DMF <lb/>(20 ml) was added dropwise to a mixture of HATU (234 mg, 0.615 mmol) in DMF <lb/>(20 ml) at 0 °C. After addition, the mixture was stirred at 0 °C for 1 h. LCMS <lb/>indicated that B30% of the desired product was detected. The solvent was <lb/>evaporated under vacuum, and water (60 ml) was added to the mixture, which was <lb/>extracted with EtOAc (3 Â 100 ml). The organic layer was washed with aqueous <lb/>Na 2 CO 3 aqueous solution (5 Â 50 ml), brine (5 Â 50 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and <lb/>concentrated in vacuum to give the crude product, which was purified by silica <lb/>gel chromatography (silica gel, eluent: CH 2 Cl 2 /methanol ¼ 10:1, R f B0.4) to <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>give the crude compound (70 mg), which was further purified by preparative <lb/>TLC (silica gel, CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 10:1, R f B0.4) to give 7-amino-2,10,16-tri-<lb/>methyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo <lb/>[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile 5 (45 mg, 25%) as a <lb/>yellow solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 434.0 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d <lb/>8.48 (d, J ¼ 1.2 Hz, 1 H), 8.18 (d, J ¼ 2.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.84 (s, 1 H), 7.42 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 <lb/>H), 6.86 (s, 1 H), 5.77 (q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 4.94 (bs s, 2 H), 4.39 (q, J ¼ 14.0 Hz, 2 <lb/>H), 4.08 (s, 3 H), 3.17 (s, 3 H), 1.85 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno) pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate 4. A mixture of 7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-<lb/>nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile 5 (300 mg, 0.692 mmol), (Boc) 2 O <lb/>(1,510 mg, 6.92 mmol) and DMAP (42.3 mg, 0.346 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (20 ml) was <lb/>stirred at 15 °C for 16 h. TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1) showed that the 7-amino-<lb/>2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno) <lb/>pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiaza cyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile had been <lb/>consumed with one new spot being detected. The reaction was concentrated in <lb/>vacuo to give the crude product, which was purified by silica gel chromatography <lb/>(CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1) to give the crude product. This was further purified by <lb/>preparative TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1, R f B0.6, carried out twice) to give pure <lb/>di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-<lb/>2H-8,4-(metheno) pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclo tetradecin-7-yl] <lb/>imidodicarbonate 4 (300 mg, 68%) as a white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 634.1 <lb/>[M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.50 (d, J ¼ 2.4 Hz, 1 H), 8.26 (s, 1 H), <lb/>8.18-8.16 (m, 1 H), 7.40 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.19 (s, 1 H), 5.81-5.76 (m, 1 H), <lb/>4.48-4.38 (m, 2 H), 4.13 (s, 3 H), 3.18 (s, 3 H), 1.83 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H), 1.52 <lb/>(s, 18 H). <lb/>Separation of (1R)-1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol and (1S)-1-(2-iodo-5-<lb/>nitrophenyl)ethanol. The analytical chiral separation was performed by SFC on a <lb/>Chiralpak AD-3 (150 Â 4.6 mm I.D., 3 mmparticle size), which was eluted with <lb/>5-40% isopropanol (IPA) (0.05% diethylamine (DEA)) in CO 2 (Supplementary <lb/>Fig. 6). The flow rate of 2.5 ml min À 1 gave Rt (Peak 1) ¼ 5.32 min and Rt (Peak 2) ¼ <lb/>5.65 min. The racemic mixture of 27 (20 g) was purified by preparative SFC <lb/>(Chiralpak AD 300 Â 50 mm I.D., 10 mmparticle size, which was eluted with 25% <lb/>IPA with 0.05% NH <lb/>4 <lb/>OH at a flow rate of 200 ml min À 1 ) and gave peak 1 ((R)-27) <lb/>as a yellow solid (8.9 g, 45%) and peak 2 ((S)-27) as a yellow solid (9.3 g, 47%). <lb/>(1R)-1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol (Peak 1). 99% ee. Shown to be <lb/>(R)-enantiomer by VCD calculations. <lb/>(1S)-1-(2-iodo-5-nitrophenyl)ethanol (Peak 2). 99% ee. 1 H NMR (400 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 8.42 (d, J ¼ 5.2 Hz, 1 H), 7.98 (d, J ¼ 8.8 Hz, 1 H), 7.82-7.79 (m, 1 H), <lb/>5.12 (q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 2.01 (br s, 1 H), 1.50 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>The synthesis of 7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-<lb/>3-carbonitrile, 4 via a direct aryl approach (Supplementary Fig. 7) is described <lb/>below. <lb/>Methyl 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy) <lb/>ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoate 36. To a stirred colourless solution of methyl 2-{1-[(2-<lb/>amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate 31 (18.9 g, 47.70 mmol) in <lb/>dry CH 2 Cl 2 (300 ml) was added DIPEA (18.5 g, 143 mmol) and DMAP (2.91 g, <lb/>23.9 mmol). Boc 2 O (83.3 g, 382 mmol) was then added to the mixture in a dropwise <lb/>manner, and the resulting brown reaction mixture allowed to stir at 20 °C for 20 h. <lb/>TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc 2:1) indicated that most of the methyl 2-{1-[(2-<lb/>amino-5-bromopyridin-3-yl)oxy]ethyl}-4-nitrobenzoate had been consumed, and a <lb/>major new spot was detected. The brown solution was diluted with CH 2 Cl 2 (100 ml), <lb/>washed with brine (20 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated to give the <lb/>residue as a brown oil, which was purified by silica gel chromatography (petroleum <lb/>ether/EtOAc 3:1) to give methyl 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-<lb/>bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoate 36 (25 g, 88%) as a light-yellow <lb/>viscous oil. <lb/>2-[1-({2-[Bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-<lb/>nitrobenzoic acid 29. To a yellow suspension of methyl 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-<lb/>butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoate 36 (25 g, <lb/>41.916 mmol) in water (125 ml) was added at 0 °C, to THF (125 ml), followed by a <lb/>solution of aqueous NaOH solution (1 M, 62.9 ml, 62.9 mmol). The orange <lb/>suspension was stirred at 28 °C for 16 h during which time, the mixture became <lb/>clear. TLC (petroleum ether/EtOAc 3:1) indicated that the methyl 2-[1-({2-[bis <lb/>(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoate had <lb/>been consumed. The mixture was acidified with 1 N HCl to pHB2, and the <lb/>colourless solution was concentrated to remove the THF, during which time a <lb/>white solid precipitated. The suspension was extracted with EtOAc (3 Â 25 ml). <lb/>The combined organic layers were washed with brine (25 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 , <lb/>filtered and concentrated to give 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-<lb/>bromopyridin-3-yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoic acid 9 (21.8 g, 89%) as a white solid. <lb/>Di-tert-butyl{5-bromo-3-[1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl) methyl] <lb/>(methyl) carbamoyl}-5-nitrophenyl) ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}imidodicarbonate 30. <lb/>To a suspension of 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-<lb/>yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoic acid 9 (21.8 g, 37.431 mmol) and 3-(aminomethyl)-1-<lb/>methyl-1H-pyrazole-5-carbonitrile hydrochloride 10 (10.0 g, 44.9 mmol) in <lb/>2-MeTHF (220 ml) was added below 35 °C TEA (15.2 g, 150 mmol) under a N 2 <lb/>atmosphere. After the addition was completed, the mixture was stirred at 20 °C for <lb/>30 min. T3P (47.6 g, 74.9 mmol, 50% in EtOAc) was added slowly at B25 °C, and <lb/>then the brown suspension was allowed to stir at 20 °C for 5 h. TLC (EtOAc) <lb/>indicated that the 2-[1-({2-[bis(tert-butoxycarbonyl)amino]-5-bromopyridin-3-<lb/>yl}oxy)ethyl]-4-nitrobenzoic acid had been consumed, and a new spot was detected. <lb/>The brown cloudy solution was diluted with EtOAc (500 ml) and cold H 2 O (100 ml), <lb/>and the layers separated. The organic layer was washed with brine (100 ml), dried <lb/>over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated to give the crude product, which was purified <lb/>by silica gel chromatography (petroleum ether/EtOAc 1/1) to give di-tert-butyl <lb/>{5-bromo-3-[1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl)methyl](methyl)carba-<lb/>moyl}-5-nitrophenyl) ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}imidodicarbonate 11 (21 g, 79% ) as a <lb/>light-yellow solid. <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetra-<lb/>hydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate 4. A colourless solution of di-tert-butyl {5-<lb/>bromo-3-[1-(2-{[(5-cyano-1-methyl-1H-pyrazol-3-yl)methyl](methyl)carbamoyl}-<lb/>5-nitrophenyl)ethoxy]pyridin-2-yl}imidodicarbonate 11 (7.0 g, 9.76 mmol), KOAc <lb/>(3.17 g, 32.3 mmol), Pd(OAc) 2 (167 mg, 0.745 mmol) and H 2 O (176 mg, <lb/>9.80 mmol) in 2-methyl-2-butanol (210 ml) was flushed with N 2 for 3 min. <lb/>CataCXiumA (267 mg, 0.0.75 mmol) was added, and the mixture was flushed with <lb/>N 2 for a further 3 min and the yellow reaction mixture was then stirred at a reflux <lb/>for 16 h. LCMS indicated that 11 had been consumed, and the desired product was <lb/>formed. The yellow mixture was poured into ice (20 g) and extracted with EtOAc <lb/>(3 Â 250 ml). The combined organic layers were washed with brine (3 Â 50 ml), <lb/>dried over Na 2 SO 4 , filtered and concentrated to give a residue, which was diluted <lb/>with EtOAc (15 ml), and subsequently filtered. The filter cake was washed with <lb/>EtOAc (5 ml Â 3) and dried to give di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-<lb/>nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno) pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate 4 (4.0 g, 79%) as a grey solid. <lb/>7-Amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8, <lb/>4-(metheno)pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-<lb/>carbonitrile 5. To a stirred solution of di-tert-butyl [3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-<lb/>12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo [4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate 4 (4.0 g, 6.31 mmol) in EtOAc <lb/>(30 ml) was added HCl(g)/EtOAc (4 M, 30 ml) at 0 °C. After the addition was <lb/>completed, the light-yellow solution was allowed to slowly warm to 20 °C and <lb/>stirred for 16 h. LCMS showed that the starting material still remained, and as such <lb/>a further portion of HCl(g)/EtOAc (4 M, 20 ml) was added. The suspension was <lb/>stirred at 20 °C for 20 h before a further portion of HCl(g)/EtOAc (4 M, 20 ml) was <lb/>added. The suspension was again stirred at 20 °C for 20 h, after which time LCMS <lb/>showed that the starting material had been consumed with a new major peak being <lb/>the desired product. The suspension was concentrated, and the residue diluted <lb/>with H 2 O (20 ml), and basified with saturated NaHCO 3 solution to pHB8. The <lb/>suspension was filtered with the filtrate being discarded. The cake was eluted with <lb/>EtOAc until no further product could be detected in the filtrate. The organic <lb/>layer was collected, dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated to give 7-amino-2,10,16-<lb/>trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo <lb/>[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclo tetra decine-3-carbonitrile 5 (2.4 g, 88%) as a <lb/>yellow solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 433.9 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) <lb/>d 8.48 (d, J ¼ 1.2 Hz, 1 H), 8.18 (d, J ¼ 2.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.84 (s, 1 H), 7.42 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, <lb/>1 H), 6.86 (s, 1 H), 5.77 (q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 4.94 (bs s, 2 H), 4.39 (q, J ¼ 14.0 Hz, <lb/>2 H), 4.08 (s, 3 H), 3.17 (s, 3 H), 1.85 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H). <lb/>Separation of (10R)-7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecine-3-carbonitrile (R)-5 and (10S)-7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-<lb/>15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile (S)-5. With 31 synthesized, Boc-<lb/>protection and standard ester hydrolysis provides the acid 9, which is condensed <lb/>with the previously reported pyrazole 10, to give the direct arylation precursor 11 <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 8). Again, direct arylation under standard conditions leads to <lb/>4, which is accompanied with minor amounts of mono-Boc-protected material as <lb/>well as 5. Exhaustive acidic deprotection leads to 5 in 71% yield over two steps. <lb/>The analytical chiral separation was performed by SFC on a Chiralpak AD <lb/>(100 Â 4.6 mm I.D., 3 mmparticle size), which was eluted with 40% ethanol (0.05% <lb/>DEA) in CO 2 . The flow rate of 2.8 ml min À 1 gave Rt (Peak 1) ¼ 1.193 min and <lb/>Rt (Peak 2) ¼ 1.799 min. The racemic mixture of 5 (13 g) was purified by preparative <lb/>SFC (Chiralpak AD 250 Â 50 mm I.D., 10 mmparticle size, which was eluted with <lb/>45% ethanol with 0.05% NH 4 OH at a flow rate of 200 ml min À 1 ) and gave peak 1 <lb/>((R)-5) as a yellow solid (4.94 g, 38%, ee ¼ 100%) and peak 2 ((S)-5) as a yellow <lb/>solid (6.01 g, 46%, ee ¼ 98%). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>9 <lb/></page>

			<body>(10R)-7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-<lb/>8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile <lb/>(R)-5 (Peak 1): 100% ee. LCMS (APCI) m/z 434.0 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (600 MHz, <lb/>CDCl 3 ) d 8.47 (d, J ¼ 2.3 Hz, 1 H), 8.15 (dd, J ¼ 8.4, 2.3 Hz, 1 H), 7.81 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 1.8 Hz, 1 H), 7.41 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 6.85 (d, J ¼ 1.8 Hz, 1 H), 5.76 <lb/>(q, J ¼ 6.3 Hz, 1 H), 4.94 (bs s, 2 H), 4.39 (q, J ¼ 14.0 Hz, 2 H), 4.07 (s, 3 H), 3.16 <lb/>(s, 3 H), 1.84 (d, J ¼ 6.3 Hz, 3 H); 13 C NMR (151 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 167.82, 149.77 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 4.9 Hz), 149.39, 143.66, 142.93, 141.53, 138.88 (d, J ¼ 2.6 Hz), 137.61, 127.51, <lb/>127.40, 123.09, 123.05, 118.39, 114.59, 112.61, 110.60, 71.40, 47.52, 38.90, 31.64, <lb/>22.60. Correlates to material synthesized from (S)-27. <lb/>(10S)-7-amino-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-<lb/>8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile <lb/>(S)-5 (Peak 2): 98% ee. LCMS (APCI) m/z 433.9 [M þ H] þ . <lb/>The synthesis of di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-12-iodo-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-<lb/>oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-6 (Supplementary Fig. 9) <lb/>is described below. <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-4. A mixture of (10R)-7-amino-2,10,16-tri-<lb/>methyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-<lb/>h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile (R)-5 (600 mg, 1.38 mmol), <lb/>(Boc) 2 O (3.02 g, 13.8 mmol) and DMAP (84.6 mg, 0.692 mmol) in CH 2 Cl 2 (40 ml) was <lb/>stirred at 25 °C for 16 h. TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1) indicated that the starting <lb/>material had been consumed and a major new spot detected. The reaction was con-<lb/>centrated in vacuo to give the crude product, which was purified by silica gel chro-<lb/>matography (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1), which was further purified by preparative TLC <lb/>(CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1, R f B0.6) to give di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-2,10,16-tri-<lb/>methyl-12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-<lb/>h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-4 (670 mg, 76%) as a <lb/>white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 656.0 [M þ Na] þ . 1 H NMR (600 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.50 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 2.2 Hz, 1 H), 8.25 (d, J ¼ 1.9 Hz, 1 H), 8.16 (dd, J ¼ 8.4, 2.3 Hz, 1 H), 7.39 (d, <lb/>J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.19 (d, J ¼ 1.9 Hz, 1 H), 5.78 (q, J ¼ 6.3 Hz, 1 H), 4.51-4.34 (q, <lb/>J ¼ 14.03, 20.85 Hz, 2 H), 4.12 (s, 3 H), 3.18 (s, 3 H), 1.82 (d, J ¼ 6.3 Hz, 3 H), 1.51 (s, 19 <lb/>H); 13 C NMR (151 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 167.88, 151.18, 149.39, 148.29, 144.54, 142.04, <lb/>141.92, 141.17, 137.90, 127.12, 125.73, 125.46, 124.20, 123.31, 121.37, 113.81, 110.06, <lb/>83.58, 71.94, 47.52, 39.14, 31.66, 28.13, 22.85. <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [(10R)-12-amino-3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-12. A solution of Na 2 S 2 O 4 (165 mg, <lb/>0.947 mmol) and NaHCO 3 (79.5 mg, 0.947 mmol) in H 2 O (10 ml) was added in a <lb/>dropwise manner to a mixture of di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-<lb/>12-nitro-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11] <lb/>benzoxadiaza cyclotetradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-4 (150 mg, 0.237 mmol) <lb/>in THF (10 ml) at 0 °C. The mixture was stirred at 20 °C for 16 h, at which point <lb/>LCMS showed that B60% of the starting material remained. A solution of Na 2 S 2 O 4 <lb/>(165 mg, 0.947 mmol) and NaHCO 3 (79.5 mg, 0.947 mmol) in H 2 O (5 ml) was <lb/>again added in a dropwise manner to the mixture at 0 °C. The mixture was stirred <lb/>at 20 °C for 16 h. The mixture was extracted with EtOAc (30 ml), and the organic <lb/>layer washed with brine (10 ml), dried over Na 2 SO 4 and concentrated under <lb/>vacuum to give the crude product as a yellow solid. The crude product was further <lb/>purified by preparative TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 15:1, R f B0.5) to give di-tert-butyl <lb/>[(10R)-12-amino-3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8, <lb/>4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl] <lb/>imidodicarbonate (R)-12 (83 mg, 58%) as a white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z 588.9 <lb/>[M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.25-8.23 (m, 1 H), 7.21 (s, 1 H), 6.96 <lb/>(d, J ¼ 5.2 Hz, 1 H), 6.71 (s, 1 H), 6.53-6.51 (m, 1 H), 5.74-5.72 (m, 1 H), 4.61-4.59 <lb/>(m, 1 H), 4.39-4.37 (m, 1 H), 4.11 (s, 3 H), 3.12 (s, 3 H), 1.75 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H), <lb/>1.53 (br s, 2 H), 1.47 (s, 18 H). <lb/>Di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-12-iodo-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclote-<lb/>tradecin-7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-6. To a stirred solution of di-tert-butyl <lb/>[(10R)-12-amino-3-cyano-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-<lb/>8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-7-yl] <lb/>imidodicarbonate (R)-12 (230 mg, 0.381 mmol) and isoamyl nitrite (89.3 mg, <lb/>0.762 mmol) in CH 3 CN (20 ml) was added CH 2 I 2 (204 mg, 0.762 mmol) at 10 °C. <lb/>The mixture was stirred at 80 °C for 4 h. TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1) indicated <lb/>that no starting material remained and several new spots were detected. The <lb/>reaction mixture was concentrated under vacuum to give the crude product as <lb/>yellow oil, which was initially purified by preparative TLC (CH 2 Cl 2 /MeOH ¼ 20:1) <lb/>to give a yellow solid. This was further purified by preparative HPLC (to yield <lb/>di-tert-butyl [(10R)-3-cyano-12-iodo-2,10,16-trimethyl-15-oxo-10,15,16,17-<lb/>tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(metheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]benzoxadiazacyclotetradecin-<lb/>7-yl]imidodicarbonate (R)-6 (59 mg, 21%) as a white solid. LCMS (APCI) m/z <lb/>714.6 [M þ H] þ ; 1 H NMR (400 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.27 (d, J ¼ 2 Hz, 1 H), 7.93 <lb/>(s, 1 H), 7.65 (d, J ¼ 8.4 Hz, 1 H), 7.17 (s, 1 H), 6.94 (d, J ¼ 8.0 Hz, 1 H), 5.66-5.61 <lb/>(m, 1 H), 4.52-4.38 (m, 2 H), 4.12 (s, 3 H), 3.13 (s, 3 H), 1.76 (d, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 3 H), <lb/>1.50 (s, 18 H); 13 C NMR (101 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 168.99, 150.84, 148.29, 144.86, <lb/>141.71, 141.17, 137.42, 137.23, 135.00, 127.22, 125.58, 125.33, 121.27, 113.49, <lb/>110.07, 96.80, 83.11, 71.87, 47.46, 38.90, 31.45, 28.06, 22.72. <lb/>(R)-19-Amino-13-(7,9-dioxo-6,10-dioxa-8-spiro[4.5]decylideneiodo)-4,8-<lb/>dimethyl-16-methyl-9-oxo-17-oxa-4.5.8.20-tetraazatetracyclo[16.3.1.02, <lb/>6.010,15]docosa-1(22),2,5,10(15),11,13,18,20-octaene-3-carbonitrile (R)-13. <lb/>To a solution of aryl iodide (R)-6 (0.1 g, 0.14 mmol) in anhydrous acetonitrile <lb/>(8 ml), under an atmosphere of Ar(g) was added trimethylsilyl acetate (63 ml, <lb/>0.42 mmol), followed by Solid Selectfluror (0.1 g, 0.28 mmol). The reaction mixture <lb/>was stirred at room temperature for 20 h and volatile contents were then removed <lb/>by rotary evaporation. Ethanol (2 ml) was added to the residue followed by a <lb/>solution of 6,10-dioxaspiro[4.5]decane-7,9-dione (0.024 g, 0.14 mmol) dissolved in <lb/>aqueous Na 2 CO 3 (1.5 ml, 0.4 M). The reaction mixture was vigorously stirred <lb/>at room temperature for 0.5 h, until full conversion of iododiacetoxy starting <lb/>materials was determined by TLC. The reaction mixture was then diluted with <lb/>water (B8 ml) and extracted with CHCl 3 (3 Â 10 ml). The combined organic <lb/>extracts were dried with anhydrous Na2SO4, filtered and concentrated. The <lb/>reaction mixture was purified by flash chromatography (10% MeOH in EtOAc) to <lb/>yield the desired product in 36% yield (0.044 g, 0.05 mmol). <lb/>1 H NMR: (300.1 MHz, CDCl 3 ) d 8.18 (d, J ¼ 1.9 Hz, 1 H), 8.04 (d, J ¼ 1.8 Hz, <lb/>1 H), 7.71 (dd, J ¼ 8.4, 1.9 Hz, 1 H), 7.26 (d, J ¼ 8.3 Hz, 1 H), 7.11 (d, J ¼ 1.9 Hz, <lb/>1 H), 5.73 (q, J ¼ 6.4 Hz, 1 H), 4.31 (m, J ¼ Hz, 2 H), 4.12 (s, J ¼ Hz, 3 H), 3.17 <lb/>(s, J ¼ Hz, 3 H), 2.19-2.14 (m, J ¼ Hz, 4 H), 1.82-1.78 (m, J ¼ Hz, 7 H), 1.58 <lb/>(s, J ¼ Hz, 18 H) p.p.m.; 13 C NMR: (75.5 MHz, CDCl3) d 167.30, 164.24, 151.75, <lb/>148.27, 144.61, 143.21, 141.86, 138.74, 138.46, 133.29, 131.44, 129.15, 125.75, <lb/>125.62, 123.13, 115.27, 114.30, 113.72, 109.75, 83.67, 72.74, 55.56, 47.20, 39.00, <lb/>37.39, 31.49, 29.69, 29.26, 28.18, 23.35, 22.52 p.p.m.; HRMS (m/z) [M þ H] þ <lb/>calcd. for C 39 H 44 IN 6 O 10 , 883.2158 found 883.2169 and [M þ Na] þ calcd. for <lb/>C 39 H 43 IN 6 O 10 Na 905.1978 found 905.1989. <lb/>General method for radioisotope production and preparation. One-step radio-<lb/>synthesis of [ 11 C]lorlatinib. Following the &apos;loop method&apos; on a GE Tracerlab FX FN <lb/>radiofluorination module was cleaned and the HPLC loop cleaned and dried <lb/>according to standard methods. Briefly, the methyl iodide delivery line and HPLC <lb/>loop were washed with 10 ml of water, 10 ml of ethanol and 10 ml of acetone. The <lb/>methyl iodide delivery line was reattached to the GE FX M module and helium <lb/>purged through the system for 20 min to ensure that the HPLC loop was dried. <lb/>One milligram of the unprotected precursor (R)-2 was dissolved in 100 ml of a <lb/>solution prepared from 12 ml of 1 M TBAOH in methanol dissolved in 1 ml of <lb/>anhydrous DMF. Eighty millilitre of this solution was transferred to the HPLC loop <lb/>just prior to the release of the activity from the cyclotron. A concentration of 0.7 <lb/>equivalents of the TBAOH base was used to allow for only the partial removal of <lb/>the amide proton and to insure that no other acidic protons should be removed. <lb/>11 CO 2 (800 mCi) was converted to 11 CH 3 I using the GE FX M (gas-phase methyl <lb/>iodide production module) and the carbon-11-labelled methyl iodide formed <lb/>(B365 mCi) was transferred to the HPLC loop in 4 min with a slow stream of <lb/>helium. Then, the 11 CH 3 I was allowed to react on the loop for a further 5 min. <lb/>Semi-prep purification of the crude material is shown in Supplementary Fig. 12. <lb/>This trace shows that it is not possible to separate the product [ 11 C](R)-1 from the <lb/>starting precursor (R)-2. <lb/>Two-step radiosynthesis of [ 11 C]1. 1 mg of the diBOC-protected precursor (R)-3 <lb/>was dissolved in 100 ml of a solution prepared from 12 ml of 1 M TBAOH dissolved <lb/>in 1 ml of anhydrous DMF. A volume of 80 ml of this solution was transferred to the <lb/>HPLC loop just prior to the release of the activity from the cyclotron. 11 CO 2 <lb/>(1,270 mCi) was converted to 11 CH 3 I and the methyl iodide formed (B620 mCi) <lb/>was transferred to the HPLC loop in 4 min with a slow stream of helium. Then, the <lb/>methyl iodide was allowed to react on the loop for a further 5 min. The crude <lb/>reaction mixture was purified by semi-prep HPLC 60:40 Acetonitrile: 0.1 M <lb/>ammonium formate, 5 ml min À 1 , Phenomenex Luna C18, 10 mm, 10 Â 250 mm. <lb/>The labelled protected intermediate was collected at B16 min and the collection <lb/>was restricted to only 1 min to allow the pH in the subsequent hydrolysis step to be <lb/>reproducible. The collected peak was transferred to the reaction vessel through the <lb/>Red path (see Supplementary Fig. 13). The line between Valve 18 and the collection <lb/>bulb was cut, and a male and female leur connection was placed there, allowing <lb/>easy conversion between the standard set-up and the set-up for the two-step <lb/>carbon-11-labelling reaction. <lb/>Prior to collecting the methylated intermediate, valves 13, 24 and 25 were <lb/>energized and valve 11 was de-energized, once V18 was energized, 1 min of the <lb/>peak was collected. Since the concentration and volume of the acid to be used in <lb/>the hydrolysis are fixed (0.7 ml of 6 M HCl), only 5 ml of the HPLC solvent <lb/>containing 0.1 M ammonium formate may be collected. If a larger amount is <lb/>collected (1.5 min), then there was a significant amount of the protected material <lb/>observed in the final product. A typical semi-prep HPLC trace is shown in <lb/>Supplementary Fig. 14. <lb/>The hydrolysis was performed at 80 °C for 5 min, and then the reaction mixture <lb/>was transferred back to the collection bulb. The bulb was preloaded with sodium <lb/>hydroxide (4.5 ml, 1 M), sodium acetate (6 ml, 3 M) and water (6 ml). The sodium <lb/>acetate was added to act as a buffer, which allowed for the reproducible <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<body>neutralization of the reaction mixture and thus the trapping of the desired product <lb/>on the HLB Light Sep-Pak cartridge. The cartridge was then washed with sterile <lb/>water for irrigation (10 ml) to remove any remaining salts and acetonitrile. The <lb/>product was eluted from the SPE cartridge with ethanol (1 ml, USP, 200 proof) and <lb/>diluted with sterile saline (9 ml, 0.9% solution). <lb/>Analysis of the HLB Sep-Pak indicated that 499% of the radioactivity was <lb/>trapped on the cartridge. The trapped radioactive material was eluted with ethanol <lb/>(1 ml) followed by elution with saline (9 ml, 0.9%). Final analysis of the HLB <lb/>Sep-Pak indicated that o0.01% of the radioactivity remained on the cartridge. <lb/>Quality control of the final product is shown in Supplementary Fig. 15. <lb/>[ 18 F]Fluoride production. A GE PETtrace 16.5 MeV cyclotron was used <lb/>for [ 18 F]fluoride production by the 18 O(p,n) 18 F nuclear reaction to irradiate <lb/>18 O-enriched water. A GE high-yield niobium target containing 497% enriched <lb/>O-18 water (Isotec, Taiyo Nippon Sanso or Rotem) was bombarded with protons at <lb/>integrated currents up to 65 mA to produce [ 18 F]fluoride. [ 18 F]Fluoride was <lb/>delivered to a lead-shielded hot cell in 18 O-enriched water by nitrogen gas pressure. <lb/>[ 18 F]Fluoride was prepared for radiofluorination as follows: a solution of base (for <lb/>example, tetraethylammonium bicarbonate, 3 mg) in acetonitrile and water (1 ml, <lb/>v/v 7:3) was added to an aliquot of target water (r1 ml) containing the appropriate <lb/>amount of [ 18 F]fluoride in a V-shaped glass vial sealed with a teflon-lined septum. <lb/>The vial was heated to 110 °C while nitrogen gas was passed through a P 2 O 5 -<lb/>Drierite column followed by the vented vial. When no liquid was visible in the vial, <lb/>it was removed from heat, anhydrous acetonitrile (1 ml) was added and the heating <lb/>was resumed until dryness. This azeotropic drying step was repeated an additional <lb/>three times. The vial was then cooled at room temperature under nitrogen pressure. <lb/>Manual synthesis of [ 18 F](R)-1 via (R)-5. Manual radiolabelling with tetraethyl <lb/>ammonium [ 18 F]fluoride ([ 18 F] TEAF) was carried out following standard labelling <lb/>procedures using precursor (R)-5 (3-4 mg) in DMSO and heated at 215 °C for <lb/>15 min. Aliquots of the reaction mixture were measured by radioTLC and showed <lb/>no significant yield of the desired product. Subsequent analysis of the reaction <lb/>mixture by radioHPLC indicated that o0.1% of the [ 18 F](R)-1 was being <lb/>produced. <lb/>Microfluidic synthesis of [ 18 F]1 via (R)-4. It has been well documented that the <lb/>use of microfluidic technology may lead to increased radiochemical conversion for <lb/>reactions with challenging substrates, where there is loss of material due to <lb/>decreased incorporation, degradation or inability to use high temperatures on a <lb/>conventional system. To this end, radiosynthesis of (R)-1 was repeated and the <lb/>reaction parameters optimized using a commercial microfluidic system and <lb/>following the optimization procedure. The radiosynthesis was then attempted using <lb/>the Discovery mode of the Advion NanoTek microfluidic system 38 , and the <lb/>optimal conditions were determined to be B14 mg ml À 1 (3 mg) of the nitro <lb/>precursor (R)-4 in DMSO (200 ml), a 100 mm Â 2 m reactor at a temperature of <lb/>220 °C, with a flow rate of 40 ml min À 1 . To ensure complete deprotection of all <lb/>labelled materials, the product was hydrolysed using 1 ml of ethanolic HCl, at <lb/>100 °C for 3 min; however, complete HPLC separation of the nitro precursor from <lb/>the final product proved to be problematic. <lb/>However, despite these efforts, the isolated yield of this reaction was only just <lb/>over 1%. Efforts to improve the RCY by carrying out the reaction under less basic <lb/>conditions by using tetrabutylammonium sulfate in lieu of tetraethylammonium <lb/>carbonate yielded similar results and we focused our attention on preparing (R)-13 <lb/>(Supplementary Fig. 10). <lb/>Manual labelling [ 18 F]1 via iodonium ylide (R)-13. Precursor (R)-13 (2 mg) was <lb/>dissolved in DMF (400 ml) and added to a V-vial containing azeotropically dried <lb/>[ 18 F]Et 4 NF (typically 2-4 mCi). The reaction was heated at 80 °C for 10 min. The <lb/>reaction mixture was cooled for 3 min and then HCl was added (4 M, 1 ml) and the <lb/>reaction heated at 80 °C for 10 min. The reaction mixture was cooled to room <lb/>temperature and neutralized to pH 5 with the addition of a mixture of NaOH (5 M, <lb/>0.8 ml) and NaOAc (3 M, 0.2 ml). The resulting mixture was further diluted with <lb/>water (16 ml) and passed through a Waters C18 Sep-Pak, which had been activated <lb/>by flushing sequentially with ethanol (1 ml) and water (5 ml). The Sep-Pak was <lb/>flushed with water (2 ml) and the desired product was eluted with ethanol (1 ml). <lb/>Product identity and purity were determined by radioHPLC (30:70 CH 3 CN:H 2 O <lb/>þ 0.1 N ammonium formate, Waters X-Bridge phenyl column) and radioTLC <lb/>(EtOAc þ 5% EtOH; Supplementary Fig. 19). The product was 485% <lb/>radiochemically pure. RCY was determined as the percentage of radioactivity that <lb/>was isolated as the final product from the amount of activity present in the V-vial <lb/>before the addition of (R)-13 to dried [ 18 F]Et 4 NF, and is not decay-corrected. <lb/>Using SPE only for the purification of the final product, [ 18 F]lorlatinib (R)-1 is not <lb/>sufficient to purify the radiotracer as there is a radiochemical by-product that is not <lb/>removed during the C18-SPE purification, as well as a number of cold impurities as <lb/>evidenced by the ultraviolet HPLC trace. <lb/>Purification of (R)-8 on the GE TracerLab FX FN . Precursor (R)-13 (2 mg) was <lb/>dissolved in DMF (400 ml) and added to a V-vial containing azeotropically dried <lb/>[ 18 F]Et 4 NF (24.7 mCi). The reaction was heated at 80 °C for 10 min. The reaction <lb/>mixture was cooled at 0 °C for 1 min and then diluted with water (2 ml). The crude <lb/>reaction mixture (19 mCi) was placed into RV2 of FX FN synthesis module and <lb/>manually loaded onto HPLC equipped with a Phenomenex Luna C18 5 u <lb/>Semi-Prep column that was previously equilibrated with 60:40 MeCN/0.1 M <lb/>ammonium formate. The desired compound eluted B17 min at 5 ml min À 1 HPLC <lb/>flow and was collected in a bulk vessel with water (25 ml). The contents of the bulk <lb/>vessel were passed through a C18-SPE cartridge that has been previously installed <lb/>on the FX FN module. The SPE cartridge was washed with water (10 ml) and taken <lb/>off line. The total activity on Sep-Pak ¼ 4.64 mCi. A volume of 1 ml of EtOH was <lb/>used to elute product into a clean V-vial À 4.64 mCi, RCY ¼ 19% non-decay-<lb/>corrected. To the contents of the v-vial was added HCl (4 M, 1 ml) and the reaction <lb/>heated at 90 °C for 10 min. The reaction was cooled to room temperature and <lb/>neutralized to pH 5 with the addition of a mixture of NaOH (5 M, 0.8 ml) and <lb/>NaOAc (3 M, 0.5 ml). The contents of the vial was loaded onto a prepared HLB <lb/>cartridge (3.55 mCi) and [ 18 F]Lorlatinib (R)-1 was eluted with EtOH (1 ml) <lb/>À 3.36 mCi in a RCY of 14% (non-decay corrected). Radiochemical <lb/>purity ¼ 497%; specific activity ¼ 101 mCi mmol À 1 . <lb/>Automation of [ 18 F]lorlatinib. After all reagents and materials were installed on <lb/>the GE TracerLab FX FN , the [ 18 F]fluoride, 7 mCi, was transferred to the GE <lb/>TracerLab FX FN and the automated sequence was initiated. After completing the <lb/>HPLC purification of intermediate (R)-8, the compound was eluted from the <lb/>Sep-Pak using 1 ml of ethanol into a clean V-vial À 3.5 mCi. To the contents of the <lb/>V-vial was added HCl (4 M, 1 ml) and the reaction heated at 90 °C for 10 min. The <lb/>reaction was cooled to room temperature and neutralized to pH 5 with the addition <lb/>of a mixture of NaOH (5 M, 0.8 ml) and NaOAc (3 M, 0.5 ml). The contents of <lb/>the vial were loaded onto a prepared HLB cartridge (3.55 mCi) and [ 18 F]lorlatinib <lb/>(R)-1 was eluted with EtOH (1 ml) to give 1.22 mCi at 84 min of [ 18 F]lorlatinib (R)-<lb/>1, which was 497% radiochemically pure. <lb/>Animal husbandry. All animal experiments for both rodents and NHPs were <lb/>conducted in compliance with the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee <lb/>(IACUC) guidelines and the Guide for the Care and Use of Laboratory Animals. <lb/>PET image acquisition. All experiments were performed in compliance with the <lb/>procedures authorized by the Institutional Animal Care and Use Committee at <lb/>Massachusetts. Studies were performed on two adult male rhesus macaques <lb/>(B10 kg body weight). Animals were sedated with ketamine (10 mg kg À 1 , <lb/>intramuscularly) and transported from housing to the imaging suite where <lb/>anaesthesia was maintained by isoflurane (1-2% in 100% O 2 at 2 l min À 1 ). <lb/>A flexible catheter was placed in the saphenous vein for administration of <lb/>radiotracer and the animal was positioned in the bore of an ECAT EXACT HR þ <lb/>PET scanner. Transmission data were acquired for 210 s at each of six consecutive <lb/>bed positions, with location and overlap corresponding to those used for <lb/>subsequent emission data collection and with field of view covering the entire head <lb/>and spanning down approximately to the knees. Approximately 4.5 mCi of <lb/>[ 11 C]lorlatinib prepared at high specific activity was infused intravenously over 60 s <lb/>followed by flush with sterile saline. Collection of emission data was initiated <lb/>concurrent with the start of administration of radiotracer. The dynamic multibed <lb/>acquisition consisted of six bed positions (matching the transmission scan <lb/>described above) and 11 passes. Emission data were acquired in a three-<lb/>dimensional mode for 60 s at each bed position during the first eight passes and <lb/>180 s per bed position for the final three passes. Accounting for latencies during <lb/>transition between bed positions, the emission data were collected out to 128 min <lb/>with data acquisition starting at the follow times for the successive passes: 0, 8.5, 17, <lb/>25.5, 34, 42.5, 51, 59.5, 68, 88.5 and 109 min after start of scan. PET images were <lb/>reconstructed on a grid with 2.57 mm voxels in plane and 2.43 mm slice thickness <lb/>using the manufacturer&apos;s implementation of the filtered backprojection algorithm <lb/>with corrections for photon scatter and attenuation, random coincidences, system <lb/>deadtime and detector inhomogeneity. PET radioactivity concentrations were <lb/>decay-corrected to the start of the scan and normalized by injected dose and subject <lb/>body weight to produce images in units of SUV. Images are shown below for each <lb/>animal, with data summed either prior to decay correction (displayed in units of <lb/>Bq/cc) or after decay correction (in SUV units). <lb/></body>

			<div type="availability">Data availability. The data that support the findings of this study are available <lb/>from the corresponding author upon reasonable request. <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>1. Kelleher, F. C. &amp; McDermott, R. The emerging pathogenic and therapeutic <lb/>importance of the anaplastic lymphoma kinase gene. Eur. J. Cancer 46, <lb/>2357-2368 (2010). <lb/>2. Cheuk, W. &amp; Chan, J. K. Timely topic: anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) <lb/>spreads its influence. Pathology 33, 7-12 (2001). <lb/>3. Iams, W. T. &amp; Lovly, C. M. Anaplastic lymphoma kinase as a therapeutic target <lb/>in non-small cell lung cancer. Cancer J. 21, 378-382 (2015). <lb/>4. Takeoka, K., Okumura, A., Honjo, G. &amp; Ohno, H. Variant translocation <lb/>partners of the anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) gene in two cases of <lb/>anaplastic large cell lymphoma, identified by inverse cDNA polymerase chain <lb/>reaction. J. Clin. Exp. Hematop. 54, 225-235 (2014). <lb/>5. Malik, S. M. et al. US Food and Drug Administration approval: crizotinib for <lb/>treatment of advanced or metastatic non-small cell lung cancer that is <lb/>anaplastic lymphoma kinase positive. Clin Cancer Res. 20, 2029-2034 (2014). <lb/>6. Johnson, T. W. et al. Discovery of (10R)-7-amino-12-fluoro-2,10,16-trimethyl-<lb/>15-oxo-10,15,16,17-tetrahydro-2H-8,4-(m etheno)pyrazolo[4,3-h][2,5,11]-<lb/>benzoxadiazacyclotetradecine-3-carbonitrile (PF-06463922), a macrocyclic <lb/>inhibitor of anaplastic lymphoma kinase (ALK) and c-ros oncogene 1 (ROS1) <lb/>with preclinical brain exposure and broad-spectrum potency against <lb/>ALK-resistant mutations. J. Med. Chem. 57, 4720-4744 (2014). <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/>ARTICLE <lb/></note>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications <lb/></note>

			<page>11 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>7. D&apos;Arcangelo, M., Wynes, M. W. &amp; Hirsch, F. R. The role of anaplastic <lb/>lymphoma kinase inhibitors in the treatment of advanced nonsmall cell lung <lb/>cancer. Curr. Opin. Oncol. 25, 121-129 (2013). <lb/>8. Ceccon, M. Ceritinib as a promising therapy for ALK related diseases. Transl. <lb/>Lung Cancer Res. 3, 376-378 (2014). <lb/>9. Song, Z., Wang, M. &amp; Zhang, A. Alectinib: a novel second generation anaplastic <lb/>lymphoma kinase (ALK) inhibitor for overcoming clinically-acquired <lb/>resistance. Acta Pharm. Sin. B 5, 34-37 (2015). <lb/>10. Costa, D. B. ALK inhibitors: plateauing systemic and intracranial activity? <lb/>Lancet Oncol. 17, 404-406 (2016). <lb/>11. Dempke, W. C. et al. Brain metastases in NSCLC-are TKIs changing the <lb/>treatment strategy? Anticancer Res. 35, 5797-5806 (2015). <lb/>12. Klempner, S. J. &amp; Ou, S. H. Anaplastic lymphoma kinase inhibitors in brain <lb/>metastases from ALK þ non-small cell lung cancer: hitting the target even in <lb/>the CNS. Chin. Clin. Oncol. 4, 20 (2015). <lb/>13. Zou, H. Y. et al. PF-06463922, an ALK/ROS1 inhibitor, overcomes resistance to <lb/>first and second generation alk inhibitors in preclinical models. Cancer Cell 28, <lb/>70-81 (2015). <lb/>14. Elleraas, J. et al. Conformational studies and atropisomerism kinetics of the <lb/>ALK clinical candidate lorlatinib (PF-06463922) and desmethyl congeners. <lb/>Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 55, 3590-3595 (2016). <lb/>15. Gainor, J. F. et al. Molecular mechanisms of resistance to first-and second-<lb/>generation ALK inhibitors in ALK-rearranged lung cancer. Cancer Discov. 6, <lb/>1118-1133 (2016). <lb/>16. Iragavarapu, C. et al. Novel ALK inhibitors in clinical use and development. <lb/>J. Hematol. Oncol. 8, 17 (2015). <lb/>17. Shea, M., Costa, D. B. &amp; Rangachari, D. Management of advanced non-small <lb/>cell lung cancers with known mutations or rearrangements: latest evidence and <lb/>treatment approaches. Ther. Adv. Respir. Dis. 10, 113-129 (2016). <lb/>18. Sullivan, I. &amp; Planchard, D. ALK inhibitors in non-small cell lung cancer: the <lb/>latest evidence and developments. Ther. Adv. Med. Oncol. 8, 32-47 (2016). <lb/>19. Toyokawa, G. &amp; Seto, T. Updated evidence on the mechanisms of resistance to <lb/>ALK inhibitors and strategies to overcome such resistance: clinical and <lb/>preclinical data. Oncol. Res. Treat. 38, 291-298 (2015). <lb/>20. Yamazaki, S. et al. Mechanistic understanding of translational <lb/>pharmacokinetic-pharmacodynamic relationships in nonclinical tumor models: <lb/>a case study of orally available novel inhibitors of anaplastic lymphoma kinase. <lb/>Drug Metab. Dispos. 43, 54-62 (2015). <lb/>21. Zou, H. Y. et al. PF-06463922 is a potent and selective next-generation <lb/>ROS1/ALK inhibitor capable of blocking crizotinib-resistant ROS1 mutations. <lb/>Proc. Natl Acad. Sci. USA 112, 3493-3498 (2015). <lb/>22. Bernard-Gauthier, V., Bailey, J. J., Berke, S. &amp; Schirrmacher, R. Recent advances <lb/>in the development and application of radiolabeled kinase inhibitors for PET <lb/>imaging. Molecules 20, 22000-22027 (2015). <lb/>23. Hicks, J. W., VanBrocklin, H. F., Wilson, A. A., Houle, S. &amp; Vasdev, N. <lb/>Radiolabeled small molecule protein kinase inhibitors for imaging with PET or <lb/>SPECT. Molecules 15, 8260-8278 (2010). <lb/>24. Holland, J. P., Cumming, P. &amp; Vasdev, N. PET of signal transduction pathways <lb/>in cancer. J. Nucl. Med. 53, 1333-1336 (2012). <lb/>25. Holland, J. P., Cumming, P. &amp; Vasdev, N. PET radiopharmaceuticals for probing <lb/>enzymes in the brain. Am. J. Nucl. Med. Mol. Imaging 3, 194-216 (2013). <lb/>26. Holland, J. P. et al. Alternative approaches for PET radiotracer development in <lb/>Alzheimer&apos;s disease: imaging beyond plaque. J. Labelled Comp. Radiopharm. 57, <lb/>323-331 (2014). <lb/>27. Liang, S. H. et al. Discovery of a highly selective glycogen synthase kinase-3 inhibitor <lb/>(PF-04802367) that modulates tau phosphorylation in the brain: translation for PET <lb/>neuroimaging. Angew. Chem. Int. Ed. Engl. 55, 9601-9605 (2016). <lb/>28. Costa, D. B. et al. CSF concentration of the anaplastic lymphoma kinase <lb/>inhibitor crizotinib. J. Clin. Oncol. 29, e443-e445 (2011). <lb/>29. Rotstein, B. H., Stephenson, N. A., Vasdev, N. &amp; Liang, S. H. Spirocyclic <lb/>hypervalent iodine(III)-mediated radiofluorination of non-activated and <lb/>hindered aromatics. Nat. Commun. 5, 4365 (2014). <lb/>30. Rotstein, B. H. et al. Mechanistic studies and radiofluorination of structurally <lb/>diverse pharmaceuticals with spirocyclic iodonium(III) ylides. Chem. Sci. 7, <lb/>4407-4417 (2016). <lb/>31. Stephenson, N. A. et al. Iodonium ylide-mediated radiofluorination of <lb/>18F-FPEB and validation for human use. J. Nucl. Med. 56, 489-492 (2015). <lb/>32. Wilson, A. A., Garcia, A., Jin, L. &amp; Houle, S. Radiotracer synthesis from [ 11 C]-<lb/>iodomethane: a remarkably simple captive solvent method. Nucl. Med. Biol. 27, <lb/>529-532 (2000). <lb/>33. Zoltewicz, J. A. &amp; Deady, L. W. Relative rates of N-methylation of o-substituted <lb/>pyridines. Steric and electronic effects. J. Org. Chem. 37, 603-607 (1972). <lb/>34. Gomez-Vallejo, V. &amp; Llop, J. Fully automated and reproducible radiosynthesis <lb/>of high specific activity [ 11 C]raclopride and [ 11 C]Pittsburgh compound-B using <lb/>the combination of two commercial synthesizers. Nucl. Med. Commun. 32, <lb/>1011-1017 (2011). <lb/>35. Philippe, C. et al. Optimization of the radiosynthesis of the Alzheimer tracer <lb/>2-(4-N-[ 11 C]methylaminophenyl)-6-hydroxybenzothiazole ([ 11 C]PIB). Appl. <lb/>Radiat. Isot. 69, 1212-1217 (2011). <lb/>36. Bilsland, J. G. et al. Behavioral and neurochemical alterations in mice deficient <lb/>in anaplastic lymphoma kinase suggest therapeutic potential for psychiatric <lb/>indications. Neuropsychopharmacology 33, 685-700 (2008). <lb/>37. Zanotti-Fregonara, P. &amp; Innis, R. B. Suggested pathway to assess radiation <lb/>safety of 11 C-labeled PET tracers for first-in-human studies. Eur. J. Nucl. Med. <lb/>Mol. Imaging 39, 544-547 (2012). <lb/>38. Pascali, G. et al. Optimization of nucleophilic 18 F radiofluorinations using a <lb/>microfluidic reaction approach. Nat. Protoc. 9, 2017-2029 (2014). <lb/>39. Ungersboeck, J. et al. Radiolabeling of [ 18 F]altanserin-a microfluidic <lb/>approach. Nucl. Med. Biol. 39, 1087-1092 (2012). <lb/>40. Zeng, Q. et al. Discovery and evaluation of clinical candidate AZD3759, <lb/>a potent, oral active, central nervous system-penetrant, epidermal growth <lb/>factor receptor tyrosine kinase inhibitor. J. Med. Chem. 58, 8200-8215 <lb/>(2015). <lb/>41. Yudin, A. K. &apos;Macrocycles: lessons from the distant past, recent developments, <lb/>and future directions&apos;. Chem. Sci. 6, 30-49 (2015). <lb/></listBibl>

			<div type="acknowledgement">Acknowledgements <lb/>We would like to thank the staff at the radiochemistry programme, Division of Nuclear <lb/>Medicine and Molecular Imaging, at Massachusetts General Hospital, for technical <lb/>support. We thank WuXi AppTec for partial chemistry support. S.H.L. is a recipient of <lb/>NIH career development award from the National Institute on Drug Abuse (DA038000) <lb/>and N.V. thanks National Institute on Ageing of the NIH R01AG054473) and Pfizer Inc. <lb/>for support. <lb/></div>

            <div type="contribution">Author contributions <lb/>T.L.C., N.S., E.L., S.H.L., W.W. and P.R. contributed to the chemistry and <lb/>radiochemistry. M.D.N., D.W.W., S.A.E, M.G.S. and G.E.F. contributed to the PET <lb/>imaging and dosimetry study. J.C., K.M., R.N.W. and U.M. contributed to the study <lb/>design. T.L.C., P.R. and N.V. prepared the manuscript and supervised the project. All the <lb/>authors discussed the experimental results and commented on the manuscript. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Additional information <lb/>Supplementary Information accompanies this paper at http://www.nature.com/ <lb/>naturecommunications <lb/></div>

            <div type="conflict">Competing interests: The authors declare no competing financial interests. <lb/></div>

            <div type="annex">Reprints and permission information is available online at http://npg.nature.com/ <lb/>reprintsandpermissions/ <lb/>How to cite this article: Collier, T. L. et al. Synthesis and preliminary PET imaging of <lb/>11 C and 18 F isotopologues of the ROS1/ALK inhibitor lorlatinib. Nat. Commun. 8, 15761 <lb/>doi: 10.1038/ncomms15761 (2017). <lb/>Publisher&apos;s note: Springer Nature remains neutral with regard to jurisdictional claims in <lb/>published maps and institutional affiliations. <lb/>Open Access This article is licensed under a Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution 4.0 International License, which permits use, sharing, <lb/>adaptation, distribution and reproduction in any medium or format, as long as you give <lb/>appropriate credit to the original author(s) and the source, provide a link to the Creative <lb/>Commons license, and indicate if changes were made. The images or other third party <lb/>material in this article are included in the article&apos;s Creative Commons license, unless <lb/>indicated otherwise in a credit line to the material. If material is not included in the <lb/>article&apos;s Creative Commons license and your intended use is not permitted by statutory <lb/>regulation or exceeds the permitted use, you will need to obtain permission directly from <lb/>the copyright holder. To view a copy of this license, visit http://creativecommons.org/ <lb/>licenses/by/4.0/ <lb/>r The Author(s) 2017 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">ARTICLE <lb/>NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 <lb/></page>

			<note place="footnote">NATURE COMMUNICATIONS | 8:15761 | DOI: 10.1038/ncomms15761 | www.nature.com/naturecommunications </note>


	</text>
</tei>