<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="0"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
			<front>$ € <lb/>£ ¥ <lb/>social sciences <lb/>Article <lb/>Young Children&apos;s Learning about Hunger and Satiety through <lb/>the Lens of the Norms of Those Who Feed Them <lb/>Anne Dupuy 1,2, * , Sophie Nicklaus 3 , Camille Schwartz 3 , Stéphanie Goirand 1 and Laurence Tibère 1,2 <lb/>Citation: Dupuy, Anne, Sophie <lb/>Nicklaus, Camille Schwartz, <lb/>Stéphanie Goirand, and Laurence <lb/>Tibère. 2021. Young Children&apos;s <lb/>Learning about Hunger and Satiety <lb/>through the Lens of the Norms of <lb/>Those Who Feed Them. Social Sciences <lb/>10: 292. https://doi.org/10.3390/ <lb/>socsci10080292 <lb/>Academic Editor: Nigel Parton <lb/>Received: 20 May 2021 <lb/>Accepted: 26 July 2021 <lb/>Published: 30 July 2021 <lb/>Publisher&apos;s Note: MDPI stays neutral <lb/>with regard to jurisdictional claims in <lb/>published maps and institutional affil-<lb/>iations. <lb/>Copyright: © 2021 by the authors. <lb/>Licensee MDPI, Basel, Switzerland. <lb/>This article is an open access article <lb/>distributed under the terms and <lb/>conditions of the Creative Commons <lb/>Attribution (CC BY) license (https:// <lb/>creativecommons.org/licenses/by/ <lb/>4.0/). <lb/>1 <lb/>Centre d&apos;Étude et de Recherche Travail Organisation Pouvoir, UMR CNRS 5044, CEDEX 9, F-31058 Toulouse, <lb/>France; stephanie.goirand@univ-tlse2.fr (S.G.); tibere@univ-tlse2.fr (L.T.) <lb/>2 <lb/>Institut Supérieur du Tourisme de l&apos;Hôtellerie et de l&apos;Alimentation, University of Toulouse-Jean Jaurès, <lb/>CEDEX 9, F-31058 Toulouse, France <lb/>3 <lb/>Centre des Sciences du Goût et de l&apos;Alimentation, AgroSup Dijon, CNRS, INRAE, Université Bourgogne <lb/>Franche-Comté, F-21000 Dijon, France; sophie.nicklaus@inrae.fr (S.N.); camille.schwartz@inrae.fr (C.S.) <lb/>* Correspondence: anne.dupuy@univ-tlse2.fr <lb/>Abstract: This article focuses on parental perceptions of signs of hunger and satiety in children <lb/>under 4 years of age and their effects on feeding practices, in a sample of parents of children with <lb/>typical development. Discourse analysis shows the close relationships between social food norms, <lb/>nutritional norms, medicalized child care norms, and educational norms in adults&apos; determination of <lb/>children&apos;s appetites according to their perceived needs and psychomotor development. The results <lb/>also indicate how these norms are expressed according to social position, parental experience and <lb/>context. More broadly, this article addresses top-down education-from adults to children-in food <lb/>socialization, and points to the varying attention paid to the signals given by the child. It thus <lb/>highlights some of the processes by which biological, psychological and social factors interact in <lb/>socializing children to food. <lb/>Keywords: hunger; appetite; satiety; satiation; socialization; children; norms <lb/></front>

			<body>1. Introduction <lb/>Current knowledge about the determinants of hunger and satiety in young children <lb/>is based on two observations. The first concerns the innate ability of infants to control <lb/>the amount of food they eat. In this case, stopping sucking and later eating when they <lb/>are satiated. The second relates to the diminishment of this ability as infants get older <lb/>(Birch 1990; Birch et al. 1991; Birch and Fisher 1998; Remy et al. 2015; Shloim et al. 2018) <lb/>and to their socialization contexts, which are primarily studied based on parental feeding <lb/>practices or interactions between the feeder and the infant. The growing interest in this <lb/>area of research lies in a better understanding of the behaviors of children who are eating <lb/>beyond the sensation of satiation. <lb/>The development of overweight and obesity in young children has led to a focus <lb/>on the role of the caregivers during feeding. The aim is to analyze the incentives to <lb/>eat more (or less) and their impact on food regulation (Remy et al. 2015; Hetherington 2017; <lb/>Monnery-Patris et al. 2019). Some findings suggest that discordant parent-child interaction <lb/>during a meal results in increased intake amounts and/or frequency, and impairs the <lb/>infant&apos;s innate ability to adjust energy intake to their needs (McNally et al. 2016). Others <lb/>question parental feeding practices. The use of pressure (forcing one&apos;s child to eat or finish <lb/>a food), restriction (voluntarily limiting the consumption of a food or food group), as well <lb/>as emotional feeding (offering a food to a child either as a reward for good behavior or <lb/>in response to a negative emotion) appear to interfere with the infant&apos;s innate ability to <lb/>respond to hunger and satiation signals (Schwartz et al. 2011). These aspects would result <lb/>in accelerated infant weight gain (Di Santis et al. 2011). The &quot;responsive feeding&quot; approach <lb/>(Perez-Escamilla et al. 2017; Pérez-Escamilla et al. 2019), which refers to a way of feeding <lb/></body>

			<front>Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292. https://doi.org/10.3390/socsci10080292 <lb/>https://www.mdpi.com/journal/socsci <lb/></front>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>2 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>that is more centered on the expressed needs and behavior of the child, is an illustration <lb/>of the shifts in the nutritional management of educational feeding practices between <lb/>scientific contributions and the production of public policies. For instance, in France, <lb/>some recent developments in understanding the regulation of food intake are leading <lb/>to new recommendations in nutritional policies (ANSES 2019; HCSP 2020). These new <lb/>recommendations were based on the nutritional policy of the United States, in particular <lb/>that gathered in the Feeding Guidelines for Infants and Young Toddlers included in the <lb/>Dietary Guidelines for Americans. These changes may generate some norms, particularly <lb/>in professional parenting support and medicalized child care. <lb/>The present research is carried out in this context of knowledge development and <lb/>normative contents centered on the child. The socioanthropological angle analyzes parents&apos; <lb/>perceptions of signs of hunger and satiety or those associated with child development, <lb/>in their social dimensions. This article focuses on the close links between social food <lb/>norms and educational norms in the social regulation of the child&apos;s appetite and satiation, <lb/>determining when the child can or should be hungry and at which moment to eat and to <lb/>stop eating. The interest of a multidisciplinary approach lies in the articulation of these <lb/>social processes with the psychosensory and psychomotor dimensions as perceived by the <lb/>adult nurturers, and from which the feeding and food education practices are organized. <lb/>The aim is to identify what, in these practices, refers to adjustments to signals emitted by <lb/>the child or perceived as such, and what pertains to the social food norms internalized by <lb/>the parents and implemented in an educational situation. The focus is on the ways in which <lb/>dietary and educational models (in feeding) deal with the physiological (hunger, satiety, <lb/>satiation), psychosensory (pleasure, displeasure) and developmental (growth, weight <lb/>status) signals of the child. Additionally, how this management is deployed according to <lb/>the social group, the child&apos;s sex and the parental experience, which can oscillate between <lb/>reflexive or self-evident education, but also between top-down and bottom-up education. <lb/>The social regulation of feeding behaviors involved in the socialization of infants is <lb/>a long-established topic in sociology (Durkheim [1894] 1981) and anthropology (Mauss <lb/>1936). In particular, research emphasizes the increments of circadian rhythms on social <lb/>rhythms, which then play on the biological level through the influence of social norms on the <lb/>physiological competence of infants. The socioanthropological perspective underlines the <lb/>fact that these social processes affect the biological via interaction phenomena; at the level <lb/>of the individual, they will socialize the biological body and the impulses (understood as <lb/>psychological impulses generating motricity) and, at the level of human generations, they <lb/>will participate in the expression or inhibition of genetic characteristics (Poulain 2005). The <lb/>interplay between the social, the biological and the ecological is pointed out to show how <lb/>eating behavior is determined in the course of development and socialization. In the <lb/>dialogue with nutrigenetics and psychology, the process of expression or non-expression of <lb/>certain phenotypes resulting from these interactions is shown-so are the programming of <lb/>the infant&apos;s physiological competences, all the sensory-motor and sensory learnings, and <lb/>table manners acquired later during socialization within social food spaces (Poulain 2002, <lb/>2005, 2017). <lb/>This article seeks to extend this analysis. In line with Matty Chiva&apos;s work on the <lb/>sociocognitive, relational and affective modalities at work in child development, we are <lb/>interested in the interplay between the biological, the psychological and the sociological, <lb/>which is all the more significant given that the infant comes into the world in a state of <lb/>incompleteness (Hubert 2000), since it survives only through total dependence on its nur-<lb/>turing environment (Dupuy 2017a). While this aspect is mostly addressed by examining the <lb/>transition between sensation and perception from gusto-facial reflexes to the development <lb/>of neophobia (Fischler 1990; Fischler and Chiva 1986; Birch et al. 1987; Pliner 1994; Nick-<lb/>laus et al. 2005; Rigal et al. 2006; Rochedy and Poulain 2015), the bio-psycho-sociological <lb/>co-shaping of physical sensations related to hunger and satiety is less documented. Some <lb/>studies focus on the social processes that dictate when, how, and for how long children <lb/>should eat (Bril et al. 2001; Gojard 2001; Poulain 2002; Ochs and Shohet 2006; Ricroch and <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>3 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Saint Pol 2012; Skafida 2013; Dupuy 2013; Lhuissier et al. 2013; Poulain 2017). Others ex-<lb/>plore further the socially differentiated modalities of incorporating and regulating physical <lb/>sensations such as the expression of appetite and satiation (Le Pape and Plessz 2017). In <lb/>studies focusing on the sociology of food, transmission and incorporation of normative pre-<lb/>scriptions are viewed instead through the lens of parents&apos; socially structured relationship to <lb/>nutritional and child care norms (Gojard 2006; Dhuot 2018) in order to emphasize the early <lb/>acquisition of social differentiation processes. A previous analysis of the corpus collected in <lb/>our research focused on the perceptions of hunger and satiety by home-based childminders <lb/>by looking at the &quot;food work 1 &quot; they implement in the exercise of their job (Dupuy et al. <lb/>2018b). We have seen, based on other studies (Dupuy 2013; O&apos;Connell and Brannen <lb/>2016; Dupuy 2017b; Cardon et al. 2019), that &quot;food work&quot; requires significant adjustments <lb/>between parents and professionals. These vary with experience (professional or parental) <lb/>in child care and with the gap between parents&apos; and professionals&apos; social positions, as these <lb/>aspects affect professionals&apos; educational positioning. Through the analysis of the &quot;food <lb/>work&quot; contours, the teaching of social rules relating to the management of appetite and <lb/>satiation-strongly emphasized by professionals-was interpreted as a way to establish <lb/>a double legitimacy: both professional and social. Finally, in another article, attention <lb/>was paid to the derogatory modalities involved in the interactions between the feeding <lb/>environment and the infant. This focus on feeding contexts encourages consideration of <lb/>the complexity of feeding relationships and educational practices (Tibère and Dupuy 2021). <lb/>This article extends the analysis of the bio-psycho-social processes involved in regu-<lb/>lating hunger and satiety through a discussion focused on adults&apos; perceptions (and their <lb/>socially differentiated modes of expression) of such processes in the young child. The <lb/>objective is to identify the ways in which parents perceive the needs and state of the young <lb/>child and how these perceptions influence the &quot;food work&quot;. The aim is also to understand <lb/>the status of the child&apos;s psychomotor development in these perceptions, the evolution <lb/>of the food repertoire associated with these changes, and the dynamics that shape chil-<lb/>dren&apos;s daily eating practices, such as those that underlie the relationship to pleasure or <lb/>the consideration of the staturo-ponderal growth, which also partly determine the con-<lb/>trol of children&apos;s appetite and satiation through their socialization. This article proposes <lb/>to answer the following research question: How do standards structure food parenting <lb/>practices? Methodologically, this research question involves (i) identifying norms visible in <lb/>the discourses of parents (lexicometric analysis) and (ii) socially appropriate in the lived <lb/>experience of their children&apos;s food socialization (content analysis and photos elicitation). <lb/>This double analysis then makes it possible to identify the standards on which parents <lb/>actually rely to educate their children and to discuss the process of appropriation of new <lb/>standards resulting from scientific knowledge (and their use in public policies) that may <lb/>go against their sense of top-down parental education. <lb/>2. Materials and Methods <lb/>2.1. Study Design and Participants <lb/>This qualitative study, based on semi-structured face-to-face interviews conducted in <lb/>the respondents&apos; homes and/or workplaces, was conducted in 2016 in France and involved <lb/>28 parents of children under the age of 4 and 25 home-based childminders. Our research is <lb/>based on the analysis of the dietary socialization of children with a development considered <lb/>in pediatrics as&quot; typical &quot;, but no exclusion criteria were, however, considered. We reconcile <lb/>approaches on child development (psychology) and those on socialization (sociology) but <lb/>we do, however, assume a critical perspective regarding the primacy of developmental <lb/>thought, in the West, which institutes &quot;normal&quot; childhood. <lb/>A combination of methods for data collection were used: two interviews per family, <lb/>the &quot;photo elicitation interview&quot; method (Collier and Collier [1976] 1986) to understand <lb/>the child&apos;s diet and contextualize it (Dupuy et al. 2018a), and finally cross-interviews of <lb/>parents and home-based childminders, including six parents/home-based childminders of <lb/>the same children dyads. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>4 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>For initiating contact, intermediaries were sought, i.e., individuals who had either a <lb/>weak or strong indirect link with the participants. For parents, the &quot;snowball&quot; method <lb/>was adopted and combined with direct contact in parks and child care facilities with an <lb/>inclusion criterion: to be a parent of at least one child aged 3 years old or less. No exclusion <lb/>criteria. Recruitment was conducted directly orally or indirectly in writing by presenting <lb/>the research objectives. Of the parents, 20 were interviewed twice, at least one month apart, <lb/>with an average of two and a half hours of interview time per family. Each interview was <lb/>recorded and then fully transcribed. <lb/>For this article, we focus only on the parental data. This is a comprehensive type of <lb/>qualitative sociological survey in a view close to Grounded Theory, which breaks with the <lb/>hypothetico-deductive model. Thus, the a priori definition of the number and characteris-<lb/>tics of respondents to be selected is not subject to representativeness in the statistical sense <lb/>but responds to a dynamic of back and forth and constant adjustments between research <lb/>hypotheses, analytical work and the accumulation of data from the field which leads to <lb/>saturation effects, e.g., when the new data no longer modify the gradually developed <lb/>theoretical framework. <lb/>2.2. Socioeconomic Characteristics <lb/>The interviews took place mainly in the Toulouse area, the fourth largest city in France. <lb/>The parents came from a variety of socioeconomic backgrounds: eight parents had a high <lb/>socioeconomic status, four were downgraded (their professional status was lower than <lb/>what they could expect given their level of education), nine were of the middle class, four <lb/>belonged to the working class, and four were in a state of poverty. <lb/>Among the 28 families, the mothers&apos; ages ranged from 24 to 42, with an average age of <lb/>32 years (σ = 4.84). Fathers ranged in age from 22 to 49, with an average age of 34 (σ = 6.51). <lb/>Of the families interviewed, sixteen had a single child, eight had two children, and <lb/>three had three children. Of the 28 households, 24 were couples and only three were <lb/>single-parent families. Of the children represented in this qualitative study, there were <lb/>nineteen boys and eleven girls; they ranged in age from 5 to 48 months, with an average age <lb/>of 23.7 months. Among them, three were primarily looked after by their parents, thirteen <lb/>were looked after by a home-based childminder, ten were in a collective day-care center, <lb/>and four were in an alternating parent/childminder arrangement at home. <lb/>The characteristics of the parents and their children are detailed in Table 1. <lb/>Table 1. Socioeconomic characteristics of participants. <lb/>Status in the Household <lb/>Mothers <lb/>Fathers <lb/>Children Involved <lb/>Population, n <lb/>28 <lb/>25 <lb/>30 (11 girls, 19 boys) <lb/>Age in months or years, n <lb/>&lt;6 months <lb/>6-11 months <lb/>12-18 months <lb/>19-24 months <lb/>25-30 months <lb/>31-36 months <lb/>24-29 years old <lb/>30-35 years old <lb/>36-40 years old <lb/>41-49 years old <lb/>Unknown <lb/>8 <lb/>12 <lb/>5 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>6 <lb/>(7 + 1 *) <lb/>6 <lb/>6 <lb/>2 <lb/>1 <lb/>4 <lb/>6 <lb/>4 <lb/>7 <lb/>8 <lb/>Socioeconomic status, n <lb/>High <lb/>8 <lb/>Middle class <lb/>9 <lb/>Working class <lb/>4 <lb/>Downgraded <lb/>4 <lb/>Poverty <lb/>3 <lb/>Childbirth, n <lb/>Primiparous <lb/>16 <lb/>Multiparous (including twins) <lb/>12 <lb/>* Information provided by a single mother with primary custody, with her former spouse having the child every <lb/>other weekend. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>5 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>2.3. Ethical Criteria <lb/>The qualitative survey obtained retrospective ethical approval (N • : IRB00011835-2019-<lb/>09-24-180, Université Fédérale de Toulouse IRB # 1). This study was also published in <lb/>the CNIL declaration n • 2214433. The objectives of the research were explained to the <lb/>respondents and their consent for recording and obtaining the photo files was obtained. <lb/>All interviews were strictly anonymous and fictitious names were given to the people <lb/>interviewed. Finally, respondents were not compensated in any way. <lb/>2.4. Qualitative Survey Material <lb/>Among parents, the perception of children&apos;s signs of hunger and satiety was addressed <lb/>in relation to (1) family characteristics (social position, composition, organization); (2) char-<lb/>acteristics of the family diet, in particular those of the children, ranging from food shopping <lb/>to the management of leftovers, by also exploring food intake (composition, quantities, <lb/>frequency, duration, contexts); (3) perceptions of the signals emitted by the children; (4) the <lb/>modalities of educational delegation in the field of nutrition, this term referring to the <lb/>guidelines and instructions given to the childminder by the parents; (5) milk diets, then <lb/>diversification; and finally (6) perceptions relating to the food educational settings (Table <lb/>A1 in Appendix A). During the interviews, the parents were asked to describe their child&apos;s <lb/>expression of hunger or satiety, to talk about the pace of their child&apos;s mealtimes, or to <lb/>describe their child&apos;s appetite, its constancy or variations, according to different situations, <lb/>such as when the child is feeling good, tired or ill. The interview guide was drawn up <lb/>from the exploratory literature review and collection tools constructed in other sociological <lb/>surveys relating to nutrition during early childhood conducted by some of the authors of <lb/>this article. Then, the survey guide was tested in an exploratory phase and adjusted before <lb/>the implementation of data collection. <lb/>For twenty households, two interviews were conducted. The two interviews were <lb/>spaced 44 days apart on average (σ = 28.6). The objective of the second interview was to <lb/>explore the dimensions previously mentioned while focusing on the changes and stabilities <lb/>observed by the parents in the child since the first meeting. A second meeting generally <lb/>leads to greater reflexivity, enabling the dynamic processes at work in socialization to be <lb/>revealed. Finally, the methodological protocol allowed the parents to express themselves <lb/>via photos that contextualize food intake, which anchored a number of discussions about <lb/>everyday life. It is noteworthy that only the least employed parents or those from the least <lb/>educated social groups refused the second interview, with the exception of one parent, who <lb/>accepted the photo protocol but not the second meeting, and who was a downgraded type <lb/>parent, the interview being quite demanding in terms of commitment. <lb/>2.5. Analyses <lb/>A methodological analysis of each interview was carried out, including the initial <lb/>contacts and the exchange process. In this article, particular emphasis is placed on the <lb/>gender order (Connell 1987) in early childhood socialization inquiry. A sociological analysis <lb/>was also carried out, taking into account the discursive and social contexts and the so-<lb/>cioeconomic variables. As a result, topic-based analyses of the statements were combined <lb/>with lexicometric and statistical analyses using the free software IRAMUTEQ (Version 0.7 <lb/>alpha 2, LERASS Laboratory-REPERE, GNU GPL License ©2008-2014 Pierre Ratinaud, <lb/>University of Toulouse Jean Jaurès, France). This software enables to cut, code and interpret <lb/>speeches by lemmatization. The lexicometric analysis brings out classes of statements that <lb/>are significantly connected to the qualitative survey guide (Table A1 in Appendix A). How-<lb/>ever, it is interesting to note those that move away from it and compare the distribution of <lb/>&quot;lexical worlds&quot; (Rouré and Reinert 1993) within the corpus. The Reinert method employed <lb/>in this article (Appendix B) captures the internal organization of the speeches based on the <lb/>segmentation into classes represented by dendrograms and tables (Appendices C and D). <lb/>This method aims to identify the main themes mentioned in the corpus. Each interview <lb/>is therefore divided into text segments presenting similar lexical profiles (e.g., the same <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>6 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>words) grouped into discourses classes. Each of these classes is then described from the lex-<lb/>icon which characterizes it, which corresponds to the words significantly over-represented <lb/>on the basis of a Chi2. Then, the sociodescriptive variables are injected a posteriori to study <lb/>the statistical link between these variables and the discourses classes (Appendix B). The <lb/>factorial analysis of correspondences gives a graphic representation of the correlations. <lb/>This supports the interpretation of the differentiations identified between the classes. The <lb/>different lexical registers identified are interpreted according to the methodological and <lb/>qualitative content analyses conducted in the first stage; they are then used to support <lb/>or discuss the statistical results (Scheme 1). The quotes from the respondents presented <lb/>in the analysis correspond to quotes significantly over-represented in the profiles of the <lb/>discourses classes to which they are associated. <lb/>oc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/>7 of 38 <lb/>Scheme 1. Analyses of qualitative survey data (in bold, the corpora on which this article is based). <lb/>Concerning the parents, a first analysis was based on a corpus of 28 texts, correspond-<lb/>ing to the 28 households surveyed (cf. Section 3.2). A second analysis, which was dynamic, <lb/>was based on the corpus of 20 parents who were twice interviewed (see Section 3.3.1). To <lb/>study the differences in the discourses classes of parents interviewed twice, a second anal-<lb/>ysis was performed comparing the discourses of the first interview with those of the sec-<lb/>ond interview in order to study whether the narrative process engaged over time has ef-<lb/>fects on the discourses, e.g., relating to the perception of dynamics of change in the child&apos;s <lb/>food repertoire and the expressed needs. <lb/>This textual statistical analysis was completed by a content analysis combining the <lb/>photo elicitation method with the two interviews. It highlighted the various contexts in <lb/>which the normative contents involved in socialization take place, based on the staturo-<lb/>ponderal growth, the tension between pleasure and satiation, and the daily food manage-<lb/>ment. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Gender Order <lb/>Although the interview was indiscriminately addressed to either parent, only three <lb/>fathers responded, one of whom responded during the second interview only. Thus, when <lb/>referring to the parental corpus, it would be more accurate to speak of the maternal cor-<lb/>pus. The lexical universes thus brought to the analysis reflect the gender order relating to <lb/>the discrepancies between mothers and fathers, women and men in the division of food <lb/>and care duties within the household. In this sense, they mask the gendered differentia-<lb/>tion of parental norms and food, nutritional and educational practices that help structure <lb/>Corpus total <lb/>Lexicometric analysis <lb/>Content <lb/>sociological <lb/>analysis <lb/>Methodological analysis <lb/>Parents first and second interview <lb/>comparison (n = 20) <lb/>Home-based childminder <lb/>(n = 25) <lb/>Parents (n = 28) <lb/>Comparison of parent and childminder <lb/>dyads (n = 6) <lb/>Scheme 1. Analyses of qualitative survey data (in bold, the corpora on which this article is based). <lb/>Concerning the parents, a first analysis was based on a corpus of 28 texts, correspond-<lb/>ing to the 28 households surveyed (cf. Section 3.2). A second analysis, which was dynamic, <lb/>was based on the corpus of 20 parents who were twice interviewed (see Section 3.3.1). <lb/>To study the differences in the discourses classes of parents interviewed twice, a second <lb/>analysis was performed comparing the discourses of the first interview with those of the <lb/>second interview in order to study whether the narrative process engaged over time has <lb/>effects on the discourses, e.g., relating to the perception of dynamics of change in the child&apos;s <lb/>food repertoire and the expressed needs. <lb/>This textual statistical analysis was completed by a content analysis combining the <lb/>photo elicitation method with the two interviews. It highlighted the various contexts in <lb/>which the normative contents involved in socialization take place, based on the staturo-<lb/>ponderal growth, the tension between pleasure and satiation, and the daily food management. <lb/>3. Results <lb/>3.1. Gender Order <lb/>Although the interview was indiscriminately addressed to either parent, only three <lb/>fathers responded, one of whom responded during the second interview only. Thus, when <lb/>referring to the parental corpus, it would be more accurate to speak of the maternal corpus. <lb/>The lexical universes thus brought to the analysis reflect the gender order relating to the <lb/>discrepancies between mothers and fathers, women and men in the division of food and <lb/>care duties within the household. In this sense, they mask the gendered differentiation <lb/>of parental norms and food, nutritional and educational practices that help structure <lb/>children&apos;s relationship to appetite and satiation; this may be the basis for the differential <lb/>socialization of girls and boys, a dimension that we have studied elsewhere (Dupuy 2017b; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>7 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Dupuy et al. 2018b) and that was also identified in other works (Birch and Fisher 2000; <lb/>Birch et al. 2003). <lb/>3.2. The Lexical Universes of Parents <lb/>The system of classification (Figure 1) distinguishes five hierarchical classes as follows: <lb/>Classes 1, 5 and 4 refer to the social conditions of food socialization, in contrast to Classes 2 <lb/>and 3, which represent food repertoires. Class 1 differs from Classes 5 and 4 in the sense <lb/>that 1 refers to a parental discourse supported by the scholarly, rather medical, norms <lb/>of pediatric nutrition and medicalized child care, whereas 5 and 4 refer to social norms. <lb/>Classes 2 and 3 are distinct from each other in that they are based on two distinct food <lb/>registers, one associated with the world of sweet foods, the other with that of salty foods. <lb/>The significant relationships for these analyses are presented in Appendix C (Table A2). <lb/>Correspondence factor analysis shows, on a horizontal axis, an opposition between Class 1 <lb/>and Class 2, which could be positioned on a &quot;nutritional recommendations&quot; axis, because <lb/>of the strong supervision of access to sweet foods, and a second axis where Classes 3, 4 and <lb/>5 are spread out, which would correspond to &quot;the child&apos;s socialization to food&quot; (Figure 2). <lb/>Class 1 (22% of the content segments analyzed) includes content associated with <lb/>parents&apos; concern for medical issues, particularly nutrition, at various stages. Parents <lb/>with the highest levels of education and income and whose children are followed by a <lb/>pediatrician and a general practitioner are more strongly represented. This class-which <lb/>we call &quot;Relating to the medical&quot;-relates significantly to body weight (in the sense of <lb/>losing weight), height, anxiety, issues, reflux, concern, and girls. The medical dimension is <lb/>present with significant occurrences of the following words: health, curve, pediatrician, <lb/>doctor, notebook, general practitioner, growth, allergy, weight, vomit, body, sick, as for this <lb/>respondent, statistically over-represented in this class. <lb/>&quot;When I come home from the doctor, that&apos;s the first thing I do, I graph. It&apos;s something <lb/>I love, I always look forward to graphing, I don&apos;t know why, but it&apos;s seeing if they&apos;re <lb/>progressing well, tracking, I don&apos;t know. Yes I look to see if they&apos;re in the norm. And <lb/>they are pretty much in the norm&quot;. [Mother (p &lt; 0.0001; Chi2: 43.08), high social <lb/>position, 4-year-old daughter and 11-month-old boy]. <lb/>Recommendations for dietary diversification are based on timelines, which combine <lb/>the child&apos;s age (in months) and the diversification of the food repertoire. They are proposed <lb/>in numerous channels or media, ranging from medical follow-up by a pediatrician to <lb/>communication by the food industry, including child care facilities in services dedicated <lb/>to early childhood. The dissemination of these recommendations has intensified with <lb/>&quot;nutritionnalisation&quot; (Poulain 2009), a process of thinking about one&apos;s relationship to food <lb/>through a purely nutritional lens. These recommendations are thus easily accessible to <lb/>parents from all social backgrounds, even if they are not always followed and viewed <lb/>as legitimate (Gojard 2001; Gojard 2010; Régnier and Masullo 2009; Depecker 2010). In <lb/>addition, many studies confirm the importance of nutritional recommendations during the <lb/>transition to parenthood, particularly for a first child and during the first months of life <lb/>(Anderson et al. 2001; Corbeau 2010; Dhuot 2018; Moura and Aschemann-Witzel 2020). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>8 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>A2). Correspondence factor analysis shows, on a horizontal axis, an opposition between <lb/>Class 1 and Class 2, which could be positioned on a &quot;nutritional recommendations&quot; axis, <lb/>because of the strong supervision of access to sweet foods, and a second axis where Clas-<lb/>ses 3, 4 and 5 are spread out, which would correspond to &quot;the child&apos;s socialization to food&quot; <lb/>(Figure 2). <lb/>Figure 1. Dendrogram-parental corpus. <lb/>Figure 1. Dendrogram-parental corpus. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 2. Correspondence factor analysis based on Reinert&apos;s classification-parent corpus. AFC of <lb/>the two dimensions summarizing the most data-factor 1, eigenvalue: 0.29; %: 33.99; factor 2, eigen-<lb/>value: 0.21; %: 24.99. <lb/>Class 1 (22% of the content segments analyzed) includes content associated with par-<lb/>ents&apos; concern for medical issues, particularly nutrition, at various stages. Parents with the <lb/>highest levels of education and income and whose children are followed by a pediatrician <lb/>and a general practitioner are more strongly represented. This class-which we call &quot;Re-<lb/>Figure 2. Correspondence factor analysis based on Reinert&apos;s classification-parent corpus. AFC <lb/>of the two dimensions summarizing the most data-factor 1, eigenvalue: 0.29; %: 33.99; factor 2, <lb/>eigenvalue: 0.21; %: 24.99. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>9 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Class 2 (17.72% of the content segments analyzed) overlaps with lemmatized forms <lb/>designating the purchase or consumption of sweet foods when desserts or snacks are <lb/>mentioned. This class illustrates the &quot;relationship to the sweet food repertoire&quot; of parents <lb/>with respect to their children, particularly in terms of how they manage their appetite for <lb/>sweet foods. The structure of meals is a social organization of food intake that gives dessert <lb/>a particular status as the end of the meal, which serves as the finale of the meal (Tibère <lb/>and Dupuy 2021). The social organization of the end of the meal, which is often sweet, <lb/>is transmitted to and processed by young children during their socialization. They thus <lb/>learn to regulate their consumption according to a dietary time frame. Dessert is also a <lb/>technique used by adults to regulate food intake of simple non-carbohydrate nutrients <lb/>and ensure that the child is properly fed. Class 2 also refers to afternoon snacks, which <lb/>in France remain resolutely associated with the sugary, pleasurable, and indulgent world <lb/>(Diasio 2006) despite certain nutritional recommendations that promote the &quot;cereal + fruit <lb/>+ dairy&quot; formula (Tibère et al. 2018). More than the other meals of the day, the afternoon <lb/>snack is organized according to the child&apos;s desires and, implicitly, those of the parents <lb/>(Dupuy 2013), which reminds us how mothers&apos; eating habits and preferences can affect <lb/>their children&apos;s diet (Dhuot 2018). This class reflects an attraction to sweet foods, such as <lb/>chocolate, cakes, sweets, sugar, which are prevailing among parents with the lowest levels <lb/>of education and resources, even though many mention their control over the purchase <lb/>and consumption of industrial sweet products. <lb/>Some parents wonder about the links between their children&apos;s attraction to sugar and <lb/>their preferences. <lb/>&quot;And then, does it matter or not, I have a sweet tooth, so obviously I ate a lot of sugar <lb/>during my pregnancy and that may have had an effect, but I don&apos;t know if there is a link. <lb/>So since I tend to eat more sugar, maybe I got her used to sugar&quot; [Mother, middle-class <lb/>social position, one 33-month-old daughter]. <lb/>Pictures 1 and 2: Daily situation: Meals and leftovers, 11-month-old girl <lb/>Mother, working-class social position (p = 0.00065; Chi2: 11.62). <lb/>to food through a purely nutritional lens. These recommendations are thus easily accessi-<lb/>ble to parents from all social backgrounds, even if they are not always followed and <lb/>viewed as legitimate (Gojard 2001; Gojard 2010; Régnier and Masullo 2009; Depecker <lb/>2010). In addition, many studies confirm the importance of nutritional recommendations <lb/>during the transition to parenthood, particularly for a first child and during the first <lb/>months of life (Anderson et al. 2001; Corbeau 2010; Dhuot 2018; Moura and Aschemann-<lb/>Witzel 2020). <lb/>Class 2 (17.72% of the content segments analyzed) overlaps with lemmatized forms <lb/>designating the purchase or consumption of sweet foods when desserts or snacks are men-<lb/>tioned. This class illustrates the &quot;relationship to the sweet food repertoire&quot; of parents with <lb/>respect to their children, particularly in terms of how they manage their appetite for sweet <lb/>foods. The structure of meals is a social organization of food intake that gives dessert a <lb/>particular status as the end of the meal, which serves as the finale of the meal (Tibère and <lb/>Dupuy 2021). The social organization of the end of the meal, which is often sweet, is trans-<lb/>mitted to and processed by young children during their socialization. They thus learn to <lb/>regulate their consumption according to a dietary time frame. Dessert is also a technique <lb/>used by adults to regulate food intake of simple non-carbohydrate nutrients and ensure <lb/>that the child is properly fed. Class 2 also refers to afternoon snacks, which in France re-<lb/>main resolutely associated with the sugary, pleasurable, and indulgent world (Diasio <lb/>2006) despite certain nutritional recommendations that promote the &quot;cereal + fruit + <lb/>dairy&quot; formula (Tibère et al. 2018). More than the other meals of the day, the afternoon <lb/>snack is organized according to the child&apos;s desires and, implicitly, those of the parents <lb/>(Dupuy 2013), which reminds us how mothers&apos; eating habits and preferences can affect <lb/>their children&apos;s diet (Dhuot 2018). This class reflects an attraction to sweet foods, such as <lb/>chocolate, cakes, sweets, sugar, which are prevailing among parents with the lowest levels <lb/>of education and resources, even though many mention their control over the purchase <lb/>and consumption of industrial sweet products. <lb/>Some parents wonder about the links between their children&apos;s attraction to sugar and <lb/>their preferences. <lb/>&quot;And then, does it matter or not, I have a sweet tooth, so obviously I ate a lot of sugar <lb/>during my pregnancy and that may have had an effect, but I don&apos;t know if there is a link. <lb/>So since I tend to eat more sugar, maybe I got her used to sugar&quot; [Mother, middle-<lb/>class social position, one 33-month-old daughter]. <lb/>Pictures 1 and 2: Daily situation: Meals and leftovers, 11-month-old girl <lb/>Mother, working-class social position (p = 0.00065; Chi2: 11.62). <lb/>&quot;White chocolate, I made her taste it. Even I tasted it, I thought it was really good! The <lb/>first time I gave her some, I even opened a second jar for her because she gobbled it up! I <lb/>thought &quot;oh great! &quot;(...) And she loved it, I gave her a second one, although she didn&apos;t <lb/>finish it, but that&apos;s normal! (...) But it&apos;s true that I tended to do that at the beginning <lb/>&quot;White chocolate, I made her taste it. Even I tasted it, I thought it was really good! The <lb/>first time I gave her some, I even opened a second jar for her because she gobbled it up! I <lb/>thought &quot;oh great!&quot; ( . . . ) And she loved it, I gave her a second one, although she didn&apos;t <lb/>finish it, but that&apos;s normal! ( . . . ) But it&apos;s true that I tended to do that at the beginning <lb/>and when she discovered the different cream desserts, when she had finished and kept <lb/>opening her mouth, I would open a second jar. But she would never finish it, it was mom <lb/>who finished it&quot;. <lb/>Among parents from middle-class backgrounds, dessert and afternoon snacks are <lb/>characterized by a preference for fruit and fruit compotes, preferably organic or bought <lb/>at the local market, as well as dairy products such as yogurts and cheeses. As for sweet <lb/>foods, they are mentioned in relation to the control that parents maintain over their child&apos;s <lb/>consumption, or even their refusal to buy them. Thus, this class is rather characterized <lb/>by a discourse expressing control, or even rejection, of the consumption of sugar or sweet <lb/>products, with the exception of naturally sweet products such as fruit and compotes. We <lb/>find this idea in the following remarks: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>10 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;And then on top of that I don&apos;t want to buy . . . anyway, there are organic ones but they <lb/>are sweet and I find that insane, all the &quot;baby&quot; products are sweet, it&apos;s crazy!&quot; [Mother, <lb/>middle-class social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;Yes, they love compotes, so I buy them, I get them without added sugar because I tell <lb/>myself they are small anyway&quot;. [Mother, working-class social position, 14-month-<lb/>old boy and girl twins]. <lb/>&quot;They make this organic stuff with oranges, well, stuff without sugar or anything, it <lb/>suits him very well, I mean he can tell the difference&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social <lb/>position, two boys aged 29 months and 4 years]. <lb/>Class 3, accounting for 21.21% of the corpus segments, is associated with two registers: <lb/>the ingredients present in purees-especially when parents refer to diversification-and <lb/>the main courses at lunches and dinners. Discussions include vegetables, such as carrots, <lb/>tomatoes and zucchini, as well as starchy foods such as pasta or rice and animal proteins <lb/>such as meat or ham. This class is called: &quot;relating to the salty food repertoire&quot; and <lb/>involves a parental discourse centered on cooking preparations, recipes or proposed meals <lb/>or a nutritional discourse of attention focused on dietary balance, the presence of certain <lb/>nutrients during a given meal or day, particularly concerning the alternative &quot;animal <lb/>or vegetable products&quot;. This class is significantly associated with parents reporting an <lb/>important concern for nutritional or medical recommendations, having a daughter and <lb/>having a high level of education even if the level of resources, compared to the level of <lb/>education, is low. <lb/>Pictures 3 and 4: Daily situation: Pea puree and leftovers offered during the interview <lb/>Mother, high social position, two boys aged 5 and 29 months (p &lt; 0.0001; Chi2 26.54). <lb/>characterized by a preference for fruit and fruit compotes, preferably organic or bought at <lb/>the local market, as well as dairy products such as yogurts and cheeses. As for sweet foods, <lb/>they are mentioned in relation to the control that parents maintain over their child&apos;s con-<lb/>sumption, or even their refusal to buy them. Thus, this class is rather characterized by a <lb/>discourse expressing control, or even rejection, of the consumption of sugar or sweet prod-<lb/>ucts, with the exception of naturally sweet products such as fruit and compotes. We find <lb/>this idea in the following remarks: <lb/>&quot;And then on top of that I don&apos;t want to buy ... anyway, there are organic ones but they <lb/>are sweet and I find that insane, all the &quot;baby&quot; products are sweet, it&apos;s crazy!&quot; [Mother, <lb/>middle-class social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;Yes, they love compotes, so I buy them, I get them without added sugar because I tell <lb/>myself they are small anyway&quot;. [Mother, working-class social position, 14-month-<lb/>old boy and girl twins]. <lb/>&quot;They make this organic stuff with oranges, well, stuff without sugar or anything, it <lb/>suits him very well, I mean he can tell the difference&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social <lb/>position, two boys aged 29 months and 4 years]. <lb/>Class 3, accounting for 21.21% of the corpus segments, is associated with two regis-<lb/>ters: the ingredients present in purees-especially when parents refer to diversification-<lb/>and the main courses at lunches and dinners. Discussions include vegetables, such as car-<lb/>rots, tomatoes and zucchini, as well as starchy foods such as pasta or rice and animal pro-<lb/>teins such as meat or ham. This class is called: &quot;relating to the salty food repertoire&quot; and <lb/>involves a parental discourse centered on cooking preparations, recipes or proposed <lb/>meals or a nutritional discourse of attention focused on dietary balance, the presence of <lb/>certain nutrients during a given meal or day, particularly concerning the alternative &quot;an-<lb/>imal or vegetable products&quot;. This class is significantly associated with parents reporting <lb/>an important concern for nutritional or medical recommendations, having a daughter and <lb/>having a high level of education even if the level of resources, compared to the level of <lb/>education, is low. <lb/>Pictures 3 and 4: Daily situation: Pea puree and leftovers offered during the interview <lb/>Mother, high social position, two boys aged 5 and 29 months (p &lt; 0.0001; Chi2 26.54). <lb/>Mother cooks mostly vegetables for her boys who eat no meat in the evening and on <lb/>weekends. <lb/>&quot;In terms of vegetables, he eats everything. Yesterday, he ate parsnips, and my grand-<lb/>mother said, &quot;But parsnips are disgusting;&quot; well, he liked them. Anyway, it was not too <lb/>strong, it remained bearable, he ate, he ate everything. (…) So what works immediately <lb/>is green beans, peas, that goes down really well, and... So the sweet potato last time I <lb/>Mother cooks mostly vegetables for her boys who eat no meat in the evening and on <lb/>weekends. <lb/>&quot;In terms of vegetables, he eats everything. Yesterday, he ate parsnips, and my grand-<lb/>mother said, &quot;But parsnips are disgusting;&quot; well, he liked them. Anyway, it was not too <lb/>strong, it remained bearable, he ate, he ate everything. ( . . . ) So what works immediately <lb/>is green beans, peas, that goes down really well, and . . . So the sweet potato last time I <lb/>made it a little too thick, so it was weird, so it didn&apos;t go down well . . . But beans, peas, <lb/>and also leeks go down well. <lb/>[Interviewer: And you use leek alone?] <lb/>Yes, only leeks. I don&apos;t put a lot of potatoes, in fact, because I was told that with vegetables, <lb/>for the taste, it was better not to put too much potato. And he likes it. ( . . . ) So it&apos;s <lb/>strange because the first time I made him taste peas I had put green beans too, so it&apos;s <lb/>actually the first time that he is eating plain peas, only peas. It seems to be going well. <lb/>Okay, there&apos;s a little bit of a funny face though . . . <lb/>[A few minutes later] Will you close your mouth? You cheeky boy! Eliott? I&apos;m going <lb/>to try the little train again, &quot;Eliott, choo-choo&quot; [she makes the little train with the <lb/>spoon to his mouth], does it work? Well now I think that . . . Well, you&apos;ve eaten a little <lb/>more than half of it, that&apos;s not bad!&quot; <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>11 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Class 4 (14.57% of the content segments analyzed) corresponds to &quot;the temporal <lb/>framework of food socialization&quot;. This register does not so much refer to learning by <lb/>children, who are themselves subject to social conditions, as to the way in which parents <lb/>organize themselves to incrementally set food rhythms. This class sets schedules for food <lb/>intake and meals and by modifying responses to their children&apos;s physiological needs. <lb/>Parental learning about feeding management, with the sleep cycle of newborns and infants, <lb/>is addressed: there are, for example, references to the words morning, evening, night, noon, <lb/>wakes up or time. <lb/>This class significantly includes parents who declare that their child is followed by a <lb/>pediatrician, parents with a middle-class social position, parents with a medium level of <lb/>education and resources, and less significantly among parents with a low level of education <lb/>and resources and primiparous mothers. This class is titled: &quot;temporal framework of food <lb/>socialization&quot; as illustrated in the following interview extract: <lb/>&quot;And for the afternoon snack it&apos;s the same, he has always been used, since he was little, to <lb/>having a snack when he gets up from his nap. So when he gets up, he says &quot;let&apos;s go and <lb/>have a snack&quot;. But I think it&apos;s more out of habit than hunger. It&apos;s because he&apos;s used to it <lb/>that when he gets up from his nap, he knows he&apos;s getting a snack. But other than that, <lb/>we try to make sure he eats at fixed times&quot;. [Mother, intermediate social position, a <lb/>30-month-old boy]. <lb/>Class 5 (24.48% of the content segments analyzed) is associated with the &quot;social frame-<lb/>work of food socialization&quot; in particular with learning table manners. It is characterized by <lb/>the occurrences of the following words: table, play, hunger, meal. In this class, the regulation <lb/>of appetite is learned within meals and not through eating outside of meals. This reminds <lb/>us of how important the acquisition of social practices related to food is. Mealtime is a <lb/>space for the acquisition of table manners, based on parental and professional educational <lb/>practices as in the following interview extract for this mother of high social position who <lb/>&quot;teaches&quot; her education through play. These include the ways of behaving at the table, <lb/>which vary according to what adults and their social norms consider appropriate or inap-<lb/>propriate for the child&apos;s age. During their early socialization both within and outside the <lb/>family, children internalize these norms by imitating adults and other children. Getting <lb/>children to eat &quot;well&quot; is an educational challenge. Here, again, there are different possible <lb/>strategies from parents and different attitudes from children depending on social and <lb/>cultural backgrounds that influence educational and family models as well as adjustments <lb/>during interactions. <lb/>&quot;With the green puree, when he played with it, when he dipped his hands in it, I thought <lb/>it was so cool. It was carnage, I was painted, the floor, his chair too. But he ate it all. He <lb/>played with what he had on his hands. And I thought, &quot;I&apos;m never going to get mad at <lb/>him when he does that, I&apos;m going to let him do that, that&apos;s cool&quot;. We also agree on this <lb/>point of view, we are not going to ask him at 5 months to eat properly. As long as he <lb/>wants to put his hands in, he will&quot;. [Mother, high social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>Picture 5: Daily situation-Meals and leftovers of a 7-month-old boy, <lb/>Mother, high social position (p = 0.00381; Chi2 8.37). <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>12 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>13 of 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Picture 5: Daily situation-Meals and leftovers of a 7-month-old boy, <lb/>Mother, high social position (p = 0.00381; Chi2 8.37). <lb/>&quot;No, I still hold him, but I don&apos;t want to get into a fight with him, and since I can tell <lb/>he wants to play with the food, I bought him an apron with sleeves and I let him put his <lb/>hands in it. [...] [commenting on the photo] Yes, he puts some in his hands and has <lb/>fun closing his hand, so it comes up and it makes him laugh. Because with diversifica-<lb/>tion, I read that it&apos;s good for him to know the shape of the food, so I think I&apos;ll put some <lb/>well-cooked pieces in his puree so he can touch and know the shape of the vegetables&quot;. <lb/>[Mother, high social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>The educational practices of adults are shaped by the adjustments that occur in inter-<lb/>actions with children (Laurier and Wiggins 2011). Moreover, the use of play depends on <lb/>the level of tolerance for the playful register at the table or when eating (Corbeau 2008; <lb/>Lalanne and Tibère 2008) as well as on socially differentiated conceptions of childhood <lb/>(Lahire 2019). <lb/>&quot;I don&apos;t force him, if he doesn&apos;t want to, then he doesn&apos;t want to. We take a little break <lb/>with a toy and then he eats the rest&quot;. [Mother, high social position, 7-month-old <lb/>boy]. <lb/>Young children&apos;s difficulty in controlling their bodies and resisting the urge to move <lb/>is reflected in their parents&apos; remarks, especially when the child switches from a highchair <lb/>to a regular chair. In some families, these chairs are used alternately, giving the child some <lb/>flexibility and allowing for a quiet meal in the evening. With the exception of the parents <lb/>who are downgraded and belong to the &quot;cultural capital&quot; (Bourdieu [1972] 2000) and who <lb/>teach table manners, Class 5 is over-represented among the parents of a modest social <lb/>position and with a low level of education and resources, who mainly mention the playful <lb/>and convivial aspect of this learning. This aspect, while it may reflect a bias of social at-<lb/>tractiveness, may also reveal educational strategies used by these parents to establish a <lb/>certain &quot;respectability&quot; in food education, as highlighted elsewhere (Le Pape and Plessz <lb/>2017) through the teaching of a legitimate rhythm, in this case the duration of the meal as <lb/>we observe in these two parents. <lb/>&quot;We don&apos;t let them play with food much, the only time is with the letters that are in the <lb/>soup but otherwise, no, not at all&quot;. [Father, middle-class social position, one boy 48 <lb/>months old, two girls 5 and 10 years old] <lb/>&quot;Well, for her age, she knows how to behave, she is not messy, she eats well with her <lb/>spoon. Then I&apos;m probably too manic but it&apos;s something I can&apos;t stand. She doesn&apos;t play <lb/>with the food, she doesn&apos;t spit with it, and when it&apos;s too dirty I tell her &quot;wait, settle down <lb/>and only then we&apos;ll eat more&quot;. But she eats well, she is clean, sometimes she will play <lb/>with the ham, but I tell her &quot;it&apos;s not very nice, we don&apos;t play with the food&quot;, she is quite <lb/>&quot;No, I still hold him, but I don&apos;t want to get into a fight with him, and since I can tell <lb/>he wants to play with the food, I bought him an apron with sleeves and I let him put <lb/>his hands in it. [ . . . ] [commenting on the photo] Yes, he puts some in his hands <lb/>and has fun closing his hand, so it comes up and it makes him laugh. Because with <lb/>diversification, I read that it&apos;s good for him to know the shape of the food, so I think <lb/>I&apos;ll put some well-cooked pieces in his puree so he can touch and know the shape of the <lb/>vegetables&quot;. [Mother, high social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>The educational practices of adults are shaped by the adjustments that occur in <lb/>interactions with children (Laurier and Wiggins 2011). Moreover, the use of play depends <lb/>on the level of tolerance for the playful register at the table or when eating (Corbeau 2008; <lb/>Lalanne and Tibère 2008) as well as on socially differentiated conceptions of childhood <lb/>(Lahire 2019). <lb/>&quot;I don&apos;t force him, if he doesn&apos;t want to, then he doesn&apos;t want to. We take a little break with <lb/>a toy and then he eats the rest&quot;. [Mother, high social position, 7-month-old boy]. <lb/>Young children&apos;s difficulty in controlling their bodies and resisting the urge to move <lb/>is reflected in their parents&apos; remarks, especially when the child switches from a highchair <lb/>to a regular chair. In some families, these chairs are used alternately, giving the child <lb/>some flexibility and allowing for a quiet meal in the evening. With the exception of the <lb/>parents who are downgraded and belong to the &quot;cultural capital&quot; (Bourdieu [1972] 2000) <lb/>and who teach table manners, Class 5 is over-represented among the parents of a modest <lb/>social position and with a low level of education and resources, who mainly mention the <lb/>playful and convivial aspect of this learning. This aspect, while it may reflect a bias of social <lb/>attractiveness, may also reveal educational strategies used by these parents to establish a <lb/>certain &quot;respectability&quot; in food education, as highlighted elsewhere (Le Pape and Plessz <lb/>2017) through the teaching of a legitimate rhythm, in this case the duration of the meal as <lb/>we observe in these two parents. <lb/>&quot;We don&apos;t let them play with food much, the only time is with the letters that are in the <lb/>soup but otherwise, no, not at all&quot;. [Father, middle-class social position, one boy 48 <lb/>months old, two girls 5 and 10 years old]. <lb/>&quot;Well, for her age, she knows how to behave, she is not messy, she eats well with her <lb/>spoon. Then I&apos;m probably too manic but it&apos;s something I can&apos;t stand. She doesn&apos;t play <lb/>with the food, she doesn&apos;t spit with it, and when it&apos;s too dirty I tell her &quot;wait, settle down <lb/>and only then we&apos;ll eat more&quot;. But she eats well, she is clean, sometimes she will play <lb/>with the ham, but I tell her &quot;it&apos;s not very nice, we don&apos;t play with the food&quot;, she is quite <lb/>clean and delicate, she doesn&apos;t run around too much&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social <lb/>position, 30-month-old daughter]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>13 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>3.3. Perceptions of Hunger and Satiety: Social Dynamics of Adjustment <lb/>The content analysis, focused on practices and based on interviews and photos, <lb/>highlights three complex determinants involved in the perception of hunger and satiety as <lb/>well as their links to educational norms and models: the dynamics of the child&apos;s growth <lb/>linked to the evolution of physiological, social and emotional needs; the dynamics of <lb/>hunger and satiety associated with pleasure and the management of desire; and finally, <lb/>the dynamics of daily preparation practices and routines that question the evolutions in <lb/>textures and portions. <lb/>3.3.1. Growth Adjustment Dynamics <lb/>As children grow in size and age, their physical and physiological characteristics <lb/>change. Adults-both parents and professionals-adjust their diets to these characteristics. <lb/>These dynamics can be seen in the lexical analysis of parental discourse. The com-<lb/>parison of the two corpora spread over time shows changes between the first and second <lb/>interviews, as a result of changes perceived by the parents in the child&apos;s sensorimotor and <lb/>psychomotor development; the perception of these changes leads to responses regarding <lb/>feeding. <lb/>When comparing the discourse during the first interview (Figure 3) with that of the <lb/>second (Figure 4 and Table A3, Appendix D), the classes relating to the foods consumed <lb/>(Class 1 &quot;relationship to the salty food repertoire&quot; [16.5%], and Class 3 &quot;relationship to <lb/>the sweet food repertoire&quot; = [n = 29, 3%]) contrast more visibly with Class 4 &quot;temporal <lb/>framework of food socialization&quot; (15.35%) and Class 2 , a new class that illustrates the <lb/>greater attention paid to the child in terms of &quot;perceived evolutions in child development&quot; <lb/>(38.9%) with words such as child, month, curve, weight, girl. These results show changes <lb/>in the parents&apos; discourse classes between the two interviews and reveal a focus on child <lb/>development. However, although perceptions relating to this dimension emerge in the <lb/>discourses, they seem to be less associated with responses to the signs of hunger and <lb/>satiation expressed by the child than with internalized normative patterns. The class <lb/>&quot;perceived changes in the child&apos;s development&quot; appears in the second interview precisely <lb/>because a period of time occurred between the two interviews, letting changes take place <lb/>in the child&apos;s diet and expressed needs, and also letting the parents learn to identify them. <lb/>Therefore, the occurrence of this class results from the methodological protocol as well as <lb/>from the questions and reminders proposed by the interviewer. It seems that these feeding <lb/>practices are less the product of an adjustment to changes and signals perceived in the child <lb/>than the result of a distinct temporal order and the mobilization of top-down educational <lb/>models, which are themselves rooted in feeding models. Furthermore, the discourses that <lb/>propose listening to the child&apos;s rhythms and needs, and trusting the child&apos;s ability to express <lb/>them, correspond more to a rationalization in front of the investigator than to spontaneous <lb/>educational views. Finally, the fact that no marked social differentiation is visible for <lb/>this class indicates that this educational model is present in all social backgrounds with <lb/>a p &lt; 0.0001, even if the chi2 for the high social position is a little stronger (50.66) against <lb/>40.23 for the more modest social positions. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>14 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Dendrogram-first interview-parents. <lb/>Figure 4. Dendrogram-second interview-parents. <lb/>The staturo-ponderal growth is an indicator that adults rely on in order to adapt the <lb/>amount of food served, as expressed in Class 1 (see Section 3.2) and Class 2′. Parents also <lb/>rely on the evolution of their child&apos;s weight-height curves, which is recorded during med-<lb/>ical consultations, or they refer to age-related food guidelines. This staturo-ponderal <lb/>growth is assessed subjectively in comparison to the staturo-ponderal growth running in <lb/>the family, particularly that of the parents and siblings, but this assessment is also based <lb/>on a wider family circle. As a result, comparisons start linking the family&apos;s growth expe-<lb/>Figure 3. Dendrogram-first interview-parents. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>Figure 3. Dendrogram-first interview-parents. <lb/>Figure 4. Dendrogram-second interview-parents. <lb/>The staturo-ponderal growth is an indicator that adults rely on in order to adapt the <lb/>amount of food served, as expressed in Class 1 (see Section 3.2) and Class 2′. Parents also <lb/>rely on the evolution of their child&apos;s weight-height curves, which is recorded during med-<lb/>ical consultations, or they refer to age-related food guidelines. This staturo-ponderal <lb/>growth is assessed subjectively in comparison to the staturo-ponderal growth running in <lb/>the family, particularly that of the parents and siblings, but this assessment is also based <lb/>on a wider family circle. As a result, comparisons start linking the family&apos;s growth expe-<lb/>Figure 4. Dendrogram-second interview-parents. <lb/>The staturo-ponderal growth is an indicator that adults rely on in order to adapt the <lb/>amount of food served, as expressed in Class 1 (see Section 3.2) and Class 2 . Parents <lb/>also rely on the evolution of their child&apos;s weight-height curves, which is recorded during <lb/>medical consultations, or they refer to age-related food guidelines. This staturo-ponderal <lb/>growth is assessed subjectively in comparison to the staturo-ponderal growth running in <lb/>the family, particularly that of the parents and siblings, but this assessment is also based on <lb/>a wider family circle. As a result, comparisons start linking the family&apos;s growth experiences <lb/>and the evolution of the child&apos;s body. They also correspond to socially differentiated <lb/>somatic cultures. These elements are likely to determine both what is given and how much <lb/>is given to the child (Nicklaus et al. 2019). Some studies have also shown the impact of <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>15 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>the mother&apos;s weight experience on the restrictions placed on children, particularly girls <lb/>(Birch and Fisher 2000; Birch et al. 2003; Bournez et al. 2018; Hetherington 2017). This is <lb/>this situation we encounter with this mother: <lb/>&quot;I would go to the doctor and follow the advice because in fact as a child I was fat and it <lb/>used to be annoying. It wasn&apos;t a disease but it was just a little bit like it . . . it annoyed <lb/>me because it was harder to make friends, they said I looked like a meatball so it was more <lb/>like that. But it wasn&apos;t about my health, it was just annoying&quot;. [Mother, downgraded <lb/>social position, 36-month-old boy, 6-year-old girl] <lb/>However, if the evolving growth of the child is rooted in family standards, its transfor-<lb/>mations are an object of a social gaze, whether approving or disapproving, that defines <lb/>and shapes it to a large extent, just as do the practices of early childhood professionals <lb/>described by Delphine Serre (1998). When documented in the child&apos;s health booklet, the <lb/>evolution of the child&apos;s weight and height curves allows parents to evaluate their child&apos;s <lb/>development in comparison to a staturo-ponderal normality set by medical institutions. <lb/>The parents then look at their child&apos;s changing body and whether or not it falls within the <lb/>curves of &quot;normal&quot; development. The child&apos;s biological body is a social body (Diasio and <lb/>Vinel 2017). In our societies, the changing body of the child is considerably medicalized <lb/>and is the object of monitoring devices, especially during the first days and months of life. <lb/>André Turmel (2008) has shown how physical and psychological measurements, thought of <lb/>in terms of maturation, set developmental standards that help to socially organize growth, <lb/>aging and body transformation. In this way, this process of normalization also contributes <lb/>to establishing a normality and an abnormality of growing up, particularly expressed in <lb/>our qualitative study in relation to children considered too thin. <lb/>As has been shown (Turmel 2008; Diasio and Vinel 2017), the child&apos;s age is also <lb/>a relevant and legitimate criterion to enable the evolution of the dietary repertoire (in <lb/>terms of content, texture, and quantity) to be assessed according to the child&apos;s needs. The <lb/>biological age, on which the recommendations are based, acts as an identification marker. <lb/>Expressed in months, the schedule of food diversification distributed in many child care <lb/>media contributes to naturalizing the biological age of the child by making it the objective <lb/>and objectifiable variable (in the sense that it is measurable) to base the evolution of the <lb/>food repertoire. This repertoire also depends on social and institutional definitions of <lb/>childhood; those definitions are linked to specific institutions that mark the various ages of <lb/>life. For instance, the start of schooling, which in France occurs around the age of three, <lb/>helps to socialize children into integrating food models and table manners through bodily <lb/>dispositions that prepare them to be hungry when it is time to eat, and to feel satiated at <lb/>the end of a meal. These perceptions may be objectified by the medical profession on the <lb/>basis of growth curves, or they may remain attached to family memories. They can also be <lb/>shaped by professional practices or by both institutions and the norms they disseminate <lb/>concerning the child&apos;s social body. They affect the food and the quantity of food that <lb/>parents offer their children. They also influence the ways in which food is accessed and <lb/>controlled, especially for children in the lower and upper curves of our corpus. <lb/>However, the child&apos;s advancement in age and the physiological changes that come <lb/>with it, even if they remain a relevant category, are not without socially differentiated <lb/>interpretations. We have thus shown that the professional experience and social position of <lb/>home-based childminders set up a distance from child care norms, particularly concerning <lb/>the diversification stages perceived as dietary fads by the most senior professionals in the <lb/>field (Dupuy et al. 2018b). This distancing may affect parenting practices by changing <lb/>them. In another study, the polysemy associated with the notion of &quot;specificity&quot; of child <lb/>feeding was questioned by showing that, among parents, specific feeding for their child <lb/>does not only concern the foods or ingredients offered but also the textures, the quantity, <lb/>the quality, and finally the material, temporal, emotional, and social contexts-places, <lb/>times, duration, and interactions associated with food intake (Dupuy and Rochedy 2018; <lb/>Dupuy et al. 2018a; Wiggins 2019). Furthermore, biological age can be socially reappropri-<lb/>ated, but this reappropriation always occurs within a time window defined in medical <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>16 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>recommendations for initiating diversification (Bournez et al. 2018; Dhuot 2018) like what <lb/>is expressed here. <lb/>&quot;[Interviewer: But on the progression of the quantities?] As we went along, we <lb/>added little spoonfuls; in the evening we would obviously add less than at lunchtime. <lb/>For example, when he was still eating a mixed diet, I tried to give him a little less than <lb/>at lunchtime, because at lunchtime he was obviously hungrier. [Interviewer: And in <lb/>the evening?] I would take a little bit off, but in the evening, he would ask for less. <lb/>[Interviewer: Did you do this because you realized that he was eating less in the <lb/>evening or was it by anticipation?] Because we were told to eat a little lighter in the <lb/>evening. [Interviewer: Is it your pediatrician?] Yeah, I think it says that, on the back <lb/>of the sheet&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, 21-month-old boy]. <lb/>The implicit developmental logic that underlies this process, which prevails in our <lb/>societies, and the norms that are associated with it, particularly through medical institutions, <lb/>confirm the logic of physiological development (in particular the maturation of the digestive <lb/>tract) and psychomotor development in feeding the young child. This double implicit effect <lb/>also modifies the food repertoire and notably the quantities served so as to transform the <lb/>physical and physiological characteristics of the child. In this case, it is the child&apos;s &quot;healthy <lb/>growth&quot; that is targeted, which implies differences in perception according to social origin, <lb/>experience or even the family&apos;s staturo-ponderal experience. Certain foods, such as dairy <lb/>products, are served in greater quantities to encourage growth, although sometimes drifts <lb/>such as the lipophobia identified in certain social environments, has the effect of reducing <lb/>children&apos;s access to fats (Bournez et al. 2019). Those drifts are sometimes reflected in our <lb/>corpus. Moreover, what looks like an approach aimed at a child&apos;s &quot;healthy growth&quot; is <lb/>also accompanied by the idea that successful growth is a guarantee of a child&apos;s progress <lb/>through developmental stages. This link between growth and psychomotor progression <lb/>results in some parents, especially mothers who are concerned about dietary standards, <lb/>seeking to optimize the food repertoire and the quantities of food available. Vegetables, <lb/>dairy products, fruits, oils and fish are labelled as &quot;superfoods&quot;, especially when they are <lb/>organic and cooked from raw at home, as with this interviewee. <lb/>&quot;I always followed the doctor&apos;s recommendations to the letter. As it was the first one, I <lb/>acted as a really anxious mother: it really mattered that there was a spoonful of oil! In <lb/>the mashed potatoes! If I forgot it, I made him drink it! No no, it was really important, <lb/>everything had to be there. And then I introduced a lot of vegetables very quickly, he <lb/>always ate everything, he always finished his plates, he was a good baby, a big baby&quot;. <lb/>[Mother, downgraded, two boys, 18 months and 4 years old]. <lb/>The growing child&apos;s body is subject to family, extra-family, or institutional assessment <lb/>and monitoring that affect the amounts of food being served and allowed. <lb/>3.3.2. Deciphering Pleasure and the Dynamics of Satiation Adjustment <lb/>The perceptions of hunger and satiation are also determined by the dynamics of <lb/>satiation and pleasure perceived by the caregivers. Mention of the sick child is strong in <lb/>this category, as the illness always illustrates the lack of appetite for food and the return <lb/>of pleasure, and the recovery from illness. In this case, there is a greater tolerance for the <lb/>quantities that are eaten, as well as for the type of food and the way in which it is eaten <lb/>like here: <lb/>&quot;And in the evening, after he had a long day . . . I never bother, I offer him something <lb/>to eat, he doesn&apos;t want it, I give him his bottle of milk and he goes to bed.&quot; [Mother, <lb/>middle-class position, two boys aged 36 months and 6 years]. <lb/>The most relevant context in which this dynamic appears is the way in which both <lb/>adults and children deal with the tension between pleasure/satiation on the one hand and <lb/>social norms and rules on the other. The management of sweet products is emblematic of <lb/>this tension as here: <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>17 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>&quot;It&apos;s not a problem. And then if he doesn&apos;t want to finish his plate, he doesn&apos;t finish his <lb/>plate, it&apos;s not an issue. There are little rules that we apply, that is, there is no dessert if <lb/>there is no proper meal&quot;. [Father, high social position, daughter 7 months and son <lb/>4 years]. <lb/>&quot;But if he ate three carrots and then wants an ice cream, that&apos;s not gonna work (chuckles), <lb/>but if he had three bowls of soup and then wants an ice cream, yeah . . . Not like the <lb/>American way, I mean eat whenever you want, but it&apos;s ok to eat as much as you want <lb/>in the time dedicated to meals&quot;. [Mother, middle-class position], two boys aged <lb/>36 months and 6 years old]. <lb/>Eating rhythms set physical dispositions in children by transmuting hunger into <lb/>appetite (Bourdieu [1972] 2000). The social organization of food intake also provides a <lb/>reference point for children and the adults who feed them. The following extracts show <lb/>this learning of parents. <lb/>&quot;I can tell the difference, because we got him used to eating at a certain time. So I <lb/>could see when he wanted to eat and was hungry&quot;. [Mother, low social position, <lb/>23-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;But then they are so set in their ways, the bottle is at such time, the meal at such time, <lb/>that you are used to it, you know your children and you don&apos;t think about it. If he cries, <lb/>it&apos;s because he&apos;s hungry, if you arrive at 11:30 AM and there are cries, it&apos;s because he&apos;s <lb/>tired and hungry, because then it&apos;s time for a nap. And if it&apos;s not that, it is often because <lb/>they are sick. It&apos;s pretty easy to feel these things&quot;. [Mother, middle-class position, two <lb/>boys aged 36 months and 6 years]. <lb/>Within a feeding sequence, especially when the child is not yet speaking, how do <lb/>parents know when the child is no longer hungry? There is a large body of work that <lb/>identifies verbal and non-verbal mimics and their interpretations to help understand the <lb/>mechanisms governing appetite and satiation in children (Skinner et al. 1998; Gross et al. <lb/>2010; Hodges et al. 2013; Hetherington 2017; McNally et al. 2016; McNally et al. 2020). <lb/>The following extracts from interviews show parents&apos; difficulties in interpreting signs <lb/>of hunger: <lb/>&quot;If he wants more, he knows how to say &apos;more&apos;, so he says &apos;more&apos; and even before he spoke, <lb/>I had taught him the &apos;more&apos; sign. [ . . . ] There&apos;s baby sign language. It&apos;s like this [she <lb/>gestures]&quot;. [Mother, high social position, boys 29 months and 4 years old]. <lb/>&quot;We saw that she saw us eating and we can see by her eyes, even though she&apos;s small, but <lb/>we can see that . . . she looks at the spoon and she goes . . . [She imitates her daughter <lb/>who follows the path of the spoon from the plate to her mouth with her eyes]. <lb/>And if we sit her on our lap it&apos;s so cute because she sees the plate and she does the same <lb/>thing [again she imitates the child following the path of the fork with her eyes]. <lb/>So her eyes kind of say how scandalous . . . &quot; [Mother, middle-class social position, <lb/>11-month-old daughter]. <lb/>&quot;She&apos;s much more awake when she&apos;s hungry I think. She&apos;s more awake, more commu-<lb/>nicating than when she has something that&apos;s bothering her or she&apos;s a little bit sick . . . <lb/>I rock her for five minutes and if after that she doesn&apos;t go back to sleep, I just make one <lb/>[a bottle] for her. Then maybe it&apos;s an easy solution and the bottle knocks her out. But, <lb/>uh . . . &quot; [Father, high social position, daughter 7 months and son 4 years]. <lb/>&quot;It was clear, &apos;I don&apos;t want it&apos;, she would close her mouth or turn away, well it was clear. <lb/>When she finishes everything, I tend to think I could have added more, anyway now she <lb/>just says &quot;more&quot;. And before, when she was smaller, I don&apos;t think she ever really finished <lb/>her jars, but I would always do a little more than I had to, but actually she would stop. <lb/>And she would usually stop by herself. And I never forced her to finish. As anxious as I <lb/>am that she eats well, but . . . And I would tell the nanny, not to force her. In fact, I was <lb/>in between, I mean to stimulate but not to force!&quot; [Mother, high social position, one <lb/>31-month-old daughter]. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>18 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>Other issues are involved in the strategies parents and children put in place to manage <lb/>this tension. Literature on the reward status of food, especially sugary food (Chiva 1979; <lb/>Birch 1987; Cooke et al. 2011), is extensive as is the role of playful eating (Corbeau 2008). <lb/>Other elements were observed here: serving vegetables before meat thus making more use <lb/>of hunger mechanisms; acting on the temporalities of meals, particularly on their duration; <lb/>reversing the structure of meals by starting with a fruit or dairy product and continuing <lb/>with a protein dish; not serving water at the table. These illustrations show a distance from <lb/>social, nutritional and educational norms as here. <lb/>&quot;But here&apos;s the thing, the dessert is his goal I think. Because the nanny&apos;s got this weird <lb/>way of doing things: she puts a tray in front of each of them and puts everything on <lb/>it. So she puts the starter, the main course, the cut fruit, the cheese. So actually they <lb/>eat in the order they want. [ . . . ] But actually, at home I&apos;m not in favor of it because <lb/>I think that at school they won&apos;t get . . . Well, for me, the meal goes from the starter to <lb/>the main course and dessert. It&apos;s true that at home I had a bit of trouble getting him to <lb/>understand that he had to wait until he had finished the main course to have dessert&quot;. <lb/>[Mother, middle-class social position, economic capital, 30-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;Yes, but he doesn&apos;t mind going back to salty after sweet. Yeah, the salty-sweet order, <lb/>we&apos;re the ones who decided on this salty-sweet order but they don&apos;t care&quot;. [Mother, <lb/>middle-class social position, economic capital, 30-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;When he comes home it is like &quot;give me food, give me food!&quot; so we often start with the <lb/>dessert and by the time I finish he usually has an apple, a banana or a yogurt, then he <lb/>eats the main course . . . for me it doesn&apos;t matter if he eats the other way around, it&apos;s not <lb/>a big deal&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, two boys aged 36 months and <lb/>6 years]. <lb/>Moreover, the child is not just a receptor; they quickly learn to decode the strategies of <lb/>their caregivers in order to adopt to them, just as they learn the social norms relating to <lb/>ending meals with a dessert (Tibère and Dupuy 2021). For example, children who learn to <lb/>save themselves for dessert in anticipation of sensory promises will tend to eat a smaller <lb/>quantity of their protein dish. More common is the situation of going beyond one&apos;s hunger <lb/>to please a caregiver who is being pushy and has forcing behaviors when it comes to food <lb/>(Birch et al. 1980; Odgen et al. 2006; Gross et al. 2010). The following interview passage is <lb/>very illustrative of a rigid control of the feeding behavior of the child: <lb/>&quot;He drove me crazy on that dish. Because I wanted to do what I had been told: &quot;you will <lb/>not get any other food until you finish this&quot;. At 18 months old it&apos;s a bit hard, but at the <lb/>same time this child drives me so crazy that I told him &quot;ah okay, fine, you leave the table&quot;. <lb/>And so I let him cry a little bit, he was crying because he wanted his caramel yogurt and <lb/>there is no caramel yogurt if he doesn&apos;t eat that. Besides, if he had eaten it, he would have <lb/>had plain yogurt. Yes, because there is a correlation: if he eats well, he gets a good yogurt, <lb/>but there is no good yogurt if he does this. [Interviewer: It&apos;s pleasure yogurt only IF <lb/>. . . ] We don&apos;t like saying &quot;good&quot; yogurt, but hey, we&apos;re really into blackmail. Well it <lb/>works well! He actually ate it a little bit, in the end. So I put him back and I told him <lb/>curtly: &quot;you want the yogurt, well you eat this!&quot;; we had to try again several times by <lb/>showing him. &quot;If you want the yogurt, you eat this. He was crying and eventually he <lb/>took the scoops. He took four. So we told him &quot;thank you, that&apos;s a good job&quot; and then we <lb/>gave him his yogurt&quot;. [Mother, downgraded social position, two boys 18 months <lb/>and 4 1 <lb/>2 years old]. <lb/>The modalities of access to pleasure probably depend on the child&apos;s sex (Bournez <lb/>et al. 2018), with gender norms participating silently to socialization and contributing to a <lb/>stricter control of girls&apos; eating practices, especially in the middle and upper social classes <lb/>(Nicaise et al. 2019). This also occurs with older children (Dupuy 2013) as here: <lb/>&quot;Lina I would say that she is more . . . well I find that she has her daddy&apos;s tastes, she likes <lb/>sausage, cold cuts, cheese . . . I&apos;m not so much into cheese but Lina, she loves cheese. So I <lb/>feel like she has more of her daddy&apos;s tastes, but I also try to influence her. [ . . . ] [Talking <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>19 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>about her partner] He&apos;s a big guy! (laughs) To give you an idea, when I met him he <lb/>was 103 kg, and now he must be over 120 kg, I mean it&apos;s getting quite big. Well, he is <lb/>tall, he is 1.93m, but still. Like I say sometimes, as Lina has Victor&apos;s taste, we have to be <lb/>careful, so I do think about it. But to be honest, she has Victor&apos;s tastes, but I think that <lb/>education is also important, and she is starting to learn, and for example, she likes fruit a <lb/>lot, you see, for example, she often has fruit for dessert&quot;. [Mother, high social position, <lb/>4-year-old daughter and 11-month-old son]. <lb/>&quot;It&apos;s been 6 months now, he was going to the pantry. He&apos;s got a good idea of where that is. <lb/>[ . . . ] But we have to limit him. The other day, we went to the neighbors&apos; and I thought <lb/>that he was going to eat all the cakes and not leave any for anyone, so yes, you have to . . . <lb/>I told him, &apos;That&apos;s enough, leave some for the others,&apos; but he doesn&apos;t care, as long as you <lb/>don&apos;t put them out of reach, it&apos;s complicated . . . well, it can be complicated&quot;. [Mother, <lb/>high social position, 20-month-old boy]. <lb/>As a consequence of the child&apos;s staturological growth, and as we have pointed out, <lb/>parental management of the child&apos;s access to pleasure depends on the family&apos;s staturological <lb/>history: parents project their own experience or that of their partner to discuss how their <lb/>child relates to the pleasure of eating certain foods. In the same way, they sometimes project <lb/>their own suffering in relation to their belittled body. Even if this issue appears later in the <lb/>mechanisms of appetite and pleasure control in children (Dupuy 2013), what really matters <lb/>here is the child&apos;s weight trajectory and its perception by the parents, as is expressed here: <lb/>&quot;It is said that apparently children&apos;s weight determines adult weight. Say, if a child is very, <lb/>very chubby as a child, there is a good chance that he will grow up to be so. Besides, we <lb/>are the type of people who cannot eat anything without getting fat. Therefore, you have to <lb/>be a little careful about what you eat, and I think that he will have this predisposition too&quot;. <lb/>[Mother, intermediate social position, economic capital, 30-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;No, nothing in the morning, just water, it calls out. I know we can&apos;t afford to give <lb/>him more, like I know he&apos;s at the top of the curve&quot;. [Mother, poor social position, <lb/>8-month-old boy]. <lb/>It is also possible to distinguish certain processes that the caregivers have observed <lb/>in the way the child learns to play with his hunger and satiety for his own pleasure or <lb/>that of his family. This means that adults are not the only decision makers in children&apos;s <lb/>eating practices, as children learn to decode and anticipate the reactions of their caregivers <lb/>by shaping their own eating habits. These aspects underline the role of the interactions <lb/>that take place from the earliest age between infants and the adults who feed them, thus <lb/>contributing to the construction not only of food repertoire but also, in part, of personalities <lb/>and individual and social identities (Chiva 1979). This is tempered by the adoption of <lb/>an adult-or child-centered stance on needs and their expression, which in turn is often <lb/>dependent on a number of determinants and normative processes about the role to be <lb/>granted to children in their socialization. In this sense and to keep things simple, it is more <lb/>accurate to speak of ideal-typical views. <lb/>In the first view, the adult considers himself competent to understand the needs <lb/>expressed by the child. The adult&apos;s intervention responds to the child&apos;s expressed needs <lb/>within the framework set by the adult alone. In this mode of interaction, the adult may <lb/>encourage the child to eat more, deny access to more food, or put food out of reach or out <lb/>of sight. This mother expresses the difficulties and the anguish of feeding a child who does <lb/>not eat which explains the incentives to eat: <lb/>&quot;That&apos;s the problem, Agathe never asks for food, never makes you feel the urge to eat, so <lb/>. . . [ . . . ] Yes, but then as she loses focus very quickly, we often put her at the table with <lb/>us, so she starts to eat and then she starts to lose interest or to look to the right or to the <lb/>left, and often we help her so she can eat a little more fully otherwise it will pass, she&apos;ll <lb/>forget and then she&apos;ll be grumpy. So she&apos;ll never say she&apos;s hungry, if we ask her she&apos;ll <lb/>say &apos;no&apos; but in fact she is, so we help her&quot;. [Mother, downgraded social position, <lb/>18-month-old daughter] <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>20 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>In the second view, the adult intervenes only to respond to the needs expressed by <lb/>the child, who is considered to be competent to correctly express his or her hunger or <lb/>satiety. The adult responds to the child&apos;s requests but does not insist, refuse or encourage <lb/>them. This analysis thus extends reflections on feeding styles (Hughes et al. 2016) as well <lb/>as reflections on feeding temperaments in children (Farrow and Blissett 2006). Recent <lb/>experimental work shows that at 11 months of age, if the pace of spooning is slower <lb/>when spoonfuls are large (reflecting more responsive feeding), infants have better energy <lb/>adjustment abilities. In other words, they are better able to cut back on the amounts they <lb/>eat at mealtime after eating a high-energy first food (Brugaillères et al. 2019). <lb/>Furthermore, these adult-or child-centered views are linked to normative and imagi-<lb/>nary productions that people have about childhood, i.e., the competent child, the respon-<lb/>sible child, the victimized or vulnerable child (Hamelin Brabant and Turmel 2012), all <lb/>of which are deployed differently depending on social environments. Eventually, these <lb/>dimensions may evolve as children advance in age and in autonomy as what is expressed <lb/>by these parents. <lb/>&quot;But for example, when it is 6 o&apos;clock in the morning, she is not going to say &quot;I&apos;m <lb/>hungry&quot;? Ah no, she has no idea&quot;. [Mother, low social position, 17-month-old <lb/>daughter]. <lb/>&quot;In terms of quantities, he manages himself, and so we don&apos;t have to give him anything, <lb/>so it&apos;s nice, we&apos;re focused on our plate, well we check where he is, etc., but we don&apos;t have <lb/>to hand him the fork, the spoon, etc. Each one manages his own plate&quot;. [Mother, low <lb/>social position, 32-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;Yes, she says it, but hunger I think is the thing she knows how to express the least [ . . . ] <lb/>She never says &quot;I&apos;m hungry&quot;, she says &quot;ham&quot;, I think hunger is the thing she expresses <lb/>the least&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, 30-month-old girl]. <lb/>&quot;I know that he is aware of his needs, his hunger and everything. Last night he said &quot;well <lb/>I didn&apos;t eat much daddy, I&apos;m hungry&quot; so he took another slice of pizza. So, he knows <lb/>when he is hungry, how to deal with it, and he expresses it well. So it&apos;s pretty easy in <lb/>that respect&quot;. [Mother, low social position, 32-month-old boy]. <lb/>&quot;Because the pediatrician probably told me that it was at that age that it had to be done. <lb/>Because at some point they sit up, they grow up and eating is good, integrating food <lb/>as they go along, developing taste, I figure it&apos;s extraordinary rather than drinking milk <lb/>forever, . . . and then for them, this discovery, the face they make when there is this or that <lb/>taste in their mouth, the look they make when they refuse such food because for them it is <lb/>unthinkable to eat that . . . Well, anyway, it also shows that they are human beings in <lb/>their own right and that they develop their own tastes. So there you go, I really followed <lb/>it up, as closely as possible&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, two boys aged <lb/>36 months and 6 years]. <lb/>For this same view, the lexical analysis indicates a parental discourse that values the <lb/>&quot;natural&quot; rhythms of children and their ability to express their needs. Perceptions are then <lb/>based on trust in the signals given and, depending on the social environment, on the image <lb/>of the &quot;healthy&quot; child or on listening to what &quot;the stomach can handle&quot;. <lb/>&quot;When they request food, I give them food and when they don&apos;t need to eat, I just don&apos;t <lb/>insist. [ . . . ] You trust them. We have children who are very healthy when it comes to <lb/>food, so we&apos;re lucky. It&apos;s an opportunity to trust them&quot;. [Father, high social position, <lb/>daughter 7 months and son 4 years, p &lt; 0.0001]. <lb/>&quot;He says &quot;Mommy, I want an ice cream&quot;, so he chooses an ice cream he likes, he doesn&apos;t <lb/>finish it, so I tell him &quot;well Victor, you chose an ice cream that you didn&apos;t finish . . . &quot; <lb/>but I don&apos;t see the point of forcing a child to finish something, I figure that naturally <lb/>he&apos;s not hungry anymore. I don&apos;t know . . . he ate a piece of his ice cream, he ate 3 <lb/>4 of it, <lb/>I think it was a little big for him, I don&apos;t want to be a food Hitler. So I think to myself <lb/>&quot;it is not just a whim to want food, but at some point I think that he is 3 years old, that <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>21 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>he has a stomach that can handle so much . . . &quot; because when it comes to my children, <lb/>I often work as though it were happening to me: I want dessert, but I am not hungry <lb/>anymore, I am not gonna gorge myself on dessert just to finish my plate. So no . . . when <lb/>I see friends doing that, it hurts my heart so much that it&apos;s unthinkable, if you&apos;ve opened <lb/>a bottle of wine, I&apos;m not gonna force you to finish the whole bottle. No but it doesn&apos;t <lb/>apply to everything. He wanted dessert and then he didn&apos;t want it anymore, so that <lb/>means he&apos;s had enough to eat&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, two boys aged <lb/>36 months and 6 years]. <lb/>3.3.3. The Dynamics of Daily Food Routines <lb/>The practices of daily meal preparation to feed a child consist of a sequence of opera-<lb/>tions, ranging from procurement to the management of leftover storage. These operations <lb/>are sequenced through routine practices (Gottlieb 2000; Dubuisson-Quellier 2006). The <lb/>coordination into action sequences of such practices constitutes a cognitive economy (Piette <lb/>2013) consisting of adopting mental shortcuts to purchase, produce, consume, and manage <lb/>leftovers (Poulain 2002, 2017). In previous research, we have shown that &quot;food work&quot; and <lb/>the associated routines are inserted into the constraints of families (Dupuy and Rochedy <lb/>2018) as well as those of professionals (Dupuy et al. 2018b). This has implications on the <lb/>food produced for children, in particular the presence of a certain monotony in terms of the <lb/>repertoire of foods given and textures offered (Dupuy et al. 2018a). No longer weighing, <lb/>no longer measuring out quantities, guessing meal portions or even serving them by the <lb/>&quot;ladle&quot; means that daily preparation practices have been routinized with the experience <lb/>acquired through the recurrence of situations as here. <lb/>&quot;I followed, I mean I figured out the quantities. For the ham, for example, I would give <lb/>half a slice. Yes, it did seem very, very precise, but for example I never used the weighing <lb/>scales, I used the eye but I think I would put less than more. Then, from the age of one, it&apos;s <lb/>easier because there&apos;s more quantity. Yes, since in 5 months the quantities are multiplied <lb/>by 5&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, 21-month-old boy]. <lb/>It has been shown that the least educated social classes have fixed practices while <lb/>families with a middle or high level of education have more varied practices (Southerton <lb/>2006; Diasio and Julien 2018). Discussing the dynamics of daily preparation practices <lb/>amounts to better accounting for the effect of contexts on &quot;food work&quot; routine practices <lb/>and their impact on quantity dosages and portion sizes served to children. Diversification <lb/>in very young children involves expanding the food repertoire in terms of content, quantity <lb/>and texture. During this process, which may vary according to the situation, location and <lb/>socialization context, periods of stabilization and transition can be distinguished, which, <lb/>as generated and motivated by parents, also affect their workload as food providers. This <lb/>mother explains the seasonal adaptations that she implements: <lb/>&quot;I try as much as possible, knowing that it&apos;s been a few weeks since I started to rebalance <lb/>my diet, because we are getting close to summer and so in the evening I tend to go for <lb/>raw salads rather than the heavy dishes. So in the end, pasta . . . well, we had some one <lb/>evening, two days ago, but other than that, I hadn&apos;t made pasta or rice or wheat for weeks. <lb/>I usually save that for lunch&quot;. [Mother, middle-class social position, economic <lb/>capital, 30-month-old boy]. <lb/>When stabilization reflects a habit-building effort, it reinforces routinization and has <lb/>a beneficial effect on parents, as it allows them to mentally relax into the &quot;food work.&quot; <lb/>However, the fact that less cognitive energy may be spent leads to nutritional errors such <lb/>as when the quantity is sufficient yet the caloric density of the preparation is not, much <lb/>like what this mother mentions on several occasions in the two interviews: <lb/>Interview 1: &quot;But I actually thought I was weighing, but actually I wasn&apos;t weighing, I <lb/>was looking at the dose. Because that evening when I put my puree on, I said to myself, <lb/>&apos;Damn, it&apos;s compact&apos;. Sometimes I add water before mixing, but in this case I didn&apos;t add <lb/>any, I thought there was enough. But then he must have taken maybe 300 g of puree, I&apos;m <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>22 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>not sure. [ . . . ] But in fact I hadn&apos;t measured it and I think there was more [ . . . ] But <lb/>actually it&apos;s a bit stupid, because actually you have to weigh it. Because it depends if your <lb/>puree is light . . . it&apos;s not the quantity that will count in fact it&apos;s the weight. And that&apos;s <lb/>where I fooled myself because my puree was very compact, and I think that this portion <lb/>weighed much more than an industrial jar, which in fact contains a lot of water and <lb/>everything&quot;. [Mother, high social position, a 12-month-old boy and a 4-year-old girl]. <lb/>Interview 2: &quot;And so I no longer measure. It used to do my head in, but not anymore. <lb/>I pretty much get the quantities now. Before, when he was little, I used to fill the jars <lb/>full, you know . . . Well, now it&apos;s pieces, it doesn&apos;t mean the same and now I can tell it&apos;s <lb/>a small bowl and if he doesn&apos;t finish, he doesn&apos;t finish, it&apos;s up to him&quot;. [Mother, high <lb/>social position, a 12-month-old boy and a 4-year-old girl]. <lb/>This was particularly observed in the choice of texture and in the number of ingredi-<lb/>ents comprising the meal, but it is also the case with the quantity served to the children. <lb/>Since &quot;food work&quot; is tied to temporal, material and organizational constraints, and since <lb/>it operates within a search for cognitive economy, dietary changes may be deferred, con-<lb/>sciously or unconsciously. Indeed, putting an end to a routine requires reflexivity and <lb/>renewed decision making, such as increasing the quantity served or the number of food <lb/>intakes, modifying and diversifying the number of ingredients and textures offered. Rou-<lb/>tinization ultimately reflects what works best, what has been successful and/or what the <lb/>child prefers, allowing the caregivers to feed without hindrance and with minimal effort. <lb/>Change, on the other hand, generates potential mental and physical burdens resulting in <lb/>fatigue, without necessarily guaranteeing success in terms of actual consumption. This <lb/>food management, a kind of daily micro-management, affects the quality as well as the <lb/>quantity offered to the children. <lb/>Even when parents are forced to innovate, as a result of changes in children&apos;s diets and <lb/>because they respond, to a greater or lesser extent, to dietary standards and injunctions, and <lb/>also as a result of the interactions, situations, and contexts in which socialization occurs, <lb/>the integration of the child into the family&apos;s dietary repertoire is then an opportunity <lb/>to ensure family socialization, while also alleviating the physical and mental burden on <lb/>the caregivers. Learnings are carried out in a social environment marked by parental <lb/>consumptions, which are themselves socially and culturally determined (Fielding-Singh <lb/>2017). This integration dimension becomes even more obvious when the child is not the <lb/>first born sibling. Parents report that for the second child, diversification and integration of <lb/>the child into the family food repertoire occurs more quickly (Yuan et al. 2016; Bournez et al. <lb/>2018, 2019; Dupuy et al. 2018a). Older siblings are models of integration that the child looks <lb/>to for socialization. The alleviation of physical and cognitive burdens that results from this <lb/>daily socialization, through serving the same ingredients as for the rest of the family, has an <lb/>impact on shopping, supplies, preparation, and budget, while food is specifically tailored <lb/>to meet needs that are more or less perceived and expressed in terms of tastes, nutritional <lb/>composition, quantities, and portion sizes. Sometimes the quantities are identical between <lb/>siblings (as, indeed, for groups of children cared for by home-based childminders in our <lb/>qualitative survey). <lb/>Moreover, as previously identified (Lalanne and Tibère 2008; Tibère et al. 2018), re-<lb/>ported routines-that is, what is presented by parents as usual practices-may be distinct <lb/>from what is observed and analyzed during the survey situation, i.e., the actual routines. <lb/>This research shows the importance of contextual changes, or contingencies, in terms <lb/>of the social, temporal or spatial environment of food intake. The impact of social con-<lb/>texts can also come into focus in understanding the role of derogations on what is given <lb/>and how much is given in connection with various educational tensions (Lalanne and <lb/>Tibère 2008; Dupuy 2013; Dupuy 2017b). These are not epiphenomena in the course of <lb/>socialization. Their recurrence affects the quantities offered and ultimately consumed. In <lb/>this sense, contextual derogations correspond to determinants of children&apos;s appetite and <lb/>satiety, and, more broadly, to the regulation of food intake in children, and reveal forms <lb/>of normative distancing in situ. The following excerpt is an exchange with a concerned <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>23 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>mother during the second interview, which comes along with the viewing of photos taken <lb/>of eating situations. It shows the momentary difficulties encountered by this mother with <lb/>her 18-month-old son, which repeatedly resulted in milk intake and a refusal to consume <lb/>anything other than a bottle. <lb/>&quot;So this one is a serious regression! He was always taking Babybio, except that it is <lb/>for 6 months old, he is 18 months old; we decided that we would evolve, we would buy <lb/>Blédichef, but Blédichef has pieces, so he doesn&apos;t eat them, he just turns his head. So we <lb/>ended up giving him a bottle. So from time to time, when we have some, we serve him <lb/>a Babybio, he takes it ok, but now for example at lunch he had a bottle. Because yeah, <lb/>I brought out the Babybio from last night that he didn&apos;t eat, and he didn&apos;t want it . . . <lb/>But since I&apos;m so tired, &quot;well, have a bottle&quot;. [The mother goes to change her son&apos;s <lb/>diaper] And the craziest thing is that Arnaud doesn&apos;t eat anything, but you wouldn&apos;t <lb/>believe how many poops a day he makes . . . But poops of what? Right now his poop is not <lb/>brown, but rather beige, like milk poop. I&apos;m 18 months old, I make milk poop&quot;. [Mother, <lb/>downgraded social position, a 18-month-old boy]. <lb/>Picture 6: Arnaud, 18 months: Dinner &quot;failure&quot;, after failed attempt of a jar, proposal <lb/>quiche/cucumber like the rest of the family, but without success. Did not eat anything, <lb/>bottle offered and ok. <lb/>can also come into focus in understanding the role of derogations on what is given and <lb/>how much is given in connection with various educational tensions (Lalanne and Tibère <lb/>2008; Dupuy 2013; Dupuy 2017b). These are not epiphenomena in the course of socializa-<lb/>tion. Their recurrence affects the quantities offered and ultimately consumed. In this <lb/>sense, contextual derogations correspond to determinants of children&apos;s appetite and sa-<lb/>tiety, and, more broadly, to the regulation of food intake in children, and reveal forms of <lb/>normative distancing in situ. The following excerpt is an exchange with a concerned <lb/>mother during the second interview, which comes along with the viewing of photos taken <lb/>of eating situations. It shows the momentary difficulties encountered by this mother with <lb/>her 18-month-old son, which repeatedly resulted in milk intake and a refusal to consume <lb/>anything other than a bottle. <lb/>&quot;So this one is a serious regression! He was always taking Babybio, except that it is for <lb/>6 months old, he is 18 months old; we decided that we would evolve, we would buy <lb/>Blédichef, but Blédichef has pieces, so he doesn&apos;t eat them, he just turns his head. So we <lb/>ended up giving him a bottle. So from time to time, when we have some, we serve him <lb/>a Babybio, he takes it ok, but now for example at lunch he had a bottle. Because yeah, I <lb/>brought out the Babybio from last night that he didn&apos;t eat, and he didn&apos;t want it... But <lb/>since I&apos;m so tired, &quot;well, have a bottle&quot;. [The mother goes to change her son&apos;s dia-<lb/>per] And the craziest thing is that Arnaud doesn&apos;t eat anything, but you wouldn&apos;t be-<lb/>lieve how many poops a day he makes... But poops of what? Right now his poop is not <lb/>brown, but rather beige, like milk poop. I&apos;m 18 months old, I make milk poop&quot;. [Mother, <lb/>downgraded social position, a 18-month-old boy] <lb/>Picture 6: Arnaud, 18 months: Dinner &quot;failure&quot;, after failed attempt of a jar, proposal <lb/>quiche/cucumber like the rest of the family, but without success. Did not eat anything, <lb/>bottle offered and ok. <lb/>Pictures 7 and 8: Arnaud, 18 months: Evening meal: Carrot puree, did not eat it. Tried <lb/>a chunk of cooked carrot without success. Ended up with a bottle of milk. <lb/>Pictures 7 and 8: Arnaud, 18 months: Evening meal: Carrot puree, did not eat it. Tried <lb/>a chunk of cooked carrot without success. Ended up with a bottle of milk. <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, x FOR PEER REVIEW <lb/></note>

			<page>25 of 38 <lb/></page>

			<body>4. Discussion <lb/>Although the interviews are partly regulated by the tools and protocols that support <lb/>them, they remain social improvisations insofar as the interviewers do not control the en-<lb/>tirety of the interactions and the content expressed, unlike quantitative protocols which <lb/>are based on closed questions. It is therefore interesting to note the extent to which the <lb/>child&apos;s appetite and satiation seem to be regulated by social, nutritional and educational <lb/>norms; these norms can be objectified by the statistical analysis produced here. These lex-<lb/>ical universes stem from social and normative contexts that play a significant role in the <lb/>socialization of children and greatly condition the type, amount and timing of food intake <lb/>by setting food repertoires, in particular the type and alternation of food intake (solid/liq-<lb/>uid) as well as the structure of meals (starter and/or main course and/or dessert, drinks <lb/>and snacks, etc.), food rhythms which include synchrony, social manners and forms of <lb/>consumption, in particular commensality. <lb/>4. Discussion <lb/>Although the interviews are partly regulated by the tools and protocols that support <lb/>them, they remain social improvisations insofar as the interviewers do not control the <lb/>entirety of the interactions and the content expressed, unlike quantitative protocols which <lb/>are based on closed questions. It is therefore interesting to note the extent to which the <lb/>child&apos;s appetite and satiation seem to be regulated by social, nutritional and educational <lb/>norms; these norms can be objectified by the statistical analysis produced here. These <lb/>lexical universes stem from social and normative contexts that play a significant role in <lb/>the socialization of children and greatly condition the type, amount and timing of food <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>24 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>intake by setting food repertoires, in particular the type and alternation of food intake <lb/>(solid/liquid) as well as the structure of meals (starter and/or main course and/or dessert, <lb/>drinks and snacks, etc.), food rhythms which include synchrony, social manners and forms <lb/>of consumption, in particular commensality. <lb/>Among parents, mostly mothers, the results confirm the importance of nutritional and <lb/>child care norms, but also the status of food models in their social dimensions, including, <lb/>in particular, an ambivalent relationship to sweet foods, the importance of salty foods <lb/>at meals, the learning of food rhythms, and the rules of commensality on which parents <lb/>rely to determine appetite and satiation. The proportions associated with these classes <lb/>reflect their importance in the whole corpus, allowing them to be ranked in a hierarchy. <lb/>Class 5, which relates to the social frameworks of commensality, i.e., the learning of table <lb/>manners and conviviality, is the most represented, followed by Class 1, which relates <lb/>to the relationship with medical norms, insofar as infant nutrition is strongly regulated <lb/>by medical, early childhood and family authorities. In France, the social norms that are <lb/>expressed in terms of table manners and the medical norms regarding infant nutrition <lb/>are the most socially marked determinants; they are found to be more or less articulated <lb/>according to the parents. Additionally, the significant interest of parents from wealthy <lb/>social backgrounds for medical norms is established as has been identified elsewhere <lb/>(Gojard 2000; Régnier and Masullo 2009; Dhuot 2018). <lb/>These elements concur in considering the importance of social and medical norms in <lb/>the perceptions of adults concerning these two aspects, and invite us to identify how these <lb/>norms are incorporated by young children, transforming their hunger into appetite, and <lb/>their satiety into satiation. There are three dynamics that characterize the way in which the <lb/>social system takes charge of certain perceived signals: the one that is focused on the child&apos;s <lb/>growth and the evolution of his physiological, social and emotional needs; the one that <lb/>is focused on the signals associated with satiation, in line with food pleasure and desire; <lb/>and finally, the one related to practical and daily preparation practices, where routines are <lb/>established, particularly in the management of textures and portions, thus establishing <lb/>normative compliance with or distancing from the norms in situ. <lb/>At first glance, these results seem to reflect a top-down education-from adults to <lb/>children-regarding socialization and, in particular, hunger and satiety. Beyond physi-<lb/>ological sensations, the issue of social integration of children is prevailing, with a focus <lb/>on preschool admission and school meal attendance and also a gendered relationship to <lb/>food. This reveals how hunger and satiation are, respectively, transmitted into appetite <lb/>and satiation through the inculcation of normative frameworks and the more or less strong <lb/>respect of educational principles. Social frameworks and normative goals are combined in <lb/>the recommendations of the French public authorities, such as the examples of menus that <lb/>are adapted according to the age of the child in the guide &quot;L&apos;alimentation pendant la petite <lb/>enfance (de la naissance à 3 ans)&quot; of the Programme National Nutrition Santé, available <lb/>at the time of the qualitative survey on the website Manger.bouger.fr. This guide sets out <lb/>the structure of a day and food intake. This jumble of normative registers can be traced, <lb/>to a greater or lesser extent, in the parents&apos; speeches revealed by this investigation. It <lb/>changes according to the parents&apos; social background, forming a relationship of attachment, <lb/>distancing or even rejection to food and nutritional norms, as has been shown in other <lb/>studies (Gojard 2000; Régnier and Masullo 2009; Dhuot 2018). It also changes according to <lb/>experience, like the differences that can be found in families with one or more children, <lb/>or the distinctions between parents and professionals in the modalities of educational <lb/>delegation (Dupuy et al. 2018b). This aspect echoes a salient finding from Séverine Gojard&apos;s <lb/>survey relating to the level of experience caring for young children and autonomy in <lb/>relation to prescriptions (Gojard 2010). However, what varies less is this relationship to <lb/>the normative content on which parents rely to express themselves, both because parental <lb/>practices, especially maternal ones, are framed by a &quot;moral magisterium&quot; (Garcia 2011) <lb/>that is prevalent with the rise of child obesity and associated pathologies, but also because <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>25 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>these norms correspond to models of conduct that are widely followed in society or in <lb/>certain social groups and that are considered appropriate (Poulain 2002, 2017). <lb/>As scientific findings evolve, dietary and educational standards on feeding fluctuate <lb/>to describe what constitutes &quot;good&quot; behavior to maintain young children in a state of good <lb/>health and well-being. The norm of &quot;responsive feeding&quot;, which is more inclined to a less <lb/>vertical relationship between adults and children, by making the caregivers more aware <lb/>of the child&apos;s needs, is giving rise to new recommendations and prescriptions. These are <lb/>disseminated by the medical community, public authorities and their agents. The effect can <lb/>be to question the importance of the vertical relationship or even to accompany it with new <lb/>recommendations, which are meant to correct it. However, this often happens without any <lb/>regard for the importance of the contexts in which the norms that parents rely on to varying <lb/>degrees of intensity are produced, and their sociohistorical anchorage. The discrepancy <lb/>between medical prescriptions and daily socialization should not result in addressing, from <lb/>the angle of lack of parental and often maternal nutritional skills, situations that public <lb/>policies have trouble grasping in their complexity and plurality as well as in their social, <lb/>cultural and historical depth. <lb/>5. Limitations of This Study <lb/>The dynamics at work in children&apos;s eating were not systematically and directly ob-<lb/>served in the research protocol. However, their observation would probably allow re-<lb/>searchers to prioritize these determinants according to the child&apos;s gender, biological and <lb/>social age, lifestyle and associated constraints. <lb/>However, the iterative method used and supported by the use of photo elicitation <lb/>reduces the effect of declarative and social desirability by revealing discrepancies and <lb/>deviations between norms and practices, on the one hand, and declared routines and actual <lb/>routines, on the other, as illustrated by the following situation: <lb/>&quot;Now it&apos;s true that, compared to what we said last time, I think I actually tend to give <lb/>him a lot of food in terms of quantity. Because afterwards I discussed it with my partner <lb/>and he did say to me &quot;you&apos;ve never seen the quantities they give at the nursery, but it&apos;s <lb/>really small portions, and compared to what you give him, it&apos;s just enormous&quot;, well I <lb/>mean it&apos;s more. [ . . . ] Because basically his baby plate shouldn&apos;t be full, and actually <lb/>sometimes I do fill it up. And I don&apos;t know where that comes from . . . &quot; <lb/>[Mother, high social position, two boys aged 5 and 29 months]. <lb/>Additionally, this multistep investigation process encourages the emergence of a <lb/>reflexivity made possible by the identification, during the interaction, of situations of <lb/>derogation linked to the numerous contexts that intervene in the socialization. <lb/>This study mainly concerns children with what could be considered in pediatrics <lb/>as &quot;typical&quot; development. Despite the fact that no exclusion criteria were set related to <lb/>pathologies or early events which could have a potential consequence on the organization <lb/>of child feeding (such as gastroesophageal reflux disease, cow&apos;s milk protein allergy, naso-<lb/>gastric intubation, congenital abnormalities of the digestive tract, and extreme premature <lb/>birth), it is obvious according to parent responses that children within this sample were <lb/>not presenting any of these conditions. The present results can only be interpreted for <lb/>this population. For children with specific conditions, the application of more normative <lb/>feeding practices may actually be beneficial for child development (e.g., food restriction in <lb/>the case of food allergy; nutritional enrichment in the case of extreme premature birth to <lb/>ensure growth catch up). <lb/>6. Conclusions <lb/>This article provides an overview of the levels and modalities involved in the percep-<lb/>tion of hunger, appetite, satiation and satiety in young children by the adults who feed them. <lb/>It highlights the influence of nutritional, social and educational norms on which parents in <lb/>France rely variably according to their social backgrounds and parental experience in order <lb/>to supervise the practices of young children. These levels of perception are also part of the <lb/></body>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>26 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>day-to-day &quot;food work&quot;, which, through social practices, activities and interactions around <lb/>food, inhibits or reinforces the effect of normative frameworks and educational models <lb/>and thus socializes children and determines how much, when, what and how to eat in the <lb/>household and other contexts. Finally, this article clarifies the conditions and limits of a <lb/>top-down education-from adults to children-on hunger and satiety. To that end, this <lb/>article relates this process to the fluctuating recommendations of &quot;good&quot; behavior likely to <lb/>maintain young children in a state of good health and well-being and which are in keeping <lb/>with scientific discoveries. In terms of applications, this study calls for better consideration <lb/>of these aspects in nutritional recommendations so as not to increase the moralization of <lb/>behaviors considered non-compliant. The redefinition of food education standards, on <lb/>which nutritional policies for parents are based, must be established in accordance with <lb/>the standards on which households rely. The risk is otherwise of saturating the already <lb/>numerous normative mechanisms in France by which parents find their way, which would <lb/>be counterproductive. The risk is also to participate in reinforcing the effects of &quot;parental <lb/>determinism&quot; (Furedi 2002) by reinforcing the idea that parents are bad educators. <lb/>On the epistemological level, this work brings to light a number of connections <lb/>between the psycho-sensorial, psycho-cognitive and socioanthropological dimensions of <lb/>food, as well as food-related education. It sheds additional light on the ways in which <lb/>socialization unfolds in the interactions between the child and those around him, but <lb/>also in the more or less strong and conscious movements back and forth between dietary <lb/>and educational social norms, physiological, psycho-sensory and psychomotor signals <lb/>emitted by the child and decoded by adults, and finally in the interactions with the <lb/>daily environment, concrete practices and routines that organize socialization. In this <lb/>respect, work on the food socialization of young children can contribute to a deeper <lb/>understanding of the processes by which the biological, the ecological, the psychological <lb/>and the sociological are shaped together. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Author Contributions: A.D. designed the protocol, conducted the field qualitative survey, analyzed <lb/>and drafted the results, and wrote this article. S.N. secured the funding and coordinated the ANR <lb/>research. S.G. participated in the data collection. S.N., C.S. and L.T. participated in writing this article. <lb/>All authors read and approved the final manuscript and consent to publication in this journal. <lb/></div>

			<div type="funding">Funding: This research is supported by the Agence Nationale de la Recherche in France. ANR-15-<lb/>CE21-0014, PUNCH, Promoting and Understanding healthy food choices in Children. The authors <lb/>wish to thank the parents, home-based child care providers, and children who participated in this <lb/>research. We also thank Margaux Huille and Audrey Bardet, ISTHIA trainees for this study, Joël <lb/>Courant and Pierre Ratinaud for computer science support and Christelle Abraham for the financial <lb/>management of this research. Thank also the ISTHIA. We would like to thank Marie Laurent-Badin <lb/>Vilain for translating this article into English. Finally, we thank the reviewers from Social Sciences, Jean-<lb/>Pierre Poulain, guest editor, and Marina Crina, assistant editor, who contributed to the improvement <lb/>of our article. The study was conducted according to the guidelines of the Declaration of Helsinki, <lb/>and approved by Ethics Committee of Université Fédérale de Toulouse IRB # 1 (retrospective ethical <lb/>approval N°: IRB00011835-2019-09-24-180, 9/24/2019). <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Informed Consent Statement: Informed consent was obtained from all subjects involved in the <lb/>study. <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Conflicts of Interest: The authors declare no conflict of interest. The founding sponsors (ANR) had <lb/>no role in the design of the study; in the collection, analyses, or interpretation of data; in the writing <lb/>of the manuscript; and in the decision to publish the results. <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>27 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Appendix A <lb/>Table A1. Interview guide. <lb/>Parents <lb/>Topics <lb/>Subtopics <lb/>Information about the respondent <lb/>and his/her family <lb/>Family situation and organization <lb/>Food at home <lb/>Provisioning, including focus on child <lb/>Meal preparation, including a focus on the child <lb/>Preparation of child&apos;s meals: help, influences, <lb/>recommendations and consideration of needs and wishes <lb/>expressed by the child <lb/>Child&apos;s relationship to food <lb/>How does the child express that he is hungry? That he is <lb/>satiated? How to describe the child&apos;s appetite <lb/>Child&apos;s nutrition and child care <lb/>arrangements <lb/>Educational delegation and food delegation <lb/>Dietary adjustments according to <lb/>the child&apos;s advancement in age <lb/>Evolution of the diet <lb/>Relationship to weight in childhood <lb/>Before diversification <lb/>Breast-feeding methods and weaning <lb/>Educational styles and eating styles <lb/>Transmission issues and life experience <lb/>Differences between children in multiparous families <lb/>Photo protocol <lb/>Meals and leftovers contextualized according to specific <lb/>situations (e.g., when the child is tired, when you are tired, <lb/>the child liked, the child did not like) <lb/>Second interview <lb/>Link with the previous interview: changes, clarifications <lb/>to be made according to the respondent <lb/>Forgotten questions, poorly conducted follow-up, <lb/>paradoxes identified by the interviewer <lb/>Description about the photos taken (contexts, reasons for <lb/>selection, quantities served and leftovers left by the child) <lb/></div>

			<div type="annex">Appendix B. Details of the Lexicometric Analyses Carried Out on the Corpus <lb/>To constitute each corpus, preparation is necessary, consisting of division into units: <lb/>here, each parent constitutes an initial context unit to which certain characteristics are <lb/>associated. These additional variables are introduced to compare their distribution in <lb/>the classes of significant statements. These classes are generated following a hierarchical <lb/>top-down classification that combines vocabulary and statements similar to each other and <lb/>distinct from those of other classes. For each corpus, a hierarchical top-down classification <lb/>is conducted to identify, using an iterative procedure, the classes of significant statements <lb/>and to highlight the general themes of the corpus as well as the internal organization of the <lb/>discourse. In addition to the frequency of words within classes, the analysis enables us to <lb/>understand the variety of discourse, the meaning of words and their relationships. <lb/>The results (selection) are represented by dendrograms and tables (in Appendices C <lb/>and D, below), allowing identifying the segmentation of the corpus into classes. Each class <lb/>contains a certain number of words, which are sorted by their strength of association with <lb/>the class. The words appearing at the top of the list of the class words (or in large characters <lb/>in the dendrograms with associated words) are the most representative words of the class <lb/>according to the value and the strength of their chi2: the higher the chi2, the more likely <lb/>the hypothesis of dependence between the word and the class. When a word is found in <lb/>several classes, its position in the word list means that it is characteristic of that particular <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>28 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<body>class compared to others. Finally, the lower the p value, the smaller the margin of error of <lb/>the dependency test. <lb/>Concerning the corpus (see Section 3.2), the analyses are carried out on a corpus of <lb/>28 texts, corresponding to the 28 households surveyed, comprising 430,926 occurrences, <lb/>6874 lemmas and 2594 hapaxes (0.60% of the occurrences-38% of the forms). The average <lb/>number of occurrences per text is 15,390. As a result, 14 initial context units have been intro-<lb/>duced to differentiate each parent. In the software, these are starred words to characterize <lb/>the number of the parent in order to differentiate him/her: the status of the respondent <lb/>(mother or father), the number of children, the social position of the household based on <lb/>the level of diploma and resources of the parents, the level of diploma and resources of <lb/>the household, the sex of the child, the medical follow-up of the child, the age of the child, <lb/>the relationship to nutritional recommendations declared by the parent based on the ques-<lb/>tion about the sources of advice for breastfeeding, weaning and diversification, duration <lb/>of breastfeeding, age of diversification, season of diversification, type of diversification <lb/>(salty or sweet) and type of food served for diversification (homemade, industrial jar, or <lb/>combination). <lb/>The dynamic analysis is then processed on the basis of the corpus of 20 parents <lb/>interviewed on two occasions (see Section 3.3.1). In this analysis, the lexical universes are <lb/>compared within a period of 44 days on average (σ = 28.6). The analyses cover a corpus <lb/>of 40 texts. For the corpus relating to the first interview, it includes 245,527 occurrences, <lb/>5330 lemmas and 2057 hapaxes (0.84% of occurrences-39% of forms). The average number <lb/>of occurrences per text is 12,276. For the corpus relating to the second interview, it includes <lb/>121,928 occurrences, 3861 lemmas and 1617 hapax (1.33% of the occurrences-42% of the <lb/>forms) and the average of the occurrences per text is 6096. <lb/></body>

			<div type="annex">Appendix C <lb/>Table A2. Classes, ratio, Chi2 and p for parents: first associated words. <lb/>Words <lb/>Subtotal to Total Ratio <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>p <lb/>Class 1 <lb/>Relating to the Medical <lb/>2507/11,387 = 22.02% of <lb/>Classified Segments <lb/>Weight <lb/>98/104 = 94.23% <lb/>318.8 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Height <lb/>40/50 = 80% <lb/>98.34 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Concern <lb/>58/78 = 74.36% <lb/>125.33 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Problem <lb/>86/162 = 53.09% <lb/>92.4 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Difficulties <lb/>67/123 = 54.47% <lb/>76.29 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Reflux <lb/>34/37 = 91.89% <lb/>105.56 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Worry <lb/>41/78 = 52.56% <lb/>42.69 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Girls <lb/>49/76 = 64.47% <lb/>80.33 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Health <lb/>43/47 = 91.49% <lb/>132.67 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Curve <lb/>66/66 = 100% <lb/>235.14 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Pediatrician <lb/>125/168 = 74.4% <lb/>272.58 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Doctor <lb/>96/116 = 82.76% <lb/>251.85 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Booklet (Health) <lb/>19/19 = 100% <lb/>67.41 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>General practitioner <lb/>19/19 = 100% <lb/>67.41 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>29 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Table A2. Cont. <lb/>Words <lb/>Subtotal to Total Ratio <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>p <lb/>Growth <lb/>21/26 = 80.77% <lb/>52.39 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Allergy <lb/>22/26 = 84.62% <lb/>59.48 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Weighing <lb/>24/34 = 70.59% <lb/>46.86 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Vomiting <lb/>29/44 = 65.91% <lb/>49.56 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Body <lb/>14/16 = 87.5% <lb/>40.02 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sick <lb/>54/116 = 46.55% <lb/>41.09 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with high education and <lb/>income <lb/>201/615 = 32.68% <lb/>43.08 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Children followed by a <lb/>pediatrician and a general <lb/>practitioner <lb/>869/3385 = 25.67% <lb/>37.5 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Class 2 <lb/>Relationship to the sweet food <lb/>repertoire <lb/>2018/11,387 = 17.72% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Chocolate <lb/>136/179 = 75.98% <lb/>423.27 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Cakes <lb/>129/231 = 55.84% <lb/>235.0 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sweet <lb/>136/191 = 71.2% <lb/>381.07 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sugar <lb/>103/124 = 83.06% <lb/>367.09 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with the lowest levels of <lb/>education and income <lb/>98/450 = 21.78% <lb/>5.29 <lb/>p = 0.02150 <lb/>Fruits <lb/>238/334 = 71.26% <lb/>676.34 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Compotes <lb/>230/355 = 64.79% <lb/>556.69 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Organic <lb/>130/155 = 83.87% <lb/>471.56 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Markets <lb/>94/150 = 62.67% <lb/>210.58 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Dairy products <lb/>147/480 = 30.63% <lb/>57.22 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Yogurts <lb/>270/369 = 73.17% <lb/>804.12 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Cheese <lb/>114/273 = 41.76% <lb/>110.83 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with high levels of <lb/>education and income <lb/>137/615 = 22.28% <lb/>9.25 <lb/>p = 0.00235 <lb/>High social position <lb/>795/4206 = 18.9% <lb/>6.36 <lb/>p = 0.01164 <lb/>Class 3 <lb/>Relationship to the salty <lb/>food repertoire <lb/>2415/11,387 = 21.21% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Vegetables <lb/>328/473 = 69.34% <lb/>684.29 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Carrot <lb/>202/226 = 89.38% <lb/>641.27 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Tomato <lb/>113/121 = 93.39% <lb/>381.3 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Zucchini <lb/>97/105 = 92.38% <lb/>321.26 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Pasta <lb/>221/310 = 71.29% <lb/>478.33 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Rice <lb/>106/147 = 72.11% <lb/>230.9 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Meat <lb/>248/316 = 78.48% <lb/>637.99 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Ham <lb/>118/132 = 89.39% <lb/>371.56 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>30 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Table A2. Cont. <lb/>Words <lb/>Subtotal to Total Ratio <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>p <lb/>Parents compliant with the norms <lb/>1470/6274 = 23.43% <lb/>41.27 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with a daughter <lb/>1117/4810 = 23.22% <lb/>20.22 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with a high level <lb/>of education <lb/>327/1347 = 24.28% <lb/>8.6 <lb/>p = 0.00335 <lb/>Parents with low income but <lb/>high education <lb/>419/1769 = 23.69% <lb/>7.69 <lb/>p = 0.00554 <lb/>Class 4 <lb/>Temporal framework of food <lb/>socialization <lb/>1659/11,387 = 14.57% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Morning <lb/>239/378 = 63.23% <lb/>743.73 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Evening <lb/>308/668 = 46.11% <lb/>567.1 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Night <lb/>128/167 = 76.65% <lb/>524.75 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Noon <lb/>207/384 = 53.91% <lb/>494.06 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Waking up <lb/>99/113 = 87.61% <lb/>489.21 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Time <lb/>166/306 = 54.25% <lb/>397.76 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents reporting medical <lb/>follow-up of their child by <lb/>a pediatrician <lb/>1112/6687 = 16.63% <lb/>55.24 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents of a middle-class social <lb/>position <lb/>424/2544 = 16.67% <lb/>11.58 <lb/>p = 0.00066 <lb/>Parents with a moderate level of <lb/>education and income <lb/>384/2294 = 16.74% <lb/>11.58 <lb/>p = 0.00097 <lb/>Parents with a low level of <lb/>education and income <lb/>222/1291 = 17.2% <lb/>8.07 <lb/>p = 0.00449 <lb/>Primiparous <lb/>1073/7002 = 15.32% <lb/>8.33 <lb/>p = 0.00390 <lb/>Class 5 <lb/>Social framework of food <lb/>socialization <lb/>2788/11,387 = 24.48% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Table <lb/>241/321 = 75.08% <lb/>457.3 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Play <lb/>165/247 = 66.8% <lb/>244.53 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Hunger <lb/>237/429 = 55.24% <lb/>228.14 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Meals <lb/>244/632 = 38.61% <lb/>72.19 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Parents with low social position <lb/>226/748 = 30.21% <lb/>14.22 <lb/>p = 0.00016 <lb/>Parents with a low level of <lb/>education and income <lb/>201/692 = 29.05% <lb/>8.29 <lb/>p = 0.00397 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>31 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Appendix D <lb/>Table A3. Classes, ratio, Chi2 and p for parents in the second interview: first associated words. <lb/>Words <lb/>Subtotal to Total Ratio <lb/>Chi2 <lb/>p <lb/>Class 1 <lb/>Relating to the salty food repertoire <lb/>245/1485 = 16.5% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Tomato <lb/>23/26 = 88.46% <lb/>99.48 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Meat <lb/>33/48 = 68.75% <lb/>98.31 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Egg <lb/>22/26 = 84.62% <lb/>89.13 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sauce <lb/>17/17 = 100% <lb/>87.04 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Season diversification <lb/>208/864 = 24.07% <lb/>86.07 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Diversification at 5 months <lb/>153/563 = 27.18% <lb/>75.04 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Class 2 <lb/>Perceived changes in child&apos;s <lb/>development <lb/>577/1485 = 38.86% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Child <lb/>43/58 = 74.14% <lb/>31.63 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Month <lb/>34/47 = 72.34% <lb/>22.91 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Curve <lb/>14/14 = 100% <lb/>22.24 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Weight <lb/>15/16 = 93.75% <lb/>20.52 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Girl <lb/>20/24 = 83.33% <lb/>20.31 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Diversification at 5 months 1 <lb/>2 <lb/>61/70 = 87.14% <lb/>72.1 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>High social position <lb/>95/143 = 66.43% <lb/>50.66 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Standards_promotion <lb/>148/265 = 55.85% <lb/>39.21 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Class 3 <lb/>Relating to the sweet food repertoire <lb/>435/1485 = 29.29% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Buy <lb/>70/95 = 73.68% <lb/>96.56 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Yogurt <lb/>57/71 = 80.28% <lb/>93.6 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Compote <lb/>43/51 = 84.31% <lb/>77.19 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Fruit <lb/>34/44 = 77.27% <lb/>50.4 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Dessert <lb/>27/32 = 84.38% <lb/>47.91 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Chocolate <lb/>32/45 = 71.11% <lb/>39.18 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Standards_distance <lb/>42/63 = 66.67% <lb/>44.37 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>No breastfeeding <lb/>82/161 = 50.93% <lb/>40.82 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Follow-up_pediatrician <lb/>259/709 = 36.53% <lb/>34.31 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sex of child_boy <lb/>235/668 = 35.18% <lb/>20.31 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Class 4 <lb/>Temporal framework of food <lb/>socialization <lb/>228/1485 = 15.35% of <lb/>classified segments <lb/>Wake up <lb/>16/16 = 100% <lb/>89.17 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Bottle feeding <lb/>27/41 = 65.85% <lb/>82.74 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Night <lb/>16/17 = 94.12% <lb/>82.09 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Morning <lb/>29/49 = 59.18% <lb/>74.9 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sleep <lb/>13/13 = 100% <lb/>72.3 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Bedtime <lb/>17/21 = 80.95% <lb/>70.53 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Time <lb/>19/26 = 73.08% <lb/>68.85 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Salty type diversification <lb/>196/1000 = 19.6% <lb/>42.48 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Sex of child_boy <lb/>140/668 = 20.96% <lb/>57.78 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Follow-up_pediatrician <lb/>141/709 = 19.89% <lb/>21.46 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/>Family_Multiparous <lb/>120/589 = 20.37% <lb/>18.93 <lb/>p &lt; 0.0001 <lb/></div>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>32 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<div type="annex">Notes <lb/>1 <lb/>&quot;Food work&quot; is defined as household and caring work related to food to highlight gender differences in materialist feminist <lb/>approaches (DeVault 1991; Cairns and Josée 2015; Parsons 2015; O&apos;Connell and Brannen 2016). Our conception of &quot;food work&quot; <lb/>extends this perspective. We add parental work, as well as relational, affective and emotional work related to meal preparation <lb/>because it brings additional physical and mental loads in the nurturing activity (Dupuy 2013; Dupuy 2017a; Dupuy et al. 2018b). <lb/>This addition is relevant in a context favorable to &quot;parental determinism&quot; (Furedi 2002) and to the increase in injunctions to <lb/>&quot;good parenting&quot; (Martin 2014). <lb/></div>

			<listBibl>References <lb/>Anderson, Judith V., Deborah I. Bybee, Randi M. Brown, Donna F. McLean, Erika M. Garcia, M. Lynn Breer, and Barbara A. Schillo. <lb/>2001. 5 a Day Fruit and Vegetable Intervention Improves Consumption in a Low Income Population. Journal of the American <lb/>Dietetic Association 101: 195-202. [CrossRef] <lb/>ANSES. 2019. Avis De L&apos;anses Relatif À L&apos;actualisation Des Repères Alimentaires Du Pnns-Jeunes Enfants (0-3 Ans). Available on-<lb/>line: https://www.anses.fr/fr/content/avis-de-lanses-relatif-%C3%A0-lactualisation-des-rep%C3%A8res-alimentaires-dupnns-<lb/>jeunes-enfants-0-3 (accessed on 19 February 2021). <lb/>Birch, Leann L. 1987. Children&apos;s Food Preferences: Developmental Patterns and Environmental Influences. Annals of Child Development <lb/>4: 171-208. <lb/>Birch, Leann L. 1990. The control of food intake by young children. The role of learning. In Taste, Experience and Feeding. Edited by <lb/>Elizabeth D. Capaldi and Terry L. Powley. Washington, DC: American Psychological Association, pp. 116-35. <lb/>Birch, Leann L., and Jennifer O. Fisher. 1998. Development of eating behaviors among children and adolescents. Pediatrics 101: 539-49. <lb/>Birch, Leann L., and Jennifer O. Fisher. 2000. Mothers&apos; child-feeding practices influence daughters&apos; eating and weight. The American <lb/>Journal of Clinical Nutrition 71: 1054-61. [CrossRef] <lb/>Birch, Leann L., Sheryl Itkin Zimmerman, and Honey Hind. 1980. The influence of social-affective context on the formation of <lb/>children&apos;s food preferences. Child Development 51: 856-61. [CrossRef] <lb/>Birch, Leann L., Linda McPhee, B. C. Shoba, Edna Pirok, and Lois Steinberg. 1987. What kind of exposure reduces children&apos;s food <lb/>neophobia? Looking vs. tasting. Appetite 9: 171-78. [CrossRef] <lb/>Birch, Leann L., Susan L. Johnson, Graciela Andresen, John C. Peters, and Marcia C. Schulte. 1991. The variability of young children&apos;s <lb/>energy intake. New England Journal of Medicine 324: 232-35. [CrossRef] <lb/>Birch, Leann L., Jennifer Orlet Fisher, and Kirsten Krahnstoever Davison. 2003. Learning to overeat: Maternal use of restrictive feeding <lb/>practices promotes girls&apos; eating in the absence of hunger. The American Journal of Clinical Nutrition 78: 215-20. [CrossRef] <lb/>Bourdieu, Pierre. 2000. Esquisse d&apos;une théorie de la pratique. Précédé de trois études d&apos;ethnologie Kabyle. Paris: Seuil. First published in 1972. <lb/>Bournez, Marie, Eléa Ksiazek, Sandra Wagner, Claire Kersuzan, Christine Tichit, Severine Gojard, Xavier Thierry, Marie-Aline Charles, <lb/>Sandrine Lioret, Blandine de Lauzon-Guillain, and et al. 2018. Factors Associated with the Introduction of Complementary <lb/>Feeding in the French Elfe Cohort Study. Maternal and Child Nutrition 14: e12536. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Bournez, Marie, Eléa Ksiazek, Marie-Aline Charles, Sandrine Lioret, Marie-Claude Brindisi, Blandine de Lauzon-Guillain, and Sophie <lb/>Nicklaus. 2019. Frequency of Use of Added Sugar, Salt, and Fat in Infant Foods up to 10 Months in the Nationwide Elfe Cohort <lb/>Study: Associated Infant Feeding and Caregiving Practices. Nutrients 11: 733. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Bril, Blandine, Estelle Hombessa-Nkounkou, Jean-François Bouville, and Célina Ocampo. 2001. From milk to adult diet: A comparative <lb/>study on the socialization of food. Food and Foodways 9: 155-86. [CrossRef] <lb/>Brugaillères, Pauline, Claire Chabane, Sylvie Issanchou, and Camille Schwartz. 2019. Caloric compensation ability around the age of 1 <lb/>year: Interplay with the caregiver-infant mealtime interaction and infant appetitive traits. Appetite 142: 104382. [CrossRef] <lb/>Cairns, Kate, and Johnston Josée. 2015. Food and Femininity. London: Bloomsbury. <lb/>Cardon, Philippe, Thomas Depecker, and Marie Plessz. 2019. Sociologie de l&apos;alimentation. Malakoff: Armand Colin. <lb/>Chiva, Matty. 1979. Comment la personne se construit en mangeant. Communications 31: 107-18. [CrossRef] <lb/>Collier, John, and Malcom Collier. 1986. Visual Anthropology: Photography as a Research Method. Albuquerque: University of New Mexico <lb/>Press. First published in 1976. <lb/>Connell, Raewyn. 1987. Gender and Power. Society, the Person and Sexual Politics. Stanford: Stanford University Press. <lb/>Cooke, Lucy J., Lucy C. Chambers, Elizabeth V. Añez, and Jane Wardle. 2011. Facilitating or Undermining? The Effect of Reward on <lb/>Food Acceptance. A Narrative Review. Appetite 57: 493-97. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Corbeau, Jean-Pierre. 2008. Nourrir de plaisir, Se nourrir de plaisir: De la recommandation à la condamnation. In Nourrir de Plaisir. <lb/>Edited by Corbeau Jean-Pierre. Cahier n • 13 de l&apos;OCHA. Paris: OCHA, pp. 154-62. <lb/>Corbeau, Jean-Pierre, ed. 2010. Trajectoires alimentaires et parcours de vie. Paris: INPES Éditions. <lb/>Depecker, Thomas. 2010. Les cultures somatiques: Rapports au corps et diététique. Revue d&apos;études en agriculture et environnement 91: <lb/>153-84. <lb/>DeVault, Marjorie L. 1991. Feeding the Family. The Social Organization of Caring as Gendered Work. Chicago: University of Chicago Press. <lb/>Dhuot, Raphaël. 2018. La genèse précoce des différences sociales dans les habitudes alimentaires. Ph.D. dissertation, Université <lb/>Paris-Saclay, Gif-sur-Yvette, France; 596p. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>33 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Diasio, Nicoletta. 2006. Adultes et enfants entre pouvoir et insoumission. In Eléments pour une sociologie de l&apos;enfance. Edited by Régine <lb/>Sirota. Rennes: Le Sens Social, PUR, pp. 245-55. <lb/>Diasio, Nicoletta, and Virginie Vinel, eds. 2017. Corps et préadolescence. Intime, privé, public. Rennes: Le sens social, PUR. <lb/>Diasio, Nicoletta, and Marie-Pierre Julien. 2018. Anthropology of Family Food Practices: Constraints, Adjustments, Innovations. Bruxelles: <lb/>PIE Peter Lang. <lb/>Di Santis, Katherine I., Eric A. Hodges, Susan L. Johnson, and Jennifer Orlet Fisher. 2011. The Role of Responsive Feeding in Overweight <lb/>During Infancy and Toddlerhood: A Systematic Review. International Journal of Obesity 35: 480-92. [CrossRef] <lb/>Dubuisson-Quellier, Sophie. 2006. De la routine à la délibération. Les arbitrages des consommateurs en situation d&apos;achat. Réseaux 1: <lb/>253-84. [CrossRef] <lb/>Dupuy, Anne. 2013. Plaisirs alimentaires. In Socialisation des enfants et des adolescents. Rennes: Presses Universitaires de Rennes; Presses <lb/>Universitaires François-Rabelais, Coll. Tables des hommes. <lb/>Dupuy, Anne. 2017a. Société, culture et alimentation. In Alimentation sous influences. Edited by Boris Cyrulnik. Savigny sur Orge: <lb/>Philippe Duval, pp. 103-13. <lb/>Dupuy, Anne. 2017b. La division sexuelle du travail alimentaire: Qu&apos;est-ce qui change? In Que manger? normes et pratiques alimentaires. <lb/>Edited by François Dubet. Paris: La Découverte, Recherches, pp. 164-75. <lb/>Dupuy, Anne, and Amandine Rochedy. 2018. Socialisations alimentaires et pratiques rituelles durant la petite enfance. Anthropology of <lb/>Food. Available online: http://journals.openedition.org/aof/8253 (accessed on 28 July 2021). <lb/>Dupuy, Anne, Rochedy Amandine, and Charlotte Sarrat. 2018a. Feeding young children with home-made food: Routines, necessary <lb/>disruptions and production of domestic rituals. In Anthropology of Family Food Practices: Constraints, Adjustments, Innovations. <lb/>Edited by Nicoletta Diasio and Marie-Pierre Julien. Bruxelles: PIE Peter Lang, pp. 183-215. <lb/>Dupuy, Anne, Laurence Tibère, and Stéphanie Goirand. 2018b. Travail alimentaire et délégation éducative. Le cas des assistantes <lb/>maternelles à domicile. Revue des politiques sociales et familiales 129: 37-50. [CrossRef] <lb/>Durkheim, Emile. 1981. Les règles de la méthode sociologique. Paris: PUF. First published in 1894. <lb/>Farrow, Claire, and Jackie Blissett. 2006. Maternal cognitions, psychopathologic symptoms, and infant temperament as predictors of <lb/>early infant feeding problems: A longitudinal study. International Journal of Eating Disorders 39: 128-34. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Fielding-Singh, Priya. 2017. A Taste of Inequality: Food&apos;s Symbolic Value across the Socioeconomic Spectrum. Sociological Science 4: <lb/>424-48. [CrossRef] <lb/>Fischler, Claude. 1990. L&apos;homnivore. Paris: Odile Jacob. <lb/>Fischler, Claude, and Matty Chiva. 1986. Food likes, dislikes and some of their correlates in a sample of French children and young <lb/>adults. In Measurement and Determinants of Food Habits and Food Preferences. Edited by Joerg M. Diehl and Claus Leitzmann. Report <lb/>of an EC Workshop. Giessen: EURO NUT, pp. 1-4. <lb/>Furedi, Franck. 2002. Paranoïd Parenting. Why Ignoring the Experts May be Best for your Children? A Cappella Books. Chicago: Chicago <lb/>Review Press. <lb/>Garcia, Sandrine. 2011. Mères sous influence. De la cause des femmes à la cause des enfants. Textes à l&apos;appui/Genre &amp; Sexualité, La <lb/>Découverte. Paris: Coll. <lb/>Gojard, Séverine. 2000. L&apos;alimentation dans la prime enfance. Diffusion et réception des normes de puériculture. Revue française de <lb/>sociologie 41: 475-512. [CrossRef] <lb/>Gojard, Séverine. 2001. Meal schedules in early childhood: A study in contemporary France. Food and Foodways 9: 187-203. [CrossRef] <lb/>Gojard, Séverine. 2006. Changement de normes, changement de pratiques? Les prescriptions alimentaires à destination des jeunes <lb/>enfants dans la France contemporaine. Journal des anthropologues 106-107: 269-85. [CrossRef] <lb/>Gojard, Séverine. 2010. Le métier de mère. Paris: La Dispute. <lb/>Gottlieb, Alma. 2000. Où sont passés tous les bébés? Vers une anthropologie du nourrisson. In En Substances. Textes pour Françoise <lb/>Héritier. Edited by Jean-Luc Jamard, Emmanuel Terray and Margarita Xanthakou. Paris: Fayard, pp. 367-85. <lb/>Gross, Rachel S., Arthur H. Fierman, Alan L. Mendelsohn, Mary Ann Chiasson, Terry J. Rosenberg, Roberta Scheinmann, and Mary Jo <lb/>Messita. 2010. Maternal Peceptions of Infant Hunger, Satiety, and Pressuring Feeding Styles in an Urban Latina Wic Population. <lb/>Academic Pediatrics 10: 29-35. [CrossRef] <lb/>Hamelin Brabant, Louise, and André Turmel, eds. 2012. Les figures de l&apos;enfance: Un regard sociologique. Quebec: Presses Inter-Universitaires. <lb/>HCSP. 2020. Avis Relatif À La Révision Des Repères Alimentaires Pour Les Enfants Âgés De 0-36 Mois Et De 3-17 Ans. Available <lb/>online: https://www.hcsp.fr/explore.cgi/avisrapportsdomaine?clefr=924 (accessed on 19 February 2021). <lb/>Hetherington, Marion. 2017. Understanding infant eating behavior-Lessons learned from observation. Physiology &amp; Behavior 176: <lb/>117-24. [CrossRef] <lb/>Hodges, Eric A., Susan L. Johnson, Sheryl O. Hughes, Judy M. Hopkinson, Nancy F. Butte, and Jennifer O. Fisher. 2013. Development <lb/>of the Responsiveness to Child Feeding Cues Scale. Appetite 65: 210-19. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Hubert, Annie. 2000. Alimentation et santé: La science et l&apos;imaginaire. Cahiers de Nutrition et de Diététique 35: 353-56. [CrossRef] <lb/>Hughes, Sheryl O., Thomas G Power, Teresia M O&apos;Connor, Jennifer Orlet Fisher, and Tzu-An Chen. 2016. Maternal feeding styles <lb/>and food parenting practices as predictors of longitudinal changes in weight status in hispoanic preschoolers from low-income <lb/>families. J Obesity 2016: 7201082. [CrossRef] <lb/>Lahire, Bernard, ed. 2019. Enfances de classe. De l&apos;inégalité parmi les enfants. Paris: Seuil. <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>34 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Lalanne, Michèle, and Laurence Tibère. 2008. Quand les enfants font craquer les modèles alimentaires des adultes. Enfance 60: 271-79. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>Laurier, Eric, and Sally Wiggins. 2011. Finishing the family meal. The interactional organisation of satiety. Appetite 6: 53-64. [CrossRef] <lb/>Le Pape, Marie-Clémence, and Marie Plessz. 2017. C&apos;est l&apos;heure du petit-déjeuner? Rythme des repas, incorporation et classe sociale. <lb/>L&apos;Année sociologique 67: 73-106. [CrossRef] <lb/>Lhuissier, Anne, Christine Tichit, France Caillavet, Philippe Cardon, Ana Masullo, Judith Martin-Fernandez, Isabelle Parizot, and <lb/>Pierre Chauvin. 2013. Who still eats three meals a day? Findings from a quantitative survey in the Paris area? Appetite 63: 59-69. <lb/>[CrossRef] <lb/>Martin, Claude, ed. 2014. Être un bon parent. Une injonction contemporaine. Rennes: Presses de l&apos;EHESP. <lb/>Mauss, Marcel. 1936. Les techniques du corps. Journal de Psychologie 32: 365-86. <lb/>McNally, Janet, Siobhan Hugh-Jones, Samantha Caton, Carel Vereijken, Hugo Weenen, and Marion Hetherington. 2016. Communicating <lb/>Hunger and Satiation in the First 2 years of Life: A Systematic Review. Maternal and Child Nutrition 12: 205-28. [CrossRef] <lb/>McNally, Janet, Siobhan Hugh-Jones, and Marion Hetherington. 2020. &quot;An invisible map&quot;-maternal perceptions of hunger, satiation <lb/>and &apos;enough&apos; in the context of baby led and traditional complementary feeding practices. Appetite 148: 104608. [CrossRef] <lb/>Monnery-Patris, Sandrine, Natalie Rigal, Audrey Peteuil, Claire Chabanet, and Issanchou Sylvie. 2019. Development of a new <lb/>questionnaire to assess the links between children&apos;s self-regulation of eating and related parental feeding practices. Appetite 138: <lb/>174-83. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Moura, Andrea Ferreira, and Jessica Aschemann-Witzel. 2020. A downturn or a window of opportunity? How Danish and French <lb/>parents perceive changes in healthy eating in the transition to parenthood. Appetite 150: 104658. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Nicaise, Sarah, Martine Court, Christine Mennesson, and Emmanuelle Zolesio. 2019. Vêtements, soins et alimentation: L&apos;inscription <lb/>corporelle des différences sociales. In Enfances de classe. De l&apos;inégalite parmi les enfants. Edited by Bernard Lahire. Paris: Seuil, <lb/>pp. 1137-57. <lb/>Nicklaus, Sophie, Vincent Boggio, and Sylvie Issanchou. 2005. Food choices at lunch during the third year of life: High selection of <lb/>animal and starchy foods but avoidance of vegetables. Acta Paediatrica 94: 943-51. [CrossRef] <lb/>Nicklaus, Sophie, Marie Bournez, Eléa Ksiazek, Marion Taine, Barbara Heude, Jeremy Botton, Anne Forhan, Marie-Aline Charles, and <lb/>Blandine de Lauzon-Guillain. 2019. Débuter la diversification alimentaire: Une décision influencée par la croissance de l&apos;enfant? Colloque <lb/>International Beco &quot;Bébé, petite enfance en contextes&quot;. Toulouse: Mai. <lb/>O&apos;Connell, Rebecca, and Julia Brannen. 2016. Food, Families and Work. London: Bloomsbury. <lb/>Ochs, Elinor, and Merav Shohet. 2006. The cultural structuring of mealtime socialization. Next Directions for Child and Adolescent <lb/>Development 111: 35-49. [CrossRef] <lb/>Odgen, Jane, Rebecca Reynolds, and Andrea Smith. 2006. Expanding the concept of parental control. A role for overt and covert <lb/>control of children&apos;s snacking behavior? Appetite 47: 100-6. <lb/>Parsons, Julie M. 2015. Gender, Class and Food: Families, Bodies and Health. London: Palgrave. <lb/>Perez-Escamilla, Rafael, Sofia Segura-Pérez, and Megan Lott. 2017. Feeding Guidelines for Infants and Young Toddlers. A responsive <lb/>parenting approach. Nutrition Today 52: 223-31. [CrossRef] <lb/>Pérez-Escamilla, Rafael, Sofia Segura-Pérez, and Victoria Hall Moran. 2019. Dietary guidelines for children under 2 years of age in the <lb/>context of nurturing care. Maternal and Child Nutrition 15: e12855. [CrossRef] [PubMed] <lb/>Piette, Albert. 2013. Au coeur de l&apos;activité, au plus près de la présence. Réseaux 182: 57-88. [CrossRef] <lb/>Pliner, Patricia. 1994. Development of measures of food neophobia in children. Appetite 23: 147-63. [CrossRef] <lb/>Poulain, Jean-Pierre. 2002. Sociologies de l&apos;alimentation: Les mangeurs et l&apos;espace social alimentaire. Paris: PUF. <lb/>Poulain, Jean-Pierre. 2005. S&apos;adapter au monde ou l&apos;adapter? L&apos;alimentation en mouvement, des grandes migrations au tourisme. <lb/>Diasporas, Histoire et sociétés 7: 13-30. <lb/>Poulain, Jean-Pierre. 2009. Sociologie de l&apos;obésité. Paris: PUF. <lb/>Poulain, Jean-Pierre. 2017. The Sociology of Food. Etaing and the Place of Food in Society. Translated by Augusta Dörr. London: Bloomsbury <lb/>Publishing. <lb/>Régnier, Faustine, and Ana Masullo. 2009. Obésité, goûts et consommation. Intégration des normes d&apos;alimentation et appartenance <lb/>sociale. Revue Française de Sociologie 50: 747-73. [CrossRef] <lb/>Remy, Eloïse, Sylvie Issanchou, Claire Chabanet, Vincent Boggio, and Sophie Nicklaus. 2015. Impact of Adiposity, Age, Sex and <lb/>Maternal Feeding Practices on Eating in the Absence of Hunger and Caloric Compensation in Preschool Children. International <lb/>Journal of Obesity 39: 925-30. [CrossRef] <lb/>Ricroch, Layla, and Thibaut de Saint Pol. 2012. Le temps de l&apos;alimentation en France. INSEE Première 1417: 1-4. <lb/>Rigal, Nathalie, Marie Laure Frelut, Marie Odile Monneuse, Claude Marcel Hladik, Bruno Simmen, and Patrick Pasquet. 2006. Food <lb/>neophobia in the context of a varied diet induced by a weight reduction program in massively obese adolescents. Appetite 46: <lb/>207-14. [CrossRef] <lb/>Rochedy, Amandine, and Jean-Pierre Poulain. 2015. Approche sociologique des néophobies alimentaires chez l&apos;enfant. Dialogue 209: <lb/>55-68. [CrossRef] <lb/>Rouré, H., and Max Reinert. 1993. Analyse d&apos;un entretien à l&apos;aide d&apos;une méthode d&apos;analyse lexicale. In JADT. Paris: ENST, pp. 418-28. <lb/>Schwartz, Camille, Petra Scholtens, Amandine Lalanne, Hugo Weenen, and Sophie Nicklaus. 2011. Development of Healthy Eating <lb/>Habits Early in Life: Review of Recent Evidence and Selected Guidelines. Appetite 57: 796-807. [CrossRef] <lb/></listBibl>

			<note place="headnote">Soc. Sci. 2021, 10, 292 <lb/></note>

			<page>35 of 35 <lb/></page>

			<listBibl>Serre, Delphine. 1998. Le bébé &quot;superbe&quot;: La construction de la déviance corporelle par les professionnel(le)s de la petite enfance. <lb/>Sociétés contemporaines 31: 107-27. [CrossRef] <lb/>Shloim, Netalie, Irfan Shafiq, Pam Blundell-Birtill, and Marion Hetherington. 2018. Infant hunger and satiety cues during the first two <lb/>years of life: Developmental changes of within meal signaling. Appetite 128: 303-10. [CrossRef] <lb/>Skafida, Valeria. 2013. The family meal panacea: Exploring how different aspects of family meal occurrence, meal habits and meal <lb/>enjoyment relate to young children&apos;s diets. Sociology of Health &amp; Illness 35: 906-23. [CrossRef] <lb/>Skinner, Jean D., Betty Ruth Carruth, Kelly Houck, James Moran, A. Ann Reed, Frances Coletta, and Dana Ott. 1998. Mealtime <lb/>communication patterns of infants from 2 to 24 months of age. Journal of Nutrition Education 30: 8-16. [CrossRef] <lb/>Southerton, Dale. 2006. Analysing the temporal organization of daily life: Social constraints, practices and their allocation. Sociology 40: <lb/>435-54. [CrossRef] <lb/>Tibère, Laurence, Amandine Rochedy, and Charlotte Sarrat. 2018. Goûter en France. In Dictionnaire des cultures alimentaires. Edited by <lb/>Jean-Pierre Poulain. Paris: PUF, pp. 682-86. <lb/>Tibère, Laurence, and Anne Dupuy. 2021. L&apos;apprentissage de la régulation de la faim au cours de la petite enfance. Ajustements <lb/>autour du dessert et du jeu. In Socialisation familiale des jeunes enfants. Edited by Anne Dupuy, Christine Mennesson, Michelle <lb/>Kelly-Irving and Chantal Zaouche Gaudron. Collection Enfance &amp; parentalité. Toulouse: Editions ERES, 264p, pp. 133-47. <lb/>Turmel, André. 2008. Une sociologie historique de l&apos;enfance. Pensée du développement, catégorisation et visualisation graphique. Québec: <lb/>Presses de l&apos;université Laval. <lb/>Wiggins, Sally. 2019. Moments of Pleasure: A Preliminary Classification of Gustatory mmms and the Enactment of Enjoyment during <lb/>Infant Mealtimes. Frontiers in Psychology 10: 1404. [CrossRef] <lb/>Yuan, Wen Lun, Christine Lange, Camille Schwartz, Christophe Martin, Claire Chabanet, Blandine de Lauzon-Guillain, and Sophie <lb/>Nicklaus. 2016. Infant Dietary Exposures to Sweetness and Fattiness Increase During the First Year of Life and Are Associated <lb/>with Feeding Practices. Journal of Nutrition 146: 2334-42. [CrossRef] </listBibl>


	</text>
</tei>
