<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<PAPER>

<BODY>
<DIV><P>
</P>
<P>[0001] Liquid Compositions for Treating Plant Propagation Materials [0001] The present invention relates to liquid compositions and methods for treating plant propagation materials to protect against pest infestation in useful crops. More specifically, the present invention relates to methods for protecting crops against insects and fungi comprising applying to the plant propagation material an effective amount of a fast-drying liquid composition. The present invention further relates to plant propagation materials treated by said liquid compositions and to methods for promoting suberization in cut plant propagation materials. The present invention also relates to methods for speeding the drying time of plant propagation materials treated by liquid compositions.
</P>
<P>[0002] Seed treatments are used on a large variety of crops to control many types of pests.
Seed treatments are commonly used to ensure uniform stand establishment by protecting against soil borne diseases and insects. Systemic seed treatments may provide an alternative to traditional broadcast sprays of foliar <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.537" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.420" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne> for certain early season airborne diseases and insects. [0003] Many seed treatment materials are available for on-farm use. Some are known as hopper-box or planter-box treatments wherein liquid or dry formulations are applied to seed as it passes through an auger from the transport bin or truck to the planter boxes. These formulations are a very convenient way to apply seed treatment onto bulk seed right before planting. However, some seeds are treated and stored for later planting. Conventional dry treatments generally are formulated with talc or graphite which adhere the treatment chemical to the seed. Liquid seed treatments are less common due to the development of moisture-related problems such as fungal growth during storage. Good seed coverage is required for maximum benefit from any seed treatment formulation.
</P>
<P>[0004] However, obtaining thorough seed coverage can be difficult when attempting to treat seed. For example, dry formulations can present unacceptable worker exposure to the fungicidal and insecticidal active ingredients. In addition to the increased risk of inhalation of dry formulations, it is often necessary to use larger quantities of dry formulations to achieve adequate seed coverage. Certain liquid formulations can become inhomogeneous on storage, such that particle sizes or viscosity do not remain constant. Additional problems can arise such as unacceptable drying times, material build-up in the seed treater, low seed flowability, poor seed coverage and dust-off of the active ingredients from the seed prior to planting. As a result, handling is rendered difficult and the biological efficacy of the seed treatment is reduced.
</P>
<P>[0005] These problems are especially prominent in certain types of seeds. For example, tubers and bulbs, which may be planted whole or cut, require special care during seed treatment. In the case of tubers, such as potatoes, the cut portions of the potato seedling are especially vulnerable to bacterial and fungal infections because of the exposed surface of the potato. Potato tubers are easily skinned, nicked, and bruised during handling operations, causing seed damage which may affect plant growth.
Because of this vulnerability, dust formulations are usually preferable for cut seed as liquid dip treatments may inhibit wound healing or suberization. Additionally, liquid treatments do not dry quickly enough to prevent fungal growth and bacterial spread during the time between cutting and planting. [0006J There is a need in the art for alternative new liquid pesticidal compositions that dry quickly and are especially effective for use with cut seeds and other vulnerable plant propagation materials. More particularly, there is a need in the art for new liquid pesticidal treatments which promote wound healing or suberization on treated plant propagation materials.
</P>
<P>[0007] The present invention includes a fast-drying liquid composition for treating plant propagation materials, especially cut seeds, including tubers, against pests and promoting suberization. More particularly, the present invention includes a fast- drying liquid formulation comprising at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.1" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.61" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne>.
</P>
<P>[0008] The present invention relates to a fast-drying liquid composition for treating and protecting plant propagation material. In one embodiment, the present invention relates to a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.369" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.2" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.62" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.324" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.465" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>. The fast-drying liquid composition provides protection to the treated plant propagation material and dries within 90 minutes of application.
The present invention also relates to a method for treating plant propagation material, including seeds, comprising applying the fast-drying liquid composition. [0009] The present invention further relates to a method for preventing pest infestation in useful crops comprising treating plant propagation material, including seeds, with a pesticidally effective amount of a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.370" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.3" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.63" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.325" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.466" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00010] The present invention also relates to a method for enhancing suberization in plant propagation material, including seeds, comprising treating the propagation material with an effective amount of a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.371" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.4" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.64" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.326" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.467" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00011] The present invention further relates to a method for enhancing the drying time of plant propagation material treated by a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.475" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> comprising applying a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.372" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.5" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.65" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.327" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.468" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00012] The present invention also relates to plant propagation material treated with a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.373" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.6" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.66" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.328" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.469" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00013] The present invention further relates to a method for selectively loading a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.476" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> onto the skin side of a cut tuber, the method comprising treating the cut tuber with a fast-drying liquid composition comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.374" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.7" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>, and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.67" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> in combination with a blend of a drying agent, a wetting agent, a dispersing agent, a suberization agent, and optionally, an <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.329" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:909" name="antifreeze agent" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:762786" relevant="false">antifreeze agent</ne> and a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.470" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00014] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.538" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">Fungicides</ne> and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.421" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne> for use in treating seeds of useful plants are generally known, and processes for making them are described in The Pesticide
Manual [Twelfth Edition, Editor: CD. S. Tomlin]. For example and not for limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.69" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>, a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.248" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:720" name="neonicotinoid systemic insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:362718" relevant="false">neonicotinoid systemic insecticide</ne> useful for seed treatment, is described as entry number 792. <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.1" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">Fludioxonil</ne>, a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.249" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:721" name="phenylpyrrole fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:520271" relevant="false">phenylpyrrole fungicide</ne> used in treating seeds of useful plants, is described as entry number 368.
</P>
<P>[00015] The present invention includes a liquid formulation comprising at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.9" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.69" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne>. The formulation is fast-drying, providing a dry treated seed within less than 90 minutes of treatment. More specifically, the liquid composition of the present invention comprises <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.375" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, an effective amount of active ingredients containing at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.10" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.70" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne>, and a blend of the following components, by weight: a. about .05-20% at least one wetting agent; b. about .05-10% at least one dispersing agent; c. about .05-5% at least one drying agent; d. about .01-20% at least one suberization agent; and, optionally e. about 0-20% <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.406" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne> and optionally f. about 0-20% <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.471" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00016] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.539" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">Fungicides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include any agent useful for the prevention or treatment of fungal pests. Such <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.540" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> may be particularly useful in controlling certain phytopathogenic fungi, and provide high fungicidal activity and relatively low phytotoxicity. The active ingredient mixtures according to the invention are effective against the following non-limiting classes of related phytopathogenic fungi: ascomycetes (e.g. Venturia, Podosphaera, Erysiphe, Monilinia, Mycosphaerella, Uncinula, Leptosphaeria); basidiomycetes (e.g. the genus Hemileia, Rhizoctonia, Puccinia); Fungi imperfecti (e.g. Botrytis, Helminthosporium, including solani (silver scurf), Rhynchosporium, Fusarium, Septoria, Cercospora, Alternaria, Pyricularia and in particular Pseudocercosporella herpotrichoides); oomycetes (e.g.
Phytophthora, Peronospora, Bremia, Pythium, Plasmopara). [00017] More specifically, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.541" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include, but are not limited to, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.250" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:722" name="diazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:636035" relevant="false" type="CLASS">diazole</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.254" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:723" name="triazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38597" relevant="false" type="CLASS">triazole</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.591" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1110" name="phenylpyrrole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:673027" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phenylpyrrole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.428" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2105" name="strobilurin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:631631" relevant="false">strobilurin</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.273" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:726" name="carboxamide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23004" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carboxamide</ne>, carboxanilide, especially ortho-substituted carboxanilide, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.574" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1108" name="carbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:13941" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamate</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.585" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1109" name="anilinopyrimidine" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:479868" relevant="false" type="CLASS">anilinopyrimidine</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.165" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1828" name="phenoxyquinoline" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:968251" relevant="false">phenoxyquinoline</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.425" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2104" name="benzimidazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36622" relevant="false">benzimidazole</ne>, systemic and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.175" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:705" name="phenylamide fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:325267" relevant="false">phenylamide fungicides</ne>. More particularly, the present invention includes the use of systemic, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.429" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2105" name="strobilurin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:631631" relevant="false">strobilurin</ne>, and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.500" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:711" name="phenylpyrrole type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:967024" relevant="false">phenylpyrrole type fungicides</ne>. Even more particularly, the present invention includes the use of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.501" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:711" name="phenylpyrrole type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:967024" relevant="false">phenylpyrrole type fungicides</ne>. [00018] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.177" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:706" name="Diazole fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:656179" relevant="false">Diazole fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include imidazoles and pyrazoles. Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.178" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:706" name="Diazole fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:656179" relevant="false">diazole fungicides</ne> that are useful include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.38" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1808" name="imazalil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:210229" relevant="false">imazalil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.172" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1830" name="oxpoconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:638152" relevant="false">oxpoconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.173" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1831" name="pefurazoate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:198091" relevant="false">pefurazoate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.174" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1832" name="prochloraz" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:110125" relevant="false">prochloraz</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.175" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1833" name="trifulmizole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:528478" relevant="false">trifulmizole</ne>. Mixtures of such <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.179" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:707" name="diazoles" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23677" relevant="false" type="CLASS">diazoles</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00019] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.180" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:708" name="triazole fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:771042" relevant="false">triazole fungicides</ne> that are preferred for use in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.176" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1834" name="amitrol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:125241" relevant="false">amitrol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.177" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1835" name="azaconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:324589" relevant="false">azaconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.178" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1836" name="bitertanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:737283" relevant="false">bitertanol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.179" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1837" name="bromuconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:979992" relevant="false">bromuconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.180" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1838" name="climbazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:921756" relevant="false">climbazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.181" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5991" name="clotrimazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:3764" relevant="false">clotrimazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.182" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1839" name="cyproconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:60590" relevant="false">cyproconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.183" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1840" name="diclobutrazol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:877671" relevant="false">diclobutrazol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.184" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1841" name="difenoconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:479267" relevant="false">difenoconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.185" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1842" name="diniconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:951232" relevant="false">diniconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.422" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2101" name="diniconazole-M" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:812635" relevant="false">diniconazole-M</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.187" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1843" name="epoxiconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:401995" relevant="false">epoxiconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.188" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1844" name="etaconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:234324" relevant="false">etaconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.189" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1845" name="fenbuconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:728623" relevant="false">fenbuconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.190" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1846" name="fluquinconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:687254" relevant="false">fluquinconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.191" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1847" name="fluotrimazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:358105" relevant="false">fluotrimazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.192" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1848" name="flusilazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:934212" relevant="false">flusilazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.193" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1849" name="flutriafol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:570349" relevant="false">flutriafol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.194" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1850" name="furconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:520302" relevant="false">furconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.230" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1885" name="furconazole-cis" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:229834" relevant="false">furconazole-cis</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.196" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1851" name="hexaconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:212449" relevant="false">hexaconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.198" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1853" name="imibenconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:237268" relevant="false">imibenconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.199" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1854" name="ipconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:537802" relevant="false">ipconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.200" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1855" name="metconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:577723" relevant="false">metconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.29" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1803" name="myclobutanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:484133" relevant="false">myclobutanil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.201" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1856" name="paclobutrazol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:2640" relevant="false">paclobutrazol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.197" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1852" name="penconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:297614" relevant="false">penconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.27" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1802" name="propiconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:132189" relevant="false">propiconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.204" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1859" name="quinconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:312257" relevant="false">quinconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.202" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1857" name="simeconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:262707" relevant="false">simeconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.40" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1809" name="tebuconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:689052" relevant="false">tebuconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.203" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1858" name="tetraconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:24103" relevant="false">tetraconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.205" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1860" name="triadimefon" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:243175" relevant="false">triadimefon</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.51" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1815" name="triadimenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:583663" relevant="false">triadimenol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.206" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1861" name="triazbutil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:500432" relevant="false">triazbutil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.207" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1862" name="triticonazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:769177" relevant="false">triticonazole</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.208" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1863" name="l-(4-fluorophenyl)-2-(lH-l,2,4-triazole-l- yl)ethanone" comment="1-(4-fluorophenyl)-2-(1H-1,2,4-triazole-1- yl)ethanone" chebi-id="WO2007005470:178923" relevant="false">l-(4-fluorophenyl)-2-(lH-l,2,4-triazole-l- yl)ethanone</ne>. Mixtures of such <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.181" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:709" name="triazoles" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35727" relevant="false" type="CLASS">triazoles</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00020] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.182" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:710" name="strobilurin-type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:954081" relevant="false">strobilurin-type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.22" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1800" name="azoxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:335764" relevant="false">azoxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.209" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1864" name="dimoxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:594696" relevant="false">dimoxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.210" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1865" name="famoxadone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:829101" relevant="false">famoxadone</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.211" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1866" name="fluoxastrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:486066" relevant="false">fluoxastrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.212" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1867" name="kresoxim-methyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:856086" relevant="false">kresoxim-methyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.213" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1868" name="metominostrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:670748" relevant="false">metominostrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.214" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1869" name="picoxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:383199" relevant="false">picoxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.215" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1870" name="pyraclostrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:42015" relevant="false">pyraclostrobin</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.25" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1801" name="trifloxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:85210" relevant="false">trifloxystrobin</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.531" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:943" name="strobilurin type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:624840" relevant="false">strobilurin type fungicides</ne> can also be used. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.532" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:944" name="strobilurin-type fungicidies" comment="strobilurin-type fungicides" chebi-id="WO2007005470:134209" relevant="false">strobilurin-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00021] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.183" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:711" name="phenylpyrrole type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:967024" relevant="false">phenylpyrrole type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.2" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.216" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1871" name="fenpiclonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:835705" relevant="false">fenpiclonil</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.499" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:942" name="phenylpyrrole-type fungicidies" comment="phenylpyrrole-type fungicides" chebi-id="WO2007005470:250018" relevant="false">phenylpyrrole-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00022] Examples of amide and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.184" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:712" name="carboxamide type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:711973" relevant="false">carboxamide type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.217" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1872" name="boscalide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:529054" relevant="false">boscalide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.34" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1806" name="carboxin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:353516" relevant="false">carboxin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.218" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1873" name="fenfuram" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:823893" relevant="false">fenfuram</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.219" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1874" name="flutolanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:706700" relevant="false">flutolanil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.220" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1875" name="furametpyr" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:739793" relevant="false">furametpyr</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.221" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1876" name="mepronil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:844051" relevant="false">mepronil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.36" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1807" name="oxycarboxin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:102358" relevant="false">oxycarboxin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.222" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1877" name="mandipropamid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:305149" relevant="false">mandipropamid</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.223" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1878" name="thifluzamide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:662695" relevant="false">thifluzamide</ne>.
Mixtures of amide and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.185" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:713" name="carboxamide-type fungicidies" comment="carboxamide-type fungicides" chebi-id="WO2007005470:605679" relevant="false">carboxamide-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00023] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.495" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:939" name="carboxanilide type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:862313" relevant="false">carboxanilide type fungicides</ne> include, especially, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.186" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:714" name="ortho- substiruted carboxanilide type fungicides" comment="ortho- substituted carboxanilide type fungicides" chebi-id="WO2007005470:815056" relevant="false">ortho- substiruted carboxanilide type fungicides</ne>. <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.554" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">Fungicides</ne> in this class include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.231" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1886" name="3 -difluoromethyl-1 -methyl- lH-pyrazole-4-carboxylic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:231382" relevant="false">3 -difluoromethyl-1 -methyl- lH-pyrazole-4-carboxylic acid</ne> <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.232" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1887" name="(2- bicyclopropyl-2-yl-phenyl)-amide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:596436" relevant="false">(2- bicyclopropyl-2-yl-phenyl)-amide</ne> and the isomers thereof; and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.233" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1888" name="3 -difluoromethyl-1 - methyl- 1 H-pyrazole-4-carboxylic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:345824" relevant="false">3 -difluoromethyl-1 - methyl- 1 H-pyrazole-4-carboxylic acid</ne> <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.234" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1889" name="[9-isopropyp- 1 ,2,3,4-tetrahaydro- 1 ,4-methano- naphthalen-5-yl]-amide" comment="[9-isopropyl- 1,2,3,4-tetrahydro- 1 ,4-methano-naphthalen-5-yl]-amide" chebi-id="WO2007005470:161516" relevant="false">[9-isopropyp- 1 ,2,3,4-tetrahaydro- 1 ,4-methano- naphthalen-5-yl]-amide</ne>, and the isomers thereof. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.497" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:940" name="carboxanilide-type fungicidies" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:217018" relevant="false">carboxanilide-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00024] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.498" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:941" name="carbamate type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:592195" relevant="false">carbamate type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.235" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1890" name="propamacarb" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:923218" relevant="false">propamacarb</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.237" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1891" name="propamacarb hydrochloride" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:232755" relevant="false">propamacarb hydrochloride</ne>.
Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.187" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:715" name="carbamate-type fungicidies" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:500940" relevant="false">carbamate-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00025] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.533" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:945" name="anilinopyrimidine type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:617479" relevant="false">anilinopyrimidine type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.224" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1879" name="cyprodnil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:470993" relevant="false">cyprodnil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.225" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1880" name="mepanipyrim" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:402457" relevant="false">mepanipyrim</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.226" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1881" name="pyrimethanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:442379" relevant="false">pyrimethanil</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.534" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:946" name="anilinopyrimidine-type fungicidies" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:846801" relevant="false">anilinopyrimidine-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used. [00026] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.188" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:716" name="benzimidazole type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:44961" relevant="false">benzimidazole type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.227" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1882" name="benomyl" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:3015" relevant="false">benomyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.228" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1883" name="carbendazim" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:954149" relevant="false">carbendazim</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.229" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1884" name="fuberidazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:446712" relevant="false">fuberidazole</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.47" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1813" name="thiabendazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:45979" relevant="false">thiabendazole</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.535" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:947" name="benzimidazole-type fungicidies" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:720797" relevant="false">benzimidazole-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used. [00027] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.189" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:717" name="systemic type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:6568" relevant="false">systemic type fungicides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.20" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1799" name="mefenoxam" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:287128" relevant="false">mefenoxam</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.238" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1892" name="metalaxyl-M" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:39263" relevant="false">metalaxyl-M</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.49" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1814" name="thiophanate-methyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:513889" relevant="false">thiophanate-methyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.239" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1893" name="benalaxyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:379488" relevant="false">benalaxyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.240" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1894" name="cymoxanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:837252" relevant="false">cymoxanil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.241" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1895" name="cyprofuram" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:579151" relevant="false">cyprofuram</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.242" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1896" name="furalaxyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:926003" relevant="false">furalaxyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.243" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1897" name="ofurace" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:844971" relevant="false">ofurace</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.244" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1898" name="oxadixyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:893686" relevant="false">oxadixyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.245" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1899" name="fosetyl-aluminium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:51844" relevant="false">fosetyl-aluminium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.246" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1900" name="phosphorous acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36361" relevant="false">phosphorous acid</ne> and its salts. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.536" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:948" name="systemic-type fungicidies" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:442892" relevant="false">systemic-type fungicidies</ne> can also be used.
</P>
<P>[00028] Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.559" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> are also contemplated. For example, and not for limitation, mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.190" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:717" name="systemic type fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:6568" relevant="false">systemic type fungicides</ne> in combination with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.426" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2104" name="benzimidazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36622" relevant="false">benzimidazole</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.588" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1109" name="anilinopyrimidine" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:479868" relevant="false" type="CLASS">anilinopyrimidine</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.577" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1108" name="carbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:13941" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamate</ne>-, carboxanilide-, amide- and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.276" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:726" name="carboxamide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23004" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carboxamide</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.596" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1110" name="phenylpyrrole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:673027" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phenylpyrrole</ne>-, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.430" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2105" name="strobilurin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:631631" relevant="false">strobilurin</ne>-, or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.256" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:723" name="triazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38597" relevant="false" type="CLASS">triazole</ne>-type <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.561" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> are contemplated by the present invention.
</P>
<P>[00029] Preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.562" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> include <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.248" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1901" name="metalaxyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:312628" relevant="false">metalaxyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.3" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.23" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1800" name="azoxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:335764" relevant="false">azoxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.30" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1803" name="myclobutanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:484133" relevant="false">myclobutanil</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.18" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1798" name="difenconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:565941" relevant="false">difenconazole</ne>. Particularly preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.563" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne> include <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.4" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00030] The fast-drying liquid compositions of the present invention comprise a fungicidally effective amount of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.11" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne>. More particularly, the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.12" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is present in an amount from between about 1 % to about 40% by weight of the total composition. Preferably, the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.13" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is present in an amount from about 5% to about 30% by weight; about 5% to about 25%; about 5% to about 20%; about 5% to about 15%; about 5% to about 10% by weight. More preferably, the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.14" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is present in an amount from about 6 % to about 8 % by weight.
</P>
<P>[00031] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.422" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">Insecticides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include any agent useful for the prevention or treatment of damage caused by insect pests. <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.423" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">Insecticides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include those classified as <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.39" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:651" name="neonicotinoids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:308348" relevant="false">neonicotinoids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.37" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:650" name="pyrethroids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:541709" relevant="false" type="CLASS">pyrethroids</ne>, phosphorus compounds, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.41" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:206" name="carbamates" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23003" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamates</ne> and others. [00032] Examples of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.378" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:921" name="neonicotinoid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:651594" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticides</ne> that are useful in the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.53" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6033" name="acetamiprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39163" relevant="false">acetamiprid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.55" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4173" name="clothianidin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39178" relevant="false">clothianidin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.57" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4176" name="dinotefuran" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39183" relevant="false">dinotefuran</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.59" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.65" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6037" name="nitenpyram" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39171" relevant="false">nitenpyram</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.67" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6042" name="thiacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39175" relevant="false">thiacloprid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.70" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>. Preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.379" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:921" name="neonicotinoid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:651594" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticides</ne> include <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.249" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1902" name="clothianidil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:909489" relevant="false">clothianidil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.60" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.71" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.380" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:921" name="neonicotinoid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:651594" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticides</ne> are also contemplated.
Particularly preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.381" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:921" name="neonicotinoid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:651594" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticides</ne> include <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.72" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.61" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne>. [00033] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.295" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:729" name="pyrethroid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26413" relevant="false">Pyrethroid insecticides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.250" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1903" name="alpha-cypermethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39331" relevant="false">alpha-cypermethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.251" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1904" name="beta-cyfluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39314" relevant="false">beta-cyfluthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.252" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1905" name="beta- cypermethrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:360317" relevant="false">beta- cypermethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.253" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5122" name="bifenthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:3093" relevant="false">bifenthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.254" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1906" name="bioallethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34572" relevant="false">bioallethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.255" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5124" name="bioresmethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39280" relevant="false">bioresmethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.256" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5132" name="cycloprothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39283" relevant="false">cycloprothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.258" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5134" name="cyfluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:4034" relevant="false">cyfluthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.269" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5149" name="cyhalothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:4035" relevant="false">cyhalothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.268" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1908" name="cyperaiethrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:509992" relevant="false">cyperaiethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.267" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5125" name="cyphenothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:31450" relevant="false">cyphenothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.266" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5156" name="deltamethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:4388" relevant="false">deltamethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.265" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1907" name="empenthrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:708382" relevant="false">empenthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.264" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:2860" name="esfenvalerate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39346" relevant="false">esfenvalerate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.263" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5158" name="fenpropathrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39353" relevant="false">fenpropathrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.262" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:2859" name="fenvalerate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5014" relevant="false">fenvalerate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.261" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:2862" name="flucythrinate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34763" relevant="false">flucythrinate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.260" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6625" name="flumethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39361" relevant="false">flumethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.259" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5150" name="gamma-cyhalothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39323" relevant="false">gamma-cyhalothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.276" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1912" name="imiprothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39389" relevant="false">imiprothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.273" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1909" name="lambda-cyhalothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39325" relevant="false">lambda-cyhalothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.275" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1911" name="methothrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:168550" relevant="false">methothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.277" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1913" name="metofluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:465240" relevant="false">metofluthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.278" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5146" name="permethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34911" relevant="false">permethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.279" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5109" name="phenothrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34916" relevant="false">phenothrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.280" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5129" name="prallethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39391" relevant="false">prallethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.281" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5123" name="resmethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:8811" relevant="false">resmethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.282" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3868" name="tau-fluvalinate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39367" relevant="false">tau-fluvalinate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.283" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5152" name="tefluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:9430" relevant="false">tefluthrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.285" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4552" name="tetramethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39397" relevant="false">tetramethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.286" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1914" name="theta-cypermethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39333" relevant="false">theta-cypermethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.287" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5160" name="tralomethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39400" relevant="false">tralomethrin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.288" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5147" name="transfluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32253" relevant="false">transfluthrin</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.289" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1915" name="zeta-cypermethrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39334" relevant="false">zeta-cypermethrin</ne>. Prefe[pi]"ed <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.387" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:729" name="pyrethroid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26413" relevant="false">pyrethroid insecticides</ne> include <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.284" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5152" name="tefluthrin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:9430" relevant="false">tefluthrin</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.274" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1910" name="lambda cyhalothrin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:774404" relevant="false">lambda cyhalothrin</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.388" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:729" name="pyrethroid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26413" relevant="false">pyrethroid insecticides</ne> are also contemplated.
</P>
<P>[00034] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.296" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:730" name="phosphorus insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:126706" relevant="false">Phosphorus insecticides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.290" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4500" name="phorate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38764" relevant="false">phorate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.291" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5385" name="phosalone" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:8121" relevant="false">phosalone</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.292" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4502" name="phosmet" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38786" relevant="false">phosmet</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.293" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4432" name="phosphamidon" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38832" relevant="false">phosphamidon</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.294" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4504" name="phoxim" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38812" relevant="false">phoxim</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.383" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:730" name="phosphorus insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:126706" relevant="false">phosphorus insecticides</ne> are also contemplated. [00035] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.297" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:731" name="carbamate insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38461" relevant="false">Carbamate insecticides</ne> useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.295" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3822" name="pirimicarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:8248" relevant="false">pirimicarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.296" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4292" name="benfuracarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:3014" relevant="false">benfuracarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.297" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3797" name="carbaryl" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:3390" relevant="false">carbaryl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.298" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4296" name="carbofuran" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34611" relevant="false">carbofuran</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.299" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4299" name="carbosulfan" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38476" relevant="false">carbosulfan</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.300" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3798" name="ethiofencarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38483" relevant="false">ethiofencarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.301" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3800" name="fenobucarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34304" relevant="false">fenobucarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.303" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3802" name="formetanate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38491" relevant="false">formetanate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.304" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4297" name="furathiocarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38504" relevant="false">furathiocarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.305" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3804" name="isoprocarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38505" relevant="false">isoprocarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.306" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3806" name="methiocarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38508" relevant="false">methiocarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.307" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3808" name="methomyl" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:6835" relevant="false">methomyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.302" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3811" name="metolcarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38537" relevant="false">metolcarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.308" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3813" name="oxamyl" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38539" relevant="false">oxamyl</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.309" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3814" name="propoxur" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:34938" relevant="false">propoxur</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.310" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4302" name="trimethacarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38569" relevant="false">trimethacarb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.311" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1916" name="3,5-xylyl methylcarbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38571" relevant="false">3,5-xylyl methylcarbamate</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.312" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:3818" name="xylylcarb" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35048" relevant="false">xylylcarb</ne>. Mixtures of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.391" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:731" name="carbamate insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38461" relevant="false">carbamate insecticides</ne> are also contemplated.
</P>
<P>[00036] Mixtures of the classes of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.435" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne> are also contemplated. For example, and not for limititation, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.392" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:731" name="carbamate insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38461" relevant="false">carbamate insecticides</ne> may be mixed with pyrethroid, neonicotinoid, or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.384" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:730" name="phosphorus insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:126706" relevant="false">phosphorus insecticides</ne>; <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.389" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:729" name="pyrethroid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26413" relevant="false">pyrethroid insecticides</ne> may be mixed with <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.581" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1108" name="carbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:13941" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamate</ne>, neonicotinoid, or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.385" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:730" name="phosphorus insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:126706" relevant="false">phosphorus insecticides</ne>; <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.382" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:921" name="neonicotinoid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:651594" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticides</ne> may be mixed with pyrethroid, phosphorus or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.393" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:731" name="carbamate insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38461" relevant="false">carbamate insecticides</ne>; <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.386" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:730" name="phosphorus insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:126706" relevant="false">phosphorus insecticides</ne> may be mixed with neonicotinoid, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.583" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1108" name="carbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:13941" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamate</ne>, or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.390" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:729" name="pyrethroid insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26413" relevant="false">pyrethroid insecticides</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00037] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.444" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">Insecticides</ne> are present in the fast-drying composition of the present invention in amounts ranging from about 5 % to about 50 % by weight. Preferably, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.445" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne> are present in amounts ranging from about 20 % to about 45 % by weight; about 20 % to about 40 %; about 20 % to about 35 %.
More preferably, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.446" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne> are present in amounts from about 25 % to about 30 % by weight. [00038] Wetting agents useful in the fast-drying composition of the present invention include, without limitation, one or more <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.333" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:382" name="anionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:473584" relevant="false">anionic surfactants</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.337" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:911" name="nonionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38828" relevant="false">nonionic surfactants</ne> and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.339" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:912" name="zwitterionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:453533" relevant="false">zwitterionic surfactants</ne>. [00039] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.334" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:382" name="anionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:473584" relevant="false">Anionic surfactants</ne> include, without limitation, one or more of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.53" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:657" name="alcohol sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:668813" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.43" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:652" name="alcohol ether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:117629" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol ether sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.45" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:653" name="alkylaryl ether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:983252" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylaryl ether sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.47" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:654" name="alkylaryl sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:459993" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylaryl sulfonates</ne> such as <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.49" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:655" name="alkylbenzene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:612831" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylbenzene sulfonates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.51" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:656" name="alkylnaphthalene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:623570" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylnaphthalene sulfonates</ne> and salts thereof, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.57" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:305" name="alkyl sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:365727" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl sulfonates</ne>, mono- or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.320" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:746" name="di-phosphate esters of polyalkoxylated alkyl alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:948533" relevant="false">di-phosphate esters of polyalkoxylated alkyl alcohols</ne> or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.375" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:745" name="alkylphenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:779658" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylphenols</ne> , mono- or di-sulfosuccinate esters of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.566" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1105" name="C]2-CiS alkanols" comment="C12-C15 alkanols" chebi-id="WO2007005470:621854" relevant="false" type="CLASS">C]2-CiS alkanols</ne> or polyalkoxylated <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.567" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1106" name="Ci2-C]5 alkanols" comment="C12-C15 alkanols" chebi-id="WO2007005470:994472" relevant="false" type="CLASS">Ci2-C]5 alkanols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.78" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:661" name="alcohol ether carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:349356" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol ether carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.80" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:662" name="phenolic ether carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:195167" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phenolic ether carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.82" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:663" name="polybasic acid esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:466598" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polybasic acid esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.84" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:664" name="ethoxylated polyoxyalkylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:605365" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated polyoxyalkylene glycols</ne> consisting of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.87" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:666" name="oxybutylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:16686" relevant="false" type="CLASS">oxybutylene</ne> or the residue of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.84" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:239" name="tetrahydrofuran" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26911" relevant="false">tetrahydrofuran</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.374" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:920" name="sulfoalkylamides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:866904" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfoalkylamides</ne> and salts thereof such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.86" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1816" name="N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:33515" relevant="false">N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate</ne> Na salt, polyoxyalkylene <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.89" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:667" name="alkylphenol carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:355867" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylphenol carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.97" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:668" name="polyoxyalkylene alcohol carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:621589" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyoxyalkylene alcohol carboxylates</ne> <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.99" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:669" name="alkyl polyglycoside" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:353651" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl polyglycoside</ne>/<ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.101" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:670" name="alkenylsuccinicanhydride" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:132374" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkenyl succinic anhydride</ne> condensation products, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.103" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:671" name="alkyl ester sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:429236" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl ester sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.105" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:672" name="napthalene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:301225" relevant="false" type="CLASS">napthalene sulfonates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.107" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:673" name="naphthalene formaldehyde" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:818176" relevant="false" type="CLASS">naphthalene formaldehyde</ne> condensates, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.109" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:674" name="alkyl sulfonamides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:206432" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl sulfonamides</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.111" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:675" name="sulfonated aliphatic polyesters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:619059" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfonated aliphatic polyesters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.113" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:676" name="sulfate esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:763783" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfate esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.115" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:677" name="styrylphenyl alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:346518" relevant="false" type="CLASS">styrylphenyl alkoxylates</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.119" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:678" name="sulfonate esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:131495" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfonate esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.116" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:677" name="styrylphenyl alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:346518" relevant="false" type="CLASS">styrylphenyl alkoxylates</ne> and their corresponding <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.90" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.104" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7084" name="potassium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26216" relevant="false">potassium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.108" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.114" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7091" name="magnesium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25107" relevant="false">magnesium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.118" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7669" name="zinc" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27363" relevant="false">zinc</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.120" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4221" name="ammonium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28938" relevant="false">ammonium</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.121" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:69" name="alkylammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:382183" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylammonium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.125" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1817" name="diethanolammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:317292" relevant="false">diethanolammonium</ne>, or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.423" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2102" name="triethanolammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:527907" relevant="false">triethanolammonium</ne> salts, salts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.1" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:166" name="ligninsulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:636370" relevant="false">ligninsulfonic acid</ne> such as the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.91" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.105" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7084" name="potassium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26216" relevant="false">potassium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.115" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7091" name="magnesium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25107" relevant="false">magnesium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.109" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne> or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.121" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4221" name="ammonium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28938" relevant="false">ammonium</ne> salt, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.123" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:679" name="polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:649009" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether sulfates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.125" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:680" name="polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether phosphates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:488366" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether phosphates</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.127" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:681" name="sulfated alkyl phenol ethoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:506126" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfated alkyl phenol ethoxylates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.129" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:682" name="phosphated alkyl phenol ethoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:588481" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phosphated alkyl phenol ethoxylates</ne>. Preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.335" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:382" name="anionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:473584" relevant="false">anionic surfactants</ne> include, without limitation, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.87" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1816" name="N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:33515" relevant="false">N-methyl- N- oleoyltaurate</ne> Na salt; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.130" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1820" name="tristyrylphenol sulphate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:281715" relevant="false">tristyrylphenol sulphate</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.3" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:167" name="ethoxylated lignin sulfonate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:866949" relevant="false">ethoxylated lignin sulfonate</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.132" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1821" name="nonylphenol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:688325" relevant="false">nonylphenol phosphate ester</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.110" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne> <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.131" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:683" name="alkylbenzene sulfonate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:900915" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylbenzene sulfonate</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.133" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1821" name="nonylphenol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:688325" relevant="false">nonylphenol phosphate ester</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.136" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1822" name="tridecylalcohol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:112574" relevant="false">tridecylalcohol phosphate ester</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.5" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:168" name="lignosulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:934977" relevant="false">lignosulfonic acid</ne> Na salt;
and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.138" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1823" name="naphthalenesulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:284489" relevant="false">naphthalenesulfonic acid</ne> Na salt. [00040] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.452" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:213" name="Non-ionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:968638" relevant="false">Non-ionic surfactants</ne> useful as wetting agents in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, one or more <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.133" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:684" name="polyarylphenol polyethoxy ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:784561" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyethoxy ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.135" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:685" name="polyalkylphenol polyethoxy ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:897843" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkylphenol polyethoxy ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.137" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:686" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of saturated fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:684782" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of saturated fatty acids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.139" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:687" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of unsaturated fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:882968" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of unsaturated fatty acids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.141" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:688" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of aliphatic alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:803587" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of aliphatic alcohols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.143" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:689" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of cycloaliphatic alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:48637" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of cycloaliphatic alcohols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.145" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:690" name="fatty acid esters of polyoxyethylene sorbitan" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:471917" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty acid esters of polyoxyethylene sorbitan</ne>, alkoxylated vegetable oils, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.147" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:691" name="alkoxylated acetylenic diols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:141280" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkoxylated acetylenic diols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.149" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:692" name="polyalkoxylated alkylphenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:46651" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxylated alkylphenols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.151" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:693" name="fatty acid alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:371342" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty acid alkoxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.153" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:694" name="sorbitan alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:434316" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitan alkoxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.155" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:695" name="sorbitol esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:457693" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitol esters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.163" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:699" name="C8-C22 alkyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:742655" relevant="false" type="CLASS">C8-C22 alkyl</ne> or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.161" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:698" name="alkenyl polyglycosides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:411570" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkenyl polyglycosides</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.157" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:696" name="polyalkoxy styrylaryl ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:536319" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxy styrylaryl ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.159" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:697" name="alkylamine oxides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:179541" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylamine oxides</ne>, block copolymer ethers, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.317" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:744" name="polyalkoxylated fatty glyceride" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:722942" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxylated fatty glyceride</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.165" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:700" name="polyalkylene glycol ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:362748" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkylene glycol ethers</ne>, linear aliphatic or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.171" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:703" name="aromatic polyesters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:389618" relevant="false" type="CLASS">aromatic polyesters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.173" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:704" name="organo silicones" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:969023" relevant="false" type="CLASS">organo silicones</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.167" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:701" name="polyaryl phenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:564204" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyaryl phenols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.169" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:702" name="sorbitol ester alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:880245" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitol ester alkoxylates</ne>, and mono- and diesters of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.327" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4751" name="ethylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30742" relevant="false">ethylene glycol</ne> and mixtures thereof. Preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.453" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:213" name="Non-ionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:968638" relevant="false">non-ionic surfactants</ne> include one or more <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.298" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:732" name="ethoxylated fatty alcohol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:872185" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated fatty alcohol</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.313" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1917" name="ethoxylated tristyryl phenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:561493" relevant="false">ethoxylated tristyryl phenol</ne>; <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.315" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:743" name="ethoxylated lauryl alcohol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:351302" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated lauryl alcohol</ne>; ethoxylated castor oil; <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.312" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:741" name="ethoxylated nonylphenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:305485" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated nonylphenol</ne>. [00041] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.340" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:912" name="zwitterionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:453533" relevant="false">Zwitterionic surfactants</ne> useful as wetting agents in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, alkanol amides OfC8-C]8 <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.457" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:935" name="fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35366" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty acids</ne> and C8-C is <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.461" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:936" name="fatty amine polyalkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:463782" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty amine polyalkoxylates</ne>, Cm-Cis <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.394" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:922" name="alkyldimethylbenzylammonium chlorides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:240898" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyldimethylbenzylammonium chlorides</ne>, coconut <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.568" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1107" name="alkyldim ethyl aminoacetic acids" comment="alkyldimethylaminoacetic acids" chebi-id="WO2007005470:61446" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyldim ethyl aminoacetic acids</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.570" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:36" name="phosphate esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:5553" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phosphate esters</ne> Of C8-J 8 <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.462" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:936" name="fatty amine polyalkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:463782" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty amine polyalkoxylates</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00042] <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.397" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:923" name="Dispersing agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:904599" relevant="false">Dispersing agents</ne>, or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.396" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:422" name="emulsifying agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:590495" relevant="false">emulsifying agents</ne>, useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, alkyleneoxide random and block copolymers such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.396" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.404" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2013" name="propyleneoxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38685" relevant="false">propylene oxide</ne> block copolymers (EO/PO block copolymers) including both EO-PO-EO and PO-EO-PO block copolymers; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.397" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.408" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2014" name="butyleneoxide" comment="butylene oxide" chebi-id="WO2007005470:849714" relevant="false">butylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers; C2-6 alkyl adducts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.398" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.405" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2013" name="propyleneoxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38685" relevant="false">propylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers; C2-6 alkyl adducts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.399" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.409" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2014" name="butyleneoxide" comment="butylene oxide" chebi-id="WO2007005470:849714" relevant="false">butylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.26" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:54" name="polyoxyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:966514" relevant="false">polyoxyethylene</ne>- <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.28" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:55" name="polyoxypropylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:954458" relevant="false">polyoxypropylene</ne> monoalkylethers such as methyl ether, ethyl ether, propyl ether, butyl ether or mixtures thereof; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.412" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1406" name="vinylacetate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:56014" relevant="false">vinylacetate</ne>/<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.414" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2015" name="vinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:892223" relevant="false">vinylpyrrolidone</ne> copolymers; alkylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.415" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2015" name="vinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:892223" relevant="false">vinylpyrrolidone</ne> copolymers; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.17" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:71" name="polyvinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:426640" relevant="false">polyvinylpyrrolidone</ne>; and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.15" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:170" name="polyalkyleneglycol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:961991" relevant="false">polyalkyleneglycol</ne> including the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.19" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:171" name="polypropylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:416541" relevant="false">polypropylene glycols</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.21" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:73" name="polyethylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46793" relevant="false">polyethylene glycols</ne>. Preferred <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.398" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:923" name="Dispersing agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:904599" relevant="false">dispersing agents</ne> include copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.146" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO and acrylic graft copolymer in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.376" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.418" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2016" name="propyleneglycole" comment="propylene glycol" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propyleneglycole</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00043] Drying agents useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, one or more <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.617" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:80" name="metal oxides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:600270" relevant="false" type="CLASS">metal oxides</ne> such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.9" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silicon dioxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.316" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7651" name="titanium dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32234" relevant="false">titanium dioxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.319" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1919" name="aluminum oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30187" relevant="false">aluminum oxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.321" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:235" name="zirconium oxide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:292068" relevant="false">zirconium oxide</ne> and fumed <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.359" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1434" name="silica" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silica</ne>; and polymer wax, including oxidized and non-oxidized <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.31" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> wax, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.32" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> copolymer wax, Montan wax, and polyether wax. Preferred drying agents are <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.10" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silicon dioxide</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.33" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> wax.
</P>
<P>[00044] Suberization agents useful in the composition of the present invention include, without limitation, one or more <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.40" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:258" name="starches" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:436288" relevant="false">starches</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.370" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:917" name="alkyl triols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:301710" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl triols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.371" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:918" name="alkyl diols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:820183" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl diols</ne>, phenolic polymers, aliphatic polymers, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.372" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:2" name="carboxylic acids" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33575" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carboxylic acids</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.373" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:919" name="dicarboxylic acids" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35692" relevant="false" type="CLASS">dicarboxylic acids</ne>. Specific suberization agents include corn or potato <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.42" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.142" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1824" name="propane- 1 , 2, 3-triol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:142" relevant="false">propane- 1,2,3-triol</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.323" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:680" name="octanoic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28837" relevant="false">octanoic acid</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00045] The composition may further comprise formulation agents known in the art of <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.330" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:910" name="pesticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticides</ne>. Such agents include, but are not limited to, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.399" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:924" name="antifreeze agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:122297" relevant="false">antifreeze agents</ne> (such as but not limited to <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.326" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:875" name="glycerine" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:17754" relevant="false">glycerine</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.328" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4751" name="ethylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30742" relevant="false">ethylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.330" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:25" name="propylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.335" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1921" name="monopropylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:482879" relevant="false">monopropylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.336" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1922" name="hexylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:73946" relevant="false">hexylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.324" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1920" name="1 -methoxy-2-propanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:219141" relevant="false">1 -methoxy-2-propanol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.325" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4785" name="cyclohexanol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:18099" relevant="false">cyclohexanol</ne>), <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.612" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1111" name="buffering agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:701115" relevant="false">buffering agents</ne> (such as but not limited to <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.337" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7174" name="sodium hydroxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32145" relevant="false">sodium hydroxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.338" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1185" name="phosphoric acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26078" relevant="false">phosphoric acid</ne>), <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.415" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:870" name="biocides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:799811" relevant="false">biocides</ne> (such as but not limited to <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.343" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1923" name="l,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:410349" relevant="false">l,2-benzisothiazolin-3-one</ne>), <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.614" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1112" name="preserving agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:596244" relevant="false">preserving agents</ne> (such as but not limited to derivatives of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.344" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:811" name="benzoic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30746" relevant="false">benzoic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.345" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:726" name="sorbic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35962" relevant="false">sorbic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.346" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4560" name="formaldehyde" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16842" relevant="false">formaldehyde</ne>, a combination of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.347" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1924" name="methyl parahydroxybenzoate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:361834" relevant="false">methyl parahydroxybenzoate</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.348" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1925" name="propyl parahydroxybenzoate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:40059" relevant="false">propyl parahydroxybenzoate</ne>), <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.616" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1025" name="stabilizing agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:534687" relevant="false">stabilizing agents</ne> (such as but not limited to <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.605" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:500" name="acids" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:37527" relevant="false" type="CLASS">acids</ne>, preferably <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.598" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:370" name="organic acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:269854" relevant="false">organic acids</ne>, such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.349" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1926" name="dodecylbenzene sulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:12807" relevant="false">dodecylbenzene sulfonic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.350" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:445" name="acetic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15366" relevant="false">acetic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.351" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:475" name="propionic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30768" relevant="false">propionic acid</ne> or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.352" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1927" name="butyl hydroxyl toluene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:376949" relevant="false">butyl hydroxyl toluene</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.353" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1928" name="butyl hydroxyl anisole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:802223" relevant="false">butyl hydroxyl anisole</ne>), thickening agents (such as but not limited to <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.50" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:320" name="heteropolysaccharide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:334048" relevant="false">heteropolysaccharide</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.41" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:258" name="starches" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:436288" relevant="false">starches</ne>), <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.342" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:913" name="pigments" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26130" relevant="false">pigments</ne> and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.454" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:934" name="colorants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:775716" relevant="false">colorants</ne> (such as but not limited to <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.611" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:970" name="dyes" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:390589" relevant="false">dyes</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.317" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7651" name="titanium dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32234" relevant="false">titanium dioxide</ne>), and antifoaming agents (such as but not limited to those based on <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.49" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:259" name="silicone" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:48140" relevant="false">silicone</ne>, particularly <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.23" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:26" name="polydimethylsiloxane" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:48137" relevant="false">polydimethylsiloxane</ne>). Such additives are commercially available and known in the art.
</P>
<P>[00046] When a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.15" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.71" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> is incorporated into the formulation, the formulation may optionally comprise a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.472" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne>. The <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.473" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne> may be either <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.377" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> insoluble or slightly <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.378" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> soluble. <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.379" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">Water</ne> insoluble solvents include, but are not limited to, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.354" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1929" name="isobornyl acetate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:536966" relevant="false">isobornyl acetate</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.355" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1930" name="methyl oleate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27542" relevant="false">methyl oleate</ne>, aromatic solvents and mixtures thereof. Slightly <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.380" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> soluble solvents include, but are not limited to, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.356" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1931" name="2-hepatonone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:555677" relevant="false">2-hepatonone</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.357" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5317" name="acetophenone" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27632" relevant="false">acetophenone</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.365" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:632" name="alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30879" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.369" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:634" name="ketones" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24974" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ketones</ne>, and mixtures thereof.
</P>
<P>[00047] Preferred fast-drying liquid formulations comprise about 20% to about
</P>
<P>35% by weight <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.73" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> and about 5% to about 10% <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.5" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> and the following components, by weight: a. about 1 -5 % at least one wetting agent; b. about 2-8 % at least one dispersing agent; c. about 0.2-5.0 % at least one drying agent; d. about 0.05-8.0 % at least one suberization agent; e. about 12- 18% at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.408" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00048] More preferably, the fast-drying liquid formulations of the present invention comprise about 25% to about 30% <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.74" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> and about 6% to about 8% <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.6" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> and the following components, by weight: a. about 1-5% at least one wetting agent; b. about 2-8% at least one dispersing agent; c. about 0.2-3.0% at least one drying agent; d. about 0.05-8.0% at least one suberization agent; e. about 12-18% at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.409" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne>.
</P>
<P>[00049] The inventive compositions contain and/or may be applied together or sequentially with further active compounds. These further compounds can be <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.451" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:933" name="fertilizers" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33287" relevant="false">fertilizers</ne> or micronutrient donors or other preparations that influence plant growth. They can also be selective <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.419" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:928" name="herbicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24527" relevant="false" type="CLASS">herbicides</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.564" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:949" name="fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicides</ne>, other <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.447" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:929" name="insecticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticides</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.448" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:930" name="bactericides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33282" relevant="false">bactericides</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.449" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:931" name="insect growth regulators" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:475159" relevant="false">insect growth regulators</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.450" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:932" name="plant growth regulators" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26155" relevant="false">plant growth regulators</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.417" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:926" name="nematicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25491" relevant="false">nematicides</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.418" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:927" name="molluscicides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33904" relevant="false">molluscicides</ne> or mixtures of several of these preparations.
</P>
<P>[00050] The liquid compositions of the present invention are useful in a method for preventing pest infestation in useful crops comprising treating plant propagation material, including seeds, with a pesticidally effective amount of the fast-drying liquid compositions.
</P>
<P>[00051] Pests may include, without limitation, fungi, bacteria and insects. The composition of the present invention may be used to prevent infestation by fungi pathogens including Pythium, Tilletia, Gerlachia, Septoria, Ustilago, Fusarium, Rhizoctonia, Oomycetes such as Phytophthora, Plasmopara, Pseudoperonospora, Bremia and others, as well as against the Botrytis species, Pyrenophora, Monilinia and further representatives of the Ascomycetes, Deuteromycetes and Basidiomycetes classes.
</P>
<P>[00052] Bacteria prevented and/or treated by application of the composition of the present invention includes, without limitation, Erwinia, Cornybacterium, Enterobacter, Pectobacterium, Pantoea or Brenneria, Acinetobacter, Serratia, Lactobacillus, and Flavobacterhim.
</P>
<P>[00053] The aqueous compositions of the invention are formulated for protecting cultivated plants and their propagation materials. The inventive compositions are advantageously formulated for seed treatment applications against fungi and soil inhabiting insects that can damage the crop in the early stages of plant development. For example and not for limitation, the compositions can be formulated to target insects and representatives of the order Acarnia including: [00054] from the order Lepidoptera, for example, Acleris spp., Adoxophyes spp., Aegeria spp., Agrotis spp., Alabama argillaceae, Amylois spp., Anticarsia gemmatalis, Archips spp., Argyrotaenia spp., Autographa spp., Busseola fusca, Cadra cautella, Carposina nipponensis, Chilo spp., Choristoneura spp., Clysia ambiguella, Cnaphalocrocis spp., Cnephasia spp., Cochylis spp., Coleophora spp., Crocidolomia binotalis, Cryptophlebia leucotreta, Cydia spp., Diatraea spp., Diparopsis castanea, Earias spp., Ephestia spp., Eucosma spp., Eupoecilia ambiguella, Euproctis spp.,
Euxoa spp., Grapholita spp., Hedya nubiferana, Heliothis spp., Hellula undalis,
Hyphantria cunea, Keiferia lycopersicella, Leucoptera scitella, Lithocollethis spp.,
Lobesia botrana, Lymantria spp., Lyonetia spp., Malacosoma spp., Mamestra brassicae, Manduca sexta, Operophtera spp., Ostrinia nubilalis, Pammene spp.,
Pandemis spp., Panolis flammea, Pectinophora gossypiella, Phthorimaea operculella,
Pieris rapae, Pieris spp., Plutella xylostella, Prays spp., Sci[phi]ophaga spp., Sesamia spp., Sparganothis spp., Spodoptera spp., Synanthedon spp., Thaumetopoea spp.,
Tortrix spp., Trichoplusia ni and Yponomeuta spp.;
</P>
<P>[00055] from the order Coleoptera, for example, Agriotes spp., Anthonomus spp., Atomaria linearis, Chaetocnema tibialis, Cosmopolites spp., Curculio spp.,
Dermestes spp., Diabrotica spp., Epilachna spp., Eremnus spp., Leptinotarsa decemlineata, Lissorhoptrus spp., Melolontha spp., Orycaephilus spp., Otiorhynchus spp., Phlyctinus spp., Popillia spp., Psylliodes spp., Rhizopertha spp., Scarabeidae,
Sitophilus spp., Sitotroga spp., Tenebrio spp., Tribolium spp. and Trogoderma spp.;
</P>
<P>[00056] from the order Orthoptera, for example, Blatta spp., Blattella spp.,
Gryllotalpa spp., Leucophaea maderae, Locusta spp., eriplaneta spp. and Schistocerca spp.;
</P>
<P>[00057] from the order Isoptera, for example,Reticulitermes spp.;
</P>
<P>[00058] from the order Psocoptera, for example,Liposcelis spp.;
</P>
<P>[00059] from the order Anoplura, for example, Haematopinus spp.,
Linognathus spp., Pediculus spp., Pemphigus spp. and Phylloxera spp.;
</P>
<P>[00060] from the order Mallophaga, for example, Damalinea spp. and
Trichodectes spp.;
</P>
<P>[00061] from the order Thysanoptera, for example,
Frankliniella spp., Hercinothrips spp., Taeniothrips spp., Thrips palmi, Thrips tabaci and cirtothrips aurantii;
</P>
<P>[00062] from the order Heteroptera, for example, Cimex spp., Distantiella theobroma, Dysdercus spp., Euchistus spp., Eurygaster spp., Leptoeorisa spp., Nezara spp., Piesma spp., Rhodnius spp., Sahlbergella singularis, Scotinophara spp. and
Triatoma spp.;
</P>
<P>[00063] from the order Homoptera, for example, Aleurothrixus floccosus,
Aleyrodes brassicae, Aonidiella spp., Aphididae, Aphis spp., Aspidiotus spp., Bemisia tabaci, Ceroplaster spp., Chrysomphalus aonidium, Chrysomphalus dictyospermi, Coccus hesperidum, Empoasca spp., Eriosoma larigerum, Erythroneura spp., Gascardia spp., Laodelphax spp., Lecanium corni, Lepidosaphes spp., Macrosiphus spp., Myzus spp., Nephotettix spp., Nilaparvata spp., Paratoria spp., Pemphigus spp., Planococcus spp., Pseudaulacaspis spp., Pseudococcus spp., Psylla spp., Pulvinaria aethiopica, Quadraspidiotus spp., Rhopalosiphum spp., Saissetia spp., Scaphoideus spp., Schizaphis spp., Sitobion spp., Trialeurodes vaporariorum, Trioza erytreae and Unaspis citri;
</P>
<P>[00064] from the order Hymenoptera, for example, Acromyrmex, Atta spp.,
Cephus spp., Diprion spp., Diprionidae, Gilpinia polytoma, Hoplocampa spp., Lasius spp., Monomorium pharaonis, Neodiprion spp., Solenopsis spp. and Vespa spp.; [00065] from the order Diptera, for example, Aedes spp., Antherigona soccata,
Bibio hortulanus, Calliphora erythrocephala, Ceratitis spp., Chrysomyia spp., Culex spp., Cuterebra spp., Dacus spp., Drosophila melanogaster, Fannia spp., Gastrophilus spp., Glossina spp., Hypoderma spp., Hyppobosca spp., Liriomyza spp., Lucilia spp., Melanagromyza spp., Musca spp., Oestrus spp., Orseolia spp., Oscinella frit, Pegomyia hyoscyami, Phorbia spp., Rhagoletis pomonella, Sciara spp., Stomoxys spp., Tabanus spp., Tannia spp. and Tipula spp.;
</P>
<P>[00066] from the order Siphonaptera, for example, Ceratophyllus spp. and
Xenopsylla cheopis;
</P>
<P>[00067] and from the order Thysanura, for example, Lepisma saccharina; and crucifer flea beetles (Phyllotreta spp.), root maggots (Delia spp.), cabbage seedpod weevil (Ceutorhynchus spp.) and aphids.
</P>
<P>[00068] The term "plant propagation material" is used herein to refer to all the generative parts of the plant that can be used for the multiplication of the vegetative plant material such as cuttings and tubers (for example potatoes). There may be mentioned, for example and not for limitation, the seeds (in the strict sense), roots, fruits, tubers, bulbs, rhizomes, and parts of plants. Germinated plants and young plants, which are to be transplanted after germination or after emergence from the soil, may also be mentioned. These young plants may be coated before transplantation by a total or partial treatment by immersion or the like. In a specific embodiment, the method of the present invention has particular application for coating the plant propagation material of cultivated plants. Such plants are those plants that are cultivated by man, or from which is harvested parts or products that are used by man. Suitable cultivated plant propagation material includes, but is not limited to, seed selected from monocotyledonous, dicotyledonous, and multicotyledonous (gymnosperm) plants.
</P>
<P>[00069] Specifically, plant propagation material includes seeds and cuttings and other generative parts of plants including tubers (such as but not limited to potatoes, Jerusalam artichokes and yams), bulbs (such as but not limited to onion, hyacinth, squill, amaryllis, snowdrop, tulip, daffodil, narcissis, lily and orchid), root vegetables (such as but not limited to carrots, beets, arrowhead, arrowroot, cassavas, Chinese artichoke, globe artichoke, horseradish, parsnips, radishes, and the like), trees, shrubs, and other ornamentals, including roses.
</P>
<P>[00070] The liquid composition of the present invention may be used in a method for preventing pests, including fungi and insects, in cut seeds and propagation materials. For example and not for limitation, some planting regions cut seedling potatoes prior to planting, exposing the inner flesh of the seedling to the elements. Such exposure increases the risk of infection by fungi, bacteria, insects and other pests. The liquid composition of the present invention provides a barrier against these elements, preventing contamination of the seedling, thus resulting in reduced decay of the plant propagation materials.
</P>
<P>[00071] The fast-drying liquid compositions of the present invention are exemplified by the following non-limiting examples.
Example 1- Formulation
</P>
<P>[0078]
EMI16.1
</P>
<P>[00072] To a suitably sized vessel equipped with a Cowles mixer, charge the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.381" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and start agitation. Charge pre-heated (up to 50&lt;0&gt;C) copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.147" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO and agitate until homogeneous. Charge acrylic graft copolymer and agitate until homogeneous. Under a hood, charge <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.139" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1823" name="naphthalenesulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:284489" relevant="false">naphthalenesulfonic acid</ne> <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.93" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne> salt and agitate until homogeneous.
</P>
<P>[00073] To this mixture under agitation, charge the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.24" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:26" name="polydimethylsiloxane" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:48137" relevant="false">polydimethylsiloxane</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.331" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:25" name="propylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.363" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:98" name="glycerin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:17754" relevant="false">glycerin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.339" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1185" name="phosphoric acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26078" relevant="false">phosphoric acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.43" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne>, and biocide, and mix until homogeneous.
</P>
<P>[00074] Under a hood, charge <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.75" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.7" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> to the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.382" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> mixture under agitation. <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.11" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">Silicon dioxide</ne> can either be added at this time, or post milling if product has been separately micronized. Mix for 15 minutes to half an hour. Check pH and adjust with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.94" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7174" name="sodium hydroxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32145" relevant="false">sodium</ne> hydroxide solution if necessary (target pH in neat mixture is between 5.5-6.5). Using a high shear mixer (type Ross, Silverson or Ultra Turax), pre-grind the mixture until 95% of the particles are below 150 microns.
Using a horizontal mill (type Dyno or Premier) charged between 80-85 % of total volume with 1-2 mm glass or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.366" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7443" name="zirconium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33342" relevant="false">zirconium</ne> beads, mill the mixture under cooling system (temperature should not be higher than 35[deg.]C during the entire process), until 50% of the particle is between 1.5 -3.0 microns. Filtrate product through a 100 mesh sieve. Check pH and adjust if necessary with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.340" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1185" name="phosphoric acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26078" relevant="false">phosphoric acid</ne> and/or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.95" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7174" name="sodium hydroxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32145" relevant="false">sodium</ne> hydroxide solutions until pH of neat mill base is between 5.5-6.5. [00075] Separately, in a vessel with Cowles mixer, prepare a 2% heteropolysaccaride gel in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.383" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>. Allow the gel to fully swell for several hours prior to use. To the mill base, add the amount of gel necessary to reach a final neat viscosity between 300-500 cPs. Filter final product through a 50 Mesh sieve.
Example 2- Formulation
</P>
<P>[0083]
EMI18.1
</P>
<P>[00076] To a suitably sized vessel equipped with a Cowles mixer, charge the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.384" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and start agitation. Charge pre-heated (up to 50&lt;0&gt;C) copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.148" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO and agitate until homogeneous. Charge acrylic graft copolymer and agitate until homogeneous. Under a hood, charge <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.6" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:168" name="lignosulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:934977" relevant="false">lignosulfonic acid</ne> <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.96" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne> salt and agitate until homogeneous.
To this mixture under agitation, charge the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.25" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:26" name="polydimethylsiloxane" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:48137" relevant="false">polydimethylsiloxane</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.332" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:25" name="propylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propylene glycol</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.364" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:98" name="glycerin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:17754" relevant="false">glycerin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.341" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1185" name="phosphoric acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26078" relevant="false">phosphoric acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.44" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne>, and biocide, and mix until homogeneous. [00077] Under a hood, charge the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.76" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.8" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> to the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.385" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> mixture under agitation. <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.34" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">Polyethylene</ne> wax can either be added at this time, or post milling if product has been separately micronized. Mix for 15 minutes to half an hour.
Check pH and adjust with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.97" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7174" name="sodium hydroxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32145" relevant="false">sodium</ne> hydroxide solution if necessary (target pH in neat mixture is between 5.5-6.5). Using a high shear mixer (type Ross, Silverson or Ultra Turax), pre-grind the mixture until 95% of the particles are below 150 microns. Using an horizontal mill (type Dyno or Premier) charged between 80-85 % of total volume with 1-2 mm glass or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.367" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7443" name="zirconium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33342" relevant="false">zirconium</ne> beads, mill the mixture under cooling system (temperature should not be higher than 35[deg.]C during the entire process), until 50% of the particles are between 1.5 -3.0 microns. Filtrate product through a 100 mesh sieve. Check pH and adjust if necessary with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.342" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1185" name="phosphoric acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26078" relevant="false">phosphoric acid</ne> and/or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.98" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7174" name="sodium hydroxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32145" relevant="false">sodium</ne> hydroxide solutions until pH of neat millbase is between 5.5-6.5. Separately, in a vessel with Cowles mixer, prepare a 2% heteropolysaccaride gel in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.386" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>. Allow the gel to fully swell for several hours prior to use. To the mill base, add the amount of gel necessary to reach a final neat viscosity between 300-500 cPs. Filter final product through a 50 mesh sieve.
</P>
<P>[00078] The liquid compositions of the present invention are fast-drying compared to other liquid treatments for plant propagation materials. The compositions of the present invention dry in periods between about 30 minutes and 200 minutes. Preferably, the liquid compositions of the present invention dry after application in periods between about 60 minutes to about 180 minutes. More preferably, the post-application drying time of the liquid compositions of the present invention is between about 75 minutes to about 90 minutes. [00079] The following non-limiting examples demonstrate the decreased drying time of the liquid compositions of the present invention.
Example 3 - Drying Time
</P>
<P>[00080] Drying times of the liquid compositions of the present invention were compared to existing liquid treatments for plant propagation materials. Specifically, compositions of the present invention were compared to (a) a liquid formulation of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.9" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> (Maxim(R) 4FS) and (b) a powder formulation of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.10" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> in combination with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.42" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1810" name="mancozeb" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:553992" relevant="false">mancozeb</ne> (Maxim(R) MZ).
</P>
<P>[00081] Potato tubers of approximately 5 cm&lt;3&gt; were treated with liquid compositions of the present invention and with <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.11" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> formulations known in the art (Maxim(R) 4FS and Maxim(R) MZ). Using a recommended application rate/100kg tubers and adjusting to constant total volume for all treatments (0.626g slurry/0.5kg tubers), the liquid composition was added to a treatment bag, the cut potato tubers were added, and the bag was shaken for about 15 seconds. The tubers were then removed and allowed to dry at ambient temperature. The results are provided below. [00082]
</P>
<P>[0090]
EMI20.1
*applied dry as dust treatment
**already dry after 60 minutes, but product flakes off tuber when touched
</P>
<P>[00083] The following non-limiting examples demonstrate the reduction in decay of three different types of potato seedlings.
Example 4 - Fungal Decay
</P>
<P>[00084] Using the formulation described above in Example 1, labelled A 14382, different types of cut potato seedlings were treated and tested for Fiisarium decay against untreated control (UTC), and a liquid formulation of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.12" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>, Maxim(TM) 4FS (Syngenta). Each variety included all three treatments. [00085] For each variety, seed was cut and treated on seven (7) different treatment days. These included the day of planting (0 days), 2, 5, 7, 9, 12, and 14 days before planting. After being cut, the seed was stored in burlap bags at 50[deg.] F and 90% relative humidity until the planting date, except for the last treatment day in which the seed was cut, treated, and planted on the same day. [00086] All of the seed was inoculated the day of planting with a slurry of
Fiisarium sambucimim isolate FID 71-6 (<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.361" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1249" name="Benzimidazol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36622" relevant="false">Benzimidazol</ne> sensitive), F, sambucinum isolate FID 212 (<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.362" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1249" name="Benzimidazol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36622" relevant="false">Benzimidazol</ne> resistant), and F. solani var. coeruleum isolate MR-6. 4.2 ml of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.387" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> suspension at 1.6 X 10&lt;4&gt; CFU/ml was applied to 48 seed pieces for each treatment.
</P>
<P>[00087] Data reported here are 7 or 9 days before planting. Data collected here shows early season field evaluations where the plants were dug up and evaluated for seed piece decay. Seed piece decay was evaluated in percentage of Fiisariiim "dry" decay, soft rot decay, or a combination of the two in each seed piece, as well as percentage of all of the seed pieces in each treatment which have decay.
Russet Burbank DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - "DRY ROT"
</P>
<P>[0099]
EMI21.1
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - "DRY ROT" INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0101]
EMI21.2
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT
</P>
<P>[0103]
EMI22.1
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0105]
EMI22.2
Nordonna DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - DRY ROT
</P>
<P>[0107]
EMI22.3
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - DRY ROT INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0108]
EMI23.1
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT
</P>
<P>[0110]
EMI23.2
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0112]
EMI23.3
FLl 833
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - DRY ROT
</P>
<P>[0114]
EMI24.1
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - DRY ROT INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0116]
EMI24.2
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT
</P>
<P>[0118]
EMI24.3
DESTRUCTIVE SAMPLING - SOFT ROT INCIDENCE (% OF SEED PIECES WITH ROT PER TREATMENT)
</P>
<P>[0119]
EMI25.1
</P>
<P>[00088] Cut seedlings undergo a process of self-healing, called suberization.
During suberization, the cell walls of the seedling excrete suberin, a biochemical that protects the cut area by forming a cork-like barrier between the environmental elements and the inner flesh of the seed. Suberin is composed of two distinctly different biochemical components: a polyphenolic component and a polyaliphatic component. Once the plant material experiences a trauma, which includes cutting and bruising, the plant's own cells initiate suberization to form the protective, healing coating.
</P>
<P>[00089] As shown in Example 4, the fast-drying formulation of the present invention promotes the cut tuber's natural suberization process, allowing the self- protecting coating to protect the cut, or other trauma cite, and fight against external pathogens. Accordingly, the present invention further provides a process for promoting suberization in plant propagation material comprising applying to the propagation material an effective amount of the liquid composition described herein.
Example 5 - Suberization
</P>
<P>[00090] Suberization is objectively measured using a process called the
"suberization index." The following protocol is used to obtain the measurements. [00091] Eight seed pieces from each treatment are removed for evaluation at 2,
</P>
<P>3, 6, 8 and 13 days after cutting and treating.
</P>
<P>[00092] A rectangular block of tissue, approximately 1 x 3 x 0.5 cm, is cut from each seed piece at the center of the juncture of the two cut planes. Under a dissecting scope, three serial sections approximately lmm in thickness are cut from each rectangular block of tissue. The outer-most sections are discarded and the other two sections are mounted in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.388" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> on a microscope slide.
</P>
<P>[00093] The sections are evaluated on a phase contrast microscope using both incandescent and ultraviolet light.
</P>
<P>[00094] All measurements are taken at 10OX magnification, at which 10 units are equal to .08mm.
</P>
<P>[00095] Evaluations include measurements and observations of the number of cell layers and the thickness of the suberized cells, the uniformity of the suberin development across the cut surface, the inception and development of a meristematic region (phellogen) and the periclinal cell division which forms the phellogen, the final stage of the healing process. These measurements are all used to calculate the
"suberization index".
Example 6~SeIective Loading
</P>
<P>[00096] Generally, treatment of potato tubers and/or cut seeds with liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.331" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:910" name="pesticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticides</ne> results in the majority of the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.478" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> settling on the cut side of the seed rather than on the skin side of the seed. Such affinity for the cut side is thought to be based on the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.332" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:910" name="pesticides" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticides</ne>' affinity for <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.389" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>. Because of the naturally-occurring suberization of the tuber or seed, the cut surface is believed to provide better protection against pests and does not need as much <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.479" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne>. Rather, the pesticidal action is more useful on the skin side of the tuber, where the eyes are present and where germination occurs.
</P>
<P>[00097] The formulation of the present invention demonstrates a tendency to selectively load the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.480" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> on the skin side of the tuber. Although not wanting to be bound by any particular theory, it is thought that the nonpolar nature of the waxes and silicas present in the formulations of the present invention have affinity for the skin side, causing a greater loading of the active ingredients on the skin side. Such affinity is demonstrated by the following results, wherein the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.77" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>/<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.424" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2103" name="fluidioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:484183" relevant="false">fluidioxonil</ne> formulation of Example 2 of the present invention is compared with the same formulation of Example 2 without wax.
</P>
<P>[0135]
EMI26.1
EMI27.1
</P>
<P>[00098] As shown in the table above, the amount of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.78" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> present on the cut side of the tuber is essentially the same for either formulation; however, the selectivity of the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.79" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne> for the skin side is more defined for the wax- containing formulation. Additionally, the amount of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.13" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne> present on the skin side of the tuber is greater than that of the cut side.
Example 6 - Insect Protection
</P>
<P>[00099] Comparative trials were conducted to show the protection of the formulation described herein against different insect pests. [000100] In two trials measuring the control of Colorado Potato Beetles on potatoes, the formulation of Example 1 showed improved control versus the untreated check and slightly better control than or the same control as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.62" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne>.
</P>
<P>[0139]
EMI27.2
</P>
<P>[000101] In trials testing the number of Green Peach Aphids per sample of potatoes, the formulation of Example 1 showed greater reduction in the number of aphid pests than the untreated check or Tops MZ Gaucho(TM) (Bayer Crop Science; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.63" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne> formulation). Results are measured as aphids per sample.
EMI28.1
Example 7 - Improved Yield
</P>
<P>[000102] The formulation of the present invention has shown improved yields on trials of potato crops. In trials conducted in Washington and Idaho, the crops resulting from potato seeds treated with the formulation of Example 1 showed better yield, as measured by plant stand, than the untreated control and better or comparable yield when compared to Tops MZ Gaucho (Bayer Crop Science).
</P>
<P>[0143]
EMI28.2
</P>
<P>[000103] The invention as set forth herein solves a problem known to exist in the art. As various changes could be made to the above composition and processes without departing from the scope of the invention, it is intended that all matter contained in this description shall be interpreted as illustrative only without limiting the scope of the present invention.
We Claim:
</P>
<P>1. A liquid composition for treating plant propagation material comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.390" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, an effective amount of active ingredients containing at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.16" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> and at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.72" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne>, and a blend of the following components, by weight: a. about 0.05-20% at least one wetting agent; b. about 0.05-10% at least one dispersing agent; c. about 0.05-5% at least one drying agent; d. about 0.01 -20% at least one suberization agent; and optionally, e. about 0-20% <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.410" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne>; and optionally f. about 0-20% <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.474" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:843" name="solvent" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46787" relevant="false">solvent</ne> wherein the composition dries within 90 minutes of application to the plant propagation material.
</P>
<P>2. The composition according to claim 1, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.17" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is selected from <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.253" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:722" name="diazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:636035" relevant="false" type="CLASS">diazole</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.257" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:723" name="triazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38597" relevant="false" type="CLASS">triazole</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.597" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1110" name="phenylpyrrole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:673027" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phenylpyrrole</ne>-, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.431" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2105" name="strobilurin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:631631" relevant="false">strobilurin</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.277" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:726" name="carboxamide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23004" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carboxamide</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.584" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1108" name="carbamate" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:13941" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamate</ne>-, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.589" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1109" name="anilinopyrimidine" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:479868" relevant="false" type="CLASS">anilinopyrimidine</ne>-, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.166" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1828" name="phenoxyquinoline" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:968251" relevant="false">phenoxyquinoline</ne>-, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.427" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2104" name="benzimidazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:36622" relevant="false">benzimidazole</ne>-, systemic- and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.176" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:705" name="phenylamide fungicides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:325267" relevant="false">phenylamide fungicides</ne>.
</P>
<P>3. The composition according to claim 1 , wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.18" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is selected from <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.14" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.19" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1798" name="difenconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:565941" relevant="false">difenconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.21" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1799" name="mefenoxam" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:287128" relevant="false">mefenoxam</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.24" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1800" name="azoxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:335764" relevant="false">azoxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.26" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1801" name="trifloxystrobin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:85210" relevant="false">trifloxystrobin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.28" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1802" name="propiconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:132189" relevant="false">propiconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.31" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1803" name="myclobutanil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:484133" relevant="false">myclobutanil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.32" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1804" name="captan" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:437500" relevant="false">captan</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.33" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1805" name="thiram" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:56999" relevant="false">thiram</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.35" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1806" name="carboxin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:353516" relevant="false">carboxin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.37" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1807" name="oxycarboxin" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:102358" relevant="false">oxycarboxin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.39" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1808" name="imazalil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:210229" relevant="false">imazalil</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.41" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1809" name="tebuconazole" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:689052" relevant="false">tebuconazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.43" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1810" name="mancozeb" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:553992" relevant="false">mancozeb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.44" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1811" name="maneb" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:121096" relevant="false">maneb</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.45" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1812" name="pentachloronitrobenzene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:785120" relevant="false">pentachloronitrobenzene</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.46" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:1690" name="streptomycin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:17076" relevant="false">streptomycin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.48" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1813" name="thiabendazole" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:45979" relevant="false">thiabendazole</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.50" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1814" name="thiophanate-methyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:513889" relevant="false">thiophanate-methyl</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.52" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1815" name="triadimenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:583663" relevant="false">triadimenol</ne>.
</P>
<P>4. The composition according to claim 3, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.19" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:648" name="fungicide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24127" relevant="false">fungicide</ne> is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.15" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>.
</P>
<P>5. The composition according to claim 1 , wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.73" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> is selected from <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.40" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:651" name="neonicotinoids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:308348" relevant="false">neonicotinoids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.38" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:650" name="pyrethroids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:541709" relevant="false" type="CLASS">pyrethroids</ne>, phosphorus compounds, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.42" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:206" name="carbamates" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:23003" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carbamates</ne>.
</P>
<P>6. The composition according to claim 5, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.74" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> is a <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.59" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:659" name="neonicotinoid insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:714542" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticide</ne>.
</P>
<P>7. The composition according to claim 6, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.60" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:659" name="neonicotinoid insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:714542" relevant="false">neonicotinoid insecticide</ne> is selected from <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.54" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6033" name="acetamiprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39163" relevant="false">acetamiprid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.56" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4173" name="clothianidin" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39178" relevant="false">clothianidin</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.58" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4176" name="dinotefuran" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39183" relevant="false">dinotefuran</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.64" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6039" name="imidacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:5870" relevant="false">imidacloprid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.66" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6037" name="nitenpyram" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39171" relevant="false">nitenpyram</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.68" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:6042" name="thiacloprid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39175" relevant="false">thiacloprid</ne>, and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.80" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>.
</P>
<P>8. The composition according to claim 7, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.77" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:660" name="insecticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:24852" relevant="false">insecticide</ne> is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.81" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>.
</P>
<P>9. The composition according to claim 1 , wherein the wetting agent is selected from one or more <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.336" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:382" name="anionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:473584" relevant="false">anionic surfactants</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.338" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:911" name="nonionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38828" relevant="false">nonionic surfactants</ne>, and <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.341" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:912" name="zwitterionic surfactants" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:453533" relevant="false">zwitterionic surfactants</ne>.
</P>
<P>10. The composition according to claim 9, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.55" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:658" name="anionic surfactant" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:914324" relevant="false">anionic surfactant</ne> is selected from one or more of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.54" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:657" name="alcohol sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:668813" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.44" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:652" name="alcohol ether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:117629" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol ether sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.46" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:653" name="alkylaryl ether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:983252" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylaryl ether sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.48" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:654" name="alkylaryl sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:459993" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylaryl sulfonates</ne> such as <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.50" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:655" name="alkylbenzene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:612831" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylbenzene sulfonates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.52" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:656" name="alkylnaphthalene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:623570" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylnaphthalene sulfonates</ne> and salts thereof, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.58" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:305" name="alkyl sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:365727" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl sulfonates</ne>, mono- or <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.321" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:746" name="di-phosphate esters of polyalkoxylated alkyl alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:948533" relevant="false">di-phosphate esters of polyalkoxylated alkyl alcohols</ne> or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.319" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:745" name="alkylphenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:779658" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylphenols</ne> , mono- or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.322" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:747" name="di-sulfosuccinate esters of Cj2-Ci5 alkanols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:635783" relevant="false" type="CLASS">di-sulfosuccinate esters of Cj2-Ci5 alkanols</ne> or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.323" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:748" name="polyalkoxylated C]2-Ci5 alkanols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:632946" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxylated C]2-Ci5 alkanols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.79" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:661" name="alcohol ether carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:349356" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alcohol ether carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.81" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:662" name="phenolic ether carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:195167" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phenolic ether carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.83" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:663" name="polybasic acid esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:466598" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polybasic acid esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.85" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:664" name="ethoxylated polyoxyalkylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:605365" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated polyoxyalkylene glycols</ne> consisting of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.88" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:666" name="oxybutylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:16686" relevant="false" type="CLASS">oxybutylene</ne> or the residue of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.85" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:239" name="tetrahydrofuran" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26911" relevant="false">tetrahydrofuran</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.86" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:665" name="sulfoalkyl amides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283439" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfoalkyl amides</ne> and salts thereof such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.88" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1816" name="N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:33515" relevant="false">N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate</ne> Na salt, polyoxyalkylene <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.90" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:667" name="alkylphenol carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:355867" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylphenol carboxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.98" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:668" name="polyoxyalkylene alcohol carboxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:621589" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyoxyalkylene alcohol carboxylates</ne> <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.100" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:669" name="alkyl polyglycoside" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:353651" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl polyglycoside</ne>/<ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.102" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:670" name="alkenylsuccinicanhydride" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:132374" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkenyl succinic anhydride</ne> condensation products, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.104" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:671" name="alkyl ester sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:429236" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl ester sulfates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.106" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:672" name="napthalene sulfonates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:301225" relevant="false" type="CLASS">napthalene sulfonates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.108" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:673" name="naphthalene formaldehyde" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:818176" relevant="false" type="CLASS">naphthalene formaldehyde</ne> condensates, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.110" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:674" name="alkyl sulfonamides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:206432" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl sulfonamides</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.112" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:675" name="sulfonated aliphatic polyesters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:619059" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfonated aliphatic polyesters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.114" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:676" name="sulfate esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:763783" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfate esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.117" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:677" name="styrylphenyl alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:346518" relevant="false" type="CLASS">styrylphenyl alkoxylates</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.120" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:678" name="sulfonate esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:131495" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfonate esters</ne> of <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.118" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:677" name="styrylphenyl alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:346518" relevant="false" type="CLASS">styrylphenyl alkoxylates</ne> and their corresponding <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.99" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.106" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7084" name="potassium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26216" relevant="false">potassium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.111" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.116" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7091" name="magnesium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25107" relevant="false">magnesium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.119" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7669" name="zinc" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27363" relevant="false">zinc</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.122" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4221" name="ammonium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28938" relevant="false">ammonium</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.122" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:69" name="alkylammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:382183" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylammonium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.126" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1817" name="diethanolammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:317292" relevant="false">diethanolammonium</ne>, or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.127" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1818" name="triethanol ammonium" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:295850" relevant="false">triethanol ammonium</ne> salts, salts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.2" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:166" name="ligninsulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:636370" relevant="false">ligninsulfonic acid</ne> such as the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.100" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.107" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7084" name="potassium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26216" relevant="false">potassium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.117" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7091" name="magnesium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25107" relevant="false">magnesium</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.112" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne> or <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.124" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4221" name="ammonium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28938" relevant="false">ammonium</ne> salt, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.124" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:679" name="polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether sulfates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:649009" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether sulfates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.126" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:680" name="polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether phosphates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:488366" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyalkoxyether phosphates</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.128" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:681" name="sulfated alkyl phenol ethoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:506126" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sulfated alkyl phenol ethoxylates</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.130" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:682" name="phosphated alkyl phenol ethoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:588481" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phosphated alkyl phenol ethoxylates</ne>.
</P>
<P>11. The composition according to claim 10, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.56" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:658" name="anionic surfactant" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:914324" relevant="false">anionic surfactant</ne> is selected from one or more of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.89" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1816" name="N-methyl- N-oleoyltaurate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:33515" relevant="false">N-methyl-N-oleoyltaurate</ne> Na salt; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.131" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1820" name="tristyrylphenol sulphate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:281715" relevant="false">tristyrylphenol sulphate</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.4" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:167" name="ethoxylated lignin sulfonate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:866949" relevant="false">ethoxylated lignin sulfonate</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.134" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1821" name="nonylphenol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:688325" relevant="false">nonylphenol phosphate ester</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.113" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7090" name="calcium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:22984" relevant="false">calcium</ne> <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.132" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:683" name="alkylbenzene sulfonate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:900915" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylbenzene sulfonate</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.135" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1821" name="nonylphenol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:688325" relevant="false">nonylphenol phosphate ester</ne>; ethoxylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.137" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1822" name="tridecylalcohol phosphate ester" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:112574" relevant="false">tridecylalcohol phosphate ester</ne>; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.7" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:168" name="lignosulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:934977" relevant="false">lignosulfonic acid</ne> Na salt; and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.140" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1823" name="naphthalenesulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:284489" relevant="false">naphthalenesulfonic acid</ne> <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.101" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne> salt.
</P>
<P>12. The composition according to claim 9, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.344" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:914" name="nonionic surfactant" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38828" relevant="false">nonionic surfactant</ne> is selected from one or more <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.134" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:684" name="polyarylphenol polyethoxy ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:784561" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyarylphenol polyethoxy ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.136" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:685" name="polyalkylphenol polyethoxy ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:897843" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkylphenol polyethoxy ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.138" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:686" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of saturated fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:684782" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of saturated fatty acids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.140" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:687" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of unsaturated fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:882968" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of unsaturated fatty acids</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.142" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:688" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of aliphatic alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:803587" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of aliphatic alcohols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.144" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:689" name="polyglycol ether derivatives of cycloaliphatic alcohols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:48637" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyglycol ether derivatives of cycloaliphatic alcohols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.146" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:690" name="fatty acid esters of polyoxyethylene sorbitan" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:471917" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty acid esters of polyoxyethylene sorbitan</ne>, alkoxylated vegetable oils, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.148" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:691" name="alkoxylated acetylenic diols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:141280" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkoxylated acetylenic diols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.150" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:692" name="polyalkoxylated alkylphenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:46651" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxylated alkylphenols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.152" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:693" name="fatty acid alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:371342" relevant="false" type="CLASS">fatty acid alkoxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.154" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:694" name="sorbitan alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:434316" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitan alkoxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.156" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:695" name="sorbitol esters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:457693" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitol esters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.164" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:699" name="C8-C22 alkyl" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:742655" relevant="false" type="CLASS">C8-C22 alkyl</ne> or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.162" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:698" name="alkenyl polyglycosides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:411570" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkenyl polyglycosides</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.158" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:696" name="polyalkoxy styrylaryl ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:536319" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxy styrylaryl ethers</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.160" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:697" name="alkylamine oxides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:179541" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkylamine oxides</ne>, block copolymer ethers, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.318" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:744" name="polyalkoxylated fatty glyceride" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:722942" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkoxylated fatty glyceride</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.166" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:700" name="polyalkylene glycol ethers" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:362748" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyalkylene glycol ethers</ne>, linear aliphatic or <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.172" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:703" name="aromatic polyesters" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:389618" relevant="false" type="CLASS">aromatic polyesters</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.174" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:704" name="organo silicones" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:969023" relevant="false" type="CLASS">organo silicones</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.168" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:701" name="polyaryl phenols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:564204" relevant="false" type="CLASS">polyaryl phenols</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.170" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:702" name="sorbitol ester alkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:880245" relevant="false" type="CLASS">sorbitol ester alkoxylates</ne>, and mono- and diesters of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.329" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4751" name="ethylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30742" relevant="false">ethylene glycol</ne> and mixtures thereof.
</P>
<P>13. The composition according to claim 12, wherein the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.345" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:914" name="nonionic surfactant" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38828" relevant="false">nonionic surfactant</ne> is selected from one or more <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.299" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:732" name="ethoxylated fatty alcohol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:872185" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated fatty alcohol</ne>; <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.314" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:742" name="ethoxylated tristyrylphenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:673019" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated tristyrylphenol</ne>; <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.316" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:743" name="ethoxylated lauryl alcohol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:351302" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated lauryl alcohol</ne>; ethoxylated castor oil; <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.313" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:741" name="ethoxylated nonylphenol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:305485" relevant="false" type="CLASS">ethoxylated nonylphenol</ne>.
</P>
<P>14. The composition according to claim 9, wherein the <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.346" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:915" name="zwitterionic surfactant" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:335320" relevant="false" type="CLASS">zwitterionic surfactant</ne> is selected from <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.308" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:737" name="alkanol amides of C8-CjS fatty acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:417232" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkanol amides of C8-CjS fatty acids</ne> and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.309" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:738" name="Cs-Cis fatty amine polyalkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:740424" relevant="false" type="CLASS">Cs-Cis fatty amine polyalkoxylates</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.310" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:739" name="Cio-Qs alkyldimethylbenzylammonium chlorides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:714792" relevant="false" type="CLASS">Cio-Qs alkyldimethylbenzylammonium chlorides</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.311" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:740" name="coconut alkyldimethylaminoacetic acids" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:445146" relevant="false" type="CLASS">coconut alkyldimethylaminoacetic acids</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.304" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:735" name="phosphate esters of Cg-is fatty amine polyalkoxylates" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:541041" relevant="false" type="CLASS">phosphate esters of Cg-is fatty amine polyalkoxylates</ne>.
</P>
<P>15. The composition according to claim 1 , wherein the dispersing agent (b) is selected from bl) alkyleneoxide random and block copolymers such as <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.400" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>- <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.406" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2013" name="propyleneoxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38685" relevant="false">propylene oxide</ne> block copolymers (EO/PO block copolymers) including both EO- PO-EO and PO-EO-PO block copolymers; <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.401" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.410" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2014" name="butyleneoxide" comment="butylene oxide" chebi-id="WO2007005470:849714" relevant="false">butylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers, C2-6 alkyl adducts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.402" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.407" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2013" name="propyleneoxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:38685" relevant="false">propylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers, C2-6 alkyl adducts of <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.403" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2012" name="ethylene oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:27561" relevant="false">ethylene oxide</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.411" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2014" name="butyleneoxide" comment="butylene oxide" chebi-id="WO2007005470:849714" relevant="false">butylene oxide</ne> random and block copolymers, b2) <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.27" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:54" name="polyoxyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:966514" relevant="false">polyoxyethylene</ne>-<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.29" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:55" name="polyoxypropylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:954458" relevant="false">polyoxypropylene</ne> monoalkylethers such as methyl ether, ethyl ether, propyl ether, butyl ether or mixtures thereof; b3) <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.413" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1406" name="vinylacetate" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:56014" relevant="false">vinylacetate</ne>/<ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.416" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2015" name="vinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:892223" relevant="false">vinylpyrrolidone</ne> copolymers, b4) alkylated <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.417" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2015" name="vinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:892223" relevant="false">vinylpyrrolidone</ne> copolymers, b5) <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.18" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:71" name="polyvinylpyrrolidone" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:426640" relevant="false">polyvinylpyrrolidone</ne>, and b6) <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.16" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:170" name="polyalkyleneglycol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:961991" relevant="false">polyalkyleneglycol</ne> including the <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.20" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:171" name="polypropylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:416541" relevant="false">polypropylene glycols</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.22" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:73" name="polyethylene glycols" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:46793" relevant="false">polyethylene glycols</ne>.
</P>
<P>16. The composition according to claim 15, wherein the dispersing agent is one or more of copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.149" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO and acrylic graft copolymer in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.391" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.419" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2016" name="propyleneglycole" comment="propylene glycol" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propyleneglycole</ne>.
</P>
<P>17. The composition according to claim 1, wherein the drying agent is one or more of inorganic oxides or polymer wax.
</P>
<P>18. The composition according to claim 17, wherein the drying agent is an inorganic oxide.
</P>
<P>19. The composition according to claim 18, wherein the drying agent is selected from <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.12" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silicon dioxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.318" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7651" name="titanium dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:32234" relevant="false">titanium dioxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.320" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1919" name="aluminum oxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30187" relevant="false">aluminum oxide</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.322" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:235" name="zirconium oxide" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:292068" relevant="false">zirconium oxide</ne> and fumed <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.360" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1434" name="silica" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silica</ne>.
</P>
<P>20. The composition according to claim 19, wherein the drying agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.13" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silicon dioxide</ne>.
</P>
<P>21. The composition according to claim 17, wherein the drying agent is a polymer wax selected from oxidized and non-oxidized <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.36" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> wax, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.37" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> copolymer wax, Montan wax, and polyether wax.
</P>
<P>22. The composition according to claim 21, wherein the polymer wax is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.38" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> wax.
</P>
<P>23. The composition according to claim 1 , wherein the suberization agent is selected from at least one <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.45" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.300" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:733" name="alkyl triol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:734179" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alkyl triol</ne>, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.301" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:734" name="alky] diol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:353652" relevant="false" type="CLASS">alky] diol</ne>, phenolic polymer, aliphatic polymer, <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.302" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:551" name="carboxylic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:33575" relevant="false" type="CLASS">carboxylic acid</ne>, and <ne id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.303" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:466" name="dicarboxylic acid" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:35692" relevant="false" type="CLASS">dicarboxylic acid</ne>.
</P>
<P>24. The composition according to claim 23, wherein the suberization agent is selected from at least one <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.46" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.143" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1824" name="propane- 1 , 2, 3-triol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:142" relevant="false">propane- 1,2,3-triol</ne>.
</P>
<P>25. The composition according to claim 1 , further comprising <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.613" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1111" name="buffering agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:701115" relevant="false">buffering agents</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.416" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:870" name="biocides" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:799811" relevant="false">biocides</ne>, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.615" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:1112" name="preserving agents" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:596244" relevant="false">preserving agents</ne>, thickening agents, <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.343" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:913" name="pigments" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26130" relevant="false">pigments</ne>, and antifoaming agents.
</P>
<P>26. The composition according to claim 25, comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.392" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.82" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.16" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>, and the following components, by weight: a. about 1-5% at least one wetting agent; b. about 2-8% at least one dispersing agent; c. about 0.2-1.0% at least one drying agent; d. about 3-8% at least one suberization agent; and optionally, e. about 12-18% at least one <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.411" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne>.
</P>
<P>27. The composition according to claim 26, wherein the wetting agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.141" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1823" name="naphthalenesulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:284489" relevant="false">naphthalenesulfonic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.102" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne> salt; the dispersing agent is acrylic graft copolymer in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.393" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.420" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2016" name="propyleneglycole" comment="propylene glycol" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propyleneglycole</ne> and copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.150" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO; the drying agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.14" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:169" name="silicon dioxide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:30563" relevant="false">silicon dioxide</ne>; the suberization agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.144" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1824" name="propane- 1 , 2, 3-triol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:142" relevant="false">propane- 1,2,3-triol</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.47" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne>; the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.412" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne> is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.333" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:25" name="propylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propylene glycol</ne>.
</P>
<P>28. The composition according to claim 25, comprising <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.394" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.83" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:4178" name="thiamethoxam" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:39185" relevant="true">thiamethoxam</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.17" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1797" name="fludioxonil" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:283179" relevant="true">fludioxonil</ne>, and the following components, by weight: a. about 1-5% at least one wetting agent; b. about 2-8% at least one dispersing agent; c. about 0.2-3.0% drying agent; d. about 3-8% suberization agent; and optionally, e. about 12-18% <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.413" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne>.
</P>
<P>29. The composition according to claim 28, wherein the wetting agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.8" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:168" name="lignosulfonic acid" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:934977" relevant="false">lignosulfonic acid</ne>, <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.103" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:7085" name="sodium" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:26708" relevant="false">sodium</ne> salt; the dispersing agent is acrylic graft copolymer in <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.395" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:COMPOUND:5421" name="water" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:15377" relevant="false">water</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.421" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:2016" name="propyleneglycole" comment="propylene glycol" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propyleneglycole</ne> and copolymer <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.151" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1825" name="butanol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:280657" relevant="false">butanol</ne> PO/EO; the drying agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.39" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:145" name="polyethylene" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:982208" relevant="false">polyethylene</ne> wax; the suberization agent is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.substance-names.48" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:SUBSTANCE:127" name="starch" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:28017" relevant="false">starch</ne> and <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.145" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:1824" name="propane- 1 , 2, 3-triol" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:142" relevant="false">propane- 1 , 2, 3-triol</ne>; and the <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.414" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:925" name="antifreeze" comment="" chebi-id="WO2007005470:147374" relevant="false">antifreeze</ne> is <ne type="CHEMICAL" id="WO2007005470.HC.chemical-names.334" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:COMPOUND:25" name="propylene glycol" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:16997" relevant="false">propylene glycol</ne>.
</P>
<P>30. A method for preventing pest infestation in useful crops comprising treating the plant propagation material of a useful crop with a pesticidally effective amount of a composition according to claim 1.
</P>
<P>31. The method according to claim 30, wherein the plant propagation material is selected from seeds, roots, fruits, tubers, bulbs, rhizomes.
</P>
<P>32. The method according to claim 31 , wherein the plant propagation material is a tuber and is selected from potato, Jerusalam artichoke, and yam.
</P>
<P>33. The method according to claim 32, wherein the potato is a whole or cut potato.
</P>
<P>34. The method according to claim 31 , wherein the plant propagation material is a bulb.
</P>
<P>35. The method according to claim 34, wherein the bulb is selected from onion, hyacinth, squill, amaryllis, snowdrop, tulip, daffodil, narcissis, lily, and orchid.
</P>
<P>36. A method for preventing pest infestation in useful crops comprising treating the plant propagation material of a useful crop with a pesticidally effective amount of a composition according to claim 27.
</P>
<P>37. The method according to claim 36, wherein the pest is selected from fungi, bacteria, and insects.
</P>
<P>38. A method for preventing pest infestation in useful crops comprising treating the plant propagation material of a useful crop with a pesticidally effective amount of a composition according to claim 29.
</P>
<P>39. The method according to claim 38, wherein the pest is selected from fungi, bacteria, and insects.
</P>
<P>40. A method for promoting suberization in plant propagation material comprising treating the material with an effective amount of a composition according to claim 1.
</P>
<P>41. A method for promoting suberization in plant propagation material comprising treating the material with an effective amount of a composition according to claim 27.
</P>
<P>42. A method for promoting suberization in plant propagation material comprising treating the material with an effective amount of a composition according to claim 29.
</P>
<P>43. Plant propagation material treated with the composition according to claim 1.
</P>
<P>44. Plant propagation material treated with the composition according to claim 27.
</P>
<P>45. Plant propagation material treated with the composition according to claim 29.
</P>
<P>46. A method for decreasing the drying time of a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.481" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to plant propogation material, comprising treating the plant propagation material with a composition according to claim 1.
</P>
<P>47. A method for decreasing the drying time of a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.482" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to plant propogation material, comprising treating the plant propagation material with a composition according to claim 27.
</P>
<P>48. A method for decreasing the drying time of a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.483" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to plant propogation material, comprising treating the plant propagation material with a composition according to claim 29.
</P>
<P>49. A method for selectively loading a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.484" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to a cut tuber to the skin side of the tuber, comprising treating the cut tuber with a composition according to claim 1.
</P>
<P>50. A method for selectively loading a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.485" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to a cut tuber to the skin side of the tuber, comprising treating the cut tuber with a composition according to claim 27.
</P>
<P>51. A method for selectively loading a liquid <ne type="ONT" id="WO2007005470.HC.class-names.486" epochem-id="EPOCHEM:NEW:CLASS:937" name="Pesticide" comment="" chebi-id="CHEBI:25944" relevant="false">pesticide</ne> applied to a cut tuber to the skin side of the tuber, comprising treating the cut tuber with a composition according to claim 29.
</P></DIV>
<DIV><P>
</P></DIV>
</BODY>
</PAPER>
