<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei xml:space="preserve">
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="ietf-rfc7654.txt"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">Internet Engineering Task Force (IETF)<lb/></note>

	S. Banks<lb/> 

<note type="doctype">Request for Comments</note>: 

<idno>7654<lb/></idno> 

VSS Monitoring<lb/> Category: Informational<lb/> F. Calabria<lb/> 

<idno type="ISSN">ISSN: 2070-1721<lb/></idno> 

Cisco Systems<lb/> G. Czirjak<lb/> R. Machat<lb/> Juniper Networks<lb/> 

<date type="publication">
	October 2015<lb/>
</date>	

<docTitle>
    <titlePart> 
Benchmarking Methodology for In-Service Software Upgrade (ISSU)<lb/> 
    </titlePart>    
</docTitle>	

<div type="abstract">
	Abstract<lb/> Modern forwarding devices attempt to minimize any control-and data-<lb/>plane disruptions while performing planned software changes by<lb/> implementing a technique commonly known as In-Service Software<lb/> Upgrade (ISSU). This document specifies a set of common<lb/> methodologies and procedures designed to characterize the overall<lb/> behavior of a Device Under Test (DUT), subject to an ISSU event.<lb/> 
</div>

<note type="other">
	Status of This Memo<lb/> This document is not an Internet Standards Track specification; it is<lb/> published for informational purposes.<lb/> This document is a product of the Internet Engineering Task Force<lb/> (IETF). It represents the consensus of the IETF community. It has<lb/> received public review and has been approved for publication by the<lb/> Internet Engineering Steering Group (IESG). Not all documents<lb/> approved by the IESG are a candidate for any level of Internet<lb/> Standard; see Section 2 of RFC 5741.<lb/> Information about the current status of this document, any errata,<lb/> and how to provide feedback on it may be obtained at<lb/> http://www.rfc-editor.org/info/rfc7654.<lb/>
</note>

	Banks, et al.<lb/> Informational<lb/> [Page 1]<lb/> RFC 7654<lb/> Benchmarking Software Upgrade<lb/> October 2015<lb/> 
	Copyright Notice<lb/>
	
<note type="copyright">
	Copyright (c) 2015 IETF Trust and the persons identified as the<lb/> document authors. All rights reserved.<lb/> This document is subject to BCP 78 and the IETF Trust&apos;s Legal<lb/> Provisions Relating to IETF Documents<lb/> (http://trustee.ietf.org/license-info) in effect on the date of<lb/> publication of this document. Please review these documents<lb/> carefully, as they describe your rights and restrictions with respect<lb/> to this document. Code Components extracted from this document must<lb/> include Simplified BSD License text as described in Section 4.e of<lb/> the Trust Legal Provisions and are provided without warranty as<lb/> described in the Simplified BSD License.<lb/>
</note>

<byline>
	<docAuthor>
Sarah Banks<lb/> 
	</docAuthor>
</byline>
<byline>
	<affiliation>
VSS Monitoring<lb/> 
	</affiliation>
</byline>
<email>
Email: sbanks@encrypted.net<lb/>
</email>

<byline>
	<docAuthor>
Fernando Calabria<lb/> 
	</docAuthor>
</byline>
<byline>
	<affiliation>
Cisco Systems<lb/> 
	</affiliation>
</byline>
<email>
Email: fcalabri@cisco.com<lb/> 
</email>

<byline>
	<docAuthor>
Gery Czirjak<lb/> 
	</docAuthor>
</byline>
<byline>
	<affiliation>
Juniper Networks<lb/> 
	</affiliation>
</byline>
<email>
Email: gczirjak@juniper.net<lb/> 
</email>

<byline>
	<docAuthor>
Ramdas Machat<lb/> 
	</docAuthor>
</byline>
<byline>
	<affiliation>
Juniper Networks<lb/> 
	</affiliation>
</byline>
<email>
Email: rmachat@juniper.net
</email>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
