<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002633"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="page">287<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Address correspondence to</note>
	

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Pai C. Kao, Ph.D.,</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Emeritus Office,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Plummer N10, Mayo Clinic, 200 First Street SW, Rochester,<lb/> MN 55905, USA;</address>

	<email>e-mail: kao.pai@mayo.edu.<lb/></email>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Filter Paper Collection of Plasma for IGF-I Test<lb/> in Patients with Acromegaly<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Ta-Jen Wu, 1 Eugene Hsin Yu, 1 Lu Song, 2 Robert L.Taylor, 2 and Pai C. Kao 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Section of Endocrinology and Metabolism, Department of Internal Medicine,<lb/> National Cheng Kung University Hospital,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Taiwan, ROC, and<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Division of Clinical Biochemistry and Immunology, Mayo Clinic,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Rochester, Minnesota<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract. The concentration of insulin-like growth factor I (IGF-I) was determined in paired specimens of<lb/> liquid plasma and of plasma that had been applied to a filter paper disk, dried, and eluted; the measurements<lb/> were performed by an immunochemiluminometric assay (ICMA). The 129 paired assays showed good<lb/> correlation: y = 1.04x + 4.99; R 2 = 0.934, where y is the result on dried samples and x is that on liquid<lb/> samples. In 18 patients with acromegaly who lived on an island off the West Pacific Rim, plasma specimens<lb/> were collected, applied to filter paper, dried, and mailed to a laboratory in the Upper Midwest of the United<lb/> States. IGF-I was eluted from the filter paper disks and measured by ICMA. IGF-I concentrations ranged<lb/> from 101 to 254 ng/ml in 11 patients with newly diagnosed but untreated acromegaly, 138 to 503 ng/ml in<lb/> 4 patients with recurrent acromegaly, and 27 to 88 ng/ml in 3 patients with surgically cured acromegaly.<lb/> These data demonstrate that plasma specimens of patients with acromegaly can be collected on filter paper<lb/> disks and mailed to a laboratory on a distant continent for measurement of IGF-I. Such use of laboratory<lb/> resources in one continent to help another continent, &quot;Laboratories Without Borders,&quot; is somewhat analogous<lb/> to the program &quot;Doctors Without Borders.&quot; (</div>

	<note type="submission">received 11 January 2002; accepted 29 January 2002)<lb/></note>

	<keyword>Keywords: acromegaly, plasma transport, filter paper, IGF-I, immunochemiluminometry<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
