<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003044"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Adaptive algorithms for<lb/> managing a distributed<lb/> data processing<lb/> workload<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>by J. Aman<lb/> C. K. Eilert<lb/> D. Emmes<lb/> P. Yocom<lb/> D. Dillenberger<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Workload management, a function of the<lb/> OSf390&quot; operating system base control program,<lb/> allows installations to define business objectives<lb/> for a clustered environment (Parallel SysplexTM in<lb/> OSl390). This business policy is expressed in<lb/> terms that relate to business goals and<lb/> importance, rather than the internal controls<lb/> used by the operating system. OSf390 ensures<lb/> that system resources are assigned to achieve<lb/> the specified business objectives. This paper<lb/> presents algorithms developed to simplify<lb/> performance management, dynamically adjust<lb/> computing resources, and balance work across<lb/> parallel systems. We examine the types of data<lb/> the algorithms require and the measurements<lb/> that were devised to assess how well work is<lb/> achieving customer-set goals. Two examples<lb/> demonstrate how the algorithms adjust system<lb/> resource allocations to enable a smooth<lb/> adaptation to changing processing conditions. To<lb/> the customer, these algorithms provide a single-<lb/>system image to manage competing workloads<lb/> running across multiple systems.<lb/> A<lb/> lthough there has been an important role for<lb/> a computing environment that has a single ma-<lb/>chine and a single copy or image of an operating sys-<lb/>tem, a number of factors have converged to moti-<lb/>vate use of multiple machines, especially when<lb/> connected in a parallel fashion. These machines<lb/> could be logical or physical configurations of what<lb/> might otherwise be deemed a single machine, but<lb/> each is controlled by a separate copy of an operat-<lb/>ing system.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
