<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003945"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Regorafenib (BAY 73-4506): a new oral multikinase inhibitor of<lb/> angiogenic, stromal and oncogenic receptor tyrosine<lb/> kinases with potent preclinical antitumor activity<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Scott M. Wilhelm<lb/> 1 , Jacques Dumas<lb/> 1 , Lila Adnane<lb/> 1 , Mark Lynch<lb/> 1 , Christopher A. Carter<lb/> 1 ,<lb/> Gunnar Schütz<lb/> 2 , Karl-Heinz Thierauch<lb/> 2 and Dieter Zopf<lb/> 2<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>1 Bayer HealthCare Pharmaceuticals,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Montville, NJ<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>2 Global Drug Discovery, Bayer Schering Pharma AG,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Berlin, Germany<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Angiogenesis, a critical driver of tumor development, is controlled by interconnected signaling pathways. Vascular endothelial<lb/> growth factor receptor (VEGFR) 2 and tyrosine kinase with immunoglobulin and epidermal growth factor homology domain 2 play<lb/> crucial roles in the biology of normal and tumor vasculature. Regorafenib (BAY 73-4506), a novel oral multikinase inhibitor,<lb/> potently inhibits these endothelial cell kinases in biochemical and cellular kinase phosphorylation assays. Furthermore,<lb/> regorafenib inhibits additional angiogenic kinases (VEGFR1/3, platelet-derived growth factor receptor-b and fibroblast growth<lb/> factor receptor 1) and the mutant oncogenic kinases KIT, RET and B-RAF. The antiangiogenic effect of regorafenib was<lb/> demonstrated in vivo by dynamic contrast-enhanced magnetic resonance imaging. Regorafenib administered once orally at<lb/> 10 mg/kg significantly decreased the extravasation of Gadomer in the vasculature of rat GS9L glioblastoma tumor xenografts.<lb/> In a daily (qd)34 dosing study, the pharmacodynamic effects persisted for 48 hr after the last dosing and correlated with tumor<lb/> growth inhibition (TGI). A significant reduction in tumor microvessel area was observed in a human colorectal xenograft after<lb/> qd35 dosing at 10 and 30 mg/kg. Regorafenib exhibited potent dose-dependent TGI in various preclinical human xenograft<lb/> models in mice, with tumor shrinkages observed in breast MDA-MB-231 and renal 786-O carcinoma models. Pharmacodynamic<lb/> analyses of the breast model revealed strong reduction in staining of proliferation marker Ki-67 and phosphorylated extracellular<lb/> regulated kinases 1/2. These data demonstrate that regorafenib is a well-tolerated, orally active multikinase inhibitor with a<lb/> distinct target profile that may have therapeutic benefit in human malignancies.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
