<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003722"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Clinical Science (2008) 114, 687–697 (Printed in Great Britain)</reference>

	<idno type="DOI">doi:10.1042/CS20070352<lb/></idno>

	<note type="page">687<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Enhanced expression and activation of<lb/> pro-inflammatory transcription factors<lb/> distinguish aneurysmal from atherosclerotic<lb/> aorta: IL-6-and IL-8-dominated inflammatory<lb/> responses prevail in the human aneurysm<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Jan H. N. LINDEMAN<lb/> * , Hazem ABDUL-HUSSIEN<lb/> * , Alexander F. M.<lb/> SCHAAPHERDER * , J. Hajo VAN BOCKEL<lb/> * , Jan H. VON DER T<lb/> USEN,<lb/> Dave L. ROELEN and Robert KLEEMANN<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>*Department of Vascular and Transplantation Surgery, Leiden University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2300 RC Leiden, The Netherlands,<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Pathology, Leiden University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2300 RC Leiden, The Netherlands,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of<lb/> Immunohematology and Blood Transfusion, Leiden University Medical Center,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2300 RC Leiden, The Netherlands, and<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Vascular and Metabolic Diseases, TNO-Quality of Life,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>2301 CE Leiden, The Netherlands<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">A B S T R A C T<lb/> Inflammation plays a key role in the pathogenesis of an AAA (abdominal aortic aneurysm); however,<lb/> the nature of the inflammatory factors and cellular response(s) involved in AAA growth is<lb/> controversial. In the present study, we set out to determine the aortic levels of inflammatory<lb/> cytokines in relation to downstream inflammatory transcription factors and cellular responses. A<lb/> comparison of AAA wall samples with atherosclerotic wall samples taken from the same aortic<lb/> region allowed AAA-specific inflammatory parameters to be identified that distinguish AAAs<lb/> from ASD (aortic atherosclerotic disease). RT-PCR (real-time PCR), ELISA, Western blotting and<lb/> immunohistochemistry were combined to assess cytokines and transcription factors at the mRNA<lb/> and protein level, and their activation status. Compared with ASD, inflammatory parameters<lb/> associated with Th1-type [T-bet, IL (interleukin)-2, IFN-γ (interferon-γ ), TNF-α (tumour necrosis<lb/> factor-α), IL-1α and cytotoxic T-cells] and Th2-type [GATA3, IL-4, IL-10, IL-13 and B-cells]<lb/> responses were all increased in AAA samples. Evaluation of major downstream inflammatory<lb/> transcription factors revealed higher baseline levels of C/EBP (CCAAT/enhancer-binding protein)<lb/> α, β and δ in the AAA samples. Baseline p65 NF-κB (nuclear factor κB) and c-Jun [AP-1 (activator<lb/> protein-1)] levels were comparable, but their activated forms were strongly increased in the AAA<lb/> samples. Downstream target genes of p65 NF-κB, c-Jun, IL-6 and IL-8 were hyperexpressed.<lb/> Molecular and cellular processes associated with IL-6 and IL-8 hyperactivation were enhanced<lb/> in the AAA samples, i.e. the expression of phospho-STAT-3 (signal transducer and activator<lb/> of transcription-3) and perforin were elevated, and the content of plasma cells, neutrophils<lb/> and vasa vasorum was increased. In conclusion, our findings demonstrate that an AAA is a<lb/> general inflammatory condition which is characterized by enhanced expression and activation of<lb/> pro-inflammatory transcription factors, accompanied by IL-6 and IL-8 hyperexpression and<lb/> exaggerated downstream cellular responses, which together clearly distinguish an AAA from ASD.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Key words: abdominal aortic aneurysm, atherosclerosis, cytokine, inflammation, interleukin, transcription factor.</keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
