<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002041"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>J Clin Ultrasound 18:477-485, JulylAugust 1990<lb/></reference>
	

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Ultrasound Diagnosis of Gastroesophageal<lb/> Reflux and Hiatal Hernia in Infants<lb/> and Young Children<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Sjirk J. Westra, MD,* Bart H. M. Wolf, MD,? and Chris R. Staalman, MD*<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract: In 30 young children suspected of gastroesophageal reflux (GER), the<lb/> G-E junction was examined with ultrasonography directly after a feeding while<lb/> these children were on overnight extended esophageal pH monitoring (EEpHM) (32<lb/> simultaneous ultrasound/EEpHM studies). The two tests showed 81% to 84% agree-<lb/>ment in the detection of the presence or absence of GER, depending on whether the<lb/> whole period of EEpHM or only the part of it covering the ultrasound observation<lb/> period were used as the standard. The discrepancies between the two tests were<lb/> explained by the much longer monitoring period of EEpHM compared to ultrasonog-<lb/>raphy and the inability of EEpHM to show reflux of neutralized gastric contents<lb/> directly after milk feedings. The two studies probably measure different aspects of<lb/> clinically significant reflux and must be correlated with the clinical symptoms.<lb/> Morphological findings associated with significant reflux were (1) a short intra-<lb/>abdominal part of the esophagus, (2) a rounded gastroesophageal angle, and (3) a<lb/> &quot;beak&quot; at the gastroesophageal junction. Barium meal findings confirmed these<lb/> sonographic signs, indicating a sliding hiatal hernia of the distal esophagus, either<lb/> fixed or intermittent. Ultrasonography can be recommended as a useful and physio-<lb/>logical screening test to demonstrate clinically significant GER and a predisposing hi-<lb/>atal hernia of the esophagus in symptomatic children. </div>
	
	<keyword>Indexing Words:<lb/> Children, gastrointestinal tract * Esophagus, reflux -Stomach, reflux * Hernia,<lb/> hiatal * Gastrointestinal tract, ultrasound studies<lb/></keyword> 
	
	<div type="introduction">Gastroesophageal reflux (GER) is a common dis-<lb/>order in infants and children. In the great major-<lb/>ity it constitutes a &quot;physiological.&quot; event and is of<lb/> little clinical<lb/> However, this often<lb/> apparently benign and self-limiting disorder is<lb/> now increasingly being recogniz,ed as a cause of<lb/> failure to thrive, extreme irritability, unusual<lb/> posturing, esophagitis, chronic blood loss, esoph-<lb/>ageal stricture, recurrent pneumonia, reactive<lb/> airway disease, and possibly apnea of infancy<lb/> even in the absence of overt e m e s i ~ . ~ . ~<lb/> Considerable confusion exists; over what con-<lb/>stitutes significant GER and how best to diag-<lb/>nose it. The barium upper gastrointestinal study</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
