<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002940"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note type="other">W3C Working Draft </note>
	
	<date>5 October 2010<lb/></date>
	
	<note type="other">Latest Editor&apos;s Draft:<lb/></note>

	<ptr type="web">http://dev.w3.org/2006/waf/widgets/<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">This version:<lb/> </note>
	
	<ptr>http://www.w3.org/TR/2010/WD-widgets-20101005/<lb/> Latest version:<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/widgets/<lb/> Previous versions:<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/CR-widgets-20091201/<lb/></ptr>

	<ptr type="web">http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-widgets-20091029/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/CR-widgets-20090723/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2009/WD-widgets-20090528/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/WD-widgets-20081222/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2008/WD-widgets-20080414/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2007/WD-widgets-20071013/<lb/> http://www.w3.org/TR/2006/WD-widgets-20061109/<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="other">Version history:<lb/> Differences between the last published draft and this document.<lb/> Differences between latest editor&apos;s draft and latest version.<lb/> Editor:<lb/> Marcos Cáceres, Opera Software ASA<lb/></note>

	<note type="copyright">Copyright © 2010 W3C<lb/> ® (MIT, ERCIM, Keio), All Rights Reserved. W3C liability, trademark and document use rules<lb/> apply.<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract<lb/> This specification standardizes a packaging format for software known as widgets. Widgets are<lb/> client-side applications that are authored using Web standards such as HTML5, but whose<lb/> content can also be embedded into Web documents. The specification relies on PKWare&apos;s Zip<lb/> specification as the archive format, XML as a configuration document format, and a series of steps<lb/> that runtimes follow when processing and verifying various aspects of a package. The packaging<lb/> format acts as a container for files used by a widget. The configuration document is an XML<lb/> vocabulary that declares metadata and configuration parameters for a widget. The steps for<lb/> processing a widget package describe the expected behavior and means of error handling for<lb/> runtimes while processing the packaging format, configuration document, and other relevant files.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
