<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003701"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Towards an Automated Analysis of Neuroleptics&apos;<lb/> Impact on Human Hand Motor Skills<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>M. Dose , C. Gruber * , A. Grunz * , C. Hook ** , J. Kempf ** , G. Scharfenberg ** , and B. Sick *</docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Mental Health Institution</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Taufkirchen, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>email: m.dose@bkh-taufkirchen.de<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>* University of Passau, Faculty of Computer Science and Mathematics</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>email: gruberc@fmi.uni-passau.de<lb/></email>
	<email>email: sick@fmi.uni-passau.de<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>** University of Applied Sciences</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Regensburg, Germany<lb/></address>

	<email>email: christian.hook@mathematik.fh-regensburg.de<lb/></email>
	<email>email: juergen.kempf@mikro.fh-regensburg.de<lb/></email>
	<email>email: georg.scharfenberg@e-technik.fh-regensburg.de<lb/></email>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract— The fact that neuroleptics may have a more or less<lb/> noticeable influence on fine motor skills is well-known. However,<lb/> up to now there is no system that allows one to measure and<lb/> to quantify such an impact of neuroleptics or other drugs. This<lb/> article goes a first step into this direction by demonstrating how<lb/> the handwriting dynamics of a healthy person can automatically<lb/> be distinguished from that of a schizophrenic and, therefore,<lb/> appropriately medicated person. Moreover, it is shown that<lb/> differences can be detected even for a very simple kind of hand<lb/> movement. That is, the persons trace a given meander. The<lb/> handwriting dynamics are measured by means of a pen equipped<lb/> with force and tilt sensors (Biometric Smart Pen). Then, the<lb/> parameterized script generator model proposed by Hollerbach is<lb/> used in order to extract characteristic features from the measured<lb/> signals, e.g., features describing deviations of measured time<lb/> series from predicted model time series. These features are then<lb/> used as inputs of support vector machines that classify whether<lb/> the handwriting has been provided by a healthy or a diseased<lb/> person.<lb/></div>

	<keyword>Index Terms— biometric smart pen, handwriting dynamics,<lb/> script generator model, support vector machine, neuroleptics,<lb/> medical diagnosis<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
