<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002449"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>

	<byline>
		<affiliation>University of Huddersfield Repository<lb/> </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<byline>
		<docAuthor>Leeungculsatien, Teerachai<lb/> </docAuthor>
	</byline>	

	<docTitle>
		<titlePart>Novel Multi-Electrode Electromagnetic Flow Meter<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<reference>Original Citation<lb/> Leeungculsatien, Teerachai (2009) Novel Multi-Electrode Electromagnetic Flow Meter. In:<lb/> University of Huddersfield Research Festival, 23rd March -2nd April 2009, University of<lb/> Huddersfield. (Unpublished)<lb/> </reference>

	<ptr type="web">This version is available at http://eprints.hud.ac.uk/4635/<lb/></ptr>

	<note type="copyright">The University Repository is a digital collection of the research output of the<lb/> University, available on

	Open Access. Copyright and Moral Rights for the items<lb/> on this site are retained by the individual author and/or other copyright owners.<lb/> Users may access full

	items free of charge; copies of full text items generally<lb/> can be reproduced, displayed or performed and given to third parties in any<lb/> format or medium for personal research or study, educational or not-for-profit<lb/> purposes without prior permission or charge, provided:<lb/> @BULLET The authors, title and full bibliographic details is credited in any copy;<lb/> @BULLET A hyperlink and/or URL is included for the original metadata page; and<lb/> @BULLET The content is not changed in any way.<lb/> For more information, including our policy and submission procedure, please<lb/> contact the Repository Team at:  E.mailbox@hud.ac.uk.<lb/> http://eprints.hud.ac.uk/<lb/></note>

	<div type="introduction">Systems Engineering<lb/> Computing and Engineering<lb/> CONCULSION<lb/> FUTURE WORK<lb/>
	
	The multi-electrode electromagnetic flow meter shows considerable promise as a means<lb/> of measuring the local velocity distribution in highly non-uniform single phase flows.<lb/> Recent work undertaken at University of Huddersfield also shows that the device can be<lb/> used to measure the local water velocity distribution in multiphase flows.<lb/> @BULLET To increase the spatial resolution of the measurement form 7 pixels to 120 pixels<lb/> in the flow cross section<lb/> @BULLET To improve the accuracy of the velocity profile obtained from the matrix inversion<lb/> algorithm.<lb/> @BULLET Apply the electromagnetic flow meter to measure the water velocity distribution in<lb/> &apos;water continuous&apos; multiphase flows (e.g. oil-in-water and solids-in-water flows).<lb/> @BULLET Use the electromagnetic flow meter in conjunction with an EIT system to<lb/> measure the volumetric flow rates of both phases in two phase flows.<lb/> @BULLET Investigate electrode material which minimise voltages generated due to<lb/> electrochemical effects.<lb/> @BULLET Investigate the effects of dimensional errors in the flow meter on the values of<lb/> the weight functions.<lb/> @BULLET Investigate alternative matrix inversion methods such as the conjugate gradients<lb/> method.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
