<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003151"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Journal of Membrane Science 373 (2011) 5–13<lb/></reference>

	<note type="other">Contents lists available at ScienceDirect<lb/></note>
	
	<note type="other">Journal of Membrane Science<lb/> </note>
	
	<ptr>j o u r n a l h o m e p a g e : w w w . e l s e v i e r . c o m / l o c a t e / m e m s c i<lb/></ptr>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Improving fluxes of polyimide membranes containing gold nanoparticles by<lb/> photothermal heating<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Katrien Vanherck<lb/> a , Ivo Vankelecom<lb/> a,* , Thierry Verbiest<lb/> b<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Centre for Surface Chemistry and Catalysis, Department of Microbial and Molecular Systems, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Kasteelpark Arenberg 23 – Box 2461, 3001 Heverlee, Belgium<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b Molecular and Nanomaterials, Katholieke Universiteit Leuven</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Celestijnenlaan 200d – Box 2425, 3001 Heverlee, Belgium<lb/></address>

	<note type="other">a r t i c l e i n f o<lb/></note>

	<note type="submission">Article history:<lb/> Received 3 November 2010<lb/> Received in revised form 3 February 2011<lb/> Accepted 9 February 2011<lb/></note>

	<date>Available online 23 February 2011<lb/></date>

	<keyword>Keywords:<lb/> Gold nanoparticles<lb/> Polyimide Solvent resistant nanofiltration<lb/> Photothermal heating<lb/></keyword>

	<div type="abstract">a b s t r a c t<lb/> Polyimide (PI) is a well known polymer to obtain membranes for solvent resistant nanofiltration. How-<lb/>ever, when compounds with a very low molecular weight need to be separated, very dense PI membranes<lb/> are required that generally have very low fluxes. It was previously shown for cellulose acetate membranes<lb/> containing gold nanoparticles that the membrane permeance increased by photothermal heating of the<lb/> membrane during filtrations. In this work, PI membranes were prepared containing different amounts of<lb/> gold nanoparticles and the membranes were locally heated during filtrations by irradiation with continu-<lb/>ous green laser light. The gold nanoparticles and the membrane structure were thoroughly characterized<lb/> by UV–visible spectroscopy and diffuse reflection spectroscopy, scanning electron microscopy and trans-<lb/>mission electron microscopy. The photothermal heating effect on the temperature and the permeance<lb/> behavior of the membrane depended on the concentration of gold nanoparticles in the membrane, their<lb/> aggregation and on the laser intensity. It was shown that the effect on the permeance was higher for<lb/> membranes with an intrinsically lower flux, due to a lower energy loss by convection in the membrane<lb/> pores and/or free volume. Most remarkably, the rejection of the membranes was not affected by the laser<lb/> irradiation. Overall, it was thus shown that localized heating of PI membranes can significantly improve<lb/> membrane performances in solvent resistant nanofiltration.<lb/></div>

	<note type="copyright">© 2011 Elsevier B.V. All rights reserved.<lb/></note>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
