<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002989"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>JOURNAL OF BIOSCIENCE AND BIOENGINEERING<lb/> Vol. 90, No. 3, 289-293.<lb/> 2000<lb/></reference>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Effective Onion Vinegar Production<lb/> Fermentation System<lb/> by a Two-Step<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>JUN-ICHI HORIUCHI, * TOHRU KANNO, AND MASAYOSHI KOBAYASHI<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Chemical System Engineering, Kitami Institute of Technology,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>165 Koen-cho, Kitami,<lb/> Hokkaido 090-8507, Japan<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 10 April 2OOO/Accepted 9 June 2000<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">A two-step fermentation system combining a repeated batch process using a flocculating yeast with a charcoal<lb/> pellet bioreactor was developed for onion vinegar production. Juice from the red onion R-3, which contained<lb/> 67.3 g/Z total sugar, was smoothly converted to onion alcohol containing 30.6 g/Z ethanol by repeated batch<lb/> operation using the flocculating yeast Saccharomyces cerevisiae strain fR-2. Stable operation was possibie and<lb/> the maximum productivity was about 8.0 g/Z/h. A packed bed bioreactor containing charcoal pellets produced<lb/> from waste mushroom medium was then applied to continuous onion vinegar production from the onion<lb/> alcohol. Onion vinegar was successfully produced, with a maximum productivity and acetic acid concentration<lb/> of about 3.3 g/Z/h and 37.9 g/Z, respectively. The total acetic acid yield calculated from the amount of sugar<lb/> consumed was 0.86. The two-step system was operated for 50 d and proved to be competitive with other systems<lb/> in terms of its high productivity, high acetic acid yield, operational stability and low production costs.<lb/></div> 
	
	<keyword>[Key words: vinegar, charcoal pellet bioreactor, onion, repeated batch process, flocculating yeast]<lb/> </keyword>
	
	<div type="introduction">Vinegar is widely produced from rice, malt, apples,<lb/> wine, and various other starting materials (1). In a re-<lb/>cent study, we reported the production of a new type of<lb/> vinegar rich in amino acids, organic acids and certain<lb/> minerals from commercially worthless onions that had<lb/> failed to meet the quality standards required for market-<lb/>ing to customers (2).<lb/> Since conventional vinegar production is usually time-<lb/>consuming, many studies has been carried out with the<lb/> aim of improving the production procedures (3). Vinegar<lb/> fermentation is essentially a two-step process: the anaero-<lb/>bic conversion of sugars to ethanol and the aerobic<lb/> oxidation of ethanol to acetic acid. Hence, to improve<lb/> the overall performance during vinegar production from<lb/> carbohydrate resources such as agricultural products,<lb/> both the ethanol fermentation and the subsequent acetic<lb/> acid fermentation process need to be optimized.<lb/> Saeki (4) reported effective vinegar production from<lb/> saccharified rice in a two-stage bioreactor system using<lb/> microorganism cells immobilized in calcium alginate,<lb/> which realized high productivity and yield levels in con-<lb/>tinuous operation. However, the high cost and the fact<lb/> that the immobilized cells lacked long-term stability were<lb/> critical drawbacks in terms of the practical application<lb/> of the system. Saeki (5) also examined a two-stage biore-<lb/>actor system that used free cells. The system was rather<lb/> simple and continuous operation was realized with a<lb/> high yield. However, since the cell concentration was<lb/> relatively low, the operation would be unstable during<lb/> long-term operation. Thus, further improvements are<lb/> required to establish an effective continuous vinegar pro-<lb/>duction process.<lb/> With regard to ethanol fermentation, a repeated batch<lb/> process using a flocculating yeast is widely recognized as<lb/> a promising method for effective alcohol production due<lb/> to its simple configuration, ease of cell recycling, and<lb/> stable operation (6-8). The repeated batch process is<lb/> considered to be more suitable than a continuous proc-<lb/>* Corresponding author.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
