<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003004"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<note>C H A P T E R<lb/> 2<lb/> </note>
	
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>MPLS TE Technology Overview<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">In this chapter, you review the following topics:<lb/> @BULLET MPLS TE Introduction<lb/> @BULLET Basic Operation of MPLS TE<lb/> @BULLET DiffServ-Aware Traffic Engineering<lb/> @BULLET Fast Reroute<lb/> This chapter presents a review of Multiprotocol Label Switching Traffic Engineering<lb/> (MPLS TE) technology. MPLS TE can play an important role in the implementation of<lb/> network services with quality of service (QoS) guarantees. The initial sections describe the<lb/> basic operation of the technology. This description includes the details of TE information<lb/> distribution, path computation, and the signaling of TE LSPs. The subsequent sections<lb/> present how Differentiated Services (DiffServ)-Aware traffic engineering (DS-TE) helps<lb/> integrate the implementation of DiffServ and MPLS TE. This chapter closes with a review<lb/> of the fast reroute (FRR) capabilities in MPLS TE. Chapter 4, &quot;Cisco MPLS Traffic<lb/> Engineering,&quot; covers in depth the Cisco implementation of MPLS TE in Cisco IOS and<lb/> Cisco IOS XR. In addition, Chapter 5, &quot;Backbone Infrastructure,&quot; discusses the different<lb/> network designs that can combine QoS with MPLS TE.<lb/> </div>
	
	<div type="introduction">MPLS TE Introduction<lb/> MPLS networks can use native TE mechanisms to minimize network congestion and<lb/> improve network performance. TE modifies routing patterns to provide efficient mapping<lb/> of traffic streams to network resources. This efficient mapping can reduce the occurrence<lb/> of congestion and improves service quality in terms of the latency, jitter, and loss that<lb/> packets experience. Historically, IP networks relied on the optimization of underlying<lb/> network infrastructure or Interior Gateway Protocol (IGP) tuning for TE. Instead, MPLS<lb/> extends existing IP protocols and makes use of MPLS forwarding capabilities to provide<lb/> native TE. In addition, MPLS TE can reduce the impact of network failures and increase<lb/> service availability. RFC 2702 discusses the requirements for TE in MPLS networks.<lb/> MPLS TE brings explicit routing capabilities to MPLS networks. An originating label<lb/> switching route (LSR) (or headend) can set up a TE label switched path (LSP) to a<lb/> terminating LSR (or tail end) through an explicitly defined path containing a list of</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
