<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003407"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Novel Bioreducible Poly(amido amine)s for Highly Efficient Gene Delivery<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Chao Lin, Zhiyuan Zhong,*<lb/> . Martin C. Lok,<lb/> Xulin Jiang,<lb/> Wim E. Hennink,<lb/> Jan Feijen,<lb/> and Johan F. J. Engbersen* ,<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Biomedical Chemistry and Department of Polymer Chemistry and Biomaterials, Institute for Biomedical<lb/> Technology (BMTI), Faculty of Science and Technology, University of Twente,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 217, 7500 AE Enschede,<lb/> The Netherlands,</address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>and Department of Pharmaceutics, Utrecht Institute for Pharmaceutical Science (UIPS), Utrecht University,<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>P.O. Box 80082, 3508 TB, Utrecht, The Netherlands.</address>

	<note type="submission">Received July 6, 2006; Revised Manuscript Received November 8, 2006<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">A series of novel bioreducible poly(amido amine)s containing multiple disulfide linkages (SS-PAAs) were<lb/> synthesized and evaluated as nonviral gene vectors. These linear SS-PAAs could be easily obtained by Michael-<lb/>type polyaddition of various primary amines to the disulfide-containing cystamine bisacrylamide. The SS-PAA<lb/> polymers are relatively stable in medium mimicking physiological conditions (pH 7.4, 150 mM PBS, 37 °C), but<lb/> are rapidly degraded in the presence of 2.5 mM DTT, mimicking the intracellular reductive environment (pH 7.4,<lb/> [R-SH] ) 5 mM, 37 °C). The polymers efficiently condense DNA into nanoscaled (&lt;200 nm) and positively<lb/> charged (&gt;+20 mV) polyplexes that are stable under neutral conditions but are rapidly destabilized in a reductive<lb/> environment, as was revealed by both dynamic light scatting measurement and agarose gel assays. Moreover,<lb/> most of the poly(amido amine)s possess buffer capacities in the pH range pH 7.4-5.1 that are even higher than<lb/> polyethylenimine (pEI), a property that may favorably contribute to the endosomal escape of the polyplexes.<lb/> Polyplexes of four of the seven SS-PAAs studied were able to transfect COS-7 cells in vitro with transfection<lb/> efficiencies significantly higher than those of branched pEI, being one of the most effective polymeric gene<lb/> carriers reported to date. Importantly, also in the presence of serum, a high level of gene expression could be<lb/> observed when the incubation time was elongated from 1 h to 4 h. XTT assays showed that SS-PAAs and their<lb/> polyplexes possess essentially no or only very low cytotoxicity at concentrations where the highest transfection<lb/> activity is observed. The results indicate that bioreducible poly(amido amine)s have excellent properties for the<lb/> development of highly potent and nontoxic polymeric gene carriers.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
