<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003770"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>J Artif Organs (2003) 6:173–178<lb/></reference>

	<note type="copyright">© The Japanese Society for Artificial Organs 2003<lb/></note>

	<idno type="DOI">DOI 10.1007/s10047-003-0224-x<lb/></idno>

	<note type="other">ORIGINAL ARTICLE<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Shunya Shindo, MD · Koji Ogata, MD<lb/> Kenji Kubota, MD · Atsuo Kojima, MD<lb/> Masahiro Kobayashi, MD · Yusuke Tada, MD<lb/> Katsumi Okuyama, MD<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Vascular prosthetic implantation is associated with prolonged inflammation<lb/> following aortic aneurysm surgery<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<div type="abstract">Abstract The purpose of this study was to semiquantify<lb/> the magnitude of surgical stress in patients undergoing<lb/> aortic surgery by measuring inflammatory responses<lb/> perioperatively, focusing on cytokine secretion. Serum con-<lb/>centrations of interleukin (IL) 1α, IL-6, IL-8, and tumor<lb/> necrotizing factor (TNF) α were measured in patients<lb/> undergoing abdominal or thoracic aortic aneurysmectomy<lb/> preoperatively and periodically thereafter for 2 weeks.<lb/> Urinary trypsin inhibitor (UTI/Cr) and C-reactive protein<lb/> (CRP) concentration and the systemic inflammatory re-<lb/>sponse syndrome (SIRS) score also were determined. Indi-<lb/>ces of inflammation and cytokine concentrations peaked at<lb/> 1–3 days after surgery and decreased thereafter; however,<lb/> IL-8 increased again after day 7. Concentrations of IL-8,<lb/> UTI/Cr, and CRP and the SIRS score were still higher 14<lb/> days after surgery than preoperatively. The maximum con-<lb/>centrations of IL-6 and IL-8 were higher after thoracic than<lb/> abdominal aortic repair; however, the maximum values of<lb/> cytokines were not correlated with operative factors in all<lb/> patients. A patient suffering from graft infection showed<lb/> an increase in cytokine concentrations on day 7. The<lb/> inflammatory response does not return to preoperative<lb/> values within 2 weeks of surgery in patients undergoing<lb/> thoracic or abdominal aortic aneurysm repair. The pro-<lb/>longed secretion of IL-8 suggests a host reaction to the<lb/> synthetic prosthesis. A large increase in inflammatory<lb/> cytokines on day 7 may indicate infection of the vascular<lb/> graft.<lb/></div>

	<note type="submission">Received: December 17, 2002 / Accepted: June 2, 2003<lb/></note>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>S. Shindo (*) · K. Ogata · K. Kubota · A. Kojima · M. Kobayashi ·<lb/> Y. Tada<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Second Department of Surgery, Faculty of Medicine, University of<lb/> Yamanashi,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1110 Shimokato, Tamaho-cho, Nakakoma-gun,<lb/> Yamanashi 409-3898, Japan<lb/></address>

	<phone>Tel. ϩ81-55-273-9682; Fax ϩ81-55-273-6767<lb/></phone>

	<email>e-mail: sshindo@res.yamanashi-med.ac.jp<lb/></email>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>K. Okuyama<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Department of Anesthesiology, Faculty of Medicine, University of<lb/> Yamanashi,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Yamanashi, Japan<lb/></address>

	<keyword>Key words Inflammatory cytokine · Aortic surgery · Vascu-<lb/>lar prosthesis · Interleukin-8 · Surgical stress<lb/></keyword>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
