<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55002383"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Dielectrophoresis-based programmable fluidic processors<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>Peter R. C. Gascoyne,* a Jody V. Vykoukal, a Jon A. Schwartz, a Thomas J. Anderson, a<lb/> Daynene M. Vykoukal, a K. Wayne Current, b Charles McConaghy, c Frederick F. Becker a<lb/> and Craig Andrews d<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>a Department of Molecular Pathology, The University of Texas M. D. Anderson Cancer Center<lb/></affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1515, Holcombe Boulevard, Houston, TX 77030, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>b University of California, Davis, ECE Dept.,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>Davis, CA 95616, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>c Lawrence Livermore National Laboratory,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>7000 East Avenue, M/S L-222, Livermore, CA<lb/> 94551, USA<lb/></address>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>d Lynntech Incorporated,</affiliation>
	</byline>

	<address>1701 Rock Prairie Road, College Station, TX 77845, USA<lb/></address>

	<note type="submission">Received 23rd March 2004, Accepted 27th May 2004<lb/> First published as an Advance Article on the web 1st July 2004<lb/></note>

	<div type="abstract">Droplet-based programmable processors promise to offer solutions to a wide range of applications in which chemical<lb/> and biological analysis and/or small-scale synthesis are required, suggesting they will become the microfluidic<lb/> equivalents of microprocessors by offering off-the-shelf solutions for almost any fluid based analysis or small scale<lb/> synthesis problem. A general purpose droplet processor should be able to manipulate droplets of different compositions<lb/> (including those that are electrically conductive or insulating and those of polar or non-polar nature), to control reagent<lb/> titrations accurately, and to remain free of contamination and carry over on its reaction surfaces. In this article we<lb/> discuss the application of dielectrophoresis to droplet based processors and demonstrate that it can provide the means for<lb/> accurately titrating, moving and mixing polar or non-polar droplets whether they are electrically conductive or not. DEP<lb/> does not require contact with control surfaces and several strategies for minimizing surface contact are presented. As an<lb/> example of a DEP actuated general purpose droplet processor, we show an embodiment based on a scaleable CMOS<lb/> architecture that uses DEP manipulation on a 32 3 32 electrode array having built-in control and switching circuitry.<lb/> Lastly, we demonstrate the concept of a general-purpose programming environment that facilitates droplet software<lb/> development for any type of droplet processor.<lb/></div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
