<?xml version="1.0" ?>
<tei>
	<teiHeader>
		<fileDesc xml:id="55003087"/>
	</teiHeader>
	<text xml:lang="en">
		<front>
<lb/>
	<reference>Aust Vet J Vol 79, No 6, June 2001<lb/> </reference>
	
	<note type="page">431<lb/></note>

	<note type="other">Scientific<lb/></note>

	<docTitle>
	<titlePart>Eradication of ovine footrot by repeated daily<lb/> footbathing in a solution of zinc sulphate with surfactant<lb/></titlePart>
	</docTitle>

	<byline>
	<docAuthor>PD JELINEK, LJ DEPIAZZI, DA GALVIN, IT SPICER, MA PALMER a and DR PITMAN a<lb/></docAuthor>
	</byline>

	<byline>
	<affiliation>Agriculture Western Australia, </affiliation>
	</byline>
	
	<address>PO Box 1231, Bunbury, Western Australia 6230<lb/></address>

	<div type="abstract">Objective To investigate the effect on ovine footrot of<lb/> repeated daily footbathing in a solution of zinc sulphate with<lb/> surfactant.<lb/> Design Merino sheep were allocated to control and<lb/> treatment groups of 119 sheep each at week 0. The sheep<lb/> had a history of S1, U1, T and/or U6 types of Dichelobacter<lb/> nodosus in interdigital and underrunning footrot lesions. Feet<lb/> were not pared prior to treatment.<lb/> Procedure Treatment sheep were footbathed in a 15 to<lb/> 18% (w/v) solution of zinc sulphate with surfactant for 10 min<lb/> on five consecutive days during week 1. At week 2, and<lb/> fortnightly to week 52, all feet were inspected, lesion scores<lb/> were recorded and samples were taken for laboratory tests. At<lb/> week 53, all feet with no lesions at week 52, but with<lb/> underrunning lesions prior to week 1, were pared and<lb/> samples were taken.<lb/> Results After footbathing, there were no lesions in any<lb/> treatment sheep at any inspection to week 52. The<lb/> percentage of feet of control sheep with lesions increased<lb/> from 9% (391 of 4284) between weeks 20 and 36, to 14%<lb/> (593 of 4284) between weeks 36 and 52. Ninety-five of 96<lb/> control sheep with no lesions at week 20 were still<lb/> asymptomatic at week 52. D nodosus was not isolated from<lb/> samples taken from 99 and 87 pared feet of treatment and<lb/> control sheep, respectively.<lb/> Conclusion Repeated daily footbathing combined with<lb/> prolonged exposure to a dry environment eradicated footrot in<lb/> sheep with both interdigital and underrunning lesions in feet<lb/> that were not pared prior to treatment.</div>

		</front>
	</text>
</tei>
